<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00021f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T07:30:41.312Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">f w y I p ► I** v. A no. y• ;&gt; ^un /j . ^•miiuri uulf Kes nuBhir e f the Votti jstnwry i*l**a y*l 946 1946 * J ^ XT am TO The Mon’ble air Jeffrey &gt;rior* k.0 9 1«^ # » iolitical ueeident, leraian Guli * *ihe aeoretary to the iloYernmeat of India in the external ^Ufairo Departwet.t, h « « 1) is! L H 1 • air # I haTe the honour to enoloee for the order* of the Covernment of India an &amp;pref&gt;&amp; Letter no # a*iia6 dated the 9th Auyuot 1945 on the eubjeot of the aultar; of ttuaoat** deeire to oonaolidate hie authority in the interior of Oman* I found thie letto r waiting for me on icy arrival in the Giilf, hut took no action upon it pending a vioit to irueoat, wmk aa 1 wi whed to di eouee the pro otala with Hie Highneae arid form a clearer picture of what wae involved. kt. Hallows has expreaeed the Blaster v ry lucidly and 1 agree generally with him. 2. ueiore leaving for toueoat 1 ahuwed the pap ere to &amp;r. reilj, who has considerable experience of rubcat v and he taadfc the point that Hia Highnefe* would be very surprised if, in agreeing to sup art him on so substantial a scale. we made no attempt to improve our own position. fhie point appeared to me to have considerable force, and 1 considered both on uy ay to muscat and after uiscussion with ^r.Hallows what concession we could appropriately demand. ihe extension of a protectorate over Muscat which has frequently beta ooii»idered, would, in the pr sent state of the »rat&gt; worlds be neither in our interests nor in those of the i.tate, and the most favourable concession that we cun huge for would be to obtain the ultan's agreement to conducting all his foreign relations through us -- in other words a modification of hie treaty posit ion. This seemed to me outside the range of practical politics and 1 therefore decided to concentrate upon obtaining from him an agreement that if we came#to his assistance he would bind himself and hie heirs In the future to obtain euch advisers as he required from ue. «tr. Hallows was, in fact, very doubtful that he would even agree to this but it is better to aek for too much than too little in such matters. 3. the ilultan did not take long to raise the question and 1 reminded him of what I had told him at my f iret visit in 1940, that it was my hope to see the power of his dynasty * reasi erted over the interior and muscat restored to ite former proud position, and at this his face brightened. It is true that I had at the time no authority eithtr from His iraj esty*s *3overni:jent or the uovernii.ent of India to make this statement, but it seemed to me so obviously in our interests that nuscat should control the hinterland that 1 felt justified in doing so. I pointed out the practical difficulties of his proposal to the Julian, and i^de it clear ij r ^jthat the end of a long war whose aftermath still remained to be cleared up, we dejijred than t o become / involved— JjriYolveu amon^fct tha crag* and praoi icee o i alao observed that h© would require aubetantial sup,lice of weapon© and money and to aome extent men to oariy out hia proj eolb• I 4. nia Highness explained to »e that he waa not relying aolely upon military action to obtain hia tnda, -“T* | a© he felt that he would obtain much better reeulte by | political means and that he had been feeling hie way with •the ihaikhe of the interior for a lonp time past and had [already achieved a very aubetantial measure of auoueee* hat he required was a backing of force and trailed men to hold the forta which would fall into hia hauae. h« did not intend to take any action until the imam died f but that the moment thie happened he must be in a oeitlon to move at once a© the op ortuuity then given might not recur and could not be mieued* He must therefore obtain the equipment he required aa early aa poaeible and be certain that he had our ay mouthy and eupport* 5# 1 pointed out that hia plane, if auoceeeful, would bring him very aubetantial benefit© and that whereas he was J now in fact the ruler of only a portion of hie territories, he would greatly extend hie eway if eve ly thing turned out a a he hoped# I added th**t he wae aeking for a very substantial meaeure of help from hie raj e sty's Government and that we had nothing to gain ~ in fact any help we gave him might be misinterpreted elsewhere, and recoil u on our heads# 2 said that if he was prepared to *i ue some quid ro quo it would cake the proposals more attractive aid suggested that he should agree to turn to us alone in future for such advisers ae he might require. 1 pointed out that we had a somewhat similar agreement with Iraq, not that it was necessary for this undertaking to be in the form of a treaty as the position oould be satisfactorily obtained by an exchange of letters# l added that in any case he would have to turn to ue as no one else oould provide the ty f e of staff he required. I said that I felt that if he oould make this position clearer Government would robarly be more willing to help# His Highness made no corument on all this and I did not press the point# 6# sext day His Highness came to see me at the agency and I had a two-and-a-half hour dlsouasion *i th him covering all points outstanding between us# m reverting to this question, he said that he could of course take action at the death of the Imam without our help but th^t he always relied upon the British Government and to who© else should he turn now X endeavoured to secure some idea of what he actually bad in mind in toe w^&gt; of weapons and the figure he gbve me was U&gt;to rifl-s and -aritish oft leers to train his levies*# I pointed out that we should infallibly be accused eleevdierc of supplying arms which oould fall into wrong hands and be re-exported free wueoat an* that the amount appeared large# To out a long story short His Highness finally agreed that in the event of our eupi orting him in his plane he would agree to give me a letter binding himself and hie heirs for the future to obtain advisers exclusively from British sources. mis 1 feel is extremely eatisfactory# 7# It eeems to me that there is muoh to be gained and little to be lost in assisting His Highnesi to reassert / controlI ^ * • » f' | • 3 •» control ©Ter the Interior* indeed we ere under some moral obligation to uo eo* The rolltioal ii^ent hae ehown that the upheavale &lt;di’ch ended in the loee of the hinterland were largely brou^t about toy o r ineletence on the abolition of the art»a traf io jui»t aa at an earlier day aaiyid furki eaa embarraeied by hia loyal cooperation in the abolition of the ; lave Trade* we have had to tend troo-e to euao t on eeveral occaaions to reatore order and the greater the extent of the sultan * a control, the leea likelihood there will bo in future oi dlfcoonten t bang fo;wer.ted agaj net hie rule* Koe thut iet oleum oox&lt;eoa&gt; iona limited are in a poaitloa to 0 , 01 ^ up their eporattona it ia obvloualy in our intereata that the i»tale ehould be in a position to aup ort them in their journey» mui orinure their aafe conduct eheiewr they wieh to go* without thie it will never be poaelole ior them to aac^rtnln the value of their conoeat: i n. I foal therefore, from every point of view, both a a an act of grace to a ruler who gave uo valua le support during the war and in our interftftte in ti* ia area gor^ rally we ehould agree to hia Higtuieaa* re^ueut and aup. ort him by every moaiift poftbible* No } i» CVS*' 0 Ofrrv- (/} tfc* ,1 «* i^« ftupport we uhoulo be projared to give him is aa folio*8*uj to 1000 rifle a with equipment and loo rounds per rifle,' 6 martari* of modern ty, e in addition to the preaoat of «*rtil 1 eiah i have reo^mended aeparately/ and two sections of maohlie guns complete* in addition His highness sdiould be allo*ed to purchase such ter^tage, trans, ort 9 medical supplies an&lt;i sfgnalilng etiuij&gt;ment as he may require, we ourselves presented the dtate with artillery in i ,7i ard with fur less cause, and seal other states have done the same* Indeed there is every risk that if we will not provide his requirements others will gladly do so* in addition Hie Hlghnesfe would require another ptritisli of leer for his bevies together with several retired Indian officers arid f *3*r.a, These could aim should be made available and His High neb. should be enocuraged in every way to |.laue his Levies upon a tVfjproughly sound footing* ws noed iiave no fear that the Multan will use these forces recklessly or involve us in any complications thereby* for he is extremely eagacioue and lealises clearly that he must rule by consent if his position in the Interior ie ever to be re-estahlished• j do net recommend thut tie should be &amp;i ven any enoo*4rag«(nent to believe vthat uri tish troo s will be made available though it is conoeivable that at some tl«* some asclstance from the v.a,V# &gt;^1 might be desiiable, 1 would be glad to kiiow as early as jli. possible what reply i should convey to His Highness* 1 am sanding s copy of this letter to His majesty’s Secretary of ntate for India, ani to the political Agent at vusoat* i have the honour to be, dir. Your most obedient servant. Ml* Sd. Gt50' FKTOY PRIOR iolltlcal Resident, j ersi an uulf iUL fi t u ' S I Copy of Express Letter .No,. '^ /l t 3.26 r l a ted 19th August 1946, from Political Agent, Muscat to Political Resident Bushire. Xhe Sultai: visited me recently at the Agency to discuss the. ctkte Budgci fer 1945, find, when I ag&amp;in drew hie attention to the need for Investing the row substantial reserves in his Treasury, he replied that he did net intend tc aake any decision on this until December when he hoped tc nave u cle:.rer idea cf the r?; in which affairs in Oman might develop* He then went on to discuss in some detail his hopes for the consolidation of his authority in Oman. Kuler of Muscat, he said, could regain setis» fled with the present state of affairs. In the past the sense of frustr lion produced by the realisation that, with the fiieagre resources of his SUte, ther* was littl* hope of the re-establishment cf the authority cf his House in Coaii in his time, had nede him feel acutely despondent* New however the position had changed: the State wts sound financially and lied a sufcst^tisl reserve; he was now able tc entertain and givo presents to the influential Shaikhs oi the interior In a manner befitting his position; and above ell he new had the moans to acquire arms and ammunition to enable him to support his growing influence with force* The Imtm could not be expected to live much longer: . with a :;how of force t./id th^ support he hopped to receive from the tribes, action t? kon immediately the net s of the Imam's death waa received wculo enable him to re-oecupy Oman with out bloodshed* He intended to make no move until the Imam died, but in the aeaii time wisaed to make whatever prepar ations were possible, firstly by encouraging friendly rel ations with the ftjore important shaikhs, and secondly by preparing plans for military coercions designed to seize certain oi the forts* The first of these two preparatory stages was his concern, but the second - on which every thing depended - would only be possible ^ith the assistance of the British Government. He would require additional military stores and equipment, including artillery and would need the assistance of British officers. In discussing these affairs he *isned to make it clear that whatever advice were given him by the British Government he would accept, though he sincerely hoped that this would not be unfavourable tc his intentions. Kis aims were clearly reasonable, for without its unification under his Rule, he could see no future for his Stste. Did the British Govern- raent wish Oman to remain as it was? This he could not belie e. He fully realised th«t the successful control of the interior wouio depend upon nim personally end would give him 2 great de ? 1 of added responsibility* He was con fident, however, of his ability to manage the tribes, who were generally dissatisfied with their isolation: when the time came he would perhaps transfer his capital to the interior* The Sultan concluded his statement by a request for an indication of the degree of support which he might expect from His Majesty's Government. 3. In reply, I informed the Sultan that the matter would be referred to the political Resident for instructions, but that in the mean time he should do nothing which would be likely to upset the tranquillity of the State by acting in any way contrary tc the agreement reached at Sib in 1920 on whicn his present relations with the interior were based. a /I addedpresent time, with the wer against Japan still te be r/on, any inter fere nee ^wc uld, I was sure, be &gt;1 rr;v» tr&gt; His 1(&amp;jesty f s Covtrnment. d taking or contrary The any particularly unwelcome to Sultan assured me that he had no intention of action, either before the death of the Imam | to the a-'vlce given to him by Bis Majesty's Government sr.d thrt be fully understood tne particular importance of internal peace at the present Hi®e. So frr a^. the Sib egreeKiont was concerned, he admitted that so long as the XmsK remained in authority he was bound by its terms, laid th t between the tino of Moli&amp;mmed bin Abdullah al Khalili's derth and the election cf a succesror the Ggreer^ent would be In abeyance, with the tribes once again in h position of independence and at liberty tc enter Fhto stpi rote agreements with whomsoever they wished. It was because the success of his venture would depend on his ability to net before the appointment of a successor that he wished to know the attitude of the British Government as early as possible. 4« The political affairs of Orru&gt;n are still mainly influenced by the division of the tribes into the two gro; t factions, the Hlnsv/i and Ghrflri, rhich took place in the 18th century. Territorially there is no cividing line between the two factions and the fact that throughout Oman Hinawi and Ghafiri adherents live interndngltfd has led to the upholding of the brltnce cf power and tc the recognition of the importance cf a rLodus vlvcndj. . Rel igiously, the Kinr.wis are mostly Ibrdhis rhile the Ghafiris Include a substantial proportion of orthodox iunnis. Both factions heve their centre of influence and power dominated by a recognised leader. The centre of Einawi activity has always been the Shsrqiyrh with the principal ohaikh cf the Birth tribes at its ueadi and astute lead ership of a people more inclined to fanaticism than the inhabitants of the rest of Omar, h&amp;a given the Kinawls a controlling voles in the councils of Imams te in sjite of the numerical superiority of their oporents. The Ghsflri confederacy is centred in the region of the Jebel Akhdhar ana the Wadi Sumail and its leader is the chief Shaikh cf the lenl Aly^ir who claims descent from an an cient dynasty of u.aiika ^ The Chafiri have, in addition, s strong supporter In tjfci person cf the Shaikh of the beni bu All. a poeerfu3| of the noighDCarhcod of Sur. Very generally speckin^^r can therefore be said that the main current of events in Gnuin is controlled by three persons - the principal Ghaikh of the Hirth, Shqikh Isa bin Salih (Hinswi), the Ghaikh of the Jebel Akhdhar region, f'* Shaikh Sulrfman bin Hamyar, (Ghafiri) and the Shaikh of the Beni Bu All, Shaikh All bin Abdulla (Ghafirl). The last of these Shaikhs is under the effective influence of the Sultan, and his interest la the Imamate is concerned with purely factional issues. In securing, through a packed house, the election of a relative as the present Imam, bhtikh Isa's influence remained paramount for many years. Bow, however, Isa is an oid raan, incapable of any great physical exertion, while fortunately for the state xiis sons do not appear to possess any of the qualities which would enable them to maintain their father's position, i while Hlnawi influence is therefore on the decline - the Sultan received ® letter fro® Shaikh Ise some months ago stating that he intondedv,ake no purt in any afflars rel ating to the future of the Imamate - the two Ghajftri onaikhs have snown much activity in stmegthening their /confederacy,- 3 - mm, confader&amp;cy, aiid, #hat is important to the subject of the latter, &amp; desire to'support the Suiter. Their meeting at Sur in Febru«»ry, their willingness to remain there fcr over two months until they wo’Jld see the Sultan, and their prompt acceptance of his invitation to them to be his quests at Muscat were deveiofments of $rest signif icance. ihia was not coiy tne first time th&lt;»t the Shaikhs had met, but also the first time Shaikh Suldtean bin Hem- yar had visited the o^ltan and the only occasion en which he had travailed outside oman. The ensuing conversations at Muscat guvo great satisiaction to the Sultan Y&lt;ho is certain that both shaikhs will actively support him in his airas. Xheae Ghaflri activities h&amp;ve naturally caused ccnsterxu ticn auongst tne ikinavl faction ^nd the present sttte of the interior is uneasy and likely to remain to. 5. To this brief description of the state of tffwirs new pievailing in Oman it is necessary to add some mention of thu system of succession to the Ipjetnate. It is one of the cardinal principles of the Tbadhi sect that their spiritual leader shouix be elected in every caL'fc. Prior to 1783 Imains, including the first of the line of the *1 bu Sriu fctre appointed by election, the persons elected teing persons possessing outstanding religious sutiibutt*. From 1784, when the letmate ceased to siist, until its recreation in )913, succession rem ained hereditary with th» administrative functions of the post carried out by persons having nc particular religious qualifications - and governing under the secular title of 'Saiyid 1 * or 'dultan' • The bultan seoms to have real ised that his general acceptance in Oman would be influen ced by his religious qualifications for he has now ab olished all secular courts in rfusc^t and I'atrah and es tablished the Shara law as the only recognised law for his suo.locts. Hia devotions are cost rigorous sr.d correct ard unlike his father, he neither drinks nor smokes. The question of the prohibition of liquor and tcbacco is known to oe occupying his mine, perhaps for the added reason that this subject formed one of the objections to ^aiyid Faisals regime voiced by Shaikh Isa at the peace negotiations of 1919. Th t in the early stages at any rate, the stability of his position ir the interior would rest as ouch if not more, on moral or religious force, than on arterial force, ne is doubtless fully aware. By this I do not mean 'List the Sultan’s aim is that he should suceed to the Imamate for this is certainly not the case. Sis object is t:.3 uc.txtuou l . fchfl Iu I '.T - substitution of his own rule* backed by f^rce for the Ineffective authority of the la-am. 6. The Sultan’s statement of his aims must 1 think be received with considerable sympathy for although the unfortunate events leading to the virtual independence of Oman in 1S20 have been represented in the nest in a light very unfavourable to the A1 bu Sale, the more fundamental reason which united the Interior against the Sultanate w*!s perhaps lost sight of. The use of force n..,1 cure to suppress arms traffic in Muscat and to abolish the right of the Sultan to import nnc sell arms was probebly the biggest single factor which enabled the differences between the Hinawis and Ghafiris to be dissolved ir this common purpose of opposing the Sultan. There Is no doubt that tho conso]idation of Omsr under a single ruler could bring Inestimable benefits to the State. The present Sul ten is one of the most capacle Arab rulers of his time; he is young, well educated, has broadened his vision by extensive travel, possesses strength /•INWARD TELEGRAM (Jl i. &lt; !/ I 7162 Allotted to External DQpartrfiigiil,, 46 kN 0 ® V 27093 CYPHER TELEGRAM (0 , T &gt;p .) , From Political Resident in Persian Gulf To Secretary of State for India Kept.to Government of India, copy to Muscat Rated Bahrain, 10.10 hours, 19th October 1946 Received 10*00 hours,. 19th October 1946. loam:. Your telegram 18,114 October 8 th% Muscat oil. 2 ^ Following is repetition of Muscat telegrem C.,43l ? October 17th* Begins, : p. Sultan is sxtremely concerned at probable effect in Oman of hie formal assent to direct negotiation with tribes oflbri Dhank area and X have been unable to secure his confirmation to hie Agreement mentioned in (?para,raph 6 ) of your express letter 0.828 September 16th., 3 He has however informed me privately that if C ompaxty Sish to penetrate this area at their own p'itiative and risk this might be done without reference -go him, so taa b he oan fce free to deal with any unfortunate impression which may gain ground among tribes* 4 . Sultan's fearfl are entirely reasonable. Suggest therefore that P.C.L. be given permieaion to explore ior^ i)hank area without Sultan's concurrence, on the underat^nuing th-.t tbie will form no precedent for future operations ana - - - -u do noVgo beyond area stipulated. Sultan will of course watch developments' cloaely and on Company's aMlity to avoid compromising his position will depend hie willingness to a^ee to further exploration of interior* ^ Sultan has agreed to make necessary arrangements for Company to visit Baraimi, Yankal, Wadi Howasinah and Wadebeniomar araa on receipt of reoueet to do'so from Company. Snd^E COPY. jg ^OVHRlSlMENT OF INDIA- Department. £56(3 express Better (air mail). zm ~ [N.B. No. C/828. To Repeated ._J This i» an ORIQINAL mesmge sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, V)itk the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save tune and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form^af a, telegram.- It. is auths/iticated by the. sianature p/ o , responsible officer of the Department.) UlllCc Ol trie * 0-Ll t 1 C&amp;i. Resident^ Persian Gulf , Camp, Muscat. Dated &gt; the 16th September Retaxandum London Foreign New Delhi. Political Muscat. ReferenceIndia Office Express Letter No.Ext.52^5/46 the 20th August 1946. m6 *30 SEP 1949 c h- , ro c s sM 0 tIFfl c K/i*'*) \ fa, ('tUtle*-*) vk/cwMik Mi &gt; -u M-h ; A'- rl 5/46 dated ^ 4 ljl3 2. At an interview on the 15th September I informed the Sultan that His Majesty f a Government were unable to give him the assistance of the R.A.F# in his scheme for the subjugation of Oman by force for the reasons stated in paragraph 1 of India Office telegram No. 12479 dated the 7th July 1946. 3. The Sultan took the news very calmly but said that it meant he must definitely abandon the scheme referred to above which means that at any rate for the present he will not require the arms asked for vide correspondence ending with my telegram No. T/205 dated the 28th May 1946. 4. The Sultan still hopes however that when the Imam dies the tribes of the interior will ask him to rule over them. In reply to a question of mine he stated that he could almost certainly secure election as Imam but that he did not wish this as it would mean the continuance of an elective Imamate. He wishes to abolish the Imamate altogether aid incorporate Oman in Muscat State. 5. On the subject of oil exploration I spoke to him on the lines proposed in paragraphs 5 and 6 of my Express Letter ^25^- No# 0/525 dated the 24th July 1946 emphasising the point made in your express letter under reply. He promised to think the whole matter over and let the Political Agent have his reply. He did however say that he would have no objection to the P.C.L. negotiating direct with the tribes at Ibri provided ground exploration only was intended and his position under the agreement was safeguarded and that he had already agreed to the tfadi Howa- sinah being visited. He pointed out that Ibri was directly under the Iman^s control - it is actually the headquarters of one of his tfalis • and expressed some doubt whether the tribesmen who had invited Lermitte to visit their country (vide paragraph 3 my express Letter No. C/525 of 24th July) did so with the Imam 9 s concurrence. (Signature) ^d* if .R. HAY. Political Resident,Persian Gulf. Attes ted. w \\9 s. 44 . for Secretary to the MfM GUlf (Designation) Mp- cclo. RHLDRAFT EXPRESS LETTER From: Secretary of State for To : Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrein. Repeat to : Government of India, External Affairs Dept. Political Agent, Muscat 2 0 AUG 1946 L ( rt + /Yn ' / 0(y)il r Reference your express letter No. C/S25 of 24th July. Development of Muscat oil resources. 2. Your information that some, if not all ; of the tribes of the interior are already anxious for ary oil deposits to be exploited puts a new complexion on the matter. In /mi the circumstances ^ agree that the best course would be for you to speak to the Sultan as proposed in paragraph 5 of your letter. You should however make it clear to Mm that the essential requirement/requirement at the moment is only for the Comparer to be permitted to carry out ground surveys of the interior. Until they have done this they cannot even be sure whether there are in fact ary suitable locations for drilling nor whether the oil development of Muscat will be a practicable proposition. F. A. K. HARRISONAny reply to be addressed :— The Secretary. Telephone : Abbey 7000 Telegrams: Minfupo, Sowest, London.” Reference: PL, 859/4/2# Your Reference: Dear Harrison, MINISTRY OF FUEL AND POWER, Petroleum Division, 7, Millbank, London, S.W.l 15th August, 1946. With reference to your letter of the 13th August, 5255/46, concerning the development of the oil resources of Muscat and Oman, it seems to us that from the point of view of the Sultan there is considerable difference between making payments to tribes to obtain survoys acce^^anS'lir^ing agreements for the exploitation of the oil which would definitely recognise their ownership of the subsoil rights. It did not seem, therefore, necessary before we even know whether exploitation would be possible to suggest direct dealings with the tribes for the exploitation stage. Your draft reply to the Political Resident meets our point, however, and v/e concur in its terms, I am sending a copy of this letter to Wikeley at the Foreign Office. Yours sincerely. F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.1./ilk August, l%b. Dear Itorrell, Thank you for your letter No. M).859AA of 9th August oa canting on the Balltical Resident f s express letter of the 24th July on the subject of securing the cooperation of the Independent tribes of the Interior In the development of the oil resources of Muscat and (loan. 2. We do not read Into paragraph 3 of the Political Resident’s express letter any sug estion of entering at this stage into separate agreements with the tribes for the exploitation of oil deposits. That the ftjlitical resident proposes in paragraph 3 of his letter is that he should explain to the Sultan hov. urgently necessary it is for us to search for oil in Muscat and exploit any deposits that may be found there. It vvould be difficutt, so far as the tribes are concerned, to draw any fine distinction between prospecting and actual developoant. The point is that negotiation with tribes will be necessary even for the obtaining of access for an exploration party and the question is v^ther such negotiations can be effected through the Sultan. 3 . In the circumstances we would propone, if you and Foreign Office concur, to reply to the hhlltical Resident as in the attached draft. 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to Yikelqy at the foreign Office. Tours sincerely. J.W. Farrell, Esq., Ministry of Fuel &amp; Bower, Millbank, S.W.l. f. A. K. HARRISON* Any reply fco be addressed :—* The Secretary. Telephone: Abbey 7000 Telegrams: Minfcjpo, Sowest, Londox.” Reference : PD # 859/4/2 # Your Reference: Dear Harrison, If a miNis’tky of fuel and power, f ^ V 'Y* P ETI oleum Division, 7, Millbank, 3534 Augu 4 t &gt; 19/ ^* - A » London, S.W.l yiS'f' have received a copy of the express letter of the 22fth J uly from the Political Resident, Persian Government, concerning the proposals which were made to enable I.P.C. to obtain access to the Muscat Hinterland* We think that the conclusions drawn by the Political Resident from these proposals go too far. The essential point is that we want the Company to carry out a survey of the interior so that we can know whether it is worth while going on with oil prospecting. Such a survey may, in fact, show that there are no |suitable locations for drilling and the awkward political difficulties deferred to by the Political Resident wo ul d not then arise. For the purpose of making the survey, all that we require' is to buy the good will of the tribes concerned, so as to have free access to the area. There would not at this stage be ar^y question as suggested in . ^ - — - ^ —O ~ w w-*-&gt;✓** ^ ^ •*-** 0AOfjparagraph 3 of the letter of entering into separate agreements with the tribesmen for the exploitation of the oil deposits. It does not seem therefore to us that there is any necessity at this stage to raise with the Sultan the awkward question of making agreements with the tribes for the exploitation of oil. All we want is to have his agreement to the Company^ representatives buying their way into the area for exploring for oil. If, in fact, suitable locations for drilling are found, we will then, of course, have to face up to the problem of whether the value of obtaining oil in this area at an early date outweighs the advantages of maintaining the good-will of the present Sultan, but this problem hardly appears to arise at this stage. F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., India Office, V/hitehall, S.W.1. /Ifr- ■ ^ M- - 2 - If a face saving argument is required for the Sultan, we might point out to him that in this country, although H.M.G. owns any oil which may exist in the ground and issues licences for exploration and exploitation, the licensee must still pay the local landowner for access to his land* These arrangements dp not bring in question off the sovereign rights of H*M*G. We might even argue that such payments are covered by the term of the concession, which requires the Company to buy or lease lands for their purposes other than the uncultivated lands of the state, Whilq, no doubt, the areas in question are uncultivated lands, they may for face saving purposes be regarded as private property, I am sending copies of this letter to ’Tikeley at the Foreign Office, Jacobs of the War Office, and Johnston of the Air Ministry, Yours sincerely, C\J . ^ (J.W. FARRELL)*Minute, Please refer to the submission at Ext.4513/46* The Political Resident's comments on our suggested alternative plan are given in his express letter of 24th July below. The main point he brings out is that most of the Oman tribes are already anxious for the oil to be exploited, but are unwilling to share any of the p-oceeds with the Sultan. This is an aspect i The problem is summed up in the Political Resident's words in paragraph 4: M We want the oil urgently and the tribes are probably willing to let us have it provided we deal with them direct. On the other hand, if we do this we risk alienating the Sultan, who has been a good friend to us, for ever'. The right course now seems to be for the Political Resident to talk to the Sultan on the lines proposed in paragraph 5 of his express letter. A draft letter to the Foreign Office seeking their agreement to this course is submitted. y■ i' DRAFT LETTER. C.W. Baxter, Esq., G.M.G-. , M.C. Foreign Office, a W. 1. C Cc~*o)■ J V * &gt;' Copy to: K.L. Stock, Esq. Ivl/Fuel &amp; Power. Dear Baxter, You will no doubt have seen the Political Residents express letter No,C/525 Of 24th July on the subject of securing the co-operatioh of the independent bribes J fU in the development of the^ oil resources of Muscat and Qnan. 2. The new point brought out by the Politic Resident is that most of tiie Oman bribes are olitical ^hlready anxious for the oil to be Exploited, but are unwilling (jMt, t fir* T4j J . fto share any of the proceedis mth theTJultan. J TEe jrigkt course now seems to ub to be for the Political ( ****'^ij Resident to talk to the oultkan on the lines proposed in paragraph 5 of his expresjs letter. Will you kindly let me know whether you agree, in order that we may instruct the Political Residqit accordingly? 3* I am sending a copy ^&gt;f this letter to Stock at the 1 inis try of Fuel and Power.Si FILE COPY QftVRRf&lt;lni^T OF INDIA. 5255 (j^artment. W EXF^ESS^ETTER (AIR MAIL), (Tk) 8 xC C R i£ T, [N.B .—This is an ORIGINAL messige sent by AIR MAIL which providis a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram^ r&gt;U is apthenUcaled. bu the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] UII1C6 01 LrlC Political Resident, Persian Gulf, No* C/525 » To Repeated Dated &amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;. Camp, Bahrain, .the 24th July 19 46, * a / Reference 7 ? W 8 th July 19* C*h C 7.. - , fift fa 7 *- India Office impress 1-etter Ho . iilxt•4513/46 dated^.^ Secretary of State for India, London Government of India, New Belni. Political Agent, Muscat* 2. At first sight I must confess that I feel myself somewhat doubtful about the success of the proposed scheme even if the Sultan were to accept it. It must be remembered that tne majority of the tribes of the interior owe no allegiance of any kind to the Sultan and at present show little or no desire to come under his sway. I feel that if the expedition were to set out as proposed accompanied by an armed escort provided by the Sultan some kind of clash would be inevitable unless the ground had been long and carefully prepared before-hand, which is not the case. 3. With regard to paragraph 4 of the ilxpress Letter under reference so far as I know the ‘'want” is already there and some if not all of the tribes are anxious for any oil deposits in their country to be exploited. They want however to reap the full benefits of such exploitation themselves and not to share them with the Sultan* Lermitte reports that when he visited Baraimi last year some tribesmen from Ibri definitely invited him to explore their country. It would therefore I think be comparatively easy to enter into direct relations with the tribes. This however would have a disastrous effect on the Sultan and would probably result either in his abdication or in his retirement to Bhofar and neglect of the affairs of his State. His one ambition is to obtain control of the interior but he can do very little towards this until the Imam dies. Meanwhile he is unwilling to negotiate with the tribes of the interior for the ac^ces^ for oil or locust parties as this cannot be done without recognising the authority of the Imam which he is endeavouring to undermine. If we deal direct with the tribes now we shall certainly prejudice the Sultan's cnances of obtaining control over them after the Imam's death. 4 . The problem is a difficult one. We want the oil urgently and the tribes are probably willing to let us have it if we find it provided we deal with them direct. On the other (Signature) / hand &amp; 44. MGIPC—SI—2385(S&amp;P)MFP-(M-1744)—3-12-40—20,000. (Designation)y ■ — - 2 - # hand if we do this we risk alienating the Sultan, who has been a good friend to us, for ever, 5, I consider that the first essential is to discuss tue oituation with the Sultan as fully and frankly as poSoiolc, ^ e must first tell him tnat we cannot give him aSd: *- 3 ^ anGe schemes for subjugating Oman together with the reasons for our refusal. This will undoubtedly oe a great disappointment to him and may make subsequent negotiations more difficult but we must be frank: with him. The next step will oe to explain to him how urgently necessary it is lor us to searnh fpr oil in Oman and exploit any deposits that may be found there. we should tell him that we ueiieve it possible for us to do tnis by direct dealings witn the tribes and that we cannot afford to wait for the° Imam’s death which may not take place for some years. Ve should then ask him whether he has any scheme to suggest whereby we can obtain what we want ana at the same time save his face. 6 * . hermitte has informed me that the first expedition wliic^i his company wish to organise is planned to start from Has al Khaim ah and work southwards through Baraimi to DrianAv and Ibri. It will then work down the had i Howasinah and _ rom there turn northwards and explore both sides of tue main^range. Last year a P. C.L. Party visited Baraimi ana tne Jebel Hafit and was able to carry out its worx tnere witnout any serious interference vide paragraph 4 of enclosure to India Office Printed setter B o. jfiscto 3167/46 date^ tq.g 9 ta ^Lay—The Sultan was not asked to send a representative although he claims part of Baraimi and a representative of his was present when the Company carried out explorations there in 1938. On that occasion it was found that the representative had little or no influence locaiuy. Indications are, cf. paragraph 3 above, that the company would encounter little difficulty in continuing their explorations during the coming cold weather as far soutn as lori. ^o what extent they could carry out the rest of their programme as stated by Lermitte with or without tne oultan's co-operation I am not at present in a position to^say. I consider however tnat we must do all we can to obtain tne Sultan's acquiescence in their programme and that we must accept any reasonable proposal he makes to ensure that his interests cio not suffer. If he refuses to accord uis approval we snail have to decide whether we should carry on without it. This will be a difficult decision to make and on the whole I am inclined to think that at any rate xoi the time oeing we should not allow the Company to carry out tneir programme witnout the Sultan's concurrence but that we should go on pressing him to give it. 7. So far as I can see there is nothing in the Agreement of 24th June 1937 made between the Company and the Sultan to prevent the Company from approaching the Oman tribes direct but such action would be against tne spirit of Article 12 of the Agreement. Further it would appear tnat tne Company would be bound to pay the Sultan the full royalties etc. under Articles 6 and 11 of the Agreement and that any payments made by them to the tribes would be in addition to this. 8 . If His Majesty's Government approve the line of action proposed in paragraph 5 I would suggest that the l / Sultan3 early in September. The month -vit^^ dhan ! hl0 5 13 a ’° out t0 begin more or le3s coincides ltn jtle montu of August and the Political A„ent Muscat is on recess until the beginning of September. I ^ in any case hoping to visit Muscat myself as soon as the Political Agent returns there and can myself tahe part in tne talks with the Sultan, 3 cl. w.R.HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gull'. Attest ed. for Secretary to Political Residen the t, Persian Gulf.' :y DEPTL. No. r DRAFT TELEGRAM CYPHER W FMs*] (§) From Secretary of State for India, 1 C2 d ' j - ^ ° *—- To politic^ Resident in the Persian Gulf ? Repeated to Government of India, External Affairs J)ept« \ able SEND &amp;»■ ; i h DESPATCHED iU‘4-&lt;% . 19.HO 3 ST® W COPY TO ■ Art wo- ( £ $ (&lt;*&gt;)/) ffp/*f fw No lA't.'H Your telegram T/205 of 28th May. H.M.G. have careftiily examined proposal for promisijig Sult^T of* Muscat I^AP assistance pirrt irf ^ fnr ftntnhlinhlnc authority over interior^ They recognise ons in favour of proposal reas&lt; partiaJLarly as a means of hastening time when PCL will be e to survey possible oil bearing areas of interior hitherto inaccessible on the ground/’ They are however averse in principle from use threat foifce ifTindependent State even at the ruler’s request since this might well lead to bloodshed and wotild almost^certainly give rise to criticism and misinterpretation ^ ^ /S' s' s / / in interested quarters'. It might even lead to H.M.gT beiiig^ arraigned before Security Council of United Nations. Mere demoristration by^Fly-over would no^be sufficient unless it were 'a f fort a IaT 7 r CC&amp; QrtlO St*ft fM i4502) Wt. 41647—Pi7&lt; Gp. 620 accompanied by demand X e «g* by dropping le afle^s) for^submiss ion of tribe Men t&lt;T^ Sultbn^s authdidty, To^be effective such a demand wouldTliaVe' td^be^cfeirp 1by threat f ^ of yews action in the event of refusal to comply. /ItProm* Secretary of State for India. DRAFT EXPRESS LETTER To; Political Resident in Persian Gulf. Reference paragraph 2 of ray Repeated to: Government of India, External Affairs Dept. telegram l&amp;uYj of /Assistance and to Sultan of Muscat in establishing, Political Agent at Muscat authority over interior. 2. Following is plan that has been suggested. A small and well equipped expedition, to be led by a British Political Officer, and to include technical oil experts, (with suitable armed escort provided by the Sultan) should be despatched to gain contact with the leading Sheikhs in selected areas. It would be the task of the leader of the expedition to explain to them the Sultan* s intention to press forward with the resources and to impress on the local Sheikhs the advantages they would obtain intentions, this representative would take with him and distribute to the tribal leaders gifts calculated to make the greatest appeal to the recipients and promise that more would be forthcoming if the tribesmen agreed to co-operate. The expedition, being small, could probably not carry many gifts in kind and the first payments would no doubt have to be made largely in cash. The expedition might, hoiwver, usefully distribute some samples affording practical demonstration of the advantages of enhanced economic economic development of the country by the exploitation of potential oil from co-operating in this policy. . 3. As proof of the Sultan’s good ^ 1 /prosperityprosperity &lt;o£j^ the region, as shown by the higher standards of living now enjoyed by the . States, e.g. Bahrein, where oil development has already begun, 4* The essence of the scheme is that a 'want” should be created in the minds of the tribesmen and that they should be brought to connect the satisfaction of.this want with the exploitation of the oil deposits in such a manner that they will welcome, or at least not oppose, further expeditions. The Sultan is presumably better qualified than we are to know what would appeal to the tribesmen and as the scheme will be carried out under his authority, it is thought it wil4 appeal to him. It would cost him little or nothing and he would thereby not only begin to strengthen his influence over the tribesmen, but would also be opening the way to a possible substantial increase in his own revenues in the shape of oil royalties. 5, Another Arab ruler, Ibn Sand, has achieved conspicuous success in controlling his tribesmen by subsidies rather than by armed force, 6, Obviously, further consideration must be given to this scheme before we could eirbark upon it and I should accordingly be grateful for your observations at an early date. If you are reasonably satisfied that the Sultan* s acceptance * in principle of t his scheme could be obtained if sought, I should be grateful for your views on the following points;- (1) an indication of the areas to be visited (2) the. timing and duration of the operation (3) size and composition of the party; (4) strength and armament of the escort; and (5) approximate overall cost, which would /includeinclude cash subsidy to be placed at Sultan* s disposal, with particulars of the volume and nature of any goods which it is thought may appeal to the tribesmen* You should also state whether one expedition would suffice or whether a series of tours would have to be undertaken. 7. If cost is likely to be more than Oil Company might reasonably be expected to meet question of contribution by British or Indian revenues w#u3Ld hare - to be considered. &gt;vg''■I map Tel. No. Abbey 3411 Ext. a C.O0350/46/3.6. Indexed Dear Donaldson, P, L£ Copy AIR MINISTRY, King Charles Street, Whitehall, S.W.1. EXT 4513 )th June, 1946. We* have no amendments td 1 suggest to the note of your meeting on Muscat on v i^frh June. 'The word ^were” in the last line of para. 4 is an obvious misprint for 'was'. 2 . With regard to the telegram to the Political Resident, we feel that your draft fills the bill. As you say, it would be advantageous to shorten it, but perhaps this is easier said than done. We like Farrells suggestion for adding an opening sentence on oil at the beginning of para. 4, if only because of the ever-increasing importance of finding new oilfields. 3 3. I am sending a copy of this to Wikely, Farrell and Jacob. Yours sincerely, (G.S.N. JOHNSTON). E.P. Donaldson, Esq., India Office, King Charles Street, S.W.l.Tbe Secretary! 6 addreSSed ~ Q^Ig^RY OF FUEL AND POWER,1^) Telephone: Abbey 7000 Telegrams : Minfupo, Sowest, London.” Reference : Your Reference: Dea* jtnaldson. I '' •, OLEU^ 4 jf* A 4546 INDEXED s 24th June, 1 &gt;46 4R Division, 7 Millbank, London, S.W.l Y/ith reference to your letter of the 19th June concerning R.A.F. assistance to the Sultan of Muscat (3930/46), I concur in the draft minutes of the meeting* As regards the telegram which you propose to send to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, I would suggest that you make it clear that our desire is to get ahead with oil development as soon as possible and independently of the Imam dying, I would suggest, therefore, adding to the beginning of Paragraph 4 the following 'Moreover, it is very desirable that oil development should take place as soon as possible and any scheme dependent upon the death of the Imam may involve, in fact, a considerable delay. u I have also received Yfikeley^ alternative draft* From our point of view this would equally be satisfactory, except that it omits any reference to our own interest in obtaining access to these territories (your paragraph 2). The Political Resident might assume therefore that if the Sultan were content to drop his request for an R.A*F, demonstration, then the alternative proposal need not be considered* I think, therefore, that the considerations set out in your paragraph 2, plus the amendment I have suggested as regards the timing of oil development, should be included if Y/ikeley’s alternative draft is decided upon. I I also think that we should not attempt in this telegram to suggest alternative ways of meeting the cost* This hardly seems the E.P. Donaldson, India Office, Yfaitehall, S*W.1. /concern- 2 concern of the Political Resident, and until we know the amount involved, I think it v/ould be undesirable to put forward the idea of the treasury bearing any share of the cost, I suggest, therefore, omitting in Paragraph 3 of Wikeley’s draft from ’’and that” in line 9 to the words ,, R.A.P.'in line 15. It might possibly alscO^ undesirable even to suggest that a question internal to Muscat was appropriate for raising on the Security Council in the United Nations as has been done on paragraph 2 of the draft, I am sending copies of this letter to Johnston, Jacobs and Wikeley. iv* A Yours sincerely, J.. O. t^dL (j.w. parrell)(E 5692/86/91) FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.1. 22nd June, 1946. Dear Donaldson, Your letter No. Ext 3930/46 of 19th June about Luscat. I have ventured to redraft the telegram you propose to send to the Political Resident so &amp;s to bring out rather more clearly the idea underlying the proposed scheme. I enclose twD copies of this redraft which will, I hope, be of assistance to you. I am sending copies to Farrell, Johnston and Jacobs. Should we not tell the Treasury of what is JjuStA* J brewing? //• (T. Wikeley) E.P. Donaldson, Esq., India Office.T.v; June 9 1946 Political Feaiuent Persian Gulf. r i o • • • Datea* • • Repeat to: Govt- of India (External Affairs Dept •) (From the 6ecre- tary of Etate for India) Your telegram T.206 of 26th May: Muscat• n«M«G« have carefully examined tue propopal for ar■. ietance to be given to tne Sultan of Muec&amp;t by nuut 8 of E.A*F« uemon- rtralion, to re-aeeert lAs authority over recalcitrant tribesmen of the interior of Oman on the oceanion of the Imam’s death. £• H.H.G* are averse in principle from the use of the threat of force in an inae- iendent State, ever at the ruler’s request, since this might well leaa to blooashea and vsoulu almost certainly give lire to criticism aid misinterpretation in interested quartern# It might ever Irau to *M.G. teing arraigned t efore the Security Council of tar United Kationr. Mere demonstration by fly-over would not be sufficient for the purpose in view unless it were accompanied by a demand (e#g. by cropping leaflets) for remission of the tribesmen to the Sultan’e authority# To te effective such a deitand woula have to be backed by the threat of air action in the event of refusal to comply# presented might rucceed in Lringing the A^,, h // nS? ^ A? an alternative to force, w’e might JJtt&amp;fl Mm - Imari ana the trital Chiefs of Oman into line.in vIpw of the no aoutt impovrriBneG conaition of^e tril rs in iuestion* it ip thought that tiie ataourft need not be large ana that, accordingly, it may be po© Bible for trie Oil Company to supply tiie nFceseary funds. It is possible txiat H.M. Treasury might agree to bear part of the cost, k*. i * vv;.ich{would in any case be much]less tn^n the cost of giving tiif Sultan full “scale assistance by the K.A*F. The foliowing suggestion is therefore ht f orward for your consi.. i it ion# 4. A s trial 1 and well “equipped expedition, to be led by a British Political Officer, ana to include technical oil experts, (with suitable armed escort provided by the bultan) Should le despatched to gain contact with the leading Sheikh© in selected areas* It would be the task of the leader of the expedition to explain to them the Sultan’s intention to press forward with the economic development of the country by the exploitation of potential oil resources ana to impress on the local Sheikh* the aavantages they v.ouia oi tain from co-operating in this policy* 5. As proof of tne Sultan'* good intention*, his representative woulu take with him uika distribute to the tribal leaders gifts calculuteu to make the greatest appeal to the recipients and promise that more would be forthcoming if the tribesmen ugreea to co-operate. The expedition, being email, could probably not carry many gifts in kind and the first payments would no uoutt uuve to tr made largely in cash. Tne expedition might, however, useful]y distribute some sample* affording practical demonstrat ion/dcmonPtrt.tion of the advantages of eniianc ea econor;ic proeperit^ of the region, as shown by the higher rtar.daras of living no?- enjoyed ty the States, e.g« Bahrein, where oil develop ment has already begun. 6 . Tne es ence of the cheme ie that &amp; ’’want’* enoula be created in ti*e minae of the tribesmen ana that they enoulu be brought to connect the Patisfaction of this want with the exploitation of the oil deposits in such a manner that they will v«elcome, or at least not opnose, further uitione• The fultan is presumably better qualified than v,e aie t&gt; v/nat would appeal to tne tribesmen ana as tne scheme will be carried out unuer hie authority, it is thought it will appeal to him. It would coet aim little or notning ana ue would thereby not only begin to strengthen his influence ovfr the tribesmen, but would also be opening the way to a possible substantial increase in his own revenues in the shape of oil royalties. ®. Another Arab r wler. Ion baud, a as achieved conspicuous success in controlling his tribesmen ty subsidies rather than bj armed force. be given to tnir scheme before we/emtark aoon it ana I should accordingly be grateful for your observations at an early date. If you are reae marly satisfied that the Sultan’s acceptance in principle of thie scheme can re 8. Obviously, further consideration murty^ur virws on the following points an indicttion of the reas to be visited; (4j strength and arraaiaent of the escort; and ( l o) approximate overall cost, wnich would include casa subsiuy to be placed at Sultan's disposal, with particulars of the volume ana nature of any gooas whicn it is thought may a rai to tne tritesiien* You should also state whether one expedition would suffice or whether a series of tours would have to be unaertaken. 9. Question of incidence of Vxpenaiture need not be considered at t:.is stage, tut it is realised that Indian revenues cannot in present circum 0 tances be exoectnd to c ntrit ute any large share the cost, since results, if achie ved, “ re H^ly to advance British rather than Indian interests. (£) the timing and duration of the opf ration (2) size and cotnpoeitlon of trie party;1 . Please refer to the submission at Ext. 353 Q/ 46 * 2. An interdepartmental ireeting was held on June 12th, and draft minutes will be found below. It will be seen that the general feeling of the meeting was against promising the Sultan R,A,P. support. Prom the point of view of obtaining access to Muscat's oil resources it was agreed that it was, in principle, desirable to help the Sultan to establish his authority over the interior, but the amount of the oil resources was as yet unknown, and the date of the Imam's death, on which the Sultan's plans hinged, was quite uncertain. Various suggestions were made for helping the Oil Co:i£&gt;any to obtain access to the interior for surveying the ground. ^ 3* The draft telegram below is subject to the concurrence of the various departments represented at the meeting. /u 0J “tx ^ (k*. 'tt /W/u^ ^ AT Co. Cf Alx Qst^rys. civ lx+s ^ ^ ^ J*Jt0CjU*o . *&gt;&lt;T*ux-ir/U*J' fcyjrtyU- *■ ScAaa^ji f U^trflftrulc^ (oOV^A u*(z t-A / tivC 0~X^~e ~d^0. (xci&lt;K^/i r ~flbu+Jc, «'/ ft (T^X ^ crt^tA^-C , fiv. ^ /*&lt;• a.G-.S.N. Johnston, Esq., Air Ministry. DR^T t« JIN 1146 Dear Johnston, I enclose herewith a draft note of the meeting on June 12th about R.A.F. assistance to the Sultan of iviuscat, together with draft tele grain to the Political Resident. I should be grateful if you would let me know 0^- UK (uit ^ f. Ui.lktl* ; . ftV f 'ffP’ . factK’, * ? D P JUN I946 i# 1 the Air Ministry have any amendments to suggest to the note, and whether they concur in the draft telegram. I am sending a copy of this letter to Wikeley, Farrell and Jacobs, and would be grateful if they would inform me likewise. &gt; ul&lt;«^ ouy (rt ^ SHYlAJUkJl-*&gt;4r- SLjTy%e&lt;AMs} » ^4) S. p. DONAL***'*zfc&lt;M Note of a ivieeting held at the India Office on 12 th June, 1946* Question of promising R.A.P. assistance to the Sultan of Muscat to enable him to consolidate his authority over the interior of Oman on the death of the Imam, FRjJSj^NT : Mr, E.P. Donaluson Mr, G-.S.N. Johnston J \7ing-Goramander YuleJ* Mr. T. W ikeley - Ivlr. J.W. Farrell Ivlajor G-.S.L. Jacobs. . Colonel Carter } Mr. F.A.K. Harris onJ ( India Office) In the Chair IilinisU^ j ' [Air liinistry|| Foreign Office^ 'Ministry of Fuel &amp; Powerjr Yar Office^ ^ ■ia QfP±^g-&lt; India Office|f Mrx 1 • The Chairman said that the main question which had to be considered was whether the advantages of lerding the Sultan the assistance of the R.A.F, to enable him tb establish his authority in the interior outweighed the disadvantages of possible embarrassing publicity. The timing of the Sultan* s projected operations for the re-establishment of his authority was dependent on the death of the Imam, which might occur at any time, though when was quite uncertain. 2. Mr, Wikeley said that the Foreign Secretary was opposed to the use of the R.A.F. for operations against recalcitrant tribesmen. Mj^the authority to take effective It was agreed that demonstration flights by themselves, €rcJ\ iSUs*-c/~ ) u the R.A.F. i^aaring irt r^gr.-rva/ the authc actioiuwere not a practical proposition. Major Jacobs said that the War Office shared the Foreign Office* s misgivings. Mr. Farrel l said that the Ministry of Fuel and Paver regarded it as a matter of urgency to press on with the development of new oil respurces in the Middle East, and that there were particular advantages in development by a British oil company such as P.C.L., in which there was Aiiierican participation. From the strategic S&gt; aspect Muscat was v/ell placed, better jgay than Koweit or South Persia. The M.F.P. felt that it was desirable to give P.Q.L. the fullest possible support in the development of Muscat’s oil resources. If/kA ft r p .,. ^ ■ \*~jr»+*M *** t yu^ ‘^\ ^ ^ ; V\ If they could achieve nothing the Company rni^at he inclined to give up their concession. JT. On the question of oil development the meeting discussed the possibility of a direct approach being made to the Imam and local ^ Sheikhj 4 The^objection to such an independent approach was, as mentioned by the Political Resident in his telegram No.Ty^02 of 2?th May, that it would prejudice the eventual success of the aA . hr Sultan* s plans # -mny^ ftn-u-»ni-.Agiaq - 4 ft work^^ through the Sultan. l&lt;Ir. Wikeley suggested that a possible way &gt;^the Sultan C extendi^fi his influence into the interior, thereby miabliiig- oil .oui^ey party tn ent^y, would be by the judicious distribution of gifts, either of money or goods, to influential chiefs. Money for this purpose mi^it be provided either by the t Oil Coiipany, or if they were unwilling by H.M.G., if the Treasury ase willing to agree. It was agreed that this suggestion might be put to the Political Resident. /$. Mr. Far rell suggested that the R.A.P. mi^it be able to help the Oil Company to carry out an aerial survey. Mr. J ohns ten said that the R.A.P. could probably not undertake such a comnitment if it were at all extensive. It was agreed, however,^it wiii be worth while asking the Conrpaiy whether assistance from the R.A.P. would be of any use to them, if they had not their am aircraft for the purpose. The conclusions of the meeting were as follows: (a) The reasons in favour of premising the Sultan R.A.P. assistance at this stage, when the date of the Imam* s death could not be foretold, were not solidly enough grounded to outweigh the disadvantages .ffi/If, TllWUUui'j goed ev»d ■ ooig^Hge produced of the existence in Muscat of oil supplies in considerable quantities, then theremi^htDe a case for reconsidering later, on strategi 9 **gfounds, the decision against promising the Sultan th^gupport of the R.A.P. (b)/^ /v4W6v*^ (&amp; urni) '■ £uch assistance/ as v/as possible should be given * - to the Oil Company to carry out a pi’olicm'mi^r survey^/in order to assess the oil prospects of Oman, and they mi^t be asked whether the R.A.P. could give them any useful assistance in this direction. AvtmjUf -fr* The possibility of providing the Sultan witi^gifts to distribute to local chiefs mi^it be considered in this connection. W* L&amp;AjmA** 4 1ft. The India Office undertook to discuss the mat ter/with /Cu, iV*iv* ► representatives of P.C .L. ,^and^circulatey^draft telegram to the Political_Resicient*/for the~^concurrence oFthe^epau^bments^^ represented at the meeting^fry DEPTL. No. DRAFT TELEGRAM CYPHER Q.I.P. From Secretary of State r 'Pq Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Repeated to Grpvernment of India, External Affairs Dept. SEND DESPATCHED 19. COPY TO Foreign Office, Air Ministry, War Office, Ministry of Fuel.. &amp;. Power War Staff (4371) Wt. 41648—PI72 25m. 12/44 G.S.St. Gp. 620 No. Your telegram No. / . Muscat. H.M.G-. have carefully examined proposal for assistance to be given to Sultan of Muscat, by means of R.A.F. demonstration, to reassert his authority over recalcitrant tribesmen of the interior of Oman on the occasion of the Imam* s death. 2. They fully recognise untnuln.'iniftiirti advantages to be gained both from political angle of enhancing Sultan's prestige and extending his sway over territories where his writ does not at present run and^/frcm economic standpoint by (a) enabling P.C.L. to carry out search for oil bearing areas in potentially promising places in Oman Hinterland not hitherto accessible to ground exploration,and (b) ty promoting oil development in Oman generally so as to provide State with revenues enabling Sultan to consolidate his authority and introduce improvements in his administration. 3. Nevertheless they are averse in principle from use of threat of force in independent State even at the Ruler's request since this might well lead to bloodshed and would almost certainly give rise to criticism and misinterpretation in interested quarters. Mere demonstration by fly-over would not be sufficient unless it were accompanied by demand^ e.g. by dropping leaflets)far submission of the tribesmen to Sultan's authority. Such demand would/ Vwould have to be backed by threat of air action in the event of failure to oomply* 4* iroreover, II. 1*.f thiitr air demonstration wuld either be most effective or least expensive method of achieving object ^ ' n HfACc red in paragraph 2 above. • SJa* 5 j/prefer to consider whether any practicable alternatives t p ***~ 2 - can be devisecJ and suggest that TjWLtaeu you ijgjf™i , h'T scheme on following rlUnJL tzLejKfiA* Y (fyUt u ^ 6rvJj&gt; 1 ti r r ii vliill ^ i ini prnrtii-r jmi nhrmlri senk ®n&gt;&lt;TkAJ uC- (k covw«I~j Sultan’s consentIto the despatch of a small . Miy^e^uipped expedition, to be led byjPolitical . ^-'SEdfcf, ^to include technical oil jlM-A d^ experts, with suitable aimed escor^ to gain contact with leading Shaikhs in selected areas* It would be task of leader to explain to them His Highness’s intention to press forward with economic development of the country by exploitation of potential oil resources and to impress on local Shaikhs necessity far 'tom to- artrfriu^ 3 i /co~ op era ityin thi.s policy. 5* Party would have to be furnished with adequate financial resources and be authorised to offer suitable inducement in Sultan’s naraft to achieve desired results* Supplies of . /^k consumpWp*» goods wuld also be~requirecT^se that material advantages of enhanced economic prosperity of the region as shown by higher standards of living now enjoyed by States, e.g. Bahrein where oil development has already been begun, oeuld be gi'ycn prkcfcical dBiinjunsU-atiun*’ 6 . If,, affccy diooapoiono GuPfegat* yotr-are rt Skto fCtj 5*+* ohlo ■■mmm twi acceptance in principle of scheme/ { ii 3 l ■rflscheme outlined ahove^ detailed proposals should be prepared for nay consideration. These should indicate areas to be visited, timing arri duration of the operation, size and composition of the party, strength and armament of the escort and approximate overall cost which would include cash subsidy to be placed at Sultan's disposal to be supplied. It should also be stated whether one expedition would suffice or if a series of tours would have to be undertaken. 7. Question of incidence of expenditure need not be considered at this stage, but it is realised that Indian revenues cannot in present circumstances be expected to contribute any large share of cost since results to be achieved are likely to advance British rather than Indian with particulars of volume and nature of goods interests,.DEPTL. No. EJ/Vllp/^C DRAFT TELEGRAM CQBPr CYPHER From S.eQ.ret&amp;xy of.State...for..India.. To Pp lit ical Res idea t. ..in., the. Persian Gulf, Bahrein. Repeated to Ck.verit.jont of India, External Affairs Dept. SEND DESPATCHED 19 COPY TO Foreign Office Mr. Yfikeley Air Ministry Mr. Johnston . Jar Office 1 ajor Jacobs '$*&amp;)I M.F.P. Mr. Farrell Treasury Mr. James Admiralty Mr. Dodds tVawifvJj- ' (4371) Wt. 41643—P172 25m. 12/44 G.S.St. Gp. 620 (5J) No. SZC/l&amp;T- • Addressed Political Resident repeated Government of India. Your telegram T/205 of 28th nay, and. connected correspondence. R.A.F. assistance to Sultan of Muscat. 2. H.M.G-. have considered matter further-, but V feel that reasons in/favour of promising the Sultan R.A.F. assistance at this stage, when the date of the I/nam* s death is^uncertain, are not solidly enough grounded to outweigh the disadvantages /of exposing thei.(selves to charges which might ] 6 e gravely embarrassing. could be i/roduced of^e^istence in iilusc^kt^of 7 / oil suppE^jg^in large quantitj^R there might be a p or reconsinerma^decision at a later t i^in any case desirable to give P.C.L. everj assistance to survey the interior as soon 3. as jpssible. Aerial survey should give them soup information, but for coiplete survey ground party is of course essential. In the li^it ofj the foregoing I should be glad if you would CL*) [idf imkwY P+ &gt;nsider^practinability of following suggestions.' (a) Visit by a small geological survey party /acconqpanied by a political officer to certain selected areas in the interior. (b) The provision to the Sulta^either by Oil Gompany or if they were unwilling by H.M.G.^of money for the distribution of gifts either in tt&amp; cUuh&gt; muney or goods to influence pareone in the interior. This might help the Sultan to extend/extend his influence by peaceful means, and make it possible for Oil Conpar^r to gain access to interior at an earlier date,, 4 * I must leave to you manner of approach to Sultan, but I trust that you will make clear k.M.G-'s veiy real difficulties in the matter.Fext, ;® 0) FILt-Cl'* 1 , 3y3t) . GTriiiiR (O.T.r.). SiiiCRIiiT, | ■ V Political Agent, Muscat, ^— L~« . , / fo Political Resident, at Banrain. TiiliSGRAi Prom To No. G 277. Bated 29th received 30th May 1946. rtf. Your telegram T/206. Assistance to Sultan. Imam’s age is between 60 and 62. He is generally ** not sent to India Off ice ^ reported to be frail and incapable of any great exertion. His weak condition (which is confirmed by Thoms) maxes it possible that an illness such as malaria would result in his death. Impression I have formed is that no one would * be surprised to hear of his sudden demise. - POUTICiil - To. G/175. Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Gamp, Bahrain, Bated the 50th Kay 1946. 311* Copy forwarded, with compliments, to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India) ✓ The India Office, London, The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Bepartment, New Delhi, with reference to Political Resident’s telegram No. T/205 dated the 28th May 1946. RHL.FILE COPY^ inward telegram fc 15034 ^ ^46 /Hotted to Externa . Copies to Telegraph EXT 3906 Dept Branch and MaiL Room* /i r Prom To' Dated Received V. WORD CODE TELEGRAM Political Agent, Muscat fa-j I, I Si.' Oryjy ^k^nt/^cSArrJL' Secretary of State for India* i.TK Muscat 09«30 hours, 4th June 1946* 14*10 hours, 4th June 1946« 1&amp; &lt;?). o. % G.263 Circular* .1 am leaving for recess to Karachi* 2 2. Until further notice correspondence requiring my personal attention should he addressed to me care of Chief, Secretary, Government of' Sind*ifiJK Tel. No.: Whitehall 1234 Your Reference Treasury Reference? ^ IREASURY CHAMBERS, GREAT GEORGE STREET, LONDON, S.W.l. J Treasury Referenc ^.*.. i .-i _ , - 4th June 1946 I refer to your letter to Johnston, Air Ministry, of 3^t May about assistance to the Sultan of Muscat. Dear Harrison, So far as we can judge the Treasury are not likely to he needed at your proposed meeting, hut I should he grateful if you would let us have a copy of the note of the meeting so that we can keep in touch with developments. WJbu&amp;Y Yours sincerely, F.A.K. Harrison Esq., H &gt; India Office. l /fa ^4Whitehall 9400 Ext 1769. Prom Major G.3.L. Jacobs, ' The War Office, GS(W)l V/hitehall S. W.l. 4th June, 1946 03(^)1/9223 With reference to our telephone conversation regarding the meeting to be held at India Office on 'Wednesday, 12th June, on the subject of assistance to Sultan of Muscat and Oman* We agreed that I should not attend as there -would be no matters of War Office concern to discuss, but if in the mean time it became essential for me to be present you would let me know. &lt;Whitehall 9000. Extension* 808. Admiralty, S.W.l. £/- June, 1946. Dear Harrison, Thank you for sending me a copy of your letter to Johnston about assistance to the Sultan of Auscat. 2 . I hardly think we need attend your meetin-; on the 12th of June hut we should like to he kept in touch with developments. Yours sincerely, F.A.i:. Harrison, Esy. , India Office, London, S.W.l. GGBD/PFi Note_by Sir D. Monteath dated 28th Mav With regard to P.S.O.*s note it should be remembered that, as the earlier papers show especially Ext.735/46, the Sultan's intention is to make no move till the Imam's death is announced. ‘rhere will then be a period during which the Sheikhs argue as to the recognition of a successor Imam. It is at that juncture that the Sultan (who is already 'working on' some of the Sheikhs by diplomacy) proposes to assert himself by seizing certain fortresses and strong points - no doubt with the connivance of such Sheikhs as he has 'won over'. But in the conditions of Oman one does not win any one over effectively without being able to show a strong fist in the velvet glove. The Sultan's aim is to establish his authority without bloodshed by a show of overwhelming force: and to establish it not over any Imam but over the Sheikhs before they have selected an Imam round whom to rally. I think this first step is to have the issues examined departmentally: and I commend the draft.Please see Political Resident*s telegrams Nos .681 and 682 and the minuting above them. The Government of India's comments have now been received and are given in their telegram No.-4460 of 16th May. They leave to H.M.G. the question of considering R.A.F. assistance* The main considerations are set out in the attached draft letter to the Air Ministry which suggests an inter-departaiental meeting to consider the matter. From H.M.G.*s point of view, perhaps^ the most important consideration is the fact that unless we take this opportunity of helping the Sultan to re-establish his authority any possibility of developing Muscat's oil resources for sane years to come will vanish since the Oil Company will be unable to obtain access to the interior. It is understood from the Ministry of Fuel and Power that, so far as the Middle East is concerned, the oil resources of Eastern Arabia are now regarded as having an increased importance from the strategical point of view since they are less likely, ^ than the oilfields of Iraq and South Western Persia,^ to be put out of action in the first stages of any future war. This consideration would apply to Muscat even more than those parts of Arabia nearer to the ^ , /I /£» ow? ; 2^^n head of the Persian Gulf. Cn the whole, therefore, Pfl't Mbo it seems desirable that we should support the Political ^ *** Resident’s arguments in favour of thsu^Sultan being given the assurance^ he desires aboutJus£n{y the R.A.F. With regard to the Sultan's request for an assurance about the further supply of rifles and ammunition referred to in paragraph 3 of the Political Resident's telegram No.681, we may perhaps agree with the Government of India's ccmmentsin paragraph 3 of their telegram N 0 . 446 O that this request is too imprecise for consideration. L War Staff Per observations. '-j if hill ^ ^ £ j I still dislike the whole business of aiding and abetting the Sultan - a secular leader against the Imam - a religious leader. It seems to me to be a seeuxar xea-aei** l cxLnau , — . —~~ ■ ~ —- - especially tricky if our assistance is to take the form of air action which could not be restricted to demonstrations if the patients called our bluff. fccvmj Is it really true that the source of oil supply in the hinterland of I j, Oman can be made available to us only by helping the Sultan to overwhelm e / X n fi Imam by force? If so, it is a question of weighing up the material whiu*; advantages against the political risks, which strike me as being very real. I agree with your draft. I would like the War Staff to be represented at the Meeting - either the B.G.S. or myself. •-h i~€jK 4aINDIA OFFICE, Fxt, 3550/4-6 . SECRET V/HITEHALL, S.W. 1. 3 l(l~ May, 1946. i'. r itn reference to the Meeting held at the India Office on April 3rd on the subject of the assistance to the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, you will now have seen copies of the Political Resident's telegrams Nos, 681—2 in which he urges reconsideration of the line taken at our meeting, namely that it was undesirable to make any advance commitment to the Sultan regarding assistance by the R,A,F, (The Government of India's telegram No, 4460 of 16 th May and the Political / Resident's T/205 of 28th .-vy, of which I attach spare copies are also relevant). -*- s clear irom the Political Resident's telegrams Nos, 681-2 that whether the Sultan does or does not^pursue his plans for the re-establishment of his authority in the interior depends on v/hether we can give him the desired assurance about the use of the R.A.F. There is, as the Political Resident points out, a precedent for the use of the R. A. F. against recalcitrant tribesmen in Oman, since in 1932 air action, after the dropping of warning notices to avoid loss of life as in the case of operations against tribesmen on the N.W.F. of India, was authorised. In point of fact on that occasion it was not actually necessary to drop bombs since the preliminary flights had the desired effect. The Political Resident wrote at the time; 'There is no doubt that the flights of aircraft over Jaalan had an enormous moral effect; hitherto these tribes residing in the interior and largely have considered themselves invulnerable. They now realise that they are not'. It is, however, I think, fairly clear that if we are to give an assurance to the Sultan Mbout the use of the R. A. F. we cannot limit our undertaking merely to demonstration flights since if the tribesmen Once succeeded/ G. S.N. Johnston, Esq., Air Ministry,0 (jy once succeeded in calling our bluff the value of any further demonstration flights \vould be negligible. (This is not to say that, in point of fact, anything more than demonstrations would actually be required). The exact wording of any assurance to be given to the Sultan will also have to be carefully considered and it does not seem very likely that he will be satisfied with a stipulation that the flights should be at the sole discretion of the R. A. F. unless something is also added to the effect that due regard will be paid to the v/ishes of the Sultan. 3. The question is, therefore, whether H.M.G-. consider that the advantages v/hich would accrue to them from the Sultan re-establishing his authority over the interior outweigh' the possible disadvantages of embarrassing publicity being given to the use of the R.A.F. in Oman. It is difficult to estimate in advance the likelihood of publicity being entailed, but if action were confined to the interior the chances would not seem to be very large. On the other hand, the account which Petroleum Concessions Limited have given of their recent discussions with the Sultan (see India Office telegram No. 8528 of 5th May and the Political Resident’s telegram No. T/202 of / 27th May of which copies are enclosed) seems to suggest that unless we take this opportunity of helping the Sultan to re-establish his authority there will be no possibility of our developing the oil resources of the interior of Oman for several years at least. I understand that Muscat and Oman may, from its strategic situation, be of considerable importance to H.M.G. as a source of oil supply and this point will clearly have to be given serious consideration in arriving at a decision. 4. There is also the further point about the Sultan's request for additional supplies for his Levies and irregular forces referred to in paragraph 3 of the Political Resident’s telegram No. 681, but in view of the Resident's further comments in his telegram T/205 perhaps this may be left over for the present. 5 . I suggest that the most suitable way of considering the matter would be by a further meeting of officials of the Departments/0 (g) - 3 - Departments concerned viz. Air Ministry, Foreign Office, Ministry of Fuel and Power, War Office and India Office with the Admiralty if they care to attend, and would propose 11 a.m. on Wednesday, 12th June, in the Committee Room here. I am accordingly sending a copy of this letter to Wikeley, Stock, Jacobs and Dodds and would be glad if they would let me know whether they would be ready to attend. ¥ ? ~j A, f t C W 5 V* &gt; r A. K. HARRISON/Draft Paper. EXTERNAL Departmen s~\ G*S.N. Johns ton. Esq*, Air Ministry. SECRET (*- r \ %r*£ &lt;y+ * Copy to : T* Wikeley x (F*0. ) v. K.L.Stock (M.P.P.) Major G-.S.L*Jacobs (War j r ), VQ iildJUx 'cr • cxu-uuo ^ tl ^ G-.C^B*Dodds (Admiralty) R.L.M.James (Treasury) Office/ IViu . 0 ^Vll!96 With reference to the Meeting held at the India Office on April 3rd on the subject of the assistance to the Sultan 7 -tTZvkAw of Muscal/, you will now have seen copies of the Political Resident’s telegrams Nos.681-2 in which he urges reconsideration of the line taicen at our meeting ^hat it was undesirable to make any advance^ i canmitment to the Sultan regarding assistance by the R.A.F ' 2. It is clear frcm the Political Resident’s! ^ telegrams Nos.681-2 that thu quustimi whether the Sultan does or does not pursue his plans for the re-establishment of his authority in the interior depends on whether we can give him the desired assurance about the use of the R.A.F. There is, as the i (10337) Wt.l4054/P.104 10,000 3/39 A.* E.YY.LUi. Gp.685 (11764) Wt.26696/I\28:&gt; 10,000 9/39 Political Resident points out, a precedent for the use of the R.A.F. against recalci trant tribesmen in Qnan^since in 1932 air action, after the dropping of warning r notices to avoid loss of life.* as in the yt case of operations against tribesmen on the N.W.F. of India, was authorised. In point of fact^ on that occasion^ it was not actually necessary to drop bombs since the preliminary flights had the desired affect. The Political Resident wrote at the time / M There is no doubt that the flights of aircraft over Jaalan had an enormous moral effect/1 ( Effect; hitherto th^se tribes bb siding im the interior and largely self-supporting have considered themselves invulnerable. They now realise that they are not'. It is, however, I think, fairly clear that if we are to give an assurance to the Sultan about the use of the R.A.P* we cannot limit our undertaking merely to demonstration flights since if the tribesmen once succeeded in calling our bluff the value of any further demonstration flights would be negligible , (this is not to say that, in point of fact, anything more than demonstrations would actually be required). The exact wording of any assurance to be given to the Sultan will also have to be carefully considered and it does not seem very likely that he will be satisfied with a stipulation that the flights should be at the sole discretion due regard will be paid to the doeiiiPOB of the R.A.P. unless it/is also added^that of the Sultan* The question is,therefore, whether fo&gt;Jk ! nrr rn-rr^r^ 1 i~ -th~ H-H-ir— of embarrassing publicity being given to the use of the R.A.P. the advantages which would accrue to • ^ * them from the Sultan re-establishing his authority over the inter! IT 1 It is difficult to estimate in advancefthe likelihood of publicity being entailed, but if action were confined to the interior the chances would not seem to be very large. On the other hand, it Is clear—the account which a LPetroleum Concessions Limited have given of their /X /C * r r * rr recent discussions with the Sultan (see India Office telegram No.8528 of Jjth Maylof which^ copj^ie enclosed)^that unless we take this opportunity of helping the Sultan to re-establish his authority there will be no possibility of our developing the oil resources of the interior of Muscat- for several years at least. I understand ( £ 1) y that Muscat may, from its strategic situation, be of considerable importance to H.M.G. as a source of oil supply and this point will clearly have to be given serious consideration in arriving at a decision. , 4. There is also the further point about the Sultan*s request for additional, supplies for his Levies and^regular forces referred to in paragraph 3 of the Political Hesident's telegram No.681$, the Government^of^India's comments on^tfiis are given ip^qSaragraph 3 of their&gt;€legram No.4460 , which we are inclin^cl to agree. 5 . I suggest that the most suitable way of considering the matter would be by a further meeting ofjisaxas* concerned viz. Air Ministry, Foreign Office, Ministry of Fuel and Power, War Office and India Office^poooibly with the addition- Cji&amp;T y oJXju*} the Admiralt^and would propose tl ^ * in the Committee Room here. » A ' ir-i' i (l am accordingly sending a copy of this letter to Wikeley, Stock, Jacobs and Dodds and would be glad if they would let me know whether they would be ready to attend# j to attend* lUutUtSivi - t ~ 0 w' ^2 * v » fcsrfH £ a# 252 3 Z,o Z 3*121*. 3 0 MAY 1948/=. 0 . INWARD TELEGRAM !tv,D£X£t r 3 \ ' ~ ■ ' FILE COP'* V * 3 4 5 &amp; Allotted to internal Department • ( 5 op i e s ~c 1 r c u la t. e d * Prom To H- 3 peateci to Dated Deceived CYPHER TELBORAM (O.T.P.) Political Resident in the Persian Oulf Secretary of State for India Government of India Bahrein, 13#50 hours, 28th May 1946 19*30 hours, 2Qth May 1946 No » T/ ^ P 0 © o Government cf India telegram 4460, May 16th® Assistance to Sultan of Muscat® ~ 2 * Reference paragraph 3 * I do not read paragraph 6 and paragraph 8 of residency lett er No,64S« J anuary 15th, as meaning that arms and ammunition are required for levies only. 1 □ h P 1 -sd.has' confirmed this and states rifles and ammunition, hut net, of course, mortars and machine guns, are required for the irregular forces, viz., friendly tx v iheamen viiich it is the Sultanas intention to employ. 3. Pntil assurance of direct support hy R.A.R. Is given, Buitan does not propose to prepare detailed plans in consultation with military adviser, cf* paragraph 2 Muscat telegram repeated under Prior 1 s tele gram 681, May 3rd . In the circumstances, it is difficult to be precise aDous additional supplies that may bo required for levies but Political Agent reports that Sultan will not claim substantial increase in his regular forces and that additional requirements of rifles for levies aro not lihely to exceed 200 . 4. The main desideratum at present is an early and favourable reply to Sultan regarding use of R.A.F., cf. paragraph 3 my telegra m T202 1 Mgv 27th &gt; and I would propose, untfl this matter has been decillecl, consideration of other points' should ba suspended** m INWARD TElrEGRAM* ' ♦ r-x. « - , 1 Allottee! to Sxterml B *f~x J&amp; 3726 trtment* /i c 143S6. CYPHDH TilLi gC f RAIvi (0 &gt;. T, P.) ^ From Political Resident in tiie Persian G-ulf. To Secretary of State for India, Repeated to Government of India, Rated Bahrain* 14.C0 hours, 3?th Iv!ay,1946, Received 16,10 hours, 2 Yth May,1946V Ho,T/ 2 C 2 , Your telegram 35R8 May 6 th* Visits of P.C.L- representative to Muscat* 3 , 1 do not consider there is any likelihood of Sul tan mod ify ing .his attitude until he has extended his influence’over interior of Oman* It is. true 7 /e have promised him assistance to this end hut he is awaiting •(?Imam) 'before making a move vide paragraph. 4 of Prior’s letter 84S January 15th, Meantime any attempt to force the pace or tO) enter into separate negotiations with Imam or Sheikhs is likely to prejudice eventual success of Sultan*s plans, I would suggest^ therefore that the Company should 'be advised_ that until the situation develops they should limittheir activities to areas to which Sultan has agreed and where his writ runs. It will be noted with reference to para Taph 5 ( 2 ) of your telegram that he has no objection to'air surveys, r-v provided aircraft do not fly too low, vide (corrupt group) Prior v s letter 560 S May 6 th* 3* Paragraph 5 of your telegram serves to emphasise importance of (a) expediting supply to Sultan of arms and ammunition already promised and (b) giving him favourable reply regarding assistance by R.A.F., vide correspondence ending with Government of India r s telegram 4460 May 16th* With regard to (a) I am pressing (??olitical Agent),Muscat, to furnish information asked for in Government of India telegram 5734 April 24th.Clarence House, Katthew Parkier Street, S. Y/ # 1 . 23 rd Hay, 1946. F12179/46 Dear James, Y/ill you kindly refer to your letter of the 10th April, Ho. S. 45336 to Donaldson about the adjustment of the cost of the Muscat subsidies. I have discussed the matter vdth Coburn, who is at present in this country, and he agrees that in deference to 3 'our wishes the adjustment may be made through the Defence Plan. I am sending a copy of this letter to Key and to Major Jacobs, Var Office. Yours sincerely, R.L.K.James Esq, Treasury Chambers, C-reat George Street, S.k. 1. (Sgd.) R.S.Brown.... v De a r-' Harrison, ■ROTHH e , rl 3'! 5 r * _E GORY V IGN OFFICE, S.W. 1. 1^3th May, 1946. •/..Pledge*';refer to the political Resident’s telegrams Hos. 681 and 682 of 3rd May. ?&gt;;&gt;'' x\ — th^t the Sultan of Muscat desires, and that:.the Political Resident recommends, the promise of Royal Air Force assistance on a scale eons'iderably greater than that we have so far contemplated. Our understanding of the position is that such assistance should be limitea to demonstration flights at the discretion of the Air Ministry. Y/e should have to think very carefully before we could agree to the participation of the R.A.F. in active operations against the Sultan’s recalcitrant subjects which is what both the Sultan and Prior seem to contemplate. In the circumstances we v/ould be grateful if we could be consulted before any reply is sent to the telegrans under reference.(9828) Wt.9938/P.126 6,000 (2 BorteJ 4/39 A.A E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 V / ^ 4a/^ &amp;A /(Mfwu fctt'Jri* ffM/tJ ^ ^ f* Minute Paper. ^ Department, ^tc $S' \[\^ /Lee ^ ,»/ ■■ tUfc tJn**' ^ hu i4&lt;—*■ / X ^ 'UA/y/tt+ss Lus. tftC-u-W “tov' ^ v ^(^ s . T7- Assistance to the Sultan of Muscat. It is understood that Mr. Henderson would like a note on this subject in connection with the Political Resident's telegrams Nos. 681 and 682. The background of this question is dealt with at length in the submission at Ext. 735/46. Very briefly the position is as follows: the Sultan of Muscat, who is an independent ruler in special, treaty relations with H.M.G-., exercises his authority over only a very small part of his extensive dominions. His effective authority is, in practice, confined to the coastal areas while the tribes of the mountainous and desert interior look to the Imam of Muscat ^insofar as they look to anyone^ as their ruler. The present relationship between the Sultan —of T mfl m is governed by a working agreement arrived at in 1920 (after the rebellion of the tribes at the time of the war when H.M.G-. were compelled to give armed assistance to the Sultan to enable him to maintain himself) whereby the '• • n Sultan undertook not to interfere in the asternal affairs of Oman while the tribes agreed to remain in peace and amity with the Sultan's Government. The Imam is now expected not a e • a to live much longer and the Sultan sees an opportunity with his death of establishing his/authority wtt* the tribes of the interior. He recently asked the Political Resident whether H.M.G. could support him to this end by making available to him supplies of arms and British officers to train his levies. In return for this support he promised that he would bind himself and his heirs for the future to obtain advisers TTot 4 'Zc**+f*~*+*A * exclusively from British sources. In India Office telegram No.7741 or the 18th April/we agreed to the April^we agreed to the Sultan being promised the supply ^partly at half price and partly at full price^of 1,000 rifles plus ammunition, 6 mortars, 4 machine guns plus other stores and the services of another British officer and Indian/N.C.0 1 s for his levies. We said at the same time that /H.M.G.H.M.G-* did not wish any commitment to be made to the Sultan regarding the use of the R.A.P. in support of his plans. The Political Residents telegram^ Nos. 681 tmd ( 38 ?- reports the Sultans reactions on this offer being made to him. His main point was that he regarded the support of the R.A.P. as an essential part of his plans for re-establishing himself in Muscat and said that unless this could be promised he would not be able to carry them out. We are now awaiting the Government of India's comments on the Political Resident's telegrams and it will probably then be necessary for the/promis4~£ air support to be considered further by H.M. G* Demonstration flights by the R.A.P. in themnlyro on ^rera.ouo occasion^ Oj» had a great effect on/Oman tribesmen, even without the dropping of bombs. A consideration that will have to be taken into account is the importance to H.M.G. of the development of Muscat's oil resources/*- Prom recent discussions which the Oil Company's representatives have had with the Sultan it is clear that until the Sultan is enable to establish his authority in the interior the Company will not for a long time be able to exploit the oil which is believed to be there in large quantities. In view of the present threat to the Persian and Iraq supplies the development of Muscat oil^nay become a matter of considerable strategic importance to H.M.G* before long.INWARD TELEGRAM }? ^/'p -)D^ 6 MAY !946 f o $$) Al lotted _to_ Copi es 'oirgu From Politioal Seaident in the Persian Gulf To Government of India Repeated to Secretary of State for India Dated Received Bushire, 15*0*0 hours, 3rd May 1946 82*00 hours, 3rd May 1946 No * 681 India Office telegram 7741 April 18th and connected correspondence* Following is repetition of Muscat telegram 0226 April 30the Begin s* Your telegram 645 April 26th. Assistance to Sultan* 2* Sultan was informed in writing as instructed* At subsequent interview he stated he was grateful to His Majesty r s Government for assistance promised but was disappointed that no reference was made to use of Royal Air Force* Air support at any critical stage he regarded as s ine qua non to him undertaking operations in Oman for (I) he could pot ignore possibility of combined opposition from a few of more powerful tribes (especially from Sharqiyah) proving too strong for hie force b ? (II) ho could not feel justified in investing large proportion of his financial resources in consolidation of his authority unless success was assured, and (III) that his resources would not permit long drawn cut struggle® He requested specific statement from Hia Majesty's Government on this point, adding that if this was-unfavourable he would not proceed further with his plan. in emergent circumstances was agreed he should be given assurance that (A) as rifles and*ammunition which His Majesty s Government had agreed to supply him would be required for his irregular forces, any reasonable additional needs of .Levies for the purpose in view would be supplied separately; and (B) that in the event of operations proving more difficult than he would have anticipated, further supplies for irregular forces would be immediately available. I consider this request reasonable* rea~sons~ 'that 3* Sultan also requested if use of Royal Air Force /4« I strongly4* 1 strongly urge fevoura'blo conaideration of Sultan ' 1 e request for assistance l»y Hoyal Air Force a His reasons for this are cogent and he can be relied on to do everything possible to avoid situation arising which would necessitate air action* To avoid general unrest throughout Oman suppression of any strong opposition in shortest time is in my view essential. Only method of ensuring this is aval lability of air support»OUTWARD TELEGRAM External D ep artme nt. Extl &lt; OYPHBR TELSQRAI'I (0.T.P. ) Prom Secretary of State for India#' £» 0 Political Hessidant invthe Persian G-ulf# Repeated to Government of India, External Affairs Eept. and to Political Agent, Muscat. Despatched 16,20 hours, 5th May 1946, 8528. SECRET . My telegram 6957 of 5th April* Vi jit of PVC.L* representatives to Muscat. 2 ' Company are disappointed 'by result of this visit particularly since Sultan was unable to promise access on the ground to most of the areas in which they are interested* Their representatives gave Political .Agent fall account of discussions with Sultan. 3 * Exploration programme which Company would wish to carry out beginning in autumn, 1946 Is:- ( 1 ) Geological ground examinat16ns of a) Khahura to Yancul, Dhank ard Ibrl b) Jabal Akhdhar c) Muscat to I ski through h-fli Samail e) f) h) Sup to Wadi Bathe via udl thleii Wadi Bat ha area from Juma.Ua (China) to I bra Ground surveys to ’?h&amp;tover extent th® ’geology .warrants over a.tr®&amp;.s from Dhot ar along the coast to the northeast. (2) Geophysical Surveys by lane, and/co * It practicable coast south of Rae e~l Hac-.d to tha Persian , b) The coae ; pruS hinterland between Has al Hade, results of recorihaisaiancc :&gt; Pi .t w uld- indicate- c) The Ba t i nah C o a s i b (■ t w e e n a - c«t and Bohar, 4. The ma;)or part of .these areas s indicated by Sultan to be at present inaoceeslblo., I should be glad to 'bxsvehave your recoumendations fori advice to be given to Company to enablr them to draw up for the future programme. bo you consider there is any likelihood of' Sultan modifying his attitude in near future in view of assistance with arms epc» (, hica we are promising him and what prospects can be held out to She Company?* There would presumably be less objection to ajerial survey of . areas indicated .in (2) of paragraph 5v . j • 5,. • I You will appreciate that exploitation cf Oil resources hf Muscat may before long become of increasing importance to jh£.!••;., and it is therefore Advisable to do what Is possible to hasten on Company's operations. R ministry of buel and Power Mr. Stock) Addlii alty - Mr* G.C&gt;B*bobbs}v s ^ V#' « *»•'!» 1 •x b: .■ 3i i ' list prices will 'be made on receipt of detailed requirements. 3, As regards personnel please tele^rapfc^^ n’.imber of Indian Officers and N,C,O r a required with details of rank and terms of service * In case of additional British Officer please indicate rank of officer required and whether British or Indian service preferred. 4e Government of India agree that in communicating offer to Sultan it should be made clear that personnel f arms eto,, are being made available at his request, They would he glad cf your comments by telegram on paragraph 3 of telegram under reference.FILE. COPY IN WARD T Allotted to Itat e rnal.pj -r CoQies Circulated► 2876 4 a Of-u.. dkt.f.rP- 11241 . 112 From CY PHER TELKGi^Ui ( 0. T&gt; P&lt; ) Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. •Po Government of India, Repeated to Secretary of btaue a or India. Dated Received IMPOR TANT . 625* April iSth. Bushire 12.16 hours, 23rd April 1946. 13.30 hours r 23rd April 1946. India Office telegram 7741, Assistance to Muscat. 2* As you are aware(Resident J s letter 117S February 23rd 1932 refers), Sultan gave^us letter on his accession undertaking to be guided by us in important matters and, though I have never alluded to it in the past seven years, I am sure it has had useful Influence, ;,_r &lt; g s in conversation with His Highness I specifically avoided suggesting anything in the V nature of formal agreement and said that letter S'' from him would suffice. He would* however, consider himself bound by this when once given /andand would be anxious, in his own interests-, to see that it received no publicity,. I therefore reconiaend that y after Sultan's'wishes have been met over supply of arms. Political Agent should convey to him that I would like letter on the lines agreed to verbally between us, I I should be grateful for. very early orders.Tel. No. _ Prom: Sfi/. ; J sccobs, , G3(v/) ,iS&gt; -—dhr WAR office, (^x ’iVHITBFIAITi. ' ' Any further comnrfSnication ou this subject should her addressed to :— The Under-SecretaryJ of State The War Off ce (as opposite and the following quoted. 'I 4 , WEETSHAIX, ixmm, SW1. GS(W) 1/92^3. fg April, 19A6. Your Reference ' J DOfiLT*’ - Kv mi I em ■writing with reference to your letter to me of 13 April 'IJl+S, in which you enclosed the Minutes of our meeting on the Muscat Subsidy, together with a draft of a cable you are proposing to despatch to the Governnent of India. The 7/ar Office agrees paragraph 2 of your proposed cable, which is the paragraph that concerns us. The financial side of this transaction, should you decide to insert such a paragraph in your cable, is as stated in Charlton's letter No. M)VSv5/200^/(pi) dated 16 April 1946 to James at the Treasury, of which you have a copy. Paragraph 2 of your letter to me is I think covered by Charlton's letter referred to above. I am sending copies of this letter to the recipients of yours. Yours ^ ■E.P. Donaldson Esq., C. 1 ...G., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.1.V M.O. VB M. 2002. (F.1.) JDear James, f \i E COPY E H T 2792 1946 i A ^ Wj. 0. e**' &gt; 16 th - v P r i ! -# 1&gt;4 I receired a copy of your 1-tter to Donalcison of the India Ofdice datetl loth April, arising out of the meeting h-ld at the Inoia Office on 3rd April, wh~re the pi.x&gt;pOoed sale of certain military stores to the Sultan of iuuscat at 50 of the list price was discussed* I have also seen a copy of the notes of the meeting referred to# I was rather puzzled Dy the statement attributed to you in paragraph 4 of the record of the meeting, and have discussed the point : .vith Fetch# He confirms inqpression that th* re is no question of showing *the loss involved in selling the arms and ammunition’* in the *var Office Vote. ..hat in fact will happen, will be that India will carry out the sale and will credit H.M.CJ# through the defence expenditure plan with the 504 of the list price, plus 55, • of 50,i in respect of the chare vAilch India offer to j ^ear / of the reduction in price# fhis total credit will not be berm.- out separately in the Indian accounts so far as I am aware, but will ue in diminution of the charges raised ultimately cy India against the War Office. I am sending a copy of this letter to Fetch f «id 0 Tcylor ai^d Xtonalcteon# Yours sincerely. ll#L#M# James, Treasury, ^sq#, d* w • 1# (Sgd.) T. A. G. CHARLTONMr. Janes' letter of the K)th April (below) deals with a matter which, I think, falls within the purview of this Department and if you agree I wi^l^ccept transfer of it. As to the altemativel^^r oearing the ^ cost of the subsidy to the Sultan of Muscat, I would \ aentiioB'# preference that it should be shared with [ta- ^ &amp; Y** through the Defence Expenditure Plan. If it were to be ' 4 pAM • borne on the India and Bunna Services Vote a supplementary this autumn will be essential, and as the amount involved is rather large compared with the size of the Vote I think it would bring the matter into the limelight and might provoke discussion. On the other hand, if it is included in the Defence Expenditure Plan it will be swallowed up in much larger sums. I recognise, however, that this is an argument fran expediency and before putting it to Cobum I shall obtain the views of the Under Secretary of State. 33*^“ In your letter of the 13th April to Major Jacobs you say that the Governsent of India propose to credit H.M.G. with 59? of the amount received from the sale of arms and anmunition through the Defence Accounts. I am not sure fl.K.tfr. what is your authority for this statement. The Government of India's telegram of the 8th March, No.2343* does not say so and I doubt whether this statement is correct. If there are to be any further meetings at which the incidence of this expenditure is to be discussed, I think it is very desirable that either Mr. Taylor or I attend. should C lea. May/May I have copies of the (rovenment of India* s telegram of the 5th March, Vo.2%.}, and of your letter to Mr. Baxter of the Foreign Office of the 25th March, for record on the Financial Department file? (S»i.) R s. BROWN. 16 APR 1346 sd# msfi oev.' se suit io cc d , I I tMo-xaM .Any reply to bo addressed The Secretary. FILE COPY MINISTRY OF FUEL AND POWER Telephone ABBEY 7000. Telegrams: MINFUPO, • Sowest, London. Reference: PJ) Your Reference; * w PETROLEUM DIVISION, 7, Millbank, London, S.W.l. 5th April, 1 9b6* Dear Dor aldson^ 9 ^ With reference to your letter of the 15th April to Jacobs concerning assistance to the Sultan of Muscat, we concur intfeproposed draft telegram to the Government of India, I have no comments to make on the draft minutes. Yours sincerely. jk U. 4~rJlEXT.2615A6 (S? TREASURY CHAlvIBERS, GRE/'T GEORGS STREET LONDON, S.W.1. Treasury reference 3.4533^ 10th April, 1946. Dear Donaldson Following our meeting at the India Office on 3-^ April T have discussed the question of Muscat subsidies with nry colleagues here. The meeting proceeded I think on the assumption that the orevious subsidies to Muscat were given on military considerations and were being adjusted through the India Defence Expenditure Plan. It appears, however, frou. Brown s letter of 2nd April (F. 11996/46) to Fetch that India are arranging to adjust previous gifts of arms and ammunition through the Defence Plan but that they take the view that the so called war subsidy which was I think a cash contribution is purely a civil transaction which should not go through the Plan. Our view has always been that there was a strong military interest in the cash subsidy and for this reason we should be prepared to see its cost snared through the Defence Plan. The only possible alternative that we can see is to provide for the U.K. share on tne India and Burma Services Vote and it is for the India Office in the first place to consider which of the two alternatives they would prefer. There is of course, a similar dilemma in connection with the proposed sale of arras and ammunition which we discussed at the meeting and as you know we are awaiting the considered bar Qffice view as to whether the U.K. share of the reduction in^ price can be treated as a normal disposals operation adjusted from the Defence Plan. I am sending copies of this to Charlton and to Major Jacobs at the War Office. P.Donaldson Esq., C.M.G., India Office.mmmmmamm I N W A TE M 1 ' (- 1 Allotted to Bxt er nal De^t c Copies cTrcula^ed*. EXT 2504 ' I 9^fi frr o 9644 F o • From CYPHER TELEGRAM (Q.T.P. ). Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To Government of India. Repeated to Secretarjr of State for India. Dated Bushire, 1&amp;.40 hours, 5th April 1946. Received 22.10 hours, 5th April 1946. IMPORTANT . 544 Your telegram 5855, March 21st. Assistance i;o Muscat. 2. Position of British officer would be similar to that of present Military Adviser. He would be seconded to Muscat Infantry and would be second in command. He would deputize for Military Adviser whenever necessary. 3. Additional Indian officers and non-commissioned officers would be in identical position to those already serving. If not already retired, they would be on deputation and directly under orders of Military Adviser. 4. -Responsibility for the activities of officers and non commissioned officers seconded would be Sultan’s, who would be guided by advice of his Military Adviser regarding use of his forces. Political Agent suggests that it may therefore be necessary to provide Sultan with more senior and experienced officer as Military Adviser than present incumbent. 5. Sultan will naturally withdraw offer mentioned in paragraph No. 6 of my letter 84S of January 15th 1946 if he is compelled by circumstances to act without our support. Possibility also cannot be overlooked of his turning elsewhere for assistance if it is not forthcoming from ua. Moreover, since offer was made verbally to me, Sultan would probably treat it as having lapsed with my departure, if not formally accepted. 6 . I should be grateful for very early reply in view of urgency of matter.■■■■■■ Colonel, Arms for MUSCAT. Further to my Note dated _6 April. I have today visited the W3 2 (Amm) and ITS 14(Arms) ^ _ actions of the lar Office. They state that from the point of view of the redundant stocks located in India there should be no dificulty in declaring the small quantities required as globally surplus ,but that,of course,it will be for the far Office staff proper to decide this. The of icial request will,therefore,require to be channelled from the India Office(War Staff) through the concerned mXZ staff branch of the .'far Off ice, (presumably AR.l and/or 0 3 ( f) ). In this latter connection,please see the copy of Extarnal Dept draft letter No.1741/46 addressed to Major Jacobs, GS (.Y H 1), Jar Office (attached on the External Dept file). It is presumed that upon the receipt of t is letter,G3( y)(l) will initiate action and will decide in conjunction 'with DG1R,whether the items required will (i) be drawh from the Defence stocks or (ii) be declared globally surplus with instructions to the Govt of India to dispose of locally. I I '^Gol.03. 8 April. 46. f. 09 m*. Y* C«Ul (r+t Kca cju ^ ^&amp; £&gt;) Mr. Donaldson (\) Mar Staff (Col. Craddock) J r\ I attach drafts of the Minutes of the Meeting held here on April 3rd. about assistance to the Sultan of Muscat and a telegram to the Government of India. #ith reference to the method of accounting for the loss involved in the sale of Arms and Ammunition at half list price, we have now had a copy of Mr. R.S. /&amp; Brown* s lettor/fi’ciii which it appears that in the . , „ . « _ o _li -i «v*+ -ill p&gt;r*'vr. «imnT V IS I ^ QJL*. for the u-overnment uj. o- — : - - certain sum through the defence accounts (presumably with the War Office). Alternatively Col. Craddock has suggested that a solution would be for the stocks to be declared Flobal surplus and the Cover me nt of Indxa instructe to dispose of them. These suggestions ore included in a draft letter to the War Office submitted below. £ /* y /v 6 '(g) Ext. 1741/A-6 «* April, 1946. Dear Jacobs, / * / I enclose herewith a draft note of the Meeting about assistance to the Sultan of Muscat which you attended on April 3rd together v/ith a draft telegrain to the Governnent of India. You will no doubt have seen by now copies of the Political Resident’s telegram No,544 and the Governnent of Indp_a’‘s telegram No,32 12, but spare copies are enclosed herewith for P.R’.s telegram 544 ) ease of reference. G/l’s telegram 3212 ) 2, As regards para ,4 of the Note, we have recently heard from the Government of India that the section of Mountain Artillery which is to be presented to the Sultan as' a token of appreciation for his assistance during the war (reference India Office telegram No .3642 of 20th February, a copy of which was sent to Major Stileman on 22nd February) is being drawn from Defence stocks paid for by H.LI.G. and that it is proposed by the Government of India to credit H.M.G. with 55/ of the amount to be received, through the Defence accounts. (janes' letter to me No.S.45336 of 10th April refers). Do you see any reason why the present proposal should not be treated as a disposals operation in the same way? Alternatively it has been suggested here that the arms might be declared 'global surplus' and the Government of India instructed to dispose of them. Ve have consulted the Provision Branches concerned at the War Offire and from their point of view there would appear to be no difficulty in pursuing this course. .The amount credited to H.M.G. could then be treated v as their share of the disposal. Will you let us know the War Office view on these suggestions? The method of accounting for the War Subsidy, which is discussed in para,2 of James' letter to me of 10th April, might I think be considered separately. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter and its enclosures to /James ajor G.S.L. Jacobs, C.S.(w)l, War Office, S.W.1.3 \ I t Janes at the Treasury, Johnston at the Air i/Iinistry, Henderson at the Foreign Office and Farrell at the i.Iinistry of Fuel and Paver, and would be glad if they would let me know as soon as possible (preferably by telephone) whether their Departments concur in the draft telegram and whether they have any amendments to suggest to the Note of the Meeting. Yours sincerely, i (S^d) E. r./ EXT. 1741/4-6 ItRAOT LETTER Major G-.S.L. Jacobs, C.S.(J)1, War Office. !13 APS 1945 Copy/toj- R.L.li. James, &gt; 9 Treasury, G.S.N^^cftins^on, Esq., Air Ministry, t 3/6.) person. Esq. % ice. J.P.T Porei&amp;n J.W. P^rrell, (is try of Fuel &amp; Povsjer. d ^ ■ Dear Jacobs, I enclose herewith a^note oA- the Meeting about assistance to the Sultan of Muscat which you attended on April. 3rd. together with a draft telegram to the Government of Inuia. ^ ^ ^ 2_, As regards para .4 of the Note, we have j*srfc heard from the Goverrment of India that the se||*ction of Mountain Artillery which is to be presented to the Sultan as a token of appreciation for his assistance during the war (reference India Office telegram No. 3&amp;4-2 of 20th February, a copy of which was sent to Major/ ^ r . r ^ &lt;}Major StUeman on 22nd i^bruary) is being h drawn frcm pkfence stocks paid for Jcflm HJI.a. and that it is proposed by the G-ovemment of* India to credit with 55 &gt; of the amount to be reoei-ved through ]&lt;***£. / — ' tl.e defence accountsoj&lt; Do you see any reason ff'h^ * why the present proposal should not be treated a. in the same way? Alternatively it has been suggested^that the arms might be declared ^global surplus and the Government of India instructed to dispose of them«^^The amount credited to H.M.G. could then be treated as their share of the disposal. Will you let us Ubrc^rhCU^r* 4 _. _ 7 JU lenow vi’h' t vou thir.«. sugge s tl on» . '&lt;\Ti r, ^ ^ j-jizu h 1 1 'We W &amp; 0e (Pv C«WC*« •£, I am sending a copy of this letter and its enclosures to James cdT the Treasury, Johnston at the Air Lin is try, -Henderson at the Foreign Office and Farrell at the Ministry of Fuel and Power, and would be glad if they would let me know as soon as possible ible //^ whether their Departments concur in the draft and whether they have any amendments to suggest to the Note of the Meeting* Yours sincerely. ($£d) E. P. DONALDSONjj'rcxii : i.Iajor G.S.L, Jaco bs, G-,£&gt;. ^ * VifHItehall 9400 , The War Office, I have received a copy of your letter dated 23th March, 1946, to iiaxter of the Foreign Office. Stileman has now leit the War Office and I have taken over from him; I should be pleased to attend your meeting to discuss the Muscat subsidyj on April 3 rd * G-.8. (W) 1/7962/1 Ext. 1783 Whitehall, S.W.l a'J March, lAb, Your Reference. Yoi E.P. Donaldson, xisq*, India Office, ■Whitehall, S.W.l.BBBT ^ ' *n&gt;m» u lu . . the Sultan. 3 # With regard to the question of obtaining an undertaking from the Sultan to obtain advisers in future solely from British sources, fi.M.G. are anxious that no written agreement shouD-d be mads which might later be used against BUM.G. as an example of interference in the sovereignty of an inde pendent state. If you and the Political Resident think that such an assurance in writing if given spontaneously would be of real value for the future they have no objection to it being accepted but they consider that it should not in any case be specifically linked with supply of arms 4 d H-M.G. do not wish that any commitment should be made to the Sultan regarding the use of the RAF» Copies Circulated* Copy to F.O. (Mr. J.T.Henderson) A.M. (Mr. G-.S.N. Johnston) W.O. (Major G.S.L. Jacobs) M• F. P«. (Mr. J:W. Farrell) Admiralty (Mr.G.C-B.Bodds) Treasury(Mr.R.L.M• James) Finance Bept(Mr.R.S.Brown);ct .17 ViA-6 (%) H I* Note of a Meeting A at the India Of - i * A-riT'-i T ' iQ Li L Note of a Ivieeting A at the India Office on April 3rd t L ^ # r t*, »N Ass^^tixnce to the dultan of Muscat to enable biai to consolidate his authority over the interior of Oman on the death of the Haai.i Major G.S.L. Jacobs (Nar Office) Mr. J.W. Farrell ^Ministry of Fuel po.verj Mr. R.L.M. James v &gt; Ti , easuiy) ♦ * Mr. G-.S.N. Jotinston (Air Ministry) Mr. J. T'uyne Henderson (Foreign Office) MojovF.H. Nangle (India Office) Mr. F.A.- . Harrison (India Office) Miss Odgers (India Office)* • The Meeting considered a proposal that certain arms and ammunition as set out in Mr. Donaldson 1 s letter to departments of 25th March should he supplied to the Sultan of Muscat at half list price; that he should he allowed to purchase / certain military stores and to obtain the services of a British officer^ a retired Indian officer and N.C.O , s for his levies. The Jar Office representative agreed that the equipment nigh! he sup -lied provided that the Goiiiuander in Chief, India 9 sees no objection, and that the stores are surplus to India* s requirements, and no call will he mane on the Jar Office for replacement. j. The Foreign Office representative saw no objection to the supply of equipment or of officers and II.0.0*s provided that; it / — was quite clear in ary exchange of letters that the Sultan's request for them was s;pontaneous. With regard to the suggested quid pro quo that the Sultan should hind himself and his heirs to obtain advisers solely from British sources in future, the Foreign Office were anxious that no sort of agreement should oe put in writing which might he used against II.M.G-. at some lauer\ Present: Mr. E.l. Donaldson in the Chair Oai$r such undertaking by the Sultan should not be recorded in v/riting and in any case should not be uientioned in the same document as that \ dealing with the supply of equipment etc. t.. v,t '‘ i. wa on the other hand that the excliange of letters | would not be published, and^the possibility of such apvritten undertaking ...being used against Ii.h_.G-. at a later date was somewhat, rei.ote. The ; obtaining of such an undertaking might be of value to H.1.1.G-. in that without it the Sultan and his successors might be more disposed to turn^for example - to the Americans for advisers. The Treasury representative then raised the question of the department responsible for showing on its estimate H.II.G- 1 s sliare of the loss involved :n selling the arms and ammunition at half the list price. It was/a greed .hat there was some advantage in treating the• transaction if possible .imply as a disposals matter (in which case it would presumably be jncluded in the War Office Vote) rather than as a political one, in which ■use it would probably have to come on the India Office Vote and might nvite unnecessary publicity./ The War Office rewneseivtative undertool; . . ^ a» fi Ih j’rtivUiA J] Jki u axe further enquiries in the War Office on t iiia v rirft . J f kturtcubitu 4L&amp; CK. $t»/9**lo KvUti* . f The meeting then considered the question of possible assistance to the Sultan by demonstration flights by the R.AkP. The Air k.inistry representative emphasised that the operation would have to be under the oonplete control of the R^A.P. It was agreed that it was desirable that no advance commitment on the point should be made with the Sultan. (•) The India Office undertook to prepare and circulate for concurrence the departments represented a draft telegram to the Government of India on the conclusions reached.Whitehall 9000, Ext: 808 @ 'M.0499/46' Military Branch I, S.W.i. 30 th March, 1946 Admiralty, Dear Donaldson You sent me a copy of your letter of the 25th March to Baxter about assistance to the Sultan of Muscat. 0. I do not think the Admiralty are very closely concerned ajt this stage and unless you particularly want us to be present, we should not propose to attend your meeting on April 3rd, 3. ^ As you know, we are all in favour of anything which will keep the Sultan sweet and the present ° developments seem to be in that direction^ Yours sincerely E.p. Donaldson, Esq., India Office, London, S.W.I. GCBD/DEfIV 4 £ W. * *4 Register No. o SECRET. POLITIOAir- DEPARTMENT Letter Telegram from Dated Idee. 193 Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To ^lulnmin Under Secretary Secretary of Statj?^. Committee Qk (f fa;*-'* fa A/nivtcML &amp; fC+tCAt* k o^Mi U u, cujk^ * in***- ^ V/47 ■ Under Secretary Secretary of State _ ./© SECRET SKI. 1741/4-6 INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL S.W.l Dear Baxter, With reference to the Political Resident's despatch No.SA-S of 15th January, I enclose herewith a copy of a telegram / from the Government of India in which they put forward certain No.2343 ) proposals for assistance to be given to the Sultan of of 8th Mar.) Muscat to enable him to consolidate his authority in the interior of Oman on the death of the Imam. The Government of India’s proposals, when read with the Resident’s despatch, appear to amount to the following: the expenditure of Rs.60,000 involved to be divisible between Government of India and H.M.G. in the proportion of 55:45* (b) The Sultan to be allowed to purchase at 'list price” certain other equipment such as tentage, transport, medical supplies and signal equipment (also, presumably, from stocks held in India); (c) The Sultan to be assisted to obtain another British officer for his Levies, together with several retired Indian officers and N.C.O’s, (a) To supply the Sultan at half 'list price” from stocks held in India, with the following:— 1,000 rifles 100,000 rounds ammunition 63' mortars 4 machine-guns; A C.W. Baxter , Esq., C.M.G. , M.C., Foreign Office, S.W.l.( 2 ) 2. You v/ill recall that the Sultan has told Sir Geoffrey Prior orally that in the event of our supporting him in his plans for the re-establishment of his authority he would give the Political Resident a letter binding himself and his heirs for the future to obtain advisers exclusively from British sources (paragraph 6 of the Political Resident’s despatch No.84*-S of 15th January). The-obtaining of such an undertaking would, of course, in itself be of very considerable value to us as a means of insuring our position in Muscat. Apart from this, the consolidation of the Sultan’s authority over the interior would be to H.M.G’s advantage, particularly in view of the desirability of opening up the interior for oil development by Petroleum Concessions Ltd. At the same time, v/e shall have to walk warily if we are not to lay ourselves open.to hostile criticism and it has been suggested that there might be some advantage in linking any supply of arms if possible with the token gift of mountain artillery which we were already proposing to give the Sultan in recognition of his assistance to us during the war (paragraph 3 of India Office telegram to Government of India No. 3^42 of 20th February refers). This possibility of criticism applies also to the loan of British and Indian officers and N.C.O’s to train the Sultan’s Levies; since, however, it is not altogether clear upon what basis it is proposed that these officers and N.C.O’s should be made available to the Sultan and the degree of responsibility for their activities that would attach to H.M.G. v/e have telegraphed to the Government of India asking for an elucidation of the proposal on this point. 3* With reference to paragraph 3 of Government of India’s , telegram, we are rather doubtful about the desirability of giving the Sultan any definite undertaking in the way of assistance by demonstration R.A.F. flights, but the Air Ministry will no doubt have views on this. . I think the simplest way of settling what we should /say 4^ v :. ') i . iOOiWALUSC say in reply to the Government of India’s telegram. No. 2343 of the 8th March would be by me 0 ^ 3 of a short meeting at which the interested departments might be represented. I suggest at l\• ft . in the Commit cee Room^ Inaic^ Office ^ might be Q convenient time and place and I am accordingly ^ending copies of this letter to Najrsmyth (Treasury), Humphreys-Davies, (Air Ministry) , Stileman (War Office) , Dodds (Admiro.lty) and Stock (M.W.P.) who v/ould perhaps let me know if they will be able to attend. Yours sincerely,. I DRAFT LETTER C.W.Baxter, Esq., C.M.G-. , M.C., Foreign Office, S.W.l. EXT. 1741/46 25 MAR 1946 6P / /&lt; 2 3*3 tj frt** Copy to :- ^ Mr .Naysmyth (Treasury) M Humphreys-Davies, A , (Air Ministry) &gt; Stileman (War Office)/^ Dear Baxter, With reference to the Political Resident's despatch A- No. 84 ^ of 15th January, I enclose herewith copy of a telegram u from the Government of India in which they put forward certain proposals for assistance to be given to the Sultan of Muscat to enable him to consolidate his authority in the ^Interior of Oman on the death of the Imam. The Government of India's fa ilSfikhk i h A*wo~% r IT , proposals, be ■eummflrised -follows:^-- /T ' ' - , (Jp to supply the Sultan at half list pric^ wit hfi^ fa Ucwf ^ 1,000 rifles fic .jcT */&gt; 100,000 rounds ammunition Dodds (Admirailty^ ' Stock ^ (M.F.P.) x- ^ aZ 73^ ’ V 6^ 3' mortars 4 machine-guns llr) tlie Sultan to be allowed to purchase at list pr ,c^ r f^ntage,, 7ri*ansport,, (Medical supplies ^ (^gnal equipment^ (t) ~ La\} j &amp; the Sultan to be assisted to obtain another British officer for his levies, together with several retired Indian officers and N.C.O^, fT&amp; 2. You will recall that the Sultan has pcomieed Sir cnJk G-eoffrey Prior/that in the event of our supporting him in his plans for the re-establishment of his authority he wiii give the Political Resident a letter binding himself and his heirs the future to obtain advisers exclusively from British sources (paragraph 6 of the Political Resident's Despatch No.84^.3 of 15th January) # ihe obtaining of such an undertaking would, of course, in itself be of very considerable value / to us as a means of insuring our position in Muscat. Apart from this, the consolidation of the Sultan's authority over /thethe Interior would be to H.M.G 1 s advantage, particularly # in view of the desirability of opening up the interior for oil development by Petroleum Concessions Ltd, At the same time, we shall have to walk warily if we are not to lay ourselves open to hostile criticism and^/there might be some advantage in linking any supply of anns^ if possible^ with the token gift of mountain artillery which we were already proposing to give the Sultan in recognition of his assistance to us during the war (paragraph 3 of India Office telegram to G-overnment of India No. 3642 of 20th February refers). This possibility of criticism applies also to the loan of British and Indian Asu-**' ^ f officers and N.C.0*s to train the Sultan*s levies; since /it is not altogether clear upon what basis it is proposed that these officers and N.C.0*s should be made available to the r ur-ijz.jrunM) or***- a n.n Sultan^ we have telegraphed to the Government of India asking ' for an elucidation of the proposal on this point. 3 . With reference to paragraph 5 of Government of Indian telegram, we are rather doubtful about the wisdom./of giving the Sultan any definite undertaking in the way of assistance by demonstration R.A.F. flights, but the Air Ministry will no doubt have views on this. 4 . I think the simplest way of settling what we should oeadL in reply to the Government of India’s telegram No. 2343 of the 8 th March would be by means of a short meeting at which the interested departments might be represented. I suggest [T.^uMniiitl at |ll-0 ^ tlie Committee Room, India Office, might be a convenient time and place and I am accordingly sending copies of this letter to Na^smVth (Treasury), Humphie.ys-Davies, (Air Ministry) , Stileman (War Office), Dodds (Adniralty) and Stock (M.F.P.) who would perhaps let me know if they will be able to attend. (Sgd) E ! . DONALBSOtyr / INWARD TELEGRAM • •Lti COPY 'l B,;T 1 1741 A1 lot ueel t o External t* Deva.Ftm4rtlA Q . ' * ,a,r t / ^^iv^C opies Circulated , CYPHER TBLSGRAlil (O.T.P.) 6861 . • Z^/ *}■ Government of India, External Affairs Department*3,^ ^ Jkirl- ifrom To Secretary of State for India# - Repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Bated New Delhi, 2S.50 hours, 8th March, 1946, Received IMPORTAN T No * 2343* 19,40 hours, 8th March, 1946,. n 7 \ 'JXg. political Resident's letter 84 - S, January 15th* Assistance to Muscat* 2* This proposal was discussed with Prior'during his recent visit to Delhi* His 3,atest information from Muscat shows that Sultan broached subject Avith Political Agent again on February 19th stressing urgency of early decision in view o f In am * s f a i 1 in g he a J t h« ■ 3„ Access to Oman Hinterland has been denied for too long and opportunity of opening it for development of oil and other resources, v/hich extension of Sultan's control would provide* is too good to be missed# We therefore support proposal to supply Sultan with 1,000 rifles (and ammunition), x 1*1 6* o' inch ( 6^ 3) mortars and 4 machine guns# List price of' • this equipment is roughly Rupees 1^30 ? 000 but we consider that, as in ease of military stores recently supplied to Afghanistan, list price should be reduced by 601o, difference of approximately Rupees 60,000 being shared by H.MuG* and Government of India in same proportion as Muscat war subsidy, namely 45 : 65* We propose, subject to concurrence of London Munitions Assignment Board, to release equipment from stocks held in India, ' * c V, ^ 4., We also propose to assist Sultan to obtain other equipment and -personnel required but do not repeat not propose to provide equipment below list prices*, 5v We must leave to H.IvUG* decisions regarding possible assistance from R^Adm In discussion with Political Agent on February 19th, Sultan laid particular emphasis on value of such assistance and expressed conviction that flights over Oman at any critical stage, would be as effective as in 1932 against the Bani Bu All at Jaalan, CF Political Resi dent's letter 180 - S dated March 29th 1952, f /£\ 6 „ We shall oe grateful for early replyEXTERNAL Political Department. NOTES FOR REGISTRY. (Jlj &amp; wtn rfuU 2 Sb* i}* 1 ■ 07- REGISTER NO./ P- 3xt.735/46 Under Secretary Secretary of State J.. )mmittee * Under Secretary Secretary of Sfate 19.AL. Initials. ' m SUBJECT. Anxiety of the Sultan of Muscat to assert his authority in Oman on the death of the Imam Suggested assistance from / * iA/m } A 7 ' ru ^ ^ IHJ- 1 do M. U „ U&gt; ^ '' ' I - r ' t /^K «u.(' t . lU-Uu- - -‘ L t U ‘- ^ LH„ -Uj^- (10308) Wt.l3671/P.159 1,000 5/39 A.&amp;E.W.Ltd. Gl).6l (10854) Wt.l8826/P.221/2 3,000 (2 sorts) 6/39 FOR USE BY DEPARTMENT ONLY. Please see submission at Ext,3494/45 The Sultan of Muscat has always been anxious to increase his influence over the hinterland, and during last year he entered into negotiations with various Omani Sheikhs, The present Imam is not expected to live much longer and the interval between his death and the appointment of a successor should provide the Sultan with his opportunity. In an interview with the Political Agent, Muscat last August the Sultan discussed the position pointing out the need for unifying his State and bringing the tribes of the hinterland out of their isolation; the opportunity which the death of the Imam would give him for re-occupying Oman with little bloodshed; and his own increased influence with the Omani Sheikhs, The latter is due to a great extent to the sound financial position of the State which enables the Sultan to entertain the Sheikhs in a manner befitting his position, and to obtain arms and ammunition to back his growing influence with them. The Sultan assured the Political Agent that he would not act contrary to the advice of H.il.G. and /in .685 11 Or- in any case would do nothing until the death of the Imam, in the meantime he would encourage friendly relations with the Sheikhs and would prepare for military operations designed to seize certain forts. There he would need the assistance of the British G-overnment for he would require stores, equipment and British officers for training his levies. Mr. Hallows is of the opinion that the Sultan in spite of signs that he has recently been increasing his religious observances, does not wish to succeed to the Imamate but rather is working for its abolition and the substitution of his own rule. He does not consider that the Sultan wishes to be established by British arms which would hardly make for the stability of the State, but that H.M.G. should give him facilities for acquiring arms and equipment and should endeavour to strengthen his authority while maintaining the traditional policy of non-interference in the hinterland. He considers the Sultan is one of the most capable Arab rulers of the present time and thinks that he should be well able to assert and consolidate his authority over Oman. The Political Resident in an interview with the Sultan later in the year told him that he hoped to see his authority re-established in Oman, but that H.M.G. had no wish to become involved in military operations in the interior which might be misinterpreted elsewhere. § / / / , Awn nniri mao nnr, ^n^h^in-vnnH- no ^ jC CvT+J” f / nfrfrnn firm'll^ ,n,-q I hi** l** l*** fr^*** 4 * to obtain their Advisers in future exclusively from British sources. ki r uA- (rh fc pz* Although the Political Resident acted without instructions it ' is clearly in the interests of H.M.G. that the Sultan*s writ should run in the interior particularly as the Oil Company is likely to begin operations in Oman in the near future. In paragraph 8 of his letter Sir Geoffrey Prior sets out the arms and equipment which he suggests that H.M.G. should be prepared to give the Sultan and further supplies which he might be allowed to purchase. The Political Resident emphasises, however, the importance of not giving the Sultan any encouragement to think that British troops would come to his aid.should anything go wrong with his plans. bir Geoffrey Prior’s letter is addressed to the Government of India and we may await their views before taking any action. War Staff. % For information, wYi ya J S $/£ ^’ • r T* i I I hesitate to cormnent on the political aspect of the gift to the Sultan of Muscat of British equipments for the scarcely veiled purpose of enabling him to establish his authority, if necessary by force, in the Oman hinterland; but it seems to me to be a tricky business, to say the least of it, especially if British and Indian officers and N.C.O*s are to train his Levies for the seizure of forts on D.Day. If, however, the gift of arms etc were made before the death of the Imam a s a reward for the Sultans services to the Allied cause, things would look much better; but I would still doubt the wisdom of giving him additional help to train his Levies. I foresee no difficulty in providing the equipments which Sir Geoffrey Prior recomnends. ^ffiNERAL, 20 . 2 . 46 . 20 . 2 . 46 . trfc kc^j. u-vru^ u™ . A r/L t?L ^ ^ ^ ^ C*n&lt;hs~ f?^*** 1 * c i r l^TjUjU S(*~- urt .n • 1 n *rr. n Uxf, )_ ZL ^ ^ ■strength of character, is supremely shrewd and enjoys a .egree of natural prestige* Given the opportunity he could, in r y opinion be capable of holding his own arsonist any of tie tribal leaders and by the sagacious handling ox the tribes, might bring an era of enlighton r ient to the people whose self-imposed isolation has precluded all advance* as an instance of nis capabilities may be sited tht- cese ol the province of Ghofer* »«)\en ho first visited vnoiar shortly after his accession, disorder was rife and this authority ox' his governs at did not extend much beyond the coastal strip oetween Haisut and ^erbpt* Wow his eifective influence covars the entire inhabited co*£tal and hill areas I'rojn has ShuvraMiyah to the borders 01 the Aden I rotsetorate, The hhaikhs of the qara and ruithir recognise his authority and regular visitors to his p&amp;lacs when he is ti^ere, and to his ,Vali in his absence* 7. I do not imagine that the Sultan’s idea of British forcej estaolishing i ? bin as de fact^ duler of Oman (and prooably having to naintain hi* in that position) is one that would coisiend Itself to either i;is ^ajeat/’s Government or to the Government of India - unless stratetic considerations of thu f-ture n-e ccnsidorud us requiring' further examination of the proposal for a protectorate itr-t •Jude In li^O. Assuming trat no such raiical c-icngc in our awtituae of nor-lnterfero ice T«ith the interior can be contemplated, it wuld, I invest, he unwise for us to associate ourselves directly v?ith tha Galtan’s eima and thereby incur rssponsioilities wliich we ar« not .preoared to carry out to tha fill* Our j^oneral policy should I submit, ?cnti:rac to be one of st.2’cngti*MivLng whe authority of the Guitar while making it clear thut thy extension of his influence nuut oe at n..3 reeponaibility ana achieved by his own exertions. My c^n view is that U«e attitude of the Ghaflri Ghaikh is one more exHinele of the nrab's Kye bein f t ’’fixed unflinchingly In tin main chence”* Vho healthy condition of the utate treasury re already beginning tn exort e stren^; centri petal force, a f 'uin&amp;t which tha Imam hat no effective counter measure, and given the rnccssary ^terials to u^ocouragc hiaawi opposition the* Suttsn would probably have ritt-e diiflealty in rw-e«tablishing hi.cnelf. by action on jls Initiative and without direct support from outiidts, ho wt^aLd not only enhance his own reputation aniougst the tribes, but would alao be forced to aase his actions on the more AM stable foundation of consent* ^ ^ t/ic Jin’s nance of this oolicy 1 would suggest trat the Gultan bij given facilities .’or ac uir lag additional arrss ana equiptaent in reasonable y^antities. At the end of tiie war large stocks of surplus military stores will presumably become available and it Tii^ht tile a be possible *o mi :o a representation to hin r number of snail field gi.is with amr-unition and perhans uortars. This suggestion 5«1 for* the subject oi‘ a rc-ar-tt refet^nce ’ in'ed to the faciLit-ies he hna given to us during ths Tur. -n any levsiopnent* towards Oman, tlie pusitioh of .ish Adviser, if one is wrpointea, fould I think l - i f -J b&lt;. I _ «i . * 9- in t-if &gt;rit^w&gt;. , -L.i MI.T La , fO.: m i cninK remain anuffacted as he ^oald presuiiably occupy himself principally /-5 principally with relations with tht Agency and Ihe Adciinlstrative affairs of the coastal rrea, So far as the Levies are concerned, it see ns desirable that when our war-tise responsibilities for interne! security end, the utate should be encouraged to depend less on ou* assistance in the adslaistcat .on and cc n.iand of its military force. In his half-brother, Saiyid Tarlq, the oat tan has a **an who has jupt returned from extensive training with the Lhob Militia and the G^iagai Levy Corps and w iose sax’ vices could probabl/ br« ^ost suitably utilised in this sphere. 1C. It is relevant to observe in conclusion that If the advice tenderad to Uu Jultan is unfavourable to his airas, Lie Is ll/csly to b^couie a despondent and disinterested Itttlor and to retire finally* to Dhofar - with unfortunate, if not serious, consequence to the State. 11. I shall be glad to receive your Instructions In duo eouroc. Su. R.I. Hallows, olitioal «.gent, useat•V^ lb l CONFIDENTIAL No. 872 - g. From To Copy to .o-r COPY 'i' v,* The Hbn’ble Cjt^g PoljJtical Resident,'?^ Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire, 15th October 1946. a Bushire . H.M f s Secretary of State for India, T '''don, ^ °or % y- The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi . ‘ J The Political Agen £ A £ Jut . ' t ^ t. it MEMORAKniTM 2 7 OCT U • . *' fa*' ■ Z^x ■ His Highness the Sultan of Muscat has informed the Political Agent of his intention to stay in Muscat for a further summer and not to visit Dhofar in the meantime. The Sultan*s decision to remain in Muscat is due principally to developments in the interior (please see correspondence ending with my letter No. 617-S dated the 4th June 1945) Sd/- A.C. Galloway Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. aAJL cr 5 Vrf* / 7 ) YGt £■*&gt; De.'u* Longrigg# ID aL&gt;-o^-V * i t xbJ &gt; . /&gt;JK tM.r Sj&amp;tU. 19t!t July. 1913, ii Ilan'inon lias Just gone off for a v/eok 1 g leave and has passed on &lt;0 ine youi* letter of the 17 th July which arrived just before he left. . e are of course anxious to assist your Ocrtoany in any way that vie properly can and it was \7ith this motive that we let you have a sight of Calloway's report for your personal information, we rather assumed that you would not make a copy of the report, but as you have now done so, we are agreeable to your retaining it provided that you take care to ensure thtit it remains within your o/m custody. Yours sincerely. r9f&lt;M n ** OLWMm brigadier S.1I. Longi-igg, Ling House, dominion treet, Ixwidon, K.C.2#C j &lt;) V ^.H. LONGRIGG 4b.H. LONGRIGG •■• ^o v fL Clu^j . &gt;w Ling House Dominion Street London. E.C.2, Ling House. My dear Harrison, Many thanks for your letter dated ilth July enclosing Galloway’s very interesting report on his journey to Jeneh and back. His information increases one’s curiosity to know the lie of the land as between the various forces in central Oman and whether any additional unity or additional disunity is likely to appear when the Imam dies. I believe it would give the Sultan a great opportunity, but to use it would take a stronger personality than he possesses. Although your letter says that the Galloway report (herewith returned) is for my personal information, I have, in fact, made a copy of it which I retain. If you don’t like this, I will faithfully destroy it! It will be most interesting to have something further from your people on the spot as soon as they have it. Meanwhile many thanks for the steps you are taking. Yours sincerely. F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1. — --n ~ l 19 JUL' 10/ir INT’ * EnelBritish Consulate and Political Acency, Muscat. D.O. No•S.434-8/62 Dated 18th March, 1945. I»ly dear 3ir Geoffrey, Will you please refer to the correspondence ending with your demi-official letter No. 964^dated the 31st. December, 1944. 2. In Delhi I obtained the Sultan*s concurrence to my visiting the Jabal Akhdhar, and so on my return I wrote to Shaikh Sulaiman bin Hemyar, suggest ing a visit. He replied saying that he would welcome a visit from $6, but added that he was leaving his own country for the 'green country of the east'. He has since this written again inviting na to visit him. 3. As It was unlikely that he would be back In the Mountain within a month, and as it was certain that by then I should not have the time to make the Joarney. I decided to make a preliminary visit to see Shaikh Hamad bin Hamid at Jeneh, close to Motl, at the foot of the Mountain beyond the Wadi Sunail in the Wadi Ruwahi. 4. I therefore asked Ral Bahadur GokaIdas to obtain some fast camels, and suggested to him that he might accompany ue. This he did, and I am grateful for his company and assistance. We set out from Sib by lorry to the foot of the hills where, after considerable difficulty from the guide lost the way. we picked up the camels which had been sent on ahead overnight. We entered the hills at Rasal, and continued eastwards up x the Wadi Rasul for so ie two hours, and passed the small villafees of Jafnain and Maraira. At maraira the track winds through the hills, and after passing Batih, leads to Finj^geh. There was no running water in the valley in contrast to many others we travelled in later, and the village water supplies are from wells. The hillsides near the villages*bristle with old watch towers, all of which are abandoned. Fingeh can be doscribed as a small town, and is situated on a northern slope overlooking miles of fine date gardens planted on the north side of the river bed. There is a fair siaed perennial stream of sweet water which supplies the town and gardens. The town is protected by two large towers situated on promontories at each end of the town which is built on a cliff overhanging the valley. These forts were newly whitewashed, and in good re pair. 6. • From Fingeh we rode southwards up the valley passing the villages of Sharu, ’Anikat. Hilayana and Kurta, until we arrived at Bidbid. This is a large village which gets its importance from the presence of a square serai type of fort in which the Wall lives. Neither he, nor the Qazl, were there when I passed through. At Bidbid I saw for the first time fields of wheat and other crops watered from cliannels on the Persian system. There are only date ? ^lms at Fingeh, and we found it impossible to buy ucer-ne for our canols there. Fodder should be brought from Bidbid, and I think we were thought to be rather stupid for not knowing this. The Hon'ble dir Geoffrey Prior,K.C.I.S. Political Resldant,Persian Gulf. 3h.Pi:RB_..- 2 - Bldbid we rode over a broad stony plain for auout two hours before we entered the Wadi duriall, norti oi jurur• Surur is the nost northerly village of a Intervals alone the banka of the valley tu 1 2 ° 2 11 ^ She northern end of the valley &lt; ,?P' ttnd fruit gardens aro not ranarkable for thalr r 5 r »C llt3r ,? r fcl ? e 3l2e o f the tr&amp;es, but In the centre of the valley In the neighbourhood of the fort I saw tno iinest uate gardens I iiavo ever seen. There are large mango and other fruit trees also. We s -xmt one uii,,!!. at uumaxl in the guest house of the Wali. was most hospitable and friendly, and sent me a lamb „ lhls »es a Croat treat, especially for dwellers In f.uscat where the only neat killed, excont on rare occasion?,1s one goat a day. He told ne that the lack o; rain In the last few years had resulted m a diminution m the number and size of the flocks due to the lack of grazing. Tints may be so, and it is * ( ^£°-&gt; true th ff t Qre very few flocks to be seen. -ith the next breath, however, he complained the excess 0 3U ® :;1 ®r liai^ruined .tjio date crop. Tonpoint '* 0 it that, the rail, would eventually result In an addition to i-he viator supply by reviving the springs was a too 1 long-tera policy to be rocelved with favour. The rain d ? a ? not really spoil the date crop, but the drying of &gt;.he dates. In Oman there Is a kind of date which ' tney ga ‘-her just before It is ripe, ~d boil in lar^e earthenware pots. They then spread the boiled dates on the river bed to dry. If it rains during the drying period considerable loss is sustained. 7 r j A3 Surauil numbers of Shaikhs and the leading Cazl Zv i e 10 cuest houae garden where I sat under hM? 2 l|n f 0 trec , 3 - - h «y talked a little of the war, but did not show much interest in it beyond its effect upon tnemaelves. They asked me if the 'control system' were an invention of the British CJovernaont, and if I thought tha» it was necessary. They said that it caused great Hardship to themselves as it resulted in their i*r&amp;ln. I replied saying thet certainly in war tirao it was absolutely necessary to Wh0I i m worQ to the conversatio tne ua i suddenly as^d to be allowed to leave for a few ninutea. /hereupon he and his greybeards i/ent away and held a confabulation just out of earshot behind the eaie back after wliat seemed an inter- for it was nearly 11 o'clock at night and 1 bad been riding all day, and turned to the weather as a subject 01 conversation. I suppose their native caution had overcome then, S # The Sunail fort is q large stone building perched on a rock some 100 feet high in the middle ofthe valley where it broadens out a little. There is a small bazaar stinking fish is sold. The people buy smill «r ^ i ! , . and 2 arry it: hoae danglinp on a piece o. sticx, and that is not to be wondered at either, ''he entrance to the valley from the south is guarded by two large a or .3 a.so situated on the top of out—crops of r ° c ”f , to ?* Photographs of these, but could not do so o. the j imail Aort as the Vail said that the taking of photographs via 3 against his religion. It is from the south oa Buna11 that the Jabal Akhdhar Is first seen. 9. fVe continued our Journey over barren stony country in a broad,/-&lt;&amp;) © a broa^ valley a^x&gt;ut 10 lalles acrosig. After a 3 hour’s ride it narrowed to a pass by which we entered the iVodi Ruwahi. The northern entrance of this valley is guarded by the usual towers and forts built on rocky promontories but here the fortifications are strengthened - or were for all is now falling to pieces - by a wall tiktics linking tnen ^ up. There was more soil here and each village - we passed illngeah, Ghelay and Mureila - has its wheat fields irrigated in tlia Persian style* as well as date gardens and mango trees. After a 5 hours’ fast ride we arrived at Jeneh at the southern end of the Wadi Ruwahi. This is the home of Shaikh Hamad bin Hamid, who was once in the service of the Sultan of Muscat f but who now lives on his own property through which travellers from Unseat and the Batinah aust pass to roach Nozv;a, the town of his father-in-law, the Jmam. He was very pleased to see ie, and during t)e iialt of a day and a half took rae for walks in the hills and gardens. He asked numerous questions about the war, and regretted that his radio was out of order. I have sent it to India for repairs, but after its return am faced with the problem of supplying him with charged batteries. 10. Ho told me that the Imam was very ill and that it was not thought that he would live much longer. He said that that was the reason for 3haikh Sulaiman bin Hamyarr’s going to PCarnil to meet 3haikh Isa Bin Saleh al Harthi. They wished to settle on a policy to foliar after the Imam’s death. According to Hamad bin Hamid their plan was to divide Oman into t*o parts, and fir Sulaiman bln Hamyar to rule the western part and Isa bin Selelh the eastern. Hanad was concerned that the Sultan was apparently playing no part, and he asked ne if I know the reasons. I £new no tiling about it, and in any case was sceptical. There is no doubt though that there is some big game afoot, for uot only have the leading Shaikhs met at Kamil and sent a message to the Sultan, but also Hamad asked me if the British Govern ment would take direct action to assist should a certain event take place. I was not to be caught so easily as that, and aslced what event he might be thinking of. But he would not say, so I replied that I must first know the proposition before I could give a reply. It is interesting to know that the Shaikhs of Oman have been, and perhaps are, contamplating making a proposal to the British Government. The treating at Ka~.il, vide my deni-official letter Ho. 423-8/63 dated the 17th Harch, lb46, also proves timt should they do sc it will probably be in connection with the distribution of supplies over which there appears tc be considerable ill feeling in Gtaan. I hapre informed the Sultan, and suggested tiiat ha should look into the natter on his return to Muscat. It is, lu fact, essential that we should do so. 11. The eastern slope of the Jabal Akhdhar, which is very steep and which is covered with scrub Jungle at the t6p, towers over Jeneh and forms an impassable barrier to the went. To the east also the valley is bounded by fierce mountains. To the south it appears that the valley opens cut, ftncdbc but I did not go beyond Jeiieh. I hope to do this later, for I Have received kind messages from the Imam telling me that he has informed all his Walls that I au to be assisted and honoured wherever I travel in Oman. 12. We returned by a valley west of the Fadi Smaail from which it is separated by barren mountains. We passed/--4- I d ( paafjod the villages of Silica, Hob, Gaila, Furepa and Laval ■■pv disuse through the dr/ing up of t\w springs, or through des~ traction bv raraudlng tribes* From Fingeh we rode down the tffarii rhodh, out ?nto the plain and on to Sib. ihe Wadi Khodh has a fine perennial strean winding about in the river bed, but nuch of the veter see r is to go to waste. It would be difficult to use it a?_l for the banks of the valley are rocky and steep and unsuited to cultivation. An attempt was once nade to carry it from one valley to another as is evidenced by a long water channel built well up the mountain side so as to keep tax the water at a high level to get it over a saddle into the next valley. 'The story is that the work was started by a rich unn to ta v e water to an almost waterless village aa an inducement to a certain villager to part with a lovely daughter. They say that the rich jui died before ho had completed the work. 13. The Journey I an afraid does hot rake an exciting tale, but as a preliminary it has achieved more than I could have hoped for in establishing contact with the Jctbal Akhdhar Shaikhs, and ascertaining their attitude towards the British Government. Yours sincerely. Sd/- A.C. Galloway. Political Agent, Muscat. .^ »y INDIA Ntf Burma Office. NOTES FOR REGISTRY. REGISTER NO. ^) act.j^V'W C V v\. 194 . 6 '. Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary (MAN Relations between the Sultan and the Sheikhs of the hinterland Secretary of State / Committee • ♦ Under Secretary Secretary of State Pe/usal - FOR USE BY DEPARTMENT ONLY. With the transfer of the capital from Rastaq in the interior to Muscat on the coast at the end of the 18th century, the position of the Sultans vis-a-vis the Onaiii tribes weakened; for the next hundred years various attempts were made to dethrone the Sultan, culminating in 1916 by the rebel tribes gaining complete control over Cman and organizing a Government there under the Imam of Onan. After prolonged negotiations in which H. M G. supported the Sultan, a settlement was reached in 1920 under the terms of which the Sultan undertook among other things not to interfere in the w internal affairs' of Cm an; and the tribes agreed to remain in peace and amity with the Sultan's Government and to undertake that travellers to Cman on their lawful business should be free and safe (P. 4 . 640 / 28 , paragraphs 50 and 51 flagged on Collection 20/2). The Treaty was not renewed on the abdication of Sultan Syed Taimur Bin Faisal and the succession of his son, Syed Said Bin Syed Taimur,- the present /Sultan;'I Sultan; but the Qnanis appearea to consider it unaffected by the change of rulers (PZo46/33 PZo37 1 /3^- flagged on collection 20/2). The present Imaai, Luhairmad Bin Abdullah al Khalili, who lives xainly at the ancient capital of Rastaq is believed to be almost entirely under the influence of Sheikh Isa Bin Saleh al Harthi. He acknowledges the Sultan’s suzerainty, but is in fact independent. The Sultan’s influence in the hipterland has increased however in the last few years, partly by contact with the Sheikhs of the various tribes, partly by his control during the war of imported goods and partly oecause the establishment of an R.A.F. air base at Salalah gave the tribes visual evidence of the strength of H.KG.’s support. In i\.arch of this year Colonel Galloway, who was then Political Agent Muscat, visited the Jabal Akhdhar and stayed with Sheikh Hamad Bin Hamid, son- in-law of the Imam, from whom he learnt tha^ the Imam was dangerously ill and that Sheikh Sulaiman Bin Hamiyar al pabhani and SheiKn Isa Bin Saleh al Hart hi had met and apparently hatched a plot to divide Cman between them on his death (iixt. 191 &lt;4/^-5 below]:. After the meeting, where Sheikh Ali Bin Abdullah al Beni Bu Ali was also present Sheikh Sulaiman Bin Hamiyar went to Sur and from there sent a message on behalf of the Sheikhs to the Sultan that they wished to see him. The Sultan agreed to receive a representative in Dhofar and by him returned a message that he would lieak his journey to l.uscat at Sur and see Sheikh Sulaiman Bin Hamiyar there (Hxt. 2247/45 below). The Sultan arrived at Sur on 4th May and persuaaed Sheikh Sulaiman Bin Hamiyar and Sheikh Ali Bin Abdullah to go to Muscat as his guests; once there he did everything in his power to impress them (Ext.3494A-5 below). Both Sheikhs have declared that they will take no part in the election of a new Imam; as has Sheikh Isa Bin Saleh of the Sharquiyetu Meanwhile the Imam has written to the Sultan saying that he is sending an emissary to Muscat to discuss important questions. Hxactly what is behind all this is impossible to see from here. Colonel Galloway suggests in his letter of 4th June (Ext. 3075/45 below) that the Sheikhs wish to abolish the Imamate and the Sultan hopes to extend his influence over the hinterland probably relying on a H network of agreements' with the various Sheikhs. The outcome is of importance to us however for two reasons - oil and locusts. In the Winter of 1936-9 Petroleum Concessions Ltd., who hold oil concessions from the Sultan in respect of Muscat and Dhofar sent survey parties into the hinterland, one of which travelled .under the auspices of the Sultan, to the Baraimi oasis via the Batineh Coast, Ibri, Yanqul, Jabal Kafit and returned via Sohar (PZ.m- 70/39 flagged on Collection 30/110(3)). They were forced to travel too rapidly to make an effective survey, hov/ever, and had hoped to return to that area in the Winter of 1939-40, but that project and any further exploration had to be abandoned owing to the outbreak of vrar (PZ. 5742/39 fl&amp;ggeu on Collection 30/110(3)). The Company now wish to resume operations and propose to send a small mapping party to the Jabal Fayah - Baraimi — Jabal Hafit area a proaching it from the North, and possibly endeavour to penetrate inland from points along the coast between Ras al Hadd and Masirah (Ext. 1758/45 flagged on Collection 30/110(4)). The Political Resident considers that they should be asked to postpone the second half of this programme as 'any attempt to penetrate the hinterland from the uscat side this Winter ’would fetter the Sultan's freedan of action'‘(2xt*3^57A5 flagged on Collection 30/110(4)). The success of Petroleum Concession Ltd.’s operations in this area may well depend largely on the outcome of the present negotiations with the Sheikhs and the amount of protection the Sultan is able to give them. The Inter-departmental Camnittee on Locust control proposed that locust reconnaissance parties should penetrate Chian both from the North and the South Iasi Summer (Ext. 2242/45 flagged on File 6705 / 41 ). The Sultan refused permission for the Northern recomaissance nowever in view 'of the delicate situation in the hinterland' (Ext.3073/45 flagged on File Ext. 6705/41 )• The Locust Committee are anxious that such a reconnaissance should take place this Autumn and Mr. Thesiger who is to be in charge of this operation is leaving London for the Gulf next month, where he is to consult the Political Authorities and possibly the Sultan in the hope that the situation may by then be sufficiently stable to allow the penetration into the hinterland of a party of locust experts (Ext. 3805/45 flagged on File Ext. 670p/4l )• c/wj. &amp; 0. Secre h*vi\f A c or 'inf ormation, di ^ ^ '4 • J-iil UX l.ul U-LVJJL 1 # ^ ~ / M&amp; Confidential* D.O. No.S.771-8/62 The Politioal Agency, MUSCAT. 17th May, 1945. Dear Colonel Galloway, Will you please refer to demi-official letter No.S.428-a/fi2 dated the 17th March to Sir Geoffrey prior concerning the Sultan’a meeting with Shaikhe Sulairoan bin Hamyar and i\li bin Abdulla at Sur? and was auoceseful in persuading the Shaikhs to come to Muscat as his guests. The nature of their business was not disclosed at Sur and since their arrival at Muscat the Sultan has been busily engaged in doing Sverything possible to impress them. They were taken out to Bait al palaj and shown the armoury, and musketry practices from Mi.rani fort have been an almost dally occurence. Today they are being entertained at a special banquet and the Sultan has asked to be allowed to bring them to the arab dinner I am having here on the 19th. Both Shaikhs were present when I made my official call on the Sultan on the 16th. meeting of the two Shaikhs at Sur was the strengthening of the Ghafiri Confederacy to which they now wish to scours his approval and support. day or so but I do not expect to hear the outcome before the nail closes. The sultan arrived at Sur on the 4th May The Sultan considers that the object of the He hopes to start discussions within the next Yours sincerely Sd . R.I. Hallows. The Hon'ble It.Col.A.C.Galloway,OBB., Officiating political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bashire. % \t CO .FIDa.iTIAL J.O. Ho. 617-4 . Persian Julf Residency, Dear Sir Olaf, Will you please refer to the correspondence a ending with our Endorsement No. 584-S of the 3Oth * ay, 1945 ? 2 9 The situation as regards Oman now is that the io«no~,&lt;x mos t influential Shaikh of the Jabal Akhdhar, Sulaiman anti - reconnaissance bin hamiyar of the abhani, and Ali bin Abdullah of the pavI d la penctrad H, c Beni bu All of iiastom Ja’alan are now in :luscat and have HmJv ^ GC ^ a:rGcl that they will take no part in the election ,4of a new Imam after the death of ^uhaunad bin Abdullah al Khalili who is reported to be very sick. Shaikh Isa bin daloh of the Bharquiyeh, the most influential of all the Shaikhs in Oman, has made a similar declaration, I should have thought that this openly expressed determination to do away with the Imamate would be likely to encourage the Imam to take a new lease of life, actually he has sent a letter to the Sultan saying that he is sending an emissary to Muscat to discuss i iportant questions* 3m It is difficult to see clearly at this stage what the Sultan and the Shaikhs are really aiming at. It may be that the Sliaikhs desire the abolition of the Imamate, and possibly the Saltan may acquiesce in this, realising that there is no hope of being elected himself. The Sultan's main object is to extend his influence over the hinterland and he will probably, therefore, have to rely on a network of agreements with the various Shaikhs, I cannot see these latter giving up their independence and recognising the Sultan as their suzerain, though they must band the knee to him a little because of his control over i ports. The Imam's attitude will probably bo guided by an endeavour to secure some inheritance for his posterity. 4. The outcome is of importance to us because Petroleum Concessions Limited (vide India Office letter No. Ext. 1768/45 of the 84th April 1146) are now considering sending a geold fical survey party Into the Jabal in the winter of 1945-46. X think, on the whole, the present state of affairs is likely to assist our approadh rather than the reverse. I am sending a copy of this letter to Peel. Yours sincerely, 3d/- A.C. Gallowyy. sir Olaf isaroe , K, C«I ,&amp; *, 0.6,1., 1 , 0 . 0 ,, secretary to the Government or India in the External Affairs Department,t No •T),6053-MT2/ 45 • ^\&gt; ~JL ' ^ » x- 49 /v EXT 72384 ’JLu OPY External Affairs Department, New Delhi, The. 1 - W 45 CD i v &lt;%$ i 9 M-V V'' Please refer to Prior’s demi-official letter No&gt;372-3 o fjhe 12tte April 194_5 giving cover to Galloway’s report on his visit to the Jabal Akhdhar forwarded with his demi-official letter No.S.2070 of the 12th December 1944 . This is a very interesting account and it is understood that this is the first visit paid to this region since the time when Sir Percy Cox was Political Agent in Muscat, H.E, the Viceroy has read the report witn appreciation and regards Galloway’s journey as a useful opening into the interior of Oman which may prove valuable when oil- prospecting in this region reaches a firmer stage. Apart from the most interesting account of this fertile region of Arabia, the report suggests political developments of considerab e interes 1 and indicates that closer relations have been established witn a number of leading Shaikhs. I am sending a copy of this letter to Busnire. U-° fir’ &amp;L fcj &lt;h c*t^ / ^ /j- fU l* a* ^ i fU* c ✓v ^ j D.ti.Cleary, Ssq.. , .(S India Office. Whitehall, London, S.W.i. % Yours 5 u— Cu^t.1^ &amp;VL~P,LE co ^ CONFIDENTIAL. azaixx D«0. No. 361-3 ' - r,» ir*;**:-; INDIA DIRECT 47 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf presents his compliments to 945 Sir Olaf Caroe, K.C.I.E., C.S.I. ,I.C.S., Secretary to the Government of India, in the External Affairs Department. NEW DELHI . R.T. Peel Esquire, C.B.E., M.C., The India Office ,y LONDON, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s).»r f i R^py mm ho. 4 frok i uscat, © 1*4 ' • . ... mm affairs. 2247 59.- The Shaikhs of the Ban! Khalld ii the Ja'alan area have complained to Shaikh Suleiman bin Haihya#5that Shaikh All bln Abdullah al Uaraudaii the Shaikh of Ja'alan has appointed Sunni Qadhi over them. Shaikh Sulaiman has proceeded to Ja'alan to use his influence in obtaining the appointmant of an Abadhi Qadhl since -.. A b Ban! iChalid are Aoadhi* The *il bu daid ura Abaihis, better loiown ns ' Kl^warij” or 'The aevoltars'. rjsc;j . mm kK* :X.£&gt; (for the period 1st to 15th March, 1545) 74. Reference serial To. 59 of 1945, fhe discontent in Oi.an has led to a fleeting bct*G6n the dtiaiichs of the U.ast and Sulaliuan bln Hajiyar of tile Kabhani in the Jabal Akhdar. The meeting took place at harail, about 30 Allies south of Sur, after which Sulaiaan bin Hamyar proceeded to Sur. From th^e he sent a massage to the Sultan on behajf of the Shaikhs that they wished to see him iRUfcedlately. Eventually, the Sultan agreed to receive a representatIre in Dhofar and Shaikh Khainis bin Saif al Samedi was selected. This man once went to Bushire as represent- alive of the Beni Bu All to see the Resident over the tribe's claim to independence. On this occasion he has met with no success with the Sultan, who returned the reply that he might break his journey to Muscat at Sur to sea Sulaim&amp;n bln H a nyar if he Is still there.Notrs for Registry Under Secretary... Secretary of State .j. m ittee Under Secretary... Secretary of State Perusal 19 A«l Initials. Q VW ^ 7 EXT^mAL Department JXt,1 Subject: Visit of Political gent, ..•'jig cat, to the Jabal iilchdiiar i/XM' , r j?his entertaining report contains imich interesting information about conditions in the Jabal Akhdiaar and on the route from ..discat, an area about which little appears to oe known. It v/as visited by Sir Percy Cox and later by Bertram Thoms, but no political Agent has been there in recent years• Col.- Galloway motored to Sib and from there went by camel to Bidbia and thence down /adi Sumail, with its fine date gardens to Sumail where he was entertained by the /ali and talked with a number of Shailchs and Qazi v/ho cauplained of tlie ‘Hardship engendered by the 'Control System' Prom Sumail the political Agent journeyed up the /adi iiuwahi to-Jineh where he stayed 'with Shaikh Hamad Bin Hamid son in law ox the Ijnam, v/ho told him that the ]3nam vas unlikely to live much longer and of the plans of the Shaikhs to divide Oi.an/ (26620) Wt.88611/P.141 6,000 10/48 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685Oiiian at his death. The party returned by a valley west of the fadi Suinail to I’ingeh and ao\m the Wadi Khodh to Sib. (a very rough sketch map of the route is attached.) Gol. Gallovfay seems to have done good work in making contact with the . Shaikhs of the Jabal Akhdhar and in ascertaining their attitude towards His idL je s ty * s Gove rams nt.British Consulate &amp; aiitlcal Age nicy, Muscat, the 12 :h 194 ll : y dear -&gt;ir Geoffrey Just before my departure for Jalalah in -/ovei oer 5 I received an interest !'2 letter from JhailGi Sulaiman bin Hamyar al Nabhani. He resides at Tanuf in the Jabal A^idhar, and is the leading Shaikh in the western part of the ran^e. He styled himself king of the Nabhani, and enquired in gracious terms about the British Government, jyself, vives - in the plural - and my children. His two sons also sent their compliments. the purchase of some rice by his messenger. I did this, and also sent him a few bags as a return present for the pomegranates and walnuts he had sent me. 9• This approach to the .igencv is the first for lany years, and I should .like to follow it up. I intend to^mention to trie Bultan that I should like to visit the area, and shall make the approach on the grounds that it seems that the supply*' situation there needs attention. 2 His 'ain object was to ask me to facilitate Yours sincerely dd/- A.C. Galloway The Hon’ble Gir Geoffrey frioy Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf. fJBHIRB.% - ^ Dear Gallo-vay, Please refer to your demi-official letter No. 3. 2070 dated the 12th Dec eater, l r c44 regarding Shaikh Sulai'^an bin Hamyar al Nabhani. 2. This sounds promising and I should be very interested to hear what progress you make. 3d/-G30FPRSY PRION MajttJr A.C. Oallo'vay, O.R.E Political Agent, ^. us cat.British Consulate and Political .-ipency, r.uscat. D.C. No.3.434-8/62 Dated 18th Parch, 1945. . y dear 3ir Geoffrey, //ill you please refer to trie correspondence ending with your demi-official letter No. 964^dated the 31st. Dece her, 1844. 2 . In Delhi I obtained the Bultan’s concurrence to y visiting the Jabal Akhdhar, and so on ry return I wrote to Bhaikh Sulairaan bin Hamyar, suggest ing a visit. He replied saying that he would ’welcome a visit from #e, but' added that he was leaving his own country for the 'green country of the east'. He has since this written again inviting me to visit him. 3. As it was unlikely that he would be back in the mountain within a month, and as it was certain that by then I should not have the ti le to 'lake the joUrney, I decided to lake a preliminary visit to see Bhaikh Hamad bin Hamid at Jeneh, close to oti, at the foot of the Hountain beyond the 7/adi Bumail in the Nadi Huwahi. 4. I therefore asked Rai Bahadur Gokaldas to obtain some fast camels, and suggested to him that he 'night accompany me. This he did, and / am grateful for his company and assistance. 7/&lt;ju set out from Bib by lorry to the foot of the hills where, after considerable difficulty from the guide lost the way, we picked up the camels which had been sent on ahead overnight. * Ne entered the hills at Rasal, and continued eastwards up the Nadi Rasal for some two hours, and passed the small villages of Jafnain and araira. At flaraira the track winds through the hills, and after passing Batih, leads to Fin/geh. There was no running water in the valley in contrast to many others we travelled in later, and the village water supplies are from wells. The hillsides near the villages bristle with old watch towers, all of which are abandoned. Fingeh can be described as a small town, and is situated on a northern slope overlooking miles of fine date gardens planted on the north side of the river bed. There is a fair sized perennial stream of sweet water which supplies the town and gardens. The town is protected by two large towers situated on promontories at each end of the town which is built on a cliff overhanging the valley. These forts were newly whitewashed, and ih good re pair. 5 . From Fingeh we rode southwards up the valley passing the villages of Bharu, |Anikat, I’ilayana and Hurta, until we arrived at Bidbid. This is a large village which gets its importance from the presence of a scmare serai type of fort in which the Nali lives. Neither he, nor the .azi, were there when I passed through. At Bidbid I saw for the first time fields of wheat and other crops watered from channels on the Persian .system. There are only date palms at Fingeh, and we found it impossible to buy . luce:cfiie for our camels there. Fodder should be brought from Bidbid, and I think we were thought to be rather stupid for not snowing this. The Hon’ble Bir Geoffrey Prior,H.C.I.I.^ Political Resident,Persian Gulf. 3h &gt; 1 /r * - 2 - over a broad ston v:f ■' p aTCu JK 1 J ^ p 1 a iv' t’or thl 9^£ley 6 . From Bidbid we rode about two hours before we entered t.ie ,/adi Lunail, north of ourur. 3urur is the ! iost northerly village of a number dotted at intervals along the banks {p f t for about 12 miles. At the northern end oi the datv and fruit gardens are not re iarkable for ftheir (fertility or the size of the trees 3 but in the centre of the valley in the neighbourhood of the fort I saw the finest date gardens I have ever seen. There are large mango and other fruit trees also. V, r e spent one night at bumail in the guest house of the /ali. lie was most hospitable and friendly, and sent ie a lamb for dinner. This was a great treat, especially for dwellers in I,Muscat where the only meat killed, except on rare occasion^,is one goat a day. He told me that the lack of rain in the last few years Had resulted in a diminution in the number and size of the flocks and it is be seen. the excess . Tonpointr an addition was a fco due to the lack of grazing. This may be so, quite true that there are very few flocks to ,*ith t e next breath, however, he complained of rain last summer had ruined'-,the date crop out that the rain would eventually result in to the water supply by reviving the springs long-term policy to be receive.d with favour. The rain does not really 'spoil the date crop, but the drying of the dates. In Oman there is a kind of date which they gather just before it is ripe, -nd boil in large earthenware pots. They then spread the boiled dates on the river bed to dry. If it rains during the drying period considerable loss is sustained. % I® 7 . as Bu iail numbers of Ihaiklis and the leading w azi visited me in the guest house garden where I sat under the large mango trees. They talked a little of the war, but did not show much interest in it beyond its effect upon themselves. They asked me if the ’’control system” were an invention of the British Government, and if I thought that it was necessary. They said that it caused great hardship to themselves as it resulted in their being short of cloth and grain. I replied saying that certainly in war time it was absolutely necessary to control supplies. 7/hen we were warming to the conversation the V/ali suddenly asked to be allowed to leave for a few minutes. //hereupon he and his greybeards went away and held a confabulation just out of earshot behind the guest house. They came back after what seemed an inter minable time, for it was nearly 11 o’clock at night and I had been riding all day, and turned to the weather as ‘ a subject of conversation. I suppose their native caution had overcome them. S. The 3umail fort is a large stone building perched on a rock some 100 feet high in the middle of the valley where it broadens out a little. There is a small bazaar there where stinking fish is sold. Hue people buy smAll quantities of this, and carry it home dangling on a piece of stick, and that is not to be wondered at either. The ’ entrance to the valley from the south is guarded by two large forts also situated on the top of out-crops of rock. I took photographs of these, but could not do so of the iumail fort as the ./ali said that the taking of photographs was against his religion. It is from the south of 3umail that’ the Jabal *mkhdhar is first seen. 9. ,/e continued our journey over barren stony Gauntry in a broad/-r -o- a broad valley about 10 miles across. After a 3 houi^s ride it narrowed to a pass by which we entered the .7adi Huwahi, The northern entrance of this valley is guarded • by the usual towers and forts built on rocky promontories but here the fortifications.are strengthened - or were for all is now falling to pieces - by a wall diking linkin them up. There was more soil here and each village - we passe ' kingeah, One lay and Llureila - has its wheat fields irrigated in trie Persian style, as v/ell as date gardens and mango trees. After a 5 hours’ fast ride we arrived at Jeneh at the southern end of the ./adi Auv/ahi. This is the home of Shaikh lamad bin Hamid, who was once in the service of the iultan of I.uscat, but who now lives on his own property through which travellers from I'uscat and the Batinah must pass to reach Nezwa, the town of his father-in-law, the Imam. He was very pleased to see ae, and during t'e halt of a day and a half took me for walks in the hills and gardens. He asked numerous questions about the war, and regretted that his radio was oat of order. I have sent it to India for repairs, but after its return am faced with the problem of supplying him with charged batteries. i 10. He told me that the Imam was very ill and M that it was not thought that he would live much longer. He said that that was the reason for Ihaikh Julaiman bin Hamyar's going to Tamil to meet bhaikh Isa Bin Jaleh al Harthi. They wished to settle on a policy to follow after the Imam’s death. According to Hamad bin Hamid their plan was to divide Oman into two parts, and fir Sulaiman bin Kamyar to rule the western part and Isa bin laleih the eastern. Hamad was concerned that.the Sultan was apparently playing no part, and he asked me if I know the reasons. I knew nothing about.it, and in i any case was sceptical. There is no doubt though that there is some big game afoot, for not only have the leading Shaikhs met at Tamil and sent a message to the Sultan, but also Hamad asked me if the British Govern ment would t^ke direct action to assist should a certain event take place. I was not to be caught so easily as that, and asked what event he might be thinking of. But he would not say, so I replied that I must first ’mow i the proposition before I could g r ive a reply. It is interesting to know that the Shaikhs of Oman have been, and perhaps are, contemplating making a proposal to the British Government. The meeting at Tamil, vide my demi-official letter Ho. 423-8/62 dated the 17th march, 11-45, also proves that should they do so it will probably be in connection with the distribution of supplies over which there appears to be considerable ill feeling in Oman. I have informed the Sultan, and suggested that he should look into the attar on his return to Huscat. It is, in fact, essential that we should do so. 11. The eastern slope of the Jabal Akhdhar, which is very steep and which is covered with scrub jungle at the t6p, towers over Jeneh and forms an impassable barrier to the west. To the east also the valley is bounded by fierce mountains. To the south it appears t' at the valley opens out, faxxix but I did not go beyond Jeneh. I hope to do this later, for I have received kind lmessa:es from the Imam telling me that he has informed ! all his Halls that I am to be assisted and honoured * 1 wherever I travel in Oman. 12. We returned by a valley west of the Wadi ouiail from which it is separated by barren nountains. We passed/-\ r t -4- passed the villages of 3inga, ■and came out again at -Fingeh. number of disused and broken down water channels built of rocii and lime. They may have either fallen into disuse through the drying up of the springs, or through des truction by marauding tribes. From Fingeh we rode down trie Jadi' Khodh, out into the plain and on to 3ib. The V/adi luiodh has a fine perennial strea r i winding about in the river bed, but much of the water seems to go to waste. It would be difficult to use it all for trie banks of the valley are rocky and steep and unsuited to cultivation. An attempt was once ’ ade to carry it from one valley to another as is evidenced by a long water channel built well up the mountain side so as to keep 1fex t?ie water at a high level to get it over a saddle into the next valley. The story is that the work was started by a rich man to take water to an almost waterless village to a certain villager to part with a They say that the rich man died before the work. as an induce nent lovely daughter, he had completed The journey I an afraid does not make an exciting than I 13. tale, but as a preliminary it has achieved more could have hoped for in-establishing contact with the Jabal Akhdhar' hhaikhs, and ascertaining their attitude towards the British Government. Yours sincerely. 3d/- A.3. Galloway, Political Agent, uscat.CONFIDENTIAL. No - C/373 of 1940. FILE COPY l”.. 69/ 5 fa io 1 . 1940 j ^,4 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to h j)-**-. 1. O.K.Garoe Eaquire, CIE. f Ic:S., Secretary to the Government of India, External Affaire department, Hew Delhi. 2L. R.T*Peel Hi^uire, C3E.,MG., j The India Office, London,* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). 2. The Political Resident is glad the Political Agent, Muscat, will soon be in possession of a reliable launch. 4 British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp, Bahrain• P) Htpr l 23rd October, 1940. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Subject. Muscat letter Lo.C/461 of 27th August 1940*with enclosures• Muscat letter Ho.G/462 of 27th August 1940. Political Agent Muscats recent journey to SUR etc. 4 J 1 H ’ICopy. D.O.No. C/461. f 'I &gt; i British Consulate and itolitical Agency, Muscat, the 27th August 1940. My dear Colonel Prior, I enclose a brief note on my recent journey to Sur. I found the land part very trying and sincerely hope that circumstances at Sur will not arise making my immediate presence there necessary. It is a severe physical strain especially at this time of the year. The way from C^ariyat to Dhibab is much the same as from Swakum to Dhibab but less trying. 1 did not go that way as it would have involved my going by donkey to ^ariyat, a four hour journey. The trip was in every way satisfactory. 1 was able to renew my acquaintance with the Wali, discuss matters of moment with the Hindus who I found well satisfied with their lot, and well they might be, and at the same time examine the coast and means of travel. I was particularly impressed with Ghail bhaab and the wonderful water there within fifteen to twenty yards of the sea i so convenient for renewing a failing water supply by ocean going craft. On examining Lorimer I see that 'olives” are reported to be grown at Hail al Ghaf• This is of course absurd as geographically the place is quite unsuitable to the cultivation of olives. I had previously been confused by statements that olives were to be found at Baraimi and in other parts of the lower level districts of Oman. This confusion is due to the fact that the local name * * l for the guava is (J 5^/ and not 80 where Lorimer says 'olive” please read 'guava”. The Hon f ble Lt .Col.C.G.Prior, CIS., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, i Bushire. Yours sincerely, ed. T.Hickinbotham.Copy Reasons for four. Communications ^ /I P' REPORT ON A VISIT TO SUR IN AUGUST.1940&gt; Sur is the second largest sea port in the terri tory of the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. A very considerable trade in 'wet* and 'dry M dates is carried on with India and quantities of rice, sugar, and piece goods are imported from India by native craft. Practically the whole of the trade of the port is in the hands of the British I Indian CoLimunity. The British Indian community consist of 62 Hindu merchants, naturally various problems must arise from time to time and period! cal visits by the Political Agent at Muscat are necessary to examine these problems and to make such representations as may be desirable to the local officials and if necessary to the Sultan himself. • The normal means of communication with Sur which is situated on the coast about one hundred miles from Muscat and twelve miles from Ras Al Hadd is by country craft. This form of travel is extremely uncertain depending as it does on the strength and direction of the wind and a voyage may be as short as twelve hours or as long as twelve days. Sur can also be reached by land via ^ariyat, Dhibab, and Tiwi. The land journey takes four days and is a very difficult and trying undertak ing even in the cold weather as it is possible to Motor only as far as &lt; L ariyat and from there onwards donkeys are the only means of transport which can negotiate the extremely difficult and rough track. A well engined launch could do the journey in ten hours in all weathers except the very worst storms. Unfortunately such craft are not avail able locally. The Political Agent not being supplied with one and there being none owned by the local business houses. On the present occasion 1 determined to examine the land route partly because it would, in an emergency be the only one practicable if there were contrary winds or storms at the time an emergency occurred, and partly because a visit was long overdue and the only power craft at Muscat, a decrepit thirty foot launch capable of a maximum speed of five knots in a flat calm, was reported to be out of commission being laid up with engine trouble. However this launch was ready the evening before I was due to start and so I decided to hire it and arranged for it to accompany me by sea while 1 travelled by land. 1 travelled by land as far as Dhibab and then took to the launch as land tr vel in the heat was difficult and from Dhibab onwards the track is decernable from the sea and a full idea of the difficulties to be overcome and the distances to be covered can be obtained. My return journey was made by launch to ( b ariyat and from there to Muscat by land. The launch broke down twice on the way to Sur and twice on the return journey. I am glad to say that the sea was calm / whenS'1940 J , when we were stationary carrying out repairs and except for the excessive heat and delay were not inconvenienced* While at Sur the launch on two occasions broke down completely after I had embarked to go to Khor Jarama but I am pleased to record we were only a short distance from Sur on each occasion. The launch was so unsatis factory that I hired a local craft for the return journey and actually left Sur in her but as the wind changed to dead ahead and the launch appeared to be working unusually well I transferred to the launch and with the exception of a breakdown for two hours in the middle of the night off a rocky shore the journey was completed without incident. The country craft followed ready to render assistance should it be necessary and a system of pre-arranged signals was worked out* Sur. As I have already noted the Hindu population is 62. 1 found them very contented with their situation. Their relations with the local Governor are very good and 1 gathered that trade is also in a very satisfactory state* I had several interviews with them collectively and also saw individuals privately. There were several points which they asked me to take up for them and I am glad to say 1 found no difficulty in havjng them dealt with to the satisfaction of the local authority and the merchants themselves. A problem of more importance in regard to the safe guarding of their business premises 1 reserved for discussion with the Sultan at Muscat. The tribal situation in the town is satisfactory and will not be likely to deteriorate as long as the present Governor remains in office • i am not so happy about the tribal situation in Jaalan as the feud betv/een the Beni T Hasan and the Beni Bu Ali still continues and I see no immediate likelihood of a settlement being reached* I am distinctly uncomfortable about our lack of communica tion with the British Indian community and cannot too strongly urge that steps be taken without delay to provide a reliable powerfully engined launch so that assistance can be given in the shortest possible time should the need arise .APiOTDIX. Land Route to Sur from Muscat * Muscat to Swakunu 50 mile a. Swakum :«* A large date garden the property of Mohammad Naaib Khan, a Muscat subject* A motorable track which would be impracticable in wet weather* Swakum to Hail al Ghal . 12 miles, (Lorimer Vol.II page 603)* A very difficult track v/hich crosses very rough high ground# Donkeys and camels can be used, the latter with considerable difficulty* ^resh water available at Hail. Hail to Dhibab * 17 miles# Dbibab A scattered fishing village# A difficult mountainous track along which only donkeys can pass and in parts riding is impossible* Fresh water available near Dhibab* Dhibab to Tiwi * 22 miles. ^Lorimer Vol.II page 1906). A rough rocky track useable by camels and donkeys. Ho fresh water is available until Ghail Shaab is reached which is a mile and a half west of Tiwi and where there is unlimited fresh water in close proximity to the sea* The water at Bamma and Fins is brackish. Tiwi to Sur . The same hard trail negotiable by donkeys and camels. Water is available at ^alhat which is half way between these two places. Scale of char ges. Donkeys from t 0 ariyat to Sur via Swakum cost four rials each for the journey. The cost of the animals T food being on the owner and of the owner’s food on the hirer. (Donkeys are not available at Sv/akum). , Camel hire is one rial aday with the same conditions as to food. 1 Donkeys from ^ariyat to Swakum cost one rial and as the journey is only a short one of four hours the (iuestion of food does not arise.D.O.No.C/462. August 27th, 1940 I have just returned from a tour to Sur. I travelled partly by land and partly by sea* I called in at several places between here and Sur, in particular Quriyat, Dhibab, Ghail Shaab and Tiwi. I was impressed by the v/ater supply at Ghail Shaab and suggest that the place would be well worth a visit. Ghail Shaab is about one and a half to two miles from Tiwi on the Muscat side. There is a small village with a single round tower situated on the east bank of a wadi some hundred yards in width which issues from a very precipitous valley. The village is some one hundred and fifty to two hundred feet above the Wadi, approaching from the sea the tops of a few palms are visible over the top of the shingle beach. Just the other side of the sh ngle and no more than twenty yards from the sea is what can only be described as a fresh water lake. The water is not brackish and is slowly moving. 1 have no idea of the length of the lake as 1 only went about two hundred yards up the wadi. The bed of the wadi is green grass and the lake has a gravel bottom. An ideal place for an ocean going craft to refill with fresh water if the where abouts of the lake are known which 1 think doubtful. Large dhows en route from Sur to Basrah fill up with water regularly and after five had filled up 1 saw no diminution in the supply remaining. 1 measured three foot of water at the ford which is some hundred and fifty yards from the sea. Yours sincerely, sd. T.Hickinbotham. Captain C.M.Graham, R,N. , Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf.-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00021f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2999</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00021f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2999</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/39 'Muscat: Tours of Political Agent; General Situation in Oman; Including assistance to Sultan of Muscat - RAF support'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-20T22:14:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (138 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 140; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence, notes, and minutes relating to the situation in the interior of Oman. The papers cover the following matters:the Sultan's ambition to assert his authority over the tribes of the interior of Oman due to the Imam's ill healththe question of what military (arms and personnel) support the British should provide for the Sultan, including the appointment of a Military Adviser and a cash subsidythe financial responsibility for such supportthe question of whether to provide Royal Air Force (RAF) support to the Sultanthe question of securing the co-operation of the tribes of the interior for the development of oil resources in the region.Principal correspondents include officials at the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, India Office, Government of India (External Affairs Department), Admiralty, War Office, Treasury, Ministry of Fuel and Power (Petroleum Department), Foreign Office, and Air Ministry.Also contained in the file are the following reports:'Report on a Visit to Sur in August 1940' by Tom Hickinbotham, Political Agent at Muscat, with a letter to the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf regarding fresh water sources in the area, dated 27 August 1940 (folios 137-140)Report on a trip to Jabal Akhdhar by Arnold Crawshaw Galloway, Political Agent at Muscat, dated 18 March 1945 (folios 131-34, with sketch map on folio 127).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Military support</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Treasury</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>War Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Division</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Ministry</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Internal politics</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00021f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>