<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000170_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T04:10:08.311Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Telegram:- xndian 4 ,ord dole. 4.1 O • “ 245. tec:- ‘13rd hebru; ry 1121. Prom:- Political Bahrain. Po :~ Postmaster General Karachi. td:~ ^ecretary Bushire. Owing 1 increase staff and records regret impossible louse post Office from 1st ^ril in ‘xi ;enc7 buildin u dan however give use two suitable rooms adjoining guard room which with small alteration, would be suitable. I.„.L hupervisor is present and could estimate cost and put work in hand. Only alternative would be to build special room adjoining lostmaster T s quarters.4 rM Telegram:- Indian »&lt;ord Code. No:- 245. Lated:- 23ru February 1921. From:- Political Bakrain. To:- Postmaster General Keracki Rptd:- Secretary Buskire. Owing increase staff and records regret impossible kouse Post Office from 1st April in Agency building. Can kowevor give use two suitable rooms adjoining guard room wnick witk smell alteration wouic? bo suitable. F.u.!■ Supervisor is present and could estimate cost and put work in band. Only alternative would be to build special room adjoining Postmaster’s quarters. No: iy-(7 . Political Agency, Bakrain.tke 23rd Februpry 1931. Copy forwarded to tne Post i*Iaster,Bakrain. Political Agency, Baki-ain. ~TELEGRAM From 3 a3L! : ,v &lt;jL - j.R.Lo.LLu La tea 'L-L-oi COLS L.P•T. Karachi. Political, Bahrain. Latea nil (receivea Era Larch 1931). No. ea/8 ea/8 aaa Your telegram 23rd X&amp;hKixxigc receivea mutilateo two pieces aaa Presume present post office building reauired political purposes ana aaaitional rooms proposed to be built for post office will be at Political expense for wuich rent will be charged this aepartment aaa if so no apparent objection aaa Suggest you obtain estimate for conversion of rooms adjacent guard room also and.submit both proposals with site plan ana furtner details for final consiaeration.Government of India letter No«976-£st B, dated tne 10th April 1912)that the Post Office was maintained largely for political reasons, and that the expense of 7661/- was too great for a small post office* In his letter No.426 dated the 10th August 1912 to the Residency, the Political Agent disposed of this argument, and proved conclusively that the Post Office had been making, as it does now, a handsome Post Office for years past. 4. Complications now arose regarding the site but in his letter No.2314 dated 22nu September 1912 to the Government of India, Sir Percy Cox brought to their notice the letter No.426 mentioned above, and concurred in the view that the Post Office was by no means a losing concern 5. In his letter No.143 dated the 6th of March 1913 the Political Agent requested the Resident to have the work put in hand as soon as possible, and again in his letter No.133 dated the 3rd of February 1914 he urged that the building might be expeditea, pointing out that it had been sanctioned in 1910. The matter was, however, bound up with the question of clerks quarters, and in 1915, in his telegram No.33 dated the 7th of January 1915 the Political Agent agreed to the Post Office remaining in site for the time being. During the war years the matter apparently remained in abeyance. 6. It will be seen that the provision of a Post Office has been overdue since 1908. Now, with an additional clerk sanctioned and another to be sanctioned from the beginning of the new financial year, the need is more imperative than ever. Further, the records increase as time goes on, and, with the vast volume of judicial work require considerable additional space each year. It has just been brought to my notice that some have suffered from damp through being improperly housed, and if ur-enF action is not taken others will deteriorate. 7. It did not seem to me that a Ueyv ajs high cost was required at the momerLfr^ Ae-L great delay in obtaining tne necessary grants* It is convenient to both the Post Office and the Agency that they should be close to each other, and I therefore searched for some out-building that could be made to serve the purpose* In the cells by the front door the very thing was ^veiiatrhe and since the prisoners are now kept in the Bahrain Govern- -ment jail, the rooms could be made available. The word f cells ; has an unfortunate sound, but it will be seen that .they are in reality fine lar;e and well built rooms, andy needless to say ; of solid construction, and with slight alteration they will serve their purpose admirably. 8. It will be noticed that the estimate I forward comes to Rs*2205 (plus a small charge for reinstalling electric light fittings), but of this only 1500 can be debited to the work proper as the rest consists of repairs which the Public Works Department would in any case have to undertake shortly. In other words the Post Office can secure convenient and suitable accomodation for a cost of Rs.1500, as against 7600/- for the last estimate made in 1914 for a new building. On whom this 1500/- should fall I cannot say The Postal Department are making a handsome profit out of Bahrain, and primafacie they should find the money, but the rent agreement between them and the Public Works Department may alter the case. My only request is that the matter should be decided as rapidly as possible and the work put in hand. Failing this arrangement I fear the Postal Depart -ment will have to lease a building elsewhere as I cannot agree to allowing them the space they now occupy a moment longer than is absolutely necessary. I have the honour to be, Sir* Your most obedient servant V - m \ si ( ill Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to:- The Post faster General/Karachi. •,Copy of tli« tcie^mw #ved/&amp; dated nil received 3rd &amp;arch 1931 fr*om Director, Posts nod Telegraphs, Karachi to the Political iigent, Bahrain. ed/8 aaa Your telegram 23rd received mutilated two places aaa Fresurae present post ofiice building required political purposes and additional rooms proposed to be built for post office will be at Political expense for which rent will be chargee this department a&amp;a if so no apparent objection aaa Suggest you obtain estimate for conversion of rooms adjacent guard room also and submit both pro£&gt;osals with site plan and further details for final consideration.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Depakiuent. EXPRESS LETTER — Ihh is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to le treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched^] F&amp;om Political Bahrain. To Secretary Bushire. No. Dated 25th April Please refer my letter No:351 dated 15th March 1931 regarding Post office on which apparently no action taken. Post Master General states he cannot find funds for building * in control of other department,but that if the two rooms mentioned are handed over permanently he will find funds necessary alterations. I see no objection and trust Resident will agree. Request matter may receive^dCrly attention. Sd/- C.G.Prior. s. e. MGIPC—FP-596DCF-iS&amp;P—(C t. 1807;—7-i-a7—?,00,000,flc. m cf 19.31. British Besi&amp;ency &amp; Ocnsulate-Oeneral Bushtre, the April 1931. To The Icaitical Ate it B A H B B I N Mencrandum. | ■Reference your letter No.351, dated the 15th March 1931. 1 forward, herewith, for your information a copy cf letter No.y/355 dated the 9th April 1931, received from the Assistant Engineer, Persian Oulf Suh-Division, which explains the position regarding the cost of additions and alterations to the portion cf the du ilding occupied oy the Po^t Office and recovery cf rent for this portion from the Postal Administration Please forward fresh estimates and plans for carrying out the necessary alterations. The papers received with you letter under reference are returned herewith By order» Oaptain, Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian G-u^f.CJcpy ci‘ letter Nc.W/355, la.tel the 9th A^ril 19 31, from the Assistant ^iigineer, Independent Persian Gulf* Suh-Divistcn, Bushire, tc the Secretary tc the Political ■Resident in the Persian ^u-tf, Bushire. '5; Pest crrice at Bahrein. »*ith reference tc ycu^ No.652, dated the 27th/28th March 1931, forwarding Political Agent, Bahrein’s letter Nc.351, dated the 15th March 1931, in original, on the above subject, for remarks, i have the honour tc state that since the construction of the Agency Buildings at Bahrein in the year.1902, a room was provided by the then Political Agent for use as Post Office, Excepting this, there is nothing else on the record of this office tc show As tc ^n what conditions the use cf the room in Question as a Post Office was allowed. The Government w India have, however, decided tc recover rent from the Commercial Departments for the accommodation supplied to them by the Public Works Department in the Central Buildings, with effect from 1st April 1929, and, the necessary rent statements in respect of such amount cf accommodation as has already been supplied for Post and Telegraph Offices at Bush ire, Bahrein and Muscat, res pectively, have been prepared and submitted tc the Govern ment cf India, through the Accountant General, Central ■Revenues, New Delhi, and their final sanction as tc the amount cf rent tc be recovered, from the departments concerned,, is still awaited. 2. The cost of proposed additions and alterations and Special repairs will be borne by the Central Government and not by the Postal Department. 3. The Political Agent’s letter is herewith returned.C’s. P. P.—L (in) 977— 400-1-30—k. No. _Jl2 2^_of 193 j/. The Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the l&gt;jro *93 i To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident MEMORANDUM Pleaso refer to ^emorcnduni .'io:772 oated tae 14in Lpri 1 retrain# tne transfer of inc a rain dst Of lice to tnen 1 h? ve no objection to the work bein' carried out by tne central Government and not by the 'ostai I apartment# in this apparently desireu by him,for i nave no means of coin.;; it rnysefl one of rreat uryoncy,Enci if there is any lii/Xihood of wty hitch, in his bein/; supplied with funds by the central Government 4 it would be far better to xi&amp;ve the two rooms nanded orer to tue ostai lopartment so t^at they may allot the funds run tai:e the necessary steps imediately* .ney will,! understand,carry h out the work tkrouyh the agency of the ublic orks l epartment if the rooms are handed orer to them# tu the ostai ley? rtraent*then 1 ’.^oula re quest trial tx*e ost telegram so L.at no r-i&amp;y make the necessary application for funas,but if it is ueciued that the work should be carried out ! by us and rent charged as before,then i would be glad if the department of ublic works could be instructed to make what alteration they consider necessary in the estimate arid have ^ ^ the &lt;vork put in hand at the earUest possible opportunity, another site if t^e assistant ingineer is confident that he can obtain funus without delay for the additions ana alter- ations to the two cells so as to accommodate the ost office, 1 would point out,however,teat the uestion is aster General at arachi may be informed accordingly by sTELEGRAM From To CODE. Political, Bahrain. Resident, Busiiire. No.605(not telegraphed). Dated the 17th May 1931. My 522 dated 3rd May 1931. How does matter stand? Third vernacular office clerk expected next down mail.I. E. No. 687-IgA Dated 20-5-31. TELEGRAM CODE. From Secretary, Bushire. To Political, Bahrain. No. nil Dated and received 2uth May 1931. Your telegram dated 18th May Post Office accommodation. Public Works Department asked to submit estimates urgently.Cott.- 4 (X Indian Posts and Telegraphs Department. ' , \ No. ED-8 r Fhom The Director of Posts and Telegraphs, Slna and Paluchlstan circle. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Number of enclcsures C ■V Dated Karachi , the Subject:- Sir, 30 th Aprij. Transfer of block of prison cells in the residency at Bahrain to the Indian Posts and Telegraphs Department. With reference to your letter No.351 deted the 15th March 1931, to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf a copy of v.hich vas furnished to me, I have the honour enquire the terms on vhlch the Residency prison cells vlil be transferred to the Indian Posts anc Telegraphs Department. It is presumed that no debit v.ill be raised against this department for the present value of the building. y i V ’i I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, K. ■: J Director. (iP 51 GiPAJb.—1317—1-I1-28.—2,50,030. Vo M kTo v No. ‘ftO of 1931. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General. Bushire, the May 1931. The Assistant ^gineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sul)-Division, Bushire. ' ii * i i Meracranduia . Beference your memorandum No. W/355 dated the 9th April 1931. Kindly submit, urgently estimates for converting the two rooms adjoining the entrance of the Bahrein Agency building into offices for the Post office. By Order, 1 ■I &gt; Under Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copy tc the Political Agent, Bahrein with a refer*ence tc his letter No. 522 dated the 3rd May 1931. (J { t\i 7TilLEGHill GODS. From Political, Bahrain. To Secretary, Bushire. No. Dated the 18th June 1931. Please inform me whether alteration guard rooms for Post Office approved and if so earliest date work can be put in hand.ITo. /3W of 1931. British. Kesidency &amp; Consulate-General. Busjoire, the Zff/' June 1931. (z J The Political Agent, Bahrein. ^&gt;'7 -i8/l( Memorandum. Your telegram dated the June, 1931 regarding seconversion of guard room into offices foe Post Office. l*he estimates have been approved by the Hobble the Political Resident and the Assistant engineer, Independent Persian Gulf ^ub-l)ivision is instructing the supervisor at Muscat by telegram to proceed to Bahrein to take the work in hand i$r orderPolitical Agency, Bahrain, the 27th June 1931. From The Political Agent, Bahrain To The Director of Posts &amp; Telegraphs Sind &amp; Baluchistan Circle Karachi• Sir I have the honour to refer to your letter No:SD/8 dated the 30th April 1931 and to say that it is not now intended to transfer the prison cells of the Agency to the Postal Department,and that the work is now being undertaken by the Department of Public Works for the Residency. Instructions have been given for the work to be put in hand at once and I presume that the for rent arrangement will held good mmA the Post Office changes to its new site. I have the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant Political Agent,Bahrain.\ Ko. 121 of 1931. Office of the Supervisor, P.W.D Bahrain. Dated 9th July 1931. ; (Vdv 92*' flS^ll f-7-V. &gt;^ 4 ,^ To The Political Agent, Bahrain• Sir, 7 Subject Conversion of two cells into lost Oft -/P With reference to youf Ko. 820 dated 8th July 1931. with a copy of Subiost Plasters letter Ko. 138 dated 8th July 1931. putting forward some suggestions in connection with the conversion the two cells‘‘to lost Office, 1 beg to/report that the sugges tions are good and they ought to have been told before the preparation of plans and estimate by the PUblick „orks^e P art. ; ven now it is not too latS.but have to prepare a suppimentaxy estimate, and obtain necessary sanction and allotment. The following are the suggestions from the Sub Post blaster. 1 To build parcel room in new verandah. It can be done, since there is provision for putting up a parcel room of expanded metal and timber. 2 providing extra door and windows to front wail. Cost amounts to aa20/ which is to be provided » Plastering of floor and white washing of walls. Plastering of floor is prided in the estimate, and white washing will be done as it does not cost much. 3 Removal of centre wall between two ceils. j Can be done and the cost can be met from contingencies and 1 other saving's. 4 Raising the present walls hy 3 feet. Cost amounts to Ks400/ and is to be provided. 5 Making roof water tight. Can only be done by providing 1 Ply rok roofing, the cost amounts to Ssl86/ is to be provided. 6 Pixing of 4 almirahs into wall. | Can be done and cost can be net from savings.V v In conclusion I Deg to say that there vail he an excess of '^00/ P over the present sanctioned estimate,and further without the proper sanction I can not deviate an inch from the sanctioned plan and estima ^ te f Th e proposed suggestions a** no doubt are very good and inorder to make the building look decent, and useful they are to be carried out, so the matter may please be refered to the Assistant Engineer, ushrr- I 'beg to remain, Sir, Your most otoedient servant, Supervisor. p.vv.D Bahrain.i.'o: S3/. Political Ag-ncy, Bahrain,tne 11th July 1531. To, The Assistant Engineer,, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division, Bushire. Memo randum . I enclose for your information a copy of a letter addressed to me by the Post Master,iahrain,and the reply to his requests by.the Public ;/orks Supervisor here. several of the r oat Master T s requests and I am asking the Supervisor to do so.but that others require a considerable sum of money which has not been sanctioned. These items 'NorSU hxtra doors and windows — Hs.lSO/-.” These doors and windows will improve the room and if funds are available may be provided. 'Item Mo:4. The raising of the walls” would also improve the building considerably and if the Rs.400/- reqnired is available 1 would be glad if it could be done. ho:5 - making the roof water tight. If this can be done and funds provided no doubt it would be very advantag eous^ t if the roofs leak the Post Master will not be the only one in this predicament since every room in my house, save one, leaked last year. reasonable and if funds are available I would be glad if the alterations could be sanctioned,but I particularly funds are not available I would like the work sanctioned to proceed so that the gresent Post Office may be avail' It will be noted taut it is possible to meet in short the requests of the Post Master arev l&gt;o* ISl of* TGhrain dated 10th July 1951, ' 1 ) {pi sd % S' ■ i 10 The Asaiotsbt ingineep. Independent Persian ulf Gub Division, Bushire* Mr, Jubject- Proposed further additions and altera tion to prison cells, which are to be converted into Post Office at Bahrain. I beg to submit the attached rough sketch of the proposed lost office at Babraih, as per suggestion of the Post master, for your infomation. The proposed alterations are quite necess ry,even from the Tsgin eering, and Hygienic points of view, and the lost master complaints that the plan was not prepared according to his wishes. Since the proposed alterations are.essential,I beg to submit a copy of supplimentary estimate for the proposed further additions ajO alterations to the building, in case the wishes of the Post master t are to be carried out, and has proper support of high officials. As we build once,let it be 1?,sting one,so in the intrest of ti^ art, I beg to request that though not all the proposed items ,but t4 i at of providing roc roofing to roof may atleast be provided and san , tioned, so that there may not be room for complaint, when it rains and spoils valuable articles, and .cord, pecially hhrain ro fs lc and reqires some thing to prevent it* I beg to rena in, Mr, Your most obedient serv;jat. Supervisor.No: Jfjfr. Political Agency, Bahrain,the 13th July 1931• From:- The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Assistant Engineer,P.W•D*, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to refer to letter No:125 dated 10th ^uly 1931 addressed to you by your Supervisor at Bahrain And to say that I approve of the suggestions contained therein subject to the work of altering the building and its conversion into a Post Office not being unduly delayed. You will notice that the proposed site for a parcel room is that which I originally suggested but which you considered as being somewhat exposed from the point of view of safety. I do not think any real danger need be apprehended on this score and I suggest that it should be constructed as requested by the Post Master. I have the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant, P .tical Agent,BahrainTELEGRAM CODE. From No. nil To Asstender, Bushire Political, Bahrain Dated and received 23rd July 1931. Your despatch dated 11th July 831 and your despatch dated 13th July 841 Expanded Metal already shipped regret too late alter parcel room Resident being approached for raising wall kindly furnish Supervisor copy of this. No. of 1931. Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 25th July 1931. Copy forwarded to the Supervisor, Public Works Department, Bahrain, for information. For Political Agonx, uanrain .-1WCJopy of oodecl telegram dated the 23rd July 1931, from the Assistant .sngineer, independent Persian Gulf 3uh jJivision, jbushire, to the Political Agent, Bahrein* T3A1ISLATI ON:' “Your despatah No. dated July 11th 331 and your despa tch no. dated July 13th 341 expanded metal already shipped for raising wall kindly furnish Supervisor a oopy of this.* dopy forwarded, with compliments, to the Political- Agent, Bahrein, in confirmation. Owing to the urgency of the work, a telegraphic order was placed with the firm for the supply of materials, which having been already shipped, it is impossible now to make any * alteration in respect of the Parcel Boom. As regards the other suggestions, it is hoped that extra openings in the mud wall oan he made out of savings and that further funds are only needed for raising the walls and providing extra clere-storey windows, for v/hich the Hon‘hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, is being approach ed. Meanwhile the work will be pushed on as originally proposed. regret too late to alter parcel room president being approacea ginde pendent Assistant ifingineer, Persian Gulf Sub Division.T2L3GRAM Prom To I.W.GODE. Asstenger, Bushire. Abdul Yfahab Supervisor, Bahrain. Dated and received 29th July 1931. r Second supplementary estimate raising wall clear away story window sanction will be conveyed by wire. Dismantle mid wall raise 3 pillars each two feet by two feet stones and gutch. i Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for infonnation. Supe rvis or, P.W.D., Bahrain. .1X X X V 4. If the new post office is finished the Post Faster should irove into it as quickly as possible so that his part may be done up for the clerks to move into. Please have the question of wiling the nev/ rost office taken up. T f nothing has been done inform the Assistant Engineer. It is the P.W.D pigeon to fight these things out. x X X y H.C. For necessary action. 19/10/31 1 ^ — -|&gt;A o ^ e ^ ^ ^ . ^ t€jL_ #.. , ^ V.JThe Political A^ent, Bahrain. . ?-//&gt;*&gt;/ I &gt; Subject Completion Certificate of Repairs I beg to submit the attached Completion Certificate of Iiepr.irs for favour of disposal. I beg to remain, Ac comp 1 .H 3ir Your most obedient servant, Cupervisor• 1No. //4^ . Doll ti cal ligency, Bahrain, the 22nd October 1931. u ■to* If To The Sub Postmaster, Bahrain . Memorandum . Please note that I shall be resumiag the rooms now used as a Post Office with effect from the 1st November 1931 and would be glad if you would vacate them by that date. The new Post Office has been completed and is at your disposal. If you wish it to be wired you will no doubt infqjyn the Public Works Department and in the mean time the^lamps formerly used will be sufficient for the illumination. Political Agent, Bahrain. A* J. [ HP IIIH* B* M . Political Agent. Bahrain. BAHRAIN. NOV • 7th f *A'io.,..W3? - /g/&lt;&lt; HSIA! .Dear Sir, _ With reference to your letterNo 12id0 of even date in connection with the wiring of the new Post Office in BAHRAIN, we have pleasure in quoting as follows; To supplying and fixing 4 new light points. To wiring for two new ceiling fans and switches and fixing fans supplied. Rs. jo • 0 • 0 Rs • 44 .u .. u Total U* t, fi. JL iL (Rupees One Hundred &amp; Twenty Two Only) State Government of BahrainP.O.No. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 12th NoTember 1931* Dear iiteele la it poeeible to irake &amp; temporary connection from the guard room light by taking flex through the window eo ae to give the Poet Master one temporary light «t least. W.B.Steele, Esquire State Engineer, Yours sincerely, Bahrain Government, BAHRAINBahrain* If or* 12 th* 1931 • /§£&gt; T hajiic you for your D* 0* of tc^-day re tensor ary connection from the guard room at the Agency to the new post office 1 have arranged to fix two temporary lights in the post office, one outside where the sorting is done % and one inside* the leads to oome from the guard room* I would have done this to — day* hut have had an'unforeseen occurrence' on the hew Sea Hoad* It will he done to - morrow morning* Bahrain.No./3/Y Political iigoncy, Bahrain. Dated the 28th November, 1931. From The Political -agent, Bahrain To The Director of roots e. Telegraphs, 8ind and Baluchistan Circle, Karachi. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that I have resumed the rooms hired to'your department by the Public Torks and that the Post Office is now installed in the building specially constructed for it. 2 . It has not been found possible,however,to transfer any portion of the electrical collection fixed there by you.except the fans’ and switch boxes. The Bahrain Crovenu-ent estimate for wiring the new Post Office (utilising the fans vve have given up) is 3s.122/-. I am giving the estimate to llie Post faster,together with a copy of this letter,for such action as he nay care to take* The remainder of the wiring installed by you is of little value,but any correspondence regarding it may be referred to the Public forks Department at Bushire,by whom the rooms were leased to you. I have the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant Political Agent,.BahrainHo. /3/y of 1931. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 29th Noyember 1931. Copy together with a copy of the estimate, forwarded to the Poet Master, Bahrain, for information and snoh action as may be necessary. Political Agent, Bahrain.of 1932, 115 . I/ Cit/ ■Bushire, dated £% -1-1932. From The Assistant Ung ineer, Independent Persian G-ulf Sub Division, 3 A H H U I : T . + . . ■ -» -»\^ ' DU3JECJT:- Eleotrioal installations in the old Post Office Building, Bahrein. lith reference to your letter Ho. 1314 dated the iiSta NovetiDer ±931, to the Director of Hosts and Tele graphs , Karachi, I have the honour to request you to intimate me the date on which the Post Office 3 Bahr was actually installed in the Agency old cells converted for use as a Post Office. This information is required for the. assessment of rent to he recovered from the Postal Department. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, / An si s •Dant Dn L ineer,political Agency, J3a&gt;- rain, the 7th J^ne 1932# To 'The Postmaster, i5ah rain. Memorandum . 1 forward, herewith, a Dill Ko.±)I/l21 dated the 5th June 1932 for R3.3/» received from the state .engineer, .Bahrain tiovernment, .Bahrain, for direct payment# A« J •Corr.-40. hit- Indian Posts and Telegraphs Department. yo. DK .3 Fiiom: The Superintandent of Post offices, Lower Sind and P.G* Division. S'? Number of enclosures To The political Agent, Bahrain. Dated Karachi r j-* , ine 15.6. 193 6 Subjects- Repairs to Bahrain Post Office building. Sir, I h^ve the honour to say that the Inspector of Post offices Hyderabad Sind Sub Division while inspecting the office has observed that two additional shelves are quite necessary to be fixed in the wall inside the iron cage for the storage of parcels. As the building belongs to your department I requesl you kindly to arrange fixing of the reg^steretl shelvesaax ^ as early as convenient . The favour of an early reply is requested. I have etc, Jisil ■ £ - Supe rintendent. Tf.c?iir?AK—* INo•1759-18/4. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 4th July 1936. To Captain T# Hickinbotham, I.A. f Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain. The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Karachi. iknairs .to...the Post Office at Balirain. /P .DK 3 dati With reference to your letter No.BK 3 dated the 15th June 1936, I have the honour to inform you that since the Public Woifis Department are in sole chaige of the Agency building, there appears to be no reason why you should not refer the matter to the Assistant Angineer, Independent Persian Gulf Division, British Consulate- General, Bushire, to whom I am sending a copy of this correspondence for his information. I have the honour to be, Sir, lour most obedient servant, X) v/ Captain, Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain.The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to;— i’he Assistant ikgineer, Independent Persian Gulf Division, British Consulate -General, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). for information. s The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 4th, .July. .1936. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. f n, \ Name and Date. Subject. 11 1 . Letter No.DK.3 dated the 15t*h June i 93 ? tiie Superintendent of Post Ofiices, Lower Sind and P.G. Division, Karachi. 2* Letter No.l759-18/4'lated the 4th July 1936 19 the Superintend- ^ 9^ ces j. Lower Sind and r.tx. Division, Karachi. Bepairs to the Post Office at Bahrain.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000170_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1633</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000170</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1633</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 18/4 Correspondence regarding conversion of the two old cells into Post Office and repairs thereto'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-12T22:30:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (62 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. File Notes appear on ff 62-63.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this file commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 64. These numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present between ff 3-61. This sequence runs from 1-49 and 71-79. These numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between the Political Agent, Bahrain, the Post Master General, Karachi and the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, regarding the move of the Post Office from inside the Bahrain Agency building to two rooms adjoining the guard room. Most of the file contains requests for estimates from the Political Agent to the Public Works Department, the requested estimates, and discussion between the Political Agent, the Supervisor, Public Works Department, Bahrain, the Assistant Engineer, Public Works Department, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division and the Sub-Post Master, Bahrain regarding suggestions from the Sub-Post Master for the new Post Office.Folios 17 and 39 contain plans of the proposed new Post Office.The file also discusses the question of whether rent is payable by the Post Office to the Public Works Department and the wiring of the new Post Office with electricity. Later correspondence in the file relates to repairs to the roof and the installation of new shelves.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000170#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>