<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000037_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:07:15.533Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">✓ &amp;Repeated Saving to:- Brussels No 0 286, Budapest No 0 95, Oslo No* 59, Belgrade No, 167, Angora No 0 10 4, Madrid No 0 239, Prague Nor 100, Sofia No, 171, Rome NOo 550, Manila No 0 17. Washington No.^ 1447, Moscow No 0 470, Berne No 0 503, Helsingfors No* 38, Copenhagen No* 98, Athens No, 254, The Hague No* 186, Bucharest No* 147, Cairo Nc 0 24-1, Stockholm No* 111, Lisbon No, 174, Tangier No* 51, Warsaw No, 178, Canton No* 1, Shanghai No 0 2, feint Bin No, 1, Strasbourg No, 23, Mr 0 G-oodden, c/o, G« 5* Division, Displaced Persons, FIAT Main, B.A*0.R. No* 41, ' ' Office of Political Adviser to Commander-in- Ohief, Germany, Lubbecke, No. 326, , Mr* Williams, c/o ACABRIT, Vienna No. 50. $ $ # &gt;!i The following is a revised list of consular posts now open in liberated territories. Belgium Brussels Consular Section Antwerp Consulate-General Ghent Vice-Consulate Bulgaria Sof ia Consular Section Czechoslovakia D enmark Finland Prague Cotisular Section Karlovy Vary Consulate (Pilsen (Consulate) has been closed) Copenhagen Consular Section Helsingfors Consular Section /Francev France Paris Lyons Marseilles Nice Strasbourg Bordeaux Lille Rouen Toulouse Consular Section Consulate-General do«, do 0 do 3 Consulate Consulate Consulate Vice-Consulate Greece Athens Salonica Patras Pireaus Corfu Canea (Crete) Fiorina Kalamata Kavalla Samos Volo • Consular-Section Consulate-General Consulate do, ' do„ Vice-Consulate do, do* do © do, do 0 Hungary Budapest Consular Section Italy Rome Florence Genoa Milan Naples Bari Palermo Taranto Trieste Consular Section Consulate' Consulat e-General do, do. Consulate Consulate V ice-Consulate (Representative of British (Political Adviser to (S.A.C.M.E.D, The Netherlands Amsterdam Rotterdam C onsula t e-Ganera1 do. Norway Oslo Bergen Stavanger Consular Section Consulate Vice-Consulate Poland Warsaw Katowice Danzig Consular Section Consulate' Consulate-General ^vj mania Bucharest Consular Section Yugoslavia Belgrade Zagreb L jubl^na Skoplje Split Consular Section Consulate-General Consulate —^ ^aSu late do. 2. Austria (All zones) Foreign Office Re- present at iVv^, c/o ACABRIT, VIENTTA, /Germany&lt;5^ OUTWARD TELEGRAM FILE COPY ? (TH. an? IT K. 11457/^10/250. [EN CLAIR] CU.fi. ^ ^ .-^y Mr- is » »- / -&lt;. * 5 c il ,,J js ?9k!j£cM&gt;S- I 945 W *' •'—;: - ——^ DEPARTtiiEMTAL Mo.l . . • 4 ‘ 4:j * a - FROM F0R3I&amp;N OFFICE TO PARIS \c 1 » W^^oiaiS^ 51 '' W ‘ No&gt; 1845 Saving 4th August, 1945 ^ Repeated Saving to: Brussels No. 164 Sofia No. 60 Budapest No. 38 Rome No. 318 Oslo No. 24 Manila No. 10. Belgrade No.- 75 Washington No. 731 Istanbul (Constantin- Moscow No.. 193 ople) No. 16 (Angora) Berne No.- 393 Madrid No. 119 Helsingfors No.. 21 Prague No. 37 Copenhagen No. 43 Athens No. 130 Sir W. Bland No.69 Bucharest No. 61 Cairo No. 147 Stockholm No. 71 Lisbon Mo. 101 Tangier No. 21 Yfarsaw No. 7. o &amp; &amp; &amp; My telegram No. 1532 Saving of 27th June. Following for Tottenham Smith from Consular Department The following further posts have now been opened:- Greete. Italy The Netherlands Norway. Poland Yugoslavia Canea (Crete) Milan Tte»iteae Amsterdam Bergen Warsaw Vice-Consulate Consulate-General Consular -Sec t ion Consulate-General Consulate Con s ulafcse c tion Zagreb Skoplje Ljubljana Split 2. ’’Mitylene - Vice-Consulate :l should be deleted from my telegram under reference. Consulate-General Consulate Vice-Consulate. Vice-Consulate. EftOLOftURC IN Am MAIL LETTER No. 3 3 18 AUG .d4t&gt; FROM SECRETARY, EXTERNAL DEFT,, INDIA OFFICE RECo. PQL -3 AUG 1945 INDIA OFFICr H KH OUTWARD TELEGRAM Ur ML&gt;*y y 3&lt;4Vck JLol W “, With th« Compliment* of the &amp; ^rfitzry of StaiM H' K. 11457/810/250.. [EN CLAIR] FILES FROM FOREIGN OFIICE TO RiiRIS No* 1,879. SAVING. 10th August, 1945. Repeated Saving to: Brussels Budapest Oslo Belgrade Istanbul (Constantinople) Madrid Prague Sofia Rome Manila Washington Moscow Berne Helsingfors Copenhagen Athens Six N« Bland / Bucharest Cairo Stockholm Lisbon Tangier Warsaw No. 167 No. 59 No. 25 No. 77 No. 21 No. 121 No. 39 No. 61 No. 327 No. 12 No. 749 No. 204 Nc. 400 No* 22 No. 46 No. 133 No. 72 No. 63 No. 150 No. 72 No. 103 No. 24 No. 16 @@@ My telegram No. J^845 j&amp;viru of the 4th August^ Following for Tottenham Smith from Consular Department. Under 'The Netherlands' delete 'The Hague: Consular Section.' ENOLOaURE IN AIR MAIL LETTER No. 3 H 18 AOb »d 4 b FROM SECRETARY, EXTERNAL DEPT,, INDIA OFFICE IToulouse Lille Greece Athens Corfu Fiorina Kalamata Kavalla Mitylene Patras Piraeus Samos Zante Salonica Volo Hungary Budapest Italy Rome Naples Bari Taranto Palermo Genoa Florence The Netherlands Rotterdam Norway Oslo Philippine Islands Manila Roumania Bucharest Yugoslavia Belgrade 2 # We will let you know i posts that may be opened. Vice Consulate Consulate Consular Section Vice Consulate do. (being opened) Consulate do. Vice Consulate do. Vice Consulate Consulate do. Vice Consulate do. Consul ate-G-ener al Vice Consulate« Consular Section Consular Section Consulate General Consulate Vice Consulate Consulate Consulate G-eneral Consulate* Consulate G-eneral Consular Section Consulate-General Consular Section Consular Section, due course of any other - - 1 ■ — 1 ENCLOSURE IN Am MAIL LETTER No. 3 3 18 auu (:d 4 b FROM SECRETARY, EXTERNAL DEPT,/ INDIA OFFICE |\ &gt; His Majesty’s High Commission at Rome (Consular section) ^ + His Majesty’s Consulate-General at Naples. His Majesty’s Vice-Consulate at Bari. His Majesty’s Vice-Consulate at Taranto. His Majesty’s Vice-Consulate at Augusta. The post at Augusta is shortly to be closed. Posts at Palermo and Florence will soon be opened. France. ♦His Majesty’s ♦ His Majesty* s ♦ His Majesty’s ♦ His Majesty * s ♦ His Majesty* s ♦ His Majesty’s His Majesty* s Embassy at Paris (Consular Section). Consulate-General at Marseilles. Consulate-General at Lyons. Consulate-General at Nice. • Consulate at Bordeaux. Consulate at Rouen. Vice-Consulate at iiendaye. Belgium . ♦ His Majesty’s Embassy at Brussels (Consular Section). ♦ His Majesty’s Consulate-General at Antwerp. Greece . ♦ His Majesty * s ♦ His Majesty* s Embassy at Athen Consulate-Gencr n/( a! a (Consular Section), at Salonika. Roumania. ♦ British political Mission at Bucharest (Consular Section] Bulgaria . ♦ British Political Mission at Sofia (Consular Section). Finland . ^ 11 ♦ British political Mission at Helsingfors (Consular Section).OUTWARD TELEGRAM K15#59/8973/217 [m CLAIR] ~$c c o. ^ w * L ‘- } y or oi MriSLii^s \ v%-w PROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO PARI Xjsv _ Ne. 445 SAVING ■■■5129 9th NovemT)**, L944» Ropoated to Marseilles No* 18 Saving Berner No, 1C1 Saving T944 -j 6SSSS Your telegram No,_S 6 C_[of November J5rd: reopening of consular postal Mr, R* Parr is being appointed His Majesty’s Consul- General at Lyons, which is being upgraded, and I shall be glad if you will approach the French authorities accordingly, 2* Mr« Parr will spend a few days in Paris on his way to pick up information and any papers. He hopes to leave here in about 10 days time, 3. Please take steps to inform SHABF and. as usual, to secure such facilities as may be needed in tne way of accommodation, rations and transport (with petrol and oil) for Mr* P* and his staff.FROM PARIS TO FQREIG-Ii Ivlr. Duff Cooper No. 360 3rd November, 1944 D. 7.18 p.m. GMT 3rd November, 19U A. 9.40 p.m. BSf 3rd November, 1344 ddddddd fjo l/afy? You r telegram No T 258. ^ince my te legram No. 26 S aving was drafted, varxOUo ^ new factors have __ come to ligHt. 1. Havre has been visited - please see my despatch No. t12, 19th October. 2. Havre and Rouen are within easier reach of Paris than Lyons. Both posts moreover are within Swiss relief organisation as administered from Paris, Therefore, with Mr. Niell at Rouen, these districts could be run from Pans for the present. k/o Ja*cjz No. As to Lyons, 234 Saving. you should have seen by now my telegram In any case Mr. Hutcheon has left today for Lille, Rouen and Havre. He returns Sunday evening, in the meantime it is proposed to retain Mr. Routh here, ■ENCLOSURE IN Am MAIL LETTER No. 12 2 JtL .1 FROM SECRETARY, i TERNAL DEPT,, INDIA OFFICEOUTWARD TELEGRAM 'PY ife: /. a With the Comp! K.12494/8973/217. '■■■. —^ Under Secretary of Stal? ;idn 'Affai* s» P for Forei “L —W — V* U .[EH CLAIRJ oTZ. _ FROM FOREIGH OFFICE TO MARSEILLES '&gt; 0 * s 9 Laving . Repeated Saving en clair to Paris Mo. 368. Berne No. 71. Resmed No. 86. 9 9 9 9 v' r~ D 0 N&lt;j M profit 3lst 0cto1}ei t ti.944. 3 -&amp; \ IMPORTANT Your despatch of October 7th. I certainly agree that you should reopen His Majesty s Consulate-General on November 1st and that you should then take over from the Swiss Consul his charge of British interes., except in respect of payments to British subjects. I should, of course, like you to take over the payments too hut you should not do so unless you are satisfied that your stall is adequate and that you are in a position to do so without risk of confusion. If you are not able to take over the payments you should let me knov/ at the earliest possible moment what your requirements are.OUTWARD TELEGRAM 1 v-o, ' K.'^ /9033/217. /~x [bn am] FROM TOREIGN OFFICE TO PARIS No. 328. SAVING. 26th Oototer 1944. 0 : 0 : 0:0 Your telegram No. 236 of October 18th:. opening of Consulates. Mr. Roath is now under instructions to proceed immediately to Paris en route for Havre. Please approach the French authorities accordingly. 2. Mr. Tottenham-Smith will no doubt hand oyer to Mr. Routhon his wav through Paris any enquiries relating to the Havre are . 5 . I propose also two weeks to assist Please mention this to send Mr. Ledger to Havre shortly for about Mr. Routh in reopening the post there, also to the French authorities.VC vvevy tn ')V -Cl O ojCTsafc. CO» •V^voy- ujr ir^T^u - ) 'PA. C“). 0 . [EN CLAIR] DEPARTOMTAL NO. 2 U.C* 5 .\a-&lt;h. erp FROM PARIS TO FOREIGN OFFICE IViX ft U U.X X No, 104 SAVING 1st October 1944 Mr. Duff Cooper per D. By Bag 1st October 1944 R. 8.55 p.m. 2nd October 1944 * O» z-z-z-z-z Your telegram iia.-12 B-Savin g. I do not see any great advantage in sending an inspector on a tour of provinces at this stage. Further communications are extremely difficult at present. His visit would be more valuable after consular officers have been appointed to the posts where the need is greatest. Mr, Tottenham Smith would however welcome early visit from Inspector to Paris to study local problems here. The sooner he can come the better. 2. Note from the Commissariat for Foreign Affairs at Algiers dated September 11th, copy of which was sent to Mr. Mack, gives approval only to appointments at Paris and Marseilles. It does not appear that any general approval of consular appointments in France has been given. I am asking the Ministry of Foreign Affairs for provisional recognition of Mr. Nairn's appointment to Bordeaux. 5. In the South-West, where there are no British or American forces, S.H.A.E.F. will be unable to assist. I understand however that food is everyv/here plentiful and comparatively inexpensive. As for transport, consular officers will have to make their own arrangements on the spot, appealing to me for assistance if need be. I shall discuss Y/ith Mr. Peake the question of providing facilities for consular officers in places where American or British troops are stationed.\ OUTWARD TELEGRAM K. n /8975/217. [Si CLAIR] \J.O No 4 295 Saving, Co tv^c&gt;‘ 4 / ^ S DEPART!.ISIfrAL No&gt;l^ tlhV* V uU I Q44 FRQ 1 I FOREIGN OFFICE &amp;”TWIS'' 20th October, 1944, • Repeated to Madrid Saving No.172, XXX My telegram No. 1 26 Saving, of September 27th and my telegram J^o.ll85 to Madrid of October 6 th: Consular arrangements in S.W. Prance. I think it will be possible for Mr. Nairn to leave here for Paris, on his way to Bordeaux, within about ten days. It will, hov/ever, necessarily take him some time to settle down and he will not be able at the start to look into the situation of British subjects in his district. I therefore propose at about the same time to send Mr.i 1 inch over to Paris, where lie might nominally be attached to your Consular Section for the purpose of going down to Hendave acquaint himself with the needs or British subjects in S.W. Prance and the arrangements made there and at Toulouse for their assistance. Mr.Finch could. I think, usefully make a tour of the district and report to Mr. Naim and subsequently to you. This should make it easier for Mr. Naim to enter on his duties without undue delay. 2. May I have your views?^9,0. c.o* O' S VN ^ COPY * {K HO12/3973/217) ex, \Or^- -\~c&gt;~QjLXy^s n \ovs9 /s9H3 /in DE PARTMENTS &gt;;r|i th® 0»O V4 4/ of the Imentp— n ’s* 1 Ast) of State/ A-- A S«^H. /v£^3 FROM Fq^EIGN OFFICE TO IvIAimg NO. 1. ' ^ ‘ Nor xl?4 D. 2,05 a 3rd October, 1944. Repeated to Paris No. 174 Saving, Berne No. 18 Saving, \ H'J5 C ?(- V .m. 4th October, 19^ ?=■ —&gt;~' **+**+-*■ -fy &gt;y ^ clai ¥^'^&gt;^' My telegram No f 158 Saving tn 'Pari r British subjects in Toulouse area/. /qjfSSeptember 281 } : CD.O. VD 3° $ His Majesty*s Ambassador at Paris reports that he has received information confirming the urgent need for a ,x / consular officer at Toulouse. He understands that the Swiss have not made any relief payments there for the last two months. He says that it is at the moment impossible for him to detach a member of his consular staff even for a short visit to Toulouse and that he therefore hopes that His Majesty's Consul-General Barcelona will be able to assist. 2. Can you please arrange for Mr. Farquhar to send a member of his staff to Toulouse as soon as possible to assist British subjects and report. The general idea is that relief for British subjects should be continued on the same basis as was used by thd Swiss authorities. If, by reason of changes in the cost of living, this basis is no longer appropri4d*.^fresh_ recommendations , should be submitted supported by such data 'as can te given. 3. Please report action taken. 110 m aCOPY (K 11012/3973/ iil7 ) Clair/ W FROM PARI Mr. ^uff Cooper No. 105 SAVING Ist October 1944 E'.X'i a * :• r ' L NOil. D. By Bag 1st October 1944 R« 8.55 p.m. JcJnd October 1944. z-z-z-z-z . Your telegram No. 158 BavinH. Information which has reached me since the ^ 1 *°' despatch of my telegram 26 bavins confirms the urgent need for a consular officer at Toulouse. I understand that the Swiss have not made any relief pay ments in that area for the last two months. 2. Volume of work here makes it quite impossible to detach a member of my consular section for even a short visit of reconnaissance to Toulouse. I should be grateful if His Majesty’s Consul-General at Barcelona could help. \ r (5. bee also paragraph 3 of my telegram No. 104 Savin,.OUTWARD lELEGRAM' , . X. ^ ^ i ~ - - S&gt; *- K 9885/9053/217 [CODE R] * dc* • DEI ARTIffiMTAL N0.1. tS No. 1183 PROM FOREIGN OPEjlCE TO MADRID. 1 rs 6th October,!944-« Repeated to Barcelona No. 78. Paris No. 195 Saving Marseilles Ko.l Saving Berne No. 19 Saving. D. nv4d p;my-'6tlr' October, 1944. r - £ £ £ £ £ 'TXi* ;ment» _r i’ Under Secretary of Statf^ for Foreign Atrfalre IMP0RTA1TT. v Sic - OcA^Wu^ / c? ^7/1 rr Your telegram No. 108 of September 15th: Consular arrangements in south west France] and your telegram No.1414 [of October 4th]. I am extremely grateful to you for your initiative in making these provisional arrangements which must have saved a good deal of distress among British subjects but I am afraid that it may be some weeks before a consular officer can reach Bordeaux to place the arrangements on a more ^ permanent footing. I shall, indeed, be glad if you will do your best to cast the net a little wider and include # British subjects at, say, Pau. You may perhaps think it feasible to collect a small consular team at Hendaye and to work Toulouse from there rather than by sending up a man from Barcelona (see my telegram No. 1174 L of October 5rd] ). 2. I approve your action about correspondence. 3. I shall telegraph to you later about funds. 4. I have only just seen your telegram No. 1414 and am grateful for the arrangement proposed. I was myself surprised zo hear that there were many British subjects near Toulouse. If in fact there are not this would strengthen the propose! in paragraph 1 above. I suggest that Mr.Nhitfield make a preliminary visit to investigate. taCtOtUHE IN AIR MAIL LETTfcR N o- b 2 1 OCT |S44 FROM SECRETARY, EXTERNAL DEPT., INDIA OFFICE[M CLAIR] FILES Mr. Duff Cooper D. By bag 26th September, 19U- No, 75 SAVING. R. 1.30 p.m. 29th September, 19U-. 26th September, 19LL. [][][] t+Z Q. D My telegram No* Ik Saving and my teleg ram No* 26 Saving*^ If this regular weekly service to Lyonscan be established I think opening of Consular post at Lyons should be given high priority* Has post at Marseilles been opened? j~ enclosure in ajr mail letter No. -5 14 OCT 1344 | SECRETARY, EXTERNAL DEPT., « • INDIA OFFICEOs ^ &lt;0 OUTWARD TELEGRAM LF P' K L0339/8975/2Q [EN CLAIR] DEPARTiilERTAL HO. I. E^nt-i T?nREI(RJ OFFICE TO PARIS ^0*0 . No» 158» Savlnp: &gt; • . 28th September 1944* t-O- Repeated to Madrid No, 1141. ^ ^ rrrrrr for Fo l-ru&amp;Cn B1P0RTANT I have received a report from South-Western France to the effect that there is urgent need for a consular- officer at Toulouse, -to deal with a large number of Brit subjects there, some of whom are destitute. I am told that the Swiss Consular authorities are no longer able to assure relief payments for British subjects in^this region and that the Civil Administration have no authority at present to deal even with the urgent cases. 2 # - Can you take steps to send a number of your Consular Section to Toulouse to render such assistance as may be necessary and report? If communications do not at present permit of this. His Majesty *s Consul-General at Barcelona could be asked whether he can help.- u O.o. io ? 3^ j — — 1 ENCLOSURE IN AIR MAIL LETTER No. -4 ~ * OC l ib FROM SECRETARY, In . J.^AL DEPT., INDIA. OFFICE\# OUTWARD TELEGRAM £ jO W K.9996/8973/217 . \p*1 DEPARIMOTAL NO. 2. FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO PARIS £ / Q j • 1. [EH GLAIR] Hn. 126 SAVING 4mm 1 27 th Lepte^p^i 19Hi&gt; t ^'' 0 0 0 0 ieC' Unde^ Secr^ top Poro ** 1 O&amp;mJLx.A IMPORTAMT -2 Vnnr tp.l ft p^am No. 26 SaYi ng^Q£_^eptembgr_1jJh.re-open mg insular nosts. of consular posts, I am grateful for your recommendations but realise that it will be difficult to assess needs at all closeiy until we can get at the places concerned. Do you think that the time has now come when an inspector might usefully ma e If so I will send one over as soon as possible but shall iirsr be glad to know whether he could get round. 2. Independently of the above I propose now to open Havre and Bordeaux as soon as possible. I have warned Mr. B.J.M. Nairn, at present Acting Consul at Casablanca, for Bordeaux. I assume that, on the basis of my telegram No. 1333 of August 30 th to Algiers the general approval oi m'R'ehchTi^tioriarGOTmittee of Liberation has been given for the re-opening of our pre-war posts but I shall be giaa if you will now obtain provisional recognition for Mr. Nairn appointment. 3 I shall also be glad if you will approach Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force with a view to ^eir granting any facilities that consular officers may need m the way of transport, rations, etc. 1 ? % f ENCLOSU: No. - 4 «E0RET AIR MAH LETTER • BiCs. Pi5- J 2 9 SEt- 'iS''' J | INDIA orF:iOL ? TO FOK^IGN QPFIGB &lt; :it. Duff Cooper D. Untimed. 15th September, 1^44 .o. 2b SAVI R. 2.00 p. a. 16th Septeiaber f *1944 15th September, 1944. Your telegram iio. 34 . ^Apart from Paris and Marseilles I consider that Consular posts should be opened at Le Havre, Bordeaux, Lyons, Nantes, Lille, Rouen, and Strasbourg, in that order. You will realise, of course, that without any contact with any part of France outside Paris, and without first-hand knowledge of actual i^qulrenents of British subjects and interests it is somewhat difficult to make any considered recommendations, but Civil Affairs may be able to provide supplementary information which may lead you to modify order of precedence. I have no included non-career poqts.OUTWARD TELEGRAM, ,/ . . *VJ ^ c o O-r^)' •— — ~C' ■ &gt;• .'■ 4 =TfO» K.9065/«©eS/217 [CYPHER] it. ^ CJ / y^p- 7p~ ItyiU It ! DEPARTS :THEHTAL No.2. FROi^i FOREXG-N OFMGE t 6:M^IERS ((AliBAS SAPOR) No* 1333* Dc 1«00 a.n. August 31st # 1944. August 30th, 1944* Repeated to Resident Minister Central Mediterranean, ^ Caserta No. 569 Lisbon No. H99(for Mr. Tottenham Smith and Mr. Kay) b b b b IMPORTANT Your telegram No. 1519l oiLAugust 25th:_ appointment of consuls in France] and my telegram No. 531 [of August 29th] to Caserta. It is our general intention gradually to establish consular posts in France, as circumstances permit and require, on much the same basis as before the war. Mr. Kay and Mr. Tottenham Smith, who are both at Lisbon, have been warned as Consuls-General designate for Marseilles and Paris and Mr. Franklin and Mr. Tingle, who is now here, as their respective vice-consuls^ Mr. Tingle*s appointment vail be temporary until Mr. Robb arrives. 2. I shall be glad if you will inform the French National Committee of Liberation of the above and ask for their general approval and also for their advance provisional recognition of the four appointments that it is now proposed to make. As the Committee have in the past been rather touchy on these matters, you could, if necessary, add that commissions would be submitted for exequatur in due course* 3. If the Committee’s provisional recognition is granted, I shall instruct the consular officers concerned to proceed to their posts without delay. It is my intention that Mr. Tingle should go direct to Paris to join the diplomatic mission and that Mr. Tottenham Smith should follow on shortly after.[CYPHER] DEPARTMENTAL NO. 2, FRQm aLOIERS (BI8ASSADQR) TO FQFIEIG-N OFFICE. Ivir. Duff Cooper. No. 1519 . 25th August,1944. D. 9.00 p.m. 25th August, 1944. R. 7.55 a.m. 26th August, 1944. 0 zzzzzzz I feel it most important that the Consular Officers should he appointed and sent as soon as practical to Marseilles and Paris as their presence there will he urgently required to deal with current business. O.T.P.D. 5.0* p.m, 29th August 1944* 29 th August 1944* Repeated to Ambalg. No. 1319# IMPORTANT Your telegram unnumbered of August 23rd: [appointment of Consuls in France] I am afraid I could not consider appointing consular officers as such to assist the Civil Affairs Branch. They would be appointed only after the area in question had been declared to be an interior zone and French authorities with whom they could deal had been established* 2* Mr. Kay has already been v/amed for Marseilles and my intention was that he, with a nucleus staff, should be first in the field and should report on consular requirements for the Riviera. I should also if possible arrange for the Inspector-General, to make a tour at a very early stage. 3* I propose to ask the French Committee for National Liberation for their provincial recognition of any intended appointment s. OTP L iv ,• V.:- U 1 9^.4 / ^ i ^ u ^ ccOk ^ 3. ^ ^ 3£f^^44 ».a. o^ -v^fc*-o Zrx^*. fcJ^4. Co. a . ?/. [CYPHER] DEPaRTLIEl-TPAL NO* 2 FROM RESIDMT MINISTER, CMT'TRAL liEDIPERRAIlEm'L. CASERTA TO FOREIGN OFFICE Mr, Macmillan Un umbered 23rd August^ 1944 D. 10.10 p.m. 23rd August, 1944 R. 6.30 p.m. 24th August, 1944 777 Allied Force Headquarters have asked what your intentions are in regard to the appointment of Consular officers in South France. # They say il- would help them very much if Consular Officers could be appointed as soon as possible to such pl a 9^ ?- s Rice Cannes and Marseilles to help Civil^ff^ 1 ^ 3 officers to look after the interests of British subjects.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000037_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/941</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000037</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/941</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 3866/44 'Appointment of British consuls in liberated countries: lists of consular posts'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-03-30T10:14:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (31 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 33; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains papers relating to the appointment of British representatives and consuls at various locations in several countries newly liberated from Germany towards the end of the Second World War. The papers include extensive lists of newly open positions for consular representation across the world. The majority of the papers relate to the reestablishment of British consular representation in liberated France, and especially in regions of the south and south-west. Some papers mention the presence of a large number of destitute British subjects in urgent need of aid.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Consular services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000037#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>