<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00008c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T04:45:33.367Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">J» — •« r-v ' COPY No .169 -28/37. British Consulate General Bushire Eated the 7th February, 1939. “TO To His Majesty’s Consul Shirax. 1 9 c : ■ L ‘ ’•« ^ *• -v MEMC ‘ UNSUM Special Repairs to the Shirax Consulate Building Reference your letter No.34/l0/2/l5 f dated the 14th January, 1939. 2 . It is regretted that it is too late to *ove the ^overmen* of India *o Include &gt;v ie n 3 ces«&gt;? ,,, y provision for special repairs and original works at Shiraz in the budget estimates for 1939-40. estimalds should have been submitted to ♦his office In September last, vide paragraph 4 of this Res^^ncy f s Circular nonornndum No. 330, dated the 23rf February, 1920. By order Sd. R.f • John for Secretary to the Political Resident in the -ereian Gulf. J?'o.95/l0/i/l6. British Consulate, rhlram, 13th February, 1939* Sir, 'ith reference to your Teeretary’s wenorandum No.169 -23/37 of 9*h Febfniftry,19.39, infomlnxt me that it is too late to move *he flovarment of India to make the neeessary provision for *he Special Repairs vhic** -^re required by *he buildings o£ *his Consulate, 1 hare honour to infons you tlwit I realised that the estimates enclosed with my latter No.34/10/2/15 of 14th January,1939, t 'ould have been submitted to you in September 4 .»st. At ♦ha* ♦ ^ however, this Consulate wss in chars® of an acting officer only who himself was a-bsent on special duty at Khorrumshahr and the submission of the estimates was accordingly delayed pending tty arrival. 2. It was m these circumstances that I requested on Januarv 14th that nverv effort should be made to have *h© five i*ams of maintenance included in the Budget for 1939-1940. Anticipating that wi^h your recommendation ^nero would be no difficulty In ‘■'btalning funils for *1—? urgent repairs, I did not see fit to mention than that work on item 1 (re-digging of wells) had already been put f ' hand by my predecessor, Mr.v/atkizison and item • (ceiling of Consul's office) by the acting officer, aJr.Harell. ^e Hon , b!e the Political Hesident a nd Bis Mi testy's Consul Ifcneral Bushire 3'S SB. *1..1,500/ Hln.540/ © .r\ m s J l. .■ t (Q ^ »:*; t -tj/ v/ / 3. As you ’enow, tho wells 'lansts) which are situated in the hills about 10 miles from 1hires are owned as to l/24 port by this Consulate and in order to avoid being deprived of water altogether* Mr* *atkinaon had to make immediate -rrangementa with the holders of tho ronaining 23 share* to dig new wells and clean the whole system. ■^he sum of Rials One thousand and five hundred shown in my estimates represents the proportion of the total outlay due by this Consulate. 4. As regards the celling of my office. Hr* arell found that the framework had been eaten away by white ants and that it was liable to collapse about his ears a* any minute, 'fhe woodwork has now been replaced for a sum of Kinls Five hundred and forty but has not yet been painted. 6* ^he bills for both these items are now due and X should therefore be greatly obliged if you would urgently recommend the Go Vermont of India to sanction this expenditure so that payment may be made without delay. 6. ^le remaining three Items are almost equelly in and need of immidlate attention, ^tie bathroom (item 3)/the stables (item 4) are rapidly becoming insanitary while if repairs to the various mud roofs (item 5) are allowed to slide for another year, a much larger outlay will be necessary to put right the damage caused by rain to the a structures themselves. Already 7 long storeroom in *he down *tkble has t^o large holes In the roof and several breaches1 * 1 * 19c: traachee In the wells and the entire building win hawe to be demolished if ►he necessary funds for Its repair are no* f&lt; ♦tbcoir.ing. I heve honour *o he. Sir, Y our obedient Servant Sd. AeH.King H«M.ConeulRegister No. P. z. 3253/38. Political Department. r\ T ■, Dated DD 1 ' from 193 . J elegram Rec Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To ^haitauan Under Secretary i-(* jM. PERSIAN GULF. SecretarWtaf State... Committee Under ^Secretary Secretary of State... Com lucil T, Box Table \{ jt. Lease of property at Shiraz for use of Political Resident in Persian Gulf. Copy to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Minute . Draft letter to Foreign Office. If- Z^jl i &gt;^3$, Previous Papers 1742a 500 3.33Minute Paper. P.Z. 3253/38. Department. r 2662 iTT V 1938 Please see the minute at P.Z.910/37- The lease of the Bagh-i-Shaikh property has 'been further extended for a period of one year from January 1st 1938 on the same terms as before. It is necessary each year^as the lease is renewed ,to secure the Treasury’s agreement to accept a moiety of the annually roougging expenditure as a charge on Imperial revenues (see Mr. Gibson’s note at P.Z.722/38, flagged B). A draft letter to the Foreign Office is submitted accordingly. Financial Secretary, For any observations. , , &lt;A*/vwim*. ilji - /V* , ' %6837 Wt 34001/249 10,000 1.38 m -- Draft Paper. p . z . 3253/38. POLITICAL Department. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l. Copy to In^£a. ENCLOSURE IN ^ ,r MAlL ' ^3. JUN B38 from secretary, SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFfiC^ \N 0 COPY » TO l^-T 15 VS C. With reference to iForeign Office letter No. K. Ihjl96^7/410/234 of the Uth January 1938, ac mo^ifiod-^y cti~ t&gt; *{* 7Zv» iva«. ^ 12 *. I4^r—P, J»Ui m- Soo-Vb ’ o dt o»—lector Ai' fytvO h. / W CT^&gt; N-^K» 348/3Q6/Q34 of-tho—29th Januai*y&gt; I am directed hy the Secretary of State for India to invite attention to the Government of lndia T s express letter dated 3rd May 1938 (a copy of which v/as sent to the Foreign Office with India Office letter No. P.Z. 3253/38 of the 10th May) from which it will he observed that the lease of the Bagh-i-Shaikh property at Shiraz has been further extended for a period of one year ending 31st December, 1938 on the same terms as before. I am to request that, if the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs sees no objection, the aanotion of the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty*s Treasury may be obtained to tke accept«** 9 « as a charge on Imperial revenues *©£ a moiety of the expenditure involved in respect of rent and other charges for the year 1938 . k. Pttu.[N.B •— This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provide* a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated^ on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate' formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. D.703-V38. Dated Simla rndtimhi r, the 3^ May ^38- To Zenodotia, London. 9-n 1^- nn Renewal of the lease of the 3agh-i-Shaikh property at bhiraz for tne calendar year ending the 31st December 1938. Please refer to India Office express letter No.P.Z. 722/38, dated the 9th February 1938. 2. The lease of the Bagh-i-Shaikh property at bhiraz has been further extended for a period of one year ending the 31st December 1938 on the same terms as before. In the circumstances, it is requestea that the acquiescence of His Majesty's Government may kindly be obtained to share a moiety^ of the annual recurring expenditure as heretofore. The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant oecretary to the Government of India. &amp; (With 2 3cs.) PUt. DC *T. - 9 MAY 1938 INDIA OfTlCE tfitijmtoYe) fi4;P—&lt;M-2042)—17-12-37—20,000.vy4Ut- c&lt;n~-y&lt;L 12APais57 Q7 A sic: f w--v~j ^ 3 } Vrw^ ^Vv&gt; ) W Ft io^ iv-^n r^MilAiJLA^tXA. .'fc . %m+* +*+* ^ A.a/| ' 1+ r i4^ I’rotn - The Under Secretary to the Government of India J in the Foreign and Political Department* 1937 To - The Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum No. F.297-A/36. 9 Dt &amp;.ted New Delhi* the/ March 1937, Special repairs to the Consulate buildings at Shiraar. «•••••• Reference your memorandum No#2023 of 1936* d r ted the 3rd October 1936. 2 . The Government of India are pleased to accord tho-i-. epno-M on to the execution of tho marainall^ noted special repairs at Tl New Hud-plastering the mud-roofs of the down st-ble* servants 1 quarters, etc., Rials. 2,000/- 2. Repairs to the Consulate garden drives (old ^nd broken bricks to be replaced by new bricks),. • • • Rials. 600/- 3. Wooden ceiling pro-Consul’s Office. Rials. 550/- Total Rials. 31607- an estimated cost of Rials 3,150/- or Ks. 520/- approximately. The expenditure involved is divisible in moieties between the Government of India and His H jesty’s G overnment. 3 . A provision of F.s, 500/- has been made in the budget estimates for 1937-38 on this account under »35 External Affairst-G-Works*• ENCLOSURE iN INDIA FOREiG! Lcltap if 6 to. Sd/- G.K.S. Sarma, TTnripr Secrctarv to the Government of Indr■ HI Fro® - The Mdl* Deputy Secretary to the Gtoyeraflent of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To - The Hon’ble the Political Hesidont in the Persian Gulf. yernorandom No,F.255- /34. Dated New Delhi, the ISaroh 1935. repaiys^to the Consulate i. Repairs to main gsste roofing which is sagging with ) phag|:|ng o|^ d^atro^ed b^ams, matting and repairs 2. Hemoyal of the roof of the roo servants quarters wniph are s beams, being, eaten, up by white building with ne new oeams matlSog. ,d outside owing ra te : Reference correspondence ending with your express letter No. 2530/28/37, dated the 14th November 1934, 2. The Government of India are pleased to accord sanction to the special repairs to the Shiraz Consulate buildings as mentioned in the margin, at a total estimated cost of Ra, 900(rupees nine hundred). This amount has been provided in the budget for 1935-36, The expenditure is divisible in moieties between the Government of India and Hia Lajeaty’s Government, 3. It has net been possible to secure any budgt provision for the other two items detailed in the statement attached to your express letter under reply. 3d/-7, Narahari Rao, Addl, Deputy Secretary to the Govemii|nt.offay i 686? Cojj/ of memorandum 1 n€&gt;. 2240/28/37.‘ r , dated Bushire, the ( i^o4 J 6 th October 1934, from the Hon’bie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Foreign Secretary to the it Government of India, New Delhi. Special repairs ana additions ana alterations to the Consulate buildings at Shiraz. I forward herewith a statement together with an explanatory note giving aetaila of special repairs to the Consulate buildings at Shiraz which His Majesty’s Consul, Shiraz, proposes to carry out during the year 1935-36. 2. In the circumstances explained in the note referred to above I request that the Government of Inaia will be pleased to sanction the expenditure of Rs. 1500/- (approximately equivalent to Rials 9100 at the present rate of exchange viz 595/2) during the year 19 35-36. 3. When the Hon’ble Lieut. Colonel Fowle visited Shiraz in April last he lound that the guest house attached to the Consulate was without a kitchen. As a kitchen is essential for the use of the Resident and his staff Jtixujag during their periodical tours to Shiraz I recommend that sanction may kindly be accorded for building a kitchen at a cost of Rs. 3000/-. This amount was estimated by my Assistant Engineer who inspected the ohiras Consulate buildings in i^ay last. 4. Necessary provision is being made for a sum of Rs. 4500/- in the budget estimates for the ensuing financial year, now under preparation.Extract from a letter Iso. 533/13-S. , dated the 10th September, 1934, from His Majesty’s Consul Shiraz, to the Hon* ole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. X X X X XX Item Ho. 1. Additions and alterations, with iron roofing, for the separate house kitchen wing, “Sherbetlhanah' and store room. Reparis to the roofs of this building were effected out of the maintenance grant for the current year, but it is not expected that they will afford protection from leakage for more than one year and the provision of iron roofing at the cost of Rials 3500 is highly desirable. Item No. 2. The top of the main entrance gate has sagged out of all proportion during the summer and a thorough overhaul is urgently required with repairs to the brick staircase leading to the top, which is now almost unsafe. Item Ho. 3. The roofing of the former sowars’ quarters, now occupied by the outdoor servants, has souftk sunk dangerously mostly throughout the building mainly owing to damage from white ant ana a complete overhaul is urgent. Item Ho.4. The main walls of the property are cracked and damaged in parts and I anticipate further damage to these and other places after the winter rains. The estimate of Rials 1000 has been made to enable me to effect these repairs, for which half the wall area has been provided for. X XXX / —nJnc losure No. 2 Shira^ Consulate Budget Estimate for the fear 1935-19 36. X ii REP alls 1 . Additions &amp; alterations to LLain-house kitchen and 2 embar rooms attached and iron roofing the same 56 x 20 ft e q 1120 ft. 2. Repairs to Main Gate roofing which is sagging with changing of destroyed beams, matting and repairs to brick stair case. 3. Removal of the roof of the rooms in the outsiae servants quarters which ere sinking in owing to beams being eaten away by white ants and re-building with new beams and matt 4. Mud plastering and repairing ox part of the walls round the Consulate garden ana replacing^- the rotten poles of the barbed Wi protection. Total Rials Nine thousand and one hundred only. Total Rials. 9100 3d/- H.A.D. Hoy land. H.B.M. Consul, Shiraz,GOVEREMTftTT OF IHDlA. Foreign tiiid Foil tic ril Department l r-ZPRiias LiT’-R. From Fo x e i v n» lle'vi Delhi. To Britconsul, Bush ire. No. i.255-//34. Dated October jls» . special repairs and additions and alterations to the Consulate buildin f s nt rihir^. Reference /our meftortuaduoi Ho. 2^40/^8/37» dated the 6th October 1*34. Please furnish \ er/ ur^entl/ the allocation of cost between ’original work* ana Repairs* to enable the Government of India to decide If any portion of the expenditure ch^rgeauie to His llajesty** Government. The issue 01 the above has been authorised. 3d/- S.C. Blow as, '\ 83 ietnnt Secretary to the Gov&lt; rnment of Inaia.INDEXED r FILE COP^^.^ “7 o O p X J J V ; J^rorn - the Addl, Deputy Stcretajry to the-(forgramen t of Xr*dia in the Foreign and ^ollUo^l D«vArtwenty To • The Hon’ble the Political lUieident in the Persian Julf, Ek Memorandum Ho. 1*. 288 -a/33. s~ Dated Hew Delhi, ^ie 2^^ A April 1934. V f 3/; f-* 3 3 t Electric installation in the Shiraz Consulate buildings. Heferenoe correspondence ending with your memorandurc Ho. 576/28/37, dated the 5th March 1934. 2. the OoTemaaent of India are pleased to accord sanction to the electric installation in the Shiraz Consulate buildings at an estimated cost of Rs. 1200/- (Rupees one thousand two hundred only), provision on this account has been included in the budget for 1934-35. The entire expenditure will be chargeable to Indian Revenues. 3. It is presumed that the cost of current consumed in the private, as distinct from the public rooms of the Consulate will be paid by the Consul. , 252 ' \934 -/f - IP- ir^VUMA^l Sd/- • ?v\ i v J W./1 for Addl. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. 8 193A ** '#*• “ iM- :/v I ENGLGSUKE IN INDIA rOBElQA StCriO | 6:4) . ^ 26 ^\PR 1934 ; i 4 ’AY.-1834/ ?rom - The Addl. Deputy Secretary to r the- ilov ernaen t of India * -v, • &lt;vJ- J- in the fforei^n and Political Department, To - The Hon*1)16 the Political Resident in the X i ZeraUtfi Gulf. \ . X. Memorandum Ho.,?.288-a/33. Sated New Selhl, the Beoeratoer 1933. y Electric installation in the Shiraz Consulate buildings. Reference your letter No. 2078 dated the 7th October 1933. 2. A copy of a note recorded by the Chief Engineer, Central Public Works Department, after a scrutiny of the estimate sent with your letter is enclosed. Before the proposal can be sanctioned, the Government of India would be glad to be furnished with the plans referred to in the Chief Engineers note along with the information in regard to the system of wiring that is proposed to be put in. 3. Steps are being taken to secure the necessary provision in the budget for 1934-35, but it is however requested that without the final approval of the Government of India to the work, no expenditure should be incurred thereon. Sd/- V.Narahari Rao. Addl. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. ,, v V '~Copy of a note dated the 25th Hovemher x933» recorded by the Chief Engineer, Central public Works Department. 1 return the proposals with the following remarkss- (l) It is not possible to check the quantities provided in the estimate in the absence of plans, (ii) It is not clear what system of wiring it is proposed. It would appear that it is C.T.S. (iii) The rates appear to be reasonable# but the lamps proposed are unsuitable. The bulbs should be atI, ML vWPX * Copy or letter No. 2078 of 1935, dated Bus hire, the 7th October 1933, droiL the Hon*ole the Political ,v Besident in the Persian Gulf, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Poii/ticai Department, New Delhi. n i'h i e r* T ; ~ Consulate Buildings. I have the honour to enclose a copy of an estimate * f/fi. ' P* Subjects-Electric Installation in the ahiraz ■^/j -Orl Ji ULC m^' x - ^ amounting to Rials 7,008-00 (equivalent tote. 1,200 at the current rate of exchange at Rials 584 £) which has *1 ^ 136011 °' bt ' ained fronl the ShiraZ Electric Supply Corpora- tion by His Majesty f s Consul, Shiraz, who proposes that 1 ^electricity shall be installed in the Consulate Build ings at Shiraz. 2. The proposal was first put forward by His » / ■ j Majesty*s Consul, Shiraz, in the year 1931, but was 7 ! 12 i 1933. V, -^m****** ^cxxirdjt; Q HN? 13480 !93 TrS L .. V not then submitted to Government for sanction in view of the financial situation and the imperative necessity, at the time, for abstaining from all financial commit ments except such as were of vital importance, while the provision of electricity is not perhaps a matter of vital importance, it must, in modern times, be regarded as a necessity and should not be postponed indefinitely, I have had the opportunity of seeing the present incumbent of the post and members of my staff know the Consulate, and I am satisfied from what they tell me that the installation should be provided. The cleanliness and convenience of electri city in a^ house and in an oifice, and the comfort it provides, especially in the hot v.eather, is clear, ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECP rr ^ Letter No S62 Date. 2 3 'T. 1933 ! Reopi MOVJ iS33 and/and I think that, when an electric supply is avail able, it is only reasonable Tor it to be installed in all good class houses. Apart, however, from these considerations there is in Shiraz, another aspect of the case which is important. The local inhabitants, and in particular the Persian visitors, remark on the absence of electric lights in the British Consulate; and their remarks are the more pointed as the electric generating plant is British and it is, therefore, regarded as curious that we do not support the corpora tion. The advantages to be derived from the point of view of efficiency, comfort and prestige seem amply to justify the small expenditure involved. 5. I therefore support the proposal of his Majesty's Consul, ^hiraz, and request that sanction may be accorded to the expenditure of a sum of Rials 7,008-00 (equivalent to 8s. 1,200 at the current rate of exchange at Rials 584^) and the inclusion of the necessary provision in the Budget estimates for the ensuing year.tlilS * A Statement I, Wiring and Fittings. Goods. Bef. Quantity. Price Fo • No. Rials. i. C.T.S.Cat)le double cored 241 300 m. 1,290-00 2. 0. T. S.Gal)le triple cored 240 100 m. 390-00 3. Black V.i.R.Wire 2£ mm 47 200 m. 300-00 4. Twin V.I.R.Tire 48 100 m. 180-00 5. Cl ips 219 2000 500-00 6. Black ceiling rose 36 11 176-00 7. Balancing weight 82 4 120-0 0 8. Cut-C ut 392 20 100-00 9. Switch 60 32 448-00 10. Wooden 'blocks, screws, nails etc., and the cost of wiring outside lines, approximately 1,256-10 Total Rials. 4,760-10 nr jjiuu mwStatement III. Pig tri'b uj^ Ioil. Offic e. Consul's Room. Pro-Consul's Room. Kunshi's Room. Verandah. House. Verandah. Bedroom I Bathroom I. Bedroom II and Bathroom II. Bedroom III and Bathroom III. Dining Room. Front Drawing Room. Back Drawing Room. Front study room. Back study room. Bath room. Back verandah. Pantry (2) Ki tchen. Guest Rooms (2) Bathrooms attached (2) Fain Gate entrance. 1 centre light. 1 table lamp. 1 plug. 1 centre light. 1 centre light. 1 outside light. 1 outside light at near end. 1 light centre (to he inserted in existing light.) 1 light over mantel skgj she If (swatch at door) 1 reading lamp. 1 plug. 1 light over door. As for Bedroom I and Bathroom As for Bedroom 1 and Bathroom 6 wall lights and 4 switches 2 wall lights (on each side of mantel shelf.] 1 reading lamp. 1 plug. 1 centre bracket, 3 lights. 1 plug beside piano. 4 switches at door controlling both drawing rooms. 1 centre light. 1 centre light. 1 light. 1 outside wall light. 2 centre lights. 1 centre light and i move ab le light. 2 centre lights. 2 wall lights. 1 light.F!LE COP' f o. From- The Hon’ble the Political Resident . in the Persian Gulf. - To - The Secretary to the Government of c India in the atm 'wrJr} ■ Foreign and Political Ber&gt;£-rtment. ITew Be 1 hL . Memorandum No.2073 of 1933. Bated Bushire, the 4th October 1933. Subject:- Special reparis and additions and alterations to the Consulate buildings at Bh ir az . , ll : h ^ aJrUy*^ I 7 I/I . ^ repairs and additions and alterations to the Consulate C 1 , buildings at Shiraz, which His Majesty’s Consul, Shiraz, proposes to carry out during the year 1934-35* J3 (3) Reference correspondence ending with Memorandum from jyi^^this ■Residency No. 1028, dated the 20th May 1933. (£} a statement is submitted giving details of the special r /”/ PN l r 77 ENCLOSURE INmuch I INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S | Letter No BB 2 | Da e / &gt; T. 19S Reoel 10V3i933 It will be observed that sanction to the expenditure on these items was applied for last year, but no provision was made in the current year’s budget, as the information called for ir regard to the proposed works was not received by the Government of India in time to admit of the necessary provision being made. In this connection a reference is invited to Memorandum No.F-245-A/32,dated the 16th March 1933* from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Bepartment. (4) It is requested tt at the Government of India will now be pleased to sanction a provision of Rials.8,000/-(equivalent of Rs.l,333/-at the current rate of exchange at Rials. 600 % ) during the year 1934-35 for the works specified against items 1,2 and 6 of the attached statement. It has already been pointed out in Memorandum from this Residency No.12$,dated the 21st January 1933, that these works are essential for the proper maintenance of the Consulate buildings, and that their postponement from year to year would ultimately involve a larger expenditure. Sd/- G.Loch. Cffg. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.bu a.V Six 1 .8 ^ F O (/7b 7^ Copy of a memorandum No. 1028, dated Bushrfe. ^ the 20th May 19 33, from the Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the foreign Secreoaiy to the Government of India, Simla. Special repairs and additions and alterations to the Consulate Buildings at Shiraz. Reference correspondence resting with foreign and Political Department memorandum No. f.245-A/32, dated the 1st fehruary 1933. 2. In view ox the present financial stringency, His Britannic majesty's Consul, Shiraz, has agreed to | the postponement of special repairs and additions and alterations till the next financial year. As regards the mud-plastering of roofs, funds from this Residency Central Contract Grant will he utilized to meet such repairs to the plastering as may he necessary in the meanwhile. ENGLOSURt IN NDIA FOREIGN 3ECR r:T A^''8 Letter No Dated 8 1I]H.1933 Receiv 2 'l:'!. 1933From - f P v jFJLE CGpy . .. ^3^ A/idl* 1 ) 00 uty ^e'brellary to th© GIOTenii^ent ox Inala in th© To - The Hon*'*)!* 'a? s,i Id political «*P»r$-lh 19^ .cal Has id ant in tha Df»v»tcr{ort 'll 1 1 f* Memorandum Mo»i'*^46 , 'ii/32« Dated Hew iiallvi, the /&lt;^ s iiarch 1933. Special repairs to the Shiras Consulate huilaings. Heftsrenoe correspondence ending with your Bc^ioranauia Ho.118 of 1933, dated the 21st January 1933. 2. is already stated in paragraph 2 of foreign and Pol it 1 oil Departnent memorandum No .2?. 245-V 32, dated the 1st Jehruary 1933, no provision has heen made in the ensuing year’s budget estimates for special repairs to the Shiraz Consulate bull dings. Tour meaorsndUE' referred to above was received too late to admit of any additions to the budget estimates for 1933-34. If items 1,2,6 and 7 are really urgent and cannot be postponed for another year, the Govern ment of India would be glad to know how the expenditure involved T»uld be met. As the estimated oost of these items is only Us. 1,230/- it would apparently be possible to meet it from within the total sectioned allotment at your disposal during 1933-34. On this under standing the Govern ment of India would be glad to have the plinth area estimate Tor the5© itesus* \ \ \ Utter Dated 16 ^'^La fvPRWtt o Addl.i)eputy Sd. 7, Narahari Hao, Secretary to the Ooveinment of India*v y ——y-n-iww—m FtLi copy n P.Z. 1 ^^■^^■11182 Copy ol' a niemorandum Nt. 118 of l93o, dated B A '% the 21st January 1933, from'' JJaaL^dti’^.Ie.-the Political Resident in the Persian Grulf, to the Secretary to the Government of India, in the Foreign and Political Depart ment , New DeIhi. Subject;- Special repairs and additions and alterations to the Consulate buildings ! at Shiraz. f • Reference your memorandum No. 245-A/32 dated the 8th September 1932. (2) --is Britannic Majesty’s Consul now reports that it is essential and unavoidable that work under item No. 7 mud plastering ol roois ol the Consulate Buildings at ohiraz, estimated to cost Rials 1200/- vide this Residency Memorandum No. 1689 dated the 20th August 1932, should be carried put during the year 1933-34. I concur with H is Britannic Majesty’s Consul and request that the Government of India will be pleased to sanction the provision lor Rials 1200/- (equivalent to Rs. 160-10-3 approximately at the current rate of exchange viz Rials 7^) during the /ear 1933-34 for the wor* in guestion. (3) as regards the remaining items of the estimate (i.e.some 3s. 1500/-) H.B.M-s Consul, Shiraz, is of opin ion that for the proper maintenance of the Consulate Buildings, work under items Nos. 1,2 and 3 should not he postponed /ear after /ear hut should he attended to before long, or a greater expenditure will he nccessar/ at the end. I concur with his views and suggest that the Govern ment of India will he pleased to sanction the small sum remaining to complete the works estimated for. I ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECR^ARY’S bitter No 20 m. t.trc 9' r H 1933 2 7 FEB. 1933v~'i. ndum HoT7irtB9. dated Bu8hlre» the a ,1 ip; TJopy of a 20th August 1932, from thehcn'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the loreign Secretar/ to the Government of India, Simla. Special Bepairs and Additions ana Alterations to the Consulate ouildings at Shiraz. — '%( In accordance with the instructions contained in Government of India, Foreign and Political Department memo- ^randum Bo. F.472-^3^ of ^3rd February 1931, I submit a statement giving details of the Special Repairs and Additions and Alterations to the Consulate buildings at Shiraz which His Majesty’s Consul At Shiraz proposes to carry out during the year 1933-34. The details show the nature and extent of the works. I therefore request that the Government of India will be pleased to sanction the provisionfoT Rials i4M00/- (equivalent to &gt;s*1730/« approximately at the current rate of exchange 822^5) during the year 1933-34 for the works in question. Ti93 Shiraz Consulate Original works and Special Repairs Estimate for the year 1933-34. 1. Iron roofing north verandah 2. Wooden ceiling new guest room and verandah. M 3. Extension of green-house 4. Making a zir-zsmini (under-ground) 5. Extension of garage 6. Iron roofing Consul and Pro-Consul’s Office. 7. Mud layer to the roofs. '^'CLOSURE IN I Total Rials ;N|J, A FOREIGN SECRETARY'S ? ‘-otier &amp;j 0 ff25 M. ! i^ied 8 SEP 1932 r«: ; h -26 SEP. J32 Original works 1933-34. Rials 4,000 Special Repairs 1933- 34, 1,000 1,000 1,500 500 3,000 11,000 Grant total 14,200. 1,200 2,000 3,200 LIftom - The Under Secretary to the Ooirenment of India in the Foreign ana Political Department, To • The Hon’die the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum Po. ?»M4b-V32« Datea Simla, the September 1952* Special repairs ana additions and altera* tions to the Consulate Duildi.ngu at Shiraz* Reference your aetforanduK Mo* 1669, aavea the 20 th August 1932* 2* In vie* of tne urgent need for economy, the GoTemment of India consider it necessary that all work in respect of buildings etc., should be deferred unless such work is essential on grounds of health or is unavoidable for other urgent reasons* From the details of the works attached to your memorandum under reply it is doubtful whether any of the works proposed to be carried out during the next financial year fulfil either of the two conditions referred to above. It is requested that tha necessity for the works in question should, therefore, be reexamined In the light of the foregoing conditions and revised proposals, if found necessary, be submittad to the Government of Inala at an early date, along with estimates therefor* Sd/* V. karahari Rao, Under Secretary to the Government of IndiaFIL •Vi) r.'/j. ) Y74 40 M l^s Jt Copy of a memorandum Ho.2044, dated Bushire, ^e 3rd October teal, from the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Poreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla, 1 %C ft I 7 * / niw ' EMCL08URE IN I INDIA FOREIGN SEC. FTmRV’S j Letter No 862 j Dated ,12 NOV. 1931 Receive: 60 KOu 1931 Application for sanction to expenditure incurred in excess over the Grant for Special Repairs, British Consulate, Shiraz, for the year 1930-31, 1* Reference Foreign and Political Department Memorandum No.F, 472-A/30 dated 23rd February 1931, conveying sanction to the expenditure of Rs,1184 on account of special repairs and Rs,285 for original works to the Consulate Building at Shiraz* 2* As the expenditure of Rs.285/- on account of original works had already been incurred in the previous year, the grant provided by reappropriation for meeting the cost of special repairs during 1930-31 was Rs»1200/. as submitted in this Residency memorandum Ro.92 dated 13th January 1931 . 3. 'illrough an oversight a copy of this memorandum lTo,92 dated 13th January 1931 was not sent to His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Shiraz, at the time, and the Foreign and Political Department memorandum quoted above was received here only in March 1931. 4, meanwhile, believing that the Special Grant of Rs.1500 applied for in this Residency Ro 0 2156 dated 20th October 1930 v;oulo be sanctioned by the Government of India and the need for further repairs having arisen, His Britannic Majesty's Consul, ohiraz, carried out these repairs incurring the following expenditure*- Re-erection 2 pillars Rs.59. 9. 0. Dressing stone on pillars, Rs,97, 7. o. Ceiling guest room and ambar room, Rs.166*12.0, Total Rs.323, 12.0 ThisThis expenditure added to the expenditure of Hs. 1183.10. of previously incurred results in a total/Rs. 150 7. 6. 0 which is Ks.307. 6. 0 in excess of the provision sanctioned by xxfxx reappropriation. 5. It is regretted that this excess was incurred thro* a misapprehension, and I request that the Government of India will be good enough to condone the error and to accord their sanction to the admittance of the excess in audit. 6. His Britannic Iftajesty's Consul, Shiraz, has been instructed that he should in future invariably obtain sanction before incurring any expenditure on Special Repairs or Original Works even if funds to meet their cost are available.Tom “ Under Searetary to the Govern men t of India TO in the i?Oi*ei«n ana fOlitioal Department, • the Hon*ble the irolitioai Hesident in tho : eraiun Gulf* ^«nov«stdi» ik’ Kow ^oXhi, u^e / I • L'.QViuiliei' *9oi • Repairs to the Shlras Heeidenoy buiiiince* 00 Ototete* Hoferenco ynur 'tmmQrwA'm Wo*2044 dated the 3 rd octet** 1951# 2* before sanctioning the wteofe* axpei'idi^iro w? i&lt;d\ Hao been incurred, it ia neoaoeary to coneider whetfi** any p^t of ttia expend!turo ie diviaible betveen the ^OTernnatni of India and His Majesty's Govemraont as on account of ordinary or special repairs* For thin 9 **rpes« it is requested that details of th® whole expenditure of i 3 :s*i5G'/'*6-o showing ^original works* and •Bopairs’ seimrately nsay bo fumiobed urfcntly. The Government of India note your assurance that dks irregularity in incurring the e^enditure before sanction win net recur. It is specially important in tho case of expenditure in Persia that prior sanction should be obtained as His Hajeety’s Government are also son corned who are averse to their sanation being anticipated* Sd/~ V*Barahari ilao. Under Secretary to the Government of India** In any further communication on this subject, please quote f j. K 2120/1861/234. and address— not toperson by name bv t tojmsy , Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. r kutsHmemnr^f^-l- Foreign Office. S *W*I. 25'th March, 1939. Sir, I am dii^ected hy Viscount Halifax to transmit, to he laid before the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a despatch of the 24-th January from His Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz, concerning the condition of the Consular premises at his post. 2. Lord Halifax is impressed with what would appear to be an urgent need for an adequate allowance for repairs, if the capital value of the buildings is to be maintained and the dignity and comfort of the Consular Officer assured. Whatever the ultimate decision as regards the disposal of the property in question may be, it would appear to be most undesirable to allow undue depreciation for lack of a relatively trivial outlay. Lord Halifax hopes therefore that it may be possible to make a provision for repairs as suggested by Mr. King. The Under-Secretary of State, I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, jjj\ ^ crvT r y ' MR MkU* India OfficeCopy* (K 2120/1861/234). No.10. (53/10/~/15). P.Z. British Consula-je^ 1962 Shiraz, 24th January, 193! 059 J Sir, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a copy of a despatch No* 24/10/2/13 of January 9th, 1939, addressed by me to His Majesty’s Consul-General at Bushire and also a copy of his reply No.79-60/21 of January 19th., 1939, regarding the provision of funds for petty repairs at this Consulate. 2. On my arrival at this post I found that instructions had been received from Bushire in October last that no further expenditure should be incurred under the annual grant of Rs.800 for petty repairs during the remainder of the financial year ending March 31st, 1939. In other words I found myself in charge of a house, offices, guest house, servants' quarters, some 800 yaoxb of mud wall and a miscellany of outhouses, without authority to spend a penny on upkeep throughout the winter months. 3* I have already spent a few pounds from my own pocket on repairs to fireplaces and roofs which I considered indispensable and I am prepared to spend further sums up to a total of £12 on similar repairs which may become necessary before April 1st 1939. 4. If I recoup myself for these disbursements from next year's decreased allowance I shall be doing so at the expense of other urgent repairs which will have to be . neglected/ His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State For Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office,S.W. 1 . - u-'TT ■ neglected. I should therefore be grateful if I might be informed whether it would be possible for such sums as I may spend within the above limit to be recovered for me by means of a corresponding reduction in the contribution towards the maintenance of this establishment which is deducted from my salary. 5. I would also request in view of the utter inadequacy of the present decreased allowance that the Government of India be asked to relieve me in future of any responsibility I may have for extra expenditure due to negligence in the care of these buildings. 6 . I would add that the present state of delapidation appears to be due partly to lack of funds for minor repairs over a period of years and partly to tbs system of accounting with the Government of India whereby my predecessors have been forced to spend their Petty Repairs allowance on special maintenance works recovering the amounts when the latter have been sanctioned, perhaps a year later, by which time the petty repairs have become twice as extensive as they would have been if attended to immediately. 7. I am sending a copy of this despatch to H.M.Consul General at Bushire for information. I have, etc. Sd.A.H.King. H.M.Consul*British Consulate No. 24/10/2/15. Shiraz 9th January, 1939. Sir, With reference to your telegram No. 124 of October 14th # with instructions that no further expenditure should he incurred under Central Contract G-rant and to Bushire memorandum No. A. B. 984 of 26th November 1938 enclosing a statement showing that the annual allowance of Rs.800 made to this Consulate for Petty Repairs had been reduced by Rs.183, I have the honour to request that sanction be obtained to cancel this retrenchment and to restore the allowance to at least the original amount of Rs.800. * 2. In the report of the Assistant Engineer, Independent &gt;&gt; u-* ^ Persian Gulf Sub Division, dated May 5th., 1934, and forv/arded ’'attending to floors and rectifying bad workmanship 11 and that this neglect is chiefly due to the heavy maintenance charges of a lot of cheaply built out-houses and compound wall. It is noted as essential that adequate funds should be provided forthwith and it is recommended that for ordinary repairs a sufficient sum would be Rs.1040. v ‘ 'walls, varnishing doors and windows, replacing broken \k* r W# 3./ The Honble the Political Resident and His Majesty's Consul General British Consulate General Bushire.3. The adequate funds which the Assistant Engineer advised should he provided H forthwith ,, were, as you know, not so provided hut the work which he recommended should he done in 1934, was carried out, largely from Petty Repairs funds, over a period of four years, with the result that other repairs v/hich became necessary in the interval, such as painting and varnishing and general renovation of floors, walls and ceilings, were neglected and the buildings, in spite of the money spent on them, are now in the same state of decay and delapidation as they were at the time of this inspection^ 4. Moreover it should he realized that since 1934 the cost of living in Shiraz has increased by at least 50^ and that any sum reckoned at that time as adequate for the proper maintenance of this property should he increased accordingly^ in other words the sum of Rs.1040/- estimated for ordinary repairs then has become Rs.1560/- now, or nearly double what the allowance was even before the present reduction. 5. There are certain repairs such as distempering and painting v/hich chiefly affect the appearance of the property but which if economy is essential may possibly be left for a few months without much damage ensuing. There are others however such as re-lining of fire-places, re-rolling of roofs and re-plastering of mud walls which recur regularly in Shiraz in the winter season and v/hich if not at once attended to will later on have serious structural conse quences. I cannot think that for the sake of a few rupees I am expected to allow these repairs to slide and so imperil the safety of the buildings in my charge. In the expectation therefore that my request for the restoration of the full, though now inadequate, allowance of Rs.800/- will/1962 j -'939 i will “be conceded, I propose carrying out the more urgent repairs immediately as they occur, and in so doing I do not anticipate that I shall have to incur expenditure in excess of the above limit before April 1st. I have, etc., (Signed) A.H. King. H.M. Consul.m V P.Z. Enclosure to Shiras despatch No-10 of 24th J No. 2. Cop./ • (K 2120/1861/234). No. 79-60/21. British Consulate General Bushire dated the 19th January, 1939 Sir, With reference to your letter No* 24/10/2/15 of the 9th January, 1939, I have the honour to state that the funds of the Central Contract Grant have been subjected to a 10% reduction by the Government of India* This Residency, therefore, cannot provide funds above the allotment, and any expenditure of money above the decreased allotment cannot be met by government funds I have, etc., (Signed) L*S.T. John for Political Resident in the Persian Gulf To His Majesty’s Consul ShirazFILE COPY In any further communication on thig subject^please quote. A K fl .R'3o?6//rt//j*4 P „j 4 ~ *-,•/-«*» /iic t/mt* Knt tn — *not to anjt person by name, but to— Secretary of S^ate,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. f rv i THE Under-Secretary of State for ^Fore^g^^airsy presents his cortiplim^ftts to r^uted an&lt; ^’ by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy” of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Reference to previous correspondence Description of Subject. enclosure nTniit •»*«- ltTXtH NO- 1 from secretary, ROutical and 8EC' ET DEPT. INDIA OFFICECopy. • (K 3076/1860/234). No.J.3. (97/10/2/15). sJ ‘ c ^ c. t J His Majesty^ Consul at Shiraz presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office and has the honour to transmit to him the under—mentioned documents for his information. British Consulate, Shiraz, 18th February,1939. Reference to previous correspondence:- Shiraz despatch No.9 (36/10/2/15) of 14th January,1939:No.10 (53/10/2/15) of 24th January, 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date* Subject. Copy of a Memorandum No. 169 &lt;- 28/37 dated the 7th February, Budget Estimate for 1939. 9th from the Secretary to the repairs etc. for the year Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to His Majesty*s 1939-1940. Consul, Shiraz. Copy of letter No.95/10/2/15 of 18th February 1939, to the Hon’ble the Political Resident etc. in the Persian Gulf, from His Majesty’s Consul, Shiraz.JNOSaE Copy of *m o datod the 9th Uay Foroi^i, New Delhi rasa letter No. 1113-60/42. Uar 1944 from Britconaul, Bushire to &lt;V- 0 , i / il 1 ^ ■ '' ' , / four talograta Hoe 73^A/ Qarap aa^oa ju 3 ^ a if +3 1943 ^ Ordinary ropaira allotaont of the ^hira Consulate* ; ^p/\ dated 7th J 2* Ifis Ikiesty 1 ® Consul has pointed out that ^ between 1939/40 nwhen his allotoaent was fixed at &gt;4 , rtr „ y)\ h. 1,500/- and 1943/44 when it was raised to //o r1 ‘ h^wk&gt;s 3 f 000/- there has been an increase of 900% to 1000 % in the cost of buildings materials in one ^ case amounting to as ouch as 3,400%, while during ^ ^the same period wages of carpenters, masons, and coolies hare increased by 366 % to 500 %• He is . therefore finding it inpossible to maintain the jawt building in a xtx satisfactory state of repairs “ on his present aHotraent and has applied for his \ 10. g ran ^ present year to be increased to •y y rt3»i 4,500/—* 3* In view of the reasons fjiven in para* 2 above I I recoraaend that grant for 194^45 be increased j to fe* 4,500/* and request that sanction be conrauni- , 1 Gated to me by telegram* The extra expenditure w uiffolyed cannot be met from my existing grant, but wil^ be included in niy statement of excesses and ^•gvjLjig* in due course* \ 0 ^ J • Aid issue of the above has been authorised* -2 7, fb » IN 10 &lt;^1 aA k *u rj^u *_ °t f9 ®*pre 88 letter No. 979-28/37. dated the 7th June 1943 from Britconsul , Bushire to Foreign. New /'?') Delhi. , 4 i,\; ^ S/ Ordinary repairs to the Shiraz Consulate . 1 ) flllP ‘4 t4 Reference telegram No, 127-A dated 1st March 1940 70 fixterru (tM./ fiJho fk+'k vtshjy ^Lcrft /I from OoTernment of India, External Affairs Department to Secy/ ll L 2* , I^ndon. with copy to me, providing aum of p fee 1,500/- under this Residency's Central Contract Grant for ^ ordinary repairs to Shiraz Consulate, C/Q 2* His Majesty's Consul, Shiraz, has represented that^ owing to torrential rains from November 1942 to March 1943 great been caused to mud walls round Consulate premises/ in ^ &gt; 0 U V* He considers present annual allotment of fe. 1,500/- meet half the cost of repairs necessary during L943-44 and asks that allotment be increased to fe. 3,000A. ?• . request that Government of India's sanction increasing allotment rt to te. 3.000/- for current financial year be accorded by telegram. Additional amount required during current financial year will be met by reappropriation. The issue of the above has been authorised, i \ % ^ ) lA V J-Telegram No. 73-A/Caap, Dated Simla, the 7th July 1943. From i- Foreign, Simla, To: - - Britconsul, Buehire. / ^ Tour Biprees Letter No. 979-28/37 of June 7th. Repairs to Shire* Consulate. Proposal sanctioned.Political Department. NOTES FOR REGISTRY. REGISTER NO. P.2 1XV6 T^ram from f ^ Letter 19tW Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary 1C) V ^Per\Jb40^w Cory^xjJLarf £ Secretary of State Committee ... S^cu^: H-M. Under Secretary ^ ^ocoJZ. : ?^cf^u tui Secretary of StateP.Z.2296/41. The Under-Secretary of Foreign Cifice, S.W.l. (D DBaFT LETTER . State, India Office. 2 1941 ^rt Sir, With reference to the Foreign Office letter of the Srd May, Rc.K 4173/1422/224, on the subject of the charges claimed from His Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz by the local Municipality, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to state that he agrees to accept a moiety of the further demands amounting to 16215.10 Rials as a charge on Indian revenues^ on the understanding that payment will be withheld pending further negotiations with the Iranian Government in respect of the obligations of the Iranian Legation in London. (Bud.) J. p GIBSON© * A but to— not to any person by name '94 ■ ' Foreign Office. S.W.l. ' The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. 3rd May, 1941 Sir With reference to India Office letter P.Z.1473/40 of the 14th March, 1940, concerning charges levied hy the Municipality of Shiraz against His Majesty^ / Consul at that place, I am directed hy Mr#Secretary Eden to transmit herewith, to he laid before the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a letter addressed hy the Foreign Office to the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty*s Treasury, from which it will he observed that a further demand, amounting to 16215.10 rials has been made hy the Municipality. 2. The Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury have replied authorising His Majesty’s Consul to meet this demand, provided that a moiety of the expenditure should he accepted hy the Government of India as a charge against their funds. Their Lordships see no objection to the proposal that no payment should he made to the Municipality until a more accommodating attitude has been adopted hy the Iranian Government towards the outstanding rates which are owed hy the Iranian Legation in London. 3. I am to encuire whether the Government of India is prepared to accept the charge to Indian revenues of a moiety of the sum of 16215.10 rials, on the understanding that payment will not he made to the Shiraz Municipality until further negotiations with the Iranian Gove -nment have been undertaken on the lines indicated in the preceding paragraph. REC». POL. cr F t, I am INDIA OFFICE Sir, Your oberient Servant Tie Under-Secretary of State India Office.■Hi MM Co^. (K* 1423/1423/234) Sir, 22 Q 8 P0 f TGN 0PPTG3, s.w.i. Uth March, 1941. 94 1 J ^ With reference to Treasury letter E 8404/2 of the 30th April, 1940, concerning charges nresented hy the Shiraz Municipality to His Majesty’s Consul, T am directed hy Mr- Winston Churchill to transmit herewith, to be laid before the Lords Commissioners of His ^ f Majesty’s Treasury a copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran, from which it will be observed that further demands amounting to 16215.10 rials have been made. 2. Mr. Churchill considers that His Majesty’s Government must admit liability for these charges, and T am to express the hope that Their Lordships may authorise this expenditure to be incurred in due course. Unless, however. Their Lordships see any objection, Mr.Churchill nroposes to adopt Sir Reader Bullard’s proposal that the Iranian Government be informed that payment to the Shiraz Municipality will be withheld until the Iranian Legation in London shows a willingness to meet outstanding indebtedness for rates. These rates which represent an analogous liability formed the subject of correspondence between the Foreign Office and the Treasury Valuer, whose reference was D.R./10920/R/40. Up to the 21st March, 1940, the sum involved amounted to £264.Os.lid., and will be increased by approximately £180 in respect of the year ending 21st'March, 1941. Although the total sum considerably exceeds that for which His Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz is liable, Mr. Churchill considers that for the latter to withhold payment may induce in the Iranian Government a due sense of its responsibilities. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Signed) A.3. Hutcheon. The Secretary to the Treasury. ■■r \ Q&amp; Up. 9 (89/1/41) 19 anuary, 1941 40 With reference to ^orel^ai Office tule^ ra n 8£: n t the 4th Hay, 1940, sanctioning the payment of Hiula 8123750 for the asphaltlag of the pavenent and other work carried out by the municipality of vihirua in front of ilia Majaaty , a Consulate in that town, I have the honour to report that the British Acting Consul at Chiraz has received from the municipality further demands in respect of (a) completing and pointing the *ater channel adjoining the pavement in front of the Consulate, and (bj constructing and edging with cement a pavement 1.8 metres wide along the entire length of the west wall of the Consulate premises# These demands amount to Hiale 808.50 and Rials 15,406.60 respectively. in the past, and since the opinion was expressed in Foreign ffiCi 5045/5045/034) of the 19th , 3958, thaX there were no valid grounds for declining to meet such charges, I have the honour to requeet that sanction may be granted for the payment of fialf 16,215.10. *ranian Oovarnmcnt to settle its own municipal debts in the case of the rates payable on the premises of the Iranian Legation in i ondon (in thif; connexion please see the correspondence ending with my, deBDatch :to. 244 of the 15th November, 1940), I would' r est that, if sanction is granted for the payment of the sum now in^question, I should nevertheless be authorized to cause it to be weaporarily witaeld until thex*e is evidence of a more accommodating attitude on the part of the Iranian Government in respect of ito own obligations. I do not assume that the demands now being made by the Shiraz municipality are legally on tne esme footing as charges in respect of rates, due from the Iranian Legation in London, and in any representations X might make I would only propose to link the two matters together in an tznofficial manner, in the hope of thereby bringing the Iranian Government to a greater sense of its obligations. I have the honour to be with the highest reelect, blr. Your most obedient, humble Servant, In view of the fact that similar d© .an&amp;a have been raet laving regard, however, to the reluctance of the ullard The ight Honourable .‘Oithony JSdsa, 1.0., f. o. # ©tc* - #»t. +/■»- m INDEXED A la any further communication un this subject, please quote No. K. 5630/59/234. and address— not to any person by name but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. 3^0 FILE COPY A * , . ) f j 'p'o ^ -A- * - .♦ ^ i o o 9 ’340 j Sir, 22nd March, 1940. With reference to India Office letter P.Z. 1552/40 of the 16th March, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to state for the information of the Marquess of Zetland that sanction has been obtained for the charge to Imperial Funds of a moiety of some 1,850 rupees representing the estimated cost of executing certain special repairs to premises of His Majesty’s Consulate at Shiraz. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,Political Department. i NOTES FOR REGISTRY. REGISTER NO. P.Z. Uo Telegram fronl Letter 19 k*.. Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary Secretary of State 14 • 3 //f / ..Committee ... Under Secretary Secretary of State 3 FOR USE BY DEPARTMENT ONLY. &lt;rf| wuftf -Sfe ni THE ADVISERS CONCUR 20 MAR 1940ya&amp;SS* J FILECOFT the 8th February 1940« The Hon # ble the Political Hesident in the Persian (iulf, bus hire • To The Secretary to the liovernment of Indiat&gt; eternal Affairs Department, New Delhi* No •189-28/37* Fran p.z. 1 Datq 1484 1940 Special Repairs to the Shiraz Consulate Buildings* Sir, 1 have the honour to refer to this office letter No*860 dated the 6th October 1939, forwardir^ among others the budget Estimate of the Shiraz Consulate for 1940«*41. in that estimate a sum of Hs*1,500/- was provided for under Works - ’’Petty constructions and repairs M * This amount was based on certain items, of works as estim- ted for by His Majesty's Consul, Shiraz, in the sub-joined schedule marked 'A'* 2* bis Majesty's Consul, Shiraz, has now submitted a revised estimate mounting to bials 22,200-00 which at the present rate of exchange, viz* Rials 12 to the mpee, works out to Rs*1,850/- resulting in an excess of Rs.350/- provided for in the budget # Why it has been founc necessary to revise the estimate has been ecplained in detail by His Majesty # s Consul, Shiraz, vide the enclosed copy of his despatch No* 54-10-2-3, dated the 25th January 1940* It will be observed from paragraph 3 thereof that to take advantage of the more favourahle tender submitted by one of the masons, the contract of rebuilding the wall should be given before 24th March, 1940*3. I have, therefore, the honour to request that a sum of Ks#1,850/- may be allotted for special repairs to the Shiraz Consulate buildings during the ensuing finan i year and that sanction to take on hand the rebuilding of the wall before 24th March, 1940, be accorded by telegram. i am forwarding a copy of. this letter to nis Majesty s Consul, Shiraz* 1 have etc., 3d /- for Political Resident in the Persian0 SOHSPULlii 'A 1 * . AN Shiraz Consulate Budget ultimate for the year 1940~41. # . I M SP5CLVL HEP.U:^. !♦ New mud plaster for coping of all walls, supporting poles for barbed wifce to be replaced where necessary. 2. Re-pointing lower brick work of main varandah and office. 3. Jfew mud plaster for the remaining roofs of kitchen, well-house, store-rooms, green-house and laundry, etc. .. 4. Demolishing long store-room in lower stables, roof of which has fallen in, and removing rubble. .. 5. C-ravel for drives e •Rials replaced with new iron sheeting •» 1400 400 2200 /- 500 600 4000 Total Rials 9100 (Total Rials 9100 @ flials 6 to the Rupee Rs.1,500/-)No. 54 / 10 / 2 / 3 . British Consulate, Shiraz, 25th January, 1940 # Sir, With reference to my despatch No*472/l0/2/15 of September 26th 1939, enclosing a statement of the Special Repairs required at this Consulate for the year 1940-1941, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a translation of a notice which i received from the Municipality of Shiraz in October last and also the traHalation^f a letter dated January 15th 1940 from the Head of the Municipality requesting me to take steps to have the west bound airy wall of the Consulate rebuilt in accordance with municipal regulations® 2® The side streefc| formerly a lane, bouncing the Consulate to the west, is in process of being graner converted into a thoroughfare thirty two feet wide and in accordance with article 9m of the law axa^KHDoix concerning the widening of streets passed by the Medjliss on November 15th 1933 all frontagers may be compelled to reconstruct their walls to the desigi laid down by the Municipality as befitting a street of this dimension* The property owner on the other side of the way has as stated by the t i n^ad of the Municipal^ been obliged to put his wall back ten feet and recontruct it from to- bottom® The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, Bushires o 26^ 000. ^8. 12. Hs.2333. ’Us.ie^ooo. Rl 8.16, 000, o ihe present (Jonsulste whII, i^iich is sonie 300 yards long and 10 feet high is a mud construction entailing heavy maintenance charges every year* It is required that it should be encased in stone to a height of two feet and the remainder framed in brickwork* i have obtained two estimates for this work, one from the meson usually employed by the Consulate lor Hials Twenty eight thoasand* equivalent at the present fate of exchange of rtials Twelve to hs *1 to rupees Two thousand three hundred and thrity three, and the other from the mason employed on the wall opposite for rtials Sixteen thousand iRs*1333^* As I consider the latter tender extremely favourable I have induced the mason to sign a contract which will be valid provided the order is given for the work within two months from to-day* After that date the contract would be subject to revision and that, in view of the steady rise in the cost of all materials, would certainly be an upward one* 4. 1 should therefore be extrememly grateful if you would Urgently recommend to the Government of India that a supplemetary item of rtials Sixteen thousand be added to my budget estimate for special repairs for 1940-1941 and that sanction be given to me, if necessary by telegraph, to start work before two months have expired* 5* Should this item be sanctioned, two other items in my budget estimate may be struck out, namely No*l '•New mud plaster for the coping ofaci all walls etc' Rials 1400, as the wall which it is now proposed to reconstruct was responsible for the bulk of this expense and No.4 • Demolishing lond store-room in lower stablds' Rials 500, as the structmre in question abuts on to the wall end demolition can be effected at the time the wall is reconstructed at a fraction of what it would otherwise cost* The small charges which these items would then involve could be tea borne by the newly revised allowance /for*.**for Petty Repairs. Furtneriaore this allowance will now be suflicient to cover items 2 ana 5* I accordingly enclose an amended bucket estimate on these lines 6* In this connection I would point out that the opening up of this siae streets must necessarily improve the capital value of the Consulate property* Cardans in the neighboorrhood are already being offered as building sites at twice the price demanded only six months ago# Reconstruction of this wall in conformity with municipal requirements cannot therefore be considered an idle expense* Moreover, regulations apart, it must be admitted that a mud wall built when this property was surrounded by open fields can no long^ be regarded as either fitting or proper for this Consulate now tik t it stands well within trie town. I trust, therefore, that the necessary expenditure will be readily approved# I have ettf#* SdA A#H#King H*M*Consul*.No*9477* &lt;1,7 [9 Tr anslation NQTICT * From:- The Municipality of Shiraz ttcilaing anu lana owners in Khiaban**i-ESana ana in the siae stress of the Khiaban axe hereby notifiea thz tlir t they must within a period of 15 days from the above date cover their walls facing the Khiaban or aide streets with a framework of bricks in order that the xafk walls may not become ruinous or look dirty in the rainy season* They must also lay stone foundations properly cementea or cover s*. ch foundations with cement* Shoula it be seen after the ab4^e period that the owners have not taken steps in the matter, they will be recognized as (Offenders ana be prosecuted* Sd/“ Municipality of ShirazTr anslfatior. No.14864. Jated 24-10-16 Jan 18, iy-±U. From — The ^iesh of the Municipality, Shiraz*. To - The British Con suite at Shiraz*. I nave the honour to state thtt as you have seen the Municipality has casued Mqai rustchi, the owner of Bagh-i-Shaikh, to aemolish and put back his wall in the street behind the Consulate three metres 5 also to build his wall aceoraing to the instructions of the Municipality• Since the wall of the Consulate which is opposite the wall of bagh-i-Shaikh, is an old wall and is not fit for a street of 10 metres, please instruct tret the^ a wail oe built according to the wail of iiqai Pustchi* Cf course if the Consulate with a view to beautifying the wall of their garden ana buildings, wishes to make an even better w^ll 1 shall be grateful* Sd/- heaa of the Municipality, Bealeo by the Municipality of Shiraz*Shiraz Consulte rtevised Budget Estimates /or the year 1940*1941 &gt; SP^XI AI mm^TAIHS e !• New mud plaster for remaining roofs etc Hials 2200* 2. Iron roofs of drawing room and guest house badly leaking owing to having been llailed when first J&gt;ut up, to be re-placed with new iron sheeting * 4000* 3*Hecons truction of west boundary wall to conform with municipal regulAtittas * 16000* Total Hia Is 22200# Hials Twenty two thousand and two hundred*Proin The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, To The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office London, S.W*1* st N]cx^cJ^ Dated New Delhi, the 1940. SUBJECT:- Payment for asphalting the pavement, Sir, With reference to your letter No* P.Z.653/40, dated the 7th February 1940, I am directed to say that the Government of India accept a moiety of the expenditure involved in the asphalting of the pavement and the pointing of the water conduit outside His Majesty 1 s Consulate at Shiraz as a charge upon Indian revenue. etc., in front of His Majesty^ Consulate, Shiraz. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant for Secretary to the Government of India. REC*. IK&gt;L. PtTI ) t I MAR 040 INDIA OFR2Er. X0&amp; 2V % ■ ^ t;f5 ' V '&gt;■ 1 2o3 1940 J Allotted to Politioal Department. 55 words. it+4 1541. DECODE OP TELEGRAM. Froui Government of India, External Affairs Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhi, 18.10 hours, 1st March, 1940. Received 17.16 hours, 1st March, 1940. 127A. Reference correspondence ending with your letter No. P.Z.6084/39, October 10th. British Consul-General at Bushire reports that special repairs to Shiraz Consulate buildings, estimated cost rupees 1,850, urgently required during ensuing year and asks for permission to start work before March 24th to enable Consul to take advantage of favourable terms offered by contractors. Copy of correspondence being sent to you by air next v/eek. Kindly telegraph His Majesty’s Government’s concurrence to share expenditure. REC». POL. BEPt. 2-MAR1940 INPIA OFFICEINDEXED In any further communication on this^subjec^, please quote and address “ The Under- J \A^ y 7 * r-cc, tv.L-' i (y. &gt; No./i &gt;3^7^72 3f . —not to any person by nfame, blit to— I J vj &gt;&lt; :r-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, $.W. i.l W.L- THE Under-Secretary of i ^tate IfQ 4 Qeign^ Affairs presents his compliments to — ^O'^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^ of the ur^der-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, JLeb\4*S, £ 1940. 4 ^ - Reference to previous correspondence P'*'- Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. C-^lviqcvi^ l^a 16, Rj. CLl^ 5 h Clsi /Ecdtai'ix^ of' -SiLv'yicc^ - ENCLOSURE IN AIR MAIL LETTER No. 9 _1 MAR 1940 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL DEPT. INDIA OFFICE Similar letter sent 14 ENCLOSUtE IN WEEKLY LETTER No. 10 e.viAR mo ^ FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRETBritish ■Consuls No.10. (45/10/2/3). IV L. 1243 ” 1940 J Shiraz, January, 1340. Mr, 'Uh further re^er»ence to my despatch No. *6 Hs . 1.500 • of August List 1939, regarding the provision of fuj ^or ordinary re pairs at this Consulate, X hr* * the honour to report that authority has now been given me through the Hon r ble the Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf to incur expenditure on ordinary repairs up to a limit of Rupoes One thousand and five hundred during the current and subsequent financial years. 2* this Is the amount *M*h f stated &gt;&gt;• adequate for the purpose in paragraph 8 of my despatch of Aprt? 4th 1939 a-dressed to ♦he Hcn'ble the Political -ssident in the Persian tfulf - copy of wnich m-s fcrrraed to tn« foreign Z 0fflce un&lt;3er cover of Shiraz printed letter No.17 / ^ of April 4th 1939. tt should therefore now be po* ’* v \e with this sum at my disposal to put, ar r * maintain, these buildings in a proper state H of repair. His Majesty's ^rihcipal ^ecret?ry of State for Foreign Affaire, Foreign Oii.;ce, S.?.l. I havt the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, Sd• A.H.King. R.M.Consulmm Foreign Office. S.W.l. 31st January, 1940. With reference to India Office letter P.Z.4162/38 of the 28th June, 1938 concerning a charge for asphalting the footpath in front of His Majesty’s Consulate-General at Meshed, I am directed hy Viscount Halifax to transmit herewith, to 'be laid 'before the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires at Tehran indicating that a similar charge has now 'been presented to His Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz 'by the local Iranian authorities. 2. On the grounds advanced in Foreign Office letter of the 18th May, 1938 Lord Halifax considers that there are no valid grounds for declining to meet this charge and I am to express the hope that the Government of India ma^ oe prepared to accept the charge of a moiety of the sum of 8,123.50 rials as a charge against Indian revenues on analogy with the similar payment made in respect of His Majesty s Consulate-General at Meshed. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, / V The Under-Secretary of State, India Office.mmm Cop,/. (K 679/59/234) Original sank at sea. 21/12/39. No. 379 . (831/3/39) 5th December, 1939. My Lord, I have the honour to invite Your Lordship’s attention to correspondence ending with your despatch No. 23 6(K 7863/5045/ * 234) of 13th July 1938, on the question of whether His Majesty’s Consul-General at Meshed should pay the municipal authorities for street improvements outside his office and house. 2. A similar situation has now arisen in Shiraz, where His Majesty’s Consul has been requested to pay the sum of Rials 8123. 50 for the asphalting of the pavement and the pointing of the water conduit outside his office. 3. Although in the case of Meshed it was decided that there were no valid grounds for declining to meet this charge, and His Majesty’s Consul-General was authorized to include the amount in his account with the Government of India, I have thought it well to enquire of Your Lordship whether that decision should be regarded as a precedent, and whether His Majesty’s Consul at Shiran should, after checking the municipality’s assessment of the area , pay for the street improvements as private persons would have to do. 4. I have instructed Mr. King in the meantime to inform the local authorities that he has referred the matter to His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom. I have , e tc. , (Sd.) Walter Roberts. The Right Honourable The Viscount Halifax, K.G. , G.C.S.I. , G.C.I.E. , etc. , etc. , etc. , FOREIGN OFFICE.d The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, To £ do ^ , J The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S*Y/.l. / December 1939. Dated New Delhi, the Maintenance of the Shiraz Consulate premises® Sir, With reference to India Office letter No* P*Z*6084/39, dated the 10 th October 1939, I am directed to enclose a copy of this Department Memorandum to the Hon'ble the Political Resident * in the Persian Gulf noted in the margin, from which it will be seen T No.F. 12.2-A/39, dated the ^ December 1939* J jj that necessary action has been taken to } make available to His Majesty's Consul at Shiraz requisite funds for the maintenance of the Consular premises* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, RECo 18 pOL OEP T - 0E.C1939 for Secretary to the Government of India. io~H u&gt; \HD\bOZ[}C£Memorandum No* F*122&lt;-A/39* Dated New Delhi, the New Delhi, the * December 1939* ^ December 1939 Maintenance of the bhira* Consulate premises* Reference India Office letter ho. P*~*6084/39, dated the 10th October 1939,(copy sent to you direct). grant of Rs* 1,500/- (Rupees one thousand five hundred) for the mainte nance of the Consulato premises with effect from the current financial year* Ihia is subject to the condition that the total central contract grant in any year is limited to 2 per cent of the total cost of all the ouildinga in Iran under your administrative control* for the current year forwarded with your Memorandum No. 980-60/23, dated the 24th November 1939, the increase in the maintenance grant for bhir&amp;x sanctioned in this Department Memorandum No* if.iaa-iy^, dated the 11th October 1939, has been taken into account. The small additional expendi ture involved in the current year by the raising of the grant to Rs.1,500/- niay be met from the existing allotments at your disposal, but if this is nci possible, the net additional allotment required, over and above what has already been applied for in your Memorandum of the 11th October 1939 referred to above, may be imimated urgently. i ® has been made in the estimates proposed by you under Central Con— tract Grant to meet the additional expenditure connected with the Shira* premises* 2• In the circumstances explained, the Government of India are pleased to agree that the Consul, Shiraz should be allowed an annual It is presumed that in the statement of savings and excesses As regards next year, an increase of Rs* 700/- (Rupees seven Sd/— GoK.S.S&amp;rma* Under Secretary to the Government of India.\ s«® &amp; m I list LE COPY No. vr 4 r 4 i Fr ora F.122-V39. j I ^r*. \ i 'l * ■W- v V- 7 —11 im i tH.^n ****/ The Secretary to the Grovernraent of India in the External Affairs Department, To The Under Secretary of State for India, political Department, India Office, London, S.7.1. Dated New Delhi, the October 1939. n to onsular premi ses at Si: iraz . Sir, ^ith reference to the correspondence ending with the India Office letter no. ir. 4416/39, datea the 28th July 1939, I am directed to say that the Government of India agree that the question ox tne transfer of the 3hiraz premises may be .held in abeyant for the present, and that the existing arrangements for their maintenance may continue, till the general question regarding Consular representation in Iran is settled. , ,, , . I have the honour uo ue Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Secretary to the Gov eminent of Inaia. *&gt; (g s G Jd. POL. DEf7 ’0OC11939 &gt;IA OFFICE(6610) Wt.25956/235 10,000 9/38 A.&amp;E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 Minute Paper. Mr. Gi Jason, p.z. 6O84/39. Department. K. . Y 3*-^. '[O JlY A, 4i# ^ ^rrw-vAC^ t» Ip. Proposed increase in repairs allotment to Shiraz Consulate. There is a certain repetition of papers on this Uo.'j’V file since the Consulate at Shiraz has. 'been goaded into applying alternately to the Government of India and the Foreign Office for relief. What they ask for is an increase of Rs. 700 (£52:10:-) in the annual allotment for petty repairs. On receiving this request the Government of India temporised by saying that it had better await the outcome of their suggestion to us that His Majesty’s Government should assume responsibility from the end of the present financial year^for the maintenance of the Consulate buildings (vide P.Z.3699/39). The suggestion has now been negatived by the Foreign Office and the Foreign Office letter has been sent to the Government of India H for consideration” (P.Z. 4416/39). It follows that the Consulate would be entitled to ask the Government of India to reconsider its interim reply. Actually the Consulate have appealed to the Foreign Office to secure a reconsideratior via the India Office (enclosure dated August 21st, P.Z. 6084/39). In consequence I submit for approval the draft letter below. In view of the wording of the first sentence in paragraph 3 to the enclosure dated 21st August to the Foreign Office letter, should we forward this enclosure with the Foreign Office letter or not? The Government of India are already familiar with its substance from the enclosure dated 4th April at X P.Z. 2814/39, a copy of which was forwarded to them on the/ 'Draft Paper. P.Z. 6084/39. Department. DRAFT The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department. Dated 28th September (^with enclosures) \\ wo'r COPY SP^’T ''v » 0C__/3 P.ft. 1 uniL&lt; CiAtiX^o. IR MAIL (z Po '* ‘ / 11 OGT 1959 j6i&amp; C&lt;rfa 4^*4 ^ if/j. LETTER. ^0 OCT 195}; Sir, In continuation of correspondence resting with India Office letter vw. P.Z. 4416/39 dated the 28th July, regarding the expenditure on repairs to the Consular buildings at Shiraz, I am directed by the Secretary of State to forward for the consideration of the Government of India a copy of the marginally noted letter from the Foreign Office on this subject. Lord- Zetland oonoure-with the Secretary of Qtate for Foreign Affairs that there -is-an urgent In. &lt;s(* five necessity for the petty repairs iei-evw&lt;i. to ao dotail-ed by H.M. Consul at ^erv- fUeve e . * tirw Shiraz^ (-In- thio connection please refer to the Despatch No. 164/10/2/15 of the 4th April 1939, ftfom H.M. Consul, Shiraz to jfche Political Resident in the' Persian Gulf, a copy of which^as forwarded with India Office letter No. P.Z.2814/39 on the fke S. &lt;?(- S\ ith May )» I... am- -te-express- the hope* that the Government of India will CtmcnJV- u* fU*. [&gt;^Opcrxt^L- agroe- t-o—sanction-the increase of (10337) Wt.l4054/P,164 10,000 5/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 Rs. 700 a year in the annual allotment for these repairs which bkj^y required . uhJA iji tb XfJ^A^uX a4* cu*. dLxtb . U U4U, ^ a . u, theINDEXED COPY In any further communication h on this subject, please quote No. K 11791/1861/234. and address— not to any person by name but ' The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.I. 1939 t Foreign Office. S.W.I. 8th September, 1939. Sir, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to refer to India Office letter P.Z. 4688/39 of the 1st August concerning the maintenance of the premises of His Majesty 1 s Consulate / at Shiraz, and to transmit to be laid before the Secretary of State for India a copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s ‘Consul at that post, pointing out the need for an increase to 1,500 Rupees a year of the annual allotment for petty repairs without waiting for the outcome of the proposal that His Majesty’s Government should take over the responsibility for the maintenance of the premises in future. 2. As the repairs in question are of a nature which do not permit of further postponement, Lord Halifax hopes that the Government of India may be persuaded to agree to this proposal. I am accordingly to request that Lord Zetland will, if he sees no objection, take steps to obtain their concurrence I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office. enclosure in air mail letter I No 40 -3 OCT 1939 FROM SECRETARY, rOL! ! K AL DL INDIA OFFICE INDIA OFFICE(K 11791/1861/234) No. 26 (401/10/2/15) \ Sir, C x ^ 0 * British Consulate 'wj Q 4 | Shiraz. !G3*S /August 21st, 1939. Rs. 800 Rs. 630. V/ith reference to my despatch of April 4th, 1939 (164/10/2/15) addressed to the Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, a copy of which was transmitted to you under Shiraz printed letter No. 17 of April 4th, 1939, regarding the provision of funds for petty repairs at this Consulate, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a copy of a memorandum No. F.122-A/39 of July 18th, 1939 from the Under- ■ | X V Secretary to the Government of India addressed to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, stating that before considering the question of increasing the Shiraz Consulate allotment (for petty or ordinary annual repairs) the Government of India would prefer to await the outcome of their suggestion, made to the India Office, that His Majesty’s Government should take over the responsibility for the maintenance of the Consulate buildings with effect from the next / financial year. 2. In this connection I would observe that out of V\ my present annual allotment of Eight hundred rupees for ' ^ \ i the year ending March 31st, 1940, I have already incurred i t \ necessary expenditure amounting to Six hundred and thirty rupees. Two thirds of this amount was the cost of paint and painting, which owing to the cracked condition of the woodwork after ten years of neglect, was an especially heavy item. Apart from general petty repairs there remains to be done:- (l) internal /whitewashing His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office, London, S.W.1.mmmm whitewashing - a necessary annual health precaution which has not been taken this year owing *to~“I&amp;dtr at funds and as a result the house is infested with sand flies, (2) varnishing of windows and doors exposed to sun and rain, and (3) replastering of the 800 odd yards of mud walls. I estimate that these items alone will require the expenditure of not less than Six hundred rupees and I can safely state that if the last item is not attended to before the advent of the winter rains, the cost of repair next year will be considerably more than twice as great without reckoning on the possibility of structural damage. 3. I therefore venture to submit that the Government of India be approached through the India Office with the request that the question of raising the annual allotment of this Consulate to One thousand and five hundred rupees should be considered without waiting for the outcome of X their suggestion. It may be remembered that this is not the first time this suggestion has been made. In 1936 the Government of India declined responsibility for original works at this Consulate on identical grounds but whatever justification there may have been in that case, I feel strongly that the provision of adequate funds for the ordinary running repairs of these buildings should not also be held up pending the decision as to ultimate ownership. 4. I would add that the additional funds mentioned in the last sentence of the Government of India's memorandum under reference concern the special repairs for this year which were the subject of my despatch of January 14th, \ 1939 to Bushire, a copy of which was transmitted to you eos t Rs.600 Rs.1,500 • r-. Ulo. *k\ GtfV under Shiraz printed letter No. 9 of January 14th, 1939, \ \ and the extra expenditure last year which I incurred out /of( of my own pocket and which was to the Foreign Office No. 16 of funds have 'been duly allotted t Residency at Bushire. 5. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for his information. he subject of my despatch P IP A L April ?3rdtY These me b^f th^ r political w O o j I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, Humble Servant, (Signed) A.H. King. H.l f . ConsulEnclosure to Shiraz despatch No. 26 of 21et August, 1939. I r.'R' I v v‘ sj r j COPY Prom - The Under Secretary to the Gove in the External Affairs Department rnmeLt. • : - • ' ' of India J To - The Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum No. P.122-A/39. Dated Simle, the 18th July, 1939. SHIRAZ CONSULATE BUILDINGS. Reference your letter No. 865, dated the 24th June 1939. 2. Before considering the question of increasing the Shiraz Consulate allotment under Central Contract Grant, the Government of India would prefer to await the outcome of the suggestion made to the India Office that His Majesty's Government should take over the responsibility for the maintenance of the Consulate Buildings with effect from the next financial year, vide this Department endorsement No. F. 122-A/39, dated the 7th June 1939. As regards the current year, it is presumed that additional funds will be allotted to His Majesty's Consul at Shiraz as suggested in this Department Memorandum No. F. 122-A/39, dated the 7th June 1939. (Signed) Sarma, Under Secretary to the Government of India.indexed F, r LE COPY -2 7 JUI SQ 1 W 39 I No. 865. W i ,r-\ o^* r 4 0 rfO Br r-' tish Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 24th June, 1939. From - To The Hon r hie Sir Trenchard Fowle, KCIE.,CBE., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. Subject Shiraz Consulate Building. Sir, In continuation of my memorandum Ho.622-28/37 of the Sqql&gt;^ 5th May 1939, I have the honour to forward herewith a copy of a letter No.164/10/2/15, dated the 4th April 1939, from His Majesty 1 s Consul, Shiraz, requesting that a substantial increase be made in his annual allotment for the upkeep of the Shiraz Consulate buildings. 2. His contention that the sum of Rs.800/-, which is allotted to him annually for petty repairs from this Residency T s Central Contract Grant, is inadequate, cannot be disputed and it is a fact that the Consulate building is in a deplorable state of repair. It is not possible hovjevei to increase his allotment from the Central Contract Grant without materially reducing the sums allotted for the upkeep of the other Consulates in the charge of this Residency. The attached statement shows the distribution of the Centra] Contract Grant to the various Consulates which is based on tbe c apital cost o f their respective buildings. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY^. UTTER No. D'-'U 7 130 I 0-7 26-7-1939 3.-irzn.. - 2 - 3. Mr. Consul King maintains that the value of the Shiraz Consulate property has appreciated considerably, but whether this is ^is not so is immaterial to the point at issue which is this Residency r s inability to accede to his request without depriving other Consulates of a portion of their already somewhat inadequate allotments, 4. In vidw of the prevailing financial stringency I find it difficult to ask for an increase in the Central Contract Grant of this Residency. On the other hand, to accord with Lord Halifax’s wishes as expressed in Foreign Office letter No.K#2120/1861/234 of the 25th March which formed an enclosuiB to India Office letter No.P,Z.1962/39 of the 4th April to your address, doubtless the possibility of granting such an increase will receive the sympathetic consideration of the Government of India. 5. A copy of this letter is being sent to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran,and to His Majesty’s Consul, Shiraz. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your moat obedient servant, 3d/- T.C. Fowle, Political Re afrit in the Persian Gulf.© COPY. ’ ~ 'is “V Brit i sh C on sulat e, 4593 I Shirs '- No. 1S4/10/S/15. -t'tf h April, 1939. Sir, I have the honour to request that you will recomnend to the Government of India that a substantial increase be made in the allowance allotted from your Central Contract Grant for annual ordinary or petty repairs at this Consulate. 24th, 1939, a copy of which was forwarded to you under printed letter No.54/10/2/15 of January 24th, 1939, I pointed out that the present state of decay and delapidation of these buildings was evidently in part attributable to a lack of funds for petty repairs over a number of years. Now after a quarters experience at this post I find that I have had to spend the sum of nine pounds, or nearly two on urgent minor and temporary repairs alone. In other words after merely patching up the main buildings in any one quarter I should have remaining for the heavy annual recurring charges of painting, whitewashing and varnishing, replastering and renovation of mud roofs and walls, besides repairs to storerooms, outhouses, stables, garage, yards, £ 6. Rs.80. paths and drive, the sum of six pounds or Rupees eighty per quarter, which is ludicrous. 2. In my despatch to the Foreign Office No.10 of January Rs.200. thirds of my quarterly allowance of Rupees Two hundred, 3. It may be suggested that repairs during the winter rains The Hon|ble the Political Resident and His Majesty 1 s Consul-General, in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.rains are heavier than in summer and that the March quarter expenditure is not a fair guide for the whole year. On examining my predecessors’ accounts however I see that on the contrary the ravages of white ants in summer far outstrip in expense the damage caused by rain. 4. In looking into the method of assessment of my allowance I find an increase is long overdue on that account alone. On April 8th, 1918 in a despatch (No.705 Est.B) addressed by the Secretary to the Government of India to the Deputy Political Resident at Bushire the arrangements for the execution of public works in the Persian Gulf were revised and the allowance for annual or ordinary repairs at Shiraz was fixed at Rupees eight hundred and seventy or 2$ of the capital cost of the property, which at the time of its purchase in 1901 was Rupees Porty three thousand three hundred and five. Out of this amount however the sum of Rupees Seventy or approximately 10% has from the outset been retained annually at your Residency as a contribution towards a reserve fund from which to assist, in the words of the Deputy Political Resident’s memorandum No.11/330 of February 23rd, 1920, 'any of the sub-offices requiring funds over and above their allotments for urgent repairs in any one year'. So far this office does not appear to have drawn on this fund but it seems to me likely to have to do so in the current year. 5. Thus for the last twenty one years a sum of Rupees eight hundred has been paid to this Consulate (except in 1938 when it was reduced by 23^} for annual charges and petty repairs without any account having been taken of the increase in the cost of living (300$ as against a 200$ dropTs.42,000. - 3 - drop in the rate of exchange) or of the increasing antiquity of these buildings entailing heavier repair bills year by year. 6. it the time of the original assessment Lieut.Colonel Hotson, His Majesty T s Consul, doubted whether in view of the inferior material and workmanship of the Shiraz buildings a Z c jo allowance on the original capital value would p¥Qve sufficient and by 1927, as was anticipated, Mr.Chick found it had become inadequate and brought the matter to the notice of the Bushire Residency in a despatch dated September 17th, 1927. An allowance of Rupees One thousand was then recommended but apparently was never sanctioned, and from that date onwards in spite of the subterfuges to which my predecessors have had to resort to maintain the buildings in any sort of proper repair, general neglect became inevitable. 7. To remedy this state of affairs I suggest that the allowance be re-assessed on the present day value of this property which fortunately for the Government of India has greatly appreciated. Taking as a basis the price obtained in 1934 for the adjoining garden of 10 acres (Bagh-i-Shaikh) formerly occupied by the Indo-European Telegraph Department, namely Forty two thousand tomans, reckoning the area of the Consulate grounds to be 7 acres and allowing for a 50$ rise Ts.45,000. Rs.75,000. in internal prices since 1934, the figure of Forty five thousand tomans or Rupees Seventy five thousand is obtained. This corresponds closely with the figure given by an Italian architect in 1936 who put a replacement value on this Ts. 47,675. property of Forty seven thousand six hundred and seventy five tomans. ! 8. On this estimate the allowance would be Rupees One thousandthousand five hundred which, again allowing for a 50$ rise in prices, is approximately the amount recommended by the Assistant Engineer, Persian Gulf Sub-Division in his report of May 5th, 1934, and which under present circum stances I consider would be adequate, and I therefore earnestly request that the Government of India be asked to sanction this amount with effect from April 1st of this year. Anything less will surely result in the continued and rapid deterioration of this otherwise valuable property. 9. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Foreign Office for information. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, (Sd.) A.H. KBIG H.M. Consul.E x v f t PZ Pz. y Hie Under 3ecret/iry to the Oovernwent of India in tne lixternai Affairs ^©yTirtiflont, To - The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Qulf. Memorandum No, F. 122-V39, e, ;Jated jimla, the ^ ^ July 1939, Reforence your letter No. 865, dated the 24th June 1939, 2* Before considering the question of increasing the Chiras Uonaulate allotment umar Central Contract Grant, the (rovernmtmt of India wuld prefer to await the x outcome of the auggostion unde to tiie India Office that Hie Majesty’s Govarment should take over the responsi bility for the maintenance of tiie Coneulate buildings with affect from the next financial year, vide this Department endorsement Jo.?. 122-i/39, dated the 7th June 1939. As reg’iTds the currant year, it is presumed that additional funds will be allotted to His Majesty’s Consul at Ghiraa as suggested in this Jepurtraont Merao- randua No.P. 112-v/39, dated the 7th June 1939* ki/- C«IUi*,&gt;iuniat Under Secretary to the Grovernraant of India#^*No. K 7982/1861/234 In any further communication on this subject, please quote and address— not to any person by name Foreign Office. but to— The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, S.W.l London, S.W.l. 17th July, 1939* Sir, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to refer to India Office letter No. P.Z.3699/39 of the 20th June concerning the Consular premises at Shiraz and to state for the information of the Secretary of State for India that in Lord Halifax’s view it is desirable to allow the question of the transfer of this property to remain in abeyance pending a settlement of the general position regarding Consular representation in Iran. 2. It would follow, if the Secretary of State for India concurs, that the Government of India would continue for the time being to provide the funds necessary for the maintenance. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant The Under-Secretary of State India Office.(NOE* 8 * irff FILE COPY 1 No*. F. 122-i/39. 00 From \^ v To The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, LOUD ON 31.;*1, Dated Simla, the 7^ (0&gt;i ' /u Ksf June 1939. OHIHAZ CONSULATE BUILDINGS . Sir, With reference to your letter No* P.Z.1962/39, dated the 4th April 1939 and subsequent correspondence ending with Shiraz Consulate Despatch to Bushire, No. 164/10/2/15, dated the 4th April 1939 (received with RECd. POL. DEPt. 14JUN1939 INDIA OFFICE necessary action is being taken to provide additional funds to the Shiraz Consulate for carrying out urgent repairs to the Consulate buildings. In this connection, I am to say that the present practice whereby the Government of India arrange for provision of funds for I repairs to the Shiraz Consulate buildings appears to be anomalous for the following reasons (a) The Shiraz post is under the control of His —rfife.jesty t s Government* (b)2 (b) The buildings are at present used exclusively by His Majesty T s Consul and a proposal to transfer them to His Majesty , s Government on payment of the capital cost (less amount already borne by them) is under consideration, vide correspondence ending with India Office letter to the Foreign Office, No* P*Z.6260/36, dated the 25th September 1936. As there is every likelihood of the buildings being eventually transferred to His Majesty T s Government - vide Foreign Office letter dated 13th June 1935 received under the India Office endorsement No* P.Z.4237/1935 of the 21st June 1935, the Government of India are of the opinion that their maintenance including the pay and other charges of the two gardeners costing about Rs* 700/- annually should be taken over by His Majesty r s Government„ subject to the condition that so long as the present system of sharing the expenditure in Iran and the Persian Gulf is in force, a moiety of these charges will be borne by the Government of India* I am to request therefore that if the Secretary of State has no objection. His Majesty f s Government may be approached to take over the responsibility for the maintenance of the Shiraz Consulate buildings with effect from the 1st April 19:40 I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant for Secretary to the Government of India* Vo* 3699 From - The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushir 1939 To - The Secretary to the Government of External Affairs Department, New Delhi. Memorandum No. 622 - 28/57 Dated the 5th May, 1939 Original works in and Special Repairs to the Shiraz Consulate Buildings. I forward herewith copies of letters Nos. 34/10/2/15 dated the 14th January, 1939, and 95/10/2/15 dated the 18th February, 1939, from Kis Majesty's Consul, Shiraz, furnishing estimates for urgent special repairs and original works which he proposes to carry out during the current financial year. 2. The reasons for the omission of these estimates from the budget estimates for 1939-40 are explained in his letter of the 18th February above quoted. 3. I would request that, in view of the explanation proffered by His Majesty's Consul for the omission, the Government of India may be pleased to accord sanction, as a. special case, to the execution of the repairs enumerated in column 1 of the estimate and to provide funds for the purpose during the current year. In this connection I would refer you to India Office letter No. P.5. 1962/39, da/ted the 4th April, 1939, and attached correspondence, to your address, copies of which were sent to me under cover of India Office Printed Letter No. P.5. 1962 of the same date.'N. . 1939 j 4. The estimate ander the head 'Original Dorics * may Be ignored as it will be included in the estimates for the year 1940-41# SdA for Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf •I Tom - The Under secretary to tip GaY«rn?aent wf India in the External Affaire I^epartment* To - Tho Kon'ble the political lie aidant in the Persian haasraadma Ho. F. 122-A/M. Dated JiifUa, the June 1939. i^farsnoe your Metooranduti lie. 622-26^37» dated the 5th tiny 1539. 2. In the circii-ia'.rjiuca explained, the Oowmtaant of India art pleased to accord sanction to the execution of 1. Re-di e ^inti of wells f v&gt;V o 5 2.Renewal of oeiliiiK of Gonaul’a office. 3. Betilia^ of Consul*8 bath-rooto 4* He •laying flooru of a own &amp; table and yard »• 5. Re dots to aiid-roofe of sWule^i, sex'vaiita* c^uartere. .aotor i^arfi^e axia verandah of min bui Idxnp' - - — ^ 600 500 1,500 .400 the epteial repairs to the Shiraz Coiisulate buildii^s detailed in the mar^n at an estimated coat of liials 5,500/- (Five thousand five hundred) or Rs. 920/- (Rupees nine iumdred find twenty) approximate ly. The expenditure is uiviaxbie in moieties between the Governaent of India and Hie ;jajeety*8 Ooverncoent. It is requested tliat every endeavour my be made to allot the necessary funds from your total sanctioned grant for the current year. 3. A reference io invited to the correspondence noted in tne margin, copies of which have been sent to you direct. It is reco^nifsed that the reduction made by you in the Central Contract Grant for dhira* in 1938-39 was nece«8iated by the economy cut imposed by the Government of India, but as His Majesty *3 Consul was obliged to incur expenditure amounting to £ t/17/8 (ei^it pounds seventeen aMllij\^ aixi eid^t i) Aniraz Consulate Despatch to the Foreign Office, No. 10, dated the 24th January 1939. ii) Shiraz Consulate Despatch to the Toreii Office, No. 16, aateu the ,h:d April l r2 eigtt penco) on certain essential repairs to the Consulate building frou hia own pocket, it is corjBidt?red Uiat i.he amount ohoula now be roixubursed to him. It is recjuested that the liability my bo met from your budget for the current year. / 3* In vie^ of the lump cut of Ha. 10,000/- made under ♦Contir^enoies • in the Busliire Residency budget for 1939-^10, it is prenumoa that a proportionate reduction has been made in the current year also in the annual allotment of He* 600/- for bhirat from the Central Contract ^ant* If so, it is requested timt every endeavour my kindly be laide, by the curtailment ot orponditure olae^herc, to allot the full sum of He, 800/- to tiiirae, in view of the unsatisfactory condition of the Consulate builain^Li, 4. A copy of this Department letter to the India Office, Ho. F. 122-4/39, dated the June 1959, is bein^ enaorsed to you Reparately. 5d/- G.K.3. Saraa, Under 3ecretfury to the Ooverastni of India. Copy to the Accountant General # Central Revenues,(161/10/2/15) Ko.16. British Consulate, [ Shiraz, 19.5!-^ * April, 1939. ^ith reference to paragraph 4 of my despatch (^lc Z v ?o* 10 of January 24th,^.939, regarding the lack of fuijC* for petty repairs at *Vb Consulate, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a statement tei r'-*d dinars seventy Incurred and paid for by ms ir aspect of urgent petty repairs during the quarter ended March 31s*,1939« 2* None of these repairs could have been neglected without risk of structural damage or without danger to hoalth, except item 9 which I nevertheless considered necessary as the old screen which the new matting replaced was ragged and greon with age and constituted a most unsightly object at t^e very entrance to the Consulate grounds* 3* I therefore ven*ui^ to request tha* X -.ay be autii^ized * 0 charge the cb—? amount to the Foreign Office in my accounts for the current deducted from the amount I am called upon to contribute for the maintenance of these buildings* 4* I have obtained vouchers for each item of Rls.710.70 of expenses amounting to Klals Seven hundred and £8.17.8 quarter or that Its oterling equivalent o f Eigh t pot r* -1 seventeen shillings and e pence be His Majesty’s expenditure shown on the enclosed statement, which Principal r&gt;cretsry of State for Foreign Affairs, can Foreign Office, ’'.'/•l.•If! n.s* can be forwarded If required. 5. As regards ♦he inadequacy of the funds for pe*ty repalri this Consulate, even when available, I am addref'.xng a separate despatch to His ajesty^ Consul- General at Bushire, a copy of which I will transmit to yeu in due co rse. 6. A copy of this daspatch is being sent to His ^ajesty’n Consul General at ^ushire for information* Z have f he honour be, fir, Your roost obedient, humble Servant, Sd, A.H.King H*^.Consul* COPY. K 5275/1861/234) No. 17 (165/10/2/15) His Majesty's Consul at Shiraz presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit to him the under mentioned documents for information. British Consulate, Shiraz. 4th April, 1939. Reference to previous correspondence : Shiraz despatch No. 16 of 3rd April 1939. Inscription of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Copy of despatch No* 164/10/ 2/15 of 4th April, 1939 to the Fu:- &gt;r Hon’ble the Political Petty Reparis. Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.3. It may be suggested that repairs during the v/inter rains are heavier than in summer and that the March quarter expenditure is not a fair quide for the whole year. On examining my predecessor 1 s accounts however I see that on the contrary the ravages of white ants in summer far outstrip in expense the damage caused by rain. 4. In looking into the method of assessment of my allowance I find an increase is long overdue on that account alone. On April 8 th, 1938 in a despatch (No. 705 Est.B) addressed by the Secretary to the Government of India to the Deputy Political Resident at Bushire the arrangements for the execution of public works in the Persian Gulf were revised and the allowance for annual or ordinary repairs at Shiraz was fixed at Rupees Eight hundred and seventy or 2% of the capital cost of the property, which at the time of its purchase in 1901 was Rupees Forty three thousand three hundred and five. Out of this amount however the sum of Rupees Seventy or approximately 10^o has from the outset been retained annually at your Residency as a contribution towards a reserve fund from which to assist, in the words of the Deputy Political Residents memorandum No. 11/330 of February 23rd, 1920,'any of the sub-offices requiring funds over and above their allotments for urgent repairs in any one year'. So far this office does not appear to have drawn on this fund but it seems to me likely to have to do so in the current year. 5. Thus for the last twenty one years a sum of Rupees eight hundred has been paid to this Consulate (except in 1938 when it was reduced by 23%) for annual charges and petty repairs without any account having been taken of the increase in the8./ - cost of living (300% as against a 200 % drop in the rate of exchange) or of the increasing antiquity of these buildings entailing heavier repair hills year by year. 6 . At the time of the original assessment Lieut. Colonel Hotson, His Majesty*s Consul, doubted whether in view of the inferior material and workmanship of the Shiraz buildings a 2% allowance on the original capital value would prove sufficient and by 1927, as was anticipated, Mr. Chick found it had become inadequate and brought the matter to the notice of the Bushire Residency in a despatch dated September 17th, 1927. An allowance of Rupees One thousand was then recommended but apparently was never sanctioned, and from that date onwards in spite of the subterfuges to which my predecessors have had to resort to maintain the buildings in any sort of proper repair, general neglect became inevitable. 7. To remedy this state of affairs I suggest that the allowance be re-assessed on the present day value of this property, which fortunately for the Government of India has greatly appreciated. Taking as a basis the price obtained in 1934 for the adjoining garden of 10 acres (Bagh-i-Shaikh) formerly occupied by the Indo-European Telegraph Department, namely Forty two thousand tomans, reckoning the area of the Consulate grounds to be 7 acres and allowing for a 50% rise in internal prices since 1934 the figure of Forty five thousand tomans or Rupees Seventy five thousand is obtained. This corresponds closely with the figure given by an Italian architect in 1936 who put a replacement value on this property of Forth seven thousand six hundred and seventy five tomans.8 . On this estimate the allowance would he Rupees One thousand and five hundred which, again allowing for a 50% rise in prices, is approximately the amount recommended hy the Assistant Engineer, Persian Gulf Sub-Division in his report of May 5th, 1934, and which under present circumstances I consider would he adequate, and I therefore earnestly request that the Government of India he asked to sanction this amount v/ith effect from April 1st of this year. Anything less will surely result in the continued and rapid deterioration of this otherwise valuable property. 9. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Foreign Office for information. I have, etc. (Signed) A. H. King. H.M.Consul</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00008c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3578</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00008c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3578</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/21 'Shiraz: consulate buildings'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-20T22:02:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (126 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 128; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns maintenance of the British Consulate buildings at Shiraz.The file covers:descriptions and budget for works and repairs to the buildings in 1931, and 1935electric workslease of property at Shiraz for the use of Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, in 1938descriptions and budget for works and repairs in 1939-40, and 1940-41repairs to the buildings in 1948.The file is composed of correspondence between the Foreign Office, the India Office, the Government of India, the British Consulate at Shiraz, the British Legation at Tehran, and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consulate</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Diplomatic service</topic></subject><subject><topic>British</topic></subject><subject><topic>Consular services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Building maintenance</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00008c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>