<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00033a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T13:23:51.562Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Telegram - P. From Beaidciit, Buohire To Political, Bahrein No.417 Bated &amp; Rcd./tand April 1928. At any cost please find out v/hat Bin Hathlain’s plans and actions are.Trancslation of a lot t or iio. M/7/2^ # dated the 5th Shawwal 1^46 (57-^-1928) from HIe ^lajorty al-Inara Sir •Abdul •Aziz bin *Abdur Ra^raan al-i'aiBal aa-Sa'ud, King of Hijaz, Najd and ^opondoncioc to tiie iionVblo Colonol L*B.Ho Haworth, Political Heeident 1 n tlio x '9 rw i an Gulf. After ^orapliraonte. Vo bog to acknowledge the receipt of your letter Ho. 93-C,, datod the 20th Kaaadhan (12-^-1928) connunicated to you by the British Govornraent in reply to our letter flatod 27th Blia’ban (i»e. 19-2-28) (we think you mean yth bha'ban i.e. ^ 0 - 1 - 28 ) in wliioh we protected againet the announce- raent of tlie f lraq Governnent that they intend to raid our country.In r^ply to which (your letter) we repeat our regret for the pains und troubles which we experience as a result of the lines of action of the tlraq Government and the action of eorae of British Officials there (in •Iraq). And we are surprised to see (re?.d) you inform (us ) in your letter that the operations of the British aeroplanes were only to pursue tin actual raiders and warn persons who threaten to raid (however the pursuing of criminals within our lands and threatening them there is a principle against which we protest and which we cannot accept). The fact is not so, and it appears that the news given to the British Government about the action of their aeroplanes is not correct, ^'he persons who raided ‘Iraq is the Uawisli with a few Mutairs but the aeroplanes did not pursue the Da wish and did not go to him and those who participated with iiira (in the raids) but have borabed our boundwpy (as we mentioned to you before) along the line and have mingled the criminal with innocent. They (aeroplanes) have thrown their bombn on our troops who are keeping a watch on the frontier, on the north&amp; ^ 2 north-weet 1'or tho protection of f Iraq. Wo roquoet tlie gritlwh ^ovommont to cause enquiries to be nade in this respect wliich had a bad effect on the good relations between the two Kama*, countries and which had added to our great difficult!ei *3 said in one of our provious letters that strong bande (parties) at a result of the action of the aeroplanes hav^ gone down towards Hraq and this is what .ve w$re afraid arould 2iappen* w e isoued our orders to Sultan bin Bijad one of the ooraT?ander8 of our arrsy to go to the reiders and pursu^.de then th return but after he had left we still were not asax: confident, and have therefore e-mt an Amir of our Royal family that is Sa’ud bin 'Andul # Aziz ae-Sa’ud to follow the raiders and purou^de then! to return* In view of the importance of the critical situation 0 at the front!or we prefer to go ourselves aft«r a few c days towards the north in order to take prudent action and convince the Najd people, who all wish to face oneraity with enenity, to wait and suspend hostilities (become quiet) until we settle this matter by negotiations with the British viov^mment. We want to assure the British Ciovernment that we have no pretext to convince the wajd people witl^so that they may wait, except our promise to * f them that their four Just demands which we asked from the British Uovernraent in our letter No* M/7/23 dated l-^th Ranadhan (8*3-38) will be carried out; and wo hope from our friend the British Government that they win get us justice from t : ose who caused the breach of the undertakin s by taking a decisive action which will prevent any further similar breach soConfidtntial Ho. C/ (2~^ of 1928. The Political agency, Bahrein, 8th April 1928. To The Secretary to the Political Resident in the Peruian Gulf, Bushire. Himorandum. Reference my telegram Ho.121 dated the 4th April 1928. I forward the original letter dated the 7th Shawal received from Bin Saud, together with its translation. Political Agent .Bahrein* V Translation of letter date d 7th Shauwal 1^46= 29-3-28, from His Majesty Abdul Aziz bin Abdur Ralinan al-l’aisal ae-sa’ud, ...0.1.7., King of llija: IT a jd and Depondencier to the Hon'bio Co lonal Haworth, E.B.M's Political Roaident in tl^e Persian Gulf, Bahrein. After Compliments, &lt;?9 We have received your letter i»o. 98 dated 23rd Ramadlian 1746= 15-3-28 in which you inform that as a result of our letters to his majesty's Government sent through, you and the Representative of H.Kls Government at Jeddah ihs Excellency Sir Gilbert Clayton has been appointed by H.Ll’s Governmoit to interview us for settlement of the present difficulties. I like you to inform H.M’s Govemmn t of our gratitude fcr their giving consideration to our point of view in matters in which we are concerned ard to inform them that we also receive their desire t'oc the settlement ol’ the questions in the same spirit and that we are doing cvr best to effect a settlement of the natters which, have cropped up from old affairs and about which we have informed you in our previous letter. We agree to the proposal of H.M’s Government };hat our interview with His Excellency Sir Bilbert Clayton should take place in Jeddah. We hope that the interview will come off on the first of Dhul Qa'da! Wo request you to Inform II.M's Government of this 9 reply from us, we also will inform H.h’s Reprerentativ&lt; at Jeddah. U.E.Coftfidtntial . Ho.C//Zr of 1928. The Political Agency, . q 0. April Bahrein, 0 ‘ xBahx*±n 1928. To The Air Staff Intelligence Officer, Air Headquarters, Iraq, Baghdad. Sir, In reply to your telegram Ho.2144 dated the 7th March 1928, I have the honour to enclose a list showing the Hejd population which is likely to obey a summons from Bin Saud. The list shows (a) the settled and (h) the nomad elements. The second column ohov/s the esti mated total population while the third coluran gives the number of men under arms. Every ma.p questioned had his own widely differing estimate of the population and so I cannot state that the figures now given are accurate hut they are an average estimate from information received. The total population of Hasa district is stated to he 200.000 of which two thirds, say 130,000, is Shiah. The population of the qatif District is given at 60,000 out of which at least 5C,000afcd* Shiahi In the unsettled time of the Turks the Shiahs were all armed and ready to resist Bedouin raids at a moment’s notice. The era of peace which ensued on the Saudian conquest has led to the disposal of many of the rifles formerly possessed. It is estimated that not more than 3.000 rifles, many of antiquated pattern, are now in the possession of Qatif Bhiahs. The number of rlCec in the poassesaion of llasa Shiahs willwill ctrtainly not ba moro than 10,000, The fighting • &lt; value of the C&gt;tif and Haaa Shiah io not great. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, * r' Your moetobedient servant, Political Agent,Bahrein. i&amp;i Iki \*0. c /126 of 1026 Political Agency f Bahrain Bated the 6th April 1028 The Political Agent,Bahrain His Majesty Al-Injan Cir Abdul Aziz bin ’Abdur Hahnan al-Paisal ae^Sa'ud a.C.l. •» King of iiijaz Najd and Dependencies. After ConplinentE, I have been dirsctod by the Hon’ble the Political Henident to send Your lajeety the following nercage*- Hie hajeety 'r Oovormaent PtJite tliat they are greate- rul fo r the ^eseage cont ined in lour ajesty’s Ko.h/^/S? of 7th Bhauwal 1846. Sir Gilbert Clayton will proceed to Jeddah, with the leant possible delay It ie improbable however that he can arrive nuch before the end of April. Your Jiajeety will realise that t^e dr.to mentioned i.e. 1st Dhul-.a'dah is rather early seeing that ^ir Gilbert Clayton has to come out from England but every effort will b^&gt; made to insure hio arrival at the earliept posrible nonent. The message ends hero. The last day of April corresponds to 10th stfkfc Dhul^Qn*dah • If.S. From To \ N0.e//jtJ0f 1928. The Political Agenoy. Bahrein 9th April 1928. Copy together with its translation in Arabic* is forwarded to the Secretary to the Political Resident with reference to the Resident’s telegram No.452 dated the Qth April 1920. Political Agent# BahreinI e Telegram - P. Prom Political, Bahrein lo Heoidtiit, Buahire No.1^7 Dated 9th April 1928 It is. reported that bin Plathlain and other Akhwan chiefs with possible excep tion of jjawioh have disT)ersed their for- c,es. In proof of this Beouing are now A bringing ghee for sale into towns where price has fallen from 36 to 26 dollars. Bin Baud has prohibited trade with Trans Jordan. Haesan Q,usaibi just returned from I las a informs me however that ^khv/an are concentrated at Jurat near Bjjraidah where they have been immobilised by Baud A1 Arafah. Bin Baud will leave Riadh on 25th current Arabic month meet the Akhwan chiefs including Bin Hathlain at Buraida^ and thence proceed by Hail and Medina to Jeddah. The whole journey will be performed by motor. I interpret that Bedouin out for loot have left bin Hathlain etc., but chiefs themselves and their personal following are still at Jurat awaiting arrival of Bin Baud.Telegram “ Code Prom Heoidexit, Buchire, To Politica?., Bahrein, No.461 Dated 9th (Red.10th) April 1928. My telegram No.452. Please wire date message v/as despatched Telegram - Code. Prom Political, Bahrein, To Resident, Busnire No. nil Dated 10tn April 1928. Your telegram No.461. Afternoon on 8th April.Telegram - P. From Kesident, Bushire To Political, Bahrein, No. nil Bated 9th (Red.10th) April 1928. Your ttlegraki No . 127 . Pleate repeat word already spelt With J. Telegram - P Ptom Political, Bahrein, To Resident, Buchire No.131. Bated 10th April 1928. Ceginning JurabTelegrion - P. From P.A.Bahrein, To Resident, Buahire Ho•134 Dated 21st April 1928. Han who left Buraidah 6th ^pril states Bin Saud arrived 4 days before / he left, lie met all ^vkiiwan Chiefs except Hurnaid and Dawish, who failed to appear alleging fear. Bin Saud sent ^irafah per sonally to grant them safe conduct. Bin Saud warned those he met against raiding Iraq and stated aeroplanes had inflicted 100 casualties.No. 325-S. CONFIDENTIAL, A ^ ,27) Political Agency, Kuwait, 18th April 1928, To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. M5K0RANDUM. I forward herewith Residency endorsement No,155-3 dated the 15th April 1928, which reached me to-day hy ss. Bandra' together with various other papers in an outer cover addressed to me. Lt•-Col* 9 Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy for information to the Secretary to the Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire*Telegram P. Prom High Commissioner! Baghdad. To Secretary of State for the Colonies, London, No. 197 Bepeated Political Resident, Bushire, ) Covernment of India, Delhi. ) ) No. 71-3. High Commissioner, Jerusalem.; High Commissioner, Cairo. / British Consul, Jeddah. ) Dated 2nd received 3rd April 1928. The concensus of opinion here, based on reports from Kuwait, Bahrain, Iraq, desert tribes and special information received by King Faisal, is that notwithstanding previous rumours of Ibn Saud having stopped raid, IBN HUM AID is about to start or has already started from the neighbourhood of JATvAB, west-north-west of ARTIWIYAH with mixed force consisting principally of ATAIBA with some HARB and AJMAN element. Maximum numbers probably about 3,500. Desert tribes think that the objective is either the desert posts or the ANBZA, but King Faisal is convinced that it is BASRAH, as he says he has good information that HUMAID has sworn to enter Basrah and massacre its inhabitants whether he gets away after or not. Officer Commanding concurs in this telegram. HIGH COMKISSIONKR) BAGHDAD.Telegram Prom To Repeated P. High aonuaissloner, Cairo. secretary of State for Foreign Affairs 9 , v 4 , London, Ho. 194. Jigh Co misoioner, Baghdad, 3 igh i oiumissioner, Jerusalem, , lolitioal Resident, Bushire. British Consul, Jeddah. No. 194. listed 2nd received 3rd April 1928. /tX/U -c Cj Reference your telegram No. 130. HAFIZ HhRkB points out that failure of oon- V -ference totween Sir Gilbert Clayton and Ibn Gaud would » * lead to a vei*y aangerous situation. He thorefore urges that H.A *s. Government should beforehand sympathetically excU’drio tai Jaud*s two principal demands i.e. demolition of desert fortifications and mutual surrender of fugitive criminals, and make every effort to put Clayton in a position to satisfy I bn Gaud on these t»o points. HAFIZ WAHAB was told that we could not express any opinion on these tow points. I do not know to what extent H.M # s. Govem- -ment are able to go on these two issues but it would seem desirable anyhow that they should be very carefully considered before Clayton*3 departure and that the con- -seguences of the failure of the conference should be clearly envisaged. If Clayton’s mission comes off he should be asked to pass through Cairo en route to enable me to explain to him hafiz hshah's point of view.p Telegram From Political ^osiclenti ^uahire. To Secretary of State for Colonies, London, Mo. 75. Repeated Government of India, Mew Delhi,} ) No. 426. High Commissioner, Baghdad, ) ' who is requested to forward copy hy air mail to Jerusalem and Cairo. Dated 3rd April 1928. Article in Urnia al ^.ura of 24th February 1923, published at Decca ana written from Jiadh, states the Nejd case practically in Ibn 3aud f s own words. It twice states that there is no well between the frontier and Busaiyah post, and this is unquestiofcably Ibn Baud f s chief mistake. He also gives intimate details of Busaiyah fort and states it is built so that it can hold at least 140 men. v;ould High Commissioner send on copy of article on receipt from Kuwait.Tolsgram From To I.opoatod Datod 3rd April 1928, My tolegraia flo. 73. Ibn 3aud's latoat letters. He will probably reach Ilasa in a few days and may make snort halt there for enquiries. may expect him to give a date for a meeting to he held in about ten days or fortnight hence. This is perhaps a little optimistic but it is better to bo ready, too soon so that any delay may not be due to us as it will bo getting hot. I think it would be sounder policy to spring on him fact that there are three wells between Busaiyah and frontier and not to xxx write and inform him of fact in advance. K SSIDKNT. P. Political Resident, Bushiro. .Secretary of Btate for tho Colonies, London, No. 76. Government of India, Delhi. High Commissioner, Baghdad. ) High Commissioner, Jerusalem.) Ho. 427. High Commissioner, Cairo. British Consul, Jeddah.Telegram From i o epeatod Ho. 160* Bated Sni received 4Ui April 1928. Secretary of state for the Colonies*, liOndon. j olitical i.osiaent, Jiuahire. High SoKimlssioner, Iraq, Baghdad. Kuwait. Your telegram JIo. 83 of 29th larch. You will understand that my telegram of 27th arch was not intended to tie your hands in the matter of landing parties. Full discretion is left to you in consultation with Air Officer Co sanding, Iraq., to arrange for e re-embarkation as soon as you and he consider that this can safely be done. You will of course recognise tho necessity for acting in close ««« mmdtium consultation with the Air Officer Commanding Iraq in this or any other question concerning the defence of 1 uwait and for consulting him on efich occasion before suUaitting recommendations to me. aKClviZrAiCf OF 6?ATS FOR TER COhOKIBB.2 ^ P. Politloal Agent, Kuwait. secretary of State for the Colonies f Irondon. Political Resident, Buahire. High OonijRiiBSloner, Baghdad. High Coxomissloner, Jerusalem. Ho. 513. Dated 3rd received 4th April 1928. ' I mentioned subject of Bus hi re telegru No. 421 to the Shaikh of Kuwait and he told me that the men referred to in my telegram Ho. 311 heard a rumour in Jaryah, which they did not believe, that I bn Jaud was probably going to Qasia very soon. POLITICAL AGBOT, KUWAIT. '..I ; iTologra© Fraa - f To epoetecl High Ooiiiiniasioner, Cairo. . eorotary of State for Foreign Affairs, . onuon. l;igh Cox^iasioner, Baghdad. iolitical lesident, Buehire. High (onoaisaioner, Jerusalem. iiritish Consult Jeddah. To. 197. Datoa 5ru roooived 4th April 1920 iiafiz Walitoato has received a telegram from ^ bn fcJ aua saying that the latter has no objection to 'operations being suspended whilst negotiations are in 'course” arid that 'Question depends on demolition of forts ana two clauses connected therewith.* Hafiz ahab is not sure what is meant by 'the two clauses”, ibn Haud adds tiiat details are following uy ( post ?}• The King 9 s telegram was despatched before he could have received the invitation to meet Cir Gilbert Clayton.Telegram Trow To vQpeatod Political 7\esiclent Mo. 505. rated 5rd received 4th Kpril 1928 Political Tiesident, Buchire. In accordance with your telegram Mo. 1100 or 50th Parch the following Joint report is submitted. It io not considered that the Jehad is mentioned in henior Naval Officer’s 2551 of larch 50th area is closely watched by air reconnaissance. A raid of this description can in no way be interpreted as Jehad. ;ir Officer Commanaing, Baghdad, in his message to Oommander in Chief, 72ast Indies, of 20th March, and of Benior 'aval Officer’s subsequent prpposals contained in his telegram Mo. 2000 of 24th Parch to Political Resident, which latter were most definitely concurred in by Politic- -al resident in his telegram Ho. 76-T to the iolitioal rigent, Auwait, it is not considered that there is any justification for retaining naval landing parties ashore at Kuwait. Mhis confirms the opinion expressed in Benior Naval Officer’s telegram No. 957 of 29th Parch to Commander in Chief, Rast Indies. The landing of these parties has immobilised the whole of the I ersian ::ulf Squadron for five weeks and consequently it is impossibl&lt; to obtain information on the state of affairs on the Trueial coast so expressly desired by Political Uesiaent in his telegram No. 1—T of 9th Parch and repeated to Commandor in Chief, Mast Indies. likely to take place. The reports of possible raids and 1915 of April 1st are not as yet confirmed. The In view of the proposals put forward by No degree of readiness is considered necessarynoceasary boyonu the Xollowin: propoatxl diapoaitione It ia considered politic to retain one sloop at luwait lor the present and for the other sloop to be sent to the /rucial Coaat and on relief hy H.H.6. M SlfTTCu iU:j to return to the .;hatt«*al-Arah. to piocood to badan to complete Kith oiling and lator cruise off tho Trueail Ooast and as required. This will ensure two ships of tho squadron boin^ in close touch with Kuwait* There seems no necessity to • maintain one sloop on the 1 orsian coast for the present* SENIOR NAVAL OFFIC IH, PNKSIAN GULF. Tele&amp;ram Mrom TO repeated No. 507. hated 4th P. Senior Naval Officer, Iorsian Oulf § H.M.G. •3HTKBPEIGS* 9 off Kuwait. Commander in Chief, T:aat Indies station. Political Resident, Bushiro. received bth Larbh 1928. In continuation of my telegram of 3rd vpril, !Io. 305, the situation may now bo considered to have aofinitely oleared and no raida on Kuwait are con- -aldereu likely for the present. 31TOI0B NAVAL 0FF10TJB, PNHS1AN GULF.V ’'ologram From lolitical Agent, Kuwait. To Political J.Qsicient, Bushiro. No. 313. Bated 4th received 5th April 1928. KePerenee i'onior Naval OXTicer’s tolegrama Nos. 305 and 307. I did not agree with the Pormer at the time when it was despatched except as regards question of X?e- -tainlng landing parties ashore, which I Itak look on as one which he can decide best himself, as I considered it premature to relax precautions. In view of your telegrams Nos. 423 and 425, my telegram Ho. 318 and results of recent reconnaissances however I now agree with his telegram No. 307. This being so my views are again those expressed in my telegram of 25th Parch, No. 278. I think however that the restrictions recommended by the enior Naval Officer in his telegram No. 2000 of 24th larch tlicit sloop should not go further than Chatt al Arab or Bushire or cruiser further than Henjam might with advantage bo observed until the danger is definitely past. POLITI0AL AGBHT, KUWAIT.Telegram P. From political Resident, Bushire. To Secretary of State for Colonies , London, Repeated Government of India, Delhi. ) No. 77. High Commissioner, Baghdad, j High Commissioner, Jerusalem,) No. 433. High Commissioner, Cairo, British Consul, Jeddah. ) Dated 5th April 1928. Kuwait telegram No. 316. Ito 3aud evidently means in his letter, of which I cabled summary in my telegram No. 73, that he is proceeding to KA3IM, in which case my telegram No. 76 is beside the mark. RNSIhSNTTele&amp;raia :rom To No. 454. Dated 5th April 1958. i:. Political eaiaentf Bushire. ;ir &lt; Tficor, ’omi/iandingt l^achdad. r^eraron oq Kuwait tolo^raxa No. 518. Senior Daval Offioer consider*} and I olitic- 1 -al lcent, Kuwait, concurs tl^at there is no imrnodiato danger or raids. Political Agent suggests reversion to previous plan or Bonier Naval officer of keeping sloops in I orth and oruiaor in Persian 3ulf with only one sloop actually at Kuwait. ;enior Uaval officer considers one sloop could go as far as Truoial Ooast until relieved by - which will oil at Abadan, ould you let ae know your views ? Au it is now 14 h&amp;wal ana as there is no suggestion of gathoring of the tribes situation is no longer affected by Kaaaaan. .Telo&amp;raizi 'Tom TO ' ,r o, 435. iatou oth April 1928. iolitical osidont, Bushira. onior |’aval ffioor, I oral an uir. • •^ ; # # off Kuwait. , lour telegram dated 3rd April. a hero la ao Question of my concurrence to relaxation of deienalve measux'oa propoaed. I concurred in my telegram Ho. 76-T to i olitical Agent, Kuwait, and I confirmed it in my telegram Bo. 3Si to you.Telegram Hlgk ?omialaaioner, Baghdad* Docretary of ntato for &gt;olonlee f Tondon ~ w ‘;or*£05. i.epeated lolltical oaidont, Buahire. High Somaiaaionert Cairo. } l^tod 6th received at 7th April 1926 Bushire telegram of April 5th , : o. 73. Heading together the letter dated arch 17th from lafiz ^ahaha, sent to Foreign Office with in Ihn Jaud*s letter now received *he is grateful to Kis 'ajcsty•a Government for considering his view point” I destruction of desert posts, etc., imve boon aoceptod as is challenged at once Clayton may be met by an assertion similar to that desoribod on page 32 of Clayton’s ©port (riddle ^st f Ho. 7) regarding KAF, namely that the King has pacified his tribesmen by informing thorn that T iio lajosty’s Cfovornment have accepted his demands and that to retreat from this position will damage his x^rostige and make his pcx&gt;P^® believe that tho British Covemiuont has broken faith. I suggest that when informing tfftafyxam ion Saua that Clayton will proceed to Jeddah as proposed it should bo made porfoctl; Lloyd’s despatch of larch 23rd, Ko. 262, and the sentence fear there is no doubt that he is rosorting to the time honoured device of oriental diplomacy of assuming bofore the conference that all his principal demands, such as thep a preliminary to tho conference. Unless this position fis ffiajesty^ Government nor Iraq hi -liminary condition wliatever.Telo&amp;ram p, ^°® lolitieal A^ont, Kuwait* Political Beuidontf Buatiire* !*o* ZQZ* Bated and received 7th April 1923 # The Shaikh of Kuwait will be very grateful 101 anything you can do to expedite Lewis guns and machine guns. His men under instruction are shaping well and ha now has the opportunity of taking into his service two really well trained ex-Levy Arabs, but before doing so he wants to know that there is a chanoe of getting his own weapons reasonably soon. The foregoing is with reference to your telegram to Secretary of State for the Colonies, no. Sd, last paragraph. POLITICAL AGKIFT, KUWAIT* Telegram p # Brom ]olitical Resident, Bushire* Political Agent, Kuwait. To. 4B0* Bated 7th April 1928. &amp; I am awaiting reply from Government of lnd.ii regarding price. This refers to your telegram No. 322. RKSIDKNT.Telegram From To .6p&lt;3&amp;tad 1 . High u'oimals^loner 9 Cairo• jeorotar^ of Ctato for Foreiijn Affairs• ^ ^ London,tox High Comiiiissioner, Baghdad. lolitical Bsaldentf -duyohiro. High CofiUftld8ioner» JoruaalQja. l^ritioh Conaul, Jeddah. ::o. aoB. l;atod Vth received dth April 192d. fiagliaad deapatoh ho# 314 to oecretary of tato for the Oolonios. 1 have repeatedly told Hafiz Wahato ttiat I tiave no information whatever and can give no opinion in regard to Ifcn ^ud # s partioular deoign# whioh muot he lol't lor diacusalon with Clayton ( sao o.g. ants ponultlm- -ats paragraph of ay talograa of April 2na, lio. 194). '■'i^at talagraa allows that up to April 2nd liafla iahab hla- -aelf was under no lllxmlon and waa still urging ua to make concessions to Idn :)aud*8 aamanda. He therefore oannot be under the impression that any of Ibn Saud's { demands have been accepted as a preliminary to the confer* -ence. His letter of March 17th merely expresses his satisfaction that H.K's. Covornnont have agreed to what he had urged so strongly viz. a conference between I bn 3aud and 3ir Gilbex't Clay ton or any other delegate not from Iraq or the Iersian Gulf. Cn the face of it the phrase of Ibn :&amp;ud # s letter -ho is grateful to H.f• a. Gov -emmont for considering his vievii point' may be merely a courteous response to the first sentence of H.f 9 s. &lt;ovoBn- •ment f s message ( vide your telegram r;o. 130). However# if you still think it advisable, ^ could make some taxftn intimation in writing to Hafiz ahab in any form you may wish to indicate and confirming the fact that neither Ell v s« Goremment nor Iraq have accepted any conditions whatsoever beX'oro the conference. LLOYDTolograia From P Air OlTioer Commanding, Baghdad. To Political Bosldontf Bushiro. NO. 2244. Dated 7th received 8th April 1928. Your telegram of 5th April, No. 434. Although we have no definite ne.-s that the ATAIBAH have abandoned their intention to raid and have dispersed I agree that the ships at Kuwait can he reduced to one sloop and aenior Naval Officer's pre- -vious plan can he reverted to. AIB OFFICER COMMANDING, BAGHDAD. Repeated on 9th April as follows Secretary of State for the Colonies, London, No. 81. Government of India, Hew Delhi, No. 456.Telegram From r. Commander in Chief, East Indies Station. To Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated Air Officer, Commanding, Baghdad. S.H.O.P.G., w EOT 3KPRIS E ^ , off Kuwait. No. 1215. Dated 8th received 9th April 1928. With reference to Joint report in Senior Naval Officer’s message of 3rd April, No. 2004, Admiralty inform me that there is no objection to withdrawal of naval landing parties at Kuwait and redistribution of ships proposed by Senior Naval Officer provided Resident, after consultation with Air Officer Commanding, B&amp;ghaad, concurs. Ilequost information as to whether concurrence can now be given. COLANDER IN CHIEF, EAST INDIES STATION. repeated to Govemxoant of India under Kosiaont's Ho. 464, dated 10th April 1928.Telegram P. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Secretary oi* State for Colonies, London, No. 82. repeated . Government of India, Delhi, No. 457. AiM- Dated 9th mesh 1928. Your telegram No. 160. Please see Air Officer Commanding’s tele- -gram o• 2244, which was answer to my query on subject. It seems most unlikely that attack will now take place but if tribes begin to move we should have ample news of Xkxxr their intention. Also Ibn Gaud will have seen them and presumably he would now himself warn us • if their intentions seemed hostile. Thus as long as one sloop remains at Kuwait and the other in the north of the Gulf with the cruiser within 24 hours recall I think we can with safety agree to dispersion of Navy from Kuwait if you agree. On receipt of more definite satisfactory hjo nov/s these restrictions can be removed. RGoIDENT*z\ Jolltioal r.eaidantt BusUlrti* Cionior Kavr&gt;l OXYioer, '•OT ; a-Ua ;•*, off, Kuwait• No. 459. Dated 9th April 192a. I have telegraphed Secretary or atate for the 'olonloa recoaEiending on the lines of your previous QDf^oation that one sloop resiains at i uwaiti other north of Ouir and *cruiolne within ran^;© of recall. Cn reoelYiag reply 1 will inform aommander in CThief, aat Indies f repeating to you. CJould you then make it convenient to coao to Bus hire on route Prom Ahaclan ? I should like if possible to have opportunity to discuss air route with you. JmiiY-OT.Telegram p. Trom oecretary of State for Colonies, London. To Political resident, Bushire* I^epeated High Commissioner, Baghdad. Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 166. Dated 9th received 10th April 1928. After consulting me Admiralty have address- -od following telegram, No. 434, dated April 7th, to Commander in Chief, Nast Indies Station, repeated to Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, begins. 'Your 1409/S. No objection to withdraw- . -al of naval landing party from Kuwait and redistribution of ships as proposed by Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, || in his telegram No. 2004/3 provided Resident, after con- *f -sultation with Air Officer Commanding, Baghdad, agrees H 'nds. SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE COLONIES. Repeated to Government of India under Resident's. No. 463, dated 10th April 1928. J.C.Code (§) S3 ' i Telegram jj'rom To Hepeated Pollticalf .Kuwait Secretary of State for the Colonies* London he sident* sushire Hlghooma* Baghdad &amp; Highcoma* Jerusalem ho* Bated (&amp; received) the 10th April 1928* het&amp;iner of the ^haiich of Kuwait* believed to be reliable* who left hiyauh on blst Larch arrived here yesterday evening (honuay)* He confirms report that Baud al-AT&amp;fah was sent after Xbn Kumaid to tzy and prevent raids* ana says that he sent a letter to Ibn Baud to the effect that he had arranged meeting between him (Ibn Baud) and Ibn Humaid and Bawlsh to tahe place outside Buraidah on 4th April* and that the latter two had undertaken to give up raiding and obey his instructions if Xbn Baud m I 1 ! i would agree to their demands* He did not hear what these ds 1 demands were# When he left iiiyadh Ibn Baud was preparing to leave for Buraidah arid a convoy of about 30 cars was being got ready* It was thought that Ibn baud would (go) straight on to Hedjaz if everything passed off satisfactori ly at meeting* but not otherwise#Telegram P. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. 'ENTERPRISE**, off Kuwait. I.epeatifcd _ No. 465. Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. No. 84. Government of India, Delhi. Air Officer Commanding, Baghdad,) No. 465. Political Agent, Kuwait. ; Dated 10th April 1928. Reference Admiralty telegram No. 434 I concur. RESIDENTp. Political Kesident, Bushlre. Gacretai-y of State for the Oolonioa, London, No, 85 Government of India, New Delhi. High Comnissloner, Baghdad. ) Flgh Commissioner, Jerusalem.) No. 468. High Commissioner, Cairo. ) April 1928. Cairo telegram Ho. 205. I trust the following observations will not be considered beyond my province. I feel assured that I bn Gaud is even more anxious for peace than we are. Present unsettled con- -ditiona contain seed of danger to him and I am certain that a mixture of sympathy with firmness will produce result that we require. But it is necessary that neither wo nor he should forget that origin of trouble was tiio attack on Gusaiyah and that he is quite wrong in ids belief that no wells exist between that place and the frontier. Thus the whole groundwork of his contention is without foundation and he lias no right to object to the existence of the fort or to demand its not being occupied. Its destruction now might be misunderstood. While we desire that Ibn Gaud should rule and should control his tribes we cannot forget that he, and still more so his tribes, are Orientals and that therefore if we find it assists our object to meet him in any way ( for instance that the fort should not bo occupied to enable him to show that he can control his tribes) it is nocessary that he should completely realise that it is a friendly gift from our strength to strengthen him for our common object and not a concession through weakness or a desire to placate tribes of whom we are afraid. Telegram From To . .ep ea t od La ted 10 th IasasMa^dSatSBBWBH mmm (&amp; SL I have been, strongly atjainat any crossing of his frontier for punishment of tribes until I bn :;aud himself had failed mainly because 1 considered this policy was wrong as policy unless wo wore forced to it by cognate circumstances but also because I realised that it assisted Ibn Hand to obscure the main issue viz, his own responsib ility towards us. As long as we desire to hold him responsib le for Arabia it is necessary for us to strengthen him not to weaken him, but in doing so we must pin him to the underlying groundwork of omr policy which, r.s far as the present issue is concerned, is his responsibility for the actions of his tribes. This line of argument may result in certain modifications on his stating his difficulties but such tiodifications should be to a common end and be clear in fcheir intention. It may also be stressed that raiding is largely economic and part of the normal life of the tribes, thus only man who can prevent it is Ibn Jaud, I still think that a Frontier* Commission of an officer from us and one from I bn 3aud ( which officer from us should not be the Political Agent, Kuwait) to watch the frontier and adjudicate would be worth the money until the frontier becomes more settled. BCSIDKNT. *Telegram From To repeated Fo. 1188• P. Commander in Chief, Fast Indies Station. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.&amp;.3. *'NTFKPHI3E*, off Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire. Admiralty, London. Dated 11th received 12th April 1928. Your telegram of 10th April, No. 2322. Naval force should he re-embarked as convenient and vessels distributed as proposed in your telegram No. 305. COUMANDRR IN CKI3F, EAST INDIES Repeated to Govt, of India under Resident’s No. 480, dated 12th April 1928. J.CTelo&amp;r&amp;ffi P. from H.U’a, Consult Jeddah. To Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Lonaon, Ho. 27. Repeated Political Resident, Bushlre, | High GOiiimiasionar, Baghdad, | t t^O. ‘t • High Couxalasioner, Jeruaalem,) High ooiMmiasioner, Cairo. ) Dated 12th received 13th April 1923. I have received a com unioat ion dated April 5th from Ihn Saud. He states ho is delighted at His t/ajeaty # 3 Govemmont^ choice of Clayton, whom he hopes to moot at the beginning of ^ilgada at Jeddah. 3e is grateful to His uajosty’s ^vomment for their sympathetic desire to reach a settlement of questions which are causing trouble to both parties. The liniater for Foreign Affairs tells me that Ibn Saud is now at Buraida, whither he has summoned Chiefs for a conference*. t hen he received the message of His :aJoaty*s covernmont offering to despatch air Gilbert Clayton he had sent his cousin aaud to IQBA to Induce the Chiefs to disperse the forces gathered there and to go to Buraida where Ibn Gaud would meet them and explain hie intention of clearing up the situation by negotiation with tho British Government. Minister for Foreign Affairs is confident that danger of attack on Iraq in force is now definitely reaoved. :^oia Buraiua conference Ibn Baud proceeds to Hall, thence to Jeddah via Medina - Damluji - ster- -abad. Your message on the subject of the aato of Clayton'e arrival will reach Ibn Baud before ho lias made his plan$f for return and that date will suit him excell- -ently. BBITIBK OONGHL, J.SDDAtt*Telograxa From To ppeated iionior Kaval OfTtcer, ^oraiun Zuli\ II.K.3. ’•BHSHALD* f oft Kuwait* Commancior in Chief, Kaat Indies Station Admiralty, London* Air Officer Commanding, Baghdad* Political resident, Bushiro* *!o* 1307. April Patod 13th received 14th xknfc 1928. landing parties were re-emharked today, 13th April* s.n.q.psrsian aui.r. *• t-r— Telegram p* ^om Political Agent, Kuwait* To Political Besident, Bushire* No. 328. Bated 13th received 14th April 1928* Your telegram No* 300 of 4th Inarch* . Naval landing parties ro-emharked today. I understand that Senior Naval Officer has telegraphed to you 6fe suggesting that the Shaikh of l/oharamerah he thanked for the use of his palace. POLITICAL AG 'INT, KUWAIT.Code Tele&amp;ram irom PoXitloalf Kuwait To secretary of btate Tor the Colon!e&amp; 9 London Lepeated he&amp;ident 9 Bu&amp;Mre Hlghooma f Lgghdad &amp; High.coma # Jerusalem Ho. 229 Lated (&amp; received) the 14th April 1928. JHajaia who leTt Cudair on 8th April arrived here. They oonTina the report that meeting between Ibn daud and the lithwan chiefs has been arranged to taice place at Jalah 9 shurt distance north of x&gt;uraidah. Ibn Laud had sent on heavy luggage anu was leaving immediately hy car. Ion humaid had already left Ajiboah Tor Jalah. hawisn was at ATtawiyah but was gving to Jalah as soon as he he^rd that Ibn baud hau left niyadh. Political.riynfldcntlttl.t Ho.C/154 of 1928. The Political agency, wn kay 19^8. J=3 To The Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Suli, Buehire. Menoraudun. met It ia uaid tluit Bin Saud itittb/ovcr l!b,000 idchwano during hie recent, vieit to Bui'aidah* The de- mandu they made were*- 1. Abolition oX tho tax on aaoep entering the towns for sale. 2. Abolition of all telegraph Stations throughout Nejd, 3. Permiaaion to visit JJeoou. 4. Demolition of Busaya Port, Bin Baud ia said to have agreed to Noo,l &amp; 5, to have refused to consider Bo,2 and to have promised to dis cuss Bo.4 with H.U'u Government, I have not heard definitely that Bin Jairish and Bin Huimid attended the meeting but persons who have arrived in Bahrein say that they met these chiefs cn route to meet Bin Baud, Arrivals from i-atif by motor launch yesterday state that Bin Saud is preventing Nejdis from leaving for Bahrein and that 2 men were actually removed ) from their launch after embarkation. It is presumed that the prohibition of emigration of Kejdia is in order to have them ready in the event of a Jehad being proclaimed. I think it will be found that the correct explana tion is that the 2 Bejdis were debtors who were prevent*^- fromal . wo. 0 / or 19£8 . The Political Agency, Bahrein, May 19£8 . * 1 To The Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H i R E. Menorandun. The following information is gathered from the Bahrein Bazaan- 1 * Si* * 1 Dawiah did not meet Bin Saud, but desired the latter to cone outside Buraidah to meet him. He made several conditions preparatory to a meeting, which B±n Saud was unable to accept. Among others he demanded to see the treaty with the British Government. has been prohibited, but Husawis are allowed to leave. It is said that Bin Saud intends to raise an army, but it is not iaiown against whom it is to be employed. The departure of Wejdjs and Bedouins from UJair Political Agent, Bahrein.Wo. C/164 Ol* 19£8. The Political Agency# Bahrein# 13th may 1928 To The Secretary to the Political Heel dent in the Persian Gulf, Bushire Meiaoranclun. Shaikh Abdulla bin isa has informed no on the authority of Saad al Badanah a servant of Shaikh Muhammad bm Abdul Rahanan bm Saud tJiat the Nejd people have been prohibited from leaving the country, as the jmam wants to increase his army. At&gt;c ^ ullG thinks that it is only a question of new drat ta to take the place of time expired men in the Hejaz. A man who left Riadh via Huoaimyah has been found murdered arid robbed of his money and arms. Bin Jilav/i is searching for his murderer. Faisal Bin Dawish did not meet Bin Saud at Buraidoh. It had been Bin Baud's intention to bestow large presents on the Akhwan but on the advice of the Amir of Analzah he adopted a stranger attitude. The inhabitants of Buraidoh ' tjieir ar/w in their shops and elsewhere where they could be seen and scowled at the Akhwan# to show their disapproval of their actions and ^support of Bin Saud. At the conference the Akhwan condemned the action of Bin Dawish m defying Bin Saud and stated that he was worthy of punishment. Bin Dawish is said to have come to the netghbourhood of Buraidah with 6000 men and left with 8* The figures are obviously exaggerated but Bin Dawish's prestige appears to have 7 /aned. QusaibiTelc&amp;raifc r. from Political Agent, Kuwait* 3ecretary of :tate &gt; loniea, London* .epeatod Political Resident, Lushir©* High Coaiuisaionor, Baghdad* High Coiomi as loner, ^ erusalea* No. 327. j^atoa 2ist recoivad 22nd April 192d* A report has boon received here that a fow days ago camp of AWA2I1', south-west of ••' FlvAil, in territory common to Kuwait and Pejc, was raided oy a party, XKryggttfi TcmYtm only twelve in nu; bar, reported to oa under &amp;IDBAJ ABU SHU VAZHIBAT• of BUIAIH KUTAIP., but a rafuree in I esop- -otaonla ( whose relation, ALI ABU . &lt;% &gt;H ‘ I HI/AT, recently ceme here and tried to incite raid into .ojd, pratending that he was acting on behalf of the ting of Iraq.)* The Shaikh of Kuwait himself discredits the report so far as the lUXAIK are concex'ndd but says that the truth will be known in a short time. POLITIC/Mi \0*Wf f KUV.AIT*Code JFrom political, iuivait To Keeidexity ijusiiire No* 332 Dated (&amp; receired) the 26th April 1928* Wireless messy^ Ho.1/534 of 26th April from Special, Kuwait, to Aviation, etc., begins; Man who left Riyadh on l?th April arrived here on 25tii etates that he heard meeting of Aichwan tooM piece on 14th April, but result was not known, on road he heard that uawish sanctioned Buraih watering at Hafar. They hope to graze at Tawal Adh-Dhafir. Enormous loss of grazing » in northern 14ajd due to locusts* Aeroplanes were seen at Abraj ivalijah on 23rd and went east* Ends* pollticol*Code Telegram From Political, Kuwait To y-r Secretary of State Tor the Colonies*London* Kepeated Resident, Bushire Highcoma* Baghdad &amp; Highcoma* Jerusalem Ho. 333 Bated t&amp; receired) the L7th April 1928# A Najdi known to the Shaikh of Kuwait and considered reliable left Uabh&amp;ah in Sudair on 18th April and arrived here yesterday evening (Thursday)* He says that Hajd is practically stripped bare by locusts*un 10th April Ibn Saud left Riyadh for Buraidah* and was still there when he left* Ibn Humaid was at Jalah* about 25 miles north of Buraidah* with hio standards and all his forces* On 14th April Bawish* also with a large force* joined him there* Ho meeting between them and Ibn Saud had taken place* as (he) demanded that they rhould both come in to I Ruraldah together* and they demanded that he should come outside town and meet them in desert* They had ofiered to go in and see him one at a time* but Ibn Caud said that they must come tngethwr* Matters were consequently at a dead lock* but messages were still passing between them* political*code Telegram From T© Ho. Dated political, Kuwait. Resident, Bushire. 339 30th April 1928 ( received the 1st May 1928 ) Wireless message 1/535j^Oth April from special Kuwait to aviation begins* uejid Awazia raided on 14th April having been ferced into Koweit territory by locusts damaging grazing arrived SUDANI HI YAH 27th April where I visited them today* Sheikh and men en scene confirm raid was led by 7ALAH ABAW SHUWAIKIBAT (nick named MIDBAJ) of MUTAIR and SHAIPAH AMU SHIJ AhAH of AJkAM as reported in my 1/526jldlst April* Raiders spent previous night with MIJHIM 8 UWAIJI ef SAHAMAH section of MUTAIR who confirm* In addition to 11 animals reported as Stolen a further 29 were taken shortly afterwards* Total 40 M Camels looted and 1 Camel herd, qULMAH BIN DUKHAIH, killed* Ibr^aud lias been informed* I have taken notej^amel brand-w-^opy by post* Local opinion strong that raiders would make for the tents of ANIDAH tribe* Sheikh willing to send representative to identify properties if found in Iraq and by aeroplane if required* Attitude was friendly* ends* politicalTelegram i’r®^ Cod4 political, Kuwait To KeBident 9 Dushire Ho« 540 J)at6d (&lt;Sc received) the let May 19^8. extracts fro* wirelese message 1/539 of 50th April from Special, Kuwait, to Aviation, begins; bhailch of Uajd Aw&amp;zim who left Riyadh on 19th April states that he heard there that force of ibn Huauaid was completely broken up and only persenal escort rexaaiiied with him* He heard that meeting between IJchwan chiefs and Ibn 3aud took place but had no details except that ibn baud agreed he would pay compensation* to Mandatory Government for attach on Husaiyah post while r/awish would have to compensate the bhaikh of Kuwait. Shaikh obtained leave from Ibn baud to move into Kuwait or Iraq for grazing. Camel herde of Ibn Jiluwi of Hasa are also moving into Kuwait in search of grazing locusts. Ends. Special obtained above * ««*;*• a t ^utjaihlyah yesterday, and information regarding meeting avowedly only hearsay and does not appear to be convincing. Political.&gt; Telegram p. From To ±To • 344 • Dated and received 3rd Kay 1928. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Besident, Bushire. Captain De GAUBY leaves for England tomorrow having 'been appointed Adjutant of his 'battalion. No one is coming to replace him as Special Service Officer at Kuwait. The foregoing refers to my telegram No. 184. POLITICAL AGENT, KUWAIT. nji Telegram P # from Air ! ffleer Coiamanding, ^aghdUid• To Political ;aaident # Buniiirm* ISO* r *lo* )ated vith receivod 6tU lap 192 &amp;* CM ooction of araourod caro is Deing withdrawn from Kuwait leaving there one section of armoured cars and on© flight* A• 0 «C• Baghdad• CONFIDENTIAL . No. 184-S• British Residency and Consulate-General. Bushire, 6th May 1928. Copy forwarded to The Government of India in the Foreign and Pol. Dept, :Poll *4 c al ~ A.Kent. Kwait . 'me Politic al Agent. Bahrain. - in continuation of this office endorsement No. I8i-s dated 5th May 1928. 182-3 By order, iCL*— ^ Capt., for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian £ulf #IS* \ Ttltgram Cod# From political, Kuwait Secretary of State for the Colonies, hondon Repeated Kesident, Jbushire Hi ghc oma, ha^huad &amp; Highcoma, Jerusalem O r 548 hated l&amp; receiTed) the 7th May 1928. Reliable man who left Zilfi on 27th April and arrived here yesterday (Sunday) evening reports as follows* Ibn Saud was at -duraidah but was leaving on or about the 28th April for Jeddah via Hail, Medina and Mecca. Uzaiyiz, son of ha wish, was with dbn Saud at Miraiauh. Neither iJawieh himself nor Ibn Hum&amp;id had met Ibn Saud at all, but an agreement had been arrived at through the instrumentality of Ibn Musaad, by which Ajdawan leaders unuertook to abstain from raiding for the time being. The terms of agreement were not known, and according to some it was only to hold for two months. For the present, however, s the&gt; have certainly returned to their respective headquarter and disbanded all their iorces# political.Telegram From P. Xolliloal \gent, Kuwait* To polltioal Uealdent, Bushire, rf o. 340 . listed 7th received 8th Vajr 1928. Hy telegram No. 318 of April 4th. In view of my immediatGly preceding tole- -gram I no longer see any necessity for a ship to regain permanently! nor aeroplanes and armoured oars either for that matter*! particularly as locusts have ua£e move- -ments of large force impossible. Cne section of armoured cars leaves to- -morrow and in any case it would be awkward for the remaining section and for aircraft to stay on after the ships goes as they dejjend on it for water etc. POLI flSAI, AGTWT, i U^AIT.CONFIDENTIAL NO.208-S. of 1928. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General Bushire, the 19th May 1928. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Political A^ent, Bahrain, in continuation of this office endorsement NOol95-S., dated the 12th May 1928. 1. S.N.O.P.G*s unnumbered telegram of 15th May 1928. 2. Political Residents telegram No.628 of 16th May 1928. 3. A,0.C.Baghdad *s telegram No.Z/305 of 18th May 1928. 4. Political Kesident^ telegram No.93 of 18th May 1928. 5. Kuwait telegram No.358 of 18th May 1928. By order. For Secretary to the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf. 6*. Commander Lupin’s telegram of 19th May.Telegram - Code From - Political,Bahrain To - Major Barrett,Shiraz No.475 Dated auut 25th and received 26th July 1928 Saiyid Hamad bin Ibrahim bin Azz&amp;n Busaida of Rostock and ffazam Oman now guest of Shaikh Hamad visited thi morning witn lAtter ana iniorms me that he would go to Hasa for pleasure trip. According to ousiae reports unuerstand that he is very likely to go to Riadh to meet Bin Saud . He might pousibily be in temporary command asks for letter of introduction please instruct addressed to Shiraz repeated to Bushire. Telegram - Coue Prom - Barrett,Shiraz To - Political,Bahrain(repeated to Secretary,Bushire) No. - 3 Dated - 26th July j.928 Your telegram No.475. I do not Know him. Ask him to get letter of introduction from Political A^ent.xxsxxix Muucat addressed Bahrain repeated Bushire.Telgraia From To Ho. Code Political, Bahrain Major Barrett, Shiraz 563 hated and received let September 19^8 ImmKhlATii.. lour telegram dated diet Aug;uyt^No.2.7. Report about Bin Bijad proved to be wrong. Muhammad al Shawi of Riyadh and nephew of Bin Sa*ud arrived here and are under medical treatment. There are rumours intended hostility on f Iraq &gt; frontier after one month when Bin Sa f ud is expected to return to Riyadh. PoliticalTelegram Code from Political, Bdirain To Major Barrett, Shiraz No. 207-C Dated 5tli(reoei red 6th) September 1928 Persistent rumours based on letters and staement of fresh arrivals from hajd say that Bin Sa^d has ordered noblization of tribes on the *Ira &lt;4 frontier but hostility would commence after his return to Riyadh within a month* Reason given is so called failure of Iraq missionVht.n I was on the S. S. 'BunGtra' a friend cf mine who was in the employ of Bin Sa»ud at ’Uj^ir and was goin^ to Kuwait on leave gave me the following information which seemito be interesting:- When Shaikh Abdullah bin dalaw-i visited Riyadh in the. month of Ramadhan 1345 one of his servants quarreled with a member of the Al-ash-Shaikh(a well known and respected familyiinxlijqji of hajd »Alims). The latter called the servant of Bin °;*lawi a Kafir. 1'he serv^nywent ana reported the matter to his master v/ho became very much excited. Bin Jula\ i sent for the man who insulted his servant and then gc.ve him a harsh beating as a result of which the man died The family cf Al-ash-Shaikh got very much angry c.nd ceased to Cu.ll on Bin ^a&amp;ud who was not pleased with the action of Bin Jalawi. They being very influencial in ITajd and their word is much respected by the Ikhwans Bin Sa£ud was forced oo ask their pardon and mobile Bin Jalawi ace^the same. But though Bin Su*ud had tuvken so much trouble to srtisfy them they were not so in the: hearts though ouwrdly they showed us if hey were contenrec,. They, to cre ate, trouble :j)r Biii__Ja 1 aw_i , wrote a Ratwa to the Ikhwans sa^/ing that fc they cannot tolerate to see Shi T as in the le-.nd of Muliummad^.ws and cannot allow them to go and visit the tombs *Iru&lt;1 ^.nd tther places, that they cannot see max(duty on goods imported or exported) taken on the goods which the^t Muslims consumgV They also sent a copy of this ^ twa to the news-papers at Egypt. By this uction hey thoght that hey have revenged for them selves from Bin Jalawi anc Bin *Sa ? ud who disgraced them , would be very difficuilt to Bin Jalawi to ueal v.’ith Shi f a sh^&gt;jects whom the Ikhwan want to convert to Bunnis . Vi'ifoool- a MO Ps 2&gt;S - « rTelegrtin - P, Prom - ReBident, Bushire. To - Political Agent, Bahrein. No. 973 Dated 8th October 1928. Please obtain all possible information about Bin Baud’s visit to Hasa and the position among his tribes.TEL E GRAM From - To No. 210 Raj at. Political, Bahrein. Resident, Bushire. Dated 11th October 1928. (jjsaibi says Bin Saud expected Hasa inNo* 48l-S. Political Agency, Kuwait. 3tat October 1Q28. To The Political A^eht, BAHRAIN. Reports about the Situation la Najd. MEMORANDUM. I enclose herewith a copy of my telegram No.480-3 vt. of to-day’s date, regarding a report on the Situation in Najd which has reached me via Bahrain - having been broujbt by a passenger by ss. 'Bankura', which arrived here yester- 4 day evening, -f I v/ould suggest that it would be a great help to ♦ me, and a probable saving of money, if you could send me by post copies of all telegram about Ibn 3a’ud and the Ikhwan which you despatch, so that if in future reports reach me via Bahrain, I will know whether or not you have had them and passed them on, I doubt if reciprocal action on my part would help you, but if you think it would I will post you copies of my telegrams. Political Agent, Kuwait.'© \d^ Tele^ra^i (j). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushlre; repeated to Hi£hcoma, Baghdad, 2»o. 480-S. Dated Dtst October t9d8. ”y tele^raa lie.-'78-3. 1 siaa who la well laforaed regarding; Ilajd, who arrived here yesterday evening, Tuesday,by steaaar fros Bahrain, reports as follows: Ibn Sa’ud has Induced Ion Humaid to come In to Riyadh in person* Dawish has definitely refused to come in himself, but has sent his son. On the other hand, when Dawfsh heard of the Mutair proposal to attack the ’Awazlra, he vetoed it on the ground that it would be contrary to the orders of Ibn Sa'ud, and that the case must be referred to him. Ibn 3a'dd has sent word to Ibn Jiluwi that he hopes to arrive at Hasa on the 22nd November* I am sending you this report, although I expect you have already received it ffcon the Political Agent, Bahrain, &gt; ■\i ; ,No. 395-3. of 1923. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 7th November 1923. From The Hon’hie Sir F.¥.Johnston, K.C.T.B., C.3.I., T.C.S.|| \\ Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to forward a copy of a despatch] dated 14th August 1923 from His Majesty’s Secretary of State for the Colonies and to ask that you will favour me with your views on the economic and political side of the question. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.cj -v T?m OOPY. Downi^e; Street, list 2 £ ^8 Sir A.3 you are aeare, the Hi^h Soj^nissioner fur Ira(i uu^^ebted, after the raide on Iraq, which were aerr- “ied out hy Nejdi trices 1st .inter, that hlockade ef the Has a eiiorld he imposed as a means of 'bringing pressure to hear upon Thn Sana ana his recalcitrant trihos. That suggestion did not, however, aaimnend it- huve reoently been considering, in o- e it suould he necessary at any time in the future to threaten to im- fact he necessary to ensure th.at .uca hlochaue wouia I do not desire you to assume that Hio Majesty -*s Government are seriously conte plating the impositioi -ade effective is being considered merely as a precaut- -ionary measure in case it should he necessary at some future cate to threaten t© impose such a block- -ade. he effective. \ccordingly, T have tho honour to request that you ill, after consulting the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, furnish me hy despatch with your’ cons-L^erau view^ on the subject. of such a blockade in the near future. The question of what measures would he required to make such a clock- I have the honour to ha, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servantTtltgram - P. Fr»m - Political Agtnt, Bahrain. T# - Rtsidtmt, Bushirc. N#• 229 Bat«d - 18th gMYwtaie Ntvsm'bor 1928. H«jd Ctnftrtnce has dlspsrssd aftsr mtsting Bin Saud’a wishss in matter #f telegraphs etc. It acknowledged his sen Saud as heir. Be definite infermatien regards Iraq hut it is said decision was postponed. Informant fairly reliable. Copy to the Political Agent, Kuweit by pest.Tele^run - P ?r•m - High Comrninrrioncr ; Bughdaci. To - Political Ag**nt, Bahrain. ITo. 159 S ^»ated and rrcrived PPnd Hove rah or 1928. Pleaoe inform Bin Sand ac cuicklv as A V possible that 400 tents of MUTAIP under HANAIYaIi, IBH LIUHaUjIB, AIM.AiL DIYaHIH and' • tilers are now camped in Iraq territory about 30 miles north ' eastern end of neutral zone. Ask him whether they have come with his permission. Addressed Bahrein , repeated Secretary of State f03’ the Colonies Ho. 585 and British Agent Jeddali3* A ref «r •sioe te tlie Bahrein Cue teas Heuee returne fer the year ending 5lwV September 1926 shew* that the value € tr^de with Arabia wa« F*e 73 t OO # OOai4lf thes tetal # expert® aneunted t® approximately B® 63 a 000 # Q00 and import® B® 10 # 00 c 000. The main item® ef export were (•) Bice 27,00.000 (b) Piece geed® m 16.60,000 (o) Sugar « 12,00,000 On i the import side there appear (a) Ghee n 6.60,000 (b) Bate® m 3.00,000 (o) Tebaco® • m 2,26.000 (*) Liveotock.......... m •. . • 66,000 (t) Household geed®.... it . .. • 26,000 (f) Skin® «i 22,000 The import ef tobacco 1® mainly frem Oman re-expert aaeui»tl; 2 g te about Be 60.000 in value i® inoenoider- •able• The expert of eugar. though manifeoted fer Arabia, probably find® it® way mainly te no*Arab pert®. 6n the ether hand the Cuetem® return® make ne mention of ker£eoine oil. a® thi® is shipped by Tuouf Kanee, agent of the Angle-Persian Oil Cempany, direct from the Company 1 ® eteoaer te dhows which carry it te Arab perte without landing at Bahrain. Piece geode a nd ris e are brought from England and ’ ^ Japan via Bombay. Sugar comes from the hast and Antwerp largely through Bombay. Beth are shipped te the Ilaoa and te the ether Arab parts approximate ly in the proportion of 2 te 1 • Bice and piece geode are eooaelenally shipped between Bahrain. Kuwjtet and Dubai te balance the market, but the total value of ouch transaction® 1® small. 1 consider it would be a fair reugh estimate te ▼alu® Bahrain*® ®xp®rt t® Jubail. ^atif and Ikiair at 46.00.000 ®ut #f which Bo 41;.00.000 w®uld be staplearticle* ef feed and cletiilng. The tetal imperte ef the throe perte frew *11 seuroeo eheuld *pprexl»fcite ha d0 9 00 9 000« aheuld 4 . A blockade ef thoee pert*/at first h*Y* a cenoidea * -able effect en the Bedouins Hiring in the eastern districts ef Bejd v ehe would find their c*rtyv-iy^^aupplieo ef rice and doth out off. The effect would however be considerably mitigated if. as I believe, ther are reserves in store on the mainland. Bahrain Itself is overstocked with rice and prices are very low. If the Hah blockadci were long continued I anti* -clpate that KuwAet. and even Iraq merchants, would see an opportunity for enriching themselves,that they could not resist. In addition to Dubai and Abu Dhabi about which I have ns details, Dshah and ivakrah under ^atar would derive considerable benefit at the expense of Bahrain, b. The takings of the Dohah Customs House at 5 ^ ad valorem, amount to about Bo 1,20,000 annually. Th# total value ef geode imported should therefore be h* 24.00,000. The ether email ports ef katar would bring the total to Re 2b,00,000. As the Catar peninsula contains a very small population a considerable quantity ef theee imports must find kh&amp;k way to Hass and th* border tribes such as the AbL MOPJRaH, who new obey bin da Jilawi. I am informed that a monthly caravan leaves Bshah for Hefuf. I have as yet boon ab^s to get n# estimate ef the amount and nature ef the goods imported into Hasa by this rsuts. whatever the quantity may be, a very considerable Increase may be expected if the direct route^via the Hasa ports,wore out off. In order effectively to blackade Hasa it would be necessary therefore to include supervision ever (iatar and probably ever Dubai and Abu Dhabi,in the organisation. The merchandise from Dubai would probably go to Abu Hhabi by \ dhep owing te the difficulties and length ef the land route 6. The blockade would deal a very severe blew attix« main trad« af Bahrain, whioh, axoluHinn; j^aurls, la In r loa and plaoa gaada. Till a traua io ctiXl vary largaly In tha B^nds #f Hlndhl Bannlaha, wha would tiiua bo the ohlof •ufforora finanolally. Tho ordtr of oxoluolon of Hindu® from Qatif, which appoara to bo laporfoctly onforood, aa I oaw two Bannlaha in (iatlf during sjy rocont Tlolt, haa faTourod tho ^rab and oapcoially tho Hg^dl morchant at th« oxponao of Uio Hindus, but tho main portion of tho Import of rice and piece goodo into ^atif and U^alr otlll paaaoa through their hrndo. Tho trade bot«;«on Bahrain and &gt; Juball atemo ta bo largoly in the handa of Abdul A*1 k Q ua^lbl and Caaapny, who aro Bin Baud's agonta in Bahrain, 7. The Bahrainis both Buiwi and Shiah, who depond on tho poarl fisheries for tuei* livelihood would not bo very badly hit by tho blecfcade, but it might have the offset of driving out tho Bannlaha. Those men have no permanent etafco in the lolando. Zf they saw their trade suffering they might novo on bloqtf to Bubal in the hope of carrying on oporatienii from there, aa ?2h*ihh Abdullah will not odzalt them to ^atar. Zf once established in Bubal, many of them night prefer to remain there rather than make a see end move. Their presence night divert to Dubai a portion of thv trade now coming to Bahrain and thuo give a fillip to a tendency, already discernible, af tho Qatar ports to receive their goods via Dubai instead of by the Bahrain route, 8, Z estimate that the blockade of tho Hasa porta would bring an immediate lose of Customs revenue amount-* ~lng to rupees two lafcus out of an annual income of rupees ten lakhs accruing to the Bahrain State from this source. Zf one effect of tho blockade wore te be the diversion of trade, to however small an extent, to other ports the injury done te the State would be permanent. This in itself would antagonise tho ruling family, who aro dependent on tho State rovonuos for their livelihood. 3. The lame Shiah usmilation who*'*’ areMainly oonfln^d t# yearling and date growing and wiie UftTt ne reaeen to be grateful for mhabi rule, owing to ito treat- «sMmt of their oe-religieniete in H&amp;oa and ^atif, would probably be paseive. The^ night even weloene bod relatione between Bahrain and Bejd. Their Sunni confrerea, although •ufftring little econeoioaliy would be drawn towards Hojd ^ the religious ulo* lusuf hanoo an influential bi-mh oweng then, would be an actual eufferer freia the bleohade. 10* Bln Baud, although disliked by nany and feared by nere, lo the ene big Arab ef Arabia. As such, when epposed te foroignoro, he stakes a strong call en the national and religious feelings of the Oulf Arab. The blockade) would there- -fere be extremely unpopular, mere eopeclally if, as X suppose it must, it were based en Bahrain. In * atar ef which the ruler lo a professed nahabi, there can be ne doubt what- -ever ef the anti-British feeling that would be aroused. The Shaikh informed the Political Resident in April 19:7, in a meeting at which 1 va* present that he could take ne action th*t L-igiit displease the -akhwan. My secret reports shew that, even new, there is an anti-British feeling in the country. The blockade would at snoe cause the British ts replace the Persians as the chief enemy ef the Arabs* prsfsund admiration for Bin Baud. He shews the nest intsnss 'do desire te comply with any request from him or his Amir in i Ha... H* fuvtum us&amp;lbl, Bin SituA*. ugont, utov. *ll U B*br*l dl.t*.t.ful t. ilia. At til. mm tla. h* w.uld ucc.pt *ny ad via. ' tiiat Hi. •« O.v.riua.nt might .ff.r t. hia. Hi. h.art, h.tr.v.r, w.uld n.t b. in hi. do.da, and the yalu. • r hi « •»» o.-.p.r*tiM, and that .f hi. .ubj.ota, w.uld th.r.by b. ady.ra.ly affected. All w.uld hn.w that ShaiJch Hanad had bean fared t. ad.pt a oauhdtt. which h. wa. .pp...., ^ hi. pa.itl.n a. a puppet rul.r, which it i. Britihh p.lioy tp c.no.al w.uld b. laid bar. t. th. criticism, af th. Shaikh Hamad th. ii.puty Hul.r af Bahrain ha. a T. tag. aoti.n against Bin Baud bauld b. int.n.iy.iy Persian.Dated the 1st December 1928. To H. M. King Abdn Aziz ibn Sand. After Compliments. In continuation of my letter No. 231 of 22nd November, I have the honour to inform Your Majesty that I have now received a telegram from the High Commissioner, Baghdad asking me to intimate to you that the mutair have now re-crossed the frontier into Nejd.COOTSSIIi^.- JUO. 425-a of 1928. .British Kesidency &amp; Consulate-General, hushire, the 23rd jMevemher 1928. To The political Agent, 1C u w a i t / . Bahrainv/ Memorandm ii. Please forward direct to the political Agent, jl^ait' C ° Py ° f &amp;11 letter8 anu pott cop y of all telegreme conveying aesert intelligence. As compliance will te taken for granted in the case Ox tulegrams the iact that a post copy is being despatched need not be specified therein. ay order. UftLvL captain, under secretary to the political pesiden in the Persian Gulf.H. C. F. 16. SECRETARIAT OF H E THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR IRAQ £ Baghdad, —££jL -JlaXflMkftJTL, I 92 Q . By direction of His Excellency the High Commissioner for ‘Iraq, a copy of correspondence as marked jjpw is forwarded with compliments to :— His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. nclosures :— M.I, 28. Confidential letter No.S.O. dated the of November, 1928, from the Political Secretary to H.S. the High Commissioner -or 'Iraq, Baghdad, to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with enclosure.-onfidsntT*! Baerftt triat of H. C. th«? dlph Conuai««tiloner for ’Ir&gt;u f 5«o.n.o Sir, Pursuant to Instructions froia th« Sscrstary of ^tats for ths Colonies 1 am lirscted by iiis ixosilsnoy ths iiigh Co^issloner to enclose herewith a copy of a note to be addressed to Ibn Sa'ud by the British tcent at Jiddah. The draft note was despatched from London to Tlddah on : orember 1st, and a copy has also been sent to the Bonnie the Political Resident from the Colonial Office, but will not reach him before the middle of ecsaber. The Colonial Office are anxious that the Political /\gent at Bahrain should, if he meets Ibn 9a'ud, be aware of what is proposed, and hare therefore requested the high Commissioner to send direct to Bush ire, and to the Political tgent at Bahrain, copies of ths not** 2* A copy of this despatch, with its enclosure, is being sent direct to the Jollticil gent at Bahrain. 1 hare the honour to be, Sir, four moet obedient servant, fSdU R S M Sttrrg Political Secretary to H* the high Commissioner for 'Iraq. :&gt;ecretaiy to* the “in'bln th. PoUti**! So.i-lant w *0* P.r.lun Culf, au«hlr«m (&amp; TS ?HXFT or PR0P03 ?D N0X3 TO KING XBN 3 I'D. Your Majssty, I hare the honour to inform Your Majeaty that I have been instructed by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, on behalf of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, to address the following communication to Your majesty. 2* His Britannic Majesty’s Government, while fully appreciating the friendly spirit in which the recent conversations between Your Majesty and Sir Gilbert Clayton were held, have learnt with deep regret that those conver sations have not resulted in any agreement on the major question at issue namely the interpretation of Article 3 of the First Protocol of Uqair* 3* His Britannic Majesty's Government have given the most careful and sympathetic consideration to the views and arguments put forward by Your Majesty, and they are parti cularly anxious to do everything in their power to assist Your Majesty in YouAoanifest efforts to maintain peaceful conditions on the frontier* But on the other hand, they cannot but regard it as a matter of fixed principle that the Government of every country is entitled, in the absence of specific undertakings to the contrary, to carry out such measures of internal administration within its territory as it may from time to time think necessary. The inter pretation which Your Majesty seeks to place upon Article 3 of the First Protocol of Uoair is one which, in the opinion of His Britannic Majesty’s Government and the Government of '*raq, is not only inconsistent with the text of the Article, t&gt;ut would involve an unwarrantable departure, to the detrimentdetrimant of ‘Iraq, from the above mentioned principle. It ie for these reasons that Your Majesty* s interpretation is unacceptable* 4 . In the conversations which he was privileged to have with Your iiajesty, Sir Gilbert Clayton emphasised the pacific and friendly nature of the reasons which had caused the 'Iraq Government to construct and maintain certain poste in the desert. He also made it abundantly clear that the poste in question were not intended to interfere with the customary rights of grazing and watering enjoyed by Hajd tribes, or to hamper their lawful movements and migrations across the desert areas of South-Western *Iraq; and he gave Your Majesty explicit verbal assurances to that effect. Both His Britannic Majesty*s Government and the •Irac Government desire formally to repeat those assurances which correctly represent their considered policy. 5. In earnest of their desire to arrive at a fair and peaceful settlement of the question at issue, and to remove all obstacles in the way of consolidating the relations of amity and concord between the two \rab States, His Britannic Majesty’s Government and the * Iraq Government are prepared, should Your Majesty so desire, to submit the points in dispute to an arbitrator to be selected in consultation with Your Majesty and in agreement between the Governments concerned. I am authorised formally to offer to Your Majesty this proposal of arbitration and to invite Your Majesty to inform me whether you are prepared to assent in principle to a settlementsettleiaant on th%t basis, so that the mode *nd conditions 0 r ' 25 proposed arbitration m&lt;ay be discussed without delay. Britannic majesty’s Government desire to repeat the assurance given to Your kajesty by Sir Gilbert Clayton, to the effect that they regard the provisions of Article 6 of the i3ahra Agreement as applying to British as well as to Iraqi forces, and that they fully intend to observe the stipulations of that Article, provided of course that -our Majesty's subjects abstain from hostile acts of aggression of a nature and on a scale likely to endanger the security of 'Iraq. liie Britannic Majesty* s Government hope that their proposal of a settlement by arbitration will commend itself to our Majesty, not only for the sake of settling in a manner which is fair and honourable to all parties ti s point? in digputs, but also because such a settlement 1 r&lt;3f S conclusion of formal agreer ents on the various question affecting Najd, •Iraq and Trans- Tordan which were discussed and agreed upon in principle by Your Majesty and Sir Gilbert Clayton. Ihose questions relate to agreements on Bon Voisinage, extradition, the surrender of fugitives from justice, the appointment of diplomatic representatives and cognate questions. ^.f, on the other hand, Your Majesty should not agree to seek a settlement on this basis and would prefer, rather than have recourse to arbitration, to leave the question unsettled, with the resultant risk of unrest on t ie frontier. His Britannic Majesty*s Government and the ’Iraq Government could only regret such a decision on the part of Your Majesty.m -4- 9* that casa, tha Goveriii_»6nts concerned /cust ag^raa for tlia time being to postpone any aottlonient as to the true meaning of vrticie 3 of the First Protocol of Uqair. l&lt;everthele»e, the ▼arious treaties and agreements regulating the relations between the Governments concerned remain in full force and effect; and it is the firm intention of His Britannic Hajesty’s Government and tne ’Iraq Government scrupulously to observe the obligations imposed upon them by those instruments, and to direct their energies to the prevention of any incidents of a nature to provoke disturbances on the frontier or to disturb the friendly relitions of tho two countries* They are confident that four hajeety will discharge your obligations with the same scrupulous regard ind they not# with satisfaction Your Majesty’s assurance to Sir Gilbert Clayton that the Goverruient of the Hijaz and of Bald and its Depend ancles intends strictly to observe the terms of all trsaties and agreements in its relations with the neighbouring States. U.I. 28.SOP*.. 621...1081...5,OOO...18 9 28 V3V H. C. F. 16. No-S- 0 ' SECRETARIAT OF H E. THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR IRAQ. Baghdad, — 3-Q .—Jio veir.b e r ,. / 92 8 . By direction of His Excellency the High Commissioner for ‘Iraq, a copy of correspondence as marked ;|ow is forwarded with compliments to :— Hie Britannic Majesty’s Political \gent, Bahrain. Political Secretary to H. E. The High Commissioner for 'Iraq. 7E Despatch Conf iden tial ^dated the of November, 1928, from H. 3.the High Commissioner for ’Iraq, Baghdad, to the Secretary of State for the Colonies, London, with enclosures, on the subject of the relations between King Ibn Sa’ud and the Akhwan Shaikhs.Sncr*t o«622. Cffic* of th« \dfnini»tInopector, In-ch%r^o Southern Desert. Busiiyah, dated the 17th NoTeiobor, 1928* io Tho Adrioor, Ministry of Interior, Baghdad. subject:* iKy^t,L.xoyftok n^.td . !• ihe iAeetinfe at Riyadh # On 16th NoTember, 192b, the Administrative inspector visited Abdul Hassac ibn hallaf, Shaikh of the Said section of th# Shafir, at Al Batiyyah. lie was the first reliable Shaikh to return from the meeting at adyadh, and gave the following account of the situation* The Duwish had been corresponding with Ibn Ha’ud, backwards and forwards, since before the latter** return to Riyadh, his first letter contained the earns old demands as last ysar, already ssvsral times reported, namely: (1) Abolition of telegraphs and oars* (2) Abolition of taxation of bedouins* (3j Removal of dsssrt poets* To these demands, Ibn 3a*ud, according to Ibn uallaf, replied as follows: (1) That modern inventions were of assistance to the kuslimin in making head against the modern Govemr ente which nur rounded them. (2) Ibn Sa*ud agreed to abolition of taxes, but &gt; out that he would of course have to cease to make pr^etnta and to pay the Shaikhs at the same time. (3) Hegarding(3) ttaevriing th# de»«rt yont«, h# th^t h« had not th« power to dootroy thorn. Ho further said that, before the T*iwi«h started raiding ‘Iran regularly, the hritieh Goremcrient had been of great Telue to tho .ueliinin, giving thewi weapon* md money, much of which hae been paneed on by Ibn Sn’ud to the Hheikhe. Xhe nuwi«h , e acte had firet caueed the tovern- ment to out off hie pay, and had then forced Covezmiont to send force* and to build poet* in the denert. The Duwieh himrelf wa* therefore reeponeible for the exietAnce of the poet*. A* long a* the latter maintained hie old attitude, Ibn Ba’ud could not demand the destruction of the posts, and had not done *o yet. but if the Duwish repented, openly made •ubaieeion and signed an undertaking to be obedient in future, Ibn Se’ud might then approach the Coyernment on the (subject of the noete at the forthcoming conference at U^air. Ibn Sa'ud explained that he had no liking for infidel* or Christian* nor for the British, but that their friendship wa* of value to the iaielimin, and that hi* policy was to get as much out of them as he could for the benefit of the true ^ttslims. ihe Government and he had long worked on a policy of pi** and take, ^ut the Duwieh had upset the whole situation. If he persisted. Government would become more angry 'till, and could ea*ily overthrow himself (Ibn Sa'ud) and the ^wiih, and ruin the kuelimin, who after all were only bedu*. if, on the other hand, the fliwish wanted to destroy the po*te himself, he could do so* Perhaps he would defeat the Government. If so, Ibn 3a 1 ud wished him joy, but he would not himself have ally part or lot in the matter. (Mote. ihe above is probably the fist of Ibn tia’ud** r «piie* to the T)uwi*h, and of his public pronouncements.) As the correspondence continued, Ibn Sa*ud became firmerflrrcar, and! th« !)uwi»h bei? inu^cliiab down**. fiY^ntunlly the latter «ent hie seal to Riyadh, telling Ibn Se'ud to affix it to any documents he li&lt;ed f that he.Fnieal, wov-tld obey all hie orders, but thit he could not co^e to Riyadh beoaune he wae afraid. It is generally conjectured that, if Ibn S^ud could seise the person of Faieal, he would detain him in hie suite personally, much is he has done with Ibn rtashid On receiving the uwish's last submiesive letter, accompanied by the teal, (Ibn Jiallaf allcgee) Ibn Ba’ud turned hie attention frora the Duwish to Ibn Humaid. he h^d written to him that, if h** *i&lt;3i not coiae to diyadh, he had better tidy up hie rnudhif and prepare dinner for Ibn 3a*ud. It is stated that Ibn iiumairi replied that he could not cone, and that he had no raudhif in which to receive Ibn Sa^ud. Ibn Hallaf thought that Ibn Ha*ud was probably pretending to be temporarily satisfied with the fuwish's letter in order to turn hie attention to Ibn iumaid. ihe great object was to separate them. it was believed that Ibn Humaid wae already angered with the rttwish, for sub mitting so far. Dhaidan Ibn Uithlain his also refused to reportito Hiyadh, but nobody seems to be attaching much importance to him either way. Having ewom a loint oath with the ^wieh and Ibn humaid before, he is deterred from visiting Ibn Sa'ud for fear of punishment, rather than from insubo rd in at ion. 2. \xmuDa o? th:-s u^i ^vn. The Administrative Inspector asked Ibn hallaf whether it was his opinion that, should the Duwish and Ibn ftumaid persist in their refusal to mset Ibn fta*ud, the latter would march against them. ^e replied that he thoughtthought this rsry unlifcsly. In hit visw, Ibn Ss’ud had no forcss to put against therrj orcspt ths town«i«en of Hafd, who were not sufficiently numerous. Had ibn Sa’ud unfurled his banner last January, Harb Shanmar, 4waaim,.ahtan and many other tribes would hare joined hin against ^utair and Ibn humaid. in fact they were daily expecting such an order. Instead of this, however, Ibn Sa'ud did nothing, and the Itawish proceeded to raid Ibn Sa'ud’s own tribes. ibn Kumaid than moved up, and camped .at Ajibba, on top of hahsin al Firm, whom he terrorised into agreement with him, although \1 Firm had, until then, been looked up as Ibn SA'ud** especial man. Finally at buraidah, Ibn Sa^d had poured out gold and gifts to ths very people who had been disobeying hie orders and raiding his subjsots. ihere had, however, been no compensation for the Tiotims* As a result, nobody would now declare openly for Ibn Ba^d against the Ttawiah or Ibn humaid, lest they be raided by them* Ibn Hallaf said that he found that, when he broached the subject cautiously to Majd Shaikhs in Riyadh, they hastily said 'we follow ths road of Islam', and changed the subject* Mahsin al Finn, when summoned to Riyadh six weeks ago, was afraid to proceed, lest the 3uwi»h be annoyed and raid him, with Ibn 3a 1 ud impassive far away in Riyadh. Mahsin is one of th^ principal Akhwan chiefs, and was previously a firm supporter of Ibn Sa’ud. but he was afraid to visit Riyadh, until \saiyix al Duwish went* In Ibn hallaf’s opinion, Ibn 3a»ud is not the man he was* As he put it ths hlng only wants to finish his day* in peace, *nd would leave the AJchwnn to their own devices if he could, even though the stripped the abba offhi* to'icjc* i^ut h« cannot loavo affair* to run th«i r caureo, a* ho is proo^od by tho Oorommont on th« ona hand and by tha Akhwan on tha other, Xha TJuwiah and Ibn Humaid ara not opposed to 'Iraq or tha daaart posts, but ara chafing against Ibn Sa^d 1 * authority. Meanwhile Ibn Sa'ud, by his procrast ination and waaicn*s«, has, in Ibn Kalians ▼iaw, missed his chance of armed support by tha Akhwan tribes against tha ineubordinate chiefs. According to ibn Hallaf, the majority of the Akhwan in Riyadh are pressing Ibn Sa»ud to leave the Du wish and Ibn humaid alone. '^e, they say, will promise to obey all your orders. If these two try ^nd create trouble again, we shall not .loin them, liut they are only two men, leave them alone, what is the use of pressing them further?*. In brief, the malcontents do not desire to fight Ibn 8a # ud, and are prepared to make their submission by Istter, and to promise to keep quiet. But they still refuse to appear in person. Ibn Sa’ud has so far apparently scored a success, in that the malcontents have greatly moderated their tone, and the Jewish has sent a submissive letter and his seal. But it is doubtful if Ibn Ba’ud will have the power to force the affair to a final issue, because, in Ibn hallaf 1 e opinion, the tribes would not now join Ibn Sa*ud in arms against the malcontents. 3. VISITORS TO RIYADH . The Dhafir relate wonderful tales of the entertain ment of bedouins in iyadh. Estimates of the numbers present ▼ary from 12,000 to 16,000, though both are probably \ •**gge rated. The bedouins were all accommodated in tents outside the town. ihe townsmen, \nd contingents from other towns ^urridah, uiaisah etc., were received within the walls of Riyadh,• 6 » -iiy^dh, wer« indued wltft rifla» and a; -unit!on, and were rotted to guard the wall*, ^he gate* were closed at dunk, and the town contingent* held the wall* until dawn, which they greeted by firing a feu-de-foic in the air, apparently to ehow that they were awake. ibn .la’ud wae apparently in *ome approhen*ion of a coup de Min by the bedouin*. Owing to the great number of guest*, the lesser men and many of the numerous escort*, were presented with gift* an^ clothing, ind diauifleed i» soon ae possible, presumably to avoid continued expense on hospitality. ibn hallaf left before the end with * 0 , e of these people. ihe principal Shaikh*, including Vfami ibn Suwait, md all head* of Akhwan colonie*, are etill detained in Riyadh, Ibn Sa*ud having ordered them to remain until hi* corre«pondence with Ibn mimaid and the Ouwieh reache* a definite conclution. Iln Hallaf allege* that the Thafir ehaikh* received g^ncrou* gift* from Ibn Ba’ud, conniderably in exee*a of those given to the Nafd Cha/rc ar for example. On the other hand, he think that Ibn Sa»ud told Jami that it wa* not expedient for him to build an ^khwan village. 4 * IjgimiONS - IK The \dmlni*trative Inspector then enouired of ibn iiaU.f wta.t «.r. th. inUntion. of th- hafir. a. rapli.d “•hat, JB f ar h. wa. concamed. h. would much pr.f.r to r«tin in 'Ir*.. in il*|d. th. 2hafir w.r., a. it w.r.. oii.nt., .tranR.r. allow.d to rw.ain on *u'•f.r.no.. ih. kn.w that f.ar had comp.u.d th« Wir to Join th®., they treat ed them aono rdingly. .jtcept for the pereon of Ibn Sa’ud himself, who rec.iwad then, cordially and loaded them with presents, they had no friends in da Id. bnfortunately-7- Unfortun^ttly, Gov*nwo«nt adopted the ean'.e policy of procrastination, promisee \nd inaction, ae did ibn Sa’ud. The latter eat inactive in hie palace at Riyadh, 'vhile hie friends were being raided, with the result that nobody would now openly declare for hii». in the same way, the Government •at on the 'Uphratee or in Baerah, and ordered the *irac tribes to ba loyal* but*they had seen no Covernment forces, and the subjects of the GoTemment had been raided ^ith the same impunity as had the friends of ibn Ba’ud* obody could quite understand why both Ibn Ba’ud and the f overnment, eho either single or united were invincible if they would only act, allowed the Duwish to work havoc right md left aatongst their friends* ihe fact remained, however, that while the Government and ibn Sa’ud talked and messed about, the foiwish was the only wan who acted* \s a result, nobody now vsntured to dsclars openly either for ibn Sa*ud or the ooverntuent. if the latter were to brin* down sufficient forces to the vicinity of the frontier, he for one would join the Covemr&lt;ent. But as long as Government remained in the poets or on the river, he hoped that the \dministrative inspector would excuse him if he reorossed the frontier and camped with tutair. ^his was a statement of his own policy. is could not answsr for the Kuwait family. ^o much for Ibn hailaf. ihe present idea of the I^hafir in Majd appears to be to keep in, as far as possible, with both Government and Ibn Ba'ud, uid to carup with * utair• Ibn 3a*ud ie a ueeful friend gives away large sums of money, *nd may of course emerge victorious over * utair. regards the Government, the hafir depend on »Iraq for supplies, and may also need to camp in »Iraq. hut hutair »rs the only people who act, and hence to be safe, it is •s^ential to camp with them* j»'«U I H ' I i I i -5 *.0V&amp;r5HT8 - *.irr\I4. Ali ibn 4«hwm f and with him a ^r&lt;sat part of ^raih, in fact most of tho nomad iutair who spent the suuimer in the Neutral tree, are now camped in * Iraq territory between vl \dhami and the Neutral Area* xhey are not rery desirous of moving too far south into Nald, owing to the (incertainty of the situation Tig a vis ibn ^a'ud* It is stated also that their recent escapades with the Awasim have provoked the wrath of the Duwish, who is trying to plaoate Ibn Ra'ud # while utair are continually making fresh trouble. Ibn Ashwan and Co. are therefore not too sure what their reception would be, even in Artawiyah* They therefore, according to the hafir, hope to remain in the vicinity of the frontier, in the Hafar - Neutral Area Batin district. As regards their crossing into •Iraq, they do not appear to have done so with the idea of see King asylum with the •Iraq Govsrnment. having, however, spent the summer in the Neutral urea without interference, even after Abu nanaiyah’s raid on the Dahamshah, and having seen no sign of Government foroee, they do not appear to consider the attitude o r the Government to be a factor of any importance in the situation. It is quite probable that they will shortly drift bacn across the frontier of their own accord. Neverthelers it is thought that a great opportunity has been missed, for showing to Ibn Sa*ud and to the world at large, that we intend to adhere to our promise. It was reported only a few days ago, that Ibn usa’ad had said that it was quite probable that the Government was in secret correspondence with utair. The prompt eviction of i^utair from •Iraq by force, would, it is believed, have produced an ercellent effect. AS1 h%T« dl*cuati*d th« i utair incursion with th# Priifl# *ini®tar and ^r. Cornwallia. Xha Prim® i^inlater thinica that. If they have come In peacefully for ^rasing with their fawiliee thie may constitute a useful pledge of peaceful behaviour on their part, although it is disagreeable to the 1 irao Government to permit a tribe which has committed raids and has number* of ‘Iraai camels with it to stay in ‘Irao., without punishment. further he fears that, if the Government were to take active measures against thsm owing to their coming in without permission, thie might illogically annoy ibn fa'ud and precipitate a conflict with the Akhwan. He wishes therefore that Giubb should be directed to tend messengers irroedlately to the »utair to ask why they have come in without permission of the 1 Iraq Government and whether they have had the permission of Ibn Sa'ud. Government action would depend on their reply. If it is defiant, then they should certainly be^tumed out by force. i&gt;f not defiant, then Government would some to a suitable decision, after having ascertained Ibn Sa’ud’s views. lo save time, he thinks ibn Sa’ud should be telegraphed to at once, to inform him of the entry of the fcutair ind to enquire whether they have come with hie permission* Althoufh tr» Cornwallis is rather inclined to advise firmer action immediately, we both think that there ie no serious objection to the foregoing course.eour«e« interior will therefore send the neceeeer^ instruction* to Captain Glubb; and we should telegraph at once to Political \gent, Bahrain (repeating to Jiddah) for communication to ihn a’ud# r o « • 21/X1/26. Jw,l..1 Telegram i\ Pr orn To The Political Agent, .Bahrain, ho. 1221. Dated 1st Decembe rl928. The Political Kesic.ent, Bus hire. Colonies, Wo following from Secretary of State for 462, wovember 29th, begins : ’’His Majesty 1 s Government agree that invitation to meet ibn Saud in Hasa should be accepted by political Agent, Bahrain. High Comiais si oner, Baghdad, has been asi^ed to despatch to vou ana to Bahrain draft of Wote conveying His Majesty*s Government’s decision on'the Clayton negotiations which His Majesty’s Government have instructed the British Agent at Jeddah to communicate to ibn Saud. ibn Saud may not have received that note before the meeting takes place but the Political Agent ^Hould not himself deliver it. on enquiry it ne finds that the note has not yet reached Ibn Baud he should content himself with in- forraing ibn Saud that the note is on its way ana of its general purport. in no case ahax should he communicate its actual text, is not empowered to commit His Majesty’s Government in any respect; this should be ma^e clear to ibn Saud. Please explain •accordingly to Political Agent before meeting take s place.” Please act aoccordingly. Reference is to your telegram uo. 226, November 16th. - RESIDENT. He Post copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain, ref erence his telegram wo 267 of ]|$ie 6rd December 1928. //Curry .— ^ Undersecretary to the Pol. Resident, Persian Gulf. British Residency and Consulate -General Bushire, 6th December 1928.OO NFIDKUTIAL. Telegram (P). ' From Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Bushire. No, 501-S, Dated 6th December 1928, A second hand report of doubtful reliability regarding the Riyadh Conference has reached here to the effect that the Ikhwan’s objection to wireless telegraph, motor cars, etc,, was refuted by pointing out to them that their very rifles were Just as much invented and made by Infidels, The real trouble was over the 'Iraq Desert posts, which are viewed by the Ikhv.au as the thin end of the wedge in a systematic en croachment on Najd. Ibn Sa'ud eventually satisfied them for the time being by telling them that he would make one more attempt to get them demolished by peaceful negotiation, and promising that if he failed to do so within two months he would be with them and give his full support to an attack on 'Iraq, Copy forwarded by post to:- The Political Agent, Bahrain,Telegras (0)* Froia Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad. No. 503-S. Dated 8th December 1928. Hilal al-Mutairi, the retired pearl merchant, tells me on the authority of a man who left Artawfyah after ‘Uzaiyiz got back that when the Ikhwan objected to motor cars, etc., at the Riyadh Conference, Ibn Sa'ud agreed that it was undesirable to use Infidel made things if it could be avoided, and said that he was quite ready to burn them all and do without them if they would agree to burn their arms and ammunition, which were equally infidel made. After much discussion with the it was decided that both were lawful. He confirms the report that the chief trouble was about the Iraq desert posts, and says that Ibn Sa’ud eventually per suaded them to take no action for two months to enable him to try negotiation once more. He laughs at the idea of Daw£sh and Ibn«Humaid being really deposed, and says that the reports to that effect were mere words which no one in the Desert takes seriously. Copy by post to the Political Agent, Bahrain.Britich Residency and Consula te^General, Bush ire, 6 th December 1928. So. 3&amp;• Sir, STith reference to your deupetoh of the 14th August 1928, I have the honour to forward copies of the 1. Letter ho. 41, dated x6th .November 1928, from the Senior Naval ' Officer, Persian Gulf Division. 2 . Letter ho. C/232, dated 2bth November 1928 from the Political Agent, Bahrain. correspondence noted on the margin felative to the feasability of imposing a H, biocade of the A hasa ports. 2. It seems from Colonel Barrett’s letter to be extremely doubtful vAiether any blo^ade of the Hasa Ports could be really effective unless it became in practice a blodade of the ports from Kuwait down the A whole length of the Coast, as it would seem to be practically impossible to control the despatch into the Such a biocade interior of supplies from these ports, would inflict permanent financial loss on Banrain and alienate the Shaiidi, anc Colonel Barrett has, 1 thinks rightly estimated its effect on the other Shaikhs on the Coast. Further, vfeing to the ability of the King of Hejd to bring up supplies from his reserves in the in* terior, i t is these Chaikhs ana their people ttfio will be the His Majesty’s Secretary of State for the Colonies, Colonial Office LOBIXIM.! * fa - 2 - m .1 the hanicot hit at first by any scarcity as was shown ±» in 1920 when the Arab ports in the Gulf were rationed as regards rice. ^ In these circumstances „he imposition of4 biocode might well have a result exactly the opposite to that in tended, asthe loss and irritation caused by it might well drive the Shaikhs on the Arab Coast into the arms of ibn f&gt;aud. **• Copies of this letter are being sent to the Government of India, to Hie Excellency the High Com missioner for f Iraq arm to the Senior mtval Officer in the i^ersian Gulf. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble s e rvan t. SI)/ 9. V. Johnston, Political Heeident in the Persian Gulf aSECRET Blockade of flajd .Ports . * Prom The Senior haval Officer, J-'ersian Gulf Division, H.M.S. ”TRIAD H . To The Political Residne in the Pei’sian Gulf, Bus hire. Dated 16th November 1928. Humber 41. / With refereBce to letter 594-S. of 1928 dated 7th November 1928 from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf the Senior Naval Officer forwards herewith a copy of his submission Number 41 dated 7th November 1928 addressed to the Commander-in-Chief of the East Indies Station. SD/ H. Boyes, Cap tai n Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf.secret PROPOSAIS OF THK SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER FK GULF IN CONNECTION WIiH THPl POSSIBIE INSTITUTION OJ? ECONOMIC BLOCaHE OF TUB NEJD FCRTS. i The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Dividio H. M. S. 'TRIAD**. The Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station. From To Dated 7th November 1928. No. 41. The Senior Naval Officer has consulted the High Commissioner for Iraq, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Political Agents at Kuwait and Bahrain. There are two methods of preventing imports into Arabia through Nejd Ports* (a) Prevention of exports from India (b) Blockade of the Nejd Ports. All authorities consulted advise that the first of these alternatives would be impilitic. Trade from India to Arabia proceeds, in the main, through three ports: Debai, Bahrain and Kuwait. Bahrain is the distributing centre for qatif, Ojair and Dohah. It may be accepted as certain Ahat most of the trade for Nejd goes via Bahrain. 4. centre and effective control established over vessels making for Qatif, Ojair and Dohah merchants would consider alternative routes through Debai and Kuwait; the latter could be controlled locally with the assistance of the Royal Air Force; goods passing through the former would probably be very costly when delivered in Arabia and as a result the quantities supplied would not be large enough to defeat the purpose of the Blocade. There would be three main routes by which goods would go into Nejd ^ I I 3 \ On the institution of a Biocide with Bahrain as a) Dhow from Trucial to Nejd Ports |b) Re-exports from Bahrain to Nejd Ports c) Smuggling from Persia. This would quite likely be assisted and encouraged by the Persian authorities as retaliation for the amount of smuggling now carried out from Bahrain into Per si a. 6.6. The positions of the Ports for iiejd are: qatif 26 34 50 2 E No chart Ojair 25 39 N 50 14 K No chart dohah 25 17 K 51 32 E Chart unreliable, 7. To enforce an effective blocade the following would he required^ One sloop mtationed at Bahrain One sloop on patrol One slopp as relief. (£he fuelling of these ships would require special consideration and the shallowness and lack of survey of the water on the partof the raa coast to be blockaded would be a handicap to their usefulness;. Four motor dhows manned by ftaval crews. Three of these could watch the three ports with the fourth as relief. (They would have to be protected with steel plating and fitted with w/Y; armament one 3pdr Gun and Lewes Guns. Four pulling cutters for work xx* close in shore. (There are four cutters laid up at Bahran belong* -ing to the Port directorate; they would require to be fitted with sails; armament should be Lewes Guns). Seaplanes based at Bahrain would be of very great service. Sd/ H, Boyes, Captain, Senior Malal Officer Persian gulf.v&gt; i ti ~ Telegram (P)^ CONFIDENTIAL. Political, Kuwait, Resident, Bashire; repeated to Highco/na, Baghdad; copy by post to Political Agent, Bahrain. 507-S. 12th December 1Q28, The independent reports &lt;fff recent arrivals from Qasfm and Jaryah confirm the information contained in my telegrams Noo, 501 -S and 503-S (including Ibn Sard’s promise to support the liihwan in an attack on the 'Iraq posts if he failed in his attempt to secure their demolition by negotiation witin a period of two months), A Ibn Sa ud apparently agreed to the Ikhwan's demand that he should cease levying taxes, other than zakat , on the tribes; and they agreed to his demand that they should only deal with such places as he approved. On the conclusion of the Conference he showered presents of money, arms, camels, etc. on 'Uzaiyiz and the other leaders• The general orinion in Kuwait is that, much as he wishes to do so, it will be quite impossible for Ibn Sa'ud to keep the Ikhwin quiet beyond these two months if the posts are still standing and occupied.CONFIDENTIAL, Telegrara (P) To No From Kighcoma, Baghdad. Political, Kuwait; repeated to Resident, Bushire 167-S. Dated IDth December 19^8 A report has been received that a raidin£ party of twenty ftfutalr on ten camels left Samah in the Neutral Zone on the 8th December. Their objective is not known, but it is thought probable that they will come round by Kuwait terri tory and try to raid the Dhaffr or 'Awazfm near Luqtah. An aeroplane reconnaisance has been sent out this morning with orders to fly over Samah and return along the Batin, and have been given authority to bomb the raiders if they can identify them definitely either in 'Iraq or Kuwait terri tory. Please inform the Shaikh of Kuwait. No. 509-S. Political Agency, Kuwait. Kuwait telegram No. 508-S of to-day's date, if forwarded herewith for Information to the Political Agent, Bahrain. 14th December 1928 A copy of the above telegram, referred to in Political Agent, KuwaitCONFIDENTIAL- /■*&gt; Telegram (Pj, From Political, Kuwait. Highcoma, Baghdad; repeated to Resident, Bushlre; To No. Dated Copy by post to Political^ A^ent, Bahrain. ft 506-3. 1 Hh Deoenber 1028 . Your telegram No. t67-S, delayed owlne to an Interruption m the telegraphic communication, only reached me to-day.I have Just seen the Shaikh of Kuwait, and he tells me that two days ago he heard a vague rumour to the effect that i*jo Ibn L£ml, who left the Riyadh Conference without permission and has recently been generally insubordinate, was thinking of 601116 ° Ut As he is said to have been In the Neutral Zone and the numbers are such as he might be expected to have, it may well be he. Shaikh Ahmad says however that another report has Just reached him that Dawfsh has sent to him ordering him to return to his headquarters, as he Is not going to have him stirring up trouble during the truce of two months which has been arranged.&amp; &amp; To Telegram (C). Fron Political, Kuwait. Resident, Bushlre; repeated to Hi£heoma, Baghdad; copy by post to Political A fc ent, Bafcraln. 5tJ-B. 21st December 1928. i ; B 1 Tbn Jlluwi has sent a strong detachment under the command of Muhammad bln Mansur to prevent Najd tribesmen from trauiiig wlth Kuwa it» It at present encamped near Jahrah. ,Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait, Resident, Bushlre; repeated to Hi^hcona, Baghdad; copy by post to Political A^ent, Bahrain, 5 14 - 5 . &lt;:tst December 19^0* TO No. Dated Man of the Shaikh of Kuwait who left Riyadh on 9th December arrived here this evening, Friday. On the way he heard from a reliable source that Daw£sh had just sent messengers to Ifen Sa'ud, informing him that he had sent out scouts to ascertain the whereabouts of Ibn Mijlad, and that if their reoort was satisfactory he was going to r&amp;id him at once* The only news from Riyadh was that Dhaidan, who da didTelegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad; COPT *y Post to Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 521-S. Dated 30th December 1928 . The Shaikh of Kuwait has received a report from his rep resentative at Jahrah this morning, Sunday, that according to a man who arrived there last night, a big raid is about to »e made. Ibn Lami actually started off on the 2?th December (the report does not say from where) and Dawfsh had sent on a force and was following in person almost immediately. Dhaidan al-Hithlain was also out and had Joined Fuqm at Jaryah, and it was thought that Ifcn Shuqair would Join in with these. The man did not know whether one hugh united raid was intended or independent raids, or any** thing about objectives. The Shaikh has sent out patrols, but thinks there is little Imam fear of any action against Kuwait, except possibly by Dhaidan inthe event of independent raiding, and considers ’Iraq a much more probable objective for all. Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad; copy by post to Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 522-S. Dated 31st December 1928. My immediately preceding telegram. A man of the ’Awazim who arrived here from Jaryah last night, Sunday, confirms the report of the arrival of the 'AJman raiding party there. He is vague as to numbers and objective. He too heard that Daw£sh was preparing for a raid.Telegram (C) # From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad; copy by post to Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 5. Dated 6th January 1929. A man, believed to be reliable, who left Riyadh on the 21st December reports th a t there had been talk of impending raids for some time. Ibn Sa'ud had sent word to Ibn Humaid that, as he would not come to Riyadh, he proposed to come to see him at Ghatghat. Ibn Humaid replied that he would not agree to this either, but that he was willing to meet him in the desert. Eventually a meeting was arranged to take place at Shauqi, 93 miles north by west of Riyadh,and Ibn Humaid had invited Dawish and Ibn Hithlain to attens as well. When the man left Ibn Sa'ud was still at Riyadh,but preparations were being made for his journey to Shouqi. It is thought that Ibn Sa'ud is trying to prevent the raid- ing or at least to induce them to delay action, and, al though there is a rouraour that ihx Ibn L^mi raided some Shammar in the Hajarah two days ago, no more raiding seems probable, at any rate until this meeting has taken place. Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad; copy by post to Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 6, Dated 8th January 19^9* My telegram No. 513-S of 21st December. The detachment has left the neighbourhood ajid is believed to have returned to Hasa.Tele 0 ram ( 0 ) Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Kuwait; repeated to and copy by post to Politicti Hi^hcoma, Baghdad; Agent, Bahrain* No. 8 . Dat ed Mth January 1929 . Report rso-»lv»d thlo a mine, Friday, fron a oan of the Awazim, who arrived here last nljiht that ) Xba Hithlaln hae gorn raiding* Objective urumown* Telegram (C). Prom Political, Kuwait* To Resident, Buahire; repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad; and copy by post to Bahrain* No* 12* Dated 16th January 1929 * My telegram No. 8 * No confirmation of the report which is now considered to have been untrue*I%0 \* I i Telegram (c)# Prom Political, Kuwait To Resident, Bushire HoB.M# Consul, Ba; Agent, Bahrain* No# 16* Dated 21 st January 1929 , My telegram No.15. I have obtained the following details. Tne news was brought by a Salabi, who was gathering truffles at Sira' al-Marru// to the north west of Jahrah, and was advised to leave the neighbourhood by a Rashfdi, who told nim tnat I bn Hlthlain was raiding and that he was one of his scouts. He said that the party would spend to-night at Umm al-'Amarah and raid to-morrow morning, Tuesday (not to-day, as I originally heard), and that their objectlv was the 'Iraq shepherd tribes and others in the north west part of Kuwait territory# Nothing is known of the realiability of either man. Tne Shaikh has advised all who can to close in on Jahrah.Telegram, P. Frem - Political Agent, Bahrain, To • Political RooiAent, Buoixire. No. 11 BateA £4th January lvh9. The following information hao been Aerived 1om ABi&gt;ULIAH BIN NiiSIR SUDAIRI who him come, here for medical treatment beginu Bin Jiluwi hay left Haoa for BiaAh leaving his oon BAUD in charge. Hie visit to Bin SauA io said to bo in connection with a warning icoued to Aichwan to be ready to move. The Ulaxaa have privately notified Bin SauA that Jihad io still in existence and that it is his duty to lead the army of Jihad hiwaelf instead of leaving ouch a matter to Dawioh. It io thought therefor© that Bin Saud intends to lead a big force in peraon probably against Kuwait or Iraq as Bin Musad of Hail has sufficient men to deal with Trans Jordan ends Yemen is possible objective. It was mentioned by Nejdia in quoaibi'g majiis that DHAIilAN bin Hathlain intends to raid Iraq tribesmen and Arab of Kuwait. Ho. C.- of 1*29. Political Agency, Bahrain. The 24th January 1929. Copy forwarded for information to the Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram From To ( 0 ) Political, Kuwait. and^Britl sh^onsul lalrah^ t0 H 1 S hcoma ' Baghdad, Agent, Bahrain. ’ * c °Py by Post to Political No. 17 Dait-a 21st January 1929© My telegram N 0 . 16 . Colonel Watson who left here for Basrah shortly before the news of the raiders was received has Just come back. At 1340 hours, when his car got to the Sha'fb Abu Saham in the Abitih, 30 miles beyond Jahrah and 26 short of Safwan, they came up on the raiders in two parties: one of twenty camels with two men on each to their left and a much larger party in front of them which was too.far off to estimate accurately. The raiders on their left opened fire 0 • L! which turned and got away. Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushlre; copy by post to Political, Bahrain. No. 19 . D^ted 22nd January 1929. Following telegram has been received from H.B.M. Consul, Basrah, dated 21at January. Begins. Reference your telegram No.17. Two * • cars with the two Cranes and Bilkert attacked by a dozen raiders about fifteen miles south of Safwan and returned to Basrah with Bilkert and the two Cranes safe..Please inform the American Mission and regard the road as temporarily unsafe. Ends. Bilkert is an American Missionary in Basrah and the others are of Watson's party. Vide your letter No. 2016 of 28th October.Telegram (C) From Political, Kuwait To Resident, Bushire No. 22. Dated 22nd January 1929 , ('Sr copy by post to Political, Bahrain. Following telegram ha s been received from the High Commis sioner for 'Iraq No. 295. Begins: Your telegram No. | 7 . Party consisting of two Cranes and Bilkert, American missionery, travelling yesterday by car to Kuwait were attacked by raiders fifteen miles south of Sanam. Bilkert killed. Both Cranes returned to Zubair safely. Ends. X rear* Basrah, must, have omitted a group. Telegram (P) Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; copy by post to Political, Bahrain. No. 23. Bated 22nd January 1929. The following telegram haa been received from the High Comissioner for 'Iraq No. 5/S dated 22nd January. Begins: An aeroplane has forced landed fifteen miles south of Jabal Sanam in Kuwait territory. Armoured cars are proceeding to its assistance. Ends. Telegram (C). Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad, &amp; H.B.M, Consul, Basrah; post copy to P.A,, Bahrain. No. . 25. Dated 23rd January 19^9* My No.17. Man captured by raiders and detained until yester day afternoon, Tuesday,reports that the party consisted of 1^.0 camel men and 40 horsemen led by Ibn Hithlaln and loxi Lami. They expected to arrive at Umm5( Ruus, 12 miles S.S.W. of Jahrah with what plunder they had taken yesterday evening. Shaikh has mounted troops out.Telegram (C). cr\ Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; postal copy to P 0 A,, Bahrain. No. 26 . Dated 23 rd January I 929 . ’ f y telegram ilo. 22. Bilkert was killed. It was a codifying mistake on the part of Basrah. Telegram (G). From To No. Political, Kuwait. 3U ? hi = e! re P eated Highcoma,Baghdad, and H.B.M, consul, Basrah; postal copy to P,A,,Bahrain. 28 . Dated 24th January 1929 . My. No.25. According to latest information the raiders camped the evening of 22nd January between Saddah and Umm Ruus,after sending on the plundered sheep. They moved on at' dawn,hoping to reach Ma’raj as-Sauban, ,5 miles N .W. by N. of Wafrah,last ni-Btotj Wednesday. - ’ Ira&lt; l road safe again. Telegram $C). Prom Political, Kuwait. T ° H e R i M en ^n 3 U i 1 T rei repeated t0 Hlghcoma, Baghdad,and H.B.M. oonsul.nasrah; postal copy to P.A., Bahrain. Wo, 29 . SI* Dated 24th- January I 929 , My No. 28 . Two armoured cars, under Caswell and patrol cars 'Iraq Army under Macartney Pilgate have just come into Kuwal for petrol and are leaving at once for Basrah. They got to Place where raiders camped near Umm Ruds yesterday, Wednesday, after they had left. Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait, No Resident, Bushire; repeated as usual. D*ted 24th January 1929 . My do. 28 . Raiders are said to have killed six men altogether had^noQuarrel*with %LTlTelegram (C). From Highooaa, Baghdad. Political, Kuwait; repeated to Resident, Bushire, No. 35. Dated 27th January I 929 , reporLs indicate the liklihood of further raids through northern Kuwait aeroplanes are being sent to-day to recon noitre Kuwait territory between Adhaibah, Jal al-Liyah, Umm Qasr, Safwan and RKhatl Ruhail. Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Highcoma, Baghdad; repeated to Resident, Bushire, &amp; H.B.M* Consul, Basrah; post copy to P.A., Bahrain. No. 31. Dated 2?th January 1929 . Your telegram No*36. Would be glad to learn who is thought likely to be raiding now. No reports to that effect received here, o.id, as stated in my telegram No. 28, according to l^a i opm sl t*ion available the Kuwait - ‘Iraq road is considered safe again. No mail car has arrived here from Zubair since the 21st January; mail cars left here on 23rd and 23 th and a private car on 24th. Telegraphic communication has been Interrupted for the last forty eight hours until a short time ago, and, as no cars arrived, the Shaikh sent an armed car to Zubair to-day to find out why. I have Just now seen the Shaikh, and he has heard no rumours of any fresh raid, and considers it highly improbable that there will be another in the near future.Tele&amp;rkm (C). From Highcoma, B&amp;ghdad. To Political, Kuwait; repeated to Resident, Bushire No 3 ' 7 / C Dated 28th January I 929 . Your telegram No.31. Informant from Najd reports that Ibn Yumaid arrived at Artawfyah eight days ago en route for raid on Iraq. It is said that his intention was to raid simultane ously wich Ion Kithlain. Juwirln tribesmen also report having seen strange horsemen near Shlqqat az-Zukhaih who fled on their approach. Telegram (0). From Political, Kuwait. Frafla To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad/ Copy oy post to P.A,, Bahrain. No. 35. Dated 28th January 1929. Baghdad telegram No.37. Minor shaikhs of Kuwait have been out hawking over practically all the country between Jahrah, the Shiqqahs and the Batin - and even across the Batin - during the last two or three days and have seen nothing suspicious. Yesterday some of them met the son of Watban, a close relative of Dawfsh, in the Dibdibah, ahere he was with his women and children. Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad,and Admintor, Basrah; copy by post to P.A,, Bahrain. No. 39 . Dated 30th January 1929 . I have just seen ’Ajll al-Falih as-Sa’dun who arrived from Riyadh this morning,Wednesday. He has no very recent news how ever as he left there about the beginning of January &amp; came qy way of Hasa. He says relations between Ibn Sa'ud &amp; the Ikhwan are very strained and sees no prospect of reconciliation.Miatif and Jubail are being fortified. He heard rumours on the way that Ibn Humald was going raiding against ^Iraq - according . to one he was to leave G-hatghat on 31st January.Telegram (3). (!£* xn Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; Admintor, Basrah; No. 43. Dated 1 st February 192Q. M/ I\o• 39• Mar. who arrived from Sudah vesterday evening,Thurs day, had heard a rumour there that Ibn Huaatd and Dawiah were both ready to raid and were expected to move any time. Telegram (C). Prom Higheoma, Baghdad* To Political, Kuwait. j No. 46. \ Dated Idt February 1929* i Your No. 39 . Informant reports Ibn Rubai'an expelled Ibn Humaid from Ghatghat. Latter with his followers arrived and \ camped near Artawfyah. Dawfsh has moved out his war banner. Some think Dawfsh and Ibn Humaid intend to raid 'Iraq, others that they intend to attack Ibn Rubai' an. Telegram (G). Prom Political, Kuwait* To No. Dated 2nd February 1929* My No. 39 . Confirmation received that Jubail and Qatff and also Hasa are beinf fortified. At Jubail difficulty is being felt owing to lack of suitable clay for building. Rumour has reached here that Ibn Humaid recently summoned Ibn Rubai'an to Ghatghat. Latter was afraid to go alone but sent a message to Dawfsh begging him to come and accompany him,to given tTtr 18 rep0r ' ted t0 have a Sreed. .Vo credence at all is given to the rumour, but it doe, indicate that bad feeling exasts oetween these two 'Utaibah shaiiths. Shaikh of Kuwait tell, me that from Information available he i» Practically certain that Dawfsh at any rate Is still at his headquarters* Higk Resident,Bushire; repeated to Highcoma,Baghdad, &amp; Admintor, Basrah; copy by post to P.A., Bahrain. 45oNo. 77-S. (&lt;&gt; Politioal Agency, Kuwait. I^th February \^2^ 0 To The Political Agent, . BAHRA'IN.* MEMORANDUMo Copies of my telegrams Noo. 55 of 8-2-2y, 62 of 12-2-29, 6 ? of 15-2-2* and 71 of 17-2-29. The raid predicted in the last two telegrams has not yet taicen place. » iL) || Lieut.-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram (C) Political, Kuwait. Resident, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad &amp; Basrah* copy by post to P.A., Bahrain. 67* iDth February I 929 . Urgent. Shai^oi of Kuwait has just received information from a reliable eouroe that a bi 6 raid is Just about to taite Place. One party consisting of contingents led by Ibn Hith- lain, Ibn Shuqalr and Fuqm was at Ma'raJ as-Saub4n yesterday evening, Thursday, is due to arrive at Umm al-Hfran ( 60 miles south-west of Jahrah) to-day,' and intends to raid the tribes in the northern shaqq and Abatlh areas - pre- sumably to-aorrow aorning, Saturday. At the saae tiae Dawfsh -ith .another party is going to raid up the Batin. Telegram (0). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad &amp; Basrah; &amp; copy by post to P.A., Bahrain. No. 71. Dated 17th February 1929 . My No. 67 © A well Known Najdi who often acts as messenger for Ibn Sa'ud's Agent in Kuwait has arrived here.He heard on the way that Ibn Hithlain was at Sarar on the 14th Feb., out was just about to leave for Ma'raJ as-Sauban, where his’ standard already was. Fourteen camels were stolen from two or three Dhafir while asleep a short distance outside Jahrah on the night of the 15/16th February. A party was sent in pursuit in cars yes terday, Saturday, and it succeeded in Recovering the stolen animals and capturing the robbers, wno consisted of one man of the Jiblan Mutair and six of the Rashaidah. This ia con sidered theft - not raiding. The men are in prison in fit V Kuwait.V Telegram (G). From Political, Kuwait. To i?0 No. Dated Resident, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad 4 Basrah copy by post to P.A., Bahrain. wasrah, 55. 8 th February I 929 * My telegram No. 4 5 . It is reported on good authority that Dawfsh has gone to mediate between Ibn Hlunald 4 Ibn Rubai'in. Alter that he intends to raid the 'Ir*q tribes with Glubb near the Batin* Iflegram (G). From Political, Kuwait# To liOo Resident, Bushire copy by post to P ; repeated to Baghdad &amp; Basrah; *A», Bahrain. 6 *. Dated t2th February 1929 „ My telegram No. 55. A man of the Rashaldah reports that Banin Dawlsh has been successful in bringing about a recon ciliation between Ibn Humald and Ibn Rubai'in, and has gone to Jarab where he has unfurled his standard and is awaiting Ibn Hithlaln and Fuqm for certain and probably Ibn Shuqalr and others as well for a big raid. This Is confirmed by a man of the 'AJaln, who left Ibn Hithlaln s camp at Wabrah on the afternoon of the 8 th February, and states that he was-expected to leave the next day to Join Bawfsh at Jarab Bat where all the Ilchwan leaders had been Invited to come - but according to him for a conference. A raid however seems more probable and may be expected In two or three days.T«l«gram .P. From • Political Agent, Bahrain, Te • Heaident, Buohire. No» 31 Dated 28th February 1929» It is reported that BIN RaBAIAN has been ordered by BIN SAUD to encamp at (^aSIM and there await orders. BIN DAWISH has gone to meet BIN HUliAIDjdh, Addressed Resident Bushire repeated Johnston Delhi. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Kuwait. el Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram P. Prom H. K. the High CommiBoinner for Iraq, BaghdacU 'Po H.M’b. Secretary of State for the Colonies, London, ho. 78. Repeated Political Resident, Bushire, ho. 19-S. Dated 2ist (received 22nd ) February 1929. IMMEDIATE . There is no grazing or water in Iraq deaert for flocks of shepherd tribes now concentrated 50 miles south of BUSAIYAH: they will suffer very heavy mortality unless they ge£ at least one month more of good grazing before retiring to summer quarters. Good grazing is obtainable only in neutral zone or Kuwait. in view of general uncertainty of situation and of reported con centration of ikhwan tribes at Jarab, impossible to x±±j allow tribes to graze either in neutral zone or in Kuwait without adequate protection. Paragraph 13(2J of Summary of Dobb ? s memorandum on Desert Defence -- * vide despatch Secret A of 12th October 1928 -- pro- vedes for entry of Iraq army and police cars into neutral zone in situations such as that which have now arisen, but does not provide for entry of armoured cars into neutaal zone. Air Officer Commanding does n not consider armed cars of police and army safe with out further protection of armed cars so long as there is serious danger of raid. On the other hand neutral zone is nearer than Kuwait, and move to latter place may involve consideranle casualties to stock. Also it appears from Bushire telegram dated the 16th Febru that there may be difficulty about armed cars of Iraq army or police accompanying tribes to Kuwait. Tribes must leave present location in three da#'^ time at most. 1 request immediate permission to adopt at discretion *Not received in Bushire.0 ^ Bep«at«d Political neoident, 0/o iforeign aiiu Political rf*^ artif»e*nt, new Delhi. Ku. 122. Dated 2^rd .‘♦'february 1929 X?aiKDlA?K . High Comisiua ioner for Iraq hat) a»ia.*d the Colonial Office for pension!on to move Iraq shepherd tribes immediately for the periua of one month to either Kuwait territory or neutral zone,oi»ing to lack of grazing or *ater in Iraq desert for them. hey are now concentrated bQ Aiiles south-west of HusAiyah. In eitiier case they will be accompanied by police and Iraq Army armed cars as well as British armoured cars. Would the Shaikh of Kuwait object to presence of Iraq for ces. The above telegram is repeated to Political Resident for information. - POLITICAL. Post copy to the Political Agent at for information. for Under Secretary to the Political Keaident in the Persian Gulf. Bushi re, 24th February 1929.Telegram From H.M'b. Secretary of istate for the Colonies, London. oil tic?il Heeid en t, hue hire. Pepeated H.M'b. High Commissioner for Iraq, Ha^haad Ho. 75. Dated 23rd (received 24th ) February 1929. I should be glad to Jaiow whether Iraqi as well as Kuwaiti tribes suffered in raid on January 21st and in that event whether in your view it would be desirable for Hif Majesty's Governnent to address, on behalf of the fhaikh of Kuwait, formal protest to His Majesty King ^ Ibn »&gt;aud. Tome doubt is felt here as to wisdom of such a protest as result might be further to complicate relations between Bin 3aud and the Bhuiich of Kuwait, and thus neutralise any advantage to be secured by protest. '’lease furnish your views but pending receipt of further His ijccellency ( instructions ao not approaah^in the natter. Any &gt; protest made would be on behalf of both the ! huikh and Iraq Government. Has reference to Baghdad telegram Ho. 58, repeated to Bushire under Ho. 55. i - 8KCHKTAHX OF STATS j&lt;t)R ™ ; colohl s. Telegram P. From Secretary to Resident, Bushire. ’'o ’olitical Agent, Kuwait. Repeated Political Resident C/o K. &amp;. p. Bept. , Delhi Ho. 133. Dated 25 th s^ebruary 1929. Following from Colonial Office, begins: '(Here insert text of telegram Ho. 715, above,/.' iCbds. Please wire your views repeating to Sir F. w. # Johnston. a ?P POLITICAL Ib^RIUKHT OMLY . Pree-ume you will reply to Colonial office. POLITIC A'T«U«gram p. ?rma r-noretary of utmU for Colonie®, ixindon. y ° rt • i '* tht iiiigh CoEHiiaui ont r for Ir Bagluliid. no. 76 . &gt;oliileal Mimicient. Miohlre, no. Start (received 24 th ; /ebruary 1929. aq # 77. iiSEliiO.* j;e ^‘opueals contained in your tele grama tioe. 61 and 76, dated the 12th arid 2iet ^ebrua^y reapeetivetyare approved in tie fajr a» they relate te entry into Kuwait provided Uiat iila Knee lie it oy the bhaikh eees no objeetion to concentration in Kuwait of armoured care for the protection of Iraqi tribes for so long a period as one month. hie Kajenty* Oovern- nwnl’e approval to Uieoe arrange!ante la given on the under*tanding U&gt; Uimt pemieaiaa granted is strictly confined to period of present emergency; (;?&gt; that •ituatlen la reviewed by Sir Gilbert Clayton on hie arrival in Iraq; and (3) that further reference shall be made to hie &amp;Jtijeety f » Govemuent ahouio oircuuBtancea at a later stage require reconsideration of problea or grant of fresh authority on lines now given. taxadaw Hie iugeety** GovernMtmt are unable, in viww oi Military and olitical ebjeetione to auoii a course, to agree to for com proposed to aoeoapany tribes into neutral zone since thie wouig involve risk of serious misunderstanding with Hi« ils^ esty King Bin Uauc foroeo which aocompany tribes to Kuwait shoui be redueca to absolute miniwum. and British cars only shouldIngram P. Tram Secretary to Political Kenidtct, auehire Puli tical A 4 ;ent, iluwait. To Repeated Political nesident C/o foreign mid Political No. 150. Dated 24th February 1929. Provided the Shaikh of Kuwait oeea no objection to concentration of armoured cars in Kuwait for bo long ms a period a* one raonth f Hie MajeBty'e Secretary of State for the ColonieB has approved of propo«al to move •Iraq tribes into Kuwait. minimum and that British care only tihould be used unless use of 'Iraqi curs is unavoidable. He has refused to agree to forces proposed accompanying tribes into neutral zone. Please telegraph urgently if his Kxcellency the Shaikh objects to concentration mentioned. Foregoing has reference to my telegram «o. 122. Department, new Delhi H. M's. Secretary of ^tate hae directed that forces accompanying tribes shoul i be oleduced to absolute politi cal. \D£H 1 im post copy forwarded to the Political Agent at for information. Bahrain* for Undersecretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bub hire* 24th February 1929.Teiegrura P. ?row H.U 1 a• ConMfiiesi oner for iraq, H.l/’a. reci*etary of Statd for the Coftoniea, I^ondon, JNo. 87. Political (SUqeiuctKadc HcBidcfnt. BuBhire, ; repeated( j No. 21-S. (Britieli Afjent, Jeddah. j Ko. 21-8. Bated 25th (received 26th ) February 1929. IlfPQUTAKT. 1 hope protest on behalf of Iraq Government will not be delayed. I had assumed that it would be sent immediately on receipt of my telegram giving detail*&lt; In the meantime section of JSAYYAB tribeo has been attacked while grazing in Nejd territory near LAUqAN on tiie 19th ??ebruory by Hejd tribes thought to be SHAMUAH. 250 destitute refugees arrived at 3HABAICHAH state; all property looted and 30 men Killed. Details not con firmed; but I suggest immediate protest. OJuUBN ordered ZAYYA0 to come into safety but owing to lack of grazing had gone to LAUQAH. Poregoing refers to your telegram «o. 7b. — HIGH C0?IHiBr.IONKR. Post copy to the Political Agent at for information. for Linder Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bashire, 26th February 1929. |_Til,fgraiq I From. Political Beaidant in the Persian Gulf, New Delhi To. High Oooml38loner, Baghd id. t Repe ted Political Kuwait, Bushire • No. 0/1. DatiKi 26th (Reed 27th' ; February i929. Presence of Iraq troops has been generally secured by Sheikh in his territoryibut he ?) fe&amp;rs that it will ere tetf a precedent which might incon venience him later. necessary but trusts it will be found possible for only British forces to be utilised. Post copy forwarded to the Political Agent at Provided that latter point is s- feguarded against he will agree if it is considered for information. Bushire, 2nd March 1929. for Under Secretary to the Political ^esicent in the rersian Oulf.Tele gram P. Prom H.U T t. High Conmisuioner for Iraq, Haghdad. To Private Secretary to H.K. the Viceroy, helhi. Repeated Political Kcaicient, Hushire, and Political Agent, Kuwait. Mo. 22-S. 1 st Bated 28th February (received Xuit March; 1929. IMPORTS . Polio win^ for i&gt;ir Prelie rick Johnoton, begins:- » M At present Iraq array cars are not at Kuwait. in view, however, of Kuwait telegram to you which was repeated to me on 20 th instant from Bus hire 1 am not sure whether the Shaikh of Kuwait has yet hiraself expressed an views on the subject o* whether his objections are uefely anticipated » by the Political Agent. I should be glad of an enlighten ment on this point, and also as to Whether objection extends to Iraq police cars.' 'Has reference to your telegram Ho. e-1 of 26th &lt; February.' - HIGH COMMISfUON] Post copy to the Political Agent at fa for information. 7 for Und^r Secretary to the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, 2nd March 1929.(W \vt Teie^rani (G). Prom Politioal, Kuwait, To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad &amp; Basrah* &amp; copy by post to P.A., Bahrain, No, 79 , Dated 20th February 1929* hy telegram No, 62, A man in the employ of the Shaikh of Kuwait, believed to be reliable, abtained information from t,ne Mutalr in the Dibdibah that, after all preparations for a big combined raid had been made, envoys from Ibn Sa'iid came to Jarab and succeeded in persuading Dawfsh to delay opera tions until ,the end of Ramadhan. Ibn Sa'ud apparently urged that he was at the present moment negotiating with His Majesty's Government and that any raiding now would greatly damage his chances of bringing the negotiations to a satis factory eoncliision. If he failed to do so,it would be a different matter and he would then be with them, and he hoped to know one way or the other by the end of Ramadhan. Whatever Ibn Sa'lid's actual arguments were, they were successful, as Dawfsh has cancelled all arrangements and returned to Artawlyah with his standard. Ibn Hithlain, Ibn Shuqair and Fuqm, who are now at Umm as-Sudairah, have received an urgent message from Dawfsh not to raid until after the fast, and they too have disbanded their men. Ibn Humaid, whose recon ciliation with Ibn Rubai'an is confirmed and who was to have taken part in the raid,is near Zllfi, and he also is delaying action. .g) Telegram (C). Prom Folltical, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushlre; repeated to Baghdad 4 Basrah; 4 copy by post to F.A., Bahrain. No. Dated 83. 23rd February )y2C m A few families of Kuwait and 'Iraq tribes camped at Umm Ruus ¥ were warned by a man of the 'Ajman late last nig£t that a small raiding party under Ibn Shuqair, Fuqm and Ibn Lami was about to attach them. He advised them to move at once which they did and came into Jahrah this morning, Saturday. The Shaikh has sent warning by car to the tribes south-east of Jahrah. Truth of the report not known. Telegram (0). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad &lt;£ Basrah, copy by post to P.A., Bahrain. No. • 90. Dated 24th February I 929 . and My No. 85 . No report received of any raid having taken placeTelegram (P). From Political, Kuwait. To No. Dated Hlehoo “' 1 98, 26th February 1929 , Me88en6erB Sent ^ th « Shaikh of Kuwait to I bn Sa-Ud left Hiyadh on their way back on 17th February and have arrived baok with a letter from him. In it Ibn Sa-rfd informs the j Shaikh that he is takine the field in person and is leavir* for ,a 8 fm on * 5 th February with all his forces, but he does ! not say what his objective is. He had not disclosed this point in Riyadh either, but had talked openly about the Desert Posts, Kins Faisal's intrigues, etc, as if to give the idea that he was going to attack Ir4q. There was little doubt however thajj his real intention to try and bring Ibn Humaid into subjection. Ibn Huaald was then in camp between Zllfi and Buraidah and haa eleven standards with him. It was thou^t that his inten tion was to raid Salmon by way of Dinah, and that Firm, who then at AJibbah, was to go with him. According to what they heard from Ibn Sard's servants Ibn Jiluwi had been ordered to march on Llsafah (safah) Dawlsh was at A rt£wlyah when they left, but a report has Just 1 been received here from another source that he moved out to I M Uma al-JamaJim on the 21 st February, MTele&amp;raai (J). Fran Political, Kuwait. To tfo. Dated Political, Sushire; copy by post to P,A repeated to Baghdad &amp; Bushlre. ., Bahrain. ’ 99. 26th February 1929. My No.85. A man of the Raahiidah has Just come la who was told oy a member of the raiding, party that it did actually start, but, on learning that the tribes they intended to raid, had concentrated round Jahrah, they decided to abandon the project. All accordingly went back except a small party of Jiblan who said they -would tr£ and raid some ’Awazim in the Neutral Zone between Kuwait and Najd. It is not known yet whether they did so or not. Telegram (C). Political, Kuwait. Political, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad &amp; Basrah,&amp; copy by post to P.A,, Bahrain. 108. 28th February 19*9. My telegram No. 99. A rumour has reached here that a party of kxsaik Buraih (not Jiblan) raided some ’AJman in the Shaqq a day or two ago thinking they were 'Awazim. On discovering their mistake they restored the plunder. From To No. DatedTelegram (en olair - Jode to Bushire). e Froa To No« Politicaiy Kuwait* Hibhcoiua, Batiidad; repeated lo Adaintor i Special, Basrah find to Bushire; copy to P,A., Bahrain, 114. Dated 3rd March I 929 * My telesran No. 112. The fifty tents off the Ban! Malik are ! If now oelng attacked by raiders under Ibn Shuqalr, Puqm and Ibn Umi at Jalfb ash-Shuyukh, a short distance outside the walls of Kuwait. If aeroplanes could con* now they Ml aight catch them. * Telegram (^ode - en clair to addresses in ’Iraq). From Political, Kuwait. To Ko. Dated My telegram No.,,4. No firing audible now, 0830 hours, but no further details received. The Shaikh has patrol cars out to keep the raiders under observation but the force Is too Mg for him to attack. Kuwait tribes who were further away believed all concentrated Jahrah. 115. 3 rd March 1929 . Political Agency, Kuwait. 3rd March 19 ^ 9 . A copy of the above two telegrams is forwarded herewith for Information ,to the Political Agent, Bahrain, eut.-Col ., ’dlltlcal Agent, Kuwait. ' 'To yoP Telegram (jode - ea clair to addresses ia ’Iraq). Froa Political, Kuwait. Resident, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad &amp; Basrah: &lt;&amp; Q opy by post to P.A., Bahrain. 116. 3rd March 1929 . My No.115. Patrols report 1030 hours that raiders who have five standards are withdrawing south west with such plunder as they have taken. Many tribesmen escaped and saved con- , j j{|| siderable number of sheep which they are now bringing into ' j j 1 town. Several Ikhw4n killed but details not known yet. : Ni A copsr of the above telegram is forwarded here with for information to Political Agent, Bahrain* Lieut.-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agency, Kuwait. 3rd March 19*9. mTelegram,, P» From - Secretary, Buoliir«o To - Political Agent, Bahrain, Ho, 156 Dated and received 4th March 1929, Please repeat sentence about DaWISK in yoor 31, Telegram, P, From - Political Agent, Bahrain, To - Secretary, Bushire„ No. 34, Da.ted 4th March 1929, DANISH is going to join HUMAlDA, Is this what you want„Telegram, P. Frem - Pelitical Agent, Bahrain. Te - Resident, Buehire 0 No. 41. Dated 18th March 1920. BID JILAwI has forbidden departure of Najdia except with hio special permission. This is said to presage early movement/ of troops. It is fact that ne Hajdis have khblh arrived in Bahrain for 3 days. Copy forwarded to the Pelitical Agent, Kuwait, for information. Political Agent, Bahrain.Talteram. P« i'ron - Political A^«nt, Kuwait» To - Political Agont, Bahrain. No. 180. Patoci KiiKxrJiEiiiyjidlQth and rec«iv#dl9tii March 19^9. Have you received information as to whether IBN JILUwT has marched north from Hasa yot or not? Telegram. P Prom - Political .agent, Bahrain. To - Political Agent, Kuwait. Bated 19th March 19P9.TEIEGKAli. p. It 9 m - Palitleal Bahrain. T« - Heaidtnt, Bushir*. N«. 4o Dated 20th March 1929 Rtpertod that BIJH uUIIaID attacked 3 uh-*t^ti#n ef HARB. UJAIR Cuatems which w«r* iasuing passperti received •rderu #n 14th March to discontinue practice, return passport forms to BIB JILAoI and rofor applica.ntB to Hasa 0 Object was to prevent NAJDIS who wore being conscripted from leaving country. estimated to bo two thousand men while SAUL IBP AdDUL A-IZ will command army collected in C,ASIM. King himself will not leave NAJD before his son marches for destination which is still not known. defeated and killed and that Qatif fired guns in honour of ft victory „ Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Kuwait. FaIIaT uIlT JITA-I will load HASA forces Unconfirmed rumour that HUMAII) iias boon PoliticalTelegraa (a). Prom Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Dushire; repeated to Baghdad &amp; Basrah; &amp; L copy by post to P,A., Bahrain. No e 119 , Dated 3rd March 1929 . My telegram No, 116 . It appears from the report of the Shaikh's patrols and the statement of a Salabi whom the raiders captured and subsequently released that the raiding party was aoout six hundred strong and consisted of two standards only - those of Ibn Shuqair and Puqm, Ibn Lami was not present, and the other standards reported were only cloths displayed as a ruse, \s a result of the fight this morning nine Ikhwan and ten 'Iraq tribesmen are known to have been killed and two of the latter oiought Into hospital wounded. The Ikhwan are known to have had sorae wounded. Car patrol saw the boabine, by the aeroplanes and speak most enthusiastically of their work. They say however that owing to the sandy nature of the ground many of the bombs did not explode. As far as they know only three camels and one mare were killed and three men wounded. As the raiders are hampered by the plundered sheep, they can hardly be out of Kuwait territory by tomorrow morning, Mon day, Political Agency, Kuwait. 3 rd March 19^9. A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith for information to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Lieut.-Jol., Political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram (j) No Dated Prom To Political, Kuwait* Political, Bushlre; repeated to Baghdad &amp; Basrah; and copy by post to P.A., Bahrain. 127. 5th March 1929. Man describing himself as being In Glubbs employ who arrived Jahrah yesterday evening, Monday, brings rumour staunch member of the IkhwAn at Llnah on or about the &lt;i4th February. I » This report is confirmed by a sheep dealer who arrived here last night from the gaslift direction. He adds that Dawfsh 1 raided Liz&amp;a Abu Dhira’ of the Dhaf£r, who is also regarded as a partisan of Ibn Sa’ud and was with him in Riyadh quite recently, in the TawAl north of Hafar about the 28th camels. He further reports that Ibn Sa'ud is said to have reached Buraidah. A copy of the above telegram is forwarded here with for information to the Politi - ^ 1 J ‘ '~“ that Ibn Humaid raided Ibn RlznfiCl of the Shamaar and a February, and captured his sheep and tents but not his Political Agency, Kuwait. 8th March 19^9.I Tel«&amp;r&amp;a (C)• Ffoa Political» Kuwait* To Political, Bushlre; repeated to Baghdad &amp; Baarah, No. 125. Dated 7th March 1929. My telegrao No* 96. A aeaaenger who left Riyadh on the 27th February reports that Ibn Sa'ud was still there then, but was leaving for Buraldah by oar hleeelf on the 2nd March, and his force under his son, Sa'ud, was Marching soon after that date. He heard that Ibn Huaald had gone raiding, but not Dawish, who was believed to be at Artawlyah. Political Agency, Kuwait. 7th march &lt;929. A copy of the above telegram la forwarded herewith for Information to:* The Special Service Officer, Kuwait. The Political Agent, Bahrain, - Lieut.-Col., Politic a Agent, Kuwait.Tele^ra* Fro* Political, Kuwait. To Rebideat, BUbhire. J56. Dated l^th March 19^9. A aan of the 'Awazin who has Just arrived froa the south reports that the advance party and ba^a^e of Ibn Jiluwi’s force arrived at Anta' on the tOth March and are awaiting hia there. The ’Awizii* had had orders to 'love out on the 13th Earoh t0 3,e * t Ibn Jiluwi Who was to naroh fro* Hasa with a A oop/ of the above tele b ra* Is forwarded herewith to here &lt; Political Acency, Kuwait. IJth March 19^9. Political A^ent, Bahrain. Special Service Officer, Kuwait.Telagra®-X (&amp; 1^ Dated High Commissioner, Baghdad. Secretary ef State f#r Colonies,!^© 92. Repeated Bushire, Kuwait and Jeddah,N® 23 3rd (reed 4th) March 1929. This morning feur to five hundred Akhwan raiders attacked Iraq sheperd trihe near Kuwait. Raiders were followed up hy aeroplane which came in contact with them about 20 miles south of Kuwait. Raiders opened heavy fire killing one wireless operator; they were bombed and machine guned with go )d result. Within the last 6 weeks this has been the fourth raid on Iraq tribes as it nov/ appears that there was a raid on February 19th on Iraq Shammar at Gaisuraa in Nejd as well as raid at Lauqa reported in my telegram of 25th February No 87,repeated t® Bushir® and Jeddah No 22-3. • Acc®rding to information sent by Bin Baud in his letter to Sheikh of Kuwait ,former was to leave Riyadh on February 25th for Qasim with all his forces. Bid Saud did not state kix the onject of his movement but his most likely object seems to be to secure control of tribes. It therefore seems most desirabLe that a strong protest should be made t© him at once against these repeated attacks on Mesopotamian tribes fail fa, . Telegram P Fr®m. Political,Bushire. To. Foreign and Political Department,New DeiC* N®. 154. Dated the 4th March 1929. This .X X X tribes. Ij ij Foregoing is f®r Political Resident fr®m High commissioner,Baghdad t® Secretary of State for Colonies 92 repeated Bushire,Kuwait and Jeddah 23-S. (rTS -v.' CCZ' f h. i --isksum* 277 ^roDt }olltlo 1 Hsaldsnt, Busblro* To. High '/OEfliiaaioner, Bachdad J epaated Politioal /igent, Kuvalb. No. 180. Bated the 15th March 1929 Tour telegram 29-3 1 am in general agreement with iolitioal Agent* Kuwait's telegram Ho 160. 1 I understand that owing transport dim- r oulties deputation oould not leave and its going later would be little use. ahsikh however is making full enquiries. Hequlrlng stoppage of , ;2UTAlE supplies at preaant stage would bring the 3heikh into the quarrel and in view of his peculiar position I see no advantage in doing this unless and until necessity la shown and we are in position to afford him full support if attacked. hen I bn Jiluwl gets closer possibly difficulty may solve Itself. Host copy Bent to the Political for inform*tioiybnly. Agent at Bushire, 16th March 192 9.s (Z2g) r. From. Political Besident, Bushire. To. Polltioal Agent* Kuwait. no. 131. I*t«d tbe 15th March 1989. Berorence your telegram repeating aiut)oa. ^ In view of your 160 I see no reason to threaten Sheikh who realises gravity of situation and will doubtless aot up to his romise to deal draaticall y with his offending subjects if any plunder is found. Post copy sent to the Political Agent at lor inforraatlor^bnly. 'I Bushire # for Unc er Secretary to the Political Kesident, J J ersiari Gulf. 16th Mardi 192 9.Tolagraa (C). ?roni Politic il, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad &amp; Baarah^ also In absence of Special by W/T to Avia tion, Glubb, Howea &lt;4 Special, Baarah. No. 1^6. Dated *lat Marcd Shaiich has received letter fron Ibn Saud written at Shaqra on 7th XXXMXXXXX March when on way to Buraidah* It cane via Bahrain and contains no news. ) i Kuwait man has arrived from Hasa having left on nth March. A force was being organized but It was not Jcnown when it would march or whether or not Ibn Jiluwi would lead it in person. Prom another source it is rumoured Ibn Jlluwl has been ordered to stand fast pending further instructions. Opinion gaining ground here that Ibn Saud will not fi^ht. Political Agency, Kuwait. &lt;;let March 19 * 9 . * A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith to The Political Agent, Bahrain. ,ieut. -dol., Political Agent, Kuwait. ; i In i -Tele^raa (0). (S’) Polltioal, Kuwait* Resident, Bushlre; repeated to Hi£&gt;hco;ia,Ba&amp;kdad # St * Adnintor, Basrah; also (by W/T) to AYiation,Baghdad, Glubb, Howes,b’Eslriyah &amp; Special, Basrah* 205 22 nd March &lt;929* Unoonfirned ruaour reached here that Ibn Rubalan and Pira hare seized and tfk surrendered to Ibn S&amp;ud soae of the m MAHACHIP'' (ex raiders) and plunder froa Ibn Huaaid's Shaaaar raid, and also that Dawish has sent Ibn Saud conciliatory aessage* Addressed Resident repeated as ay 196 Political Agency, Kuwait. 22nd March 1929. A copy of the above telegraa is forwarded herewith to The Political Agent, *Tele&amp;raa (C). Froa • Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Buchire No 212 Dated 24th March 1929* Man who left Jau Manakh in Suaaan on 18th March reports that aessen^er froa Dawish had ju&amp;t arrived there with orders for all Mutair in neighbourhood to Join Dawish ' f forthwith- These orders had been ibsued with iiitexition of attacking Firn at AJibbah, but Just us Kesse^er was about to leave Dawish’s caup letter arrived froa Ibn Hunaid urt,int Dawish to come to his aid at Ja'lah at once as Ion Saud had aoved out of Buraidah and was advancing towards hir* with a very large force# Ibn Saud was still talking about peaceful settlement in accordance with the religious * law but Ibn Humaid did not believe his peaceful intentions and considered fight inevitable. ? r an who brought news still in 'Uraibdar camp but has been sent for. Addressed Reticent, Bushirc by cable; repeated by W/T tc Hlohcoaa cc Aviation, Acmintor a Special Basrah, and Glubb; copy to Howes on arrival Political Agency, Kuwuit 24th Uarch 19^9* X copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith to The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Special Service Officer, Kuwait. Political Agent, Kuwait(?V) Telegram Gode. prom political, Kuwa it. To Resident, Bushire. No. 236. Dated 28th March 1929. Qlubb'B 914 March ^7th. heginB. Man from yraibdar states camelmen from Najd reports Ibn 3a*ud at Buraidah and stories skirmishing ^vith Ibn Bumaid untrue. Ibn Hithlain Joined forces with Awaaim Bani Ha jar and other tribes. Reported also wrote to Naif Aba al-Kilab to join him. Messengers also sent by him to Ibn Sa , ud and Ion Giluwi purport unknown. Other man from Awazim denies they joined Ibn Hithlain. If they nave latter must now have large forcec Reports Ibn Jiluwi moving out now denied. All reports confirm inter-raiding between Mdtair Barb and Sebei. Najd in chaos and news very difficult sift. Tele&amp;ra* (0). Fro* Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Buihipe, No. 239* Dated 28th March 1929« Glubb’s 916 of 28th March. Begins. Ruaoured here two Mutairii passed en route Kuwait stated ’Uzaiyiz Dawish visited Ibn Sa’ud and arranged Ibn Huaaid return loot taicen fro* Najd tribe*. Ibn Sa’ud accepted settleaent this basis. Dawish surety for return of all loot. ■mp' - Political Agency, Kuwait. 28th March 1929. A copy of the above two telegrams is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ / L-1 7 / L l/ j. £/ Lit,—Ool., Political Agent, Kuwait,Telegram Eri olair. pro m Qlubb, To Advisint, Avn. NO. 917. pated ^7th March. 1929. Man who claims to be servant Mubarak bin Durai Shaikh » Awazim arrived here. States bearer message from his master to efleot Awazim are on side of Government and ibn Sa'ud . Strenuously denies Awazim joined Ibn Hithlain. States ibn Majid of Mutair Dushan raided camels from Ibn Hithlain. Ibn Shuqair and Puqm at Jar^yah. Ibn Hithlain at Ma’&amp;ijili. Naif Aba al—Kilab at jau ManaKh in suarngg summan objective unknown. Awazim all collected east of Subaihiyah with Bani Khalid thirty miles south of them. No sign of life from ibn Jiluwi. Confirms accounts inter-raiding betwe-n Mutair Sebei and Harb. • Former also raided two flocks camels belonging Ibn Jiluwi. Reliability unknown. Telegram (C) prom political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bus hire. No. 240. Dated 26th March 1929. Extract Glubb*s 917 March x X joined Ibn Hithlain. Ends. Political \genc.T, Kuwait. 28th March 19-29. K copy of the above telegraa is forwarded herewith to Bahrain Political Agent, KuwaitTJ-k S Telegram En olair. Fro m - Qlub b. To - Avn, Advisint, Howes Kuwait. No. - 930. % Dated - 30th Mar oh 1929. Agent from Awazim reports that tribes all joined ] Hithlain. Confirms Mutair raided Ibn Hithlain»s sheep a oamels whioh were camped in summan. Majority but not ail eventually paid back. Reports Abu Shnwairi-^at raided 1 but repulsed with loss . on return home found few tents • Harb with Mhtair and raided them to revenge his defeat. Tele gram (c) . prom - politioal, Kuwait. To - Resident, gush ire. No. - 253. Dated 30th March 1929. A copy of the above telegram is forwarded to the Politioal Agent, Bahrain. Olubb's 930 March 30th. Begins. Agent x x X X x defeat. Ends. Politioal Agency, Kuwait- Dated the 30'th March 1929.Tele^raa (C) Pro a Political, Kuwait Resident, Bushire 2^8. To No Dated 31st March 19^9* Extract froa Glubb's No. 938 of 30th March. Beeins. Agent froa the Mutair usually reliable reports that Mushari bin Musaiyis acconpanied ’Anqari and other^ religious leaders froa Ibn Sa’ud to Ibn Huaaid and Dawfsh. Believed offer to refer disputes to religious law accepted. Both parties proceed to rendezvous, 'Ain Ibn Fuhald. 2nds. A copy of the above telegraa is forwarded herewith to P.A., Bahrain. Political Agency, Kuwait 31st March I 929 Political Agent, KuwaitCode Telegram Prom high Comal bb! oner, o&amp;ghdad To aecretary oT ctate for the colonies ao.iCli he^eateu nusAlre, i.uwalt and Jeadah ho»i.i4« Dated tue 2drd (received 24thJ March x9Z9* COhPIDhhTlAL* Poliowixig ib brief appreciation sit- uatiun in nortnern X\ie w d baoed on recent ruporto from more reliable eource* (ij fbn baud moved from iii^adh to j^uraidaii at tx^e be ginning of March and has ^iven out txxat he in colledii^ forces to subdue refractory section of At&amp;iuah, i.utair and Ajman tribes wriich have been responsible for recent raids, (ii) Tnere have been strong rumours that ibn jiluwi Qovernor of hasa, at Ibn baud's instructions was collecting forces of H&amp;sa tribes to co-operate. Latest reports state there are some doubts on truth of these rumours, (ill) Ibn Humaid (Ataioanj Paisal al Dawish (hutair; anu Ibn Hithlain (Ajiaan; against which ibn bauds prepara tions are said to be directed appear a^prehensive, i bn huxiiaid after nis recent raiding expeuitiuns to Hozul area has travelled r&amp;pialy soutn ana iias prooably joined forces witn nawish between Ajibba ana Artiwi^an, ibn iiithlain's lorce and certain Autair section under ibn .iitu^air, ibn Lugiiia aiid Ibn Lami are reported betweexi soutnern oorder oi Kuwait and Al bafa protecting ttie flaunt of main Autair force from ibn Jiluwi, wnile threatening to raid •Iraq tribe tiirougn Kuwait territory# (iV) It is doubtful whether ibn baud really intends to attack rebellious shelihis or merely to bring then to terms. Tribal opinion discredits former alteruetive a^d it is ni - niiioant tnat ibxi liusaad of hail appeura to be taking no action so tnut Ibn baud's forces are unlikely to oe reatly superior in number, moreover ue msy ^ reluctiuit tc force a*, issue at a time when pilgrimage i tt imminent and will re-Telegram P From. Political Resident, Bushire. To. High Commissioner, Baghdad 'Repeated Political . gent,Kuwait. No. 210. Dated the 26th March 1929. Present case seems essentially one in which correspondence should go through the Resident. I regret therefore that Political Agent cannot he authorised to convey his opinion direct. Foregoing is with reference to your Political Secretary's No 673 dated the 21st March. Telegram P . From. Political Resident t Bushire. To. Political Agent,Kuwait. No. 213. Dated the 2oth Marc*. 1929. Can I expect to receive your reply through Basrah hy fast mail of 1 arch 36th. • Foregoing is in continuation of my telegrm No 210. Post copy to the Political Agent at for information only. / / * For under Secretary to the Political Resident in the .Persian Gulcf. Bushire, 27th March 1929.Telegram P From. Political Resident, Bushire. To. Secretary flff State for the Colonies No 5 Repeated Foreign,New Delhi f Political {No 211. Kuwait and High Conunissioner,Baghdad} Bated the 26th March 1929. I agree entirely with Political Agent. Above is with reference to Political * Agent Kuwait’s telegram repeated as follows Begins No 210 dated March 24th X. x X Ends B / Post copy to the Political Agent at for information only. For under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Peruian Ouifccf. Bushire # 27th March 192 9.' T^le^raa (a). p ron Politieal, Kuwait. To Rweldwnt, 3u»hirw; repwatwd to Hit^iooaa,Baghdad and Adaiator, Basrah. NO. ft6iZ£ m Dated and April 19k9. Man beliavad to be reliable arrived 'Uralbdar aajxp reports that he left Jarab on \$th March. Ibn Huaaid and Dawleh whose united force* amounted to about ?00C men both left there that day for Slbilah. He heard from the Mutair in the Suaaan whoa he left on 27th March that botn had since aoved into Zilfi itself. Ibn Sa’ud’s force believed to be at Ja lah. ^Negotiations were in progress and Dawish was anxious for peace but Ibn Huaaid was more stubborn. Addressed Resident in Persian Gulf repeated High Commission^ er and Basrah also to Glubb Political Agency, Kuwait. 2nd Marsh 1929* A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith to Political Agent, Bahrain. Speeial Service •ffioer, Kuwait. mM / ^^'Tdeut.-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait. Tv /ooi^idmtxal. No. 245-S. Fro^ Political Agency, Kuwait. 28th March 1929. Lieutenant-Colonel J. C. More, D.S.Q Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Le t ter» for I bn 5a 1 ud_. Sir, I hare the honour to request that you will forward the enclosed letters to King 'Abdul Azfz c.s-Sa ud by the quickest means available. I received then from the Political Secretary to His Excellency the High Commissioner for 'Iraq for onward despatch from Kuwait, but owing to the disturbed state of the country at present it is impossible to guarantee their safe arrival from here direct. I have the honour to be. Sir, * Your most obedient servant, r., ,ieut. -Col., Political Agent, Kuwait. dopy, with compliments, in continuation of my telegram No. 244 dated 28th March 1929* to The Political Secretary to H.5. the High Commissioner for 'Iraq, Baghdad. The Secretary to the Hon'ole the Political Resident in tne 'D a. n ill 11 mi Vi \ IT* G* ^, ' • , ■ T®ltgra» w . Trtm High Com Ins loner, Bu^hdod. To ■olitioul Monitiont, Hun hire. ^•pe«*«&lt;l tolitl sol Agent, Auwoit. Mo. 33- &lt;&gt; • Duted let (reoeiTed 2nd ) April 192V* ✓ Within a tew day» Iraq tribes ehouici all be on northern rrontler. They however will itareto reiaain thera for bob* time and will doubtlese be grafting across into Kuwait territory# shitty will tiien he exposed to possible sporadic raiding no i should liice rhaikh*e consent to our taking such aeasuree as rmy be neoessa^ to control and protect then# left;rence is to your telegrtm Ho. 223. HIGH OCUUX MOHVn. l^o■ t copy to the Political Agent at \jCbb/V*****’ for information only. for Under Secretary to the ’olitical Kesicent in the Persifln Guj.f. Bub hire, Snd April 192 91'Z2P1 Tele gran 9» Itroin 'oil tx c&lt;a Kcuidcnt, but) ;Ju*e . To Hlgla (Joraiiaeiono r for Xra*; 9 Heyaatoa roXltioaX Agent, Kuwait. Ho. 258. ’Hated 2nd Ayril 19i!9. Shaikh haft already coneentea to short extension of tin* after int April. PXease state store expllaltly E&amp;easures you desire nhaiJch’s oonuent to taking thereafter. Foregoing refers to your , dated 1st April. - he aider! t. i 3 ©b t copy to the Political Agent at for information only. for Under Secretary to the '’olitical Resident in the Persian Gu^f. But hire, 2nd April 192 91— ‘ —con *n&gt;T:nr xal. Ho. 86-tJ• of 1929. British Hesidensy i^d Consulate-General, Bushire, 26th March 1929. yro» The lion # ble Sir F.w. Johnston, K.C.I.B., C.S.I., Politieal Hesident in the Persian Gulf, To The foreign Secretary to the Govem/ient of Inciia, Bee Delhi. Sir, Xn continuation of ay endoraeaent ho. 7b-li., dated the 9th Maroh 1929, X have the honour to forward a copy of a letter Bo. S.O. 673, dated the 21st March 1929, from the Political he ore t ary to the High Cotatais si one r for Iraq, Baghdad, and of my telegraphic rej.ly Ho. 210, dated the 26th March 1929. 2. There has of late been noticeable a tendency on the part of the High Commissioner to desire to deal direct with the Kuwait Agency dn all matters, and, while 1 can see no objection, in fact distinct advantage in the '•'olltical Agent, Kuwait's sending direct to Baghdad telegrams containing information or statements of fact that are useful and urgent, there seems to be the strongest objection to any direct correspondence on questions of policy as in the present case. 3. As regards the subject matter of the letter, there would been to be no advantage in offering any criticism/ ±7- Copy ofConfidential letter No. S.0.673, dated 21st March 1929 from the Political Secretary to the High Comraissioner-fo r Iraq, Baghdad, to the Secretary to the Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (Attached) I am directed to enclose, for the information of the Honourable the Resident in the Persian Gulf, a copy of two Notes by Captain Glubb, Administrative Inspeetor-in-Charge Southern Desert, on the subject of the attitude of the Shaikh of Kuwait in connection with the recent raid by Akhwan upon the Iraq tribes. ^ 2. A situation such as that described in this correspondence neutralizes all the efforts which are being made to protect innocent shepherds from these brutal and ruinous attacks but before considering what measures should be taken to remedy an intolerable state of affairs, His Excellency the Acting Commissioner txxx would be glad to learn how far, in the opinion of the Political Agent at Kuwait, the Shaikh of Kuwait could give a satisfactory answer to any of the accusations levelled at him by Captain Glubb. A copjir of this despatch is being sent direct to the Political Agent, and His Excellency would be grateful if he could be authorised by telegram to convey his opinion direct to Baghdad, in order to avoid the delay involved in sending it via Bxghntatit Bus hi re. Any interim comments on the situation which the Resident may desire to make would be welcomed. 3. A copy of tills despatch is also being sent to the Secretary of State for the Colonies. toLv •.L‘ ^Copy of SECRET Mote Mo. 754, dated 12th/l5th March 1929, by Captain J. B. Glubb, Adminietrative Inspector In-Charge Southern Desert, Adhaira, to the Adviser, Ministry of Interiot, Jbticgd Baghdad. fth.fcjc ct; Relation Y/ith Kuwait. As is well known, the principality of Kuwait was until a few years ago, one of the chief powers in Arabia, and dealt on an equal footing with Ibn Sa’ud, Ibn Rashid and the Sharif. XtaBh Though his territory was not so very extensive nor his tribes no numerous asthose of hit) allies or rivals, his financial resources, chiefly derived from pearling, were considerable. Moreover the Kuwait deserts, though not comparatively very extensive, supply most excellent grazing, and the Ajman, Mutai*, Rashaidah, Awazim and other large tribes have frequently in the past placed themselves under the protection of the Shaikh. The present Shaikh from the time of his kuxbhXbxj accession, however, has shown ftimself completely incapable of dealing with the crisis with which the Akhwan menace have threatened his town. Almost all the tribes which owned allegiance to Kuwait when Ahmad ibn Subah succeede have gone over to the Akhwan. Many of them, such as t) Awazim, continue to live in Kuwait territory, but own allegiance to Ibn Jiluwi, the Governor of Hasa, who ta them and orders ]&amp;hem about within the boundaries of Kuwait. The miserable remnants of the Kuwait tribes have, for the last two or three years, spent most of their time cowering beneath the walls of the town. Although Ibn Subah is generally reputed to have plenty of money, he does not seem to relish spending it on defending his country. This year, however, the situation has taken on an entirely new aspect. For the past 18 months, ever since thethe Duwish has been virtually in revolt against ibn ‘ &gt;a, ud, he has endeavoured to secure at ally in Ibn Xx£xA Subah. All bedouins have to purchase their necessities in some coast or river town, a bedouin * banned by the authorities of all the towns, can be brought to book without fighting. liutair, threatened a blockade on one side in hajd, and on the other in Iraq, were until recently in a very alcward position. 1 Last autumn, however the Duwish and Ibn Subah made a private agreement, according to which the latter would break the blockade of both Ibn Sa»ud and the Iraq Government and throw Kuwait open £o Mutair, on condition that the Duwish promised not to raid Kuwait any more. This agreement 1ms since px ripened into a regular alliance, and the Shaikh has undoubtedly not only opened Kuwait to Uutair but has helped the rebellious Ak&amp;wan, Ajman as well as Mutair, in every possible way. It is even reported that he has made gifts of money, arms and ammunition to Mutair, « tout this cannot at present be proved. The okaikh, however, does not of course desire entirely to alienate His Majesty’s Government. He therefore denies his shady transactions with Mutair, and even endeavours to maintain an appear, anoe of friendship by dolins out occasionalJ,its of intelligence to the Political Agent. THR IBfl HI-’HLAIN T?ATT&gt; . It is not easy to prove anything against Ibn Subah in the case of the Ibn Hithlain raid, except in so far as it may be said that a large part of the tribal group subject to Kuwait and known as Araibdar, are themselves Ajman and that details of all the movements and intentions of the AJchwan V| f Ajman are daily knovm in Kuwait. Moreover Ibn Subah had probably received a prior assurance from IIbn Hithlain that he would not raid Kuwait tribes. On his return from his successful raid on the Iraq shepherds Ibn Hithlain actually passed Jahrah and «amped at Umm Rus, where, he divided the lofct. Ibn Hithlain had only about 140 men, whereas Ibn Subah ean certainly raise four or five hundred horse and camelmen. Yet not a shot was fired by the Kuwaitis. This may perhaps be attributed to the weakness or cowardice rather than treachery. Still weakness and cowardice are not desirable qualities in one who professes to be an ally. Since then, however, affairs have become far worse. There can be little doubt, from in numerable reports, that Araibdar have been acting as regular spies for the Ajman and liutair for the past month. In this connection, please see this office telegrams tos. 333, 360 of 11-2-29, 12-2-29, respectively. Sa’ud ibn Hajruf is one of Ibn Subah’s principal men. IBH SHPAIR'S RAID . The crowning disgrace of these altogether shady incidents, however, was the recent raid by Ibn Shqair. As already explained to the Ministry, al most the whole of the Bani Maliif dira has been awarded to Kuwait in the Anglo-Hajd-Kuwait agreements. Ibn Subah has long been a patroO of this tribe. At the time of Ibn Hithlain’s raid, the greater part of Bani Malik fled to Safwan. Aportion of the tribe, however, took refuge with Araibdar, with the idea pt placing themselves under the protection of Ibn Subah. In accordance with this plan, it is reported that, on joining Araibdar, they visited Ibn Subah, and presented him with tribute in the form of 'dhibihas'. It is stated that this tribute was accepted. By Arabcustom, the acceptance of such 'khawa' involves a moral obligation to defend the giver, even with one's life. Anyone who does not propose to defend the g™* givers of 'khawa' should refuse to accept the latter. Ibn 3h(jair and Al Fugham originally moved up, with the intention of raiding Iraq tribes in the Vmm al Madafa-'taudhatain area, as hud been successful! done by ibn JUthlain. on reaching Aba al Miran, however, (Abu al Haram on mapj they received reports of air reconnaissances ana car patrols in front of these tribes. They had no desire to fight a battle or risk losses, but, according to the almost invariabl Akhwan habit, they hoped to surprise a camp which they could outnumber by ten to one, and massacre it without loss. They therefore abandoned the idea of raiding in the Umm al Madafa area, and went into camp. At this stage, they heard of the presence of Iraq shepherds with Araibdar. They had received xxxX: instructions from the Duwish not to raid Araibdar themselves, as Ibn Rubah was an ally of Mutair, But here was a small camp (about fifty men to their five hundred) of Iraq subjects, who had innocently placed themselves under the protection of an ally of the Buwish. Ibn Shqair accordingly sent a messenger to X Ibn Rubah, warning him to move Araibdar away from the shepherds, as the Kuslimin were about to raid the latter. On receiving this message, Araibdar hastily moved south and camped close to Mutair, leaving the shepherds alone at Jahrah. The latter fled to Kuwait where they camped beneath the walls of the town, and appealed to Ibn Subah. it is stated that Ibn Subah ”■** said to Ibn Shqair's messenger that X 3 §&amp;i&amp; Wutair could nnt raid the shepherds in their then position which was almost in Kuwait bazaar, but that they could do so as they liked if the shepherds moveda little way off. Mutair accordingly picqueted the shepherd camp and also placed men in Kuwait town and Jahrah, to watch for any sign of movement by the shepherds. A patrol car from Bani Malik at Safwan, accompanied by a camel constable in plain clothe*, at this time visited Jahrah to obtain news. They report that ^^~ saw a number oi Akhwan camelmen staying in the house of one of Ibn Subah's men in Jahrah village. On enquiring they were told that these men were the scouts of Ibn Shqaif's raiding £&amp;rty. The shepherds at Kuwait at this time sent a message to the Administrative Inspector, asking for help. The Administrative Inspector cross questioned the messenger carefully as to whether the cam* was in any danger at the moment. He ( the son of Shaikh of Bani Malik) replied -oh noJ they are quite safe where they are. They are almost in Kuwait town. But they cannot ge£ out without ris^, as they are surrounded by scouts of the raiders, who are also sitting in Kuwait and Jahrah-. nobody imagined it possible that Ibn Subah would allow the shepherds, who. to Arab ideas, were under his protection, to be raided at the very gates of his town. The Adminis trative Inspector therefore sent his telegram tio. 558 of 28-2-29, to Air Headquarters, asking for assist ance to escort the shepherds hack from Kuwait, but. in Air Headquarters’ telegram ho. JB/l of 1-3-29, the request was refused. He thereupon sent the messenger back to Bani Malik, with instructions to arrange fuxx a date with them on which he (the Administrative Inspector) with the *** police would meet and escort them back. The day after, however, the camp was raided.6 i&amp;Z) The Administrative Inspector has since nx&amp;k examined ttie tracks of Ibn rvhqair^ raiding party, when they advanced to attack. ’f’hey crossed Al Hhaqq north of Miniaqish and must have passed almost through the camps of Araibdar. While this march was of course accomplished at night, yet if Araibdar had sent word to the shepherds during the previous night or even an hour before the attack, the majority of them could have crowded into the market place within the town walls. It is eve 3^ alleged that the night before the attack Ibn Subah sent messengers to warn Araibdar, but I have not found any proof of this allegation. .i:ie attack took place on a level plain ex— tenaing from the wallsof the town to a distance of about three or four miles away. Police who examined the site state that the tracks of the charging horses ol the raiders wheeled only a few hundred yards from the town walls. The noise of shots, and the shouts and shrieks of the combatants and victims , were heard by the people in their houses in Kuwait. As soon as the raid began the Hhaikh order ed the town gates to be closed. A number of the men of Bank Malik were inside the town* Mad with excite ment at hearing the shout and cries of the sons and brothers outside, they struggled to ge/ out to their assistance, but it is said that the Shaikh's men refused to open the gates and bea/back the shepherds with blows and the flats of their swords. Meanwhile on tiie level plain outside the walls, the Akhwan were busy slaughtering. They outnumbered the shepherds by about ten to oner There was no way of escape, behind them was the sea, and to their flank the town walls. It is said that about four men took refuge in a rnined building near the walls, where they opened(*■73) - 7 - opened a heavy fire and repulsed Xxm their pursuers. The remainder of the camp ivas exterminated. Hever has the present writer heard of 4 more disgraceful or brutal incident in the history of Arabia. Kuwait is a large town and the Shaikh has hundreds of retainers. If these men had e^en manned the walls and opened the gates to the fugitives, some survivors could have found shelter. UUSABLAH. irl It is well known that all bedouins depend entirely on towns for the purchase of their necessities, and if access to towns can be forbiddento them, they can be bcough t to ahstn obedience without fighting. Now it is not a question of Ibn Subah T s maintaining neutrality between Iraq and Ibn Sa’ud. Mutair and their allies are outlaws, rebels against Ibn Sa’ud and hoitile to His Majesty’s Government and Iraq. Both Ibn Sa’ud and Iraq have for several months attemp ted to enforce a blockage against them, with the result that, by last autumn, they were in considerable straits 'The T&gt;uwish then made a private agreement with Ibn Subah, promising seouruty to the latter’s subjects from Akhwan raids, on condition that the Shaikh sup plied the rebel Akhwan with food and other necessities from Kuwait. The bargain had been observed. The Puwish has warned all the Akhwan that no Kuwait tribes are to be interfered with, and Kuwait town has been billed with Mutair caravans since last autumn up to the present day. Mutair have ample money, sheep and property taken in their many raids on Iraq and nowthat they have betured the alliance of oneof the principal ports in Arabia in which to dispose of their loot and buy supplies there is no reason why they should not hold out against Ibn r&gt;a’ud and the Government indefinitely.indefinitely. This is Ibn r»ubah f s chief crime. He may argue that he was not bound to help Bani Malik and he may deny that Araibdar are assisting the Akhwan, but he cannot fret away from the fact that he himself is definitely prolonging the present state of chaos by supplying the rebel Akhwan with those necessities which both Ibn 3a*ud and the Government are attempt ing to deny them. Incidentally ammunition, which is very scarce in T Iraq owing to (Jovernment measures, is said to be both cheap and plentiful in Kuwait, where the Akhwan are purchasing it freely. There can be no doubt that the prolongation of the present state of ohaos due to the Duwish - Ibn Sa’ud alliance is costing and will cost His Majesty’s Government large ^ums of money. Unless His Majesty’s Government is willing to bring pressure to bear on Ibn *oubah to enforce a blockade as is being done by Iraq and Ibn 3a’ud, there is little prospect of peace on the Najd frontier. S©/ ^3T-Gitabb, Admin io^-po, t-i- ve—1 -b oterr »-Copy of Secret Bote Bo. 773, dated 15th March 1929 by Captain J. B. Glubb, Administrative Inspector, In-Charge Southern Desert, Adhaira, to the Adviser, Ministry of Interior, Baghdad. Subj ectHelations tith Kuwait. My Ho. 754 of 15th March 1929. On 14 -o- 29 I met Lieut.-Colonel More, Political Resident in Kuwait. Me showed me a telegram reoeived by him from His Excellency the High Commissioner with reierence to my telegram Ho. 696 of 10th March 1929, and his draft reply thereto. In regard to the latter, 1 think that the sug gestion that rumours to the discredit of Kuwait may be circulated by persons in Iraq who desire to see Kuwait annexed to that country, is rather far fetched. The allegations in question have all been made by the local Iraq nomad tribes, who are indignant because they believe that Araibdar are assisting the Akhwan to raiu them. These tribesmen have nnly the vaguest idea of the political relations between Kuwait, Iraq and high His Majesty’s Government, and it can scarcely be imagined that they are actuated by political aims when they accuse Araibdar of having their sheep. Since writing my Ha. 754 of 15-3-29 I have obtained the following further details from Bari Malik who ■ere raided at Kuwait. The Khirsan section of ■*** Bani Malik alone gave 'khawa' to Ibn Subah. The •iva was accepted, and the chiefs were presented with ziboons and told to camp with Araibdar. Encouraged bj this reception, portionsof the Shuraifat, Tu’us, Shillib and other se.tions joined aan. All camped with Araibdar near Jahrah. Everybody knew Hi at Araibdar were friendly with MutairP70 Mutair, and there were many Akhwan always coming and going in their camps. One day Abdulla^ al Jabir, brother of Shaikh Ahmad, arrived at Jahrah. Here, before a large concourse, including Araibdar, Bant Mallkand many Akhwan, he said 'the Akhwan are coming to raid the Kuntafik shepherds. Araibdar must separate from them. ibn Hubah has nothing to do with the liuntafik'. ?he shepherds were dumbfounded by this sudden blow. They held a hasty consultation. Some jrf were for a night flight towards Safwan, and others for fleeing to Kuwait. The former was sixty miles away, while it was only fifteen miles to Kuwait, The impression conveyed by Abdullah al Jabir's speech was that the Akhwan were about to attack any moment. The shepherds were therefore afraid to risk the long march to Safwan unprotected, and decided to flee to Kuwait, camp beneath the walls, and send a message to t the Administrative Inspector asking for help. it never entered their minds (or anyone else's ) that they would be attacked beneath the walls of Kuwait. They complain bitterly of Abdullah al Jabir's conduct in saying publicly before Araibdar And the Akhwan that Ibn Subah would not interfere to protect them. Ii, they say, Abdullah had, instead of this, taken them quietly aside and said 'look here, you are going to be raided and we cannot protect you, so yd, you had better retire to Iraq', they would have sneaked away the same night to Safwan. As regards the battle, the shepherds appear to have put up a magnificent residtence. It is now stated that they killed about thirty of the raiders, seventeen mares and many riding camels. it is thought that twentyfive of the shepherds were killed, and about fifteen survived, having taken refugerefuge in some detached buildings outside the walls. The action raged for four hours, during any time of wit which the intervention of even thirty or forty ifiresh men from the town would have sufficed to repel the raiders. During all these hours, however, the gates remained closed. Crowds of spectators on the walls (the final scenes of the battle , as attested by the dead horses still lyingthere, were only two to four hundred yards from the walls; witnessed this tragic contest of five hundred against forty. Nothing more brutal can be imagined since the days of the Roman Gladiators, it is stated that the many men within the town, not only shepherds but sympathisers disgusted gates to assist the shepherds, but were prevented by the Shaikh’s men. The Khirsan section were massacred and raided with others, in spite of their 'khawa' and Ibn Subah’s 'Wajh'. Bani Malik are absolutely positive in their assertions that Araibdat) themselves joined in the raid. in the night march previous to the attack, actually passed through the Araibdar campe. if any man of Araibdar haci cantered on ahead he could have warned the shepherds. killed were recognised as belonging to Araibdar. It is even said that one of the Hajruf family, the Amirs of Araibdar under Ibn Subah, was killed. Khalaif al Bashag, a Shaikh of the Shurai that his women, who stayed in his tent du raid, informed him that the raiders came tent accompanied by a woinen, and began to woman asked to whom the tent belonged, an&lt; told Khalaif al Bashag, she said to the r at this brutal slaughter, struggled to geiT gei- out of the Firstly there seems to be no dou)it that the raiders latter sweair that at least two of the maref['Khatiya! let us leave Khalaif’s tent'. It is of course unknown for women to accompany a raid and any how a Mutair woman would not know who Khalaif al Bashag was. The shepherds believe that these people were from some Araibdar camp® close by. Flight Lieutenant Howes informs me that xkx he knows the name of at least one man of Araitdar who was with the raiders. I do not imagine that the Shaikh of Kuwait would ofltder Araibdar to raid the shepherds. In fact, if tnv did so, the Shaikh was probably unaware of the Zsut fact until after it had occurred. Bedouins are naturally covetous and all sorts of rag-tag and bobtail join in raids. Still the Shaikh is responsible for his tribes. i* After the bombing, a large number of Bank Malik sheep and donkeys scattered about the vicinity and were collected by Araibdar. The shepherds went out with a representative of the Shaikh and collected tfiat they could find. They complain, however, that Araibdar extorted money from them before consenting to hand over their property. One man says that he was compelled to pay Rs. 15/- to recover three of his donkeys.iuuejcx The average value of a donkey is about Rs. 8/- each, so that, if his statement is true he very nearly bought his donkeys back. Another man allege® that he was made to pay Rs. 5/- fof two donkeys. I was informed by the shepherds that a minor chief of the Bank Malik called Hajji Za’airi, was killed in the raid, and his mare wounded. All his worldly property was looted. The mare was sub sequently caught by Ibn Subah's men and taken to the Shaikh. Some of the shepherds went to the Shaikh to ask for the mare, uhich they hoped to sell for the benefit of the family of Huj£i Za’airi. They allege, however,5- TArHr however, that Abdullah al Jabir, the Shaikh^ brother, refused to hand it over unless a fee of five majidis was paid. As the family of the deceased Hajji Za f airi were completely penniless, they not raise thissura, and tha mare is still with Ibn Subah. TV The shepherds, ms^r of whom after the raid had only the clothes they stood up in, and were moreover burdened with large numbers of women all of whose menfolk had been killed, complain bitterly that no one in Kuwait would so much as give them a meal. On the contrary, they state that the Kuwaitis took advantage of their xXxX situation to endeavour to make money. Some who desired to visit the scene of the bombing to collect any of their pfopwrty left behind by the raiders, were asked exorbitant prices for the hire of a cart or horse. Vttien they were informed by the Special Service Otficer that cars would come to Kuwait to escort the refugees back to the Iraq tribes, the Kuwaitis did all they could to persuade the shepherds not to leave, with the idea of buying their remaining shpep from | them at a low price. This fact is attested by outside witnesses. In i egard to the battle , and the non-interference of the fthaiiih, many of the shepherds and others, in cluding a plain clothes constable of the Camel Corps, allege that the Shaikh stated in public that he was prevented from coming to the assistance of xhe shep herds by orders from His Majesty’s Government and the Political Resident. Some also state that he *x said that, previous to the engagement, Government had told him to evict the shepherds and hot to protect them. All the above statements are of course derived from tribal sources. I cannot absolutely vouch for them. I think, however, that there can be no doubt whateverVlr uJf iBiiatever that the shepherds and the Iraq tribes generally are absolutely convinced of th^complicity of Axaibdar in the raid. Should you desire to press the question further, I suggest that sworn statements be taken from the Bani Malik refugees. I attach a list of losses of B&amp;ni Malik pro perty, compiled by Flight Lieutenant Howes in Kuwait. He tells me that he has sent a list of the killed to Air Headquarters, but he did not send me a copy. The total of deaths was, 1 believe, twentyfive.XolQ ^raifi r . : ' roas * High ComaiaaionGr, Baghdad# iO# I olitical Hrisldontf Buajiijra Bepoated Politioal A«©nt t Kuwait. No. 35/3. Jated 4tliirQcd 5th) April 1929. •in audition to aerial action over Kuwait territory already agreed to the Jtaeaourea which sheikh's assent would herequired are those detailed in latter part ol my telegram or February 12th No 14-S. Above refers to your telegram No 232. 'bst copy to the Political A^ent at SnBirrT for information only. for Under Senretary to the Political Heaicient in the Peraian Gulf Bu all ire, 6th April 1929./ Telegram (c) From politioal, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire, repeated to Highooma Baghdad and Basrah. No. 596. Dated 4th April 1929. A Mutair caravan which arrived today states Ibn Humaid agreed under pressure from Dawish and Ibn Hithlain to submit to decision ox‘ shara Court. No developments had however ensued when caravan left Summan on 31st March. Addresred Resident in the persian Quir, repeated to High commissioner for * Iraq and Basrah. political Agency, Kuwait. Dated &lt;±th April 1929. A copy of the foregoing telegram is forwarded herewith to the Political Agent, Bahrain.(fj) Telegram (c) prom political, Kuwait. To political, bu shire: repeated Lincoln,Muhammarah. No. «63. Dated 6th April 1929. reports indicate beyond reasonable doubt that battle was i ought near 2ilfi on 29th ijarch in which Ibn sa'ud gained decisive victory and inflicted heavy casualties, ijwaish died of wounds and Xbn aimaid fled first to Artawiyah then south. 'Uzaiyia suing for peace. Addressed Dushire repeated Muhammarah for Resident. political Agency, Kuwait, uated the 6th April 1929. A copy ox the foregoing telegram is forwarded to tie political Agent, Bahrain. Lieut-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait. 11T«le^r .:* (2). Teleorw* ?rom PolltioAl, Xuw&amp;it. DAt»d 6 th April 19 ^ 9 * 7 tel^&amp;raa M«ui who loft MAjaa’ah &gt;Cth K&amp;roh report* defeated Ixh.an retired first to Artawlyah. Iba Hmaald tried to persuade Dawrsh, who was badlj wouuded to ooatinue stru^le but without success. He then left and fled towards Hijaz, plundering cartels of Ibn Musaiyis and the SuhUl on his way. ibn Sa’ud has suaaoned all the .^utalr in the Suanan and elsewhere to coae in to hia but the Jlblan were talking of refusing. A copy of the aboire tole^aa is forwarded herewith to The Political A^ent, Bahrain. The Special Service Officer, kuw ‘ Political Agency, Kuwait. 6 th April &lt;** 9 .Teleoraa (0). 'iTt* Political, Kuwait, Political, Bu^hire; repd. Muhanaarah for Resident, 478. 8th Jtpril 1949 . Extract froa aeseafce from Special, Kuwait, dated 8th April. Bellas. Two Dhaffr left Artawfyali lad April etate definitely 1 Dawfah dead. Ibn Sa'ud pardoned 'Uzaiyiz, but not all Mutalr aa yet. Ends. Political Agency, Kuwait. 8th April 1949. A copy of the above telegram io forwarded herewith to The Political Agent, Bahrain. Lieut.-Gol., Political Agent, Kuwait. !VI3 COBrnKHTIAh «0. 105-3. of 1989. Britiaii Koolden^y and Coneulato-uoneral 4 Axmhir*, 8th April 1929. i ftir. 1 mu dlrooted to «ttkno«lodge Uie reoolpt of your letter Mo. 8.0. 673, dated the 21»t Mur oil 1929, m&lt;X to enclose in this eonneetlon a copy of a letter Bo. 250-5., dated the 29th far eh from the Political Agent at Kuealt. 8. Colonel Kore's letter gives a version of the natter substantially different to the highly coloured and eonewhut unbalanced deserlption in Captain Olubb'e notes and, as the f iraq tritace were to have left Kuwait by the end of Mar eh, the Political Keuident thlnke that a better ccurtie might have been to forward in a wore dispassionate spirit for verification the obvious ly exaggerated statements of Captain Clubb. also, as head of administration in the Persian Gulf, have appreciated being as«*d for his own views instead of tlioee of one of his subordinate officers. 3. The position of the Shaikh of Kuwait, stand ing as he does unsupported between two strong contending partiec Me would j*L The Pelitleal fteeretary to His ¥&amp;deilensy the high Coevals si one r for Iraq, : U0KDA9 .portlea, both of whon frooly u«e his territarieo, U ono of «xtr«is« difftoulty, aw no eon afford to offend neither* the 9 Iraq trlbee he han readily jperaltted to tfraae in hie oeuntry and. in default of hie o«n ability to proteet xhm 9 hae pemitted outside pro tective arrangemnts to be imde for t'mm, and if t£»»e tribee had not entered hie country, the preentit situation ecu Id apparently not imve arisen* The ohaiJch ie not strong enough without outside support to take sides in the quarrel and his polioy. though admittedly not a strong one, has been than which is inevitable in the case of a weaker power placed between two strong contending powers one forocu by lack of outside support to attempt to maintain neutrality* 4. The position of the rhaikh would be radio*!- ly altered in the event of Xbn 3a 9 ud 9 s definitely breaking with and attacking his subject tribes, and the situation In that ease has been dealt with in my telegram of the mh narch. no. gU/b. Until that situation arises the state of affaire does not seem to be sash us to warrant our forolng the Shaikh of Kuwait to take sides in the quarrel. with the necessary oorollary of sending troops and ships for his iawiediate protection and the added probability of creating a position In the future whieh would neoesslhate our maintaining in definitely protestive eomitmonte in the Kuwait State* A ospy of this letter is being sent to the Government of India end to His Majesty*w Userstary of $tate for the Colonies* 1 hat e the honour Sir. four most obedient to be. servant. HD/ H. n.'r&gt;. Dickson, hieut.-Colonel. Deeretary to the Moiiusal Hesident In the i*eralioa Gulf. oCopy of a letter from the Political Agent,Kuwait to the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf.Bushlre, No. 250/S,dated the 29th March 1929. Attitude of t. he Sheikh of Kuwali;., I have the honour to refer to letter No a.0.673, dated the 21st March 1929 from the Political Secretary to His Excellency the High Commissioner for Iraa relative to the atitude of His Excellency the Sheikh of Kuwait In connection with the recent Ikhwan raids on lra&lt;i tribes, as depicted in two notes by Captain J.B.Glubb,C.B.B.,M.C., Administrative Inspector in charge of the Southern Desert of xraq.,who is at present in charge of the Iraq tribes in Kuwait territory. In my opinion Captain GlubVs notes are widely ex- travagant.and convey an altogether exaggerated idea of the true facts of the case. Had I read them a month ago, I should have been amazed that Captain Glubb could have written them,but since the Iraq tribes have been in Kuwait territory I have naturally had a great deal of correspon dence with him regarding complaints put forwarfl by Kuwait subjects against Iraq tribesmen or by Iraq tribesmen against Kuwaitis,and,although,I have nothing but praise for the assistance he has given in the former type of cases it has been impossible for me not to notice in the latter how ready he is to believe anything discreditable to Kuwait which an iraq tribesman likes to tell him. As examples of the above and the following instances will suffice to prove what I say:- On the 21st March he wrote to me that some the Dhafir had complained that,as they were returning from Kuwait the previous evening,they had been attacked ear Jahrah by two parties of camelmen - one of three and the other of four men. Dhafir had succeeded in driving off their assailants who had retired to a camp of the Uraibdarnear toy. I gave Captain Glutoto’s man a letter to the Shaikh and told him to take the actual Dhafir to whom the alleged incident had oocured with him so that they could give him all poasitole details. They,however,told a totally different story from what Captain Glutoto had written. '’hey said that when they got to near the Mutla(four miles on the other side of Jahrah) on their way to -not to from a man Etching them from somelLittle dis tance off and another man with three camels. They called out and aske^lf they were Dhafir,whereupon the man went to the camels and they all wetot off towards the nnr-t.ft , where they presumably went to a camp of the Zaiyad tritoe of Iraq, -there were certainly no Uraitodar in that direc tion. The Dhafir further said/they had never actually seen Captain Glutoto himself at all. On the 24th March Captain Glutoto wrote to me that he was sending in one of his men who said that he, with representatives of the Bani Malik,had found six sheep belonging to the latter with one of the Uraitodar. This man had alleged that he had bought the sheep from a caravan coming down from Nejd. His man consequently had left the sheep,as custom does nnt. r . rmlt thfl Ee£&lt;miPh of animal a fm, nd in thft „ ngCiQC , Q &lt; , ifitoe who bought th»n -. f roin the In view,however,of a previous case in which the Sheikh had pointed out that it is the Bedouin custom that if anyone recognize &amp;i 8 property in a case of this sort,and can produce witnesses to prove that it is his,it is his right to have it returned to him without having to compensate the man who had bought it,and that it is up to the latter to get his money hack from the man he bought it from,and that anyone who buys an animal from another without safe guarding himself with a definite assurance,given by theseller in the presence of witnesses f that the money will hereturned if the 'beast is proved to 'belong to someone else,obviously done so at his own risk, - with which ruling,although it unquestionably j^s in accordance with that it should be applied to these six sheep. On enquiry it turneciput that the man of the Uraibdar with whom they were found had only just bought them from another man. The latter was questioned at the time,and proved to the satisfaction of everyone,including Captain Glubb*s man, that four out of the six animals had belonged to,and beon bred by # Kuwait Arabs, and that only two were alleged to have been bought from the Ikhwan.C aptain Glubb*s ma n afcterward3_,acKnowledged to me personally that this was the case # The two which had been bought from Ikhwan and had belonged to the Ban! Malik were sold by the Gheikh^s orders and their value sent to their ori&amp;inal owners• I quote the above oases,not in any carping spirit at Captain Glubb f s work,and indeed I admire his ability and like him personally very much,but merely to show that he has a distinct bias ,and that, able as he undoubtedly is, he is very far from being infallible. You will undoubtedly have noticed yourself how very inaccurate he is regarding the history of Kuwait at the beginning of his note No 754 datedtbe 12th/15th March 1919. It was of I course in the late Shaikh Salim*s days that the tribes were lost to Kuwait,the Awazim,the old Kuwait tribe par excellence , being seduced f.om his allegiance by Ibn It was indeed inevitable that,with the Ikhwan * revival , tribes should prefer to be on their side rather than against them,and should transfer their allegiance to Ibn Saud accordingly. WheJ? Sheikh Afemad first j ■became Buler of Kuwait,he had,as now,no tribes other than - sustom,Captain Glubb does not agree. He urged however action over the Ajman.the Uraihdar. In this connection it might not be out of place to point out that the Uraibdar are not a tribe,as one would imagine from para 77 of Intelligence hoport Mo 6 dated the 13th March 1929,issued by the Secretariat of His Excellency the High Commissioner for Ir w ,but are,as their name implies, the •Household Arabs' of Kuwait. They are also sometimes called Fidawiyah,and are usually spoken of by the Sheikh himself as ’our servants* Actually they belong to various tribes: Eaahaidah.AJman, Mutalr etc., all of which however are of the Nejd type. To revert to Captain Clubb’s notes: it is perfectly true,of course, that the Mutair are allowed to buy supplies in Kuwait,and I absolutely agree *ith Captain Glubb that an agreement has undoubtedly been ar ived at by which the Kuwait Uraibdar are to be left in peace in return for this privilege. The Sheikh naturally never told me when he mad. this agreement, and has no uoubt all along been nervous that we might stf® in and force him to close Kuwait to the Mutair- which from his point of view would mean plunging his country into a sfcate of insecurity similar to that of last year, and denying a source of trade to his subjects. He has how ever always said that Kuwait is open to all who rti like to come to trade there. Thisnis certainly as far as he ; gone, and to say that this agreement has ripened^' regular alliance and that the Sheikh helps the rebelli ous Ikhwan in every way possible, is,in my opinion, merely absurd. 'ith regard to ibn Hithlains raid on the 21st January, I can show that he definitely tried to frustrate it_in so fay as ha .gould without .mbrollln. ...^ v i^ikhman.as.as soon as he received information about it, * in addition to informing me ( which he could hardly help doing) he sent a private telegram to Zubair for a taxi to he sent out to warn as many sheperds as possible,and it was this taxi oomlas back which the i.t. Mr ^His party met shortly xXtmx before they were fired on.X agreeof course that he probably could,and If so certainly should,have taken active steps against the raiders as the raid was in his territory. That he did not may, I think, oaxely be attributed to weakness and his dread of getting embroiled in the quarrel again. &lt;ith regard to ibn Shuqair's raid on the Ban! i'alik, the incident in which Ibn Bhuqair is alleged to have ill sent a messenger to the Gheikh,warning him to move the || Uraibdmr away from the sheperds.is probably the same in origin as that reported in my telegram No 85,dated the 23rd iebruaiy.in whioh^reported that 'A few families of Kuwait ' sartasmd at Item Buus were warned by a man of the A Jman late last night that a small raiding party under Ibn Shuqair.iuqm and Ibn Lami was ^bout to attack them. Ho advised them to move at once which they did and came into Jahrah this morning,Saturday.The Sheikh has sent a wanning by oar to the tribes sout-east oi'' Jahrah: The warning may have J^en intended for the Draibdar alone, hut I think that*®* is no doubt that the Sheikh passed it on to all alike,^o he can hardly be blamed if it was. On the 28th February I received a telegram from His Excellency the High Commissioner to the effect that it was reported that fifty tents of the Bani Kalik who had been camped with the tiraihdar had received warning of a raid and flea to Kuwait town,but had been *±r driven away by the Sheikh and were camped between Jahrah and Kuwait, ana asking me to warn them to fall back on the main con centration of Iraq tribes at Itam-aJ-Kadafi &lt;ah. 1 Sheikh at once, and he told me that he had already advised them to join the other Iraq tribes where they woul* be safer,as there was not room for them as well as the Uralbdar to take refuge; within the walls of Jahrah in case of need. He said he was ve|y glad to Itex* hear that the High Commissioner wanted them to go, as their flocks made an attractive -bait* for raiders and he did not likewould convey H. K. the High CoramioBioner *b warning to them The above is no doubt the origin of what Shaileh Abdulla al Jabir (who incidentally is the Shaikh’s oecond cousin, not his brother) is alleged to have said, and also of the story about the Shaikh having said that Government had told him to evict the shepherds and not protect them both in garbled form . On the 1st March a deputation of four of the Bani Malik carneto see me and aaid that the Shaikh had sent word to them that he could no longer be responsible for their safety, that a telegram had come from the Iraq Govemnertt that they mere to join the other Iraq tribes, and that they were not to stop there any longer. I told them that the telegram was one which I had received from H.E. the High Gommissioner, who wanted them to £o where they would be safe. They said th«$ quite realised that they would be perfectly safe if they once got there, but that there were so many spies about that they dare not risk the journey, and asked mt to request the High Com missioner that an escort might be provided for them. I accordingly telegraphed to H.E. the High Commissioner conveying their request in my telegram Ho. 112 of 1st Mar oh, at the same time telling the Shaikh that I was doing so, and asking him to let them remain here and make the best arrangements he could for their safety pending a reply. This was on the 1st March, and the blow fell on the morning of the 3rd,before any reply had been received. With regard to the actual happenings on the morning of the 3rd March. The first I knew that anything was happening was to hear the firing when 1 was out for a walk in the early morning. X then saw a horseman gallop in the direction of the Shaikh’s pomace, and heard that the Bani Malik were being raided. I hurried back to the Political Agenby, vdiere 1 met the Shaikh just arriving to tell me the news in a state of great flurry and distress Shortly(7) Shortly after despatohingmy first telegram I got into a oar, and drore out to the wall to see if I eould learn anything further of what was happening, and tm* 1 from what I saw then I find it rather difficult to believe all the stories afcout the shepherds being beaten back with the flats of swords. The gates were shut, of course, if 1 as one would expert them to be under the oireumstances, || but I actually saw one party of two or three men allowed «|! r out '■ though by that time the fighting was |l over in the vicinity of the town. ;Jj&lt; I suggested to the Shaikh at the time that I ( thought he might send out a force in cars to pursue the raiders and try and recover some of kite plunder as he had 11| tone to Hi^a’i in January 1928, but he said that he could (I net possibljr risk it, asthe raiders were much soo strong |j for any force he could send out. As I said in my telegram |j No. 160, dated the 14th Kareh. Jfck I think it quite possible ' that his desire to prevent his people from becoming lj| involved in the quakrel may have influenced the Sfcaikh i n coming to this deoisiBn, and I consider that if this be i so he was very much to blame. I most emphatically do not believe, however, that the Shaikh was implicated in any other way. r.ven if one or two of the Uraibdar actually took part in the raid it would prove nothing worse against him than that he is not a very strong ruler, and it is 1 fear a fact that he is not. When one considers «ho and what the Uraibdar are, and thinks how raiding appeals to all Bedouin, it would not be very extraordinary if one or two did join in, but if they difyg. I am sure it was without his knowledge or approval. 'he accusation brouufrit against the Uraibdar of retaining large numbers of animals be Kinging to the Bani Malik have been disproved, as, although they have been given every facility to see for themselves, only sixteen sheep, twelve lambs, and seven donkeys have been found( 8 ) found, which I think everyone must acknowledge to be a negligible number under the eiraastanceB. Moreover eleven of these animals which were plundered from the Bani Malik in the raid of 21st January and two others which they lost in the raid of 3rd March are reported to have come into the possession of the Uraibdar by purchase* I can say definitely that the allegations made by the Bani Malik refugees that 'no one in Kuwait would so mudi as give them a meal w are deliberately untrue* I have already given it as my opinion in my Kuwait .News Mo. 5 of 1929 that the Kuwait people were very kina to the refugees, and not only were they given food and clothing, but a subscription was got up for them as well. It mus be remembered however that people like these Bani Malik who have lost their all are naturally dissatisfied with the world in general and distrustful of everyone in the place where they have suffered their loss. I think this, and the natural suspicion of Shi * ah shepherd tribes of Iraq at a time like the present of everything Majdi, or resembling fifee Najdi (like the Uraibdar of Kuwait; are responsible for most of the accusations against the Shaikh, Uraibdar and people of Kdwait which have been made to Captain Glubb, and I would rex^eat what 1 said in my telegram Mo. 160, dated the 14th March 1929, that anti- Kuwait rumours may even have been suggested to these tribesmen by the politically minded as propaganda*. To sum upl the Shaikh’s policy has undoubtedly been to keep out of the quairrel at all costs as long as possible. ITe probably has obtained a guarantee from the neighbouring Ikhwan leaders that they will not raid his tribesmen in return for the privilege of buying supplies in Kuwait. He may even have allowed this desire to fceep out of the quarrel to influence him in deciding that raiders in his territory were too strong to attack, and, if so, he was certainly to blame for this. X do not think however thatone can justly accuse *2 him of anything worse thaw( 9 ) a** than this. Ab regards the merits of hie poliey: there is nothing gallant or noble about it, it is true; but it haa opened up a certain amount of trade for hie people, and it saved has nuacsok his tribesmen from being raided, and all his subjects from the Hear of attack to vdiich they were exposed last year. ConsequeAtiy, I think vre can say that in the interests of his own subjects it is probably the best policy which he could have followed. From the British point of view, his policy is certainly somewhat annoying in so fa* as outf interests in Iraq are concerned. On the other hand it saves us the inconvenience and expense of keepitfC or more of His Majesty’s Ship* here, as w«/ had to do for so long last year, and as we would almost certainly have to do again if the Shaikh were again to incur the hostility of the Ikhwan. The Shaikh woulc , I know, be the first to own, as is indeed patent to everyone, that Kuwait owes its independence to us alone, and consequently 1 think we have every right to distate what policy the Shaikh should mx follow in a matter of this wort, and to force him to abandon any policy which we consider opposed to ou* in* terests. I have already expressed my opinion, in my tele gram Ho. 210 of 24th March 1929, as to what action we should take in the event of Ibn Saud;defeating the tribes which are now flouting^iis authority, and the latter washing to take refuge in Kuwait, and you have endorsed that opinion. It only remains t lie ref ore, to consider whether it is, or is not, to our interests as a whole to compel the Shaikh to abandon his present policy now, and to close Kuwait forthwith to the Mutair and other Ikhwan tribes who are now defying Ibn SaAd v s authority. How that the Iraq tribes are leaving Kuwait territory again it is really only this question of blockade Mhlsh concerns li!our interests in Iraa at all. In this connection I would point out that the Special Service Officer, Kiiwait, said in his message No HK/U5 dated the 28th March 1929, that an agent whom he considers very knowledgeable had suggested that Ibn Saud was attempting to weaken resistance (j by,waiting until the rebels* supplies are exhausted,when l! he hopes they will either surrender or attack him. This man had stated that caravans which visit Kuwait are totally inadequate to replenish rebel* supplies,and that all other desert ports are closed to them . This tallies entirely with my opinion,which is that this question of — with Kuwait - although certainly an important one - is hardly as important as Captain Glubb leads one to suppose. Cn the whole I am inclined to think that the advantages which we would gain in Iraq by forcing Kuwait to close its doors to the Ikhwan would be more than out weighed by the disadvantages of having to protect Kuwait- as we would almost certainly have to do . This is, however,a matter of opinion.Telegram. ( In Code ). From - Resident, i3u£ldr« 0 T# - Political ^gcnt, Ralirain. Nt. 265. Datod and received 16th /ipril 1929. Your 57 hotter More he has latest but victory over 2 sections seems t© have $ua boon fairly complete third was on flank watching Bin Jaluwi.Telegram. ( In Code* j „ Prem - High Cemmiattiener # Baghdud. To - Political ^gent, Bahrain, N*c 145. Bated and received cn 19th April 1929. Importanto Addreoaed to Bahrain repeated to Bughire. reference latter*s telegram No. 258 . Pleaue atnd following message fret: my self to IBN SAUB a&amp; soon ae possible hogins . 1 have received with pleasure news oi Your Majesty *b victory over certnin of your subjects who had disregarded your wishes and committed acts el hostilities against Iraq tribes. 1 feel confident this timely assertion of Your Majesty’s authority will assist greatly towards restoration of peace in desert and will eventually make it possible for both Iraq and Nejd tribes to graze in their accustomed haunts without fear of molestation. . Certain of Your Majesty’s recalcitrant subjects have in the past made approaches t© administrative inspector Southern desert in hope they would welcome into Iraq there shielded from Your Majesty's wrath, all such approaches have been sternly repulsed and it is tnerefore hoped those who have boon recently punished by Your majesty will not attempt to soek for an asylum in Iraq. If however they should endeavour to do so Iraq Government would be comps Hod to deny refuge to all those who have boon concerned in recent unprovoked attacks on Iraq tribes and will therefore spare no effort to turn them back in order that they may return to Nejd and submit to Your Majesty’s authority, in this connection Your Majesty may wish to inform me names and address ef any individuals whose possible flight into Iraq Your Majesty would particularly wish prevcntedjendso I understand Resident in the Persian Gulf proposes to send a message to IBN SAUB through you at the sane time.Ttl«gr*m [ In C«d« ) 0 Prtm - Rtttidont, Bu®Jair«. T« - Political iigont, 3ahrain 0 No. 284. Dated and received 20th April 1929. IMPORTANT. Addressed t© Bahrain repeated to Baghdad reference Baghdad’s telegram 145 please send at the same time following message from me. Bogins. 1 have received news of Your Majesty’s victory over certain of your subjects who had dis- -regarded your authority and committed act*, of hostilit/ios against Iraq tribes and in so doing have violated neutrality ei KuY/ait State. I 1 eel cenfident this timely assertien ef Yeur Majesty’s autherity will assist greatly tewards resteratien ef peace in desert and make it possible for all tribos to grazo in their accustomed haunts without fear of molestation. Cortain ol Your Majesty’s recalcitrant subjects have in the past been grazing in huwait district in which they have ebtained supplies. New that Yeur Majesty hhag made known your displeasure with thses tribes and your desire they should not be shielded from your wrath Shaikh of huYfait has declared ;&amp;ut£ his desire te give all assistance to Yeur Majesty in his pewer and has stated that he will certainly net now allow tribes which are in rebellion against you to obtain their supplies from huv/ait and that he r/ill do all that is possible to- prevent such subjects taking refuge in huY/ait territory so that they may return to Nejd and submit to Your Majesty’s authority. Ends.7AT- Trandation of letter dated 14th Dhul ^a’dah 1347- i.e. 24.4. 1929 frorr His Vajeaty oir ’Abdul ’Aziz bin ’Abdur Hahran al-Faiaal aa-ja’ud,G»C.1.3., King of KijaZjNajd and its Dependencies to Lieut-Colonel C.C.J.Barrett,C.J.I. C.I.ii.g H.B.V’s Political Agent,B^Kraino After Cotrplirents, is I beg to acknowledge the receipt of your letter Ko.49 of 1929 dated the 25th Jhauwal 1547 (5.4.29) with the two letters enclosed in it frorr His Excellency the ^igh Cor-rrissioner for ’Iraq y for which I thank you very vuch. Enclosed also please find two letters in reply to those of His excellency Noe. 31 8c 42 and also a third letter No.98 v which I request you to send to His Excellency by the earliest opportunity. U.E/ ■■■ 7^^ Telograra (G), Froia Political, Kuwait, To ' Rebident, Bushire. No. db9- Dated 15th April 1929* My No. 2tJ?* Another boat arrived fron Jubail yeeterday evening, with ne&gt;*b that the firing wa» to celebrate another victory gained by Ibn 5a'ud, a force of hit bent in pursuit in care having wounded and captured Ibn Huiiaid and Killed his son. I am not yet satisfied that the information is authentic. Political Agency, Kuwait 15th April 19^9. A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith to The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Special Service Officer, Kuwait. Lieut.-Gol., Political Agent, Kuv;ait.OOMFIDSjmAL r Tel*irai (P)» ?rora Political, Kuwait -o R«alde.it, Suwhire, No. 297. Datwd 17th April 1929. ± * 10 ^ollowla^ i« the j^let of a W/T letbu^tt eeut bj Glubb on t6th April. Be*ias. A aaa whose reliability is not known xx ■X who claim* to have been present at the battle,a*»*jutiuUi says that Iba Sa'dd was extreiely unwilling to attack the Ikhwaa,'but the town»n®a forced him to do bo,First two at- Ucke he made were repulaea with heavy lose,but third suc ceeded as rebels ran short of ammunition.Though vlctorloue, Ion oa ud is in weak position owin^ to heavy losses 0 Ibn HUmald is to west of C-hat^hat,where he is thought to intend to carry on guerilla warfare.lt is believed that Mutair at Hafar have been granted an amnesty. Snd*. Political Agency, Kuwait. 17th Ap^il 1929 . a copy of the above tele^raia is forwarded herewith to The Political Agent, Bahrain. xnieut. -Col., Political Agent, Kuwait.30* Tele&amp;raa Proa Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Suahire; repeated HifcJicoata, Baghdad, Idmintor, 3 »erah and to Glubb. Ilo# Dated 26th April Shaikh of Kuwait*» meaaenger to Ihn Sa'ud who has long DILKAMi V* been expected arrived back thia morning, # haring left Shaqr* on «9th April. He wa* In Riyadh at time of battle and Joined Ibn Sa'Ud at hie camp outside Artawfyah opinion le that his wound Is mortal, It being through stomach and gangrenous. Official figures of Ibn Sa'uua casualties only ten killed. Ikhwin casualties not cnown but heard up to thousand mentioned as killed. Ibn Humald went to Ghatghat after battle but was followed by force of twelve standards under Ibn Sa*uds brother 'Abdullah to whom he eventually surrendered without fighting. Informant himself saw him brought in to Ibn Sa'tid at Shaqra mammmtMkmmmmu on 16 th April and he is still a prisoner* Ibn Sa'ud was leaving Shaqra for HIJax on 20th April* A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith to P # A* , Bahrain* S*S«0* f Kuwait* He saw Dawfsh brought in on stretcher and says medical Political Agency,Kuwait. 26th April 1929. #IlltfgM 1% Prom# High Commissioner, Baghdad# — To. Political Resident,Bushire,repeated Kuwait# Political No. 39/&amp;. Dated 12th (rood 13th}April 1929# Tour telegrams Nos ZZZ ana 232 inaicati that oonsant of Sheikh to presence of armoured cars had first hean obtained up till the end of Karoh and then for a few days longer# My telegram 35/3 read with my Ko 35/8 indicated that permission was desired to retain them in Kuwait for periods of several days at a time so long as Iraq tribes are grazing acroak the frontier# In the ciroumBtanoes I find that amazement of Politic Agent is somewhat inoomprehensiole* If presence of cars is objected to by Sheikh or you consider their presence undesirable position will have to be reconsidered by me but at present I have no indication that that is the case# Above refers to your telegram No 231# yost Copy fcent to the Political Agent at I] CvUt*** for Information only, iIt* • +% /«• Bushire, /? April 192 9. Under Secretary to the Political resident, t'ereian uulf.ISLlSGTM Froui, Hl^h Co^iaalon«r f BagUaad* To# Foiltioal iU»aldatit 9 jbusiilrd# Ho# 40/3. Dated and Hood lath April 1929. eeorotnry of state for the Colonies haa inatruotod me to ropoat following telegram of the lit April H© 125 for &gt;our kntormBtion and nooesaary actio hy you Your tolegraa Ho 13tf dated the 6th I!io ^aj3aty*s GoTern^ent agree that it la not deair- in Kuwait and that 3heikh should he urged to deny the© aupplioa and to attempt^ with forces at his . , so disposal to keep the© out of his territory aa far as that Is possible, if anYwhen situation demands Kla Majesty's Ooverraaent will be^repared to afxord naval protection. I bn 'Xaud should be ind orsed through Q.uici ost possible channel of the steps which will be taker should refugees taka refuge^ in Kuwait or Iraq. The possibility of assisting the aheikh in preventing refugees froit entering or remaining in Kuwait is engaging the attention of Kio Eejsty’s Government, will be sent to you A further tclegr&amp;m/on this point which should not be mentioned to I un aaud for the present fohutj# Post Copy sent to the Political Agent a “ information only. (lJ(j(4A*44.4. QjL Bushire, Under Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Uu3 , 11 April 192 9.Telegram. I; From. High Oomiiiissloner, Baghdad. To. Political Besident, Bushire,Ko 41/3- Bepeated Secretary of State for Colonies, It is not quite clear whether/to Ihn Saud is to he sent hy me or you. I propose telegraphing to Bahraii^epeating to you, message regarding the action to he taken should refugees take asylum in Iraq., leaving it to you to send message as regards refugees in Kuwait. Do you agree ? Foregoing is with reference to telegram No 1B5 from Secretary of State for the Colonies which I had repeated to you in my immediately proceeding telegram. No 14ft. Dated and Heed 12th April 1919. Impartant message Post Copy to the Political Agent at for information only Under Mcoretary to the Political KeeiCent, reraian Oulf Bushire, April 1929 wTelegram From* Politloal Besldentf 3ushlre* To# High Coirnnl as loner, BagMad,Ko 258# Repeatod Secretary of State for Colonies Uo 8. Dated the 15th April 1929. Important. I oonour. Political Agent Bahrein has been instructed accordingly* Above refers to your telegram Ho 41/3. Fowl Copy to Ihe Political Agent at for information only. Under Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. -Buehire, H April 1929V. i°7 Iala«r*a p. Trom, Political Agant, Bushin. To. Senior fJaval Officer, R.X.a.l.upln*. SO. 240. Bstea the 15th April 1929, It might he necessary in order to assist haTI a loop 11 in k * a3&gt;ln4S out B9 J a refugees from Kuwait to/ sJup at Kuwait. Could you keep one ,so as to be ready to proceed if called on,in Upper part of Oulf . Post Copy to the Political Agent at for information only. Under Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Bushire, April 192992£i®S£3S_P. From. Politioal Besident, Buahlra. To. High Oomiaaioner, Baghdad No 272. Repeated Secretary of state for Colonies, Dated the 17th April 1929. Politioal Agent has Been assured By Shaikh of Kuwait that he will not allow triBes which are in rebellion against IBn 3aud to obtain their supplies from his territory and that he will do all that that is possible in preventing any suoh triBes from taking refuge in Kuwait territory. Above refers to Colonial Office telegram of the 11th April No 126. oet copy »ent to the '•'ollUoal A^ect at for inforimtion only. No 9 •Jnder Secretary to the political Resident In the i’ereli® Gulf, Bue hire # 'po April 1929.Tclcgrmn Pm f* Z*1 from, Political Resident in Gamp (Muscat). Te. Senior Karal,Officer,Persian Gulf, repeated Political Bushire. Ho. Vl6- Dated 10th (reed 11th) May 1929. In view of possibility that Ajaan may force themselves on to Sheikh^ hospitality he ? asks that gunboat may be in readiness to proceed tx at short notice to Kuwait » ^opy to the Political l^gent, Bahrain. (titu.. &lt; Under Secretary to the Political Resident to the Persian uulfo WTelegram P» 7toUo Political Resident (Muscat)* Te« High Commissioner^ Baghdad 9 repeated Secretary of State for Colonies ( Political Kuwait Agent t SxKh±ZK and Political Bushirce Ho» B/I 80 Dated 11th (reod 12th) l£sy 1929« f /, 1 agree that action by RoA*7» to (expel ?) rebels from Kuwait territoxy should be taken if Sheikh applies for assistance which he probably will do should Ajman enter his territory and refuse to leave when ^ ordered or if Ibn Mashur has not crossed frontier by spe olfled 1iate May 14th- Ab0V (Jbjfr Ho 46/S ( 182 to Secretary of State for Colonies)* Copy to the Political ^gent,Bahrain. Un&amp;er Secretary to the Po_itical Resident in the Persian G-ulloTelegram P. •4 Proa Government of India, yorelfn and Political De x jartiacnt. Bimla. 70 Politiaal KcBident, BuRhirc, Mo, 1727/F5e Bated 22na (received 23rd ) May 1929. 'In regard to Hajdi tribeoiaen taking refuge in Kuaftlt, 'I agree, reluotantiy, to Shaikh's being asked to concur in ase of aiilhary force, if necessary, if His Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies and the Air Ministry considered such a request was still essential on condition that nature and extent of such iorce should be determined by the Air Officer Commanding Iraq, in consultation eith the Resident in the Persian Gulf. 'British Agent at Jeddah telegraphed on 8th May message from Ibn raid requesting that steps should b * taken t0 re8i8t bands of rebels sho intended to move towards Iraq. High Commissioner at BagMad telegraphed vies that refugees were more likely to make for Kuwait territory. Colonial Office accordingly, with »y concurrence, authorised High Commissioner, on the Uth May. to approach the Shaikh through the Resident with a request in terms previously agreed upon.' he -oregoing la 11.M's. Secretary of State for India's telegram gated the 18th May. No. 1600. - TORBIOM. Post copy to the Political Agent at itoEkmaXisiiLMuiEhjfx for information.only. for Uncle: Buohire. 24th May^l929? GuIf\ 0;llUCta Resid 'ntUOttt nifeh Goi-imi&amp;tii Oixer fur .pa^iiUc d ivtiBiaeiit Jbuuiixre Ttlegram jf’rom To Ko. toil Latuu aiia reoervua tn : Jth I IT 01 &gt;T ART # Rioting Miaiater lor foreign Al‘fairs t jiepiiOiied ia® liiis morning from Mecca arid saici he ha d been oharged to convey following mesoage from ibn uaud. Begins '• We underatand band of our subjects fleeing fron our punitive expedition intend to uove towards 'Iraq. Thqy have chosen as their base Sobania and frontier none north of nasa and near Kuwait territory- moving northwards towards Kuwait, vie understand moreover that they are wlll&lt; mg to co.anit hostile acts on 'Iraq ai.d in frontier zone. They are being pursued by our punitive force and we are druid they will eventually oe compelled to edmnit in ■Iraq acts viiica we disapprove. we therefore request his majesty’s Uovernment to take steps to resist them so txxut uny MXwfwrtv further trouble on frontier may be avoideti ^ ^iidB# minister of foreign Aflairs said this message uia not mean to imply ais i.ajesty gave his consent article 6 hahxa Agreement to crossing of frontier. Minister of i'ereign Affairs stated he would confirm massage in writing to reach me tomorrow. ' H X G HC C1IA “ aopy to the Pol^joal Xeent ,.3aiiraia Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Sulf*Telegram V7 From* High Commisai oner, Baghdad• To* Secretary of State for Colonie b*Ho 182o Repeated to .^litital Reo ident ,Bus hire .Political Agent, Kuwait and Jeddah Ho 46/8 and reed Dated/9th May 1929 « $m mm mm mm Important^ Bin Saud hae already been infouned that the Government of Iraq intend to refuse asylum to Afchwan rebels* Recent developments which I hare reported in my telegrams 163 and 181 indicate that Akhwan rebel refugees are more likely to make for Kuwait territory aa Bin Mashhur has done already* Aetion by Royal Air Force here to expel them from at Sfteikh of Kuwaiti request •approved by the Resident/ Such request would be welcomed by me as action in Kuwait territory could seem only possible means of recovering any of Iraq loot whieh may still be in possession of Bin Mashhur and others. Foregoing refs From, Political Bushire* Bo, Political Resident (Muscat), No * 426, Dated the 10th May 192£ • Following from High Commissloner,Baghdad 46/3 May 9t h Begins Bin Saud X X Kuwait telegrapgh his comments to you direct and to repeat®* here, Kuwait territory will of course not be taken encept Persian Gulf, to Jeddah tele: 71(55 to F,0,) which has been repeated Resident Persian Gul and Kuwait, Telegra m P, Ends Political Kuwait has been instructed to c*/.Trm» High Gonmiocionor* Baghdad* To* Political Resident 9 Bushire Bil. Dated and rood the 10th hair 1929o Important o Jeddah telegraphs as gollose to foreign Office Ho Begins Minister for foreign Affairs was told by to be (aTailriole ?) in Jeddah ricinity* A nuaber of British pilgrim ships are of course lying idle in harbour* They will not be required until after HaJ and for the purpose in view they are suitable* Minister for foreign Affairs informed me that he quite understood that for eorviooe now desired payment was necessary* 1 gather however that they desire to keep cost as low as possible and think that it would be cheaper to hare a British troop ship* than a pilgrim ship* Z was also informed by Minister for foreign Affairs that a reply at the earliest possibls moment was desired by the King ; Minister pressed me to obtain a deolsion atvan early date* me that 1 considered it unlikely for a British troopship ji Copy by post to the Political Agent 9 tom uit-* Un^er Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Ouif•Telegram «f P . 3'^ t 3?4 froa* High Commiasioncr, Baghdad « To* cal Resident 9 Buahlro» MO* Mil* and rood Dated/ the 10th Kay 192 9. Importanto Foil oiling telegram 72 reoeired from Jeddah. My telegram 52 to Foreign Offiee urgent is repeated as follows Begins This morning Bin Sand arrived Jeddah. Acting Minister for Foreign Affaire X 30DC Ka begh __ to meet Hie Majesty ; on his return he saw me and stated that owing to Bin Hithlain's death Xing anticipated trouble with A$man. He accordingly wished to despatch imragliately a force to Hasa but was confronted with fact that he had dispersed troops recently assembled Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian uulfo in Hejd and that he had transport difficulties* Copy to the Poll teal Age|[t, Bahrain— V)' 0 TGigkr&amp;in P o from* High Commissioner, Bagfrd&amp;do To* Secretary of State for Colonies ho 166,re(c ated Bushire, Jeddah and India No 49/3 Dated and Rood 10th Hay 1929 Important» (offer ?) I hare no ohjeotlon/to Ibn Baud's sped fie requests I agree that we shouM,in principle, do everything possihlem to assist him to reassert his authority* and pacify frontier dlstriet* In (response ?) to Ibn Sand's request forces in Iraq are (ready ?} to cooperate by dealing with any rebel* lious Hejdi tribes who may seek to enter Iraq*{n this connection please refer to my telegrams 182 Hay 9th,46/s to Bushire and Jeddah/* Action so far in Kuwait is confined £o protection with Sheikh's specific pemission of all tribes grazing in his territory* If a similar request is made hy Ibn Saud as regards Kuwait where Hashhur and some of Ajxnan rebels have taken refuge already with large quantitiesof loot from Dahaimshah and other Iraq shepard tribes I con sider that we should comply by affording such assistao ce as may be desired by Gheikh of Kuwait with Political Resident's concurrence * I hope that a reminder as regards the large quantities of loot taken from Iraq tribes by his recalcitrant Chiefs which is due for restitution mu will accompany may promise of assistance to Ibn Baud* fefers to your telegram dated the 9th Hay No 157. lopy to the Political Agent,Bahrain, U n 4er Secretary to the Political Peaident in the Persian (iulf*Telfcgrttm J'roiQ. Hic;h Coraxaiasloner, Sa^clad lit leal Kesla en*, ”^ichii , e Ko* W^l 0 Dated and Heed the 13th Uw 1939* If© 185 of the 10th May* In view of message oontained in ttle ho 55 from JedtfRhf Ho 71 to you) it ifi clearly undenirable that \ Kuwait territory# You should therefoi*e approach aheiJch through Bolitical J^osident onl Invite hiia concurrence to uee/ military force extent and nature of utiich uhould he de termined by Air Officer Corananding Iruq in consultation with Political Resident with a view to prevent this* Ibn r.aud should be informed by you through Jeddah as regards the measures that are being adopted to secure this obejet* IIease xrnom*x repeat/ to Political Resident ,Knds OL-^Csx i Copy by post to the Political Agent»Kuwait* hejd refugees should be allowed to enter or i*em&amp;in in Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Peraian G-ulif#^7^ T alagraa J? Trora. High Couimissioner # Baghdad. To* ^olitival Heoldent, Buehire. Ho. 5l/0o JDatf»d 16th (r?c4 17th) 1929. Jcddali’a t«l#?rram to 3for«ifm Office Ho 61 dated May IDth and repeated to Baghdad and India under Ho 78 Ibn Saud sent Minister for Foreign Affairs to Jeddah to enquire as to the position regarding the arms and ammuni tion required; (if ?) ttourn /arrival was delated they would be of no use. The need for them was urgent. Cn lines of your telegrams Hob 46 and 46 X endeavoured to reassure Minister for Foreign Affairs but his anxiety oouldnot be relieved entirely. He said that even if 500 rifles machine guns available immediate steps (for despat on ?) would be a great help. I was aked by Minister for Foreign Affairs whether some further information for early •oramunication oould not be obtained* oopy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain is as follows Begins My telegram Ho 60# This morning their T’nder Secretary tc the lit teal He si dent in the Persian Gulf*Tela^raa i&gt; f _ Fr««. Political Agent, Kuwait. Toe Political Hetidcnt (Henjam) restated Political Bushiro* He, 340* Dated 10th (reed Uth) itay 1929 • raoiz as a ? ^uald liJte to Sheikh says he cannot obtain restitution® As raids were In Mejd and Ibn Maahur lug obtained or at any rat a appligd talwn only action at whit* Bin Sand oannot ooa- pUln in ordering bin to leava Rub ait territory, 'i th rtiat aninala be ban (a/though polnta are not mentioned by bin,Bin .laud'a olain to natinmi.Kov , should be reaieiabered) • Above reiers to Baghdad 9 s telegram Ho 164» Oopy by post to th© Political Agent rftmmiU Under Secretary to the rolltioal iiesident in the Persian uuUf• 4■■ • - •yn Telegram P» Tram. Political Agent,Kuwait* To. Political Resident (Hcnjaa) repeated Political Buskite• No. 339. Dated 10th and reod 11th Msy 1929* If Ajman cone to Kuwait territory and do not leaTC when ordered to do co or if Ibn Maehhur has not croeced thefrontier hy specified date (he should do so by 14th May) I think it ic probable that Sheikh will ask for suntxatan assistance. I think we should agree if and when he does ask. Above/ refers to telegran 46/S from Baghdad* Gopy to the Political ilgent,Bahrain. (llfkL-L. Unler 3eoretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gull*.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00033a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/91</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00033a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/91</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/18 III Major Head:- Political. Subject:- Sultan of Najd's relations with Iraq.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-05-19T00:28:38</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (347 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are filed in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after the relevant covering letter.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 349; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 7-348; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file deals with political relations between the King of Hejaz and Najd [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd] (commonly referred to in the papers as Bin Saud or Ibn Saud) and the states of Iraq and Kuwait, particularly in terms of raids by Akhwan [Ikhwān] tribes from Najd, and Bin Saud's efforts to control the Akhwan.The correspondence is mainly between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Political Agent, Bahrain (Major Cyril Charles Johnson Barrett); the Political Agent, Kuwait (Lieutenant-Colonel James Carmichale More), and the Secretariat of the High Commissioner for Iraq, Baghdad. There is also correspondence between British officials and Bin Saud. Enclosures to correspondence from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf include copies of correspondence with the Political Agent, Kuwait; the Secretariat of the High Commissioner, Iraq; the Colonial Office, London; the Government of India; the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf; and other British officials in the region; enclosures to correspondence from the Political Agent, Kuwait include correspondence with the Secretariat of the High Commissioner for Iraq, and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; enclosures to correspondence from the Secretariat of the High Commissioner, Iraq, include reports from Captain John Bagot Glubb, Administrative Inspector, Southern Desert.The papers cover: diplomatic contact between the British and Bin Saud; list prepared by Political Agent, Bahrain of estimated Nejd [Najd] population likely to obey a summons from Bin Saud, 8 April 1928 (folios 18-19); action by Bin Saud against the Akhwan; raids by Akhwan tibes, especially Mutair and Ajman; involvement of Hafiz Wahab [Shaikh Hāfiẓ Wahbah]; Iraqi frontier posts; reports of intended raids; movements of desert tribes; defensive measures; movements of British naval forces; references to Dawish [Fayṣal al-Dawīsh]; Bin Saud's negotiations with leaders of Akhwan, 6 May 1928; report by Political Agent, Bahrain on economic and political implications of blockade of Hasa [al-Aḥsā’] ports, 28 November 1928 (folios 118-123), and further, December 1928; attempts by British to preserve frontier peace (e.g. folios 132-135); reports by Captain John Bagot Glubb, Administrative Inspector, Southern Desert, November 1928, March 1929; reports of Riyadh Conference, December 1928; reference to 'jihad', 24 January 1929 (folio 181); United States (US) missionaries caught up in raids, January 1929 (folios 184-186); reported successes of Bin Saud against Akhwan, April 1929; report by Political Agent, Kuwait on attitude of Shaikh of Kuwait [Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ] to Ikhwan raids, 29 March 1929 (folios 291-300); discussion of need to assist Shaikh of Kuwait to expel refugees defeated by Bin Saud from Nejd, May 1929; Iraq to refuse asylum to Akhwan rebels, May 1929 (folio 332).The Arabic language content of the file consists of approximately twenty-five folios, with translations in English, mainly copies of correspondence between the Political Agency, Bahrain and Bin Saud.The date range indicates the covering dates of the main run of correspondence. However, the earliest document in the file is a copy of an enclosure dated 27 March 1928 on folio 9.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ikhwan, military and religious brotherhood</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Hejaz and Najd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Iraq Government Service, Administrative Inspector, Southern Desert</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Military operations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00033a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>