<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000179_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:33:47.065Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">1/2/49) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN 22nd January, 1949. /! ) I enilose herewith a copy of an article by Miss Elizabeth Munroe on ’’Russia's Oil Impe rialism'. At the present stage this is intended for your own personal information, but if you see no objection copies may be distributed to the manager/managers of oil companies for such publicity as they consider suitable. * i,v. ■) /c C.J. Felly, Esq., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. /-v Po ~ c ' v ^ y, Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.RUSSIA'S OIL IMPERIALISM by Elizabeth Monroe Miss Monroe 5 who is on the staff of ' Mie Economist' (London) was formerly Diploma tic Correspondent of 'The Observer' Hov^much oil has Soviet Russia ? Is her supply genuinely shorty if not, why is she despoiling the Central European oil fields ; And why are her eyes on those owned by the Middle Eas ternstates Figures are necessary for the answer to thes- leading questions. Contrary to expectation, they are available They ar^' fragmentary, but they exist. Russia’s present oil production is somewhere between t1 mil- lien tons a year, and the 35.4 million tons target set in the live year plan that will end in 1950, Much progress has been made, t orefore, since production sagged to the low level of under 2C million tons a year in World War II. The currer^ fi- gme is a long way short of the 60 million tons target set in btalm-s election speech of February 1946. But it is also iar short of what Russia can an* will produce once she breaks some ere- senu bottlenecks. These botvlenecks are due partly to a clumsy’ industrial set-up but partly, also, to understandable delays in recovering from the destruction caused to the industry by the w r. Russian statistics show that home production, as well as increasing, has lately become much more widespread. It is i a 1:. - ger exc-.-sively centred, as it used to be, 'in the vu- iera 1 'ie a - ” near the Caucasian frontier. .Great efforts are being devoted tT spreading it over remoter areas. New fields are being steadily discovered. Some are already yielding satisfactorily^ as the iollowing figures show. Current production is about the same as that of 1940, In that year 90 per cent of total output came from tie Caucasus. -low the area between the Urals and the Middle Volga - ofiielalmy aub ed the 'second Baku' - is growing almost as prolific. (. oto* its relative nearness to.Moscow and the Upper Don basin indu. tr ies,. The so-called Emba district, north and ea.^t of the Cas pian Sea, is not far behind. The latest figures available show uhac whereas Caucasus production has dropped as a percentage f the tota to 42 per cent only, the 'second Baku’s' has risen ol.o per cent and that of the Emba area to 20.6 per cent. Total restives, of course, are problematical, but home' d foreign guesses nut them at some 15 to 20 per cent of the world fi^i j. m a wore, they are immense, and are not at present being t .pnec nearly to the full. P.iA. Rese-&gt;- ues Of Neighbours . Why, then, is Russia so interested in the oil reserves of her neighbours ? Why, wherever the Red Army goes in Europe, is 'he local oil industry at once browbeaten and shaped to suit Russian needs ? Could not local oil be left in local hands ? things stand, the producing areas of Poland and Estonia hare actually been incorporated in the Soviet Union whether the like: -t or no. Defeated Rumania has been made not only to pay vast uepc rations in oil, but to place much of her now small exportable surplus as Russia’s disposal. Agreements with Hungary and Aus tria ha^ r e secured for the Russians a predominating grip on the oetre leun industries of both countries. Their local staffs have Roe.-' accused of sabotage and. 'reckless artificial decrease of / production'O CJ - 2 - production' whenever they have Tailed to hand over their out put} and have been replaced. Once in control, the Russians are using the fields at what western experts believe to be a destructive rate. Why sieze and exhaust them ? By comparison with what could be u^odu- ced inside Russia their output is sma^l. Four million tons! cumuaily from Rumania, and two from Austria and Hungary, is no grecit figure. But it is ample for the local needs of the Red Ar my and Russian civilian occupiers. It is for this immediate pur pose that the fields are being exhausted today. Russia comes first. ^ The situation in the Middle East is rather different. To see^it clearly, a distinction must be drawn between two different series of oil;, deposits there. The lesser deposits lie in north 5 °u the Caspian shore and just across the mountains near lehran„ here resources are unproven, and production on a commer- cial scale is untried. Immensely greater deposits lie far to the south, on the Persian Gulf in Arabia . nd in Iraq. The oil in nor th Persia (In which the Russians lately tried and failed to gain a controlling interest by agreement with the Persians) belongs geologically and practically speaking to the Caspian fields. If oil were found here in commercial quantities it could more econo mically be exported northward to Russia than southwards across the ranges the:t separate it from the open sea. To secure Russian participation in its management would therefore be logical} but is dreaded -by the Persians because they fear a fate like Hungary's - an absorption of their oil for armies of Russian servants, whe ther in or out of uniform, and the establishment of a politicaJ spearhead inside Persian territory. They fear that the Russians want their oilfields both as a resource and as a jumping off place Pers ian Gulf Mid Iraq The same cannot be said of Russian ambitions in the far more valuable areas of the Persian Gulf and Iraq - areas whose combined output was, last year, over 40 million tons of oil. Here chu as signs of Russia have few connexions with ± her armies of servancs abroad. For the Persian Gulf is a long way from Russia. And e^en if the Russians were to wrest control of the fields from their present owners - that is, from their Persian and Arab ground land lords, and from their British and American tenants - they could not carry away the produce without control of the seas. Russia's target in the Middle East is not possession. It is wreckage of the yield on which the non-Russian world counts for stability and prosperity. What, in sheer material terms, would such wreckage entail for producer anc 1 customer ? The Persian c id Arab producers lose Royalties and payments in the form of wage bills that amount to as much as one-fifth of their total national budgets Indian ana Pakistani customers would see the whole of their 'oil fuel for industry and defence in jeopardy; nations farther east, though Tu SS T epen ^ ent on the Persian Gulf, would see a useful source threatened«. ,, , handicapped likewise. It is seldom realised tnat the Marshall Plan countries are counting on Middle East 0 i L ' L oi° r 38,6 P Gr cent of their requirements in 1948, and for asmuch s 8^ p^r cent by 1951. To hamper Middle East oil production is n easy way to sabotage the. M. rshall Plan. If, as a by-product oi that process,^ Asia’s oil supplies are jeopardised, so much the ’worse for Asia. So are they thinking in Hosco?/. Russian, policy sets out to stem Middle East oil production in two guisess. Under the cloak of communism, it reaches at the / workerSECRET . j&amp;jj£/£=£L&gt; No.c7L-64. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to 1. The n olitical Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, 2. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrein Petroleum Company, Ltd., Awali, 3. The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrein, and has the honour to transmit to him three copies of the undermentioned document, for such publicity as they consider suitable. H.E.M'S POLITICAL AGENCY, Dated 3rd February, 1949. Reference to previous correspondence* NIL Description of enclosure Subject. An article by Miss Elizabeth Munroe RUSSIA'S OIL IMPERIALISMINDIA OFFICE RECORDS M!£Rofilm</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000179_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/914</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000179</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/914</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 43/6 Russia's Oil Imperialism'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-04-23T00:13:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (8 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 8; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains a copy of an article written by Elizabeth Monroe (then of
                           The Economistand formerly diplomatic correspondent of
                           The Observer) that is entitled 'Russia's Oil Imperialism'.The article analyses the oil policy of Soviet Russia (with reference to the Gulf) and was sent to Cornelius James Pelly, Political Agent in Bahrain by William Rupert Hay, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf on January 22 1949.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000179#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>