<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000145_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T03:37:30.758Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">T«legr«jn From To Ke. Nil Da t ed Thirteon ImixJt Sheikh Abdulla, Dukha* Political Agent, Bahrain The 6th and received herethe 7th February, 1949. Assietance been given to all Somalieo you mentioned sent t© 3 ahrain by launch. - Sheikh Abdulla■bMM A POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 7th February 1949 LANDING PERMIT It is requested that thirteen Somali subjects arriving from Qatar may be permitted to land in Bahrain. - f &amp; OLITICAL AGKNI, BAHRAIN. 7 /*/71 ~ v - Y ? Stat ment made by the undernamed thur Somalis who were sent to Bahrain by the ruler of Qatar. \ ihe owner of the boat is a local merchant called Haji Ebrahim Bin Ahmud subject of Adan. The craft on board of which we were crew was chartered by the Government of Adan. It was used in carrying petrol from Dherfar ( a city situated at Muascat where the R.A.F. station is ) to Adan. On the last journey which started from Adan in which the tragedy occurred the number of all the persons on board the boat were thirty men out of which twentyrone were crew and the remaining pass engers. AThile we were journeying somewhere on the sea of Muscat a sudden storm arose which resulted in capsizing the boat. We were all thrown in the sea and trusted ou^.elves to the mercy of God and the waves. After a long weary swimming we were Relieved by a trsve- lling boat which happened to sail in that part. They disem barked us at Muscat. The Sultan of Muscat objected to our . entry into the town. Accordingly we made our way towards Dubai for which we had to walk ten days on feet. On our arrival at Dubai we approached the ruler. We explained to him all particulars about our pitiable condition but sorry to say that he did not give any attention to it . Finally we appeared before a local merchant at dubai who kindly afforded to us facilities and ordered for a launch to carry us to Qatar where we expected to join the company there and earn our living. At Qatar we took our refuge in a place which by the help of Suieh Aimanea' we procured. Saleh Almanea* instructed us that our case had been referred to the Political Agent at Bahrain and that our appearance before him is required. We are thirteen men reaching Bahrain safely. The rest are seventeen men out of which eight died and the remaining are suffering from ill health and were left at Qatar for medical treatment. Now we leave our case for you to decide. CHEW Mahmood Othman Abd Hersi Abdulla Ahmud Osman Dheri Ebrahim Hassan Fareh Mohd. Mohammed Mahmood Yousuf Husein Husein Fareh Mohammed Jamia* Husein Gaidah Taher Elipi Hersi Adam PASSENGERS Mahmood Chamia’ Mohammed Hersi Jamia’ Yasin Hassan lamia* Aral! Ahmud Hassan Yasin Ahmud Mohammed■MM &lt;r (B&gt; Sn Clair Saleh Almana, Dukhan. Political Agent, Bahrain. The 8t&gt;» and received the 9th Feoruary, 1949 &amp; AS YOUR ORDER 13 SOiULIES WERE SENT AND 7 ARE LEAVING tvis day. - POLITICAL -POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, No.R-74 The 13th February, 1949 Dear Residency, Twenty Somalis alleged to have been crew and passengers of a boat that sank somewhere near Muscat have recently arrived in Bahrain from Qatar. A copy of their statement is enclosed herewith. 2. These Somalis who are now destitutes have made a request to us to arrange for their repatria tion to their homeland in the British Somaliland and until such time as arrangements for their repatriation have been made to be provided with maintenance allowances. 3. We should be grateful if you would kindly let us know if it is in order for us to grant maintenance allowances and arrange for the re patriation, and if so, how these expenses may ultimately be recovered. W5 should also be glad to know from what funds advances for maintenance can be made. Yours ever, AGENCY. s . ?No.404- POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 19th February, 1949. The undermentioned telegram is forwarded with compliments to:- Mr.B•H.Lermitte, Petroleum Conce sions Ltd., BAHRAIN . for favour of despatch by his company’s wireless FOE POLITICAL AG..NT, BAHRAIN. Telegram No.112 dated the 19th February, 1949, from Political, Bahrain, to Saleh Almana, Doha. f(162/3/49) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, ISth February, 1949. R/74 of the 13th February about the maintenance and repatriation of twenty Somalis. Similar cases have occurred in Muscat and Kuwait, and the difficulties have been found to be, firstly, that there is no proof of their having been ship-wrecked (in Kuwait some who claimed this was found to have been discharged from Aramco, for whom they had been working), secondly, there is usually no proof of their British nationality, which makes the payment of any money to them difficult to justify, and thirdly, in cases where money has been*advanced to ^ them for repatriation, it has not been used for the intended purpose. It is presumed that the men concerned are still able bodied, and in the circumstances we would suggest that it might be possible for you to arrange for them to work their passage back on some vessel. Should they really wish to return to their homeland, they will no doubt take advantage of this.C. 12.46. TELEGRAMS : PETROQAT. BAHREIN ‘ CODES: BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED • I J. W. aoruE, C.B.F.. Sir W. Frasfr. C.B.E.. N. A. Gas*. C. S. Gulbenkian (eormeruy Armenian) J. B. A. Kesslkr. (dutch; OE METE, (trench) R. OE MONTAIOU. (TRENCH) R. W. SEU-ERS, M.C.. O. A. SHEPARD, (CITIZEN OP U.S.A.) J. SKUROS. O.B.E. Please refer to your No*404 dated the 19th February 1949, The telegram mentioned therein was duly transmitted to Saleh Al Mana. In this connection we have received the following signal from our representative stationed at Doha which we quote for your information and any action you deem necessary: ‘‘Reference telegram to Saleh Almana Political 112 stop Saleh declines send Somalis until he knows who is to bear cost of passage stop For information this Somali business is likely to occur again and again since new ones are always arriving stop Could not Political people warn off Somalis in Aden and Somaliland to avoid further cases of stranding stop” BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF Q/tasc/7065 Confidential 23rd February, 1949 H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain, SOMALIS Yours faithfully. 9 For &amp; on behalf of 'OLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED MANAGER fma/acmSAVIWGfiAM . POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. To PRODROME, BAHRAIN. No. 91 Dated P7th February, 1949. Reference correspondence ending with your letter ho.(162/3/49), dated the 19th February, 1949. 2. Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited report that in their opinion more Somalis are likely to land in Qatar and suggest that authorities in Aden and Somaliland be told to warn their people against this wandering in search of work. I do not know on what information Oil Company's supposition is based, but ask that action suggested by them,vis a vis Aden and Somali Governments, may please be taken. POLITICAL■■ (162/8/49) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 8th March, 1949. Dear Agency, Will you plea§e refer to your savingram No. R/91^6f the 27th February about Somali labour in the Gulf? 2. The Political Resident will shortly be visiting Aden and will discuss the matter with the authorities there. You will be informed of the result on his return. Yours ever,&amp; No. /JfcS- / ^ of 1368 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 15th J/Awal, 1 368 March 15 &gt; 1949. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum The Passport Officer reports that 31 Somalis entered Bahrain recently from Qatar, without passports, 'but with letteiv addressed to you 'by the Shaikh of Qatar. They were registered on the following dates 14.1 .49 - 7 men. 7.2.49 - 13 ' 4.3.49 - 11 ” There are now a number of Somalis living in Manama, some are employed, others are not. Somalis are notoriously truculent and there have already been some minor incidents between them and the Police. The Government would like to restrict the entrance of Somalis to those who have proper passports and visas for Bahrain and also wishes all Somalis who are unemployed to go elsewhere. Can you give me any information about the 31 Somalis from Qatar who came with a letter from the AY.No. JT 0 POLITICAL AGENCY, BA^^RAIN, Dated 27th March, 1949. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Memorandum . Reference your memorandum No.1203-15, dated the 15th March, 1949. 2. The 31 Somalis mentioned were alleged to have been ship-wrecked in Qatar, but it looks as if they went there in search of work in the oil company which did not wish to employ them. They appealed to this Agency for assistance and were sent here by the Shaikh of Qatar. 3. There is no objection to the Government res tricting the entrance of Somalis into Bahrain, but it is difficult to deport those here at present as the question arises as to who is to pay their expenses (SGD) C.J. PELLY Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED . ■J^/v for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.No.3229-16/31 Dear Secretariat, © Political Agency, Bahrain, November 16, 1949 We have received a passport apnlication from one Jama Yessir, who claims to be a national of the British Somaliland, being of the Habr Yunis Musa Abdulla, Farah Mohamed. We enclose an affidavit signed by Haji Jama Hirsi of Burao. The annlicant states that this latter will sign a bond for him. This man has work as a shoe maker and we recommend that if his claims are sub stantiated and a bond signed, we should be per mitted to grant him a passport. Will you please let us know if you agree? Would you please return the en closure with your reply? Yours ever, Agency. The Secretariat, Hargeisa, British Somaliland.SAN 1950 ^ahra\^ THE SECRETARIAT, HARGEI3A, SOMALILAND PROTECTORATE, 21st January, 1950. Dear Agency, 15 S'W V/e refer to your letter No.3229-16/81 of the 16th November, 19L9, concerning an application for a passport for Haji Jama Hersi, H.Y. Musa Abdulla, and return herev/ith the enclosures and Bond, which has been duly executed. 2. There is no objection to the issue of a passport. Yours ever SECRETARIAT SPF/AADpolitical agency, BAHRAIN, November, 16th 1949* have received a passport application from one Jama Yessir, who claims to be a national of the British Somaliland, being of the Habr Tunis Musa Abdulla, Parah Mohamed. TTe enclose an affidavit signed by Baji Jama Hirsi of Burao. The applicant states that this latter will sign a bond for Him. This man has work as a shoe maker and we recommend that if his claims are substantiated and a bond signed, we should be permitted to grant him a passport. Will you please let us know if you agree ? Would you please return the enclosure with your reply ? Yours ever. AGENCY J.G. THE SECRETARIAT, HARGEISA. BRITISH SOMALILAND.AFFIDAVIT Affidavit of ffeji Jama Hirsi Tribe Hagr Abdulla, Farah Mohamed, duly^affirmed stated That Jama Yessir Habr Yunis, Musa Abdulla, Farah Moh’d, is one of my tribesmen and is thus British Protected Person of the British Somaliland Protectorate. That his profession is Shoemaker. That the purpose of executing this/dtocax Statement is that it may be of use to him for identification purposes regarding his nationality. In witness whereof I have hereunto set my hand in Burao .'British Somaliland this tey of August, 1949. affirmed LTM. of Haji Jama Hirsi, Habr Yunis Musa Abdulla, Farah Mohamed.r British Agen Doha, 6th June, 1950, Many more Somalis seem to be coming to Qatar recently than was formerly the case, and when they are unable to get work with the Company, they tend to beseige me, and demand their rights as 'British Subjects', This does not worry me unduly, but they have lately shown signs of greater excitement at their lack of success, and of being under the influence of one or two 'agitator” typres, 4. I do not wish to suggest in any way that the situation is beyond the powers of the Qatar Police to manage, but I should be glad if any steps could be taken, especially before Raraadhan, to decrease the flow of these people, who have little chance of finding employment here. Cochrane and Sultan Saif are of the opinion that Ali bin Hassan al Somali in Bahrain is arranging their movement into Qatar, and that the increased numbers are due to the fact that with Kuwait, Saudi Arabia and Bahrain virtually closed to them, Qatar is the only place/for him to send them. 3. If you think that this is the case, and if there is any hope that a word in season to Ali bin Hassan would lead to a diminution of his activities in this res pect, I should be grateful if the word could be spoken. There is still very little that the Government of Qatar can do in the way of physical prevention of landing* C. J. Pelly Esq., 0.3. E., Political Agent, Bahrain.Dear ffllton, Political Agency, Bahrain, 11th June, 1950. I have had a word with Ali bin Hassan al Somali, who has of course denied that he has had any thing: to do with the movements of Somaiis into Qatar, I have told him that if I haar that this ig, the case I will expel him from Bahrain. Your 7/72/50 of 6th June refers. /) Yours sincerely, A, J. Wilton, ' scj., Political Officer, Qatar, Doha.4 % y. 5 '. Cmce arer Me f ^!t att ^ h ! d *i etter i£ seated ^ the Arabic ruler nf stated that these Somalis have approached the the La o? oat a th ' lr boat has sank somewhere repatriate ?Lm f a ? d » the before, they requested him to i.wp&lt;itriate t^em to their home. He adderf that t^erp i c; of™“ar? ° n ^ thlS res P® B ^ ^tween the P.A. and the ruler I.T.D. M.A. A.P.A. ■ 7 / 2 Have the Somalis come? Ask bearer to come in. I.T.D. J.E.H. Confirmed Somalis have come. Have we any pps? I.T.D. J.E.H. C o 0. No pps. Supt. No pps. P.P.C. The telegram referred to by the ruler of Qatar was not issued from the passport office. On 5.2.49, we two^omL?!? ap P llcat ?- on for Landing Permission from two Somalis (pps. below) and the ordesshre in the ■I.T.D.K.R.M. 7/2 ss.’SS 4 .;: ■ iu ^ I.T.D. J.E.H. a/4: */U* Z ^ ^ y - /i ^ &lt;£) /C^v cs&amp;f ' ? - £ - Y ^ (3 The total number of Stomal is who have been sent ^ here from Qatar is W persons. Their statement taken by my assistant is submitted below. These persons are destitutes and request that, they may either be provided with employment or be repatriated to their homeland at Government's expenses, lease? ./ ^.. . , ^ L &lt; dU (JU-mtm W s cS In the last para of the p.u.c. the Residency suggest //• that it- might be possible for us to arrange for the Somalis to work their passage back on some vessel, ^his is not within the realm of practical achievement in Bahrain where there no local countrycraft plying between Bahrain and Somaliland or between Bahrain and Aden. The only alternative would be for us to help them get employment in Bahrain until such time as they have earned sufficient money to pay their passages home. But again^f this alternative has its defects, as apart from the fact that it would constitute a precedent and would encourage more Somalis to come to Bahrain and approach us for such help, it would never be possible to say when they have earned sufficient money for their passage. They can always pretend to be penniless and in case pressure is brought to bear upon them to leave they can again demand to be repatriated at Government's expenses. For orders, please?13. No. Sir; there are no dhows leaving Bahrain for Aden or Red Sea ports. Such dhows may be available in Kuwait and Basrah from which dhows sail laden with dates for those parts, % please? h luyUU CL* ^ r r Av /. /f- On enquiry from a Kuwaiti merchant in Bahrain I am told that the sailing season lasts for another 15 to 20 days and that there is every possibility of dhows being available until then, please. A. £&lt;A. o*. Jflsi A^UM. &lt;v*. If fax. A iW { k&gt; )u*xr*s •SL^yJ k ^ JtA* &lt;?4 Aa. &lt; be X jcL, x4evr AaI.: S 11 -w (Vhv*. tnr&lt;^ ^ fUW ic ^&lt;- hrM io ^ ^ ^ctsjyuAsisL ■ fX. i'k*™ kl’A. i'K s^U- lu^ ■ ~■ /W- ny- *&lt;/ v (f, ; /?- 9 / , ^ A? - l-* I , t tL~ / O °°f' 3 /*/ ■ y^t/— Salih Al-Mani’ in reply to our telegram at S # 5 declined to send the Somalis to Bahrain unless he first knew who would pay for their repatriation expenses. Please see S.8 in this connection. The Somalis have been allowed to land in Bahrain and have come to the Agency. I asked them what we could Homeland tSoraaTilandJ at Governments cost or to be helped in securing emjbloyment in Bahrain. Their appearance does not bear out the allegation made by them that th&amp;y are ship-wrecked. However, in view of the Residency’s reply at S.7, their demand for repatriation cannot be ra&lt;*frt. Similarly their request for assistance for them to get employment locally is impossible to grant, as this would constitute a precedent and encourage more Somalis to approach us with the same request. May reply as suggested in the Residency’s letter, o.y, pxeaserice th ^ 3 ^ y A !&gt; 11 i nf 6 \^J&gt; j ^!\ 7 ^ y cS/ ^ ' ? - V 7 Y X^&lt;&lt;Ua o/^ « c&lt; c 1&lt;_ 4_ /C ^ 1 Q. ^ ft'&amp;'&lt;&amp; /7 /y^ ? The 31 Samalis referred to in the p.u.c. came to Bahrain from Qatar and were allowed to land here on the understanding that they were ship-wrecked and therefore entitled to repatriation at Government's expenses to their homeland in Somaliland. Reference to this effect was made to the Residency with a request to approve of Government's bearing such expenses as the maintenance and repatriation of these Somalis would entail; but the Residency, for certain reasons declined to accord their approval and suggested instead that, they might be helped to work their passage home on some vessels (vide flagged pages S.4 and S.7) 0 x he restrictions the Bahrain Gorernment likes us to impose on the entry of such Somalis are alreadyin force and it is for the Bahrain Government passport authorities to eheck and see that no Somali lands at Bahrain without being in possession of a proper passport duly visad for Bahrain. The fcdtljttfitxi Agency has already asked the Residency to represent to the proper authorities in Aden and Somaliland the undesirability of Somalis coming to the Gulf in search of employment and the necessity of steps to be taken to prevent them. In this connection, please see flagged pages 9 &amp; 11. The Bahrain Government's expressed desire that those Somalis who are not employed should be asked to go elsewhere cannot be complied with. They can be deported to their homeland but in that case the question arises as to who will pay for their passage. &gt;^P. A'. &lt;. cluINDIA OFFICE LIBRARY and RECORDS Photocopying record REFER.TO THE SPECIALIST CONCERNED</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000145_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1590</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000145</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1590</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘16/81 Re: Somalis Arrived in Bahrain’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-18T23:04:50</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (31 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 27-31) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 33; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-18; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Papers relating to twenty Somalis who arrived in Bahrain from Qatar in February 1949, claiming to be survivors of a shipwrecking off the coast of Muscat. The papers include:an account by the survivors of their shipwrecking and journey to Bahrain (f 5, f 9);correspondence exchanged between the Bahrain Political Agency and Persian Gulf Political Residency concerning the provision of maintenance for the Somalis, and possible repatriation to British Somaliland [Somalia];correspondence between the Political Agent at Bahrain (Cornelius James Pelly) and the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain (Charles Dalrymple Belgrave) on the increasing numbers of Somalis in Manama, and speculation that the Somalis who arrived in Bahrain had in fact travelled to Qatar to seek work at the oil company in Qatar (Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited);papers exchanged between the Bahrain Political Agency and the Secretariat of Hargeisa [Hargeysa] in the Somaliland Protectorate, for a passport application submitted by a Somali. The papers include a bond and affidavit, both bearing British Somaliland stamps (f 21, f 23).Some of the correspondence in the file is in Arabic with English translation.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretariat of Hargeisa</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Qatar</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Deportation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Migrants</topic></subject><subject><topic>Passports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000145#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>