<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003a5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T14:42:14.671Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Bahrain OQITFID^IAL. Dear Alban, As is uaual at the beginning of the New Year Shaikh Hamed has brought up thfe question of the amount which he receives from the oil royalty and the Civil List. About a w^k ago he wrote a letter add reaper to the Senior shaikhs. Shaikhs ] oharamed, Andulla and Sulman, and myself, desiring us to consider the matter of his Privy Purse. The letter was somewhat vague but the gist of it was that as his 0 7 h eb uary 1941. (9 expenditure was go great he was in need of more money from state lands. Shaikh Hamed T s complaint of being short of money, which is an annual event, is one of the most difficult things hich 1 have to deal with. There has been much correspondence about it in the past with the Agency because it has not always been possible for the matter to be arranged without it going beyond this office. 2. The Shaikhs and I had two long meetings an^ then we all went to see Shaikh Hamed and discussed the matter with him. It was decided that 1 should ascertain from you, unofficially, what would be your reaction to an increase of two lakhs being paid to Shaikh Hamed in addition to the oil royalty and Civil List to cover the cost of his entertaining and to increase and give new salaries to some of the fa mily . In the meantime Shaikh Hamed mentioned the matter to you but, as you told me, nothing definite was said. Shaikh Hamed however seems to have understood that you approved of the suggestion of an increase I and on Thursday morning the Shaikhs came to see me and told me that they had heard from Shaikh Hamed that you had approved. They wished then and there to decide who should get extra allowances but 1 told them that you were considering the matter and nothing had been definitely settled. I should be g ateful if you could write to me saying that the matter is under consideration, I feel it is a matter [that will need considerable consideration. *3. Although Bahrain in some ways ressembles an Indian Native State, where I believe it is not customary for the Government of India, normally, tcjassume any direction of the State’s finances, yet here the Ruler accepts the advice of the Government of India in such nattec-'S— - k » The Budget is forwarded to the i^litical Agent every year as well as being published locally and when the oil revenue began to come in y there was a discussion with the Political Agent, Colonel Loch, at which Shaikh Hamed and the Senior Shaikhs and m self were present where it was agreed that one third of the future oil royalty should be paid to the Ruler’s Privy Purse, in addition to the Civil List. It was also agreed that the Civil List should not be increased. This / arrangement has been in force till now and in the beginning Shaikh Kamed was satisfied with the amount which he received. Shaikh Hamed I rxow appears to believe that the arrangement which was made was that | ne should have one third, the family should have the other third and the rest would be spent on the State. The Senior Shaikhs suggest that if he had two more lachs he would not ask for the whole third. A 4. Prom the third of the royalty which he now received Shaikh Hamed pays a number of allowances to members of the family and other persons. Details of these will be sent to you. He also gives money to innumerable Arabs from outside Bahrain, which annoys his own family and the general public. The custom is based on the old idea that if mainland Arabs are given regular payments when an emmergency arfises , such as an attack on Bahrain/these desert'Bedu^will rally to his standard. The Shaikh is not now in need of the doubtful allegiance of^riainland Arabs. The amount which is spent on entertaining guests is a comparatively small sum and when a personage like King Ibn Saoud visits Bahrain much of the cost is born by the State. •5* Shaikh Hamed is a very wealthy Ruler. His necessary expend -iture is small, he lives very simply, he has no expensive tastes but he is easy going and people find it easy to get money from him. Much of his income is spent on buying houses and cars and paying bills for some of his relations and many of his hangers—on. He is stupid ove&gt;■ money and incredibly careless. His household expenditure is in the hands of people who are known to be dishonest and thefts from the safe in his house are frequent. His relations know the state of things in his household and have discussed it with me constantly and though w r e have tried to make changes it has been impossible to improve conditions in his establishment. T he.3 t &gt; © introduction of the Factor, who is paid hy the State, was intended to improve the management of Shaikh Hamed’s money affairs. He does not like the Factor who is only allowed to deal with the town and garden property. 6. During the last four years, on my advice, Shaikh Hamed has invested about £ 90,000. in British War Loan. He has bought much valuable house property in Manama iiicluding G.A.S.O.G. and P.C.L. premises and Mohammed Ali Zainal’s h use and land and various other houses and properties amounting to over Rs 300,000. In some cases ^ ie paid too high prices but in every case he offered more than the price which 1 and his brothers advised. He has also lent to the Kozaibi family Rs 200.000 Qh interest secured by mortgages on all their most valuable property. In four years he has invested in securities, loans and by purchase of property over Rs 17,00,000. It is for this reason that he has sometimes found himself short of cash at the end of the six months before the oil money is paid and because of this he fancies that he is hard up. He never considers the money which he has invested, which brings him in a considerable income, If he had not invested this money he would not now complain of being poor. 1 persuaded him to invest money because I believed it was to his own interest, if I had not done so the present ■^pleasantness would nHixkHXEXsRK have b-en avoided. 7. I am preparing a statement showing Shaikh Hamed f s income and expenditure for the last year which 1 will send to you, it will take a little time to sort out the various headings. The accounts are kept by me and I sign all cheques on his personal account on his written orders but 1 do not always know on what the money is spent. I am postponing the Budget until this matter is settled because a difference of two lakhs will affect it considerably. I anticipate a big decrease in revenue this year owing to 25% less oil revenue in the second half of the year. If an additional two lakhs goes to the Privy Purse 1 do not think it will be possible to add more than 10 ixk lakhs to the Reserve Fund this year. Unfortunately this is not an argument which would appeal to Shaikh Hamed. yours sincerely,■ • INCOME l/3rd Oil Royalty Interest.- On War Loan Bonds On Loan advanced to Messrs. Gosaibi &amp; Co.—V The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to ; His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him -ar-copy--of the undermentioned documents, for information. No :— P/ Dated February 18, 1941. Description of enclosure. Subject.I'lsl i; * ^ ■ '-f. IP r ill \ Q /&lt; The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to : His Britannic Majesty f s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a-€©py~ef th&lt; undermentioned documents. Advisers Office, Manamah, Bahrain. No P/ l ■ Dated February 22, 1941. Description of enclosure.A zl&gt; No. SiS.JSo.fi Bahrain, Dated, March 12, 1941. C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to inform you that I have received the enclosed letter from His Highness Shaikh Hamad. At a discussion which took place this morning at which Shaikhs Mohamed, Abdulla and Salman were present it was decided that I should send a copy of the' letter to you before taking any action in the matter. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the Government EnelTranslation of letter dated 13th Safar, 1360 from His Highness Shaikh Hamad bin Isa Al- Khalifah to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. After Compliments It is not hidden from you that after we met at Sakhir with our brothers Shaikhs Mohamed and Abdulla and our son Shaikh Salman and after fully discussing our opinions the least possible estimate which can be taken as a basis at present is that we should take 2 lakhs from the middle third of the oil royalty and set aside from it 1 lakh for entertainment and the other lakh to make up what is lacking in the A1 Khalifah pay. Your friend is convinced that the great and the small of the family are aversely affected. I am sending this letter to you by the hands of our brothers Shaikhs Mohamed and Abdulla and our son Shaikh Salman and I trust that you will con clude this matter so that all may have rest after this trouble. Usual ending.D.O.No. ff 83 I Bahrain, March 12, 1941. Dear Alban, Herewith figures showing amount paid to Bedu etc. during the last five years. Before 1355 there was no separate account of this expenditure but the sum was very small. Approx: Rs. 1,14,000 1.14.000 1.42.000 1.08.000 30,000 No record maintained. Yours Sincerely, 1359 1358 1357 1356 1355 1354 Major R.G.E.W. Alban, O.B.E., H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain.fi ! v u &amp; The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to : His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for information. Advisers Office, Manamah, Bahrain. No:— p/ ^ £6 //- &lt;2- Dated March 13, 1941. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. EXPENDITURE BY THE FACTOR Reference to previous correspondence:— His Highness’s Accounts. S.Z.The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to : His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a—eepy—of the undermentioned documents. Advisers Office, No P/ 3 4^/1. Manamah, Bahrain. Dated:— March 19, 1941. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. 6 copies in English and 3 copies in Arabic of List showing members of the Khalifah Family who receive Reference to previous correspondence S.Z.List showing members of the Khalifah Family who receive salaries for duties. Name. Duty. Amount. Shaikh Khalifah bin Mohd bin Isa AlKhalifah. ^ Shaikh Ali bin Ahmed AlKhalifah. Shaikh Abdulla bin Hamad AlKhalifah. Shaikh Daij bin Hamad AlKhalifah. Shaikh Rashid bin Mohamed AlKahlifah. Shaikh Mubarak bin Hamad AlKhalifah. Shaikh Ahmed bin Hamad ALKhalifah. Shaikh Mohd bin Ali bin Mohamed. Shaikh Ali bin Khalifah bin Daij. Sup’t of Police. Magistrate, Bahrain Court. Amir of Rafaa. Bapco Employee’s Representative Magistrate, Bahrain Court. Magistrate, Junior Joint Court. Magistrate, Bahrain Junior Court. Presidant, Majlis Tijarah. Supervisor, Sunni Wakf Dep’t. School Master. 400 300 100 50 300 300 315 200 100 100 100 55 50 Rs.2,370© UROKNT 2iat March, 1941* Will you plaaae confirm that th« State RasarTO la invested in Starling, and give the actual amount, and also aa&gt; what amounts have baen invested since the war began* 2, What do the Shaikh 9 s investments amount to and are they in Sterling or Rupee securities* How much has been invested in Sterling securities since the war began* investments be made in other than Rupee securities without consulting me* 0*D.Belgrave Esquire, C*3*3*» Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain* UConfidential. D.0.C/367-2/AL. P- 3 ' Bahrain, March 22 , ' 7^,00 \ Of J C* 9 / &gt; Dear Alban, A 'V' Vs With reference to your letter dated 21st March 1941 on the subject of the State Reserve• The total investment up to date amounts to £500,000. and is in sterling. Of this i/» * &gt; £134,750. was invested since the outbreak of — 1 ■■■ T the war. 2. The Shaikh’s investments are also in sterling and amounts to £90,827.2.10. Of this n £14,814. was invested since the outbreak of war. ' .i 11 —— 3. I shall consult you before making fur ther investments. Yours sincerely, Major R.Gr.E.i. Alban, O.B.E., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. ' sX &gt; Ov^Telegram 7 ram To Repeated S. Political Resident, at Bahrain. Government of India, New Delhi. Secretary of State for India, London. No. T/113. Dated the 23rd March 1941. 1 am having trouble over finance with Shaikh who wishes to help family at expense of State Reserve, i hope to overcome this but have just discovered that whole of reserve shown in rupees in budget is actually in sterling and now amounts to 66^ lakhs. Similarly bulk of Shaikh’s private fortune of 12 lakhs is in sterling loans. Of these sums 18 lakhs and 2 lakhs respectively have been remitted since war broke out. 2. undesirability of reserves incurrency subject to depreciation by exchange is obvious and as they have been built up at our insistence Shaikh would expect us to make good any loss. Moreover in view of possible damage to oil fields they must be readily accessible and not subject to possible restrictions on movements of capital. Since Government of India have repatriated very large sums of capital 1 presume there will be no objection to Bahrain transferring their investments into rupee securities and 1 propose to advise them to do so. 3 # l understand Government of India allow States to invest in certain stocks without deduction of income tax and would be glad of advice in due course as to what securities i should suggest to State. W.L. - Resident. Copy given to Political Agent, BahrainNo. Bahrain, Dated, 4-77- 2 VV/- April 14, 1941. From C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. To His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. SlK, State Reserve. I have the honour to inform you that the Bahrain Government wish to invest a further sum of seven lakhs of rupees to he added to the reserve and to request your advice in the matter. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, (A G'J'*- / Uno. fir- ** '/* Bahrain, Dated, April 14, 1941. From C. Dalryinple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. To His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sik, I have the honour to inform you that His Highness Shaikh Hamad wishes to invest one lakh, Rs.l,00,000/-, of his personal income. I have informed him that investment in rupee currency, not sterling, is recommended and he wishes me to obtain your advice as to where the money would be best invested, taking into consideration the question of income tax. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the GovernmentConfidential No C/336-4/1. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) and to request instructions as to the reply to be given. The agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated ' the 17th April Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. x 1. Letter No.577-2V*L dated April 14, 1941 from the' Adviser to the Bahrain Government to the Political Agent, Bahrain. State Reserve. 2. Letter N0.578-SE 1/2 dated April 14, 1941 from Adviser to the Bahrain Government to the Political Agent, Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. i No. 1360 Office of the Mviser to the Government. Bahrain. Dated, R/Awal 20, 1360 ipril 17, 1941. C« Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C«B«Ee, Mviser to tne Grovernmeiit of Bahrain, Bahrain o I have the honour to refer to the conversation which I had recently with the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Colonel 0* Go Prior, on the subject of the Reserve Fund of the Bahrain Stateo This fund, with the approval of His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa Alkhalifah, has, from the beginning, been invested in British Government securities, War Loan and Government of India stock. His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad f s own investments amounting to £90,827• &amp; also in 3tjb War Loan. These invest ments in the past have been made with the knowledge of His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political xigents in Bahrain and have been referred to in annual reports and in quarterly financial returns. I would not assume the responsibility of investing over half a million pounds sterling belonging to the state and its Ruler without first obtaining the opinion of the Political Agent as to in what loans it should be invested. From To His Britannic Majesty’s Political ^igent Bahrain. t- 2 - Colonel Prior was unaware that the Reserve Fund was invested in sterling stock and he very strongly recommended that it should be withdrawn and transferred into rupee investments* He was of the opinion that the money could not easily be converted from sterling into rupees* I enclose a copy of a letter from the Manager of the Eastern Bank in Bahrain, from which it appears that this transfer is possible* 3o The government holds £450,000 in War Loan and £50,000* in Government of India stock* The former was quoted in London on 6th April as standing at 104£* If it was sold at this price it would realise approximately £468,000* I do not know at what price the Indian loan is standing at present but assuming that it is at par the total investment if realised would produce £518,000* This converted into rupees is approximately Rs. 69,04,940/-* The original cost of the whole stock was Rs 66,50,864/-, the difference would be approximately Rs 2,54,000/-* This, in itself, appears to be a profitable transaction* 4* I have examined lists of Government of India gilt edged securities and there does not at present appear to be any investment which would give as good a yield, free of income tax, as the present investment* I do not know the position of the Bahrain state regard ing liability for income tax or investments in India* Colonel Prior mentioned certain Government of India stock which might be obtained without liability of income tax in which the funds of some of the Indian states are invested* I should be obliged if you could obtain the advice of the Government of India about this stock* The state wishes to invest a further 7 lakhs now —3—-3- lakhs now and His Highness wishes to invest 1 lakh so I should be obliged if advice could be given as soon as possible« 5« With regard to the half million sterling invested in London, the Bahrain government can instruct its bankers immediately by cable to sell all or part of the investments and to transfer the capital to India but before doing so I should like to be assured that it is the opinion of the Government of India that this step is to the financial advantage of the state I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant Mviser to the Government« r—Copy of a letter dated 17th. April 1941 from the Manager, Eastern Bank, Limited, Bahrain, addressed to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrauu (Private and Confidential). Dear Sir, With reference to your personal letter DoO© No* 496 of the 5th of April to the undersigned, we give below a copy of a telegram dated the 15th of April we have received from our London Office in reply to your enquiry regarding the sale of both the government f s and His Highness T s Sterling Securities* n Yours 6th no official restriction here on transactions mentioned stop Bahrain govern ment holdings in our name we r could effect immediate sale stop Shaikh Hamad stock his name cannot sell till arrival transfer deeds we forward blank deeds todays mail”• Yours faithfully, Sd/ M* Gunn. Manager*Confidential yj . No. C/341 - 4/1 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) j . t ,/ / The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 19th _ Apr 11 1941 _ / Reference to previous correspondence: // , / In continuation of Bahrain P.L. No. C/336 dated the 17th April 1941 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. L Subject. Letter No. 604-2.W.L. dated the 17th April 1941 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. State Reserve - Bahrain Finances.p s JM0.185-S of 1941# British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 10th April} 1941. / \ i To T r The Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject ? Bahrain Finances. •w Memorandum . Enclosed are two letters to the Shaikh of Bahrain, Nos.l83-S and 184-S of todays date. Could you kindly have the Arabic version filled in before forwarding them to His Highness^ 2# Copies of both for your records and a copy of No.l83-S for the Adviser, Bahrain Government, are included, also an additional copy of each letter which may please be returned after the Arabic version has been entered thereon.CONFIDENTIAL. 7 No. 187-S Of 1941. 1 -^ \ &amp; b%)l The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Secretary to the Government of India, internal Affaire Department, Hew Delhi, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). Dated...lO.to.Aprl.l. .I94.lv Reference to previous correspondence: » Political Resident's telegram flo»T/li3 of 23rd March 194l. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Translation of letter dated 13th Safar,1360, from the Shaikh of Bahrain to the Adviser to the Bahrain , Government # /x 2. Letter No.l83-S of 10th April 1941 to the Shaikh of Bahrain, with enclosure • Bahrain Finances • Copy forwarded, with co Political Agent, mpliments, to the 'Bahrain* / ^ j l^/^\Translation of letter dated 13th Safar t 1360* from His Highness Shaikh Hamad bin Isa a! Khalifah to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. After Compliments, It is not hidden from you that after we met at S&amp;khir with our brothers Shaikhs Mohamed and Abdulla and our son Shaikh Salman and after fully discussing our opinions the least possible estimate which can be taken as a basis at present is that we should take 2 lakhs from the middle third of the oil royalty and set aside from it 1 lakh for entertainment and the other lakh to make up what is lacking in the a! Khalifah pay. lour friend is convinced that the great and the small of the family are adversely affected. 1 am sending this letter to you by the hands of our brothers Shaikhs Mohamed and Abdulla and our son Shaikh Salman and I trust that you wiil conclude this matter so that all may have rest after this trouble. Usual Ending.Confidential No* C/o4j — 1 Political Agency, Bahrain, 2ist April 1941. To The Adviser to the Bahrein Government, ' BAHRAIN Memorandum I am sending herewith e cover addressed to His Highness the Shaikh of Behrain, containing two letters from the Honourable the Political Resident. I should be grateful if you would kindly forward this to his highness. 2. I enclose also a copy for your records of letter No. Ibb-S dated the 10th April i941 which the Honourable the Political Resident has written to His Highness. L. Political Agent, BahrainNo. C/L50 - 4/1 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:—. The Honoyreble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, V and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated—,2.1st Apr il. 194 1._ Reference to previous correspondence:, p * ^ Resident’s memorandum No. 18b-S dated the 10th Kpril 1941 Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^ fv . Letters No. Ittl-S and No. 184-S dated the 10th A^ril 1941, with Arabic versions rilled in. Bahrain FinancesTelegram From Q. Political Hesident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 295 Dated and received the 25th April 1941. Your Printed letter No.C/341 dated April 19th 1941. Do your records show any reference to Resi dency before investments were made ?From Political £gent, Bahrairw To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 95 Dated the 28th April 1941. X Your telegram No.295 According to our records, no specific reference has ever been made to Political Resident before invest ment. General mention of amounts already invested or proposed to be invested has been made in budgets and statements for past years forwarded to Political Resident. PoliticalConfidential No .0/381-4/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 28th Apri&amp; 1941. To The Adviser to the Bahrain Oovern/nent, v Bahrain. Memorandum Reference my memorandum No. C/349 dated the 21st April 1941 forwarding two letters for His Highness from the Hon'ble the Political Resident. 2. Would you kindly let me know if there is any reply; I shall be glad to forward it to Bushire. L. Political Agent, BahrainD.C. No. 678/2WL. Bahrain, April 29, 1941. Dear Alhan, In my last three annual reports, for 1356, 135^7 and 1358, the fact that the Reserve Fund is invested in sterling is shown on the follow ing pages.— 1356 - page 47 1357 - ' 4 &amp; 6 1358 - ' 11,66 &amp; 68. Yours sincerely, Major R.G.E.W. Alban, O.B.E., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidentail I % No. 7*t - w of 1360 Office of the Adviser to the Government , Bahrai n Dated, 4th R/Thani, 1360 April 30, 1941. \ His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: - Reference your memorandum No. C/381-4/1 dated 28th April, 1941. I spoke to His Highness about the matter today and an answer will be sent shortly. He wishes to discuss the matter with the senior Shaikhs before replying. Adviser to the Government. S.Z.Uoni iden txa-i ^ w-t- I- R D.O«lAo.27t&gt;-b. /a “ The Hesidency, / i^ushire, the 1st May 1941. Dear AlDan, L the Government /-&gt; A' t . A x enclose a copy of a telegram irom of india in reply to my telegram wo. 27b of the 18th April 1941* of which copy is also enclosed* \ 2# The simplest course appears for the shaikh's own oalance to De invested with that of the State, as by this means he will escape paying income tax and his heirs will avoid any difficulty over succession or estate duty* if this proposal does not commend itself to the hahrain Govern ment then i will apply for permission for him to purchase notes m the special form governed by paragraph 03^2) of the Government securities Manual 1921# 3* Please let me know if my assistance is required; otherwise it would appear in order for helgrave to deal direct with the secretary of the Keserve hank of mdia. fours sincerely.I Telegram &lt;** From (iovemment oT xndiaf bimla. To Political rtesident, uushire. wo. C. Dated 26tii received Z'ftn April 1941. lour telegram 27t&gt; April 1.8th. investment of Bahrain rupee Dalance. All investment oy bahram uovernraent m v/overn- ment of *ndia loans will oe exempt irom income tax. btate may thei*ei ore invest its rupee Dalance oy purchasing securities of any government of xndia loan m market or Dy Secretary of deserve dank of india should be consulted direct it amount to De invested is large as dank may be able to make arrangements that win avoid rise m prices owing to possibility of market being short of particular loans desired# position has been explained to deserve dank of india. direct subscription to current 3^ Defence Loan 1949-t&gt;2. - FORiJJKiK - ITelegram '‘Q,' © j&gt;’row To political rtesident, uushire* uoveminent of xndia, new Uelhi no, ^7o L)ated Idtn April 1941* Last instalment of royalties leaves .Bahrain Government with large rupee balance which they wish to invest m uovernment of India loan, Glad if you would Kindly indicate loan in which States are allowed to invest money without payment of income tax. - BiUTCUWSUL\ © Confidential No. C/409-4/1, Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th May 1941. To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. State Reserve Memorandum Reference ybur letter No.577-2WL and 578-SE 1/2 dated the 14th April 1941. 2. All investment by the Bahrain Government in Government of India loans will be exempt from income tax. It is therefore recommended that the State in vests its rupee balance by purchasing securities of any Government of India loan in market or by direct subscrip tion to current 3% Defence Loan 1949 - 52. The Secretary of the Reserve Bank of India, to whom position has been explained, should be consulted direct if amaunti iiwubLud 1U IflPgg as Bank may be able to make arrangements that will avoid rise in prices owing to the possibility of the market being short of particular loans desired. 3. As regards investments by His Highness, the simplest course would appear to be for the Shaikh’s own balance to be invested with that of the State, as by this means he will escape paying income tax and his heirs will avoid any difficulty over succession or estate duty. If however this proposal does not commend itself to the Bahrain Government /.- 2 - Government, then the Hon 1 hie the Political Kesident is prepared to apply for permission for the Shaikh to purchase notes in the special form governed by paragraph 53 ( 2 ) of the Government Securities Manual 1921• 4* Would you kindly let me know if any assistance is required 5 otherwise it would be in order for you to deal direct with the Secretary of the Reserve Bank of India. Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential The D. 0. No. C/418-4/1 © 'A Political Agency, Bahrain, the 7th May 1941. Dear Colonel, \ u &lt; Your telegram No. 274 dated the 18th April 1941. 2. As requested in your memorandum No. 186-S dated , the 10th April 1941, your two letters Nos. 183-S and 184-S were translated and sent to His Highness. / U 3. His Highness has now replied and I enclose his letter together with a translation. I also enclose a copy of Belgrave* s note to me on the reactions of the Shaikhs. One of the things that has stung them (and Belgrave) is that a merchant should have had the temerity to voice a criticism l I may say here that during the last few years the policy has been to allow the A1 Khalifah to keep on increasing their ascendancy over the public and to deprive the latter of any means of voicing grievances either to the Adviser or to the very Political Agent. Belgrave is/inaccessible to the public, complaints against the administration are not allowed and, even to this day, visitors to the Agency are strongly discouraged in various ways such as being called 'Agency spies' etc. It is not therefore surprising that the Shaikhs and Belgrave have had somewhat of a shock. 4. At the Joint Court this morning Shaikh Hamad spoke to me on the subject. He said he was much upset at the suggestion contained in your letter No. 184-S that/- Hon'ble Lleut-Colonel C. G. Prior, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.that he had given the donations to the Fighter Fund in order to ask for more money. He said that he and his family were ready at all times to give all the help within their power to the British Government and that his request for Increased allowances was only made in view of the rise in the coat of living since the war which had hit those members of the family who get the smaller allowances. 5. I replied that the Political Resident had the welfare of the State at heart and that he certainly would nod' wish to accept any subscriptions from the Shaikhs if this meant that they would ask for Increased allowances afterwards. 6. We have, however, the Shaikh's assurance that he will not for the duration of the war, at any rate. Reserve oil make any inroads on the •Jrd^revenue. Yours sincerely,©Y Translation of letter dated the 8th Habi-ul-Thani 1360 (4th May 1941) from His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ^ * After Compliments. I was honoured by the receipt of your two letters Nos. 183 and 184 dated the 10th April 1941 and read all that you wrote in connection with my letter to Mr. Belgrave about the Bahrain revenues and the arrangements necessary for this year. Your Honour, I appreciate your valuable advice and the sorrow you expressed for past years when the revenues were small and insufficient to meet the expenditure and your pleasure when conditions improved. The reason for my wishing to increase the allowances of my family, the A1 Khallfah, is the apparent increase in prices of all things. There are also certain individuals of the family for whom no allowances have been made and others whose allowances are small but I agree that we shopld not touch the ^rd reserve under the present difficult circumstances. I thank you for telling the merchant who told you about something which does not concern him that you do not cafe to hear such things. We shall try as much as possible to order our expenses in a proper manner. I repeat my thanks to Your Honour for your good intentions towards my country and myself. Usual EndingConfidential 6 th May 1941. Dear Alban, The Shaikhs were very upset by Prior’s letter. It was not so much the fact that he did not approve of H.H’s suggestion - I have told them both before the matter became official and afterwards that I was sure he would not approve - but the style of the letters hurt them. Shaikh Salman has aken it most to heart. They think that some of the remarks in the letter originated from criticisms of the Shaikhs made by Yusuf Kanoo, Khalil Moayad and one or two others who, they think, hope to profit by making trouble between the Shaikhs and the Agency. I think Y.K. has been making some rather silly remarks which were repeated to the Shaikhs. They don’t agree with all the figures of H.H’s expenditure saying that the amount spent on Bedu etc. includes some other items sent the figures to you there should have been a discussion you had asked for details and that I was sending them but I did not discuss the figures with the other three Shaikhs. The letters have been seen by some of the sons and H.H. himself shows great reluctance to discuss it, he wrote the replies without consulting anyone, in fact I have not seen his answers. and I think the three senior Shaikhs feel that before I about the amounts with them. As you know I told H.H. that a number of the servants and hangers on at Sakhir. Sd/-C• Dalrymple Belgrave Major H.G.E.W. Alban, O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to : His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents. ^or information. Advisers Office, No:— Manamah, Bahrain. Dated May 12, 1941 . Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. Letter No. 784/WL dated May 10, 1941 addressed to The Secretary, The Reserve Bank of India, Bombay. State Reserve, Reference to previous correspondenceNo. 784/ttL. Bahrain, Bated, May 10 # 1941. From C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. To The Secretary, The Reserve Bank of India, Bombay* Sib, The Government of Bahrain has a Reserve Fund amounting to approximately £590,000. sterling now invested in 3i$ War Loan and about ite 7,00,000/- in the Eastern Bank, Limited, Bahrain. The govern ment of India have recommended that the Reserve Fund should be transferred from England and invested in Government of India securities. 2. I am informed by His Britannic Majesty’s Political agent in Bahrain that all investments by the Bahrain government in Government of India loans will be exempt from income tax. 3. The Bahrain government would like to invest the whole amount in Government of India securities which will produce a yield of as near as possible 3i$. I understand that there is a 3# loan 1963 - 65 now standing at about 94i. This appears to be the most suitable investment. 4. I should be very grateful if you would advise me whether you could make arrangements for this — V\— - ^Lllli '■■I'l.. this investment, possibly by aegrees, in such a way that a rise in prices could be avoided owing to the market being short of the particular loan which is required. I am informed that the position has been explained to you and I should be much obliged for your advice in the matter. Yours faithfully, cc.Pa 9 £B«Confidential The Residency, Bushire, the 21st May, 1941 D.O«No.328-S. Dear Alban, 0 li Please refer to your demi-official letter Ho.C/418- 4/1, dated the 7th May 1941, regarding Bahrain finances. 2. I enclose a reply for the Shaikh complimenting him upon his sagacious move and hope that you will have no further difficulty now. I intervened in the matter myself so as to save you the unpleasantness of coming into conflict with the Ruling Family at the outset of your time as Political regent, but these matters are normally your pigeon, and 1 now return the ball to you. 3. As regards the hurt feelings, 1 may say that I have a very long experience of financial arguments with the al Khalifah and 1 have never yet seen money kept away from them v/ithout some “misunderstandings rt or hurt feelings arising somewhere. Once, when money was far scarcer than it is now and I complained that though the al Khalifah kept on increasing the Civil List could not be expected to keep pace. Shaikh Muhammad bin Isa claimed that I had advocated birth control which was contrary to the Holy Quran 1 4. 1941 to Shaikh Hamad, saying that I do not wish to receive contributions from the al Khalifah to the irersian Gulf Fight Fund, you will see that the reference was to the al Khalifah (who have so far not contributed a single cent) and not to His Highness. Would you kindly make this clear to him and / say - 4 If you refer to my letter Ho.l84-S of 10th April Major R.G.Alban, O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain• c &lt;7/no intention say that I had, of course, no intention of reflecting on his generosity which has been most marked and for which we are very grateful indeed. lours ^sincerely,Confidential. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 21st May 1941. To The Political Agent, Bahrain (v (t- * &gt; u \ Meiporanduiia . Please have the Arabic version filled in before forwarding letter !To«329-S, dated the 21st May 1941, to the Shaikh. Copy is enclosed for your record, also a second copy which may please be returned with the Arabic version. By Order. /J '•hr f for Secretary t*o the political Kesident . in the Persian Gulf. 4l_ v n J JL-aJI ^UJU-X •Mil t l ^ (g) . Ho»329.d of 1941* British Residency It Jonsulate«»General t Bush re f the 21st Msy, 1941* (.^1^ juiH lr^“ 0-( J“ ^.1 ij* **A*’ ^ f./^'cXj^r* 1 j (t-ite •»-*&lt; J -»* - kt • a £, yji •^r* u'-T'***' ^ jl» f 3*“JJp'**' *«&gt;'*' • J’illL.W-Jl u- il,jjl « jjk ^1* f**\) J-IH) ^^5J' J-*' IJ? 1 ** 11 *^ 1 ' Ji^j\ \±r &amp;3 ' W 0 &gt; kM— Jl A ^ &gt; jj 'j-* (^iy- 3 -. fr~ &lt;j ^ JJSU1I •w^» jj-jUJI 1^**J (^LKu^grJ'r^ To His Highness Shaikh Sir TTaroad bin Isa a. 1 Khalifah # K«C«I*H»«gG«B«I Ruler of Bahrain• After CooplimentSt A \ } Vx V Z wish to refer to Your Highness* letter dated the 6th iiabl«&gt;uJUihani 1360 on the subject of the Bahrain revenues* I an very glad that Your Hlghneee has decided not to touch the one-third now allotted to the Reserve and oongratul. ate you upon this wise and far-seeing step. It is most inportant to think of the future* and I an sure Your Highness is acting in the best Interests of Bahrain by doing so* as regards certain Individuals of the Tanlly for whoa no allowances have been Bade and for those whose allowances are snail* it **111 be possible to provide for them within the Units of the one-third now enjoyed by Your Highness* With sincere wishes to Your High* ness and assurances of my deep and perman ent interest in Bahrain* X remain* Your sincere friend* sd. C.G.Prior. political Resident in the Persian Gulf*CONFIDENTIAL. No. o57-3 of 1941. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment ($). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated... 2.5th. Uay. 1.94 1 r. tj Reference to previous correspondence 'f. Residency ^.0* let ter ho. &lt;i7b-3 dated 1/5/41. Description of Enclosure. S Name and Date. Government of India -a.A.l)., 31.0. ho. D.18o9-N/41, dated doth April 1941. Subject. B AKRAIh Hi YESTMEHTS.iix.terna,l Affairs Department, 3 I U L A, Tlie 30 th April 1941. D. 0. N o. _D1 359-M/41 . Bahrain i nvestments* liy dear Prior, \ A In continuation of our telegram Ko. 2b-G, dated the 26th April 1941, I am desired to explain, in case of any misunderstanding, that it is net possible to arrange for exemption from income tax tc extend to investments of tne Shaikh’s privat e funds. Yours sincerely, Sh/- K • W e ightinan To The Honlole Lieutenant Colonel C.G. Prior, , Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. :Confidential No. C/564 Political A S ent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:- The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) 3th JUne 19 41 Reference to previous correspondence: Q ^ (£ Resident's memorandum No. 330-S dated the 21st May 1941 Description of Enclosure.&gt;&gt; ' From Mo. of 1360 Office or the Adviser to the Government. Bahrain* Dated. R/Awal 1360 April 17, 1941. TL\ The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. To His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to forward for your information a copy of the budget for the Bahrain State for the year 1360. It was not sent before because it has only now been approved and signed by His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa Alkhelifah who, in a covering letter has stipulated that an adjustment in the budget may perhaps be made by devoting a portion of the surplus, which it was proposed to add to the Reserve Fund, to the Civil List in order to relieve the want caused by the general rise in the cost of living among members of the ruling family. 2. Revenue has been estimated on a conservative basis. The estimated revenue is 10 lakhs less than the amount estimated in the 1359 budget and 13 lakhs less than the actual revenue- of that year. In 1359 there were two abnormal receipts, 4 lakhs was paid by the Bahrain Petroleum Company on the signing of the new oiloil concession and Rs. 1,69,000/- was received from the price of rice which was sold by the state to local merchants* Oil royalty is estimated at 25i lakhs. This payment is made twice yearly, the amount due for the first payment is known and the second instalment has been estimated at 25$ less than the first instal ment. I consider that it would be unwise to assume a larger revenue from oil owing to the unsettled con ditions and the lack of tanker transport* Customs revenue has been estimated at approximately 2 lakhs less than in 1359. This is a conservative estimate but the reduction of the activities of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company, increased import trade through Kuwait and the amount of unemployment in Bahrain affect the volume of the import trade in Bahrain. Other sources of revenue do not differ greatly from last year* 3* On the expenditure side the Civil List and one third of the oil royalty which is paid to the Ruler amount to Rs. 12,90,000/-. This figure is liable to vary according to the amount of the oil royalty. The cost of administration is approximately the same as in last year’s budget. 4. Expenditure on public health is higher than last year. It includes special anti-malaria work, quarantine services and provision for the hospitals working at full capacity throughout the year. In 1359 the hospitals were only in use during part of the year. 5. Public Protection includes the State Police at full strength, the natur force and the new Special Police force which did not exist in 1359. The Special Police are provided with uniform and rations. When the defence scheme was inaugurated the duties now carried out by the«w^ai -3- the Special Police were undertaken by nature who were not given rations or uniform, 6, Other recurrent expenditure on Education, Municipalities etc. does not differ to any extent from last year. A surplus of Rs. 6,09,000/- is anticipated which will be added to the Reserve Fund together with part of the surplus balance from 1359. 7, Most of the non-recurrent expenditure on public works consists of completion of works already as in hand such/the surgery building in the hospital, the Manamah-Muharraq bridge and the new Technical School, Provision has been made for new married police quarters at the Fort and for making permanent the new drain from south east of Manamah to the sea. The building occupied by the customs clerks, behind the post office is in a dilapidated condition and it is proposed that the ground floor should be converted into shops and quarters built on the first floor. 8, At present the bulk of the state ! s revenue is from the oil royalty which is likely to decrease and eventually cease. It will be seen from the budget that revenue from oil is estimated at 25i lakhs and other revenue at approximately 10 lakhs. Since the oil royalty began to come in it has been the object of the state to build up a reserve which will provide an income in the future that will compensate for the future diminishing oil royalty. In this year T s budget the normal recurrent expenditure, deducting the third of the oil revenue, the contribution to the Reserve Fund, special public works and allowing 2 lakhs only for publicpublic protection which might be considered adequate under normal peace time conditions, amounts to approxi mately 15i lakhs* The expenditure has been estimated on a liberal basis. Accordingly it would appear that the state needs a further assured income of 5i lakhs before it can look forward to permanent financial security and the ability to carry on the administration on the present scale when oil revenue begins to fail. I have the honour to be, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the GovernmentHospitals:- BUDGET - ln3 6 0 Public Works Dep^ . Surgery Block. 50,000 Mortuary. 2,500 Kitchen. 1,500 Garage. 1,000 Store. 1,000 Servants Quarters. 4 3,000 Incinerator. 500 Isolation Hospital (Septic Tank). 1,000 60,500 Police married Quarters. 30,000 Prison Gate House. 1,500 Police Station (Dormitory) 1,000 32,500 &gt;e:- Construction. 2 ,15,000 Raising level and building room on side. 10,000 2,25,000 Technical School Completion of Main Building, Anti-Malaria:- Construction sides to new water channel and making channel from Wireless Pool. Rebuilding Customs Staff Quarters. Parapet on Moharraq Sea Road. Land Department Additional Office. Special Repairs to H.H. Palace. Cow Sheds west of Fort. Budayya Garden. Latrines for Government Office Staff Gozaibia Banglow Fencing Maintenance Roads. Rs.11,000. Annual Repairs tch Gov’t Bigs. 9,000 . 10,000 14.000 15.000 3.000 1,500 2.000 750 1,000 250 800 20.000 Rs.3,86,300No. 7/V- - 2* Bahrain, Dated, 3rd May, 1941. From C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. To His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sm, With reference to my letter No. 619-21 dated 17th April, 1941, forwarding therewith the budget for year 1360, I forward herewith five copies of the summary and detailed statement of the revenue and expenditure of the State for the Arabic year 1359. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, EnelGOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. Bahrain, May 5, 1941. Dear Alban, Ref. your note dated 1st May about 'notes on actual revenue and expenditure for 1359”. 1 enclose herewith five copies of the notes. Yours sincerely, Major R. G. E. W. Alban, O.B.E., H.fi.M ! s Political Agent, Bahrain.Revenue 1359. The estimated revenue in the Budget for 1359 was Rs 45,07,000/-. The actual revenue collected was Rs 49,01,499/-. The actual revenue exceeded the anticipated amount by Rs 3,94,449/-. The actual revenue in 1358 was Rs 45,78,765/-. Revenue in 1359 exceeded that of 1358 by Rs 3,22,734/-© The 1359 receipts however included two abnormal items amounting to Rs 5,61,972/- being the payment made by the Bahrain Petroleum Company on signing the oil con cession over the additional area and the price obtained by the government from the sale of rice which had been bought in 1358 as a special war measure. If these two items of abnormal revenue are not taken into con sideration the revenue in 1359 was Rs 43,39,527/- which is Rs 2,39,238/- less than the revenue during the previous year. Customs revenue was approximately Is lakhs lower, oil royalty was approximately Rs 83,000/- less and there was a decrease of approximately Rs 48,000/- in land revenue. This last item in 1358 included some abnormal receipts. Other sources of revenue produced slightly less than in the previous year. During the year Rs 16,52,745/- was added to the Reserve Fund and invested in War Loan.Expenditure 1359. The total expenditure during the year was Rs 29,14,372/- excluding the amount paid into the Reserve Fund. Approximately one half of the total expenditure was paid to the Ruling Family in the Civil List and one third of the oil revenue. The amount spent on special public works, mostly of a non recurrent nature was Rs 3,18,000/-. This was about three lakhs less than the budgeted amount owing to the non completion of the Manamah-Muharraq bridge. The cost of administration which includes the various government offices, courts, education, medical services, municipalities and recurrent public works was approximately 7 lakhs. Unforseen expenditure, Rs 46,000/-, includes the cost of bazaar property amounting to Rs 39,000/- which was purchased by the government when sold by a Persian subject. Total expenditure in 1358 was Rs 36,75,434/- and in 1359 it was Rs 29,14,372/-. The expenditure in 1359 was approximately Rs 7,61,000/- less than during the previous year. In 1358 a contribution of Rs 4,0Q,0Q0/- was given to the British govern ment towards the cost of the war and Rs 1,36,000/- was spent on purchasing rice; excluding these sums the normal expenditure in 1358 was approximately Rs 31,39,000/- and the 1359 expendi ture was about 2± lakhs less than during the previous year. Special Public Works. The expenditure was 3 lakhs less than the amount anticipated in the budget for 1359; in this budget provision was made for Rs 6,21,000/- to be spent on special public works whereas the actual expenditure was Rs 3,18,000/-. The chief expenditure on special new works during the year was on the Manamah-Muharraq bridge and the government hospital. The bridge was expected to have been finished during the year but owing to the war it is not yet complete. The entire super structure and machinery for opening the bridge was ready for shipment from England many months before the end of the year but- Sh owing to transport difficulties it failed to arrive* Three piers and the reinforced concrete dolphin were completed and much of the reinforced concrete extension was built® The piles and about 30^ of the deck of the dolphin were finished during the year® It is estimated that it will take about five months from the date of arrival of the material to complete the whole work® Local labour was used in the construction work under the supervision of British foremen® iirab divers were specially useful in fixing the central submarine ✓ The women 1 s hospital was completed and opened on May 25, 1940 (Rabi althany 18, 1359) and the men’s hospital was brought into use some months later® The ground floor walls of the administrative building were built and the hospital, kitchen, male nurses’ quarters, walls, gates and mess room were completed during the year* The administrative building will contain two operating theatres, X-Ray rooms, stores, laboratory and offices* The two hospitals have a combined capa city of 100 beds but in case of emergency a considerably larger number of patients could be accommociated* The expenditure during the year on the women’s hospital was Rs 15,600/- and on the men’s hospital Rs 49,000/-* The expenditure on the administrative building, staff quarters, kitchens etc. was Rs 32,800/-® The total cost of the men’s hospital including electric, water and sanitary installations amounted to approximatelyRs 1,32,000/-* The nurses’ quarters and the Lady Medical Officer’s flat and Matron’s flat cost approximately Rs 86,000/-. Approximately Rs 16,500/- was spent on the man amah Fort. hll the outer walls and the four corner towers have now been rebuilt® The north east tower containsa large office on the first floor and a store on the ground floor, this and the eastern wall and the north eastern tower were built during the year. Additional latrines were made and the inside garden was fenced. Work was commenced, but not completed, on the new Technical School workshop. The building, which is 120 f x 40 f is adjacent to the existing Technical School and its dimensions are according to the recommendations of Mr. G*. E. Hutchings, Principal of the Baghdad Tech- nical School, who visited Bahrain in order to advise the Government on technical education. The roof is carried on reinforced concrete beams supported by rein forced concrete pillars. Owing to the price of steel beams and the difficulty of obtaining them this method of construction was adopted for the first time in Bahrain. The old building together with the new workshop will provide accommodation for about 100 boys. The amount spent on this building was Rs 13,000/-. Some improvements were made to the customs premises during the year including an office at the entrance to the pier and trolley lines and lighting on the pier extension. The cost of this was approximately Rs 10,000/-. Other work included additional government garages, additional class rooms in the Manamah school, an exten sion to the Haim dispensary, enlarging the jail at Jida, building stables for the government cattle, building a coffee shop and a bathing shelter at Adari and the upkeep and repairs of government buildings, roads and bridges.D.O. No. 928/SF. Bahrain, May 29, 1941 Dear Alban, I am sorry that my note on the revenue and expenditure for 1359 was not clear, a figure was left out which makes it confusing. I enclose a revised statement which compares estimates and actuals of this year and last year in a way that can be more easily followed. The figure of Rs 70,000/- was arrived at as follows Actual revenue 1359 - h 49,01,499 ' 1358 45,78,765 Excess in 1359 over o oo 1358 • * Actual excess over 1359 estimates Hs 3,94,449 Less n 1358 ' 3,22,734 71,715/- On the expenditure side there is a mistake in the figures which I made myself. I have redrafted the note and included the rice item which should I think be mentioned in both years. 1 should be grateful if you/-would replace the first two pages A' - of my 'notes' with the enclosed. I am very glad that you spotted the mistake. Yours sincerely, Major R.G-.E.W. nlban, O.B.E., H.S.M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. -Confidential No. C/591 Political Agency, Bahrein, the 12th June 1941. From Ms,)or P. .G.i’j.'A. Alhan, O.P«E., Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Buahire Sir, I have the honour to forward herewith the following papers *- J C) £ (1) A comparative statement showing receipts and expenditure for the years 1358 and 1359 and the budget estimate for the year 1360. ( &gt; (2) Final figures of Revenue and Expenditure of the Bahrain State for the year 1359, together with a summary exhi biting details of the State Reserve. C T ^ (3) Notes by the Adviser on Revenue and Expenditure for (4) Revenue ^nd Expenditure Budget figures for the year 1360, together with a schedule of public works. (5) Notes by the Adviser on expected Revenue and Expenditure. 2. Re ceipts During the year 1359 receipts dropped, by Rs 3,22,734; this was due mainly to drops of Rs 1,55,888 in Customs receipts and Rs 82,843 in Royalty on oil, due to some shortage of tankers as a result of the war. The drop in Customs revenue is the beginning of a decline due to the reduction in activities of the Oil Companies and the poverty and uriemployment prevailing in the Island. These in fluences are continuing in an aggravated form during the current year and the Adviser has rightly allowed for a further drop of about Rs 2 lakhs in Customs revenue and about Rs 6 lakhs in Royalty• 3. Expenditure the same year. Expenditure in 1358 was fc 36,75,434 and in 1359 it amounted to Rs 29,14,372. Deducting the Shaikh’s gift of2 - f\C Rs* 4 lakhs towards the cost of the War, the net reduction in expenditure was Rs 3,61,062. Of this the most important item was a decrease of Rs 3 lakhs in Public Works expenditure due to the non-completion of the Manama - Muharraq bridge. For the current year it is estimated that expenditure v/ill amount to Rs 29,65,000, but there is likely to be an increase under the head 'Experimental Farms' (which might be replaced by the more usual head 'Agriculture'), on the arrival of the Agricul be necessary to form a small department in order to enable him to function at all. If the new Principal of the Technical College arrives a further increase under the head 'Education' will result. The most outstanding point is that the Ruling family is likely to take a reduction in income of about Rs 2 lakhs in the current year. 4. Investment Surplus would be exceeded and this has proved correct, as it was possible to add a sum of over Rs 16^r lakhs to the Reserve at the end of 1369. The present situation is not favourable for making fore casts but it is possible and even probable that the estimated surplus of fc 6 lakhs for the year 1360 will be exceeded by 2 or 3 lakhs. 5. Submission of the budget has been delayed owing to errors in calculation of figures by the Adviser which necessi tated his rewriting part of the notes. tural Expert from Egypt as, in addition to paying him, it will My predecessor, in his notes on last year*s budget, considered that the estimated sum of Rs 13 lakhs for investment I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant Political Agent, BahrainConfidential D«0« No• C/592 Dated the 14th June 1941. Pleaae refer to your deci-official letter No. 2. I duly handed over your letter referred to in paragraph 2 to Shaikh Hamad and also 9 ae desired In paragraph 4, explained that in your previous letter you had not been referring to him in any way but to the Al Khallfah. Shaikh Hamad said that he quite understood and that he was very grateful for the sentiments you have expressed to him and your care for the welfare of the State. He smiled faintly when 1 explained that it was the Al Khalifah whom you had in mind, who had not contriouted a single proa towards anything and who are the people who always worry His Highness about increasing their allowances. His Highn again thanKod you and asked me to convey his respects to you. The Hobble Lieut-Colonel C.G. Prior| C.X.jS « 9 Political Hesident in the Persian Oulf f Bushire. 328-S dated the 21st Kay 1941 Yours sincerely f u *1^4 Confidential No. '\b^&gt;) ^ r%5? C?593 v/f The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 14 th June 1941 Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Statement of Revenue and Expendi ture at end of R/Awal 1360 (3 months) Subject. Bahrain Finances.u k Confidential No. C/621. q % (\Ck) 'XtJt Political Agency, Bahrain, the 18th June 1941. V. To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, v BAHRAIN f- Memorandum Beference my memorandum No. C/4G9 dated the 6th May 1941. £ (I, -) 2. I am desired to explain, in case of any mis understanding, that it is not possible to arrange for exemption from income tax to extend to investments of the Shaikh*s private funds. Political Agent, Bahrain, /No.C/645-4/1 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain and has the honour to forward herewith copies of the under mentioned documents. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated the 23rd June 1941. Reference to previous correspondence Political Resident 1 s D.O.No. 275-S dated the 1st May 1941. Description of EnclosureCONFIDENTIAL. No - C/22« of 1941. M' The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to !• His Majesty 9 * Secretary of State for India, London* 2* The Political Agent, Bahrain,^ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). Letter Mo*0/225 of 27th June 1941 to the Secretary to the Goyernment of India, External Affairs Department, Simla, with enclosures* To Bahrain only. Government of India letter No.D.2098-N/41,dated 6th June 1941. &lt;0* British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated....$7.^. damp, Bahrain . Reference to previous correspondence : To 1 only* Residency Printed letter Mo*274-S of 1st May 1941* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject.confidential Ho.J/ 225 of 1941• Olfice of the Political Hteident in tho Persian Gulf, Jamp Bahrain Dated the 27th June 1941* in the Persian Gulf From The Hon'ble Lieut^-Golonel J.G.l-rior, a.I # S„ Political Resident in the Persian Gulf To The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla Sir ending with Government of India letter Ho,I).209fc-N/4i, dated the 6th June 1941, regarding the investments of the Bahrain state iteserve* volved, one which is dealt with in the above mentioned letter, namely, the question of the transfer of the Reserves xww^held in sterling to India, and the other, the investment of the balances which have recently accrued and which are held in rupees* 2* The latter question was referred by the iidviser, Bahrain Government, to the Political Agent in his letter No.577-2 W.U, together with his letter Ko*578-bBl/2, both dated the 14th April 1941, copies of which are en- » closed* The matter was referred by me to the Govern ment of India in my telegram No*275, dated the 18th ^pril 1941, and their reply was received in Government of India It will be recalled that two questions were in- then telegram /5 . / telegram No*25 C 9 dated the 26th April 1941# Jopiec of these two telegrams are also enclosed for ready reference* It will be seen that the letters of the Bahrain Government refer only to the investment of rupees and in my telegram to the Government of India and in their reply this transaction was throughout referred to as the investment of the State’s 'rupee balance'* 3« The orders of the Government of India were correctly passed on by the Political Agent to the Adviser in his confidential Memorandum No*C/409-4/i t ' Memorandum Reference your letter No*577-2WL and 578-SS 1/2 dated the 14th April 1941. £• All Investment by the Bahrain Government in Government of India loans will be exempt from in* come tax* It is therefore recommended that the btate invests its rupee balance by purchasing securities of any Government of India loan in market or by direct subscription to current Defence Loan 1949 - 52* The Secretary of the Heserve Bank of India t to whom the position has been explainedf should be consulted direct as Bank may be able to make arrangements that will avoid rise in prices owing to the possibility of the market being short of particular loans desired.' dated the 6th May 1941, which read as follow.,3. Mr, Uelgrave understood this to refer to the •ntire amount of the Reserve Fund including the Reserves held in sterling, and having been informed that the Bank should be consulted direct, he concluded the transactions without further reference to the Agency or this Residency, 1 only laar “t uvon my arrival that the entire Reserve had been brought out from Ragland and haa been re-invest ed in India. It aypeare that Mr.Belgrave consulted the Shaikhs, who approved of the transfer in writing, and that the whole transaction resulted in a net profit of 2 lakhs ot rupees. nhile, therefore, I regret that it is not possible to carry out the orders of the Government of India contained in their letter of the 6th June 1941 , it appears that the transfer was entirely due to a mis understanding which has, however, been profitable to the Bahrain Government. t I am eending a copy of this letter to til* Hie -a-jeety 1 * v^eoretary of Jtate for India and the iolitioal Agent t Bahrain, I have the honour to be, Sir, /our meet obedient servant, ad. CeG. Prior. Political ^ettident in the ieraian Gulf. * under I.L.Ko.J/226 dated 27/6/41Copy 4 AIR MAIL. COHFIDEKTIAL. No.D.2098-N/41 From - The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affaire Department, To - His Majesty’s Under Secretary of State for India, London* Dated Simla, the 6th June 194l. Investments of the Bahrain State Reserve* Sir, v ^ v Resident of which am directed to refer to the letter from the jfolitical in the Persian Gulf No.272-S, dated the 1st May 1941, a copy was sent to you direct, in which the Resident reconmends, in effect, that the Bahrain Government should be advised to transfer their present sterling securities to rupee securities and in future to maintain their reserve solely in rupee currency• £• The Government of India are of opinion that this is a matter in which the final decision as to the advice to be ■jiyen to the Bahrain State must rest with His Majesty s Govern ment, but they believe that it may be useful to place their own opinion on record. 5 In the first place, the Government of India are unable to endorse the Resident’s deduction that the Persian Gull Residency was not informed of the advice given to the Advieei to His Highness the Shaikh to invest the Bahrain balances in British War Loan and Government of Inu^a Stealing Stock. Though the late Resident evidently misnamed these investments in his letter No.C/785, dated the i 5 th October 1938 to the India Office(of which the Government o. have no copy), it is sufficiently obvious that he must have beln aware^of the real nature of the investments. They have no reason to criticize the advice given in 1934, and in their opinion the securities selected are, from the point of ' 1 of the Bahrain State, as sound today as they were then. Th Government of India do not share the Political tl apprehensions about what he considers the probable depreciation of^sterling in terms of the rupee and do not see any reason to believe that the experience of the period immeaiately foil ing the last war will necessarily be repeated aft ®f a t “i® , .. . present one. Nor do they think it axiomatic, as the Political Resident believes, that a State’s reserves can be appropriate- Iv invested only in securities in its own currency. Apart from the fact that in many o ircu ® sta “ oe8 ® xt ® r ^ 1 B n®i^ e8 are held in a currency with international value like s t verv useful, the close connection between sterling and th rupee and the practical interchangeability between the two ^present mLe tt Unnecessary to draw f y distinction between sterling and rupee securities for investment so far as Bahrain is concerned. 4. In the opinion of the Government of India, therefore, there is no reason to advise the State to change its existing u / securitieseecuritiee. As regarde any further euroe that may become available, they may be advised there ie no objection to invest ing them in rupee securities if they so desire on the assumption that the contingency which the reserve is supposed to guard against is a shortfall in revenue, in which case what the State will require will be funds in rupee currency. 5. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Since there must be some interval before the final advice of His Majesty's Government can be communicated, the Political Resident is being instructed to inform the Adviser to the Bahrain Government that the matter has been referred to His Majesty's Government, but that pending the receipt of the views of His Majesty's Government they would strongly deprecate any action to dispose of the State's sterling securities. Copy to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, with the request to proceed as indicated in the concluding paragraph of this letter. A copy of the foregoing paper ie forv/arded to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, with reference to his telegram No.667, dated the 17th June ^941. i have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd.O.K.Caroe, Secretary to the Government of India Deputy Secretary to the Government of India By order, etc., sd. H.Weightman, Air Mail * Confidential NO.D.2737-N/41. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. External Affairs Department. Dated Simla, the 18th June 1941 By order, etc., d. f 0 t Secretary to the Government of India. VCONFIDENTIAL. 3/293 of 1941. \P' fl ' ] \vh The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s).OOHylDBKTIAU Ho.C/292 of 1941. © Office of the lolitical Reeident In the Persian Ciulf, Ganpt Bahrain* Dated the Uth July, l94l* FroEJ • ’fhe Hon’ble ld«ut*-Ceionel C#C*iTior t C*I*S. # Poli tical Reel dent in the 1 ersltja Wulff To • The secretary to the Government of i-ndia# ^xterm*.! Affaire Department, Simla* sir. . V 93 | X have the honour to forward for the information of the Government of Indie a copy of a letter 3*0*0/591# dated the iBth June 1941 # from the Political A^ent, Ihafcrala#(to- gati-.or with ita wualoaurss) which #xp3-Hin« iteelf. . ! V' it will b« bosh iron th« /udvle«r*B lettar .•■.0.619-21 of 15GG, dated the i7tii April 1941, tliat Hie Highneas Shaikh Hamud iifcd contempiated makinti further raids on the public funcis in ord«r to relieve *want* aaon^dt the al Khnllfah* This difficulty hne been met and overflow aiid td.e al halifah * oill content themselves for the oonintf year with the sums provided for in the oudget* 1 have considered at vurioue tUea whether the amount a allotted to this Vamily should not be still further reduced but have come to the conclusion that it is not practicable at present* At the $i*e the present holer agre d to give up two-thirds of the oil oyaltiea retain only one-tnird for himself it wue considered that he was being extremely generous, and public opinion would not auppoxt us in any further attacks on the Vriry Purse* X have sown the seeds fox an eventual reduction of the one-third to one-fifth* but the idea has made little headway ec *ar and / sinceCONFIDENTIAL. C/294 of 1941. \- IL ( 6 eft The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Carol Esquire, CSX « 9 CIE * 9 ICS v9 Secretary to the Goyernment of India 9 External Affaire Departiuent 9 Slntla 9 and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). ✓'I British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated, 11th • July- • 1941* V-' Bahrain. Reference to previous correspondence : Rl/|idency Printed litter No*335-S of 22nd May 1941, v- /\ • ') o Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. j Subject. Uttar No.C/592 of 14th al Bahrain Finance a. June 1941 from the Politic Agent 9 Bahrain* i V Copy forwarded, wi th compliments, to Major R.G.alban, for informati Political Agent, Bahrain on*CONFIDENTIAL . No.C/369 of 1941 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document fat- Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. Dated. ^ e . .g cm etl94 1 . Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed Letter No.C/293 dated 11.7.1941. Description «/ Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Government of India letter No. D.3407-N/41 dated the 6th August 1941. Bahrain State Budget. Lf.n'Confidential. No. D.3407-N/41. VV1 From The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Deptt. lb Tlie Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. New Delhi, the 6th Aagast 1941. Subject x- Bahrain State budget. ' . ,&lt;n Slr ’ ■ A I am directed to acknov/ledge receipt of your letter No. C/292, dated the 11th July 1941, and en closures and to say that the Government of India have noted your remarks. 2. I am to add that a copy of this correspondence is being sent to the India Office. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd.H. Weightman. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.Confidential ^ . . .MA No.C/989-4/1. Tho Political Ageat, Satirain, Proseats his compliments to :— The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Bushire. Persian Gulf, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( 8 ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated 17th October 1941. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject Statement of of the Bah for the first v : revenue &lt;8b Expenditure rain Government half of the year 1360.CONFIDENTIAL. No. J/505 of 1941. Cm*&gt; /- im The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The I-olitiCcil Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the utidermentioned document(s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp BAHH.ri.Ih. D;ited.. .4 th # # lTo vembe r _ _ 1941 Reference to previous correspondence : I * Hesidency Printed Letter lTo.CJ/226, dated the 27th June 1941. Description of Enclosure. . Name and Date. Subject. Letter Ho.Ext.4174/41, dated the 16th august 1941, Investment of from the India Office, Londor Bahrain State Reserve. to the Government of India, External Affairs Department. 1 *(Received under India Office ITo .oxt .4174 dated 23rd ^.ugust 1941.) of 1941, ixternal. Ext.4174/41. by air luii v:u durb^. CONFIDE IT Tliil 18th ^uguat 1941. Sir, Investment of Bahrein State Reserve. ^.lo4 I am directed to refer to your letter of the 6th June, No.D.2098-N/41, on the above subject, and to acquaint you with the views of the Secretary of State for India thereon. 2. It appears from Mr. Belgrave f s letter of 17th ^pril that Colonel Irior took the initiative in recommending the transfer of the Reserve Fund from sterling to rupee invest ment, and expressed “the opinion th^t the money could not easily be converted from sterling into rupees', actually, there is no difficulty, nor is any apprehended, in the conversion of sterling investments or monies into rupee form; and there is no intention of allowing the rupee to become appreciated in terms of sterling. The Government of India’s own affairs are conducted on the assufjpticn that sterling and the rupee are, and will continue to be, fully and freely interchangeable on the basis of the present parity cf ls.6d. 3. News has been received recently that financial circles in neutral territory had received reports that it was intended to raise the exchange value of the rupee. These reports, however, are known to have come direct Irom Berlin, and are obviously a part of the German propaganda machine’s attempts to cause confusion and uncertainty. Efforts are and will be made to counter them whenever they come to light. They may- 2 - re&amp;ch the j^ereian Gulf also, and it is preferable that the Political Resident should not by his attitude lend colour to the eg, 4. The becretary of btate agrees with the Government of India’s comments on Colonel Prior’s view that a btate’s reserves can be appropriately invested only in securities in its own currency. In cases where there is any reality in the choice of currency, the selection would naturally depend upon the urposes for v/hich the reserves were main tained, some weight being accorded to the exceptional inter national position of a currency such as sterling. The correct view is clearly stated in the last sentence of paragraph 3 of your letter. 5. In view of the interchangeability of sterling and the rupee, it might be inferred that it is immaterial whether the Bahrein Reserve is kept in sterling or transferred into rupee securities. This is not the case, however; for if such a transfer were made in present circumstances not only would a suspicion that this was due to distrust of sterling be likely to arise automatically ( vide paragraph 4 of the Government of India’s telegram of 10th April, Ho.1681, to the Political Resident), but it might well be impossible to conceal the grounds on which it had originally been suggested by the Political Resident, and this would lend colour to any such suspicion. 6. I am therefore to express agreement with the Govern ment of India that (i) there is no reason to advise the State to change its existing securities, and (ii) as regards any further sums that may become available the State may be advised that there is no objection to investing them in rupee securities if they so desire. It would ap^e^r oetter not to make this dependent on the assumption at the end oi paragraph 4 of your letter, as this might seem to oast soiae-3- bohjC unintended doubt upon the interchangeability of sterling and the rupee. 7. For the purpose of any rupee investments that may be made in the light of (ii) above, the Government of India may with now to transmit to the Political Resident the information asked for in paragraph 3 of his telegram -t&gt; . . of k3rd Farch, No.S/113. 1 8. a copy of this letter is being sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. r I am, bir, Your obedient servant, bd.R•Pe el. The becretary to the Government of India, External affairs Department.Confidential No. C/1128 - 4/1 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Preseats his compliments to :— V The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire• and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated 29th_JNov ember -1941r Reference to previous correspondence : Name and Date. Description of Enclosure Subject Statement, of Revenue and Expendi ture of the Bahrain Government up to the end of Rajpadhan 1360 (9 months) Bahrain State Finances.^ ] r gove Confidential . D.0.NO.1282/9A . Dated, July 13, 1942. Yesterday His Highness came to the office and discussed, among other things, the Residents appeal for contributions towards the Bahrain Fighter Fund, which appeared in the local paper on Thursday. His Highness said that it was not a good time for making the appeal because there is so much poverty in Bahrain at present and all those who can afford to give any money are giving it to the local relief committees. He decided to give Rs. 20,000/- from his own and Government funds to be divided equally between the Sunni and Shia committees. ^ h v His Highness brought with him a copy of a letter addressed to the late ruler from Colonel Prior dated April 1941, refer- ^ £&gt;* O'j ring to Shaikh Hamad’s request that a larger proportion of the - v oil royalty should be paid to his privy purse. In this letter Colonel Prior stated that he had given orders to the Political Agent that no contributions from the Ruler of any of the Ruling Family in Bahrain towards the Fighter Fund were to be accepted in future. I do not appear to have a copy of this letter. His Highness indicated to me, very clearly, that neither he or any of the family would do anything about the Fighter Fund while this letter was in force. At the same time he said that he had no objection to the schools or any other institutions organising plays on behalf of the fund. His Highness did not ask me to tell you this but I think it is desirable that you should know. E. B. Wakefield, Esquire, I.C.S., H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.V// m Confidential , g Ago.C/1 125. The Agency, Bahrain, the 28th July 1942* Thank you for your confidential demi-official letter No.l282/9A dated 13th July 1942, about the Persian Gulf Fighter Fund. 2. I did not know before about Colonel Prior's letter of April 1941, and I am grateful to you for drawing my attention to it. Yours sincerely, ^C. Dalrymple Belgrave Esq., C.B.E., Ojt Adviser to the Government, Bahrain.P.R^s Confidential demi-official letter No«1164-S dated 13/11/1942. I have discussed v/ith P.R. all the matters referred to in the above letter. The only item on which it is necessary to record a note is No.6 coupled with No.7. 2. H.H. the Shaikh gives his uncle Shaikh Mohammed Rs6,000 per mensem and his uncle Shaikh Abdullah Rs7,000 per mensem. These allowpnces are the same as those which the former Ruler used to give. H.H. gives Rs400 p.m. to his brothers. To other members of the family he gives cash presents when required. There has been no alteration in the Civil List. H.H. gave his uncles cash presents shortly after Shaikh Hamad*s death. The exact amounts are not known but were in the neighbourhood of Rs 10,000/-. Sd.3.B. Wakefield. 4/ 2/42. —The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to ; His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for information. Adviser's Office, No P/ Manamah, Bahrain. Dated January 19, 1943 Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. List of members of the Ruling Family who draw pay separ appointments in va of the Bahrain Government - as on 1st Moharram 1362 (January 8, 1943). ately for holding rious departmentsConfidential . office of the Political ■ He si dent in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. D.O.No.C/977. Dated the 17th December, 1942 Dear Wakefield, As you are aware, the question of Al Khalifa allowances has been the subject of much correspondence in the pasty^i hare heard nothing about it for some time now. Could you very kindiy let me have a brief note at your leisure showing what the present position is ? Political Agent, .Bahrain.V TjH' The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to : His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents. I \ y t V - Adviser’s Office, No p/ ^ ^ y\ Manamah, Bahrain. Dated:— January 20, 1943. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. Reference to previous correspondenceNo. /&lt;,*/' 1 A of 1362 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Moharram 20, 1362 January 27, 1943. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: CIVIL LIST. The actual payments from State funds in the Civil List during the 1356 1357 1358 1359 1360 1361 last six years were as follows:- Rs. 4,45,773-11- 6 4,45,792- 4- 5 4,38,234-10- 7 4,34,905- 8- 0 4,34,782- 2- 3 4,28,108- 0- 0 This represents the monthly allowances to members of the Ruling Family and to certain old servants and dependents. Some other items have been included under 'Civil List' in the past but in future these will be shfcwn separately. The additional items are payments made from State funds to or on behalf of members of the Ruling Family, by orders of the Ruler, they include such items as the following:- pay of the Factor (Rs.6,000 per annum) and passages. Allowances to Amir of Rafaa for upkeep of Rafaa wells. Education of Shaikh Mohd bin Isa sons at Beyrout. Cost of presentation swords. Expenses of annual accession celebrations. FinancifcCas si stance for Shaikh Mohd when at Malta. In some years additional allowances were paid from the Civil List to members of the Ruling Family by orders of the Ruler and the amounts were refunded by him to the Treasury at the beginning of the following year. The Civil List for 1362 will amount to fts.4,26,000/-. Adviser to the Government. S.ZConfidential Political Agency * % D.O. No. C/187 Bahrain, 11th February 1943. Will you please refer to your demi- ofiicial letter No. C/977 dated the 17th December 1942. 2. I enclose, as desired, a brief note indi cating the present position in regard to allowances to the A1 Khalifah. «e Honourable Lieutenant-Colonel C. G. Prior, C. I. E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BushireDuring the later years of his rule Shaikh Hamad took for hie Privy Purse one-third of the Oil Royalties while the remaining two-thirds vtaa oaid into the Bahrain Government Treasury. Since Shaikh Pal/aan became Ruler the Oil Royalties have continued to be apportioned in the same manner. 2. Those members of the A1 Khalifah who have official appointments under the Bahrain Government draw the salaries shown in the annexure to this note, other sources of revenue to the Al Khalifah are *- (i) Civil List Payments and (ii) Allowances given by His Highness the Shaikh from his Privy Purse. 3. Civil List Payments during the last six years have been as follows s- 1356 ... Rs 1357 1358 1359 1360 1361 4,45,773 11 6 4,45,792 4 5 4,38,234 10 7 4,34,905 8 0 4,34,782 2 3 4,28,108 0 0 These payments represent monthly allowances to members of the Al Khalifah and to certain old servants and dependents. As will be seen from the figures given above there is no tendency for payments from the Civil List to increase. 4. Prom his Privy Purse His Highness Shaikh Salman gives allowances aggregating Ha. 11,139/- monthly to various members and dependents of his family. In addition to these monthly allowances His Highness makes special payments twice a year v;hen Oil loyalties are received. On these six monthly occasions he gives each of his two uncles Pa. 20,000/- and to other members of the family a sum eaual to their normal monthly allowance. Occasionally His Highness has given members of his family sums of money equal to two months' allowance but this is the exception rather than the rule. 5. Hiring recent months there has been a phenomenal rise in the cost of living in Bahrain and members of the Al Khalifah have found difficulty in maintaining themselves and their house hold. His Highness has invariably given financial assistance, when he thought it justified, from his b'ivy Purse and has never suggested either to the Ad*4ser or myself that additional payments should be made to the Al Khalifnh from Btate funds. His Highness is careful in financial matters and deliberately keeps the purse strings tight in order to make the members of his family continually aware of their dependence on him.List of members of the Ruling Family who draw pay separately for holding appointments in various departments of the Bahrain Government as on 1st Wuharram 1362 (January 8, 1943) Shaikh Khalifah bin Mohammad al Khalifah Pay as Superintendent of Police 425 Conveyance Allowance 130 Shaikh Ali bin Ahmed Al Khalifah Pay as l agistrate, Bahrain Court 300 Pay as Amir of Haraa 100 Pay as Bapco employees’ represent- 50 atlve Pay for looking after Raffa well 100 Shaikh Rashid bin Mohammed Al Khalifah Pay as Magistrate, Bahrain Court Shaikh Daij bin Hamad Al Khalifah Pay as Magistrate, Bahrain Court 0 C 0 I - 0 - 0 - 0 - 0 i l I &lt;) i Shaikh Mubarak bin Hamad Al Khalifah Pay as Magistrate, Small Joint Court Shaikh Ahmed bin Hamad Al Khalifah Pay as Magistrate, Bahrain ^mall Court Shaikh Mohamed bin Ali bin Mohamed Pay as Magistrate, Bahrain omaii Court Shaikh Ali bin Khalifah bin Daij Pay as President, Majlis Tijarah Shaikh Atipatullah bin Abdulrehman Al Khalifah Pay as Supervisor, Sunni bakf Department 555 0 550 0 315 0 300 0 200 0 200 0 200 0 100 0 82 0The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to ; His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. three copies and has the honour to send him %z:££ypyz of the undermentioned documents, for information. Advisers Office, No:— p/ - 21 Manamah, Bahrain. Dated:— February 9, 1943. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. Reference to previous correspondence :— ■i PL- c/'K, ^ 'M* 3 s.z.Yfl The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to : His Britannic ilajesty T s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for information Adviser s Office, Manamah, Bahrain. No Dated February 24, 1943. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. 1. 3_copi es of Summary of Revenue &amp; Expenditure for the year 1361. 2. 3,copies of Statement of hovenue 8c Expenditure I I ,1 ■ for the year |.361. Copy of end. sent to P.R. under P.I . No. C/278 dated 28th February 1943. Reference; to previous correspondence :■!onfidsiiti«a, v o.g/97 To ^fxice of the Political Resident Persian Ouli, 4^ \ \ Baiirain, ^ \&gt;i i V LOiLfMDLll, The loliticax ^tnt, Baruain • , - 1 - 51 -u.ix a xxi • ; 3^th F^roh 194 3^1. ^uxii'am Pinance t (P l ^ P.fcfereuoe^jTour nttooraatta Ho.C/186 dated the nth Feb ruary 1543 and C/278 dated the 28th February 1943 . fi 1 The for the year 1361 does not an ear^iifhave oeen forwarded to this office and that for the year 1362 is not accompanied by the usual explanatory notes by the Adviser and comment by yourself. Moreover no e^lanation is given of the Tact that only a sum of X 62,688/13/0 has been added to the Reser-e Runu during the year 1361 whereas the receipts from royalty on oil during the year, a third of which is normally ^ crelited to the Reserve ?und, were is 26,21,412/6/0. In his note on the Reserve ?und at pages 13-14 of the Annual Rei,oi't of the Oceinuei.. of Ranrain for the Arabic year 1360 the Adviser estimated that investment during 1361 would amount to fe 14 lakhs. Please ask the Adviser to furnish a brief note on the finances of the i ea^ l3oi giving t.oe reason for the comparatively small cre ^ i ted to the Reserve Bund during the year. Sd* C.G.Prior. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf 8 ATTBSTBR. 1 u.^r Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. v ; ■ ' /. : ■ k&gt; A&gt; LfLjdi od P S'&amp; dr 13,6^ ^vA w / 2-1 r f 0 A^. C5 &amp; ^ k V /Vo.No.C/471. To Political Agency, Bahrain, 6th April 1943. ? The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, B A H R A I N . Memorandum Reference the enclosures to your Printed Letter No.406 dated the 24th February 1943, copies of which were forwarded by me to the Honourable the Political Resident. 2. The Political Resident has noted that a sum of Rs.62,688/13/- only was added to the Reserve Fund during 1361 whereas receipts from Oil Royalty during the year, a third of which is normally added to the Reserve Fund, were Rs.26,21,412/6/-. The Political Resident also observes that in your Note on the Reserve Fund at pages 13-14 of the Annual Report of the Government of Bahrain for 1360 you estimated that investment during 1361 would amount to Rs.14 lakhs, dould you please let me have, for the information of the Honourable the Political Resident, a brief note on the finances of the year 1361 giving the reason for the comparatively small sum credited to the Reserve Fund during the year 7GOVERNMENT BAHRAIN. No. ^ X-1 0 f 1362 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 23rd R/Thani 1362 April 29, 1943. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- With reference to your memorandum NcK. C/471 dated 6th April 1943, enquiring why the Bahrain Government did not invest more than Rs.62,688/13/- in the Reserve Fund during 1361. During the early months of 1361 the Bahrain Govern ment hoped to be able to purchase from India a sufficient stock of rice to last the country for about a year. Funds which might otherwise have been invested were kept free for making this purchase which eventually was not possible owing to the restriction on export of rice from India. In the Budget for 1361 I estimated that the total expenditure under Budget headings would amount to Rs.37,00,000/-. This included a contribution of Rs.9,80,000/- to the Reserve Fund. During the year abnormal expenditure, not anticipated in the Budget, was made amounting to Rs. 10,04,000/-. Of this amount Rs.l,00,000/- was the refund of the Depreciation on the Electric Department Reserve Fund from the Consoli dated Fund into the Electricity Account, Rs.l,31,534/- was paid to the Manamah and Moharraq Municipalities being the cost of buying their shares in the Electric Undertaking and Rs. 7,73,000/- was the amount spent upon food supplies which were held by the Government at the end of the year. The cash balance in the Consolidated Fund and other bank accounts at the close of the year was Rs.3,52,966/-. During the first quarter of 1362 the sum of 5 lakhs was invested in Government of India Stock and added to the Reserve Fund. Adviser to the Government.'/I 1 The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to : His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents, lor information. Advisers Office, Manamah, Bahrain. No ?/ i Dated May 13, 1943. P’S Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. 1. Summary of Revenue h c Expenditure at end of months) R/Awal 1362 (3 2. Statement of Expend; .ture ending R/Awal 1362 (3 months) 3. Statement of Revenu&lt; } ending R/Awal 1362 (3 months). 1 Reference to previous correspondence\ /'■ From To CONFIDENTIAL. No. 472-S . British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 1st June 1943. ’ The Hon* tie Lieut.-Colonel C.G. Prior GIF 1 Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ’’ Bushire. The Secretary to the Government of India m the External Affairs Department, , IxT! * NEW DELHI . | ' Sir, f ^ ' X have the honour to forward for^e information of the^ Government of India a' copy of th&lt; Bahrain State Budget for the ye a r 1362. y f 2. Although the receipts from.^oyalty on oil during the year 1361 ( a third of which is normally credited to the Reserve am^ed Joy. ^ 26,21,412/6/0, only Fi. 62,688/13/0 was added to the Reserve Fund during the year. I reproduce below an extract from a note by the Adviser giving reasons for this comparatively small investment: ^ ^ . .'? n the ^dget for 1361 I estimated that the It 1 ay^O^OO/ 6 Wi Z^ et headin 2 s would amount of 9 7 30 °P 0 n/'; J hl f inoluded a Contribution 01 y,oU,000/- to the Reserve Fund. During the year abnormal expenditure, not Es t io 1 04 000/ n the Gf U ?h® t ’ WaS ? ade amoll nting to s# this amount Rs. 1,00,000/- was the refund of the Depreciation on the Electric ^nto^hfh Trh Fu ? d rrom the Consolidated Fund ^nto the Electricity Account, Fs. 1 , 31 , 534 /- was tlie Manamah and Lloharraq Municipalities being the cost of buying their shares in the Electric Undertaking and Fs. 7,73,000/- was the amount spent upon food supplies mich were held by the Government at the end of the year.'* ^ I ' f iT 8 3. During the first quarter of 1362 a sum of 5 lakhs was invested in Government of India Stock and added to the Reserve Fund. I am surprised that it was not possible to'anticipate' such an item a s Es. 1,00,000/- for refund of depreciation. This appears, moreover , to be a book transaction, and I will make further inquiries regarding it on my next visit to Bahrain. / A.A copy of this letter is being sent to the Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sb. C.G.PRIOR. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ■with reference to Bahrain iienio rand uni lo.C/610, dated the 5th May 1943* No.473-S British Residency &amp; Consulate General, Bushire, 1st June 1943. with compliments, to The Political Agent, Bahrain,No. /3 t J ^ of 1362 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 13th J/Thani,1362 June 17, 1943. K. B. 1 f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: - V/ith reference to your memorandum No.C/787 dated the 9th June, 1943, a sum of 1,3.1,00,000/- v/as paid from the Hlectric Account into the Government Consolidated Fund in the year 1360 ceing part of the repayment of a sum of m.1,61,825/- wmch the Bahrain Government had advanced to the Electric Department for purchasing additional machinery. The Auditors suggested that the sum of m*. 1,61,825/- should be added to the capital of the electric undertaking, and that the sum of Ks. 1,00' 000/- should be repaid to build up a ^Depreciation Reserve” to provide for future replacements of riant and machinery. The sum of i:s. 1,00,000/- was actually repaid from the Consolidated Fund into the Electric Account with the Eastern Bank Limited, Bahrain, during Adviser to the Government. 3.Z.Confidential No. C/986 To Political Agency, \^A Bahrain, the 21st July 1943. The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* Memorandum Refer 472-S, (feted e paragraph 3 of your confidential letter No. -i-st of June 1943, to the Government of India. tik* -f ln y ear the .Electric Department credited to the ?i SUm ,° f * 1 ’ 00 ’ 000 ^ be held as a deposit? item is correctly shown as a deposit with the Bahrain Gove-n AO E } ec ^ ric department* s Balance Sheet for 1360 (vide + rj v. Bahrain i.nnual Report 1360). an error of accounting the Bahrain Government did not place this sum in a deposit account of Revenue°and PvnLd??® but + credit ? d dt to Revenue (?ide Statement 1360? Tn ^P^^ureat page 10 of Bahrain Annual Report for ortheir^e^alt T J 3 tK h ® R 6 ® 1 ^ 10 Department required a refund tha ■ I:f . the 8Um had been correctly accounted for by £efu£de£ th^T ?+ ® dpos ! t ln 1360 ' the sum would have been rerundefl from the deposit account. But as the sum had. inrorTw+i^ been credited to Revenue in 1360 it had to be debited lo Expendi- ^ u U ^ e ^ Wben .p^ was re ^ un&lt; i e&lt; i i 11 1361. If proper accounting methods ad been followed the actual figures of Revenue during 1360 would S ^“’S 00 , ' h • “ t “ sl ture during 1361 would also have been reduced by the same amount. fife IC&gt;£ Political Agent, Bahrain,€ The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to ; His Britannic Majesty’s Political Ay;ent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for infomatiou. Advisers Office, No P/ ~ Manamah, Bahrain. Dated:— July 20, 1943. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. \1© ^ 1. Summary of Revenue arid Expenditure &gt;dt end of Jamad al TJrani 1362 ( 2. Statement of Revenue period ending Jamad c six months). under Budget heads for ?• \0 period ending Jamad al Than! 1362 (six months). 3. Statement of Expenditure under Budge - ; heads for 1 Thani 1362 (six months) . — n .3. P *I / CONFITKiyriAL Politinal Agency, Bahrain, 15th Octeber 1943 From *•.C/1363 T. 1 _ xrthsm, Pelitical Agent, Bphr^in* % T« The Adviser t» the Bahrain Q^vemxient, Tha Gev ernment ef India have he tic.'id that there 4ire considerable variations in the figures under certain heads 5 both of revenue and expenditure, in the Bahrein budgets for the years 1360, 1361 and 1362. I believe that the Assistant Political Atfent has already asked you to let us have an explanation oi these variations for the infor mation of the Government of India. I hope that you will bo able to do so in tho very near future. Bahrain Sir Political Agent, Bahrain,*4 ^ /,\0' r 7 'V No. Bahrain, Dated, October 21, 1943. 4k&gt;) n\ v From To C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, * v Persian Gulf. \ ! . His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sik, / I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your lg honoi 'fyi dat( letter No.C/l3§o dated 15th October 1943, and am en closing a summary of the Budget Headings for the three years with notes on the variations each year. I hope that this will clarify the subject.. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the Governmentt sk. Revenue. 1360 1361 1362 Oil Royalty 25,50,000 26,00,000 26,00,000 Customs 6,75,000 7,00,000 6,10,000 Interest of Reserve 2,35,000 2,62,000 2,50,000 Other Receipts &amp; Taxes 1,04,000 1,38,000 1,97,000 Suspense Account proceeds from sales of Foodstuff s • • • • • • 7,73,000 35,64,000 37,00,000 44,30,000 Expenditure 1360 Ruling Family 12,90,000 1361 12,92,000 1362 12,91,000 Administration 3,38,800 3,34,000 4,01,000 Public Health 2,52,200 2,64,000 3,18,000 Public Protection 4,15,000 4,00,000 5,28,000 Education 1,32,300 2,40,000 2,60,000 public Works 3,86,300 69,000 90,000 Municipalities 60,400 61,000 51,000 Unforeseen, Agriculture etc 80,000 60,000 67,000 To Reserve Fund 6,09,000 9,80,000 6,16,000 Poor Relief • • • • • • 35,000 Suspense Account For purchase of Food supplies • • # • • • 7,73,000 • 35,64,000 37,00,000 44,30,000 Oil. * The estimate of future oil revenue is based upon previous actuals and upon discussion with the staff of the Bahrain Petroleum Company who afford some information of expected output. Customs. Owing to the uncertainties of trade due to war I have during the last three years assumed that customs duty would decrease, in 1361 pearling licenses were reduced by half and in 1362 they were suspended.Interest on Reserve. The amount shown in the estimate for 1361 included the interest due on the reserve and the interest for six months (second half of 1361) on Ks.9,80,000/- which I had anticipated would be added to the reserve in 1361. It was not possible to invest this amount during 1361 owing to the state having to purchase foodstuffs. In 1362 the interest due on the existing reserve was shown in the budget. Other Receipts and Taxes . In 1360 no revenue was expected from 'Hedical Receipts”, In 1361 I assumed that this source of revenue would produce iuj.5,000/-, twice this amount was obtained. In 1362 I have anticipated an income of Ks.55,000/- from hospital fees, the * greater proportion being on account of service in-patients who occupy the two service wards in the State hospital. Bridge tolls were not included in the 1360 budget. In 1361 I assumed that Ks.30,000/- would be forthcoming from this source, and a similar sum in 1362. The variations in estimates of the other sources of revenue such as Court fees Passport Receipts, Rents etc. are not considerable. A sum of Ks. 13,000/- was included in the 1362 Budget under Sales of Lands.Negotiations were proceeding for the sale of a piece of land to the Royal Air Foce and I assumed that this sum would be forthcoming. The total anticipated revenue for the three years was, 1360, Rs. 35,64,000; 1361, Rs. 37,00,000/- and 1362 Rs. 36,57,000/ Expenditure . Total estimated expenditure in the three years, 1360, 1361 and 1362 was Rs. . ^5,64,000, Rs. 37,00,000 and 36,57,000 respectively.3 (nj) viH Ruling Family, Oil Royalty . This payment is dependent upon the amount of oil royalty. His Highness The Shaikh received l/3rd of the royalty payment. Civil List . In 1360 and 1361 certain pensions paid to non members of the Ruling Family were included in the Civil List. These payments were shown separately in 1362. Admins tration . The cost of Administration in 1360 was about £325,000/- less than the allocated amount. Owing to increasing costs I allowed approximately the same amount;for the following year?) During the current year I have anticipated additional expenditure under this heading of approximately Bs. 67,000/- owing to War Allowances, h^igh cost of transport fares, stationery etc. and the maintenance of the Food Department which is a new branch of the Customs Department. Public Health . Estimates of expenditure on Public Health for 1360 and 1361 differred by Es.12,000/-. In 1362 I allowed an additional Ba.54,000/- to cover the very great rise in the cost of food, drugs, medical stores etc. This allocation includes the costs of the two European service wards from which it is expected revenue amounting to about R3.50,000/- will be received. Public Protection . The cost of public protection in 1360 was over estimated by Rij.26,000/-. In 1361 I anticipated that expenditure under this heading would not exceed 4,00,000/-. The actual amount spent was R3.4,51,000/-. The extra cost of public protection was due to higher cost of rations for State forces and prisoners, the war allowance paid to the Natur force and the- 4 - includes under this heading Rs.65,000/- for new equipment and uniforms of which only a portion is likely to he spent during the year. Education. In 1360 Rs.1,32,000/- was provided for Education, the actual expenditure was ms. 1 ,57 ,000/- . During this year the Secondary School was increased in size and the hostel for students was enlarged. In 1361 the sum allocated to Education was Rs. 2,40,000/- of which Rs. 2,24,000/- was spent. Provision was made in the Budget for Rs.35,000/- worth of tools and equipment for the Technical School which expanded considerably during theyear and also for Rs.18,000/- worth/' of furniture and equipment for Boys and Girls T Schools to provide accommodation for the increasing numbers of pupils. Both the Secondary School and Hostel were moved to larger buildings and several village schools were enlarged. For the current year Rs. 2,60,000/- has been provided for Education to cover war allowances, increased costs of school books and materials used in the schools and for Technical training. Public Works . In 1360 Rs.20,000/- was assigned to maintenance of roads and buildings and Rs.3,66,000/- for certain new works inc luding Shaikh Hamad Bridge, hospital buildings and new married lines at the Fort. In the following two years owing to cost of building and the fact that the Public Works Department was mainly occupied with work for the Royal Air Force no important public works were contemplated. The remaining items of expenditure in the Budget such aw Municipal Grants, Unforeseen, Contribution to Reserve Fund and Poor Relief do not appear to require any explanation.t caftnDwim Ho.0/1582. \ Political Agency, To Bahrain, 23rd November 1S43. The Secretnry to the Hon*bio the Political Reeirtont in the Porsim Gulf, Buahire. ^ vvA t'KMORAHDU?.* Reference your memomndum No .754-3 dntcd the 9th September 1943. 2. The budget for tho year 1361 is et page 52 of the Annual Report for tho yenr 1360. / 3. -ho Adviser*0 explanatory memoranda for the years 1360 and 1362 are contained In the Annual Repo ta for thene t\^o years, copies of which have already been for- . warded to you. I now enclose q copy of n memorandum from the Adviser on the more important differences of the various budget hoadir^is for the three years 1360, 1361 and 1362. 4. The year 1362 has very nearly come to an end and although my cor-menta on this year, which form an enclosure to this letter, may be of some value when the budget for 1363 is compiled, I do not consider that any useful purpose can be achieved by cay commenting on tho budget for the year 1361. 5. I have not yet had sufficient leisure to examine « the investments of the Bahrain Government and Bahrain iSloctrical Department but will do so as soon as I can find time and will furnish you with my views should I notice any points of particular interest. 6. Provided the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf sees no objection, 1 propose to forward a copy *f my memorandum to the Advisor to tho Bahrain Government.•&gt; t BAB-HAMf BU'XSaT to: 1362 i - oarguL The occounua of tho Bahrain .Icct^ricnl Dopartaont and the Bu iget for Uie Bahrain tiloctrienl Department have been kept separate from the 3tnto Bulget and the state Account#* This ia, in ny opinion, euite wron.^ and the aasete of the £loetrical Department should be eho^tn as assets of the Stnte and the department should be budgeted for in exactly the seme *ay as any other department of the Oovemaent* !• 'Profit and Lona Acco unt !l 1361. On the receipt side of the M Profit and Lons Account' there is only one item which re^ds 'Sundry Revenues and Receipts'* The receipts should be detailed under their major heads and should there be any snail receipts of not sufficient importance to receive a heading of their own, they should bo described as 'Sundry'* The revenues from rentals, telephones, sale of appliances, sale of current^ond installation charges, dc*, should be clearly shown. On the expenditure side the use of the word 'Reserve' in conjunction with 'Bed Debts' and 'TSngine Dpa^es', does not soem to be appropriate* 'Operating Reaerve' does not describe the purpose for which the money is to be used* If the item Rs*48,761-13-1 is intended to finance the operations of the Electrical Department then it would seem to me th t it should have been transferred to the liability side of the 'Balance Sheet' and not appear in this account at all* If, however, it is in fact the excess of receipts over expenditure, i*6•, the profit on the year's working, as it would appear to be, then it should be described as such* 8*' Balance ifooeV There is no indication th t any interest has accnued from the fc$*8,18,465-7-3 noted in the'Balance dheot' for 1361 /asmoney has only Juat been invested and therefore dividends have not become duo* On the liability aide of the 'Balance 'Sheet’' 1361 we see s free use of the term 'Reserve'* 'Depreciation Reserve' could possibly be better described as a 'Replacement Fund' while It should not be necens' ry to have a 'Reserve for Bnd Debts' in your 'Balance Sheet'* although 'Bad Debts' might, and frequently do, figure in accounts* Under 'Operating Reserve' there is the eura of 1,36,409- -16-3 without any indication of how this sum was arrived at* we have already noted an 'Operating Reserve' of *48,761-13-1 In the 'Profit and Loss Account' 1361. Jrughg The graphs showing 'Units Generated' and 'Revenue in Hip e^ are misleading, for the revenue is shown at half the scale of the units generated* Thus the variation in the Revenue' graph is only half ns gre&lt; t as the variation in the 'Unit'graph* Tho 'Revenue' scale should in future reports be the same as the 'Units Generated' scale* III - ST * TK BUDGET RiaV&amp;WU&amp;G 1* Oil Royalty * The Adviser is correct in giving a conservative estimate under this head* I hove been given to understand that the expansion of the Refinery nlil not affect the royalty paid to the Bahrain v'^overreftent this year. 2* ustoms . As the Bahrain Customs duties sre assessed on the value of the articles imported and not on the quantity the revenue will only decrease when the value of the total imports falls below that of the previous year* I see little likelihood of this occurring in view of the continual rise in prices and 1 consider that this should hav * been taken into account when assessing the probable revenue under this head* I believe that the customs revenue this year has already exceeds the budget figure by some six lakhs of rupees* 3* .lusponse *»ccouht « The sum of te*7,73,000 has beenshown on the * t Kevenue' , side as proceeds of sales of food-stuff* to the general public. The same figure appears on the “Expenditure' side for the purchase of food supplies. Thus It would seem that the Bahrain Government do not Intond to aeet the additional expenditure necessitated by the employment of additional staff to suporvlse the purchase and distribution of food supplies toy a slight increase In the eale price of those supplies. In fact they have budgeted for It under 'Customs and Food Control'. * This amounts to a subsidy by the Government to the people and for purpose* of assessing exactly how much assistance the Government la giving to the people it would be better to have the Food Control expenditure shown as a separate Item to the Customs expsndlture. ■apatroirjHg. (a) Paasaort noportaent . Tha Passport napartmant la being run at a loss. This is probably due to the fact th t owing to the restrictions on foreign travel the sale and renewal of Bahrain Government passports has greatly decreased. At the same time, the work of the Passport Department has increased owing to the additional services now being run by the British Overseas Airways Corporation. W Transport * fe.06 f OOO h*s been budgeted for 'Transport' (Item (g) of paragraph £ of the Budget). This sum Is usod to keep up a Govomment garage which mends and services Bahrain Government transport and municipal transport. The heading 'Transport' Is misleading and It should be 'Government Grrage' and be budgetted for it under the heading P.w.n. The municipalities should pay for services carried out ty the Government garage and this income should bo shown in the accounts as revenue and If necessary they should have their grants Increased to meet this additional expenditure.2« Public Fte&amp;ltii ,. Tiiere im* b#en an iucruase under this head and such Increase is. In my opinion, justified &gt; by the additional cost of food*stuffs and the high prices of drurfs. I expect that the reeenue during the present year v&amp;ll greatly exceed that budgeted* 3* Puplic Protections The fact that the State Police do not receive a fthr Mloeance is not apparent frorc the budget but they alone of all oie Departoents of Govormaent have had no alteration In their pay since the vs&amp;r began« They are undoubtedly entitled to at least a 25$ increase in their basic pay and a budget provision for this should be aade In the budget for 13£2» 4. PuUiiC haifca itepfcrtaBEQti* It «ould qppear that toil Bopartsent costs the State e*4d 9 000 and only supervises the expenditure of P»d0 9 U00« This ls 9 I as glad to say 9 not the M' cnUx/ case, for the Public Works Depart sent/ deals with the 'Shaikh yL tud'/uKA&gt; aamao Bridge' 9/ 'Se% Buildings', ussd during the course of the last year sa supervised, free of cost, a considerable build* ing programs* for the Defence Services* The Public Works Department should undoubtedly N y y be a major heading and should include the 'Upkeep of Tio&amp;ds and Government Buildings', 'The Shaikh Hamad Bridge' and 'Public Works, Sew Buildings', The Department snould appear on the revenue aide as well as on the expenditure side# When considering tae amount spent under the 'Upkeep of Bonds' it must be realised that the roads alluded to are the roads lying outside the municipal limits and outside the Oil Company*s area. The municipalities are res* pocuible for the upkeep of their ovn roads and grants to the municipalities amounting to i,31,003 (item 6 of the Budget) are made by the Government to assist them in carrying out this work. It would bo beneficial if the Municipal Budgets besides being puollahed In newspapers were shown in the Annual Reports* / 5* &gt; r~ the Budget is incorrectly worded, for no contribution is made for the relief of the poor but ^he Bahrain Government do in fact distribute food to poor people and funds are found from this budget head* There are various other poor relief schemes in being in the Islands but I am assured that this is purely a Government measure and although the municipality assists in the distribution of the relief they have no respon- sibility for the relief* The heading should be “Smergency War Poor Belief f * to make it clear that the measure is purely a war measure. Bahrain, 24th November 1943. PoliLical 4gent, Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. &lt;3 £1 Office of the Adviser to the Govermient, Bahrain Dated, Moharram 24, 1363 January 20, 1944. (9 From \.\S / im\. C. Dalrynple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.S., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain Bahrain, Persian Gulf. To His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to enclose, for your information copies of the Budget of the State for the year 1363, together with a Summary of receipts and expenditure for 1362 and a note explaining the various items in the Budget. In order to facilitate a comparison of actuals and estr tes I have shown the revenue and expenditure figures for 1362 on the same sheet as the estimates for 1363. A Summary of the Budget of the Electricity Supply Department has been included below the State Budget. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant Adviser to the Government Enel2/- BODGUr 1363. Kjrmw'z . The revenue for the budget year is estimated at 40 lacs of rupees, the actual revenue during the previous year was 47 lacs. The expenditure for the budget year is estimated at R«.35,30,000/-, the actual expenditure in the previous year being H.33,29,000/-. I have anticipated a surplus of revenue over expenditure amounting Rs.4,70,000/-, for investment in the Reserve Fund. The total anticipated revenue for the budget year represents a decrease of Rs. 7,00,000/- on the actuals for the previous year. 2. Out of the whole estimated revenue of the State, 40 lacs, the sura of 26{ lacs is to be obtained from oil royalty and 8-jj lacs from customs sources. The third largest soiree of revenue is now the income from the Reserve Fund which amounts to 2£ lacs. 3. Oil royalty has been estimated at slightly less than the actual of 1362. Customs receipts in 1362 were astonishingly high, they amounted to just under 14 lacs which is more than double the sum which I anticipated in the Budget for 1362. No customs records are available before 1344 but during the last eighteen years the peak year, 1346, produced only ll£ lacs from customs sources. When I prepared the Budget for 1362 I entertained grave apprehension as to the effect of the war upon customs revenue, it seemed likely that owing to shipping diffi culties and various restrictions in trade there would be a diminution in the quantity of imported goods resulting in less duty. The increase in the customs revenue during 1362, which was over 5 lacs more than the previous year’s actuals, was due mainly to the rise in the prices of the imported goo-^ds and partly to the revenue from food supplies in transit through Bahrain to other Gulf States. In spite2 of a successful year I have anticipated only 8l from customs in the budget year. lacs 4. Interest from the Reserve Fund represents 3$ on the capital which now amounts to Rs.91,41,000/- face value. Medical Receipts consist mainly of the fees received from the Army, Navy and Royal Air Force for service patients who are admitted to the special wards in the State Hospital. Land Revenue is obtained ffom registration fees on sales of property and rents from land which is leased out by the GrOTenmmect. There is no land tax in Bahrain of any kind. Education receipts include an annual grant which is made by the British Council, school fees and the proceeds from the sale of work carried out by the Technical School. The last item was not shown separately last year but was credited to Technical School Expenditure. The revenue from motor taxes and driving licenses has been estimated at less than last year owing to the probable decrease in the number of vehicles on the road. Passport receipts have decreased during the war owing to fewer people travelling abroad on book passports. Judicial receipts were unusually high in 1362 owing to the fines which were imposed in cases of smuggling and offences against food control regulations. In estimating considerably less revenue under this heading than in 1362 I have assumed that there will be a decrease in smuggling activities. I have shown receipts from the Government garage as a separate item, these receipts ate, in fact, book transactions between the various Government departments axxL the garage. Oil gauging fees paid by the Bahrain Petroleum Company for gauging, which is done by the State Engineer and the Government gaugers, of products exported by the Company in ships which are not owned by the Company. Some reduction in bridge tolls is expected owing to the decreasing number of vehicles.3 \q&gt;« 5. The summary of the Slectric Supply Department’s budget has been included v&amp; th the State Budget. This shows an estimated revenue of Ra.2,18,000/-. The revenue includes the interest from the Depreciation Reserve which is invested in the Government of India Securities paying 3%. A surplus of revenue over expenditure amounting to Ri.35,000/- is expected which will be added to the Operating Reserve which is a provision against future replacement of plant and machinery. 6. In the budget for 1362 a Suspense Account of Rs. 7,73,000 was shown which represented the value of the food supplies held by the Government at the end of the year. I have not included this in the budget for 1363 but have shown it in the Summary of Revenue and Expenditure.BUDG3T 1363. The estimate for expenditure for the budget year exceeds 35 lacs and id higher than any other year in the history of the State. It exceeds the actual expenditure in the previous year by 2 lacs. Out of the 35 lacs the allowances to the Ruling Family absorb 13 lacs which is more than one third of the whole estimated expenditure. The Budget Surplus is estimated at Es.4,70,000/-, but as the revenue has been based on very conservative lines and more than sufficient has been provided for most of the items of expenditure it may reasonably be hoped that the Surplus will be more than the sum which is shown in the budget. Almost the whole of the expenditure consists of salaries which for the most part are paid to Bahrain subjects living in the country. In past years the expen diture included the provision of large sums for purchases from abroad such as building materials, motor vehicles and for the construction of Shaikh Hamad Bridge. This money went out of the country but the expenditure in the 1363 budget is almost entirely local. The expenditure on State Departments is estimated at El.4,50,000/- which is ^ lac more than the actuals of the previous year. Customs expenditure in 1362 was abnormally high as it included certain payments on account of leave etc., made to the retiring Director of Customs. The cost of the Food Control Department has been shown this year as a separate item, it has expanded considerably since last year owing to the building and opening of new Government shops. In several Departments provision has been made for a full complement of staff which does not at present exist and it is doubtful if the vacancies will be filled during the Budget year. The increased rate of war allowances, which was introduced in the latter partof 1362, higher wages and the normal annual increments have all contributed to the greater cost of administration. The provision of Education exceeds last year’s expen diture by over one lac. In all schools, except t^e Tech nical School, the number of teachers has increased and one large new school was opened. War Alio wane es at the present rate were not paid throughout the year 1362 but have been orovided for during the whole of 1363. A sum of ms.28,000/- is allocated for higher education and expansion, this includes fees for boys who may be sent to study abroad during the next school term, provision for two new Kinder garten schools and some additional more qualified teachers for the existing schools. Out of the i.60,000/-, which is provided for the Technical school R3.8,000/- is the cost of material which is expected to be recovered by the sale of work. The increased expenditure on Public Health is to a certain extent offset by the anticipated revenue of % ha.65,000/- which is expected to be received in fees. The higher cost is due to the high prices of stores and equipment, war allowances, increments and the cost of food. Defence and Protection now costs the State almost 6 t lacs. It has risen steadily since the beginning of the war and is likely to increase. The bum in the budget allows for the scales of pay existing at the end of the year 1362 and no provision has been made for any further increases which may become necessary during 1363. Only hi:.20,000/- has been provided for uniforms and equipment as in 1362^ a quantity of new material was purchased by the State. The Special Police, who are paid for entirely by the State, are employed solely on protective duties at the Refiner:, and oil fields. This expensive responsibility was under taken by the State when the military authorities decided that it was necessary to employ a Special police Force to prevent sabotage etc. Towards the end of 1362 the ^Police were given they were granted - 3 - a concession hy which instead of paying for certain iteras of their uniform from their uniform aliowanee all uniform was issued and replaced freely and the men were allowed to retain their clothing allowance for themselves. The Special Police were also provided with tickets entitling them to free transport once weekly between Manama and their cajpp. The cost to the State of the pay and rations of a policeman is now Rio51/- per month which does not include clothing, housing etc. The Police receive rations on a generous scale, including rice, and the quantity of cereals per head per month is more than tba-n double the quantity of tne cereals which is issued to the public. Most of the other items of expenditure in the budget are self explanatory. Out of the sum which is provided for Poor Relief the G-ovemment distributes a small quantity of dates to majay hundreds of poor people daily in Manama and Moharraq and also loaves of bread to the undernorished children in the country schools. The new works which are mentioned under Public Works include a new Womens Dispensary in Moharraq, in place of the present hired house and some additions to the Port and the Schools. Under State Sngineer’s Department the expenditure shown against Shaikh Hamad Bridge is rs. 41,000/-. The actual expenditure is estimated at Ks.17,000/-, annual depreciation is Rs&lt;&gt;8,000/- per annum. In 1361 and 1362 no sum was set aside for depreciation. A new account has now been opened into which the annual depreciation on the bridge will be paid and the depreciation ^ ^ for 1361 and 1362 has been included on the expenditure A side of the 1363 budget. In 1362 the State sustained a loss of Ri.56,500/- over the sale of food supplies to the public. This was caused by the State selling certain commodities at less- ^ - (VtfJ than cost price and also by being obliged at times to sell foodstuffs before the costs were ascertained. The sum of Is.60,000/- has been provided to cover similar eventualities in 1363. In the past Departmental expenses such as stationery, furniture etc, for all Government Departments were shown in a separate budget heading. In the new budget these expenses have been divided among the Departments concerned. In the Budget for 1362 the amount spent by the Govern- ment on the food supplies which it held at the end of the year was shown as a Suspense Account. This year a new account has been opened for Food Supplies on a commercial basis and the amount which had been spent by the Gove mm ait at the end of 1362 is shown as an advance^to that account against purchase of foodstuffs. The sum outstanding at the end of 1362 was approximately 14 lacs, normally this sum would have been added to the Reserve Fund and would have produced an income of Fuj.42,000/-. In addition the State has provided for/possible; loss of Ks.60,000/- by the skle of foodstuffs apart from the cost of administering £ Food Control. S.Z.'h 8th February 19^. D.O.No.C/292. tVould it be possible for you to let ne have the detailed budget of the Electri city Department, the Educational Department, the Medical Department, and the Public Works Department to enable me to fulfil Sir Geof frey^ request for my comments on the State /^L C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain.r D.0.No.C/354. f Xbi Political Agency, Bahrain, 24th February 19^±4i My dear Belgrave, Please refer to my demi-official letter No.C/292 dated 3th February 1944. 2. When may I expect to have the detailed budgets of the different departments? Yours sincerely * ///tfr/ 1 '' C. Dalrymple Belgrave, 3sq. , C.B.F.., Adviser to the Government, Bahrain.A IVu.D. Budget. Rs. 46^00 Pay of P.;».D. Staff including allowances Provident ?und 5 leave passages. Pay of persons and animals employed at Raffa wells IQfo of State Engineer’s salary and allowances to municipal Secretaries bn account of work done for the Government Stationery and drawing materials Upkeep of P.^.D. vehicles Contingencies 's. 33,400 3,400 2,200 2,0 JO 4,0u0 GoO 45,GOO.T3C HITICAL JGIiQOL. Rs. 60,000. Staff: Salaries and allowances. Maintenance allov/ance of students. Hostel fees for 12 students. Transport. Clothing. New tools and plant. Materials used in training. Stationery, books etc. Timber, metals etc., recoverable from sales. Power and fuel. Gaiae s. Contingencies. 37,000. 2.500. 2,160. 900. 750. 5.000. 1.000. 1.500. 8,000. 300. 250. 1,200 . 60,560. b &amp; The salaries and allowances includes one Principal, three Syrian teachers and a possible two new Syrian teachers, one local teacher and two workmen instructors.COHFIDENTIrtL Political Agency, D.O.No.C/390. Bahrain, 28th February 1944. r My dear Belgrave L \ Please refer to your demi-official letter No.418-^1 dated 24th February 1944. 2. Education . (a) Technical School . I notice in the details of the Technical School budget which you have sent me that there is no mention of any income whereas in your State budget you show an income of 8,000 rupees under Technical School (item No.6 (c)). The detailed Technical School budget amounts to Rs.60,560 whereas item 3(f) of the State budget is Rs.60,000. (b) Bovs 1 Schools . No revenue has been shown in the detailed budget whereas items 6 (a) and (b) of the State budget show a revenue of Rs. 11,000. 3. Public Works Department . No revenue is shown in the detailed budget nor have any of the details been provided of items 10 (a), (b) and (c) of the State budget. 4. Electric Supply Department . Telephones, and A.C. Unit sections are budgeted to run at a loss. This does not appear to be sound finance. 5. Public Health . No mention of the Rs.65,000 which is anticipated will be received from fees during the year is made in the detailed budget. I shall very much like to discuss these points and one or two others arising out of the State budget at a time con venient to yourself in the near future. Yours sincerely C. Dalrymple Be^rave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. /itcc::7iD3: T Ti.-a. 2 : 0 . 147-S . Bri t i sh He si d en cy one u la te - den er a Bushir e, the 24th Fetruaiy 19 44. 2. It ia requested that the Bahrain Government Budget for the year 1363 together with a copy of the Adviser*8 detailed notes on it and your detailed comments may kindly be forwarded to this office before the pat. April 1944. 3d. GSCWlim BUCK. Bolitical H^sident in the Be r si an Gulf. ATTB3TAD. for Becretary to the Bolitical Hesi^er.t in the lersian Gulf.D.O.No.C/457. Political Agency, Bahrain, 11th March, 1944. My dear Belgrave, I shall be very glad'if you could let me have the information which you promised at our discussion of the subject matter of ay demi-official letter I T o.C/390 of the 23th of February 1244 as I have to report to oir Geoffrey before the 1st of April. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.3.E. Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Yours sincerely, s /{f. rtf $The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to ; Major T. Hickinbothar,, O.B.T?.. H. B. U T s political A^ont, Baiirai n. and has the honour to send him -ar-copy - .of the undermentioned documents. Advisers Office, Manamah, Bahrain. No - /bSF Dated:— March 14, 1944. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. Reference to previous correspondence 1. P.A '3 D.O.No.C/390 dated 28th February 1944. 2. P.A f s D.O.No.c/457 dated 11th March 1944.2/ HOT !] ON BUDGET FIGURES P/.7.D. NFV/ \m%3 . The following are the particulars of new works for which allocation has been made, however owi’;- to lacn materials it is highly improbable that item No. 2 will be undertaken 1. Additions to Naim Dispensary. 2. New Womens Dispensary in Moharraq in place of hired house. 3. Dhobi Ghat at Naim. 4. Additional rooms in Teclinical School. 5. Re-surfacing, leveling and oiling Mene Road. This has not been done before and is a new work. 6. Additions to various schools. 7. Stable at Fort. 8. Maintenance of Roads and bridges. 9. Upkeep and repairs to Government buildings. 10. Completion of Jida Jail. 11. New Motor vehicles. Ri. 1,000 23,000 2,000 3,000 10,000 10,000 3,500 25,000 25,000 5,500, 18,000, n*. 1,25,000, TFLNPH0NF3. Running Expenses last year were Ei.10,700/-. Estimated expenditure for 1363 is 1*. 15,000/- which includes cost of a supply of new dry cells for which ms.2,000/- is included. An additional m. 1,000/- has been added to running expenses to cover higher cost of materials and extra repairs to old material now in use. A. C. UNITS. These have shown a loss during the last three years. As they form a part of the whole electric concern the loss can be set against the profit which is made from sale of energy. The account of A. C. Units was shown separately on the recommendation Ofthe Bahrain Petroleum Company Committee which advised the Bahrain Government on the method of accounting in the Electric concern. K h3DICAL RECBIPT3 . Total receipts for 1362 were shownas ..*.69,000/-, ..*.55,000/- from Service patients and R*. 14,000/- shown as general fees. The latter item included B*. 7,600/- received from Services on account of 1361 also general f ees.No,0/525. Political Agency f Bahrain, the 23rd March 1944. From Major T. Hickinbotham,C.I.E. f O.B.K., Political Agent, Bahrain To The Hon'blo the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. ■ © Sir, 1 have the honour to enclose couios of;- (a) The Bahrain Government Budget estimatos for the year 1363. &amp; (b) An explanatory note on the budget by the Adviser to t the Bahrein Government. y'\o / Cc) A further note on the budget figures by the Adviser which was compiled at my repuest. 2. General Conservative officials when budgetting have a tendency to under estimate revenue figures and to over estimate expendi ture figures. Provided this tendency is kept within reasonable limits no h^-rm is done but when the difference between antici pated expenditure and revenue,and actual expenditure and revenue is great one of the principal objects of a budget is defeated. In my opinion the Adviser, who is responsible for the preparation of the Bahrain State Budget, has been too cautious in his budget for 1363 and the revenue figures are not a reason able forecast of what can be expected from the various sources of revenue from which the State obtains its money. On the expenditure side a false impression of the amount required to run the State Department# is given by including projects in the budget which it is almost certain will never be carried out, in seme cacea owing to the impossibility of obtaining materials and in some cases owing to the difficulty of obtaining skilled /persons --2 /^v /v, \ A^Us ' Qy ^ via/ persons to fill Government appointments* 3* Revenue There are three items on the revenue side of the budget which merit attention. They are$- (a) Customs Receipts (b) Judicial Receipts (c) School Fees. (a) The actuals for last year (13€2) under the head 'Customs** iSuu amounted to Re• 13 f 96 f 500 which the Adviser only budgeted to receive fc«6)10 f 000. During the present financinl year the Adviser hns budgeted to receive rs*8 t 60,000| apparently anticipating a decrease on last year* s actuals of fe.5,36,500. As the import duty is levied on the value of the goods imported and not on the quantity and as • no reasonable person can expect any substantial decrease in prices during the coming twelve months, in fact everything Indicates a further rise in prices, and as at the same time the quantity of Imports has already decreased to what must be considered as the barest minimum it is reasonable to suppose that last year’s actuals will be maintained. Therefore to budget for a 38*3 fall in revenue is unnecessarily cautious. (b) The budget caters for a reduction in the Judicial revenue amounting to fo.34,500 and the Adviser has stated in his explanatory note that this reduction will be due to a decrease in fines because he assumes that there will be a decrease in smuggling activities and food control offences. I rogret I cannot find myself in agreement with the Adviser on this point for in my opinion the greater the scarcity of material and the highdr the prices in surrounding countries where price control has not been as successful as in Bahrain the more probable it is that smuggling will increase. Human nature being what it is and prices being That they are 1 do not for one moment believe that offences against food control regu- latlons will be any less in 1363 then they were in 1362. At the same time it Is reasonable to assume that the efficiency of the police in bringing smugglers and profiteers to trial will not /deteriorate .3 deteriorate during the coming year and that the judges will thus have the opportunity to maintain their high standard of fines. (c) Tichool fees| item 6 (b) of the budget, are shown os baing only %.4,300 during' tho year while the expenditure on education is .2,64,OCX). Those school fees are tho only contribution towards non-tochnicol education paid by tho people of Bahrain. i^xpanditui^a There is of course a general rise in expenditure which tho Adviser has in »ny opinion rightly ascribed to increases in war allowances and other causes brought about by the unsettled state of the world in general. 1 find little to criticise outside the State Knglneer's Department but I think it right to draw attention to tho amount which tho Bahrain Govornment is paying for tho Special Police. The role of the Special Police has been described in tho Advisor^ note which forms an enclosure to this letter but ho has in no way stressed the fact that they should be considered at least in part as a contribution towards the cost of the var by the Gov or run on t of Bahrain. It is true that they are employed in safeguarding thj principal source of the State’s revenue. It Is equally true that oil is of vital importance and that if His Highness had taken the line that ho was in no way responsible for tho war and that the liability for toe guarding of the Refinery and Oil Field should therefore devolve on His Majesty’s Government we should heve boon faced with tho unpleasant duty of either forcing the Shaikh to mactiMg toss expenditure or mooting It ourselves. I think it fair to consider at least half of this expenditure as a contribution from the Bahrain Government to His Majesty’s Government for toe prosecution of too war. 6. State Krifllnoor’s Department . (a) I still do not understand why too Shaikh Hamad Bridge /whichwhich appears \o me to fee a public work and is in fact the principal public work in the Islands should be administered by the State Bngineer and not by the P.W.D. and I have been unable to obtain a satisfactory explanation of this phenomenon. It would be surprising if it were in any other department to see that no depreciation has been charged on the structure for the past two years• (b) I have been unable to obtain a satisfactory explanation Service are consistently run at a loss. To budget for a loss when it is unnecessary is bad finance especially when the deficit balance the expenditure. As it is at the moment people who are not sufficiently fortunate to own a telephone or an air conditioning unit subscribe to provide their more fortunate brethren with tele phones and the employees of the Bahrain Government, with air has prepared/satisfactory budget which is expected not only to cover expenditure but to produce what for the fifth year of the war must be considered as a very satisfactory surplus. from the Adviser why the Telephones Service, and the Air Conditioner; can be expunged perfectly simply by increasing the charges to conditioners. 6. In conclusion I think a reasonable comment on the budget for 1363 is that the A4viser, although too conservative in outlook, a I have the honour to be, Sir, Your nest obedient servant Political Agent, Bahrain.No. 523-3 c 0 f i d e n r i a l '■?(■ ll'itl£h P.esi.Joricv &amp; Consulate General, ' Buahire, the 3rd June 1G44. Frora To The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSIIIRE \. K A^. , The Secretary to the Gpvernment of India, In the External Affairs Department, NEW DELHI ,: v Copy to:- Political Agent, BAHRAIN . (5 BA^mAin 3TATS 3JDGEI f’ J / \ I JEtiOKAIIDUa ^ ^ ^ *.u Reference Residency letter No. 146-b dated the 24th F ° b 2^ ar ^opy 4 ls enclosed of letter No. C/G25, dated the 23rd March 1944 from tile Political Agent, Bahrain, a nd of its enclosures. , , . .. ^ 3. I agree with the opinion expressed by the Political Agent in paragraph 6 of his letter. Sd. GEOFFREY PRIOR. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED fjtfr^Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.wmimuk- No. C/135. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Shiraz, The 12th August, 1§44. Prom CoaiiantiaL BAHRAIN RECEIPT, ■NaP-ibS- /VV ' The Hc^ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. To The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi• BAHRAIN BVPQfiXt laSS .V mmmm- ^ Reference External Affairs Depeirtment letter No. D.6958-ME/44, dated the 5th July, 1944. ~ 2. Steps are being taken to bring the comments contained in paragraphs 2, 3 and 5 of the Political Agent, Bahrain*s letter No. C/525, dated the 23rd March, 1944, to the notice of the Bahrain Government. It is not, however, considered advisable to communicate to the Bahrain Government the views expressed in paragraph 4 of that letter as that Government fire of opinion that the cost of the Special Police should be met by His Majesty's Government. No objection is seen to the points mentioned in the Political Agent's report of 24th December, 1943 to which attention has been drawn being commended to the Bahrain Government and action to this end is being taken. Sd./ GEOFFREY PRIOR. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ATTESTED . od«/ J• Craning« for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf..rded To Ihe Joint Secretary to the OOTemment of India in the fixternal Affaire Department* The Hon f ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bpshire. Dated Hew Delhi, the July 1944. Subject: Bahrain Budget, 1363* SlX, p r) 4JL I am directed to acknowledge receipt of your letter ho. 523-3, dated the 3rd June 1944, and enclosures, and to say that the Government of India have noted your agreement with the opinion expressed by the political Agent, Bahrain, in paragraph 6 of his letter Ro.C/525, dated the 23rd fercn 1944* They would, however, be glad to kndk whether steps have been or are being taken to bring the ooazBonts contained in paragraphs 2 to 5 of his letter to the notice of the Bahrain Government in a suitable manner* They also note that the criticisms made by the Political Agent in Section I and paragraphs 4 and 5 of Section III (Bxpenditure) of his report on the budget for 1362 ( yiie enclosure to your letter R0.146-S, dated 24th Pfeoruary 1944) equally apply to the current budget, and would be glad to know whether you see any objection to these points also being commended to the Bahrain Government: it is considered that if this is not done the value of suoh comments is greatly reduced* 2* Copies of your letter with enclosures, the political Agent, Bahrain f s report on the budget for 1362 dated 24th Roveaber 1943, and this letter are being sent to the India Office* I have the honour to be. Sir. your most obedient servant. (SD:) R.R. BURNETT. Joint Secretary to the Government of India* JUHti-’C-MflDRWl’IAL Political Apen^y, Bahrain, loth September 1944. i!0 .&lt;'/l.';l23. Major T, Hi^kllbothara, ^.1.5., PoiltiAai Agont, Bahrain* The Advlaor to the Bahrain Goveriimont i Bahrain. MKuAiy BUDGLI 1 liavo the honour to inform you that 1 have boen directed by t-he Government of India to forward tho following; obsorvationa ^ ,U 1 4„ . rq u on tho Bahrain buctKatn for 1362 and 1363. 1* Bahrain Budflot 1362 , filg-^triral Vwx\rxp qi\x&gt; Tho a^^ounts of tho Banraln Rla&lt;? j^lral Dopartu;ont and tho budget lor the Bahrain Etootrioal DGoartujoiit wore kept separate from tho State budget and the Stnte a^rounta* Thia la not ^on- aidored to be the oorreot procedure as the assets of the Sle^tribal Department should be shovui ss State assets and the Department should be budgeted for in exe^tXy the a&amp;me as other departments (b) ^ bUr* xorks Ibe^rtmant Xt Is considered that tiie Public Works Dopartment should b€ a major heading and should Include 'Upkeep of Kouda and Government Buildings', n the Shailch Uamad Bridge' f and 'Public ; orks - Kew Buildings'* The department should be shown cn the revenue side of the budget ao veil os on the expenctiaire side* In view of the fa^t that the aatnirip&amp;liiiea are responsible amountiiv; to is*31,000 ere ovide by the Government to sissist them in Afirrv^in/ cut Uu..3 vork it is dosirrbxs for the muni-ipa! budgeto to be shown in the Annual v©ports* w w (c) Itefn No.10 under '5xi&gt;enditure' is incorrectly worded for no contribution is made for the 'Heiief of tho Poor' although it for the upkeep of their own roads end ^cvjxtz to u’x.i-ipslities /isif tru«i Xhxit th© Bahrain Oovcrnmant do diatribute food to the poor. It is suggested thnt the heeding should be 'Eaer/^en^y V.er Poor Itelief' T to Indicate clearly that the raensure Is of a tymoorary nature. \'&gt; &lt;P IX. Bota’P in th id^ot - 1363. (fc) Gon&lt;jrcI $/ It l« oonsidortd thf.t undu« caution hns been shov/n in the forecast of the revenue figures for 1363 end that in the expendi ture eide the in^luaion of various project# rhi^h will, oniet elaoet certainly never be carried out, owing to the difficulty of obtaining ■atcriale and tisane* gives a misleading improsslon of the amount roouirec to run the State Deoartmnntr.. (b) Knyonue ^ u^tc ^is fho actuals for the year 3.362 under this head amounted to &amp;• 13)96*500 while the anticipated receipts fimounted to only fe.6*10,000. in the present financial year the vState anticipate a revenue of li.#8*60*000, Uheit is, K&gt;.5 ? 3G,60C loss than waa received last year. In view of the fact that iranorts have already decreased to a ftlnlioum .and thnt thorn are indications uhnt yi^i^ea nay be oxpectod to incroaaa rtitl ftirtnor* to btidgot for ,*5 38 percent fall in revenue fro/s Import duty, which ±a loviod cn the value of £ool!i iirporcrd md not. on the oivintity, is unnecessarily cautious. (r) ^ylAcAviA • . _ It is not considei'cvi reasonable to allow for *♦ reduction in the judicial revenue amounting tc ft.34*500 due + o a decrease In fines on the arsumption that smuggling mici food control offences will be le^a tlvn in 1362. Indi^atione suggest that the reverse will bo tho 'I'&amp;q for scarcity of an tori?. Is combine&lt;1 with high prices in neighbouring ^ountriOR will tend U) result in an increase in £M»uggling while ha ,r i‘*n ncturo being what it i© no fnllin^; off in the number of offencen n^iast Food Control Regulations -* 0 uld be expected until there is a con/?ldersblB fall in the cri^osi of all coraaodltles. It muet be assumed thst there will bo no deterio ration in the offWan-y cf the police m bringing smugglers or profitoerors to booic nor that the Judges wilt lower their standard \ of flnas. /(d)(jS&gt;) (a) school Foo«. It is notod v&gt;ith aurprioo that while fcho annual •xpanditum on eduction Is fora-nst at lh.4 s W,000 the annual «nti-ipate« ^nu-itoution towards non-ta-hniral odor at ion paid hy the people of Bahrain would appear to bo Ks»4*3G0» (*) 3tato ' K 'Th*» ShniKh Mttiwd Bridge' should movaoipronrir.tely bo adudnia- tarod by the vublir Works Dapurtsjent and not by tin Stata Bnginoer. It is' surprising to note that no depreciation has been rlBirgod on , the ^orvitrnation for t.ho two yoar^ • Tiwro appears to ba no satisfactory explanation why the telephone aorvicc and the air conditioner service are consistently run at n lose when the daficlt can bo Mtoungad by increasing ths cargos to glance the oxpeediture. At prauont the defidt is borne by the general public who use electrical current for lighting ov fans* /cant, ^hratn.Telegram Q. From Political Hesident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 229. Dated the 31st January and received 2nd February, 1945* Is Zakat or land revenue still levied in Bahrain Amount mentioned as land revenue in budget is very small but A1 Khalifa probably do not pay. 2. If levied what is rate per cent, of actual incomeTelegram From Q. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire To No. 83. ^ ' • Dated the 5th February, 1945. Your telegram No. 229 dated January 31st. 2. No zakat or land revenue levied. POLITICALNo. 185-3 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. 0 and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 8th .bruarV fl 1945 Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Government of India Letter No. D. 18261-UE/44 dated 21st December, 1944. Residency letter No. 172-J dated 6th February, 1945. BAHRAIN REPORT 1362. \— I | ■ ■ I JiHGilKT. No. D. 18261-KE/44 From To The Joint Jecretary to the Government of India, in the External Affairs Department, The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ' Dated New Delhi, the 21st December, 1S44 Subject Bahrain Report, 1362 . M: ■ ■ 'k 3ir, I am directed to acknowledge receipt of a copy of the Government of Bahrain’s annual report for the year 1362, and to say that the Government of India have observed with satisfaction the successful manner in which the affairs of Bahrain have been handled during the year under report, which they consider reflects credit on His Highness’ Government and their Adviser. They would* however, invite attention to the fact that the allowances of the Ruling family absorb a proportion of the total revenues of the State which.,, is higher than is generally considered appropriate. It is recalled that in your letter No. C/292^of the 11th July 1^41 you stated that you had sown the seeds for an eventual reduction of the Ruler's share of the oil royalties from one--third to one-fifth, bpt that since the State had all the funds it required the matter was not then being pressed. Although it is recognised that with the increased costs of living now prevailing the present time also may not be regarded as particularly auspicious for urging a reduction in His Highness' Privy Purse, yet the necessity for economy in all directions is likely to be increasingly felt, and the Government of India trust that you will lose no opportunity of impressing upon His Highness the desirability and importance of reducing his personal expenditure and the scale of allowances of his family as soon as this becomes possible. It may be of interest to you to know that, in an Indian State with an annual revenue, Rs. 40 lakhs, current political theory and practice would regard any thing between 10 and 15/ as a fitting and not unreasonable proportion of the total revenue to be allotted to the privy purse; though, if the ruler of such a State asked for advice, it would be suggested to him that he should keep the allotment as near to 10/ as possible. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, / 7 3d/- IV.E RICHARDSON Joint Secretary to the Crovernnent of India.7 CO:IFID^:. T TXAl# No, 17^ S British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, ^ Bushire, the 6th February, 1946• The Hon'ble Sir Geoffrey Prior, K.C.I.E., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E . The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, NEW DEL H I . I have the honour to refer to External Affairs Department Letter No. D. 18261-4E/44 of the 21st^ December, 1944, regarding the Bahrain Report, 1362. 2. I regret to say that I have not yet found time to read this Report, but the facts are well known to me and there is no difficulty in answering the question raised. In the first place consider the present moment most inopportune for suggesting any reduction in the Privy Purse, as it would almost inevitably lead to a request for more money, which His Highness has not so far made, and which might be difficult to refuse. It must be remembered that the Ruling Family in Bahrain now receive almost exactly the same amounts they drew in 1941, although the cost of living has trebled, and, since their financial position has obviously greatly deteriorated they would consider it most inequitable to be asked at this stage to exist on smaller stipenas. 3. I would also deprecate analogies being drawn from Indian States and applied to the Persian Gulf, where they have little real relevance. Colonel Barrett, who was a very experienced Political Officer with Arabs, stated in 1927 or 1928 when the late Shaikh Hamad was making one of his periodical demands for money, that the A1 Khalifah considered that the revenues of the State belonged to them, and that any portion they surrendered for the use of the administration must be regarded as an act of grace. This position still exists in Kuwait, with which the Bahrain Family could appro priately compare themselves, and also in Saudi Arabia to whom, and not to an Indian State, their eyes would naturally turn. It is impossible to move very far in advance of public opinion in these States, and so far as I know the handsome allowances paid to the Al Khalifah are regarded rather as a tribute to our administrative ability than an oppression which should be alleviated I In fact, if I were to attempt to reduce the allowances now, there is not the slightest doubt that I should be accused of starving the Ruling From To Sir, U ’~9Family, and that widespread indignation would be aroused* 4. Finally, the proportion quoted in the above mentioned letter requires some examination* Any officer on the internal side and especially one who has been on foreign service in a State, is well aware that a paper Privy Purse of 10 or 16 per cent of the Revenue is a very different figure in actual practice unless the Finance Officer and the Accountant General are both servants of the Government of India. Then, in an Indian State the main source of income is land revenue, which is levied at an exceptionally high rate, and it is only reasonable that the Ruling Family should content themselves with 10 or 16 per cent of it. In Bahrain, however, the position is entirely different There is no land revenue or zakat, and the main source of revenue contributed by the public is a very light customs duty. As is well known, their wealth arises from their mineral possessions, and in ensuring that only one third of thin falls into the hands of the Ruling Family, I feel that a very great deal has already been achieved* In actual fact there is no shortage of money vdiatever 1n Bahrain and the real problem is not as it formerly how to save money, but the happier one of spending it wisely* Your most obedient servant, 3D/- GEOFFREY PRIOR Political Resident, Persian Gulf'W' GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. No. of 1364 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 10th R/Awal, 1364 February 22, 1945. From C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.3., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. To His Britannic Majesty»s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to enclose, for your information, three copies of the Budget of the State for the year 1364. A summary of the Budget of the Fleotricity Supply Department has been included below the State Budget. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the Government. 3nc 1Confidential The political Agency, No.C/313 Bahrain-, the 3rd March 1945. To * - The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. O. V ' Memorandum Reference your letter No. 503-21, ! ated 22nd F-hruary 1945, forwarding the Bahrain State Budget for the year 1364. 2. I shall be grateful if you will furnish the usual explanatory note on the Budget. (* if/,, Political Agent, Bahrain.A. y i i % - 1I0TJ OTT TrliC 1364 BUDGET, The estimat ^ receipts for the year 1364 amount to 4^ laKhs| the e?tinates for expenditure amount to Rs. .&gt; • lakhs and an excesv^ of revenue over expenditure of 10 lakhs is anticipated which will he added to the Reserve Fund. REV.JUJE . Oil 27 lakhs. !• '-Che actual receipts n rom oil royalty in 1303 ’v ere Rs.07,00,00C/-; for 136^ royalties ape estimated at fo lakhs. There seems no re^pon to suppose that the outputBahrain oil will, decrease during 1364. The oil concession provides for a revision o^ the royalty payment hut the time ^or this revision is still compa- ^atively distant. 2. Customs Receipts, Rs.15,60,000/-. Customs Receipts produced Rs.20,40,000/- in 1565. In the budyet for that year they were underestimated. .rk if e^ence o Rs.4 ,' m 0,000/— has been all owed between the 1565 actuals and the 1364 Budget expectation. The 1563 actuals included certain payments on account imports during 1362 and in view of the lowering prices of piece goods in India it is likely that duties on these goods will decrease. 3. Interest on Reserve, Rs.3,20,000/-. This represents the income from the State Reserve Fund which is invested, in Government India stock a nd. British Saving Bonds. Medical Receipts, Rs. 43,000/-. The actuals for 1363 were Rs. 56,000/-, most &gt;f thip came from Service patients fees. The establishment 0 * other service medical facilities in Bahrein is likely to reduce the number of patients.copt of oooks and materials has increased considerably and a second religious school, under the direction of the Sunni Kadis has been opened. , 3. Public Health, Rs. 4,72,000/-. Provision lias been made for a number of nurses whom it is hoped may be obtained during the year. At present the hospital is understaffed. The price of all drugs and appliances are higher than before and the cost of feeding patients has risen considerably. 6 . Defence and Protection, Rs.P,00,000/-. The heavy increase in the expenditure on the Police arm 1 Naturs is due to the high rise in their pay which came into force at the beginning of the year. A certain pro portion of this expenditure including the Special Police, the provision for British Police and part of the natur force can be regarded as war time measures. 7. Public Works, Rs.1,95,000/-. Provision has beer made for a full Public Works Department staff though at the end of 1365 only a skeleton staf° existed. The grant ^or upkeep of roads a nd buildings has been increased. 7. Municipalities, Rs.87,000/-. The contribution by the Oovernmait to each Munici pality has been increased by Rs. 12,000/- per annum. 11. Agriculture. It is proposed to extend the Government garden at Budeya d irinr the coming year and funds have beer- allowed to cover the cost of fencing ard labour. The other expenditure head ings do not seem to require any particular comment or explanation..ieeeltai'ieous. Ur/ler the handing in 1363 was includec’ the price obtained by sale of some cattle belonging to the Govern ment, sale of some surplus Police rations to the Pood Gontrol Department and ca sum of Rs. 56,000/- refunded to the Bahrain Government from the Pood Control Depart ment against a loss amounting to this sum which was sus tained in 1362. B XPBITDITURB . 1. Allowances to the Ruling Family, Rs.13,20,000/-. This expenditure comprises one t’ ird of the estimated oil royalty and tae Civil List, which is a fixed amount. Pensions are shown separately as the persons who receive payments under ''Pensions” are not members of the Ruling Family. 2 . State Departments, Rs.3,03,000/-. In the estimates for Customs and La 2 nd Departments provision has been made for sane additional sta^^. 3. Judicial, Rs.96,000/-. Provision has been made for two additional Kadis to fill vacancies in the Shera Courts. 4. Educa tion, Rs.4,19,000/-. There is an increase of approximately one lakh in the cost of Eg ucation. In the boys' schools provision has been made for the pay o^ the new Egyptian teachers for twelve montus as well as for higher rates in pay to many or the local teachers. The second primary school which started in Manama last year was not open during the whole year, the cost of this is now included in the Budget. In tue girls schools some new Syrian teachers have been employed and a new school was started in Manama. The5. Land Revenue, Rs.31,000/-. In estimating the land revenue r -it less than in land prices obtaining during 1363 an? the improba bility of the land boom lasting. 6 . Education Receipts, Rs.19,000/-. A decrease o*' Rs. 1, nOO/— has been all ov/ed under It appears unlihely that the demand ^or motor drivers will assume the large proportion that it has reached in recent years and no new cars are being imported by the public, it therefore seems probable that revenue from this source will decrease. R ; Passport Receipts, Rs.10,000/-. A large number of new Bahrain passports were-issued during tee second half of 1363 which raised the income from this source above the normal amount. 9. Judicial Receipts, Rs.20,000/-. Important civil cases are more and more infrequent, possibly owing to the prosperity in the country and fewer fines were collected in 1363 than in 1362. Judicial Receipts are estimated at Rs.13,000/- less than was collected in 1363. 10. Bridge Tolls, Rs.20,000/-. The possibility of a revision in the scale of c harges for military vehicles has been taken into account in estimating this revenue at Rs.26,000/- less than the actuals of 1363. 1363 consideration has been given to the abnormal * 7. Vehicle Taxes, etc., Rs.25,000/-CONFIDENTIAL No. C/393. Bahrain, the 21st March, Political Agency, From Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.S., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain To The Hon»ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir I have the honour to enclose a copy of the Bahrain ' $ n t /'■J /-v ^ f~\ m 4- n-r *1 A TT »^ ^ ^ W a ^ » ' State Budget for the year 1364 A.H* which corresponds to 1945 A.D. and a brief note on the aforesaid budget by the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. and solely to save a certain sum of money and has made his estimates accordingly without due regard to the urgent needs of the state and the necessity for forward planning to meet post war conditions. The budget is an uninspiring document. The ,, note , ‘ which is correctly described as brief throws but little light on the reasons for the reduction in the estimates and for the increases forecast in the expenditure. What stands out above everything else is the extra-ordinary fact that the state haw^succeeded in * saving no less than Rs. 13,92.000 during the 5th year of the world war and this in spite of very considerable increases in expenditure. Almost as astounding is the Adviser^ forecast for a saving of Rs. 10,00,000 on the working of the present year. With the sum which has become available for transfer to the Reserve Fund as a result of last year's credit balance the amount now to the credit of the Bahrain Government in British and Indian Government stock has reached the satisfactory figure of Rs. 1,01,18,947. I feel strongly that the policy of saving at the expense of the well-being of the population and the material progress of the state which has been followed in the last three Bahrain Government budgets is neither reasonable nor correct. It is true that owing to war conditions materials for building and other purposes have not been available, but unfortunately it is equally true that there is a tendency to cloak inertia wich the excuse that progress is impossible owing to war conditions. Not only can progress be made at the present time but plans can be thought out for post-war expansion and estimates can be worked out for improvements which will be profitable to the people and financially advantageous to the State. Unfortunately I see no sign of any desire on the part of the Bahrain Government to improve living and working conditions in the country rather they incline more and more to the unhealthy accumulation of a large reserve. 3. On the 'Receipt' side of the Budget the principal item is of course the 'Royalty' from oil exported by the. Bahrain petroleum Company and I am in agreement with the Adviser that there is no reason to suppose that there will be any diminution in revenue from this source. 2 It would seem that the Adviser has budgeted simply-2- has budgeted for a decrease in customs receipts amounting to approximately Rs. 4,80,000 on the grounds that it is probable that the price of commodities will fall during the present year with a corresponding reduction in the amount of tax recoverable, and because certain payments were received in 1363 for goods which were in fact im ported in 1362. Although it is not possible to judge the effect of this last item, as the figures have not been disclosed, it is probable that there will be a falling off in revenue during the present year and the Adviser is probably correctly cautious. I cannot agree that a reduction of Rs. 23,550 in the receipts from M Land Revenue'' is reasonable. I should have been inclined myself to have estimated for at least as much as was received in 1363 especially in view of the Air developments which are known to the Adviser and to myself. The small reduction in the 'Educational' receipts is not in the least justified for with an increase in educational facilities in Bahrain, in particular on the female side, the Adviser should expect to receive an increased return for the outlay and the budget estimate for 1364 should be greater than the actuals for 1363. I consider the large reduction in the estimate for this year compared with the actuals for last year under 'Vehicle Taxes and Driving Licences' is not justified for the indications are that the activities of the Oil Company will bo continued and that as soon as the construction work of the refinery has ceased the export of some 50,000 tons of surplus coke will be embarked upon and thus all available transport will be employed. Nor is there any reason to suppose that new Bahrain passports will not be issued 'during the present year with a consequent decrease in the income from 'Passport Receipts'. 'judicial Receipts' have been reduced by a considerable amount without, in my opinion, adequate reason, for it is impossible to forecast what civil suits will be instituted and estimates should normally be based on averages for previous years nor is it wise to indulge in the- annual wish that every body will be better behaved in the new year and therefore the magistrates will not have to inflict such heavy fines as they did in the old year. Jhere would be more chance of this dream coming true if the judiciary would inflict larger and more adequate fines than is their present practice. It is true that the question of 'Bridge Tolls' is under consideration but even if the proposal for a fixed monthly contribution put forward by the Royal Air Force is accepted by the Bahrain Government it is possible that there will be no diminution in the receipts. In fact if the present system of charges is reasonable,/such is the contention of the Bahrain Government, then there should be no reason to anticipate a fall in revenue. 4. On the 'Expenditure' side I have no comments to make on the allowances tt&gt; the Ruling Family and I con sider that an increase in the staff of the customs Department is long over due, but I am puzzled by the considerable increase in the forecast, for the 'Land Department' which is not explained by the Adviser and in view of the anticipated reduction in revenue from this source seems scarcely justifiable. There is also no explanation for the additional grants in the first /1 hr e e....three items under the heading 'judicial” and for the Rs. 15,000 increase in the cost of the Technical school. This last item is the more difficult to follow if one has been privileged to read the superintendents annual report for 1944 in which he endeavours to explain a falling off of nearly 50^ in the number of students attending the institution. Nor is there any explanation for the increase in the expenditure on the hostel under 'Education”, and the decrease in the amount which it is intended shall be spent on expansion and higher education. The public Works Department has been granted an additional amount of Rs. 43,000 over the actual expenditure for the previous year, but nevertheless I am of the opinion that this Department is being starved. The roads in Manama vand Muharraq are in a shocking condition ana at least Rs. 1,00,000 should be spent immediately on their improve ment before they become so bad that the cost of repairs will be even more costly. The road across the shaikh Hamad Bridge and Causeway is in a disgraceful condition in spite of the fact that a sum of no less than Rs. 66,000 was obtained last year from tolls levied on this road. I should be surprised to learn that the Bahrain Governraent had spent as much as Rs. 5,000 on the upkeep of this road during the past twelve months. Many of the Government buildings are in a sorry state and I feel that budget provision should have been made for the purchase of materials should they become available during the present financial year. There is ample paint available in the towns but no attempt is made to apply it to the sun blistered wood of the public offices or to repaint the road signs which are no longer decypherable. I note that the contributions by the Government to the two municipalities of Manamah and Muharraq have been increased by Rs. 12,000, but there is no indication in the Adviser*s note of the purpose of this grant or of why the increase has now become justifiable, nor is there any indication of why the 'Unforeseen' should leap from Rs. 3,000 last year to Rs. 10,000 this year. 5. The Electricity Department is budgeting to save Rs. 27,500 on the present year's working, but there is. no indication that any budget provision has been made by this department for the cost of the new generating engine which it is expected will arrive from the United Kingdom during the next two or three months, provision does not appear to have been made for the very extensive renewal and replacement of machinery, appliances, and installation equipment which is long over due. I note that the 'Telephone' section is still being run at a considerable loss in spite of the suggestions which were made to the Bahrain Government on their budget last year. I suppose that in view of the inefficiency of the present system and the general and justified dissatisfaction of the public the time was not considered opportune to increase charges for this service. It would seem from the loss under 'Air-conditioning' that the general public are still expected to contribute indirectly to the comfort of a few selected officials of the Bahrain Government. 6. I am taking this opportunity to put forward my views on what I consider should be the present and future 1 /policy/I -4- r ^ u ^ policy of the State, views which I regret to say are not in accord with the present practice of the Bahrain Govern ment. ’’Forward” should be the watch word of the adminis tration and a policy designed to prepare the way for post war development must be introduced forthwith, plans must be thought out, advanced orders placed for essential mate rials, and provision for an adequate staff made so that no time will be lost in putting into execution at the earliest possible moment the many works the lack of which has delayed the development of these islands. The Bahrain Government should take immediate steps to obtain the services of a qualified liluropean Engineer for the public works Department and having obtained such a person he should be required to prepare with the aid of an adequate staff accurate town plans of Manama and of Muharraq with a view to wonting out an improvement scheme to include the widening of the present narrow thorough fares, the provision of proper communication lines through the town, and the preservation of likely business and residential areas for the purpose for which they are best suited. He should also undertake the adequate and imme diate repair of all the roads for the upkeep of which the Bahrain petroleum Company are not responsible, and as materials become available the reconstruction of the public offices, markets, and lavatories. The possibility of introducing a water borne sewage system should be investigated and if practicable incroduced as and when funds can be allotted and materials procured. 7. The Electrical Engineer is over-worked and required to do various tasks which should never have been allotted to him. An assistant should be obtained as soon as possible and should, in my opinion, be a young man who would be pre pared to worK for two years as assistant with a view to taking over as Electrical Engineer for a further period of two years after which his contract should be terminated and the then assistant promoted in his turn. Not only is an assistant engineer required but also an adequate staff of mechanics, fitters, air-conditioning experts, and garage hands for at present the power house and installa tions are ludicrously understaffed and as far as I am aware no attempt has been made to recruit suitable per sonnel nor nas any budget provision been made for such a purpose. The future will see a tremendous demand for air-conditioning and if the Bahrain Government do not produce an efficient and adequate supply of electric power and lighting current they will find that private enterprises will import their own units. The present power plant is antiquated and inadequate and the new electrical engineer should be required to carry out a survey immediately of the power plant ana electrical equipment and he should be instructed to make recommendations for a new plant designed to meet future demands for electric current for lighting and energy and also for a reasonable generating reserve to enable proper servicing to oe carried out. Once the survey has been completed a firm of Consulting Engineers should be asked to give their views on what machinery should be installed and advike on to what manufacturers should be given the contract for the provision of and installation of the equipment. The Consulting Engineers themselves would, no doubt, provide a skilled engineer to watch the interests of the Bahrain Government during the erection of the plant.ka I believe it will be £.2(X) &gt; 000 from the present state Reserve for this pur pose, but I feel that the yield from this re-investment will silence the most pessimistic critic. What is more important still is that state funds instead of being at the disposal of a Corporation or Government for a very inadequate return will be profitably employed for the improvement of the living conditions of the people of the State. Air-conditioning is essential in the Persian Gulf and the Bahrain Government should be planning the provi sion of adequate air-conditioning facilities for their own staff and possibly the installation of large units for the air-conditioning of groups of private residential houses. It would be to the Bahrain Government»s advantage to get in touch with some reputable firm of manufacturers ^ of air-conditioning units with a view to inviting an expert to visit' the islands and advise on a policy for the f u tur e. o 8. Bahrain must be prepared to meet possible competition from neighbouring ports especially the new Saudi Arabian port of Has '^anura. The best and only way to do this is for the customs Department to make this port more attractive than others by providing better and cheaper facilities and a more efficient and less officious administration than possible competitors. I should like to see the present Customs pier enlarged to nearly twice its size at the land end, and extended to the deep water lying two hundred yards to the north of the present pier-head. Large and convenient Customs sheds should be erected on the west side of the town r' end of the pier and they should be available on payment of rent .to merchants for the storage of bonded goods. New re-export procedure and regulations should be introduced and merchants should be encouraged to bring their goods to Bahrain by being granted special facilities whereby goods could be kept for any length of time and then re-exported to neighbouring markets without loss to the owner. I should like to see the present rule whereby the importer is ^ required to pay full customs duty on goods which he has declared as 'Re-export' on import should he fail to re-export them within a period of t?Tanty days altered to enable cargo to enter Bahrain to the bonded warehouses free of customs duty the only charges leviable being the usual porterage and harbour dues plus the cost of the rental of the ware housing facilities. Before however any large expenditure is embarked upon it would be advisable to consider the relative merits of the Sitra and Manamah anchorages and the possibility of the construction of a wharf at the former alongside which ocean going steamers could discharge and load. 9. The possibility of constructing a light railway from Hanamah to the Bahrain petroleum Company's premises at Awali and Sitra shall be investigated. Such an innova tion would undoubtedly be to the benefit of the wor&amp;ing class population and I see no reason why the Bahrain Petroleum Company, who have been for years and will be for years to come faced with transport problems, should not either under take the installation themselves or agree to give the Bahrain Government such financial guarantees as would ensure that there was a reasonable prospect of profitable working. /10. Lastly.. ... ^ NUoo ^ -p*' 5 5'//^ /o/z10. Lastly I hold the view that the Bahrain Government should give their early consideration to the construction of an up-to-date and cominodious hotel. There is no doubt that for many years to come Bahrain will be a centre for air travel. The introduction of adequate facilities for travellers is long over due, ana i believe that the British Overseas Airways Corporation would consider favourably any reasonable suggestion made to them by the Bahrain Govern ment either that they should undertake a proportion of the construction cost or that they should enter into an agree ment to manage a hotel to be erected by the j3ahrain Govern ment. Possibly they would prefer to guarantee an annual subvention on the Bahrain Government agreeing to reserve a percentage of the accommodation for their passengers I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant Political Agent, Bahrain4/1. Telegram Q. Frora Political Hesident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 534. g&gt;$) Reference our discussions. Please send by mail list of proposals for reconstruct ion in Bahrain State in order of importance. - PRIOR - R.M. I.R. 214.Telegram From To No. 193. Q* Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. Dated the 24th March, 1945. Reference your telegram No. 534 dated March 23rd 2 . I have incorporated proposals in comment on the budget which Chitty will bring over. POLITICAL -li'0 Talegra.u S(Pad). 4/1., Icrii i'/) &gt; ' \ From Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire To No. 199 Dated the 26th March, 1945. T Paragraph No.8 of my letter No.C/393 dated March 21st. 2. Anderson told me privately that Bahrain Petroleum Company were proposing to extend Sitra causeway to provide advise that Bahrain Government be pressed to co-operate so that mail steamers et cetera can use these facilities. It will be necessary to combine this with scheme suggested in my paragraph No*9, Company will welcome co-operation of Bahrain Government in both schemes. four deep-water berths for ocean going steamers. Strongly POLITICAL - R.MCONFIDENTIAL . No - 4I5-S. ConfidentiaL BAHR \ r r 'EOEIPT. ; 3(?r4.:..'ftS.. I V 4 ,^ The Hon ble tlie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to - The Political Agent, BAHRAIN f a/'' %+■ and lias the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (x). &amp; Persian Gulf Residency, BUSHIRE. Dated..}*?.. tVZ.UJ.??* • Reference to previous correspondence: Bahrain Letter No. C/79?;, dated the Plst March ^945. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Residency Letter No.795-S, dated the ?Oth April 194R. Bahrain State BudgetTTom Ho. d9&amp;-S» !!*• Hoii*bxo bir irior. Political he aidant, Parelftn Gulf, aoyyiDBHTiAL . t er elan (JulT ke aid enoy t Buahiie f the 20th April 1945* To Tko seoret&amp;ry to the Gove rumen t of India in the Sxternal Affairs Department* rar Diaia. Sir, I hare the honour to □r the information of the aovaraxent of India a letter from the Politioal /^ent, Bahrain, regard!the Bahrain State Bui ;«t ?/ith shich I / 1 _ .. M _ A » -• » • ik m. diaousK^d by ray preueoeaisor in his demi-official letter Ho. 883-S dated the 22nd December 1937 it was ualaulnted that the Bahoiiu oil field might be exhausted in 15 yeare. Sight years have now passed and since great dewlopment is still taking piauo 1 feel tixuc we mey oertainly count on a longer life than was originally e»tit»ated and thnt a less conservevdvt finuuai«l policy siioula ue adopted, more especially as the reserve of the State now exceeds IOC 2aKha« 3. I regret that nor other preoaoujatlone prevent me from giving the at^aiilcn to Bahrain affairs that 1 should wish, but it has become clear to me that tha altitude of the Financial jtaris«sr 9 Mr. Belgrade, to any new proposal is unduly cautious. He is still* to my mind, guided by his recollection of hit. early year's In BMhrain when the most rigid economy was sseential and he has failed to adapt himself to the era of abounding prosperity in much he now Unde himself. I was surprised to find, for example, that tiher the last heavy rains occurred in iitduuin ail Uie roads of the Capital beftame impaesable, and still more surprised to eee in his own annual report that persons had urea of starvation in a State with near a half a million pounds in the lank. 4. I reooramaid, therefore, that the Political Agent f e re commend *tl one should be accepted in principle, and that lie should be requested to initiate a more forward policy in the Bahrain State, Since the actual details will depend to some extent upon the materials available and the presence or other wise in aanraia of the Financial Adviser and the Director of Custome a considerable degree of flexibility *111 be necessary. 1 have the honour to be Sir* Your most obedient servant. Sd. aEOFFHBY PRIOR. lolilreal hesiaaat* Persian GulfAyesha should be advised to sell some of her jewel lery. The disgrace which this would bring on the Ruling Family would, he thought, induce Shaikh Salman to act more generously towards her. I communicated this suggestion to Mr. Belgrave who thought this line of approach to the problem would be effectiveythough Shaikha Ayesha might be reluct ant to do anything which would demean herself and the A1 Khalifah. Mr. Belgrave thought that an even better plan might be for Shaikha Ayesha to ask for permission to sell a garden in order to meet her current expenses. Such a request would come before the Khalifah Property Committee of which Mr,Belgrave is a member. He thought the Shaikh might be induced by this means to give Shaikha Ayesha a more generous allowance. '■‘■'he advantage of this approach would be that there would be a chance of achieving the desired end before, rather than after, any public disgrace had been brought on the Ruling Family. 10/12/42. &gt;.Q. A/o.c/m, oL. A/2 if. / i ^ • rf r. n ± 'yrrf. I / Coyy ViAmaA- %VL ^ -Ifc, Me .c/V' *\yl\ , U V /'' 'TuaX?^ *' u *&lt;s 4^, (ty £3 ^&lt;A*n&gt; ■—. /. Z/^/V aA^UJ &amp; 4/ 7 ?Z s &amp; tf4,cb. &lt;, j)^'. iHcA^l Vf~AU^ ^ ^ £ fLyU fustf 1 ' ,t?0 sa^ s^r ^ fcrA&amp;ct.c TyJ- n( ' (0 PA CUy t-fj- ? da(fQ Reference Note above. 1* This amount of Hs• 1,61,825 was not advanced to the Electric Department in a lump sum in any one year, but represents sums paid at various times to me&lt;± the loss incurred by the Department in the early stages, and the cost of additional equipment purchased in 1357 and 1358. 2 . We do not receive the Auditors* Reports. In 1941 the accounts of the Electricity Dept, were examined by a committee from Bapco (at the request of the P.A. and the Adviser) and a report submitted (pi. see page 74, file 6/13-A); I believe that every year the accounts of the Electricity Department are sent to Bapco for examination, in addition to their being audited by the Bahrain Govt, auditors.P. 160 C%x) i/ Reference paragraph 3 of'Political Resist’s confidential letter No. 472-S, dated the 1st of Ju?e 1943, to the Government of India. 2. In the year 1360 the Electric Department credited \ to the Bahrain Government a sum of Rs. 1,00,000 to be held as a deposit. This item is correctly shown as a deposit with Lhe Bahrain Government in the Electric Department’s Balance Sheet for 1360 (vide page 42 Bahrain Annual Report 1360). By an error of accounting the Bahrain Government did not place this sum in a deposit account as they should have done but credited it to Revenue (vide Statement of Revenue and Expenditure at page 10 of Bahrain Annual Report for 1360). In the year 1361 the Electric Department required a refund of their deposit. If the sum had been correctly accounted for by the Bahrain Government as a deposit in 1360 the sum would have been refunded from the deposit account.. But as the sum had, incorrectly, been credited to Revenue in 1360 it had to be debited to Expenditure when it was refunded in 1361'. If proper accounting methods had been followed the actual figures of Revenue during 1360 would have been reduced by Rs 1,00,000 and the actual figures of Expenditure during 1361 would also have been reduced by the same amount. 14th July 1943. tfax. ^ SrW. 1 Hi • a / b cUiU. -~1 - 4 i l-k • P- R , //y Pl./\o. P//?(&gt;3 r 2i fy. ato.^ A*- /Urvi* 3 ~^Ltke ^(1/ 0-y* u- 3 ^ sr* - rBahrain Government Budget Estimates for 1363 f General ? The revenues have been estimated very conservatively but the expenditure estimate would verge on being liberal. The disparity betweert the estimates and actuals^for the year 1362 has been very great. (36*} lacs and 47 lacs). The estimated expenditure was 30} lacs while’actuals rose up to 33^ lacs, in 1362. Interest from 'Reserves” seem to be low, All available during the year. Rationing and Food Control Department can work on a commercial basis debiting the public with its cost and any incidental losses in its working. bring in no revenue. Administration of Justice is a charge on the revenues should bear a portion of the expenditure. The increase in revenue under liedical receipts from Service Wards is estimated at only 5,00C. With the new rates and probable influx of in-transit Service personnel during the year the income may be much more. A comparative statement showing the difference in for revenue funds do not appear to have been invested. Passport Department working at a heavy loss. The P.W.D. seem to expect no work for the R.A.F. to the extent of 4} lacs and the revenues are estimated to be less than 13,000. The V/akf and Minors Departments Investment under the head 'Agriculture” seems to is placed below. (actuals and estimates) revenue and expend!turenduring the two years 1362 and 1363 xmzi</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003a5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/198</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003a5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/198</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'4/1 Bahrain State Finances 4'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-04-29T00:12:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (270 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present between ff 10-253; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out to prevent confusion with the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains copies of the financial records of the Government of Bahrain that were sent to the British Political Agency in Bahrain by Charles Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. The records cover the years 1359-1363AH (1941-1945). These records include details of the expenditure and budget of the government. A number of lists containing details of the salaries and allowances of members of the Al Khalifa family are also included throughout the file.The file contains correspondence that discusses Bahrain's financial situation, notably details of how and where investments should be made for Bahrain's state reserve fund, details of Shaikh Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa's [Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah] excessive spending habits and the impact of the Second World War on Bahrain.The file also contains copies (in English and Arabic) of correspondence between Charles Geoffrey Prior, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Shaikh Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa.Of note are folios 198v and 199v, on which financial details from 1943/44 have been printed on the reverse of two unrelated British Government propaganda posters - presumably due to a paper shortage during war time.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Khalīfah (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>National Economy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003a5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>