<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000080_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T02:07:25.588Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">It is requested that in any further communication cm this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, Whitehall, Ixmdon, S.W. 3473. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 23th E&amp;jjtmb&amp;r, 2912. Sir, I qm dir®ot&amp;d by tk® S®cr®bary of Sbat&amp; for India to aeknowl&amp;dg# th&amp; r&amp;o&amp;ipt of your l&amp;tt&amp;r of th® 10th instant, asking for his ooncurmnc® in th&amp; answer to bs rabum&amp;u to th® enquiry of th® Mam2 Oormamimr-in- Ohimf wh®£h®r His Moj&amp;sty'a shifts should rmuimr ass is- tone® to th® Sultan of in sailing ams ana u munition b®longing to Frmoh subjects or smrohing dhows flying Frmoh colours in Fuse at wat&amp;rs* In r®ply I m to say that th® Marqu&amp;ss of Vrm® concurs that in n®ith®r cuss should such assistance b® r®na&amp;r®d&gt; ana 1 am to invit® attention in this connection to th&amp; t®ms of th® pwmllimat* paragraph of th® tala- gram, adarmssad to th® Govarntmnt of India on th® 17th x Fahrmry 1910 * Oojpy communicut®d ) 19 February 1310.) I cm to a,id that, as will b® s&amp;m aboo®, th® ®xpr®ssi®n 'in Muscat waters ' in th® Naval Oowaandar- in-3hi&amp;f's t®2®grwn is \ mo&amp;rstood to r®f®r to both h®ods of his anquiry, Th® Murquass of Or®#® would b® glad to l&amp;am #h®n th® reply issuss, in oniar that th® tal&amp;grm of which a draft is onelosod may bo addr®ss®d to in® Oomrrmant of India. I hav® th® honour to h®. The Under Secretary of State, Sir, Tour nost obodimt FOREIGN OFFICE-% \x i, V/5 In any further communication on this subject, please quote ,37644/12. No. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. \ ■ lO 1 Foreign Office September 10th, 1912. PresBing. Sir: - With reference to the letter which Secretary Sir E. Grey un^eratande wap addreBBed to you hy the Admiralty on the 6th. instant on the Bubject of the ArmB traffic at Muacat, I am directed to transmit to you herewith the draft of the reply which it is propoped to return to a similar letter which has been received from the Admiralty in this Department. Sir E. Grey would be glad to know with as little delay as possible whether the Marquess of Crewe concurs in the terms of this reply. I am, , Sir, Your most obedient. \ *10 SEP 1312-} &amp;c 4L humble Servant, R t C ' O \ \ ’ The Under Secretary of Stare, . iU£ ( India Office.DRAFT Foreign Offtea to Admiralty Confidential and Immediate September IMS Sir I am directed etc. to acknowledge the receipt of the letter from the Admitalty of the 6th instant, Confidential, forwarding copy of a telegram from the Commander in Chief, Fast Indies, in which instructions ate reguested for the event of the Sultan of Muscat asking for assistance from H.M. ships to seize arms and ammunition belonging to French citizens and to search dhows flying French colours in Jdiscat waters. You enquite what ansimr should, in the opinion of the Secretary of State, be returned to this question. I ob. to state in reply that Sir E.Grey is of opinion that the Sommander in Chief should he informed that in neither ease should H.M. ships render assistance to the Sultan. I m to add that the Secretary of State for India concurs ift' the terms of this letter.Conf Ident ivX nnd Lme d 1 ate :~ Sir # e t an oonmanded by my TjofI^ Commissioner'! of fho Arimimity to transmit herewith for the information of the Secretary of Skate for India in Council ( oopv of « tetegm which has been received from the Commander-in-Chief, 'ast Indies f respect in,y the seizure by ' , .y.Ships of arms belonging to mrenoh subjects and the searching of dhows flying French colours In ‘dusgat waters. J, ly Tjords would be glad to learn what answer should in the opinion of the Secretary of State he made to the question raised by the Conmander-in-Chief who has,, I am to state, in the meanwhile been directed to await definite instructions before taking any action. \ similar letter has been sent to the Foreign Office. t am. The Under Secretary of State, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (X 7 vw«^^ India Office, S.W.Doeypfeer of Telegram FROM - The C-in-C Fast Indies AT - Diyatalawa DATED - 6 September 1913. TO - The Secretary, Admiralty No:- 13 2 It is considered possible that Sultan of Muscat may request assistance from H.M.Ships to seize arms and ammunition which are beirg exprtod so as to avoid their being deposited in warehouses. Early instructions by telegraph whether in event of his doing so arms and ammunition belonging to French subjects may bo seized and dhows flying French colours may be searched in Muskat waters.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. and address— I Q ^ The Under-Secretary of State,' Foreign Office, London. r ' °Y 'O INDIA “f 20 SEP 1912 SECn(-;i' «r!Y‘S N2 38 ^ •\/' 0^) The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop V of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 9B on txiijoasJ 2161 d 3 S OS _VlnNl Q 1 AdOO sep^ u Reference to previous letter: ■jl. , xLpi&amp;yF f z Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject.38447/12. *omfr Qwir, ^ and I’nmediute. Sir:- 1 )t i St. ur :be % 1912 I arn directed by Secretary Sir E. Grty to xdcao - ledge the receipt of the letter from the Admiralty of the 6th instant Confidential, forwarding copy of a telegram from the Commander in Chief, last Indies xn which instructions are requested for the event of the Sultan of Muscat asking for assxstaace fro Y, \ His Majesty’s ships to seize arms and ammunition belonging to French citizens and to search dhovs flying French colo ;rs in 'uscat waters. Y^u timuire what r sho-lu, in the opinion of the Secretary of State, be returned to this question. I aw to state in reply thc*t Sir F. ''.re, i- of opinion that the Commander in Chief should be informed that in neither case should His Majesty’s ships render assistance to the 3 It&amp;n. I am to add that the Secretary of State fo^ India concurs ?cretary )f the Admiralty.[This Document is the Property of His,Britanmc Majesty's Government.] [A] ARMS TRAFFIC. CONFIDENTIAL. [March 15.] Section 1. [ 8921 ] No. 1. ('Confidential.) Sir, Foreign Office to India Office. Foreign Office, March 15, 1Q1 ■\VITH reference to your letters of the 17tli, 21st, and 21th February last, and to the letter from the Admiralty addressed to you on the 21st ultimo, respecting the arms traffic in the Persian Gulf, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to state, for th“ information of the Secretary of State for India, that he has taken the various questions raised therein into his careful consideration. The main points which concern the 1’oreign Office are : 1 The position of a dhow under the French flag in Persian or Muscat territorial waters, and the powers of the Persian or Muscat Governments to restrain such a vessel from carrying on a traffic in Govemmen t to support the Sheikhs of Koweit, Bahrein and Mohammerah, and the Trucial chiefs in any difficulty that may arise with the French Government, in consequence of seizures of cargoes of arms effected under the authority of those rulers in their territorial waters. . , mi tj 3. The possibility of referring the attitude of France in Muscat to The Hague for arbitration, and,'in connection with this, the question of arbitration on re-export of arms from Jibuti. Sir E. Grey’s opinion on these points may be expressed as follows 1. The reported action of M. Goguyer’s agent in purchasing a dhow, and reffisterino* it at the French consulate in Muscat under the French flag, would seem, under present conditions, to provide the dealers in arms with a vessel that is exempt from^e^rcToVsetre by’ His Majesty’s ships. The questmu l^s ruimardy on the powers of the Persian or Muscat Government to exercise restiaxnt on such a oliow, and secondarily on the extent of the mandate to exercise restramt on then e , respecting which Persia or Muscat may be able to accord to Gieat Britain. _ respecting wmen ^ / esses full ex t ra -territorial jurisdiction in 1 ersia land holds ’a similar position in Muscat, so that the same consideration holds goo for both countries), and P Persia has parted to France with her jnrisdi^ion over I rene i citizens, and cannot derogate from her own grant ^ « 0 ' f “ rl 'f rs ° i ' ^“Lriffi wateS jurisdiction or power to interfere with French dhows the S ultimo t (Jrev therefore agrees with the view expressed m your letter ot ttio ziui umme, bir Vjrey tneieioie vv iwpmhpr 1897 does not authorise the iVie* SHflv-i A 7 am s letter of the loth uecemoer, ±o«v/, p • with iU right to prevent . eontrabanil trailo ''.'l' 11 ' f carried on under the flag of France, or any ot 3 , s for the internal r, szsz HSJStZ to Y'j^AsSSSLSS^ citizens from acting illegally, by means of the ^^procedure in Persia- Sir E. Grey does not possess any P r « clse ,“ f “ ra ^^Xmin' that France does not in cases of smuggling offences by French cltl “ .’. her eitiz e ns f ro m committing Cits S ^e strong outside pressure may be considered to be doubtful. [2659 p—1] -The Persian Government have of course a perfect right to take active preventive measures in their territorial waters or on Persian territory to stop the importation of arms bv dhows under the Prench flag, but in practice this would^ be beyond their unaided powers to effect, and they might therefore confer on British naval officers powers to act, for this purpose, in the name of, and as the servants of, the Shah. But though technically such an arrangement might be held to be valid, it is unnecessary to point out the very serious friction that would at once ensue with Prance, nor would it be easy to oppose a Prench claim that such powers should, in the case of dhows under the Prench flag, be accorded to Prench, and not to British, officials. 2. Sir E. Grey understands that Prance has no special rights in Koweit, Bahrein, ]Vfohammerah, or on the Trucial Coast, and he therefore is of opinion that the line of action proposed in paragraph 2 of your letter of the 24th ultimo, in xegard to the rulers of this district, should be adopted. 3. Sir E. Grey entirely agrees with the view expressed in your letter of the 21st ultimo, that the cases of Jibuti and Muscat should be treated separately in anv reference to arbitration. PV T itli regard to Jibuti, he is not, as at piescnt advised, satisfied that the case is either strong enough to call the Prench Government to The Hao-ue, or, even if it were submitted to arbitration with the result that a decision was given in favour of His Majesty’s Government, that this result would be commensurate with the friction and expense involved. In respect to Muscat, I am, in the first place, to observe that if it can be held that the Sultan is free to prohibit the import of arms into his country, Sir E. Grey would advocate the course of introducing His Highness to take action to^ this end, and leaving it to the Prench Government to summon him or H*s Majesty’s Govern ment to arbitration, since the practical effect on the arms traffic would be greater and more immediate ; and if the case itself is considered by His Majesty’s Government strong enough for arbitration, action taken in accordance with their view of the case would also be justified, unless and until the court of arbitration pronounced against them. In the present instance, however, an examination of the arguments advanced in your letter last referred to does not convince Sir E. Grey that they would hold good in an international court. Taking these arguments in the order in which they are placed in your letter, Sir E. Grey is of opinion with regard to 1. That to hold that the arms traffic did not exist in 1814, and cannot therefore reasonably be held to be covered by the treaty of that year, would, if maintained, result in cutting out of the benefits' and application of the treaty all trade that did not exist in 1844, and commerce in anything that has been invented or discovered since that date. 2. Sir E. Grey believes that the view which, on the whole, finds favour with international jurists at the present day is that a commercial treaty which contains no provisions for termination or denunciation is a perpetual treaty, and cannot be terminated by one of the parties without the consent of the other. Sir E. Grey is not prepared to maintain that this is without doubt a correct interpretation of international law, but it is clear that if it is the general view the probabilities are that it would be upheld by a court of arbitration. In the case of a perpetual treaty of which the subject-matter had entirely disappeared, so that there was nothing left to which the provisions of the treaty could apply, it would ex necessitate rei lapse or become extinguished. So also if the conditions environing the subject-matter had become so absolutely changed that the treaty in no respect covered the ground on which the parties originally contracted, or the natural development and modification of that ground which the lapse of years had brought with it, it might then be argued that nothing remained of the original subject-matter, contemplated by the parties, for the treaty to operate upon. It is in the present case no doubt to some extent a question of the degree to which the original conditions have been altered, but it would be difficult to argue that they have been altered to such a degree as to justify one party in withdrawing from the treaty against the wishes of the other. 3. If it could be successfully shown that the growth of the arms traffic at Muscat was a real source of danger to that State, involving her in internal disorder or embroiling her with neighbouring territories where the import of arms is forbidden, it would then be lawful for the Sultan, acting on the maxim “ Salus reipublicae suprema lex,” to override the provisions of the 1844 treaty with France in thisrespect, and to prohibit the arms trade in his dominions. But such a proceeding* must he absolutely bond fide, and the result of the conviction of the Government oi Muscat, and if it'should in any way appear to he in reality due to the initiative of an outside Power, and the pretext alleged seem to he merely specious, it would he open to criticism, and Prance would have a right to protest. 4. Although it is true that all the Powers represented at the recent Arms Con ference with the exception of Prance, were prepared to give His Majesty’s Government a free hand to deal with the arms traffic in the Persian Gulf, none of those Powers raised any question as to the legal right of the Prench Government to maintain their attitude, nor did the various delegates give expression to any views which might seem to condemn Prance from a moral standpoint. The general attitude was rather one of recognition of the inconvenience of the traffic to His Majesty s Government, and ot readiness not to hamper a fellow civilised Power in defending itself against warlike and savage neighbours, hut there was no condemnation of Prench action as m any way derogating from the recognised standards of modern civilisation Por this reason, and also on general grounds, Sir E. Grey is inclined to think that it would be difficult to represent to Prance that Muscat—a State of low civilisation—was about to denounce the treaty because the conduct of Prench citizens, as approved of or at least unrestrained by, the Prench Government, was contrary to undisputed doctrines ot public law and to the view universally held with regard to morals, which is, in Sir E. Grey’s opinion, the practical form in which the fourth argument mentioned m your letter would have to be applied. , c ,, In view, therefore, of the considerations advanced above, and ol tne many practical difficulties in the way of action in the Persian Gulf without the consent ot trance, Sir E. Grey would suggest that the French Government might first be approached direct on the subject. The negotiations attempted hitherto have, it is true, resulted in failure, and Sir E. Grey would not propose to renew at present any offers of concessions of territory or other compensation ; but the situation in Morocco presents a close analogy to the position on the North-West Frontier of India and it wi be difficult for the French Government to_ refuse to recognise the right of Hs Majesty’s Government to ask for the same friendly treatment in the Persian Gult as they have accorded to France in Moroccan waters. 4 ™ I am accordingly to transmit to you herewith a draft memorandum to the French Government which has been prepared in this department, and I am to state that Sir E. Grey will be glad to learn Viscount Morley’s views as to the desirability of making this communication, and to receive any amendments or alterations w ic his Lordship may consider should be made iu its terms. ■ T j: In the event of this proposal being approved by the Secretary of ktate Ind a and of its meeting with an evasive reply from the French Government, or a retusal on their part to comply with the request of His Majesty s Government, it will then become necessary to 1 consider what further steps can be taken to exert P ressure the French Government to assume a more reasonable attitude towards the question of the arms traffic in the Persian Gulf. I am, &amp;c. W. LANGLEY. * Draft memorandum for the French Government.p 34 Ur£ From Viceroy, 2&gt;rd September 1912. Foreign Secret. Following from Political Agent at Muscat, dated 1st September:— “ Government’s interpretation of Rule XI. has been carefully explained to Sultan of Muskat, who fully accepts it. Your telegram No. S. 515, notice issued as directed. Copy by mail. Steps will be taken with reference to consignments coming by sea after 1 st September, and clearance of Customs House has been explained to Flis Highness who informed me that he will arrange accordingly. Before I officially received notice already referred to. His Highness sent me, under unofficial cover, copy of a letter just received from the French Consul in which the latter, under telegraphic instructions just received from the Minister for Foreign Affairs, informs His Highness that the French Government abates none of its rights under the Treaty of 1844, and for all damage or loss resulting to French merchants residing in Oman or France, or foreign countries, will demand all necessary compen sation and satisfaction. French Government has reminded French Consul that it has not consented to enforcement of new regulations on French subjects. French letter ends. “ In forwarding above His Highness reminds me that be shifts burden of compensation, if any has to be paid, to our shoulders. I have considered it essential in view of this fresh warning by the French, immediately to reassure His Highness in writing, and I quoted to him Resident’s assurance already communicated to him, vide Condition 1 of vernacular letter enclosed in Resident’s No. 136 M., dated 5th June, addressed to Foreign. Trust that you will approve of steps taken. “ I have received French Consul’s reply to His Highness’s letter forwarding confirmation of notice ; reply contains nothing new, merely reiterates former objections. Copy of the correspondence will be forwarded as soon as possible.”Docyphor of Telogram FROM - The Coramandcp-in-Chiof, East Indies AT - Diyatalawa DATED - 4 September 1912. No:- 129 Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf reports Muscat norraal. French subjects have made formal protest against the regulations.From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 26th August 1912. Foreign Secret. My telegram dated 20th. August. Muscat. His Majesty s j Government approve Rule 11, ou the understanding that clause (b) means ; that a license will be refused to a purchaser only if he already possesses 4 arms in sufficient quantities to justify the inference that he does not require them only for his own use, and not merely if he possesses any arms at all. From Viceroy, 28th August 1912. {Repeated to Residejit at Bushire and Political Agent, Maskat.) Your telegram of the 23rd August last. Maskat. Political Agent reports that Sultan objected strongly to expression “ to expect him to compensate would be unreasonable ” in the reply suggested in your telegram of 20th August. Political Agent accordingly allowed him to alter this to “ payment of compensation would be unreasonable. this appeals unobjectionable. Sultan replied accordingly. Knox telegraphed on 25th August:— . . , . . , ,. “ French Consul has now replied to His Highness communication stating that he has no doubt as to His Highness’ independence and foreign I owe! (sic) but he does not see the connection between them and subject ol his letters “ Next refers to freedom of trade and limit of duties to 5 per cent. “ Lays stress upon French Treaty of 1844 and fact that it cannot le changed without the consent of signatories of the Treaty. _ “ Repeats orders of his Government and that it will not admit enforcement of new arrangement without compensation. „ . “ He says that rights of France are preserved according to law ot nations although His Highness will not accept liability for compensation.” We consider Sultan should now be advised to reply, “ Four attitude m regard to my proposed regulation of trade does concern and affect my independence which is jointly guaranteed by Governments of France and Great Britain. The question is one for discussion between those Govern ments, and I regret I cannot further discuss this question with you. i into to proceed with the regulation of arms traffic as announced, lo t 118 “ ^ shall publish on 1st September an order to effect that sale or removal of a and ammunition'VUrnot be permitted except after passing through special warehouse, and that Maskat subjects will be severely punished if they assist m such ske or removal. I trust you will direct French subiects to comp y like others with rules and deposit their stocks in warehouse I “'ke to hold such stocks in trust pending decision of question by two Goveinmec , in Europe.” r i, u u Should modus vivendi with French Government not be reache y 1st September we propose that Sultan should issue ^LLrehouse o^ after fortnight’s grace should order seizure and removal to warehouse o all fresh consignments coining by sea. As regards existing stocks he should place cordon round refractory dealers’ warehouses and arrest al Maskat subiects assisting in sale or removal. In accordance with preamble of the original notification Sultan should on or about 14 th September publish subsidiary notification confirming all rules approved by that date. From Viceroy, ‘61st August 1912. Foreign Secret. Mv telegram' of 28th August. Muscat. Cox and Political Agent at Muscat telegraph urging desirability oi putting nl '' 8I ' force from 1st September, and thereafter taking all consignments of arms arrivine bv sea or now lying in Customs House into special warehouse. Such action ts not only expected locally, but Sultan has committed himself on snbiect and expressed determination to supervise work himself, ft is most undesirable to^damp him at this juncture. Moreover, Knox reports that French dealers as test case are intentionally allowing consignments to he in Customs House. Further, German steamship “ Eklatana arrives on .,1st August with small consignment for Muscat, and Knchs steamship Mask.on £ expected to arrive on 10th September with large consignment We have accordingly authorised Knox to advise Sultan to act according y. This does not of course, affect question of confiscation which under rules r oes not arise till a month after confirmation of rules, but merely ensures that consignments by sea and in Customs House will be sent to warehouse, and not allowed to leak out into the countiy. ^ From Secretary of State to Viceroy Foreign Department, 31st August 1912. Foreign Secret. Your proposals are approved. Extra territorial ng respected.Do cypher of Telegram m *Sf 4 T T ^ ^1* %»’- ! * - .* * t 4^-. FROM - Tho Coni!andci3-in--0hiof, Fast Indies AT - Diyatalawa . DATED - 2 September 1912. TO - The Secretary, Admiralty. No:- 127 Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf reports Muscat perfectly quiet ani that 500 ©ifles 200 cases ammunition believed to be French property have been roaoved from Custom House to warehouse without incident. The Senior Naval Officer in 'Espiogle' remains at Miscat for tho present.Enclosure 1**tec i ’ r ctnry, India. ^o.33 y. qu^.j 15 AUG 191k i m 3 S^f- 194. Telegram P., No. 811, dated tlie 8th (received 9th) August 1912. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla (repeated by post to Maskat). Please refer to Maskat telegram* No. * Serial No. 187. ^23 of 5th August. The nosition now is that French have officially intimated that unless their traders' are compensated they will not tolerate warehouse scheme. It does not seem to me that while - careSm^ French Government wi a U “P^ without thereby incurring liability to compensating French traders them what the figures might not reach compensate others; and it is diffic J of „ trader |.» I presume there- if manufacturers are inolud to assist Multan to maintain his refusal of fore that we shall do our utmost to recaU, in this connection, acceptance of principle of ^pensati • ? offl dated the ls t April paragraph 3 of letter from India ^^freignu . made n0 demand 1911 Could we not ^“f.^nl Sd. based on what is a mere regular for compensation and that the F Sll ]tan’s independence and the declara- legitimate trade is incompatible with. Suita s moep^ would , no doubt, he a ^^^SenSV;^ Jagree to a total prohibition, and wp should be ready to consider it. W6 S Subject to bearing of ^“^ d 0 ^^™g^fi 0 ^oyCTnment^nce^thrannou^e- t di Suid ^ the question whether Government of Jndia^houldn^^ ^ hig delegation of authority to discuss q ^ Sultan’s illiterateness and the recommend this course £?°ssiWe, ^ S k t0 manage his correspondence, incapacity of his clerks, it is very a duo ^ French armg dealers Political Agent, Maskat, reports t lodge their stocks in ware- are boasting about their determinat o ^8. tb s t e amers, the people of house and to take consignments ^f^n accepted fact and there is a STS l the interior, and prices $re going up rapidly* 195 Telegram P., No. 573 S., dated the 9th August 1912. fhom—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To-The Political Resident in the Person Gulf, Buehire. it q nf vmir letter* No. 1563, dated the 27th Proposal made in paragrap regarding Superintendent, Arms •serial No. isi. Warehouse, is approved. ' ~ 'r t120 196 No. 120, dated Maskat, the 4th (received 12th) August 1912 (Cofidential). From— Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britatmic Majesty^ r ' Consul, Maskat, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to submit herewith a copy with translation of the reply sent hv His Highness the Sultan of Maskat to the letter of the French Consul, dated the 27th Tamuz 1912, in accord- * Sena. No. 175 . ance dj rec ft ong conveyed to me in your telegram* No. 450 S., dated the 2nd of August 1912. 2. The message that “ the principle of compensation is not likely to he admitted by Government and that His Highness will be unwise to hold out any hopes thereof to the French Consul ” was duly communicated by me to His Highness at an interview that took place on the 3rd of August 1912. 3. A copy of this letter has been forwarded to the Political Hesident and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General in the Persian Gulf. Translation of draft prepared by Political Agent, Maskat, with Sultanas Secretary replying to French Consul's letter of 27th July 1912. After compliments ,—Your honoured letter,! dated the 27th Tamuz 1912, has reached and what you mention there- t Appendix b, Serial No. 183. in has become known to your friend and it has appeared to us from its import that $ Appendix A, ibid. Your Excellency has not understood the purport^ of our letter, dated the 11th Shahan 1330 H. And the meaning of our letter referred to was not except that we shall consider Your Excellency’s representation as is suitable for all that comes to us from Your Honoured Excellency. And then we inform Your Excellency that we, at present, see nothing that attaches to us liability from the scope of our two proclamations, and especially in the matter of compen sation, because the two proclamations are for the regulation of the lawful trade, not for the stopping of it and, after full consideration, there will come finally to Your Excellency our reply.— Usual ending. 197 No. 124, dated Maskat, the 6th (received 12th) August 1912 (Confidential). From— Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul at Maskat, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. In confirmation of my telegram§ No. 123, dated the 5th August 1912, to § serial No. is7. ac ^ress of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and repeated to you, I have the honour to submit herewith the copy of a letter, dated the 4th of August 1912, with its translation, from the French Consul to His Highness the' Sultan of Maskat in reply to the letter from His Highness the Sultan of Maskat to the French Consul, of which a copy was forwarded under cover of II Serial No. 19 &amp; m y confidential letter|| No. 120, dated the 4th August 1912, to your address. 2. In the face of the emphatic disclaimer of any likelihood of the orant of compensation to French traders by Government and of the impossibilfty of suggesting that His Highness should satisfy them himself, the question arises as to how the refusal of the French Government to allow the rules of His Highness’s proclamation of the 4th June and 11th July 1912 to be enforced against French subjects is to be met. It is clear to me, upon the attitude of121 locnl traders, that, if French traders are allowed to buy and sell freely their existing stocks without let or hindrance, other merchants will immediately transfer their stocks to French godowns and thereby secure the inviolability of their goods; the existing stock of arms and ammunition will be sold under French names; and, to a great extent, rules 1, 2 and 3 of His Highness’s Proclamation of the 11th July will remain inoperative. 3. I take it for granted that, in no case, will His Highness be justified in violating French godowns or boats, sailing under the French flag. 4. It seems, therefore, that, to render his proclamations effective, His Highness will he reduced to— (A) Action against French goods outside French godowns and French boats, such as is provided for under rules 6 to 9. (B) Measures against such of his own subjects and foreigners subject to his jurisdiction as may purchase arms and ammunition from French traders. 5. I have, therefore, the honour to request that I may he directed as to the advice which I may be permitted to tender to His Highness as to whether it is considered that he will be justified in removing goods, arriving after the 1st of September and consigned to French traders, direct to the Arms Warehouse in accordance with the terms of his proclamation {vide rule 4). This point will have to be decided in a period of less than twenty- five days. 6. It may, I venture to think, he taken for granted that an immediate formal demand will be made for their surrender. To this demand should His Highness return a reply that he will consider the matter or a direct refusal ? 7. If His Highness is to be permitted, under our advice, to enforce his rules against French subjects, independently of French consent, it would seem that he will, under rule 3, be entitled to treat the formal refusal of the French Government to allow the rules to be enforced as against their own subjects as a fact of which he may, so to speak, take judicial notice; treat French arms traders as openly defying his proclamation and the rules made thereunder; and immediately proceed to the confiscation of such goods as may come into his bands, viz., arms imported after 1st September, and dispose of them as he pleases subject to the rules and regulations, governing the issue of arms and ammunition from the Arms Warehouse as to licenses, sales and marking, or subject to our advice. Shall I be authorised to advise him accordingly ? The above measures show how I would propose to deal with the question raised in 4 (A). 8. But, if the warehouse system is to run satisfactorily, it will also he necessary to take drastic action against his own subjects ^ or foreigners, other than French, who venture to purchase arms and ammunition from the French traders who, I have presumed, must be regarded as offenders against the proc lamation. Such action will he difficult and will require, for strict enforce ment, a better organised and more loyal body of police that His Highness can count upon. But much can he done. 9. I fear I hear lay myself open to the charge of going over old ground and that this question, and others, have been raised by me and submitted to Government bv the Political Resident in * Serial No. 180 . the Persian Gulf in his No. 1561,• dated 27th Julv 1912, and that I have received a clear intimation that an early answer to these problems is not to be expected. 10. I find it, however, difficult to dissociate the reply which the French Consul requests from His Highness in the letter attached and the reply to the problems raised. Perhaps it will be simpler to reduce them all to one general question and ask “Is His Highness going to enforce the proclamation and rules against French subjects irrespective of French consent ? ” The answer, for the present and in general terms, seems clearly to be in the affirmative, so far as he can do so without violating Treaty rights. 11. In that case, it would seem that, in his reply to the French Consul, His Highness should repeat his letter of the 4th of August and say that, after122 mature consideration, lie adheres to his original opinion that, as the Arms Warehouse is for the “ Ikamat ” (the word seems convenient, as it can be read as the “ promotion ” as well as the “ regulation ’ , ) of legitimate trade, he sees no liability attaching to him for compensation to French traders; that he ^ considers the scheme entirely consistent with his obligations under Treaty, and is determined to enforce his proclamations, with the accompanying rules, against all his own subjects and such foreigners, as are subject to his jurisdic tion • and that, if, in the course of the measures taken to those ends, the ± rench traders find that their trade is hampered, they will have only themselves to thank for it on account of their defiance of reasonable local regulations, in no way inconsistent with their Treaty rights. 12. A copy of this letter will be forwarded to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf by next mail, reaching him on the 15th instant. Translation of a letter from the French Consul, Maskat, to His Highness the Sultan of Maskat dated the 4th August 1912 (received under cover of a private note from His Highness the Sultan of Maskat, dated the 20th Shaban, 1330 Hijra). After compliments—In reply to your honoured letter, dated the 20th Shaban 1330 Hijra, which repeats the meaning of the former one, which was understood, let it not he hidden from Your Majesty that our glorious Govern ment has not ordered me now except that I should ask your greatness of your august intentions in the matter of compensating our merchants, the arms traders ; and, if you agree that you will compensate them, then our Govern ment likewise agrees that the new regulation, done without consulting it (Government) and opposed to the Treaties in force, shall be made to lun against the aforesaid merchants; and, if you refuse, then our Government as I informed your presence in my letter, dated the 23rd of Tamuss 1912, likewise refuses (to allow) the enforcement of the new regulation against our subjects. And, as I informed Your Majesty also, the question is not now of the quantity of money compensation of which the method of settlement will come (later) between the two parties bound by mutual love, but it is on the admission of the fact, apart from the quantity and on the agreement to pay or the refusal thereof. And, as I informed Your Majesty also, we ask of your generosity the reply about that so that commercial matters may not be delayed. Now our glorious Government, may it not be concealed from you, does not love liars and helps them in nothing and, accordingly, should anyone'pretend to compensation and be unable to prove his loss at the time of the settlements in any manner whatever, then there is no doubt at all that we shall reject him.— Usual ending. 198 Telegram, No. 822, dated the 11th (received 12th) August 1912. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—I he Foreign Secretary, Simla. Your telegram* Superintendent of Arms Warehouse. Please see my tele gram, dated 26th February, 143. Am I • Serial No. i9a. to UD( j ers t,and that Government are satis fied with his credentials and approve Political Agent’s acceptance of his appointment if terms comply with spirit t Serial No. isi. 0 f paragraph 2 of my despatchf of 27 th Julv, 1563.1 FOREIGN SECRET TELEGRAMS. Secret Department. From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 2nd September 1912. Foreign Secret. Muscat. Following is translation of body of note from French Minister for Foreign Affairs, dated 29th August, in reply to memorandum of 22nd August communicated by Bertie, sent by mail of 30th August:— “ French Government consider that in virtue of treaty of 17th Novem ber 1844, between France and Muscat, the trade in arms ought to remain quite unrestricted at Muscat, and that French nationals should retain complete freedom to buy or sell arms with whomsoever they will. French Government have therefore informed Government of Muscat that generally speaking it stands by all the rights derived from treaty, and will, moreover, claim compensation for any injury which the enforcement of contemplated regulations concerning trade in arms may cause to French nationals who are especially interested, and to trade of country. French Government is entitled by Anglo-French declaration of 10th March 1802 to treat this matter directly and alone with Government of Muscat, taking into consideration French rights and interests only. “ French Government is, however, always glad to take British interests into consideration. Impressed by advantages of various kinds which Great Britain would derive from repression of free trade in arms at Muscat, French Government has already shown itself disposed to surrender rights derived from Franco-Muscat Treaty of 1844 as well as those assured to France by Anglo-French declaration of 1862. “ But French Government naturally could not sacrifice, even in favour of a friendly country, French rights and interests without obtaining indemnities and compensations on one hand for traders who are personally interested, and on the other for France. French Government would examine any proposal made in this respect by British Government with utmost desire to reach satisfactory understanding. Meanwhile, French cannot but uphold at Muscat rights of France, and eventually defence of interests of French nationals.i , CONFIDENTIAL. 33^4 9 t / Sir F Bertie to Sii / r r rn/ Grey.—(Received August 31, 10‘45 a.m.) {No. 2. Africa.) R. X Paris, August 30, 1912, 8*20 p.m. MY telegram No. 1, Africa, and my despatch No. 40, Africa, of 28th August. Following is translation of body of note from French Minister for Foreign Affairs dated 29th August, replying to my note of 22nd August: Y” “ French Government consider that in virtue of treaty of 17th November, 1844, between France and Muscat, the trade in arms ought to remain quite unrestricted at Muscat, and that French nationals should retain complete freedom to buy or sell arms with whomsoever they will. French Government have therefore informed Government of Muscat that generally speaking it stands by all the rights derived from treaty, and will, moreover, claim compensation for any injury which the enforcement of contemplated regulations concerning trade in arms may cause to French nationals who are especially interested, and to trade of country. French Government is entitled by Anglo-French declaration of 10th March, 1862, to treat this matter directly and alone with Government of Muscat, taking into consideration French rights and interests only. “ French Government is, however, always glad to take British interests into con sideration. Impressed by advantages of various kinds which Great Britain would derive from repression of free trade in arms at Muscat, Fiench Government las already shown itself disposed to surrender rights derived from Franco-Muscat Treaty of 1814 as well as those assured to France by Anglo-French declaration of 1862. _ “ But French Government naturally could not sacrifice, even in favour of a friendly country, French rights and interests without obtaining indemnities and compensations on one hand for traders who are pepsonally interested, and on the other for France. French Government would examine any proposal made in this respect by British Government with utmost desire to reach satisfactory understanding. Meanwhile, French cannot but uphold at Muscat rights of France, and eventually defence of interests of French nationals.” | COPY TO INDIA 191 h.. SECHBTAfiY'S N°Ji 767—1072Immediate and C^hfidentiaL 137 3&gt;t The Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the fluyf' accompanying copy of a telegram, as marked in the margin. \^c&lt;. : ^. y&gt; Jx' ' Foreign Office,Immediate .. A and Confidential. .S' ' The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs nts his compliments to C'jj and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copy of ^telegranifi as marked in the margin. ^ ^ r, i 1 'I ° ^ ' Foreign Office, l , i9 [ 16 j1 Sir F.Bertie to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received September 1, 8 a.m.) (No. 3. Africa.) R. Pari8 ’ August 31, 1912, 11’5 p.m. INFORMATION contained in your telegram No. 1, Africa, of to-day com municated this evening to the political director, for the information of the Minister for Foreign Affairs, who is absent from Paris. COPY TO INDIA 19l3r. sEcn.ftTAnw?^ 7f)7- 1047CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir F. Bertie (Paris). (No 1 Africa.) Foreign Office, August, 31, 1912, 2'30 p.m. ^ YOUR telegram No. 1, Africa of 28th August : Muscat. French Minister for Foreign Affairs appears to be under a misapprehension as to interference by His Majesty’s ships with ships carrying French arms. No new orders have been given, and no such interference is contemplated. You may so inform the Minister for Foreign Affairs. ^ /i/, ^ t+rUsL COPY TO INDIA 191.2. aftCRfeTADY'S NH.J.4..... [767—1071]From Viceroy, 30th August 1912. Foreign Secret. Muscat. Please see penultimate paragraph of your tele gram of 23rd instant. Cox and Knox fear that Admiral’s arrival might be misunderstood by Sultan as indicating intention to coerce him. I agree and consider it undesirable for Admiral to go to Muscat unless there are indica tions of despatch of French warships to Muscat. Admiral’s presence may, however, be very desirable about beginning of October when time arrives for confiscating existing stocks not stored in warehouse according to regulations. Admiral’s October visit being normal would not excite remark and would probably be welcomed by Sultan himself. / X From Viceroy, 31st August 1912. Foreign Secret. My telegram of 28th August. Muscat. Cox and Political Agent at Muscat telegraph urging desirability of putting rules m force from 1st September, and thereafter taking all consignments of arms arriving by sea or now lying in Customs House into special warehouse. Such action ts not only expected locally, but Sultan has committed himself on subject, and expressed determination to supervise work himself. It is most undesirable to damp him at this juncture. Moreover, Knox reports that French dealers as test case are intentionally allowing consignments to he m Customs House. Further, German steamship “ Eklatana arrives on •&gt; 1st August with small consignment for Muscat, and Krichs steamship Mashon is expected to arrive on 10th September with large consignment. We have accordingly authorised Knox to advise Sultan to act accordingly. This does not, of course, affect question of confiscation which under rules does not arise till a month after confirmation of rules, but merely ensures that consignments by sea and in Customs House will Lie sent to warehouse, and not allowed to leak out into the country.Immediate and C tjidentiaL The Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit accompanying copy of a telegram, as marked in the margin. Foreign Office, theCONFIDENTIAL. Sir F. Bertie to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 29, 10 a.m.) (No. 1. Africa.) Paris, August 28, 1912, 1T2 a.m. YOUR despatch No. 49, Africa, of 26th August. When I had carried out this morning’s instructions contained in your despatch No. 47, Africa, of the 26th August in regard to traffic in arms through Jibuti, during discussion with Minister for Foreign Affairs, he reminded me that French Government had refused to adhere to Brussels Act in the matter of arms. His Excellency informed me that he had examined question of arms trade in the Persian Gulf, respecting which I had made representations to him on 22nd August. He found that under treaties of 1844 and 1862 France has the right to trade unreservedly with Muscat. The trade in arms being a legitimate one, French subjects have the right to carry it on and to look to the French Government to protect them in the exercise of it. As His Majesty’s Government found that the trade is injurious to their interests, French Government are quite ready to enter into conversations with His Majesty’s Government on the subject, and to endeavour to find a solution of the question without delay, but they cannot admit a right on the part of His Majesty’s Government to deal with matter in the manner set forth in the memorandum which I had left with his Excellency on 22nd August, and I showed to his Excellency my despatch to you of that date reporting my conversation with him, and I added that you had informed me that His Majesty’s Government intend to continue their support to the Sultan in putting a stop to the traffic, and have sent two ships to assist his Highness in dealing with traders who carry it on. Minister for Foreign Affairs said that it would be a very grave proceeding thus to interfere with a legitimate French trade with Muscat. I replied as matters stand we do not propose to interfere with French trade with Muscat. What we object to, and have taken measures to prevent, is the transfer from Muscat of arms brought in there to other destinations. That would not be an interference with the French trade with Muscat. Minister for Foreign Affairs contends that, though His Majesty’s Government may legitimately intercept in the British waters arms intended for destinations where trade is prohibited, they have no right to interfere with vessels carrying such French arms, either in Muscat waters or on the high seas. He said that announcement of the intention of His Majesty’s Government to interfere with such trade would cause great surprise and ill-feeling in France, and it would be very difficult to persuade French Parliament to sanction an arrangement with England if she were to take so serious a step as to forcibly interfere with a French trade which, being a well-established interest, could only be abrogated by an arrangement of a compensatory character. I reminded his Excellency that the demands of the French Government in the conversations which had taken place were not such as we could accept. Minister for Foreign Affairs says that he is quite ready to have fresh conversations at once with every desire to come to an agreement, but that he cannot accept mode of proceeding contemplated by His Majesty’s Government. He is telegraphing on subject to the French Embassy in London.From Viceroy, 28th August 1912. Foreign Secret. Muscat Warehouse. telegram of 28th August. Following from Knox :— “ I have just received from Sultan of Muscat, who has in this case only especially asked me to refer it to Government, letter from French Consul in which it is stated he has by mail of to-day received stringent orders from French Minister of Foreign Affairs to repeat ’ to Sultan that French Govern ment cannot consent, relying on treaties, especially 1844, to enforcement of new arrangement on French arms traders. Sultan seems perturbed. I would recommend if possible repl}' referring French Consul (to) Foreign Department’s suggestions of last message.”hi reply quote M o/uuo Confidential. ? 1 n A dmiralty, / / 0 iAr I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit for the information of the Secretary of Stale for of a telegram dated Cu^^- No.yj f&gt; 'om / am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, Office. 125/6/11—[2925] 19694/P651 500 10/llv G&amp;S 2409—X [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Govarnraant ] [A] arms traffic. ''N CONFIDENTIAL. [August 24.] Sbotion 1 . [ 35672 ] No. i. Sir F. Bertie to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 24.) (No. 36. Africa.) Paris, August 23, 1912. M. POINCARE returned from Russia on the evening of the 21st instant, and I had an interview with his Excellency this morning with the object of carrying out the instructions which you did me the honour to address to me in your despatch No. 43, Africa, of the 19th instant on the subject of the arms traffic in the Persian Gulf. I told M. Poincare that I had by your direction to speak to him on a matter which was becoming very serious, and before discussing it I should be obliged if he would read the memorandum which I had brought with me and would leave ■with him. After his Excellency had read the memorandum he said that he was not well acquainted with the question dealt with in it, but he ’would study it. There was a treaty right at issue, and the French Government were bound to defend the rights of French commercial firms. I reminded M. Poincare that we had not hesitated, in order to be agreeable to the French Government, to give them the right of search of British vessels in Moroccan waters, and it was natural for us to expect to have our interests in the Persian Gulf treated in an equally considerate manner. His Excellency thought that the right of search had been only temporary, for he stated that the French military authorities complained that great injury was done to French interests by the importation of arms for the use of the natives from Antwerp, arms of precision chiefly of German manufacture, and the trade was carried on a good deal by Spaniards. On this, I observed that in 1907 the Spanish Government had refused the right of search, and M. Clemenceau had made this refusal the subject of complaint to me in September of that year, and on my reporting the matter to you Spanish opposition was, at the instance of His Majesty J s Government, witndrawn. The 1 rench Government still had the right of search so far as British vessels were concerned. We then returned to the question of the traffic in the 1 ersian Gulf, and I said that 1 thought that if France w^ere in the difficulty in which England found herself there His Majesty’s Government would not hesitate to facilitate matters for her. M. Poincard rather demurred to this view, for he observed that he admitted that in questions where treaty rights w r ere not concerned England was very easy-going and considerate, but when such rights were involved she was, he thought, immovable, and, in the matter of trade with Muscat, France had well-defined treaty rights, lo this I replied that what we opposed was not a French trade with Muscat, but the making of that Sultanate the dep6t for the distribution of arms brought m by Frencn traders for introduction into other States where their importation was prohibited. I said that I knew that French firms with important political influence were interested m the sale of arms discarded from use in the French army, but it was a trade which was not only injurious to the friends of France, but would ultimately be hurtful to French interests, as would certainly he the case before long in Africa owing to the facility with which arms found their way through the custom-house at Jibuti. M. Poincare admitted that French firms of importance with political influence were interested m such sales, and that arms reached far into the interior of Africa to the detriment of French interests, and when I suggested that discarded army rifles should he bioken up instead of being sold, he objected that the French Ministry of Pmance w^ould be verv unwilling to consent to such a mode of dealing with obsolete arms, for their sale brought in a considerable revenue. I answered that the injury reciprocally done y European States to each other through sales to uncivilised people far outweigned m its result the pecuniary benefit derived from their disposal m such manner, ^nia ly, M. Poincare promised to go into the question thoroughly, and when I expressed the [2592 aa-w-l]2 ,,- hope that he would do so bearing In mind the interests of a friend, he answered that he would consider those interests whilst bearing in mind the treaty rights of French subjects. I have, &amp;c. FRANCIS BERTIE^ Enclosure in No. 1. Memorandum: communicated, to M. Poincare' by Sir F. Bertie. HIS Majesty’s Government learn that official protest has been made to the Sultan of Muscat by the French consul in regard to the new regulations issued by his Highness for the control of the arms traffic. He has apparently notified to the Sultan that those regulations will not receive the approval of the French Government unless the Sultan be prepared to recognise the right to compensation of the French merchants interested in the traffic Sir Francis Bertie has been instructed to explain to M. Poincare without delay the attitude of His Majesty’s Government. The question of this traffic is a matter of vital importance to the Indian Empire as a civilising Power in Asia, and the continual introduction of arms into the regions on the Indian frontier from Muscat is a cause of constant unrest and serious danger to peace and good order. In Persia also the maintenance of order is rendered impossible owing to the smuggling of arms into the country from Muscat, and, seeing that French citizens are prepared to participate in the provision of capital for the Trans- Persian Railway, the French Government are themselves interested in the maintenance of order in the dominions of the Shah. An instance of this smuggling is given in a recent report from His Majesty’s consul in Fars, which states that large consignments of rifle ammunition lately arrived in Shiraz, bringing down the price of Mauser cartridges in the open bazaar by more than 50 per cent., and that just as the tribesmen were beginning to feel the want of ammunition. His Majesty’s Government were not successful in their appeals to the French Government before and at the time of the Brussels Conference for assistance in putting an end to the traffic, and, therefore, in order to minimise its danger they had no option but to engage in naval operations of a very costly character, entailing much hardship on the officers and crews. The object of these operations was to prevent arms, a considerable portion of which would eventually find their way to tribes upon the Indian frontier, from being smuggled into territories the rulers of which had forbidden the import of arms in the ordinary course of trade, and had sought the assistance of His Majesty’s Government in preventing it. The operations had had a good but not a conclusive result, and His Majesty’s Government therefore welcomed the co-operation of the Sultan of Muscat when he agreed to assist in the prevention of this illegal traffic by issuing the regulations of which the French consul complains. These regulations do not infringe in any way the treaty rights of any foreign Power, as it is, in the opinion of His Majesty’s Government, the incontestable right of the Sultan, in virtue ot his sovereignty, to supervise the trade in weapons carried on in his dominion, and to retain control over their distribution. This is likewise incumbent on him in view of his relations with neighbouring States, where the importation of arms is forbidden. It is therefore out of the question that his Highness should be expected to compensate merchants who may consider that they suffer inconvenience by the existence of any regulations at all, and His Majesty’s Government have promised and are fully determined to support in refusing any such compensation. They trust, however, that the claim advanced by the French consul will not be countenanced by the French Government. In 1907 the French Government, who were anxious to prevent the introduction into Morocco of arms and ammunition which might be used by the natives to the detriment of Trench interests, sought and obtained from His Majesty’s Government the right of search of British vessels in Moroccan waters. On that occasion His Majesty s Government, in their desire to do all in their power to aid F’rance in her difficulties, at once acceded to the French request, although no obligation to do so lay upon them, and they feel confident that the French Government will not refuse to recognise their right to ask for the same friendly treatment in Muscat as they accorded to France in Morocco. Paris, August 22, 1912.From Viceroy, 28th August 1912. [Repeated to Resident at Bushire and Political Agent, Maskat.) Your telegram of the 23rd August last. Maskat. Political Agent reports that Sultan objected strongly to expression “ to expect him to compensate would be unreasonable ” in the reply suggested in your telegram of 20th August. Political Agent accordingly allowed him to alter this to “ payment of compensation would be unreasonable.” This appears unobjectionable. Sultan replied accordingly. Knox telegraphed on 25th August:— “French Consul has now replied to His Highness’ communication stating that he has no doubt as to His Highness’ independence and Foreign Power (sic) but he does not see the connection between them and subject of his letters. “ Next refers to freedom of trade and limit of duties to 5 per cent. “ Lays stress upon French Treaty of 1844 and fact that it cannot be changed without the consent of signatories of the Treaty. “ Repeats orders of his Government and that it will not admit enforcement of new arrangement without compensation. “ He says that rights of France are preserved according to law of nations although His Highness will not accept liability for compensation.’ We consider Sultan should now be advised to reply, “ Your attitude in regard to my proposed regulation of trade does concern and affect my independence which is jointly guaranteed by Governments of France and Great Britain. The question is one for discussion between those Govern ments, and I regret I cannot further discuss this question with you. 1 intend to proceed with the regulation of arms traffic as announced. To this end I shall publish on 1 st September an order to effect that sale or removal of arms and ammunition will not be permitted except after passing through special warehouse, and that Maskat subjects will be severely punished if they assist in such sale or removal. 1 trust you will direct French subjects to comply like others with rules and deposit their stocks in warehouse. I undertake to hold such stocks in trust pending decision of question by two Governments in Europe.” Should modus vivendi with French Government not be reached by 1st September we propose that Sultan should issue order as above, and after fortnight’s grace should order seizure and removal to warehouse of all fresh consignments coming by sea. As regards existing stocks he should place cordon round refractory dealers’ warehouses and arrest all Maskat subjects assisting in sale or removal. In accordance with preamble of the original notification Sultan should on or about 14th September publish subsidiary notification confirming all rules approved by that date.'[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Goverrvmcnt ] (No. 43. Africa.) ^ Foreign Office, August 19, 1912. ALTHOUGH the French Ambassador has not, since the date of my despatch No. 36 of the 26th ultimo, recurred to the question of the new regulations issued by the Sultan of Muscat for the control of the arms traffic, I learn from the accompanying telegrams,* which have been communicated to me by the Secretary of State for India, that official protest has been made to the Sultan by the French consul, who has apparently notified His Highness that the arrangements would not receive the approval of the French Government unless the Sultan is prepared to recognise the right to compensation of the French merchants interested in the traffic. I therefore think it desirable that you should explain to the French Minister for Foreign Affairs without further delay the attitude of His Majesty’s Government. Your Excellency is aware that this traffic is a matter of vital importance to the Indian Empire as a civilising Power in Asia, and that the flow of arms from Muscat into the regions on the Indian frontier is a cause of constant unrest and serious danger to the peace and good order of the country. In Persia also the maintenance of order, in which the French Government are themselves interested (seeing that their citizens are prepared to participate in the provision of capital for the Trans-Persian Railway), is rendered impossible by the smuggling of arms into the country from the depot at Muscat. For instance, as your Excellency will see from the enclosed copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran,! the acting British consul at Shiraz reports that large consignments of rifle ammunition have recently arrived there, bringing down the price of Mauser cartridges in the open bazaar by more than 50 per cent., and this just as the tribesmen were beginning to feel the want of ammunition. His Majesty’s Government were not successful in their appeals to the French Government before and at the time of the Brussels Conference for assistance in putting an end to the traffic, and they therefore had no option but to engage in naval operations of a very costly character, entailing much hardship on the officers and crews, in order to minimise the danger which was threatening the Empire. The object of these operations was to prevent arms, a considerable portion of which would eventually find their way to tribes upon the Indian frontier, from being smuggled into territories whose rulers had forbidden the import of arms in the ordinary course of trade, and desired the assistance of His Majesty’s Government in preventing it. The operations had an excellent but not a sufficient result, and His Majesty’s Government therefore welcomed the co-operation of the Sultan of Muscat when he agreed to assist in the prevention of this illegal traffic by issuing the regidations of which the French consul complains. These regulations in no way infringe the treaty rights of any foreign Power, as it is, in the opinion of His Majesty’s Government, the incontestable right of the Sultan in virtue of his sovereignty to supervise, without preventing, the trade in weapons carried on in his dominions and to retain control over their distribution, and this is equally incumbent on him in view of his relations with neighbouring States, in which the importation of arms is forbidden. It is therefore out of the question that His Highness should be expected to compensate merchants who may consider that they suffer inconvenience by the existence of any regulations at all, and His Majesty’s Government have promised, and are fully determined to support, him in refusing any such compensation. They trust, however, that the claim advanced by the French consul will not be pressed. * Government of India, Telegraphic, July 25; ditto, August, 5; ditto, August 8; and ditto, August 14. 1912. t Sir W. Townley, No. 134. , [A] ARMS TRAFFIC. [August 19.] CONFIDENTIAL. o &gt;_ c. Section L j -&gt; U [ 34578 ] Sir Edward Grey to Sir F. Bertie.• &amp; 2 It is hardly necessary to remind your Excellency that His Majesty’s Government, when similar circumstances arose in Moroccoj at once made their^ own commercial interests subservient to their desire to do all in their power to aid France in her diffi culties in those regions, and they hope that the French Government will not refuse tor' recognise their right to ask for the same friendly treatment in Muscat as they accorded f to France in Morocco. . . I request that your Excellency will see the Minister for r oreign Alrairs and make strong representations to him on this question, using such arguments in the sense of this despatch as you may consider desirable. I am, &amp;c. E. GREY. The Undw Forei3 $ &lt;i )h '' In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. us subject, please qi Sb/jtS . V. \ ' V' Aj f 1Y 50 and address— The Under-Secretary of Stat Foreign Office, London {Q t tate, \J} K *Jy •» \ v ^ r/' ^ v (K k. f i H - v The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for -— and, by direction of the Secretary of t State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, &lt;2 7. J 9 I 2 . Reference to previous letter * p v l ■''i... —^ Description of Inclosure.(5567a/ia). Shuula thy quystlon ht* arbit*ata&lt;i ulony and a dociulon by givyn In our favour, Jibuti iu likoly to bo cmba a d.op8t for thu anus truuu on m large a acala as yuseat, and ovon tha ordinary traffic is, as I huvo pointed out in another daspatch, vor^ dangorouu tho ptiaco of our possessions in tlio Bouuan and hnst Afi lea* It Is thoruforo very important that this traffic should, * if posoiblo b&lt;~ otoypud, and m havu in our opinion, good ground for holding that it is contrary to 111© Brussels Act to allow tho almost unrestricted import of arms into Abyssinia, Knowing that those anas will find their ‘way' into ths hands of tribesman, and equally contrary to the Brussels Act, as was pointed out in id95 by Baron Laiiboraont, 4^1 allow the export oi to pi? cos out- side thu wno from which they are Known to bo re introduced within the sous* moreover, what Baron Taxibunaont said of export from Jibuti scums to apply really to the passage of arms into the interior, for instancy, his conclusion that 'la Puissance locale a done robli ration s trie to do Ml la laser re exporter los I arms a(35d7ii/ia). to uj -4 it u-a a .aau-iito ol a«igo elating a C 4 &amp;- px'Oiaiao, With vmm?&amp; to .iiuucat tho quo®tIona v/hich arbitration Tribunal »ould havo to dociu-o .^uuiti bo i'irot^ .fhuthor tho rocont action of Uu Multan io rn infringo- uont of treaty right® which roMoro hlia Uablo to pay coaponoutlon, and oucona. If oo # -/hat extent of com- punaatlon ho uhoulci pay to tho Froach Govornmont, it buing unaurutooa that they /»ill not object to tno now ruloa if the compoaaation ic aaoquntc. If pou.-iblo, also compen.i»r.tion should bo limited to the arms ulr^uuy in tiuacat or in transit /hen the Sultan icauoti his waiining of the intendod ragulatlona* Should arbitration bo auggaatua by the French Gov- arnmont Your HxcoHoney uhoula insist, as f?u' as poaai- bia, on tho arbitration of all of the throe question® to which I have referred, but if it should ultimately prove necessary’to crop thou® relating to Jibuti and Abyssinia, you should prose the aura strongly for an arbitration of the muscat question within the limit® eh i ch(35672/12) which wa Arnlm. I should by glad to loarn whothor Your axcjlloncy concur® in this lino of argufy at, unu to roc ;lvo any obaorvationa %hloh you touy havo to offor. It. io and or- utood that thouo suggositionB arc only intoadud to bo acted upon in the event of Ilona i our Poincare pro pac ing arbitration ant. that Your Excellency thou Id not | | take any initiative in this direction. Moan*hlla, it la the intention of Hie Lajeaty 1 ® Government to continue their fine support of the Sultan and Your Excellency ialght ^aako the French Gove muont aware of this and of the fact that two of Pis Majesty*» Ships are being sent to land their ueoistance to His H Ighnoss i f no ury in deal ing w i th tradors. I ma, with groat truth and respect. Sir, Your Excellency * s most obudlont. /,Q' ; ■ , ; 1 Oroive.In reply quote, M Confidential. r U Ov' v. in A dmiralty, 24th August 191 2 Sir / am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council docypher of a telegram dated 24th instant No. 117 from tho Commander-in-Ch iof on tho East Indies Station, relating to the state of affhirs in the neighbourhood of Muscat. I am. Sir, l our obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, IDIA Office. 125/6/11—[2925] 19694/P651 500 10/llv G&amp;S 2409i ^ I. V 4 Dccyphor of Telegram FROM - The O-in-C East Indies AT - Diyatalawa DATED - 24 August 1912, TO - The Secretary, Admiralty, No:- 117 With reference to telegram 72 from Admiralty S.M.O, Persian Gujf has been already directed to be at Muscat a few days before September 1st and to remain there until he is satisfied that there is no likelihood of any disturbance aetirg in concert with Political Agent S.N,0, is now being directed to proceed there at once. Political Agent does not anticipate trouble. I can roach Muscat in about seven days. Flagship is in dock.Enclosure *' i^+tsr from Ft j\c. 3 2v, dats ,j g AUGIy rz IfTzrv-p (Jl 168 Telegram P., No. 447 S., dated tlie 31st July 1912. From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Reference Admiral’s * Serial No. 153. telegram* No. 65, dated 22nd July 1912, regarding arms handed over by S.S. “ Patiala ” and please telegraph your opinion thereon.96 171 Telegram P., No. 67, dated the 29th July 1912. From—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, Diyatalawa, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department. The Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf has made the following report:— It is reported that in June eight thousand rounds of ammunition and three rifles were landed at Serahukan, which is near Hiinji, by a dhow belonging to Ahmed-bin-Esa, and that on the 19th July ammunition and rifles were sunk off the same place by the same dhow. The dhow was found hauled up on the beach and one of the crew captured. The “ Pelorus ” has brought her to Jask for further enquiry.172 Telegram P. } No. 783, dated the 1st (received 2nd) August 1912. From- Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. Pelese refer to your telegram* No. 433 S., 25tli ultimo, which was repeated ^ * serial No. 156 . to mG and addressed to the Political Agent at Maskat. Prom the wording of it I understood the meaning to he that the Prench Consul should be informed by the Sultan ad interim that the Consul’s representation was being considered by him and he would reply after doing so: and that in the meantime our views were (awaited ?) on the demand for compensation and as to nature (?) of the terms of the reply which the Sultan should be advised to send to the Prench Consul. The Political Agent’s views were awaited by me and have now been received. Prom a letter addressed to you a copy*of which with its enclosures should reach you on Monday, I find that Major Knox from your above f mentioned telegram understood the meaning to be that the grant to Prench merchants of compensation was in principle admitted; and that on this assumption the Sultan wrote on 27th ultimo by his advice to the Prench Consul saying that he was ready to listen to all that might be put forward by the Prench merchants through the Prench Consul and to consider it and reply after reflection. On the same date the Prench Consul replied and thanked His Highness for his kindness and asked him to complete it by stating whether he would undertake to pay the amount found to be deserved. A reply is asked for by the Consul. Por the warehouse scheme one of the main advantages claimed was, vide Government of India telegram to Secretary of State, No. 409, dated 10th July 1911 and my telegram No. M.—11, dated Maskat, 14th November 1911, that it afforded a means, and some hope, of avoiding payment of compensation. I cannot, therefore, think that the interpretation taken by Major Knox of your telegram was what you intended. I would suggest, if my view is correct, that advantage be now taken by the Sultan of the opening afforded to him by the second letter from the Prench Consul and a reply sent to the effect that legitimate trade is in no way calcu lated to be prejudiced by his measures, and that, although ready to receive representations from the Consul, as in duty bound, he can in no way admit any title to compensation on the part of the traders concerned. He should, if he is to reply in this sense, do so without delay. We can, when the Prench Government begin to worry the Sultan, then, as in the Prench flag case, come in on his behalf and make the best terms we can. Before offering further observations on Major Knox’s proposals or in reply to your telegram No. 4 33, I will await a reply to this message. Bepeated to Major Knox.98 - 174 Telegram P., No. 780, dated (and received) the 1st August 1912. Prom— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.T., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. Please refer to Poreign Department » Senai No. 168. telegram* No. 447 S., dated 31st July. I a°Tee with Admiral that we should destroy arms and ammunition in question” Owner is in imprisonment at Bushire undergoing six months. 175 Telegram P., No. S., dated the 2nd August 1912. From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—The Political Agent, Maskat (repeated to Resident, Bushire). Please refer to the telegramf from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No. 783, dated the 1st August t Semi No. 172 . 1912. You have apparently completely misunderstood my telegram J No. 433 S., 1 Sem 0 ' ' dated 25th July 1912, which directed you to advise Sultan pending further orders to give to the French Consul an entirely non-committal reply. You should now advise him to reply to the second letter from the Consul to the effect that Consul has apparently misun derstood his meaning, which was merely that his, i.e., French Consul’s, re presentation would be duly considered, and that he (Sultan) at present does not admit any liability whatever for measure which is calculated not to check but only to regulate legitimate trade, and that he will send a final reply later after full consideration of the case. The fact that Government is not likely to admit principle of compensation, and that he will be unwise to hold out any hopes to Consul of such admission should be made clear to the Sultan by you. i179 Telegram P., No. 122, dated (and received) the 4th August 1912. From—The Political Agent, Maskat, rj&gt; 0 The Foreign Secretary, Simla (repeated to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf)* The instructions which are contained in your telegram* of the 2nd August, 450 S., have been carried out and * serial No. 175. message has been communicated. lam sending a copy by post with translation. 180 No. 1561, dated Bushire, the 27th July (received 5th August) 1912 (Confidential). From—L ieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.L, Political Resident m the Persian Gulf, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to report that the Political Agent, Maskat, informs me that His Highness the Sultan, discussing with him the probable attitude ot French traders towards the warehouse scheme and the probable attempts o other merchants to transfer their stocks to French names, has asked 1m advice as to the possibility of (i) seizing and confiscating immediately from purchasers, arms bought from French merchants, (ii) punishing purchasers in addition, (iii) seizing French or local arms in transit between French godowns and French booms, and (iv) seizing French arms in Maskat bottoms. All this in the event of French traders declining to deposit their arms m ..m» s fl i offifn/iA nf thp French Government between now and India will be of a like opinion. « it is as well however, that all such problems should be placed before SfcSSiSSy w™ to fd.. t» dispositions o««t™CONFIDENTIAL. 181 No. 1563, dated Bushire, the 27th July (received 5th August) 1912. From—L ieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. y I have the honour to forward, for favour of consideration, copies of com- No. 104, dated isth July 1912. , munications received from Major Knox in Ko. 105’ dated 2ist July 1912. connection with the appointment by His Highness the Sultan, of a superintendent for the projected Arms Warehouse. 2. With reference to Foreign Department telegram No. S-116, dated the 8th March 1912 ; as the payment, or continuance, of the enhanced subsidy depends on our will and on the fundamental condition that the Sultan maintains the warehouse on a footing satisfactory to us, it does not appear to me of great importance that we should insist now on the exchange of fully official communi cations in connection with the appointment of the superintendent; but it seems essential that the Political Agent should remind His Highness on behalf of Govern ment that the superintendent will be a most responsible official and that his effi ciency will obviously be the chief factor on which the success of the whole measure will dependthat it is consequently necessary that in some form or another we should be assured both that the pay which he will receive will be high enough to place him beyond the reach of temptation and that the other terms of his contract are generally suitable ; and that it is therefore expected that His Highness will acquaint and consult the Political Agent fully, if informally, on these points. 3. As to the suitability of Saiyid Kasim, he seems 'primd facie a desirable candidate and if his antecedents prove satisfactory on varification, the Govern ment of India will, I hope, be pleased to acquiesce in his appointment provided that suitable terms can be arranged. Extract from a communication No. 104, dated the 18th July, from the Political Ayent, Maskat, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (First part deals with other matters). ******** —- x am arranging to put up His Highness' appointment of Saiyid Kasim officially for the approval of Government and am leaving alone for the present the question of his pay, as I think that I might do more harm than good by saying anything now. I understand from the Saiyid that his application is going through all right and that His Highness will inform me officially of his choice and will ask me to inform my Government, expressing a hope that his choice will meet with their approval. This seems to be the right formula. Would it be possible for Government, in their reply, or you, in forwarding it, to note that no mention has been made of the emoluments that Saiyid Kasim is to draw, and to say that you would like to know this and that you hope that His Highness has given particular attention to this most important point, and that the pay he will receive will be high enough to place this responsible official beyond the reach of temptation. v No. 105, dated the 21st July 1912. XYom—The Political Agent. Maskat, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. In continuation of my letter No. 104, dated the 18th July, paragraphs 2 and 3. There was a hitch in the submission by His Highness of his official letter an nouncing the appointment and I found it necessary to go round myself and see him about it which I did yesterday afternoon.2 I found His Highness extremely reluctant and he told me that he considered himself responsible for the working of the new arrangement and that an official submission of his nominee^ appointment, besides being an encroachment on his independence, would fetter him and render the dismissal of his servant without the consent of Government impossible. To this, His Highness wopld not submit. I had sent in a draft and asked His Highpess if an alteration of the terms thereof would meet the case/ His Highness said it was not the draft he objected to but the thincr itself. I did not press the matter further and hope that the testimonials which I now submit with the following additional information may perhaps be found to meet the case. Saivid Kasim is nearly 40 years of age ; the exact date of birth would be found in his service book, which is with the authorities of the East African Protectorate, or at the Colonial Office. He was educated at St. Vincent’s High School, Poona, and obtained a mat riculation certificate from the Bombay University in 1888. He entered the ser, vice of Government in 1889, served in India in the Post Office, Poona Division, until 1894, and the rest of his services can be reckoned from the letter, dated 21st April 1908, of the Postmaster-General, British East Africa and Uganda Pro tectorates. This with the information I have already sent is, I fear, all that is available. I will get Captain Little to examine him as to general health and will wire result to you. At our conversation of yesterday, His Highness said nothing that \\ould lead me to suppose that he was, as I had feared at first, in any way dissatisfied with Saiyid Kasim, whom he proposes to send to Bombay by next mail to select and print books and forms and order dies and stamps. His Highness begged me again to visit the godowns with Saiyid Kasim before the latter leaves for Bombay. I am not sure that I have grasped the significance of this last request, but both Saiyid Kasim and myself think it is only to tease the arms merchants. Z-lll. GOVERNMENT TELEGRAPH DEPARTMENT. Certified that Saiyid Kasim of the Postal Department, has been under a course of instruction in Telegraphy at the Bombay Pydhoni Training class, that he can read by ear 15 words open circuit, and 14 words closed circuit and send 20 2 words per minute, Morse signals, that he is able to put up all the connections of the Morse instrument of the pattern used in the Indian Telegraph Department, including a battery of the Minotti pattern, and that he can adjust a relay, a sounder, and a bell. He has a sufficient knowledge of the rules and rates contained in the Indian Telegraph Guide. He understands the rules for the transmission and delivery of messages, the keeping of the message registers, and the submission of message drafts and returns to, the Check Office as laid down in the Traffic Code. (Sd.) J. E. DEMPSTER, Assistant Superintendent, Bombay Island Sub-Division. Dated Bombay, the 20th of April 1891. Mombassa, March 18th, 1908. I have known Mr. Saiyid Kasim well for many years, nnd have always regarded him with great respect.Mr. Bemington, the late Postmaster-General, has more than once spoken to me in the highest terms of regard and respect of Mr. Kasim both as an official and a man. He was absoluelty trustworthy. I have always looked upon Mr. Kesim as a personal friend, and I regret that such an efficient servant of Government should be forced to retire while in his prime owing to his eye-sight. C. A. BEDDIE, District Commissioner. MOMBASSA, East Africa Protectorate, To 16th April 1908. SAIYID KASIM, Esq., First Personal Assistant to the Postmaster-General, Mombassa. Sir, We, your friends and admirers, feel it our duty on the eve of your departure for India, to express our feelings of heartfelt gratitude for the valuable services render ed to the pubic of Mombassa in connection with Postal Service of this Protectorate, your readiness at all times to advise your countrymen and friends on any subject tending to their welfare, place you pre-eminently as one of those Indians who have made a name in this Protectorate. We know your merits and cannot refrain from publicly acknowledging them, and as a small token of our esteem and affection we request your kind acceptance of a silver photo-frame and silver cigarette case which we have subscribed for. In conclusion we wish a pleasant voyage to India many prosperous days and success in any career that you may wish to enter. With our best wishes we subscribe ourselves, Yours sincerely, (Sd.) J. A. C. BUKKE, Barrister-at-Law. (Sd.) WILLIAM A. BOWEN, M.B., and 13 more signatures. Mombassa, April 20th, 1908. Dear Mr. Kasim, It is with much regret that I hear you have been compelled through illness to retire from the Protectorate service. During the 11 years I have had the pleasure of knowing you, I have always found yop. most courteous and obligingj and I have never in my official capacity as Auditor of this Protectorate had the slightest fault to find with your work. That you may be spared for many years to enjoy your well-earned pension is the heartfelt wish of Yours most sincerely, (Sd.) H. C. E. BABNES, Local Auditor, East Africa Protectorate.W'Vmrr 4 Presented to Saiyid Kasim as a token of esteem and good-will by the Post master-General of East Africa and Uganda and the officers of the General Post Office, Mombassa, on the occasion of his retirement from the post of Chief Assistant in the Department after 15 years of meritorious service in East Africa. During this period he has by his unvarying kindly disposition greatly attached himself to every member of the Staff and it is with the greatest regret to all that he vacates this position. The signatories hereto sincerely wish him every sucess and hope that in the more favourable climate of his native land he may recover from the illness which has led to his retirement and may he enjoy many years of happiness and prosperity. (Sd.) J, GOSLING, Postmaster-Generaly and 37 signatures of the Officers of the General Post Office, Mombassa. Bated 18th April 1908, British East Africa and Uganda.^ Saiyid Kasim is to-day leaving this department having been invalided with a small pension on account of a disease of the eyes, 2. He first entered the service of the Imperial British East Africa Company in 1894 and was taken over by the Imperial Government in 1895. He was my predecessor’s Chief Assistant for some 10 years and has been similarly employed during the 4 years of my own control of this department. 3. Saiyid Kasim’s work and conduct have been excellent. He has creditably filled a position of trust and responsibility for some 14 years to the complete satisfaction of his superior officers, (Sd.) J. GOSLING, Postmaster- Generaly British East Africa and Uganda Protectorates, General Post Office, Mombassa, The 21st April 1908, p k Certified that I have to-day carefully examined Saiyid Kasim and cannot find any signs of organic disease and consider him fiffor the duties of Superintendent of the Arms Warehouse. Maskat, '1 J. W. LITTLE, Captain, M.B., I.M.S., The 22nd July 1912. ) Agency Surgeon, Maskat. €t. M. Press, Simla.—No. C-318 F. D.—&amp;8-I2.—66.—B.A.182 No. 1B66, dated Bushire, the 27th July (received 5th August) 1912 (Confidential). From— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to submit a copy of a communication received from Ko. 104 A., dated 19th July 1912, with enclosures. -^cdifical Agent, Maskat, OU the subject of the special warehouse accom modation for the storage of arms which the Sultan proposes to provide under the new arrangement. 2. My original idea was a new warehouse built ad hoc, but, in the first place, it was very difficult to find any suitable site for such a building, and, secondly, His Highness the Sultan, wise in his generation, believes that, if the arrangement takes full shape, the trade will cease to exist after a year or two, and that it would be waste of money to expend a large sum now on a new building which will be useless in a few years. He, therefore, wishes to utilize godowns which he has already got. Though the arrangement cannot be so satisfactory as the provision of a new building, I hardly think we need insist on the construction of the latter, and if the Government of India see no reason to differ, I would request the favour of the issue of telegraphic authority for the Political Agent to proceed on the lines of paragraph 5 of his letter. No. 104 A., dated Maskat, the 19th July 1912 (Confidential). From— Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Maskat, To— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, I have the honour to submit, herewith, the copy in duplicate of a sketch, of which the original was prepared by Mr. Ahmed Shubaili in the employ of His Highness the Sultan of Maskat. This sketch was handed to me by His Highness with the intimation that His Highness was prepared to allot any or all of the State godowns marked on the sketch for the purposes of the arms warehouse. Tiie sketch was handed over to me personally on the afternoon of the 17th July. 2. Mr. Storrs of the Public Works Department happened to be staying in Maskat at the time and I arranged with His Highness through Siiyid Kasim, the proposed holder of the appointment of the Superintendent of the Arms Warehouse, that I and Mr. Storrs, accompanied by Saiyid Kasim, should inspect the proposed warehouse accommodation the following day. 3. It was found at our inspection that the sketch, though rough, gave a very fair idea of the ground, and that the measurements were generally accurate. The buildings were substantial and generally in fair repair but light and air was badly needed ; and it would be essential if they are utilised for arms warehouse purposes that good substantial doors with stout locks ] should be provided. More than that, for reasons stated below, I do not think i is required. Mr. Storrs and I noted down briefly the essential repairs which are attached in statement A accompanying this report. 4. I have reason to believe that His Highness is averse to any large expenditure on godowns at the outset and am inclined to sympathise with his reasons for holding this view. It is very difficult to estimate exactly what accommodation will be required and there is every reason to hope that, if the arms warehouse scheme proves a success, the accommodation required will, in a couple of years or so, prove to be ^th or less of present requirements. Statement B attached to this report will show why I trust that godowns A to E, a fairly compact mass of contiguous buildings, will, with 1, be adequate for the purpose. •2 5. I have now the honour to request that I may he favoured with the tentative approval of Government to the scheme foreshadowed in the above paragraphs, and that I may be instructed to inform His Highness that there is no desire to involve His Highness in any immediately large expenditure on buildings, but that I am directed to press for the immediate and essential repairs to be carried out with the utmost despatch and that the Government reserves to itself the right to press for the provision of thoroughly secure and suitable buildings when the trade has been reduced to its legitimate propor tions and when His Highness has, in consultation with the Political Agent, been able to arrive at a just estimate of the permanent accommodation which will he required. 6. On the return of Mr. Storrs to Maskat in about a fortnight’s time, I will endeavour to obtain from him estimates of the expenditure to which His Highness will be put in connection with the repairs noted in statement A and will forward copies as early as possible. 7. In conclusion, I have the honour to request that sanction, if granted, to my proposals, contained in paragraph 5, may be communicated to me by telegram. «Statement A. 1. All fanlights to be changed from cement to wooden frames with iron bars. 2. The chandals in the south end of room D are rotten and require to be shored up by a beam supported on two wooden pillars. It is difficult to replace these chandals, because the upper floor is a dwelling house. 3. Enlarge the south window in south wall of D eastwards of eight feet broad, height as at present. 4. Two windows in wall between C and D on either side of door. o. Large window required in south wall of B. 6. Long window in wall between 3) and A. 7. Connect A and E with long window. 8. Close existing windows in west and north walls of room E and put long window in each wall at height of 10 feet. 9. New outer doors to be provided throughout buildings in place of existing outer doors. All doors to be 4' X 7', exclusive of frame. If possible, they should be iron barred and planked. 10. There is another pair of godowns marked on sketch I. They are coloured as if private godowns, but it is understood that they are available. They would probably prove useful as a record room and the inner godown for confiscated arms and arms adjudged to His Highness. Statement B. Showing relative net cubical capacity of godowns which His Highness the Sultan of Maskat proposes to allot for Arms Warehouse purposes as com pared with the cubical measurements of arms and ammunition imported during the 1st quarter of the financial year, April to June 1912. The net cubical capacity of each godown has been calculated as follows :— Length and breadth by 10 feet— l.xb.x io ft. h— .- npit cubical capacity of godown. Although the godowns are usually from 10 to 17 feet in height, the height has been arbitrarily fixed at 10 feet owing to the impossibility of piling cases higher than 10 feet. Cubic feet. Godown A 31 X 11 X 10 - 31x11x10 4 = Godown B HZ 18 X 18 X 10 - 18x18x10 4 = Godown C I 38 X 8 X 10 - 38x8x 10 4 = Godown D 18 X 20*5 X 10 - 18 x 20-6 x 10 4 = Godown E == 22 X 13 X 10 - 22 X r3 X10 4 = 2,558 2,130 2,280 2,768 2,115 Total nett capacity of A to E Godown E = 35 X 15 X 10 Godown G = 16 X 10 X 10 — Godown H = 16 X 18 X 10 ... 12,181 35x15x10 3,938 16X10X10 __ 1,200 16x18x10 O ,160 4 ’ Total capacity of all State godowns offered ... 19.4796 Cubic measurements of arms and ammunition imported into Maskat during the months of April, May and June 1912— N.B .—One case of 15 rifles reckoned as 11 cubic feet. One case of 1,500 round ammunition reckoned as one cubic foot. Cubic feet. Rifles imported 387 cases—387 X 11 = ... ... 4,257 Ammunition imported 3,581 cases—3,581 X 1 = ... 3,581 Total cubic measurements 7,838 It may be inferred from the above that godowns A to E will suffice as, at the opening of the arms warehouse on 1st September, large quantities of the importations, unprecedently large, of the 1st quarter of the year will have been got rid of. The existing stocks of British merchants have been calculated and would appear to amount to only 1,600 cubic feet approximately. Probably such existing stocks as are surrendered will only fill half the accom modation available in godowns A to E. It is impossible to say what the effect on importations after 1st September of His Highness’s establishment of an arms warehouse will be. Large stocks are no doubt held in Sohar and the interior but the following up of these and placing them in the arms warehouse will be extremely difficult. The first raid on Sohar, for example, would be the signal for the withdrawal of other stocks held in the interior to places beyond pursuit. S. G. Knox, Major, Political Agent and Sis Britannic Majesty's Consul, Maskat• C\ %CONFIDENTIAL. 183 Confidential No. 112, dated Maskat, the 28th July (received 5th August) 1912, From— Major S. G. Knox, C.I.FL, Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Maskat, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your telegram,* No. S-433, # N 56 dated 25th (received the 26th) July 1912, and, in accordance with the directions contained therein, to submit my proposals as to the manner of dealing with the situation, created by the receipt by His Highness the Sultan of the letter from my French colleague, of which a copy, with translation, was forwarded to you under cover of my confidential endorsement,| t Pro. No. 160. No. 107, dated 23rd July. 2. I take this opportunity of enclosing the translation of the ‘ ‘ add interim reply (Appendix A to this report) sent by His Highness, acting on the advice given him in accordance with the instructions, contained in your telegram already quoted, to my French colleague. X visited His Highness that same evening and he handed to me the French ConsuFs reply. It has been copied and translated, and the copy, with translation, forms Appendix B to this report. 3. From the terms of telegram^ No. 433, already quoted, I take the liberty of postulating that the grant of compensa- t Pro. No. 156. tion has been admitted, in principle, to the French merchants, and that the only matters, now left for consideration, are to whom, how, and on what terms such compensation should be granted. This assumption is considerably strengthened § Serial No. 121 . enclosures to the Secret§ Despatch No. 24, dated India Office, London, 14th of June 1912, to the address of His Excellency The Right Honourable the Governor-General of India in Council, of which a* copy has been forwarded tome through the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4. Pending the receipt of the French proposals in detail, it is somewhat diffi cult to lay down the reply to meet their case, but I trust that the conditions of compensation which I have tabulated separately so as to form Appendix C to tais report may be found useful as a basis of discussion. 5. These conditions of compensation show the general lines on which X ven ture to suggest the negotiations should proceed. It remains to be considered how they should be conducted. We would be much further on our way i i would be possible for high authority to direct me to advise His Highness to admit frankly to my French colleague, in reply to his last letter which seems to call for some such admission, that he is prepared to grant money compensation, pro vided it can be arranged on terms satisfactory to both parties. 6 The draft of this replv seems to call for most cautious handling. I mis- trust especially the words “ right to compensation which are the key-note ot my colleague’s letter, and am anxious to find a way, to convey to him, withou ofiending French susceptibilities, that His Highness considers that the French, and the French only, by good fortune stand in an exceptionally favoured position under a treaty which did not, at the time, contemplate the conditions that have since arisen, and that His Highness is prepared to grant the money compen sation in order to free himself from the difficulties in which the arms traffic has involved him with good friends and neighbours. This might be considered an unnecessary, and perhaps even irritating, piece of quibblng, were i no ^ certainty that, when once the public announcement of the French ^ hu3 , been made, His Hghness, in fact ourselves will be from all others interested m the arms trade that, if the French have “ rights ” that cannot be disregarded, we also have “ rights which ms be reckoned with. If we can delicately convey that we regard the French claims C317FD1 2 as a kind of legitimate extortion, to which we are unfortunately compelled to sub mit, we can, perhaps, meet the clamour of others with greater confidence. I have the honour to submit a draft reply (Appendix D to this report), in which, to the best of my poor abilities, I have endeavoured t o meet the situation. 7. In that draft, I have foreshadowed briefly the latter half of condition of compensation (A). This is especially important and should be done early, as I learn that it is already a matter of common report in the Maskat bazar that French traders will be compensated, and that British merchants are busy transferring, at half price, their stock in trade to their French brethren. However irritating such chicanery may be, from another point of view it is eminently satisfactory, inasmuch as it shows that the conviction has been borne in upon the minds of the trade that the arms traffic has come to an end. 8. An important advantage that I anticipate from the despatch of this reply to my colleague is that I hope thereby that the establishment and working of the Arms Warehouse will proceed smoothly and unfettered. It would only be neces sary for His Highness to give his personal guarantee that arms, the bond fide pro perty of French subjects, will not, pending an adjustment of this matter of com pensation, be subject to rent charges and that, in the event of no arrangement being come to between the two Governments, he will restore those arms to the French Consul. 9. The only point that, in my opinion, remains to be considered is whether it would be possible, or expedient, for me to appear personally at any stage of the proceedings. As soon as the draft reply, if approved, has been despatched, it would no doubt tend to clearness and celerity, if His Highness would authorise me to treat in this matter on his behalf and if my French colleague could also receive instructions to accept me as an intermediary and act himself as the autho rised agent of the French Government and of such of its subjects as are interested in this trade. I do not know if it is too much to hope that the conditions of com pensation, after such editing as may be found necessary, may be settled by High Authority at home and laid down for our mutual guidance.APPENDIX A. Translation of a letter from His Highness the Sultan of Mashit to the French Consul, Maskat dated 27th July 1912. After compliments, Your honoured letter, dated 23rd Tamuz 1912, equivalent to the 7th Sh’aban 1330 H., has reached us and all you have mentioned has become known to your friend, especially in the (matter of) compensation for loss which will fall on your merchants, as they allege. Now I am ready to listen to all that your merchants may put forward through the intermediary of your honoured excellency and to consider it and, after full consideration and reflection on their demands we will reply to Your Excellency. Usual ending. True translation. ♦ S. G. KNOX, Major, Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Maskat.Translation of a letter from the French Consul, Maskat, to His Highness the Sultan, Maskat, dated Z7th July 191%. Aftek compliments, Your honoured letter, dated the 11th Sh’aban, 1339-H.,has reached me and your friend has understood all that Your Majesty has mentioned therein, that you are prepared to hear the demands of our merchants through me and will reply after full consideration thereof. Yes ! You have been most gracious and we have no doubt that Your Majesty will complete \our jjjj^^ 2 iess and will answer us in the present matter, 1 mean to say, If our merchants show the loss and trouble to them from the new proclamation with perfect clearness, so that there remains no doubt to their right to money compensation, will Your Greatness accept to pay that com pensation ? ” And now, of this alone. We ask a reply of Your generosity and, if you grant it, as is hoped, then there will be, between the two parties, bound by mutual love, the method of arrangement in the fixing of the amount (to be paid). And may you remain among the thanked and greeting from your friend, the French Consul. (Sd.) A. JEANNIER. True translation. S. G. KNOX, Majpr, Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Maskat. coflf Frew totF rcl&amp;t' by I say ; ove: resi 1 i rAPPENDIX C. li CONDITIOKS OF COMPENSATION, If the two Governments, France and Oman, find themselves agreed on the question of •compensation, it is understood that all French traders in arms now in Maskat, and all future French arms traders, will be subject to the regulations, already issued by His Highness, relating to the Arms Traffic, and to all such (reasonable) (1) regulations (short of total prohibition) (1) relating to the Arms Traffic, as His Highness may be pleased to issue hereafter, A In the matter of compensation, only bond fide transactions and transactions which originated before the 22nd of July 1012, (2) will be considered. Any transaction which appears, on the face of it, to be a deliberate attempt on the part of merchants of other nationalities to escape the effect of His Highness’s proclamations will be ruled out. B Arms of French origin in the hands of French arms traders will be bought outright by the Sultan at market price (3). C No compensation to be paid for arms of which the origin is not traced, that is to sav, when the French holder is unable to show by what transaction they came into his hands. D No arms which have remained in the hands of the same French holder for a period of over two years will be entitled to compensation (4). E. Only bond fide French subjects, or proteges, are entitled to compensation (5). F A distinction must be drawn between arms, the actual property of French traders, resident in Maskat, and those for which they are merely agents : - (a) If the principal is a French firm, full compensation will be paid, i.e., the arms will be bought outright at market price. (b) If the principal be a foreign firm, i.e., other than French, only compensation 1 agency rights will be paid and the arms will go into the Arms Warehouse and be sold in the ordinary way. On the sale of such arms, the French trader should repay to His Highness, from the price of the arms, some fixed proportion of the agency compensation already paid. If the arms are merely got rid of (2) at a loss, in bulk, by transfer between traders, (6) no agency compensation need be returned J7). 1. Notes to the above. ? 1 Portions in brackets to be conceded, only if French insist theron, as they probably will. 9 This date has been selected as the nresumed date on which the instructions of the Frenc MiniLr t Foreign Afialrs reached m/French Colleague. It would be a great advantage, if it could be set back to the date of the proclamation. T 3 On the presumption that the British Government will ha^e to pay the price (apart l , o. Un tne presu p tQ be id tQ Hig U p 0 n terms already arranged inh^ttef of the establishment of the Arms Warehouse), these arms will be the property of the British Government who will be entitled to dispose of them as [it pleases. Any arms wh oh n Xhness might wish to retain for his own purposes would be paid for by him in such manner^as mayarranged. It will be necessary to make this clear to His Highness, but it is a side issue and does not concern the French. 4. The presumption is that they are dead stock, unsaleable. 5. For this purpose at least, French proteges must not include other nationals, their part- ners, or in their permanent employ. 6. The agent must be excluded from such transactions as a principal. 7 Agency compensation might be reckoned according to fixed percentage of the difference between the invoice value of goods and their market price, regard being had to trade custom in this respect. S. G. KNOX, Major, Political Agent and His Britannic Majestifs Consul, MasJcaLAPPENDIX D. Draft reply which it is suggested that His Highness the Sultan of Maslcat should send to the French Consul’s letter, dated the 27th July 1912. After compliments, I have received your honoured letter of the 27th Tamuz and have understood its contents. To avoid misunderstandings on the part of others concerned in the arms trade, I think it well that your friend should explain to your honour that this unrestricted arms traffic has been the source of much disturbance in other neighbouring stStes, has caused me myself some anxiety and might have involved me in difficulties with my neighbours. While I am fully aware that this traffic has enriched many French traders to whom you now desire I should pay additional profits, I am equally aware that, under a treaty, now nearly 80 years old, which certainly did not, at the time, contemplate the condition of affairs that has since arisen, rights have accrued to those French traders and I have no desire to escape from any liabilities, in which I may have unfortunately become involved. I therefore assure your honour that I am ready to pay suitable money compensation to all such French traders as can show that, in the ordinary course of trade and before they have had time to adapt themselves to the new conditions, they will be put to loss by the new arrange ments. These arrangements I have determined to enforce throughout my territories, so that other nations, to whom I am bound no less than I am to the great and friendly nation of France, may have no reason to complain of my country, or ports, being used to their detriment. But whereas unscrupulous persons of other nationalities are attempting, as I hear, to pass off their goods as French goods and even themselves as French protected persons, I must warn you, 0 my friend! that I cannot tolerate any such attempts to evade my lawful authority and impair my independence. Others, and I fear that some of your nationals may perhaps not be entirely free from connivance in this respect, have, I hear, been transferring their goods to French traders in order to escape these proclamations. I feel sure that you will countenance no such attempts of tin's kind and that I may rely on you to examine with the utmost care all such claims as you may present and that they shall only concern—- (a) Goods of French origin. (b) Goods, the bond fide property of French traders. (c) The agency rights in goods, other than French, in tne sale of which French traders may be interested as agents. I also understand that, in return for the promise that I now give to pay full compensation for proved loss, and my personal guarantee, which I now give also, that, if the two friendly Governments, France and Oman, fail to arrive at a friendly settlement of this question of com pensation, all goods now in Maskat territory, which your traders may deposit in the Arms Ware house, will be restored to you free of all rent, or other charges, I understand I repeat that your nationals will submit, without other reserve than those mentioned above, to my proclamations, relating to the arms traffic ; and that any French trader, found guilty in your court of offending against those regulations, will be excluded, ipso facto, from the benefits which I propose to confer upon your nationals. Usual ending. S. G. KNOX, Major, Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Masked. G. M. Press, Simla.—No. C,-317 F. D.—8-8-12—f&gt;6—B, A,188 Telegram P., No. 128, dated (and received) the 5th August 191£. j^rom—The Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. Following addressed to Political Resident, Persian Gulf -Begins. I an* forwarding by this mail to you a copy of the French Consul’s reply to the Sultan of Maskat and on Wednesday next to the Government of India, Foreign Department. It begins by acknowledging the receipt of the letter which he says repeats the meaning of the former which he understood. The French Government agrees to the enforcement of the new regulation, done without consulting French and opposed to Treaties, against French subjects if the Sultan of Maskat agrees to compensating French subjects. If Sultan refuses, France will do likewise. The Consul has been authorised by Government for the present not to settle amount but only to ask for the admission of the principle money compensation. French Consul disclaims on the part of the French Government support of false or unproved claims for compensation. Reply is requested to avoid delay to commerce. Ends.From Secretary of State to Viceroy, 2Qth August 1912. Private. My Foreign Secret telegram of the 23rd August. Muscat I have asked Admiralty to send naval Commander-in-Chief in person' on Slade s strong advice, but as there are two ships already at Muscat they have contented themselves with asking him by what date he can arrive himself if required. In view of delicate questions that may arise and of recent misunderstandings between Fox and Senior Naval Officer, are vou satisfied that subordinate officers will be sufficient ? From Viceroy, 21th August 1912. Pnvate. Muscat. Your private telegram of August 26th. Political Agent, Muscat, and Cox have telegraphed with reference to penultimate paragraph of your Foreign Secret telegram of August 23rd, that they fear arrival ol Admiral might be misunderstood by Sultan as indicating intention to coerce him. I think they are right, and consider it undesirable for Admiral to go to Muscat unless there are signs that French are despatching ships to Muscat. Admiralty might be asked to be on the look-out for any indication of this. In the meantime presence of one English war vessel in the Gulf in Muscat will suffice. Presence of Admiral may however be very desirable at commencement of October, when time arrives for confiscating existing stocks of arms stored outside bonded warehouses in defiance of Regulations. His arrival at that season is not unusual, would not be liable to be misunderstood, and would probably be welcomed by Sultan.Fr)m SecreHry of State to Viceroy, 2Qth August 1912. Private My Foreign Secret telegram of the 23rd August. Muscat. I tiave asked Admiralty to send naval Commander-in-Chief m person on Made’s strong advice, hut as there are two ships already at Muscat they have -.Gntentedr-themaie^^ what date he can arrive himse ^ renuired. fc-view of delicate questions that may arise ad»unders Land and Scidfn-F^vtrKhhccr, are you satisfied that subordinate officers will be sufficient ? From Viceroy, 27th August 1912. Private. Muscat. Your private telegram of August 2Gth. Political Agent, Muscat, and Cox have telegraphed with reference to penultimate paragraph of your Foreign Secret telegram of August 23rd, that they fear arrival of Admiral might be misunderstood by Sultan as indicating intention to coerce him. I think they are right, and consider it undesirable for Admiral to go to Muscat unless there are signs that French are despatching ships to Muscat. Admiralty might be asked to be on the look-out, for any mdication^ofdi^^g one English wa r vessel in the Gulf in ^ Presence of Admiral may however be very desirable at commencement of October, when time arrives for confiscating existing stocks of arms storei outside bonded warehouses in defiance of Regulations. His arrival at thi t season is not unusual, would not be liable to lie misunderstood, and would probably be welcomed by Sultan.L.P.—No. 8. In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote u - m44, ' 7 i. and address letter to— The Secretary, Admiralty, Whitehall, London, S.W. i J -^Sorificfentiaf' and Immediate :■ J/vf 0150 6/7 21,/g Admiralty, 23rd August 191 2. Sir, In reply to your letter of to-day's date. Ho.P.3250 relative to affairs at Muscat, I am commanded / by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to state / that H.M.Ships 'Espiegle” and 'Pelorus' are now at / Muscat. 2.- Copy of a telegram which has to-day been sent in cypher to the Commander—in—Chief, East Indies, is enclosed for the information of the Secretary of State. The Under Secretary of State, India Office. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,Copy of Cypher Telegram FROM - The Mmiralty DATED - 23 August 1912. TO - The Comaandor-in-Chiof East Indies ATv - Diyatalawa Bo:- 7 2 Arrange for continuous presence of H.M.Ships at Muscat to support Sultan during dispute with French Stop By what date can you roach there yourself if required.f loo put u.'v with.. Secret Department. Letter from Dated Bee. Formally acknowledged 191 Under Secretary. Secretary of Spate. Committee Under Secretary.. Secretary of State. Date. I Initials. SUBJECT. yuj /i. h}. $ Ccsrvrx(l~ dd/YYv^’ Copy to \ ► ^ (vPL^) 7?0. FOE USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. OiMpal - ^ ^^7 Previous Papers:- j ^ i U' 1 11859. I. 1993. 1000.-10/1911. [I. 1992.]From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 23rd August 1912. Foreign Secret. My telegram dated 20tli August. Muscat. It i s necessary to consider carefully position that will arise if modus vivendi with France is not reached by 1st September. Under proclamation Sultan may confiscate future consignments to dealers who do not comply with the regulations, and he will presumably do so after allowing reasonable grace, say a fortnight. But existing stocks which are very large must be dealt with also and confiscation of these might raise questions of extraterritoriality which must be avoided. It has been suggested that in the first instance Sultan should set guard round stores of dealers who refuse to comply, and allow no arms to be removed except to bonded warehouse. Please consider this in consultation with Cox. Foreign Office are prepared to support Sultan in this if you recommend it. , i • nm r . i I am urging Admiralty to instruct Naval Commander-m-Chiel to proceed to Muscat in person at the earliest possible date in order to anticipate nossible French action. F Your telegram dated 20th. Sultan should be warned as Fnox proposes.p 5a From Viceroy, 21st August 1912. Foreign, Secret. My telegram of 20th August. Muscat arms warehouse. Following telegram of 18th August received from Cox “ Political Agent’s letter No. 124, dated 6th August. Position from local point of view is still as stated in my Despatch No. 1561 dated 27th July, and I can do no more than impress on Government approach of 1st September, and preliminary need for some knowledge of real attitude of French Government. Apart from issues already raised, Knox (? states) that a local dealer, subject to Sultan’s jurisdiction, who acts as commission agent of Germans amongst others, has received instructions from German Consulate in Gulf to store all arms held, or claimed to be held by or for German subjects, in a separate private storehouse under lock and to refuse to deposit them in customs warehouse on the ground that they are German property. Sultan, can, I hope be supported in ignoring snch pretensions. The status and disposal of Sohar depot after 1st September has to be considered. I will communicate after hearing Political Agent’s view.” Letters referred to were forwarded with weekly letters No. 32 M, dated 8th August and 33 M, dated 15th August.Secret, No. 24. India Office, London, 14th June 1912. To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. My Lord, W ith reference to the telegram of your Government, dated 16th Sultan of Muscat and the Arms May \ ° n the sub i ect of tbe treaty Traffic. relations of the Sultan of Muscat . with the French Government in t eir bearing on the arms traffic, I forward, for the information of Your * India Office to Foreign Office, dated ExCellenC y in Council, copy of 22nd May 1912. correspondence* with the Foreign Foreign Office to India Office, dated Offiro frnm U ui n 30th May 1912. wmce, irom wincn it will be seen that His Majesty’s Government could not advise him to prohibit the import of arms. I have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) Crewe.A ENCLOSURES. Enclosure No. 1. India Office to Foreign Office. a- India Office, wj *. i n , . 22m\ May 1912. ; Vlt ^ f eferenc ® to this Office letter of the 13th instant forwarding C0 Py &lt; of a telegram from the Resident, Bushire, regarding the treaty relations between France and Muscat in respect of thf armsUaffic I am ofThft 7 i 6 'fTUL S y tef ° r ImJia to ^close for the information IGth MwTq^fh Lh e i for 1&lt;orel 8‘ 1 ;\ ffalrs «°py of a telegram dated Ibth May 1912 that has been received from the Government of India on the same subject. hv Q^ e p M n rqmS °} 0rewe w , 0 ' ld L ver - v §' lad if the arguments advanced L q L r 0X ’u an n sll PP 0 rted by the Government of India, should appear to Sir Edward Grey of sufficient strength to justify His Majesty’s Government in advising the Sultan of Muscat to prohioit the import of arms and ammunition. For his own part he is inclined to doubt whether the silence of the I reach Government with regard to the prohibition ssued by the 1 ersian Government is not due rather to the absence of any direct trade in arms between France and Persia than to an intention to admit the validity of the prohibition. tt ! s * lso Levant to observe that the treaty of 1833 between the United States of America and Muscat, the advantages of which are secured to France by tne operation of the most-favoured-nation treatment clause m her own treaty, provides that “munitions of war may be freely sold without any restriction whatever ” in all the ports of Oman. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. I am, &amp;c., L. Abrahams. Enclosure No. 2. Foreign Office to India Office. Sir, No. 22,000. Foreign Office, 30t,h May 1912. I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letters of the 13th and 22nd instant (P. 1844) respecting the proposal made by Sir P. Cox that the Sultan of Muskat should be advised to prohibit the importation of arms and ammunition into his dominions. In his telegram of the 11th instant, Sir P. Cox refers to the prohibition of the importation of arms into Persia and to the com mercial treaties existing between Persia and other Powers. I am, however, to state for the information of the Marquess of Crewe that Sir E. Grey does not consider that it would be possible to treat the two cases as analogous. As Sir P. Cox points out, the majority of the treaties between Persia and other Powers, though not that with France contain a stipulation to the effect that traders are to be subject to the laws of the country in which their trade is carried on, while not only is there no such stipulation in any treaty between France and Muscat, but it is even laid down in the Treaty of 1844 (Article XI.) that “ Aucun “ article quelconque de commerce ne sera prohibe, soit a Fimportation, S. 163. A 2“ soit a I’exportation, dans les Etats de Son Altesse le Sultan de u Maqrate ” Sir E. Grey considers that m vie\\ oi the terms of M this provision the Sultan would undoubtedly place himself m the wrong were he to prohibit the importation of arms, and he consi s that ft would be impossible for His Majesty s Government to advise him t0 &amp; I am further 1 tcf add that, as Lord Crewe is aware in the discussions with the French Government on the subject of the arm^aftc 1 Majesty’s Government have always admitted that M 16 J?re acting strictly within their treaty rights in carrying on the . tladl „ v Muskat Inhrese circumstances it would be difficult, in view o “phcit terms of the treaty provision referred to a bove “ow to pu forward the view that the Sultan of Muskat would be acting within powers in prohibiting the tiade. The Under Secretary of State for India. I am, &amp;c., W. Lain gley . V I144 Telegram P., No. 800—35 M., dated the 18th (received 20th) July 1912. From—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, Simla, To—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief. ^ The destructions by fire of the two dhows referred to in Your Excellency’s * Serial No. 129. telegram* No. 61 , dated the 4th July 1912, is agreed to by the Government of India. It is requested that necessary instructions may kindly be issued. \ 145 To His Majesty the Great Sultan, the Syud Faisal, son of the Syud Turki, Sultan of Maskat and Oman. Consulate of France at Maskat, Maskat; 11th Tamzu 1912. May his prosperity and majesty and independence endure ! Amen ! After increased greeting and prayer for well being and prosperity for ever. To-day your honoured letter, dated the 15th Eajab, on the details of the notice, dated the 16th Jamadi-al-Akhra, reached us, and your friend understood all it contained, but, as we wrote formerly to Your Majesty, it is impossible for us to enforce this arrangement on our subjects without the order of the Glori ous French Government, whose rights are safeguarded by the present treaty between the two Great Governments and let it not be hidden from your presence that, since the date of this treaty, no agreement has been come to between the two Governments for its alteration or not. This is what it was necesssary to describe and may you remain thanked. A . Jeannier.147 No. 869, dated Maskat, the 13th (received 22nd) July 1912. From— Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul at Maskat, To—'The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, I have the honour to forward, for your information, the copy of letter No. 867, dated the 13th July 1912, with its enclosures, which I have addressed to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. No. 867, dated Maskat, the 13th July 1912. From— Major S, G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul at Maskat, To—Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I have the honour to forward, for your information, a copy of the Note on the Arms Traffic in Maskat prepared in my office for the quarter ending 30th June 1912 with a copy of the statement showing the figures of arms and ammunition imported into Maskat for the same period. 2. To same time, copies of this letter with its enclosures have been for warded direct to the Hon’ble the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, the Secretary to His Excellency the Naval Commander- in-Chief, East Indies Station, and the Chief of the General Staff. Note on the Arms Traffic in Maskat. The attached statement shows the extent of arms and ammunition that each country has sent out during the three months ended 30 th June 1912. 2. The total value of arms and ammunition imported into Maskat during the quarter ending 30th June 1912 has amounted to the surprising figure of Rs. 14,75,118 as against Rs. 4,10,355 for the same period of the proceeding year thus showing an increase of Rs. 10,64,763 or as against Rs. 17,91,829, the total trade of the year 1911-12. 3. Of the Rs. 14,75,118, the value of rifles alone has amounted to Rs. 9,82,700 as against Rs. 3,09,635 or Rs. 6,73,065 more than that import ed during the same period of the last year. The value of ammunition is Rs. 4,92,418 as against Rs. 1,00,720 showing an increase of Rs. 3,91,696. 4. It will be noticed that of the total trade for the quarter Belgium has taken the largest share and then come England and Germany in rank. 5. The reason given for the enormous increase is that the merchants are alarmed at the British attitude in the traffic and are thorefore getting in their contracted quantities quicker than they would have done otherwise in order that they may get rid of the goods before the proposed restrictions are brought into operation. 6. Arms dealers have attempted to cancel their forward contracts but, it is said, the home manufacturers have declined to listen. Maskat, The 12th July 1912. i M. A. Fernandes, Head Clerk, Pol. Agency and II. B. M.’s Consulate, Maskat.86 V 148 No. 1449, dated Busliire, the 14th (received 22nd) July 1912. From—L ieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident » in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to refer to the application of the Shaikh of Kuwait to Kuwait Agency, No. 38 c., dated the i5th May he permitted to import a further, or en- 1912 , forwarded with letter* from Resident to hanced, quantity of arms and ammuni- Foreign Department, No. 167 M., dated the 10th ^ 1 ‘. , lii*^*!* June 1912 . tion, preferred in the Political Agent’a • Serial No. ioi. ' letter marginally cited. 2. I thought it advisable for several reasons to call at Kuwait before returning to head-quarters, and I discussed this question fully with the Shaikh. Beferring first to the question of the experiences of the dhows, of which he had complained, I repeated the explanations and expressions of regret author ised by Government and already communicated to him by Captain Shakespear, and informed him that their claims to compensation would go on with my support. He replied that he had been extremely upset about the matter at the time as he felt his dignity greatly lowered before his dependants, but was grateful for the action taken and hoped all would go right in future. Subsequently, after discussing the wireless question, we turned to the subject of his application for arms. I found the position to be as described in paragraph 2 of Captain Shakespear’s letter No. 38 C., dated 15th May 1912. He had not yet actually availed himself of the permission granted to him last July. The arms were still lying at Maskat, hut the fact was that he had received justifiable applications for arms so much in excess of the 2,500 weapons then authorised that to import that amount only would place him in a dilemma as to how to distribute them. He then went into the same details as given in his letter of 14th May asking urgently for authority to import the following :— Por his subjects— (i) Shamlan (a big Pearl-merchant) and his depend ants on the east side of the town ... 1,500 (ii) Nasir-ul-Badr (a big Pearl-merchant) and his dependants on the west side of the town ... 1,500 (hi) For himself, personally ... ... ... 1,000 (iv) For his tribesmen ... ... ... 2,000 Total ... 6,000 with 400 rounds per (rifle ?). ^ I could not get him to abate the indent, hut he repeatedly asseverated that the arms were solely for his pearling community and his own requirements, and that we might be absolutely assured that they would not go across the Gulf. He expressed his readiness to postpone bringing them up if we desired, until after 1st September, so that they could come through the Sultan’s special 'Warehouse ready marked, and reiterated his readiness at all times to mete out the severest punishment to any subject of his smuggling or selling arms out side his territory. 3. It is the fact that, though the indent is a large one, the reasons Shaikh Mubarak advances for the need of the arms are difficult to overcome, and that so long as they remain in Kuwait territory our interests are not immediately affected. 1 do not quite see how we can very well avoid compliance in this case* nor do I think it will be politic to do so. I therefore beg respectfully to support the demand on the same terms as last years and to request that, if Government can see their way to give decision by telegraph, they will be pleased to do so.Telegram P, } No. 63, dated the 19th July 1912. From—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, Diyatalawa, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, wires It is reported by Major Oraufurd that the dhow has been identified wrongly and that its owner has arrived at Jask. Guilt is admitted by the owner of the other dhow. Release of the former dhow is suggested by Major Craufurd and I have concurred in this suggestion. Instructions for the destruction of the ether dow have accordingly been • Serial No 144 issued. This is with reference to Marine Department telegram*', dated 18th July 1912, No. 800—35 M. 151 Telegram P., No. 108, dated (and received) the 24th July li&gt;i„ From—The Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. I received from His Highness this afternoon a letter, dated the 24th instant, from the French Consul conveying the instructions of his Governmen upon the proclamation issued by the Sultan. A translation as well as a vernacular copy of his letter will be sent to you by to-day’s mail. The follow ing is the gist of the letter:—“ Complaints have been lodged by merchants to the Minister for Foreign Affairs at Paris regarding the losses they will suffer if the arrangement is enforced. The French Consul is also directed by the Minister of Foreign Affairs to inform the Sultan that unless the merchants are compensated accordingly French approval is impossible. The Consul enquires what His Highness the Sultan’s intention is in regard to the matter of com pensation which he suggests is a question for arrangement between the Oman and French Governments. Reply as soon as possible please.” In acknowledg ing the receipt to His Highness I begged him to await the result of my consultations with the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Govern ment of India as to the reply. Repeated to Colonel Sir P f Z. Cox, Bushire.88 152 Telegram P., No. 800—39 M., dated the 23rd July 1912. From—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, To-His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Squadron. The destruction of the arms referred to in Your Excellency’s telegram* • semi No. 138. ■^°* 62, dated the 9th July 1912, is agreed * i .n x . to by the Government of India It k requested that necessary instructions may kindly be issued. « 153 Telegram P., No. 65, dated the 22nd July 1912. From—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, Diyatalawa, ^ 0 e P^ti.r rine Department (repeated 41 ammun!tion^ U an.cf* arms ZudSZyZ^ SF &amp;£; 8^7^“ steamer « Patiala » to His Majesty’s shir Alert . This is with reference to my telegram*, dated the 29th May 1912, No. 46. J # Serial No. 71.a, 'Agreed la - ^ 89 155 No. 212—1462 XIV N.-19, dated Diyatalawa, the 7th July 1912. From His Excellency Rear-Admiral the Hon'ble Sir A. E Bethelt, K.C.M.G., Commander-m-Chief, East Indies, To '- The ^cretary to the Government of India in the Marine Department. With reference to telegraphic correspondence ending with your telegram* • Serial No. 117, No. 800—29 M„ dated 26th June 1912, I t i-u • r .. „ have the honour to forward herewith fer the information of His Excellency the Viceroy and Governor-General of the Persian r n ,i}f’ the at 1 t . ach ®? detailod report from the Senior Naval Officer in e Persian Gulf, regarding the capture of the arms running dhows “ Adetre- man and ^handan ’ by the Armed Launch “ Miner ” on the 22nd May. oof ty’sship Capture of two dhows by “ Miner, ” 22nd May 1912. H. M. S. ‘‘ Fox ” at Hanjam; 15th June 1912. Sir, With reference to my telegram f No. 67 of 28th May 1912, I have the t Serial No. 71. honour to submit herewith the detailed n tttm n v report of Lieutenant and Commander dSlT/tZe dho e wt med LaUnCh “ Miner ” reSardiDg the ea P ture and 2. I have also received from the Political Resident a copy of his telegram t Semi No. 82 . { of 5th June, on the subject of these dhows. (Addressed to Foreign and repeated to Admiral.) I have, &amp;c., James C. Tancred, , . Captain and Senior Naval Officer. The Commander-in-Chief, His Majesty’s Ships and Vessels, East Indies. Sir, H. M. S. “ Miner ” at sea; 31st May 1912. I have the honour to report that H. M. S. “ Miner”, under my command captured the dhow “ Adetreman ”, owned by Pibi, a Hindu of Maskat* Nakhoda Carsum-bin-Subadar, under British colours, manned by a Maskat crew of eight, on the high seas, Lat. 25° 15' N., Long. 60° 24/ E. at 4 p.m. on the 23rd of May 1912, bound from Maskat to Charbar, she carried no* papers concerning her cargo and no permit from the Sultan of Maskat; dhow00 * carried one mauser pistol, 210 rounds of ammunition, she was in ballast, but carried one passenger Murad-bin-Chashi, bis wife, mother, two sisters and child. Murad reported that eight rifles, six mauser pistols and ammunition were thrown overboard about midnight on 22nd May, after meeting two badans, who reported that H. M. S. “ Miner ” was off Charbar. Carsum*bin-Subadar, the Nakhoda, whilst his dhow was been towed to Jask, confessed to a previous conviction and punishment of 40 days’ imprison ment for running arms. He says he was captured by H. M. S. “ Philomel ” about two years ago with 400 rifles. H. M. S. “ Miner” also captured the dhow “ Chandan”, owned by Abdu^ Shaloo and Haji Abdul Hussain, British subjects of Charbar, Nakhoda Doda- bin-Carsum, under Maskat colours, manned by a Baluchi crew of ten, off Charbar, Lat. 25° 18' N., Long. 60° 35' E., 9 p.m., 23rd May 1912, she carried no papers relating to her cargo. Dhow carried one mauser pistol, no ammunition. She carried eleven Baluchi passengers and a cargo of— 16 bales of linen, 1 bag of rice, 4 boxes of kerosene oil, none of which was owned by passengers or crew. Also one donkey, the property of one of the passengers. The Nakhoda was in charge of three bags of money, said by him to belong to Haji Abdul Hussain of Charbar (owner of the dhow) and to contain respectively— (а) 300 reals. (б) 300 rupees and 100 reals. (c) 1,000 rupees. This money was locked up and placed under a Guard until arrival at Jask, when it was counted and found correct except (b) which contained more than stated. The money, after being counted by Major Craufurd and myself, was placed in a sealed bag with a receipt of contents, and placed in the Guard Hoorn at Jask. Both dhows were towed to Jask, beached and thoroughly searched, no more arms being found. The cargo was landed and placed under the charge of a Military Guard ashore. Passengers and their effects were landed, and released after all informa tion required had been obtained from them, with the exception of Murad-bin- Chashi, who was made a prisoner and turned over to the Military Authorities, on account of information received from His Majesty’s Consul, Maskat. Dhows’ crews and effects were turned over to the Military. Dhows’ sails were unbent, rudders unshipped and placed on shore with cargo. Boats were hauled up on the beach. Dhows were moored off opposite the guard with two anchors down. In the “ Chandan,” the pistol was aft, under the cargo and sand ballast alongside the keel, the bottom of dhow was full of mud and water. In the “ Adetreman,” the pistol and ammunition was in a mat bag stowed under about one foot of sand ballast, aft. I have, &amp;c., The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. George Wilson, Lieutenant- Commander.156 Telegram No. 433 S., dated the 25th July 1912. From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To-The Political Agent, Maskat (repeated to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf Bushire). ’ Please refer to your telegram* No. 108, dated 24th instant. We await * Serial No. 151 . y our proposals, but in meantime Sultan , should be advised by you to send reply to French Consul that he will consider representation, and after full consideration that he will reply finally later. \ 159 Telegram, No. 1683 E.-A,, dated the 28th July 1912. From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. •SerialNo 141 Your telegram,* dated Uth July, 721. Kuwait. Amount of compensation sanctioned. 160 Consulate of France at Maskat. Maskat; 23rd Tamuz, 1912. To the presence of the great Sultan, the Syud Faisal, son of the Syud Turki, King of the Empire of Maskat and Oman. May his good fortune and Majesty and independence endure ! Amen ! Greeting to you and the blessings of God upon you for ever ! And after wards, it is petitioned to Your Majesty that all our merchants, the people92 concerned in the arms traffic, complained to His Excellency the Minister for Foreign Affairs at Paris and represented to him the great loss which will fall upon them if the new arrangement affecting their property and person, as written in your honoured proclamation, were approved. And our Glorious Minister wrote to me on the subject saying that the approval of the enforcement of the aforesaid was impossible for our Govern ment without compensation for the loss which will fall on our merchants and ordering me to inform Your Majesty accordingly. And upon this I do myself the honour to ask your greatness about your august intention in the matter of this compensation. And now the matter is on the basis of compensation alone, depending on the quantity thereof, which may be a matter of arrangement between the two Governments, bound by mutual love, Oman and France, if you accept it, as is expected, and we hope for a reply from your generosity, and may you remain among the thanked and greeting from your friend, the French Consul. A. Jeannier, True translation. The 23rd July 1912, S. G. Knox, Major, Political Agent and Eis Britannic Majesty's Consul, Maskat. Endorsement No. 107, dated the 2Srd (received 30th) July 1912. Copy, with copy of vernacular original,* forwarded with respectful com- » Not nrinted. plements of the undersigned to the P . Hon’ble the Secretary to the Govern- ment of India in the Foreign Department. S. G. Knox, Major, Political Agent and Eis Britannic Majesty's Consul, Maskat, 161 Telegram P., No. 66, dated the 26th July 1912. From—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, Diyatalawa, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department (repeated to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf). The proposal to destroy by fire the dhow which is used as a water boat at Jask and is beyond repairs and to retain in lieu captured dhow for the con- • Serial No. 149 . veyance of water, is approved by me. This is with reference to my telegram,* dated the 19th July 1912, No. 63.V From*'*His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, Diyatalawa, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Marine Department. On the 8th instant, I received the following message from Sir Percy Cox:— &lt;£ The letter from Your Excellency on the subject of the arms on board H. M. S. £ Espiegle * has been settled recently with His Highness the Sultan of Maskat on the assumption that the arms were to be destroyed. I consider that this can be done now as a matter of course.” I request that authority may be given for the destruction of the arms. The above is with reference to Sir E. Slade’s telegram* No. 36, dated the 12th April 1912, regarding the capture &lt;&lt; T?,c nipo’l A 5, . • Serial No. 71, Part VIII. of these badans by the “ Espiegle J140 IMo. 589—-46 M., dated (and received) Simla, the 12th July 1912 (Secret). From—The Officiating Secretary to the Government of India in the Army (Marine) Department, To—His Excellency Reae-Admlral the Hon'ble Sir A. E. Bethell, K.C.M.G., Commander-in-Chief, His Majesty’s Ships and Vessels, East Indies Squadron. With reference to the correspondence ending with Your Excellency’s telegram* No. 56, dated the 17th June 1912, I am directed to forward, for information, the accompanying capy of correspondence regarding the question whether, hut for the extension of the naval blockade measures to the Persian Gulf, two or at any rate one of the additional ships might not have been dispensed with. * Serial No. 105. Telepramf from the Secretary of State for India, dated the 26tb June 1912. TelrgramJ to the Secretary of State for India, No. 394 S., dated the 5th July 1912. f Serial No. 116. t Serial No. 128. 2. I am to request that the Government of India may he favoured with Tour Excellency’s views on the situation as it now stands in respect of the arms traffic operations, so that they may he able to submit to the Most Hon’ble the Secretary of State for India the report called for in his telegram,§ dated the 26th March 1912, a copy of which was forwarded to Your Excellency with Marine Department letter No, 589—-31 M., dated the 12th April 1912,141 Telegram. No. 721, dated the 14th (received 15th) July 1912. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—-The Foreign Secretary, Simla. Kuwait affairs. ‘Witli reference to paragraph 2, my letter* No. 167 M., * Serial No. 101 . please await letter. As regards enclosures t serial No.' 132 ! to Kesidency letter t 1276, 30th June, thanks to direct access of Political Agent to claimants, amount arrived at m paragraph 2 is very reasonable and I recommend that I may he authorise o pay it forthwith.DRAFT TELEGRAM. 4| SECRETARY OF STATE TO VICEROY, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla) Co^ i/C. Gapti (LJ^ A n aaj y ^ Ip n&gt; Despatched o2 3 Usd. 191^- . 12304. I. 242P. 500.-11/1911 Foreign Saorat. My tel&amp;grm 20th August * IMscat. It is necessary to consider carefully position that v:ill arise if nodus vivendi with France is not reached by 1st Septem ber. Wider proclamation Sultan may confiscate futute consignments to dealers who do not comply with the regulations arod he will presumably do so after allowing reasonable grace- say a fortnight. But existing stocks which are very large must be dealt m with also and confiscation of these might raise questions of extra- territotialityX It has been suggested that in the first instance Sultan should set guard round stores of dealers who refuse to comply and allow no arms to be removed except to bonded warehouse. Please consider this in consultation with Cox. L F.O.are prepared to support Sultan in this if you recommend it. N.P. I cm urging Admiralty to instruct Naval Commander in Chief to proceed to Muscat in person at the earliest possible date in order to anticipate possible French action. N.P. Your telegram 20th. Pulton should be loomed as Knox proposes.Copy* India Office. 21st August 1912 My dear Tilley, I spoke to Slade yesterday about the position at Muscat. 1. As regards sending a gunboat, he quite agrees, and thinks that the Naval Commander-in-Chief should go there himself early in September; he advises that we should, write to the Admiralty in this sense, and, if Foreign Office concur, I propose to put up a draft to Lord Crewe. 2. He thinks we should, consider at once very carefully what is to be done with existing stocks, if the French refuse to send them to the warehouse. (The importance of this is illustrated by the enor v m.ous imports during the last quarter, and. by the Sultan 1 s rather unguarded utterance reported in the O. of I's telegram, of the 20th sent to you yesterday). The penalty for non-compliance with the regulations is the confiscation of future consignments. Slade thinks it would, he dangerous to confiscate existing stocks in French possession, because questions of extra-territoriality might be raised. He therefore suggests that the Sultan should, put a giard round the houses of dealers who refuse to comply and. to prevent any arms from leaving except for the purpose of being taken to the warehouse* I propose the enclosed draft telegram,, but I send it to Foreign Office for concurrence before putting it up to Lord Crewe, because it is for Foreign Office to say whether the procedure proposed is consistent with the French treaty* If you say it is not, it is no use asking GovernmentGovernment of India to consider it. Will yon let me know as soon as possible, as the time is getting very short? Yours sincerely, (Signed) A. Hirtzel.In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. 35401/12. and address—- The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Foreign Office August 21St, 1912 tame ^ate Sir:- I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to acknow ledge the receipt of your letter (P.5199) of the 19th. / Instant regarding the traffic in arms at Muscat, and to state that he concurs in the terms of the telegram which the Secretary of State for India proposes to despatch to the Government of India, authorising the recommenda tion to the Sultan of Muscat of terms of reply to the representations of the French Consul. Sir E. Grey would propose an addition to the draft telegram to the Viceroy enclosed in your letter under reply, of a paragraph advising the Sultan to infoim the French Consul at Muscat that the matter is one which must he discussed between His Majesty's Government and the Government of the French Republic.In any further communication on this subject, please quote no.' 54578/12. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Ofhce, London. life*. Foreign Office August 20th, 1912. Sir: - I a r n directed by Secretary Sir E. G-rey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No.P.3066 of the 15th. instant, respecting the attitude of the French Government in relation to the Arms hare house at Muscat. As regards the reply vhich the Sultan should be advised to make to the representations of the French Consul, I am to state for the information of the Marquess of Crewe, that Sir E. Grey concurs in the proposal made in the Viceroy’s telegram of the ctn. instant that his Highness should reply in the sense of the communication made to Monsieur Gambon. His Highness might further make use of the arguments employed m the despatch ado.ressed to Sir 1. Bertie on the 19th. instant, in the terms of which Lord Crewe concurred, dealing with the question of compensation and with the sovereign rights of the Sultan. Should the French The Under Secretary of State India Office.(34578/12) French Consul refuse t»o accept an answer on anese lines Sir F. G-rey considers that he should be informed that tne matter is one for further discussion between the irencn Government and His Majesty’s Government in Europe. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,From Viceroy, 20th August 1912. Foreign Secret. My telegram of the 14th August. Muscat, warehouse. Knox telegraphs 17th:—“I am informed on good authority that Iriday last French merchants saw Sultan m open durbar. They said that they were not going to send their arms and ammunition to warehouse, sultan informed them if they did not obey proclamation he would have their shops watched and imprison all their customers. He added that he had no intention of burdening his and British subjects to French piofit. fully sympathising with motives that led His Highness to make tl declaration, I fear Government may find it premature. Step has been taken without consulting me, probably on the spur of the moment J report in case you may desire me to warn Sultan that his intentions In better not be disclosed until the moment comes to act, and perhaps mat before taking action he would do well to consult us.’In afly further communication on this subject, please quote No. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. iiqcjr Foreign Office August /J 1912. Sir: - i I am directed ty Secretary Sir E. Grey to trans mit to you herewith to he laid before the Secretary of State for India the draft of a despatch which it is proposed to address to His Majesty’s .Ambassador at Paris respecting the complaints made by the French Consul at Muscat in connexion with the regulations for the new Arms Warehouse. Sir E. Grey would be glad to learn whether Lord Crewe concurs in the terms of this draft. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,Registry No. a Draft. Sir F, Bertie. No. Africa. 3 ! 9 &lt;7- F. O., i Ir* Sir:- \\l/ $ igi 2 . Although the French Ambassador has not, since the date of my despatch No. 36 of the 26th. ultimo recurred to the question of the new regulations issued by the Sultan of Muscat for the control of the anns traffic, I learn from the accompanying telegrams which have been communicated to me by the Secre tary of State for India that official pro test has been made to the Sultan by the French Consul, who has apparently notified His Highness that the arrangements would not receive the approval of the French Govern ment unless the Sultan is prepared to recog nise the right to compensation of the French Merchants interested in the traffic. I therefore think it desirable that you should explain to the French Minister for Foreign AffairsAffairs without further delay the attitude of His Majesty’s Govemirient. Your Excellency is aware that this traffic is a matter of vital importance to the Indian Empire as a civilizing Power in Asia and that the flow of arms from Muscat into the regions on the Indian frontier is a cause of constant unrest and serious danger to the peace and good order of the country. In Persia also, the maintenance of order,in which the French Government are themselves interested t is rendered im- K possible by the smuggling of arms into the country from the depfrb at Muscat. For in- -stance as Your Excellency will see from the enclosed copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran, the Acting British Consul at Shiraz reports that large consignments of rifle ammunition have recent)- ly arrived there, bringing down the price of mauser cartridges in the open bazaar by more than 50% and this just as the tribesmen were1 were beginning to feel the want of aimnunition. v 3 » Llaje sty’s Government were not success ful in their appeals to the French Government before and at the time of the Brussels Confer ence for assistance in putting an end to the traffic, and they therefore had no option but to engage in naval operations of a very costly character entailing much hardship on the of ficers and crews, in order to minimize the danger which was threatening the Empire. The object of these operations was to prevent arms, a considerable portion of which would eventually find their way to tribes upon the Indian frontier, from being smuggled into territories whose rulers had forbidden the import of arms in the ordinary course of trade and desired the assistance of His Majesty’s Government in preventing it. The operations had an excellent but not a sufficient result and His Majesty’s Government therefore wel comed the co-operation of the Sultan of Muscat when he agreed to assist in the prevention of this illegal traffic by issuing the regula tionsu regulations of which the French Consul com plains . If These regulations in no way infringe the treaty rights of any foreign Power, as it is, in the opinion of His Majesty's G-ov- ernment, the incontestable right of the Sultan in virtue of his sovereignty to supervise, without preventing, the trade in weapons carried on in his dominions and to retain control over their distribution; and this is equally incumbent on him in view of his relations with neighbouring states, in which the importation of arms is forbidden. It is therefore out of the question that His Highness should be expected to compensate merchants who may consider that they suffer inconvenience by the existence of any regu- -lations at alluand His Majesty’s Govern ment have promised, and are fully determined to support him in refusing any such com pensationc ompenaat i on ,^tnd in car^jrng---arrange- wh-^^i-hQ hac propoaod* They trust how ever, that the claim advanced by the French Consul will not be pressed. It is hardly necessary to remind Your Excellency that His Majesty’s G-oveminent, when similar circumstances arose in Morocco, at once made their own commercial interests subservient to their desire to do all in their power to aid France in her difficulties in those regions, and they hope that the French G-ovemrnent will not refuse to recognise their right to ask for the same friendly treatment in Muscat as they accorded to France in Morocco. 1 request that Your Excellency will see the Minister for Foreign Affairs and make strong representations to him on this question using such arguments in the sense of this des patch as you may consider desirable.Qfa k3p lU CUa^i Prom Viceroy, X^ih August 1912. Foreign Secret. ^Reference to my telegrams of 8th August. Maskat \V arehouse. F rom 1 rench Consul’s letter to Sultan (copy now received) it is clear, unless Sultan admits principle of compensation, French Consul will support French traders in resisting warehouse scheme. As arranged this comes into force on 1st September, that is, within 17 days. To postpone it would indicate weakness and damage our position with Sultan and in Gulf generally. W e strongly deprecate any admission of principle of compensation. It appears from India Office letter of 18th July to Foreign Office that question of exchange of territory and interests with France has dropped, and that Maskat case must therefore be fought on its merits. Your Lordship doubtless recalls arguments suggested in paragraph 3 of India Office letter to Foreign Office of 1st April 1911. On this analogy it might now be xxnnted out to French Government that His Majesty’s Government are refusing to support claims for compensation by British firms whose rights are identical with French traders and whose interests are much greater, because such support is inconsistent with declaration of 1862, since warehouse scheme is merely regulation of, and not violation of, legitimate trade. If French Government support present attitude of French Consul, we recommend Sultan be advised to enforce warehouse rules against French traders, although it would be better to avoid this if possible. Cox recommends that Sultan should now be asked to delegate his authority to discuss question with French to us, but at present this seems unnecessary. Political Agent reports that with the exception of French and Arab traders people of Oman take cessation of trade as accepted fact with consequent rise in prices. As Sultan is very nervous and little time is left, we would ask for very early orders.From Viceroy, 5t/i August 1912. Foreign Secret. Maskat. My telegram of 25th July. M e have now received French Consul’s letter which contains little more than summary o-iven by Knox. We would suggest that Sultan should be advised to rep y fo French Consul in terms of Sir E. Grey’s reply to M. Cambon (v^de Foreign Office letter of 12th June forwarded with Political Secretary s letter No ^8, dated 12th July), with addition that therefore question of compensation does not arise. From Vicevoy to Political liesideut, Persian Gulf, Sth August 1912. (Repeated to Foreign Department.) Foreign Secret. My telegram of 5th August. Knox telegraphs 5th August: — “ Copy of French Consul’s reply to Sultan of Maskat goes by this mail to you and to Foreign Department of Government of India. (? It) begins by acknowledging the receipt of letter which he says repeats meaning of foimei which he understood. If the Sultan of Maskat agrees to compensate trench subjects, f rench Government agrees to enforcement of new regulation, done without consulting French and opposed to treaties, against French subjects, if Sultan refuses French do likewise. Consul authorised by Government only to ask for admission of principle of money compensation, not at present settling amount. T? , n 1 Reply is requested to avoid delay to commerce. trench Consul disclaims on the part of French Government support of false or unpioved claims for compensation.’ 7[This Document is ARMS TRAFFIC CONFIDENTIAL. the Property of His Britannic Majest^V- Ccpyerament.] [32153] Np - h Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Carnegie. (No. 36. Africa.) Foreign Office, July 26, 1912. ^ 'I SPOKE to M. Gambon to-day about the regulations for Muscat respecting arms. I observed that fairly interpreted, they were not a breach of French treaty rights. The raffic io arms was a very invidious thing. It had cost us a great deal of money and caused dancer in some localities. I hoped that the French Government would feel that their treaty rights should be construed fairly, and not in an extreme sense. M. Gambon said that the treaty rights gave the French freedom of commerce, and that the regulations were an impediment to commerce. I urged that freedom of commerce could not be understood to mean that commerce was to be free from all regulations. What was now being done would regulate, but would not suppress, the trade. Had we been m the position of the French, I was sure that we should have discouraged the traffic m arms, feeling what an invidious thing Wa M. Gambon said that his Government were quite ready for us to take Muscat or t0 ^Yanswered 1 ^ Yes; but the price they asked for either was enormous.” M. Gambon, in the course of the conversation, mentioned arbitration as an eventual possibility. j am, &amp;c. E. GREY. [2561 cc -1] ,l»^ '5X f irom His Excellency the Naval Commander-In-Chief, Diyatalawa, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department. th e e ^ instant ’ 1 received from the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Ouit the following message which had been repeated by him to the Political Resident m the Persian Gulf :— For some time owners of common badans have been engaged in illicit traffic in ammunition and arms in small quantities. The fact is not denied by the owners who have both gone to Islam Khan for compensation. I beg to suggest the destruction of the two * senai No 114 dhows. This is with reference to my telegram* No. 86 . Where complicity in the smuggling of arms has been proved, it is very desirable that examplary punishment should be awarded. It is requested that in the event of Sir Percy Cox concurring in the proposal, sanction may be accorded to the destruction of the dhows by fire. ,1 130 Telegram, No. 684, dated the 6th July 1912. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. Admiral’s telegram,! 4th July, to Marine Department. I concur in + serial No. 129. thinking that dhows should be burnt. Addressed Poreign Secretary to Government of India and repeated to Admiral.(31 132 No. 1276, dated Bushire, the 30th June (received 8th July) 1912 (Confidential). From—J. H. Bill, Esq., First Assistant Resident, Bushire (in the absence of the Resident), ,, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. With reference to the correspondence ending with Foreign Department • Serial So 102 telegram* Mo. 340 S., dated the 17th June 1912, 1 am directed to forward, for the information of the Government of India, a copy of the communication m ^ ^ ^ To.i T itvio marginally noted, received from the No. 264 . dated the 12 th June 1912 . -p. i.°. , ^ , . Political Agent at Kuwait, on the subject of claims for damages to Kuwait vessels searched by His Majesty’s ships in April last. 2. Sir Percy Cox asks me to say that he will send bis views by telegraph. No. 264, dated Kuwait, the 12th June 1912. From— Captain W, H. I. Shakespear, Political Agent, Kuwait, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. With reference to paragraph 5 of my letter 39 C., dated the 15th May, I have the honour to submit herewith the detailed statements of the Nakhodas and claims for damages to their vessels when searched by His Majesty’s ships in April last. 2. A perusal of the statements will show that in the case of one boat only, the “Fateh-al-Khair ,s , Nakhoda Abbas Ali, was the damage of areally serious nature. This vessel was searched by ilis Majesty’s ships “ Karanja ” and “ Alert ” and the bad weather at the time would appear to account largely for the damage done. The next most serious case is that of the “ Salmi ”, Nakhoda Nasir-bin-Abdul Latif, the claim being due principally to a damaged stem, which will necessitate considerable work in opening out the bagla’s stem, replacing the stem-piece and re-fixing her planking. In two cases, the damage is comparatively trifling, whilst in one no claim has been lodged. Summarised the claims are as follows:— Bs. a. By “ Fateh-al-Khair ”, Nakhoda Abbas Ali ... 1,346 8 0 By “ Salamati ”, Nakhoda Khalifa-bin-Sbahin 38 0 0 By “ Salmi ”, Nakhoda Nasir-bin-Abdul Latif 423 0 0 By “ Fateh-as-Salam ”, Nakhoda Ahmed-bin-Ghanim 108 0 0 By “ Suhail ”, Nakhoda Maiyuf-bin-Nasir-al-Badr ... Total ... 1,915 8 0 All these vessels excepting the first were searched hy H. M. S. “ Fox ”, whilst the last was also searched by an armed launch near Jask whose name I have not been able to ascertain. 3. With the detailed statements and claims for actual damage attached hereto, I have the honour to submit for consideration whether, in the circums tances, compensation should not be paid. No arms were found in any of these vessels, and the total claims amount to less than Us. 2,000 and, though the claims may not be sustainable in the face of our agreement with the Shaikh and his proclamation thereunder, I would venture to submit that it would be politic at the present time to remove, by the grant of compensation as .far as possible, such resentment as has been caused. It would be desirable, in the event of my suggestion meeting with approval, to emphasize the point that the searches were justified, and that compensation has been paid only as an act of grace./ 62 Statement of Abbas-bin-AH, Persian, Nakhoda of boom “ Fateh-al-Khair ”, owned by late Haji Muhammad Takey &amp; Sons. States— After reaching Maskat from Yemen on our homeward voyage, we stopped there nine or ten days, during which we took on board only seven corpses and no other cargo. We were about eight days out from Maskat and near Mughu on the 27th March (I am quoting from my ship’s diary log) when at about 4 o’clock, Arabic time, in the forenoon, as we were passing a small British armed launch, we were hailed and ordered to lower our sail and to come close up to her. We were then made fast and towed towards the land into nine fathoms of water, where we both anchord. The wind was a “ Kos ” at the time. Before we anchored, we asked the officer who boarded us when we were first hailed to have us towed to the safer harbour of Charak, but this was not done. When we anchored, the Captain also boarded us. The two vessels were then put along side each other, and they began to put the ribs and elbow timbers which we had as cargo on board the armed launch. When all these ribs had been transferred to tbe launch, they brought up the cases of fish-oil (sil) which we had stowed below and ranged them round our own decks. By this it was about 10 o’clock, Arabic time (late afternoon), and the wind had changed to a fresh “ shimal ”, the sea got up. We then said that there was nothing for it, but that they must tow us to the shelter of Charak. This the launch started to do, and we reached Hasina by 3 o’clock, Arabic (evening), one officer and an interpreter remaining on board of us during the tow. There our tow T line was cast off, and we were told to anchor. As we were in nine fathoms, we said our anchors would not hold, even the two w 7 e let go at first. Then the officer asked whether we had another, and we said yes, but that the three anchors drawing together would be certain to cut their coir cables, but the officer said “ No matter let it go ”, which we did. During the tow, the sea was so bad that the boat-ribs ^yhich had been transhipped to the armed launch, kept falling off her and floating away. We pointed this out to the officer with us, but he could do nothing. Our big anchor held us, and we passed the night there with the officer and interpreter on board our boom. During the night our anchors had dragged, and by morning we were in seven fathoms, when the launch came to us and having taken off the officer and interpreter went back to her anchorage. During the night and on our journey, the waves had been so bad that the cases of fish-oil which had been ranged on our decks were thrown down by tbe boat’s pitching into the hold and a good many broken. It was now the 27th March morning. The weather got worse and finally we made distress signals and shouted until, at last, at 8 o’clock, Arabic (afternoon), the launch came to us and cast a tow- line over the side. We could not reach it without sending out a man with a line to swim for it. All this time we could see our boat-ribs being washed off and rolling overboard from the launch the sea being so bad. When we got the tow-line we made it fast and the launch went ahead slow to help us get the anchors up. As we were getting in the big anchor’s cable, it parted, and the cable-end alone came in. Then we hove in the other two successfully. The launch then towed us on to Charak, where we arrived two hours after nightfall. There we dropped one anchor and held on with a line to the launch until the morning of the 29th March. About a half-hour after sunrise, the captain came tons, and, after some signalling to the launch, they sent an anchor into three lathoms and gave us the end of the line on which we hauled in our boom to the anchor. There they began to take all the fish-oil out of the hold where most of it had fallen and to put it on our own deck. 1 his continued until 5 o’clock, Arabic (about noon), when a big ship showed up. The Captain of the launch took her to the big ship, and the other officer remained with us, At 6 o’clock (Arabic), the launch came back and towed us to the big ship, where we were put alongside, but even on the lee side the sea was so rough that we were much damaged bumping against the big ship’s side; it \a as better after she put a stern anchor out to give us a lee, but even then ad. then the big ship took our cases of fish-oil on board of hersfelf working until three hours after sunset. Three blue jackets were then put into our boat, and we spent the night on a line astern of the big ship. Next day, the 30thMarcli, in tbr morning, the remaining cases of fish-oil were transhipped as well as the corpses. The coffins were each weighed, and one was eventually opened, though we had a letter from the Political Agent at Maskat. Everything we had even sails, ropes and gear was all transhipped. When our ’boat was empty, a carpenter came to us and inspected the planking to see if there was anything inside, and at 7 o’clock, Arabic, a diver was sent down who went for two hours all round the outside and bottom of our boat sounding her with a hammer. Then having satisfied themselves that we had no arms, the Sidi sailors on hoard began throwing back our cargo, without any regard for stowage or breakages, &amp;c. We begged to be allowed to load it properly, but nobody would listen, until the Captain came and allowed us to have the cargo handed down to us from the ship while we stowed it properly. This went on until four hours after sunset, by which time the cargo taken by the big ship was finished. Then I went on board the big ship and explained to the Captain that the cargo was ail consigned on Bills of Lading to merchants, and that I wanted a receipt for the damage and loss. He said he would give me a certificate and did so saying that there had been only a little damage. I produce it. (Copy taken of Commander Somerville’s certificate, dated 2nd May.) He refused to he responsible for what had happened while we were with the armed launch, and said I must go to her Captain for that. Next morning, the 31st March, I went to the launch and loaded back what was left of the boat-ribs and elbows which had remained on board her all this time. I then asked for a certificate of the damage and loss, and the Captain of the launch began writing out a long paper which he eventually tore up and then gave me this small piece I produce. (Copy of Lieutenant and Commander Blagrove’s note, dated 3rd May, taken.) When I complained that he had destroyed the detailed one he said I could take the smaller one and make my complaint in Kuwait and he would give his answer in detail, when asked for it. Then I pointed out that I had no big anchor and could not continue my voyage without, so asked him to lend me one from his ship, which I would deliver to the British officer in Kuwait on arrival, but he refused and offered to take me to the ground where we lost it and drag for it; we pointed out that the bottom there was soft mud and there was no chance of retrieving the anchor. Then he said we could remain where we were and he would try for it. He then went off in the armed launch, hut not towards the place as we could see it, being only five miles off. When we saw that he was going elsewhere, we left for Kuwait, going to Kais Island only on the journey. We suffered a lot from delay, damage and loss and so on, but we were not abused or anything of that sort, and the Captain took the responsibility of anything being found short on their vessels. My boat is a boom, “ Eateh-al-Khair ”, registered in the deceased Haji Muhammad Takey’s and his son’s names. The ship’s papers are sealed by Shaikh Mubarak. Bead over and admitted correct. Kuwait ; W. H. I. Shakespear, Captain, 17th May 1912. ) Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy of a letter produced by Abbas Ali, Nakhoda of boom “ Fateh-al-Khair H. M. S. “ Alert ”, Charak; 2nd May 1912. This is to certify that the dhow “ Eateh-al-Khair ” has been to-day and yesterday cleared and her cargo restored. Owing to the oil tins not being securely closed, a small quantity of oil was unavoidably spilt, probably 3 or 4 gallons. H. C. Somerville, Commander.Copy of a letter produced by Abbas All, Nakhoda of boom “ Fateh-al-Khair Charak; 3rd May 1912. This is to certify that I am they are said to concern me. concerning his cargo against me. prepared to answer any questions as far a&amp; As to any alleged damage, he may claim H. E. C. Blaghoye, Lieutenant and Commander, H. M. S. “ Karanja Office note by Political Agent, Kuwait. The discrepancy in dates is accounted for by the fact that these illiterate Nakhodas navigate by some kind of noon observations for which some use tables and others do not. The more educated (?) endeavour to keep their logs with English dates and frequently, as in the present case, are months wrong. Working backwards it would seem that— for 27th March should be read 29th April. „ 28th „ „ » 30th „ s , 29th „ „ „ „ 1st May. „ 30th ,, jj » 3 &gt; 2nd ,, 31st 3rd and the a. The armed launch in the statement refers to H. M. S. &lt;c Karanja big ship to H. M. S. “ Alert Kuwait ; y W. H. I. Shakespear, Captain, 18th May 1912. ) Political Agent, (Translation.) Keo’arding the damage to property, shipped in the boom “Eateh-al-Khair”., Nakhoda Abbas-bin-Ali, owner Muhammad Takey-bin-Ghalib &amp; Sons, from the ships of the British Government at sea on voyage from Maskat, as below Rs. Item 1.—From a total of 123 scores of boat-elbows (damaged and lost), 29 scores @ Rs. 13 per bhurja Item 2.—From a total of 1,526 cases fish-oil (damaged and lost), 98 cases @ Rs. 4-4-0 a case Item 3.—Lost and damaged cases amongst'remaining cases, 500 cases at 4 annas a case Item 4.—Damages and breakages in boat, gunwale, and “ Kaim ” (standing timbers on poop) Item 5.—Anchor and coir cable parted and lost in the sea ... Item 6.—Cost of repairing second anchor Item 7.—Box belonging to Suliman-al-Badr, containing five scores and four white Bengali lungis, estimated damage thereto Item 8.—Damage to main-sail from fish-oil, at least 377 0 P- 0 416 8 0 125 0 0 55 128 5 40 200 Bated 4th Jamadi-al-Akhir 1330. 1,346 8 0 Muhammad Takey &amp; Sons, (as estimated by Nakhoda Abbas). Statement cf Khalifa-bin-Shahim, Nakhoda of bagla “ Salamati”, owned by Shahin-al-Ghamm. States— I have not brought my diary log, but remember what happened We left Maskat on the 24th Babi-al-Akhir, having been there eight or nine days owing to rain and wind. We loaded nothing at Maskat, and on y65 discharged some wood at Sur. I started from Maskat in company with the dhangia “ Fateh-as-Salam ” in which my uncle was, and a boom, belonging to Nasir-al-Badr, commanded by bis grandson Maiyuf. It was a Saturday that we left, and we wanted to make a landfall near Jask, intending then to alter course I was leading, and on Thursday, the 30th Rabi-al-Akhir, we made Jask where we saw H. M. S. Fox ” at anchor. It was about 5 o’clock, Arabic time (nearly noon), when a steam-boat left the “Fox ” and came towards us firing either a small gun or a rifle, presumably blank, for I saw no shots fall. It is the signal to lower sails, so we hauled down ours. At this time the other two boats were a long way off but visible. The launch came alongside, and an officer in the boat questioned us through a Somali interpreter. He asked us where we were from, we replied “Malabar”; had we touched Maskat ? Yes. How many days had we stopped there ? eight or nine. Had we taken up any passengers? Yes, four darweshes and three divers, all for Kuwait. The officer repeated this by signal to the “ Fox Then apparently the launch got orders to take us to the ship and two blue jackets climbed into our hagla and we were towed alongside the “ Fox ” where we were ordered to anohor.° Then the Captain himself came on board and after a while some men from the ship. Under the Captain’s orders they started to search the bagla, tellino* us to stand aside. As we were afraid that the parcels and things we ' had for a number of different people would get smashed and damaged in the search, we asked to he allowed to move any cases which they might suspect and which * to search, as we knew which contained breakable things. JBut they would not agree to this, and as you know that the sailors are strong men who handle things roughly; various things got broken, such as a jar of chutney, a case of sherbet, some packages of halwa, and a boat-lamp which had cost us Rs. 7, of which perhaps the Captain saw some and some he did not: any way, when we told him, he ordered the men to be more careful. This went on for two and-a-half hours, when they finished. Before the Captain left, I asked for a certificate to say that he had found nothing on us, but he refused saying that I might go elsewhere and load up arms and then this certificate would protect me. I pointed out that, owing to the Shaikh’s orders, we did not now load up arms and had been specially warned by Saiyid Yusuf Zowavi in Maskat not to do’as in the old days, or the Shaikh would punish us. But the Captain would not Give us a letter, and so we merely said that we had asked, and it was his to give or not as he liked. Just then a “ bagla ” belonging to Abdul Latif-bin-Esa of Kuwait, was leaving, and the Captain said he had searched her and had given her a certificate, which he now regretted, and so would not give me one. We waited for the other two boats to catch up and they arrived about sunset and anchored close to us for the night. In the morning, the « pox’s ” steam launch went to them and asked them details and went back to the ship. Then I put down our dinghy and rowed over to my uncle in the dano-hiya to pass the time of day and have some coffee and came back. Then an officer came over to me from the ship and accused us of transferring things from the other boats. We denied this and explained why we had gone over°&amp;c but they only got angry and threatened us. However, eventually they went away and took the danghiya alongside the ship and cleared her out. I went on board to get some medicine for one of my men and then the Captain asked where the other boom was. He meant Maiyuf’s boom which soon after its name had been taken got her sail up and left, we naturally thought with the man-of-war’s permission. From what the Captain said apparently she had left without their knowledge though it was broad daylight. They finished with the danghiya that day, Friday, and then on Saturday morning the two of us left together. We made Oharak on our journey and left it the day the small armed launch was towing in Haji Muhammad Takey s boom. After that we came direct to Kuwait. We never saw Maiyufs boom again, and she has not arrived yet in Kuwait, nor has Abdul Latif s bagla which left Jask just before us. We had no damage done to our “ bagla ” - *1 • • T vn Q U A 53 11^1. 53,Tm but there are a few things short and missing, of which Bead over and admitted correct. Kuwait; I can make a list and send in. 2Ut May 1913. W. H. I. Shakespear, Captain, Political Agent 3 Kuwait.Note by Political Agent, Kuwait. Apparently this boat “ Salamati ” was searched on the 18th April by H. M. S.‘‘Fox” J 21st May 1912. W. H. I. Shakespear, Captain, Political Agent, Kuwait. Translation of list of damages. The loss at sea from H. M. S. “Fox” to bagla “Salamati” on 30th Rabi-ath-Thani 1330— 1 lantern • •• Ps. ... 7 2 pots of spices • •• ... 8 1 box of sherbat • • • • • • ... 16 1 pot of halwa ... • •• • •• ... 6 38 K halifa-bin-Shahin-al-Ghanim. Statement of Nasir-bin-Abdul Latif, Nakhoda of bagla 'Salmi”, owned by Abdul Latif- bin-Esa. States— On the 13th Rabi-ath-Thani, I left Maskat after having remained there four days, during which we loaded nothing. X have no “ roznama ”, but the 9th day from Maskat we were pulled up by a large ship H. M. S. “ Fox” and made fast to her about 3 in the forenoon (Arabic time). She towed us to Jask and took about 12 hours doing it. On anchoring in Task harbour we were brought alongside, though it was about three hours after sunset, and the sailors began taking all our cargo out on the man-of-war's deck. It was mostly wood, coir, &amp;c. They worked all night and emptied the bagla by about daylight, then they went round her looking at her bottom by lifting up bilge boards and mats even. When they had done this, they returned the cargo we working with them, and all the cargo was back and finished with by about 9 Arabic (afternoon). In bringing us alongside the previous day our dinghy was broken, which will require Rs. 60 to repair, &amp;c., and our mainyard (about Rs. 30 will be cost of its repair) and the stem of the bagla which will cost Rs. 300 to put right. They also took one of our big blocks, value Rs. 10, claiming it was a Government one. It had the Govern- ment mark, but we bought it from a Borah four years ago in Bombay. One bundle of tamarind, value Rs. 8, fell into the sea when the cargo was beino* returned. Some 150 cocoanuts, valued at Rs. 15, were taken by the ship's people, 1 can t give the exact number, because they are not down in a Bill of temporarii e y ng ^ pr ° perty of our sailors - The shi P ^paired the yard for us • ^ h f en the 7 u ha £ finished, the Captain gave me a note (produced and copied) to say that he had searched my ship and found nothing in it. The dav mok f m th ® mornin e‘ M bad weather off Bandar Abbas, and so took shelter m Clarence Strait, passing through the strait towards Bassidu thence we came on straight to Kuwait and entered no other port, except we took up water for drinking from Kharag Island. * Read over and admitted correct. Kuwait, 5th June 1912. j • &gt; W. n. I. Shakespear, Captain, Political Agent, Kuwait.Note by Political Agent, Kuwait. List of repairs and damages claimed by Nasir-bin-Abdul Latif— Us. Repairs to dinghy 60 „ main yard 30 „ stem of bagla ... 300 Cost of large block taken ... 10 1 bundle tamarind lost ... 8 150 cocoanuts taken 15 Total ... 423 W. H. I. Shakespear, Captain, 5th June 1912. Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy of note given to Nasir-bin-Abdul Latif. Searched at Jask after being to Maskat, Thursday, 16th April 1912. James C. Tancred. This should not be any guarantee that no arms are on board if he has visited any ports on Trucial or Oman Coast. Statement of Ahmed-bin-Muhammad-bin-Ghanim, owner and Nakhoda of the dhangia “ Fateh- as-Salam States— I am Nakhoda of my dhangia as well as the owner, and on the 21th Kabi-al-Akhir, I left Maskat in company with the bagla “ Salamati ” in charge of my nephew. We had remained about eight or nine days in' Maskat, but took up no cargo, only having discharged a little wood there. Nasir-al-Badr’s boom also accompanied us. On the 30th Babi-al-Akhir, we made Jask. It was a Thursday, and we arrived under own sail and anchored just before sunset. Immediately we anchored, a steam launch came to us from a big man-of-war there and an officer and a Maskati interpreter, named, 1 think, Muhammad Lutian. They went round the dhangia and looked into places, but without moving anything, and then, after asking our name, &amp;c., they went back to the ship without leaving anybody on board of us. We were close to the ship. We lay there the night. Next morning, Friday, we started getting up our anchor and sail to leave, but the launch came to us and told us we were not to. Then we pulled down our sail and waited until they had finished with the bagla of my nephew Khalifa. Then the launch came to us and towed us alongside the ship where we were made fast. Then the blue jackets and soldiers came down and started moving ail our cargo into the man-of-war. They cleared out the wood, coir, rope, tamarind, &amp;c., which we had stowed in our amidspips hold. Then an officer came down and searched all this witn a light. Then they moved every thing out of our quarters aft on to the deck of the dhangia until they were empty too. They found nothing. In this place they found a small ^ brass saluting cannon which I have had for a long time and which was down in my list of cargo. I told them of it, but they took it on board. After a bit the interpreter came and told me the first Lieutenant wanted to speak to me. He asked me to sell him the gun or any other old coffee pots we had. I refused, as I was angry at having had my cargo turned upside down. Otherwise I would have given it to him. They did not search the forehold. While my cargo was being put on board the ship it all passed over and w'as thrown across our dingy which was stowed on our deck. When returning the cargo the same thing happened only worse as the wood, &amp;c., was thrown back regardless of stowage and damage. In this process our dinghy was smashed up and some of the goods* I mentioned it to a officer standing by, but he said nothing, and when they had thrown back our cargo they cast off our line and we anchored close by and•'irJiFk « spent the rest of the day re-stowing all the gear. When they went through our gear, the sailors who all carried knives ripped open the bags and cases which were sewn up and damaged them a good deal. The night we spent there and sailed the following morning. We only made Charak, the one port before Kuwait, and went nowhere else. The damage done to us I have put down on a paper I hand it, the eatables belonged to my crew and that I have paid them. The wood, &amp;c., for repairs has been got ready and you can ask the carpenters. Bead over and admitted correct. W. H. I. Shakespear, Captain, 6th June 1912. Political Agent, Kuwait. • {Translation.) List of damage to dhangia “ Fateh-as-Salam We started from Maskat, 24th Rabi-al-Akhir 1330, on the Thursday at Jask late in last day of month. On Friday searched us on this, the 1st Jamadi- al-Awal, at 7 o’clock in the morning— Ms. The dinghy (damaged) ... 65 Halwa (damaged and lost) ... 16 Spices (two jars broken) • •• ••• Box of sherbat (broken) 15 Total ... 108 Statement of Maiyuf-bin-Hamud Nasir-al-Badr, Nakhoda of boom “Suhail” belonging to Nasir-al-Badr. States— I am a Nakhoda and part owner of the boom “ Suhail ” with my grand father Nasir-al-Badr. We reached Maskat from Malabar and remained there in Matrah harbour for some 18 days. We unloaded wood there and only took up a couple of bags of cotton. I left Maskat in company with Ahmed-bin- Ghanim and his dhangia. When we were some 12 to 15 miles from Jask we were searched by an armed launch. She sent a boat alongside and the search was rather perfunctory, but they did a certain amount of damage prodding bags, sails, &amp;c., with a rod especially to the sails, without knowing what was inside them. They turned some of the things up, but not searched right down to the bottom of the boat. They were all white sailors, accompanied by a Bushiri interpreter and an officer. This took place in the morning. We then went on to Jask and got there after sunset behind Ahmed-bin-Ghanim and anchored. Next morning, a party came off from the big ship there and asked us questions, looked at our manifests, articles, &amp;c., but did not search us. Their officer walked round and that was all. We told them that we had already been searched by the armed launch. They left the ship, and as we thought we had been finished with, we got up our sails and after waiting a few minutes sailed away across their bows. They did not attempt to stop us, and so we carried on until the next day when, near Clarence Strait, we saw another small launch towing another boat, which passed us and repassed us the foilwing day but said nothing to us. We called at Kishm to unload wood and then passed through the Strait, stopped at Lingah to take up some rice, and came on to Kuwait stopping only at Charak for shelter from a shamal and water. We suffered no damage from the search, but only annoyance as they hurried us and were rather rough in their handling. Bead over and admitted correct. W\ H. I. Shakespear, Captain, Political Agent, Kuwait* 10th June 1912.70 .e*. rP ^ 134 No. 86, dated Maskat, the 2nd (received 8tk) July 1912. Prom Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Maskat, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. In compliance with telegraphic instructions received from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, I have the honour to submit herewith the translation of the Notice and of the detailed rules Nos. 1 to 12, to which His Highness the Sultan of Maskat was pleased to signify his approval at two separate interviews that His Highness kindly granted to me on the 12th and 30th June, respectively. 2. These rules are those promised in the concluding paragraph of the Notification published by His Highness on the 4th of June, and reported by the Resident in his letter* No. 136 M., * semi No. 91 . dated the 5th June, to your address. The only reason for the delay in their publication is that His Highness expressed a wish that I should, before the final publication, consult higher authority on the question whether these detailed rules should be published, before Foreign Consuls, residing at Maskat, receive and communicate to him the replies of their Governments to their representations. I accordingly ^ ^ nr i a 4 - T^T/v complied with His Highness’s wishes, as From the Political Agent, Maskat, No. 76, dated ... the isth June 1912 . will he seen from the accompanying From the Political Agent, Maskat, No. 82, dated telegraphic correspondence, quoted in the the 30th Jun* 1912. • 1 -i , fi t.* At, . • From the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, margin, between the Political Resident 1U No. 193 M., dated the 1st July 1912. p ers i an G u lf and myself. 3. Unfortunately, by some error, the Resident’s telegram No. 182, dated the 24th June, from Hanjam has not yet reached me, but immediately on receipt of his No. 193 M., dated the 1st July, I asked His Highness to grant me an interview, but I regret to report that His Highness who, my dragoman informs me, seems to be feeling the heat at Maskat, to be in indifferent health and in need of a change of air and scene, was unable to accede to my request for an interview to-day. 4. I shall, however, take the earliest opportunity of laying the Resident’s reply to the doubts expressed by His Highness before him, and trust that I shall be successful in inducing him to proceed to the immediate publication of the notice and of rules Nos. 1 to 12. 5. I venture to add the request that I may be favoured with about 20 or more printed copies of these rules as soon as possible, as His Highness might be pleased to use these as convenient for distribution to Foreign Consuls and traders. It would be an additional advantage, if they could be printed in a form suitable for publication. The Arabic original of the Notice and rules will be forwarded to your address by next mail. Similar printed copies of the Arabic would also be most useful. Telegram, No. 76, dated the 13th June 1912. From—The Political Agent, Maskat, i To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Please refer to rules arms warehouse. Discussed question this afternoon with His Highness who expressed his willingness to publish second Notice and rules 1 to 4 as first instalment exactly as prepared between you and me. In spite of my arguments against such a course, he is doubtful whether these rules should be published before Foreign Consuls receive and communicate to him the replies of their Govern- w ments to their representations and is anxious that question be referred to Government for decision. Is it necessary to obtain sanction of Government to publication of these rules and should they be wired to Foreign ? His Highness appears to object to publication en bloc and prefers instalments. I see no reason why we should not humour him in this. r71 Telegram, No. 82, dated the 30th June 1912. From—The Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. His Highness at interview to-day expressed his willingness to publish up to and including rule 12 without alteration, and from observations lie let fall seems inclined to publish the whole set of regulations and forms. I venture to press for early decision on my demi-official No. 77, dated 14th instant, and telegram No. 76, dated 13th instant, which have, I hope, reached you ere this. His Highness, on my representing that local arms merchants, not French : and notably Syud Yusuf-az-Zowawi, have been boasting that they will refuse to deliver up their stocks, renewed most strongly his assurances that he was determined strictly to regulate traffic. He further informed me that he had been most emphatic in his replies refusing to listen to remonstrances from the tribes in the interior. Telegram, No. 193 M., dated the 1st July 1912. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Political Agent, Maskat. Your telegram 82. I have already replied to your 76 and 77 by my tele gram 182 from Hanjam on 24th, saying “ Send copy of rules accepted to Gov ernment officially and remainder demi-officially. If, however, Sultan is definitely ready to publish the whole at once, I see no reason why it should not be done in anticipation of Government concurrence. If any particular modification proves necessary, it can be made subsequently.” NOTICE BY HIS HIGHNESS SIB, SYUD FAISAL-BIN-TUBKI, G.C.I.E., SULTAN OF MASKAT AND OMAN. The following draft rules for the establishment, maintenance and control of the Arms Warehouse are published for the information of all concerned. The said rules will be held to apply to all arms and ammunition or parts thereof held in our territories by traders for sale on the date of the introduc tion of the said rules, and to all such arms, ammunition or parts thereof as may be thereafter imported into our territories. On, or about, but not before, the 1st Se ptember 191 2, a subsidiary notice will be issued in due course confirming these draft rules and notifying the date on which the rules so confirmed shall come into operation. DBAFT BULES. Rule 1. All arms, ammunition or parts thereof, held by traders for sale to the public within my dominions, shall be deposited forthwith in the Arms Warehouse in accordance with these regulations. The Warehouse Superinten dent will grant detailed receipt to the depositor for all such arms, ammuni tion or parts thereof in the form attached and marked A. Rule 2. After the expiry of one month from the date on which these rules come into operation, all arms, ammunition or parts thereof, found in the possession of traders (except in accordance with the provisions of rule 15 hereinafter mentioned), contrary to the provisions of rule 1 aforesaid, shall be confiscated. If the offending trader be a Maskat subject, he will be severely punished; if a foreigner and amenable to my jurisdiction, he will be liable to expulsion from my territories. . If the offending trader be a subject of any of the Powers in treaty relations with me, information will be laid against him to the Consul of the Power, whose subject or protege he may be, and the aforesaid Consul will be requested to deal with him according to law and treaty and the spirit of these regulations.72 1 Rule 3. In addition to all or any of the penalties imposed by these rules, should any trader be found guilty in the proper forum of offending against the provisions of rule 1 aforesaid, all arms, ammunition or parts thereof, held in the Maskat Arms Warehouse to the credit of such offending trader, or f* that may subsequently be deposited in the Arms Warehouse in his name under the provisions of rule 4, will, without further sentence of forfeiture, be liable to confiscation. Rule 4. All arms, ammunition or parts thereof, which may hereafter be imported into Maskat territory, will be taken direct to the Arms Warehouse and there deposited. Rule 5. For the more effective carrying out of the provisions of the preceding rule, the masters of steamers importing arms and ammunition or parts thereof will be required to produce on arrival and furnish to the represent ative of the Warehouse Superintendent who will attend on hoard, the copy of a separate manifest, ie-dSngMsh and in the form attached and marked B, showing all arms and ammunition and parts thereof, destined for importation into my territories and carried on board their vessels. Rule 6. All arms, ammunition or parts thereof, destined for import into Maskat, but not detailed, or incorrectly or insufficiently described, in the separate manifest (form B) especially with regard to the marks on the packages or the name of the consignee, shall, as soon as such arms, ammuni tion or parts thereof have left the ship’s tackles become liable to confiscation. Exception. The sole exception to the operation of this rule shall be in the case of arms, ammunition or parts thereof, landed by mistake in good faith and clearly destined for some other port, to which the import of arms and ammunition is not prohibited. The burden of proving that such arms and ammunition were intended for import to a port, to which the import of arms and ammunition is not prohibited, shall lie on the steamer’s agent, importer or consignee. No claims under this exception will be entertained after a period of three months from date of landing of the goods, in respect of which the claim is made. Rule 7. All arms, ammunition or parts thereof, deposited in the Arms Warehouse in accordance with the provisions of rule 4, shall be claimed by the consignee within a period of three months from the date of deposit in the Arms Warehouse. On such claim being made, the Warehouse Superintendent will, subject to the provisions of rules 8 and 8 (a) immediately following and after due veri fication of the Bill of Lading and steamer’s agent’s delivery order, grant a detailed receipt in form A above-mentioned. Rule 8. As soon as, in accordance with the provisions of rule 4 aforesaid, arms and ammunition or parts thereof are brought to the Arms Warehouse to be there deposited, the Superintendent, Arms Warehouse, shall notify the Superintendent of Customs of the arrival of such arms, ammunition or parts thereof by form attached and marked C Arabic in order that duty may be collected thereon by the Superintendent of Customs. Rule 8(a). As soon as such duty has been paid, the Superintendent of Customs shall immediately return to the Superintendent, Arms Warehouse, the form marked C duly endorsed with a certificate that the duty has been fully paid on the arms, ammunition and parts thereof noted in the form aforesaid, and the Superintendent, Arms Warehouse, shall in no case grant the detailed receipt in form A unless and until he shall have received back the form marked C duly endorsed as already described by the Superin tendent of Customs. Rule 0. Failure by consignee to comply with the provisions of either of the three preceding rules shall render the arms, ammunition or parts thereof liable to confiscation.Drratum slip for the India Office 'In rule 5 of the rules enclosed in the letter from the Political Agent, Mashat, No. Qb, dated tne 2nd July j. 912, copy of which was forwarded to the India Office with the Joreign Secretary’s letter No. 28-M. , dated the IIth July 1912, please omit the words 'in English'. foreign Department, Simla; The 16th July 1912.&lt; 73 Issue of arms, ammunition or parts thereof from the Arms Warehouse. l&amp;ule 10. Any person proposing to purchase arms, ammunition or parts thereof from any trader, owning arms, ammunition or parts thereof stored in the Arms Warehouse in accordance with the provisions of rules 1 and 4 above, and duly claimed under the provisions of rule 7, and on which duty and warehouse charges have been fully paid in accordance with the provisions of rules 8 and 16, respectively, will he permitted to withdraw arms and ammunition or parts thereof on the production of, and to the extent covered by, a license in form marked D and attached. On the application of the trader concerned, who must he present at such withdrawal, the Warehouse Superintendent shall draw up the license aforesaid and submit it for my approval and signature. Mule 11. It shall he the duty of the Warehouse Superintendent to refuse to draw up any such license, should he have reason to suppose— (a) that the purchaser whose name it is proposed to enter in form D as “ hearer ” intends to resell the arms, ammunition or parts thereof to any other person; [b) that such purchaser is already, whether by license in form D pre viously issued or otherwise, in possession of arms, ammunition or parts thereof, whence it may he inferred that the arms, ammu nition or parts thereof, covered by the license under question, are not required solely for the personal use or protection of the purchaser. Mule 12. It shall further be the duty of the Warehouse Superintendent to ensure that— (a) all rifles issuing from the Arms Warehouse under the terms of any license, issued in accordance with the provisions of these rules, shall be clearly marked on the barrel before withdrawal with the official mark and on the butt with the serial number of issue; (b) no more than 200 rounds per rifle per annum shall he issued from the Arms Warehouse to any holder of a license under form D; (&lt;?) in the event of a license under form D being issued for ammunition only, which must not in any case exceed 200 rounds per annum per purchaser, the purchaser produces, for the inspection of the Warehouse Superintendent, the weapon in respect of which the ammunition is required.77 -r Form D. LICENSE TO WITHDRAW ARMS, AMMUNITION OR PARTS THEREOF FROM THE ARMS WAREHOUSE, MASKAT. Please permit the bearer . 9 son of nationality 9 to take from my stock in the Arms Warehouse the following :— Dated (Signed) Arms Trader 9 Mask at. Recommended. Dated Warehouse Superintendent. Approved. (Signed) [ ] Sultan of Maskat and Oman. Seal of His Highness the Sultan. Verified and issued. (Signed) No. . Warehouse Superintendent^ Maskat. Dated N. B. —This document should be made out in duplicate, the original will be held by the purchaser of the goods and carefully preserved a» a license to explain his possession, while the duplicate will be retained by the Warehouse Superintendent as a voucher.MASKAT ARMS WAREHOUSE. Traders' license to keep sample arms and ammunition on his business premises. Please permit the bearer » son of » nationality &gt; to take from my stock in the Arms Warehouse the following sample arms and ammunition:— I guarantee that the above arms and ammunition taken as samples will not be sold to any purchaser without special permission in writing from His Highness the Sultan and that the ammunition will only be utilised in practice and testing weapons. (Signed) Arms Trader&gt; Maskat. Warehouse Superintendent. (Signed) Sultan of Maskat and Oman. Dated (Signed) Warehouse Superintendent. N.B. —This form should be made out in duplicate, one copy will be retained by the Warehouse Superintendent as a voucher while the original will be retained by the trader and should be carefully preserved by him in order that it may be produced, should the reason for the possession of his sample arms be challenged. iSecretar i wretatf ol bts69 Telegram P., No. S.—278, dated the 3rd June 1912. From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Maskat. Maskat arms warehouse. Please refer to your telegramsf Nos. M.—95 Serial Nos. 57 md 58. aud 96, dated the ^3rd ultimo. Please act on sanction conveyed in Secre tary of State’s telegram,J dated 1st instant, which was repeated to you direct by the India Office, London.73 Telegram P., dated the 4th (received 5th) June 1912. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Maskat, To The Foreign Secretary, Simla. * Serial Iso. 69. Please refer to your telegram* No. 278 S., dated the 3rd instant. To-day the Sultan issued the notification omitting^ m the body of the preamblef as being superfluous the t Vide Serial No. 58. words: “ Saiyid Sir Faisal Bin Turki, G.C.I.E., Sultan of Maskat and Oman The Press in India and London, I would suggest, being given the purport of the notification. In acknowledging the despatch notification, the French Consul says that he considers it contrary to Treaty and without “structions fronj his Government, to whom he is referring, it cannot apply to French subjects.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, _ London. 7 The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop (f of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Reference to previous letter : Description of Inclosure.h- i m 1 Peris i 0 25 djh^CjL- June 17th 1912, r m »!jn I9n v l CJ 0 ni9 * )ir: - I have the honour to transmit to you he re ~i th an article extracted from the 'Dcrech© Goloniale* of today’s date corn- renting on the ne^ retaliations instituted, by the Sultan of L'uscat in regard to the traffic of anas. The article after briefly reviewing the engage -ents of England and France respecting ! uscat, explains the nature of the contraband trade in arms carried on in the Persian Gulf and describes the costly and arduous operations which England is compelled to undertake in order to suppress it. Attention is drawn to a sreech on the subject made by Lord horley in the louse of I Lords in the course of which he said that tils I njesty s Govern* rnent could not ask France to sacrifice ner ri tits gratuitously. The new regulations, the article continues, being in formal contradiction to the canitul• tions oi 1L44, inasmuch a they af feet ^ Ught Honourable Gir Edward Irsy Part K.G. H.1 . Etc., etc., etc. VA In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. 24900/12. and address— The Under-Secretary of State. Foreign Office, . London. Put s- * ay Foreign Office June j^ 1912. Sir:- With reference to your letter P.2175 of the 10th instant, I am directed by Secretary Sir E.Grey to state for the information of the Marquess of Crewe that the substance of the Arms Notification by the Sultan of Muscat was communicated to the Press in the form agreed upon after private concurrence with your Department. Copy of the communique, as published in the ”Times M of June 12th, is enclosed. I am. I X U W t- * v te 10 a.m. 19 iUN I9A2 INDIA OFFICE. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, Under Secretary of State, India Office. ropv to i v &gt;s ‘a 12 JUL 1912 ■ o tin\ r \ N / ' 9, N l c V&gt; S i - • • . &gt; , ^ ' 2 8 I ![This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's £'£-■8' pufaway w arms traffic. [June 11 CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2. [24318] Press Communication. Arms Traffic Notification by the Sultan of Muscat. THE Sultan of Muscat has now issued a notification, dated the 4th instant, providing for the proper regulation of the trade in arms and ammunition in his dominions The notification refers to the danger caused by the present system of keeping large stocks of arms and ammunition stored without proper control in private buildings in the town o f Muscat, and explains that, in order to remedy this state of affairs, His Highness has decided on the establishment of a warehouse in which arms and ammunition will be stored under proper precautions The general lines on which the warehouse will be conducted are as follows :— On and after the 1st September next all arms and ammunition imported into Muscat territory will be taken direct from the steamer to the Control, and all dealers in Muscat territory will lie required to deposit in the warehouse stocks remaining in their hands on that date. Any trader offending against this regulation will, m addition to other penalties, render all future consignments of arms arriving in his name liable to confiscation. ., No arms will be allowed to issue from the warehouse without a licence, nor until duty has been paid thereon in the usual way. The licences will be prepared by the superintendent, and countersigned by the Sultan, and will not be granted to traders, but onlv to approved individual purchasers or their agents, on the production ot satisfactory proof that the number, quantity, and destination of the arms and ammunition to be withdrawn are free from justifiable objection. All arms withdrawn from tbe warehouse will be marked. Detailed rules on the lines indicated in the notification are under preparation, and will be published by the Sultan as soon as possible. Foreign Office, June 11, 1912. [2518 1—2]FOfEIOM OT'PICK, rica, 15638/12). Sir: .June 13th 1912 The French Aabaesador showed s«e to-day an extract from a newspaper giving o»n account of the new regulations Bade by the Sultan of Muscat as to the Arms Traffic In i,tuscat, the correspondence with regard to “.hlch is no doubt already familiar to Your Excellency froa the Confidential Print, lions lour Caohon observed that he doubted whether the new arrangement was not an inter ference with the liberty of couaarce. I replied that liberty of commerce could hardly be construed to mean freedom from all regulations and that what was being done was to regulate but not to prohibit the traffic. nclosed herewith. Your Sxcelloncy's most obedient humble Servant la Excellency The Hight Honourable Sir F.Bertie, G.C.B., G.C.M.G., &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.Question NOo 1 ? aated 25th. Junso 'Nlir J« Dc Reea-g- To ask the Unaer Secretary for India* whether he can give tne House any information ‘regarding the regulations issued by the Sultan of Muscat regarding traffic in imported annso Answero The following is the text of the notification regulating the trade in arms and ammunition issued by the Sultan of Muscat on the 4tho Instoo- 'ihereas; large quantities of arms and ammunition are at present stored without proper control in private buildings distributed in this our town of Muscat and thus exposed to the risks of attack* robbery* or fireo We a impressed by the serious menace to trie safety of our capital arising therefrom* have resolved to remedy this state of affairs in accordance with the needs of tne times and the requirements of our municipal administration by tne construction and establishment of a special Customs House* Magazine, or ArmsoWarehouse, for the storage of arms and ammunition under safe precautionso It is proposed to introduce this warehouse arrangement from on or about Isto September next* It will be conducted on the following general lines:- Firstlyo- On or after 1st. September next all arms and ammunition or parts thereof imported into my territories will ’ be taken direct from the steamer to the Control, of which a Special Superintendent will be appointedo 1 ers in my territories | wi quir; * to : ' iV ' A ' ,s on 1st. pt ember in tne said warehouse. Any trader of lending against this regulation will in addition to other penal .es !.nna all future consignments of arms and ammunition arriving in his (name)(name) liable to confiscation unless and till he complies with this regulation in lull. Thirdly ,* No arms will be allowed to issue from the warehouse until duty has been fully paid thereon to the Customs Superintendent in the usual way. Fourth! v a - The withdrawal of arms from tne warehouse will oe regulated by tne issue of special licenses prepared by the Superintendent and contersigned by myself. Fifthly. - Such licenses will not be granted-to traders» but only to approved individual purchasers or their duly authorised agents, on the production of satisfactory proof that the number, quantity, and destination of arms and ammunition, &amp;Ce, to be withdrawn from tne warehouse are free from justifiable objection. Sixthly ,* All arms issuing from tne warehouse will be with a special warehouse mark and serial number. Seventhly a ' Special rules will be drawn up providing for and regulating issue to approved traders ot sample stock for exhibition in ineir shops 0 Sightly.' Rules providing lor the collection ol arms warehouse charges, on stocks tnerein deposited, ril;. be drawn up on the analogy oi the present Custom House regulations &gt;for the levy of such xees on genera* merchandise. Ninthly?' Special rules will be drawn up governing transfer between traders oi stocks deposited in tne arms warehouse. Isntalv:.. Scecial relaxations will be arranged lor r ' leniencyleniency (’towards) flintlocks, muzzle-loading gun? , and caps in reasonable quantities. Lastly. * Detailed rules embodying the above principles are unaer preparation, and will be published in due course %\ for further information of all concerned*In a ny further communication on this subject, please quote and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. no. 22935/12. 2122 I June 1st. 1912 n IM^- ' w-q I. ' Ir®ediate \ 9\2 Sir:- I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter P.1952 of the 28th. ultimo, en closing copies of telegrams from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf respecting the arrangements which the Sultan of Muscat is prepared to make for regulating the trade in Arms and Ammunition. Sir E. Grey concurs in the view expressed by the Marquess of Crewe with regard to Clause 5 of the draft noti fication by the Sultan, and he agrees that the conditions required by the Sultan may be accepted, it being understood that His Majesty’s Government will give His Highness any support which may be rendered necessary oy trench oojecuiono to the Scheme. rey therefore concurs in Lord Crewe’s proposal to 'he Under Secretary of State, India Office.(22935/12). 2122 i.9;2 to accord his sanction to Sir P. Cox’s proposals. I axn, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,( 2 ) Frovi Political Resident, Persian Gulf, 23rd May 1912. [ZoZ Negotiations regarding special arms warehouse. . , . Subiect to written assurance regarding conditions mentioned below ultan is now readv to take next step, namely, to publish notification set &gt;rth in my telegram of last night (?), sending copies with a polite covering &gt;tter to foreign Consuls. Conditions aie . (1) that British Government undertake full responsibility to give him a necessary support to dispose of objections that may ensue from that it is understood that arrangement does not give witisii Government or officials any right to take action m his teintones ,11 th^rrom^htierndV understanding with him as to suitable i0) ^krngements for the supply of 6o«« fide needs of his administration (4) that di^Vromfse^to compensate (him) on the (terms) already agreed on is confirmed. . There seems to be nothing objectionable either m notification or m altan^s stimulations, and I earnestly solicit immedi^ answer to a^e now ,nt Sultan is in rmht mood. As soon as notification has issuetl, ms ighi^ and PoliticaT Agent will proceed to frame detailed regulations for pproval which however will take some furthei turn.TW 10 From Political Resident, Persian Gulf, 23rd May 1912,.^- Following are terms of Notification which will now be issued by Sultan :— J Whereas large quantities of arms and ammunition are at present stored without propel conti ol m pnvate buildings distributed m this our town of Muscat and thus exposed to the risks of attack, robbery, or fire, We, Saiyid Sir Faisal Bin Fuiki, Gr.C.I E., Sultan of Muscat and Oman, impressed by the serious menace to the safety of our capital arising therefrom, have resolved to remedy this state of affairs in accordance with the needs of the times and the requirements of our municipal administration by the con struction and establishment ol a special Customs House, Magazine, or Arms Warehouse, for the storage of arms and ammunition under safe precautions. It is proposed to introduce this warehouse arrangement from on or about 1st September next. It will be conducted on the following general lines : — f irstly. On or after 1st September next all arms and ammunition or parts thereof imported into my territories will be taken direct from the steamer to the Control, of which a special Superintendent will be appointed. Secondly. —Similarly all arms dealers in my territories will be required to deposit stocks remaining in their hands on 1st September in the said ware house. Any trader offending against this regulation will in addition to other penalties render all future consignments of arms and ammunition arriving in his (name) liable to confiscation unless and till he complies with this regulation in full. ' , Thirdly. —No arms will be allowed to issue from the warehouse until duty has been fully paid thereon to the Customs Superintendent in the usual way. Fourthly. —The withdrawal of arms from the warehouse will be regulated by the issue of special licenses prepared by the Superintendent and counter signed by myself. Fiftldy. —Such licenses will not be granted to traders, but only to approved individual purchasers or their duly authorised agents, on the pro duction of satisfactory proof that the number, quantity, and destination of arms and ammunition, &amp;c., to be withdrawn from the warehouse are free from justifiable objection. Sixthly. —All arms issuing from the warehouse will be with a special warehouse mark and serial number. Seventhly. —Special rules will be drawn up providing for and regulating- issue to approved traders of sample stock for exhibition in their shops. Eighthly. — ilules providing for the collection of arms, warehouse charges, on stocks therein deposited, will be drawn up on the analogy of the present Custom House regulations for the levy of such fees on general merchandise. Ninthly. —Special rules will be drawn up governing transfer between traders of stocks deposited in the arms warehouse. Tenthly. —Special relaxations will be arranged for leniency (? towards) flintlocks, muzzle-loading guns, and caps in reasonable quantities. Lastly. —Detailed rides embodying the above principles are under preparation, and will be published in due course for further information of all concerned.I 2. O 5~ (co H)' 47 131 Telegram P., No. S.—116, dated the 8th March 1912. Prom—The Foreign Secretary, Calcutta, To The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Please refer to your telegram* No. 143, dated the 25th Pebruary. Maskat negotiations. Proposals approved. It is • serwi No. 117. presumed that Sultan understands that increased subsidy will he withheld in event of his not acting up to terms of arrangement. This proviso would enable us to compel Sultan to dismiss officer selected if he be found corrupt or inefficient and, if necessary, it might be made plain to Sultan. 133 Telegram P., No. S.—117, dated the 9th March 1912. From— The Foreign Secretary, Calcutta, T 0 The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire. Communique regarding arms trade was published to day.GUN-RUNNING FROM MUSCAT. ACTION BY THE SULTAN. We understand that a new arrangement has been devised by the Sultan of Muscat with regard to the export of arms and ammunition, which, it is believed, will effectively stop the illicit trade with those countries which have prohibited the importation of arms. [%* As has been frequently explained in The. Times, the gun-running traffic across the Gulf of Oman, which in recent years has put a very large number of modern rifles into the hands of the tribes upon the Indian Nort h-West, centres cliiefly at Muscat, where it has been protected by a Treaty concluded m 18ow between France and the State of Oman. J he , Sultan of Oman has been willing to prohibit the traffic, but has been prevented by the existence of these Treaty rights, which, m spite 1 of many representations from the British Govern ment. have not hitherto been relinquished by France. The value of the arrangement now announced must therefore depend very largely on the attitude of the French Government and on the actual measures which the Sultan pro poses to take. Till some further explanation is given on these points no just opinion oi its efficacy can be formed.]mmi From Viceroy, 1st March 1912. Foreign Secret. Muscat negotiations. Your telegram of 30th January. Cox telegraphs, 25th :— “ On the way from India I have discussed further with Sultan, Muscat question of management of bonded warehouse. Have been unable to induce him to accept, even temporarily, the services of a Government official owing to the objections, from his point of view, which I have previously described ; but as an alternative His Highness suggests that as soon as the working- regulations of the warehouse have been agreed upon between us, we should make our own selection of a trustworthy man from among his employes or subjects or from the inhabitants of Muscat, and that if we cannot discover an individual in whom we both place [group apparently omitted] His Highness (?) should engage a man in India, whose identity and character would be referred to Government of India for enquiry and approval before the Sultan’s contract with him was concluded. , , , , , “ I made it clear to His Highnes that neither the lakh for the past nor the enhanced subsidy would be payable until arrangements lor the inauguration were complete, and in these circumstances I recommend that Government intimate their acceptance, in principle, of the course proposed by Sultan. Formulation of working details can the!*, be proceeded with m %l concert with Sultan, and Reuter telegram for discouragement of shippers might be issued. n ... , , t? _ &gt; “Sultan has been generally instructed as to lines of reply to Irenen enquiries, and will specifically consult Political Agent before replying to any cominunication^received^gj apparently dropped] of our negotiations with Sultan has already appeared in a Zanzibar vernacular paper. ^ We agree with Cox’s recommendations and think communique through Reuter’s Agency might now issue.No. 52169/1911. Foreign Office, January 1, 1912* Sir, I aril directed by Secretary Sir E. G-rey to acknowledge the receipt of yo^tr letter P. 20o6/ll, of the 1st instant, respecting the proposals of the G-overnment of India for the regulation of the Muscat Arms Traffic by the creation of a bonded warehouse, with a system of registration and control of all issues* Sie E. G-rey concurs in the view that the moment is now favourable for immediate action with a view to the adoption of the proposals put forward, and agrees that instructions to this effect should oe sent to India* Sir E* G-rey further concurs in the proposal that a communication should be made to the press to the effect that 'It is understood that an arrangement has been made for the regulation of the Muscat Anns Traffic', and the nece ssarv steps for this purpose will be taken by this Department on hearing from you that the Sultan of unseat has finally accepted the terms offered* «- I am. Six j . ,. i uX Tour most obsciient . ax / * Under Secretary of Staia;, for India. ^7 mble Servant,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000080_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/235</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000080</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/235</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 868/1912 Pt 1 'Arms traffic: arrangements at Muscat for its regulation'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1910/1912</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-13T22:19:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (225 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume. The subject 868 (Arms Traffic - Muscat) consists of 6 volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/235-240. The volumes are divided into 7 parts with parts 1, 2, 3, 6 and 7 comprising one volume each and parts 4 and 5 comprising a volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the first flyleaf with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 225; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, notes, printed reports and a press cutting relating to the arms traffic in Muscat and arrangements for its regulation.Issues discussed include:negotiations between the Foreign Office, India Office and the Sultan of Muscat for supervision of arms exports from Muscat by creation of a bonded warehouse;the Sultan of Muscat's proposed arrangements for regulating the sale of arms;the Foreign Office's approval of the Sultan of Muscat's draft notifications and conditions and a proposal on communicating these notifications to the Press;the 1844 Franco-Muscat Treaty and the 1862 Anglo-French declaration which guaranteed France's right to trade with Muscat;Anglo-French diplomacy on the matter involving the French Ministry of Foreign Affairs;correspondence between the French Consul, Muscat and the Sultan of Muscat;Authorisation for British naval ships to board dhows flying the French flag if requested by the Sultan of Muscat;implementation of the new rules involving the removal of arms and ammunition to a warehouse;formal protests by French subjects against the regulations.The file includes two press cuttings: from the Times (f 182) and a French newspaper (f 178).The principal correspondents in the volume include: the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Percy Zachariah Cox;the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf; the Political Agent at Muscat; the Viceroy; the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Sir Edward Grey; the Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office; the Ambassador to France, Sir Francis Bertie; the Lord Commissioners of the Admiralty; the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies.The volume is part 1 of 7. The part includes a divider which gives the subject and part numbers, year the subject file was opened, subject heading, and list of correspondence references contained in that part by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence (f 2).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>French Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to France</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Permanent Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Arms traffic</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000080#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>