<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00008e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:51:47.707Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">70 f Memorandum by Lieutenant-General J. W. Schneider, C.B. * nt ’Fi, 0l0n ;i e - 1 K;itc . hener ’ s remarks, in respect of Socotra and its dependencies, the adjacent islands, have apparently been written under some the le T° n ' ? « tr “? that the SultaI1 of' Socotra resides cliiefly on e, n 0 PP 0S ite the island, that is to say, at Kisheen on the Arabian coastbut lie is represented at Socotra by one or morel of his sons, who rule there m his name. When I concluded the existing treaty or agreement at Kislieen with the u an e^rly m the year 1876, he had then three sons living on the island, the eldest being considered as Regent. The yearly subsidy of #300 is pay able at Socotra, and a reference to my report will, I think, show that I laid great stress on the necessity of the island being visited annually by an officer irom the Aden Residency, in order that our interest and connection with the place should not he lessened. The very nature of the treaty or agreement wil piove that the British flag Avas never hoisted at Socotra, and con sequently it could not have been hauled down. The erroneous idea on the subject entertained by Bieutenant-Colonel Kitchener may have been derived from an historical sketch published by “Phil. Robinson” in the year 1878, where it is mentioned, “ the island of Socotra upon which the British flag “ has recently been hoisted lies 148 miles east of Cape Gardafui.” I quite concur with Lieutenant-Colonel Kitchener as to the importance attaching to the possession of Socotra, and it was on this account that I urged on Government the necessity of acquiring certain rights over the island and its^ dependencies. The treaty or agreement is binding on the Sultan, his heirs and successors, and *Avas signed by all the principal members of the El-Afreer family, including, of course, the three sons then resident on the island; and in the Despatch, No. 14, of the 6th April 1876, addressed to the Governor General of India, Her Majesty’s Government stated that the terms of the agreement executed by Sultan Ali bin Abdulla El-Afreer appeared fully to secure the objects for which the negotiation was set on foot. The necessity for the construction and maintenance of a lighthouse at Cape Gardafui or Ras Hufoon—the so-called Ealse Cape—lias been repeatedly brought to the notice of Government by the several Political Residents at Aden who have held office since the opening of the Suez Canal, from which time wrecks and loss of life have been of yearly occurrence during the south west monsoon. The erection of a lighthouse is now only a question of expense, and how it is to be met. The very able Assistant Resident and Consul for the Somali Coast, Major Hunter, should he able to overcome all difficulties with the Myjerteyn or other local tribes. A fortified enclosure, somewhat similar to the one at Perim protecting the lighthouse, with a small garrison of Native troops provisioned for six months, would, of course, be necessary for some time. A condenser might also be required. The ports of Berbera and Zeyla are, for all practical purposes, already occupied and protected by the British Government. Referring to Lieutenant-Colonel Kitchener’s observations regarding the island of Perim, it is well known that the question of fortifying this position has come under frequent consideration. The earliest report on the subject emanated from Sir W. Jervis, R.E., about the year 1870, when, in con nexion with the strengthening of Aden, a large expenditure was proposed at Perim for new defences and the mounting of heavy guns. If I remember lightly, General Tremenheere, R.E., was opposed to any considerable outlay afTPerim, being of opinion that, so long as we continued in possession of Aden and held the command of the seas, little or no advantage would follow from fortifying the island, which is a barren rock^ quite waterless, and yielding nothing. The existing enclosure at Perim is intended to guard aeainst attacks from the tribes on the African and Arabian coasts, and to 121G9. I. 2857. Hiprotect the lighthouse. It also holds the garrison of Native troops and stores. hv T A putenant-0olonel Kitchener that there I think it has been ovc ^ of Ba b. u l-Mandub. The one on the are two passages throUsh miles broad, while the other on the African Arabian side is less tha . pasga( , e _i s ten miles in breadth. This side— the longer and moie c L p e y; m _ The width of the passage passage is taken by s t ea ™® ' , h reasons why it has been held that the on the African side of the ^ perim wouia be useless to fortification and mounting f the Bed Sea. Even to mount a command the approach to and exit fr ^ pfrim of the whole or part of few large guns would entail of barracks and other Kt “oulS caused b, lb. fre-sce ot British rioop. aud ISsSSS tsssr s foimed by dreaging a establishing a fortified port there, this 3 doub£ be a menace against Perim, and the question of mounting heavy guns on the island, or adopting other measures, would the 1 ! c nbrllr the consideration of the British Government. Until this period arrives I cannot see the necessity for further strengthening i enm. the presence there occasionally of a man-of-war will, m my judgment, be SU Betwera 1872 and 1877 the Turks were in occupation of Shaikh Saced, and a detachment of their troops was stationed there. It will be remembered that a French Company settled and erected a block-house at Shaikh Saeed, and that they were ejected by the Turks. This occurred shortly before I became Political Resident in July 1872 The Turkish detachment, which was drawn from Hodeida, is probably still located at Shaikh Saeed. _ _ ., ^ • j T 'W ftvitTXTI.iTTVl'T! 8, Queensborough Terrace, 23nd Eebruary 1886.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00008e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B42</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00008e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B42</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memorandum by Lieutenant-General J. W. Schneider, C.B.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1886/1886</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-03-17T10:20:18</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (1 folio)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 74, and terminates at f 74, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of a memorandum from Sir John William Schneider, Politcal Resident at Aden, on British interests in Socotra.It includes opinions on Lieutenant-Colonel Kitchener's misapprehensions with regards to British influence at Socotra [Suquṭrā]; discusses the treaty or agreement concluded in 1876 which bound the Sultan Ali Bin Abdulla El-Alfreer and his successors, and the necessity of acquiring certain rights over the island and its dependencies. It also notes the need for the construction and maintenance of a lighthouse at Cape Gardafui or Fas Hufoon; and raises the question of fortifying the island of Perim [Jazīrat Mayyūn] against attacks from the tribes on the African and Arabian coasts, and to protect the lighthouse.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Socotra</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Socotra</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><subject><topic>Lighthouses</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00008e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>