<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00032d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T23:21:56.743Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">the Bahrein Petroleum Company limited N0:Ph-159. Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, April 6, 1937. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. Dear Sir, Our Ref : - Shipping Notice #4-9 : We enclose herewith certificate covering two boxes containing a centrifugal pump with electric motor, &amp; water treating accessories which are being returned to U.3.A. via Bombay on or about the 9th inst. by the S.S. f, Bamora , . , Please return the certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, TilS BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD Or. W. R. Sl.HTH Chief Local Representative.Ef*f T 0 -7 No.794-5/3. Political Agency, Bahrain, the VthbApril 1937 To, The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limitea, 3 A H R A 1 IU in/ Dear Sir, | &lt;*ith reference to your letter No.PA-159 uateci the 6th April 1937, I return Herewith a certificate covering two boxes containing a centrifugal pump with electric motoi anu water treating accessories, duly certified. Yours faithfully, * ML for Political ,BaiiraiThe Bahrein petroleum company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, April 11, 193’i No. PA-166. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. U R GEN T. Dear Sir, Please find enclosed original and four copies (one of which is for your files) of a Certificate of Authenticity, covering the Crude Oil despatched in the T/V 'TEAECYOOD' yesterday to France, .'/ill you kindly certify the signature of Mr. R.M. Brown, Assistant Refinery Superintendent? For your information I quote a paragraph in a letter from the American Vice Consul in Baghdad dated February 24, 1937:- 'Inasmuch as difficulty is experienced in deciphering the signature of the British Political Officer at Bahrein, it would be appreciated if you would kindly endeavor to have the name of the officer typed under his signature.” If you can see your way clear to comply with its request I will be very grateful. Yours faithfully. G. VY. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. Enel:THE 3 AFREIN PETROLEUM OCiOPAIIY LDOITED Bahrein Island 9 Persian Gulf April 10 9 1937 CERTIFICATE OF AUTHENTICITY (Conforming to the French Decree of July 29, 1928) The undereigned, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, certify that the total amount of CRUDE OIL 9 &amp; 563 0 975 Tons, loaded April 9/10, 1937, at Sitra Terminal, Bahrein Island, in the British T/ 'TEAIT/OOD', is of current quality, coming from Bahrein fields, and that it has only been produced, dehydrated or stabilized and that nothing has been added to it other than the natural gases which ing normal production operationSo Three 5-gallon samples of this crude oil have been taken by ourselves, sealed, and marked as follows :~ EAKftOOD', Bahrein Island, Persian Gulfo April 9, 1937o BAHREIN CRUDE PETROLEUM THE BAHREIN PETROELUM COMPANY LIMITED, CEiflifiil) that tm gi^&amp;tujrts market 'V an« T x f above oi i r. ; ; l# arts gtnuine* For Refinery Superintendent THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED .So He BROWN, For Refinery Superintendent M 0 B. STEELE, State Engineer li*i** f s loliuoiil jEarai/*/o/q/b^y/ a/l/l ji. yt9 - a Telegraphic Address: OftAY lv.ACKENZia &amp; COMPANY, I MITED '’GRAY' Codes used: Bentley's Complete Phrase Code Bentley's Second Phrase Code IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE N? L/462. L yy The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Bahrein, 13th April Y y ay \ ^ /&lt;9 2,7 A'- /i/t A We would refer you to the amount of Rs.5/- paid to your oifice on the 13th February 1937 oil account of a certain for. R.T.Can.eron, of the Bahrein Petroleum Company. We are now advised by the Oil Company that that they have no R.T.Gameron on their staff and the I.r. R.Cameron, one of their employees, has no knowledge yi d-p yy havin s incurred this expense in connection with w \ attestation fees on documents. We shall therefore be glaa if you will kindly supply us more details in order that we may identify this debit. For your information, we would advise that this amount was paid in to the agency, together with a sum of Rs.12/8/- in connection with attestation fees on certain documents of for. foax Thornberg. Yours faithfully, i-iy /k'V^k / ] n The Bahrein petroleum company limited © Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf April 15, 1937 -*7 Colonel Gordon Loch, The Political Agency, Manama* Dear Colonel Loch: Enclosed is a copy of a letter from Lyon &amp; Lyon to the Standard Oil Company of California concerning the difficulty ex» perienced in Washington D.C* in requesting the British Ambassador to recognise Captain A.C. Stewart's signature, which copy you requested from me this morning* Very truly yours. WPAiFVK Enel:LYON &amp; LYON Mareh 24, 1937. Standard Oil Company of California, Standard Oil Building, San Francisco, California. ATTENTION: Mr. J. N. Adams Gentlemen: Re: Shlffler &amp; Anderson Reissue Ai)T)l t n - Docket 44/47 The reissue application above noted, executed by Mr. Anderson at Bahrein Island, has presented quite a problem in that the British Ambassador refused to recognise the signature and was not in position to certify that whoever signed the papers was authorized to administer oaths. The signature of the political agent which appeared on the original was almost unintel ligible and the British Ambassador, upon being Interviewed and upon checking up with the files, found that a Gordon Loch is now the agent at Bahrein Island whereas the signature did not fit this particular name at all. Mr. Mason interviewed the Law Examiner, the Chief Clerk and the British Ambassador and finally filed the application for reissue in order to save time. Some objection will probably be raised as to the formality of the signature but the application will apparently be given a filing date and the Examiner will proceed to act thereon. The new papers which are attached should be executed by Mr. Shiffler and then forwarded to Mr. Anderson with the following instructions: (1) - H.B.M.*s Political Agent should affix his seal to each and every page of the entire application and to the gold seal which holds the ribbons together. (2) - H.B.M. v s Political Agent should have his named typed on the last page immediately below the agent's signature so that we and the British Ambassador can have some means of identifying the man. (3) - The papers should be returned to us so that we can procure a certificate from the British Consul or from the British Ambassador to the effect that this particular Political Agent is duly authorized to administer oaths. Please send these instructions to Mr. Anderson and ask him to specifically infoim us as to the Agent's name and ascertain that the signer has been duly authorized to administer oaths. Very truly yours, Sd. Lyon &amp; Lyon.f\O copy LYON $t LYON * © 7 March 24, 1937. Standard Oil Company of California, Standard Oil Building, San Francisco, California, ATTENTION: Mr, J. N. \daraa Gentlemen: Re: Shlffler » Anderson Hei^gue Ap^1* n'- Docket 44/47 The reiasue application above noted, executed by Mr, Anderson at Bahrein Island, has pre ented ruite a problem in that the British Ambassador refused to recognise the signature and vas not in position to certify that whoever signed the papers was authorized to administer oaths. The signature of the political agent which appeared on the original was almost unintel ligible and the British Ambassador, uron being interviewed and upon checking up with the files, found that a Gordon Loch is now the ag^nt at Bahrein Island whereas the signature did not fit this particular name at all. Mr, Mason interviewed the Law Examiner, the Chief Clerk and the British Ambassador and finally filed the application for reissue in order to save time. Some objection will probably be raised as to the formality o* the signature but the application will apparently be given a filing date and the Examiner will proceed to act thereon. The new papers which are attached should be executed by Mr. Ghiffler and then forwarded to Mr. Anderson with the following instruct!ons-i (1) - H.B.M.’s Political Agent should affix his seal to each and &lt;»very Page of the entire application and to the gold seal which holds the ribbons together. (2) - H.B.M.’s Political Agent should have his named typed on the last page immediately below the agent’s signature so that we and the British Ambassador can have sooe means of identifying the nan. (3) - The papers should be returned to us so that we can procure a certificate from the British Consul or from the British Ambassador to the effect that this particular Political Agent is duly authorised to administer oaths. Please send these instructions to Mr. Anderson and ask him to specifically inform us as to the Agent’s name and ascertain that the signer has been duly authorized to administer oaths. Very truly yours.The Bahrein petroleum Company limited We enclose herewith Certificate covering 1 box containing 4 - 11.75-24 Tyres which are being returned to Bombay on or about the 20th instant per S.S. CHANTALA. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges to our account. MI. Enclo : Certificate, c.c. Storehouse. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD., G. W. R. SMITH. Chief Local Representative.1^0.920-5/3. Political iigency, Bahrain, tat 19th npril 1937. Iho Chiei Local Representative, the Balirain Petroleum company Li mite. , Bahrain. X Lear Sir, ith reference to your letter No.PA-178 hated tne 16th april 1937, i return herewith a certificate covering 1 box containing 4 - 11.75-24 Tyres, duly certified. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent,oahrain/ '''S Enel: % The Bahrein No. PA-180. Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, April 20, 1937. His Britannic Majesty f s Political ^gent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, URGENT. I enclose original and two copies of the Certificate of Origin and original and two copies of the Certificate of Authenticity - both in connection with the shipment of Crude Oil made yesterday in the T/7 'POSEIDONE' to Fiume, Italy. Will you please certify the signature of Mr. J.T. Deane on the original and one copy of each of these documents, returning them to me? The third copy of each document is, as usual, for your files . Yours very truly. G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, 0 I i A Bahrein Island c Persian Onlfo Aprf.l 19 # 1937 „ WE HEREBY CERTIFY THAT PRODUCT SHIPPED APRIL 19, 1937, in the T/V 'POSEIDONE' TO FIUME, ITALY IS CRUDE OIL AS COMING OUT OF OIL WELLS EXCEPT WITH REGARD TO WATER AND SEDIMENT AND THAT THE CRUDE HAS NOT UNDERGONE ANY REFINING OPERATION OUTSIDE OF THE ORDINARY DECANTING TO LEAVE OUT MOST OF THE WATER AND SEDIMENT CONTENTSo THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, T 0 DEANE, lefioery Superintendent oa-.TlFI&amp;i tiiat toe signature isarkeu above oi !r. J/i.D aNl is genuine.The Bahrein petroleum company limited n Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, April 21, 1937. No.PA-182. His Britannic I.5ajesty f s Political Agent, BAHRXEN. U R G Dear Sir, In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude Oil made today in the British T/V 'GOLD SHELL' for a French Port or -^orts, I enclose original and three copies of the Certificate of Authenticity. Will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. J.L. McKee, retaining, as usual, one copy for your files ? Yours faithfully. G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.&amp; CERTIFICATE OF AUTICSNTICITY’ FOR CRUDE PETROLKUM OIL I the undersigned Jo n Lockhart McKee who ar. Chemist certify that the cargo of the T/V 'GOLD SHELL' caisistlng of 11,904.261 English Centre, and 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 Wing: by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, destined for the Refineries of the See5ate Anonyme des Petroles Jupiter at Pauillac and/or Petit-Couronne is corapored of crude oetroleuiis obtained freifi Bahreino subiected to any operation other than decantatIon, dehydration or stabilisation, and no product -as bosn added to it other than benzine resulting from the condensation of natural gases which fom part of this crude oil when it is in the ground. Six (6) certified s-.aple;- of t is crude oil as loaded on the T/7 'GOLD SHELL' accompany this Certificate^ Signed at Bahrein on April 21 k 1937 Tons loaded on April 20/21 1937 Into Tanks Nos^ 1, 2, 3 ; 4, This petroleum crude oil is of current quality, has rot been CERTIFIED that the signature marked f X f above oi' Mr. John Lockhart McKee is genuine. C/^ ( ^ H.B.M f s Political i^gent,Bahrain APR 211937Bahrein, April 23, 1937, T am enclosing herewith an Invoice covering 93 empty Oxygen and 36 empty Acetylene cylinders which Mr. C.tf. Deacon is returning to P.R. Behring Company, 89 Broad Street, New York, TT.S.A. These cylinders are to be shipped on this week’s down boat to connect at Bombay with Dollar Line steamer for onward shipment to New York* I shall be grateful for your returning to me the Invoice duly certified, debiting me with the cost of certification* Yours faithfully, Chief Local Representative, BAPCO. L '^ mrimm' 1 — 1 ■ »WMHi The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited In connection with the shipment of Crude Oil mde Certificate of Authenticity Original and two copies. Certificate of Origin Original and two copies. Will you be kind enough to certify the signature of Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, April 28, 1937 No.PA-193 His Britannic Majesty T s Political Agent, BAHREIN. URGENT. Dear Sir, yesterday in the T/v 'LUCIFERO' and with the Crude Oil shipped today in the T/V w KOLLGRIM ,, , please find enclosed the following documents for each shipment Mr. J.T. Deane on each document, retaining, as usual, for your files one copy of each Certificate. Yours faithfully G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, Enel:Ceroiiicd. caat tne articifes mentioned in the attacned lists ire the personal property of Lieuten; nt- \ Colonel Gordon Loch, C.I*£., end I heve satisfied myself thet they e.re being imported into Greet Britain for his personal uss. I1 'I /s $2) OHS BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, Bahrain Island, 'srsian Gulf o WE HEREBY CERTIFY THAT PRODUCT SHIPPED APRIL 28, 1937, IN THE T/V 'KOLLGRIM' TO TRIESTE-EAULE, ITALY IS CRUDE OIL AS COMING OUT OF OR './ELLS EXCEPT WITH REGARD TO WATER AND SEDIMENT AND THAT THE CRUDE HAS NOT UNDERGONE ANY REFINING OPERATION OUTSIDE OF THE ORDINARY DECANTING TO LEAVE OUT MOST OF THE WATER AND SEDIMENT CONTENTSo 7 E BAHREIN PETRt;L:. XI' TTfCn efiaery Superintendent. C^TIiiiiL that the aignature Marked ? X f above ol . r. J.T.D^JS is genuine, kinu April 193 V. / ^ n Agent, * :kraiA ~ (Perm* §^f.ju I The Bahrein petroleum Company limited No. PA-209 9/ y \(&amp;\ Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf ^ May 4, 1937, £?&gt;) l 1 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sirs I am enclosing herewith two powers given by Mr. E. A. Skinner to Mr. C. I. Graham of Ihe Texas Company (India) Limited, Bombay. Will you kindly authenticate these documents as you did in the case of similar powers given to Mr. M. H. Bush, and return them to me as soon as possible. Yours very truly. Enel: G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. w k i kz •- -'I. sbPrinted in England. Oct., 19»6. (400 pads.) /\ 27 a /-/96 If/JIS'/t, Under instructions from our Divisional Manager, Karachi, we return herewith for cancellation, the Power of Attorney issued to our Mr Bottomley. Yours faithfully. Officer in Charge, Cable !e Wireless Ltd,, Bahrain, Encs- Power of Attorney No 5 of 1936 - Co-*' ... 7 ^ i / c V O $4V Uo. 1001-5/3 PoXitical Agency, Bahrain, the 1st May 1037. aTT To The Officer-in-Chfcrge, Cable and tireless Limited, BAHRAIN. \A Dear £ir. With reference to your letter No. 15/3 dated the 26th April 1337, I return the Power of Attorney, No. 5 of 1336, issued to Mr. C. Bottomiey duly cancelled* Yours faithfully. n A for Political Agent, Bahrain.No.1032-5/3. Political Agency, Bahrain, tne btn May 1937. To, The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limi tea, Bahrain. Lear Sir, With reference to your letter No.PA-209 da tea the 4th Itey 1937, I return herewith two certificates covering powers given by Mr.S.A.Skinner to Mr.C.I.Graham, uuiy attested. Yours fathfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain,GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; Co. (incorporated in ENGLAND.) HEAD OFFICE: 122, LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON, E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES used: BUSREH AMARAH KUT BRANCHES: KHORAMSHAHR BAHREIN AHWAZ (FOR KOWEIT BANDAR-SHAHPOUrt) DUBAI BUSHIRE SHARJAH BUNDER-ABBAS MUSCAT LINGAH Ltd. BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE In reply, please quote Bahrein, 10th.Lay, 19 37 The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Owing to the change of the name of this firm from 'The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation, Ltd.' to 'Gray Mackenzie and Co.,Ltd.' we have been endeavouring to effect the necessary alterations with the Adviser, Bahrein Government. For your information, we would mention that this Concern has actually three Title Deeds, but the last one was re gistered in connection with the re-claimed ground given by the Lana Department of the Bahrein Government which came into exist ence uhen, so that there are no further formalities required. With regard to the other two Title Deeds, it appears now that they were never registered with the Land Department of tne Bahrein a-overnment but at the Political Agency prior to the creation of the Land Department by the Bahrein Government. We shall be glad if you will have an endorsement put on the enclosed xible ueeds, similar to the endorsements in respect of previous transfers, to the effect that the property now becomes that of Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co.,Ltd. We, in turn, will send these Title Deeds to the Adviser who will, after a certain period, send us,c x Pa^re Two 1 (5 new Title Deeds. In support of our request, we are enclosing herewith copy of a letter from our Dusreh Office, together with a copy of a Deed of Transfer executed by the Liquidators in favour of Gray Lackenzit &amp; Co.,Ltd. We shall be grateful if the original Deed of Transfer may kindly be returned to us, and copy retain ed by you after it has been duly certified, as we will, in due course, require the original one for registration purposes in manner similar/with the Bahrein Government. As a period of 90 days is required by the Bahrein Government for a Proclamation, we would thank you to kindly return the enclosure to us as early as possible. Thanking you, Yours faithfully, Pur GLi Snc: fCOPY. GRAY MACKENZIE &amp; CO.LTD. •^Telegraphic Aadress 'GRAY” No.3RD/PRP/494. Busreh, 6 th May, 1937. BAHREIN. In continuation of our letter SRD/PRP/457 of the 29th ultimo, regarding transfer of properties, v/e now hand you herewith formal deed of transfer executed by the Liquidators in favour of Messrs. Gray Mackenzie and Co.,Ltd. Kfi We trust that the presentation of this docu ment to the Bahrein Government will enable you to have the Title Deeds transferred from the name of the M.P.C. Ltd., to the name of this Company. Please communicate with us immediately if any further information or documents are required in this connection. For GRAY MACKENZIE &amp; Co.Ltd., sd/- R.M.BROWN. * !..--s COPY. We, JAMS3 ANGUS AiMOUR and GERALD FORD PEARCE, Joint Liquidators of THE MESOPOTAMIA PERSIA CORPORATION, LIMITED, in Voluntary Liquidation, do hereby declare that the properties situate in Bahrein, and for which Title Deeds are held in their name, are hereby transferred to GRAY MACKENZIE &amp; COMPANY LIMITED. Joint Liquidators of the ( (sd/- James A. Armour Mesopotamia Persia Corpn.( ( Limited (In Voluntary ( (sd/- G. F. Pearce Liquidation) ( Busreh, 1st May, 1S37.GRAY. MACKENZIE &amp; Co., Ltd. ( INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND. ) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE: 122, LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON, E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES used: BENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BUSREH AMARAH KUT KHORAMSHAHR BAHREIN AHWAZ (FOR KOWEIT BANDAR-SHAHPOURl DUBAI BUSH1RE SHARJAH BUNDER-ABBAS MUSCAT LINGAH In reply, quote No. p ie a fie P89. Bahrein, 10th May, 1 The P 0 litical Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, We have been asked by our Busreh Office to obtain a Certificate from you that no mortgages have been registered at the Political Agency in respect of our property in Bahrein. This Certificate is required by Messrs.Lynch Brothers whose Accountants are, at present, investigating the accounts of The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Ltd., as at 31st December, 1936. We enclose herewith our Busreh Office’s letter in original, as well as a letter we have received from the Adviser to the Bahrein Government. We shall be glad if you will kindly return these original letters to us, with a Certificate which you may deem necessary to issue. Thanking you, Yours faithfully,o Political iigency, Bahrain, tne Ibtn May 1937, Messrs* Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limitec, Bahrain. BL Dear Sirs, With reference to your letter No.l/462 dated tne 13tii April 193/, tne name of your employee was in actual fact ' !r * ^•CANNON - and not .Ir.R.T.Cameron. Will you kindly debit tne former in place of Mr. Cameron for the fee of As. 5/- which has now been received, ihe erwor is regretted. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.*The Bahrein petroleum Company limited r Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, May 15, 1S37. No .PA-226. His Britannic Majesty f s Political Agent, BAHREIN. URGENT. Dear Sir, In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude Oil made yesterday in the Norwegian T/V W CHR. TH. BOE' for a French Port or Ports, I enclose original and three copies of the Certificate of Authenticity. Will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. J.L. McKee, retaining, as usual, one copy f&gt;r your files ? Yours faithfully. G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.No. -5/3. Il’l*' Political AgeuC,y, Bahrain, tne 18tn Iw v U3V. To, Messrs. Gray, Slackensie and Company Limitea Bahrain. Dear 8irs, With rei'erence to your letter No.?89 dated tne 10th May 1937, I am enclosing a certificate as requested by you. The original letters lorwaraed with your above letter are returnee herewith. 2. Will you please remit a sum of Rs.3/8/- on account ol the following charges:- Fee for the certificate Rs.2.8.0. Search fee ’» 1.0.0. Total Rs.3.8.0. Yours faitniully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.I made a search in the Document Registers but could not find that any document of mortgage concerning the property of Messrs. Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Ltd. has been registered in tfcis Agency. 13/5/37GRAY. MACKENZIE &amp; Co.. Ltd. mead office: 122. LEADEN HALL STREET. LONDON, E.C.3. telegraphic address: GRAY CODES used: (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) BRANCHES: BUSREH KHORAMSHAHR am ARAM AHWAZ (FOR KUT BANDAR-SHAHPOUR) BUSHIRE BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH 1® BAHREIN KO WEI T DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT 19 stEtin^ tnat the cost of this amounts to Rs.3/8/-. We have also to acknowledge receipt of your letter No.1179/6/3 of the same date, returning to us two Title Deeds and a Deed of Transfer, and we none that for such a transfer the sum of Ks.5/- is to oe paid. he tnank you for your kind attention in granting the certificate and making the transfer on the Title Deed, and we have pleasure in e^iclosing herewith the sum of Rs.b/b/- receipt of which kindly acknowledge. Yours faithfully,No. -5/3. Political Agency, Baiirain, the IPtu thj \337&gt; To, Messrs. Cray, Mackenzie ana Company Limiteci, Banrain. Dear Sirs, \ it i th reierence to your letter No.?/88 da tea the 10th May 1937, the two title deeds are returned herewith duly endorsee as desired. The Deed of Transfer is also returned herewith. 2. Will you please remit ine a sum of Rs.5/- on account of fees. dp Yours faithfully, 0^ for Political Agent,.Bahrain.Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited, Bahrain, having applied to me for a certificate giving particulars of registered mortgages, if any, in respect of the property mentioned below 1. A plot of land situated on the seashore at Manamah. Length, from east to west 19V uharas and breadth from north to south, 160 anaras, the title deed whereof has been registered in this agency under No.l of 1909. Big house with a small nouse adjoining it on the east side ana on the west by a compound, both situate on the seashore at I&amp;namah, the title eeed whereof has been registered in this Agency under No.2 of 1909. I hereby certify that a search has been made in the ‘’Register of Documents” maintained by H.B.M f s Political Agent, Bahrain, from 1st January 1914 to the 30tn npril 193V, and that no such encumbrances afiectm the said property were found to have been registered. Captain, H.B.M T s Political Agent, Bahr Ml 71937 Application presented on lltn l.lay 193V. Searcn completed on 13tn May 193V. U r[tl- ^ . 9/ 7 /f/j7The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, May 22, 1937. No. PA-255. His Britannic IWfetjesty’s Balitical Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude Oil made yesterday in the Norwegian T/V 'STORANGER', will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. J.L. McKee on the original and two copies of the Certificate of Authenticity enclosed ? One additional copy of the Certificate is enclosed for your files. Yours faithfully, G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel:CERTIFICATE OF AUlHMTICr'K FOR CRUDE PETROLEUM OIL uV I ths undersigned John Lockhart McKee vdio am Ches&amp;ist cei'tify that the cargo of the T/T 'STORANCER” consisting of English Tons loaded on May 20/21, 193? into Tanks Noa 0 l c 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 6 S 9 Port, l^ 2, 3* 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 Starboard and 1 after 1 forward B 2 after 2 forward, 4 after 4 forward Susxaertanks by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited destined for the Refineries of the Societe Anonyme dsa Petroles 'JUPITER' at Paul 11ac and/or Petit-Couronne is cce,;x.'^ ed of crude petroleum obtained from Bahreino This petroleiim c^de oil is of current quality, has not been subjected to any operation other than decantation c dehydration or stabilisation^ and no product has been added to it other than beaz-ire resulting froc the condensation of natural gases which forr* part of this crude oil when it is in the ground- Six (6) certified samples of this crude oil as loaded on the T/V 'STORATlGER' accomi any this Certificate 0 Signed at Bahrein on May 21, 1937 0 A/ OWilfllD tn&amp;t tne signature ■irked f X f above of Mr. J.L.McKee, is genuine. 22nd May 1937 , Political igent,Bakrain. &lt;5^The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No. i^A-241 , May 24, 1937 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, Tflfe are enclosing herewith American passport application forms of Messrs. D. Nix and J.P. Schloesslin which were signed in your presence on May 8th 1937. We are informed by the American Consulate-General in Baghdad that your signature and seal should be affixed on these forms at the point marked x and we would much appreciate it if you could do this and return the forms to us at your e arly con venience. Enclo: G.V/.R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LHIITED.Fo. l°61-5/3 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 27th lay 1937 To The Chief Local Tlenresentative, Tiie Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain* ' Bear Sir, ’Vith reference to your letter Ho* if PA-241 dated the 24th M ay 1937, I return the forms in question duly signed and sealed. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahraini - t Dear Captain Hickinbotham, When returning to the United States, for Customs purposes and income tax, it would be extremely helpful if I could have a statement from you to the effect that I have resided in Bahrein from May 27, 1931 until June 20, 1937. The only exceptions have been several leaves during that time. It would also be helpful if I could have a state ment that the 15 boxes I am shipping to California contain nothing but personal and household effects that have been in Mrs. Skinner’s and my possession one year or more. We would be willing to make an affidavit to this effect before you and we could also get witnesses. If you could do anything for me in either, or both, of these matters I would appreciate it very much.The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, June 1, 1937 No.PA-259 His Britannic Majesty’s Iblitical Agent BAHREIN U R G E N T. Dear Sir In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude Oil to France in the Dutch T/v 'EULOTA' yesterday, I enclose original and three copies of the relative Certificate of Authenticity; will you be kind enough to certify the signature of Mr. J.L. McKee on this document ? I also enclose original and two copies of the^Consular Invoice and Certificate of Origin*in connection with the shipment made today in the S/S 'BAMDRA' to Saigon, French Indo-China. Will you be kind enough to certify the signature of Mr. J.T. Deane on the original and one copy of this latter document ? One copy of each of the above mentioned documents is for your files. Yours faithfully G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED,APm^rriCITY FOR CRUDg PSTROLEUI’i OIL I the undersigned John Lockhart IfcKse who amChesist certify 4 ha'- the cargo of the T/Y 'EULOTA' consisting of 8 p 669o994 English and l 9 2 # 3, 4„ 5, 6 9 7 f 8 WTing (Port and Starboard) by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited destined for the Refineries of the Societe **0 ed to any ope ttion other than decantation, dehydration or stabilisation^ and no product has been added to it other than benzine resulttCL frcm the condensation of natural gases which form part of this crude oil when it is in the ground. Six (6) certified staples of this crude oil as loaded on the T' ^StTOTA' accompany this Cert Ifi cate a Tons loaded on May 30/31, 1937 into Tanks NoSc 1, Z 9 3, 5, 7, 8 Centre, Anonyroe des Petroles M JUPITER' at Pauillac and/or Petit-Couronne is cc*aposed of crude petroleum obtained from Bahreir cf current quality, has not been. Signed at Bahrein on May 31, 1337 * 0i‘ Ms-* Joim iodchart t£i*&amp; wtiatr th&amp; ai^a«tu:re m feki X aton lm* &lt;ujdfch&amp;ct i : 43km Lb \D*0* No*X301-5/3* The 2nd June 1937. Will you please refer to your demi-official letter of May 31st to Captain Hickinbotham con cerning the certificate of sojourn. I 1 !*! sure he will be very glad to do it for you - or if he is detained I will do it for you myself. If you get the necessary papers ready perhaps you would care to bring them along on the 5th June. E.A. Skinner, Esquire, BahrainThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited No.PA-265. Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, June 3rd, 1937 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, V.e find that by an oversight no copy of the passport photograph of Thomas Nevill Deane was certified by you when authenticating the passport applications for him and his sister. We are enclosing herewith one copy of this photograph and would very much appreciate it if you would certify and return at the earliest opportunity. Yours very truly Enclo; G. W. R. SMITH Chief Local Representative. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LIMITEDThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, June 9, 1937 Dear Tomlinson I am enclosing two documents which I would like to have you authenticate if possible* It seems to me that the one regarding our residence would be more effective if it were on your stationery, but if there is any objection the copy enclosed should suffice. Many thanks for your trouble B. L. Tomlinson, Esq*, Manama, Bahrein.Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf June 9, 1937 TO WHOM IT MAY CONCERN: It is known to me that Mrs, Irene H. Skinner and Mr, E. A, Skinner have resided on Bahrein Islands in the Persian Gulf since October 1931 and May 1931 respec tively, except, of course, for regular periodical leaves.The 9th June 1937. TG WHOM IT MAY CCNCKHtf: It is known to me that ? T rs. Irene H* Skinner and Mr* E*A* Skinner have resided on Bahrain Islands in the Persian Gulf since October 1931 and May 1931 respectively, except, of course, for regular periodical leaves. &gt; vThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ©&gt; Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, June 9, 1937 PA-267. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: I am enclosing herewith two substitute powers of attorney in favor of Mr. C. W. Deacon, Acting Resident Manager of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited; also a letter from the Head Office in New York authorizing Mr. E. A. Skinner to make this assignment. Would you please authenticate the two documents, returning them to us when you have done so? Sincerely yours G. W. R. SMITH Chief local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, URGE N T. T/V 'KOLLGRHVI” sailed yesterday with a cargo of Crude Oil for Trieste-zaule, Italy, and in connection therewith please find enclosed the following documents Certificate of Authenticity Original and two copies Certificate of Origin Original and two copies. Will you be kind enough to certify the signature of Mr. C.M. Cutbirth on each document, retaining, as usual, for your files one copy of each Certificate ? Yours faithfully, / G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel:No* 1353—5/3 • Political Agency, Bahrain, the 11th June 1937. To The Chief Local Kepr&lt; sentative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited Bahrain* Dear Sir, 'ith reference to your letter No. PA-267 cated the 9th June 1937 X return the powers of attorney duly certified. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, BahrainNO.X355L5/3* Political Agency, Bah-cein, the 11th June 1937# To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain • Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No* P.A.268 dated the 10th June 1937 I return the Certificate of Authenticity and Certificate of Origin duly attested. Y our 3 fa i th \il ly, % for Political Agent, Bahrain.J ? THE BAHREIN PRTROIEUM COIJPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island 9 Persian Culfo \T&amp; FJSREBY GERTIE TilAT PPJCITCT SIHPPED JON'S 9* 193?, IN THE T/Y w K0LI/&gt;RIM H TO TRIS3TE-ZAULE, ITALY IS GRIDE OIL AS COMING OFT OF OIL mLS EXCEPT WITH REGARD TO WATER AND SSDBiENT AND’THAT THE CRUDE HAS NOT UNDERGONE ANY REFINING OPERATION OUTSIDE OF THE ORDINARY DECANTING TO LEATB OUT MOST OF THE WATER AIT) SEDIMENT CONTENTS o THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, Foj s? e: r i i ie / t j signature marked X above 0-. d. ■ # o .L, Gutbirth is genuine. M. B. ms. Political Agent, £ahram, (Persian QuiJ.J ; t CUTBLOT, y Super!ntendeat 0MH ' CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY A1 Khobar, Saudi Arabia June 13, 1937 TC T .VHQP.* IT VAY CONGER?! In accordance with the Power of Attorney granted me by the Board of Directors of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company on T.'ay 11, 1937, I, Floyd William Ohliger, hereby appoint Iv'r. Charles Isaac Graham, bearer of this letter, as The Agent of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company with full power and authority to arrange for Indian workers to be engaged for the service of this Company in Saudi Arabia, and to take such action in connection with the emigration of such workers as may be required by the Emigration Act, 1922, endorse in the name of the Company, deposit with the Protector of Emigrants, and collect interest on the following bond:- I specifically authorize Mr. Charles Isaac Graham to Government of India 3^ loan 1951/1954 bond ITo. B001059 for Es. 2,000 CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANYthe Bahrein petroleum company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, June 16, 1937, No.PA-275. His Britannic Majesty r s Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude Oil made yesterday in the Italian T/V 'POSEIDONE', please find enclosed original and two copies of each of the following documents, viz Certificate of Origin Certificate of Authenticity Will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. A. Fellows on the original and one copy of each document, retaining one copy of each for your files ? In addition to the above documents, I am also enclosing original and three copies of a Commercial Invoice in connection with the shipment of two sample drums of Diesel Fuel Oil to Manila, Philippine Islands in the B.I. S/S 'BANKURA'; will you be kind enough to certify the signature of Mr. M.H. Lipp on the original and two copies of this invoice, retaining the fourth copy for your files ? Yours faithfully, L /L^ G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THS BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel:June 15 9 1937 0 WE HEREBY CERTIFY THAI’ PRODUCT SUPPED JOTIE 15, 1937, IN THE T/V 'POSEIDONE” TO TRIESTE-ZAIJLE r ITALY IS CRUDE OIL AS COMING OUT OP OIL WELLS EXCEPT WITH REGARD TO WATER AND SEDIMENT AND THAT THE CRUDE HAS NOT UNDERGONE ANY REPINING OPERATION OUTSIDE OF THE ORDINARY DECANTING TO LEAVE OUT MOST OF THE WATER AND SEDIMENT CONTENTSo THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, By A. FELLOWS, For Refinery Superintendentothe Bahrein petroleum company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, June 19, 1937. No. PA-233. if V . ' v O / ' ! frV?;' \ ^ -T 0 j(JI^ ^ H. B. lifejesty’s Political Agent, X.. ' V. - . Bahrein. URGE N T. Dear Sir, In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude °il made yesterday in the Danish T/V 'HSNNING MASRSK', will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. J.L. McKee on the original and two copies of the Certificate of Authenticity enclosed ? One additional copy of the Certificate is enclosed for your files. Yours faithfully. G. .7. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHSIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.No, C /471 Political Agency, Bahrain, dated the PSnd June 1 jc7* To F# Y,. Ohli^er, Fsquire, California Arabian Stanaard Oii. Company, AJL Kuo bar. Sir, With reference to your r quest that I should certify that you are duly empowered to take the action st ted in your Notice dated the 13th June 1J87, I regret that X cannot sign the desired certificate. I am pre pared to state that I have examined tne minutes of the Meeting of the Board of Directors of the California Ara bian Standard Oii Company, dated Tuesday May the 11tn, 1937, and that a resolution was passed constituting you as their true and lawful attorney with full power end authority on behalf of the Company to arrange either directly or through such agent or agents in British India as you may appoint, for Indian workers to be eng. g a for the service of the Company in 8a f uci Arabia ana that you with the emigration of such workers as may be required by the provisions of the Indian Emigration Act, 1j22, through such agent or agents. I can further certify that evidence has been produced before me to the effect that the minutes of this Meeting were sworn to, subacrlbec are further autuorisod to take such action in connectionTEE BAHREIN PETROLEUM GO.LTD. A a Bahrein Islands, 20th June 1937. H.B.M. f s Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear* Sir, I send you herewith an Invoice in duplicate one Monarch Submarine Hose, for favour of attestation. The attestation charge will be paid by me. Ycurs faithfully, G. W. R. Smith, Chief Local Representative, Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd. Erie. 2. ►No.1419-5/3. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 23rd June 1937. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Reference your letter dated the 20th June 1937. \ \ 2. I return the invoice for one Monarch Submarine Hose duly attested. The attestation fee of os.2/8/- may please be refunded early. Yours faithfully, fThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, June 27, 1937 No .PA-296. His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, BAHREIN. made yesterday in the Italian T/V 'DJCIFERO', please find enclosed original and two copies of each of the following documents, viz on the original and one copy of each document, retaining one copy of each for your files ? Certificate of Origin Certificate of .Authenticity Will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. A. Fellows Yours faithfully, G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDI 7 TJD 2 BAHREIN PETROLEUIvl COMPANY' LIMITED, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulfo June 26, 1937c WE HEREBY CERTIFY' THAT PRODUCT SHIPPED JUNE 26, 1937, IN THE T/V 'LUCIFERO' TO TRIESTE-ZAULS, ITALY IS CRUDE OIL AS COMING OUT OF OIL WELLS EXCEPT WITH REGARD TO WATER AND SEDIMENT AND THAT THE CRUDE HAS MOT UNDERGONE ANY REFINING OPERATION OUTSIDE OF TIE ORDINARY DECANTING TO LEAVE OUT MOST OF THE WATER AND SEDIMENT CONTENTSo THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LB,IITED, A. FELLOWS, For Refinery Superintendent 0 CKBTIFI3D that tne sirma tore rnarKou 'V above ot 'Jr- A,F^LLCWr&gt; is genuine. Dated June 1^3?.CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY A1 Khobar, Saudi Arabia June 28, 1937 Captain T* Tlickinbotham, Political Agent, Bahrain, Sir: Thank you for your letter TTo. C/471 dated 22 June 1937, in which you state the conditions under which you are prepared to attest the Notice submitted for your signature, I will call at your office semetime next week so that you may witness my signature and prepare the statements you suggest. This letter acknowledges the receipt of the documents relative to my Power of Attorney, Sincerely, ^. o,t F. W. OHLIGEH Resident T'anageri^ear Sir, I enclose herewith in duplicate, invoice covering material being returned to t Lie United States zor xavour of certification. Cost of this certification will be paid by this office. . fours faithfully, (G.U.R. Smith) Chief Local Representative. Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, July 14, 1937. No.PA-319. His Britannic Majesty f s Political Agent, BAHREIN. URGE N T. Dear Sir, In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude Oil made yesterday in the Dutch T/V 'MCGMA.' for a French Port or Ports, I enclose original and three copies of the Certificate of Authenticity. Will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. J.L. McKee, retaining, as usual, one copy for your files ? Yours faithfully. G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel:© 77 CERTmCATE OF AUTHENTICITY FOR CRUDE PETROLEUM OIL ; I the undersigned John Lockhart McKee who am Chemist certify that the cargo of the T/V 'MACOMA' consisting of ll s 060 t 350 English Tons loaded on July 18/13, 1937 into Tanks Nos* x t 2 9 3, 4 8 5 S 6 , 7 Centre, and 1 9 3, 4 9 5 W 7 Wing (Port and Starboard) by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited destined for the Refineries of the Societe Anonyms des Petroles 'JUPITER' at Pauillac and/or Petit~Couronne is composed of crude petroleum obtained from Bahrein* This petroleum crude oil is of current Quality, has not been subjected to any operation other than decantation* dehydration or stabilisation, and no product has been added to i„ other than benzine resulting from the condensation of natural gases whioh form part of this crude oil when it is in the ground* Six ( 6 ) certified samples of this crude oil as loaded on the T/V 'MACOjMA* accompany this Certificatep Signed at Bahrein on July 13, 1937* \1 CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY BsLrein, Persian G-ulf, July 19, 1937. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein, Persian Gulf. Attent ion of Mr. B. _ L. Mi. Tomli nson Bear Sir: This will acknowledge receipt of your letter of July 18, 1937, with which you enclosed various docu ments covering Mr* Lloyd William Ohliger’s appointment of Mr. Charles Isaac Graham as agent in British India to recruit Indian workers for service with the Califor nia Arabian Standard Oil Company, A 1 Khobar, Saudi Arabia. As Mr. Ohliger 1 s signature on the letter of authorization was attested by you, I am enclosing the attestation fee of Rs. 2 - 8 - 0 , Thanking you, I am Yours very truly, W. M. Porker m &amp;L y~ xHM tx&gt; '■ r 6V 2-1 1 F cc Mr. L. W. OhligerI re&amp;pectfully beg to state that I had purchased two carpets in 1931 for ray personal use and since then they are in my possession. As I wish to take them with me to India for my personal use there, I respectfully beg to request you kindly to favour me with a certificate to the effect that the two carpets are in my possession for the last seven years and they are for my personal use only. I beg to state that I have no receipt with me as they were purchased on cash payment. If you will kindly grant me the certificate as requested above, it will save me from unnecessary troubles given by the Customs authorities in India. I therefore beg to i request you kindly grant me the certificate if possible.Dated the 16th July 1937• TO ALL WHOM IT 'MY CC*mm The bearer of this letter Mr* Abdul Jabbar Aneari is an official of this Agency f and is proceeding on 8th months’ leave to India* British Government Officials in India are requested to afford him all proper facilities of which he may stand in need* for Political Agentf Bahrain*Dated the 16 th July 1937. Certificate of Ownership» Certified that the personal effects of Mr* Abdul Jabbar Ansari f an official of this Agency f include the two carpets the dimensions o &gt; which are mentioned below, and they are in his poseessicn for the last seven years and they are for his personal use only* One carpet 9 • x 6 , -8* Cue Carpet 8 * x 6* 9 W / , for Political Agent, Bahrain^ m &gt;' 1 ;, \ /The 16th July 1937• I hereby certify that I have examined the minutes /' &gt; y of the Meeting of the Board of Directors of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company, dated, Tuesday, May the 11th, 1937, and that a resolution was passed constituting j\ ur* Floyd W* Ohliger as their true and lawful attorney with full power and authority on behalf of the Company / to arrange either directly or through such agent or f agents in British India as he may arpoint, for Indian i Workers to be engaged for the service of the Company in Sa'udi Arabia and that he is further authorised to take such action in connection with the emigration oC such workers as may be re ,uired by the provisions of the Indian Emigration Act, 1932, through such Agent or Agents*, I further certify that evidence has been produce' before me to the effect that the minutes of this meeting were sworn to, subscribed to and executed before the Notary Public of the City and County of San Francisco. ~) Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain.no. / s' e s* Political Agency f Bahrain the 18th July 1937* To F*W« Ohliger Esquire, California Arabian Standard Oil Company, A1 Khobar* Sir, With reference to your letter dated the 28th June 1937, I forward herewith the certificate and the relative documents ,duly signed and attested by me the receipt of which please acknowledge* Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain*THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 4 BAHREIN, 17th July 1937 The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith two invoices in duplicate in connection with export of cylinders for favour of the necessary certification. Kindly return same to this office when done with Yours faithfully, /Ld (G.W.R.Smith) Chief Local Representative, Bahrein Petroleum Company.CERTIFICATE OF AUTHENTICITY FOR CRUDE PETROLEU1I OIL I the undersigned John Lc*ekhart McKee v/ho an Chemist Certify that the cargo of the T/V 'HENNING lAERSK' consisting of 14,464 0 934 English Tons loaded on June 17/18, 1937 into Tanks Nos 0 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 Centre, and 1, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 Ylng (Port and Starboard) by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited destined for the Refineries of ' the Societe Anonyms des Petroles 'JUPITER' at Paulline and/or Petit~ v Couronhe is composed of crude petroleum obtained frou ;3ahi»in 0 ■subjected to any operation other than decantation, dehydration or Stabilisation, and no product has been added to it other than benzine This petroleum crude oil is of current quality, uas not been resulting from this condensation of Jiatural gases ?/hich fom part of / // | Six: ( S) certified sa pie 3 of this cm ? oil loaded on the &gt; / /• Certified that the sl/jr^turc niarkeci X above of *£r* J*L* Mckee is genuJiie* K B. M's. Political Agent, B ahrain. (Persian Guij.)THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, July 27, 1937. No. PA-539. His Britannic Iviajesty's Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, URGE NT. In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude Oil made on July 25, 1937, in the Italian T/V 'LAURA CORRADO”, please find enclosed original and tv/o copies of each of the following documents, viz :- Certificate of Origin Certificate of Authenticity Will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. A. Fellows on the original and one copy of each document, retaining one copy of each for your files ? Yours faithfully. G. W. R. SMITH, ; '' Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel: 'X// V 27 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, July 25, 1937 WE HEREBY CERTIFY THAT PRODUCT SHIPPED JULY 25, 1937, IN THE T/V 'LAURA CORRADO' TO TRIESTE-ZAULE, ITALY IS CRUDE OIL AS COMING OUT OF OIL WELLS EXCEPT WITH REGARD TO WATER AND SEDIMENT AND THAT THE CRUDE HAS NOT UNDERGONE ANY RE FININS OPERATION OUTSIDE OF THE ORDINARY DECANTING TO LEAVE OUT MOST OF THE WATER AND SEDIMENT CONTENTS„ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED By For Refinery Superintendent Certified that the signature marked X above of Mr* A* Fellows is genuine* 1 \The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, July 28, 1937. No. PA-317 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, After duly examining the powers of attorney granted to Mr. Deacon by the Board of Directors of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, and by the Board of Directors of the California Texas Oil Company, Limited, will you kindly certify that the names and signatures appearing on the attached are true and correct, and that he has acted within his powers in issuing the limited powers to the employees whose names appear thereon? Yours very truly, G. W. R. SMITH Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.- * - ' -(g&gt; 9 1 3let July 1937. After duly examining the powers of attorney granted to Mr. Deacon by the Board of Directors of The Bahrein Petroleum Com any Limited, and by the Board of Directors of the California Texas Oil Company, -Lmited, I hereby certify that the names and signatures appearing on the attached are time and correct, and that he has acted within his powers in Issuing the limited powers to the employees whose names appear thereon.The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, August 2, 1937♦ No*PA-349. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, URGENT. Enclosed please find original and three copies of the Certificate of Flash Points in connection with the oils to be shipped in the T/Y W BELITA ,, which is expected to sail for Colombo, Ceylon, tomorrow morning. May we ask you to be kind enough to certify the signature of Mr. J*L. McKee, Chief Chemist, California Texas Oil Company, Ltd., using the words 'Sworn to before and sealed by'? We are instructed to send this Certificate of Flash Points with the ship herself to Colombo, and, for this reason, we ask you, if possible, to return the original and two copies to us today. The third copy of the Certificate is for your files. Yours faithfully, / G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel:The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited -V rv Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO: PA-362. August 8, 1937. His Britannic Majesty*s political Agent, Bahrein. TBB-809 Sir, I enclose herewith certificate covering 11 empty Acetylene cylinders which are being returned to New york for refilling. These cylinders are being shipped to Bombay on or about 9th inst. per s.S. 'BAMOHA' thence by Dollar Line to new York. please return the certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to xoy account. Yours truly. Gr. W. R. Siam Chief Local Representative. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited ^yv A Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, August 11, 1937. No .PA-565. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. URGENT. Dear Sir, In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Diesel Fuel made yesterday in the Italian T/V 'CLEIIA CAMPANSLLA', please find enclosed original and two copies of the follow ing document Certificate of Origin . Will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. A. Fellows on the original and one copy of the document, retaining one copy for your files ? Yours faithfully, G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY T-T^TEp Enel:i His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent Bahrein. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering 8 empty Freon (Dichlorodifluorooethane) Cylinders which are being returned to New York for refilling. These Cylinders are being shipped to Bombay on or about 23rd. instant per S.S. 'BARFETA' thence by Dollar Line to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to my account. C. W. R. SMITH Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.X Montu 0* Sousa hereby declare on oath that say India General Service lie dal 1908 with clasp Wazlrlatan 1U19-21 has boon lost oy me and cannot be recovered despite my endeavours to Ouom and attested before me on thl 5'C/0 The Bahrein Petroleum Co: Ltd., Bahrein, 9th. August 1937. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrein. (Ilanama) . Sir, I have been advised by the Defence Department Government of India, to forward to them a statuary declaration, i. e. (a declaration on oath}, and as such, I beg to apply to you for same. I had lost my full bar containing four medals in Bombay last September and although same was reported to the Police, I have not been successful in recovering same, in spite of my endeavours to do so. Name of the medals . General Service Medal ) Victory Medal } No: 5192 Montu D’Souza. Iraq Medal. ) Vaziristan Medal 68 , bearing No: 7091. I am also enclosing all the correspondence to the Army Department, and the Director of Posts &amp; Telegraphs, which I pray may be returned to me after your inspection. I hope you will please give me the Declaration so that I can forward same to the Defence Department. Thanking you in anticipation, I remain, Sir, Your obedient servant, Montu D’Souza, c/o Bapco Mess EallThe Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. August 24, 1937. No.FA-377. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. URGENT. Dear Sir, In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude Oil made yesterday in the Norwegian T/V' n BELITA t1 for Bordeaux, France, I enclose original and four copies of the Certificate of Authenticity. Will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. A. Fellows, retaining, as usual, one copy for your files 7 Yours faithfully. G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.August 23, 1937. CERTIFICATE OF AUTHENTICITY (Conforming to the French Decree of July 29, 1928) The undersigned, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, certify that the total amount of CRUDE OIL 9,649.688 Tons, loaded August 22/23, 1937, at Sitra Terminal, Bahrein Island, in the Norwegian T/V 'BELITA', is of current quality, coming from Bahrein fields, and that it has only been produced, dehydrated or stabilized and that nothing has been added to it other than the natural gases which escape during normal production operations. Three 5-gallon samples of this crude oil have been taken by ourselves, sealed, and marked as follows T/V 'BELITA', Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. August 22, 1937 0 BAHREIN CRUDE PETROLEUM 1HE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, By ^ “T ' A. FELLOWS, — For Refinery Superintendent. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, By a7 fellows, ' For Refinery Superintendent. Witnessed by THE BAHREIN GOVERNMENT, By I To CROWTHER-^aTH, Acting State Engineer&lt;f 0 H 01794 - 6 / 1 . British Agency * The Station Superintendent! Imperial Airways Limited f Sharjah* Dear Sir f Reference your letter No .HWC/5/442 dated the 8th September 1937* the regiateration of Motor Launches at Dubai* Copy with compliments to Political Agent,Bahrain, for information, together with copy of the Station Superintend- . There are no Regulations at present regarding Yours faithfully, enVs letter referred to above*@ f(J j Sharjah, SthSeptember 1937# The Residency Agervt, Sharjah# Dear Sir, I should be grateful If you will confirm that there are no regulations here regarding the registering of Motor Launches at Dubai* Copy* Ho•BSC/S/442• Yours faithfully, for &amp; on behalf of Imperial Airways Limited, Sd: R.M.Cole, Station Superintendent*The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. September 17, 1937. No.PA-408. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. U R G B N T. Dear Sir, In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude Oil made yesterday in the Dutch T/V 'GENOTA' for a French Port or Ports, I enclose original and three copies of the Certificate of Authenticity. Will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. J.L. McKee, retaining, as usual, one copy for your files ? Yours faithfully, G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel:THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LIMITED. Bahrein, 18th September 1937 The Political Agent BAHREIN. Dear Sir, We enclose herewith Invoices for empty Acetylene Calol and Carbon Dioxide cylinders which are being forwarded to U.3.A. by t his week f s Down Boat, for favour of attestation, Y 0 urs faithfully C. L. R. Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd (G.W.R.SMITH) Ends: Two invoices in duplicateTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, September 26, 1937. No.PA-425. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. URGENT. Dear Sir, In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude Oil made yesterday in the Norwegian T/V 'VANJA' for Bordeaux, France, I enclose original and four copies of the Certificate of Authenticity. Will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. A. Fellows, retaining, as usual, one copy for your files ? Yours faithfully. G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.S3*?.The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, October 12, 1937. No.PA-451. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHE3IN. URGENT. Dear Sir, In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude Oil made today in the Dutch T/V 'EULOTA' for a French Port or Ports, I enclose original and three copies of the Certi ficate of Authenticity. V/ill you kindly certify the signature of Mr. J.L. McKee, retaining, as usual, one copy for your files ? Yours faithfully. G. 1(7 • R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED,r (£zo) //^ CERTIFICATE OF AUTHENTICITY FOR CRUDE PETROLEUM OIL I the vndersigned John Lockhart McKee who am Chemist certify that the cargo of the T/* 'IULOTA ,, conaiatlng of 8,556.839 English Tons loaded on October 11/12, 1937 into Tanks Nos„ 1, 2, 3, 5, 7, 8 Centre, and 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 Wing (Port and Starboard) Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited destined for the Refineries |&gt;f the Societe Anonyxne dee Petroles 'JUPITER' at Pauillac and/or Peti^- Couronne is composed of crude petroleum obtained from Bahrein. This petroleum crude oil is of current quality, has not been subjected to any operation other than decantation, dehydration or stabilisation, and no product has been added to it other than benzine resulting from the condensation of natural gases rhicb form part of this crude oil afcen it is in the ground. Six (6) certified samples of this crude oil as locded on the T/Y 'EULOTA' accompany this Certificate. Signed at Bahrein on October 12, 1937 JOHN LOCKHART McKEE &lt; Cert, if led that the signature marked X above of Mr* J*L*McKee is genuine* H. B. M } i % Political Ageni, B akrain. (Per nan OxU/ JThe Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, NO:PA-460. October 13, 1937. His Britannic Majesty’s political Agent Bahrein. TBB-997 Dear sir, I enclose herewith certificate covering 11 empty Acetylene cylinders which are being returned to New York for refilling, ofliese cylinders are being shipped to Bombay on or about 17th inst., per S.S. 'BAMORA' thence by Dollar Line to New York. please return the certificate duly attested at your convenience , debiting charges in connection to my account. Yours truly, Cr. W. R. SMITH Chief Local Representative. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.V *■ BRITISH CONSULATE, GOA, Mormugao. 25th* September 193 7. From ,/AHDE j5jSC[* ^ M# C• 5 B • 3c* 5 A«M*X* C*E• ^&lt;SzC• 5 His Britannic Majestys Consul for jam, the Portuguese Possessions in India The Political Agent, BAH RAIN. Sir, In sending herewith the attached Power of Attorney which has been presented at this Consulate for my countersignature, I have the honour to request you to be so good as to let me know if the same was in fact signed before you, and if so, please send me your full name (IN BLOCK LETTERS) and a spe cimen signature for this Office record. Please return the document under registered cover for which I enclose herein annas - in Br. postage stamps* EncloS; 1* EPA I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, H.B.M's CONSUL.2136 - 6/3 Political Agency, Bahrain,the 16th October 1937. Sir, With reference t,© your letter No# 31/729 dated the 26th September 1937,1 have the honour to inform you that the power of attroney was counter-si^^ned by Captain A#C# 3TEWABT, who has since been transferred from Bahrain as His Britannic Majesty’s Vice Consul, Khorramshahr, Iran# 2# The Power of Attorney is returned herewith# Please acknowledge receipt# I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain# His Britannic Majesty's Consul, for the Portuguese Possessions in India British Consulate GOA.IN REPLY REFER TO FILE NO. 804.9 JCO/wjp^ t THE FOREIGN SERVICE OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA DEPARTMENT OF STATE , American Consulate General ^ Baghdad, Iraq, October 19, 1937 s ; y (‘Ni' - The British Political Agent, Bahrein Island, Bahrein, Persian Gulf. Sir: n I have received frora Mr. ?. .7. Ohliger of the Cali fornia Arabian Standard Oil Company a power of attorney signed by Mr. Albert Averett Rutan and acknowledged be fore Mr. 3. M. Siddir (?) under the title of 'Indian Assistant to the Political Agent, Bahrein, and Magistrate of the Second Class.' As the Consulate General will be glad to perform this service if possible and proper, I should be grate ful if you wuuld inform me whether the aforementioned official is authorized to perform notarial services. If such is the case, I should also appreciate receiving a specimen of his signature and seal in order that I nay be permitted by the instructions by which I am governed to authenticate his signature. Yours very truly, rse;h C. Satterthwaite American ConsulNo.2219-5/3 Poll ti cal, Agency, Bahrain, the 28th October 1937 To Sir The American Consul-Seneral Baghdad, ’IRAQ. With reference to your letter No.804.9 JCS/wjp dated f the 19th October 1937, I have the honour to iniora you tnat the Indian Assistant to tne Political Agent, haarain, is not authorised to perform notarial services. It will, I fear, be necessary for hr. F.W.Onliger to have a fresh po#er of attorney attested by tne Political Agent. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obeuient servant I.C.8., i Political Agent, BahrainThe Bahrein petroleum company limited NO: PA-492. 2 ^ Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, October 28, 1937. His Britannic Majesty’s political Agent, Bahrein. Return of empty preon - Sir, cylinders on FBB - 30. I enclose herewith certificate covering 8 empty preon cylinders which are being returned to New York for return to suppliers. These cylinders are being shipped to Bombay on or about 31st. instant per s. S. n BANI0JRA ,, thence by Dollar Line to New York. please return the certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to my account. Yours truly, 0. W. R. SMITH Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.UNITED STATES OF AMERICA LEGATION OF THE Baghdad, Iraq, January 27, 1938 The British Political Agent, Bahrein, Persian Gulf This Legation from tine to time receives requests that your signature which you have been good enough to affix to a notarial document for some person in Bahrein be authenticated in order that the document nay be used in the United States. It will be greatly appreciated, therefore, if you will be so good as to furnish a specimen of your signature and the seal of your office for the Legation’s files, in order that authentications in the future may be performed with the greatest possible expedition. May I take this opportunity to thank you most cordially for your courtesy. Very respectfully yours, P. Knabenshue, Minister Resident and Consul General. File ho. 804.9 &lt;y3/gkm@) / / p No. 3/0- - 5/3 Political Agency, Bahrain,the 21st February 1938. Sir, In reply to your letter dated the 27th January 1938 I have the honour to furnish below a specimen of Assistant Political Agent * s signature and the seal of my office, for your record. f J To Specimen Signature of Lieutenant R.E.R. Bird, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Office Sir, Your most obedient servant, iS- for Political Agent, Bahrain. Minister Resident and Consul General, Legation of the United States of America, Bag idad .Lc ted the S8th April UZ7 Dear Dirs, I have 2d packages of personal effects which I wish to have sent to Great Brit, In to be delivered at Ginlithgow Station by goods train. The boxes are all done up in gunny and each is marked with a number by the address. I attach a list of the numbers and also of a detailed statement of the contents of each box with the usual Certific; te given by the Political Agent stating thc.t the articles are my personal effects and for my personal use in Great Britain^ which are locked. A greater part of the effects are cover ed by a kit insurance but I should like the wooden box marked CIM insured separately for £ 20/- (pounds twenty sterling only). I should like it covered from the Agency to my Home (Binns, Binlithgow)• I also enclose eignteen keys of the various boxes Yours faithfully # Dieutenant-Coloncl. Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie end Company limited. B A H E A I H. J- /las- ^ \The Bahrein petroleum company limited @&gt; /i# Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, November 4, 1937. In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude Oil made today in the Swedish M/S 'BAIAKLAVA' for a French Port or Ports, I enclose original and three conies of the Certificate of Authenticity. WiH you kindly certify the signature of Mr. J.L. McKee, retaining, as usual, one copy for your files ? Yours faithfully, G. W. R. SMITH, Chief local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROIEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Encl:CERTIFICATE OF AUTHENTICITY FOR CRUDE PETROLEUM OIL I the undersigned John Lockhart McKee who am Chemist certify that the cargo of the M/S 'RALAXLAVA' consisting of 10^600 o 879 English Tons loaded on November 3/4, 1937 into Tanks Nos 0 1, 2 9 3, 4 9 5, 6 , 7, 8 Centre, and 1, 2, 3, 4 Wing (Port and Starboard) by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited destined for the Refineries of the Societe Anonyms des Petroles 'JUPITER' at Pauillac and/or Petit-Couronne is composed of crude petroleum obtained from Bahrein,, This petroleum crude oil is of current quality, has not been subjected to any operation other than decantation, dehydration or stabilisation, and mo product has been added to it other than benzine resulting from the condensation of natural gases which form part of this crude oil when it is in the groumdo Six ( 6 ) certified simples of this crude oil as loaded on the M/S 'BALAKLA^A' accompany this Certificateo Signed at Bahrein on November 4, 1937 e By \ OHN LOCKHART McKEE, Certified that the aignature marked X above of lire John Lockhart 5'cKee is genuine •no. 2 - 2 -£ Political Agency, ■Bahrain,the 6th November 1937 To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain* Dear Sir, Will you please arrange to send hs 17/8/- due to this office, on account of attesting share transfers on behalf of I'ajor Ferguson -Thomson* Yours faithfully, /u Folitical gent, T ’«hrain.No. 31/734 0 f i 93 7. BRITISH CONSULATE, CCA, M or mu geo, 3-S U • ,,\i 0 V'-Tilfc) 01'* 193 ' Fy om R.H.V7ARDE, Esq. ,M. C. ,B. 3c., A#M#I#G.E. ,&lt;ScC. , His Britannic Majesty*s Consul for G&amp;cti the Portuguese Possessions in India To The Political Agent, B AHRAIN . — \ Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of the Power of Attorney returned with your letter No.2136-5/3, dated the 15th ultimo. EPA. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, y\\. B. M' s CONSUL.'1 T’ l/w ^ 'JO / LV The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No. PA-508 November 10, 1937. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agents BAHREIN . Dear Sir: In reply to your letter No.2287 of November 6 , /*' , , 1937, we enclose cheque for Rs. 17/8/- on behalf of Major Ferguson - Thomson. Please sign the attached receipt and return it to this office. Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel. By G-. W. R. SMITH Chief Local Representative L A- l W A I w/imTH3 3AHR3IIT P3TR0L3m COMPANY, LTD. Bahrein, 21st November 1937. on account of Rigging Material being returned to U.5.A. and shall be glad to have same attested by yourself and returned to this office when done with. Thanking you, *\J | A ' Yours faithfully, (G.W.R.Smith) Chief Local Representative. Bapco. ncl two pagesThe Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, N0:PA~549. December 14, 1937. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent Bahrein. TBB-1209 Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering 13 empty Acetylene Cylinders which are being returned to New York for refilling. These cylinders are being shipped to Bombay on the 14th i.e. today per S.S. 'BAKORA' thence by Dollar Line to New York. Please return the certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to my account. Yours truly, G. W. R. SkxETH Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. — 'JTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, January 4, 1938. In connection with the shipment of Bahrein Crude Oil made yesterday in the British S/S 'TAHCHEE' for Bordeaux, France, I enclose original and four copies of the Certificate of Authenticity. Will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. A. Fellows, retaining, as usual, one copy for your files ? Yours faithfully, G. V/. R. S1. JTH, Chief Local Representative, TffiS BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LI MI TED. Enel: \ Hy'V’ 4,0The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ^ NO :PA-7. Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, January 5th, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political \gent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We are handing you herewith application for passport by Mr. C. 7. Deacon. v:e shall be glad if you will kindly affix your rubber stamp against your signature to the ’’Oath of Allegiance' sworn before you yesterday and return the application to us. Yours very truly,No. The Political Agency, Bahrain, 6th January 1938• To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleurr! Company Limited B A H R A I N. Dear Sir ill you please recover and forward to me the sum of Rs. 9/= being the fee for witnessing signatures on their U.S.A. passports at the rate of Rs. 3/- each from the follow ing:- T/r. gnglehart Mr# I'itchell Mr. Miller. 2. On frequent occasions recently the emnloyees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company have appeared before me to have their signatures attested and have then stated that they have not brought the fee with them. In future, therefore, persons desiring attestation of their signatures will be re quired to pay their fees in advance to the Head Clerk of my Office before appearing before me. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, BahrainUr. Dhaman&amp;ual Is3ardas f Bahrain. Bear 3ir f I write to thank you very much for the Christmas cake which you sunt me and also for your card of Good wishes for the ^ew Year* which I most heartily recipro cate* Yours faithfully, / yOffice to note this carefully and no person will be sent up to me until he has paid his fees. Tf he states he has forgotten the fee he should be sent away to get it. Fees, excepting purely notarial fees for v/hich notarial stamps are required, will con tinue to be credited to the Agency Funds. 6th January 1938The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, t' •?r- Ho. Pit- 14. January 9, 1938. his Britannic kajesty’s Political .Agent, BAHREIN . P \\ Bear Bin ;je are in receipt of your letter No. 27 of January 6 , 1938 and enclose herewith cheque for Rs.12/-, being the fee for witnessing signatures on U.S.A. passports, of the following at the rate of Rs. 3/- each:- l.ir. Engelhart Lr. Lite hell kr. liller Mr. Bell, A.D. te Will you please sign and return to us the attached receipt, at your convenience. k Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETR0LEU1.1 COMP AMY LIMI'IED. ylOiJUu, EET/kBB ♦ By Gr. W. R. BIBETH Chief ix)cal Representative EnelThe Bahrein petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, January 15, 1938 PA-23 His Britannic Majesty’s Political iigent, Bahrein. Bear Sir, I am enclosing herewith two documents signed by Mr. C. W. Deacon, Resident Manager of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. Would you please authenticate the signature on the two documents, returning them to me when you have done so ? Sincerely yours G. W. R. SMITH Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED W /cz. o ,A o A' \AJ ^ /'Ll y /iuNo.tfS ■ Political Agency, Bahrain,the 15th January 1938. To The Chi&lt; f Local Representative! Rahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, Reference your letter No. PA-23 dated 15th January 1938. I return the two documents , one copy of each of which has been authenticated. Plea se forvard a sum of Rs 2/8/— in r espect of the power of attorney. Yours faithfully, I Political Agent, Bahrain.The Bahrein Petroleum company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-29. January 18, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. P3B-169-A Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering 31 empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders which are being returned to San Francisco. These cylinders are being shipped today per M.V. 'Hoegh Silverlight” of the Silver-Java Pacific Line. Please return the certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to my account. Yours truly, G-. W. R. SITTH Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-48. January 31, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, TBB-1422 I enclose herewith Certificate covering 13 empty Acetylene Cylinders which are being returned to New York for refilling. These cylinders are being shipped to Bombay today per S.S. 'BARODA', thence by Dollar Line to New York. Please return the certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to my account. Yours truly, G. W. R. SMITH Chief Local Representative. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No .PA-57 February 6 , 1938 by The Resident Manager of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited with the request that you countersign in the space provided and return to us. Yours very truly, BLACK Chief Locatz Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDI The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited NO: PA -68 Aar—, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, Februairy 14, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, Return of empty Carbon Dioxide Cylinders for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering 12 empty Carbon Dioxide Cylinders which are being returned to New York for return to suppliers. These cylinders are being shipped to Bombay on or about 20th instant per S.^S.^BARALA” thence Dollar Line to New York. Please return the certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. Sir Return of empty Sulphur Dioxide Cylinders : For Credit I enclose herewith Certificate covering 30 empty Sulphur Dioxide Cylinders which are being returned to New York for return to suppliers. These cylinders are being shipped to Bombay on or about 21st instant per S.S. 'BARALA' thence by quickest for transhipment at London to New York. at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Please return the Certificate duly attested Yours truly THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDCALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY Bahrein, Persian Gulf February 21, 1938• Dear Sir: This letter will confirm my this morning’s request for an appointment with you for Mr. F. W. Ohliger on Wednes day, February 23, 1938, and which you granted for 12 o’clock noon. Am enclosing for your perusal the Tarious documents covering the purpose for which Mr. Ohliger desires to see you, as well as the letter to me which explains in detail what he requires. Shall appreciate very much your returning the letter to me as soon as it has served its purpose. Thanking you, I am/r/ The Bahrein Petroleum company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-89. March J, 1938, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. Dear Sir, Return of 44 empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders on PBB-140 &amp; 169. I enclose herewith Certificate covering 44 empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders which are being returned to San Francisco for return to suppliers. These cylinders have been shipped to San Francisco on the 26th ultimo per Silver Java Pacific Line boat 'M. 7. BOEGH TRANSPORTER”. Please return the certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, J. Chief Loc SLACK. Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.i The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA- 1 Q 4 , March 14, 1938. His Briteimie Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, Return of 114 empty Acetylene Cylinders for Credit. I enclose herevdth Certificate covering 114 empty Acetylene Cylinders which are being returned to New York for credit. These cylinders are being shipped to Bombay on or about 20th instant per S.S. ft BAM0RA n , thence Dollar Line to New York. Please return the certificate duly attested, at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, Chief Local representative TBL BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.r THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, N0:PA-110. March 19, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. Sir, Return of Empty Ethyl Fluid Drums. I enclose herewith Certificate covering seventeen 55-gallon empty Ethyl Fluid Drums which are being returned to suppliers. These drums are being shipped to Bombay on or about 20th instant per S.S. 'BAMORA' thence Via Dollar Line to Philadelphia. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, vl(3 J. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel: 1 MI.The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited N0:PA-121. Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, ay-a March 26, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent. Bahrein. TBB-1628 Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering 11 empty Acetylene Cylinders which are being returned to New York for refilling. These cylinders ere being shipped to Bombay on or about 27th instant per S.S. 'BARALA ,, thence by Dollar Line to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, End: 1. MI. J. SC BLACK Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited / L , v Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. N0:PA-129. March 30, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, Return of Empty Sulphur Dioxide Cylinders - For Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate coyering 10 empty Sulphur Dioxide Cylinders which are being returned to New York for credit. These cylinders are being shipped to Bombay on or about April 3rd., per S.S. ,, BANDRA ,, , thence by Dollar Line to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account • Yours very truly, Enel: 1 MI. J.-Sy BLACK Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, NO :PA-131, March 30, 1938. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrein. FBB-297-A Return of one defective G.E. Refrigerator for repair or replacement by Manufacturers. I enclose herewith Certificate covering one box containing a defective G.E. Refrigerator which is being returned to manufacturers for repair or replacement. This is being shipped to Bombay on or about April 3rd. per S.S. 'BANDRA* thence Via Dollar Line to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly. End ; 1 J. SilBLACK Chief Local^Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. 3. V MI£, h THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED / Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-152. April 7, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. BR - 11504 Return of 6 complete Westinghouse Turbine Rotors. I enclose herewith Certificate covering two boxes containing 6 Westinghouse Turbine Rotors which are being returned to New York for Credit. These Turbine Rotors are being shipped to Bombay on or about April 9th, per S.S. 'BARODA' thence by Dollar Line to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. A Attachment (1) RNKiMI Yours truly. J • BLACK Chief LocaX/Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. c.c. Storehouse.The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Attachment (1) Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, N0:PA-187. April 30, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Return of 6 incorrect rotation Sir, Westinghouse Style 1016152 Fans received on BR-10507 &amp; FBB-420. I enclose herewith Certificate covering six Westinghouse Style 1016152 Clockwise Rotation Fans which are being returned for Credit to New York. These Fans are being shipped to New York on or about May 1st. per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. 'BANDRA' with transhipment at Bombay. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account• Yours truly, MI. BLACK. Chief LocsO? Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.£ The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited \ i \ Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO :PA-217. May 11, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, Return of 26 empty Acetylene Cylinders - for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering 26 empty Acetylene Cylinders which are being returned to New York for Credit. These cylinders are being shipped to Bombay on or about 15th instant per S.S. ’’BAROBA”, thence Dollar Line to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly. J. /a^&lt;BLACK Enel : 1. Chief LocaiTtfepresentative. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. in « '*lr.Attachment (1) mm The Bahrein Petroleum company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, N0:PA-233. May 26, 1938, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. Sir, Return of 83 empty Flamo Sc Calol Industrial Gas Cylinders for Credit I enclose herewith Certificate covering 44 empty Flamo and 39 empty Calol Industrial Gas Cylinders. These have been shipped to San Francisco for Credit per Silver Java Pacific Line boat M.V. 'DJAMBI' which sailed on or about May 21st, 1938. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account• Yours truly, J. S. BLACK, f 1 Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. V MI.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Attachment (2) Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, N0:PA-247 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. Sir June 1, 1 On March 19th, our letter No.PA-110, we requested &amp; subsequently received attestation of a certificate covering 17 empty Ethyl Fluid Drums for return to TJ.S.A. as per form attached. Consignees have now requested 2 more copies of this and we should be much obliged if you would complete &amp; return the attached at your convenience. Yours truly. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. J. S. BLACK Q MITHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Attachment (2) Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-264. His Britannic Majesty’s Bahrein. Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering 14 empty Acetylene Gas Cylinders which are being returned to New York for refilling &amp; return. These empties have been shipped to Bombay on June 5th, per S.S. ”VITA tT thence by Dollar Line to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, THE Chief Locai BAHREIN FETRO' SLACK, [epresentative TJM COMPANY LIMITED. MI.-—1-7/) ' THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-273. June 15, 1938 His Britannic Majesty’s political Agent Bahrein. Sir Return of empty Ethyl Fluid Drums. I enclose herewith Certificate in quadruplicate covering nineteen 55 Glln. empty Ethyl Fluid Drums which are being returned to supplier. These have been shipped to Bombay on 12th instant per S.S.'BARALA' thence Via Dollar Line to New York. attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Please return the Certificate duly Yours truly, THE BAH _ . . ITED MI. Attachment (4)mmm ^7 The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-294. June 26, 1938. His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, Return of empty Anhydrous Ammonia cylinders for credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering 12 empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders which are being returned to San Francisco for return to suppliers. These cylinders will be shipped to sen Francisco on or about June 28th per Silver Java pacific Line boat 'M.V. 'TOSARI'”. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly,The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, I enclose herewith certificate covering 10 Empty Acetylene Gas Cylinders which are being returned to New York for refilling &amp; return. These empties are to be shipped to Bombay on or about July 16th per S.S. 'BARALA' thence by Dollar Line to New York. Please return the certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our eccount. Yours truly, BLACK. Chief LcfB&amp;L Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI. Attachment (1) J ' L. A ? \ x, r- 1 \973, ( ) y Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2 nd July 1938 To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire• llemorandus: &gt; I enclose a declaration dated the 2nd June 1938 made by Mr, Mohammad Sharif son of Allah Din of Sohal, District Gurdnopore, changing his name to Mohamad Sharif Malik and request that it be published in the Gazette of India, The charge for publication will be defrayed by Mr, Mohamad Sharif on your informing me how much it is. c Mi- tor Polit -•r 1 Agent, Bahrain.From The Hoi^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire To The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. Memorandum Bo. i *-67/1. Dated the ^ July, 1938. I enclose a declaration dated the 2nd June, 1938, made by Mr. Mohammad Sharif, son of Allah Din of Sohal, District Gurdaspore, by which he declares a change in his name to Mohamad Sharif Malik. It is requested that the change may be published in the Gazette of India as desired by the applicant. The charge for publication will be recovered from Mr.Hohanad Sharif Malik on my being informed of the cost. for the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copy forwarded to the Political reference to his memorandum No. t, Ba hra i n dated the , with 2nd July , 1938.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, No .FA - 301 July 3, 1938 v Hio Briteunic Majestv»s Political » Bahrein. Dear Sin, jfe attach our cheque No.1656 velua Rs.2. 8. 0 in payment of Attestation Fee, reference your account of 30th Jine. Please return our official receint, duly signed, at your very earliest convenience. Yours verv truly THE BjAttachment (1) THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED N0;PA-523. July His Britannic Majesty's political Agent, Bahrein. Awali , Bahrein Sir, Return for credit of 1 - 3-5/8' McCullough Gun Perforator. I enclose herewith Certificate covering one 3-5/8' McCullough Gun perforator ( Oil Well Drilling Tool ) which is being returned to New York for credit. This has been shipped to Bombay on July 16th per S.S. 'BARALA', thence Via Dollar Line to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly. Chief Lcrda; THE BAHREIN PETRO 'BLACK 'Representative. !UM COMPANY LIMITED. MI.Attachment (1) I wmmm @)//s THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO :PA-335. July 27, 1938. ^ I enclose herewith Certificate covering 20 empty Freon (Dichlorodifluoromethane) cylinders which are being returned to New York for refilling &amp; return. These empties have been shipped to Bombay on July 25th per S.S. 'B.AM0RA' thence by Dollar Line to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. T MI. Yours truly, J*. aT BLACK Chief Loc^A/Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-344 August 1, 1938 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent. Bahrein. dated July 27th covering return to U.S.A. of 20 empty Freon (Dichlorodifluoromethane) cylinders, which however we are returning herewith in the belief that it should carry your official stamp. Will you please return at your convenience. Attachment (1) ^ Yours truly T Chief Lo THE BAHREIN ! ^IMITED MII, X i 1 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali t Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, /$/ NO:PA-376. August 22, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, Return of empty Anhydrous Ammonia cylinders for credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering 40 empty Anhydrous Ammonia cylinders which are being returned to San Francisco for return to suppliers. These cylinders are being shipped to San Francisco on or about August 24th per silver Java pacific Line boat M.V. 'HOEGH TRANSPORTER”. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, Hr ^ Vi ,1^ TT^rmcT Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED ! M r. MI. i rThe Bahrein Petroleum Company limited AWALI, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO.PA-386. AUCrUST 29, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Return of 83 Empty Flamo Sir, and Calol Industrial Gas Cylinders for Credit . On May 26th we applied to you for Certificate as per copy attached, which was duly attested by you and returned to us. We have now received advice that this document has been mislaid in our San Francisco Office and we therefore have to request your attestation of the duplicate herewith which is required for Customs purposes. Please debit charges in this connection to our account. Yours truly, Chief THE BAHREIN Ends. 2. RNKiSKSMNO.PA-233. May 26, 1938. His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrein. Return of 83 Eapty Flamo &amp; Calol Sir, Industrial flas Cylinders for Credit . I enclose herewith Certificate covering 44 empty Flamo and 39 empty Calol Industrial Oas Cylinders. These have been shipped to San Francisco for Credit per Silver Java Pacific Line boat M^.^DJAMBI' which sailed on or about May 21st, 1938. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, Attachment (1) SD. C. W. DEACON f. J. S. BLACK Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED SKSMseei t es \bu ses-A^.oH ,^no^A a»^d’BetBM DinneditcS sj^H .nleTuisa IoIbO A ocfll^ aoi/j-aH « ^lfcenO lol aieJjnilxO sbP iBli.teutnl t^iS Y^cfin© ££ sni'ievoo ri^lweieii ©boIoxi© I ee©rfT •aieJbnilxO bbO Ibit; dax/JbxiI IoIbO Ydqraa QC bna omarf avs^ levIiS *i©q difceiO lot ooeionai'S ob 8 od £»9qqi:ri8 need evarf dx/ods 10 no Jbellsa xlodxiw ”ISMAliC M «V*M dsod ©niJ oIIIob 4 ! .aeei t dais ybm •n/ox ds £&gt;ed 89 ddp ed bo llidieO edd niird©*! ©a©©! 0 ' ♦ dmxoooB ufo od xioidoennoo ni ee^iBrio ^rrldldefi ©sonexinevnoo tX-Iaad aii/oY maAZG ,W .0 ,G 8 X 0 AI 8 *a .X . 1 ' ,©vldBdn©B 9 iq©H IbooJ lelxlO .G3TIMIJ YmqMOO MUSJ0OT38 MIPHHA 8 SHT (I) dnecixiosddATHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED AWALI, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, N0&gt;PA«388. AUGUST 27, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. BR-11504 Sir, Return to U. S, A, of Six Complete Westinghouse Turbine Rotors. On the 10th of April you issued to us Certificate for the return of above to U. S. A. in accordance with our application contained in our letter No.PA-152 of April 7th. It appears that the consignees have mislaid this document and in consequence a Bond has been deposited with the United States Customs for entry. Will you please be good enough to attest the copy of the same document that we attach hereto debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly,Sir, I have the honour to request that the attached original copy of the agreement between the Royal Air Force, Habbaniyah and Gray Mackanzie Ltd., Bahrain may be stamped and registered in accordance with the Indian stamp act as applicable to Bahrain. I have the honour to be Sir, Your Obedient Servant Squadron Leader. Air -Liaison Officer. ■^ydjL-r TO H.B.M f s Political Agefat Bahrain. Enel.-: Original of agreement.Political Agency, No. 134^ -5/3. Bahrain, the 4th September 1938. To, The hir Liaison Officer, Bahrain. Memorandurn. With reference to your letter No.ALO/Equip/82/3 dated 30th August 1338, I return herewith the agreement between the Boyal Air Force, Habbaniyah, and Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited, duly registered. 2. Sill you please remit Rs.b/8/- on account of cost of court fee stamps and registration fees. ui for Offg*Political Agent,-Bahrain.(7n) From Air Liaisob Officer, Bahrain, To n.B.M’s Political Agent, jmhrain. uate 5th. September 1958. Ref. ALO/Equip/82/5. SUBJECT. REGISTRATION OF AGREEMENT. The receipt of your 1549-5/3 dated 4th. September 1938 and enclosed agreement is herewith acknowledged. 2. I enclose nupees five annas eight (Rs 5/8) in pay ment of registration fees etc. and it is requested that you will sign and return the enclosed receipt. .unci. Rs 5/8 Receipt. Squadron Leader, Air Liaison Officer.the Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali , Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. NO :PA-398. September 5, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. TBB-2249 Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering 13 empty Acetylene Gas Cylinders which are being returned to New York for refilling &amp; return. These empties have been shipped to Bombay on September 4th, 1938, per S.S. 'BARALA', thence by Dollar Line or any other direct sailing to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, MI. Attachment (1)THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-404. September 10, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent. Bahrein. FBB-569 ^ r * 1 - Defective Refrigerator I enclose herewith Certificate covering one box containing a defective G.E. Refrigerator which is being returned to Manufacturers for repair or replacement. This has been shipped to Bombay on 5th instant per S.S.'BARALA M thence Via Dollar Line or any other direct Sailing to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly,* ■ I rThe Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident to the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. — Dated. \efereDce to previous correspondence Bahrain Memorandum Uo.^973, dated the 2nd July, 1938. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Copy of Memorandum No.D*2892- N/38, dated the 6 th Septem ber, 1938, from the Govern ment of India in the Extern Subject. Declaration by Mr.Mohammad Sharif regarding a change in his name . nal Affairs Department.From — The Under Secretary to the Government of India in the nbcternai Affairs Department. To — The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Meraorandan No. D. 2392-N/38. Dated Simla, the ifc September 1938. Subject:- Declaration by Mr. Mohammad Sharif regarding a change in his name. Reference your memorandum No. 1348-67/1, dated the 19th 0 c* July 1938. ( . 2. As it is not the practice of the Government of Jndia to publish such notices in the Gazette of India, it is requested that Mr. Mohammad Sharif may be advised to give publicity to his declaration through the public press. 3d/- I.3. Gondalves, for Under Secretary to the Government of Indiam NO:PA-437 September £5, 1938. His Britannic Majesty^ political Agent. Bahrein. Agent. 27/ FBB-569 Sir, 1 - Defective G.E. Refrigerator I enclose herewith Certificate covering one box containing a defective G.E. Refrigerator which is being returned to Manufacturers for repair or replacement. This is being shipped to Bombay per S.S.'BANKURA' leaving on or about September 25th, thence Via Dollar Line or any other Direct sailing to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly MI. Attachment (1)1 i the Bahrein Petroleum company Limited nrf. 13 ■v’ Ht&amp;gLt 'f 3£hpv '■ Awal i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-480. October 11, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent. Bahrein. Return of 32 empty Anhydrous Sir, Ammonia Cylinders for credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering 32 empty Anhydrous .Ammonia Cylinders which are being returned to San Francisco for return to Suppliers. These cylinders are being shipped to san Francisco with Transhipment at Singapore per silver java pacific Line M.V. 'SOEMBA' leaving Bahrein October 10th, 1938. Please return the certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. MIK The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awall, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-481. jlA ' V ^||o- October 11, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent v Bahrein. Sir, FBB-972-D Return of 1 - 5-9/16 ff Bowen L.H. Special Rotary Fishing Jar. I enclose herewith Certificate covering one box containing : - 1 - 5-9/16” Bowen L.H. Special Rotary Fishing Jar. which is being returned to U.S.A. This is being shipped to San Francisco with Transhipment at Singapore per M.V. 'SOEMBA' leaving Bahrein October 10th, 1938. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, Arv' Enel. 1. Chief THE BAHREIN jACK Representative ifOLETJM COMPANY LIMITED. MI.Enel. 1. / ) THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Jy ■ Awali , Bahrein Isi^nd, Persian ^ October EO, 1938. NO : FA-49 7 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. FBB-21 Sir, Return of one 4-7/16” McCullough Gun Perforator (Drilling Tool) I enclose herewith Certificate covering one box containing 1 - 4-7/16” McCullough Gun perforator (Drilling Tool) which is being returned to Los Angeles for return to Manufacturers. This is being shipped to Los Angeles per Silver-Java pacific Line M.Y. ”HOEGH SILVER-STAR” on or about 18th instant. at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Please return the Certificate duly attested Yours truly THE BAH I TED MIEnel. 1. SSPPnr (pt?) the wvn. BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 2 OCT. 1938 --&lt;5 Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-495, October 20, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s political Agent. Bahrein. Af/o Return of 11 empty Freon Sir, Cylinders for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering 11 empty Freon (Dichlorodifluoromethane) Cylinders which are being returned to New York for Credit. These empties have been shipped to Bombay on 17th instant per S.S.'BARPETA' thence by Dollar Line or any other Direct Sailing to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, MI. Chief THE BAHREIN PE Representative ^LEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Enel. 1. the Bahrein petroleum Company Limite Awali , Bahrein Island, Persi NO : PA-49 4 October 20, 1938 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent. Bahrein. TBB - 2409 Sir I enclose herewith Certificate covering 13 empty Acetylene Gas Cylinders which are being returned to New York for refilling and return. These empties have been shipped to Bombay on October 17th, 1938, per S.S.'BARPETA' thence by Dollar Line or any other direct sailing to New York. at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Please return the Certificate duly attested Yours truly Ch THE BAHRE MI.Enel, 1. N (£77) ff Q the Bahrein petroleum Company Limited , xii* ^ .-a n | ^ r 193» Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-496. October £0, 1938• His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Return of 16 empty Anhydrous Sir, Ammonia Cylinders for credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering 16 empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders which are being returned to San Francisco for return to Supplier. These empties are being shipped per Silver-Java Pacific Line M.W’HOEGH SILVER STAR” leaving Bahrein on or about 18th instant. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly,Enel 4. — ii \ the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited r 2.oo jr* Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO :PA~3. ^ October ^5,^1938 ‘It ^ * Hi His Britannic Majesty r,r F‘ H ?oiftical Agent. ‘ Bahrein. Return of 24 empty Sir, Ethyl Fluid Drums. I enclose herewith Certificate in quadruplicate covering twenty-four (24) 55 Gal. empty Ethyl Fluid Drums which are being returned to supplier. These have been shipped to Bombay on 24th instant per S.S. 'BANDRA', thence via London to New York. Please return the Certificate in quadruplicate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly,waisam 1 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awal i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-24. November 7, 1938. / 2-OZ. t His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. Sir, Return of 10 empty preon cyls. I enclose herewith Certificate covering (10) Ten empty 'Freon” (Dichlorodifluoromethane) Cylinders which are being returned to New York for return to Suppliers. These have been shipped to Bombay on the 6th instant per S.S. 'BAMORA”, thence Via London to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, Chief L THE BAHREIN PETR Representative ,EUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI. Enel. 1.lA ] * - Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-25. November 7, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s political Agent Bahrein. Return of 11 Anhydrous Ammonia cylinders for credit S ir, / V The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited I enclose herewith certificate covering (11) eleven empty Anhydrous Ammonia cylinders which are being returned to San Francisco for return to suppliers. These empties have been shipped per silver-Java pacific Line M.V. 'HOEGH SILVERSTAR' on the 3rd. instant. Please return the certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. MI. Enel. 1. Yours truly, J Chief Lo THE BAHREIN PET JJLACK Repr es ent ative &gt;LEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Enel. 1. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited LA C ,, i \ ; i NO: PA-45. Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, November 22, 1938, 300 - % 4J His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Return of one empty defective Sir, Carbon Dioxide Cylinder for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering one empty carbon Dioxide Cylinder which is being forwarded to New York for return to suppliers. This has been shipped to Bombay on November 21st. per S♦S.'BARPETA' thence Via London to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. MI. Yours truly, i—- Chief THE BAHREIN PETR BLACK Representative jEUM COMPANY LIMITED.GO-10-1 PB 3-37 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein island, Persian gulf., November 22nd. 193 38. FOR CUSTOMER’S USE —S— ar- charge / The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. \ PRICE TERMS f TO \ 130 East 43rd Street , i \ New York City. U.S.A. / F. O. B. CHS. TO ' APPROVAL TRANSP’N. RECEIVAL CALCULATIONS AUDITED TERMS sh.ppedW P er S . S . Tt BARPETA n w/Transhipment at Bombay Ifrom Bahrein. DATE Nov.21st VoB and London. 4 1938. VIA CAR NO. FRT. PPD. OR COLL. CUSTOMER’S ORDER NO. REQ’N. NO. INV. NO. I, M.H. Lipp, Manager, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, do solemnly and truly declare that the Cylinder herein specified is, to the best of my knowledge &amp; belief, truly and bonafide of the manufacture of the United states; that it was exported from United States per 'PENNLAND/ FRAUENFELS/ROTINFELS' on or about August 7th, 1937, and that it is returned without having been advanced in value or improved in condition by any process of manufacture or other means * 1 - Empty Carbon Dioxide Cylinder (Defective) $15.00 Signature ORIGINAL SIGNED BY M. H. LIPP Declared to before me this _ . day of „ . 1938. — Wovombeg HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT. BAHREIN. MI.Enel. 1. V x THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali t Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-54. December 3, 1938. His Britannic Majesty 1 s political Agent. Bahrein. Return of 11 empty Sir, Acetylene Cylinders. I enclose herewith Certificate covering (11) eleven empty Acetylene Cylinders which are being returned to New York for return to suppliers. These have been shipped to Bombay on November 29th per S.S. 'BANDRA' thence Via M.V. 'VITO' to New York. Please return the certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly,' ’ *, ■ &gt; 2-0-7} the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited \ / NO: PA-59. Awali , Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, December 7, 1938. \ His Britannic Mejesty’s political Agent. Bahrein. Dear Sir, Return of 32 empt}' calol Industrial cutting Gas and 4 Flamo Gas cylinders for Credit. I enclose herewith certificate covering (32) thirty-two empty Calol Industrial cutting Gas and (4) four empty Flamo Gas Cylinders which are being returned to San Francisco for return to suppliers. These empties have been shipped per silver-java pacific Line M.V.'DJAMBI” on the 4th instant. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, MI. Enel. 1. Chief THE BAHREIN J/ Representative ;eum company limited.Enel. 1. the Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-58. December 7, 1958. His Britannic Majesty*s political Agent. Bahrein. Return of 28 empty juihy4^e«s Sir, Amnonia cylinders for Credit. . r* I enclose herewith Certificate covering (28) twenty-eight empty Anhydrous Aumionia cylinders which are being returned to San Francisco for return to suppliers. These empties have been shipped per silver-java pacific Line Boat M.V.'DJAMBI' on the 4th instant. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, MI. Chief Lo THE BAHREIN P fS^BLACK Representative )LEUM COMPANY LIMITEDGO-lO-t PB 3-37 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED STOREHOUSE, BAHREIN ISLAND, PERSIAN GULF.,. December 7th. 193 8 . CHARGE TO The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. Bush Street, San Francisco. California. m per Silver-java Line M.V.'DJAMBI” to San- Bahrein. date Dec .4th. F . O B . Francisco. ra.o Kin 1938 • FOR CUSTOMER’S USE PRICE /V TERMS FRT. PPD. APPROVAL TRANSP’N. RECEIVAL CALCULATIONS AUDITED CUSTOMER’S ORDER NO. REQ'N. NO. I, M.H. Lipp, Manager, The Bahrein Petroleum company Limited, do solemnly and truly declare that the Cylinders herein specified are, to the best of my knowledge &amp; belief, truly and bonafide of the manufacture of the United states;^ that they were exported from United States per 'PRES.HARRISON” July 2nd, 1937, 'HOEGH TRANSPORTER' December 18th, 1937, 'HOEGH SILVERSTAR' February 17th, 1938, &amp; 'DJAMBI' March 17th, 1938, and that they are returned without having been advanced in value or improved in condition by any process of manufacture or other means. 28 - Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders a *15 .00 each = $420.00 Signature Declared to before me this _day of December 1938. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S POLITICAL AGENT. BAHREIN. MI.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited A w a 1 i. Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, November 26th t 1938 No. PA-47 Dear Sir His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrain. I am attaching the following Powers of Attorney for registra tion by your office: 1. Two copies of one Power issued by California Texas Oil Company, Limited, in favor of Messrs. C. E. Davis, M. H. Lipp, 7/ard P. Anderson, and J. T. Deane, authorizing each of them to handle Customs transactions. One copy 2. 'Bse each of 5 Powers of Attorney issued by The Bahrein Petroleum Company, Limited, in favor of: (a) F. A. Davies, (b) C. E. Davis, (c) M. H. Lipp, (d) H. N. Phillips, (e) G. A. Kellenberg. You will please note that all 5 of these Powers include authority to issue substitute.Powers. We also wish to notify you at this time that the following Powers of Attorney have been revoked: 1. E. A. Skinner - covered by resolution adopted by the Board of Directors on September 14, 1931. 2. C. W. Deacon - Delegation to him of E. A. Skinner’s Powers covered by substitute Power of Attorney issued by E. A. Skinner dated June 9, 1937. 3. F. A. Davies - covered by resolution adopted by the Board of Directors on March 5, 1935. Yours very truly 4 DKW:VS Enel Chief Lo THE BAHREINThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, November 26, 1938* No. PA-48. Dear Sir, Please refer to my letter No. 47. I am enclosing herewith two Powers given by Mr. M. H. Lipp to Mr. Lloyd Cannon Kemp of Caltex (India), Ltd., Bombay. Will you kindly authenticate these documents and return them to me as soon as possible.. Yours very truly, Enel: fM/// j. Chief THE BAHREIN iepresentative, £QLEUM COMPANY, LTD., DM: VS2JZ- Political Agency, Bahrain, the 13th Uecember 1938. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Reference your letters Nos. Pa-47 and PA-48 dated the 26th November 1938. 2# Please forward to this Agency the sum of Rs* 98/8 (ninety eight and annas eight only) representing the charges for registration and copying of the documents sent with the above-quoted letters.-4NMI The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited No.PA-65* Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, # ' December 14, 192)8 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein* Dear Sir, As requested in your letter #1946 of 13th December 1938 we are forwarding herewith cheque to value of Ks.98-8-0 being fees for registration and copying of Powers of Attorney forwarded to you with our letter&amp;#PA-47 and #PA-48*-5/3. (Z^&gt; 6 Folitical agency, Bahrain, the 20th December 1938. To The Chief Local Kerresentative, The Bahrain Petroleum Conmany Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, BeTerence your letters Nos. PA-47 and PA-48 dated the 2bth November 1938. 2. The Powers of Attorney are sent herewith, duly registered in this Agency. Two powers given by Mr. M.H. Lipp to Mr. Lloyd Cannon / Caltex,are also returned duly attested. 3. Would you please forward to this Agency a further sum of iis* 7/8/- which was not included, by error, in our letter No. 1946 dated the 13th December 1938 in respect of the above documents. Yours faithfully, for Political Agen^, Bahrain.The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. No.PA-79 Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, December 21 , 1938 Dear Sir: We have to acknowledge receipt of your letter #1991-5/3 of 20 th December, 1938, and enclosed Powers of Attorney,, and as requested enclose herewith our cheque to value of Rs.7.8.0 to make up the registration fees for these documents. Yours very truly Chic THE BAHREB ffLL'Repre s ent at i ve : 6 leum company limitedMBM -5^13 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th January 1939. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Reference your letter No. PA-71 dated the 17th December 1938; Will you please send to this Agency a sum of Rs.11/8 representing the charges for registration and copying of the document sent with your above quoted letter, as scheduled below. Yours faithfully, ^ - for Political Agent, Bahrain. Court Fee Stamps Copying fee Rs. 7-8-0 (3 copies) ••• Rs. 4-0-0 (321 words) Total.. Rs.11-8-0 y-Enel. 1 the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited NO:PA-72- Awali , Bahrein Island, Per^^/Culf, December 18, 1938. His Britannic Majesty’s political Agent. i Bahrein. Return of 5 empty Sir, Acetylene cylinders for credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering (5) Five Empty Acetylene Cylinders which are being returned to New York for return to suppliers. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s s.S. ' BAMORA' on 12th instant to Bombay, thence Via .American President Line Boat 'PRESIDENT MONROE'. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, Chief THE BAHREIN JLACK fal Representative toLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI.Enel. 1. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED f' *76 ■ Awall , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, ✓N ■ ^ NO:PA-157. February 1st. 1939. His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent. Bahrein. Return of one empty Liquid Chlorine &amp; 19 empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders Sir, for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering One empty Liquid Chlorine and Nineteen (19) empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders which are being returned to San Francisco for return to Suppliers. These empties have been shipped per Silver-Java Pacific Line Boat M.V. t, HOEGH SILVERLIGET' on January 26th. 1939. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account.Enel. 1. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 3?r. Awal i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-138. February 1st. 1939. k His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Return of 45 Empty Defective Oxygen Cylinders : TBB-2712. Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering (45) Forty-five empty Defective Oxygen Cylinders which are being returned to San Francisco for return to Suppliers. These have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. ’’HOEGH SILVERLIGHT” which sailed from Bahrein on January 26th. 1939. at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Please return the Certificate duly attested Yours truly, MI.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-89. December His Britannic Majesty^ Political Bahrein. Sir, Return of 6 Defective Westinghouse Model WP-19 water coolers for credit I enclose herewith Certificate covering (6) Six Defective Water Coolers which are being returned to New York for return to suppliers. These have been shipped to Bombay on 18th instant per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S.'BARALA', thence Via American president Line Boat '’PRESIDENT ADAMS” to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, j MI.the Bahrein petroleum Company Limited r Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-139. February 1st. 1939. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. TBB - 2736 Sir, Return of 1 Defective Khockmeter MI. Enel. 1. I enclose herewith Certificate covering One Defective Knockmeter which is being returned to New York for repair. It has been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. ”VARELA” which left Bahrein on January 29th, 1939, thence Via American President Line Boat S.S. ’’PRES. HARRISON” sailing on February 11th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, Chief L THE BAHREIN BLACK Representative .OLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Enel. 1. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-111. January 14th, 1939. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Return of 10 empty Acetylene Cylinders - for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering (10) Ten empty Acetylene Cylinders which are being returned to New York for return to suppliers. These have been shipped to Bombay on 10th instant per S.S. 'BANKURA' thence Via Kerr Line S.S.'SKAGERAK' leaving Bombay on January 22nd for New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly,Form 103 C. 3.38. zzjr TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED Dlk . ORS: Lord Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) G. Legh-Jones R. Cayrol, D.S.O.. D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser. C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy J. A. Meny (French) „ _ . _ &gt; H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) PC L/G^A .2/1366 R. W. Sellers ' ' J. Skliros CONFIDENTIAL BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 11th February, 1939. H.B.M.’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, INCREASES OF CAPITAL We enclose herewith certified copies in duplicate of a Resolution authorising an increase of Capital of the following Companies : Petroleum Concessions Ltd. (from £100,000 to £150,000) Petroleum Development (Q^tar), (from £100,100 to £300,100) Ltd. We shall be grateful if these increases may be registered in due course in accordance with the usual Bahrain procedure. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED, U MANAGER.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali » Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-151. February 12, 1939. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. Return of 2 empty Amnonia cylinders for credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering 2 empty Amm onia Cylinders which are being returned to New York for return to suppliers. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. ’’BANDRA” on the 6th instant to Bombay, thence Via American President Line Boat ’’PRESIDENT HAYES” to New York. at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Please return the Certificate duly attested Yours truly Chief I THE BAHREIN PI MI. Enel. 1.308-5/13 Political Igency, Bahrain, the 20th February 1939. To The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain. v Pear Sir, Reference your letter ?t 0 . PCL'/CAA. 3/1366 dated the 11th February 1939. „ oo. - , 2. Please send to this Agency a sum of &amp;• -i8/-, representing the charges for registration of documents forwarded with your above quoted letter, which is made up as under Court Fee stamps Copying fees Total Rs • 10 — 0 li • 10 - 0 ns. 20 — 0 3. The documents are returned herewith. Yours faithfully, Enclosures : 4(ZZ2) 2 f BAHRAIN , PERSIAN GULF. DO/3881. 22nd February, 1939 My dear j In your letter 308-5/13 dated 20th. February, there is a discrepancy in the figures you ask for Rs.18/- whereas the detail totals Rs.20/- - which is correct? Yours sincerely. Capt. J.E.Howes, The Agency, Bahrain. TLt. w n. s {L,. -yyff- I***-*'-n.C.No. 339-5/3. The 25th February 1939. Your deni-offici 1 letter ?To. 3B81 dated the 22nd February 1939 about fees. I am very sorry about the discrepancy. If you will send us the Hs. 10/- stamp fees, the copying charges can go this time • »V• Packer, require, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain. k'-i■m i THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED AntQ.ll t Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, March 5, 1939• No.PA-175 His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, BAHRAIN. \ ' J Dear Sir, U R G T In connection with the shipment of B-849 Fuel Oil made on February 23 in the Dutch M.S. 'OYUIA' for Djibouti, French Somaliland, I enclose Original and two copies of the Certificate of Origin. Will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. J. T. Deane, retaining one copy for your files. Yours faithfully. ZXl Fo/~Z. S. BLACK,” ' ' Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY I/ED.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Enel. 1. swell, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-161 February 26, 1939. s' /Jt His B^itannic s l?a3es J ty , s Political Agent Bahrein. Sir, Return of 11 empty Acetylene Cylinders for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering 11 empty acetylene Cylinders which are being returned to New York for return to suppliers. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co^s S.S. 'BAMORA' on February 20th. to Bombay thence Via American President Line 'PRESIDENT POLK' to New York. at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Please return the Certificate duly attested Yours truly, MI.qpMOMT ~ MOll THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awall, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO.PA-168. February 26, 1939, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: RETURN OF 2 AMMONIA CYLINDERS FOR CREDIT. Further to my letter No.PA-151 of February 12th, I should be glad to receive the Certificate that was attached thereto duly receipted in order that it may be sent after the shipment which has gone forward. Yours truly. Chief THE BAHREIN Representative, jEUM company limited.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Enel. 1. Awal i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-186 —- — , 4 .. 7JS. March 8, 1939. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent Bahrein. Return of 10 empty Flamo and Cutting Gas Cylinders for Credit. Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering (10) ten empty Flamo &amp; Cutting Gas Cylinders which are returned to San Francisco for return to Suppliers. These empties have been shipped on February 26th per B.I.S.N. 'VASNA' to Bombay thence Via Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. Tt H0EGH MERCHANT' on or about March 11th to San Francisco. at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Please return the Certificate duly attested Yours truly Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED mEnel. 1. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-185 March 8, 1939. His Britannic Majesty f s Political Agent Bahrein. TBB-1584-E Sir. 7J 2 - Return of 138 - MacClatchie Water Valve Seats, n Incorrect Taper”. I enclose herewith Certificate covering one box containing 138 - MacClatchie Water Valve Seats which are being returned to Los Angeles for return to Manufacturers. This box shipped to Bombay on February 26th per S.S.”VASNA” will be transhipped thence to Los Angeles Via Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. tT HOEGH MERCHANT” on or about March 11th. 1939. at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Please return the Certificate duly attested Yours truly - j . s. BLAUh Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Enel. 1. Awal i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-184. March 8, 1939. His Britannic Majestyls Political Agent Bahrein, 7Sf- Return of 29 empty Anhydrous Sir, Ammonia Cylinders for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering Twenty-nine (29) empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders which are being returned to San Francisco for return to Suppliers. These empties have been shipped per S.S. 'VASNA' on February 26th to Bombay thence Via Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. 'HOEGH MERCHANT” on or about March 11th to San Francisco. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED MI.Enel. 1. The Bahrein petroleum company limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, Bahrein. NO:PA-SO9. March 2S, 1 Sir, Return of 7 empty Acetylene 2 s f&gt; Cylinders for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering seven empty Acetylene Cylinders which are being returned to New York for return to Suppliers. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co. T s S.S. 'BANDRA' on March 14th to Bombay thence Via American President Line 'PRESIDENT GARFIELD' on or about April 8th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience,debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, C THE BAHR [TED. MI1. Letter No.PA-159 dated the 6th April 1937 from the C.L.xi. Issued letter No.794 dated the 7th Apnl 1937 to the C.L.n. 2. Letter No.PA-166 dated the 11th April 1937 from the C.L.n. 3. Letter No.L/462 dated the 13th April 1937 f^om Gr^ay Mack. Go Letter dated the 13th Ap-il 1937 from Mr. A.P. Ande'-son. b. Letter No, PA.176 dated the 15th April 1937 f~om the G.L.Pu Issued letter No. 920 dated the 19th April 1937 to the C.L.L. 6. Letter No.PA-180 dated the 2(Dst April 1937 f^om the C.L.K. 7. Lette- No.PA-182 dated the 21st April 1937 from the C.L.n. 8. Letter dated the '23rd Ap^il 1937 from the C.L.xi. 9. Letter No.lb/3 dated the 26th Ap^il 1937 i^om the G.&amp; .&lt;• iitd. Bahrain. 6.Up.2. ^ Ne can do this - it is an useful t^ick- DutA.P.A T s had better sign as H.B.M T s Assistant Political Agent and it might be well to let fo~ example the Ambassador in Washington know through the P.L. and G. of I. of the post of A.P.A. G.L. 26.4.37. X ll u * a* fLyvih Please sreak. In future add the word T Assist ant 1 (Political Agent) as I am now competent to attest dociments. Phis will avoid trouble over titles etc. such as the case of Mr. Anae^son - about which please speak. B.i 1 . 26/4 3.No.3. Please check. Mtw-'- jk B.i 1 . 11 67 r. 13/4. 3.Nos.4. Captain Ste.,a~t was a Magist^te so coula administer the oath which was required in this case - but Ambassador did not presumably know this. We must have him informed about A.P.A. G.L. 18/4 c .No .9 . Cancel please and inform C &lt;P N. B.i’. 37/4r^-l JOo/VVjjJ '-liioOCl IV , iO .O / li Oiii» ^xLiC i X c*uk Consulate GOiicrali lia^jii-uaci. x 5 .pc . T.H. 21.10.37, There are no pps on ti'^e cnbjcct. ji, few day c a^o Hr. x or Jic r of tx.e Cuiil ornia to me for aetecting his signatures on a power of attorney^ to -:o oacK to al-iuxobar tire sanic day. I attested the docuiaciio in my capacity as a magistrate and put my seal on i t. ^^ccoraiij- to article 68 , haxirain Order-in -oouncxi (flag. ed) ; only ±‘. R. and P.xi. are autiioriseu to act as a Notary Public. But I.a. can also attest signatures as a hagiotrate, though not as a Notary Public. 4. As the documents of the British or American employees of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company are afiK usually attesteu oy - the -American Consul , Baghdad, is doubtful a tout I.a.’s signatures and seal. 5 . hay be informed that the I.a. is authorised to attest signatures on documents ana a speciman of l.-n’s seal and signatures bv. o&lt;nt to him please. Arauian Standard Oil Company Drought . r. I 1 ..-. Oblige r /f f-i . C q.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00032d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1174</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00032d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1174</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 5/3 II Registration of Documents'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-18T12:17:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (247 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after their relevant covering letter, and terminate in a set of notes (folios 239-247).</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 249; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel throughout except for the two leading flyleaves; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the registration of documents by the Political Agency, Bahrain, which formed part of the Agency's notarial duties.The papers consist of correspondence between those applying to register documents and the Political Agency, Bahrain. Much of the correspondence is with the Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO). The documents submitted for registration are principally certificates for oil company shipments, but also include title deeds, powers of attorney, passport applications, certificates of residency, and certification of change of name.There is also some correspondence about the need to be able to recognise the Political Agent's signature in the course of his notarial duties (e.g. folios 9-11).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Notarial instruments</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00032d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>