<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024052054.0x00002a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T23:46:57.524Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">government advertisement. Public, Department* rr«IE Heads of Offices at the Presidency, and Subordinales, are reminded, that the following X Statements are required to be delivered into the Office of the Auditor of Civil Accounts, on or before, the 31st of May next. UlFrom the Heads of every Office, or Department, a list of the Establishment and Allowances for the Office, as the same may stand on the 1st day of May 18151 specifying so far as it will ad- mil the names of all the Company's Servants, and of the European, and Native Ass.stants em- ployed therein; with the Allowances that maybe drawn for the Office, or for any contingency; Ling careful to include therein every erpence, thatufixei in Us nature, accompanied with cop.es of the authorities on which each charge Is founded. m V From the Head of every Office or Department, a Statement contrasting the aforesaid men- tioned Allowances, with what the same stood on the 1st May 1811/ , with a column explaining the Le of any incase or decre ^that may have tahen place, from the 30th April 181^.0 the 30th A 3l 181 ^om the Head of every Office, or Department, a detailed Statement of the Pensions payable from each Office or Department, as the same may stand on the 1st May 181 , accompanied with Copies of the anthorities granting them, as also a contrasted Statement of each Pension Establishment 95 ill From every Covenanted Servant on the Bombay Establishment, a'Statement of the monthly, annual, or other Civil or Military Allowances drawn by him from the Company, and also of all the emoluments he enjoys in consequence of any Office or employment held under tins Government on the 1st of May 181 .T, specifying the same, and the source from whenco he derives such emo- lument. J, K/iYE, BOMBAY CASTLE. Auditor Jc * mnt *- Q jetice of A udit, 2/2/jpril 18iv5</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100024052054.0x00002a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/17, pp 73a-73d</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024052054.0x00002a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/17, pp 73a-73d</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter from John Kaye, Auditor of Civil Accounts, Public Department, Bombay to Lieutenant William Bruce, Resident at Bushire</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1815/1815</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-17T01:35:08</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 folio</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter is a printed circular calling for statements of establishment as they stand on the 31 May 1815. The precise information required is listed and outlined.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024052054.0x00002a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>