<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000cf_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T05:13:19Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">v &gt; His Majesty r s Secretary of State for CommonwealtH Relations, Downing Street, LONDON.S#W*i. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Residency «fe Bahrain, €e»mrim!e-G©ner»l, BOBBERS. Dated 14th January, 1948. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject. Charge Certificates of Mr. C.J. Felly, O.B.E. and Major J.E.H. Hudson.Certified that I have handed over with effect from the ????..of ...A January, 1948, charge of the duties of the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, which I held in addition to my own duties as Political Agent, Bahrain. PoliticaKSgeat, Bahrain. (Believed Officer) Certified that I have taken over charge of the duties of the assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, with — effect from the 1^of the .5. January, x948. (J.B. Hudson)FIL £*sro OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. * ' v y ' o Telephone — TEMPLE BAR 8484. Address for Inland Telegrams — HICOMIND, ESTRAND. LONDON. Ca6/es—HICOMIND, LONDON. Please quote the undermentioned reference, and address any further communication to The High Commissioner for India, s&gt;^ &gt;9 Public Department, i NDIA House, Aldwych, London, W.C.2. 15th December 1947 and not to any individual by name ^ j ^ ^ Reference ^ ^ ^ Prom: Q The High Commissidher for India, Public Department. To: The Under Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, Commonwealth Relations Office, Whitehall, S.W.1. Sir, I am directed by the High Commissioner for India to refer to letter No. D• 3551-BPO/47 addressed ~by the Under Secretary to the Government of India^to the Under Secretary of State for India^_Ext ern al^epartment. India Office, on the 19th August ^947, oiTlTie subject of the - conferment of judicial powers on the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. The Government of India in an express letter have now intimated that since the Governor General of India in Council mentioned in Articles 14 and 35 of the Bahrein Order in Council, 1913&gt; is no longer the appropriate authority under the Indian Constitution which came into force since the 15th August 1947&gt; presumably the two notifications of the 19th August 1947, will have to be issued by His Majesty’s Government unless the Order in Council is amended. 2. The High Commissioner has been asked to bring this matter to the notice of His Majesty’s Government and would be glad if he may be informed of the action taken by them in the matter. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedienjL Sery&amp;J}t, Secretary Public Department■r? ■r —I—... ^ r~s ,f&lt; k f Ko. 2358-65/10 . 1L. m J*L;A '6 fc°i. 11 ^ &amp;aJ £1K ' . JW3 ttalfcoio^ PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, ' BAHRAIN. 6th November, 1©47. a From /////. &gt;/ tv; ? To The Hon T ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN. The Under Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, King Charles Street, Whitehall, LONDON. Sir With reference to your letter No. Ext. 1953/47 dated 6th October, 1947, I have the honour to confirm that during the period of his posting as Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, from the 8th to the 16th July 1947, Mr. G«N. Jackson did not sit either as a magistrate or a judge. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, Political Resident, P sian Gulf. mmrr/I 0 1 f /. DRAFT LETTER i^r ^ ic To: Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bahroin» Sxt.1953/47 6 OCT 1947 &amp; ' / i. / &amp;~U'^ Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations to refer to your tele gram Ko* 8?6 dated the 7th August, 1947 on the subject of the conferment of judie-iad.-^oworo on (yy cAx -» nX C. c 1 —t —G.W-JarPann, assistant Political Agent, Bahrein, and to enclose for your information a of letter No.D. 3531-3PG/47 dated the 19 th ^ugust, 1947 fran the Secretary to the Goverrment of India, Department of External iiffairs and Commonwealth Relations. I am to observe that Mr. Jackson held charge of the post of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein, from the 8 th to the 16th July, 1947 only, and that if, as appears likely, he performed no judicial functions during this iL^l; period ( the question of the proper conferment upon /him' !— A •&gt; \ - him of judicial powers need not be pursued. I am accordingly tcj/request confirmation that during the period of nis posting as Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein, Mr. Jackson did not sit either as a Magistrate or a Judge. I an to add that for the future the pov/er of conferment of judicial and magisterial authority in the case of subordinate British Courts in the Persian Culf will be exercised by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations until the 1st April, 1948 and thereafter by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs# atad —autnority- so cor^forrod will —oq publiaucd -in the Tinndon .-G-a7.ptte.u -■ C ■■ u.^- ^r, , T n. r ''3 ' (11178) Wt.21321/P.248 6,000 (2 sorts) 7/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 It is requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S.W.l. P. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.WA.OUTWARD TELEGRAM COPY Frosa C(HFIDEim £L_ g-jDa Secretary of State for India FoXitisal Heaident in ^itie Persian Gulf Despatched 10® 15 hours, 15th July 1947 IMPORTANT Addressed Political Resident, copy ^&gt;y raail to Gorernraent of India* My telegram Ko©91B1 to Government of India* H©M*Go are most anxious to secure services of officers and staffs at present in post* Agre€Cient has heea reached ttiat this can best be done by offering to keep on officers and staffs at approximately present rates of pay and conditions of service at any rate for time being* 2* Fello\?irg emergency terms have been worked out for following officers at posts named at a meeting he^e. (It Is proposed if you agree that on Kay*s return from leave you should take over as P.A. Kuwait and Tandy if he is willing should rel1eve Pettigrew)&lt; (1) Galloway * Political Agent Kuwait* Salary plus language alTcwcnce £90^ Personal a3.1armnce 52500® While acting as Political Resident above allowance to be increased by 5500* (2) p elly * Political Agent, Baarain. Salary £1320 plus lunguageSlowance £90® Personal allowance £1750* (3) Stewart ® As he h&amp;a been accepted for Foreign Service no contract offer is required but intention is ;o poet him a&amp; political Agent to Muscat with provisional foreign allowance of £1500® (4) J ackson ® Sani© aa for Stewart, but Intention is to post him as political Officer, Trucial Coast, with provisional forei.gn allowance of £1075 and language allowance of £90® (6) Tandy * Secretary, Bahrain® Salary £900 pluo language allowance £90* Personal allowance £1575* (5) Eudaon* Under-Secretary, Bahrain* Salary £575 plus £90 langrag© allowance* Personal allowance £760c (7) Pe ttigrew ® As this officer wishes to leave Gulf anyway pres^i- pay and allowances will be continued In accordance with Indian rules ilt&gt; as is hoped* be will continue to serve as Secretary Bahrain until Political Resident can release him or until 31st December next whichever is sooner* If he accepts please report his exact present pay and allowances (a) Ranee® Assistant Political Agent Bahrein. Salary £900. PerioSaT allowance £1425® 3® Above salaries and language allowances are sub ject to U*K. income tax. Personal and foreign allowances are not® Fumiehea quarters will be provided in addition where available or rented as a charge to H.M.G* where not* /4. Foreign4» Foeeign OffXcae would like to otfer 6 and 8 above 3 yoar contracts (or 18 months if preferred) at these places on terms given above* Please approach oilleers urgently and telegraph whether they would be willing to accept© If any of above are admitted to Foreign Service subsequently contract terns would automatically laps©* If Ranee obtains employmen* subsequently under Colonial office we would nc*t a How contract now offered to stand in his way © 3© Sir Rc Hay attended meeting at which above sehorae ws worked out© Both he and ourselves very much hope officers named will accept offers which are generous by Foreign. Service standards® If officers act In posts other than those designated personal allowances will be subject to variation cci wtiich views of Political Resident will be Bought* Copies of this telegram are being sent to those officers on leave in this country to whom we are making offers direct© Conditions regarding leave etc® are being worked out and a separate telegram will follow on this subject© G® Please see my immediately following telegram about subordinate staff® CopissLlat- Treasury® Foreign office (Mr© ^ ‘ CMr© — do (Mr® -•»&gt; do '*• ilir® do (kr© S»&amp; ajiepartmmt© Ifinanclal Department (Mr. R.S* &amp;ro^n) * A.a. , s Department (Mrr Conder). Oovemment of XTidia (It*Col© ^rlco&gt;on ; &lt;- Caocia) t Oardener;® pyiaan)* Henderson) © Fisher) •OUTWARD TELEGRAM ' , (*it .Kxter*nal Dentn - ‘ CONFIDSI^TIAL GODB YKLEG’ &lt; AT! f From Secretai*;/ of State for India. To (xovernneiifc of India, External Affairs Dept. Repeated to Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Deep. 22,50 h-^urs, 22nd October 19^6. 10846, From Hay for Crichton repeated to Gallov/ay* Galloway’s telegram 1162 October 18th and your tele&lt;2»am 8973 of same date. Postingc. 2, Unless another officer with Gulf ex &gt;erienc 9 can be made available for frucial Coast I still consider Ranee should go there. His fondly oould continue to occupy A.P. A, s s house at Bahrain and I could accoiiEnod- ate Olver at Jufair to begin with, I do not know Murphy but if Galloway is confident that he can^fill the Trucial Coast satisfactorily I should have no objection to him. Final decision might perhaps be deferred until my return uo Bahrain which I hope will be about November 3rd. 3, Pai?©graph 4 your telegram 8973. I am strongly in favour of posting A.P.A. to Muscat and extending sanction for post after March, 1947 especially as Sultan is likely to be in Dhofer at any rate until autumn of 1947. . // A I N W A R DA EiLEORAM 7163 Allo-tted^^E^ternal 4feartm^n1 i /? 27037 CONFIDEM 1 IAL CQDI ’i TE LKjRAIvI From Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* To Secretary of State for India* Repeated to Government of India, Dated Bahrain, 14,30 hours, 18th October 1946, Received 16,00 hours, 18th October 1946. 1162- Your telegram 18395 dated October 14th, which I presume was from Hay. Froit Galloway for Hay repeated to Crichton, 2, Ranee has been in Bahrain, only eight- months and has oust learnt the work. To move him now would not only unset that post but also means that life would lose family accommodation. He haa now ten years Civil Service and should be entitled to tenure of post of over eight months. Ranee himself does not wish to he transferred and has nowhere to send his family, neither could he take children to Trucial Coast, Under these circumstances I hope you will agree, to .Ranee's remaining assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, 3. As regards Trucial Coast. If an officer qi experience is required there I suggest Murphy be given another trial. He is about due to return from leave and from a letter from him a g a trier fie would welcome re-posting to the Gulf. He is bachelor/INWARD TELEGRAM l ^ .Si 27026 l lo 46 ^• ■ muj' Bi: mr. .xacvxririnwil n——✓ CONFIDENT IAL CODE TET.E0HAM • •innrcv .mr .1 From Government of India, External Affaire Dept t * 1 To Folitioal Resident In the Persian Gulf* Repeated to Secretary of State for India (for Hay)* Dated New Delhi, 15*56 hours, 18th October 1946* Received 12.30 hours, 18th October 1946. 8973 Your telegram No# 1126 dated October 12th and connected telegrams* 2. Giver is arriving at Bombay on S.S. Georgia approximately October 30th and is being inatructed to proceed to Bahrain. He should take over as A.P.A. vice Ranee, who will relieve Hudson as Political Officer, Trucial Coast. 3. Hudson should proceed, to Muscat as A.P.A. and provided Sultan will accept him as Military Adviser he may take over from Kirat on January let. Presume Hudson is- willing to accept deputation post which should give him valuable experience© 4. No decision has yet been taken on Magor's posting. Regret it will not b© possible to post Political 01 fleer as personal assistant or on deputation for language study. But I shall be grateful for your views on necessity o.f posting an officer as A.P.a'. Muscat up to or after MarcH 1947, when present sanction for*post expires (paragraph 6 of your telegram 1623 dated October 8tlfl945 refers).&lt;3 i4&gt; •; t From \«\i^ E COPY. e &gt;; t 3PI J 2 oIvolM ^ • Ha or BY FAST AIE MAIL. No.D.844-BPp/46. '1 r To The Secretary to the Government of India in the ’ External Affairs Department, The Under Secretary of State for India, External Department, erf India Office, ndbn. .// ^ London, 3&gt;- £ Dated Nev/ Delhi 3, the ^. ^Auu^s-t, 1946. Subject:- Conferment of judicial powers on Captain J.E.H.Hudson, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I am directed to report, for the information of His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India, that on the recommendation of the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Governor General in Council, in exercise of the powers conferred by Article 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, by sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Act V of 1898), and by sections 22 and 22-A of the Bombay Civil Courts Act, 1869 (Act XIV of 1869), as applied to Bahrain by the said Order, has appointed • Captain J.E.H. Hudson, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to be a Magistrate of the first class and a Subordinate Judge of the first class. He has also been invested with the jurisdiction of a Court of a Subordinate Judge of the first class. 2. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of His Majesty’s Secretary of State,for India in order to satisfy the requirements of Articles 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council,1913, I am to request that P.T.O.His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India way kindly be moved to confirm the action taken by the Governor General in Council ‘in the present case. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, / *■ f or Secretary to the Government of India .^Jj t &gt; U raaJ L I^af, &lt;-i&gt;)J^fX. ^ OUTWARD TELEGRAM Financial Department. F.123W/46 'Fa ' Word Code Telegram Zlo From Secretary of State for India. Government of India, External Affairs Department. Despatched 3rd May, 1946. 00.05 hours. % 8526 Tour Express letter D.540 -E(d)/ 46 dated 18th April. Leave salary of Captain Bird. I approve your proposal.BY FAST AIR MAIL Fiat4-«/4-b -^°rc*a To GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, External Affairs Department* express letter Foreign, New Delhi* The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, London, S.W.l* No* D.5W&gt;-E(D)A6. Dated New Delhi 3 # “the 18 th April, 1946 * Subject:- Drawal of leave salary in Iran and the Persian Gulf Correspondence ending with your letter No. F* 11165/45, dated the 29th October, 1945, on the above subject* 2. Captain R.E.R. Bird, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, has been granted leave on average pay for six months to the United Kingdom. He desires to draw his leave salary in rupees at Bahrain. Government of india consider that Captain Bird should be permitted to draw his leave salary for first four months at Bahrain. Request sanction of the Secretary of State, which may kindly be obtained and communicated by telegram. The issue of the above has been authorised* (SGD.):»AHA&lt;WNQTON- Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, WE.7^ A. Ext.l979A6 r- Sir, X am directed toy the Secretary of State to refer to your letter No.O. 1973 -I&amp;A£ of 5th iiarch, 194 o, reruing the oonfennent of judicial poeare on Captain H.D.H. Hance, Assist^mt Political Agent, Bahrein, and to inf cm you that he confirms tne action ta en General in Council# I am. Sir, Your obedient Servcint, P. A. K. HARRirON The Secretary to the Government of India, external Affairs dept*TO The XF' g rery of St^te for In rr^ 1 DG partus nt , mdl-* Office , London. D-ted Few *3c Ihi 3 &gt; ^ [arch 1346. Subject:- Conferment of judiei-. 1 powe rs on C - j/ta in H. o.H. L - ncr .n ssiatant ?o lit ic-1 nt, 3e hr a in. ir Majesty's •&gt;• tion of the Hon' am directed to report for the info mat Ion of His 'ecretary of State for India that on the recommenda- the political Resident in the Persian Culf, the dov- mor C-^ne r^l in Council, in exercise of the pov^: rs conferred by Articles 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, by sections 12 'end 37 of thd Code of Crim in a 1 Procedure , 1393(Act V of 1898)., ^ivil Courts act, 1869(act XIV of Capt a sections 12 and 37 of thd Code of Crim ina 1 Procedure ind by sections 22 and 22-A of the Bombay as applied to Bahrain uy the said Order, has appointed Captajh , ,-iSdistant political Agent, Bahrain, to be a Mag 1st rate of the first class and a Subordinate Jud^e of the first class. He has also been invested with the jurisdiction of a Subordinate Judpe 1 s ^Court of the first class, and with powers totry^cases summarily defined (vet V xfi section 26 j of 139S ?o) • [he'Code of Criminal Procedure , 1398 2 . is in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of His Majesty's Secretary of ’tare for India in order to satisfy the requirements of articles 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order, in Council, *1 j13 , I am to request that His majesty's Secretary of State for India may kindly be move a to con Tim the action taken by the Gove p re' nt cu . nor General in Council in the I have the honour to be , 3 ir ? r our most obedient servant, Gove rnment of In dia.V. From &gt;! r .,iU BY iilK lIa.IL. ^ The Secretary to the Government of India in the external Affairs Department, The Under Secretary of dtate for India, external Department^ India Office, ; iuuMDOM^ | j ^ ^ ^y,ss^ • Dated i\e^ Delhi, the May 1945 # \ s D | Subject:- Confeorment of judicial powers on Captgin R.D^ 3 ird^ Assistant dti bahrain. Sir, I am directed to refer to the correspondence resting, with your letter No »bx t»1046/45, da ted the_ 10th March 1945 and to repdrT fbr the informatrion drills Majesty^s Secretary of State for India that on the recommendation of the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Governor General in Council, in exercise of the powers conferred by section 14 of the Bahrain Order in Council ? 1913 and by sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Pro cedure 1898 (Act V of 1898) as applied to Bahrain by the said Order, has invested Captain PUB PR. Bird, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, a Magistrate of I the First Class, with powers to try cases summarily as defined in section 260 of the Criminal Procedure .Code* 2 * as in such cases it is necessary to obtain try the assent of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India in order to satisfy the requirements of sec tion 14 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, I am to request that His Majesty’s Secretary of itate for India‘may kindly be moved to confirm tne action tfbkerl.by the Governor General in Council in the present case* j j iave ^he honour to be, ^ | Sir,; Cpffijj prc Your most obechfent servant, for Secretary to the GpTi^rment^ TnrH« u *DRAFT LETTER Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department* Ext *1085/45 (v^ q %. wq 1045 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State to refer to your letter of 20th February, No.D.1883 M.S./45 regarding the conferment of judicial powers on Mr.Mohd.Abdul Hafiz, Indian Assistant to the Political Agent, Bahrein^ and to inform you that he confirms the action taken by the Governor-General in Council. tv K r. HARRISONA*- H ^ From { ■■ f, „ ;i w : r ( 5 ) N o.L.1710-Mfi/45 ^ t (U:n f: t - ^ Lj -The Secretary to thei Grovefrimeritr of’ Inaia T TO in the External Affairs Departrneht, , -pv I ^ I . [ /\S&lt;&gt; The Under Secretary %or India, External Department, India‘OTTice, London. Dated New Delhi,tne\i&gt; February 1945. Subject:- Conferment of judicial powers on Captain R.E.R.Bird, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I am directed to report for the information of His Majesty 1 s Secretary of State for India that on the recommendation of the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, the G-ovornor G-encrai in Council, in exercise of the- powers conferred by Articles 14 and 3D of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, by sections 12 and 37 of the Cone of Criminal Procedure, 1898,(Act V of 1898), ana by sections 22 ana 22-A of the Bombay Civil Courts Act, 1869, (Act Xiy of 1869), ,as apnlied to Bahrain by the said Ord^r, has appointed Captain R.E.R.Bird, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to be a Magistrate of the iirst class and a Subordinate Judge of the first j class. He has also been invested with the jurisdiction 7 01 p Subordinate Judge’s Court of the first class. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent oi Kis Majesty’s Secretary of State for India moraer to satisfy the requirements of Articles 14 and 3D of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, I am to request that His Majesty’s Secretary of State for In-la may kindly be moved to confirm the action t aken by the Governor General in Council in the present case. I have the honour to be, Sir,^ &gt; Your most ooedient servant, for Secretary to the Government of ■■ ■ Inaia. I INDIA OFFICE!Conferment of judicial powers on Mr. Mohd. Abdul r-zhhul, Hafiz, officiating Indian Assistant to the Political * lk0 ' A^rent« Bahrain. _ Sir, I am directed to report for the information of His Majesty's Secretary of State for India th e t on the recommendation of the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Governor General in Council in exercise of the powers conferred by Articles 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, by Sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, (Act V of 1898), and‘by Sections 22, 22A, 24 and 28 of the Bombay Civil Courts Act, 1869. (Act 111 of 1869), as applied to Bahrain by the said Order, has appointed Mr. Mohd. Abdul Hafiz, officiating Indian Assistant to the Political Agent, Bahrain, to be a Magistrate’of th* second class and a Subordinate Judge of the second class. He has also been invested with the jurisdiction of, a Court of Subordinate judge of the second class and a Court of Small Causes for the £rx±s± trial of suits cognizable by such courts up to the amount of two hundred rupees. 2. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of His Majesty's Secretary of State for India in order to satisfy the requirements of Articles 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, I am to request - that His Male sty’s Secretary of State fo** Indie may be moved kindly to confirm the action taken by the Governor General in Council in the present case. I have the honour to b*. Sir, Your most obedient servant,Jtfom To ir. I! o. Q.8266^/44.~'7 7 '&lt; / 5 Ihe Secretary to thp- ^ . Government of li:idi^r v in J ohV External Affairs Departmenft, yi\ i qa a ^ file Under* oecx e^^r y-of' S'feteP £&amp;c india External De par linen t, India Office, Londoti* Date.d Sew Delhi, the ol8^~ June 1944, Subject: Conferment of judicial powers on ir. T.D. Borers, Assistant political Agent, Bahrain* I am directed to report for the information of His :ajeuty ? c Secretary of State for India that on the recoLiraendation of the Hon’ble the Political decadent in the Persian G-iuf, the Governor General in Council, in exercise of^os/ers conferred by Articles 14 and 3D of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, by sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal procedure, 1898, (Act 7 of 1898), and by sections 22 and 22-A of the Bo-bay Civil Courts Act, 1869 (Act 117 rf 1369), as applied to Bahrain by the said Order , has a _»p ointed_' h. IVdr 3ofeers, Assistant Political A^^nt, Bahrain, to be a I.ja&amp;istrate of the first class and a Subordinate Juoge of the first class. He has also been invested with the jurisdiction of a Court of subordinate Judge of the first class. «H — ' BECo. BlU 22* As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of His I^jesty f 's Secretary of etate for India in order to satisfy the requirements of Articles 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, I am to request that His Majesty^ Secretary of otate fey India ’may kindly be moved to confirm the action taken by the‘Governor General in Council in the present anse• Your most obedient servant I have the honour to be, - * ’Sit, /t— bBct.l548A4 ?.A. COO. DRAPE LETTER Thv. Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department* Sir, m % 19 ^PH1944 I am directed by the Secretary of State to refer to your letter of the 26th January, No*570-N/J»4, regarding the conferment of judicial powers on Mr* R.M.Hadow, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein, and to inform you that he confirms the action taken by the Governor- General in Council* I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, ft A. K. RARRKrvv al ♦2y/ / -L a m n 2* Jxq ir suoh caftog? it 1 b ' eceBBaiy to obtain the assent of His Majesty*a -»ecr of State for India in order to satisfy the requirements of Articles 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Gouncil. 1913, I am to request tlmt His majesty's Secretary of State for India mfiy kindly be moved to confirm the act!or taken by the Governor General in Council in the present case* I have the honour to be, air, Your most obedient servant. for Secretary to the Covernmerit of India. IA aTL+J3? INWARD TELEGRAM 11788 to External Department .L CODE TEIaEGRAM Prom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To Dated Received Secretary of State for India* Bushire, 16,00 hours; 4th April, 1944* 23*45 hours? 4th April? 1944. 861 Your telegram 12,365 October 4th 1941. Following are general summer postings* (l) RogQi , Q Consul Bandar Abbas proceeds on one month’s leave on relief by McConaghey® (2) Tandy Political Officer Trucial Coast* proceeds on home leave in May on relief by Kadow* (o) Rogers relieves Hadow as Assistant Political Agent Bahrain. 'v * (4) Polly Political Agent Koweit proceeds on home leave on relief by Jackson. (5) Hickinbotham proceeds on one months leave in July. Rogers officiates. (6) On Hickinbotham return? Hadow proceeds on one month’s recess handing over to Rogers as Political Officer Trucial Coast (?) On Hadow 8 s return Rogers proceeds to Shargah. 3 e Government of India are unable to spare a Political Officer as Vice-Consul* Rhoramohahr ? but are (? endeavour)ing to find a replacement for (” MeConaghoy). 4 . For period between Tandy's departure to Rogers relief by Hadov? there will be no resident Political uxf.lccr on Trucial Coast as pr*esenes of two officers is necessary in Bahrain.&lt;$&gt; • Pit. in the iil^ternal Affairs Lfepartoent. ■ l 94 $ fhe Under Secretary of State for 'Th^ra'; - w Asternal Department, India Office, London, Subject;- Conferment of judicial powers on Captain 7 T D D f r 1 Po Vi/'lir Pi I i -4- -i .1 /-&gt; 4- Sir, I am directed to report for the information of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India that on the recommendation of the Hon f ble they?olitical Resident in the Persian Grulf, the Governor General in Council, in exercise of powers conferred by ArticlesT^and 3D of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, by sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal procedure, 1898, (Act V of 1898), and by sections 22 and 22-A of the Bombay Civil Courts Act,1869, (Act XIV of 1369) as applied to Bahrain by one said Order, hag appointed Captain r*p.O r C Tandy Assistant Political Agent, Banrain,. to be a-Llagis orate of the first class and a Subordinate Judge of the first class. He has algo been invested with the jurisdiction of a Court of Subordinate. Judge of the first class. 2. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of His Majesty’s Decretary of State for India in order to satisfy the requirements of Articles 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, I am to request that His Majesty’s Secretary, of State for India may kindly be moved to confirm the action taken by the Governor General in the present case. 7 Dated Pew Delhi, the September 1943. H.P.O’C Tandy, assistant political Bahrain. I have the honour to be, * Sir, Your most obedient servant. V for secretary to the Governmental J0 Xli X -iXzilu - «?' * ‘ ii- / ’ n 4 U vj ^ - Allotted to Externel Department. OCt-II^IDKNTlAL CODE TELEGRAM ^2- Frurr Government of Indie, External Affairs Dept. To Minister at Tehran» Kept, to Jecretary of State for India and Consul General Meshed. Dated New Delhi 19.56 hrs . 17th Aug 3 1943/» Reed. 12*30 hrs, 18th Aug, 1943* No* 246? Addressed to Minister at Tehran repeated to Secretary of State for India 6913 and Consul General Meshed* It is proposed to post Captain. M.G• Dixon Indian Political Service at present Assistant (? Political Agent) Bahrain as Vice-Consul Meshed in December next vice (?Hadow) who will replace Dixon in Bahrain? If no objection necessary agreement may kindly he obtained*IND^ OFFJpEj From To : — OPY F0.5223-K/42. ' The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, The Under Secretary of State for India, External Department, India Office, London. Dated New Delhi, the 3 August 1942. Subject:-Conferment of judicial cowers Captain i. .G. Dixon, a.L.a. 5a. _ _ on Bahrain. Sir, I am directed to report for the information of His ii ajesty* s Secretary of State for India that on uhe reconmenda* tion oi the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian exercise of powers rain Order in sections ana cy oi me Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, (Act 7 of 1898), and by sections 22 and 22-A of the Bombay Civil Courts Apt, 1869, (let XIV of 1869), as acolied to Bahrain bv the said Order, has aooo in ted Captain aPPl . .G, lied to Bahrain b Dixon, Assistant trate of the firs of the on oi me urst class ana a buoorainaLe juoge oi i class. He has also been invested with the junsdicti of a Court of Subordinate Judge of the first class. 2. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of Majesty’s Secretary of State for India in order to satisfy the requirements of Articles 14 and 3G of the Bahrain Order m Council, 1913, I am to request that His lajesty’s Secretary of State for India may kindly be moved to confirm the action taken by the Governor General in Council in the present case. I have the honour to be, Your most obeSient servant, .M.A* for Secretary to the Government of India. rc V S'®*) Vc AV -a/ ‘ y: G vi-c ^ J£ , A fThe under Secretary of State for India, External Department, India Office, London« Dated New Delhi, the 1942. Conferment of judicial powers on Dr. S.M.Siddiq, Indian As si? tant to the Political Agent Bahrain. Sir With reference to the correspondence ending v^ith yo ur letter No .P«Z.3006/38 , dated the 25th May 1938, I stn directed To r eport” for the' information of His Majesty f s Secretary cf State for India that on the recommendation of the Hobble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Governor General in Council, in exercise of powers conferred by section 15 of the Qatar Order in Council, 1939, and by sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Act V of 1898) as applied to Qatar by the said order, has appointed Dr. S.M.Siddiq, Indian Assistant to the Political Agert, Bahrain, to be a Magistrate of the first class. As in such cases it is necessaryjto obtain the assent of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India in order to satisfy the requirements of section 15 of the Qatar Order in Council, I an to request that His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India may be moved kindly to confirm the action taken by the Governor-General in Council in the present case. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, v f ' joint Secretary to tne Govt, of India / Uy§■7 • '(•' r * ' I P.Z.4411/40. The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Dept,, Mr « Qirh son , ? to issue. In an earlier case Mr. ieel agreed that unless they possessed some unusual feature ; no reference to Departments or submission need be made in these cases. This is cpiite straightforward, similar powers having been conferred on previous holders of the post. I am directed by the secretary of state to refer to your letter of the 8th July NO.D.3496-N/40 notifying the conferment of judicial powers on Khan sahib Mirza Ismail Barduli, Indian Assistant to the political Agent, Bahrein, and to inform you that he confirms the action taken by the Governor- General in Council. J. p, GJBSONVNDt'AF-D FILH No. D.3496-N/40. l\i*V X ' . /£&amp; From To The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, The Under S^crefayy of State for India, Political-Department, India Office, m i Date I Si md 16 j July 194D. Conferment of judiciax powers on Khan Sahib Mirza Ismail Barduli, Indian Assistant to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I am directed to report for the information of His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India that on the recommendation of the Hon’bie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Governor General in Council, in exercise of the powers conferred by section? 14 and f 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, and by sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, and by sections 22.22A,24 and 28 of the Bombay Civil Courts Act, 1869, (XIV of 1869) as applied to Bahrain by the said Order, has appointed Khan Sahib Mirza Ismail Barduli, Indian Assistant to the Poli tical Agent, Bahrain, to be a Magistrate of the second class and a Subordinate Judge of the second class. He has also been invested with jurisdiction as a Court of Small Causes with paver to hear suits up to an amount of two hundred rupees. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of His Majesty's Secretary of State for India and in order to satisfy the requirements of sections 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, I am to request that His Majesty's Secretary of State for India may be • moved... ♦ HECo. i*OL. D£.Pt. P.T.O. - 8AUG &lt;940 INDIA OFFICEmoved kindly to confirm the action taken by the Governor General in Council in the present case. I lave the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, (M for Secretary to the Government of India, lJ? ^ From To 5o The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London* Dated Simla, the June 1939# Conferment of judicial powers on Mr. R*I* Hallows, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain* Sir, I am directed to report for the information of His Majesty's Secretary of State for India that on the recommenda tion of the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Governor General in Council, in exercise of powers conferred by sections 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, by sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898,(Act V of 1898), and by sections 22 and 22-A of the Bombay Civil Courts Act, 1869, (Act XIV of 1869), as applied to Bahrain by the said Order, has appointed Mr. R.I* Hallows, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to be a Magistrate of the first class and a Subordinate Judge of the first class* He has also been invested with the jurisdiction of a Court of Subordinate Judge of the first class* 2* As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of His Majesty's Secretary of State for India in order to satisfy the requirements of sections 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, I am to request that His Majesty's Secretary of State for India may be moved kindly to confirm the .action taken by the Governor General in Council in the present case* I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant.4715 Allotted to Polltic e 1 Department 0 Cpplt/ ^ CireuXateda 1958 J DEC YP H E R O F T L K &lt;3 R A M, From Government of India to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and repeated by former to Secretary of State for India, Dated He’* Delhis 12 0 20 hours 25th December p 1958 0 Received ll o 00 hours, 25th December, 1938, X Addressed to Bushire s repeated to gecretery of State for India, Your confidential demi-official letter 587-8 of 14th Nov ember® Spring postlngSc. Following postings proposed by you are approved, Galloway to Koweit vice de Geury, who may have his leave, Howes to Muscat till Autumn vice Watts, who nay have his leave. It is proposed to send Hallows, who is expected to complete his training about the end of June, to Bahrainana » : &gt; i ^ From To 71 7Q &gt; '1*0 tJo .D .3615-N/38 • i !333 The Uecrexary to the Government of India in. the External Affairs Department, The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, Londono Dated Simla, the A? October 1938. Conferment of judicial powers on Captain J.B. Howes, Assistant Political .Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I am directed to report for the information of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India that on the recommendation of the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, the Governor General in Council, in exercise of powers conferred by sections 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council 1913, by sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Act V of 1898) and by sections 22 and 22-A of the Bombay Civil Courts Act, 1869 (Act XI? of 1869) as applied to Bahrain by the said Order, has appointed Captain J.B. Howes, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to be a Magistrate of the first class and a Subordinate Judge of the first class. He has also been invested with the jurisdiction of a Court of Subordinate Judge of the first class. 2. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain r the assent of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for IndiaIndia in order to satisfy the requirements of sections 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Oouncil, 1913, I am to request that His Majesty's Secretary of State for India may be moved kindly to confirm the action talcen by the G-overnor G-eneral in Council in the present case. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant,HZ $ ^ * * I y No.D•1309-M/38. From p. zT l -zncifc d 5 &gt; fM ^ -C^ M'*'- H - 938 To The Secretary to the G-overnment of India in the External Affairs Department, The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London. Simla, the April 1938. Conferment of Judicial powers on Dr.S.k.Siddic, Indian Assistant to the Political Agent, Bahrain. kv Sir, fi 1 $ ^ i \ In continuation of ‘Government of India in the External Affairs Department letter No .D. 1833-11/37, dated the 20tlr Nay 1937, I sun directed to report for trie information of Kis Uajes- ty’s Secretary of State for India that on the reop..mendation of the Hon’ble the I olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf, tne Governor-General in Council, in exercise of powers con ferred by section 14 of the Bahrain °rder in Cou cil, 1913, and by sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure 1898 (Act V of 1898) as applied to Bahrain by the said order, has appointed Dr. S.L.Siudiq, Indian Assistant to the ‘ oli tical Agent, Bahrain, to be a magistrate of the first class. He has also been invested with powers to try cases summarily as defined in section 260 of the Criminal Procedure Code. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of mis Hajesty’sSecretary of State for India in order to satisfy the requirements of section 14 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, I am to request that His majesty's Secretary of State for India may be moved kindly to confirm the action taken . S « rj 0SB&amp;. rA r 29 APR 1938 INDIA OFHOF.FH-fc From „ [ t-'.'. r i o - r* t- ' ' &amp; No. D.1296-N/38«. j 0 4- fi* ' U i . r , .~ _ v - r - . The Secretary to the G-overrirpent of India in the External Affairs Department• To The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London. Sir, Dated New Delhi, the April 1938. Conferment of magisterial powers on Lieutenant R.S.R.Bird, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. I am directed to report for the information of Kis Majesty* s Secretary of State for India that on the recommendation of the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian 3-ulf, the G-overnor G-eneral in Council, in exercise of powers conferred by section 14 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, and by sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, has appointed Lieute nant R.E.R.Bird, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to be a magistrate of the second class. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India in order to satisfy the requirements of section 14 of the Bahrain Order in Council 1913, I am to request that His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India may be moved kindly to confirm the action taken by the 3-overnor General in Council in the present case. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant,P.Z. 1550/38. Extract from Intelligence Summary of the Political Agent, Bahrein, for the period 1st to 15th February, 1938. Secret . No. 3 of 1938. 14(iii) Lieutenant R. Bird arrived from India by the s.s. ,, Bankura u on 5th February and took over charge as Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein, from Captain Galloway on 13th February.1913 / No ♦F*593-N/37. From The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, To The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office* I am directed to report for the information of Kis Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, that on the recommendation of the Hon’hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Governor General in Council, in exercise of the powers conferred by sections 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure and sections 22 and 22-A of the Bombay Civil Courts Act, 1869, has appointed Captain A.C* Galloway, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to be a magistrate of the first class and a Subordinate Judge of the first class, and has invested him with the jurisdiction of a Court of Subordinate Judge of the first class* 2. As in such cases, it is necessary to obtain the assent of His Majesty’s Government so as to satisfy the requirements of section 14 of the Bahrain Order in Council powers on uaptain A.u^u-a Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated New Delhi, the /$ ' December 1937. Conferment of magisterial and judicial powers on Captain A.C. Galloway,Assistant Sir,1913, I am to request that His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, may be moved kindly to confirm the action taken by the Governor (General in the present case. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant nt of India.t No*D.1833-N/37 # ; X '; / \ From The Secretary to the Government' of India in the External Affairs Department, To The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London. Dated Simla, the ^ May 1937. Conferment of judicial powers on Dr.S*M*Siddiq, Indian Assistaift to the Political Agent, Bahrain. • • • • Sir, I am directed to report for the information of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India that on the recommenda tion of the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Governor General in Council, in exercise of the powers conferred by Sections 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council 1913, and by Sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, and by Sections 22,2;&gt;A, 24 and 28 of the Bombay Civil Courts Act, 1869, (XIV of 1869) as applied to Bahrain by the said Order, has appointed Dr.S.M. Siddiq, Indian Assistant to the Political Agent, Bahrain, to be a magistrate and Subordinate Judge of the Second Class. He has also been invested with jurisdiction as a Court of Small Causes with power to hear suits up to an amount of two hundred rupees. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India in order to satisfy tne requirements of Sections 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, 1 am to request that His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India may be moved kindly to confirm the action taken by the Governor 'General in Council in the present case* J W. I have the honour to be. Sir Your most obedient servant, I fti&amp;tt. ' T&amp;t' ' 7UUN193?J 'ICE lor Secretary to the Government of India. 2 &lt; &lt; )\fFrom To No. D# 1417-N/37. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London* 4 ^ Dated New Delhi, the /475T April 1937. Conferment of magisterial powers on Lieutenant B.L.L. Tomlinson, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I am directed to report for the information of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India that on the recommendation of the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, the Governor (General in Council, in exercise of pov/ers conferred by Section 14 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, and by Sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure. 1898. has appointed. Lieutenant B.L.M. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, Tomlinson,/to be a magistrate of the second class. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India in order to satisfy the requirements of Section 14 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, I am to request that His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India may be moved kindly to confirm the action taken by the Governor General in Council in the present case. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your post obedient servant, for Secretary to the Government off India. ( mC/r X Vr-r )NO.D.18-N/37. ($5) t 20 VC* V Prom To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, % His Majesty’s Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, » India Office, LONDON Dated New Delhi, the J p.z. Conferment of Magisterial and Judicial powers on Captain A.C.Stewart,Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. / 0 Sir, U'( v i H I am directed to report for the information of His° V Majesty’s Secretary of State for India that on the recommendation of the Hon’hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Governor General in Council, in exercise of the powers conferred by Sections 14 and 35 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, Sections 12 and 37 of Code of Criminal Procedure and Sections 22 and 22-A of the Bombay Civil Courts Act, 1869, has appointed Captain A.C.Stewart, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, Ul \ jc-' to be a Magistrate of the first class and a -subordinate Judge of the first class, and has invested him with the I w ~ ' ^'^jurisdiction of a Court of a subordinate Judge of the As in such cases it is necessary to obtain first class. the assent of His Majesty's Government in order to satisfy the requirements of Section 14 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, I am to request that His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India may be moved kindly to confirm the action taken by the Governor General in Council in the'present case. “I have the honour to be, Sir, recd. pol mx 8FEBl93y° ur niost obedient servant INDIA OFFICE] for Foreign Secretary to the Government of 0 India. ( &lt;x. 4 tfo. )fl Ijetter r relegram from Register No. P. z. 6441/36 Political Department Dated Rec. 19 Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Chairman Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee '/I ftt/c BAHREIN Conferment of the powers of a First-Class. Magistrate and of a Second-Class Subordinate Judge on Khan Bahadur d s Abdul Haiy Js. Hashni, Indian Assistant to Political Agent, Bahrain Under Secretary Secretary of State... •/ Box Uouncw m 7 7 7 Table 4' i, ^ ’ Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft letter to Government of India sanctioning action taken. Previous Papers :— 4408 b 500 3.302956 6000 7/34 22- Minute Paper. P.Z.6441/36 Department. r\ t /P KaU tA — ■ ( ^ VSMAhJ/*' aV ^ ^ \\ r &lt;- x-. i • 1 ^ n -7 r— ^ » y The powers of a Second-Glass Magistrate were recently conferred upon the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein: see papers at P.Z.5414/36. The Assistant Political Agent at Bahrein is now chiefly occupied with his duties at Q,atar and the Trucial Coast, and it is therefore very likely t4awt i4 been found that he is not available to assist the Political Agent in the performance of judicial duties at Bahrein. Additional help in this field is therefore necessary, and it is submitted that the action taken by the Government of India should be confirmed. o iOJ b[oo /C A* Legal Adviser , Secretary. P. &amp; J. Department , For the favour of any observations.Draft Paper. P.Z.6441/36 Department. Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, F. &amp; P. Department, Simla. 24 sep t 936 Jf Sir, I am directed hy the Secretary of State for India to refer to the Government of India’s letter of 19th August, No. D. 5526-A?/ 36, regarding the I K-CxtJL conferment of t-he powers of a Firot-g^ggs- Tiingi ntrntn onii of a Srrjonfl HI Dubwdinatc Judge on tJfte gontlomcaft Khan Bahadur Abdul Haiy Hash«i, Indian Assistant to the Political Agent, Bahrein, and to say xhat he confirms the action which has been taken in this matter by the Governor-General in Council. Sgd.) M. J. OLAU®O n■ '. y wmmtfil Prom NO.D.5326-N/36. 7“'—; I 64^ I The Foreign Secretary -... to the Government of India, iff To The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S.W.l. Dated Simla, the / ^August 1936. Suh iect:-Conferment of Judicial powers on Khan Bahadur Abdul Haiy El Hashmi, Indian Assistant to Political Agent, Bahrein. I Sir, rr ' In continuation of Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department letter No. D .4517-N/36, dated the 7th July 193 6, I am directed to report for the information of His Majesty's Secretary of State for India that on the reconmendation of the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Governor- General in Council, in exercise of powers conferred by Sections 14 and 35 of the Bahrein Order in Council, 1913, and by Sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, and by Sections 22, 22-A, 24 and 28 of the Bombay Civil Courts Act, 1869, (XIV of 1869) as applied to Bahrein by the said Order, has appointed Khan Bahadur Abdul Haiy El Hashmi, Indian Assistant to Political Agent, Bahrain, to be a Magistrate of t)ie fjjg£t£3SLass and Subordinate Judge of the second class. He has also been invested with powers to try cases summarily as defined • • •2 . defined in Section 260 of the Criminal Procedure Code, and with jurisdiction as a Court of Small Causes with power to hear suits up to an amount of two hundred rupees. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of His Majesty's Secretary of State for India in order to satisfy the requirements of Sections 14 and 35 of the Bahrein Order in Council, 1913, I am to request that His Majesty's Secretary of State for India may be moved kindly to confirm the action taken by the Governor-General in Council in the present case. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, forPoreign Secretary to the Government of India.(g) Register No. vv P. z. m/ ^ 5414/36 Political Department. Lercter 'I'elegrani from Dated Rec. Formally acknowledged 19 Date. Initials. 0 Chairman Under Secreta^ / Secretary of $tate... Committee. Under Secretary Secretary of State... (Weil £Z, / 1 able SUBJECT. BAHREIN Conferment of magisterial powers on Lieutenant J.B. Howes, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein ytx C/\ AW»v&gt; ►Vv-i Previous Papers Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY, Draft letter to the Government of India sanctioning action taken. 4408 b 500 3.30 /%7 2956 6000 7 34 Minute Paper. P.Z.5414/36 Department. A precedent for this case will be found at P.Z.5751/35. Experience has shown, presumably, that the conferment of magisterial powers Second-class is sufficient to enable the Assistant Political Agent at Bahrein to assist the Political Agent in the performance of his judicial duties. This is clearly a necessary duty for the Assistant Political Agent, and it is submitted that the action of the Government of India should be confirmed. Legal Advise r. Secretary, P. &amp; J. Department . For the favour of any observations. ‘f/'r3938 5000 7.35 n Draft Paper. p.z. 5414/36 Department. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Dept., Simla. 13 AUG 1936 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to the Government of India's letter of 7th July, No. L. 4517-/^/36 , regarding the conferment of magisterial powers on Lieutenant J.B. Howes, Assistant Political Agent at Bahrein, and to say that he confirms the action which has been taken in this matter by the Governor- General in Council. i (Sd.) J. C. WALTON.sS&gt; ’H N0.D.4517-K/36. From The Foreign Secretary to the Grover.rment of India, To ^ h- \ The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, vW Dated Simla, the / ’ July 1936. Conferment of magisterial powers on Lieutenant J.3. Howes, Assistant # . Political Agent, Bahrain. o l ^ . w rt I am directed to report for the information of His Uajesty’a Secretary of State for India that on the recommen dation of the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian C-ulf, the G-overnor General in Council, in exercise of powers conferred by Section 14 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913 3 and by Sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, has appointed Lieutenant J.B. Howes, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to be a magistrate of the second class. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India in order to satisfy the requirements of Section 14 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, I am to request that His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India may be moved kindly to confirm the action taken by the Governor General in Council in the present case. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. REGn T - 2 7 JUL1936•&gt; n 3/&gt;cA T*1 •grsjn Ho.l08S-g Dated 23rd Octooer 193o. F'ro* .For ifm, -Aw^a. ff K To •britof&gt;na«l f Hus-lire. Hefer«ace your UUtr No. 2000, datod 29th Sapttosber 1935. aoTernor Qonoral in QouriCil is pie to sanction creation of^po^t of temper* ry clerk, for office of Political Agent, Bahrain, on pay of fe.120-6- 150»10^250 efficiency bur at Is.180 plus 3ulf special pay of %35 per mensem and house rent allowance of 54.50 per mensem for a period of one year, with effect iron: 1st November 1935* Expenditure involved during current financial ye&amp;r aho Id be met from sanctioned budget grant at your disposal* Steps ar^ being taken to include provision for next year's expenditure in budget estimates for 1936-37. (ACCOUNT? GENbj j *i i se; I 15 NOV 1935 »U/&gt;i. (o/nf&amp; ■ ■ s / i ) Copy of a letter No. 2000,: d*tt«W. tli« 2t : tl'i September I93ii, from tiie Hai’ble tiie political Resident in the Persian Gulf, (Oi- . , to tfie Foreign Oecretp to the Govor; .xsnt of India, e-inOa. iiufcjectj- Revision of the clerical LetuHLishnent of the i oil deal Agency, Hahraln. I have the honour 1 to inforr.i you that, before he proceeded on leave, colonel Fawle tended to m a proposal of the Acting : oiitioal Agar-t, Bahrain, for l»eist: or in the lagU ffic© of the rolitlsal AflMey. Z. There is no doubt that a-sistmeo is rot ulred, I attach statofoants sitowiag the increase in the correspon dence handled and in the receipts a nd pEjascnts /tide by the treasury, auch figtires do not, however, convey a true 1’aprcssicn of the iaorvase of work, men of which is conducted direct with the persoiie concerned and so takes up a dispreoartianate mount of tiro. The increase of work is due ;.,rlncinally:- (i) to too dovoiopEcnt of the .ia hr aln petroleum Gcsapany’s ail field and the ostublistaaraat of the California Arabian dUtnaard oil Cougxwy in lisa. (ii) to the tn nsfar of the Ruv l otutiou to Bahrain, (iil)to the use of the amb Coast by toe Royul Air Force tad Iraporial Airways, -i (iv) to toe negotiations snd intrl£pes in skater mid on tisO Trucial Coast over air laoilitios and ell mid other minerrJLP, and (v) to toe appeintrnent of an Assistant Political Amt to relieve the political Agent, which has thrown mare oorir. on the clerical establishment.&lt; 12 - 3. An Instance of the my in wnloh petty v/ork has been Increa^od by tue instituticaie oantioued above le afforded by the diffioultios and time taJi.en up by ccntro lling liquor liaior'ts now that the Eur^iean ui*i /uaerlcan population lias i isan frua sobjc telf-a-dossen poiuons to over an hundred, apart from casual visitors such as the Royal Air Force. 4. In 1930 an acldltloruil cleric of the upper wlvlslan. was sanct (see Mr* Heruiiorl Rae*e Momoranaum :;o. .3,(2)-. •/*&gt;o dated the loth Juno itfSOj for the English Office, but hid time is entirely taken up by oocfldentlal Wei . 1 work is do&gt;w In a room off the i olltioal Agent’s -.orsoma office, where all ti«o cmfi- dentlal records eie kept. This arraivjemeiit Is inconvenient but there are so many people Interested in the political Agent’s correspondonce that special steps have to be taken to safeguard It. The present incumbent of the post Is a quick worker anti 'na&amp; dealt with the correspondence, mostly air aid oil natters with their attontlaxrt intrigues, since it began to grow so heavy. Be is, however, proceeding on leave in April 1936 and is likely to be promoted at the and of hlu leave.In any case,he ootid not have continued to do the weKk single-handed and t. newcomer will certt inly not be able to do so.harae limed late help is, therefore, required In the confidential bransh.iaore particularly as it is often necesnary to take the confidential dbrk on tour. I propose that this help shall be given for the present by the Head Clerk. 5. The clerical estabilahiaent of the angllsh office proper remains at the sans strength as it was prior to 1929, nairely, an Heed Clerk,a becond Clerk and a Passport Clark♦The last nuaeu holds a special post created to ue; 1 with/with passport and visa vroartc and paid for from the passport and visa fees, Put In practice helps in the English oilloo woric 'vnen free to do so. This staff is inadequate for the \iovk v/iiicii It is new called upon to do. . Apart from the increase in work explained in the second and third paragraphs above, a further Increase of work will undoubtedly take place whan the /uiglo-Iranian Oil Ccnpaay begin working tiwlr conceeslan In t atar next 1 month and the Trucial Coast is calling for more and joore attention as it beoxnes further opened up by nlr and by the Interest taken in oil and other minerals (far example, oxide of iron and gypsura). The trutii is that it is no lunger powsiode to regard aid Bahrain ^ency office as a political office of tue old days in the Persian Gulf and it needs to be reorganised to meet the new upon it. Z m not yet, however, in a ositlai at present to make pro-xjsals to this end. 7. in tt» laoantlae, in order to cope with the urgent need of the moment, I raocBiaand that the ^Aglish office of the Bahrain rolitlcal A/jency should be strengthened at cvice by the addition of one dark of the upper Division for one year in the first instance, and to send tisero a clerk with a first class ki'.jwiu.-.ge of ucoounts* 8. This additional clerk will relieve the Head Clerk by taking over (under the Head Clerk’s supervisionJ tie accounts work of the Agency and tiius enable tto Head Clerk to devote a part of his tine to helping in the confidential branch. The additional clerk will also have certain other duties allotted to him to relievo the strain on the office in general. 9. A proposition statement is or,.dosed and I request that provision ray be nude to meet the cost of the post In tho &gt;idgot oat it .utes of lv'.&gt;-&gt;37. The axtn expenditure durlxvg/wmwu.m. Curing tiio oarsreat 'jogx' will bo mt rroia autioipatou savings in the existinc buaget grants of tills keslackey under tho sub-huid v ay of ; stall Isii'onts.'' 10. In view of the urgent need of assist,uiee in the Bahrain Agency office, i request that oruers my bo sent by telegram or air mall.—/ Minute Paper. p.z. 5751/35. Department. &lt;s&gt; ' p &amp; J ■' 3(i27 It is clearly desirable that the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein, should he in a position to assist the Political Agent in the performance of his judicial duties. Mr. Worth, the first incumbent of the post of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein, was granted the powers of a First Glass magistrate and subordinate judge in 193U* (See P.Z.3505/34). The Government of India have now appointed his successor. Lieutenant Metcalfe, to be a magistrate of the T/c jrtj~ J /«'«'• Second Class. Phit/ is presumably due to the fact that Lieutenant Metcalfe lacks the judicial experience which Mr. Worth possessed. The Government of India have asked the Secretary of State to confirm the action they have do ee. // /Ytfc~yC taken, and it is submitted that to should de (~ 4 £^ei(&gt; /v&lt;»\ ? c « k&lt;. i o* to rt-l n A 5 oj? T Wo?) 3436b 5000 1.35f n P.Z. 5751/35 Minute Paper Department. p&amp; j 'Mi 21 .'3436b 5000 1.35 It is clearly desirable that the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein, should he in a position to assist the Political Agent in the performance of his judicial duties. Mr. Worth, the first incumbent of the post of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein, was granted the powers of a First Glass magistrate and subordinate judge in 193U* (See P.Z.3505/34). The Government of India have now appointed his successor, Lieutenant Metcalfe, to be a magistrate of the T/t jrt^h .( /e&gt;/cr Second Class, ffae^is presumably due to the fact that Lieutenant Metcalfe lacks the judicial experience which Mr. Worth possessed. The Government of India have asked the Secretary of State to confirm the action they have taken, and it is submitted that should de -se^ * 0 /A /VePc^yC p c l/ vi C ^ I 0Draft Paper Department P. Z. . 5751/35. fob f6o n 2 6 SEP 1955 The Foreign Secretary to the G-ovemment of India, Foreign and Political Dept., I am directed hy the Secretary of State for India to refer to the Government of India’s letter of the 30th July, Do. D. 3125 N/35&gt; regarding the conferment of magisterial powers on Lt.Metcalfe, Assistant Political Agent at Bahrein, and to say that he confirms the action which has Been taken in this matter hy the Governor-General in Council.9 Prom The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India ^0 V The Under Secretary of State for India Political Department, India Office, London. Dated Simla, the 1935 Metcalfe, Assistant Political Agent,' Ba Conferment of magisterial powers on Metcalfe, Assistant Political Agent,' Ba Sir I am directed to report for the information of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India that on the recommenda tion of the Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Governor General in Council, in exercise of powers conferred hy Section 14 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, and 'by Sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, has appointed Lieutenant R.D. Metcalfe, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, to he a magistrate of the second class. As in such cases it is necessary to obtain the assent of His Majesty's Secretary of State for India in order to satisfy the requirements of Section 14 of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, I am to request that His Majesty's Secretary of State for India may he moved kindly to confirm the action taken hy the Governor General in Council in the present case. I have the honour to he Sir Your most obedient servant for Foreign Secretary to the Government of IndiaINDIA OFFIGE, LONDON, 3.T. 1. £5tb June 19^5. Ly deur George, You wrote to use on 20th April, No.659, about Mr. FaruK*s house. Unfortunately I had to go on leave lnmediately after and ttulton has been so over- whelBied witn wortc tiiat it has been iflipossi'Dle for him to take tile matter up, and I fear that It Is now too late in the day. I ought, however, to say that we did, in fact, feel some little diffidence in coming in, as »e aid not know the local conditions, and it «as felt here that tuere was some awkwardness about the main Office making a direct approach to Paruk ana so exposing the secretary of state to the possibility of e rebuff if he said either that he aid not wish to discuss the matter at all or that he was not prepared to consider any offer other than that which he has already put forward anu which has been rejected, and the view taken was that it would be difficult to distinguish/ Captain G.A. Cole, I.A Political agency, Bahrein.* - &amp; - distinguish between personal approach by an inaiviuual taeicber of the Office and a niore foraal approach with which the Office as such would be associated. I am very sorry, but hope that your own pleadings have produced some affect upon him. J. G. LA1THWAITE.*7 '/ : -A 4 D.O. No:659 I enclose a copy of a letter which is self explanatory if a little badly woraed. Colonel Fowle tola me to write to you both on his behalf ana my own and ask you to see Mr.Faruk, and try to get him to accept our terms. Faruk is a rich pearl merchant who has built a large house behina the Agency in which he nas never livea, ana which we shoula like to rent for the Assistant Political Agent. He has consistently refused very gooa but we feel that the personal touch woula over-come the difficulty. Could you please help us to this extent. J. G-. Laithwaite Esquire, C.I.E., The Inuia Office, LONDON S.N.i.Toj I ./} D.O.No.658 20th April 1905. Lear Mr.Paruk, The new post of a permanent Assistant Political Agent has been created here, and at present there is no suitable house for him. lour house behind the Agency could be made suitable if certain repairs could be effected ana electric light installed. Whether you lease tne nouse or not the former will nave to be oone to prevent the nouse falling down. The only extra re piirements are two European bathrooms and electric light, whicn I assume should you ever wish to reoccupy the house you would have aone. I should be most obliged to you if you coulu see your way to leasing the house to the Agency ana effecting the above repairs and additions. The most I can offer you at present is a three year lease at Rs.i50/- per mensem, which I understand through your agent you are not prepared to sccept unless the tenant bears the cost of improvements mentioned above. The latter suggestion I need hardly pOi.nt out is in no part of the world c practical proposition nor fair 10 tne tenant. I should therefore oe most grateful if you would verify the *bove to me by Airmail, fee should prefer your home to any other in Banrain, but cannot make a oeiter offer than the above. Having seen your nouse rc-cently 1 assure you that in any case unless you are prepared to repair it, it *ill soon be little better than a rum ana kdite uninuaoitable. Prom tnat point of view my offer is to your advantage. I am ..riting to my friend Mr. J. Q. Laithwaite at the India Office about this affairma ne will I tnink assure on behalf of fihlonel Fowle the Honourable the Political Resident ana myself that if you can see your way to accent To M. Faruk hs .uire, 10/14 Cnarternouse/Htrect LQHDON. a._(Lb. ourI mmINDIA OFFICE* LONDON, 3.V.. I. private . 8 U 1 April 193t». My dear George, Hfr tn y tdantcs lor your letter of Slet torch, which I was glad to get. It has, 1 tulaic, crossed one froir, me to you. so far as we can juage at tills stage I see no likelihood whatever whatever of their abolishing the post of A.P.A. worth ruleea the same point with me when I saw him a few days ago and mentioned that uncertainty on this point was holding up construction of a house for the A.P.A. I will take to Loch about this when he turns up, as he should in the very near future. I hope this may reassure you to eotis extent. I will write again next week. I am sending this off at once so as to catch the air mail. I send tills off in haste only to sty that Captain C.A. Cole The Agency, BahreinNotes. Minute Paper. Register No. P.A SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT Dated Rec. Date. Initials. To Under Secretary Zf &lt;ca.3f Au Secretary of State... Committee i;.k IfL Under Secretary Secretary of State.... SUBJECT. SEEN POLITKDAL GOwlMI 4 JAN 1955 Previous papers Post of Assistant political Agent, Bahrein. Copy of to FOR INFORMATION. please see previous sutaission on P.Z. 7531/33, flagged below. From Colonel Fowle's present despatch it is clear that the post of Asst, political Agent, which was (4a (L^akX. (p-dr' established on a provisional basis age on the Resident 1 s recommendation and after discussion with Mr. Metcalfe during his leave in this country, has entirely justified itself. Colonel Fowle now recommends that it should be made permanent. The case is prima facie a strong one and it is to be hoped that the Government of India will agree. 0/‘ i A Villi' M' 2730 1000 4.34CONFIDENTIAL. ((TO) '3 S, x 1190-S of 1934 i 1234 1 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com. pliments to 1. j.G.Laithwaite Esquire, The India Office, London• 2. Lieut. -Colonel Gordon Loch, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (//. Demi-official letter No. ^ + 1189-S of 12th December 1934 Post oi Assistan to the Foreign Secretary to the Political Agent, Government of India. BahraLu. British Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. Dated..12th. December..1934. '0r' Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject.! , /. Confidential D.0.NO.1189-S of 1934. { 1 Q 3/t_T h§ /« Heeidency, Buehire, 12th December ,1934. Please refer to correspondence ending with Foreign and Political Department telegram : 0.1866, uateu September 3934, on the subject of the post of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. The poet wae originally sanctioned for 6 month* which expired last month, and was then in the communication referred to above sanctioned for another 6 j months, i.e. until May 1935. 2. The experience which we have had of this new post has shown that under present day conditions at Bahrain it is absolutely essential to the efficient conduct not only of the political Agency there, but of affairs at *atar and the Trucial Coast. In the last five years the importance of Bahrain, and of the volume and variety of the work of its olitical Agent has increased out of all knowledge. lharc are now multitudinous ^estions connected with Oil - the Bahrain ietroleum Company is now in full swing there, with the Civil Air Route - Bahrain is an important station on the Civil Air Route to India, with the Royal Air Force - who have recently made a considerable purchase of land there, with the Kavy - who have done likewise, with Ibn Saud - the thorny matter of transit dues for example, with the prospects of British trade - Bahrain is the largest port in the dull with the exception of Basrah and fcohammerah, with ■ ersia - the ill-treatment of Bahrainis in that country, and so forth, in addition to these special problems the .olitical Agent has to keep an aye on, and advise the Resident on the activities of the Bahrain Government« Law and Order, folice Kon'ble Mr.H.A.F. Metcalfe, Foreign secretary to the Government of # Ladia, ]inane©, /finance, etc., in addition to carrying out his own judicial duties as District and Sessions Judge, and over-seeing the routine of his office. 3 . Nor is this all. s^atar is likewise within the political area of the Political Agent and at &lt;atar Oil activities are now beginning in earnest. iurther, during the past year or so I have placed the Trucial Coast, subject of course to my general control, under the Political Agent, Bahrain, who - especially with the development of the Civil and Strategical Air Routes - is more favourably placed than any other Political Officer for visiting it. 4 . # X neea not labour the point, which is suiiiciently obvious, that it is quite impossible for the Political Agent to carry out his manifold duties indicated above without an Assistant, and the latter even during the short time the post has been in existence has proved himself very useful. when the }olitical Agent is in residence the Assistant Political Agent takes much of the routine duties which need supervision off the Political Agent’s shoulders, thus allowing the latter time for that personal contact with Arab notables which is one of the main ways by which we can keep and extend our influence at Bahrain - as elsewhere on tue ^rab Coast, when the political Agent is on tour the Assistant Political Agent holds the fort, or, alternatively, goes on to a* while the Political Agent remains at Headquarters. Loch, for instance, has just returned from a most useful and extended tour of tne Trucial Coast (in connection with air isciiities at ias anu Abu Jhabi, and with tne collection of information with regard to the Blue Line) which would have been quite impossible if Worth had not been in Bahrain to carry on during his absence. 6. /5* Thera ia anothar way too in which the Assistant iolitieal Agent serves a useful purpose. It nas always been desirable that officers serving in the trying conditions oi tne Gulf should have as much leave as is practicable, and now that the ,-vrab Coast is only 4 days from London by Air (instead of nearly as many weeks as in the old days by sea), or some 10 days by the Taurus i^x^ress, there is no reason why such officers should not go home more frequently on spells of short leave in the hot weather for 3 months or so at a time. The Persian Gulf Cadre, however, being a small one this is difficult, and sometimes impossible to arrange, since it generalo-y entails asking Government to send a relief officer from Inaia. This relief is neither easy for the Government of India to arrange nor satisfactory from m# point of view. It involves the detailing of an ©x’fieer to proceed to the Gulf at its worst season, and for such a coi^aratively short period that he is only' just beginning to become acquainted with the somewhat peculiar local conditions when it is time for him to hand over again to the regular incumbent of the post on the latter’s return from leave. In 1933, for instance, there were difficulties over rinding a relief for Dickson who had to post pone his leave until this year. 6. The same remarks apply mu tat is. mutandis to the difficulties of finding an emergency relief in the case of sickness ©f an officer on the Gulf Cadre. 7. With the creation of the post of assistant political Agent , however, the difficulties mentioned above to a large extent disappear. while it is quite is^ossiLfe tor t ; olitical Ag**rt, Bahrain, to function efficiently single-handed throughout the year, it is practicable ior a single oifieer either /either the Political agent or the assistant olitical agent to carry on for a few months during the hot weaoher when nonualiy things are fairly quiet# ftext year, for instance, it has been found possible to let Loch have his well-earned leave by arranging for the assistant oiitical Agent to act for him, thus avoiding any dislocation of tiae Gulf Cadre, or indenting on tit© Government of India for © relief officer# In a similar way by a little ringing of tne changes it will be practicable in other years to let other officers have a much needed breath of fresh air at home# B. In conclusion 1 would be grateful if the post of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, could be made permanent as soon as possible# 1 am afraid I have dealt with this matter at some length. Jky excuse must be that the main point at issues the efficient performance of political work at Bahrain, ^atar and the Truclul Coast, for which I am responsible to his bajesty's Government and the Government of India, Is of considerable importance • 1 am sending a copy of this letter to Laithw&amp;ite anc. Loch. Yours sincerely, sd.T.C.Fowle.\\sj ns Register No. P.z. ?/ ' ' ' ? 6 3505/34. Political Department. r\ Letter Telegram from Dated Rec. 19 Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. To Chairman .&amp; Under Secretary .. Secretary of ^tate... Committee. Under Secretary. Secretary c/f State... Council Copy of SUBJECT. Bahrein Order in Council 1915. G.of I. propose to grant powers of 1st Class Magistrate and Subordinate Judge (1st Class) to the Assistant Political Agent. to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY D raft telegram to G.of I. approving, tl JUN 1934 i-lL. t 4408 b 500 3.30'ED -7 *— v . CWP/AW, (57 groups) 3137. FILE COPY /* :505 ! dil)' DB CYP HER OF TB1BGRAM . I’rom (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India* Simla, 25th May, 1934. Received 25th May, 1934, 10,30 a.m. 1199. Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated to Bushire. Political Resident, Bushire, recommends grant of powers of First Class Magistrate and Subordinate Judge, First Class, to Worth, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein, we propose to confer powers under Sections 14 and 35 of Bahrein Order in Council, Sections 12 and 37 of the Code of Criminal Procedure and Sections 22 and -2 A cf t.*e bombay oivil Court Act, 1859. Do you approve?H9 v lr^ A. fv u ' f INDIA OFFICE, (^l** ' •WHITEHALL, 3.W. 1. Dear Staffora, Mr* Kereuitii Worth, of the Indian political Department, wnose passport I enclose herewith, has been appointea Assistant Political A^ent at Bahrein AjLtot A»-ce^z i is going out oy air at Uie end of thin*BWElfa* we should be grateful if the Passport Office could obtain the necessary visas (if* possible diploisatic) for him. In this connection the Political Resident has asked that, as Mr. worth will probably have to visit him at Bushire in the fairly near future, we should obtain on his passport a Persian visa valia for as long a period as possible. Could you assist us over this also? As you know, the question of Bahrein is a very disputed one as between us ana the Persians and if it is possible to get the visa without any reference to the fact that worth will be stationed at Bahrein, it Vvould probably ease matters, but on this you may care to have a wora with the Eastern Department. Yours sincerely. J. Stafford, ^sq., 0.3.K., rassport Office, S.W. i. J .Of. LAITHWAITE..2406/34. (41 words) 04307 COPY OP TELEGRAM. Prom Foreign Secretary to the Government of Foreign and Political Department. To High Commissioner for India, London. Dated New Delhi, 9th April 1934. Received 9th April 1934. 11.15 a.m. Via Eastern Cable. 266E. Your telegram dated April 4th 2930.M. Worth. Bahrein appointment has for the present been sanctioned for 6 months but question of making it permanent is under consideration. Political Agent at Bahrein is arranging for a house and has written to Y/orth by air mail giving requirements. Please inform Worth accordingly.P.Z.2406/34 (24 words) 04385 Prom To Dated Received COPY OP TELEGRAM Political Agent, Bahrein, High Commissioner for India, London. Bahrein 7th April 1934. 9th April 1934. 10.10 a.m. Via Empiradio. 69. Following for M. Worth. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein. Begins. Resident in the yw Persian Gulf may wish to visit Bushire shortly. Please get (visa for) Persia valid for long as possible. Ends. TOCKECKED.COPY OF P.Z. 1930/34. SDS/DAP. (38 words) COPY OP TELEGRAM &lt;yffi III 04217 PROM: Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, TO: High Commissioner for India, London. DATED: New Delhi, 19th March 1934. RECEIVED: 19th March 1934. 5 p.m. Via Eastern Cahle. M. 203. Please inform Worth, Political Department that he will he required to join appointment APA Bahrein end of April. This will amount to compulsory recall from leave. Suggest he should come hy air so that he enjoys as much leave as possible. Much regret inconvenience to Worth.^arsonal ^eeidfr cy, Bushire, the ^nd 1?ebruaiy 1934 On the subject of the 'aropoeed 'ooet of ,V 3 Blstant Political Apreht, Bahrain. If Firarce T 5 ?t&gt;ve 8 sticlcy over -die pi'cposal, developments in connection with Oil at Qa*ar nay provide some ’powder and shot’. Whatever +he exact turn of events may he ^ thinlc our reBnonsihil itieo there will materially increase, and the India Office contemplate the coneibility of a ’oli^icnl A^ent for that area. If '‘he nor,t of Assistant Political A*?ent, Bahrain, in created there would not^be any need for this Political A#?ent as the Assistant Political Afrerrt, Bahrain, 8&gt;iould be able to supervise Qatar by nayiry it frequent visile. I sun sending a cony of ttis letter to La ithwai t e. I think fours sincerely. sd 0 M .G.Bowie. ,T *he Hon’ble Mr.H. A.B.Metcalfe ,C. 0.1. , n tv. if^r.nlie 34 Confidential GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Deparime’^t 1934 EXPRESS LETTER &lt;xS [A 7 , B.—This is a?? ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraph) expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is uvrded and signed as if it had been so despatched^ From Resident Bufihi re* - Government of India, Hen &gt;elhi# Peneated India Office, London* Na ‘ 1923-n Of 10 33. Dated 16th riecer-iber BTTB JEG*?' : As distant Political Agent for ^ihrair • Vy*?/ ify desT&gt;atch Ho* 1779 -r&gt; dated 30tji October 1933. / * I enclose cony of an Express Letter Ko.0/579-3/8 dated the 10th Lecemb^r 1933 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, which shows conclusively how much 1 is work has increased of late# (sd#) ^.C.^owle, Lt.-Colon el, Political Pesident in the Persian Gulf. ATTBSTTfl). for Secretary to the in the Persian Gulf. r-^eeldent H 9i DCFP—1565S&amp;P—(M*1821)—27 9-32—2^0,000.Confidential. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, EXPRESS LETTER [N* B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent hy post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sw'e time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Fftosi Political Bahrain. To Resident Bushire. ■ Vo * C/bV9-3/«. THei 10th December J3 h: lour letter 1779-2 October 30th,1933. Assistant Political Agent for Bahrain. 3. The decision of The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited to extract 700 tons of oil a day by July 1st,1934,means an immense increase in their activities and consequent increase in the work of the Political Agent and his office. Indeed,the increase of work connected with the Company had,even before their decision to expand rapidly,made itself lelt. Almost all the Bahrain Petroleum Company correspondence is kept in my Confidential Office and the figures of the confidential Office of inward and outward communications support my statement (2) DCFP—\505S&amp;P—(M-1821)—27 9-32—2,50,000.2- Year. Inward Nos: Outward Nos: 1931. 133 196 1932. 253 362 1933 (to ?th December) . 570 947 I would,however,emphasise that figures of correspondence do not give an ade^ate idea of the demands on the time of the Political Agent and his office by an institution such as a growing Oil Company. Sd/- G.Loch. Lieut-Colonel. Political iigent,Eahrain.Notes. 12 Minute Paper. Register No. P.Z 7f3l (hi**, hi SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Dated 19 . Rec. Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary j Secretary of State... Committee 2 . /1 . /&lt;f 1 - :T Persian Gulf. proposed appointment of additional political officer as assistant Political Agent, Bahrein. Under Secretary Secretary of State... Copy of to FOR INFORMATION. Colonel Fowled letter below is to some extent the result of discussions during his recent leave. It is self-explanatory and calls for no very detailed comment. Given the constantly growing Importance of the Gulf, and tne increase in the amount of urgent work to he dealt with, the change in tie situation resulting from the coming into being of the Persian Navy and the active development of oil in Bahrein and its not improbable development in (Hasa, it is more and more difficult to leave the u-ulf agencies, as was possible in the past, in the charge of a Previous Papers :— Sub-Assistant surgeon or the like, during the ud ssnce roI'7H — FoTTt ica.1 j^gent,, ana a strong case is afforded for proviaing the Resident 5041 2000 with/ tEBN POLITICAL COMMITTBlE 2 0 DEC 103&amp;'- a - &lt;L. with a rather larger reserve on which he can fall hack if necessary. As Colonel Fowle points out, there is the further argument that the creation of an additional post at this stage will result in increasing the number of officers at the uisposal of the Government of India with some Gulf experience. 2. As matters stand, the/Office irT^f his appointment is agreed to, will he a charge on Indian revenues. The Government of India may well feel that, having regard to the^Imperial advanced nature of the arguments/by the Political Resident, they might claim some contribution in respect of him. This point was discussed with Colonel Powle and Kir. Metcalfe, but it was thought on the whole better tnat trie Resident should put up his proposals with out raising tne financial point, leaving it to the Government of India to raise it if they thought fit. We might conceivably be able to get some contribution towards the cost of an officer such as the present from the Treasury, but to raise 6 irt0Ts likely to involve not inconsiderable delay in a decision, unless it can be regarded asjbeing raised without prejudice to the general question of the distribution of Diplomatic and Consular Expenditure in the Persian Gulf. r\ 133 37- ** 7/e will await the G. of I.’s recommendation, bat prima facie I agree that it would be wiser not to raise the question of a contribution from the Treasury. The Persian Gulf.Sheikhdoms ! i are under the control of the G. of I. as regards administration, and if the latter suggest sharing the expenditure, it will tend towards reopening the question of control. l\vCONFIDENTIAL. No. 1780-S of 1933. 5' 3 / The Hon’l?fe the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to HIb Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment m/ British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 3 0 ct * e r » 3 * Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Political Resident’s despatch N 0 .1779~S dated the 30th October 1933, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India • Creation of a nevr appointment of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.COH^ITJW^IAI. HB.1779-S of 1933. British ‘^ssidercy A Connulats-General, BUr?KIBB f the 30th October, 1933. 'Tran - Hon’hie Lieut .-Colonel ”*.C.?o^le, C. Political Resident in the 'eraian Oulf, To - ’’’he 'toTeim Secretary to the ao’r-rnwent of India, Hew ^elhi. Sir, After discussion with Colonel Loch, Political Apent, Bahrain, I have the honour to nake the eupst estlon that an extra officer should he added to the cadre of the Political O^fice^s in the n ersiar Cmlf hy the creation of a new appoint ment of ABsistant hlitical Airent, Bahrain, ?. r *he arfmments in favour of this miff-eotion are as follows. (a) It is unnecessary for me to emohaaiBe the fact that at Bahrain,as, indeed, all over the Gulf, the work has much inc-eaaed of late, both in volume and importance, in connection with such quest!one ae the Iraoerlal air ~oute, Oil, commercial and political relations with Baudi Arabia, and so forth, {atar likewise comes under the oil ti cal Affent, Bahrain, and, with the commencement there o** oil exploration by +he Anfflo- 7 erni an Oil Company, is becoming of increasing interest to us. In addition, the 'racial Coast, by reason of the openinff of the air port at Gharjah, has acquired a special importance, and in order to facilitate(tTn 73 / a doss touch with It X have, ae I Informed the Government of India uorae tine a^o in another connection, placed the '’racial Coast unde’' the charge of the ’o i ical tren', Bahrain, nho can in these days visit it easily and quickly hy air. At Bahrain, therefore, there are continually arising problems which need the careful and ue'-sonal con sideration of the Political Vrent. 1’his is all the wore the cnee since so much of the actual work has to be done by negotiation with the Arab Bhaikhs and Notables, with whom the personal touch, accessibility, and the opportunity of beine- granted long Interviews, counts so much. In the interests of Government the Political Agent should be able to devote a considera'le part of his time to f hese various problems, manv of which raise complex and serious Issues. Hu oh consideration , however, is at present impossible, since there is a lar#*e volume of routine *ork which mist be done and whicfri at least should be supervised by an officer, the Indian Assistant bein* fully engayed day in and day out in his court, I would add that a *reat proportion of the trade of *Bahrain is with India, and Bahrain is the headquarters of numerous Indian firms, whose affairs (especially their civil suits) take up a considerable time. It is hoped that the discovery of Oil fields in Bahrain, and possibly of others elsewhere, will lead to an increase in thin trade and to the development of other openings for Indian wares. But this a&lt;min demands time from the ^lifical Ajjrentthere is a utrorm case for the appointment su^rested. r ^here are, however # other ar^mmente in favour of it, (b) At present the Oulf cadre of officers is sufficient to carry on provided that no casualties occur and no officer wishes to proceed on short leave. Casualties in the way of sicknesn do, of course, occur in a climate like that of the Oulf, and officers, either for this or for other reasons # do wish to take short leave, ^‘Tie recent case of Colonel ^iekson, who wished to ??o on leave, but *ho could not be replaced, is one in point. Personally I think it would be an excellent thinp* if officers in the (hiIf could proceed to TSngland on short leave in the hot weather, and this now is quite practicable frosi the tine point of view, since by air it taken no longer to travel from Bush!re, for instance, or Kuwait to London than it does from these pos*b by steamer to Karachi. 'he officers concerned would benefit not only by a change of climate, but equally by the mental tonic which even a short stay at home provides, while their presence in ^Jngland would give the Departments interested in the Oulf an opportunity of personal contact and dis cussion, ^o meet a temporary absence from a Gulf post it is not practicable to send an officer from India, who normally would only become thoroughly liil fait with local condit ions in the fhilf by the time the permanent incumbent would be due to return, ^ith an extra officer as Assistant Political \gent, Bahrain, however, it would be quite possible^ to meet any contingencies from within the Gulf cadre, (o) A third argument in favour of my suggestion is that the post of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, would provide an excellent opportunity for junior Political Officento obtain experience of the Gulf - a consideration ehich has *eifrht bavin# regard to the small number of officers in the ’olitioal Department *ho a + present possess wmh exnerience. I am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty’s Secretary of Gtate for India, I have the honour to be # Sir, Tour moat obedient servant, (Bgd.J 'f. C. Fovfle, Li eut.-Colone1, Political ^.esiden* in the Persian (Julf.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000cf_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3645</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000cf</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3645</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/69 'Bahrain: appointment of an Assistant Political Agent'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-25T10:50:38</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (132 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing)commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 134; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-134; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns recruitment of Assistant Political Agents at the Bahrain Political Agency, and conferment of Magisterial and Judicial powers.The file covers:creation of a new post of Assistant Political Agent, due to the increase of work for the development of oil fields, 1933appointment of R D Metcalfe as Assistant Political Agent, 1935. Conferment of Magisterial powersappointment of Khan Bahadur Abdul Haiy El Hashni as Indian Assistant Political Agent, 1936. Conferment of Judicial powersappointment of A C Stewart as Assistant Political Agent, 1937. Conferment of Magisterial and Judicial powersappointment of B L M Tomlinson as Assistant Political Agent, 1937. Conferment of Magisterial powersappointment of Dr S M Siddiq as Indian Assistant Political Agent, in 1937 and 1938. Conferment of Judicial powersappointment of A C Galloway as Assistant Political Agent, 1937. Conferment of Magisterial and Judicial powersappointment of R E R Bird as Assistant Political Agent, in 1938 and 1945. Conferment of Magisterial and Judicial powersappointment of J B Howes as Assistant Political Agent, 1938. Conferment of Judicial powersappointment of R I Hallows as Assistant Political Agent, 1939. Conferment of Judicial powersappointment of Khan Sahib Mirza Ismail Barduli as Indian Assistant Political Agent, 1940. Conferment of Judicial powersappointment of Maurice Patrick O'Connor Tandy as Assistant Political Agent, 1943. Conferment of Judicial powersappointment of R M Hadow as Assistant Political Agent, 1944. Conferment of Judicial powersappointment of Mohammed Abdul Hafiz as officiating Indian Assistant Political Agent, 1945. Conferment of Judicial powersappointment of H D H Rance as Assistant Political Agent, 1946. Conferment of Judicial powersappointment of J E H Hudson as Assistant Political Agent, in 1946 and 1948. Conferment of Judicial powersappointment of G N Jackson as Assistant Political Agent, 1947. Conferment of Judicial powers.The file is composed of correspondence between the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, the Foreign Office, the India Office, the Government of India, the Secretary of State for India, and the Office of the High Commissioner for India.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner of India to the United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Recruitment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000cf#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>