<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00010d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T05:25:00.154Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">6749 INL&gt;uXcO With the Compliments of the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs © \$A&amp; S ' Foreign Office, &lt;l4L &lt; zflfto4 , 1941 • CC&lt;h»w&lt;nMi)»*U^ 33592British Embassy, Jedda. No.161/7/49 23rd March 1949 3ir f VYith reference to your letter No.PS 55/5 of the 7th March, 1949# I am directed by His Majesty’s Ambassador to thank you for your kind offer of a 36 foot open- decked Naval Pinnace and to inform you that it is gratefully accepted. It is presumed that a Pinnace of this type will not draw more than 2’ 6”, and that'this craft is sea- wort y and in no need of repairs, as no repairs can be done here, nor can spare parts be found. Would you be good enough to inform this Embassy in due course of the date on which it can be expected at Jedda and whether H.M. Shin or R P yal Fleet Auxiliary which bring it, can also take the Embassy’s own launch the whole, or part of, the way to the Royal Naval Dock yard at Malta to undergo the urgent overhaul which must be finished before about the begin ning of June. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, M./;. EHROCK. Captain C.D. Arbuthnot, Royal Navy , Royal Naval Liaison Officer, V RT SAID. . ,/© FOREIGN OFFICE, 1 7, Carlton House Terrace, 28 th I larch, 1949* S.W.l. (XA0510/250(^/49)) l fV 3 &amp;L ,f ' 1 Dear Crook There is a launch at our Embassy in Jedda, which, in the past was used by the former Government of India Vice-Consul. 37^ the costs of its maintenance and operation were charged to the former Government of India, who also contributed 37a' s original cost of purchase. Joint ownership of the launch is not a satisfactory arrangement now that the Pakistan and Indian Governments have their own representatives in Jedda, and we wish to come to some arrangement with the Indians so that full ownership of the launch is secured for His Majesty's Government and for the Malayan Coverrsnent, which at present owns a quarter of it. The craft is in need of an overhaul, and we are arranging to send it to the Naval Dockyard at Malta, for inspection and repair. We propose to get the Admiralty experts there to value it, and to offer to the Indians 37|/J of the valuation. If you deem it to be necessary will you please ascertain whether this basis of settlement is agreeable to the Governments of India and Pakistan. I assume that this former Government of India asset at Jedda should be dealt with in the same way as other movable properties the original cost of which was shared between the former Government of India and His Majesty's Covernnent in moieties. I am sending a copy of this letter to His Majesty's Ambassador at Jedda who copied his despatch No. 47 of the 6th March 1949j paragraph 4 of which deals with the launch, to the United Kingdom High Commissioners at New Delhi and Karachi. Yours sincerely. K.R. Crook, Esq, (T. Willson) Commonwealth Relations Office.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00010d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3707</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00010d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3707</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/118(8) 'Embassy launch at Jedda. Arrangement for ownership'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-25T22:39:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (7 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file. There are notes at the beginning of the file, on folio 2. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file; they give a brief description of the correspondence with a reference number, which refers back to that correspondence in the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 9; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the ownership of the launch at the British Embassy at Jedda, which could have been claimed by the Government of India and the Government of Pakistan.The file contains correspondence between the British Embassy at Jedda, the Foreign Office and the Commonwealth Relations Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Partition</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commonwealth Relations Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Embassy in Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Launches</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00010d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>