<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000085_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-06T12:25:19.762Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">^R|uv rxtracts iron Persian Gulf r 'cr Trade Bureau Report No. 13. A. PERSIA. IRA C C . Bi HRI Ii'j :ui /-i. I umerous letters and tele.^raras seen in the Bureau the period under report ; Iso confirm that merchan Persia were ; ttemptin^ to bring quantities of sugar India to Dubai or I useet first e nd then to tranship to Persie.. ' bdulie Yazcani end ' r ohd. /min of r ubei to be the principal inter lediaries at Dubai in this i letter deted 6-l-4i’from Pharan / rdeshir He ?hi h Karachi to Hr. /bdulla Yazdani, Rubei country crafts which were loaded with during s in from them a ppec r trade. t. referred to two sugar and destined for a port in Omen. The writer stated that after the Customs formalities in Oman were concluded the crafts were to be sent on with their lo^ds to Bunder /bbas. r fhe writer with sugar^ which had been sent to Dubai for transhipment t o Bund er /bba s. (c /s export of rice f are trying to evade Dubai writing to Da the addressee to wr shipped to Dubai wa then be able to get merchants in Persia Shaikh of Dubai. I- - v n . ^ ■ : - j ;o P m- . - oj ‘ J be i r-on Dubai has been prohibited, merchants this prohibition. Ibrahim TT . Galadari, had el 'Yrzook, Karachi, on 14-4-42 asked ite a letter to him saying thft the rice s for transhipment. The writer would. * permission to sell the commodity to by producing the letter before the { ' r- 4- s me Y - rom interceptions in the Bureau as well as from a summary (No.115) ast Intelligence Centre It appears that merchants seen recently of the ' T iddle Fast intelligence Centre it appears from Basrah are trying to buy all piecegoods and textiles they and that good quantities of by firms can find in Bahrain end Dubai, buffalo and cow hides are being purchased in Baghdad in Turkey in exchange for Turkish soap. (c) Dice and wheat fmour - BPirain.: per country craft f ’'-imru - n extract fro i -tetter e a ted from Eatanchand Dipchahd Karani, Bahrain, to Thakar Karson, Cutch 'fandvi, is given below :- 19-4-42 Ha r Ira m 7 O ~ ^ ^ • ’’There are veiY r good prospects for trade here, please ship to us in country crafts from Cutch 'Hncvi, rice or who; t flour, as much as you can If you wish to send the goods on your please mark them P.D. so that they can to an outsider. YJe can get a. very good for goods marked r .D. ?T account be sold price Co tr -purchases from Dubai - In a letter dated 15---42 /bdulrphnan Fakhroo, Bahrain informed T ' 0 hd. Yusuf Fakhroo c/o Dahad arzook, Karachi that as he was unable to buy tea locally he had sent his brother li to Dubai to buy at least 100 boxes of tea from there. -- ... Alghanim, Karachi, in his letters dated 20---42 advised eight merchants in Kuwait end Dubr i to send him telegrc is at his expense under different names ordering shipments of large quantities of rice, v/heat flour, sugar, etc. so that he might satisfy the authorities in India on production of those telegrams and obtain export permits for the quantities mentioned therein.3**“*™'' — v CD 7' Extract from Persian Gulf T .7ar Trade Bureau Report No.14. under report shov; that efforts were still being made by i erchants to send sugcr from India to Rubai for re-export to Persia. In this connection the following telegra ' dated 8-5-42 from Eartoshty :c Sons, Bombay, to Abdulla Y; zd••: I, pub; i, r har jah is of interest 'Ship remaining Bushire sugar imme&lt; lately by vessel /gain shipped 502 bags mark TFRJH Fifty mark TZ Documents sent air Arrange shipment Bunderabbas If future shipment possible wire we- will help you / gain.' (P.ef: Report No.IS pa - e 1). On the other hand many letters from merchants in Rubai referred to the prohibition imposed by the Rubai Government on the export of tea and sugar. Some stated that export would be pernitted once more by the Government on payment of ; fairly heavy tax on the goods. This prospect appeared to cause them no dismay as profits were said to be extremely large in the sugar trade, ''ost of the letters complained bitterly that if the export gone, as all merchants then lived only for Abe n -export Some suggested setting up business in Bombay instea^d^HTtfr the most part they &lt;p^e; red confident that the prohibition would either be set aside, or evaded, in some fashion. very recent interception states that though the export/pi ohibition on sugar export by special permit and on payment of heavy duty. it is gathered from the same interception that thousands of bars of sugar are lyir,_ in the ' erchant T s _odowns and thousands of bags a re on the wa y to Rubai. cey _ . . na f - R ; in - The fol-Owii; c . _xt: cts from the interceptions seen in the Bureau refer to panicky conditions in Bahrain - (i) . xtra ct froi a letter d ; t f ' 17-^- -^ f: o : ohd, Riddiq, c/ P . . 0 - » ^ CQv-^td^Jyu^ Be ^ . 1 ., i . bdu l I~: - g , . Fi - '/ few days back the Government of Bahrain made an announcement that Bahrain was in danger and warned the people to _o and live in the gardens outside the city. This announcement has caused great panic among the people. Nany Indians a -e ready to leave by the steamer 'Barman' which is expected to £ rrive here soon. ’ T ost of the Indian employees of the Oil Companies are resigning their jobs and goin_ to their native places'. (ii) /xtra.ct fi o-'. i lett • i; date'/ :./. e ^ . . ~ A - . ... ■ 1. m .r. .m li - 'The Government of Bahrain have issued a circular t....at this place (Bahrain) is now in the War zone. Those who wish to leave this place should do so now. There is c danger of air raids. People should go and live in the gardens etc. /bout 15-20 employees of the Company have resigned. people are sending away their families on the steamer-' that is due to sail on the 22nd.(Ill) rxtrfc.ct fron c: .L-tter doted g-f—:L frori _ ,^ ,^ 2 . hri in to ^Lh^-obhci ^id; husc in rhL.i.crcV/oiL. f PQ.:bc.v ;- 'The situ: tion here (Bchr^in) is getting _'ro bed to worse. There is no business at all and the market is getting lower and lower every day due to the ban on export from Bahrain, ^oofs of all the houses in the hie rket have been removed (by Governments and owing to the terrible heat, no customers or merchants visit the rket. r,o not send any oocs at present because we are going to reduce our business, despatch our 'i'lvri s balance oods to Sidhpur fror Bombay, '.'e are expectin, an order fro Covernrent to leave Bahrain at any time, i t present Government is building cottages outside Bahrain (nearby villc ges'' . Extract from Persian Gulf r Jar Trade Bureau report ITo.313. (c) (ii). T xport from India via rubai. - n the previous Report (Go.Id) reference was riE de to the i position by the Shaikh of Rubai of a duty of .10 per bag of sugar re-exported to Persic . Interceptions seen during the period under review confirm that restrictions have also been imposed on export of tea from Rubai. In this connection the following extract is of interest letter da ted 17-5-42 from ' 11 Fkbar Fezapoor Lari R 3ros_. , nubai. to Trane ^ £ astan Tracing Co.. Karachi; - 'The export of commodities to Persia and Iraq is prohibited from Rubai but sugar and tea are under control The Government is charging a Customs Export Duty of m.10 per bag of sugar and .5 for each case of tea. The Government is considering keeping in Customs bond the articles of foodstuff End cloth and instituting permit system for export thereof. We have already informed you that Rubai is not a big market but that all the goods received in Rubai are intended for Iraq and Persia.” 'h .qeelie-neous foodstuffs - iree , . lu ppyt into Persia The following is an extract from a letter dated 17-5-42 written from Lingah to a merchant in Karachi ity/e are pleased to inform you the t an order has been received' from Tehran Customs permitting free import of all food supplies. This, of course, is a great boon. It is, however, regrettable that export from Rubai is prohibited.” (a) mov:.m:mut oil - / letter dated 1 )-5-42, from G orb hand as Rarandas, Bombay, to . odul mziz y.li /.I Basse n, Bahrain, contained two invoices covering the despatch of 1500 tons of cement valued at ...12 / ,500 and 20 barrels oi groundnut oil valued at .2,802. fb) Gur..esGea expoie_ cQnarQ_L evas-uon - p leater dated 18-5-42 from Mohd. ; T a'rzook. Karachi* to Abdul iz li Bess am. p; hvain shows how Ar^h TH Tnbi^ trvincr to cr^t. larger quota for e'vort. The following is an interesting extract:- ”The Customs4 cD I 'Jr 'The Customs suthorities here press for the production of the orders received by merchants for exports. Your orders, therefore, should be continuous in every letter for shipment of 5, DO, 10 , 'DO or £0,000 so that vre - ay present*then to the Customs and ship whttever is permitted. u ice cnc t d .j t.—•. —j——i-i- ■ - 1 . —-» -r—1 n '' - . r-, . r- T/'-V'i ' •» 'f' r ^ ' letter dated 18-5-41. from Fahad T 'arzook, Karachi to Mohc. -usuf Fakhroo, Bahrain, revea-S that tne writer na.s yc., ■ ! ■ bae-s of rice and 4,600 bags of ; tta awaitiiy several ports e g. Kuwait, 1 &gt; bar, Sur, rtc. Extracts from Persian Gulf ,,! ar Trade Bureau Report No &gt; 17/ 2(c) tils . - / letter dated 4-5- 1 froa . &amp; F.H. Lari 1 Co., Bor:-bay, H.B.H. 'nshiri, Bushire, to x n n recuests addressees to ship 10o bags -iou: c j. ! ^ bags a^n.i -s up‘to rubai at least. The writer is ready to arrange trans port fro Tube i to Busnire comtiy c ra.s-oS. (f) -ugar aiK tea — (i'* . ai'. c oe aiici — . he o. - -&gt;~ these co imodities in Persia continuec steom s e o. •' . Piiafons d Co. of morba.y wrote to Goa and stated that tney were interested in exporting sugar fhon _»a .o a. sia. L g _ some letters there were suggestions that tea and sugar migho be shipped to Persia from ports in the Indian 'tates ana 110:1 j?r s -h Africa, mhe intensity of demand for these gooes may oe ! u 'ad fro a letter dated 7-4-42 f] on f. ^-l^h ri, r ]ehr mi iLrGZc. Por Dcy — T, _. w&amp;s c^i lIig poi- ^ ± u t o — ^ y for further consignment (2000 bags) of suga.. h ut youi - -y- -ran, stating that the season of country craft would^end by the end of March, prevented me to do so. The other day i _ cabled you for 500 tons of Indian sugar I want you to bear in mind this point am a t ■ ria., ever you find any commodity such as sugar, tea, coffee or spices in a large scale and ready for sale please cable me 1 mediately, particularly sugar. Or even i- you have any means to et it from Africa or Mauritius either reaay m Bombay bond or direct in tranship via Bombay for Bunder ,bbas Rubai, Kuwait or Bahrain.’ 1 2(r''s 8ocp. - From interceptions seen recently it is noticed thetTairge quantities of soap are being exported from Bombay by steamer and country craft to raq and otner destinations up the Gulf. Ganera 1 Cone — tions ; — n. ^^ m -n—-• — appears from many interceptions seen in the Bureau that there is a shortage of food stuffs, particularly atta, barley, etc. m Bahrain. The following extract fro:-, a let per da pec. 83-4-4a from Khans ah eb ; be. ul Hus a. in &amp; Bros., Bahrain to Hcba.tnl-a &amp; Bros., Bombay, explains in brief the posaIron:- tr/t present it is very difficult to get flour over hen . Bread is unobtainable. In the last boat 300 bags Ox flour were received, out of which, accorain^ to^Govern ment regulations only one to two {ojL pouncs are allowed for household consumption. All the bakeries are being closed. God knows whet ier ilour v.a be oooamable in the future or not. The market is quite unsteady present. T?.DUBi.1. Suf-:gr. teo. etc :- Lc-rge imports bv coiJLntrv cr&amp;fts .- In a letter dated £3-5-4^ Iron , .K.H.--'. /-bbas, f-ubai, to ; . Abbas, Bombay, the writer informed addressee th; t 5 or 6 country crafts with cargo of sugar, tee, and pepper from Bombay and Karachi arrived at Bubal on 23-5-42 and nearly 4000 bags of sugar were among the cargo. It is also gathered from the same letter that many more country crafts were on their way to arrive. ddd. . r n . : - . Extracts from Persian Gulf War Trade Bureau Report Wo.19. 1(a) Su. fcr and tec - The market for sugar and tea con tinued to be active in Persia and considerable quantities were despatched from India, m; inly be sea. Several letters referred to the flourishing trade in Bunder /bbas due to goods being forwarded from Bubal. Sugar was said to be bought in Indie, for .22 to .27 per ba g and sold for .88 to .90 in Rubai . nd merchants were authorising their agents in India to btty at 2CT' higher than the current rate, as they were confident of a king e good profit out of the sale of this commodity in Persia. The price at Bunder /bbas is said to be fluctuating between 1740 and 1850 riels ( .178 and .189) per bag . (a) General c on., it on s - S atisfectorv fooc situation - letter dated 31-5-42 from B.S. T, *adhok, B*. .P.C.O., Bahrain to Dr. E.P. Khama, Lahore referred, to the satisfactory food situation in Bahrain. The following is an extract:- 'Yet on the whole the condition regarding food is satisfactory compared to other places as we hear, food control department has managed the affair in excellent manner, otherwise the public would have a great deal at the hands of the hoarders and the shopkeepers.' very The an suffered crooked (b) ; i h'- .r - T ^ : i .' - fo w 1 - - —. K: c.T • - letter dated 25-5-42 from the Bahrain Petroleum Co., Ltd., Behr£in to B.J. Hanna, 130 Fast 43rd Ltreet, 'e York refers to the planning of a scheme for the destruction of thw Bahrain Oil Plants in case of a successful invasion by the enemy. Extracts from Persian Gulf War Trade Bureau Report , .Pllim . 1(c) (ii). Su f -c r via Bubal and Bharin ^R^ahrc irE - recent interceptions it appears that attempts are still made to export sugar from India to Persia., via rubai and Bahrain. In this connection the following two extracts interest:- (i) ;:t-: ct //‘O' c 1 tt' i rg t-c 13-8- .;-. Rro r ~: . ti gros . Bombay to T ~ / '.T~ .3 . i ^■a.ic.ooiii . Puba.i - 'This week about 251 bags of sugar will be shipped to you and hope you will take the delivery and ship same by any means to Hessrs. Reherji, Bunder /bbas.' Rmtim ct from a 1 tt' . ■: ' ti ■ -6- fi o. ~L;itam-soa s Corporation. Bombay to Y/s Hakim B Co.. Tehran: 'As to our information, some of the Iranian Importers purchased here goods, and exported them to Bharin, end we under_ stand that from Bharin they have transshipped or imported the Ho.20. Prom being are of(i) - 6 - lo the su ;ar to Iran. Perhaps this nil! be the reason why you 1 onderec ho\ v/e can not export su y r to Ir; n, while the other exporters did it. The direct export of sugar to Iran from Bombay is impossible, in spite of all our interventions, when you could arrange the import of su ;ar to Bharin, then wc could export su ar fro:- ' here, the stock of Java sugar is very sma11, and therefore the prices today are about .17 to .38 per cwt.' (iii) r n ar ■ co I/r • from . xric; - In a teleyra dated. 16-6-41 to filsizian Inc., 'ew York, Yamazie Bros., Bombay asked for 5000 tons Cuban sugar and 200 tons coffee to be shipped, to Bushire’in July or iugust. vonthiy cuota for Pubai i ..nselv cxceecs re-ui: ants - The following extract from a letter dated 18-6-1942 from La tiff, Dubai to dbdul jalil Sc ibdullat if i, Bombay, explains the position:- TT I don’t suppose that to get a quota for Dubai should be difficult. Because, from the quantity which the merchants imported openly ';&gt;« C.ov i._ .a. fixed the monthly ' Y' for Dubai which immensely exceeds the requirements T’ - ''olio’ - v is the .c:r*'-_ v _uota fi'°d n- tb ovi -r ' nt for Dubai excluein_ piecegoods which has a separate quantity. Dice of different varieties DaJOO . s; c cff• 550 b; s; su : r jOj ba c; tea 297 c? ses; flour 2 90 b^ s; wheat 1500 bags. In a case like this when such a huge qu ntity is allowed to be exported fro: India to Dubai, the quota system becomes meaningless. During these 10/1.- c • ys over 8000 bags have been exported to Bunder . bbas and some to Dushir- .” extracts from Persian Gulf War Trade Bureau Deport r 6.22. /&gt; pprct ' . ii - - -L- . i . demand for pieeegoods in Persia continued, strong. In a letter dated 26-6-42 to Masoodyah Co., Karachi, Sherkate Sahaui Tejar? ti Khorzistsn, 'hwaz, inf or] ' :i d the . dcr ssees that other chants, particulc T ly the 5 The writers inti..ated th^ t they were interested in Indian * nd Japan' sc cotton• piece oods a'd also in silk and artificial silk cloth and a si .G the addressees to obtain export permit for piecegoods to the value of 2.5,00,099. Another letter dated 5-6-42 from K.E. Ispahan i, Khiabf.n Yonirich, T ehr,;- • , apply in. for nri export license for cotton goods (valued &lt;t rupees one If kh or over) to be forwa rded to Persia during the fiscal year 1942-45, via Gulf Ports or Nokkiendi. (O reported that s.s (i) sugar to Dubai letters from many merchants referred to their consignments £' on this ship b ing fo. re-ship ent to Bunder bbas, Sharjah and Dushir c and sometimes to such inland destinations as Yezd. in £ letter dated 29-6-4o rtoshty pons. Do bay, informed 'y'd All Golshani, Bushire that 251 bags of Java sugar had been shipped to ,T ./.R. Yousof Khoori of Dubai with instructions that the consignment be transhipped to the addressee in Bushire. The firm of Damanmal Iserdes is reported to be making ''ood profit out of this business. In a letter the Dubai partner ofr. 1 , c.r wo ? : 5 i■ V--: :v t;■ - . tt pt_s r ■ £ _so oein.; mc.de to export sugar Trucial 0 an) • In this coni.:-o .ion the iol^o 1 in xtract f: o a letter dated 5-7-42 from Fahad Marzook, Karachi, to Ebrahim Yusuf J e s d' h, K&amp;tar, vi e P e m e in is of r: it or o s t: - T, /s re ards your se le of 100 begs of sugar to i Izunaidi @ *95 (per b: ;) foi re-expo, t by hi..; to Khessanshahr, you have re? lly made a iiistake. could be exported to Khassc: she hr \.e could entrust you to export it on our Ecco nt bccaust, e s you mst mow the rate there is about .100 per bi . 'Iren you lmei r that you could pay to the Shaikh an export duty of .5 per bag and that the conveyance would cost about only, vi . e total expense of .If only, then ..hat w: s the good of this sale? The rate at Dubai will shortly go up to Pi. 100 per bag as sugar is almost non-existent in India now.” . o P -: ; 1 ' .-!■ : : - h-' shortage of rice and flour in DahrEin was mentioned in the last report. Various interceptions seen recently in the Bureau indicate theb the position became more serious in the beginning of July. In this connection the following extract from a letter d? ted i-7-4a from the British Indie Steam !Taviga tion r o. Ltd., Bahrain, to . On Ins r sc., o/o ‘Packinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co., Karachi, is of interest:- ”BelgrE.ve, the /dviser to the Bahrain Government, has just been in to see me regarding shipments of rice and flour for Bahrain arb has asked, in view of the fact hat for some time past very little rice or flour has been coming here for some reason or otbe: which the Coverment cannot fathoi , but which I ima ine he s so: .ethin- to ( O with the system of issuin; export permits in Indie, whether tekinnons are in a position to purchase i nc^ship rice and flour to Bahrain on account of the Bahrain government. Stocks of both commodities are very low at present, in fact, there is practically no flour, and I should be rat nil i_ you would let c know as soon as possible whether you are interested in this, and if so, what quantities you would be able to ship monthly.' (a ) T T :w.s c wc -'ubes want w m T 'ubr - - / s \ r dhavc: s 'ordhan- das Parpie, Dubai, in tbu.ir letter dated 28-6-4L to / s Lilaram Kewahain, Kharadhar, Karachi, wanted to know per return post whether the addressees could supply them rubber tyres and tubes of any manufacturers in India of various sizes for lorries. The writers also requested the addressees to forward a price list c.s they hoped to place a bi order for these articles with the Indian firm. (b) Bo us orders - Interceptions have bean s■ -&lt;'r. in the Bureau show in instmees of bogus orders placed by 'ubai firms with Indian fir; s with a vie to helpin the latter to secure large export quotas. In letters dated 3-7-42 jbdul Rahman,_ ~’al; knag, Dubai, enclosed orders for shipment of the following articles from Karachi (i) Coders placer with Bond, li Doha. Das hid, Bastc.ki, Karachi - rice 1500 bags, flour 900 bags, wheat 500 bars, sugar 300 bags, soap 100 boxes, silk goods 100 bundles, vegetable ghee 1000 tins. (ii) Orders placed with M.M. Sharif, Karachi - rice 1000 bags, flour 450 bags, sugar 300 bags, wheat 500 bags, soap 100 bexea cases, vegetable ghee 1000 tins, silk cloth 70 bundles, tea (Ceylon) 100 cases, peppermint 20 cases.Extract from Persian Gulf ' ar Trade Bureau Report uo.la. (iii) _ ■ . - 'a ' 1 •ctivitles C a.'Dle and 'Pireless Coi.ii--e.nics - In a cover dated 30-5-12 to the officer-in-Charge, Cable u ' ire Its.: Ltr ., T uscat, Cc.ble cc ire less Ltd. Karachi, enclose inter alia confidential co^jies oi their Head C:~ice services K/KS Larch and B/''! May as follows:- nan,, ’fey 1942. i;K562/C. MD CC Coys Impire Stns Via Cable only 285 rUK M/Ln to Mote Bee l ore evidence available amen coies Ml &amp;ns invade empire and other areas to our det-r 1- ment given in recent ancn publicatns Mn ^1 bring notice authties wen opportune x telegraph and telephone age ior Feb 1942 printed article headed quote radiotel carriers start widescale cct expansn unquote article states ancn radiotel carriers be an last ,onth ‘eel effects cessati-on of comron with continental Europe and pacific points and so moved cuickli to extend their facilities with double ain providing adequate links ' ith USA and of r aking up i^or a owe of lost business x chief step was taken by ' 0/. and acx.a, seeking authty federal conn ns commission for inauguatn radio cats, to all imptnt British and Dutch colonies and other points x for RC/. this invled authorisation for ccts with Iran India S /fee Burma Fms New ^Ind B. Guiana and Bda x for Mackay it invlvd ccts with Turkey Syria Fgput Java Siberia Goldcoast Gambia Bda Burma Inc ia Fr:s T . ^land Iran and S./fce FCC authorised parallel radio ccts with these daces end of article as you 3now demands of amens have much exceeded these recuests x in recent EC/. A publicatn stated EC/ formed 1919 'give R / preeminence in radio whereas 12L_ US.' dependent British cables now RC/ has det cor: n with 49 countires to benefit amen commerce x today US/ commn center of world whereas 20 y a,rs ago twas C-' x US/ now supreme every phase radio TCi ahead of events established ccts /ith Greenland Iceland Cr Brazzaville FCh Ectl /fee x as tmnl after in Europe captured Indio ccts leading to USA established at nee; sites end of articles x the deliberate policy is clear.” nx/E 155/0 MR CG Cable only E pire Stns 278 Fi_ 'larch 42, Stations 278 Fil, K/NS confidential policy of American s egression in wireless core .unication has now reached con siderable len tlis x /merican companies have taken advantage of war situation to force long cherished policy of opening wireless circuits between US/ and many parts of empire and elsewhere no doubt as a means of future economic and communications ewo&amp;nsion x federal com unications commission after having adopted policy of not authorising^second American company to o^en competitive channel with any articular foreign place has now authorised widespread single or duplicate circuits both to EC/ and ackay radio coii any with . laces in the entire arid else' were where no traffic necessity can be siad to exist for such arrange ment x over twenty new circuits between USA and various parts of enq-ire have latterly been e plitude 'y federal com tunications commission whi st various other circuits, some of them duplicate, i ith non e poire countries such as Eritrea, Persia, Iraq and Egy_t, countries more or less ’rents are calculated to diminish our traffic and transfer rates and maintenance of strategic cables were based from our organisation to the _oekets of Americans and . they are . and post war expansion to. the detriment of British interests x the policy was adopted without any prior consultation whatever with us'x the innovation is all the more regret table because it probably endangers the empire^rate structure upon which our activities have been louwded x when nec ess axil, act with discretion in defence of , in this matter and keep head office infd.Extracts from Persian Gulf War Trade Bureau Report No.23 i f it A. PERSIA. 2(c) Sugar - Demand for sugar in Persia continued strong as usual. It appears from interceptions seen during the period under review that Persian merchants are still obtaining sugar from India via Dubai. Merchants, however, are apprehending that this sort of business will not be allowed any longer and in this connection the following extract from a letter dated 13.7.1942 from Ali A. Kazim, Bombay, to M/s Mahmood Kachani &amp; Bros., Seraye Mir Ali Naghi, Tehran, is of interest;- 'Since long time, the exports of Java and Indian Sugar are prohibited by the Government of India, for all foreign countries including Iran and Iranian ports. The only port of Dubai was admitted. At that time, a certain quantity of sugar was shipped by country craft to Dubai and re-exported to Iran. So, I had sent you many cables recommending strongly to purchase and remit us directly and telegraphically free exchange for the total amount, as we expected that this port will be also prohibited. We have received a letter by Air Mail from our agents at Dubai informing us that the country craft SHAHDAD has arrived safely. The goods will be re-shipped to Bunder- Abbas, so we have requested you to wire us the name of your agent at Bunder Abbas, to take delivery of the goods. Sugar market at Dubai is very high owing to the scarcity of goods and also no more import from India to Dubai. The present rate at Dubai is Rs.110/- per bag, which we have informed you in our telegram of the 11th mst. In case you require to sell the goods please let us know.” (d) Tea, soda and sal-ammoniac- fi) Proposal to import into Persia via Dubai - In a letter dated 20-6-42 H. Aminee, Tehran, requested M.J. Mowla &amp; Sons Karachi, to ship good quantities of soda and sal- ammoniac to Dubai obviously with the intention to tranship them to Persia. The following extract from the letter is interesting:- 'Please purchase and ship tea worth Rs.40,000 to Khorram- shahr for which credit has already been opened. I am awaiting for the sugar consignment to be sent to Dubai. You should ship &amp;ea soda and sal-ammoniac to Dubai if possible and the money will be remitted in due course.” (A few other interceptions contained suggestions to ship tea to Dubai for onward despatch to Persia). C. BAHRAIN . Vegetable oil to Bahrain - Ravji Jhaverchand &amp; Co», South Napier Road, Karachi, in their letter dated 7-7-42, to Haridas Janimal &amp; Co., Bahrain, enclosed a D/L for 1500 tins of vegetable oil and intimated their intention to ship the goods per s.s. ”Virginia”. D. DUBAI. Rice for Dubai - proposal to sell while in.transit - A letter from R.A. Ghafoor, Bombay, to Mohamed Ali Badri &amp; Co., Dubai, dated 4-7-42, stated that the writer had shipped rice (1000 bags valued at Rs.18,214 ?) to Dubai from Karachi, and hoped the addressees would sell it in transit at a very profitable rate. Failing this the Dubai firm was advised to ship them to Bahrain in transit for Abdul Aziz Ali Bassam. Camp, Bahrain, 15th August 1942. The Political Agent, Bahrain.Secret. |^V Extract from Persian Gulf Trade bureau Report Ato* 18* A. PERSIA. (ii) Trade conditions at Bandar Abba s, jj^ a letter datea 24*5»42 to A.J^Khunji, -Bombay* Abdulwahid it .J .Klionjim Bunaer Abbas refers to trade conditions in the latter port, ihe following extract is of interest i- . . , “It is 3 days since i arrived in Buncer Abbas, tnis city’s trade is very encouraging and there are many buyers ready to buy the goods in cash and whoever imports any goods earns very enticing prafit. Specially the merchants here are not competent enough. Actually the Government of Iran lias given lots of facilities to the importers, most of the merchants import the goods from Dubai, on its arrival the import permit is granted and the foreign exchange sanctioned at 9t Rials per Rupee immediately.” 2 . Miscellaneous. x 0&gt;) Su&amp;ar. tea, gun ny_bg^t. x ri ce and whs At f lour - x Re cent interceptions confirm that there was a great demand for these commodities in Persia and that Persian merchants art attempting to obtain them from India either through Lubai or by ' : - lane route. B. IRAQ.. 2. Miscellaneous. x ^ „ ( q] Provisions, preserved - Chowgule Brothers, Marmag ao ‘hour, in their letter dated 2 D .3.42 to Basra Commercial Bureau, Hatbour, __ _ - ^ , Basrah, while enclosing an invoice for 20 cases of preseived provisions, states thus* «por your information we would like to advise you that there are no restrictions on export of preserved provisions which are manufactured here. The slapping space could be Mbx had for such small shipments .....There are many firms in Bahrain who import preserved provisions manufactured by our factory. At that port any one can do business, the factory has decided to keep that port open for any Therefore send us more orders from there as of their agents, also. The monopoly of selling these Iraq and Syria is solely ours and in the same to you. -^f you can give us business from Bahrain, we can try to at that port also under our monopoly* products in Iran, our turn we have given some substantial fix up the business C. Bahrain. 2. Miscellaneous . t a) Cars-high prices A letter dated 3*6.42 from T.J.Brown, / B.A.P.C.C#-2- 13 q5) B.A.C.S.O. .Bahrain.to Ste»art hicol, Srinagar. Kashmir refers to high, prices of cars in Bahrain as follows * * 4 . ^ fnr b.is -Gar prices are rocketing, heslie Smifeii got R 8 . 3 , 6°0 for his h'ord (like mine) last week, i’m being pestered to sell but have set Rs. 10000/- to scare off bidders, ihe Arabs are a^l aettind nervous and moving out of Manama to the coas.al v^Uages so the merchants are paying phenomenal prices for lltt ic brine them into town each day. At least, that is the ?V,PV ?!ll but as a large number of the cheques for cars^olf are® d^ by 8 Kanoo. G I suspect he has some funny business under way.' The Kanoo referred to above is probably Khalil Bin Ebrahim Kanoo, Bahrain (lrevaref*p* • (hl 0 Lment r - shipments from Okha for t - A letter dated 30 ^ia^fromkohd.fousuf Pakhroo, Bahrain, tcTkahad Marsook, - - irom mohu *xou cemfent in Bahrain from referred to the arrival of 30,000 ^s oi cemen Bahrai n and Pnvt Okh» in India by a steamer* I0,uuu oags the ''remainder was in transit. The consignee was Abdul Aziz Al All. D. DUBAI. pv x x 1 X (b) i'wereSerous and ^b vinous ly 3 * mos t of the goods were intended for re-dxpor U Une .j.-i xan- etfioks of rice held by merchants in -^ubai ils IhooS bagl^f faS lbs 6 each, an that a Recent notification had fixed the selling price at Rs.17/- pe. bag. tg-ytract from Persian Gulf Tar Trade_gure.au R^prt Mo.jjj, A. PERSIA. 1. Persian trade with Allied or neutral countries - x X X X (b) S ugar - Sugar from India continues to be in good demand in Persia^ - As regards India's export to Persia via Dubai, tne following extract from a letter dated P 7 , 4 A J^Vllros' Tehran explain^how the r^tnetions Jav t a h Sugart- r Tour'credit of Rs.50,000 for purchasing sugar -fnr DibAi 10 u should know that now the quota granted for Dubai is only 100 tons a quarter, end this allotment comes to a trifling quantity when distributed to different merchants. But due to our acquaintance with a European firm, zhcse influence helped us to ship your two lots, consisting of 251 bags and 70 tegs to Dubai, you have been notified b&gt; caole ol tte ixajrtxxhdilpatch of your sugar, fte are “6 e f o 0 ^!_ f the further 251 bags which are ready here, and hope * in the near future. As this commodity is quoted atRs.lW per bag in Dubai, you will gain an attractive profit from these (c) '‘‘Tea*- Interceptions seen in the Bureau recently show that the mirket for tea in Persia is, as usual, ver y aoUTe ' chants in Persia imported the commodity from India via the an- frontier in very large quantities, at the end of^June, 1S4 . ^ y ‘ X B. IRAQ,. conditions in Basr ah - The followi ng extract from a letter dated 5.7742 from Ahmad kakroo &amp; ‘Marzook* Karachi, gives some idea about the present day business conditions in Basrah *- H I arrived Basrah a week ago and had a mind to proceed on to the north, but have been detained here for six days in studying the market and other business conditions locally* Matches* The rate has improved than before* i-t is Dinars 15/- for a case of matches containing 40 sticks per box and I.D^ 20/21 for that of 60 sticks. Oil* Oil had arrived through Kings and is selling @ 270/- per maund since there is no tax on oil* Oil comes from -india, but how ? I cannot say* its export in tins is prohibited, but you can ship a quantity in joint account to Dubai in wooden drums ? At Dubai it can be filled in empty tins* Or if possible ship it direct to Basrah and it can be filled in empty tins here at the time of delivery* The duty on it is fils l/- per kilo only. Dates. The committee is expected to ask the monopolists to raise the price of the last year by 50#. It is doubtful whether Govt, will allow export as usual. The total produce of Iraq is about 3 , 000,000 maunds. The monopolists need about 1 , 000,000 mds.while more than a quarter of the whole produce is consumed locally in Iraq. It is therefore open to question whether any of the remaining quantity will be allowed tu be exported. Zahdi (dates) was sold the other day @ 32/- Dinars and shipped to mo hammer ah ♦ Oil , More oil arrived after Kings and was sold @ 240/-. The demand still exists. X X x x x X XXX C* BAHRAI N * Scarcity of tyres and position with regard to stock of scrap- iron in Bahrain - The following extract from a letter dated 7.7.42 from Abdul Tayeb Sarafally, Bahrain, to Koorbhai Allibhoy Malai, Karachi, explains the positions t- ’’As for the motor tyres, for which you had asked me to inquire in Bahrain, please note that I have made every effort to find some but no one has any stock of tyres here, are making the best use of whatever stock they hold, so much so that they even use their worn out tyres after due repairs. Bo mmch of your scrap-iron is lying here. Most of the stock would be sold out, if soneone from you person ally came to this side and saw to its sale, because this is easily saleable here.' XX XX E* DUBAI. 1 2 1 , Trade conditions - in his letter dated 8.7.1942 addressed to Ravishanker T. Trivedi, Kathiawar, Ravishanker ftarainji Trivedi, Dubai, described the trade condition of that place as follows t- J *At present the market is dull, kurther there is no aemana from Bunder Abbas as plenty of goods have reached there. Moreover, as the lorries which used to transport goods to the upper part are at present engaged in transporting government goods $ there is no trade but the market is still, very strong *••• Since 2 days the Shaikh has penuitted to export 2,000 gunnies to uuttar and hence the market rate of rice has gone high.** 2. Miscellaneous * ( a ) Brandy - attempt to smu^Kle to Dubai through Muscat - The following extract from a letter dated 13.7.42 from Bahman Ardeshir Kaghighat, Karachi, to'Abdul^iahr Shahverzi, Muscat, is interesting i- M You should also try and obtain a permit from the Customs Officer or from the shaikh About Hennessy brandy, please do not send it by steamer but either by a country hoat or / through/-V (£&gt; -4- through z reliable person who can deliver the same to Shamsa. Da not sk&gt;w this cargo in the “Manifesto” as it is meant for Dubai* 't would be much better if you could send the same tnroug;. Tindal Silim Mohd*Balloch with instructions to carry it to Sosa or , Minai , &amp;nd to hand it ove/r to Shamsa* •••••-Hease send 20 bottles jither in one lot or more* The object is that it should not be slipped by steamer but by a country boat or through a reliable Tindal. You know better how to proceed.' X X X X X l c) Fictitious orders - Large orders for foodstuffs from India were priced by Abdul Rahman u’alaknaz and Damodardas Hemandas of Karachi, with Mohamed Ali Mohamed, and Valabhdas S.Dhamodardas of Karachi# respectively# in the second week of July 1942. Appar~.. ly these were fictitious orders to secure large export quotas. (Previous Ref .page 3 of Report J^o.22). Copy uffice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf# Camp, Bahrain. Dated the 30th August, 1942. forwarded, with compliments, tot- The Political Agent, Bahrain• I 5^Jxtract&amp; from lersian Gulf War Trade Bureau |6 (5&gt; 1. (b) ( ii ). Deeiatoh v i a Dubai of sugar arid tea - Bubal it still being used as a tranait port for trade between India and Persia. A good number of interceptions seen in the Bureau during the period under review relate to attempts to despatch sugar (Indian and Java) and tea from India to Dubai for ultimate shipment to ler&amp;ia. The following merchants in Persia and Dubai are playing an important part in this trade. Messrs. Meherjee (Bunder Abbas), ^bdulla Gelledary (Tehran), Goladari (Bunder Abbas), G.R. Ilafsinj&amp;ni (Bunder Abbas), 5yed Mohd. Husain Tabatabai (Bunder Abbas), Fohomed Golbarani (Bunder Abbas), HM'.H.Z. Farsidooni (Dubai Ahmed &amp; Mohomed Abdulla Abbas (Dubai) Haji Abdulkader Haji Mohomed Abbass (Dubai), Mohomed and Abdulla Haji Yusuf Fhoory (Dubai) and H.M.H. 8c H.M.H.R. lari (Duabi). 1. .(c). Piecegoods and glass - export through Duba i Besides sugar and tea, attempts are being made to export piecegoods and glass to Persian Gulf countries through Dubai. In this connection the following extract from a letter dated 14-7-42 from H.M.H.Z# Faraidooni, Dubai, to Messrs Tafti Bros., Bombay, is of interest:- '•In reply to your telegraphic enquiry v/hether the export of tea, piecegoods and glass from Dubai is permitted, please note that the only commodities of which the export is prohibited are rice and flour. The rest are allowed by paying import duty of 3^-^ and export duty of 10% but for sugar we have to pay an export duty of Es.lO/- per bag.' 2. (c). Tea - pr o posal to ship to Dubai and then to re ship to Basrah - The following extract from a letter dated 16-7-42 from A.&amp; K,A«H. Abbas, Bombay, to M. 8 A. H.Y. Fhoory, Dubai, is inters sting j- “It seems that Hamad Ali iilkafi had 3CCC cases of tea for his Basrah clients but he could not ship it to Basrah and he is going to ship to Dubai and from there reship it to Basrah. He has been introduced by R.a# Fazim to the firm of Abdulkarim Faruk in Dubai, I don’t know how far this rumour is correct but it seems that the said tea will arrive by 2 or 3 steamers to Dubai.” (a). Food position and prices - The following extract from a letter dated 16-7-42 from Fhan Saheb Aodulhusain and Bros., Bahrain, to a. Hebatulla 8c Bros., Bombay, explains the present positions- ”There is a great demand for toilet articles viz. Hamam, Palmolive and lifebuoy soaps. The rate for Hamara soaps has gone up to .45 per gross. If possible, send 25 gross from Messrs. Tata &amp; Sons at the market rate. ”2 3. ~)UBaI . (b) Fictitiou s o rde rs - Large orders for rice and v/heat flour v/ere xTlaced by (1) Yousuf Ali Akbar /i.li Reza (ii) Yahraood Abdulnabi Bushire, (iii) Abdulaziz Ali Albassam (iv) Aboody Yacoob Zeloof &amp; Sons and Yousuf Akbar Alireza, of Bahrain, v/ith (i) Indian Flour Fills Ltd. (ii) R am c hand Maganraal (iii) Fahad Farzook ( iv) HaJ i Suleman Adam Fothari 8c Co., of Farachi, respectively, in the month of July 1942. Hoarding of rice at Bubai - Fahad liarzook, Karachi, in hi s letter dated '23-7-1942, informed Shaikh F. Abdullatif, Dubai, as follows:- H »/e have shipped per s.s. •BARPFTA' 1000 bags of Ballam (rice) weighing 78 seers each. 500 of them are marked F^-/^ and 500 FAa/AHa on our own account. These are consigned to you. Please take delivery and store them with you for the time being and do not sell them till we write to you. The consignment is insured against damage.' Fisuse of export permit*.- In a letter dated 15-7-42 addressed to Pars Company, Farachi, Habeeb Hassan, Joosbeiri Sharjah, while placing an order for 200 bags of rice, ICO bags of flour, 50 bags of wheat, 15 bags of gram, 15 bags of barley and 100 tins of ghee, added as follows:- 'Regarding wheat, you have written that you could purchase export permit, so please purchase for me export permit for 500 bags.' o.C/859. OFFICE OF TH3 POLITICAL RESIDEFT in the Persian Culf, Camp, Bahrain, 7th September 1942. Copy forwarded to - The Political Agent, Bahrain. * ^ Wx &lt;? ' » '0 ’ ■ 'CA &gt; % O'a. - - y v r / 13 B-ORE T Hb.62 90VBRH4BKT OP IIEIA 9 External Aff!*J.rs Departmert. Dated New Delhi, Septr: 1 42. The undermentioned paper is forwarded to the * 1* Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 2*Iolitical Agent, Bahrain, 3. ” Kuwait, 4. M '* Muscat, for information (in continuation of endorsement from the Govt, of India in the External Affairs Deptt., No. 6102-N/42, dated the 5th Septr: , 42), ( ) To No. B y order^ etc., l-(Copy of Report of Persian Gulf War - Tr?p^ Bureau, No.29, dated the 7th Sep mber 1942.) 2.Extract from Report of Persian Gulf War Trade Bureau, No.29, dated the 7th September 1942.PERSIAN GULF- r . AR TRADE 3DBS1IJ REPOR T NO. 29 PART I - STATISTICAL PORTION ' NIL. PART II • ■ Sumrnary.of information relating to Persian G-ulf countries received ih -the Persian Gulf frar Trace Bureau during the week ending the 3rd September 1942. JL-EISSIl Pe rsian t rade with hIlieA^or_n eui£&amp;l_co\mtries - (a) Artificial si lk goods - despatc h to Pers ia v ia Dubai- It appears from inLe?cepLions seen Tn tne Bureau recently that artificial silk piecegoods were despatched from India in the month of August 1942 to Dubai with the intention of forwarding them&gt;*on to Persia'. The following extract from a letter dated 22.8.42 from # Zartoshty &amp; Sons, Bombay, to M/s Mohd. &amp; Abdulla H.Y.Khoory, Dubai, is of interest in this connection 'Enclosed cut piece samples care of 15 cases art silk piece- goods which have been shipped to you. You are requested to let us know at what rate you can get us an offer for same. If found economic we will instruct you to sell them there, otherwise a part is to be shipped to Meherji, Bunder Abbas and part to Gulshani, Bushire. (b) Sugar' - shipme nt from East Africa -_ A telegram dated 7,8.42 from Rashid MoEdma Co., Mombasa, to Sahib Singh, Charag Burg, Teheran, offered 3000 tons of sugar at the rate of £30 per ton c.i.f. Bushire or Bunder Shahpur and asked addressee to arrange for import permit through Military authorities who should also wire to the^Supply Board, Nairobi, to allow export_licence. It was stated that shipment of the goods was not possible without an export licence. (c) Tpa - (i) Desp a tch f r om India - Several interceptions seen.in the Bureau during the weeE under report show that tea is still in greet demand in Persia and good quantities appear to have been •&amp;B^tchedfrom India in the month of August 1942. In view of the Government of India’s orders stopping licences for export of^tea to Persia, it is presumed that these despatches were made under licences previously obtained. A recent interception (telegram dated 20.5.42 from Randerian, Calcutta, to Faizmohamed Faiz, Zahe- dan),however, refers to some arrangement under which tea is being allowed to be exported to Persia. The following is a copy of the telegram:- 'According our arrangement all tea allowed for Iran. Please inform all customers.' (ii) Despatch from India v i a Dubai - Given below is a copy of a letter dated 22.8.42 from Tafti Bros., Bombay, to Haji Mohamed Haji Zainal Faraidooni, Dubai, which reveals how with a view to circumvent the recent restrictions imposed.by the Govern ment of India on exports of tea, merchants are making attempts to ship tea to Dubai for onward despatch to Persia :- 'I had an. iris true t ion from V.H. Tafti, Yezd, to buy 100,000 ibs of tea and 25 cases art silk piecegoods and same to be shipped to you to Dubai. Accordingly the said -- 2 - ; tea with its ordinary ouota and the art s.ilk piecegoods purchased are ready for the purpose 0 As a rule the order ought to come from the source where the goods are to be shipped. You are therefpre requested, on receiving this letter to cable me as you think beat for the above mentioned goods to be shipped tq Dubai, so that it may be a document and we are not faced with any difficulty to^ ship them, otherwise the purchased goods will be a loss to us„ You must not mind any expenses that are incurred nor should you'disclose anything to anybody about them , • ' • , (ni) Persljin_merchant_desires_tea_tp be_desnatched from Cal cutta tO-hBia ; phi_on_his__accpunt - In a letter dated 2.8,42 to MulcEand Chanderohan, Karachi llohd. Hassan Shirafat, Shiraz, thanked addressee for his trouble in obtaining the licence-for 400 chests of tea' and stated but I found a more suitable way of utilizing the transaction. I, have, wired you to place an order for 400 chests :-oi tea to Delaver- knan oi Calcutta to book same in your name for my a/c and instruct them to send the documents to Karachi.' The motive behind this transaction is not clear. • - ! ' ty) T^Bj^X-^-StatutorY,listed, fir m in Persia - In their letter aatea 11.8 a 42 to the Imperial 'Bank of Iran, Tabriz, Persia#which was. intercepted at Karachi on 21,8.42 and released, Lloydb Bank Ltd., Calcutta;, enclosed At Sight Bills for Es.18,000/- and R5.15,000/- Drawers, Messrs Iran Trading Co c , Drawees, Ali Miskerzadeh and Bros., Tabriz,and Hail Mohd. Ali Shalchi, Tabxiz, on account of tea 304 chests^ and 25o chests respectively, despatched by Railway to Zahedan via Nokknndi.- ■ vAjc •x, Miskerzadeh &amp; Bros,, have been placed on the statutory list with effect from ; 28.8.1942 ••(.'already-reported: ; by telegram). r ^ • ( v 4 r) Paghdad_firm_interested in obtaini ng tea for Per sia from lubia - The following .is an extract from a letter dated •5578742 from Hiralal Raichana &amp; Co., Bombay, to M/s David Heskel. Murad, Post Box No,90,•Baghdad: • 1 ' calo l e . 0 f , 19th instant you asked us to book 12,000 lbs 1/10 costfreight Khorramshahr, this we had to refuse and telegraphed you that our final price costfreight Khorramshahr was Ro.1/12 as we have to undergo here lot of expenses. So far there is no reply from you c Moreover in our-cable of 20th we have informed you that against your order of 30,000 lbs booked for Khorramshahr i.e. 18,000 and 12,000 lbs, we are shr to 7°/ in all 33,000-lbs as we hold Tea Export -‘Licence for. ' : oOO cnests each of 110-lbs packing and we cannot alter this under any circumstances. Total amount of Export Permit wen / obtained for Iranian Ports was 7-,500 chests but finding that you.are slow to book^orders for Iran, we had to sell - our Export Permits at fair premiums, but we have reserved for you a' quantity notifiea previously 1 and in case we do not receive your orders in time, we shall have to sell this reserved quantiLy also so please do not delay to book Iran Orders.' B. IRAQ • j 1. Transit_.trade_ihrough_Xraq - The latest position of this trade is shown in Appendix I. - „ (a). SfiUgn-- af£sr_ijLA^Turki 9 'b.fir mltQ_a. 'P,S.A. f irm - A letter fnom^ A.R.Barki &amp; Co., Izmir, to Mr r Nathan Hurwitz, 4504 18th Street, Washington, dated 7*7.42.. stated that the writers had friends in Iraq who wished them to sell cotton on their account, and that they would therefore like to olfer the addressee 2,000 tons Iraqi cotton, which would be shipped frcm Basrah.(b) Motor c ars - ru se to obt ain perni it The following is an extract fr.o'i'.a..letter dated 21-5,41. fr art JaM.Shashoua 9 Bombay, to 'Motor Gars:- I understand that SALIM DAI'.'G-OOR, who is working with F5^LER &amp; CO., (he is in-charge of their Bombay Branch) is shortly shinning a New Buick Car 1941 model for his mana ger Mr. DE.COURCYol understand that Mr. Be Courtly himself wa. able to obtain this special permit,, because he is working with the British Authorities in Iraq. I think you should definitely get in touch with Mr.EAoT- T/OOD and try and get something in this matter; you can^ arrange to obtain the necessary permit in his name, and 11 you want, give him part of the profit. There is one thing quite definite, thaw is, that if you can obtain letter f^cm the British authorities, stating that youare supplying them • then it will be quite easy to obtain special permits tor all things. If you cannot get such a letter let Mr, iastw^ood try. Furthermore, if you can obtain a letter stating that you are supplying the Government P _ this v/i 11 alsO (j be just as good:. Please see what you can do in this matter. (c) -Hp-a for Basra h via Dub ai or Khorr^mshahr - It appears . that merchants in Irac are still*trying to import tea to Basrah^via Dubai, but in view of the recent restrictions on exports of ^eoa- stuffs from India to Dubai, the volume of such trade is expected to be reduced in future.'In this connection the following extract from a letter dated 22 c 8 6 42(?) from Koweity &amp; Suleiman, Abdul Jabar.Khedairy Road, Ashar, Basrah, to Y.E. Softer, Bombay, is interenting ' Tea - Before, shipment of tea to Dubai was free and there is still no restriction on shipments of this &gt; stuff from Dubai,to. Basrah. Now-we understand that it is no mqre easy to ship to- Dubai. However, we agreed with you to ship the whole lot to Khorramshahr, The market there is not favourable, but we do not expect a loss. We required Bill of Lading by cable because tliere is a chance of bringing the goods to Basrah. The market here is stronger than ever and we could cancel the previous sales at Fils 700, while the market to day is upto Fils 900 which is a marvellous rate. God help us to bring your shipment to Basrah. Urgent cabling of the • B/Lading must-be’used. (d) Re-exports to Syr ia and Persia„frQm_stpck^_helei in l£^g* (Previous ref: page 2 o? Report No.287 - In his letter datecj?22.8.4c to Sion Balass &amp; uo., Baghdad, MoshiS.Sofer, Bombay, while thank ing the addressees for conveying to him the information that the goods in transit to' Syria would b^ allowed from stocks held in Iraq, continued as follows:- , , _ , . ' I should thank you if you would be good enough to let me know in your reply if the same position holds with regard to Iran, viz. goods’no*t originally consigned to Iran, if they are allow ed to be re-exported to Iran or not. The rumour here is least very strong that stocks in Iraq might be allowed to Iran if they are purCihased by Iranian buyers.' QJilMAlT Shaik hFs order: wheat smuggling- The following extract from a letter da'Ee3 14.8,42 from Mohamed Dawood Marzook, Kuwait, to Mohamed Dawood Marzook, Karachi, is of interest:- •. . ' 'The Shaikh has ordered that the house and shqp of everyone who has got rice and- does not dispose, of it v/ithin 3 days, will be broken open. God save us from this..,As regards the wheat and barley-, which is in the hands-of the. Control Committee, this may last for 3 days only. Wheat is smuggled here, but very little, and immediately upon arrival it is snatched away by people alMlk- per It cwts.' IkDUBAT Fictitious_p rders ?-From recent interceptions it is seen that Abdul Rahman Falaknaz and Abdul Kader H.Mohd.Abbas, of Dubai, have placed very large orders for grain,..flour.., soap etc. with Indian merchants. (Previous ref: pages 4-5 of Report No.26).-4- PART III-A Summary of information relating to activities of enemy, neutral and Allied countries. (i) G-ermany (a) Wuminium^and__ma gnesium prod uc tion - In a survey ra^feased by George S\ Armstrong &amp; Go, Inc,, industrial engineers and management consultants, it is stated that German production of aluminium in 1943 will amoun\ to about 300,000 short tons (272.154 metric tons). This shows an. increase of only 35,000 short tons (31,751 metric tons) over tbf 1940 figure. It is estimated that German production of magnesium will be 40.00(1 short tons (36,287 metric tons) in 1943, as compared with 20,900 short tons (18,960 metric tons) in 1940, The survey shows that Germany leckthe United States in the output of both metals during 1940, but is compsietely unable to match American expansion plans. Z American Metal Market (U.S.A.) 49, No,45, page 6 March 1942 _/. (b) Geni ianylg_Mr craft Industry - The annual specification da^ for German military a^irpraft m 1942 includes/information of 53 models specified, 66 % use aluminium alloy for wing structure and 75^o use it for fuselages. The.abo\e figures include airplanes specified as using 'ffetal' which most probably is aluminium, Z Aviation vU.S.A.) No.2 pages 209-210, February 1M2_/. (iiKltaly aircraft ind u stry - The ’act hulleW“f ihg^7®t,, idras, dated April 1942, are of Aluminium ancj magpesiurgi following extracts from ^TEe Abs' Canada, to Jeewanlal (^929) Ltd. interest:- ,'lialXt Although Italy possesses considerable bauxite the Country has conducted extensive ^experiments on the employment of leucite as an aluminium raw material; by such use it is hoped not only to supply a part of the aluminium requirement but also to obtain considerable quantities of potash salts. The utili- \._...A,,..zation of alunite also has been consiaered. Magnesium produc- . \ ti°n has been estimated to be around \,800 tons a year, although it was announced the output would be 3^000 tons by the end of 1941.. A Government/sponsored concern in the Italian Alps is building a plant for the manufacture of magnesium from local dolomite.' ’ \ -* * * k ^ -^It alian..air crafV industry - Aviation (U.S.A^) 41, No.2, pages 211412'February 1942. The Italian military aircrafts specifica tion for 1942 shows that of 47 models listed 25% employ alumi nium alloy for the wing structure and 45% for tn^ fuselages.' • Z (iii) Switzerland STd .3 s, i ,.trade with India via Brazj.1 - A letter from Sandoz Pharmaceutical Department, J.L. Morrison, Son and Jones (India) Ltd., Bombay, to lys Sandoz Ltd., Basle, dated 14.8.1942, referred x to regulations concerning the shipment of Swiss goods. The writ ted that in consequence^of these the Swiss Trade Commissioner f bay had had a consultation with the Brazilian Consul, that Swiss ships should go direct to India via Brazil, be # difficult to load these ’ ■ ~* JV oo •- , Switzerland on the for Brazil should lian goods for Switzerland^ new sta- Bom- ,eSted woixld4- Secret. f - -No.6413-H/42. Government of India. External Affairs Department. New Delhi, the September 1942. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf the Political Agent, Bahrain,^ the Political Agent, Kuwait, the Political Agent, Muscat, in continuation of endorsement from the Goverme of India in the External Affairs Department, No. 6252-N/42, dated the 12th September 1942. By order, etc.. Assistant Secretary'tb the Govt, of India port of Persian Gulf lar Trade Bureau, dated 14th September 1942. * Report of Persian Gulf Jar Trade Bureau No.30, dated 14th September 1942. £ Extract from Report of Persian Gulf War Trade Bureau, No.30, dated~14th September 1942. *For Persian Gulf. £For Political Agents Bahrain, Kuwait &amp; Kuscat &amp; G.s.-ia/iL(0 7) q o ’TSTJU «ST. pM SiMLAl IHll 14TH pPflJpSR 1^4? PERSIAN GU LF...S i2JrBi£a-BUBSiU EIEfiBl_HQ^O • 3_Q_O..SJLX_S. PART I -STATISTICAL PORTION PART II - SUMMARY OF INFORMATION RELATING TO PERSIAN GULF COUNTRIES RECEIVED IN THE PERSIAN GULF WAR TRADE BUREAU DURING TP V.FSK ENDING THE 10TH SEPTEMBER 1942 (Pages 1-4) Pages 1 • • ♦ 1-2 i Conditions in Persia , **4 . . Ian trade with neutral oh Allied countn es - rax Hi oil ux auc wx uia v* a a) Drugs from India to Persia l fl T , D f b) SilR worm eggs C?) from FraftOS t&gt;4 India via Persia I c) Sugar 3* Miscellaneoua “ 1 1-8 * ♦ • 4 i i • ♦ * (a) Export to Persia from Indian States ports (b) Job for Adolphe Brasseur of Teheran with the British Consulate B-t-IBiD • • • 1. Transit trade through'Iraq 2. Miscellaneous - * * • * * « (a) Charcoal, groundnut oil, matches, etc. - arrange ment for despatch from Veraval to Basrah . b) Tea - awaiting shipment for Basrfih from Dubai dj Vegetable ghee - proposal to send direct to Basrah or via Dubai 1*2 2 2 2 3 3 3 3 3 3 «* • k T - BAPCO closing down through lack of tankage - German radio comment 4 s+jmm - Business conditions in Kuwait ^ FART III-A - SUMMARY OF INFORMATION RELATING TO ACTIVITIES tAJa a ^ENEMY, NEUTRAL OR ALLIED COUNTRIES (Pages 4-0 (i) .Germany - (a) Aeroplane putput of Germany, Italy, France, Russia, Britain and the ILS.A. (b) Distribution of the Worlds raw*materials between the Axis and the Allies * • ♦ 4-5 4-5 5 (ii) Fxansg. - ••• a) Conditions in France ^ ,, b) New potash deposit in South-western trance cj Traffic between France and north ports of Africa stopped ,,• (iii) Holland - Manufacture of synthetic rubber (iv) Switzerland - Swiss.trade with India through Turkish intermediaries •*« (v) China - Production in oilfields of ChinaPERSIAN T .'XR TRADI BUICAU xl •: •; RRPO RT PC.3 0. : ; PART I - STATISTICAL PORTION ' :■ ; ' n I L PART II. • Surimary of information relating to Persian Gulf countries received in the; Persian Gulf War Trade Bureau during the week ending the.10th September 1942. _ : • • EiBSIAj. 1» Trad e co n di tions in Persia The following extract from^a lette^ated 3.8.1942 from Ryder Amini, Teheran, toM.M.K. Shirazi, Srinagar, Kashmir, speaks of improved trade conditions in Persia:- 'I am thinking of shifting my business to Shiraz because in business matters we have nothing to depend on in*Teheran now. I 'am of the opinion that the Exchange Department will be abo lished as the banks are free to sell exchange drafts up to any limit. Goods can also be imported without permit and the Customs import permit can also be obtained at.the ports. Nor is it necessary to have a certificate of origin. Many of the prohibited articles haverlso been freed'! 2. Pers ian t rade v dth n e utral .o r Allied count r ies - (a) Drugs from I ndi a t o Persi a “ In a letter dated 16.7.42 to the Manager, Lloyds Bank Ltd;, Karachi, the Imperial Bank of Iran, Meshed,while confirming the following telegram, enclosed a form stating that the payment was against export of drugs from India to Persia :- ' ' . 'Pay Mulchand Chanderohan, Bombay Ba!zar, Karachi, rupees ten thousand account lohamed Shah Sharifzadeh,Herat.' (b) Silk worm eggs (? ) f rom F ra nce to India via Persia .- Given below is a copy of a telegram dated 26.8.42 from Commintel, Teheran, to Chief Silk, Srinagar, Kashmir 'Following from Jouvel stop your letter number 141 of July Wentyn'inth stop further copy of promised letter follows by Government of India bag stop order of 5000 ounces leaving. France any moment except for 1500 ounces w/hite Baghdad which . I can have supplied from. .Iran stop please telegraph w/hether ■ you agree.' - • • : ■ . i ■ (c) Sugar - • ' ' : (i) Desp atch of-'^ugar to Pe rsia via Dubai - In a letter dated 25.8,42 Mirzanassan &amp; Bros., Dubai, informed Saji Jafar Abdul Rahim, Muscat, that they would be sending 200 bags of sugar by boat to Khorramshahr. (Previous ref: page 1 of Report No.28). (ii) Ce ntr a l S upplies Com m ittee . T e heran, granting licences t o Persian merchants fpr i mport of s us^ar from India :- A good number or interceptions seen Tn the Bureau during the 'week under^ report shows that Persian merchants placed orders in the latter half of. August with their correspondents in India for considerable quantities of sugar stating that the. Central Supplies Committee,.Teheran, had granted licences for'same and that authorities‘in India had been informed accordingly. In this connection the following telegram dated 20.8.42 from Djafar Akhavan, Teheran, to Ghazanfar Mowla, Karachi, is interesting :- 'Obtained from English General Supplies.Committee under number 224 dated twelve August instant export permit for 500 tons '- 2 - s^ar please refer to mentioned committee ship 500 tons sugar .to- Khorramshahr immediately wire result will extend credit 11 price changed will accept please telegraph amount value 500 tons sugar will open rest wire result stop obuained expprt permit alsoior several thousand tons telegraph what ouantities which price can you offer c.i.f. Khorramshahr. M But from another interception /telegram dated 29.8.42 from^ Ghazanfar Mov/la, Karachi, (with whom most of the recent praers ^c ro , , placed), to (i) Hassan-Hashemi*-(ii) Mahmood Laieverdi* (ill) Behdashty Bros., (iv) Abbas Sarrafian, (v) Tedjarati Syndicate, (vi) Diafar Akhavan, (vii) Arzoam'anian Bro'S., of Tehera^i/it appears thaiAne Government of India had not been approached by the Central Supplies Committee in connection with export licences. The following is a copy of the telegram referred to abovej- • - m ’’Reference sugar licence we approached Indian authorities at Delhi but they have no instructions from Teheraii telegraph urgently exact address to whom Central Supplies Committee have telegraphed.” (iii) Suga r position in Persia ' The following is an extract from a letter dated 201?.42 irom Adolphe Brasseur, B.P.26, Teheran, to Leon Brasseur,1676 Street, Nev; York:- . /■ ”Sugar: The Societe d’ Avances from Egypt answered me: Aaolphe Brasseur, Teheran, Sugar Egypte can sell nothing. On the other hand Dabir, whom 1 rang up, told me that no orders had been placed with the U.S.A. since the first, about which you know. It is likely that Government y/ill reduce the ration, 1 but there are enough big stocks .of crystallised sugar, imported from India, 'which is being xk sold now at the rate of 22-23 xinld per iikink I have written to you that Chaoul saw at the ’’Currency Commission” a sugar permit of’ % 20.000 for Laad, but he could not see. the name, of the supplier.” (Previous ref: item 13 on page 7 of Report No.10). extract from (a) rg.-Ea.esia.lroSLlxI.Cli.aS,, SiLatgS ponts - An extrac a letter dated 4.4.8,42 from Khoja Gulamaliy Mohamedali, Rajkot (Kathiawar), to Mohamed Alii Bhai Jammalbhai, c/o Karim Jammalbhai, iadan, reads as follov/s :- ’’The Rajkot State authorities have prohibited the export of sugar, rice, cement and food-grain, and it is *aaid that they are going to prohibit . the export of other things' too. Export of matches from Veraval (Kathiawar) is already stopped. It is rumoured th^t all the States are going to impose ax ban on the export of goods from their territpries. Export is permissible only if we have a permit from Delhi, where we have to apply before shipping any goods.” • (b) Job for Adolp he Bra sseur of Teheran w ith. T the_Brrtish_^pnsulate- The following extract from a letter bated 11.7.42 from .Adolphe Brasseur, Teheran, to Leon Brasseur, 16 76 ..Street, New York,is of interest :- ”Employment: The i'ob with the British Consulate _ has been decided ana I think that 1 shall leave in two days. It is rather_tiresome . and difficult work, namely to discover wheat which is being hidden and that is almost impossible and may become dangerous, as also the task of stopping prevarications. I told Squires that I am perhaps the least Dad Tor this job and that I do not promise to succeed absolutely but I shall do my best. Anyhow, 600 tomans per month in our present position cannot be refused. It is true that this is'only for 2 or 3 months, but from now till then, God is great.'rr..- -3- B IRAQ. ^ 1. IraiiMi^iiarle^through^Ira^ trade is shown In Appendix I. 2. Miscellaneous - - The latest position of this t_ fo: ■asran, sen' 1942 'Boom hayitf sailed empty prepare 300 matches, 10Q0 seham (sic) 300 groundnuts oil 1500 charcoal. : . 1 . ' (b)..Tea• - awaiting shipment_for Basr ah f rom Dubai - In their &gt;br dated'-25s8.42 TotiajiJafar AbHui Ranim, Muscat, Mirza- ! Hassar^ : ;and Brothers, Dubai, stated •as follows:- letter (via Karachi)&gt; 'Immediately your telegram was received, we replied, ’B&lt; .available. Should we ship or not 0 Gable.’ ;Your reply ii Boat is still awaited. A big boat of Malak Ibrahim G-illadari is'bound for_ Basrah, find will touch at Kuwait and Kohartnesal The price of tea /at Basrah is understood to' be. good. I myself have sent about ,-2000 chests from Dubai to Basrah by boats and steamers.' (c) Ghee - The following is an extract froifi A letter dated 1 6,8,1942 from United Africa Co. (Kenya) Ltd., P.0.B.580, Mombasa, .-j-to Messrs. African and Eastern (Near East) . Ltd., Basrah tt Ghe0;'- with reference to our letter No.9 of the # 18th ultimo, our Application of the 17th ultimo for export licence for 1000 tins ghee has now been returned and we quote literally the covering letter from the Kenya Supply Board dated the 4th instant'- ’With reference -to the attached application, I am directed to inform you that the export of ghee is not permitted at present.’ • \ We take, this to mean‘that for the time being schee cannot be exported, and we shall .p apply again at a later dat9» Gould you help matters by 'having your'- authorities make representations ‘that'ghee is urgently reauired in your area $ We can get the ghee.* ' , . ' ' : -i /V y ... * . &lt;• V r M ( y t ^ - . (d) Vegeta bl e *ghe e - propos al to se nd direc t to*Basrajm or vi a Dubai - The^; following is an extract from, a Tetter * dAted 21.8.42 'from Yousuf Abdul Rahman Fakhroo,:Bahrain, to, Fahad 'Marzook, Karachi bar 'According to a telegram from brother t vegetable ghee at Basrah is Ks.245/- per of the Indian Gan you arrange export-of 2000 tins on joint a/c. to, Basrah? If not, can you sepdithem to Dubai leaving onWard arnaa?ig#xmt to us thence ? 7;#/e,have purchased (from Dubai) 500 tips between Fs.19/- arld* r ?c.20/8/- and 300 tins. Es,23/-. /These are being shipped in boats ■ for.;BAsrah, A tin- contains 40 lbs. .and v/hatever the' expenses may come to they are little. A tin will fetch'over Rs.55/- at the above rate, and.there is no duty on it in Iraq. Can you do anything in the matter ? I await.your reply.' •. • ; ' ;-,r. I • ■ . vr. .■ • ^ -• y *'t -i -\-Confidential. &gt;r ^ •SI'*-' No.iOOO-S. British Residency A CSnsulate- General, Bushire f the 26th Septr. 1942. Copy, with copy of enclosure, forwarder with compliments, to s- The Political Agent, Bahrain, for report. ' 9 k — ~ • r,- t ' IINDIA OFFICE. ECONOMIC &amp; OVERSEAS DEPAHTMENT EXPRESS IETTER(AIR MAIL) CFAST) (ir.B.- This l 3 &amp;a original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as If it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatch ed.) From - Secretary of State for India To - - Government of India, External Affairs Department. Dated 29th Atgust 0942. No. E. &amp; 0. 17093/42. Your telegram No.306 of 6th August to H.M.Minister, Tehran regarding ©-ordination of Indian export and Persian import controls. Certain passages vtoich have appeared in the reports of the Persian Gulf War Trade Bureax suggest attempts to evade trade controls. The following may be qioted as exaapled *- ^ J Para. A2(d)i and D of Report No.23 Para. D of Report No.2i and paras. A2(c) and B3 (i) of Report Nb.09.^k.2 You have doubtless considered in conjunction with the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf what measures should be taken to combat such attempts, both from the Indian &amp; Persian Gulf ends. Similar attempts Will presumably be made to evade export control to Iraq which it is hoped will shortly be introduced. See my telegram No. 13949 of 8th August to Commerce Department. - v ' rd . The issue of Hi e above has been duly authorised. &gt;r &gt;r A Sd/- Illegible.Confidential To Political Agency y Bahrain, the 13th October 1942. The Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject : Re-exports from Dubai to Persia and other countries. Reference your Endorsement Ho.lOOO-S, dated 26th September 1942 under which you forwarded to me for report a copy of External Affairs Department letter No.6074-N/42 dated 16th September 1942 2. Dubai is not only the principal port for the Trucial Oman and Qatar$ it also carries on a large entrepot trade with Persia. In April 1942 I discussed with the Shaikhs of IXibei and Sharjah, and also with the Residency Agent, the problem of supplies for the True!el Coast and the extent to which re-export of commodities could reasonably be allowed having regard to the interests both of merchants and of the general populace. At the beginning of June, after I had secured a statement of stocks in Dubai, I wrote to the Residency ^gent and asked him to give to the Shaikhs of Dubai and Sharjah the following advice which was based on the principles being followed in Bahraim- (a) In regard to essential foodstuffs which do not deterior ate e.g. rice, sugar, coffee or wheat, 6 months 1 supply should be kept in reserve. I explained that by months* supply 11 I meant the amount required for consumption over 6 months in Dubai, Qatar and the Trucial Coast and which is normally imported through Dubai or Sharjah (b) in regard to foodstuffs which deteriorate e.g. spices or wheat flour, only 3 months* supply should be kept in reserve. (c) In regard to piecegoods, qualities which are not used locally might all be exported. In regard to other piece goods, 3 months* supply should be kept. / (d)v\ Ul (d) As long as supplies for the periods named were kept in reserve, all surplus stocks might be exported. 3. Quota goods are rice, wheat and wheat flour, grains and pulses and sugar. During the months of June, July and August 1942 (the last months for which figures are available) no wheat or wheat flour has been exported to Persia or Iraq from Dubai or Sharjah; exports of rice amounted to only 72 cwts, and no grains or pulses were exported with the exception of 8 cwts. of barley. It seems that the re-exports from Dubai to which the Government of India refer in their letter must be mainly sugar. During the five months April to August 1942 45,992 cwts. of sugar were imported from India and during the same period 34,798 cwts. were re-exported to Iraq or Persia. If the advice which I gave has been strictly followed there should still be 6 months' stock of sugar in Dubai and Sharjah. I am writing to the Residency Agent to confirm that this is the case. 4. So far the Shaikh cf Dubai has given willing co-operatior in the exercise of control over the re-export trade and he would, I am confident, be willing to co-operate in any further measures which may be thought necessary to protect the interests of the inhabitants of the Arabian side of the Gulf. Political Bahrain.Confidential, Political Agency| No,C/1548, To Bahrain, the 13th October 1942, The Residency Agent, Sharjah, Memorandum. Will you please refer to my confidential memorandum No,C/769 dated 4th June 1942 in which I advised that 6 months 1 supply of sugar should be kept in reserve, 2. Re-exports of sugar to Iraq and Persia from Dubai have been very heavy in recent months and I shall be glad if you will let me know what is the present estimated stock of sugar in Dubai and Sharjah. You will remember that monthly requirements of sugar have been estimated at 193 tons. Political Agent, Bahrain.,r ' I if' ' i C&gt;)l Confidential* By air mall* D.O.H0.6252-H/42. 0&gt; Kxternal Affair* Department 9 NSW DSIHI* The 12th September, 1942* Please refer to your deml*offiolal letter No*C/643t dated the 15th August 1942* In future you will be sent the complete copy of the Persian * not Gulf War Trade Bureau Weekly Report while the Political Agents will forward- 136 aent onl ^ portions of the Report which relate to the Persian Kuwait, Tour “ Bahrain &amp; Muscat* To The Hon'ble Lieut*Col*W*R*Hay, CIS*, Political Reeident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* 8d * C^G*S.Curtis* No*1006-S British Residency &amp; Co sulate.General, Poll tl oa 1 Age nt, Mus oat •I : '-} SIMLA: THE 21ST SEPTET^BER 1942 PERSIAN 'GULF V/AR TRADE BUI^EAU, $ REPORT NO,31 OKIE J T PART I - STATISTICAL PORTION PART II - STMiARY OF INFORI ATI0N -RELATING TO PERSIAN -GULF COUNTRIES RECEIVED IN-THE PERSIAN GULF WAR TRADE BUREAU DURING THE WEEK ENDING THE 17TH SEPTEMBER 1942 (Pages 1-4) A. PERSIA - ... ... — ,,,.1 .1.. 1. Persian trade with neutral or Allied countries - (a) Cotton piecegoods ~ ... „ (b) Tea 2 . ..Miscellaneous - ... ... (a) New import regulations in Persia. (b) Scarcity of tyres and tubes; new road from •' India to Persia; cornering of wheat. (c) Shipment of goods'from India to.Persian ports ' J ' requires sanction of.Ministry, of War Transport, Basrah, or Middle East Supply Centre - attempt to evade this restriction, &gt;(d0 Persia *s claim of suzerainty over Bahrain; difficulty in sending letters from Persia to Bahrain. ... B. IRAQ - . 0 . 1. Transit'trade through Iraq ... 2. Miscellaneous - ... ... (a) Charcoal, fire-wood, empty gunny bags, jute twine, hessian cloth, silk and woollen Pages i , goods , cotton thread, medicines, electrical goods and goat-hair, cloth. (b) Tea for Basrah via Dubai, Sharjah, Kuwait and Khorramshah?. ... (c) Traffic between Mohamara and Basrah closed. C. BAHRAIN - ' „ ... (a) Food and oil situation relieved in Bahrain. (b) Thread - evasion of export regulations ? (c) Official arrangements for transport of goods from Bahrain to Saudi Arabia. D. MUSCAT - — ■■ ■ ■I..!... 0 0 0 o • 0 (a) Fictitious orders requested from Muscat with a view to obtaining quota. ... (b) Muscat Customs confiscate wheat. PART III-A - SUMMARY OF INFORMATION RELATING TO ACTIVITIES OF ENEMY, NEUTRAL AND ALLIED COUNTRIES (Pages 5-7) (i) Greece - Conditions in Greece ... (ii)T urkey - (a) Conditions in Turkey ... (b) Railway from Turkey to Europe re-opened (c) Swiss firm buying carpets from India for Istanbul. (d) Hessian cloth - despatch from Bombay stopped by order of Ministry of War Transport, Basrah. ... * 9 1-2 1 1 1 1-2 1 1-2 2 3 3 3 3 3 3-4 3 3-4 4 4 4 4 5 5-6 5 5(ii) C 0 N T E NTS - Contd. (ii)T urkey * Contd. (e) Turkish firm interested in representing an Indian firm. ... (f) Skins and sugar from India ... (lil) Japan “C (a) Requisitioning of foodstuffs from N.E.I, and proposed monopoly of raw materials in Sxt * South China Sea area ... (b) Communication between Japan and Portugal (iv) Brazil - Japan&amp;ue control tea industry in Brazil. Pages 6 6 6 6 6 6-7 PART III-B - SUMMARY OF ^FORMATION RELATING TO SUSPICIOUS ACTIVITIES OF VARIOUS COUNTRIES AS GATHERED FROM MOST SECRET INTERCEPTIONS RECEIVED IN THE BUREAU„ (Pa.ge 8) 0 JAPAN -V' . (i) Japan-Indo-China (li) Japan-Thailand APPENDICES - 9-10 (i) Appendix I - Transit trade to Turkey. 9 (ii) Appendix II - Names of persons or firms referred to in Parts II &amp; III-A and in Appendix I (excluding Indian firms and names which appear only in relation to correspondence relating to non-commercial or minor matters). ... io (iii) Appendix III - Index of names in Part III-B. 10PERSIAN GULF 7/ AR TRADE B UBBAU . Part I - Statistical Portion. NIL Part II. Suramary of information relating to Persian Gulf countries received in the Persian Gulf War Trade Bureau during the week ending the 17th September 1942.. r •a i 1, Persian trad e v/ith neutral or Mlied-^untpe^, - (a) Cptton pi ece good s - Interceptions^seen in the. Bureau recently' r sEovr’tm : E there was considerable demandafor.'‘piecegoods in Persia. 65 bales of gotten piecegoods appear to have been shipped by Shgrkat-.Iranian. and .Go. &gt; Karachi ,on account of .two firms in lie shed durihg^tlie last week-.of ; August. , : p ; ; ppp'r- r pip. c p(i') 1 Large despatches from India - It,is :noted: from several interceptions seen in'the Bureau during the week under report that Ll.II. Ispahan! Ltd, ,’Galcutta, shipped from B-omb.ay and Calcutta over 200,000 lbs. of tea’Tor'several firms in Persia in - the latter half of August. In this Connection attention is invited to page 1 of Report No.29. 0 yGIven uerow is-a-cbpy.^oftelegram of M .E. S, Centre(?) - .42-,from Ispahan!, Calcutta, tpi Hasham'Ispahan!, Teheranr;- •p.-UirLU.c.. 'Tea steamer&gt;agents refuse booking cargo . uniees Middle r ; East Supply Centre Cairo cables .instructions'please v / ’' approagh''underhot-ed• buyers to' Cable - immediate instructions ^ 1V^:. tprough - CoteulatC'. Teheran also balayide-buyers must make “ ,, M s.i':dlar ^prangement-s .at once because' 1 export' prohibition r' : .;en : f pr cement 'duo ..Step wire urgently result, efforts Nemajee * JJ 'five.hundred chests Larakoliam fivefiftyfive’ Moghaddam Se.vehhimdPcd Ansari two seventy seven Faiz two hundred Hassam ;; . .-Farad sevefthundPed • Ghandcliari sixteenhundred Forshamader '.■■'threef ortyseven Muieshlcbar-Fars twohundred Ettcfaghieh / r .h' | tT/othdhBa;nd : ’ your self • s ixh’uhdrcd'. .; • t. J ^ tEii^spl^eetalBo paragraph 2(ii4-). Wlow)./’ 1 ’ '. V (iii) or^export_lpf tealL^froin-CMlpn -to •sto ppe d - A telegram, datod 2.9,42..from Finlay Co., ovxw.uv-’v» ou. V;oon, P.JD;, Box 3, Baghdad) states tiiat tiie Export ContydliGr has- ceased issuing ticences for Persia and Iraq. (a) New' Import regulat ions. ,in Persia - In a letter dated 3.3.42 to KanayalaT Deepcnand Hinduia^ Shikarpur, Parmanand Deep- chand, Teheran^ enclosedra cutting from the Teheran newspaper w Itlaat?t reproducing^•'^/notification the Ministry of Commerce and Industry.’regarding 1 import from other: countries. The notifica tion is, not available in the Bureau but # it appears from the interception.that the!notification requires, that before importing goods the imported ■will apply for a permit .to the Ministry which, i,f it sanctions the-import, Vd-11 approach the Government of the -country of origin for transport facilities.;A long list of goods Ih ; ,three bategoFieS'-vis reported to have been published, buf &lt; . permission at' present will only be giveriff'or certain goods like n foodstuffs ,61C. 1 N /• / ' ° ' p- : ;; '- '..i ./ : ( b ) Scarc ity of tyres an d tu bes: t new roa d from India to Persia: c omp ring of wHeatl -K~Tne~ foil owing is an interesting extract from, a letter dated'5.7.42 (seen in the-'Bureau recently) from Dr. Miss K., Blackwood, 1G.M.S. Hospital) Kerman, , to Mr. G. Blackwood, Sale, Crippsland,.:.Australia : ^ d . /'They travel^at night to save the tyres for it is veryo - 2 - hot these days and tyros are getting scarcer and scarcer. In fact they- have taken orf some of the post buses and soon, rumour hath it, one will be going to Isfahan by camel and taking weeks, to do it* They are building a new road from east to west - from the Indian border - and there is much activity resulting and we get quite a lot. of work from them in the shape of illnesses and accidents. It would be a great help if it were not for the shortage of wheat - there is wheat cornering going on better than they ever rose to in England a century or so ago. After a good harvest everyone is going short of bread (except us - we • eat much less than the average Irani and can afford, to buy other things). It is very worrying because tfe see our workers going short and can do nothihg - they are not satisfied with nor able to eat much of the meal and eggs that we live on. We are trying to get a Idrge load oi beans cheap for them to hel•p'oUt* ,, ( : &lt;* ) so^s £rc23_lDdia_ij2_££raia3_2firt£_miiJipa iJiQisixX-OOarllraasEfli;^. .attemp t to e vade this, r estrict jpg - Below is given a cop^v or a letter ; dated 29.8.42 fromGore and Co., P.O.Box v342, Bombay, to M. Hoschander, P.O.B. No. 95, Teheran •• J 'With reference to the orders placed by you We beg. to inform you that a new order has come into force whereby no goods can be shipped to Khbrramshahr or* other. Iranian . Ports unless sanction is obtained from the* Hinistry of War Transport, Basrah, or Middle East Supply Council. We shall.therefore thank you to kindly approach the authorities at your end and obtain this sanction...' Alternatively.if you are so inclined we 1 can ship the goods up to Basrah showing the final destination only as Basrah, the onward transport to be arranged ,by yourself, in which case, we understand, no permissionifrom the ' authorities aforementioned is required;’ 1 :: ; (i) Pgrsia-S _sla_ia.-C&gt;| . suzerainty overBahrain - diffic u lty in 5£C^in£lcttGra_fronLPorsia_t2_Bah£aiD - The following extrac from a letter dated 26.8.42 from Rocniram &amp; Son, Abadan, to Hochiram &amp; Son, Hyderabad (Sind), is of interest :’ w . 'I had given a letter for Bahrain to Mirza Baqar for sending it by registered post from Basrah. ' Because letters for Bahrain are not accepted at Abadan for the simple reason that the Iranian Government claims that Bahrain is their ancestral dominion. Wherever they find oil, they argue that they have ancestral claim-over it. ^ Consequently, we are compelled to send.letters to Basrah. They have stationed a full fledged officer at Tahuma who searches everybody. He asks people to take off their pant', socks and shoes even. '..Whatever Baqar Khan said, the same happened about 3 to 4 days back. They did not allow him to send the letter along with the Legation post. . They told him that he could send it direct through some body because all letters were intercepted by the Censor. . ■ Thus he brought the letter back. Yesterday morning, I sent the letter by registered sea mail via Khorramshahr. No one knows when the steamer will start/ For the present the steamer is lying at Abadan having returned from Basrah after ; uploading the goods. Now, we have the same difficulty in regard to Bahrain letters. In short, Persian Gulf has also become like , hell. We cannot get flour, vegetables etc. for eating, nor -do they grant_us any other facilities.'-3- B. IRAQ . Transit trade /through Iraq - The latest position of this trade is shbwnrin 'Appendix I. 2 . Miscellaneous - f; (a) • Charcoal, fire-wood, empty gunny bags, .jute twine , hessian cloth, silk and woollen goods, cotton thread, medicine s 9 electrical goods and goat-hair cloth - These goods are in good demand in ; draco ' It is •'■gathered from a better dated 25.8.1942 from Abdul Latif Esniail, Baghdad^ to M/s Ravji Javerchand ? Karachij that import permits'are' not ‘required for goods that go to Iraq per country craft. (b) Tea for Basrah .yia/pubai, Shar.iah, Kiv.;ait and Khorram- v shahr -&gt; From interceptions .seen ih the : -Bureau during the week under e irjeport it;d.s seen -that tea.Is being imported into^ Basrah via Dubaij -Sharjah, Kuwait and also via Khorramshahr. In this connection an extract is given beloW from a,letter dated 29.8^1942 from Koweity &amp; Suleimany Abdul Jabar Khedairy Road, Ashar, Basrah’,: to•'Y.E. Soffer, ^Bombay: - ' ,f -• r ;; I. l.r .ck “Tea,. In a previous;cable!:'you stated Shipped .thrOefifty tea... » • o and ifl;your recent dable you state.: f Tea 350 -Khorramshahr still ; ' dock shipment very shortly 1 and such contradictions may involve * r; ’ us unnecessarily in a serious inconvenience. r Anyhow, we wish you :r:. not to forget that the relative B/lading.is• required by cable very ' urgently in order we may begin working to,bring the goods to Basrah. The balance of ; the quantify is to be shipped to Basrah, i': if not possible^to Dubai in which oase the s/lading to be cabled to Abdullah -Alzunaidi^ Dubai, Sharjah Post, if not - possible they are to be shipped to Khorramshahr and B/lading to be telegraphed to us if still not 'possible ship to Kuwait and telegraph b/l to Abdul Rahman Baher, Kuwait. We are to be advised in each and every case, in order we-may attempt re-shipping of the goods to Basrah. Whenever, export permits.-to Basrah are available, we : L.;ii.Mll...certainly :-place'aaev^ ofdcrsv“tPf evioiis ; ref: p.3 of JReport j.C : No. 29) •; . “T- M t • Recent re-exports of tea from Dubai;to.Basrah appear to have been £o 'heavy that the stock in Dubai has almost'been exhausted and the rate has «gone up-so that a pound i of tea-can not .'be had for Rs. 2 / 10 /- even* ' si: .- ' • .. •: i.. (c) Traffic between Mohamara and Basrah closed - In a letter dated 24.8..1942 addressed to Sheth Madhawji 'llhaverbhai, Karachi, Raybjee Lakhajee/Mohamarastated that goods'valued, at Rs. 150,000/- arrived at Mohanara from Bombay, but the traffic between Mohamara and Basrah was closed..- ^ ‘ C -- '■ C. BAHRAIN .1 a ’t.- 1 ” (a) Food and -oil- situation relieved in Bahrain - The following is an extract from a letter written ’i^rom Bahrain by ^Paul ' 1 and forwarded to Rev. G.P. De Jong, Kodaikanal, S. India, by G. Nykerk, American Mission, Kuwait, on 28.7.1942:- “Everything is as usual here. The food shortage that seemed so serious for some weeks has been relieved. Wakefield the Consul did a good piece of work there. Five oil tankers stand toge ther being loaded yesterday and today till they fill up and go. I imagine that pleases the refinery folk for tankers have boon a bit short at times. It takes a lot of tankers to accommodate the refinery and keep it busy,' (b) Thread - evasion of export regulations ? - Following is an extract from a letper from Mohamed Bin Husein Haji Bakir, Bahrain,-4- to Naryambuit Abdulla, c/o T.E. Roberts, Karachi n A sample of thread is attached hereto, please when you come here bring as many as 100 doz.'of different deep colours; green, blue, pink, yellow, brown and red# These threads are mostly saleable in Bahrain and they are more profitable* to.,you than bringing money.' (c) Official arrangements for trans-port of -good-s from Bahrain to Saudi Arabia - The following extract from a letter dated 24.8.1942 from Yusuf Abdul-. Rahman Fakhroo, Bahrain, ytd Fa had Marzook, Karachi, explains the position:- v-;-.--- ./ ‘ 'Two days ago we were asked by the Political Agent to submit a detailed statement of all the rice, flour and.sugar imported by us. This has been presented by us and your name has'been given therein as the shipper. Today there was a meeting in the P.A.*s office and there he;,explained to us how transhipment of goods to r Saudi Arabia will in future be arranged. Its isummary/'ls as :- v follows l ' • • •' ’ ■' r; [ The quantities of rice, flour and wheat permitted by the Govern ment, of India for export to Saudi territory are fixed, and these will be 'shipped from 3 places, viz., via Kuwait, Bahrain, and Jeddah. Those shipped via Bahrain will be dealt with by ll/s ^ Gray Mackenzie who:Wiil take-over the shipping documents from- the merchantsvof Bahrain on payment of the Invoice value plus a profit of 10 to 20$ as fixed by the Supply Directorate of Bahrain. All expenses.towards securing shipping facilities 7 'etc. if added to the Invoices will be refused. The Invoices will be carefully - scrutinized, and compared with similar Invoices from others. The P.A. himself stated that the time of bribery, is, now gone, the * quota for Saudi Arabia is fixed, by thei Government of India and anyone claiming additional undue expenses willlhimbelf be liable to prosecution^ &lt; • • .r : . : 1 '-v Now that the matter has reached such a stage and gbods will have to be;‘sold at a fixed margin the transit business ioses all importance.'. r v'. *•' D. MUSCAT. (•; . - (a) Fictitious orders requested from Muscat with a view to obtain ing- quota The following is an extract from'a fetter dated, 19.8.1942 from Fars Co., Karachi, to Khoja Abdul Hossain Gulamali Matra, Muscati- 'We have to submit an evidence on the 20th of every month to the Customs authorities for the export of foodstuffs. Therefore ' please; wite'to'us as follows for the. goods required’bylyou:- Rice b ags v Wheat flour £&gt;ags, Pulses^^ bags^ Whea.t b ags and so on for. grams,• barley, cloth, ghee etc. You should continue to write letters like that and please pote that you. will get permit for instance-for 100 yds. of cloth only if you place an order for 10,000 yards,of cloth.' (b) M uscat Customs confiscate'wheat ' In a letter dated 5.8.1942 to Ha ji -K o psa •' Ha ji Suleman, Bombay, Kho j a Hass an M ohd • Fa j a 1, Mus ca t, informed that whatever small quantity of,wheat flour reached Muscat was being taken away and sold by Customs .authorities.4 Confidential. NO. C/858-34/3 C O/u -v. v&gt; 5/ British Agency, Sharjah. 25th October 1942. / / To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum. . U u Reference your confidential memorandum No .C/1548 dated 13th October 1942 para 2. 2. Following is the present estimated stock of sugar in Dubai and Sharjah:- Dubai .. Sharjah. 14000 bags 300 ' 3. Owing to the increased price of sugar local consumption has decreased and, in my opinion, the above quantity is sufficient for a period of ohe year. Re-export of sugar to other them sdatcU* and the Trucial Coast has been prohibited since the beginning of September. (M a Residency Agent,Sharjah.J GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. 0) Department. \ v \ \ V V ^ EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL) [N.B .—Thin is an ORIGIN AL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more p/m+AitiniLA t.inv* th* nrdiviarij nuiil and %a rhf.avp.r than the teleQTCtvh, It is intended to be treated, -. 1 . . eneral* responsible officer of the Department ) Bustilre, 10 32-3 **** 27th October 1942 XX No W Government of India, hew I&gt;elhi To Repeated ** your iJxpreaB Letter No. 6506-N/42 dated 26th Septem- Reference ber 1942. 2. The desirability in their own interests of prohibiting exports has already been impressed on Arab Rulers. The trade with Iran is however profitable both to Rulers and merchants and aa lont; as any surplus exists there will be a strong temptation to export it to Iran, not only in exchange for necessities such as livestock, which the Arab States can obtain only from the Persian Coast, but for profit. The most effective control can be exercised from India, by the limitation oi experts I would however prefer to reserve my views until I have been able to examine the position on the s^p/t» which i hope to go 3d. C.G. Prior. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Jsor Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. {Signature) S. 44 . MFP—1048 S&amp; P—(M.2042)—17-12-37—20,000. Designation)Telegram From To No *990• Dated 4th Yusuf Bebehanl has today November 4th telegraphed Hassan al Rahman Sharjah to buy and ship by launch 100 bags of sugar to Khorramshahr. Q Political, Kuwait. Political, Bahrain. 1 received 5th November 1942 -POLITICAL-Telegram G.T.C* From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Residency Agent, Sharjah, No.751. Dated 5th November 1942. IMPORTANT. Reference your memorandum No .0/858-^4 5 I /3 October 25th regarding sugar exports. Political Agent Kuwait reports Yusuf Bebehani yesterday telegraphed Hassan al Rahman Sharjah to buy and ship by launch 100 bags sugar to Khorramshahr. -POLITICAL-£ Telegram G.T.C. From Residency Agent, Sharjah. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No.893. Dated and received 6th November 1942. Important . ) ^ i' r Your telegram No.751 November 5th. Three days ago Mirza Hasan Rahmah tried his best to get permission to export sugar from Customs but was not successful. Launch belonging to Khan Sahib Hussein Amih left for Mohammerah November 3rd with tobacco and piecegoods. Both Shar.jah and Dubai assert that if sugar found in launch it must have been smuggled. BRITAGENT .A A Confidential No.C/1690* To Political Agency* Bahrain, the 7th November 1942. The Hon* ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject! Re-exports from Du bai to Persia and other countries. Reference para 3 of my Memorandum No.C/1547 dated 13th October 1942. 2. Stocks of sugar in Dubai and Sharjah are / ^ estimated by the Residency Agent Sharjah to oe rather more than 700 tons. The monthly sugar quota for the Trucial Coast and Qatar is 193 tons, but the Residency Agent reports that, owing to the phenomenal rise in the price of this commodity, local consumption has greatly decreased. Assuming a current rate of con sumption of 120 tons per month (which is probably an over-estimate), stocks of sugar in Dubai are sufficient to meet the requirements of the Trucial Coast and Qatar for a period of 6 months* The re-export of sugar from Dubai and Sharjah to Iraq or Persia has been prohibited since the beginning of September. Political Agent, Bahrain^§,-16/10,. Confidontial.. .ill UH \. All s 7 No. 7100-11/42. . 5 It G-overment^ of India. Sxtornal Affairs Dopartment. 0 ,£ N 0W Delhi, the /?$ October 1942. The undermentioned paper is forwarded to the 1. Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Lruir, 2. Political Agent, Bahrain, 3. Political Agent, Kuwait, 4. Political Agent, Muscat, for information in continuat^n of the endorsemtn\ from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department No.6667-N/42, dated the 26th September 1942. va^&gt; By order, etc.. Assistant Secretariate the Govt, of India ♦For No. 1. +For IIos. t 2 to 4. OTOf ;tract from Reports of the Persian Gulf War Tfalo Bureau Nos.32 - 34 dated the 28th September, ±B 5th October 1942, and 10th October 1942 respectively.5*1 (ii) CONTENTS (CONTD.) A. JATTST - (i) Japan- - Intio-China . .(ii) Japan - Thailand B. II'DO-CHINA - — '' r —— « i (i) Indo-China - China . (ii) Indo-China - Japan . JDICJS - Pages 8 . 8 . 8 . 8 . 8 . . 8 (i) Appendix I - Statistics of imports into Persia from enemy countries and exports from Persia to enemy countries during the period 21st February to POth/Carch _L J'-kC, # # .(ii) Appendix II - Names of persons or firms referred to in Parts II &amp; III-A (excluding . ’ Indians firms and names which appear only in relation to corres- pondence relating to non-commercial or minor matters). (iii) Appendix III - Index of -names in Fart III-3 9-10 10 10PRRS TAT; fflJJJ 1 WAR TRADE BUREAU - REPORT NO. 32 Part I - Statistical Portion. LULL. PART II . SiiTiary of information relating to Persian Gulf countries received in the Persian Gulf Par Trade Bureau during the week end ing the 24th September 1942. ' A. PSRSI A 1. Ge ne ra l cond it ions in Persia - A letter dated 2.8.1942 from Gharan SingH, c/o. British. Gonsulate General ? Bushirej to Vilayati Ram, Karachi, describes living conditions in Bushire as follows:- 'I have reached Bushire but am in great difficulty. Wheat flour is selling at Es.3/- per seer, ghee at Rs.2/- per lb. and sugar at n* 4/- per seer, and that too of not a very good quality. One is - put to inconvenience for almost everything, A tinful of water costs As.8/-. If . one were to put Ms minimum daily consumption of water at two tinfuls it would cost him Re.l/- per day thus making a monthly total of It,30/- for water alone. Under the circumstances one cannot hope to save a single penny out of one f s pay. I have got thoroughly fed up with this place. When water for drinking purposes can be had with so much difficulty how can one expect to find water for washing himself. I want to resign my job and come back.” 2. Pe rsian tra de wi th Allied or neut ral countries - (a) Butto ns - From a telegram dated 5.9.1942 from babb, Jan Pension, Bombay, to Michel oaab, Teheran, it is gathered that the writer nroposed to ship large quantities of buttons to Persia in the first part of September 1942. (b) Chevro le t c ars - Following is a copy of a telegram dated 15.9.1942 from Piles, Calcutta, to Haslam, U.K.C.C., Zahadan :- 'understand from Teheran there a,re twentyseven new^ Chevrolet cars complete with spares and tyres lying at Pokkundi and they would like us to arrange purchase and take delivery for them stop please proceed Hokkundi immediately ascertain full details of cars owners names and if possible for you purchase locally advise us and Teheran price for Zanidan stop have referred Government of India regarding export licence.” (c) D rugs - A cover dated 2,8.1942 from the Imperial Bank of India, Peshed, to Lloyds Bank Ltd., Karachi, contained a Bank slip for the transfer M Es.5000 from Basrah Office to Bombay Account on account of drugs sent to Peshed, payee being Sherkat Taz Ghandehari, Meshed, (Preyious Ref: p.l oi Report No,30). (d) Plecegoods - The demand for piecegoods in Persia continued strong. Sherkat Iranian Co./Karachi, are noticed to have shipped piecegoods to the value of Rs.3,77,750 to various firms in Persia during the period June 10 to August 30. (Previous Refgp.l of Report No.31), j Khoshkish Ismailzadeh, Representative of Finance Ministry of Iran/ Bombay, stated in his telegram dated 8.9,1942 to the Finance Ministry Poamelat, Teheran, that he had shipped 18,586 bales out of 22,200 bales purchased by him. (e) S ugar - demand from .India - It appears from recent interceptions that merchants in Persia are still trying to obtain sugar from India. _ In a telegram dated 7.9.1942 to Bahman Kaghighat, Karachi, Ardakani Galedary, Teheran, asked addressee not to cancel sugar (contract?) as he hoped to 'obtain a licence.- 2 - Another tGlegran dated 12:9.1942 fron Abdulla G-aledary,Teheran, to Abdulla Zainaly, Karachi, reads as follows ”¥e hope to obtain licence 200 tons sugar by Zahedan Railway very shortly therefore quote i^nediately will open credit stoio recover your and our Dubai losses''prefer to purchase through you keep confidential.' (f) T ea - (i) Pos ition of trade in tea betwee n India an d Pe rgia .~ The following extracts from a letter dated 16,8.1942 from II.H. Ispahani, Khaiaban •llonirieh, Teheran, to M.II. Ispahan! Ltd., Calcutta, are of interest 'As matters are shaping with tea restrictions there is little likelihood of the resumption (?f trade other than by the Government and that with the U.K.C.C. . . o . The Food Control here will probably ; fix prices at a low level which coupled with the 122% over-paid for this season's tea will scarcely leave any margin to the poor trader for his trouble and prolonged lock up of capital. You will moreover see by the enclosed announcement of the Ministry of Commerce that prices of their foreign imported teas have been reduced by 8 Rials a packet - a decline of 25% ll What with the advance of 100% in India.and this decline the poor trader is between the Devil and the Deep Sea : I now come to that part of your letter referring to the fixing of quotas on an average basis of 8 million pounds. Your assumption that Persia imported nearer 50 millions than 8 millions is incorrect. I have taken the trouble to ascertain from the Finance Ministry average figures for the 11 years 1926/1937 showing a total average yearly import of 11,750,000 lbs. Therefore the 8 millions fixed seems to be more than enough when we take into consideration the enormous increase in values on your side which will certainly have a great influence on consumption.' (ii) Indian m erchants executi ng or ders o f Per s ian clients_frpm_Cplombo - The following is an extract from a letter dated 25.8 C 1942 from M,J.. Mowla and Sons, Bombay, to Khawjeh Rajabali Tabaraki Dezfouli, Dezfoul (Persia) 'Actually.it is a month since the export of tea from ^ Bombay and Calcutta has been prohibited. In spite of it the orders of our clients have been executed direct from Colombo, the quantity of course being very big, there fore, your order cannot be executed as you wanted the tea to be despatched v^.a Zahedan.' (iii) Te a from Pa sta!: to Linrah - Given below is an extract from a Tetter dated 3.9.1942 from H.A.R. Fakri &amp; Sons,' Bastak (Persia), to Sbrahim Yousuf Zienal Ali Reza, Bombay :- '37 cases of tea which you had shipped have arrived and are re-shipped to Linga. I hope you'have shipped 3 cases more now.' 3. Miscel la ne ous - (a) Bund er Abbas the o nl y o pen port i n Persia ? - In a telegram dated 9.9,1942 to Gomdji Masri, Teheran, Abdulezer, Bombay, while intimating despatch of tea to Bunder Abbas port states that there is no permission to ship goods from India to .any other port in Persia.- 3 - (b) Persia^ trade y'ith ene my^co untries - Detailed statistics of excort and import trade of Persia witn enemy co'jntries during the period 21st February to 20th March 1942 as shown in the Customs Monthly Bulletin No.150 published by the Persian Ministry Finance, are given in Appendix I . of letter 4 - ’ ne dated Anglo- (c) Persia supplyi ng oil 'to Afg hanistan ? - A le 7.9.1942 from Burman-Shell Oil Co., Ltd., Karachi, to Iranian Oil Co., Khuzistan, -.Abadan, reads as follows 'Reports reaching us here indicate that large quantities of petrol are being imported into Afghanistan from the Herat siae. Supplies from Russia ceased some time ago and it would there fore appear that these supplies are coming fronglran, and we should'welcome any information you can give us,' • (d) Persian suspect firm’s connections_with_Inaia - G-iven below are conies of two telegrams wEicK show the nature of the business connections'which ’Akhavan 1 of Teheran has with India, This firm may be the same as H.M.Hussein Akhavan and Son which is a suspect firm and is proposed to be placed on the Statutory idst shortly. I. Telegram_dated_10 JL 9 JL 1942_f rom_Akhavsn J ._T§h^ran J ._to_R^za ; kzad^, Kara ch i - licence number 255 for 400 cases tea in*name Ahmed Akhavan from Central Supply.Committee, Teheran, wired to Indfan G-oyernment ■ we informed Tejaretkhaneh Akhavan, Bombay, to ta^ke action for ship ment 200 cases'tea Sharkate. Hussein ilk ha van? - Referring your telegraphs ministry r ar Transport states Fas no intimation stop about export licence of tea ana sugar ^ referred to Delhi stop Shipment to Khorramshahr and Bushire unallowea unless sanctioned by Ministry ¥ar Transport Basrah but trying for permit to ship Khorramshahr stop shipped Bunderabbas 286 cases tea and 100 - 50 cases Salamat stop Interseas Corporation demand creait for towels do you allow shipment pending opening of Credit stop 50000 not received.’ ^ B 1 -lAv. Transjt trade thro ugh Irao -.No useful information relating It trade through Iraq is available from interceptions-seen 1. to trans*~ — in the Bureau during the period under review. 2. 14seell ane o us - (a) Charcoal, gr a insacks, p i scegoods , A _rBI_cpttpn^,!ice^.. _ turmefic. gh ee, soap, matches and bo l ack pe pper - Large qrders tor t goods were placed by Adamali Noorbhoj Halai, Basrah, with. Noorbhai Alibhai Halai t Sons, Karachi. f o (b) Cold - gmuggled from Ir aq to a diacent_countries - ihe flowing is an extract from a confidential report on tne working |’ r—~ q from 24.11.41 •-- ^ ^ astern Bank, Kar of the exchange control in Iraq from 24.11.41 to 31,5.42 forwarded *1^. 'j ’ -1 ^ Tj 1 r- TD ^ /-y g r-s 4] 4- ^ T r&gt; IT', 1-4 lO 1V I' O V* O i by Dastern Bank, Baahdav id, to gives •' . w ' 'COLD. Schedule , C’dfig ur es of- the Licences of the importation of gold into Iraq since 2 granted in respect t ±th November.1941. 14th ir-aa^s very. long land frontier, it is almost impossible to check smuggling and there is very little doubt that.much oi . the gold imported is subsequently smuggled to surrounding countries, particularly Turkey and Iran where. the price, at the present time-presents a wide margin of profit. As much.pt the go la was coming, from Bahrain the authorities there assisted by prohioiting the export of gold except under licence.and although this.wouia appear to have had the aesired effect as far as Bahrain, is concern ed', it is now becoming apparent.-that the previous Bahrain traceis being transferred to Dubai and it is hoped that the Dubai authorities j/i 11 be vailing to 'place si mi lap restrictions on the export of gold.. Ifuch of the gold which reaches Iraq from places such as Bahrain, Dubai, etc., would appear to be smuggled from India and the'Indian authorities have been fully advised as tc the position. During the period under review no Bxport Licences for gold have been granted . • • SCHDDULS gQID. Imports into I r an . F or the period Decemb er r 41 to Larch *42 . Bahrain Kuwait Turkey Total Gold Sovereigns 65,441 14,230 15 79,686 Gold Liras '353 353 Gold Bars(Ounces) 2,735 \ ■ . - 2,735.' ^ (c) Leather - larg e., order s from India - In their letter dated 31.8.42 to L/s D. Abraham and Sons, Bombay, Ezra* M. Hakkak &amp; Sons Ltd., Post Box No.16, Baghdad, enclosed an order for large quantities oi leather (including G-lace kids, Suede kids, Box calf exc.) and stated as follows : Lordpn_Pppdroffe_ Leather ^ Mfg . Go.. Lt d.. P allavar am - be en ^se herewith an order v/hich kindly place with tEem. You will advrse them that the goods are required for Basrah and under no \ circumstance mention our name to them. You will actually ship the^goodsto Basrah without insuring them. When, the goods arrive and we are to pay the value, please cable us the amount and we shall remit you same telegraphically. Should Messrs. Groroon ask you to pay them an earnest money on the order, please do so.' ,14^ Lpr_Iraq fr om Kathi av/ar - In his letter dated 8.^.1942 to Abdulla Named Alsagar, Kuwait, Ali Eshak Zaveri, Veraval Kathiawar, states that^ the export of matches (from Kathiaw r ar) to ler of the Government but the same can Muscat and Dubai, ivciuii-Lcivvcu , a tabes unau one expo: Iraq has been stopped by an ord&lt; be exported to Kuwait, Bahrain, (e) o r g unp owbe r - Sion Kooby, Baghdad, sent the ran ner R I ^ l\Wo,TTT^ '' r -D t in Vo . following cable to Moshln Sofer, Bombay/on 12.9.42 7- Telegraph urgent cif Basrah 150 tons best quality salty vg ,r tor gunpowder; will secure recommendation from British forces. Require 50 tons immediate shipment.' , (f) Soa r fr o m Aden for Baghd ad the Manager, Cable &amp; Wireless, Ltd., Q,A. Beknor, Baghdad, states, as foil - In a letter dated 22.8.42 to Eastern Telegraph Co., Aden, ows-: - rt £ ne °? our clients has asked us to obtain for him an offer for Marseille Soap’ 1 made in Aden which, he understands, is avail- abae in important quantities. Ve _ shall be glad if youmll please put usTitouch-with. a reliable firm in Aden who would be prepared to 5^L er .1000 cases Marseille Soap (Goat Brand) 45 grams per piece, 400 pieces per case. If the firm cables us a c.L.f. Basra price ■ we might be able to close 'the deal by telegraph. We require a firm who has no agent in Iraq.' . 8 , .8 . W ; ' i: • — (g) Tea_ for Ba srah v ia Bun der Abbas - The following extract from a letter^dated 11.9.42 from Ali Hramood Shaya, 'Bombay, to Haji Mohamad-Abdulla Matraak, Ashar, Basrah, reveals _ that attempts are still being made to import tea into Iraq, not direct but via Bunder Abbas and other Persian Gulf ports. (Previous Ref: page 3 of •Report No. 31). The following is an interesting extract from the letter 'In reference to the tea. of which I previously informed you, I am'glad to say that I have been able to ship to Bunder Abbas per's.s. 'Dhapu* 450 c/s toa totalling 49,000 lbs, (valued at K4L,15,000 nearly). At the time you were informed that the/ K? C* ~ 5 - , and we are~doubtful whether you know anybody there. In this connection yesterday we wired to you that we shipped 450 c/s v tea to Bunder Abbas and asked you to wire•us where we should send the B/Lading. I understand, from Abdullah Lohamed that .he refuses to sell the gooes at that end, hence it vill be better if you could send a man at our cost to Bunder Abbas to load the’goods into a country craft (Boom) which can easily be obtain able either from Dubai or anywhere else. If you think it cpnveni- ; ent to bring the gooes to Basrah you should-obtain a certificate ''•'from, the •'authorities at huhammara certifying the arrival of ‘ the 1 'goods in Iran. If this arrangement is successful, well and •good, but if you can find a better way then arrange things at your discretion...^.... Y.e have in hand further 292 c/s.E&amp;t Out of this quantity we have succeeded in obtaining permit for 150 c/s only which we shall ship to Bunder Abbas by first opportunity. r *e have forgotten altogether to tell you that the goods are subject to duty in Bunder Abbas, and^if they are 'shipped to Basrah from' Bunder Abbas naturally duty should also be paid in Basrah, so they-should be shipped to Luhammara. If you deem it more convenient to pay duty ir/Muhammara than 'Bunder. Abbas arrange to do so. It is not necessary to request you again to take prompt action otherwise_the delay might probably cause shortages in the goods, and if such shortages'are found try to obtain shqrtage certificate from the Shipping igents in order to claim for the quantity actually;: snort. The goods are of B.,0.P. quality as per samples sent to‘you by air mail. Be ate sending you blank invoices as we are not going to send you any invoice for same. M ; - ' c. Bahrain Flour^rice and ghee fo r t roops partly dis posed of by the Naval Contractor i n t he loc al mar ket - A;letter from~Dhamamial r Isardas, Bahrain, to Dhamanmal Isardas, Bombay, dated 2.9.42, referred to an ordap ,pJ^£ed by the Naval Commander through his Contractor for the import dr flour, rice and ghee for the troops. The goods were ship]: from Karachi and when they arrived in Bahrain neither the Naval Xx Commander nor the Customs were informed of - their arrival and the contractor disposed of a portion of the consignment in the local opea market t higher pri s before his action was discovered. D.mmil _ taa controllod by &amp;ovt . - In a letter dated 4.9.42 Abqul Rahman Bin Lohamec ■ Bin Bah&amp;r, Kuwait, informed Fah Marzook, Kprachi, as follows r , .' iad- 'Now the Government of Kuwait has. issued an order for control bf sugar and tea, and nothing will .-be sold therefcm without -the .permission of the Government. Therefore, the prices of sugar anc: tea have come down.'-6 ''“N PART III-A. Summary of information relating to activities of enemy ? neutral and Allied countries. (i) Switzerland . Shortage of su^ar and use of powdered eggs in Switzerland - A letter dated 1.6,1942 from H.S. 'Fawer 9 ,C/o. Conf.Fah, Davos 1 9 Switzerland^ to A.F. Bombeli, C/o. Davico's Ltd. ? Simla ? .(seen in the Bureau recently) referred to the shortage of sugar in Switzerland 9 and efforts made to find substitutes' for it. Every means were being tried to make sugar go a long- Way by using sucro milk 9 glucose 9 honey and ginger sugar. Ginger sugar was described as a kind of fruit sugar 9 brought from Bratislava. It was white and looked and tasted like artificial honey. Sucro milk was made of ginger sugar and skimmed milk and looked like milky molasses. The writer further stated that a factory for production of wood sugar was going to be finished at Ems (Germany). It was said that 450 kgs, sugar could be obtained^ from 1000 kgs, wood and while this was probably an exaggerated es^i- mate 9 hope was expressed that something would be produced thereby securing the sugar supply. Reference was also made to the use of fresh frozen and powdered, eggs. The powdered eggs were made of milk or other similar albumens 9 whereas the'frozen eggs came from Hungary. (ii) Turkey . ( a ) Hides from India - following is a copy of a telegram dated 16.9.1942 from Consul General? Galata? to Customs 9 Karachi;- 'Guarantees obtained 150 tons hides Bechir and Chefik Hariri Istanbul from Ra-lTi Brothers Karachi.' (b) Suga r b ags from India for Turkey, Syria and Egypt - In a letter dated 15.8.1942 (seen in the^ureau during the week under report) to the Overseas Trading Co.? Lucknow? Peter Solarijl? Cherif Pacha Street? Alexandria? after discussing the possibility of ordering sugar bags to be sent to Syria the writer confirms a cable order for 50 bales of sugar bags on account of M/s Totah Chamtob &amp; Co, of Alexandria and also states;- - 'I' have also enquiries for TURKISH 'PORTS (Fersina-Alexandretea). but you need to sell with NAVICERTS. Buyers in Turkey will assume the task to arrange for the cabling of the UNDERTAKING in Calcutta? through the British Consulate in Turkey. Please 1 go exhaustively into this matter? because there are large enquiries for Turkish Ports? mainly.in SUGARBAGS &amp; HESSIANS/TENS.' (c) Goods for Turkey cannot be sent via Basrah - Given below is a copy^of a telegram dated 16.9.1942 frdm Kackinnon Fackenzie? Karachi? to Moreno Algranti? B.P.297? Istanbul;-, 'Yours tenth under instructions Ministry cannot now ship cargo for Turkey via Basrah telegraph if ,we..may ship via Suez.' (iii) U. S. A . Scrap, metals from India for U.S.A. - The following extract from a letter from Dilsizian Inc,? New York? to Vahan Dilsizian? Connemara Hotel? Madras? dated 7.8.1942?is of interest;-u O CT ^ iwm .' v Ir^ if -w* L ^ t-swn jl ^ SB:LA: THE 5TH OCTOBER 1942, PERSIAN GULF WAR TRADE BUREAU, REPORT NO.33. Q. Q.NTENTS PART I - STATISTICAL PORTION Pages 1 PART II - SUMMARY OF INFORMATION RELATING TO PERSIAN GULF COUNTRIES RECEIVED IN THE PERSIAN GULF WAR TRADE BUREAU DURING THE WEEK ENDING THE 1ST OCTOBER 1942 (Pages 1-3) A. PERSIA - , . el-2 1. Trade conditions at Bunder Abbas , ’ l 2, Persian trade with Allied or neutral countries - 1 (a) Goat-hair - purchased by the U.S.A. on barter basis? . „ 1 (b) Tea - large orders placed with Indian firms 1 3 0 Miscellaneous - » ' „ 1-2 (a) Banque Mbllie of Iran transferring account from the Eastern Bank Ltd, to the National Bank of India Ltd. . c l (b) Central Supply Committee’s work in Persia 1-2 B. IRA Cj - „ . 2-3 1. Transit trade through Iraq . e 2 2. Miscellaneous - . a 2-3 (a) Coffee , r 2 (b) Mica - enquiry from Baghdad 6 2 (c) Military equipment - large orders from Basrah 2 (d) Saltpetre and rubber vulcanising rolls (e) Tea * , (f) Attempt to avoid restrictions on export of military equipment to civilian firms C. BAHRAIN - (a) Food situation in Bahrain . (b) Exports from Indian States to Persian Gulf ports , 7 2 2 2-3 3 3 3 D. DUBAI - PART III-A Sugar and vegetable ghee - export from Dubai prohibited . . ..BUI'IMary of information relating to activities of enemy, neutral and allied countries (Pages 3-5) (i) Germany . * £a) Scarcity of foodstuffs , (b) Margarine industry . , (ii) J a pan - Petroleum position in the Far East (iii) France - Castor beans cuTtivation . (Bv) No rway - Norwegian Government wants jute to be stored up in Calcutta * 1 c (v) Rumania - Utilization of reeds e (vi) Eire - German submarine bases in Eire? (vii) Turkey - '(a) Piecegoods, yarn, hides and tea ! (b) Scarcity of dry fruits; mercury offered to India • . 5 APPENDIX^ - Names^of persons or firms referred to in Parts names which idence rela- -ers) ... r 6 3-4 3 3—4 4 4 5 5 5 5 5PBRoIAIv 1 &amp;ULF 1 ' r Afl TRAPS BUREAU R3P0RT NO.33 Pi3T I - STATISTICAL PORTION •• 'S - N I L '' / : 1 : : ' ■ . PART II . Summary of information relating to Persian Gulf countries receivea in the Persian Gulf r ar Trade Bureau during the week enaing the 1st October 1942. A. PRRSIA 1 Bunder • ,-ilMe_condiiions_at_Bunder_Abba,s - Trade conditions at Abbas are statec, to be dull in a letter dated 25.8.1942 from Abdulla Zainal Zainaly, Bunder Abbas,' to Abdulla Zainal’Zainaly, Karachi, an extract from which is given below Ml G-iven market cono.itions of Bunder Abbas are very dull. The merchants, .lor not having been aile 'to sell their merchandise, are hard pressed tor money. If things continue as they are, it will be very troublesome. All imported goods are lying and there is no sa^e. Only a small Quantity of sugar exchanges hands once a ’/ anG ^ zt too at a loss. Its present rate here is Rials 1 , 000 /- and at the present rate or expenses from Dubai, there 1. s a loss oi loO Rials on each bag. Fiecegoods have no sale a - ’ b ?9 ause 'the. transport expenses from Bunder Abbas to Jha interior are very high* To Kerman the charge per ton is surs&amp;.&amp;sg. 6 * “«»’ to isfat “ 730 «■»».'»* ^ 2. Persian_trade^wdfh^Alli^d_pr_neutral cou ntri es - (a) Gpat-h£ir_-_purchas ed_b y the U.S. A f on barter basis 9 - lelow ^ ~ • — ''- 1 -’— M ^ ‘ &lt; 1 —- rr , . is:an extract from a letter dated 16.9.1942 from Hail 11_was stated_in your previous letter that the Americans are buying hair on barber system. I would like to know in detail whether the exchange takes place at Karachi, or'in America, anc what kind of goods, they give in exchange ? M • - n ’ n oxciers placed_with_Indi^n_firms - Karachi it fs fram , t ®i®§ ra?n ? se8n recently ^K^T^h^red that large orders for tea are still being placed Sharjah a^d B-srah^' merchaJ:lts : in Za hcdan, Teheran, Shiraz, idiscell a.neonR - Rn „ k T /) ^nq]je ki) 1,13 of-Iran tr^nsferring.. account from th e Sastsm fe4Bfe-W., ;W vog I.ational Bank of Ind lft L^ n - Tn a letter ditid7 fhAA+Kf p st g n *&gt;ank Ltd., Karachi, inform their head office at hnvo G +V L i lc 4 lns P 1 ii' 8 9 1 al i L,hey have done, the Banoue Kellie of Iran BaT A I tKAlv the r r ac g unt from the Eastern Bank Ltd. to the Nation! anK ° A l^-dici Ltd.., . I^ra.chi, owing to the present world conditions. • (b) Gpnbral_Sup^ly_^ommitt e e ^ s work in Persia — Given bp low/ -55. ^ X T^ aa i/ij' om T a Tetter dated 51.8.1942 from~Sherkat Skharni jmac &lt;*• ttd -&gt;’ »*«». km-,, w ' ™dp r l v Au„AA f s ? result of the endeavours and representation maocDy the ^merchants, a special representative of tfie Central Bupply Gommittee for the tiddle East, has'come to PeAia A U ?X in i the .formation of a Joint Committee, for meeting th neeao of th;s.country in connection with the requirements or~ 2 ~ goods from foreign countries. This Committee will servo two purposes, - (l) to form an estimate of the articles needed.and' the countries from which these can be imported and if necessary to communicate with them telegraphically for the sale of these articles; and (2) to provide facilities and arrange'means of transport for the above goods either by sea or land. Each commodity will be allotted xx a special No. and the seller on being informed of this No. by the importer, will arrange to send the goods by whichever means available to him for Persia, Since the No. will be- : allotted by the Customs authorities of the country of origin, no restric tions will be placed pn its export i.e, the export permit will be given immediately the goods'are presented for shipment. ' 1. Alansif_iradg_f hrough Iraq -No useful information relating to transit trade- through Iraa is available from interceptions seen m the Bureau during the period under review* during '2, Misc el l aneo us N (a) Coffee - In a letter dated 5.8.42 (seen recently in the Bureau) to Tanganyika G-eneral Agency, Box 40, Bukoba, Meir Heskel Murad, P.u t B 0 11, Baghdad, stated as follows i 1 ** ^In view/of the stoppage of imports of coffee from the Dutch past Indie,s there exists a golden opportunity for you to intro duce your coffee into Iraq ’undeterred, • ■: • w: ;. • •• v n .'/i 11.you please let us have by return air mail your lowest prices m pounds sterling preferably CIF Basrah or B.aghdad, together ..with representative samples of the different grades you can supply.' . (b) LjdB* - gniauiry^from B.aghdad - Coir Floor Furnishing Co., South Inaia, in pa* letter dated ^ 379,42 to Jacob Mectabian, Baghdad, encioseo two^letiers from Continental Fjxport &amp; Import Co. '(Madras) irede unless exact u.zes ano grados were knov/n. These letters were in reply nf ,W 0 el ? Q - u 3;, r y,- at ? u l t.mica made by Coir Floor Furnishing Co. on betelf of i,i/s Jacob Lectabian, Chourja Bazar, Baghdad, ■ j 0+ ^ lamfi-orasrs from_BasrBh - In a letter etc: 1 ^ stated tlatbhl^mucfdifficultfbhgfg^^^bleio 163 ’ India ob ^ ain 9X1 ex P or ^ licence more easily from the G-overnmont of on Q Sii^i£^tr^-i:ijbfc^£_vulflaiia iijg rolls - From a. cable dated 2U.9.42 sent by Edward Abooay, Baghdad, to Edward Aboody, Bombay, it appears that orders for good quantities of saltpetre and rubber vulcanising rolls were received by the Indian firm, ± T -f ~ Thu following cable was s'ent by Saleh Sougui, Basrah, to Jacob Snashoua, Bombay, on 19-9-42 ’ ..Ship tea in three crafts proyi ^ed inside hull not over deck try anyway to Basrah stop if • impossible ship Ehorraifishahr wire . result name number-crafts and masters •insuring hare.' (7) _ Ati6mnt_to_^yoid„.restrictipns_pn exoort of millitarv 'SSPVigPfeaeiffiti: - 1 ” 8 iCTaro'cfed stated as follows G-ate, Baghdad, M. Azam &amp; Bros., Ludhiana, noto that now parcels for civilians or firms cannot be 1orwaided except addressed to Military Officers so please give us' Berlin ; Commencing June 1st 1942, the amount of oil used in the manufacture of margarine will be decreased. This will enable a larger quantity to be made to meet the required demand without decreasing the allotted ration. During the second year, of War the number of margarine factories was heavily reduced, whilst now in the third year the number has fallen tp 49 - a decrease in three years of 140 factories. Of these 49 factories, 33 are in Altreich, 11 in Ostmark and*5 in other provinces. (ii) Japan position in the. Far East - The following extracts from the magazine 'Chemical and Engineering News' sent by News Edition, Easton Pa., to the Mysore Iron and Steel Works, Badravati (India) are of interest;- 'The Netherlands East Indies in 1941 produced about 62,000,000 barrels of crude oil, while British Borneo yielded 9,500,000. barrels e The oil fields and refineries (in a highly damaged state) are in the hands of the Japanese, ^ According to Kessler oil installations in the Dutch East Indies valued at #500,000,000 were developed over a period of 50 years and thoroughly destroyed before Japanese occupation. Many of the oil wells were plugged with cement so that a reopening of the well could not be accomplished without redrilling completely Burma in 1941 produced 75762,000 barrels of crude oil with several operative refineries 3 A thorough 'scorched earth’ policy v/as carried out by the British^* * * * £ * s.tittrbes.; The substitutes in use in Japan at the present time § as generated irom charcoal, wood, coalite, and acetylene irom calcium carbide; and natural gas petroleum gas, and methane iron garbage, etc. Natural and compressed eas is ns^d nniv ■i n tin o plane* engines , the latter especially for air-dUC 1 * SIMLAI THE 10TH OCTOBER 1942. PERSIAN GULF WAR TRADE BUREAU * REPORT NO.34 CON TEN T S PART I - STATISTICAL PORTION • ♦ PART II - SUMMARY OF INFORMATION RELATING TO PERSIAN GULF COUNTRIES RECEIVED IN THE PERSIAN GULF WAR TRADE BUREAU DURING THE WEEK ENDING THE 8 TH OCTOBER 1942 (Pages 1-3) A. PERSIA - Persian trade with Allied or neutral countries - 1 taT Paper and acid - proposal to send goods from Persia to Iraq . • • (b) Sugar, tea, silk piecegoods and sal-ammoniac- despatch to Persiar via Dubai, . (c) Tea • -c • • Pages 1 B« IRAQ - • o • • • 1, Transit trade through Iraq • • 2, Miscellaneous - . . • (a) Auto-parts . . • • (b) Coal, timber, cement etc.- large orders from Baghdad , • • • (c) Gunny bags for Basrah • . (d) Spare parts of Linotype - to be despatched in the name of army officer (e) Tea - despatch to Basrah against old permits C. BAHRAIN - Trade in Persian currency notes on a considerable scale • D. KUWAIT - Groundnut oil for Kuwait from Veraval . 1-2 1 1-2 1-2 2 2 2 2 2 3 3 E. ARABIA - Gulf currency PAR1L III-A -'-r SUMMARY OF INFORMATION RELATING TO ACTIVITIES OF ENEMY, NEUTRAL AND ALLIED COUNTRIES (Pages 3-4)# (i) Italy - . «» • • • ^ (a) Italian workmen in Germany • . . 3 (b) Jews being employed for agricultural work in Italy 3 (ii) Yugoslavia - Compulsory labour • • * 3-4 (iii) Belgium - Belgian industrial firms refuse to transfer operations and technical staff to the Reich.4 (iv) Switzerland - Tea from Ceylon • • • A (v) Turkey - Hides from India , • • A (vi) UTSTA. - U.S.A, A overnment’s plan of purchasing goatskins, • • • , 4 PART III-B - SUMMARY OF INFORMATION RELATING TO SUSPICIOUS ACTIVITIES OF VARIOUS COUNTRIES AS GATHERED FROM MOST SECRET INTERCEPTIONS RECEIVED IN THE BUREAU(Pages A£ GERMANY - Germany - Afghanistan B , JA PAN - ,(i) Japan-Argentina (iiJ Japan- Chile • (iii) Japan-l-nlhdo— China (iv) Japan-Thailand C. THAILAND - (i) Thailand-China (i i) ThhllaM -J a pan APPENDICES (i)A &gt; ? p 6 ndence~f elating , matters). . „ , .• „ (ii)Appendix II-Index of names m Part III-B. 5 5 5 5 5 6 6 6 7 in Parts II ear.only in r minor 1PE RSIAN G ULF WAR TRADE BUREAU REPORT NO.34 , 7 ; Tf-,. PART I - STATISTICAL PORTION • •. ; -I NIL, PART II '■ f Summary of information relating to Persian Gulf countries received in the Persian Gulf War Trade Bureau during the week ending the 8 th October 1942, A. PERSIA P ersian trade with A l lied or neutral countrie s - (a) Paper and acid - p roposal to send goods from Persia to Iraq - The following is an extract from a letter dated 20.9.42 from Noorbhoy Alibhoy Halai &amp; Sons 9 Karachi 9 to Seth Noorbhai Goolamhusain 9 Karachiwalla 9 Post Box 33 9 Abada-n;- M I know what brother writes me about paper. I am- prepared to give you on account 9 whatever you want. You have already sent 7 tons of them and about 3 tons still remain c Please send them soon and also make a fresh agreement to supply 'Some more for Basrah. You have also contracted to supply to us at Basrah 10 tons.of Acid. Please send for the bottles and ssnd the quantity to Basrah at once. Please note you will not suffer in the least by .'Sending these goods to Basrah for sale,' (b) Sugar &lt;, tea.) silk piecegoods and sal-ammoniac- -.^les^dfchp to Persia..via Dubai - Given below is an extract from a letter dated 5.9.42* (seen in the Bureau during the week under report) from H. Amini 9 Teher.an 9 to l , J.Fowla &amp; Sons, Bombay s- n Hope you have shipped 25 tons of sugar to Dubai by now. Please ship the following goods to Dubai, if it is not possible for Irans ,: 20 cases .of silk piecegoods 500 ' of tea, and 10 tons of Salanmoniac' (Previous Refs page 2 of Report No.23) (c) Tea - The following is an extract from a letter dated 20.9,42 from Noorbhoy Alibhoy Halai &amp; Sons, Karachi to Seth Noorbhai GoolamhuSain, Karachiwalla, Post Box 33, Abadan :~ M I have the order (export permit# for sending 1000 cases of tea’ to Persia and I will start for Persia after shipping this, quantity from here. If I do not come I wil 1 send the re lative B/Ls for the goods. These goods will cost.us at least Ks, 200 , 000 /-.” B. IRAQ Transit trade through Iraq - The only information available in the Bureau during the week under report relating to transit trade through Iraq is that a packet sent by N.Khoory &amp; Co,, Bombay, to Ejemil Naayem, .20 Avenue Des Francias, Beyrouth, contained an invoice for 12 parcels of .pearl buttons despatched to the Beyrouth firm via Iraq by parcel post. 2, Miscellaneous - ( a ) Auto-parts - H.S^Abed, A1 Rashid St., Baghdad, in his letter dated 8.9.42 to S. Abed, Karachi, placed orders for some- 2 - auto-parts to be despatched urgently by parcel post. 22.8.42 (b) C oal , In a letter dated zz.o Idohd. liar z ook 9 Kara chi 5 Sa himself as an old customer addressee for considerable and sailcloth. (c) Gunny bags for Ba .c) The following is Noorbhoy Alibhoy Halai &amp; S Nisa T T ia Street,Khank Road t icber , conent, etc . - largo orders frgn-B agh&amp;va. - (which was recently seen in the Bureau) to leh Abdul Sagar, Baghdad, after introducing of Jethabhai Gokal placed orders with the quantities of coal, timber, cement, long cloth 3 rah — a n ex tract f r ori a 1 e t t^ er d a t ed •18.9.42 t r or i ons, Karachi,to Adamali Roorhhai Halai, , As hear, Basrah ;~ »«I have heard that export of empty gunny bags from Bombay has been stopped and such a time will come, when we.will hardly be able to export a single gunny bag. It is also said that empty gunny bags will also be controlled by the Government. There is already commotion in the market about this. Today’s rate is 53/8/-” The writer encloses a rough invoice for 300.bales of empty gunny bags (value Rs.58,900/7/6)exported, iron Karachi to Basrah. (d) Spare parts of Lin otyp e - to be despatched, in the^.naine, of ar my offic er — In a letter d a t ed 17.9.42 to. 1 /s Linotype and La chi- nery'Ltd,, Bombay, the-Times Press, Baghdad, while placing an order with the addressees for spare parts of Linotype to be despatched by parcel post in the name of l ajor J a C.Wilder, British Army Public Relations, G.H.Q. , Persia and Iraq Force, Baghdad, stated as follows: ”We are asking you to send these parts to the address given above to avoid the necessity of an import permit. There is no customs duty on printing machinery imported into Iraq. Your bill should be sent direct to us, not to Major Wilder”. (e) Tea - despatch to Basreh agai nst old permits, - ^ The following cable was sent on 21.9*42 by Alkazi, Bombay, to Paha&lt;l . Alrashid, Sulaiman Aldukain, Kheclair Attar, Basrah I 'Some exporters shipping to Basrah about twelvethousand cases tea against old permits in future export prohibited.” C. BAHRAIN * ' Trade i n Persian curren c y notes on a considerab 1 e s_cal_e - Tin foil owing extract from a letter dated 7.9.1942 from Kewalram &amp; Sons, Bahrain, to Haridas Kewalram Bhatia, C/0 Kev/alrar &amp; Sons, Tatta (Sind), is of interest «#\ 'At present the rate of Persian Currency Notes is 1,030. In this mail Pahanal received eight parcels of them valuing Rs.20,000/-. You have also the licence for Rs.3,500/-. If you can buy them at this.rate, please send them by post parcels, after having them censored by the Censor authorities. Please have all our parcels insured ....o You write t hast irate ■ of Persian C/Notes at your end is 1,175/80. You have the licence for 3,500/- and if you can buy that much goods at tMs rate, please send them by air mail parcels or else by post pa reals. You may also try for some more, licences or ask Messrs. Ramchand Laghanmal to help you to secure some new licences. As mentioned above, please try to send me some more parcels of Persian C/Notes. They come cheaper by post-parcels. Please try to send me as much as possible, Panamal also received hi«~&gt; eight parcels valuing F-s, 20 , 000 /- which he had bought at the rates of 1,115/- 1,170/- and which he has 1 been able to dispost of at 1,037 and thereby has been able to make some- good' profit.”D. KUWAIT Groundnut oil for Kuwait ir on Veraval - In a letter dated 17.9.1942 to Ha ji Hasham Abdulgani Maklai' ? i/’e^/al, Kathiawar, Ahmad M. Alghania, Kuwait, enclosed a Kuwait Customs certificate dated September ..14th in connection with the landing of. 100 tons groundnut oil from Veraval per boom ’Abbasi 1 on 2nd June, 1942. E. ARABIA Gulf currency - The following extract from a letter dated 25,8.1942 from California Arabian Standard Oil Co,, Saudi Arabia, to California Arabia Standard Oil Co,, 20 Bush Street, San Francisco, is of interest s- 'We did not consider the Riyal as being greatly .affected by the demands of the pearling inddistry, because the final pearl reservoir is not in Arabia, However, we understand that some Rivals have been finding their way to Iraq. These are purchased in Kuwait and other east coott'cities for gold. The Riyals are then used to purchase wool and other produce from the Arabs which is exported from Arabia!. We do not know the extent of these transactions. Also, the Easterners 1 habit of hoarding has contributed to the present difficulty. Since the Riyal has a higher silver content than the Rupee, it is the mo^t desirable coin. The Riyal at present is.&amp; more favourable coin in gold transactions thah is the Rupee, particularly is this so in our immediate area. One thing that probably bears on the points mentioned by the bank is the fact that all new issues of Rupees have a lesser silver content than the older issue. The Riyal has not been debased. As pointed out in the attached letter, the M Old Rupee' is commanding a premium of from 5 to 8 %. whereas the Riyal is quoted at from 10 to 16$. over the new. Rupee,' relating to activities of enemy, neutal Summary of information and Allied countries. (i) Italy (a.) Italia n workm en in Ger many - f Neue Zurcher Zeitung 1 of Zurich in its issue of 4.6.1942 reports'as follows 'The Stefani Agency reports that up to date there are about 300,000 Italian workmen in Germany. They are used to further war production. Thesbxworkmen are looked upon as scldiersi 1 (b) Jews being employ e d for a gricult ural wor k in It aly - The following news appeared irr ther ZSm'pBpsr referred to above in its issue of 5,6.1942s- 'A Swiss correspondent reports that 5,000 Jews are being used for a gricultiival L work in Italy'. \ \ (ii) Yugoslav ia \ Compulsory labo ur - The following.is an extract from the issue dated 12,6,1942 of the Zurich paper referred to in the preceding paragraphs- 'Budapest; The Minister of Justice has, by a decree 9 introduced compulsory labour In Croatia. According to information received from Agram, the decree affects all males between the.ages- ‘of- 4 *- 18 and 60 except the officials 9 the students and persons whose profession serves the national interest. The municipalities will register all persons subject to the decree. The administration with the help of military authorities will post these persons to various jobs connected with agriculture# forests, road making •etc* (iii) Belgium / Belgian i ndustrial firms refuse to transfer operations and technical staff to the Reich - Given below is an extract'from the magazine \News from Belgium 1 Belgium Information Centre, New fork, dated 23.511942;- 'Belgium Government sources reported today that seven Belgian industrial construction firms had rejected initial requests irom Germany to transfer their operations and techirkial staffs . to the Reich to rebuild the Krupp Works at Essen damaged in R.A.F. raids 0 n ly) Sw itzer land. Tea,from_C.e^loh - A letter dated 17.9,1942 from Volkart Bros., Colombo, oo Volkart Bros., Bombay, showed particulars of a substan tial quantity of tea purchased for shipment to Switzerland at the earliest opportunity. (v$ T urkey Hi des from_India - Below is quoted a copy of x±x telegram dated 23.9.1942 from the Consul General, Galata, to Customs', Karachi;- 11 Guarantee obtained tons buffalo hides 25 tons ox hides M.Bechir P .Chefik Hariri Istanbul frpm Fohamed Elmarzook Karachi,' (Previous Ref; page 6 of Report No.32) (vi) U. S. A . / \ \ g«S±A. Govornmont's plan of pur c hasi ng goa tskins - Givan below is an extract from a letter dated 18.8.1942 (.s 9 en in the Bureau recently) from Bingham &amp; Co.Inc,, 96 Wall Street, New York, to Hall Maherbux .Moulabux &amp; Sons, Karachij- \ 'The goatsMn market is absolutely dead. There is no chance to do any further business^until the Government purchasing plan has seen completed. It is now in process ayid as a matter of fact contract has already b\en shown to the only slightly from the regular £xbki form been issuing for your account^ Under the men from the goatskin tanners/all over the Goatskins will be purchased by Mr, J.J, a tentative f-orm of writer. This varies of contract we have proposed plan threp world. All the India Rentley of Surpass Leather Cc 0 with whom the writelyis quite familiar and we are assured of considerable business for your good selves once/the buying starts. While we are. on the subject wo ask that you_kindly make arrangements to resehye a commission 1 or us on any direct purchase which might be made'by Mr«Bentley or through Mr,Parks of India or through any other direct stunner, Purchases will be cost and freight with fluctuations in freight lor buyer's account and payment will be made as heretofore, by Letter of Credit opened either by the Government or dne 'of the large tanners. The contracts sHall be v/ith the Defence Supplies Corporation of Washington who will allocate the skins to the various tanners after the skins have actually arrived.' «/ have been selected by the-Government of various goatskins from to do the purchasingSifiCKBT. No. 7309-m/42. UOVEHNJIENT OF INDIA. External Affairs Department. New Delhi, October 1942. The ondementioned paper is forwarded to : . J . the Hon* hie the political Hesident ^ ,«U in the Persian Gulf* s y?-' J 3&gt;' political Agent, Bahrain/ Political Agent, Kuwait, Political Agent, Uiscat, for infomation in continuation of tie endorsement from the Government of India in the External Affairs Depart ment No.7180-N/42, dated the 17th October 1942.\ x By order, etc., for Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. nnpv of q Report of the Persian Exsrac t from*- GuJ-f far Trade Bureau, No .35, dated th. -19th October 1942. Q for P.R. only. * for P.As. only (4' 1 filiSyiOabli LA ; THE 19TH OCTOBER 1942. PER SIAN GULF WAR TRADE BUREAU. REPORT NO. 35 CONTENTS PART I - STATISTICAL PORTION PA*RT II - Stri .ARY OF INFORMATION RELATING TO PERSIAN GULF' COUNTRIES RECEIVED IN THE PERSIAN GULF T VAR TRADE BUREAU DURING THE WEEK ENDING THE 15TH OCTOBER 1942 (Pages 1-5). ' ' A^PERSIA - 1. Conditions in Persia - . (a) General conditions in Abadan . ! [ (b) Trade conditions in Persia . . ] 2 # Persian trade with Allied or neutral countries — Diamonds - demand from India . 3. Criticism of the control on trade of tea by the U.K.C.C. and the Government of India 4. Miscellaneous ....... (a) Import of goods into Persia against export of carpets not possible (b) Khorramshahr Customs officials misappropriate articles ? (c) Persian rice in exchange for Soviet wheat B«._IR i 1Q i 1. Transit trade through Iraq .... 2. Miscellaneous - . , . . (a) Date crop situation in Iraq .’ ] (b) Matches from India to Iraq: anxiety of London / \ _.^ merchant icj Oil mill - to press groundnuts and copra . d Tea . . . . . . / . (e) ’'.Tieat C . BAHRAIN - 3xport of Persian currency notes, D. DUBAI - Tea for Dubai ...... PART III - A Pages 1 1- 3 1 1 1 1-2 2 2- 3 2- 3 3 3 3- 4 3 3-4 3 3-4 4 4 4 5 5 - SUMMARY OF INFORMATION RELATING TO ACTIVITIES OF ENEMY, NEUTRAL AND ALLIED COUNTRIES (Pages 5-6) (i) Germany - ....... (a| Shortage of foodstuff and clothing ! (b) German submarines in Dakar (ii) France - .... ( T n *••••»» a) Food shortage in France due to dryness of summer an d increased German demands . . (b) Palmyrah fibre from India via Switzerland . (iii) Switz erland - Tea from India~'to Switzerland via ✓ . \ m * ~ . Lisbon . (iv) T urkey, ~. Opium - offer to U.S.A . (v) Palestine - Skins from India via Kuwait . . Appendix I, - Names of persons or firms referred to in Parts II &amp; III-A (excluding Indian firms and names which appear only in relation to correspondence relating to non-com mercial or minor matters). 5-6 5 5-6 6 6 6 6 6 6 7r ?&lt; &lt;3® PER SI AN GUL F UAR TRAD E BUREAU. REPORT NO. 35. Part I - Statistical Portion. N_I_L. Part II Sumary .of information re la t inf; to Persian Gulf countries jived in the Persian Gulf.War Trade Bureau during the week end- rece ing the 15th October 1942. A. PERSIA. 1. Con ditions in Persia - (a) General c onditions in Aba dan - In a letter dated 1.9, from I snail Abdul Flawed. Abadan, to Flasir Irani, Karachi, the writer points out that the position with regard to foodstuffs in /I o ^4. Abadan Is f the letter r from satisfactory. The following is an extract fron 'You state the conditions of Abadan might improve shortly. No, they are getting worse day by day' and the life is getting harder, since we have neither a, Government nor a King. .Whoever wants to do anything, he does it. For instance the'rates of foodstuffs are in the hands of a shopkeeper himself. He can sell a thing at any rate he likes. My dear, you do not know how many of our brethren are dying of' hunger Stones will melt to hear our fate. Foodstuffs are very, dear, and bread is secured with difficulty. Whoever goes to a baker f s shop'to get bread and returns safely is called a ’strong man’’. People look at him amazingly thai he has ..returned safely out of crowd of famished folk. Indians are, however, better because' the Company provides them with all their needs, but for us, Persians, only tea and flour are provided, and that too under a system. For instance, a person drawing more than 11 ryals gets 6 seers of flour and a packet of tea monthly besides Y loaves a day, and those drawing less than 11 ryals get •packet of tea monthly and 3 -loaves daily. The rest or o supplies we are hound to buy from bazar, where the rates are very high. However, thank God, we are still living.' a from Another letter'dated 8.9.1942 Abadan, to a.Madras correspondent, 'We arc raying a rial an egg rationed at C lbs. a month. J.S. Jesuadian, c/o A.A.Club states as follows :- if we could get it. Sugar is butter 1 lb. a month.' (b) Trade condi tions in Persia - A letter dated 28.8.1942 rron liaison do Commerce Meherjec, Bunder , Bombay,.while giving an account of (.se-en in the Bureau rocentlyT Abbas, to lip's Tafti Bros., market conditions in Persia'at the end of August 1942, stated money was very scarce both in Bunder Abbas and the interior and consequence prices of all commodities had come down and even so no cash buyers could be found. Sugar costing 1660 rials a bag as imported from Dubai was offered at 1450 rials but no buyers were available even then. Piecegoods market was still worse and two big-merchants in Shiraz had been declared bankrupt to the extent of 6,000,000 rials each, which had affected many.other small merchants. The writers, however, hoped that conditions would soon enable- them.to obtain their outstanding dues and remit money to Bombay. 2.Persi an trade with Alli ed or neutr al countri es - cha u in .Diamonds - dema nd f rom India' - A Tetter dated 5.9,4 from Teiarat Ehaneh' Husainzada, Teheran, to A G 5 ------ -- s r — uw xx.xx. Haruni, Bombay referred to the writers’ endeavours to obtain diamonds from Incua. The writers stated that they were willing to pay any money to obtain an export licence and suggested that' in case uat article was not permitted to be sent direct it should be despatched- 2 - via Iraa. They stated that there was enormous scope for this , trade and swrested that if no permit was forthcoming, the addressee should smuggle out the goods. (Previous ref. Report # No.27 page 1). 3 . Gritic ism of_thu_contrp 1 on t r ad e of tea by,the U.II.C.G. and th e Go ve rnment o f- I ndig. ■ , The following extract from a letter dated 9,9,1942 {'seen in the Bureau recently) from I/Iirza Alined. IL'l Ispahan! Ltd.’, Calqita, to i.H. Ispahan'i, Khiaban llonirich, Teheran, is of interest 'With regard to the United Kingdom Commercial Corporation having the monopoly of the trade, the' same is still being discussod.with the G-overnment of India. All the Indian merchants protest against the U.K.C.C. taking over the private trade. We consider this to be unjust and strong representations arc being made to the Government of India in this direction. It Is left to be seen whether His .Majesty’s. Government will force, the Government of India ^ to bow to their demand as they hold the. whipnand with regard to freight. Coming to the question of. the reduction of price by the Iranian Government on their ' holdings by 8 rials a packet, I have nothing to comment except probably the Iranian Govorn- ■ 'merit-might have been induced to take over. all their requirements of tea fpom the British V .Government at a fixed price,cutting put -all the ■middle men and they making the distributors’ pro- • fit at the other end. This the Iranian merchants should protest as we are protesting here against Government interference in ordinary trade,special ly with neutral countries like Iran,Iraq,Egypt,etc. We are quite, willing to be out of this trade, ■■ but we refuse to be sent out by the Government, - lock, barrel and stock - with their interference in the commodities that v r e have been dealing in for the- last half a century .Every commodity is now on the anvil of control.Some of them have been con trolled to the detriment of the merchants.If by • this control it helped the war efforts I would noth have any objection,but control has brought , nothing but mismanagement. ~ * It is now left to the.Iranian merchants to make representations to the British Consul for the.. Ministry of Supply Centre at Cairo to give us the necessary freight' for the .20 and odd thousand cases of different sales that we have in our books and it is af so left.to the Iranian merchants to protest with all the vehemence at their command against the. , Government taking away•their business from them. It is best to lodge protests,whether they may be hoard today or not, it is a different matter. lot if it is,, on record it will always be useful .to be as a pointer to what the trade- thought when such interference was forced on them.' 4. Miscellaneous - . (a) Impor t of goods- - into - Persi a aga inst expo rt of _ c a rpets net p oss i bl e - mile enclosing a copy of invoice for 81 bales of .r &gt; -3- ? arsian .carpets % ,a.nd rugs (valued at Rials 713,669,95) 9 , Iranian Carpet'-Co, ltd-..,, Teher.-.n, in their letter dated 26,7,1942, re quest* the East India Carpet Co, Ltd,, Amritsar, to make a T # T. remittance for the/amount as the regulation to import goods against the export of carpets- Has' been, abolished and merchants have to sell foreign exchange instead to the Government, (b) Khorramshahr Customs,,officials, misappropriate articles? The following is an extract from a letter dated 23.9,1942 from M/s Rochiram &amp;'S 6 ns, Ibadan, to M/s Rochifam &amp; Sons, Hyderabad (Sind)s- 'Goods are. being r isappropriated in the Customs office at Khorramshahr. Even the Customs employees form a clique and steal articles from the cases. This sort of complaint is prevalent among merchants. In short, Government adminis tration is carried on on the lines of Sheikh Hazal.” / (c) Persian rice in exchange for Soviet w heat - The follow-. ^ ing appeared in the Iraq Times dated 2.9,1942 T- 'A Teheran report says that arrangements are now being negotiated between Russia and Iran under which the latter will supply the Soviet with rice, receiving Russian wheat in exchange 0 M ‘ - - - , IMi * ; ,1 . 1, Transit trade through Iraq - M/s Frank Fehr &amp; Co., Holland House, Bury St. , London, E.C.3, asked M/s Gore &amp; Co=, P.0.B.342, Bombay, to make offers on the basis C. &amp; £L Basrah, of all types of Indian cotton yarn for shipment to Turkey, 2. Miscellaneous - (a) Date, crop situation In I raq - A letter from the Hills Brothers Eastern Co. Ltd, , Basrah,' to the Hills Brothers Eastern Co. Inc-., New York City (intercepted on 1,10,1942) contained a review of the Date Crop situation. This was stated to be poor. An extremely small crop and high costs of living and cultivation had crdated a bad.situation and unusually high demands from Syria and Palestine had made this worse. The Monopolists had re- ^ quested the 5.Food Controller in England for an increase in prices, -but this had been formally refused. A new committee of the Date Association.had just been elected and some of its members were going to Baghdad to see the Prime i inister on the price question. The writer'stated that if the-British Government would not pay the high prices claimed there seemed a .good ■•chance of Weir giv ing up the concession as growers were determined not to deliver at the proper concession prices. 1 (b) Matches from India to. Iraq; anxiety of .London merchant - The following is an extract, from a letter: dated 3,9,1942 from Trummer &amp; Co. Succrs. Ltd. , 15, St. Helen’s Place, London E.Co3,-.: to the Swedish Match Co, , Bombays- A ’’The comparatively large -country craft shipments by our competitors (to Iraq?) have been and are causing us an xiety. They have definitely stolen a march on us here and thereby established themselves in certain markets, which will be to our detriment if the Indian Government restrict their future export licencing policy on a fixed quota system. It will, greatly interest us to know if individual firms of Indian-exporters- as distinct from-5- Co Bahrain. b' I Expo rt of Persian Currency Notes (Prev i ous Ref: Report No» 34 - p.2 1 - In a . p-ost card dated 27.9,1942 addressed to Jet ha- nand Tejanma'l 'Bahrain- r Ravji Jlrav ere hand &amp; Co., Karachi, ack nowledged receipt of Is. 5,000/- which were to be credited to the account of IT/s Permanand Jethannal of Dubai. A note from one Ram ttxxx Naraindas, representative of Girdhandas Jethanand (of Dubai) was added to the letter- in which Rapi Naraindas stated as follows?- V- • . 4 i; n I have sent you three parcels of .Persian C/Notes out of which the last one contained 31,38'5 Kerans. These parcels were sent through Hir jimal D.hamanmal, of which please acknowledge the receipt. Since then the market here has . gone up considerably and so please try to dispose these lots at favourable rates D.DUBAI . Tea for Dubai The following is an extract from a letter dated 26.9.1942 from Gokaldas Kewalram, Karachi, to Udhavdas ^Gordhandas, Dubai?- n He (the representative of the sender at Bombay) has ex' ported 75 cases of tea from Bombay per the S.S, Dahpu. I have written to him to buy another 200 cases *©f tea and ship the same to you.” •* ' /, Part III -A • ■ : Nummary of information relating to activities of enemy/ neutralSpnd Allied countries. (i) Germany . • .. (a) S horta^. of food s tuff a nd clothing^ - The) foilowing ex tract from the ^bulletin ’International Economic News Service* sent by I.C.A. News, Services, 14, Great Smith Si^rpet, London, to the InternationalVCoroperahors* Association of India, Myldpore, Madras , dated 9.7.1942 s is. of' interest ?- n Clothing rations raduced ..: The -validity of the .present Ger man clothing ration, of 120 points, which originally was issued.for a period of'16 months, that is to 31st December 1942, has been prolongeatto the end of September 1943, without a change in the pMnt value of the clothes. This means a reduction in the cfyilian clothing ration of no .. less than 36 per cent. \ .... ^ Potato and vegetable shiortage .h As a result , of the po*tato .shortage in big towns which /is \ikely to last until the main crop is brought.in, rations'have been fixed locally which are sometimes extremely small - for instance, 4 A- lbs. per week, which is. far belovr the' noWnal consumption. A significant proof of the growing foo%y,difficulties during 1941 was the increasing direct purcha^ by &gt;the consumer of fruit and vegetables from the product, With the result that official marketing organisations werfc not able to collect more than 50 per cent of the quantities collected in 1940. Fruit and vegetable growers often u^ed their pro- ■ ducts to barter for other commodities in shor\ supply. This has now been stopped and ail direct purchases, hqf fruit and vegetables by the consumer from the producer haVC been pro hibited. In future the marketing organisations will collect the entire crops from the producers.” ■ (b) German subma rine s in Dakar - The following is an extrac 1/from letter daf e$ 9.9.12 from Peter,Grand Hotel, Khartoum. 9 '* to 'Mrs,H.fl . Thaddeus 5 'Simla :m The Afaerican we met came over ; to Egypt in. thChClipper' from the TJ.S. He saw a convoy off the American coast and. Saw a forms-V - 6 - pqrt torpedoed in a huge flash of flame. Also saw 5 German submarins off Dakar lying in shallow water together ; they could do nothing as tney^had no'bombs.', (ii) France . (^.) go od sho r tage in Fra nce due to ;dr yn ess_of increased G-orman demands - A talegrain from France. Libre, London, to GouverneUr-SonvinT Pondicherry, -stated that irom inforrmation ; obtained' from the most serious sources in France, it was obvious that the feed situation in that country for the fourth winter oi the war would be extremely serious, chiefly on, account of the ex cessive dryntes of the : summer and increase of .German aemanas. ine grain harvestLwas expected to be 50 million quintals of which Germany was taking 8 a&amp; against 5 in 1941,_whereas befpre the war iranee herself consumed, more than 80 million* Exhaustion of the cattle nau extremely diminished the butter production and there was a oeiicit oi 44,000 tons in animal fats in relation to the quantity necessary tor the present rations 1 * Pearly all condensed milk &gt; had. been-commandeered for the German army and it was feared that babies would go short. The' fodder harvest w&amp;s only half of last yeafs and Germany would take 50/o of this. Consequently many cattle yvould be slaughtered ana presumably the Germans would acquire considerable quantities oi meat at low prices and store it’for their winter campaign. There was a great development in the Black llarket, high Vichy functionaries who had made large profits benefitting from this. (b)'Palrwrah fibre .fr om Indi a via Switzerla nd - A' letter dated 19.8.42 from Volkart Bros7 ? wlntertBur, to V 9 Ikart Bros., Karachi, ^ gave a list of the writers outstanding invoices, one of which related to 80 bales of palmyrah fibre {valued atF.fr. 63730.50) per S.S. ’’Toensbergfjord H 'v/hich was shipped, from India on 11.4.42 and re-exported to France. (iii) Switzerland. ' Tea...from India to Switzerland via Lis bo n - A letter from Lipton Ltd.i Bombay, to M/s'Delagoa Bay Agency Co., Lourenco Marques, (intercepted on 2.10.42), contained documents referring to'60 cases of tea snipped on the ’’Psipingo' to Lisbon; ultimate consignee M/s Auj; Planteurs Reunis, Route Bel-Air 1, Lausanne, Switzerland. (iv) T urkey - \ ■' Op ium - offer to U.SiA y - A letter from Sisag ve Jiraye Simpadysn, IstanbuIT to M/s. Levant. American Commercial Qo.,' New York, .dated. 22.7.42,stated that, as the addressees probably knew-, the sale of opiam in Turkey was now Government.monopoly. The writers stated that: a New York business house had for many years bed*/buying opium in the Turkish market on account, of the Peruvian'Government, Shipments had been made via Hamburg, New York to Calao-, the many transhipments were probably in order to conceal the ultimate destination. The ^ writers went on to say that they were ready to enter into any similar transaction should the addressees rind a buyer or try to identify whoever had. acted for the Government of Per.uy They added that quite recently 30 tons of opium had been purchased for the said government and a special steamer sent from Egypt to take delivery of it from' Alexandretta. : M'- (v) Palesti ne Ski ns fro m Indi a via Ku wait - Below is quoted the text of ci. telegram dated 6*10.42 from CBaloi^oiei 1 , Karachi, 00 bhalomoieYi, 280 Measheorim Street, Jerusalem:- 'Delivered Eastern Express ten bios 2520 skins Kuwaio shipment this week stop twentylive bales Kuwait-despatched eleventh stop have order for' eight thousand skins Muitaii BoriycriOil buying there, stop carpets shipment impossible, till lurcher order.' . -- 7 - APPENDIX I Names of^persons or firms referred, to in Parts II and III-A (excluding Indian firms,and names which’ appear only in relation to correspondence relating to non-commercial or minor matters). Ref:to is Names Aux Planteurs Reunis (Lausanne) *6 Ghalomoieff (Jerusalem) 6 Delagoa Bay Agency Co.(Lourenco Marques) 6 Pastern Express 6 Fehr, Frank, &amp; Go. (London) 3 G-ordhandas, Ucihavdas (Dubai) 5 Hills Brothers Eastern Go. (New York &amp; Basrah) 3 Iranian Carpet Go. Ltd.(Teheran) 3 Ispahani, L.H. (Teheran) 2 Jethanand, Girdhandas (Dubai) 5 Jethammal, Permanand (Dubai) 5 Lassow, N.J.(Basrah) 4 Levant American Commercial Go. (Nev; York) 6 Liaison de Commerce Meherjee (Bunder Abbas) 1 Peter (Khartoum) 5 Rqchiram &amp; Sons (Abadan) 3 Sisag ve Jirave Simpadyan (Istanbul) 6 Tejanmal^, Jetnanand (Bahrain) 5 Tejarat Khaneh Husainzada (Teheran) 1 Trummer and Go. Succrs. Ltd.(London) 3 U.K.G.C. 2 Vegetable Oil Extraction Go. Ltd. (Bagh- , dad) 4 VoIkart Bros. (Vinterthur) 6 S-26 - 17.10.42.r* SB.LA; THE 26TH OCTOBER 1942 r. PERSIAN GULF Y^AR TRADE BUREAU. REPORT NO.36, CONTENTS Pages 1 PART I - STATISTICAL PORTION PART II - SUMMARY OF INFORMATION RELATING TO PERSIAN GULF COUNTRIES RECEIVED IN THE PERSIAN GULF WAR TRADE BUREAU DURING THE WEEK ENDING THE 22ND OCTOBER 1942 (Pages 1-5). A. PERSIA - ... 1-3 1. Conditions in Persia - . • 1-2 (a) Econorric conditions of Teheran resulting from Government control . . 1 (b) Scarcity of money in Persia • 1 (c) Unsafe condition of road between Bushire and Teheran . • .. 1-2 2, Persian trade with Allied or neutral countries - 2-3 (a) Second-hand cars - proposal to import from India via Dubai? • • 2 (b) Tea - despatch per country craft from India to Persian Gulf countries . . 2 (c) Wheat and wheat seed . • 2 (d) Purchase of smuggled and stolen goods 2-3 B. IRAQ - ... 3-4 1. Transit trade through Iraq . • 3 3-4 3 3 3 2 . I iscellaneous - . . . (a) Leather . • . (b) Sugar . 7 . . (c) Tea for Iraq v’ia Dubai • . (d) Yarn - evasion of export trade control by using country crafts? . . 3-4 (e) Agent of enemy firm trying to purchase goods in India . . . 4 (f) Indirect shipment of prohibited goods to Iraq 4 C. BAHRAIN - Smuggling of cycle tyres, tubes and accessories 4 D. PIUSCaT - Gold per passenger in country craft . 4 JUBA I - . - . . 4-5 (a) Persian Currency Notes per officer of British Airways * . , 4-5 (b) Shipment by country craft from Karachi to Dubai 5 PART III-A - SinjJ'iARXT OF INFOR38ATTON RSL'iTiNG .TO ACTIVLBIES .Qf .ENB: Y, NEUTRAL AND ALLIED COUNTRIES (Pages 5-6) (15 Germany - . « .5 (a) •Germany's oil supplies . . 5 (b) French dye industry under German control - production of gasoline ? motor fuels and methane in Germany . . . 5 (11) Pola nd - Extension of German chemical works in Poland 5-6 (iii) Portugal - U.S.A_* firm_interested in obtaining lambskins — from India for Portugal. . 6 (iv) Syria r . ,, . _ . 6 Turkey?6 APP M 8 I fl±-A ^ 8 iu 8 Li e fg 8 ?In 0 fiaPlnS e £lSll d vA 2 ci ri a^Sl! SSly in relation to correspondence relating to non-commercial or minor matters;* , # # 7c ! i ' -« PERSIAN G rULF ¥AK TRADR BUREA U. REPORT ...NO ,36, I Part I - Statistical''Portion.. ' ■■ ' • If f L . . : ; 'v&gt;/ Part II. Sanxiary of information relating to Persian Gulf countries received in the Persian Gulf War Trade Bureau during the week end ing the 22nd October 1942. , , . ~ ^ ... A. PER SIA. 1 . Cond itions in Persia - (a) Economic conditions of Teheran re su l ti n g from Gov e rn ment control - The following extract from the monthly report of the Banque Re Hie Iran for Hay 1942 (seen in the Bureau during the week under report), is of interest 'The City of Teheran F.,1. has attempted on several occasions to fix maximum prices for regular consumption articles. The passive resistance and ill will of the traders have annuled its effect although they have not: resulted in advance in prices. . Inqpite of the inefficiency of the information system and economic control our Government has achieved certain results, now that the difficult times have come, firstly has it been able to quiet to a .great extent the uneasiness of the popula tion, proving-that uhe pessimistic rumours did not tally’with the facts, it has secondly assured the supply of provisions and maintained the.indispensable transport m spite of scarcity of material...,,. • . It is necessary to make' a systematic effort: to obtain durable results but the first condition is to give the country adequate economic-and administrative armament which permits the organi sing authorities to fix’ production price, the volume of national production and import of stocks. The best method seems to be to maintain the monopolies of tea, wheat, sugar, tobacco and textile fabrics, the- administration of which is not a burden on the budget, on the condition that enough is imported to secure the revidualling of the country, with or without rationing.' •(h) Bc&amp;rcity of m oney in Pe rsia It is gathered from a letter dated 4.9.1942 from Raison de Commerce lieherjeo, Bunder Abbas, to R/s Zartoshti &amp; Sons, Bombay, that due to scarcity of :es of commodities money there has been'a continuous drop in pr. in Persia. The following is an interesting extract from the letter:- 'There, is-extreme scarcity of pioney throughout the country and the prices of sugar ? tea, piecegoods have dropped to a dangerous extent - sugar at Rials 1380, oiecegoods at'Rials 20 per Rupee for cheaper stuff .and-others at Rials 18'and these are nominal rates no considerable business can be done. The fact that scores of customs declarations are lying uncleared for goods belonging to so called first.class merchants of Yezd shows very clearly : what the shortage of .funds must be at Yezd.All of them advise their agents to- sell sugar, tea.,etc., at current •i rates ■ thinking that-perhaps' there are big buyers in Bunder . Abbas knowing very'little that Galladaries, or Rafsanjani, Ettefaghias, Roshiris are only clearing agents. There are no such merchants in Bunder Abbas who wouadgaare to buy any large quantities of goods on their own account.The result therefore had been: a continuous drop in''prices.' (c) Unsafe condit ion of road betwe en B ushir e, and Teheran - Given below is an extract from a letter dated 12.9.1942 from J.R. Rowes,.The Consulate, Bushirb, to Rrs. A.D.C. Pottyfer, c/o. Grind Lay 1 s, Karachi- s - 'The road between Bushire and Teheran is stiff with bandits and it is always, quite a to; ier one gets’..anywhere 1 wr Colivi. J-O i. 1Ucull -LO OVJJ.J.X Vv'XUil UGjIICLX UO oss up when travelling now as to without losing everything, includi ng*T\ ~2~ the clothes on one's back.’ An Anerican officer whofleft Bushire two days ago arrived in Shiraz ninus 400 rials, his revolver and his books. Another nan was robbed two weeks ago. They took every stitch he was wearing and even the leather, covers off the seats of his car. He improvised a sort of Honolulu skirt of horse hair fron the upholstery of the car and drove into Shiraz in that. 2. Persi an tr ade with Allie d or neu tral countr ie s - (a) Second-hand ca rs - prop osal to impor t fr on Ind i a via Du bai? - Below is quoted the temt of a 'telegram dated 7.10.1942 fron Abdulla G-aledary, Teheran, to Bahnan Haghighat, Karachi:- 'Gan you purchase and ship by Baghala to Abbasi or Dubai two secondhand motor car Buick or Chrysler system 1942 or 1941 Lemousinc or Cabriolet telegraph price reply*' (b) Tea - despatch pe r country c raft f r om Ind ia to Pe rsi an Gul f c ount r ies - Bombay Censor Station reports that a good number of references to shipments of tea by country craft from India to the Persian Gulf have been noticed recently. Among the destinations of such consignments were Teheran, Khorramshahr, Dubai, Shariah,Lluscat, Basrah and Baghdad. (c) Whea t an d wheat seu d - O (i) Wheat.for Persian Gov e rnme nt account from India - In three telegrams dated.14,10.1932 Ilackinnon Mackenzie, Karachi, asked Gray Mackenzie^to deliver 3,500 bags of wheat to Customs Iran Govt., Bushire and 2,300 bags to Customs Tran Government, Bunder Abbas. (ii) Wheat seed f rom India for Persian G ove r nme nt - Given below are extracts from two letters from the Consulat Imperial de IP Iran, Karachi, to the Custom Officer, Bunder Shahpour:- J ~ I. Letter .(dat ed 25. 9.19 42 ?) - 'Nine hundred “bags of wheat seeds have beengshipped to Bunder Shahpour ner country craft Bovanipasor' Tindal Hosa for Agricultural Department and also 495 bags_of wheat seeds per country craft Fathulkhan to same destination. And a separate letter has been given to each tindal for the Custom Department. Please, after taking the delivery of the goods, leave the country craft to sail/' II* Le tter_d ated 5.10. 1942 - 'Thousand bags of wheat seed weighing 100 tons on account of the Ministry of Agriculture &gt; Persia, have been shipped per c.c. 'Hussain 1 ’ Tindal Llohd. Abid for Shahpour. Please take delivery of the ; wheat and return the boat immediately to enable me to snip the remaining wheat seed .without delay.' (d) lyrchase of snuggled and sto len goofls -■ Following extractg i a, letter dated 30.9,1942 from Lj/s PocETram &amp; Son, Abadan, to -y s Rochiram &amp; Son, Hyderabad (Sind), is interesting:- The Bata Shoe Co, refuse to supply us ladies shoes for Bahrain as they have agents there. They are. prepared to supply us for Iran but the import of the same is restricted* ...Many clerks arrive here by every ship from Bombay. Whatever you would have been able to send us along with those vould have reached, us without any inconvenience and expense. Permits could also have been obtained. ...Yesterday I bought 1 doz c Coty perfume bottles of medium size for Riyals 1000/- from an American, who works in Lagraj. This man is short statured. He is a regular smuggler. He had 23 bottles of perfume and 4 doz, boxes of Coty powder. I did not purchase the powder boxes as he demanded Riyals 50/-each. He told me that he would give me only 1 doz. perfume bottles as I was not purchasing any powder and further that he would sell the remaining 11 bottles to him who purchased powder from him. I will sell each of these bottles for Riyals 250/-...He had gents nickel watches, which were.of good Quality. He demanded Rivals.900/- for each, I offered to purchase a doz. at Riyals 700/- each (i.e, Riyals 8400/- in all for a doz.). He said that he would consult his master. Let me see what he says today. He further said that he had 6 doz. ladies gold ' watches of 14 and_18 carats which he. would bring after a couple of weeks. I replied that he might bring them and that I was prepared to strike a bargain. They are disposing of the goods appropriated -by them from, shops during the loot at Basrah and Baghdad.' B. IRA r . 1 . Transi t__tr adgl.thro ugh Ira q - _No useful information relating to transit trade through Iraq is available-from interceptions seen in the Bureau during the period under review. 2 . h-iscellaneo us - (a) Leather -'Some quantities of greased buffalo sole leather, suedes and glace kids were despatched from.Bombay for (i) E.D.Dabby and N.H. Said &amp; Go., Baghdad and (if) Ezra Id. Hakkak &amp; Sons,Baghdad, probably in the first week- of October 1942. (i) Mozamb iq ue s uga r for Basrah and Kar achi dated 6,10.1942 to Kaji Jethabhai G-okal, Basrah, Haji , - In a letter w . -- — , —, , Jethabhai Lokal, Karachi, enclosed'an airgraph addressed to them by someone in London which contained the following paragraph 'gb have recently heard that there is 'business to be done in Mozambique^sugar for Basra. The quality is similar to Java TM.0. or 25 Dutch standard, and if you are interested I would be pleased to have your enquiry and against same would quote you G.I.F. Basra (if of interest for Karachi would quote you for that port also).” ^ . (ii) Sugar f or Basrah via Dubai and Mo h ammarah - The folipwing is an extract from a letter dated 7.10.1942 from R.N. Suleiman, Basrah, to Mohamed Albahar, G/o Rashid Abdul Cthaio&amp;n*Bombay 'Received your cable informing us' that you have purchased 1000 bags of sugar to be shipped to Dubai in' this week and further , you have asked us for our advice about the shipment of the same to Llohammarah by country craft in partnership with Rashid Abdulghafoor. v/e remitted to you fe.50,000/- immediately and cabled you to ship the same to Mohammarah via Dubai, be exnect the shipment to be over by this week.” ( G ) Ie^_for_Ir _aq via Duba i - Transhipment of tea from Dubai to Basrah seems to be still' continuing. In 'this connection the follow- ing telegram dated 12.10.1942 from Reuben Suleiman, Basrah, to Bahar, G/o Rashid Abdul ULcJqor,-B-ombay, is off,Interest:- 'Tea.accepted cable billlading Dubai arrange immediate reshipment Dubai to Basrah remitting after holidays.”' / d) Yarn - ey as f ^n_pf... exp o r t trade con tr o 1 by using coun t ry craits ? - In a letter dated 30.9.1942 addressed to Textile Stores &amp; Machinery Gorpn., Ahmedabad, H. Salem, Khan Dalla El Kabir No.19, Baghdad:, stated as follows:- • ' 'The difficulty ypu^might have experienced in trying to obtain licence (for yarn) is appreciated' and it would have been neces sary to be aware o^this fact before offering. Anyhow, the• -4- matter being so happened, it is necessary t 9 arrange shipment by. country crafts or booms the season of . sailing thereof ha.s •now begun'. Immediately upon receipt of the present, please contact your • .'shippers to arrange shipment by-booms and'cable me of the fact without fail,'- . ' (e) Agen t of en dmy f irm tr ying to purchase good s in India - In a letter 'with^postmark date 2579.1942 aadrosse3 to Iraq Trading Co., Baghdad, (a firm on the Statutory List.), Ram Narain, .Karachi, informed as follows:- 'I have arrived safely. Business is dull here. The article which you ordered me to purchase is out of stock. I shall have to ^o to Bombay and you shall have to bear the expense. No goods can be exported without a permit. You should obtain permit from there so that I may carry on my work with*ease. Reply early.' (f) Indirect shipment of prohib ited good s to Irac - The following is an extract from a letter dated 30.9.1942 from Kohd. M.A. A1 Ghanim, Basrah, to Fahad Karzook, Karachi . - v Y/e npte that export to Iraq is prohibited and that to Dubai, Bahrain.and Kuwait it is permissible, be'do not mind shipments to Dubai where custqms duty will be paid and the goods will proceed on to Iran in the same boat/ It is said' that the Dubai Government levies 5% export duty on goods exported from Dubai.' C. BAHRAIN. • • Bg.ygglim u _pf' eyele_tYr_es, t ubes and acces s ories - In an enclosure oaten £9,9.1942 for Abdulali Mumenji, Lunavada, MX, &amp; Bros. Kothamba- wala, Bahrain, advised as follows“~ 'Bring with you goods from Karachi as per list enclosed. The Bates cycle tubes together with solution should be packed in a gunny bag. The tubes- should be removed from their packets and should be vnapped into a bundle and -should be put into the bedding. You should bring .that in a gunny bag. There is one Mohamed Mussalman in Faiz. ■ You-should talk to him. He would ■arrange things -in the Customs. If you have to pay anything from .e. 20 /- to Es.bO/- do payw You should bring these goods with care. The business is very brisk but there are ho goods to be- sold.' In .another two letters dated 30.9.1942 to . Abdulali Mumenji, Lunavada, the sender gave the following list of things to be smuggled:- Cycle accessories such as tyres, tubes,, solution, axles. (These be put into a gunny bag)/ Hinges, panel-pins, blue tacks, Hercules seats, brake ruboers, .valve tubes,.ducopaint and a pump (These to be put into trunks), • D. MUSCAT, i : v '- •’ ; . Gold permasengex in coun try craft - The following is an extract from a letter dated 7.15.1942 from Essa Ali Mamadh, Guaaur, to Sonara Abdul Rahim Daw/ood, Cutch-Nalia:- ,'? ar °on ha S gone to Muscat by a country craft and carried with him 70 tolas of gold, which we had bought at L c 55/56 per tola.' _DUBAL.' v ' ‘ v ( 9 ) E a Dkidn_Currency_Notes : _.peri_pfficer_of_Britj_sh Airways - The 10 lipwing is an extract from a letter daTM 371071942 from'Sobhrai Gajna, British Air- r ays , . Karachi , to Ratanchand Tarachand, Dubai m-i sen l 799 b 7 bhe last air mail Iranian Notes through Asanmal . iikamdas ana attached is their bill for Rs,2135/9/- which I have '-5'.. ' vy these consignments now. It was through .the favour of an officer that this parcel was accepted. It will therefore be difficult to send you another pare01 by air.' .(b.) Shipment by country craft from Karachi to | Dubai - Three letters between Bombay and Dubai were intercepted by Bombay Censor.Station. They alluded to shipment 'by country cr^ft from Karachi to Dubai. One shipment was of 500 bags of rice and an other of 350 bags” the third concerned 50 bags of wheat. PART III-A. Summary of information relating to activities' of enemy ? neutral And Allied countries. ( i) Germany . I' ; * • ’ * • \ , • •• ...... (a) Ger^iany^s oil supplies - The following is An extract from the magazine 'National Petroleum 1 News' , Cleve/_an.d, Ohio, dated 24.6.42;- , A... / \ ' '' /1 'Germany ? in cleaning up the Low Countries and France in 45 days 9 uspd 12 9 500,000 bbls. of oil, said Dr. Egloff. But the Nazis-'got 20,000,000 bbls. from French — stocks, and another 4 O 5 OOO 9 OOO bbl^. a year from Po land. In the German,drive .on Russia, the Nazis were • r consuming oil at the rate of 250.,000,000 bbls. a year - or more than 21,000,000 .bbls. monthly on the average. Top estimates of available oil supplies to Germany, synthetic and natural, are 135,000,000 bbls. — , .. a year, with lowest estimate at 98,000,000 bbls. ■ - according to Dr. EgloffV estimates.' (bK Ffench dye-industry under German control / production of gasoline, motor fuels and-methane in Germany - The following extract from 'Chemical &amp; Metallurgical Engineering' Magazine, New York, to G.D.Naidu, United Motors Ltd., Coimbatore, dated July, 1942, is of interest;- 'The French dye industry is now completely under the German I.G. Farben control,- follov/ing the fall of the Kublmann concern, its chief competitor in France. I.G. holds 51% pf the' stock of 'Francolar' , the new French dyestuff combine, and three leading French producers share the rerfeining interest. The new ; i ; ' organisation has taken over all the stocks of dye, raw materials and finished products in the country. Syndicate and cartel arrangements are also being carried out under German.direction in Belgium. To provide more scattered targets for air raids smaller synthetic gasoline plants are being erected in Ger many. The mammoth new synthetic gasoline plant, in tended to be the largest in Germany is costing 200 million RM and is expected to have a capacity of 400,000 metric tons of motor fuels a year when finish ed. Sewage sludge'-gas is being used increasingly as a fuel for trucks in Germany. In 1935, there were 53 German cities recovering 18 million cubic metres of methane from sewage plants. The amount has un doubtedly increased since then. Germany's latest fully synthetic fibre 'Parlon' will soon be in large scale production. 'Parlon', it is said, will be used at first only for shoe laces, for toes and heels of socks and stockings and for other hardwearing textile pur poses (ii) Poland . Extension of German chemical works in Poland - An ex tract from the * Chemical and Engineering News' of the American Chemical Society, Easton P.A. (dated the 25th July 19^2), aPERSIAN GUL F WAR TRADE BURE AU REPOR T NQ.37 , •• PART I - STATIGTICAl/PORTION In continuation^of Part I of Reports 1 and 16, Statistics v relating to trade with the Persian Oulf countries from 1937-38 onwards as far as available in the -Bureau are.shown in a consoli dated fvr/oYn in Schedules A to G annexed to- this report. Although owing to the fact that there are considerable re-exports from the minor Persian Gulf countries to Persia and Irao, the figures furnished do ( not always represent correctly the total imports into the various importing countries from India and the other exporting countries- for which statistics have been given,it is felt that their consolidation may be of some value for reference purposes. As an lUustration, the'Persian Trade Accounts for 1939-40 show 17c,oo6 lbs. Of.coffee as having been imported from India whereas we Indian statistics show that exports of coflee in that year to Persia ware of the order of 1,120 lbs only. The.Indian trade accounts, however, shTO large exports.of this commodity to Bahrain and the Ooher Native States in Arabia and it is more than likely that yhere were considerable re-exports from these places to' Persia, trus swelling the Persian figure of imports and accounting for the considerable divergence between the Indiah export figure ana the Persian import figure. The value of the statist!dal tables appended to this repart is much impaired by such factors and they must, therefore, be interpreted with considerable caution, for Lhis reason no attempt has been made at an exhaustive analysis of these statisticsinthe.Qb^rvations that fo 1 low. ^* As regards. Jchedule A of exports by sea from India to the Persian • R rinci P ai v ^ ich recorded: on- the - whole so n advanc m 1941-42 as compared with the previous four years are noted below:- Gommodit.y Countries to which exports Remarks sh ov^ed ad v ances __ • police » All Persian Gulf countries Probably due to cessa- except Iraq, , rtion of imports from - the .N.E.Io cotton piece- All Persian Gulf countries. Due to the cutting off S° ods of other sources of supply. Jute manufactures Iraq (canvas, gunny cloth and. rope and twine) Lyrobalans Persia Oilseeds - Irao. non essential Silk manufac tures Spices Sugar Muscat Territory and Trucial Oman. . Persia and Iraq, Bahrain,.Muscat Territory and Trucial Oman and Other Native States in Arabia. Probably also to Persia &amp; Iraq out figures for . these countries are not available-due to cutting off of supplies from the N.E.IVRemarks - 2 - Commodity Countries to which exports sho wed' advances Tea All Persian Grulf countries As regards Persia, there except Persia is also considerable • [ export of tea by land. Vegetable non- Persia and Other Fative essential oils States in Arabia. ♦ ' . - • % / , r , t • ■ •?••• . f '• , . . ■ , a • ... • • r. ’ r . r heat and wheat All Persian Gulf countries* a . .V:’; flour i. ; a / ' ■ r, , Exports from India to'Iran of coffee, vegetable non-essential oil^, spices and cotton pie'cegoods durirc, the two months April -and May 1942 for which figures, are. available ? considerably exceeded the average and of soap, fruits and : vegetables, and .jute 1 rope &amp; twine exceeded the total imports fop 1941-42 (Vide Schedule B), During the. same period Persia,also took more ouantities of cotton piecegoods, hides and skins raw, cotton canvas, rope and twine (jute), wood &amp;,timber and cotton thread'than^ in the whole of 1941-42. r, • 1* ' ' 3. As regards land trade to Persia figures for which are given in Schedules C &amp; D, oh the basis of available data,' it may be noted that the_commodities which were exported to Persia via Nokkundi in •1941-42 in larger Quantities than, m the-.^previous years are main?^ uheat and ^Sugar but considerable increases were also'recorded in respect of fcement, Ihegetable .oils, Apices •■'textiles and fyres. During the two. months April and May 1942, the quantities' of Shellac, Sugar/' Junnybags and Cotton piecegoods despatched to Persia'via Nokkundi Tar exceeded the exports by this route in the whole 'year 1941-42. The Shellac and gunnybags were presumablygbor Russia. Schedule E shows that exports of some commodities to the Persian bulf countries from Kenya and Uganda recorded.increases in 1941-42 an the whole as: compared with the.previous years. The most noteworthy are the following - ' Coffee ( to Persia, Oman and Hadramaut), Wbod andntimber (to Iraq', Oman' and Kuwait), fettle. extract (to Persia) grains, coconut &amp; .sesame^oilsysoap -and jagjery (to Hadramaut). During the period April- JuLy 1942.exports of coffe^ to Persia, Iraq and Hadrarr.aut, and grains, sugar &amp; jaggery to Hadramaut exceeded the total exports in 1941-42. exports of wood and timber to Iraq*during this period also exceeded total exports during 1941-42, Schedule F shows that in 1941-42 exports of Uea from Ceylon to lersia and Iraq were apprecia/bly higher than the average exports in the preceding four years. On the basis of figures reported' for the six months April to September 1942, it is very probable that exports ol tea to those cquntnes during the year 1942-43 will be higher ?n^ 11 ;n IricreasGS ex P or ^ s °T cardamom to Bahrain and Arabia'in r^l-42 as compared .with the previous years are also noticed. Oonsiaerable quantities of rubber and tea were exported to Iraq and nahrem Islands respectively during the six months April-September , fb Schedule J shows that the export trade of Aden is mainly limited to the three adjacent countries viz. Saudi Arabia, Yemen and Muscat rerritorylincluding Trucial Oman and Kuwait), of which the first two are the most important. Exports are said to be .controlled but only to the extent that they are not permitted to exceed pre-war levels, xxcept in the case of fruits-and vegetables and kerosene oil there was generally a decline in exports of the principal commodities 1 rom Aden to Saudi Arabia, Yemen and Muscat Territory in 1941 as compared with 1940. During the first five months of 1942 the export trade in a few minor commodities showed' some advance, the most noteworthy being the increased shipments of coffee to Muscat xerr 1 tor* and Iraq. . w- 4 - of the instruments. It is only they rho^can carry on in this Company and pull on here in this place. 1 . £cnera 1 _conditions - exorbitant_price of fpgd_etc^_in Baghdad - The'following is an extract from a ^tter dated 7.10.1^ from A.V. Martin, I.S. Rys., S.C.H., Baghoad j.ytp Gr.,H.- Lai tin, 3 » * C.I. My., Abu Road, India . 'i L ■ : 'Prices rise hourly, here are.a few to compare with those oi • ;• India , Loaf bread 9 as. a loaf BQejf 6 Fs. a bottle Tea •' 4 Rs.a lb. Lhisky 40 Pe. a bottle G-hed BO Pe. a kerosene .oil tinful’ Rice 100 Rs., t a bag. Atta ‘ -2 Rr.a'seer Sugar - On rations, 2 seers a month per head, at IRe 2 as. a seer. In fact, nearly everything is up in the skies - and rocketing.' 2; Li seel lane ous ~ ‘ •• : (a) Oernent_ L _grpiindnuts_and_matches_-_prpppsgl_fpr__sendin£_to Karachi, *Lohd. Abdullah'Latrook, Basrah, stated that he had remitted telegraphically to Fahad Larzook Rs, 10,000 to be •placed at- the ^ addressee's disposal and asked him to send matches, groundnuts ano cement to Basrah direct if possible or, in the alternative, co Khorramshahr by a boat with instructions to the boatman to sneak to him (the writer) on telephone on reaching at Fao.so Lhat he &gt; might'-heIp the boatman in expediting matters onward. .- (b) Hides_z_arrangement„fpr_importing._intp_Irao_gnd._Turkey Lcrb n 'Ct t Tii Rt.fif] firm of Befrhaad - From a letter-, dated 22.9.1942 • f ere iirm on ■ Lne la.n.;.er juisoy, bo aeveiup w± on oiio auui &lt; by importing hides from India into Iraq 'ind Turkey and that the scheme, would be financed by the Baghdad firm. The addressees we: instructed to declare the goods in the shipping, documents as 'in transit to Turkey' and the writers shoula;'be shown as ultimate 6 onsignees,the B/L to be made out to the order'of the Baghdad fixm^ or their correspondents, according to their instructions. In ano the i. letter dated 25.9.1942 the- Turkish firm informed the Bombay firm that A .B/.Shubbar -of Baghdad who visited Turkey:would communicate with the addressees after return to Baghdad in connection with the purchase of 1000 Karachi dry cowhides, and 1000 Agra dry arseni- cated cowhides of which half the quantity was - to be sent to Iraq for Shubbar and the othdr half to Turkey for the writers. They repeated their instructions conveyed in their first letter and added that in preparing certificates of origin the writers should not declare any named if possible. If absolutely necessary only the writers f name or preferably Lr. ShubbaRs or his Bombay correspondents' navie' may be inserted. The letter concluded with the following remarks 'Ke shall be glad in case it w i 11 - b e. - pq s sib Id for you-to come to business with our Baghdad friend not only for hides which -he will be importing -for Ifaa -.but also through his financing lo arrange the ’means for some additional business between us as well. ..... vf ■’ ■ 'V. (c) Til-seed intended for Bas-rah despatc hed to .Dubai In a letter dated 13.lD.l542 Lohd. Yusuf Fakhisoo, c/o Fahad A1 Larzook, Karachi, informed Abdullah Yus iff Fak-hroc, c/o Ahmad A1 Ghanim,-14- SCHEDULE B OF Ci €X STATE:ENT oIIOKIRf TOTAL EXPORTS ( INCLUDING RE-EXPORTS) BY SEA RTAIII SELECTED. ARTICLES EROLLINDIA TO COUIITRI^ BORDERING ON THE PERSIAN GULF DURING APRIL aND MAY, 1942. (FIGURES ROT YejT AVAILABLE FOR LATER MONTHS), Commodity Persia Iraq .Bahrain Islands JasKat Terri tory k T. Oman Other Native r States- 'in Arabia Coffee(Cwt) 80 7,348 7,985 3,769 7,855 Coir, manu factured (excl. rope) . . 41 2,‘506 (a) (a) (a) (Cwt) Dyeing and Tanning subs-, tances - -Myrobalans&gt; (Cwt) | 53 (a) (a) -Llyrobalan ^ . Extracts &gt; (Cwt) &gt; 1.(53) (a). (a); • Total of fruits and vegetables (inc. dfied, salted' or pre served, not being canned, or bottled) (Ii.) (aj 16,198 9,114 Drain, pul’s e and flour # • -pulses(Ton) 13 9 -rice(Ton) 22 9 1,185 (158) -rice flour(Ton) • • (a) (a) -Wheat(Ton) 9 O 3,508 13 -Wheat flour(Ton) • • , 52 -Other grains(Ton) 9 * Dams &amp; Resins, all sorts(Cwt) 1 (a) 335 (335) (a) Hides &amp; Skins, raw,all sorts (Ton) 138 (a) \clj (a) Note! * Figs- in (a; indie bracket i: ntes that (a) (a) Figures shown un der Persia relate to 'Total of dye ing and tanning / . ' • substances.' (a) (a) Fig. shown under Iraq relates to 'Fresh fruits and vegetables' only. The total quanti ty of dried fruits (a) (a) &amp;. vegetables ex- • * ported to Irq/g during April-'lay 1942 amounted to ** 2386 tons. 20 112 3,472 7,147 (515) 16 (a) 12 38 • 1 210 ' ' 938 15 161 (a) (a) (a) (a) icato share of re-exports, igures arc not available.&amp; Commodity .-Persia Iraq Lac,all sorts(Cwt).. Leather - Hides or.. — ; 'Skins, tanned or dressed (Ton) (a) 155 Metals.ores a' minerals - Copeer wrought &amp; other sorts . . (Cwt) 25 Iron, nif: (Ton) 12 Steel tars (Ton) 16 Iron or Steel manufactures 1 (Ton) 135 Lead, p.ig(Cwt) .. J ^ Lead,other &gt; sorts (Cwt) ,. , I 43 Tin,wrought &amp; unwrought. .' .. (Cwt) • • Zinc or / Spelter(Cwt) • * Oils,mineral (gals.) .. (a) Oils,vegetable, 0 on-essential, 11 sorts( iii556 .. (gals.) 44,740 Precious stones and pearls, unset (L,) • • Provisions - -butter(Cwt)| — -other 0 (a) sorts(Cwt) 3 2,563 Rubber manu factures 118 (Ks. 000 )_ (a) -15- SCffijDULE B -■Contdi Islands Terri- Native &gt; tory k States .... ' T. Oman in Arabia Remarks (a) 10 300 (300) G ( 6 ) 107 (a) TaT (a) (a) 9,161 (9,161) &lt; . (a) (a) Ta7 (a) Re-export figs, are not avail able. . Fig. shorn re lates to'Iron, excluding ore,' Figures shown relate to 'Iron or Steel.'' ..) Re-export figs, are not avail able. Re-export figs, are not avail able. (a) 6,009 6,676 I ; -;r (a) (a) Note Figs, in bracket indicate share of re-exports,, (a) indicates that figures .are not available./ ( ' (1 V No.C/1776. (*9 ^ Political Agency, Bahrain, the 25th November 1942. To The Residency Agent, 3harjah. ■ E Memorandum I enclose for your information a copy of an extract from a letter dated 7th October 1942 from Ratanchand Tarachand Gajria, Dubai, to Sobraj Jamnadas Gajria, Karachi:- 'Insure all the goods and consign them for Margavan. The reason for consigning them for Margavan is that the authorities at Dubai have imposed control on the prices of rice and therefore they do not allow the merchants to earn. Besides that, the cost of exporting from Dubai comes to Rs.3/- per bag and that too is not permitted for the present. We have good influence at Margavan, therefore, we shall get good rates, and we shall be able to send the goods out easily. I have come to this decision after con sulting a good Arab gentleman. Here we will get good profit because of no control. I have arranged with one good Arab gentleman for taking these goods to Vajireljub which is a small town near Margavan; there we will get Re.l/- to'F;.2/- raore on each bag and will also get all the facilities. The Shaikh of Dubai at present has adopted such a trade policy whereby he alone can benefit to the exclusion of others. n The place referred to as 'Margnvan' is presumably Umm al Qaiwain. Political Agent, Bahrain.i -/ s a C H E T. K0.7876-K/42. J $ Government of India. External Affairs Department. Dated New Delhi, the //^November *42. The undermentioned paper is forwarded to the: 1. Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 2. Political Agent, Bahrain, 3. - ' Kuwait, 4. * ' Muscat, for information,in continuation of endorsement from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department No.7700-N/42, dated the 9th November 1942. \ _ F ! ° By order, etc., Assistant Secretaryjko the Govt, of India. ♦For No.l. ♦ Copy of report of the Persian Gulf War ♦For lJos.2, + Extract from 3 &amp; 4. Trade Bureau, No.38, dated the 9th November 1942.^ A &lt;&gt;) . NO.8025-N/42. \j.' P GOVERNMENT OP INDIA.. &amp; W External Affairs Department. Ne w QeIhi, tn.eJt/&amp; Noveraber 1942. The underjoentioned paper is forwarded to she political Vgent, Bahrain, for inforaation 9 in continuation of endorsement from the Gowernment of India in the External Affairs Depart ment No.787b~N/42, dated the 16tn Nowember 1942* By oruer 9 etc.. As diet an V Secretary to the GoTonmmt of India* Extract from Re-oort of the Persian Gulf ar Tra3e Bureau, Mo. B9, dated the 16th November 1942.SECRET. No.81£_ GOVERNMENT. OF INDIA External Affairs Department New IJelhi, the/^ igrtsaber 1942. The undermentioned paper ia forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information in continuation of endoraement from the Government of India in the External Affair a Depart ment NO.8025-N/42, dated the 21at November 1942. By order, etc.. Assistant-Secretary to the Government of India§ : v * t/« q. ' Political Resident, Bushire. Government of India, New Delhi. 1 &lt;A^ y P O Telegram From To No. 418* Dated 2nd February, 1943. For Weightman. Please see page 2 Persian Gulf War Trade Bureau Report No. 44. Tea. what does ’’O.N.S. in Arabia' mean ? - Britconsul. Government of India, New Delhi. Political Resident, Bushire* Telegram From To No. 872. Dated 4th, received 5th February, 1943. For Prior. Your telegram No. 418 February 2nd. rt O.N.S. rt stands for 'other native states in Arabia.' Curiously enough this ancient phrase connotes Yemen Hadramaut Kuwait and Saudi Arabia. - Britconsul. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire•a QOKFIDSITTIaL. No. 690-S. V B- ’ _ nT%l L f 2&gt; # | British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, Dated the £9th July 1943. * 1 2 3 A copy of the undermentioned document is forv/arded, v/ith compliments, to 1 . The Political Agent, Kuwait. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain.v 3. The Political Agent, Muscat. with reference to Residency Printed Letter No.C/402, dated the 31st August 1941. Government of India, Commerce Department, Office Memorandum No.68(2)-B.T.(A)/43, dated the 5th May 1943.(Received under S.A.D. Endorsement .N0.3388-N/43, dated 13/5/43) 'o.60(2)-J.T.(A)/43. Qovornnent of -India. Depp rtnent of Comerce. S ini a, tho 6~ ft~ ::Hky : t 1^3. v? (9 Office Monorandun. Vitlraeferengo to this Department Office Memorandum No. ^0(6)-_,.i.(A)/4i, dated the, 4th July 1941 s to the Home Department, etc., regarding the creation of the Persian Gulf War Trade Bureau attached-to this Department, the_undersigned is directed to inform the Home Department, etc., that in view of the fact that circumstan ces have.so changed* since the establishment of the Bureau, as to deprive- it, in a large measure, of its utility, it has, been 'decided to abolish the Bureau with effect from.the 1st May 1943. for Deputy feecry/tary to the Government of India. To The Home Department. The external Affairs Department (with 5 spare copies), the Political Department. The Central Board of Revenue. The Supply. Department. The General Staff Branch (G.H.Q.) Tho General Staff Branch (Chief Censor, India) (with 20 spare copies). The Tar Department (Navy Branch] The Director, Intelligence bureau. The Finance Department. The Communications Department.No.68(2)-E,T.(A)/43. . Copy also forwarded to:- 1. The Econoraic Adviser to the G-overnnent of India. 2. The Controller of Enemy Tradin' in India, Bombay (with 20 spare copies). O • 4. • 6. 7. The Director of Commercial Intelligence, Calcutta. The Director of Statistics, Calcutta. The Collector of Customs, Bonbay/CalcuttaAiadras/Earachi. Th; Principal Officer, Mercantile Marino Department, Bonbay/Caleutta/i.'adras/Karachi . The Export Trade Controller^, Bonbay/Caleutte/Madras/I^rach By order, etc., Under Secretary to (yio/Government of India, A/ ^ - 7 2</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000085_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/737</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000085</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/737</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 28/42 Persian Gulf War Trade Bureau Reports’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1943</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-13T10:54:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (95 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 92-93) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 95; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional mixed foliation/pagination sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-94; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.Two previous foliation sequences, which are also circled, have been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises: 1) copies of extracts, or complete copies of, Persian Gulf Trade War Bureau reports, numbered 29 to 37, and issued weekly and dated between 15 August 1942 and 2 November 1942; 2) copies of correspondence concerning the re-export trade from the Arab Coast, chiefly from Dubai to Persia [Iran] and other countries.The Persian Gulf Trade War Bureau reports are arranged by country (Persia, Iraq, Bahrain, Kuwait, Dubai) and by subject or commodity (sugar, tea, cotton, etc.). They contain extracts and intelligence gleaned from intercepted mail and telegraphic correspondence, chiefly from merchants but also from newspapers and other organisations, and report on a range of subject matter related to trade, including: suspected or known cases of smuggling, fictitious orders used to increase quotas, and the re-export trade from Dubai. Some of the reports contain intelligence relating to wartime developments in Europe, which is struck through in red or blue pencil. The final report in the file (ff 76-87) contains statistical tables showing trade in various commodities between India and the key ports of the Persian Gulf.Correspondence related to the re-export trade from Dubai chiefly takes place between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Lieutenant-Colonel William Rupert Hay; Lieutenant-Colonel Charles Geoffrey Prior), the Political Agent at Bahrain (Edward Birkbeck Wakefield), and the Residency Agent at Sharjah (Khan Sahib Saiyid ‘Abd al-Razzaq), and discusses the reasons behind the flourishing re-export trade from Dubai, methods of limiting the re-export trade, stock levels of sugar in the Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Interception of communication</topic></subject><subject><topic>Market intelligence</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Dubai</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Smuggling</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trade (practice)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Imports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000085#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>