<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00025e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T06:04:23.534Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">of 193? Britisn Residency &amp; Consulate General, Bustire* Bated the 17 ^ February 1937. Memorandum. Beferenoe attached copy of petition dated January 1937 addressed by Messrs Khubchand Bamodardas Karachi, to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, of which a copy has already been sent to the Residency Agent, Sharjan. tne Residency ^gent, Sharjah, to institute enquiries into the petitioners* claims, render them or their agent such assistance as possible, and report the results. The petitioners have been directed to approach the Residency Agent, Sharjah, on tne subject I shall be obliged if you will instruct Secretary ti olitical Resident in t] ;ian Gulf* By OrderKaraoii/datel January 1937 To The honourable the Political Resident in the Persian dulf, Bushire. ■ Respected Sir, Je the undermentioned British subjects having come to know £bout your honour's generosity, equity and GJnristian piety, and being seriously grieved at tne treatment meted out to our legitimate rights within the jurisdiction of your honour, hereby beg to encroach upon your honour's most valuable time with tne d hope that your honour will redress tie wrong perpetrate upon us for no fault whatsoever. Ve tne petitioners beg to state as follows;- 1 . That we tne petitioners were carrying on business at Dubai till lately. 2. That we the petitioners have since closed our business at the above-mentionemplace (Dubai, in Persian Gulf) and are now residing under the British Buie in Karachi. s 3. That during tne time we were carrying on our busines at Dubai within your honour's jurisdiction, we had advanceolsaveral sums of moneys to several parties sno.vn in tne schedule hereinafter given which have remained unrecovered in spite of constant demands made to txie authorities from ti$e to time. 4. That we had complained to the then Political Agent * of Oharga (Snarjaa), Isa bin ibdul Latif who unfortunately did no tiling in tne matter. 5. That subsequently we approached the Besidency Agent who was kind enough to have taken a sympathetic look at the Tatter amd seeijsto ftave forwarded the oapersyour aonour for disposal. 6 . Haat it is siaae long that we nave waited and nave not aeard anytning fron your iaonoar from any one else. ?• inat we na/e left no stone unturned to reoover tne amounts by instalments. 8 . mat before our representative left Dubai, he approached the Residency Agent and offered him an application which was not accepted on the ground that it would be taken at the time of Ohuffal. 9. fiat tie present petition is a last resort of the nurable petitioners. 10 . that we the petitioners humbly pray that youi^ionour ; will be graciously pleased to take personal interest in the matter and be pleased to assist the petitioners ip the recovery of their rightful dues. 11. That as consequence of the efforts of your honour ohQuid the onject of the humble petition be served your honour's humble petitioners siall ever oray for your honour’s long life and prosperity. Je beg to remain, Resnected Sir, ts your most obedient server Borrower Schedule Amount Khubchand Damodardas. ^ate Remarks Rasir oin Rs• 2&lt;3?,00/- £ 6 tn Jumada In the joint Rasaid of Jram al-Thani, 47 name of the ul-Q.aiwam petitioners &amp; Rat an ch and oc Tar^^is Rs. 2 500/- paid Muhammad bin Rs.27600/- 1 st Shaban Bayat of Dubai 1348 Total - ’* SDSOO/- Mil Less received 2500/- Net balance due Rs.48300/- ( Rupees fottyeigat thousand uc three hundred only ^opy forwarded to the Residency Agent at Sharjah. Address:- Kan Demand Lamodaraas, Bombay Bazar, Rampart Row, Karachi.Political Agency, wo.91-B/10-4. - \ Bahrain, the 10th Marcn 1907. To, The Hesioency iTgent, Sharjah. Memoranaum. Reference petition datea January 1937 adaressea by Messrs. Khubchand Danioaardas, Karachi, to^the hodourablt the Political l^esiaent in the Persian ^ulf, oi* which a copy * has alreaay been sent to you. ^ 2 . Please institute enquiries into the petitioner: claims, render them or their agent such assistance as ^ossibl ana report the result. The petitioners have been #irecteu to approach you am the subject. v Captain, lor Poii'Cicai Agent, Bah rainN0.1U4-B/1U.4 Political Agency, Bahrain, the bth April 1938. To, The Residency Agent, Sharjah. I. n Memorandum. Reference my memorandum No.91-B/l0-4 dated 10th March 193V regarding the claims of Messrs. Khubchand Lamodardas of Karachi against certain Trucial Coast subjects Please let me know how the case stands for Political Agent, Bahrain</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00025e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1871</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00025e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1871</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File B/10 IV CLAIMS OF MESSRS KUCHBAND DAMODARDAS OF KARACHI AGAINST THE SUBJECTS OF THE SHAIKH OF SHARJAH’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-01-18T00:50:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 8; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-6; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence relating to a debt recovery claim in 1937 made by Messrs Khubchand (also spelt Kuchband) Damodardas, merchants of Karachi, against two subjects of Umm ul-Qaiwain [Umm Al Qaiwain] and Dubai respectively. The correspondence consists of the following four items: a petition from Messrs Khubchand to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; a memorandum from the Secretary to the Political Resident to the Political Agent, Bahrain; two memoranda from the Political Agent, Bahrain to the Residency Agent, Sharjah. The memoranda concern the commencement of an investigation into the claim, to be carried out by the Residency Agent, Sharjah and reported to the Political Agent, Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Messrs Khubchand Damodardas</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Umm ul-Qaiwain</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Debt recovery</topic></subject><subject><geographic>Dubai</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Claims</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00025e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>