<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000f3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T02:51:32.115Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Ujn N.c (i) CONFIDENTIAL No. 13 - S PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. the 2nd January, 1947. To The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Muscat. His Majesty*s Consul, Bushire /■ MEMORANDUM Copy is enclosed for information of an extract from the “Iraq. Times” of the 31st August, 1946, regarding a proposal to form an Iraqi Shipping Company. Shaikh River Transport Company, has already approached His Majesty*s Consul General to enquire whether His Majesty* s Government would have any objection to the establishment of an Iraqi Shipping Line by himself and certain associates. His Majesty’s Consul General has been informed, in reply to a request for instructions, that there can be no question of objection to such a project by His Majesty’s Government but that in view of the doubtful economic value of such a line of ships run by Iraqis in competition with infinitely more experienced shipowners no encouragement should be given. 2 Michael Hanna Shaikh, a partner in the Hanna /} Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Confidential, BAHRAIN RECEII9 A m mx.zm , Em t i m es,, - gw august ,, ims. There is an interesting news about a proposal to form an Iraqi shipping company. Mr. Albert G. Asfar has been consulted by the Ministerial Committee as an expert on the subject and has put before them a plan for the formation of a company, of which the main points are as follows : - The shares of the company should be limited to ID. 2,000,000. The company would buy six ships at first, the freight of each not to be less than 6,000 tons. As a financial guarantee, some of these ships would be mortgaged with London companies, through the Baltic Exchange, a method practised by the most famous and rich world shipping companies. Shares to be offered on the market, 61 per cent to Iraqis only and the remaining 49 per cent to Iraqis and foreigners together. Ro sale or transfer of shares to others would be performed without the consent of the managing committee. If subscriptions within one year from the date of issue of shares did not reach ID. 2.000,000 the remainder of shares would be mortgaged by the Privy furse, at an interest not exceeding 2i per cent per annum. The Privy Purse would ./r have the right to sell the mortgaged shares, keeping in mind that not more than 49 per cent of the issue total is to be sold to foreigners. British shipping companies in Iraq who have sea lines, like Stricks, Grey Mackenzie and African and Eastern should be urged to buy shares, in order to prevent competition and to pave the way for the inclusion of the Iraqi shipping company in the pool now organised by the leading foreign shipping companies. A managing committee of five persons, would be selected from share-holders, under the supervision of the Communica tions Ministry, the number of Iraqis so selected not to be less than three out of five. Co-operation of the Managing Committee with British shipping companies in Iraq. Members of the Iraqi Managing Comnittee would have the right to amend, postpone or reject decisions taken by a foreign firm navigating an Iraqi ship. If the managing committee authorised a foreign firm to navigate Iraqi ships, this firnfmust submit to the former a detailed account of each voyage of an Iraqi ship showing income and expenses, confirmed by receipts. The Company* s agents abroad must be of wide experience and specialised in shipping work. They should preferably be shipowners who have connections with Iraq and have agents in Iraq, in order to prevent competition. The head office of the company should be in London to fix dates of shipping and consigning, receive payments, repair and clean ships, appoint or dismiss masters and crew, buy or sell or replace ships as necessary and perform every thing connected with the management of ships, as known and practised by all shipping companies which have sea connections with Iraq. Copied G.A.”.INDIA OFFICE RECORDS 3^ MICROFILM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000f3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1508</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000f3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1508</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 16/11 Arab shipping companies’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-13T10:37:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s single piece of correspondence (with enclosure) is followed by a single page of file notes (f 4).</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 5; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises a single piece of correspondence, a letter sent by the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Cornelius James Pelly) to the British Political Agents and Consuls in the Persian Gulf region, dated 2 January 1947 (f 2). Enclosed with the letter is a typewritten extract of an article originally published in the
                           Iraq Times, dated 31 August 1946 (f 3). The newspaper extract concerns proposals to launch a new shipping company in Iraq, with details of share issue and managing committee. In his letter the Secretary to the Political Resident informs that while His Majesty’s Government has no objection to the formation of a new Iraqi shipping company, it should not be encouraged, given the strong competition it will face.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Iraq Times</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Shipping</topic></subject><subject><topic>Share dealing</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000f3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>