<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002b3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T07:44:11.208Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">© Description of Enclosure. Similar letter sent to I 4 - 6130 I4T07 (4) A,376/106/ 91) 350 . i/516/61) British Legation, Jedda. 29th leeember 1936. /Ji The Right cIC • } Sir, I had the honour to receive your views on Hr. Philby 1 a entry into the Aden Protectorat« f in your telegram H o. 135 dated December 5th. I should have preferred to riispose of the matter by another conversation with Fuad Bey, but by then he had left for Riyadh for a stay which might extend to several weeks, and I therefore wrote to the Amir Fey sal the letter of which a copy was sent to you under Ho. 319 on T ecember 8th. The reply of December Elst, which was forwarded in translation under No. 329 of December £2nd, was not satisfactory. The Saudi author ities continued to defend themselves, which was not necessary, as their disclaimer had been accepted. On the other hand they put forward what was obviously a defence supplied by Hr. hilby, including the Irrelevance ©bout the vagueness of the frontier and the impertinence about hie readiness to show his British passport had there been any frontier authorities to show it to. And they assumed, as the King of the Yemen assumed when complaining of a similar incursion by Mr. Philby into the Yemen (this was reported to the Colonial Office in Aden despatch to. 544 dated November 7th) that as a British subject Mr* Philby ought to be punished by Nis Majesty’s Government if he had committed any offence against the laws and regulations of the Aden Protectorate. I was about to reply to this letter when/ onourable Anthony Kden, M.C., M*P., Ac., Ac.when Fuad Bey returned to Jedda and I was able to speak to him again on the subject. 2. I told uad Bey that I assumed he had had a hand in the baud! reply since he had been at Riyadh during the time when my letter was awaiting an answer. The reply ignored an essential point which I had brought out clearly in my first talk with him on the subject, viz. the unannounced arrival at 8habwa with the baudi ‘'escort''. It was time that when one of hie aura broke down Mr. Phllby had had to go into the Hadhramaut for sparess the Aden authorities admitted that; but this admission did not cover bhabwa, which no necessity compelled him to visit without informing the authorities before hand of his desire to do so. Here Fuad asked with what appeared to be real surprise whether bhabwa was not in the Hndhramaut. I suspect that what had happened was this. When } uad was called upon to concoct a defence to my letter he got out his copy of the map on which I had shown him Chabwa (Geographical Section of the General Staff No.3891, 1930, with corrections to 193&amp;), and also the apologia which Mr. Philby must have sent to Ibn Saud. Jrom the lettering on the map thabwa might be in the jfadhramaut, and Mr. Philby will coubtlees have reported that the Aden authorities found it not unreasonable t;.at he should have entered the Hadhramaut for spares and suppliest hence the whole incident had been condoned by Aden. I disposed of this by saying that Shabwa, though a long way Inside the Aden Protectorate, is not in the Hadhramaut, and that it was not a need for stores and spares that drove Mr. Philby to visit bhnbwa, which was obviously his goal from the beginning. Here I reminded Fuad Bey of the incursion into the Yemen, but he replied that possibly the Imam only imagined that the places visited by Mr. Philby formed part of Jof/Jof and Marib. I did not pursue thie Bide lsBue4 5* Throughout the conversation I tried to do two things: to distinguiah clearly between the innocence of the Saudi Government and the responsibility of Mr* Philby, and to speak of Mr* Phllby^ action with what seems to me the proper mixture of seriousness and ridicule* I told 1 uad Bey that Mr* .'hilby was an old colleague and acquaintance of mine* Kveryone knew that he enjoyed being obstinate and tiresome, particularly when Hie Majesty’s Government were concerned - a quality of which there was clear evidence in the Saudi reply to my letter, as in the nonsense about his readiness to show his British passport (Iuad Bey laughed at this and did not deny that the argument was Philby’s). It was not a question of our punishing him for an offence but of our making it clear to the Gaudi Government that his action might have brought them under the suspicion of committing a serious diplomatic impropriety* He had obtained an armed 'escort” from the C.audi authorities for the purpose of topographical work in Tfajran. The results of this work would be interesting to him as an explorer, but they would also be of greet use to the Saudi Government, and Mr. PhiIby was in a way acting as their employee. (Fuad Bey did not object to this i.tetement, but on the contrary nodded assent). In any case, I went on, the 'escort” was provided for this specific purpose, but Mr. hilby, carefully concealing his intention both from the Saudi Government and from the British authorities, used it for a quite different purpose, viz. to enter the Aden Protectorate two hundred miles away. In fact, Mr. Philby had played a nasty trick upon the Saudi autliorities and we expected them to make this quite clear to him. 4. 3’uad Bey took no exception to anything in my state ment/ment, which X said I mist follow up with a letter (a copy of this letter is enclosed) to Make the point about Chabwa quite clear* He did not say that any action would be taken, but Ibn Saud will not be pleased at the dust which Mr.Philby has raised at this moment, when he is on hie best behaviour towards His Majesty’s Government. If he had an inkling beforehand, of what V vas in Mr. Philby’s mind he cannot have realised whet it would involve. On the other hand as an oriental he cannot feel called upon to be very harsh with a man who is a British subject and in receipt of a pension from British sources and whom, in hie opinion, we could punish ourselves if we wished. Moreover he cannot fail to be flattered if Mr* ’hilby tells him, as he doubtless will, that Ibn Baud's name and 'escort' were sufficient to ensure safe en try into a town which it is difficult to enter from the direction of the territory of which the British claim that it forma part. But Ibn Baud has now no doubt about our attitude in regard to the Aden boundary, and he will not lightly let Mr. Philby loose with an 'escort” again. I felt that the best line to take was that Mr. Hiilby had abused the confidence placed in him by Ibn Baud. This argument might even appeal to Hr. 'hilby himself, who seems to have a sense of loyalty towards Ibn Baud such as he does not feel towards His ajesty’s Government; but that would involve an admission that he was in the wrong, and Mr. hilby is never in the wrong. 5. I will not fail to carry out your instructions to report any explanation which Mr. dhilby may give. I foresee that he will dramatise himself as a Prometheus, bringing the fire/fire of archaeological knowledge from Uhabwa, with Hie Ck^vormacnt in the port of ^€ue» and H#iU Minieter as the vulture with no other businese in life but to peck at Mr# hilby’e long-euffering lively already deeply pitted from similar heroic experiences in In: la and Iraqi and Trana-Jor: an# 6 « Copies of thie despatch and enclosure are being sent to H# M# Chief Commieeloner at Aden* I imve, etc# 9 (t«d#) R.l. Bullard#'—copy No* 2811/516/6S* oifeon al. British Legation, Jedda. ii9th December 1956* Your Koyal Hig/iness, After Compliments, Since I had the honour to receive Your Koyal Highness's personal letter about Mr* Philby’s journey, No. 2/9/6 dated i^lst ecenber, I have had the opportunity to see His ^cellency Fuad Bey and to speak of the matter again* It is true that when one of Mr. Philby's cars broke down the Aden authorities did not object to his going into the Hamramaut to obtain spares, but no such need drove Mr. Philby to visit Lhabwa, which is incontestably in the Aden Protectorate though not in the Hadhramaut, and it was in particular on the question of &amp;h©bwa that I based the earlier conversation which I had with His Excellency Tuad Bey. No suspicion can attach to the Government of H.M. King Abdul Aziz in this matter in view of the assurances which they have given, but Your Royal Highness will permit me to say that it is for His Majesty's Government to judge how the arrival of Mr. hilby with an armed baud! force (or escort) might be viewed by persons living in the Aden Protectorate. But I o not wish to prolong this question any further, and I conclude by stressing the comment which I made to His Excellency Fuad Bey on December 26th as to the great impropriety committed by Mr. Fhilby in procuring an armed force (or escort) from the baud! Government for topographical work in Najran and using it, without their knowledge, for a quite different end an illegitimate purpose, viz. to enter the territory of the Aden Protectorate. Viith highest respects, Hie Loyal Highness The Amir Feysal, MeccaIn any further communication on this subject, please quote No - JLo£/9/ and address —not to atiy person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. r. 2 ?/. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop -y of the unde r-mentioned paper ' P. Z Foreign Office, , 193 ’ Reference to previous c\(rres Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. eU* /La. P^My «( 2g JAN .3/ ), %M-OFF^ Similar letter sent to 6&lt;&gt; 14-6130 14007 ( 4 )COPY 8/9/6. Personal. Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Mecca. 7th Shawval l?-65. Blst December 1936. Dear Sir Reader, With reference to Your Excellency*s personal letter No. P102/316/65 of December 9th 1936, I have the honour to inform you that T am glad to learn that the British Government were oleased vith the assurance given by the Denuty Minister for Foreign Affairs regarding the ^nature of the) deoarture from Neiran by r. Philby. The information given to you by the Jeouty Minister for Foreign Affairs explains the attitude of the Government of H. . the King on this nuestion. It has been a cause of regret to the Government of H. M. the King that the matter should have left any coneeouences ''literally. ,f tails”) and that an importance which it does not in fact possess should be attributed to it. Your Excellency may be assured that, in remote deserts it is very difficult to distinguish the actual frontiers if they are not fixed and known, just rs it is difficult to comply with the special arrangements concerning the crossing of the frontiers particular'’y when there are no soeci'l official* for such ouroose. oreover, as the Deputy -‘inlster for Foreign Affairs has already explained to you, the Government of H. . the King h*d no knowledge of the intention of Mr. ^hilby to go to the Hadhramaut. It was therefore impossible for the necessary application to be made for Permisaion for him to go there. I have moreover learnt th^ t when r. '‘hilby was asked by the repoonsitPe ruthorities in the TTadhremaut Ahyivhy he had gone there in such manner he reolied that he held a British nassoort and that he waa nrenared to oroduee it to the frontier officials had there been any. T have also learnt that % 'r. Phi lb,y haa exolained to the reBoonaible authorities in the Hadhramaut the reasons for his going there and that he was not entrusted with any mission by the Government of K. the King and that he only v.ent into the Hadhramaut because he had to get his cars renaired and to obtain some articles which he needed. It aonears that they were satisfied with his exnlanatlona and afforded him the required assistance. Had it not been eo, it would have been their concern, and within their nower to take the measures they thought orooer against him. In rny case I think the importance attached to the journey of ’ r. 'hilby rnd the irroresaion it caused or might have caused have heen much exaggerated especially if we take into consideration the fact that hia journey was not m'de by order of the Government nor with their permission. As to the armed persons said to have accompanied r. hllby, they were merely such guides, guards and servants as escort every one who travels in the desert to protect and assist the traveller and to supply him with his requirements. Consequently I hope that the explanation which I have given will serve to remove suspicion (literally ”what has come into the minde’ , ) and to assure of the good intentions of the Govern-ent of H.the King. Mth highest respects, Yours sincerely, feigned) ^eyeal.Minute Paper. Register No. P. z. 153/37. SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Dated Bee. 193 Date. Initials. To Under Secretary ly. [ ./t c£. &gt; Secretary of State... u Committee # 7 . /• Under Secretary Secretary of State.... . A 2 - SUBJECT. SOUTH-WESTERN ARABIA: Journey of exploration by Lr. Philby on behalf*of Ibn Saud. Copy of to % V ^ Previous papers P.Z. 8773/36 4136b 1000 10.35 FOR INFORMATION. The two articles in the 'Times’ at the top of the file are of general interest from the point of view of Arabian exploration and add farther to fir. Philby’s reputation in this respect, but the main interest to H.M.G. of the journey was that it carried Mr. Philby (who was accompanied by an armed Saudi escort) across a good deal of territory which is the subject-matter of the present frontier negotiations between Ibn Saud and H.M.G. In his own narrative Mr. Philby explains that King Ibn Saud asked him to undertake an expedition to map the extremities of his dominions in the south (i.e., towards Yemen and the Aden Protectorate, including the Hadramaut). According to subsequent explanations by the Saudi Government (flag A), he was told to fix the position of various/ Nvarious points in the Najran area (this area is undoubtedly part of Saudi Arabia). It appears, however, that I'r. Philby spent a good deal of time in the Shabwa district (which is considerably south of the furthest line claimed by Ibn Saud and is clearly in Protectorate territory) and in the Hadramaut. It was reported by a respectable Aden merchant that L'r. Philby, while m the hadramaut, spoke ill of the British Government, and suggested that the Hadramaut had a lot to gain by concluding a treaty with Ibn Saud (flag B). Subsequently a letter v/as received by the Resident from the King of the Yemen (flag C) complaining that hr. Philby, 'a British subject and still under British protection', had entered Yemeni territory with an armed party. In a letter from the Colonial Office to the foreign Office of the 19th November (flag D) the case against Mr. Philby’s activities was summarised, and representations at Jedda were suggested. The matter was taken up orally by h.M. Minister at Jedda with the Ministry for foreign Affairs, and it was understood from them that Mr. Philby had no authorisation from the Saudi Arabian Government, express or implied, to go outside the borders of Saudi Arabia. It is quite possible that Mr. Philby did indeed have no instructions to go outside Saudi Arabia or indulge &lt; * in Saudi propaganda, but that he was led away on the one hand by his zeal for exploration, and on the other by his enthusiasm for Ibn Saud. But the whole incident has naturally/Minute Paper. Department. naturally caused a good deal of agitation to H.M.G. (the Colonial Office and Foreign Office are, of course, the Departments irrmediately concerned), in view of the frontier negotiations, which have been going on intermittently for several years now and show signs of revival at the moment. CUAitM — SEEN POLITICAL COMMITTER 8 FEB 1937jSL' »ny further oommunioution on this subject, please quote No. £ (oJS^ iff! m and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments '.to fir\ &lt;!)•**(*-*■ A* /rCop* (K 8006/6404/91) Ho. £102/216/65. iS / mortal . British Legation, 8th ©comber 1926. Jedda Your Royal Highness, After Compliments, I liave the honour { to a fou/ 3 oyal Highnesu upon a matter which I treated orally with His Excellency 3 uad Bey Hamea and should have preferred to continue to treat orally, ^ only His Excellency has left Jedda and may not be back for some time. The question is the journey of Mr* Philby into the Aden . rotectorate with an armed Saudi force without notice having been given to the rotectorate authorities beforehand. I duly reported to my Government the assurance of the Saudi Arab Government that they did not know rr* Philby intended to go south of Najran, and that he had no authorisation from them, whether express or implied, to proceed with the armed force outside the borders of Saudi Arabia. His Majesty’s Govern ent were very glad to receive this assurance, which confirms the supposition which they had already for-ed on the subject, and they now understand the extraordinary occurrence. I am however to point out that the arrival of Mr* hilby in the Aden Protectorate with an armed Caudi force night have caused an incident or on the other hand might have led the tribes in those parts to suppose that r* Philby had oome on a mission from the £audi Arab Government, either of which results would have been harmful to the good relations which have subsisted for so long between the two governments* In conclusion I am to inform Your Royal Highness that His Majesty’s rovemment trust that suitable action will be taken in regard to the person whose irresponsible conduct might have led to so regrettable a consequence. Uith highest respects, (8gd.) R.W. Bullard. His Royal Highness The Amir Feysal, Mecca.v *#jO distribution. &amp; O / Decypher. D. R. No. 129. oir R. Bullard, (Jedda). 29th December, 1936. 12.15 p.m. 29th December, 1936. 1.40 p.m. 29th December, 1936. % 0 : 0 : 0 : 0:0 Reply from Minister for Foreign Affairs to my personal letter of December 3th about Philby (my despatch No. 319) was not quite satisfactory, so to end the matter I am sending a rejoinder, and I have spoken plainly to Fuad, basing the case on ohabwa. My statement concluded thus. J[ gp.undec.]^we might be injhajran, though, Philby as an explorer would be useful to Saudi Government and he was acting in a manner as their employee (Fuad nodded assent), and in any case to steal away without their knowledge with an escort granted for that purpose and to use it to enter Aden protectorate was a nasty trick and we expected Saudi Government to tell him so. I think matter can be left there. 2. Copies of correspondence and despatch follow by bag. Addressed to Foreign Office telegram No. 129, repeated to Aden telegram No. 12.In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. /'Aoy/rvov/?/. and address — not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. THE Under-Secretary of State wi compliments to U 'J .: 14 jaaz &amp; Affai/s presents his rN and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith Foreign Office, copy of the under-mentioned paper. Ac /» ■ 193 &lt; / Reference to previous correspondence :Copy (E 6451/5404/91) No. 271 (1692/316/43) •14! British Leg Jedda 22nd September, 1936, ation, 1957 J Sir, With reference to your telegram No. 93 of the 17th September, enquiring whether any light can be thrown from Jedda upon the activities of Mr. Philby in the Hadhramaut, I have the honour to report that no information of any kind has come to the notice of the Legation, from local sources, save that since the receipt of your telegram under reference enquiries made from Mr. Philby 1 s firm of Sharqieh Ltd. have elicited the fact that they have recently received a letter from Mokalla in which Mr. Philby stated his intention of returning to the Hejaz via Najran. I consider it unlikely that the clerk in charge of Sharqieh Ltd. knows anything more than the bare facts of his employer's movements• 2. It will be observed from paragraph 196 of Jedda Report for May last, that Mr. Philby was reticent about his plans, before departure on this journey, but that Sir Andrew Ryan derived the impression that the undertaking was one of Mr. Philby's periodical journeys of exploration. 3. I am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty's Chief Commissioner at Aden. I have, etc., (Signed) R. W. Bullard fi The Right Honourable Anthony Eden, M.C.,M.P., etc., etc., etc.,o n D ^ C v 6 . •XELE&amp;RAJfl from tiae Secreta.rj'' of State for the Colonies to the Hesident Aden* Sent 9*p,&gt;&amp;u 11th December, 19^6* NOo 111.. Your despatch Do.544. You are authorised to inform K.inE Yemen that i’hDiy^s journey was mads* entirely without countenance or authority of His Majesty Government.In any further communication on this subject, please quote ^ No. TO-c, / nd address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. CONl r lDEN‘ T t{£l THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith coi )p-*r of the Under - piei ft ip n^ dp a p e r. / ; 1 y • Foreign Office, [ p '7 ‘7 ^c/,193^ j * i .L^iggc Li J Reference to previous correspondence : Description of E'nclosure. Name and Date. Subject. J&amp;CfiLa-. /xx ^ ^ • PCJU f/ D.i ENCLOSURt IN WEEKLY LETTER NO. 50 T0DEC1W6 FRO^ SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE /fs-^£ u ‘- r - r fm pol. s 9 DEC'936 Similar letter sent to Co . 14-6130 13667 ( 2 )/ / kJ Decypher. N O DISTRIBUTION. Sir R. Bullard (Jedda). December 5rd 1956. D. 10. 50 a. m. December 5rd 1956. R. 11.55 a.m. December 5rd 1956. No. 122. My despatch No. 29b October 2bth.^ as soon as Fuad returned I asked for explanation of Philby's entry into Aden protectorate without permission with armed Saudi escort. Today he called to give reply from Ibn Baud. I first informed him of complaints from the Imam about Philby's entry into Yemen. (Aden desnat ch 544 N ovember 7th). Reply begins: 2. Phiiby undertook to fix position of various points in Najran area and for this purpose was given customary guides (I interpolated “and armed escort” and Fuad did not repudiate amendment). Saudi Arabian Government did not know Phiiby was going further south and first learned that he had done so when they received from the Imam a protest against his entry into the Yemen. Phiiby had no authorisation from Saudi Arabian Government express or implied to go outside borders of Saudi Arabia, bids. 5. On a map which is a duplicate one given Fuad for frontier discussions I showed Fuad that Shahwa was far south of Ibn Baud's territory even if his extreme claims were conceded, Fuad did not deny Shabwa was in Aden protectorate. 4. Reply did not contain apology but I concluded that is because it would not fit in with xejection of all responsibility on (sic) Phiiby. 5. _ I gather that on his return Phiiby would be called upon by Ibn Saud to explain his conduct. You may wich me to inform Minister for Foreign Affairs that while the extraordinary occurrence is now understooa His Majesty's Government trust person v/hose irresponsiblr conduct might have caused serious incident'harmful to the good relations between the two governments, will be suitably dealt with. Addressed to Foreign Office No.122, repeated to Aden No.6.NO DISTRIBUTION (E 7546/5404/91). Cypher telegram to oir R. Bullard (Jedda). Foreign Office. 5th December, 1936. 5.45 p.m. No. 135. St i! ? if if if if st if ;t ;i it it if it if El it ft .t slit it i? it if if it tt ft ft Your telegram No. 122 [of December 3rd; Mr.Philby 1 s activities in Aden Protectorate and the Yemen]. I approve your action, and proposal contained in final paragraph. For reasons given in your despatch No. 289 [of October ^ i 25th], in which I concur, I do not wish to labour matter, but you should consider whether to include in any further communication written or oral to Saudi authorities protest against fact that Mr. Philby was accompanied on his incur sion into Aden Protectorate by armed Saudi forces which might well have led Protectorate tribes to assume that he was travelling on a Saudi mission. Object would be to show Saudi Government that His Majesty's Government are maintaining their position regarding Protectorate frontier and do not acquiesce in any Saudi encroachment in this area. But what you have said may be sufficient, and I am content to leave decision to you. Please report in due course any explanations which Mr.Philby may furnish. Addressed to Jedda No. 135, repeated to Aden No. 108.In any further communication on this subject, please quot No. f y/72~/ y s'%-o u/f / ^■'-and address — to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ ' anc ^ t&gt;y direction ot the Secretary of State, % transmits herewith cop^ of the under-mentiohed paper. Foreign Office, I 3795 i 19 5 6 ) Reference to previous correspondence : X, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 71 OX 10 DEC PeHCLOSUBE IN r \ mo el' 17DEC1M6 14- 6130 13667 ( 2 &gt; Similar letter sent toTelegram from the Resident Aden to the Secretary of State for the Colonies Bated 31st August, 1936*. Received at 13»32 pm«21st Aug«1936 Hoo3 Xt is reported from Yeefrhum (H £008) hy Second Political Officer that PHII3Y with a party has reached Shahwa and that he is milking for Shiham in Hadhrainawt^ His further movements v/ill he communicated when known. Addressed Colonial Office repeated to K.1UCharge d f Affaires JaddaCypher Telegram from the Acting Resident Aden to the Secretary of State for the Colonies* rv --Dated 24th August, 1936* Received 6*35*p*m. 24th August* No* 62* Addressed Secretary of State for the Colonies repeated to His Britannic Majesty^ Charge d* Affaires Jedda reference to my telegram No* 3 of the 21st August. Following is further message from second political officer at Yeshbum begins. 22nd August, Philby left Shabwa four days ago for Shibam* He is said to be returning shortly via Marher and Hajar* Total armed party about 130 men with machine guns* On arrival Shabwa four men returned west to report to King Faisal* They stated that they were looking for ruins and prospecting and anyone wanting to fight could have one ends* Marher is in upper Aiuaqi country 20 miles west of Kisab* Subject to your approval I intend sending letter to Philby by air informing him of my information, asking for 31 explanation should information be correct, and request him to withdraw Saudi armed party from Protectorate if it is true that lie is so accompanied. Even if he is not accompanied by armed party. I consider passage of Philby and Saudi personnel through Protectorate without reference to H.M* Government and Aden is an impolitic and discourteous act. I shall be glad to have your telegraphic instructions as soon as possible* m -Cypher Telegram from the Acting Resident, Aden to the Secretary of State for the Colonies* Dated 30th August, 1936. Received 10el5 8 a*m. 30th August. Addressed to the Secretary of State for the Colonies repeated to H.B.M.Charge d f Affaires Jedda my telegram Wo. 62 of the 24th Auguste Following message received from representative of II.R.H. of the Sultan/Mukalla begins. We inform you that Al Haj Abdullah PMlby has visited Shabwa, Qaudha, Heinan, Al MM Qatn and Shibara in company with 30 tribesmen of Yam, Daham and Kurab and Met8© Saudis. They came in 2 motor oars and 26 camels. Mr Philby remained Shibam for 2 days and then left by car for Seiyun with one man and stayed there with the Sultan Ali Bin Mansur for a day when he returned to Shibam. On the 22ndAfiigu8t Mr. Philby and party left for Najran . Represen&amp;tive of Shibam has treated km thorn becomingly «‘ I believe that Yam tribesmen are Saudi subjects. It is not clear wheher Philby is proceeding to Markha as reported but I hope not as without previous notice there may be incidents.Cypher Telegram from the Acting Resident, Aden to the Secretary of State for the Colonies. S’ n. t Dated 31st August, 1936. Received 7 8 ? &lt;l p J rQ (l 31st August 3 No. 67 a Addressed to the Secretary of State for the Colonies repeated to Charge d' Affaires Jedda. My telegram No* 64 da».ed the 3'jth August* Philby with two Saudi servants is at present in Mukaila which he reached via Terim and Shihr while his main party is in Shabwa. Apparently one of his cars broke down near Shibam and he has now telegraphed to Aden for spares which will be forwarded to him* I have asked him to inform me of his future movements*TELEGRAM Prom •••• The Acting Resident, Aden, To .••••• Mr. Philby, Mukalla, Dated ••• The 51st August 1936. No.2504. I shall be glad to know of the future movements of yourself and Sa’udi party in the Aden Protectorate, I wish to remind you that Shabwa and the Hadhramaut are in the Aden Protectorate which is not administered by His Majesty’s Government but whose interests are governed by His Majesty’s Government. It is therefore advisable for intending travellers to obtain the permission of this Residency before visiting places in the interior. This is all the more important when the traveller is accompanied by a party from a Foreign Government. It has been reported that you wish to visit Markha on your return journey. Please let me know if this is correct so that ample warning may be given to the Upper ’Aulaqi Sultan in whose tribe Markha lies should your visit be considered politically advisable. I will make iranediate arrangements to hav ; the spare parts for your car and films shipped as soon as possible.TELEGRAM, Prom Mr. PhilLy, Mukalla, To.. The Resident, Aden, Dated..,. The 2nd September 1956. Much obliged kind offer despatch my requirements. My visit Hadhramaut itself entirely due necessity re provision purchase petrol etcetera and visit coast due breakage shaft locally irreplaceable. First opportunity communicate you duly utilised here owing defective communication remainder Protectorate area. Apart Hadhramaut whole journey lay in unexplored undemarcated territory whoso political status am not competent discuss. Respectfully deprecate such discussion. My party has no i official character whatever though inevitably organised at Hajran. It awaits my return Shabwa resume unfortunately interrupted journey. Vaguely plan making towards Beihan and working north through sanabelt to Najran. Do not contemplate visiting Aulaqi territory but many thanks offer assistance that direction.Copy* SBCKET No. 452 THE RESIDENCY ADEN, 9TH SEPl^MBER 1936 Sir I have the honour to refer to your unnumbered telegram of September 1st 1936 and to enclose, for your information, a copy of a telegram No,C-1447 of September 7th v/hich I have sent to Mr. Philby. I am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty’s Charge d’ Affaires, Jedda. I have etc., (Sgd.) M.C♦LAKE Acting Resident etc* THE RIGHT HONOURABLE W.G.A. ORMSBY GORE, f SECRETARY OF STAT- FOR THE COLONIES, DOWNING STREET, S.W.l.TELEGRAM No: C/1447 dated 7th September, 1936# To: Mr. Philby, Mukalla Prom: Acting Resident, Aden. I have been instructed by His Majesty’s Government to request you to withdraw your Sa’udi armed party from the Aden Protectorate as soon as possible and to inform you that it wouldhave been preferable for you to have informed British authorities of your intention to visit Protectorate before your visit took place. Reference your signal of 2nd September. I appreciate that necessity took you into the Hadhramaut but as far as I am aware necessity did not take you and your Sa’udi armed party to Shabwa which is definitely within the Aden Protectorate. Further the Ahl Karab who roam the vicinity of Shabwa and whose Chief lives there are nominally vassals of the Upper Aulaqi Sultan (Handbook of Arabia). The recognised Northern boundary of the Aden Protectorate from near Dhala North eastwards is indicated by a N.K. line and is as you state undemarcated and to a great extent unexplored and the political status of territory south of this line which includes Shabwa is not a matter for discussion as it is de facto under the protection of His Majesty’s Government. The BAL HARITH tribe N.E. of BEIHAN AL QASAB are under the Sharif of Beihan who is a treaty Chief, and I must request you with your Sa’udi armed party not to enter Beihan territory including that of the BAL HARITH unless traverse acrossa portion of the latter is necessary for topographical reasons, and should you desire to visit Beihan yourself unaccompanied hy armed Sa’udis to infonn me before you leave ?4ukalla* Your spareparts should leave Aden tomorrow*Cypher telegram from the Resident Aden to the Secretary of^ str? for the Colonies Dated 9th September*1936* Received at 1«28 pm*9th Sept♦1936* No«71 to the Colonial Office.*:’ repeated to His Majesty T s Charg^ d } Affaires at Jedda 9th September* Following reference PHILBY from reliable Hadramaut sources* PHILBY told liadramaut notables of Ibn Saud : s intention of constructing motor road from Mecca to Hadramaut* 300 men with PHILBY distributed between Rei&amp;atasseiar and Alabr constructing houses. As far as is known both of these places are well within Hadremaut (please refer to Reilly f s telegram of the 19th March). If these reports true PHILBY ^s assurance to me contained in telegram that his Journey had no official character appears to be inaccurato. I sent telegram to PHILBY yesterday on t lines of your unnumbered telegram of 1st September®No? 492 SECRET Sir, THE RESIDENCY, ADEN, 30th September, 1936. I have the honour to refer you to the * ■'* -v correspondence ending with my Secret despatch No?432 of 9th September, 1936 in connection with the recent activities of Mr. Philby in the Aden Protectorate. 2. I returned yesterday from a visit by air to Mukalla and the Kadhramaut valley. 3. In the course of my visit I was able to make enquiries on the spot as to the extent of Mr. Philby’s Sa’udi propaganda though enquiries were scarcely necessary as both the Qu’aiti authorities at Mukalla and shibara, and the Kathiri Sultan and influential Seiyid family of A1 Kaf in the Eastern part of the Hadhramaut valley were only too ready to open the subject without encouragement and to talk about what they considered as Mr. Philby^ unwarrantable interference. 4. I found that fir. Philby had spared no pains to proclaim the merits of Sa’udi Government at every opportunity and to assert how well the people of the Hadhramaut would fare were they to come under the rule of Ibn Sa’ud. Mr. Philby declared the country between the Western boundary of the Hadhramaut and Najran to be a 'No Man f s Land' which would soon be taken over by Ibn Sa'ud. This includes Shabwa and A1 ’Abr, of which ghabwa (which is actually more to the South than shewn on The Right Honourable W.G.A. Ormsby Gore, P.C., Secretary of State for the Colonies, Downing Street, S.V/.l.on existing maps) is well inside the Protectorate 'both tribally and geographically, while Al f Abr (which is on the main route from Najran to the Hadhramaut) is also well within the violet line and is in the territory of the Ahl Sei’ar (Sir Bernard Reilly’s Secret telegram No:20 of 19th March 1936 and Mr* Ingrams* report - Chapters I and XIX)* I have no reason to doubt the truth of the statements made to me which were given by responsible and reliable persons* 5* Mr. Philby also spread abroad that Ibn Sa’ud ’’intended to make a road for motor traffic from Mecca to the Hadhramaut”, as already reported* I have not the opportunity in this despatch to comment on the advantages of such a road being constructed. But were such a scheme to be considered it would be a matter for His Majesty’s Government to discuss with the Sa’udi Government, and for Mr* Philby to proclaim that Ibn Sa’ud ’’intends” to make the road, as if the country immediately to the West of the Hadhramaut was Sa’udi territory and not part of the Aden Protectorate, is gross impertinence* 6* I do not think that much attention was paid to Mr* Philby’s Sa’udi propaganda by those who really count in the Hadhramaut and Qu’aiti territory and possibly the visit of the Air Officer Commanding and myself with five aircraft immediately after Mr* Philby’s visit counteracted to a certain extent its effects. But there is always a faction in most comnunities who are anti-Government and an easy prey for foreign intriguers and the Hadhramaut is no exception, added to which thereis an Irshadi element which has for some years been trying to overthrow the influence of the Seiyids of the Hadhraraaut and to spread the tenets of the Wahabi faith* I, therefore, take a serious view of the diffusion of any determined Sa’udi propaganda in the Hadhramaut such as that in which Mr* Philby has recently been engaged. 7* I am not in a position to give an opinion as to whether Mr* Philby’s recent activities had the support of Ibn Sa’ud. Mr* Hope Gill, who has known both for some years, thinks not* Possibly Mr* Philby’s apparent desire to cover the whole of Arabia in the course of his travels and to try to be the first European to cross an unexplored route or to visit a town of historical interest (in this case - Shabwa) may have furnished the real reason for his recent journey, and that, being such an ardent admirer of Ibn Sa’ud, he could not resist the temptation to proclaim aloud the virtues of his hero, but, in view of the conversations now being conducted by His Majesty’s Government with the Sa’udi Government over the boundaries of Sa’udi Arabia, and of Ibn Saud’s tendency to claim more than His Majesty’s Government is willing to cede, it is quite likely that Mr* Philby’s intrigue may have had the unofficial, if not the official, support of the King, and that it was financed by the latter (vide last paragraph of Royal Air Force report enclosed)• In any case, as Mr* Philby is the proteg£ of Ibn Sa’ud, I assume that His Majesty’s Government will take up this matter with the Sa’udi Government and addressa strong protest, 8, Presumably Mr, Philby still calls himself an Englishman and I understand that he is in receipt of a pension from the Government of India. It is all the more to be deplored, therefore, that he should deliberately work against the interests of Great Britain. 9. I enclose copies of two recent reports - one from the Intelligence branch of Air Headquarters (which is probably rather exaggerated as regards the paragraphs 4 and 5) and the other from His Hi^iness the Sultan of Shihr and Jlukalla. I have, etc., (Sgd) II. C. LAKE. Acting Resident, etc.CONFIDENTIAL BL HAJ ABDULL,\ PHIL3Y: ACTIVITIES IN THE HADKRA?,TAUT It 1b reported by Sheikh OMEF BAOBEID, a well-known merchant in Aden, who arrived from his country (Shibam) last week, that EL HAJ ABDULLA PHILBY stayed many days at SHIBAM and told the people there that the object of hie visit was to open a motor road from NEJRAN to the HADHBAMAUT and to encourage the trade in Ford cars, as he is a Ford agent in HEJAZ. He praised highly IBN BAUD, ABDUL AZIZ, and advised the Aqils and Sheikhs to proceed to KEJAZ and to conclude a treaty with ABDUL AZIZ, as the latter is willing to accept this and will do his best to please them in everything* In the HADHRAMAUT most of the people were astonished to hear this and replied that their country was under British protection* He told then it was wrong to say that, as the HADHRAMAUT is an independent country and they had a lot to gain by concluding a treaty with IBN SAUD* He also said that from NEJRAN to the border of the HADHRAMAUT all the tribes agreed to be under SAUDI protection* He tried to convince the HADHRAMAUT people of the generosity of IBN SAUD and aavieed then to take this chance and to accompany him back to HEJAZ* He spoke ill of the British Government*s policy and indicted the British for their cruelty towards the Arabs of Palestine* He used his radio daily whilst there and allowed anyone who wished to hear it. His radio apparatus is said to be of a very costlycostly type and can work from one battery for a thousand hours. It is said that last year some of the Aqils of the HAI3HRAIIAIJT visited IBN SAUD and returned to their country praising the Sultan’s generosity. Three of the head Sheikhs of the well-known HADHRAMAUT tribe of SAAR, accompanied PHILBY to HEJAZ to visit the Saudi Sultan. PHILBY had with him three Ford cars (two lorries and a four-seater). He came to the HABHRAMAUT with the small car and one lorry; the second lorry was kept at SHUBWA. He was very modest and generous and the HADHRAMAUT people liked him very much. (Sgd) B. A. FRASER, F/Lt. for Sauadron Leader Air 'I”. A.H.'c w .B.F. , Aden, 26.9.1936Confidential Prom: His Highness the Sultan of Shihr and f.fukalla To: The Acting Resident. A»C ♦ After our arrival at Mukalla we interviewed Sheikh * Abdullah Philby on several occasions. gathered from his conversations with us that he highly praises the Sa’udi Government in a way which signifies a spirit of propaganda in their favour. It was clear from information received from the persons with whom he had interviews both at Mukalla and Hadhramaut, that he had spread propaganda in favour of the Sa'udi Government. He also told many persons that the Sa'udi Government are prepared to render assistance to the Hadhramaut if the people ask for it. He also explained that the tribesmen living beyond A1 f Abr have all entered into an agreement with the Sa’udi Government and that no one will dare to interfere with any traveller while on his way from A1 ’Abr to Mecca. While this does not coincide with the true facts (because Sheikh Philby himself was not able to pass through the borders of the tribesmen living beyond A1 'Abr except by means of an escort from them) yet propaganda of this nature creates anxiety in the minds of the people, and this necessitates the taking of precautionary measures. Similarly the opening of a road for motor traffic between the Hadhramaut and Najran in the manner prescribed by Sheikh ’Abdullah Philby calls for precautionary measures also on account of the results which might be brought about by the opening of such a route7 route. Apart from the fact that no one of the Hadhramis would be able to travel by this road except by experiencing great difficulties and incurring heavy expenses, the Hadhramaut itself would not gain anything by the opening of this road. We therefore wish by means of the assistance of His Majesty’s Government to take such precautionary measures as may ensure the safety of the borders. We assure you that there exists no relation ship between our Government and the Sa’udi Government other than the Islamic-Arab ties. bile we have regard for this tie we do not in any way wish them to do anything which would disturb our minds. We welcome the visit of any mission from them at any time they like to visit the Hadhramaut on condition that they obtain permission from His Majesty’s Government at Aden and ourselves. The visits of armed missions to the Hadhramaut without previous information or permission are not appreciated. We should like to bring to your notice that the Irshadiyan Community in the Hadhramaut and Java may have some connection with the Sa’udi Government. There are in this community many of the Ahl Kathir. Perhaps even the Irshadiyan Community might have had a hand in the arrival of Sheikh Abdullah Philby to the Hadhramaut for at the very time in which Sheikh Abdullah Philby came to the Hadhramaut, there appeared from the Kathiri Irshaid Community a notification both on the coast and in the Interior of the Hadhramaut containing a clear call to the people to join the Flag of* - J will be sent by next mail. of the Sa’udi Government. You will find herewith ♦ a copy of the notification attached to this letter for your perusal. The issue of such a notification necessitates the watching of the activities of the Kathiri Community at Java. We request you kindly to think carefully over this matter. We shall watch those around us in our part. Greetings.Sir, THE RESIDENCY, -V t . ‘ ^ Q C i r^DEN, 21st October, 1936. Uu ! u I have the honour to refer to my secret despatch No.492 dated 30th September 1936, and to enclose for your information a copy of a letter dated 9th October 1936 from : the Upper f Aulaqi Sultan regarding the recent activities of Mr. Philby in the Aden Protectorate. 2. The Wadi Hammam and the district of Markha are situated in the territory of the Upper f Aulaqi Sultan; (reference my telegram No.62 of 24th August), and it will be noted that Mr. Philby is reported to have arrived in Wadi Hammam on 30th September. My telegram to Mr. Philby requesting him to with draw his party from the Aden Protectorate was dated 7th September and Mr. Philby replied on 10th September in a telegram which led one to believe that he was leaving Mukalla on that day for Shabwa to act accordingly. It is therefore apparent that, if these reports are true, (and I have no reason to doubt them) Mr. Philby deliberately dis regarded the request to leave the Protectorate and actually penetrated further in. 3. I am replying to the Upper 'Aulaqi Sultan that the Sa’udi party entered the Hadhramaut and other parts of the THE RIGHT HONOURABLE W.G.A. ORMSBY G0RE,P.C., SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE COLONIES, DOWNING STREET, S.W.lthe Protectorate without permission, that the Sa^di Government has not been given authority over the interior of the Hadhramaut and that there is no intention of giving them permission to enter ’Aulaqi territory. I shall add that His Majesty’s Government is well aware of the loyalty to them of the Sultan and his people and shall express a hope that friendly relations between His Majesty’s Govern ment and himself and successors will always he maintained. I am also taking advantage of his letter, after consultation with the Air Officer Commanding, to suggest and recommend the construction of a Landing ground near Shabwa. 4. As His Highness the Sultan of Lahej has informed me that it is the general opinion in the Protectorate that Mr. Philby and his party had the permission of His Majesty’s Government and this Residency, I am having a paragraph published in the Aden Protectorate Gazette denying this. I am forwarding a copy of this despatch to His Majesty’s Minister, Jedda. I have etc. (Sgd.) M.C. LAKE Acting Resident etc.23rd Rajab 1355 (9th October 1936). Greetings. Prom To The Upper Aulaqi Sultan. The Political Secretary. A.C. We write this to inform you, oh friend, that a European with Sa’udi soldiers arrived at Shabwa some time back. We thought that they were mere travellers but they prolonged their stay at Shabwa. On 14th Rajab (30th September 1936) they arrived at Wadi Hammam with the inten tion of entering Markha but they were not allowed to do so by the Nasiyi tribe and therefore they returned to Shabwa which is situated on the trade route through which our merchandise passes to Hadhramaut. We are afraid that our subjects and caravans proceeding to Hadhramaut may be harmed. We request Government kindly to inform us whether the Sa^di Government have been given any authority over the Hadhrami interior. As far as we f Aulaqis are concerned, we do not wish them to enter our country at all because we are already in treaty relations with the British Government and do not wish to enter into any engagement with any other Foreign Governments. We are maintaining our friendly relations with the British Government. We request the British Government to reply to us on this subject as soon as possiblesin i No.558 THE RESIDENCY, ADEN, 28th October, 1936. Sir, I have the honour to refer to Colonel Lake’s telegram No.86 dated 23rd October 1936, and to enclose, for your information, copies of letters dated 8th and 14th October 1936 from Seiyid Ahmed bin ’Alawi A1 Jifri and Seiyid Nasir bin Muhsin respectively regarding the recent activities of Mr. Philby in the Aden Protectorate. 2. Seiyid Ahmed bin ’Alawi A1 Jifri is a member of an important family of Mansabs (Religious overseers) in the Upper T Aulaqi country, where he is an influence for law and order, and Seiyid Nasir is one of the Chiefs of MARKKA. 3. Place references will be found in San f a map, North D.38. 4. A notice has been inserted in the issue of the Protectorate Gazette for October that no permission of any sort was accorded to Mr. Philby for his journey into the Protectorate and that His Majesty’s Government lends no countenance whatever to the statements he is reported to have made there. I have etc., (Sgd) B.R. REILLY RESIDENT etc. THE RIGHT HONOURABLE W.G.A. ORMSBY GORE, P.C., SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE COLONIES, DOWNING STREET, S.W.l.22nd Rajato 1355 (8th October 1936). Greetings. Prom Seiyid Ahmed bin Alawi A1 Jifri To The Second Political Officer, Aden. A • C •, News reached us, oh friend, about the arrival of Mr. ’Abdullah Philby with his companions at Shabwa on the 8th Rajab (24th September 1936) and on the night of the 11th instant (27th September 1936), they were the guests of the Hammam tribe. They wanted to go to Markha but they were not allowed to do so by the Nasiyin tribe. One of the motor cars which arrived went to the lower part of the Khalifi country to a place called As-Sod to hunt gazelles and they killed one. They also went to the lower part of Jerdan belonging to the Ahl Dhabab. It may not be hidden from your honour that the people of that part of the country were disturbed and frightened on account of this Saudian raid against the Protectorate with the consent of the British Government. But if they (British Government) are backing us, we do not care either for the Sa’udi or Imam. A letter prior to this has been sent to you and we hope it has reached you. Every tribesman is afraid of Sa’udi incursions and the subjects only want those who will look into the maintenance of peace whether they be the British Government or any Islamic Government.Dated 28th Rajah 1355 (14th October 1936) Prom Seiyid Nasir bin Muhsin of Markha one of the Aqils of Markha nominally under the Upper Aulaqi Sultan. To The Political Secretary, Aden. A • G., We inform you, oh friend, that two lorries arrived as far as the borders of Markha. They asked us for permission to enter our country and to have an interview with us. We declined to grant their requests. They say that they belong to Najd and have come on behalf of BinCopy SECRET. n No.544 THE RESIDENCY, ADEN. 4th November, 1936. 7 Sir, I have the honour to submit a co^y of a letter received from the Kin^- of the Yemen on the subject of Mr. Philby’e recent journey to the Hadhramaut, in the course of which it now appears that he travelled without leave through Yemeni territory. 2. Captain Seagor, who has now returned to Aden from his visit to San*a, reports that the King lias been both offended and alarmed by Mr. Philby’s passage through his country. It is well known that the King has the strongest objection to the entry of any foreigners into any part of the Yemen without his xrevious knowledge and permission, and this Residency is always careful to respect his wishes in this respect. Mr. PhiTby f s arrival within Yemeni uorders without authority having been obtained or even sou 0 ht is therefore both an affront to the Yemeni Government and an embarrassment to the Aden Residency, through which the visits of British subjects to the Yemen are usually arranged. His inconsiderate and discourteous action has b come a more serious offence through the fact that he was accompanied by an armed party and that he appears to have indulged in propaganda unfriendly to Yemeni interests. These circumstances suggest a challenge on his part to Yemeni Sovereignty Tin: RIGHT HONOURABLE W.G.A. ORMSBY GORE, P.C., SECRETARY OF STATE FOR Til. COLONIES, DOLING STREET, S.W.l.Sovereignty over the districts mentioned in tae King’s letter to me# 3. The districts in question are AL JOF and MARIB* These have Been in Yemeni occupation since 1926 and 1927 respectively* They lie to the south of the Saudi-Yemeni frontier established by the Treaty of TAXF in 1934, and are well to the north of the boundary of the Aden .rotectorate* ’There appears therefore to be no valid reason to question the Yemeni claim to them which has been enforced in fact for several years, and it is prejudicial to good Anglo—Yemeni relations that this claim should appear to be disputed by a British subject, and especially by one who was lormerly in the service of the British Government and who is still regarded by many Arabs as occupying a quasi-representative position in Saudi Arabia. 4. Lieut-Colonel Lake has represented to you in his despatch of oOth September the unfortunate effect of Ur. Philby’s incursion into SHABWA and the HADHKAMAUT and of his disregard of the line which has for many years been accepted by His Majesty’s Government as being the northern boundary of the Aden Protectorate in that area; and I hope that it will be possible for His Majesty’s Government ' j to indicate in some unmistakable manner in respect of both the Yemen and the Aden Protectorate that they wholly condemn Mr* Philby’a mischievous adventure* X have etc* (Sgd.) B.R. REILLY RESIDENT etc.JS* In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Mer ciful. 2nd Shauban, 1355 (October 21st 1936) Prom His Majesty the Imam Yahya bin Muharsnad Hamid-ud-Din, To His excellency Sir Bernard Reilly, K.C.M.G. ,C.X .E. ,O.B.E.j Resident etc. We extend to Your Excellency our respects. We beg to call your icind attention to an incident which we regret to report to Your Excellency and which has happened during yoir absence from Aden on leave. This incident has caused all kinds of doubt and uneasiness in all parts of the country and a great deal of surprise and amazement due to our ignorance of its reason. Mr. Philby, who has chosen to reside in the Hejaz for some years, claimed in the month of July last to be the representative of Great Britain and thus earned for himself the immunities and privileges accorded to political Represen tation. He brought a group of armed men and, with them, crossed the Yemeni Boundary in cars near hajran and came down to the Hadhramaut where he told them (the Hadhramis) different stories. He claimed that he would construct a motorcar road between the Hejaz and tne Hadhramaut and that he would erect in some places stations and buildings. V'e have heai'd from certain people that Mr. Philby encouraged our people to take aggressive measures against the Yemeni Government and its territories. He entered Marib and Jof and said different things. Mr. Philby is a British subject and is still under British protection. His entrance into our country with armed men without permission violates international regulations as does his wandering about within our country and the making of declarations against our Government. His strange conduct has excited our people and we are sure that Great Britain never permitsor encourages any ouch unwarranted behaviour. We therefore earnestly beg Your iiicellency to request your Governiiient, who is av/are of every single thing that happens, to inquire carefully into the matter and to be good enough to inform us of the real reason for this strange incident. We also request the British Government to inflict a suitable punishment on Mr. Philby and to assure the non- repetition of such ail incident in the future. In conclusion we extend our respect and wishes for your ^ood health.19 Norember, 1956 n /i^ V 73150/36 Sir# I am filleted 'by Mr* .Secretary Ormsby Gore to rater to the letter from thia Department of the 7th Hovrr&amp;er eivslonlng copies of correspondence relating to the activities of Mr* Philby in the Aden Protectorate and to tranaiit to you, for the information of Sir* Secretary Kden f a copy of a further despatch and enclosure from the Resident at Aden. 2* ?£r* Orooby Gore is of opinion that the reports contained in this and previous despatches, copies of which have been transmitted from time to time to the Foreign Office, are sufficient indication that Mr* Philby did not confine his activities in the Aden Protectorate to those of an ordinary traveller, but that in the course of his visit he persistently spread political propaganda in favour of the Saudi Government* Mr* Gnasby Gore further considers THK UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, FOREIGN OFFICE.consider© that the cl retime tanoee justify a strong \ protSo#^ being made to the Saudi Govem»ient f and I an accordingly to request that, if fir. Eden sees no objecti&lt;Ma His Majesty f e Kepreaentative at Jfidda be instructed to make repre oontationa on tho following lines s- (1) Hie Majesty*a Government consider that it was in any circnssiBtasieee irapo'itic and discourteous on the part of Mr. Philby to outer the Aden Protectorate accompanied hjr Sa«di personnel without first informing the Resident at Aden and seeking permission, and that in the present case, in which the Saudi party which accompanied him was armed, his action was quite unwarrantable. In spite of t e Acting Resident’s request that he should withdraw his party, he deliberately attenpted to penetrate further into the Protectorate. (2) It is apparent that Sir. Phlltoy, in the course of hio journeys in the Protectorate sought to oonrinoe the people of the advantages which would accrue to then if they were to come under the rule of the Saudi Government, and even suggested that the Saudi Government would he preparedto render cusslstance to them if it were asked fbr. He generally gave the impression that parts of the Protectorate were a 'No Msn 9 8 Land' which would one day he absorbed Into the .’midi Kingdom* In his statemente concerning the designs of the MMbl King to constmet a motor road from Msecs to the Hadhramaut, he appears to have ignored the fact that before imp such work were tmdertaken it would first be necessary to consult the British ('overru?ient, since a large part of the territory through ,/hich the road would pass is tinder the protection of His Majesty* (3) It is clear that Mr* Philby , s visits to certain of the local Sheikhs were unsolicited and that his activities in their territories were regarded by them as being an unwarrantable interference in their local affairs* Moreover, the statements which he made appear to have given rise to a feeling of apprehension amongst certain of the local Sheikhs that some arrangement for the control of this area might have been reached, unknown to them, between His Majesty’s Govemmen endand the** Government - It appears that this feeling was sh&amp;i4d by the r^ng of the Yemen* In view of the entirely false impression erected by Mr* Fhilby it vac found necessary to insert a notice in the issue of the Protectorate Gazette for October to the effect that no permission of any sort was accorded to Ur* rhilby for his Journey into the Protectorate and that His Majesty* o Coveranent lent no countenance whatever to the stuteaients he wac reported to have made there* (4) His U&amp;J&amp;8ty*s Ctavermeffit feel that the attitude adopted by Mr* Fhilby and the statements made by him during hla visit to the Protectorate are not in accord with the friendly relatione existing between His Majesty’s Government and the Saudi Government* X am. Sir, Your moot obedient servant, 'Signed) H&lt; H, GO WELL</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002b3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2153</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002b3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2153</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 6/80 'South and South-Western boundaries of Saudi-Arabia'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-23T09:39:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (68 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 70; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file relates to the disputed south and south-western boundaries of Saudi Arabia. It primarily concerns an expedition to southern Saudi Arabia that was undertaken by Harry St John Bridger Philby in 1936, during which Philby was reported to have entered Yemeni and British territory. Much of the correspondence discusses Philby's visit to Shabwa [Shabwa, Yemen] (reportedly with an armed Saudi party), a visit considered by the British to be an incursion into the Aden Protectorate.The file's principal correspondents are the following: His Majesty's Minister at Jedda (Sir Reader William Bullard); the Acting Political Resident, Aden (Morice Challoner Lake); Harry St John Bridger Philby; the Minister for Saudi Foreign Affairs [Fayṣal bin ‘Abd al-‘Azīz Āl Sa‘ūd]; the Sultan of Shihr and Mukalla; the Imam of Yemen [Yaḥyā Muḥammad Ḥamīd al-Dīn].In addition to correspondence the file includes Philby's own account of his visit to Shabwa, in an article published in
                           The Timesin January 1937.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Minister for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Al Qu'ayṭī Sultan of Shihr and Mukalla</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Shabwa</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Chief Commissioner, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imam of Yemen</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Harry St John Bridger Philby</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Hadhramaut</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Frontiers</topic></subject><subject><topic>Geographical exploration</topic></subject><subject><topic>Territorial disputes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002b3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>