<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000bc_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T21:21:55.783Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. KDUCATION DEPARTMENT. ' “ —i v° ' October 1943 K No. 2^-30/62 F.B.M ! s Political A^ent, BAHRAIN. Dear The Brit5sh Council advanced me a sum of 1 100 sterling against repayment at an early date by th e Ocver-nmert of Kuwait, for passao-es and salaries of the Egyptian teachers engaged by me. \ in your telegram No .666 of 11th. September 1943 yoit said that this &lt;■ would be reimbursed through the Bank. ^o. yy/O I bpve today received a letter from the British Council dated 11th. October saying that this money has not yet been repaid. N Since my departure from Cairo the Council have paid, in addition, the sum of £5 3 V to the twelvth school teacher whom I had no time to engage myseif. Will you nleese ask the Political Agent, Kuwait to instruct the JKuwait Crovernment to repa 77 ' the sum of £E 427 immed- iatel^r ( £ 400 St.= £E. 390). In the mean time I am held personally responsible for this amount. Yours sincerely, Dirg^Hor EducationfW, ,, ( yr'*’ &lt;j* ^ ijtllll y-ilj O' ^ ^ ^&gt;L&gt; 1^ ^_g ^ -4 .. i J__,U-JI ^ OJjj *J &gt; I v * • in future. He should receive no extra pay for this (see rule 9 of Staff Rules)• I shall be submitting a full report on my inspection of your schools in the near future, in the Meantime may I con *ratulate you on the excellent progress made during the pest twelve months, progress which I ka sure will be continued in the coming years. Tours sincerely. Scrd.F.-T. 'fe^elin, Educational Adviser, Kuwait. y The ftjlitioal Agent, Kuwait. The Director of Education, Bahrein.ABDULLA MULLA SALEH &gt;»il jiM KUWAIT Kuwait«24th November,1943 % dear Aijazali, T am enclosing herewith 2 letters, one addressed to Mr* Highwood,^Adviser on Arab Af L arrs to the British .-onsul in Ngypt, and the other addressed to the Eyptian Minister of Education. The both letters are from Education Department of Kuwait* I shall be very grateful if you will kindly forward these two letters to Mr.F.J.Wakein Bahrein* Thanking you for same and with my best wishes.— i &lt;■ 4-/is Confidential . D.O.No.C/830 -4/13 . /i4- ^ The Political Agency, KUWAIT. 25th November, 1943. Dear Takelin, I have had the list of books (enclosed) examined, but it is a very large one, and without the books themselves, I am unable to say more than that those marked with a pencil cross are politically undesirable. 2. Yusuf bin Mishari was a student at A1 Ajhar and in May 1941, the Egyptian authorities being about to order his deportation for the circulation of anti-British propa ganda, he was detained in Palestine under the Defence Regulations at the request of G.H.Q.,Middle East. He was then deported to Kuwait and arrived here in June 1942. I have no record of him after that, and should be interested to know whether you have heard anything significant about him. 3. Your letter to the Education Committee has been sent to them and a copy to you separately. 4. I hope you will excuse the liberty T have taken of omitting paragraph 4 of your letter to the Sheikh dealing with the question of the title of Sheikh Abdullah bin Jabir. I have only done this in the knowledge that, if you disagree with my views, you are at liberty to urge your own on His Highness at a later date. I want to point out, though, that your mention of 'His Excellency Sheikh Abdullah bin Esa al Khalifah, Minister of Education, Bahrain' may have the effect of prompting an imitation here; and such a developement is /opposed to...... F. J. Wakelin, Esquire, Director of Education, Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN. 4f) 1 ■opposed to my own view, shared, I helieve hy the Government of India and the Political Resident, that the use of grandiloquent titles for their employees should 'be discouraged in small states. The practise fosters their natural inclination to favour show at the expense of results. 5. I hope that you arrived safely at Bahrain. Yours sincerely,Telegram From To Fo.T/1178. Kuwi 4/lZ&gt;J * 9 ^ 1 Poll ti*ca3^^esilent at Bahrain. Political Agent, Kuwait. Dated and received 24th November,1943. Your telegram No.601 August 21st. T understand (?omission) definite promise to dispense with his services Shamlan is still employed and on former salary. This can only lead to trouble so if you see no objection please ask Sheikh to implement undertaking. - ResidentTelegram From To No. Political A^ent, Kuwait. Political Resilent, Bahrain. 841. Dated 3rd December, 1943. Your telegram No.T/1178 November, 24th. 2. Shamlan has been dismissed from today 1st December. = POLITICALI b Translation of letter No.F/6/2198, dated 29.il.43, y from H.H. the Ruler of Kuwait, to Mr. C.J.Pelly, ICS.,O Political '“i.ent ,Kuwai t. After Compliments, I have received a letter dated 18.11.43, from Mr. F J.’A'akelin, with an v xadditional report regarding our school in Kuwait and their system. He' also has offered some advises. I think Your Excellency have already seen the letter in question. I wish to express my gratitude and offer my best thanks to Mr. Aa^elin tor the valuable advices Sc councels given by him and in the meantime I wish to inform you that I have ordered the Educational Committee to execute all the suggestions mentioned by Mr. Wa^elin in his letter. The reply of the Educational Coinmittee is enclo sed. I request Your excellency to inform Mr. -iaxelin of b the contents of the reply after your j^eusal. Usual Eniing.ICONFIDENTIAL. No. C /^ The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to 1. T&gt; e Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Caiip Bahrain. 2. l*r. F.J. /aKelin, Director of Education, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the Oeo either y 194v5. Reference to previous correspondence : DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No.R/6/2198 dated the 29th November, 1943, from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, to the I^olitical Agent, Kuwait, with translation. KUWAIT K’'UCATIOH.as ss ss n = n e==sss Copy of lettf.r No.H/6/2193 dated the 29th November, 1943, from His Ili/hness the Ruler of Kuwait to the Political Agent, Kuwait. I have received a letter dated the 13th November, 194^, 1 rom Lr.i‘.J. aicelin, v/ith an additional report regarding our schools in Kuwait and tht.ir systeit. He also has offered some advises. I thinK Your Excellency have already seen the letter in question. I wish to express my gratitude end offer my best thanks to Mr. Raicelin for the valuable advices and counceis given by him and in the meantime I wish to inform you that I have ordered the Educations! Committee to execute all the suggestions mentioned by Mr. ^ -orelin in his letter, die reply of the Educational Coroiriittee is enclosed. I reouest Year Excellency to Inform Mr. deicelin of the contents of the reply after your perusal.s Copy of translation of the decision reached by the Education Conanittee, Kuwait, which was held on the 20th November, 1943, The Committee held a meeting under the presidency of Ohainh Atdullah Jabir and the membership of the Director of Education, and all the members except Daiyid Abdul Mohsin al-Kherafi # The follovins decisions were reached 1* It has been agreed to execute the order of His Highness Shaikh Sir Ahmed al Jabir As-3utah, K.C.I.E., C.3.I., the Huler of Kuwait, for the dismissal of Ustadh Abdul Latif Shanlan, fori-.er Director of Education. 2. Transferring of the finance of the Education Department to the Imperial Banic of Iran. A Committee has been elected to conduct the accounts. Yusuf bin Isa and Abdul Mohsin Kharafi form the ssid Committee. 3. It has been approved to give the Director of Education Ha.250/- per month as petty cash and to authorise him to spend the amount as he wishes without referring to anybody. 4. To agree upon His Highness RhaiKh ir Ahmed al Jabir As-Subah's acceptance of the idea of the proposed visit of the Director of Education to Bahrain and to wait for the approval of His Highness Shaikh Abdullah bin Isa al-Khalifa, Minister of Education, Bahrain to this visit, owing to the benefits which are to be derived from such visit. 5. The approval of the rules placed by Mr.F.J. Vekelin, the Educational Adviser and to request the i^odification of Article 11 which contains the following my teacher who leaves the job during the year, will have to pay equivalent to his pay for the remaining period of the school term and Article 14 which reads, if the Education Department dispense with the services of any of their employees during the school term, the Department will have to pay him for the remaining period of the school year session, but this modification depends on Mr. ’Vakelin, the Educational Adviser’s approval. 6 . The ap.;roval of the suggestion regarding Ustadh Kamal Saleh Abda. 7. It has been approv d to Increase the salary of Ustadh Ali Haixtal to ii3.350/- and that of Ustadh Ahmad Dheif to hs.250/-. 8 8 . It has been approved that the Commercial night classes be arranged and Ustadh Ahmad At-Tuhami Ash-Shannawi will have to divide his programme between MubaraKia School and the night classes and that he will not draw any extra pay. This should also be according to the opinion of the Director of Education and the Head master of the Hubarakia School.( (. APPROXIMATE ESTIMATE OP THE BUDGET OP ' . -P~ ir .'' r ■ .t ^ . : ‘iT^t: The current financial year from (1st Rejab, 1362 to the end of Jamad Axchar, 1363). The :;irector of Education held a meeting with Nusf al-Yuouf, Abdullah Az-Zaid, the two members of the Education Department and has drafted the following report Expenditures. Incomes. Customs Rs. 159,000/-. Transport &amp; Landing Co...' 9,000/-. Total.... ..' 168.000/-. Salaries &amp; Dearness Allowances. .Rs. 138,000-0 Exp.for Education Missions ' 10,560-0 Assisting the school energy....' 600-0 Cost of boolcs &amp; Articles without value.•••• Cost of furniture and Articles kept at present ' Cost of repairing the property.' Petty cash.««*«..««......... ass ' Cost of water « Cost of building the Qublyia school for boys, two rooms at Ahmadyia school and one room at Sharqia school for boys.....' 60,000-0 Total ..' 225.600-0 8,400-0 1,440-0 1,800-0 3,000-0 1,300-0 I115/19/43 / British Embassy, CAIRO. 17th November,1943. Dear Agency, COHFIDKNTIAL , Kuwa it Kecei Af# Dated ■£ uTT /Thank you for your letter No. C/778-4/13 of the 3rd November enclosing draft No. 55/19 for £400. We have passed this to the British Council in refund of the amount advanced by them to Mr. P.J. Wake1in. Yours ever, CHANCERY. Political Agency, KUWAIT.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN EDUCATION DEFAItTMENT. ' coNFiiy^ : No:43-30/62 kJ 22nd # November 1943 H.E.Nagib Hllali Pasha, Minister of Education, Minia cry of Education Cairo* 11 E^tlan Teachers Seconded to Kowelt * Excellency, I have just returned to Bahrain having completed my half-yearly inspection of the Ko'weit Schools. I am happy to report that all Eleven arrived and are now working in the schools satisfactorily. (a)They are carrying out the following duties: Ustad All fteyk&amp;ls 11 Ahmad Dheif; Director of Head Master Education Mobarakieh Secondary and Salary £E*25 p.m. Primary School. tt £E.18i p.m. n Abdul Qadiri Wakil TI Tt Tt • Tt £E. 12 p.m, ti Ahmad Jaw da t: Asst.Master tt n tt tt £E. 12 p.m, ti Sabir AlGamal .it w • tr TI Tt tt £E. 12 p.m, !T Ahmad Shanawi: n M n TT Tt Tt £E.12 p.m, ft Abdul Ghani VHead Master Ahmadieh Primary School tt £E. 12 p.m, It Ahmad Thaoit :Wakil n tt Tt tt £E.12 p.m r M Abdul Moneem :Head Master Sharkieh Primary School tl £E. 12 p.m. n Ali Salman :Art Master for 4 schools TT £E. 12 p.m. H Kamai Abdou :Games Master for 4 schools TT £E. 12 p.m. (b) In addition to the eleven mentioned above we have.Sh. Zaki Mohammad Abul Nasr from Al^Azhar University v/ho is teaching religion in the Mubarakieh School at a slary of £E.12. p.m. Should he not also receive a salary from the Egyptian ^Government? He is a very able teacher and a great assest to the community. (c) Ten of these men have only been here a short time but I am satisfied that they are working well and will continue to do so.They have been given a hearty welcome by Koweit and I hope that they will be happy there. I shall visit them again in March. In the mean time I keep in close touch with them by post and I hope to arrange for the Director of Education to pay me a visit in Bahrain in the Spring. (d) Ali Heykal and Ahmad Dheif both hold responsible positions in the Department In view of this fact will you please consider raising their grade from that of Primary School to that of Secondary School Teachers? This will only effec them,of course, on their return to Egypt. (e) I believe that from time to time the Ministry of Education publish pamphlets and books for the guidance of their teaching staff in Egypt. We should much appreciate it if all such publications could be sent to both Koweit-Bahrain so that we may keep in touch with modern educational development. (f) I am enclosing a copy of the contracts given to the Egyptian teachers in Koweit for your information. I beg to remain. Excellency, Copy i*o: ^ Political Agent,Koweit Director of Education, Kov/eit. MM. Yours faithfully Educational Adviser to Koweit and Bahrain Governments.Copy of terms of Agreement between 4 - +- the Koweit rmy ernment and E pyptiana teacher^s De partment of the seconded, to Kowelt^ Egypt . , to tho Kowe it Government by the Minister of Education,/ You have been seconded to tne unaer the following conditionsi %' YOU win be paid Inn p!m' L'tdditlon to the Ibove by the Egyptian 4/' You e wni n ie paid a war allowance by the Koweit Government which may ,7 Th&lt;7Kowe^t^Government 0 will provide'Vith free unfurnished quarters or an allowance in lieu rlereof. with a se cond class passage 6/ * from^Ino trSf at the P be S lni^ of your contract and from Ko.ltt 7/ l’h* C Koweit t Government U will pay you a bonces of £i.. 15 at tr.e conclusion ’ of your firtt years ^vioe. Kducatlonal Adviser on 8/. You will obey the rules laid down oy 18th. November 1943. Note:- fS *$• “rn 0 b.'’Sw th. Oovernment.mm*L ^ucation Department, IBth November, 194i5. Kuwait, TJ : r : . .,v : , K. U A I F. rs5..' The attention of all staff is dra*n to the following rules of the Education Department 1. 2 . 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10 . 11 . 12 . 13. 14. Ustad Ali HaiKal is appointed Director of Education. He is responsible for the internal organisation of ell government schools in Kuwait. Head masters and distresses are under the control of the Jirector. No changes in school organisation may be made without his written consent. He has the authority to issue instructions concerning the programme, methods of teaching, booics to be used, outside activities etc. All Head masters and distresses must teach not less than 16 and not more than 18 period per week. All Second masters and distresses must teach at least 20 lessons per v/eek. It is their duty to keep school records. All Assistant Masters and Mistresses must teach at least 26 periods per week and not more than 30. Any written communication with the Director must be addressed through the Head master and mistress. No Egyptian may communicate directly with the Ministry of Education, Egypt. Any correspondence must be conducted through the Adviser. Corporal punishment can only be given by Head master or Mistress. Masters visiting all schools are directly responsible to the Director of Education. Teachers f woric is not limited to the hours they teach. They must be present in the school 34 periods per week. In addition to wor.t in school hours they must be ready if called upon to taKe part in school activity on h If days, Fridays and in the evenings. The time spent with pupils in outsine activities is equally valuable as the hours devoted to teaching. No member of the staff may be absent from school without the permission of the Director. In the event of sicicness lasting more than 3 days a doctor’s certificate must be produced. For each day of absence without permission one day’s salary will be deducted. No member of the staff may resign without giving written notice to the Director. In the case of locally engaged staff a period of one month and of foreign staff of three months warning must be iven in writing. In default one month’s pay In the case of local staff and 3 months’ pay in the case of foreign staff must be paid to Al-Maaref. No member of the staff may participate in any political activities. No Paember of the staff may engage in any business unless given written permission by the Director which can only be given with the approval of His Excellency Shaikh Abdullah Al-Jabir. Al-Maaref may dismiss any teacher by giving, in the case of locally engaged teacher one month’s notice or one month’s pay in lieu thereof and in the case of foreign teacher engaged abroad 3 months notice or 3 months pay in lieu thereof./- 2 thereof. In the case of proven misconduct Al-Maaref i-iay dismiss a teacher without notice or pay in lieu thereof. iiducational Adviser, Kuwait.wmm PHOGRAMKS OF USTAD K.AMAL EFFENQI. Kamal Abdoul Effendi will visit the 4 town schools and will be directly responsible to the Director of Education, His duties are threefold:- Physical Training of schoolboys which includes lessons in school hours, running of Scout Troop and organisation of football, basKet-ball, volley-ball for all 4 schools. Training of school teachers outside school hours in exercises to be tought to schoolboys and supervising of P.T. lessons ta^en by other masters in all 4 schools. Organisation of football and sports teams for school staff and other young men who are working in Kuwait. PHYSICAL TH INING OF SCHOOLBOYS . He must personally teach class 1 and 2 of the Secondary School taking the two classes together twice a week. The Physical Training in all Primary and Kindergarten will be taken by other masters (see 2 (b)). Kamal Effendi must make out a syllabus to be used in all schools^ The Scout Troop should be taken as one group, boys from each school taking part. Running 4 separate troop involves too much organisation and wastes the scout master’s valuable time. The boys of each school will be in separate 'Patrols”, the four working together as one 'Troop”. (d) Inter school matches should be arranged in all games, there will be an inter sports meeting. In March (a) All Physical Training masters must attend a class of practical Physical training instructed once a week outsiue school hours. (b) Kamal will h&lt;ive a full programme of about 26 teaching points which will include the two lessons of the Secondary school. During these periods he will be present with the Physical training masters and will train and assist them during the classes. Matches between masters and boys should be arranged and when possible with teams outside the schools. Employees of the various Companies in Kuwait and youths working in the bown should also be invited to take part. The money which has been collected for sports apparatus for the different schools should be pooled and divided equally between the 4 schools. This apparatus should be stored in each scnool. It is necessary for Kamal Effendi to have his own office in each school. In any case existing space will not permit this. With such a programme he should find his time fully occupied and there will be no time to be spent on the Girls’ schools or the villages. These must wait at le^st until next year. —I A CONFIDENTIAL . Kuwait Receipt^ N® L &lt;-1 Dated Government of Bahrain, Education Department* R®f.61/30 2nd.December 1943. Dear Pelley, Mr.Simon of the British Council writes: ’On presenting the draft for £400 (sterling) received from the Government of Koweit for payment in Cairo,we found that the draft was inscribed as 'payable at your buying rate for dr fts on London',and Barclays Bank have accordingly credited us with the proceeds of the draft at PT*96*5(equals £l.Stg.),the rate in question. The draft has accordingly realised only £E.386 instead of £E.390.,the amount advanced to you as Representative of the Government of Koweit.I am sure that the Government of Koweit would not wish the British Council to be out of pocket to the extent of £E.4.on ‘s ccount of the Council having given their Representative in Cairo aggomodation at a moment of financial stringency;and we would llaccordingly be grateful if you would arrange for a furthrt draft for £E.4.(Pour Pounds Egyptian) to be forwarded to this office in order to liquidate this out standing liability. *1 enclose herewith duplicate receipt from Barclays Bank Ltd. showing the amount realised upon the draft received for £400 (sterling).’ Will you please instruct the Education Department to pay the balance of £E.4 to the Council and let me know when this is done.I enclose the copy of the receipt mentioned above. ^ * I enclose a copy of a letter to Simon *ith lists of books required I by the schools.The Council send them in special green bags which should be returned as soon as possibble.I have said that you will see to this.I hope |i that this in in order.I have asked them to send the goods addressed to you i and the invoices to me here in Bahrain. * 1 enclose my report to His Highness with a copy for yourself. There is also a copy of my confidential report to The Political Resident. What news of the list of library books? Or of Shimlan and wife? I have written to the British Council in London asking them to send you Picture Post,Illustrated London News,Sphere,Monthly Science News,British Book News,Britain Today and War Illustrated. Will you pass the enclosed on to the Director,please.It Is a note asking for that letter that the Head Mistress wrote to me.It is too y precious to lose! With best wishes. Yours sincerely. Educational er,Bahrain &amp; Koweit.27 Enclosures. Dear Simon, CONFIDENTIAL Kuwait Receipt I Na liolS D ated Pef Books for Bahrain ^ Kpwelt , Government of Bahrain Education Department. 1st ♦December 1943. (1).A11 bookf» ana material aespatched to us by the Bocks and periodicals Section XX up to 25th.0ctober 1943 have now been received'.You will be pleased to know that everything,including the pictures and maps arrived in perfect condition. * 31 I enclose 10 blue forms being the receipts for XX packages recently received.Of these 28 were in bags, all of which have now been sent off via the Institute,Basra.In the first consignement there were 4 other bags sent us some time age.I hande these four &lt;,o the Publicity Office many months aro On mv return to Bahrain in October I made enquiries and was told that they*were to be mysel^° Cail,D ftt the enci or tbe y ear »l shall therefore in future despatch them I also enclose 7 Bar Return Slips. ^ enclose ; ; book Request Forms on behalf of the Bahrain Government ^ mos. urgent being Hah.2. 1 shall be most grateful if can purchase all these* -&gt;ok3 tor us end send them to Bahrein.The Bahrein Government will of course bear the cost including transport. (.TO.Our finarci&amp;a year ends on 29th.December 1943.Will you please let me have a statement of oui&gt; account oo that I may X&amp;XXX&amp; setclo it before that daoe.^x . ,.a_l to do this j shall forfeit this year’s allocation. 1943, (4;. books on th&amp;se Re&lt;iuasc Foitis will be paid for after 29th. December % (bQ.The schools in Koweit are as desperately short of uooks as we were uas ; year.l a i for^rd'dinf you o Bock dequest funis hoping that v.&gt;u ..ill be a ole to help Koweit as you have helped !3ahrain. cost of t.he books end transport wi3.1 be borne \j'' t the Kov/eit Covernmon.. ,he foiitlcal Agent,Kowcit wi^l bo x-osponsible ffcr tiie rotum of bags. I you are able to assist u in rliis way please send, the books wicii*ked: Education Dsparument, (J ov er.ru aei t of fwo w e l t, C/o ii. l&gt;. w ! 3 i'Ofitical Agent, K0W15IT. klease send the invoices to mo and j will ari*ango jii-ymcut from here* (C}-HeVw«.ic«&gt; jou.- letter CUX/l/l or 82nd.iJov«ab«r 1945 X have asked the roiibicai Ageru, oO instruct tuc iioweil Govojflu*nxflonw to pay you the £iL.4 still outstanding. Copy: Pol: tica 1 Agent, Kovre5 b. H &gt;J I T p. O Jk -L - - v* • File 30. C.C.h.Simon Esq., British Council, 25 , Ab ou 1 Set a.s, Cairo. Yours sincerelv Educ.a-tIo?ja Adviser , 'iraln &lt;&lt; Kowe' t.Dear Highwood, Education Department, Gov eminent of Bahrain. 3rd.December 1943. I have just returned from a very strenuous visit to Koweit. Owing to transport difficulties I was only there a week and so had to pack into six days the work of a fortnight. On the first occasion I consulted the committee about the boys sent to Cairn and Alexandria.The following points emerged* (a).The original eleven are at Cairo boarding schools at the expense of the Egyptian Government. (b)The five non-mission boys are at the Tanta Boarding School.The fees of these boys are being paid by the Koweit Government direct to the Ministry of Education,Cairo. (cO*Marzook al Ghanim is at the Alexandria University .His fees will be paid by Koweit direct to the Ministry of Education. (d).The Koweit Government have forwarded to you through the bank a sum of £S* 160.This is meant for pocket money for the 16 boys in Cairo and Tanta at the rate of £1 per month for 10 months.I do not knovi whether you will/ be ready to take on this responsibility or not.If you do not wish to do ' so I suggest that the money be paid to the Head Ma ters who can then pay the boys monthly. (e).The Koweit Government are making their own arrangements about clothing through a Cairo firm.‘ The members of the committee were delightfully casual about the whole affair.As you remember they sent me all sorts of contradictory instruct ions ton Cairo and eventually sent 5 instead of 4 in additionrl to the original party.They had never given a thought to the question of the fees of these five! All that however is now put right.During my recent visit I established real control of Koweit Education. The committee have asked me to express their appreciation of your assistance.! too wish to thank tyou for your help not only*with the boys but also with Kamal Abdou.He is now in Koweit.I shall be writing to Yates about him soon.In the meantime please say that he settling now fairly well. If anything he is a little ambitious but I think he will do well. The weather Is still overpowering.Our minimum temperature so far v has been 70 F.Every evening about 6 of 7 p.m. i$ gets steamy and continues so until about9.30 p.m.How we long for a cold spell! museum, and the Do not forget to let me have a line or two about the agricultural With best wishes to you and Mrs.Highwood,Mfl[ both for Christmas New Year, Yours sincerely. R.H.Highwood Esq., British Council, Cairo. Copy totPolitical Agent,Koweit. Enclose^ are copies ttters re PublicityNo.C/897. POLITIC AX AGENCY, KUWAIT, 2ist DeoemLer,1943. (fly Dear Simon, j&gt; Please refer to your demi-offioial letter to Eakelin regarding refund of £.13.390 advanced 'by the British Council to him - and the shortage of £.S.4 received when cashing the draft for £.400. 2. I enclose herewith a draft No.55/23 for £.E.4 as desired. I should he glad if the receipt for the remittance could he sent in due course. It was a pity that it w*^s short in the first place and that you had to write about it. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter to Vakelin. Yours sincerely, °ic 4ft? pol t tical Agent, Kim it. G.C.H, Simon, Esquire, British Council, 25, Ahoil Sehaa, CAIRO.(43/ ^ D,Q .No.C/396 POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT, 21st Dacsmber,1943, / Dear Wakelin, / Thank you for your D.O.No.61/30 dated 2nd December,1943. I am sending Simon a draft for £.E.4/-. It was a pity he was sent the amount short in the first place, I have noted that you want the green hags carrying the school hooks returned to the Council. Regarding the list of library hooks with you please refer to my D.0,No.C/830-4/13 dated the I understand that his wife is still employed though I have noted your remarks about her in your report dated 18tn November,1943, to His Highness. 25th November,1943 Shimlan .vas dismissed on the 1st December Your letter to the Director was sent to him With best wishes for the New Year Yours sincerely, E.J. Wakelin, Esquire, Director of Education Bahrain Government, Bahrain.' _ CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/521 CONFIDENTIAL Kuwait Receipt j No ^3 y -Dated “$&gt;£) 'Cb- j (Vi The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Tine Political Agent, Kuwait. */' ■J r and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated f 19 43, Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. i Mr. J. Y/akel in * ^ report on dated 2nd December 1943, Report on Education in Kut Mr* J* WfJiQl in, dated 4 th/ for forwarddrlg to H.H. the liducation in Kuv, a it Nov.1943^ t by the Educational Adviser c ember 1943. (Two copies, one $h a ikh of Kuwait). ix i *r zaivipnmL Bahrain f 2nd Decanber 1943. To The Hon # ble the I'olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf. ^us&amp;Ufla JdL;m^L\.% I sailed from Balirain on dunday 7th November and reached Kuwait on the mornine of Thursday 11th November. Early on Friday 19th November f 1 left Kuwait and re-ched Bahrain on Sunday » 21st November. I travelled both ways on the 'Resanc”. During my visit I stayed with the Political Agent f Mr. C.J. Polly. My program© was as follows t- Thursday - 11th Nov. has $et by Shaikh Abdullali bin Jabar. Dis cussed cs^sral oattors with hin and later with the director of education. ’ Friday - 12th Nov. Called on II.H. Gir Ghailth . hnad. Called a ooeting of the Education Coonittee. Reportei on ay work while in Cairo and laid ray plans before them. Saturday - 13th Nov. Inspection of Mobarakieh Primary School* Party at this school to meet all staff. Dinner with Egyptian and other senior staff. Sunday - 14th Nov. Inspection of Mobarokieh Secondary Gchool. Meeting of Mobarakieh staff. Monday - 15th Nov. Inspection of rthmadioh fchool. i^sical Training display at Uobar&amp;kleh dchool. Tuesday - 16tfc Nov. Inspection of wlurkieh »na % ublieh schools. Inspection of dharkleh Girls* School. Wednesday - 17 th bov. I ns pec tiorr of Jahrah Village chool. Inspection of s.ublieh Girls* School. Dinner for staff at Shaikh ifbdulla*s house. Thursday - 13th Nov. Discussion of inspections with dhaikh Abdulla and the Director of iAlucatlon. Schools* Prise Giving. Dinner for staff at Abdulla h*ulla*s house. My reception was much more friendly than on the occasions of my two former visits. In November last I w^s most hospitably received but It was obvious that my inspection was looked upon as a pure formality and no steps were taken to carry out ray recommendations. On ray return In March the Schools we © con veniently closed for a fortnight's unexpected holiday so that I Wi.s able to do little but visit the staff and glean what little information 1 could from them. Vvhile on leave in Cairo I undertook the engagement of i^yptian ataif and the arrangement of accomjao,ation of 19 Kuwait students in :^ypt. This service /was -was much appreciated by the Education Committee. They are now eoavinced that that we are endeavouring to help rather than to interfere* The result has been that control of the schools— apart from the financial side — has now boon put in ny hands. «hile in Cairo I discussed with the new director of Educatio ali Heykalf plans which 1 wanted to put into action. These included the replacement of all tyrian teachers In the boys* schools by Egyptians or local staff| the division o: the lov/er schools into throe Kindergarten anu fo^ir Primary years f a uni fied control of all schools 9 a rcaodellinK of the entire syllabus and the purchase of school books. host of those had been effect® satisfactorily before I reached Kuwait. In addition to the Director of i^ducation there are eleven Egyptian teachers. Except for the Head faster of the hobarakieh school all were newly engaged this year. I hold no special fcrlef brief for Egyptians, but as they are the only foreigners in the boys* schools this should help to eliminate those petty quarrels that so frequently arise from Jealousy and suspicion among a mixed staff. The Director is a good man. He is able and what is equally Important is not over-bearing with the Kuwaitis or his own cotxtry- men. He has the backing of ohaikh /bdulla who supports him in all that he does. ahaikh Abdullah, though a gifted man, is not familiar with the internal organization of schools and is quite prepared to act as figure-head ^nd leave the administration to the Director, so long as the latter is ros/onsible to no. It may be well for me to make clear the manner on engagemon ' of these Egyptians. The Minister of .Education in Cairo h v!ng given me permission to engage t7*elve masters I chose ten men in addition to the two who were in Kuwait last year. I was at liberty to pick whom I pleased. Several of them were working in private schools and were in no way connected with the liinlstr) I then submitted the list to the Minister who approved it. One of the conditions of the contract is that none of the e men may /correspondi s' 3, ^ corres onu with the WIniatry of i-iducation or any o^xicial in Lgypt except through me* It cennot thereroro be clainod that the Egyptian Government have sent these men to take charge of Kuwait education. I an glad to report that ail of then ®~e carrying out their work satisfactorily* Thn late di rector of l.ducatlqr^ I was s^orprisod to learn ttuxt i^hinlan had not boon dis*» missed from the department at the ond of last tcrnj f as was promised master by His Highness| but that he was working as on assistant^at his former salary of F.s.340/** per mensem j which is considerably hither than that of the present Director. I immediately as' cd for his removal. I stated that I considered him unsatisfactory and that it was useless to expect him to work under a former subordinate# He is an intriguer anu a danger to the department. His Highness while agreeing said that it would be dii ficult to dismiss him at this stage without a definite reason. I replied that there were several reasons that could be given. H# said that he would do as I wished but left on a hunUnt trip before taking any action. Unified, -d ontrol of all QhSQla*. Head Masters and Mistresses are now responsible to the Director who controls the syllab'usi allotment and length of lessonsi chois© of books| etc. I have formulatod rules *or all staff* a copy Cf which is attached. Ue have settled the retails of the school calendar and are prepar ng a scale ox pay and increments. The new arrangements have already lead to a remarkable improvement in the tone of the schools. Formerly bitter foutls raged between Head Masters and even between some Head Masters and the Director. I saw no signs of this durin* this visit. Night classes are held regularly for the local staff. They are given tuition in teaching methods* Psychology* English* Arithmetic, and other subjects. I was truly astonished to see the improvement in the teaching of some of the Kuwaitis. Several /ofor the old ISullai of 20 to 25 years service are now ualng aoaorn nethods with creat success, I!an 5 r of the youncor aen too have benefited greatly from these classes* arithmetic renalns the worst taught subject^ in all schools* 4 This, I fear, is common throughout the w&amp;st. Enlightened masters capable of teaching other subjects with imagination never lift themselves or their p ipils from, the dull routine work whoso only aim seens to be the filling of pages with figures. Perhaps it is early yet to Judge as the Egyptian Eathematics specialist has been in Kuwait barely a month* In any case until the boys are provided with text books nothing can be hoped for. I am writing to the British Council asking If they can help with the purchase of books, as they did for Bahrain. The money is available but transport is the difficulty. The standard of English h&amp;s much improved. The Egyptian master speaks English only moderately well but his method is excellent. T!e has don© good work in training the local staff. The Management of the Imperial Bank of Iran has offered an annual award of P.s.125/- to l)© given to the best English scholars. I shall hold a special English examination in March. Es.75/- will be given to the first and &amp;.50/- to the second boy. I was not permitted to visit the Girls 1 Schools when the pupils were present but I did so after school hours. There was little to show. The Head ills tress of the bigger school is the wife of Shimlan. Ehe appears to me to be incompetent and I have recommended her dismissal. Early this term she resigned after her cemand for a &amp;.100/- rise had been refused. Ehe was later asked to withdraw her resignation. The wife of one of the Egyptians, a trained dress making # teacher, has been appointed Hoad distresscfthe smaller school. It is too early yet to Judge her ability. In both schools Domestic Science, Needfe-work, and Dress making ore taught in addition to Arabic, arithmetic and Religion.The income ox the schools is chiefly derived from the Kuwait Transport Company and the Customs. These pay and £ ^ respectively of their weekly takings in cash to the Finance Department and this is passed on to the Education Committee. The money is then kept in a safe in the office. Cash in hand is frequently lent out at interest for short periods or used for speculation on the market. I have recommended that an account be opened at tho Bank and all payments to the department be paid into this. This aeeon account should be operated upon by three members of the Committee* the signatures of at least two being required one of whom must be Shaikh Abdulla. The Committee do not favour this as it seens that all Kuwaitis have an aversion to leaving money lying idle in the Bank. I suspect also that it will deprive them of valuable opportunities for personal gain. Shaikh Abdulla is strongly in favour of this and I have asked the Political Agent to press the matter with His Highness.Bahrain. 4th December 1943. Report on Education in Kuwait by the educational Adviser Vr.b'. J. v akelin. Thiu, tne f iret of my s ix monthly viei te to i^u^ait in the school year 1943-44, extended from Thureday 11th. to iriday 19th November 1943. During this time X inspected the lour boys* schools snd the two girls’ schools within the town walls. The only village school that I visited was that of Jiahrah. This was because I know that no improvement can be expected until we can send out daily, well trained staff, and as Inis can not be considered until si'ter the war there was little point in ny revisiting the villages. Their inspection cun he safely left to the Director of Education. -”y first cuty wac to meet the Education Committee and to discuss with them the affairs of the Department. 1 gave then, a report on my work vhile in Cairo and put forward to them piano for the future. The following are my observations on the work in the schools•— 1. The Director of -ducation , Jstad A1 i Raykel is an able man and well suited to his job. I formulated a set of rules for his guidance which regularise the relations between him end the staff. In my letter ol 17th November 1943 to the Committee I have i ecomuiendec. that he be paid the same salary ss the former Director was receiving, viz. Re.540/- per mensem. All questions concerning the internal control of the schools shoulc be left in his bancs. I roblezns arising from the choice of syllabus, books used in the schools methods of teaching etc. will be referred /• 2 - be referred to me. The Committee will retain the control of finance. 2. The Staff . The improvement in the teaching methods of the Kuwait staff is moat marked. This improvement is due chiefly to the influence of the present Director and Ustafid Ahmad Dheif, Head faster of the Mobarakieh School. Old men and young alike are displaying a new keenness for their work which is clearly re flected in the pleasure the boys take in their studies. It is too soon to give more than a brief mention of the new Egyptian teachers. All of them are working well and with three exceptions I have no criticisms at all. These criticisms do not so much concern their work os their attitude cowards their colleagues. In each case I have spoxon firmly and at length of the vital importance of co-operation and good will among the staff. I trust that no further action will be neces sary. In toy letter to your Highness of November* I hove, already expressed toy views on the need for opening an account with the Imperial Bank of Iran in the name of the Education Department* which can be operated on by three members of the Committee. Two signatures should appear on each cheque* one of which should be of Shaikh Abdulah All Sabah. In this same letter I also recommended that an annual budget be prepared with detailed estimated income and expen diture. My third point was thai* the Director should be paid a sum of Ks.250/- monthly for petty expenses. He must produce an account with receipt vouchers each month. Items of more than Ks.30/- each require special sanction from the Committee and should be paid from the main fund. 4. Unified Co ntrol of the 'fthoole . Head iiaaters and Mistress, are now responsible to the /Director3- Director. There is a common syllabus for the four boys* schools in the town. The subjects taught, and the number of hours per week allotted to each subject are fixed. Head Masters ore then allowed to arrange their programmes to suit their own staff. The Art Master and the Physicial Instructor visit all four schools. 5. The j obarakieh School . This school comprises kindergarten, Primary and Secon dary sections. The Mead faster is Ustad Ahmad Dheif, one of the Egyptians who was working Kuwait last year. He is capable and enthusiastic. Me has working under him four of the new Egyptians who teach mostly in the ^Secondary classes. His team of Kuwait Pasters are working well and improving fast. little The time has now come to house the Secondary School in a separate building. It is undesirable that infants and youths of 1? and 18 should be in the same school. This move would free three rooms thus supplying the additional accomodation so badly needed by the rest of the school. The room of class 4 Primary is too close to the latrines to be used as a class room. This should be vacated as soon os oossible. The Staff Room is a desolate barn. What little furni ture there is is old and broken. This should be replaced. Without it Masters can not be expected to spend the hours when they are teaching in marking and preparation. :science is an important subject in the Secondary curri- culam. There is little or no apparatus. I am aware that in war time it is difficult to obtain supplies, but provided that a money ip available a considerable amount of valuable apparatus con be made locally from materials found in the bazaar. In Bahrain I have made a complete set of apparatus for a year’s course in Heat and Electricity. 5. The Ahmadieh School . The Head Master of this school is Ustad Abdul Ohani, an /Mnyp^ian-4 f O / K(* 3 ; iSgyptlanf He is undoubtedly one of the beat of the new teachers • He has a dignified but friendly manner and is proficient in work f and sport* His assistant is an Egyptian, Ustod Ahmad Thabit* The school is efficiently run* Here again the local teachers are showing promise and are really keen on their work* 6* The Oublleh .School * This is the only school where the staff is entirely local. The Head Master 9 Uetad Abdul Malik is the best of the Kuwait staff f He has a son and a daughter teaching in other schools* His staff support him well* There is one Skelkh how ever, who teaches Arithmetic who should be replaced by a youn ger and more energetic man. Ustad Abdul Malik deserves a new building for his school* Progress is always slow under the best of conditions but here with badly lit, Inadequate rooms he is severely handicapped* I hope that this will soon be put right* Surely the only all- Kuwait school should bo given every opportunity* 7* The Sharkieh School * This school has as Head Master the Egyptian Ustad Abdul Monelm and is housed in a splendid new building yet it was the one that impressed me least of all* The staff seemed asleep* They were using the same bad methods I saw there twelve months ago* One afternoon of my inspection was devoted to outside activities* T visited each school in turn* In all the others I was entertained by drill, songs, sports and comic sketches with great enthuAd I arrived at the Sharkleh school a quarter of an hour after the apponted timo to find the school closed with only^Fnrmsh present to tell me that the boys had been dismissed an hour ago* Abdul Moneim was one of the three Egyptians I found it necessary to speak to severely* He is rather overbearing and was not willing to accept the authority of the Jirector until I officially instructed him to do so* It was a question of obeying the letter of the law without being guided by its spirit /spiritSpirit* I anticipate an inprovament by the tine of my next visit* l*he ^i;»te of the school le by no means due entirely to the present Head paster* He in the third man to hold that post in less then three years* The Syrian %ho was there before him «ae inexperiend^d and conceited. He made no effofct to train his staff j«nd concentrated most of his energies on a small roup of Hoy :eouts: chosen from his own school* Us tad Abdul Mcfcimhas a big Job before him in that he aims to bring the school dp to the standard of the others. The Director will give him every support end I hope to see rppid Improvement* 8* The Jshrah Village ;chool * Until trained staff are sent to the village schools little can be hoped for. here are two classes of about 15 boys each in separate rooms taught by an ignorant old Mullah who runa fron room to room. He himself knows very little. Exam ination of the nuplls showed fchat wht»t few things they had learned were meaningless strings of words to them* After the war 9 village education must be radically revised. ‘hat is needed ia the intelligent teaching of reading f nd writing the • oran and a 1 Din, simple arithmetic, hygiene and a course of general knowledge which has e strong rural bias* included in this general knowledge will be practical geography and a little local history. 9* The Girls* Schools * I visited both of the girls* schools after school hours with Dheikh Abdullah* I was very disappointed in wh*t I sew, or rather in what I failed to see* Although it had been known since the beginning pf the terra that I should be in Kuwait in November and although they had given three days notice of my inspection there were no signs of needle work, cooking, dress making or h*nd-work except ci’kes nd paper patterns which were obviously made Xxy the teachers for my benefit* The Head Mis tress of the lharqpieh ichool the wife of Uetad nhimlan, le in my opinion unsatisfactory. Hhe thinks fur more of her■tfrintea far more h^r poraonal advene ament than of that of the school* T recommend that if she does not leave when her husband is dismissed she be asked to resign at the end of the term* It is too soon to judge Dorieh i.hairy, the Egyptian, as she has only been Head Mistress of the cublieh 'School a very short time All cooking in the schools is done on Primus stoves* Char coal fires should be used ©a well* Not all the girls will be able to buy Primuses in their own homes* In any case with cooking on a large scale, as is done in many Arab homes, charcoal nnd wood fires are essential* The cleaning of the schools should bo done entirely by the girls themselves * ach day*one girl in each class should be given i the privilege of cleaning the room before the school opens* Before ironing and dressmaking can be successfully taught large tables are necessary* 10* Furnlturo * In all schools new furniture is needed. 3pecial tables •• ^ should be provided for handwork and kindergarten classes* Cup boards and notice boards are also required for all class rooms. Larger bladkboards should be provided especially in tho lower school* 11* A School Doctor * with eye diseases,sores boils end other ailments so pre valent in the schools a doctor who can devote his full time to pupils should be emoloyed. The Egyptian Government train men for this particular joo. They work for the same salary as assistant masters* I will write to the Minister of Education in Cairo and make enquiries. It is possible that he will second such a man to 12 Kuwait under the some conditions as for the/teachers. 12 • iho Teaching of Arithmetic * Arithmetic it still the worst taught subject in all the schools. Special attention must be given to those lessons. AH /ArithmeticArithmetic teachers should be given training by the tagyntlnn thematics specialist* 13* .Chocl iicoJtJ5 * Iftitil sufficient books ore provided for all puoile In ell subjects progress v&lt;lll be retar dod. I nm now In touch with the ?ta*itiah Council, ^ ilroy asking then to assist us to obtain them* The Committee hspe agreed to olloeaVi otleast C 300 for thi»+ 14* Fur ther Imv ) 0 c &gt; 11 nn a * I expect to pay next visit to Kuwait in i!nrch or April 1&lt;544* I hope that Youx* Highness will nermit the ixiroctor to visit Bftfcrein early next year no that ho nay lenrr something of the work tliat io being done In the nehoola here* Dir&amp;otor of EducationTelegram 4 From Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No.56. Dated 22nd January 1944. Grateful if you would pass following from me to Jakelin if you have no objection. Begins. Shaikh of Kuwait wishes all repeat all your correspondence with educational authorities here to come through me. Kindly take action accordingly ends.INDIA OFFICE \no. co.v/ r ' v?vr, _l!: \ K'' ' : . / I 91- lnu&lt; ‘ &gt;V (4Sy EXTERNAL DEPARTMENT EXPRESS LETTER (AIR M/OL) From Secretary of State To Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf. Repeated to Political Agent, Bahrein. Repeated to Political Agent, Koweit. Repeated to Government of India, External Affairs Department, Dated / 5 November, 1943. No.Ext. 6147/43. A U . ii Reference your Express Letter No.c/146 dated 30th June. Travelling expenses of the Director of Education, Bahrein on his visit of inspection to Koweit. 2, The British Council has agreed to meet the travelling expenses incurred by Mr. F, J.Wakelin on his visits of inspection to Koweit. Payments will be made by the Council to the account of the Bahrein Government with the Eastern Bank, London, as proposed in paragraph 4 of your express letter. (The issue of the above has been duly authorised) 3 / it 't/I (p3CONFIDENTIAL J / Kiiuwitltexjrt Government of Bahrain, j No p u pated jEducation Department. No. 35/30. H. B.M 1 s Political Agent Sell! criii. // - /. / v -^&lt; (c/Ol^U Memorandum: 26th* January 1944. I enclose one cover containing letters to Sheikh Abdulla As Sabah and the Director of Education, Kuwait for transmission to the Rais Al Maaref,Kuwait.dated Following are the main points of letter/£2nd January, from Mr. F.J. ’Yak: el in, Adviser to the Education Department, Kuwait, to Shaikh Abdullah Al-Jabir As-3ubah, Head of the Education Department, Kuwait. 1 ..'-t-T 1944, c (a) Regarding the way of sending £E.15 to his son Jabir at Cairo and about the present which the Shaikh v/ants to send to Mrs. T iller. Mr. 'Vakelin suggests to postpone the Question of sending the present until he visits Kuwait in the near future. (b) Mr. Wekelin agrees upon starting the Night Classes. (c) Mr. ' r akelin confirms that he was informed by ohe Director of Education, Ku ’ait that Shamlan had resigned. He then aids that he suggests that any teacher (Egyptian) who might be dismissed will have either be given a i^hree months notice or three months pay. He admits that Shamlan T s case was a special one. He then v/rites Tt There is another article which I think it is necessary to be added i.e. If one of the teachers falls sick and possess a medical certificate, he or she will be given a full salary for the first month and half salary for the second month and will not be given any salary after that until he or she resume his duty or her duty, provided that this rule will be applied to all. I hope you will agree to this addition. In my reply to the Director of Education, copy of which is enclosed, I have asked him to have all his correspondence sent through you and to receive instructions from you, because I am not the Head of the Education Department but only the Adviser.' (d) Mr. Wakelin suggests that the schools holiday in Kuwait should start from 3rd March to 17th during which Ali Baikal will be visiting Bahrain. (e) Mr. Wakelin Quotes an extract from a long letter received by him from Mr. Haywood, of the British Institute, about the Kuwaities schoolboys in Cairo, as follows have arrived in Cairo. Arrangements have been made for their lodging. Jabir joined Orman school, ten boys Saiydya school and the other five Tanta school. W.arzook is stud; ing medicine in Alexandria. r ill you write to the Head of Education in Kuweit to kindly communicate directly with the University telling them that the Kuwait Government is responsible for this boy. I think it would be good if Kuwait Government would send I to t he Ministr y of Educatfon in Cairo and to : us' a st ateme nt slipwlfla; one expenses^ of the boys who are not mem ber s^ of tn.e'~miss ion. I' wish that yoV wi 11 explain 'to the Government ofKuwaTt that I personally, and no other member of the British Institution is able to take the responsiblility of these students as that is the duty of the Ministry. I am quite prepared to take care of them as a father and to write a report about them every now and then and it seems that the Ministry have declared this subject. I think it is necessary that a letter should be sent from Kuwait to the Ministry in this sense. Mr. /akelin concludes by saying that a letter should be * written to the Ministry confirming that the expenses of i the 5 boys at Tanta and 1 at Alexandria will be paid I by ohe Kuwait Education Department directly to the I Ministry and the other 10, their expenses will be paid \ by the Egyptian Government, and a copy to him so that he may send it to the British Institution in Cairo.. tUi ■sj ) l/ATranslation of letter dated the 22nd January, 1944, L r r. Takelin, Bahrain, to 4stath Ali Baikal, Director of Education, Kuwait. from After Compliments, 1. I enclose a receipt for £3.37 sent through me to the British Institution in Cairo. 2. According to your letter dated 1st December, 1943, in v/hich you asked me to order Sports* tools etc from Egypt, I wish to inform you that I am unable to do it as ohe British Institution will send books only, 3. Reference to your second letter of the same date and your telegram of 4th January and your letter of 5th January, 1944, I wish to inform that I have written to Shaiich Abdullah Subah about that matter which is settled now. There must be a mutual understanding. I, oeing the Adviser, have recommanded few plans which have been agreed upon with little modification. You must decide to act according to Shaikh Abdullah Sub8h f s wish, as you are to receive my orders through the Head of the Education Department. 4. n hank you for the two copies of your booK(Proposed Education) and the three copies of (Curriculum) which I am studying them carefully. 5. I will discuss the question of inspection of Arabic language when we meet again. In the meantime I advise you to carry it on as you are capable to do it. • 6. I am glad to know that the funds of the Education Department have been deposited to the Bank and that you are receiving Is.250/- for miscellaneous expenses and also that you are preparing the necessary furniuure. 7. The Bahrain Government grant the Religious school about •s.120/- per month and it has the right to inspect the school. You must assist such schools in the same way in Kuwait. 8. I an sending the two documents signed by Duria Kharee to the Ministry of Education. 9. I have received a letter from the British Institute stating that they are endeavouring the purchase the * suitable books and they will send them to you in the near future. 10. Please thank the Egyptian teachers and Khalid Gharabli for their Xmas Greetings.D.Q.No.60/30. CONFIDENTIAL No I Kuwait Receipt j I n't Dated _ii^— Government of Bahrain, Education Department. &amp; 1 7th.Pebru Books from British Council. 1944. ~ I enclose a statement of account with invoices—attached for bocks purchased by the British Council for the Kuwait Government.Will you pleese settle this direct.The books are now on their way and are being sent via Bahrain.They should be here on the next down mail. I On receipt of the books will you please arrange to return the canvas bags through the Director of tl e British Insti^ut©, Basrah ara&gt; ( forward the enclosed Bag Return Slips to the Cairo office of the British Council. C.J.Felly Esq.C.B.E., H.B.M T s Political Agent, Kuwait Education al ser,Kuwait,CONfWESTlAL &gt; ; vo l&amp;&amp;__Dated JJ: Kuwdit Receif THE BRITISH COUNCIL, is, SHARIA ABOU EL SEBAA, CAIRO. KUW/1/1 14th January, 1944 Dear Sir I have to acknowledge receipt of your letter C/897 of 21st December, 1943, enclosing a Bank draft No. 55/28 for £E.4, in accordance with the request contained in our demi-official letter KUW/l/l of 22nd November, 1943, to Mr. Wakelin. A receipt for this amount is enclosed herewith. Yours faithfully Assistant Britig in the Net The Political Agent Political Agency, Kuwait.I lA BRITISH COUNCIL CAIRO§£# CONFIDENTIAL Kuirail Receipt, . No I Dated fo / 1 -l Ref.40/30. Govermaent of Bahrain, Education Department. 27th.January 1944. Dear Felly, ± &lt;-rx r\. Thank you for your letters of 25th.November and 21st.December 1943.1 am leaving the question of the library books until I can see them personally. 2.Yusuf bin Mushari was mentioned to me as one of the more promising local teachers.When speaking of him to Sheihk Abdullah bin Jabir he referred to his former record,but added that his present conduct was satisfactory. 3.1 have received from you the copy of the decisions reached by th4 Education Committee on 28th.November 1943.The modification of Articles 11 and 14 of the Staff Rules is in my opinion most undesirable. The Articles as they stand are applied universally.Should a teacher be dismissed at any time he should receive three months^or one month)notice (according to whether he Is foreign or local) or the equivalent pay in lieu thereof.In the case of a teacher resigning he should give three(or one month)notice JtMXX or forfeit the equivalent pay.The purpose of the notice is to give the Department time to find a replacement. 4.At the time of the dismissal of Shimlan the Committee paid him the sum of Rs.3795/- being 11 months salary,thus creating a dangeroas precedent.! have received several letters from the Director of Educatin about this matter.I enclose a translation of my reply.The second enclosure is a copy of the covering letter that I sent to Sheikh Abdullah, the &amp;&amp; original of which I have sent to you for forwarding.lt will be more I satisfactory if in future all communications from the Director are sent •through you. 5.1 was asked by the Committee,when last in Kuwait, to arrange for the return of Ahmad Edwani,who is studying at Al Azhar University In Cairo.I wrote to Mr.Highwood of the British Council asking him if he would kindly assist in the matter by passing on a draft for £E.25 for the fare to Kuwait.On 21feh.January 1944 I received a telegram from the Director saying that the Committee wished Edwani to remain.In my reply I asked whether Edwani had been informed.The answer was in the negative• I can,of course,cable to kr.Eighwood asking him not to send the man, and am in fact doing so today.I should like,however,to point out that this is not the first time that this sort of thing has happened.The work that I undertook for the Kuwait Government during my summer leave was prolonged and made difficult by the contradictory instructions that I received.I was obliged to UatM leave the final arrangements to Mr.Highwood who was kind enough to take on the responsibility on my behalf.When the party arrived five non mission boys were included although no definite arrangements had been made,and Marzook,who had applied to be admitted to the Alexandria University was alee in the party in spite of the fact that his acceptance was not definite. The Committee’s attitude has always been that as everything turned out satisfactorily all is well.Is it not possible to convince them of their own responsibility in the matter? 6.1 have today received your message that His Highness wishes all correspondence to come through you.V* ( 2 ). „ 7 •On 21st•December 1943 I received a draft for £E.250 from the Director of Education *ith a request that I pass it on to the Ministry of Education^in Cairo.This sum was in payment of fees for the non mission students•Vould it not be better if such sums were paid through you?In this case I have forwarded the money to Cairo. 8.1 am not yet able to say when I shall be able to make my second visit to Kuwait.Unfortunately we have unexpectedly lost the Head Master and Second Master of the Secondary School so that our original staff of four is sadly depleted.X have been obliged to increase my own teaching programme to 14 periods per week as we have no one who can teach Mathematics or Science.Until I find a suitable replacement I shall be unable to get away. 9.The British Council Books Department has already despatched many of the books required by Kuwait.I shall be interested to know when they reach you.Copy of Translation. Siieiiik Abdul iah al Jahar as Sabah Rais al Maaref, Kuwait• Government of Bahrain, Education Department. SBth.MKharram 1363. (22nd.January 1944). S. Dear Sheikh Abdullah, Jaber hi°self! 1 J in ° h&amp;r ^ e of the H ' stel arid t° her for a receipt frai . ««1 Ar I f a ‘ unoer ^ aln whether Mi-s.Mellor would accept a present.St mipht be easier .o leave the matter to the end of the term.I hope to visit Cairo a**ain if 1 ! took 6 * ° 860 t i ie ^ U ! alt 3tud6nts and I think that it might be better attain ir ,M -hnr nt,that y0 ^, might Vl '' ish to ^a^e^As I shall be in Kuwait again li, a short time we can discuss the matter then. , . 3 *;t th . nk that your 3U Sgestion that you hold night classes in English •-^*- nd Arabic is an excellent one,and wish then every success. 1 o V ?*? n January the Director of Education wrote to me about the dismissal wishln^that tUZlLl ifclosed! 51 ^ ^ mU3t d ° 38 313 Highne8S Snd y0Ur3elf wnether educational or not.If a teacher is dismissed he receives either 3 montl ° r T 10 f hS i: ay 111 lieu of adra i fc ^at ShimlanTs case was xcepLionel but I hope,ior the sake of the Department,that the rules will stand . r + u l L another clause which in m opinion should be added.That is that if a teacher is sick and has a doctor's certificate he or she will be paid l0r and lialf salary for a second month after which no rther salary will be paid until the teacher returns to work.This rule is also applied universally and Imhope that vou will agree to add it. ' .In my reply to the Director I have asked him that all his communicating DCjiie be sent through you and have reminded him that he should take his instructions, fraa you as I am only Adviser and not Rais al arcf. ( Aif m u V ff y T P ?' eaS f d ^ t0 learn that Kls RirJrmess has agreed to alloKw t0 visit Bahrain.Our mid term holiday is from 25th.February C0 • 1 ^ h 4’ M S r 2 h I I .?^ 8gest that you have y° ur holiday from 3rd. to 17th.March anu .hat Ustad All spends that time with us and returns to Kuwait with me wnen I make my second visit of the year to you. p . B.Mr.bighwood ol the British Council has written to me about the boys in Cairo.He says: J . &gt; ' 1 h b ,P a f rl ^ e f i h C ? i b° °? the “ ornin B 6th.October.They were met at I; 3 station by Mehu.Shalabi who had b.-en sent by the Ministry of F.ducotion. t the sta h° n and at 8 * 30 P * M ' Shalahi rang up asking btlp.with the assistance of the two lad$ secretaries of the British ^-^atltute the 17 rather dirty and hungry young men were temporarily housed .n tne Institute.As if was Thursday nothing could be done at the Ministry and so we arranged to put them all at the Orman School under the charge of Mrs.seller who was very kind and helpful.They remained there until the' school year began. * 1 saw Naguib Hashem,Controller General of Kis ions,many times before we were able to decide on their d stlnatlons.Abdullah Jaber Is at the Orman' School and 10 at the Saidieh School.The problem was what to do with the remaining five.Eventually after much discussion and arranging the Head Master 05 the Tanta School agreed to accept them.I was in Tanta last week and saw the boys who looked well and happy.I am told that they are good in Arabic but their English is very week indeed.The Head Master,Affifi Bey,is an exceedingly good man and the school is a fine clean looking building,so I think that thev are in good hands. ^( 2 ). nf ^ he *.ff C i ilty ° f Medicine at the Alexandria University.The Diroctc of the British Institute, Mr.PhiHip®,Is keeping an eye on him.I myself sign a Lis application form acting on your behalf.Will you ask the Rais al Maaref in Kuwait if he will please write direct to the University saying that the Kuwait Government are responsible fo the boy. 4 - t S ?. it w111 be a good thin ^ if the Kuwait Hovermnent sehd o the Ministry ol Education in Cairo and to us a statement of the finances 0 , • v lC +? 0n b °y 3 as I gather that some of them have plenty of money which they keep with them,and this,I should think,is not very satisfactory. Bel ore long I i 6 pe to send you a more detailed report on the boys. ■. I would,like you to mak it quite clear to the Kuwait Government that I neither as an individual nor as a member of the British Council can accept responsibility for these boys.This is the job of the Ministry.I am however quite ready,as I told you before,to keep a fatherly eye on them and to report co you from time to time.It seems that the Ministry is not clear on this pOj.nt.A letter from Kuwait to the Ministry stating the position is.I think, necessary . 1 99 Vnhat is required is a letter to the Ministry confirming that the fees of five boys(those in Tanta* Alexandria) will be paid by the Kuwait Government, direct to the Ministry and that the 10 at the Said!eh School and the Orman studying and living at the expense of the Egyptian Government.A copy should ^sent to me for transmission to the British Council,Cairo. Yoyrs sincerely. Educations Bahrain.-77 y t Copy of translation of letter to Director of E.,Kuwait. Dear Ustad Ali Haikal, Government of Bahrain; Education Department, « 22nd.January 1944. I enclose a receipt for the £E.37 sent to the British Council by me. 2. Reference your letter of 1st.December 1943 asking me to order games equipment etc.from Egypt I have not been able to do so as the British Council send only books. 3. Reference your second letter of 5th.January 1944 and telegram of 4th.January I have written t&lt;t&gt; Sheikh Abdullah about t his matter which is now settled. A word of explanation is perhaps necessary,In my position as Adviser I recommended certain regulations which were accepted with certain modifications.Your further actions should then be determined by the wishes of Sheikh Abdullah.My authority over you is through the Rais alMaaref. 4.Thank you very much indeed for the two copies of your book A1 Tarbia al Maqsood and the three copies of the school syllabus.I amat present studying them with interest. 5.1 will discuss the question of the inspection of the Arabic teadhing when next we meet.In the mean time I advise you to continue as you are the man best qualified to do it. 6.1 am glad to know that the Education Department funds are now in the Bank and that you receive Rs.250 p.m. for Petty Cash, and also that you are preparing the furniture. 7.In Bahrain the Government supports the religious school with a grant of Rs.120 pPdanRs and has the right of inspection.In Kuwait you should raise the standard in the same way. 8.1 am passing on the two documents of Dorieh Khairi to the Ministry of Education. 9.1 have received a letter from the British Council saying that they are buying what books are available and will send them on to you at the earliest opportunity. lO.Pleaae thank the Egyptian masters and Khalid Ghorabeli for their Christman Cards. Yours sincerely. Ustad Ali Haikal, Director of Education, Kuwait. Educational. Adviser,Kuwait, •ain.A -_ inted in England. Sept. 194Z ( 4 , 100 . pad *.) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (incorporated in enolano.) (nAX? 5 The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named:— Prefix Letters and Number of Message. Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. Circuit. J Clerk’s Time Name. Received. VTE A. H 1730 cr* VT14/T BAHRAIN £5 14 1150 LC POL I T I CAL AGENT KUWA I T ASK ALMAAREF FIX HOLIDA V AND INFORM ME STOP CAN HAIKAL COME FOR STAFF REFRESHER COURSE 4 MARCH STATING TWO WEEKS = WAKELIN = ?.A. MARK YOUR REPLY Jmsi&amp;uaC t&lt;r( ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.D.O.No.C/136 Political Agency Kuwait. 19th February 1944 0 Dear 'Yakelin Thank you for your letter No.40/30 dated the 27th January 1944. 2. I see that you have written to Shaikh Abdulla al Jabir regarding the Educational Committee’s proposal to modify Articles 11 &amp; 14 of the Staff rules and I shall forward his reply as soon as I receive it. 3. In future, as all correspondence between you and the Educational authorities here will come through me I shall be in a position to do my best to prevent the difficulties you mention in para graph 5 of your letter. 4. Tith regard to your paragraph 7—1 agree that payment of the fees mentioned should in future be through me. 5. I hope you will be able to make your visit here for a period sufficient to settle any questions between you and the Kuwait educational authorities. They are far more likely to accept your advice and to carry it out when given to them through personal contact rather than in long range correspondence carried on through me. 6. The books have not yet arrived from the British Council although their bill has. Yours sincerely F.J.tfakelin,Esquire, Director of Education Bahrain Government, BAHRAINTranslation of letter No.R.6.226b, dated 15th February, 1944, from H.H. the Ruler to the Political Agent,Kuwait. t ) s : After Compliments, I have the pleasure of acknow 1 edgihg the receipt of your letter No.C/61-4/13-iii dated 10.2.44, along- with the statements of the value of. books purchased f r us by the British Council, amounting to 2.£.445.760, I have the pleasure of enclosing a cheque for 2.£.445.760 in favour of the British-Council, Cairo. Please ackno ledge the receipt of the cheque. Usual Ending. ./v.&amp; etter No.R,6.&lt;i27.'5 dated 18.1,44 r of Kuwait, to the Political Trans from H.H, A^ent, Kuwait. After Compliments, I have the hohour of acknowledging the. receipt of your letter No.'aa of 16.2.44, together with the translation of the telegram received from Mr. ?. J- Wakelin, the contents of which I have fully under- I wish to inform you that it has been decided that the spring holiday will begin immediately after the six-monthly examination,i.e. Saturady 4th 'larch, 1544. % The Director of Education will leave her e s • t after the examination, i.e. on 4th March,194'±. Usual Ending.57 TO PREVENT MISTAKES ATTENTION IS CALLED TO THE IMPORTANCE OF LEGIBLE WRITING. Karachi, May 1!)42, C'AHl.K AND WlliELESS EIMITE 1 ). (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) No. Charge. h,sections “Via Imperial” OFFICE STAMP AND DATE. Clerk's Name» No. iind Circuit and 1 ime forwarded. No. Words Time Instructions to be Signalled. To Name Address.. 'w AXE LIN BAHRAUT , i p MIT f T •Mi •HOUPATS fTSD ?ROff 4TH- MARCH STOP HA1HAL V.1LL HEAVE FOURTH POLITICALCOM DITIONS. 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government telegraph Administrationjly whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course o e telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram °'S it has been received for that purpose; but in such case the amount paid Tor transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegfaph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or i amagt arising resulting from non-transmission or non-deliver, of the telegram or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred oven though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration any officer or servant in their employ. 3 This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations sbal be deemed to be binding between the sender and this er any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom tins telegram ,s or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4 The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any oilier means whatsoever. HOTS.—Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from wh,ch the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. , , If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks contmmng tiyurel and letters, are r«cd in code directed destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance for must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable word, m the text and signature Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company’s BranchesCONFIDENTIAL Kuwait Receipt }&gt; ^ Dated u Z 1 X 14 ^ &amp; THE BRITISH COUNCIL, 25, SHARIA ABOU EL SEBAA, CAIRO. KUW/I/IO 3rd March 1944 Hear Sir, I beg to acknowledge with thanks receipt of your letter with enclosed cheque amounting to L.E.445.760m/ms in settlement of your account. I enclose herewith our official receipt ITo .785. ■ Yours faithfully. .-Adamopoulos. Books Dept Accountant. The Political Officer, Kuwait .HERS I AIT GULP. V ^ \ 4BRITISH COUNCIL CAIRO Cairo, the..?:A v?. A/ no 785 (&amp;'/j.fuxc.W ^ Government of Bahrain, (^7 : v« (t LSAa /^a&gt; fTT^Education Department, Ref.170/30. Deai 1 Felly, »/y| gQth.Ivlarch 194 4. CONFIDENTIAL Kuwait Receipt No i-i.G % Dated - I enclose a letter to His Highness thanking him for allowing All Kaikel to^isit Bahrain.Will you please forward it.The copy is for your files. O.J.Felly Esq.,0.3#E., Political Agent, Kuwait. Yourstranslation of letter A To. V./ 6/2338 dated the 9th April, 1944, from His Highness tiie Ruler of Kuwait, to the'Political '.rent, Kuw ait. \fter Compliments, z' 1 v .• I have acKr^v/ledr;ed the receipt of your letter Mo.137 dated the 4th April, 1944, enclosing a letter addressed, to me from Mr* Karelin 'on which I thanKed you ^or'the sar e. I am enclosing a cover in reply to his letter and shall he rrsteful if you will kindly forward it to TT r. fekelin with my best compliments.K' ■mV Governrient of’ $ahrain, Education Department. 29th.April 1944. I enclose my report on 'Education in Kuwait with a copy for the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 2. The only point that vitally concerns His iiighness is that of 'the dismissal of Abdul Moneian,Head Master of the Sharqieh School. I have expressed my opinion as forcibly as I can.You will see that since discussing- my report with you I have added the hint, in the last paragraph of the opening section,that the Egyptian Ministry of Education might consider it advisable to withdraw Abdul Moneim on the grounds that he is a disturbing influence among their teachers. 3. His Highness has expressed his interest in some maps printed in Arabic that T nave obtained from Cairo through the British Council. I am therefore sending him two,one of Euroue and one of Asia.! shall despatch them on the first up mail addressed to you. il -1 you please present them to His Highness on my behalf. C.J.Pelly Esc.,O.B.E., H'.B.M*s Polltice 1 Agent, Kuwait• \ *- jrr —y T ' Dort on Educa tion in ruvjalt by i..r.F» ’ .akelln, du c at lon a l -V i sor . 26th.April 1944 . L'v second visit of tie year was from l«5tL. cc 26tl.x 1 t}.e day of my arrive 1 I calle on His TT ichness Sir Sheikh Ahmad al Sabah and later discussed v-ith Shcildj. Abdullah bin ykais ,aref,tne state of educational af‘airs.He indicated that all was^ noo \.‘ell ^/itnln the Department and the following day at a meeting c. t-a. Educettron Com ittee reports by the members confirmed that there v.o.s coricus trouble among the staf Durinr the days that followe made a routine irag.'ocuioji of all the schools and meanwhile took every opportunity of hearing the points Ily assessment of the situation rs as follows! In September 1943 Abdul Aziz Shimlan,the former ^jirecuor of xaducat.; was replaced by Ustadh Ali Hakal,one of the four Egyptian teachers who had been working in Kuwait for the past year.At the same time oen otner Ervptians were engaged as teachers.At the time when tue ap; ointment o Haikal was und r consideration I pc'.nted out that the most impor^„.n ttspec of the Director’s work was that of maintaining harmony among -m said that it was unlikely that Haikal could do this as Ms qualifications are similar to those of the other Egyptians although he has a little more teacMng experience, then any difficulty arose between tne plrectwr ana one of Ms own countrymen the teacher showed his resentment at Doing ^iven orders by one whom he considered no better than himself.Invarwabxy differences of opinion concerning the work took on a personal aspect ana frequently both parties descended to personal abuse. Soon after my visit in November last two groups were formed among the a'Tptians,each of which sought the help of influential people -no 0 x local staff. 1 very point,no master low small - routine or otherwise - was used by both sides in attempts to bring discredit on the other party. Tie Director in order to enforce Ms authority adoptea a dictatorial attitude thus alienating the s. Mes of those who were able to take a more dispassionate view of these personal quarrels. It is clear that Haikal must go.Fe.lings have been too deeply stirred ton all sides,for a compromise to be possible. 1 have b en askc^ D t/ , e Comr. ittee to nominate a successor.I. shall endeavour to find an Egyptian with good qualifications and administrative experience and - what is more important -with tact and patience. The Committee are convinced that when Haikal is replaced all Mil be well.I can not agree with this optimistic view.I have made every effort to heal the breach in the ranks of the Egyptians but without success. Personal relations have been strained too far.A group^o^ ohree, idnuil i/oneira, Kamal Abdou and Tuhami,are in constant opposition to the others. I aaii certain that as long as this group remains in being the tiouoles of the past year will continue.The Committee do not agree wi-h believe P that the bitter feelings existing can easily be dissipated by a little kindness.ily recommendation#that Abdul honeim be asked uo terminate Ms agreement at the end of tMs year,ana Kamal given ux.e option of working in Kuwait or Bahrain were not agreea to. In my opinion Abdul Eoneim,Head Master of the Sharqieh Scmo 1 is a '-•chief maker.He does not hesitate to spread malicious gossip ana is accession,His Highness's Investiture an,: the School Pl-’yAattemptod toI Page 2. ' . to give the impression that he was the accepted leader of the Egyptians and in some way superior to his colleagues.The fact that Haikal was hasty or overbearing' does not absolve Abdul Koneim from blane^.It tabes two to . f rel - one 2 clap alone.His bohfitTjgDur durln past few days does not show him up in a very favourable light.Tie has openly rejoiced at the downfall of Haikal and has claimed that it was brought^ about tlirough his own machinations*He he s even gone so xar as to say ■-'hat he is to be aonointed Director* Both Tuhami and Kamal Abdou are good men and have made^ a success of their work.They are however headstrong and have found it hard to work under Haikal. But I am certain that without Abdul Moneim to mislead them they v/111 devote their whole energies to teaching rather than expend ir them on petty intrigue. It is my considered opinion that unless Abdul Foneim is asked to resign,no matter who the new Director may be,trouble will again develop in the future.The Committee hold that there is no^definite reason one can offer to the man when asking for his resignation*Surely the o.act t' t the unity o ' the at; 'f depends upon it is cuff .c5.eiiG• Pen . • ^ -^roii the Ministry of gducation,Cairo, is necessary before he c r r( Ign.This permission I know will be forthcoming as they will consider working of their teachers of vital importance.Should he go the nma Director' will have every opportunity ©^making a success of his work without the handicap of having to lead a team divided within itself. Inspection of Schools . (a) .Boys 1 schools. I inspects .the four JOTS f Schools in the town and the village schools of iTowclli,Fantas,Abuheliefoh and Pahahiel. the sc ho well taught sn thn Thore is a marked improvement in all the Secondary School.There the subjects are have shown great resource in utilisi-ig vliat few m bori in these difficult times.The Science Room is a credit to th Ustadh Thabit is to be congratulated on his enterprise. particularly 1 lasters Is are avallabb schorl and The standard of English has risen considerably in all schools. This is due chiefly to the untiring efforts of Ustadh Dhief who has done so much to help the local staff.Some of these local teachers are taking great trouble over their work*Those who spend time preparing theii lessons are making excellent progress.There are some however who are o obviously slack about this and who are consequently making mistakes which could easily be-avoide • Throughout tie schools Arithmetic is still very badly taught.(kith the one exc € 11 on ef the Far si eh Girls * Scho^ll .1 am aware ohe lack of books has in the past b' n c handicap,but now that that problem has been overcome there shouD.d be no excuse for bad teacning in tne future.The old method of copying a few worked examples from the board must be replaced by that of working out a large number of examples at speed with little or no help from the teacher. Through the as istance of the British Council in Cairo about_ 1450 worth of school books were obtained .! rom ngypt so that now every child in each of the town sclio&lt; Is has textbooks for all subjects. The number of pupils in the kindergarten classes must be steadily decreased to abott 20 - 25 per room.Hew entrants should be restricted ata two teachers should be present during each lesson.This is also a very convenient method of training new staff. Of the kindergarten teachers Oqab IQiatib of the Mobarakieh Lchool is out standing. Other Kuwaitis who ire doing particularly well are harnad Hejaib of the Ahriadieh and Khalid Gharabeli and Saleh Abdul Malik of the hubarakieh. Ly last Visit to the village schools was in November 1942.1 was pleased to find a great improvement at Fantas and Kowali.Both these schools are provided with desks and blackboards.The standard is still low but the pupi1s appeared well looked after.The Department has provided good clothing for- many of the pupils and the general standard of cleanliness has improved.The school at Abuleifeh v/as shut as the Head Master.had gone shopping in Kuwait.At Fahaheil a few children who were squatting on the dirty floor were supervised by a child of about 13 while the Head Master (whom I found sleeping in the’ middle of the room on my former visit) was resting at home• 'when he was sent for he was unable to say at first how many classes or children he h; d in the school. PO • The Jaffarieh School . This school is maintained by the Persian community.The medium is chiefly Arabic but Persian is also taught.The standard is far belov that of the Government schools.I suggest that the Education Department take over the school and supply good teachers,books and equipment .The Government syllabus should be adopted but modified to include Persian and the Siiia religious instruction.I recommend that when a boy reaches cl * ry he should be off ere elm choifie^ * ■ at ^ ie Jaff^rieh School and studying Persian or of being transferred to one of the present Government schools and taking up English. (c).The Girls 1 Schoolslt is not possible for me to give a detailed criticism of the Girls’VSchools as I can visit them only after school hours. Whether the needlework that I was shown was all done by the pupils themselves I am not in a position to say but there was an impressive display in both schools.Arrangements should be made for parents and friends to visit the schools and see the work being done. Schools at present.The case of the mistress Labibeh of the Sharqieh Scho 1 has been brought to my notice.She is entitlrd to a pas age to Egypt from the American Mission and wishes to avail herself of it this year.Under these circurdstances she should be offered a two year contract as in the cases of the other Egyptians with the usual conditions in respect of travelling and housing allowances. v ) /English Examination . I On Monday 24th.April 1944 the English examination for the Eastern B-mk lAward was held in the Mobarakieh School.There were two papers both of wMc! Lore set,invigilated and marked by me.Ten candidates presented themselves bf whom five passed.Prizes were awarded to the first three as under: 1st. Abdul Mutaleb Rajab 2nd. hoshari Mohammed Jasem 3rd. Abdul Mohsen Rasheed (e).Games• Ustadh Kamal Abdou has done a great deal towards the development ofPage 4. aT r of organised games.I was much impressed by the weekly Kxywyr activities held in each school,which were well organised and carried out with obvious enjoyment•I was sorry that the annual sports meeting was not held during my visit.lt ap ears that the Director irybrder to bring discredit on the do cs Master made his orders as vague as possible and the Games raster in order to be revenged on the Director deliberately misunderstood his instructions!The result was o postponing of the meetingjuntil after my visit (e ) . The School Play . On Tuesday 8th.April 1944 I attended a play given by the Education ■ ^.With one exception the atftorn Were all Kuwaitis*.The play was produced by Ustadh Gowdat,an Egyptian master from the Ilobarakieh School. It v/0.3 a great successW.The acting was good although there were certain nervous mannerisms- which were rather irritating .The seating arrangements were not all that might be desired.llext year there should be two performance] the first for the members of the Royal Family,prominent members of the Kuwait community and the Europeans;the second for the general nublie including schoolboys.A charge of Rs.5/- or Rs.lO/- shold be made* for the first and of Rs.2/- on'::.!/- for the second. j (f).Art. Ustadh. Ali Cul. u.n 1 . de t progre s * ‘ t! : 5 s ,rt clarso' 4 his training of the local staff.Some sort of exhibition should be arranged at the end of the year so that parents may see the excellent work being done. The Education Com ittee. At a meeting of the Com ittee on Tuesday 25th.April t made th-'' following recommendations which were all an roved: (1) .Any teacher leaving school before the end of term should forfeit I I pay for the period of hi^absence. (2) .The summer holiday should be from Thursday 29th.June to Saturdav 9th.October. (3) .All staff must be present in Kuwait at least one week before the opening of term.Any teachers failing to do so must forfeit their pay for their period of absence. (4) .Ustadh Kamal Abdou should be paid from the day on which he left Cairo and not from the 1st.October 1943. (5) .Owing to the further increase in the cost of living the war allowance of the local teachers should be increased as soon as possible. (6) .The mid day break should be reduced from 3^ hours to 2 hours in order to give more tine for games and other activities after school hours. (7) .From late April to early May until the end of the term there should, be one ses Ion of six lessons lasting from about l-g hours after sunrise until about one hour after mid day. (8) .Smoking should be forbidden in the schools during school hours except in staff rooms.During my inspection I was astonished to season several occasions teachers smoking in fron£ of the boys. __page 5. ^ % page 5. Ill'conclusion I wish to comment on the steady improvement during the year'in all the schools in spite of the ell the difficulties encountered. I have every reason to believe that this improvement v.ill be maintained ^.fd 1 am certain that with the readjustments of staff that I have tlaa.t even grerter progress v.ill be su'de in the future. Educational Adviser. 26th.April 1944 J.Z. rCONFIDENTIAL. No.C/37y The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUoRInZ . and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Bated the 18thLay 1944 . Reference to previous correspondence : DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. RKPOHT DAT3D 26TH APRIL. 1944. ON EDUCATION IN ri:tf AIT Ibt MR.F.J* 'aAl^ELlX. aDUCA- tlONAL ADViSKIi .KUW/l/l Hie British Council, 25, Sharia Abou el Sebaa, Cai ro • 8th April, 1944. Dear Prior, Following on our conversation of 7th February, I have had a letter from the British Council in London saying that they would be prepared to agree in principle to the proposal that an Educational Adviser should be appointed in Kuwait, but warning us of the extreme diffi culty at the moment of finding suitable personnel for such posts. In addition to any developments in Kuwait, we shall have to find a replacement for Wakelin, who is due to leave Bahrain in 1945. I am afraid this is not very encouraging, but the Council will certainly consider with the greatest care any scheme put up to it and will do what it can to meet the requirements. Yours sincerely, Sd. T.S.R. BOASE. Sir Geoffrey Prior etcI)# 0# So# 363fc»fc*# Th« Ke&amp;ldency f Bu»hlri f th« 6th Kay X944 te6 Dear Boaae ilease refer to your letter Ho# l/i of the 8th A^rll 1944 regarding an SAueatlonal Aivleer for Kuwait# wai elln oaeie up In toy steaner with me from Bahrain to Kuwait# and eo I w&amp;a able to go Into the question of Kuwait affairs with hi® in more detail than I have hitherto been able to do# It appears that there has been a good deal of oppoeition to hire there# meetly of a rather uninformed description# and that one of the pointe to whloh objection waa taken was tht fact that he was described as 'ftluoational adviser* possibly beoauet it was thought that this opened the way to further administrative penetration on our* side I I told him that thla could &lt;iuite easily be me t describing him ae British 'lounoil Representative, and I only mention it as m instance of the way some quite unimportant anl trifling matter my prejudice the general alms that we have in view# 3# 1 was not in Kuwait very long, but 1 had several talks udth the Shaikh who seamed well pleased with the assistance he got from the British Council and their help in obtaining teachers and supplying bo^ka, and there was little doubt that the vlnister in charge is very oo-dperative and glad of the help he gets# The Committee, however, who arc mostly Ignorant or semi educated merchants, are very influential and all have axes to grind and are not very helpful, and I have suggested methods of reducing them to their ;&lt;xoper proportions# whan I left wakelin seemed to be getting on muoh better, and I have since heard privately from the Political Agent that the general attitude towards him has greatly improved# I do not feel however that the moment has yet come when we should consider a /hols-time man for Kuwait, and it would be muoh better to proceed slowly and wait till the State is more conscious of the benefits and has more money to spend# 4# 1 suggest therefore that we oonoentrate for the time being on obtaining a really good replacement for v,akelin in 1945, and endeavour as far as possible to have a Tr*n who would be prepared to stay at least three years so that he oan become well known to local personalities# 1 sending a copy of this latter to the India Office, and the Government of India# Yours sincerely Sd. -GBOFFRSY PRIOR Professor T*8*K# Roams, British Counoil Represcatatlvs, Middle Bast# C A I R 0 #4^ Translation of letter No.R.6.2362 doted 25th 1 ' 1 of Kuweit, to the Mr. I*. J. Wo Selin’s report about the proceedings of the education of our Education Department. I wish to thank you for sending me the report and in the same time I request you to send my best thanks and to Mr. Wake1in for his care and interest in our Education Department. Usual Ending. receiot of your 4 together withPrinted in England. Aug. 1941. (8,(100 puds) The first line of thi» Telegram contain* the following particulars in the order named :— Prefix Letters ind Number ol Message, Office of Origin, Number of Words. Date, Time handed in and Officia! instructions—if any. VT 55 /D BAHREIN 20 31 0045 LC POL ITI CAL KJWA I T KAMALA3D0U LA 8 IBEH SAB I HE H N A H A L HAVE APPLIED WORK HERE STOP WE.WILL NOT CONSIDER WITHOUT COMMITTEES APPROVAL IWAKEL I N MARK YOUR REPLY Jhn/ie?ua&amp; NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY.■‘■elegram From To © Political Agent, Kuwait Political Resident, Bushire No 454 Dated 6th June 1944. Your telegram No.13 2. Copy of Jake 1 ins report has 'been given to Sheikh. Yith difficulty I have got him to the point where he has prom ised to consult the Education Department and then to inform me of what he decides to do about Abdul Moneim. Am leaving note for Jackson. Letter follows. == Political ==COH^nSNTIAL. Political Agency, Kuwait, Gih June 1944. Dear Sir There ie little comment I can add to tile facts given in my telegram No.454 dated 6th June. I am told that ’Izzat Jaffar, His Highness* 'Social Secretary* takes sides in the disputes amongst the Egyptian teachers. He has, of course, His Highness* ear, is a supporter of Ahdul Moneirib and trying to persuade His Highness not to get rid of him. This, I believe, is the reason why the Sheikh put me off twice (by saying he had not read ’fakelirfs reportJ when I raised the question of his getting rid of Abdul Moneim. I shall ask Jackson to press it. As a 'test case' as to whether 'yakolin , s advice is to be accepted (apart from it*s intrinsic importance) it will be necessary to insist on Abdul Moneim's services being dispensed with. yours sincerely, The Hon*ble Sir Geoffrey Prior, K.C.I.E Political Resident in the Persian Gulf BU SHIRED.O.No.309/30. A KaJ\. • i\W ‘ \ iV Ff L l. M 6 ft/ Mft • Government of Bs.hi* A i n &gt; Education Department. I I'V'' (@ X am enclosing six documents in connection with the most recent consignment of 'books from the British Council that I sent on to you on the Resang. ,g/ 2 . I have not yet had a reply to our telegram of 30th.May 1944 asking if the four Kuwait teachers had obtained the permission of the Committee before applying to us for jobs. 3. I am still awaiting His Highness 1 comments on my report of April.I expect to be leaving for Cairo at the end of this month.lt is most necessary that I receive my instructions before then so that I may make whatever arrangements are necessary with the Minister of Education,Egypt,before he goes on leave. Will you please forward the enclosed letter to Sheikh Abdullah bin Jabar,a copy of which is attached. 5 # Have you seen the photographs of the Investiture in the issue of Akhbar al Harb dated 31st.may 1944? C.J.Pelly Esq.,0.B.E., H.B.M‘s Political Agent, Kuwait.TO PREVENT MISTAKES ATTENTION IS CALLED TO THE IMPORTANCE OF LEGIBLE WRITING Kiwichi, iiav 1942 CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORAl tD IN ENGLAND.) No. No. Words Charge. OFFICE STAMP AND DATE. 1 &gt; &gt; “Via Imperial” Clerk's Name, No. and Circuit and Time forwarded. Time Instructions to be Signalled. To Name IMPORTAilT (VAKEUUJ POUTICiO. • Jt. w.Jci Address Not to be telegraphed) 1 rcailcsl that tbc nliove TcloKram m.J te tocWMded .abloct uHl.ff con.iitionl prlotcd on iMk of tM» form l,y wMob 1 woo to bo bonnei. Signature of Sender. x-r., A*. - T &lt; ll 'P h « e N °- r.7 t oCONDITIONS. 1. Tbe Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in tbe ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose; but in such case tbe amount paid for transmission will be refunded to tbe sender at bis request. 2 Neither tbe Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall bo liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-trausmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company ^ or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram 1S or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by tbe Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. NOTE.—Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office oj origin. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks .containing figure, and Utters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance mth the Rules for charging, must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any oj the Company's Branches# f w Translation of letter No.R,6.2.'5 7 4 dateri 12th June,1944, from Hi Highness the Reler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. i (OA After Compliments, with reference to my letter No.R.o.2362 dated the 2bth May, 1944. I am enclosing a letter in original, received from the Head of Education Detreatment, Kuwait in reply to Mr.F.-T. ’akelin's report. The letter speaks for itself. Usual Ending.Translation of letter dated l^th June,1944, from Shaikh Abdulla al-Jabir as-Subah, Head of Education Department,Kuwait, to,His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, After Compliments, In reply to the report by Mr, F.«T, Wakelin, the Educational Advisor, dated 26th April,1944, and the Ajen&lt;by f s letter No.195-4/13 dated 3rd June,1944, I wish to state as follows:- V ^^ Two meeting were held by the Education Department s Committee one was held on 24th May,1944 and the other on 'Hh June,1944, The following decisions were decided by the memoers:- 1, The dcision regarding Jafarfya School has been postponed ^ untill an' understanding with the department of that school has been reached, 2, Every teacher should be forced to carry on witr his duties in case he wishes to leave his post during the school year without a legal excuse, ^ 3, Summer holiday should begini^r the 5th of Rajab, 1363*? 3* and the additional examination Should begin on the 5th of shawal ,1363, and the school year should be^in on the 12th Shawal,1363. 4, The question of the school hours will be postponed -o the next year. ._ . „ ,, 5. The following should be added to the terms of ,ne contract:- , , « mA ny teac&gt; er who fails to be present a. week before the beginning of the teaching season without a leagal excuse, Committee will have the right to punish - diim with what they will find it sui tab! e , and if he ^iXl be absent two weeks after the beginning of the season without a legal exceuse, he will be liable to be dismissed,' 4 . Ustadh Kamal Abdo will be free either to stay in Kuwai - go to Bahrain, Labiba, the teacher, Syrians. ^ „ « tvt Tho Committee have agreed that Labiba .^ua man, Nun. of the Edu- 6. or 7. will be treated like her sisters the 8. Mufti I 1 J I W-m* he _ and Sabeeha Jamal remain in the service cation Dept, as they have accepted that. 9 We understood from Mr. Wakelin f s report and m°ntioned there regarding Ustadh Abdul-Muneira, when he said ' This permission will be forthcoming' which means that he will dismiss Abdul-Muneim from the service, and this is against our agreement with the Advisor, which was agreed uoon in the meeting held on 15th April, when we decided -o keep him in the service of the Education Department during 10^ The Committee has agreed on all other points of the report. Usual Ending,Printed In England. Aug 1041 . (8,000 puds) 5 /- 1 G 8 The first line ofthii Telegram contain* the following particular* in the order named Pt*f'» Letters »nd Number of Messeje, Office of Orijin, Number of Word*. Date, Time handed in and Official instruct!. f—U any. VT7/f BAHRAIN 16/15 19 £000 10 POLITICAL KU/VAIJ 'ob REFERNCE MV TELE GRAM 30/5/4'4 DU COMMITTEE APPROVE STOP LEAVING BAHRAIN TvVE N T V SE VE N TH = WAKE LIN = ?.A. MARK YOUR REPLY *2%a Jm,2eUa£^ hxj. NO INQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION Of THIS COPY.D.O.No. -4/13 Political Agency, Kuwait 25th June 1944 # My dear Tfakelin, Please refer to your D.O.No.309/30 of the 6th June, 1944. The documents you mention in your first paragraph have 'been passed on to the Education Department* ^!\I&gt; I also enclose a translation of a letter from His High ness the 3heikh forwarding the comments of the Head of the Education Department on your report* under consideration. The letter referred to in the fourth paragraph of your letter has 'been passed on to Sheikh Ahdullah 'bin Jahir* I notice that you headed the letter •Education Department, Bahrain Government• in arahic* I think you will agree that to address a Kuwait Government Department as from the Bahrain Government might invite objection. I would add that the case of Abdul Muneim is still Mr. Pelly saw the photos of the Investiture in Akbar al Harb Yours sincerely E.J. Wakelin, Esquire. BahrainCONFIDENTIAL Government of Education Department. D.O.No.333/30 17th.June 1944* British Couni nts for Kuwait. I have received intimation from the iiritish Council in London that the sum of £.3000 has been allocated to Kuwait for the financial year 1944-45.Half is for 'British Teachers' and half for 'Locally Appointed Teachers'.A copy has been sent to Sir Geoffrey. as I have seen no correspondence about the matter.I have written to London asking for further information.When in Cairo last summer I strongly urged the Representative of the Council to subsidise the Egyptian teachers in Kuv.ait rather than allow the Egyptian Government to do so.By 'Locally Appointed Teachers' they may mean Egyptians.At the same time 1 pressed for a grant so that we might appoint a British Director.£.1,500 will more than cover his passage,salary and allowances. These allocations have come as a complete surprise to me C.J.Felly Esq.,0.B.E., H.B.M’s Political Agent Kuwait.Kef.332/30 By Ban e Oovwi*ni:ient of Bahrain# Education Dopartmen - 17th. June 1944. Allocations «» 1944»45 . 17th. May 1944# enclosing a copy of the Persian Gulf and Kuvoit Al3-Ocations for the financial year 1944-45. X note tliat a copy has been sent to Sir Geoffrey Prior. Allocations is that I have so fur received nothing of the increase in my salary authorised as from September last. complete surprise to me as I have seen no correspondence whatsoevor in this connection. The grunts are none tho less welcome but I shall be grateful for more information.Does this mean that it will be possible to appoint a British Director of Education? I shall be leaving for Cairo at the end of this month.Will you therefore address your reply to me at the Council Office there. My only comment on the Bahrain The Kuwait Allocations have come as a R.B.Knowles Esq., Regional Officer British Council, 3,Hanover Street, London, W. 1. for the Persian Gulf, Copy to iH#B#M f s Political Agent Kuwait.CONFIDENTIAL. No, 844-4/13-111. The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, Eeference to/previous correspondence : Kuwait Printed Letter No.C/377 dated the 18th May, 1944. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No.R/6/2374 dated the l£th June, 1944, from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, to A KIT AIT EDUCATION the Political Agent, Kuwait, (with enclosure)•'T 1 J.C.Ho.0/945-4/13-111. 1 ^ Political Agency, Kuwait, n zF/ 1st July, 1944. ^)ear Sir Geoffrey, ^ y' Ple%g^ refer to letter No.K/5/2374 dated the Kuwait Printed Letter 1944. X&gt; ^' vVk the enclosure to His Highness* 12th June, 1 944 # forwarded under -4/13-1IX dated the 29th June, ^ 1 up the question of Abdul Koneim shortly afterwards with His Highness and remarked that there seemed to have been some misunderstanding of Mr.Javelin*s remarks aLout the permission froa* the 1 inis try of Education, Cairo. t , ?to?h his reply it was clear thet any tiisunderstanding had been intentional. He said that he thought that all the trouble in the past had been due to ilaikai and that he had so far found no fault with Abdul liOneixa. he intended to keep him on for a few months to see how he shaped under a new director. # he added that, had he oeen privately asked by e Political vgent to rtLiov© l. iin, liir* dismissal would have presented no difficulty; but his removal had been advocated by aKelin in hie report, which had been seen and discussed by the Acuca^lon ooiiiiiit^ee, had been the subject of gossip Hie lif.rcnant community, and intrigue among the friends of the teachers. Now that so many knew the source of the propose 1 it v,6s very difficult for him to insist on dismissal., in the lace of opposition, without incurring the charge of allowing hiivself to be dictated to b$ the Hducetional Adviser - a point, T have no doubt, that Abdul Honelm's friend© will have been at pr»5ns to stress. ^ replitjd that if he kept on Abdul Honeim he v;ould oi course be taking upon himself a larger measure of the responsibility for the satisfactory working of the department,and relieving the Adviser correspondingly. 6. ^ You will by now have received ?elly*s comments on «-re case. 1 have not been here long enough to have any very definite views; but it appears to rue that, if Abdul Moneim is as bad as Hakelin reports, it will not be Ions: before he is an embarrassment to the Shaikh and to the Education Department, ^ w bich case there can be no doubt where the responsibility lies. Time will tell; and I would suggest that we do not attempt to force the Sheikh’s hand for the present, but rather that we await developments. * The Hon’ble Sir Geoffrey .Prior, K.C.I.3., fours sincerely, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. DUSiURT, ,Abdunfal-JaMr al-Subah' ^.1^, (1. 7 . 44 ) fro» Shaikh^ .• Mr. F. J. Wakelin, Iduoational MyLerf idUCatlon ^^tment.Kuwait, to - ^ { \3&gt;£ After Compliments, &lt;Ve ^ish to inform that the Education Council'has decided to have the Ja fariya School attached to the Government schools, provided that the government syllabus will be adopted an i in addition it will include the Ja’fariya religious instructions. We have received their reply, in which they insisted upon having the Persian language taught in their school. As the loco! Government is a / Arab Govt, and the Education Dept, does not confess that the Persian lan^ua^e is an official language, we therefore have informed them that no other language beside Arabic, except English language, will be taught in the schools. The discussion ended in W** -ra -3 manner. The teaching season for this year has come to an end. We need not to add any further information about the troubles and misunderstan- dings ani grudges which have caused a great loss for us in the results of the teaching. It has become worst when we entrusted the question of the examination to committees formed out of the teachers, reserving the rights of entering the secret figures in their places by the department, after having the committees passed their judgement regarding the exami nation. The work of placing the correct figures, is naturally to he done by the Director of the ~ept.,i.e. Ali Haikal, and this gentleman, as we believe you have already understood him and have known his conducts; this . , cent man paid no attention to honour, manliness or human kindness to his inno- stuients, but he, this man, in order to crush some of th* teacher and ^cad-casters, started playing with the results of the examination. He started rubbing out the figures, adding to some of them and reducing Ohe others, according to his wish, and when ve wanted to investigate the case, we found out that he had hidden all the answers of the students whose marks he had altered, and they were 449 sxjswsxx examination papers. Ve were obliged to ti decide to re-examine the boys whose papers were altered, and this will ;ave to be done before the opening of the next season, even if the opening of the schools will hgve to be postponed for a week or more. Ve wish to dr 0 -' ycm' attention that Ali Haikal has nomi- nated himself to become the s-uijo rvi; of the Kuvaiti Educational Missions in Egypt. ’Ve do not wish to co-operate with such a man in any Vwork.si i - ^ We have submitted to you a statement of the names of the studen. for the third Mission to Egypt. We now wish to add the name of Mu'jib ad-Dawsari and we suggest should be s^en a free choice of the o r t which he would like best, either Tan or -rawing. We are expecting your reply about these students and whether they will be accepted by the Egyptian Government, and we would like you to kindly take up the matter quickly, so that they may be able to join the schools in the beginning of the school year. We have received a letter from Khalid 4hmad al-Jassar, one of the members of the Mission who is at SaeidiyaSecondary scoftl. He '.wishes to study in the Islamic Law College at Azhar, and as know this boy’s inclinations, we therefore support him and agree to what he has decided to do. We request you help him by assisting him to join the Islamic Law College at Azhar. Usual Ending. *'l3£ CONFIDENTIAL, No. c The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to P.J. Wakolin, Esquire, G/o British Council Representative Near East, 25 Sharia Aboud 21-3ebah, C and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 10th Ju1 ?* 1944 Reference to previous correspondence DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. * 1365 Subject. Letter Ms dated the 10th Rajah, 1365 (1st July, 1944) from Shaikh Abdullah Jabir As-Subah, Head of the Education Department, Kuwait, to Mr.F.J. Wakelin, Education Adviser.Kuu ■ '* ' / \noJlou /m?.. GovernBient of- Bahrain, Education Department, 29th, J\me 1944* I enclose the reports of the ten Kuwait hoys at the Saidieh School, Cairo,received this morning.Will you please pass them on to Sheikh Abdullah bin Jabar. ^/^Yould you also inform him of the contents of the covering letter attached and return it to me. I am leaving for Egypt via Arabia this morning. ^ T n n _ Yours sincerely C.J.Felly Esq., H.B.M f s Political Agent, Kuwait.BRITTS 1 ? INST TTUT3 Ref:- INS/21/1 y 3, Sikket SI llaghratiy, CAIrlC. 14th June, 1944. -^ear Mr. lakelin, Mr. Highwood has asked me to forward the ten yearly reports which we have received from the Headmaster of the Saidai Secondary for the Kuwaiti hoys. On the recommendation of the Headmaster it has 'been arranged that the undermentioned six hoys v/ho failed in English should follow an English Course at this Institute and this they are doing now*. Khalid Al Oassar. Dawoud Mussaid. Khalid Thunoyan. Muhamed El Eahd. Kassim Mashary. Yussef Shaigi. Soi' the four hoys who passed in English arrangements are being made, also on the suggestion of the Headmaster, that they should attend the Summer Course at the Institute due to start in July. Ali Zakaria El \nsari. Ahd El Hazik El Edwani. Abd Aziz El Sarawi. Ahmed Aurayfan. Yours sincerely, Sd/r D. Paul. Secretary to Director. E.J. ITakelin Esq.., Director of Education, Bahrain.s^S C.OKFID. iiXIAL , Hiu-Ht- Office of the Political Resident in ; l ' CONFIDENT!/. L the Persian Gulf t Camp, Shiraz• the 24th,August 1944# To«- Kuwait Recinpt H#M,Secretary of State for India, India Office, LOUDON . Copy toi- Th© Political agent, Bahrain. The Political agent, Subjects- Travelling expenses of the Director of education, Bahrain, on^hjis_visits_o£ inspection to Kuwait# Reference India Office Express Letter No#Ext# 6147/43, dated the 13th November, 1943# 2# Copy is enclosed of .'.iemorandum No# C/1102.dated the 24th July, 1944, from the Political agent, Bahrain, and of its enclosures. It is requested that the British Council isay be asked to refund to the Bahrain Government the expenditure incurred, by payment to the account of the Bahrain Government with the Eastern Bank, London# AITi^D Sd. GEOFFREY PRIOR, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. l for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf#Confidential Political p Bahrain, the 24th. July,1944 No. C/1102. ' To The Hbn»ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 3 u ^ s h^j L r e Hemoranduja Reference India Office Express Letter No. Ext.6147/43 dated the 13th. November, 1943. Travelling expenses of the Director of Education, Bahrain, cn his visit of inspection to Kuwait. 2. I enclose herewith a copy of memorandum No. 1395-2E dated the 12th. July, 1944 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, together with its enclosures, for favour of necessary action. VEM* Sd/- T.E.Rogers. Political Agent, BahrainCopy of Memorandum No. 133E—2E d^ted the l^th. July # 1944 # from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government to the Political Agent, Bahrain* lx* iu N With reference to my memorandum No* 1165/2E dated the 28th* May, 1943 and No. 2043/2E dated the 28th. October, 1943 and your reply No. C/1482 dated the 3rd. November, 1943, I now enclose herewith a further statement of expenses incurred by the Bahrain Government for the trips to Kuwait of Mr. F.J. Wakelin, Director of Education, Bahrain, amounting to Rs. 694/- and should be obliged if you would obtain settlement of the amount.^) IxNOUHHrJ) ON U4, F,J. FEMm^^g VXglT.JEfl (December) Steamer passage to Kuwait paid to Messrs, Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co,, Ltd, H eturn trip as Mr, Wakelin»s bill, (April) Stearner=fare to Kuwait Return fare and expenses as per bill from Mr, F,J, Franklin, Rs, 121—8—0, Rs. 170-0-0 . 291-8-0. Rs. 121-8-0. Rs. 281-0-0 . 402-8-0 Rs.694-Q-( (Total six hundred ninety four rupees only)THE BRITISH COUNCIL 25, SHARIA ABOU EL SEBAA, CAIRO. BY BAG 1st September, 1944 co: Dear Jackson IlbC I have been asked by the Kuwait Government to arrange for the further education in Egypt of twenty-three boys at the expense of the Egyptian Government and five at their own expense. The Minister of Education, Cairo, is ready to provide free education, but cannot accommodate any of them. He points out that already ten Kuwait boys are studying here at the expense of the Egyptian Government. I have gone into the question of a hostel for Kuwait students, with the British Council. Nothing can be done at the moment. As it is altogether undesirable that schoolboys should live in lodgings these boys must remain in Kuwait for this year. The Minister has been most helpful over the question of the Director of Education. I hope to have some definite news in a few days’ time as I am going to Alexandria to see His Excellency on Saturday next. Yours sincerely u Educational Adviser Kuwait N. Jackson, Esq., H.B.M.’s Political Agent Kuwait. epffft ■^ele^pam ^rorn To Political ,\fent, I'u iT ait. Political A^ent, Bahrain. No. 73o Dated 2nd October, 1044. I understand 'akelin has returned to Bahrain. If this is correct,can you please ask him firstly whether he had any success in obtaining a new Director of Education for Ku^ait^and secondly when we can expect the Egyptian teachers to arrive here; Orateful if 3 r ou con telegraph gist of his reply.The first tine of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named .— Prefix Letters end Number ol Messite, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. Printed in England. Aug 1941. (8,000 puds) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (incorporated IN ENOLANO.I Clerk’s Time Circuit. Name. Received. ‘ VIE .a. r 0930 / VT18/H DF BAHRAIN LC POLITICAL J ,T SJnjge! 34 2 1143 KUWA I T ENGAGED SADEQ HAMD I AS DIRECTOR STOP BASIC SAL AR f FOR T T &amp;ND HALF POUNDS MONTHLY STOP EXCEPTIONAL EXPERIENCE AND QUALIFICATIONS AGED FIFTY STOP LEAVING CAIRO MIDOCTOBER WITH WIFE STOP OTHER TEACHERS RETURNING =&gt; WAKEL I N » f 1 , MARK YOUR REPLY NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION Of THIS COPY.THE BRITISH INSTITUTE /T) Telkphonk : Cairo 47700 41042 Telegrams : ‘Institute”, Cairo. D.0.400/30. i vH, Director 3, SIKKET EL MAGHRABY, CAIRO. 25th#September 1944® cation for Kuwait* At the request of the Education Committee I went to Cairo to engage a suitable man to replace Ali Baikal as Director of Education. I am today in a position to state &lt;that I have at last found a first class man who is ready to accept the post*He will be released by tne Egyptian Government on 30th.September 1944 and will leave for Kuwait at the earliest possible date.I estimate that he will reach Kuwait about 20th.October 1944 at the earliest. ‘ I give below details of his qualifications and experience: Name:Sadiq Hamdi. Age:50 years. Religion: Suni Moslem. : He is a married man and will be accompanied by his wife. Education: Higher Training College Diploma 1916. Experience: Lecturer on Islamic Civizllation at A1 Azhar University,Cairo. If or 9 years. Teacher in the Government Secondary School (Tofiqieh) Shubra for 3| years. ‘^Head Master of a Government Primary School for 6 years. Inspector of Literary Subjects in Primary Schools in the Delta Area for one year. jHead Master of the Government Secondary School at Suez*for 2 years. He speaks English and French fluently.He has spent most of his vacations travelling in Europe. He is strongly recommended by the Minister of Education,Najib Hilali Pasha,who looks upon him as one of his most promising men. His salary is £E.40/500 per mensem.A man of his grade is entitled to a first class passage according to the Egyptian Ministry regulations. I have not gone into the question of Cost of Living Allowance with him as this is a master for the Committee to decide. I have seen Sadiq Hamdi on several occasions and have had long talks with him about his work.The impression that I received was that he is a steady,reliable man; one capable of dealing with others in a calm and tactful way.I am confident that he will be able to fulfil his duties satisfactorily and that he will be liked and respected by all. It has been no easy thing to persuade the Minister to realease him.This year the Egyptian Government is embarking on a programme of compulsory free Primary Education.This involves the opening of. very many new schools and the employment of hundreds of new teachers.Every man of experience is being used.!ngineers and Agriculturists are being given a f ew months training sothat they may staff the new schools. P.T.O.QV Page 2 The Minister is therefore very naturally disinclined to allow any more teachers to leave the country,particularly those with high qualifications.I first approached the Under Secretary,Hassan Bey Fayek, who deals with these matters,early in June*As soon as I reached Cairo I call d on him hut was unable to obtain a definite answer.After lengthy correspondence and iliumerable visits to the Ministry I was informed that the matter would be carefully considered.! then went to Alexandria and laid the case before the Minister personally.! * * stressed the fact that unless the was a aompetent man to fill the post the work of th3 other Egyptians in Kuwait would be frUiitless.He gave me an assurance that such a man should be found.This was 3rd.September. On ray return to Cairo the next day I ag&amp;in emphasised the need for Mediate action.A few days before the , Aid , I was asked to interview the nominees.Sadiq Hamdi was obviously the man.As the offices were closed during the holiday he visited me in my hotel and later brought his wife to see me.He returned to Suez,where he is still working,before the end of the ! Aid« so that it was not possible for me to inform the Ministry of ray approval until 21st.September.Today I have received word that the Minister has definitely approved his release and that Sadiq HAmdi has agreed to go. arrangements are being made for his passport and passage.He should be able to leave about 15th.October.I have recommended that he flies as this way is not only quicker but cheaper.1 have handed over £E.70 to him as an advance against his travelling expenses and salary. He is rather concerned about accomodation.! could say very little about this. I hope that a suitable house can be found.His * wife is a middle aged lady and has been used to a degree of comfort that will be difficult to achieve in Kuwait.Perhaps Sheikh Abdullah^ property, formerly occupied by Dr .Greenway,is still empty.If so this should suit them admirably. Of the former teachers three are not returning.Ali Haikal is remaining in CairojGowdat has been forced to resign due to continued ill healthKamal Abdou is going to Bahrain.! have selected two men to replace the last two.They are Mohamed Sabri al Saadi.He has the same qualifications as Kamal his salary being £E.12 p.m.The second, Ebrahim Abdul Gawad is a graduate d&gt;f the Institute of Education where Abdul Aziz al Mullah is studying.His subjects are Arabic,History, Geography and English.Eis salary is £E.15.This is £E.3 more than Gowdat was receiving but he is a superior type and has special teaching The other teachers should have left weeks ago and if they are late there is no excuse whatever. Several spoke of resigining but I informed them that this was impossible under the terms of their contracts. I also asked the Director of Personnel to see that they return^ immediately .The Under Secretary hopes that the Committee v/ill take the necessary disciplinary action against them by deductions from their salaries. He has now to hand over to his successor in Suez.In the meantime training. N.Jackson Esq., Kuwait.Bahrain h D.0.401/30. CONF. i I 3rd.October 1944. , (l&amp;J A'/ |Y 4 ^ o/ ^ $ ^ I have today received your I^w^o.£89-4/13 of 25th.June 1944 enclosing a translation of a letter from His Highness the Sheikh forwarding the comments of the Head of the Educatioh Department on my report of 26th.April 1944. \ I have noted your comments on the heading of my letter to Sheikh Abdullah and will in future use the address * Bahrain* only. K x have also noted the comments on my report.In paragraph 9 it is stated that I shall dismiss Abdul Moneim against the wishes of the Committee.This is of course impossible.The passage referred to reads:’Permission from the Ministry of Education,Cairo,is necessary before he can resign.This permission I know will be forthcoming as they will consider the harmonious working of their teachers of vital importance.*The Egyptian Ministry are ready to be guided by the wishes of the Committee and would approve the resignation of dismissal of any of the teachers should the Committee as^for it.I did not however raise the point when in Cairo as I had received no further instructions from His Highness. ^ Now that a competent Director has been appointed it should be possible to settle questions of school hours and other routine matters v/ithout reference to me f but I shall be ready at all times to give what assistance I can. - Your c/52b-4/l3 with the enclosure from Sheikh Abdullah reached me in Cairo on 2nd.August 1944 when I was in hospital.I was much concerned to hear about the disgraceful behaviour of Ali Haikal in connection with the examinations.! made a verbal report on the matter to the Minister and asked him to ensure that Haikal had no contact with the Kuwait Mission. In my D.O.No.400/30 of 25th.September 1944 I have mentioned that the Egyptian Government are now providing free educatio n for all their own nationals of school age.This means that this year their schools are very overcrowded and that they are having to limit the number of foreigners attending them.When deciding whether or not they can accept students from abroad they have taken into consideration the number from each country already in Egypt.As there are already 18 Kuwait students in Egyptian Government educational establishments,not counting those at Al Azhar,they feel that they can not increase the number without penalising other countries less fortunately placed.The Minister therefore could mot agree that the third Kuwait Mission should be sent. 1 This being the case it is unnecessary to appoint a supervisor for the boys already in Egypt.lt would in fact be Impossible to do this without giving offense to those under whose care the boys are.Both in Cairo and Tanta the schools are fortunate in having excellent Head Masters .Mr.Highwood of the British Council keeps in close touch with the boys so that there is no cause for concern for their welfare. i I have a proposal to put before the Committee which I will set forth in detail in a future letter.This is for the establish ment of a Hostel in Cairo run by the Kuwait Go^ernment.Other Governments do this and are thus able to send as many boys as they wish as the main problem of the Egyptian Government is that of accomodation.The Minister himself is ready to assist should the proposal be favoured by the Committee. 0\ I applied to Al Azhar University for the admitance of Khalid Ahmad al Jassar.lt is unlikely that he will be accepted as he has not the necessary qualifications.His Head Master does not in any case advise the move as he consiiders him an outstanding ptlipil.V Pag© 2 ISS IJi I received Sheikh Abdullah.fs letter of 19th. June 1944 when in Cairo.He asked me therein to purchase certain educational materials, I was unable to obtain any of them.Certain items were available in very small quantities but the prices were so high thfct I did not attempt to buy.e.g.I could have obtained a few Iwad pencils at about one Rupee each.Paper is unprocurable. The only items that I was able to find were v/hite chalk and the Gestetner Machine.I have asked the British Council to purchase the former and Sadeq Hamdi,the new Director, the latter. I enclose a bill for £E.41.750 from the British Council for Arabic books purchased on behalf of the Kuwait Government.Will you please settle this direct and send me a copy of your letter. N.Jackson Esq., Political Agent, Kuwait. II yPGDA/JK 1400/2/44 COr ■ • Kut /: BRITISH 0ATB0. 30th September, 1944. Sir, T have the honour to inform you at the request of the ^gyptain Government, that the Egyptian Ministry of Education has decided to terminate the delegation on a Teaching Mission to the Government of Kuwait of M. Ahmed Gawdat Osman, in view of this gentleman’s state of health, as from the 1st September, 1944. 2. The Egyptain Government request that this decision may he communicated to the Government of Kuwait. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your obedient servant, Sd- . The Hon’hie the Political Resident of the Persian Gulf, Kuwait.CONFIDENTIAL flo 3 &gt; • if The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon •hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document with the remark that the letter was opened here as it appeared to refer to Kuwait. A copy has 'been taken and action taken on it. POLITICAL AGENCY, KDWAIT * Date 1 Reference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTION OS’ ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject Letter No.1400/2/44 dated the 30th September, 1944 from Terence Shone, British Embassy, Cairo to the Hon'ble the Political Resident of the Persian Gulf, Kuwait. It. AHMED GAUDAT OSMANu D.O.430/30. CO ' y &gt;KN r riAL A/- &gt; ti. iteceipt Ba] rain. 'th. October 1944. !U \6^ The enclosed was handed to me only today.lt is a letter that I wrote to Sheikh Abdullah the day before I went into hospital.I handed it to my clerk for despatch to you for forwarding but he addressed it to Sheikh Abdullah himself in oahrain!Small wonder I waited in vain for the money.Please offer my apologies. N.Jackson Esq., Political Agent, Kuwait. K ..At/?--!;Telegram 7rom To No Political \gent, Kuwait Amilassador, Baghdad 7^ Dated 30th October, 1944. Kuwait Government have received telegram from / ^OSUL that two Egyptian teachers 3A3UR and THAJBIT en route to Kuwait to t^ke up appointments under the Kuwait Government have / ✓ / / ^ ^ been prevented from proceeding. Cause of hold up not stipulated. ^ x / j ' j Grateful for any assistance you can afford them. PoliticalD.0.1 j' 1944. Bahrain /y} V/ I (have recently received many urgent enquiries from the Books &amp; Periodicals Officer of the British Council,Cairo asking for the return of 27 green canvas hags in which school books, purchased by the Council on behalf of the Education Committee, were sent to Kuwait•They are numbered: 1329 to 1380 1597 to 1599 and 1993. I left the first consignment in Kuwait in April,the others were sent up by ship in May .Will you please make enquiries ano. let me know as soon as possible when the bags left Kuwait and by what route. N.Jackson Esq. IN . O • H.B.M.’s Pol tical Agent, Kuwait.I have received today a cable from Mr.Highwood of the British Council,Cairo saying: f Kuwait teachers awaiting visa permission your end 1 . I have sent off a cable this morning to you saying: f • •' * 4 . J 0 ’Egyptian teachers unable obtain Kuwait visas from Cairo* When I left Cairo the Personnel Department of the Ministry of ? • Education were arranging visas.I submitted a list of those teachers who wished to travel to Kuwait to the British Council for transmission to the Consulate,from whence application for visas would be made-to you. I presume that the teachers referred to are th6se recently • engaged by me,as the others would naturally provide themselves with entry visas before leaving Kuwait in June.I shall be very interested to hear exactly v/hen these men return.They went to Egypt at their own expense and on their own responsibility.A few of:.them called on me in Cairo but I saw little of them.Labibeh was the only one who asked for assistance in obtaining visas.The Council was able to obtain them for her.Although I can be in no way responsible for teachers under contract to the Kuwait Government who are on leave I was ready to give what assistance was in my power.I met Ali Salman and Tuhami in September and urged them both to return to Kuwait at once.Ahmad Dheif caused me considerable annoyance by appearing at my office on 7th.September saying that he was not returning.! pointed out to him that he had not given the required notice and that in March of this year he had definitely elected to stay.I referred the matter to the Ministry and he was instructed to return but nevertheless he wasted hours of my time in fruitless interviews and nearly drove me distracted by following me from door to door in the Ministry. P.T.Or* Bahrain D.0.442/30. 15 th.* Qc toher 1944* /C ^ \b2. '' t I enclose the statement of account of the students in Egypt,from which you will see that there is a sum of £E*52 owing to me. pay anything to the Head Master of the Tanta School for the boys f pocket money,and the sum\ left with the Head Master of the Saidieh School is sufficient for a few months only*At the beginning of each year there are certain items of expenditure such as health insurance etc.which total about £E.2 per boy.In all cases this was deducted from the sums paid to the schools on 1st.January 1944# Each Head Master is submitting a detailed statement to Mr.Highwood who will pass it on to me. the increase in Pocket Money.He is not in favour of any further increase.He is also much concerned about the large sums of money which are being sent to those boys who are being maintained by their parents.These boys have now opened bank accounts and the Head Master will control withdrawals strictly.They are to be allowed pocket money and other expenses at the same rates as the others. Parents who send such large sums must be prepared for the demoralisation of their sons.In certain cases boys have been caught smoking or breaking other school rules.In future deductions will be made from their pocket money as punishment.vVhether or not a boy receives the full £E.2 per mensem will depend on his behaviour. The last item of £E.63 represents my hotel expenses from 11th.to 27th.September 1944.My original intention was to leave for Bahrain on 12th.September and took a flat until the-llth The (..Minister did not give his decision concerning Sadiq Hamdi until 25th.September so that I was forced to stay on,together with my wife and family.This entailed the cancelling(and therefore the loss) of our plane passages through to Bahrain as well as considerable incidental expense.I therefore have no hesitation in asking the Committee to pay this especially in view of the fact that both last year and this I have spent the greater part of my leave working for the Kuwait Government in an honorary capacity. favour of the Director,The British Institute,Cairo on Barclays Bank,Cairo for Pocket Money for 10 boys @ £E.2 p.m. for 10 months. I will then forward this to Mr.Highwood who will pass it on to the Head Masters at Giza and Tanta. As my letter of 31st.July 1944 went astray I was unable to I spoke to the Head Master of the Saidieh School about Will you please let me have a draft for £E.200 in N.Jackson Esq., H.B.M f s Political Agent, Kuwait•Telegram ?rom To No H.M. AmlDassador, Baghdad Political Agent, Kuwait 27 L&gt;ated 1st received 2nd November, 19 Your telegram No.780 Tvo Egyptian teachers named were held up at NOSUL from October 22nd to October 28th owing to quarantine regulations in force in Iraq as a result of outbreak of Plague at They were allowed to proceed October 28th. H. ?r . Representative.T he first line of this telegram contains the following particulars in the order named : — Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and facial instructions—if any. 6/-184 Printed in England. Sept. 1#41. (1,200 pads) . ^ CABLE AND WIRELESS (MID-EAST) LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) VT82/E 3AHREIN 1 Q 2 1110 LC rOL I T I CAL KU.VA I T HAM D I LEAVING FOURTH TEACHERS LEFT THIRTTFIRST 'WAKEL I N MARK YOUR REPLY ‘2%a Jm/ieSua£ NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OP THIS COPY. REPLIES SHOULD BE HANDED IN AT ONE OF THE COMPANY'S OFFICES.&gt;~v His Majesty’s Consul at Damascus presents his compliments to the British Political Agent, Kov/eit, and has the honour to state that he has been informed by Mr. Adnan Aidi, Principal of the Ulmieh hi tanieh School in Damascus, that a certain Abdel Rahman Meshaan Ehoudair and a cei'tain Yacoub Youssuf Homaizi of Kov/eit have been registered in the English Section ol this school for the ad&amp;demic year 1944 - 1945. He requests the competent authorities to facilitate their journey to Syria. The Ulmieh Watanieh School has been helped in various v/ays by the British Council end there is no objection on the part of this Consulate to facilities being granted to th.ese young men to attend it. BRITISH CONSULATE, Diii. ^SCUS, 10t}' Cctober, 1944. //(21106) Wt.8673/807 5,000 4/42 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd Gp.685 ( (73 Minister His Majesty's Ambassador presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at IKo’weifc.. and has the honour to transmit herewith a copy of the under- 15th October, ic ^4 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Prom: R.E.M.F.A. No: 39.72/1 (374) Date: 9.10,44. Decision to terminate the mission of Aly Mo- hamed Heikal as Direc- of Education at Koweit as from 1st September, To: R.E.M.P.A. No: 379 Date : 15.10.44. 1944 .PGDA/GfB No. 380 14C0/J/44 His Majesty^ Aiabaaay prssaiit thsir compliments to the lioyal i^gyptian JJiniatry of Foreign Affairs anu aith reference to tlie Miniatry^s note No. 377 (39/7^A) of 9 th October, have the honour to inform them that the dueision of the Egyptian Ministry of Education to tenuinMte tho mission of iimud Cawdat Osman at howet as from let Oeptembur 1944 has been communicated to the Honourable The Political Aaoiaunt the Persian Gulf for the information of tho Govern ment of Koweit. His Majesty^ nmbaoey avail themselves ox’ tin is opi^ortunity to renew to the Hoyal i^yptian Ministry of * oioign Affairs the assurance of tliulr v^rj high consideration. HUITIJH mtihbY, CwIBO. IJth October, 1944cc:iyiparriAL 0. 769-J :iAL ,VM British Hesi CON FJO 1 the 11th i ^ j. -i- ^ J- x x ( Bushire British Residency &lt;§ Consulate General, Bushire, the 11th October 1044. 17^ x H rom. Ihe Hon’ble ~&gt;ir Geoffrey Prior, K.C.I.B., Ihe Hon’ble ^ir Geoffrey Prior, K.C.I Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BUJHIRE The Political A^enJtC OP,/AI T / 1 have the honour to say that I feel that insufficient support has been given in the past by your Agency to the British Council Representative, and that steps should be taken in future to see that he has expert advice i* Loth forming his plans and in handling the'Ruler and the Educational Committee. was not very happy, but there can be no doubt about the importance of this work and the necessity for ensuring that the British Council Representative is given the fullest support until either a whole time Educational Adviser is appointed or tne administration of Kuwait is placed on a more organised basis. 3. The British Council Representative will inevitably be ignorant oi Kuwait and its.politics and will almost certainly be unfamiliar with the appropriate method of dealing with Oriental rulers. I would be glad if you would make it your duty to see that the fullest guidance and support is given to him in future: He should be encouraged to explain his intentions in advance and advice should be given him as to the best method of attaining his ends. If his proposals appear unwise he should be informed of this, and*if he appears reluctant to accept advice a resort should be made to this Residency. The inception of the British Council scheme in Kuwait A copy of this despatch should be placed on the handing over file of your Agency. Bir, Your most obedient servant, I have the honour to be, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Th* firtt line ot this I eiegram contains the following particulars in the order named : — Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Cy'ce of Origin Number of Words, Date, Time handed In and Official ins xc’ians—if any. 5/-184 Printed in England. Sept. lf&gt;41. (1,200 pads) CABLE AND WIRELESS (MID-EAST) LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) 'VT34/S BASRAH 28 14TH 14 EJAT 3G IMMEDIATE IMMEDIATE PULITICAL KUWAIT H'AMDIE 3E V HAMDI EGYPTIAN E DUCAT I UN ADVISER AND WIFE LEAVING FUR KUWEIT 1400 HOURS TUESDAY / BRITCUNSUL MARK YOUR REPLY Tba '?7n/ie?ua&amp; NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OP THIS COPY. REPLIES SHOULD BE HANDED IN AT ONE OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.The firit line of this I eiegram contains the following particulars in the order named Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin Number of Words, Date, Time handed In and Official instructions—if any. Printed in England. Sept. (1,200 pads) CABLE AND WIRELESS (MID-EAST) LIMITED. 5/—184 (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) ,1MED I AITEL f VT57/3 BASRAH 3 I 14 1710 IMMEDIATE BGOVT ET IMMEDIATE PUL I T I,CAL KUWAIT F|jR SADDIQ HE V HAUDI DID NUT REPEAT NUT LEAVE/KUWAIT tudat tuesdav stop, understand he is awaiting car TO HE SENT FROM KUWAIT TO FETCH HIM CUN SUL GENERAL MARK YOUR REPLY Via ^Tri/ie^uaC NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION Of THIS COPY. REPLIES SHOULD BE HANDED IN AT ONE OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.from His Highness the'Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political Aje n t, Kuwait. In reply to your Letters Hos.32o # '526 iatei 16.10.44, in conneotion of the new Director .of Education ani his qualifications, the n e teachers, and Mr. '’/ak el in’s suggestions about the Education Mi ,9ion. I, therefore wish to inform you that I have instructed our Sdncitio&amp;'.Domiiito consider your ^ j ^e s t i n os in this respect, and I arr^ enclosi^c ^ our son Abdula al-Tabir, le + ter froVthe Head of Education Dspor^meot. The letter is self-explanatory. A dhefhe on the Kuwait, for Rs.56 /10/- in payment of the books ourchased by the Rr‘ ? ‘ M e v ' Council, onbehalf of the Kuwait Government is enclosei. Usual ^ndinyPrinted in England. Sept. 1»41. (1,200 pads) */-184 VTI67/S BAHRAIN 22 1 LC POLITICAL KUWAIT URGENT SEND HIGHWOOD 360 PuUNDS FOR TEARS MV LETTERS BRITlSH/INSTITUTE POCKET MONEV STOP CAIRO DRAFT PLEASE RE PL V WAKEL I N MARK YOUR REPLY Via Jjn/ieSuaCl NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION Of THIS COPY. REPLIES SHOULD BE HANDED IN AT ONE OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.Printed in .England. Sept. 1H41. (1,200 pads) 6/-184 VT48/Z CAIRO 13 RP 8 \ 00 POL I T I CAL M A V I GRANT VISA TE ACHER / 1 1 326 3G ETAT KIM A I I !SMA I L IBRAHIM CONSUL Z A ID EGYPTIAN MARK YOUR REPLY 'Via Jm/ieSUad NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY. REPLIES SHOULD BE HANDED IN AT ONE OF THE COMPANY'S OFFICES./&gt;? 9 Trie British Council presents its compliments to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and has the honour to forward herewith the Allocations for the benefit of Bahrain and Kuwait for the financial year 1944-45. The Council has increased its grant of £500 to £763 towards the salary of the Educational Adviser in Bahrain, Mr. F.J. V/akelin, which was increased to £1,068 gross as from 1st September, 1943. The sum of £100 has been included to cover the leave allowance to which dr. .Vakelin is entitled this year. The sum of £240 has ' . n inc i d‘if to cover the cost of a projector for which a request was made by Mr. V/akelin early this year. Geoffrey Prior, Political Resident, Persian Gulf. No.C/430. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, BAHRAIN, the 2nd November 1944, Copy forwarded with compliments to - 1) The Political Agent, BAiiRAIH . (with copy of all 2) The Political Agent, KUWAIT, (with copy of Kuwait enclosures) Allocations only)=? &lt;? c FORM AC1 RECURRENT ALLOCATIONS -Ze? THE BRITISH COUNCIL ALLOCATIONS FOR THE FI NANCIAL YEAR 1944/45 COUNTRY: KUWAIT ITEM ALLOCATION No. ACTIVITY at full yearly rate PERSONNEL £ SALARIES (Schedule PS2) Subsidised Posts Locally Appointed A 1 Teachers 1,500 THE BRITISH COUNCIL. SCHEDULE PS2 LOCALLY APPOINTED ALLOCATIO NS FOR APPROVED POSTS FOR THE FINANCIAL YEAR 1944/45 COUNTRY: KUWAIT ITEM No. POST GROSS SALARY at full SUBSIDY at full yearly rate yearly rate A 1 KUWAIT GOVERNMENT British Teachers / £ 1500 to to to(26396) Wt.47328/942 5,000 1/44 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 Vf / 3 . 5 (1400/9/44gter ' &gt;oV His Majesty’s Ambassador presents his compliments to The Political Resident in the » Persian Gkilf, xt. ^ Koweit. and nas the honour to transmit herewith a copy of the under mentioned paper. *i~*l British Embassy, Cairo. 7th November vrint. . Reference to previous correspondence : ^^^ oooooooooooooo Description of Enclosure. \ Name and Date. From: Royal Egyptian Ministry of Foreign affairs. No.431 of 7/11/44. To ditto Note No. 421 (1400/9/44) of 7/11/44. Subject. I.I. Zeid is being sent to Noweit on educational mission. .uthori- ses gratis visas, and advise Govt, of Koweit.PREVENT MISTAKES ATTENTION IS CALLED TO THE IMPORTANCE OF LEGIBLE WRITING. Printed in Karachi August 1944 (200 pads). CABLK AM) WIKKLKSH (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.') No. cial .ructions Charge. Via Imperial” IN U . Words Time OFFICE STAMP AND DATE Instructions to be Signalled. 7 9^ LIMITKD. % 9oy Clerk’s Name, No. and Circuit and Time forwarded. • To iVmne BRITCONSUL Addfess _ CAIRO YOUR T^LilGRAM NOYEUjIBER 21ST NC OBtTCCTICN YOUR ORANTINO KU;7AIT VISA FOR ISMAIL IBRAHIM ZAID TEACHERCONDITIONS. 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram i° or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose: but in such easf&gt; the amount paid for transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in .the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their 'respective officers or servants shall be liable to make cormwnnation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through what ever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Compaii} or Administration or any officer or servant m their employ. 3. -This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or trovernment Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other •means whatsoever. NOTE .—Code word* vned in the text of telegram# must, not contain more than 5 letters. Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged &gt;o produce the rode from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origtn. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containang figures and letters, are used in rode telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text an&lt;i signature. Full information respecting roar t.etetjrnms may be obtained from any of the Company's Branches.EXPRESS LETTER (AIR VERNMENT OF INDIA ^ Department, Deuel [N.B.— Th.%8 is an ORIGINAL message sent by AW MAIL which provides a means of communication more Middle Last, Cairo, with refaronce to his memorandum No. :5LALI/l/l da tod 2nd October 1914 r*r\ 1 i F 1 r* o 1 . 4 ri Bahrain and Kuwait for the financial year 1945/1946 prepared by the British Council Hepresentative in the Middle Last. 2. I approve generally of the estimates. Aith regard to item C I the question of the provision by the Bahrain and Kuwait Governments of a hostel at Cairo for their students is being pursued with the two Governraents. expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, viith the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] aa /rom The Hon*ble the Politic*! Resident Pers to H.M f s Principal Secretary of Gtate for Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office, London yonr ^y- Kepea ted The British Council Hepreaent&amp;fciv© in the Copy Is enclosed of the proposed estimates for Gd. GLOPKHKY PHIOR POLITICAL HKSIDLST, P£KoIAN GULF A XIL .j i i.‘ i) for secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. DLG? S. {Signature) S. 44 MFP—1015 S&amp;P—(M-1870}—9-2-39—20,000. {Designation--- . Item No. A 1 B 1 C 1 THE BRITISH COUNCIL ESTIMATES FOR APPROVED POSTS FOR THE FINANCIAL YEAR 1945/46 COUNTRY: PER SIA!. GULF (BAHRAIN) Post. Basic salary at full yearly rate Subsidy at full yearly rate BAHRAIN GOVERN’.MT SUBSIDISED STAFF Educational Adviser TECHNICAL STAFF Educational Adviser ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF Supervisor of Persian Gulf Students in Cairo 806 525 525 1050 806 £1586a FORM EC2 NOW RECURRENT ESTIMATES o't THE BRITISH COTOJCIL ESTIMATES FOR THE FINANCIAL YEAR 1945/46 COONTRY: PERSIA N GULF (BAHRAIN) — 1944/45 A B ITEM No. ACTIVITY Original Revised allocation, expej 1945/46 Estimated expenditure. A 1 Projectors and Epidiascopes Projectors 240 240 (240) (£240) /NExplanatory Notes to the 1945/46 Allocations for PERSIAN GULF (BAHRAIN) EORM EC1 - RECURRENT ALLOCATIONS PERSONNEL Salaries Items A1 and B1 See notes on Schedule PS1. Allowances GX - Lo.S..? a I. l AlJ,owanc? This is calculated at 85 per cent* (Bahrain rate of local allowance) of the basic salary plus 85 per cent, of the marriage allowance item in the case of Item PSl/Bl, and 60 per cent* (Egypt rate of local allowance) of the basic salary plus 60 per cent, of the marriage allowance item in the case of Item PSl/Cl. In both cases the allowances have been calculated at full rates, although in the event of furnished quarters or other indirect remuneration being provided an adjustment of the rates of local allowances will be required. In the case of the Adwiser designate (PSl/kl), It may be anticipated that free furnished quarters will be provided by the Government of Bahrain when he takes over from the outgoing Adviser, if not at an earlier date. Columns B and C have been left blank in Form EC1, as, for reasons stated in Schedule PS1, a supplementary allocation may be required in respect of PSl/Bl in the 1944/45 financial year. It, era C2 - Marriage Allowance This is calculated at one-eighth of the basic salaries shown in PSl/Bl and Cl. Columns B and C have been left blank as a supplementary allocation may be required in 1944/45 in respect of PSl/Bl. General Services Item D1 - Leave Allowance Provision has been made for the allowance to be paid to a married official and his wife at £50 each. The outgoing Adviser Mr. Wakelin, will not qualify for the allowance from the British Council in 1945/46. asaEiaaE, psi* mm App pm ap s iaff It will be noted that financial provision has been made in these estimates for the presence in Bahrain of two Educational Advisers in 1945/46. Arrangements are in hand for the replacement of the present Adviser, Mr. Wakelin, by another Council official next year. It would, however, be desirable for Mr. Wakelin's successor to proceed to Bahrain several months before Mr. Wakelin's departure, in order to ensure a satisfactory take-over. Item A1 - Subsidised Staff This post is at present occupied by Mr. Wakelin, and will presumably continue to be occupied by him for salary purposes until his contract with the Government of Bahrain terminates in September 1945. His present gross salary, towards which the Government of Bahrain contributes £300 per annum, is £1068.15s.6d. per annum. On the assumption that he will receive a normal increment of £20 basic salary as from 1st September, 1944, his gross emoluments from that date • • • •2 ■«*&gt; date will be £1106.5s.Od. per annum, increasing the Council's contribution to £806.5s.0d. per annum. It will be seen, there fore that a supplementary allocation of £22 under PS1/A1 of the Persian Gulf allocations for 1944/45 is required to cover the increase for the remainder of the current financial year. When Mr. Wakelin's contract with the Government of Bahrain expires in September. 1945, it is assumed that the unexpended portion of the allocation under Item A1 of these estimates will be used to pay the subsidy towards his successor's salary until the end of the 1945/46 financial year. Any adjust ment to the rate of the subsidy necessitated by the appointment of a successor whose gross Council emoluments differ from those of Mr. Wakelin can only be made after the event. Consideration has already been given in London to the possibility of requesting the Government of Bahrain to increase their present contribution of £300 towards the salary of the Educational Adviser, but a decision on this point has not yet been reached. Iten B1 - Technical Staff This allocation has been proposed in order to cover the basic salary of Mr. Wakelin's successor for the period of overlap during which there would be no contribution from the Government of Bahrain and the British Council would therefore be expected to accept full financial responsibility for the Adviser designate. An allocation would not be needed after the date that the Adviser designate officially took over from the outgoing Adviser. If, as would be desirable, a successor is appointed before the conclusion of the current financial year, a supplementary allocation would be required in the 1944/45 financial year. The usual allowances for this post have been provided for in Form EC1. Item Cl - Administrative Staff. It is hoped that, as from September, 1945, it will be possible to appoint a Supervisor for Persian Gulf students studying In Cairo at schools or universities. This appointment will pre sumably be dependent on the provision of a hostel by the Bahrain and/or Kuwait Governments, with suitable accommodation for a resident English Supervisor or Warden. The number of students involved would be approximately 80. Provision has been made in the estimates for the appoint ment of such official entirely at the Council's expense. It Is possible, however, that the post would be partially subsidised by the Government concerned, in which case the allocations would require adjustment. The usual allowances for this post have been provided for in Form EC1. FORM EC2 - Hon Recurrent Estimates See notes on Schedule EXT. - iffCT RAPE D I K AR JJj S An allocation for the purchase of a cinema projector in 1945/46 is proposed on the assumption that the allocation granted for this purpose in 1944/45 remains 'unspent owing to non availability of a projector. If the purchase is not made in 1944/45 • • •1944/45 there will be a saving of £240 under EXT/A1 of the 1944/45 allocations. The entry in Column D of Form EC2 has been placed in brackets to denote that the allocation is contingent upon an equivalent saving in 1944/45.THE BRITISH COUNCIL ESTIMATES FOR THE FINANCIAL YEAR 1 COUNTRY: KUWAIT C\ i 0 c/J ^ FORM EC1 RECURRENT ESTIMATES ITEM No. ACTIVITY 1944/45 1945/46 B Original Revised Commit- Estimated alloca- expend!- ment at expenditure tion. ture. full at full yearly yearly rate rate. A 1 sm smsk SALARIES (SCHEDULE jaaT Subsidised Posts Locally Appointed Teachers 1500 250 1500 400 £400Explanatory Notes to the 1945/46 Estimates for Kuwait&gt; m M ,m - mq ww i? ALLa c moM-i: PJSR SO MBL See notes on Schedule PS2. Item A1 In the 1944/45 allocations there was a grant of £1500 for the purpose of subsidiesing, if necessary, the salaries of Egyptian teachers seconded by the Egyptian Government to Kuwait. The Governraent of Kuwait has not requested any financial support in this connection, and the salaries of the teachers are shared equally by the Egyptian Government and the Governnuant of Kuwait. It is not now anticipated that the latter will apply to the Council for financial assistance in this respect. view that the appointment of a whole-time British Educational Adviser to Kuwait would be premature at this stage, and he has suggested instead the appointment of an Egyptian Educational Adviser. Steps are therefore being taken in Cairo at present for the selection of a suitable man on a two-year contract. The Egyptian Government would be expected to contribute 50 per cent, of his salary and it has been suggested by the Political Resident that the balance should be provided by the British Council. the expenditure from the grant under PS2/A1 during the current financial year would be not more than £250, and the recurrent commitment would be £400. A saving of £1250 can therefore be declared on PS2/A1 of the 1944/45 allocation, and the entry in Column B of Form EC1 has been adjusted accordingly. The Political Resident recently expressed the If final approval for the appointment is given/*//» ' Telegrsml From® To® No. 2203. Dated the 9th December 1944. Political Resident Persian Gul£j Bushire® H.M« Ambassador# Cairo. / «/ From Political Resident Persian Gulf for British Counci !• Your mem or an sum No.MEALl/l/l October 2nd 1944. Please confirm that Council will provide £400 half 800 per annum for Egyptian Educational Adviser at Kuweit. PRIOR. C 2 TI'I ^NTJAl Office of the Political Resident N O® 8 ^ 6 -S Persian Gulf# Bushire # dated the 9th December 1944. Copy forwarded with compliments to#s . ' 2 Mi 'BRITISH C0KSULATB-G3NSRAL 3 . ° BASRA. 15th Deceiober 1944* Dear Agency, The following is an account of expenses with vouchers, incurred hy us on behalf of His Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait, in meeting A.3. Hamdi Bey, Education Officer, Kuwait, and making arrangements for his onward journey to Kuwait. Date. Particulars. Axfiount. ID,fils. 14 .11 • 44. Cost of an unnumbered telegram the Political Agent, Kuwait. to 1,364 ii Cost of an unnumbered telegram the Political Agent, Kuwait. to ,792 16 . 11 . 44 - Taxi hire as per voucher. * o o o Total = I.D. 3,156 No. 2476. (5A/11) / 2. ,7e shall be grateful if you will obtain the refund of this ‘amount from His Excellency the Shaikh in due course.So. C/6b-4/13 Political Agency., “ it Kwai. . The 18th December 1945. . From. To. The Political Agent, Kuwait The British Conneii # Oairro. Sir, / / \ I have the honour to enclose herewith a draft for £E 41.750 heing the cost of 'books purchased hy you on hebalf of the Kuwait (ro verarncnt. Please acknowledge receipt. I have the honour to oe, Sir, your most obedient servant fv/ Political Agant, Kuwait eje^/ H|l 1 jWf, D.O.No.539/30 Gov or nine nt of Bahrain, EducatiOn Department. 3 ■U KeC 2ZZ 1944. Dear Jackson, /7wfjf /y//.2^_ j (^ y I enclose a bill for £E.41.Vo$ payable by the Kuwait Education Department to the British Council,Cairo,which has been outstanding since May .1944.This is the third time that it has been presented.! sent the first two to you on 6 th.June and 3 rd.October 1944.Kill you please se- that this bill is \ paid at once. Yours sincerely, N.Jackson Esq., Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy to:Chief Accountant,British Council,Cairo.Tel. 49426 MIDDLE EAST OFFICE, KABBANI BUILDING, 138, SHARIA FUAD EL AWAL ZAMALEK, CAIRO. 27th November ,o 4 4 F. J • in i /U~v V Director Of Education- Bahrein Dr. to THE BRITISH COUNCIL To account rendered as per our D/l/KOW/j dated 2 2nd June and I5th August 19^» amount to be collected from H.B.M. Politi- -cal Agent Koweit. Accountant Books Department a. B.Kanarian. L.E. 41. ***** M/ms, 7902 . 1 st.jiov£moe£.l$ 44 , from H/s Hi^h &lt;ess the Ruler of Kuwait, to th4 Polat ^gent, Kuwait. f^Xfl /? a°\ icentd&gt;— ^ Translation of letter No.R. 6 .date! the Uj/ ‘com. li/s - aI 'gent r i r^*— After Conpl I wish to acknowledge the receipt of your letters Nos. C/3b4,355,356 ^ 357 dated 7 / 11/44 together with the eo 1 f ^nd hafe fully under stood all what was -nentioned therin about the Education Department and wish to thank; you for th^t. I, therefore am enclosing a letter in original which I received from our son Abdulla al-Jabir in reply to the suggestions and opinions of Mr. Wakelin, and t .e letter is self explanatory. Usual Ending.Tr-'inalation of letter dated 20.11.44, from Kuera.it Education department, Kuait.to His Highness the Ruler of ' TTnwn.i t. After Complinents, I have the honour to give the replies to the letters received by Your Highness from the Political Agency as follows* Ref. Letter no C/354 of 7 .ii.44 j i n connection with the I T r&gt; I /i m el ay o l h4-s letter addressed t-yne and for vhichy^pe asks to be excused, I wsih to state that I have accepted his excuse and wish to thank him for that. . 2 . o % Ref. Letter Eo.C/359^of 7.H. 44 ,in which Mr. .Vaxelin advises us to avoid ^e repeatingof what has haooened this Egyptian year and how the/teachers were delayed and could not come in time. The Commi t tee'-will take all the necessary steps to prevent the occurance of sucK delay. ^y 1 3. Reference letter .No.C/356^f 7.11.44, regarding the empty bags in which the school books were sent by the British Council,and which the Council wants us te return, I wish to inform Your Highness that the empty bags of the two consign ments were sent to the Political Agency by Ali HaiKal, the former Director ot Education. They were twenty seven bags 0 4. to the balance of the account due to Mr. Wakelin according to his bill and which amounts to £5. E.Pounds, I am enclosing a draft on the Kuwait in favour of the Political Agent. But as .to the 200 Pounds,which Mr. Wakelin has asked as a new fund for the Mission, this has been post poned untill Mr. Wakelin comes here. 5. I had informed Your Highness that the Education Dept. Egyptian had decided to enforce the rule against the/teachers who were late and to deduct (certain amount ) from their salaries, I, now wish to inform Your Highness that the Committee have decided to excuse them , and all the others,too. Usual ^nding.D* 0,No.585/30. Government of Bahrain, 27th.December 1944. i. -/?-/« i. . /ro25. Lb. )$! 3 - / 6^ 5. Please refer to my letters of: /, ? 16 • 9*44 re Kuwait schoolboys./ 9.44 No.40C/30 re the new Director.,/ 10.44 No.401/30 re the Director, &amp; a bill of £E.41.750. X 10.44 No.430/30 re a letter for Sheikh Abdullah./ 10.44 No.442/30 re pocket money for students and a claim for expenses. / V - . 44 - Q • 450/30 re visas for teachers v/ishin^ to travel from 10.44 No.460/30 re canvas bags belonging to the British Council/ -^'oc. 7 '• j-• 4'i No. 539/30 re the bill for OE. 41.750 outstanding since -/ . 4'i ^ ^rf./A/Cn, c « 2 . the the the and my telegrams: 10.44 re the Director./ 10.44 re visas for. teachers. . 11.44 re the Director/^ 11.44 re pocket money for students in Egypt./ I nave not yet received even acknov/ledgement of anr of above. The only intimation that I have had of the arrival of mumcbOi 1 vvho.:&lt; I engaged on behalf of the Committee was from oroadcast of the Kuwait Letter. /.• „ The assistance given to the Kuwait Education Committee e,y the British Council has been considerable. If this help *s to increase or even to continue it is essential that I be kept -wormed of vhat is going on in the Depart lent. \,hether or hot the Council hill prepared to continue keep a watch on the students -ail-c and ant depends on the readiness i.ith which the pocket T / y ® x P en ses of the schoolboys is paid by the Committee. ' - Pg-sg/he. Council ns accepted considerable financial responsxjiu. _ v on behalf of the Kuwait Education Depart ent at my tLL \ h; providing for instance £.400 for fares,purchasing several . ndi-eas of pounds worth of books and paying pocket mone^- to the students when the funds from Kuwait havemrun low. I shall not be S he' aSk fo rd heii ' t8lp in « uch ^ters unless I E Z r -' - .in . .fat sufficient monej has been sent to y a I the fort n?hn 0 cover wotet money and incident? 1 expenrH up to iii March i 044 t**'*? 0 onao the bill for b 1 purchased what^eLEha^d® 6 ? / d - ? an yo« Please let me know when and bv J °‘ ini3 ' JU ° 3rifeiSil Council canvas bags were sent back to Cairo-. / r/ nogyot beL C mp? Tie ^ /h/ch the e 8neroslt y of the British'council”^ and' back being ^id —&lt; tr&lt;X L to Kv 3lt sunncv''ie&lt;.'v js^ dealing^with Caif^r^L^^^ 3 ^ 0 na L ° considerable inconvenience. 1 J - 3 ^Page 2. 5• I have not yet been able to visit Ku' alt this school year o v .ing to pressure of work. As soon as circumstances'pennit I shall do so. Meanwhile I shall be glad to have your comraents on the work of the new Director and information on the points that I have referred to in the above. Yours sincerely. N.Jackson Esq., Y.B.U's Political Agent, Kuwait.\ i i f- J.O.No. ^'^3. R)liticul Agency, .^.u’ u i t # (2 33/ 25th January, 1945. My dear Wakelin, k Please refei' to your demi-official letter Mo,505/50 4' dat d the 27th Jecember, 1944, jUN^ Tour demi-official letters of the 2, / v Tour demi-official letters of the 1st toptenbcs and No.442/30 of the 15th October and your telegram of the 7th November, 1944, were passed on to His Highness. A draft for JBJ5.337 was sent on the 29th November for pocket money for the boys up to December, 1944, and to meet the cost of winter clothing. This included sums for the boys whose education is paid for by their parents. I have today seen Shaikh .vbdulloh and explained to him the inconvenience caused to Mr. iiighwood by money not bein^ sent in advance, and he has now promised to send a farther draft to ’ r. Hi^nwood to cover pocket money up to the end of the school year, - 3, £3.41,750 asked for in your deml-offiolel letters Mos,40l/30 and 539/30 doted the 3rd October and the 3rd December, 1944, Y/as paid to British Jouncil, Oairo, 9 y \A 4, Your letters Nos,400/30 and 450/30 dated the 25th September and the 16th October, 1944, together with your telegrams dated the 2nd October and the 2nd November were passed on to His Highness, I enclose a cheque for j, 702/-, the equivalent of ££•52, the bn lance outstanding on account of your expenses. Arrangements have now been made for teachers to get visas for their return to Kuwait before they iea*e here, and steps are being taken to help new tescliers to get visas for Kuwait without delay. Action to obtain visas for the teachers had already been taken before your telegram of the 16th October was received. \VA 5, Your letter to Shaikh Abdul Idh which formed the enclosure to your deni-offiolel letter No.430/30 dated the 11th October was forwarded to him. , ^ A 6. The green canvas bags referred to in your demi-official letter No.460/30 dated the 16th October were sent to British Jouncil, Cairo, through the Director of the British Institute, Basrah, on the 27th June, 1944. 7. I agree with you that the new Director seems to be a very superior person, and congratulate you on securing him. 'haikh Abdullah has done his best to accommodate him suitably and has pi.ced a new builaing at his disposal, which I think is the Lest that can be none at the moment. He is getting down to his work and has lots of ideas. He is at present engaged in trying to get suitable stationery for general subjects, and other equipment required to teech domestic find scientific subjects; and I hope that the goods will be on the way by the time you get here. 8. I hope you will be able to fit in a visit fairly soon to see how things are going, and also to discuss your project for c hostel in Cairo, cheikh Abdullah has reserved tnis subject for discussion on your next visit. Yours sincerely, F.J. -akelin, bsquire, Director of. ilucation, B H „ I M. /W[MEALL/I/15/6 The British Council, Middle liast Office, Sharia Fuad el Awal, Zantalek, Cairo. 18th December, 194d Lt • j 1 : yji Dear Sir, Ni /if This iS/Xo confirm cable of 16th December, in answer to your 2203 of 9th December as follows 'UNaBLE CONFIHLI COUNCIL WILL PROVIDE £400 HALF £8000 PER ANNUM FOR EGYPTIAN EDUCATIONAL ADVISER AT KUWAIT.' It is understood that our London office has already written ( December 2nd ) to Mr. Wakelin, Director of Education, saying that u there is at the moment no question of the Council making a grant of £.400/- p.a. as a contribution towards the Director^ salary. It is understood, further, that this decision was reached in consultation with the Foreign Office. Yours faithfully, Sd/- C.G. BIdwell. The Political Resident, Government of Bahrain, Persian Gulf. CONFIDENTI iiJU EL 74-i British Residency Sc Consulate-General, Bushire, the 16th January 1946 Copy forwarded with compliments to:- The Political Agent, KUWAIT . in continuation of Residency Endorsement No. 933-S dated 21st December, 1944Translation ot letter iatei 22/2/64(545) from the K’rvai t T5&lt;1noation -^ept . ,Kn^a j t , to Mr. Highwooi, Cai ro. After Conpli y nents. be wish to iraw /our attention to the following P o i n i s: - 1. We have rentittei to you telegraphically 360 through theftJirclaya Bank, fan the expenses of the second Mission for a period of six nonths, bejinninj from 1st January,1946 to to th c end of June 1946. TEe are enclosing a s'atenent of the names of the students of the 2nd Mission. 3. Pay each student -3 per nensuai( accordinj to the decission reached by the Council) fro Pocket Money. 4 . Total amount of pocket money for the 6 months will be 288 . 5. There will be a balance of this is for mee- tinj the school exoenses for the special Mission and other necessary expences for the members of the seco^^ TT i v^ion. 6. be have instructed the student, Aodulaziz Husain, of Hijh Training Institution at Jeeza, to communicate with and receive the monthly allowance for all the students. This will make the ratter easier, and he will be able to distribute the money apainst receipts signed by each one of them.. n , I request that each member of the Mission should sij,n for the amounts he received from you. These will be^kept by the Kuwait Education Dept, for the purpose of payment. Usual Ending. ft The telegram re*’^~ r * c ‘'* to was sent on 6.2.46.u ^.0,116/30. /y, Bahrain. ‘ ^/i 0th.February 1045. if - -y 27$ - ' XHo 2-^3 Thank you for your D.O.'~o. /2-&lt;-/l3 of f ~th. • T lua.'y 1945, enclosing the draft for '..702/- being the equivalent of £2.52,the balance outstanding on account oi ray expenses. 2 . I note that a draft for £E.R37 was sent to Mr.t- T ishvood on 29th.November 1014 and that a further one is to be sent soon, .ill you pxer s i ask Sheikh . bdull ah to inform me when this i done. 3 . I also note that the outstanding balance owiny to the British Council for books purchased on behal ‘ o the fuwsit Education Department was paid on 3rd.December 1 0 . 1.4 and th- t the tne Director of°the British Institute, Basrah, on 0 7th., T une l n 44. 4 . 1 mn rlad to know that the nei Director settling down to his work. I can appreciate the fact- that, he is having difficulty in obtaining equipm.nh for the schools, e have tried from several sources but so fur have had no success. 5 # if it is convenient to you and to Sheikh Abdullah I should like to visit Kuwait after our Sprin- holiday vhich ends oh 2 nd.March. I can not come before as ro organising a school ci i ip clurin that 1 eek. I h ive he arc th t th e: araina 4 ion-, begin on•2nd.larch in Kuwait so this should be a good time to come as I have not yetnsebn the schools at examination time. I shall not 1 ait for ship but try to fly to B sr h . n th n motor down. 0 . j^le-se give ray respectful sal • s to TT is Highness . and remember me to Sheikh 1 bin Jabar• ■.‘.•ill you please ps ss the enclosed note on to oikh Abdu ?.’’ 1 al ; obi r. 1 , 0 . . .. T+ ' is a letter Congratulating lira on his recent award.TO PREVENT MISTAKES ATTENTION IS CALLED TO THE IMPORTANCE OF LEGIBLE WRITING Printed in Karachi Aantwt 1#44 (iJOO pads). CABI-K AND WIKELKStS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND,) No. Charge. OFFICE STAMP AND DATE Clark’s Name, No. and Circuit •I and Time forwarded. Official (. Instructions • Via Imperial” No. Words Time Instructions to' be Signalled. , T O Name ifAXSlIS) « Address ^ BAHTtAIN USB 0.0. ilg/»o T ^ T* l r \ G(^T V ?T’W’ ^TJ *Ofr&amp; TO FTT^AIT nA;?CH SlvCON'u TTO? YOTT 30 NOT DELAY VISIT AS SHAIKH Af.jDtLLA JABIH IS GOING TO INDIA IN SECOND W*m IN MARCH * POLITICAL I request that the above Telegram may lie forwar led subject ta the ro ditioes priutod on back of this farm by which I agree to lie bound. Signature of Sender Telephone \o. Address (Not to be telegfaphed) V T. O.CONDITIONS. 1. Tbe Company or any Telegraph Company or (Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service he forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose; but in such caSe the amount paid for transmission will be refunded to the sendwr at his request. 2. Neither tlie Company nor any Telegraph Company, or (Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this .telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic servich be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of telegrapi, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery ther&lt;;Af, j tJi^ougA what ever cause such non-transmission, non-delivory, delay, .orror, or ^mission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or deAi^lf hf TOch Company or Admj^jjpratiou or.^ny pffic^r or servant m tlmm emp^y. ^ ^ 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance witfi tile provisions of the f TnterrthtihtdO Telelrrnph Eegnlfitions and the ‘prrtVisiotts’of inch Reg'SIStions shall he deemed to he binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company 13 JY Y ATKT fr Ca*e&gt;^nenfOP'elegriiph Administratiou by whom'This telegrahi') ie ‘or wonM in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. Aian,. t.i above mentionefM conditions also nppl v to i'•Ingrams' tendered to or delivered, by the Company by teleplume, oy(‘r a private Jine, m-. l^any other means whatsoever. I A’ 5.8 NOTE.—Coda words used in fha text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The 'Jsc aJ r 'dO£ejifhd'letters is not permitted in code words. By International Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been com) iled, if requested by the office of origin. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing ligures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European ilestinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with th» Rules for charging must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and^ signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may hr obtained from any of the Company's Branches. • ^Praflx Letters and Number of Mr , Office of Origin Number of Words. Date, Time handed In and O. i Instructions—if any. Printed in England. Sept. 1#41. (1,200 pads) • CABLE AND WIRELESS (MID EAST) LIMITED. 5/-184 r {INCORPORATED IN EMC LAND.) Clerk'a — Time Name. Received. V FE H . A . 1410 /_ V T1 LC FL H AND 25/^ BAHRAIN 14 22 1 POLITICAL KUWAIT INC BASRAH TWE NT TEIGHTH OR FIRST MOTOR I NS KUWAIT NEXT DAT' WAKEL I N MARK YOUR REPLY SnyieruajC NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION Of THIS COPY. REPLIES SHOULD BE HANDED IN AT ONE Of THE COMPANY’S OfHCES.Ne./f/ -4/13. The Political Agency, Kuwait. The 26th February, 1945. Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No. 2476 0//4/11) dated the 15th December, 1944 and to send herewith a Bank draft for 3.156 Dinars on account of expenses incurred by you on behalf of His Highness the Shaikh of Kuwait on meeting A.S. Hamii Bey, Director of iSddcation, Kuwait. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. I have the honour to be, Political Agent, Kuwait. t B. M ? s Consul G-eneral,jl Mo. O/^'J Political Agency, Kuwait The 26th February, &lt;2£^ 1945. His Hi^ineas, Shaikh Sir Ahmei all Jabir As-3ubah, K03I*, ;&lt;OIiSe, Ruler of Kuwait* &gt;-J*k I —a:* fi jP LiaJ Lj ^Jm Jj 1 if J 1 v-At 1 * .y-* 1 u' /-‘^ t ~‘0 WJ^ * p^ 1 if j ^Wy-*- 1 , - sli After CompliwentG, I have the honour to inform Tour Highness that Hr. Wakelin will fly to Basra on the 28th February or tho 1st March and is expected to motor to Kuwait the next day. Usual Boding, Political Agent, Kuwait.CONFIDENTIAL. M &lt;7 The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). 1* Note from Embassy Cairo dated 26th December 1944 with enclosures. 2. Cairo letter No. 642/2/45 dated 30th January, 1945. with enclosure. ♦ The Political Agent, for necessary action. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated....17.t.U.Eeb^hary,..^145 Reference to previous correspondence: * V Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject.INo. 4 (185/1/46) ills Majesty's Embassy present their complimen to -the Royal Egyptian Ministrey of Foreign Affairs and with reference to the Ministry's Note No. 507 ( 39.73.1) of the 36th December, 1944, have the honour to inform then that the enclosures destined for the Egyptian teachers delegated for service at Aden, and Lahej and at Kuwait and Bahrain are being communicated to His Excellency the Governor of Aden and to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf respectively for onward transmission. opportunity to renew to the Royal Egyptian Ministry ' of Foreign Affairs the assurance of their very high His Majesty’s Embassy avail themselves of this consideration. BRITIBII E MB A3 BY CAIRO 4th January, 1845642/2/45 tr/jj BRITISH EMBASSY CAIRO. 2&lt;£6 30th January, 1945 Sir, I have the honour to transmit herewith a copy of Note No. 33 dated 25th January, 1945, from the Egyptian Minis try of Foreign Affairs requesting that Ahmed Sadek Kamdi who is delegated for an educational mission'in Koweit, be inform ed that he should transmit a receipt proving that he has paid to the Directorate of Religious Institutes the sum of £E. 174. 269m/ms. in respect of arrears of pension contributions during the period of his temporary service in the Religious Institutes i.e. up to 1st September, 1944. 7 * 2 . May the above message please be conveyed to ilimed Sadek Hamdi, provided that you see no objection ? I have the honour to be Sir Your obedient Servant KILLCAl The Political Resident PERSIAN GULF.'MOV.from H.H. the Ruler of Kuwait, Vjent, Kuwait. Translation of Letter No.R.6.2643 iated 11 . 2 . 45 , H.H. the Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political xtff After GompLim.ent lUo Our Educatio frartmeut requires a rrintin^ machine,Jestetanor, together with its equioraents, an i wish to £$et it from Egypt. This machines is to to order some bocks an; maps required for the schools, as it is stated in the attioVv list. I request you kindly to coBraunicat° with + he authorities cono r ^r'ed in Cairo and ask them to permit the purchase and export of the machine, bocks I hope that these will be obtained through your *ind assistance. be used by the said department. The Dept, also wishSTdiji./iKM’ OF THE BOOKS HE^UIREO BY \U^LT EDUCATION JjiiP.anl-cE.NT ANU iv ILL bn, OctDBiRED t&gt; nO&gt;A TnE h .si INI STttl OF ED UCA TION I: A IE OF THE BOOtC eSc SUBJECT. NUMBEL OF THE COPIES L ’ikU IR E D» School Books for r he Primary schools. 150 copies of each book sanctioned for the four years. School books for the Secondary schools. 50 copies of each book sanctioned for the four years.(Education Period.) Horae Ecoonoriios fof* Female Education. 100 copies of each book sanctioned for each of the four years. House koeoinr‘ • 100 copies of each book sanctioned for each of the four years.(Female Education.) Cleaning, Washing and Ironin T . • 1 00 copies of each book sanctioned f1 or each of the three years.(Embroide ry Arts.) Child Welfare, Nursing and Health. 100 copies of each book sanctioned for each jf the four years.( Female Education.) Embroidery, Drawing and Decoration Arts. 100 copies of each book sanctioned ^or tachi'o^rthe four years. (* Female Educotion. ) Cutting, Sewing and . „ Embroidery. . 100 copies of nach boo&gt; sanctioned for eaoh of the four years.( Embroide ry ^rts.) Cutting, Seeing, Embroidery, and Hew PesMone. 100 conies of eich book sanctioned for each o f ‘♦'he four ears.( Higher Embroidery Arts. ) • P - ' e 1 i me n 0 r ' ,r Reedin? Books. 500 copies o' esc* of the/Readin^ Boohs ^ t r or ^ach of the three years t'or Kindergarten. One jestefi’rtor Prinkin^ tiachine, f»ith all the equipment required for it, to be imported from Egypt, as per permit issued by .the Ministry of Finance. ( Egypt.) \ uermit is required to be obtained from Egyptian Ministry of Interior r or the Eaport^bfcs^veral Arabic books. 4 list of such books will be submitted later.(143/21/45) *4 U , HIS Majesty’s ArnTDassador at Cairo presents his compliments to H.M.Consill, Koweit, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British... J&amp;rihassy.,. Cair.o... ON 1&lt;1&gt; liM iv u il IK. t/V t Dated ///I. Reference to previous correspondence Peb.. ^ 194 ...5 *N I Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. b-M Subject. From: Note from Royal Egyptian Ministry ' of Foreign Affairs No. 58 of 8/2/45 Requests delivery of letter to Director of Education,Koweit. 3479a 26047 (4iCopy to; The Political Agent, Kuwait, o C/o The Bolioical Agency, Kuwait, 11th 14aroh, 1945. 265 As Educational Adviser to His Highness the ShaiKh of Kuwait I am writing to you on behalf of the Education Committee. curing recent years considerable progress has been made in the Government schools. The standard so far reached is not very nigh but an excellent start has been made. Within the town walls onAn fiVe ,? 0hO ° l8 f0r boya and two for Sirls *ith a total of about &lt;J000 pupils. The majority of these are in Infant or Primary Classes, which cover the first seven ye rs of instruction, xhere is a small Secondary Section to the biggest of the schools but this has only about 25 pupils. This will be developed year by year as larger numbers progress through the Primary Sections, fhe complete pre-college education consists of three years Infants, four Primary and five Secondary. As yet we have only the first three years of the secondary school. Arabic is the medium of instruction but apart from this the curr cuium is similar to that of English schools. n t lish is taught irom the second primary grade upwards. teaching staff is entirely Arab, being recruited from &gt; yrla * ie are now sending boys to Cairo and hexrut for training as teachers. At present there are 21 abroad Jf ulalne r we * A( ?pe increase this number to at least 40. most oX these boys will taKe a special short course of one or two re ^ urn to ^wait. In this way we hope to bridge the gap between ohe standard of our own schools and that of others in more advanced countries as quickly as possible. le realise that the advent of oil companies to Kuwait will f ? r y°^hs who can be trained as clerical and c nical staif. e intend to do everything we can to meet that remand, but the fruits of education are slow to ripen and all we can do is to see that conditions are as good as we can make them, i At present we are much handicapped by lack of materials. hav ® 1 ° r retime wished to set up an evening school for typing but have been unable to do so because of the impossibility of ~ ^ to wo!ad-be y olerK 3 ? r3 ‘ ^ in3truotlon woulJ b * ot G r e et value Knowing of your sympaohetic interest in the work of the education Aepartment I v/rite to ask you if you could helo us in this matter. Would it be possible to obtain from the Atates say halx a dozen second-hand typewriters with which we could start our classes? I as* because I feel that It is a Batter of great importance. W. could of course wait until supplies are ea-ler to in 6 8r^t U dJ£nd. iS f ° r in the Ver ^ utur « typists will be you round^tSe^ schoo^s^ 0 T alirain ^o^orrow and so cannot offer to show what is being done I have as*ed C to see for yourself of Kduoatlon oo get iHoulh with vou Erector He will be only too pleased to arrange I H ° llday - Yours sincerely, • Jfetriek, Esquire, educational j ser, Kuwait, General Superintendent, Eestern aulf oil Co..Ltd., KH-ATT/'rgnslatlon of letter No.n/6/2642 2 ^ dHterl the 12th '-’ebruary, 1945, from His Anent? S Ku'anr jler ° f KU ’ 78it ' t0 the ^^iticel After Coiripliments, Our Aducntion Department is in need of ordering cert-in chemical goods, maps, and sports equipments detailed in the attached listo. I request you kindly to communicate with the authorities concerned in the JJ.J.A, or India to permit the export of the equipment. Usual Inding. ✓ A UtrLJm**' ‘ / * /j h* ^ lis , / tv^KoA h' ^ / k / r r '/ y ' *Kuwait• c'* / 11th # iwarch 1945 ikfi 1 am enclosing an Arabic translation of my report on my inspection of the schools in the Amirate of Kuwait for forwarding to his Highness together with a copy of the Arabic and of the English original for your information. As Sir Geoffrey is in Bahrain I will take a copy with me and present it to him myself. You will seC from this report that I have undertaken among other things to arrange for the establishment of a hostel in Cairo for Kuwait stud nts by September next. This will be no light task particularly as I am already fully occupied in Bahrain. I au* however hoping for assistance from British Council staff in Egypt. For some time i have been convinced that there should be a British Council officer stationed in Cairo whose sole job would be to advise on educational affairs in Kuwait and Bahrain. It is not more difficult to visit Kuwait from Cairo than from Bahrain and so much more could be done here if the Adviser's time were equally divided between the two states.When I see Sir Geoffrey in Bahrain I shaS± A tai;e t 8 is matter up with the British Council, and I shall be grateful if you will also give your supoort. iMjackson Esq. , H.B.M's Political Agent, Kuwait.REPORT ON EDUCATION IN KIT,/AIT BY MR.ff.J. WAKELIN . EDUCATIONAL ADVISSRl “ ZlO ( 3RD ~ 12TH MARCH. 1945 ) It is unfortunate that this my first visit of the year to the Amirate of Kuwait should have been so long delayed and then have coincided with Shaikh Abdullah Jabir f s absence in India, It is to be hoped however that I shall have the opportunity of meeting him in Bahrain on his return to Bahrain. (a) INSPECTION OF SCHOOLS . •I made an inspection of all the town schools in the week before the examinations began. I was unable to go out to the villages but I have discussed their problems with the Committee. The main changes since my last visit are the addition of a third year to the Secondary School and the separation of the infant classes from the Mubarakia School. The establishment of an Infant School is a most important advance. Children straight from home require the individual care and attention of specialised teachers. Under the old system the little ones were left to the mercy of whatever teachers could be spared from the primary classes most of whom were raw beginners or old men of the Mulla type. In this new school the best of the Kuwait teachers are working under Oqab Khatib, a young Kuwait man who is particularly suited for such work. It is in the infant classes that the foundations of education are laid. It is therefore of great importance that as soon as possible the infant classes of the other three schools be housed in separate buildings. Little improvement has yet been made in the teaching of Arithmetic owing to the lack of trained teachers and the scarcity of books. At least two Mathematics specialists should be engaged for the next school year. Then with the arrival of the necessary books which are now on order from Egypt there should be a rapid advance. Looking back over the past two years one sees a considerable improvement in the standard of English but here again much remains to be done before the situation can be regarded as satisfactory. Among the Egyptians there is only one whose English is even moderately good. He has.done much to train the local staff but most of the teaching is mechanical and lacking in imagination. Our aim should be a standard whereby a boy who has completed his fourth primary year should be in a position to read and write simple English fluently and to be able to make use of what he knows in conversation out of school. At present this is not even true of boys who have completed their third secondary year. The engagement of three English specialists for next year is essential. With the re-opening of work by the Oil Company in the near future there will be a great demand for youths with a working knowledge of English and a sound training in Arithmetic. Unless the schools can provide these men the Company will have to seek elsewhere for employees. A knowledge of English and Arithmetic are not the only requirements for a boy setting out to earn his living. He must also be thoroughly grounded in his own language. Reports on the boys studying in Egypt indicate that the Arabic language is well taught in the schools of Kuwait. There is however one tendency which is to be deplored. In most of the schools Arabic Reading is taught with emphasis on speed rather than on understanding. Both boys and teachers regularly spend hours reading aloud at great speed paying no heed to punctuation or phrasing. To learn to read words from a book is a very different thing from being able to absorb what is written therein. The/3 ZTf ^ , • Tlle Geography and History syllabuses have a^ain been rim-fi?+ d -f n!i i? 0re T attention is paid ln tlle ea rly years to L'^ 3611 -. In tllese days when attention is focused on are 1 ^ vftfli’ S i t ° exteat not “own before these two subjects re of vital importance in a progressive educated community. P tll erefore gratifying to see that they are being taught in a manner which emphasises their relationship to the life of the people themselves. 1 ? n a community where most parents are uneducated and ° au f es o:f m health hygiene lessons should -P P ?P ant ^ pl ? Ce ln tlle our riculum. The employment of a bCt bv f?Lip e t S p 3 p is . a valuable ste P ^ the right direction, is aVL 36 t ^ °f traclloItta and ulcers, valuable as it P'.° an d ° llttbe ln tlle l° n g run to raise the standard of health. The only sound method is to improve conditions in the home ana this can be done by making school children fully aware oa uses and dangers of diseases prevalent in Kuwait, and tbem Practically how they may be prevented, steps de8n made 111 this direction by the provision of h ysienic system for drinking water, n tention should now be paid to the exclusion of flies, the hB 1 P™ aSent f ln Phe^ spreading of eye diseases. There must also e a more rigorous inspection of heads and ears. Water is scarce and expensive in Kuwait but no boy who washes himself even twice a week need be as dirty as some of the primary schoolboys whom I have seen._ Cleanliness is a habit which we 1 have to learn. The earlier it is acquired the better. wor &amp; this kind being done among the girls will ultimately have an even greater influence that among the boys. This is because the conditions under which the family live are controlled largely by the women. Herein lies the imporilnce of the education of girls. The curriculum of these schools A hf U Pf d tbe need s Of Kuwait. In addition to Arabic and Arithmetic they study Cooking, Domestic Science, Hygiene Needlework, Dressmaking and Child Welfare. In both schools t clobhing^ Vaded &amp;nd Very Wel;l ' P r °duoed display of food and •^■ s P is not yet possible to send girls abroad for further training it will be necessary to engage additional mistresses. A capable inspectress should be found as it is B??^t^ ble r f °fi, tile -' D P ector of Education to give the necessary attention to the girls' schools. In addition six well trained assistant mistresses are required. The premises of the Qiblieh Girls' School have recently / been considerably improved but those of the Sharqieh are still hopelessly inadequate.. Expansion being impossible a new building is required. (b) THE DIRECTOR . Your Highness is to be congratulated on the eneaeempnt nt sadeq Hamdi, the Director of Education. In the short^Ce thaf J 56 ? 11 Jlere he has done much to overcome the serious d i™ udtlea create d hy his predecessor. He has won the respect of the Committee and his staff and in spite of the man y obstacles which are the product of war conditions the Department is running smoothly and efficiently. I attended two meetings of the Committee during mv visit and was gratified to note the friendly spirit of co-operation which prevailed. The impressions that I had received during the first few days that the Director has been well received were fully conxirmed. The Committee expressed the opinion that although Sadeq Hamdi f s contract expires this summer it is essential/essential for tlie continuity of tlie work of the Department that he should continue in the service of Your Highness a sentiment I heartily endorse. I understand that he is ready to do so. J (c) PROPOSED HOSTEL . The chief point discussed at these meetingswas that of the future of missions abroad. There are at present 19 students from Kuwait studying at Egyptian schools in Cairo. I was asked by the Committee last summer to arrange for the schooling ol 28 boys in addition but this was impossible as there was no accommodation available in the Egyptian boarding schools, nor is the situation likely to improve in the near future. The great need in Kuwait at the moment is for as large a number ox students as possible to take special courses abroad which will enable them to raise the standard of teaching in Kuwait as quickly as possible. This will bring about a far more rapid improvement than the complete training of a chosen few. There is no reason why, at the same time a small number of selected students should not embark on secondary education with a degree as the ultimate aim. In order to do this it is necessary to establish a hostel in Cairo where these students can live under supervision. This has been done by many Governments including those of Saudi Arabia and Iraq* These boys could then be placed in whatever schools are thought suitable. The scheme would open up many valuable possibilities. Besides the Government Secondary Schools there is a Branch of the excellent Victoria College, the Heliopolis English School, training colleges for elementary teachers, the Institute of Education for more advanced training, trade schools of various kinds and art schools also. « The Committee has agreed to the proposals and has asked me to prepare estimates and to take immediate steps to’ find a suitable building in Cairo and to arrange for its furnishing. I am already in touch with the British Council concerning this hostel and will report to Your Highness as soon as possible. (d) EGYPTIAN TEACHERS . The Committee has agreed to offer all the Egyptians at present in the Department renewal of their contracts for a further period of two years. I shall convey this decision to the Ministry of Education in Cairo. I shall also apply for additional masters and mistresses as soon as it is decided what extra staff is required. (e) EQUIPMENT . An order for stationery has already been placed in India and I am asking the British Council in Cairo to purchase books in Egypt and to arrange for their export as they did last year. It gives me great pleasure to report to Your Highness such a satisfactory state of affairs. With a competent Director, an enthusiastic and co-operative Committee and the generous support of Your Highness real progress is being made. Plans/4 a V Plans are being formulated and put into action which will being great benefits to the Amirate of Kuwait. There is every reason to believe that your schools will in the future serve not only Kuwait itself but will be a means of bringing education and enlightenment to people of neighbouring states. Kuwait, 11th March, l__9jl__5.2^7 HO. C/276-4/13 Kuwait. The 17th March, 1945 To 'From The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Hon •hie the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRS . Sir I have the honour to refer to the British Embassy, Cairo letter No. 642/2/45 dated the 30th January, 1945, copy forwarded to me under your printed letter No. 229-S dated the 17th February, 1945, and to enclose herewith a statement in original together with a translation made by Ahmad Sadiq. Hamdi which is self explanatory. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant itical Agent, Kuwait MBi Britibh tiaibasb^, Cairo, Pebruax^ 1945. COSil V'/r ; bir, Kuivak r •• 1 have the honour to tranemit herewith a copy of a note addreefced to this Smbaeby by the Egyptian Ministry of Voreign Affaire resetting certain inforraation regarding the seryice of Sgyptian teachers who have been delegated to Kuwait and Bahrain. £• //ill you please be good enough to forward to me the information required for transmission to the Egyptian Government ? I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, Killean•From The Ministry of Foreign Affairs, r ^ Consular Department No. 39.73/1. 74 ( NOTE. The Boyal Ministry of Foreign affairs presents his compliments to His Britannic Majesty's Ambassador and has the honour to inform him thatjwith a view to regularising the conditions allowances and other ammolurnents of the Egyptian teachers delegat ed to Kuwait, Bahrain, and Aden, theBoyal Ministry of public Instruction would he glad to know the date of departure from Egypt of each of the teachers, the date of his return, and also the dates of commencement and termination of the school holidays in the schools to which the teachers are attached. The Boyal Minist**? will he obliged to Kis Britannic Majesty's Ambassador if he will bring this to the notice of the competent authorities in the above mentioned countries, and ^ takes this opportunity to renew hia assurances of his highest consideration. Cairo the 17th January, 1945. To. His Britannic Majesty's Ambassador., CAIRO. The above was translated by C.N. Jackson, Esquire, Political Agent, Kuwait^ on March 19th, 1945.TK/3AB. Uyi. British Enbassy, Cairo. 642/1/4 13th January, 1945. COh &gt; ‘ ' Sir With reference to ry letter of 27th November, 1944, enclosing copy of a note from the Egyptian B-inistry of foreign Affairs regarding the delepation of Ismail Ibrahim'2eid for employment as a school teacher in Koweit, I have the honour to transmit herewith cony of a Jote in which t?ie Ministry of Foreign Affairs request payment of the sum of f.22.700 in respect of the cost of one second class ticket from Haifa to Basrah supplied to the above-named official by Messrs. Thos. Cook &amp; dons Ltd., Cairo. A copy of the bill presented by Messrs, fhos. Cook 8 : don to the Egyptian i inis try of Educa- , tion in this connection is also transmitted herewith. 2. The Egyptian Ministry of Foreign Affairs request that the Government of Koweit may be asked to refund the above amount. Will you kindly communicate this request to the Government of Koweit for such action as they consider appropriate. with reference to Residency.Printed letter‘No.C/394 dated 6th Octobeh,/ 1943, for necessary action. I have the honour to be dir, Your obedient dervant dd. KILKARN. The Political Resident Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN. No.C.16. Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. Dated the 26th February, 1945. Copy with enclosures in original forwarded with compliments to: The Political Agent Kih/AlT. LB.acknowledge with thanks.-the receipt of your letter No.191^4/13 of the 26th February, 1945* enclosing a bank draft for the sum of three Iraq. ID3/156 dinars and one hundred and fifty-sik fils, being in refund of the expenses incurred by us on behalf of His Highness the Shaikh of Kuwait on meeting A.S. Hamdi Bey, director of Education, Kuwait. 2. An official receipt is enclosed. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obje-dient servant, 3^7 ice-Consul for acting Consul-General The Political Agent, Kuwait.Printed in England. Aug. 1941. (40730 pads CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) 6/-47P 1 ^ C A t ' Charge. OFFICE STAMP AND DATE. Clerk’s Name, No. and Circuit and Time forwarded. No. r- aft Official Instructions 6 Vul No. Words Time Instructions to be ^£naned ; __ To Name _ 'ATflEr A ddress — ? A ETAIS PLEASJS ..... EXACT.. ADB^SS OF SDUOATIOK^L munn A3.B.0.CIA.T.IC..,; :. POLITICAL 37 * r I raqiMt tkat &lt;k« ik*«t TM^rtia asy k« f«r«arS*4 Mk|«ct to to* coaSItiMi prlutos m kack •! toil Itra fcy vktoh I ten* to to toato. Signature of Sender £22£ Telephone No Address (Not to be telegraphed) ICONDITIONS. 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward sifch telegram although it has been received for that purpose ; but in such case the amount paid for transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. NOTE.—Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging, must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company’s Branches./ C ONFIDWI AL NO. C/353. The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon’hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIHB. and has the honour to transmit to him two copies of the undermentioned documents. Residency endorsement No. C/51 dated the 8th March, 1945. The Political Agency, KUWAIT. Dated the 10th April, 1945 Reference to previous correspondence : DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURES Statements regarding the service of Egyptian teachers delegated to Kuwait.NO. ... «—Sj Kuwait Educational Department./// ^ r0in POLITICAL AGENT, KUWAIT. 10 POLITICAL RESIDENT, BUSHIRE, K( peated GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. NEW DELHI. No. 753* Dated 19th April. 1945. Subject:— IM PORT ASS ISTANCE RE COM MENDATION. Reference Goyemment of India letter No. D. 3154-N/42 dated 18th May, 1942, forwarded under Bushire Printed letter No. 655-S dated 25th June, 1942. 1. Ihe particulars required by para 3 of the letter under reference are given below : (i) Name of would-be importer:— (ii) Name &amp; address of agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply :— (iiij Full description of the goods required:— Kuwait 4u0«iilou TGpartKwnt, ulf). ) Ill h i’«i| 'i~y t^ ■■***',* • oharta* rodola* Iji bora Lory (iv) Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. of the goods required:— (v) Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported :— (vi) Special reasons justifying (a) Supply of goods required:- l even owtet. us* in bh# Kuwait oovarn&amp;ent •ahools* The rtoo^ff ure r«qulr«d to onuip sahooli hrlnr* nnlursoU on th« adYloi of Brltiah Counoll# (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country:— ttoc avnliable for export from Inala. or Iraq* (vii) Description of the urgency with which the goods are required, and the latest date which will be suitable:— (viii) Order identification references : — \ CATEGORY :- rfaoaaaury v j .urin;: Liw ftMNfl Lslf or 1940# Order will he aleeed throu t\ \ hrix,lah outoil# -hV^ A' * (ix) (a) Whether included in half yearly programme:— : — •: c * &gt;* ' J- duinid 19ta oril. (b) Head under which included in programme:— 'i * . • l/W 4F Political Agent, Kuwait.D«0#No.381« Political Agency # Kuwait, 19th April, 1945. Ky dear V/akelin, Please refer to our conversation about the supply of Educational gear for the Kuwait schools. ►* 2. The director has now produced a new list of requirements from Egypt and the United Kingdom (enclosed in original) which is still, I am afraid, rather mixed up. However, 1 erielose an Import Assistance Recommendatio: to assist you to get shipping space for the goods the Kuwait Education Department want from the United Kingdom; but as they appear to be of rather a specialized kind I think ii, will be necessary to asK tne India Office to assist in getting such equipment released for export. This can, I think, best be done through British council and I would ask you move them to recommend Kuwait's case to the India Office. I would also ask you to invoke the assistance of British Council in obtaining and exporting the equipment required from Egypt. Yours sincerely, / /.«T. Waxelin, Esquire, Director of Education, BAM-wmIN .No. 0/399 Political Agency, Kuwait. The 23rd April, 1945. Sir, With reference to your letter No. 642/1/45 dated the 13th January, 1945, to the Hon •hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, I have the honour to enclose herewith a hank draft No. 260338/57/11 dated the 11th April, 1945, for E.£ 22.700 on account of cost of one second class ticket from Haifa to Basra issued to Ismail Ibrahim Zaid. I have the honour to he, Sir, Tour most obedient servant, 3d/ II.P.O’C Tandy. Political Agent, Kuwait. His Britannic Majesty’s Ambassador., British Embassy., CAIRO. Copy forwarded to the Hoiible the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to his endorsement No. C/16 dated the 26th February, 1945.Th« fir*t nhi'«i . viegram contains the following particulars in the order namtid Prefi* Letteri *nd Number of Me i Office of Orljin Number of Words, Date, Time handed In and C instructions—if any. Printed in England. Sept. 1941. (1,200 pads) CABLE AND WIRELESS (MID-EAST) LIMITED. 6/-184 ^ &gt;1 VT 36 /V BAHREIN 14/13 1? 0813 LC POL ITI CAL KUWA I T ADDRESS ESA I 7 I/I 8 I HIGH DOLBORN LONDON wy wci WAKEL I N * . t \ MARK YOUR REPLY NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OP THIS COPY. REPLIES SHOULD BE HANDED IN AT ONE OF THE COMPANY'S OFFICES.Translation of letter No.89 dated 5.5.46(the ^ 17th April, 1945) from the Director of Education Dept., Kuwait, to H. H. the Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments, I have the honour to request for permits for the male and female Egyptian teachers, with vhom the Kuwait Education Dept, is going to gpc.tsx ma^e contract, through the Education Advisor in Egypt, so that they may be able to enter Kuwait in Ramadhan or Shawal, 1364( August or September, 1945.) and that will be according to a statement which will be submitted to the British Consulate in Cairo. This will help to open the schools regularly on the next school year,1364-1365. Usual Ending.Translation of latter No»90 dated 5* 5* 46 (l r7 .4.45) from Kuwait Kduaation Dept., to H.H. the Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments, I have the honour to submit to ]four Highness the decision reached by the Education Committee in their meeting held on 21st Rabi Awal 1364U- J ' regarding the renewal of the contract of UstaHh Ahmad Sadiq Hamdi, Director of Education, for another year to begin *x on the 1st Sh awal,1364. I request Your Hi^n*** to comuunicate with the Egyptian ftovt. to agree to this renewal, after being sanctioned by Your Highness. Usual Ending.-tj,: :rinL GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER &gt; ^6 [ X V, Tj—TIiis is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed, 1 o save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Political A^ent, Kuwait. No. 360-J • l^ued 10th .April 103 45 Cony is enclosed of a letter dated 22nd Parch, 1945 from the Educational Adviser, Kuwait, and of its enclosures. 2. Please (a) obtain an assurance from the Kuwait Government that funds for the proposed hostel in Cairo will be forthcoming with regularity and (b) furnish your views by mail on the Adviser's recommendations in so far as they affect Kuwait. POLITIC 3d/-GEOFFREY PRIOR AL RE3IDEKT,PERJI^K GULP n - 1-7 ■'Ttvrj it A 1 J- iW for secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. DLG. S. 6. MFP—1206 S&amp;P—(M-1723)—4-2 36—200,000.Bahrain. 22nd , i arch, 11 45. The Hon ! ble the Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf. 3ushire. 3ir, I have the honour to submit the Bullish original of my report on my recent inspection of the^ Educational iysten in the Amirate of Kuwait, of which an Arabic translation was forvjarded to His Highness 3ir Shaikh Ahi.,ad al Subah by the Political Agent,of Kuwait. I was unable to visit Kuwait in the autumn^ as in oast years because of pressure of wor^c in Bahrain, me Egyptian teachers whom I engaged in Se-tember did not reach Bahrain u -.til November and it was not possible for me to leave until I was satisfied that they had settled down. The Political Agent had asked me to visit Kuwait early in March as it was expected that Shaikh Abdullah Jabir would be leaving for India about the middle of the month. It so happened that he was able to get a passage by steamer earlier than he had anticipated so' he left a day or so before my arrival. I am hap-y to report that this year the affairs of the Education Depart ent are running smoothly, f’-e' Egyptian Director of Education appointed in October is' well suited for ti e difficult tg^ and has the whole hearted support of the Committee. He is res pected by his staff and well liked by the people. The Committee took pains to make it clear that my visit was welcome a id that it is eager to a^ail^ itself of what assistance I can give. The chief task that I have undertaken is the establish ent of a hostel in Cairo. It is my opinion that the time has novj come ±or the appointment of an Adviser who can devote ore time to Kuwait. The present arrange lept whereby the Director of Education.of Bahrain pays infrequent visits when his other duties permit and does what he can during his su imer vacation is not satisfactory. It is impossible to make much headway during such brief visits as negotiations are always protracted and one usually leaves Kuwait feeling that one's contacts are only superficial. Long distance corres pondence brings meagre results as there is^always tne feeling that once away from Kuwait my chief conc&amp;rn is with Bahrain. The Committee asks that it should have the right to the services of the Adviser at all times. I have the honour to enclose a memorandum which deals more fully with this point, a copy o± whicn I am sending to the Representative of the British Council in the middle East. I shall be gra^eiul i.or your approval and support ox this. The Kuwait Government is fully prepared to set up a hostel/-r - 2 - a hostel in Cairo but does not xvish to cooperate with t/ie Bahrain Government in this. The number of students in Cairo will be increased to 50 and the necessary funds iade available. The Con ittee expressed the view that joidp financial control by the two Govern ments would raise too nany problems and that an independent hostel for IJuwait is to be preferred. Furniture and one year's rent’will cost about £ 2,500 and the running expenses will be about £.700/- per mensem a considerable part of which will be borne by parents. The Committee does not wish to avail itself of the offer of the British Council to provide an Bullishman as Supervisor but asks that the adviser be in a position to keep// in close touch with their own Garden. This is in accbrdance with its policy of aiming at preserving its independence of action and at the sa e time reaping what benefit it can from outside sources. If the British Council appoints a man in Cairo as I nave suggested tills should be oossible. - / The Committee will provide 'the noney for this project but ask that the British Council under take the actual worlf of setti ig up the hostel. I have written to r. ighwood, their Adviser on Arab Affairs asking for his assistance. It is he who has done so much for the Kuwait and Bahrain students in Cairo. During ly sum* er leaves I have obtained permission Bocri the Bgyptian ministry of education for these boys to study in Bgypt but on my return to Bahrain I have had to leave the arrangement of details to him. As I am due for home leave at the end of June I shall have to ask him to undertake this not inconsiderable task. All the Bgyptian teachers who are wording in Kuwait are to be offered a renewal of contract as their services have been satisfactory and I have been asked to a rrange the engagement of 8 male and 7 female teachers for the next school year. I very much regret that I was unable to reach Bahrain in time to discuss t ese matters with you personally. I was unfortunately held up at Zubeir on my way for three days and at Basrah for eight on my return so that I did not reach Bahrain until 20th March. I have the honour to be, Jir, Your obedient servant, 3d/- F. Jake 1in. Educational Adviser, Kuwait. DLG— It is unfortunate that this my first visit of the year to the Amirate of Kuwait should have been so long delayed and then have coincided with Jhaihh Abdullah Jabir’s absence in India. It is to be hoped however that I snail have the opportunity of seeting him in Bahrain on his return to Bahrain. (a) ITBBICflON OF oCBOOL^ . I' made an inspection of all the town schools in the week before the examinations began. I was unvole to go out^to the villi'es but I hat’e discussed their problems with the committee. The main changes since y last visit are the addition of a third year to the Secondary Jchool and the separation of tne infant classes from the Bubarakia School. The establishment of an Infant School is a most important advance. Children straight from home require the individual care and attention of specialised teachers. Under the old system the little ones were left to the mercy of whatever teachers could be spared from the primary classes most of whom were raw beginners or old men of the Bulla tgpe. ^nis new school the best of the Kuwait teachers are working under Ooab Khatib, a young Kuwait man who is particularly ^ suited for such work. It is in the infant classes tnat the foundations of education are laid. i-t is therefore o-i. w reat importance that as soon as possible the infant classes o- the other three schools be housed in separate, buildings. Little improvement/ has yet been made in the teaching of Arithmetic owing to the lack of trained teachers and ^ the scarcity of books. At least two Latnematics specialises should be engaged for the next school year. Then with^the arrival of the necessary books which are now on order from Egypt there should be a rapid advance. Looking back over the past two years one sees a considerable improvement in the standard of English but^here a?ain much remains to be done before the situation can ^e regarded as satisfactory. Among the Egyptians there is only one whose English is even moderately good. Hehas^done much to train the local staff but most of the teaching is mechanical and lacking in imagination. Our aim should be a standard whereby a boy who has completed his ^our mi primary year should be in a position to read and write sxxpsixx simple English fluently and to be able to make use of what he knows in conversation out of school. At present this is not even t-rue of boys who have completed their third ysax secondary year. The enga ement of three English specialists for next year is essential, nth the re-opening of work by the Oil Comoany in the near future there will be a great demand for' youths with a working knowledge of English and a sound trainin y in Arithmetic. Unless the schools can provide these'men the Company will have to seek elsewhere for employees A knowled ~e of English and Arithmetic are not the only requirements for a boy setting out to earn his living, -e must also be thoroughly grounded in his own language, xsx xustualsa '-be.'-thoEaugKly cgrouned : Be ports on tne boys studying in Egypt indicate that the Arable language is well taught in the schools of Kuwait. Tnere is however one tendency which is to be deplored. In most o^ o s scnools Arabic Reading is taught with emphasis^ on speed ratner nan on understanding. Both boys and teachers regularly s P en hours reading aloud at great speed paying no heed.to punc- tuation Sr phrasing. To learn to read words^ahooc is a very different thing frora being able to absorb ,nat.is written therein. The Geography and History syllabuses have again been revised and lore attention is paid, in the early years to i await itself. In these days when attention is focused on world affairs to an extent not known before these two subjects are of vital importance in a progressive educated community. It is therefore gratifying to see that they are being taught in a manner which emphasises their relationship to the life of the peo:Is themselves. In a community where lost parents are uneducated and ignorant of the causes of ill health hygiene lessons should take an important place in'the curriculum. The employment of a doctor for the schools is a valuable step in the right direction, but by itself treatment of trachoma and ulcers, valuable as It is, can do little in the Ion- run to raise the standard of health. The only sound method is to improve conditions in the hone and this can be done by making school children fully aware of the causes and dangers of diseases prevalent in Kuwait, and teaching them practically how they lay be prevented. Steps have already been made in this direction by the provision of suitable latrines and a-hygienic system for drinking water. Attention should now be paid to the exclusion of flies, the chief agents in the spreading of eye diseases. There must also be a more/ rigorous inspection of heads and ears. Hater is scarce and expensive in Kuwait but no boy who washes himself even twice a week need be as dirty as some of the primary shoolboys whom I have seen. Cleanliness is a habit which we all have to learn. The earlier it is qccguired the better. The work of this kind being done among the c irls will ultimately have an even greater influence than that among the boys. This is because the conditions under which the family live are controlled largely by the women. Herein lies the importance of the education of ^irls. The curriculum of these schools is well suited to the needs of Kuwait. In addition to Arabic and Arithmetic they study Cooking, Domestic Science, Hygiene, T eediework, Dressmaking and Child welfare. In both schools I saw a very varied and very well produced display of food and clothing. As it is not yet possible to send girls abroad for further training it will be necessary to engage additional mistresses. I cap Hole inspectress should be found as it is impossible for the Director of Education to give the necessary attention to the girls’ schools. In addition six well trained assistant mistresses are required. The premises of the -iblieh Girls ichool have recently been considerably improved but those of the Jharqieh are still hopelessly*inadequate. Expansion being impossible a new building is required. (b) THE DIEECTCil . Your Highness is to be congratulated on the engage ment of Cadeq Harndi, the Director of Education. In the short time that he has been here he has done much to over come the serious difficulties created by his predecessor. He has won the respect of the ' Committee and his staff aid in spite of the many obstacles which are the product of war conditions the Department is running smoothly and efficiently. I attended two meetings of the Committee during my my/-my visit and was -ratified to aote the friendly spirit of co-operation which prevailed. The i pressions that I had received during the first few days that the Director has been well received were fully confirmed. ^The Committee expressed the opinion that although ~&gt;adeq Handi's contract expires this summer it is essential for the continuity of*the work of the Department that he should continue in the service of Your Kighnessj a sentiment I heartily endorse. I understand that he is ready to do so. (c) PRO DO DP D hC-&gt;x 1 Dh . The chief point discussed at these eetings was that of the future of missions abroad. There are at present Ih students from Kuwait studying at Egyptian schools in Cairo. I was asked by the Committee last summer to arrange for the schooling of 28 boys in addition but this was impossible# as there was°no accommodation available in the Egyptian boarding schools 5 nor is the situation likely to improve in the near future. The great need in Kuwait at the moment is for as large a number of students as possible to take special courses abroad which will eriaole the' to raise tne standard of teaching in Kuwait as quickly as possible. This will bring about a far m0re rapid improvement than the complete training of a chosen few. There is no reason why, at the same time a small number of selected students should not embark on secondary education with a degree as the ultimate aim. In order to do this it is necessary to establish a hostel in Cairo where these students can live under supervision. This has been done by r any Governments includin': those of Caudi Arabia and Ir~c;. These boys could then be placed in whatever schools are thought suitable. The scheme would open up many valuable oossibilities. Besides the Government secondary Schools there is a Branch of the excellent Victoria '-•olleas ) the Heliopolis English School, training colleges for elementary teachers, the Institute of Education for tore advanced training, trade schools of various kinds and art schools also. The Committee has agreed to the proposals and has asked me to nrepare estimates and to taue im ediate steps to find a suitable building in Cairo and to arrange for its furnishing. I am already in touch 'ioh the Britisn Council concerning this hostel and will report to Your Highness as soon as possible. (d) SGYPTIaK fEjiCHKaD. The Committee has agreed to offer all the Egyptains at present in the Department renewal of their contracts for a further period of two years. I snail^convey this decisioh to the rain is try of Education in oairo. also apply for additional masters and mistresses as soon as it is decided what extra staff is required. (e) EQUIPMENT . An order for stationery has already been^placed in India and I am asking the British Council in ^airo to purchase books in Egypt and to arrange for their export as they did last year. It ves me reat pleasure to report to Your Your/-Your Highness such a satisfactory state of affairs. ^ ./ith a competent Director, an enthusiastic and co-operative Comriittee and the generous support of Your Highness real- progress is being made. Plans are being formulated and put into action which will bring great benefits to the Amirate of Huwait. There is every reason to believe that your schools will in the future serve not only Kuwait itself but will be a means of bringing education and enlightenment to people of neighbouring states. Kuwait. 11th arch, 1. 45. 3d/- ?.,J. 7/akelin. Educational Adviser. \D.O. No. 202/30 Bahrain, 22nd I arch^ li 45. Dear Tiijhwood, lostel for Kuv/ait students . The Kuwait Government has approved the scheme for opening a Hostel for Kuwait students in Cairo. The original plan was for Bahrain and Kuwait to cooperate in this but as no definite proposals have yet co le from the Bahrain Government the Kuwait Committee feels* that as ti ie is short they must act at once and on their own. It is intended to'increase the number of students studying in Bgypt to 50. All of these will be either secondary school*boys or young teachers such as those we sent fro i Bahrain. They are prepared, at a preliminary estimate, to set aside £.2000 to £2500 for furnishing and one year’s rent and to pay £.700 per mensem in running expenses. These figures are based on the following rough estimate: Ealary of Supervisor £, 20 per aensem Salary of assistant £. 15 per i nensem. Kenial Staff £. 30 Per mensem Electricity, Hater, Fuel £. 25 Per mensem Food for 50 ^ £.7 p. 1 . each £.350 Per mensem Pocket Honey for 50 at £.2 p.m. each £.100 Per mensem Extras £.160 Per i 'ensem £.700 Per mensem The above is based on what I know of the 3audi Arabian and Korocan Hostels in Cairo and I shall be glad to have your comments. The Committee does not wish to avail itself of the Council’s offer to provide an English supervisor as they wish to appoint &amp;bdul iiziz Hussein as Harden, but they do ask that their new Adviser be a Council man stationed in Cairo who can keep in close touch with the Hostel and visit Kuwait from time to time. Kuwait is ready to provide the necessary funds but we shall have to deal with the job of setting up this Hostel. I sav ”we”, but as yon. know I hope to go to England in July and until then I shall be fully occupied as my successor has so far failed to materialise. I had hoped that Nilley, or whoever is taking my place, would have been here before now thus giving me the opportunity of dealing with these affairs myself. Can it be done ? Have you the time to spare ? If not is there anyone else who can do the job. Enthusiasm in Kuwait is great. Applications from parents who want' to send their sons at their own expense were already pouring in before I left. The same will be true of Bahrain if the Government also decides to open a separate hostel, which I understand is more than probable. sd/- F.J.Hake1in. H.H.Highwood, Esq. Education Adviser. British Council, CAIHQ.6 V VoiBortjndiim on l^ucaticn In the chcola of the OovennMKite of end i u^ait by Xlr* F«J* . akciln f ^ueatlonel Adviser 9 Mif, .AiAiL* Apert fron the need for eoueated youths in uovemmont l o^ertmonts the work of the oil companies in Behreln 9 luwalt end ^astern eudi&amp; rxebie will absorb ell whoa we can produce for several years to come* Clerical and technical trainees are already being sought and the demand will increase as the new production prograsuses ce&amp;e into action* This expansion of the oil Industry will mean also a general development of trade and the creation of new opportunities for private business* In both Bahrain and ruw&amp;it the demand for education is * not yet being fully met* jny new buildings or extensions added in the pest four years have been utilised for pupils already at school rather than for new entranta y In tha process of reducing the number of children per roors to a workable 11 It, Only In the lower school are ..tore than 30 children fotaad in one group* flew Infant Schools are required at once In both states to reduce this figure still further and to accommodate the 200 or so who are turned away aach year through lack of accommodation* This will entail the engagement of additional trained teachers. The work that has been begun in Bahrain and Mi wait is merely the prelude to the development of a coordinated educational system thr Ajghout the Gulf and Eastern Baudla Arabia* within this area there is nothing to compare with the schools of 5*ihrain or Fuwait except in the hejjus, which province is so remote that it can scarcely be inc uded in our sphere* In rapidly increasing numbers boys from oaudla Arabia and other neighbouring states are joining our schools • At present we era able to provide a sound orlaary course of seven years and * an introduction to a secondary education of three years*2 s~\ * &gt; rovld«d oup «»ch&amp;clxi aro cxpnndac ««id our saocrndApy MteoXs waU. aquippaci ai«ci ataiT^d ^^ucli itpablH.ua will aatid thalr sens to bahraiu or i uwuit rati^r thar. to Cairo op Bairut aa th© anvlronaut iu Vu^Me aaiiill /i-Pab atataa la niora suited to their needs* bahraln *uLread&gt;* haa hj* axaellent hostel which can be fe*iet~ciati whoi* ii€K3a33^r&gt;'« Ui ijmXi . .v.lJ8.,;-rr4« Xha huaait hducatica Coaidttea is fully aware of the position and la aahii; d preparation* lor development and expansion* Hie new infait sc^iooltt will be opened in September 1945 and 16 ore gyptian testers ard wiatreaaeo engaged* The Cosaaittee lrit«ida to set tp a i*o»tel in Ceiro to house 60 atud«r«ts from Kuwait, tho initial ooat belnit CkOOO and the running e&gt;p««iaea 17C0 per Meissnt these youths will attend sehocls and oollegas in that city* Xhe intent on is that aost of then v»llx take short purees of one or two years of training as teaoiisra. This will bring about a rapid lape^rrenent of the IcchI teachers who form the mejorlty of the staf r* Foreign teachers will be employed chiefly Hi the secondary schools ynd upper classes of the primary schools. These will be gradually replaced by graduates of the Kuwait facondery School and those already at secondary schools abroad whan they hare taken a course et e training college either abroad or possibly in Kuwait* m&amp;sua tf jjsaiitiii* blallar uoticn .list be taken in Bahrain* A start has been made In that nine students were sent to hgypt Hi the sunm«r of 1944 f thr^c of whoa are at e secondary school, three at a teachers training college and three at s technical school* This number should be increased to at least 30 this year* If th« Oorernment will set up s hostel-aany pmrmitB nill bm tr t:©nd thoir at th«ir cm\ ax'^an^a* If Buhraiii la to attract «\iltablft foreign teacher* and to retain thalr ii^rvlcea better conditions ’luet ba provided• The terras of service compare oat unfavourably with those of the luwalt Govcrnnert • ijccept for a h uae allowance of rather leaa than £2 per ttan*em 9 which la only a fraction of the rent of a small house, r* proTl*t«n 1. *ad.. *.1. done In huwalt special quarters wist be act aside, or if nccesaary btdlt* These rl:ict»ld be suitable for # i^arrled cotiple as ^st teachers are married* «claries should be paid from the dt*t« of leaving Kgypt and adequate detention allowances should the man be hold up on his way to or from Bahrain* Passages for wives are also paid to huwalt employaei Thus their teachers ere encouraged to continue their services with the Government over a period of years* All tliose wi*© have completed their first contract ore alining on for another* It 1* doubtful whether the Egyptians in Bahrain will stay for a second year even* The Director of Edueatlon should have e first class Arab assistant and as soon as the man power problem eases a British head faster for the eecorid^rj* ncnool should be appointed* Under present conditions the Director la, among other things, Chief Clerk, confidential Typist, Inspector General, Supervisor of ngliah studies and Adviser to the Kuwisit uovernment* Only in hia spare % moments can he devote thought to administration and policy, which should be his prime concern. The sslary of such an Assistant would be about £1000 per annum plus allowances, half of which would be paid by the Egyptian Govarruaent *ere he aecended by the Ministry of mucatlon. (The salary of the Director of uducaticm, luwait is £irxx) p«a« plus £400 p.a* allowances, paid half by Kuwait ani ivalf by Mjypt)*mm Si c, H4iyAA ntiAk* Vhe txia* i&amp;t yst ri^cr to appoint a British Director to Kuwait, Ihm poaition of the ^tueatlcaal Advisor is now satisiaotoril^r a»tau^i^Aiird # iue on^.; (^oiapiain^t of the coairaittee is that kXx he is able to n.evote so little tine and attention to Kuwait affairs and can visit iheu only 'then his duties in Bjahraln parsdt* They fully appreciate that the Um di^agaiaaiit of for^i^n staff the placing of students abroad wouid bo c^trotuaxy difficult without the help of the British douncil# That «« able to find sc 'Suitable a bireater of Lduoaticn for tnen was xi.deed a feather if. our cap* It iats completely ooiiVinceo thee of our 2-onourable intantioiiSl Ihey hnow too that they oaui not open the Cairo liostei uuu.eai» the Council mtdertfcles a jaajor part of the work* Vhat they ask for is an adviser residont ii: Cairo t wtiexe most of their stunerits will be f who can f cep in close touch with th&lt;ir boys 9 engage their teachers and visit then regularly s scucone whom they have Ujc right to calx upon for auvloe mic aaelstsnee rethor than a casual visitor viiio does what he cun in the ii-dtod ti^^e at his disposal* In conclusion I give be.x* s suiroary of the part the British should play* !• he legate aii official in Cairo to continue the work of educationa l adviser to the Kuwait Government and to supervise the Kuwait and Bahrein (?) hosteltf in Cairo* 2* Continue the iErant to the uahrain Government end # ^l^ieps increase it to cover the director 1 * full salary alien he is mabled 9 through the appointment of an Arab Assistant, to devote joro of his time to adtilnistration »md policy. \ 3* ^eccjfid an official as Director of ducat! another period of four years*CONFIDENTIAL. No. •365-1 * l{k.\. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Tha Political Agent, BAHRAIN, The Political Agent , KUW AIT, and has the honour to transmit py of the undermentioned document (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated...^ April. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. : Name and Date. Subject. London letter No*CYP/43/l8 dated 20th March, 1945 with IR. WILLEY DIRECTOR OP enclosure. EDUCATION.* T HE BRITISH COUNCI L 3 Hanover Street, London.W* No. CYP/43/18 3Y BAG Dated 2v0th March, 1345. My dear Prior, I am glad to inform you that the Council has appointed Mr. K.M. Willey to succeed Mr. F.J. Wakelin as Director of Education in the Persian Gulf. We are hoping that Willey, who is at present on home leave, will arrive in Bahrain in May and will thus be able to work v/ith Wakelin for several weeks before the end of the summer term. Willey, a copy of whose curriculum vitao I attach, was appointed to the British Council 1 s service as Director of the Mansura Institute in Egypt in 1933. He entered the Councils Permanent Overseas Service in 1941 and was subsequently transferred to Cyprus where he has remained until recently as the Council's senior official in that territory. He was responsible there for the opening of five Institutes and a Junior School. I think you will agree that his qualifications should fit him well for the important Bahrain post. The terms of Willey's appointment to the Bahrain Government are, I understand, the same as those for Wakelin, except that the contractual period will be for three years Instead of four as has already been agreed. *DETAILS OF QUALIFICATIONS &amp; EXPERIENCE OF K.V WILLEY Born 20. 6. *04. 1921-1923 - aged 17 - Junior Master in Prep.School,Potter *s Bar. 1923 -26 - Balliol College, Oxford. 3rd Class Honours English. 1926 -31 Superintendent of Education, Nigeria, B.W.Africa. During this time (1) Senior Assistant Master Unnahia Training College. (ii) Assistant Taster, Kln^s College, Lagos. (ill) Lecturer for Teachers 1 Evening Classes. (iv) Superintendent in charge of Province, educationally. (Left Colonial Education Service owing to malignant malaria contracted in West Africa). 1932 - Senior English Master, St. Paul’s School, Sao Paulo, Brazil. 1933 - Senior English Master (Junior Partner) English School. 1935 Petrolopis, Brazil. 1936 -37 External Tutor to Students of Union of Chile a nd English Lecturer in Sumner School, Union of Chile. 1937 - Tutor to son of Lt, Colonel Sir Cuthbert Headlam, Durham. 1937 -38 Tutor to son of Colonel Charles, Saxmundham working for Education Diploma. 1338 - Appointed to Egyptian Education Department, Commercial School. Languages:- Some French, Portuguese, very little Spanish. Passed Government Exam, in W. African language. Outside interests: general, sailing, swimming, riding, squash and tennis.No. C/429 PO T !TTC\ T . \GTTTCY KIJ' r A.TT the 7th ? f ay f 1945* His Majesty f s Political \gent at Kuwait presents his compliments to His Majesty # s ambassador, Cairo, and has the honour to request that visas for Kuwait may kindly he granted, on application, to 8 male and 7 female teachers whom the Kuwait Mucation Department propose shortly to engage in Kgypt. His Majesty*s ambassador, British 'Smhassy, Cairo.A \ -/''s EXPRHS3 L?TTSR. from political Kuwait. To Resident Rushlre. NO. 449. Dated. 12th Hay, 1945. Reference your Express Letter No. 360 - 3 dated 10th April, 1945, paragraph 2 (h). Kuwait Education. 2 . The fact that I have only recently arrived here and that Shaikh Abdullah Jabir has been absent in India since my arrival makes it difficult to offer comments at present with the conviction that they will be of value, but the following observations are made for what they are worth. The most pressing need in Kuwait itself appears to be the introduction of a full course of secondary education. Some of the Kuwaiti boys who have gone to Egypt for secondary and college education will be continuously absent for no less than ten years from their families and their state. That parents should be willing to part with their children for so long a period says volumes for their enthusiasm, but I would prefer to see the bays complete their secoaiary course near their homes and that only such boys as have shown themselves fit for education abroad should be sent to Egypt or elsewhere. It seems that everything possible is being done to provide for a sufficiency of indigenous and imported teachers to step up education to this stage but the question of accommodation for a secondary school does not appear yet to have received consideration. 4. It is unlikely that funds for building a suitable school would ever be obtainable by the present system whereby education is financed by a grant of l/6 # 5 of the customs receipts and 30 % of the profits of the Landing and Transportation Company, and the capital cost will have to be found elsewhere. This should not be difficult as merchants, who have made very considerable fortunes in the l^.st few years, are the members of the cornmuiity keenest on education, and as His Highness will probably shortly receive a handsome accretion to his income in the form of oil royalties. But, before taking steps to raise funds, it is necessary to work up enthusiasm and to convince the people of the advantages of the project, no less than to ascertain what the capital cost would be. I suggest, therefore, that the British council be asked to provide us with plans for a school of modern design with playing grounds and living accommodation for the headmaster, who would probably be a foreigner. I am confident that the Kuwait Oil Company will do all in their power to help with technical advice and assistance. 5. I heartily endorse the Education Adviser # s recommendations with regard to improving the standard of English. English has long been the commercial lingua franca of the world and Kuwait is largely dependent on trade. There is a demand for adult evening classes in English here which is not yet being met. Young Kuwaitis who have obtained their education abroad frequently find / that they have nott that they have not sufficient command of English to carry on 'buginess with countries outside the ’{iddle East# The Kuwait Oil Company, also, are interested in increasing the knowledge of English as this will expand the source upon which they will have to draw for local employees. The British Council might consider taking special steps in this direction in collaboration with the oil company and independently of the Kuwait Education Departments programme. A.t present, there seems little prospect of more than a fraction of the Oil Company's needs being met from the thirty odd students receiving secondary education here. finished his education in Egypt* as varaen or rneir nusue-L jJI Cairo will mean that a large measure of responsibility - including, probably, financial responsibility - will devolve upon the Educational Adviser to Kuwait who, it is proposed, will reside in Cairo. It should be appreciated that it will be necessary for him to carry out executive as well as advisory duties. 7. I understand that the Egyptian schools close for four months in the summer and that at present the Kuwait students in Egypt spend these four months lodging in their schools, bored and discontented. hen the boys are concentrated in the hostel it should be possible to arrange educational tours and perhaps summer camps. These activities should be combined with an intensive course in English. It is understood that one of the boys is studying at an Egyptian Law College. \s Egyptian law is founded on the code Napoleon and its study involves considerable knowledge of French it is difficult to see how this boy's labours will benefit him or the State on his return to Kuwait, and the Adviser should take particular care to see that boys are directed into avenues of study which will give them knowledge of use to them in their own country. The fact that the Kuwait Education Department wish olitical *gent, Kuwait. G.A. hNo. C/455 POLITICAL AGENCY, KN7AIT. the 14th May, 1945 To K. M. Yilley Esquire, Director of Education Bahrain. Dear Sir, The Kuwait Education Department have decided to retain the services of Ustadh .Ahmed Sadeq Hamdi, the present Director of education, for a further period of one year. 2 . I shall he grateful if the authorities concerned he requested to sanction the renewal of his contract for another year. Yours faithfullyQIL^ Tr^nsl^tion of letter No.R.6.2835 iatei the )|2ni May,1943 from H.H. the Rulerof Kuwait, to the Political 4^ent, Kuwait. After Compliments, In reply y^^r letter No.C/146 iatei the 12th May,1943, I wish to inform you that I have instructed the Education Department here to arrange the nayment of the necessarv amounts required for the running in Cairo for the Kuwaiti Council in Cairo. Usual Ending. of the proposed hostel stident, to the British No y 2 .3 Date'i £&gt;'. \1*rom To No. Dated. EXPRESS LETTER. political Kuwait. Resident Bushire. C/483. 24th May, 1945. Reference paragraph 2 (a) of your express letter No. 360 - S of the 10th April, 1945. Kuwait education. 2 His Highness has informed me that he has instructed the Kuwait Education Department to arrange for the payment of the amounts required for the running of / the proposed hostel for Kuwaiti students in Cairo to the British council there.Telegram G. T. C. From political Resident., Bushire To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 990. Dated. 26th received 27th May, 1945. Your express letter No. 449 May 12th. 2. Have you obtained assurance requested in paragraph 2 (a) of my express letter No. 360 - 3 dated April 10th 0 GallowayTelegram Trora To No. 494. Dated. 29th May, 1945. G. T. C. Political \gent, Kuwait. Political Besident, Bushire. V Beference your telegram No. 990 May 26th. Kuwait Education. 2. His Highness has informed me that he has instructed the Kuwait Education Department to arrange for the payment of the amounts required for the running of the proposed hostel for Kuwaiti students in Cairo to the British Council there. = Political =s 2. I will write to the Ministry of education, Cairo, asking for their sanction for the renewal of the Director's contract# 3. I see that you addressed the letter to K#M.Willey Esq. So far we have no news of him except an unofficial message that he left England on 30th.April 4. will you please pass on the enclosed to the Director. Captn.ivi.P. 0. C. Tandy, H.B.M's Political Agent, Kuwait.2. 1 have written to the British Council, London asking them to send you the periodicals mentioned direct by post. I have also requested their Books Department to supply you quarterly with a selestion of books similar to those that we receive in Bahrain. No charge is made for these. Captn.M.P.O.C.Tandy, H.B.M’s Politics! Agent, Kuwait.Ref. P&amp;/I Dear Sir, THE BRITISH COUNCIL MIDDLE EAST OFFICE, 138, SHARIA FUAD EL AWAL, ZAMALEK, CAIRO. Attached please find our official receipt No.I 367 for L.E. 41.750 in settlement of the account for books as per our statement of 22nd June,1944 to H.B.M. Political Agent,Kuweit. Yours faithfully, B.Kanarian. Accountant Books Department. Passed on to : Political Agent, F.J.Wa£elin Esq., Director of Educa-tion, Bahrein, Persian Gulf. 8863/ PM EB/1 -5/44AliVuirwlL % C0FY * ( p 0R Political Agent, Kuwait). EASTERN GULP COMPANY, LTD. Kuwait, Arabia. i&amp;rch 13, 1945 Mr• F. J.Viakelin, Educational Adviser Bahrain Persian Gulf jdeer ^.Vi&amp;kelin; I was please to rfccetVe your letter of i&amp;rch 11 and was most interested in the inforiaation included therein. I have written to our people in the United States andiiave asked them to do everything that they possibly can in order to obtain and ship six second -hand typewriters which we would like to donate to the schools here in Kuwait. We of course realise that the typewriter production in the United States has been severely curtailed for a number of years andthat in general the typewriter situation there is rather critical. Nevertheless we hope that we may be fortunate enough to obtain the machine s requested as we most certainly would lika to aid the Kuwait schools in this respect. It is apparent that good work is being done ,in rather difficult times with the r extension of Education and I sinceraly trust that this good workwiil continue. Sincerely yours. HVS/L T.E.Patrick General Superintendent-3,0 ^ &lt; - U'i' No. 345/41. Government of Bahrain, Education Department. 20th.May 1945. i&lt;f&gt;' Kamal Saleh Ahdou. In the summer of 1943 Kamal Saleh Abdou, an Egyptian teacher, was engaged by the Kuwait Education Committee. According to the engagement letter given him by me orfcehalf o# the Committee he was entitled to a second class passage from Kuwait to Cairo at the end of his contract. In June 1944 he was, at my suggestion, sent back to Cairo where I reengaged him for Bahrain. (See paragraph 6 of my report of 26th.April 1944). The Kuwait Government did not pay his fare from Kuwait to Cairo to which I consider hfi is entitled. Tills matter has only recently been brought to my notice. Will you please take it up with the Committee and urge that it be settled speedily. Captain M.P.O.C.Tandy, H.B.M 1 s Political Agent, Kuwait.LETTER SENT IN xiRABIC TO: All Essawi Salman Sabir A1 Gamr Ahmed Thabit Mohd. Abdul Moneim A1 Bulchin Abdul Ghani Ali Abdul Gawad Ahmed A1 Tuhami A1 Shenawi Alimad Gowdat Usman Abdul Q.adir A1 Saad Zaki Kohamed Abul Nasr. school teacher where you will be offered a contract X1LK including the following conditions: 1. ) The contract shall be for two years. 2. ) The Kuwait Government shall pay you a salary of .€.12 per month. 3. ) The Kuwait Government shall provide you with a second class passage from Cairo to Kuwait at the beginning of your contract and from Kuwait to Cairo at its conclusion. 4. ) The Kuwait Government shall provide you with free unfurnished % quarters or an allowance in lieu thereof• 5. ) The Kuwait Government shall pay you a cost-of-living Allowance which may vary from time to time. If you will call at this office on Thursday 9th September at 10.0 a.m., I will hand you the sum of €.37 This is made up of €.25 to cover your fare to Kuweit and €.12 being an advance of salary which is repayable to the &amp;uweit Government in not more than nine monthly installments. 8th September, 1943 Dear Sir You have been selected to go to Kuweit as a Yours faithfully, (Signed) F. J. Wakelin, Educational Adviser to Kuweit Government^o- 3 ■ 4^- Bahrain, 26th.May 1945. Itar Tandy, _ Just as I was sealing up my letter to you this very ielsted epistle arrived. Some bright clerk in Cairo had addressed t to Tehran! Can you wire the committee's reaction? Yours sincerelyBritish institute. 3,Sikket al Maghraby, Cairo. INS/21/1 - Hostel. r lO ' r “ My deer Wakelin, I enclose herewith an estimate for the setting up of a hostel for Kuwait stud nts. It has been worked out on the basis that there will be 30^ You will observe that the amount estimated of LE.10,000 is to be^?D:en as low and will only incl ide the minimum requirements; moreover, ohe standard of equipment will not be high. The figure as given in these papers does not include the rent, which is likely to be high, but at the moment in uairo accomodation id so restricted that it is impossible to make any move towards a building or a flat and therefore I am not prepared to give you any estimate for this. Having considered the figures, your next step should be to write officially to the Ministry of Education here asking them to assist you to get accomodation. This Ministry is able to make demands o&amp; t&amp;e Military Governer, who is all powerful in the allocation of accomodation. Obviously I cannot make any move in this direction unless the Kuwait Government is prepared to contribute the LE.10,000 plus the rent. It may be that Abdel Aziz Hussein has already sent some estimate based on the Saudi Arabian Hostel and the Moroccan Hostel. I do not know the latter. He may also have mentioned the Sudanese Hostel, but as this was a gift of the King one cannot drew any useful information from it. I may say that I have already approached the Technical Adviser, Shafik Bey Ghorbal, who indicate^ that an official request might meet with some success for accomodation, and he added chat they would very much prefer the students from Kuwait to be housed in a building and not included in the boarding accomodation of the Egyptian Secondary Schools. I should be very grateful if you would examine all this and let me know ps soon as oossible so that I can give you further help to lay plans for next year and it may be possible for you to go into definite and final negociations when you pass through here in July. BBS Incidentaly I diould say that I expect to be leaving for England in May. 12th.April 1945. (Received 26/5/45 via iehran). Signed: R.W.Highwood. Mr.F. J.Wakelin,E Director of Education, Bahrain. DirectorSummary of Estimate for Furniture k Yearly Lodging and Boarding expenses for 40 students. I Furniture &amp;&gt; Equipment II Board &amp; Lodging III Clothing IV pocket Money V Washing* Ironing, shaving etc. VI Housekeeping 8c Maintenance VII General Expenses £g # m/Ms. 24£7.500 3732.000 1000.000 960.000 480.000 300.00C 900.000 £ 9859.500 It will be remembered that the total does not provide for Rent and the figures, which are subject to changes, are taicen after the lowes quotations.- 2 - II BOARD ou LODGING* Rent Light &amp; /fater Food - cost for each Clerk's salary Cook’s ' Cook’s assistant &amp; ’Vaiter 2 Servants salary 1 Messenger w Door keeper ' per month w ^S^m/ms, &amp;.000 5.000 Monthly Expenses Yearly Expenses not including Rent III CLOTHING. Yearly cost for each Total for 40 students 25.000 TV POCKET MONEY. At the rate of per student per month 80.000 Yearly total for 40 Stud. Y WASHING» IRONING. SHAVING etc , At the rate of €1 per student per month Yearly total for 40 students -VI HOUSEKEEPING &amp; MAINTENANCE . ♦ Yearly expenses 40.000 VII GENERAL EXPENSES. Medical Treatment Excursions Sundries &amp; General Reserve Yearly Expenses € 200.000 200.000 500*. 000 300.000 900.000Usual Ending. 354v ^ VA Translation of letter No.R/6/2854 dated ute 8th June, 1945, from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent Kuwait. ° * I have acxyiowledged the receipt of your letter No.J/183 dated the 3rd June 1945, in which you refer that the Egyptian teacher Kamal Saleh Abdou was not paid by the Education Department the cost of the second class passage from Kuwait to Cairo according to the agreement with him. 1 therefore wish to inform you that I La/e ordered the Education Department to give a reply and I enclose herewith the letter received from them enclosing a bank draft 1 ^ .~*10 / “ in settlement of Kamal Abdou f s account as explained in their letter. CONFWEh Kmr /i • 4 ■ ^i&gt; After Compliments(? Translation of letter No.122 dated the'’ 5 '’' ^4-6-04(5-6-45) from the Education Department Kuwait, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments, 7e have the honour to submit the approval of the Education Department of Kamal Saleh Abdou’s demand in respect of the cost of return passage from Cairo to Kuwait m reply to the Political Agent f s letter No.0/183 dated the 3rd June, 1945. It appears that the said teacher v/as spent on him at the termination of the schoois last year a travelling allowance of / t s , the ti ? ket passage is fixed.at balance will therefore remain - which is enclosed herewith by bank draft No.57/43. Usual Ending.Translation of letter No.R/6/2857 dated the 9th June, 1945, from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. After Compliments, confidential i No Dated 11 • .4 I forward herewith a letter, in original, from the Education Department here requesting for the intervention to the Egyptian Ministry of Education and also to His Excellency the Military Administrator of the Egyptian Government to permit them to rent a house in Cairo for the boarding of the Kuwaiti students there. Usual EndingTranslation of letter No.119 dated the 21-6-1364 (2-6-45) from the Education Department, Kuwait, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments, I have the honour to request Your Highness to intervene to the Egyptian Ministry of Education and also to His Excellency the Military Administrator of the Egyptian Government to facilitate the finding of a SHitahi® house to be suitable for boarding tl e Kuwaiti students in Egypt according to the decision of the Kuwait Education Department. I hope this decision will meet Your Highness T approval. Usual EndingTranslation of letter No.R/6/2860 dated the 9th June, 1945, from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. I have ^apfcnowledged the receipt of your letter No.G/184 dated the 3rd June, 1945, enclosing a statement giving details of the approximate expenses for the boarding which the Kuwait Education Department determine on renting for the Kuwaiti students residing in Egypt. fojvard herewith a letter received from the Education Department in this respect. The letter is self-explanatory. After Compliments I wish to offer our thanKs for this and Usual Ending . ■f *&gt;2. -Translation of letter No.123 dated the 24-6-64(5-6-45) from the Education Department, Kuwait, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments, 'Ye have the honour to submit to Your Highness the Education Committee's approval of undertaking the scheme of a Kuwait hostel for which the initial expenses comes to £.E.10,000/- excluding the yearly rent. It has been decided that £.E.6,000/- to be spent on the following items:- £.E.2500/- to furnish the Kuwait hostel according to the estimate made by the British Council. ^£.E.1500/- yearly rent for the hostel according to the estimate made by the Education Committee, Kuwait. £.E.2000/- current account to be spent on the following items for the scholar year 1945-46. ^(a) Pocket money for the second bursary members starting first of -July, 1945 till the execution of the new order which is to be followed when the Kuwait hostel is opened. (b) School books and books for the Education library and Hestetner and other articles for the schools of girls and small children. (c) Travelling expenses for all the new teachers and mistresses who will be employed in the Kuwait Education Department, and also for those who have renewed their contracts of the former teachers. As to the other expenses needed for the administration of the hostel and food etc. would be paid by the Education Department by three advanced yearly instalments and the first payment will be made just by notifying the Committee that the hostel has been finally rented. Eormarly the Kuwait Education Department negotiated the Egyptian Government officially to facilitate in finding a lodging for the Kuwaiti students in Cairo. Kuwait Government Education Committee thanks the British Council in Cairo for their thankful exertion on their assistance and asks special request from the British Council in Cairo to facilitate the financial task of the Kuwait Education Committee as much as they can. Usual Ending.Translation of letter No.R/6/2862 dated the 10th Tune, 1945, from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political A.gent, Kuwait. With reference to the conversation with my Secretary according to my order on the 9th Tune, 1945, in respect of our order to Mr. Ahmed Sadiq Hamdi to undertake the task of renLing and furnishing a hostel for the Kuwaiti students in Egypt and have the pleasure of enclosing a letter, in original, received from our Education Department in this connection. The letter is self-explanatory. Therefore we request that after having gone through the Education Department’s request to inform us of your opinion. After Compliments, Usual EndingT ^ n3lat:l - orl of letter No. 131 dated the 23(1:11 29-5-64 (10-6-45) from the Kuwait Education Department, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments, v t— • have tile great pleasure to submit to ..our Highness the Education ComMttee’s decision 1 ? eetin S of the 29 th lamad Al-Thani 13o4 in which agreed that Mr. Ahmed Sadiq Hamdi Director of Education, is to undertake the * establishment of a hostel and all the affairs of Education Department in Egypt and have given iim a full power in these cases, owing to the absence of Messrs. Highwood and '/akelin during this summer and due to the fact that no other° person to undertake the abovementioned affair of ohe Education Department there. This power will concinue till Mr. Highwood returns. r e request the British Council in Cairo o render him all the assistance which we trust they will render always to the Director of Education. „ tT . this suggestion is acceptable to :our Highness we beg your approval on it. Usual Ending.D.O.No. C/541 POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. the 13th June, 1945 /r7o ’ty dear Willey, , , Please refer to Wakelin’s demi-official letter No. 345/41 of the 20th iiay, 1945, regarding Kamal Saleh /'.hdou's fare from Kuwait to Cairo. £ 15/- against his travelling allowance and enclose a cheque No. 57/43 for the halance of £ 10A which I forward herewith. I notice, however, that he is not one of the persons to whom the enclosure to your letter under reference was addressed. 2 The Kuv7ait Education Denartment state that they advanced Kamal Saleh Ahdou the sum of Yours sincerely K. M. Willey, Esquire, Director of Education Bahrain. G.A.MTelegram ITrom To No. 545. Dated. 13tii June, 1945. Enel. Political 4.gent, Kuwait. 'Tilley Director of Education, Bahrain. Reference Takelins letter d^.ted ?Iay 26tn. 2. Kuwait Government agree. 3 . They understand that neither Highwood nor Takelin will he hack in Cairo until Ceptemher and do not wish to wait until then for house to he selected. 4. TTill you therefore please arrange for Ministry of Education and Military Governor to assist Hamdi to rent a suitable building as xhostel. ' - Political =• -V U\)i CONFIDENTIAL Telegram Trom To Repeated &gt; T o. 422. G-. T. C. qi ^ Dated Mt- bi&gt;. | Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. political Agent, Kuwait. Bated and received 14th June, 1945. 2+' 'Tilley took over as Director of Education from Takelin on June 10th. PoliticalCONFIDENTIAL . No. 590-S - ,/^7 \+ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain . The Political Agent, Kuwai: and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). Persian Gulf Residency, lkkisia&gt;15rwieitlais;G£H«3&amp;i;xBU S H IRE. Dated....3131. fv.ay 1945* Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Enclosures to Erabassy, Cairlo endorsement Ho. 1070/1/45, dated 2Rth Aoril. 1945. Subject. Admission of foreign students to Egyptian schools.• - junction fro. th. WbXlo Ui-i-W of . • osord to t» acoeptnnce of forolf. »t«l.»t» In chools. candidature A „„4. Q n is necessary that the ranAlxta* of foreign s u iho uld be from their Governments that have connections with ;he Egyptian Ministry of Foreign Affairs in this regard, and 10 individual request will be consider 2 . The requests must be sent to the Kgyptian 1 inistry of Foreign Affairs during a set time, ' lhj - ch ' ,li:L circumstances be extended. 3. All papers of the students that have reference to e r acceptance, and any. other papers, must be sent before e arrival of the students in Egypt) to the Ministry of or g ^ Affairs for careful scrutiny for the purpose of choos ng ^* 4-4 pntrv into the schools of who fulfil the conditions Ox Egypt.CONFIDENTIAL. §2?-3 /;3. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to ^ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). 2. To Bahrain only . It is requested that a translation of the Arabic be sent to us for record. Persian Gulf Residency, BUSHIRE. Dated... g.th--June,-•1&amp;45-4-* dated 31st May, 1945. The Political Agent, Bahrain . The Political Agent. Kuwait Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Enclosures to Embassy, Cairo, Printed Letter No. Admission of foreign students 1070/2/45, dated 15th May, into Egyptian schools. 1945.1 \ K/USl/l/ 1 V'' ^ H.H, CONph)HNT!Al. Government of Bahrain, Bducation Department. iSth.June 1945. Kuv'nil iu-ci'lfrl i iVo (o H if buir* Dear Lfejor Tandy, —^ ilr. Highwood, of the Britiah Institute in Cairo, has pointed ou + that one of their employees there has been looking after t'rve nuyait accounts in his spare time for the last ten months. These accounts have been fairly involved and had we engaged a special man to look aluei ..em, it would have cost about £ 8C. llr. Highwood suggests - and I support his suggestion - that the Kuwait Government might be willing to give this accountant a gratuity for £ 25 in recognition of his work. I hope you can arrange for this to be done. Tours sincerely, Major M.P.O.C. Tandy, H.B.M’s Political Agent, Kuwait. K.M. Wiliey Director of Education.NO.C/^/-? Political Agency, KUWAIT. The 30th June, 1945. To His Highness, Shaikh Sir Ahmed al Jahir As-Suhah, KOSX., KCI13., Euler of Kuwait. After compliments. I have the honour to forward your Highness a copy of Notes Nos., 178 and 197 dated the 19th April and the 2nd May, 1945,respectively from the Egyptian Ministry of Public Education. Usual ending. r / Major, Political Agent, 0 ^. KUWAIT . LB. / 'D.O. No. c/618. POLITICAL AGENCY,' KUWAIT. the 9th July, 1945, Jear It. 7illey, jbM 9, Please refer to your demi official letter No. K/HST/l/l of the 19th June, 1945, in connection with a proposal to pay an honorarium to the man who is looking after the Kuwait Government accounts in Cairo. 2. The Kuwait Government have approved of Mr. Highwood’s suggestion and have sent me a cheque for £ 25/- which I enclose. As ten months seems an inconvenient interval at which to make payments, I suggest that this sum be taken as covering the first year’s work of the accountant. 3. His Highness has asked me to take the opportunity of expressing his gratitude for the valuable assistance rendered by Mr. Highwood to the Kuwait Education Department and to the Kuwait students in Egypt. Yours sincerely, M. IVilley, Esquire, Director of Education, Bahrain.Government of BaiH* a in, Education Department. cue ca#ri*zuimu. op m: OP k+MKtS&amp;lQiB 26th* June 1945. the Governments of Bahrain and &amp; request for assistance. It is the desire o# both governments to establish in Cairo hostels for students fro* these two countries, so that those Zs who are already studying at Egyptian Schools hyt£ vinri arranp-ement of Tour Excellency's Ministry, can live unaer Sropefc^fwith their compatriots. This will also relieve the Egyptian Schools which so far have had the courtesy to acce.t these boys as boarders • I should greatly appreciate theta if the attention of tho Mttter/ Governor could he directed to our need for house s Z this purpose .one for the Bahrain Hostel capable of accomm- odltiS 25 ^tudents and one for the Kuwait Host.lf orabout ZstuLnW. Without the assistance of Tour Excellency and the co-operation of the Military Governor, I am well aware that are unlikely to find suitable houses. Ahmed Handl bey, the Egyptian who is Director °f. Education in Kuwait, expects to be in Cairo ^ of Julv X myself expect to be there towards the end of July an with yoir permission shall give myself the pleasure of calling onyou at that time. Until then, X hope I may rely on the assistance of the Ministry of Education. I have the honour to remain. Excellency, Your obedient servant. H.E. Abdul Kaxzak Sanhoury Pash, Minister of Education, Ministry of Education, Cairo* K.M*Willey Director of Education, Adviser in Education, Bahrain Kuwait. Copy to: Political Agent, v x Kuwait. ► , y* « &gt;, /• ?■ ,Vc ?iVv S ! 11 tO *•' /Government of Bahrain, Education Department, 26th« June 1945* Excellency, I have been asked by the Governments of Bahrain and of Kuwait to approach you with a request for assistance. It is the desire o$ both governments to establish in Cairo hostels for students from these two countries, so that those boys who are already studying at Egyptian Schools by the iHnd arrangement of Your Excellency's Ministry, can live under proper carewith their compatriots. This will also relieve the Egjptian Schools which so far have had the courtesy to accept these boys as boarders* I should greatly appreciate them if the attention of the Military Governor could be directed to our need for houses for this purpose, one for the Bahrain Hostel capable of accomm odating 25 students and one for the Kuwait Hostel for abou 30 students. Without the assistance of Your Excellency and t. e co-operation of the Military Governor, I an well aware that we are unlikely to find suitable houses. Ahmed Hamdi bey, the Egyptian who is director of Education in Kuwait, expects to be in Cairo in the early par of July; I myself expect to be there towards the end of Julj an with your permission shall give myself the pleasure of calling on you at that time. Until then, I hope I may rely on the assistance of the Ministry of Education* I have the honour to remain. Excellency, Your obedient servant. ) H«B*Abdul Razzak Sanhoury Pash, Minister of Education, Ministry of Education, Cairo* K.M.Willey Director of Education. Bahrain Adviser in Education, Kuwait. Copy to: H.B.M’s Political Agent, ^ Kuwait. \i i . ..... V* f »; v $ j t' ./ ,:f : V.-■A'Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire, the 3rd July 1945 Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BI33HIRE , 2l:i8 British Gouncii Repres^ntatiY in the Middle iSast, JaIRO . Repeated - Political KUWAIT. Political . prom To No. 734-3• ijated the 3rd July 1945* Reference Mr • wak el in *e letter Ro.202/30 dated 22nd iiarch 1945, to Mr. Highwood on the subject of a hostel for Kuwait students* 2* The Bahrain Govcrnnieiit have also decided to open a hostel at Cairo for about 30 Bahrain students, and that Government has been asked to arrange for Mr* Willey to take up details with Mr. Hignwooi or other British Council official at Cairo. 3. in a recent memorandum cn education at Kuwait Mr. itfukelin reported that the Kuwait Government were very anxious for the appointment of a Supervisor provided by the British Council, to be resident in Cairo, who would supervise their hostel ir* Cairo (they will have their own Kuwaiti warden), kes F in touch with their students, engage teachers on behalf of the Kuwait Government and visit Kuwait to advise th*..!. They feel that the short visits of the Sixectox of Education Bahrain and Kuwait are inadequate to meet their rapidly growl rig educational needs. 4* In your budget estim&amp;tos for Bahrain and Kuwait for the financial year 1945-46 provision was made under item C 1 for suoh a Supervisor, and I trust that sanction has bean accorded* Now that the Bahrain Government also are op ©ling a hostel at Cairo, tho need for such an appoint;r«nt is greater* 5* As there is already a resident director of Education in Bahrain the Supervisor in Cairo could perhaps pay visits to Kuwait to advise the educational authorities there, and thus relieve the official at Bahrain of this duty. 6* It is understood that the Egyptian schools oloss for four months in the summer, during, which the Persian Gulf students stay on in Cairo* The provision of a Supervisor would facilitate the arranging of educational tours, summer camps am possloly a special courte in Engli*h • Sd. A . C * GA1LG •* AT • Political Resident, Persian Gulf* ATTESTED* ' * CON FID KNT I Ao J_jti fbdr deoretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf RHLThe Undersigned, Acting British Consul at Damascus, presents his compliments to the British Political Agent at Koweit and with reference to his note of the 10th of Octoher, 1944, has the honour to recommend to his good offices Mr. Adnan Aidi, Principal of Ulmieh Watanieh School in Damascus, hearer of the present letter, for the grant of all such facilities as may he * consistent with the Regulations in force. facilities for students from Koweit who are receiving or wish to receive instruction at the Ulmieh Watanieh School. Mr. Aidi is visiting Koweit to arrangeThe Political Agent, Kuwait* MEMORANDUM. Reference paragraph 4 of your Express Letter No*449 dated 12th May 1945* Kuwait Education. 2* Please take up with the Educational Adviser, Bahrain and Kuwait, question of the provision by the British Council of plans for the proposed new schools. CONFIDES N* /^ t Y Date* _j Sd. A.C.GALLOWAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ATTESTED . for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. TSR.The Political Agency, Dated the 4th August, 1945 Subject: Decondary School for Kuwait I enclose an extract from my Express Letter No.449 dated the 12th May, 1945 to the Political Resident. Colonel Galloway has asked me to take up with you the question of provision of plans for the new school. 2. If the British Council could provide us v.ith suitable plans it would strengthen our hand when trying to divert some of the Shaikh^ anticipated income to this very laudable purpose. K.M. WILLEY, ESQUIRE, Director of Education, Government of Bahrain, Education DepartmentWith the compliments of the ACTING CONSUL, DAMASCUS. (Copy of letter of recommend ation given by the Damascus Consulate to Mr. Adnan Aidi, Principal of Ulmieh tfhtanieh School in Damascus).* The Undersigned, Acting British Consul British Political Agent at Koweit and with reference to his note of the 10th of October, / 1944, has the hone to reconmend to his good offices Mr. Adnan nidi. Principal of Ulmieh Watanieh School in Damascus, bearer of the present letter, for the grant of all such facilities as may be consistent with the Regulations in force. Mr. Aidi is visiting Koweit to arrange facilities for students from Koweit who are receiving or wish to receive instruction at the Ulmieh Watanieh School. at Damascus, presents his compliments to the /rQNTIDKXTIU,. No . C/128 . m &lt; v -«f , ffi . ^ ..,(}■ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait . and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). Tor necessary action and return of questionnaire direct to Cairo. Persian Gulf Residency, British Consulate-General* Camp, Chiraz. mUSHTRE. Dated 25th.. J.'AU r .&gt;. .124 5. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Enclosures to Cairo Printed Letter No. 185/7/45 dated 31st May, 1945. Subject. Questionnaires to be completed by Egyptian teachers in/Aden. j | 1CONFIDENTIAL EJLPJUL3J3 L^Kjr^T^EJl B3litioal f Kuwait To Galloway, Shiraz* Repeated Prodrome, Cairo. No.C/750. Dated the 13th August, 1945. Reference Embassy’s Printed Letter May, 1945 to Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Egyptian Teachers in Aden. As the teachers are now all in Egypt on recess it is suggested that the Egyptian Government be asEed to obtain the answers to the questionnaire from them direct. . &lt;3| V . /F No.185/7/45 dated 31st . m M — ( &lt;K&gt;) It will not be possible to obtain the answers here until October. LES\ O , l&lt;q w //. I9&amp; • No. Uojio d. Snjlluct ' P.A. Mr, Wakelin has raised the following points in his letter: 1. Conduct of Yusuf bin Mushari, 2. Modification of Articles 11 and 14 of the Staff Rules. 3. Payment of 11 months T salary to Shamlan at the time of dismissal. 4. Letters from the Director of Dducation to Mr.V/akelin to be sent through the Agency. 5. Return of Ahmad Edwani to Kuwait. 6. Further education Kir-aiti boys. 7. Remittances for the non mission students in Cairo and Alexandria. 8. Acknowledgment of boo^s from Cairo. Reference 1. No further action appears necessary. 2. He has already written to Shaikh Abdullah ,Tahir vide paragraph 5. 3. In the absence of the agreement between the Education Department and Shamlan it is very difficult to say whether Shamlan was given generous treatment or he received eleven months f salary in consideration of his long service. 4. ^his contradici* Mr. '/aKelin f s instructions to Ali Haikal - please also see para 6 of Hr. /akelin f s leoter to Shaikh Abdullah Jabir. 5. No action appears necessary. 6. Arrangements were made for 11 boys and it was agreed that their fees etc will be paid by the Egyptian Government. The Education Department sent 16 boys to Cairo and 1 to Alexandria. The expenses of these extra 6 boys are being paid by the Kuwait Government. I think it is too late to enquire from the Kuwait Government why 17 boys were sent when arrangements were made for 11 boys. 7. Remittances can be sent through us if you see no objection. 8. Noted.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000bc_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/197</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000bc</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/197</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/13 III Kuwait Education'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-02T22:14:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (419 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 421; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Two additional foliation sequences are present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence related to the development of education in Kuwait, specifically the activities of a British educational official named F J Wakelin, who was on secondment from the British Council and acting as adviser to the Governments of Bahrain and Kuwait at this time.A number of reports regarding Kuwait's educational system written by Wakelin are contained in the file. Topics discussed include the hiring of teachers from Egypt, educational reform and the role of the British Council. The appointment of a replacement for Wakelin in 1945 is briefly discussed towards the end of the file.In addition to correspondence between Wakelin and other British officials (notably the Political Agency in Kuwait), the file also contains a large amount of correspondence between him and the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jaber al-Sabah and Kuwait's Department of Education (much of which is in Arabic accompanied by English translations). A limited amount of correspondence between British officials in Egypt and the Egyptian Ministry of Foreign Affairs is also present (this is largely in French and occasionally in Arabic).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Education</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000bc#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>