<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000365.0x000388_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T14:06:16.843Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM* -«* I</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000365.0x000388_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/51</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x000388</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/51</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 1855/1904 Pt 9-10 'Koweit'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1903/1912</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-30T18:37:09</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (314 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.The subject 1855 (Koweit [Kuwait]) consists of five volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/47-51. The volumes are divided into ten parts, with parts 1 and 2 comprising one volume, parts 3 and 4 comprising the second volume, part 5 comprising the third volume, parts 6, 7, and 8 comprising the fourth volume, and parts 9 and 10 comprising the fifth volume.</extent><extent>Condition: there is evidence that two folios have been removed from this volume between ff 1-2 and ff 200-201; staining on folio 238 has caused the ink to fade and adversely affected the legibility of the text.Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 314; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out. The front cover, and one leading flyleaf have not been foliated.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains parts 9 and 10 of the subject 'Koweit' [Kuwait]:Part 9 (IOR/L/PS/10/51/1) concerns the rights of the Ruler of Kuwait to the islands of Bubiyan, Warba, and Umkasr [Umm Qaşr].Part 10 (IOR/L/PS/10/51/2) concerns the Ruler of Kuwait's relations with the Ottoman Empire, and his properties at Fao [Al Fāw] and Fadaghia.Each part includes a divider which gives the subject and part numbers, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references contained in that part by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.The date range gives the covering dates of all the documents in the volume; the Secret Department minute papers, which enclose those documents, are dated 1904-07.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to the Ottoman Empire</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Koweit</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x000388#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>