<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00024e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T15:35:06.753Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">♦of 1901 (») No. Prom, Captain P.Z.COX H.B.M.’s CONSUL &amp; POLITICAL ACxENT, To, MUSCAT. Lt-Colonel C.A.KEMBALL, t Offg: POLITICAL RESIDENT in the PERSIAN GULP, BUSHIRE. H.B.M.'s CONSULATE &amp; POLITICAL AGENCY. Dated Musdat 25rd July 1901. SIR, I have the honor to address you in the following connection:- At a recent interview the Sultan informed me that the ctiief members of the community’at Khor Pakan on the Batineh Coast had several times made .overtures to him, which they had just lately repeated,with a view to their port being again brought under Muscat jurisdiction^and His Highness asked for an ex pression of my personal views on the subject,both on its merits and with reference to the possibility of his having our support should the project eventually be taken up. I replied that my files contained something on this subject and that I should, like to look them up and if necessary make a reference to you before giving him a reply. 'Support* 1 would presumably mean the presence of one of our men-of-war if required. 2. Khor Pakan,as is doubtless within your knowledge is a collection of hamlets situated on the shores of a spa cious bay of the same name on the northern Batineh Coast, in lattitude 25°- 21 / - 15'N. and longitude 56 - 25. Broadly speaking I should say that the territories comprised inin the Sultanate of Oman are at present considered to extend irom .the Westerly limits of Dhofar on the South,to Khasab at the ex tremity of the Roos-el-Jubbal on the North,but the interjacent strip of coast line lying between the 25th and 26th parallels of latitudethas, from the days of the Wahabee incursions at the commencement of the last century,been the scene of frequent strife,in the course of which the ports along its shores have V* m several' times changed hands. As far as the Archives of this Agency enable me to state with any degree of accuracy the following are the chief land marks of Khor Fakan history during the last 100 years and I take the liberty ,of recording them for facility of reference;- 1808 . . . Seyyid Saeed bin Sultan, Imam of Muscat, assisted by his Uncle Kais besieged and reduced the port A which the Jowasmees had converted into a rendez- vous and depot in connection with their piratical enterprises in the Gulf. 1808 to 1852 . Khor Fakan ruled by the Jowasmee Chief, Sultan bin Sakar, in fief for the Imam of Muscat. Captain Brucks R.N. in his Memoir of the Navigation of the Gulf issued in 1827 writes 'It belongs to the Imam of 'Muscat whose nominal revenue from it is about '3000 German crowns.' 1852 . . . Sultan bin Sakar, taking advantage of the disturbed state of the Imam Saeed bin Sultan's affairs, as similated Khor Fakan and other adjacent ports and held the *for himself. A 18&lt;S&amp;o 1851 . After 1852 the Imam and the Jowasmee Chief seem to have made up their differences and the latter returned to his allegiance to Seyyid Saeed's suc- iAsy*-C\JL - cessor, Seyyid Thpweynee (&lt;fe?«aardfather of Seyyid Feisal) for it appears that in 1850 when Kais bin Azzan attacked and captured Khor Fakan from Sul tan bin Sakar the latter appealed to the Sultan of Muscat, Seyyid Thoweynee bin Saeed^for assis tance. The Sultan however informed his vassal that he was too busily employed elsewhere to make * anyany diversion in his favour and -bhati he, Sultan bin Sakar,must manage the business himself. The Jowas- mee thereupon determined to try his fortune alone ■ i*j :.Z fiex ; el and was successful in recovering Khor Fakan from Kais. Although Seyyid Thoweynee's inability to come to the Jowasmee's assistance in his hour of need became the cause of temporary estrangement iso o ;io.~; -c* . %, between them they soon became reconcildd but $ey- OJ 'to C . J Oyl.'l- J n 0 V 0 . ' »'• r.j : ’ • • ‘ ; '* f yid Thoweynee did not apparently trouble himself c. • j ;. ~oo c nr i 70 c after this with the affairs of the Northern Bati- neh ports and from that period up to the present they have remained under the domination of the Jowasmee Shaikhs. o . i . . ; ■ t o ■ n. - ’.sui •'rrt u ... 3. So much for past history. His Highness Seyyid Fei sal informed me that he believed that the community now pay no tribute to the Jowasmee Shaikh, but it can hardly be that the present Shaikh of Shargah would view with equanimity any attempt on the part of the Ruler of Muscat to re—assert him self in that quarter and in view of the decided opinion ex pressed by Colonel Miles as Resident in Residency letter No.Ill dated 6th July 1886,1 should not think it necessary to trouble you with a reference,were it not that the general position has been a good deal changed since that correspon dence took place by the increased interest taken by &lt;: /a. evs in the politics of the Gulf. 4 4 . Under existing conditions it is theoretically in the interests of British policy that the Ruler of Muscat should extend or re-assert his effective influence and juris^ diction as far as he reasonably can,in order that as much oi the coast-line of Oman as possible may be brought within the limits of the territory which we can claim,as against France. to be covered by the declaration of 1862, by which our res pective Governments mutually agreed to respect the Sultan's independence. Otherwise there would seem to be nothing to prevent France or any other Foreign Power ^rom acting on the presumption that the ports on the strip oi coast—line beiore specifiedspecified were either communities independent individually ,or else that they were collectively subject to an independent Jpw- asmee Shaikh. In this connection I have the honor to attach in original for information one of a series of letters which ap- x /s peared some weeks ago in the Depeche Coloniale and which are believed to have emanated from Muscat,from a perusal of which it will appear that the locality in question has not escaped the specific attention of our neighbours. I may mention also that the yacht ’'Selika” touched both at Khor Fakan and Dibba in the course of her recent sojourn in these waters. In conclusion it seems to be a point worthy of consideration whether we could exercise more influence over the locality in * • * k i, question as part of the Muscat Sultanate or as an appanage of *.l. Sf; -i the Jowasmee Chief. Trusting to be favoured with your views and instructions at ) I an early date. I have the honor to be. SIR, Your mo 1 t servant. Captain, H.B.M.’s CONSUL &amp; POLITICAL AGENT, MUSCATMUSCAT Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 285, dated 23rd July,1901, and to forward for your information copy of a letter which I have addressed to the Government of India on the subject. I am instructing the Residency Agent at Shargah to ascertain quietly how the Shargah Chief looks on the matter of his possessions on the Batineh Coast and what tribute he now gets out of the various places. I shall be obliged if you will inform me more exactly as to the limits of the Sultan's possessions North of Dibba. KhassabKhassab I understand to be on the western siae of i / Cape Ihissendum . Is not Bokha which appears to be just to the South of it also an appanage of Muscat ? Does the Sultan exercise any effective authority over the part of the Coast North of Dibba I think it is highly advisable that Khor Fakan f Dibba and Lima should be visit ea by one of His Majesty's ships, and I shall be obliged if you will ask the Commander of the next ship of war which visits Muscat and may be available for the work to visit these places. It is possible that he may be able to find out what the 'Selika' did there. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant j Offg; Political Resiaent in the Persian Gulf.(COPY) (sOrtjUs -c£.e-n / No: of 1901. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bush i re , ^Augus t 1901 . From Lieut-Colonel C % A. Kemhall, Offg . Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To H. S. Barnes Esquire,C.S.1., Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, SIMLA . \ Sir, I have the honour to forward, for the information of the Government of India, copy of a report submitted by Captain Cox, Political Agent at Muscat, on the subject of a place called Khor Fakan on the Batineh Coast of the Gulf of Oman. I am at present only in a position to submit an ad-interim report on the subject, but the matter is one of consider able importance and it is advisable that the Government of—~— • of India should know of the reference which has been made to me on the subject. 2. So far as the question of the right of jurisdic- Co Cm Ci^&gt;— tion over Khor Fakan k there can,I think,be no doubt. This place is undoubtedly an appanage of the Joasmee Chief of Shargah, who has certain rights over the strip of the Batineh Coast from Dibba on the North to Khor Kelbeh on the South,Khor Fakan being situated about midway / between these two places. I would invite a reference to the correspondence ending vnth the letter No: - 2188 E.P., dated 17th September,1881, from the Under* Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department to the address of the Resident in the Persian Gulf, in which Colonel Ross's view that the strip of Coast above alluaed should be considered subject to the operation of the Maritime Truce, was acceptea by the Government of India. I am instituting inquiries with a view to ascertaining the degree of authority which the Joasmee Chief maintains along this stretch of Coast, and at present I can only express my opinion that this Chief would certainly not view with equanimity any attempt of the Muscat Ruler to assert himself in that quarter, while on our part^the factc 4 - &lt;r i ^ ' % 2 fact that we have held this strip of the Batineh Coast to be subject to the Maritime Truce and prevented the Joasmee Chief from taking action by sea to assert his authority there, would certainly I think debar us from giving the Sultan any countenance or support in the matter. Any ex tension of the Sultan's rule over this part of the Coast could only be obtained by means of friendly agreement between His Highness and the Joasmee Chief. If the Sultan desires to bring this region again under Muscat control, he might, if the Government of India approve, be author ized to submit proposals through the Political Agent, Muscat, which I could refer to the Shargah Chief for an expression of his vievjs on the subject. Although the acquisition by a foreign power of Khor Fakan or other places on this Coast belonging to the Shargah Chief would not be allovjed by us in view of our Agreement of 1802 with this Chief, it might,! think be more convenient that the whole stretch of Coast from ^ fuse at to Mussendum should be subordinate to the Muscat Ruler. ' V _ The extract from the Depeche Coloniale forwarded by Captain Cox is of considerable interest. It will be seen that Dibba (Deba) and Lima are both alluded to as excellent anchorages and apparently as outside the Sultan's dominions^ i i i Lima_ Lima will be found described at page 621 of the Bombay Government Records No. XXIV, new series, and Dibbah at page 623. Lima is considerea by us to be within the territories of the Sultan of Muscat but I am not avjare what degree of authority he exercises over the portion of the Coast line from Dibba North to Khasab. The 'Selika*, I believe, spent some time at Dibba. It has been very difficult to ascertain what this yacht really came up the Gulf for / and vlhat she did here}, but her movements were,! consider distinctly / suspicious. I hear on good authority that she is again to come to the Gulf this Winter, but I propose to make this a subject for a special report. Meanwhile, I think, it is highly desirable that one of His Majesty's ships should visit the Batineh Coast at an early date, calling in at Khor Fakan, Dibba and Lima. Her Commander ' * may be able to ascertain what the Selika did at these places . I have instructed the Political Agent, Muscat, to arrange for this being done on the first suitable opportunity of one of His Majesty's ships visiting Muscat.mm I have etc' ( Sd ) C. A. Kemball, * Offg : Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Extract from a Report of Proceedings dated 11th Sept 1901, from Captain //. A. Phillipps ,R.N., Commanding S. Sphinx”, to Lieut-Colcnel C. A. Kemhall, Offa: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, o. + + + ana so proceeded to Lina where J arrived at 9 APR on the 10th, and also visited Dihla and Khar Fakan the same day. 7 ‘ 171 WJ op^on,neither of these places would he suit- able for a coaling station, as they are all open to the northward, and a very heavy sea would run in on the occas of a shamal blowing. Fi ve miles to the north of Dihla is a very snug little land-locked cove called Duhat Raff a, and in my opinion a coaling station could he maade there. unsuitable Tor vem J V8r y 10 ng ships,as it is , **•''**' ** «&lt;”•* I. anchors mt.Ue In 10 fathom ‘ protected from the ehamal. &gt;• 1'thla mas the only place the Selna- vtsited. the Sh„Hh reporting that hen machinery had trope, dome, ^ Officers of the ship used to lard,tut he did not see them ose any instruments for surrey,ng a ,d he third It would be theyNo: //Z of 1901. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bush i re , ^September 1901 . A copy of the foregoing extract is forwarded to If. B, M's. Consul and Political Agent .Muscat t for informa- tion^with reference to this Office Confidential letter No: 96 dated 16th August 1901. B&gt;y Order. /ZtV uy First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Confidential No. 509. of 1901. To Lieutenant Colonel C.A. Kemball Officiating Resident Bushire. Dated Muscat August 7th: 1901 Sir I have the honour to forward Foreign Department letter No. 1255 F.A. dated received this day under flying seal to your address. Copies have been retained in this office. (2) Inview of the purport of it I respectfully suggest the advisability of referring to the Government of India the cuestion dealt with in this office letter No. 285 dated 25rd July 1900. to your address. In that connection perhaps it is well that I should emphasize the fact that I was only speaking accurately (as far as the investigation of available records enabled me) with regard to the particular of coastline between Khor Fakan and Limeh and that my observations with regard to the ac cepted northern limits of the Sultanate of Muscat must be taken 'oroadly” and may require modifying after further investigation of that particular question. I shall make the report now called for in due course. I I have the honour etcCONFIDENTIAL. No.1253 E.A, From, The Under SECRETAKY to the GOVERNMENT of INDIA in the FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. To, t Lt-Colonel C.A.KEMBALL POLITICAL RESIDENT in the PERSIAN GULP. ( Under flying seal to the Political Agent Muscat.) Dated Simla the 25th July 1901. SIR, In continuation of my letter No.690 E.A.dated the 1st May 1901 I am directed to forward a copy of the marginal ly noted correspondence on the subject of the selection of a . naval base in the Per- Secret dispatch to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India No.66 External dated the 2nd sian Gulf. 1901. Secret dispatch from ditto No.15 dated the L4Ua the114th June 1901. t-: :- l-.d - ^ ic 1901. 2. I am to request that you will fTarnish an early re port upon the points noticed by the Secretary ,of State and that you will at the same time favour the Government of In dia with suggestions as to an^ measures of preparation which might in your opinion be quietly taken in anticipation of the contingencies to which this correspondence refers. Cap tain Cox should be directed to submit a report as to the ac tual limits if Muscat territory beyond Sohar in the direc tion of Cape Mosandim. So far as the Government of India Jr are aware the Sultan of Muscat has neither exercised nor | claimed authority over the isthmus of Maklab and the promon tory beyond It,which is understood to be inhabited by aborig_ jinal and independent tribes. I have etc Sd/ J.B.WOOD Under Secretary to the Government of India. uL ^&lt;&gt;Y )$C|V c If W '-4 &gt;- * M y 9 y &amp; No,66 of 1901. GOVERNMENT of INDIA. FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. SECRET EXTERNAL. To, The Right Hon’ble LORD GEORGE F.HAMILTON, His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Simla the 2nd May 1901. MY LORD, With reference to Jour Lordship's secret dispatch No. 30 date the 23rd November 1900,regarding the selection of a British Naval base in the Persian Gulf,we have the honor to fcrward a copy of a letter from our Political Resident in the Persian Gulf which No. 17 dated 1st February 1901 with ends. gives cover to a repbrt upon the islands of Hormuz,Kishm and Henjam by Lieu- tanant Hunt who was till lately Vice Consul at Bunder Abbas. 2. We are strongly of opinion that in the event of the Russians occupying Bunder Abbas or any other Persian .har- bournear the entrance of the Gulf or acquiring political or naval priveleges there such as would constitute a violation of the understanding of 1834 our Naval Officer Commanding in the Gulf should have instructions at once to plant the British fzlag upon the three islands of Hormus Henjam and Kishm. We would occupy Hormuz not with the idea of making it our princi pal naval station but in order to prevent its being taken by Rasia,and because its possession would give us command of Bun- dB'r Abbas. Henjam and Kishm in our opinion must necessarily be taken together. The smaller isalnd is required because the best available harbour in this part of the Gulf appears to be that which lies between it and Kishm and Kishm is necessary to us because we already possess a plot of British territory upon it at Bassidore,and because it would be indispensable as a base of supplies for Henjam.. Your Lordship is aware of the Vide the Viceroy's telegram of the 18th March conditions under 1899. which we holdJt M K Q 1 possession of Bassidore. Though we no longer use the place as a coaling depot we keep an agent there who flies the Bri tish flag, which seems, for the present,to be all that is re quired, as an assertion of our pproprietary rights. There are no independent local chiefs or authorities in the islands with whom we could enter into relations. With the exception of the tract in our possession at Bassidore the islands are under Persian authority and since Lieutenant'Hunt*s visit the Kalantar of Kishin. Sheikh Hasan, is said'to have been superse ded at the instance of the Director General of Customs in Southern Persia by another official. The Harbour of Khorash Shem or Elphinstone's inlet upon the Western side of the Musandim promontory possesses many advan tages but we consider it less suitable for our ultimate na val station at the mouth of the Gulf because of its distance from the main track ,of steamers and from the Persian Coast, its total lack of supplies,and the uncivilised character of the aboriginal inhabitants of Musandim. We should however see no objection,in the contingency comtemplated, to the si multaneous hoisting of the British flag on the isthmus of Maklab between Khorash Shem and Ghubbeh Ghazireh,not neces sarily with the view of ulterior occupation,but in order to &lt; anticipate seizure by any other power. The isthmus might we think be annexed without seeking permission either from the Sultan of Muscat or from the Arab tribes in the same manner a-s it was occupied by the Eastern Telegraph Company in 1869. We have etc ^ (Sd/-) CTJRZON ' A. P. PALMER. ' C.M.RIVAZ ' T.RALEIGH. M E.F.G.LAW. ' E.R.ELLES.INDIA OFFICE. LONDON 14th' JUNE 1901. SECRET NO. 15. To, HIS EXCELLENCY THE RIG-HT HONOURABLE THE GOVERNOR GENERAL OF INDIA IN COUNCIL. MY LORD, I have received your letter No.66 (Foreign Secret) .of Persian Gulf:Selection^ of a naval base. the 2nd May, on the subject of the selection of a naval base' in the Persian Gulf in view oi certain contingencies. 8.1 have communicated a copy of Your Excellency’s Letter to the Foreign Oxidce,but there are certain points upon which X request that you will furnish me with further information. 3. There appears to be some doubt as to the exact position of the Kalantar in the islands of Kishm and Henjam. He is spoken of in Lieutenant Hunt's report as if he were practically betond the control of the Naib Governor of Bunder Abbas of whose district the islands are nominally an appanage. On the other hand it is stated in your letter that Sheikh Hassan who was Kalantar when Lieutenant Hunt wrote 'is said' to have since been superseded. It is of importance that' the local conditions .of the various places should be definitely ascertained,and,in particular, whe- oher the position of the Kalantar Is hereditary,and of suffi cient practical independence to make an arrangement with him possible and politically advisable, or whether he is merely liable to removal at any time by the Persian Government. 4*&gt; As to the isthmus of Maklab, I do not clearly understand whether it iorms a part of the undoubted territories of the Sul tan of Muscat or whether the Arab tribes of the locality claim independence. In the former case the action suggested by Your Excellency's Government might in some circumstances raise a question with the French Government under the Anglo-French De claration of 1862. I commend lurther to? Your Excellency's consideration the questionhow far measures of preparation could be quietly taken in anticipation of the contingencies to which this correspon dence refers. I have etc Sd/ GEORGE HAMILTONConfidential. No. 334 of 1901. / o ^ To, The Resident August 28th: 1S01 Sir, I have the honour to submit the report called for in para. 2 of Foreign Department letter No.1253 E.A. dated 15th: July 1901 to your address on the subject of the selec tion of a naval base in these waters. (.2.) In dealing with the several ports or stretches of coas£ line I will commence with Sohar and proceed northwards. SOHAR. is governed by a Wali appointed by the Sultan and owing to the extent of its jurisdiction this governship is looked upon as an influ ential and important one. Treating of the coast-line only, the authority of the l Tali MAJIS. extents to Majis, Shinas, and to the coast SHINAS. villages from thence as far as Mureir. At mureir. Shinas a deputy 'Va] i is entertained who is appointed from Muscat but for ordinary pur poses of administeration is under the imme diate orders of the governor of Sohar. The reason of Shina^. being thus- selected among other small ports in the neighbourhood for the location of a special official is, no doubt that there are 8 or 9 British Indian traders resident there. At the other seaside villages jurisdiction is exercised through the local tribal shaikhs, and there are no British subjects north of Shinas. The tract between Mureir and Dibba, including KHOR KAIjBEH Khor Kalbeh, Fujaireh, and Khor Fakan, has FUJAIREH for a good many years at all events been KHOR FAKAN subject to to Jowasmee influence but this locality was dealt with in detail in my re cent letter No. 285 to your address on the subject of the Sultan's desire to reassert Muscat influence over the lastnamed port; it seems unnecessary therefore for me to do morf than refer to that correspondence now.r m ♦ . 'DIBBA. With rogcird Dibba however it will be advisable to enter into some detail, as mentioned in this office Political Diary for the week Sth July I called at ^-bba in H.M.*s S. 'Assaye* on 5th: July, but at that time I had no knowledge of the aspirations of H.H. the Sultan in connection with FZhor Fakan, or of the possible selection of a naval base by the British Government in those waters I was merely prompted to visit the place, which is a convenient night's run from Sohar, by the reference to it in the article in the D^peche Coloniale which was forwarded to you with my letter No.285 above mentioned . I found the place occupied by two rival communities, whose habitations as is often the case in Oman are separated from one another; broad dry Wadi A running between them. On the one side are the Jowasmee governed by a negro Wali on behalf of Shaikh Ahmed bin Sultan el Kasmi now residing at SJaargah or Has el Khyma, and paying excise or some form of tribute to him. 6&gt;vthe other side live section of a tribe com monly known as the ’’Shihooh' though in books and maps I see the name is sometimes written 'Shihiyeen' . The two forms are merely alternative plurals of the same word ’’Shiheh'. Of the tribe as a whole I shall say further in a subsequent paragraph suffice it to state at this -juncture that the section inhabiting Dibba and the environs pay no tribute either to the Jowasmee Shaikh or to the Sultan of Muscat but pay a certain dues to their own local Shaikh Yasir bin Sanan, who however is not strictly speaking a Shihooh but a Kumazereh, a tribe which will find mention later in this report. It was the inhabitants at Dibba who informed me that the A ’’Selika' had visited their port and alsoKhor Fakan but I could not ascertain that she had done than /v use her dredging or sounding apparatus in the har bour. (.2.) Including the northern half of Dibba as above set forth, and from thence onwards through Lima round Masendum. the promontory of Masendum to Khasab, and. thence Khasab. almost to Ras el Khyma, and embracing all the hinterland north of a line joining Dibba and Ras el Khyma, the hill country and the ports are be lieved to be inhabited almost entirely by the Shi- hooh, and a small tribe dependent on thenuthe Kum- azireh, who believe live on the Musandum of the Maklab isthmus, at Kumzar and other hamlets. These Shihooh are a numerically powerful tribe numbering about 14000souls and are of Himyarite i.e. Yemeni origin. As a whole they are understood to profess allegiance to, and recognise the sover eignty of Seyyid Feisal, but IZhasab adjacent to the Maklab isthmus is the only one of their ports at which they pay H. Highness any tribute, here the Sultan has a T Vali appointed under the follow ing circumstances. About 10 years ago the section? of the Shihooh occupying Khasab could not agree among themselves and therefore applied to the Sul tan to send, them a '.Vali to maintain peace and ordev^* Seyyid Feisal complied and appointed a Muscat Arab of the Beni Ruwaheh tribe, named Kali4- bin Sanai Khasab ( continued ) to the post. This individual has remained in the appointment up to the present time and is allowed. to retain the dues which he levies amounting to Masendum 700 or 800 Dollars per annum as his salary. (.4.) As before mentioned incidentally the Masen dum peninsular is tenanted though scantily by the small tribe of Kumazereh. The origin of this trib£ is a matter of a good deal of doubt and interest.“ ~ They are simply called 'Kumazireh” because their chief village is ”Kumzar M . They speak a dialect Kumzar their own which is unintelligible to the ordiu ,nary Arab, but as it appears to contain a good many words of a semi-Persian or Balooch form, it seems probable that they are immigrants from the opposite shore of the Gulf. As is natural however their numbers have proved too insignifieaht to allow them to maintain their independence and individuality and they have blended with practi^-^ A ally become absorbed by the bhihooh. It was one of these Kumzar^ villagers who was the- fortunate finder of the valuable pearl which i or two years past has been as an apple of discord in the Gulf, and. in these connections as is known to you the right of H.H. the Sultan, as sovereign of the soil or of the finder of the gem, to a shf share of the sale proceeds, was recognized and determined by the court of arbitrators . / c Prom Khasab to Bokha the country is exclu- sively Shihooh and one of the two principle shaiv whose influence predominates over this portion, Ali bin Mahomed divides his time between Bokha, &gt; Kada (an offshoot)of Khasab), and Muscat. He is we 11 known and respected in Muscat as he is a man of influence and learning and is personally known to me. Bokha. (continued) Pudar Ghamtha Tibba. Shuarn. Between Bokha and Ras el Khyma come the villages of Fudar, Ghamtha, libba and Shu- Q1 , These are also looked upon as Shihooh but from Bokha southwards and villages, - in the hills in the vicinity of Has el Khyma itself, owing to the circumstances of their situation the sections of Shi hooh residing there acknowledge the jur isdiction of and probably pay tribute tothe Shaikh of that port. Shaikh Ali Mohamed however in formed me that whereas circumstanoes obliged these members of the tribe with the cognizance of the rest, to bow to the Jowasmee nevertheless in an important matter affecting the common interest they would join the majority and that the Shihooh were in fact a united tribe. (.6.) In the foregoing paragraphs I have furnished the most reliable information that I am in a position to.obtain otherwise than from the Sultan or his officials, I think therefore that it may be re garded as a fairly correct statement of the situation but necessar ily from a Muscat point of view. Briefly stated it appears from the foregoing that the Sultan's jurisdiction extends effectively only as far as Mureir; that from Mureir to Dibba (including how ever only half of the port) there is reason to suppose that the Shaikh of Shargeh may make good prescriptive claim to exercise jurisdiction : that over the country from Dibba on to Ras Musendum and thence round to Khasab and Bokha, the Sultan if asked would probably claim rights of sovereignty and jurisdiction; and that from Bokha to Shuarn the coast is mainly occupied by sections of the Shihooh who for practical purposes at present recognize the autho rity of the Shaikh of Ras el Khyma. In conclusion, if I may presume to do so I would respectfully ex press the opinion that as regards the Malcolm and Blphinstone in lets on either side of Maklab and. the promontory of Ras Musendum the exercise of the Sultan of Muscat's authority thereover is of such a conveniently uncertain character that it would seem possible for Her Majesty's Government to treat the question of its existence according to the political exigencies of the moment. If we require a base there it might be possible to explain to the Sultan that his claim to assert his authority there or power to make it effects is of such an unsubstantial nature that H.M.'s Government are un able to recognize it,but regard the Shihooh (including the Kumazi- rehj as independent tribes. I think this is in any case a measu re with regard which Seyyid Beisal would not feel strongly seeing that he derives no practical or pecuniary benefit from that part of Oman and that he might be prevailed upon to cooperate with us inOn. the other hand it seems to me that in the event of any other power endeavouring to gain a footing in the neigh bourhood ' vV ’ e can adduce sufficient grounds for maintaining the position that the locality in question is paru the Sultanate of Oman. If to this end it should be considered. necessary to make Muscat iniluence more evident there, it could easily be done by arranging with the Sultan to ap point Walis to one or two of the ports a measure which I w do not think prima facie that the Shihooh would resent provided that the said Wall did not make any serious innov tions in the direction of collecting tribute. No doubt the most satisfactory way of ascertaining the leanings of the Shihooh Shaikhs and tribesme^n and evidenc as to the question of influence and jurisdiction is to make inquiries from the inhabitants themselves on the spot and in addition to the coastline from Khor ?akan to Lima as you suggest, I vrould propose with your approval to take an early opportunity of visiting the whole of the coast between Shinas and isofcha and quietly making inquiries lo- cally ports. (.7.) The map which I have used for reference in connecti with this report is Admiralty Chart headed*’ Entrance to -^q Persian Gulf” and dated 18825. I I have the honour to be etc.A mmmi With reference to my Confidential letter No’ 96 dated 16th August 1901, I have the honour to forward for your information copy of a letter No: 1641 E % A % dated 2Sth September 1901, from the Government of India to my adaress . 2. I have not yet received a reply from our Agent at Shargah on the subject of the views held by the Shargdh Chief regarding his possessions on the Batineh Coast , but4 Your subsequent letter No: 334, dated 28th August J dealt fully with the question of the Sultan's authority in the direction of flussendim and at Mussendim itself ana has been submitted by me to the Government of has also visited Lima Dibba India. Captain Phillipps ,R.N y l '*'A copy of my forwarding letter No: 136 dat ea 10 th Sept, 1901, i s enclosed for your information . and Khor Fakan and has submitt ea a report on these places. It might,how ever f be advisable that you should f as suonested by the Government of India ; avail yourself of a suitable opportunity of visiting the Coast. 1 have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant Offg: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.No: 1641 E.A. From The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Dej&gt;artment % i o Lieutenant-Colonel C. A. Kemball, Gffg: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Fated Simla, the 26th Septr : 1901. Sir, I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter So:148, dated the 16th August 1901 t regarding Khor Fakan on the Batineh Coast. 2. Pie question raised in this letter is connected with tnat of the actual limits of Maskat authority in the direction of Cape Musandim, on which you were askea to report in my letter No: 475-E.A., dated the 25th July. Tn the opinion of the Government of India it is very desirable that along this Coast there should be no inter val between the territory of Maskat, which, as against trance, is protected from aggression by the Anglo-French declarationdeclaration of 1862, and the dominions of the Cheifs of Shargah and Ras-ul-Kheimah, who are hound by treaty not to cede or sell any part of their territory t save to the British Government. It is presumed that there s no doubt as to the reality of Maskat authority as far north as Khor Kelbah. As regards the tract along the coast from Khor Kelbah to Dibba, which includes Khor Fakan, the Government of India have at different times aecidea that this portion o? the coast is under the suzerainty of and tributary to the Chief of Shargah y that it is subject to the (No:1426-E.P. dated the 4thJuly 1881 % \No:2188-E.P. dated the 17th Sept. 1881^, Maritime Truce, and that I o: 1696-E. dated the 27th July 1886. it is highly inadvisable that the Sultan of Maskat should interfere with it. If the authority of the Shargah Chief in this tract continues to be obvious and real, the Government of India see no reason to modify these views, and the present Sultan should not be encouraged to encroach in th is direction beyond his present 1imits . 3. Northward of Dibba, and rouna Cape Musandim to the territories of Ras-ul-Kheimah , it is improbable that at the present day the Sultan of Maskat retains, if indeed he has ever possessed, any real control. Vi/hatV/hat is the present real situation at Lima and at Khasab is also unknown: nor from such information as is possessed by the Government of India does it transpire whether there are Chiefs at either place or any where along this strip of Coast with whom it may be desirable to make agreements similar to those concluaea with the Trucial Chiefs in 1892, so as to ensure the exclusive right of the British Government to occupy any of the Inlets on the Has Musandim Promontory. There is indeea so much doubt as to the actual position of affairs on this pjart of the Coast, that the Government of India agree with you in thinking that it should be visited at an early aate by a ship of war. I am to suggest accordingly that Captain Cox should undertake this duty as far north as Khasab in one of His Majesty’s ships as soon as he returns from the examination in October of the coal mines at Pur. I have etc .* (Sa) H. S. Fames Secretary to the Govt of India.(COPY) confidential No: 166 of 1901. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 10th September 1901. From To Lieut-Colonel C. A. Kemball, Offg: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; H. S. Barnes Esquire,0.S.1. , Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department t Simla Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No: 1233 B.A. dated 25th duly 1901 on the subject of the selection of a naval base in the Persian Gulf. 2. There can,I believe / be no doubt whatever that with the exception of the British Station at Bassidore, the Persian right of possession over the island of Kishm as also over the islands of lien jam, Hormuz and Larak is com plete ana unaisputed.I understand that the Arab Sheikh of Kishm or some nemher of his family usually occupies the position of Kalantar, and as the succession to the Sheikhship is hereait&amp;ry, the position of Kalantar may also to a certain degree he considered to he so. The arrangement however has apparently been adopted for convenience sake and could undoubtedly be terminated at any time if the Persian Government saw fit to establish a Kalantar in the island independent of the Arab Sheikh, I am of opinion then that the position of the Kalantar is not of sufficient practical independence to make an arrangement with him possible or politically ad visable. I find that Sheikh Hasson, the Sheikh and Kalantar of Kishm, has not after all been superseded. It was the intention of the Persian Government to reinstate one Sheikh Abdulla / a relative of Sheikh Hass an and a former Kalantar of Kishm, and Monsieur Simais the Director-General of the Gulf Customs Administration took Sheikh Abdulla from Lingah to Bunder Abbas in the Persepolis for this purpose. The arrangement hovi- ever for some reason or other fell through ana Sheikh \ Hass an is still Kalantar of Kishm.$ % 3. As to the Isthmus of Maklah and the question of the actual limits of f/tuscat territory beyond Sohar in the direction of Cape Mosandim, I have the honour to forward copy of a report submitted by the Political Agent at f'usca'fr. Tt will be seen that Captain Cox Expresses the opinion that n as regards the Malcolm and tilphinstone inlets on either side of Maklab and the promontory of Has Mosandim the exercise of the Multan of Muscat's authority thereover is of such a conveniently uncertain character that it would seem possible for His Majesty's Government to treat the question of its existence accoraing to the political exigencies of the moment'. In other woras ? we can claim the Isthmus of Maklab to be either a part of the territories of the Sultan of 'fuscat or else to be independent of his or any other control. The Government of India will be aware that in 1864 when our Telegraph Station vjas locatea at Mosandim, the actual Elphinstone Island within the spot occupied being on/Elphinstone inlet or Khor-ash-Shem. Some correspondence ensued regarding the right to juris diction over this part y and the Bombay Government , vide their Resolution No:3248, dated 26th October 1864, deqjre- catea 'any investigation of the claims of His Highness of the Imam on the one hand and the Chief of Ras-ul-Kheima onon. the other to dominion over Cape hfussenaim'. Since then His highness the Sultan has established a Wali at Khasab situated on the Elphinstone inlet and furthe nor oh the Sultan's authority with regard to Kumzar near Has liosandim is now apparently not contested by. the Joasmee Chief, as pointed out by Captain Cox in para. 4 of his letter. It seems to me therefore that from our point of view, as we are hardly likely to require Khor-ash~Shem as a naval base, it will be more convenient to recognize the tract as within the territories of the Sultan of Muscat'. It will be per haps advisable that the Sultan should be induced in the manner indicated by Captain Cox to make his in fluence more apparent in the locality in question and I would solicit the orders of the Government of India in the matter. I attach a photographic reproduction of the Admiralty Chart showing the places referred to in Captain Cox's report. 4. I much regret that I am unable to offer any suggestions as to the measures of preparation which might be quietly taken in anticipation of the contin gencies referred to in the correspondence now under consi derat i onAS. Offg: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. consideration . It seems to me that we must perforce wait until one or other of the contingencies referred to arises or is seen to be imminent. The occupation of the islands and their maintenance against attack will in the first instance I presume have to be undertaken by naval force and the question appears to be chiefly one for the naval authorities to consider. In my opinion no anticipatory measures are immediately required. I have etc; (Sa) C. A. Kemball t^OTT.'fc clcritccz, / Zb No: /AZ of 1901. British Residency cma Consulate general f Bush ire /^^Bovember 1901 . A copy of the foregoing letter is forwarded to ' s Consul and Political Agent, Muscat, in continuation of the correspondence ending with the undersigned's letter No: 126, datea the l?th October 1901. Offg: PolitYcal^ResYdent in the Persian Gulf, From the Unaer Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. No : 1863 E.A. (Confidential) dated the 31st October 1901.[ Confidential. ] No. 1863 E.-A. Ebom The UNDER-SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of INDIA in the 'Foreign Department&gt; To Lieutenant-Colonel C. A. Kemball, Officiating POLITICAL RESIDENT in the PERSIAN GULP. Dated Simla, the 31st October 1901. Sib, I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of yonr letter No. 166, dated the 10th September 1901, on the subject of the selection of a naval base in the Persian Gulf. 2. It has already been suggested* to you that, in order to ascertain the * Vide m y letter No. 1641 e.-a., dated the 25 th actual limits of the authority of the Sultan September 1901 . 0 f ]yj as k a t in the direction of Cape Mosan- dim, the Political Agent at Maskat should visit the coast at an early date: and the naval authorities will now be asked to place a vessel at his disposal. Pending a further report from Captain Cox as to the actual political situation at the various places on this coast, the Government of India w r ould prefer that no steps should be taken to extend the authority of the Sultan beyond its present limits. I have the honour to be, Sib, Your most obedient servant, J. B. WOOD, Under •.Secretary to the Government of India. Foreign Office Press—No. 1598—1-11*01—42.From S i r , flo: : /Z6 British Residency and Consulate-General, Bush ire, /'‘/uQctober 1901, Lieut-Colonel C, A. Kemball, Of fa: Political Resiaent in the Persian Gulf; ILBJVs. Consul and Political Agent, Muscat In continuation of my letter Ho:121, aated the 11th instant, I have the honour to foryjard for your informa tion copies of two lists, which have been furnished to me by the Residency Agent at Shargah, containing informa tion about the places on the Batineh Coast and northwards I have the honour to be Your most obedient servant Offg; Political Resident in the Persian Gulf♦ / 4 3' (B No. Z&lt;^ $ of 1002. &gt;v To, H. S # BARNES ESC.UIRE I.G.b. : C.S.I. bECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of INDIA in the FOREIGN DEPARTMENT SIMLA. Dated Muscat 4th July 1002. Sir, T have the honour to forward copy of a letter 1 0*200 of 2nd July 1002 addressed by me to the Resident in the Persian Gulf on the subject of the Sul- tan^ jurisdiction In Northern Oman; being the report called for in Foreign Department letter No.1863 E.A. dated 31st October 1001. I I have the honour etc- Major, H.B.M.»s CONSUL &amp; POLITICAL AGENT, MUbCAT,No./^Jof 1902. To, The Officer Commanding H.M.S.” Redbreast' Muscat. Dated Muscat 4th April 1902. Sir, I understand from the Government of India that His Sxcellency Admiral Bosanquet has been requested to place one of His Majesty's ships at my disposal for the purpose of examining the extent of the Sultans authority on the Northern Oman Coast and neigh bourhood of Ras-Masemdum. • I am now ready to start upon this duty and have the honour to reuest the favour of your conveying me to Bushire, (starting on or about the evening of the 6th instant) where I wish to remain a day or two in order to confer with the Resident, and thence to a point on the Northern Oman Coast subsequently to be agreed upon, from which I can conveniently make a start. It is impossible for me to fix dates after leaving Bushire, but I should hope to be finished and back in. Muscat in 5 weeks. M I should be accompanied by 3 of 4 natives, and am also desirous of taking 4 negroes to Bushire for disposal by the Resident. I trust that this will be possible. I I have the honour to be,etc,. Major, H.B.M.'s Consul &amp; P.A. MUSCATThe •whole Ca Queen Regent hi resignation. Her Majesty form a Concent members of the groups^ Senor Sagasta task on the gre difticult of forma The Queen R noon with the P Senate. It appears to Cabinet, under t Rios, President ( friends of Seuor not exert their ii M. LOUBE r J FROM Calais, Havre, Loubet to use Russia. He will probal of May. He may return The .Z T '’Voe Vre Count Tols tvorse. On the night slept at all. D night he w T as in li weakness was mo is generally abo quently stops. r l o’clock in the eve Though yesten seemed to have patient appeared ing’s bulletin st; night and that strength. Otherwise his ( same. Mr. Rhodes is owing to the w r eat His general c changed. At to-day’s sit Conference, the G Jorkasch-Koch, E 'Finance, review conducted with E tion since 1896. He said, in con been considering | sugar output, am on the subject wil ^UlLl The Minis question in ( bility of a with Argent e'i had t *ction would the measures accelerate a si3H i \ 1902. f SPANISH CABINET. RESIGNATION ACCEPTED. FROM CUR CORRESPONDENT. MADRID, March 13. The whole Cabinet has resigned office, and the Queen Regent has announced her acceptance of the resignation. Her Majesty has requested Senor Sagasta to form a Concentration Cabinet from prominent members of the Liberal Party and the dissident groups! Senor Sagasta has declined to undertake this task on the ground that such a Cabinet would be i difficult of formation and dangerous to the country, i The Queen Regent had conferences this after- ! noon with the Presidents of the Chamber and the Senate. It appears to be probable that a Concentration Cabinet, under the Premiership of Senor Montero Rios, President of the Senate, will be formed if the friends of Senor Sagasta and the Conservatives do not exert their influence against it. M. LOUBET’S VISIT TO RUSSIA. FROM OUR CORRESPONDENT. PARIS, March 13. Calais, Havre, and Dunkirk are requesting M. Loubet to use their ports on his journey to Russia. He will probably start from Dunkirk on the 17th of May. He may return by Havre. COUNT TOLSTOY’S ILLNESS. [REUTER'S TELEGRAM.] ST. PETERSBURG, March 13. The ^ivoe Vremya learns that the condition of Count eo Tolstoy has suddenly changed for the worse. On the night of March 10 the patient scarcely slept at all. During the whole of the following night he was in low spirits, and the general state of weakness was more pronounced. The pulse, which is generally about 104, is very feeble, and fre quently stops. The patient’s temperature at seven o’clock in the evening was 99'5 Fahrenheit. MR. CECIL RHODES. [REUTER’S TELEGRAMS.] CAPETOWN, March 13. Though yesterday the condition of Mr. Rhodes seemed to have distinctly improved and the . patient appeared to be much brighter, this morn ing’s bulletin stated that he had had a restless j night and that this had told on his general strength. Otherwise his condition remains much about the same. CAPETOWN, March 13, 9.20 p.m. Mr. Rhodes is better than he was this morning, owing to the weather having become cooler. His general condition, however, is still un changed. THE SUGAR QUESTION. [REUTER’S TELEGRAM.] VIENNA, March 13. At to-day’s sitting of the Parliamentary Sugar Conference, the Government representative, Baron Jorkaseh-Koch, Departmental Chief in the Ministry of Finance, reviewed the negotiations which had been conducted with European States on the sugar ques tion since 1896. He said, in conclusion, that the Government had been considering the question of restricting the sugar output, and would come to an agreement on the subject with the Hungarian Government. QHILI AND ARGENTINA. [REUTER’S TELEGRAM.] VALPARAISO, March 13. The Minister of Foreign Affairs, replying to a question in Congress to-day regarding the possi bility of a direct arrangement being concluded with Argentina, stated that no steps to this e^I had been taken, and that any such • ction would in any case be out of place in view of the measures taken by the British Government to accelerate a settlement of the boundary dispute. Chili however, he added, would read 1 ]V .ieeenr MARLBOROUGH HOUSE, Thursday., His Majesty the King received in audience this day the Earl of Denbigh and Desmond on his return from a Special Mission to the Pope at Rome. The Earl of Pembroke and Montgomery, Lord Steward ; and Rear-Admiral Fawkes, Private Secretary to the First Lord of the Admiralty, also had audiences of his Majesty. YORK HOUSE, ST. JAMES’S PALACE, Thursday. The Prince and Princess of Wales, attended by the Countess of Airlie, Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Arthur Bigge, and the Hon. Derek Keppel, returned from Knowsley this afternoon. ~ / iVAVAL AND MILITARY INIl^LIGENCR In order that the battleship Bulwark which is to be commissioned at Devonporc next weel^ may proceed to the Mediterranean Station without delay she will not be fitted with wireless telegraphy apparatus until she arrives at Malta. The repairs of the cruiser Undaunted are to be completed with all speed, so that she may be commissioned as sea going tender to the gunnery ship Cambridge at Devon- port early in April. The battleships Beribow, Empress of India, and Besolu- tion, port guardships at Greenock, Queenstown, and Holyhead respectively, arrived at Plymouth yesterday at the close of the Reserve Squadron’s cruise. The Empress of India proceeded to Devonport Dockyard for the most extensive refit ever carried out there. The gunboat Renard, tender to the Resolution, arrived later. Capt. G. M. Henderson, of his Majesty’s ship Irresistible, is to be tried by court-martial at Portsmouth in connection with the collision between his ship and a car^o vessel off Beachy Head last week. The Peninsular and Oriental steamship Malacca arrived at the Royal Albert Docks yesterday afternoon with 16 officers £60 non-commissioned officers and men, chiefly time-expired, and invalids, from China and India. ARRANGEMENTS FOR THIS DAY. Their Majesties hold a Diplomatic and Official Court at Buckingham Palace, 10. Princess Christian presides at Annual Sale at the Royal School of Art Needlework, Exhibition-road, S.W., open 2.30 to 6.30. (Last day of sale.) House of Lords—Lord Windsor on Musical Copyright; Lord Ribbledale’s question on the purchase of horses for the Army in Kansas, 4.15. House of Commons—Debate on the motion that the Speaker leave the chair on the Civil Service Estimates, 3. German Society of Benevolence—Banquet (his Excellency Count Paul Metternich presiding), Whitehall Rooms, Hotel Metro pole. The Earl of Rosebery presides at the Annual Meeting of the City Liberal Club. Mr. Asquith at St. Leonards. Imperial South African Association—Mr. Evelyn Cecil, M.P., at the Constitutional Club, Bristol. The Archbishop of Canterbury opens the new St. John’s with All Saints’ Schools, Waterloo-road, Lambeth, 3. The Lord Mayor presides at the Annual Court of Governors of the Royal Hospital for Diseases of the Chest, City- road, 3. London Sketch Club—Smoking Conversazione, 175, New Bond-street, 8. Lord Charles Beresford speaks at the London Chamber of Commerce on “The Lack of Administrative Efficiency in our Organisation for Defence and its Remedy,” 2.30. National Liberal Club—Lecture on “ Taxation ” by Mr. Alfred Milnes, 8.30. Lecture on “Forestry ” by Dr. R. T. Cooper, St. James’s Hall, 8. Scientific and Learned Societies—Parents’ Educational Union, 3.15 ; Royal College of Surgeons, 5 ; Institution of Junior Engineers, 7.30 ; Institution of Civil Engineers, 8 ; Viking Club, 8.30 ; Royal Institution, 9. South-Western Polytechnic—Boys’ Gymnastic Display, 8. Racing—Lingfield; Haydock Park. NOTICES. Smart, Inexpensive Gowns, Emeleine, 41, New Bond-street. Waring’s Great Special Show of New Lace Curtains for 1902 takes place to-day and following days. Original, exclu sive, and charming designs in Swiss, Belgian, Nottingham, and French varieties, at very low prices. Exceptional muality, artistic patterns, unequalled in value. Galleries: ft 11, Oxford-street, W., and 175, Sloane-street, S.W. Her Majesty the Queen and her Royal Highness 'rincess Victoria were present at the Globe Theatre last .ight to witness the performance of “Sweet Nell of Old Drury.” Her Royal Highness Princess Louise Duchess of Argyll and the Duke of Argyll again visited Liverpool 5 ON THE PERSIAN GULF. POSSIBILITIES OF BUNDER ABBAS. “EARMARKED BY RUSSIA” RAILWAY DEVELOPMENT. THE GOVERNMENT OF THE SMAIS. WRITTEN BY H. J. WHIGHAM, OUR SPECIAL CORRESPONDENT. BUNDER ABBAS. Feb. 1. Leaving Bassadore, we skirted the south coast ok ! Kishm for three hours, until we came opposite the end of a red range of volcanic hills which runs down at right angles to the shore from the centre of the island. Here we landed to explore the famous salt caves that have been for centuries the only valuable asset of the island, which is said to have produced quantities of corn and vegetables and wine in the days when Nearchus sailed the gulf in support of the conquering hosts of Alexander the Great. The caves, which are apparently very numerous, can be discovered only by following up the streams of salt which run from the foot of the red hills to the beach. The entrances are generally a few feet high, but the interiors widen out into cathedral-like halls, with vaulted roofs, from winch gleaming stalactites of pure salt hang like icicles. The cave that we first entered tunnelled its way sheer through a hill five or six hundred feet in height into a little valley beyond, in the circumference of which there were other cave mouths like gigantic rabbit burrows at the foot of the hills. The floors of ail the caves are pure salt, into which the foot sinks as in the sands of the sea, and the supply seems well-nigh as inexhaustible. The outer surface of the hills are red with iron oxide, except where they are discoloured by sulphur, and they are so destitute of vegetation as to make the existence of gazelles about their slopes seem almost miraculous. The salt industry is carried on by a few Arab dhows, and is evidently guarded somewhat jealously by the Sheikh of Kishm. It can hardly be doubted that with scientific exploitation this part of the island might be made to yield a valuable output of sulphur, iron, and per haps copper, as well as salt. The caves in any more accessible part of the world would be a mine of wealth to an enterprising agent for holiday tours. The Islands of Kishm and Ormuz. Just east of the eaves, and easily visible from the red hills, is the Island of Henjam, which, lying off the south coast of Kishm, forms a channel that might be converted into an excellent deep water harbour. Passing to the southward and then turn ing again north-east we ran between Kishm and Larak, and dropped anchor off the town of Kishro, which is at the extreme eastern point of the island, just sixty miles from Bassadore on the west, and which contains the residence of the Sheikh. We found the town in partial ruins owing to an earth quake that occurred a year or two ago, and we had difficulty in believing the Arab guide who put the population at seven thousand. It is, in fact, a settlement of very little importance, being-the capital of a peculiarly arid island whose agricultural wealth, if it ever existed, has long since vanished, and whose mineral resources, which may be considerable, are quite undeveloped. The small population subsists for the most part on a meagre carrying trade similar to that of Lingah, but on an infinitely smaller scale, and likely in the same way to be spoiled, such as it is, by the new customs administration. The climate in summer was fatal to the British force which was camped a mile or so from the town in 1820, and it is intolerable even to the natives, who desert it altogether if they possibly can during the worst months. From Kishm we went to Ormuz, a small island nine and a half miles to the east ward of Kishm, if anything more desperate! ..o-t-.- » &gt;.-w ssas^.s-.—-.In • -m 1902. 5 SPANISH CABINET. RESIGNATION ACCEPTED. FROM OUR CORRESPONDENT. MADRID, March 13. The whole Cabinet has resigned office, and the Queen Regent has announced her acceptance of th© resignation. Her Majesty has requested Sen or Sagasta to form a Concentration Cabinet from prominent members of the Liberal Party and the dissident groups! Senor Sagasta has declined to undertake this task on the ground that such a Cabinet would be difficult of formation and dangerous to the country. The Queen Regent had conferences this after noon with the Presidents of the Chamber and the Senate. It appears to be probable that a Concentration Cabinet, under the Premiership of Senor Montero Rios, President of the Senate, will be formed if the friends of Senor Sagasta and the Conservatives do not exert their influence against it. M. LODBET’S VISIT TO RUSSIA. PROM OUR CORRESPONDENT. PARIS, March 13. Calais, Havre, and Dunkirk are requesting M. Loubet to use their ports on his journey to Russia. He will probably start from Dunkirk on the 17th of May. He may return by Havre. COUNT TOLSTOY’S ILLNESS. [REUTER'S TELEGRAM.] ST. PETERSBURG, March 13. The ^ivoe Vremya learns that the condition of Count eo Tolstoy has suddenly changed for the T?orse. On the night of March 10 the patient scarcely slept at all. During the whole of the following night he was in low spirits, and the general state of weakness was more pronounced. The pulse, which is generally about 104, is very feeble, and fre quently stops. The patient’s temperature at seven o’clock in the evening was 99'5 Fahrenheit. MR. CECIL RHODES. [REUTER’S TELEGRAMS.] CAPETOWN, March 13. Though yesterday the condition of Mr. Rhodes seemed to have distinctly improved and the patient appeared to be much brighter, this morn ing’s bulletin stated that he had had a restless night and that this had told on his general strength. Otherwise his condition remains much about the same. CAPETOWN, March 13, 9.20 p.m. Mr. Rhodes is better than he was this morning, owing to the weather having become cooler. His general condition, however, is still un changed. THE SUGAR QUESTION. [REUTER’S TELEGRAM.] VIENNA, M a rch 13. At to-day’s sitting of the Parliamentary Sugar Conference, the Government representative, Baron Jorkasch-Koch, Departmental Chief in the Ministry of Finance, reviewed the negotiations which had been conducted with European States on the sugar ques tion since 1896. He said, in conclusion, that the Government had been considering the question of restricting the sugar output, and would come to an agreement on the subject with the Hungarian Government. MARLBOROUGH HOUSE. Thursdat. His Majesty the King received in audience this day the Earl of Denbigh and Desmond on his return from a Special Mission to the Pope at Rome. The Earl of Pembroke and Montgomery, Lord Steward ; and Rear-Admiral Fawkes, Private Secretary to the First Lord of the Admiralty, also had audiences of his Majesty. YORK HOUSE, ST. JAMES’S PALACE, Thursday. The Prince and Princess of Wales, attended by the Countess of Airlie, Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Artlyur Bigge, and the Hon. Derek Keppel, returned from KrjOwsley this afternoon. ' / MAVAL AND MILITARY INTDjth^ENGK In order that the battleship Bulwark which to be commissioned at Devon port next weely may proceed to the Mediterranean Station without delay she will not be fitted with wireless telegraphy apparatus until she arrives at Malta. The repairs of the cruiser Undaunted are to be completed with all speed, so that she may be commissioned as sea going tender to the gunnery ship Cambridge at Devon- port early in April. The battleships Beribow, Empress of India, and Resolu tion, port guardships at Greenock, Queenstown, and Holyhead respectively, arrived at Plymouth yesterday at the close of the Reserve Squadron’s cruise. The Empress of India proceeded to Devonport Dockyard for the most extensive refit ever carried out there. The gunboat Renard, tender to the Resolution, arrived later. Capt. G. M. Henderson, of his Majesty’s 2 &gt;Xl\X) Irresistible, is to be tried by court-martial at Portsmouth in connection with the collision between his ship and a cargo vessel off Beachy Head last week. The Peninsular and Oriental steamship Malacca arrived at the Royal Albert Docks yesterday afternoon with 16 officers£60 non-commissioned officers and men, chiefly time-expired and invalids, from China and India. ARRANGEMENTS FOR THIS DAY. Their Majesties hold a Diplomatic and Official Court at Buckingham Palace, 10. Princess Christian presides at Annual Sale at the Royal School of Art Needlework, Exhibition-road, S.W., open 2.30 to 6.30. (Last day of sale.) House of Lords—Lord Windsor on Musical Copyright; Lord Ribbledale’s question on the purchase of horses for the Army in Kansas, 4.15. House of Commons—Debate on the motion that the Speaker leave the chair on the Civil Service Estimates, 3. German Society of Benevolence—Banquet (his Excellency Count Paul Metternich presiding), Whitehall Rooms, Hotel Metro pole. The Earl of Rosebery presides at the Annual Meeting of the City Liberal Club. Mr. Asquith at St. Leonards. Imperial South African Association—Mr. Evelyn Cecil, M.P., at the Constitutional Club, Bristol. The Archbishop of Canterbury opens the new St. John’s with All Saints’ Schools, Waterloo-road, Lambeth, 3. The Lord Mayor presides at the Annual Court of Governors of the Royal Hospital for Diseases of the Chest, City- road, 3. London Sketch Club—Smoking Conversazione, 175, New Bond-street, 8. Lord Charles Beresford spaaks at the London Chamber of Commerce on “The Lack of Administrative Efficiency in our Organisation for Defence and its Remedy,” 2.30. National Liberal Club—Lecture on “Taxation” by Mr. Alfred Milnes, 8.30. Lecture on “Forestry ” by Dr. R. T. Cooper, St. James’s Hall, 8. Scientific and Learned Societies—Parents’ Educational Union, 3.15 ; Royal College of Surgeons, 5 ; Institution of Junior Engineers, 7.30 ; Institution of Civil Engineers, 8 ; Viking Club, 8.30 ; Royal Institution, 9. South-Western Polytechnic—Boys’ Gymnastic Display, 8. Racing—Lingfield; Hay dock Park. NIILI AND ARGENTINA. [REUTER’S TELEGRAM.! VALPARAISO, March 13. The Minister of Foreign Affairs, replying to a question in Congress to-day regarding the possi bility of a direct arrangement being concluded with Argentina, stated that no steps to this e^l had been taken, and that any such .etion would in any case be out of place in view of the measures tal.en by the British Government to accelerate a settlement of the boundary dispute, rihili however, h e added , wojjh 1 readily K.V might'teacT to a prompt settle- NOTICES. Smart, Inexpensive Gowns, Emeieine, 44, New Bond-street. Waring’s Great Special Show of New Lace Curtains for 1902 takes place to-day and following days. Orkinal, exclu sive, and charming designs in Swiss, Belgian, Nottingham, and French varieties, at very low prices. Exceptional quality, artistic patterns, unequalled in value. Galleries : 181, Oxford-street, W., and 176, Sloane-street, SAY. IG IN MANCHURIA. REUTER’S TELEGRAM.] ST. PETERSBURG, March 13. nvalid announces to-day that the staff has received from General jatch stating that on March 3 nenko encountered a body of three tses north of Hubandsy. it the Tunguses and two hundred of o killed, and three guns and many aken by the Russians. The Russian loss was two Cossacks wounded. PRINCESS RADZIWILL’S CASE. [REUTER’S telegram.] CAPETOWN, March 13. The action in which Princess Radziwill seeks to recover the sum of £2,000 from Mr. Rhodes on a bill alleged to have been forged came before the Supreme Court to-day. The judge postponed the case until the result of the criminal proceedings against Princess Radziwill in respect to the promissory note on which she is suing is known. BRAMANTE'S FRESCOES. FROM OUR CORRESPONDENT. ROME, March 13. The Museum of Brera, in Milan, has acquired a new attraction in the form of eight frescoes by Bramante which have been detached from the walls of the Palace of Lorenzo Prinetti. Five of the frescoes represent Knights and Barons of the epoch. Two are more than life-size figures of swordsmen, and in the eighth the figures of Heraclitus weeping and Democritus laughing are shown seated on the two sides of the world. The character of the painting clearly shows ttiij 1 Knf it-, also attests Her Majesty the Queen and her Royal Highness Princess Victoria were present at the Globe Theatre last night to witness the performance of “Sweet Nell of Old Drury.” Her Royal Highness Princess Louise Duchess of Argyll and the Duke of Argyll again visited Liverpool Hospital, buih by the David Lewis legatees at a cost of £130,000. Hospital accommodation is provided for two hundred and twenty patiehts. The Lord Mayor, president of the hospital, accepted the buildings on behalf of the trustees. After opening the hospital, her Royal Highness and the Duka of Argyll left for London direct by the express. Senor Gutierrez-Ponce, the Colombian Minister to the Court of St. James and to the German Court, .has returned to London from Berlin, accompanied by Senora Gutierrez-Ronce and daughters, in order to attend the Court at Buckingham Palace this evening. The Marchioness Cassar de Sain is leaving town to-dav by the Orient Line for Cairo, and will not return to L ndon till the middle of May. The general condition of the Earl of Kimberley was not so satisfactory yesterday, but he was reported to have passed a more comfortable night. The Earl of Ducie and Miss Oakley have arrived j,t 16, Portman-square. Viscount and Viscountess Wolseley are prevented Attending their Majesties’ Court to-night by the death of Lady Wolseley, wife of Lord Wolseley’s brother, General Sir George Wolseley, Commander-in-Chief at Madras, which took place at Hillside, Whitchurch, Oxon, on Tuesday. There was no change yesterday in the condition of Lord Connemara. Lord and Lady Alington left town yesterday for Crichel, Wimborne, Dorset. Lord Lister is leaving England for an absence of several weeks, during which letters will not be forwarded to him. Lady Raglan has not sufficiently recovered from her long illness to be able to attend their Majesties’ Court this evening. Lord and Lady Barnard have taken 20, Belgrave- square for a term of years, and will shortly move there. They are at present residing at 1, Wilton-terrace. Mr. and Mrs. Leo Bonn and the Misses Bonn have returned to 22, Upper Brook-street. Mr. and the Misses Mackenzie have arrived at 42, Great Curaberland-place from Pawley Court, Bucks. Mrs. Baines, of Bawtry Hall, Yorkshire, desires to express her grateful thanks for kind sympathy in the loss of her son Oswald in South Africa, and hopes in time to answer each letter, their great number preventing her doing so as quickly as she would wish. There will be a memorial service at Bawtry to-day at four o’clock. The marriage arranged between Captain Dighton Dick, Royal Scots Fusiliers, and Miss Lilian Ricardo will take place on the 24th of April at St. Thomas’s, Portman- square. The marriage arranged between J. Henry H. V. Lane, of King’s Bromley Manor, Lichfield, and Grace, third daughter of Lady Kensington, will take place at St. Paul’s, Knightsbridge, on Saturday, the 12th of April. The marriage arranged between Captain Rowland Holroyd-Smyth and Miss Alice Ponsonby is unavoidably postponed. The second meeting this year of the Fox Club was held last night at Brooks’s, when the following members were present: Sir H. D. Le Marchant, Mr. J. D. Walker, K.C., Mr. F. A. Inderwick, K.C., Mr. W. G. Gould, Mr. A. H. H. Atherley, Mr. Guy Stephenson, Colonel Vesey Dawson, Mr. A. Du Cane, Mr. Hussey Packe, Mr. H. Le Roy Lewis, Mr. Victor A. Williamson, Mr. L. A. S. Bigge, Mr. A. Bonham Carter, Mr. E. H. Pember, K.C., Sir W. ffolkes (in the chair), Mr. H. F. C. Cavendish, Mr. H. Seymour, Sir A. K. Stephenson, K.C., Mr. R. P. Blennerhassett, K.C., Mr. O. Magniac, Colonel Graves Sawle, Mr. O. N. L. T. Scott, Mr. W. E. Davidson, K.C., and Mr. E. St. Aubyn. His Royal Highness the Prince of Wales has been pleased to grant to Messrs. Pugh and Co., of 16, Buckingham Palace-road, a warrant of appointment as coal merchants. Pier Royal Highness Princess Christian will lay the foundation-stone of the country branch of the Mount Yemen Hospital for Consumption, Hampstead and North- wood, at Northwood, on May 13. The Marquis de Leuville gives the first of his usual Friday weekly “at homes” since his illness at his town residence, 31, George-street, Hanover-square, to-day, from four till seven o’clock. A dinner will be held at the South Kensington Conservative Club on the 21st inst., at which Earl Percy, M.P. for the division, will take the chair. Lord Raglan, Under Secretary of State for War, will also bo present. The death is announced at Brecon of Colonel John Morgan, who was eight times Mayor of the town. He was one of the most wealthy citizens of Brecon and a liberal public benefactor. He was Mayor when the Duke of Clarence and Avondale visited Brecon. ON THE PERSIAN GULF. POSSIBILITIES OF BUNDER ABBAS. “EARMARKED BY RUSSIA” RAILWAY DEVELOPMENT. THE GOVERNMENT OF THE SHAH. WRITTEN BY H. J. WHIGHAM, OUR SPECIAL CORRESPONDENT. BUNDER ABBAS, Fee. 1. Leaving Bassadore, we skirted the south coast oi 1 Kishm for throe hours, until we came opposite the end. of a red rangs of volcanic hills which runs down at right angles to the shore from the centre of the island. Here we landed to explore the famous salt caves that have been for centuries the only valuable asset of the island, which is said to have produced quantities of corn and vegetables and wine in the.days when Nearchus sailed the gulf in support of the conquering hosts of Alexander the Great. The caves, which are apparently very numerous, can be discovered only by following up the streams of salt which run from the foot of the red hills to the beach. The entrances are generally a few feet high, but the interiors widen out into cathedral-like halls, with vaulted roofs, from which gleaming stalactites of pure salt hang like icicles. The cave that we first entered tunnelled its way sheer through a hill five or six hundred feet in height into a little valley beyond, in the circumference of which there were other cave mouths like gigantic rabbit burrows at the foot of the hills. The floors of all the caves are pure salt, into which the foot sinks aa in the sands of the sea, and the supply seems well-nigh as inexhaustible. The outer surface of the hills are red with iron oxide, except where they are discoloured by sulphur, and they are so destitute of vegetation as to make the existence of gazelles about their slopes seem almost miraculous. The salt industry is carried on by a few Arab dhows, and is evidently guarded somewhat jealously by the Sheikh of Kishm. It can hardly be doubted that with scientific exploitation this part of the island might be made to yield a valuable output of sulphur, iron, and per haps copper, as well as salt. The caves in any more accessible part of the world would be a mine of wealth to an enterprising agent for holiday tours. The Islands of Kishm and Ormuz. Just east of the caves, and easily visible from the red hills, is the Island of Henjam, which, lying off the south coast of Kishm, forms a channel that might be converted into an excellent deep water harbour. Passing to the southward and then turn ing again north-east we ran between Kishm and Larak, and dropped anchor offthe town of Kishm, which is at the extreme eastern point of the island, just sixty miles from Bassadore on the west, and which contains the residence of the Sheikh. We found the town in partial ruins owing to an earth quake that occurred a year or two ago, and we had difficulty in believing the Arab guide who put tho population at seven thousand. It is. in fact, a settlement of very little importance, being-the capital of a peculiarly arid island whose agricultural wealth, if it ever existed, has long since vanished, and whose mineral resources, which may be considerable, are quite undeveloped. The small population subsists for the most part ou a meagre carrying trade similar to that of Lingah, but on an infinitely smaller scale, and likely in the same way to be spoiled, such as it is, by the new customs administration. The climate in summer was fatal to the British force which was camped a mile or so from the town in 1820, and it is intolerable even to the natives, who desert it altogether if they possibly can during the worst months. From Kishm we went to Ormuz, a small island nine and a half miles to the east ward of Kishm, if anything more desperate! towaius tile ‘ mtuuiandv ^Orrauz is of volcanic hills four miles in both length and breadth, rising to a height of 690ft., and re sembling irregular heaps of red earth and white lime. The red is oxide of iron, the white is salt. There is no water on the island except what is collected in tanks from the scanty rainfall, and very little life of any sort beyond a few hundred fishermen huddled together in huts on the site of the old Portuguese city and the ubiquitous gazelle, which seems to thrive on red ochre, and is credibly asserted to slake his thirst in the salt- waves on the beach. Ancient Habitations. Ormuz, which was once the richest mart of tha East, the great, emporium where the trade of tha East met that of the West, is now a barren island, scarcely inhabited, and about as picturesque as any piece of waste land which has re cently been turned over to the tender mercies of the jerry builder. Yet on closer inspection one has no difficulty in believing that the little spit of level ground which projects to tha north and ends in the ruins of a once impregnable fortress was the site of a city of forty thousand inhabitants. In fact that number might be well within the mark, for of the square mile and a half of level ground between the fort and the hills there is not a yard which is not covered with the rubble of ancient habitations now sunk in sand and coated with salt. The fortress is interesting as being tha strongest of th'e many defences that the Portu guese built for themselves along the shores of Arabia and Persia, as the special work of the great Albuquerque himself, and as the cynosure of many experienced travellers. One can well imagine that Ormuz, with its frowning stronghold and beautiful churches and clustered white houses reflected in the blue waters of the gulf, with its bulky galleons and rakish frigates lying at anchor beneath the castle, was once a pleasing sight to eyes that had grown weary with the long beat up the barren Arab coast. It is a sight that is never likely to be seen again, however, even though the Moin-ut-Tujar has got a concession to exploit the island, and Ormuz should send red ochre in tramp steamers to London in place of tha pearls and silks and spices which once burdened the argosies of Portugal. From the fort to tha mainland is not quite three miles, but Bunder Abbas, which is all that is left to represent tha glories of Ormuz and Gombroon, is some distanca along the coast, and altogether twelve and a half miles from our anchorage at Ormuz. Trade and Politics of the Gulf. To tell again the history of Bunder Abbas anj its neighbouring Islands of Kishm and Larak and Ormuz would be simply to borrow, and spoil in the borrowing, the admirable littla historical fantasia — if the metaphor may be allowed—which is by no means the least charming part of Lord Curzon's “ Persia.” It will be suffi cient to indicate the position which Bunder Abbas holds in the trade and politics of tiie gulf to-day and to speculate for a moment on the probabilities and possibilities of its future. In following my brief argument I would ask the reader to bear par ticularly iu mind that Bunder Abbas is the port which Russia is supposed to have ear-marked^ for herself, and which writers in the Spectator, the National lievieiv, and the Fortnightly have recom mended as an acceptable offering to our Asiatic rival. Unlike Lingah, Bunder Abbas is no longer a distributing port for the gulf to any appreciable extent, nor does it to the slightest degree fill the proud place of Ormuz as a half - way house between East and West. It is sim ply the terminus which connects the long caravan route from Yezd and Kerman with the sea ; otherwise there would be no possible reason for the existence of this long line of dingy houses built on a dingy shore, destitute of fresh water, and caught between the direct rays of a pitiless sun and those which are reflected from the sheer wall of mountain rock that rises to the height of 7,690ft. just 15 miles to landward. From Bunder Abbas to Kerman the distance is three hundred and eighty miles, and thence to Yezd there are a good two hundred more. The Bunder Abbas route should thus have matters all its own way as far as foreign trade is concerned. But up to the present time Bunder Abbas has aspired, not without success, to spread its tentacles to Teheran in the north and Seistan and Meshed in the north-east, and even sends a por tion of its trade beyond the bounds of Persia to Kabul and Central Asia. The Trade of Bonder Abbas. In the last year for which the administrsima reports of the Persian Gulf are available, i.e., 1900, there was a sudden decline of between 50 per cent, and 60 per cent, in the total value of the BunderCOTIFIDENTIAL No.Jt jC of 1902. From, To, Major P.Z.COX, H.B.M. ’s CONSUL &amp; POLITICAL AGENT, mSCAT. Lieutwnant-Colonel C.A.EEIvTDALL, POLITICAL RESIDENT in the PERSIAN GULF. H.B.M.'s CONSULATE &amp; POLITICAL AGENCY. Dated Muscat 1902. SIR, I have the honor to submit the report called for in Foreign Department letter No.1863 E.A. dated 31st October 1901 regarding the nature and extent of the jurisdiction of the Sultan of Muscat in the direction of Cape Musandam and in Northern Oman generally. 2. For some time after my return from the second coal Prospecting expedition near Soor in December last passing events necessitated my presence in Muscat and a convenient opportunity for extended absence did not present itself un til 6th April,when His Excellency Admiral Bosanquet was good enough to place H.M.S.'Redbreast” at my disposal for the pur pose of visiting the neighbourhood in question, I have to express my cordial thanks to Lieut.-Commander Quayle commanding that vessel,who accommodated his movements in every way to my requirements and in throwing his ship open to visitors at ports of call and in the extension of civility to natives met with,spared himself no pains or in convenience in order to leave ; behind a favourable impression of the 'Redbreast's' visit. 3. Using3. Using Admiralty Chart No.753 of 1872 for reference L and follov^ing its spelling to avoid'confusion, I propose, in the first place,to record seriatim the state of things at present existing in each locality along the coast from Muscat north- wards,as it appears from circumstantial evidence and informa tion gathered from the natives, in order that you may he in position to form your own opinion on the facts elicited,. I shall afterwards venture to submit,for such consideration as they may deserve,the conclusions to which X have myself been brought in view of the correspondence which has recently passed in connection with the possible aims of Foreign Powers in these waters. 4. The jurisdiction of the Sultan of Muscat along the ©man Coast northwards from the capital MUSCAT to MUKEIR. to the 25th parallel of latitude just beyond the village of Mureir, admits of no doubt. It is generally recognized,and as things go ef fective, falling as it does within the districts governed by His Highness's Wali at Sohar. Up to this point the line of low-lying coast which forms the frontage of the narrow belt of fertile plain known as the '’Eatineh' is unbroken by any abutment of the Maritime Range upon its shores. Just beyond Mureir however this Batineh plain comes to an end, or rather is oroken up by ixj-egulai clusters of foot—hills, until eventually spur is thrown for ward to the sea just short of Khor Ealba,5 miles from Mureir, which feature may be considered to,.form the natural northern boundary of the Eatineh Coast. 5 # From Khor Kalba the chain of desolate mountains, re tiring again for a time from the sea, describes a semi-circle, having the coast line for its chord, and a diameter of 9 or 10 miles,and encloses within the arc the vil lages of Kalba, Gharf ah, Fjijaira and Sakam- kam,just beyond which a second spur is thrown out seawards. KHOR KALEA FUJAIRA KHOR FAKAN. Thenz (§) Then follows another stretch, of 10 miles,which in the chart under reference is shewn as open plain,hut which is in real ity composed of a mass of low hills coming close down to the sea,relieved by many little indentations in the coast line containing small hamlets and date gardens,until at 10 miles the large village and bay of Khor Fakan is reached. Over this tract (Khor Kalba to Khor Fakan) the jurisdiction of the Sultan of Muscat cannot at the present day be held to extend,and when the 'Redbreast' approached the shore the white bordered flag of the Jowasmi ArahS^^s seen flying ovex the forts of Kalba and Ghurfa,as it is also known to do at Khor Fakan, in each of which villages there is a representa-^, tive of Shaikh Hamad bin Majid, cousin of the Chief of Shar- gah^who holds the village in fief and levies what tribute he can from the inhabitants in the date season. The situation at Eujaira is at present somewhat complicated. This village,with the small but apparently well defined foxt #2t ' appertaining to it,is about If miles from^shore in the midst of extensive date groves,and is controlled by Shall: Hama bin Abdulla of the Sharki tribe,who for some time past has been complaining bitterly of Jowasmi oppression,; and endea vouring to set up a claim to independence or,failing that,to come under the protection of Muscat. This attitude on his behalf has resulted in a good deal of dissension and unrest in the vicinity as well as amo- g the Chiefs of the Pirate Coast and must have bee . the cause not a little anxiety to the Residency. As the case is still,I understand,sub judice,it is not ad visable to enter into details here,but,in orddr that what fol lows may be understood it is necessary that I s .ould me in passing that while on the one hand it appears that Shaikh Hamad abovemehtioned executed a document before the Resident 20 year* ago in which he admitted his subordination to the hand, iudgfng from circumstances -1 -i 'K'h C*. whichwhich have come to light in the course of the present dispute^ it is manifest that the Chief of Shargah is at present unable to accord his quasi-dependent that protection and justice which the latter is entitled to expect from him by virtue of such an agreement as that abovementioned. Between Khor Fakan and Ras Dibba lie seven small villages, also belonging to the Sharkiyeen, These are generally subject to the Jowasmi feudatory of Khor Fakan but the status of one or two of them in which the influence of Shaikh Kamad bin Aodulla of Fujaira is paramount, is affected by the question now at issue regarding the last named village. 6. On rounding Ras Dibba we come within the purview of the port of that name,the southern half of which, as mentioned in my previous report is likewise sub— , J ’ V ■ &gt; * 1 're ject to Jowasmi influence, having,until lately, been held in fief by another relative of the Chief of Shargah } namely his uncle Ahmed bin Sultan. This Shaikh died however at Ras el Khaima during the past year and the inheritance has. DIBEA. I understand,descended to his son Rashid^who will presumably levy dues from the community during the present season. I ap pend as an enclosure for ready reference in the above connec tion a family tree of the last few generations of the Shargah. family. The northern half of the bay is occupied by the Shihooh under a Shaikh of their own,especially appointed by the tribe for the maintenance of order in a community which circumstances ren der motley and fluctuating; the fact being that during the sum mer months large numbers of Shihooh flock in from Kumzar and other fishing villages along the coast,the well to do m order to tend date gardens which they themselves possess,and the poorer among them to work for hire in the plantations of others. From Dibba a well defined camel track wind's through the hills and crosses the promontory to Ras el Kiaima on the Pirate Coast meeting the Ras el Khaima-Bereymee road on debouching into the maritime plain. North of this tract the country is a maze of barrenbarren mountains tenanted when and where water-holes exist by small communities of hardy Shihooh shepherds accompanied by their flocks of goats and aspiring to a little cultivation where suitable ground and a sufficiency of water make it possible. 7. Following the coast between Dibba and Lima the 5 inlets, Duhat. Haffa,Duhat Shargah and DIBBA to LIMA. Kubat Akaba are passed. /There are no villages of size or importance in these havens, simply small moveable fishing hamlets af Shihooh pay* ing tribute to no one and in case of disagreement appealing to their Shaikh at Dibba or Lima as convenient. Lima,owing to the existence of a comparative abundance of sweet water together with an open space admitting the culti vation of dates,is one of the chief Shihooh colonies,and is governed by Shaikh Mahomed Eeraim of the Beni Shetair section of the tribe. This Shaikh pays no tribute to anyone but col. lects and keeps for himself such tithes or duty as he is able to levy in cash or kind during the harvest. In the abstract however he recognises his subordination to Seyyid Feisal and on my producing the passport given me by His Highness he at onoe expressed his willingness to give me every assistance in his power and said that Seyyid Feisal^s wishes we^e law to him. It Jiad been my intention to disembark from H.M. S. 'Redbreast at, Lima and explore the rest of the promontory by land, but a more intimate acquaintance with the locality made it clear that this was not feasible,at all events at this season of the year. Between most of the Coast villages there is no communication other than by sea at any time,except for a cragsman;and,as regards the hinterland,even had any trans port been available,which it was not,the great scarcity of water which has resulted from the drought of the last two years and which has driven many of the shepherds down to the seaside villagesi-made travelling in these baked and barren hills unbearable during, the heat of April and Hay. I was consequently obliged to complete the tour by sea. Leaving 8 .DUHAT KAEAL. Leaving Lima t,he 'ReflbreasV' ent»ered the Duhati Kabal^ in the innermost, cove of which inlet, dwells a small permanent, communitiy of t»he Shihooh, consisting of 4 or 5 families living in rude shingle huts and passihg their existence in a state of peaceful and contented poverty, .They possess a few goats but their main staff of life is a shell fish of the strombus family which abounds in the shallows of their cove. These people were the wildest met with and disappeared into the hills on the approach of the ’'Redbreast', and although she anchored there for 2 days only two of the men could be pursua- ded to come on board,the women and children never appearing. The men had no firearms and those we met were perfectly friend ly but having never seen a white man or a steamer before wex e naturally scared and apprehensive. The two days spent here were occupied in an excursion to the summits of the neighbouring mountains,guided by one of the local natives,in the hope of falling in with other Bedouin Shi hooh, but owing to the drought just mentioned the two or three natural reservoirs for rain water that we visited were dried up and the usual encampments in the vicinity deserted. Three shepherds were however met with,who,like their comrades down below,carried no arms and were very frank and friendly. Asked how it was that they could thus wander afield unarmed they replied that they had' no need of weapons as their enemies the Jowasmis could hot penetrate to their mountain haunts by land btCi and the 'Nasara'fi.e.English] gave them immunity by sea. The V A / 'Nasara' seemed to be to them a mysterious institution,X might almost say fetish,which they did not profess to understand,but with regard to which they were content to know that it made the sea safe for them. I found this sentiment agreeably prevalent not only here but in all the out—of—the—way places visited in these waters,both on the coast and in the group of islands in the southern part of the Persia.n Gulf. Natives mot with who had never before seen a white man at close quarters and to whom the explanation 'Angrez' (English) in reply to queries as to who we were,of itself conveyed nothing, invariably followed upup their first question by inquiring whether we belonged to the nation 'who kept the sea' and on finding that we did,en deavoured to show their respect and friendliness for us forth with. On such occasions one could not but be possessed for the moment by the spirit of the pride of the race and by the kindred hope that this honourable heritage,the Pax Britanni- ca,or as they call it 'the keeping of the sea' might not come to be shared with any,at all events in our generation. Questioned as to the direction in which they were accustomed to turn for protection or redress,they proved to have hazy notions on the subject,owing no doubt to the fact that from the circumstances of their life they seldom fall in need ei ther of one or the other. They had indeed heard of'bin Turki' of Muscat but the name was evidently not connected in their minds with any idea of territorial sovereign\ty and it is certain that they pay tribute to no one. The naiae that car ried most weight with them was that of Zaeed bin Khalifa the Trucial Chief of Abu Thabi, who,as Temimeh or leading light of the Hinawi persuasion in Northern Oman,is very generally respected and appealed to by. disputants belonging to that political division of the community,not because they are ne cessarily in any way subject to him,but simply because he is regarded as the nearest institution carrying sufficient weight to give them justice. would Asked finally with whom they^side supposing^that^Abu Thabi and Muscat were at war they replied that presumably^for Abu Thabi but that this was a matter in which they would be guided by the leaders at the headquarters of their tribe. This last sentence no doubt correctly gauges the situation, the fact being that the Bedouins or jungle-dwelling members of the community are too ignorant to have any decided id..as such a subject and would follow the lead of their elders at -the coast ports. 9&gt; While the Shihooh sparsely inbabit all the hills betweenbetween the two seas which wash the proinontory,there is a small break in their occupation of the coast line,which nevertheless is tenanted by a tribe to a great extent subject to them. In each of the next three bays are villages of the Zahooriyen (plural of Zahoori) / a tribe of Ghafiri persuasion whose hame has not been before mentioned. The names of their villages on the eastern shore of the (1.) KUBBAT GHAZIRA (Malcolm's Inlet.) (2.) KUBBAT SHABUS fg.) DUHAT SHISA. promontory are:- f Habalein In Kubbat Ghazira \ Makaka '.Filarn In Kubbat Shabus. . Shabus In Shisa Shisa The political status of this tribe is peculiar and needs ex planation. They claim to be part of the powerful Zahoori tribe inhabiting the Eereymee oasis and the Dhahireh district of Oman but admit that they have long since separated. At a later date I saw a good deal of the Bereymee stocl^ who distinguish themselves by using another form for the plural of their tribal cognomen,viz Zowahir instead of Zahooriyeen,and I questioned them regarding their kinsmen on the East coast. They said that they were aware that the tribe in question claimed kinship with them and while not prepared to disprove the claim to a common origin they had at any rate no present connection with the dwellers on the coast and were for all intents and purposes a distinct tribe^ belonging as they did to the Hinawi persuasion while the Zah ooriyeen posed as Ghafiris. The Zahoori villages referred to on the Mtusandam Coast are merely fishing hamlets whose occupants maintain themselves du ring the winter months by piscatorial enterprise. During the summer,from May to September,with the exception of a few indivi duals left behind for care-taking purposes,they migrate bodily to Dibba,Khor Fakan or Khasab,where they bivouac in the date plantations and attach themselves to one of the communities at those places. While on the Musandam Coast,which is their per manent home,they necessarily follow the fortunes of the Shihooh3^ /- J r who surround -them, although a Zahoori Shaikh if asked the question directly is naturally loth to admit that his tribe^ which comes of totally distinct stock and is 'Ghafiri'^ is tributary to another which is Hinawi; and in the event of any general Shihooh movement which the Zahooriyeen did not wish to join,it is possible that they might be driven to de sert the important Malcolm and Elphinstone Inlets which are now occupied by their villages exclusively,and to throw in their lot permanently v/ith the Jowasmis of Khor Pakan and Dibba. The vacated harbours would no doubt still be claimed by the Shihooh as part of their tribal territory and so the situa tion, so far as it affects the questions now under considera tion, might not be altered but the contingency seems to be one worth mentioning and taking into account. As regards the Sultan of Muscat I noticed that the Zahoori— yeen spoke respectfully and while not paying any tribute to him or his Wali at Khasab they seem to recognize His High ness in a patriarchal way and say that if any momentous dis pute arose amongst them they would appeal to him. 10 . .The next inhabited place after Shisa is Kumzar on KUMZAR, the northern face of the promontory,the home of the Kumazireh tribe^whose origin has been the subject of so much speculation among wri- ters on this part of Arabia. X took the opportunity afford ed to iiivestigate this question, but for the purposes of this report it is sufficient to say here that they are now com pletely merged in the Shihooh.who themselves are undoubtedly of Himyarite origin,and that there is ho need to different!- to betiween hhe t/wo bribes. he local elders claim a population of 1000 souls for Kumzar .n the winter but as there are not more than 200 houses .here is reason to think that this is an overstatement of Here\ X r* Here the people unequivocally and unhesitatingly acknowledge the sovereignity of* the Sultan of Muscat and aver that the whole of the Shihooh country is his territory and that all the Shihooh,except those occupying the village of Shuam and the. villages w.ot of it,, who from their situation have become dependent on the Jow- * asmea^ of Ras— el—Khaima,are the loyal subjects of Se^yid Pei sal and ready to fight for him when occasion demands# As this is the principal Shihooh-cum-Kumazireh village,the ex pression of the above sentiments by the elders is A some impor tance, but nevertheless needs to be discounted to some extent as the inhabitants knowing that I was Consul at Muscat and a friend of the Sultan would be inclined to exaggerate their ex pressions of good will to him in order to please me. Kumzar possesses no cultivation whatever,out they own 40 or 50 small sailing craft and 5 or 4 dhows which ply to Linga and the Batineh Coast of Oman with dried fisl for sale. Hone of their dhows engage in the pearl fishery,but a few individuals among them take service on board Shargah and Dabai pearl-fishing vessels. As they possess no plantations in Kumzar or its dependent ham lets, no duty is paid whatever in those places but during the date season all but about 200 of the community migrate to the date gardens of Khasab and Dibba and then pay whatever local dues are 't' here in fo rce * 11% The JQlor Ghub Ali is tenanted by three small hamlets of the Shihooh and Kumazireh. In the Elphinstone Inlet there are 5 villages,Shema,Sibi,Mada,Kanna and Nazifi. KHOR GHUB ALI KHOR-ASH-SHEM or (Elphinstone Inlet) KHASAB. These are all tenanted by the same Zahooriyeen mentioned as occupying the coast on the other side of the Maklab Isthmus, in Malcolm's Inlet. Like their fellows the inhabitants of these villages migrate in a great measure during the summer months but while in their permanent quarters they are included among the Beni Hadiyeh section of the Shihooh. Here they pay no tribute of any kind,but those among their number who own date gardenslUs o gardens in Dibba,Klior Fakan,or Khasab^or export, dates in any =- considerable quantity from those places p become liable for the customary duty collected therein. Khasab itself is a fine village with extensive date planta tions and an abundance of fresh water,to which it owes its Prosperity and popularity. Like Kumzar it is a permanent centre of the Shihooh and Kumazireh tribes. The Sultan's Wali,Kalid bin Sanai,appointed about 13 years ago at the in vitation of the Shihooh elders for the purpose of assisting them in keeping order among the heterogeneous migratory po pulation, is a quiet venerable old man of about 60. Accord ing to information given me by his son,the Wali does not re ceive any regular salary from Muscat but in lieu thereof makes what income he can from the duty which he is able to collect on the date produce and export. The amount collected must depend in a great measure on the good-will of the traders,as the Wali is not in a position to enforce his demands,but according to present information the sum realized varies from 300 dollars to 600 dollars per an num. Khalid bin Sanai’s functions are mainly of a Consular nature,in’connection with the floating population. With the permanent community of Shihooh he has^little or no concern, their affairs being managed by their^elders. IS. A little westward from Khasab lie the offshoot ham. lets of Kadda and Mookhi;thence after KHASAE to .TIBBA. rounding Cape Ras-esh-Shaikh-Masaood the coast-line turns southwards to- wards the Pirate Coast. From this point as far as Tibba the mountain range runs close to the sea.as it does on the east ern shore of the promontory;but at the basfs of some of tie deeper re-entrants lie sandy coves where sweet water is found below the surface,and these coves are occupied . spec tively by the Shihooh villages of Jirri, Jadi.Eokha.Fuda (or Fazghah),Ghamtha and Tibba,the c icf S alkh Mahomed bin Suleiman of the Peni Hadiyeh section. LikeV. Like t»he others they pay no tribute to the Sultan or any one else but express friendly and loyal sentiments towards him and their Shaikh abovementioned periodically pays a complimentary visit Seyyid Feisal in Muscat and has just now done so. Their particular friend in their own neighbourhood is the Trucial Chief of Debai,who is also a firm friend of Seyyid Feisal,and in any ordinary dispute which they could not settle locally they would in the first place ask the former to arbitrate before ap pealing to distant Muscat. A short distance beyond Tibba the mountain chain throws out a pronounced salient to the waters edge,making a palpable terri torial boundary,and then receding again, leaves at its base a gradually widening maritime plain resembling the Eatineh belt, until finally it makes a complete change of direction to the south and leaves the coast altogether. The inhabitants of the Shihooh villages,lying in the plain just mentioned, viz Shuam, Ghaleeleh, Khoweir and Rams are for practical purposes cut off territorially from the rest of their tribe and although in the event.of a general Shihooh rising they would no doubt throw in their lot with the Shihooh,they have for reasons of present expediency become subject to the Jowasmi of Ras-el-Khaima. Beyond' Tibba therefore the influence of the Sultan direct or indirect does not now extend and this point may be taken as the limit of the territory which can be held to fall within the scope of this report. 13. The conclusions to which further acquaintance with the subject have brought me differ little from those expressed in paragraph 6 of my letter No.534 dated 28th August 1901 to your address: .They are briefly:- (a.) That as far as and including Mureir the Sultan's jurisdiction is effective and indisputable. (b.) That from Kalba as far as and including the • southern half of Dibba the coast is subject to Jowasmi influence,which however is ineffective and 4and inconvenient,. (c. ) That, from and including the northern half of Dibba 3 round the Musandam promontory to Tibba on the Per sian Gulf shore the country is under the control oi* the Shihooh tribe, who, according to the ordinary acceptation of the term,are independent,seeing that they pay no tribute to anyone and manage their own tribal affairs,but who nevertheless look towards the Sultan of Muscat as a. friendly patriarch whose subjects they are pleased to call themselves and for whom they would probably fight if called upon, (d.)That owing; f irstly^to the fact that in the course of the protracted dispute regarding the sale df a valuable pearl,which has figured in the last 3 An nual. Administration Reports of this Agency, the Sultan's rights over and through a Kumzar tribes man were not disputed by the Pirate Coast Chiefs; and, secondly,owing to the fact that for some years past a Muscat representative,mainly ornamental though he is,has resided at Khasab,the Sultan would doubtless,if asked the direct question,claim jurisdiction over the Maklab Isthmus,and the Ras Musandam promontory. On the whole however I repeat the opinion that His Highness' so called jurisdiction is of such an ineffective and flimsy nature that it would be possible for His Majesty's Govern ment, if prepared to maintain their position either way a- gainst outside argument, to recognize or ignore its exis tence as may best suit our interests in these waters; for at the present moment no other power can have at their disposal the detailed information necessary to enable them to ques tion any statement of the position which we may formulate. They must either accept our exposition or prove an alter native one,which they can hardly have the local knowledge to attempt. AsAs to the selection or the alternative it is beyond my proviiice t»o offer, any remarks but I may perhaps be excused for expressing tie opinion that whichever direction the decision of Government take there should be no delay in following it up with such pur suant action as will serve to strengthen the position adopted against future question. 14. In this latter connection the following possible measures suggest themselves to me:- (a.) It will have been gathered from paragraphs 5 and 6 of this report that such jurisdiction as exists in the tract between Kal- TKE EXTINCTION OP JOWASMI JURISDICTION j ba and' Khor Pakan,and again at . Dibba,is not exercised in any way by the ruling Jowasmi Chief himself,but that the said ports having been originally alienated by his grandfather and uncle are now possessed by the descendants of the latter; persons who do not trouble themselves about the tranquility of the country but who it may be presumed are merely concerned in making what income they can *' - - * i * out of it during the date season. In any case it is evident that at the present epoch the Tiru- cial Chief of Shafgah who should be responsible for the maintenance of order in the tract in question,is unable to control it or to give ad- ’ * « equate protection and justice to persons,like the Shaikh of Pujaira,residing in it. The result of this state of things is,as you are aware from correspondence which has passed between us,that the non-Jowasmi Shaikhs of Khor Pakan and Pujaira have during the past year both offered their alle giance to the Sultan of Muscat and appealed to him to take the country over and save them from Jowasmee oppression. Under these circumstances it seems worthwhile considering whether the Sultan as soon as he becomesbecomes possessed of a steamer could not conveni ently be allowed to resume jurisdiction over that part of the coast now dominated* by the Jowasmis. If left to his own devices His Highness would pro bably set about the business by sending his stea mer to put Walis into the forts of 'is friends at Khor 5!akan,Fujaiira, and Dibba,with a sufficient force of merce^naries to hold them. If this course, were considered undesirable,pressure might perhaps be put upon the present holders in fief to accept, xrvd upon Seyyid Feisal to off er, in consideration of their retirement,a money payment in cash down or in a stated number of instalments representing in the aggregate the equivalent of 15 or 20 years* revenue. According td my information the incomes at present realized are approximately:- From the Khor Kalba,Khor Fakan tract .... 1000 dollars From Dibba 1500 dollars. By the above means the coast from Muscat to Dibba would be brought under the Sultan*s eifective ju risdiction. With regard to the Maklab Isthmus and the promon tory of Musandam, should Government think there is Kfi-OQCUPATION OF TELEGRAPH POST IN ELPHINSTONE INLET. any likelihood of the Elphinstone Inlet being required and should they be prepared if occasion ari- ses,to ignore the Sultan’s jurisdiction,I would suggest that,as a preliminary measure,and on the ostensible grounds that it would probably be re quired in connection with a contemplated extension of the MuscaWask Cable to Bunder Abbas, the old Telegraph Quarters in Elphinstone Inlet be re-oc cupied by the posting there of a native Agent m charge of a British Flag,as at Bassidorejor if considered preferable he might be posted on the IsbhmusIstilunus itself. This measure should in my opinion be carried out by t'le Res through th® telegraph .ship w Patrick dtewart” ident at Bushire without reference to the Sultan 01 /\ Muscat,who could subsequently be informed verbally by the Political Agent,if he asks any questions, in the sense abovementioned. The Government of India is,I htink,well awaxe that from a clima tic point of view the Elphinstone Inlet can only oe described as an Inferno during the hot weather months,any current of ail that penetrates it being heated up by the sunbaked hills over which it passes,and blowing through it as .3- fUi. ri ace. To take the other alternative: if Government decide that it will be more convenient to consider the Isthmus and pfomonotory as part of Muscat territory covered by the declaration of 1862 the Sultan should I think be pressed to assert himself in that neighbourhood as soon as he gets his steamer, by appointing VJa- lis at (Dibba), Lima,Bokha and Kumzar; a measure to which I do not anticipate that any opposition would be offered oy the tribes concerned so long as no fresh impositions were laid upon them. A copy of this report will be India by the next mail. forwarded to the Government 01 I have the honor to be, SIR, Your most obedient servant, kAJ OR, H.B.M.*s CONSUL &amp; POLITICAL AGENT, MUSCAT.GENEALOGICAL TREE of the JOWASMI FAMILY OF 3HARGAH. 3haikh 3uggar (now ruling Ras-el-Khaima) ** Up to ohaikh oultan’s death the ruling shaikh held the Jowasmi Colonies on the Oman Coast in his own hands. His son Shaikh Salim alienated them, giving Dibba and dependencies to his brother Ahmed, and the strip from brother Kalban to Khor Fakan to his Majid in fief. Rashid has A now succeeded Ahmed and Hamad has succeeded Majid.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00024e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/22</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00024e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/22</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File XVII/1 Naval Bases in the Gulf. Correspondence Concerning Above - Report by P.A. Muscat re. Sultan's Boundaries &amp; Limit of Jurisdiction in Northern Oman'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1901/1903</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-01-30T22:10:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (46 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 48; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-47; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials, primarily at the Political Residency in Bushire and the Political Agency in Muscat concerning the boundaries of the Sultan of Muscat's jurisdiction in northern Oman (Musandam Peninsula).In addition to this correspondence, the file contains the following:An extract from
                              La Depeche Colonialeentitled 'Les interests Francais Dans la Region de L'Oman' (folios 6-7)Map of the Musandum Peninsula (folio 21)'List of places on the coast from north of Dibba to Ras-el-Khymah' (folios 31-32)Extract from newspaper article entitled 'On the Persian Gulf', March 1902 (folio 35)A report 'regarding the nature and extent of the jurisdiction of the Sultan of Muscat in the direction of Cape Musandam and in Northern Oman generally' (folios 37-44)'Genealogical Tree of the Jowasmi [al-Qasimi] Family of Shargah' (folio 45)'List of Villages along the coast from Khor Fakan northwards and thence round to Tibba' (folio 46).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00024e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>