<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000028_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T14:18:04.260Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">^ t: c^ 'jv\cri^^ (x ~2- ^ I. ,!- JK - mamaiina. . V*.*- 0 -** D.Q. Ho. D.38Q£-I^44. Biternal Affairs Department, New Delhi, The May, ' 1944. * ^ T' •&gt; f- (V-tU }xJk JL wmm- , ■•r**’. /*• 4 ^1 V.' '-rJ You will have read Prior’s despatch Nx) r 5*B of J anuary 26ttu the last three paragraphs of which in partiuiilar'draw a sad picture of the state to which the South Persian Coast has been reduced by the Persian systems of State monopoly, control of distribution and'exchange control. In view ofxhe situation depicted by Prior, the possibility of doing something to help in the way of • cotton goods has been under consideration here. 2. The last quarter’s quota of piecegoods for Persia was 250 tons, of which 200 tons were earmarked for the Persian Goveranwit and 50 tons for private importers, in India and was exported only by Government, and we are naturally anxious lo see T.naT, piecegpoas sent from India are used to the best advantage. It has been suggested that a anall part of the total Persian quota, should be specifically earmarked for the South Persian coast; and since it is evident from Prior’s despatch that if this sub-quota is actually to reach the people of tne coast special arrangements would have to be devised for its despatch to the ports and its subsequent distribution, it would be necessary to obtain information regarding a) approximate minimum quantities required in yards, 'b ( ports of entry, } o) to whom to be con sipped, and ,dj arrangements for payment. To do the most good to the greatest number of people distribution to the villages rather than the towns would be the objective and this would probably have to be effected through local Khans end Shaikhs recommended by Prior. They would no doubt make some profit but better they than the Persian Government officials (c.f. paragraph 18 of Prior’s despatch) and the benefit would at least accrue to the tribeSw 4 * 9 - ‘ “ ’ r ■ ■ 3 . prior may think that distribution could be effected under arrannanents made by his Consul. If not,, an alternative surKestion is that approved merchants on the Trucial Coast should be^icensed to re-export the cloth to the Persian Government under the supervision of the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, much as licenses have been given covering the export of a proportion,of Persia's sugar quota via the Trucial Coast, thereby encouraging and reviving the ancient barter trade b»tweenfthe two shores of the Quit* . 14. The Stobassy’s views on the proposal to earmark a part of the total Persian quota anH piecegopds for the Gulf Ports are invited. 1 am sending copies of this letter to Peel and Prior and asking the latter for.his. views on the suggestions made regarding distribution of the piecegooos. Yours sincerely, 3d. ?t.R. Burnett, Lt-Col. A.S.H. Macann, Counsellor, British Legation, Io.kaiLL</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000028_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/932</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000028</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/932</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 3389/44 'South Persian coast as result Persian systems of State monopoly etc. help with cotton goods'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-26T12:08:29</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (2 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 4; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence from the External Affairs Department, New Delhi, to the Counsellor, British Legation, concerning the Persian system of state monopoly, control of distribution, exchange control and proposed responses, including the export of cotton goods from India and supervision from the Political Officer, Trucial Coast.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000028#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>