<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000884.0x0001b4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:56:02.795Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CONFIDENTIAL. ASSURANCES, UNDERTAKINGS AND AGREEMENTS, ETC. MADE BT CERTAIN CHIEFS AND KHANS OF SOUTHERN PERSIA THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT AND CERTAIN BRITISH TRADING COMPANIES. CALCTJTTA 1 GOVERNMENT OF INDIA PRESS , 1926Assurances, Under takings and Agreements, etc., made hy certain Chiefs and Khans of Southern Persia with the British Government and certain British Trading Companies. Serial No. Title. Date. 1 Translation of an Undertaking given by certain Notables of Luristan to Lieutenant A. T. Wilson in regard to the construction of a cart road through part of Luristan. June 8th, 1911. 2 Correspondence regarding right of option granted to Persian Railway Syndicate for construction of certain railway lines. February 9th, 1913. March 4th, 1913, January 10th, 1920. 3 Memorandum by Captain E. Noel on the position in 1917 in regard to concessions for roads and railways in South- West Persia. 1917. 4 Concession for the construction of a commercial road be tween Ahwaz and Tehran, with a branch from Burujird to Isfahan, and the establishment thereon of a transport service by wagons, carriages, etc., granted by the Persian Government to the Imperial Bank of Persia and subse quently transferred by them to the Persian Transport Company. August 5th, 1890. 5 Correspondence between the Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Haidar Khan, Hayat Daudi, C.I.E,, regarding the Pilotage fees, and guarantee of a payment of Tumans 2,000 per annum to latter, for duration of his life. February 12th, lO'JO. February 26th, 1920. 6 Agreement concluded between Messrs. Lynch Bros, on the one side, and Isfendiar Khan, Sirdar Assad, Mohamed Hussein Khan Sipahadar, and Haji Ali .vuli Khan on the other for the construction and maintenance of a road from Ahwaz to Isfahan, and from Shushter to Isfahan. March 3rd, 1898. 7 Concession granted by the Persian Government to Mr. W. K. D'Arcy for the exploration and exploitation of oil in the whole of Persia with the exception of the Provinces of Azerbaijan, Gilan, Mazandaran Astarabad and Khorasan. May 28th, 1901. ' 7(a) English translation of ditto 8 Agreement between Messrs. W. K. D'Arcy and the Con cession Syndicate Ltd., on the one hand, and the Bakhtiari Khans on the other, for the exploration and exploitation of oil, in the latter's territory. November 15th, 1905. 8(a) Telegram from His Britannic Majesty^s Charge d^Affaires, Tehran, intimating refusal of the Persian Government to recognize the Agreement between the Bakhtiari Khans and Messrs. W. K. D'Arcy and the Concession Syndicate Ltd., dated November 15th, 1905. i January 12 th, 1906.11 Serial No. Title. Date. 8{b) Letter from the Bakhtiari Khans to His Majesty^s Consul, Ahwaz, dealing with certain points raised in connection 'with their agreement with the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, dated November 15th, 1905. October 20th, 1906. 9 Agreement concluded between Mr. W. K. IVArcj and the Kili Sayyeds whereby the latter were compensated for loss incurred by them in connection with the D^Arcy Conces sion. October 1st, 1906. 10 Agreement brought about by His Majesty^s Consul, Ahwaz, with His Excellency Shahab-us-Saltaneh Ilbegi of the Bakhtiari in connection with the establishment of the Oil Company whereby the Ilbegi assumes temporarily all res ponsibility for protection and dealing with the Company. March 25th, 1907. 11 Agreement concluded between the Oil Company and the Bakhtiari Khans for the purchase of certain lands, cart, pipe-line and telephone roads required by the Company for their operations. May 1st, 1911. 11(a) Power of Attorney appointing Sardar Muhtesham and Sardar Bahadur as Agents for the Bakhtiari Khans with power to conclude negotiations with the Oil Company on their behalf. • 1910. 11 (i) Orders issued by the Bakhtiari Khans to their tribesmen not to interfere in any way with any of the Oil Company^s re presentatives. May 1911. 11(c) Undertaking by the Bakhtiari Khans to settle any claims put forward by the Kili Sayyeds to land sold to the Oil Company by the Bakhtiaris. May 1911. 12 Agreement made by the Oil Company with the Bakhtiari Khans for the protection of the pipe-line. April 28th, 1911. 13 Supplementary Agreement concluded between Mr. W, K. D'Arcy and the Kili Sayyeds with a view to facilitating the work of the Oil Company. February 10th, 1911. 14 Agreement concluded by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company with Parwiz Khan Gunduzulu for guarding Dar-i-Khazina and roads, etc., in neighbourhood. February 20th, 1911. 15 Agreement concluded between the Anglo-Persian Oil Com pany and Amir-i-Jang, Wali of Pusht-i-Kuh, for the explo ration and exploitation of oil in his territory. September 19th, 1919. 16 i Agreement concluded between the Anglo-Persian Oil Com pany and the Bakhtiari Khans regarding the terms on which land required lor the Company^s operations may be acquired. April 20th, 1921.iii • Serial No. Title. Date. 17 Agreement concluded between the Anglo-Persian Oil Company and Haidar Khan, C.I.E., of Hajat Daud, for the exploration and exploitation of oil in his territories, and for the protection of the Company's employes and works; and two letters regarding area of the Jarib in so far as it affects this agreement. October 6th, 1921. October 22nd, 192J. November 13th, 1921. 18 Agreement concluded between the Anglo-Persian Oil Company and the Kashkuli Khans for the exploration and exploitation of oil in their territory, and for protection of the Company's works and employes. October 14th, 1921. 19 Agreement concluded between the Anglo-Persian Oil Com pany and the Ilkhani of the Qashqais for the exploration and exploitation of oil in Qashqai territory, and an under taking by the Ilkhani to abide by the Kashkuli Agreement. May 20th, 1922. f-Assurances, Undertakings, Agreements, etc., made by certain Chiefs and Khans of Southern Persia, with the British Government and certain British Trading Companies. No 1. UNDERTAKING GIVEN BY CER TAIN NOTABLES OE LURIS- TAN IN REGARD TO THE CON STRUCTION OE A CART ROAD THROUGH PART OE THEIR TERRITORY. [ Translation. ] Undertaking in regard to the Lnristan- Arabistan road from the Saidmarrah River to Khorramabad made by the Sardar Akram (Nazar Ali Khan), Agha Eabbiya, Habibullah Khan, Diwan Begi, Walizadeh, Mirza Rahim Khan, Begler Begi, in the following terms:— In the event of the Persian Govern ment and the Amir Mofakhkham, Governor-General of Luristan, seeing fit and permitting a British Company to open a commercial road through Lnristan, via Tarhan and Chigni, the undersigned are agreed on the following terms to arrange for security on the road and to cause to pass merchandise, caravans and travellers without injury or molestation, so long as the wages of sowars and tofangchis are fixed and paid:— From Saidmarrah to the Kash- gan River, under the control of Sardar Akram Total Tor 4 stages . • From Kashgan to Khorramabad under control of Agha Rabhiya, Habibullah Khan Diwan Begi and Mirza Rahim Khan Begler Begi who have jointly made themselves responsible T ot AI o s Stages. S Td e) Oi w Sowars, stage. Tnmans Tmnans Tumans 4 1 to 15 5 at 8 40 ... 15 160 Total per mensem 275 Tumans. 2 1 ditto 5 ditto 5 ditto ... 15 80 50 Total per mensem 145 Tmnans. It is a condition that nothing shall be taken by the undersigned by way of ' Baj ' (road levy).2. The Company have the right to act in regard to the road in accordance with the concession which the Company possess from the Persian Government: they have not the right to go beyond it, and we agree not to object to it. 3. Wherever the Company desires to construct shelters and serais, it has the right to do so, and we are agreed not to demand any money for the land required for the cart road or buildings and the place of the serais but the selection of the locality should be with the approval of the undersigned. 4. The Company must provide quarters in the serais for the sowars and footmen. 5. The undersigned agree themselves to appoint the above-mentioned Tofangchis and to see that they are always present and to give them weapons and animals. 6. The Company should pay the sowars' and footmen's wages as above agreed upon in Khorramabad to the undersigned or their agents against their receipts, namely, 15 Tumans per headman, 8 Tumans per so^ar and 5 Tumans per Tofangchi, and it is moreover understood that the sowars and footmen must always be under the orders of the Company, and obey its direc- tious. /. If masons and labourers are needed for the road, and if they are not available in the lands of the undersigned, the Com pany has the right to import them from outside, and the Company's agent must fix the rate of wages to be paid to such men, and has discretion in the matter. 8. The undersigned are responsible that the sale of bread and food and straw and barley and fodder shall be free and that whoever of their subjects may sell, and whoever may buy, there is no restriction on buying and selling, with the caravan serais and caravans, and no objection shall be raised, and the undersigned themselves will fix a cheap current rate which shall be equivalent to what is just. 9. The Company has no right to levy tolls or any kind of tax on tribes who have formerly moved along the route on the condition that they may not load merchandise because the Company have the right to levy tolls on the latter. 10. If within the boundaries within which the undersigned have made them selves responsible, any damage accrues or loss by robbery occurs, owing to the action of tribes of Luristan or elsewhere, whether to merchandise, cash, goods, or to animals of muleteers, travellers, etc., whether by day or by night, the undersigned are3 responsible and agree to pay compensa tion without delay, on the condition that whoever or whatever tribe creates distur bances or robs caravans, when the under signed inform the Company's agent at Khorramabad, in order to assist in main taining the security of the road and the punishment of the guilty parties, an order shall be obtained from the Persian Government and the Governor-General of Luristan for the undersigned by the said agent, in order that they may take steps to obtain compensation, and if the thief is not known, it will be ex acted, according to custom, from the land of whatever tribe was near the locality of the robbery. 11. If at any time a force over and above that above provided for be required for the pursuit of robbers and the exaction of reparation for thefts that may have occurred, the undersigned have no right to demand anything under this head from the Company, but are themselves respon sible. 12. We, the Sardar Akram, Nazar Ali Khan, Wali of Pish Kuh, Habibullah Khan Diwan Begi, Mirza Kahim Khan, Begler Begi and Agha Rabbiya, are four persons who have jointly agreed as above and are sureties for each other, and will put in force the conditions of this agree ment. 13. I£ disorders occur and caravans be delayed, and the road be blocked, the wages (of the sowars, etc.) will not be paid, and the undersigned have no right to demand them, and if any theft takes place and we have not paid compensation, the Company will deduct the same from the monthly dues. 14. After all the above conditions have been given effect to and the arrange ments are to the satisfaction of the Com pany, a yearly wage shall be fixed by the latter and paid to the undersigned. 15. If any kind or property is required by the undersigned and the Company can obtain it from England, for the under signed, the Company shall obtain such goods according to customs, after all ex penses have been paid and 10 per cent, taken as profit, the Company shall send on the goods after receiving the cash. These clauses have been written as an agreement, on the understanding that as4 regards the despatch of goods the Com pany shall take a deposit of 10 per cent, and the remainder after the arrival of goods, as is their contract with merchants, let it be so with us. Dated 8th Jamadi-us-Sani 1329—(8th June 1911). L. S. SAEDAE AKRAM. L. S. MIRZA RAHIM. L. S. HABIBULLAH KHAN. L. S. AGHA HABBIYA. (Original Persian left in custody of Mirza Ali Akbar, British Consular Agent at Khorramabad.)5 No- 2. CORRESPONDENCE REGARDING RIGHT OF OPTION GRANTED TO PERSIAN RAILWAY SYNDI CATE BY PERSIAN GOVERN MENT EOR CONSTRUCTION OF CERTAIN RAILWAY LINES. Telegram (R.) No. 58, dated Tehran; the 9th February 1913. From—Sir W. Townley, To—Sir E. Grey. Your telegram No. 66 of 8th February, Minister for Foreign Affairs has written letter to Wood in following terms :— ' Persian*Government grant the right of option to Persian Railway Syndicate for construction of a railway from Mohammerah or a place adjacent thereto to Khor- ramabad, that is to say, either ahovementioned syndicate shall build railway in question by means of loan on conditions to be hereafter arranged as a State railway at the expense of the Persian Government, or the Persian Government shall grant Syndicate a concession for con struction of the abovementioned railway on conditions to be arranged hereafter. In latter case Syndicate shall build at its own expense and responsibility. In order to be in a position to choose one of the two above mentioned methods and to draw up the necessary conditions a preliminary survey is necessary. Persian Government agree to commence this survey now in co operation with Syndicate, ex penses of survey to be defrayed by Persian Government, on condition that if, after the com pletion of survey, Persian Govern ment, by virtue of their right to select one of the two abovemen tioned methods of construction, should decide to grant a con cession to syndicate, the same shall refund to Persian Govern ment expenses incurred in survey. ' Obviously Persian Government will provide at their own expense means for protection of engineers and surveyors. Period of this right of option is for two years from date of this letter.'6 la communicating to me a copy of above letter ' chef de cabinet' was in structed to express hope that Syndicate would be good enough to submit at as early a date as may be convenient a draft concession in order that conditions of the two draft proposals may be taken into serious consideration at once with a view to no time being lost in making selection between the alternative methods of construction.Copy. 4th March 1913. Your Excellency, On behalf of the Persian Railway Syndicate, Limited, I have the honour to accept the railway option as set forth in the letter you kindly handed to me on the 2nd instant, and of which the following is an English translation :— 'To Mr. Wood, Director of the Im perial Bank of Persia and Representa tive of the Persian Railways Syndicate.' 'In view of the numerous verbal dis cussions and the proposal which you, as Representative of the Persian Railways Syndicate, have made to the Persian Government, I have the honour to inform you that the Persian Government grants the right of option to the above Syndi cate for the construction of a railway from Mohammerah or some spot adjacent there to, to Khorramabad, that is to say, either the above-mentioned Syndicate shall build the railway in question by means of a loan, on conditions to be arranged hereafter by mutual consent as a State Railway at the expense of the Persian Government, or the Persian Government, on conditions to be arranged hereafter by mutual consent, shall grant the Syndicate a concession for the construction of the above-mentioned railway. Since, in order to arrive at a decision in the matter, and for the drawing up of the necessary con ditions, preliminary study and survey are necessary, the Persian Government agrees to begin the above-mentioned study and survey from now in co-operation with the Syndicate and at the expense of the Persian Government, on the condition that, if on the completion of the survey and study the Persian Government should decide to grant a concession for the con struction of the railway to the Syndicate, the Syndicate refund to the Persian Gov ernment the expenses which that Govern ment has incurred for the study and survey. Obviously, the Persian Govern ment will provide, at its own expense, the means for protecting the engineers and sur veyors. The period of this right of option is from this date until the lapse of two years, within which period the Persian Government shall communicate its deci sion to the Syndicate; but the result of the survey with the necessary information must be submitted to the Persian Govern ment six months before the end of that period. Should events of force majeure hinder the operations of the surveyors,8 the period of the right of option and the period fixed for presenting the result of the survey will be prolonged for a period equal to that during which the above- mentioned operations have been delayed.' I have the honour to be, Your Excellency, Your obedient, humble Servant, (Signed) A. 0. WOOD. His Excellency Vossugh-ed-Dowleh, Minister for Eoreign Affairs, Tehran.9 Tersian Minister for Foreign Affairs to Persian Raihoay Syndicate {Limit ed). January 10/1920. Sirs, following the option granted the Persian Railways Syndicate by my Gov ernment on the 24th Eabi-el-Awal, 1331, and the Minister of Foreign Affairs' letter of the 19th March, 1914, I have the honour to inform you that my Govern ment agree to the extension of the Mohammerah-Khorramahad line men tioned in the above documents to connect with a point on the prospective Khanikin- Tehran-Enzeli -Bailway. It is, however, understood that the said extension shall be governed by the terms specified in the arrangements concerning the proposed Khanikin-Tehran-Enzeli Railway. I am, etc., PIROUZ. Tersian Minister for Foreign Affairs to Persian Railways Syndicate {Limit ed). January 10, 1920. Sirs, Referring to the memorandum o^ the 2nd December 1919, forwarded to me by S. Pearson and Son (Contracting Department) (Limited), with reference to the construction by your Syndicate of railways in Persia, I now have the authority to reply thereto as follows :— 1. My Government are glad to take note that the Persian Railways Syndicate has been strengthened by the association with it of Messrs Vickers and Armstrong- 'Whitworth. They recognise the right of the Persian Railways Syndicate in connection with the construction of the Mohammerah-Khorramabad line under the terms of the option of the 24th Rabi- el-Awal, 1331, and of the Minister of Poreign Affairs' letter of the 19th March 1914. 2. The Persian Government, moreover, grant to the Persian Railways Syndicate (Limited), the right of option for the construction and equipment of a railway from Khanikin to Tehran, via Kerman- shah, Hamadan, Kazvin, with branch to Enzeli on the Caspian Sea, or from Khanikin .to Hamadan and Tehran by10 such other route as may ultimately be decided after survey, provided in any case that railway line shall be extended via Kazvin to Enzeli on the following con ditions :— (а) That the Persian Railways Syndicate undertake immediate ly a survey of the said railway, in which work they will receive the co-operation of the Persian Government's representatives free of cost to the Syndicate. (б) That the cost to the Syndicate of the surveys (including any pre liminary and admi nistrative expenses to be agreed between the Persian Government and the Railways Syndicate in connection with organisation and prepara tion) be in the first place borne by the Persian Railways Syndi cate (Limited), such cost to be recouped to the Syndicate with interest at 7 per cent, per annum, such interest to be pay able by the Government at the end of each year until full recoupment, either:— (1) By the Persian Government if construction is undertaken as a State railway for the account of Persian Govern ment , or (2) By the eventual railway company to be formed, if such company should ulti mately be decided on. 3. The preliminary plans and estimates for the railways mentioned in paragraphs 1 and 2 shall be submitted to the Persian Government within eighteen months from this date, subject to such reasonable extension of time as may be agreed upon by both parties as necessary owing to possible difficulties arising from force majeure, and in one year thereafter the Persian Government shall either :— (a) Decide to have the railway built as a State railway in manner above-mentioned ; or (&amp;) Shall grant to the Syndicate a concession for the construction and working of the said railway on customary and acceptable terms as may be agreed. 4. In the event that the railways should be constructed and equipped as State railways by the Syndicate for the account of the Persian Government, payment for11 the undertakings (together with an agreed percentage for the profit of the Syndicate) shall be made by the is r ue from time to time as the money may be required by the Syndicate, of Persian Government Bonds bearing an agreed rate of interest, with capital amortisabie at fixed dates, and secured by the necessary guarantees, or in such other manner as may be agreed. In the event of the syndicate being granted concessions for the said railways, the Persian Government will guarantee the financial requirements on such terms as may be necessary and practicable, 5. If the railway or railways are run as State railways the Syndicate shall have the right to work them on behalf of the Persian Government for a period of years on terms to be arranged. 6. For the purpose of survey, construc tion, and working of the said railway, the syndicate shall be entitled to the free use of all roads and bridges, and shall be entitled to carry passengers, goods, and materials which may be required for rail way work. 7. Should the Persian Government, after the expiry of the periods of time mentioned in Article 3, decide not to con struct the railways as State railways, and should the Syndicate not be agreeable to accepting a concessit n on reasonable and practicable terms, then the Persian Gov ernment shall give notice that after six months following the above-mentioned period they will take over the plans and surveys and pay for them a price equal to the cost thereof and interest thereon. Please write me a formal acceptance of these terms. I am, etc., FIROUZ. Fersian Minister for Persian Mailtoays ed). Foreign Affair % to Syndicate {Limit' January 10, 1920. my Dear Sies, Eeferring to the paragraph 6 of letter of this date granting the Persian Railways Syndicate the free use of all roads and bridges in connection with the construction of the railway and its work, it is hereby noted that the Syndicate will ■12 be allowed the following facilities with regard to the rights-of-way :— If the lands required to constitute the rights-of-way or to be used for the build ing of works, operating plants, stations, etc., are State property, their use will be allowed the railway free of charge if they are not cultivated, or if cultivated a reasonable charge will be made in the owners interest. If, however, the lands belong to private individuals the Syndi cate shall agree with the owners as to the price to be paid, but the owners will in no case be allowed to exact a price exceed ing that ordinarily charged in the province. As to all other materials and facilities which the Syndicate may require for the survey, construction, and working of the railway, if these materials belong to the State, the Persian Government hereby agree to furnish them either free of charge or, in cases where these have an established monetary value, at a reason able price. And if the above-mentioned materials and facilities are controlled by private ownership the Persian Govern ment agree to use their good offices in favour of the Syndicate, securing them on reasonable terms and at prices ordinarily current in the respective districts. I am, etc., PIROUZ. Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs to Fersian Hailways Syndicate {Limit ed). January 10, 1920. Dear Sirs, Referring to the agreement made with you for the prospective construction of the Khanikin-Tehran-Enzeli Railway, I note that the Syndicate is anxious to have the right to exploit the available water powers which may be needed in connection with the construction and operation of the said line. While I agree in the necessity to fur nish every facility to the Syndicate for the execution of the contemplated railway project, and I am ready to undertake, in due course, all practicable plans to the end, I am, however, constrained to note the following consideration The proposition above referred to is of such complex nature and vast scope in its13 possible interference with the property- rights of individuals, and with the muni cipal interests and public utilities of vari-' ous districts, for which certain concessions have already been granted to other parties, that I find it impossible to come to a definite decision upon the matter at present. I, however, believe that the best means for reconciling the urgent needs of the proposed railway in this respect with the above consideration is for the syndicate to send a hydro-electric expert to Persia with the Eailway Survey Commission who is to start shortly for that country, to make a survey of the water-power sites in the vicinity of the projected railway line. As it is the desire of my Government that the railways should be worked in the most economic manner, I can assure you that, after the report of the water-power expert has been submitted, they will be willing to make a favourable decision within the limits dictated by the urgent needs of the railway and the interests of the country. I am, etc.. miouz.14 No. 3. MEMORANDUM REGARDING CON CESSIONS FOR ROADS AND RAILWAYS IN SOUTH-WEST PERSIA UP TO 1917. The Persian Transport Company whose shares are held privately in the names of the shareholders of the Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company and the Imperial Bank of Persia own the concession for the Tehran to Ahwaz and Mohammerah ohaussee with a branch to Burujird and Ispahan. The chaussee has been completed from Tehran to Kum and Sultanabad. The mora important provisions of the concession are— (а) The Persian Government is entitled to 20 per cent, of the net profits. (б) The Company is said to have the monopoly of the transport service on the road. (c) Uncultivated land is granted gratis. A good deal of misconception exists in regard to the interests of the Persian Transport Company in the existing Ahwaz-Ispahan Caravan road. This is chiefly due to the road being known as the ' Lynch road ' which has given rise to the impression that Messrs. Lynch Brothers own the concession, and that they transfer red it to the Persian Transport Company along with other rights. This is, however, not the case. The concession was obtained direct from the Persian Government by the Bakhtiari Khans, and the only interests in the undertaking, which Messrs. Lynch Brothers were in a position to dispose of, are limited to— («) The option to find any further capital required by the Sakhtiari Khans for the improvement or conversion of the present caravan road. (6) The right to collect the tolls on the present road as a collateral security for the repayment of the money advanced to the Khans for the construction of the road. The sum outstanding on the road con struction account is one which the Khans could easily afford to pay at any time and the Persian Transport Company's interests in the present Ahwaz-Ispahan road consist only in their right to advance the capital required and carry out the con-15 struction of any conversion or adaptations of the present track from a caravan into a cart road. As, however, the present concession is not one that would cover the construction of a motor road or railway, and even if in consequence the Khans applied for a fresh concession, it is an open question whether the Persian Transport Company's right to advance capital and carry out construction would still remain valid. On the other hand, the Persian Tran sport Company as the inheritors of Messrs. Lynch Brothers' interests, may be said to possess certain moral claims and a vested interest, in that they were the pioneers of this route, have always been closely associated with its development, and this year displayed some initiative in sending their engineer to examine the new alignment. The only other stake that the Persian Transport Company possess in South-West Persia is a half share in the Persian Kail- way Syndicate. Shortly after the latter was formed and obtained the option for the construction of the Khorremabad line, the Persian Transport Company pointed out that the proposed activities of the Ilailway Syndicate would be an infringe ment of their rights. As a result of their representation the Foreign Office sug gested to the Persian Railway Syndicate, who agreed, that they should admit the Persian Transport Company to a half share, viz., to subscribe £15,000 of the £30,000 capital of the Syndicate. Turning now to the rights and interests of the Railway Company Syndicate. As already stated they have obtained the option for the Khorremabad line, which however requires renewal, and in 1913 they incurred considerable expenditure in connection with the preliminary surveys. Further the fact that they have come to an arrangement with the Persian Tran sport Company, practically assures them an open field in Luristan. It has already been mentioned that there should be an amalgamation of interests in South-West Persia. Perhaps the most promising means of bringing this about would be for the parties interested to extend to the Bakhtiari country the principle of amalgamation already success fully applied in the case of their Luristan interests. A round table conference in London should be able to reconcile any divergence of views or interests, if such exist.16 No- PEESIAN TRANSPORT COMPANY'S CONCESSION POR THE CON STRUCTION OP A COMMERCIAL ROAD BETWEEN AHWAZ AND TEHRAN AND THE ESTABLISH MENT OF A TRANSPORT SER- VICE THEREON. Article 1. —The Persian Government grants the concessionnaire for a period of sixty years commencing from the date of the signature of the present concession, the right:— {a) of building one road between Ahwaz and Tehran, and another between Burujird and Ispahan; (6) of buildiag at his own expense, wherever he may consider it suit able, caravansarais, bridges, workpeople's houses, stables, blacksmiths' and carpenters' shops, which may be necessary for the construction of the road; (c) of establishing of regular trans port service of goods and travel lers ; (d) of constructing watercourses along the road wherever he may consider it necessary and no water is to be found, and of cultivating all arable lands be longing to the State and situated within a radius of 4,000 yards from the centre of each station ; (e) of selling and exporting the pro duce of these lands; (/) of letting out the ground brought under cultivation by the conces sionnaire to Persian subiects only; (ff) of levying atoll only on the bridges built by the conces sionnaire, the road itself being free from toll; he must come to an arrangement beforehand with the Government about this toll. Article 2. —The Government grants the ground on which the buildings above men tioned shall be raised free of charge, in so far as it belongs to the Government; if it belongs to individuals, the concessionnaire must either buy or hire the ground from the owners thereof. Article 3.—The road, buildings, material, and all works carried on, with all their buildings, shall be under the high protec tion of the Government, and with a view17 to attract the carriage of goods and travel lers, and to increase commerce, the con- cessionnaire, in all that concerns the road and the carrying out of his various works, as well as regards the transport service, will have the right of being protected by the Government, and the Governors of the districts and provinces through which the road passes will receive formal orders to facilitate the execution of the conces- sionnaire's engagements and to protect the road and all the property of the conces- sionnaire by force of arms if necessary. Article 4. —The concessionnaire shall have the right of calling in foreign capital and of procuring the assistance of foreign employes and engineers for the works of the road. Article 5. —The concessionnaire shall have the right, specially recognised by His Majesty the Shah, of pledging the building works of the road, as well as the houses, kanats, watercourses, etc., and the material and stock of the transport service to the capitalists who shall have lent money for the building of the said road, the material, houses, etc., as a guarantee for the security of their funds. The present concession shall not be withdrawn for sixty years, and until the capitalists have been fully reimbursed for the sums they have advanced, and the works of the road are completed. The road must be completed in 2J years.* Article 6. —The works shall begin six months after the issue of the firman, other wise the said concession shall be null and void. Article 7, —One year after the transport service has been started the concessionnaire shall pay at the end of each year a sum equal to 20 per cent, of the net profits of the working to the Government, and the Government shall not levy any land or other tax on the cultivated ground or on the produce of this ground, or on the buildings raised for the works or any of the moveable or immoveable property of the concessionnaire, and shall further admit, free of duty, all machines and material necessary for the working of the road, but the Customs House officers may examine this material in order to ascertain whether it is in fact destined for the work ing of the road. Article 8. —The concessionnaire shall carry the Imperial mails at half rate, and as regards the transport of goods and pas sengers shall guarantee that no person is given preference to another, but shall • bubje-iuently extended to 27th May 1913,18 treat the public cm equal terms, and give no offence to any person. Article 9. —The concessionnaire may employ a maximum number of 30 Euro peans, who are bound to respect the laws and customs of Persia. Article 10. —In order to be able to levy the 20 per cent, of the net profit, the Per sian Government shall have the right of examining the account books of the firm by means of a special delearate every six months. Article 11. —The concessionnaire shall deposit with the Imperial Bank of Persia caution money to the amount of £10,000 for which sum he shall hand over the re ceipt of the Bank to the Persian Govern ment as a guarantee for the completion of the road, which must be finished in three years after the date of issue of the firman. This caution money of £10,000 shall be repaid to the concessionnaire in portions of five, that-is to say, £2,000 for every fifth part of the road completed, and in case the road shall not be completed at the time fixed, the remainder of the caution money shall lapse as of right to the Per sian Government. Article 12. —At the expiration of sixty years from^ the date of the issue of the firman, in tne event of the concession not being renewed, all the immoveable pro perty shall belong to Government, and in case the Government should require the moveable material, it shall buy the same from the concessionnaire. (L. S.) seal of the AMIN-ES-SULTAN (L. S.) seal of the QAWAM-UD DAULEH. In the Shah's handwriting :— By God's wish, this concession for the Arabistan and Tehran road is correct. ' It is correct ' Dated 1807. I hereby certify that the above is a true translation made at this Consulate General. i - ut* FRANCIS B. CEOW, British Vice-Consul. Gulaheh, August 6tht 1S90.19 FIRMAN. (Translation.) As the period of ten years stipulated in the firman, dated 19th Jemadi-ul-Avel 1320. for the completion of the roads enu merated in the said firman, terminated on the 19th .Temadi-ul-Avel 1330, and as the Lynch Company, which is the owner of the concession for the above-mentioned roads declared that force majeure prevent ed it from completing the above-mentioned roads and requested an extension of time, the Government of His Imperial Majeaty the Shah gives the owner of the aforemen tioned concession time from the date of this document up to seven years for the completion of the roads on the following condition :— If during the course of these seven years extraordinary events and disorders occur in the kingdom which can be de scribed as force majeure* and on account of which the completion of the said roads will not be possible for the owner of the concession, three further years will be added to the seven years. If at the ex piration of the last three years the build ing of the roads is not completed, the said concession will be entirely terminated and null and void, and the owner of the con cession will on no account be able to make any excuse or urge force majeure for an application to the Persian Government for a renewal. If during the course of this period which is available to the Company for making the roads, the company pro poses to exchange its numerous documents relating to the concession, for one single concession, and should an agreement be come to with the Persian Government authorities, there will be no refusal. 34 Rebi-ul-Arel 1831 (March 3,1918).20 No. 5. COMPENSATION POE LOSS OF PILOTAGE PEES, AMOUNTING TO Ts. 2,000 PEE ANNUM TO BE PAID TO HAIDAE KHAN, HAY AT DAUDI, C.I.E. 1 No. 94, dated Bushire, the 12tli February 192(&gt;; From —Lieutenant-Colonel A. P. T revor, C .S .L, Deputy Political Resident, Persian Gulf, • c f To— H aidar K ha * H ayat D audi , C .I .E., Bandar Rig. After compliments. —With reference to the correspondence ending with my letter No. 5, dated 3rd January 1920, regarding the question of the pilotage fees for pilots taking vessels across the Shattel Arab bar and up the river to Basrah, I have pleasure in informing you that the Civil Commis sioner has been able to settle the matter in accordance with the suggestions of your late friend Mr. Bill in a very satisfactory manner according to my view. In your letter of the 1st Eamazan last you estimated your annual income from this source at Tumans 1,200—2,000 per annum. The Civil Commissioner now informs me that the Port Authorities at Basrah will agree to the annual charges to the higher amount; the Mesopotamian Administration is therefore prepared to pay you commenc ing from January the 1st of this year 1920, the sum of Tumans 2,000 every year, and to guarantee this payment to you for the duration of your life. You may take it for certain that during the next few years the Shattel Arab bar will be dredged, and thoroughly well lighted and buoyed, after that of course, the Captains of ships will take their ships across the bar and up the river themselves ; then will there be no need for pilots at all. In these circumstances you must regard this scheme as extremely advantageous to yourself and in point of fact not as a pay ment of pilotage fees in the future, but rather as a reward for good services render ed to the High Government in the past.. k-i*/® Ojl w m &lt;A m ^ m ^ irrA ***' ^ l wjh** yjr Pr o ls/C r/* -AKXS) &lt;AjJ I—TjtA. j Oj|o oU^ - I m ) ^ s'j -- I i j. I p** aj o iTf^A j-jjo v£j.bl J dj dJGL (j]jS (J./ pSla*. if ^]j jJisr*'** lj J xj I dJiw-^I ^r- ^■3 d-l ^-v ^ O - SVVM/ dJL'WiX' J| diillMf |j OjA. ofjjlc di«ii&gt;/ ^Uio| ^ % y &amp;i . jy*^ ^ iXfcav® jib d-T jjs*} )ik|j isAdj tjy jj-fjs*y^y d^«-Ji ^ ^y y/bz- $jc j *1 0 JUoU* j . ^yjyj* dJU|^f- ^LijLjk^ ^ '^5 ]a2&gt; jyk. JU dS Jkblaj - cVioUjj jiyJaf obj «_Ui^ ; c-jU» j]y djtrk. O^j ^A.jO l» OMiiSx/* jykc jjL. j] |O^i. y^i ^y icVjl y ^i* ^ d^ *y*&amp;} L*' ^1121 In view of the facts above and of the probability that in a few years' time no pilots will be required, it is obvious that the arrangement suggested is personal to yourself and will cease with your lifetime. Should the employment of the pilots have ceased at the time of your demise it must be understood that payments will lapse in toto&gt; otherwise a fresh agreement will be made with your successor according to the circumstances of the moment. As remarked above I regard this pro posed settlement as very satisfactory, and advantageous to you ; it will assure you a fair income from this source and obviate any difficulties of collecting it or corre sponding with the Eesidency or the Basrah authorities regarding its recovery and strongly advise to accept the arrangement. I i X mi c?, JJ jii iS iol/cJkiL •J j (jj* ^ m L ' ^)| 4/ j .&amp;j Jt-*' i** iS . dj) ^^5- /I J cfk* 0 * 1 iyy (i/j o^j ^JkLT j L«UJ . ^4 Aa.j is dk^lulj v jj.woL-e L| 0 ' ^ t^f HI; lij.mt.k'* l - £&gt;j'* otjuaiii/c jjfs* ijji jj sjjjjiaj U.A (wA ii i) 6y 'r^ ) Sf/ ^ J &lt;/' u; J / Jr'; J ^ — Mt ■ ^ ut-*' «&gt;b ^|jk'ju^ OJyo ^b) *y{t&gt;isx*.i jjly vJilT iU^j veJjsjjjjJb ^IS urJ U }*22 Dated 5tli Jamadi II, 1338 (26tli February 1920). Received 1st March 1920. From—H aidar K han H ayat D audt , C.I.E., Zabet of Hayat Daud and Kharg, Bandar Rig, To—Lieutenant-Colonel A. P, T eevoe , C.S.I., C.I.E., Deputy Political Resident, Per sian Gulf, Bushire. After compliments. —I was glad to re ceive your letter of 11th Eabi II No. 5 •which you wrote in reply to my letter of 4th Rahi II on the subject of pilotage fees, and which was very satisfactory and gave me much hope; and I was waiting for your second letter so that I may get the desired result in this question when I received your letter of 21st Jamadi I on the 1st Jamadi II. I read it with great pleasure, understood its contents and it was the source of great gratitude and pride for me. I am satisfied, pleased and grate ful for the sanction of payment to me of Tomans 2,000 per annum with effect from the month of January of this present English year 1920 heretofore, i.e., during my lifetime, on account of pilotage fees in accordance with the late Mr. Bill's sug gestion which was approved by the Civil Commissioner of Mesopotamia and your new proposal in continuation of the late Mr. Bill's suggestion to the Civil Commis sioner. You said that I should not consider this amount as a pilotage fee but as a recog nition of past good services. It is so of course and I admit that the kindness and attention of the authorities of the High British Government and the assistance of the Besidency have been and are greater and better than my services. I consider this special consideration and connection a valuable treasure for my descendants. | A iiw * JI^V; jyiy CV XajJ; iiuJUj Jy^j! teyj* &lt;—0 4^ (3^aA. to «tUJ »U fj-yf I J ) j is dijJlAJ j &amp;l'y* j mji i^sjzyl OjJ ^ t^uu dJlJtAM./ 4 | jii &amp;sr};^ is t&amp;yj ^ O ^ L a ^ ^31| ^ ^ &lt;0L -c- it/® ^ 1 ^ ^ Ojbj y UJO| b tsyyla/o j hycj.** y s.3j,y]a./* y j I - ^ ^ U*-*! | q (-♦ di-Jl ssb jl j* «j&gt;b oU^^i Ij ^^*-1 t-AJkRj (J j.) ijc ^ clijao.** CijJls* J (jlj- £ ij--^ ^1 y j \ys^ S«j^vS.C jO ^'Lc Jjji ^ ^S'Lsr? va^jb vi/-^ iJOOj-T ^ diJoI ^ ^4*'j j ^ o h &lt;j^' c vi^' ^ aaa. 1 } ^i)jo cdy-js. ^ Oc^cl*«fc/ ,e j ) ^^AIOI AJyj j i A^UA,^ j ioj) tsyi oU&lt;A2 w jl yi v J ^ j iwjlai! ^ 1^3 \j jl ' &gt;»j|^Av&lt; ^ w—•«.*&gt; |j d^Lka^ ^./&lt;) j I vAll^J j«aa^, ^saa* v^rllo) yt^cllsl ^ ^-ala/# ' Sf 0 j' 0 if23 No. 6. AGBEEMENT CONCLUDED BE' TWEEN MESSES. LYNCH BEOS. AND CEETAIN BAKHTIAEI CHIEFS EOE THE CONSTEUC- TION AND MAINTENANCE OE A EOAD EEOM AHWAZ TO ISFAHAN AND SHUSHTEE TO ISFAHAN. Article 1. —Isfendiar Khan, Sirdar Asad, Moliamed Hussein Khan Sipahadar, and Hadji Ali Kuli Khan having jointly ob tained a concession from the Imperial Persian Government, under the date 23rd April 1897, for the construction and main tenance of a road with its caravanserais from Ahwaz to Ispahan, and from Shushter to Ispahan and having in virtue of Article b the right of calling in the aid of capital ists, Messrs. Lynch Brothers agree to make such advances for the execution of the works as hereinafter appear. Article 2. —The concessionnaires agree to pay Messrs. Lynch Brothers 6 per cent, per annum on their outlay, and to repay the capital sum in the course of 25 j ears by annual instalments of 1, 100 Tumans, with the proviso that during the first and second years, commencing from the date of the signature of this Agreement, no payments whether on account of interest or of instalments shall be made. The first interest and first instalment shall be paid at the end of the third year, counting from the aforementioned date. Subsequently, the interest and instal ment shall be paid at the end of each suc ceeding year, the interest being calculated on the balance of capital after the deduction ,of the instalments paid on account of capital. Payments of interest and instalments of capital to be made to Messrs. Lynch Bro thers at Ahwaz. Article 3. —The concessionnaires agree to intrust the whole of the work of adapting existing ways or tracks for caravans and of the formation of diversions and of construc tion, whether of bridges or caravanserais or in any way in connection with the roads to Messrs. Lynch Brothers, who, on their part, agree to carry out the following works as soon as practicable after the signa ture of this Agreement, namely, to place an iron bridge over the Karunat Godar-i- Balutak, to build a bridge at Pul-i-Amarat, j jb ^ )) a* J' j) (AqV ft' J j| dl' ) &lt;^1 jkxi)jd J J-i* j)J* Jl J^s ) ; ^ ^ j's J) oJUJla- j j Jj' 4xAX/* ojb (UU jlj'j (.Jt - ' J ; | ; SxALc J ; } ; tyijjOji) ^jx f ioLw.3| y jA- J jO 4))0 if J totix* J Jl tXsO * Jj) jljjbjsj jj JjJ J^l iol^if JtWlAXib if I jjj JI S.*JlXy* y ixjj j 1OLMJ| J is*i &gt;■ ' - —| fh*' ) ]j £ (s jy* jlja/e) t]y j j| j ^■'v j ^ I; y, ) ^ \jh^y ) 3 aioUJ vb'hi J S.f dy * 1 ! j] j* ^ &lt;^.Ua&gt;&lt;c| j] O aj | j (j/il j' ^ (jj o^l^c1 24 to clear the present track of boulders wher- eyer M essrs. Lynch Brothers deem it neces sary or expedient, and to build caravan- serais and temporary or other residences for engineers or work-people at such points^ as they (Messrs, Lynch Brothers) may consider necessary for present exigencies^ Messrs. Lynch Brothers undertake to exe cute the works aforesaid for a sum not ex ceeding £5,500, and it is understood that the conditions of the concession granted to 1 the concessionnaires by the Persian Gov ernment have been complied with when they have been executed. Should it be deemed expedient at any time by the con cessionnaires and Messrs. Lynch Brothers to spend more capital, as by converting or adapting any road from a caravan into a cart road, increasing the number of cara vanserais or in any other manner, Messrs. Lynch Brothers are to have the right to advance the capital and carry out the con struction upon the terms as nearly as prac ticable as those hereinbefore agreed upon. All details of construction of bridges or caravanserais or in connection with the road shall be left to the discretion of Messrs. Lynch Brothers. The number, size, and locality of the caravanserais shall ftlso be left entirely to their option. Article 4.—The concessionnaires bind themselves to always keep the roads and bridges, etc., in good order, and, whenever repairs are necessary, to carry them out &gt; Whenever engineers are necessary, or the repairs are such as the concessionnaires cannot execute themselves, the engineers of Messrs. Lynch Brothers will be employ ed, and in that case all expenses incurred fey Messrs. Lynch Brothers will be paid by the concessionnaires. Article 5.--The concessionnaires agree to supply to Messrs. Lynch Brothers such labour and materials as may be locally procurable at fair and reasonable ratesj and also to supply land free of charge for the erection of the caravanserais. Article 6. —The concessionnaires agree to afford all necessary protection to the engineers, workmen and others employed by Messrs, Lynch Brothers without charge- dtf dJaal ^ jj &amp;JU ^ Ij Ur 5 ? cUJJ 6j y ^ ^ y aobj it ]j if oySo/* ^.taj b Juwlx) I iyd j] y ^ I; (ir* Jpy I y jU'L*) ^.xj ^ y* U| r -j|^^ Jf^cb J.ui' v&gt;\j£ ^1;;^ 8 |; ^ j ^ jti* £ b oixi' sjbj )j ^ {j 0 j* vJ[^v ^ &gt; »♦ diuuw a/ ^ lyb 4Xij|J |^| ^XjJ jljj2k.b i]ji j C j J ^.AjiAy Cfy') v ^ I ^ y ■ cy) ij^st tyjt jxi IAI I) tyh ^ ) j* j f\yi vviolyu j oymi ph y gJuJ \y\ ds J jj ai|«4&gt;y - JUL*? j aJl6.£ is cVuUijk/* J^wjUx«| tyz law ^b*) is *\j A * ft**** j JI 4/ jjxi jbu&gt;l viO 4 ^ UHtbiv*25 Article 7. —Tlie conccssionnaires gua rantee the passage of all animals, materials and goods imported by Messrs. Lynch Bn&gt; thers for the purpose of construction of all or any of the works absolutely free of all charges, tolls, rahdari, etc., whether local or Imperial. Article 8. —The tolls are to be collected by collectors from time to time appointed by the concessionnaires. The tolls on animals making the whole journey are to be collected once only, either at Ahwaz, or Shushter, or Ispahan, or such other place as may be found convenient. Article P.—The concessionnaires agree to reduce the rate of tolls, and to charge the following rate only during the first and second years following that on which the road is opened for tratric, that is to say :— Por laden animals—camels 5Krans; mules 5 Krans; donkeys 3 Krans. After the lapse of these two years the concessionnaires shall, in the interests of the road, in consultation with Her Majesty's Legation, consider the necessity for a continuance of these reduced rates for a further period. But the concessionnaires undertake not to raise the rate above 8 Krans for camels and mules and 5 Krans for .asses, without the consent of Her Majesty's Legation, and it is understood that the above-mentioned tolls represent in full the sum which the concessionnaires are entitled to levy. Tor laden animals or animals engaged in the carrying trade making use of a por tion or portions only of the road or way, proportionate rates only shall be charged. These rates will be fixed in consultation with Her Majesty's Legation. jlya. jl &amp;s jj* &gt; oU 4&gt; )/ * 5 J | Ovib j g* - ^ ^ !j ^ U j jl j.) 4/ ^ b b b - cL-b •A-ib axAJ k—«xa n jl ^ ; J; I J'- f ; ^ jjxcj gl) Jjj ;l; 5 j 1 jy j V/';- 'b ' jj 3 r t^ m o'; 5 0 0 1 1 ' jtjl^l dJa^iUj ju jl olaL-l pjJ jjjji jj jej osvj jh* b v — ^ iS j^l yj) jl ; SijxCi jX-t# Jy j 1 ; ^Ub ^.b c ,jI ; J jUMl ^ jjojl) (jp- kai j b SyiS-x* JU*i«.I )ji]j jl ^^3 fm* - a-i t'xij? ^b Uitjl26 Article 10. —In consideration of Messrs. Lynch Brothers having undertaken to con struct the road, and having provided the necessary means of this work without any material guarantee from the Bakhtiari Chiefs for the due payment of interest and repayment of capital, Messrs^ Lynch Bro thers being associated with the Bakhtiari Chiefs are entitled as a collateral security to have control over the tolls in case of arrears of payment of interest or capital. They will also have the right of sending inspectors to examine the road, in order that they may be able to advise the con- cessionnaires in regard to repairs or other questions. Inasmuch as Messrs. Lynch Brothers have undertaken this work with the purpose of promoting the interests of their riverain traffic, it is agreed by the concessionnaires that during the period of the concession Messrs. Lynch Brothers shall be entitled to enjoy the most favour able terms accorded to any other party or parties in respect of the rates of tolls or any other facilities whatsoever. (L. 8.) For Messrs. Lynch Brothers. CJIARLE8 HAEDINGE, His Britannic Majesty's Charg^ d'Affaires. Seals of Bakhtiari Chiefs. (L. S.) (L. 8,) (L. 8.) Registered in Her Majesty's Legation. J. R. PEEECIL May 23rd, 1898; Agreement dated 2l8t Jamadi 1135 (19th October 1897). The Persian Government having taken cognizance of the Agreement made between the Bakhtiari Chiefs on the one side, and Messrs. Lynch Brothers on the other, for the construction of a road from Ahwaz to Ispahan, and from Shushter to Ispahan, give an assurance that the aforementioned Bakhtiari Chiefs, or such Chiefs as may be appointed by the Persian Government in their place at the head of the tribe, will be made to carry out the terms of the said Agreement, and one of the conditions of the Chieftainship of the Bakhtiari tribe will be that the terms of this Agreement Khali be carried out. (Seal of Sadr Azam.) (Seal of Mushir-ed-Dowleh.) Dated the 2ith Rajab 1815 (19th December 1897). s4£s ]j JaCL* giiJ ssbii jia'y )) ^ jti sslxjy ^ *■' &gt;*** jo gh if is lj tfj if oJ| uxft j** oja. oV '-v jljJy-l iS^iSx* J^5 jUj&gt;| OUjlyAaj - Jj**' J' ' CJ&gt; j UL~ jSjO Jjl*) &amp; rr J^y ( ^jr* A If fo 1*1 ^jy 1^1 C^JjO v^iaXi jl 5aii*x/» jl c J j -I b Jl ^1 ^.1 ; ; v^' 1 ? jl ^ jl if ojl 801J j ]ja*) 1; *J ; UU iiji J-Jkii-* JJJLa. J.jkJ bjS v^j5 ^ OjltA) Ij AJ j IS/* loy* if oji &lt;sa}j.2* flaelja* jf* jy* rri» vt; ri® py27 The Persian Government promise that in tlie event of the Bakhtiari Princes and Chiefs not paying the interest and yearly instalments on the fixed dates, in accord ance with their Agreement and guarantee made with Messrs. Lynch Brothers, the officials of the Persian Government will be responsible for the collection and payment of this money. (Seal of Sadr Azam.) (Seal of Mushir-ed-Dowleh.) ^ t, ikkxx./* ^ j^ j &gt;UJj| U jyty* J^J ) . ^Jac| jy* a j« ijj /* jya True copy. British Consulate-General, Tehran. G. T, HAVAED, E. M's Vice-Consul, 17th June 1921. ; T r. : • J:--:X , r::; Z 1 _33 No. ha). ENGLISH TRANSLATION OF D'AECY OIL CONCESSION. The following has by these presents been agreed on and arranged, viz. *— Article 1. -The Government of His Imperial Majesty the Shah grants to the Concessionnaire by these presents a special and exclusive privilege to search for, obtain, exploit, develop, render suitable for trade, carry away and sell natural gas, petroleum, asphalte and ozokerite throusrhout the whole extent of the Persian Empire for a term of 60 years as from the date of these presents. Article -This privilege shall comprise the exclusive right of laying the pipe lines necessary from the deposits where they may be found one or several of the said products up to the Persian Gulf as also the necessary distributing branches. It shall also comprise the right of constructing and maintaining all and any wells, reservoirs, stations and pump services, accumulation services and distribution services, workshops and other works of arrangement that may be necessary. Article 3. —The Imperial Persian Government grants gratuitously to the Concessionnaire all uncultivated lands belonging to the State which the Con- cessionnaire's engineers may deem necessary for the construction of the whole or any part of the above-mentioned works. As for cultivated lands belonging to the State, the Concessionnaire must purchase them at the fair and current price of the province. The Government also grants to the Concessionnaire the right of acquiring all and any other lands or building necessary for the said purpose with the consent of the proprietors on such conditions as may be arranged between him and them without their being allowed to make demands of a nature to surcharge the prices ordinarily current for lands situated in their respective localities. Holy places with all their dependencies within a radius of 200 Persian archives are formally excluded. Article 4. —As three petroleum mines situate at Schouster Kassre-Chirine in the province of Kermanshah and Daleki near Bouchir are at present let to private persons and produce an annual revenue of two thousand tomans for the benefit of the Government it has been agreed that the three aforesaid mines shall be com - prised in the Deed of Concession in conformity with Article 1 on condition that over and above the 16 per »cent. mentioned in Article 10 the Con cessionnaire shall pay every year the fixed sum of 2,000 (two thousand) tomans to the Imperial Government. Article 5. —The course of the pipe-lines shall be fixed by the Concessionnaire and his engineers. Article 6. —Notwithstanding what is above set forth the privilege granted by the^e presents shall not extend to the Provinces of Azerbaijan, Gilan, Mazandaran, Astrabad and Khorassan but on the express condition that the Persian Imperial Government shall not grant to any other person the right of constructing a pipe-line to the southern rivers or on the south coast of Persia. Article 7. —All lands granted by these presents to the Concessionnaire or that may be acquired by him in the manner provided for in Articles 3 and 4 of these presents as also all products exported shall be free of all imposts and taxes during the term of the present concession. All material and apparatuses necessary for the exploration working and development of the deposit and for the construction and development of the pipe-lines shall enter Persia free of all taxes and Custom House duties. Article 8. —The Concessionnaire shall immediately send out to Persia and at his own cost one or several experts with a view to their exploring the region in which there exist as he believes the said products and in the event of the report of the expert being in the opinion of the Concessionnaire of a satisfactory nature the latter shall immediately send to Persia and at his own cost all the technical staff necessary with the working plant and machinery required for boring and sinking wells and ascertaining the value of the property.34 Article 9. —The Imperial Persian Gorernment authorises the Concessionnaire ta found one or several Companies for the working of the Concession. The name statutes and capital of the said Companies shall be fixed by the Concessionnaire and the Directors shall be chosen by him on the express condition that on the formation of each Company the Concessionnaire shall give official notice of such formation to the Imperial Government through the medium of the Imperial Commissioner and shall forward the statutes with information as to the places at which such Company is to operate. Such Company or Companies shall enjoy all the rights and privileges granted to the Concessionnaire but they must assume all his engagements and responsibilities. Article shall be stipulated in the contract between the Concessionnair^ of the one part and the Company of the other that the latter is within the term of one month as from the date of the formation of the first exploitation Company to pay the Imperial Persian Government the sum of £20,000 sterling in cash and an additional sum of £20,000 sterling in paid-up shares of the first Company founded by virtue of the foregoinsr article. It shall also pay the said Government annually a sum equal to 16 per cent, of the annual net profits of every Company or of all and any Company that may be formed in accordance with the said Article. Article 11. —The said Government shall be free to appoint an Imperial Com missioner who shall be consulted by the Concessionnaire and the Directors of the Company to be formed. He shall supply all and any useful information at his disposal and he shall inform them of the best course to be adopted in the interest of the undertaking. He shall establish by Agreement with the Concessionnaire such supervision as he may deem expedient to safeguard the interests of the Imperial Government. The aforesaid powers of the Imperial Commissioner shall be set forth in the statutes of the Companies to be created. The Concessionnaire shall pay the Commissioner thus appointed an annual sum of £1,000 sterling for his services as from the date of the formation of the first Company. Article The workmen employed in the service of the Company shall be subjects of His Imperial Majesty the Shah except the technical staff such as the Managers, Engineer, Borers and Foremen. Article 13.—M any place in which it may be proved that the inhabitants of the country may now obtain petroleum for their own use the Company must supply them gratuitously with the quantity of petroleum that they themselves cot previously. b Such quantity shall be fixed according to their own declarations subiect to the supervision of the local authority. Article M—The Imperial Government binds itself to take all and any neceswv measures to seeure the safety and carrying out of the object of this Concession of the plant and of the apparatuses of which mention is made for the purposes of the undertaking of the Company and to protect the representatives, agents and servants of the Company. The Imperial Government having thus fulfilled its engagements the Concessionnaire and the Companies created by him shall not have power under any pretest whatever to claim damages from the Persian Govern xnent. AHiele 15.—On the expiration of the term of the present Concession all inaterials, buildings and apparatuses then used by the Company for the exploitation of its industry shall become the property of the said Government and the Comnanv shall have no right to any indemnity in this connection. ' ^ Article 16. If within the term of two years as from the present date the r™ cessionnaire shall not have established the first of the said Companies authorised by void ^ A ' reerueut the P res 'it Concession shall become null and Article 17.-In the event of there arising between the parties to the present Concession any dispute or difference in respect of its interpretation or the rights or responsibilities of one or the other of the parties therefrom resulting such dilute or difference shall be submitted to two Arbitrators at Teheran, one of whom halls35 be named by each of the parties and to an Umpire who shall be appointed by the Arbitrators before they proceed to arbitrate. The decision of the Arbitrators or in the event of the latter disagreeing that of the Umpire shall be final. Article 18. —This Act of Concession made in duplicate is written in the French language and translated into Persian with the same meaning. But in the event of there being any dispute in relation to this meaning the French text shall alone prevail. Tehran, 9th Safar 1319 of the Heeira, that is to say, 28th May 1901. WILLIAM KNOX D'AECY, hy his Attorney ALFRED L. MAEEIOTT. Certified that the above signature, etc. (Signed) GEOEGE GEAHAME, Vice-Consul. This document has been seen (by us) and it is in order. Dated, Teheran at the Sahib-Qiraniyeh. Palace in the month of Safar 1319 Ood-Eel. This is the concession granted for natural mineral wax and bitumen and which has been duly signed by H. I. M. the Shah. Signed. Ali Asghar. Sealed Atabek-i-Aazam. This is the document containing the concession granted for natural wax and bitumen which has been duly signed by H. I. M. the Shah (may we be sacrificed in His cause) and it has been registered in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Persia under No. 892. Dated 9th Safar Ood-Eel 1319. Signed Nasrullah. Sealed Mushir-ud-Dowleh. Act of concession This concession has been executed in duplicate in the French language and has been translated into Persian and has been interchanged by the parties concerned. Both copies have been duly signed by H. I. M. the Shah (may we be sacrificed in his cause) and have been duly signed and sealed by H. E. the Atabek-i-Aazam and also by Mushir-ud-Dowleh H. I. M.'s Minister for Foreign Affairs. Dated the 9th Safar Ood-Eel 1319. Sealed Nizam-ud-Din, Minister for Mines,No AGREEMENT BETWEEN P'AECY SYNDICATE, AND THE BAKH- TIAEJ. The following is a translation of the Agreement entered into between the following two parties:—the first party being W. K. D'ABCY, Esq., and those assoeiated with him in the Oil Concession granted him by His Imperial Majesty the Shah of Persia, the second party being the Chiefs of the Bakhtiari tribe, and is included in the six following para graphs : — (1) The first party has the right for a period of five (5) years from the date of signing this Agree ment to make all examinations, borings, enquiries and investiga tions necessary for the finding of oil in the Bakhtiari country, and the said first party can make such high-ways, roads and pipe lines in connection with this business as he may think neces sary and expedient. Also the said first party can build dwelling houses, store-buildings, workshops, etc., etc., as he may think necessary for the carrying out of his work. The Chiefs of the Bakhtiari tribe will give free of cost all uncultivated ground required for this work, but ground required on which to build houses for the men to live in, should it be cultivated either by men as of irrigation or by rainwater, the first party must pay for at the usual price for such land current at the time. 'Wherever the first party may form a permanent camp, he should build also near by two towers in which ten guards can live. Should any difference of opinion exist on the subject of the price to be paid for such land, the question must be referred to His Bri tannic Majesty's Consul, r Mohammerah, and the head of the guards appointed by the second party in accordance with Article 4, and their decision must be final. Tlit second party, in consideration of an annual payment of two S. irrr^-$M r* ,v i ^•ei® £.51^ if et—I jlxx*} &amp;j*l j f J) v* } b L ^ v 1 ®; J)! J»» OJk/0 ol^asvftJ ^ j dxlo-C u ^ u iij ^ j c^Ju MJO r U3| iXulJo pjV iS jx^. jJ* j U yt ; cuju jujuu-| jf] oy&amp;i ^ jisiyt) iyao 2 OjUc U^k/ jA J kUAkAJ ]y] jy*&gt; ^ j O cUiA.U jjks° j** )* ^ OjUi ^AlaaaBki^/* ^iHjLa.} r aj l«l dJolr aJO'X ; ^iU^I r m ^ &amp;&gt;J| jthousand pound sterling (£2,000) undertake to appoint guards on the road and guards to watch the houses, buildings, and dwellings and structures of every kind and afford necessary protection for those who are working, and drilling, and all workmen employes of the first party who may be engaged in the execution of his work. This Agreement takes effect from, and remains in force till, the first party commence work and till they stop work respectively, in the lands of the Bakhtiari, and if the first party stop work before the expiry of five years, the second party has no right to ask payment on this account, but so long as the first party work so long will the above sum be paid by him to the second party, quarterly in advance, the first quarter's payment amounting to £500 sterling being made on this Agreement being signed. In consideration of this payment the second party is responsible for any robbery which may happen or loss or damage which may occur through the men of the Bakhtiari tribe or others in the Bakhtiari country, to the employes of the first party or to the houses, workshops, machinery and property of the people in the camp, and every sort of loss which may happen in the Bakhtiari country the second party under take to pay compensation. It is incumbent on the agents of the first party that they keep all money locked in iron cash safes and in a safe place. The second party should therefore punctually appoint good and proper guards for protecting the public road and the road which will be constructed by the first party and to guard the persons and houses, factories, machines, tools and properties, etc., of the first party. And until the find ing of oil the Khans shall appoint and station two parties of guards in two spots which will be allo cated by the Company s Agent for the purpose of protecting their things as mentioned above. As soon as oil is found the Khans must station as many parties of guards as necessary for guarding the Company's belongings m different spots, so that thus the safeguarding of all the Company s things enumerated above shouLd be ensured. *** ) tjxcj ^ j j** j ahljjk/* ^ijj itfil j* j fUj ^f\j&gt; j mjx CiJLcl ^ U y UjU^) y JjU/* ) cjax* ^5; jl AXjuo* IJ 3b oJ^IaxS j JOJU jliT j ISJ ^14. Jl—^ JI J&gt;a5 /I j ft j ply j;xJUa/« j.A AjiT U^w| tjxi j y • &lt;Jmw Jkifrj^ak. ;fj! oLiaij ^j| isjjxzy* ^Uac 4/ pSy* jJoUi/* is j b ^ ys: v g IjJ ly c-ila. jO ( Jj I jl {.A «|j j lA J j ^ j .Uj is tjh*) j ) iOyX j| ajb ^31^ I; j* ** jlj )* *-^^0 b ^ j ^ iJbwlj )) y ^ 2 tvl) dJLLU t&amp;Alj ^1;} j ^yt sjslh j Ji' ; jl cM ; ^ J'y*' J ; lA i J j S j j S Alaiii jo jii cj&amp;jjj/* d^sJelftA. j* ^ j* ^ , ^ yt j* v^ ; !^ &lt;0,A * 1/e - oj£&gt; oLyy88 (2) It is hereby agreed that if oil be found sufficient in quantity and of good quality in the lands of the Bakhtiari and the first party proceeds to refine and trade in it, the terms of the first section of this Agreement will be binding so long as the concession under which the first party is working continues in force. | After the pipe-line for the conveyance of oil be laid to convey the oil to . the refinery and the oil be ready to pass through the said pipes, the first party agrees to pay to the second party one thousand pounds sterling per year, quar terly in advance, so that the total payment will then be £3,000 paid quarterly in advance for the safe guarding of pipe-lines, roads, houses and property in the camps as above agreed. Further also, after the formation of one or more companies to work oil in the Bakhtiari country, and after the oil is passed through the pipes, the first party undertakes to give to the second party 3 per cent, of all the ordinary shares issued, which shares must be fully paid up. (8) If the existing springs of oil be spoilt by the work of the first party and be of no further use, the said first party agrees to compensate the second party. In the event of dispute in respect of the amount of this compensation. His Britannic Majesty's Consul at Ispahan shall be Arbitrator. (4) The Khans must appoint respected, distinguished and special Gover nor and Chiefs for and in the different gangs of guardsmen to control the guards and the Persian labourers with a view to securing facility in the execution of the J;l J-^ jo j j IJ I , (Jjoljl Jjo abUxv-o J^x5 ; J/^ 0 ; VV j* w 'W** jjLi) ijx) Jlv ^ f 4- it Jjl fjJyyxlxy* ji ^ g(,/« p JLAM jji&gt; ioL««« *- j * * jc&gt; ^3Uv/ (J^^J JI }¥ j J* j) l v y J* V Tli. jO Ci-ib is OJAL* OA.) J &amp;** ^ j* j' L ' -'■IS y cVjkifcJJ yi* Sijxti j' fY* • | fx*** sU. J j .v5 dJ Axli' Joa- (-Uaf ) J-l®'-; ; I; jr* c/- 1 ^iiLce AJkyJ u&gt;.JjO J^-y ^ jOjl efly ,) J j' J 0 ^ Ji,-; ^Company's objects. Should any of the guards, employes or the Persian labourers fail to perform his duty they (the Governor and Chiefs) must, with the approval of the Company's Agent, warn and compel him to work. They must also not allow any differences to arise among the said employes and must not allow the latter to do anything which is not their proper work or to work in a lazy manner. In case the employees behave unsatisfac torily the Governor or Chiefs must, with the approval of the Company's Agent, punish the culprits. They should, in short, secure facilities for the Company's undertakings, objects and works and to ensure the confidence of the Company and the immunity of their belongings mentioned herein. In any case, they have to serve honestly giving satisfaction to the first party and to guard efficiently. (5) The payment made by the first party to the second party of this Agreement is for the specific purposes mentioned above, but should the employes of the second party fail in their duties, the first party has the right to ask compensation for any loss, after reporting to His Britannic Majesty s Consul, Ispahan, this Agreement still holding good. The second party is responsible and will deal with any people who cause trouble in not accepting the terms of this Agreement. (0) After the expiration of the period of the concession granted by His Imperial Majesty the Shah, such buildings as were the property of the first party will then belong to the second party. All the contents of the contract written above are correct. SAMSAM-ES-SULTANEH. s All the contents of the contract written above are correct, SHIHAB-ES-SULTAKEH. jo cyUvUx j' 1^1 JjJj jjl» ^ ixiaj h citjy** jo j jjjUj ; J* 5 ; b ' * j j ■ txjkjLoj JUr) JljLS /* jl Ol^tau A/ i) ^s&gt; jk j jjuhjj'l* k ^ 2 00)1.3 j*. J^3y Jly^ aijUij 0)^lav5 r^ 1 ol^laxS )*&gt; 14 - &gt;yy jk Jt ^ . ^ cUic £h s: ' 0 uy^IoiS l^yy* v 0 !/* Ut—I v^J V*V41 No- 8(a). REFUSAL OP PEESIAN GOVERNMENT TO RECOGNIZE AGREE MENT BETWEEN THE D'ARCY SYNDICATE AND THE BAKHTIARIS. Telegram, dated the 12th (received 13th) January 1906. From—E. M. Grant Duff , Esq., His Britannic Majesty's Charge d'Affaires, Tehran, To—-ihe Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. Please refer to your telegram No. 87, dated the 28th November 1905, regarding the D'Arcy petroleum concession. The Persian Government decline to recognise the arrangement with the Bakhtiari Chiefs, made by His Majesty's Consul at Ispahan, stating that the former had no right to make it. The Persian Government consider that they are only bound by terms of concession as D'Arcy shoujd first have referred the matter to them.42 No. 8(b). NOTES ON THE BAKHTIAEI AG REEMENT OE NOVEMBER 15th, 1905. October 20th, 1906. To Me. Lorimer, British Vici-Constji at Ahwaz. After compliments:— Certain matters relating to the Oil Company which we discussed with you are submitted below in writing for your perusal:— (1) I. As regards the construction of houses and buildings, and the necessity of the Oil Company's determining before hand the extent and the dimensions of the same:— Whereas the Oil Company is unable at the present moment to deter mine the extent and the locality of such buildings, in this matter we have no objections to urge. II. As regards the necessity of selecting and appointing a Superintendent- in-Chief from among our immediate rela tions to the control of the two parties of the guards employed on behalf of the Oil Company, with reference to which we deposed in Tehran in the presence of the Legation that it was necessary that the Oil Company should make an annual payment of £500 on account of the pay and the expenses of the said Superinten- dent-in-Chief, oyer and above the £2,000 fixed for the pay of the guards: this Superintendent-in-Chief is absolutely necessary for the administration of the two parties of oil guards, for whose pay and expenses the Company must pay a sum of £500, (1) (2) III. The sum of £2,500 is for the guards at two places only, which at present are Mamatain and Maidan-i-Naftun. Should the Oil Company want guards for a third place, at a distance of 4 farsacks, and start work at that place, and we provide a guard party for it, then it will be obligatory for them to fix and grant a sum on account of the pay and the expenses of that guard party in 'addi^ tion to the £2,500.43 IV. Whereas we raised the point that the Local Superintendent of the Oil Com pany pays excessive wages to his employes, thereby causing us trouble with our guards, in this matter the Local Superin tendent is his own master, and we have nothing to say. V. With regard (to reference of cases) to a Karguzar, our desire is that the Ilkhani of the Bakhtiaris should be consi dered as Karguzar and (that reference should) not (be made to) a Persian Gov ernment Karguzar. As the desire of the Oil Company in this matter and our desire are one and the same, we have, therefore, no point to raise. (3) VI. In respect to compensation and the necessity of fixing beforehand the extent of our liability: as up to the present no considerable loss by robbery (or theft) has occurred, and as a limit of compensation cannot be fixed, we have also dropped this point. VII. As regards the (Guard) money instalment which we determined should be payable against the signatures of the Ilkhani and Ilbegi: since the Oil Com pany have accepted the ruling of the Legation that the receipts should be signed by the Ilkhani and • Ilbegi, in this matter too we have no objection to raise. Seal of the Samsam. (Ilkhani). Seal of the Shahab. (Ilbegi). jSardar Asdd's note. With regard to the compensation referred to in the text: the point on which satisfaction is required is that whenever a case of robbery (3) (or theft) occurs and it is established that it is attributable to outsiders (i.e., other than the Company's employes) compensation is payable by us. On the other hand when it is established that the robbery is attributable to 'insiders ' [i.e., employes of the Company) the loss is to be borne by the Company, and no claim lies against us. Seal of Ilkhani. FINIS. Notes, (1) It has not been noted, but it was Terbally desired that the payment should be in quarterly instalments.44. (2) The stipulations in this paragraph are chiefly mine. (a) To make it clear that the pay ment of £2,500 will not hold good only for the two places specified but for any two places the Company may eventually wish to work at in place of them. (5) To prevent the Khans claiming necessity of supplying separate guard parties {urdus) for separate borings, say a mile apart. (c) It was proposed by the Khans that the sum fixed for a third camp should be on ' the same scale as for the first two/' j had this suppressed, the probabi lities depending on locality are that it should be on a much lower scale. (3) In conversation with the Sardar Asa 'd liability for both robbery by force (gharat) and theft (duzdi) was admitted, whether committed by day or night. There is of course nothing in this docu ment nor was there any question raised in discussion to restrict the larger defi nition of compensatable loss contained in the original Agreement. D. Lr E. LORIMER, Vice- Consul,Ko. AGREEMENT BETWEEN MR. W. K. D'ARCY AND THE KILI SA1YEDS DATED 1 ST OCTOBER 1906. 1. In accordance with Article 13 of the concession granted by His Imperial Majesty the Shah of Persia, to Mr. Wil liam King D'Arcy the following Agree ment is concluded with the Sadats who work the Oil at Maidan-i-Naphtun springs and with Agha Sayyed Lotiollah, son of Sayyed Karim, and Sayyed Aghai, son of Sayyed Muhammad Sharif, by virtue of the Power-of-Attorney they hold, on their behalf and on behalf of their partners, the Kili Sayyeds and others in Shush tar who now lease the oil. 2. In return for stopping the Sayyeds from working the oil in accordance with the concession, he, Mr. D'Arcy, agrees, to supply through his Agent Mr. G. B. Reynolds each year to the Sayyeds who have worked the oil 1,500 (fifteen hundred) maunds Shushtar of bitumen, the same amount 1,500 maunds Shushtar of crude oil, in accordance with the samples provided by them. This oil and bitumen will be supplied in equal quantities in the month of October each year, and Mr. W. K. D'Arcy binds himself not to sell any crude oil or bitumen at Shushtap or Dizful. 3. Over and above the oil and bitumen he will supply, Mr. W. K. D'Arcy agrees through his Agent to pay to them annual ly the sum of 350 Tumans (three hun dred and fifty), to compensate for any other possible loss which may accrue to them, and to gain their assistance and good will in his work. 4. It is hereby agreed that the crude oil given them shall be delivered at a spot at Maidan -i-Naphtun, to be decided on by the Agent of Mr. D'Arcy, in a tank which he will supply, and after delivery all res ponsibility for the oil rests with the Sayveds. The bitumen to be supplied by Ur' W. K. D'Arcy will be delivered at Shushtar, but the Sayyeds are permitted to take two hundred and fifty donkey loads pei IVM AL-J)) 4&gt; ' l, j'/ ddJl—akJ JXw 15) ^£*4 OfjU- J) UJifj - ^^5 - Jji V di j| if pUJj ylwO '% yi AXjL - IciI) lii &lt;Sx~ ti) J til ^ &amp; O 'ol -g* mjz* j) y is &amp; j [ - jO tfxcy - j ,i| io ' o rfjtjk.tw is ^3 j&gt;-«»•/• JiJn j\Sky« (jit ^ j Jl i;|c&gt;jb^xs y ^1; jxtm* ] j I Ci-AJ ^ - Jy ; 0 ^ jo IJJ&amp;j ty&amp;y* aolo Ai' ^45; ^ Isy* ^ uXj'-JO ^l*4,'xs: /c jyc CI-- ^J,j | &gt;^xxo ^ 80^6.3 y ^Liol Ji3 &gt;!ij| ^ oii iS «cyJ Jj-x* l-aj) — ^ oy* ^ J' k —% u oJ^j ds ^ oltjU** \a~-a'} ijii j o46 annum of natural bitumen found in the neighbourhood of Maidan-i-Naphtun free of cost, and the cost of carriage of same will be borne by the Sayyeds. 5. That this payment in money and in kind in oil and bitumen is accepted in full satisfaction of all claims, Mr. D'Arcy having the right to work on the above- mentioned oil lands, and that it is a just and equitable award is confirmed by the signatures of the Mujtaheds of Shushtar appended below, and this is accepted in final settlement of all legal claims, and claims other than legal, so that in the future no possibility of trouble or worry may occur and the Sayyed relinquish all claim of subsequently asking for anything over and above these terms granted above. 6. In order to facilitate the execution of the terms of this contract by the Agent ol Mr. D'Arcy and by the representatives of the lamily of Sayyeds who have worked this oil and with whom this contract is made, the said representatives will affix their signatures and seals at the bottom or foot of this Agreement and they must furnish a document, in accordance with, Muhammadan Law that they are vested with full authority by the entire family of the above-mentioned Sayyeds. The address of Mr. 'W. K. D'Arcy's Agent will be care of His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Mohammerah, which address will always find him. 7. It is hereby agreed that this deed will remain in force so long as the conces sion, granted by His Imperial Majesty the ^ r * ^ • K- H'Arcy, lasts and that the said Mr. W. K. D'Arcy has the option of terminating, this Agreement or extending it for a further period of three years after the lapse of each three years subsequent to date of execution* The first annual payment of cash will be made when this document is executed, it being signed by the representatives of the Family of Sayyeds, vide paragraph 6 above, and the Mujtaheds of Shushtar, and each subsequent payment will be made in the presence of the Agent of Mr. W. K. D Arcy on the 1st October to the above- mentioned Sayyeds, or to such as may be pointed by the Kili Sayyeds as being their heirs. Until such times as the Agent of Mr. D'Arcy be ready to supply the oil and bitumen above agreed on, jjki yjoy&amp;s*. ys ^ ^ lisjf jjO if ■ oIjLm j) ^JJb j {J**** j ^ U-Ab jt lojz pv yj 0 // j*. jbd if w-iJa/e ojo v ; Jf J y ji j&amp; j Jj| ijj+i jl** j.isj aXJ^A — j jji tjj&amp;y p Ci-ii JJJJUU IJUU jhjiy ^ jjj j ^xjioj j la^i Jjj ^ I Jo aLW^. jj jf jfl a-ib ofoL, jl** 6lly vj^* ^ ^ 4jl j Ji-yl Jjwyj J' aXxiUjG' oiU wfo u ^ /! ; )j &lt;ui| ^|j JL. r ^ ojSCi JL. r ji a*jU) ^ r Ujj| ; ^ u j „uj ^ J;' ^iUJU txx*' Jij—♦ y0 ^ ryy ^ *&gt; g u ju 0 &gt;[5 k ^yX* OMU V^JU jj [ythe Sayyeds will make their own arrange ments to supply themselves, and when ready to supply them himself he will give them one month's notice to cease collec tion of the oil themselves. 8. As on the expiration of each three years the tenant has the right to terminate this agreement, should he do so, and after he has given over the oil to the Sayyeds, he will have no right to discuss matters, and can put forward no claim on account of any erections and expenses against the Sayyeds, and he must hand back the rights to the oil and bitumen to them without demur. It is hereby declared that the above 8 clauses are accepted by Sayyed Lotfollah, son of Sayyed Karim Kili, and Sayyed Aghai, son of Sayyed Muhammad Sharif, with all the Sadat Kili and other inhabi tants of Shushtar. As admitted by himself. (Sealed) Aqaee Al-Moosevi. Eight hand thumb impression of Aqa Sayid Lutfullah, son of the late Aqa Sayid Karim Qiri. Left hand thumb impression of Aqa Sayid Lutfullah, son of the late Aqa Sayid Karim Qiri. (Sealed.) Lutfullah-Al-Moosevi. His Name is Exalted. The above conditions duly written and confirmed by their being duly sealed are in accordance with the letter written to me by Mr. Reynolds which I have handed over to the Qiri Sayids and their correct ness has been confirmed to-day verbally by Haji Sayid Nasrullah, agent of the said Mr. Reynolds. This deed is executed in two copies one being kept by the Sayids and another by the said Mr. Reynolds. _ (Sealed.) Jaafar bin Abdul Samad. Al-Moosevi. Ij tVAb ^ is ai| OIOL uk U-l joL-of AXajU] y* j - c^A3 j &amp;o V b si 0)o o^b 4jLa.|j&gt;i i^xc b b jis j j JoSJ txxm* tsj &amp;U)l—fljflj JJU- uF J^f-* j* &lt;^1 J;V jlity* - JJJ y ^.15 dl^U ' ' (^ ) J 1 /' er® 151 - - ci^Uc) - \jfj£ (*~/ ^ pajj* jJUI V—AW isx— . r l/ (V) jr* u ) jj*'* h ^Ir ' ^obu. ^ c^jy* 0 !r^ ) jL* Ji&lt;) sS JUi u^-i ^ t/.i j 'wj'/' ^hyj' . Ui—I jjiy y-' 0, ' 5t ' ^ U-) Ur® 3 ufr; JI Witnesses. (Sd.) M. MORTON, Major) E.E» (Sd.) AHMAD KHAN, Vice'ConsulatCi Ahwaz-4 .8 No. 10. AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE OIL COMPANY AND H. E. SHAHAB- ES -SULTANEH, ILBEGI OP THE BAKH1IARI DATED THE 25TH MARCH 1907. Dated the 35th March 1907. From—Bis Majesty's Consul, Ahwaz^ To—His Excellency Shahab-es-Saltaneh, II- begi of the Bakhtiari. You have requested me, confidentially, to communicate with the British Legation at Tehran (asking them to) communicate with the Persian Government in order that the chiefship of the Eels as well as the affairs concerning the Oil Establish ment and the ' Sliahi' road of Ispahan and the other affairs relating to us may be entrusted to you by the Persian Gov ernment and the responsibility thereof may be laid on yourself., i Therefore, I thought it necessary to let you know my views in regard to the estab lishment of the Oil Company, so that you may accept the following matters in case the Persian Government agrees to entrust the chiefship of the Eels to you, and you may have no dispute in future. Please write in this paper what you agree to, and seal it with your seal. Firstly. —That you should fully accept the contents of the first contract which had been signed by the four respectable Khans and you will also receive money. Secondly. —The salaries and expenses of/ the guards who are employed at s Mayaten ghardin and Maidan Meistoon and the watchmen and sowars who are accom panying the chiefs of the Oil Establish ment and the caravans, etc., should|be left at your hands according to what you your self may fix, and we may then recover the amount from you, so that the guards may engage themselves in doing their work. rAirrfly.—That the other Khans of Bakhtiari should have no right to make any demands or communications in regard to the Oil Establishment, in any way, and all questions and answers may be (made) to you. ■ l*!; j ] j* J j | dikUJl ^ i »v r 9 ^.151 ^JUJj vJa ) dilaLJl SjS]^* djJLc &amp;S Ojl y OfcL* o|j|y*l ^ OUJJ ^ 4^ ajJUi if j-ti* ^ 'I; ) -V -ilA. j] MM I L^L A.) »JyC jO j JjljUarf - cj) O^ik. cjiijisy* if j* j** O j |J «j |o| Jl iT Ij J^i5 Jtsotia. Job JJ0 6j*j9y ollja J ^ I;*-* jx** ; f)*)'* &gt; 0 ^ ^ ^ *$1* .l-lsf ^ JJI Ol^oia 4X)| vj 2 11/® 1^ ly) oUyy oJI ■ isjt £- ^ uij* ^jJsbU jO ^jdaisilw* Uib 1 j j »;|JI t^l fcxLitwu- ijx£j Jjly» ^Jk*/* oja* ismiij tjjj oj*. jlujixa. oja. Jl ]j jyty* £^' e (j'J' ^JoyJ JUf JO is ^ c^-V iy ItV® ^ AiJUay* m Jwib JbdlLa. 0 y ^i J *(§) 49 fourthly. —That you should afford us satisfaction in regard to all our affairs or matters in coanection with the Oil Estab lishment, the ' Shahi' road of Ispahan, etc., and you should make the utmost en deavours in managing them. Fifthly,-—I request you, until the result of the communication (concerning) the Eel Khani and the ' Kaees ' of the Oil is known, to safeguard the watchmen of the Oil Establishment and keep that place safe. Inshallah you will maintain order in those districts. (Sd.) D. L. R. LORIMER, Captain, E. JR. MJs Consul, Ahwaz % The facts mentioned herein are correct and accepted. And I hereby declare that as regards the £2,000 for the guards which had been fixed in the Contract, it should be paid by the Oil Establishment as well as the £500 which had bee a arranged, afterwards, for one head guard, making a total of £2,500. I should receive (this sum) by instalments as arranged. And, in case the Kohgeluh may cause any evil and ill-treatment (towards) and fire shots at the employes of the Machines, the British Legation should stringently co-operate, so that those who have committed any evil doings or (fired) shots may be brought to book and punished through the Ministers of the Persian Government, or they may obtain permission from the Government that I myself may take vengeance from those who commit evil-doing in case the entire chief ship of Bakhtiari and Char Muhal may permanently be given to me. Dated 9th Safar 1325. (Sd.) GHULAM HUSSAIN SHAHAB-ES-SALTANEH. fcCtj UU oUy* ^ jl «AjI) ijXZy 'I; ; jl i t *'*' j (.lalak - ^.Uoo) | O (.J j) , | A [ ^ «j)j| ^ i^-laiLsr^ if j| oj'ix) ij loUu jl^Af jtXZy* v _^jd£j| JjxS j is^kw* o'jJal* j| tf 4jl*Xx « jlfbl tjiol diXi Lflf? ^^jJj jij uX «jUlc if jjjj t&gt;j|j jfj'i j| job dk-oJ Jo| ^ / fjja j Ojl^ l_&gt;lxv, I Ojliw ci^ob jjji U djjLv&gt; oLk. if ^ Ai} ixx* jj'** axajlj' j| ajjx &gt;w ; | la*tj.l} AJLXU ^ j dy^. is dax/ uj J j O jl *Xi| b jJkjiUi 4jok'j|^ jti aAO ^UUI Ojl^ {:/ xxXjy* jl jjjjU Uiiiw* ^ I TO &gt;r AlaJ| /v i jJibNo. LAND AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE OIL COMPANY AND THE BAKHTIAKI KHANS DATED 15 th MAY 1911. The object of this aide memoir is as follows:— In accordance with the agreement executed on the 15th November 1905, at Shalamzar, the Sardar Muhtesham, llbegi, and the Sardar Bahadur (the latter acting for the Samsam-us-Sultaneh Ilkhani per sonally on their own behalf and as agents for the Bakhtiari Khans on a power-of- attorney which they possessed and have handed over to the Company) have sold all, and in their entirety the Maidan-i- Naftun, Maidan-i-Naphtek, Tembi, the cart, pipe-line and telephone roads, the boundaries of which are defined on a map and are demarcated by stone and gatch pillars which the Khans have approved of and accepted. The above lands are possessed by the Bakhtiaris and they have been sold with all that is appertaining thereto together with such springs, streams, etc., etc., that may be therein to the Bakhtiari Oil Com pany and the Eirst Exploitation Company tor the sum of £22,000. Of this sum £5,000 has been advanced to the Amir Muffakham and Amir Mujahid last year; an instalment of £10,000 will be paid on the 1st June 1911; a second instalment of £5,000 will be given on the 1st September 1911, and a sum of £2,000 will be paid (together with the first instalment) to Sardar Muhtesham and Sardar Bahadur, as the negotiators and agents for the said lands. All these sums to be paid in Persian currency in Ispahan. Therefore the above-mentioned and defined lands hereby become the absolute property of the Company and they have entire proprietary rights over the said lands; to drill wells, to erect machinery, to build houses, to cultivate the land, to make gardens, etc., and also to utilize any water power of springs or of rivers which may be therein. The rights under this Agreement shall remain in force until the expiry of the Imperial Concession, after which the land and the houses will revert to the Khans. 11. ^ j'y AXbl oLJj' jl yi ! ^ • o w-p-yj ^Uae j| J (W ^ cv-wj jO pUoc J| iS dJl^ •V ^ OyiS j^ S ii ' ft ^ 11 m-i' • ^ (* UlLC ^ I ^ j ^ ail Olftl*ve J J J JJIa. O,^ jlj* j j j v .Lb*/ ^s) dj^ol* dJu*. jj jjjj is *0 J oJI «^)t) JAIje-'* ti'*! ^ h ^ J;' J 0 ^ j!)* j 'tiM I 1 I I dA-w j x+ixa* jy jo iLb Ja^iu aj oU^sl^l y ;[)' i j* J;! &gt;j.*- j &lt;3 sdlyj j]6ja» ^ »o|J sjjf s* oU^y aiaJjk/® &lt;^1^1 ^ e^.A) j—ix^s Jj'OI (wCbo d&gt;LXV7lj) j*3 ol^jux ^ olw ^ «la. jf JU*J^) l^ail ^ otib y £jJ ^ ptjJko.| lijjCa-M dit&amp;. jyU'# ^(Joc oj^Lf© 51 No one of the Lurs has any right to lodge complaint, to interfere, to prevent (i .e., exercise of rights) or to claim owner ship of the above-mentioned lands. Should there occur danger, damage, or loss of any kind to the Company, through the Agency of any obstructors or any claimants of the land, the Khans are responsible for the indemnification for same. Moreover, no one of the Bakhtiari Khans shall have any right to make any further monetary claims in connection with this transaction, and should any one of them do so, it shall be disregarded. Further, in the future, any Lurs who have hitherto inhabited and cultivated t hese lands, shall have no right to do so, or to graze their flocks and cattle within these boundaries. And thus also, any Lurs inhabiting the neighbourhood of the said lands, shall have no right»|whatever to enter, to culti vate, or to graze their flocks and cattle within these boundaries. Should they come and transgress the boundaries or disregard the rights of the Company or cause any damage the Khans shall be held liable in compensation for Bame. The maps in which the boundaries of the above -mentioned lands and maidans are defined have been executed in dupli cate ; one copy has been accepted and sealed by the Khans as correct and handed over to the Company ; the other has been signed by the Company and handed over to the Khans. The land for the pipe line and telephone commences from Maidan-i-Naftun and ends at the Bakhtiari border, at which place the Company have built an ambar (shed), the length of this being 17 miles and the breadth 12 English yards. This, also the cart road which extends from Maidan-i-Naftun to the Bakhtiari border, is 25 miles in length and 11 English yards in breadth. A Jarib shall be held to mean a piece of Iknd measuring 25 X 40 ' Shah ' zars, winch according to Persian calculation amounts to 1,000 square zars, each zar being the equivalent of 42 English inches. iVoU-b JI Jl ^ ; J 1 ^ f)j ]aL ft* J* ; Scyo j oJkitjo lyl ^ J' tXxi/ ^&gt;1 oU^i jjyy i &lt;ujI JO eUUi' Ui:- £jj j y oil f I; Oji oUI^ J ) j wil&gt;i ;•&gt; ^,Vl •wftlc oyl. ; ) 4A5 j )&lt;A3 ijdf dJiyo jl ijh** ) ; 0 jb ; ss sjs) **** jl ** pO O-oil _ jyf u h ^ * Li ^ jjxj » ; |ol ) **/ J^ 5 *** ^yuU ; 4^ »!; u ^ j*** &lt;lix*s wh* ** ^JJj) ;!; ' V j/*' # b ; jl f; ; A Aiby ^ »!; tjyis* »l; ^ 15 ^ yj ^.1 j ^ 9 »u ^ ^ ^ ^ ej; ^^ ; Jvt sU ^j;^ 1 #u53 No. 11 (5). THE BAKHTIAEI KHANS' OEDERS TO THEIR TRIBESMEN REGARD ING THE OIL COMPANY'S EM PLOYES. All the Alas wand, Shahani, Neseer, Bawarsad, and other tribesmen who live about the Maidan-i-Naftun, Masjad-i- Sulaiman, Naftak, the Cart road and the pipe-line are hereby urgently notified. In accordance with this Order you are neither allowed nor permitted to live in the lands which we have sold to the Oil Company on behalf of the great Khans' families in general; you have no right either to graze your flocks in their graz ing fields. Should you act contrary to the pur port of this Order or transgress and cross the boundaries fixed and which we have sold to the Company, and thereby you cause some trouble for the Company or cause destruction to their cart road or telephone lines, whomsoever of you be found guilty of such acts he shall be responsible for the guilt and is liable to severe punishment; whatever punishment or fine he is liable to the same shall be meted out to him without remission. You should therefore act as directed above and not contravene the orders. Dated Jamad-ul-Awal 1329. (Sealed.) GHULAM HOSSEIN BAKHTIARI. J A AFAR QULI BAKRTIARI. No. 11(c)- UNDERTAKING MADE BY THE BAKHTIABI KHANS BEGABDING THE KILI SAYYEDS. Should the Kili Sayeds claim ownership of the lands which we have sold to the Oil Company, their claim shall he null and yoid and they shall have no right to put any hindrance in the way of or give any trouble to the Oil Company. Should they have anything to say m this connection, we shall hold oui selves responsible for questions or any replies required. Under any circumstances the responsi bility rests with us and the Company is in no wav concerned therewith. Dated Jamad-ul-Awal 1329 (May 1911). (Sealed) SARDAB Ml) iiTASHAM. JAAEEB KULLI BAKHTIABI, {swdqt jsuhctduf* J J if iiji s]j j j t * fj+e Jl ^J) si fj t «j!j| 6.i dlxLa.. (j axir f,}] 4^ jl ^ id J*.') j (wftlsr' ^ idjt 80|0 ^ lyl;*-'* sljjl b cijy* y j j*aa* j mi a. iS*u 3 f jy* l 13 o.X-J - Osi) ^^5 oloL- *r e-AiU y ^5 O|JU Uol 6lljy kai &lt;0 is*' ) &lt;J^b lyjl 4li|J e/i' ^ aiAlysr 3 wt-A) O''' 6 ' j* j*' tjs&amp;sxf* ■&gt; ]J r54 No- 12. AGREEMENT EOE PROTECTION OP PIPE-LINE. In accordance with the Agreement, executed on tne 15th November 1905 (17th Eamazan 1322) between their Excellencies the Bakhtiari Khans and Mr. D'Arcy, regarding the guards for the road and pipe-line in the Bakhtiari terri tory whose salary was to be paid by the Bakhtiari Khans, it is now agreed between Sardar Muhtesham, Ilbegi and Sardar Bahadur (acting for the Samsam-es- Sultaneh, Ilkhani) and the Oil Company and its associates under the Imperial Concession as follows:— With respect to the £1,000 payable for the protection of the road and pipe-line mentioned in the above dated Agreement, £300 shall be handed over to the Oil Company in order that they should pay the guards for the road and pipe-line, and the balance, i.e., £700, shall be paid in instalments, to the Bakhtiari Khans, together with the other guarding instalmeots, as per the above-mentioned Agreement. All the guards shall be under the orders of the Fields Manager or his assistant. They shall carry out any orders he may issue for the protection of the road and pipe-line, and not disobey them. Should any of them disobey orders they shall be punished with the cogni zance and concurrence of the Fields Manager. The salary of the guards is fixed at 12 Tomans per sowar and 7 Tumans per footman, per mensem, which will be paid in accordance with the Company's rules in this regard. „ • It is agreed that the £700 for this year shall be paid in advance to the Khans, but, from the 15th May 1912, the said sum shall be paid by instalments and together with the other guarding instal- ments» Should any robbery, loss, or damage, occur within the Bakhtiari territory to the officers or employes of the Company, or to the pipes, wires or telephone poles; or, if any parts of machinery or pipes be stolen, or the pipes be damaged or des troyed, the cost of such shall be met by the deduction of one-half of month's salary of all the guards, the respons ibility for it shall rest with their Excellencies the Bakhtiari Khans, ly iaia. s'xm jx/»y fu** e/iV- in'f IV (3^ jotyj jhj** j (J^ - is aiiUiib* |y| iS }y} axoj io)j tlj Ji£&gt; JaiLs' 6 ^! jii i-' | isaa.xs.ib jul tyi) Jl j jilij u u y jlr ; aotjo 5 I j { yxlsasr : ^~* j ^ 19 1 r Ai- I 9 ; aiiaj 4iajlac-^| ^a, ]ol^,5| jO &lt;siji is^ixslt, vjrjlj'* ^(Jar v;/ juyp? k«J dj la«.&gt; ;;r i b - V 1 c 51 ; j^r' t)' 01 ^U 1 J ft' ) ^ ^ IjIa ijjjj ojjj Lk LJ jl lyl aiiT ^ j lu. axixv* |*uj aauo Vijf jJaiusr A ^ / *^l 4 j 4AU J' ^.Uax J55 to recover it from the guards and pay it to the Company. Should the said guards run away or should they be unable to pay the said balance the Bakhtiari Khans themselves shall pay such balance in cash to the Company. _ After the Oil has passed through the pipes and the Bakhtiari Khans have handed the said £300 to the Company for payment to the guards for the road and the pipes and Tambi, should the Bakbtiari Khans deem it necessary to increase the guards for the greater protection of the Oil in the pipes, they shall themselves meet the extra expense so incurred and the Company shall not be concerned therewith. It is further agreed that the Company shall pay out of this sum of £300 the cost of guarding the workshop and the following buildings at Tambi, namely, the condensing plant, the pumping station, an office, two fodder umbars, a machinery store, one stable, the engineer's houses, the cook houses and servant's quarters, the guards' house and the coolies' barracks; but should the Company erect other buildings than these, and should they require more guards, they will be responsible for such extra expenditure so necessitated. Dated 28th April 1911. (Signed) GHULAM HUSSAIN BAKHTIARI. (Sealed) SAEDAE MUHTASHEM. (Signed) JAFEEB KULI BAKHTIABI. (Sealed) J AFTER KULI BAKHTIARI, Sardar Bahadur, For Bakhtiari Oil Company, For First Exploitation Company, (Signed) M. Y. YOUNG. ojwo J j ) j | dj il',J j) • • ^ IjJO txsii jj l X mi U sjjj A ,IJ u * J jb 'h; j' 4J sS iLXx-o-t to )j plJi-C j (jfc AJ j J jtJ j ^.Uic j| ts sx&amp;s) ^jxiasis 1 ^ to ^)]y* U jUj| J*. j j U' jfji (3^1 oUaUr (JjUo) t—Q &gt;UJ tj/sy* O^Uc «jllc cLU*^ i\&gt;jb ctjk. ii\ y s v ^ ajj'jjj ^ MM Ji^ljy* rA ( ^*1) *• p jslx^. { ) ( ti* )56 No. 13. SUPPLEMENTAEY JlGEEEMEXT BETWEEN M r . W. K. D'ARCY AND THE KILI SAO EDS. Whereas Mr. W. K. D'Arcy, through Mr. G. B. Reynolds, in accordance with the separate Contract in October 1906, which they made with Kili Sayyeds, therefore, in order to facilitate work, with the consent of both parties. The Bakh- tiari Oil Company, through H. B. M.'s Consul at Ahwaz, and through its Agents at jduhammerah, make a contract anew, in accordance with the following fixed clauses, viz. :— Clause i.— Sayyed Aghai, son of the late Sayyed Sharif, and Sayyed Lotfollah, son of Sayyed Karim, Kili, personally on their own part and acting as Agents for the Kili Sayyeds, in accordance with the power-of-attorney which they are in possession of, accept to take it in respect of 1,500 Shushtar Maunds of bitumen, at the rate of 5*75 Krans per maund which amounts to the sum of 862 Tumans and 5 Krans, and 250 loads of natural bitu men, at 1 Tuman per load, which amounts to 250 Tumans, they shall be paid every year, as long as the Imperial Concession is in force, without their demanding more or less, so that in future they shall have no right to work at the oil springs and to take away natural bitumen. They shall get in payment annually from the Company only the said sum with the addition of 350 Tumans for any possible loss. And with regard to the 1,500 maunds of crude oil, as agreed upon, the Company shall hand it over on the 1st of October in an iron tank. After handing over, all responsibility rests with the Sayyeds. Clause 2. —With regard to the Oil in the Nullah near No. 1 bore-hole, should the Company not require that oil and not desire it, and it runs to waste, the Com pany, out of kindness, permits that from the said Nullah only having taken the oil, they may prepare bitumen. Should the Company not grant permission, or should the oil in the said nullah become dry, the Kili Sayyeds shall have no right whatsoever to lay any complaint or to make a claim, or to collect oil, or to prepare bitumen. Should the Company, out of kindness, grant them permission to carry away oil ^from the said Nullah in ^ ^ ^ - Jj j —J;1 ^ &lt; Sxm Ul fciJ. AJUk.cn.t Jju*. til ^ &gt;— &lt; * J j1y&gt; o-jtj jl ojoUiv* JvXj Oilj J 1 /- uiy jv v* j* jt; ) vr—JjO J tH ;Jj .uh y ^ —yj ii ^.b aJU» i.4jt ojjlo «obj J ^ c; 0 / £ &amp;*■ iA-aA— jo-ib Axiljj i.'L. 4^.4 j| J ; ; l&gt;4 L-C c^obj| ; oJ ; |o jj ^ ^ Jj' j 1 * u^y*- j 0 iLd-a. jl fcXuUijy* oIk)L» - outw ij^xj ij+s va^ob j|—Je^i ; Ojloi r jll 1^1 ^ ; J ^ |j) iS iSAtSXj* sjla.) uy ^ iaaj S* Sjii tjyS ijd Ajj| b aAjJ «;U.J 0 bj^LT ^ CL&gt;!Ju« t€jm - jxi tjd jl tS (AAJ &gt;bJj| job jx3 oijorder to prepare bitumen, its representa- tiyes shall fix the site for the collection of oil and the preparation of bitumen. Clause 3.—It is agreed upon that the Company, out of kindness, shall pay annually, a sum of 60 Tumans, that is to say, 20 Tumans to Sayyed Aghai, and 20 Tumans to Sayyed Lotfollah, and $0 Tuipans to Sayyed Nasrullah, as long as the Imperial Concession remains in force. Clause 4. —The Company agrees that with regard to the payment of the sum of 1,522 Tumans and 5 Krans in respect of prepared bitumen, and natural bitu men, and every possible loss, and for the annual allowances., as above written, they will pay every year in Slmshtar on the 1st of October through the Agents of the Company to those two Agents already mentioned, or to whomsoever may be their representatives or heirs. Clause 0. —Should the Company desire to shut down work temporarily at Maidan-i-Nafiun, the Sayyeds have the right to receive the cash and oil, and this Contract holds good as long as the Imperial Concession is in force, and the right to determine the Contract shall be with the Company. Should the Com pany determine the Contract, they will, without further controversy, hand over to the Sayyeds the bitumen-oil, and they will not claim any expenses from them, and the Sayyeds aho shall have no claim whatsoever. And in future both parties shall act in accordance with , this Agree ment. Summary, —In order to facilitate the work, with the consent of both parties, the Bakhtiari Oil Company agrees that, with regard to the 1,500 maunds of prepared bitumen, and the 250 loads of natural bitumen, and the 350 Tumans (paid) for possible loss, and the 60 Tumans annual allowance, all these amounting to 1 ,522 Tumans and 5 Krans, as above written, shall be paid annually in Sbushtar on the 1st of October to the said Sayyeds. And regarding the 1,500 maunds ^ of crude oil, it shall be handed over in kind to them. And the oil in the Nullah near No. 1 bore-hole, not bring required by the Company, and having given its permission and lixed the site for the preparation of bitumen, the Sayyeds may take it away. Should the Company shut down work temporarily, the said Sayyeds have the right to get the cash and oil. la. - abUi &lt;JL» lilaJ ^ y ^ o s-f *-■** ~ - ojk-e G olm U j| J^» h* yi ) j ^3'J ; ^xl £.Ly» j* ^.y £&gt; J'/* ffy' j** )*' (j' V \ ^ J;' j 0 o|jl«w - fjjj J &gt;11, jjffifc (sis jOi 0 !;^ 5 J b &gt;? ; ^1* jji 2 ^ r 1 '^ 1 13 OtoL, r xwj irjlise y ^jcV) Ij j *s C^-A' tijf (O ^ ^.Lcol j soj*.i cXaJ AA dy*** jijyij Jl j-f aijUiv- t xj jh *uh ; J jXJ ^ vly-tiz' 2 a-ax*' j j J^3b J) j\yb t -AJLAA. dsiUU. «&gt;•«-) jj}* £*&gt; j u^y )**) o)j'—-) jih dJL« boa a^aib J i£j.&gt; c^objlj JlIJUJ cVijUi Uxc r ar h** v : ^Vv ; jsa. oti)U yxi58 Should the Company determine the Contract, it shall hand over the bitumen- oil 1 to the Sayyeds without further controversy, and there shall he no claim on either side. And in future both parties shall abide by this Contract. 16th February 1911. Equivalent to the 15th of the month of Safar-ul^Mozaffar 1329. It is correct. SAYYED LOTFOLLAH. (Sealed) SAYYED LOTFOLLAH. It is correct. SAYYED AGHAT. (Sealed) SAYYED AGHAI. Witness SAYYED NASRULLAH. (Sealed) SAYYED NASRULLAH. In His name, may His name be exalted. 'Whatsoever is written herein, men tioned and agreed to by the Sayyeds (I hereby witness). (Signed) SAYYED ABDULLAH MXJSAWI IMAM, SHTJSHTARI. (Sealed) SAYYED. ABDULLAH MUSAWI IMAM, SHUSHTARI. In the name of God Almighty. The Say ids mentioned herein have admitted before me the correctness of what is contained in this deed. Sealed and Signed— SAYID EBRAHIM, son of SAYID MUHAMMAD AL MOOSEVI. Witness hereunto- Signed and sealed— SAYID HUSSEIN AL-MOOSEVI. For Strick, Scott &amp; Co., For Bakhtiari Oil Ca, For Anglo-Persian Oil Co. Ltd. Signature and seal of M. Y. YOUNG, 16th February 1911. (Signed) C. T. WILLANS, Acting Fields Manager, jjjijJ - -MM v^);^ X s f 1 - i rr ^ ^ j^M, t &amp; - {jx* . ( JX m - }y9jle] [y* yof] - (U— I &lt;jJJ (Jjx OloL-l f ^ ^*1^) *5^ | L* - (jv'V) 69 No. 14. AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE ANGLO-PEBSIAN OIL COMPANY AND PiEWIZ KHAN.GUNDUZLTJ. Translation. It is now agreed between the Anglo- Persian Oil Company and Parwiz Khan, Gimduzlu, that 7 guards for Dara Khazina and 3 sowars to accompany the vehicle* be appointed and supplied by the latter and the pay of the guards shall be 70 Krans and of the sowars 120 Krans per man per mensem, all of which pay shall be paid to Parwiz Khan himself and all responsibility for all thefts, etcetera) shall rest with Parwiz Khan and the pay shall be handed over to Parwiz Khan in accordance with the practice of the Company. Should the Company restrict its opera tions at Dara Khazina, the Company has the right to decrease the guards, but should the Company require more guards or sowars Parwiz Khan is bound to provide them, and the pay of these (extra) tem porary guards and sowars shall be 2 Krans per diem for the former and 5 Krans per diem for the latter. Should any robbery take place in the lands appertaining to Dara Khazina, half the monthly pay of the guards and sowars shall be detached and deducted till the equivalent value of the stolen goods is recovered. During such a time as the Company has a Depdt at Dara Khazina 2,000 Krans shall remain deposited with them of Parwiz Khan's money, by way of security; when ever the Company removes its Depdt from Dara Khazina, this deposit shall be repaid to Parwiz Khan. In addition to the above-mentioned guards and sowars Parwiz Khan shall supply two guards for the protection ot the telephone line and the pipe-line fj' 01 ^ Abgunii to Haddam and their pay shall be paid as for the other guards, and the responsibility for these two men rests with Parwiz Khan, to whom their pay shall be paid. The Company has the right both to discontinue or alter this Agreement, and should Parwiz Khan break or fail to carry out any of the terms of this Agreement, he shall forfeit the right to repayment of his 2,000 Krans security. * Translated as ' gyrus' in original translation and altered to ' vehicle.' A ^ ( Liii ) jlj •U* J Ub JVS- ^ b JaaxOw/e joj 0|*&gt; v*** t ji^) ^j e jth'* j** ***) 80 j'; 0 v/jlr' ) jl r u5 ; ojlo ^ j? JLli) ^ jl)ji to «j!a| jO is O j IJ j' 0 &gt;.U^ ) OjU Uaj) j\y ) Ojb 0.4^? b sJjd Jy c;'/ ; 0 iJ^y 0 diUL* v B jjb j ] j &gt; m j &gt;UA| ^ ixij*. ^ «;l^l ^ ^ c:— J vULi)^) L f 3 ) jl \) ^ ^ b ; ir** tfy y l ) u ; ji y ^ ) cXitjj sijj v ' Si y&gt; ^ ; 0 yo 4^^ jbjiy jjjt }j ^J.) ; 0 ;' J j 1 ^ ; ^j; 1 ^ ^ e^ srJ 0 ' t&gt; &gt; )'y Ojlaj ^iLur jl I;K 1 60 Moreover, in addition to the pay of tlae guards and sowars, 200 Krans per mensem shall be paid to Parwiz Khan monthly in accordance vith the practice of the Com pany. Further, either Parwiz Khan or one of his brothers must always be present in Dara Khazina to attend to the work of the Company. Dated 20th February 1911. This Agreement is correct. (Signed and sealed) PAEWIZ KHAN, GUNDUZLU. For Strick, Scott &amp; Company, „ Anglo-Persian Oil Company, „ Bakhtiari Oil Company, (Sd.) CHAS. RITCHIE. (Sd.) M. Y. YOUNG. 20th Fehrnary 1911. *■ '*-• -- ... ;.... ^ ^ u S j IJI 'MM jy ;l ; 5 ri (jy* ) ^ W .-ow r &lt; -yij tP JNo. agbebmbnt between the anglo-persian oil company and the wali of pusht-i-kuh. An Agreement, entered into between Messrs. Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Limited, on the one part, hereinafter called the 0 Company,' and Ghnlam Eiza Khan, Amir-i-Jang, Vali of Pusht-i-Kuh, on behalf of himself, his heirs and suc cessors, and on behalf of all his tribesmen, on the other part, hereinafter called the 44 Vali,' in respect of the privileges re quired by the said Company in the territories of the Vali, to explore for petro leum and to derelop this industry under the exclusive rights of the concession granted to Mr. W. K. D'Arcy by the Imperial Government of Persia in 1901. The following Articles have been agreed io by both parties - ; j lUUff I OjA. t, ijb jl tl~.lus J) t^clsij jjm Uf wi;''! ^ Jl J OyA, . )ji* si amj x) oja. v«_aj|^t ^ j {xxla*. ^lu a / if ixsaia* otj&gt; liUvi *«| aj ijJLT ^ kii u 033 -^ if jUly«) &lt; U| J.^1 c-jUaiw* i ^ £ UIJJ»&gt; - lajoy M* I Article 1.—The Company shall have the right to drill for oil, and to make all investigations and experiments necessary in connection with oil, in any part of the Vali's territory; to construct roads, paths, houses and sheds, whether for their staff or their work ; to erect tanks, punip- inp' stations, telegraph and telephone lines, and all kinds of machinery; to lay pipe lines, and to carry out such construction work as they may deem necessary, in any part of the Vali's territory. Article 2.—All lands required by the Company for the purpose of in accordance with Article 1 of t i Agreement, whether arable or non-arable land, together with an adequate supply water, shall be granted to the Company bv the Vali, or his heirs and successors, free of charge, and without let or hin drance from any of his relatives, depen - ents or any of his tribesmen. And it is hereby agreed that any claim for com pensation put forward by a t^rd party m respect of such land, shall be met y Vali or his heirs and successors, and thai under no circumstances shall the Company be held liable to pay compensation for ttie same The Company shall give the vali to notice of the areas of land which they Ir? it jjj ik± — &lt;-b' uJLL laUi jl liaiu jA JO iaii .S J &lt; ^ ^ ; r JJ) ^ ^)| r W «&gt; is J j 6k± jO j ^ 0 ;;^ ^ oj.aLX-'* ; oixij' wv-aj ^ jl ^ vvxiU £—]y*\ ^ ^Jj) kAi ^ 1;^; lai) Ay OUif . OooUi UJ ^ J-U ^Ijl ixW — ff ^ tkh* ^ Jjl ^ ^ . (•jl' las.-' *-!;? ^ r 5l3 ; 0 jl ' j) cLU^ ^ c;^-' b by) jl *01 J.j^ j.)Ui &amp;Ux&gt; jl */ ^ ; l/ ^ ^ v 50 J 0 jb ^b 1 ^ tt/i'y l£J ; &amp;b) ^ 0 ;^ 1 dUi^ ^V? j *y. ji;/ J 3 ,62 may need to take up in any part of his territory in connection with the Oil- TV orks, and the Vali undertakes to hand oyer the same to the Company for the exclusive use of their work. The selection of sites for buildings, houses, machinery, and any other neces sary construction work, shall rest with the Company. The Company shall have the right to collect, free from anywhere in the Vali's territory, whether within or without the areas granted to them by the Vali, all gatch, stones, clay, wood, and water, whether from riyers or springs, necessary for their work. All lands granted by the Vali to the Company under the terms of this Agree- inent shall be demarcated by boundary pillars whereyer it is possible to do so, and the respective areas thus granted in any part of the Vali's territory, shall become the property of the Company for the period of this Agreement; and the Vali, his heirs and successors, or any of his tribesmen, shall have no right to culti vate, or graze their flocks on such lands, nor demand compensation for any damage or loss that they may suffer from trespass into the Company's boundaries. The Vali accepts full responsibility for all loss caused to the Oil-Works by such trespass within the Company's boundaries. All houses, shops, etc., which the Com pany may deem necessary to build for its staff and labourers, on the land handed over by the Vali to the Company, shall be free of all local taxes, and the Vali, or his Representatives, shall have no right to collect such taxes from any of the people so employed by the Company, or otherwise permitted to settle on the land in their possession. Article 5.—The Vali undertakes fo give all the protection in his power to the Com pany, or to any oi their staff or labourers, m any part of his territory, from thefts' mghway robberies, assaults, etc., provided that, in the case of attacks by large forces from neighbouring tribes which he cannot be expected to meet successfully without outside assistance, the Vali shall not be held responsible; similarly, he under takes to protect all houses, effects, stores, roads, pipe-lines, all kinds of machinery and any of the Company's property which may be exposed to wilful damage by any ^kxl &lt;l[xj ssxtty i) jjl}'' j icij - •&gt;■&gt;;!*&gt; sjuaJti* ixb} jjU j iij^l Jjlj^ £-0^ sf ojlo ; r)b ] ^ *}) j' ; Vjt J j* ohhis j ioaj U jl j* mjds* jl j fir* i lir^ t jjy c j 0 ^ iiwi v^;; ^ b ^ b j 0 ;r*j 0 ) ^ y 3 lyib JaiJ uc-xfy: ^ | ^ tx^j aj r^ ^ u/y* *~-b- ^ KJ JjlXy ixtf kij ^ ^ ^ aal^ ^l. ; oljju jl jil jjou y /^il 0 oyi tSI ioUalmw* ____ b xULx Ux^ it ^ ^ OyL f ^ ^ Ij jxlifjtj ,1^1 jl ^ jl Ojjo kjAsS 1 ^ ao j; 1 wAjy, u-' &gt; 0 oo y^j^ -=-1^ ^ ^1^ d-T (•ufl jy iejial (j^-lo | jjll* ^ JJ-1 63 of his tribesmen, or to possible loss by theft. Tor the above purpose, the Vali shall provide the Representatives of the Com pany with trustworthy guards, whether mounted or unmounted. He further undfrtakea to recover any property stolen and to compensate the Company for any damage sustained within his territories. In the event of non'recovery of stolen property, the value thereof shall be deducted from the salaries of all the guards, and should the amount claimed be in excess of their salary, the Vali him self shall be responsible for the payment of the balance. The number of guards required in any district where the Company may operate, shall be determined by the Company's Eepresentative. Their salaries will be paid monthly by the Company on the following scale : eight Tumans per month of the Christian Calendar without food, for unmounted guards, and sixteen Tumans per month for the head (when required) of the unmounted guards ; fifteen Tumans per month for mounted guards, without food or fodder, and thirty Tumans per month for the head of the mounted guards. Further, the Company will pay to H. E. Ashraf -ul-Mulk, Deputy Governor of 8afhai -Kurd (which extends from Patek to Bagh-i-8hahi), or to his blood brother, the sum of one hundred Tumans per men sem, so long as they continue to operate in that area, on condition that the said Deputy Governor renders every possible assistance to the Company s Representa tives. In the event of the Company working in any district in Pusht-i-.Kuh other than Safhai-Kurd, the salaries of the guards shall be on the same scale; provided that, so far as the salary of the Deputy Governor is concerned, the whole of Pusht -i-Kuh shall continue divided into three districts, and that in the case of any further district being created sub sequently, the Deputy Governor of such district shall not be entitled to the above mentioned salary. The foresroing salaries will be paid to the guards in dividually, fifteen days subsequent to the end of the month during which they were earned, as in the case of all other employes of the Company. jO tijx, fj jjb a ^ ^ J' 0^*.^ L* ^ ij}**- ^ 'V j Jy-'* lyi ixjlxky* ^ ^xxxj jo/ ^ Jji&amp;A djj+ tLU+f if f j—lxas c^* j* j** ttil h ~ LfJi ^ yzjlsyi ui-.&amp;a j } r* j tb' }' j* tju*j . 'wUJ h c-jj) fjxu , gjl** ts uju v«xlj| v_ij.il j^| ^ilaj ^b J) st^] |oU G' Aj'UaI* 4jJ| CJUJU.£ C^-a.b« tlx* laioUJ jj^S* j - ojk*L./* jjb JI jxc j^XXvlo iobu jii oajL* jj**- ocijf olxl^r jjjx&amp;y* ¥ clijaeu* ijJLT ajjj .0 jlsr'txa^ ^ jwiti (0.a.b ixjl^laxy* ~ j * •* j • ' • r 'i jj ijjlj 4JLft.U i-^ib ^J.) ijJjb Ji5 «U isy+j* ^ - ajjb' tyur- 6i The engagement of guards by the Com pany shall be confined to such persons only as are appointed by the Vali or his representative in the various districts m which the Company may operate; pro vided that such guards perform their duties to the satisfaction of the Companv s Representatives, and so long as the \ all s assistance in the detection and punishment of thieves continues real and effective. Should any mounted or unmounted simid, or any employe of the \alis tribesmen leave the Company s service ■without duo notice of one month, fifteen davs of his pay will be forfeited, and this rule, without exception, shall apply to all native employes engaged by the Com- pany. it jlT ^ aUI sw CyOA A? )fr* ^ J b - 4 ' j, ^ jaj U 3 y. ; ; J ju*J lSx ^ aJ) jja*^ cUjij' J ) oijUi ^~4&gt; yi ^ JI cIJ/yk J JU£i| ij jy^ 0 r il ^ oUj^ jl 6 l- ^ 6y^ j' J;j -5 ^ y j &gt;Uiju.| 3 dJjJU In order to obviate trouble, and to facilitate the Company's operations, it is hereby stipulated that the mounted and unmounted guards appointed by the V ah and engaged by the Company shall be trustworthy men, who will carry out the orders of the Company's Eepresentatives. The suards must not be changed irequentiy without valid reason, and, in any event, a head guard should not be relieved of his post without due notice being given hy the Vali to the Representative ot the Company. Any sppli«ation from the Company's Representative to the Vali, for the change of any head guard or subordinate, on grounds of disobedience or inefficiency shall be complied with, and under no circumstances shall ahead guaid remain at any camp, unless with the consent and approval of the Company s Representative. The Company reserve to themselves tbe rio&gt;ht to punish any guards, or other native employes, by fine or dismissal, or both, and in the event o any heavier punishment being required, the offenders shall be handed over to the Yali s loca l representatives, and the Yah undertakes to see that punishment shall be inflicted, and to use his utmost endeavours to uphold the authority of the Company s Pepresentatives over their employes, thereby avoiding unnecessary trouble to both parties of this contract. ouu* v ; axJ! fk** ^ Jjy. ; ^ ^ ^ i-ir i ; iixU. j ^ jxsil jj ^Dol aIaV ^ r 1 *** ^ ^ *-v) JIJJJ AJ^i Alxwly ujU/* b ^xsj b ~ c ^ £lJ • , - JjUi c^-Jj J| ^fji' y&gt; is cdj ^ Jar/wz* AlAif s-V ^y- u b - b Ij l^j u J) y ail fk** jt »sxi,ui aj c0 / AA JI pla*/e Of-flA. ^ ' j Ai 0 /^ ^ ^ «_|y l ; A^K' \ss* ,i Aulflk. ii tS yjfj* ; l/ v ^j AJ-ftiiU ^ OUA}It shall be the duty of any head sniard appointed by the Vali, with the consent of the Company's Representatives, to keep order in the camps where the Company may operate, but he shall have no right to interfere in any disputes amongst the Company's native employes, unless called upon to do so by the Company's Repre sentative. As a deterrent to others, the Vali undertakes, on the representation of the Company's Representative, to inflict severe punishment on any head guard or subordinate, found guilty of taking bribes, or extorting money from any of the Com pany's labourers, shopkeepers or any others in their employ. Article 4. —It is hereby agreed that any or all of the natural springs of oil in the Tali's territory, shall be handed over to the Company for their exclusive use during the period of this agreement. Due notice ■will be given to the Vali by the Company whenever the said springs may be required by them, and the springs shall then become the property of the Company for the period during which this Agreement remains in force. Thereafter no one shall have any right to collect oil from the said springs without the permission of the Company's Representative, and the Com pany shall not be held liable for any damage or loss due to trespass committed at any spring of which they have taken possession. No one shall have any right to approach, or interfere with, any springs of bitumen, lying in the vicinity of an oil field, which are likely to cause loss or damage to that oil held, and the Vali undertakes to hand over such springs to the Company when need arises, and on due application being made by them to this effect. J I oUi^r s.S |j ^UaX ) jo fj-a. rf-UU. dlajo oUjiiu* uJtjJe Jj sJjfjA Oj|v&gt;i 0 ^ r J AUla. 4j*. js OljW'* 4/ JOdjUi u 4x / ' ^ JJ Jl f]^ jj w~5U jjU*. b AKmS dixLak ^3lxoi J) 0 Cjj.*&lt;a,a, Ojjijafc laftj u*j- £ aj ix jix'si/* . i c—]jj ^ **** ^ &amp;/* 1 y*' '*'* »o|o ajJI pis** 0,^3^? J &lt;sa&gt; y ^ ^ CjtAXxA/* tin* - am ] Cl3tXAL*/&lt; ^ jjjjia. ojiy ^ ^ ^ 1 ^.-6.a.a. i.ljt ^LAi ^JL» ^ &lt;^A)»3r J e.— ]jJ j la a. b jjJc tXw 4 &lt;5^ j' jyy ^ djj-jsa ^ LyAAZk-a. sjys {»ft' ^ J' ^.Laliu tj *jJ| ^la*^ Ij m 6ytj Article 5.—This contract shall remain in force for any period that the associates of the Company retain their concession with the Persian Government and for the period of any extension thereof, or for any less period during which the Com pany may desire to work in the Vali's territory. 15 gjjfcU/* ^1 ^:sn.XJ SoLo djJLr u ^J.o b |j o^xjtju-e^ a UI .?^ loLs.xj) o&lt;j&gt;/« b ^ 4LJL£!O S^J ^Ijf' is tXJ &lt; ^' e ' fcV^b (Jjiil/* &lt;^1 lijlsa* jt)Should the Company be successful in finding petroleum in the Vali's territory, both parties accept, and agree to carry out, all the conditions stipulated in this Agreement, and when a new Company or Companies are formed for the working of the oil industry in the Vali's territory, the Vali shall become an associate of such new Company or Companies, and he shall be granted three shares out of every hundred shares issued by such Company or Companies. These shares w ill be given to the Vali free of all charges, and he will thus participate in any dividends that may be declared by the said new Com pany or Companies from time to time thereafter. In the event of the Company failing to discover oil in the Vali's territory; or, if oil should be discovered in such small quantities as to be unworkable; or, if for any other reason, the Company desire to stop work in the Vali's territory, they shall have the right to do so, and the Vali shaJl have no claim to the above- mentioned privileges. Due notice of the cessation of work shall be given by the Company to the Vali, whose guarantee of protection shall cease, on removal of the Company's staff and property from the Vali's territory. Thereupon, or, in the event of a new Company or Companies being formed under Article 5 of this Agreement, then, at the expiration of the Company's concession or any extension thereof, all immoveable property left in situ by the Company, shall be handed to the Vali, or his heirs and successors, in trust for the Persian Government, to whom such property reverts under the concession granted to Mr. W. K. D'Arcy by the Persian Government. Article 6. —The Vali solemnly declares that he will carry out all the conditions of this contract faithfully and loyally, and that he, or his heirs and successors, shall be its guarantors, and shall accept full responsibility for any claims by any person in his territory questioning the validity of any of the stipulations m this contract. In the event of any differences arising between the Company and the Vali, whether in respect of the meaning of any of the foregoing Articles, or other wise, such matters shall be settled in an unofficial and friendly manner between the two parties. Failing a friendly settlement, the points in dispute shall be referred to one of His Britannic Majesty's Consular Officers having jurisdiction to arbitrate and to settle them. And, in the last resort, the case shall be referred to His laiu i « ]j lailj* sjlf is wVbUi (.j l ^ kaj JjJOah. J| dJkJ) (Xul JjJLiuji dxj| jjax* tj ,zi jbt j] fy** 4j ^ . 7 ^ ( ^ 4^1 ftJox/* 4JUJ ^1 - j OUxo.^E-' djj./ Ij y* jo &lt;^ '1 laiu 1. I jO &lt;U laa) js] b tVA yd'i O^a.^. ij.a'i jxc ^ h ft !/• j ajJ| piaxst r sjjf (&gt;■« 0|j(.JLL«| J .J / iS j *- S ^ Jt f -* J| jjt** CjA*. j/ X '* ) ji\X} - jjy s-Jji ^ AjJ ) pia*&lt; lajciA. b ^Si t&amp;Jjj* b isaxi SiAii'*/* I sjt/« jJpUa/« jO iolwxj} b &gt;l^aai| ^iye ^ jx£ cj'aijlx* ixif Ojj iUr U/o ^ i&amp;jjj b JiJl I 4J tXui JJa.) fcjlk'iL**/® jj^o j'i'i/*! ' jur b jjJ ) fk** j ]j ^1 ijiK ss Ojlo jt^lal jxiy djJ| ^SJLy* o^^aa. ^ solo ditSol-f . i.) bjoJ/» c ici 1 ^ ti Icol V j* ^ koljAW j\ ja 40 jrii (JJ.J) y ^x)t*xi olillAa.! b jf J) jit o(.A*J m jy k l jjfs* &lt;o ixo^aj j dsi c '.A j) t j, b* tXAjj .ak ^ A .A .vi'' ^ jo s.£ c-ylj v-^jJy &lt;u iisoa.) j j[h /e jljj c—tS! U 1 ?'!68 No. 16. LAND ACQUISITION AGREEMENT BETWEEN ANGLO-PERSIAN OIL COMPANY AND THE BAKHTIAEJ KHANS. The object of this paper is as follows Whereas in accordance with Article 1 of the Agreement executed on the 15th November 1905, between the Bakhtiari Khans and the Company, regarding the land which may be required by the latter in Eakhtiari country. Therefore, in this paper, dated 10th Shaaban 1339 (19th April 1921), it is hereby agreed between His Excellency Amir Muffakham Ilkhani, on his own behalf, and on behalf of the Haji Ilkhani family, and His Excellency Murtaza Kuli Khan, on his own behalf, and on behalf of His Excellency Samsam- E-fealtaneh and the members of the Ilkhani family on the one side, and the Oil Company on the other side, as fol lows :— Avtide 1. —Whenever the Company should ^ require land for their operations, the price of each Jarib of arable land situated in the Bakhtiari Garmsir (hot country) should be at the fixed rate of 10 tomans per Jarib of 1,000 square Zarhs (yards). Provided that this rate shall not apply to the plain of Malimir, to Gut wand, Abbid and Lali, and nlso to Irrigated land anywhere in Bakhtiari Garmsir (hot country). Further, that any non-arable land required by the Company excepting in the districts iust mentioned, shall be at the rate of 5 Tumans per Jarib. These rates shall apply to all arable and non-arable land, whether owned privately by the Khans themselves, or belonging to the tribes. Moreover, should the Company require land in any of the districts above mentioned, the difference m the price of such land from the rate now fixed, should be a fair and reasonable one. Article 2. All lands acquired bv the Company in future under this Agreement, siiaii be the absolute property of the Company for the period of their Conces sion, and the Company shall have full proprietory rights over these lands. At j il Xp i ry of tlle Con cession, the' ands Kbans 6 SeS tllereon ' slla11 ^vert to the ' Jr^ ^ M ♦o | 0 A/«l) o/o jlyjl J^l jjU** JA5 Airr^ cJ/l -- ? i r f Jtyj | q b Jx*is j| hjhj ; Oj± I jju| sf 15 ' v&amp;w j 1 &lt;0^1 ^lo ixhuy^ ^15, ^ j Jjuc'i , di'yt, - j\yi (J.j j jO L AJ a UL -V b oVj —J;I »0U a-ib Aiib ^ J 0 Jj15 ^ j!;5 Jl jlj oUkS ; &gt;u^«b J 3 1 Jjti; t'i ; 0 &gt;r ^ ^ C/-' j' f c l ^ tXA/ji. * 1M AJ b « a - 0 / jc UJji 4J ^Usu. LA; ^3 ^ ajb k*.* 3 - J-^b 43^1^ ij[a*ax* j 0 *h) c/i* tzdu ^j^oj 0 laaj 4jjj f ^ yfc (txlr ^ ^ b , jy f^ ^ ^ ' ^(Jir ^&gt;31^ o^Uf69 1 Article 3. —All land acquired by the Company under this Agreement, shall be measured in Jaribs by the Company's Engineers, the number of Jaribs shall be fixed by them, and demarcated on the ground by stone or gutch pillars. A map should be executed in duplicate and despatched to the Ilkhani and Ilbegi of the day. One copy should be signed by the Company and retained by the Khans, and the second copy should be signed and sealed by the Khans and returned to the Company as correct. Article ^.—Should the Company desire fco occupy land which is either inhabited or under cultivation, they should give three months' notice to this effect to the Governors of the day, whose duty it shall be to remove the tenants within that period. The condition regarding the removal of the inhabitants shall apply to encampments of tribes and their sub divisions only, but not to settled villages. Article 5. —All tribal land acquired by the Company from the Governors of the day, whether arable or non-arable, whether inhabited or uninhabited land, should be paid for in full to the Governors of the day, and the latter must supply other land to the ryots or pay them for same. Article 6. —With regard to private property owned by the Khans, it is hereby agreed that half the price thereof shall be paid to the owners of the land as certified by the Governors of the day, and the other half shall be paid to the said Governors of the day. The Governors of the day hold themselves responsible for any further claims made by any owners of land acquired by the Company under Agreement. Article 7. —The tribes shall have no right to graze their flocks on any land acquired by the Company under this Agreement, and should they do so, the Khans undertake to punish them. Should they transgress the Company's boundaries, and should any of their flocks or cattle meet with any accident owing to gas or other cause, the Company shall not be held responsible. V-ir* if jj uji j 4*^ viJb tjsAS lyklse* 3 )j iix* &gt;La*) 1*^ d/ O j |J ttjj &gt;Lay) ) j - ddjc kai 6.*jitx/* pj)' ' &gt;u j ^ ooUi ^Ux| »U Aaw JO |J - oUJ ii j) ^1 ^ jh* ) yjy^ t))j* jp) ^U5 Jjb alCx- iaii ) h fj jy 4 - li rfJokJ-f&gt;. Cfc-5j i) }j j&amp;t&gt; ^ frVj 0 o'V' ^ ^ &amp;°i' ^ |J ' tJ - u ii op^ ^alio v,/ 0 ' 4 * j!/' m L |« -*J / v; Jr. b 1; AjJyo itj '-aaa** ^ bV- r' ^ j}/* jl /b ^ jl ^5 ; ; u jd ; ^ ys'* j* 1 V ; 'M' ^ V ; JU Jlxljl a*J J 0 tjjjj jv Ja* jl . jjj a*}}**70 Article 8. —The conditions of this Agree ment shall remain in force for the period of the Concession, with the exception of the condition relating to the price of land fixed in this Agreement. This condition shall remain in force for a period of 15 years only from the date of signature of this Agreement, and on the expiry of this period, the price shall be cancelled and revised by arrangement between both parties. (Signed) LUTF ALI. (Sealed) AMIR MUITAKHAM, BAKHTIAEI. (Signed and Sealed) MURTEZA QULI BAKHTIAEI. For Bakhtiari Oil Co., Ltd., For First Exploitation Co., Ltd. (Signed) M. Y. YOUNG. 20th April 1921. Witnessed by— E. G, B. PEEL, Captain, Sis Britannic Majesty's Vice^ Consul, Ahwat* 20th April 1921. &gt;Laaj) G ol j&amp;is - JJOjC 771 Eo. 17- AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE ANGLO-PERSIAN OIL COMPANY AND HAIDAR KHAN, C.I.E., OE HAYAT DAUD. Translation. An Agreement entered into between Messrs. Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Limited, on the one part and hereinafter called ' The Company 'and Sarkar Haidar Khan, C.I.E., Zahit of Hayat Daud and Kharag, on behalf of himself and his brother Mnhammad Khan, his heirs and successors and on behalf of all his tribesmen, hereinafter called ' The Zabit,' in respect of the privileges and^ lands required by the said Company in the territories of the former, for the purposes of their business under the exclusive rights of the concession granted to Mr. W. K. D'Arcy by the Imperial Government of Persia in the month of Safar 1319 equiva lent to the month of May 1901. Article i.-—The Company shall have the right to search for, obtain and use water and to construct tramways, roads, paths, houses, sheds, bricks and reservoirs whether for their staff or for their work, to erect tanks, pumping stations, telegraph and telephone lines and all kinds of machinery, to lay pipe-lines and to carry out such construction work as they may deem necessary in any part of the said territory. Article 5.—All lands required by the Company for the purpose of their preli minary exploration for oil whether arable or non-arable in the territories of Bayat l&gt;aud together with an adequate supply of water so far as it is available shall be granted by the said Zabit to the Company free of charge, and without let or hindrance from any of his relatives, dependents or any of his tribesmen. And it is hereby agreed that, in cousideration of the sums paid to the Zabit laid down in Article 3 any claim for compensation put forward by a third party in respect of such land shall be met by the said Zabit or his heirs and successors and that under no circum stances shall the Company be held liable to pay compensation for the same. The Company shall give the Zabit due notice of the areas of land which they may need to take up in any part of the said territory in connection with the oil works and the Zabit undertakes to hand over the same to the Company for the exclusive use of their works. Jajl/i o'jla. Oya;*. ^ UJLtfj J| Jij)' j] j Jl iajt-i .]jS AJJI 7 \y&amp; y j) sx - zfj*. ss a UV j&gt;^ — Jj' ^ ^j'.l Islai jl vl JoUi UaBl d/ AjJl ; sxh] yu (U)l jJ ^Uil ol^Uc ; j ; fj' *!; j U fckjb j ; 'I)?-! J.J15 jac jj**' ''' jjj-'o ****** £ —I/? ^ &amp;') £* ^51; ; 0 ; J r j^ ^ yjp** ^ 6.) &lt;uJ) ur&gt;*^ jl I o ; ^A. dJUjL'i jl b ^ V y ^ijl ^1 ^ iju * ^ ^ j ] j* fly' *^3^ *t)b lct&gt;| ^ ^IAjI pi 15 ; k 0 J L *3/ ^&gt;1 ^ ^ 3 '^ r ^ 1; ^b 1 ^ r 3 -'/ j 0;JA. yti oU-AisU rfjJl j M f? ol^Ul^l ]j jy-y 0 ^|;l ^ *4*1* .iur72 Article 8. —As soon as the Company has been successful in finding oil in suffi cient quantity to justify the laying of a pipe-line and as soon as the said pipe-line has been completed and the oil is being exported thereby, the Company hereby undertake to rent or purchase at their option and the Zabit hereby undertakea to rent at the option of the Company whatever land may be required by the Company for their operation at the follow ing rate:— For erery Jarib of 1,000 square Zarhs ten Tumans per Jarib for arable land and 5 Tumans per Jarib for non-arable land whether owned privately or belonging to the tribes or to sell at the rate of one hundred Tumans and fifty Tumans per Jarib, respectively. All lands acquired by the Company as above shall be the absolute property of the Company for the period of their Concession or any extension or renewal therefrom and the Company shall have full proprietory rights over these lands. At the expiry of the Concession or any extension thereof, all immovable property left in situ by the Company shall be handed to the Zabit or his heirs and suc cessors in trust for the Persian Govern ment, to whom such property reverts under the Concession granted to Mr. D'Arcy by the Persian Government. All lands rented or acquired by the Company under this Agreement shall be measured in Jaribs by the Company's Engineer the number of Jaribs shall be fixed by them and demarcated on the ground by stone or gutch pillars. A map should be executed in duplicate and copy sent to the Zabit. One copy should be signed by the Company and retained by the Zabit, and the other copy should be signed and sealed by the Zabit and returned to the Company. Article 4. —Should the Company desire to occupy land which is either inhabited or under cultivation they should give 3 months' notice to this effect to the Zabit whose duty it shall be to remove the tenants within that period. The condition regard ing the removal of the inhabitants shall apply to the encampments of tribes and their sub-divisions only bat not to settled villages. All tribal land acquired by the Com pany from the Zabit whether arable or non-arable and whether inhabited or un- mnabited should be paid for in full to the Zabit and the latter must supply other land to the cultivators or pay them for the ioai ^0^/ ^ ^ j j* ; fUi'i ^ IjUkl (j isija ^ j* A* J' rJ 1 ' b ^ z 11 *' ^ ^ v-r^r?. ^ J 1 vjV «-M 5 j* ;!;•» jl fjj J J* ; o fjj ^1)) r s] jjj ^ ^ ^ jul* ^ k ju)* oo^. u jojujol- ojl jib o)ja^) ; j** &gt;ua.| ; o j ^5b dUV Jt , aT Jjlj jUi-l au*&gt; j ^j jo y ^ fb-j &amp;ljj b jJI ^ v*' di ^ ^ ij b «.l^| o|j J c/^ v o|a*j' sjy v j2jujj ^XJ j jjjijxj j uwxr •o^j u-i ^ ^jTj ,^5 l&gt; j ^ ij U/-I i • ^ ^ ^ ,0^ ^ L.V JO — aib JJ/OUX^ ^ ^ J JjUi L j U ^ i 1 oiiwA V vyi' oi »u r - 4&gt; ^Ubl * &amp;)}* y* &gt; c '] 0 jUbi u/M ^ o^j' ui ; r Uj ajb ujUav. rfjJ) vfiu ; )■&gt; ji J w Ltil o^. (, ^ LjRime. With regard to private property it is agreed that half the price thereof ihall be paid to the owners of the land as certified by the Zabit and the other half shall be paid to the said Zabit. The Zabit holds himself responsible for any further claim made by the owners of land acquired or rented by the Company under this Agreement. Article 5. —The tribes and cultivators ■hall have no right to graze their flocks on any land acquired by the Company under this Agreement or in temporary occupation for purposes of exploration and should they do so the Zabit under takes to punish them. Should they trans gress the Company's boundaries and should any of their flocks or cattle meet with an accident the Company shall not be held responsible. Article 5.—The selection of sites for buildings, housing machinery and any other necessary works shall r. st with the Company. The Company shall have the right to collect free from anywhere in the Zabit's territory whether within or with out the area sold as above to them, all salt, sulphur, stones, clay, wood, water, whether from rivers or springs, necessary for their work. All houses, shops, etc., which the Com pany may deem necessary to build on the land sold as above or temporarily occupied shall be free of all local taxes and the Zabit or his representatives shall have no right to collect such taxes from any of the people so employed by the Company or otherwise permitted to settle on the land in their possession. Article 7. —The Zabit undertakes to give all the protection in his power to the Company or to any of their staff or labour ers in any part of his territory, from all thefts, highway robberies, assaults, etc. Similarly, the Zabit undertakes to pro tect all houses, effects, stores, roads, pipe lines, all kinds of machinery, and any of the Company's property or of its em ployes which may be exposed to wilful damage by townsmen, tribesmen or culti vators or to possible loss by theft. ^*1^1 ajJI ^ ' CyiaH iktai y fi-LJ v&gt;j ji - WyC j| J&gt;V.JU»A &lt;Jk]| » tj-aJ j| tA«j O j UL v * ^J-Jk ■a*'' JJ*- jlr* c/-' j a'Jyo o|J Jy—.&lt;• - ji/ &lt;xij| »oU *^1^ b Ijicj o'*. iili. ^ o'^lUa.) 4^)1 &gt;Ui| if O j IJ ja. j/j.* Ojf yS V—Cj (Jou* Jl ^ ^ J* jl - •wUi *jJ| j J ^|j| ** 'j-h vif** ; ^ rf** J 0 ^ yj**' ^fsjj* ^ oUL- jf ^yu Uj *s j| oUJU ^fiol d^Jtiay- j# 0 b isx'lm.* y *jJf iajLi Cl^a^ -— ijU ; ^ ^ ^ •trA- ji) iwTI*, ijdr j*&gt; lj jjiiur jIT JUIsT dlU*. j Ojti ^ ^ iysj*u.x* ^xxsi^m . y lojla*. (3^0 ijlx*! sy ^Js•*!;»/* kjof-* )* V^^13 ^ jf - j iojkx'* tijmi b «AJ)Article 8. —For the above purposes it is agreed between the Zabit and the Com pany that the former shall appoint in con sultation with them permanent trust worthy guards under a reliable man of good family, whose pay and that of the guards shall be provided by the Company and who shall remain there summer and winter. If in spite of the efforts of the said guards thefts should occur, the Zabit undertakes to recover any property stolen and to compensate the Company for any damage sustained within his territories. In the event of non-recovery of stolen property, the value thereof shall be deducted by the Company from the sums due to the Zabit. The number of guards required in any district where the Company may operate shall be fixed by the Company's Eepresen- tative. Their salaries will be paid month ly in arrears by the Company on the following scale Eight Tumans per men sem of the solar calendar without food for unmounted guards and ten Tumans without food or fodder for mounted guards. Two Tumans food allowance shall be given for each man until the next harvest and ten tomans for each horse for fodder, etc. These allowances to be subject to monthly revision in communication with the said Zabit monthly thereafter. The Company shall provide arms and ammunition lor these guards and the said Zabit shall be responsible for their safe custody by the said guards. Two or three head guards shall be appointed for places of importance to be guarded at twelve Tumans per month. The salary of the Head of the I Guards shall be fixed from time to time by the Company in commu nication with the Zabit and the Company shall erect a dwelling at Ganawah for the representative of the Zabit. Article 9. —The engagement of watch men by the Company shall be confined to such persons only as are approved of by the head of the Guards who will be ap pointed by the Zabit in consultation with the Company. The said watchmen are subject to dismissal or fine by the Com pany. In the event of any heavier punishment being required the offender shall be handed over to the Zabit and the Zabit undertakes that punishment shall be inflicted and to use his utmost endeavours to uphold the authority of the Company's representative on account of their em ployes, thereby avoiding unnecessary trouble to both parties of this contract. (tJLuU* ^ U lilc c&gt;j^isu *jJ| SJMIjo ^juoU ^ aUU. djolj' y J J.-iU JuLilo ^-a»y AvJI ^ olai*L« J) ai OJUj laa^- AW,/ * j* )) ^ 0 iU*r 0 rfjfo ^jj) ieliij J| tfJaS) ^ Jo^j* «U jl j' «U ■* jj i,— (i jyj OvV® jj ^U/* *** c/-- 1 ^ v^ J ' I ^UloL&gt; *1 AiLibLaJ ioji/® - (0)0 ■ jjiy* j i^sisu jyiw* 8J J^ ^JUX^ aLJ^. ^yx+s . ixi «O|J &gt;lb Jjjlif jO djJ) cjjaa, sjJkjU) iya. m O^eJ cXit b ^ c)) c w ft | # w ]j jsaa.sc auia. J 4jJ | s j iiijf )j jtasue ss aysts'* ^|*) t #jj..r 4^ ajj'o - oUAJArticle 10. —It shall be the duty of the above-mentioned Bead of the guards to keep order in the areas in which the Com pany may operate, but he shall have no right to interfere in any disputes amongst the Company's native employees unless asked by the Company to do so. Article 11. —This contract shall remain in force for any period that the Company retain their concession with the Persian Government and for the period of any extension or renewal thereof or any less period during which the Company may desire to work in the Zabit's territories. Article 12. —In the event of the Com pany failing to discover oil or if oil should be discovered in such small quantities as to be unworkable and the Company desires to stop work on the Zabit's terri tory, they shall have the right to do so and the Zabit shall have no claim to the above payment. Due notice of the cessa tion of work shall be given by the Com pany to the Zabit, whose guarantee of • protection shall cease on the removal of the Company's staff and moveable pro perty from tlie Zabit's territory. Article i5.—The Zabit solemnly de clares that he will carry out all the con ditions of this contract faithfully and loyally and that he or his heirs and suc cessors shall be its guarantors and shall accept full responsibility for any claim by any person in his or their territory ques tioning the validity of any of the stipula tions in this contract. In the event of any difference arising between the Com pany and the Zabit, whether in respect of the meaning of any of the foregoing articles or otherwise, such matters shall be settled in an un-official and friendly manner between the two parties. Failing a friendly settlement, the points in dispute shall be referred to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to arbitrate and to settle them, and his decision shall be accepted as final by both parties. This Agreement, however, cannot be cancelled except as provided above. 6.( - JoU't ]j ij AXXJU) U b o|oJ&gt;) U jlu^l i—OjtXsk. jO ]j oUJU.fi iJj^Lv ' tiji ^50 Jjjj 4JL)| iaij l&gt; (jjj* law j* &lt;sis oUi «£ ssjlo.) ^.iu6.r j i&gt;juj j.4,* )j fj-o* duJI (jf-ot. aJLJJ.*. J l ' ^ -«jm IJ ^jLx/* y Vi* ' ^XJD) AJJ) Jlxjj dJjJla. &lt;JvJO T / ^iUJ' oLfti*X^ (JAJ y JUa&gt;j| ^ o!J JUi' b (ijJI ^AOjXw. iobo AJJLT J^]o\ J golo y fj ) '^1;; k ^ J l jib ^ A/'b lail^ jl v— cjrf ^ «— olillla.1 J»3 JoUuz* iiy&gt;y i/«u »&gt;&lt;£ &lt;jka-aj jx£ jjla) &amp;) [y* JklU) I izijjle*. ilamt))} ^1 ^ a* t+y ; J^ 5 w **/ ,a ^ h^- d^u jljf yjj™. )/** }*- j'/ 5 ' OJU/ Jicb76 Dated this 4th day of Safar 1340, equiralent to the 6th day of October 1921. (In Persian.) (Signed) HAIDER KHAN HATAT DATJDI. (Signed) MUHAMMAD KHAN HATAT DAUDI. irr* j** jt* cAt • ^ I ^ r i i ^Oy»)oUa.*U:r' # »UA^J — For Messrs. Strick Scott &amp; Co., Ltd., Managing Agents, Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Ltd. (Signed) A. T. WILSON, Resident Director. Witnesses:— 8. CLEGG, British Vice-Consul, Bushire. M. KHALIL, Chief Dragoman to Residency. For Messrs. Strick Scott &amp; Co., Ltd., Managing Agents, Anglo-Persian Oil Co., Ltd. 6th October 1921. Witnesses :— A. T. WILSON, Resident Director. S. CLEGG, British Vice-Consul, Bushire. M. KHALIL, Chief Dragoman to Residency. ' cv.. - ir' J; •- l77 Dated 20th Safar 1340 (S2nd October 1921). From—S ir A. T. W ilson , Resident Direc tor, Messrs. Strick Scott &amp; Co., Mohammerah, To—H aidak K han H ayat D atjdi , C.I.E., Zabit of Hajat Daud and Kharg, Bandar Rig. After compliments,— With reference to the agreement which was concluded and signed between this Company and you, Article 3, although I informed you, during our interview, that a jarib of 1,000 Zara's was 70x70 square Zara's and accordingly you agreed, on my return to Mohammerah I made enquiries in this connection and it appears that in the purchases and leases entered into with His Excellency Sardar Aqdas, a jarib is 68x68 square Zara's. Therefore, I express my regret for this mistake, and shall be obliged if you will signify in writing your acceptance of the above-mentioned measurement, viz., 68x 68 Zara's. A satisfactory agreement has been also concluded with the Kashkuli Khans, and I hope that operations will be commenced as soon as the first rain falls. n *»&gt;«• , :. ; i JU p /l J .A .I c-jUaiw* I j'SX) Jajl-i J ,13? AJ U5! ^ Oj|o oU&amp;. Afijlls ^ v^-ob j| *- if ^[xij^asxi UUi ol5)Ay« ^ ) olli* j* t»luU I) olo jlyj &gt;UJ ' ti ACjLit^Lsk) J iSijA, J*} L»' ij;,jlvVily* Viftw U jjlij j ^A.V* Jylii' tj ui OIJ C J;'? J ; 1 J^aaoJ ^lo kAV*! J oojjt *«JU. - oUUx I hereby certify that the above is a true and faithful translation of a document in Persian registered on pasre 5 of the Begister Book lio. 3 kept in this Consul ate-General at Bushire. Dated at Bushire this eighth day of December 1921. S. CLEGG, British Vice-Consul. ms.r Certified true copy. W. E. Q. 8HULDHAM, Captain, Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Fersian Gulf.78 Dated 12th Rabi-al-awal 1340 (13tli November 1921). From— Haidau Khan Hatat Daudi, C.I.E., Zabet of Hay at Daud and Kharg, Bandar Rig, To-— Sir A. T. Wilson , Resident Director, Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Mohammerah. J 1 , , After compliments,— I beg most respectfully to state that I have had the honour of receiving your honoured letter dated 20th Safar 1340 corresponding to 22nd October 1921 which reached me on the 10th of the present month through Mr. Sharp. I have read it with great pleasure and am extremely obliged for your enquiries after my health and for the expression of your kindness. I have fully understood the contents of that letter. With regard to jarib, the accurate measurement of which you have explained to be 68 X 68 square Zara's, I have taken due cognizance of the matter, and hereby express my agreement to the abovemen- tioned measurement. In conclusion I beg to express my sincere and loyal sentiments and my readiness to perform any orders that Your Excellency may send me, and wish you a long life, welfare and prosperity. I hereby certify that the above is a true and faithful translation of a document in Persian registered on page 6 of the Begister Book No. 3 kept in this Consul ate-General at Bushire. Dated at Bushire this eighth day of December 1921, S. CLEGG, JBritish f ice- Consul- Certified true copy. W. E. Q. SHULDHAM, Captain, Vnder Secretary to the 'Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Li-?*) j** ^51 ^i-') O j Ua/O ^ v 5 ! tj f f j** •^ e ixxi pf] pi jjjl}* ^Jus) ^|v) WjlA ^(51 ^ ***** 4.L«l&gt; Jl oljiaj j) OyJ J' J A • •* 0 »• •• •• ut ^ u ' |y' &amp;&amp;*■&gt; ji lxso j r&gt;v ^ J j jjoji ,0^/y j &gt;—&gt;o|^l A-d-J jij y m &lt;J&gt;AJ ciyae*, y*\ )b olxco)^ j ^ J| )j OyL ^' c j jJOLtw jtjlM; L' _etU j .h\ it h'b '■ i..v J • i ,' 'f \ ' &gt;.;■ • ■ ■ 1 ' ; t ,i79 No. 18. AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE ^JUJ* j Jlio) jjb OJ ANGLO-PERSIAN OIL COMPANY AND THE KASHKULI KHANS. ' [Tmnslaiion^ An Agreement was entered into as follows between Messrs. the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Limited, on the one part here inafter called the Company and (1) Abul Path Khan Kashkuli on behalf of himself and all the descendants of the late Abul Hassan Khan Kashkuli, to include the descendants of Akbar Beg and Askar Beg Kashkuli and all their heirs and successors and all their tribesmen and dependants. (2) Hadi Khan Kashkuli on behalf of himself and all the descendants of the late Haji Muhammad Karim Khan Kashkuli, to include Hassan Quli Beg and all his descendants and all their heirs and succes sors and all their tribesmen and depen dants. ( (3) Ghulam Husain Khan Kashkuli on behalf of himself and ail the descendants of the late Kazim Beg Kashkuli and all their tribesmen and dependants. (4) Ilyas Khan Kashkuli on behalf of himself and all the descendants of the late Muhammad Ali Khan Kashkuli and all their heirs and successors and all their tribesmen and dependants. (5) Eathullah Khan Kashkuli on behalf of himself and all the descendants of the late Haidar Ali Khan Kashkuli and all their heirs and successors and all their tribesmen and dependants. (6) Muhammad Quli Khan on behalf of himself and all the descendants of the late Muhammad Hassan Khan Kashkuli and all their heirs and successors and all their tribesmen and dependents on the other hand hereinafter called the Kashkuli Khans, in respect of the privileges required by the said Company throughout the whole extent of the territories in occupation of the Kashkuli tribe in their winter quarters, for the purposes of the Company's business under the concession which they hold from the Persian Government. ♦Mo jl/ J/* kfti J^U ojj iS ) ( l) j ^ tiyxs* L) ^ ^ ixw j Oj j* ^ (r) **** V j' t3 ^ 1 - ajuU ' ^,3 LwJ2 ; (f) ) J* cy*-f ^ - 4*jIJ jj[£.e j 0Ua.| jjkj) (o) ; oU^lj j 0^1 - ^je vlt; ^ U&gt;jl° jl J*- S*** (^j) j ^ ^is wsl9 y* jjiy jh* AXJJUT'* |«UJ J 0,jLa. dar^l) 4 jji; j} - AUj? s&lt;y£j (lax. .. \ \80 Article 1.—The Company shall have the right to drill for oil and for water and to make all investigations necessary for the purpose of their business in all parts of the said territories and to construct and erect tramways, roads, buildings, machi nery and telegraph apparatus of all kinds in any part of the said territories so far as may be necessary for the purposes of their business. The Company shall have the right to collect and use free anywhere in the said territories stone, gach, salt, sulphur, clay, wood and water whether from rivers or springs for the purposes of their works. The selection of routes and sites for such work shall rest with the Company. Article 2 —All lands whatever required by the Company for the purpose of their preliminary exploration for oil including all or any natural springs of oil in the said territories together with an adequate supply of water so far as available shall be granted by the said Kashkuli Khans to the Company free of charge and without let or hindrance from any of their relatives or dependents or any of their tribesmen or of third parties. And it is hereby agreed that in consideration of the sums to be paid to the Kashkuli Khans under Articles 8 and 9 any claim for compensa tion, reward or subsidy put forward by a third party in respect of such land or of the protection to be rendered to the Com pany by the Kashkuli Khans shall be met by the said Khans or their heirs and successors and that under no circumstances shall the Company be made to pay com pensation for the same. If the Company finds itself obliged to pay other parties in order to ensure the safety of their work the amount paid may be deducted by the Company at their option from the amount due to the Kashkuli Khans. Article 3. —As soon as the Company have been successful in finding oil in sufficient quantities to justify the laying of a pipe-line and as soon a^ oil is being exported thereby the Company hereby undertake to purchase and the Kashkuli Khans hereby undertake to sell whatever land may be required by the Company for their operations at the following rates : for every square of 100 yards on each side ten Tumans for arable land and five Tumans for non-arable land. ja*. ^ ' J;' OyA. JUxf Vg'') JxCfcJ ; irfj* ifltftj ax L / jO tjk. OlUU/* Jjjj jA j] a) mlts) JuSjt f ^ ^ } JUc| jlj-ii/- j* j* b lo-bj* Joai iijL &lt;j^b |*jii ^*^1® o^b ts o) ; i)^L- ; j f\y\j bu^ l*si&gt; u|J j| pl± JiUw j) b ^l*j) b ^1 b ^Ijb ^1; olo jy, )) ioU ^0 ci—-} ^ ^ j A ^ ^ ^ b j J V^5^ r0 I; v* 6 ^ I; or*? J' j** ^Ujl jx&amp;s}£&amp;&gt; lj ^iib j*} ^itxa.r dXxj) &lt;J^jp.&lt;0 - |*^4W sjj] ja'i) if jjty* jj kai j jfiy* «xib j * is uU«- &lt;iym pj)l oljki^c ' *^Lj \*sj I 10 Ji) A*J* £jJ cZ-ti £jj ix* j*Land so acquired shall be the absolute property of the Company for the period of their Agreement and the Company shall have full proprietary rights therein. Article 4.—No one shall have any right to graze flocks on land so acquired or in ' temporary occupation of the Company for the purpose of exploration and should they do so the Kashkuli Khans undertake to punish them.. Should anyone transgress the Company's boundaries and should they or any of their flocks meet with an acci dent (which God forbid) the Company •hall not be responsible. Article 5. —All houses, shops, etc., which the Company may build on land sold as above or temporarily occupied shall be free of all local taxes and the Kashkuli Khans or their representatives shall have no right to collect taxes from any of the people em ployed by the Company or temporarily permitted to settle on the land in their possession. Article fi.—The Kashkuli Khans under take to give all the protection in their power to the Company and to their staif and labourers in any part of their territory from thefts, highway robbery, assault, etc. Similarly, the Kashkuli Khane under take to protect all the property of the Company and of its employees which may be exposed to wilful damage or to possible loss or theft. Article 7.—For the above purpose it is further agreed that the Company shall appoint permanent trustworthy guards to the number of 30 at present to be increased as necessary at the option of the Company, under a reliable man of good family whose pay and that of the guards shall be pro vided by the Company and who shall remain there summer and winter. If in spite of the efforts of the said guards theft should occur, the Kashkuli Khans undertake to recover the property stolen and to compensate the Company for any damage sustained in their terri tory. In the event of non -recovery of the stolen property, the value thereof shall be deducted by the Company from the Bums due to the Khans. o?V j l [ ' J oU r ,AJ - !(j ^ r o(.-a3c^ J ixij* l ' 1 ** I k&gt; '■i' -'■! OyM ijyljs* lotiij jO Ak/ jt] ) (Ufii' 1^1 if a v .*j V^bl ^ sJJL - LA f Jk^ **) |*UJ - i r^- j* sjk** .♦ ^ , ;L*/« I J £ jit jl c\jUi - tMJktw.A (OC* ^ '1)^' ) I) C^laCftA. is j\ Jj*. Jlac-^'jl oLnJUc &amp;*) (fhf, , *ajl*x^ r u j ' is ^ j sj lXmj ^ Lt - oijUi «4x* ( c) ^ju^r if jui 0)0 tol/* ll)Lx x L^j) «ar if olJUf (Jitj oUk.U'ia.| j yu t— oyu ; *•** OJ*** ) 8^/yU^ jl «jk£ iVijUi ju-y u a^b'4 t ^ ju r ^;y&gt;y jylsj^y*. ty* ^1; jjk)Uj l^j 45^*1*'® Jl^l ^ *A^Ai/c82 The number of guards at any place where the Company may operate shall be fixed by the Company. It shall be the duty of the above-men tioned Head of the Guard to keep order in the areas in his charge to such extent as the Company may order him. He shall have no right to interfere in any dispute among the Company's servants unless asked by the Company to do so. In case of misconduct the said guards are subject to dismissal or fine by the Company. In the event of any heavier punishment being needed the offender shall be handed over to the representative of the Kashkali Khans and the Kashkuli Khans undertake that punishment shall be inflicted and to use their utmost endea vours to uphold the authority of the Company's employees thereby avoiding unnecessary trouble to both parties of this contract. Article 8.—Until oil is exported by the pipe-line from the said territories the Company shall pay to the Kashkuli Khans the sum of 10,000 tomans per annum payable half-yearly from 21st March next in arrears in equal proportion to the signa tories of this Agreement. The division amongst their relations of the sums paid as above to the six signa tories is their own concern and does not affect the Company. But it is to be noted that Hadi Khan has agreed to pay 250 tomans annually from his own share and that of his section to Hassan Quli Beg, and also that Abul Path Khan has agreed to pay 250 tomans annually from his own share and that of his section to Hamza Beg. And it is hereby agreed, with the consent of all the Kashkuli Khans, that in addition to the sums payable as above, the Company shall pay— (1) to Ghulam Husain Khan Kash kuli, on behalf of himself and all the descendants of the late Kazim Beg Kashkuli and all their tribesmen and dependents, the sum of 334 tomans annually in order that their share may be brought to a total of 2,000 tomans annually; and (2) to Muhammad Quli Khan Kash kuli, on behalf of himself and all the descendants of the late Mu hammad Hassan Khan Kashkuli and all their heirs and successors i) iiOLyAj j) ^1 olxUc jjo ^ j*)* b cJuija J jUJ ^ 5,. iiuJo 9 j jc) ))| AJ ja JJ - J-iUi jx) j JI ^ ^ jjoaS) ss jjjlo ^jl^ay aiL* diib ^.1 yvj 0 r;i J oU ^ m O) Oj! ji c^«,| AXJJIa Ayij iaii ^ jjo iitjJU- j) c ^ Jjl jo J^l la—S is ^4 oyi J)l j 0 P* ^ &gt; y6 j? A ''^ J&gt;i ^ ^iljl ^ jy L- ^ ij dja*. j vi/''* dio) Jjlai ^ ojk. jl aj [j^y* j iiUJL* is idy*.} y J ay*' - oJL-jJ fy^f* ^ 'wCw ij**- v iLxir p'l&amp;k i»&gt;L- ^Xy» j ds &lt;s£i jf** ^A» jc V,«3JU. AJ I X JI MI ^yyi ^jda^e jytsj jl r Uij oU^| ; ^) j;; ijUf« AxJli' *&gt;jl^ (y** ) ^ y *y* j]&gt; A )* )5 a**' « &gt;ijA3 a) 83 f and all their tribsemen and de pendents, the sum of 334 tomans annually, in order that their en are may be brought to a total of 2,000 tomans annually. Article 9. —Should the Company succeed in finding oil in paying quantities in the said territories and as soon as oil is ex ported by the pipe-line the Company agreed to pay to the Kashkuli Khans a further sum of 10,000 tomans annually making a total of 20,000 tomans annually, divisible amongst the said Khans in the same way as above. Whenever the Company decide to issue shares to the Kashkuli Khans in any new Company or Compaeies which may be formed for the extraction of oil in the said territories, the said Khans shall be granted three shares every hundred shares issued by such Company or Companies. These shares will be issued in the name of the Kash kuli Khans and Ihe dividends that may thereafter be declared anmmlly by the said Company or Companiei shall be divided equally amongst the said Khans. The above shares shall be paid by the Company to the Kashkuli Khans in return for the protection and assistance they hare undertaken to provide for the Company's staff and work, on condition that they have in fact provided it, but it is hereby agreed that the said amount of 20,000 tomans shall cease to be paid after the first declaration of a dividend on the shares. The Kashkuli Khans hereby undertake not to sell, mortgage, transfer, or otherwise dispose of such shares, if issued, and in order that such shares may permanently remain in the Kashkuli Khans' family they hereby agree to deposit the script with the Company against a receipt for the same. Article 10.—In the event of the Com pany failing to discover oil in sufficient quantity they shall have the right to- stop work at their option and the Kashkuli Khans shall have no claim to any of the above payments. h** y ; 0 1;; ; iiUJU Jjkijl ft** if ajW dJotj I ** - J Si iaii j]yb j]}t yi ^Jb u; &amp;s j]}* Oj'O yxi ^,1,^3 .jU-oi' y dy* f****■&gt; jy.} 1 * s * b i—G h ) ^0 kaj ^ b cU-jl )) jjl)* \s.myx) jl jOlk) ^1)° ^ ^ V;-®' ^xj axjUi ^ - Ookl^A. jyj* j*' j) ih'j IJailan^ j o)a*L^ oUy*? ao)o lyil oUUx ; f !}+1 *! i's j ^ j is'f cy&amp;.y* jj** j ai-ib O!jjU ^ £»IUJ ^lj ^^1 J' u*i ^ tjyt jw* rfjbJb* jljii ^5 ^ ; A it yb ^ &gt;ssyi*y* iX v *v* ) £xi *J l;V' ^ d4&gt;,J V 1 ? *jy AXA b JlSi3| b ^ b jj pij* ^ ^ awlJj ^5b JyUJ ij db^.1 djd/ v^jb*b ^ , JSU «%- / - ' )U 4J- 0,10 ^ ^ ^ j| ^ ^jtJ Ji^*j Ij ^ fJSV* ^ i1 ' 1 - ij yjj)(3y p*/*) rr A '• ' 4 ' T &gt; | L Xj J T A d ^ &gt; rp- r i i ) l L £ 1 i 'J. £ .ii r J -CArticle 11. —Kasbkuli Khans solemnly declare that they will carry out all the conditions of this contract willingly and faithfully and that they and their heirs and successors shall be its guarantors and shall accept full responsibility for any claim or dispute by any person whether in their territory or beyond it questioning the validity of any stipulations of this contract. This contract cannot be cancelled except as provided as above and shall remain in force for the period of the Company's con cession from Persian Government or any extension or renewal thereof. In the event of any difference arising between the Company and the Kasbkuli K-hans it shall be settled in an unofficial and friendly manner between the two parties; failing a friendly settlement the dispute shall be referred to one of His Majesty's Consular officers for arbitration &amp;nd his decision shall be accepted as final. Signed at Chihil Chasmah on this 22nd day oi Mizan, 1300 Takhakui-il, equi valent to 14th October 1921. Ifor Messrs. Strick Scott and Company. Limited. Managing Agents, Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Limited. A. T. WILSON, Rc^idsni Director*. The Uth October 1921, u t. „ ,• ^ Witnessed by several minor chiefs and Kadkhudas. v ABUL PATH KHAN. HADI KHAN. GHULAM HTJSAIN KHAN. ILTAS KHAN; FATHULLAH KHAN. MUHAMMAD QULI KHAN, )j 4]o j]j9 j a]y* AjJir tajj ci y y jit y j*&gt; IA. a-ib iS jjt J| b ]y£ti 4jy( s£l,~sn*ai I ^ l^j| ^ I iLa. tyj| lyjj JjL JO? U ob ,|y \j olj jji ^j) tJ j isij I a j paj ioU jfij AAlr j) jyj* ^ tixjl sJlo ' 0 y ^ ^ V//H&gt; 5 J 1 ^ *? &amp;+-J jakj.UJ sf j* j loj+j - ^-1 j ***&gt; Airr- ^ r aoj]^ - ejijj JaI cy») - ajUy J -fAj 0 ir — For Messrs. Striek Scott &amp; Co., Ltd., Managing Agents, Anglo- Persian Oil Co., Ltd. A. T. WILSON, Resident Director 14th October 1921. ' - e^) ' 'ixo.si* - UL-wl kz/ x/ * - *y &gt;A. - £**** v ^ ' '• ' ' JJI@ ri |r 85 I hereby certify that the foregoing writing in Persian is a true and faithful copy of a document in original registered on pages 1, 2 and 3 of the Register Book ^o. 3, kept at this Consulate-General at Bushire. Dated at Bushire this twenty-seventh day of October 1921. S. CLEGG, British Vice- Consul, JSushire* ' . i , ; 1 J U- -ix86 No. 19. AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE ANGLO-PERSIAN OIL COMPANY AND THE ILKHANI OF THE QA8HGAIS. [Translation.] Article i.—The Company shall have the right to drill for oil and for water and to make all investigations necessary for the purpose of their business in all parts of the said territories and to construct and erect tramways, roads, building machinery and telegraph apparatus of all kinds in any part of the said territories O so far as may be necessary for the purposes of their business. The Company shall have the right to collect and use free anywhere in the said territories stone, gach, salt, sulphur, clay for building purposes, wood and water whether from river or springs for the purposes of their work, provided that the taking of the water is not detrimental to cultivation in the boundaries in question. The selection of routes and sites for such work shall rest with the Company. It is hereby explained that as long as the Persian Government have left salt and sulphur in their natural state and free, the Company will utilize them free of charge. In the event of the said articles being monopolized by any Company or bv any one under any concession, the Company will communicate with the Government and effect an arrangement. Article All lands whatever required by the Company for the purpose of their preliminary exploration for oil including all or any natural springs of oil in the said territories together with an adequate supply of water so far as available shall be granted by the said Ilkhani to the Company free of charge, provided that the taking of the water is not detrimental to cultivation in the boundaries in question and withomt let or hindrance .from any of his relatives or dependents or any of his tribps- men or of third parties. J T. 1 .u A ° dit 1 ishe ! eb . y agreed that in consideration of the sums to be paid to the Ilkhani under articles 8 and 9, any claim for compensation, or subsidy put forward by third party m respect of such land or of the protection to be rendered to the Company by the Ilkhani shall be met by the said Ilkhani or his heirs and successors and that under no circumstances shall the Company be made to pay compensation for the same. If the Compary finds itself obliged to pay other parties in order to ensure the safety of their work the amount paid maybe deducted by the said Company at their option from the amount due to the Ilkhani. Article 5.—As soon as the Company have been successful in finding oil in sufficient quantities to justify the laying of one or more pipe-lines to one or more spots on the coast or elsewhere and as soon as oil is being exported thereby the Company hereby undertakes to purchase, and the Ilkhani hereby undertakes to dispose of, his grazing and other rights over whatever Government or other land may be required by the Company for their operations at the following rates :-tor CU-TV' square of hundred yards on each side ten tomans for unirrigated arable land and five tomans for non-arable land. It is to be understood that it will still be incumbent on the Company in accord ance with the concession to acquire the said lands from the Persian Government in the manner specified m their concession or from the lawful owners, whoever they may be, by purchase or otherwise. ' wnuever mey The Ilkhani further undertakes to sell whatever land may be in his own personal possession at the following rates :-for every square of huudred yard, on each side ten tormm lor unirrigated arable land and five tomans for non-arable land Irrigated land must be acquired by the Company at a reasonable value in accordance With the concession they hold from the Persian Government! accordance of tii^ agreement and anvlvt ^• abSOlutC P r0 P ert y of Company for the period or tneir agreement and any extensmn or renewal thereof, and the Comnanv shall have full proprietary rights therein. company snail in temnorarv oTclToVn^T ^ 40 flooks 011 «&gt; acquired or a s. xr87 Company's boundaries and should they or any of their flocks meet with an accident (which God forbid), the Company shall not be responsible. Artide 5. —All houses, shops, etc., which the Company may build on land sold as above or temporarily occupied shall be free of all local taxes. The Ilkhani or his representatiyes shall have no right to collect taxes from any of the people employed by the Company or temporarily permitted to settle on the land in their possession. Article 6.—The Ilkhani undertakes to give all the protection in his power to the Company and to their staff and labourers in any part of his territory from theft, highway robbery, assault, etc. Similarly the Ilkhani undertakes to protect all the property of the Company and of their employes which may be exposed to wilful damage or to possible loss or theft. Article 7.—Por this purpose (as long as the Persian Government have not detailed regular forces in accordance with the Company's concession) it is further agreed that the Company, in consultation with the Ilkhani and with the knowledge of the Persian Government, shall appoint permanent trustworthy guards at whatever place they may wish to work under a reliable Persian of good family whose pay and that of the guards shall be provided and fixed by the Company in consultation with the Ilkhani and who shall remain there summer and winter. If, in spite of the efforts of the said guards, theft shall occur, the Ilkhani under takes to recover the property stolen and to compensate the Company foi any damage sustained in his territory. In the event of the non-recovery of the stolen property, the v^alue thereof shall be deducted by the Company from the sums due to the Ilkhani. The number of guards at any place where the Company may operate shall be fixed by the Company in consultation with the Ilkhani and with the knowledge of the Persian Government. It shall be the duty of the above-mentioned head of the guards to keep order in the areas in his charge to such extent as the Company may order him : he shall have no right to interfere in any disputes among the Company s servants unless asked by the Company to do so. In case of misconduct, the said guards are subject to dismissal or fine by the Company. In the event of any heavier punishment being needed, the offender shall be handed over to the representative of the Ilkhani and the Ilkhani undertakes that punishment shall be inflicted and to use his utmost endeavour to uphold the authority of the Company's employees, thereby avoiding unnecessary trouble to both parties of this contract. Article 8—Until oil is exported by the pipe-line from the said territories, the Company shall pay to the Ilkhani the sum of one thousand English pounds per annum payable half yearly from the 21st March in arrears. Article 9 —Should the Company succeed in finding oil in paying quantities in the said territories and as soon as oil is exported by the pipe-line, the Company aeree to pav to the Ilkhani a further sum of one thousand English pounds annually, making a total sum of two thousand English pounds annually. ^ Whenever the Company decide to issue shares to the Ilkhani in any new company or companies which may be formed for the extraction of oil m the said territories (including those covered by the agreement of the Company with the Kashkuli Khans), the said Ilkhani shall be granted three shares out of every hundreu shares issued by such company or companies. These shares will be issued m the name of the Ilkhani and the dividends that may thereafter be declared annually by the said company or companies shall be paid annually to the Ilkham. ^ The above shares shall be paid by the Company to the Ilkham in return for the protection and assistance he has undertaken to provide for the Company 8 staff and W on tle condition that he has in fact provided it, but it is hereby agreed that the said amount of two thousand English pounds shall cease to be paid after the first declaration of a dividend on the shares. The Ilkhani hereby undertakes not to sell, mortgage, transfer or otherwise dispose of such shares, if issued, and in order that such shares may permanently88 remain in his family, he hereby agrees to deposit the script with the Company against a receipt for the same. Article 10. —In the event of the Company failing to discover oil in sufficient quantities in any place where they may he working, they shall have the right to stop work at their option and the Ilkhani shall have no claim to any of the above payments. Article ll.—li is hereby understood that should anyone be appointed by the Persian Government as the Ilbegi to participate in the management of the tribe belonging to the Ilkhani and should he interfere with this agreement or raise any claim, the Ilkhani himself will be answerable. Article 12. —The Ilkhani solemnly declares that he will carry out all the con ditions of this contract willingly and faithfully and that he, and his heirs and successors shall be its guarantors and shall accept full responsibiJity for any claim or dispute by any person, whether in their territory or beyond it, questioning the validity of any stipulations on this agreement. This contract cannot be cancelled except as provided as above, and shall remain in force for the period of the Company's concession from the Persian Government or any extension or renewal thereof. Article 13.-In the event of any difference arising between the Company and the Ilkhani, it - shall be settled in an unofficial and friendly manner between the two parties, failing a friendly settlement, the dispute shall be referred to three arbitrators, one of whom is to be nominated by the IJkhani, second by the Company and the third by the said two arbitratorSj and the decision given by that body shall be accepted as final. Signed and sealed at Dokohak this 22nd day of Eamadhan 1340 equivalent to the 20th day of May 1922. I his agreement which consists of thirteen articles and which has been con cluded between my son, Muhammad Nasir Khan, and the Anglo^ Persian Oil Company, is hereby confirmed and is correct. (Signed) ISMAIL QASHQAI. (Sealed) ISMAIL (SAULET-ED-DOWLAH). Por the Anglo-Persian Oil Company. _ 0 - 7 (Signed) A. T. WILSON. May 20th, 1922. (Signed) MUHAMMAD NASIR QASHQAI. (Sealed) MUHAMMAD NASIR. Agreement concluded between Messrs. The Anglo-Persian Oil Company and Muhammad Nasir Khan, Ilkhani of the Qashqais, on behalf of himself, his heirs, successors, the headmen and tribesmen of the Qashqais. •i II 1 kh 1 ani a ^ rees to confirm the agreement dated the 22nd Mizau Takhaqui il, 1300, concluded between the said Company and the Kashkuli Khans, on the condition that:— Firstly,^ the said Khans obey all the orders and instructions of the Jlkhan m every respect and do not procrastinate in carrying out their duties and obligations with regard to him. Secondly, that the said Khans pay their revenues to the Ilkhani in accord ance with tribal custom and do not fail in paying the same at all. Thh dly, that if the Khans should fail in any one of the two conditions men- iiontd above, the Company should in no way support them. 2. The Ilkhani undertakes that as long as the aforesaid Khans duly observe and act upon the conditions mentioned in the first clause, he (the Ilkhani) will, also, accord them kindness and regards and will not subject them to his wrath and displeas ure.89 S. The Company undertakes to ^ive the Ilkhani the three per cent, of the shares which it had given to the Kashkuli Khans in accordance with the agreement referred to, and it will pay the said Khans only the sum of ten thousand six hundred and sixty-eight tomans which the Company had stipulated to pay to them. 4. The Ilkhani undertakes to see that the Kashkuli Khans abide by the condi tions contained in clause three and bring about no trouble and annoyance for the Company. Written this 22nd Hamadhan 13i0 equivalent to the 20tli May 1922. (Signed and sealed) MUHAMMAD NASIR QASHQAI. This agreement which consists of four clauses and has been concluded between my son, Muhammad Nasir Khan, and the Anglo-Persian Oil Com pany is hereby confirmed and is correct. (Signed) ISMAIL QASHQAI. (Sealed) ISMAIL (SAULAT-ED-DOWLEH). We confirm this agreement on our own behalf and that of the other Khans who have signed the agreement dated the 22nd Mizan 1300 and we do undertake that neither we nor they themselves will create any difficulty or raise any objection for the Company and the Ilkhani. Dated the 23fid Ramadhan 1340. (Signed and sealed) HADI KASHKULI. GHULAM HUSAIN KASHKULI. Por Anglo-Persian Oil Company. (Signed) A. T. WILSON. May 20th, 1922. MGI PC—S6—Xl 11—11-1-27 ^5-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000884.0x0001b4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/20/C231</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000884.0x0001b4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/20/C231</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Assurances, Undertakings and Agreements, Etc., Made by Certain Chiefs and Khans of Southern Persia with the British Government and Certain British Trading Companies'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1926</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-11-07T00:12:18</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">per</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (52 folios)</extent><extent>The assurances, agreements and undertakings compiled in this volume are arranged according to serial number from 1 to 18. These appear roughly in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover, and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume is a printed report, published by the Government of India Press (Calcutta: 1926), constituting a collection of assurances, undertakings and agreements made by chiefs and Khans of Southern Persia with the British Government and trading companies between 1898 and 1922. The volume is marked 'Confidential' on the front cover and contains a table of contents (folios 4-5). The agreements, some appearing in both Persian and English, are ordered by serial number and they include:No. 1: Undertaking Given by Certain Notables of Luristan in regard to the Construction of Cart Road through Part of their Territory (8 June 1911);No. 2: Correspondence regarding Right of Option Granted to Persian Railway Syndicate by Persian Government for Construction of Certain Railway Lines (9 February 1913, 4 March 1913, and 10 January 1920);No. 3: Memorandum Regarding Concessions for Roads and Railways in South-West Persia up to 1917 (1917);No. 4: Persian Transport Company's Concession for the Construction of a Commercial Road Between Ahwaz and Tehran and the Establishment of a Transport Service thereon (5 August 1890);No. 5: Compensation for Loss of Pilotage Fees, Amounting to Ts. 2000 per annum to be paid to Haidar Khan, Hayat Daudi [Ḥaydar Khān Ḥayāt Dāwūdī], C I E (12 February 1920 and 26 February 1920);No. 6: Agreement Concluded between Messrs. Lynch Bros. and certain Bakhtiari Chiefs for the Construction and Maintenace of a Road from Ahwaz to Isfahan and Shushter [Shushtār] to Isfahan (3 March 1898);No. 7: D'Arcy Oil Concession (28 May 1901);No. 7(a): Translation of the D'Arcy Oil Concession (28 May 1901);No. 8: Agreement Between D'Arcy Syndicate and the Bakhtiari (15 November 1905);No. 8(a): Refusal of Persian Government to Recognize Agreement between the D'Arcy Syndicate and the Bakhriaris (12 January 1906);No. 8(b): Notes on the Bakhtiari Agreement of November 15 1905 (20 October 1906);No. 9: Agreement between Mr W[illiam] K[nox] D'Arcy and the Kili Sayyeds (1 October 1906);No. 10: Agreement between the Oil Company and H. E. Shahab-Es-Sultaneh, Ilbegi [Shihāb al-Sulṭānah Īlbagī] of the Bakhtiar (25 March 1907);No. 11: Land Agreement between the Oil Company and the Bakhtiari Khans (15 May 1911);No. 11(a): Power-of-Attorney Appointing Sardar Muhtesham [Sardār Muḥtasham] and Sardar Bahadur [Sardār Bahādur] as Agents of the Bakhtiari Khans (1910);No. 11(b): The Bakhtiari Khans' Orders to their Tribesmen Regarding the Oil Company's Employees (May 1911);No. 11(c): Undertaking made by the Bakhtiari Khans regarding the Kili Sayyeds (May 1911);No. 12: Agreement for Protection of Pipe-Line (28 April 1911);No. 13: Supplementary Agreement between Mr W K D'Arcy and the Kili Sayyeds (10 February 1911);No. 14: Agreement between the Anglo-Persian Oil Company and Parwiz Khan, Gunduzlu [Parvīz Khān Gunduzlū] (20 February 1911);No. 15: Agreement between the Anglo-Persian Oil Company and the Wali of Pusht-i-Kuh (19 September 1919);No. 16: Land Aquisition Agreement between Anglo-Persian Oil Company and the Bakhiairi Khans (20 April 1921);No. 17: Agreement between the Anglo-Persian Oil Company and Haidar Khan, C I E, of Hayat Daud (6 October 1921, 22 October 1921, and 13 November 1921);No. 18: Agreement between the Anglo-Persian Oil Company and the Kashkuli [Kashkūlī] Khans (14 October 1921);No. 19: Agreement between Anglo-Persian Oil Company and the Ilkhani of the Qashgais (20 May 1922).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>William Knox D'Arcy</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Oil</topic></subject><subject><topic>Transportation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000884.0x0001b4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>