<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000a3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-14T11:27:50.566Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">© BRITISH CONSULATEVery Secret From, Ko.C/$'? of 1935. Politico! Agency &amp; H.B.M'e Coneulote. Muscat, 11th February 1935. Major C.E.U.Bremner, K.C., Political Agent &amp; H*B.M*e Coneul, Muecot. To, The hobble Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Eushire. Sir, 1 have the honour to submit herewith separately a brief resume of the political situation in ^ uscot os it stands at present, and my deductions therefrom. The latter have been formed from my own observation of 'signs of the times”, from private conversations with various members of the Ruling family and others, and from a series of incidents which, although jftgr seemingly insignificant, appear to indicate the direction in which the wind is now blowing. 3. The situation is one that will require careful watching in the future and I am of the opinion that before long it will be essential to issue His Highness the Sultan with a very definite warning os to his general attitude. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Major, Politicel Agent &amp; H.B.If'e Consul. Muscat.1. Soiyid S 0 id 'bin Toimur ot the age of 22 years, succeeded his father to the Sultanate in *arch 1932. He hod ic President of the Council of till then been th&lt; Ministers and, and hy his keeness end aptitude for work, hod A shown considerable promise and was popular with his father^ subjects. He readily sought the advice of the -heeident and 2 . Political Agent and woe generally inclined to be guided thereby, he hod hod the assistance of a Financial Adviser for several years and, by virtue of the foregoing, the finances of the State were so far redeemed from their former chaotic condition, that it was possible in 1933 to pay off the lost instalment of the loon which hod been generously afforded the State by the Government of Indio. 3. This event, in itself normally on happy aOgury, undoubtedly marked the birth of changed ideas in the mind of the ^ultan and remarks mode by him at the time os to 'now being free' are singularly poignnnt in view of subsequent events. 4. In April 1933 His Highness proceeded to Dhofar, where he ensconced himself for close on a year, during which period he was practically completely out of touch with the British Authorities. It was however apparent to the Political Agent, on the one occasion that he was enabled to visit Dhofor, that the Sultan had wasted no time there. H© had carried out vatt improvements in his town of Salola, he had practically changed the shape of his 'palace' and introduced sanitary and other arrangements there that portended more than mere casual and occasional sojourns ot Saloloi he hod commenced building a large Customs House and, by successive tour in the province, hod token for greoter pains to consolidate his influence in Dhofor than he has ever token in Muscat proper or the Botinoh. 5. Both during his stay there and since his return to Muscat2 Muscat, constant quiet despatch has been mode of stores, furniture, arms end money to Dhofar and his entire stable has been retained at Solaln* 6. Money to the extent of Rs.l7000/surreptiously 'borrowed' from the Government Treasury for the Dhofor visit of 1933, has never been 9X1&amp; repaid and this item has been studiously omitted from all State accounts and Budgets. 7. During his sojourn in Dhofar the Sultan still further consolidated his position by contracting a marriage alliance with the family of Sheikh Said bin Ali ol Ma-aishi. a powerful Qura mountain Sheikh. The marriege, it is believed, has yet to be consummated. His entire entourage ore likewise said to hove contracted marriages at Sclalo, but onlhCev- return to Muscat these were annulled by divorce. 8. On his return to Muscat, the Sultan abolished the poet of Financial Adviser, announcing his intention of taking over all finance himself. The Financial Department, os such, has ceased to exist. In lieu thereof the Sultan has created the poet of 'Director of Revenues' and has appointed thereto hie confidant, R.S. Dulichand, a bannia of Mionwali, whose bent and proclivities arc widely and well known to be entirely ontjfc-British. The finances of the State ore now wholly run by the Director of Revenues in conjuction with the Sultan and the Treasury itself has been moved into the Palace proper. 9* The State Budgets, os now presented annually, ore wholly fictitious, and whilst large items on both the credit and debit side ore never shown, the palpable ±xsxBxx±jig inaccuracy in figures would appear to indicate deliberate juggling. 10. Meanwhile, freed from the control and supervision of a Financial Adviser, the Director of Revenues has seen fit to inaugurate methods of taxation that con but be termed oppressive, if not tyrannical. Many instances hove only3 ©V lately come to light where these taxes are demanded from British and ^ritieh Protected subjects, in direct contraven tion of Treaty obligations. Numerous incidents from all sides ore heard of the high-handed action of this individual and of general introduction of 'bonnia raj'. Thilst Muscat subjects fear the result of complaining, British subjects refrain from formulating complaints for fear of subtle forms of reprisal which con but accelerate the ruin of their businesses. 11. The Omani likewise complains of infringement of the treaty with the Muscat Government whereby only 5 % duty is imposed on imports. This agreement stipulated that 5 % would be imposed ad valorem on all goods imported. In practice a duty, is being imposed on loads , which amounts to 10 % or more on imports from Oman and the interior. 12. In Muscat and Matrah merchants complain that in spite of way bills and invoices the Customs authorities recover duties on thjfeir own enhanced assessment and that merchants thus find it hopeless to transact business. Instances are known where goods, on which duty has already been paid in the Botinoh, have again been taxed on re-importa tion by sea to Muscat, and this in spite of the production of Customs receipts. 13* The Naval Contractor, Mohamad Khan son of K.B.Nasib is being constantly put to trouble over the importation of provisions for the Hoyal Navy, which ore exempt from Customs duty. This is entirely at the instigation of Dulichond who has cist xx&amp;Bxxly seduously prevailed on the Sultan not to pay his large outstanding debts to Mohamad Khan.* i4. The whole of these objectionable practices are directly attributable to this individual, but it is inconceiv able that they con go on without the knowledge and authority of the Sultan. 15 r he all pervading idea is obviously the collection18 of ob much money oe possible and to this end Dulichond is given o free hrnd. The feet that fiie Highness expends none of his revenue in improving the condition of his people, — ——* ■ _ —-— &gt; whether it be in Kuscot ond Motroh, or in the outlying districts of the Botinoh, tends to confirm the view that money is being collected for on ulterior purpose, i^e. the embellishment of Dhofar with the ultimate object of transferring the seat of Government to that Province. 16. The Director of Revenues since hie accession to pov/er, has spared no opportunity of consolidating his own position by introducing his own friends ond relatives to every Deportment of Government, from the Muscat Infantry to the Muscat and Gwadur Customs. There is no doubt that his influence with the Sultan is supreme and is chiefly directed to misleading the Ruler and alienating him, as far as possible from British influence ond control. 17. Another potent onti-Eritish influence to which the Sultan is exposed is afforded by one Itmoil Sffendi, a young Palestinian, of the scmi-cauccted, know-oll 'intellegensio' type, so common now in Palestine and elsewhere. This young man, a relic of the school masters imported from Palestine by Mr. Bertram Thomas, has been employed in a private capacity by the Sultan since the closing of the Muscat school ond should the school ever be opened is certain to be appointed Head master thereto. He is rabidly anti-British but, lacking the finesse of his Hindu compere, he is unable to restrain his feelings and gives full vent publicly to his anti-British sentiments. He is the close and constant companion of the Sultan who, jdus to quote His Highness* own words to the Political Agent, has ,? a great admiration for the extensive learning and wide knowledge of Ismail Effendi'. There is no doubt that he exercises a great influence on the Sultan, to whom he constantly retails the 'horrors' 1 ond' iniquities' of British Administration in Palestine.5 18. Temnil Sffendi, who is at present on leove, was obviously the author of on article on Muscat which recently appeared in on Arctic news sheet published in Palestine. The article, which was mainly devoted to lauding the Sultan, made objectionable allusion to the expensive luxury of employing British Officers in the State. It is alleged that this individual has been summoned to return at once to Muscat. 19. From what I have both gathered and observed, these two individuals, i.e. Dulichrnd and Tcmcil Effendi (both British subjects), seconded by leaser lights, have incessantly impressed on the Sulten the necessity for asserting hie own importance and for demonstrating his complete independence of any outside (i.e.British) influence. The Sultan^ youth has undoubtedly made him prone to imbibe the flattery and bad advice of both these individuals and the results are manifest in his present attitude, which even since end particularly since his recent return from Indio, has been marked. Although the oulton skilfully veils his real feelings by a disarming personal charm of manner at interviews, his discourtesy in certain recent incidents cannot be excused on the plea of ignorance. 20. Prior to his departure for India His highness privately informed me that he hoped to proceed to Bhofar again after the monsoons, ^e has however since confidentially informed a friend of the Political Agent that he wishes to go there as soon as possible, 'probably in a month’s time' 1 . He has invited Dr. Harrison of the American Mission to visit him there. 21. Pro* the foregoing indications I am personally convinced that the Sultan^ ultimate intention is virtually, if not actually, to transfer his headquarters to Dhofar. He seeks thereby to render himself inaccessible and to thus pose os being 'independent' of British influence. Resting assured Of our continued protection, which ho 0 nd the public ot6 large well know is the only safe guard that stands between himself and his dynasty being driven lock, stock and barrel into the sea by the Omani, or even his own subjects, he will leewe a nominal representative at Muscat, without power, to serve os a channel of communication. 22. In case of emergency, and in order to be still further independent of us, the Sultan is determined on the purchase of an wholly useless 'ship H which is earmarked to carry him in State to Ohofar. 23. Under our protection hie creature Dulichond will continue to grind the poor and weak to ensure sufficient revenue and it is he that will virtually be the Ruler in Muscat territory, a position to which he has already very nearly attained. 24• If and when trouble threatens, an appeal for assistance will assuredly be mode to the British Government and in the event of its refusal, His Highness will be at liberty to advertise that his friends the ^British hove 'let him down'* • 25* It would therefore seem desirable before the situation attains these proportions to issue Hia Highness with a very definite warning and demand the dismissal from otote service of R.S* Dulichmd, who should under Wo circumstances be permitted to reside in any capacity within Muscat limits. The same interdict might be mode applicable to i,hc H.S 1 a relations and importations and also to Ismail fiffandi* Until the oulton has shown a complete change of his present attitude I consider that no idea should be entertained of affording him any further financial or other assistance, except on terms dictated by Government. By firm action now I consider thot His Highness moy he brought to realise the relative importance of his position in the world and that much subsequent trouble will be eliminated.INDIA OFFICE RECORDS (D S iT-t j MICROFILM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000a3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/388</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000a3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/388</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 11/36 Political Situation at Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-09-06T22:16:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (7 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 9; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-7; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of a letter concerning the political situation in Muscat that was sent to the Political Residency in Bushire by Major Claude Edward Bremner, Britain's Political Agent and Consul in Muscat.The letter focuses on the relationship between British authorities and the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Said bin Taimur [Sa‘id bin Taymur], and includes a discussion of the Sultan's financial arrangements, political intentions and attitude towards Britain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000a3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>