<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024174347.0x000022_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T01:13:09.294Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024174347.0x000022_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/38, ff 73v-74</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024174347.0x000022</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/38, ff 73v-74</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No. 841 of 1866 from Charles Gonne, Secretary to Government, Political Department, Bombay Castle to Lieutenant-Colonel Lewis Pelly, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1866/1866</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-30T01:17:49</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Letter forwarding a telegram from the Commissioner in Sind regarding adopting precautionary measures at Gwadar and asking Pelly for his thoughts on the matter. Pelly's response can be found on folio 53.Enclosed telegram from the Commissioner in Sind, Kurrachee [Karachi] to the Chief Secretary of Government, Bombay forwarding a telegram from the Assistant Political Agent at Gwadar reporting on the popular feeling in Gwadar that matters in Maskat [Muscat] may impact on them, his concerns over the agent to Sayed Soulem [Salim II bin Thuwaini] at Gwadar and how to handle matters as he is not aware what the Government's policy is towards Soulem. The telegram goes on to request either a War steamer to provide protection for Gwadar or to be given answers to his points outlined above in order to know how to respond to and deal with Maskat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024174347.0x000022#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>