<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00031b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T19:33:03.521Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">British Raeidancy and Consulate-General. Bushire, 31st Llarch 191^. Th*# politioal Agent, t . h r a i n. MEMORANDUM. Reference previous correspondence regarding the snug^lin^ of tea, sugar and 6ther goods from Bahrain to Tangistan for the use or the hostile tribesmen, and measures to checlc same. It has occurred to me that the Shaikh might consent to make the owners or Nakhudas of boats or shippers of cargo deposit a cash security, exceeding the amount of duty leviable in Persia on the goods carried, to ensure that the vessel proceeds first to Bus, ird or Lingeh. This cash security would be returned to the said owner or Nakhuda on his producing a certificate from this Residency or the Bushire Customs (or from Residency Agent or Director of Customs at Lingeh) that the fepat- with the same quantity of goods on board has called at Bushire or Lingeh first. The Persian Customs Directors at the petty ports are not to be trusted. I think this wil.l be a good check if the Shaikh will adopt it: Nakhudas belonging to hostile villages or those carrying cargo to hostile places will not care to call at Bushire, and boats belonging to friendly places will not have to go much out of their way to come here, or go to Lingeh if they are bound for the shibkuh ports. In the jvent of a Nakhuda obtaining a clecranee from Bahrain to leave for Bushire and not proceeding there the Shaikh could confiscate the security: this miprht be an induce- ment to him to start the arrangement. If the shaikh agrees, all that he would have to do would be to issue a notice that no boats should leave^ Bahrain .without obtaining a clearance and permit to leave before starting; that 'lakhudas must declare where they intend to discharge • their cargo, and if they are going t'o the Persian side they must prbc eIprocaed in the first instance to Bushire, Lingeh or B.sw^ar Abbas, that they must deposit a security equal to twice the duty leviable in Persia on the goods carried, and this security will be returned on their (or their agents).producing the original clearances signed by the Customs Director at the Fort named or by the British representative at Bushire, Lin^eh and Bandar Abbas. % Clearances could be made out on a form similar to the one annexed which is on the lines of a Basrah form, and there would be no objection to a small fee, of Re.l/- say, such as is levied by all Customs Department, being charged for the clearance paper. If the suggestion is approved I could get some forms printed here for the Shaikh. You may have seen from papers brought by dhows from Basrah that a similar plan has been adoptecyther^ to prevent dhows from taking supplies to places where they can reach the enemy, or from proceeding to blockaded paKixx coasts. The only dif ference is that the Basrah authotities make the owner or shipper or Nakhuda deposit a cash security equal to the whole value of the cargo. This seems rather severe and perhaps the shaikh would not be able to enforce such a measure. Major, Deputy Political Resident,Persian Gul IcU ^ fa _ , IIit - ' l»H« »■'*■ ^ m yte--Ti • T -, s Clearance for sailing craft leaving Bahrain. ulji I Name rf Craft Rig- No .of masts. Flag. TTaine of ovmer. Name of Kakhu Nature and Destination Amount of &gt;•) . da. amounf of deposit. cargo• r • J^U a. O \ The ahove described vessel is leaving this day for , where this clearance should be' produced for favour of countersignature by the British Representative or the Director of Customs at that place as proof of completion of voyage. - JLJ U l&amp;'uhJ^JiZ-'^ I Bahrain, Jlli the of 1916. «• ' tf PNo. ^ To * ^ BAHRAIN. The 18th April 1916, The Deputy Political Realdent, BUSTTI^K. Memorandum, Your memorandum No.621 of ^lat March /3rd April 1916 su^eatin^; deposit of cash security by owners or Makhuda of boats leaving Bahrain to ensure that the boat proceeds first to Bushlre or Lin/rah. His E!xcellency 'haikh Isa has agreed to adopt these pronosals and is now issuing the neceanary orders to his officials. He will be obliged if you will kinilv send him a supply of clearance forms. ''a Jor, Political A^ent, Bahrain./k\ After ComplinentB, With reference to T.E. pronlse to issue a notice that no boata shoulrl leave Bahrain without obtaining a clearance and permit to leave before starting; that Nakhudas must declare where they intend to discharge their cargo, and if they are going to the Persian side they must proceed in the first instance to Bushire, Lingah or Bunder Abbas, that they must deposit a security equal to twice the duty leviable in Persia on the goods carried, and this security will be returned on their (or their agents) producing the » original clearance signed by the Customs Director at the port named or by the British Representative at Bushire, Lingah and Bunder Abbas Your Excellency's request^that exception should be made for boats clearing to Charak, Magam, Kalat, Cherub, ShiwSfh, Naband, Tah#rt and Rangoon,^that boats proceeding to these ports with clearance papers should be signed by your friendly Arab - Persian rulers of these ports in the absence of Ww- Oustoms Directors / is allowed tentatively. I am sending Y.E. 20 forms of clearance for immediate use. More forms will be sent to you oj •eceipt from Bushire. I hope your Excellency will issue the promised notice* wiL^tout further delay. /No. BAHRMN. The 13th Hay 1916. To The Deputy Political Resident, BU3HIRR. Mernorandum, -&gt; With reference to this office No.251 of 18th April \ 1916 rerrardin^ depooit of caoh oecurity by Tfathudas of boat a leaving Bahrain to ensvre that the hoat proceeds firat to Buahire, Linrah or Bundor Abhas, rhalkh lea hao not irauod the notice aa yet firatly heoauae he vlahen to Imov whether his suggestion to exempt hoats goinr to the follovinr friendly ports has been accepted or not and secondly because he is awaiting the aupply of forms. Names of Rulers. (1) Shaikh Saleh Charaki (2) Shaikh Ibrahim bin Ahdulla al Hammad (3) Shaikh Abdullah al Abaidli (4) Shaikh Vadhkoor bin Hassan bin Madhkoor (Ruler of Oanband) (5) Shaikh Muhammad bin Ahmad Khalfan (fl) Shaikh Khatim bin Jubarah Ports. Charak Mapram 5: Kalat Chiruh Shiwuh Naband Tahirl (7) Shaikh Saif bin Shaikh Ibrahim bin Madhkoor# Kangoon I enclose a copy of letter No.295 of date to Shaikh Xaa in which I said his request is allowed tentatively and I wan ted to add 'subject to the approval of the DeDUty Political Resident r but this has not been done aa I think he would further delay issuing the notice till he hoars whether you approve it or not. I also enclose copy of a note dated 17th April 1916. As several boats from Amari and Tjawar are coming manned with suspected Nakhudas who could have been dealt with if Shaikh Isa published the notice at once. I may be informed whether there anv objection to agree with Shaikh Isa's request. Head Clerk,f ^ BAWHAIK. The 17th May 1916. V /jUcJ I am pivln^ you the purport of the Inatruotiono n&gt;^loh aro to be strictly obaorved rorardinj? boato loavlnrr for the Persian porta. (1) No boata ahould leave Bahrain without obtaining a olearanoe and permit to leave before Htartlng* (2) The Nakhudaa muat declare where thev Intend to diaoharge tholr oarp:o, and if thev are poinpr to the Peralan aide tl^ey nmnt proceed in the first instance to nuahlre, Linpah or Fundor Abbas* (3) The owners or -Talhudari of boats or shlpnera of carfro must flepoait a security equal to frrioe the duty levi able in Peraia on the ^ooda carried, and thia aeourity will be returned on their (olTtheir amenta) producing tho orlf?l- nal clearance signed by the Cuatoms Director at the port named or by the British representative at Bushire, Linoiah and Hunder Abbas. In the event of a nakhuda obtaining clearance frora Bahrain to leave for Hushire, Lln^rah or Bunder Abbas and not pro ceeding there the GhaiVh could confiscate the security. A fee of Re.l/- may he charge for clearance paner. Boats leaving for the following ports may be allowed to go direct aa a temnorarv measure provided the naV^udas are subjects of those Shaikhs. The clearfince paners are allowed to be signed by the rulers of those places. Names of rulers# Port. (1) Shaikh Saleh Charaki Oharak (2) ' Ibrahim bin Abdulla al Hamad Maqam &amp; Kalat (3) * Abdullah al Abaidll Chiruh (4) Madhkoor bin Hassan bin Madhkoor (Ruler of Ganband) Shiwuhyr NO. 3X1 Of POLITICAL AOENOY. BAHRAIN, the 29th May 1916. To The Director of Customs, BAHRATH, Dear Sir, I am sending herewith one hundred forms of clearance for boats. Yours faitJ^fully, Head Clerk, Political Aprencv, BATTRAIW. (In charge current duties)No, p/ of 1916. British Residency and Consul ate -G -eneral , Bushire , 27th May 1916 . To The Head Clerk, Bahrein. Memorandum. - Your Memorandum No. 297 dated IJ^h May 1^16. I enclose a letter to Shaikh Isa (together with translation) which explains wby it is difficult to agree to the exemptions which he has suggested. I hope he will agree to enforce the prohibition, if it leads to prohibition of export to Bahrein by the Shaikhs of the Persian Coast please let me know at once MaJ or, Deputy Political Resident Persian Gulf.1 r i ' 1 I PI £ m £r:: NO. 2L&gt;1 of 1916 British Residency and Consulate-General, Busliire , 24th. May 1916, To His Excellency Shaikh Isa bin Ali A1 Khalifah C.S.I., Chief of Bahrein . After Compliments, I have been informed of your Excellency's request that goods for certain Shaikhs of Shibkuh and Banadir i Thalatheh ports on the Persian Coast should be exempted from the decree, which it has been agreed that Your Excel- lency will issue, prohibiting as an emergant and temporary war measure the direct export of any goods at all to ports on the Persian Coast other than Bander Abbas, Lingeh and Bushire, and ordering boats with cargo for any other Per sian ports to proceed first to one of the three principal ports named, I am well aware of the relations which you and mem bers of your family have with certain of the Shaikhs whom- you have named to the Political Agency at Bahrein, and also of the frequent shipments of goods between some of those ports and Bahrein. I should have liked to accept your suggestion that the ports of these shaikhs should be exempted from the prohibition but I regret I cannot do so for the following reasons. Your Excellency on your part is aware that the autho rities of the High G-overnment have for some months past had good reason for having the trafiic to and from the small ports, on both side of the G-ulf strictly supervised, and regulated, in order to prevent supplies reaching places and persons hostilely inclined to the British Govern ment. Boats sailing from Bushire to the ports in lower Dashti or of the Banadir i Thalatheh, for instance, have only been permitted to take small quantities of certain goods under passes^ this is due to the hostility of some of the Dashti sections who Joined on the. attack on Bushire- If therefore the import of goods from Bahrein is allowed 4'S,allowed freely to such ports as Kangun T^hiri and Naband for instanoe, the utility of the strict control from Bushire is nullified. While i have no objection against the Shaikhs of those ports, I would still re quest you as a temporary measure to c^use vessels sail ing thither from Bahrein to proce; d first to Bushire, or Lingah for two months at least, when I hope a normal state of affairs will have been restored, and the Per sian malcontents and rebels inland entirely subdued by their Q-overnment &lt;■ As regards the ports of Chiru, Shiu and Asalu, the results of the enquiries made by the British authorities and His Excellency Darya Begi showjbhat Shaikh Abdullah of Chiru, Shaikh Mazkur of Qaobandi and Ali Akbar Khan of Qiladar, who control those ports, are all guilty of having assisted the Tangistani murderers of Khan Bahadur Agha Badr, and facilitated their escape through their territories, despite the orders of His Excellency Darya Begi . To keep such miscreants is as I am sure you will agree a dastard ly act which merits the reprobation of all God-fearing and just men. - These chiefs must be punished for their hostility, and evil action, and meanwhile I request that Your Ex- cellency will have nothing to do with them, and strictly forbid all your subjects not to trade with the inhabitants of those ports and districts, and not permit men from those places to land in Bahrein- If vessels were allowed by you to a take goods to Naband, and Tahiri , it is probable that the same vessels would call at Chiru, Asalu and Shiu; and this is an addi tional reason wby it would be preferable for Your Excellen cy to issue your decree, as at first arranged, for all vessels , no matter what port on the Persian coast they desire to visit to proceed first to Bushire, or Lingah, I shall be glad to hear when Your Excellency has issued the decree in Bahrein ; I trust it will not be necessarynecessary to keep it going long , and that the Persian Ooveminent will soon be able to get the upper hand of itA unruly subjects- I do not think Your Excel ency need r fear that the prohibition will have much effect on the imports of cattle, sheep, wheat etc into Bahrein, because the trade pays the exporters from the Persian side far well for them readily to give it up. Sd/- A - P . Trevor, Major, Deputy Political Resident Persian Gulf,i No# ^ 3 BAHRAIN. The let June 1916. The Deputy Politloal Resident, BU3HIHE. MeTaoranduiii, I aoknowledire the receipt of your menoranduin No.901 datod 27th May 1916. I delivered your letter to His Exoellenoy Shaikh Isa and I enclose his rer^ly herewith. I also enclose a oopy of. notice issuei by Shaikh Isa dated 17th May 1916. Head Clerk, Political Agency, Bahrain. (In charge current duties)ft .1 &gt; No. of 1916. British Rasidency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 2nd September 1916# To Political Agent, Bahrain, Lasmorandum . Referenca your office memorandum No.^32 dated Ist June 1916, forwarding a copy of Shaikh Isa's notice imposing oertain res trictions on boats leaving Bahrain. I enclose herewith (u.f.s.) a letter to Shaikh Isa suggest ing that the restrictions may be modified to some extent. x'he Blockade has now baen removed from the Tangistan: O orts all and normally one would remove/restrictions, but as tho British Admiralty are still utilizing the Customs ship 'Muzaffar' and the armed launch 'Azarbaijan', thus leaving the Customs with no pre ventive service, it seems only fair that we should maintain certain rsstrictions to prevent whole sale smuggling, in the absence of the ,, garde3-cote^ ,, . Ma jor. Deputy Political Resident, Persian Gulf. t/f 4 ^ ^ ' ^BAHRAIN. The 20th Hepternbar lOlfi. The Deputy Political Resident, BUSHIRE. Momorandum, ith reference to your letter No•1492 dated 2nd instant, I have to state that several Tanpsiri boats call here without a passport or a Customs Clearing parser fron their norts. The nalrhudas of these boats state that they nave not been told that clearing paners are required to be' taken out when they leave their ports. la t^is correct? If not could you nlease inform me what action I should take against such nakhudas. Captain, Offg. Political Aprent,I?AT T RATN•No.c/ /f3 Y of 191«. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bnshire, 30th Septenber, 1P1«. Officiating Political Aront, Bahrain. snorandunu Reference your Venorandua No.^27 dated 20th instant, no passport or Gustons clearing paper is required fron Nakhudas of Tangisiri boats on their original outward jonrney fron Tanj»-is- tan ports for Bahrain; only when they loave Bahrain on their re# turn Journey will they require to mice the declaration and de posit nr »ntio ed in the last para of thr enclosure in ny No.1492 dated 2nd instant. • ajor. h- L I ii i n 11 y Pi i I m 11 11 Resident in the Persian C-ulf.H.B.M's Political Agent Bahrain. C C C No 11 of 1917« CUJTOM HOUJE Bahrain dated the 3rd July 1917• C. Craft Muja Hil I have the honour to inform you that the Nakhudha Jar ad Mater of the ahove mentioned C.Craft arrived here yesterday with the cargo enumerated as under, shipped originally from Lama 'bound for Busrah, states that owing to the unfavourable Weather on the way to Bus rah he was compelled to turn his 'boat at this side. He was asked for the relative Manifest to which he says had 'been taken 'by the Officials on the Way &amp; he had 'been given some documentry evedince instead &gt; in the Italian Characters which I am sending herewith for your persual. He bas-jsold^out of the cargo, 2 'bags Alooch ( Incense) &amp; ome/wood herei. I ohall now te glad to have your ind tructiono in the matter, Details of the Car^o Chandled. I have the honour to 'be Jir Your obedient servant %Vy/^X&gt;c^ rector Custom House.Bahrain. V/ tr~lC 'Political Aponcy, \ : ■ &gt;#sJi No.575 Bahrain, the Srcl July l 0 ! 0 . . To, The Director of Ouatoraa, Bahrain. Dear Sir, , With reference ^o your letter 'To.ll of July 3rd, 1917, I thinlr tbe naVrhuda 3alih Samantar ^ay be allov/od to proceed. Hia Italian naners are a clearance certifi cate - permlBaion to fly the Italian mercantile fla.tr and a list of the crew. \ ;)uty ahould of oouree he ta^en An the tMnrs sold here* He should be remitted to land hid ohandala if necessary for'the repair of his hoat -.ind in that can 9 ro allowed to take them on to Basrah without hein^r c^arrer! . duty. ♦ • / Youra faithfully. i I fJ: f-' Captain, Political Acrent,'Pahrain. 'i - U i..V : C H No 9 of 1917. CUJTOM HOUJE. Bahi'ain dated the 27th June 1917 To, H.B.M'o Political Agent Bahrain • Jir, I have the honour to let you know for your information that Nakhudha Haji Bin Mahomed of Jali 'boat B,U.219 was intend leaving the Harbour with under mentioned Cargo 'bound for Bushi -re( 30 far he says)with out Uujtoia clearance Pado. 5 'bags Turmeric. 3 ca^eci Cajjia. 4 Bdles Gunny Bags, 1 bdle Mats, • 1 M Jail cloth. 1 Bag Pice. The 'boat in tjuestion wacs scearched of &amp; found 4 'bags Tea atout £ monds in weight in the comer of the Boat^ which he quite denies to Ije awaie of them. I have however detained the Boat &amp; shall be glad to have your instructions in the Matter. I have the honour to 'be oir, Your most obedient servant H.G. Director -i — € H No 10 of 1917. C U J T 0 M H 0 U o E . Bahrain dated the 29th June 1917. To, H VB.M's Political Agent 4 Bahrain. Jir f I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter No 547 of 28 th init &amp; in reply thereto 'beg to explain in connection with the Boat No attemping to leave the Harbour with out C. PSo3, as followj. That on the 27th indt the man of Abddol Kaaim Jhirazi inform -ed Uo of hid shipping dome bdlej Jkiru 'by the daid 'boat. The udual customary of the Custom id thi^ that the goodj dhould in no caje 'be put in the Boat unlejj the dame id examine*/'by the Cudtom Officiald. like wide thede Jkind w^ere lying the Jiore . Our man after exaatlned the cargo of the daid Jhipper adked him to take the C.Padd from the C 1 -idtom. He then went on the Boat which wad anchored in the water near H.E. Jakh'd Jtandard &amp; dav/ the excedd Cargo named in my letter no 9 of 27th indt. He adked the Nakhudha whether ohe cargo had 'been examined 'by the Oudtom &amp; whether the C.Pa^d had already Jbeen granted to He dtated that he know nothing of the Cargo and made dome doubt -ful dpeech . On thid our man wad doubted and ieach^the whole Boat and found thede 4 'bagd STea hidden in one of the Corner &amp; ^he information 'oo Lhid effect had been given to you. Ad dedired , I give you 'below the lidt of the cargo with their redpective value; 5 oagd Turmeric 3 caded Caddia 4 Ddled G. Bagd 1 'bdle Matd 1 w dail Cloth Brf 176-0-0. \ ' 180-0-0 '' Y'l 80-0-0. tfyf - 10-0-0. ** 50-0-0 ;4 H Tea M 100-0-0. After landing the cargo on the dhore we have found 17 'bags Butian more, which were lying oelow the ahove mentioned goods the value of which id 170-0-0,. I have , aj per your instructioni, kept the goodj together with the Rudder in my custody and sending the hagd Tea herewith^ I have the honour to be Jir, Your moot obedient ^ervant ^'Director Cudtom 'BaJirain. /. 0) a; b) tu fi*- ^ L^ 0 ! hv-^ [sM^yy C*S y ~-'NO.560.. POLITICAL AGENCY. Bahrain, the SOth June 19 17, To The Director Of Custoras, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No. 30 of June 29th, 39 17, the nakhuda has 'been fined R!.300/- which please recover from him before permitting him to proceed and send to me for transmission to His Excellency Shaikh t lBa. The nakhuda or owners of the goods mentioned in your letter should pay the / usual security. I have confiscated the tea. , &lt; - , Yours faithfully. Captain, ^Political Agent, Bahrain.\ Bahrain 2nd July 1917. Dear Mr D* Codta The Naichudha Haji tin Mahoraed of Boat No 219,dta'be that owing to hid poorest condition he id quite unable to pay the amount of the fine Rd 300/-.&amp; re^uedt fruther that the owner of the Boat Mr^Abdool Nabi Kazrani may Le adked for the darae. Will you pleade therefore let me know • ad to how thio matter id to he treated now. H.Cr. Yours Jincerely /■ r flUuO ' — w / . $ r /.Ho. 616* POLITICAL AOEKCY. Bahrain, the 23th July 19 17« To The Director of Cuetoes, BAHRAIN Dear Sir, v ith reference to your No. C.H. 10 of June 29th, 19 17, I am sending herewith P^.SOO/- on account of fine levied from nakhuda Ha ;J.Ji 'bin Muhammad for shipping tea and goods without * getting a Customs permit. ^ » Ynrs faithfully, /f Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain. r ♦ '•T' r-i-1' 1C G No 14 of 1917. CUJTOM HOUJE Sahrain dated the 13t(h July 1917 • To, Political Agent Bahrain. f' ff. / .f 3ir, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter no 616 of even date sending therewith the sum of IU 300/- ±or u which I thank you. I have the honour to 'be Jir, Your obedient servant Director Custoia^ouse. Bahrain. H.G.^r, Memorandum. HO.A.B. &lt;^'&lt;0 of 1917. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 4th August 1917. ... ^ ^ tr*-/ b ^ The political Agent, - Bahrain. Your Memo. No.561 dated 30th June 1917 to the address of His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Bushire. The four bags of tea realized Krans E36 which at 235 equal xx Rs.100-6-9. Of this I have paid to the Treasury Rs .68/- on account of cost of service labels and the balance viz Rs.32-6-9 is being remitted to you by Monejf Order less annas 6, postal commission. Please acknowledge receipt. fL By order. —^ C^JE. Major, Jfirst Assistant Resident. 7 / : / ^ • &gt;&lt; ■ a MS ■ r Uy*.i$e/ -ymr ' . „ ^ il' ^No Jtfafy $ of 1917. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 29th July 1917. - I: VV yf ftU ' The Political Agent, Bahrain. MEI! ORANPUI.I. 1 enclose a copy of a letter dated the 15th instant from the Provincial Director of Custons at Bushire, with the copy of an enclosure in Persian from the'Mudir at Lawar on the Dashti coast. Khur Khan is a barren spot a little to the south of the estuary of the Mand river in Dashti, and Khalu Hussain is the chief at Burdakhun, some miles inland from Khur Khan across a desolate Mashileh. I should 'be glad if you will enquire into the Mudir's complaint (which is doubted by the Provincial Director) ^f an understanding between the Shaikh of Bahrain and Khalu Hussain permitting the export - without passes - of goods from Bahrain for Khur Khan: and I scskssi al-so draw your attention to the Director's observation^ that for some time past permits from the Customs of Bahrain for exportations to the Persian coast, . i under deposit of duty, have rarely reached him. You might let me know what you recommend: we wish of course to hamper smuggling by chiefs cia the Tangistan and Dashti . coasts more particularly. On the other hand we donH wish to take such strjngent measures as will react dm the supply of fresh moat, fruit and vegetables to Bahrain. Lieut-Colonel, Deputy Political Resident,Persian Gulf. PH PS. ■ -Ho. 867. P 0 L I I T'l C A L A G I i-C Y Bahrain, the 6th September 19 17. To The Deputy Political Resident, BUS H I R E. % MEMORANDUM. , A f : 1 In continuation of my Memorandum Ho. 835 of August 85th, 19 17, s I seni herewith a list of all shipments for Persia from Bahrain as far as is known to the Customs Director.' The passes have not been received back yet in the oases of those items ' r marked with red 'x 1 . To save labour I have not kept an office copy of the list, but can trace any item by the date and name from the Customs books. The Director of Customs says that he has once or twice been asked by Shaikh 'Isa to issue a pass without taking a deposit for Khalu Husain who, it appears, gives hawks to the Shaikh and his family. I have arranged with him to try to catch Khalu Husain returning hero without bringing the passes countersigned by the Persian Director of Customs, i ^ushlre. Possibly the above gave rise to the report of an arrangement between the Shaikh and w Khalu Husain, but I do not think that there is one. It is more . likely that he is a smuggler, pure and simple, but cunning enough to be friends with the local authorities here. Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain.■k • ;f Ko.t //£rZ-/ . s — // Chief Political Office. Basrah, the 20th August 1917, .'I'G ' .y ■ . The Political Agent, Bahrein. Itemora ndum • Your me&amp;o 719, August 6th. Collector of Customs, Basrah, remarks in connection therewith. 'If it is intended that the vessel's papers / shall take the form of a manifest of the goods actually shipped it is probable that considerable facilities can be giyen, it is usually difficult to get a disinterested persons statement of the complete contents of Native Craft from many of- the Gulf ports.' Captain, Deputy Chief Political Officer. nu ^ ' I# /U -a /£No; CCC 19 of 1917, ; C U o T 0 M HOUJE Bahrain, dated 5oh Octo'ber 1917• To H.B.M'd political Agent Bahrain, iir, Aj perjonally dejired I 'beg to encloje herewith two rormj of clearance certillcatea. CI: certificate like No; 196 U given for the 'boats carrying cargo to the Perjian ports leaving wit 1 '' the Custonio Bdh •y rain deposits retumaMe to the nakhudas on their producing these certificates countersigned 'by the Provincial Director oi oustoms Bushire. CI: certificate like No: Al is given for boats coiry ing cargo to Busra when no deposit is taken; hence no necessity foi nakhudas to either get the certificates countersigned or to return them to the Customs Bahrain. Further I beg to state that Nakhuda Haji Yousul of the C .crift • jultani • wishes to sail for Karachi ; kidly instruct whether he should Ve permitted to go. Only 202 bags Bice has been landed ex; the above craft. I oeg to remain, Sir, your most obedient .jervant Dire cto^-^^ Custom House Bahrain. P. J.Kindly return the Certificate No: 196 when done with, /1143. POLITICAL AG N C Y. Baiirain, the 9th Novenber 1117. To The Deputy Chief Political Officer, BASRAH. MEMORANDUM. Your emorandum Wo. 1152 1/ of August 26th, 19 17. 0/1. All nakhudas of sailing craft who wish to can get a manifest in the attached form from the Bahrain Customs Department fit?Cc^tin# ' wiiloh ia comparatively .odiaTslo^ I propose to ipsue a notice ■ , advising the public to take advantage of this and saying that, provided the nakhudas arrive with goods ar- detailed in the manifest, the Basrah Customs Department will be able to afford considerable facilities for (jaick clearance. As soon as people find t ey benefit, they will, I think, adopt the plan. Before issuing the notice I write to say that many boats sell part of the cargo at ports en route if prices happen to be good; would the Customs Department accept the manifest if amounts sold en route were certified for on the back of the manifest by the Qatif or Kuwait Customs or, in case of a smaller place, by the local Amir or Shaikh. Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain.h k-xx''.--- • C 0/27 To II ' Cuctom House Bahrein dated 29th Dec, 1917 Political Agent Bahrein. W lr ' I heg to acknowledge the receipt of your memorandum No;; 1344 of yesterday's date and sending there with ^ISo/- for which I thank you. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your obedient servant Customs Bahrein. I ft n j*'Z</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00031b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/60</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00031b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/60</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File V/11 Clearance Papers for Sailing Craft Leaving Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1917</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-02-20T00:01:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">per</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (76 folios)</extent><extent>This file is arranged approximately in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation system starts at the front cover and continues through to the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled and may be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between the British Political Agent at Bahrain; the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire; ‘Abd al-Ḥusayn, the interpreter of the British Political Agency at Bahrain; Jāsim al-Chirāwī; Shaikh ‘Īsá bin ‘Alī Āl Khalīfah, ruler of Bahrain; and Seth Rao Sahib Tirathdas Maharaj, Director of Customs at Bahrain. These papers concern the issuing of clearance certificates in the context of the Tangistan blockade in 1916 which prohibited boats leaving Bahrain without obtaining permission from the Political Agent and other miscellaneous issues regarding shipping and smuggling.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Tangestān</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Economic sanctions</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00031b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>