<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000289_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:00:35.578Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">FUTURE ADMINISTRATION OF MESOPOTAMIA. IC xtuact kuom L oud C hslmsfoud's P rivate L etter oe the IS tii O ctober 1916. In paragraph L'i of your letter of 13th September you ask me for my views with regard to the future administration of Mesopotamia. This question, as you know, was considered by Hardiuge as long ago as February 1915, and you probably have in the India Otlice a record of his views along with those of Ilirtzel and Crewe. I have very carefully considered these memoranda, but I think perhaps it would be more convenient if I were to summarise the position, as 1 see it, in my own words. You say in your letter '1 think you must feel that the Government of India already have sufficient responsibility.' I entirely agree. We have even in the cognate matter of Persia expressed ourselves strongly against increasing our indirect responsibilities ; but I doubt, as in the case of Persia, whether circumstances will not be too strong for us, and whether willy-nilly we shall not be forced to take on the additional responsibility. The question we have to face is, is it practicable to dissociate India from the administration of Mesopotamia • (ft) Mesopotamia will for some time to come require a garrison. The troops lor this service will, in all probability, be drawn from India and, in the event of any emergency, the reinforcements will almost certainly have to come from her. And if India is to be called upon lor military forces for the needs of Mesopotamia, surely the corollary is that India must have a voice in the political affairs of Mesopotamia. She could hardly be asked to hold her forces at the disposal ol' an Administration over which she had no control. (h) I turn next to India's political position in the Persian Gulf; and though the situation there will be vitally altered by the elimination of the Baghdad Railway menace and the disappearance of Turkey, this much, 1 think, is certain. Someone will have to control the Gulf; control could scarcely be vested in a new Administration struggling to find its feet, and a dual control, assuming an independent Basrah Administration, is obviously to be deprecated. The control of the Gulf must then remain with India, and, if friction is to be avoided, it seems to me inevitable that India, along with the control of the Gulf, must control Pasrah. . (c) I pass by the arguments in favour of such a policy based on commercial and religious grounds, and on India's present relations with the Chiefs situated in the Gulf region. These seem to me purely subsidiary to the governing factors mentioned in sub paragraphs (a) and (6). 1 cordially agree with you in disliking the position, but the logic of circumstances seems to be too strong for us. There remains to be considered the form of administration. I do not altogether agree with your view that the problems and people of Mesopotamia are too dissimilar from those of India to make direct Indian administration advisable. India has a very varied assortment of races, and a Government that already administers efliciently Burmans and Pathans, Bengalis and Baluchis, Moplahs and Marwaris, can hardly be written down, even by Mark Sykes—for 1 know this to be his theory—as incapable of ruling the Arab. The Government of India, moreover, is not rigid in its system of administration, as witness, for example, the differences between the R 338 20 117 A- : .7,-. '■ administration of the Shan States, the Abors, the North-\\ est i^rontiei Province, Baluchistan and the Aden Hinterland. But though j leel con- strained to protest against your view that direct Indian administration is per tc inadvisable, I am not prepared to advise that India should m fact directly administer Mesopotamia. I should prefer an administration that was in large measure independent subject only to control by India as regards its external relations and such matters as might involve India in military operations. 1 am not very familiar with the administration of the Soudan, and unfortunately I speak without the book, as I have no authorities by me to which I can refer, but my impression of its administration is that of a Government practically autonomous, but associated with and controlled as to its main lines of policy by, Egypt. I contemplate some such administration for Mesopotamia and we have the machinery for it more or less to hand. 1 Enclosure A. | onc l OS e a tabular statement 1 from which it can be seen that Sir \\ Cox has a great number of oflicers already working under him, all of whom will thus qualify themselves for^ service in this region. Hardinge was, I understand, inclined to curtail Cox s demands for men on the ground that he was overstaffed. I would differ from Hardiuge's policy in this matter, because I regard it as all important, in view of the future, to train on men to be our luture administrators. hey can no be improvised, and if, as we believe. Great Britain will, at the end of the war, take over the Basrah Vilayet and perhaps a more extended region, it is •essential that we should have men ready to hand for this purpose. 1 here would be no idea of flooding ^Mesopotamia with Indian subordinates. We should fill the lower posts, as far as possible, with local men. 1 am afraid this is a somewhat rough note, but, if you wish, will have it elaborated and drafted as a despatch. 1 hope, however, that it is a sufficiently clear reply to your question.3 J. — M kmokandv on tiik Future Administration of Mesopotamia, prepared at Mr. Chamberlain's Request, rv Sir T. \V. Holderness. I am in general agreement with Sir Arthur Hirtzol. If the end of the war should see His Majesty's (Jovernnient in possession of a considerable territory in Southern Mesopotamia and under agreements with an Arab State or Confederacy of Arab States importing political obligations and creating a sphere of economic interest, some other Agency than the Governor-General of India in (buneil should, 1 venture to think, be constituted for dealing with these new responsibilities. The loose administrative control which the Viceroy suggests seems to me impracticable for reasons which will be hereafter given. The supposition is that the Basra vilayet will become British territory and that some form of British protectorate will be established over the Bagdad province. If the Indian Government is to be responsible for governing the British Province and for superintending the political allairs of the protectorate, it will be necessary to include the former in the legal definition of ' British India,' and the latter probably in that of ' India.' For unless this is done, the British Province of Basra could not lawfully be governed by His Majesty through the Governor-General of India or through some governor or other officer subordinate to him. But if Basra is included in British India, a number of consequences will occur with which the Viceroy ^joes not reckon and which evidently he is anxious to avoid. The rarliamentary Acts defining and regulating tiie Government of India will become applicable to the new province, aiid to the protected territory ' under the suzerainty of His Majesty exercised through the Governor-General of India.' Full responsibility for every act of internal and external administration will rest on the Governor-General in Council, and, subject to any arrangement as to sharing expenditure that may be made with His Majesty's Government, the revenues of India will be liable for the revenue and capital requirements of the territory. There is nothing inherently impossible or absurd in this solution of the problem. A similar problem arose in connection with our successive annexations in the Burmese peninsula and was solved in this way. But the circumstances making for the addition of Burma to the Indian Empire were much stronger than circumstances in the present case, and the Viceroy himsell does not contemplate such a solution. He is evidently averse from a formal extension of the boundaries of the Indian Empire, such as would embrace a large region in Mesopotamia and weight the Government of India with additional and unfamiliar responsibilities. But is there any alternative method possible whereby the Government of India can exercise control to the extent and within the limits suggested by the \ iceroy ? ('onsider w T hat this implies. Someone and some department will have to be responsible and accountable to Parliament for the policy and the acts of the local authorities of the new territories. If the Governor- General in Council is to be in any way responsible, his responsibility could not stop short at external relations. For internal administration may and does affect external relations, and certainly affects the ability of the administered province to meet the expenditure which its foreign policy occasions. I he responsibility of the Indian Government would therefore be almost as groat as it would be if the new territory were formally incorporated in India, and it would be very inconvenient, if not impossible, to hold the Governor-General and his Council responsible for the affairs of a country which is not within their legally defined orbit of government. On the other hand, i! no lesponsibility is to attach to the Government of India, their part would be confined to that of an irresponsible adviser to the Foreign Office, as is now tin 1 case with regard to Persian affairs. They would provide troops on the usual terms as and when recfuested, within the limits of their abilitv. 1 he} would similarly lend the services ol civil officers, and would in other ways assist the new administration. They would advise on all questions on which their advice was sought. But they could hardly undertake duties involving supervision. I his would mean sharing responsibility with the Foreign Office, and would bring us back to the difficulty of holding the s a.'?8 x 2Indian Gov e mm en t responsible for matters beyond their defined sphere of duty. Jt would therefore seem to follow that the logic of circumstances, so far from compelling the Government of India to undertake a measure of control, falling short of direct government, over the territories to be acquired in Mesopotamia, points in the opposite direction. If the Indian Government are to be implicated in the administration of these territories, they must be legally seized of them. To this the objections, as Lord* Chelmsford recognises, are very serious. Jt has often been represented that the inclusion of Aden in British India is bad both for Aden and for India,, as it burdens the Indian Government with problems with which they are unfamiliar, and places them in the dilemma of either sacriticing Aden affairs to those of India or diverting the revenues of India to meet the needs of this little corner of Arabia. The objection would be infinitely greater to the inclusion in India of a Mesopotamian province and a Mesopotamian pro tectorate. Great things would be expected of the Indian Government by the civilised world, which for years has been fed on wonderful accounts of the potential riches of this wasted land. If they lived up to these expecta tions they would have to provide capital on a scale which might seriously impede their ability to meet the urgent wants of India. They would have to create an administrative machine out of unfamiliar material and might be impelled to transport wholesale the institutions of an Indian province to a region where much simpler conditions prevail. They would have a new political frontier and new diplomatic, military, and strategical problem#. Whether they made a success of the enterprise or not, it would make enormous demands on their attention, especially on the attention of their Foreign and Political Department. This Department has the Viceroy for its head. It is safe to say that for many years to come the first pre occupation of successive Viceroys would be the affairs of this new dominion. This would not be good for the Viceroy nor for India. The Viceroy of India is probably the hardest-worked man in the world y and India, as it exists at present, is the most onerous and difficult charge in the British Empire. These considerations were no doubt present in the Viceroy's mind when he put aside the idea of a direct Indian administration in Mesopotamia. They point, it is submitted, to the complete detachment from India of the new Dependency which is to be carved out of the Ottoman Empire in that region. T. W. H. 9th January 1017. II .— Notks by Sill A. Ill rtzel. • It is assumed that if Mesopotamia is not to be administered by India, a new dependency will be created which will include the whole of Arabia, Egypt, and the Soudan—a unilingnal and unicultural area, from Solium to the Turco-Persian frontier. If this is not to be done, the argument for Indian administration will be much stronger, from the military as well as the civil point of view. Taking the Viceroy s three points (a), (6), and (c) separately : — 1 have discussed with Sir E. Barrow point (a), and he agrees with me that it does not really carry us very far. It has never been argued that India should control China because she has four or five battalions stationed there, or Egypt because, in the event of serious trouble, she would probably be drawn upon for reinforcements. She would not in a strict sense hold her forces at the disposal of Mesopotamia. She would merely raise x more regiments than she does at present, and Mesopotamia would pay the entire expense. In case of emergency, the Army in India would form a kind of strategic reserve, as it already does for the Empire generally. As regards (/;), it seems to me that, with the disappearance from Mesopotamia of Germany and Turkey and the recognition by Russia (which we must hope to get) of our predominant position in the Gnlf, the Gulf willbe eliminated from it.e region of 'high policy,' and its routrol will become merely a question o local police. We must beware of making a fetish of ,t. In future there should be little to do except keep the slave ami a nif, tralhc undei, and suppress attempts at piracy on the Arab coast The ess we interfere with the Sheikhs the better-we have been tending latelv 10 do no a httle too much. ()n the Persian side it will be many vears before any large problems come into existence. The questions of an inter- national nature that will require unity of control are questions like the nearl lishery to keep out interlopers—and lighting and buoyage. The Basin administration ought to he quite capable of dealing with these-indeed tho tl,el :'- ter a,,&lt;l ^.preaches to the Sha't-eh -\rab) Ttills automatically within its sphere. 11 Mesopotamia and Arabia are kept separate from India, the 'Political Resident, I ersian Gulf will cease to have much ; the affairs of the (hi I ports will be sufficiently attended to by the local consular officers and what His Majesty s Minister, Tehran, has sometimes regarded as a vcxiuio, is anomaly will have been got rid of. On this point f am in agree- dumiI with LieuteiiaiiM olouel 0 (Connor as regards the future rho separation of Mesopotamia and Arabia from India will leave the government oMndia free to attend to what is their natural sphere, Southern 1 ersia. honl ( helmslord js surely right in thinking that they will have \n illy-in liy to take on additional responsibility there. It is their natural sphere lor reasons that have long been recognised—historical, ethnological and geographical. 1 he years succeeding the war will almost certainly be yeais of great internal activity in India, and (Government will be fullv occupied in dealing with it. To assume additional responsibility both in I ersia and Mesopotamia will surely be impracticable. Lord Chelmsford recognising this, proposes that Indian responsibility for Mesopotamia should be reduced to a minimum. As to this, please see below. The more natural course, it appears to me, is to discard it altogether, and concentrate on u- 1 he considerations mentioned under this head are, as the Viceroy says, subsidiary ; and I do not think they are of great weight in themselves. It is not clear to me why Indian administration should necessarily be a commercial advantage. Krom the religious point of view there are the Oudh bequest and a certain amount of Shiah pilgrimage to be considered. As regards relations with the (Julf Sheikhs, undoubtedly continuity is desirable fut policy will presumably remain the same. 1 do not know how much India counts lor as a political conception to any except the bigger men (Mohan, merah, Koweit Bin Sand, Muscat); but, generally speaking, I should haAe said that it is the Political Agent and His Majesty's ships that count most, and that so long as they are there it matters little whether the power behind them is the (lovernment of India or some other. It is quite true that the (lovernment of India, as the Viceroy says rule a very mixed assortment of races; but none of them is quite analogous to the Arab, and the problems which they present are not quite analogous to that presented by the task of ruling not only Arabs but a section onlv of the Arab world I he task ol governing Bengalis (which, to judge from the condition ol Bengal during the last 10 or 12 years, is not easy) would surely be much more ditficult if their politico-religions centre of gravity lay in some region outside India and the greater part of the Bengali-speaking people were under (say) the Colonial Office. As for capability of ruling the Arab it is dilhcnlt to say a prwrt. But I believe that the Turks have generally been unwilling to have advisers and officials from India, them as if they u erc 1 ndtan*. I he Arabs are not likely to feel loss strongly 1 he (tovernment of India may not be rigid in its system of administration. ) '' ' 1 ^ nu id be, ol Indian Acts already applied to Mesopotamia {see pp of the Irak Code) indicates a tendency to rapid svstematisation which Ts not ol very good omen. And with it must come sooner rather than later- all the Indian mechanism. The Arabs may endure the white man-that remains to be seen -but it is surely doubtful if they will endure the Indian ; and it the Government ol Iudia administer Irak the Indian public will certainly look upon the country as their preserve.This seems to me to be one of tlio main objections to Indian admini stration and to be likely to make the kind of loose control which Lord Chelmsford conlemplates difficult to realise in practice. The Imperial Legislative Council will not allow it; and especially when it is a question of spend in if Indian money on Mesopotamia (which will be necessary for some years, and for which, by the way, legislation in Parliament will presumably be required), it may Ije anticipated that the control will be greatly stiHoned and the demand for interference in details of administration will be increased. , _ Moreover, as 1 said in my memorandum of .1 ith March IDlo, the 1 ower which detaches from Turkey regions with the history and the potentialities of Mesopotamia makes itself morally responsible to humanity and civilisation for their reclamation and development. Whatever system of administration we set up there we cannot, it is submitted, ]ca\e it to its own devices. A good deal might be said as to the actual difficulries in the way of administration from India. But as Lord Chelmsford has referred to personnel, 1 will mention one point in connection with that. Unless Mesopotamia is to be very closely administered by a large British staff (which is not desirable in itself), the Service will be too small to be self- contained. It will therefore presumably be recruited by loan from India. But this will mean that it will be exposed to all the vicissitudes of transfers, t^c., necessitated by purely departmental considerations in India. As, for example, now when Mr. Dobbs has begun to acquire a considerable amount of experience, and has done valuable work, as Revenue Commissioner at Basra, he is diverted, on return from leave, to Baluchistan. Moreover, the system on which the postings are arranged in the foreign and aohtKal Department is apparently that of encouraging interchangeability. That is, no doubt, very convenient departmentally; but it could not be good lor a country like Mesopotamia to be administered by a constant stream ol inexperienced officers (however able) from the whole vast region covered by the Foreign and Political Department. A. H. 30th December '910.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000289_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B246</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000289</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B246</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'FUTURE ADMINISTRATION OF MESOPOTAMIA'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1917/1917</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-16T13:42:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at folio 102 and terminates at folio 103, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between folios 6-153; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The item consists of:Extract from Lord Chelmsford (Frederick John Napier Thesiger)'s private letter of 18 October 1916: regarding the Government of India's existing responsibilities in relation to Mesopotamia; the likelihood of those responsibilities increasing; whether it might be possible to dissociate India from the administration of Mesopotamia; India's involvement in the Persian Gulf; India's likely future involvement with Basrah [Basra]; and Lord Chelmsford's vision for a largely independent administration in Mesopotamia, with India controlling external relations and military operations.Memoranda on the future administration of Mesopotamia, prepared at Mr Chamberlain's request, by Sir Thomas William Holderness, 9 January 1917: Regarding the potential need for a new agency, instead of the Government of India, to be responsible for territory in Southern Mesopotamia and agreements with Arab States that might be acquired at the outcome of the war (World War One); and the possible requirements and implications of administering such an area.Notes by Sir (Frederic) Arthur Hirtzel, 30 December 1916: regarding the need for a new dependency to be created, to include Arabia, Egypt, and the Soudan [Sudan]; the expected future role of the British Government in the Persian Gulf; and the likely need for the Government of India to take on responsibilities in Southern Persia.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000289#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>