<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T04:07:27.716Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">urgent. No.1141 Political Agency, Bahrain The 11 th April, 1946. To The State Engineer, Bahrain. Memorandum. Please have the two 6 volt batteries brought by bearer examined, and, if they are not sound, replaced. The bill should be sent to the Agency for payment. •for Political Agent, BahrainAQ ■ OOYSRU^iilJT OF BAHIUIH 3TATS ^KGINSKR’S DKPARg.SOT NO.PA/ \\ /65 BAHRAIN. 13th April, 1946 Dated; llth j/Avfal, 1365 h ■ ■ out, H.B.M’s Political Agent, BAHRAIN . ?\ Memorandum:- * Ref.your memorandum No.1141 dated llth April, 1946. The two batteries have been inspected and found to be unserviceable. Two new batteries have been issued to the Government Garage in replacement and I will inform you when they have been charged and are ready for collection. tate Engineer, Government of Bahrain.URGENT , No,1791• Political Agency, Bahrain, The 6 th June, 194-6. To The State Engineer, Bahrain. Memorandum. Will you kindly have these two batteries 'topped up' and meanwhile supply me temporarily CAMENDMENT TO CAR RULES * Substitute the following for Paragraph 7(a) and (b), of the Car Rules dated the 26th July, 1946:- '7. A charge of annas three per wcWke* will be/made for private bookings’ 1 . ^ . Qjrvlxup /- ^ FOR POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. / Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the 25th March 1949. NNR-g, jL.fi BJLiLJS-Ji 1« Th« ear la only to be driven by the drlver f by the Political Agent or by the Assistant Political Agent* 2* Not more than four persons, other than the driver, may use the car at any one tine* 3* Only the staff of this Agency my use the car* For except ions to this rule special permission will have to be obtained previously from the Assistant Political Agent through the Clerk in charge of car boa rings* 4* Qua Clerk will be In charge of car bookings* 5* Those Intending to use the car must give notice not later than 10 *.». on any day of Intended reservations for that day* For Friday reservations notice must be given on Thursday morning* 6* The Clerk in charge will check the log book before Issuing chls for petrol* 7. 8* Duty trips will take precedence over pleasure trips* 9* The log book must be entered up Immediately after a trip Is completed* A Transport Fund Is to be created* The Clerk In charge of bookings will arrange bookings so that the driver is not too heavily burdened on any one day* Appeals from his decisions may be made to the Assistant Political A ent* s Bahrain* 26th July 1^46* Political Agency, POLITIC All AGENT, HAH A IN. msD.O. No.C/1233. Dear Belgrave, At about 5.30 0* clock on the evening of the 30th October the Vauxhall car belonging to this Agency was involved in a collision with motor vehicle No.516 belonging to the Bahrain Government and suffered damage to its left rear mudguard. The driver and an Agency clerk were occu pants of the Vauxhall car at the time. I have received a statement from this clerk in which he informs me that M the car was returning from Adari when at a point a little beyond the Manama Western School a truck suddenly backed out from a side road to the left of the main road being hidden until the very last moment by the new buildings which have been built at that spot. The truck did not sound its horn nor did it give any other warning before entering the main road. By swerving violently across to the right the driver of the Vauxhall averted what may have been a very nasty accident, but the two § vehicles collided in passing and the car suffered the damage Mentioned above. The car was travelling at about 15 m.p.h. / /when the collision took place.' / 2. It would appear that the driver of the truck was res ponsible for the collision and should be called to account for his dangerous driving. As the truck was a Bahrain Government vehicle the case has not been officially reported to the police but you may perhaps think it advisable to take departmental action against the driver. Yours sincerely,&amp; O' D. 0 .No Adviserate, November 12, 1946 * With reference to your D.O.No. C/1233 dated 3rd November 1946, I am sorry that one of our Government vehicles should have caused an accident. The driver was our Egyptian agriculturist. I have ticked him off severely and told him that if any thing more of this sort occurs he will be given a horse instead of a vehicle. If you will let me know the cost of repairing the mudguard I will deduct the amount from his pay. Confidential.D.O. No.c/1266. The 13th Nov., 1946. Dear Belgrave, Thank you for your demi-official letter No.2379-42-16 dated the 12th November, 1946, and for your offer to refund the cost of repairing the mud guard of the Vauxhall. In view however of the action already taken by you, I should prefer to waive the recovery of the small sum involved. Yours sincerely, (1) C.D. Belgrave, IjScj# , C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. iTRANSPORT FVlU . y for Recoveries from O^A. for the financial year ending with 31st March 1947, is to be submitted by this day. Following were the duty trips upto-date. 581 miles @ As .6 per mile Rs. 217-14-0 r (Rupees two hundred and seventeen and Annas fourteen only) M$y credit Transport Fund. ' 31.3.1947. • , i;JL Ml kfidlMirza, driver of the Agency truck, has been working for this Agency for otfer six months. During thi period he has behaved himself in such a manner as to justify me in accusing him of insubordination and of working in an irresponsible manner. To quote one typical example of recent date is that which took place yesterday when I asked him to open the dynamo of the 'o( car and handed^to me to repair. He refused to do so and replied that it was not my lookout. He is the person responsible for the loss of the plugs of your battery and for fixing the spare wheel of your car inside-rout side. Under the circumstances I cannot but suggest , that ^driver be engaged in his place and his services # be dispensed with, as I can no longer take ever the % responsibility for the cars when those directly handling them act in this manner. * f?AA 7 &lt;§\fSLxjL A&gt;vvvv* Cu^a /Vl vy*. (XrvxX C-eUsX* ; Sayid Amin.D.O. No. 1548 POLITICAL AGENCY BiiHPAlN. The 5t}i May 1947 Tho Political Agont is anxious to have the Agency truck repainted, preferably gray. 2. would it be possible for you to have this done In your workshop? if so# I should be grateful if you would kindly let me know, and X will then arrange for the truck to be brought round whenever you wish. Yours sincerely, Group Captain H.P.G. Leigh, State Kngineer Government of Bahrain, Bahrain.GOVERNMENT Op BAHRAIN 0 TRANSPORT DEPARTMENT D.O.No.TD/ /J5/66 Datedr BAHRAIN. 1 6th J/Thani,l3 6 th May, Ref.your D.O.letter No. 1548 dated 5th May,1947. Please arrange for the Agency Truck to he delivered to the Bahrain Government G-arage at your earliest convenience. It will he required for approximately 4 days for repainting as requested hy you. Yours sincerely, a . &gt;t NcuoO !ii?: v STATE E) :/ GOVERITIvlEN Captain li.D.H.Ranee, H.B.M’s Assistant Political Agent, BAHRAIN.POLITICAL AGiiNCY, BAHKAIU. The 12th May 1947, &amp;) \\ The Superintendent of Police, .' •, i \ Bahrain^ Dear Sir, // !, \ » Could you kindly let me know if there is anything in your records against Hassan Haji Ahmed, Bahrain subject, holder of driving licence 323-64 issued on 13th Rajab 1364. He has been engaged as a driver in the Agency recently. &gt; j Yours faithfully, for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN,VI / 0 V i Ho. 860/66 of 1366 Office of the Superintendent State Police, Bahrain Dated the 27th J*Thani, 1366 17th May, 1947 * &lt; Reference vour letter No*1625 dated the 12th May, 1947. There is nothing in the Police records against Hasan bin Haji Ahmed who has been engaged as a driver in the Agency recently. ■V Statement of Yusuf bin Muhammad, driver of the Agency, aged 20 years. Yesterday (28.7.47) at about 5.45 r.m. I had Mr. Srininvasan in the Vauxhall and proceeding from Mananah to Jufair the spring of my car broke. This spring is the old spring - not t'he one newly fixed. I was driving at 20 miles’ speed when the spring broke. Thumb impression of Yusuf bin Muhammad. 2. 3 — [ex, 7^ i,A(- ~ Sif &lt;?**- Lr*~ '* * tfpzsb-d, . lX }n n O u77Thft Agency Vauxhaul^s battery is dead New batteries are not available in the market; but I understand that they are available with the State EngineeriDepartment. If A.P.A. approves, we may buy one from them. In order to get the new battery charged with sulphuric acid etc,, it will at least take 4 days time, therefore, I suggest that the State Engineer may kindly be asked to lend us a battery for use on the Vauxhall at present, until we get the new battery ready. -~ Th« State ijingineer, Bahrain. POLITICAL AG3NCY, BAHRAIN. The 13th August, 1947. ivleraoranduiii I shall be grateful if you will kindly Ch&lt;\*q*cl supply me with one new battery (12 wolt) for the use A- of Agency car (Vauxhall). . 2. The cost will be paid to you on receipt of your bill. for Political Agent, Bahrain. MMAfL • A \M\v] GOVERNMENT OP BAHRAIN Ih TRANSPORT DEPARTMENT NO.TD/ /66. H.B.M’s Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Dated: BAHRAIN. 20th August , 19i(-7 Ref. your memorandum No.2626 dated 13th August , 19U7 regarding purchase of one new {charged) 12 Volt car battery. It is regretted that we are not in a position to spare any at present,please. W - STATE GOVERNMENT 0? BAO^AIN.-17/27 The To POLITICAL AG2NCY, BAHRAiri. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum ConiDany Bahrain. 13th September, 1947. Dear ^ir, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs.136/3/- (Rupees One hundred and thirty six and annas three) only In full settlement of your Invoice No. L.7-66, the cost of petrol supplied to Agency during the month of July, 1947. Yours faithfully, v -'bWH -17/27 To POLITICAL AOttNCY, „ a BAHRAIN. The ^^October, 1947. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs.90/5/- (Rupees Ninety and annas five) only in full settlement of your invoice No.L.8-79, for the cost of petrol supplied to Agency during the month of August, 1947. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain. MMANo* f-17/27 To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. w The N o ve^b e r, 1947. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain . Dear Sir, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs. 109-12-0 (Rupees One hundred and nine and annas twelve) only in full settlement of your invoice No.L.9.99, for the cost of petrol supplied to Agency during the month of September, 1947. Yours faithfully, MMA Political Agent, Bahrain.mamJo. -17/27 POLITICAL AGLNCY, BAHRAIN. The 25th November, 1947. To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Lta., Bahrain * Dear Sir, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs. 114-6-0 CRuoees One hundred fourteen and annas six) only In tun settlement of your Invoice No.L-10-86, for the cost of petrol supplied to Agency during the month of-October, 19 - Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully,No.3899- The 14th December, 1947. To Messrs. Mohamed &amp; Sons, Bahrain. r Dear Sirs, The shock absorber of the Agency Vauxhall has become defective and needs urgent rep lacement. 2. I shall be grateful if you will kindly supply me with a new shock absorber, if available, or else let me have a shock absorber of some other make, which can be used in the vauxhall. 3 # Blease also supply one complete set of rear springs for this car. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain.TELEPHONE NO. &gt;09. CODESt-BENfLEY’S. MOHAMED ABDULAZIZ ALAJAJI &amp; SONS. BAHRAIN /IN d 7 ) CP. GULF) H.3.1 . 1 s Polit?.cal A ;ent, Pahj’ai n. ^ / TELE ADD: MOHAMED ALAJAJI. Dec. 15, 1947 Dear Sir; n \te thank you .for your letter ho.3899 of the 14th instant. he rejrret to adviise you that the J auxliall parts shipped per s.s.’Castlodore’ have beer over-carnied to some other port, h© have so Par no information as to its contents, and as soon as ”. r e pet the cases '.ve will supply your requirements, if included in the contents. he tried the local market as well as Austin and Standard agents, but were not successful. V/e are very sorry that we are not able to serve you an this instance. At the same time we are ordering the same teli c raphicall; to Bombay. * Yours faithfully. miATSD ABDTilAZlC AIAJAJI h SOUS Sole Agents for —Buiok, Oldsmobile Cars, G. M. C. Trucks &amp; Firestone Proiucts at Bahrain. Sauli Arabia A Qatar.Telegram - From - To - No. 617. Dated the 29th December, 1947. Please despatch airfreight one axleshaft and housing assembly rear for Vauxhall model VXO year 1946 serial number 17809. n st&gt; Enclair. r Political Agent, Bahrain, Vauxhall Motors, Luton, Bedfordshire. KW + POLITICAL AGENT +J 1 Telegram - Enclair Fro* - Vauxhall Voters, Luton (England) To - Political, Bahrain. Dated the 30th and received the 31st December, 1947. Yours twentyninth. Requirements not clear. Order through General Motors Agent, Bahrain. - Vauxhall Motors - &gt; I.R, No. 3 * //No. 3;2£ -n/&gt;.'7 POLITICAL AOANOT, AIiJ. The 1st February, 1343. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain . Dear Sir, I enclose herewith 44 cheque for Rs. 116/3/- (Rupees One hundred and sixteen and Annas three) only in full settlement of your invoice No.Na.L .12.106, for the cost of petroleum supplied to Agency during the month of December, 1947. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully,1. Date of despatch 2. List of enclosures DEPARTMENT/OFFICE. Letter Draft Memorandum Telegram No. DRAFT Dated File No. Serial No. 1 VAUXHALL MOTORS, LUTON, BEDFORDSHIRE. -&amp;£»Dfc¥ DISPATCH AIRFREIGHT ONE LEFTHAND TORSION •/ SHAFT AND TUBE ASSEMBLES* ANjk ONE REAR GPRTffG Hi FOR WAUXHATX.HODElTV} VXO YEAR 1946 SERIALPOLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. No. -17/27 The 21st February, 1948 To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain . Dear Sir, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs.156/13/- (Rupees One hundred and fifty six and annas thirteen) only in full settlement of your invoice Nos.L-1-90, L.1-58, for the cost of petroleum supplied to Agency during the month of January, 1948. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, BahrainPOLITICAL AGENCY n BAHRAIN. No.9^7-17/27 ^he 23rd ;iarch, 1948 To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain . Dear Sir, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs.137-4-0 (Rupees One hundred thirty seven and annas four) only in full settlement of your invoice No.L-2-90 for the cost of petroleum supplied to the Agency during the month of February, 1948. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, r for Foiitical Agent, Bahrain.D.0.No.1117- D*ted the 10th April, 1348 I spoke to otob«*rt just before he left on the subject of tyres for our Dodge truck, but I do not know If he \/*s Abie to do anything about it. ihe oosition is that two of our outer tyres are completely unserviceable, and although new ones *re »ctu*lly obtainable in the bazaar, it is only at the inflated price of about Is.400/-/- which seems pointless in view of the age of the truck. 2. However, I think there were about 5 to 6 new out covers in the stores I took over fro:* i4r. Aiyer, and as the hesidency truck was fitted wit new tyres soon -ifter ay arrival, 1 wonder if you could snare us two of these. or A.b.A. Dredge, Secretary to the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Yours sincerelyNo. 1146 The Political Agency, Ba hrain. Dated 10th April, 1948 To The Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf Bahrain. Subject:- Transport of office staff by official vehicles. MEMORANDUM In view of the climate of Bahpain during the summer it is felt that some case might be made for requesting the Foreign Office under paragraph 3 of the Official Car Code for sanction of the use of official transport for normal attendance at the Office npi-gfaraMY ja without payment. 2. It is however, understood that the subject has already been raised by the Residency with E &amp; 0 Department and I would be grateful if you would let me know whether an answer has been received, and if so whether the decision is applicable to the Political Agencies as well. Sd. R.McC. Andrew for Political Agent, Bahrain.A. A. ZAYANI &amp; SONS &amp; • Tele J GRAMSJZAYAN1 PHONEF 5 M. DISTRIBUTORS : AUSTIN CARS &amp; TRUCKS PERSIAN GULF Bankers: EASTERN BANK &amp; IMPERIAL BANK OF IRAN. Bahrain 10th April, 1948 H.B.M’s Political A^ent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, He Austin 16 H.P. Shooting Brake Vve regret the trouble you have experienced with the new shooting brake delivered recently. We have today cabled Austin Company’s works at Birmingham for a replacement of piston complete to be forwarded by airmail. As soon as received these parts will be handed to your repairer. The damaged piston will be forwarded to the technical branch of Austins for a report, a copy of which we shall be pleased to pass on for your information when received. Haturally, as this repair is being carried out by another repairer when we have our own workshops, we are not responsible for any charges incurred or future breakdowns under the guarantee. Yours faithfully,© No. 1114-30/20 . PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 21st April, 1948. To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. MEMORANDUM. Reference your memorandum No. 1146 dated 10th April , 1948. 2. Owing to the exceptional conditions prevailing at Bahrain, it is agreed that staff living some distance away from office should be permitted to use official transport for normal attendance without payment.AH*TTN SHOOTING BRAKa TOOL LIST Double ended spanners:-3/16 M x 5/16' x f', 7/16“ x I” Box spanner:- 3/16” x 1/4' Tommy bar Adjustable spanner ~ Tappet adjusting spanner Screwdriver Distributor-screwdriver Tappet clearance and sparking plug gauge Starling handle Sparking plug spanner Jack operating lever Tyre pump Dunlp tyre valve tool Oil gun corapletetfwtih adapter Valve grinding tool Key for spare wheal compartment Envelope containing literature Tool wrap Packer Missing tool Wheal brace Tyre lever Combination pliers Contd, list of tool 1/4' , Double ended spanner 2 Putch spanner 1 Tyre lever 2 File 1 Wheal spanner 1*w HUMBER SUPER SWIPE TOOL t V Tool Rollv J Emergency Tool Bago ^ Do So Spanner l/4' X 5/l6 w . V' DoEo Spanner l/8' X 3/l6', / DoEo Spanner 7/l6 M X l/2', N. Do So Spanner 9/l6' X 5/8'. ^ Tappot Spanners. Plug Box Spanner Lifting Jade &amp; Handle. Starting Handle. Screw Dri-ver. Pliers, 1 Adjustable Spanner. y lyre Pump. lyre Levers. If Wheel Nut Brace. Grease Gun. Carburettor Spanner. * Distributor Key. V Tonny Bar. Valve &amp; Plug Gauge. V Bloedor Wrench. Bleeder Tube in Container ;; LIST.-TRANSPORT FUND. r Statement of recoveries for the month of Jarch, 1948. To ^uty tfi'P 3 ^97 miles (S* ^-is 6 per mile Rs.298-8-0 Total Rupees Two hundred and ninety eight and annas eight only.IIGOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN BILL NO TDB//&amp;£/67 (D i+th RajalD,1367 BAHRAIN Da 1 th May, 1 948 H.B.M's Political Agent, D«. TO: BAHRAIN, THE BAHRAIN GOVT. TRANSPORT D ept, ToiCost of charging one new 12 volts battery for your new Humber Super Snipe car during Jamad Awal,136?. Rs.20-0-0 (Rupees twenty.only). /PPICER-IN-CHARGE, government transport dept, Rupees Twenty only. May pay and debit Transport Fund a/c? CL^^l ZSXxGJ.tylXjC. K.V.A. 27-6-'48. iNo. / POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 28th June, 1948o Messrs. Mohameci A.Aljaji &amp; Sons, Bahrain. Dear Sirs, I enclose hertewith a cheque for Rs.3l/l2/- (Rupees Thirty one and annas twelve) only in full settlement of your invoice No.283/3, dated 10th February, 1948. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully. for Political Agent, Bahrain.POLITICAL AGSHCY, BAHRAIN. No. Thw 23th *&gt;une # 1948. *r&lt; r Messrs. Khalil bin Ebrahim Kanoo, B ahrain* Bear Sirs, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs.kO/-/- (i^upees twenty) only in full settlement of your invoice No.INV.KJB* 119/48, dated 1st May* 1948 for the cost of 1 sealed Beam supplied to the Asency. Ploase scknowledge receipt. Yours f aithfully. for Political Agent, Bahrain.POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 28th June, 1948. Messrs. Abdulreteoan H. Algosalbi, Bahrain. Dear Sirs, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs.15///- (Rupees fifteen) only in full settlement of your invoice dated 24th February, 1948, for the csot of Exhaust pipe supplied to the Agency. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.No* D-OZf POLITICAL AGS2JCY, BAHl-iAIU. The 28th June, 1948, Haji Abdul Razak Abdulla, Garage Mechanic, Bahrain. Lear Sir, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rfl.351-0-0 (Rupees Three hundred and fifty one) only in full settlement of your debit Rote 48/1.5. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully. for Political Agent, Bahrain. MMAPOLITICAL AGmCY BAHRAIN. t Uo. Z'O&amp;l' The 29th June, 1948. (^) Messrs. Yousuf Abdulrehman PaJchroo, B ahrain . Lear Sire, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs.4i/- (Rupees Porty and one) only in full oetfclement of your invoice dated 22nd April, 19*6, for the cost of Chamois leather supplied to Agency. Please acknowledge receipt. Yo tire 'ait: .Tully t for Political Agent, Bahrain.POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. No. The 28th June, 1948. The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs.292/l/-(Rupees Two hundred and ninety two and annas one) only in full settlement of your invoices No.L.3-102, and L.4-124 for the cost of petroleum supplied to the Agency during the months of March and April, 1943. Please ack nowledge receipt. Yours faithfully. for Political Agent, Bahrai: JQS1Ho. 2 0J.S POLITICAL ACrJiiJOI, BAHRAXH. Th« 29th June, 1948. The Offioer-in-Charge, Behrain Government Transport Dept*, Bahrain. Memo ranorm I enclose herewith a cheque for Hs.20/- (Rupees twenty) only in full settlement of your invoice tTo .TITE/lSfi/e?, dated 11th May, 1948, for the cost of charging ore new batter:/' of my Humber Super Snipe. Please acknowledge receipt. for Political Agent, Bahrain.•0V3Riir,3ITT OF BAHRAIN ort depart; NO.TDC/ 2-1 /67 The H.B.M’s Political Agent, The Political Agency, Bahrain. Memorandum: Dated: BAHRAIN. 25th Shahan ,136? 1st July ,1948 I acknowledge with thanks receipt of your letter No.2023 dated the 29 th June ,1948 together with a cheque No .326267 for the sum of Rs.20- 0-0 (Rupees twenty,only) in full settlement of our Bill No.TDB/l 66/67 dated 11th May ,1948. An official receipt No.00492 of 23 th Shahan, 1367 is enclosed,please./ r.AVRRNSVIENT OF BAHRAIN TRANS PORT DEPT No DATEI / \ ■&amp;a.£or &lt; ? POLITICAL AGEMC BAHHAIK. Th« 28th June, 1948, Messrs. Khalil bin Ebrahim Kanoo, Bahrain. Bear Sirs, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs.20/-/- (Rupees twenty) only in full settlement of your invoice llo.IKV.ICB. 119/48, dated 1st May, 1948 for the cost of 1 sealed Beam supplied to the Agency. Please acknowledge receipt. - Yoursi aithfully,/ No. ZOZi POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 28th June, 1948. Haji Abdul Razak Abdulla, Garage Mechanic, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs.351-0-0 (Rupees Three hundred and fifty one) only in full settlement of your debit Note 48/15. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, - MMA for Po. itlcal Agent Bahrain. *Statement of Ahmad bin Yusuf, driver of the Agency truck. Recorded at the Agency, on the 27th May, 1948. Yesterday at about 1.40 p.m. after I had taken Mr. Vishunadhan to his house, I stopped the truck at the premises of the Municipality waiting for Mr. Vishunadhan to read the speedometer and enter it in the log book. Meanwhile a lorry bearing No.p. 1191, which was parking right in front of my truck, made a move backing his lorry towards the truck. I sounded the horn several times in attempt to stop him; but he did not until he hit the truck, thus causing the breakage of/the glass of the left-hand front light. Mr. Vishunadhan was an eye-witness to this accident. D/27.5.48. i.e Ahmad bin Yusuf. cUrC'* to Covv£e&gt;. ^ ~ w rui&gt;c^f LsCkaalI Ujl./ OUSUF ABDULRAKIAN FAKHROO - BAHRAIN. Arabia. 30th June 194-8. The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, We acknowledge receipt of your letter No.2022 of 29th instant and have to thank you for enclosing cheque for Rs.41/- in full settlement of our Invoice dated 22nd April 194-8. Yours faithfully, FOR YOUSUF ABDULRAHMAN FAKHROO,/ No. 9 7 Xbx£&amp;1£x POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN* The 19th July, 1948, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., s Bahrain . Lear Sira, I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs.103-12-0 (Rupees One hundred three and annas twelve) only in full settlement of your invoice iSo.L-5-135, dated 31st my, 1948, for the co&amp;v of petroleum supplied to the Agency during the month of my, 1948. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, MMA for Politicals Agent, Bahrain f &gt; Im o To, The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. Dear sir. I enclose herewith a cheque for Es. 149/14/ (Rupees one hundred forty-nine and annas fourteen nly) in full settlement of your invoices Nos. .V. 6-6 and F.V. 7-6 dated 30th June, *48 and 31st July, • 48 respectively. Yours faithfully, k for Political Agent, BahrainHA V Political Agency, B a hran, No. ^ 13th September, 1948. Kersrs. A.A. Zayani &amp; Sons. Bahrain. Dear sir?, I enclose herewith . 30/- (Hnneos thirty only) in full settlonent of your bill No. 4203 datrl 13.8.48. Please acknowledge a receipt. U.ir&amp;t' ior Political Agent, Bahrain.ZAYANI &amp; SONS DISTRIBUTORS : s T ELt AUSTIN CARS &amp; TRUCKS Bankers: GRAMS: ZAYANI PHONE: 5 M. H.B.M’s Political Bahrain Dear Sir, EASTERN BANK PERSIAN GULF Re.Ib H.P. Car Shooting Brake Further to our letter dated ipth April 1948, we enclose copy of a report,received from Austin Motor Export Corporation,which is self-explanatory. We are refunding the cost of spare parts and enclose herewith a cheque in your favour for RsI4/-, receipt of which kindly acknowledge. Meanwhile we remain.THE AUSTIN tIOTOK KXPOHT COHPOHATION LTD BIRMINGHAM SERVICE CLAIMS/RMT 21.6.48 bi/s A.A.Zayar.i &amp;. Sons Bahrein. Bear Sirs Re 16 H.P. Car Further to oar letter of the 7th instant ref SERVICE CLAIMS /RMT concerning one piston which you returned to these Vvorks from the above type of shooting brake. Vve have now had an opportunity of examining this piston and we find that it has been seized badly on both sides of the piston skirt. It is difficult by just examining the returned part to give an accurate report as to why seizure has occured, but if it was taken from a new car the most likely reason for the failure is th&amp;t the car had been over-driven. We are, however, as a gesture of goodwill cancelling the charges made for the replacment piston which our Service Export Department state they have already despatched to your good- selves . We trust that this decision will meet with your statisfacti- on. Yours faithfully For THE AUSTIN MOTOR EXPORT CORP LTD SGD SERVICE CLAIMS DEPARTMENTPolitical Agency, Bahrain, 26th September, 1948. To, Dear Messrs. sirs. A.A.Zayani &amp; Sons, Bahrain, The cheque for Rs. 14/- (Rupees fourteen only) sent under cover of your letter dated the 26th August f 1948, has been received with thanks. % Yours faithfully, i for Political Agent, Bahrain.*; -n (U) No.V/ )Qb Political Agency, Bahrain, D/ 28th September, 1948. To Messrs. A.A. Zayyani &amp; Sons, Bahrain. Hear Sirs, With reference to the painting of the rear raud-gaards of the Agency Shooting Brake Austin station wagon, I would request that the painting should be done in a colour to match v/ith the original one. If this, however, is not possible, I should like you to inform me accordingly. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain, A.M.Statement of recoveries from Aastin duing the month of September, 1948. Rs As. Ps. Mr. Stobart 166 Kilos @ As. 4 per Kilo. 41 8 ' '' c Mr. Aiyar 44 Kilos @ As. 4 per per Kil#. 11 Mr. Carrau 72 Kilos O As. 4 per Kilo 18 po i- * Mr. Mohammed Ali 28 Kilos @ As. 4 per Kilo 7 Major Hudson 2 Kilos @ As 4 per Kils. 8 44 1* - Total 78 -t^'4 t Total Bs. syenty-eight only to be collected and credited (%o@a&gt; jjg-fXin the Transport Account. &gt; $Jf/l -1°'t &amp;d&lt;. lU-'t. -•yv / 4 - 4 . %[XA 051] Revised Form SIX-MONTHLY REPORT ON OFFICIAL MOTOR VEHICLES, HIS MAJESTY’S FOREIGN SERVICE. Agent or Garage/ „ • Date Address To : The Under-Secretary of State Cost of Overhaul 4_j3jLc^ r t- ‘ \£e ■ (including parts) £ for Foreign Anairs, v &amp; 1 ' The Foreign Office, London. Description of Vehicle. Makefrrr^&lt;f^i^r?^r^V. Registered No H.P. Type or Series Year Chassis No Engine No Caro -and Station Wagon^—^Seating Capacity Trucks—Carrying Capacity Number of tyres on Vehicles and size .../vui-i^... Speedometer reading Average weekly mileage on all business during past six months ... . \l&lt;u&amp;&amp;r3. Petrol consumption m.p.g. Oil consumption // . m.p.g. 13172e 35900—9 [overCONDITION REPORT The following have been inspected. Repairs have been effected as stated. Engine Comment. /J Fan Comment ~o — Clutch I F twill Flywheel Comment. ^ . Universal Joints /? V*/ Comment. Gear Bow / *-, ^ y Comment, &lt; f' T ransmission Comment. Rear Awle O CJ Comment. Front Axle Comment. Steering Box Comment. Brakes Comment. Front j Rear Springs; Shackles Comment. Electrical Comment. Petrol Tank ft ^ Comment. y'O ~D d 0 Tyres and Equipment Comment Body—General Condition Comment. / / Trcy-e i General Remarks and Recommendations Comment. ^ ^ The vehicle completely roadv/orthy. It is likely to give good service for a further period of Signature of Agent or Garage Manager Counter Signature of Head of Post (or a responsible member of the Foreign Service deputed to sign on his behalf) ■ //• h6/ Chalon No. 2 of 1948 £. brain PolUjcal Anen cy Treasury Name of pe son paying In Moneyi Particulars of Amount Payment into Treasury On whose behalf paid To What Head Creditable Collection from the A ency staff for the month of October, 1948 for using the Austin car for private purpose i fc. £9/13/- X — Foreign Office Account Received the sum of fis# 89/ll/» (Rupees eight^y-nine and annas eleven Bahrain, 6th December, 1948. \/ 37 • c tatement of recoveries from Austin for the month of November, 194P. Mr. IVir Mr. Abdul Rahman 45 Kilos As. 4/- p.k. Carrau 93 Kilos @ As. 4/- p.k. and 39 Kilos &amp; As. 2/- P.k. . 27/?/- Arrears for the month of Ju 1948 Rs. 3l/ c / Ringrow 92 Kilos At As. V- p.k. &gt;. 23/-/- 7 Arrears for the month of ( Juife, 194 . Rs. 27/7/-j K.V. Vidhyanathan 36 Kilos @ As.1/6 p.k. and 14 K. @ As. 4/- p.k. , 6/14/- Arrears for the month of August, 194 p Rs. 11 58 50 :/ 15/4/- \ 22 Mr. Mr Mr 12 9 ^ Mr. Mr As. 4 15 ^ Ps p*a&gt; 7 P/uJ - 4y Mohd. Ali 36 Kilos @ As. 1/6 p.k. and 39 Kilos (S* As. 2 p.k. K. Viswanathan 73, Kilos a A s. 1/6 p.k. and 44 Kilos @ As. 2/- p.k. Aiyar 37 Kilos @ As. 3/7 per Kilo and 23 Kilos @ 4 p.k. / R.V.Ramani 16 Kilos @ As. 4/- p.k. and 37 Kilos $ As. 1/6 p. k. and 44 Kilos $ As. 2 p.k. Murthy 4 Kilos (4 As.4/- p.k Club 4 Kilos @ As.4/- M Total^rupees one hundred eighty-seven and annas six only to be collected and credited to the Transport Account. The following are overtime charges for the driver, das c an Foolad, after 8:00 P. M. ' ’ ' r. Ringrow Mr. Carrau Mr. Mohd. Ali . 6/- l * ■ 1 / 3 /-' pi. ( H Km ' iL Mk'- 5th December!, 1948. £14 c/b\ o/p/e* •/ POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHH.IN, NO. V. 3 THE 10th JANUARY, 1949 To, The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Co. Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith cheque No. 399010 for fis. 60/9/- (Rupees sixty and annas nine only) in full settlement of your invoice No. 1-11-128, dated the 30th November, 1948. 2. The enclosed receipt in duplicate may kindly be signed and sent back to me. Assistant Political Agent, / t ' Bahrain. MA/ h POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, THE ?2nd January, 1949. To, The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith cheque No. 399012 for Re. 74/12/- (Rupees seventy o- r and anras twelve only) in full settlement of your invoice Mo. 1- 12- 129, dated the 31st Decern' er, 1942T. 2. The enclosed receipt in duplicate may kindly be signed and sent back to me. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. £AMENDMENT TO CAR RULES Substitute the following for Paragraph 7(a) and (b), of the Car Rules dated the 26th July, 1946s- '7. A charge of annas three per mile will be made for private bookings”. ' FOR POLITICAL AGSNT, Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the 25th March 1949. BAHRAIN. NfiRNo.694-17/27 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN., The 25th March 1949 Dear British Agency, Please refer to your letter No.209.0130, the 7th March, 1949. dated We forward herewith a copy of the Official Car Code (XA/5/0/1) of April 1946, and six copies of S.O.Book 136, to be used as Vehicle Log Book with the following headings:- Date 5 Kilometre 5 Journey 5 Journey K Initials 5 Petrol Issued 5 or 5 Performed 5 whether { j 5 mileage { No. of j[ on duty 5 5 $ Reading 5 miles orjl or 1 5 kilo. 5 private 5(XA 5/0/1) FOREIGN OFFICE, APRIL, 1946. THE OFFICIAL CAR CODE Since it is desirable to define the responsibilities of Heads of Posts in the use and care of official motor vehicles, to guide them in their proper maintenance, and to avoid contro versy over the respective responsibilities of an outgoing Head of the Post and his successor, the following rules have been made: RESPONSIBILITY 1. The responsibility for the proper use, care and maintenance of official vehicles will rest entirely with the Head of the Post, whether the vehicles be driven by himself or by an official chauffeur or temporarily by any member of his staff. It Is emphasised that especial care must be taken of official vehicles, because they are supplied at the public expense and are not the personal property of the Head of the Post or his staff. It is his responsibility to ensure that the vehicles are properly serviced, that the log-book supplied for use with each vehicle is regularly kept and that all instructions concerning repair and running cost, accounts and insurance are carried out. The official motor vehicles are entirely at the disposal of the Head of the Post who may at his discretion authorise their use by subordinate members of his staff if and when he sees fit. During absences from his post or on his transfer to another post, the outgoing Head of the Post will ensure that the vehicles are handed over to his substitute or his successor with their complete equipment and full complement of spare wheels and tyres, tools and spare parts, and the fact reported in a separate paragraph noting any exceptions, in his handing-over report. USE 2. The use of official vehicles may be differentiated under three headings: official, representative and private. 3 # The term M official use” includes:- official visits by the Head of the Post and members of the staff to public bodies, British subjects, foreign colleagues and so on; the meeting of distinguished arrivals, attendance at official receptions (luncheons, dinners, cocktail parties, funerals, &amp;c); and collection of Foreign Office bags and mail from King’s Messegers and landing grounds • The cost of su&amp;huse is to be chrged to public funds. Journesys for normal attendance at the office can only be regarded as ’’official' when special sanction has been granted by the Department. The present practice is to require the staff to make a payment for such journeys. The cost of journeys made on behalf of Dominion or Colonial GoveER- ments should be charged to the Dominion or Colony conerned and and credited to this Department. 4. The vehicles may also be used for representative or private purposes, in which case the cost is to be paid to the official funds at the post by each person concerned at the approved fixed rate per mile per vehicfe and shown as a credit on the 'Transport' schedule with the quarterly acccntmts. Representative use of the vehicle includes visits of a less than official nature, which nevertheless $ust be paid in order to maintain touch a/ltv* cn wlth people and affair sThis of course includes attendance at parties arid places which are not strictly official. 5. 'Private use” of the vehicle is a self-explanatory term and may chiefly be applied to the use of the vehicle for recreational purposes. MAINTENANCE 6. The proper driving and maintenance of official vehicles are responsibilities of the Head of the Post* who must ensure that the vehicle is not driven at an excessive speed (taking into consideration the local standard of roads and of driving) and that the economical cruising speed of the vehicle is not needlessly exceeded. When a chauffeur is necessary the Head of the Post must satisfy himself that the chauffeur's standard of driving and maintenance is adequate. 7. The Head of the Post must alsoensure that the vehicles are serviced at regular intervals (according to th instructions in the handbook of each vehicle) and that an accurate record of maintenance, repairs and replacements is kept. A log-book for each vehicle is to be kept in the front pocket, &amp;nd petrol and oil consumption and mileages at the time of replenishment are to be entered in it, as well as the records of trips. Where not supplied with the vehicle, an inventory of equipmest, tools and spares, should be prepared and revised as necessary from time to time, and care should be taken that these article are not lost. Both the log-book and the Inventory at wixlpx ■silk should be checked every month, preferably on a specific date such as the first day of each month, and deficiencies accounted for and made good, if necessary privately. All proper vehicle expenses not arising out of negligence or fault are chargeable to public funds. 8. In particularly hot climates c re is to be taken to' ensure that the cooling system is working efficiently, ail special attention should be paid to correct tyre pressures (as given in the handbook). Where roads are rough, care should also be taken to remove stones or flints which may have become embedded. All the covers before they have cut through to the inner tube, and road springs should be periodically inspected for signs of breakage. In climates where great extremes of cold are experienced attention sho- Id be paid to the necessity for ”Anti-freeze” in the water system. It is to be emphasised that from the point of view both of smartness and upkeep the tasks of washing and polishing are important, as also are those of oiling and greasing in the interests of continued efficiency. Where the official vehicles of a post Include trucks or lorries, over-loading should be avoided and correct distribution of load (with the bulk of the weight will forward between the axles) observed. 9. Each official vehicle should be overhauled every six months and a report furnished to the Head of thePost. For this, as for all maintenance and repairs, the local agents of the makers or their advised local garage (if there is one) should be used, or else the best local garage. The expenses of overhauls and reports are chargeable to public funds. 10. At large posts it is probable that the Head of the Post will m wish to delegate the supervision of maintenance, &amp;c., of official vehicles to a competent member of his staff, but he will at all times remain himself responsible./ (J42 • 3 • SIX-MONTHLY REPORT f 11. In order that a proper check may be kept in London on the state of official vehicles abroad, ari with a view as far as possible, to avoiding eventual disputes both as to the necessity of replacing old vehicles and as to the condition of vehicles at times of handing-over, a six- monthly report is to be furnished to the Establishment Offter of the Foreign Office. Such reports, drawn up by a competent firm of motor-engineers as indicated above, if one is available, should cover:- a) The state of the engine and chassis. b) The state of the coachwok. c) The condition of the tyres. d) Petrol consumption per mile. e) Oil consumption per mile. f) The mileage run from time of delivery and during the past six months, and must be submitted on the 1st October and the 1st April of each year, countersigned by the Head of the Post. The reports should, where possible, state the causes of any defects which may come to light as the result of examination; a*}d distinguish between those due to fair wear and tear and thos arising from other causes such as original defects, abnormal road and climatic conditions, careless supervision or driving Ac. ACCOUNTS 12. Accounts for the running costs and maintenance and repair costs of each officii vehicle will be sfomitted Ath the quarterly accounts in a separate ^Transport” schedule. In such schedules are to be included separately the costs of running expenses, spares, repairs, replacemnts, overhauls, reports, chauffeur's wages and uniforms, insurance (where necessary;, &lt;5rC. Payments in respect of private use and use on behalf of Dominion or Colonial Governments, as laid down in paragraphs 3 and 4, should be entered as an item on the Dr. sii of the quarterly account, supported by a schedule showing in detail the composition and amount of each individual payment. INSURANCE 13. Official vehicles wll not be insured, unless the law of the country in which they are in use so dem nds, in which case the Foreign Office must first be consulted; since His Majesty's Government do not as a rule insuF their own property and since they accept in consequence all the risks involved, which in the case of official use of official vehicles are borne in the public interest and in the case of their private and representational use are covered by the mileage rate. DOCUMENTS 14. Specimen copies of the proposed log-book, six-monthly report form and monthly maintenance eheck-list accompany tikis Code which should be kept readily available at each post./ iff -17/27 . ;;a POLITICAIj agency, BAHRAIN* The 13th April, 3.949. Dear British Agency, We forward herewith a copy of Foreign Office Circular No.(XA051(13/49)), dated 16-3-1949. 2. We oropose to charge here lOj* annas per mile( at Ks.13.26 to a poundy( or annas six per kilometer for private use of our Government vehicles, and suggest you introduce the same rate with effect from 1-4-1949. To The British Agency, S H A R J A K . KVA ■ , &gt;-*•» YOURS iSViJR, AGENCY. yA. A. ZAYANI &amp; SONS I 4 J Tele GRAMS: ZAYANI PHONC: 5 M. DISTRIBUTORS : AUSTIN CARS &amp; TRUCKS PERSIAN GULF Bankers: EASTERN BANK &amp; IMPERIAL BANK OF IRAN. H.L.M’s Political Agent, Banrain. Bahrain 14 th April *49. ufc Dear Sir, AUSTIN 16 H.P. ''Station-wagon' Uve beg to report that the above-mentioned car requires de-carbonising and change of Cylinder-head gasket as the one in use is leaking. Secondly,the body has rusted in certain parts and touching-up will never match the original shade. e would, therefore, suggest the car to be repainted in one of the various attractive 'DUCO” shades and would particularly point out Sun Beige as an outstanding choice. Both decarbon ising and re-painting should take'not more than 5 to b da v s. Assuring you of our best service. Yours faithfully, ;ner* A. A. ZAY-Wl’A SONS. mm i'/ _HdBB ) i URGENT. PORITICAL AGENCY, , -i ^^ BAHRAIN. No. 't 1 ? -c -17/27 . The 21st April, 1949. 41 To Messers A.A.Zayani &amp; Sons, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Will you please refer to your letter dated the 14th April, 1949, and send me an estimate for de-carbonising and change of - cylinder head, and repainting the Austin Station Wagon showing each item separately. IFours faithfully^ ^ FOR POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KVAA. A. ZAYANI &amp; SONS (g) GRAMS: ZAYANI PHONE: 5 M. DISTRIBUTORS : AUSTIN CARS &amp; TRUCKS PERSIAN GULF Bankers: EASTERN BANK &amp; IMPERIAL BANK OF IRAN. H.B.M’s lolitical Agent, Bahrain. Bahrain 2'ixd April ’49. Dear Sir, We acknowledge with thanks your letter ref. 1052-17/27 dated 21st instant and have pleasure in giving hereunder our estimate for work on the AUSTIN 16 H.P. Station Wagon. De-carbonising and change of Head-cylinder gasket ... ... Re-painting/ Nj^UTorJLZZ POLITICAL AQKWCy, BAI-IEAIN • The 2nd May, 1349* To Messrs, A*A*Zayani A Sons, Bahrain. Dear Sirs, Reference your yesterday^ telephonic conversation with the Superintendent of this Agency it is confirmed that your estimate for repainting and de-carbonising etc.the Austin Station Wagon is approved. Yours faithfully, KVA /.-FOR POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. / I¥ L - / A. A. 2 AY A N I &amp; SONS. (3&gt; AUSTIN CARS &amp; TRUCKS. PERSIAN GULF. Bahrein Islands and other Qulf Ports* Very soon we will be receiving sone of those models but thought It wild be advisable to let you have son© advance Iniornation thereon* Having this In nlnd f we enclose here^th a few brochures which deal with the outstanding achieveoents of tiie 4-vheel drive Land iover and Statioa-Lagon* We are certain that you will feel the urge for possoosin- so:o:‘ those uultl-nurposvc ilcle:* -nu we look forward to your esteemed enquiries whioh will receive our best attention* In the aeantlme t holding ourselves fully at your service f we rema 1 n. f l i ** jxL HaA f ffc a-M, }h&gt; K 4-*-+*v Yours falthfully t ^ J Partner, ♦ V'V I &amp;n ir i A. A. ZAYANI &amp; SONS. C: ' DISTRIBUTORS. : AUSTIN CARS &amp; TRUCKS. PERSIAN GULF. Gable : 'ZAYANI” Phone: 3 7 1. Bankers: EASTERN BANK LTD. &amp; IMPERIAL BANK OF IRAN. Bahrain 7th January 1950* H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. 55 r V-L r ; ^ • •• Ai \' Dear Sir, cy--' - c H Bahrain- Austin 16 H.P. ShootingBr We write to inform you'that your above Station- Wagon was surveyed in our garage and the following faults have been reported: Leakage from the cylinder block to the sparking plugs, apparently due to wearing out of piston rings. Leakage from the radiator. The first item would entail a dismantling of the engine taking about 5 to 7 days and we could arrange to fit oversize rings where necessary, the total cost of operations not to exceed Rs96/-. However, after opening out the engine, if we find the fault to be else where than indicated above we will let you know. The radiator requires soldering and we can do this for Rsl5/- Yours faithfully, TU h ////- * f M- A'P'A * J ^ Q Rz:Nm. INo. //(? Political Agency, Bahrain, 14th January 1960 Dear Sirs With reference r letter dated the 7th January I960, I have to inform you that the necessary repairs to our Austin Station Wagon as proposed by you may please be taken in hand as soon as possible. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent Messrs.A.A.Zayani &amp; Sons, Bahrain.t •v / |§ i dmH vtF^ TELEPHONE 440 .A.KOOHEJI tc SONS GENERAL MERCHANTS &amp; COMMISSION AGENTS TELEGRAMS: 'KOOHEJI' BENTLEY'S CODE &amp; DISTRIBUTORS: STANDARD &amp; TRIUMPH CARS REF. NO. BAHRAIN P. GULF February 15, 1950 H« M f s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear sirs. @ *950 MODELS. 'VANGUARD” AND 'MAYFLOWER' We have the pleasure to enclose herewith the illustrated leaflets which we hope would be of great interest to you. In these leaflets you would notice that a large number of improvements have been added to encrease the beauty, performance and durabiity of the vehicles. Assuring you of our best services and prompt attention at all times.No.F- /ji -17/27 Political Agency, Bahrain, 13th March 1950 Dear Department, Since the receipt in this Office of the Foreign Office Circular 19 of 15th March 1949, the members of our sta^f using official vehicles for repre sentational and private Purposes have been paying at the enhanced rate of Ish. per mile per vehicle. But we understand that the Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, Mr.Gardiner) were allowed to continue to charge at the old rate of 6d. per mile. The sanction was conveyed to them in Foreign Office No.XA05l/34K2A(8/49), dated the 10th June 1949 from Mr.Ridley. concession was intended to apply to the Agency, but we should be grateful for it to be so applied as the conditions in Bahrain are the same for both offices. We are not sure whether this Yours ever Bahrain Agency. The Finance De Foreign Office Department /Political Agency, . Bahrain, No. /D5; -17/28. 25th March, 1950. The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Co.Ltd*, Avjali, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM: Please refer to your invoices Nos.L/ll/169 v and L/12/139 for petroleum products supplied during the months of November and December 1949 respectively. 9 2. I enclose herewith a cheque in your favour for Rs. 130-9-0 and cash Es.29-7-0 both of which make up the total of your two invoices referred to above. Please return to me the enclosed receipts in duplicate duly discharged. 3. It is requested that in future you should submit an invoice in the name of the Political Agency, Bahrain for the Petroleum products supplied to this Agency’s vehicles viz. Austin &amp; Humber cars and separate invoices for products supplied to the private cars of the officers of this Agency. V\ for Political A gent, Bahrain.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited OUTSTANDING ACCOUNTS T~LE t089.1 Dear Sir, In checking through your account we find that our billing L-ll-169 of 30th November, 1949, has remained outstanding, whereas payment for subsequent billing has been received. Assuming that the subject invoice has either not reached you or escaped your attention, we are attaching hereto a copy for your reference, and would appreciate receiving a cheque in settlement at your early convenience. Yours very truly, R. M. BROUN CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Attach:69/31/50 COPY BRITISH RESIDENCY, BAHRiilN. 19th April, 1950. Dear Department, Will you please refer to your letter XC051/ 91K1/450 of the 3rd April, about rates charged for the private use of official transport. 2. We had always understood that the reduced rate of 3 annas per kilometre had been authorised solely because the Residency is situated 4 miles distance from the town while the Agency is a few minutes walk from the shops (see Sir Rupert Hay's letter to Gardiner D. 0. 605-30/20 of 2nd March, 1948, and your letter XA051/34K29C17/48) of 23rd August, 1948). However, we agree that the position is some what anomalous, and are instructing the Agency to charge at the reduced rate with effect from 1st [ April. They inform us they will not be able to apply this measure retrospectively. 3 . We did not understand from Mr. Fisher's letter X051/34K2A(30/48) of the 8th December, 1948, to which you refer, that we were supposed to treat all transport as one pool: as we read it,'this letter dealt only with the P.R.0. truck. The Residency and Agency here are completely separate establishments, and hitherto the Agency, like other Agencies in the Gulf, has corresponded direct with the Foreign Office on questions of supplies and stores 4. We are sending a copy of this letter, and your letter to which it refers to the Political Agency Bahrain. Yours ever, Residency. Conference &amp; Supply Department, The Foreign Office, L ondon, S.W.l.COPY (XC051/91K1/450) Unclassified. FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l 3rd April, 1950. Dear residency,. We have received a letter from the Political Agency asking whether they may use official transport . for non-official purposes at the reduced rate author ised for you in didley's letter to you of the 10th June (XA051/34K2A ( 8 / 49 ). The answer of course is, yes. We must repeat the request made in the last paragraph of Fisher’s letter Xa051/34K2a(30/48) of the 8th December, 1948, and point out that from our point of view Bahrain is one post, and not divided into 'Residency H and 'Agency'. Your transport is run as one pool in our eyes, (How you may allocate vehicles locally for convenience is your own affair) ana regulations laid down for running it apply equally to all Foreign Office vehicles on the island. We deprecate very strongly that the Agency has been paying at a higher rate than yourselves for recreational transport for the past six months and more, and if it is possible to adjust this retrospectively we hope this will be done. Yours ever CONFERENCE AND SUPPLY DEPARTMENT The Residency, Bahrain.wl ■u~&gt; M) (XA053/91K1/1450) UNCLjiSSIFIBD i %P ,vn FOREIGN OFFICE, S. V/.l. 11th Uay, 1950. %^ n ' t Dear Agency, We have received the Inspector’s repor and are surprised to find you in possession, ntvt Super Snipe, but also of a small general- make, of which we do not seem to have hcsTrd on your transport, only of the Humber ose vehicle of unspecified before, It is extremely difficult for us to deal with your transport needs as distinct from those of the Residency, and in our eyes all Bahrain official cars other then the Political Resident’s own Pullman, should be regarded as one pool. In this connexion we quote to you part of the text of our letter to the Residency of the }rd April. 'We must repeat the request made in the last paragraph of Fisher’s letter of the 8th December 1948 and point out that, from our point of view, Bahrain is one post and not divided into 'Residency' and 'Agency'. Your transport is run as one pool in our eyes, (how you allocate vehicles locally for convenience is your own affair) and regulations laid down for running it apply equally to all Foreign Office vehicles on the island'. This being so, we expect the Residency to submit biannual reports on the condition of your vehicles as well as its own, and to include the cost of running yours in its costing reports. For our part, we must obtain authority for the addition of your two vehicles to the post’s transport establishment.of one saloon, one station-wagon, and one truck used by the Residency. To help us to do this we should be glad if you would send us full particulars of the small second vehicle, as well as confirmation that your Humber Super Snipe is the one with chassis number 873018? for which we have received one mechanical report dated 21st January 1949. Please send new reports for both vehicles, together with figures showing the mileage which each has travelled on (a) official business and (b) non-official, during the past six months. We should also like an account of the uses to which the vehicles are put. We are sending a copy of this letter for the Residency and should be glad if, for the sake of simplicity, you would submit all correspondence about transport through them in future. Yours ever, CONFERENCE AND SUPPLY DEPARTMENT British political Agency, Bahrain.No. [Qbb Political /gency, Bahrain, 11th June, 1950. Dear Sirs, X ^ I thought you might be interested to hear that on a recent official tour from Sharjah on the Trucial Coast I used two Land Rovers for long distances over desert country, sand, salt marsh and the like. I was tremendously struck by the reliability of these vehicles and their ability to go anywhere with heavy loads without . faytltering. You may make any use you wish of this tribute. &lt; H.B.M 1 ! Agent. Messrs. The Rover Company Ltd., Solihull, Birmingham, England. Your i ~No.R- 2?^ -17/28 Political Agency, Bahrain. 28th June i960 Dear Residency, Please refer to/Conference and Supply Department’s letter N0^053/91X1/1450 dated the 11th May 1950. We are replying to the points raised therein through you as the letter asked us to submit all correspondence about transport through you in future. dated the 19th April 1950, a copy of which was received with your complimentary slip No.69/31/50 of 19th April, had cleared up the point made re garding the treatment of your and our transport being regarded as belonging to one pool, but we note that for the Conference and Supply Depart ment's purposes this should be done so in future. the 28th March 1948, it was requested that the Foreign Office should be asked to take this Agency cars in charge including the Austin 16 h.p. shoot ing brake which is the 'general-purpose vehicle of unspecified make' referred to by the Conference and Supply Department. We do not of course know whether the Department was in fact asked by you to take this vehicle on charge. Its particulars are enclosed on a separate sheet. 4. Our Humber Snipe's chassis number is 8730377. 5. We enclose reports for both the Humber and the Austin. 6. The Humber has travelled 2086 miles during the last six months, all of them on official business. The Austin has travelled 3080 miles on official business and 565 miles on non-official business (the Austin records are kept in Kilometers which its speedometer records. They have been converted at 8 kilometers for five miles). 7. The Humber is used for journeys to the Residency on official business, calls on His Majesty's Ships, on His Highness the Ruler of Bahraih, members of the Ruling Family and other Shaikhs, occasional business visits to oil companies, meeting official visitors, travelling to and from the aerodrome when proceeding on or returning from tours. Apart from these uses by the Political Agent The Perrian Gulf Residency, We thought that your letter No.69/31/50 ^ 3. 5. 5&gt; &lt;7/^-9 In Agency memorandum No.977-17/28 dated Bahrain.it is occasionally placed at the disposal of important visitors, the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, and the Political Officer, Qatar, when they visit Bahrain on official business. The Austin is used for official use by clerks, living at a distance of one mile or more from the office, for attending the office daily, by clerks required for urgent ^»ork after the office hours, for receiving and seeing off official guests, urgent messages to the Residency, R.A.F., and International Aeradio and the Bahrain Petroleum Company, and for delivery and collection of mails to and from Sharjah through the R.A.F., for collection of official bags, packages etc. from the Post Office, Shipping Companies, and Airways Office. The Austin is used for non-official purposes by officers and clerks for which they pay monthly. Yours ever, Agency/ (XA 051) Revised Form © SIX-HONiHLY REPORT ON OFFICIAL MOTOR VRHICLRS. ( f t H Ay If $oj % J HIS MAJESTY'S FOREIGN SERVICE. ct-aslf! Address To: The Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, The Foreign Office, London. Cost of Overhaul (including parts) L o;8 -7 -« Description of Vehicle. .. % t^kiu. Wi Year, . Registered No .h ..... JA i/.8 Type or Series. .. Chassis No, . Engine No..... .*^. A6. Cars and Station, Wagons - Seating Capacity.Q Tx^ieiwa Capacity. '. Number of tyres on Vehicles and size. rrr. | Speedometer reading.. .^VVv &lt;^7. v — v d c&gt; ^ h S ** * J / / -j Average Weekly mileage on all business during past six months. .* Petrol Consumption..... f ...../. m.p.g. f Oil Consumption. • .%VM ^.Ar-liA^. Ku^i-rg-. v CONDITION REPORT The following have been inspected. Repairs have been effected as stated. Engine (H©- Comment ^ Fan /cl U Comment ^ Clutch/Fluid Flywheel (y\£^ Comment * * Universal Joints 0-^2-*. Comment • ' Gear Box Comment Brakes Comsient Rear Axle Comment Steering Box Comment Transmission Comment Front Axle Comment Front/Rear Springs: Shackles Comment ' • Electrical Comment (OVERPetrol Tank Comment Tyres and Equipment Comment Body - General Condition A' V Comment v v General Remarks and Recommendations Comment c*- J t' I I ‘ i, : i J C s The Vehicle is/completely roadworthy* It 'is 'likely td give good ‘Service fdr a further period of V . , ^ ? Signature of Agent or Garage Manager Counter Signature of Head of Post (or a responsible member of the Foreign Service deputed to sign on his be&amp;alf)UNCLASSIFIED 69 / 62/30 f| v f W BRITISH RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN • 3rd August, 1930. Dear Agency, Please refer to the attached copy of a letter to Gray, Mackenzie. 2. All official transport is in future to be insured in London. We must accordingly send full details, e.g. make, year, h.p., seating, chassis and engine Nos., of all cars to be insured, to reach London by the end of the month. 3 . Please let us have details -of your official transport, urgently, for inclusion in our report. Yours ever, The political Agency, BAHRAIN.BRITISH RaiSIDiMOY* BAHRAIK. ( 69 / 61 / 50 ) 3rd August, 1950. Sir, ( z Please rex'er to your letter 'HJ of iiarch 6th, and to the Motor Union Insurance Policies !&lt;os. 223060 and ^&gt;46139, covering our Ford and number cars, and Austin Austin Station Wagon and L’ruck, 2. I have been informed by His Majesty 1 s Foixiign Office that in future all official cars will be insured by the Foreign Office in dondon* I a therefore, instructed to request you to inform me of the terms on which you are prepared to terminate these policies but not that on the Chevrolet, on October 1st, and wluit refund, if any, will be payable. I should be glad to have the same information also in respect of the off icial cars of the Political Agency which I understand are insured with you. 3. I ai required to send this information, to reach H.tf , 8 Foreign Office by August 31ot» and should be glad accordingly of an early reply. Yours faithfully. Administration Officer. Phe Manager, Messrs. Gray, Madeemsie &amp; Co. Ltd. 9 BAHRAIN.No. -17/27 * 28 Political Agency* Bahrain* 9th August*1950 Dear Residency, Please refer to your letter No # 69/62/50 of 3rd August, 1950« 2* The following are the particulars called for therein in respect of the two Official cars of this Agency:* 1. AUSTIN LiTAXI0N*WAG0N * Make Austin Station-Wagon . (Shooting Brake) Year 1948 H.P. 16 H.P* Seating Six Seater Chasls No* \ 10424 0 Engine No* IB 16215 HUMBER SUPER SN1PU SALOON* Make Humber Super Snipe Year 194? H.P* 27 Seating Five Seater Chasls No* 8730377 Engine No* 8730377 The Residency* Persian Gulf* Bahrain* Yours everTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i, BAHREIN tetXXH. PERSIAN GULF. PA-303. His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, The Agency, X Manama, Bahrein. OUTSTANDING ACCOUNTS . File #089.-1. Dear Sir, For your information we are tabulating below the status of the ' Agency Vehicles' account as of 30th June, 1950, for which we would appreciate receiving a cheque at your convenience : Invoice No, Particulars. Amount (1950) L 1-103 L 2- 99 L 3-188 L 4- 86 L5 -137 L 6—149 Petroleum products supplied during January, 1950. February, March, April, -May, June, Rs. 7 5— 0— 0 97-Ur- 0 43- 5- 0 41 - 11 - 0 39- 1- 9 .- 17 / 27 . Political Agency, Bahrain, 12th September, 1950, No Sir, It is regretted that there has/been delay in replying to your letter of the 27tn July (PA-303). This has been due in great measure to the difficulty I have experienced in reconciling vour invoices with the vouchers (your form BP-97-Rev.) this Agency hands over to the Manama Service Station when obtaining supplies. These vouchers do not accompany your invoices in support of them. Please arrange for this to be done in future. 2. I enclose herewith two cheques for Rs. 192-8-0 and Rs. 15-2-0 to cover the payment of your following invoices:- AGENCY VEHICLES: L-3-188 for March L-4-86 for April L-5-137 for May L-6-149 for June L-7-140 for July V.M. HOSPITAL BILLS: L-3-112 for March L-5-139 for May L-7-138 for July Rs.31- 6- 0 ' 43- 5- 0 ' 41-11- 0 H 39- 1- 0 » 37- 1- 0 Rs. 192- 8- 0 Rs. tt 9-12- 0 1 - 10 - 0 3-12- 0 15- 2- 0 Please let me have your official receipt in duplicate. 3. Your invoices for the months of January and February do not appear to have been received. Please be good enough to send duplicate invoices supported, if possible, by vouchers. Payment will then be made. 4. Settlement of your Invoices for supply to private cars belonging to members of the staff of this Agency will be made shortly. In future please bill direct to such persons and not through the Agency. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, J.E.Hartley, ^ for Political Agent. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Co.Ltd., Bahrain. r37433—5 A s UNCLASSIFIED 69/7^/50 The Political Agency, Bahrain. WITH THE COMPLIMENT OF » HIS MAJESTY’S POLITICAL RESIDENCY With ./reference to P.0, letter No. XC051/91K1/2350 of 26th July to us, which was copied to you.4 'It ( 69 / 76 / 50 ) UNCLASSIFIilD BRITISH RESIDiiNCY t BAHRAIN• 18 th Septeuiber, 1930* Dear Conference and Supply Department, Please refer to your letter No.XC051/9HC1/2350 of 26th July, about the Agency transport. 2. Wc h^ve drawn the Agency's atteixtion to the last paragraph of your letter. But we would liice to /v-r^ • , point out that the rate which we have been charging / hx**^'**' throughout,on the authority of your XA051/34&amp;2A/8/49 of the 10th June, 1945 1 is throe annas a kilocaetre ai.d not three annas a mile as now mentioned by you. This works out to about 5d. a uiile, and was based on the proposal that the rate should be applied to all journeys within Bahrain and not only to those between Manama and Jufair. We should be grateful therefore, if you would permit us uG continue tuia all-round rate, as amenities in ^ahauin are few and certain members of our staff are given the privilege of membership of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Club at Awali, which is 14 miles from Manama and slightly more from Jufair. The Contract Staff also use transport to go to the R.A.F. Cinema at Muharraq, v/hich is approx imately 7 miles from Jufair. There are no other amenities for them and they could not possibly afford to hire off icial transport at a shilling a t .CLle, as this* would be even more expensive than the local taxis, which themselves arc beyond their moons. The journeys between Jufair and Manama are made for essential shopping and not in reality for recreation, as no recreational facilities are provided there. Yours ever. RESIDENCY. Conference and Supply Department, The Foreign Office, London.Ho. - 17 / 27 . Political Agency, Bahrain, 30th September, 1950 Dear Residency, Please refer to your/comoxirnentary slip of September 18th (69/76/50;# 2. We do not seem to have received a cooy either of Foreign Office letter of July 26th (XCoS 1/91X1/2350) or of their XA051/34K2A/8/49 of June 10th referred to by you# Please could ne have copies# 3. We similarly charge at the rate o three annas per kilometre for private use of official transport# Yours ever. Bahrain Agency# The Residency, Persian Gulf, Bahrain#IS* No.3178 poiicioai Agency, Bahrain, 22nd Oct. 1950. Sir, Wich reference to the annual registration of motor vehicles, the en closed list shows the official cars of this Agency and the private cars owned by members of its staff as on the 13th October, 1950. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd.) J.E. Hartley for Political Agent The Superintendent, State Police, Bahrain.t CIRCULAR No. 67 [ XC 051/6450 ] Foreign Office, 26th September, 1950. Use of Official Transport Dear Consulate (-General), One of His Majesty’s posts abroad has recently asked tor an official interpretation of the word “ normally ” as used in para graph 26 of Chapter 29 of the Foreign Service Regulations, part of which reads: “ An officer of car-owning grade will not normally make any call on official transport for his personal use. He is moreover expected to use his private car when he needs transport for his official duties.” The discussion on this matter in the Foreign Office has produced -*he following views and opinions which it is felt may be helpful -io staff at posts abroad. In the first place it is the considered opinion that any officer of car-owning grade who prefers not to own a private car, despite the fact that he has a private car element in his allowances, shall not have any lien on any car in the official pool. Also it has been noted that there is an all too prevalent practice of earmarking official cars for specific times and journeys, e. ( g., to and from lunch. This should not be allowed. Officers of car-owning grades are expected to use their own cars for all official journeys outside of office hours, but, within office hours it is felt that anyone who has official business to do is entitled to use official transport if the use of his private car is inconvenient. As an example of what is meant, we would not expect staff in busy capitals such as Paris or Rome to take their private cars and fight their way through streets and then perhaps waste valuable time in searching for parking space, when an official car with a driver could run them round quickly, drop them, and return to the Mission to await a call to bring them back. We realise too, that wives of senior officers very often have jobs to do in “ office hours,” and we do not insist that an officer should — se his car for official purposes at a time when it is essential that Pis wife should have it for representational or family duties. In effect the regulations stand, and nothing we have now said makes any alteration to the rule that an officer may not charge for the use of his private car on short runs within the local ten mile limit; but, we appreciate the varying circumstances at different posts. What we expect is that the spirit of the regulations will be observed, and that we can assume that officers will not abuse the use of official transport. Additional copies of this circular are enclosed for distribution to Consular Officers under your superintendence. A similar circular has been addressed to Chanceries (as No. 0110). Yours ever, Conference and Supply Dept. His Majesty’s Consulates (-General) 16392 39266—28Xt - 3 SSj CIRCULAR No. 67 XC 051/6450 ] Foreign Office, 2bth September, 1950. Use of Official Transport Dear Consulate (-General), One of His Majesty’s posts abroad has recently asked for an official interpretation of the word “ normally ” as used in para graph 26 of Chapter 29 of the Foreign Service Regulations, part of which reads: “ An officer of car-owning grade will not normally make any call on official transport for his personal use. He is moreover expected to use his private car when he needs transport for his official duties.” The discussion on this matter in the Foreign Office has produced ' he following views and opinions which it is felt may be helpful ~to staff at posts abroad. In the first place it is the considered opinion that any officer of car-owning grade who prefers not to own a private car, despite the fact that he has a private car element in his allowances, shall not have any lien on any car in the official pool. Also it has been noted that there is an all too prevalent practice of earmarking official cars for specilic times and journeys, e.g., to and from lunch. This should not be allowed. Officers of car-owning grades are expected to use their own cars for all official journeys outside of office hours, but, within office hours it is felt that anyone who has official business to do is entitled to use official transport if the use of his private car is inconvenient. As an example of what is meant, we would not expect staff in busy capitals such as Paris or Rome to take their private cars and fight their way through streets and then perhaps waste valuable time in searching for parking space, when an official car with a driver could run them round quickly, drop them, and return to the Mission to await a call to bring them back. We realise too, that wives of senior officers very often have jobs to do in “ office hours,” and we do not insist that an officer should —4se his car for official purposes at a time when it is essential that his wife should have it for representational or family duties. In effect the regulations stand, and nothing we have now said makes any alteration to the rule that an officer may not charge for the use of his private car on short runs within the local ten mile limit; but, we appreciate the varying circumstances at different posts. What we expect is that the spirit of the regulations will be observed, and that we can assume that officers will not abuse the use of official transport. Additional copies of this circular are enclosed for distribution to Consular Officers under your superintendence. A similar circular has been addressed to Chanceries (as No. 0110). Yours ever. Conference and Supply Dept. His Majesty’s Consulates (-General) 16392 39266—28/ CIRCULAR No. 67 [ XC 051/6450 ] Foreign Office, 26th September, 1950. Use of Official Transport Dear Consulate (-General), One of His Majesty’s posts abroad has recently asked for an official interpretation of the word “ normally ” as used in para graph 26 of Chapter 29 of the Foreign Service Regulations, part of which reads: “ An officer of car-owning grade will not normally make any call on official transport for his personal use. He is moreover expected to use his private car when he needs transport for his official duties.” The discussion on this matter in the Foreign Office has produced 'fie following views and opinions which it is felt may be helpful to staff at posts abroad. In the first place it is the considered opinion that any officer of car-owning grade who prefers not to own a private car, despite the fact that he has a private car element in his allowances, shall not have any lien on any car in the official pool. Also it has been noted that there is an all too prevalent practice of earmarking official cars for specific times and journeys, e.g., to and from lunch. This should not be allowed. Officers of car-owning grades are expected to use their own cars for all official journeys outside of office hours, but, within office hours it is felt that anyone who has official business to do is entitled to use official transport if the use of his private car is inconvenient. As an example of what is meant, we would not expect staff in busy capitals such as Paris or Rome to take their private cars and fight their way through streets and then perhaps waste valuable time in searching for parking space, when an official car with a driver could run them round quickly, drop them, and return to the Mission to await a call to bring them back. We realise too, that wives of senior officers very often have jobs to do in “ office hours,” and we do not insist that an officer should /■itse his car for official purposes at a time when it is essential that nis wife should have it for representational or family duties. In effect the regulations stand, and nothing we have now said makes any alteration to the rule that an officer may not charge for the use of his private car on short runs within the local ten mile limit; but, we appreciate the varying circumstances at different posts. What we expect is that the spirit of the regulations will be observed, and that we can assume that officers will not abuse the use of official transport. Additional copies of this circular are enclosed for distribution to Consular Officers under your superintendence. A similar circular has been addressed to Chanceries (as No. 0110). Yours ever. Conference and Supply Dept. His Majesty’s Consulates (-General) 16392 39266—28COPY $ FOREIGN OFFICE, S.V/.l. XC051/91K1/2950 3rd October, 1950, UNCLASSIFIED Dear Residency, Thank you for your letter 69/76/50 of 18th September - about transport rates. We apologise for the error in our letter of 26th July; we should, of course, have said three annas a kilometre , not three annas a mile. journeys only. 1. Trips to and from the Club at Awali* 2. Visits to the R.A.F/ Cinema. 3. Journeys between ivianctma ana ouiurr as heretofore. cheap rate, but it seems that these journeys will cover most 4 recreational use. Home-office transport should continue at an equivalent of Id. per mile per head, ana all tnese —— ^-'privileges spply, naturally, to both nesiaency and Agency. I No doubt you will inform the latter of the contents of this * letter. 2 . e can approve this rate for the following speciired a. .&lt;e cannot unfortunately give indiscriminate approval of all use of official transport for private p.urposes at the Yours ever, CONFERENCE AND SUPPLY DEPARTMENT. The Political Residency, Bahrain.0NCLASSIFIED 69/3675o“' BAHRAIN. WITH THE COMPLIMENTS OF HIS MAJESTY’S POLITICAL RESIDENCY With reference to your letter No. r- 396-17/27 of 30th September, 1950. BRITISH RESIDENCY, 17th October, 1950. BAHREIN, PERSIAN GULF. 37433—5m\ ■ (XCI^51/91Kl/2350) UI'fCLASSIPIBD -/ Dear Residency, Thank you for your printed letter 69/49/50 of 10th July passing on to us a letter from the Agency about their transport. We enclose some blank forms of the new type of transport returns. We should be glad if you would see that the Agency received them so that next time they submit returns (with yours at the proper half-yearly time) we shall have up- to-date accounts of each vehicle. The report on the Austin was not attached when we received the letter although the report on the Humber was safely received. It appears from the contents of the letter that home-to-office transport is provided free of charge in official vehicles to certain members of staff. Please draw the Agency’s attention to the standard rate of a penny per person per mile for home-office journeys and also to the(X^1/34K2A( 8/14-9)) COPY FOREIGN OFFICE, S.V/.l. 10th June, 1949. Dear Sir Rupert, As transport laatters are now the concern of Conference and Supply Department, I am replying to your letter 94/17/49 of the 10th Llay to Gardener about the charge of 3 annas a kilometre for the use of official cars for private purposes. Your original request of the 2nd March, 1948 for the application of this rate was approved and we wrote to you accordingly in our letter XA051/34h2A( 17/48) of the 23rd August last year. ,/e have since been told that in special cases, such as this one, where an application has been made and approved for a rate below the official one, the authority remains effective and is not altered by the terms of Foreign Office circular No.027 raising the standard charge from 6d. to 1/- a mile. It is therefore in order for you to continue to charge only 3 annas a kilometre as before. Yours ever, Sgd./ YY.Y/• Ridley. Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., BAHRAIN2-' NOV 1950 ' s e P tei nb er &gt; 1950 (vs) Dear Political Agency, v&gt; — Official Transport: Vehicle Log Books and Records * It has been realised for some time now that there exists a need for a standardized form of vehicle log book for the use of those Posts abroad which run official transport. A cross section of major Missions who have contributed their own observations and suggestions has enabled two books to be prepared; a copy of each is sent herewith. The old log books will be discontinued”. 2. The primary purpose of any log book is to produce in a convenient form a consolidated record of the mechanical history of each vehicle, with its mileage and fuel comsumption. This information is necessary in order to enable the transport officer to see at a glance whether the vehicle is up to standard, to supply information for the various transport returns, and to support any application for renewal. The small log book No. C.S.5 (buff) is designed to meet these needs exactly. The record of the mileage and fuel consumption should be a daily entry to bo added up monthly, on each page. The book is intended to last the life of the vehicle and to accoi.pany it on transfer. No provision is made here, however, for a record of those details of journeys without which the administration Officer cannot quickly satisfy himself that transport ia being properly and fully employed. Such a‘record of journeys will also be necessary for the control of private use of transport and for the recovery of charges in connexion therewith. Complementary to this . log book, therefore, Posts will require a separate journey record which we think they will find more convenient to prepare themselves in the local language on the lines of the record to be seen in log book No. C.S.3. 3* The larger log book No. C. 0,3 (blue) is designed to meet the requirements of those Missions or Consular Posts whose transport is limited inmmbors and whose journeys are not sufficiently numerous or varied in character to need the more elaborate system of separate records. Here the detailed record of journeys is incorporated in the log book and the mileage and fuel consumption figures are added up at the foot of each page and carried forward in convenient periods, i.e., weekly or monthly. 4* We hope that the production of these log books will not only save Posts time and trouble, but will also help towards greater efficiency. Will you please consider carefully which of those two books is best suited to your particular circumstances and enter your requirement in Part III of the Annual Stationery demand? Will you please return the discarded book for re-issue elsewhere?, A British Residency, Bahrain. 10th* ITo^mber, 1950 (69/92/50) ^ear Agency, &amp; T *7ill/you please refer to your letter ITo- B. 333-17/27 d 23 of 9th August about the insurance of official cars. / A 2. We enclose a copy of Foreign Office Circular ITo. 086 of 21st July which was the cau c ^ ^ 011 ^ receive. We also enclose for your in y of our reply to the Foreign Office ITo. 69/68/50 of the 25th August, in which we listed the cars in the Bahrain pool for which global insurance was required. '. T e have now received a further letter from Conference and Supply Department I T o. (XC 056/1450) of 34th October, of which we enclose a copy, and on which we presume you will take the action required through us in the* case of any of the eventualities mentioned. 3. You vail notice that there have'been certain omissions in the list forwarded to the Foreign Office in respect of the official cars in Qatar and the Trucial Coast. As these are not included in the Bahrain car pool we consider it will be better, provided you have no objection, for you to forward these details direct to Conference and Supply Department at the earliest possible opportunity. V/e will inform Conference and Supply Department in our reply that certain further details will be forthcoming. 4. V/e observe that no mention has been made of insurance for launches. T, !e are making enquiries about the present policy of the Foreign Office in Hi is respect, but in the meant lie we would be glad to know if your launch is insured, and if so, whether for third party risks only. Vm n r» o Qtrar* The Political Agency, Bahrain.(XC 055/450) CIRCULAR Uo. D 86 Foreign Office, 21 st July, 1950 btsuraitch: of official auis Sir Uith reference to official circular ITo. 0203 of 14th December, 1S47, it has been decided that, from 1st October, 1250, all official vehicles which are to be insured ggainst third party risks shall be covered by one global policy which will be effected in London. Detailed instructions of the operation of the scheme will be sent to you in due course. 2. The following particulars should therefore be submitted to Conference and Supply Department without fail by 1st September, 1950:- (a) Complete identification of every vehicle in your territory to be covered by the policy on 1st October, i.e., make, year of manufacture, horse-power, seating or carrying capacity, chassis and engine numbers, local registered number. (b) Name of Government Department owning the vehicle where this is different from the Foreign Office. 3. In those cases where the vehicles are at present insured locally, steps should be taken to terminate the policy on 1st October and to claim a rebate for the unexpired period of the policy. If no rebate can be obtained the insurance should be allowed to run out, and you should report, also by 1 st September, the date on which such vehicles will cease to be insured locally so that they may be incorporated in the London policy at the appropriate time. 4. The cost under the new scheme will be a flat rate of £ 10 per vehicle per annum. In the case of non-Foreign Office vehicles, refunds will not be repayable locally, as hitherto, but will be collected in London^ 5. Heads of Hiss ion cars which are run on the new basis, whereby their cost of upkeep is met direct from public funds and not from frais, will be insured against third-party risks only, under the global policy, and should be included in lists submitted. Local comprehensive policies should be cancelled as described in paragraph 3. Gradually all Heads of Mission cars will be brought into the new scheme and comprehensive insurance will cease to exist. This circular therefore supersedes circular despatch Ho* 0109 of 10 th June, 1947. 6 . This circular is also being addressed to Consular Officers outside the metropolitan territory of the Government to which you are accredited, and to Consular Officers who have no Superintending Mission, if they have official cars. '.here there is more than one such Consular Post in the same territory the senior officer should submit particulars of all official vehicles in that territory. 7. These instructions do not apply to posts in countries vhere there is a Tar Office Claims Commission. I am, with great truth and regard Sir, Your obedient Servant, K.G. YOUNGER.( 69 / 68 /-)) BRITISH KSSlDlSI^CYf BAlBiAIH. 26th August, 191&gt;0* Door Departoent, Please refer to Circular no .066 of July 21st about Insurance of official transport* Official cars in our territory are:- R}&amp;Il)KnCY; {lake Type Year HJP. Oapaolty Chaeoie UnclXMJ 1.BEDFORD Lorry 1949 29 2 ooater, 13 owt. ) KD.126259 JCtl. 138724 - R. 587 2^0D0E —do— 1944 35 2 seater) 19 ewt. ) 2115798 T.222-33436&lt;^ R. 722 3 •HUMBKH Pullman 1949 28 7 8731087 6731087 R. 1 O 30 4 (FORD V.8 Pilot 1950 30 5 7227704 7227704 R.1366 5.FORD (U.S.A 1 .) Sedan 1946 35 5 971756 59A—8 R. 767 6.AUSTIN Vnn 1947 AOKI.'OY: 10 6 283753 I/; .298779 R. 463 | ^ Super- Snip© Saloon 1947 27 5 8730377 8730377 8.AUSTIN Station Wagon 1948 16 6 10424 IB 16215 A. 476 Of these oars, llos* 2,3,9 and 6 are insured with t io local agents for Hotor Union Insurance Co* These polioies oaspire on Rove Jber 3rd, 1990, and as they are so close to expiry date we are Inforuied that no refund can be given* nos*1,4,7 und 0, due to errors on our port, are not insured at all* As it is now so close to the coauenceraent of the global policy, we ou w .cot that it would be better not to Insure the^e cars locally at this stage* We are advised by the local agents that ooie reduction of praiiuia is due on future policies, for the oars already insured, for w no claluis bonus* clauses* If you require the policies for that purpose please let us know* 2* A.s regards Ho *2, the Dodge Lorry, a. id Ho*9 the Ford Kedan, these are the property of the Oovemiiont of India and their disposal is under consideration. They have been re- Laced by the Bedford Lorry(Ho*l) and the Ford Pilot Saloon No*h) and it is not therefore considered necessary to reinsure theca* l 3. The Austin van(!, f o*6) is in suoh a dilapidated state that we feel that it 9 s Insurance would be a waste of uioney* Yours ever, IdiBlDKHCY* •&lt; /PO ; JGN OFPICB, S.W.l. (XC03t, 1450) 24th October, 1950. gHClAiiSIPIelD Dear Heoidency, Inaurance of official caro» 1 lease refer to Circular JEo. 066 of 21et July, 1950, concerning inaurance of official vehicles against third—party risks, by iueana of a single global policy in London* 2* Any i^otor-accidente or incidents involving your official trans port which are liable to have repercussions leading to a claiia by a third party should be reported at once to the local agent of the Caleuonian Insurance Conqpany who sho Id of course be furnished with ^ all information and documents concerning the case* Your local agent is:- Oray,Mackenzie A Co*, Ltd*, BAHRAIN* ! J e is fully informed of his liability towards you and of the terms of the policy* Any advice or guidance concerning it that you require, he will be able to give you* 3* Additions and deletions of vehicles to the policy should be reported to us by air—bag on the day of the vehicle's coming in or going out of use* unangea of vehicles at consular posts should be reported direct to us, with a copy of the letter to you. deports of accidents to consular vehicles should be made to the agent through you, except in those cases where a considerable amount of time will be saved by the consular post reporting direct to the agent(e.g* the agent in Israel lives in Haifa; Haifa therefore reports direct and not through Tel Aviv*) We also want to know about all accidents which -lay occur, of course, and about all claims which are hiade under the policy* 4« Please make sure that the consular posts in your territory are informed of these instructions* Yours ever, CONyKHKNOK Aid) SUPPLY DfiPARTliSHT. Hie Majesty's Political Hesi ency, Bahrain*I /H 6 / 2o/ I have to report that this evening when returning from Adari the Agency V^uxhall car narrowly escaped running into another vehicle but fcunped it and suffered damage. The car had just passed the Manama V/ehtern School (a Bahrain Government school for boys) when a truck suddenly backed out on to the road from a smaller road to our left without sounding its horn or giving any other signal or '^ferning,'being*hidden from sight until the moment of its emergence by the wall of a building. The car driver swerved violently across to^right to escape running^.t but in getting past he bumped the truck and damaged the le. t rear mudguard of the car. I stopped the car and got out and spoke to the trucK driver but he adopted a truculent manner, insisted it was our fault, and that we should have - S^ en his truck, etc. I - therefore asked the car driver to take the number of the truck and we got into the car and drove off. The truck, which was much the sturdier vehicle,drove off a little before we did and seemed to have suffered no damage. I looked a t the clock when we got back into the car and it showed three minutes past 5.30 o’ clock. The whole incident could not have lasted more than a minute to a minute and a half from the time the truck backed out on to us to the time I got back into the car. The car was travelling at about 15 m.p.h. at the time of the accident. A.P.A. J 30.1C. '46, ^ k? fth'- ■ P 'h‘ J ki&lt;:'The driver informs me that he needs a cycle to travel to 4 and from the Agency especially when he is needed urgently or the intermission periods betvfeen trips are short, Sa^d Amin was given a cycle by the Agency for this purpose, and I lent the last driver my own cycle, I woulde be Willing to sell this cycle for Rs. 25/- and if A.P.A. agrees it may be bought for the diiver and the money paid fax tha from the transport fund. Intld. J.A.N.E. 8 / 12 . A.P.A . Let me see the'cycle pi. Intld. H.D.H.R. 8 / 12 . C.C H/W,Any damage noticed has been inflicted by last driver Intld. J.A.N.E. 8/12 Approved. Intld. H.D.H.R. 8/12 Received Rs. 25/- only. Intld. J.A.NXE. 10/12 ‘ I have to report that the flagstick of the Vauxhall was » wrenched off the car by one of a party of drunken sailors who were returning to H.M.S. Challenger on the night of 25/1PA6, when the car was parked outside one of the Residency blocks. Intld. J.A.N^. 6/1 A .P.A . PI. have it repaired and replaced. I don*t think, \ in view of the date of the occurance, any further action need be taken. Intld. H.D.H.R. 6/1 Intld. J.A.N.E. 7/1I find it extremely difficult to engage or retain a driver for the Vauxhall because of the number of commissions he is called upon to carry out both during and after office hours. In view of this and in the light of other experience gained during the time I have managed the car I suggest the following : Y* N K h' ~ • ' (3*1 ( 4 .) bM oXX 6t&gt; • That the car and truck drivers should receive the same amount in wages. That only one of these two drivers should be on duty after office hours on any one day, and that he should drive the car or the truck, as preferred or as circumstances necessitate. This would have the advantage that only one driver would be on duty on a Friday, and he would get the following Friday off. That a special tariff of Re. 1 should be levied for every .journey made by the car/truck after S p.m. on any evening, to be paid by the occupants, and to be in addition to the usual charge on mileage covered. This could be paid to the driver concerned at the end of the month and would do much to alleviate the dissatis faction felt at present wh n a driver is kept out late of an evening. That Rule 7(a) of the Car Rules should now be altered so that the charge of 4 as. per mile for- a private booking of the whole car should only be allowed where the occupantsof the car/truclf ape a clerk's wife and children. The rate of 2/lJ- as. should be paid for every other person who occupies the car/truck. That both the car and the truck should be under the same charge. Supdt. and C.C. could alternate as Clerk in Charge for ar month at a time. That Rule 5 of the Car Rules should be more strictly observed than it hap been. It may however be amended as follows:- “The Clerk in Charge of Transport should be given notice of a private booking not later than * , 11.30 a.m. on week days, and before that time on Thursday for a private booking on Friday. That both the car and the truck should carry a log book as per specimen page attached. I have two candidates in view for driver and would be gfateful for A.P.A's comments on these proposals before I seek to engage one. Id/- J.A.N.C. A.P.A. For Comments pi.* 6.2.47 H.D.H.R. 6/2 b 1 Para 1 I agree Para 2 It is destiable that^the car or the truck should be handled bes one person so that he is made entirely responsible for the vehicle in his charge; instances therefore of the driver of one vehicle being made to drive the other should be kept to the minimum and should, preferably, be allowed only in the case of the truck which will be required on all Fridays to fco to the NAAFI. Para 3 I agree. Para 4 I 'do not think that the present rates need any revision At any rate I suggest that this question be deferred until the 1 st April when we will have a clearer idea of the cost of the maintenance of the truck.ii. Para 5 Para 6 Para 7 I agree. In fact I consider that the Sup^dt. should be in charge of the vehicle-s at all times. I I agree. I agree. Para 8 I agree. I further suggest that the car accounts, together with the debit notes, should be submitted not later than the 10th of each month, and that the clerk who maintains the car account should be given an honorarium of Rs. 15/- per month. ir* , i J_ Ct_. ^ I y 9 9 I O II IS h £ y . L *~l €x^y °\/ ir u &gt; • w 2_ Ref. n/pafas l(3) and 5. It is not clear whether the truck and the car are to be used on alternate days or whether the drivers are to have alternate evenings and Fridays off. In exceptional circumstances both truck and car may have to be used of an evening but it is suggested that Supdt should draw up a schedule covering these points. Ref. n/paras 12 and 13. I presume this will be paid with retrospective.effect to Mr. Sahadevan. j*™ .P.A. _ . . 15/2/47. /IS’- yj . » / &lt;si/i * ^ ^ ^ ^ P f\A cfl &lt; •v&gt; “-t y/ kJL+cJPj . •H eA^-k a &amp;J\SA/ -O-A tkkQ-j 1C, '7 CxxjCkXaux^At +—■ J1* The car is only to be driven by the driver, by the Political Agent or by the Assistant Political Agent. 2. Not more than four persons, other than the driver, may use the car at any one time. 3. Only the staff of this Agency may use the car. For exceptions to this rule special permission will have to be obtained previously from the Assistant Political Agent through the Clerk in charge of car bookings. 4. One Clerk will be in charge of car bookings. 5. Those intending to use the car must give notice not later than 10 a»ni. on any day of intended reservations for that day. For Friday reservations notice must be given on Thursday morning. 6 . The Clerk in charge will check the log book before issuing chits for petrol. 7. (a) A charge of 2 Annas per head per mile or 4 Annas for a private booking by one person will be made. * * (b) A charge of 6 Annas per mile will be made for duty trips; -and Officers will pay Annas 6 £ a mile when drawing/?.A. for a journey. 8 . Duty trips will take precedence over pleasure trips. 9* The log book must be entered up immediately after a trip is completed. A Transport Fund is to be created. The Clerk in charge of bobkings will arrange bookings so that the driver is not too heavily burdened on any one day. Appeals from his decisions may be made to the Assistant Political Agent. Political Agency, Bahrain. 26th July 1946. POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.requost the The- raoaburs of tho Agency Club pleasure of the company of at a party at their Club on the 14th August 1947 at 8 p.m. to celebrate Indian Indopendonc The members of the Agency Club request the pleasure of the company of -t a party at their Club on the 14th August 194 ? at 8 p.m. to celebrate Indian Independence.(a ^ - f 'X ”■ • I have been to see Vessrs Mohammad flajaji about the supplying of a new torsion tube for the Vauxhall 14. ^he Vauxhall ^ 0&gt; replied to their cable on d Jan^ stating that no spares were available in their factory. They promise to send the part by air as soon as they have one. *lajaji has also written by air mail to a dealer in London and expects either the part o^ a negative reply by the end of Feb. If there is no result through either channel by then, I propose telegraphing Vauxhall .in your name, asking them to grant us some sort of priority on the grounds that the car is urgently required for the public service. n l ^ ^ 1 ^ I u OuCJ*f ^ ^ 01U /&gt;r ' J (jL-t Ch* v/Ptf so . A\ p ^ ! V ~S'/$ ^ ^/ J &amp; f ’ P ^ ^ • tA 0^ l\ (Kl«* &gt; ' ! ■I tu^i / S 4J&lt; f - a a *4^ (a^„, yA/ tr' //-- H*' f ^ 84 85 86 I understand from Saiyed Ahrain that the tools kept by him in the P.A.*s garage are not the P.A's private property but Gov*t*s property. As that is so they must be listed, but as they are not many in number, I think it should be possible to divide them out between the two cars and the truck and include it in thiertool lists. . Saiyid Amin has asked me for a Saand for holding water for t iieaning the cars. If this cai\ be obtained in the bazaar at a , reasona4&amp;?price it may be sanctioned. purchases Incidentally an all such pTBfriKBX as the above, which are record ' - noteKpendible, taken on charge and a n&amp;xft kept, if not some j system will have.to be instituted. ltd. R.M. M.Andrew n 9 ' i - * ' 0 ^ ' U$ It O-aJL?**' (yQ4A^- C&amp;s6-4a~ OU^. At 'S, 4 P / huCanyts ^ ^h^-tno n_o^&gt;-e^&gt; Ql- ^ (Lo-Xo. . thLAJlt- IkNOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN.NOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN. S.s^ / O' Minutes. Letter No.PA-303 dated 27th July,1950 from C.L.R.Bapco* Bills for the months of January &amp; February never appear to have been received by us. Bills from the month of March,1950 are outstanding. While submitting their bills, Bapco never attach the relevant chits issued by us for checking the quantities mentioned in their invoices. Every time it has been the practice to send for the chits from the Manama Service Station and the Service Station people cause undue delay in sending them. I had to send Hassan Folad several times before I obtained the chits and that too has hot been obtained for the month^ of April so far. Even after receiving the chits, while checking them with the invsKi invoices, there is always some difference as will be obvious from the pencil statements attached to the bills below. We wrote to Bapco sometime back requesting them to submit separate bills for the Official Vehicles from those for the Private Vehicles. Ofcourse we are receiving separate bills as desired, but unfortunately, they send one combined bill for all the private vehicles with the- result it becomes very difficult to ascertain which officer is to be debited how much, especially in the absence of relevant chits in full (i.e. some chits are always missing). The foregoing explain how the payment is delayed. I have placed the bills so far received in three groups, A.Official Bills, (B.V.M.Hospital Bills (also official) and C.Private Vehicles Bills. I suggest that all the official bills i.e., groups A &amp; B may be settled right now in the assumption that they are correct. As regx^cs the bills for private vechicles, I am afraid, we should go into them further in order to decide who is to pay how much. V/e have also to call for duplicate bills for Jan &amp; Feb which do not seem to have been received by us. D.F.A. to C.L.R. Bapco. Li, dAUscju^L , , C-fi to a'V. Nothing to be Written in this Margin.On behalf of Messrs. Vaidyanathan and Moorthy, Mr. Viswanathan has spoken to me about the use of official transport for attendance at the office without payment. These officials live at a distance of one mile from the office,in the bazaar. I agree with Mr. Jakins (his order of 22nd September, 1949) that the '’Shumal' need prevent hkeh no one from walking, but , since no workmen in England now-a-days would be required to walk to # their work, I do not see why officials here should have to do so - in cold or hot weather. Mr. Viswanathan has some times to make the trips more than twice a day and the other two sometimes twice. 15-11-49. tfo- tyc&gt;s ^ ft/*'I</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1628</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1628</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 17/27 AGENCY TRANSPORT'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-01-07T18:05:43</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (237 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 239; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional mixed foliation/pagination sequence is also present in parallel between ff 3-26; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns the use and maintenance of the Bahrain Political Agency's official vehicles. The file largely consists of the Agency's correspondence with various suppliers and distributors of vehicle parts in Bahrain.The file contains specific details of the vehicles used by the Agency during this time (the Agency appears to have had two vehicles for official use at any one time between 1946 and 1950). Vehicles used by the Agency during this period include a Vauxhall VXO, an Austin Station Wagon and a Humber Super Snipe Saloon.Also included in the file are the following: monthly statements regarding staff use of the Agency's vehicles, which provide details of trips (including the names of the members of staff on duty and the distances travelled) that may be credited to the Agency's transport fund (later referred to as the transport account); details of two accidents involving an Agency vehicle; Foreign Office guidance on the use of official transport; copies of reports on the condition of the Agency's vehicles.The principal correspondents in the file are the following: the Political Agent, Bahrain; the Government of Bahrain's State Engineer; Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain; the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited; A A Zayani and Sons (general merchants and commission agents, based in Bahrain); the Foreign Office's Conference and Supply Department.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office, Conference and Supply Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>A A Zayani and Sons</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Car industry</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Bahrain, State Engineer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Cars</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>