<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100038753431.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T22:15:30.723Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [January 9.j Section 1, [389] No. 1. Foreign Office to Persian Transport Company. Sir, Foreign Office, January 9, 1912. I AM directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 29th ultimo respecting the extension of your road concession in Persia, and am to inform you, in reply, that His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran has been authorised to assist your local manager in his negotiations with the Persian Government Of, after consultation with Mr. Wilson, Sir G. Barclay is satisfied that such action on his part would be to the advantage of your company. I am, &amp;c. GUIS MALLET. [2329 1] ^ A* A i ii I[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL 308 ! December 22. Sectton 6. [51306] No. 1. Mr. Greenway to Foreign Office.—(Received December 22.) Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, Sir, December 21, 1911. I AM in receipt of your No. 50139 giving the result of communications with Sir G. Barclay on the subject of my enquiry of the 11th instant. I note that the old road concession includes no right to construct railways, and regret that my information led me to suppose that the contrary was the case. I now find that the claim which the holders of the concession believe they have to prior rights to railway construction is not based on anything contained in the concession itself, but on a letter written at the time the concession was granted by Amin-es-Sultan, the then Grand Vizier, to Yayha Khan, the then Minister of Foreign Affairs, to whom the concession was originally granted. This letter, I understand, gave very definite assurances that the concessionnaire would be entitled to the first claim to railway construction over the route covered by the concession, which assurance was, I believe, later on confirmed or supported by the British Government. This being the case, my informant (whose name I mentioned to Mr. Mallet) is of opinion that if the road concession is renewed without specific exclusion of railway rights the holders of the concession will consider themselves entitled to claim the benefit of the above assurances. Should you agree with this opinion, I would suggest that Sir George Barclay might be asked to suggest to the Persian Government that when renewing the road concession they should be careful to specifically exclude all rights to railway construction. I have, &amp;c. C. GREENWAY. [2286 ?/— 6 ] cr D Y TO INDIA 26 JAN 1912 FORETARY’S N2 4[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] P ^ PERSIA. 308 [December 30.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 6. 1912 —J [52284] No. 1. Persian Transport Company to Foreign Office.—(Received December 30.) 3, Salter's Fall Court, Cannon Street, London, Sir, December 29, 1911. I HAVE the honour to refer you to your letter of the 7th February last and to our reply of the 11 th idem, referring to the extension of the period allowed in this company’s concession for the construction of roads in Persia. We have recently been in telegraphic communication with our agent in Tehran, and received yesterday from him the following telegram under date of 27th instant:— “We require assistance of His Majesty’s Minister in Tehran. Please request Foreign Office to give the necessary instructions,” which we submit for your information and for any action you may consider it desirable to take. We have, &amp;c. (For Secretary), FRED. W. PARRY. [2286 gg — 6 ] s' QO py TO INDIA 26 JAN 1912 . SECRETARY’S N2 4 \ Sj tin * i- 2-5 JAN 1912k: %&gt; ! - ^ r—— ' L^vc&lt;Xi^) ^Put away wilh ;^ OL ^/^ CONKIJtF.NTIAL. 7H V&gt;' Sir Edward Gh'ey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 450.) Foreign Office, December 13, 1911. MY despatch No. 127 [of 18th October]. ^ Mr. Green way States that Wilson has obtained your support to Lynch’s application for an extension of his road concession, including right of railway construction. Please report how matter stands and what are prospects. k fU 0 V A COPY TO INDIA /iT 1 Q 1 / SECRETARY^ NS, 1 i[46493] No - L Mr. Greenway to Foreign Office.—(Received November 21.) Winchester House, Old Broad Street, l London, November 20, 1011. 1 BEG to acknowledge your letter of the 10th instant, replying to mine of the 26tli ultimo, addressed to Mr. Mallet, and enclosing copy of the amended telegram which was dispatched to Sir George Barclay. _ 1 have placed your letter before my co-directors on the Persian Railway Syndicate, and am desired to express the hoard’s appreciation of Sir Edward Grey’s expression of assurance as to the bona fides of the syndicate. _ I am also desired to* say that the board are in complete accord with Sir Edward Grey as to the desirability of arriving at an understanding with Russia on the question of railways in Persia, and are quite ready to send a representative to St. Petersburg!!, but they are of opinion that before doing so they should await some clearing up of the present political situation, in order that they may he able to form a better idea than they can at the moment as to the nature of the proposals that it would he most desirable to place before the Russian Government. As matters stand the syndicate has arrived at a complete agreement with the treasurer-general as to the form that their contract should take, anu it was the intention of the treasurer-general that this contract should, if practicable, be made the basis for contracts with Russian syndicates for railways in the Russian sphere. But this contract has not been presented by Mr. Shuster to the Persian Government, and, according to the latest advices, there appears to be some doubt as to whether Mr.’ Shuster will he in a position to deal with the matter for very much longer. Therefore, until the Persian Government, in the person of the treasurer-general or someone else, is in a position to continue the negotiations from the Persian side, it appears to the syndicate that it would be premature for them to send a representative to St. Petersburg!!, because any proposals that they might put before the Russian Government might not be acceptable to Persia. Should Sir Edward Grey, however, still hold a contrary view, and be able to give some indication as to the representations which it might be desirable to make to the Russian Government, the syndicate will be quite ready to send their representative to St. Petersburg!! at once. I am, &amp;c. G. GREENWAY. [2249 x —1] COPY TO INDIA ! SECRETAHY’S ' v. - { - [This Docnment is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] [November 21.] SECRET SERIES. IX A&gt; EASTERN DEPARTMENT.mSKiXi t [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] S EASTERN DEPARTMENT. 24N0V1911 [November 16.] SECRET SERIES. ' TVyV ^ Section 2. V [44621] No. 1. Foreign Office to Mr. Greenway. Si r? Foreign Office, November 16, 1911. WITH reference to the letter addressed to you from this Office on the 10th instant, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to inform you that Sir George Barclay understands the treasurer-general to have abandoned the idea of submitting any schemes for railway construction in Persia to the Medjliss until after the elections. The reason for this appears to be the uncertainty as to the legality of the present sittings of the Medjliss, whose existence, it is asserted in some quarters, should legally have terminated in October. I am to suggest that this delay should be turned to the best advantage by your syndicate in arriving at an understanding at St. Petersburgh. I am, &amp;c. LOUIS MALLET. [2249 9 — 2 ] COPY TO INDIA 1 Q 1 f iy I..., seOHSTARY’a NS±Z. .. ..— JT;. /Register No. Minute Paper. Secret Department. [9 ; lii■ s (xO This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] EASTERN DEPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. * \ »* i7U0V19lVy [November 10 .] Section 1. [42449] No. 1. Foreign Office to Mr. Greenway. Sir, Foreign Office, November 10, 1911. * itary Sir Edward Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter to Mr. Mallet of the 20th ultimo, explaining the attitude of your syndicate in I AM directed hy Secrei regard to railway construction in Persia Sir Edward Grey has never doubted the bona fides of the Persian Railway Syndicate in its negotiations, hut he continues to think that the best chance of securing a satisfactory outcome of those negotiations lies in the visit to St. Petersburgh of a representative of the syndicate. It is clear that a previous understanding with Russia is necessary for the construction of a line or any part of a line in the Russian sphere, whatever powers the treasurer-general may obtain from the Medjliss, and Sir Edward Grey trusts that the syndicate will arrive at an early decision in this matter. ^ I am to transmit to you herewith copy of the amended telegram which he has now despatched to Sir G. Barclay. I am, &amp;c. E. A. CAMPBELL. [2249 A—1] fj* C ) 'b - 1 ' ! 8 illLflslrO [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] EASTERN DEPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. CO [October 27.] l7l 40M]9lU a Section 1, [42449] No. 1 . Mr. Greenway to Mr. Mallet.—(Received October 27.) Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, Dear Mr. Mallet, October 26, 1911. I HAVE to acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 24th instant, conveying Sir Edward Grey’s views on the recent procedure of the Persian Railways Syndicate and of copies of a telegram from Sir George Barclay and draft of a proposed reply. 1 have submitted these to my co-directors to-day, and they desire me to point out, as I did briefly at my interview with you yesterday, that Sir Edward Grey’s remarks are to some extent based upon misapprehensions. In the first place, the syndicate has not decided against sending a representative to St. Petersburgh. They have merely deemed it advisable to delay this action until it is known whether or not the treasurer-general has succeeded in getting from the Medjliss the powers which he intended asking for, as advised in Mr. Brown’s telegram of the 16th instant, viz., to make contracts for the construction of a line from Julfa to Mohammerab on the basis of the terms and conditions already arranged with us. And the syndicate’s telegram of the 19th instant was sent chiefly with a view to pointing out the desirability of his obtaining powers to conclude contracts for the whole line, oi any section thereof, so that, in the event of there being any difficulty m securing Russian co-operation in the building of the Julfa-Khoremabad section, or of it only being practicable, for financial or other reasons, for Russia to undertake a portion of that section, say, from Julfa to Kasvin, or Julfa to Hamadan, the treasurer- general might be free to conclude contracts accordingly. Secondly, the syndicate are quite ready to co-operate with a Russian syndicate and to assist in trying to overcome any difficulties’there may be with the Russian Government, but until it is known what powers, if any, the treasurer-general mav be able to obtain from the Medjliss, they are of opinion that it wmuld be premature ’ and a needless expense, to send a representative to St. Petersburgh, as, in the meantime they have no definite basis for proposals. Thirdly, the syndicate have never had any intention of endeavouring to secure any concession for railways extending into the Russian sphere. The reference to Burujird and ultimate extensions to Tehran, &amp;c., in the draft contract were, as I think has been explained to you, and was explained to Mr. Brown and to the treasurer- general, only put in in order to make the scheme more palatable to the Mediliss but the contract itself is strictly limited to railways inside the neutral sphere. ? The mention of Burujird as an alternative to Khoremabad as the terminus of the southern line was, of course, understood only to be practicable provided Russian co-operation could be secured. 1 In this connection I may mention that, in mv conversations with M. PokTewski at lehran, the selection of this town rather than Khoremabad as the first objective of le me 10 m r ohammerah wms discussed, because, owing to its road connections it wou d tap a far larger share of the internal trade of Persia than would Khoremabad and, therefore, a railway built to this point would offer much better prospects of remunerauve working; but it was clearly understood between us that the section Russia 1 De ' 10m Khoremabad to Rurajird could only be built by arrangement with Fourthly’ the syndicate have always fully understood that no final arrangements weie to be made by them without the approval of His Majesty’s Government and G W 01 a P pI ‘°7 al 7 0uld necessitat e the acquiescence of the Russian Government. fact, without such approval the syndicate would not for a moment contemplate committing themselves to any financial risk whatever other than the money required for expenses during the period of negotiations, and they would like it to be understood that it was only in the belief that His Majesty’s Government were Ti 77 f Se J eS extr l en I el y desirous of securing the construction of the lines now under negotiation, and that the syndicate’s efforts in this direction would receive the [2232 dd — 1 ]■ H r Governmeut’s fullest support, that they have undertaken the onus of the negotiations 3t a The above explanation will I hope clear up any doubts as to the bona fides of the syndicate SUS pi c ions which have apparently been engendered in the minds of the Russian Government in consequence of our negotiatmns, I would venture to suggest that they should be advised that the negotiations which the syndicate are now carrying on are on precisely the same lines as those discussed by Mr Preece and the writer with M. Poklewski, in the presence of Sir George Barclay and Mr Young in April last, with the exception that we have since included (at your requesti the connection from Bunder Abbas to Mohammerah, and that no final arrangement will be concluded without their knowledge and approval. . f may point out that the giving of this assurance does not necessitate delaying the completion of the contract as now drafted, inasmuch as this is purely a provisional contract, dependent upon the syndicate being satisfied with the sufficiency of the securities which may be offered, and upon various other conditions which may neVe These U su!pteions, however, seem to owe their origin to the fact that M. Poklewski has not recently been kept au oourant with the progress of our negotiations, but when the writer was in Tehran it w'as fully understood that the Russian Minister would be kept fully posted up in all that was going on and as there is not the slightest objection to this from the syndicate’s point of view I beg to suggest that the proposed telegram to Sir George Barclay should be amended m accordance with the With Tefe-ence'’to Sir Edward Grey’s disapproval of the action of the syndicate expressed in the last paragraph of your letter, I am desired to point out that there has never been any intention or desire on the part of the syndicate to take any action without the full approval and knowledge of both the Russian and the British Govern ments for as above stated it has been their understanding all along that M. Poklewski was beino-kept fully informed of every step in their negotiations In order that there may be no further misunderstanding on this point, however, I am lemin mg Mr. Brown by wire to-day that he must keep His Majesty s Minister at Tehian fully posted up. Yours sincerely, C, GREEN WAY. i, Enclosure in No. 1. Draft of proposed Amended, Telegram to &amp;ir G. Barclay. YOU mav tell M. Poklewski that the Persian railway syndicate hope shortly to send a representative to St. Petersburgh to discuss scheme of Mohammerah railway and other lines, as the Medjliss will not consider any scheme limited to spheres of influence With a view to meeting this objection the syndicate had sketched out possible connection by Russia of some of the lines into Russian sphere but m order to avoid any possible misunderstanding, I have informed the syndicate that it would be better that they should come to an agreement with some Russian group. Y ou mav tell M. Poklewski which lines the syndicate propose to ask for, and generally what were the connections which they had in mind for construction by Russia. You may add that conversation between M. Poklewski and Green way, m your presence, whereby it was proposed that for any lines constructed by British syndicate m the south Russia would arrange to build equivalent, and as far as possible connecting lines in Russian sphere, and that section from Ivhoremabad to Buiujird it under taken should he built either by or in co-operation with Russia, still holds good and forms the basis of syndicate’s negotiations, and that syndicate’s representative will explain everything at St. Petersburgh. There is no objection to Poklewski seeing draft contract as it now stands, and you may keep him fully informed as to progress.£-6 D sThis Document is the Prope rty of His Br i tannic Majesty’s Government ,] * PERSIA [October ^IL.] CONF 1 DENTIAE. [43478 SEcmoN 4 . Question asked in the Bouse of Commons, October 31, 1911. Colonel Yate,—To ask the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs whether considering the effect a Trans-Persian railway will have on British and Indian trade in Southern Persia, steps will be taken to lix the break of gauge between the Indian and Russian railways at Ispahan, or to the north or west of that place, and not anywhere to the east or south of it. A nswer. The whole question is still under consideration, and is not sufficiently advanced for decisions to be taken on all points of detail; but, of course, if a scheme for a Trans-Persian railway matures sufficiently, such points as that referred to in the question will be carefully considered. [2219 hh —4] i F f t ;r Id )U )U :e, be Dg er- lod ive ski . asCONFIDENTIAL. x-~3 i x Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received November 11, 9 a.m.) (No. 555.) Tehran, November 11, 1911, 11T5 A.H. MY telegram No. 487 [ ], last paragraph : Persian railways. I understand that Shuster, owing to some uncertainty which exists as to the legality of the present sittings of the Medjliss, which some contend should have legally terminated last month, has abandoned intention of submitting any schemes to it until after the elections.CONFIDENTIAL. 3 I* iiuov^^ \ Q /f'rn rsT'V ,|/ ( [Amended Yeesion of No. 315.] &gt;Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 557.) K. Foreign Office, November 10, 1911. MY telegrams Nos. 315 and 316 [of 23rd October]. You may now tell M. Poklewski that the Persian Railway Syndicate hope shortly to send a representative to St. Peters burgh to discuss scheme of Mohammerah Railway and otner lines, as the Medjliss will not consider any scheme limited to spheres of influence. With a view to meeting this objection the syndicate had sketched out possible connection by Russia of some of the lines into Russian sphere, but, in order to avoid any possible misunderstanding, I have informed the syndicate that it would be' better that they should come to an agreement with some Russian group. You may tell M Poklewski which lines the syndicate propose to ask for, and generally what w l e] | ' e i tlie connections which they had in mind for construction by Russia. You may add that negotiations which syndicate has been carrying on were on lines explained by Mr. Greenway to M. Poklewski in April last, and that it has always been understood that section from Khoremabad to Burujird, if undertaken, should be built by or in co-operation with Russia. Representative of syndicate would explain everything at &amp;t. Peters burgh. There is no objection to Poklewski seeing draft contract as it now stands, and you may keep him fully informed as to progress. 1, * : 973—474][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] EASTERN DEPARTMENT, [October 23.] SECRET SERIES. Section 3. [41594] No. 1. (No. 175.) Sir, Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received October 23.) Gulhek, September 18, 1911. WITH reference to your telegram No. 166, I have the honour to report that Mr. H. Gr. Hart, formerly in the employ of the Imperial Bank of Persia, came out to Tehran in July to replace Mr. Osborne as the representative of the International Oriental Syndicate be seen that the syndicate have made no progress in their negotiations. There appears to be an impression in Tehran that the International Oriental Syndicate have no very substantial backing, though I am assured by Mr. Hart that they have Messrs. Pearson and Messrs. Samuel behind them; in any case Mr. Shuster, without whose consent no loan or concession can be negotiated, shows no disposition at present to look for loans further than to the Persian Railway Syndicate for railway con struction, and to Seligman’s for general purposes. The International Oriental Syndicate’s railway proposal would doubtless be more acceptable in principle to the Medjliss than the proposals of the Persian Railway Syndicate, as it altogether ignores the spheres of influence, but Mr. Shuster is at present all-powerful with the Medjliss, and I understand that he is hopeful of overcoming any objections to the syndicate’s proposals on this score. I should mention, however, that Mr. Shuster’s views differ widely from those of the syndicate as to the syndicate’s remuneration, the latter, as you are probably aware, demanding 5 per cent, on the gross receipts as well as 5 per cent, of the estimated cost of construction, whereas Mr. Shuster is only willing to give them 5 per cent, on the profits. P.S. September 30.—Since writing the above I learn that Mr. Shuster is offering as remuneration to the syndicate 15 per cent, of the net receipts with a minimum of J 5,000/. a-year. I CAME out to Tehran as the representative of the International Oriental Syndicate, by request of the Persian Minister in London, in order to obtain an authorisation to construct a railway on behalf of the Persian Government (say) from a point on the Persian Gulf to Julfa (Araxes), with branches to Tehran and Ispahan. My first interview was with yourself on the 15th July. On the 17th July I lunched* with Muin-ul-Yezareh. Hovanes Khan, who had been deputed to meet us by the Regent, was also present. The question of railway construction was discussed. We had previously informed the Persian Government that we were prepared to arrange for a loan to them of some 10 , 000 , 000 /. for this purpose. Guarantees :— 1. Railway and receipts. 2 . Persian Government’s total interest in the D’Arcy oil concession. A general charge on the u npledged revenue of Persia. To clause 3 the Persians objected, Hovanes Khan suggesting that an additional loan should be floated to cover the deficit that there would certainly be during the first few years of working. I enclose a statement, with which Mr. Hart has furnished me, from which it will I have, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. G. B. Enclosure in No. 1 . Memorandum by Mr. Hart (of the International Syndicate). [2232 z-3]I was then asked to make a proposal in writing, which I did. Receiving no reply. On the 3rd August I had an interview with his Excellency Yossough-ed-Dowleh, who told me he would place my proposals before the Cabinet, He asked me not to fl mention to Mr. Shuster the reason for my coming to Tehran I saw Mr. Shuster the same day, but I told him why I bad come to Tehian, alsqf^ that the stumbling-block in negotiations was that we required ^ general charge on the revenue. “ Well,” he replied, “ I think we can give you that.’’ I learnt later that, in virtue of a law^ passed by the Medjhss on the 13th June, all proposals for concessions, or for anything in the nature of a concession, must be presented through Mr. Shuster. . . , ., ,, , , On the 11th August I saw Mr. Shuster again, when he told me that he could on no account agree to a general charge on the revenue as guarantee for a railway. On the 21st August I laid certain definite proposals before him m writing, which he vetoed absolutely^ saying that he could on no account agree to the tying up of the revenue which our proposals involved. On the 28th August I saw M. Poklewsky, who seemed to think that his bovern- ment would have no objection to an international railway (with a board consisting of British, Russians, and French) running through Persia. Nor did he think that his Government would require the northern half of the railway to be policed by Russians unless it were at any time in danger of destruction. 4 But, he added, you cannot possibly arrange anything here.” t ^ ^ , , A Some eighteen months ago our syndicate offered to consolidate the whole ot the existing debts of the Persian Government at 5 per cent.—87^. This proposal was also made officially to them in writing on the 21 st February, 1911. le guarantee was: a prior charge on all the revenues of the country, particularly the customs^ ewe ^ ^ offer p ersona Hy to Mr. Shuster on the 11 th August, and he promised to bear it in mind. I also informed him that we were quite prepared to make any sort of a loan to the Persian Government on reasonable guarantee being 0 61 On the 28th August I saw Mr. Shuster again, when he asked me to make a proposal for a loan of 4,500,000/. to the Persian Government to be expended solely on 44 permanent reproductive public works '—security, all the unmortgaged revenue of the Persian Empire. ... I telegraphed home, and on the 9th September made a proposal in writing. To this Mr Shuster replied verbally that he had answered my letter to the effect that negotiations for a loan with Messrs. Seligman, involving the conversion of the Russian Bank debt, were so far advanced that the Persian Government could not consider the question of any other loan at present. I have not yet received the letter he said he had written. It is regrettable that Mr. Shuster should have asked me to make the proposal and then have replied as he did without even a suggestion as to the suitability or unsuitability of our terms. I may mention that, before my arrival, Mr. Osborne was continally negotiating with the Persian Government, and had made definite proposals to them. Tiie Persian Government never informed either of us of the law of the 13th June authorising Mr Shuster to carry on all negotiations for concessions, &amp;e., on behalf of the Persian Government. Nor would they even write a letter to me referring me to Mr. Shuster, although I repeatedly requested them to do so. T t v D H. C. HART. September 15, 1911.[Tins Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government,j EASTERN 1) EPA RTM ENT. SECRET SERIES. \ .. 11 NOVI 9111 | November 1.] Section 3. 43068 No. E Foreign Office io \lr. Greenwny. t Foreign Office, November 1, 1911. WITH reference to the letter addressed to you from this Office on the 6 th October and to your reply of the 30th October 1 am greeted by Secretary Sir iHUvard Grev to inform you that Sir George Barclay considers it advisable that the Sheikh of Uohainmerah should defer making to the Persian Q. vernment, at the present moment, his proposed communication with a view to safeguarding his rights under his firmans in all matters in so far as concerns lands covered by any railway agreement I am to add that, in Sir George Barclay’s opinion, article 4 ot your syndicate’s draft contract is, in its present form, not unlikely to give rise to difficulties in Persia both as regards the sheikh’s territory and the property of important private owners. I am, &amp;c. LOUIS MALLET. 12249 «—3]Lf-.(rl '2- 3 (This Document is the Prop erty of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] EASTERN DEPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. 3 11 NOVI 911 [October 31.] [430)0] No. 1. Persian Railwais Syndicate to Foreign Office—[Received October 31.) Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, Sir, October 30, 1911. I BEG to acknowledge your undated letter No. 38746. I have submitted this to my co-directors of the Persian Railways Syndicate, and they desire me to say— 1. That the position as regards the Russian Government is, as shown by other writings, quite understood; and 2 . That they have taken note of the fact that the acquiescence of the Sheikh of Mohammerah is required to article 4 of the draft contract, and await your further advices on this point. I am, &amp;c. C. GREEN WAY, Chairman. [2232 hh —2]y * - 3 [This Documen t is the Proper ty of His B ritan nic Ma j esty’s Gover nment.; EASTERN DEPA RTMENT. SECRET SERIES. I November \ Skction 2. [43232] No. 1. Mr. Greenway to Mr. Mallet.— {Received November 1 ) Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, t\,i a/i n f October 30, 1911. HAVE Emitted previously to acknowledge your letters dated loth and '* fittfiSSSi — S .u- •«. co-diict*. ... «. M . T g»S »i the hoard and we have taken due note of the point that there may be some difficulty in connection with the clauses in our draft contract, based on terms in the twhgman loan contract relating to the position of the treasurer-general. wftrust however, that Russia’s objections to these clauses may not be serious as if they are’it would indicate a determination on Russia’s part to absolutely bloc, any attempt by Persia to put her finances on a sound basis.^ C. GREENWAY. [2249 a—2][This Doeument is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Gcyyeirmvprtf 1 I SAW Mr. Greenway this morning. He is willing that Sir G. Barclay should communicate the draft contracts for railways to M. Poklewski and assure him that no step will be taken as regards construction without a complete understanding with the Russian Government. I strongly urged that the syndicate should send a representative to Russia at once, and Mr. Greenway thinks it might be arranged three weeks hence. He maintained that it will be much simpler to negotiate with Russia when Shuster had got powers from the Medjliss for arranging a contract for the construction of a Mohammerah-Julfa line or for any section of it. On my pointing out that the syndicates action in urging Shuster to obtain these powers might be misunderstood, Mr. Green way explained that Shuster had already announced his intention of obtaining these powers, and that it was not their suggestion. He appeared to regard our letter as satisfactory. Telegraph to Sir G. Barclay to communicate the draft contracts and to give the assurance, and repeat to Mr. O’Beirne. . L. M. Foreign Office, October 25, 1911. EASTERN DEPARTMENT. [October 25.] r * SECRET SERIES. Section 1. [42273] No. 1 Minute by Mr. Mallet. [2232 bb—l][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government,] SIR EDWARD GREY regrets to learn that the syndicate have decided against sending a representative to St. Petershurgh to discuss railway projects, as a scheme for a railway concession extending into the Russian sphere of interest will have no chance of success unless the Russian Government agree to it, and will receive no support from and that any action on the part of the syndicate which may give reason to think that they are endeavouring to obtain railway concessions in the Russian sphere without the knowledge of Russia must have very undesirable consequences. ^ _ . , . _ , , . The Russian Minister at Tehran, believing that the Russian sphere is aftected, is Dressing for information respecting the draft contract (see enclosed telegram from Sir G.° Barclay),* and Sir Edward Grey would propose to send Sir G. Barclay instructions in the sense of the draft telegram annexed.t He does not approve of the syndicate’s instructions to their agent to urge Shuster to make a contract for the Julfa-Mohammerah line without giving previous notice to the Russian Government, because it will he open to misconstruction. Sir Edward Grey would he glad to have the syndicate’s answer as soon as possible. EASTERN DEPARTMENT. [October 24.] SECRET SERIES. w llN0V1911j_ Section 1. [41982] No. 1. Mr. Mallet to Mr. Greenway. Dear Mr. Greenway, Foreign Office, October 24, 1911. I am, &amp;c. LOUIS MALLET. * Sir G-. Barclay, No. 508, Telegraphic, f To Sir G. Barclay, No. 315, Telegraphic.Lf(rrx-3 is the Property of His Britannic Maiest ^ EASTERN DEPARTMENT. [October 23.] SECRET SERIES. Section 4. — [41982] No. 1. Minute by Mr. Mallet. MR. PREECE, of the Persian Railway Syndicate, called to inform me that the syndicate had had a board meeting and had decided not to send a representative to Russia to discuss co-operation, at any rate for the present, and had sent a telegram to their representative to urge Shuster to take powers from the Mediliss to make contract for Julfa-Mohammerah Railway, or any section thereof, so that the contract for Mohammerah, Ehorremabad, or Rurujird line may be concluded at once thereby facilitating arrangements for construction of northern section by Russia ’ I told Mr. Preece that I did not think that you would approve of this without consulting the Russian Government, and he said that Mr. Green way and he had taken this line at the board meeting, but that Lynch, who was opposed to the entente with Russia and wished to wreck it, was strongly opposed to negotiations at Enclosure 1 in No. 1 . . Persian Railway Syndicate to Mr. Brown {Tehran). (Translation.) (Teiegraphic.) Winchester House, Old Broad Street, October 19, 1911. LOU EE probably arrange co-operate with Russian syndicate, but this would entail great cle ay, owing to necessary approval both Governments, and might indefinitely shelve all railway construction. Persia, because of Russian policy° is against railway construction. Therefore think treasurer-general should obtain power make contracts for construction of line from Julfa to Mohammerah, or any section thereof, thereafter concluding our contracts from Mohammerah to Khorreinabad or Rurujird, as this would be best possible means ensuring construction by Russia JuJta and other railways in north, because construction such railways would be essential for protection Russian trade. Enclosure 2 in No. 1 . . Mr. Lynch to Mr. Wilson {Tehran). (1 ranslation.) (Telegraphic.) October 20, 1911. SEE Shuster; inform him “Times” to-day contains letter from myself, urging* strongly English Russian co-operation with himself. Inform him, confidentially that my opinion is proposal the Persian Government constitute joint syndicate would m\o\e engthy negotiations, and this wdll haye the effect of side-tracking railway scheme indefinitely. I realise objections the Persian Government recognition spheres, but I regard it as essential from Persian point of view that milway Khorremabad should be constructed by British capital without delay, otherwise interest of British public opinion towards Persia likely languish, thus pave wav for Russian occupation. Britain will never want to occupy this part Persia, and most reluctant occupy any part, therefore encouragement British capital in neutral sphere Persist be reSai ’ ded as safe § uard against complete Russian predominance throughout [2232 a—4]y y 1 [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] EASTERN DEPARTMENT. '■K' — SECRET SERIES. 1 1 NOVI 911 [October 9.] [39496] Section 4. No. 1. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received October 9.) (No. 173.) ^ ; Gulahek, September 11 , 1911. ITH reference to my despatch No. 81 of the 31st May, I have the honour to transmit herein copy of a note from the Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs in reply to my note of the 25th May respecting possible railway construction in Persia. This somewhat vague pronouncement is all I have been able to obtain. Both the late Minister for Foreign Affairs and the present one have obstinately refused to o'ive any undertaking referring expressly to railways in the south, which they feel would be m some measure a recognition of the spheres of influence. Both have however repeatedly reminded me of the rescript of Nasr-ed-Din Shah, the binding character of which the Persian Government do not dispute. Thev do not understand why we should need more than this. ^ In any case, I presume that the written undertaking vou desired me to obtain is not so much needed now that the Persian railway syndicate have presented their proposals, and I shall not press the Persian Government further for aiivtliino- more explicit unless you instruct me to do so. I have, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. Enclosure in No. 1 . Vosouk-ed-Dowleh to Sir G. Barclay. (Translation.) Your Excellency, Tehran, September 9 , 1911. IJS reply to your Excellency s note of the 25th May last and with reference to the personal conversation which has taken place between us, I have the honour to say that although the Persian Government cannot express their final opinion on particular ponits regarding railways without the necessary investigations, still, being fully aware ot the profit and advantages of railway construction in the countrv, and feeling strongly the necessity for the construction of such lines as are profitable to commerce 3 and cause the material progress of the State, should British syndicates make proposals to the Persian Government in this respect they (the proposals) will naturally receive the consideration of the Persian Government, who will be ready to enter into negotiations with them (the syndicates), and, after the necessary investigations to come to an understanding on conditions compatible with the interests and advantages ot both parties. ° I avail, &amp;c. VOSOUK-ED-DOWLEH. 1 m A w i 1 Lfl ! ' Ji f* 2232 i—4] ; d V I illV [This Document is the Property of His Britannia Majesty^ Government,] 1 EASTERN DEPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. / c-;&gt; [40250] No. 1. [October 18.] Section 1, Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay. (No. 127. Secret.) Sir, Foreign Office, October 18, 1911. I HAVE to transmit to you herewith copy of a letter from Mr. Green way to Mr. Mallet, enclosing a telegram sent to Mr. Brown on the subject of Mr. Lynch’s road concession and the Mohammerah-Khoremabad Railway.* I am, &amp;c. E. GREY. See “ Eastern Department: Secret Series ” Print, October 13, 1911, Section 2. [2232 s—1][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government,] BELIEVE that Lynch pressing for renewal of road concession for further term of years. Gan you discover intention in getting renewal for road beyond Sultanabad and Khoremabad to Mohammerah seeing that railway would render road useless ? In any case ask treasurer-general warn Persian Government that if they renew concession they must clearly reserve power to build railway without compensation to road concessionaires. EASTERN DEPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. [October 13.] Section 2. [40250] No. 1. Dear Mr. Mallet, Mr. Greenway to Mr. Mallet.—{Received October 13.) Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, October 12, 1911. C. GREEN WAY. Enclosure in No. 1. Mr. Greenway to Mr. Brown {Tehran). (Confidential.) (Telegraphic.) October 11, 1911. [2232 n —2][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] COMMUNICATE the following to C. Greenway :— “ liefer to our letter of the 30th August. Treasurer-general of Persia states it is very important four article should be included in order to provide for continuity administration, finance, and development resources Persia. Treasurer-general of Persia believes he can push contract through Medjliss, but Medjliss resign the 1st November, and it is treasurer-general of Persia’s opinion there will not be any other Mediliss ; consequently there is no time to lose. Treasurer-general of Persia requires for Medjliss estimated cost construction each railway.” (Private.) Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, (Telegraphic.) September 19, 1911. Keferring to your telegram of the 18th. Do not understand attitude of treasurer-general. Does he think syndicate philanthropic ? if not, where does he expect them to get their remuneration from ? It appears to us that the difficulties he is raising regarding remuneration security gauge, &amp;e., are with the object of making us withdraw because of other proposals. What is Hart doing ? Reply at once. Communicate the following to C. Green way :— “ W. Morgan Shuster says remuneration syndicate is profit rate of issue of the loan 5 per cent, nett receipts railways and one-half nett receipts in excess of 5 per cent, interest on capital employed, which treasurer-general of Persia considers ample remuneration. W. Morgan Shuster says H. G. Hart has talked to him about proposal international syndicate, but up to the present has submitted nothing definite. Believed not to be serious.” Referring to your telegram of the 18th :— Article 5 we agree (to) submit for approval with estimates lists of articles to be imported free, but cannot give actual weight, &amp;c. Suggest import certificate signed by syndicate manager same as Anglo-Persian Oi] Company (Limited) stating EASTERN DEPARTMENT. [September 27.] ' • SECRET SERIES. 'I 137861] No. 1. Papers communicated by Mr. Greenway September 27, 1911. ( 1 .) Mr. Brown (Tehran) to Persian Railways Syndicate. (Private.) (Telegraphic.) [Received September 19, 1911]. (3.) The Imperial Bank of Persia (Tehran) to Mr. Brown (Tehran). (Private.) (Telegraphic.) [Received September 20. 1911.] (Telegraphic.) (4.) Persian Railways Syndicate to Mr. Brown (Tehran). Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, September 22, 1911. [2195 dd—2]t 2 articles required, for construction and working will meet case. P. 5, line 6, remuneration on construction sine qud non, other remuneration indicated problematic and quite inadequate for risks involved; but if treasurer-general wishes cover it, suo-o-estfs) it should be included in estimates under article 13. P. 7, line 5, agreed p to in cash or in bonds at 87i per cent. P. 4, line 15, delete from “of” to “or,” substitute “ not more than.” Syndicate would under no consideration agree finance wide guage which some Persians want because (of) cost absolutely prohibitive and remunerative working impossible, also quite unsuited mountainous country. P. 4, line 21, insert (in) “ and/or.” P. 14, line 21, after “ be ” insert (in) “ fixed in currency country.” P. 14, line 23, delete “ be fixed,” substitute, if necessary, “ be adjusted.” P. 12, line 2, must be gross as otherwise syndicate might get no remuneration during working for several years. Payment on nett absolutely unsound because (of) inducement to starve upkeep and consequent endless disputes. Veto power conceded treasurer-general afford ample protection Grovern ment. page 12, line 22, delete “or passenger”; p. 8, line 14, delete “Southern Persia.” Impossible fix contract more definitely at present because (of) Government. Cannot now offer security showing at present revenue adequate income for service bonds, nor can cost be estimated before gauge settled and survey made. Pirst railways probably require bond issue 4,000.000/., requiring 200,000/. for service, whereas post telegraph opium offered only now yielding 100,000/., 4,000/. D’Arcy concession nil. Therefore if it is desired conclude contract speedily there is no alternative but to leave security to be arranged later. Page 14, line 29, insert “ should treasurer-general object to any payments made or to be made in connection with working, maintenance, or replacement of the line to which objection syndicate shall not agree, question in dispute shall be referred to arbitration.” Article 24, add rider “should security offered by Government for bonds to be issued for construction lines, secondly, thirdly, fourthly described be in opinion syndicate inadequate, Government shall be at liberty (to) offer bonds third parties price not less than 87^ per cent, proceeds issue up to 871 per cent, nominal value shall be dealt with similarly as mentioned.” Article 20, “ for the purpose of enabling syndicate construct such line.” All term(s) relating (to) construction and payment for construction line first herein described shall [so far as applicable] apply (to) construction and payment line irrespective (of) which bonds issued. (5.) Persian Railways Syndicate to Mr. Brown (Tehran). Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, (Telegraphic.) September 23, 1911. Referring to our telegram of the 22nd:— For “ p. 14, line 29,” read “ p. 13, line 30.” ( 6 .) Persian Railways Syndicate to Mr. Brown (lehran). (Private.) Winchester Blouse, Old Broad Sheet, London, (Telegraphic.) September 23, 1911. “ Pirst source remuneration very problematic, and might be loss owing unsettled future country ; second, would not mature five years, and then very small ; third, nil. On these terms syndicate would not consider business at all. Point out first source purely finance profit, and that several years’ services on construction work must be separately and adequately remunerated, and also subsequent expert working. You have not explained treasurer-general’s attitude. He is apparently hostile, otherwise would not raise these impossible objections. Referring to your telegram of the 19th, agreeable include articles subject to approval Poreign Office. Will telegraph shortly.”3 0 l n &gt;e 10 ly )r v (7.) (Telegraphic.) [Received September 25, 1911.] Eeferring to your telegram of the 22nd. Article 5, treasurer-general agrees to importation materials clearly necessary for the actual construction of line stations, telegraph, telephone(s), fence(s) machinery duty free, all other articles to pay duty, and, if found necessary for railway equipment(s), duty to be included in bond issue. Treasurer-general insists (upon) that syndicate not being railway^ engineer(s) should not expect remuneration as constructors; their remuneration should come from financial transactions. Suggests as alternative that technical features contract be settled, leaving price(s) bond(s) later determination; for instance, firm(s) price(s), 86/. 10s., might be acceptable (to) for issue(s) first line. Government willing (to) pay reasonable office(s) expenses syndicate, London. Treasurer-general agrees to 7^ per cent, nett receipts contract should leave gauge wholly free for determination construction engineer with knowledge (of) funds available. Treasurer-general considers your estimate(s), 4,000,000/., for first line very excessive, in view of nature of country, which mostly fiat; 8,000/. mile very outside for metre gauge. Treasurer-general very well disposed towards the railways, and determined to put contract through. Treasurer-general insists (upon) time limit which may he liberal one, for completion first line. Parliament dissolves 23rd October. Acknowledges receipt of the altered copy of the draft contract enclosed with our letter No. 5. ( 8 .) Persian Railways Syndicate to Mr. Brown {Tehran). Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, (Telegraphic.) September 26, 1911. Eeferring to your telegram 25th : duty. We accept. Syndicate performs three functions—first finance, second management and supervision, construction, third future management working railway. Eemunera- tion for first will be covered in price bonds; second will involve immense work extending over number of years another similar contract provided for 15 per cent, on gross expenditure plus 5 per cent, on all material purchased abroad, if treasurer- general prefers we can arrange 5 per cent, to be included in contractor’s estimate, but syndicate must be separately remunerated for this work in addition to office expenses. Syndicate do not anticipate profit on bond issue and if necessary you can agree refund to Persian Government difference between purchase price and actual nett proceeds realised allowing 1 per cent, to syndicate for expenses; third we cannot accept less than 10 per cent, on nett receipts before paying bond service with reasonable minimum, say 10,000/. per annum. Guage, we agree. Impossible make reliable estimate before actual survey, but flat couutry very difficult, necessitates bridging two wide rivers, and intervening country badly cut up by water courses. Time limit difficult fix before survey, but if absolutely necessary we agree six years from approval survey. sttled 1 &gt; 1 . iource istb You erffise of ^ jgraph[ This Document is the Property of His B ritannic Majesty’s Govemubentj ■ i i i ■■■■in.,. mi —n i. ■mm— \ i \ [September 22.] Section 2. Persian Railways Syndicate to Foreign Office.—(Received September 22.) Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, Dear Mr. Mallet, September 19, 1911. I HAVE to acknowledge your letter of the 9th instant and to advise you that yom suggested alteration in article 19 of the draft railway contract has been duly adopted, as shown in the enclosed telegram dated the 11th instant to Mr. Brown. In addition to the above telegram, I am enclosing copies of several others exchanged with Mr. Brown subsequent to those of which you have already had copies. Is it possible that we could be allowed to see Lieutenant Wilson’s report on the route from Mohammerah to Khoremabad, as this wmuld aid us materially in arriving at the figures which we require to put before the Treasurer-General in regard to our proposals ? Yours very truly, C. GREEN W AY, Chairman Enclosure 1 in No. 1. (Private.) (Telegraphic.) Mr. Brown {Tehran) to Persian Railways Syndicate. COMMUNICATE the following to C. Greenway :— [Received September 19, 1911.] “ Refer to our letter of the 30th August. Treasurer-general of Persia states it is very important four articles should be included in order to provide for continuity administration, finance, and development resources Persia. Treasurer-general of Persia believes he can push contract through Medjliss, but Medjliss resign the 1st November, and it is treasurer-general of Persia’s opinion there will not be any other Medjliss, consequently there is no time to lose. Treasurer-general of Persia requires for Medjliss estimated cost construction each railway.” Enclosure 2 in No. 1. Persian Railways Syndicate to Mr. Brown (Tehran). (Private.) Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London (telegraphic.) September 19, 1911. REEERRING to your telegram of the 18th. Do not understand attitude of treasurer-general. Does he think syndicate philanthropic ? If not, where does he expect them to get their remuneration from ? It appears to us that the difficulties he is raising regarding remuneration, security gauge, &amp;c., are with the object of making us withdraw because of other proposals What is Hart doing ? Reply at once. 1 Enclosure 3 in No. 1. Persian Raihvays Syndicate to Mr. Brown (Tehran). % n x Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London. (telegraphic.) September 11. 1911. REEERRING to your telegram of the 1st. Article 16 v r as intended to cover syndicate’s remuneration but to meet treasurer- general s point. Alter contract as follows :— [2195 y —2]• x i “ actual” ! p. 5, line 4&lt;, delete Referring to draft concessiriii p. -J, ^ „ ] tjU|te « als0 5 p er cent, upon “ for,” substitute “ up to ” ; p. 5, line 6, delete ■», , ^ services ^ to cover ». estimated cost as aforesaK » „ th } e rewit h ” and substitute “ in event of p. 7, lines 5 to 13, delete non v v contracts and m respect of aggregate amount ^^ess'than estimated as in article 13, syndicate shall, interest and expenses ^ em » 1 f f i - r OT) tion either pay Persian Government when railway “J^^^T aZunt lids Lued in excess of sueli cash equivalent at 87 2 per ^ bonds at par . If such aggregate amount aggregate amount, or deliver ment shallj wb l en ca ii e d upon hy syndicate, greater than estimated costs, dmilnrlv secured at 87i per cent, to satisfy issue to syndicate additiona rai way from ^ the ” to “syndicate,” substitute ^TTevenue^f 8 out ton Persia as may he applicable to the purpose and be approved.” r Enclosure 4 in No. 1. Mr. Brown {Tehran) to Persian Railways Syndicate. (Telegraphic.) [Received September 11, 1911.] igrapnic.; , u EOLLOWIJS G are proposals of treasurer-general Referring to draft concession, p. 2, line 26 , delete “ free of cost.” Referring to draft concession, p. 2, line 29, after &lt;' works ” add “ such reasonable outlays if any.” Referrmg to draft concession p. 2 line 31, I t “ imnort duties ” insert (in) in article 5 “ customs duty according to tantt to be pai brsyndicate and included in costs.” Referring to draft eoncessron R 4, Rne 1 delete from “use” to end of line. Article 11, strongly recommends four months twelve months respectively. Article 12, gauge to decided when e S timat submitted Referring to draft concession, p. 4, lines 17, 18, 19, delete J “ situate,”*substitute “shall he of first-class construction and work^nship touted to the class and needs of the country traversed p. 5, ime 19 , delete , substitute “ three ” ; p. 6, line 15, after “ per cent, mserd which syndicate, hereby agrees to accept at that rate” ; p. 6, line 22, delete six, substitute thiee , p. 7, lines 5 to 13 delete from “ the ” to “therewith”; article 17, delete from upon to “issued,” substitute “railways to be completed three years from d^f dehvery o bonds to syndicate,” delete “ notified ” ; p. 7, line 32, after “ per cent, nseit net p. 8, line 6, “ date to he fixed for amortisation at J per cent, (per annum) of the^bond , which shall be approximately five years after proposed date !“ r . 0 P e ““? ?° a d , public traffic.” Article 20 proceeds : “ of these bonds to be deposited to the joint ordt of Government and the syndicate. Draft thereon to be authorised by both (of) ; Synaicate to send reasonable requisition as required from time to time to the Government, and the Government undertakes to authorise same. Interest on these funds to be accounted for to the Government.” P. 12, line 2, delete “gross,’ substitute net ; p. 12, line 22, treasurer-general questions expediency of insurance. Cancel article . “ Rate to be fixed by mutual agreement. Treasurer-general suggests as part security post and telegraph revenue, and ail revenue arising from Governmen m eres s D’Arcy’s concession.” I foresee difficulties regarding southern customs, which will he required for future loan to keep Government afloat. Treasurer-general strongly recommends insert m agreement all four articles enclosed in referring to my letter of 30th ultimo. Enclosure 5 in No. 1. Persian Railways Syndicate to Mr. Brown (Tehran). Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, (Telegraphic.) September 14, 1911. REEERRING to your telegram of the 11th. Referring to draft contract concession enclosed with letter dated the 17th Angus!, 1911, p. 2, line 22, after “ land ” insert “ and other land belonging to Government free cost ”; p. 2, lines 24 to 29, delete “the” to “works.” Article 5 must stand.We consider its deletion extremely unsound, because would increase cost and bond issue considerably, and render remunerative working more difficult and depreciate issue price bond. P. 3, line 32, p. 4, line 1, delete “together” to “ import.” Article 11, agree “ 4,” but “ 18” must stand owing to difficulties weather and insecurity. P. 4, line 15, insert after “ gauge ” “ wffiich gauge to be decided when estimate(s) submitted. P. 4, lines 17, 18, 19, delete “the” to “situate,” insert after “rack” “and shall be of first-class construction and workmanship adapted to the class and need(s) country traversed.” P. 5, line 19, agree(s) to “ 3.” P. 6, line 15, agree(s) to your insertion (in). P. 6, line 22, agree(s) to “three.” P. 7, line , article 17, rider to must stand, as it is impossible to fix period before completion survey. Page 7, line 32, agree net. P. 8, line 6, agree J per cent.; p. 8, line 7, after “ the ” insert “ date on which it is anticipated (that) the,” delete “ shall have been,” substitute “will be.” Article 20, line 17, after “the” insert “joint,” after “ of ” insert “ Government and.” Line 18, delete “ applied,” insert “paid to*” Line 23, after “ hereof ” insert “ Syndicate to send reasonable requisition as required from time to time Government, who undertakes to authorise payment of same within fifteen days thereafter. Interest on proceed to be accounted for to the Government and be applied either in payment of outlay mentioned in article 19 or in payment of subsequent interest of bond.” P. 12, line 2, gross absolutely essential; syndicate not philanthropic. P. 12, line 22, insurance' usual, no other fund(s) available for possible damage(s) to line(s) and customer. Article 33, agree stop. P. 11, line 17, delete “ the said,” insert “ such”; line(s) 17,18, delete “ or ” to them ” ; line(s) 19, substitute “ J per cent. ” for “ 1 per cent, ”; line(s) 26, delete “ so ” ; line(s) 26, 27, 28, delete “as” to “thereby,” substitute “in a proper and efficient manner.” Enclosure 6 in No. 1. Persian Railways Syndicate to Mr. Wood {Tehran). Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, (Telegraphic.) September 14, 1911. COMMUNICATE the following to D. Brown :— “ (Private.) “ Referring to your telegram of 11th September, after word ‘ agreement ’ to end. In view of desirability completing contract earliest possible moment, and present inability Persian Government offer security that would provide adequate marketable basis for bond issue, it is necessary leave question of security open, and to conclude contract in accordance with present wording article 19. Similarly suggested four articles referred to in your letter of 30th August will be dealt with at same time. In the meantime, however, arrange with treasurer-general to reserve post telegraph W. K. D’Arcy’s concession as collaterals to main security eventually arranged. Telegraph estimate of post telegraph revenues.” Enclosure 7 in No. 1. Mr. Brown (Tehran) to Persian Railways Syndicate. (Telegraphic.) [Received September 8, 1911.] TREASURER-GENERAL strongly objects article 5, which will (would) lead to endless difficulties and friction. As an alternative suggests, but does not recom mend, that detailed lists of articles to be imported duty free giving actual weights of the rails, bolts, &amp;c., must be submitted for approval with the estimate. Referring to draft contract concession, p. 5, line 6, under no consideration can he accept remuneration clause. Page 7, line 5, to end of article, is not sufficiently definite; it should be stated in event of cost being less than estimate, syndicate has the option of refunding difference in cash or in bonds at 874-per cent. Page 4, line 15, width gauge should not appear in contract, because should it be decided later adopt different width, it would be necessary obtain permission pari passu. Page 4, line 21, delete “ or,” substitute “and/or.” Page 14, lines 21, 22, 23, delete from “be” to “the tariff rates must be fixed currency country.” Page 12, line 2, will not agree gross but agrees to net, not^ as remuneration, but as a bonus giving syndicate monetary interest in economical working and development railways. Page 12, line ,treasurer-general considers insurance of lines and stations bad finance, but under no circumstances should customers be insured. Page 8, line 14, delete “ Southern Persia.’ Treasurer-general states that it is essential (to) security for at least first railway should be fixed in contract, otherwise syndicate might postpone construction on plea security not approved. For subsequent lines clause will be necessary that, should security offered not be approved by syndicate. Government to have right to offer identical security to others, and should it be accepted by them, Government will be free give construction of such lines them. Treasurer-general proposes following secu rities': post and telegraph, present net revenue 120,000 tomans, but should yield 250,000 under new English Telegraph Administrator. Persian Government’s interests, D’Arcy’s concession, first charge on up to 100,000/. per annum, every and any net revenue which may be established. This does not include opium receipts, estimated at about 400,000 tomans, which treasurer-general wishes to retain for other purposes, but if absolutely necessary he will give them also. Treasurer-general insists upon veto, but suggests proviso that should anything vetoed not be approved by railway general manager it should be submitted to arbitration.M- VT) ; [ This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] EASTERN DEPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. ^ — [35420] [September 8.] Section 2. Mr. Greenway to Mr. Mallet—(Received September 8.) Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, Dear Mr. Mallet, September 7, 1911. •WHEN writing my letter of the 4th instant I assumed that the figure of twenty-five or thirty years given for the tenure that would be secured by an amortisation fund at the rate of 1 per cent, per annum was about the correct actuarial figure, but on looking into the cpiestion I find that the actual figures are as below : — A 1 per cent, accumulating sinking fund invested at— 5 per 4 H cent, per annum would require 36f &gt;&gt; &gt;&gt; 38^ &gt;&gt; &gt;5 41 &gt;&gt; 5 ) 4:4:^ &gt;&gt; &gt;5 )) 4/ &gt;&gt; 50^ years to extinguish the principal. ” &gt;&gt; &gt;» &gt;&gt; »» &gt;&gt; ” J5 ” ” &gt;» Therefore the tenure secured by a 1 per cent, amortisation fund applied in annual purchases of the bonds [the most remunerative method of employing the money, and therefore the quickest method of extinguishing the bonds) would be 36^ years, plus the five years before it came into operation, ?.&lt;?., a minimum period of 41^ years from the date of opening any one line for traffic. I do not understand the reference you have had from the Board of Trade, because we have had no communication with them on the subject. Possibly their letter’referred to some other negotiations for railways in Persia ? In any case we have not suggested any payment by the Persian Government towards the sinking fund, other than the 1 per cent, per annum which is to be provided out of the railway earnings, or by the Government if the railway earnings do not suffice to cover this 1 per cent., in addition to the working expenses, interest on bonds, &amp;c. Our syndicate, of course, desires to secure the longest tenure possible, and will bear this m mind in ananging the details of the amortisation scheme with the Persian Government. Under the Bagdad Railway concession the Germans, I believe, have a tenure of 100 years, and this we should secure if we can arrange that the amortisation be enected by annual drawings at the rate of 1 per cent. Yours, &amp;c. C. GREENWAY. Enclosure in No. 1. Contract between the Persian Government and the Persian Railway Syndicate. Contract entered into between the duly accredited representative of the Government of His Imperial Majesty the Shah of Persia (hereinafter called “ the Government ”) of the one part, and the Persian Railways Syndicate (Limited), a company incorporated under the laws of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland (hereinafter called c ‘the syndicate”), of the other part, for the survey, construc tion and working of the railways and other works hereunder mentioned, subject to the provisions of this contract. i, ■ AR T ICLE t The, Government grants to the syndicate the exclusive priviWe nig le period of this contract for the survey, construction, and working of the railways hereunder mentioned in the kingdom of Persia, to be worked entirely part by steam or by electricity, at the discretion of the syndicate [2195 /i—2] or m B9 Firstly.—A line of railway commencing from Mohammerah and [or] Khor Musa, or other convenient point adjacent thereto, and running to Khoremabad or ^Secondly. A line of railway commencing from Bunder Abbas, or other convenient^ point adjacent thereto, and running to Kerman ; . Thirdly. A line of railway commencing from Bunder Abbas, or other convenient point adjacent thereto, and running to Shiraz ; . Fourthly. A line of railway commencing from Bunder Abbas, or other convenient noint adjacent thereto, and running to Mohammerah ; and also of constructing and working a harbour or port at any of the above-mentioned termini. The expression “railways” or “railway,” where used m this contract, shall include such harbour or port. Art. 2. Unless the Government and the syndicate shall otherwise agree, the survey and construction of the said railways shall be proceeded with in the order mentioned in article 1 hereof, and, subject to the provisions hereinafter contained, the survey and construction of the said railways subsequent to the railways hereinbefore first y described shall not be proceeded with unless and until the railway immediately proceeding shall have been opened for public traffic. _ Art. 3. The Government guarantees to the syndicate that during the period of this contract it will not permit the construction of any other parallel or competing line of railway of timber or of wire cables, or any parallel or competing organised system of mechanical transport within a zone of 50 kilom. on each side of the line of any of the said railways, without the previous consent in writing of the syndicate. _ Art. 4. The Government shall grant to the syndicate, free of all cost to the syndn cate or the said railways, such zones or strips of land as may be required for the the said railways, the stations, and the appurtenances thereof, and the syndicate shall be authorised to take on such lands the timber, materials, &amp;c., which may be lequired for the construction or maintenance of such works. Ihe Government shall also, by direct grant, or by arrangement with the local chiefs or other owners, grant to the syndicate the right, free of cost, to take on other lands belonging to the Government or such local chiefs or other owners timber, materials, &amp;c., required for the construction or maintenance of such works. _ . . . Art. 5. The Government grants exemption from all import duties, navigation dues or charges, and all other fiscal dues or charges for all the materials of the said railways, rails and their accessories, rolling stock, tools, implements, machinery, instruments, apparatus, camp sheds, wire for telegraphs and fences, telegraphic and telephonic apparatus, and all other articles whatsoever which may be required for the survey, construction, working, and maintenance of the said railways, and grants to the syndi cate the right to use all rivers and roads within the Empire of Persia foi the conveyance of all such materials and things. Art. 6. The said railways and the enterprise of the survey, construction, and maintenance thereof and the receipts therefrom shall, during the period of this contract, be exempt from the payment of any Imperial, departmental, municipal, or local tax or fiscal charge, and also from any registration, transfer, or ether duty on any deeds or documents connected with the service thereof, and from stamp duties of all kinds. Art. 7. The employes, workmen, and other staff in the service of the said railways shall be deemed to be Government servants, and in such capacity shall be exempt from military service and from any civil or police duty other than in connection with the said railways. Art. 8. The Government shall furnish free of cost to the syndicate or the said railways the police or military force which may be necessary for the safety of persons or of property on any part of the said railways, both during the survey and construction thereof and after the same shall have been opened for public traffic, and shall afford the syndicate and its agents every assistance in its power to enable the syndicate or its agen ts to obtain an adequate and efficient supply of labour for the purposes of such survey and construction. Art. 9. The syndicate may import mechanics, workmen, and labourers, together with all articles for their private and domestic use, free of import duty and other fiscal imposts. Art. 10. During the period of this contract the chief officials in Persia on the said railways in connection with the construction, maintenance, and working thereof shall be British subjects to be nominated by the syndicate.Art. 11. The syndicate will commence the surveys for the tracings for the railway nereinbefore firstly described within six months from the date of this contract, and will employ competent persons to complete the same with all due diligence, and not later months from the date of this contract. The line of the said railways shall be a single track of 2 ft. 0 in. or 1 metre gauge, and shall be provided with all necessary auxiliary lines and sidings. The lines may be partly adhesive and partly rack. The curves shall be of the largest possible radius having regard to the nature of the country in which the same shall be situate. The said railways shall be provided with at least one telegraph or telephone line throughout the whole length thereof, with all necessary apparatus for working the same. Art. 13. On the completion of the said survey the syndicate shall forthwith submit to the Government the plans with the surveys of the general tracing of the said railway and the stations and the appurtenances thereof, together with a specification of the works necessary for the construction thereof and of the materials, locomotives, rolling stock, plant, and other articles and things requisite and necessary for the construction and equipment thereof, and together also with an estimate of the cost of the construction and equipment thereof. The said estimate shall include the actual cost of the construction and equipment, together with all engineering, freight, and other charges, and also an estimated amount for the payment of interest for a period of two years after the same shall have been opened for public traffic and for all expenses of and incidental to the issue of the railway bonds, mentioned in article 19 hereof, in Europe. The said estimate shall be based upon an average cost per mile or upon the cost per section, or upon such other basis as the syndicate may determine to be preferable. Art. 14. The Government shall make such criticisms or objections to the said plans, surveys, specifications, and estimates as it may think proper, and, subject to any objections which shall have been made in writing by the Government and shall not have been complied with or overcome by the syndicate and shall be still outstanding, such plans, surveys, specifications, and estimates shall be considered as approved and accepted by the Government at the expiration of six calendar months from the date of the delivery thereof to the Government. Art. 15. The said survey shall be undertaken by the syndicate at the sole cost of the Government, and the syndicate shall during such survey render to the Government monthly accounts of the costs, charges, and expenses incurred by the syndicate in connection therewith and shall submit to the Government reasonable vouchers for all such costs, charges, and expenses, and the Government shall reimburse the syndicate the costs, charges, and expenses comprised in any such account within one calendar month after such account and the vouchers relating thereto shall have been delivered to the Government. Any balance of any such costs, charges, and expenses to be incurred by the syndicate on behalf of the Government remaining unpaid shall be paid to the syndicate by the Government on or before the delivery of the plans, surveys, specifications, and estimates to the Government in accordance with article 13 hereof. The costs, charges, and expenses of such surveys may, at the option of the Government, be paid and satisfied either in cash or in Imperial State bonds similar to the recent issue of State bonds. Should the Government elect to satisfy such costs, charges, and expenses in Imperial State bonds they shall give to the syndicate notice in writing of such election, and thereupon the Government shall deposit with the Imperial Bank of Persia at the said Imperial State bonds sufficient at the price of 87jr per cent, to cover the costs, charges, and expenses to be incurred in making such surveys, with authority to such bank to deliver to the syndicate, on production of monthly certificates signed by the company’s engineer, an amount of bonds sufficient at the said price of 87^- percent, to satisfy the amount of such monthly certificate. Art. 16. At the expiration of the period of six months mentioned in article 14 hereof, thesyndicate shall have the right to construct the said railway hereinbefore firstly described upon the basis of the said plans, surveys, specifications, and estimates to be delivered by the syndicate to the Government in accordance with article 13 hereof, subject to such modifications thereof as shall have been agreed between the Government and the syndicate. The syndicate shall be at liberty to enter into any contracts with any persons or companies approved by the syndicate [sic] for the construction of the whole or any part of the said railway, or the supply of the whole or any part of the materials required for the construction or equipment thereof, provided that the liabilities of the Government and the syndicate hereunder shall not by reason of any such contract be respectively increased or diminished. The syndicate shall be entitled to retain for its own benefit the balance, if any, between the estimated cost of the construction and equipment of the said railway and the actual cost of the construction thereof for the --.than eighteen Art. 12.purpose of defraying any costs, charges, and expenses which may he incurred by the syndicate in connection with the subscription of the bonds mentioned in article 19 hereof or otherwise in relation to this contract and for its profit in connection therewith. Art. 17. Upon the completion of the said survey the syndicate shall notify the Government the period within which the said railway will be constructed, in order that^ the same may be opened for public traffic, and shall commence the construction thereof within a period of six calendar months after the bonds mentioned m article 19 shall have been issued by the syndicate, and shall proceed with the construction thereof when commenced with all due diligence, in order that the same may be opened for public traffic as speedily as the circumstances will permit. Provided that the period to be notified by the syndicate for the construction of the said railway shall be subject to such extension as the circumstances may require in the . event of the labour available for the construction thereof being inadequate or in the event of any delay arising from adverse political conditions. Art. 18. The Government will appoint a qualified British or American engineer, who shall be subject to the reasonable approval of the syndicate, for the purpose of examining the works and of certifying that the same have been constructed in accordance with the said surveys, plans, and specifications, and that the same are ready to be opened for public traffic. Art. 19. Before the syndicate shall be required to proceed with the construction of the said railway the Government shall create and the syndicate shall be authorised to issue a special loan of railway bonds sufficient at the price of 87J per cent, to provide the amount of the estimate mentioned in article 13 hereof. Such railway bonds shall constitute a direct obligation of the Government to the holders or bearers thereof, and shall carry interest at the rate of 5 per cent, per annum from the date of issue, and shall be repayable by means of an amortisation fund of 1 per cent, per annum commencing five years after the said railway shall have been opened for public traffic. The principal moneys, interest, and other moneys payable in respect of the said railway bonds shall constitute a first charge upon the railways and the net receipts of the railways mentioned in article 1 hereof, and shall be further secured by a charge or appropriation in a manner and to an extent to be approved by the syndicate upon such revenues of Southern Persia as may he applicable to the purpose and be approved. Such customs duties or other securities shall be paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia at some branch in Persia to be named by the syndicate to a special account twenty-one days prior to the date for payment of each half-year’s interest in respect of the said bonds. Should the amount so paid in not be sufficient for the payment of the said interest and to provide the proportionate part of the yearly amortisation fund, the Government shall forthwith make up any deficiency. The amounts so deposited shall be applied by the said bank in paying the interest to become due in respect of the bonds next after the date when such payment ought, in accordance with the provisions of this clause, to have been made, and the bank shall apply the balance of the moneys so deposited, or such paid; thereof as may be necessary, in redemption of the bonds in manner provided by the conditions endorsed on the bonds. Should the sums so deposited exceed the said liabilities, the Government shall be entitled to withdraw the balance in its favour immediately after the making up of each half-yearly account. The interest upon the said railway bonds during the construction of the said railway and for a period of two years after the same shall have been opened for public traffic shall be paid and provided by the syndicate so far as the provision for that purpose contained in the estimated cost will extend. Provided, however, that, should the company be prevented from constructing the railway on account of circumstances over which the syndicate has no control, the interest and amortisation fund in respect of the bonds shall, during the period that the syndicate are so prevented from constructing the railway, be paid by the Government. Art. 20. The proceeds of the issue of the said railway bonds shall be deposited in a bank in London to be approved by the syndicate to the order of the syndicate and shall be applied by the syndicate as and when required for the purpose of defraying the cost of the construction of the said railway in accordance with the plans, surveys, specifica tions, and estimates hereinbefore mentioned and of paying the interest upon the said railway bonds during the period and to the extent mentioned in article 19 hereof. Art. 21. The Government may at any time within a period of five years from the date of this contract require the syndicate to proceed with the survey of any of the railways mentioned in article 2 hereof other than the railway hereinbefore firstly described upon the same terms as are hereinbefore provided in respect of the railway hereinbefore firstly described.^ rt - 22 - ° n completion of the railway hereinbefore firstly described, or earlier if the Government and the syndicate shall so agree, the Government may require the syndicate to proceed with, or the syndicate at its option may require the Government to grant to it the right to proceed with, the construction of the railway hereinbefore secondly described upon terms identical with the terms hereinbefore contained relating I 11 fi constructlor ; of . tlie railway hereinbefore firstly described, and the syndicate shall thereupon, and subject to the provisions hereinbefore contained, be bound to proceed with due diligence with the construction and equipment of the railway hereinbefore secondly described. r Ar ^ the completion of the railway hereinbefore secondly described, or ear ler if the Government and the syndicate shall so agree, the Government mav require the syndicate to proceed with, or the syndicate at its option mav require the Government to grant to it the right to proceed with, the construction of the railway hereinbefore thirdly described upon terms identical with the terms hereinbefore contained relating to the construction of the railway hereinbefore secondly described and the syndicate shall thereupon, and subject to the provisions hereinbefore contained’ be bound to proceed with due diligence with the construction and equipment of the railway hereinbefore thirdly described. r Ar ^ 2A the completion of the railway hereinbefore thirdly described, or earlier if the Government and the syndicate shall so agree, the Government may requne the syndicate ky proceed with, or the syndicate at its option may require the Government to grant to it the right to proceed with, the construction of the railway hereinbefore fourthly described upon terms identical with the terms hereinbefore contained relating to the construction of the railway hereinbefore thirdly described and the syndicate shall thereupon^and subject to the provisions hereinbefore contained’ railway herembefore fourthl^descnbed* ^ C ° n “ ion a “ d the Art - ^ 5 - Each of the railways mentioned in article 1 hereof, as and when completed hehaff of^ ff P I 1 p 1C r tra ^ C ’ S ^ a W :T ked and administered by the syndicate on behalf of and for the benefit and at the risk of the Government, at least until such time tie whole of the railway bonds to be issued for provision of the necessary funds for the construction and equipment of the said railways, or any one of them, shall have been redeemed by means of the amortisation fund of 1 per cent, per annum to lie constituted for the redemption thereof. The syndicate shall carry on the workino- and administration of the said railways with due diligence and proper care, and shall provide a train service sufficient for the development of the traffic upon the said railways when the same shall be opened for public traffic, and shall, subject to the provision^ of this contract, so carry on the said railways as to produce the best results both for the said railways and for the district to be served thereby. , 2 .®' Tlle syndicate shall receive as its remuneration in each year for workino in Lonlr^Z , artlcl f 25 hereof, and for the expenses of its administration railways emission at the rate of 5 per cent, of the gross receipts of the said , ..A 1 ;*' f/' I ' or tke purposes of this contract the gross receipts of the said railways shall be the aggregate amounts, whether ordinary or extraordinary, which shall be niSSitesasr' p '‘ of *'• -**&gt;» “ '» 11 &gt;* i™«. a d.S.ibSMwbfSpSSSV”'’ ,h ' rf ll ” “ ld tl “” •“ (a.) Working expenses. (b .)Cost of maintenance, both ordinary and extraordinary, of the lines buildino-s materials, telegraph, telephones, &amp;c. nuuaings, (c.) Cost of the renewal of the fixed material and rolling stock. (d.) Expenses arising by reason of accidents or thefts, fires, or force majeure withthlL?d raflways. ranCe the bulldln g*. ^rchandise, or passengers in connection (/.) The remuneration of the syndicate mentioned in article 26 hereof. construction amf fo the the syndicate to pay and provide the interest during heroof l pen0t ! ? f tW0 y ears thereafter in manner mentioned in article 19 heieof, the amounts reqmred for the payment of the interest upon and the provddmi of hereof 1 ^ tisatioj i fund for any railway bonds issued in accordance with th e P provisions or foi f the n 16 pr0V1S y i ? f funds forthe construction and equipment of the said railways or tor the purposes of this contract. ^ ’ [2195 h —2] C6 If the gross receipts do not suffice to meet the above expenses, the Government will, when and so soon as the accounts of the said railways for any year shall have been completed, and within one month after payment thereof shall have been demanded by the syndicate, make up whatever deficit there may be. &lt; In the event of the gross receipts showing a surplus over the above expenses, then, subject to the pavment of any previous existing deficit, such surplus shall be carried to^ the credit of a separate account to be applied from time to time, as the circumstances of the said railways may require, in the maintenance thereof, or in the replacement of any part of the equipment thereof, or in the construction and equipment of any extension of the said railways, and until so applied the moneys standing to the credit of such account shall be invested in the name of or under the control of the syndicate ; or In the event of the gross receipts showing a surplus over the above expenses then, subject to the payment of any previous existing deficit, one-half of such surplus shall be carried to the credit of a separate account to be applied from time to tune, as the circumstances of the said railways may require, in the maintenance thereof, or m the replacement of any part of the equipment thereof, or in the construction and equipment of any extension*of the said railways, and until so applied the moneys standing to the credit of such account shall be invested in the name of or under the control of the syndicate, and the remaining half thereof shall be handed over to the Treasurer-General of the Government. . . Art. 29. The syndicate shall, during the administration of the said railways, keep proper accounts in a form usually adopted by railways, and the 1 reasurer-General of the Government, provided that such Treasurer-General be a natural-born citizen of the United States of America, shall be entitled at all times to inspect and audit such accounts. The syndicate shall in each year during the period aforesaid present to the Government a full statement of the receipts and expenditures connected with the said railways properly classified under the respective divisions of receipts and expenditure usually adopted by railways and including all expenditure mentioned in article 28 hereof. Except in so far as any objection in writing shall be raised by the accountant or accountants of the Government to the said accounts, and such objections shall remain outstanding, the said accounts shall be deemed to be binding upon the Government and the syndicate at the expiration of three months after the same shall have been delivered to the Government. Art. 30. As the traffic of the said railways so requires, the Government will from time to time, at the request of the syndicate, provide all such additional locomotives, rolling stock, installations, stations, buildings, goods-sheds, sidings, and other like conveniences necessary for the proper working of the said railways, provided that the svndicate shall not, if the Treasurer-General for the time being of the Government shall be a natural-born citizen of the United States of America, be entitled without the previous sanction of the Treasurer-General to rt quire the Government to incur any capital expenditure which would necessitate the issue by the Government of railway bonds other than as hereinbefore provided for the provision of funds for the construction and equipment of the said railways. Art. 31. The Government may require the syndicate to execute, and the syndicate will, as and when so required, execute, at the expense of the Government, all such additional works as the Government may deem necessary or expedient for the greater security of the public, or for the policing of the said railways, or for the convenience of the traffic thereon. Every such requisition shall be in writing, specifying the works to be executed, and shall be accompanied by a deposit with the bankers of the syndicate in Tehran of the agreed estimated cost of the works so specified, and during the construction of such works the amount so deposited shall be paid over to the syndicate in proportional amounts as required. Art. 32. The tariffs of the said railways shall be calculated upon a sterling basis at the current rate of exchange, and shall be fixed from time to time by the syndicate (with the approval of the 'Treasurer-General, if a natural-born citizen of the United States of America) upon the basis, as nearly as possible, of obtaining sufficient gross receipts to provide for the expenses mentioned in article 28 hereof, the object of the Government being the development of the districts to be served by the said railways by means of a tariff* as low as can be reasonably fixed, and not the receipt of profits from the said railways. * Art. 33. Public officials travelling by order of the competent authorities, and producing a certificate signed by such authorities to that effect, shall pay one-half of the tariff rates. The syndicate shall not issue any free passes to any persons other than their own directors, staff, and employes. The syndicate may in special cases issue to special persons tickets at one-half of the tariff rates.7 Art. 34. When and so soon as all the railway bonds issued pursuant to the provisions of this contract shall have been redeemed, and all moneys which shall have been advanced upon the securities of the said railways or any of them or the receipts b '^thereof shall have been repaid, and all moneys payable by the Government to the syndicate under the provisions hereof at the date of the notice shall have been paid, the Government may thereafter, on giving two years’ notice in writing, determine this contract, and at the expiration of such notice, and upon payment of any moneys payable to the syndicate by the Government under the provisions hereof at the date of such expiration, the syndicate shall place the Government in full possession of the said railways, their dependencies and equipment. Art. 35. During the continuance of this contract the syndicate will have the preferential right of constructing any extensions of the railways referred to in article 1 hereof, and also any other railways in Southern Persia which the Government may require to be constructed. Art. 36. Every obligation of the syndicate under this contract shall be subject to the exception of force majeure, and the Government will indemnify the syndicate and the enterprise of the said railways against any damages caused by Government forces or campaign or by armed forces in rebellion against the lawful Government, the amount of the damage sustained and the mode of indemnification, in default of agreement between the Government and the syndicate, to be determined by arbitration in the manner provided by article 38 hereof. In the event of the suspension of the traffic on the said railways by /orce majeure, the obligation of the Government to make good any deficit in the gross receipts of the said railways as provided by article 28 1 hereof shall be in no way affected or diminished. e Art. 37. In the event of any payment to be made by the Government hereunder 16 being made in cash, the same shall be made at the current market rate of exchange. Art. 38. In the event of any dispute or difference arising between the parties to in the present concession in respect of its interpretation or the rights or responsibilities of he either of the parties therefrom resulting, such dispute or difference shall be submitted ffls to two arbitrators at Tehran, one of whom shall be nominated by the syndicate and the the other by the Treasurer-General, and to an umpire who shall be appointed by the nail arbitrators before they proceed to arbitrate. The decision of the arbitrators, or, in the event of the latter disagreeing, that of the umpire, shall be final, rom ives, like lithe shall violis ipitai bonds nand .dicate 1 suet treater 0 ence of orksto icatek truetioa ortionai basis af radical United ,j)t ^ross ■ t of tte Iff aysMinute Paper. Register No. kSoi ^ Letter from dQ Date. Initials. Under Secretary / JV^. Secretary of State Committee .......j Under Secretary Secretary of State / n -ir / Secret Department. Dated Rec. Ishr&amp;cfc&amp;i 191 / SUBJECT. drStCK . FOR INFORMATION. uui\ Previous Papers :—CONFIDENTIAL Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received October 31, T50 p.m.) (No. 530.) M- 1 Tehran, October 31, I9ll, T30 p.m. MY telegram No. 463 [ ]. Britisli consul at Moliammerah reports that sheikh is willing to follow our advice, but that he suggests that, with the Bakhtiaris in power, it is possible he may receive a rude answer to his communication, which would entail his taking a firm attitude, in which case he would require our support. In view of Shuster’s decision not to submit Persian Railway Syndicate’s scheme to the Medjliss, I have, with the concurrence of Cox, instructed British consul that it would be better for the sheikh to defer making the proposed communication to the Persian Government for the present. It should, however, not be forgotten that article 4 of the contract regarding free grant of land by Persian Government will sooner or later give a good deal of trouble as regards the sheikh’s territory, and also as regards the property of important private owners.CONFIDENTIAL. 230^^ %eir^ Mr. 0 Beirne to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received October 27, 3*15 p.m.) (ho. 259.) St. Petersburqh, October 27, 1911, 2'45 p.m. PER SIAN rail w ays. . 1 | iave informed Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs verbally of the substance of j^\ &gt; your telegram No. 640 [ ]. His Excellency made no comment. Since the Russian Government are desirous of postponing the construction of the line running from the south towards their sphere I do not know whether they will welcome proposed negotiations with a Russian group which mav tend to remove syndicate s present difficulties. (Sent to Tehran.) i 1973-299 JliS'oi CONFIDENTIAL. IVE {! 3Q0CT1911 £- &lt;&gt;/r Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay {Tehran). (N°. 32-1) rTT . , T1 „ Foreign Office, October 28, 1911, 12'30 p.m. . MR. MAL1ER HEAPS recently called here in connection with very comprehensive scheme for construction of railways in Persia, for which a Swiss M. Paul Zuber working with a Frenchman, M. Degoy, were working to obtain a concession, and for which they had received Persian assurances of support. He said chief backers were Persian representatives in Berlin and Constantinople, who had apparently sounded various persons in Persia. The scheme does not appear to me very serious, but I should be glad to learn whether you have heard anything of it ii W JtCONl'lDEJMTIM ♦ -fc * S 17 Edwcii d Grey to Sit G. Barclay {Tehvaii), A 7 o. 318, and Mr. O’Beime (St. Peters~ - butyh), No. 640. ( tiA^G n ^ Foreign Office, October 24, 1911. M\ telegram Ao. 315 to Tehran [of 23rd October]. • ^ ave yet decided to send a representative to St. Petersburgh. I am urging them to do so, and am telling them that any scheme for a railway concession extending into the Russian sphere of interest will have no chance of success unless Russian Government agree to it, and will receive no support from me. (For St. Petersburgh only.) You should inform Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs.53 JL tf433 «; CONFIDENTIAL. 1) 240CT19 Ng, ' V' - 'P,\' -Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 313.) CwqN Foreign Office, October 20, 1911. YOUR telegram No. 499 [of 17th October]. Syndicate are considering question of sending a representative to St. Petersburgh to discuss possible prolongation of railway lines by Russia into Russian sphere^ i I ' i [973—239] 3 t'Minute Paper. Letter from Register No. kUZb Secret Department. Dated Bee. /g Grc^blr^ lo *• 191 / . Date. Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary Cud $crS(c\ Secretary of State n \!K /7 ^ Committee / Under Secretary Secretary of State / I Copy to ( £ ZLj. • U FOR INFORMATION. | f Previous Papers:4f-£f 3&gt;'^&gt; l T^&gt; CONFIDENTIAL. ,1^\: &lt;£i Her -{Received October 17, 2'45 p.m.) Tehran, October 17, 1911, 2‘30 p.m. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edirard Grey. (No. 499.) (l^S ^ 0 L lx teJegram No. 308. I have already drawn the attention of Shuster to the rescript of 1888, and told him i thought we should msist on railways in the south being under British control. It would perhaps be better to postpone any more formal warning for the moment as I see no disposition on the part of Shuster to look beyond Persian Railway Syndicate, provided that it can negotiate on lines acceptable to Medjliss. I regret having given the impression he was lukewarm ; on the contrary, he is, I believe, most anxious to negotiate with. I ersian Railway Syndicate, if possible. i w L ±ear ; ! i( TI er ’ ^ lf syndicate cannot negotiate on lines acceptable to Mediliss, not be deterred by the rescript from attempting to negotiate with other groups more amenable to Persian prejudice regarding spheres of interest. 1 with T tll t 1 i n ' k ’ hel P ma fers if the syndicate could arrive at an understanding with Russia. In this case, ana if Shuster obtains from Medjliss powers he desires syndicate could continue to negotiate wdth good hope of success C ^PV TO indTa j 191/.^(0 CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay [Tehran). (No. 308.) j/ Foreign Office, October 16, 1911. 4 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 487 [ ]. Do you consider tliat anything should he said to Shuster in the nature of warning him that we should not allow a concession for a line from Mohammerah to the north to be given to “whom he pleases,” and of enquiring of him what are his reasons for his apparent change of attitude towards the Persian Railway Syndicate ? From the last paragraph of your telegram he appears very lukewarm towards them. I should be glad also to know whether you think that it would help matters if the Persian Railway Syndicate endeavoured to arrive at an understanding with Russia. I j ti [973—165] Win f I !CONFIDENTIAL. ^(0 t &gt;&lt;oe'Vf7&gt;V' 1400 Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received October 13, 8 p.m.) (No. 487.) (t^ Tehran, October 18, 1911, 1T0 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 308 [of 12th October]. I agree that it would be better to drop all mention of Burujird and the extensions, as there is no chance of the Medjliss accepting the scheme whether they are mentioned or not. For the scheme to be palatable to the Medjliss, invasion of Russian sphere would have to be more definitely indicated. Question is perhaps only academic, as I gather that Shuster has abandoned any intention of presenting scheme to the Medjliss. He attributes their adverse [group undecypherable] to our attitude in the Stokes affair, which brought the spheres into additional prominence, but I think that, even without this, he would have found Medjliss more difficult than he hoped. Shuster now hopes to be given free hand by Medjliss before it rises to negotiate a railway loan with whom he pleases (Persian Railway Syndicate not excluded) on similar lines to those of the syndicate’s contract, but for the construction of line from Julfa to Mohammerah via Tabreez, Kazvin, and Hamadan. [972—162]WO [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] TV EASTERN DEPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. CcfcLVjLd \ ^X. /r r [October 6.] Seotiok 1. [38746] No. 1. Foreign Office to Mr. Greenway. Sir, _ Foreign Office, October 6, 1911. I AM directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to state that, at the inception of the negotiations respecting the concession for the Mohammerah-Khoremabad Railway, a promise was given by His Majesty’s Government that, before the construction of the line was actually commenced, they would enter into a friendly discussion with the Russian Government. I am now to notify you of this undertaking for the information of the Persian Railway Syndicate. I am further to inform you that, as regards article 4 of the draft contract enclosed in your letter of the 7th September, it will be necessary to obtain the acquiescence of the Sheikh of Mohammerah. Sir G. Barclay has therefore been instructed to authorise His Majesty’s consul-general at Bushire to communicate to Sheikh Khazzal the general terms of the article in question. I am, &amp;c. LOUIS MALLET.Lt-'b'rr CONFIDENTIAL Sir Edward Grey to Mr. O’Beirne (St. Petersburgh). (No. 613.) / Foreign Office, October 12, 1911, 7‘30 p.m. / Ml telegram No. 303 [of 12th October] to Tehran and your telegram No. 240 C ]• As the scheme is m suspense for the moment and may be modified, it will be bettei to say nothing for the present to the Russian Government.CONFIDENTIAL. Cf-3^r ^f) Si?' Edward G?'ey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 303.) (Foreign Office y October 12, 191], 7*30 p.m. IT appears from your telegram No. 484 [ ] that the Medjliss would reject the scheme because it recognises the spheres of interest, whereas it is not improbable that Russia will view it with suspicion on account of the mention of Burujird, and of the reference to the extensions, although it is of course understood that the syndicate would come to an arrangement with Russia before making arrange ments for construction of the Mohammerah line, and that there would be no question of the extensions being constructed by the syndicate; these were merely mentioned to make the scheme palatable to the Medjliss. I am, however, anxious to avoid giving any cause for suspicion of our intentions on the part of the Russian Government, whose good-will is essential to the accom plishment of the object in view, so that I think it will be better to drop all mention of Burujird and of the extensions, as it is clear that so far as the Medjliss is concerned their inclusion has failed of its effect. I should like your observations. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 612.) 1972—150JCONFIDENTIAL. (* 13 OCT 1 S11 c ) Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 302.) u&gt; Foreign Office, October 12, 1911, 6 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 476 [ ]. We need not communicate details to the Russian Government until construction is arranged for, but if Russia’s objection to the clause in the Seligman loan contract respecting the retention of the Treasurer-General develops, we must be prepared to drop the analogous clause in the railway syndicate’s contract, and are so informing Mr. Greenway. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 609.)CONFIDENTIAL. » Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received October 12, 1T35 a.m.) / Tehran, October 12, 1911, 1'30 p.m. MY telegram No. 476. Slu^ter tells me that, after sounding the Cabinet and the leading deputies, he thinks that it is better not to submit the railway scheme to the Medjliss. He finds even the moderate party very cool towards the limitations which are dictated by the spheres of influence. [973—116JCONFIDENTIAL. (, iiocnsn ; % y » 1 ^ Mr. 0 Beirne to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received October 10, 9*15 p.m.) (•^ 0 - J^O.) / St. Petersburgh, October 10, 1911, 8 p.m. YOUR telegram, No. 593 [ ]. • firSt line a PP lied for is . t0 “Khoremabad or Burujird,” might it not be desirable that I should inform Russian Government that you have made it clear to the syndicate that they cannot expect the support of His Majesty’s Government as regards any portion of projected line extending into Russian sphere? Russian Government Burujird erW1Se SUSpeCt US of su PP ortin g a British concession for a railway up toCONFIDENTIAL. . . &lt; /r~' ■ . k ' ^ K'‘ A ' . A-V v P. , i-' ' Sir Edward Grey to Mr. O’Beirne (St. PetersburgK). (No. 593.) R. Foreign Office, October 9, 1911. SECTION goes to you by bag to-night. You should merely inform Russian Government what the four lines are, adding the statement as instructed in my telegram No. 584 [of 4th October], [973—110][T Ms Document -is the ^Property of His Brit^nnie Majesty s Govsysiroent. EASTERN DEPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. 8 3EP1911 CT [August 30.] Section 2. [33565] No. 1. Mr. Mallet to Mr. G. Greenway. Dear M r - G reenway, 30&gt; 19n Depaitments interested have now had time to consider your letter of the 11th August, enclosing a precis of the proposed terms of the draft contract which the ersian Kail ways Syndicate are submitting to the Persian Government. • I- S u Stem ° n the 1 contract as at P^sent drafted is based (that described m the third paragraph of your letter) has the disadvantage that the Persian Govern- ment would be able at^any time, if they could produce the money, to buy out your syndicate at two years ^ notice. _ Apart from this, the system indicated is doubtless pre erable from every point of view to that described in the succeeding paragraph, and the objection to it which I h a ve noted above might be met bv providing thaf bonds should not be redeemed otherwise than by the operation of the sinking fund, and that the redemption should not proceed at more than a prescribed rate during a given teWmnhed e tn 8 T 1 See ^ rom Ae amended draft of the contract which was actuaRy teleg aphed to Tehran (enclosed in your letter of the 16th August), that you have nserted m article 7 a provision to the effect that the sinking fund of 1 per cent, shall not come into operation for a period of five years after the opening of the line to S a 7 1 ^ and lt; ap P ears fl i°. lla a lett er which we have received from the Board of Trade that the syndicate would favour the insertion of a further provision that the Persian Government s payment towards a sinking fund for the redemption of the bond issue s ould not durmg a period of twenty or twenty-five years exceed the rate of 1 per cent. . ills wo ? ld seci R' e to the syndicate a tenure of twenty-five or thirty years in all, and T 0l i e h ? S ? le oVfiEon to the scheme, more especially in view of the fact that the chance of the Persian Government being able to pay off the bonds is exceedingly remote. J . 1 C’hserve that m article 7 of the revised draft the words “ uncharged surplus of ” are inserted before the words ‘ the customs duties of Southern Persia.” This amendment anticipates an objection which we should have had to make As regards article 16, His Majesty’s Government contemplate surveying the ushire Eiruzabad Shiraz road, with a view to the possibility of adapting it for motor traction. If it is decided that this is practicable and desirable, and if the plan is earned out, some arrangement could no doubt be arrived at with the syndicate . ^ ® not h } G the inclusion of article 22 in the contract. It would of course be impossible to avoid a recourse to His Majesty’s Minister in practice if a dispute had to be settled through the diplomatic channel, but it seems to us undesirable thus to appoint him as arbitrator In a dispute between the Persian Government and the syndicate he would certainly be suspected by the former of bias in favour of the latter and he woukl be placed m the invidious position of being both judge and advocate! - m lt k n ° t r 6 pr ? v [ de(i mst | ac | that disputes, if they cannot be settled by negotiation, , parties referred to 0ne t ^ ie ot ^ er fore ig n representatives selected by the two J Yours sincerely, LOUIS MALLET. [2150 99 -2] ''copy TO INDIA i S3/£L.191.L. j secnitAnv'sNR mi lin —*surplus customs duties Southern Persia or other securities approved by syndicate. Customs duties or other securities to be paid by Government officials as collected to Imperial Bank of Persia to meet above liabilities as they become due. 8. Syndicate to provide interest on bonds during construction^ and two years after. If works delayed by force majeure or circumstances over which syndicate no control, Government to pay interest during period works delayed. 9. Government may any time within five years date contract require syndicate proceed with survey of the three other lines or any of them on same terms as first railway. 10. On completion of first railway, Government may require syndicate, or syndicate may require Government, to allow them proceed with construction of second, third, and/or fourth railways on same terms as first railway. 11. Railways when completed to be worked by syndicate on behalf of and at expense of Government, syndicate to be entitled to, as remuneration, 5 per cent, gross receipts. Government to make good any deficiency in working. 12. On redemption of bonds and payment of all money due to syndicate, Govern ment may take over and work railways on giving two years’ notice. 13. Necessary lands to be provided free. 14. Government to provide free of cost effective protection of all working parties. 15. Exemption of taxes, materials imported free, duties same as in draft mining concession. 16. No other mechanical transport to be permitted within 50 miles without consent of syndicate. 17. Government to appoint qualified European engineer, to be approved by syndicate, to certify work. 18. Chief officials of railways to be English. 19. Tariff to be on gold basis and fixed by syndicate. 20. Full force majeure clause. 21. Exchange to be taken at current market rate. 22. Disputes to be settled by British Minister. This draft has been submitted to Foreign Office, be sent in a few days. Their eomment[s] [upon] will[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] EASTERN DEPARTMENT. [August 12.] SECRET SERIES. [31788] No. 1. 25 AUG 1911 ,v DEPp Section 2. Anglo-Persian Oil Company to Foreign Office.—{Received August 12.) Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, Dear Mr. Mallet, August 10, 1911. I THINK you will like to know that the constitution and membership of the Persian Railways Syndicate was finally settled at a meeting of the proposed subscribers which was held at my office yesterday. The capital of the syndicate has been fixed at 15,000/., and the subscribers so far arranged are as follows :— Representing the Anglo-Persian Oil Company group— The Right Hon. Lord Strathcona and Mount Royal Mr. W. K. D’Arcy .. Mr. J. T. Cargill Mr. C. W. Wallace .. Mr. C. Strick Mr. C. Greenway Mr. J. R. Preece Representing the Imperial Bank of Persia group— Sir Thomas Jackson, Bart. Sir Thomas Gordon .. Mr. V. A. C. Hawkins Representing the British India Steam Navigation Company group Lord Inchcape Mr. W. A. Buchanan Sir John Ellerman, Bart. Representing the British and Foreign General Securities (Limited)— Mr. T. B. Bowring .. Mr. Alex. B. Williamson Sir Hugh S. Barnes .. and Investments Representing S. Pearson and Sons (Limited)— Lord Cowdray Sir Clarendon G. Hyde Representing the Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company— Mr. H. B. Lynch Sir Charles Nicholson, Bart. .. Lieutenant-Colonel H. Picot .. Mr. J. F. Lynch Mr. G. Allen Sir Montague C. Turner Sir Alexander McRobert Lieutenant-Colonel H. Picot .. Trust £ 500 425 425 425 625 425 175 1,000 750 750 313 312 625 200 200 225 625 625 1,250 1,250 1,250 1,250 200 200 175 300 In reserve * Total The board has been constituted as follows : Mr. Y. A. C. Hawkins. Sir Clarendon G-. Hyde. Mr. C. Greenway. Mr. J. R. Preece, C.M.G. Mr. H. B. Lynch. Lieutenant-Colonel H. Picot. 14,500 500 .. 15,000 The post of chairman is for the time being left vacant. [2150 m—2]As you are aware, it was desired that Sir Hugh S. Barnes should take the chairmanship, but as there are official objections to this we shall have to arrange for some other suitable gentleman to occupy this position. The names of Lord Lamington and Sir Mortimer Durand, either of whom is, I believe, willing to act, have been suggested, but pending some clearing up of the present political situation in Persia it is thought desirable to leave the appointment of chairman in abeyance unless some person of less pronounced views on Persian politics can be found. At the meeting which was held yesterday the present political situation was discussed, and a very strong feeling was expressed in favour of a representation being made to the British Government as to the extreme desirability of their giving their very strongest support to the endeavours of the Treasurer-General of Persia to carry out the financial reforms so necessary for the establishment of constitutional government and for the general welfare and future development of the country. I was requested to call upon you to lay the views of the members of the syndicate before you, but at a subsequent meeting with Sir Thomas Jackson I arranged with him to call upon you for that purpose either to-day or to-morrow, and he will explain to you fully the views of the syndicate. Yours sincerely, C. GREENWAY.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.! EASTERN DEPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. Vc 35AUG 191 j ' [August 10.] Section 1, [31522] No. 1. Anglo-Persian Oil Company to Foreign Office.—(Received August 10, 1911.) House, Old Broad Street, &amp;U ’ T • * 1 , , , . , London, August 9, 1911. I BEG to enclose copy of telegram which I received yesterday from Mr. D. Brown with reference to the application for railway concessions. I have, &amp;c. C. GREENWAY, Managing Director. Enclosure in No. 1. Mr. Brown to Mr. Greenway. THERE is strong feeling (?) here in favour of pressin^T^ml^s) 1 'to secme(s) development(s) of country m event of any political change (?). It is essential, therefore, that you telegraph immediately draft(s) contract in order that I may press(es) forward without delay(s). To ensure secrecy telegraph via Eastern.[Tte_poenment is the Property of His Britannic M a .i fiR t.v’ g 1 EASTERN DEPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. [July 20.] Section 3. [28487] No. 1. Anglo-Persian Oil Company to Foreign Office.—(Received July 20.) Q - Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London bir ’ tttaw+u 1 , ! A July 19, 1911. 1 ] 6 hono ^ r to en S &gt; lo ® e C0 PT of a telegram which I have just received from our agent m Tehran re Persian Kail way concession. I have, &amp;c. C. GREENWAY. Enclosure in No. 1. Mr. Brown to Mr. Greenway. ^ 'RFH-TTMT i r m t , / x Tehran, July 19, 1911. KlibliN 1 expressed approval of railways syndieate(s) (in) their (his) opinion Persian Government could continue line to Hamadan. He suggested we should connect(s) (with) Ispahan with Khoramabad and/or Kerman or Shiraz. Treasurer General states that southern customs already fully mortgaged, and inland revenue at present entirely worthless as a (an) secunty(ies) ; but as soon as he has put new organisation m order he will be able provide ample security(ies) for railwavfsl construction, and will give his full support to our proposals. J ' ' [2123 m—3]FOREIGN OFFICE, August 21, 1911. ^Immediate. Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 17th instant, relative to the terms of the contract which the Persian Railways Syndicate propose to present to the Persian Government in connexion with the con- ich they are about to apply for the 'kk® Syndicate should be asked to put ^ forward in the first instance the latter of the two alternative bases of agreement detailed in their communication of the 11th instant. -mit to you herewith copies of a letter from the Board of Trade, who were also consulted on the subject, suggesting a means by which, in their view, the objection to the former alternative which was urged in the letter from this Office of the 15th instant would be removed, and of a telegram from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran, giving reasons for preferring the alternative. to agree with the Board that their suggestion obviates the disadvantages which would otherwise attach to this course and to recognise the advantage of adopt- railways in Persia in which it is With reference to this point I am do trans- I am to state that Sir E. Grey is disposed -ing Ihe Undersecretary of State for India.2. -ing it pointed out by Sir G. Barclay and that he would suggest, if the Marquess of Crewe shares this view, that the Syndicate should be informed according- -iy. I am to add that, from the point of view of the Syndicate, this procedure would have the further advantage of absolving them from the necessity of redrafting the contract. I am to request the favour of an early reply to this letter. lam, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant0 ^ ^ I u mediate and Confidential . 32759). Sir: - BOARD OF TRADE, (Commercial Department), G-WYDYR HOUSE, V/HITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. August 18th 1911. I am directed by the Board of Trace to acknowledge the receipt of your letter (unnumbered) of the 15th August, with enclosures, on the subject of the proposals put forward by the Persian Railway Syndicate, and to of fer the following observations thereon for the considera tion of Sir E.Grey. The arrangement proposed by the Syndicate, and summarised in the draft telegram forwarded to your De partment by Mr.Greenway, is of a somewhat unusual char acter . The practice generally adopted is for a conces sion, subsidised or not, to be granted for the con struction and working of a line for a definite term, at the end of which the line reverts to the State, there be ing generally a provision allowing of purchase at an earlier date on prescribed terms. Subsidies, where given, may take the form of either a mileage construc tion payment, or a guarantee of a minimum revenue per mile ! Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.mile, or a guarantee of interest on capital. In some Cases (as in the Argentine) concessions limited in dura tion have subsequently been made perpetual, and in others the concessionaire companies have been bought out by an issue of State bonds. Another arrangement sometimes made is for a government to construct a line and then to lease its working, either for a fixed annual rental or for a percentage of the gross earnings. iho iioard, however, see no objection to the scheme of the Syndicate other than that indicated in your let- ui, i -Ply, namely, that the Persian Government i/vould, as the scheme stands, be able to buy out the British Company at two years’ notice, it would appear possible, however, to obviate this objection by provid ing that Bonds should not be redeemed otherwise than by the operation of the Sinking Fund, and that the redemp tion ohou Id not proceed at more than a prescribed rate during a given period of years. From informal communi cations with the Syndicate the Board understand that paragraph 7 of the proposed heads of contract has been amended by the insertion of a provision to the effect thatthat the Government Sinking, Fund of one per cent shall not come into operation for a period of five years after the opening of the line for traffic, and that the Syndi cate would view with favour the insertion of a further proviso that the Persian Government's payment towards a Sinking Fund for the redemption of the bond issue should not, during a further period of twenty or twenty-five years, exceed the above-mentioned rate of one per cent per annum. This would secure to the Concessionaire Com pany a tenure of 25 or 30 years in all; and would, in the opinion of the Department, meet the objection to the present scheme which Sir E.Grey appears to have in mind. The Board are not aware if there is anything in the constitution of the Syndicate which would prevent any pa^t ox the holding, either during construction of the railway or later when the Syndicate is operating as a working company, from passing into foreign hands. Whilst, in view of the constitution of the Syndicate, they do not regard this as a serious contingency, they think it desirable to invite the attention of Sir E.Grey to it as a possible occurrence. Subjectoubject to these observations the Board are dis posed to think that the scheme now put forward by the Syndicate might be approved by Sir E.Grey, should he see no objection on other grounds, as more likely than the second plan suggested by Mr.Greenway, to be viewed with favour by both the Persian Government and the British investor, to whom Government Bonds are as a rule more attractive than guaranteed shares. I have &amp;c., (Signed) Geo.J.Stanley.4c^1 CONFIDENTIAL Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 19, 3*50 p. M j Tehran, August 19, 1911, 3 35 p.m (No. 341.) YOUR telegram No. 235. Second alternative is, of course, at first sight the more attractive, both from point of view of possible profits and also as appearing to give more assurance of permanence &gt; • kut the Piphts seem to be remote, and, on the other hand, chance of Persia’s being able of herself to pay oh railway bonds is so distant as to be negligible and the contingency of our not being able to prevent her borrowing from elsewhere for the purpose need not, I hope, be contemplated. Moreover, unless the temper of Mediliss changes, prospect c&gt;f obtaining second alternative is more than doubtful. First alternative is more in accordance with views of those who count in the Mediliss I therefore recommend first alternative. J If it could be obtained, a stipulation that disputes between syndicate and Persian Government should be settled by His Majesty’s Minister would of course be very useM to syndicate, but would it not place Minister in an invidious position to have to act both as advocate and judge ? It might be arranged that such disputes, if they cannot be settled by negotiation, should be referred to some foreign representative at iehran to be selected by the two parties.bir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay {Tehran). (No. 15, 1911. t1l , , p . i ajlway syndicate has been formed, consisting of representatives of the An lo-fersian Oil Company, the Imperial Bank of Persia, the British India Steam TrusfVeor ''''To ' 16 ’ l | l, ! S J .S 11 '! |, ' ,jrcl S' 11 General Securities and Investments Pi iist, feaisons and Sons, and the Exiphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company. draft eo “* ract &gt; and enquire our viewsjas to ; basis of concession— until such time '• r ° rk there . on bellalf of the Persia n Government tlme a .s the latter are m a position to pay off the railway bonds or (2) whether a British railway company should be formed to work the railway on required. 11 aCC ° Unt ’ the Perslan Government guaranteeing the interest on the capital I am consulting India Office and Board of Trade, but should also be &lt;dad of vour by Ihe British Mhhster ^ t0 Stlpulatio11 P ro P osed that dis P^ee should be settled i 33 [730—271]33 Ucn\J LThkDocument is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Gov emmP .»t. 1 EASTERN DEPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. [30338] No. 1. [August 5.] Section I. Foreign Office to Mr. Greenway. Sll% r a t\i j• i , n ^ Foreign Office, August h, l§l\. 1 AM directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your Jetter or the loth ultimo, forwarding copy of the memorandum handed by you to the Persian special representative at the Coronation and to the Persian Minister at this ouit, giving a sketch of the proposals of the Persian railways syndicate with regard to railway construction in Persia. l A 1 f m t ° ? x P r . ess , t0 y° u Sir Grey’s thanks for this communication, and to state he finds nothing m the memorandum to which His Majesty’s Government could object. t , f™, t0 °y. however, with regard to the proposed extensions of the first three of the projected lines, of the intended construction of which Sir E. Grev now hears for the first time, that they will end at points touching, or within, the border of the Russian sphere of influence in Persia, and that Sir E. Grey accordingly presumes tha m view of the terms of article 1 of the Anglo-Russian Arrangement of the St ugust, 1907, the syndicate will not ask for the support of His Majesty’s Government m connection with them. J y S r F rey unc ^ rstands t^t the syndicate have no intention of applying immediately for concessions to build these extensions. I am, &amp;c. LOUIS MALLET. COPY TO INDIA /g [2150 —1]? iltoDocnment is the_Property of His Britannic MaiestVs . 1911 EASTERN D EPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. [August 2.] Section 1, [30491] No . i Anglo-PersianOil Company to Foreign Office.—(Received August 2.) o* W inchester Tlouse, Old Broad Street. Condon, ’ T , , August I, 1911. lbe&lt;lrait concession referred to will, I hope, be dispatched in a few days. I have, &amp;c. C. GREENWAY, Managing Director. Enclosure in No. 1. Mr. Brown to Mr. Greenway. (Telegraphic.) TIME(S) very favourable for puttin secunty(ies) to be arranged for later. Do concession. Tehran, July 31, 1911. g through railway(s) concession leaving you approve of? Send immediately draft [2150 6—1] COPY To qt i 33CONFIDENTIAL. TJnsDocw^ is the property oj_ the Secretary of State for India in Council Immediate. Sir, India Office, 17th August 1911 I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 15th instant regarding the terms of the concession for which the Persian Railways Syndicate propose to apply, the Marquess of Crewe agrees with the Secretary of State for oreign Affairs that it would be preferable that the railways should be permanently British undertakings—although the concession in its present form may not only be more acceptable to the Persian Govern ment but may also be more easy for His Majesty’s Government to defend against the criticism with which it is likely to meet from Russia, as regards the Mohammera-Khorremabad line, at all events. He would therefore, suggest that Mr. Greenway might be asked to put forward the’ alternative in the first instance; and by way of diminishing the attrac- iveness of the form of concession which the Persian Government are understood to prefer, it might be provided in Clause 12 that if the rai way^ is purchased at short notice the price to be paid will be proportionately higher. Such a provision is usually made in Indian railway contracts. As regards the Southern Customs, Lord Crewe sees no objection to th^B vTp part ° f the SeCUrity pr0vided that i,; i® clearly stated that the British Government s loan and the recent Persian loan have priority Mr Shuster succeeds m reorganising Persian finances it seems not improbable that the yield of the Southern Customs will largely expand and suffice for all these purposes. In Clause 7 of the draft telegram the reference should be to Clause 3 (not 2), and in Clause 10 “ 1st, 2nd, and/or 3rd railways ” should apparent y e 2nd 3rd, and/or 4th.” It is presumably intended that construction of these three railways should be proceeded with in the order named in Clause 1. H . ^ “j™ With ClauS6 16 Mr - he informed that His Majesty s Government contemplate surveying the Bushire-Firuzabad- bv Mr Ch ad W le r°T the P0SS , ibility of motor Action, as recommended iy Mr. Chick (see Mr. Langley s letter No. 26,479, of 20th July) The Persian Railways Syndicate would, no doubt, come to terms should it desiraMe^ ^ deCKle&lt;I &amp; m0t ° r r ° ad W ° Uld be P racticaW e and 1 have the honour to be, Sir, 1 our most obedient servant, r™ TT . 0 (Signed) E. Montagu. ihe Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.FOREIGN OFFICE, August 15, 1911 With reference to the letter from this Office of the 5th instant relative to the Question of rail- -way construction in Persia, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a further communication from Mr. Greenway enclosing a summary of the contract which the Persian Railways Syndicate propose to submit to the Persian Government. As regards the 3rd and 4th paragraphs of Mr. Greenway’s letter itself, ijam to enquire what are the views of the Marquess of Crewe. It would probably be easier to obtain a concession based on the system described in the 3rd paragraph, but it has the disad- -vantage that the Persian Government would be able at any time, if they could produce the money, to buy out the British Company at two years notice. As regards the terms of the contract, Sir E. Grey is disposed to inform MR. Greenway that the inclusion of the customs receipts of Southern Persia among the securities assigned by Article 7 for the provision of the interest on the bonds to be issued in connexion with the construction of the line, is inadmissible, these revenues, as he is aware, being already pledged to His Majesty’s Government, Sir E. Grey would also prefer that the stip- -ulation that disputes between the contracting parties should The Under- Secretary of State for India9 should he settled hy His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran ( Article ) should not form part of the agreement. I am to require that a reply may he returned to this letter with as little delay as pay he conven- -ient. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humb1e s e r vant,( Copy ) rf Winchester H6use, Old Broad Street, E,C. Dear Mr. Mallet, August 11, 19H. I sent you on the 9th inst. a copy of a telegram which I had received from Mr. Brown asking me to telegraph immediately the terms of the Draft Railway Contract which he is to arrange with the Persian Government. The full contract has not yet been drafted, tut our Lawyers have drawn up for the purposes of a telegram the enclosed pfgcis of the proposed terms and before despatch- -ing it I should be obliged if you will let me know if you nave any alt-era.'tions to suggest* As you will see the terras proposed are on the basis of the Syndicate entering into a Contract to construch the Railways, and to work them on behalf of the Persian Government until such time as the latter are in a position to pay off the Railway Bonds which are to be issued to cover the cost ; this being the form in which we understand the Persian Government are desirous of granting any Railway Concessions. ohould the Government however be desirous of granting the Concessions on the basis of a British Railway Company being fcrmed to work the Railways on their own account the Persian Government guaranteeing the interest on any Capital required our Syndicate will of course be equally ready to enter into a Contract on these lines. I shall be glad to have your reply at the earliest possible moment as it is evident from MR. Brown's telegram of the 5th inst. that there is great urgency in the natter. Louis Mallet Esq.,C.B. Yours sincerely (signed) C. GreenwayHie following are heads of Contract which Persian Railway Syndicate Ltd. are prepared to accept from Government. government to grant Syndicate exclusive right to construct following railways (a) From Mohammerah and/or Khoe Musa to Khorarnia- -had or Burmgird (h) From Bunder Ahhas to Kerman (c) From Bunder Ahhas to Shiraz (d) From Bunder Ahhas to Mohammerah and also harbour or port at any of above coastal termini with prefer- -ential right construct extensions of any of above railways and other railways in Southern Persia, Syndicate to commence survey first railway within 6 months. Plans specifications first railway to be submitted on completion survey together with estimate cost construction and equipment. Such cost to include engineering freight and other charges interest during construction and two years after and cost of financing scheme in Europe. Plans &amp;c. deemed accepted by Government if not objected to in 6 months afa&amp;r delivery. Survey at cost of Government and to he paid at Government’s option in cash or Imperial State Bonds similar to recent issue on monthly certificates. If in Bonds Government to deposit with Imperial Bank of Persia sufficient amount of Bonds at 87i p.c. to cover cost of survey with authority Bank to deliver Bonds to Syndicate on production monthly certificates, • Syndicate to have right construct first Railway on plans &amp;c. as approved. Line to he single track 2 ft. 6 in. or one metre gauge and have telegraph—* ' 7. ^ fiv*w 8 . 9. 11 . 12, 10 . or telephone line. Prior construction first Railway Government to issue to Syndicate 5% Bonds at 87i%, sufficient to provide estimated cost under clause above Bonds to constitute direct liability of Government for payment principal interest and Sinking Fund of 1% and to be first charge on railway and railway receipts and cus- -toms duties Southern Persia or other securities approved by Syndicate. Customs duties or other securities to be paid half yearly to Imperial Bank of Persia to meet above liabilities as they become due* Syndicate to provide interest and Sinking Fund on Bonds during construction and 2 years after. If Works delayed by force majeure or circumstances over which Syndicate no control Government to pay interest}’and Sinking Fund during period Works delayed. Government may any time within 5 years date eentraot Contract require Syndicate proceed with survey of the three ojher lines or any of them on same terms as first railway. On completion first railway Government may require Syndicate or Syndicate may require Government to allow them proceed with construction of 1st 2nd and/or 3rd railways on same terms as 1st railway. Railways when completed to be worked by Syndicate on behalf and at expense of Government, Syndicate to be entitled to 5 p.c. gross receipts. Government to make good any deficiency in working. On redemption of Bonds and payment all moneys due Syndicate. Government may take over and work railways on giving two years notice. Necessary lands to be provided free. Government to provide free of cost effective protection of all working parties. ■ I I15. exemption of taxes materials imported, free duties, same as in mining concession. i ' 0 ° 1; ' ller mechanical transport to he permitted within 50 miles without consent Syndicate. Government to appoint qualified European engineer to oe approved by Syndicate to certify work. Chief officials of Railway to be English. Tariff to be on gold basis and fixed by Syndicate. Full force rnajeure clause. Exchange to be take at current market rates. Disputes to settled by British Minister.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Govemm^n EASTERN DEPARTMENT. (iVy [July 26.J SECRET SERIES. Section 1. [29103] No. 1. Foreign Office to Anglo-Persian Company. Dear Mr. Greenway, 2 ^ • ^ ^ _ IN the absence of Mr. Mallet, who will be awav till 1911. I answer your letter to him of the 22nd July on the subject oTraOways fn PeTsia 111011 * 11 ’ note t e alterations introduced into your instructions to Mr. Brown as shown in the memorandum handed by you to Ala-es-Sultaneh and Mehdi Khan. Mr. Mallet will, no doubt, be happy to receive von on hio r-o+n n • i while you may like to know that this Office has' also bL in coirespoSlence^ilh faiW?Se ° 18 aCtag ° n behalf ° f th6 fiuS8iai1 theTanXffian Government 8 shouM°be Xnged^Ldlve 6 bShed^the^uuft ° n Y ^ MajeSty ’ S guarantee for the railway, and M. Gukassow has been told if 1 &amp; Cr0 . verni - llent L PT1 rpfpvrpd to tbp Indin ^ bee . n told that tliese questions have Deen reterrecl to tlie India Office m order that the views of the Government of Indin may be obtained It was added that the proposed alignment was adopted only^fter careful consideration by the Government of India and all the departments inteLsted and that any suggestjon for the substitution of a different one wS have to be submitted to examination by all the same authorities. D Yours sincerely, R. P. MAXWELL.[This Document is the Property of ffis Britannic Majesty’ s Gover nment, j lEASTERN DEPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. ii K- [July 24.] Section 1, S ' 4 .1 '1 Ol oioo] No. 1. Anglo-Persiaii Oil Company to Foreign Office.—{Jteeeired July 24/ Winchester Rouse, Old Broad Street, London, Dear Mr. Mallet, July 22, 1911. I BEG to acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 11th instant, containing Sir Edward Grey’s comments upon the draft telegram to Mr. David Brown which I forwarded to you on the 15th ultimo. The various alterations suggested by Sir Edward have, as you will have seen from the copy I have sent you of the memorandum handed to his Highness Prince Ala-es-Sultaneh, all been adopted. No reference was made in that memorandum to the gauge, but I have instructed Mr. Brown to leave this question open, as in the general opinion a 2 ft. 6 in. gauge will not suffice for the requirements of the country, and either the metre or 3 ft. 6 in. gauge be necessary. I have been approached by M. Goukasow, a member of the Russian syndicate for the Trans-Persian Railway, with a view to securing the co-operation of our group, and when you can spare me a few minutes I shall be glad to have an interview with you for the purpose of discussing M. Goukasow’s proposals. Yours truly, C. GREENWAY. [2123 1]%V-^7/ foreign office, August 5, 1911. *ir, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 31st ultimo, relative to the application of the Persian rL, Railways Syndicate^for concessions to construct railways in that country. I am to state that, in Sir E. Grey’s opinion, Mr. Greenway might think it discourteous if no reply were returned to his letter of the 15th ultimo, hut that in view of the considerations advanced in your communication, the answer to that gentleman will take the form desired by the Marquess of Crewe and not that suggested in the letter of the 24th ultimo from this Office. I am however to observe in this connexion that, so far as bir E. Grey is aware, the Syndicate have no intention of applying for concessions in respect of the three extensions in question at this moment and that the lines with which their present application is concerned lie entirely outside the Russian sphere and would therefore, from the point of view of the Persian Government, be open to the second of the two objections mentioned in your letter. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, The lJn der-Secretary of State for India.FOREIGN OFFICE, July 24, 1911. f* aeJULisii J to Mr. Mallet’s letter of the 11th instant ri^iartlve to schemes of railway construction in Persia, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a letter from the Managing Director of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company enclosing a memorandum relative to the projects of the Persian Railways Syndicate in this connexion, which has been handed to the Persian Special Representative at the Coronation and the Persian Minister at this Court. The Marquess of Crewe will observe that the Syn dicate propose eventually to extend three of the suggested lines to points within, or on the border of the Russian sphere of influence. oo far as bir Edward Grey is aware these proposals are now made for the first time and he is disposed, if Lord Crewe concurs, to point out to Mr. Greenway that, while His Majesty's Government understand that there is no intention of applying to the Russian Government for concessions in respect of these extensions at present, they could not authorise such an application by a British group at any time without the previous consent of the Russian Government. lam, Sir, your obedient, The Under-Secretary of State. India Office. humble servant, ([This Document is the Property of His Britannic Malays aovemmeirt.] EASTERN DEPARTMJ- SECRET SERIES. * [July 18.] Section 2. -7T8215] No. 1. Anglo-Persian Oil Company to Foreign Office,—(Received July 18.) 11 inchester House, Old Broad Street, London, Sir ’ T t,™ i • . Jul y 15 ’ 191L I Bli&lt;G to enclose copy of a memorandum which, at their request, I have handed to His Highness Prince Ala-e-Saltaneh and to his Excellency the Persian Minister, giving a rough outline of our proposals in connection with the Persian railways. Should you consider it advisable to modify what has been said in any respect, I shall be glad to hear from you, and I will, if necessary, send His Highness and his Excellency an amended memorandum. I have, &amp;c. C. GREENWAY, Managing Director. Enclosure in No. 1. Memorandum respecting Persian Railways. OUR group, which will be called the Persian Railways Syndicate, and will be composed of:— 1. The Anglo-Persian Oil Company group, including— Lord Strathcona, Mr. W. K. D’Arcy, Mr. J. T. Cargill, Mr. Tarbett Fleming, Mr. C. W. Wallace,' Mr. Frank Strick, Mr. R. W. Adamson, Mr. C. Green way, &amp;c. ; 2. The Imperial Bank and Persian Transport Company group, -including— Sir Thomas Jackson, Sir Thomas Gordon, Mr. H. B. Lynch, &amp;c. ; 3. The British-Indian Steam Navigation Company group, including— Lord Inchcape, Mr. W. A. Buchanan, &amp;c. ; 4. The British and Foreign General Securities and Investment Trust, including—• Mr. T. B. Bov ring, Mr. Alex. B. Williamson, &amp;c. ; 5. The Weetman Pearson group, including—- Lord Cowdray, Sir Clarendon Hyde, &amp;c. ; will be prepared to enter into contracts for, and undertake construction of, the following railways in Persia :—■ 1. From Mohammerah and/or Khor Musa to Khoramabad or Burujird, 2. From Bunder Abbas to Kerman, 3. From Bunder Abbas to Shiraz, 4. From Bunder Abbas to Mohammerah ; with a view to the eventual carrying on of the first three of these lines as below :— [2123 s—2]f / T • 5. (1.) From Khoramabad to Tehran, via Burujird, Dowlataban, and Hamadan, or via Bnrujird, Sultanabad, and Kom, 6. (2.) From Kerman to Ispahan, via Yezd, 7. (3.) From Shiraz to Tehran, via Ispahan, Kashan, and Korn. As Persia cannot, obviously, for financial reasons deal with the whole of thesv, . systems at once, it is proposed that they should be taken in hand one by one in the above order in accordance with Persia’s ability to provide the necessary guarantees for the capital required. The line from Mohammerah and/or Khor Musa to Khoramabad is suggested as the first one that should be constructed, because (1) it will give the readiest communication with the Persian Gulf, for the whole of the trade of the north-west of Persia, including Tehran, being connected by caravan routes or roads with Kermanshar on the west; with Burujird, Dowlatabad, Hamadan, Zindjan, and Kasvin on the north; Sultanabad, Kom, and Tehran on the north-east; and with Ispahan on the east; and (2) will, therefore, by attracting the trade of the important districts, of w hich these towns are the centres, offer the best prospects of remunerative working. It would also place Tehran within four or five days’ communication of the Persian Gulf, instead of the present fifteen to twenty days. Capital. It is proposed that the capital should be raised by means of “ State railway loans,” secured by (1) such revenues of the Persian Government as may be available for hypothecation, and (2) the railway and its earnings. At present the only revenue within sight available for such a purpose is the surplus shown in the southern customs after meeting outstanding liabilities. This, however, is too small for the purpose in view, but it is possible that the Treasurer-General may before long, either by augmenting existing sources of revenue, or by devising new ones, be able to provide the necessary security. The capital cannot, in the present position of Persia, be obtained without the securities indicated above, because (1) the possibilities of Persia as a field for the remunerative investment of capital in railways are entirely unknown to investors, and (2) even if there were more knowledge on this point investors would not be willing to invest in Persian railways wfithout substantial guarantees, because public information in Europe leads to the assumption that there is great political insecurity in the country. The bonds issued in connection with the “ State railway loans ” would be 5 per cent, bonds, and they would be purchased by the syndicate in the same manner as the bonds which are to be issued for the recent Persian Government loan of i,250,000?y ha, at say 87-g per cent, for each 100/., and the nett amount provided by the loans must for each line suffice to cover (1) cost of surveys; (2) cost of construction and equipment, including cost of wharves, jetties, &amp;c., that may be required at ports, and administration expenses during construction; and to relieve the Persian Government of this obligation until the railways are working, it would also be well to include (3) interest on the bonds during the period of construction. It might also be necessary to include amortization. The bonds would be issued for a period of years, say twenty-five to thirty years, with the right of redemption to the Persian Government at par at any time after five to ten years, either out of the amortization fund, and/or out of the Government revenues. A dm in istrat ion. The syndicate would be willing to undertake the construction of the lines on behalf of the Persian Government as “ State railways,” but they would stipulate that the construction should be undertaken by themselves, and that the railways should, as in other countries, be worked under their supervision until such time as the Persian Government were in a positian to pay off the loans. To facilitate the latter, it might be arranged that the loan or loans in respect of each complete railway should be earmarked, thus giving the Persian Government the opportunity of taking over and administering each railway as its loan (or loans) is liquidated.RUSSIA. No. 1 (1907) CONTENTION SIGNED ON AUGUST 31, 1907, BETWEEN GREAT BRITAIN AND RUSSIA, CONTAINING ARRANGEMENTS ON THE SUBJECT OE PERSIA, AFGHANISTAN, AND THIBET. Presented to both Houses of Parlia7nent by Command of His Majesty. September 1907. LONDON: PRINTED FOR HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE, BY HARRISON AND SONS, ST. MARTIN’S LANE, PRINTERS IN ORDINARY TO HIS MAJESTY. And to be purchased, either directly or through any Bookseller, from WYMAN AND SONS, Ltd., Fetter Lane, E.C.; and 32, Abingdon Street, Westminster, S. W. ; or OLIVER AND BOYD, Tweeddale Court, Edinburgh ; or E. PONSONBY, 116, Grafton Street, Dublin. ICd. 3750.] Price 1 id.I . m Convention signed on August 31, 1907, between Great Britain and Russia, containing Arrangements on the subject of Persia, Afghanistan, and Thibet. No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Sir A. Nicolson. g- r Foreign Office, August 29, 1907. ’ I HAVE to-day authorized your Excellency by telegraph to sign a Convention with the Russian Government containing Arrangements on the subject of Persia, Afghanistan, and Thibet. The Arrangement respecting Persia is limited to the regions of that country touching the respective frontiers of Great Britain and Russia in Asia, and the Persian Gulf is not part of those regions, and is only partly in Persian territory. It has not therefore been considered appropriate to introduce into the Convention a positive declaration respecting special interests possessed by Great Britain in the Gulf, the result of British action in those waters for more than a hundred years. ^ His Majesty’s Government have reason to believe that this question will not give rise to difficulties between the two Governments should developments arise which make further discussion affecting British interests in the Gulf necessary. For the Russian Government have in the course of the negotiations leading up to the conclusion of this Arrangement explicitly stated that they do not deny the special interests of Great Britain in the Persian Gulf—a statement of which His Majesty’s Government have formally taken note. In order to make it quite clear that the present Arrangement is not intended to affect the position in the Gulf, and does not imply any change of policy respecting it on the part of Great Britain, His Majesty’s Government think it desirable to draw attention to previous declarations of British policy, and to reaffirm generally previous statements as to British interests in the Persian Gulf and the importance of maintaining them. His Majesty’s Government will continue to direct all their efforts to the preserva tion of the status quo in the Gulf and the maintenance of British trade; in doing so, they have no desire to exclude the legitimate trade of any other Power. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) E. GREY. No. 2. Sir A. Nicolson to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 3.) Sir, St. Petersburgh, August 31, 1907. I HAVE the honour to transmit herewith the Convention which was signed to-day by M. Isvolsky and myself for the settlement of certain questions affecting the interests of Great Britain and Russia in Asia. I also beg leave to forward a note which I received from M. Isvolsky in response to a communication from me, of which a copy is herewith inclosed, on the subject of the entry of scientific missions into Thibet. (Signed) ' A. NICOLSON.Sir Arthur Nicolson, His Majesty’s Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary to His Majesty the Emperor of All the Russias ; His Majesty the Emperor of All the Russias, the Master of his Court Alexander Iswolsky, Minister for Foreign Affairs ; Who, having communicated to each other their full powers, found in good and due form, have agreed on the following :— Arrangement concerning Persia. The Governments of Great Britain and Russia having mutually engaged to respect the integrity and independence of Persia, and sincerely desiring the preservation of order throughout that country and its peaceful development, as well as the permanent establishment of equal advantages for the trade and industry of all other nations ; Considering that each of them has, for geographical and economic reasons, a special interest in the maintenance of-peace and order in certain provinces of Persia adjoining, or in the neighbourhood of, the Russian frontier on the one hand, and the frontiers of Afghanistan and Baluchistan on the other hand ; and being desirous of avoiding all cause of conflict between their respective interests in the above-mentioned Provinces of Persia ; Have agreed on the following terms :— I. Great Britain engages not to seek for herself, and not to support in favour of British subjects, or in favour of the subjects of third Powers, any Concessions of a political or commercial nature—such as Concessions for railways, banks, telegraphs, roads, transport, insurance, &amp;c.—beyond a line starting from Kasr-i-Shirin, passing- through Isfahan, Yezd, Kakhk, and ending at a point on the Persian frontier at the intersection of the Russian and Afghan frontiers, and not to oppose, directly or indirectly, demands for similar Concessions in this region which are supported by the Russian Government. It is understood that the above-mentioned places are included in the region in which Great Britain engages not to seek the Concessions referred to. II. Russia, on her part, engages not to seek for herself, and not to support in favour of Russian subjects, or in favour of the subjects of third Powers, any Concessions of a political or commercial nature—such as Concessions for railways, banks, telegraphs, roads, transport, insurance, &amp;c.—beyond a line going from the Afghan frontier by way of Gazik, Birjand, Kerman, and ending at Bunder Abbas, and not to oppose, directly or indirectly, demands for similar Concessions in this region which are supported by the British Government. It is understood that the above-mentioned places are included in the region in which Russia engages not to seek the Concessions referred to. HI. Russia, on her part, engages not to oppose, without previous arrangement with Great Britain, the grant of any Concessions whatever to British subjects in the regions of Persia situated between the lines mentioned in Articles I and II. Great Britain undertakes a similar engagement as regards the grant of Concessions to Russian subjects in the same regions of Persia. All Concessions existing at present in the regions indicated in Articles I and II are maintained. IV. It is understood that the revenues of all the Persian customs, with the exception of those of Farsistan and of the Persian Gulf, revenues guaranteeing the amortization and the interest of the loans concluded by the Government of the Shah with the “ Banque d’Escompte et des Prets de Perse” up to the date of the signature of the present Arrangement, shall be devoted to the same purpose as in the past. It is equally understood that the revenues of the Persian customs of Farsistan and of the Persian Gulf, as well as those of the fisheries on the Persian shore of the8 Caspian Sea and those of the Posts and Telegraphs, shall be devoted, as m the past, to the service of the loans concluded by the Government of the Shah with the Imperial Bank of Persia up to the date of the signature of the present Airangement. Y. In the event of irregularities occurring in the amortization or the payment of the interest of the Persian loans concluded with the Bancpie d Escompte et des Prets de Perse ” and with the Imperial Bank of Persia up to the date of the signature of the present Arrangement, and in the event of the necessity ansing foi Russia to establish control over the sources of revenue guaranteeing the regular service of the loans concluded with the first-named bank, and situated in the region mentioned in Article II of the present Arrangement, or for Great Britain to establish control oyer the sources of revenue guaranteeing the regular service of the loans concluded with the second-named bank, and situated in the region mentioned in Article I of the present Arrangement, the British and Russian Governments undertake to enter before hand into a friendly exchange of ideas with a view to determine, in agreement with each other, the measures of control in question and to avoid all interference which would not be in conformity with the principles governing the present Arrangement. Conveyition concerning Afghanistan. The High Contracting Parties, in order to ensure perfect security on their respective frontiers in Central Asia and to maintain in these regions a solid and lasting peace, have concluded the following Convention :— ARTICLE I. His Britannic Majesty’s Government declare that they have no intention of changing the political status of Afghanistan. His Britannic Majesty’s Government further engage to exercise their influence in Afghanistan only in a pacific sense, and they will not themselves take, nor encourage Afghanistan to take, any measures threatening Russia. The Russian Government, on their part, declare that they recognize Afghanistan as outside the sphere of Russian influence, and they engage that all their political relations with Afghanistan shall be conducted through the intermediary of His Britannic Majesty’s Government ; they further engage not to send any Agents into Afghanistan. ARTICLE II. The.Government of His Britannic Majesty having declared in the Treaty signed at Kabul on the 21st March, 1905, that they recognize the Agreement and the engage ments concluded with the late Ameer Abdur Rahman, and that they have no intention of interfering in the internal government of Afghan territory, Great Britain engages neither to annex nor to occupy in contravention of that Treaty any portion of Afghanistan or to interfere in the internal administration of the country, provided that the Ameer fulfils the engagements already contracted by him towards His Britannic Majesty’s Government under the above-mentioned Treaty. ARTICLE III. The Russian and Afghan authorities, specially designated for the purpose on the frontier or in the frontier provinces, may establish direct relations with each other for the settlement of local questions of a non-political character. ARTICLE IV. His Britannic Majesty’s Government and the Russian Government affirm their adherence to the principle of equality of commercial opportunity in Afghanistan, andthey agree that any facilities which may have been, or shall be hereafter obtained for British and British-Indian trade and traders, shall be equally enjoyed by Russian trade and traders. Should the progress of trade establish the necessity for Com- mercia geoty, the two Governments will agree as to what measures shall be taken, due regal d, of course, being had to the Ameer’s sovereign rights. ARTICLE V. Hie present Arrangements will only come into force wiien His Britannic Maiesty’s Government shall have notified to the Russian Government the consent of the Ameer to the terms stipulated above. Arrangement concerning Thibet. Jjhe Govei mnents of Great Britain and Russia recognizing the suzerain rights of China m Ihibet, and considering the fact that Great Britain, by reason of her geogiaplncal position, has a special interest in the maintenance of the status quo in the external relations of 1 hibet, have made the following Arrangement:— ARTICLE I. rrn-i Tlle j W ° . Contracting Parties engage to respect the territorial integrity of Ihibet and to abstain from all interference in its internal administration. ARTICLE II. In conformity with the admitted principle of the suzerainty of China over Thibet, Great Britain and Russia engage not to enter into negotiations with Thibet except thiough the intermediary of the Chinese Government. This engagement does not exclude the direct relations between British Commercial Agents and the Thibetan authorities provided for in Article V of the Convention between Great Britain and Thibet of the 7th September, 1904:, and. confirmed by the Convention between Great Britain and China (h the 27th April, 1906; nor does it modify the engagements entered into by Great Britain and China in Article I of the said Convention of 1906. It is clearly understood that Buddhists, subjects of Great Britain or of Russia, may entei into direct relations on strictly religious matters with the Dalai Lama and the other representatives of Buddhism in Thibet; the Governments of Great Britain and Russia engage, as far as they are concerned, not to allow those relations to infringe the stipulations of the present Arrangement. ARTICLE HI. The British and Russian Governments respectively engage not to send Representa tives to Lhassa. ARTICLE IV. The two High Contracting Parties engage neither to seek nor to obtain, whether for themselves or their subjects, any Concessions for railways, roads, telegraphs, and mines or other rights in Thibet. ARTICLE V. The two Governments agree that no part of the revenues of Thibet, whether in kmd or in cash, shall be pledged or assigned to Great Britain or Russia or to any of their subjects.'*&gt;■ '•“^1^' %?*'•' ■ (ii'l 'riiiiim : AlWBdtV X Annex to the Arvangement between Great Britain and Russia concerning 1 hibet. Great Britain reaffirms the Declaration, signed by his Excellency the Viceroy and Governor-Geueral of India and appended to the ratification ol the Convention of the 7th September, 1904, to the effect that the occupation of the Chumbi A 7 alley by British forces shall cease after the payment of three annual instalments of the indemnity of 25 00,000 rupees, provided that the trade marts mentioned in Article II of that Convention have been effectively opened for three yeais, and that m the meantime the Thibetan authorities have faithfully complied in all respects with the terms of the said Convention of 1904. It is clearly understood that if the occupation of the Chumbi Valley by the British forces has, for any reason, not been terminated at the time anticipated in the above Declaration, the British and Russian Governments will enter upon a friendly exchange of views on this subject. The present Convention shall be ratified, and the ratilications exchanged at St. Petersburgh as soon as possible. In witness whereof the respective Plenipotentiaries have signed the present Convention and affixed thereto their seals. Done in duplicate at St. Petersburgh, the 18th (31st) August, 1907. (L.S.) A. NICOLSON. (L.S.) ISWOLSKY. Inclosure 2 in No. 2. Sir A. Nicolson to M. Iswolsky. M. le Ministre, Saint-Petersbourg, le 18 (31) Aout, 1907. ME referant a 1’Arrangement au sujet du Thibet signe aujourd’hui, j’ai I’honneur de faire a votre Excellence la declaration suivante :— “Le Gouvernement Britannique juge utile, pour autant qu’il dependra de lui, de ne pas admettre, sauf accord prealable avec le Gouvernement Russe, pour une duree de trois ans a partir de la date de la presente communication, I’entree au Thibet dune mission scientifique quelconque, a condition toutefois qu’une assurance pareille soit donnee de la part du Gouvernement Imperial de Russie. “ Le Gouvernement Britannique se propose, en outre, de s’adresser au Gouverne ment Chinois afin de faire agreer a ce dernier une obligation analogue pour une periode correspondante ; il va de soi que la meme demarche sera faite par le Gouvernement Russe. “A Fexpiration du terme de trois ans precite, le Gouvernement Britannique avisera d’un commun accord avec le Gouvernement Russe a Popportunite, s’il y a lieu, de mesures ulterieures a prendre concernant les expeditions scientifiques au Thibet.” Je saisis, &amp;c. (Signe) A. NICOLSON. (Translation.) M. le Ministre, St. Petersburgh, August 18 (31), 1907. AVITH reference to the Arrangement regarding Thibet, signed to-day, I have the honour to make the following Declaration to your Excellency :— “ His Britannic Majesty’s Government think it desirable, so far as they are con cerned, not to allow, unless by a previous agreement with the Russian Government, for a period of three years from the date of the present communication, the entry into Thibet of any scientific mission whatever, on condition that a like assurance is given on the part of the Imperial Russian Government. “His Britannic Majesty’s Government propose, moreover, to approach the Chinese Government with a view to induce them to accept a similar obligation for a corre sponding period ; the Russian Government will, as a matter of course, take similar action.„ • ‘‘A* p he ex P irat '°n of the term of three years above mentioned His Britannic *1 ' ,1 ' ■. i u 1 ’ 1 necessary, consult with the Russian Government as to Thibet” 118111 ^ ° 11 ^ eil0r mea sures with regard to scientific expeditions to I avail, &amp;c. (Signed) A. NICOLSON. Inclosure 3 in No. 2. M. Iswolsky to Sir A. Nicolson. M - I’Ambassadeur, Saint-Petersbourg, le 18 (31) Aout, 1907. •i/ leponse a la note de votre Excellence en date de ce jour, j’ai Thonneur de declarei a mon tour que le Gouvernement Imperial de Russie juge utile, pour autant qu i dependia de lui, de ne pas admettre—sauf accord prealable avec le Gouvernement Rritanmque—-pour une duree de trois ans, a partir de la date de la presente communi cation, 1 entree an Thibet d’une mission scientifique quelconque. De meme que le Gouvernement Britannique, le Gouvernement Imperial se propose de s adiessei an Gouvernement Chinois afin de faire agreer a ce dernier une obligation analogue pour une periode correspondante. . ^ icste entendu qua 1 expiration du terme de trois ans les deux Gouvernements aviseront d un commun accord a Topportunite, s’il j a lieu, de mesures ulterieures a prendre concernant les expeditions scientifiques an Thibet. Veuillez agreer, &amp;c. (Signe) ISWOLSKY. (Translation.) M. TAmbassadeur, ^ St. Petersburgh, August 18 (31), 1907. IN reply to your Excellency’s note of even date, I have the honour to declare that the Imperial Russian Government think it desirable, so far as they are concerned, not to allow, unless by a previous agreement with the British Government, for a period of three years from the date of the present communication, the entry into Thibet of any scientific mission whatever. Like the British Government, the Imperial Government propose to approach the Chinese Government with a view to induce them to accept a similar obligation for a corresponding period. It is understood that at the expiration of the term of three years the two Govern ments will, if necessary, consult with each other as to the desirability of any ulterior measures with regard to scientific expeditions to Thibet. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) ISWOLSKY.confidential. 3 3 ^ /S?,r (j. Bai clay to Sir Edward Grey.—{Eeeeived April 25, 4 p.m. ) O ' »” iajj V^j^UlV-FJLl. Following is text of Persian Government’s reply : (After compliments.) -_ “Of course Britisl) Government will not lose sight of definite wording of Nasr-ed-Dm bhah s autograph letter, which is as follows Permission will never be granted to anyone to construct any other than a purely commercial railway m Persia.’ ” r j “ Although benefits and advantages of railway construction are in no way concealed to Persian Government, it is precisely from this point of view that Persian Government considers that it is excused from granting this option. Having, however, earnestly in view development of the two countries, Persian Government s wish is that it may be able to arrange for a railway in its own country, which will safeguard its political and economic interests, and to study question with regard to constiuction of a commercial railway which would be in accordance with interests of country. It is hoped that British Government, whose good relations and friendly feelino-s towards this Government have always been highly appreciated, will be in agreement with this legitimate aim of Persian Government and will show their good-will ” (End of R.) I ha\ e asked Minister for F oreign Affairs why it was imagined proposed enterprise had other than a commercial character. His Excellency replied that it was because I had made the application in the name of His Majesty’s Government. In this connection I should mention that the Persian text of rescript of 1888 contains the words “ and of English company ” between the words “ Government ” and “ over.” I told Ministei for F oreign Affairs that I believed His Majesty’s Government, if they obtained the option, intended to place the enterprise with a British syndicate, and he said that Persian Government would be prepared to consider proposals for general railway construction in Persia from a British group. I understand from his Excellency that the^ concluding sentence of his note means that the Persian Government hopes His Majesty s Government will lend them their good offices by encouraging a syndicate to come forward, but I have also understood from conversations with the Regent and Minister for Foreign Affairs that the ending of the line at Khorremabad would be distasteful to the Persian Government, as emphasising the disagreeable fact that Persia is divided into spheres, and 1 fear no group would have much chance if it applied for this line. Minister for Foreign Affairs has reminded me that rescript speaks of a line to Tehran. I see no trace of any disposition on the part of the Persian Government to back out of the rescript, but I fear there is little hope of inducing them to give us anything more concrete than the negative and conditional option we already hold. I hope to leave Friday and to have an opportunity of discussing verbally what form our next communication to Persian Government should take.— FOREIGN OFFICE . July 11th, 1911 Sir I arn directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 29th ultimo; relative to the proposed application by the Persian Railway Syndicate to the Persian Government for a concession for the construction of railways in Southern Persia. the view r of the Marquess of Crewe that it is unnecess ary for His Majesty's Government to engage in a discussion on the subject with the Russian Government at present, but he | considers that it will be proper to consult them before con- | struction is actually begun, since His Majesty's Government can hardly regard themselves as absolved from their undertak ings merely because they are neither applying themselves nor actively supporting the Syndicate's application for the con cession. Sir Edward Grey feels that omission to consult the I am to inform you in reply that Sir Edward Grey Russian Under-Secretary of State. India OfficeRussian Government eventually would be regarded rightly by them as disingenuous on the part of His Majesty*s Government. I am to transmit to you herewith copy of the reply returnee to Mr. Greenway's latter of June 15 from which it will be observed that Sir Edward Grey concurs in the views expressed in your letter and has acted accordingly. I am, Sir, your most obedient, humble servant,FORKIGt-i OPFICK. GONPIDSMIAL. fu/ July 11th.1911. I am obliged to you for your letter of June 15th, enclosing the draft of a telegram, which you propose to send to Mr. David Brown of the Imper ial Bank of Persia at Tehran, Instructing him to apply in the name of the Persian Railway Syndicate for a concession to construct railways Ih Southern Persia; It is observed that the proposed railways are to be light railways of 2ft; 6in; gauge. The question of gauge is of importance, especially on the proposed Bandar-Abbas— Kerman line, which will be a valuable adjunct; strategically and commercially, of the Trans-Persian Railway; should that railway ever be constructed; In view of this consideration Sir Edward Grey thinks it right to stipulate teat provision should be made in the construction of this line for the eventual widening of the gauge; Greenway Esq; Winchester House. Old Broad Street.It is 41 so noticed that no mention is made in the draft telegram of any connection by rail between Bandar * Abbas and Mohamraerah, the proposed line from Bandar-Abbas to Shiraz being apparently intended to stop at the latter place. His Majesty’s Government attach great importance to the establishment of railway connection between Bandar~Abbas and Mohaismerah or at all events to securing the possibility of establishing it. Sir Edward Grey therefore considers that this concession should also be applied for even though the line inay not be immediately constructed. It is proposed in the draft telegram that the int erest on the bonds issued to provide capital for the enter prise should be partly secured on a special increase of 4% in the customs duties of the southern ports of Persia. His Majesty’s Government cannot pledge themselves to agree to this increase which would involve the imposition of a further burden on trade the greater part of which is British and British - Indian and which, as it would require the consent of other Powers wotfld give them an opportunity of placing difficulties in the way of the undertaking. Sir Edward Grey wouldV would accordingly request that this point may be omitted from tm- tele jra . and v-uulu suggest that the neHly apjjointsd American Treasurer-General or his assistants might be able to devise some alternative form of security. Subject to the foregoing conditions Sir Sdward G*ey sees nothing to object to in the terras of the draft telegram. I am, sir, your obedient, humble servant.[TMs Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ftomnment.] W EASTERN DEPARTMENT. [May 10.] SECRET SERIES. Section 1, f [15143] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan. (No. 129. Secret.) Sir, _ Foreign Office, May 10, 1911. I HAVE received your Excellency’s despatch No il2, Confidential, of the 18th ultimo, relative to the proposed Trans-Persian Railway, and you may inform the Russian Government that His Majesty’s Government, after careful consideration of the projects in consultation with the Government of India, are ready to assent to it in principle, and to agree to the initiation of negotiations between its promoters in this country and in Russia subject to the following conditions :— 1. The line shall enter the British sphere at Bunder Abbas instead of at Kerman, subject to reconsideration as the result of actual survey, and shall in any case join the Indian railway system at Karachee and not at Nushki. 2. There shall be a break of gauge at Bunder Abbas, or wherever the line enters the British sphere of influence in Persia. 3. In return for the co-operation of Great Britain in the project, which examination has shown to be likely to benefit Russia far more than Great Britain or India, Russia shall pledge herself not to entertain or support, without coming to an understanding with Great Britain, any proposal for a line in the neighbourhood of the Perso-Afghan frontier within the Russian or neutral sphere in Persia. 4. Russia shall support demands made by Great Britain of the Persian Government Railway :— (a.) From Mohammerah to Khoremabad wfith a branch to port to be constructed at Khor Musa. (b.) From Bunder Abbas or Charbar via Regan and Bam to Kerman. (c.) From Bushire, via Aliabad, to some point on a line— (d.) From Bunder Abbas, via Shiraz, to Ahwaz. 5. The main line and those of the above branches which lie in the neutral sphere— i.e., (a), (c), and (d )—shall be internationalised ; but the branch which lies entirely in the British sphere— i.e., (b )—shall be a purely British project. 6. Absolute equality of treatment in all respects shall be guaranteed to British and British Indian trade passing over the line and its branches. Your Excellency is at liberty frankly to explain to the Russian Government that the first three of the above conditions are dictated by strategic considerations, and are inserted in the interest of India. The enclosed copy of a letter from the India Office, taken in conjunction with that from the Board of Trade of the 13th September, 1910, which your Excellency has already had an opportunity of perusing, will enable you to appreciate the reasons which have led His Majesty’s Government to the conclusion set forth above. You could inform the Russian promoters of the general sense of the views of His Majesty’s Government, while making it clear both to the Russian Government and to the Russian promoters that His Majesty’s Government express no opinion as to the commercial or financial aspects of the question, which are matters to be examined by the syndicates who may desire to participate in the enterprise. for concessions of the following branch lines connected with the proposed Trans-Persian I am, &amp;c. E. GREY. [2026 k—1]CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir A. Nicolson.—{Received July 1.; (Private.) Tehran, July 1, 1911. MY telegram No. 2^4. In a private letter Wilson estimates the cost of a broad [?] gauge line from Mohammerah to Khorremabad at 2,500,000b ; metre gauge line would be 1,600,000b He thinks former would never pay and that latter would only pay after many years. He says that above views are provisional and subject to modification in his official [?] reports, but I telegraph them privately in case of intending applicants pressing for some Government guarantee.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] Persian Government in the sense of your instructions, but before presenting it I showed it to the Minister for Foreign Affairs in order to ascertain whether any change of wording would be more likely to meet with a favourable response. His Excellency reminded me that his willingness to enter into negotiations with a British group applied to railway construction in general in Persia, and not specially to railway construction in the south. This was quite true, and, as I thought that to take note of such an assurance might be not altogether pleasing to my Russian colleague, I redrafted my note, omitting any reference to his Excellency’s previous assurance. I enclose a copy of this communication. I DID not fail to convey to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs the contents of your Excellency’s note of the 22nd April last, and I am now directed by him to state that he quite appreciates the point of view of the Persian Government in not wishing to grant an option for a railway in Persia to a foreign Government. He presumes, however, that when the Persian Government desire to undertake the construction of a line from Mohammerah, or of any other southern line, they will enter into negotiations with a British syndicate. ’EASTERN DEPARTMENT. [June 12.] SECRET SERIES. Section 1. [22788] Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received June 12.) (No. 81.) Sir, Tehran, May 31, 1911. ON receipt of your telegram No. 132 of the 4th instant I prepared a note to the I have, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. Enclosure in No. 1. Sir G. Barclay to Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs. M. le Ministre, Tehran, May 25, 1911. I avail, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. [2059 m—1][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] EASTERN DEPARTMENT. h' SECRET SERIES. [19608] Foreign Office to Ford Grimthor'pe. Dear Lord Grimthorpe, _ Foreign Office, May 29, 1911. I BEG to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the T2th May, explaining the situation with regard the negotiations between the Russian Government and a British group, carried on through Mr. Williams, with a view to railway construction in Northern Persia. Sir Edward Grey is much obliged to you for your full statement respecting the progress of the affair. Yours sincerely, LOUIS MALLET. [May 29.] Section 2. [2026 /f—2][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] I HAVE just returned from travelling abroad and find your letter of the 26th April, for which I am much obliged. I did not suppose that the rumours in question had emanated from the British Ambassador at St. Petersburgh, as his attitude to Mr. Williams, though cautious, was friendly, and had Mr. Williams imagined that the damaging communications came through him, he would at once have spoken to him on the subject. He telegraphed to me to find out their source and origin if I could, and I, fearing that the Russian Foreign Office might have communicated with you, at once took the steps that appeared to be required in order to put myself right with you in this matter, which is unquestionably of some importance, as it may considerably affect the employment of British capital in Russia. Mr. Williams, having been able f to satisfy the Russian Government on every point, left St. Petersburgh with a written promise of excellent business on a very large scale—in fact so large that the extent of it mainly depends upon our capacity to deal with it. As we do not intend to take up any business that we are not able to carry through, we are now engaged in forming a million-pound syndicate among financiers of the highest standing. This of course cannot be done in a day, but I hope that Mr. Williams will soon be able to return to Russia with adequate financial support to enable him to enter into a definite agreement with the Government, by means of which a splendid and unique opening will be offered to British capital, so that the exploitation of Russia will no longer be left entirely in the hands of the Germans, which the Russian Government apparently does not desire to see indefinitely continued. I do not wish to trouble the Foreign Office, or to ask for any special support beyond what I believe they are always prepared to give to British enterprise conducted on sound lines, but I do wish to keep them informed of what is going on, and to ask you to convey my thanks to Sir Edward Grey for the interest he has taken in this matter. [May 22.] SECRET SERIES. Section 2. [19608] No. 1. Dear Mr. Mallet, Lord Grimthorpe to Mr. Mallet.—(Received May 22.) 80, Portland Place, London, May 12, 1911. Yours truly, GRIMTHORPE.X !S J J JILTT y~.pi :2 &gt;7^&gt;- ( -f / f. 1 ' [This Doeament is the Property of His Britangie Majesty’s Government 1 EASTERN DEPARTMENT. .a SECRET SERIES. u. [21726] (No. 79.) Siv, No. ]. u r. r Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received June 6.) WT mTT r , i , T „ , Tehran, May 18, I9ll. Win reference to my telegram No. 135 of the 24th April, I have the honour to transmit herein the full text of the note which the Persian Government addressed t° me on the 22nd ultimo m reply to my note of the 3lst March applying for an option for railway construction in Southern Persia (of which I had the honour to forward you a copy m my despatch No. 59 of the 20th ultimo;. I have, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. Enclosure in No. I. Mohtashem-es-Sultaneh to Sir G. Barclay. ■ \ 1 .c !:U&gt; r. x (Translation.) Your Excellency, Tehran, 22nd Rebbi-ul-Sani, 1329 (April 22, 1911). I HAVE had the honour to receive your Excellency’s note of the 2Mth W&gt;lh-TrL Avvel (31st March, 1911). I have the honoui to sa\ that of course the British Government will not lose sight of the definite wording of His Majesty Nasr-ed-Din Shah’s autoo-raph letter (as follows):— &amp; “ Permission will never he granted to anyone to construct any other than a purely commercial railway in Persia.” ’ ' Although the benefits and advantages of railway construction are in no way concealed from the Persian Government, it is precisely from this point of view that the Persian Government considers itself excused from granting this option. Having, however, earnestly in view the development of the commerce of the two countries, the Persian Government’s wish is that it may be able to arrange for a railway in its own country which will safeguard its political and economic interests, and to study the question with regard to the construction of a commercial railway which would be in accord with the interests of the country. . ft i s hoped that the British Government, whose relations with and friendly feelings towards this Government have always been highly appreciated, will be in agreement with this legitimate aim of the Persian Government and will show their good-will. I avail, &amp;c. MOHTASHEM-ES-SULTANEH. Cr'M [2059/-l] 37tmmm r ~' CONFIDENTIAL \u b 1 \ l\ I j j Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay {Tehran). Foreign O ffice, May 4, 1911, 0 p.m. (No. 132.) YOUR telegrams Nos. 135 and 151. You may tell the l eisian Grovernment that I quite appreciate their point of view m not wishing to giant an option for a railway in Persia to a foreign Government, and you should take note of their willingness to enter into negotiations with a British syndicate. If you think their undertaking is not clear enough, you should ask them for a written assurance that, when they desire to undertake the construction of the Mohammerah line or of any other southern lines, they will enter into negotiations with a private British^ syndicate. His Majesty’s Government will stand aside'entirely. The Regent’s idea of a Franco-Russo-British combination is not practical, as the Russian Government does not desire to see the railway constructed, and if the French are admitted, other countries would also require admission. (Confidential.) The plan of negotiations with a British syndicate suits us better than the acquisition of an option ourselves. It will relieve us of the invidious necessity of giving a preference to one syndicate over another, if His Majesty’s Government stand aside altogether. If you agree to this course, we propose to inform the Transport Company, Mr. Greenway, and the Imperial Bank that the field is clear for them to negotiate, and we shall tell the Russian Government briefly of the Persian answer and of their preference for negotiations with a British syndicate. We shall add that before construction is begun an understanding will be arrived at with them. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 144.) [454—267]3^(71 [Thfe Doeamemt is the Property of Hie Britannic Majesty’s GoverEmmi'i EASTERN DEPARTMENT. SECRET SERIES. [17870] J U N1911 [May 31.] Section 1, Foreign Office to Persian Transport Company. (Confidential.) Foreign Office, May 31, 1911. WITH further reference to your letter of the 10th instant, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to inform you that the Persian Government have expressed a preference for direct negotiation with a British syndicate on the subject of railway construction in Persia generally, with special reference to a line from Khor Musa northwards. I am accordingly to state that, in these circumstances, His Majesty’s Government have decided to abstain from all intervention in the matter, and that it is open to British capitalists to approach the Persian Government with proposals of the nature in question. I am, &amp;c. LOUIS MALLET. [2026 hh —1]V Irrmediate Secret, poreig: June Sir I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith to be laid before the Earl of Crewe the draft of a telegram applying on from the Persian Government, which has been communicated to this Department by Mr. Greenway of the Anglo^Persian Oil Company, concession of which Mr. Greenway proposes to apply are substantially those for which His Majesty^ Govern- -ment intended to apply themselves, with the exception that the line from Bushire via Aliabad to a point on the Bunder Abbas-Shiraz-Ahwaz line is omitted and that the Bunder Abbas-Shiraz line is apparently not to be extended to Mohammerah or Ahwaz. Lord Crewe will observe that the lines for The The Under-Secretary of State for India'''■J ■nr / i i • lne omission oi 'the line fl*om Bushire via Aliabad to a point on the Bunder Abbas-Bhiraz-idiwaz line is in accordance with the recommendation of the Government of India ( see Viceroy’s telegram of the 23rd February last ) but Sir E. Grey would propose, subject to the concurrence of Lord Crewe, to point out to Mr. Greenway that His Majesty’s Government attach importance to the establishment of communication between Bunder Abbas and Mohammerah. He would further point out to Mr. Greenway that His Majesty’s Government cannot pledge themselves to agree to an increase of the Southern Customs, which would affect British and British Indian trade for the greater part and which would require the consent of other Powers, and he would therefore suggest the omission from the telegram of the mention of the 4% increase proposed. I am, Sir Your most obedient, humble servant,&lt;5 C. Greenwsy Esq., London D. Brown Esq., c/o Pehlevi, # June , 1911. Tehran. Apply in the name of Persian Railway Syndicate for concession for three light 2 feet 6 inches railv/ays first from the littoral probably Mohanunerah and/or Khor Musa to Khoramabad second from Bunder Abbas to Kerman third from Bunder Abbas to Shiraz to be constructed in this order according to Persian Government*s ability to provide guarantee. Capital would be provided by 5% Bonds at 87£ same as loan interest being guaranteed by Persian Government and secured firstly by first charge on railway and receipts and secondly by any tangible Government present or future revenue available for hypothecation. For this secondly suggest!special 4% increase in Southern Customs or any other increased tariff. Amount of Bonds must suffice at nett price to cover first cost of survey second cost of construction and equipment including cost of wharves jetties etc. at port and third interest and administration expenses during construction. You must stipulate for first British control construct- -ion and British management second free hand in appointing surveying and constructing engineers and contractors third appointment of Lloyd Scott &amp; Co. as Managing Agents.Dear Mr. Mallet, Winchester House, Old Broad Street, E.C. 'll w Pfh Ju,, / h I am obliged for your letter of the 13th and note what you wrtle about obtaining an option for constructing a port at Khor Musa. This, I think, is covered by the telegram I propose sending ( copy enclosed ) subject to some further discussion tomorrow with Sir Thomas Jackson who wishes to join the Imperial Bank of Persia in the Syndicate, Meantime Mr. H.B. Lynch has asked to meet us to discuss the question of ' transport in Persia', and &amp; propos of this I enclose copy of a somwwhat amusing letter which may interest you. This was handed’— to me by F.C, Strick and Co. Yours truly (Signed) C. Greenway.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100038753431.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/177/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100038753431.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/177/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 1702/1910 Pt 2 'Railways: Persia; Persian Railway Syndicate'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1911/1912</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-18T22:35:24</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This item includes correspondence relating to the financial structures for railway development in Persia including the impact of manouveres by Great Britain and Russia and the increased likelihood of Persia gaining access to outside borrowing.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100038753431.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>