<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000381_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-03T12:05:19.960Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Political agency a H.j^s Consulate, Muscat, January 26th, 1936. To The Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, H.U.o* 'shoreham'. Memorandum . Reference your Signal of 21st January 1936. 1 enclose herewith a Mote on the Boundaries of the sultanate of Muscat and Oman together with a rough shetch map, which 1 hope will be of some use to you. Political ~gent &amp; H.M’s Consul, Muscat.Note on the Boundaries of the Sultanate of Muscat &amp; Oman. In fact the whole of this portion of the coast is free from Muscat control. The exact boundaries of the State of Muscat and Oman have never been demarcated and in many places on the land side are not properly known. The attached rough sketch map* however, shows, sufficiently accurately for practical purposes, the limits of the sultanate. To the North the sultan's teriitory commences at the small port of Tibba in the Persian viulf. The boundary line, as shown by the red dotted line in the sketch map, from Tibba runs roughly 4^ast to a point a few miles from the coast then turns bouth anu ends at Has Bharbat All, which marks the southern limit of the bultanate. It may be noted that with the exception of the Batineh, the immediate neighbourhood of Muscat and the province of Dhofar in the bouth, the authority and control of the sultan's Government is confined to the coast. Nortfc of the Batineh district from kurair to Has sarkan are a number of small independent ports under the jurisdiction of their own bheikha. Chief of these are Kalba, khur Fakkan and Bibba/. These are marked in Green on the map*Note on the Boundaries of the Sultanate of Muscat at uuar The exact boundaries of the ^tate of Muscat and Oman have never been demarcated and in many places on the land side are not properly known* The attached rough sketch map, however, shows, sufficiently accurately for practical purposes, the limits of the sultanate* To the North the sultan's teriitory coimencej at the small port of Tibba in the Beraian dulf. The boundary line, as shown by the red dotted line in the sketch map, from Tibba runs roughly aast to a point &amp; few miles from the coast then turns bouth ana ends at has Dharbat All, which marks the southern limit of the bult&amp;natt* It may be noted that with the exception of the Batineh, the immediate neighbourhood of Muscat and the province of Dhofar in the bouth, the authority and control of the sultan^ Government is confined to the coast* Nortji of the Batineh district from i*urair to has Barkan are a number of small Independent ports under the jurisdiction of their own bhelkhs* Chief of these are Kalba, khur frakkan and Blbbal* These are marked in Green on the map* In fact the whole of this portion of the coast is free from Muscat control*In fact the whole of this portion of the coast is free from Muscat control# iSfote on 'the Boundaries of the BuXtanate of Muscat oc The exact boundaries of the ^tate of Muscat and Oman have never been demarcated and in many places on the land side are not properly known# The attached rough sketch map, however y shows, sufficiently accurately for practical purposes, the limits of the sultanate# To the Worth the bultan’s teriitory commences at the small port of Tibba in the Persian dulf. The boundary line, as shown by the red dotted line in the sketch map, from Tibba runs roughly &amp;aat to a point a few miles from the coast then turns oouth anu ends at has Bharbat All, which marks the southern limit of the Buitanate# It may be noted that with the exception of the Jbatlneh, the immediate neighbourhood of Muscat and the \ \ province of Dhofar in the bouth, the authority and control of the sultan’s Government is confined to the coast. \\ Nortji of the Batineh district from utrair to has barkan are a number of small Independent ports under the jurisdiction of their own Bheikhs. Chief these are Kalba, hhur Fakkan and Bibb^i# These are marked in screen on the map* of \\Note on the Boundaries of the Sultanate of Muscat &lt;3c Oman The exact boundaries of the State of Muscat and Oman have never been demarcated and in many places on the land side are not properly known. The attached rough sketch map, however, shows, sufficiently accurately for practical purposes, the limits of the sultanate. To the North the Buitan*s teriitory commences at the small port of Tibba in the Persian Gulf. The boundary line, as shown by the red dotted line in the sketch map, from Tibba runs roughly &amp;ast to a point a few miles from the coast then turns South ana ends at Has Dharbat Ali, which marks the southern limit of the Buitanate• It may be noted that with the exception of the Batineh, the immediate neighbourhood of Muscat and the province of Dhofar in the Bouth, the authority and control of the sultan’s Government is confined to the coast. Nortfc of the Batineh district from Murair to Has Sarkan are a number of small independent ports under the jurisdiction of their own Bheikhs. Chief oi these are Kalba, Kiiur Fakkan and Dibba/. These are marked in green on the map* In fact the whole of this portion of the coast is free from Muscat control.t Telegram. From - Political, Muscat. To - Britconsul , Bushire No. - 39. Dated 2nd March 1936. Your telegram dated February 27th No. 139. Dhahira is an independent district some fifty miles south west of Khaburah. Its capital is Yanqul. It is not in Muscat territory and any disturbances oceuring there would not involve the Sultan. -POLITICAL--'Q' - Political Agent, Muscat. - Political Resident, Bushire. - Political Agent, Bahrain. - 164. - July the 7th, 1939. Your telegram 358 July 6th. Please see Lorimer Volume 2 page 265 'Baraimi Village'. 3. Local enquiries confirm that Hamasah is in Muscat sphere. It is inhabited by A1 Bu Shamis and Naim and local Sheikh is Mohammad bin Salim Rahamah.■MHMMHMHRIi T -S L 5 G R A M. Telegram From Addressed to - 'Q' - Political Agent ? Bahrain - Political Resident, Bushire and - Political Agent, Muscat - 92. - July the 7th, 1939. - July the 7th, 1939. Your telegram 358 July 6th. Hamasa is A1 Bu Shamis village and presumably therefore in Muscat sphere. 9 V© PRIVATE. Muscat, the 1st April 1940. I 1 T\ Your private letter dated 15th March about the “ilaqas' 1 of the Sultan and Trucial Sheikhs. ^ enclose a map showing the approximate extent of these areas, also a note on the M harams M of the principal tribes. Hickinbotham is sending in a separate map, and has mentioned the three small areas on which we had some disagreement, i.e. (a) .the area north of Sha'am, (b) .the Wadi al Qaur, and (c).the Wadi Hatta. I have shown these on my sketch map with dotted boundaries and in both colours. 3. As regards (a)j the Sheikh of Ras al Khaimah claims to control up to Jebel Qir, between Sha , am and Bokha. Information in Muscat is that the northern portion of Sha’am itself is held by dependants of the Sultan. As regards (b) and (c); I have information of settlements of dependants of the Jawasim Sheikhs in the Wadi al Qaur, and of dependants of Sheikh of Dubai in the Wadi Hatta. Hickinbotham has given in his letter the limits of the Sultan's claim in these areas; but I cannot say without further investigation whether the r 'Trucial' settlements are in his area or in the tribal area. 4. Hickinbotham and I disagree more widely about the area north of Jebel Samaini. In my opinion the line on /his map The Hon'ble Lt.-Colonel C.G.Prior, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.2 his map takes into the Muscat sphere a large part of the Beni Ka’ab 'haram', including their capital, Mahadha. ^* A® regards the Naim and the A1 Bu Shamis area north ojici east of baraimi Oasis and tJebel Hafit, the opinion which I formed in Baraimi last winter was that the Sultan^ influence over these tribes was slight, and depended on money payments* I admit, however, that that is over a year ago, and that the Sultan’s influence may now be greater in this area. As you know, I was not able in the end to go up there from Sharjah this winter.1 PRIVATE. Muscat, the 1st April 1940. Not being able to agree with Howes on one or two points I have drawn a very rough map of the area I understand to be claimed by the Sultan as part of his territory. In my view the Southern boundary of the northern part of the State leaves the west coast of the Musandum Peninsula just north of the town of Sha’am and after running south turns east avoiding the town of Khatt and reaches the coast at Dibah. Only the northern third of this town is part of Muscat territory. The western boundary of the southern area runs west from the coast south of Khor Kalba to Khatm Malaha and turns south along the top of the western Hagar hills and passes west of Nasla in the 7/adi al Qaur and Shaikha in the Wadi Hatta. These two places which are each five hours by camel from the coast mark the western limit of the Sultan^ territory in these Wadis. The boundary turns south-west south of Shaikha and runs to Baraimi avoiding Jebel Samaini which is Beni Ka'ab territory. Passing through the Baraimi Oasis the line travels south to Jebel Hafit and about half way down this range bears away to the west. As regards the Baraimi Oasis the Sultan, as I understand it, claims that the villages occupied by the Naim and the Al Bu Shamis are / in Muscat The Hon'ble Lt.-Colonel C.G.Prior, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, .Bushire.2 in Muscat territory. He makes no claim to those villages held by the Beni Yas and agrees that they are under the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi. The boundary as shown is probably very inaccurate as I have little doubt that no one has worried about the barren rocks and stony desert; areas. This inaccuracy is probably greatest between Shaikha and Baraimi, and the simplest thing as regards this area is to look on the area acknowledged to be other than Beni Ka’ab as belonging to the Sultan until one reaches the outskirts of the Baraimi Oasis. The Sultan*s claim to overlordship of the Naim and the A1 Bu Shamis may be open to doubt and I have not examined the position very care fully but will do so on my return from leave. \ A /23&gt; SQMmmAL- D.O. No. C/ /^7? . Political Agency } Muscat. The 29th June 1944. Subjects Muscat Bo undaries. r Ahen I was in Salalah) the Sultan gave me details of what he considered were the interior boundaries of Muscat beginning from South of Point A 52° 23* to 22° 40* Point B as 54° 40* 22° 40* to Point C • 55° 40 1 22° to Point D — 56° £ 20° N to Point £ - 52° £ 19° N 2. The Sultan &lt; iratts but there is no si ( ( South of Baraimi). (North of Has Darbat Ali). ( i record in this office. The points however correspond most peculiarly to a Desert Zone (suggested by the India Office in 1935 and coaununicated under Residency Confidential printed letter No. 199-S of 1935)) known as the Blue Line. The Sultan, of course, should have no knowledge of this proposal. 3. The Blue Line was meant to sterilise a large area Tne £;nourable Sir Geoffrey Prior, K.C.I.iii.) ^Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.• 2 from mineral development and so keep Ibn Saud away from the Coast* There is no record here that any final decision was reached and since newspapers recently received report a large American oil drive in Saudi Arabia, the Sultan's claims may require detailed examination. Also, my recent demi-official report on the photographic activities of a Flying Fortress may have more relevance than I at first thought. 4. In 1940, Howes and Hickihbotham drew up maps of the Northern tip of Muscat and in 1936 Watts drew a map of the State from Khor Kuwai to Ras Darbat Ali, giving the Sultan authority over only a very narrow coastal strip. A copy was sent to the Senior Naval Officer but there is no record that one was forwarded to the Residency. In 1934, however, Bremner made a brief report on the subject in his Secret letter No. C/232 of 23rd October 1934.PERSIAN GULF RESILENCY, BAHRAIN, ZISL- CONFILENTIAL No. 401-S The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to:- 1) The Political Agent Musc at, 2) The Staff Officer (Intelligence) Persian Gulf, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document: dated the 13th February 1948. Reference to previous correspondence: D escri pt ion of enclosure : Subje ct^: Extract from Sharjah D.O. No. 96.0223, dated 25th January 1948 to SHINAS - SHARJAH ROAD the Political Agent, Bahrain. (Received under Bahrain Agency P.L. No. C/163, dated 5/2/48) a ■ ; -vi % ' ■ i Ip Jl7AI Extract from Sharjah D.0,No. 96*0223 datad 25th January, 1948 to Political Agant, Bahrain. 2* It so happens that the dividing line between the Sultan of Muscat’s and the Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah’s Jurisdiction in the vicinity of the track through the Wadi el Qaur is fairly closely defined and is not, as far as I am aware', disputed by either side, although this might be confirmed from Muscat. The extremity of Muscat territory is marked by a tower belonging to Muscat which overlooks the track where it passes near to village Aswad. Village Aswad which is marked on the blue print of the area, is in Muscat territory. 3. From Sharjah to the western entrance of the Wadi el Qaur there are two routes; the shorter, via Oud el Matina and south of Jabal Fayah; and the longer, via Kaqat al Hamra, FalaJ el Ali, Dhaid, Harada and Fill. I went by the former route and returned by the latter when I visited Kalba last week; and I marked them approximately on the blue print of the area. I also marked the course of the track through the Wadi el Qaur to Al Murair. 4. From Al Murair I understand the track runs through Khadhrawain to Shinas, although I did not traverse it myself. , —A 5. It may interest the Resident to know that almost the whole of the Wadi el Qaur is under Ras al Khaimah; but that he is impotent to maintain security. Previously he did so through the agency of liumaid bin Abdullah, the v Regent of Kalba’s nephew, whom he paid for this service. Humaid is now too debauched to perform it. The guards that Ras al Khaimah now maintains at Huwailat ( at the western end of the Wadi ) are paid for by the Muscat Government by arrangement with him. If any depredation \ is committed on the subjects of the Shaikhs of Ras al Khaimah oi* Sharjah on this route, it goes unpunished and unavenged. It is only when robbers loot the sunjects of Dubai or Fujairah travelling between Sharjah and the Wadi el Qaur that they are brought to book by the Shaikhs of Dubai and Fujairah themselves avenging their subjects in Sharjah and Ras al Khaimah limits. A.J.S.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000381_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/186</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000381</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/186</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/2 Muscat State Affairs: Boundary of Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-17T22:41:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (28 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 30; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-28; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns the boundaries of the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman. It includes four copies of a single page of notes on the boundaries of the Sultanate, dated January 1936 and prepared by the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat (ff 3-6), together with four versions of an accompanying sketch map showing the limits of the Sultanate (ff 7-10).The remainder of the file is mainly correspondence exchanged between the Political Agent and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, regarding whether or not certain locations fall within Muscat territory. One particular letter from the Political Agent to the Political Resident, dated 29 June 1944, provides details of what the Sultan of Muscat [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd] considers to be the interior boundaries of Muscat (these are given as four sets of degree coordinates, which the Sultan is said to have received from a previous Political Agent, Major Ralph Ponsonby Watts).Included among the correspondence are two further sketch maps depicting the north-eastern tip of the Arabian Peninsula.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Sultanate of Muscat and Oman</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Arabian Peninsula</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Boundaries</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000381#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>