<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002ec_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-10-24T10:20:25.654Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(D 45/25/^0 BRITISH RBoIDMCY, Bahrain . 25 th august, 1950 . OS it &lt;y Dear Consulate, We forward a copy of a letter No. C/195/50/ 3200 of the 9th august about the possibility of the opening up of Muscat airfield and should be glad of your comments. International .aeradio Limited have also asked us what facilities exist at Muscat as they have received similar queries and we forward a copy of the questionnaire showing the information required by them. We have told them that as far as we know there are no regular facilities and that it is * unlikely that Muscat will be capable of use commercially in the foreseeable future. But, if you see no objection, we should be grateful if you could give us the dimensions of the airfield and a rough estimate of its condition for their information. consulate, muscat *»- c**+J** t ** **£*/**» / J' •r v Yours xieslienoy. 0 d &gt; A , wmmmmsmmGOP Y No. C/X93/30/ 320O THE SECRETARIAT, ADEN. 9th August, 1950. Dear Residency, Aden Airways recently approached the Director of Civil Aviation with a view to initiating a service 'between Aden and ndia which would pass alternatively through either Masira or'Muskat. According to our known information of Muskat, substantiated as it is 'by the fact that Muskat is not included in the Muskat Air Agreement, we advised Aden Airways that the airfield at Muskat was an emergency one only and that no facilities for unseen approach or refuelling were available there. We still think this is the position and would be most grateful if you could confirm. At the same time, Aden Airways are definitely interested in going to Iviuskat if there is a possibility of the airfield being opened up. Can you also let us Know whether, if a suitable airfield does not already exist, one is in course of being prepared? 2 « Aden Airways have the idea that they can perform a useful service by linking Mombasa and Zanzibar with Muskat and, alternatively, Muskat with India. 3* We would be most grateful if you could give us your comments on this proposal and also if there is any project of Muskat being used commercially in ths fonsseeable future. Yours ever, His Excellency The Political Resident, c/o The Political Agent, Bahrain. SECRETARIAT.O' CQNFIJJ^TIaL ' 45 / 13/50 Major F.C.L. Chauncy, British Consul, MUSCAT. WITH THE COMPLIMENTS OF HIS MAJESTY'S POLITICAL RESIDENCY BRITISH RESIDENCY, 37433—5BKIilbU HB^IDEMCY, BAHRA1I. * tti *“■&gt;'» 1950 . I agree with the view expressed In your letter Ga 55/d of the 12th May that there is no Justification for surveying air field sites in Muscat territory so far as civil aviation is concerned. What I had chiefly in mind when I wrote my letter 45/4/50 of the 2bth January was that we ought to have plans ready for the construction of an adequate airfield st Muscat for implementation if required in the event of the outbreak of war f and in these circumstances 1 should perhaps have addressed Eastern rather than General Department. My letter was 9 however 9 copied to the Air Officer Commanding h.a.F. 9 Iraq and it can 9 I think, be left for him to press for further action to be taken should he consider this necessary. 1 am sending copies of this letter and of your letter under reply to the air Officer commanding R*A.F. 9 Iraq, the omnior Ravel Officer Persian Gulf and the British Middle Bast Office and Muscat. A.G.h. Bouse, iusq. , Q.B.k. 9 General Department, foreign Office, Lnnriftn- S.W. 1COPY FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l 12th May, 1950. (GA55/8) Dear sir Rupert Hay, Please refer to your letter 45/4/50 of the 26th January to James Murray (who incidentally left the Department in December and is now in Cairo). 2. You suggest that since the present Muscat air-field is unsatisfactory for large aircraft, it might be as well for us to survey alternative sites, in the event of our wishing to develop an aerodrome for such aircraft at a later date. 3« The fact is that unaer the terms of our agreement with the Sultan of Muscat we have rights and obligations only at Salalah, Masirah and Gwadur but not at Muscat itself. Furthermore we have no interest in passing local or trunk route services through Muscat which might justify expenditure on the air—field. In the circumstances we hope you will agree that there is no justification for surveying sites at present Yours sincerely, A.G.R. Rouse Lieutenant Colonel Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.K, BAHRAIN. &gt;• 9 c. b. I.,•&gt; 4fc/4/50 :8th Jan. 1950 CONFIDENTIAlN-^*^ The Political Agent, Muscat. WITH THE COMPLIMENTS OF HIS MAJESTY’S POLITICAL RESIDENCY(it) co*3t f'd % 1 *» rerun , t cmfte f t I is *»t *itb ^ u»h«» t ^nd tsi r^t ^r &lt;ien&lt;Jy f rj)4 l thlriH * sit* could ^Inoni e*rt*in!f ^cun4 h#r* t thru^. t«r*» of * oonercto st^ip imuld b# probchly n^^nssury, 1 wovld ouffoot t‘ if *n © r flc*r t« d* utodf rs I her- propound n t * lrft p*r*m *r*rb f * nho il4 v s t t? o pc • *! ^nd soloot oar for 4osrolo *h^* 14 t o nrer iitf rr' «o w 3* a »rn4inf? oc i s cf t ‘If l-ttor t tho Civil Mr • t^»ehe f tbt Mr C -'flc^r Co ana inf f lra^ f th« «*nior &gt;srM Officer, Pt^al^n Half, t « ^ritiab i id : o «at 0*Tio# t nd t-® Foil it 0*1 use^t* «?• Hvray, a ''•t Thr Oanrral Dop#rtB«fit 9 o^^irn ' ffif?* f LOflOOS.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002ec_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/100</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002ec</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/100</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2/21- Vol II BAITHAL- FALAJ LANDING GROUND’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1950/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-31T22:02:50</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (9 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 11; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence related to the possibility of opening up an airfield at Muscat. The main correspondents in the file are: the Political Agency, Muscat; and the Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Civil aviation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Airfields</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002ec#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>