<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000788.0x00038f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T06:48:24.723Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">* See page 17a. Secret Despatches to India, 1870. Letter from Foreign Office, 31st Jan. 1870 (Political). Letter to Foreign Office, 18th March 1870. Memorandum on Expenses of Zanzibar Consulate, &amp;c. For some years the India and Foreign Office, have been at a dead lock respecting the expenses, &amp;c., of the Zanzibar Agency. It may be useful to recapitulate briefly the circumstances of the case. Towards the end of 1869 a Special Committee sat at the Foreign Office, to inquire into the East African slave trade. Mr. (now Sir John) Kaye attended on hehalf of the India Office; the Foreign and Colonial Offices, Admiralty, and Treasury also sent representatives. On 24th January 1870 this Committee* pre sented their report to the Earl of Clarendon, then Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. Para. 80 reads as follows,—“ Meanwhile we are of opinion “ that, as so important a part of the duties of the “ Agent and Consul at Zanzibar is, at present, con- “ nected with this question of the suppression of the “ slave trade, it would be an equitable arrange- “ ment that the charges of the Zanzibar Agency “ and its dependencies should be equally shared “ between the Imperial and the Indian Exchequers,” &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c. The Foreign Office, in forwarding a copy of this Report to the India Office, requested an expression of the Duke of Argyll’s views thereon, whereupon His Grace caused a letter to be addressed to the Foreign Office, stating,— “ With respect to the recommendation in para. 80, that the expenses of the Zanzibar Establishment should be equally shared by the Imperial and the Indian Exchequers, I am to observe that the Secre tary of State for India in Council has always con sidered the existing arrangement, whereby the entire expense is thrown upon the Indian revenues, to be extremely unjust, and from time to time the injustice has been brought to the notice of the ^ Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. But so 1 long as the cos-t of maintaining Her Majesty’s ships ! of war in the Eastern Seas was borne entirely by the Imperial Exchequer, the Indian Government were not disposed to press the point with any greater urgency. Now, however, that a new arrangement has been made, whereby a large con tribution towards the maintenance of the Indian squadron is paid by this Government, the Secre tary of State lor India in Council cannot scruple to express a very decided opinion, to the effect that the expenses of the Zanzibar diplomatic establish ment should be equally shared between the two Governments. 16384. AUpon receipt of this letter, Lord Clarendon put himself in communication with the Lords Commis sioners of the Treasury, stating,— *&lt;***1 desire to acquaint your Lordships , that I have approved, with one exception, all the measures more immediately concerning this De partment which the Slave Trade Committee have proposed. They involve important reforms which it will be the duty of Her Majesty’s Political Agent to propose to the Sultan, and I consider it very important that these negotiations and the general direction of slave trade questions on the Last African coast should in future rest entirely with this Department, to prevent the risk of complica tions and conflicting orders, which have already arisen from the present system of divided superin tendence. “ The Secretary of State for India has concurred, in the letter of which I enclose copy, in this pro posal, but the Government of India would naturally object, so long as they alone bear the expenses of the Agency, to my assuming the control and direc tion of their Agent in matters relating to the slave trade. “ I would also remind your Lordships that the Slave Trade Vote will be considerably reduced by the abolition of three of the Mixed Commission Courts, and I hope before long to be able still further to relieve the vote by doing away with the rest of these Courts. “ The proposed charge will be of a temporary nature, and will cease when the slave trade is sup pressed on the East Coast, and the measures which are to be proposed to the Sultan will, I hope, lead to the gradual extinction of the slave traffic, and relieve the public from the heavy expense of main taining a large naval force to keep it in check. “ Moreover, as it is proposed to invite the Go vernment of India to assist in providing the extra force which is required on the East Coast, it seems only just that the Imperial Government should undertake a fair proportion of the expenses involved by the slave trade there. “ For these reasons I venture to recommend most strongly that your Lordships will give the necessary authority for charging the moiety of the expenses of the Zanzibar Agency to the Slave Trade Vote, on the understanding that this charge will cease with the extinction of the slave trade in . the Sultan’s dominions, and your Lordships will perhaps be good enough to acquaint me with your decision as soon as possible, as Mr. Churchill leaves for Zanzibar early next month.” Later in the same year, the Foreign Office asked the India Office for an account of the expenses of the Agency, including the proposed increase, in order that it might be submitted to the Treasury with the view of obtaining their sanction to the See Letter from Foreign Office to Treasury, 28th May 1870, p. 225 Secret Home Cor respondence, May to December 1870. Letter from Foreign Office, 10th Nov. 1870.Letter to Foreign Office, 16th Dec. 1870. Letter from Foreign Office, 24th March 1871. Letter to Foreign Office, 27th April 1871 (Political). payment of half the expenses out of Imperial Funds, as recommended by the Committee. This elicited a reply from the Duke of Argyll, to the effect that “ His Grace was of opinion, when he “ approved, through my letter of the 18th March “ last, the report of the Slave Trade Committee, “ that it was the intention of the recommendation of “ para. 80 of that report that the expenses of the “ Zanzibar Agency and Consulate should be equally “ divided, after increasing the aggregate amount by “ the expenditure necessary to carry out the sug- “ gestions of the Committee with respect to the “ additional Consulates named in the report.” The Lords of the Treasury having declined to provide the necessary funds to enable the Earl of Clarendon to act up to his intentions in the matter of the Zanzibar Consulate expenses, his Lordship communicated this decision to the Secretary of State for India, who thereupon addressed the following letter to the Foreign Office:— “ 1 am directed by the Duke of Argyll to acknow ledge the receipt of your letter of the 24th ultimo, giving cover to a communication written by order of the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury, in which their Lordships decline to defray from the Imperial Exchequer any part of the Consulate and Agency at Zanzibar. “ In reply to this, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India in Council to observe, that it is with extreme surprise and regret that he has been made acquainted with this decision of the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury. On the suggestion of Lord Clarendon, a Special Committee, at which the Foreign, the Colonial, and the India Offices, and the Admiralty, were represented, was appointed to investigate the whole question of the East African slave trade, and it was recommended by this Committee that, inasmuch as the duties of the Consul and Agent at Zanzibar, and the establish ment under him, were to a great extent connected with the suppression of the slave trade, and as the suppression of the slave trade was an Imperial, not an Indian question, the expenses of the Zanzibar Agency and Consulate should be equally divided between the Imperial and Indian Exchequers. This recommendation was Cordially sanctioned by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Secretary of State for India. But, as the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury have refused to accede to this proposed arrangement, the Secretary of State for India is compelled to regard the whole question of the cost of the Zanzibar Establishment from a new point of view, and to state distinctly his opinions on the subject. “The proceedings of the Special Committee sitting at the India Office, the report of which was laid before Parliament on the 24th January 1870, clearly shows the importance which the Imperial Government attach to the suppression of the EastAfrican slave trade. This, as observed by the Slave Trade Committee, is not an Indian but an Imperial question. The Government of India have, indeed, on more than one occasion, protested against the injustice of any part of the expenses attending the suppression of the East African slave trade being charged against the revenues of India. In the opinion thus expressed the Duke of Argyll concurs. It is only in consideration of the fact that there is an extensive trade between some parts of India and Zanzibar, that the Secretary of State for India in Council can sanction any expenditure at all on the maintenance of an establishment in this outlying territory. He desires, therefore, that you will state, for the information of Earl Granville, with a view to its communication to the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury, that his Grace will take immediate steps, through the Government of India, to place the Zanzibar Agency on an entirely new footing with reference to the requirements of Indian interests and commerce.’* In submitting this letter to the Lords Commis sioners of the Treasury, Lord Granville stated,— “ As this change will involve the loss of all control “ over, and probably the entire neglect of, all “ slave trade questions at Zanzibar, Lord Granville “ must again express his great regret at the de- “ cision which has provoked this Resolution on the “ part of the Government of India, and his strong “ hope that it may yet be rescinded.” Their Lord- ships, however, regretted “that they could not “ agree with his Lordship in thinking that the “ policy suggested in this correspondence warranted “ any addition to the Imperial expenditure already “ incurred on account of it.” This correspondence with the Treasury having been communicated to the Duke of Argyll by Earl Granville, who inquired “ whether, in these circum- “ stances, the Secretary of State for India means “ that the Agent is no longer to interfere in matters “ of Imperial interest, such as the slave trade and “ the traffic in slaves, and that he is to cease as “ hitherto to be under the control of this Depart- “ ment in regard to such questions,” His Grace replied as follows,— “ I am directed by the Duke of Argyll to acknow ledge the receipt of your letter of the 17th instant, enclosing a letter from the Treasury, stating that the Lords Commissioners absolutely refuse to make any payment from the Imperial Exchequer towards the maintenance of the Consulate and Agency at Zanzibar, and inquiring whether, in such circum stances, it is the intention of the Secretary of State in Council that the Agent, appointed and paid by the Indian Government, shall no longer interfere in affairs ot Imperial interest, and no longer be guided, in any respect, by instructions from the Foreign Office. In reply to this I am to state that the Governor General of India in Council has, on Foreign Office to Treasury, 5th May 1871, p. 809 Home Correspon dence, January to June 1871. Treasury to Foreign Office, 2nd June 1871. Letter from Foreign Office, 17th June 1871. Letter to Foreign Office, 22nd June 1871.5 Page 1245 Home Correspondence, July to September 1871. Letter from Foreign Office, 29th Aug. 1871. A more than one occasion, in the interests of the great dependency under his charge, protested against any appropriation of the revenues of India to such Im perial objects as the suppression of the slave trade and has even suggested the withdrawal of the Agent altogether, as an officer whose services are but little, if at all, required for purposes of a purely Indian character. Lord Granville is aware that in this opinion the Duke of Argyll has not concurred. But he considers it to be his duty to limit the em ployment of the Agent and the expenditure of the Agency to such objects as may tend directly to the promotion of the interests of India; and‘in this view it will be apparent to his Lordship that all instructions furnished to the officer selected by the Government of Bombay or the Government of India must emanate from those authorities, and that the ultimate controlling authority must be vested solely in the Secretary of State for India.” About this time a Select Committee of the House of Commons on East African Slave Trade pre sented their Report (4th August 1871), recom mending, amongst other things, that “ as the staff 44 of that establishment (at Zanzibar) would be “ largely employed in the suppression of the slave “ trade, the expense should be equally shared by “ the Indian and Imperial Governments.” Shortly after this Committee issued their Report, the Foreign Office addressed a letter to the India Office in the following terms,— “ I am directed by Earl Granville to request that you will state to the Secretary of State for India that his Lordship has waited for the Report of the Select Committee of the House of Commons upon the East African Slave Trade before taking any action upon your letter of the 22 nd June last, notifying that, in consequence of the repeated re fusal of the Treasury to contribute towards the expenses of the Zanzibar Agency, the duties of the Agent will be henceforward limited to such objects as may tend directly to promote the interests of India, and the controlling authority will be vested solely in the Government and Secretary of State for India, from whom all instructions must emanate. “ The Committee of the House of Commons having now recommended a division of the ex penses of the Agency between the Imperial and Indian revenues, a further representation will be made to the Treasury on this point, but in the meanwhile, and pending the reply of the Treasury, who, it is to be hoped, may be induced to reverse their former decision, I am to suggest that, with a view to prevent embarrassment and confusion in the administration of slave trade affairs at Zanzibar, the instructions to Dr. Kirk upon these matters might still be prepared by this Department, and forwarded, under flying seal, to the Secretary of State for India, to be transmitted by him to Zan zibar. 16384. B6 “ I am accordingly to enclose two Despatches which Lord Granville desires to send to Dr. Kiik, and to request that, if the Duke of Argyll concurs in this proposal and in their contents, he will cause them to be forwarded to Zanzibar by the earliest opportunity.” To which the Duke of Argyll replied as follows,— t( * * * In reply to your letter of 29th ultimo, I am directed to acquaint you that it is the wish of the Duke of Argyll that no sort of embarrassment to the public service should result from the present uncertainty with respect to the intentions of the Lords of the Treasury in the matter of the Zanzibar establishment, and that his Grace will be happy to forward to the Agent and Consul at that place such instructions as Lord Granville may desire to transmit with reference to the East African slave trade. I am, however, to add that the Secretary of State for India is strongly of opinion that no time should be lost in coming to a final decision respecting the recommendation of the Select Com mittee of the House of Commons, confirming as they do the opinions expressed by the Committee of Departments which sat for some time at the Foreign Office to consider and report upon the whole question.” Note .—As consequent on the refusal of the Treasury to grant the necessary funds for the payment of half the expense of the Zan zibar Consulate, the Foreign Office virtually gave up all control over the Agent at that place, legally their liability would appear to cease from the date of such abrogation of their rights, though of course the moral liability would remain in full force. In pursuance of the intention indicated in the above Foreign Office letter of 29th August 1871, Lord Granville addressed a lengthy protest to the Lords of the Treasury, as follows,— “ I am now to transmit to you, for the serious consideration of the Lords of the Treasury, a copy of the reply from the India Office, stating their Lordships’ decision has compelled them to determine that the duties and employment of their Political Agent shall in future be limited to such objects as tend directly to promote Indian interests, that all instructions sent to him must emanate from the Indian Government, and that the ultimate controlling authority must be vested in the Government. “ As the Indian Government have always held the suppression of the slave trade to be a question of Imperial, and not of Indian interest, the decision will probably involve the neglect of slave trade questions, and certainly the loss of control over the Agent at Zanzibar hitherto exercised by the Foreign Secretary. Letter to Foreign Office, 6th Sept. 1871. Foreign Office to Treasury, 16th Oct, 1871, p. 175 Home Corre spondence,October to December 1871.Telegram to Viceroy, 19 th June 1872. 7 “ The Lords of the Treasury must be aware of the heavy and important duties that devolve upon the Agent at Zanzibar as Judge of the Vice- Admiralty Court in the trial of slave trade cases, and they can appreciate as well as Lord Granville the serious mischief likely to ensue from a neglect of those duties, as well as from the absence of instruction from the only Department competent to direct the Agent in slave trade matters, but unless this decision is reversed, it is evident either that the Department must entirely surrender the direction of slave trade affairs on the East Coast, or that Her Majesty’s Government must appoint and pay special agents of their own. “ Matters are now at a complete deadlock. No instructions can be sent to the agents from this Department, and the question is reduced to the single and simple issue whether the Imperial Government shall persevere in or abandon its endeavours to suppress the slave trade on the coast. “ A Select Committee of the House of Commons, recently appointed, has, after hearing the best evidence that could be produced, reported strongly in favour of perseverance, and increased expen diture on a better system, and, without endorsing all these proposals, which have not yet been suffi ciently considered, Lord Granville cannot doubt that, looking to the strong feeling which pervades the country on the subject of the slave trade, the spirit of their report will find a response in Par liament, and in the public generally, who will insist upon more being done. “ Lord Granville is decidedly of opinion that such a general feeling cannot be disregarded by Her Majesty’s Government, and at all events, as Secretary of State tor Foreign Affairs, he will not assume the responsibility of disregarding it. It must rest therefore with the Lords Commissioners of Her Majesty’s Treasury to decide whether they will, as the first step, grant or withhold the sums necessary to meet the expenditure for such an establishment as may be required at Zanzibar for carrying out a more vigorous and better organized policy lor the suppression of the slave trade on the East Coast of Atfica under the direction of Her Majesty’s Government.” Up to the present time, no reply has been re ceived from the Foreign Office as to the decision of the Treasury in the matter, though the subject was brought to the notice of Earl Granville in the India Office Letters of 14th November 1871, 21st March (Political) and 1st August 1872, 29th July 1873, 2nd May and 7th October 1874. It is true that on 19th June 1872 the Duke of Argyll telegraphed to the Viceroy that the “ Im- “ perial Government (are) to take half expense.” This message, however, was dictated by the Duke of Argyll personally, after, it is believed, a con-8 sultation with his colleagues, aud was not founded on any official correspondence. Notr .—It may be remarked that, in a letter to the India Office, dated 17th March 1873, the Foreign Office stated, with reference to the pro posed appointment of an Assistant to Dr. Kirk, that Lord Granville “ presumes that, as it is “ arranged that a moiety of the expense of the “ Zanzibar Agency is to be borne by Imperial “ funds, this Department will be consulted “ w ith regard to an Assistant to Dr. Kirk “ before any such appointment is made.” This course was subsequently pursued. See Letters to Foreign Office, 28th March and 16th April 1873, and from Foreign Office, 25th April 1873. The letter from the Foreign Office, just received, would seem to indicate that the Treasury are pre pared to provide the necessary funds, so far, at any rate, as the future is concerned; the exact words used are as follows :— “ With reference to that part of your letter of 7 th ultimo, which relates to a statement of accounts between the Imperial and Indian Governments in regard to the Zanzibar Agency, I am directed by the Earl of Derby to request that you will state to the Marquis of Salisbury that, no provision having hitherto been made in the Consular Estimates for defraying any portion of the expenses connected with the Agency and Consulate at Zanzibar, it has not been possible to settle this matter with the India Office. ‘•It is proposed, however, to submit for the approval of the Treasury, in the estimates for the ensuing year, a statement of the expenses con nected with the suppression of the slave trade on the East Coast of Africa, and it is intended to include in this a statement of the share of the expenses to be paid by the Imperial Government in connexion with the Zanzibar Agency, and with the view to enable Lord Derby to have this estimate , framed, I am to request that you will move the Secretary of State for India in Council to furnish his Lordship with a detailed statement of the ex penses of the Zanzibar Agency, and of the salaries assigned to the persons comprising the staff of such Agency.” It will be observed that no reference is made in this communication to the question of past expendi ture, but it may be inferred that if the Imperial Government admit their liability to bear a share of future expenses at Zanzibar, that liability should commence from the period when the matter was originally settled as between the India and Foreign Offices, that is, the commencement of 1870. It may be useful, however, to recapitulate con cisely how matters stand in respect of these arrears. Letter from Foreign Office, 16th Nov. 1874Letter from Foreign Office, 18th Oct. 1872, See pp. 751-2. Home Corre spondence, July to December 1872. Letter from Foreign Office, 18th Oct. 1872. ni i 'ttibiil moil TilJovl .8781 lo 78 .oVI Letter to Foreign Office, 28th Oct. 1872. Telegram from Bombay, llth August 1872. “ Four years and a half subsidy due. No money in hand, but Rs. 22,850 paid by us for Sultan to Turki have yet to bo recovered. Last payment re ceived 6th May 1868.” ; ‘lallu Letter from Foreign Office, 18th Oct. 1872. First, as regards the subsidy from Zanzibar to Muscat. When Sir Bartle Frere was despatched on a special mission to Zanzibar (1872), he received a letter of instructions signed by Earl Granville, as representing the Imperial Government, authorizing him, amongst other things, to “ give the Sultan “ (Zanzibar) such assurances as may satisfy him “ that the payment of the subsidy will not be “ enforced against him, &amp;c., &amp;c. * * * On “ the other hand, you are empowered, on similar “ conditions, to give similar assurances to the Ruler “ of Muscat, that the amount to which he may be “ entitled under the aforesaid award will be regu- “ larly paid to him from Her Majesty’s Treasury at “ Bombay. ,, The instructions as above were forwarded by the Foreign Office to the India Office, with a request that Lord Granville might be informed whether the Duke of Argyll “ concurred in the drafts in question, ' or had any observations or suggestions to make ' in regard to them.” v Whereupon His Grace replied, * * * “ In “ common with all the members of Her Majesty’s “ Gpvernment, the Duke of Argyll takes the “ warmest interest in all that relates to the sup- “ pression of the East African slave trade, but it is «* with the political and commercial interests in- « volved in the relations of the Rulers of Muscat «« and Zanzibar with the Indian Government and “ with each other that this Department is princi- “ pally concerned. And I am to acquaint you, for “ the information of Lord Granville, that His Grace ♦* fully approves of the instructions which his Lord- « ship has issued on these important points, with « such additions or alterations as are noted in the “ margin of the drafts submitted to him. His Grace « would, however, observe that, with respect to the “ payment of the subsidy covenanted to be dis- « bursed by the Ruler of Zanzibar to the Ruler of “ Muscat, there are considerable arrears, under the « old award of 1861, to the latter State. The « Duke of Argyll has lately obtained from the Go- « vernment of Bombay information upon this sub- “ject, the details of which are annexed, and it « cannot be doubted that the question of the pay- « ment of those arrears is one which at an early « period will be brought before Sir B. Frere. The “ Duke of Argyll would, therefore, desire to be in- “ formed whether, in the opinion of Lord Granville^. “ a paragraph relating to this topic should be intro- “ duced into the general letter of instructions, or “ whether there should be a separate instruction on “ this subject to Sir B. Frere.” * * * No reply was sent by the Foreign Office to this letter, nor does either of the above suggestions appear to have been carried out. Again, in replying to a letter from the Foreign Office, requesting His Grace to defray from the 16384. C10 Indian Exchequer one halt of the expenses ot Sir B. Frere’s mission, the Duke of Argyll especially mentioned the subsidy; the exact words were,— * * * t*i am instructed to say that the ex penditure which is now sanctioned by the Secretary of State in Council on behalf of the revenues of India is the one half of the subsidy paid by Zanzibar to Muscat under the terms of Lord Canning’s arbi tration, should it be found necessary to relieve the Ruler of Zanzibar from that subsidy, together with one half of the (territorial) permanent ex penses of the Agency and Consulate, as recom mended by the Slave Trade Committee which sat at the Foreign Office, and which recommendations were agreed upon both by the Foreign and the Indian Departments of Her Majesty’s Govern ment.” Sir B. Frere’s action in the matter may be told in his own words,— * * * “It would have been within the letter of my instructions to have given His Highness (Sultan of Muscat) at once a distinct assurance that the subsidy would be regularly paid to him from Her Majesty’s Treasury at Bombay, but I thought the assurance would come with more effect from His Excellency the Viceroy, and I wished to comply with the obvious wish of His Highness, that the two questions of slave trade and subsidy should be kept clearly distinct and separate.” * * * « It was under this conviction, and in considera tion of the time which must necessarily elapse before the question of the subsidy can be defini tively disposed of, that I authorized Syed Turki to draw at once on the Political Agent at Muscat for #40,000 (8,500/.), being one year’s arrears of sub sidy, and, at the expiration of three months, for a further sum of # 20 , 000 , being half the subsidy due for the current year, unless other measures for settling the question should be taken in the in terim. * * * “I would submit, for the consideration of His Excellency the Viceroy, that the Government of India should assure His Highness, by an autograph letter from His Excellency the Viceroy, that the Zanzibar subsidy will be regularly paid, with all arrears, from the Bombay Treasury to His High ness’s agent in Bombay, as long as His Highness abstains from all aggressions on Zanzibar, and ob serves the obligations he and his predecessors have entered into regarding the suppression of the slave trade.” “ The subsidy thus paid should, I think, be punc tually and peremptorily recovered from Zanzibar.” In consequence of this strong recommendation the Viceroy of India instructed the Political Agent at Muscat to give the Sultan of Muscat a guarantee of the nature indicated by Sir B. Frere. In re- Letter to Foreign Office, 25th Oct. 1872. Enclosures in Letter from India, No. 87 of 1873. Letter from India, No. 87 of 1863. •11 Letter from India, 87 of 1873. Letter to Foreign Office, 29th July 1873. Letters from India, 149 of 1873, and 189 of 1874. * Enclosures of Letter from India, 87 of 1873. f Page 231, Printed Papers, “ Sir B. Frere’s Mission.” porting their proceedings to the Duke of Argyll the language used was as follows,— “ Para. 2. Your Grace will perceive that we have guaranteed to His Highness the payment of of the Zanzibar subsidy of 40,000 crowns, from the date of his accession to the throne of Muscat, and have promised that it shall be regularly paid during his rule, so long as he continues faithfully to fulfil his obligations to the British Government. « 3. We must leave it to Her Majesty’s Govern ment to determine the steps to be taken for the recovery of the subsidy from Zanzibar, as these measures are intimately connected with the ar rangements to be adopted for the suppression of the slave trade, consequent on the refusal of the Sultan of Zanzibar to conclude a new Treaty. Meanwhile, from the enclosures of the Despatch from the Assistant Secretary in the Political and Secret Department, No. 138, of 20 th December 1872, we understand that if any portion of the sums now or hereafter advanced to Syud Turki on account of the subsidy be not eventually reco vered from Zanzibar, the half of such unrecovered advances will be repaid to us by Her Majesty’s Imperial Government.” Copy of this Despatch was forwarded to the Foreign Office, 29th January 1873. Note .—There is nothing on the records to show that any intimation was conveyed to the Sultan of Zanzibar that he would be relieved of the payment of the subsidy, which still can be re covered from that State should the Imperial Government decide upon such a course. In fulfilment of the arrangement mentioned above, further sums were from time to time paid to Syud Turki of Muscat, who appears to have received the subsidy up to August 1874, with arrears from February 1871 (^140,000, about 29,750/. Note .—It must not be overlooked that at the time Sir B. Frere, under instructions from the Impe- Government, recommended the payment of the subsidy to Syud Toorkee, to whom he had .him self previously paid one whole year’s allowance (8,500/.), the Government of India w ? ere not disbursing* anything to Muscat; on the con trary, they had allowed the Sultan to appeal in vain for advances of money, and had written off as a bad debt f the amount owing by His Highness. The matter was therefore at an end, and had not Sir B. Frere been sent out on his Slave Trade Mission, the Government of India would not have spent any of the large sum defrayed, under his suggestions, to further the interests of Her Majesty’s Imperial Govern ment in the suppression of the slave trade.] 16384. D12 There remain a few items of expenditure, which may be briefly stated,— (1.) Government buildings at Zanzibar, the in terest on which would fairly fall on the two Trea suries, especially since some of them were pur chased, repaired, &amp;c., on the understanding, so far as the Government of India were concerned, that the expenditure would be jointly paid by the Im perial and Indian Exchequers. The value of them is roughly estimated by Dr. Kirk, the Political Agent at 9,000/. They consist of— ^ New Political Agency - - - 5,300 Original ditto - - - 1,100 Jail (repairs of) - - - - 437 v £6,837 The balance would be represented by the original cost of Jail and Surgeons’ quarters - - 2,163 Secret Letter from India, Nos. 51 of 1873 and 3 of t874. Political Con sultations, Oct. 1866, Nos. 8 to 10. Foreign General Letter from India, No. 28 of 1874. £9,000 Interest on the above would be 450/. per annum, i.e., 225/. for the Imperial Government. (2.) Half the Furlough Pay of Officers. —This, being a variable amount, can only be approximately stated at, say 800/., per annum, «.e„ 400/. for the Imperial Government. (3.) Interpreters .—In March 1873, Sir Bartle Secret Letter from Frere suggested to the Government of India that “ the India ’ No - 54 of 44 service of interpreters should be continuous, and 1873 ’ 16th June ' “ should entitle them to pensions, under the usual “ rules of the Indian Uncovenanted Service. “ They should be borne on the books of the Poli- “ tical Agent’s establishment, and charged, when &lt;c afloat only, to the vessel on board which they are “ serving.” Establishment. 2 First-class at Ss. per diem; with rations when afloat, without when ashore. S Second-class at 65 . per diem; with rations when afloat, without when ashore. 16 Third-class at 3^. per diem; with rations when afloat, without when ashore. This scheme was approved by the Government Letter as above, ot India, on the understanding “ that half the ex penditure involved in the above measures will be “ ?T' e Her Imperial Treasury and “ half by the Government of India.” This would involve a charge of 2, at 8^. per diem - 8, at 6$. „ 16, at 3^. 292 per annum. 876 876 £2,044 itMarine Letter from India, No. 9 of 1874. To Foreign Office, 12th Sept. 1874. From Foreign Office, 26th Oct. From Admiralty, 23rd Nov. 1874. One half of this, say 1 , 000 /. per annum, would fall upon the Imperial Government. [Note .—No allusion is made here to the recent correspondence respecting allowance to Naval Officers, who may qualify as interpreters, since the whole charge being borne by the Admiralty, neither the India nor Foreign Offices are con cerned in the matter.] A. N. W. Political and Secret Department, 16th December 1874.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000788.0x00038f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B11</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000788.0x00038f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B11</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memorandum on Expenses of Zanzibar Consulate, &amp;c.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1874/1874</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-01-05T18:55:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>7 folios</extent><extent>The memorandum consists of an outline of events (ff 73-78), followed by a statement of expenditure at the end (ff 78-79).</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 73, and terminates at f 79, as it is part of a larger volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 5-168; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>A memorandum explaining the deadlock between the India and Foreign Offices regarding the expenses of the Zanzibar Agency. With quotations from correspondence, the text gives an outline of the principal events since 1861 to document a historical disagreement between the departments over the principle of which department should pay for work carried out by the Zanzibar Agency relating to the abolition of the East Africa slave trade. Written by Arthur Naylor Wollaston, 16 December 1874.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Zanzibar</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight Arthur Naylor Wollaston</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Abolition of slavery</topic></subject><subject><topic>Expenditure</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000788.0x00038f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>