<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002b7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:01:28.394Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">XTbis Document is the Property of His Britannic Msjeaty b Government] SECRET. Political Intelligence Department, Foreign Office. Special No. 4. MEMORANDUM ON BRITISH COMMITMENTS TO THE IDRISI. 1HE Idrisi had for many years before the war been de facto the independent rulei of a tract of the Arabian Peninsula on the borders of Asir and Yemen. From this tract he had effectively excluded the Turks, with whom he was in a chronic state of war, and duung the Tui*co-Italian war of 1911—12 the Italians entered into relations with him, and supplied him with arms. On the other hand, Ids independence had never been recognised by foreign Powers; and in the division of the Arabian Peninsula into a Turkish and a British sphere, effected by the Anglo-Turkish Conventions of the 29th July, 1913, and 9th March, 1914,* the Idrisi s country was implicitly recognised by His Majesty’s Government as beiner under the sovereignty of Turkey. The fact, however, that the Idrisi possessed a coastline and two ports—Meidi and Jezan—over which the Turks had no control, brought him into direct relations with foreign governments on commercial matters, and he was thus in touch with His Majesty’s Resident at Aden.f In August 1913 he sent his Minister to Aden to discover His Majesty’s Govern ments attitude towards him (in view, no doubt, of the Anglo-Turkish Convention concluded shortly before). And he again had a confidential agent at Aden in September 19144 Af that time Turkey had not intervened in the war, but her attitude was already threatening, and on the 11th September, L914, the Resident at Aden accordingly telegraphed to Bombay suggesting that overtures to the Idriei should be made by His Majesty’s Government on the following lines :— “ We could make Idrisi an offer of protection and friendship and a distinct adjudication of his claims against Imam; we could also make over to him Farsan, »vhich was his property once and which was taken by Porte; also vve would leave open his ports Meidi, Habl, and Djezan.” The Idrisi, the Turks, and the Imam of Sanaa were engaged in a three-cornered duel, and, in the event of war with Turkey, it was clearly His Majesty’s Government’s interest to obtain the co-operation against the Turks of at least one, and if possible both, of the two Arab rulers. The Turks, however, made a very high bid for the Imam’s friendship, and it rapidly became clear that he would not take sides with us against them. In these circumstances the establishment of relations with the Idrisi became essential. On the 30th October, 1914, the Resident telegraphed to the Government of India reporting that the Idrisi’s agent had assured him that the Idrisi had not come to terms with the Imam and would never do so with the Turks, and proposing that a verbal message should be sent him through the agent.§ This proposal was transmitted by the Viceroy to the India Office in a telegram of the 1st November, 19141| :— “ It seems desirable that negotiations with Idrisi’s agent should immediately be commenced by Resident on lines proposed in his telegram of the 11th ultimo with these modifications. He should offer our protection and friendship and good offices to Idrisi, but not adjudication in settlement of differences with Imam, also protection of his ports Djezan, Meidi, and Habl. Restoration to him of Farsan in event of w r ar might be hinted but not promised by Resident. In negotiating with Idrisi Resident should be warned to do nothing likely finally to estrange Imam, who appears to be wavering.” * See Draft of Despatch, dated August lh!4, to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Constantinople. t Reference to trade between Aden and Idrisi ports in 12483/15. f 59460/14 and 38722/15 (reprint of correspondence communicated by Government of India). § 65723/14. JJ 66302/14 and 68203/14. [884] B2 On the 31st October, 1914,* the India Office, anticipating the above telegram, had telegraphed instructions to the Viceroy, regarding the Resident’s proposal, as follows : “His Majesty’s Government are unwilling, subject to anything which you may have to say, to commit themselves to a definite offer to the Idrisi, fulfilment of which they may be unable to enforce even in the most favourable circumstances, and they are not prepared to undertake adjudication of details between his claims and those of the Imam. His Majesty’s Government will, however, be glad to exercise their good offices in bringing the two parties together .... Assurance should be given to the Idrisi that Gfeat Britain and her Allies will not touch the Holy Places or Jeddah, and that they have no intention of taking naval action which will affect his ports. In the general settlement on the conclusion of the war, he may count upon their diplomatic assistance to secure his autonomy. You may promise him such arms and ammunition as can be spared by you. ’ Their instructions differed from the Viceroy’s in omitting all mention of the Farsan Islands, a point in which the Foreign Office concurred and on which specific instructions were sent to the Viceroy by the India Office on the 7th November, 1 9 L4.t Meanwhile, on the 4th November, 1914, the Resident had telegraphed that the Idrisi’s agent was leaving Aden to communicate to the Idrisi the terms of the Viceroy s telegram of the 1st November, 1914, and that it was urgent that the negotiations should be carried through. J On the 21st November, 1914, the Idrisi wrote to the Resident expressing approval of the suggestion that the Arabs should unite against the Turks, thanking His Majesty’s Government for the promise to send him arms and to leave his ports unblockaded, and asking that his independence should be assured, and a reliable representative sent to discuss the preliminaries for an agreement.§ In view of this letter, the Government of India made the following proposals to the India Office in a telegram dated the 20th December, 1914 |j : — “ A reply might, we consider, be sent to the Resident, either by a letter or through a reliable source, to the effect that Idrisi’s expressions of friendship have been received with satisfaction by the British Government, who are prepared to give him a guarantee of independence if he succeeds definitely in effecting a union of his Arabs against the Turks and in preventing their use of his country as a base of operations against Great Britain; also that the extent to which he co-operates will determine the question of any further reward. And on the 28th December, 1914, the India Office, with the concurrence of the Foreign Office, accordingly instructed the Viceroy by telegram as follows ^[:— “ The Imam’s attitude leaves us no alternative but to give a guarantee of independence to Idrisi, and I therefore approve your proposals, although the guarantee exceeds assurances sanctioned in my telegram of the olst October. On the 29th January, 1915, the Resident reported that the Idrisi’s Minister had arrived at Aden to negotiate,** and on the 30th January, 1915, that the Idrisi had seized the Farsan Islands, forestalling the British Navy.tj On the 3rd February, 1915, the Resident telegraphed as follows JJ:— “The Idrisi’s Minister here is quite prepared to attack the Turks at once .... He asxs for a protectorate treaty with us, and wants arms and ammunition immediately, and a sum of money to further bis object .... Terms of Hny subsequent treaty need only include his security against attack by sea, and a promise of diplomatic support after the war to secure autonomy against his rival, the Imam.” In reply to this telegram, the Government of India sent the Resident instructions, of which they informed the India Office on the 5th February, 1915 §§:— “ W e have .... authorised Resident to negotiate treaty with Idrisi on understanding that this is subject to confirmation of Government of India, and that any terms likely finally to alienate Imam while still wavering are avoided.” * 66302/14 and 68203/14. f 6;)670/14. J 67437/14. § Telegram of the 17th December, 1014, from the Resident in 84480/14. || 87030/14. 1 87030/14 and 1305/15. ** 11366/15. ff 12433/15. 13751/15 and 15889/15. §$ 14126/15The India Office replied on the 17th February, 1915, by approving the Viceroy’s action, hut requesting that they should be given an opportunity of considering the terms of the treaty in substance.* On the 9th March, 1915, the Itesident at Aden telegraphed again t “ Idrisi representative here is extremely anxious to make a treaty of friendship on the basis of security of his seaboard against all enemies, and our diplomatic support after conclusion of hostilities to effect his autonomy against all rivals. All this is as already intimated reasonable, and a necessary preliminary to a pact.” The telegram then proceeds to urge that certain additional requests for arms on the part of the Idrisi shall be granted. “ As representative wishes to leave for Djezan in three days, I ask for early sanction. After putting case before his master this agent will return to Aden to conclude a treaty.” In answer to this telegram, the Government of India instructed the Resident as follows on the 13th March, 1915 :—J “ You should inform Idrisi’s agent that, before the Government of India can contemplate the gift of further arms or money, they must first see the draft agreement which Idrisi is prepared to conclude with them, and have some positive evidence of the co-operation he is prepared to offer in return for such agreement.” And on the 15th March, 1915, the Viceroy telegraphed in the same sense to the India Office. § On the 16th March, 1915, however, the India Office replied to the Viceroy approving the proposals of the Resident in his telegram of the 9th March, 1915.|| The terms of a treaty were accordingly drafted at Aden by the British authorities there and the Idrisi’s Minister, and on the 30th April, 1915, the Viceroy transmitted to the India Office a report from the Resident, dated the 28th April, ]915,^[ announcing that a treaty had been concluded with the Idrisi, subject to ratification by the Govern ment of India, and that the Idrisi would lose no time in acting against the Turks. A copy of the treaty, signed, and dated the 30th April, 1915, was communicated to the Foreign Office by the India Office on the 26th May, 1915.** The text of it, in the form in which it was eventually ratified, is appended to the present memorandum, but a summary of its main provisions may be given here:— Article 1. Names of the signatories. Art. 2. The objects are—(a) to war against the Turks and (b) to make a pact of friendship between His Majesty’s Government and the Idrisi and his tribesmen. Art. 3. The Idrisi is to attack the Turks in the Yemen and extend his territories at their expense. Art. 4. He will abstain from hostile or provocative action against the Imam so long as the latter does not join the Turks. Art. 5. “ His Majesty’s Government undertake to safeguard the Idrisi’s territories from all attack on the seaboard from any enemy who may molest him ; to guarantee his independence in his own domain ; and, at the conclusion of the war, to use every diplomatic means in their power to adjudicate between the rival claims of the Idrisi and the imam, or any other rival.” Art. 6. “ His Majesty’s Government have no desire to enlarge their borders on Arabian soil,” but desire that there shall be friendly relations (a) between all the Arab rulers, each in his own sphere; and (b) between each of them and His Majesty’s Government. ... Art. 7. His Majesty’s Government promise to assist the Idrisi with arms and money, in proportion to the part played by the Idrisi in the war. Art. 8. His Majesty’s Government, while blockading all Turkish ports, will con tinue to leave trade open between the Idrisi ports and Aden. Art. 9. Ratification by the Government of India is necessary to make this treaty valid. On the 20th May, 1915, the Government of India commented on these terms as follows in a despatch to the India Office :—j't “ The only point that appears to require definite qualification is the expression ‘ Arabian soil ’ in article 6, as this scarcely falls in with our position in Mesopotamia. If the words ‘ Western Arabia’ were substituted for ‘Arabian soil’ this objection would be removed, and our intentions would be sufficiently defined in the treaty. || 33646/15 20143/15. t 28470/15. H 53328/15. [884] X 50398/15. ** 66940/15. § 30960/15. tt 79794/15. B 2“ It might also be urged that, by allowing the Idrisi, under article 3, to extend his territories, and, at the same time, under article 5, guaranteeing his independence hereafter, we may be bringing ourselves into an embarrassing position vis-d-vis other Arab chiefs, but our position in this matter is safeguarded by the condition that the extension of the Idrisi’s territories should be at the expense of the Turks, and, should he hereafter involve himself in a collision with other Arab chiefs by an aggressive policy, we could point to this condition, and disavow his action. “Further, it might have been desirable to insert a clause giving British and British Indian traders free access to the Idrisi’s ports, but this might legitimately be held to be a corollary of the pact of friendship which it is the object of the treaty to consolidate. “As any further assistance in funds or munitions to the Idrisi is explicitly to be m accordance with the measure of the Idrisi s activities, our responsibilities in this matter would appear to be sufficiently safeguarded. “ We think, therefore, that, although the treaty as drafted is open to objection on the ground that it is neither very clear nor very concise, it will, if the small amendment suggested (in the first paragraph quoted) above be effected, adequately meet the requirements of the situation. We would ask, therefore, for authority to ratify it as it stands, subject to this qualification. To return it for extensive revision to our Political Resident would be to endanger the ultimate success of the negotiations, and would, at any rate, involve undesirable delay. If your Lordship agrees, we should be glad of orders by telegraph.’’ In answer to this, the India Office, with the concurrence of the Foreign Office, # telegraphed to the Viceroy as follows on the 21st June, 1915 :—t “ His Majesty’s Government approve treaty with substitution of words ‘ Western Arabia.’ We prefer this not so much because of Mesopotamia as because of Sheikh Saiyid, which it may be necessary to annex after war, and which we regard as Southern rather than Western Arabia. This possibility should be borne in mind in any language used to Arabs.” And these instructions were transmitted by the Government of India to the Resident at Aden in a telegram dated the 24th June, 1915. J Copies of the treaty, which had been forwarded from Aden to Simla on the 1st May, 1915, were now sent back on the 28th June, 1915, for this alteration to be made ; but on the 20th July, 1915, the Resident reported that it was not possible at that stage to get hold of the signatories. On the 23rd August, 1915, the Resident reported § further that, in the Arabic text of the treaty, the counterpart to the English words “ Arabian soil” (Art. 6) was “ the Yemen.” “ It was explained to Saiyid Mustafa, the signatory of the treaty, who is now here, that the word ‘ Yemen ’ was not an adequate translation of the amended English, but he did not approve of any alteration. He remarked that, were the British Government to annex Sheikh Said, Mokha or Hodeida, his master would be only too pleased, as he indeed was at our occupation of Kamaran. “ In these circumstances, it is not considered politic to amend the Arabic reading. The English wording is of course authoritative. “ does not seem therefore necessary to re-write the treaty, for such a course would create suspicion in the Arab mmd.” In view of this despatch the Viceroy telegraphed as follows to the India Office on the 5th October, 1915 :— jj “ We do not consider use of term Yemen in the Arab text open to serious objection. Should we desire to take over Sheikh Said, our action would be justifiable, in view of Arab and Turkish acts of aggression, under a broad interpreta tion of clause 6 of the proposed treaty. We therefore suggest immediate ratification.” this was approved by the India Office, with the concurrence of the Foreign Office,^ on the 23rd October, 1915. # * r ^ r ? a ty was ac p or dmgly ratified by the Viceroy in Council on the 6th November, 1915,11 with the substitution of the words “Western Arabia” for “Arabian soil” in the English text, but with no alteration in the Arabic. * 79794/15. f 83129/15. || 145027/15. If 152356/15. t 126147/15. § 152356/15. ** 168899/15. ff 193583/15.Relation of Commitments to the Idrisi to British Desiderata. The British desiderata involved in this treaty with the Idrisi appear to lie (a) the extension of the British “ trucial system” to the whole of the Arabian Peninsula, and (b) the maintenance and improvement of our position at Aden. The general policy underlying both these desiderata is expressed in article 6 of the treaty ; but, as the Government of India remarked in their despatch of the 20th May, 1915, the terms seem to lack precision. As regards (a) it is an essential condition in a trucial treaty that the independent ruler who is a party to it shall liave no relations with foreign Powers except through His Majesty’s Government, and shall not lease or alienate to them any portion of his territory. In the present treaty this is nowhere laid down, and the India Office, in their letter of the 17th June, 1915, to the Foreign Office covering the Government of India’s despatch of the 20th May, 19 1 8, justly remarked in this connection (79794/15) :— “ The matter referred to in paragraph 5 of the despatch (British trade in Idrisi ports and territory) will, in Mr. Chamberlain’s opinion, be more suitably dealt with after the war, when some further treaty with the Idrisi will probably be necessary in any case, e.g., to ensure that he does not cede any port or island to a foreign Power, and to regulate the arms traffic.” Again, in the stricter forms of trucial treaty, His Majesty’s Government undertake to keep the peace between the other party to the treaty and his neighbours possessing similar treaties with His Majesty’s Government, while the other party undertakes not to resort to force for the settlement of disputes, but to refer them to His Majesty’s Government for arbitration. In the present treaty His Majesty’s Government merely undertake to endeavour, by diplomatic means, to adjudicate between the claims of the Idrisi and his neighbours. r l his was perhaps the most we could do at the time when the treaty was drafted, since neither the Sherif of Mecca nor the Imam of Sanaa were at that time in relations with us. But now that the Sherif has made an alliance with us, and the Imam has approached us with this object, it becomes important that we should place our relations with these three rulers as far as possible on an equal footing, and assume a treater control over their relations with one another. The difficulties with which we shall be confronted are illustrated by the dispute in 1916 between the Idrisi and the Sherif over the possession of Kunfida (182183/16 and 215155/16 (No. 142) ), in which the Idrisi accepted our award provisionally, but only subject to reconsideration, under article 5 of our treaty, at the conclusion of the war. 1 he still more difficult problem of demarcation between the Idrisi and the Imam was raised by the Resident at Aden in July of the same year (133274/16 and 133783/16), but this w T as deprecated by the Viceroy as premature (136686/16). Whatever settlement of these questions we may succeed in making, fresh demarcation and allegiance disputes between these three rulers will continually be arising, and it is submitted that His Majesty’s Government will not be able to deal with them effectively unless they conclude a trucial treaty on stricter lines with the Imam, and supplement their treaty with the Idrisi, and their still more indefinite arrangements with the Sherif, in this direction. As regards trade, again, His Majesty’s Government guarantee the Idrisi facilities at Aden under article 8, while there is no corresponding guarantee for British trade in the Idrisi’s ports and territory. The Government of India, however, pointed out in their despatch of the 20th May, 1915, that this may be regarded as implicitly covered by the “ pact of friendship ” laid down in article 1. Finally, as regards (b) the position of Great Britain at Aden, it may perhaps be doubted whether the words “Western Arabia” in the English text of article 6, and “ ^1 emen ” in the Arabic, do strictly admit of any territorial enlargement of our Protectorate. And our case on this point is prejudiced by our negotiations with King Husein. For in his first letter of July 1915 to Sir H. McMahon, Husein, while he excepted the Aden Protectorate from the boundaries he claimed for Arab independence, made no reference to rectifications of the Aden frontier; and Sir H. McMahon, when, in his letter of the 24th October, 1915, he accepted the proposed boundaries, subject to modifications in Syria, implicitly pledged himself, as regards Aden, to the status quo.Ill practice, however, any improvement of our position at Aden would affect not the Sherif and the Idrisi, but the Imam. And though the former may find it necessary in public to avoid signing awa} T Moslem soil to the unbeliever, or Arab soil to the foreigner, they w r ould neither of them be sorry to see their rival, the Imam, weakened by an extension of’ British power at his expense. In fact, the Idrisi’s Minister has, in private, quite frankly adopted this point of view. (152356/15.) The real struggle over the Aden boundary will come in our negotiations with the Imam, and in this case lack of precision might be fatal. Apart from the Imam, we have to consider France, with her claims to Sheikh Said ; but we have safeguarded ourselves here by the reservation attached to the self-denying proviso in article 10 of the xAmglo-French Agreement of the 16th May, 1916. The two Powers agree “neither to acquire themselves, nor to consent to a third Power acquiring territorial possessions in the Arabian Peninsula. . . . . This, however, shall not prevent such readjustment of the Aden frontier as may be necessary in consequence of recent Turkish aggression.” We are safeguarded against Italy also by her inclusion in the provisions of the above article, under article 7 of the Italian Agreement of the 18th August. 1917. As regards our desiderata at Aden, therefore, the present treaty with the Idrisi may be regarded as reasonably satisfactory. APPENDIX. Text of Ti-eaty of April 30, 1915. This Treaty of Friendship and Goodwill is signed by Major-General D. G. L. Shaw, the Political Resident, Aden, on behalf of the British Government and by Saiyid Mustafa-bin-Saiyid Abdu’l Ali on the part of His Eminence Saiyid Muhammad-bin-Ali-bin-Muhammad-bin-Ahmed-bin-Idris the Idrisi Saiyid and Amir of Sabia and its environments. 2. Its main objects are to war against the Turks and to consolidate a pact of friendship between the British Government and the Idrisi Saiyid, above mentioned, and his tribesmen. 3. The Idrisi Saiyid agrees to attack and to endeavour to drive the Turks from their stations in the Yemen and to the best of his power to harass the Turkish troops in the direction of the Yemen and to extend his territories at the expense of the Turks. 4. The Saiyid’s prime objective will be against the Turks only, and he will abstain from any hostile or provocative action against Imam Yahya, so long as the latter does not join hands with the Turks. 5. The British Government undertakes to safeguard the Idrisi Saiyid’s territories from all attack on the sea-board from any enemy who may molest him; to guarantee his independence in his own domain, and at the conclusion of the war to use every diplomatic means in its power to adjudicate between the rival claims of the Idrisi Saiyid and the Imam Yahya or any other rival. 6. The British Government has no desire to enlarge its borders in Western Arabia, but wishes solely to see the various Arab rulers living peacefully and amicably together, each in his own sphere, and all in friendship with the British Government. 7. As a mark of its appreciation of the work to be performed by the Idrisi Saiyid, the British Government has aided him with both funds and munitions, and will continue to assist him in the prosecution of the war so long as it lasts, in accordance with the measure of the Idrisi’s activities. 8. Finally, while maintaining a strict blockade on all Turkish ports in the Red Sea, the British Government has for some months past been giving the Edrisi Saiyid full and free scope to trade and # traffic between his ports and Aden, and this concession the British Government, in token of the friendship existing, will continue uninterruptedly to maintain. 9. This treaty will be held to be valid after its ratification by the Government of India. Signed this day, Friday, the 30th April, 1915 A.D., corresponding with the 15th of Jamad Shani 1333 Hijra. D. G. L. SHAW, Major-General, Political Resident, Aden. H. F. JACOB, Lieutenant-Colonel, First Assistant Resident. C. R. BRADSHAW, Major-General, Staff Officer, Aden Brigade. Signed in vernacular, en behalf of the Idrisi Saiyid : SAIYII) MUSTAFA-BIN-SAIYID ABDU’L ALL Signed in vernacular: SHEIKH MUHAMMAD-BIN-AWAD BA SALN. HARDINGE OF PENSHURST, Viceroy ami Governor-General of India. This treaty was ratified by the Vicferoy and Governor-General of India in Council at Delhi on the 6th day of November a.d. 1915. A. H. GRANT, Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002b7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B293</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002b7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B293</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memorandum on British commitments to the Idrisi'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1917/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-03-17T18:01:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) for this description commences at f 112, and terminates at f 114, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 112-114; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of a memorandum from the Political Intelligence Department of the Foreign Office concerning British commitments to the Idrisi Saiyid and Amir of Sabia [Saiyid Muhammad-bin-Ali-al-Idrīsi]. It contains quotes from correspondence by the Political Resident at Aden, the India Office, the Viceroy of India, and the Government of India.It covers: the Anglo-Turkish Conventions of 1913 and 1914; His Majesty's Government's attitude towards the Idrisi; the establishment of relations with the Idrisi; and the terms of a treaty with the Idrisi for co-operation against the Turks in return for independence. A copy of the treaty of 30 April 1915 is included in an appendix, with a summary of the main points in the memorandum. A further section is included headed 'Relation of Commitments to the Idrisi to British Desiderata' regarding the extension of the British Trucial System to the whole of the Arabian Peninsula, and the maintenance and improvement of their position at Aden.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Idrīsī Imām of ʻAsīr</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office, Political Intelligence Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002b7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>