<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000fc_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T03:40:50.860Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">INDiU uF JALI^IIT x.^P x.U, Eeport 'by Be^idency Agent p. 6 Reports 'by Secretary after visit to Sharjah pp. 21, 52 Beport to Government of India p. 53 Report to Government of India p. 104 Eeport iDy 3_enior Naval Officer p. 110 Heport to Government of India p. 115 Political Has ident's Note for circulation at Bahrain and Hasa p. 137 Letter from Aden regarding Sxile of AMur Rahman p. ^41 Earning to Ras-ul-Khairnah p. 190 'Fresh report 'by 3enior Naval Officer p. 242 i\eduction of length of deportation of Abdur Rahman pp. 260, 263.Tr*nal*tlon of a Ko.Vg, October 1»25 from the Residency A^enct, BherReh, to the Hon'ble the Political P^nldent in the P-relan fiulf, Buehlre. /).\ With reference to n- telenjrem No.347, dated ISth in Shprgah Octob re^ardln?*: the nurder/of mj ooueln Ibrahim bin Rajab on the nth October 19P5. I have now the honour to renort on the «»vent giving rtetaile, I wae Informed on the a th October 2925 by eome Baluchle, re-ldln- In the Onan Coast, that three Baluchle of MeVran have kidnapped 7 naluch boye and pjlrle from Blyaban and have brought them to the Batlnah Coast and that they will v^ry soon reach the Oman Coast by land route to sell the kidnapped persons thers, I therefore equipped one of my eons to travel In a boat to ro for making searches for these three Baluchls from fijman to ftas-ul-KhairRh and to arrest ther- »nd those with them. Or the 11th October 192P at about TO mrgm* when the boat wae about to a tart for ^man I went out of my house ftooom^anled by my priards and two of my cousins In particular. We reached the boat which had anchored to the Sast of the Agency at a distance of ^0 paces. I ^ave my son some Ins tructions in regard to the case and as to what to do if he should come across the Baluchls an^ the Mdnapped persons any where in the Trucial Coast. The boat then left the port, and I with those in my company were standing on the shore looking at the boat starting from the ^ortj ray cousin was standinp; by me. I moved e pace to the rl^ht end my cousin stood where I was sttr.ndin^. He was shot by a bullet in his chaet on the left side from a house: he fell down. Some of the /irabs present on the s^ot went at once to Phallrh Sultan bin Saqar and reported the cvsnt to hlo. I then instructod the ^1/ards to take '-y cousin's body to our houw# where he died. At this luncture I summoned ' 1 ■ ' ' /1 -(S). sirnondd son# of H.M. iubjactn such » b Rlnaun mnrt Hydera- badle, and eone foral^nars who eaw the wound In th« raur- r jd raan's body and I to 0U&gt;&gt;!nlt herewith their teetl- rnonlea for your Infomatlon. TJ ^ 'he Irh and the Inhabitants instituted sone nlarches on the first day, but afterwards they ce«sed amarching in tha town. My oousin, the mirriered wan, was a roor person living ^aininp; his livelihood frow the cultive- tlon of v^getablas and when necessary he would serve the n;ency as r?y other c^uslnn do. In my opinion,and from what T can infer, the bullet was not fired for my oousin but for wyeelf, and iod has s«.v^d ne fron it. The reason for 5t, as I thinV, ie that aftsr the ^ r^u-ffal' (end of the diving s est son) I renewed my conversation to persuade the Phslkh, his rela tives and the inhabitants in regard to the hoistinp; of a flat^steff for fviru? on th^ top of the Agency and the promise he had p; 1 ven ar r^crted In nr latter » 9 $ dated 12th August iQPS; it is M^ely that In view of -ny persistence in this o^se they have done this serious d'eed becauee whonev^r I en^ul^e from the reorls and the Shaikhs aa to who the perpetrator is thay give ro satisfactory answer. low can a man be murdered in broad day Mflftt and they be unaware of the odlprltt It cannot be be^eved that they do not ^now the men. Seeing this dire condition, what confidence can the A^enoy have in a town wnore sVch events happen and how can the A^ent move in the Oman Coast towns? Purely hence forth all will 'transgress unon the r^enoy with the same destructive deeds. /\o Town. ■ 'js T- Telegram P. From H.M.S. 'GYGLAL/EH' , Henjamradio To Resident, Bushire. Unnumbered. * Dated 17th received 18th November 1925. I? From Horner, Shargah:- It seems likely that instigator of the crime, if not the murderer, was Abdur Rahman of HIRA — caused great excitement Ajman trouble four or five years ago and was y '' banished by Colonel Trevor (see his letter of February 7, 1924, H ip ^ n j j JB No. ) to the Residency Agent). He sheltered Sultan bin Sagar before his return a year ago and is his father-in law. Sultan brought him back and everyone fears to give evidence against him though I still hope to get some in a day or two. Do you wish me to furnish a full report and stay here until , you decide on the punishment as case is regarded seriously locally, or may 1 proceed to Charbar after a day or two and report fully on return to Bushire ? HORNER. M iu No t+o, 6/ ' ^ A '7 U3 'i U . ''&gt;7, ^ .xXs, 'f/fbi-i.^ /• 2^^ ^ ^ P.RTown. 'i Telegram From Resident, Bushire. To H.M.S. 'CYCLAMEN' , Henjamradio . No. 723. Dated 18th. November 1925. For Horner. You can proceed to Charbar. Are relations cordial 'between Agent and Shaikh ? If not warn Shaikh that he will 'be personally responsible if another attempt is made. RESIDENT.Town. Telegram P. ^rom H. LIS. 'Cyclamen' , Hen jam Radio a To Resident, Bushire. Unnumbered. . Dated 20th received 21st November 1925. Following from Horner, H.M.S. 'CYCLAMEN' \ c ^ Your telegram of November 19th. Have left Shargah. Relations cordial, but Shaikh warned. Abdul Razzak bringing details by next slow mail. I hope to catch the one after and will simplify them. 1%REPORT ON THE SHARGhB MURDER GaSE. iiiter 1 had laodecj about 2 p.m. on the 13th November, shaikh Sultan bin Sa^ar came to the Residency Agent's house to call on me. 1 pointed out to him how strange it was that a murder could take place in shargah by daylight and that no trace could be found of the murderer, and warned him that I would wait a few days , but that I expected him to produce the culprit. He was alarmed evidently at my arrival , and had sent for the Shaikh of Debai to come over and get him out of his scrape . 1 then learnt from the Residency Agent that Abdur Rahman, of Hira, was supposed to be the culprit, and that this was general gossip all along the Coast. Also it appeared that there was no doubt that the bullet was meant lor Isa . . Apparently Abdur Rahman has a grudge against isa since Colonel Trevor banish ed him in Februaiy 1924, and now the young Shaikh, who had previously to his return sheltered with him and had married his daughter, had brought hiEojback to Shargah and put him in charge of some of the administration. He was therefore a power in the land and no one dared %o accuse him openly or to give evidence against him. After my return visit to Shaikh Sultan , however, Majid, his brother, came to see Isa and in a very veiled manner spoke of the culprit in such a way that it seemed obvious who he meant, though he would not name him, and it seemed as though Shaikh Sultan had sent him to spy out the land further. 1 was lurther told that one day after the occurrence shaikh sultan had called over Shaikh Said bin Maki&gt;um from Debai , realising the seriousness of the affair, and had asked his help. In their presence■ - I - - • • r - ■i - ^ .- 2 - 0 presence a meJlis was held, and all but Abdur Rahman took an oath that they Knew nothing about the criminal or who had done the crime . He apparently abstained , bat later went to the Residency Agent and took an oath in front of him, but in such a manner that it would not be recognised by Muhammadans as an oath, i-.e ', by changing the words used. Alter this one day I am told that shaikh Sultan has taken no further steps to detect the criminal , the conclusion being that he &gt;&lt;nows it is his father-in-law, or one of bis men. In this connection I am told by the Residency Agent that he can produce a woman who will state that she saw a certain manumitted slave near the place of occurrence on that day and that he had a gmn. This man is said to be connected with Abdur Rahman. The next day Sfraikh Said arrived , and after an interview with shaikh Sultan came to see me, and to confer as to a solution. 1 spoke plainly with him, and he confirmed the facts tbat are given above re the ma j lis on the day after the occurrence. He appreciated the gravity of the situation , and went back to see what he could do with shaikh Sultan. In the ei^hing he returned and said the latter would , or could, not produce the criminal but he would take the conse uences and obey any order of Q-overn- ment that they choose to pass fine , as it had happened in his limits. 1 professed my incredulity that they could not produce the criminal, when shargah was such a small place and the occurrence was in day— light, andfehaikh Said agreed , and said he would con- M * vene a Shargah me j lis the next day and see what he could do . • This- 3 - 0 V3 This day 1 also received the Bamias and Hyderabadis . They all obviously knew about the criminal but were afraid to say so — all except a Hyderabadi of Debai who was there by chance and who was not afraid to speaJi, an.d named Abdur Rahman at once . I explained to them that , as British Indian subjects , it was tda their duty to help Government and its representa tive in shargah and to disclose all they knew of the occurrence , as all that was lacKing was definite proof, and that no doubt one or other of them could show where this was to be got , and that arrangements could obviously be made for them to meet secretly either Yusuf Kanoo or Abdur Raza^ for that purpose . Though the two latter have tried to work tnis up nothing has transpired , and both think no evidence will be forthcoming in shargah, and for this reason I sent Yusuf Kanoo to Debai on the next day to see what he can do there. The result of the mejlis was simply to send for Ahdur Rahman and apparentlyjto tell him that they did not see why they should suffer for him, and he as shaikh Said told me then said that he was at the disposal of Government to \ be fined or imprisoned as necessary , but he would not admit his guilt. The Residency Ag® n t told me that evening \17th ) in conversation that if 1 went $$ away leaving the case to be settled later by the , Political Resident he would request that Abdur Rahman be temporarily deported to Ras al Khaimah where shaikh sultan bin Salim would be responsible for his behaviour, otherwise he (the(fi) ^'the Residency ) would notr stay in ghargah , but would go under pretext of G-ovemment work to Debai , as he fBared another attack- I suggested deporting him to Debai , ii shaikh Said bin Moktum would be responsible, as 1 thought this rather simpler) However on consulting shaikh Said , he jibbed a little but ended by persuading Mubammad bin Salim , of Ras al Khaimah, to accept the responsibility on his brother's behalf. This was finally settled, Shaikh Sultan bin Sa jar warned of his responsibility *, if a further attempt was made on the Residency Agsnt, and told he would avoid worse consequences if he pro duced the evidence to show who the cujiprit was in the next; two weeks . Yusuf Kanoo and ^bdur Razai will have one day in which to seek for fubther clues after Ahdur Rahman goes until the mail leaves , and the Residency Agent two weeks more to get his evidence and follow up the clue of the manumitted slave. SD/ B • Su^art Horner hargah, } 19th November 1925-;at (is) R.I.M.S. 'Lawromce^. Dated G bar rah, 20 th Noven.'her 19?5. 3rd Janadl I, 174^. To ShalVh Sultan bin Sallr, Chl®f of ^as-ul-Khaimh. A .C. T have to Irforir you that I vlsltad Shareah 1r or'dor to ra v 9 Investluatlor in the Incident Trhlch occurred to K.B. Tsa the Residency Arent at Sharflah and which you &gt;now. After ry arrival at F-harrah I found out froTn the prevailing rumours that the crlwe Is attributed to Abdur Rahran bin Muhammad of Hlrah. On referring the tratter to the Hon'ble the Political Resident at Bushlre it was decided that the snid Abdur Rahman should be sent to Has-ul-Khaimah and be Vent in your safe custody for a period of four weeVs until T arrive at Bushlre and ret orders from the Government on this case, ^n the other hand, while ho (Abdur Rahnan) Is absent from this town, Shaikh Sultan bin Saqar, will endeavour in his searches and ho may be able to ret hold of the actual culnrit; v T am s^ndinr, therefore, the said Abdur Rahman In company with your brother, Sha^Vh Muhammad bin Salim, to Ras -ul-Khaimah ftnd t^ust that o^ his a^r^val there you will \reeT) him under dose custody so that he may not be able to abscond to any where and you will be held resno^slble by the ^l&lt;?h Government. You should Iceen him under custody till the receipt of orders from the Hirh Government on arrest of the culpnlt. I am sonry that ow^nr to lacV of time t could not come un to see you. I thanlr you for your assistance to the Government In keep^nr the man In custody till the receipt of orders from the Govenrment about him. Sd. B. S. Horner. Cantaln, Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. S, J afriJjuu fib vL t* ZLcuMA uyj^aXZ^. -rf,,No. ZUtlv of 1925. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, fcth December 1925. From The Hon'ble Lieut-Col. F. B. Prideaux, G.S.I.^ C.I.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To She Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. Attempt to murder the Residency .Agent, Shaggah. Sir. 0- ' I have the honour to refer to my telegram Ko. 707, dated the 10th November 1925, in which I reported that an attempt had been made by an unknown person against the life of i.han iniiliadur Isa bin Abdul Ijatif, the T esidency Agent at Shargah, and that the latter^ cousin, Ibrahim bin Rajab, had been killed in his stead. 2. I now forward a translation of the Residency Agent's letter No. 362, dated the 22nd October 1925, describing the Incident. 3. Secretary, Captain Horner, proceeded to Shargah on the 12th November, with Khan Bahadur Abdur Rezzaq from Bushire and Khan Bahadur Yusuf Kanu from Bahrain as special atssistants, to investigate the affair and to press the young Shaiich of hargah to discover and deal suitably with the perpetrators of the outrage. 4. As will be seen from the enclosed copy of Captain Horner's report — he returned to Bushire on the 30th November — suspicion is universally directed against Shaikh Abdur Tahman of Haireh, the young Chief's father-in law. his man. under Captain Horner^ orders,has been taken to Ras al Khaima andand placed in charge of the Chief of that place. It is hoped that in his absence from Shargah some tangible clues to the Identity of the Murderer be forthcoming. t, I will address you further on this matter in due course. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lieut-Col. Political Pesident in the Persian Gulf.V Report on the murder of the cousin of the Pesidency Agent, Shargah. On arrival at Shargah I discovered that the whole Trucial Coast was discussing the attempt to murder the Residency Agent, Shargah, and awaiting my arrival to see what steps Government would take in the matter. I learnt that everyone attributed the instigation, if not the firing of the shot to Abdur Rahman, headman of Hairah, the father-in-law of Shaikh Sultan 'bin Saqar of Shargah, who had sheltered the latter 'before he 'became Shaikh a year ago. The man had been concerned in the Ajman disturbances of four or five years ago, and had later (in February 1924) been banished by Colonel revor for inurigu- -ing against Shaikh Ahalid, the then Shaikh of Shargah. I discovered that he had returned to ^-hargah on Shaikh Khalid's deposition, and had been antagonistic to the Residency Agent ever since, regarding him as the cause of his banishment. I could get no evidence in thiss case, and only one man, a Hyderabadi of Debai, would say openly that Abdur Rahman was the culprit. Shaikh Sultan called on me at once on my arrival and I expatiated on the strangeness of the facts that an attempt on the British representative^ life ending in the murder of another person could take place in boroad daylight in Shargah, that he had apparently only conducted invest- -igatione into the crime for 24 hours and that he had then discontinued all effort to trace the criminal. He was much alarmed and sent for the ShaiKh of Debai to help him get out of his difficulty. In the meanwhile, 1 was attempting to get evic.- ice and waiting for the effect of my words to be visible inin a change of attitude in the young Shaikh. I could however only draw inferences from the few pieces of inform- -ation I picked up, and they all led me to conclude that Abdur Rahman was guilty. Shaikh Said bin Maktum of Debai then came to see me, and told me that Shaikh Sultan realised his position and was prepared to accept any punishment given but he could not, or would not, produce the criminal. He added that Abdur Hahaan, though protesting his innocence, would also be prepared to take any punishment given. I then decided to deport Abdur Rahman pending a decision in the case, and leave the Residency Agent with two weeks to try and get evidence of the Identity of the criminal, with Abdur Rahman out of the way, and I hopef with everyonemouths a little opened thereby. Sd/- B. STUART HORHER.From- The ReeMercy Af?ont, ShPr^h To - Tho Hon* Mo tho ^ontl.cal ^ooMert, p orelar Gulf^PusMre ^0.4?? da tod ?^d Deoo^'hor 1^95, A.C. T bavo the honour to stato ^or your Irformatlon that on the 13th ultimo T was at Dehal for settling the claims of tf.M'a Guh .lecta a^d on the 15th ider^ H.y.S. ^Lawrence 1 ' massed Doha! on her way to Sharpah. I therefore lof^ at once / for Sharrah and there T found the 'Cyclamen' srd met Captain 13. S. Korner Your / Honour's Secretary and those with him on boa^d the man-of-vrfr. Fe Informed me that he r?ll 7ard at Sharpah. Te all landed and went to the Agency. After hevifig rested a while the Secretary desired to have an Interview with Shaikh Sultan bin Saqar. The Shaikh called on him and he (the SecreMr-y) asked the Shaikh whether he bas ^^ested the n^rderer of my cousin. The Shaikh answered that he has exerted himself in this case but that he has not, as yet, been able to arrest anyone. The Secretary told him the failure was due to his no^ having riven proper attention to this case and that lie ia responsible for the case because he is the Chief'of Shargah. The Shaikh, however, stated that he ka not left ^.ny stone unturned In instituting searches and enquiries and he hopes to find the murdorer. The Secretary thanked him for this and he then called on ^9 wC. 4* ' ^bai ^h onnar to t-^11 ^4m a'!Ivyu, I accompanied him. ^n the l^th Fovember the Secretary enquired British subjects IS such as the Bunrias and Hyderabadis at Shar^ah about the rumours they have heard, retra^ding Abdur Habman bin Muhammad in order that he should knor; aare. The aane day the Shaikh of Debai arrived at Shargah and called on the Secretary and conversation was nade in re^ar»d to what has been a^ran^ed between him and Shaikh s ultan bin Saqar and what was rumoured against Abdur Rahman bin i'uhamr.Ad. The Secretary In^o^ned Shaikh SMd J-in Yaktum that Abdur Rahman will ^o to Ras-ul-Khaimah. to remain there for 4 weeksaperbars during this De^iod rumours s-ld against Abdur Rahman shall be proved, '^r view of this the Secretary wrote his letter dated 19th Novembe; 1^95 to s ha^kh Sultan bir» C v * of of ^as-ul-iChalmah, inform- i ng fiiip. 3^ informing him of tha despatch of AMur Rahnisin to Ttoa-ul-Khalm-th •rd him to plao® tha man urder hi a own supervision ^or a period until Honour'a visit. Shaikh Sultan bin r^qar Tras to inat 1 tute Searches for the perpetrator*1^0 M aa yvJuxAA^^^, The Secretary left Sharesh in the'Cyclamen*on the POth November ly^5 and Abdur Hahman, the Secretary's letter and Shaikh Said bin Ma^tum'a men went to Kaa-ul-?:haimah. on the Plat Idem. After departure from hei-e of Abdur Rahman Shaikh Sultan and Abdur Rahman* 0 relatives besran aearchea for the culnrlt. The i ^ur^ou^s •cr+iirQf Abdur Rahman are rot aa yet proved. T trust God w^ll help us In th^ovrlnp 11 fht unon the c^minalj whifteve*^ that may trararilre later same shall be reported to you. / for tu&gt; '^TrvusO^UflAJ I (j$.4.. ij'rom TO NO.278-N^ i^e Deputy Secretary to the uiovernment of India in tiia ^'oreign and Political Department^ RE ® 75 % AX' RECEIVED O,. Aiie Homble tiie Political riesidant -'2,/j in the Persian uulf. • ' 1 ; ' ~ &gt;s;an ,,.r * h- Dated Delhi, the ''/ December 1925. r Attempt to murder tne itesidenoy iigent Siiargaii. Sir, ( ■'' 0 I am directed to acknowledge receipt of your letter 1^0.2420, dated 5tJi DecemDer and to say that the government of India will be glad to receive a further report on this case as soon as you are in a position to furnish one. i have the honour to be, Sir, Your most oaedient servant. Deputy Secretary to the liovernment of India, Ni* 1 I fyyicNo. ft $ of lo?6, British Fasidency aad Consulatt General Bushir®, 23rd January 192b« Froii Tii« Hon'bl# th« Political P«8id«nt in th» Persimm. Gulf To Th® foreign Secr«tary to th® GoT®rn*i®nt of India My letter No, 258^&gt; dated the ^nd January I9S6. I visited Shargah on the ISth January and Pas al Shaiaah on the 18th January« / Th« so* of th« Residency Agent,Shargah, had not returned fro* Barai*! before T left the Trucial Coast. T aE deferring my report until I hear from Khan idhadur Isa the result of his son's inyestigations. in tn® Foreign and Political Departiient D K L H U Memorandun Lis ^ Political Resident in the Par Lieut-Colonel sian GulfH u iu ■'■ n ■ v hS** y. p ^ i - ABDUR RAHMAN BIN MUHAMMAD, of {33) Hairah, a village in the Principality of Shargah, has caused trouble in the Trucial Coast since 1920. In June of that year, claiming that it had been the property of his forefathers, he seized the fort of AJman in defiance of the Shaikhs of Ajrnan and Shargah . The Residency Agent mediated and persuaded hira to evacuate the fort under a safe-conduct. 'Tie Shaikh of Shargah^ prohibited Abdur Rahman from living at Hairah. He was indebted to the extent of over 2s. 20,000/- to British subjects and the only hope of recovering this money was to permit hira to ply his business of pearling. He first went to Bahrain but could not iaake a liveli- -fciood there and so returned to Hairah. The Shaikhs of Shargah and Ajman, who object- -ed to his return, took up arras against hira in January 1921. However, Capt. Pearson, S.N.O. 'H .Ii. S. 'TRIAD' , succeeded in making peace between Abdur Rahman and the Shaikh of Shargah (the Shaikh of Ajman remaining obdur- -ate), it being agreed that Abdur Rahman should live at Sharga^ for a month under the surveillance of the Shaikh and then return to Hairah to carry on his business without molestation. In March 1923, Sultan, son of Saqar bin Khali'd bin Sultan, Shaikh of Shargah the Shaikh, Ehalid bin Ahmed, married a daughter of Abdur Rahman. This aroused the suspicions of Shaikh Khalid, who placed a few watchmen on the towers of Hairah. Abdur2 AbcLur Rahman expelled these and took possess- -ion of the towers. Shaikh Khalid did not feel strong enough to dislodge him and asked the 'Residency Agent to mediate. In Sept- -ember 1923 an. agreement was concluded by which both sides agreed to desist from molest- -ing or intriguing against each other. In December 1923 Colonel Trevor warned Abdur Rahman to obey the Shaikh of Shargah and desist from intrigues. But shortly after, he Joined the villagers of Hairah in deposing and imprisoning Shaikh Khalid^ Amir in the village. The Residency Agent averted serious fighting by patching up peace between the villagers and the Shaikh and ordering Abdur Rahman to leave Hairah, which he did, joining his son-in-law at Debai. On learing of thfcse happenings Colonel Trevor intimated his approval of the Residency'Agent f s action and stated that if Abdur Rahman appeared anywhere within Shaikh Ehalid's territory it seemed necessary that he should be apprehended and imprisoned or banished to Muscat or some other place far away from the scene of his intrigues. In November 1924 Abdur Rahman active -ly assisted his son-in-law in the successful •. coup d 1 e tat which won for the latter the Principality of Shargah, thus acquiring con- -siderable influence in the Principality. cfcS-'- * Swo# 6 Dated a:th January rroia. ihe neaidency Agont. anargah^ xo xhe nonuurabx© the roxltlcax ^teeident. oushire# A**C» p With reference tw my xeuter no ^7i % date&lt; ^gth ijeceaber IViffi cunceming tiae expedition of ^y eon to J3ralmi» i nave tne honour tu inform you that uiy son hae retumei from x^ralxul on the s-ra ^anuary ne has instituted enquir^isat aralni and has heart dirferent guseipe about the murder► Some attribute tae muraer bo the Intrigues of the ex Shaikh^ and sume say that it has been done at the instigation of Ahdur xvahman bin muhaiumat*. curing his staf in cralmi my son has tried to obtain proofs to estaoxlsh one of the above rumours and has been unable to obtain any fact to bear out one of the two*. I fUi ther beg to state that. If xour non^ur wixi agree / wi&amp;L the request made by the ShaiKhjof i»«bai and rvas-ux- ahaimah and the notables of ohargah in tneir iette^ dated 9t)L *•.xj.»r &gt;^/5 35^ sent to you under ^y xetter wa dated Jvtn December may be met by you* in my poor opinion the xetter will seive the purposes of an unaertaKing by them and whenever the murderer is found out. the Shaikhs irlil arrest m* ana surrender him^ jueciexon rests with yuur upiniunv (o.Z.Zlo. s ckoiilfx ^•'3. Ko. of 1926. Brltleh Hceldency and ConBulate-Oeneral, uehire, 13th February 1926. ^rom he Hon'ble Ueut-Col. ?. B. 'rldeau*, C.S.I.. C.I.T.., Political Besident In the Por&amp;lan Oxaf. The Foreign ecretary to the Oovemwent of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. m Sir, Attempt to murder the liesidoncy Agent, ^hargah. A ^ / 7 1 have ;,he honour to refer to correax &gt;() ^dence ending with my Memorandum Ko. 113, dated the Jtord January 1926, in which 1 reported that the oon of the He&amp;idenqy Agent, Shargah, who had been sent to Baraimi in pursuit of a clue as to the murderer of Ibrahim bin ajab, his cousin, had not yet re tum ped from that place. 2. he young man has since returned and reportea that he failed to obtain tangible evidence. kany of the people cl i araimi say that Abdur T-ahman bin kuhamraad of Haireh » instigated the crime. others suggest that it was the work oi the £2i~ haiJxh. of fihargah, Khalid bin Ahmad, who was deposed in liovember 1924 and is now living at Uram el tyiiwain. ne j | | eeldenoy Agent undoubtedly has other enemies, mostly made in the execution of his official duties in connection with the claims of British subjects against Arabs and Persians, and cases of gun-running, slavery and kidnapping. His half- •brother, whose paternity he has impugned, is also a private enemy. But no serious accusation is preferred against any such iicreomj in connection with the outrage under consideratioz■ • *5. «hen i visitea lebai last month I waa infomect that a letter signed by the Ihaikhe of Debai and Has aJL iQiaiiauh, as well as by the ' haikh and notables of I hargah, lia^been despatched through the Agency to me which had crossed me on the sea. ranslations of this letter and of that written by the 1 esidency Agent, giving cover to it, are now enclosed. 1 gathered on toy tour that other Shaikhs had also been acked to sign the letter but those who were hostile to Abdur ahman of Haireh would not do so. he rhai.&lt;h of Abu Dhabi apparently w s not asked. 4. he substance of this letter is contained in the following points (1). he murder of Ibrahim and the attempted murder of Khan Bahadur Isa are admitted. (2). The liability for rendering satisfaction to R.M's. Government and the family of the murdered man are accepted by the Shaikh and the townsfolk of hargah. (3). he grounds for suspecting Abdur Kahman, in view of his past history and his privileged and preponderating position at ^hargah, are considerable (4). Abdur Pahman's exclusion from ; hargah territory which included his home at Haireh, is desirable for a year at least (fa) Let the Shaikh of ^hargah be given a year in which to discover the guilty persons ! t&gt;. he Residency Agent's attitude may be summarized in the following sentences which he at various times expressed % to me. Personally I do not know whom to suspect. I a told on all sides by my friends that Abdur 1 ahman i the culprit. But years ago 1 befriended him, . perha kperhapa even saved hie life, and though recently he ma, have dieliiccd some of the aAvi.ce which 1 have r ivt,n ^he young : halkh, 1 am reluctant to believe ohat he wished to take my life. l f I puroue a blood-feud agbinet the tatiier-in-la\i/ of the Shaikh* even if hie guilt is iiovec-, B^y po ition in Chargah becoraee very difficult ao not wiDh to l0Be ay offlolal position, wtoloh I would If the Govermnent sent In my British BDlitlcRl Officer. The '.■rucial Chiefs all recot- -nl.^e the possibility of this move and consequently they wish to give ree satisfaction.' 6&gt; I have visitea the scene of the outrage and heard all the available details. he town of :harpah mainJy conPists utiaggllnt: line of houses built on a curving beach. Scores of pearling dhows were drawn up at intervals just above l.igh -.vale j mark. Between the dhews; and :the fronfwaHo of the serai-likeMiouses — many single-storied, but some having an upiw story^is the main road of the town. he Jum Pahacur's party were standing in the chade of the stern of a big dhow on the sea-side edge of the road. The shot was ilred from the upper story of a house about 150 yflqids away, 'hi' house had been the property of the e^-ihaikh and had been confiscated by his successor. Mo one was permanently resid- -in. in it; but built into its front wall on the ground floor, wui, a single roomed shop rented by a : uQni Persian (Fwaei). This 'ersian disappeared a few days after the outrage. Before going he showed a bag of rupees to a friend and said that he waji returning to hie home in rerwia. The upper ntory, from which the ehot was undoubtedly xired, has been pulled down by the Shaikh's orders since the occurrence. ojjenspace — about 30 yards by 30 yards, on a rough estimate — adjoining the .haikh's house and over the front eage of which the bullet may have passed; has been rapidlyrapidly built upon and three shops have been construeted on its front side. All these points suggest a savage's guilty con- •science and. an attempt on the part of the local authorities at Chargah to diminish the chances of guilt being brought hoiztfto some one whom they wish to protect. 7. The recent history of Abdur Pahman bin Muhammad is too long to give in a paragraph or two. I therefore append a separate note about him. It will be seen that he is one of the stormy petrels of the Persian Gulf and that he has more than once^my predecessor's injunction to live a quiet life and confine his attentions to the pearl trade. lie is a pretender to the Chiefship of Ajnan though he is not persona grate with either the Kalm Shaikh of Baraimi, his kinsman, nor with the Pultan of Wejd. In the days of the ey-Shaikh of Shargahj who was a friend of the Shaikh of Ajman, he was difficult to control. How that he has the young ihaiich of Shargah behind him it is not likely that he will refrain from troubling AJman. On my recent visit to Has el Khaimah I saw Kuhammad i the oAd father of Abdur Rahman, and told him that I very seriously blamed his son at least for not bringing the murderei to book. He was undoubtedly more in the position of iazir to his 'Son -in-law than anyone else and his apathy or incompet- -ence had been remarkable. . 'he conclusion I drew was most unfavourable to him. /( 8. The question now is .ftiat reply should be given to the Shaikh's letter of December Sfcth, and what penalties should be imposed on the Chief of Shargah 7 I am not in favour of accepting the proposal which 1 indicated in paragraph 4 suura as ^&gt;int No. b. In a yearN time the Arabs will probably find some culprit of death whom they will put forward as the murderer and offer to execu^ 1SI® It is certain that they are prepared to give the family of Ibrahin bin Pajab the ueual blood-money, 600 X£aria Vhereea dollars, and to pay a fine in addition of eay Ks. 3,000 as atonement for the in&amp;ult offered to Government• But the untatiafactory part of this settlement will be that shall have no guarantee against a repetition of the outrage, and that Abdur Rahman will go practically un- -punished. o have to live in Bebai, 10 miles from his home, or in T^as el Ahaimah, amongst his son-in-law*8 relatives will be of little hardship. 9. I am inclined to recommend that in addition to thbse money payments the Bhaikh of Hhargah should be called upon to e&gt;ile his father-in-law for a term of five years to i ^arachi and to maintain him while there. In 1905, the Chief of Bahrain was compelled to concur in the deportation of shaikh Ali bin Ahmad to Bombay for five years. hen, the offender was allowed to return in about two years; but in the present case 1 think it is desirable to remove the young Shaikh from Abdur nahman 9 s influence for a considerably longer period. If it is found that Shaikh Sultan bin Baqar refuses to sign the order or that Abdur fahman disobeys it, a possible way of reducing the two men to subjection may be found in the transfer of Haireh village to the Ajman ftodcjcfc Chief ship and the public denouncement of Abdur Kahman as an outlaw. 10. At this stage it is not necessary for me to ask the Government of India to consider the desirability of deputing a British officer to Thargah for a temporary period at least. If the attempt on the Residency Agent's life had succeeded. I think such action would have been very neceseary. A precedent for a deputation can be found in the case of Bahrain, whither Captain K, L. Durand, First Assistant to the olitical Feeiaent was sent for si&gt; months in 11. By the last post I have received a report from the Residency Agent that the r.ahhabi Governor of Hasa has commenced to encroach on the sovereign rights of the Trucial Chiefs by i 'i . 16 3 ■—v&gt; Bending a t&gt;08Be of police to ^har^ah, AJxaan and Has el flhaiisah HS99 in pursuit of a man who Ic wanted for murder committed in Kejd w A Also mention is made of an increase of elave traffic indulged in by Kajdi slave dealers, whom the Chiefs are afraid to tackle. 1 am calling for further details about this. It is possible that the authority of the Petiidency Agent will not be strong enough to compete much longer with the inoreas* -ing influence and prestige of Hajd. J In such case, I think the political position will call for serious consideration../ A copy of this ciotterr is 'being sent to H.M's. Secy, of State for the Co^ry^. ^ to be&gt; Sir, Your moot obedient servant. Lieut-Col., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. p ■ v■ ior a period of gam year from Uie date tUolr letter, ahaXX «ot fee allowed to reimln ixi HalreH or on account of viie auss^icion against him| he ohauld remain at i\as«uX« Jmijoaa or Dubai* 1 te^ to auoiait that the murder hae u reatl^ reduced uy prestige oeoauae it in a bi^ orime# and such a miafortune had never occurred in the time of predeceftoore. ihe question of your a^reein^ to uheir retiueet or oUierwise reote with you.NCT RKGAFDIHG SHAIKH mm RAHMAH BIK UUEM&amp;IAJ), K ADMAN OF HAIHTH, IH THE SHAROAH CHI' '/SHI' 5 , Shaikh Abelur tiaimsai 1&amp; the &amp;on of ]^uhaxnmad bin Abdur ahman, an old man who has reoigned hi a i/oaition to hie son. ' he family belong to the dl bu Shanis seotion of the Hatml (Bedouin) tribe, to whioh also belong the Crucial Chief of AJman and the ^aimi Shaikh (Pultan bin iluhammad al iuoimci) of y* Bataimi oasis, half of which is owned by this tribe. In June 1920 Shaikh Abdur P^iriiaan suddenly inarched with a following into Ajman town and seized the fort, claiming that he had a better ri(;ht to it than the ruling chief. he Shaikh of F'hargah sided with the Shaikh of Ajman. Abdur I ahman was besieged for six days in the fort. -he Residency Agent then intervened and got the two Shaikhs to give Abdur Pahman kjh a safe-conduct to the Agency in Bharga^i on condition that he and his men took nothing away with then of the articles they had looted. After four days at the Agency Abdur Fahman was sent off to I as el Khaimah and thence he proceeded to Bahrain. lie i aimi 1 haikh of ^araimi, as* soon as he hearci of the trouble, marched down to the Coast and from AJman wrote to Colonel Trevor in July that he had come to assist the Chief of Ajman 'because in olden times AJmun was considered a part of Baraimi.* 'haikh Abdur Pahman returned to Haireh in December 1920. 'he Shaikhs of Ajman wnd Thargah then beseiged Abdur Rahman in Haireh. 'he residency Agent represented to the Resident that Abdur Pahman was a pearl dealer and that he owed British subjects £s. 20,000. He had found it impossible to do business in Bahrain. His return to his home seemed desirable. 'he T esiaent accepted this view and sent a warningwarning to lead a quiet life and attend to his bueinees. he .%nior ^aval Officer, ^ersian Oulf, proceeded to ^hargah and effected a compromlBe between the Chief of that place and Abdur Pahman, under which it was arranged that Abdur Rahman should admit himeelf to be a subject of Bhargah and ehould reside for one month in Shargah. After that he could return to his village, Hajreh. The Chief of Ajmar dis- -approved this agreement and would not countenance it. He even caused a letter to be written by his townspeople to the Tultan of Kajd and the Political Agent, Bahrain, protesting against the outrage committed by /Vbdur Pahman against /Jman. objecting to his return to haireh and incidentally complaining against the Residency Agent. Colonel Vrevor at this Juiicture had occasion to be ^(X - aiepleased with the hailch of AJman on other accounts. iter was told inter alia, to leave Abdur Rahman alone at Kaireh. In 1923 the young claimant to the ^hargah Chiefship, Buitan bin Saqar, who had previously taken refuge with the Chief of Debai # married a daughter of Ghaikli Abdur Baliman of Jialreh. Shaikh Khalid of Bhargali seized the watch towers of Haireh but his men were soon afterwards ejected. he Residency Agent was alked to intervene, and in September 1923 both parties signed an undertaking not to molest or outrcfec against each other. in December 1923 Colonel Trevor sent a warning to Abdur Tahroan zo obey his Chief and to refrain from intrigues, afterwards oon ttftrx the people of Haireh arrested Shaikh Khalid^ 'Amir 1 ' (police officer). Abdur nahman was then persuaded by the Kesidency A^rent to leave Haireh and go to Bebai, where his son-in-law still lived. Colonel Trevor approved the Jian Bahadur^ action and expressed the opinion to him that if Abdur Rahman appeared again in Shargah territory the Chief should arrest and imprison him or banish him to I^uscat or some other distant place. In.5b Ho. 4 of 1926. British Pesidency and Conoulate -General # BushIre, 13th February 1926. Sir, I have the honour to forward for the information of Hie Majesty'e Government a copy of the correspondence mentioned in the attached schedule regarding an attempt on the life of the Pesidencjr Agent, f&gt;hargah. I have the honour to be, Kir, Your most obedient servant. Lieut-Col., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* H. M'e, Secretary of State for the Colonies, Colonial Office, Downing Street, LONBOH S.W. X.14/197. Telegram P. t/ 7roin Government of India, Simla. '3 Resident, Eushire. No. 682-S. Dated ISth received 13th April 1926. Your despatch Eo. 229 of February 13. Presume you are satisfied that Shaikh can a ■ ■ c 0 n) aintain ABDIJP I AHILAIT while in e^ile. On general grounds Government of India would prefer if he were detained outsiae India. Dould you suggest suitable place ? If Shaikh fails to comply would it not suffice to exact larger fine ? Government of India deprecate any territorial re-adjustment such as proposed transfer of HAIREH to AJI r AN as -i-ikely uo lead to prolonged troubles on the Crucial Coast. FOREIGN.Town 14/^97. 11 Telegram R. From To No. 279. Dated 20th April 1926. Resident, Bushire. Government of India, Simla &gt; 7 *. ■ O. &amp;&amp;2~S, of A^ri Your telegram Ho. 6^2-S, of April 12th.' Shaikh uan afford. Aden would be most suitable if objection as regards In^ia does not apply. Political deportees from Iraq were sent to henjam oliree years ago. Could Baghdad be asked to oblige us now.? For the moment I believe that Abdur Rahman can # be sent to Mecca on pilgrimage pending a decision as to his place oi exile. I expect a reply from Residency Agent about this shortly. RLjSIDUFT.lV^7- n 0 From. Gort of India, To. Reeident, 1DSV. Rcpt. Resident, Bushire. No. 76G-S, Dated. t6th reed tftiL April If£6. The Gort of India wish to deport SHIItH ABDUR RAHMAN, father-in-law of the present Sheikk of Shargah i* the Persian Gulf, and would like to intern him in Aden. Do you tee any objection T F0R1IGN. ■'' ! n j CC hn- ■IK \ ' ,.\Vr ' • v • I* 1 #va x -- v if From. Resident, Aden, Tel.P. To. Gort of India. Rept. Bushire. No» KK 9 Dated 1st reed 2nd May 1926. — Tour .telegram N0 .76O -S. No objeetion to the Sheikh being deported here prorided he has means to support himself. RESIDINT. Tel.P. From. Resident, Bushire. To. Govt of India. No. 196. Dated.3rd May 1926. My telegram No.279 of April 20th,^last para. Residency Agent agrees that pilgrimage is the easiest way of getting offender out of Oman. R1SIDXNT. H PP.14/197 — Yov/n (62 7f ^ Telegram -' n . From Resident, Bushlre. To H.H.S. 'TRIAD' (S. II. 0.). No. 299. ' Dated 3rd Hay 1926. I exj/ect the orders of the Government of India about deportation of the father-in-law of the Shaikh of Sharoh in a few days. Will a ship be available to visit that coast soon ? '^he Residency Agent is in BusMre now. RESIDENT.own . ,4/197 ID Government of India. Resident, Bushire. Telegram j?rom To No. 826-S. Dated 5th received 6th Hay 1926. i, n Your telegram llo. 296. Are you satisfied that departure on pilgrimage will 'be sufficient or do you propose his subsequent deportat- -ion to Aden.? Also,once in Hejaz he may be difficult to get under control again. FCREIG1I. Telegram From P. Resident, Buehire. Government of India, Simla. 1 ( I Ho. 305. Dated 6th May 1926; f Your telegram Ho.• 8^6-3 of i.lay 5th. I strongly think that the' man should be removed from Arab Coast of Persian Gulf for at least four vear s. I will I try to make him report himself in Aden but he cannot do much harm in Hejaz especially if his maintenance money is paid through us. 'his may be taken out of royalty for oxide 1 1 1 : n ^ ilfl i u i concession which Messrs. Strick pay to Shaikh of Shargah through * J me. RESIDENT.'own (14/197) Telegram R From The Governmentof India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. To H .M. Political Resident, Bushire. Ho. 861-S. Dated 11th received IP.th Mav 1926. 'dfit.f-rl Ma.v Your telegram No. 305, 'dated May 6. Question of Abdur Rahman?s e^ile referred for orders of Kis Majesty's C ©vernment. Meanwhile Governmentof India would be glad to know if the Shaikh is ac^eeable or will not resent your utilizing royalty on oxide concession in manner proposed, and whether amount is considered adequate for mainten^ ance allowance. FORE I GIT * ^ i-l &lt; ■ ■Telegram R. 1,11 a I • ^i. ' s . Political l^esident, Busii ire . ?0 Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. No. 326. Dated 15th Hay 1926. y.OMT telegram of 11th May, No. 861~S. ohaikh of Shargah will not object to payment of blood money nor to fine of Rs. 3000. Further I cio not doubt that he v.'ij-l subrni i o order about his fatherrin-law t s exile. C ol !, of latter' s maintenance at Aden may be T :s. 150 or Rs. 200 per nensem . Shaikh' p income from various sources is estimated to l '' * ^0,000 2eT_ annum. He can easily contribute Ss. 2500 ' - .a'ce and he will readily recognize the convenience o. y using the oxide royalty, annual minimum of which is Re. 2000. T 'voulci certainly prefer that Abdur Rahman resides in Aden 'nan in Kejaz and it may perhaps be considered oesirable to exercise pressure by insisting on the pa^/ment of maintenance money to the Residency which we will keep in deposit until the man reports himself at Aden. Ii he goes to I'ecca I can arrange to have all the facts about him communicated to Ibn Saud. - RSSIDSTTT.Telegram Prom To Ho. Code » Resident Busiiire, Senior Naval Officer, 'Triad', Henjam, 348, Dated the 28th May i926# li 11 No report yet received about pilgrimage proposal from Agent Siiargah nor commiAnicaption from Government of India. RESIDENT M.Y/. A. Your 305 and 326. H.M.G. agree to Abdur Rahman being exiled as proposed Please take action accordingly. FOREIGN. * Telegram P. From Government of India, To H.l/Ps Political Resident, Bushire. No. 1023/S Dated the 7th and received the 8th June 1926.— —s ■ Translation of a telegram No, 194, dated 5th June 19^:6, from the Hesiaency Agent, Shargah, to the Hon f ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf 1 (iixtWCic. I arrived at Has al Khaima on the 20th May and had an interview with the Shaikh. The Shaikh says that it is better if Ahdur Hahman be deported to ±5omuay or Karachi. I arrived at Shargah on the 50th May. 'ifte Shaikh of bhargah is not willing for deportation of Abaur rcahman. The latter also will not go willingly. Certain news of Shargah has been reported in^letter lo. 193, dated the 4th June 1926, for your information. - KESIDEI nicy AGENT. li^»: IS 'HI f hHH k ftTelegram C. From Political Kesiaent, Busiiire. To Senior Naval Officer in tne Persian Suli, H.Ial.S. 11 THIAD', Henjam. No. 376. Dated lOtn June 19£6. His Majesty's Government have agreed to Abdur Rahman's being exiled to Aden for four years and to iiis going on pilgrimage first by sea if he likes. I hear from the Residency Agent that the Shaikh oi ynargah objects to this banishment. i suggest that you visit Has al Ivhaimah and immediately send a letter ashore to the Shaikh announcing tne order of exile ana ordering tne Shaikh to bring Abdur Haruuan on board. If Abaur Hahman accepts proposal about pilgrimage ne snould be sent to the Political Agents Muscat, in custody and put on Doard a direct pilgrim steaiuer tnere# Otherwise he will be sent in custoay to Aaen on a airect vessel if possible. i suggest anotlier Snip accompanying you to Has al Khaimah. If the Shaikh of Has al Khaimah fails to bring Abdur Hahman on board please inform me. I will meet you at Dibai. I believe Government have approved proposals about ulooa-money and fine, but telegram ib not quite clear. I will tnerefore communicate with tne Chief of Shargah after hearing from you. RESIDENT.H.M f s Political Resident, Bushire, S.N. 0., Persian Gulf ,H.M.S. 'Triad' Telegram Prom To No.377. % Dajred the 11th June 1926. lease warn Shaikhs whom you can communicate with especially Shargah to observe Agreement of 1892. RESIDii^T. S.N.O., Persian Gulf, Henjam Hd., H.M T s Political Resident, Bushire Telegram From To No. Dated the 12th ffune 1926. ^our 377. Pease confirm.Agreement referred to is Protectorate Treaty year 1892. S.N. 0. Telegram From To No. 381. ^ated the 12th June 1926. Yes.I have heard that Shaikh of Shargah has asked or intends to ask Ibn Saud to send him an official resident. RESIDENT. H.M f s Political.Resident, Bushire. S.N.O., Persian Gulf, Henjam Rd. t i ♦Telegram G. From Tne senior I^aval Officerin the Persian Gulf, H.M-S. 'TKIAjJ', Henjaiii radio. To H.M's. Political Heaident, iiusiiire. Time 19.54. Dated 11th received i^th June 1926. H.M.S. ' TKIaD ' and ,, CYGLAME1^^ ,, arrived a t Kas al Knaimah, Telegram C. From The Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf, H.M.S. 'TRIAD', Henjam radio. To H .M 's. Political Resident, Bushire. Time 18.55. t Dated 11th received 12th June 1926. Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah refuses to deliver up Abdur Rahman as he is afraid of consequences. Request further instructions. Tne Shaikh has been informed that 1 hold him responsible, from now onwards for safe custody of Abdur Rahman. 1v Telegram ^^{ jl ^Tom H.M 's Political Resident, BusMre, To S.N.C., to. 3^- Dated the 12th June 1926. Can you ask Shaikh to satisfy you ta^it Abdur Rahman is still in custody by showing him to.you ashore? If Khan Bahadur is not with you please send for him and tell / « him to assure Shaikh that four years* exile is the utmost penalty at present contemplated and that defiance may produce worse conseQuences. Abdur Rahman might become outlaw for life and could not live at Hairah. Perhaps you could get Shaikh of Dibai to visit Ras al Khaina also. If negotiations entirely fail tell Shaikh that orders of Government must be obtained. Then proceed to Dibai if Shaikli hi has not already Joined you and see if he can help. L o you think it possible to put pressure by threatening to seize pearling boats or to interfere with diving? Resident.Telegram C From The Senior luaval officer in the Persian Gulf H.M.S. 'TRIAD'9 Henjam raaio. Political Hesident, Bushire. To Time 2020, Dated 12th received 13th June 1926. Am acting on your telegram No. 380. Can carry out threat to pearl diving at Has al Khaima, the more so as dhows are not expected to leave for the Oanics for another ten days.■ Telegram G. Prom Tne Senior i^aval Officer in the Persian Gulf, H.M.S. 'TRIAD', Henjam raaio. To H.M's. Political Resident, i ^wsnire. Time &lt;i0.15. Dated and received x3th. June 19^6. PKIQRITY. Shaikh of Has al Khaima refuses to deliver up AbcLur Rahman to exile as he fears consequences would, be an • * attempt on his ( the Shaikh's ) life. He is however willing to give him up to me for trial before a Mohammedan Court of Justice in any place you may decide, and has given me Ms word 01 honour that he will do so should you agree to such a course. I have adjourned to consider carefully (V) until tomorrow (Monday) to await your reply. M iii I0/ (%) H.M^ Political Resident, Bushmre, SjE.O., Persian Gulf. Telegram P. From To No. 382. Dated the 14th June 1926. I do not think that Shaikh^ proposal is acceptable as our main object is to get man away from Shargah and no Kazi is likely to, convict hiip. Do you think that ex-Shaikh could hold his own if we re instate him in Shargah? Perhaps Shaikh of Umm al Q.aiwain can give useful opinion about this. C aution a.nd secret . Khan Bahadur may be personally hostile to ex-Shaikh. One solution of present difficulty if we cannot arrest A.R. may be to place British Political Officer with infantry guard at Shargah or Dibai at least for a time. Agent will hate this. RESIDENT. ! Jill : i ilyi i i iTelegram P. * From S .N .O., Persian Gulf, H.M f s Political Resident, Bushire, No. Nil Dated the 15th June 1926. Your telegram No. 382. Propose Abdur Rahman be sent to Shargah for custody. Ultimatum to that Shaikh would follow as follows-- failing delivery of Abdur Rahman on board within certain time limit watch towers of Heirah and Shargah wwill be bombarded and no vessels from either town allowed to proceed to pearl ^ be banks. Both Shaikhs to/warned they will be held responsible for any losses of life or property to British subjects. This might have desired effect since destruction of towers will lay towns open to attack from Ajman with whom there is friction on account of debt^ of Es 17,000/- by Shargah. Alternative proposal is ultimatum to Shaikh of Ras- al-Khaimah as follows-- failing delivery of Abdur Rahman on board within time limit, town will be bombarded. This would be more effect means of putting on pressure than stopping pearl-diving, Ras-al-Khaimah having inly eight dhows. S.N.O.H.M ! s Political Resident, Bushire, S.N.O., Persian Gulf. Telegram P. From To No. 384. Dated the 15th June 1926. I fear that no amount of shelling will effect smrrender of Abdur Rahman and safety of Indians has to be con sidered. Please ask Ajman and Umm -al -Q .aiwan what e*-Shaikh has of recover/ing power if we proclaim him as chief. Then deposition of the boy and destruction of Hairah vil lage would be sufficient retribution. I think alternative is to introduce Political Agent and guard. RESIDENT. \n M f I i ji -.11 ^mm%m Telegram C From, The Senior l^aval Officer in tne Persian Gulf, H.M.S. 'TRIAD', Henjam rauio. To h.i.x's. political He si dent, riusnire. Time 17.1b, Dated ana received xuth June 1926. Abdur Kanman was surrendered to me at 17*00 to-day (Wednesday) unconditionally. H.M.S. 'CYCLAMEN' with Abdur Rahman on board leaves for Muscat at 22*00 to-day. I have not mentioned subject of pilgrimage to him. If you still wish this done please give necessary instructions to 'CYCLAMEN'. Telegram C. i 1 r om The Senior Naval Officer in tne Persian Gulf, H .M.S. 'TRIAD', He^ajam radio. To • H. m's . Political Resident, imshire. Time 18*15. Dated and received, lotn June 1926. My telegram 17*15 of June i6th. I nave assured the Shaikh of Dubai that four years is the maximum period of exile. 11 v14/193 Telegram C. From H .M 1 . Political ^esidwiit, Busnire, To The Senior Naval Officer in tne Persian Gulf, H .M. S. 'TRIAD', Henjam Xw adio. No. 386. Dated 17th June 1926. P PAI0K1TY . Your 1715 and 1815. Hearty coxigratulations and thanks. Prisoner will not be given cnoice of pilgrimage now. Pour years' exile at Aden is the correct jjtriod. ~ RESIDENT• Telegram C. Prom H.M f s. Political Resident, Bushire. To The Political Agent, Muscat. Repeated The Senior \Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf, H.M.S. 'TRIAD', Henjam raaio. No. 587. - Dated i7th June 1926. IRIQRITY. ■ H.M.S. ' CYGIAMkN ' is bringing political deportee, »Dhaii£h Aodur iiahman of Haira, to you. He should be accommodated suitably in or near Consulate under Military guard and despatched by first direct steamer to Aden. Can you borrow services of Levy escort from Muscat Government for journey ? Otnerwise I must ap^ly to India for police guard. - RESIDENT.Ifl'l] @ Telegram P jrom To I Repeated / 0s&gt; H .M 's Political Resident, Bushire, Govt, of India, Foreign &amp; Political DeptSimla, (Colonial Office, London, (Political Resident, Aden. , I 1 Ho. 5/388. Dated the 17tli June 1926. Shargah outrage against Residency Agent. S.N.O. with two warships arrived Ras-al-Khaimah June 11th, communicated order of exile to Shaikh and ordered latter to bring deportee on board for conveyance to Muscat. Shaikh had been told by young Shaikh of Shargah to refuse such demand. He therefore replied that his own life would be endanger ed if he complied. For five days pressure was applied especially through Shaikh of Dibai to compel Chief of Ras-al-Khaimah to obey. Finally prisoner was surrendered unconditionally 5 p.m. June 16 th. It is ^considered advisable now to renew offer of pilgrim age. Man will be forwarded under guard by first direct steamer from Muscat to MenTelegram G. From H .m's . political Keaiclent, iiusnire. To Tne Senior iMaval Cfiicer in the Persian Gulf, H.M .S. 'TKIAD' j Ken jam radio. No. 589. Dated 17th June 1926. Please tell the Shaikh of Shargah now (1) that he must send Rs. 150 permensem to Abdur Rahman every month through me; {2) he must jiay blood-money for death of I brahim 'bin Raj ah 600 Maria Theresa dollars; (5) ne must pay fine to Government of i n dia for outrage against British Agency Rs. 5000. 1 nave Rs. 5000 of his in deposit ana he receives at least Rs. &lt;i000 per annum from Liessrs Strick for oxide concession at ^ou Iwiusa. This money cau oe utilized towards payments if ne agrees. RESIDENT.Telegram G. From Tiie Senior Naval Officerfln the Persian Gulf, H.M.S. 'TRIAD 'S Hen jam radio, To H.M's, Political Kesident, i^usnire, r iime 18*50. Dated and received 19th June 192o, p ibf Your' 5B'9. Shargah agrees to pac/ fines. . Requests you will pay them out of his money which you hold.Telegram C. iTom The Political Agent, liuscat. 'lo H,M f s, Political xiesident, Busiiire. No. 682. Da'ced ana received i9th June 1926. PHI OKI TY . ^ (&lt;i2&gt; Your telegram Mo, 587 of 17tii June. Deportee landed ana accoimnoaated in the Consulate, Regarding Levy escort for journey, local Govern ment write ; 'In connection with your further (request?) that a Levy escort be lent for the purpose of accompanying the deportee to Aden, we would ' point out that it is impossible there will be any direct ship from Muscat to Aaen for the i &gt; ne t two or three months. we suggest there fore tnat S -ftaiKh Aodur Rahman ue despatched to Aden via Karachi or Bombay. He could be sent to one of tnese Inaian ports by the next most suitaole British India Steam navigation Company's steamer; and in this case we should be pleased to send a Levy escort as far as an Indian port'. - DeMello.Resiaent, Aden, Resident, Bushire. (01 Telegram P. ^rom To No. 63. Dated the 19th received the 20th June 1926. J ^ Your telegram 17th June, No.388. Can you give me information as to details' of Shargah out' rage? I presume that it is not intended that Shaikh Abdur Rahman should be treated as a prisoner in Aden. RESIDENT. \ i M Government of India, Political Resident. Buflhirc. Telegram ^rom To No. 110. Dated the 19th received the 20tK June 1926. Your 388- Abdur Rahman, Government of India agree. Please take action in direct communication with Resident at Aden. FOREIGN. f 4) i • 1 1 u 4 r s if m ;' records. N0 .44 .D. Sir, H.M.S. 'TEtlAD' at Dubai, 17th Jttne, 1926, ^7 I have the honour to report that in accordance with your telegram No*376 &gt; H.M.S. 'TRIAD 1 * under ny comniand with H.M,S.'CYCLAMEN' in company arrived at Raa~al-Khaima an on 11th June. ' 3. Sheikh Sultan and his brother came on board and I thereupon handed him a letter ordering him to deliver up Abdur Rahman. This he refused to do, although I warned him that failure to do so might produce worse consequences for Abdur Rahman. He remained obdurate, stating that he feared for his life if it became known that he hed given him up. I then adjourned meeting and on receipt of your 380 proceeded to Dubai where the Shaikh Said bin Maktum and his brother Shaikh Juma expressed their willingness to help in the matter and returned in H.M.S.'TRIAD' to Ras**al~Khaima on 13th June. Another conference then took place at which were present Shaikh of Dubai and his brother, Shaikh Sultan of Ras-al-Khaima and his brother and the Residency Agent. — - * This conference resulted in the proposals set forth in my telegram of 13th June with which you informed me of your disagreement in your 382. This was duly communicated to the Shaikhs the next day. I again warned everyone that failure to produce Abdur Rahman would have unpleasant consequences which might well be felt on the whole Trucial Coast. The conference then broke up, matters being at a complete deadlock and all returned tc Ras-al-Khaima with the exception of the Shaikh of Dubai's brother who remained on board. 3. Later, however, he volunteered to go ashore and with his brother point out to Shaikh Sultan the necessity in the interests of everyone of surrendering Abdur Rahman, using threats if no other means were effective. - ^ As a direct result of this, when I sent ashore A.M. on the 16th June to ascertain how matters were - proceeding, I was informed that-Abdur Rahman would be brought on board that day. At 1700 hours he was aurrendered... Honourable Political Resident, boshire.surrendered to me on board H.15.S, 'TRIAD' unconditionally, I having previously taken upon myself to ensure Shaikh of Dubai that the period of exile would not exceed four years. I took the opportunity of showing His Majesty's Government's disapproval of the defiant attitude of Shaikh Sultan ih not complying with the orders of H.M, Oovernment by not giving him the customary gun salute, and warned him that he would be held responsible for any loss or damage to British subjects lives or property occurring in his district. 5. The successful end to these negotiations is very greatly due to theefforts of Shaikh of Dubai and his brother Shaikh Juma who throughout have been untiring in their efforts to bring matters to the desired end. I am of the opinion that a letter or other mark of your appreciation to these two Chiefs would be desirable and most acceptable to them. The Residency Agent has likewise been most helpful I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servant, SENIOR NAVAL OPPICTg?, PUISIAH GULF. •Mil Ma Telegram G• Froin xi.M's. Political Resident, ^usnire. To Tne Senior liaval Officer in tiae Persian Gulf, H.M.S. ,, TRIAD' , Henjam radio, Uo. 596. Dated 23rd June 1926. I hear tiiat no steamer will go direct from Muscat to Aden for tv/o or tiriree months. As it is preferred that Abdur Rahman should not go Yia India, there seem to be three alternatives; (1) to l£eep him in custody at Muscat for the present; (2) to send him to iiasrah on a man of war or 'LAWRENCE' and transfer there to Steamer; (5) to transi er him at iiandar Aobas or liusnire without landing him. Do you see any objection (breach of faith ) to (l) which is tne simplest ? - RESIDENT. Telegram G. From The Political Agent, Muscat. To H.M f s, Political Resident, Bushire. No. 691. Dated and received 22rd June 1926. 0 ^ iuy telegraia Ho. tL-xJune 19th.. Is ShaiKh Aodur Rahman allowed to write letters to Dubai people and others ? DeMello. I i 4Telegram G. From H.M's, Bolitical Resident, Bushire, To The Political Agent, lluscat. No. 398. Dated 24th June 1926. Abaur RaJrmian will be Kept in tne Consulate until Augtist, when H.M.S. 'LUPI^ 11 will taiie him to Aden. He may walk: about and visit by aay in company with two guaras. When he gets to Aden he v/ill only be under police surveillance. He may write letters to friends. He may draw on me ks. 4 per diem lor his maintenance through you. When he reaches Aden and hires a house he v/ill De allowed Ks. 5 per diem . _ HESIDEHT. Telegram C. From H.M f s. Political Resident, Bushire. Tib H.M's. Resident, Aden. Ho. 400. Dated. 2&lt;rth June 1926. 'ifour telegrams Eos. 44, ...ay 1st, and 63 of June 19t^Lr Aoaur Ranman was twice in trouble with Residency before 1924 wnen he expelled ex-Bhaixch of Shargah and ixistalled his own son-in-law. Last year the Residency Agent was fired at and his cousin killed. Uo effort made to aiscuver muraerec. Abdur Rahman is being punished for apathetic action and for evil influence over the young Shaikh. He is sentenced to four years' internment outside the / Persian Gulf. He cannot reach Aden before August / when H.M.S. 'LUPIK' will ta±ce him there. It is proposed that he live under police surveillance cUid that he draw Rs. loO per mensem from me through your office ^ or mai ntenanc e. lh - RESIDBHT.British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 26th June 1926. 4^ from The Hon»ble Lt.-Col. F. B. Prideaux, C.S.I-» Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, S i_ m 1 a. Attempt to murder the Residency A^ent, ^ Sir, I hare the honour to refer to correspondence ending with telegram from the Government -of India Ifo. 1023-S., dated the 7th June 1926, in which I was informed that His Majesty^ Government had approved my proposal regarding the exile of Shaikh Abdur Rahman of Hairah, father-in-lvr of the young Shaikh of Shargah. 2, On the 10th June I telegraphed to the Senior L Officer at Henjam asking him to proceed to Ras al with another Ship if possible, and on arrival tht write to the Chief informing him of Government's atoout Abdur Rahman and desiring him to bring the 1 board for conveyance to Aden. 3. I heard from Captain parry on the 12th June tl Shaikh of Ras al iLhaimah refused to surrender Abdur , as he feared the consequences for himsl^f. I replied requesting the Senior Naval Officer to ^or the Residency Agent, Shargah, and to take him, wit ^ ^ Silai3cil of Dibai also if possible, to Ras al Khaimah,I also asiced for Captain Parry f s opinion as to whether a threat to interfere with the pearling operations of Ras al Khaimah dhows would effect a satisfactory result. 5- On the 13th June Captain parry returned to Has al Khaimah from Dihai. Tno chief repeated his refusal to surrender Abdur Hahman for exile, tout offered to give him up for trial in any place before any lUthommedan Court of Justice. I considered this proposal unacceptable as I iaiew that no Kazi would convict Abdur Kahman either Ox coiiimitting or instigating the murder of Ibrahim bin Kajab or of negligence afterwards in tracing the criminals* 6* Captain parry and 1 then discussed various alternative measures which might be submitted for the Government of India» b consideration and orders in the event of the local negotiations ending unsatiffactorily. These were t (1) to order the Chief of Ras al Khaimah to return Abdur Rahman to Shargah, after which the watch towers of Hairah and Shargah should be blown dovn, laying the village and town open to attack from Ajman with whom there is always unfriendliness (2) an ultimatum to the Chief of Ras al Khaimak followed by the bombardment of his town and the destruction of his eight dhows; (5) a proclamation deposing the ^ o ^ Chief of tihargah and re-instating the ex-chief» coup^ 6 ^ with thethe destruction.jjf Hairah Tillage} (4) the temporary deputation of a British Political Ofiicer with an Xnicmtry guard to reside at Shargah. 7» boiae inkling of these discussions possibly reached the Shaikhs and on the 16th June in the afternoon Abdur Rahman unconditionally surrendered himself on board H.M.S. 'TRIAD'• Thlfs ended satisfactorily a situation which might have led to very strained relations between two or more of the Trucial Chiefs and His Majesty's Government. 8. The Shaikh of Dibai, who since the aggrand izing policy of the Wahhabi Governor of Hasa has made itself lelt in Oman during the past two years, has become very reasonable and friendly in his attitude towards this R e sidency, has been, as the Senior Baval Officer has noticed, most helpful in all the stages of this unfortunate affair* I gyn writing to him a letter oi thanks as Cgptain Parry has suggested* Abdur Rahman was transferred to H.M.S. 'CYCLAMEH'* and has duly reached Museat where he will be accommodated in the Consulate until he can be passed on to Aden. I have ordered that he may be allowed to walk about freely in the town in the day-time, provided that an escort accompanied him. Itme that the Shaikh agreed to all these points. 11 • There re .121ai .ns onl^r one other matter 10 reportyin this connection. On the 8th June I received from the jR e sidency A^ent a report to the effect that the Kazi of Shargah had been sent ley the young shaikh, at the instigation of four influential Najdi residents of Shar^ah, to Hasa aiid Mecca bearing letters for the Sultan, Ibn aa^d, and for his Governor, ibn jaluwt, in which they were asked to send a Wahhabi 'Xesident' to bhar^ah. I am endeavouring to get confirmation of the report which,if true, clearly constitutes a breach oil tine shaikh's part of his treaty engagements with His Majesty's Government. 12. If the young man does not now turn over a new leaf aiiu iii.aself ready to listen to our Agent , s representa4r tionB ; I think it will be necessary in tiie near future for me to suggest to the Government of l n dia one or both of the folloiwng measures 1 (a) the restoration of the ex-Shaikh, or the re-union of bhargah and Has al iChaimah under one Chief {the present ruler of Has al Khaimah) and (b) the appointment of a British Political Officer at Shar~ah. 13. A copy of this despatch is being sent to His Majesty*s ofccretary of State fOr the Colonies. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lt.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.ivr Ho•264-S of 1926. ^ British Reeidency and Coneulate-General^ Bushire, 26th June 1926. sir, I have the honour to aoicnowledge receipt of your letter No .44 .D., dated the 17th June 1926, rgarding the action taken against Abdur Hahman of Hiratln connection with the recent outrage at Shargah, and to enclose for your information a copy of my despatch Ho.261-5&gt; g dated the 26th June 1926, to the Oovemiaent of India (copy to H.M^ Secretary of State for the Colonies), on the same subject. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lt-Colonel, Political Resident in the 'ersian Gulf. toiler Haval Officer in the Persian Gulf, ■Triad' 1 . H.M.S. ►14/197. Extract from a letter llo.44.D., dated the 24th June 1926, from the Senior Haval Officer, Persian Gulf, to the Hon'ble the Political Resident, Bushire. ^ XXX x XX 5. On arrival at Sharja, the Sheikh came on board and 1 informed him of the fines, etc, [your telegram 589) which he must pay. He requested that they might be paid out of the monies of his which you hold. A letter from him author ising you to do so is attached. X XXX XX XX XX X XXNo. of 1926. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, 3rd July 1926. To The Shaikh of Dibai. After Compliments, In connection with the settlement of the affair of the outrage committed at Shargah against Khan Bahadur Isa bin Abdul Latif, first Captain Horner, my Secretary, reported to me that you gave much assistance in the course of his enquiries. Recently, Captain Parry, the S.II.O., informed me that you and your brother Shaikh J u ma bin Maktunr worked diligently to lucike the •-'haijth.s Ox ^hargah and ^ v as—ul—Khaimah see reason and be obedient to the decision of the Government of India. If those two Shaikhs had continued to resist the S.H.O's demand, the consequences would have been bad for them, and no doubt all the inhabitants of the Trucial Coast would have been put to inconvenience Just at the time when the diving season opens. I am most grateiul to you and to your brother for the good service which you have rendered. You may be assured that I have informed the Government of India about it. I look to you now to continue giving good advice to shaikh oultan bin Saqar as you are his close neighbour. Four years hence it should not be easy for Abdur Rahman to lead him astray. 1 hope also that Abdur Rahman will profit from his residence in Aden and that he will eventually return to Oman with a more sensible mind. Id eut-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bp'leltjgratn Q # i'r om r iiie benicr iiaval Officer in the tersian Gulf, H.M.S. 'TKIAD'&gt; Henjam. To H..Lx ! s. Political Resident, -uu^iiire. r iime 11.50. Dated lutii receivea 11th July 1926.. Owing to change of programme H.M.S. 'LUPIK' will probably not be available to take Abdur Raliman to Auen. Telegram G. Prom n.Us. Political Hesident, i&gt;ushire. To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, ^imla. JUo. 455. Dated i2th July 1925 My letter lie. 26i-o., uai-ed June 2oth, paragraph 8, 4- and telegram No. 42i, July 5rd. Acaur nahman and .oaruni . Senior i^aval officer now telegraphs tnat ov^ix.^ to change of programme H.M.S. M LUPI1T M will probaoly not be avail able fof trip to Aden in August. Gould Naval Commander-in-Ghief be asi£ed whether any other Ship en route to Aden could be diverted to Lluscat during next three months ? Alternatively, may Abaur Rahman oe sent to ivarachi oi' Bombay cn a Naval Sloop and thence forwarded in Police Custody oy mail to Aden ? - RESIDENT. c., , —/ 14/197 /55 Extract from a D.O. letter from the Hor^ble the Political Resident dated the 12th July 1926, to the Financial Adviser, Muscat. * -x ■* * xxx X x X XX I hope the Sultan is not going to be tiresome about the detention of Abdur Rahman in the Political Agency. if our Infantry Detachment had not been withdrawn, i would not have asked any favour of him. By the way, l don't know what Abdur Rahman^ son wrote to the Sultan. 1 have just heard that the 'LUPLN' is not going to Aden in August. The Government of India want to avoid having the man pass through Indian x;orts. 1 smppose there is no alternative but to have him remain in Muscat sine die.I■tai 14/197. Extract from a private letter dated the 8th ^uly 1926, from the Senior X^aval Officer, Persian Gulf, to the Hon f ble the Political Resident, Bushire. ***** XXX X XX X Dhows trading here from the Trucial Coast report all is quiet there and everyone well satisfied with the results of ray recent visit there, I think it would therefore be a mistake to take any further action regarding the Sheikh of Sharja for the present, will he has had his lesson and a fright which/l think assure his good 'behaviour for some time. The villain^of the piece in I that district is 1 believe L^agouk bin Ali bin Kamil. ' LU p LN' will be able to see how things are going on when he goes there shortly. 1 intend paying the Trucial another visit towards the end of September when 1 should be able to feel the pulse of the situation. x x x x xxx x BCOWFIDEyTTTAT,, From, Major B.R. Rellly, C.T.E., Ag, Political Resident, Aden. The political Resident in the Persian O-ulf^ Bushlre, SUBJECT;- Internment in Aien of Shaikh Abdur Rahman,father-in-law of the Shaikh of Shar^ah, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your telesram^dated the 24th June 1926^ on the subject noted above. I understand that you do not wish the Shaikh to be treated as a prisoner,but to be allowed freedom of movement under the general surveillance of the police. This can be arranged,but it will not be possible to detail Police to keep a constant watch on him. Aden is a small place and our administrative control extends for only a few miles. It is therefore comparatively easy for a man to out of the town into the interior, and if Shaikh Abdur Rahman were to do this,he would not have much difficultyjin finding a dhow at some point on the coast which would take him back to the Persian Gulf. I shall of course take whatever steps are possible to prevent such an occurrence,but I wish to make it clear that it cannot be guarded against completely without treating the Shaikh as a prisoner. I would suggest that his monthly allowance of Rs.l50 be increased. House-rents are high in Aden,and he is not likely to find a suitable house for less than Rs. IIHfli ..us; (2) R b.50 a month. In my opinion at least R8.5 a day should be allowed for hia living expenses,and I therefore recommend that an allowance of Rs # 200 a month 'be made to him. i/ I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, AG: As* i^ollyical Resident,Aden, ^ JM ^ r A ' n 7i ft ^5 &lt;- W-X -U- 1 ' 'T Oil iM , 17 717th July 1926. I If J if ft (My dear Parry), (Ihope you will drop frills and call ''I j ]i me Pridaaux) I owe you a reply to an official letter and one D.O. about Trucial Coast matters, but I have been very busy, and have missed both last mail and this. I had a talk however with and he will give you some idea of my views. (D»m afraid I differ from you somewhat because, fa) I am convinced that hundreds of Arabs including the R.Agent, know *ho instigated the murder, (b) the R.A. has been privately squared or promised compensation, which accounts for his later oppositior to the banishment of Abdur Rahman. (c) it is incredi/ble that A.R. did not know that he he was to be expelled. All the Arabs were talking about it before eves you reached Ras al Khaimah,and the pilgrimage suggestion had been mooted. (d) there are ver£ grave charges against the R.A. of making profit out of slavery and kidnapping cases. The latest accusation comes from lingah, and I s^ill await the details. Both the Muscat &amp; Bahrain P.As say that tkia there are ugly stories about K.B.Isa. There the matter rests l&amp;x at present. I 'iless proofs are forthcoming about Isa, and if the II ri Wahhabi Amir of Hasa does not encroach further, he is not likely to be shifted at present, but h# is certainly a rogue ! We will talk further when we meet. t m Yours sincerely, F.B.Prideaux.Telegram G. Prom / Liir lite -1 - r ine Foreign Secretary to tiie Government of India, Siml a* - 0 H .Li 's. Political Resident, i^usnire, No. 278-N. Dated 25rd received 24tii July 1926. Your No. ^35. ho Naval vessel is available. tlease deport Abaur xiahman to Aaen oy Naval Sloop or mail boat as in your alternative su^^estion in direct cominunication v/itii tne Government of jiom&amp;ay f llease report date of departure. *' J? 1 Oxiii 1GN •'S-- vl'll NO. K. 16/26/7/26 of 1926. British Consulate and Political Agency,I'uscat. From resid ency, f?eg. 7 I Otu 1 CONFIDtNTlAL RECORDS- TO Ma .lor C ,C,J .Barrett, C .S ,1C ,1 .K,, H.B.Mo'g Consul and Political Agent,Muscat„ The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Dated,Karachi,the 26th July 1926. ''J Sir, Re Abdur R ahm an bin Mu^mirad of_Haira I have the honour to enclose herewith, a copy of a letter in Arabic, addressed by Muhammad bin Abdur Rahman to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman,requesting the latter jc to intercede on behalf of Abdur Rahman 0 2. His Highness personally nt™** +n ^ C wLXb the remark4#^that he had no wish to interfere in the matter. % 3, An English translation of the letter is also attached I hare the honour to be, ^ Sir, ^our most Obedient Servant, S v.,* u C a H .B tt r o f s Consul and Political Agent Muscato £ I i t ii V. ^ii iiiMiiniM 11 rill ■HfWIMi Translation of a letter dated the 12th Dhil Hajj 1344 i corresponding to 23rd June 1926, from Muhammad bin Abduv Rahman, to His Highness Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat. After Compliments, This year an incident took place in the Sharqah land. On that day caravans had come and it is customsry for them to fire guns. God decreed and the nephew of Isa bin Abdul Latif got a bullet. He was «ttlc walking with him. They neither heard shooting ,nor saw any person shooting. Interested persons .however came and threw suspicion on our son Abdur Rahman bin Muharanad, without any knowledge or certainty. He can take oath to acquit him of the accusation, as he was a friend of the British Agent. After some days cwne the Naib ( Secretary to the Political Resident) and Kanoo ( Yusuf Kanoo of Bahrain ) to Sharqah. Abdur Rahman was called. He obeyed and went to the Baib and the Wakil ( Residenc. Agent) but nothing was proved against him. They,however, ordered him to proceed to Has al Khaimah. for 7 weeks. He remained at Ras al Khaimah for 6 months and there was no proof against him. Yesterday came here the Kaib and ordered him to leave the place. He had no help. It is said that he Will Stay pt Muscat. Our hope from you is good and you h '' Te ' 1 ' y8 done ^ours. I appeal you in the name of God to Show the kindness which your Highness possesses. Kindly y to the High Govt good saying and thank God you are best of the people, as regards saying and doing. You 4re the ble88ed •nd Cod mux rewards those who do favours. Sod a „d there i8 no Godbut He) R|ihin|tn ^ uhannad is innocent of the accusation made against him. Request you to intercede for this man in a good way. He ^ rei,1&lt;lin With you 4111 grants relief. God willing.you untf a il. May God not deprive us of your use. Salams, xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx [0 —' Wo/»Vof loss. British ^asHorcy &amp; Corsulato Sororal. Busbl^e Btb Aucust TO. Shaikh Sultan Bin Saqar The ^uler of IB ha Arab. AiC* t with rofo^erco to your lottor dated tbo SOth Jure 1924, in wMcb you acroe to de^^ay the exDersos of AMur Rahman bin MubaTmrad durlnir tbe rerlod of bis 'fearlsbirent from tbe Oman Coast T row Inform you tbat tbe Political Resldert,Aden, bas intimated tbat tbe monthly cost of Sballcb Abdur Rabman* s maintenance at Ader In suitable style will be If 200/- So tbe total annual amount wblcb you will no doubt readily nay Is ^2400/- Tbe Sbal^h will be sent from Muscat to Bombay in a ti^n-of- war about g^tb Ausrust and from Bombay to Aden be will trawel in a mail steamer* Usual Endlncr# trleut. Colonel. Political w,©sident In tbe n®rslan Gulf.# ' till W-'jsiNo let of 1926 British Residency &amp; Consulate General Bushire 9th August 1926, To, The Residency Agent Shargah A* C • | I am directed to forward to you herewith letter No 104 datefil. 8th instant from the Honourable the Political Resiaent in the Persian Gulf to Shaikh Sultan bin Saqar the Ruler of Shargah. Please deliver the letter to the Shaikh and send his reply as soon as possible. U.E., /-y Secretary to the Political Resident in the P-GFrorp. The Residency Agent Shargah. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the PoG., No 318. Dated, 27th July 1926, A» C, &gt; I write this to state that ; late on the 14th July 1926^ H,K .S, Lupin arrived at Shargah / and I at once called on boar/./,. The Captain askeci me about the Shaikhs of the Qnan Coast an© T informecs him that they are quiet but that only the Shaikhs of Shargah and TTmm-ul-Qaiwain and the relatives of Ab&amp;ur Rahman bin Muhammad are annoyec at the banishment of the said Abdur Rahman from the Oman Coast and say that the High Government has taken him av/ay simply because an accusation was brought him for his being involved in the murder of my cousin Ibrahim bin Rajab, and that the accusabton was not proved. The Captain therefore desired that the Shaikh of Shargah should call on board the 'Lupin' 1 , On the 15th idem I accompanied Sultan bin Saqar aiW called on board the man-of-war. The Captain advised the ojx. Shaikh not to become displeased account Abaur Rahman.and A &gt; * that he should aavise the latter*s relatives that he has been taken away for his own good and to prevent him from participating in evil affairs and that during his banishmen he will gain common-sense and will abandon his propensity to take part in a misbehaviour,. The shaikh's reply to the Captain was that the Govt's orders shall beyed with due respects but Abdur Rahman's A ' parents are old and weep for him day and night because he was their breadwinner and that if now the Captain were to pay them something for their daily expenses it would be insufficient as Abdur Rahman's family consists of many persons. The Captain said in reply that Abdur Rahman is no quite safe and that after the term of his banishment is expire^he shall come back to his family safely.,After this conversation the Shaikh landed from the man-of-war and the Captain came ashore to return the Shaikh's visit :the ShaikQZ reniterea due respects to the Captain ant* the latter became Captain to Lebai. Shaikh Said bin Maktura called on boarti the man-of-war on its ariival there ; and the Captain return- e&amp; the Shaikh's visit on the 16th July .When with the Shaik the Captain asked him to give good advice to the Shaikh of Shargah and to ask him to advise the relative of Abdur Rahman bin Muhammad to banish displeasure from their minds regarding the baniehi® nt of Abdur Rahman,who shall be permitted to come back to his native place after the teim of his banishment iS expired. Shaikh Said bin Maktiun replied that he will not fail to continually give his good advice On the 17th July the Captain left for Has- us-Khaimak and we arrived there at noon time. Shaikh Sultan bin Salim called on board the man of Y/ar f where the Captain talked to him in regard to the case of Abdur Rahman„ The answer of the Shaikh of Ras-ul- Khaimah was^identical with that of the Shaikh of Shargah^and the Captain also replied to him in the same way as he replied to Shai |±l Sultan bin Saqar. The Shaikh then landed from the man-of-war and the Captain also went ashore to return his visit: the Captain remained with the yhaikh for nearly an hour and half and then returned to the man-of-war. The boat left for Henjam on thynight of 16th July ; but I remained in Ras -ul-Khaimah for a week on account of bad weather and then returned to Shargaho pleased with the Shaikh. The same day I left with the to the Shaikh of Shargah and others concerned . ll-S.Ula Zos cUu^ ■fiuo W S Cefty*.Telegram Co From H.M. S, 'LUPIN'*, Hen jam Kadio« To H.M's Political Resident,, ±Jushire. Time 10.00 Dated and received the 16th August 1926. Arrived at Muscat at 08.30. Bailed for Karachi 10,00. Have embarlced A (bdur Kiahman; for passage to Bombay. File.* F.-b.-F 17/8/26. Telegram C. From Political Resident, Aden. To Political Resident, J3ushire# Nc. C/504» Dated the 2l8t, received the 22nd August 1926. Shall be glad of reply to my despatch Ho.C/402 of July 3rd« RESIDENT.-r- ORIGINAL Oil FILE . /\ Extract from memorandum l^o-SO, dated the 22nd August 1926, fr©m the Commanding Officer, H .M.S. 'Lupin 11 , to the H©n ! ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. With reference to the attached copies of signals from the Senior l^aval Officer, Persian Gulf, Sheikh Abdur Hahman and his servant were embarked at Muscat on 16th insti and handed over to the Commissioner of Police at Bombay on 22nd inst, xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxHo »278-lT. BUSHiRE RESIDENCY Reg. No....f 9. Date ^4 CONFIDENTIAL fiECOaOS. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Hon^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bus hi re,' political Resident, Aden, for information with reference to the correspondence ending with telegram Ho#498, dated 11th August 1926. the endorsement from the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Ho»278-l!T, dated 13th August 1926. By order, etc.. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. foreign and Political Department; Simla; The August 1926. Telegram from the Government of Bombay, No.4453, dated 19th August 1926. Telegram to the Government of Bombay, lIo.278-Ivr, dated 20th August 1926. c (With 1 spare copy.) 9 'Miii — IMI mi MI iiiiii /fcfo Telegram from Government of Bombay, Political Department, Poona, To foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla* Uo.4453 Dated 19t ]i (5.44 p .m.) August 1926. Received 19th (8.10 p .m.) Your despatch July 24th 278 Shaikh Abdur Rahman. Resident Bushire has telegraphed that Abdur Rahman will arrive Bombay 23rd August by H.M.S.'Lupin H . Steamer to Aden leaves Bombay 28th August. Please telegraph orders immediately whether he should be locked up or put in Hotel and if latter should police guard escort him wherfe ever he goes, also whether 1st class or 2nd class passage be engaged and what restraint should be imposed on him by police guard during the voyage. Telegram IIo.278«N., dated 20th August 1926. From .... Foreign, Simla, To ••••.. Bompol, Bombay. Your 4453. Abdur Rahman should be kept under t survillance whilst in Bombay, should receive 1st class passage and be subjected to ordinary survillance during voyage. ♦ Please notify Resident Aden of date of arrival and ship.6^ '•ush I re resicency. No. 4453-B. Political Department, om'bay Castle, ^ 1 September 19 26. 'fl OHFiDOTAL REGQRO^ From J. B, Martin, Esquire, C .I .E ## Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department. To The Honourable the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, B U S K 1 B E. Subject Deportation of Shaikh Abdur Bah&lt; man, father-in-law of the Shaikh of Shargah. I I sir, With reference to your telegram dated the llth I August 1926, 1 am directed by the Governor in Council to state that Shaikh Abdur Bahman left for Aden by the S. S. 'Kaiser-i-Hind' on the 28th idem. The Political Kesident, Aden, has been informed by telegram. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. &amp; % secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, a*lAL. HI® Ko.391-3 of 1926. British Residency and Consulate-General Bushlre, 18th September 1926, A oopy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment for information, with reference to the correspondence ending with their endorsement N0 0 278-N, dated the 23rd August 1926 o Residency telegram dated the 11th August 1926, to which reference is made in the enclosure, conveyed the same information as in Residency telegram Ho»498 of the same date to the Government of India• Letter from the Government of Bombay# Political Department, HOo4453-B p dated the 2nd September 1926• By order Captain 0 Secretary to the Political Resident? in the Persian Gulf.H0.434 -S of 1926. British Reeiaency and Conaulate-General* Bushire, 12th October 1926. To Shaikh Sultan bin Sali]B t Ruler of Has-ul-Khaimah• After oon^limeiite« I think it desirable to write you a letter of advice to which I hope you will give heed* It is only six years since the GoTemnient of India recognised the separation of the Government of Has*ul~Khaifflah from that of Shargah and your assumption of the independent position of a Ruler of the Oman Coast having treaty relatione with the Government of Indiao You promised then 9 amongst other matters t to maintain friendly relations with the High British Government, to render any assistance needed by the High British Govern • ment and to observe all the usages 9 etc., observed by the other Trucial Chiefs on the Trucial Coast. When the attempt was made twelve months ago on the life of the Agent of this Residency, Khan Bahadur Isa, and his cousin and assistant, Ibrahim bin Hajab 9 was killed, you gave the Residency no assistance to discover the criminal, nor did you give proper advice to the young Shaikh Sultan bin Saqar. My Secretary, Captain Homer, made an investigation and concluded that the chief responsibility for the mis- government and disorder in Shargah rested with Abdur Rahman bin Muhammad, the father-in-law of Shaikh Sultan, whose previous history, as known to the Residency, is not good.Captain Homer arranged with your brother on your behalf that Abdur Rahman should be taken in custody to Rae-ul-Khal- mah on the dietinot understanding that he should be produced when required by me. I was surprised soon afterwards to hear that you had strengthened your ties with the Chief of Shargah by marriage, ' he occasion seeiaed to me to be in opportune • eventually, at my request. Captain *rry 9 the Senior i^aval Officer, communicated to you the orders of the Govern ment of India that Abdur Rahman should be expelled from the Pereian Gulf for four yearso For five days you resisted the &lt; demand for Abdur Rahman^ surrel^nder, thereby nearly bring ing upon yourself the grave displeasure of Government• liow, 1 hear that mis chief -Makers are troubling iLlian Bahadur Isa and threatening seVious evil to him if Abdur Bahnan ib not sent back© You should know that the Government of India will not agree to this, however much the Residency Agent may recommend it© In view of your past attitude in this affair I find it necessary to warn you that if any further outrage is coriaitted — whether by Bedouin or by dwellers on the Truoial Coast against the Residency Agent or any British Indian subject, I shall suspect you first of complicity in the crimo. ^or your own advantage you should do everything possible to free yourself from this suspicion© Usual ending© Lt-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian GulfNo«435-S of 1926• British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 12th October 1926. A copy of the under mentioned paper is forwarded with compliments to the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, for informationo - a Lt-Colonel, Political Resident in th^Persian Oulfo Letter No.434-3, dated the 12th October 1926. from the Political Resident in the -ersian Gulf, to the of Ras-ul-Khaimah&lt;» ^ n— - ■ u &amp; I ■ !hOOA 1 7^ jei JL vyy? WA ^ i - ) v \j The Residonoy Agent# Slmrgah* The Honourable the political Res iclent in the Persian Gulf* rNo» 553* Dated 6th Deoeinber 1926 1 * 'A.O., With referenoa to i^y telegra-i No 409 dated Member 1926,regarding the three Baluchie na:nely Baehuk bin ^-ia,laehkari bin Salih # and Ibrahim bin luhammd about whoa Ali bin LL 2®,il'Baluchi,informed me that they have talked about their bad intantiono towards me and whom I have arrested(with the assistance ^of Shaikh Suljan bin Saqar the Chief of Shargah) I have now'the honour to aubmit the statement of Ali bin ismailittA^xxTC^. i 1 have further, to state that since the 11th aoyejiber 1^26,1 xiave^ together with t ie Shaikh,'hae?i trjfcog) these men 'Uj they have / until now, not *£&amp;&amp; an&gt;»&gt;iaing admitted any of the things *^rlbuted to them and they deny saroe* I and the Shaikh have ^adrefore arrived, at the 'conclusion that if you will deem it **vl8Rble to send the said three men to ^lekran-,their own native country because their regaining in the Oman Coast is not suitable, tria in order the-t this nay beliesbon to other Baluchis and they me.y ■ e Sfcivin£; utterance to noneense.17IJ R.mi.Uon or of All M b Hail B.luoal, reoM.nt of Hire now a gu^rd in oii© tcfcer near the weile outBide S argala# Recorded on the 4oli Jaraadtt ae Sani# 245 &gt;= 11th December 1926• I was in :ny iiou .ee at .lira® Three Baluchie na ;ried P &amp;ehuk eon of Sftlili # lAekkari eon of Salih and Ihrahii -n eon of Muhaimaad call ed on ise and told rje as under 'Two days ago we got informtlon that K.B.Isa bin Abdul Lr.fcif 'the Reeidenoy Agent will travel by land from Shargah to A jmn and' 'we therefore lurked for him on the way. Two Bunnias passed ue on n en route to A jiaan 'donkeys/but we did nothing to tlieirf* We left for Shargah in day tiine* 'where we found lea sitting on the eea-ehore with some people and ,f 'liis guards had anas with the ids elves I asked them as to v/hat grievances tiiey xiad against isa bin Abdul Latif and they told me in reply that 'he banished Abdur Baiuaan bin J u hamrjad from his ne.tive place' thenj I reiaarked thc.t c/*&gt; Abdur Rahman has got relatives and they should sofisfcthing and the thro© Baluchis answered saying that the Arabs have got no zeal in thein M we therefore do what is to be done and no-one can do anything tous'. They went o® saying that they find lea molest-the Baluchis c by making from them the slaves that they want to sell and hands the b laves to uhe British and that this act of restoration of the slaves co .uaes looses to all peopleUU After I heard the above from the said three Baluchis I tkought it niy duty to inform#of the same so that you siiould be (no alert. The said three Baluchis live in Hira and are well known'• pre ona there* ^ 12-26® ^Unesees ;*&lt; Signed• Je thanand• I dirdM Signed and seale (i Ahmad bin Abdullah KJiuri',Confide ntjal.. ^ — L* yrom - The Residency Agent, shargah. To - Captain B.Stuart Horner, I .A., Secretary to the Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf„ j)gted 19th January 1927. A.C. I have the honour to state that Khadijah mother of Ibrahim bin Rajab and Ibrahim's brothers Muhammad and Ahmad sons of Rajab have enquired me as to how the case of the muraered man now stands. I have informed them that the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has done all possible to trace the murderer but he could not and that His Honour has recovered S «5» blood money from the Chief of Shargah. They TfrftfiotriiQu*-ifte that they are quite agreeable with the Political Resident's view and if have got no objection to His Honour's action, but, ^ the creditors of Ibrahim are pressing for their claims and that they (Ibrahim's heirs) desire to pay debts. In view of this intention of Ibrahim's heirs I addressed this to you on the subject. Usual Ending. ^ iImmmmmrnmrn ——g— I—in' m ■aj**gpepg»pepiie!^gggBg*p^pepi 2Cii Note 1 V The R^ . Sbargah in.his letter No.73, dated the 22rd February sports :- (1) On hearing that Ahdur Rahman will not be released he informed 'lie subjocte the A1 Bu Siiamie tribe who are residing in Hirah and Shftrgfch and by the instigation of the A1 Bu S ha mis tribe the Siiiiifeii begun to trouble the Residency Agent, Shargah. (£) For the purpose of receiving the Hon'ble the Political EeBident the Residency Agent proceeded to Ras ul Khaimh by road with 25 Bedoiiins and followers because the sea was rough and he had infori^ed Shaikli Sultan bin Saqar accordingly. When he reached al Joruf -.luhaioaad bin Salmin A1 Shamisl and &gt; • nine ot;iers Iiad occupied the place but could not do any thing bec^uee the R»A. i:iad so mny companions. Juha-nrnd bin Salmin on return to Sliargah inforrjed the Shaikh who load detailed him. (3) By the instigation of certain mischievous men Shaikh Sultan bin S&amp;qar appointed Farhan and three others to commit robbery in the bazaar and to create disturbance. The RJi. wrote three letters to the Shaikh but the \ letters remained unanswered. The R#A. wrote to the Shaikh of Debai informing him of the above, the Shaikh replied that he has been giving good advices to Shaikh Sultan bin SaQ^r. 1 i ■ wmTelegram Code From S.N.O. Persian Gulf To Resident Eushire Ho. 1315 Dated 11th. received 12th. June 1927. Shaikh Ahmad of Henjam informs me there has been a fight between dhows of Umm al Khaiwain and Sharja. Also that it is now known that Khalid bin Ahmed nov/ at Umm al Khaiwain instigated attack on Residency Agent on the oc casion when his cousin was killed. The man who fired the shot is nov/ in Sharja and was one of those who were recent ly blinded. Propose investigate these reports when I vi sit Trucial Coast. Request you will inform me action you wish taken. S.N.O. Telegram P Prom Resident Bushire To S.N.O. Persian Gulf Ho. 552 Dated and despatched 13th. June 1927. Your telegram No. 1315 of 11th. June. I should be obliged d)f you could proceed to Shar ja and inform both Shaikhs t 1 cey will be held personally responsible for breach of maritime peace, and that nay dhows containing armed men will b© fired on. Would you kindly determine facts of case and let me know. If you can do so without incurring danger please seize any dhows which may have been engaged in breac of truce, but it is nor worth while rising men's lives since object can be obtained by bombardment if necessary. I should be obliged if you could keep me in formed. RESIDENT.v&gt; m The Pvesidency Agent. Shargah. Tiie Hon , 'ble the Political Pesident, Persian Gulf. Dated 17th April 1928. yfi* TTith reference to your letter Ho.23, dated thd 6th\ To No.157 A. 0 • ss February 1928, regarding the recovery of 1200/- from Shaikh Sultan Mn ^aqar, ^hief of Shargah, on account' of c maintenance of Ahdur Salman 'bin ir ijhamr:ad, I 'be,; to statenf that on receipt of your letter T called upon the Sh^iS^ to pay up the amount hut he was putting me off 'by promises till I left for Bahrain to see the T Ton f hle the Political Resident. On my return to Shargah I ^sked him a^ain to p_y the money and after much insistence he arranged for oayment of the amount. T her to enclose a Note XT o.79361 for Ps .lO ^O/- and two other Notes No s. 114364 ^.nd 549877 for Rs.lOO/- each j.nd hope you will receive them. QT I 'bej to enclose herev/ith a letter from the Shaikh to your address in which he asks you to 'bestow your favours upon Ahdur Rahman 'bin Muhammad. T also enclose the letter of Ahdur Hahman's mother in original in ./■lich she 'begs you to feel pity on her. The mother and ^amily of AMur Pahman have often come to the Agency weeping -nd asking me to request you to forgive Ahdur Pa' man L.nd oblige them 'by allowing him to return to his home. Letter dated 14th Shawal 1346 (5-4-28) from Shaikhafc bint Pahmah (Ahdur Pahman*s mother), Fatimah hint Saif I Ahdur Pahman's wife), Nurah hint Ahdur Pahman hin lr 'JhL-;nimad (Ahdur Pahm- n's daughter^ to K.B. Isa hin AMul Latif, Pesidency Agent, Sh^r^ah. i.0. 1 he^ to st^te these few lines and pray God and Hon'hle the Political Pesident to hestow his favour a Pon me and permit my son Ahdur Pahman to return to me clS I am a poor and helpless woman. Since his departure u ^3 family, children and myself are In a very difficult i - ' -Wmmmmmm n wi'i'&lt;Mi(rT'r*Tdi from. - Shaikh Sultan Mn Saq_ar, Chief of Shargah, tq ' The Hon'hle Lt-^olonel TTaworth, TT . P. ¥ * s Political Vesicant, Persian G-ulf and Consul General for Fars, etc. Dated 25th Shawal 1346 (16-4-28). a.o. I 'be^ to state that K.B. Shaikh Tsa 'bin Ahdul Latif the Hjsidenoy igent shov/ed me your letter v /ith re^ar . to H3.1200/- on account of the maintenance of Shaikh Ahdur Halm an hin Muhanimad. In reality as T had no money I Was mucji perplexed and with ^reat difficulty T ohtai led the amount j.nd paid it to the Khan Bahadur. By the ^crace of GocL and your kindness our territory is in peace and tranquility. In view of the friendly relations which existed between my father and grand-father and the High Government T 'be^- you ^nc the tT irh Govern: ent to he stow your favours upon AMur 'Rah an 'bin Muhammad and ^ive him permission to return from Aden. For this act of kindness his mother, myself and the notables who paid their respects to you on 'board the Ghakdara at Shargah and asked you to 'bestow your favours upon AMur Hahmon will he much obliged to : ou 2.0 lon^' aL3 we are alive• God &gt;.7ill rev/ard t /.ose who forgive the evil doers. TT 'I? U • all •THE SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER. PERSIAN GULF THE POLITICAL RESIDENT BUSHIRE 2nd June 1028 rh+J) During the recent visit of H M S TRIAD to the Truclal Xi* Coast I had conversation with the Sheikh of Sharjah. He is distressed because he has not received any news as to the success of his request for the repatriation from exile at Aden of his Father-in- Ijaw, I promised to lay the matter before the Political Resident at Bushire, (kt ifc CAPTAIN SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER PERSIAN QULFHO. 529• Dated the 25t]i June 1928. yrom T^e Residency Agent Crucial Oman^^harqah* TO The Hon'tle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* After Compliments, With reference to your Confidential letter ir0.95 dated the 22nd May 1928 enquiring what influence Abdur Rahman 'bin Muhammad has on the Shaikh of Sharqah, I most respectfully submit that the influence of Ahdur Rahman on the Shaikh is on account of the relationship between them. One of the daughters of Abdur Rafcman is married to Shaikh Sultan and the other to his brother Shaikh Muhammad bin Saqar. Secondly the said Abdur Rahman has relations among BU AiySHAMAS and their Shaikhs are frequently risiting Shar&lt;jah and requesting the Shaikh about Abdur Rahman, ^t is due to the requests of those Shaikhs and the ladies that the Shaikh has requested yodr honour. The A1 Bu Shamas who are in Baraimi are beduin^s and the Shaikh thinks that the prolonging of Abdur Rahman* s deportation may lead to trouble by the bedouin^s. He therefore requests you to release^ Abdur Rahman bin Muhammad. ^s regards reducing the exile to 3^ years,I do not see any harm in it as the Shaikhs and people of the Trucial Oman are all obedient to the British Gort. The town of Shar^ah is quiet at ptesent. In my opinion if you deem fit to return Abdur Rahman bin Muhammad to gire full satisfaction at Sharqah, it will quiet down the throughts of the Shaikh. The opinion is with your honou*. MS: U.K. S^/ Isa bin Abdul Latif. Residency Agent^Tyucial Oman, Sharqah* 77/2«-Ho. 2214 of 1928. British Hesldenoy &amp; (Jonsuiate-General, Bushire, the lAovember 1928« prom To TIig Hon'ble 3ir i^redorlolc Johnston, K«0«I*E«, i ?olltioal Resident In the Persian oulf. The foreign secretary to the Oovermrient of India in tiie foreign and 'Jolitlcal Uepurtment, Delhi* aeduction of the period of deportation of Shaikh Abdur l^anman from 4 to 3 yeurs# air, I have the honour to refer to correspondonce ending with this tiesldenoy letter Mo. 261-s dated the 26th June 1926 and to report for the information of the Government of India that for some time past there has been a inove on the part of the shaikh of 3h trgah and the relatives of ahalkh AMur Hahman to obtain the latter•s return from banishment • The iiesid icy Agent at ahargah la forw rding the shaikh of shargah's petition on hehalf of Abdur Rahman considers there would be no harm in granting a reduction in the term fo vhloh abdur Hahman has been exiled. *hen air Lionel ria worth recently visited the Trucial (Joaat he was agreeably impressed with the improved conduct ^nd general balance of the young shaikh of ahurgah, and verbally promised he would see what could be done in the ^tter of getting Abdur tiahman back before his term was c oapleted« ^ir Lionel Haworth was of the opinion, that a reduction of 0 ne year in the t^rm of banishment would, as an act ofvm • 2 • clemency# have a toenefiolal effect and would go far to lengthen our Agent *8 hands on the Truclal Coast. In the clroumutances I recomniend that the period of % banishment of shaikh Abdur Bahnan he reduced by one year and that he lie allowed to return home on the 16th June 1929 wlien lie srill have oooplotGd three out of the four years for whioh^was sentenced. Should the Government of India approve my reoommendation, I might add that before the return of the deportee, I should in informing the shaikh of Shargah of Government's olemenoy, bring home to him that ho would be held personally responsible for the good Dehaviour of his uncle Abdur iiahmaa f so long as the latter resided within the confines of jhargah torrttory, and that any attempt to intrigue or again start an agitation against the residency Agent would be especially severely dealt with. I have the honour to be f Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political resident in the Persian Gulf.No. ZT.S'O of 1928. British Kesidanoy &amp; Coasulata-Ganaral. Ji— 3u»hir« , the 2^ - Novemtier 192fi. From The Secretary to the Hon^hle the Political Reaiient in the Persian Gulf. To The First Assistant, to the Political Resident, Ai-en. Sir, With reference to your letter No, 0.403, iatei the Sri July 1926 and the connected corres pondence on the subject of Shaikh Ahdur Rahman, father-in-law of the ihaikh of ^hargah, who is now a political prisoner at Aden, I am directed to make inquiries as to the state of health of Jiaikh Ahdur Eahman, Ifis relations have heard that he is ilmwell and are anxiously enquiring for new«. I have the honour to 'be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ♦ • Major, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.(Si?) n NO.J.278-K/27. jrom The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department, To The Hon 1 hie the Political Resident % in the Persian Gulf. Dated New Delhi, the tlihr December 1928, V Reduction of the period of deportation of Shaikh AMur Rahman from four to three years. Sir, . With reference to your letter ]:Io.2216, dated the 18tii Uovemher 1928, 1 am directed to convey, as an act of clemency, and subject to the warning which you propose to give to the Shaikh of Shargah, the sanction of the Government of India to the reduction of one year in the term of banishment of Shaikh Abdur Rahman. He may therefore be allowed to return to his home on the 16th Junei 1929. 2, A copy of the correspondence is being forwarded to the Government of Bombay, and the Resident and Commander- in Chief, Aden, for information. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Copy,together v/ith a copy of the letter replied to, to the Government of B omba y , Political Department , Resident and Commander-in-Chief, Aden, for information, with reference to the correspondence ending ^ith the telegram from the Government of India in the foreign and^ofitical Department, No.278-N, dated the jjOth August 1926. 23rd August 1926. h'Mr i ^auiwwigk 1- ' i?roin To . 'lie Residency Agent, Shargah. - Tae :ion , 'ble the Political Hesident, Persian Clulf No# 611 j Dated the 12th DecemlDer 1928. Reference my letter No. : 529 dated the 25ti June 1928, on the subject of bdur Hehman 'bin Muiammad, who is In 'den, j to state that Sheikh Sultan hin Sa^ar, ^hief of Sharg ia s addressed a letter to Your Honour, which has heen signed ov tae notable of Sharjah -.nd the 'Jhief of Dahai, soliciting releise of Ahdur Rehman 'bin Muhammad from /Vden. I have already stated in my letter No.-329 that the saio Sheiki considers the extension of Vbdur Re iman^ exile might lead to disturbance among Al-Bushamis Tri ^^ cu ^^ ela1iive3 or 1: ' ae said Sheikh Modur Rehman residing at . Tie Sheikh's otjeot for 'bdur Rehman's release is for the safety and security of the Town. The Sheikh is right and decision rests with you. I ve 'ture to recommend for Vbdur lehman and if it sounds advisable to you, he may he 'brought to Bombay.t) tition dated the 6th Jamadi II, 1347 (19th Noverober 1928), ^ t/ie -Jon'hle the Politioal Resident in the Persian Gulf,. A.O. I have the honour to state that it is not hidden from y 0U&gt; tiiat the Hon'hle Sir Lionel Haworth and Major Dickson, the Secretary, visited my town 3hargah in the month of October last and I had the greatest pleasure to interview I placed 'before them the case of Ahdur Rehman hin vuhanunad, who is detained in den. The lon^le the Colonel promised that he will go up to Government about the return of the said Shaikh to his own town Shargah. The lon'^le 3ir Lionel 'laworth has since left for England, I and the notables of Shargah, the signatories of this letter, therefore solicit that r I.M*s Government may 'be graciously pleased to consider the case of Ahdur Hahman and we undertake tc Your Tlonour on 'behalf of the said Vbdur Behman to 'behave correctly and refrain from doing ^.ny unlawful act in the Oman Coast and to 'behave in a satisfactory manner. In conclusion we iuni]3ly solicit from your kindness the return of the said person for which we shall remain thankful to you and wish you success and prosperity. Signed Shaikh Sultan 'bin Sagar. ' Shaikh Said 'bin Maktum. ' Hashid 'bin Muhammad* Muhammad 'bin Thadam. ' Said hin Muhammad. 1 Ui 'bin Isa. „ -llminai ^ A Mulla 'bin '.hmed/^c his brother Muhammad 'bin hmed Mminai. •s . .. , ,Uo • c- // Residency Office, Aden, 5th January 1929. From, To. The Second Assistant Resident &amp; Protectorate Secretary, Aden. The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, /■ 6^ y I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter lJo.22nO of 24th ITovember 1928,regarding the health of Shaikh Abdur Rahman,now a political prisoner in Aden. I have seen Shaikh Abdur Rahman and have satisfied myself that Hie is generally in good health. He complains of dental trouble and has asked for a loan of Rs.150 to enable him to have his teefH seen to. Are yon willing: to concede to his request ? HIWHW Wf; foo R eosiv E0 \ I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Second Assistant Resident &amp; Protectorate Secretary. AG/-No. ^ 3 of 1929. British Residency Consulate -G -eneral, Bushire, the 19th January 1929. To Shaikh Sultan 'bin Sagar, Chief of Shargah. If ter Com oilments• XLtn referenoe to your letter dated the 25th Sliawv/al 1346 (16th A.pril 1928) and subsequent requests on teiialf of your father in law Shaikh Vbdur Behman hin Muhammad, who was deported to \den, I have the honour to inform you that the Government of India, have, on my recommendation, heen pleased to show their clemency, and iiave decided to reduce the term of 'banishment of Shaikh AMur Eehman hy one year, and allow him to return to his Home on the 16ta June 1929. 2. The Government of India, in conveying their orders on tlie subject, have asked me to warn you that this reduotion in punishment has 'been granted 'by them on the clistinct understanding, that you will l&gt;e held personally responsible for the good 'behaviour of Shaikh Vbdur Hehman so long as he resides within the confines of Sharqah territory, and that any attempt to intrigue, or again start an agitation against the Residency Agent will 'be 0 speoially severely dealt with. Usual Ending. H.B.M's Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf.''Jo. 3 0 of 1929. British -Residency ^ Consulate-General, Busliire, the 2 ^ J .nuary 1929. To Tne -Resiaenoy Igent Shargah. After Compliments. I enclose herewith letter No.23 dated the 19th January 1929 from the 'Ton'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the address of Sheikh Sultan 'hin Sa^ar 'Mef of Sharaah on the subject of the clemency shown 'by the Government of India in case of Ahdur Heiiman. Please deliver the letter after perusing and keeping a copy on your record. lis reply may 'be despatched as soon as received ty you. Major, Secretary to the Political Resident in tae Persian Gulf.Uo. 3 2 of 1929. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 26th January 1929, To The Residency Agent, Shargah, A • ^ • I am directed to forward copy of a letter I have received from the oecond Assistant resident, Aden, re^ardin^ the health of Shaikh Ahdur Rahman. un receipt, you will please convey contents to the Shaikh of Shar«;ah, and at the same time obtain from him and remit to me Rs.150/-, which I shall send to Aden to enable Shaikh Abdur Rahman to have his teeth seen to. U.S. ur Ma j o r Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian • % ♦ —- i i iN». 2.0 ef 1929. British aesidency &amp; Uorisulato-Grcneral. Bush ire, the 2i£ January 1929. 0-73 Froa The Secretary t@ the Hon'ble the -Political leaident in the Persian Gulf To Gir, The Second Assistant -Irsident &amp; Protectorate Secretary, Aden. In reply to your Mo. C.ll dated the 5th January 5 929, I shall 'be grateful if you will kindly advance lis 150/- to Shaikh \hdur lahman in order that his t^eth may be attended to. I urn recovering t in anount from his family and shall remit the roon^y to you in due course. I have the honour to he, Sir, lour most obedient servant, Fajor, ■ Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, ■. - . ... s3atad 8th Ramazan 1347 (18 -2 -29). To K.B. Haji Abdur Razzaa Mn Ismail. A • 0 • Please pay tlae sun of Rs.150/- to the ^on'tile the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. It is in payment of an amount paid hy the Shaikh of Shargah teing advance taken 'by Shaikh .Vbdur Rahman hin Muhammad from the Second Assistant to the Resident at Aden. I hope you will not fail. Sd. &amp; Sid. K.B. Isa hin Ahdul Latif. ■ * I ' V ^No.o_ From, THE RESIDENCY, Aden, February 1929 The Second Assistant Resident &amp; Protectorate Secretary. To. Sir, The Secretary to the Hon'ble The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRB. With reference to your letter No.204 dated the 26th January 1929, I have the honour to inform you that as desired a sum of Rs«150 has been advanced to Sheikh Abdur Rahman. -V 4 . {,3.0 D C I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Second Assistant Resident &amp; Protectorate Secretary. AG/- ! «HH v- Is &gt; ■No. of VJZ9. British. Kebidency and Consulate-General» Bug hire, the March 1 i&gt;'&lt;i J • 77 yrom The Secretary to the Hon f ble The Political Kesident, Persian Gulf, Bushire. To The Lecond '.ssiytant Resident and Pr tectorate Secretary, The Kesidendiyt 4.den. syl b Sir, I have tiie honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter No»C-lll dated the 14th February 1929 and t^ enclose, herev.ith, a Remittance Tranfer Receipt for Rs.150/- on account of advance , made to Sheikh Abdur Hainan. 1 have the hohour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, U Lt» Colonel, Secretary to the Political liesident,Persian Gulf. di(L m.£ ■ AT' -&gt;*0 No. of 1939. British 'Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the J* Maroh 1929. To The Hesidenoy Agent, Shar^ah. A/0 T .7ith reference to your letter No. 69 dated the 19th February 1929, the amount of Rs.150/- is paid 'by Khan Bahadur ^aji A hdur Hazzaq, in full payment of your draft drawn on him. Usual Ending. \ Lt. CJolonel, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gl-uir.-r -&gt; No.p- THE RESIDENCY, Aden, March 1929. From, The Second Assistant Resident &amp; Protectorate Secretary. To, Sir, , , P c The Secretary to the Hon'ble The Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bushire. . vll I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt ofUtu Remittance Transfer Receipt for Rs.150/- forv/arded with your letter No.545 dated the 3rd I!arch 1929. I have the honour to 'be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. -M Second Assistant Resident &amp; Protectorate Secretary. AG/- % jVLeus 1 j-&lt;^ ^ im. m|mNo. C.398 Resident, Bushire (rex^eated Goverrurjent of India, y. &amp; p. Dept. Government of Bombay Political Department. p. . . despatched OJ _ '^Feceivedr - received 9th junu i929 UHGEOT. Reference letter from Government of India, Foreign and Political Department dated lith December Return of shaikh Abaul Rehman of Shar ^ah from deportation in Afiien. May I have instructions as to e^cort^if any^ charge for passag^ and route. Mail leaves Aden on 16th June 1929 for Bombay and he could travel thereon. Residentfchbh felegram* Oode, jrom. Resident, Bushire. To Resident, Aden. Fo • 544 • Dated the 11th June 1929. Cr V v r Your telegram 0. 398 dated the 9th June 1929. AMur l-^ahman will kave to 'be sent via Bombay. Please arrange with Bora'bay Oovermnent for onward despatch 'by Gulf Slow mail to lu'bai. No escort seems necessary. Presume aovernment of India will issue orders re charge passage. Please telegraph date of his departure from Aden. Addressed Aden repeated Foreign Simla and Political Bombay. Till latter kindly telegraph date of departure from Bombajb. P 3silent•ufi Telegram (Code) • ,,,Resident, Men. PftiiticsuL Resident ,Bushire • jo Dated 8th June 1929. Reference letter from GoTernment of India hiei gn and Political Department dated 11th Deoemher 1,28 return of Shaikh AMur Rahman of Shargah from station in Men. Hay I hare instructions as to .Kort if any charges for passage and route. Kail ieares Men on 16th June for Bombay and he could travel thereon. Addressed Political Resident, Bushire repeated t0 Govenunent of India foreign and Political Department and GoTemment of Bombay Political Department. Post Copy srintendent, Office, Aden. ■ I. Telegram. Oode. ITrQiP- ** foreign and Political Department! Bimla.. (jo - Political Resident, Bushire. Ho♦ 114-N. Dated the 17th (received 18th) June 1929. Your telegram dated the 11th June No.544. ABDUB 22AHx HAHMAN with one servant sails Bombay ty Fall steamer leaving Aden 16th June. Foreign. Telegram. D.T. F toqi - Secretary, 'Bushire. To - 0. C. Henjam. No. Nil. Bated the 19th June 1929. Please deliver the following Arabic message to | the 'Residency Agent, Shargah 'by first opportunity. Begins AMur Rahman safara min Aden ila Bombay fi 16 June wa min Bombay sayati ila Dubai fil faltu. Resident. Ends. r ' Secretary.nriii Telegram. D,i. ^rorn - C.G.^enjain. to - resident, ^'uchire. -ordj. 40. Dated the 21st June 1929. .Keferenoe your 39/20 imoro^al^le tnat any H.r's Ships will 'be visiting ihargati till next Friday- P^oa^e 3a; r IT message should 'be sent 'by next mail whioh touches De'bal or despatched 'by dhow. a. a. Telegram. X. x . '^rorn - Secretary, Bushire. To - C.O. -'-enjam. No. JNil. Oated the 22nd June 1929. Tour 4C/21st. Send l)y next mail if unalle to send 'by one of H.H's Ships earlier. Secretary. - &gt;-•from. To Shaikli Sultan 'bin Saq.ax* Huler of Shargalu The Hon*1)16 Ool•,Barretts Politioal Resident and Consul General, in the Persian Gulf* 4th Muharram 1348 e9-6-29. \ Dated • After Compliments I hare the honour to acknowledge receipt a / of your esteemed letter dated .7th Shaahan 1347 (19th /t ff UrC+L J January 1929; whose contents^made me very smtsii glad # afc»4^-^ noted what you wrote ahout my oousin 4'bdur Eahman 'bin Muhammad namely that the Government of India have 'been pleased to permit him to depart from \denj([ and mako for his natiie country (6nthe 16 th Junevi am very grateful for what you have done and for all the good offices rendered in this case. I,and his family give you perfect assurance satisfactory that the said Shaikh (Ahdur Rahman) shall pursue a/policy and that he shall refrain from all sorts of intrigues or initiating disputes which might displease you.And should anything 'be done 'by him you can certainly loole upun me U.S., cif 23-6-29.Telegram -From To Repeated 1271-27 /6 /29 Code Political Department, iiornbay ^^litical .Resident, Uushire jrorei^n and Political Dept. Simla JMo. 4453-B Dated 26th (received 27th) June 1929. Keference Jieaident Aden's telejram C.4ao of 14th June. Shaikh Abdul Rahman with one servant arrived iloiabay 20th June passa-e to Dubai booked by s. s. 'Banlcura' sailing from ijombay 3rd July. - K33T13 - *** £/?■ - At/L z~&gt;U From. To The R.A..Shargah is informed as per telegram No. ^ O a Dated 29th June 1929» Secretary,Bushire. C?.C?»KenJam» Please deliTer the following to Besidency Agent,Shargah, 'begins:- AlDdur 'Rahman 'bin Muhammad will start for Dehai in tie 3.S.Bankura ,, on the 3rd July ends.* The AraMo text runs as under:- SATATAWAJJiH ABDUR RAHMAN BIN MUHAMMAD ILA DSBAI PI BANKUHA THALITH JULY Secretary.'o. IS'&amp;tf of 1929. British Keatdency &amp; Jonsulate-General, Buohlrfl, the \July 1929. The 'lon 'blc the Politioal Kesident in the Persian Gulf, ^ushlre* ta&gt; The foreign 3^oretary to the Oovernraent of Ind: A In the Foreign and Politioal Department Simla* ieduotlon of the period of deportation of Shaikh Abdur Rahcian from 4 to 3 years* Sir, I liave the honour to aoknowlndge the receipt s or your letter No, F-27S-K/27 dated the 11th Deceroher *28 and to report that Shaikh Sultan hin Gaqar Huler of ohargah has heen inforaed regarding the reduction in the tenn of baniahj-aent of hia cousin Ghaikh Abdur ^hman !)ln ^uhaaaad imd the terste on which this aas heen granted# ? * enclose ( copy of a letter from 3haikh Sultan da »ed the 4th A'uharraia 1543 corresponding to 9th June 1939, In which ho expresses his gratltute and his willingness to he responsible for the good behaviour of his cousin* I have the honour to he, sir. Tour noat obedient uervant, &gt; , Gulf# Political Tlesldent In the Persian St ^ '/'Bg From To1 'Vv, P, 138 H P. 87- P. 190 A Seoretary. I resubmit the letter Ho, 157 dated the 17th li&gt;rli 1^2 3 (attached) from the Residency Agent Shargah in connection with the auoject referred to oy nim in Shargah paragraph 2. viz request of the SheiJch of and the mother of Abdul Rahman for pardon to JLbdui Rahman who was banished to Aden for 4 years in August 1^6# He actually surrendered on the 16 th June and reached Bombay on xne H^rd August. So his term expires in The whoxe case is summarized in a note which is flagged by me in File 14/1^8. Aodui Rahman»s exile was approved by H.M.a. through the government of India who communicaxed their sanction in their telegram Ho. IU23 /S. dated tne 7tn June 1926# I have flagged all corresyondence with government of India in the file, but the note givea rail account of the case, Abdul Rahman is receiv- Rs. 200 Per mensem at Aden which tne Sheixh of Shargah pa^s. A warning was also issued to the Sheikh 01 Shargah In this ofiice isio, 434-3., dated the i^th OotoDer 1^6. 0a tne whole the Sheikh or Shargah has not given fuii satisfaction and the other day we also asxed him to give better help with regard to slave cases. IJowever in this case the aggrieved party is isa our Residency Agent at Shargah and he seems to oe in- olined to let the matter droy. m any case it cannot be done without reference to Government oi India, and there are not any strong reasons in, favour or the Sheith of Shargah. 10,5.2$. PR . (st L ia JZ CLr^JL**. ^ V Xc^ST^ee ^I 4 5, 52. 56. 4» 261. &lt;4* ^ I- ^ - ^ 76 t#——• ''*- ^ U' T&amp; t f i (L ire/- -L^^t -hH ■ i ' 45| Telegram No.C.398 dated the 8th June 1929 from the Resident, Aden. 46 | JL-r5r. &amp;SVy Submitted with pp. &lt;01 i']!' i'ull report of the case of deportation of Abdur Rahman to the Govt of India appears on the pages 116,117,118 etc» Abdur Rahman was conveyed from ^harqah to M u gcat and thence to B om bay by H. M.S. Lupin and from Bombay the Politicalj^Qinbay sent him to Aden on board mail steamer under surveillance. P.R. 1 3 recommendation to foreign for reduction of term of banishment is on page 260, and 262, Govt of India sanctioned reduction of one year and ordered t'o^t—that he i&gt;e.. Abdur Rahman m av be allowed to return to his home on thf? 1/?^ J^rie 1929. The Resident ,A rt en, now asks in his telegram p.u.c. ! (a) instructions as to escort. (b). charge for passage. (c). route. As regards (a), there may appear to be no kslels. necessity for escort as the man is being released from surveillance. Resident,A^en may put him on board to Bombay and Political Bombay put him on the slow mail tor?» 269. A g regards (b). Presumably the Govt of India will meet the passage charges from special funds,but if they are to be 'oaid by ^haikh A^dur K a hman t we can recover them through the ^haikh of ^harqah on receiving the bill® Ag regards (c) 0 '^here is no possibility of any direct ships, therefore he may be sent via Bombay# J- submit a draft reply to R e sident# for approval or modification® ~rr P.H. had sent letter HO % 23 dated the 19th January 1923 to the ^haikh of ^harqah,notifying to him the clemency shown by the Govt and terms thereof. It was forwarded to K.A.Sjiarqah under N0,30 dated 23rd January 1929. Kq reply appears on this file. T^e H.A# may be telegraphed to send a reply. # ^raft telegram is submitted 1c nigjcf- n/t K/t/K). ft. ^ ^ C&lt;oU^ D AJ^ 7*- ^ l-l tx &lt;£u V ' ; A 8/1 ^ ,, ! j, . CA I U &lt;S^ !&gt;^u telegram No♦C.420 dated the 14th June 1929 from the Resident, Men • 51, P.H. Itd/J • 0 • 15 / 6.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000fc_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/279</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000fc</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/279</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 14/198 Attempted murder by Abdur Rahman of Khan Bahadur Isa bin Abdul-Latif, Residency Agent, Sharjah.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1925/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-11T00:17:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (279 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file. At the front of the file is 'an index of salient papers' on the following topics.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation system in use is the sequence of numbers appearing in a circle in the top right hand corner of each folio beginning on the front cover and ending on the back cover. The file also bears a foliation system of uncircled numbers.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence concerning the attempted murder of Khan Bahadur Isa bin Abdul Latif, Residency Agent, Sharjah at the instigation of Abdur Rahman, headman of the village of al-Hira. Correspondence discusses how the Residency Agent acquired many enemies in the execution of his official duties in connection with the claims of British subjects against Arabs and Persians, and cases of gun-running, slavery and kidnapping. Letters discuss the murder attempt which resulted in the murder of the Residency Agent's cousin, and the decision to deport Abdur Rahman to Aden for four years. Correspondents include Francis Beville Prideaux, the Political Resident Persian Gulf; Political Agent, Muscat; Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf; Shaikh Sultan bin Saqar, Chief of Sharjah.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Shaikh of Al Ḩamrīyah</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Attempted murder</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000fc#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>