<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001ea_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T07:14:52.136Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">55/54 Telegram R. 27 To i'rom Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident t Bushire No. 183 •^ated 15th received 16th June 1955. Have informed Shaikh personally of contents of your telegrams 495 and 496 and he is very grateful for your advice. He has asked me to convey following reply to you (dictated by him). (1) He is quite positive that Saudi delegates are coming with instructions to accomplish nothing. ■ 1 . (2) His Majesty^ Government are well aware of the only two possible conditions acceptable to Kuwait (see paragraphs 8 and 9 of after note in Express Letter C/93 of April 8th) which conditions have already been given to Kuwait delegates with orders not to go beyong them. they will agree to Kuwaitis conditions in a day or two or conversely they can reject them. If their orders are to argue or pu^ forward other unacceptable demands then result will still be nil even if he postpones his departure for England for another week. In no case can he agree to any other terms than those mentioned and he has often told His Majesty's Government so. (4) He will be in Kuwait for 9 days with Saudi dele- ( gates and can listen^to all they have to say. This should be enough# (5) His own departure on June 24th need in no way (3) If Saudi honestly desire settlement curtailV curtail welcome and round of entertainments arranged for delegates who, if they wish, can continue talks under aegis of Abdullah Salim, who has also been given his orders. (6) In view of above though he would much like (mut) your wishes he deeply regrets he cannot postpone his departure now seeing he is ill and warned His i^esty^s Government of his intended departure on medical advice early last April* Furthermore his air, rail and sleeping car booking have all now been arranged. - POLITICAL -53/64 Telegram R. 27 From Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire. No. 184. Sated 16th received 17th June 1935. Saudi delegates arrived this morning with 70 attendants. Have had satisfactory preliminary interview. ^irst meeting tomorrow. POLITICAL -53/64 Telegram R. From Political Agent, Kuwait. To political Resident, Bushire. No .186, Dated 16th (received i7th) June 1935. / Saudi delegates have requested information as to telegraph facilities from here to Riyadh via 'Bahrain. They state that they were given to understand that tree telegrams could be sent 'by them. Have you any information i Last reference in my possession was Secretary oj - btate xor Inaia telegram No.1675 in reply to Jedda's No.117. C IH ■ &gt; /7&lt;9 /• X f fj - Political. lc' ^ ^ - ijl tik63/54 Telegram K.27 From To i-olitical Agent, Kuwait. Political Residentj Bushire . No.186. Dated 16th (received 17th) June 1336. ^ Your telegram of 16th June No•510. I, of course, see what you mean but unfortunately Shaikh's Arab point of view differs from our own in that with him so called honour comes before everything and tactical defeat or victory means nothing if major point at issue (relief from blockade) remains unaffected. Shaikh argued very heatedly with me yesterday to the effect that (a) neither Bin Saud nor he had sought conference. (b) Former because he naturally did not wish to abandon lucrative blockade and he because he knows that no amount of talking will force Bin Saud to do so if will is not there. (c) He has been told His Majesty's Government before that the only hope of success is in direct pressure on Bin Saud. If this course does not commend itself then much better to drop the whole question and conferences only bring insults and dishonour on him. about things. If there is slightest possible chance of any thing advantageous to Kuwait coming of conference Shaikh will discover this on first day and will go all out for immediate settlement remember(?ing) I shall iayself be present at meeting. p I personally do not think that we need be over anxious Political.X r*/&gt;'V CONFIDENTIAL, . No. C-175. r L 1 lie Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to Hon'bie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. 'I- C-hs Dated the 1 2 th J un /t l^feeference to previous correspondence- / f Express Letter No, G/187 dated the 2nd June from the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Doha. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Copy of telegram No, 156 from Political, Kuwait to British Minister, Jedda. 2. Copy of telegram No. 157 from Political Kuwait to British Minister, Jedda, Kuwait - Saudi Delegation,Telegram I.F.O. 1927 1 Fiom - Political, Kuwait, To - British Minister , Jedda. No. - 156, Dated - 28tli May 19 55, . 11 ^ , ■&gt;' % 1 ✓ Your telegram No. 130, I presume it is understood that even if Cable and Wireless Bahrain waive their Charges Saudi delegation will have to pay for their telegrams from here to Bahrain, -POLITICAL-Telegram I .jf.O. 1927, From - Political, Kuwait, To - British Minister, Jedda, No. - 157. Dated - E8th Ivlay 19 35. , ^, / / ^ I V / r Your telegram No. 130 and others n For information of Government of India and Political ResidenV. Having regard to my telegraph bill I can only send these on by post, -POLITICAL-I •Oh* 53/54 Telegram R« 27 From Political Resident, Bushire. To H.M^a Secretary of State for India&gt; London. Repeated H.M f s Minister, Jedda. Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Post copy to Political Agent, Kuwait. Ho. 519. Bated 17th June 1935. Following telegram No.184 dated 16th June from Political Agent, Kuwait, beginst i Saudidelegates arrived this morning with 70 attendants. Have had satisfactory preliminary interview# First meeting tomorrow# Ends# - RESIDENT -53/54 Telegram R # 27 From Political Resident t Buahire* To H.lt*s Secretary of State for India f London, Repeated H.M*s Minister, Jedda# Copy by post to GoTernment of India, Foreign and Political Department f Simla* ir»a 5f0 # Dated 17th June 1935* IMPORTANT. Following telegram received from Political .Agent, Kuwait, 185 June 16th, begins; Saudi delegates have requested information as to telegraph facilities from here to Riyadh via Bahrain, They state that they were given to understand that free telegrams could be sent by them# Have you any information ? Last refer ence in oy possession was Secretary of State for IndiaU telegram ITo# 1675 in reply to Jedda»s Bo, 117 # Ends* - RESIDENT -53/54 Telegram R.27 Prom Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Kuwait, Repeated Secretary of State for India, London# H.M*s Minister, Jedda* Poet copy to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla♦ ITo. 521. ^ated 17th June 1935* f- In my immediately preceding telegram, I repeated your t elegram 185, I have no further information. - RESIDEKT -53/54 Telegram £.27. prom Political Resident, Bushire . •po Political Agent, Kuwait. No .522. Dated, the 17th June 1935. My telegram of today No.521. I presume Shaikh is not permitting Saudi delegates to hold up conference until this question has oeen cleared u . Before they are in a position to refer anything there must be some days' conversation• 2, Please telegraph how first meeting went ot±. - Resident.CONFIDENTIAL. No, 415-S of 1935. j-yjy \ The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla* 2. The Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). \ \ British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. /? ^ Dated.., X7X)x June.. 1935, Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. !• Political Resident's tele gram Ko. 619, dated 17th June 1935. (To 2. only). 2. Pol it ical Resident's tele gram No. 520, dated 17th June 1935. 3. Political Resident's tele gram Ko. 521, dated 17th June 1935. (To 1. only). Subject. /4 po SAUDI - KUWAIT DISCUSSIOHS, I t'I iV lli No. 1274/228/11. HIS Majesty's Minister at Jedda presents his compliments to 'the Hon'ble the Political Resident in th .e Persian Gulf at Bu shire, and has the honour to transmit to him the nnder-mentioned documents. f 'llp British Legation.,.. .«I e ^USHfRE RESlr^ENrv*! '■ L - v' '.Z. I t ■ —mi t jj .-if RCr&gt;o t nr. i 193..5. Reference to previous correspondence : Jedda telegram No.123 of 15r5.35. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. TO; Saudi Minister for Foreign Protest to Saudi Qovemment for Affairs, despatch No.75 of the violation of Kuwait territory. 19.5.35. /CL* V p, ^ ki)-i £ is!^'). 3479 957^ (2)'~Ju r b 53/54 ^ele grem G-» r '' ! . C » }?rorri Tbliticnl Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, PuPhire* No, 189 Dated the 17th received the 18th «Tune 1935 • f * My telegvan 185, '^ol lowing from Dire ct or-General of Posts nnd ^ele^rap^is Bafthdsd , begins :- -p 'Your telegram of 17th June, Arrangements have been made to accept telegrams from ''audi Legation addressed to Saudi Government by wireless via v Basrah free of charge, Please inform Legation accordingly. Addressed to Political Agent Kuwait repeated to Posts Kuwait and Posts Basrah for information,' 'Hinds, h 6VW At POL IP I GAL nitnt ele gram G»^.G. jiVorn Political Resident, Bushlre. T C Secretary/ - of State for India, London. Heneated to H •It 1 s Minister, «Iedda» ^ ^ , (1 5 opt copy to Government of India,Simla, and Political Agent Kuwait.) No. 531. Dated the 18th ^une 1935. Kuv.ait Conferen ce . Director-Genera 1 of ^osts and Telegraphs Iraq has asked Political Agent Kuwait to inform Saudi delegation -hat ariengemente have 'been made to accept their telegrams addressed to Saudi Govern ment by wireless via Basrah free of charge. BPITCOHSUL llfl £/■53/54 E 27 Political Agent, Ku-svai lolitical Heaident, Bushire. Telegram From To Ho o 1-1 Dated 18th received 19th June 1935. A K \r w Your tele gram lh* 522 first paragraph see my telegram lTo« 189 second paragraph. First day's meeting disappointing. Tone and method of speech of Saudi delegates savoured a very much of^dictator and gave considerable offence. To use their own vcrds: ,, We have nothing to offer. blockade suits us as we have directed all Kuwai t trade to our par ts. If Kuwai t makes it worth while and has practical offers to make we will talk busi- -ness. Kuwait is like a man in prison who wants to get out. Offer enough and we will let him go. 11 Kuwait delegates in reply propounded the system of customs posts ard manifests. Saudi delegates opined that Bin Saud would never agree on the grounds of expense but if offer was made in writing they would refer it telegraphically. 'ihis was done, I shall post you full particulars of daily talks. Poli tic al 453/54 VO Telegram K.27 Froui Political Residents Bushire. To H.M's Secretary of State for India, London# Repeated ±o Government of india, Foreign and Political Depar tment, Simla. s Charge d*Affaires, jedda. Copy by post Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 5 35 Dated 19th June 1935. Kuwait Conference. Political Agent, Kuwait, telegraphs that first meeting disappointing,tone of Saudi delegates being dictatorial and offensive. In their own yd rds Kuwait is like a man in prison who wants to get out. Offer enough ani we will let him go H . 2. Kuwait delegates propounded system of customs posts and manifests v/hich Saudi * s are referring telegraphically to their Government. Re sident. ( * 5 O53/54 Telegram R 27 From Political He si dent, Bu shire. To Political Agent, Kuwait* Ho. 536 Dated 19th June 1936 4 Your telegram of 18 th June, Ho. 191. I will keep His Majesty^ Government, Government of India and Jedda informed of progress as received in your telegraphic reports# Re sident.53/54 Telegram R. 27 From To Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait♦ No. 538. Bated 20th June 1935. IMPORTANT. I .V / U v / ^ Your telegram of June l9tli, 192# This is exactly the sort of delay I foresaw when I sent my telegram of June 15th No. 510. please approach Shaikh RESIDENT63/64 lp , Telegram R. -T'. From x-olitical Agent, Kuwait. rp 0 Political Resident, Bushire . Ho.197. Dated 20th (received 21st) June -95L. yf*- My tele^rairi 0.192. ITo meeting .Wednesday and Saudi delegates again as on Tuesday sent word from their house that they could hold no xurx.ne comraunicatioii with Kuwait delegates until they received mstruo- tions from King. Conduct of delegates ap. ears no Lie oad and quite unjustified seeing that at only meeting so far held CJune 7tii) when Kuwait delegates propounded system of customs x osts auu manifests Saudi delegates refused to discuss details and just left meeting. They could easily now exchange views as to these pending a reply from King. JTom their rude and unaccommodating attitude (obviously inspired) one cannot out iorm tne opiniun that the Saudi delegates are acting the i-art of men engage^ in an unpalatable task under pressure ana are out to make tne conference fail from the start. Shaikh wnom 1 saw las^ ni^ht asked if his orophecy as to outcome of conference, was not cornin^ out exactly true and ho.ed that I would bear witness oj . fact to His ICajesty's Government. Total number ox Saudi pafuy witn la^e arrivals now 83. - political.03/54 telegram R, 27 From Political Resident, Buehire, To Political Agent, Kuwait. Fo&lt;, 540 Dated 21st June 1935. | ^ tsf IMPORTAKT. I y Your telegram Ko. 197 # Conduct of Saudi delegates does not appear to me at all H odd n but exactly what I foresaw tney would do and which I think you (in this connection see first sentence of paragraph 2 of your telegram 186 of 16tn June) and Shaikh might have expected. Presumably delegates know that Shaikh proposes to leave on 24th June and are there fore deliberately holding up conference teo that Ibn Saud can tell (a) The Arab world that H friend Ahmad ranaway from the conference* (b) Hie Majesty's Government that Shaikh by his precipitated departure rendered conference abortive. ^ e&amp;se approach Shaikh bring these considerations onee mere to his notice and do your utmost to persuade him to extend time of conference. I quite agree that time limit should be set tut original week fixed by Shaikh is obviously far too short. I suggest another fortnight from 24th June# So I am emphasising Saudi delegates attitude to iiis Majesty 's Government pointing out that party has now arisen to 83 instead of the 50 promised# - RESIEEKT -Telegram From To Repeated to ■( qA&gt; Copy by poat No# 542 Dated Slat June 1935. R.27 Political Reaident, Buahlre# a Secretary of State for India, London. Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla# H.M'a Charge d*Affaire a, Jedda* Political Agent, Kuwait* lay telegram Uo. 535 of I9tli June. Kuwait Conference. Political Agent, Kuwait, telegrapha that though Saudi delegate a could aave time by exchanging viewa on detaila of Kuwait propoaala pending reply from King they refuae to do ao. I truat that Charge d f Affairea, Jedda, will be able to expedite reply. 2. Saudi party haa now reached 83 inatead of the 50 promiaed. Resident. Copy aent to Kuwait under P.L.No.429»S of 2lat June 1935. ivk55/83, 53/54 53/88 Telegram xx rrom H.M 1 s Ambassador, Bagdad. To H.M's Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London, Ho, 169« Repeated Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla, Ho, 23. political Kesident, Bushire, Bated and received 22nd June 1935, lo. 16# r I *., % * ^ Ky telegram 166. Shaikh of Kuwait arrives here June 24th and le&amp;vee for London June 28th, His presence for four days in Bagdad m^y be very embarrassing unless I am authorised to inform Tree Government that he 1ms rejected conference scheme and that they are now free to t eke legitimate unilateral measures. J shpll be grategul therefore for instructions if possible by -ondey. • CLERIUK^H - Repeated to Political Agait, Kuwait, under Bushire telegran Ko. 652, dated 2Srd June 1935#53/54 Telegram « 27 From Political A^ent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire No. 203 2. Dated and received 2Md June 1935 My telegram No» 200* Results of to-day^ meeting as follows: Saudi delegates enquired on behalf of King whether in the event of cuotoms posts and manifest system being introduced (a) Kuwait Government would give written guarantee to fc&gt;audi Government that all smuggling from Kuwait to liejd would cease for good and all (b) whether His Majesty's Government would herself gi^e this guarantee if Kuwait objected to do so. Kuwait delegates at once pointed out utter impossibility of giving such guarantee though H they are prepared to undertake to do their best to stop smugg- -ling'. As regards (b) I replied that His Majesty's Government could naturally not give guarantee ts. seeing that matter was once between Kuwait and Bin Saud. Delegates promised to convey Kuwait reply to King. Pol it ical53/54, 53/86 and 53/83 Telegram ti 27 From Political Agent, Kuwai t. To Political Resident, jiushire* Ho. 204 Dated 22nd received 23rd June 1935. ^ . ,, - Your telegram Uo# 540» i&gt;aw Shaildi to-day. He again emphasised that he had definitely come to the conclusion that Ibn Saud intended conference to fail but to forestall possi- -bility of his trying to fasten the blarce on KUTsait later he had (a) called officially on Saudi delegates yesterday and informed them hat he was leaving for iiondon on Monday in accordance with programme arranged three months ago ; that this need not affect conference now going on in the least as Shaikh Abdullah Salim had been appointed to act as fiuler with fullest powers. That he hoped discussions would be in friendly spirit and brought to a successful concimsion. That they were welcome to stay on in Kuwait for as long as necessary. (b) Sent telegram to .Bin Saud repeating what he told delegates and expressing hope that latter would be allowed to continue their labours in Kuwait. Politicaly 53 /63, 53/54, 5V88. Telegram XX. ^vom secretary of State for Indiat London. i' 0 Political He si dent, au shire, ^o. 1953 Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait^ m* 1934. covernment of India, Simla, lo. 1935. H.M f s# Aisbasaador, iiaghdad, m* 1936. Dated 22nd received 23rd June 1935# mmnjATE. ^ 1 Your Express letter of Z&amp;vtxxx. 2nd June arid your telegram of i5th June No. 512. Kuwait Srauggling. I have gone into the question again in the light of the Shaikh's attitude and should be ^lad if you would take into account the following consider a tionsi (a) we do not admit validity of Shai ii's arguments as regards Director of Customs and he a] pears to confuse smuggling with legitimate trade. Moreover ( b) while Shaikh rejects H .IT # s. Government's strong advice and says that he is prepared to face blockade by Iraq he somewhat inconsistently looks to H.H's. Governaent to limit blockade in respect of certain matters i.e. Kuwait date produce in Iraq,and water supply# though presumably stricJt blockade contemplated by Iraq Government primarily means prohibition of imports from Kuwait they have also contemplated cutting off of Kuwait water supply ( see .baghdad telegram of 19th February, jso. 47 ) His Majesty's Govern*. ' / K f are ^ Sp&gt; -ment wwHtstxJae unable to guarantee that such a r step would be held to exceed Iraq Government's le^al rights, though on groin-de of humanity alone we should of course seek to dissuade them from takingit# In any case prospect of Iraq seeking to apply such extreme laeaaures of coercion seemst apart froxo other considerationSf to make it impossible for K .r's. Government to wash their h^nds of dispute and Shaikh's request that we should secure imuu^ity of water supply and date produce in Iraq affords ^ood grounds for urging him afresh to reconsider his intransi^ance. prospect moreover that H.M f »• Ooveruaent could, if an extreme strain is .1 laced on Kuwait - Iraq relations, succeed is obtaining satisfaction over ownership of date gardens would almost vanish* $hi|.e this and smuggling problems are distinct in theory Iraq Government are unlikely to keep/ them separate in practice and finally failure over date gardens would both be expensive to H. •s* Goverament and damaging to them in the Persian uulf • s» Government have in all discussions ^iven full weight to the argitss^nts advanced by you and the (Government of India against direct inter* -vention* liey quite agree that it may be possible to let matters take their course for some little time* But they remain of opinion that intervention will be necessary sooner or later if ( as is essential ) they are to maintain their control of Kuwait's relations with her neighbours and avoid the odium of failure to protect her, which would inevitably fall back on H.M , s* rovernment dispite any disclaimer of res- •ponsibility* It has been for this reason that they have been so anxious to ( find an] equitable via media * {*)(e) If Iraq is now allowed to apply sanctions it will be qiiite iiapossible in practice for His Majesty^ Goverment to ensure that these are kept within legitimate limits or to secure any real satisfaction from Iraq if they are not. That cannot fail to do us damage locally* (f) Moreover if sanctions are sufficiently effective to make Shaikh sue for terms there can be no question that terms asked by Iraq will be far more severe than at present. (g) You will, apart from this, appreciate that if serious situation develops later and Shaikh then asks for our support His Majesty's Government might well be reluctant to risk grave breach with Iraq in which their interests are so great merely In order to extricate Shaikh from difficulty of his own making which can be avoided by him adopting a less intransi- geant attitude now# 3# If in the light of above and in particular paragraph 2 (b) you are prepared to approach Shaikh further we should welcome it and trust you will do all in your power to make him see reason# ,, ^ - 4# Since above was written 1 have seen Bagdad telegram dated the 22nd June fio •169 to Foreign Office# If Shaikh really proposes to leave for Bagdad 24th June notwithstanding advice to the contrary which you instruct ed Political Agent to give him in paragraph 3 of your telegram dated 13th June No.496 and if you decide that he should be i ke further attempt doubt consider to /to dissuade him from going to Bagdad at once or if this fails accompany him to Bagdad and to make further appeal to him before any communication is made to Iraq Government by Clark Kerr» -Secretary of State for India•tih'v, n/f} t yj/gs- » ' Telegram R 27 ^ ron3 Political Agent, Kuwait# T o Poli tical Re aL dent, i3ushire» Ho. 207 Dated and received 23rd June 1935. Immedi ate. For information. Bin 3aud has &lt; telegraphed Shailch wishing hits god speed and speedy return from London in best of health. Shaikh telegraphed King of Iraq privately yesterday informing him of his arrival at Baghdad June 24 th. Political53/83, 53/64 It 53/88 -j telegram R. 27 From Political Resident, Bashire. To Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated to Ambassador, Bagdad, Ciovernnent of India, Foreign and Politic el Department, Simla. UNHDMESRED. Dated 24th June 1935. IMPORTANT. nmkii - • KAy smctGLim Following is repetition of my immediate telegram of 23rd ^une So#564 to Political Agent % Kuwait 9 beginst Here insert Uxt of telegram Mo.5d4 0 Snds. - H1SID2SNT, Telegram R. 27 ^ r&lt;aal Political Res id en t # Bushire# Political Agent, Kuwait# OTHDMHSRED. Bated 24th June 1935. I have repeated to India Office, Ambassador, Bagdad and Gorernment of India my telegram of 23rd June Ho, 554 to you. - RESIDSHT -53/54 lj V Tele gram R 27 H.M , b Charge d'Affairest Jedda# To H.M*e Secretary of State fbr Foreign Affairs, London. Uo« 131 Repeated to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla* No* 82 Political Heeident, -tfushire. iJo« 151 Political Agent, Kuwait# Ho. 152 Bated24th received 25th June 1935* y Political '^esident t s telegram to India Office, Ho. 542. In the course of conversation with Ministry for foreign Affairs (?over) delay# I expressed personal hope that reply if not already sent would be expedi ted. / Charge d 1 Affaires.Telegram R.27# prom Political Resident, BusMre To Secretary of State for India f London* Repeated GiiTernment of India, Simla. H.M.Charge d*Affaires, Jedda. H o *566# Dated tiie 25tli June 1935« F - A My telegram of 21st June Ko # 542» V Following telegram received from Political Agent Kuwait 22nd June No.203 beginst M Resulta of King'. Ends. i r - Resident. (Copy forwarded to P.A.Kuwait under P.L. Ho.442-S of 25/6/35).u ^ Telegram R.27. jTom Political Resident, ^xshire. To Secretarj of State for India, London. Repeated Government of India, Simla. H.M.*8 Charge d 1 Affaires, Jedda. Copy by post to Political Agent, Kuwait. Uo. 56*? . Dated the 26th June 1935 # KUWAIT CONPERIHCE. Shaikh Itft Kuwait 24th June, having appointed Shaikh Abdullah Salim to act as Ruler with full powers. Before departure he informed Saudi delegates that they were welcome to stay as long as was necessary and telegraphed Ibn Saud to same effect. - Resident. (Copy forwarded to P.A.Kuwait No.442«S of 25/6/35). under P.L.53/54 Telegram R# 2? From Political Agent, Kuwaiti Political Resident, Bushire* 211 mted 25th receired 26th June 1935« My telegram 203• /] '-i Following are results of meeting June 24th® Senior Saudi delegate confirmed in more clear language (a) That only possible condition under which Saudi CrOTernment would adopt customs and man If est system was for Kuwait to guarantee that not eren a single smuggler from Kuwait would cross the border« (b) That in actual practice Saudi Crorernment would probably gire Kuwait three chances* For first, second and third offence, smuggled goods would be confiscated and Kuwait would be asked to pay duty# For fourth offence, even if it were committed by one man, Saudi ^orernment would cancel agreemento confirmed that they could only continue further negotiate ions on abore basis while Kuwait delegates replied that they could only promise to do their best to stop smuggling and hoped this would satisfy* In subseqrat letter Saudi delegates • POLITICAL&gt;3 53/54 f I v f jry f Telegram R. 27 J'rom Political Resident, Bushire # To H.M 1 s Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Government of India, Foreign and Political department, Simla. H.K 1 s Minister, Jedda. Ho. 574 Dated 26th June 1935. KUWAIT COITPEREHCE. My telegram of 25th June, 566. Following telegram received from Political Agent, Kuwait No. 211 of June 25th, beginsi (Here insert text of telegram 211 )• - RESIDENT -52/54 Tel egran From To Repeated to XX. Political He si dent, i5u shire* s Secretary of State for India, London# Government of India, foreign and Political Department, Simla* H.M t 8 Charge d 1 Affaires, Jedda* Political Agent, Kuwait. Kb* 575 Dated 26th June 1935* ISy immediately preceding t elegram in / which I repeated Political Agent, Kuwaiti telegrani lto*211« Saudi conditions are obviously absurd and designed to render conference abortive* »o Govern- -ment in the world can guarantee that not a single smuggler shall cross a foreign frontier* 3* I venture to suggest that His MaJesty^s Government should point this out to Saudi Government* 4* Has not psychological moment also arrived for some such message to aaudi Government as suggested in paragraph 2 cf my telegram no* '.1/176 of 8th June ? z' r Resident* V_/c% / j' V No. 1381/226/63. V- pH ! HIS Majesty's Minister at Jedda presents his compliments to the Hon''ble the Political resident in t le Persian Gulf at Bushire, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British..JA&amp;^.t'X.QTX9. J.e.d.dft». j o' £ 193..5. Reference to previous correspondeU 'Ce : Jedda telegram No.134 of 30.5.35i Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. oreign Office, despatch No. of 1.6.35. + enclosures. Violation of Kuwait territory. 3479 957^ (2)- ft -ir- *4. S3/&gt; mfideatial . GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Depaetment. EXPRESS LETTER V N. B.—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent hijpost to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the id ires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, ivith the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had he en so despatched.] From To PoUUc.!, *,1.. ^^ Political Resident, Bushire.' ■ ■ BUSHIRE RESIDENCY. Ko...6fU? Date.. Wo. C-19O|:3' ' ' Bated : ' • 7935 . n Baudi-Kuwai B1 oc kade^^onference'■ In continuation of my telegram No. 184r''dated the leth June 19S5, I beg to report that the Saudi delegation oonsising of (a) Khalid ibn al V/alid. (b) Hamd al Sulaiman, (c) Abdulla al Qussibi» arrived at Kuwait in the early morning of 16th June from Hoffuf,, 2. The party came in seven lorries and six touring cars and were accompanied by 70 attendants (including drivers, servants and guards), 3. The delegates reported that they lost their way the 2nd day out of Hoffuf, and narrowly escaped disaster and death from thirst owing to not being able to find water, which they had counted on. They also ran short of petrol when they at last reached Jarriya Ilya, and two single lorries had to go ahead and bring back petrol from Kuwait to enable the main body to come on. That made them a whole 24 hours late in Kuwait.4. The losing of their way and the ridiculous decision to send lorries with the party, reflects very badly on the baudi Governinent T s 'bundobast', for lorries are the worst possible means of motor conveyance, once suni^er has se ^ in and drii d sand has to be negotiated in the desert. One can only say that 1 ve»-4 we in Kuwait would have put up a much better show, the positions been reversed. 5 # On arrival in Kuwait the delegates were gi/en reiresmtients and made comfortable, after which they called on His Excellency the Shaikh, and Khalid ibn al ./alid presented a peisonal letter from H«M« King Abdul Aziz. 6. After leaving the Shaikh's presence they called on me, and similarly handed to me a short personal letter from the King, which expressed the hope that the eiforts of the aule^ates would be crowned with success and trusting that I • ou-d give them my 'full support, 7, Khalid ibn al .&lt;alid appeared to be the leader of the party, and directed the conversations, as i- he had been instructed beforehand to adopt that role. In appearance he resembled a thick set German, being very fair with a small blond beard. He described himself to me as a iripolitan, and said that he had served a period of five years detention in Rome for his desert activities against Italy, and that - or later rebellion in the hinterland of Tripoli, had nanotfl^ escaped being sent to Italy once again when he finally had to take refuge in Egypt. It was Zaghlul Pasha who had saved him. His going to the Hejaz and subsequently to Bin Saud*s Court was recent history, for he had only been there five years. Though he expressed admiration f cr the Italian arts and nobility he conveyed the impression that he was anti European, and especially anti Latin races of Europe. He- 3- ivO He volunteered the information that he spoke French and Italian fluently, and said that he had been brought up in Turkey and knew my grahdfather there, 8. Neither Hamad al Sulaiman nor Abdulla al Qusaibi impressed me much, but one gathered that they both had quite a large store of Nejdi rudeness and obstinacy in their make up. 9. On the whole the composition of the party struck me fairly favourably, though the'Sffendi' characteristics of their leader and his frequest use of French words, during the subsequent discussions with the mors untutored Kuwait delegates, savoured of a studied desire to show his superiority and to patronize them - It was resented accordingly# 10» The first discussion took place at 8 A # M, on 17th June, Kuwait being represented by the following delegates 'The latter re- (a) Ahmad al Hamaithi. placed Jasim al , (b) Mohamed ibn Thunaiyan. Budai, who died (c) Khalid al i^aid al ^lialid# suddenly the day she delegates arrived. I adopted the role of looker on or 'nathir' on behalf of H.M. Government. 11. A note on the first and subsequent discussions is submitted with this. Lieut-Colonel, Political ^gent, Kuwait.NOTE ON TH.J DISCUSSIONS BST./JEN THi biOJDI M*!) THE KIJ-/AIT REPRESENTATIVES, AS THSY TOOK PLixGE EACH DivY. (The notes were written up immediately after each meeting, as the Saudi delegates showed nervousness at my taking notes at the meeting itself)* FI-^T DAY (IvilvxONLAY 17th JUIfE) . (a) Proceedings lasted from 8 A.M. to 9,20 -ii.LA and were opened by a brief speech by the Political Agent wishing both parties success in their deliberation and asking G-od to bless their efforts. (b) ICrialid ibn al ialid then opened the ball on behalf of the Saudi Governraent by a long winded and somewhat offensive speech, in which he said that the ICing had instructed him to say that he bad no personal enmity for Kuwait; that he had sent him and his friends to see whether a 'modus Vivendi' could be c aae to, over the Blockade question: That they, the Saudi delegates, would listen to anything reasonable the Kuwaitis had to say, but frcm the first he must warn them that 'Business was business, that sentiment would not be allowed to play any part in the proceedings': That he could tell them from the beginning, that Bin Saud, his master would agree to no settlement unless he bene fited equally with ICuwait: That the Saudi Government was a poor one and had to fight all the time to find means of getting revenue, so that no proposals of the Kuwait delegates would be acceptable or even be con sideied unless they could show, some sort of finan cial advantage to Saudi Arabia. That the King had blockaded Kuwait,with the delibe rate intention of diverting trade to his own ports - That he had succeeded in this,and had now got that trade and that there fore, if it pleased him to allow Kuwait to get'a little bit' of it back,it must be on 'terms'; That theThat the Saudi Government did not, in any way, want to raise the blockade and give anything bacic to ICuv/ a it, but out of friendship for the British Government, the King was willing to discuss matters always provided that Kuwait would make a 'worth while' offer. That first and foremost therefore and before anjfc discussions or arguments could be listened to, the Kuwait delegates must state in 'die Q - l a a.j to him, exactly what they were prepared to concede by wey of advantage to Bin Saud, and exactly what their proposals werei This would be telegraphed to the King,and his orders taken. But the terms must be'concrete', and of an entirely 'positive' nature. Kamad bin SulaiLian followed by half a dozen words in which he rudely reminded the Kuwait delegates that Kuwait was in the position of a person in prison, who was anxious to get out J ine^ jailox ..as o. man open to reason, and awaited an offer from the prisoner '* If this was goou he would open the prison gates. Note by the writer . To my mind speeches (b) and (c) above were gratuitously insulting, and the Kuwait delegates, I qqijjj _(3 see, were deeply hurt. 1 liao. to ii-uervene t»actxully to prevent hot replies. (d) Abdulla al Qusaibi passed no remarks. ( e ) ichalid al Zaid al Khalid on behalf of the ivuwait delegates then replied briefly, to the effect that he was sorry that the Saudi delegates had chosen to adopt the role of 'parlimentaires' so to speak from a victorious besieging force to a beleaguered city. That at one moment they had said that their King was out to heal the wounds of the past, end bore no ill will He had used he French quivalents or concretewill 'to KiiwQ.it; j so. d 'tliGii Q-t; 'til© iigxo, ■■ delegates) talked about Kuwait 'being in trie position Ox a prisoner, wlio if he only would o ^ a liigh enough bribe3 would 'be allowed out, Thef Kuwait, seeing that she was the aggrieve a par^ , had really little to offer. All she wanted was an honest outlet for her trade with ^asim and the Interior, and wished to do business in honest an^ straightforward manner. That 311100 the CMef spolcesma of tHe Saudi Govornmaat had invited them to say what Kuwait was prepared to offer - his reply was G-ov emment (i) To pay full baudi/Customs on all merchandise going from Kuwait into oaudi ^ra-ia. (ii) To pay such duty at one or itiore GusoorixS x-osts which should be established on the ^audi side of the frontier. (iii) To allow no caravans from Nejd towns to leave Kuwait without proper manifests taken in triplicate - one to be given ^o the leader of the caravan, the other sent to the Saudi Govern ment through Al Nafisi and the third to remain with the Kuwait Government. i^iv) Nejd Bedouin to be allowed to make minor purchases for their own every day needs free of interference, but should they desire to take goods out of Kuwait above a certain quantity (this to be fixed after discussion) then they should likewise be given manifests. Mote . No mention was made at this stage of the Shaikh of Kuwait's second alternative proposal viz. that he should act as Bin Saud's Customs officer. (f) The Saudi delegates asked that the above proposal oe ^ivengiven in vvriting the same evening, if possible, and they would telegraph it to the ^-ing, (g) The xjjsmit delegates agreed,subieot to the shaikh's approval. (h) 1 here remarked that, speaking quite unofxiciany, I thought that the Km. ait terms appeared reasonable,and that from my personal knov;ledge of the hinterland, the placing of one Customs Post at 'Safa 1 or four posts at the wells of Hafar, bafa, Jarriya and Nta,would effec tually close any gaps, and be a complete success. To this the leader of the Saudi Delegation smilingly replied that he knew nothing at all of the terrain of the Kuwait frontier, but that he definitely could say that the idea of Customs Posts would certainly not meet with the King's approval, seeing that tiiey would be costly. Nevertheless if the Kuwait delegates put the proposal in writing, he would refer it to His kajesty. I pointed out that Bin Saud was already spending money on frontier preventive force of 30 men, these would still be necessary under the Customs Posts and manifest System. All that would be required extra, would be four to six Customs clerks, to take over the Customs duty when paid, (i) The Kuwait delegates then tried to initiate an open dis cussion as to the merits of the Lanifest System and to explain details of how it would work etc. But the leader of the Saudi Delegation refused to talk or discuss the matter at all. He said that until he referred Kuwaiti suggestion to the King discussion was a pure waste of time. He then got up with his friends and left the meeting. The day's proceedings then ended. (j) Before adjourning the leader of the Saudi delegation made the cool request that I should take over and pay for all their telegrams to Riath. I declined politely. I agreed however to wire the Director G-eneral Posts and Tele graphs, Baghdad and ask if IRK^ and the Saudi Govt, had come to any arrangement on the question of telegrams going free from Kuwait to the King regarding the Conference, Notehv the writer , (i) The impressions left on me at the close of the first day's proceedings were the reverse of favourable. The whole tone of the baudl delegates was too haughty and uncompromising. The spirit of good will conspiouous by its absence. (ii) The superior airs of t.lie Saudi aele^cu.es 1 leader (almost invariably adopted, I regret to say, by oauai officials) created a bad impression and hazarding a guess, I should say, was deliberately done to irritate* (ili) The head of the delegation made it clear that he believed the King would rejeet the Gustoms -/osts and Manifest System, on the lame excuse that it would cost too much money, (iv) The continual hints of 'make it worth our while financially and we will t^e business', savoured far too much of 'give us a good subsidy, and we will open the Kuwait frontier'. Perhaps this is what the bauoi dele gation is working up for. If so,it is the same pjc^Oosl that Bin Saud himself put forward several years ago, and which was reject ed. (v) The Saudi delegation would appear to possess no authority to do anything on their own, and it looks as if they will refer everything ^o the • AffTJaiTOQN 0^ FI^uT D..Y i 17t h June). (i) I received a telegram frcm the Director General Posts and Telegraphs Baghdad, that the Saudi delegates could send telegrams to do with Gonference fxee. - u^l^ informed them to this effect, (ii) The Kuwait delegates with the Shaikh^s approval addressed a very friendly and polite letter to the ^audi delegates (copy '/seen by me/ in wnich a- ter reca-iliiig -11 the past friendly relations between the house of Saud and rc* the house of the Sabah^ stated that Kuwait's sole desire was to(iii) was to live at peace with, the present a audi Gov erixieit, and to trade honestly with her, and that she proposed posts and Manifest system (detailed in para (e)(i)(ii)(iii) above, as the only possible way out of the difficulty - II in or diffi culties could be cons iclered on their ruerits j and reserved for further discussion, {iii) The Saudi delegates at once telegraphed to the King for orders, S-^OOND l/.-'J j ISth JUl..jj]) . The Kuwait dele^ites and I attended at the Shaikh's town office at 8 a.nu to continue discussions. This had been arranged between us prior to the break up of the meeting of the previous day. The Saudi delegates however did not turn up, but sent a message to say that as they had nothing to discuss pending receipt of the King's reply to liieir telegram, they did not propose attending the meeting. This rudeness was rather typical and shocked the polite not a little, I incidentally was told that the Shaikh * s daily menu for the Saudi delegates and party was six sheep a day and two bags of rice. This apart from a host of good things such as fruits and sweetmeats (An easy Rs # 150/- a day), THIRD 19th JTJIIE) , (i) I was ready at 8 A.Mo as usual to attaid the Conference, but received early notice from the Shaikh's Secretary, that the Saudi Delagation had sent word that they could discuss nothing and attend no further meetings pending orders from the King, (ii) In the evening I saw the Shaikh while playing tennis - He anilingly asked what I thought of the Saudi wpAd (delegation) and their methods at the first meeting.l 0 I (iii) I replied cautiously that 1 hoped still that all would be right. (iv) He laughingly continued rt Ncw you have seen them and the big talk they use, perhaps you and your Government will now see that sometimes Shaikh Ahmad, their small friend ' and ally is right # I have already prophesied and told you many times that Bin Saud means to do absolutely nothing, end that he has merely sent his delegaton after having practically, received orders to do so from His Majesty's Government. Having! gone so far he will do no more, but will now work for a good excuse or 'hujja' to bring about a failure of the conferenceo Believe me nothing we offer will be acceptable, except the paymait of an enormous subsidy, or the surrender of Kuwait.' (v) The Shaikh then went on to say that certain 'stragglers' had now come in from Jarriya, and that the numbers of tlie Saudi delegation had reached a total of 85 persons - The feeding of these was a difficult business and cost money, but as it apparently pleased His liajesty's Government that the delegates were in Kuwait, he was not going to complain. He wondered (said laughingly) whether it would ever strike Hi s Majesty *s Government to reimburse him for these entertainment expenses, which opined would A not fall far short of Rs. 10,000/-. (vi) For my own viev/s see my telegram No. 197 of 20th June 1935. n (Further Notes by Next Mail).CONFIDENTIAL. Air N ().455-S of 1935. 0)^ / The Hon'ble the Political Resident pliments to Persian Gulf presents his cora- 1. His Majesty^ Secretary of Statefor India, London • 2. His Majesty's Charge d*Affaires, British Legation, Jedda• 3. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the unaeSnentioned docu ment (s). British Consulate-Greneral, BUSHIRB. 0 k Dated 28th Jime 1936 Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Express Letter No.C-190 of 18th June 1936 from the Political Agent, Kuwait, with enclosure. Subject. / Saudi-Kuwait Blockade Conference• Copy forwarded, with cbmpliments, to the Political Agent, Kuwait, fjor information.53/54 Telegram R#27« Fron) Political AgQ^it, Ku-wait* To Political Resident, Bushire. 13b.2l8. Dated the 28th (received 29th) June 1935. My telegram ^o*211* As result of further exchange of letters in which Kuwait dele^tes asked that their point of view regarding impossibility of giving 'guarantee 11 should be fully explained to King as well as their willingness to give instead an under taking on Kuwait # s honour to do its best to stop smuggling Saudi delegates this morning called meeting and said that King has telegraphed them that unless Kuwait Government forthwith agreed to give 'guarantee* 1 asked for they should close dis cissions and return to jJiejd# They apologetically sa^d tnat they could do no more as they had from the first no authoriuy to go beyond King»s orders. Kuwait delegates explained with regret that they could go no further than they had gone: S a udi delegates then closed down negotiations andlueeting broke up in atmosphere of greater friendliness and good feeling than had hitherto been manifested. Sg^udi delegates probably leave Kuwait Sunday. - Political. (Repeated to India Office, under this office telegram ^0.686 of 29/6/36). (1 N .0 53/64 / Telegram xx From Political Resident, Bushire. To Secretary of State for India, London* Repeated Government of India, Simla. H.M.*8 Charge d f Affaires, Jedda. Political Agent, Kuwait. No.686. Dated the 29th June 1935» IMPORTANT. /(■ Kuwait telegram of 28th June No.218 repeated in my immediately preceding telegram. 2. Ibn Saud^ abrupt action in breaking up conference gives no time for His Majesty f s Governments immediate intervention in the conference but I venture to think that a communication to Saudi Government on the lines suggested in paragraphs 3 and 4 of my telegram of 26th June might still have a good effect. h • - Resident.In kii&lt; ^ v' -8- Notes on the discussions between oaudi Delegate s and Kw/ait Representatives, Continued . ffoljx-vlk jbu^i ^gix • No meeting. UTJTH jj^Y (gxilD^Y 21st JUx^/ . (1) No meeting• (2) Saudi Delegates intimated this morning (21st June) that they desired to meet Kuwait Delegates at 8 ^•ivi, tomorrow (Saturday 22nd June)* :ed A, (3) I enclose translation of 'Kuwait Delegates* letter' to Saudi Delegation mentioned under Note for 'iifternoon of First Day' (iii) sent you under my ilxpress Letter No. C~190 dated 18th June 1935. SIXTH D ay (S^gUiAUn-Y 32nd . V. V ^ (1) Delegates of both sides met at 8 -a,II, on Saturday in Shaikh's i.ejliss room as usual, and meeting lasted fran 8 till 9 (see my telegram No. 200 -f 2 7 of 21st June). 1 was of course present. (2) Before business actually started Chief Saudi delegate asked if 1 had had any news by Radio of world affairs and I told him of the Naval agreement with Geimany and ioiiir Saud's doings in London as well as further details of the Quetta earthqua ke. (3) Business opened by the Chief Saudi delegate ^ saying that a reply had bean received from H.Mc the King, to effect that Kuwait delegates should be asked whether in event of Customs losts and Manifest^ System being introduced (a) The lluwait Government would give a written document to the Saudi Government, guaranteeing ihat all smuggling from Kuwait-9- from Kuwait to Nejd would cease forthwith, (b) That if Kuwait G-ovemmoat would not do this whether H.LI.G. would 'be willing to give necessary written guarantee, (c) That it was imaaterial who gave guarantee, H.k .G, or Kuwait, but guarantee must be givoi to King. He as senior Saudi delegate therefore puts above questions to both Kuwait delegates and to me, as representing H.K.G. (bee my telegram No n-p (4) Before giving reply, the Kuwait delegates asked what was meant by 'Kuwait guaranteeing that there should be no further smuggling across the frontier once the manifest system was started n . To this Khalid ibn al Jalid answered, that he thought that he had put his question plainly, but to make things quite clear, the following was what was meant:- 'Kuwait must undertake in return for any such concession as the Customs Posts &lt;Sc Kanifest System, literally to allow no contraband trade whatsoever to go across the border into Saudi territory, and not even a single hair , must get through (his words), else the King would consider himself justified in denouncing any agreement arrived at'. xkaE ./hen asked how it was proposed that Kuwait should carry out such unreasonable guarantee, the reply came quick 'That is your concern not ours'. A Kuwait delegate then asked whether Kuwait would be held responsible, if say a Nejdi Yms caught running contraband from in IRAQ, into Saudi Arabia by Saudi frontier police, and the origin of goods was said to be Kuwait, by the smuggler in an endeavour to cover his tracks. 22nd June to Bus hi re ). Nejef The re clyTlie reply was 'Kuwait will be held responsible, for it will be up to her to stop all good going even over the IRikQ, border, if such goods eventually find their way into Saudi Arabia, and it can be proved that the origin was xCuwait'. another Kuwait delegate asked whether it was proposed to invite IRA , and Trans Jordan to give ^ guar ntee that no smuggling went across the border - but no reply was, given. (5) After some further discussion amongst themselves the Kuwait delegates replied that as Kuwait would find it quite ii.ipossible to carry out the under taking required of them and as they felt that the demand was entirely unreasonable, they must rejeet same and give a negative answer. At the same time they said that the undertaking they could and would give if the King would agree to it was 'The Kuwait Govemmont promises to do its honest best to put a stop to all smuggling into Nejd, and gives its word of honour to this effect' (6) The Senior Saudi delegate then asked mes, if H.K. G-. would give the necessary guarantee . To this I replied with a No I pointing out that the question was one between Kuwait and Saudiyeh and did not directly concern H.M.G-overnment, (7) The ^enior Saudi Delegate then said he would refer Kuwait's reply, which ms taken down in writing, to the King, and the meeting adjourned. (8) Before the delegates actually left the room, IY b second Saudi delegate, Hamad bin Sulaiman,'let the cat out of the bag' somewhat by remarking in grumbling tone that for his part he saw no point at all-11- point at all in the Customs Posts and 'Manifest Systein'* i tiiat it was v/aste of tii^e to tali^ fuxwlier ^fben asked why he said this, he replied that he for one would never trust the Kuwait Gustous authorities, and he saw no reason why a manifest should be given for 100 bags of sugar say to go to Nejd, when in reality 200 bags went out with the same caravan, (The odd 100 being earmarked as contraband to be run, as soon as caravan was near the border). The ICu.Hit delegates replied hotly that theirs was^Govemment as baudi Arabia was, and that all further talks would be quite useless, n (distrust of this sort was going to govern the minds of the Saudi Dele^ites: I managed to make peace, but the Saudi delegate was certainly asking for trouble, (9) After the meeting^lad adjourned, I called on the bhaikh to di^duss Political Resident's telegram No. 54^) 21st June 1955 in which I was asked to try and persuade Shaikh to extend time oi Jf' ile conference, eveiT/hi-uiseIf was cieteriiiined to leave for London on 24th t.une. The Shaikh listened to me carefully and asked me to give reply to the Political Resident that he personally had quite definitely come to the conclusion as a result of the first meeting only of his Delegates with those of Bin Saud, that 'no business' was meant, and that Bin Saud, who had obviously been ordered to send delegates to Kuwait, had from the first decided to make a failure of the Conference. This was as clear as daylight-12- as daylight. That he (Shaikh) fully realised (with the Political Resident) that Bin maud's next move would probably be to try and fasten the blame on him (Ahmad) for a break down of discussions. In order to forestall possibility of this, he had taken the following action on Friday 22nd June (although of course his coming departure was already known to ^audi delegates and to Bin Jaud). (a) He had called officially on ^audi delegates and explained that he had to leave for London on Monday S4th June in accordance with a programme arranged 3 months ago - That his departure need not affect Conference in least, as Shaikh Abdulla as Salim, his cousin would take over the reins of Government, and they,the delegate s, could look upon him as they as they looked upon himself, viz as Shaikh of Kuwait. That they were guests of Kuwait, and must not hesitate to stay as long they thought fit in Kuwait for the purpose of carrying the discussions to their logical and he hoped successful conclusion. (b) Pie sent a telegram on the same lines as (a) above, to Bin Saud, trusting that Saudi Delegates would continue their labours after his departure I n under the aegis of shaikh Abdulla,, (See my tele, ram 20 4 of 22nd June to Zushire) . x.ote . The same evening at a banquet givaa by the Shaikh in honour of the Saudi jjelegates (at which all the heads of the state were present), the ohaikh age in expressed the hope that the delegates would continue their labours after his departure, ani then read out the King's reply telegram, which had in the meantime arrived. This was very graciously worded, and wished his brother Ahmad 'God speed and an early return in completely restored health'. (c) The Shaikh then mentioned in confidence that al Nafisi (Bin Saudis Trade Agoit) had confided to him that the Saudi delegates were greatly dis turbed, because I attended the discussions. They thought proceedings shdmld be held as at Bahrain, with no British G-overnmaat official to spy on the delibera tions. The Shaikh added, how grateful he was that K.L.G, had insisted on my being present, as only through me could the offensive behaviour and unreasonable suggestions-13- 'f ■ sugisestions of the Jaudi delegates, be properly conveyed to Bush ire and London. To use his words 'Again am again I have told you and other British Political Officers in the Gulf, of the behaviour of 3 audi Gov eminent officials when they visit xZuwait, but I have never bean believed yet, because I was supposed like Snui'.ih oalim, my uncle, to be unre- son- able .ond prejudiced - 1 erhaps 1 shall be believed now'# ~D^Y 25rd tTUlL^; . No meeting. JIGIITH 24th , (1) The iiaudi and Kuwait delegates met at £ A«M* and once again for two hours discussed the nature and meaning from all angles of the 'guarantee' which Bin Saud required from the xCumit Govemnient, as a condition to his agreeing to liie Customs Posts and ..anife st Jys tem, (see my telegram No. 211 of 25.6,25) (2) The senior ^audi Delegate explained at length that, when he had said at the last meeting that Jin oaud was willing to agree to the ''Customs Posts and manifest Jystem f? being introduced, on condition that the Ku .;ai t Gover^acint guaranteed by written document that smuggling into ^audi ia-abia will forthwith cease, he had meant by that, that even if a single smuggler from Kuwait was caught by the baudi frontier guards, the shaikh of _Cuwait would have broken his agreaaent and it would be open to the lling to cancel any trade agreement arrived at at once if he chose, (3) When pressed by the Kumit Delegates to say what would actually happen in practice under the scheme as visualized by him (the Senior ^audi Delegate), the latter replied that in his opinion, if for instance, one snuggler from Kuwait was caught on the frontier his camel and goods would be confiscated the first— 14— (6) the first time , and a bill for tlie Customs recover able would be sent to the shaikh of Kuvait, who v /oulc be expected to pay. The same thing would happen up to a limit of three times . After that the ^ing would have the clear right, and would exercise such right, to cancel the whole Trade Agreement on the grou.id that Kuwait had failed in her guarantee (4) The Kuwait delegates argued very vigorously that such one sided conditions were not only unfair in the extreme, but left any agreement arrived at entirely at the mercy of the King, who could kill or keep it alive as he chose, seeing that all the world knew that the smuggling fraternity existed even in the most y/ell ordered and modern States. In other words they said that a ^rade which was to be developed, opened up and financed by ITejd and Kuwait merchants jointly, and could fall to the ground any momemt because forsooth 3 rascally smugglers might happen to get caught within a period of perhaps a week, a month or six months, was useless to them; '^uije clearly therefore they could give no guarantee under such conditions. (5) The Saudi delegates said they quite saw their point, but Kuwait delegates must also ^theirs. The King a- had given them their orders, clearly, unequivocally,, These were that they (his delegates) must make it clear that the basic principle of any trade agree ment that was to be negotiated was to be this 'guarantee' or 'thaman'. If the Kuwait delegates chose to give the guarantee, then talks could be continued, if not then they had nothing further to do but go home.-15- 7^ (5) I here myself interfered and said I tiioiaght it would be a thousand pities if for the sak ;e of this one word f, tl3aman n or ^guarantee iT , the negotiations ./ere to break down, and I urged the Saudi delegates to meke things a little easier, for the Kuwait delegates ol early oould not give a 'clear cut promise' to prevent any single smuggler from crossing the border, when next day they would be proved liars, I pointed out that supposing England and France s were trying to cone to a trade agreaaait, advantageoa to the traders of both countries, what possible shsx chance would the agreement have of going through,if France for instance insisted on a clause giving them the power to cancel the agreement without notice,if one English smuggler was caught within the territo rial waters of France. The Saudi delegates saw my point, but said I must not apply European standards to iCuwait and Kejd* (7) Not to be out done and seeing that we were nearing in impasse, I asked if smuggling went on between Bahrain and Qatar and Hassa - they admitted that a certain amount did - 'well' I said, 'do you not think in fairness that you ought to ask the Shaikhs of Bahrain and Qatar, to give a'guarantee' that no smugglers would operate from these countries into Nejd'. The reply vms that circumstances altered cases. (8) The Kuwait, delegates once again stated that if the King would only drop the 'guarantee' or 'thaman' condition, they for their part would readily give a written document on behalf of Kuwait 'promising on the honour of the shaikh, the merchants and people of iluwait to do their best, and by every me ansmeans in their power to reduce smuggling to a mininum 1 ' This the Saudi delegates refused to consider, or even telegraph 'to the King. It was case of 'thaman' or nothing now. la-&lt;? &lt;c-*' (9) Seeing that things were ag in getting the danger ■ ^ point, I adjourned the meeting myself, under the excuse that no doubt the delegates all desired to bid farewell to the Shaikh who was about to leave for London by air. (10) It was only too evident to me that the Saudi delegates had received new instructions frem the King, not to budge an inch from the 'guarantee' idea, and that t hey knew full well that the Kuwait delegates could not accept such conditions, and were out to force an issue on this point. Probably the next day or two will therefore see the break down of discussions® LixT^R . (a) An hour after the adjournment of the meeting described above, the Saudi delegates addressed a letter dated 24th June 1935 to the Kuwait delegates, translation attached (and marked B) , which was clearly meant to define their position. The Kuwait delegates at once replied by a similar letter dated 25th June 1935 recapitulating everything that the Saudi Senior Delegate had told them, giving their stand point, and asking for a final reply. A translation of this letter is attached (and marked G). Note . Both these letters are important documents in my opinion, as they prove that the Saudi delegates must bear the responsibility for the break down of negotiations now unfo rtunately eminent,-17- (b) I omitted to mention above, that during the debate of the morning, I enquired fron the Jenior Saudi delegate as to whether from reports and statistics at his disposal, he thougnu much smuggling went across the frontier into Saudi ^ratda from Kuwait today . The answer was 'Very little indeed, perhaps one smuggler is caught per month'. I next suggested that this desirable state of affairs was no doubt due to ^iie splenciio control i^iciintainea on the frontier by the King's preventive guards and their Oommander A1 Bagaawi - n That was so' - came the reply. 1 then suggested, (emphasizing that I put the question purely out of a desire to help in removing obstacles to an agreement) that as Saudi frontier control was so good today and as to existing frontier guards would certainly remain on even if the 'Customs ^-os'cs anc maniiest System 1 were introduced, whether he and nis brother delegates could not see their way to waive the 'guarantee clause', seeing that it was for all practical purposes quite necessary. The Senior delegate said he saw my point, out could } not budge from the standpoint already taken up by him - (In a. private aside to me he said he could ^ not go against the King^ orders in this matter, for they were very explicit). Note.. From the above, two things appear quite clear:- (a) The delegates are acting under the King's direct orders and have no power to do anything on their own responsibility. (b) Mr. Philby's statemait made to me when he ?/as here recently iiiat saiuggliing into Nejd was still very heavy, was not admitted by the Saudi delegates ; to the Kuwait Conference ani so cannot be relied i on. Moreover it should not be forgotten that the two Senior Saudi delegates pose as experts, whose sole job in life is to deal with Tariffs, ^ {|&gt; and frontier Customs questions qonv^ition with YU ^audi ^rabia. (see D.O.letter ^OVlOG/c d/-13.4.35 J ■ A ^ in connection with Philby'S recent visit to Kuwait).-18- v l.Tij'Trl DxxY (TUjI^Di^T 25th JU^j . (1) After receipt 'by the Saudi Delegates of the iluwait ijfi larked 'C' Delegates* letter of E5th June, see under heading 'LuTER (a) on page 16 of these notes'*, the former at onoe held a private meeting and sent another arked 'D' letter dated 25th June,translation attached, to the Kuwait Delegation. This letter speaks for itself, though its general purport is that 'You the iCuwait Delegates have not given us a final answer, you must definitely say whether you agree to give the 'guarantee* or reject same' • (2) Replying on the same day (25.6.35) again, the Kuwait delegates said they had already made it perfectly clear that they could not agree to give the 'guarantee' dananded, giving reasons, and urged that the Saudi Delegates should either now modify their last proposals in respect of 'guar ntee' business, or inform the King of their (Saudi Delegates') final proposals and the Kuwait reply, marked 'S' Translation of Kuwait letter is submitted with this.{} Translation of a letter dated the 16th Rabi* Auwal 1354, corresponding to the r 17th June 1935, from Messrs,Ahmad al-Humaidhi, Muhammad bin ^hunaiyan al-Ghanim, and IChalid az~Zaid (Kuwait delegates), to Messrs.Khalid Abul Walid, Hamad as--Sulaiman, and 'Abdulla al-Qusaibi (Sa'udi delegates) at Kuwait. oOo After compliments, In view of what is I oiotoi to you and to us, and also to every high born and poor person, of the good and friendly relations which have existed for very many years between the Al Sabah and the Al Sa f ucE dynasties, more especially between His Majesty King 'Abdul f Aziz and His Excellency Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir, and in consequence of the desire of both countries to further strengthen these relations, by removing the trade blockade of Kuwait, we have suggested below, the most suitable method as seemed to us, for the resumption of the export trade (from Kuwait) with His Majesty^ Kingdom, These are as follows:- (1) That Customs Collecting Centres should be established within the frontiers of His Majesty the King - These may consist of one post or more than one, and in such places as His Majesty the King may choose, (2) That His Excellency Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir shall, for his part, assist to the best of his power in the control and guiding of all exports to the above posts or centres - This will be by means of manifests, which will be issued in triplicate; the first copy to go with the goods the second to be handed over to His Majesty's local agent -'Abdulla an-Nafisi, and the third one to remain in the customs office of the local Government. The above is the opinion we hold, and the procedure is one which is recognized between kingdoms and nations that are good neighbours, as well as by others. U.E. —oOo— fir mmm-r n—Mii ■ wmm&amp;y : j Translation of a letter dated the 23rd Rabl T Auwal 1354 [24^6^5], from Messrs.iOialid Abul 7/alld, Hamad as- Sulaiman, and •Abdulla al-Q.usaibl, the Sa'udi delegation, to Messrs.Ahmad al-Humaidhi, Muhamroad A1 Thunaiyan, and Khalid az-Said. —-oOo After compliments, With reference to the discussion viiich we had with you today, in regard to the resumption of ^Musabalah^ (trade) between our country and Kuwait, we beg to reiterate in writing, in addition to what we explained verbally, the good intentions of our Government, and the affectionate spirit, friendliness, and good feeling which she has towards the Kuwait Government, and to say that she (the Sa f udi Government) is prepared Id continue conversations with a view to arriving at a satisfactory conclusion between both sides, and to discuss measures to remove all misunderstanding for the future. Such conversations, however, must be on the one clear basis, that the Govern ment of Kuwait shall give tf guar an tee n (dhaman) with regard to goods passing (across frontier) to His Majesty the King's territory (i.e. that nothing is smuggled apart from goods sent under manifests). This indeed is what we proposed in the course of our discussions with you. Should your esteemed delegation agree to nego tiate on this basis, we are prepared once more to discuss the subject in order to arrive at the conclusion sought by both sides. Usual ending. Note by p.A. /- / The above letter, as will be seen, is worded somewhat differently from what the Sa^di delegate laid down as /the only basis for future talks, see my telegram No.Ell of 25th June, namely that Kuwait must agree before anything else to guarantee that not even a single smuggler got across the border. The: J ine Kuwait delegates have not missed this point.and in I their reply (marked G)have pinned the oaudi delegates down 1 to what they actually did say, ^ )\ -1 W C M o Translation of a letter dated the S4tli Rabl' Auwal 1354 (25*6o35), from Messrs.Ahmad al-Humidhi, Muhammad A1 Thunalyan, and Khalld az-Zaid, the Kuwait delegation, to Messrs.Khalid Abul Walid, Hamad as-Sulaiman, and 'Abdulla al-Qusaibi, 12ie Sa'udi delegation, Kuwait. 0O0 After compliments. We have received your esteemed letter dated the 23rd Rabi* Auwal 1354 (E4*6»35), and have understood what you stated as to your good intentions as well as the good intentions of His Majesty King Bin Sa'ud's Government, namely that you are prepared to continue conversations wi th a view to arriving at a satisfactory conclusion between both sides, and to discuss measures to remove all misunderstanding, 'but that such conversations must from now onward be on the one basis, that the Government of Kuwait shall first give tt guarantee n (dhaman) with regard to goods (smuggled) passing across the frontier. You added that if our delegation would agree to the 'guarantee** condition on behalf of the Kuwait Government, then you would be prepared to continue the talks. | f ^7 f K / c? We wish therefore now to make the matter quite clear. The situation is, as we suggested to you in our letter dated 12ie 16th Rabi , Auwal 1354 (17.6.35), and as was also discussed with you in yesterday morning's meeting (24.6.35). You stated that the .^guarantee' system was desired by His Majesty's (Saudiyeh) Government, which was that nothing should be smuggled, and only goods exported according to manifests should be allowed to pass into Saudi Territory# That should any smuggler be cau^it, his goods would be confiscated, and the Kmmit Government would ha'9B to pay the Customs duty imposed on sameo Also that should this happen more than tiiree times. His Majesty's Sa^di Government should ha ve the right to cancel the agreement. At tiie same meeting we replied to you that the Kuwai tKuwait Government would give you her word of honour to do all in her power to prevent smuggling. And that should any smuggling be discovered (within her territory) the Kuvmit Grovemment would inflict the severest of punishments on the evil-doer&lt;, As regards the 'guarantee' insisted on hy you - with every precautions taken and every good will, we say this cannot be realized. Hence it is not reasonable of you to make such a condition. That which the Saudi Government is afraid of (e.g. smuggling), should it occur, will be trifling and very small, because of the measures that will be taken by His Majesty's Saudi Government and the Government of Kuwait, It should certainly not affect the good will, and the desire for a reciprocal/ agreement between His Majesty the King and His Sxcellency Shaikh Ahmad al Jabir. We have every hope,however, that owing to your deep insight you will not allow a doubtful and unrea sonable defect to stand in the way of good understanding. We beg for a reply to this, and express the hope that we shall come to a good understanding. Usual ending.Translation of letter dated the 24th Rabi 1 Auwal 1554 (25.6,55), from liessrs. Khalid Abul ./alid, Haiaad as Sulai-./ian and ^bdulla al ^asaibi, the Saudi Delegation, to Messrs. Ahraad al Huiaaidhi, Mohamad Thunaiyan and IQialid al Zaid, the iluwait Delegates. Af ter c omp 1 imen. ts, we have with due regard received your esteemed letter dated the 24th Habi* Auwal 1554 (25.6.55) , in reply to our letter dated the 25rd Rabi* Auv/al (24.6.55), but have not found in it a clear reply to what vie asked your reply for, save an outline of the talks we had with you in our last meeting, while according to your desire we as.ced you in writing to let us know whether or not you agree to the guarantee' basis, so that we may be able to arrive to a definite conclusion. Therefore we request that you will kindly inform us in clear manner as to your final decision, either you should agree to the 'guarantee' basis, or decline fr^fu it, in this way 'the situation will be made quite clear, and we can submit a report to our Cxovernmait. Awaiting your reply. Usual ending.Translati®n of a letter dated the 24tli Rabl 1 Auwal 1354 (SS.e.SS), from Messrs. Ahmad al^Iimaidhi, Muhammad Al Thunaiyan, and Khalid az-2aid, the Kuwait delegation, to Messrs* Khalid Abul Walid, Hamad as-Sulalman, and ^bdulle al-^usaibi, the Sa , udl delegation, Kuwait. After compliments, We have received your letter dated the 24th Rahi' Auwal 1354 (25.6.35), in reply to our letter of the same date, from which we understand that you consider our reply not to be clearly put, and that you now wish to be informed definitely whether we agree to the 'guarantee^ basis or not, in order that you my submit a report to your Government. Contrary to what you say we believe that we have made the position quite clear, and have not been obscure. We explained to you that the 'guarantee' basis, which you demanded in yesterday^ meeting, could not possibly be realized, in spite of every good intention and effort on our part; for as we explained the first case of smuggling that occurred would not only upset the plan, but would tend to have exactly the opposite result where the good agreement and connections desired by both His Majesty's Sa'udi Govern ment and our Government is concerned. Therefore, you should either make propositions different to the above, or submit your present proposal, together with our reply to it, to your Government. ?/e leave that to you. Usual ending53/54 Telegram G.T.C. Political Agent, Kuwait# To Political Heaident, Jbushire# Bo. 224 Dated 4th receivedSth July 1935, For information, Saudi Delegates to recent conference still here# They have been unable to leave Kuwait owing to extensive repairs required by some of their cars. Spares ordered from Baghdad and Karachi expected to arrive to-morrow ittiday. Delegates will probably get away on Sunday# Poli tical \A&gt;ij 'j/yy CONFIDENTIAL. No. C-S19n The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to the Honourable tJae Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bu shire, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s), \\ A POLITICAL AGENCY, -&lt;ii 1} J KUWAIT. Dated the 29th June 1935. Reference to previous correspondence : L '7 ^ Kuwait Printed Letter No. C-216 dated thTe S7th June 1935. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Notes on discussions between the Saudi Delegates and Kuwait representatives (from page 19 to page 22) ^Saudi Kuwait Blockade Conf erence**.Notes on Kuwait-Saudi Blockade Discussions. CONTINUED * O^Jtv P'L.rttfO&amp;S V'.pjl/**' / ^ , r' TENTH BAY (WEDNESDAY 36th JUNE) . r No meeting. The Saudi delegates referred the contents of their $ ^already) own and Kuwait delegates' letters (C)(D) and (S) dated sent to ) Bushire.) E5th June 1935 evening, to the King for orders. ELE7MTH DAY (THURSDAY 27th JUNE) . No meeting. TWELFTH DAY (FRIDAY 38th JUNE) . (1) The Saudi Delegates called a meeting at 8 A # M. and as usual I attended. (2) Before the meeting started they asked to see me alone. I agreed. The Saudi Delegates at this private meeting told.me that they had received a reply from the King the previous night to the effect that they must tell the Kuwait delegates that if they did not forthwith agree to give the '♦guarantee 11 asked for by the King, they, the Saudi del egates / must close down discussions and » return to Riyath at once# (3) They than begged me to see the Kuwait Delegates alone in the same way as I had seen them, and to explain that the final stages had been reached, and that things were no longer in their hands. That the King^ wishes were law, and that from the start, they had been given no real proper authority to negotiate 'give and take', or bargain as they would have liked. That the only thing that they could do now was to advise Kuwait to agree to the ♦♦guarantee' required of them, and try the scheme out for 6 montiis - After that both-20- ^ that both sides could renew or cancel as they liked. (4) I replied that I saw very little hope of the Kuwait delegates agreeing, seeing that they too had their strict orders from the Shaikh, and to agree to such an impossible thing as the 'guarantee' required of them, was tantamount to putting themselves into the hands of the first three rogues th^rt felt they had a grievance against the Shaikh; I however agreed to deliver their message to the Kuwait delegates (now waiting in an adjoining room). (5) As I expected, the latter rejected the proposition quietly and firmly and obviously with great feeling and regret, after which they joined the Saudi Delegates with me« (6) Here the Senior Saudi Delegate explained what had happened, and could only tell them of the King^ tele gram. It was a case of could they agree to the 'guarantee' now and at the eleventh hour or not. If not they, the Saudi Delegates, had their orders to end the discussions and go home. (7) The Kuwait delegates expressed their very great disappointment at the King's ultimatum, and said they could definitely not go further than they had gone already. If the Saudi Delegates had no fresh suggestions to make, then they supposed the conversa tions must end. (8) The Senior Saudi Delegate then asked leave to close the proceedings, and I as H.M. Governments representative^ could do nothing else but agree. (9) Then followed much polite speechifying, on the part of the Saudi Delegates, who appeared to be genuinely surprised and gratified at the wonderful receptionm 'M i'''/ -21- reoeption accorded tliem in Kuwait. (They had been invited to a sumptuous banquet either by the Shaikh, a member of the Shaikhs family, or by a leading Emir or merchant of the town, every night of the twelve already spent in Kuwait, let alone luncheon parties galore). They took pains to explain that the break down of Conversations must not be taken toounkindly, for the King bore Kuwait every good will, and they themselves would leave Kuwait, with feelings of friendship and satisfaction, and would do thiir best to persuade the King to look upon the present failure, as merely the beginning of future talks to come. (10) I myself ended the meeting by a short speech, thanking both sides for the good-will, and pleasant temper shown under often trying circumstances - It had been a great pleasure to the Shaikh, the people of Kuwait and myself to meet and welcome the King's Delegates, and I hoped that they would take back kind recollections of their time spent in Kuwait. I added/ that I personally looked upon their visit this year as a more hopeful and encouraging sign. For the last 10 years the door between Hejd and Kuwait had been locked, it had now been opened just a little bit - We in Kuwait were not going to shut it again, and would look forward to further talks being held either in Kuwait, Jedda or Rivath . which talks Ensh , Alla would result in the door being thrown wide open once more. In the above connection see my telegram No. 218 of 28th June 1935. s (11) Thus ended the Kuwait-Saudi Blockade Conversation of 1935. No Arab I fear wanted them and certainly no ArabArab expected anytMng mucli to come of tlienu (12) The Saudi Delegates will dine with me at the Agency to morrow night (29#6•1935) after which they hope to leave for Riyath on 30th June (DV).0/ yty CONFIDENTIAL No. C-223 • The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to the Hon * ble the Political He si dent in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire, •7^'. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). O 1 POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. x ' 3rd July 1935, ( '7 ^ Reference to previous correspondence : Kuwait Printed Letter No.C-219 dated 2 9th June 1955* DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. '*Saudi-Kuwait Blockade Conference'.-23- , U Notes on Kuwait-Saudi Blockade Discussions. *' t CONTDTOBD . i^LcU, * '-'/7/i «&gt; iL^~_ TTmmTHWTH DAY (SATUi^AY 29th JUKE) . ' ^' (1) I received this morning from tlie Kuwait Delegates, copies of rjced (a) Letter dated 28th June 1935 from them j«« (Kuwait Delegates), to the Saudi Delegates, in which they recapitulated all that had passed by letter, between them and the Saudi Delegates. rked (b) Letter dated 28th June 1935 from the Saudi G' Delegates in reply to (a) above. (2) Translations of both letters are attached with this and marked 'F' and 'G* 1 respectively. (3) As mentioned in para 12 of Notes for Twelfth day (Friday 28th June) the Saudi delegates dined with me on 29th June 1935. The sole other guest was Shaikh Abdul la al Salim (Deputy Ruler): The dinner passed off very pleasantly and we were all kept amused and interested by Shaikh Khalid ibn al Walid, who with refreshing candour retailed many of his experiences in Italy, Moscow, Turkey and Tripoli. (4) Shaikh Khalid apparently tXMX went to Moscow on the staff of Enver- Pasha, immediately before the latter*s abortive rebellion and death in Turkestan - He professed to have met Kara Khan Tchicherin, Kalenin and others, (5) Shaikh Khalid talked very cheerfully and freely, (a) of the steady rise of Arab Nationalism in the world, and hinted strongly that H.M. Govt, should cultivate and sympathise with this,so as in the end to find herself in the positioi. of friend and guide and not an enemy of the movement. (b) of H.M. Govemmeat's obvious policy with Bin Saud, who led and represented all that was best in Arab Nationalism, and hinted that H.M.Government would do well to give him a more-24- /r -t? more free iiand where Ba lira in, Kuwait and Oman were ooncemed. (c) of his personal friendship for Philby, who whilst being one of of the greatest and most knowledge able of Englishmen where matters of Arabia were concerned, yet curiously was one of the most ignorant of all people in that he did not yet understand the of Arab Psychology, and was profoundly ignorant of such things as Arab pride, and Be^uin Manners, and Customs. (d) of the late Colonel Lawrence, who he described /as one of those who had 'luck' among many other equally good men and should be called the 'Romancer in chief of the Great War'. (e) of Imam Yahya, who was deeply and genuinely religious, and who he absolved of all connection with the recent attempt to assasinate Bin Saud - but not so his son. (f) of Arabs generally who feancK he divided into - the really educated , the half educated and the the Bedouin . He said the first and last category were about equal in nobility of thought and actions, and that their friendship was really worth cultivating by H.M. Government and English men in general. The Half educated were 'bad to the core', especially the present generation. Their children would be different and better. (g) of the difference between English, French,German, and Turkish philosophy and Psychology - That the 'A* 1 to ,f Z n of being a good ruler and good administrator was to study and study again the Psychology of the people one ruled. (6) Before leaving my home Shaikh Khalid stated that he and his friends departure for Hiyath mi^it be delayed somewhat, owing to the non-arrival of spare parts and tyers for their oars from Baghdad. These had been wired for as Basra could not produce them.n p tt Translation of a letter dated the 27tli RaM' Auwal 1354, aorresponding to the SSth June 1935, from Messrs. Ahmad al-Humaldhi, Lluhanmad Al Thunaiyan, and ICaalid az-Said the Kuwaiti delegation, to Messrs. Thalid ^'bul Valid, Hamad as-Sulaiman, and ^bdulla al- usaibi, the Sa'udi delegation Kuwait. After oompliments. With reference to the information you imparted to us in todays meeting, that His Majesty the Sing would not agree to the resumption of trade 'between Kuwait and the Sa r udi Arabia, save on the 'guarantee' basis on the part of the Kuwait Government. \ ^ ^ As you know, we have written a letter to you, dated the 16th Rabi* Auwal 1354 (17.6.35), in which we stated the views we considered good for both countries. On the other hand, in the meeting of the Elst inst (22.6.35) you demanded a 'guarantee', and we stated in our letter of the 34th inst (^5.6.35) that that 'guarantee' was impossible to give, as it could not practically or theoretically be enforced. ; f k' ! ft' w In a second letter, also dated the 24th' inst(25.6.35) j we asked you to submit both your proposition of 'guarantee' and our reply to it, to His Llajesty the King. If His Majesty the King, as you informed us definite ly and verbally today was the case, does not agree to anything but that we give the 'guarantee' asked for, then all that is left for us is to make it known that we cannot commit our selves to any such 'guar?{antee'. Although we recognize that His Majesty the King and His Excellency shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir are as brothers, and that there is no difference between our two countries and the two peoples, neverthless we regret the failure of negotiations We do not entirely despair, however, and still hope for agree ment. We look to this conference as a first step to the under standing desired. May God destine agreement. Please acknowledge our letter. U. E.Tt Q. tt ( (} Translation of a letter dated tiie E7t3i Rabi* Auwal 1354, corresponding to tlB S8th June 193 5, from Messrs.IChalid Abul Walid, Earoad as-3ulaiman, and f Abdulla al-Qusaibi, the Sa^di delegation, Kuwait, to Messrs. Ahinad al-Humaidhi, Muhaimmd A1 Thunaiyan, and Kbalid az-Zaid, the Kuwait delega tion, Kuwait. After oompliuBnts, We have to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated the 27th Rabi* Auwal 1354 (28.6 # 35), copy of which is embodi ed herein below:- Kuwait, 27th Rabi f Auwal 1354. tt Messrs.Khalid Abul Y/alid, Hamad as-Sulaiman, and ^bdulla al-Qusaibi, Kuwait. 'After compliments, With reference to the information you imparted to us in today's meeting, that His Majesty the King would not agree to the resumption of trade between Kuwait and the Sa^di Arabia, save on tbe 'guarantee' basis on the part of the Kuwait Government. As you know, we have written a letter to you, dated the 16th Rabi* Auwal 1354 (17.6.35), in which we stated the views we considered good for both countries. On the other hand, in the meeting of the 21st inst (22o6.35) you demanded a 'guarantee', and we stated in our letter of the 24th inst (25.6.35) that that 'guaran tee' was impossible to give, as it could not practically or theoretically be enforced. .^ . - 6 &gt; fkY In a second letter, also dated the 24tif inst (25o6.35), we aksed you to submit both youc proposition of 'guarantee' and our reply to it, to His Majesty the King. If His Majesty the King, as you inibrmed us definitely and verbally today was the case, does not agree to anything but that we give the ' guar ant ee'asked for, then all that is left for us is to make it known that we cannot commit ourselves to any such 'guarantee', f Although we recognize that His Majesty the King ^ and His Excellency Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir are as brothers,, and that there is no difference between our two countries' 1 and tbe two peoples, neverthless we regret tiie failure of negotiations. We do not despair, however, and still hope for agreement. We look to this conference as a firsl step to the understanding desired. May God destine agree- men t. Please acknowledge our letter. Usual ending.' We seize this opportunity to thank you for the welcome and courtesy with which we have always been met during our discussions, and wish with you, from the bottom of our hearts, l' that/ —- 2 - / '0 J that the two oountries be given the ohanoe to come to an agreement in the near future* Usual ending.CONFIDENTIAL. No. C-2S6. s v The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ^ Bushire, $ n and has the honour to^ transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned dooument(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 4th July 1935, Reference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date Charge D*Affairs Jedda telegram No. 157 of 3rd July 1935.to Kuwait. 'Armed guard accompanying Kuwait telegram No.225 to Charge D*Affairs , Jedda. Mr. De Gaury',i i HtJ No Frcsn To Charge D Affairs, Jedda. Political, Kuprait. 157. Dated and received Srd July 1935 Addressed Kuwait No. 157. Repeated to by bag Foreign Office and Bushire. me this morning that De Gaury leaves Riadh today for Kuwait. He is being given six guards who will carry anosi As he wishes to press on and is an official anticipate any objection, and therefore passed this on to me for infoimation only. 1 gathered in reply to a question that guards would not stop on frontier but accompany De Oaury to Kuwait having to return in the same cars. My telegram No. 155. Ministry of Foreign Affairs telephones inuti- *(of this legat^'^ lated. Minister of Foreign Affairs did not I made no coniiLent I trust Kuwait will have no objectionTelegram I.F.O. 1927. No From Dated To Political, Kuwait. Charge D 1 Affairs, British Legation,Jedda 3E5. 4th July 1934. Your telegram No. 157. No objection whatsoever to guards accompanying De Gaury to Kuwait and to avoid future misunderstanding I would like to make it quite clear that Kuwait Govern ment never has and never will object to reasonable number of armed Saudi Government guards coming up to Kuwait when acting as escort to prominent persons or visitors. Similarly in a country like Arabia where it customary for every traveller to carry a rifle, there obviously can never be objection to official messengers of either State being armed when carrying letters between capitals of their respective governments* The same naturally applies also to individual tribesmen or townsmen moving to and fro between Kuwait and Nejd when engaged on purely private business. Am posting copy of this to Bush ire. -POLITICAL-53/54 y , gU /&lt;S' Q Tele gram S'rom TO Repeated to ja. H.M* s Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, JiusMre. ^o« 2156 Government of India, .Foreign and -^olitLaal Department, Simla. -No. 2157 s H.M'a Charge d , Affaire a, Jedda. ^0.2158 Political Agent, Kuwait* flo« 2159 Dated 11th received 12th July 1935. Your telegram of 29th June, 130.586 and connected correspondence. Kuwait .Blockade. Question has been di acussed with Itoad Hamza on whom its importance and urgent desirability of early decision were impressed. He is taking it up with Saudi Government and has promised to let us hear further• Papers by air mail Secretary of State for mdia.53/54 t Telegram R.30. From H.M.'s Charge' d f Affaires, Jedda. m 0 Secretary of State for Foreign Alfairs, London. No.132. Repeated Government of India, Simla. No.87. Political Resident, Bush ire - No .169. Political Agent, Kuwait. No.160. Dated 14th (received 16th) JULY 1936. ir My 128. ARMED INCURSION. Saudi Government rejoins with lengthy note covering much the same ground as note summarised in my telegram No.121. I am sending text by bag but following is a brief summary. Kote regrets that incident of little importance should be given undue significance magnified by haste in which Shaikh reported it. It reiterates that no hostile act by armed forces was committed, asserting that incident was ordinary and did not merit protest. It recapitulates in substantially same terms of earliest explanation of movement of four men and after alleging that retainers were not treated with courtesy customary between two countries and ruling families goes on to state that this is not the first instance where precipitancy has led to erroneous information emanating from Shaikh quoting an incident concerning a claim by Shaikh to certain Awaaim in December 1929 liquidated by Ibn Saud punishing tribe as sheep raiders (Political Resident's telegram to Colonial Office - Ho. 1302 of 29th December 1929 and related correspondence appears to refer). Legation nnte No .92 appears to indicate 'Chat Eis U^ji Majesty's/-2- Majesty's Government consider that Ibn Saud was attempting to exercise authority in Kuwait. Saudi Government deny that there is warrant for this and add that should His Majesty's Government and Shaikh maintain that view they would be compelled to adhere to position regarding entry int6 respective territories indicated in last paragraph of Jedda telegram No.121 unless some mutual satisfactory modus vivendi to eliminate mis understanding can be devised. Note asserts Saudi desire to promote friendly relations with His Majesty's Government and Shaikh and (apparently disregarding last paragraph of Legation note of June 9th) hopes to learn their views as to whether present frontier practice should continue or a new arrangement be sought« Meanwhile Saudi Government request that Kuwait will prevent its subjects and officials from entering Saudi Arabia without previous permission they for their part undertakinA' to observe like attitude• -Charge* d 1 Affaires#Ithf III Confidential D.O. No. C-229 mi POLITICAL AGMCY, KUWAIT. The 6th July 1935. 'Kuw ai t- Sau di Bio cka de''Confe re nee' On the principle of keeping you au fait of all that has been happening here where the conference is concerned, I write to say that this morning (6 # 7.35) Abdul la al ^usaibi, returned by air to Bahrain and Shaikh Khalid ibn al Walid and Shaikh Hamad al Sulaiman, called on me preparatory to leaving for Riyath tonight by car. 2, Both Khalid and Hamad al Sulaiman took pains to tell me tbat they hoped I would bear witness to the pleasant spirit in which the recent Conference was held; They stated that it was with real regret that they were returning to Nejd without having affected a settlement, and trusted the conversations that had been held would be the beginning of later ones to come - To use my simile they said the door had been opened slightly, and some day En Sha^llah it would be opened wide - Lastly that while in Kuwait they had seen and heard a very great deal which^ made them deeply sympathetic towards Kuwait (They referred to the IRAQ, Government's smuggling accusations). 3, Then while Shaikh Khalid al Walid was conversing with Mrs. Dickson, Shaikh Hamad bin Sulaiman confided to me in an The Hon'ble Lieut-Colonel T.C.tf.Fowle, G.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf B U S H I REin an undertone that what had really made the King so that he saw with great indignation that the IRAq Govern ment was making no effort at all to guard the IRAQ-Kuwait frontier, and that such hopeless state of affairs made it impossible for him (the King) to come to terms with Kuwait. 'If you Golonel Dickson', he said 'could only get the IRAQ, Government to patrol their borders properly, as Saudi Arabia was doing, oidy then you would see a change in the demeanour of Bin Saud, he would talk business♦ 4. Shaikh Hamad added that the King's sympathies were all with Kuwait in the snuggling trouble with IRAQ, and that he resented fiercely the attempts that were being made by IRAQ, to try and force Kuwait to do her dirty work for her. 'sticking' about the 'Guarantee' business was the fact/ jVo. 1638/364/19 P HIS Majesty 's Charge d'Affaires at J edda presents his compliments to The rion f ble the Political Resident, Bushire. and lias the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British. Legation, Jedda • ^ I . 3rd July 1935 Reference to previous correspondence : Jedda printed despatch No.1605/364/17 of 29/6/35. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. To : Political Agent, Kuwait. Telegram No.157 of 3/7/35 Captain de G-aury leaves Riyadh for Kuwait. 3479 8213 (a)telegram. To ; h. m. k oiiticai . .gent. stssrsascn—sssss: d ' -t v • a* ;'uwait» 3/7/55 ( 11-15 j lb? 3rd July 1955 # Addrea^ec; to Kuwait l«o#i57 repeated by bag to F»0» und I-y telegraia Ho«155* inivitry of oreirn ^Taira telephones me this luorniag tliat de Gaury leaves Riyadh to-day for Kuwait. Me is being given six guards %ho will carry arms* as he wishiea to preaa on and is an official ^audiu did not aJiticipate any objection and therefore pasaed thia on to me for information only» I gathered la reply to quest!c that guarda would not stop at frontier but accoiapany de aaury to Kuwait, having to return in sa^e cars. i made no comment* I truat oUeykh will have no objection* Bushire*By Air Mail. u P.Z Z . 19 'V L INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Jj Forwarded with the coinpliiueiits of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. ^Tlit Fuiui^ii C^iotaryj CloT-nrnTinrmt of Indku The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057 vA&gt;this document is the property of his britannic majesty's government - ~~ — ■ f ~ i* O EASTERN (A rabia). j uly jgss CONFIDENTIAL. —' S ection 1. ■(Copy forwai'ded to P.A- TE 4218/318/251 Kuwait under P.L.No. L C/252 of 27/7/36)J Record of the Fourth Meeting with Fuad Bey Hamza at the Foreign Office on t/h July 5, 1935. THE following were present;— Mr. Rendel. I Fuad Bey Hamza. Sir A. Ryan. j Sheikh Hafiz Wahba. Mr. Laithwaite, India Office. Mr. Ward. Mr. Malcolm. I. The first subject to be discussed was the question of the eastern and south eastern frontiers of Saudi Arabia. '''' M r . RENDEL said that no further progress appeared for the moment to be possible, and that it was now for each side to consider the arguments put forward by the other. His Majesty's Government, for their part, would await the statement which Fuad Bey had promised at the last meeting regarding the dims or tribal areas of the three and a half tribes claimed by King Abdul Aziz, with particular reference to the southern sector of the boundary proposed by His Majesty's Government. Mr. Rendel said that it would be particularly useful if Fuad Bey could accompany this statement with a map which could show roughly (in, say, gradations of shading or colour) the areas claimed as exclusively, predominantly or only partially inhabited, or wandered over, by particular tribes. FUAD BEY HAMZA explained that he would have difficulty in meeting this latter request, but that he hoped shortly to have ready a list of over 150 names of wells, water-holes, &amp;c., showing to which tribes and sections or sub-sections of tribes they were regarded as belonging. M r . RENDEL expressed the hope that the statement might be available as soon as possible; but he explained that it would, of course, have to be referred to the British authorities in the Gulf and at Aden, so that it might be some weeks before His Majesty's Government could reply to it. II. M r . RENDEL then said that he wished to speak to Fuad Bey about the SaudUriockade of Koweit, or rather, since Fuad Bey did not like that term, about tKe^roBTem oF~the^~ecMomic relations between Saudi Arabia and Koweit. He began by outlining to Fuad Bey the information contained in the latest telegrams from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf regarding the position reached in the local conference which had recently been taking place at Koweit between the delegates of the sheikh and those of King Abdul Aziz. It appeared from these telegrams that, while the King was ready to adopt the Sheikh of Koweit's suggestion of a customs and manifest system, he had instructed the Saudi delegates to insist as a condition that the Sheikh of Koweit should give a guarantee that no single smuggler from Koweit would be allowed to cross the border. In the event of this guarantee failing on more than three occasions to prove effective, the Saudi Government would terminate any agreement reached. This guarantee the Koweit delegates had naturally been unable to give. They had, however, promised to give instead an undertaking on Koweit's honour that Koweit would do her best to stop smuggling. At this stage the Saudi delegates had explained that they had no authority to go beyond the King's orders. They had consequently closed down the negotiations and returned to Nejd. [456 e— 1] bMr. Rendel pointed out that there was no legal obligation on a country having low tariffs to prevent smuggling into a country whose tariffs were high. The problem was one of frequent occurrence and, to take an example on a very much larger scale, had occurred between His Majesty's Government and the United States Government in the days of prohibition in the United States. On that occasion His Majesty's Government, though under no legal obligation to prevent the export of liquor to the United States, had, in the interests of good relations, voluntarily agreed to come to an arrangement under which they co-operated to check liquor smuggling. In a small way the position was analogous in Koweit, where the sheikh had now offered to co-operate for the purpose of checking smuggling into Saudi Arabia. But it was quite impossible for any country, even the most highly organised, to guarantee not to allow a single smuggler through. The Saudi Government's demand could therefore only be described as unreasonable. Mr. Rendel regretted that the conference should have broken down in this unsatisfactory manner when agreement appeared to have been reached on the main problem. He wished to repeat that this question of Koweiti-Saudi relations was one to which His Majesty's Government attached particular importance. It was one of the main objects of His Majesty's Government to ensure that Saudi relations with Koweit should now be regularised and set right on the same lines as had been so successfully followed in the case of Saudi relations first with Iraq and then with Transjordan. He hoped, therefore, that Fuad Bey might be able to arrange for the conference to be resumed. M r . LAITHWAITE also stressed the desire of the Secretary of State for India and the Government of India to see this result achieved and the great importance which they attached to the disposal of the question. As regards the Saudi Government's insistence on a guarantee, Mr. Laithwaite said that it seemed clear from the history of the last few years that the Saudi Government were in a position to impose an effective blockade on the land frontier of Koweit and to deal with any persons who might be caught smuggling across that land frontier. That being so, a demand on Koweit for a guarantee such as had been suggested would seem, to say the least of it, superfluous. He drew Fuad Bey's attention to the fact that if the Saudi Government's demands were to be made public they could not fail to show King Abdul Aziz in an invidious light, and indeed might well give the impression that he was not really seeking a settlement. Mr. Laithwaite added that the Saudi delegates' difficulties in negotiating, even with the help of the telegraph, were of course understood by His Majesty's Government, but he reminded Fuad Bey that Koweit was ready to promise on her honour to do her best to stop the smuggling, and he made it clear that His Majesty's Government for their part would do all in their power to ensure that this undertaking was observed. He trusted therefore that Fuad Bey would be able to suggest some way in which the Saudi Government could be induced to relax their insistence on an absolute guarantee. FUAD BEY HAMZA, in reply, explained that, while the Saudi Legation had received some information as to the progress of the negotiations at Koweit, they were not yet in possession of full details as to the points on which those negotiations had broken down. The information now given to him helped to make the position clearer. He now understood that the following proposals had been made :— (a) A system of customs posts through which trade would be canalised. (b) A system of manifests to be operated in conjunction with the system of customs posts. (c) An honourable undertaking by Koweit to do all she could to prevent smuggling across the Saudi border. This having been confirmed, Fuad Bey undertook to make enquiries by tele graph of his Government and expressed the hope that he would shortly be in a position to make some statement on the matter. At this point Mr. Laithwaite withdrew. III. The meeting then proceeded to discuss the future of the Treaty of Jedda and the connected question of the suggested abandonment by His Majesty 's Government of their right of manumission.» 3 M r . REJ s DEL said that he wished first of all to dispose of a misunder standing to which J uad Bey had given expression in conversation with Sir L. Oliphant on the pie\ious day. It appeared that Fuad Bey had gained the impression duung the conversations which were held in London in September 1934, that His Majesty s Government had declared their willingness to renew the Tieaty of Jedda in the manner now proposed by the Saudi Government, but that Fuad Bey had now found, to his surprise and regret, that they had since changed their minds. Mr. Rendel said he was satisfied, and had confirmed from the lecords of the 1934 conversations, that Fuad Bey was under a misapprehension on this point. His Majesty's Government had never taken any decision about the future of the Treaty of Jedda,and had not gone back on anything that had been said to Fuad Bey on that subject last year. He cited once more the three possibilities which had been discussed in 1934 and'which had again been quoted by Sir A. Ryan at the meeting held on the 2nd July. Of these three, the negotiation of an entirely new treaty covering all points at issue and drawn up in accordance with present conditions naturally seemed the most workmanlike. This could, however, only take place when the major questions now outstanding had been settled, ana as it now looked as though a settlement of these questions might take longe/ than had at first been anticipated, the conclusion of such a new comprehensive treaty might in consequence be delayed for a considerable time. This being so he could see no objection in principle to the prolongation of the present treaty in the way suggested by Fuad Bey Hamza, if agreement could be reached in regard to any modifications of the provisions of the Jedda settlement which it was desired at the same time to introduce. Mr. Rendel reminded Fuad Bey that it had been agreed at a previous meeting that the principal topic to be discussed before the Jedda settlement could be prolonged and amended in this way was the question of slavery in relation to His Majesty's right of manumission. He drew attention once more to the strength of public and parliamentary opinion in this country on the subject of slavery, and of the important influence of the anti-slavery societies. It was therefore essential that His Majesty's Government should be able to justify any decision which they might reach to abandon their right of manumission, on the lines contemplated in the original exchange of notes, by being able to show that a new situation now existed in Arabia which rendered the maintenance of that right inappropriate or unnecesary. He added, speaking personally and unofficially, that the draft anti-slavery regulations which Fuad Bey had communicated privately to Sir A. Ryan seemed to him to provide a hopeful basis for further discussion. It had not yet, however, been possible to submit the details of these proposals to the Secretary of State and it would be necessary, before any undertaking could be given to the Saudi Government, to submit to Sir Samuel Hoare a detailed statement showing the precise scope of the proposed Saudi regulations. It was only thus that Ministers would be able to judge whether the new arrangements would be sufficient to enable them to make an adequate defence in Parliament for the abandonment by His Majesty's Government of this important and well-known right. Mr. Rendel suggested that it would be of great assistance from the point of view of further progress if Fuad Bey Hamza could give a firm undertaking that King Abdul Aziz would, when the time came, be ready to promulgate regulations on the lines of those now under discussion. SIR ANDREW RYAN then explained the progress which he had been able to make on the previous day in a conversation with Fuad Bey Hamza (see separate record in E 4163/325/25) and gave it as his opinion, subject to one or two difficult points, that a promising position had now been reached as regards slavery. There were, however, other points which needed consideration in connexion with the future of the Treaty of Jedda, some of which had already been raised by the Saudi Government. He mentioned the question of the arms traffic as an example. He pointed out, however, that, if only in view of the close questioning which His Majesty's Government must be prepared to face, the problem of slavery was the most serious. FUAD BEY HAMZA again pressed for an assurance that Flis Majesty's Government would in principle be prepared to prolong the Treaty of Jedda. M r . RENDEL replied that, while he was not yet authorised to give a formal assurance to this effect, he did not think that His Majesty's Government would [456 e—1] b 2be likely to raise anv objection in principle to an exchange of notes which would amount to a declaration that neither party would denounce the Treaty ot Jedda for a period of years, provided that, as he had said before, agi eement could be reached on any modification in the provisions of the settlement which the baudi Government wished to take this opportunity to secure. The discussion then reverted to the question of slavery and manumission. FUAD BEY HAMZA explained that this question could only be pursued on a basis of complete confidence between the two parties. He realised that His Majesty's Government would require to have advance knowledge of the anti- slavery legislation which the Saudi Government intended to promulgate. He doubted, however, whether the Saudi Government would be willing to communi cate the exact terms of the proposed legislation to His Majesty s Government. He suggested that His Majesty's Government should be content with an understanding as to what should be covered by the legislation and leave the actual drafting to the Saudi Government. Fuad Bey again emphasised the importance of avoiding any impression that internal Saudi legislation was being carried out at the dictation of His Majesty's Government. M r . RENDEL explained that His Majesty's Government fully realised the importance of avoiding this impression. On the other hand, they must be m a position adequately to defend their abandonment of the right of manumission, and this could only be done if the legislation, in consideration of which the right of manumission would, in fact, be abandoned, could be regarded as satisfactory. They could not, therefore, give any undertaking about the eventual abandonment of their right without precise knowledge of the provisions of the contemplated legislation. It was, however, just as much in the interest of the Saudi Govern ment as of His Majesty's Government that the legislation should be actually enacted before His Majesty's Government abandoned their right of manumission, since if His Majesty's Government could say that new legislation had been voluntarily enacted by King Abdul Aziz and that a new situation had theieby been produced, and actually existed, which justified them in abandoning their right of manumission, it would look far less as though a bargain had been stiuck than if the right of manumission were abandoned simultaneously with, or m advance of, the promulgation of the legislation in question. FUAD BEY HAMZA explained that the Saudi Government must have a private guarantee that if the legislation were passed His Majesty's Government would then abandon their right of manumission. SIR A. RYAN restated the procedure, which he himself had had in mind and which, if adopted, would involve three stages, viz., (1) a private but binding- agreement that, if the Saudi Government promulgated legislation on certain lines, His Majesty's Government would renounce the right of manumission; (2) the promulgation of the Saudi legislation; and (3) the public renunciation of the right of manumission as part of the suggested arrangements for prolonging the validity of the Treaty of Jedda. M r . RENDEL saw no difficulty in regard to the private guarantee suggested bv Fuad Bey provided His Majesty's Government were satisfied as to the nature of the legislation. Indeed, if they were not, the position would be impossible, as they would not then be able to make an adequate defence before Parliament of their abandonment of their right. Although the exchange of notes might not actually need ratification, and Parliament was not technically concerned with ratifications, it would be necessary for any new agreement to be laid before Parliament, and it would never do if parliamentary criticism could not be adequately met. On the other hand, if His Majesty's Government were supplied with full and precise information as to the contemplated legislation. Ministers would then be able to judge whether that legislation would enable them to meet parliamentary criticism and to carry Parliament with them when the right of manumission'came to be abandoned. The question whether the modification oi a treaty instrument which had been ratified would itself need ratification— i.e., whether the proposed exchange of notes would have to be subject to ratifica tion — was a question somewhat outside his province, on which the necessary technical advice would be obtained., ^ HAMZA thcn said that if His Majesty's Government, rather than prolong the Treaty of Jedda as proposed, preferred to wait until an entirely new treaty eould be negotiated, or for any other reason did not wish to prolono- the tiea y in the manner now proposed, the Saudi Government would not obiect In that event, he suggested that the question of slavery and manumission could be of^ddaat all 111 ^ se P arate exc hange of notes without bringing in the Treaty a Kw?' out that tllis was an entirely new suggestion, and doubted whether it would be a satisfactory one. In practice the Jedda settlement, ^ the Treaty of Jedda and notes attached thereto, had always been treated as a whole. There might well be serious objections to any attempt to deal with the settlement piecemea^, and he thought that His Majesty's Government would probab y prefer Fuad Bey's original suggestion, that the Treaty of Jedda should be prolonged and agreed modifications introduced by an exchange of notes covering all the ground. &amp; ^ This led to a further discussion of the prolongation or modification of the Government ^ ^ regarding purchases of arms by the Saudi M r RSNDEL suggested, and FUAD BEY agreed, that this was a point of torm rathei than of substance. There was no question of His Majesty's Govern ment treating the Saudi Government in a less favourable way than any other friendly country m a similar position. The question of arms traffic was not dealt with m his department, and he would have to consult the competent authorities before saying more than this. By the words ct in a similar position ' he meant rTTl re certam coimtri f 1 s where, in the interests of the Governments concerned, it nad been internationally agreed that arms should only be supplied to the Governments themselves or to importers specifically approved by those Govern ments^ the intention of this arrangement had been to prevent arms being: used by rebel tribesmen, and he cited the revolt of Ibn Rifada as one where the limitation ot the import of arms to approved importers operated to the advantage o mg Abdul Aziz. If then there were some such general international limitation applicable to countries in the same position as Saudi Arabia, he did not think any difficulty need be caused by provision being made for it in anv arrangements between His Majesty's Government and the Saudi Government it would be time enough, however, to decide what were the most suitable arrange ments on this point when agreement had been reached on the main question of the prolongation of the Jedda settlement and of the abandonment of His Maiestv's Government's right of manumission. k 1 the treaty^ US ^ 0n WaS a ^ S0 ma ^ 0 c l ues ^ on prevailing language of RENDEL said that this was also mainly a formal and technical point on which the competent authorities would have to be consulted in due course. At the conclusion of the meeting SIR A. RYAN undertook to produce a single comprehensive statement of the position reached in his discussions on slavery with Fuad Bey, showing the lines on which the Saudi Government mio-ht be prepared to legislate. Steps might also be taken, he thought, to consult other ciepartments of the Foreign Office regarding the arms traffic and the technical questions oi form that had been mentioned. Q/. o. f z. 471-3./ir, ^• /r /' ?. 3 J ' A- ,. (3) Saudi 3Tb c lead e of K owe i t. THE SHEIKH said that in 1929 he had received a letter from H.M.G. concerning his trade with lejd, promising that if His Excellency would prevent help being given to Faisal al Duwish, H.M.G. would endeavour to reach a solution of his trade difficulties with King Abdul Aziz. His Excellency had carried out his part and had even fought with Al Duwish' s people, but H.M.G. , for their part, had as yet failed to make any progress towards a solution of the blockade. A Saudi deputation of 83 persons had recently visited Koweit, but His Excellency thought that no good had come of the conference which had taken place. MR.LAITHmiTE said that for some time H.M.G. had been trying hard to reach a solution of the blockade question with King; Abdul Aziz, and that, as the Sheikh would remember the proposal for a conference regarding it, which had now materialised, had originated with the late Sir Hugh Biscoe. He reminded the Sheikh that matters had been held up for more than a year owing to a misunderstanding about certain correspondence between His Excellency and the King of Saudi Arabia. After briefly recalling the proceedings at tne recent Conference at Koweit, he said that H.M.G. regarded it as satisfactory that the Saudi delegation had gone so far as agreeing even on the principle of a. system of manifests and Customs posts. H•M.G. entirely agreed that the Saddi demand for a guarantee as a condition of agreement on tnis basis, that not a single Koweit smuggler would cross the frontier was quite unreasonable. The India Office and Foreign/10. Foreign Olfice had already made strong representations to Fuad Bey Hamza regarding this guarantee in which they had emphasised that Koweit was however prepared to give an honourable undertaking to do all in its power to suppress smuggling. They would continue to do their utmost for Koweit in the matter. MR. REETDEL said that only that morning he had again spoken to .Fuad Bey Kamza and that Fuad Bey had telegraphed on the subject to King Abdul Aziz. His Excellency expressed thanks to H.M.G. for the action which they had taken.53/54 , X 106 TQ le gram R 30 Fro™ H .m* a Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London. To H .m 's Charge d»Affai res, Jedda. Eo.91 Repeated to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla# Political Resident, Bushire, Ho. 47 Political Agent, Kuwait. Bated 31st July received 1 st August 1935. \0 C \ „ h' Your telegram Ho. 132. 1» I am reluctant to continue this corres- -pondence but proposals summarised in paragraphs 4 and 5 of your tele gran under reference require some answer. Subject to concurrence of Government of India and Political Resident you should, unless you see objection, reply in conciliatory terms that it was pro- -ceedings of party themselves which created impression, which His Majesty's Government are glad to find was mistak- -en, that object of their visit v/as to put pressure upon certain tribes to leave Kuwait territory in order that zakat should be collected from them. You should add that far from being treated discourteously ,they were at once allowed to return to Saudi Arabia and that in any case His Majesty's Government and Shaikh adhere to the view that there is no reason to modify local practice in regard to persons crossing frontier in either direction for ordinary purposes of intercourse. Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.5 3/54 //y ^ Telegram R 27 From Political Resident, Bushire* H.M's Secretary of S^ate for India, To London# Repeated to H.M's Charge d*Affaires, Jedda# Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Political Agent, Kuwait# Hb. 679 Dated 2nd August 1935* / Your telegram Ho* 47. I see no objection to closing incident by some reply in conciliatory terms but I venture to suggest that it might be well to avoid words ••which His Majesty^ Government are glad to find was mistaken'# Phrase may be construed and possibly quoted as stating that His Majesty's Government think that blame (see first paragraph of Jedda telegram No# 132 .of July 14th) lies upon Kuwait and I feel that Shaikh would regard it as unfair to him# Resident#53/54 Telegram IU30 From H«K t s Secretary of Stf).te for Foreign Affairs, London* To His Majesty's Charge (^Affaires, Jedda t Uo.92 Repeated. Government of India, Foreign and Political Department # Simla, Fo.76 Politicrl Resident, Bushire, Political Agent, Kuwait* Dated 3rd received 4th August 1935. No. 49 Bushire telegram No.679 to India Office. You may omit phrase objected to &lt; • SECRETARY OF STATE FOR - FCREIGH AFFAIRS ^7&gt;7s-53/54 Telegram IU27 Prom Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. To Secretaiy of State for India, London. Repeated His Ma v 1 esty• s Charge' d'Affaires, Jedda. Political Resident, Bushire» Political Agent, Kuwait. Bfo. 1966 Dated 4th received 5th August 1935. f 17 L Bushire telegram of August 2nd # Fo.679» For reasons already given when commenting on Iraqi - Kuwait problem (see our t elegram of the 20th July, 1784) we think that reply to Ibn Saud should not be construbble in any way as withdrawal* He therefore support suggestion of Political Resident# • iih) 5 3 /g I 7'~ s—O *7s— . FOEKION/ n Telegram XX. 5^^ H.M 1 s Secretary of State for foreign .x Affairs, London* To H.M 1 s Charge d*Affaires, Jedda. Ub. 94 Repeated to Government of India, foreign and Political Bepar tmeiit, Simla. Political Resident, Bushire. Ko. 50 Bated 8th received 9th August 1935# .,v /y / Please see 5th section of Record of final Conversation with Fuad Hamza enclosed in my despatch Mo« 211 and Political Resident's despatches of June 28th and June 3rd. Saudi condition is of course quite un- -reasenable and Hig Majesty's Government have informed Shaikh during his visit to London that this is their view. It is therefore essential to maintain pressure on Saudi Government. Position of His Majesty's Government and y Government of India is clearly stated in the Record of the O fourth Conversation enclosed in my despatch 19 5 and you should take an early opportunity of enquiring in writing how the matter now stands in the light of conversations in ^ondon and JHaad s reference ^tb his Government. You should draw attention once more to importance which His Majesty 's Government and Government attach to settlement of this natter and urge Saudi Government to agree to Shaikhs proposals# If you see no objection you should repeat the statement made to Buad at the fourth Conversation that His Majesty's Government would do all they could to ensure fulfi Iment2. fulfilment of the honourable undertaking offered by the Shaikh which in their view is all that can be reasonably demanded# Secretary of State for foreign Affairs. 49/1/ 4. r'inistry of foreign Affairs, Fscea. i-afar 13-34# 29th i/:a^ 1956. v Your Kxce 11 eney 9 I have received -our letter of ray 19tli 1935 o.75 (l27S/s;;8/ii) in ir .'hicii jou refer to your conversation with 1'usuf vaein on ■ ay 1.5tlx 1955, ana in which you mention the particulars of the entry of what you term an^ armed party into r.uvait territory about ray 6th anu jroteet on behalf of the British Government against the entry of the said persons i to Kuwait. i inform Your Excellency that my ■loverment aid not fail to make enquiries concerning,; the incident after you con unicated it to xusuf Yaain on ]'ay 15th, and they are stilJ investigating the matter, because they do not desire that there should he any incident whatnoever be tire en them and the Sritish ov -nment or betv;e n '.-lem rip-'.;.heykh Imad t \l t)'..;ir, r* the intimate friend of if# , my lord the -. Ing# In vi w of the facts established during the investigation by my Gov rnnent I have to ex -ore as m tl deep regret at the Cona adopted over triio eimple incident i .e. in framing it so as to mean the entry of an armed force, intended to violate the sovereign aut ority of the Iie^kh of Kuwait, vhile nothing of the sort has occurred. hat ban hapx &gt;ened ir only one of the every day occurrences v /iiici-. has taken place between the two countries for a long time past, namely t ie movement of subject and messengers with their arms Ire twee n the two countries /without!Uh without previous an .lication. -lit '..-'kx qb i-soiiS 'co whom you z*©i.'6p^ wejcc» as it licis reported to us, four and not six, and did not enter Kuwait to exercise U eir .audi Vra'b authority in Kuwait ter-'itory, 'but were from, among tHe retainers or the anir of Has®, sent by him (their ••.air) to gather our beuuin subjects at a certain watrring place with a view to col ecting y&gt; .afeat 11 , ■ laving rc.;ard to the {unintelligible word usual o -dinar./ word for^soise'! possibly a mistake for Mi stance* or some unusual word meaning ^sterility') places in the territory of the .'hamnar ana the good pasture in the territory of the /:ut4r , they removed, the l utair 'beau in away from their watering places so that the lhanr ar might cone to them for a few clays, in order that they may be able to accomplish the taking or the ^akat' 1 from t em. men the detachment readied the place anl found that the -ha- - -•ar heciuin were -till within the frontiers of f await and it was not poeeible to undertake the collection of ,J ialcat** there. :.1\e covi ander of the force then sent his messengers to ' uwait in order to send a telei ram to 'jair h dull ah Ibn Jaluwi to tell him of the facts, and to rec ive his inetructions as to what he should do. f ' , ie way to he followed by th&lt; messenger© sent to Kuwait of course can be n- otuer tlian via ubaihiya and Jahra. It is possible that those mess, ngers might have informed the ham ..ar and hafir subjects of .I • the King, whom they met or- their way, of the place o the M :;akat^ officials in order that they mi ^it hasten to perform it so that t ey ould 'hot he liable to punishment in the 'uture. .?bey then went on their %?ay from ■ subainiya to Jalira 1. tending to go to Kuwait to send the telegram. Jn their way however they met a motor car in veeice. three of them drove to fu ait, entered it and asked An-hafisi to telegraph to the mir he 'Vbdullah Ibn Jaluwi about t. ieir ease, so that/3toqp might give them the necessary instruct ions. f ie loverment /ofof Kuwait however informed n -Hafisi tliat those people nhould leave the territory of Kuwait* ?hey obeys, and leftdt. It will thus appear to iOur 'Txcellency from tlxis that there was no intended invasion of the territory of /m.-ait as you stated to Yucuf Yasin in your conversation wit:;, him. /here has also been no interference in the local affairs of uwait by anned 'orees of the ^i-overnnent of , the King Abdul Asia# The wholt matter was? that four per cons entered uwait to make a com unication -mich is a cuetoroary tiling between the two countries# 'ee ■€n t .-err of le l/ hness the ■heykh of uv /ait always cone into the ter stories of . the King and go to Riyadh and :nsa 1th tJieir arms. ..-n nany oc- asions mire of Al-a «-^abah then selves and nuiaer-ms troops o'' - the mir of Ku. ait enter with tlneir ams into t e ter itches of the .3 audi Arab kingdom » without .-ipi-^lyin or permission, to hunt and shoot and no bhjectiom? huvc heen raised. If the Qoverme t of ] uwait desire to p.revent our subject© or neseengers from entering their territories v/ita or without their arms except by permission fron them, and would like us to treat then on a recinroeal basis in this respect, we are prepared to do so out my Oov^rnment think thai this is contrary to the spirit of friendship existing between the two countries and also contrary to the endeavours they ■ : - are exerting to pro ote the economic relations between the two CO ntries. sy also think that the treatment which those messengers have been given does not agree with the spirit o ..''riendship and the eealings between the tiro countries. In conse'mence of the refusal of tin British Government and the heyhh of /uwait, orders have been i sued at once to the &lt;mir of hasa to prevent anyone at all ent rin; ^iwait, with or without arms. ■' y jve• nment request that the aut' or ities concerned in uwait should prevent every olae whether Government officials or their subjects t. era, entering the territories of the •&gt;overment .•■f : .l- • the : :ing with or without arms, .hether /forfor hunting, shooting or* sending message s f fo^ any reason whatsoever, exec t after- ar-:&gt;lying for permission, until an agreement has been made as to tiie method vftrich may remove the bad Impression caused 'by the Oroverrr'cnt of Kuwait in dep rting the me 'engers of the mir of /asa* ;uch ictioi has created confusion amongst the tribes and has b&gt; n /.-eyard ed as an hostile action on the r&gt;art of the :&gt;oTcrn?8&gt; nt of j Kuwait at a tine when my ■iovvrn'- cnt, to the exti 'emc limit of tneir ability, are trying-; to make securer xm. close and fr 1 e ru1 y re 1 a t i on s • j ease ace -&gt;t my ^rofoundest re :&gt;ecta, I ' * d.,, e.ysal.• ./to IJ&gt; ' V lu CONFIDENTIAL. No.C-253. / rOLlTI C4L AG3ICY, ICUsviilT • The 10th August 1935, From Lt.-Colonel H.R.P # Dickscn, G.I.JI., Political Agent, Kuwait; i p' To I ^ £ '33 The Hon^ole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire. 1 \ ^ y Sir, Letter of thanks received by the Political xxgent, Kuwait, from i :-#L.»j£ing Bin oaud t s delegates to the Blockade Conference. ^ , £—//* X /y/. *- i have the honom' to enclose for your information and that of the Government of India translation of a letter dated Riyath, the 13th July 1955, which I received yesterday (8.8*35) from ohaikh Khalid ibn al ialid and Shaikh Hamad as Sulaiman, who were recently here with the Saudi 'Wafd'. 2. I have replied direct acknowledging the letter, and have expressed the deep appreciation felt by myself and my wife for the many kind things that have been said about us. 3. As the letter had a definitely personal touch about it, I decided not to send my reply through you or H.M 1 s Minister, Jedda. I trust I have done right. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. U rs l ) Lt. -Colonel, Polit i cal Agent, iCuwai t. P ATranslation of a letter dated the IZth Rabi 1 Thani r . L j 1354 (15.7.25) from Messrs: iaialid xibdul Walid and Hamad as Sulaiman, Riyadh, to the Politioel Agent, Kuwait. After Compliments, We 'beg to inform Your iixoellency that we arrived in Riyadh on Tuesday the 9th instant (10.7.35) in the best of health. This time we had no trouble on the way. We were received in audience by His Majesty the King the same day that we re_ached Riyadh. We gave faithful account to His Majesty the King of all the courtesy, kindness and consideration that was shown to us in Kuwait both by its Government , its Ameers and its notables. We also in special manner explained to His Majesty all that we experienced at Your Excellency^ kind hands, of courtesy, good treatment and assistance generally, and we made a point of telling him of your genuine personal attachment, and admiration for His Majesty. His Majesty was very much pleased with same. There is no doubt that His Majesty, (and you yourself are aware of this trait) has certain specific views on men, which never miss the target. He knows well your feelings towards him; and he genuinely appreciates the same. He thanks you for this affection and friendship, and for all the good treatment you showed tqfus. WeflTor our part also, seize the opportunity to express to you our grateiul thanks for aj-l that we experienced of your kindness, generosity and honourable dealings. We also thank Mrs.Cickson for her kind welcome and sympathy, and for her very gentle manners and courtesy towards us. May God protect you all and grant that you enjoy a happy and pleasant life. Usual Ending.Confldentia 1 No•640-S of 1935• British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Busiiire, the 20th August 1936. To The Political Agent, Kuwait. ,/L&gt; Memorandum * Reference paragraph 3 of your letter No.C-263 dated the 10th August 1936. 2. There is no objection to your having replied direct to the letter from Khalid Abdul ^alid and Hamad as Sulaiman. sd. G. Loch, Lieut.-Colonel• Officiating rolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested . t for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 641-S of 1935. 0 (y I ~ The Hod hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents bis com pliments to 1. His Majesty's Secretary of State for Inuia, London• 2. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. 3. His Majesty f s Charge dlAffaires, Jedda. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). 0 British Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. Dated ... 20.th. • August. 1935 Rejferenee to previous correspoateuce : Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. • Letter Ho,C-253 dated the 10th August 1936 from the Political Agent, Kuwait, with enclosure. . Memoranatim Ho.640-3 of 20th August .936 to the x olitical Agent, Kuwait. t Letter of thanks received by Uie political Agent, Kuwait, from E.M.King Bin Sard's delegates to the Blockade Conference. r j ■ &gt; Copy forwarded, with compliments, to the iolitical Agent, Kuwait', for information.4 Iersonal and Private• The Residency f Bishire, 20th .^u^ust, . 936, ! ^ ' X .sill you kindly refer to your !Ju# C-^53 dated the 10th August .335 • In sending on a copy of your letter to the Govermaent or India, the India Office ai.d Jedda, I have omitted the vjords ' : and that of the government of Imia' as it is not strictly speaking correct for a political Agent to say to whom a letuer to the olitical Resident is to be communicated* t .Col. H. R.F.Dicks on, C .1 .E., Kuwait. ) I 1 &gt;Wv&amp; f 53/ ;V 'Lfl-0^ 1 1 felegram XX. Pion Eis Majesty's Ciiarfje d'Affaires. Jedda. To His Majesty's Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London, No. 141. \\ Bepeated Government a India, Simla, Ho. 93. Political Resident, Bushire, No. 167. Dated fanhnm! 2&amp;tk (received 2£'th )Augiist 1935. ,\ \ . w \S 2!y iiatediatelj preceding belegiBm. Gonversation over dispensaries led Yusuf lasin to say that he had also been comissionedr by the King to discuss certain poinbs in Kuwait-Hijas Bailway Note ( mut. ) he also encjuired vmether they were to hear from no regarding Bahrain. He was atixious to fix our next meeting for :his morning but I rode him off until tomorrow dien I propose to note what he says but inform him that I have no instructions yet lo discuss question further. Charge dUffajres.telegram From To Repeated. xx H.M.'s Charge d f Affaires, Jedda. Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs London • No .144• Government of India, Simla, ITo # 93. rolitical Resident, H.M.S.Lupin. No.170. Dated 27th (received 28th) August 1936♦ * it o ' ? ^ Uy telegram No.141, KUWAIT. Yusuf Yasin this morning stated that since incident of armed incursion and breakdown of conference smuggling t± into Samdi Arabia had intensified. Whole caravans had been engaged and had been confiscated and smugglers severely punished. He alleged that Kuwaitis (not necessarily Shaikh of Kuwait) did not desire an agreement as present position too lucrative. He asserted that dues were levied at gates of Kuwait itself on goods leaving town which everyone knew were to be smuggled i.e. smuggling received official countenance. 2. Ibn Saud had decided to take strong measures but I was being informed for information of His Majesty's Government and Kuwait before they were^ introduced. - In future until customs dispute was settled any Kuwaiti/entering Saudi Arabia would be regarded as 'criminal' and severely dealt with and tribes harbouring trespassers would be punished. Yusuf Yasin said that note embodies above mut &gt; he dsjhowever ¥ mut. me. 3. i replied that I much regretted view I had now heard. I expressed emphatically mut. Kuwait had made sincere attempts to arrive at settlement recapitulating their proposals ard. Eis Majesty's Government's willingness to support Kuwait in carrying out an honourable undertaking. I described demand of Ibn Saud in regard to prohibition of smuggling as one no government could accept or carry out (as Fuad was informed /-2 informed in London,- • . I exuressed the opinion that if smuggling was unfortunately on the increase acceptance of Kuwait suggestions would be best calculated to check it. In stressing importance attached to whole question by His Majesty's Government I said that action now mut. in preventing free miivement over frontier ignored views of His Majesty's Government and Kuwait expressed in two Legation notes. 4. Yusuf Yasin said I saw Saudi reply I should gather that Ibn Saud subscribed to principle of freedom of movement over frontier as was age long practice. Present restrictions were provisional* 5• He continued that he was authorised to discuss question further with me by personal exchange of views. Speaking ^generally he expressed the opinion that Kuwait was disinclined to prohibit smuggling into Saudi Arabia as she would also find herself obliged to control her smuggling with Iraq a traffic twice as extensive. v/ere Kuwait to cease smuggling direct into Saudi Arabia trafiic k would still reach this country via Iraq. questions raised and in any case had better await promised note and inform you of its contents. He suggested early meeting but 1 could not ai courage him# /ou might I saio. wish to ?see text of note aid. would have to consult Depai t- ments concerned in question oi this importance. Yus dt Yasln hoped for an early reply. 6 I informed him I had no authority to discuss - Charge d*Affaires. r5 No. 1845/226/108. /■? HTS Majesty's Charge d*Affaires at J edci.a ii presents his compliments to the ' • +. Per ^an Gulf at Bus Ire 1 lent in and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. Bri tish J.eMa* PijQ^ : R E REG'^^NCY. ' NO-.- np.fn i_/ c c L V_/ . CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS 193..P* \ '' J A i io -I Reference to previous correspotiden.ee : ' ' * foreign Of rice teleeran No. 92 of 3.3.35. to Jedda. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. TO: Saudi Minister for Foreign Affairs, note No.130 of 5.8 .35. Saudi armed party in ^uv/ait territory. 3475 557S (2) ♦opies o this despatch have been sent to the Foreign Of'ice, Government of India and Kuwait.53/54 Telegram XX* From H.M f s Charge d'Affaires, Jedda. To Secretary of ^tate for foreign Affairs, London# No. 153 Repeated to Government of India, Foreign and Political Bepartment, Simla. Ko« 95 Political Resident, Aishire. ^o» 183 Political Agent, Kuwait. Ko. 134 Bated 4rd received 4th September 1935• My telegram ^o* 144. Saudi note received yesterday. Following is gist from a rougib preliminary translation. 2, After reiterating that incursion of four armed men did not justify notes (of Legation) and that had not men been ill-treated there by giving appearance of hostile intent on their part there would have been no incident; note proceeds that Saudi Government do not object to 'return* to frontier procedure previously existing but that procedure has differed at diiferent times- They sbare the view that armed forces of one country should not interfere in the internal affairs of another and desire detailed proposals for a procedure to be subject of an agreement in order to eliminate mis- •understanding. 3&gt; u 0 te regrets that after return of Saudi delegation smuggling has been intensified. Saudi Govermnent have been oonpelled to transfer forces from near Hail to the Persian Gulf Coast and thus incurred expense to prevent loss to Saudi merchants which extreme action2. action of Kuwait Government has increased. Saudi Government to reduce this expenditure to some degree and to put an end to this hostile practice will adopt following measures pending agreement with, Kuwait# Action is not beiAg taken out of hostility to KuTisait but to protect Saudi finances and merchants. Saudi Govern- -ment therefore propose to instruct all tribal leaders that all goods coming from Kuwait shall be confiscated and that all individuals from Kuwait, unless previous notification be given to Saudi authorities, shall be stopped. This arrangement to remain in force until satisfactory agreement is reached on lines suggested by ^audi delegation to Kuwait. 5. Text follows by bag* Charge d*Affaires/ \ ^ ' ^ i Telegram XX # Froin H.M*a Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London# To H.M*a Charge d'Affai rea, Jedda. Hb. 102 Repeated to Goverament of India, foreign and Political Department, Simla* Political Resident, Bushire# i^o. 55 Dated 5th received 6th September i935 # . U' U ' : / Your telegrams i^os. 144 and 153. I approve of your language to Yusuf Yasin. Subject to concurrence of Government of India and Political Resident you should reply to Saudi note on following lines explaining that His Majesty's Government have received tele, -graphic summary of note. His Majesty's Government have nothing to add to views expressed in yoair note of 5th jS* August about armed incursion incident which they regard as closed* As regards blockade they are surprised to learn of alleged increase of smuggling from Kuwait and intention of Saudi Government to restrict intercourse with Kuwait still further. As Fuad Hamza was informed in London His Majesty Government consider that Saudi Govern- -ment demand for guarantee from Kuwait that no smuggler shall ever cross frontier is unreasonable and they regret to observe that no consideration has apparently been given ^ to your note of August 12th# His Majesty f s Government desire to draw attention of Saudi Government once again to the importance they a ttach to settlement of this question and to proposals inTelegram XX. 5,3:0113 Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Kuwait# Ho« 765 Dated 7th September 1935. 1-'° Important . Jedda telegram of 3rd September, 13b. 1841 Please telegraph if possible to-day with- -out repeating elsewhere whether anything has occurred which might justify allegation that smuggling has been intensified since break down of negotiations. Re sident. 453/54 Telegram XX From Politic&amp;l Agent, Kuwait# To Political -Resident, Eushire# Ko. 271 Dated 7th received 8tJi September 1935. C? Jedda telegrarn to Foreign Office lio.153, Ify comments are as follows; 2» Frontier procedure has never differed in the past so Saudi Government * s remark is not understood, 3 (&gt; This statement is entirely untrue. Actual facts are that immediately on return of Saudi delegation last July and clearly because of Ibn Saud*s annoyance' with Kis Majesty's Government for note regarding armed incursion, blockade measures were redoubled to a degree of ferocity, hitherto unknown® 4o Measures now proposed were actually put into force on July 20th# in post (mut} See Intelligence Summary No. 14 POLITICAL53/54 Telegram XX From Political Agent, Kuwait# Political Resident, Bushire. To Dated 7th received 8th September 1935 Ho, 272 Your telegram of 7th September, 23b« 765. Only record of case of smuggling sinae v ' breakdown of conference is that mentioned in paragraph 'A v ' x 140 (e) of Kuwait Intelligence Summary. Saudi Gov- -Qrnn3ent , s remarks that smuggling has been intensified is definitely untrue and have been made obviously to justify extremely severe blockade measures already in- -troduced on July 20th. Poli tical IbCj53/54 Telegram XX. Political Resident, Bushire. To Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla# Repeated to H.M # s Secretary of State for India, London# H.M*s Charge d*Affaires, jedda. Ifc. 768 Dated 8th September 1925# • &lt; (A Secretary of S&gt;ate for Foreign Affairs♦ telegram of 5th September Ko. 102 to Jedda* Political Agent, Kuwait, telegraphs {see also Intelligence Summary paragraph 140 b but I await later information by post) that measures proposed by Saudi Government see Jedda telegram of 3rd September Spa ^o. 153 were actually put in force on July 2Cth. :• \v V? 2. His information does not bear out allegation of intensified smuggling which seems to be attempt to justify severe blockade measures introduced immediately after return of Saudi delegation# 3, i agree with terms of note to Saudi Government# Re si dent# Copy sent to Kuwait under P.L.iTo# 710-S, dated 9/9/35#er/zi ■C' Extract from Kuwait Intelligence Nummary iuo.12 for tiie period from 16th to 5lst July 193b. x x x x x x 140. Bin Sa * ud* s Blockade . (a) This was once again definitely tightened up after the departure of the Saudian v/afd, but probably was due not so much to the breakdown of the Conference at Kuwait, so much as to the annoyance felt by Bin Sa f ud at His Majesty^ Government's protest in the matter of the violation of the Kuwait frontier on 6 th May. [ See paragraph 125 of Sumnary ISo.ll). lb) fhe situation at the end of July 1935 there! ore is that ^ (a) no trade whatsoever is allowed between ^uwai- and Nejd. (bj Every single article going from^Kuwait to Sa^udi Arabia however slaall is ipso f acto declared contraband. (c) ^o Hejdi, townsmen or tribesmen}including women ca.n visit Kuwait without first obtaining a permit from Bin Sa'ud or one of his Governors, (d) No Kuwaiti may visit liejd unl ess he can show that he is going to see a relative there or is taking a present to the King* Anyone with a gift for Bin Sa 1 ud is always allowed to pass. I'here is actually nothing new in the above situation, things have only been tightened up. Conditions being as they are it is not quite understood why His Excellency Fuad Hamza in London objected to the term 'Blockade of Kuwait', for a more complete blockade than that existing already would be hard to find. (c)A s eon&lt;J line of blockade posts is now reported to have been established at the wells of Jarab-Artawiyeh and Hafar al Atz in the Dahena region, ihese are in addition to the posts at Al Maqta a -Jarriya Ilya-Safa- and Kafar al Bat in,which we may call the first line. The 1st line (less Hafar al Batin) is under Hamud al Bagaawi.-2- The 2nd line is under our old friend Ibn Arfaj• got_e. The post at Hafar al Batin is found from Hail and is ' '' under the command of 'al Khuderi'. (d) Apart from the above, motor car patrols now regularly visit the various H Dfa.hals H of the Summan region VMutair country), ^hese H dahals n number 18 and consist of natural underground caverns leading off into subterranean cisterns, all of which have v/ater of sorts in them. They are qutte useless for watering camel herds, or flocks of sheep, because of the difficulty of getting v /ater to the surface ( a man has to crawl many feet underground to the various cisterns with his goat skin to get one 'fill') but are eminently suitable places for small parties to draw drinking water from, if they are anxious to avoid the main wells mentioned above and the posts camped thereon. i'he names of the 'dahals' are given below for interests sake • Al Raggas, Al Thaiyib, Ab al Dhaiyan, Al •Jarabi, um al Q,run, Al -^haliya, Al Azaiyir. Um T/archam, Urn Jaand, Bith al Ashari, Al Shamshul, Al Ajaji, Abu Sukhaim, Al laraih, Abu Tuts ha, Ash Shami, Al Muttar, Abu riarma-i-a* (e) A Mutair party with a few bags of rice ex Kuwait, is reported to have been tracked down and attacked by a Saudian patrol at Jarab on 18th July (where Gapt.^hakespear was killed), the patrol however was beaten off with the loss of 4 men. i'he smugglers got through to ^as im. x -x- x x x x x ^ ft53/54 Telegram From To Repeated XX His Majesty's Charge d*Affaires, Jedda. His Majesty's Secretary of State for Foreign Afiairs, London, Eo. 192 Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla, No, 112 Political Resident at Kuwait, No, 216 Bated 16th. received 17th October 1935. o 4 lS O y Your telegram 102 and ray despatch 260 of September 17th. Government Note in reply received yesterday. Text, of which following is summary, sent by bag today, S. Saudi Government have no desire to revert to armed incursion incident concerning which sufficient has been said. 3. As to responsibility of present situation Kuwait and not Saudi Government must be ?blamed as latter had not asked to interfere in Kuwait affairs, that they (Saudis) should be responsible for losses caused them by Kuwait# Saudi demand(s) of Ku¥/ , ait were below (limit) and were reasonable as far as it was possible to go. Offer made by Saudi representatives (mut; ed loss to Saudi commerce and government regretted that these sacrifices which they had been prepared to make in their desire for an understanding were characterised as unreasonable. 4. Whenever Kuwait is prepared to guarantee prevention of smuggling on the basis mentioned by Yusuf Yasin to me an agreement will be possible but not unless n anabsolute guarantee of entire prevention be i2iven CHARGE D'AFFAIRES - Copy given to Political Agent, Kuwait.V No. 2179/226/126. an HIS Majesty's Charge d f Affaires a t Jed,a o '' Me '• poiiti0 * 1 '» s tTle ^ onour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Legation, Jedoa. 'NCY. C0iiFiD2N —&gt; .1.0.9.., 193..5, Reference to previou cor res pou-defice % Jedda telegram Ko. 183 jaf-2. 9, 35, Description of Enclosure. / )S 1 Name and Date. Subject. TO: Foreign Office, despatch Ho. 256 of the 10.9.35. -t- enclosure, Kuwait Blockade and Saudi armed incursion into Kuvait,vnr aov t ment ao not oppose a re um to tiie system whicli has existed between the tw couatrie© alrm he time is of ■ihc^lch Mubar-r^, Sheikh Jabir, :he s /kii cma mm&amp;to js-itsaitd ttp tc» p«^©6At t sict ou. &lt;14,,t' ^feno^s have v^..,s^3n In interpreting the? p. aoUee* t tines, it i.-s stated that acte are in aacoManoe Ith to; practice and at times ir.aguiar# ¥e.-&gt; our G venru-nt ugree that it i: not perrltmihle that forces of one 'k&gt;wmm nt should- enter ana exert in lue.aee in -.ny of tlv. internal ^falr« of an. the?' ccmatry but if we re ui -e to ta e action in egard to any of our subjects r-.- 1 siaiini«: in ••afvai.t, f4 or example, the mess .nifer fur t^at -vj jjoee? wu m ■ Ku ait ? :;n.d refers to the Sheyte in the n tier aa h:@ been current pi-actice in he paet, and ¥;ae v^r -a* hat our u-.-vem^-nt d, Gi *e&gt; owver, is a detail cl e pl.tnation of the p aetioe o Khi*:h the ayate:•. can rooe d so hat t^er.s m:..y be no mi-^unacra andin^# na it isa thirjj demanu, and an a^peement thereon# I am very sorry to intern you tor the infomation of the Uritisli uoyeroeent that the position in Kuwait after that incident and after the return of the delegation of our Government free Kuwait is that the smui^ling of good© from Kuwait has now greatly increased in quantities and in the number of caravans of smugglers# Thia has compelled our Government to send {mall) forces from the rail frontier to the ^er^ian Oulf coast and In considerat ion of the expenditure which has thereby besn incurred hy our -iove rnment without re a ©on &gt; except to prevent losses from which Saudi merchants will mtf&amp;T owing to the 0ittraw#®8JS©e of the dovemnent of Kuwait in .xei-din^ eupport to the increase of these lossss# our uoverwset^t has adopted the following mean® to offset mim of the expenditure Hum ed a .nd to prevent this emnity until an /agreementagreement ie reached, betwe: n ue and 'imait, wliei^eby tlie ha;us 'both fyom which Hy^partie^ are suffering fros tlia pr^stnt pali^ irill be rem©Ted» ••^ove.^nt^nt wialicd to let tli© British .'OVC'-'nment lu^w that z).iB should not be interprttec by them or the Cvover^imnt of ^umit as being wltriout object nor be arded as in an^r way hostile to '■ uv.ait but at the^ Have takan t .-is ^ep only for fee protection of t.hai.r finance® anu the prevention of loss to all nerenantB of the kingdom. ine aovern^ent wiah to tissue orders to all ^ aba and tribes to aeoucstrate all they ace coming fro^ ^.uwait, unless the aovcrr^ent hm information of its departure, and to stop every individual leaving Kuwait, regarding whoae departure fro?a t:iat country our «overrment has no kiioniedigt* f ihls is to prevent ^smuggling of goods and this step .ha® only been taken aftcr* mting tiv-.t mu&amp;t.llntC by caravan® is ha® reached xg a great height# ^is/clear fron the reduction in t 'ads an^ fron the losses to all merchants and to the revenues of the vove.••-. , 3aent itself* uliis regulation will remain in force until an -greement is reached in a guaranteed, way between ourselves and Kuwait, for Intercourse on the basis of the suggestions put forward by our delegation at Ku ait &gt; ana. I oeg that is Majesty's (K&gt;vemment anct the Government of Kuwait be informed#Extract paragraph 169 of Kuwait Intelligence Summary No.14 for period from 16th to 31st August x^xxxxx x 169 , INTERES T ING STORY OF A DESERT ESCAPE . (Repeated only lest the Saudi Government later lay the matter sgainst Kuwaitis door). E&amp;rly in August a Nejd subject named Salman bin Jonathan an-Nasaf i, of the Rashaida. tribe proceeded with Shaikh Trahib al shuqair of Jerriya to Riyac h v;ith some presents for H.M. King 'Bin saud. Having received a gift in return from the King, he left of jsrriya a few days later. On reaching the 'Sahul' country north of Riyath, he stele two camels, the property of some local Bedouin and resumed his journey. On arriving near the DIBIBAH he was met by a couple of Al Bagaawi's men (Frontier Blockade Officer), who interrogated him and finding him unable satisfacotily to account for the two camels he had, they marched him off to PI Bagaawi, v/ho in turn put the man in irons and sent him to Bin Jaloui (Governor of Kasa), under escort. ./hen within a few miles of Hasa, the party, halted for a short rest in a cave and went to sleep. Salman thinking this a good opportunity to escape quietly got up, and taking the rifles and ammunition belcngxng to his escort, mounted his camel. Before making off he shout ed and woke the men and warmed them not to foliow him, as he was a desperate man and would shoot him down if they aid. Tne men took the hint, and tried to follow at a safe distance. The fugitive Salman now made for Kuwait at break neck speed, and his pursuers losing the trail cf their man, made foi Jerriya, where they reported the incident to al Bagaawi. 'pjng latter reinforced the party and orciei ed them to follow up the absconder as best as they could. T^Pari^proceeded to /to Kuvm.t v/i t h v.. letter i or the shaikh, searching along the whole route, and on ari'ival they reported the whole matter to Shaikh Abdul la Salim, and applied i or his assistance. The Shaikh gave orders lor the pprty to make a thorough search amon^r Kuwait tribes assisted by Kuwaiti Fidawis. The search failed and it was later discovered that the man had left for Iraq after leaving the rifles and ammunition of his one time guards with a Rashidi woman, under promise that she should send them back to Jerriya, The man managed to get rid of his irons by means of a file which the woman gave him. The Saudi party returned to Jerriya on 21st August 193b, X X X X X x XTelegram xx From Political Resident, Bushire. To Secretary of state for India, London, Repeated GrOi ernment of India, Foreign and Politica.'! Department, New Delhi. H.M. *6 Charge d^iffaires, Jedda, Copy by post to Political Agent, Kuwc .it. Ho. 892. Dated the 25th October 1955. ' I Jedda telegram Fo.192 to Foreign Office. KUWAIT BLOCKADE. 1. Attitude of Sa ? udi Government which is apparently still that by which they deliberately torpedoed Kuwait Conference is most disappointing. Shaikh on my return through Kuwait again appealed to me most earnestly on question of blockade. As the result cf his conversations in England he has evidently high hopes that His Majesty's Government mea,n to implement their assurance on the subject of the blockade and failure to do so now on our part even though circumstances may be difficult vill mean that his trust in our good intentions towards him will receive a severe and most undesirable shock which will lave repercussions in the other Arab States of the Gulf. 3. J quite realise the importance of treating Bin Sa 'ud liberally but I have always felt (see for instance my telegram lTo.T.112 of 8th June) that the Kuwait Blockade should be made the acid test of the desire of the Sa 1 udi Government for our friendship. I venture to suggest there fore whether, in view of the persistent unfriendly attitude (fithe Sa'udi Government over^this point, it would not be practicable /piactic&amp; tie for Ry^n on his coming visit to Riyadth to intimate to Bin Sa 1 ud that any new offer from His Majesty's government re; the Blue Line question is dependent on Bin Sa 'ud adopting a reasonable attitude towards the eminently practical suggestions of the Shaikh re: manifests etcetera sub*. (vide paragraph 3 of/enclosure to my Printed letter 455-S of 28th June) • ^ - Resident. Goxoy forwarded to P#A.Kuwait under a #L# H0.789-S of 25/10/35.nonf idential II0.8O6 -S of 1935. Br itisli Residency &amp; Gonsulat e-Greneral, Bushire, the 29th. Octofcer, 1935. From - The Hon*ble Lieut.-Colonel T.G.Powle, G.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To - The Foreign Secretary to the Goverranent of India, Hew Delhi. I hfve the honour to refer to paragraph 169 of Euwait Intelligence Summary Ho, 14 for period from 16th to 31st August 1935, a copy of an extract from which I enclose for ready reference. adopted the correct procedure bf coming with a letter for the Shaikh whose assistance they ssked for. It would seem therefore that the protests made by His Majesty^ Government to the Saudi Government in connection with the previous incursion of the party of five (vide correspondence ending with despatch No.260, dated the 17th September 1935, from His Majesty 's Ghargfe d'affaires, Jedda, to His Majesty's Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs) has had a good effect. I am sending copies of this to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, His Majesty's Ghargfe d'Affaires, Jedda and the Political Agent, Kuwait. Sir 2 It will be seen that the Saudi party on this occasion I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant f- . Lieut.-Gol onel political Resident in the Persian GulfExtract from parr graph 169 of Kuwait Intelligenee Summary Ho.14 for period from 16th to 31st August 1935. x x x x x x *69. Interesting stor^ of a Desert escape # x * x x. x z the foglt ire Salman now made for Kuwait at break neck speed, and his (Saudi) pursuers losing the trail of their m^n, made for Jerriya, where they reported the incident to al Bagaawi. The latter reinforced the party and ordered them to follow up the absconder as beat es they could. The party proceeded to Kuwait with a letter for the Shaikh, searching elong. the whole route, and. on arrival they reported the whole 1 1 w e r v o iii&gt;h.a x 1c hi ft*- b d 11 a 00 1 x f?i, a nd applied for his assistence. The Shaikh gr.ve orders for the party to make a thorough search among Kuwait tribes assisted by Kuwaiti Fidawis. XX X AX XX x x x x x jc♦ , -CONFIDENTIAL. No. 807-S of 1955. The Hon'ble the Political Redder! in the Persian Gulf presents his com- pliments to 1. His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, London, 2. His Majesty's Ghargfe d^ffaires, Jedda. 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Consulate-General, p\ \ / H v BUSHIRE. Dated .2 9Xh. .O.C.t.Qber.. 1.9.35. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Letter No.806-S dated the 29th October 1935 to the Foreign Secretary to the Goyernment of India, with enclosure. Subject. A ■ . &gt; Visit of Saudi search party to Kuwait.53/54 Telegram AX, Cjove rranent of xndia, -b'oreign a nd Political Department, Hew Delhi. H.M's iiecretary of atate for xndia. From To London Repeated to h . M * s Charge d»Affaires, Jedda. Political Resident, iiuahire. flo. 2974 K /1 Jedda telegram no . 192 of October 17th and fowle* s telegram i-^o. 892 of October 25th. Kuwait blockade. •cates unwillingness to consider any reasonable arrangement and until they can be induced to modify this attitude ob« -viously no prgogress towards settlement can be made. We agree with Resident that our failure to afford any effective assistance to the Shaikh over this matter will produce de- -plorable effects upon the other Gulf Rulers as well as on the Shaikh himself since they can hardly fail to compare HisMajesty*s Government's attitude towards ibn ^a'ud on the question of the Kuwait .blockade with that adopted towards Bahrain Government over the ABaSDI incident in which it was held that the very mild endeavour to protect their revenues at the expense of ibn JSa^ud was not in accord with inter-' -national usage and must be permanently abandoned. 3, i3in Sa , ud , s blockade of Kuwait does not consist of customs cordon but of prohibition on all trade and intercourse of whatever description betv/een Kuwait and Sa 'udi Saudi Government's policy note merely indi-^a'udi Arabia under severest possible penal t aee jedda tele grains ^o»i44 of August E7th,i^o« 145 of August 26th axid i^o* 153 of oeptember 2nd)* Block- -ade of this stringency in peace time is obviously unfiieiidly act and certainly repugnant to xirab sen- -tiiaent v/hen it is remembered that ±5in Sa^ud owes his.start in life to friendly attitude of father of developments in Red Sea may make moment difficult for throwing down challenge to -oin Sa^d on behalf of CJulf Hulers and we do not leave out of account our desire for air facilities on Hasa CJoast, JMever- -theless, .bin Sa'ud's attitude in Kuwait affairs pass- -es beyond mere reason and is in sharp conflict with Yusuf xasin^s recent assurances of unwavering friend- -ship with nis Majesty's Government as basis of Sa'udi foreign policy as given to Calvert in the course of discussions of attitude of iiaudi Government. We think therefore that Calvert 1 s suggestion for linking this assurance with ou3&amp; own desiderata might well be reconsidered, see Jalvert's telegram ito*l65 of September 8th and foreign uffice reply Ho* 109 of ^ September 14th. If iiyan could first draw attention to these assurances and then point out analogy betv/een Saudi objections to Bahrain's attitude over ABMiiDI case and Kuwait's objections to Saudi blockade proceedings^ Ibn Sa'ud could hardly maintain that his demands upon Kuwait were reasonable. 2. Should this fail, we feel that more deter- -mined attitude would be desirable if His Majesty 's Government think such is possible at present juncture and present Shaikh of Kuwait. We realise that newand we thiiik tnis icould best be done by adopting suggestion nade by jfowle in his telegram i^o. 892 of uctober 25th. it may be held that such an attitude would incline ibn iia'ud tov/ards rapproche- -isent with J-taly# xhis matter is somewhat beyond our sphere but we doubt whether general Arab attitude as disclosed particularly in Dickson's re- r -ports from Kuwait and resident's telegram i^o. 1/230 of October 7th v/ould justify great apprehension on . this score particularly as oalvert s telegrams on this subject show that j-bn Sa'ud* s is himself nervous of Italian menace to Arabia. participation by Gulf Arab states in sanctions if agreed to should fur- -ther incline aaudi Government away from tonptation to rest on Italian support* iroreign c-cf ' Oo , ft'Z-fy . (X* /*■ t/v/ir) c— ( J) . L ' C c L t i/U. / / - / •^\ \ * By Air Mail. P.Z. 19 v f i hi /STS^ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, t; Ui ) Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to hv^ 11 ' Mail. 'F4^ -Seeretrrr^r 0 o vornmont-ef-fe^ia. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3681-N O DIS'jJTBlJTIOi;'. Decypher* Mr, Calvert (Jedia) c 20th October, 1955, D. 5.15 p .m. 20th October, 1955, R. 6.SO p.m. 20th October, 1955. No. 196, Your telegram No. 122, Passage encyphered substantially correct. Arabio of note is Involved and rather obscure and may be rendered by somewhat iree translation of first two sentences of paragraph 3 as follows, (Begins) baudi CTOvernment held Koweit responsible for present situation as thej had not sought to interfere in Koweit's affairs ? and Koweit therefore must be responsible for the losses they have caused to Saudi Gove rrnient. Demands of Saudis (i.e. at conference) were considerably less than 'the limit ,, and were reasonable, being as far as Saudis could go e (Ends). 2, Yusuf Yasin informs me that wording of Saudi note at this particular point is that of Ibn Saud himself. He added that although it was not clearly stated passage should be interpreted to mean that, kowsit 'and those who interfere in her affairs' must bear responsibility. Though the Sheikh did not say so I sunned the impression that he clearly meant to refer statement to jlis Majesty's Government.mmmmmmmmmmrnrnm ■■■1 53/54 / AX. H.M # s Charge d f iiffairee, Jedda. il.M*a Secretary of dtate for foreign Affairs* London, iuo. 204 CiOYerniDent of India, foreign and Political Department, jaew Delhi, i^o. 122 Political Kesident, ±iushire # jmo . 232 Dated 3rd received 4th -November 1935. Government of inid** telegram i&gt;io. 2974 to Secretary of State for J-ndia paragraph 4. I venture to express doubt whether ibn Sa'ud's desire (which may be realised) for a settlement of South ^astern frontiers shown is sufficiently strong to weigh with him over Kuwait where his feelings are so deeply engaged. It may be said that he is equally that disturbed by frontier question but i suggest/first shock over that question has now somewhat v/orn off and he might be prepared to see frontier negotiations break down rather than yield an inch. Charge d*Affaires. Telegram from To Repeated to u Copy sent to Kuwait under P.L.Uo. 843-8 dated 4/1 i/35. J?P.Z.7396/35. Copy sent to Kuwait under P.L.^o.847-S, dated 7*11.1935, rel': P.L.llo.C/529, dated 19. 10* 1935. I'Ti f / f S~-7'7flf (E 5985/206/25) Ti FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. it 11th October 128 5. My dear Clausen, / Will you please refer to your letter No,P.Z.7024/35 of the 4th October to me about the possibility of Ryan being able to make some progress with the Koweit blockade problem when he visits Ibn Saud at Riyadh? r 3 &amp; We have not, of course, overlooked/tlie fact that x the Saudis still owe us an answer to Calvert's note of August 12th (a copy of which was sent to you under cover of Foreign Office printed letter No. S 5157/206/25) and if an answer is still outstanding when Ryan reaches Riyadh, it may be that, as you suggest, he would do well to raisethe matter there. Ryan will be in London again for a few days before he leaves England on the 25th October and we propose to take that opportunity of consulting him as to the best line to pursue. Yours very sincerely, (Sd.) G.m RENDEL. Clauson, Esq.53/54 Telegram XX Fran Political Resident, Buahire. To Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi. tfo. 963 Dated 15th November 1935• IMPORTANT » PERSONAL. FOWLE TO METCALFE. Following is repetition of my telegram of 14th November to Walton, begins. Personal. Fowle to Walton. (Here insert text of telegram No. 959 of 14.11.1935J. Ends, You might also like to press for early deci sion, - BRITCONSUL -53/54 Tele&amp;san XX. Londonf 0376 ^^ 0f State for india From To Iolitical Kesident, iiushire# ¥c. 369 Dated 16th received 17th i&gt;ioveiaber 1935 Personal ^Iton to ij'owle Your telegram j^o. 959. Instructions to Kyan regarding Blockade question v/ere issued in despatches of October 3lst and November 7th. Latter, m-itten after receipt of Government of Indian telegram Ho.2974, was addressed care of Jrolitical Agent, see that copies of your telegram Bo. 692 and Govern- -ment of India telegram were enclosed in them and consideration was given to suggestions made in these telegrams though Foreign office have only been able to adopt them partially and remain /to make offer re- -garding frontier dependent on ibn Sa'ud^ attitude on Blockade question. Bahrain i^anram. Copies of these despatches have been sent you by sea mail of JMovember 14th. iou will unable Secretary of State for India.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001ea_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/517</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001ea</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/517</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 53/54 IV (D 119) Kuwait Blockade'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-20T17:49:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (218 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.An index of topics discussed in the file is contained on folio 1B.</extent><extent>A bound correspondence volume.The foliation sequence commences at the first folio and terminates at the last folio; these numbers are written in pencil, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Circled index numbers in red crayon can also be found throughout the volume.The file contains the following foliation errors: 1, 1A, 1B and 1C; 147 and 147A and the following foliation omissions: 119 and 121.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence related to a trading blockade imposed on Kuwait by Abdul Aziz ibn Abdulrahman ibn Faisal Al Saud [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd (Ibn Saud)], the King of Saudi Arabia.The correspondence is primarily between British officials attempting to mediate between the two parties and the file contains detailed notes regarding negotiations between them at a conference held in Kuwait.The file also contains translated copies of correspondence between the Kuwaiti and Saudi Arabian delegations and translated correspondence between British officials and officials at the Saudi Arabian Ministry of Foreign Affairs.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Economic sanctions</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001ea#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>