<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000130_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T11:44:18.924Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Tranelati n of a letter dated 17ti:i Jamadi-al-Awwal, ( 8th * February, 19SO) from Shaikh Sir Abdul Aaslz bin bin Abdur Pahman Al Faisal Ae S&amp;aud # ftuler of iejd and Dependanolee, to Major R.H.P.BiekBOn, C,I.E, # Polltlcal Agent, Bahrain. After complimente, I Informed your honour of the oowmunication of the reepeoted shaikh lea regarding cuBtorae dutlee# It is true I , had written to hi» as he expects me to do so in certain case urging that I shall refer (ftireotly to him and then he would settle raatters between us. As he Is like my father and as I had prorois^d to make direct coaiisunicatlon of this sort to hi«, I addressed hiw on this subject. Hy original Intention was to inform you of the matter later. At the time of writing to Shaikh Isa I also wrote to you a letter through Abdul Aziz ^usaibi, directing hiss to infona your honour of the result of ?ny com- munication to Shaikh Isa. ^ow,thank God, the desired object will be gained, a® you will be the medium in the matter. My complaint against Shaikh Isa is that he has no right to charge duty on transhipment cargo which is landed al Bahrain and then re-exported to my territories, namely, Ojaii Qatif and Jubail, Ardhlyah (ground rent) alone being charged, But Ke has every right to charge duty on goods entering the town and sold in the town by my subjects like any other |B»Ktwal goods imported by Bahrain merchants for Jahrain. Thai His Excellency mentioned to your honour that I have been charging duty on the goods of his subjects who imported mer chandise xxxxxxxxxxxxxsx* into my territories, and of course nothing enters my territories which is not sold in them and, therefore, I have every right to charge them duty juet as Hie Excellency is entitled to charfe duty on goods Imported into his territory and oold in it by my subjects; but what is brought on my shores for transhipment. 1 have no right absolu ly to charge any duty, except the ground rent. If Els Excel lency bases hie argument on the days of the Turks,these peopl were unjust to their subjects and to the people in general•(11) x8 As regards nyeelf, no arrangesient has tauten plac® between Shaik lea and myself regarding anything and the duty charged on goods of my subjects is unjust and contrary to the regulations which I donot consent to and in like manner the Migh British Govern ment will not like it, and your honour is my agent (to represen the matter) in accordance with current rules and regulations.St? ^ O • 5 • TPRMS OB A rRIllDty COIVKKTIOI KRTERSD IITO BBTWKSI SMAIEM MAHOMED BII EHALIFAE, IIDBPBIDAIT RULER Of BAIRAII,OI Til. PART 0 lIMESLlf' AID SU8CS8S0RS AID UAPTAII FtLIX J0IB8, S5R MAJESTY'S I*DI*I lAVY, POLITICAL RESIDiidl • ' OF lER BRITAIII8 MAJESTY IS TIE GULF 01- PikRSXA.Ol Thi PART OF TIE BRITISI COVi RlkkDT, 186 1. xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx I Article 4. British subjeets of ^jvery itssxiiKicxKiL denoMination, it ie understood, mj r©elde in, and carry on their lawful trade in the territories of Bahrain, their goods being sub ject only to an ad valorem duty of 5 per cent in cash or in kind. This amount once paid shall not be demanded again on the same goods if exported from Bahrain to other places; and in respect to the treatment of British subjects and dependants they shall receive the treatment and consideration of the subject and dependants of the most favoured people• iLLl offences which they may commit, or which may be committed agains them, shall be reserved for the decisions of the British Resi dent, provided the British Agent located at Bahrain shall fail to adjust them satisfactorily. In like manner the British Resident will use his good offices for the welfare of the sub jects of Bahrain in the ports of the maritime ^rab tribes of this Gulf in alliance with the British Government. xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx TRUE © 0 P Y, ♦ / ' Major, 6.I.E., Political Agent, Bahrain.19/126 i-'elegrain.Oode, From - Trevor, ^ushire. To - Dickson, Bahrain. ^o.553. Dated 10th ^arch 1920. Your raeinoranduin dated 28th February 58-C. It certainly is not customary to charge whole duty on transit or transhipment cago but I do not think any recognized scale. Most countries charge sortie duty calculated on principle of just avoiding kill ing the goose I think. I am under 'the impression that when Bin Saud took over in 1913 the Shaikh of Bahrain reduced duty of 5^ which he had charged in time of Turks to 2^ or at # the suggestion of myself. I fancy he did not lose much revenue by this until after the first year or-two of war. You might talk to him again on above lines; do you think letter from me nothing would do any good or do you think/short of one from Government of India will do any good? / . Trevor. I'ekegram.Code. From - Political, Baghdad. To - Political, ^ushire. No.3279. Dated and received 13th March 1920. Bahrain despatch of 28th February 58-C . Please furnish me with your.views by telegram. I should like matter dealt with simultaneously with request of Shaikh of Bahrain for further liberty. Political.19/126. / A TelegraruGode. Prom - Political, Bushire. 'To - Political, Baghdad. No.585. Dated 14th March 1920. # • Your telegram dated 13th March 3279. When Bin Saud took over Hassa in 1913 i arranged personally with Shaikh for duty to be reduced to 2% or 2^ forget which and on receipt ' i ■ , , , of Political Agents letter I telegraphed to him asking if he'could remind Shaikh of Bahrain and have, another try to settle matter locally before we went further with it. If this fails will tell him to take it up with liberty question, Trevor.Telegram.Code, * Prom - Political, Bahrain, To - Political, Bushire 0 No.259. Dated and received 14th March 1920. i . My letter 197/l4l 27th February, Commissioner of Sind telegram, begins. Cus.116. Your telegram dated 27th February. Am reporting this and other cases to Government but should advise your not suggesting as an exception of reversal of order, Ends 0 For your information. political* Telegram.Code. From - Political, Bushire. To - Political, Bahrain, No.589. Dated 14th March 1920. Your telegram dated 14th March 259, I think you had better go easy about matter as I have little doubt that many of these people are wilfully smuggling gold coin attracted by its enormously inflated value in India, Perhaps my general wire on the subject may have some result though I doubt it. Political eTOTE ON MY MEMORANDUM NO. ^DATED 18-5-20. In order that you may the more understand Shaikh Isa'e state of mind in the natter of Ouetoms, I think it is worth mentioning that Shaikh Isa puts the whole trouble down to Yusuf Kanoo, the pro-British merchant,here. This, in point of fact, is entirely wrong, as Bin £aud himself told me when I was in Huffuf that it was the Hassa merchants supported by the houses of Queaibi, Bassasa, etc. who had formally complained to him and had asked him to try and get Shaikh Isa to remove Yusuf Kanoo is brought into the matter in the following way. He got into disgrace with Shaikh Abdullah about two months back (see my last diary) for having had the temerity to speak his mind too boldly, at a meeting held to discuss the building of a new school. He on that occasion was badly snubbed / for after giving E? 7,000/- as subscription towards the/school,had this money sent back to him by shaikh Abdullah, with the curt message that Shaikh Isa could do without his money.' Abdullah, to Justify his action, informed Shaikh Isa that Yusuf Kanoo had insulted him and was endeavouring to make himself a bigger man than Shaikh Isa. Anyway, as a result of this and other mischievous talk Shaikh Isa was completely put against Yusuf Kanoo. The latter at the time and at my advice made^peace with Shaikh lea, but did not offer to return the money. Outwardly both are friends now, but in private Shaikh Isa is never tired of villifying Yusuf Kanoc to me. From the number of stories and imaginary griev- ances that Shaikh Isa has against him, there would appear to be a regular compaign of calumny at work with the object of rufining Yusuf Kanoo,firstly, in the eyes of Shaikh lea, and secondly, with the Agency. I gather that Civil CommisBioner ) Deputy Polit ical Resident ) 3 w *2-0 Ms tax on tranship goods(2) Jaseira Al Ghirawi is at the bottom of it all» This worthy among^ his many faults ; suoh as being Anti- British etc., is a deadly enemy of Yueuf Kanoo and would like nothing so much as to remove him from Bahrain. Abdullah, being as H putty ,, in the hands of Jassim, thinks and believes as Jasim does. And as Abdullah is Shaikh Isa^ right-hand man, the way is easy where it comes to putting the old man up against Yusuf Kanoo, Yusuf Kanoo, knowing that he is in the bad books of Abdullah and Jassim, is anxious for his future, so takes refuge under the cloak of his well-known friend ship for the Agency, and visits me almost every day. Result * One day Abdullah and Jassim visit me and tell me what a villain Yusuf Kanoo is. The next day Yusuf Kanoo does the same and accuses the Shaikhs of persecuting him. Then comes Bin Saud^ bomshell regarding the customs. Of course Yusuf Kanoo is accused of being the instigator of the whole thing. It is his way of revenging himself for the if. 7,000/- business, as Shaikh Isa said to me yesterday : Nothing that I could say would persuade the old man that this was not so. Shaikh Isa, on tbp of all, is exceedingly angry with me ; for not seeing as he does and for not taking action against Yusuf Kanoo. Shaikh Isa as good as told me I was supporting one of his subjects in an intrigue against himself. Yusuf Kanoo is, as you know, a protected subject,and far from being disloyal to Shaikh Isa^ I have found him always most anxious to show his loyaltj^ and his behaviour and conversation, both outwardly and in private has to enable always been quite correct. Ihe above note is sent/you to realize the methods of Abdullah &amp; Jassim and the miserable nature of one of their many typical intrigues. - jor,C.I.E,, Political Agent, Bahrain.COflFIDEKTIAL « 3r Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the 18th March,3S20. E ^S'OENCY. 2 ?Cj TO To The Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E. MEMORANDUM Reference your telegram No. 555 dated 10th March, 1920. Subject reduction of Custom duty on ^tranship 11 goods, Bahrain. According to your instruction given me in your above mentioned telegram, I yesterday paid an official visit to Shaikh Isa and discussed the question on the lines suggested by you. Shaikh Hamad was present at the interview. I was particularly careful to approach the matter in as friendly a way as possible and in repeating what you told me I took the line that you were anxious to appear in the light of a friendly advisor. I emphasized the point that Bin Saud was also a friend of His Majesty's tiovernment and had appealed to you to adjudicate the matter. You were bound to look at the question from ■ the point of view of a neutral, and any advice you gave was of necessity strictly impartial. Bin Saud, I said, had a grievance in that at almost every port in the world it was customary to take a minimum custom duty from tranship goods, such duty in places like Basrah being 1 ^ only, and in Bombay I believed % fo» From the very opening of my conversation, I could see. Shaikh Isa T s mind was made up,even though Shaikh Hamad did all he could to persuade his father to adopt a reasonable attitude;Shaikh Isa, having let me say all I had to say, replied that on no condition, whatsoever, would he agree to reducing the present rate of 5 ^ to S-i- ^ merely in order to please Bin Saud. Bin Saud might? (2) make as good a case as he pleased, but he (Shaikh Isa ) refused to be dictated to by another ruler in the manage ment of his own affairs. Therefore it was useless to ask him to think of reducing his customs merely in order to effect a friendly settlement between him and Bin Saud. He went on to say that on the occasion when he last re duced his 'tranship' customs,i.e. when Bin Saud took over Hassa,in 19 13, he had done so entirely of his own free will and because he wished to attract trade to Bahrain. He denied that he had been influenced by you in any way. Similarly, after he had accomplished his purpose he raised the rate to 5 ^ again, this also of his own free will and because it was his •haq* to do so. He, Shaikh Isa, would only consent to reducing his customs in favour of tranship goods on one condition, and that was if he received an official order to do so from you. In that event he would not only accept the order with alacrity ('Ala 'Aini wa 'Ala Rasi) but, as he said, his 'sharaf' would still be un-impaired, for Bin Saud would not be able to 'crow' over him and say that he,Shaikh Isa, had reduced the customs because he was afraid of him. Such an order would be one from Government, which no Arab Ruler could argue against, and which all would understand. In view of the above attitude I am of opinion that the soundest plan is for a letter to be written by you to Shaikh Isa which, if I might suggest it and you approve, might take something of the following form. You had heard that he. Shaikh Isa, had, during the war and without reference to the Political Agent, raised his Cus toms duty on tranship goods from 2± f 0 to 5 f 0 , which was contrary to the arrangement come to between him and you in 1913, and that this increase was neither just, nor in accord with general custom. Furthermore, that Bin Saud, also a friend of His Majesty's Government, had lodged aformal oomplaint against what he described as an in justice to his subjects resident in Hassa and Bahrain, and had appealed to you to adjudicate in the matter, and that after due consideration your Judgement was that Shaikh Isa was in the wrong, and that he should again reduce the customs charges to 2-| % on all goods except piece goods, which latter could continue to pay at the rate of 15/- per single bale ( according to Sh: Isa he reduced this to R® 4/- in 19 13). 2. As a sort of ,, backhand ,, concession,however, I would suggest that you add the following in your letter in order to strengthen the hands of the local Customs Authorities !- (a) That all goods for the mainland landed at Bahrain must be addressed to the port of destination via Bahrain. (b) That no goods so consigned will be allow ed to be diverted' into Bahrain without the Ruler or Political Agent's sanction. (c) That tranship goods will only be allowed to remain in the Customs House for 20 days.After that they must be re-shipped to destination. Failure to remove within the time limit to entail payment of full duty of 5$. 3. A direct order from you on something of the above lines is the only way, I think, to get Shaikh Isa to move in the matter. He, now-a-days, unfortunately, is entire ly in the hands of his third son. Shaikh Abdullah, backed by the latter^ evil genius Jassim A1 Chirawi ( he accom panied Shaikh Abdullah to England) Both the above,ever since their return, seem to have changed markedly for the worse - official records show that before going Home, Shaikh Abdullah was showing great promise. The contrary is, I fear, the case now. The whole policy of Abdullah and Jassim, now-a-days, is directed towards freeing(4) themeelvee from British control. They reject all advice and are tireless in their efforts to get Shaikh Isa to adopt a similar attitude. The wild talk of 11 the rights of small nations** which they imbibed at Home would appear to be at the bottom of all the trouble. In my opinion Jassim's evil influence over Abdullah is doing a very great deal of harm, especially is it tending to estrange Shaikh Isa, and spoil the state of friendly feelings which has existed between the Ruler and succes sive Political Agents in the past. The present is, I think, an excellent opportu nity to show that we neither intend to relax our con trol of Bahrain affairs, nor will we tolerate injustice at the expense of other friendly chiefs. Finally an order from you settling the matter and the knowledge that I am supported will have the most salutary effect locally, especially on those who are steadily working against British interests here. Major, O.I.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. 4- Copy forwarded to the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, for information.19/126. Telegram.Cod© # t From - Political, Bahrain. To - Political, Bushire. No,77-0, Dated and received 24th March 1920. In continuation of my letter No.72-C dated 18th March. Shaikh of Bahrain still imaginog that order to compel him to .reduce customs dues on tranship goods would be tantamount to breaking Treaty on our part suggest when writing to him you fully explain that Treaty he quotes in no way can be construed to apply to case in question. I Political. Telegram.Code. From - Political, iiushire. To - Political, Bahrain. No.654. Dated 24th ^arch 19S0. Your 72, 73, 77-G. Deputy Political Resident gone to India will be away about fortnight matter kept pending his return. A t political.Lj-o 19/126 Telegram - R Prom - Civil Commissioner Baghdad. T o - - Foreign Dept., Simla, Repeated - Political Bushire, and Bahrain* No., 4602 Dated - April 15th reed. April 16th 1920 My despatch of March 26th, No., 10630« Bin Saud writes March 19th asking for a decisiom by k His Majesty's GoveEhment in regard to levy of transit dues at SakKatesaa Bahrain on goods eventually destined foe Nejd* Will G-overnment of India authhrize the Deputy Political f' Basident Bushira; to instuot the Sheikh of Bahrain on lines A proposed in last paragraph of Bahrain letter of February 23th. This is more than he would be entitled to under the proposed international agreement regarding transit dues, which we may eventually have to enforce. Addressed Simla , Repeated Bahrain and Bushire. CivCoia 019/126 If- P , \ - Telegram,Code, Prom - Trevor, Bushire, Civcom, Baghdad, Repeated Political Bahrain. No,772, Dated 17th April 1920, Your telegram dated 15th April 4602, When this arrived I ha&amp; telegram ready for depatoh to Bahrain and to Baghdad (wh_ch I first cancelled and on second thoughts think: may as well issue) as follows. Begins. Your 77-0, Would shaikh ox Ba.araxn relish duty question more if he were allowed to collect full 5^ and then grant rebate of say 2^ or 35? on goods being reexported to mainland.- This would be more complicated but Shaikh of Bahrain might consider it saved his face and showed him in magnanimous light; farther it would accord better with his reading of treaty. If .0 I might write In ot p. A . B a hroi „ „ moranaMt toted JStt M.feh 72 . 0 . oalfloatloll , sugeestea ^ Trevor.19/126 f v Telegram,Code, From - Givecm, Baghdad, To - Political, Bushire. Repeated rt Bahrain, Ho.4752, Dated 18th received 19th April 1920, • Your telegram dated 17th April 772, Subject to any views Dickson may express please address Shaikh of Bahrain accordingly. Civcom.19/126 Telegram.Code To Prom Trevor, Bushire. Political, Bahrain♦ Repeated Oivoom, Baghdad, No .807. Dated 22nd April 1920. Your telegram dated 2lst April 100-0. After all if the Shaikh of Bahrain wishes the matter to be arranged 'by order it will be best to order it in marner most convenient to ourselves and public. At the same time as I understand it, transhipment cargo is merchandise addressed to a certain port via another and transhipped direct from one vessel to another at latter. In India this is allowed duty free or payment of fee for customs guards only. On the other land cargo lander has to pay duty and a drawback of 7/8 duty is refunded when re-exported. It would be advisable to decide on which analogy we had better proceed. Presume answer from Govern ment of India to Civil Commissioner's telegram dated 15th April 4602 must be awaited. Trevor19/126 Telegram,Code, Prom - - political, Bahrain. To - Political, Bushire, Repeated Political, Baghdad, No,100-C• Dated and received 21st April 1920 # \ 9 Tour telegram dated 17th April 772 also Civil Commissioner Baghdad 1 s 4732 18th April, If I may say so consider no object will be gained by approaching Shaikh of Bahrain in the way suggested. Nothing whatsoever will move Shaikh of Bahrain from stubborn attitude already taken up but a direct order from you. To ask him to take with one hand and give back with the other will in my opinion only tend to irritate and Shaikh of Bahrain will be more inclined to resent such order than consider we were trying to let him down gently. Certainly there would be greatest opposition from Customs Department and merchants to a system which will cause extreme inconvenience to latter and double work to former; I am therefore strongly in favour of direct order as per last para of my letter of 20th February, Political19/126. Telegram,Code, Prom - Oivoom. Baghdad, To - Political, Busliiro. Repeated Political Bahrain. No«5090 # Dated 27th received 28th April 1920. My telegram dated 15th April 4602. I suggest that you should ask India whether they would be prepared to consider question of Customs Treaty with Bahrain allowing increased duties subject to V . provision of* transit facilities and simple Customs rules on the subject of ship's manifest. Tariff might approximate new Persian rates. If prospect of this concession was given to Shai' h it will be easy to insist on a maximum transit duty of 1 ^ in case of Bin Saud. Qivcom. Telegram.Code, From - Trevor, Bushire. To - Political, Baghdad.^ Hopeated Political, Baghdad. No.885. Dated 5rd May 1920. Your telegram dated 27th April 5090. I deprecate making any increase of customs dues at Bahrain unless we could get sufficient guarantee from Shaikh of Bahrain tha portion at least of receipts would be spent on improvement to pier-or on something for public benefit; otherwise increased receipts woiild simply sy/ell the allowances enjoyed by the sons and other relations of the Shaikh it of Bahr'ain. I understand Political Agent Bahrain also sees objection to increased rate on commercial grounds. '#■ Trevoro f- /C| SESIDfNCTr 1 '™*! TELEGRAM CODE- ... ■.Z^CTZl From Civil CornmiSBioner, Baghdad. | | To Political, Bahrein. I fiECCfiOa, ^ No, 5090. Dated 27th ( received 28th ) April 1920. My telegram dated '15th April 4602 I suggest that you should ask India whether they will be prepared to -A-£ ^ . consider question of advising Qustoms Treaty with Bahrein / allowing increased duties subject to provision of transit facilities and simple Custom Rules on the subject of ship's manifest. Tariff might approximate new Persian rates.If prospect of this concession was given to Shaikh it will be easy to insifet on a maximum transit duty of 1$ in the case of Bin Saud. Addressed Bushire repeated Satoireln.±7 no./IS, POLITICAL AGENCY Bahrain, the 27th April 1920 8U8HIRE mmhCl ftATfc £&gt;. .... .^LdQr, ^00»flOENliAr ficGCfioi' To The Deputy political Resident, B U S H I R E. MIMORAHDUM. lour telegram Ho.Hil dated 22nd April 1920, Question of reduction Oustoma duty Bahrain on tranship goods. Your telegram arrived rather mutilated 'but I understand from it that we must decide on one of the two following pro- qeedures in the case of Shaikh Isa and Bahrain. (1) If goods are transhipped from steamer to say a dhow and such dhow with goods is taken straight off to t he mainland no duty at all is admisahle on the goods so taken away^ except a nominal Customs guard fee. (2) If on the other hand goods are actually landed on the jetty and are subsequently re-exported, though such are not actually taken into the town - then at the time of landi;qg, such goods should pay the full duty of 5^, but get a rebate on same of 7/8th of duty already paid, as soon as they are put on dhow destined for mainland. I gather from your tele gram that the above rules are in accordance with international usage. I think you have put the matter very clearly and provided the G-overnment of India approve of action being taken in 1&gt;he matter I would suggest as the best plan that a general rule be drawn up for Shaikh Isa's guidance, giving a ruling in the case of both (l) and (2) contingencies^and instructing him to act accordingly. It is conceivable that certain merchants may try and discharge goods for mainland into dhows going straight therethere. And. if we have a rule ready to meet the case. Shaikh Isa oannot put forward the contention that such a line of action is contrary to Bahrain laws. Major, C.I.I., Political Agent, Bahrain. Oopy to: C.C., Baghdad.19/126 Te1egram,Code. From - Political, Bahrain. To . - Political, Bushire. • • Repeated Uivcom. Baghdad. No. 138. Dated and received 21st May 1920. Bin Saud writes 14th May asking for early decision Government of India regarding question transit duty on Bahrain are orders likely come through soon? roiitical.l9 /ft6 £o Telegram,Code. From - Civcom. B aghdad, To - Foreign, Simla, SOpeated Political, Bushire, No.6257, Dated 24th received 25th May 1920, Your telegram dated 5th May 562V. I^ret delay*, tn reply. I have asked Deputy Political Resident to deal with case on my behalf repeating to me, Civcom, Telegram.Gode, Prom - Political, Bushire. To - Oivcom, Baghdad, No,1073, Dated 25th May 1920, Your telegram dated 24th May 6257,to Foreign reads 'Your telegram dated 5th May 562^' 'but no such reference received here To what does it refer? Political, Telegram,Code, (Pty) ■^rom v - Trevor,Bushire, To - Civcom, Baghdad, No,1074, Dated 25th May 1920, My telegram dated 25th May 1075, Reference now understood your telegram of 24th May 6256 having been received. Trevor ir/ 19/126 Telegram.Code, From Political, Bahrain, To Political, Bushire, Repeated Baghdad,• No # 138• • Dated and received 21st May 1920, Bin Saud writes 14th May asking for early decision H«M f s Government regarding question transit duty on Bahrain, are orders likely come through soon? No.1055. Dated 22nd May 1920 # political Agent Bahrain telegram dated 2lst May 158. When last there discussed matter with P.A.Bahrain and came to conclusion that simplest plan for all concerned would be for me to write 'by direction of Government and inform ShaiMi of Bahrain that it is not correct under international usage to levy full duty on goods in transit and' direct him. to reduce duty on goods addressed to mainland and re-exported within 20 days to 2$. This without prejudice to anything which may have to be done later under international agreement regarding transit dues mentioned in your telegram dated 15th April 4-602. Do you approve of this course if so presumably should wait for reply from Government of India to above-mentioned telegram unless you have received one which was not repeated here. Political, Telegram.Code. Prom To Trevor, Bushire. Oivcom. Baghdad. TrevorTelegram^R# From To Civil Ooimaissioner, Baggidad. Deputy Political Resident, Bushire, Ho # 6256 # Dated 24th received 25t3i May 1920* Your telegram, no • 1055 May 22nd 1920. Follovd.ng from Foreign 562-S Hay 5tli begins. Your telegram April 15th 4602 # Case largely turns on question as to whether (vide Btolitical Agent Bahrain's 72-G para I) ShaiMi would ultimately ^accept order with alacrity 11 Government of India have no objection to SiiaiMi being informed that they will be glad if Shaikh will reduce transit dues to 2-|- ^5 provided you have reason to believe he will be ready to comply with (t instructions). Is there any objection to minor concession detailed in para 2 Political Agent's letter quoted above. But if you are not confident of his compliance on these lines is any other solution feasiblet It has been suggested - vide para 5 Political Agent's memorandum 58-0 February 28th - that in view of present gross mismanagement by Customs Syndicate an amicable arrangenent profitable to both parties might be reached if Bin Saud undertook to pay Shaikh a fixed sum for a year or period of years for his Bahrain transit dues. Is this practicable? ends. Very sorry that owing to error in office this was not repeated to you at time. I have not replied. Your telegram 885 of May Srd no objection to your including further proviso that portion of increased revenue be spent on port improvement. Objection on commercial grounds not stated but I should remark generally accepted Customs tariffs would have had to be increased, India and England have agreed to rise in Persia. I incline to opinion that if we are to give a ruling at all it should be nothing on direct transhipment and no more than 2fo ov 2^ f? on goods landed in the course of transhipment (20 days). Will you reply to Foreign yourself in lines proposed in your telegram dated 22nd May with copy here. Civil Commissioner.5 . . ^ no, /ST- s Of 1980# British Ue-ldonoy and Conaulate-':onaral, BuJhire, Sflth May 1920, To HbaPolitical Agent, Bahrain. lot llonorm&amp;im* When your telogrm dated 31st v&amp;&amp; 158 was rocoivod I ©ant to th© Civil Qozsal&amp;nionor a tolegrar. no ,1055 dated 2Snd '-lay a oopy of tmidi. is attached* a. In reply t havo rocolvod a telega?® no♦6256 dated 24th -'ay {eopy attached) repeating the anwer of the devemsent of India to hi© telegrssa no # 4608 uhlch had 'boon ovorloolred, Ifee Acting Civil aoj:-iin;:iionor at ill mxlmm to raise tlie Tariff to eor^e- thing on the linos of the Porsian tariff# I already sent you t ie main features of the recent increases in that, I Itnow aleo that the recent tariff Oomraiasion in Persia were of opinion that th© only way to reduce smuggling in Persia would he to raise the Tariff a on the opposite side 6f the nit to approx- inately the san® figure - the idea ? in theory, is a ^ery good one, 5* i-ut in practice as to .^now the Whole adriinistrati on of alirain ie no rotten that a sirtple proTiso that momr of the money woiild have to he spent on harbour improvorent would not he crufficiont to safeguard traders against malveraation of Oustons receipts* 4 # To h#gin with, no one would ever know isiiat were too actual reooipts : - any more than IMiy do at present, and there -rould be nothing to prevent th© customs Syndicate from . Shosring the inoroaoe in receipts resulting fron the new Tariff as quite trifling and ape ding a correapondingly trifling sum in irfc'rt.vf l™n: :v58,* ♦ ■ .a Translation of a lettar datad 24th Shaaban 1338 =( 14th May 19^0) froa Bin Saud, to tha political Agant, Bahrain. Aftar Gomplimanta, All ia wall hara and thara in nothing of importanca to oonvay to your honour. As ragards tha question of Customs (Jrransit) duas 1 hava baan awaiting a dafinita raply from you conveying tha decision of tha High Govarnmant, but have so far not found any mention of it in your honour^ letters. xn these days, owing to serious lack of provisions, very large numbers of the inhabitants of Hejd, both Hadhar (town- dwellers) as well as Badia (nomads), have gone down towards the ooast ports of the Persian Gulf for the purpose 6f trade. I trust therefore th^t you will again remind His Majesty's Government about the question of transit dues in order that an early settlement of this matter may be effected, and the needs of my subjects may be alleviated. Usual Ending.4jency, Bahrain, ty ilC 1 j A V V % X) y Snd June 1^20. To The Deputy Political esident, Bushire. MEMORANDUM: Si, Reference jour Memorandum No. 158-S dated S6th May 1920« I entirely agree with what you Bay in paras (5) (4). As regards (5) whether you decide to raise Bahrain's taxation on to a level with Persia's, or think that Shaikh Isa should be allowed to increase his present import tax a little ( say to 6^ ) to compensate him for, loss brought about by the reduced tax on transit dsagK goods, I should not consult him; I should be inclined to just let the order come, so to speak, direct from His Majesty's Government, I do not thinks therefore that any object would be gained in suggest ing now that a Customs official from India be sent to reorganise his Customs. The old man would have a fit at once, and would think that this was the beginning of our taking r over his Customs, as was recently done at Mascat. Personally U se I think that even if we offered to allow Shaikh Isa to increar his Customs to the Persian scale, the proposition would meet with such a storm of opposition from his own people that he would reject the idea. To appeal to his cupidity in this way, I do not think, would work at present. As you know Shaikh Isa does not move in any of such mafters without consulting the mercantile community of hie Island: these would go dead against an increase in taxation on their own goods and I am convinced they would win their case if the matter were left to Shaikh Isa and them. Your para (6) is partly answered by above but the ch|ef commercial objections are that any greatly increased taxation1] taxation will drive merchants away from Bahrain. This, I know, j is a real fear of Shaikh Isa's and is one of the reasons he m has no Municipal taxation. Shaikh Isa has never allowed merchants to possess land and so have a stake in the Island. It is easy in consequence for a merchant here to pack up his goods and go. Shaikh Isa knows this. Regarding para (?). Yes, in^m^ opinion. Shaikh Isa will accept an ferder to reduce his ta^-ri^on transit goods addressed to the mainland with alaci^ty, provided the order is put firmly enough. Naturally he will not welcome the order, but he will not refuse. Regarding your last para. I do not think Government of India ! s suggestion in this respect at all feasible: Bin Saud would reject the idea with scorn.It should be realised Bin Saud demands that transit goods pay no tax at all. He believes he has justice entirely on his side. Finally I note from Civil Commissioner's telegram No. 6256 dated 24th May last para but one, that he favours nothing on direct (ranshipment and no more than 2 or S-^ on goods landed in course of transhipment. With this I am in agreement. I also gather from the last para of his above telegram that he approves your sending a telegram to the Government of India on the lines proposed in your 1055 dated ► 22na May. This also I agree with entirely. Two More Points. (a). Shaikh Isa will not lose as much as one might think he will, in view of Bin Saud's recent ferder diverting all Qassim trade to Hassa instead from Kuwait. Actually the order means that ^ Kuwait's trade with the interior will be diverted to Bahrain, which means Shaikh Isa is g&amp;ing to secure greater s revenues than heretofore and is going to score even if he iose^ by reason of the new reduced tax on N'j^d and Hassa goods, (h). I presume that the new transit dmes will apply jio goods addressed to entering Bin Saud's territories as a wholewhole ( i.©d Qatif* and Jubail 9.S well as ^ejd and Hassa ) I presume Qatar and Trucial Coast do not come within the scheme.It would 'be as well to have this quite clear. Major, C.T.E. Political Agent, Bahrain.•, ■ Telogram^Oodo. Prom - Deputy Political Rosident, Persian Gulf, Buehire. To - Govt of India, Foreign and'poiitical Dept # Simla # Ho.1139. &gt; Vvri ■ktU. &gt;P.R, k ; h ! Dated 9th June 1920, ^ ^ Ulut.'^ y Civil Oomiaissioner Baghdad telegram dated 24th May 6S57 # I have consulted again political Agent Bahrain about question of Shaikh of Bahrain accepting orders of Government of India conveyed in letter from me instructing him not to charge customs dues in full on transhipment cargo. Dickson*is still of opinion that Shaikh of Bahrain will accept with promptitute provided that order is expressed firmly enough# I accordingly suggest that I should write to Shaikh of Bahrain 'by direction of Government of India and inform him that it is not correct 'by international usage to charge full customs dues on tranship ment cargo and direct him to reduce duty on cargo addressed to mainland and re-exported within SO days to 2 or ^ and to y charge no customs dues on cargo transhipped direct in habour into vessels proceeding to mainland. I would add if you think it necessary that this is without prejudice to anything which may have to be done later under international agreement regarding transit dues now under consideration. Addressed Foreign repeated Baghdad and Bahrain by post. Trevor. No. S. The Residency, Bushire, 9th Juno 1920. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent Bahrain for information. By order, p-C- Lieut. Aselstant Resident,19 /l26 Telegram^Gode, Prom - Foreign, Simlas To - Political, Bushire. Repeated Oivcom Baghdad &amp; P.A.Bahrain. Wo # S80-E.A. ■ Datwd and received 12th June 1920. 4^ y Your telegram dated 9th June no.1139. Bahrain Customs © Your proposals are approved. « ^ ■ Foreign,^ // l No . ^ 0 - 19S0. British Residency &amp; Gonsulate^Gener, Bushire,/^/^ June 10^0• ?o SL^Aj*. / ^ ^ L. k / c The Huler of Bahrain. A#G. - Sh© Government of India have learnt that you are levying full custons dues on cargo destined for Najd&gt; Hasa^i, Ratif and Qatar. I have been'directed by the Governnent to write to ^our Excellency and inform you that this is not in accordance with international custom and to instruct you in future to levy only 2^ on goods destined for the neighbour ing Mainland of /,rable which are landed in Bahrain and no — duty on cargo transhipped direct from the steamer^ into dhows belonging to mainland ports which are proceeding direct to the said ports. It is however understood that cargo on which only is to be levied is consigned by name to certaid merchants on the mainland ''via Banrain M and C/o their agents at Bahrain / and that the said cargo is re-exported from Bahrain to the mainland ports within days from d^te of landing, ^ull duty may be levied on any c^rgo which remains longer than that period in your Island. I trust that the above instructions are cle^r to Your excellency. I may add that the G^eat powers are considering the question of transit dues, and eventually may make a convention on the subject, fhe above instructions are without prejudice to any advice which Government may find it necessary to give Your Excellency when the convention is made. ^ ✓fjp U~Colonel, Deputy political Resident, Persian Gulf.Ho # 1920* Bidtish Hesidonoy and Constdate-G-onoral f BusMre, l3tli Jiane 19200 To The Civil Connlssicner in Hesopotania, Ba^Jidad# £E££E25H2.* Hofornnoe my telegram nc # 385 dated 5rd U&amp;y 1920 doproaatlng on increase in Baiirain Customs Tariff # A reference to page 15 para 2 in the Bahrain diary for April- May 19S0 will show mj reasons for deprecating an increaso in Tariff ♦ if t&amp;e tariff were increased 90f? of the increased receipts would go to increase the private revenues of the Bheikh and M b sons ?/h.ich are already unduly inflated# Unless we got the Sheikh to allow us to reorganise the Ouetoms for-him (and we should have to force him to do this? he would never do it voluntarily) wo should never hnow what the actual receipts were, any more than we do now, and so should not ho in a . position to insist on any particular anount of being spent on public Improvements # In regard to the comereial objection to an increased Tariff I attach an extract froin Bahrain memo no ♦ 147-0 dated 2nd ^une 1920 giving his views, ils you will see the merchants in Bahrain m are in a r-ther peculiar (and strong) position# Deputy political Hesident, Persian Gulf# NExtract from Bahrain confidential memoranduin no« f 147-C dated 2nd June 1920 #f to Deputy Political Resident* Personally I think that even if we offered to allow Sheikh Isa to increase his Customs to the Persian scale such the proposition would meet with/a storm of opposition from his own people that he would reject the idea# To appeal to . his cupidity in this way I do not think would work at present As you know Sheikh Isa does not move in any of such matters without consulting the mercantile community of his island: these would go dead against an increase ofrtaxation on their own goods and 1 am convinced would win their case if the matter were left to Sheikh Isa and them. Your para (6) is partly answered by the above but the chief commercial objections are that any greatly increased taxation will drive merchants away from Bahrain# This,Iknow is a real fear of Sheikh Isa^ and is one of the reasons he has no Municipal^ taxation. Sheikh Isa has never allowed merchants to possess land and so have a stake in the island# It is easy in consequence for a merchant to pack up his goods and go? Gheikh Isa knows this. Regarding para(?)# Yes in my opinion, Sheikh Isa will accept an order to reduce his .tKxrt tariff on goods \ addressed to the mainland with alacrlty # provided that the order is put firmly enough. Naturally he will not welcome the ■ . . i ■ order, but he will not refuse.19/126 Tolegram.Oode. From - Poli/tical, Bahrain. To - Political, Bushire. Jfo. 162-0. Dated and received 14th June 1920. Foreign 1 s 880-E o A. Presume fXill instructions coming from you. Your 1139 dated 9th June not received here. Political. ♦ Telegram.Oode. From - Trevor, Bushire. To - Political, Bahrain. No.1167. Dated 14th June 1920^ Your t legram dVbed 14th June 162 -0. Answer is in the % affirmative. Letter to Shaikh of Bahrain posted. 1139 was practically same as my 1055 and so was posted such prompt answer from Government of India not 'being anticipated and mail having been expected before this. TrevorX* 7 Si P.O.He. 1 . office of the Civil Coimnissionsr, TTW n a^hdad the 1.5th July, t9?0, 6ftf /- .•« T y dear -huckburgh, your d/o !lo,35l2 dated tOth June, 1930. The Shaikh of Bahrain has alreaiy been warned by Trevor that any action taken now in without prejudice to any arrangements which may subsequently be rendered necessary by international agreement. Kegoti at lone are proves ping on the basis of abeoluta freedoin of transit in the caoe of goods transhipped in Bahrain direct from ship to ship and a charge not exceeding % or 2t ^ in the case of goods landed on the island in the coarse of tranphipnent and subsequently'reuhipped to the mainland within 30 days. I think that this arrangement i^ likely to be accepted both by Bin Saud ani Shaikh Tea and if^ on the whole reasonabl e. Yours sincerely, /YTV--A--V-—- J.E.Shuckburgh, ,C.R., Political Secretary, India Office, London, S.W.I. Copy to: D. P. R. Busiiire. If or ward f o r your inform at ion copier; of l /o c or re sp o n de nee with the India Office. I v» iUH.D. 0. Copy of M mh.'Io .P.3512 dated iOth June, 1920, from J.B.Shuckburgh, ^Isqr., C.B., Political Secretary, India Office, London, , to Col. Wilson, C.C. Baghdad. Your despatch dated 'arch 26th No.10630/6/18 forward- ins' copy of correspondence frorn Jhe Political Ji'iency, aar^.ir relative to the imposition by Shaik Isa of transit dues on goods passing tVmough his territories, T am enclosing here with, for your information, copies of draft clauses relating to Ports, .faterways, and Railways which have been inserted in the Treaty of Peace with Turkey. An international Convention, the clauses of which will, it is expected, closely approximate to the clauses of this chapter, is under consideration, and this fact may be of use to you in deal ing- with the situation at Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 205-G. Politioal Aganoy, Bahrain. Dated th9 17th July, 1920. From Major H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.E., ' Politioal Agent, BAHRAIN. To His Exoellenoy Shaikh Sir Isa bin All A1 Khalifah, K..C.I.Jb., C.S.I#, Ruler of Bahrain. After compliments . Acting under the orders of His Majesty^s Government, I have the honour to send you a letter from the Deputy Politi cal Resident in the Persian Gulf in which are embodied the final orders of the Government of India to Your Excellency in the matter of Customs Charges levied by lour Excellency on goods (transhipment) consigned to the mainland from India and other ports via Bahrain. In a further communication sent me by the Deputy Poli tical Resident under his No. 182-S, dated ISth June 1920, I am instructed to inform Your Excellency that the new orders laid down by His Majesty's Governne nt of India are to apply to all ports on the mainland served by Bahrain, that is to say, Ojair, Qatif and minor ports in ^atif and Hassa, also the state of Qatar. The Trucial coast towns and villages which are supplied by Dibai are not included in these ins tructions . 2. At first sight the new orders may appear to Your Excel- lency aa severe and likely to greatly reduce Your Excellency's customs receipts. I would,however, remind you that His Majes ty's Government has been informed by His Excellency Shaikh Sir Abdul Aziz bin Abdur Rahman A1 Faisal A1 Saud, K.o. 1 •Ruler of Nejd,Hassa and Dependancies that he has passed orders by which all Qassim trade, will, infuture, enter Nejd via the portport of Bahrain. His Majesty's Government are certain that what revenues Your Excellency will lose by reduced customs receipts on mainland (transhipment) goods, will be amply made up by the increase in the volume of trade that will be passing through Bahrain. Secondly I beg to inform Your Excellency that His Majesty^ Government is considering the question of fixing ■nil, customs rate^ to be taken at all ports in the Persian Gulf, whether on the Persian or Arabian shore; such rate to be the same as that already existing in Bushire and other Persian ports. In other words, lour Excellency may possibly shortly be invited to raise the Bahrain Customs tariff to the extent of that fixed by the Persian Govt. Should this take place lour Excellency may expect to receive a greatly increased revenue from your customs. Such increase will no doubt be half as much again or possibly double your existing revenues. I am informing shaikh Sir Abdul Aziz bin Abdur Kahman A1 Faisal A1 Saud, K.G,.!.£»., and Shaikh Abdullah bin jasim Al Thani, 0.1.is*. Ruler of Qatar regard ing the orders of the Government on the subject. This is what had to be said and may you be preserved. Sd/- H .n. P.Dickson, Major, G .I.ii., Political Agent, Bahrain.GQNFIDxJjmAT. . Ho. 3Z S -q T© tr , h ' 1^ N O Political Agency, Bahrain. Dat®d the 3rd August,1920 ntSiOtiul y 3 ¥ Tha Deputy Political Resident in Persian Gulf, Y~~ ^ ~~ B U S H I R E. MEMORANDUM . QUESTION: Reduction o f Customa Duties on transit good s. I beg to forward in original letter from Shaikh/l^a bin Ali A1 Kiialifaii, K.C.I.E., O.S.I., Ruler of Bahrain, in reply to your letter No. 303 dated 14th June last in the matter ©f reduction of Oustoms Duties on transit goods. Shaikh Isa's letter is dated 25th July, 1920, and was handed in to m© a week ago. Speaking generally I donot like the tone of the letter / * apart from the fact that Shaikh Isa has started an argument with regard t© your definite orders on the matter. Prom private information I am able to say that Shaikh Isa did not himself draft the reply. He left it in the hands of ohaikh Abdullah, who sent for Jasim A1 Chirawi from the pearl banks for the purpose. Jassim*s hand and style are everywhere evident in the letter. It is in my ©pinion probable that Shaikh Isa would have accepted the order without dtoir, if he had been left alone. The moment Jasim wag called in to help, the matter went out of Shaikh Isa's hands. This Jasim is, as I have frequently reported before, the Evil genius of Abdullah and a clever rascal. He is interested in the crooked dealings of the customs from which he draws a stipend 2. I might mention that before presenting your letter to Shaikh Isa, I showed it privately to Shaikh Abdullah, and advised him very strongly as a friend, as well as Political Agent, not to permit Shaikh Isa to raise any objection to Government's orders. I told him Shaikh Isa's reputation for accepting advice was none too good at Headquarters and that now was an excellent opportunity of repairing such reputation. Shaikh Abdullah promised to do his best and candidly informed me that the order was H HAQ ,, . ttc+ss i j- £? d- ■ V'T-7&gt; 3. The substanoa of Shaikh Isa's reply, as y©u will see, is as follows ; (a) H© requests to be allowed to take 2-|^ ©n goods passing through his customs for Nejd, and not 2^ as ordered by Government. (b) He pleads for cancellation of the order that no duty be taken on goods transferred direct from s.tearners into dhows proceed ing direct to the mainland. In other words Shaikh Isa very cunningly asks to be allowed to go back to the old condition of things as arranged between him and Bin Saud, before the war,i.e. taking on Najd goods only, even though he expressly refused to entertain such a suggestion when made by me vide my 72-G dated 18th March, 1920* 4. Criticisms « In my opinion^request (a) should not for a moment be entertained or even discussed, and Shaikh Isa be told that a duty of 2j£ has been fixed and 2fo It must remain. Regarding request (b). The matter at present stands as follows No cargo is ever at present transhipped from steamers to dhows and taken direct to the mainland. There is no prospect of such happening in '^e future as far as I can see, seeing that the Landing Company, also a B.I. concern is interested in landing all ~ J - They would lose heavily if cargo were put cfirect rage such transfer of cargo. Shaikh Isa therefor® stands to lose nothing by Government 1 s order^ as far as it concerns steamers transferring cargo. On the other hand, cargo arriving by dhow from foreign ports is frequently transferred to smaller craft and is sent direct to mainland. This transference takes place in the inner harbour of Manamah, and is carefully watched by Customs Officials. A tax of 5fc full is charged ©n goods so transhipped though these are never landed in Bahrain. Shaikh Isa fears under the new order to lose this particular revenue, and this is his meaning when he pl@ads for entire cancellation of order (b). As a matter of actual fact. Shaikh Isa has in existence a wretch ed local rule, which enables Hakhudas of dhows to evade paying this transhipment tax, if they care to go to the trouble of mainland. Hence the B.I. may be counted on to1H sailing out beyond the euter buoy, a distance ®f 25 miles into tbo open sea and there do their transhipment. Naturally no one oarea to do this, especially if there ia the slightest wind on, and Shaikh Isa knows this. 5• Conclusion * (a) The real fact ©f the matter is that Shaikh Isa is uncom promisingly obstinate, he posaeases vast wealth, he wants more, his policy is always to take all he can, and give away nothing,©Ten where it means bettering the conditions of his ©wn islanders. Extreme selfishness shaikh Isa's whole policy, and one daily sees this in a hundred and ©ne small w»ys in hia dealings with this Agency. Shaikh isa new begs in hia letter to be allowed to return to the 2^ tax as in existence before the war. He forgets that I spent a week trying to persuade him to adopt this very tax, and so come to an amicable agreement with Bin Saud.( according to your orders vide telegram n @. 553 dated loth March, 1920). (b) Shaikh Isa qu®r\l©usly complains that ha was never asked to put forward his views and objections, while Bin Saud's side of things was all put up to Government. Here again he forgets that I ov ©r talked the matters/fully with him, and took down'his all objections in writing and submitted them to you ( vide my 58-0 dated 28th February, 192o) • Where Shaikh Isa goes wrong is that he allows Jasim A1 Chirawi, who was never present at our interviews, to ans wer ^our letters, and the s latter makes statements which are cont rary to facts. (c) Finally Shaikh Isa forgets that Bin Saud's request was that no duty ximMXi at all should be charged en transit goods,but only ' ARDHIYAH', or ground rent. (d) in conclusion, I consider it would be unwise to make any concessions t© Shaikh Isa. He should be told that an order given by His Majesty's Government is intended to be obeyed. Should, however in future Shaikh Isa find himself in difficulties, he should be also told that if he puts forward his case then. Government -will always be most pleased to sympathetically consider them. If, ©t the other hand, you consider it expedient to make some show ©f oonoeeding something, then I suggest it should takeo • M 'r the following form only. No duty to be charged by Shaikh Isa on goods transhipped from steamers or sea-going dhows to smaller' oraft proceeding direct to the mainland, provided such ships lie outside the three miles limit, i.e. o utside the present outer anchorage buoy * Any ships transferring cargo inside this limit i.e. in the inner anchorage to pay full Z-g/o dues• The above is only put forward as a suggestion. I am personally not in favour of it. I donot know whether it can be defended under international law. t Major, G.I.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. Oopy? with compliments, forwarded to the Givil Commission er, Baghdad, for information. v„ r'7//^ f /v 0 i From- Shtikh 1st. ben ill /.l-K'iLlifeh, Z.C.I.E., Chief of Bthi;tin To - Lt-Colonel i.p.Trevor, C.S.I., C.I .E., Deputy politicE.1 Resident, Persian Gulf, Bushire Dtted 8th Zi-qtdeh 1338 (=25th July 1920). i. • C« f- V S I hive duly received your letter Ho.303 dtted 26th Rtatztn 1333 = 14th June 1920, in which you conunictte to me the orders of the Government of Indie ebout the levying of ti specUl ttx from goods arriving Bahrain and passing to the territories of the Rulers of Najd and Qatar. These orders are divided into 2 classes. (1) th^t I should levy only a 25? tax from goods consigne'd to the neighbouring interior /rabgtates which are landed at B chrtin, (.3) tha.t I should not levy any tax from the goods tran shipped directly from the steamers to the b 0 ets of /rab Ports which proceed to these ports direct. I had already learned that the Ruler of Rajd had address, the Government of India, but I certainly expected that the High Government would enquire from me about my arguments on this question, after I had heard about it from the Ruler of Najd, before issuing their orders. But, I regret to say, contrary to my expectation, these orders arrived. In snite of thisI am of the justice of the High Government, they will reconsider their orders after they come to know oi their injurious results to their friend's rights. W ith regard to the first (class of) orders, I beg to inform the High Government that the treaty between us restricts me to taking not more than 5? frnn British su bje cts only on goodsiarriving at my town irrespective of their destination. The levying by m e of more than this, or my being forcedforced to levy less thtn this, is indeed clesrly contrtry^ to the treaty. L i.s to the present Ccse # we used to 1 e v y^ during tho ve ers prior to wtr, from the goods proceeding to H^Sc end Qctif vie Bchrcin. This considerate trectnent Wcs accorded hy me of my own eccord without heying been esked, end only vm fa consideration for the commercial interests of my town, end is not en argument for forfeiting my rights under the tre ety # i.fter the commencement of the wer, when imports de ere c'sed end expenses increased es in oth§r town# we were compelled to recover our full rights in thet time. Correspondence wes Hi . | exchanged between me tnd the Politicil /gent Bahrein, Iftjor ntewLrt, G.I.E., wfio tgreed to this according to Just ice, and for about 6 months the Ruler of Ti£ id asked ne to repeat the former considerate treftnent in favour of his territory, viz.that I should levy a 0 f^ tax. But in view of the unchanged economical conditions, which forced me first to charge full dues, I did not agree to lessen them'. The Ruler of TT?jd, I understand, requests me to allow him a reduction under the International Lews and the Fip-h X h Indien Government egrees to this, end, in addition, ellows him more then whet he esked for. But I do not understend the reelity of Internetion el L^ws, end it is the first time I understand the.t Internet'ionel Lews epply to two Irih Rulers, to the detriment of one of them who £Iweys fluttered himself for his friendship and loyalty to the High Government and tlso in spite of treaties and current rules which are known to the Government, perhaps the International,ltw is more useful to me in another way and does not, I think, restrict me to the levying of 5t only. But your friend,according to his custom, respects treaty better than profit. Now, m order to continue -ny old friendship and loyalty,end in deference to the interference of the High Coyernnent, I cgree to the first (diss of) orders ec cor ding to the.ir conditions cs described in the Government T s orders, md only trust th£.t the matter be reconsidered with e view to the heing levied es requested hy the Ruler of Nc jd. i.s to the second (class of) orders, which, to he brief, prohibit me from levying my tax on goods directly shipped from ships into the bo£,ts of the /rab ports proceeding to. those ports direct. The meaning o.f this is that my portion account of its facilities which are utilised by the Ruler of IHjd, becomes his port, and no dsubt he can, wheneve^r he desires, // land goods according to the above-mentioned arrangement. This renders easy for him the importation, especially, of rice and other grains generally. This is very injurious to me, (l) in respect of my products and (2) in respect of my rights es an owner, being contrary to my expectation and title to the Hirh Government. T am unwillinr i to believe that the High Government^ whose advice I always follow, will now force me to forfeit my rights to benefit another person without his having any right and at his request contrary, to other Rulers, though I have left my s relations with them in the hands o'^ the Hir^h Government. Tn Justice I expect from them to safeguard my riphts from the transgression of others as they do theirs. I sincerely hope that they will reconsider it (the matter), and be kind enough to prevent the enforcement of this evidently injurious order.Telegram.Code. Prom - Political, Bahrain, To - Political, Bushire, Repeated Oivcom. Baghdad. No,232-0 « Dated and received 9th August 1920, l v Bin Saud writing on 28th July acknowledging my letter informing him Government orders regarding new customs duty on tranship goods. Though disappointing duty not fixed at 1 per cent he accepts Government orders gladly. Political19/126 er Telegram.Code. prom 7 Political, Bahrain. To - Political, Bushire # Repeated Oivcom. Baghdad, No.242-0• Dated and received 15th August 1920 Trust you will be able to send early reply to my memo 228-0 3rd August e Consider important push matter through as soon as possible view Bin Saud 1 s present dissatisfied state mind; letter from Siddiq Hasan confirming same being posted you. V Political. ' I'MM j I ' — -■ —i 1 50 C.) Telegram.Oode. Prom - Civoonu Baghdad, - Political, BusMre, No.9926. Dated 18th received 19th August 1920. A A i/ K Your telegram dated llth August 1484. I have now received memorandum in question and entirely agree with your views. Civcom. Telegram.Code. From - Trevor ? Bushire. * To - Political, Biishire, Ho.1519. ' Dated 20th August 1920. ^ ^ * 240-S My memo dated llth August/and your telegram dated 15th August 242-0. Telegram dated 18th August just received from Civil Commissioner entirely agreeing with my views so pro'pose to write on lines indicated 'by first opportunity. Trevor. i fNO. S Of 1920, British Rosidonoy and Oonsulata—Gonei'al, Bualilre, 28th August 1920, TO The Political Agent, Bahrain, Menorand-umu , I With reference to your memo no,888-0 dated 3rd August 1920 and oubsoquont corroapondonco ending with ny telegram no,1519 dated 20th August on the subject of the ShaiKh'a objections to the orders regarding Transhlpaont Cargo, 1 forward herewith an official letter to the Shaikh Informing him that ray previous letter conveyed the considered orders of Govemnent, which they expect him to obey without donur or cavil # In addition I enclose a demi-official letter to Shaikh Isa an adoring the points he raised in his eoraplaint on the lines suggested by you, and finally i h?vo added a private note warning the Shaikh to be oarefui of self Interested people In his entourage, meaning of course Jasim Ohirawi, My idea is that you should hand the Shaikh the second letter If you think it will help him to accept Governaent orders with good grace, nnd the third letter mi-ht be given after he has accopted the orders If you think It will do any •good and not put his back up.No. 4-37of 1020. British Residency and Consulate-Genera 1. Biishire ^\iigus t 1920. To Ss ■ H.E. Shaikh Isa ben Vli \1 Khalifeh, K .C.I .E. ♦ C.S.I. A Ruler of Bahrain. 4.C. T have had the^honour of receiving your letter dated v 3th Zi~Qa T deh 1338 making certain objections to the orders of the High government conveyed in my letter Ho.303; dated 2Gth Ranazan. In reply I have the honour to inform I.E. that my letter conveyed the considered instructions of the High Government who expect you to accept them without demur 0 p cavil and also without delay. In the circumstances the orders cannot he reconsidered and I can only repeat them, and warn Y.E. that the sooner you carry them out the better for you and all concerned. L ieut-Colonel, cy t &gt;eputy po 1 it ii^a-f ^Ros ident,per .Gulf. ~ ' - - -British Residency and Consulate-General Bushire, zq-td \ugust 1920• Shaikh Sir Isa ben \li \1 Ehalifeh, I.E.? C.C.I.&gt; Ruler 01 Bahrain. K .C. In continuation.of my official letter I write you in a friendly way to advise you to ohey the instructions of the High government if you wish to avoid their serious displeasure. in this friendly letter I answer the points mentioned in your ,letter of the 3th zi-Qadeh, Firstly, you state that you had expected that the government would have given you a chance to express your views on the question. My friend, you forget that our friend Major Dickson discussed the matter with you at length and took down all your objections and suknitted them to me. so far back as last February and I sent them on to Governinent. I must observe that the Treaty regarding Daymant of 6% duty on goods for British subjects in Bahrain applies to goods des t ined for Bahrain and remaining there and not to goods in transit for other places. This argument is therefore entirely irrelevant. How would merchants in ' t Bahrain like it if when, they order goods from Europe direcl the full Indian duty were charged at Bombay simply i ■ because the goods were transhipped there from a London e styarmsr to a Gulf steamer? \t the present time they chard nothing on cargo transhipped in harbour and only l/8th of the duty on cargo landed. If the High Government had given you instructions to act in the. same way and chtirgeonly 1th of the duty, you would only have been ahle to 8 charge 5th of one per cent instead of 2^ which is Q generally allowed-. As regards Your Excellency^ suggestion that 2i^- should' be allowed, I beg leave to point out that our friend 3 fa j o r Dickson spent one week i4i trying to persuade you to agree to this anicably, and T myself sent a message to you suggesting that this was the rate in 1913 when the Ruler of Naid first turned out the Turks and suggesting that it should be reverted to, but you refused to listen. Then the matter had to be referred to the High Government and became the subject of an order, and therefore it* was fixed at 2 I would remind Your Excellency that the Ruler of Ilald intended that no duty at all should be charged but only ardhiyeh. The High Government itself only charges 1th duty. It is 3 fortunate therefore for Y.E. that the order did not sty you could only charge lih duty I.e. 5th of 1 8 3 , In regard to the 0 nd part of the order as I have said above the High Government does not (nor do other great Governments) charge any duty at all on direct transhipments, and in this no infringement of sovereign rights or any others are involved. No state has a rip^ht to charge duty on goods destined for another country i which simply come to one of its ports by the chances of the routes of shipping, and are not even landed on its shores. I may mention however that this rule is only intendec to apply to goods properly manifested for Hasa, N^jd or Qatar, and bpought by steamer. I trust that the above will show Y.E. that the order has not been issued without due consideration and will convinceNo. ^-3fof 1920 . Br it ish Res idency p. Oonsula te -fenera 1, Bush ire ft? August 19-0. To Shaikh sir Isa ben \li \1-Khalifah, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Ruler of Bahrain. ^ p k. u. ? iy friend; I have written two letters to you today one official and one semi-official about the orders of the High Government re the transhipment car^o question. I in the 2nd have remarked in accordance with official usage that I.E. has forgotten conversation with qtuf friem Tr a lor Dickson about certain matters, but this is merely • \ a polite way of putting the matters. I can hardly think that Your Excellency has forgotten, but I think that mischief making members of your staff are drafting letter; for Y.E. to sign which are not in accordance with fact. Is an old friend and well wisher, I desire to warn Y.E. against such mischief makers, as the results of their machinations and self-interested advice is always bad. It is unnecessary to mention names ~ I mention 'self interested advice' and suggest'to Y.E. that you would be well advised to enquire privately what personal interest the persons indicated have in the Customs. op, lt . Co!o „ elj Deputy political Resident, Persian Gulf. J?CONFIDENTIAL Politioal Agency, Bahrein No. % To MEMORANDUM I am to aoknowledge roooipt of your No. 253/s dated 28th August, 1980, with enolosuraa. I have delivered all three letters to Shaikh lea and if I may express an opinion, I think your second and third letters will have a very excellent effect. In a week's time, failing a reply from Sheikh Isa, I will write and ask from what date I may expect him to put into force Government's orders regarding the revised customs dues. I will keep you informed of progress in the matter. Political Agent, Bahrein80SHIR? SJjiiOfSCJ -.,.c . Ooftfl^on^yjjssr^. Ij&lt; C - 1*^°. ^y^ 1° ^^' t9ci 15th September, 1920. 'k ^^ 7^ Qr- J W Z ti rp -o. -J Ths Deputy Political Re3i(aent 'in the Persian rmif, BUS HIRE. \ ; MEIiORATIDUM U- r % I beg to forward, herewith enclosed, three communications from Shaikh Sir Isa to your address in answer to your letters Noa. 437, D.O 438 and Private Note dated 89th August 1920, regarding Government'a ordera in the matter of cuatoma dues on tranship goods. All these letters came to me 'Closed', without forwarding 0 ' an ^ 30rt ' I took upon my self to open same, and am forwarding them under separate cover. I have drawn Shaikh laa'a attention to the fact that ha should, according to usual custom, be careful to send his letters.(addressed to you) un- sealed and open in future. ihZ) ■¥. - r-t? Major, 0.1.El Politioal Agent, Bahrein. n-ytU X t^^ jFrom- Shaikh^Isa ben \li \-Khalifah, K.C.I.E Ruler of Bahrain To Lt-Golonel \.P # Trevor, C.n.I., C .T .E.? Deputy political Resident, Persian Gulf,Bushire Dated 26th Zi-Hejjeh 1338 (=lOth September 1920). \.C. I v/as honoured by receiving jour esteemed letter No.437 dated 14 th Z i -He j 1 e h 1P 3 S and in reply to it bep- to inform you that in my desire to obtain the satisfaction of the High Government, I have issued orders to the manager o/ the Customs to enforce the collection of duty on goods landed at Bahrain and shipped to the ports of the Rulers of Najd and Qatar^as indicated in your letter No.303 dated 14th June 1920, \From- Shaikh Isa ben \li \1-Khalifah, K.C.I.E., C.r.I., Chief of Bahrain To - Lt-Colone 1 \.p.Trevor, C.G.I., C.I.E.* Deputy Political Resident, Persian Gulf,Bushire Dated 26th Zi-Hejjeh 1333 (=lOth September 10^0^. \.C. I had the honour of receiving Jour demi-official letter No.43 8 dated 14th Zi-Hejjeh 1333 and understood all that you wrote about the natter. My dear friend, I have today replied your official letter in accordance with your advice and I will no longer dwell on the question until I see you and state how negotiations started on the matter with our friend Major Dickson. ✓ Now I have become certain that if I had agreed with the Ruler of Naid directly in accordance with his request to me, it would have been more profitable to me. I thank you, however, for your declaration that if there be any difficulties in these affairs, I should report them to the High Government who will consider them with sympathy, and I expect every help from you at all times. dlr- :Ghaikh Isa ben \li \1-Khalifah, 7,C.I.E.» C.S.I.» Chief of Bahrain. Lt-Colonel \Trevor, C.S.I.» C.I.E.? Deputy political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bushire Dated 25th Zi -Hejjeh 1338 (-10th Sentenher 1020&gt;. • I had the honour to receive your kind letter of 14th Zi -Hejjeh 1333. My dear friend, I an much surprised to hear that you believe that some one of my staff gives me letters to sign that are contrary to facts, I beg to point out to you that none of nj staff dares to do so; nor do I agree to. sign letters that are contrary to facts; letters are not written except when I want then and after I order then. I an sure, however, that certain nischiefnaking persons in this town consider it their profit to create dissension between ne and the \gency by naking untrue reports. ,\s to the duty, undoubtedly, if it is increased nr decreased, its profits are for ne and its injuries accrue t o me. % From- Tor List of enclosures. !• Letter no # 303 dated 14th Jimo 1920 from Deputy Political Resident, Persian Gulf# Bushire to the Shaildi of Baiirain# 2 # Letter dated 8th Zilqadeh 1338 {25th July 1920) from Shaikh of Bahrain to the deputy Political Resident f Bushire # 5 # Telegram no, 1464 dated 4th August 1920 from deputy Politiosa Resident, ^ushire to the Civil Commissioner# Baghdad* 4 # Telegram no # 9926 dated 18th August from Civil Commissioner Baghdad to Boputy Political Resident# Bushire # 5, Letter dated isth Zllqadeh 1358 (18th July 1^20) from Bin Saud to Political Agent, Bahrain. Letter no,457 dated 29th August from Deputy Political Resident Bushire to Shaildi of B ahrain» Semi-official letter no,438 dated 29th August from ^eputy Political Resident, Bushire to Shaikh of ^ahrain# 8. Letter dated 26th Zil Hajjeh (10th Sept. 1920) from Shaikh of Bahrain to ^eputy Political Eesideni# B ushire # 9• Semi-official letter dated 26th Zil Hajjeh (10th Sept. 1920) from Shaikh of Bahrain to Deputy Political Resident, Bushire.Jo i's of 1980 . 3 r : British Residency and Gonsul ate-General, Bunhiret 23rd October 1920 • To Tlie poiitieal Agent, Batoain • - &gt; • }. ' : gomorand'i&amp;u Your endorsement no •1136 da od 14th October 1920 forwarding an anonymous complaint against the Bahrain Oustoxs .Directors# The present adiaini strati on has its faxzits and I think there is litoio doubt that the Dircctora firm mtikoa zoico profits out^f ^ apart from those which they mako indirectly 'by being able to watch the business ot rival firms etc# When the present method of adiiini strati on ras introduced, ...\ v ' however? it wp ^s a groat improvement on the old farming arrangement and greatly increased the 3hai&amp;h*a revanuos# £ai Sahib Bith Ilacr&amp;indass ^Mahara^ (now dead) himself ran the business very woll ard honestly as the winter of the letter admits# But the arrangement was originally only a stop gap the ✓ idea being to try and get the ShaiHi to ro-ox-ganis© his Customs under a Director lent b^r the dovernment of India# so far he has K never agreed to this# Perhaps later on v /hon the Chief Collector of OustOHS in 5 !osopo - air ^a has scoo wyll trained honest Arab of ficials, the 3liaiKh would not be ec suspicioua of an Arab Director if one could be borrowed from Basrah# I think this object should be Iiopt in view: perhaps meanwhile ■ the proBont direotorato oan ho frig into iaproving their adnini atration 'by throats of change etc a»a even into keeping duplicate books one set 'being to Sindhi or Gugratl and the other in English or Arabic? the former would *bo preferable from our point of view as it would simplify trado statistics etc but bettor perhaps Arabic would suit tho susooptibilities/ If so I should thirdfe they might bo rotavined until we oan get the sha~' Ich to reform the Department properly# Lieut^Ool Offg# Political Resident, Persian GulKaraoni, ^ist September 1930. &lt;jth/ AGENT. /0 the politjgal r°'/o . firi LcW ____ B R ( Persian Gulf ). •; ' Sir, It -t' V 1 Siuoe Wxiuxng you last I oeg to write you the foxlowing few lines ror your kind information. iiiat the Directors of tne Customs House i.e. Hai Sahib Marainaas TiKamas &amp; others are working as sole masters appointed Uy The Sheikh Essa Bin Alii El Khalifa sinoe last 10 to 13 years, tney ar. reaping tneir account oooks in Bania Sindhi or Gujrati charector which are never ohecked oy the Sheikh. The Directors simply give the figure 01 1 or 0 his 1; men nelJ£n DUt tn8 aooount OOOKS are never saown to him. Saeikhjdo not Know how to keep the books in reguxar course tnerefore ne handed over his Custom to these directors for management. In tne oegining taese directors were honest and faixful to his master, but now taeyare cusnonest &amp; trouoie some. When tne year ends all the account^, oooks are oeing barried into the ground of their own godowns where thSN are residing, if your honour wtll take a little trouble &amp; inquire into this matter you win atonce come to know taat wnat kind of forgery is goiig on . Instead of taking customs duty in cash tne directors used to take sometimes EMAL i.e. on 100 bags they take 5 oags as Customs duty, the said oags are never credited to tne Sneikh account but are -i.a*.en by the directors, from which tnese directors have oolieoued 13 to 15 lacs of rupees. This sort of forgery can oe proved from tne Customs account dooks as wexl as from merchants books. According to tne Sneiich 's orders wine is strict ly prohibited InvT' tili8 POrt * The Sneil ' 1,8 orcler8 are ' you find wine with y Passenger, taKe from them and threw it into tne sea at the very/O? moment, wnion is never done oy these airecx»ors, uu'C tne said wine it oeing sola oy them into tne oazeu: &amp; they earns lot. write or wrong kindly call the following merchants in your chambers privately and asit them how for it is true &amp; how the directors are trouoxing xxa to the public. 1« Yoosaf Kanoo K.b,Yoosaf Khoonji 3. Mahomed Tyao 4. Mooijimai Ratoomal 5. Bori Knahboy 6. Abdulla Alii (Arab) 7. Ukajnal Jashanmal 8. 'ruleidas tif the firm of Dwasar. The old Political Agent was very kind on tnese Directors because they used to give him presents,anal rewaras &amp; parties ana it is omy on account of him they got the title of Rai Sahib. Sir, dont fever in taking the promt steps against tnese — directors what of that if they are Rai Sahib or Rai Bahudar. It is tnereiore requested that this kind of nuisence may at once be removed and ta*.e tne Customs House in your charge. upolng to hear good news. I oeg to remain. Sir, Your most obedient servant• Sir, if you want to ascertain the aoove story whether it ib ( lam quite in favour tae urltlsn Ruxe) K m-. to19/126, Tel©gram•Code. Prom - Political, Bahrain. To - Political, Bushire &amp; Highcom Baghda.d* No.420-0• Dated 14th'received 1920. oin Saud writing on 2nd November complains that Shaikh of Bahrain not working new 'customs regulations regarding customs duty transit goods in friendly spirit, in particular he mentiones case piece goods. For many years Shaikh of Bahrair. has charged round sum Rs«15/- per bale now Shaikh demands Nejd merchants to pay 2^ on value contents bale claiming right do so under D.P.R.-s recent order comments Bin Saud's statement correct Shaikh o Bahrain technically on the right undoubtedly has introduced innovation to get his back on Bin Saud this is purely vindicative policy especially in view of fact Bahrain cust.oms has increased greatly since Mejd trade via Koweit » . transferred nahrain. Report will follow. - Political. )OQNFIDSNTIAL political Agency, Bahrein No. 452-0 . D-19 To The Deputy Political Resid| I.' '' . • V;... ■■ .d|h£t in Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E* MEMORANDUM In continuation of my tele/gram No. 420-0 dated the 14th inetant, I beg to forward, herewith enclosed, translation of Bin Saud f 3 letter dated 2nd November* (l) The situation is as follows :- Shaikh Isa, the ruler of Bahrein, has, for some years been accustomed to take R* 15/- duty on bales of piece goods destined for Hassa, which were landed at Bahrein, and re-shippsd again without being opened# i The arrangement was come to after Bin Saud had re-pre sented to Shaikh Isa the great hardship that the open ing of wirebound bales entailed on merchantg, seeing that they had -them especially made up in India, so as to ride easily on camels. Shaikh Isa at the time saw the point and agreed to charge Bin Saud on B' 15/- duty per bale. This was undoubtedly a generous concession, and much below the proper duty that Shaikh Isa might have charged. (2) Under the recent decision of Government of India Shaikh Isa was ordered to charge :- on Bahrein pier and re-shipned within 20 days to the main land provided such goods were addressed to well known merchants in Hassa. boats direct, which proceeded to mainland ports without touching Bahrein. (3) After muoh grumbling Shaikh laa accepted the (a) 2^ duty only on'tranship' goods, if landed (b) Wo duty on goods transhipped into sailing newnew order. H 9 , however, retaliated by atonce ingtructing hia Oustome authoritias to' oharge 2% duty on the con tents of all bales of piece goods going into Hasaa. Otevioualy he did this in a snirit of revenge. When T heard he had done so, I pointed out the un-wisdom of the move to his son Shaikh Abdullah, but as Shaikh Isa was technically within his rights, and as he was feeling nar- ticularly sore at having had to gi^e way to Bin Saud, I decided to let the matter rest, until raised by Bin Saud. I was further guided in my decision by the fact that Shaikh Isa, acting under the suggestion of individuals of Anti-English tendencies put dov/n the whole customs trouble to me. (incidentally, Yusuf Kanoo had a hand in this)♦ v (4) Shaikh Isa^ new order meant that Nejd merchants were rorcod with two alternatives (a) To have their wire-bound bales broken open and contents valued by the Customs authorities; (b) to Jaave their baled goods in bond until surch time as the original bills arrived on which the Customs would charge 2$# Under (a) it was impossible for merchants to allow the bales to be opened as no baling machines e xist here, and all bales from Europe or India are baled under high pressure; ^ (b) they stood the chance of having to pay full bio duty, owing to de^ay in the arrival of manufacturers invoice. Nejd merchants finding themselves between the Aevil and the devil and the deep sea, have complained to Bin Saud# (5) In conversation with Abdul Aziz A1 Qusaibi and Muhammad A1 Hawwas, both importers into Hassa, I gather that feeling among Hejdis is running high. The general complaint is that Shaikh Isa, by his n cunning moveIll move' has quits nullified any advantage Bin Saud gained would have been better off, if matter had been allowed to remain as before. They are not far wrong. (6) Ae a matter of fact, I, rather, foresaw the trouble from the first, and in my original letter to you, vide my letter No. 72-C dated 18th March,1920, para 3, i recommended that 2^ duty be charged on tran- ship goods and that R' 15/- duty per bale remain as isnsa before. My idea was that the reduced duty should effect the rice trads only» (7) I think now something should be done in fairness to Hassa merchants. I would suggest that Shaikh Isa be told that his present orders regarding M Baled goods' be revised seeing that as they stand, all the advantages gained by Hasaa merchants are nullified. As this cannot be Government's intention, and as Shaikh Isa will doubt less see the reasonableness of Bin Saud * s objection, he is instructed to bancel his orders and charge instead a round sum of 20/- per bale. This will work out to 2^? on each bale, assuming that such contains goods valued at ft: 1,000/~. A fair assumption, I think, considering bales are small and made up for camel transport. In any Shaikh Isa will get R r 20/- Instead of R f 15,/- which he used to charge. . (8) I would request that you read this in conjunc tion with my original letter^ to you on the subject quoted above, and let me have your orders at an early date. If you agree to my recommendations, T suggest the order to Shaikh Isa take the form of a letter from you as before# w Major,0.I.E., Political Agent, Bahrein. Copy,together with a copy of the enclosure,forwarded to the High Commissioner, Baghdad./Iv Translation of a letter dated 28th Safar 1359(= 2nd TTovernber 1920) from Shaikh Sir Abiul Aziz bin Abdur Rah man A1 Faisal As Saud, G.O.I.S., Ruler of Nejd, Hassa and Dependanoies, to Major H.R.P.Diokson, C.I.E.,Poli- ti-oal Agent, Bahrein. After compliments I understand that the questions of Customs Duty in Bahrein up to now are not nronerly settled. This is a matter which will adversly effect trade and will handicap my merchants. Recently, there has been much in terference by the customs authorities regarding the duty of 2% on goods consigned to Hass??,. I request your honour to inquire into the matter and to take all neces sary action to put things straight, and remove all diffi- the orders culties. I further ask you to carry into effect/that that have been proposed in conjunction with your honour, namely that no duty be charged on goods transhipped to the mainland in sailing boats direct from steamers, and that only 2^ be charged when same are landed on Bahrein Customs House pier. If you are able, I earnestly request that you arrange that the duty on piece goods remains the seime as before, even if it Is only a temporary arrangement (namely 15,/- per bale). ^Por your information, niece goods are the greatest requirement of our country now-a- days. I beg you will kindly afford every assist ance on this matter and remove all difficulties and delays in the way of trade. Usual ending.19/126 Tele-gram •Code. * • Prom - political, Bahrain. To - political, Bushire* rptd Baghdad. No# 4-52 • C • ^ f • Dated and received 28th 1920• Bin Saud writing 4th November strongly protests against Shaikh of Bahrain retaliatory customs policy argues matter on the lines already set forth 'by me in my no.420-0 14th November full translation of-his letter follows, important my mind that early orders by you be passed on matter. Political.no*3SS~ B Of 1920. British Residency and Consulatesenaral f Buehire, Sth December 1920 • To ' x h9 Political Agent # Bahrain. Mornorond^# Your none» 453-0 daiDd 15th Nov^oor rn ardln^ Jim**## D~l§ Icry 'trj Sh^lMa lse&gt; cf izcr &gt;o than EC#15/- on bnle of piece goods '■^© arrniifc*xnr.nt 1 cli ! R0«1?/- 'bale ^as levied was ■.. •prlW'to- ^no mado doirJbtloss for rcasonc of conTonlenco and ojrpodioncy t^otwom the ShalMi 1 ^ Oiistona and the Tlassa ^e^ohant This 'b^lng so# It Is? of course open to the Shaikh to jpetnidiate the awan^enent f and, as you nay, he is perfectly within his rights In chafing 2 $ duty - just as forrerly ho might hare charged 5 J?* in the circumstances it is obvious that I cannot pororptorlly order hte to talre B8.15/- per bale or anything in fact less then 2 X have however wit ten hin a letter strongly advising him to r.alre a fresh coirtpronisoj, by filing a conventional vale of Rs.lOOO/- per halo and charging 2 f&gt; *\ on that - i»o# a round sum of Rs»20/- per halo. I hope he will accept this proposal # ^ h±ent~0olm Political Kesident in the Persian culfmHO. 57' Of 198C. Brltieh Rosldency and Oonaulate^aneral, Bv.shire, Jt&amp;r Mocemb&amp;r 1920• To anallrh rdr Xsa bin All A1 Khalifa, Rial or of Bahrain# I hr.'.r that slnco tho new customs arrangement for goods destined for the Mainlajid was oado, your Gustosis official© have abolished the old custom of charging a round sum of Ro»15/- per hale on piece goods allowing them to go on un opened? and now demand 2 $ duty in full. You are aware my friend that aH the bales of piece goods ar© specially made up under pressure for transport, and that It inflicts great hardship on Hassa merchants to force them tc open tho yyi9m $ or . to wait till the invoices, tfhich are usually delayed, arrive# Xn fact this procedure wily if pereieted In, undoubtedly drive the Hasea trade my from Bahrain altogether# You ••now it ie not difficult for ships to go to K&amp;tlt er.d Juhall and ✓ wit 4 eu doubt if difficulties occur in Bahrain Bin Baud will try and arrange this. Even as matters stand if difficulties become too great it would be possible to send roods to Basrah and bad: -from.there by dhow to Juball - transhipment is allowed free in Basra£u in these circumstances your friend advises you to mafeo a conproniee in this matter and eraggeets that bales of piece - goods taight be considered conventionally to have an average value of Es*1000/~ and that 2 $ on this vist Hs#SO/- should be Charged as duty on each bale. I hope Your l^cellency will accept this suggestion, and that it will not be necessary for me a^ain to report the whole matter to the High Government• This is what had to bo said and may vou be preserved* %y\n Lieut-Col • _____ ^19/126 '7 Telegram«Code• PrOm Hi h Coramissioner, ^aglidad* To - Political, Bahrain. Repeated Political, Bushire• No-14737. Dated 9th received 10th-December 19 0. Bahrain telegram dnted 14th Kovember 420-0. 'ill be' % glad to know decision arrived at regarding customs dispute High Commissioner. Telegram.Code. Prom - Political, Bahrain. To - High Commissioner, Baghdad, lepeated Political, Bushire. No.473-0• Dated 11th received 12th December 1920. Your telegram dated 9th December. No decision has yot been arrived at. Political itili U-. SluitU L19 /126 e e 1 e gram • 0 ode. Prom ~ Reeid'ent, Bushire# To - Political, Batirain. No .2215• Dated 16th December 1920. Y.our ^elegrain No,478-0. Has Shaikh of Bahrain received my letter dated 7th December 5^0, if so-do you know what his attitude is in regard to suggostion made. Resident• Telegram•Cole. Prom - Politic 1, Bahrain# To - Resident, Bushire# No.482-0• Dated 17tli recwived 17th D ©&lt;|pber 1920 • Ycxir t.logram dated 16th December 2215. Your letter of '7th December 590 for Shaikh of Bahrain received by me only yesterday evening will be delivered today. Will telegraph as soon as I can gauge# Political#19/126 TelogranuOode# Prom - Political, Bahrain. To - Resident, ^ushire. Ho #464-0• Dated and received 20th December 1920• Your telegram dated 16th December 2215• I understand Shaikh of Bahrain is agreeable to Rs.SO/- per bale on piece- goods he might make a »how of making this compromise out of regard for Bin Saud as his agent Qusaibi has already approach ed Shaikh of Bahrain on the subject. Political. Telegram•Code. From - Resident Bushire. 0 To - Political, Bahrain No.2246. Bated 20th December 1990. i Your telegram dated 20th December 484-0# Under the c^rcumstancefi nerhaps Shaikh of Bahrain might reply to my letter that he agrees compromise is a good tiling and that in fact he has already arrived at one on lines mentioned out of consideration for Bin Saud. ^ou might convey hint to this effect to him. Resident•l%0 CONFIDENTIAL * Political Ag©ncy, Bahrain. No. £ -G. Dated 23rd D©c«rab©r, 1920- j sushi a? zimtyct I | r • * ^ i I D. T — I T O r| ... Ti-mm]!- Tho Politioal Resident in the Persian Gulf, 3 U S H I R E* * ^ MEMORANDUM Reference correspondence ending with your telegram No. 2846 dated 20th instant. I am glad to report that Sheikh Isa has, at last, agreed to charge 20A per bale of piece-goods, intended for tranship ment to Hassa. He has today sent me a letter,in reply to your No. 590-S of 7th December 1920,forwarded to me for delivery with your enclosed No. 335-3 dated 6th instant, which is/herewith. It will be noticed that Shaikh Isa says he accents your friendly advice and is thankful to you for same. I am writing to inform Bin Baud of this compromise. Khan/Sahib, Indian Assistant, In charge political Agency, Bahrein* Copy, forwarded,%dith compliments, to the High Commission er in Iraq, Baghdad, for information, with reference to his telegraphic query No. 14737 dated 10th instant. «ri Translation of a Istter datad 2^rcl Rabi-al-AwWal, 1^39, ( = 5th Daoamber, 1920) from Bin Saud, to tho Political Agent, Bahrein* After Goa-plimenta 1 hava the honour to acknowledge receipt of your friendly letters and their enclosure, the highly esteemed letter from the friend of all, the High Commissioner of His Britannic Majesty, whom God may preserve, contents of which I have fully understood. 2* As regards the news about 3HARIF ABDULLAH* As I have men** tioned before, I treated the information with some precaution at first; but I have since made further inquiries anrl now beg to in form your honour that,some days ago, I received a letter from the Amir of DAKHNAH, which I have preferred to send to your honour for perusal. 3# With regard to the question of piece goods, I would re quest you to settle as soon as possible, as it is one of the most urgent nacassitles* 4. Regarding the financial aid, my condition is not hidden from your honour, were it not for my urgent needs, I would not have insisted so much and would not have given you the trouble by making frequent reference to it. 5, i trust that in this connexion you will not relax your andeavours and efforts, for which I am thankful. I am also send ing you a letter for the High Commissioner, which I request you to kindly send to His Excellency.19/126 I Is ^ Telegram.Code• Prom - Resident, Bushire. ' Hlp-h CoEmiissioner, Baghdad# No •2275. Dated 28th December 1920. Your telegram dated 9th Deoember 14737. 8haikh of Bahrain has accepted compromiee recommended by me at the suggestion of Political Agent Bahrain to charge round sum of Rs«20/- per bale of piece-goods without requiring examination or invoices etc. Local Nejdi merchants accept this as does agent of Bin Saud. Latter has been informed of arrangement by Indian Assistant. TrevorFrom- Shaikh Sir Isa bsn \li \l-lhalifah, S.C.I.E., G.S. Ruler of Bahrain To - Lt-Colonel I.P.Trevor, C.S.I.» C.I.E. Political Resident. Persian Gulf. Bushire Dated 12th Rabi II, 1339 (-33rd Decenher 1920). ♦ 4.C. I beg to acknowledge the receipt of your letter ffo.59^ dated 25th Rabi I corresponding to 7th December regarding Customs duty on different bales. Your ^riend // really does not like that there should be any difficulties for trade especially the tride of the territory of li»E» \nir \bdul Iziz \s-Saud whon I do not like to displease at all in this connection. In compliance with your friendly advice, I agree with pleasure to your suggestion that Es.20 stiould be charged on each bale without exception. In conclusion I offer my heartful thanks for your advice and friendly counsel. Mi-No. Wof 1921. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, 6th January 19^1. To Shaikh Sir Isa hen 11 i \1-Khal ifah, F.G.I-.E., C.S.I. f Ruler of Bahrain# I ^ 4 • v-' • I have duly received your letter dated Ifth ^abi jj telling me that you have agreed to the su^rrested arrange ment regarding piece-goods for H.E. 4mir \bdul izizV territories. Your friend is glad to hear this as the settlement of this matter will remove a cause of frictio and disagreement between I.E. and H.E.. and also a restraint on trade. -Colonel, a * Political Resident, Persian Gulf.A COITFIPEKTIAL ■ No. 22/C. R I « '♦ t ^ O JJ QC^iOfcS To //^ j 2. 2-1 A h olitical Agency, Bahrain, 10th February 1921. v, i The Hon'ble the Political ^e si dent in the Persian Gulf, 1 i Bushire. o + . \ ■' ^ m; - Reference coi 'respcndence ending with my Memorandum No. 493-C dated 23rd December 1920. I 'beg to forward, herewith enclosed, Shaikh Isa* s letter to your address, sent me under flying seal. It will 'be seen from this letter that His Excellency has not only agreed to charge Rs. 20/- per hale jfrf piece-goods, . as advised, ty you, but has also conceded in the matter of smaller bales or bales of a lesser value ( containing white sheeting ) and fixed the duty at Rs. 15/- per bale etc: This concession - is mainly the result of private efforts and advice of Ahdul i Aziz Al-Q,usaibi who has long been vj si ting Shaikh Abdullah and i Shaikh Isa himself on the subject. The local merchants both Arabs and Foreigners are dissatisfied as they are not allowed this concession ot that of 2^ o^ransit goods sent to Hassa. They will probab^ approach j the Political Agent on the subject as it is detrimental to their, interests-as opposed to the Hajd merchants with whom they can not compete under present ■ circumstances. y^(t/ y, Khan Sahib, Indian Assistant, l/C Political Agency, Bahrain. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to the Secretary to the High Commissioner, Baghdad, for information. un-—- ''' ' la. l&amp;. 4 rFron- rhiikn Sir Isa ben \li \1-rha1i'ah, E.C.o.I.» C.I.^. Chief of Bahrain To ~ Lt -Golonel \,p ,Tr2voi , » C .G.I»» C.I.E# political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bushire Dated 25th Jamadi I, 1S39 (-4th February 19^1). \.C., * — T have received your letter No.10 dated 26tb Ra^i II corresponding to 3th January 1921 expressing your approval of ny agreement to the suggestions in regard to the goods which arrive by steamers and which are destined for the ports \ of \mir vMul \ziz Bin Saood. I always endeavour for facilitating trade, hut I would like to describe the position to you and invite your atten tion to this question. Firstly, the \mir did not have this suggestion in mind formerly but the authors of this are (certain) merchants V * . in Bahrain who have private interests in it and who always try to curtail some of the taxes of my Government on those goods. In view of your advice which I have accepted and whicl' were contained in your letter No.500 dated 26th RaM I, 1839, corresponding to '/'th November 1920, in regard to piece-goods bales^advising the collection of Rs.20 per bale on average, I have instructed the Customs Director to give them effect. \.nd as I am anxious to avoid any dispute, I have allowed reduction on some packages and have ordered that Rs.15/- should be charged on any package containing white sheetings with a view to facilitating trade. JlM- izjvRo. 56-s of 1981, British Rosidenoy and Oonsulato-General, Bushiro, 21st Pebniary 1921* To Tho Political Agent^ Bahrain• Momora.-idigi », J heive reooived your momo, no.22/c dated 10th February enclosing a letter fron Sliaikh lea regarding the rate of* duty on transhipped cargo for Haosa etc# I do not quite understand tho last paragraph of the ■ moxno ♦ ao objecfc o ' instituting the reduced rate of* duty is to lessen the duty on goods which would he directly im ported into Hasaa etc wore there stearaer oorts on the. •*- i mainland* it Is not Intended that Bahrain merchants having ordered goods for Bahrain and finding the marhot bad or a bettor market on the mainland, before the said goods arrive, should be able to transfer thorn to Ha sa and Katif ohd so * 1 pay loss duty on tharn# ' , ' political _ . _____ .ulf.Bo. iXzt 1921- ^ritish Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bus hire, 22nd February 1021. v i To Shaikh C ir Isa hen \li \1 K'.C. I*E», C.C. I., Ci^ief of Bahrain. \ n j have duly received your letter dated 25th Jamadi I informing me that you have not only decided to &amp;harp-e Rs,20 on bales of piece-goods but have kept the charge on sheetings at 11.15 in order to encourage trade. Hy friend ^ I am very glad to hear this. I think that you will find these concessions a good thing in the long run and that they will encourage trade, or at least prevent its going eiseTrhere by other routes which would undoubtedly happen if the transit Cusioms du£s become too heavy. Lt-Colonel, Political Resident Persian Gulf.Telegram Code. F^om - Resident, Byshire. TO - Foreign, Simla. No. 778. Dated 25th August 1923. Bahrain Customs^/ My telegram 735 August second. Would be glad to know when Bower will be available. Kesident.19/165 liu TelGgram Code# Prom - Foreign, Simla# To - Resident, BUshire. Repeated Bahrain# * No# 460-X# Dated 28th received 29th August 1925* Your 778. bi.V?3&gt; Bower sailing from Bombay about 30th August by tt Bamora tt • Foreign . Telegram Code# From - Resident, Bushire. To - Political, Bahrain# No# 787. Dated 29th August 1923• Reference Foreign telegram No. 460-X# If you would like special instructions to Bower in regard to scope of his inquiry and nature of task, endorsed 'by me to give greater authority, please send draft urgently for early consideration# Resident #19/?^- Telegram R. prom Resident t/ Bushire , To political, Bahrain. No . 811. Dated 11th September 1923- xK please show yo\jr 113-C,which I generally approve , to Bower . With regard to si^estion in your last paragraph you will of course recollect that any alteration in tariff is a big question affecting many interests and involving treaty rights . Resident. hi»• A Iq/nb From - The Undei' Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To - The Kon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ywi lUSHIRf BESiDENCY f ivlemoraJidum No.7(84)- a Dated Simla, the Septcmter 1923. |— ' BQSUDtKMA. 'u... 1 Loan of services of Mr.G.N.Bower, Imperial ^ .. Customs Service, to the Bahrein Government, i in connection with the reorganization of ' their Customs. Reference correspondence ending with telegram from the Gov enfant of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, N0.480-X, dated the 28th August 1923. 2. Sanction is accorded, with effect from the 29th August 1923, to the loan to -the Bahrein Government of the services of Mr. G.N.Bower, of the Imperial Customs Service, in connection with the reorganization of the Bahrein Customs, V / on the following terma:- (1) Pay of fis.2,000 per mensem. co^rlbution to he paid by the Bahrein Government &lt;»««• cf In-lip, Plnence and Political Department No.£05/22-Es,., 8mFehru,s ry, i§22J ne ZTvc January iy?.3 SS'S n i8th-®l4 2 ^! 8t 16,, I ****** K0.64-E.B., ^ (3) Joining time under the Fundamental Rules. (4) Pay during Joining time at the rate of Rs.2,000 per menaem. (5) Travelling allowance in accordance with the Supplementary Rules framed under the Fundamental Rules.* 5. The probable period of employment is three months. R.J.Macnabb, Under secretary to the Government of Indip R w u© b xjtiy * / . | s. W' : SuperKitendent, . Foreign and Political Department. .» | IM»//~ &gt;r I 8.&lt; 101 . _ ^ . With 2 spare copies., '' 1 CC'fflj/U No. S'sl -S of 1923. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bus hire , 18th October 1923. Copy ol the undermentioned paper is forwarded with compliments to the Politlca1 ^gent , Bahrain, for inf ormat ion. \ By order , Capt. , Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum•Ho. 7(84)~a dated 27th September 1923 from the Government of India in the Foreign arid Political Department , regarding the loan of servicea of -^r. CKN .Bower. \Th# Agency, Bahrain, 18/10/23. ». (o.vy ^ rom 2ha ^oliticalA^ent, Bahrain, 2© £he the Political Resident Bushire •^ir Bahrain Gastoms I have the honour to report that 3hai]c Haiaad,with the approval of ohaik Abdalla f has written te me asking if H.M.G. will assist him te find an Englishman te act in the capacity of ^ustoras director in Bahrain. The matter has been given very careful attention by Mr Bower &amp; myself &amp; very fully discussed with ^haiks Hamad &amp; Abdulla. The latter are of opinion that there is little hope of their customs being properly run except under European supervision.Mr Bower is putting matters in order ^ will leave detailed instructions te cover every branch of the work,but without a capabale &amp; honest Director,the fruits of his labour will be entirely lost-The horrible state of the accounts under the late Director &amp; evidence of considerable embezzlement, coupled with the fact that during the two months Mr Bower has been herethe customs receipts have enormously increased in com parison with the average for corresponding months for the past 3 or 4 years,bas completely convinced the Shaiks of the necessity for this step, Mr Bewer is of opinion that it will not be possible to induce an officer of the Indian Customs Department to come here even if he could be spared^,which is improbable. He is of opinion that the T)ost could best be filled by a young man,to whom the terms woul&lt;$ be attractive .Customs experience is not essentiel. What is required is energy &amp; integrity, Mr Bower suggests &amp; S aik ^amad particularly favours the suggestion,that it might be poss ible to employ one of the many officers who have recently,owing to redactions of astablishmant,lost thair posts under tha IraqGovernment# Shaik Hamad is desirious of first engaging saoh an office r on a three years agreement,after which time they can mutually arrange to continue the arrangement as a permanent post if desired•! think this would be fair to both parties^ The terms suggested ,to which i&gt;haik Hamad agrees are shewn on the attached list. In the meantime the present Customs Director is asking to be allowed to resign.As his services are quite useless,he will be permitted to do so.A clerk will act in the interim,but it is very desirable that a permanent Director should be found as soon as possible t© put into ef^ct the recommendations &amp;adaryx by Mr Bower &amp; to see that affairs are run in accordance with the instructions he w will leave for guidance. M r Borers principal recommendations will form the subject of a separate report in± due course. I have the honour to be, fjote., i'he political aspect of the appointment of an English Director, has been thoroughly considered both by Mr Bower &amp; myself &amp; the ^haiks &amp; every possible other solution explored.Our final conclusion is that no other effective arrangement can be made. It is proposed to have an #rab Assistant Director,who will,( tp prevent possible friction) be told from the outset,that he cannot be promoted to the directorship,but will be on a time scale of pay &amp; reciave ae tie -ing allowance during the absence of the Director on leave etc. It is recoffimanded that the remainder of the staff shoulff be recruite ojn merit only, independent of religion or caste in li«a of the present system uiider which they are all Hindus of one caste &amp; mainly tff one family . ^he Aaiks concur in these views.^ .£ ' eUSTQMS DIRECTOR,B A H R A I N o Terms of Service * PAY 9 1,000 per month (Arabic),of vrhieh 800/- to 'be paid in eash and M^200/^ to be paid into the BaiHc as contribution toward© Provident Fund# Annual increments of 50/« per ' This would give $ 1,200/- ^.n fifth year R! l f 450/- in tenth year P! 1,950/- in twentieth year and R? 2,200 in twenty-fifth year; of which R s 200/- per mensem would be paid throughout into the Provident Fund» Arrangement© should be made for compound interest to be paid on this Fund at as high a rate as possible offered by a reputable Bank,a«g# the Government of India General Provident Fund earns 5^o This Fund would grow by R® 2,400/- per year plus (at 5%) accrued interest,e.g« Years Amount Sterling Income at Bfo R! equivalent £ £ 10 28,615 1,903 95 20 76#790 5,107 225 25 1,11,264 7,415 371 FREE QUARTERS or in lieu thereof a house rent allowance of R'! 100/~ per month♦ LEAVEo One month on full pay after eleven months* service—^ leave to count from date of arrival of mail steamer in India and to end on date of departure of mail steamer from India. Furdough on half pay after four years at three months per year of service,or may be commuted to half the amount on fuM pay# Leave otherwise according to teUx the Fundamental Rules of the Government of Indiao Travellin g: Allowance #First Class passage for Director(and wife and family if any) to Bahrain on appointment# First Class passage for director and family to England when ser vices are dispensed with through no fault of his owne lan^ua.rre « Lower standard Arabic Examination to be passed on completion of first yea^s MKfcMXKHdxfefcgfcM ^illl . . ^ Ihy h Telegram From Trevor, Bushire. To Claude deGrenier, 6 Meadow Road, Tonbridge, England Dated Sth November 1923. &amp; ^Ivbpi, Are 'you disengaged? Would you like appointment of Director of Gustoms,Bahrain? Gustoms experience not necessary as work simple. Pay Rs.1000 per mensem rising by annual instalments of Rs.50 to 2200 Rs.200 of which to be paid to provident fund. Free quarters or Rs.100 per mensem in lieu. Leave rules practically same as those for Civil servants in India. First class passage jjaid out i and home on commencement and completion of contract which should in first instance be for 3 years or prefer ably 4. Think job worth having chief drawback being climate. If you accept when could you start. Trevor. Telegram From deGrenier, Eight Sheep Street, Northampton To Trevor, Bushire. Dated 9th November 1923. w ( v Gratefully accepted. Start fortnight please advise procedure. TO i^O . Dated Telegram Code From Trevor, Eushire. Daly, Bahrain. 1009 10th November 1923. Degrenier accepts Director of Customs and can start in fortnight asks which way to proceed. By what route had he better come? by overland? should I wire money or can you arrange to book passage through Mespers or otherwise. Trevor,Telegram Code. Prom Daly,Bahrain. To Trevor, Bushlre. No. 163/C Dated 11th November 1923. Following from Bower 'begins:Customs Officer delay action pending further communication next mail ends Daly Telegram Code. Prom Daly, Bahrain. To Trevpr, Bushire. No. 165. Dated 12th November 1923. Priorit y. Your telegram No.1009 crossed my 163 which is now cancelled. Please send by the mail due full name, address, when will telegraph amount required, there is no hurry. Daly. Telegram Code. Prom Trevor, Bushire. To Daly, Bahrain. No. 1013. Dated 12th November 1923. Your telegram 165. Thought-there was hurry so % that new man might arrive before Bower leaves if possible Name Claude deGrenier, 8 Sheep Street, Northampton. Trevor. \'Iju TelegraTn Code (BentlejO From Trevor, Bushire. To Degrenier, S Sheep Street, Northampton, Words 22 Dated 13th November 1923. Your telegram of 9th November. Political Bahrain will communicate with you about passage money. Forgot mention you would be in service of Bahrain Government while Director but Political Agent who under recent arrangements supervises administration would protect your interests. Trevor IV-H/f/r^ 1U5 Fa. Oib of X925. British nesl ency and Consulate General» Bus!lire, the 13th t^fovember 1923. To The Poll leal Agent, Bahrain. He form of Cue torn© House, Bahrain, and appointment of British Director. Meiaorandum. . f Reference your letter Ho. 142/1/15, dated 18th October 1923. Please see i em (1) in the -ro^oeed refox^s detailed in r/^r letter Ho.622^3, da• ed 10th November, to the Govermnent of India; in iMft I have, given a rou^h outline of the conditions under which it is proposed to appoint a British Director at Bahrain and have informed Government that I proposed to make enquiries wi h a view to engaging a roan. In the circumstances,I think, I can do so in anticipation of sanction. fhm at Bahrain I men ioned o you and Mr. Bov.er that I knew a Mr. C.deGrenier, -vho (I thought) would fulfill the requirement© as regards integrity, jseal tid energy (proviaed this did not en mil lengU^y and hurried journeys on horse or donkey back for which Mr* deGrenier is not fitted having a 'game* leg)and capability (bein an accountant by pro fession) . I was under the impression that you both agreed he would be a suitable man,so 1 wired to him on 8th November asking him if he would like the pes' and if so when he could start. I put in his question because, as 1 have i tated in isy letter to Government quoted above it seemo to be very desirable- if in ar?y way possible- that the new Director should Join his a A ointment while Mr. Bovver is still at Bahrain in order to be pu' u. to .he royee, or a', all events com© pretty soon after Er. Be war left to avoid a2 long interregunm during which a good many of the iiaprove- ments effected by Mr. Bower's good work v oulci be lost or at least diminished. The delay in .he Kuwait conference and the fact that Mr. Bover has not got to Join ano her appointment in India appears to bring he Idea of getting the new Director before he leaves within the bounds of possibility. 1 append copies of the telegrams which have passed between me and Mr. deGrenier. I think he Bahrain Govern ment might very well pay- the first was anfortunalely longer than I imended as^through an oversight,it was not resubmitted to me for cutting down before despatch as I had directed. he total cost is Kt.93/13/- In regard to the contract with the new Director, I approve of the pay # provident fund and leave arrangements proposed in the enclosure to your above nentioned letter, and suggest a contract should be drawn a}, on 'hese lines. Provision should also 'be mde for conclusion of tne con tract on three (or would 6 be better) months' notice being given by either party, also that if the Director has to be dismissed for any reason the Political gont should be consulted before final decision is arrived at, and that the Director, if dismissed, will have '.he right to appeal to the Resident and that imilarly the Shaikh will have the same right in the event of a dispute between His Excellency arid the Political Agent about dismissing, or dispensing with the services of, the Director* In view of the delay in commencing the Kuwait Conference there does not appear to be any immediate necessity for Mr* Bower to go there, and I think it would be quite soon enough if he went at the end of December or the beginning of January. If MrJSower agrees to stay on at Bahrain, I have no doubt the Ba rain Gcvernment will agree and I will try and arrange the matter v/ith Colonel Khox. Political Hesident in the Persian GulfFrom The Hon 9 ble the Political Resident in the Persian • The Foreign secretary to the dovermjentof India la the Foreign and political Department, Delhi* ■demoranduffl Ho# 6S Dated Sushi re, the 18th io 1 ? ember 19gf # Deputation of Mr. a.1 .lower to reorganise Bahrain Customs* Reference Foreign and Political Departiaent tfeeorandm So* ^&lt;S4)A # dated ^7th Septa7r.ber 19S3* Mr* lower has Tery auooessfully reorganised the Bahrain CuatOT House, one of the results being, as already reported, that the receipts are averaging Bs.lOOO/- more per dim* The Shaikh of Bahrain is very pleased with Mr* Bower # s wor^ and desires to retain his services until the Hew Customs Director who is being engaged can arrive or as long as possibl before Mr* Bower*s services are required at Kuwait* the Kuwait Conference is supposed to open about the first week in December but X do not anticipate that the various delegates will assemble until the end of the month at the earliest. It is estimated that Mr* Bower 1 s sort at Kuwait will require hi© presence there fbr about 2 months. His services for Bahrain and Kuwait together will then be required for i months. I request Mr. Bower 9 s deputation to reorganise the Bahrain and Kuwait Custom houses may be extended for « months i.e. up to the SSSth February 1924, I beg that the matter may be treated as urgent and that I may be informed by telegrsm if the further deputation of Hr* Bower for 8 months is sanctioned* Lieut-Colonel Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Copy to P.A.Bahrain for information of Mr. Bower19/126. Telegram Code. Prcm Foreign, Delhi. To Political, Bushire. No . 7 .84 . a. Dated 8th received 9th December 1^23 'i Your despatch of IRth November , No. 650. Extension of Bower's deputation up to 29th February 1924 on existing terms sanctioned . Foreign. Telegram Code. From Law, Bushire. To 'olitical, Bahrain. No. II37. Dated ICth December 1923. Following from Foreign dated ICth December Begins . 7.84.^. (Text of above telegram) . Ends. LawD. c do .jir -s. h J fhe Residency , Bushire , 22nd December 192^ 1 pe : very glad to hear that as a result of your labours the receipts of the last three months average as 1150/- daily more than the corresponding months of last year in spite of thu fact that the fall in prices hits reduced the c^sh value of the ad valorem duty. It reflects great credit on y cu and 1 am bringing your excellent work to the notice of the Oovernment of India. 1 am very sorry to near (tor nia own sake espeoiallyf that tiie Shaikh of Kuwait does not w^nt his Customs reorgan ized - His Excellency would certainly get the us and e more a year if ne did 'nave tham inspected . Jor does he want the Customs dispute with Hejd settled - nor, according to a letter we h?ve Just rec*iv c d , does Bin 8aud , so 1 am sorry tD say your deputation to Kuwait is definitely off. However your deputation has oe^n extend #1 tar J montiB to 29th February 1924, and my recent visit to Huacat convinced me thit the Sgyptian directors imported to reorgan ize the muscat Customii in 192C are not much better ti»n the Hindus at BahTv^in were . I am asKing the Government of India if these may be overhauled ®nd if necessary , reogran- iaed . Would you take that job on for a couple of months , if Ooverrment Approve ? When do you want to gat off home ? De Gremer should reach Bahrain about middle of January and 1 suppose a week would be enough to get him going ? If so^and if you like the idea of having a go at Muscat you could per haps leave Bahrain the Jrd week in January and get to Muscat by the end of the month. Ho doufct W9 could get yo^r deputation extended to tbe 28th March or even 28th April if necessary J. Bower , Es^ . f Imperial Indian Gust cms service, Bahrain.Ard if it would not inter!©re with your plans, always provided OovernniPnt of India agree to your taking on the Job» It would be a better tlioe to go noise then than now. What do you say to this idea ? .. —?(«j| - 4 Colonel A.P.Trevor, H.B.M.Politieal Resident, The Residency, BUSHIRE. Dear Sir, T received to-day a telegram, which I have decoded as follows:- 'Are you engaged? Would you like appointment of 'Director of Customs, Bahrein Customs. 'not necessary' as work simple. Pay Rs.1,000. 'per month, rising by annual instalments of 'Rs.50. to 2,200. rupees; 200 of which to 'be 'paid to Provident Fund fullstop. 'Free quarters or rupees 100. per month in lieu 'fullstop. 'Leave rules practically same as those for Civil 'Servants indebtedness (IGOHD) fullstop. 'First-class passage paid out and home on 'commencement and completion of contract 'which should in first instance 'be for three years 'or preferably four fullstop. |Think job worth having chief drawback being 'climate. If you accept when can you start? 'Trevor'. I replied to-day by telegram in Bentley's code as follows:- 'GYPIC t ACHUK SAWAMGISRY ODVADAC t KOV 'OJUSM. de Grenier, 8 Sheep Street, NORTHAMPTON.', by which I desired to state:- tefully accept. Start fortnight. Please 'advise procedure'. I need hardly say that I am deeply grateful for the kind thought which prompted you to make this offer to me; and, while I am now holding a fairly satisfactory appointment in this town, as Accountant to a large manufacturing company, I should be most glad to come back to the Persian Gulf, especially as the salary offered is considerably better than my present one. As it occurred to me that probably the necessary formalities would be entered into in London, The P^tchley, 8 Sheep Street, NORTHAMPTON. 9th November, 1923. mm fltsVofVaif j a. M htvI thought I might enquire the procedure, so that there night be no delay here, since I am not living in London. I do not anticipate that my present employers would stand in my way at all; and, as T have an/my kit ready, I do not see that anything can prevent an early departure, apart from several visits of farewell to my f relatives. 15th November , Since writing the above, I have received your telegram of the 13th inst., which I decoded as follows:- Your telegram of 9th: Political ^gent Bahrein will communicate with you about passage money. Forgot to mention you would be in service of Bahrein^ Government while Director; but Political Agent who under recent arrangement supervises administra tion would protect your interests*. Pending the receipt of these instructions, I am arranging - for my departure; and assume that you would wish me to travel as quickly as possible. I am therefore planning with this end in view, and hope to cable you with definite particulars very soon after my receipt of these instructions. I should be glad to hear if there is anythins: you require to be brought out, or any other service of that nature I may*perform. sincerely trust that both Mrs TyCvor and Yourself kin^ness inS quite well; and wi th renewed thanks for your' Believe me. Yours obediently. iUD.O. HdSo The Britlah Hoaldenoy, Bushlre, the 16th January 1924 Dear Bower, Your D ,o# of January 15th* For years In fact from the start of the Indo European Telegraph Department about 1865 to about 1907 when the Secretary of State graofuly conceded the privilege (and the British Government through the indo European Telegraph Department had to pay compen sation in lieu to the Indo European Telegraph Department officers and clerks#) the question was regulated in favour of free import, first by usage and sufferance and then by Article 15 of the Anglo Persian 'New Telegraph Convention ,, of 1B7S which runs# 11 All articles required by the English staff ^rom abroad for the service of the line shall be exempt from Customs or other duties IjThe Transalation is not good but should be I think and has certainly been read in this sense# 'All articles required from abroad by the English staff (engaged) for the (If* Material etc. for the wir.eless Station which is a boon and a blessing to the traders of Bahrein should be allowed in duty free# • (2^ The concession enjoyed by the Indo European Telegraph Department employees in Bahrein otherwise presumably they would % have to draw compensation in lieu, so as to be on the same footing as their Conferes in Persia* At the sametime to prevent abuse I think their de clarations or whatever this put in to the Director of Customs G»N•Bower, Saquire, Imperial Indian Customs Service, Bahrein#I to clear goods should be countersigned 'by the Political Agent; formerly in Persia declaration used to be signed by the Consular Officer# The countersigning officer would soon become aware of the fact if an Indo European Telegraph Department began importing for purposes of trade# I hsard from De Grenier from the Vasna and he said ho was very keen on taking up his duties♦ I know him to be a con- scientious and hard worker whose integrity is above suspicion and so I hope he will be a success as Director of Customs and later possibly as Financial Adviser as well youre sincerely.&gt; ' &gt;6, iOUFID^NTIAL /Vo Th« •''oliticSl ^ency BahEaim. 11/2/24. IUSHsBI »!S-3f'iCt. ... 1 00«fl8£im. From The Political Ag®nt.Bahrain. To j ^ atnqran ^ 11171 * The Hon f: bla tha Political Rasidont.Bushira. Bahrain Reforms. Your telegram Ho 259 of 10/2/24. I) Proposed contract for Mr De G-renier is forwarded herewith. [2) I do not feel competent to make any suggestions as to staff required for the technical work of surveying. I think that an Indian officer with Tapa or Revenue experience would be preferable .He would be of great assistance to the Assistant Political Agent,who ( if the proposal is accepted by the Government of India) would act as Revenue Adviser tt the Ruler &amp; would carry out the preliminary records of landed proper ty, or rather supervise the work of the officials engaged in it. {3) Report withheld pending receipt of your further communication. (4) It was my intention to report by this mail that Mr Bower &amp; I had arrived at the conclusion,that as long as Customs receipts maintain their present satisfactory,it would be inadvisable^&amp; unnecessary to an increase.The proposal was originally put forward when we had less experience of the results of customs reform than is now available. &lt;0 Oy^-J Major .Political Agent.AGHlJdMllfT mad© this day of A # H # 1342 ('being the day of A.B. 1924) B 1 T W ig B H HIS ifiXCKLKSNCY SHiSIKH HAMIB BIN &amp;33A 1£L KHALIFAH C.B.I. Deputy Governor of Bahrain on 'behalf of the aovernment of Bahrain of the one part and CLAUD 0 lANBBOOK L^WIS-BJ GIligNIKB (hereinafter called Hhe Director) of the other part W H ig b a S the Government of Bahrain has offered to the Director and the Director has accepted the appointment of Director of Customs ahrain IT IS WITal^aiD that in consideration of the premises the Govermaent of Bahrain agree to appoint the Director and the Director agrees to render true and faithful service to the Government of Bahrain upon the terms and subject to the conditions hereinafter set forth namely 1. PAY The Government of Bahrain shall pay the Director a salary of Bupees ^ight hundred (Hs800) only in Indian currency per month rising 'by annual increiiients of Bupees fifty (R- 50) only in Indian currency per month subject to the proviso of Clause 4, helow and subject to a maximum after twenty-five years* service of Rupees Two thousand (n 2,000) only in Indian currency per month 2. PBOVIDJ^NT ffUHD The government of Bahrain shall pay into an approved Bank the sum of Thirteen pounds six shillings and eightpence (£13-6-8) only in Bnglish currency per month so long as the Director remains in the service of the Government of Bahrain to be invested in approved securities for the benefit of the Director^after he retires from the service ofthe Oovemment of Bahrain provided that (a) The Director shall not 'be entitled to this Provident .Fund unless he serves the Governinent of Bahrain for five complete years of actual service and ('b) The Director shall not he entitled to have the use of this provident S'und during his service. Explanation : For the purpose of this agreement a month and a year shall he calculated accordiig to the Arabic calendar ALLOWAMGigS: The Government of Bahrain shall provide free quarters for the Director and his wife and family ^ LANGUAGiii: The Director shall he required to pass the Lower standard examination in the Arabic language (or equivalent examination) after one year's service and the Higher standard (or equivalent examination) after three years' service. The Director shall not he entitled to any increments until he has passed the first examination nol? to any further increments after three years service until he has passed the second examination. The Director shall only he entitled to increments from the date of passing the ahove examinations 5 # L$A\r&amp; (a) casual Leave , The Director shall he entitled to a maximum of twenty days Casual leave on full pay per year of which not more than seven (7) days shall he taken at any one time. Casual Leave may only he taken in the year In which it is due and may not he accumulated or added to other leave (public holidays excepted).(3) (t) PHIVimoi'i iM-UVa . The Director shall to allowed thirty (SO) days Priviloge Leave o.u average pay for any complete year of service Privilege Leave shall he roclconed aa coiuatenoini? on the date of arrival of the up or doim steamer oy which tlie Director leaves Bahrain liusreh or Karachi respectively, and ending on the date of departure of the up or down steamer 'by which the Director arrives at Bahrain from Karachi or l^usreh respectively. rUHLOUGH . The Director shall he allowed ninety (SO) days furlough on half average pay for every complete year of service Provid ed that no furlough shall he allowed until the Director has served fcur years from the date of appointment (seventh day of Jamal-i-Thani A.H.1342) or from date of last return to duty from furlough If the Director so desires furlough on half w average pay may he commuted to furlough on average pay for half the period due. $d) Any additional leave taken at any time shall ha without pay. (e) The period spent on furl-ough commuted furlough or leava without pay shall not count as service for purposes of calculating Priviloge leave furlough or commuted furlough nor shall it he included in the five years service entitling the Director to payment of Provident Fund upon retiring (vide clause (2) ) or in tne fi?e years service exeupting the Director from repayment of the passage money referred to in clause (?) helow. Kxplanation. Jor the purpose of clause (5) average pay means the average monthly pay earned auring the twelve completed months immediatelyl4) ^ preceding the commencement of Privilege Leave or l\xrlough. 6. HEl^NigBATIQlT 3o long as the Diroctor remains in the service of the Government of Bahrain he shall not carry on any trade on his crT own or any one else's behalf ^-^receive any remuneration for services rendered to any other party without the previous consent iH of the Bahrain Government. PA33AGig MQNirf . In the event of the Director^ services 'being dispensed with through no fault of his oto the Government of Bahrain shall pay the cost of first-class passages from Bahrain to England for the Director his wife and family. In the event of the Director resigning his appointment (except on medical advice) before completing five years of actual service he shall refund to the Governideut of Bahrain the cost of his first-class passage from England to Bahrain. TKIOONATION : of services. This Agreement shall 'be terminated (a) 'by either party upon giving three [previous ! months 'J ytiotice and upon stating the reasons for such termination in writing or (h) hy the Director reaching fifty-five years of age (provided that in the case of the present Director an extension up to sixty years may be granted An production of a certificate of fitness for further service from the Hesidency Surgeon at Bushire) and (c) 'by the Director absenting himself from duty without the sanction of the Government of Bahrain Otherwise it shall and hereby does remain in force with retrospective effect from the seventh day of Jarnal-i-Thani a.H. 1Z42 (being* the fourteenth day of January A .B, 1924) on which day the 'Director's services with the Ccvernment of Bahrain ccmmenced. IH Wlimss whereof the Deputy Governor of Bahrain (on hehalf of the Bahrain G-ov eminent) has set his seal and the Director has set his hand this day of in the year A.H # 1342, 'being the day of A.B, 1924, in the presence of)'7v- Tha Agency Bahrain Persian G^alf, 12/2/24 SUSHIR^ RlStDENCHf, .w .._^V /S K OOdHBBHA. V From -p.. Memorandum Th® Political Agent .Bahrain. ( 2he H©n T blO' the Political Re aid ent f Bashire Deputation of Mr £.N. Bower. I v f fhe period of deputation of Mr G.JT. Bower* ends at the close of this month. Shailc Hmada would be glad if his deputation could be extended till the end of March,in order that he can carry out boat registrat' on, complete the building of the pier,purchase of materials for customs shed etc.,which work Mr i&gt;e Grrenier could hardly (to successfully in addition ts his duties which are new to him &amp; which nMr Bowers: is able to instruct him in. Mr Bower is proceeding on long leave on April the first,^ his return to mdia for so short a period would be waste of timo for all concerned, would you be so good as to arrange the matter, if neccessary ,by tilegraph. I regret that earlier notice w®s not given, but several causes made it impossible to decide earlier. Major, political Agent. \Brl tiah Keoidency and Coneulate-G©ncraX. From - he Hon f ble the Political esident in the Peroian Gulf o - he Foreign Secretary to the Oov rnment of India in the oreign and olitical Department. Ho. II 1 **0. Of 1924. ' Ba ed Buehirct 17th ! ebruary 1924. ^ in eforrrm: C ub omb . t r vmmxm . Hef rence your telegram Mo . 315~S dated 8th February 1924 9 I forwaro herewith a draft agreement between OhaiJch liariad # Deputy Buler of Bahrain, and i-r. G. ae Orenier, *he newly appointed Director of Cue tome, which I think ©eex?m advan ageoue both to the ; hai&amp;h and to Mr. de Grenier, and of which 1 hope Government will approve. Mr* de Grimier arrived a Bahrain on he 14ih January and assumed charge of hi® duties at once as r. Bower fell ill the day after Mr. de Orenier arrived. I am glad to »ay that on my recent vieit jo Bahrain the Political A^ent said Mr. Bower considered, and he agreed, that Er. de Crenier was shaping well, and would probably be a succeae. Lieut-Col., Political eeident in the Persian Gulf. No. -S of 1924. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 17th February 1924. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent, Bahrein with reference to his memorandum No. 43-C dated 11th February 1924. By order, Capt., Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulfx he HeBidency t Bushire, 18th February 1924. I duly received the draft contract between the Shaikh of Bahrain and yourself, and your letter on the subject, by last mail. I am sending on the draft contract on to the Government of India for their approval as they have asked to see it. In regard to the points you mention: (1) My telegram to you was based on a minute of the proposed terms made by Major Paly in consultation with Mr. Bower. It is correct that I mentioned is 2,200/- as the ^ total figure, but then I mentioned Rs 1,000 ae the commencing figure with the proviso that Bs 200/- was to be deduc ed ! ^ monthly for the Provident Fund. I remember that in the first draft of the telegram I wrote Ks 8,000/- for the maxir-:uia pay and on looking at it again it occurred to me that you would think that as Fs 200 hats to be deducted this would really be only Ss 1,800/-, so I altered the figure to Hs 2,200/- thinking that you would realize that the nett maximum pay was Ks 2,000/- » and fc 200/- for the Provident fund. (2) According to the letter of the contract you might possibly be entitled to house rent allowance, but in a small place like Bahrain the fact that you are not paying rent to o - ' ■ Mespers would be known and I think the haikh and other people would think it rather curious if you drew rent. On the other hand if Vespers decide to charge you some rent for he rooms you occupy, or you rentec a house in he town, you would, v I think, be entitled to draw rent allowance. (3) C. de Grenier, sq.. Director of Customs, V Bahrain.7 (3) Ab regarde steamer fare I think you are entitled to the whole fare to Bahrain, P. &amp; 0. and B.I. # unleae any specific men ion of B.I. was made. As I telegraphed to you about the ma ter you were right in assuming that there was some hurry and in coming by the quickest route: I am under the impression that the B .I. steamers go only once a month or so. (4/ I put in the words w three years or preferably four H in the telegram offering you he Job as I^ajor aiy and Mr. Bower thought that tfrree years or preferably four was the minimum time which a suitable man should stay, with Oie intent- -ion that if the arrangement proved agreeable to both parties i it should be extended to a more permanent contract. I think it is understood that if you desired to leave Bahrain at the end of your first contract, which appears to be four years, you are entitled to a passage lo London, but 1 will ask Major -Paly about this.D. 0. H o ./3^-S. Ihe Residency, Bushire, 20th February 1924. I enclose a co ^ ji of a letter Mr. de Grenier sent me regarding the drcxft contract, together with a copy of my reply thereto. (1). In regard to the first point mentioned by Mr. de Grenier; the qu stion of the maximum pay being 2,000 or 2,200 depends on whether you regard the pay as including the Rs 200/- a month for provident fund or not. In the memorandum en* -closed in your letter No. 142/1/15 of 18th October 1923, you % included it and gave he pay as 1,000 rising to 2,200/- with ■ 200/- to be deducted willy nilly ; Mr. Bower in the contract t ■ puts the pay down as 800 rising 2,000, and the 200 monthly as a separate amount paid by the Bahrain Government into the Bank or invested in approved securities. here does not appear to be much in it. (2) he 2nd point has been explained in my letter to Kr. de Grenier; what is allright and quite within the letter of the law in London and other populous places might excite unfavour able comment in a small place, especially in a i.lace like Bahrain where 90 per cent of the population are inveterat e busybodies. (3) In the absence of any specific instructions to come by B.I. I should think Mr. de Grenier is entitled to his full fare, P. &amp; 0. and B.I., to Bahrain. (4) In one of your letters you said the Director should agree to stay 3 or preferably 4 years in Bahrain (if found suitable) and I put this into my telegram. Be Grenier says he Major C. K. Daly, Political Agent, Bahrain .he has agreed to 4 years. It seems to rae that if he has to leave for any reason except gross misconduct he is entitled to his fare home» But the contract seems to bind him to five years; I donH know how this period of 5 years crept in, and suggest it might be altered to four years.i Telegram Code. ! From Resident , Bushire. To * Foreign, Delrii . No - 335 • Dated 20th February 1924. Tour telegram 7-84 . Bower 1 s d eputat i on . Shaikh named asks for further extension of one month to enable Bower to complete registration of boats on which he is now engaged . Will Q-ovemment be pleased to sanction on existing terms . Arrangement seems convenient as I understand Bower has been granted leave from 1st April , so it would be useless for him to xeturn to duty in India . Trevor . Telegram Code. From Foreign, Delhi ♦ To Political, Bushire, No. 7-84-A. 0 Dated 25th received 26th February 1924. Your telegram No. 335 of 21st February. BOYffiR Proposal sanctioned. Foreign. Telegram R. Prom Secretary to Resident, Bushire. To Political, Bahrain. No. 360. Dated 26th February 1924. Your memorandum 45/C. Bower T s deputation. Foreign sanction further extension of one month. Lav/ •1^ The Residency, Bush ire f 26 th ^arcii 1924. 1 received your note of the 4th March acknowledging with thanks letter of 18th February commenting on the points you raised in connection with your draft agreement# ihen X received your first letter I was doubtful whether 1 should not refer you to Major Daly, hut decided not to do so but to answer because X had Bent the telegram offering you the post at Bahrain and you probably wanted to hear exactly what 1 meant by certain phraaeo in it* So X wrote ray letter of 18th February, but I think it necessary to inform you that I should not have made any comments if I had known you had, d after discussion with Mr. Bower, stated that you quite understood his point of view and agreed that he was right; also that af r er ' you wrote to me you discussed the question with Major Baly and never told him that you had written to me. I only heard about this when I was at Bahrain on the Slst instant, and in the circumstances as my letter was written without full knowledge of the matter, 1 think it will be best to regard it as cancelled. I am going to leave Bushire almost immediately, and my successor of course knows nothing about you, so in any case it would be useless to write to him. But, aa a friend, I advise you not to go behind the backs of the officers in Bahrain, as it is not at all a good way to behave, not mention that it will do you no good in the long run. And I ask you to remember this: the British Govern*- ~ment has instituted the reforms at Bahrain and put in an English Director of Customs to improve the Customs revenue of the Islands and to benefit the Government and people. Your metier de Grenier, sq., Director of Customs, Bahrain «/ ' / 1 [%&gt; 2 metier therefore is to work in concert with the Political Agent to achieve this object, and do all you can to increase the revenue and reduce the outgoing® of the Custom House, and as the reforms are introduced, by the British Government,10 consult the representative of the Government, to wit the Political Agent, when you have any proposals involving the Bahrain Government in expenditure, before suggesting them to Shaikh Hamad. I am sending a copy of this letter to Hajor Daly and advise you to be guided by hia advice in all matters of Importance# iishing you all success and hoping that you will, as you expressed a hope to me on the Customs jetty that you v *ould do, justify your selection for the appointment, X am, Yours sincerely.D.O. Ho.Tol -S /sv fv '^e Residency, Bushire, 26th March 1924* O 4 -4- On my return here I found a letter dated 4th March from de Grenier waiting for me acknowledging my letter of 18th February which seems to have missed a mail somehow and only reached Bahrain on 3rd March; this gave me a leg on which to ^ j write to him again# cancelling my former letter and giving him a homily. I enclose this and if you think it suitable please send it to him# But there remains the pQint that I think the comments I have made on the contract are right; the first two are nothin but as regards (3) I thought (and still think) there was a hurr, 1 telegraphed to him on 8th Kovember 1923 offering him the Job and concluding 'If you accept when could you start ? , ^ He replied on 9th November M Start fortnight 1 ', idea was to get the new man to Bahrain before Bower left, and at that time we thought he would be leaving on 28th December. Xt was then perfectly unforeseen that he would stay till 28th March. he fact that you and Bower do not wish de Grenier to come over to Bushire while Bower is there showing him the ropes, shows that it was advisable to have him there with Bower to instruct him and that I was right originally in wanting him to be at Bahrain during Bower's tenure. So I ooneider he was justified in coming quickest route possible, and entitled to the balance of the 1st class fate. As regards (4) in your memorandum 42/10/15 of 18th October on 1st line of 2nd page you stated 'Shaikh Hamad is desirous of first engaging such an officer on a three years a^r( •ment' and in a D.O. addressed to me you made use of the expression Major C. K. Baly, olitical Agent, Bahrain.2 expression'three or preferably four years' which I embodied in iny telegram of 8th November* It seems to me that even four years is too long to stay out in Bahrain without leave to r.ngland, if one expects food work* Is Bower's idea to make a contract with him for five years the last year being on leave on half pay ? If so and de Grenier agrees I see no objection# But if he doesnH I donH see how we can force him to as I offered him (in your own wor&amp;s) a contract for three or preferably four years•'iM- ♦ 0. * \ \ he Residency, Busliiro, Bth f ,vs erezTlng to my D.O* Ho • SOi** du ted 26th larch lafst I enclose for your information a copy of a letter I have received from de Grenier in answer to mine. I hope he will play up and do hie work properly no^- I am astpnished at hl6 behaviour, a« while here he always seemed bo conscientious and h&amp;r^rwor^in^* } his was not my opinion only but was shared by Parsons* his actual superior, and others who knew him. Let us how* he has realized by now what his position as Customs Director, Bahrain, is* ijor C. K* Daly, Political Agent, I'al.rain \From - The Deputy Secretary to^the Government of India in the Foreign and political Department, To - The Hm'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf .(Z*™ V E8 ™ | _H' Memorandum No. 480-X. 4 Dated Simla, the/^-' April 1924. |— sesfiBtm*. ucssat. Draft Agreement between Shaikh Jfemad, Denuty Ruler of Bahrein, and Mr.C.de Grenier, Director of Customs, Reference your memorandum No. 125-3, dated the 17th February 1924. It is stated in your letter N0.716-S., dated the 22nd December 1923, that Mr. de Grenier was offered, and accepted, the appointment of Director for a period of three years, but the draft agreement provides that he shall have no interest in the moneys to be invested for his benefit until he has done 5 yeurs actual service as defined in the draft, and also that either party may terminate the agreement on 3 months' notice. It is understood, however, that the terns of the draft are those under which Mr. de Grenier is to be actually employed, and if this is the case, and you have no further remarks to offer, the agreement of which a draft as amended and approved by the Government of India is enclosed, may be concluded forthwith. Sd.C.Latimer, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Attested. Superintendent, \y&gt; ^ Foreign and political Department. ^ ,71 3U ^ t.A ^&lt;• 1 v .-, . : ■ 'fV Agreement made JfbAg , ^ 3aj of A .H. 1342 (oeing the ^ day of A #D#1924) .Between His Excellency Sheikh Hamid 'bin -issa el Khalifah, O.S.I*, Depu 4 :]'- Governor of Bahrain on behalf of the Government of Bahrain of the one part and Olaud Oranhrook Lewis-de -Grenier (hereinafter called the Directorj of the other part it is 'between the parties hereto as follows 1 # Tb.e Govermii^nt of Bahrain shall as from the seventh day of Jamal-i-Thani A.H. 1342 {being 'he fourteenth day of January A.D. 1924)employ . the Director as the Director of Customs Bahrain and the Director shall render true and faithful service to the Government of Bahrain upon the terms and subject to the terms and conditions hereinafter contained. 2. The Government of Bahrain shall pay the director a salary of Rupees eight hundred in Indian currency per month rising subject to the provisions of clause 4 hereof by annual increments of Rupees fifty in Indian currency per month and subject to a maximum after twenty-five years 1 service of Rupees too thousand in Indian currency per month. 3. The Gcvernmpnt of Bahrain shall pay into a Bank approved the Political riesident, Persian Gulf Ihereinafter^call/»d the 1/ \ i'oli ■ ical Hesident) the sun of vouadn cir aliilliaga c Ai i in Boglieb. currency month so long as the 1,^ y\r Director remains in the service of the Government of Bahrain to be invested in Government of India securities to be approved by the Political resident and endorsed payabl e to the Poli'ical Resident and the saic, securities shall be handed over to the Director on his retiring from the service of the Government of Bahrain or in ^he event of his dying during service to his heirs or legal representatives Provided always that ~ (ij Neither the Director nor his heirs or legal representatives shall be entitled to receive the said securities until the Director has completed five years of actual service , (2} The Director shall not be entitled to receive the interest upon the said securities nor deal with the samesame in any vray during his service. 4. For the purposes of this agreement the period of a month • and a year shall be calculated accord in- to the Arabic calendar. 5. The Grovernm-nt of Bahrain shall provide free quarters for the Director and his 7 /ife and. family. 6. The Director shall pass the Lower-standard examination or an equivalent examination in the Arabic language before the expiration of one year's service and the Higher Standard Examination or an equivalent examination before the expiration • of three years 1 service. The Director shall not be Entitled to receive any increments of his salary until he has passed the first examination nor to any further increments after three i| years service until he has passed the second examination. The Director shall only be entitled to increments from .the date of passing the above examinations. 7. The Director shall be entitled to a maximum of twenty days casual leave in addition to public holidays on full pay p®r year of which not more than seven days shall o? taken at any one time. Casual leave may only be taken in the year in which it is due and may not be accumulated or added to o£her leave except public holidays. 8. The Director shall be allowed thirty days 1 privilege leave on average pay for every complete year of service. Privilege leave shall be reckoned as commencing on the date of departure of the up or down steamer by which the Director leaves Bahrain for Basrah or Karachi respectively, and ending on the Sate of arrival of the up or down steamer by which the Director arrives at Bahrain from Karachi or Basrah respectively* 9. The Director shall be allowed ninety days 1 furlough on half average pay for every complete year of service provided that no furlough shall be allowed until the director has served four years from the date of his appointment namely the seventh da3 T of Jamal-i-Thani A.H. 1342 or from the date of his last return to duty from furlough. v wif 'W*• /f a. y c ' If the Director so desiresjfurlou^ on half average pay may be commuted to furlough on average pay for half the period due. 10# Any perioc sp o nt on furlough.commuted furlouph or leave 1 o without pay shall not count as service for purposes of calcula ting privilege l«ave ; furlou.-h or ccnmuted furlough nor shall any such period he included in the five years of actual service specified in proviso (l) to clause 3 hereof or in the five years service specified in clause 13 hereof. 11. For the purposes of this agreement the expression average pay shell mean the average monthly pay earned during the twelve completed months immediately precediu , the commence ment of privilege leave or furlough, 12* So long as the Director remains in the service of the Government of Bahrain he shall not carry on any trade on his own or any one else 1 s behal£ or receive any remuneration for services rendered to any other party without the previous cons en- of the Grovernment of Bahrain. 13. In the event of the Director's services 'being dispensed with through no fault of his own the Government of Bahrain shall pay the cost of first-class passages from Bahrain to England for the Director his wife and family. In the event of the Director resigning his appointment (except on a medical * certificate&gt; before completing five years of actual service he shall refund to the Government of Bahrain th o cost of his first-class passage from England to Bahrain. 14. This Agreement shall continue in force until it is terminated - . (l) by either party giving to the other three months previous notice in writing (K (2/ upon the Director reaching fifty-five years of age Provided that an extension up to sixty years may be granted on production of a certificate of fitness for further service from the Besidency Surgeon at Bushire or (S) by the Director absenting himself from duty except for reasons beyond his control without the sanction of the Government'U . CONFIDENTIAL. Ho. iho -3 of 1924. British Residency and Consulate^General, Bushire, 5th ^ay 1924. Gopy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to this office endorsement Ho. 126-3 dated 17th Pebruary 1924, for necessary action. ■ / ' * / yj By order, Gapt., Under Secretary to the Political Ai esident in the Persian Gulf. Foreign and Political Department memorandum Ho. 480-X dated 10th April 1924, and enclosure.-r/s'/i-'-t • V ' Serial No. 296. —From the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persmn Gulf, Memorandum No . 125-S. of '1924, dated ;Bushire ? 17th (received 26 th) February 1924. Bahrain ReformsCustoms. Reference your telegram No. 315-S, dated 8th February 1924 (Serial No. 285) I forward herewith a draft agreement between Shaikh Hamad, Deputy Ruler of Bahrain, and Mr. C. de Grenier, the newly appointed Director of Customs, which I think seems advantageous both to the Shaikh and tp Mr. de Grenier, and of which I hope Government will approve. Mr. de Grenier arrived at Bahrain on the 14th January and assumed charge of his duties at once as Mr. Bower fell ill the day after Mr. de Grenier arrived. I am glad to say that on my recent visit to Bahrain the Political Agent said Mr. Bower considered, and he agreed,, that Mr. de Grenier was shaping well, and would probably be a success. Enclo. of Serial No. 296. AGREEMENT made this day of A. H 1342 (being the dav of A.D. 1924) between His Excellency Sheikh Hamid Bin Essa ErKhalifah, C.S.I., Deputy Governor of Bahrain on be half of the Government of Bahrain of the one part and Claud Cranbrook Lewis-de Grenier (hereinafter called the Director) of the other part. Whereas the Government of Bahrain has offered to the Director and the Director has accepted the appointment of Director of Customs Bahrain It is witnessed that in consideration of the premises the Government of Bahrain agree to appoint the Director and the Director agiees to render true and faithful service to the Government of Bahrain upon the terms and sub ject to the conditions hereinafter set forth namely— 1. The Government of Bahrain shall pay the Director a salary of Rupees Eight hundred (Rs. 800) only in Indian currency per month rising by annual increments of Rupees fifty (Rs. 50) only in Indian currency per month subject to the proviso of Clause 4 below and subject to a maximum after twenty-five years' service of Rupees Two thousand (Rs. 2,000) only in Indian currency per month. 2. Provident Fund. —The Government of Bahrain shall pay into an approved Bank the sum of (Thirteen pounds six shillings and eight pence (£13-6-8) # only in English currency^per month so long as the Director re mains in the service of the Government of Bahrain to be invested in. approv ed securities for the benefit of the Director or his heirs or assigns, after he retires from the service of the Government of Bahrain provided that {a) The Director shall not be entitled to this Provident Fund unless he serves the Government of Bahrain for five complete, years of actual service, and The Director shall not be entitled to have the use of this Provi dent Fund during his service. Explanation. —For the purpose of this agreement a month and a year shall be calculated according to the Arabic calendar. 3. Allowances. —The Government of Bahrain shall provide free quar ters t for the Director and his wife and family. 4. Language. —The Director shall be required to pass the Lower Stand ard examination in the Arabic language (or equivalent examination) after one year's service and the Higher Standard (or equivalent examination) after three years' service. The Director shall not be entitled to any incre ments until he has passed the first examination not to any further increments after three years service until he has passed the second examination. The Director shall only be entitled to increments from the date of passing the above examinations. Note .—Equivalent of Es 200 per mensem with which it is proposed to purchase an annuity. ^ r'. c. K. D. • v ^ ' f Suitable quarters nearly completed. ' C. K D. -fci hjPAA&amp;t*- L**' ti ' M (6)(96 ifacC 5. Leave. —(a) Casual leave. —The Director shall be entitled to a maxi mum of twenty days casual leave on full pay per year of which* not more man seven (7) days shall be taken at any one time. Casual leave may only be taken m the year in which it is due and may not be accumulated or added to other leave (public holidays excepted). p . Privilege Leave. —The Director shall be allowed thirty (30) days' rrivne^e Leave on average pay for any complete year of service. Privilege Leave shall be reckoned as commencing on the date of arrival of the up or down steamer by which the Director leaves Bahrain for Busrah or Karachi respectively, and ending on the date of departure of the up or down &gt; steamer' by which the Director arrives at Bahrain from Karachi or Busrah t respectively. (c) Furlough. —The Director shall be allowed ninety (90) days' furlough on nali average pay for every complete year of service. Provided that no fur lough shall be allowed until the Director has served fouF years from the k UH j 0 J appointment (seventh day of Jamal-i-Thani A. H. 1342) or from date of last return to duty from furlough. -Di rec tor so desires furlough on half average pav mav be com muted to furlough on average pay for half the period due. {d) Any additional leave taken at any time shall be without pay. 00 period spent on furlough commuted furlough or leave without pay shall not count as service for purposes of calculating Privilege leave fur ou.fh or commuted furlough nor shall it be included in the five years service entitling the Director to payment of Provident Fund upon retiring (vide clause (2)) or m the five years service exempting the Director from repav- ment ot the passage money referred to in clause (7) below. ' Explanation. For the purpose of clause (5) averaqe pay means the average monthly pay earned during the twelve completed months imme diately preceding the commencement of Privilege Leave or Furlough. 6 Remuneration.—So long as the Director remains in the service of the Government of Bahrain he shall not carry on any trade on his own or any one else s behalf or receive any remuneration for services rendered to any other party without the previous consent of the Bahrain Government, 7. Passage Money.—In the event of the Director's services being dis pensed with through no fault of his own the Government of Bahrain shall pay the cost of first class passages from Bahrain to England for the Direc tor his wife and family. In the event of the Director resigning his appoint ment (except on medical advice) before completing five years of actual ser- I vice he shall refund to the Government of Bahrain the cost of his first-class passage from England to Bahrain. 8. Termination of services.—This Agreement shall be terminated. (a) by either party upon giving three months' previous notice and upon stating the reasons for such termination in writing or ^ (h) by the Director reaching fifty-five years of age (provided that in the case of the present Director an extension up to sixty years may be granted on production of a certificate of fitness for further service from the Residency Surgeon at Bushire) and (*) by the Director absenting himself from duty without the sanction of the Government of Bahrain. Otherwise it shall and hereby does remain in force with retrosnective effect from the seventh day of Jamal-i-Thani A. H. J342 fbeins? tin? fnnr teenth day of January A. D. 1924) on which day the Director's services with the Government of Bahrain commenced. In witness whereof the Deputy Governor of Bahrain (on behalf of the Bahrain Government) has set his seal and the Director has set his hand *r S da &gt;' of in the year A. H, 1342, being; tlle day of A. D. 1924. SEALED by the Deputy Governor of r 1 Bahrain in the presence of . . . , . . SIGNED by the said Claud Cranbrook ^ v t Lewis-de Grenier in the presence of SCP Delhi—L XI—899—3 4-21-7. Mi i i * Si :v 1 W |tV? 19/126. Telegram R, Resident, Bushire. ^aly, Bahrain. No. 697. Dated 6th June 1924. j| Your memorandum 130 dated 1st June. Agreement is presumably signed. Alteration proposed therefore necessitates formal supplementary agreement Please draft for submission to Government of India. Prideaux.- i i lirff 9/k^ /f ^ /?/; Gonfiaential The gency Bahrain. i / ^ BUSHiRE RESIC : ^rv Persian Galfo l Re*. No. &gt;: • 7 /6 /24 -^ j | CONFiDEMTlAL REGQaDS. _ j ii'rom The Politics 1 Agent, Bahrain, To The Hon T ble the Political Resident J^ashire. ^ernoranduii Mr de (Jrenier's agreeraent with Bahrain Govemt. [ Please refer Vo your telegram IJo 697 • The agreement has not yet \ been signed pending your fihal sancti3n. ^11 that is required therefore . is to substitute Ks 2oo for the equivalent in sterliiig. It'would be [ most inconvenient for all concerned to calaSJIfete in sterling &amp; would | constantly fluctuate with the rate 2)f exchange. The original sum agreed | urjon was Hs 200 per mensem.The Stirling equivalent was only substituted | when it was intended to remit the money to an English Bank: for the purpose of purchasing an annuity for Mr de grenier.Now that the Govt, of India have directed that the money be placed in a Bank in India ^ invested in Govt.of India securities,which are quoted in rupees^it would be normal for the payment to be made in rupees.Both peirties to the I agreement also desire this.If you approve would ySu kindly wire me the single word 'agreement 1 when I will have the necessary alteration made &amp; get the agreement signed by both partieso. M s for, Political iu ent Bahrain.Confidential. No jifX/5/I9 The Agency Bahrc, in. Persian Gulf 22/6/24 i cONflOEHTlMJ 2-o| S To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ,Busliire. •''temorandum lilr G de Grenier's agreement v/ith the £0*0^ Government of Bahraam, Please refer to your ITo 346-S &lt;Sc previous correspondance. The agreement has now 'been duly signed 'by the parties ©onderned I await your instructions regarding the payment for Mr de Greniers pension contribution• As it would seem desirable that the name &amp; address of Mr de Grenier's next-of-kin should 'be on record I have obtained from him the necessary information— Uext-of-lcin — Mr Stuart Prank de Grenier 6 Meadow Road, Tonbridge,Kent.England» Executor of his will -- Mr John Lindfield Smith, Beverley Bungalow, Chorleywood,Bucks.England Ma/or♦Political Agent1^1 I ^ * / I* ^9 fj©f 1925. PQlitiaal Ag»a®y, Balaraim, Dat«d S mc I Dssaiabar 1925. |BUSH;FfR RESIDENCY (ft f- ItMe ,f:,&lt;»:,*&gt; ' 1 CONFIOE NTIAL RECORDS. Ta Maj^r, O.K.Dalj, O.I.E., , P®liti®Al Agent? Balaraia. T.te® H®Tt t bl® the Pslitisal Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire , Sir, I forward herewith copy of a letter received from Mr.DeGrenier with reference to his Arabic Examination. Perhaps you will determine the standard of the examination he is to prepare for. I might add that the standard of the first exam, passed by him does not appear to have,been that which he was informed by Mr.Bower and myself he would have to pass, which /\ was similar to the lower standard Hindustani and to include;- , i (1) Simple written translation, Arabic into English. (2) English into Arabic, (3) Reading and translating viva-voce of a simple manuscript letter. (4) ^ Conversation. The period allowed for preparation was one year. Apparantly he was examined in, (4) only. The period requisite for preparation for the latter need not, I think, exceed six months „ T^f (/*#£ C y ■}yu^ dc fr^ cY r Mr.DeGrenier had 'been in Bahrain preparing for this examination since January 192^, I have the honour to be , Sir, Zour most obedient servant, \ Major,I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. H. \ &gt;s •■IVCopy of a D/O letter No.l27-P dated lat December 1925 from Mr.DeGrenler, Director of Customs, Bahrain to the Political A gent, Bahra in• standardArabic I should like to commence study for ny higgler/examination without delay; and for that purpose, could you very kindly inform me the character of the examination, and which text books I ought to study for that purpose. My last examination was entirely oral, but I assume that this next one will require translations etc., from Arabic script and printing.V COMFIDENTIAL Ho. 472-S of 1925. British Kesideney and Consulate^General, Bushire, 14th December 1925. i i ■ From ^ ■ Captain B. Stuart Horner, I.A. # Secretaxy to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf» To The Political A^ent, Bahrain. 9 Sir, With reference to your letter Ko. 100/5/19, dated the 2nd December 1925, I am directed to state that the Hon'ble the Political Resident considers that the examination in Arabic recently passed by Mr. de Grenier should qualify him to draw his increment. This examination was based as far as possible on the Lower Standard Persian. 2. The component parts of the examination which Mr. de Grenier should prepare to pass after three years service are those of the Higher Standard in Arabic published in Notification Ko. 80, dated the 16th June 1914, by the Government of India in the Department of Ii»ducation, forwarded to you under this office endorsement Ko. 2403, dated the 16th August 1914. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Capt., Secretary to the Political Resident } C in the Persian Gulf. ■* I COilF IDKNTI AIL • y — D.0 ,NO TO lo / 6~ /1 A ^ The Pelitical Agtncy jBwoir&amp;xri.. 12/2/26. BUSHIti^ RESlOENCV NO fis « No h Oafe COKFIOBiTlW- BECOfiO^ ckjC^^j Dir«ct©r ©f Cu31oi«^-B ^Iirkin . ; HI I kavc rectntly received tk« enclosed Istttr, ti ^ , . i marked 9 * (Kliasusi) fr©m Skailc Hamad. I think t*ax tkc immediate cause f»r ifrkis letter 'bein^ v/ritten is as f©ll©v/s~ A sh.©rt time a^© I learnt that is®me merchants were preparing a petiti@n ©f c©mplaint against Mr De Grenier. As it was ©tviimsly undesiralsle tkat such a petition should materialise I asked Shaik Hamad t® use his' influence t@ put ast®p t© it.It seemed t© me that it weuld produce an unpleasant siiituatien which could n®t fail t© 'be damaging t@ European prestige h particularly t© the Agency,as Mr Be grenier^agxa^mrw-tamyt is commJsn^y regarded as ©ur selection. I heard n® mere «uf the matter until the arrival of the attached letter* I imagine that in order t® stop the petition Shaik Hamad must have premised t® take up the matter with me.He preba'tely left it pending &amp; shirked the semewnat unpleasant■task until he must have '^ctn further reminded* Y@u will recollect that in the ceurse of private cerrespendance with y©u,while we were ketk on leave,I .entioned that in my ©pinion Mr De Grenier was most unsuited fer the post he helds &amp; that the Shaik was justifiably dissatisfied with him. At that time ^®u were desireus ©f hearing from Captain Mallam whether ©r not .Mr Dt Grenier had improved. Probably you will have f ' heard Capt .Mallam's ©pinion; t© me he said he regardedk him as 'quite hopeless'. The Shaik's reference to Mr De grenier 1 s 'character 'being disagreeable t© subjects' refers I think to the fact that he has an unfortunately disagreeable,tactless &amp; overbearing manner in all his dealings^.Such complaints migkt well arise were Mr De Grenier ever zealous in the performance of his duties of i! •enforcing custems regulations. Tkis however is n«t the ca^s^it is connntn kn@wltdge that tke Customs is run 'by tk« Hindm staff &amp; n©t l»y llv De Grenier. I tkink an additional cause sf grievance is tkat tkrougii kis inability to castry on any kusinsss wkatevsr in araMc ,merchants have to deal witk junior officials v. kick some of them regard as derogatory. I am not certain as to what the Skaik moans ky -^tker matters which are n©t concealed from ^/ou 1 ' kut as examples of a numkor of prokakle petty causes ®f discontent I mention tko two following- (1) A short time after I resumed cathargo ,Mr De Grtnier kftpt akout his premises a young negro woman. I have keen told that ke ^©t rid of her owing t» a threat from the other young Europeans to report the mattir officially to me^ as they knew tkat it was causing muck critisism &amp; regarded it as 'bad for themselves. I first heard ©f it myself th»©ugh a remark made to my wifo ky one of the ladies of the Shaik's Harem. Although the moral aspect does not affect Mr De Grenier's duties,as a servant of a Muhammedan State ,such behaviour seems tactless in the extremo ^ might k*44 resulted in a murder,had ^kt the negress iseen a feekls minded destitute,who had no male relations in Bahrain. (2) I have hciard complaints that merchants importing goods, in res^pect of which,for customs purposes,t-ey have^produce invoices shtwing the a •' cost price,hav@ keen asked ky Mr De Grenier to sell him articles for his personal use.As he has the invoice of cost xxrices 'before him,&amp; in view ©f his official position,they have felt it impolitic not to okligo him^ have parted with their goods at lest than the market rate (prokakly the inveice rate) which ,of course, does not include Customs,landing charges &amp; trade profits. Although I do not suppose that such personal requiroments can have amounted to much,tkis tact- loss petty akuse of his position is kound t© cause resentment. I think that Mr De Grenier realises that his next Arakic examination,which according to his agreement he must pass 'be fore January next,is beyond his capacity. It may ke that were he given the choice ketween k termination of kis services in the terms of his agreemsnt(three months notice in writing) ©r of resigning ?/i his own accord witk more generous financial conditions,he would7*^ Tran8lati#n «f a letter fr»m Skaik Hamsid Bin 1 Isa t© Maj •r Daly Political Ag«nt Bahrain, dated 20th Ratals 1344. marked (Khasusi) Confidential. A. G. Ytur friend reminds Your excollency regarding y®ur promise 'feefere my departure on my hawking trip,that you would refer to His Excellency the Political Resident regarding the Director of Customs. It is not conceal^# from Y.E. that tht character ©f the Director now present hero is not agrooa'ble to my subjects, who discuss him very much with your friond. Y.E» will rememoer that whon v/e talked al®out tko appointDiont of an Adviser when we were in London, I requested you to replace the Director til £* xk -&gt;- Customs 'tey someone else and Y.E. informed mo that you v/ou'ld havt te consult the Hon^lo the Resident in this matter. It is not concealed frem Y.E. that the present Director is not at#le to talk aralsic and His Excellency Colonel Knox and yourself promised me,when he was appointed that the Director should either 'tee a'ble t® speak araiiic or that it would fee a condition that hi would learn quickly. Besides this there are matters which are not concealed from you. How therefore I ask your assistance in this matter and oe it understood to you that this is what was neccessary t® be submitted and may God preserve you.CONFIDENT lAL. The Residency, Bushire, 5th April 1926. B.O. No. 130-S. / / Please refer to your D.O. letter Ho. 80/5/19. t dated the ISth February 1926, about de Grenier. I have been considering the points you raise, and in view of the fact that there is no culpability proved against de Grenier, 1 think that the best method of getting rid of him, which seems inevitable after Shaikh Hamad*8 letter to you, is to offer him such terms as will induce him to tender his resignation. »ing lines s*» (1) leave to the full extent of the privilege leave and furlough earned under clauses 8 and 9 of his agree- -ment, the leave on half pay being preferably commut- «ed to half the amount on full pay, if he agrees. (2) Three months notice — under clause 14(1). (3) Permission to withdraw the amount at the credit of his Provident Fund. (4) A free passage to England. Please, now, approach de Grenier, assuming that Shaikh Hamad agrees to these terms and, if he consents to go without giving us further trouble, address me officially in the matter. I consider that these terms should be on the follow- C. K. Daly, Political Agent, Bahrain.^ iijl-yh 13,0 • Ho. i4B-S, ^ The Hesidency # Buehlre# 17th April 1926 Colonel Prideau# hae asked Bie to write to you i with reference to the post of IHrector of Customs, Bahrain, which de Grenier is probably vacating in a few months* time, to enquire whether you know of anyone in your Service, whom you can recoTitnend for this post, and who would be willing to go to Bahrain on deputation, if Government agreed, for a period of at least* four or five years. You know the local conditions, of course, and 1 need not into detail about them; the proposed pay would be Es, 300 ~ 50 ~ 2,000 plus the usual leave and pension contribution from the State# de Grenier has not been altogether a success as the Shaikh and the Arab merchants do not approve of him. So he has been advised to resign. Colonel Prideaux will be very grateful for any recommendations that you can make. 1 G. H. Bower, Fsq. # Assistant Collector of Customs, Bombay. atThe Political Agency Bahrain* 10/3/26 0 - RESIDENCY. ) Rel 3J9. | Date (H.'k-M . CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS. Fron Major O.K.Daly Political Agent,Bahraino To The Hon'ble Lieut» Colonel PoB. Prideaux CoSolo O.I.E. Hesident in the Persian Gulf # Bushire Sir I have the honour to report that Mr C* de ^renier ,Director of Bahrain Customs,has written to Shaik Hamad resigning his appointment k asking that he may he relieved as soon an i^ay he con venient o The Shaik has agreed to accept Mr de Grenier's resignation on the terms outlined in your D.Oo Ko I30-S of April 5th k in addition to the concession© aade he will pay Mr de t*renier for the 'balance of three months should ^arrange ments for his relief he completed before three months from to-day,the date of his resignation* I have the honour to 'be Sir, Your obedient servantCON FIDFJITIAL . D.O. No. 156-S, hi T/C ^l&gt; The Residency, Bushire, 20th April 1926. i) ■ / Please refer to your letter Ho. 49/5/19, dated the t 10th March 1926, concerning de Grenier's resignation. Under the Resident's direction, 1 have written to Bo^er asking him if he can recoromend anyone from the Indian Customs Service who would be willing to serve on deputation in ' ,\ . Bahrain as director of Customs for a period of at least four years. I will let you know in due course what the reply is. You will see from the Government of India's pro as -posals about the Levy Corps Commandant that/an officer of the I.A.H.O. he will be to some extent under Government's central. You doubtless also know that the Government of India will not allow Europeans to take service in Native States under their control without special permission and that they are generally very chary in giving their consent. Colonel Prideauy thinks that your lad from Garsden is much too young and inerperienced for the Customs appointment In the meanwhile,will ycu please send me another letter in substitution of ycur Ho. 49, a£ it has to go up to Government. It should not refer to D .O. correspondence, but should contain all the terms which are being jgiven to de Grenier and which he accepts. This is obviously more convenient thaifc ottA-adding the T).0. correspondence or to going into long details in the covering letter to Government. tfajor C.K.Daly, C.I.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. ^soay long enough to oe 01 assistance to tne Adviser, wie ainicuit^/ re-ardinj tne Customs director is removed, and • unttou ' :;teai y a irained ol'iicial would be preferable. As regards the yelectlon of au ex -officer, my *' su -- eat any ox-officers now in India, wfco are not proTided with employment, are hardly likely to be^tte oeai, ii. w. v-,. j-iiaxan Alto- Cliicer, iaobt of whom found more or leas uuitaole employment elsewhere. ./nile interviewing officers with a view to selecting tne Adviser for the ^ahrain titate, I met a ome dozen# 01 ex-ofxicer#, ver^ few or whom, would have been suitaole for tne post to oe filled. j.ou are aoubtiess aware wiiat as ■- - . 0 ^.. * &gt;- o c*»» oc uionar^y measure, in case it should oe or assistance, 1 aaiced mr. -^It.iave oo meat, ana taice particulars oi*, ex -Indian Ariay Officers who might be suitable. . ie saw a great number and was of opinion that most were, quite unsmitable. .here was however one who was a-pijarentlv m' •• « r-- a^drentj.^ 01 tne usmal type of permanent military officer, who was anxious for employment, and if you thinx it advisable I would suggest that we might communicate with him and that it would oe safer to take'an ex-officer who nas beexi actually interviewed (axxa it is very much in . ~r. -grave's ^tere.ts to seicot^o.^e.aa. and Suitable ^c*n mta miom he will have to work) rather'than run tne'risk oi obtaining an unsuitable person. 3i)/ C» K, jJiiLY, Liajor, loli ciccol A^ent •M COKEIDKSTIAL. The Political Agency 2^0 49/5/19 Bahrain. 2C/if^6 •- SP A -- : v 1 : v ^ Major C.K.Daly C.IJJ, Political Agent, Reg. ^ I CONFlOl:; TiAL RECOHDS. j Ba rain. To Tlie Hon'ble the Political Koadlent in the Persian Gulf. Buohire. 81r # I htwo the honour to roport tixat Mr C. de Grenlor / ' 1 • . ■ ■ Director of Customs under tho Bahrain State.hac written to His ijoccellenoy the Shailc resigning his appcintsient and asking that he may be relieved as soon at convenient. The terms on which Mr de Grenier has resigned ^ which have been accepted in writing by both parties to^ the original contract,are as follows• {I;The Director to be given all leave earned under the contract up to the date of leaving Bahrain. (E)The Director iaaub^ to be given the ben£fit of any money accumulated in his Provident }?und. (3) The Director to be given a firtt class passage to England„ ^ above ax)pear to be generous conoaaoionc? inasmuch a^^under the strict terms of the contract, these ben^its ^are not to accrue until tii.e completion of 5 years service in the « .se of (•') 4 year's in the case of (if Jk 5 years in the case of (3). ; ■tv;/. ■ 7 I have the honour to be Sir, '\ Your obedient sex^vpant x y* f* Political J^ent \y 1EOMFIDEHTIAL The British Reoldenoy B ub hire, 15th Hay 1926. W D.O. So. 191-S # Colonel Prldeaux has asked me to thani you for your deml official letter of the 29th April about a Director of Customs for Bahrain, and for recommend- ing Richardson. He has addressed the Government of India on the subject, and has aksed if Richardson's servicee can be spared on the terms, which you indicated. I will write to you again as soon as a reply is received from Goyernaente G. H. Bower^ Esq,, Customs House. 01' kjlrvi CON g IDE1I ? IAL . B.O. Ko. 195~S The British Residency, Bushlre, mh May 1926. In forwarding the enclosed copy of Tehran — despatch No. 689 to the Foreign Office (Blue Print) I am desired by CoXoneX Pridekux to enquire whether the Director of Customs, Bahrain, showed to you the communication he made to the Director of Persian Customs, Buehire, or informed you, as he should have done,, that he was corresponding with this Persian official. Major C« K. Daly, C.I.E Political Agent, Bahrain . &gt;1 /&lt;?// isi. Confidential. ^ BUSHIRE REetCTENCY. Res., No * n ^s' / ' L ' , &gt;/ ^ Date XU-Jb fl D. O.lTo .374-$ . C0NF1DEMTIAL RECORDS. /O? June 26 DIRECTOR OS 1 CUSTOMS FOR BAHRAIIT. Please refer to your letter Ho.182-S, dated the 8th May 7 ^ i a &gt; # v 1926. It is regretted, it is not possible to spare Richardson or any other British Officer of the Imperial Customs Service for service in Bahrain, If you wish it, however, enquiries will be made whether a suitable officer from the Bombay Salt Department (from which Mr.Sievwright now at Baghdad was deputed) could be made available. To The Hon^ble Lieutenant-Colonel P.B.Prideaux, C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. (Y/ith 1 spare copy).19/126 Telegram C. Prom H.M ! s. .Political Kesident, JBushire. To Tiie Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. Isfo. 407. Dated 2otii June 1926. Your demi-official letter of June 10th, Mo. 374-U. Please enquire from Salt Department as proposed. - RESIDENT.COFFIDEHTIAL. Ho. 259-S of 1926. The British Residency and Consulate -General, Bushire, 26th June 1926. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information. the Foreign Secretary to 1. D.O.letter No.374-H, from/the Government of India, dated the 10 th June i.926. 2. Telegram from the Political Resident, Bushire, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Ho.407, dated the 25th June 1926. By order ^7 Resident in the Persian Gulf.Irom - The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To - The Handle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Memorandum K'o»374-K'» Dated Simla, the ^^-September 1926. [ CQhHDEWTIAL RECORDS- | Director of Customs for Bahrain* (? 4 &gt;\&gt; Please refer to your letter Eo•18E-S, dated 8th May 1926* ^ It is regretted that the services of Mr•Richardson are not available, 'but Mr*G♦Barron of the Bombay Salt Department who is strongly recommended is available for service in Bahrain on the following terms:- (a) Pay Rs*750-100-1,150/- (b) first class passage between Bombay and Bahrain both at the time of beginning and at the end of his tour of duty; (c) one return first class passage between Bombay and Bahrain for his wife (if and when she joins him); Cd) one return passage to England - first class bet?/een Bahrain and Bombay and 2nd class between Bombay and Ingland - domig the five years of employment for himself and his wife; fe) free house or allowance in lieu; (f) free medical attendance; (g) the Bahrain Government to pay contribution to the Govern ment of India both for pension and leave salary* 3* After ascertaining whether these terms are acceptable to the Bahrain State please report your views* Atteste Sd/~ A*E*B*Parsons, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India* Superintenden; Foreign and Politicaldepartment* Copy forwarded to the Central Board of Revenue for information* With 1 spare copy* t# T /■■'I &amp; ■■ j^Ko,426-S of 1926. British Resideruay and Consulate-General, Bushire, 8th October 1926» A copy of the under mentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with a request that he will kindly ascertain and report to this office whether the terms on which Mr •W.G.Barron is available for service, ^acceptable to the Bahrain State» By order, ^ k p /y Captain, for Becaeetary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, lfo.374-K, dated the 25th Septem ber 1926* (With 1 spare copy). u s-confidential• HO. /Of/1925. Political Agency, Babrein. Dated tlae 9th October 1926# /&lt;C RECEIVED - 3(^3 |02G' - To \ V .x^r;. ' RsiA hi O 4 '' 1 -v-' The Secretary to the Hon f 'ble The Political R^Blii'ant, Persian Gulf, Sushire* Sir. , r X ^ I have the honour to invite a reference to your telegram Ho.407 dated the 25th June 1926 to the Foreign Secretary to t&amp;h Government of India and to request that I may 'be informed how the matter now stands. I have the honour to 'be Sir, Your most obedient servant, I \ --'1% 1 f \s OS T VWNT political Agent, BaJbcrein ''•A- ^ ^ ^ (1/ *7*19/176. 1/vV Telegram P. From To No. 759. Dated 19th November 1926 Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain de Grenier. I have mislaid yuur demi-official letter about Please post me three copies on foolscap. RESIDENT.Confidential. D.O. Ho.126/5/19 y\\ Political Agency, Balirein. Dated the 20th Hovember 1926 With reference to Colonel Prideaux telegram So. 759 dated the 19th instant, I forward herewith copy of my demi-official letterUn triplicate) Ho. 121/5/19 dated the 7th lovember regarding Mr .BeGrenier. I am also sending Horner an official letter on this subject by this inail. RSSlCfENC^ l U^yLy I c ' ' 4 CONFIDENTIAL REGORO^J BUSH1RE Reg. No. 11f Captain C.G.Prior, Under Secretary to The Hon'ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BUSHIRK.NTIAL. Jo.C.127/5/19 of 1926. Political Agency, Baiirein. jjated the 20tli November 1926. iiibi ii ifnrrii i ' p! • qtt P50!n'ENCY- ' To | 2&gt; ■ The Secretary to f COhRDE MTIAl. Re £ The Hon'hie the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BUSHIKB. Memo r and urn. Please refer to your lTo«426-S # dated the 8tii OctolDer 1926 forwarding me a copy of Government of India Memorandum lo.374-l. dated the 25th September^and asking me to ascertain and report whether the terms on which Mr.Barron is available for service are acceptable to the Bahrein State. Shaikh Hamad has now informed me that although there were objections formerly to the continuance of the present Director Mr.DeGrenier in the service of the State, those objections have now been withdrawn. He finds that Mr.DeSrenier is working very well and is giving satisfaction. He desires, therefore, to retain the services of an official who has learnt his work and knows the local merchants rather than to engage the services of an officer who must come as a stranger to the island. He thanks the Government of India and the Hobble the Political Resident for the trouble they have taken in this matter and for their kindness in offering him the services of Mr.Sarron, but hopes they will agree with him in considering that in the present circumstances the retention of the services of Mr.DeGrenier are in the best interests of his State. Political Agent, Bahrein.COKFIDEKTIAL. lo.C. 128/5/19 of 1926. n/i Political Bahrein. Dated the 20th KovenToer 1926 . ■ -CRESIOENCY^ y /\\ To R 143. ..M2- Dalo .. COhfiBEtsTiAL BEBOROG. The Secretary to The Hon'ble the Political Resident, Bersian Gull, S u s h i r e, Memorandum. In continuation of my memorandum Mo.G.127/5/19 dated the 20th lovember 1926, I have ascertained that Mr. DeGrenier wishes to retain his present appointment as Director of Customs, Bahrein. He is studying Arabic of which language he has a workingknowledge and he has informed me that he hopes shortly to appear for examination 'by the Higher Standard, Political Agent, Bahrein. ^D.O. Ko.121/5/19. Political .igency, BaJarexii.'^ Dated the 7th lovember 1926. Dear Colonel Prideaux, Shaikh Hamad has not given me an official reply to my enquiry whether he would accept Mr. Earron as Customs Director* I spoke to him on the subject and he replied that he personally never disliked Mr.deGrenier, but that some of the merchants used to object to him, but that he believed this was no longer the case 0 He said he would sound the merchants and let me know,, Just before leaving Belgrave told me that Shaikh Hamad was in favour of keeping DeGrenier for a bit longer. In ny opinion so far a-s Shaikh Kamad is concerned DeGrenier can stay here as long as he likes. I personally do not dislike the man, we might easily do worse and Belgrave who comes into closest touch with him reports that his Customs work is excellent, DeGrenier is cursed with an unfortunate manner especially when talking to ladies and, I think, this has a good deal to do with previous bad reports against him. Yours sincerely, Sd/- C.C.J.Barrett, The Hon'ble Lt.Col.l.l.Prideaux,C.S.I.,C.I.1., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, 1 u s h i r e.'i -vb *1 cchfip].:h?ial &gt; Ho. 50i~S. of X92(&gt; $ Britieh Heeldency and Gonsulate-GtincraX, i Buehire, 27th Koveisaber 1926. ^om The Hon'ble Ueut-Gol. F.B.Brideaiuc. Q.S.I.. C.I.E.. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the l?oreign and Political Department, Delhi. Director of CustomB for Bahrain. .it 4. .ft •• IMNI* W «•**** ** Sir, I have the honour to refer to foreign and Political Pepartment Memorandum Ho. 374~K., dated the 25th ; eptember 1926, recommending Mr. W.C.Barron of the Bombay Bait Depart* •ment for service in Bahrain as Director of Customs. 2. I now forward for the information of the Government of India a copy of Major Barretts memorandum ho . 0.127/5/19, dated the 20th November 1926. I am informed that though some of the merchants in Bahrain used to object to Mr. de Grenier this is now no longer the ca^e, and Major Barrett adds that the previous bad reports against this officer were prehapn based on the fact that he has an unfortunate manner. 3. As Hr. de Grenier's customs work is now reported to be very good, I concur with Major Barrett in considering that Mr. de Grenier's services should be retained at Bahrain. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. .ieut-Gol., Political Besident in the Persian Gulf a ' Copy to the Political Agent, BahrainI I *y 19/126, 19/172, h 19/176. / y 3 Telegrairi Code From Prior, Busliire To Political, Baiirairu Mo. 357 Bated the 20th April 1927• In anticipation of approval of Government Political Resident sanctions de Grenier proceeding on leave this summer# Separate arders follow by post regarding contracts of Par Ice and Belgrave. prior.i .-n- i 'tssfi' i t ^ j l 1 -I-- ■ COKFID'RHTIAL . Ho. 170-S. of 1927. British Residency and Coneulate-General, Bushire, 26th May 1927. i C From ^ The Hon»ble Lieut-Col. L.B.H.HawSorth, To Political ReBicient in the Persian Gulf. The foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla Modification of terms of service of the ) Director of Customs, Bahrain. Sir, With reference to correspondence ending with Foreign and olitical Department memorandum Mo. 480-X., dated the 10th April 1924, I have the honour to submit for the approval of the Government of India a copy of a ^ subsidiary agreement made between the Deputy Ruler of Bahrain and Mr. C. de Grenier, Director of Customs, Bahrain, enabling the latter to take furlough after the completion of three years' active service in the first instance and sub- -sequently after every two years of active service in place of the terms of the original agreement of 1924, under which Mr. de Grenier was permitted to take furlough only after the completion of four years 1 active service. The extent of furlough admissible remains un- -altered. As the original agreement was made with the approv- -al of the Government of India I am sending this amendment for approval before sanctioning it. I consider that four years is too long a period forConfidential♦ Mo. 142-K. From The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department, To The Hon t ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf*. Bushire• OOKfiOuTI. Da.ted Simla, the 4)' July 1927. Subsidiary agreement between the Deputy Ruler of Bahrain and Director of Customs, Bahrain* In reply to your letter Ha*. 170-S., dated the E6th May 19E7, I am directed to say that the Government of India approve of the subsidiary agreement between the Deputy Ruler of Bahrain and Mr* C» de Grenier, Director of Customs, Bahrain* Sir, I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India (With 1 spare copy)To. 237-S. of 1927. British Residency and Consultite-'GeneraXi Bushire, 20th July 1927. A copy of the foregoing is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, in continuation of this office telegrasi Ho. 679, dated the 17th July 1927. 2. Orders conveying the formal approval of the Hon'hie the Political Resident will follon in due course. By order. Capt., Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.3.vf \y 19/126, 19/172, 19/176. 'i. Telegram Code. Prom Secretary to Resident, Busiiire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 679• Dated 17th July 1927. Government has sanctioned proposals regarding agreements of BBLGRAVE, PARKS and DE GRE1TIER*Hu. 275 ~S, of 1927. British Hesiaency and Coneulate-CreneraX t Bushire § Xbth August 1927. Sir, In continuation of this office endorsement Ko. 257 -a. t dated the 20th Jul^ 1927, I ara directed to convey the approval of the Hon'ble the Political Resident 0/x the subsidiary agreement between the Deputy Kuler of Bahrain and Mr. G. de Grenier, Director of Customs, Bahrain. 2. I am also to request that you will arrange with the Bahrain 3.ate to afford Ar. de Grenier the same ooncess -ion in resj^ect of medical attendance on himself and his family as is granted to Mr. BeXgrave and Captain Parlie. X have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, - p V' Capt., Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. The Political Agent, Bahrain.Ill 17-1, From *■ The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department&gt; To The tton t ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf^ Bu shire. » AV- i —-j Dated Simla, the Sij/fc'July 1927. Memorandum Fo# D»1876-A# 4^ ^ ^ 7 • Date ■ 1 V w A ■ Deputation of Mr. G»H* Bower, Imperial Customs ServiceL | on foreign service in the Persian Gulf# ■ r ^ . Reference.- Correspondence ending with the telegram from the foreign and Political Department Ko.7(84)-A, dated the 25th February 1924# 2# lender rule 123 of the ifundarnental Rules a Government servant on foreign service may, unless special arrangements have 'been made on his transfer by the authority sanctioning his transfer, be granted leave by his employer on such conditions as the employer may determine; leave salary being paid by the employer. 3. The terms of deputation of Mr. Bower sanctioned in the Memorandum Ko.7(84)-A, dated the 27th ' J marginally noted communica- September 1923. X-M, Kf/jv^ A''So I Memorandum Ho. 749-X, dated the 4th October | tions from the foreign and 1924. ^ zs'hy-iTi L./4* » ^ Political Department did not specify any conditions for the grant of leave to him while on foreign service nor was any such leave claimed by him on the termination of his foreign service in the Persian Gulf under the Bahrein, Kuwait and Muscat States. The right course for him would have been to arrange for his leave with the States concerned, the leave salary being paid by them proportionately. 4. Mr. Bower has since asked to be allowed to count the period of his service in the Persian Gulf in calculating the amount of leave earned in the same way as if this period had been spent on duty in India.In view of the fact that Bower did not proceed on leave immediately on the termination of his deputation to Muscat&gt; the Government of India do not propose to admit his claim for leave in respect of this period. In the case of Bahrein and Kuwait&gt; however, since he proceeded on leave immediately on the expiration of his deputation, it seems reasonable, that he should he treated as being on foreign service under those States during a part of the leave taken by him# 6» In consideration of the good work done by Mr# Bower while on foreign service, the Government of India trust that the Bahrein and Kuwait States will have no objection to pay their proportionate shares towards his leave contribution. The total contribution thus recoverable calculated at the rate of 5/22nds of the period of his foreign service (from 29th August 1923 - 31st March 1924) amounts to Rs*3060/-. i 7. The exact periods of his deputation to Bahrein and Kuwait are not known to the Government of India, but it would appear from your telegram lfo.904, dated the 16th October 1923, that Mr. Bower was to reach Kuwait about 1st December 1923. If this is correct the contributions recoverable from the States would be as under Bahrein State Rs. 1320/~. Kuwait * * 1740/~. E. It is requested that the Bahrein and Kuwait States may be addressed in the matter and the Government of India informed of the result. Sd/~ A. C. Lothian, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Attested. i. Superintendent» Foreign and Political Department. Copy forwarded for information to the Central Board of Revenue / with reference to their u#o. Ho.194-C •11 .26, dated the 11th July 1927. h. ,A o ^■i P.R- - — - ■ in OFFICE NOTE. F. &amp; P. D. aemo. No. D.1876-A., dated S 29— 3,0005-12 It was originally intended that Mr. Bower should proceed to Kuwait after finishing with Bahrain Eventually, as the Shaikh of Kuwait did not desire his deputation to Kuwait,vide Col. Trevor's desp. noi 9/52-S., dated 3/2/24, to S. of S. for Colonies,the whole of his first period of deputation was spent at Bahrain, whence he^ proceeded direct on leave. (Hisydeputation^to Muscat, in regard to which the G. of I. do not propose to admit his claim,'/was after his return from leave). F. &amp; P.B. memo. 7(84)-A., dated 27/9/23, sanctioning his deputation for three months from 29/8/2J, is silent on the subject of leave or leave salary. An extension of 3 months was sanctioned in F. &amp; P.D. tel. Ho. 7-84-A., dated 8/12/23. A further extension to 31/3/24 was sanctioned in F. &amp; P.D. tel. No. 7-84-A., dated 25/2/24. Immediately after this Mr. Bower proceeded on leave. So the Bahrain State should 'be asked to con- -tribute the whole amount of Es. 3060/- Braft endorsement submitted. yi\ j y c^/ * ^ {^OJLAjxZ^ * /^/v ■ corr. in filft 19/ /165-I, in Shiraz. file 61/7 p. 101 File 19/126, p. 138. Do. p. 151. Do . p. 180.'om To Sir, R. Dis. Ho.l94-G.E«/26, GOVEHIIMSilT OF IITDIA. PIUA^iCE DEPiUiTIIEIIT (GEITTR^L KBVSilHES } Simla ? the 17tli October 1927. Y. S. Sundaram, Es'qr. , Deputy Secretary to the GoYernment of India, The Collector of Gustoms, Bombay. Foreign service - counting of, for leave and leave salary - Bower (Mr.G.T. ;, Assi ^ ta ? lt J ,9 0 :: :L ® G ^ or of Gusto .s, Central Board of .Revenue n leuoer □• bo # 194-C.E»/26, dated the 11th July 1927. With reference to the correspondence ending with the letter quoted above, I am directed to say that the Government of India'regret that, under the Fundamental rules as they stand at present, neither of the requests made by Mr. Bower in his letter R.S .R. Ho.1762/26, dated the 29th March 1926 (forwarded under, your endorsement of the same number and date) is admissible• 2. In view of the period of time that has elapsed since Mr. Bower's deputation to the Persian fiulf, the Government of India have decided that it is impossible for them now to make retrospective special arrangements under Pundamental Rule 123. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. V.S.Sundaram, 19.10.27. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India./ ji id 1^1 Telegram From To Code. Political Agent, Bahrain 'Resident, 'Ohakdara.'. Date^ 5th BecemlDer 1928. Is it definite that provided Shaikh agree De G-renier should he given notice of termination of con- -tract in January 19E9 ? If so I propose to ask Belgrave to wire him as he was contemplating matrimony. Telegram Code. From Resident, Muscat. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. T-80. Dated 7th December 1928. Please decide which is most necessary to State, Customs Officer of Officer Commanding Police. If latter, give de Grenief notice as stated in. your telegram, under reply. Resident.I i ——- ■■ tui-j n ■ Ml III -—11 Tirtir •* hm'ilii1iiii^itWt*itriiit»_U.jiiijii'_i'j].iij|jii..uui_i Jllii fc - Confidential. O $ No.C/65 of 1928. The Political Agency Baiorein, lltii February 1928 To |E5USH : ^ rssilDyNCV 1 Reg. Tlie Secretary ; ^ ste to the Political Resident COMEtiTi/iL BEG# in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E. . v ) a &gt; q . w.v^' Sir, ^ I have the honour to refer you to my telegram dated the 5th December 1927 to the address of the Political Resident and his reply ITo.TSO dated the 7th December 1927, I asked H.E•Sheikh Hamad as to which of the two officers concerned was to he given notice of termina tion of contract f J*!* decided that he would rather dispense with the services of i^r^de Grenier than those of Captain Parke. The reasons given which are typical of the Sheikh are;- (a) That Captain Parke is married whereas Mr. de Grenier is not. (b) Captain Parke was present in Bahrein where as Mr,de Grenier was on leave. On his return to Bahrein kr•de Grenier was given one year's notice of the termination of his contract• 2 It appears that according to the terms of his con tract Mr.de Grenier is entitled to draw the Provident Pund which is accumulating for him at the Eastern Bank,Bombay, only after he has completed 5 years ac tual service exclusive of leave. This period will ex pire on 1st June 1929, Mr.Belgrave informed Sheikh Hamad of this fact where upon he stated that he had no desire to lose Mr.de Grenie^s services and would greatly regret his de parture but the la;tter had to leave in accordance with the v/ishes of the Government of India. He would likelike Mr.de Grenier to complete the five years necessa ry to entitle him to draw the Provident Allowance, In the circumstances I recommend that the ser vices of Mr.C.C.Lewis de Grenier with the Bahrein State 'be continued until 1st June 1929. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, c^A AS Political Agent Bahrein. ^ &gt; - / &gt;» i i ~^ r ' 2^.3-^QQ-IFID ''INTI AT, . No. 141-a. of 1928. British Basidenoy and Gonsulate-Genoral, Bushlre, 5th April 1928. Sir, 171th refarence to your letter No. c/65, dated 11th February 1928, 1 am directed to convey to you the approval of the Hon'ble the Political Hosident to the continuance of the services of Kr. C.O.do Grenier until 1st June 1929. 1 have the honour to 'be, Sir, your most obedient servant, Oapt., for Secretary to the Political Resident i y in the Persian Gulf. The Political Agent, Bahrain19 \}y*&gt; 51 0.3-1489-A/28 A copy of the underment toned paper?, is forwarded to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for information, in continuation of Foreign and Political Department 1.o .D, 2695/ a , dated the 7th Kovemher 1927. cA' By order, etc., Under Secretary to the Government of India. oreign and Political Department Simla. The June 1928. ■ '.SH REs'- ' ^ecsveb ^ f 7?(5 'tfe /n GoTernment of India, Finance Department (Central Revenues) letter R.Dis.Bo.27-C.S./28, dated the 17th May 1^28, to the Collector of Customs, Calcutta, with enclosures. (With 1 spare copy)V 5V Copy of a letter Ho. R.Dis .27-C.B./28, dated Simla, the 17th May 1928, from the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, Finance Department (Central Revenues) to the Collector of Customs, Calcutta. Foreign Service - Counting of, for leave and leave pay - Bower (Mr.G.H.), Assistant Collector, Imperial Customs Service - Bahrein and - uscat Governments - Foreign service under - Memorial to the Secretary of State-. Your letter lio.541y dated 12th January 1928. With reference to your letter quoted above, I am directed to forward a copy of the correspondence with the 1. Letter to the Under Secretary of State for Indiaj India Office G.Ho . 27-C.S./28, dated the 15th llarch 1928. | 2. Letter from the Secretary, Services and General | noted m the Department, India Office, lo.S. 8c G. 1982/28, | . dated the 25th April 1928. _i margin. You will observe that the Secretary of State in Council has sanctioned both the requests made by Mr. Bower in his memorial I am to request that Mr. Bower may be informed accordingly.Copy of a letter C.ITo. 27-C.S./28, dated Hew Delhi the 15th March 1928, from the Deputy Secretary to the GoTernment of India, Finance Department (Central Revenues), to His Majesty*3 Under Secretary of State for India, Economic and Overseas Department, India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.I. Imperial Customs Service -Bower (G«I».) — Assistant Collector of Customs - Foreign service - Counting of for leave and leave pay - Memorial to the Secretary of State. I am directed to forward the memorial, referred %*&gt; above, in which Mr. Bower prays that (a) his foreign service of 11 months and 23 days under the Bahrein and Muscat Govern- mentiSmay count as duty for the purpose ot earning leave, and (h) the pay drawn by him during his service of 7 months and 3 days under the Government of Bahrein may he taken into account in calculating his leave salary whilst on leave m 1924, and the sum of Es.455/8/- representing the difference 'between the leave salary so calculated and the leave salary actually drawn 'by him should be paid to him. 2. The facts are as stated in the memerial, except tnat the reference of retrospective special arrangements in para graph 2 of Government of, India, Finance Department letter Ho. R.Dis.194-C.3./26, dated the 17th October 1927* is not to special arrangements for retrospective recovery of contri butions towards leave salary, as Mr. Bower assume^» out to ^ue attempt, referred to later in this letter, to recover ix possible, a part of the actual leave salary paid to Mr. Bower from the Bahrein Government. 3. When Mr. Bower represented his case in 1926, his case was examined with reference to the provisions of the Funda mental Rule?, and the Political Resident of tlie Persian Gulf was asked to recover, if possible, from the Bahrein Government their share of leave salary paid to Mr. Bower in 1924. But in view of the lapse of time, the Political Resident re commended .that it would not be advisable to attempt to recovei anything from the Bahrein Government. The Government of IndiIndia accepted the advice of the Political Resident and informed l£r. Bower through the Collector of Customs, Bombay, that his request could not be granted. 4. Owing to over-sight on the part of the Government of India no arrangements ?/ere made with the Bahrein and Muscat Government^ when Mr» Bower*s services were lent to them regarding the grant of leave of him by those Governments. On both the occasions Mr. Bower , s deputation was arranged by telegrams and, in vie?/ of the comparatively short period for which Mr. Bower*s services were lent, Mr. Bower was, in the opinion of the Government of India, Justified in expecting the Government to arrange with the foreign Governments regarding his leave, pension and other privileges. In the circumstances the Government of India are satisfied that Mr. Bower has a claim in equity to the compensation that he asks for, and recommend that his requests may be granted.I ■- SerTiCea * 25th April 1928. b General. S. &amp; G. 1962/28 foreign Service^ of Mr. G.K.Bower under the Bahrein and Muscat GoTernmenti» Sir, With reference to your letter C, Ho.27-G.S./28, dated the 15th March, I am directed to inform you that the Secretary of State in Council sanctions the proposals contained therein, namely :- (a) that Mr. Bower's foreign service under the Bahrein and Muscat Governments should count as duty for the purpose of earning leave. (b) that the pay drawn by him during his service under the Government of Bahrian should be taken into account in calculating Ms leave salary while on leave in 1924, and that the difference between the leave salary so calculated and that actually drawn should be paid to him. I am. Sir, Your obedient servant, . P.H.Dumbell, Secretary, Services and General Department. To The Secretary to the Government of India, finance Department (Central Revenues). ; / \tilt*' CQijglDKKT IAL » | ^ Ho* of X929. British Hesidenoy and ConeuXat«-ueneraJL^ Buss hire, the iOth Januaacy X929. From The Hon f ble Sir h\w. Johnston, K.C,! J ., C.ti.i.i X.C.IS., i^olitioaX HeeMcmt in Uie ferui&amp;n Gulf, TO The Foreigjfi l&gt;ecretaiy to the Government of inclia in t^ie jforeiipn and Political ^ejjartment, Hew Delhi* Sir, X iiave the honour to refer o Hi** Lionel Haworth's despatch Ito• S95-^., dated the let t e^tember 1927, on the subject of the atoini strati on of Bahrain. ho ordere appear to have been panaeA on that despatch, though it has been the ©ubjeot of certain unofficial correspondence in accordance with which tlie Blmiich has been advised that he should dispense with the services of Mr de Orenier, the OustoiaB Officer. 2. When X was at Bahrain last weefc the i haikh raised the question and stated that he specially desired to retain tlie services of Mr de orenier as he was convinced that under so&amp;e other form of administra tion the efficiency of tlie Custom would gravely deteriorate and tiie revenue exj^rience a substantial falling off. Enquiries raade frora the Financial Adviser aflnd the i^olitical Agent go to sii#w that the poet of Cue toias Officer is a viiole time job and that the financialvl WXnaxi oial Adviser ie quit© unable to give to it the ©u ienrision necessary. Aa a Qonoeuuenae the removal of Mr de Grenlcr nouM mem oithcr deterioration in the bande of Inadequately Bu^erviyed oubordinatee or the appointment of eoiae other foreigner to Bahrain, probably ieB8 efficient. As kr ae Grenier^ salary amounts approximately to one ^r cent, of the nett receipt© of the Ba^irain C ub tome, tiie question of cost does not seriously affect the issue. 5* I am in entire sympathy vtitki the policy of avoiding uadue esternisation, but i cannot see that this policy will be served by handing the Custom over to other administration, unless and until education in the State produces laen capable of carrying on the noric. Yhe work of Custom ataiinititration is a separate technical branch of the utate admin is traUon, but little connected with the general administration, and even in a country so nationalistic in its recent tendencies as Persia the benefit of the Belgian C ujb tons officers is admitted* 4. On my short acquaintance with iiahrain X shouid hesitate to express an opinion on the arrangements there - though I carmot help Uiinking that what is most open to objection is the for ce of Im ian armed police uncier British comxsand — but it is obvious from the character of the present ruler that any change must be very gradual and that a rapid reversal of policy wouJU. have the worst possible effect. Certainly the leaut o^n to objection seer^ to be tiie Customs v&amp;iioki i&amp; carried on in practically the same way as the Persian Customs with the working of which all the residents of Bahrain are familiar. In any case attempts at reform tsoula seem to be beginning at the wrong end in leaving the service and removing efficient supervision, before native supervision, possibly less efficient but at all events reasonably competent, is forthcomingforthcoming to tafcc Ite place- 5. in tlie of mkr*in oKvlomly the oaly alternative to the retention of Mr de arenier in the appolntrtieni of another foreigner to Bahrain or the farming out of the Customs with csonaequent aubetantlaX loaa of revenue arid probable internal &lt;lluputea# Inform the Hhaikh tiiat Hi® Migeoty^s aovermaent are not irepared to advlae hliQ against retaining for a further ye rlod the oervicee of Mr &lt;le urenler. 6, A copy of this letter ie being eent to Hie Ma^eaty's t;eoretary of estate for India. Copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information. In theee ciroumstariceo X would propose to kx Z have the honour to be, fcilr. Your moot obedient servant Political Kealdent In the elan oulfCQ^FIDEMTIAL, Ho. 6-S. of 1929. British Hesidency and Consulate-ueneral, Bushire, the 19th January 1929. Sir, I havethe honour to forv/ard fortiie informa tion of His Majesty's Govermnont a copy of ray despatch Ho. 5-S. of even date addressed to the Govermaent of India in the foreign and Political Department. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. ^ Political Resident in the Persian Gulf His Majesty^ Secretary of Btate for India, India Office, L 0 N D 0 M.f ' TV) The Political Agency, Bahrein. No.C/7^ the 22/5/1929. --1 J Prom U&lt;jo rj'f'H Captain C.G.Prior,I.A. Political Agent,Bahrein. The Secretary to the Political Resident, in the Perisna Gulf, Bushire. Sir, ^ I have the honour to refer to letter ITo/S, S dat ed the I9/I/29, from the Hon'hle the Political Resident to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India and to say that I have received a letter from H.E.Shaikh Hamad stating that he wishes to retain Mr G.G.L.de Grenier in his present appointment. 2. His Excellency says that When Sir Denys Bray was in Bahrein he did not mention the matter to him, and it was only after he had left that ks the order of Government to dispense ith the services of either Mr de Grenier or Capt. Parke was given him. He feels that the Govt, of India have not sanzsiEJis: considered the harm which will result from this order, and he says that the only reason that he gave Mr de Grenier notice was that he was unmarried and on leave in Eng land, while Capt. Parke was married and in Bahrein. 3. He further states that Mr de Grenier has been in his employ for five years, and during that time he has seen every year an increa.se of revenue, and a great increase from the days when it was farmed out to Hindus. If Mr de Grenier does not remain in his post he does not agree to hand over the work to anyone else as none of his own subjects are qua lified, and the appointment of another foreigner such as a Hindu will cause complaints and also a loss in revenue. 4. He concludes by saying that the work of ^he Cus-of the Cus toms occupies one man fully, and that the two posts of.iAdviser and Customs Director cannot be combined ; that all the reven ues of the State come from the Customs, and that their super vision is of the greatest importance. He feels sure that Gov^ ernment do not Y /ish to involve his ste state in loss, and that for this reason he informs me that Mr de Grenier will remain at his post of Director of Customs as he is pleased with him and his hard worlc r for his state. Finally, he says H If the (i) •xovernment of India want a cha.nge in the appointment of course they will make up any deficiency in the revenues, and we re quest Your Excellency to expl^n this matter to the Government of India l 1 5. As Sir Frederick Johnston pointed out to the Govern ment of India in the letter quoted above, it would be impos- siole to combine the posts of Adviser and Director of Customs without deterioration. I fully sympathise with the point of view set forth by the Shaikh in his letter, and I feel that it is impossible for the Government of India to go back at this stage on the reforms which they introduced with so much dif ficulty six years ago, and which have already shown such bene ficial results. 6. I do not think it is realised that Mr de Grenier is responsible ( with the revenue from pearling licenses which he also collects ) for the collection of 97 % of the revenues of the State. His revenue work is therefore of the greatest importance, for unlike British India there are no revenues ± from land, excise or income tax. In fact he is not only the Director of Customs but also the chief revenue officer. It must also be kept in mind that he has been called upon to do all passport work, which till recently was of little impor tance but now requires very strict supervision owing to the difficulties created by the Persian Government. 7. I show belov/ the collections of the customs for the past four years.1344 Rs 8.82.000 1345 Rs 62.000 1346 RsIO.58.000 run.) 1347 RsIO.70.000 ( at least, one month to It will 'be seen from these figures that there has been a very- considerable improvement in revenue in the past four years, an improvement which has been made without the imposition of any additionaltaxation, and at an administrative cost of not more than 5 per cent. The improvement in revenue seems to have found more pr less its level now, and His Excellency 1 ! claim that Government should guarantee him against loss is perfectly equitable, and I do not see how else they can oblig&lt; him to discharge an employee with whom he is well pleased. S. It must be remembered that the gradual increase in revenue 1ms been accompanied by an increase in expenditure. Should ir de Grenier t s departure result in a diminution of revenue, which seems inevitable, the results would be most kk serious. The allowances of the A1 Khalifa family, ( on a generous and ever expanding scale ) would have to be drasti- among cally reduced^ involving much discontent U* a very influential body. Expenditure on public vorks, education, medical institutions, land registration, courts and police; in fact all the benefits arising from the reforms, would have to be cut down as they are dependent for their existence on the present high rate of customs collections- 9. I confess I can think of no alternative to Mr de Gren; ier. A Qustoms officer on deputation would oresMumably be equally unacceptable to Government, and there is no one in the State, as the Shaikh observes, to replace him. The Hindus to whom the Customs were formerly farmed out proved-a failure^ and the method itself is objectionable. An Egyptian probably or Syrian would be less efficient, and ray experience of Syrian customs^leads me to think that they would be less honel Mr de Grenier is well liked by the merchants and the Shaikhv | and, as Sir Frederick pointed out to the Government, resident? in the Gulf are well used to seeing foreign a.dviisers employed, 10. In short, if there he anji ohjection to the employ-^Jl */ employment ment of Mr de Grenier, it certainly does not come from Bahrein where hi^services are appreciated, and if the Government of IndJ for reasons of policy / are determined that the Bahrein State should dispense with them, it is only equitable that they should undertake to indemnify it against the losses which it feels will inevitably ensue. There is no need for me to point ! out that the post v/as originally a creation,not of the State y but the Government of India and their agents. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, o PoliticaJ-^gent, Bahrein.i I 1 « ij'rom To The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. * Dated aimla, the /S June 1929, 4 a- Froposed retention of the services of Mr. deGrenier, Director of Customs, Bahrain, Sir, / In reply to your letter, No. 184-3, dated the 1st June 1929, l am directed to say that your views on the v .j(j ' iO general issues raised in my letter, bo•s'. 164 -1/29 dated ^ ^ Q ^ , the 28th May 1929, will be awaited before a decision is taken on the particular question of the retention of Mr. deGrenie^s services. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. ^ . (With 1 s.c.J rTil&amp; Modification in Mr. de Grenier's contract A copy of Mr. de Grenie^s contract is at p. 190. Mr. de Grenier has already served three years and 'will 'be entitled to go on furlough at once. Thereafter, his rights as regards the-periods ^ which he can take furlough -will, in practice, 'be much the same as those of Mr. Belgrave and Gapt. Parke, if the recommendations in their favour are accepted, except that his furlough will have to be taken at fixed intervals. It may 'be noted that there is no provision enabling Mr. de Grenier to accumulate his privilege* leave ot to add it to furlough; nor is he entitled to the cost of passages to and fro either on furlough or on privilege 1 leave. The original contract having been submitted to Government for approval, the present modification should also be submitted. after/g- Dookeb. From Trevor, P.A. Bahrein. To Knox, P.R. Bushire. No*. &amp; Dated, 17-5-1914. When I oalled on the Shaikh to say good bye he surprised me very muoh by saying that he was not satisfied with the receipts from the Custom House and was thinking of putting an Arab in chargs. This was an absolute surprise as only the afternoon before Mr. Maharaj the Director of Customs had been to see me and kne?/ nothing of it. The Shaikh said.he was considering the matter. I at once strongly advisfed him not to do anything in a hurry and said that in my opinion as Mr. Maharaj and his brothers had been in charge for years and there seemed to be no specific charge against the administration, Mr. V.T. Maharaj should be warned and told that he must keep proper accounts in Arabic and satisfy the Shaikh^ Govern ment that the administration was honest. If it was found after a specified time that the Custom was not properly administered ^-hey ^ould be replaced. I also urged on Shaikh Isa the inadvisability of putting in inexperienced Arabs, and informed him of the diffi- dated 29th x \pril 1914. culties mentioned in your letter No.0192^which had occurred in Koweit and other places, and which would certainly occur here if inexperienced Arabs were put in charge. I added that if he desired to put the Custom house on a proper basis it would be possible to get him the loan of the services of experienced men from India. He said he did not want to get men from India, but was thinking of putting in Arabs. I said that possibly he knew of experienced Arabs, but I did not, and that I was quite certain that the Govern ment would object to the appointment of any such men as Ahmed Yatim r Abdul Karim etc who had already been signal failures as landing contractors. I told him I was sure that Government would not agree to the appointment of inexperienced men. In the end the Shaikh said he would think over the matter. On my return to Mananr I was surprisedsurprised to hear that a report was going round that Shaikh Isa had farmed the Oustoms out to Abdulla Qassebi and Ahmed Salman for 2 years at 6 lakhs per annum. Shaikh Abdulla called to see me in the afternoon as I had missed him in Maharraq and the subject was broached. I found he was opposed to the proposed arrangement, which he said had been arranged by Shaikh Hamed. I have since heard that on his return to Maharraq Shaikh Abdulla has been doing his utmost to get the new arrangement altered^- and I hear that^AMulla Qassebi and Ahmed Salman t e-p^rrb4en: is shaky^and that all sorts of people (including Abdul Karim Khad are now trying to get the Customs. Meanwhile I have written a letter to Shaikh Isa protesting against the proposal a copy of which is enclosed. I now beg to ask whether I am authorized to tell Shaikh Isa that the Government will not accept the appointment of any inex perienced Arab contractor and that if he persists on appointing one they will have to take their own measures to put the Custom House on a proper footing. I may mention that the only definite semi-official informa tion about the change is the Shaikh^ statement that he is think ing over the matter (of making a change). I still have hopes that he will be persuaded not to pursue the matter. He is coming this afternoon to pay a first call on Captain Keyes, who arrived by yesterday^ steamer^and I hope to be able to go and see him again about the matter tomorrow.TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS, GRAY, BUSHIRE. ^ Uay Balxd, our representative at Bahrein writes me under date of 16tn instant as follows* 'News has the Sheifch ha^ l^^ed 'the Oustom House &amp; Ghupra to ^hm^d salinotx &amp; 'Ahdulla Gussahey for 6 lacs a year and I hear the 'Bunyans have received to c^uit • I have hO't y^^* had 'a chance of seeing Trevor ahout it hut will do so 'immediately after the mail. Three other names are mentioned as heihE conceded and they are Ally Zeyanl, Yusuf Kanoo&amp; Ahmed Yateem. Doubtless you already Know of the ahove Dut I it qn in case you have not heard. T taice it that such a concession will not allowed by G of I to exist any length of time. Yours sincerelyDocket From Trevor, P.A. Bahrein To Knox, P.R. Bushire No Dated 20-5-1914 Reference my docket No.546 regarding Shaikh ! s proposal regarding Customs. I enclose a copy of the Shaikh^s reply to my letter. It is not very satisfactory, but apparently the pro posal is scotched for the present. It is reported however that the contract had been actually signed with Abdulla Qasebi and Ahmed Salman and that it was taken back by the Shaikh and destroyed yesterday, so tha^ is satisfac tory. On the other hand the two contractors are adopting the 'wait and see' attitude so it is possible that some promise may have been given to them. On the other hand they may be merely bluffing. It is evident that the matter will want watohingjand I am calling the attention of my successor to it. I would add that Messrs. Gray Paul*8 representative has suggested to me that they would be very glad to take over the Warehouse work and ask if it would be a favourable opportunity to get it for them if the Shaikh v/ere to farm out the Customs. If Messrs. Gray Paul &amp; Co., had charge of the Warehouse many of the drawbacks to a farm of the Customs to inexperienced men would disappear. I therefore transmit their request for consi- deration in case the question comes up again Mr. V.T.Maharaj called on me and said that he had been sent for by the Shaikh in the morning, and that the Shaikh had said to him in the presence of all his sons that there had been a lot of talk about nothing and that he ha,d complete confidence in him (Maharaj) and had no intention of making any change in the existing arrangements. Later6 Interview with Shaikh ^sa of Bahrain, Dated 21st May. Shaikh 1 1sa,accompanied by his sons,Shaikh Hamad,Muhaminad and Abdullah and three grandsons,arrived on board R.I.M.S^Lawrence' about 9.30 a.m. He was met by me at the gangway. Major Trevor and Captain Keyes were present at the interview. Only Shaikh * Isa,his sons and grandsons were allowed up on the quarter deck. I informed Shaikh ! Isa thaj: I was glad to hear from Major Trevor that the Bunnaihs who were his servants at the Bahrain Customs still enjoyed his confidence; I reminded the Shaikh that the landing arrangements had just been put on a satis factory footing ar T d that to entrust the Customs management to unknown and untried men would upset the landing arrangements just come to with so much labour and trouble and would expose Shaikh *Isa to the worry of having goods/delivered to consignees without delivery orders, a practice that prevailed at other ports and led to endless friction between shippers and merchants and + he authorities. I had only recently been asked to report about all the Arab ports and this practice and it source had been a great/ X jkxh of satisfaction to me to learn from Major Trevor that there were no complaints at Bahrain in that connection at any rate. Shaikh f Isa said that he had no intention of changing his Customs management. Shaikh 'Isa's visit was returned by me at his Muharraq residence the same afternoon. Captain Keyes accompanied me. No controversial topics were introduced and the interview was a very pleasant and cordial one. 22-5-14. S.G.K.7 y Note on question of Bahrain Customs and necessity for Shaikh ^sa to consult the Resident before he makes any radical change in the system, p•144 Pile C.I. Bahrain. G.of I. on p.177 say that the Shaikh appears to have been within his rights in raising the import and export duties from 4 ^ to 5 ^ and the G .of I. do not consider that they can claim to be previously consulted in such a matter. G.of I. do not however say what the on effect of document/p.144 has been p.193 Prideaux reports a verbal repetition of the undertaking of p.144. p.356-357. File 19 C.8. Bahrain 126 Kemball lays down 'The Shaikh is well 'aware that his action in so doing did 'not meet with the approval of the 'Government of India,who would certainly 'view with extreme displeasure any 'fresh transactions entered into by the 'Shaikh with regard to his Customs 'administration without a previous 'reference to the Resident'. Letter No.889 of 5th September 1901 to P•357 A.P.A. gives official instructions to the A.P.A. to explain to the Shaikh of Bahrain the enormity of his conduct in contemplating a fresh lease without consultingo, p. 370 consulting P # R A.P.A.Bahrain reports a fresh instance of Shaikh f Isa undertaking verbally to refer to the Resident when making a change in his Customs farmers or granting a fresh lease• i I p.375 p. 379 P.R. directs A.P.A. to tell the Shaikh that the Resident expects to he consulted and his advice considered before the Chief enters into negotiations with the view to make any change in his Customs arrangements No.979 dated 28-9-01. Shaikh directly applies to A.P.A. for advice and assistance and asks A.P.A. to refer the matter to P.S. p.31 No.38 of 1904 dated 18th February P.R. to Foreign gives scheme for the introduction of new Customs administration at Bahrain. The trend of later correspondence so far as I have seen it in the 3 files put up which only run to 1908 (C.l 19/43 1897-1901) (C.8 19/126 1901-1904) (0.7 19/118 1904-1908) runs more in the ■ direction of non- interference with Shaikh ^Isa in the matter of his Customs management. Cur first action was rather directed against Hindu management and the farming out of customs. It was more or less of a reform when the Shaikh proposed to undertake the management of the Customs himself. It was supposed that he would get more revenue. ItIt has never yet, I think,'been seriously contemplated that he would sever his connection with the hurrahs and it occurs to me that either(l) he wishes to frighten them and secure better terms from them. Major Trevor points out that this is wrong. The Bunniahs no longer farm the Customs but are Shaikh 'Isa's own servants and render accounts and he gets 3|- lakhs a year from them. The two Arabs of Major Trevor's report offered 6 lakhs which Maharaj showed to Major Trevor,who agrees,is an impossibi lity. They would attempt to raise it by robbing merchants and the Shaikh would probably not get his Srr lakhs and the whole place would be in confusion. (2) He is afraid that the Bunniahs are getting too much under British influence and that one fine day he will find them running a modern well managed Customs department with British Officials in charge who can neither be corrupted nor controlled. \ Bahrain docket No.570 of 20th May shows that the whole matter has been satis factorily settled for the time being. The Bunniahs have had a bit of a fright and probably the best plan to work a satisfactory Customs,for we emphatically It do not want to take/over ourselves,if satisfactory local arrangements exist^, would be to work it through the Bunniahs and get a commercial clerk,preferably a good Hindu,who would be allowed by the Bunniahs access to the account on the plea10 plea of the necessijfty of keeping the P.A. informed and provided with material for his trade report. Such an appointment properly managed would give us great influence with the Customs and enable us to intro duce reforms through the agency of the Bunniahs who seem capable men and amenable to argument. As the man would not be fully occupied,it would relieve the pressure on the Bahrain office,for he would probably run the many accounts and give the Head Clerk more leisure. Let this note be faired and I will, on my return draft to Government. 22./5-14 Sd/- S.G.K/ Bushire, 28-5-1914. My dear Milborrow, X $4 K Yotos re custom house at Bahrain darted 19th May. Trevor was able to step in and stop this business. I spoke myself about it to the Shaikh and trust that we shall hear no more of the proposal. Yours sincerely, S.G.Knox.Docket Prom To No. Dated, Keyes, P,A. Bahrein. Knox, P.R. Bushire. 6'? 9. 27-5-1914. / Reference my docket No.570 dated 20th instant regarding Shaikh^ proposal to farm the Cu3tom3 / I enclose a copy of the Shaikh's reply to Major Trevor's letter for information. L.D.Ai,% \ CONFIDENTIAL. No 1693, dated Bushire, the 4th (received 15th) Jane 19(4. From— Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. I have the honour to state that, just before my recent visit to Bahrain, Major Trevor reported that, at his farewell visit to Shaikh Isa on the 15th May, he was greatly surprised to learn from the Shaikh that tha latter was dissatisfied with the receipts from the Customs House and was thinking of putting an Arab in charge. 2. I have now the honour to enclose copies of the correspondence that passed between the Political Agent and Shaikh Isa on the subject, which will, I trust, explain itself. 3. When I reached Bahrain, Major Trevor informed me that the danger had passed and that Shaikh Isa had summoned the present Director of Customs and had informed him that he had full confidence in him and his management and had no present intention of making any change. On Shaikh Isa's visit to me, I expressed my gratification at learning that a change which had, to my knowledge, excited the greatest consternation among the leading merchants at Bahrain was no longer contemplated. 4. There has been voluminous correspondence in the past on the subject of the* Bahrain Customs and the question of their management by trained Customs officials lent to the Shaikh on the recommendation of the Government of India, has been frequently mooted but Shaikh Isa's opposition has always proved unsurmountable, I have carefully examined this correspondence and find that prior to 1904 this Residency attempted to establish the principle that the Shaikh of Bahrain was bound by promises, given on more than one occasion, not to renew the contracts for farming out his Customs to Hindu bunniahs without previously consulting the Resident. Shaikh Isa almost as consistently denied the existence of any such promises and affirmed his complete liberty of action in the matter. The trend of later correspondence tip to 1908 runs more in the direction of non-interference with Shaikh Isa in the matter ot his customs management.^ The bunniahs have ceased to farm the Customs and now occupy the position of Shaikh Isa^s own servants, render accounts to him and pay him on an average some 3^ lakhs of rupees per annum on this account. Since 1^08, owing to the supposed good management of the Customs and the improved system, service rather than farming, the matter appears to have remained quiescent and attention has been devoted to the wretched landing and distribution arrange- ments rather than to the actual Customs Service. I may remark parenthetically that the recent flutter in the dovecot was apparently due to Shaikh Isa s cupidity having been excited by an offer made by two Arabs, Abdullah Qassaibi and Ahmad Sulaiman, to pay Shaikh Isa six lakhs of rupees per annum. The present Director of Customs has convinced Major Trevor that It is, in present circumstances, impossible to realise such a sum from the Bahrain Customs. It may be added that the two Arab tenderers are, I am informed by Major Trevor, in a very shaky position financially and that there is reason to believe that this offer was merely a wild attempt to restore their finances at the expense of the public, and probably the event would have shown, at that of Shaikh Isa. r Premising that the Government of India have no wish to undertake the responsibility of lending Customs officials to Shaikh Isa, provided that there is any chance of establishing satisfactory Customs management in any other way, I have the honour to suggest for their consideration a method that, at the present juncture, seems to offer some prospect in my opinion of successful butunobtrusive interference with a view to improved Customs management at no great cost to Government, certainly not out of proportion to the advantages that I hope may thereby be obtained for trade in general and British trade and Shaikh Isa in particular. It seems to me important that the Political Agent should endeavour to establish closer relations with the present Customs Director, who appears to be progressive and amenable to the Political Agent's advice and influence. The Political Agent is, however, very fully occupied and his staff are exceedingly hardworked. It is not to be expected and would indeed as arousing suspicion be undesirable for him to show a continual interest in the details of Customs management and his staff, as at present constituted, have not the leisure to do so on his behalf. This difficulty could, I believe, be surmounted by the appoint ment of a special 'commercial' clerk preferably an English knowing Hindu whose duties would be confined to noting exclusively on trade and Customs management at Bahrain, with special relation to the financial position between Shaikh Isa and his Hindu Customs department. It will, no doubt, be obvious from the above that the Hindu clerk to be appointed should be a persona grata to the present Customs Superintendent, who might well be consulted in regard to the appointment. 1 hope, in this way, to keep the Political Agent in close touch with the Customs management and enable him to introduce reforms without appearing himself, and to increase our knowledge generally on Bahrain commercial matters and on what is going on at the Customs House. The fright to which the Customs Superintendent has lately been exposed and the success with which Major Trevor's influence was exerted on his behalf should render him more than ever amenable to the Political Agent's advice and influence. 6. Should the Government of India be disposed to entertain the idea favourably, I will direct the Political Agent, Bahrain, to submit concrete proposals. Before submitting this draft, I have consulted Major Trevor, the late Political Agent, Bahrain, and Captain Keyes, the new incumbent, who both welcome the proposal. Enclosure No. i. Translation of a letter No. 542, dated i6th May /p/4, from Major A. P. Trevor, C.I.E., Political Agent, Bahrain, to Shaikh Isa bin Alt Al Khahfah, ChieJ of Bahrain. When I called yesterday to take leave of you, you mentioned that you were thinking of appointing some Arab to the charge of Customs, and I very strongly recommended you not to do anything in haste but to give the present manage ment warning that you are not satisfied with the work done and direct them to keep regular accounts, etc. I added that if eventually any change is to be made in the charge of the Customs it should Only be given to experienced persons and that if you required experienced persons I could, no doubt, assist you to get some, I trust that on thinking the matter over as you promised to do you have decided to act on my advice. If so the rest of this letter may be disregarded. On my return to Manama yesterday I was exceedingly surprised to hear a very circumstantial report that a contract for the Customs was to be given to Abdullah Qassaibi and Ahmad Salman for 6 lakhs a year, I think this is probably incorrect in view of what you said, possibly this report has been spread by the interested parties. Should there be any truth in it, however, I must take very strong exception to the appointment of these two individuals as farmers. First, because the alleged proposed arrangement is a farm of the Customs and you have on previous occasions told various Residents that you would not farm the Customs. Secondly, because the two individuals concerned are totally inexperienced in Customs work, and further as you are aware objections have been made against them individually by my predecessors for various reasons.3 I understand that both Captain Mackenzie and Major Knox spoke to you about them, and I expect you will remember this. Thirdly one of the gentlemen mentioned in the reports is I have reason to believe in a bad way financially. He has borrowed large sums of money from British subjects and recently mortgaged a good deal of property. As regards Ahmad bin Salman he is well known as one of the partners in a most unsuccessful attempt to work as landing contractop. The Agency tiles are full of complaints against him, many of which as you know were only settled with great difficuly, and a few of which remain unsettled. I understand he leu Bahrain during his contract. Such a man is obviously quite unfitted to take up Customs work. Fourthly, for the above reasons merchants will not have any reliance on these two persons and already British subjects have protested against the idea of their being put in charge. 1 expect that you would find that the majority ot merchants of all class are against the change. The Customs and lading arrangements have gradually been regularised after years of trouble and the introduction of inexperienced Customs farmers would throw them back into the old bad conditions from the merchants' point of view. Fifthly, the present landing arrangements which have been introduced with the approval of the High Government and which are working smoothly will be thrown into confusion, and neither of the persons supposed to be going to take over the Customs, having been previously unacceptable as landing contractors, could be accepted as Warehouse Superintendent. I have to say, therefore, that I cannot agree to the arrangement, which is said to be proposed, and 1 am sure that the High Government will not accept the arrangement either, and will, in tact, view it with grave disapproval. A large portion of the trade of Bahrain is done by Bntish merchants and by far the greater portion of the cargo'comes in British steamers, and I am sure that the Government would not regard such a retrograde step, as that rumoured to be contemplated, with equanimity. 1, therefore, warn you formally not to hand over the Customs on contract to the two individuals named nor to any other quite inexperienced persons. I sincerely hope that you will accept my advice and make no change in the present Customs arrangements which are running very smoothly beyond ordering a strict system of accounts, etc. But if you are determined a change 1 request that you will not make one at once but wait until I have had time to refer the matter to the Resident. • It is my duty to warn you that should you disregard my advice in this affair it is likely, in my opinion, to have serious results. 1 regret that this question should have been raised just as 1 am going away, and as a departing friend I urge you in your own interests to accept my advice about this matter. This is what had to be said. May you be preserved and salams. Enclosure No. 2. Translation of a letter, dated 24th Jamadi from Shaikh ha bin Ali Al Khalifah,Ruler Trevor, C. 1. Political Agent&gt; Bahrain. 1 have received your esteemed letter No, 542, dated the 20th Jamadi Ath Thani 1332 (16th May 1914), regarding the last conversation with your honour at the time of your visit to me about the Customs and beg to inform you that out of this question nothing has taken effect. And 1 know its requirements fully. I thank you for your friendly advices. This was to be mentioned. May you be preserved and salams. %Enclosure No. 3. Translation of a letter No. ^6o ) dated 20th May 1914, from Major A. P* Trevor, C.I.E.) Political Agents Bahrain, to Shaikh Isa bin AH Al Khalifah, Chief of Bahrain. After compliments ~ I have had the honour to receive your letter, dated 24th Jamadi II 1332 (20th May 1914) and am glad to hear that nothing has resulted regarding the proposed change in the Customs arrangements. I trust that no change of such magnitude will be made in the furture with out first consulting my successor, Captain Keyes, and giving him an opportunity of consulting the High Government if necessary. As I told you in my last letter such a change is not in my opinion one which the High Government could view with approval, and I have, therefore, thought it necessary to repeat my warning to you about the matter. This is what had to be said. May you be preserved and salams. 1 # C55FD—44—23-6-14—GCBP Simla.CONFIDENTIAL. '11 No. 1753, dated Bushire, the 7th (received 15th) June 1914. From — M ajor S. G, K nox, C .I .E., Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department^ Simla. I have the honour to forward herewith, for the information of the Govern ment of India, the translation of a letter from the Shaikh of Bahrain to Major Trevor, late Political Agent, Bahrain, replying to the last letter of the series forwarded under cover of my No. 1693, dated 4th June 1914, on the subject of a proposed change in the Customs management at Bahrain. 2. The letter is of the usual Bahrain type. It will be noticed that it amounts to a denial of the Political Agent's right to be consulted in important changes affecting the Customs management at Bahrain. As, however, the Government of India is, so obviously in a position, should it, in its wisdom, consider it ex pedient to do so, to impose its will in Bahrajn both in this and in other matters, it seems a useless waste of time to continue the correspondence. 3. If, however, it is considered that such a challenge should not pass un noticed, I would suggest that the Political Agent may be authorised to convey to the Shaikh a message somewhat on the following lines:— ' Your letter of the 25th May 19T4 was forwarded by me, without comment, in the usual course of office routine, to higher authority, and I have been directed by the Resident to convey to you the following message from the Government of India in reference thereto:— ' The Government of India expect that the Shaikh of Bahrain will con sult their Political Agent on all important matters, especially changes, connected with the Customs management at Bahrain. They will not hesitate to interfere in such matters, should such interference appear called for in their care for the important com mercial interests, both British and Foreign, which they have in charge at that place.' ' Enclosure. Translation of a letter dated the jgth Jamadi Ath Thani 7332 (=:2^th May 7914) from Shaikh Isa bin Ali Ai Khalifah, Chief of Bahrain^ to Major A. P. Trevor, C.I.E. } Political Agent, Bahrain* I have received your esteemed letter No. 565, dated the 24th Jamadi Ath Thani 133 2 ( = 20th May I9 I 4) regarding the question of the Customs and beg to say that I do not see the suitability of again opening the discussion about this question because it ended, just as I mentioned to you in my letter dated the 24th Jamadi Ath Thani 1332 that nothing topk place out of what you had heard. The real fact is that that last conversation with your honour was an unofficial talk and it had nothing to do with the official business. Had it been official I should have written to you a letter officially. I know the requirement and interest of my Government and I have also the right of changing and replacing the officials^ of the office of my Customs when 1 see necessity for that. I have confidence in the good intentions of the High Government that they would not like interference in matters specialised for my Government. I also do not ignore the points for the objections of the British Government as laid down in the agreements entered into with them. I do safeguard with the utmost care their authority and friendship. That is what was to be explained. May you be preserved and salaams. C61FD— 44~-24»6 14 —GCBP SimlaThe Deputy Secretary to the (jovernment of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To Major S. GL Knox, C. I. E., Offg. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Dated Simla, the AP • July 1914, With reference to your letters Nos.1693 and 1753, dated respectively the 4th and 7th of June 1914, on the subject of the customs administration in Bahrain, I am directed to inform you that as the idea,which was mooted of making an undesirable change in the customs management, has been abandoned, the Government of India are of opinion that the correspondence with Shaikh Esa need not be pursued further. I am, however, to request that the Political Agent at Bahrain should be instructed to maintain vigilence, and if he should notice any signs of the renival of the idea, he should remind the Shaikh, verbally in the first instance, of the terms of JJemand YI of the Ultimatum of the 25th February 1905, and impress on him that the question of the management of his customs is one of the 'important matters' in regard to which the Govern ment of India require to be consulted. Sir, 1 I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India./9/^- ' ^ ■r Political Arencv. Pfihrflin. CONFIDENTIAL « Political Agency, Bahrain, Kp.i&amp;c.:-™...: Dated 28th February, 1920• To The Deputy Political Reeident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E . SUBJECT;Objection on the part of Bin Saud,Ruler of Nejd and Dependancies, to the Shaikh of Bahrain*s policy of impoeing a 5$ tax (or maximum import duty) on goods destined for Nejd and Hassa although such goods never leaved the Bahrain Custom House, MEMORANDUM For some months past there has been growing dis-satis- faction among Nejd and merchants who have branches in Bahrain,at what they call the unfair customis charges levied by orders of Shaikh Isa on goods and food stuffs landed from B.I. Steamers at the Bahrain Customs House which are consigned to Ojair and Q.atif, the ports of Hassa and Nejd. This dis-satisfaction culminated in the form of a deputation addressing me, consisting of representatives of the houses of A1 Bassam, A1 Qusaibi,A1 - Hawwas, and by the Bahrain merchant, Mr. Yusuf Kanoo, M.B.E., K.I.H., K.S. I informed the deputation that I did not ptopos® taking action unless Bin Saud himself took the matter up. This was early in January last. The actual nature of the complaint of the deputation was as follows '•That Shaikh Isa was imposing a fixed tax of 5% (ad valorem) on all goods entering ^ahrain, whether from India or else where, which were conBigned to Hassa and Nejd, putting such goods on a par with those entering Bahrain Island®. That up to 19 17 Shaikh Isa had been accustomed to impose this 5^ tax only on goods which cleared th# uustoms House and found their way into Bahrain itself. That he used to impose a. 2% % ad valorem tax on(S) i- ( &gt; on goods conaigned and destined for the mainland, such goods never leaving tlie Gustoms Mouse sheds but being re-shipped on first opportunity on native craft. This 2ir % tax was in addition to the Ardhiya or ground rent tax charged on all goods lying in the Gustoms Warehouses. That in 19 17, on the pr4te^t that the war had greatly reduced his customs receipts,Shaikh Isa suddenly imposed the full tax of S % on all goods landed at the Customs Pier, whether such were entering Bahrain or were merely being transhipped from B.I.Steamers to iative Graft. That this tax was still in force. That lejd, Hassa and ^atif merchants consider ed it to be a grossly unfair tax and founded on no precedent and prayed for its removal It appears also that various similar tfomplaints were made to the Agency in my predecessor's time, but nothing came of them, since Bin Saud was too closely engaged, putting his own house . , A . to take the matter in order, not to mention his troubles with the Shareef Musain ./up And so the matter was dropped. S- ' Bin Saud, it would appear, has now definitely taken up the matter himself, and quite recently wrote to Shaikn Xsa (in letter dated 2Sth January, 1980), asking him in a friendly way his reasons for charging Hejd ilerchants 5 ^ on *'^}lAiSMIP ,, goods, putting such goods on a par with those entering Bahrain. Bin Saud, further, requested that for old friendship's sake, the tax be again reduced to 2% % as formerly existing. To this letter Shaikh Isa returned no letter^ but later, hearing I was leaving for Massa, asked me to sound Bin Saud on the subject. Me, at the same time, gave me his own reasons for having imposed the tax.I prooeeded to laesa on 89tli January, and whilst th«re raised the queption at issue with Bin Sand. Bin Saud expressed himself in strong language at the way his subjects had been treated by the Shaikh of Bahrain of late years, and stated that friendly endeavours to ret Shaikh Isa to behave decently towards his people had failed entirely.Me therefore, now, formally demanded that lis Majesty's Government should decide the present point of difference between himself and Shaikh Isa. Shaikh Isa had certainly be^n like a father to him in the past, and rather than start a wordy warfare with him, he preferred to put this case before Mis Majesty^ Government, and jr.et the matters settled once and for all. Me merely demanded that Customs Fagulations as understood in civilized countries be enforced in Bahrain. Me understood no Customs Tarif was ever imposed throughout the world on w TKAiSMIP' goods,i.e. those which never left the Customs iiouse, but were re-exported without entering the country where landed. Bin Saud, then, formally presented me with his letter n A*(copy attached); this was on 7th February, 1920. At the same time he requested me to forward it to Migher Authority with the request that early orders might be passed on same. 4# I give below, for the sake of clearness, both Shaikh Bin baud's and Shaikh Isa's points of view in the matter. BIS SAUDIS CASK ( 1) Me objects, as an act of injustice and contrary to all precedent, to Shaikh Isa taking full Customs Duty on goods belonging to his subjects which are landed from ships on to Bahrain customs Jetty but were destined for Masba or iejd and not Bahrain. ,Such goods are never taken out of the customs yard but remain lying there until Jlative Craft can be arranged to carry same to Ojair or Qatif (namely a week or fortnight). (2) He Claims that Inter-national Custom should decide the matter. (?) ie, of course, has no objection to raise to his subjects being made to pay the full 5 % Tariff on goods(4) %3&gt; a, w that they may bring into Bahrain and irhich are consign ed to that town. (4) The matter is one of common justice, and he him self in no way hopes to be benifited. It is merely a question of his subjects receiving fair treatment. A Kejdi bringing goods, for instance, from Bombay *to Maea has to pay the following now a days Import Tax at Bahrain. Ardhiyah in Bahrain, which amounts to about 9^ second import tax at Ojair. Thus ^Jis subjects pay 15^ tax on all comodities before they finally get their goods into lejd territories. (5) le contends that the Bahrain Tariff should only be levied if the goods pass through the Customs into the town. (6) Shaikh Isa's argument that he (Bin S'aud) has no right to charge 8% Import Tax at Ojair or Qatif, is no argument, fie. Bin Saud, would never dream of taxing cargo landed at Ojair or iatif whose eventual destina- was, say, Qatar. The Turks used to charge a 3D ^ Import Tax pre viously to his taking over lassa. Me has already re duced this to 8jJ. le hopes still further to reduce the tax when his finances are in better condition. lis is a new State just coming out of the ^rysiiis of ignorance, poverty and disorder. Me is struggling to put his house in order and is compelled, for the present, to charge a high import tarif. SHAIFK ISA 1 S CASS. arith the exception of bales iiece goods on which ^ ^ n9 admits in the past to having charged 5% on all b tfie round sum of and later 1^15/-was goods coming into Bahrain and 2#% on goods passing Jred per bale. , , { through (tranship) Bahrain for Jlejd and otner places. (2) In 19 16 he found that owing to war restrictions and poor trade generally, his Customs Revenues were goin^ down. This, added to the general increase in the—* 1 cost of 1lying#wade It necoesary to do eomethlng. a® ordsrod full S%euatoics Duty to be charged on all jtoodG landed on his pier, whether ooneigned to Mainland or not. (3) He coneidere it ie hie right to charge what Sue- tome Duty he likes provided he does not exceed Hf. duty, as fixed by treaty with fiis Viajesty's Government ('.'hen - asked to auote number and date of treaty, he referred to article 4 of Treaty Ho. 8, page 6 of Treaties and undertakings in force between Mis Majesty's GOYernrnent and Ruler of Bahrain (copy attached). (4) He complains that Bin Eaud charges Customs on his subjects when taking goods in V Oja:.r and itatif, and that,therefore. Sin Saud has no right to complain, if his own subjects have to pay full duty on goods using Bahrain Customs Bouse as a store godown, even if such goods did not enter the town. (f-) If he went back to the rule, ae in force prior to 1S1R, he feared his revenues would be enor mously reduced and he could not afford such loss. Having conversed fully on the subject with both Shaikh ^ea and Bin Saud, I am of opinion that Shaikh Isa is in the wrong for the following reasons ;- (1) The treaty which he quotes has nothing to do with the case, and refers to Britieh subjects only. (2) Clustoms Department, I believe, all over the world, do not charge Import Tax on goods until such goods are actually passed through the Customs House of the land to whicft they f rriiju Tj? fiT*© confjl^ncd • Further, his complaint that his Customs receipts be greatly reduced if he foregoes the newly imposed tax,may be quite true, but if he were a.decant ruler and made any attempt at all to rule properly, ha would know that he could raisa reve- nues by such lagitimate means as (a) slumbering and taxing his iSative Sailing Sraft. (b) Taxing pearling boats. (c) Selling some of his Innumerable gardens to the inhabi-(fl) and so introducing a regular Data lax, (d) Selling arable land for wheat and barley purposes and so introducing a Regular tJand Revenue. (e) Faririing the fisheries, (f) Sheep and camel tax, lot to mention the various Municipal Taxes which every municipal ity has a right to levy. As it is , none of the above sources of revenue are tapped| nor does Land, Pate or Municipal Revenue exist even in name, and this by reason of the suicidal policy of the Shaikh who has forbidden any land to be owned by any one but himself. Result : The island remains a dreadfully badly managed,and rapidly decaying private Estate,with no revenues accruing from it at all. Thare ramains the ^iustoms'. Practi cally the whole of ^haikh ^sa's income is obtained from this source. Yet here again, he appears, utterly incapable of putting even his own Customs louse in order. I estimate that hie custom* roughly should bring in to 20 Lakhs of rupees per annum. It actually wrings in fro® 7 to 10 .balfiis. The scandalously managed Syndicate which runs the customs must be held responsible for the deficiency. I,further, recommend the quashing of this incipient trouble at once, before it is allowed to grow bigger and give us endless trouble. Bin L'aud, now a days, imagines he is sur rounded by enemies, all trying to fleece him in some wav or othei * j his attitude is rather that of a lioness robbed of her cubs. Froa bent what I saw of him lately he seems^on getting what he calls justice done to his subjects. Should he fail to get this present complaint attended to, it will only make him more bitter, than he is already Me will only retaliate by putting an embargo on rrnig sheep, ghi and dates, and the stupid and short-sighted policy of Shaikh Isa will only come*back A to his own head, ior can ^is Majesty's Government afford to see ^in ^aud starting a quarrel with the ^uler of Bahrain, his Eastern neighbour. I recomniend Shaikh iga be ordered to remove the increased taxation and go ^ a !f a L P wan?8 t to make more revenue, the opportunity Is a good one, he wight be(?) told, of Improving his ajretom of 30T«rnrB«snt and raising other tarso by legitimate aeuns, and not at the expense of his neigh bours, who aleo are friends of Bis Majesty's Government. &gt; J &lt;W. ■6ceW ♦ ^ - Major, Q.l.E., Political Asent, Bahrain. . Oopy to the (Sivil «omBisrion«r # Baghdad, NOTE It should be clearly understood that Bin Saud demands that no tax be paid on tranship goods, but that only w Ardhiyah w or ground rental be charged. My proposals do not go as far as this though it vtould appear Bin Saud*8 contention is right in principle.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000130_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/331</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000130</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/331</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 19/126 II (C 29) Bahrain Customs'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1914/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-11-26T11:06:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (287 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.</extent><extent>Formerly a bound correspondence volume, the file's pages have been unbound and are now loose.The foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the spine (which is loose); these numbers are written in pencil and may be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Foliation errors: 1A, 1B, 1C, 1D, 1E, 1F and 1G; 3A, 3B and 3C; 74A and 74B; 143A and 143B; 203A and 203B; 216A and 216B; 234A, 234B and 234C.Foliation omissions: ff 199-200</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence related to the administration of the Customs House in Bahrain from 1914 until 1929.The earlier correspondence relates to a disagreement between Shaikh Isa bin Ali Al Khalifa and Bin Saud regarding tariff charges on goods entering and leaving Bahrain from the mainland.The bulk of the correspondence discusses Claude De Grenier, who was appointed Director of Customs in Bahrain in 1923.The details of De Grenier's appointment (including the contract agreed between him and Shaikh Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa) and his performance in the job (which was heavily criticised) are both discussed at length.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia 'Abd al-'Azīz bin 'Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa'ūd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Hugh Weightman</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Khalīfah (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Customs administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>National Economy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Religious conflicts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rights of states</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arab nationalism</topic></subject><subject><topic>Social reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Economic reform</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000130#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>