<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00032e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T23:24:35.017Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-235. April 4, 1939. i* His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent. Bahrein. Sir, u&gt; 'Hu Return of 21 empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering (21) Twenty-one empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders which have been shipped to San Francisco for return to Suppliers per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. 'BENGKALIS' on March 28th. 1939. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, MI. THE BAHREI , BLACK Representative ’OLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel. 1.the Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-221 April 3, 193° His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. v TBB-2342 Sir, Return of No.12 Corks for Credit I enclose herewith Certificate covering 4 (four) boxes containing 695 gross No.12 Corks which are being returned to New York for return to Suppliers. These boxes have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S.’’BAMORA” on March 28th to Bombay thence Via American President Line S.S. ’’PRESIDENT GARFIELD” on or about April 8th. to New York. at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Please return the Certificate duly attested Yours truly THE BAH ED. MI Enel. 1.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED His Brit Bahrein, NO:PA-23 3 , 0.6034 Sir, Return of 12 - 3.85 x 18 Firestone Tyres on TBB-1231 : For Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering one box containing 12 - 3.85 x 18 Firestone Tyres. This has been shipped for return to suppliers, per B.I.S.N. Co.’s 3.S. 'CHAKDINA” on April 4th to Bombay, thence Via American President Line S.S. 'PRESIDENT GARFIELD” on or about April 22nd. to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, THE BAH TED Enel. 1,The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited PA-244 Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, Av/ali, April 17, 1939. His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agen/^0 N Bahrein. ^ Dear Sir: V. r e are attaching two copies of a substitute Power-of-Attorney for Mr. Colin Reith. Y/ill you please register this Power, authenticate the two copies, and return them to us. Yours sincerely, Chief THE BAHREIN DKY'7: F Enel 2No. 7&lt;rt&gt; -5/tSr- Political Agency, Bahrain, the 29th April 1939. The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. A Dear Sir, Reference your letter No. PA-244 dated the 17th April 1939. 2* Please send to this Agency the sum of Rsi 8/-, representing the charges for registration of the documents forwarded jith your letter refereed to above, which is made up as under Court Fee Stamps Copying Fees Rs. 5 —0—0 ' 3- 0-0 H8 8 - 0-0 v • 3. The documents are returned herewith.Enel. 1. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-258. His Britannic Bahrein. Sir, April 26, 1939 Majesty^ Political Agent, 1 /^ is| l &lt; TBB - 2993 1 - Coleman Model 3-A Electro meter for repair &amp; return, I enclose herewith Certificate covering one box containing Coleman Model 3-A Electrometer. This has been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. ’’BANDRA' on April 17th. to Bombay thence Via ’’PRESIDENT ADAMS” on May 6th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, MI. Chief L THE BAHREIN lCK Representative )LEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Enel. 1. The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Awali, Bahrein Island. P NO:PA-261. April 27, 1939. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. TBB - 2265 Return of 23 Sets of Piston Rod Stuffing Box Packing for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering one box containing 23 Sets of Piston Rod Stuffing Box Packing for 9-l/2 tt x 8' Gardner Denver Vertical Twin Cylinder Steam Drilling Engine. This box has been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. ’’BANDRA” on April 17th to Bombay, thence Via 'PRESIDENT ADAMS' on May 6th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, Chief THE BAHREIN lCK Representative &gt;LEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited NO:PA-266. Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, May 1st. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrein. TBB - 3025 Sir, Return of 11 empty Acetylene Cylinders for refilling &amp; return. I enclose herewith Certificate covering eleven empty Acetylene Cylinders which have been shipped per S.S. M VARELA W on April 23rd to Bombay, thence Via 'PRES. ADAMS' on May 6th to New York, for refilling &amp; return to Bahrein. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, MI. Chief THE BAHREIN P SLACK &gt;c#l Representative “OLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel. 1.Enel. 1. the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited NO:PA-267. Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian May 1st. 1939. ip . His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, Return of 25 Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 25 empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to U.S.A. for Credit. These empties have been shipped to San Francisco per ’’Silver Java Pacific Line” M.Y.HOEGH SILYSRSTAR on April 23rd. 1939. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly. MI. J. Chief Loc THE BAHREIN PE Representative FM COMPANY LIMITED,- r THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED NO.PA-268. Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf* May 1, \ ////. HIS BRITANNIC MA.JBSTY'S POLITICAL A.GENT, BAHREIN. !/V Deer Sir: TBB - 2995. 1 - Coleman kodel S-A Electro- Meter for Repair and ReturnT Further to our letter PA-258 of April 26th, we return herewith the Certificate signed by you end received today, as we believe it should also carry the Official Seal and date. Will you please return at your early convenience. Yours truly, Chie THE BAHREIN al Representative, STRDLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SKSMTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED FA-278 Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Age Bahrein . Dear Sir: We thank you for your letter No.700-5/13 of April 29, 1939 returning two copies of a substitute Power-of-Attorney for Mr. Colin Heith, duly registered Herewith we have pleasure in enclosing our cheque for Rs:8/0/0 in payment of your charges, and shall appreciate your receipt therefor at your con venience. Yours very truly, Chief Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. 1 cheque.I§!£2 ( No. 796-5/3 To Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th May 1939. The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. u Dear Sir, \ / Reference your letter No. PA-278 dated the 8th May 1939. I return the receipt for Rs. 8/- duly signed by me. Yours faithfully,The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No.PA-279 May 9, 1939 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein, Deer **ir&gt; I am enclosing herewith signed certificate with regard to Mr. M.F. Young’s service in this Island. It would be appreciated if you could countersign and return. Yours very trulyK- the Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awal i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-299. May 25tli. 1939. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, FBB - 855 h- ' '' 50 MAY 193a 'Idlio/fju acrj Return of 1 Baroid H.P. Wall Building Tester for Drilling Mud (Obsolete Model) I enclose herewith Certificate covering one box containing One Baroid H.P. Wall Building Tester. This has been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. ’’BARALA” on May 15th to Bombay thence Via American President Line S.S. ’’PRESIDENT HARRISON” on June 3rd to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours truly, MI. Enel. 1. Chief L THE BAHREIN P BLACK Representative 10LSUM COMPANY LIMITED.the Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, No .PA-303, May 30, 1939 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. ^ Dear Sir, We enclose herewith signed Certificate with regard to Mr. A.W. Thomas. It would be appreciated if you could countersign and return. Yours very truly, Snclo:Enel. 1. the Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-305. June 1st. 1939. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Return of 29 empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to San Francisco for Credit. Sir, — I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 29 empty Anhydrous Amm onia Cylinders to San Francisco for Credit. These empties have been shipped to San Francisco per Silver Java Pacific Line S.S. t, SOEKABOEMI ,, on May 19th. 1939. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. MI.Enel. 1. &lt;3 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, N0:FA-304. June 1st. 1939. His Briteuinic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Return of 16 empty Calol Industrial Sir, Gas #Z Cylinders to San Francisco. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 16 empty Calol Industrial Gas #2 Cylinders to San Francisco for Credit. These empties have been shipped to San Francisco per Silver Java Pacific Line S.S. 'SOEKABOEMI M on May 19th. 1939. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. MI. Yours truly,the Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Aweli, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, No .PA-310. Arne 5, 1939 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, sre enclosing herewith signed Certificate with regard to Mr. P.H. Kirchmeyer one of our American employees. It would be appreciated if you could countersign and return. Bnclo: EBThe Bahrein Petroleum Company limited N 0 .Pa- 3£1 ein Island, Persian Gulf, une 18, 1939 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent Bahrein. Sir: SHIPMENT OF £18-55 GALLON drums - Gasoline. We have shipped £18 - 55 gallon drums Gasoline to U.S.A., 18 - per M.3.'SOUTH AFRICA' sailed March 10, 1939 with transhipment at Cape Town, £00 - per M.S.'NEDERLAND' sailed April 12, 1939 with transhipment at Durban, and inasmuch as the containers involved are of American origin and manufacture, we are enclosing herewith three Certificates in this respect and shall be glad if you will return these duly attested at your earliest con venience, debiting charges in connection to our account Yours truly SKSM ^IS^BLaCK CHIEFo^rt5lL REPRESENTATIVE the Bahrein petroleum company limited Enel (3)The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limiter v ^ ' I enclose herewith Certificate covering one box containing one Burroughs Adding Machine, This has been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. 'BARALA” on June 19th to Bombay thence Via American President Line S.S. ’’PRESIDENT POLK” to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Awal i , Bahrein Island. Persian C NO:PA-336. June 27, 1939. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. ’ Sir, TBB - 2614 Return of 1 Burroughs Adding Machine. Yours very truly, 1*' ^ p. STACK Chief LpcAl Representative THE BAHRAIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI Enel. 1.The Bahrein Petroleum company limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, June 29, 1939. Dear Sir, Enclosed please find two documents in connection vfith the shipment made in the M.3. 'SQLSTSN* on November 22/23 and on December 7/8, 1938, for Karachi, India and Suez, Egypt. Will you kindly certify signatures of !£r. W. B. Steele, State Engineer, and klr. Milton E. Lipp, Attomey-in-Fact for California Texas Oil Company Limited on these documents and return them to us per bearer. Thanking you. Yours faithfully. Chief THE BAHREIN PSTRO ;k, Representative, COMPANY LIMITED Enel:THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No .PA -343 July 3, 1939 x-T. m/W.*. ... His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, /? I enclose herewith signed certificate with regard to Mr. E.H. Smith whilst in Bahrein* It would be appreciated if you could countersign and return# KB.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awali , Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. NO:FA-348 July 5, 1939 1^ His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. V Sir, Return of 25 empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 25 empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to San Francisco for Credit. These empties have been shipped to San Francisco per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. 'TOSARI' on June 24th. 1939. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly THE BAH MI Enel. 1.The Bahrein petroleum company limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, N0:PA-351. July 6th. 1939. ^ ^ His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. C.P.1016 Sir * Return of 6 - 1-1/2' Valves I enclose herewith Certificate covering one box containing 6 - 1-1/2”, 150# Semi-Steel Yalves. This has been shipped on June 24th per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. ”T0SARI” to San Francisco for return to Suppliers. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, MI. Enel. 1Awali, July 3£, 1939 PA-377 H.B.M’s Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein. Dear Sir, Will you please authenticate the signature of Mr. M.H. Lipp on the attached specific Power-of-Attorney for Mr. Charles Isaac Graham in Bombay, returning to us as soon as possible. Yours very truly, f. Jincl (2)(27/ I t The BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, July 22nd f 1939 TO T --HQS4 IT luAY COHGERH By virtue of the full Power-of-Attorney given me by the Board of Directors of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited as the result of a Resolution passed by the said Board on 19th October 1938 f I Hereby Authorize CHARLES ISAAC GRAHAM to defend the lawsuit filed against The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited by HASIUM ALI* He has the authority to engage Advocate or Advocates; the power to compromise; and dd anything else necessary to defend this Case for The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited* THE BAHREIN FSTROLSOM COMPANY LIMITED tThe Bahrein petroleum company Limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-389. July 29th. 1939 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, Return of 36 Empty I enclose herewith Certificate in quadruplicate covering thirty-six (36) Empty Ethyl Fluid Drums for return to Suppliers. These have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. 'VTTA” on July 16th to Bombay, thence Via ’’PRESIDENT GARFIELD” on July 29th to New York. Please return the Certificate in quadruplicate duly attested at your earliest convenience, debiting charges in this connection to our account. Yours very truly, /Enel. 1. The Bahrein petroleum company limited I enclose herewith Certificate covering 15 empty Freon-12 (Diehlorodifluoromethane) Cylinders which are being returned to New York for Credit. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.3. 'VITA” on July 16th. to Bombay thence Via S.S. 'PRESIDENT GARFIELD' on July 29th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-590 July 29th. 193§\ His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir Return of 15 Empty Freon Cylinders - For Credit. Yours very truly THE BAH ,:ED MITHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Enel. 1 Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-391. July 29th. 1939. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Return of 15 Empty Anhydrous Sir, Ammonia Cylinders - for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 15 (Fifteen) Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to San Francisco, for Credit. These empties have been shipped to San Francisco per Silver Java Pacific Line M.S. 'SILVERBEECH' on July 25th. 1939. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, MI.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No, PA-596, August 2, 1939 Deer Sir, »ve enclose herewith signed Certificate with regard to Mr, Sims, It would be apprecieted if you could countersign and return* Yours very truly, TE Enclo: 3b 1 Representative PNTROLUJM COMPANY LTDThe Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-422 August 26th• 1939 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. FBB - 478 Sir Return of 1 - Waukesha C.F.R. Engine Cylinder for examination I enclose herewith Certificate covering one Waukesha C.F.R. Engine Cylinder which is being returned to New York for examination. This has been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. ’’BANKURA” on August 14th to Bombay thence Via n FRESIDENT AHAMS” on August 26th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly Chief THE BAHREUf MI Enel. 1GO-10-1 BP 7-37 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED S' BAHREIN ISLAND. PERSIAN GULF. AUgUSt 26th. ^ f «- (ft rORlHOUSE. FOR CUSTOMER'S USE PRICE charge / The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. \ TERMS F. O. B. TO / \ 130 East 43rd Street, CHG. TO APPROVAL \ New York City. U.S.A. / TRANSP'N. RECEIVAL CALCULATIONS AUDITED terms shipped^* por S.S.'’B 1 \NKDRA , ’ to Bombay thanoe 'PRESIDEI PRjSTOMER'S ORDER NO. REQ'N. NO. rKM Bahrain. ^Aug. 14th. r 0 . ADAMS'. VIA CAR NO. 1939. FRT. PPD. OR COLL INV. NO. I, M.H. Lipp, Manager, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, do solemnly and truly declare that the Waukesha Engine Cylinder herein specified is* to the best of my knowledge &amp; belief, truly and bonafide of the manufacture of the United States; that it was exported from United States per S.S. 'STOLZENPELS' on or about April 9th* 1938, and that it is returned without having been advanced in value or improved in condition by any process of manufacture or other means* 1 Waukesha ASTM - C*F*R* Knock Testing Engine Cylinder fawaBagtaeaiyhtedm for Engine #426910 Value 1141.50 Signature HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT. BAHREIN. MI.Enel. 1. The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited NO:PA-419. Awall , Bahrein Island, Persian August 26th. 1939. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent. Bahrein. FBB - 1042 Sir, Return of 92 Empty Oxygen Cylinders - for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering 92 empty Oxygen Cylinders, which are being returned to New York for Credit. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. ’’BANKURA” on August 14th. to Bombay thence Via ’’PRESIDENT ADAMS” on August 26th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. MI. Yours very truly, Chi THE BAHREIN • SLACK Repre sentative OLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. 13a (3^ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED STOREHOUSE BAHREIN ISLAND, PERSIAN GULF, AUgUSt 26th. 193 9. FOR CUSTOMER’S USE PRICE TERMS charge rne oanrexn re^roxeum uompany .Limited. \ TO f \ 130 East 43rd Street, F. O. B. CHG. TO APPROVAL \ . / TRANSPN. New York City. U.S.A. / RECEIVAL CALCULATIONS AUDITED TERMS p.r S.S.-BAHHJRA' to Bombay thence 'PRESIDE] fllWJSTOMER-S ORDER NO. FR om Bahrein. date Aug. 14/39 .o b ADAMS'. REQ'N. NO. VIA CAR NO. FRT. PPD. OR COLL INV. NO. I, M.H. Lipp f Manager f The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, do solemnly and truly declare that the Cylinders herein specified are, to the best of my knowledge &amp; belief; truly and bonafide of the manufacture of the United St ate s; that they were exported from United States per S.S# 'STEEL TRAVELER' on or about April 28th. 1939 and that they are returned without having been advanced in value or improved in condition by any process of manufacture or other means. 92 - Empty Oxygen Cylinders © #20.00 ea. s #1840.00 /“N SignatureThe Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. NO:PA-420 August 26th* 1939 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. TBB - 2597 Sir, Return of 13 empty Acetylene Cylinders - for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering 13 empty Acetylene Cylinders which are being returned to New York for Credit. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. ’’BANKURA” on August 14th to Bombay thence Via ’’PRESIDENT ADAMS” on August 26th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly. Chief itive THE BAHREIN tfY LIMITED MI End. 1.I GC-10-1 BP 7-37 _ 3? ^i_37) THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED STOREHOUSE. BAHREIN ISLAND, PERSIAN GULF,. August 26th, CHARGE TO The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited* 130 East 43rd Street, New York City. U.S.A* TERMS FOR CUSTOMER’S USE SHIPPED FROM _ r msinEW£ S.S.'BANXURA' to Bombay thence '] ft DATE AUg# 14th r o b ADAMS' CAR NO. 1939. FRT. PPD. OR COLL TERMS F. O. B. CHG. TO APPROVAL TRANSP’N. RECEIVAL CALCULATIONS AUDITED J STOMERS 3ER NO. REQ'N. NO. INV. NO. I, M.H# Llpp, Manager, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, do solemnly and truly declare that the Cylinders herein specified are, to the best of my knowledge &amp; belief, truly and bonafide of the manufacture of the United States; that they were exported from United States per S• S• 'MICHJfiNPELS' on or about January 31st. 1939 and that they are returned without having been advanced in value or improved in condition by any process of manufacture or other means. 13 - Empty Acetylene Cylinders O $50.00 ea. - #650.00 Signature Declared to before me thl s..^^ d ay of 1939. /*&gt; HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY 1 S POLITICAL AGENT. BAHREIN. MI.The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited A wall f Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. NO:PA-431 August 36th. 1939 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. FBB - 631 Sir Return of 1 Defective Selsyn Motor I enclose herewith Certificate covering one Defective Selsyn Motor which is being returned to New York for repairs. This has been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. 'BANKDRA” on August 14th. to Bombay thence Via 'PRESIDENT ADAMS' on August 36th to New York. Please return the Certificate, duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly C THE BAH _ _ _ _ ITED MI Enel. 1GO-10-1 BP 7-37 3V ^ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED STORBWOUSE. CHARGE TO / RAHRFIN KI ANH PFR&lt;?IA N fil 11 F AUgUSt 26th. iq} 9. FOR CUSTOMER’S USE PRICE The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. \ TERMS F. O. B. 130 East 43rd Street, CHG. TO APPROVAL New York City. U.S.A. / TRANSP'N. RECEIVAL CALCULATIONS AUDITED TERMS shipped iv per S.S.'BANKURA B to Bombay thence 'PRESI prom Bahrein. D * TE Aug. 14th*. o. B . ADAMS” • REQ'N. NO. VIA CAR NO 1939 . FRT. PPD. OR COLL INV. NO. I. M.H. Lipp, Manager, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, do solemnly and truly declare that the Selsyn Motor herein specified is, to the best of my knowledge &amp; belief, truly and bonafide of the manufacture of the United St ates ; that it was exported from United States per S,S. n SONNEOTELS' on or about June 1st. 1938, and that it is returned without haring been advanced in value or improved in condition by any process of manufacture or other means. 1 - Defective Selsyn Motor for driving ) Oeoanalyzer Recorder, G.B.C. 110 V. )Value $5.00 60 Cycles, Type ER, Model 2JD123A1. ) Signature Declared to before me thi s ?*// d ay of 1939. MI. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S POLITICAL AGENT. BAHREIN.1 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED % i-wali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. No.PA-418. August 26, 1939 His Britennic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, enclose signed certificates for Messrs. M.H.Lipp, 0,F. Frickson, J.T. Deane and A.A. Bila. It would be appreciated if you could countersign and return. Yours very truly, r 7The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited 6 Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, Awali, August 24, 1939 PA-417 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: We are attaching the original Power-of-Attorney given by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited to Mr. Colin Reith. A Will you please register the same, and return it to us at your convenience together with a note of the fees i 'A payable for registration? Yours very truly, Chief THE BAHREIN Repr e s ent ati v e ‘OLEUM C OMPANY LIMITED Enel (1),—No. 1540-5/3• Politics! Agency, Bahrain, the 30th August 1939. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No. PA-417 dated the 24th August 1S39. 2. Please send to this Agency the sum of Rs. 24/8/- (t.venty four and annas eight only), representing the charges for registration of the document forwarded with jour letter referred to a'oove, which is made up as undert — Court Fee Stamps Copying fees Linking fees — Rs. 2-8-0 - Rs. 19 - 8 - 0 fr - Rs. 2-8-0 Total - 24 - 8 - 0 “/’A, « Sr 9 3. The document is returned herewith. Yours faithfully, o La. for Political Agent, Bahrain. k. mIThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awal i , Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. No ,P;--453 September 3, 1939 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Bear Si^ v7e enclose si&lt;m^^ certificate of residence in respect of Messrs# z ~.k, Baker end C.D. Nendershott. It would be appreciated if you could counter sign and return to us. Yours very truly, Ag.Chief local Hepresentetive THY BAH JIN PSTROLEOM COMPANY LIMITEDThe Bahrein Petroleum Company limited .Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, September 4, 1939. No .PA-434 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BABHSIN. Dear ^Sir, U R G 3 i\ T In connection with the shipment of B-849 5\iel Oil made today in the Danish M.3. 'AASE I^AiiRSK ,, for Djibouti, French Somaliland, I enclose Original and two copies of the Certificate of Origin. Will you kindly certify the signature of Mr. Milton H. Lipp, retaining one copy for your files ? /“N Acting Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN BETROISIM COMPANY LIMITED GC/TVW Enel:pbtro; t TAH) limitsd 1$ T oaui« W # Hutton, U*rukzvr, Petrolaiun D«volopw®nt (*atar) f Ltd# # do tolaamly &amp; truly declare that I t * 08 * 4 t&amp;lllar Pistons Type 6f w complete with rubber® I•50* 00 588* 00 herein specified are, to the best of my knowledge &amp; belief, truly and bonafide of the manufacture of the tf*S*A*f that they were -v'-\ exported from the 0.3*A* per a.8.”Hoegh Silverctar” from Loa Angeles on 10th February, 1938, and that they are being returned without having been advanced in value or improved In condition by any process of manufacture or other means* i* g w n it * 80 Rubbers for Millar Pistons 0f' ft * « ft ft « ■ 160. 00 314. 00 94. 00 Signature (Jgdt.J 7 . IV- For MAKAOSK. Declared before me this 9th day of September, 1939 R.B.K.'S POLITICAL AOEBT BAHRAIN.V The Bahrein I’etAoleum Company limited K * w \ Awali , Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. NO:PA-449. September 12, 1939. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent. Bahrein. FBB - 907 — — - „ ■ Return of Syfo Clinograph I enclose herewith Certificate covering one Case containing ’’Syfo Clinograph A-107 Complete” which is being returned to New York for Credit. This has been shipped to Bombay per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. ”BANDRA” on September 11th., thence Via American President Line to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. /“N MI. Acting Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Enel. 1.Enel. 1 VL\ \ The Bahrein petroleum company Limited * A T \\ 5r &gt; Awal i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, £ NO: PA-448. September 12, 1939. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent. Bahrein. TBB - 3009 Return of Gasoline Chamber of Reid Vapour Pressure Apparatus. I enclose herewith Certificate covering one Case containing Gasoline Chamber of Reid Vapour Pressure Apparatus which is being returned to New York. This has been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. ’’BANDRA” on September 11th to Bombay thence Via American President Line to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. MI. Yours very truly, M.H. LIPP Acting Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDEnel. 1. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-446 September 12, 1939. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. Sir, Return of 19 Empty Calol Industrial Gas No.2 Cylinders. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 19 (Nineteen) Empty Calol Industrial Gas Cylinders to San Francisco for Credit. These empties have been shipped to San Francisco per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. !, HOEGH SILVERCLOUD' on August 26th. 1939. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, M.H. LIPP Acting Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED MI.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Enel. 1. Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO:PA-450 September 12, 1939 His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent Bahrein. FBB - 1042 Sir, Return of 107 Oxygen Cylinders I enclose herewith Certificate covering 107 empty Oxygen Cylinders which are being returned to New York for Credit. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. f, BANDRA* , on September 11th. to Bombay, thence Via first available American President Line Steamer to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly Acting Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED MIThe Bahrein petroleum Company limited N0:PA-447. - Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. +' * September 12, 1939. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent. Bahrein. Return of 36 Empty Anhydrous Sir ? Ammonia Cylinders for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 36 (Thirtysix) Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to San Francisco for Credit. These empties have been shipped to San Francisco per M.V. ’’HOEGH SILVER CLOUD' on August 26th. 1939. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. ^ ^ /’L-v'V'V. ^1— * ^ M'* l • /w /*&gt; — ty( L ^ * / U. f 'Zjjf Acting Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Enel 1.No. 1653-5/3. Political Agency, S** 5- Bahrain, the 20th September 1939 To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I enclose t*o copies of an application for a passport brought by Mr. W.M. Clemo for attestation by me. The forms are incomplete in one or two particulars but Mr. Clemo tells me that the inclusion of these is not necessary as he is already in possession of an American passport. I have therefore attested the forms. 2. I am recovering the usual fee of Hs. 5/- through our account with you, but would point out that if it is later found that a fresh application is necessary, another fee of as. 5/- will be charged. Yours faithfully, 4 for Political Agent, Bahrain ^ 'fe'GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. .1521. Dear Weightman, This is a list of certain locally made articles which the Bahrain Government sent to .America in connection with pearl publicity. They were sent through the Bapco. We are now asked for a list, shov/ing price, attested by H.B.M’s Political Agent. I myself made the purchases and paid the money. Would you therefore please supply \ a certificate to that effect. \ I gather that the Customs authorities in U.S.A. have asked for it. Yours sincerely, H. Weightman. Esquire, I.C.G., H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain.( -1 - 1 - - - - - _• r - - : - • V C - . _ • - ■ ~ - . - • • - • - 4 f ;f?i0 . - ; - - - . - - - - . - - - - - . V .D,O.No. 1669-5/3. The 24th September 1939. you please refer to your demi-official letter No. 1521 dated the 20th September 1939 to Mr. Weightman. 2. I enclose herewith one copy of the list duly signed. Will you please also sign the list before forwarding it to the United States of America? Yours sincerely, / C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain.v THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED / Awali: Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, September 30th, 1939. Dear Sir, We enclose herewith signed certificate in respect of Mrs. Victoria Lipp. It would be much appreciated if you could countersign and return the same to us. Yours very truly, M. E. LIPP Acting. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEU!.' Ca.TANY LIMITED. Enel: KG:CLS.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited r NOiPA-' Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, j: &amp;?*!. October 3rd. 1939. 7 - OCT. ^ J » His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Return of 31 Anhydrous Ammonia Sir, Cylinders - For Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 31 (Thirty-one) Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to San Francisco, for Credit. These empties have been shipped to San Francisco per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. 'HENGrKALIS' on September 19th. 1939. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, M.H. LIPP Acting Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED MI. Enel. 1 w* . No. 1759-5/3. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 10th October 1939. To The Air Liaison Officer, Royal Air Force, Bahrain. Memorandum Will you please send me the sum of Rs. 5/- as registration fee for a contract brought to the Agency by Mr. Murray, Works Officer, Bahrain. / h for Political Agent, Bahrain. hi- %t . ■ '3 m THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein. Sir Return of 7 Empty Calol Industrial G-as #2 Cylinders for Credit to San Francisco. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 7 (Seven) Empty Calol Industrial Gas #2 Cylinders to San Francisco for Credit. These empties have been shipped to San Francisco per Silver Java Pacific Line M. V. 'HOEGH SILVERSTAR' on October 12th. 1939. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly THE BA FED MI Enel. 1' f' ■--fT THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, October 19th. 1939 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. CQ Sir, Return of 28 Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to San Francisco for Credit I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 28 (Twenty-eight) Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to San Francisco for Credit. These empties have been shipped to San Francisco per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V.'HOEGH SILVERSTAR t, on October 12th. 1939. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. 111. V : /! Yours very truly, j./^kblack: Chief^Lock]/ Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI. Enel. 1.His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Return of 14 Empty Acetylene Sir, Cylinders to New York for Credit. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 14 (Fourteen) Empty Acetylene Cylinders to New York for Credit. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S.”VARELA” on October 11th to Bombay, thence Via American President Line S.S.”PRESIDENT POLK” on October 21st. to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, MI. tCK Chief Ltrfjaj. Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Enel. 1.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. H. B. i^s Political Agent, Bahrain. kemorandum: - 1 forward herewith a power of attorney authorizing one Shaikh Bassoon bin Shaikh Ali of Kadhemain to act on behalf of heirs of the deceased Shaikh khalaf al x^sfoor for your countersignature. A sum of ^s.S/Q/- representing the usual fee is sent herewith. //tv?- - lt&gt; '2 ) f q &lt;7 Adviser v to the Government. rHo* -5/3. The Agency, Bahrain. ll tL November 1939. To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bn hra in. Memorandum . / * With reference to your memorandum No. 1758/24, dated the 28th October 1939, I return herewith, the power of attorney duly attested. For Political Agent, Bahrain. */ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED / Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO. Pa-542. November 2, 1959. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY 1 S POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. Dear Sir: RETURN OF 28 EMPTY ETHYL FLUID DRUMS. I enclose herewith Certificate in quadruplicate covering twentyeight (28) Empty Ethyl Drums for return to suppliers. These have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co f s s.s. 'BANKURA' on October 24th to Bombay thence via first avail able American President Line Boat to New York. Please return the Certificate in quadruplicate duly attested at your earliest convenience debiting charges in this connection to our account. Yours very truly,THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Asrali: Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, November 14th, 1939• No. PA-552. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein* Dear Sir, I enclose herewith signed certificate of residence in respect of Mr. H. E. Flory* It would be appreciated if you could counter sign and return the same to us* Yours very truly, J. s; BLACK Chief^Local Representative, THE BMREIN PETROLED!! COMPANY LIMITED.The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S POLITICAL AGENT, MANAMA- Bahrein Island. Dear Sir: RETURN OF 4 EMPTY ANHYDROUS AMMONIA CYLINDERS TO NET YORK FOR CREDIT. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 4 (Four) Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders for credit. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S.N.Co's s.s.'BARPETA' on November 3rd to Bombay thence via American President Line s.s.'PRESIDENT GARFIELD' on November 18th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. I i I Yours very truly, THE BAHRE l 1 Representative 'ROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. /SKSM Attach.1The Bahrein petroleum company limited Awal i , Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, MANAMA- Bahrein Island. Dear Sir: RETURN OF 96 EMPTY OXYGEN CYLINDERS FOR CREDIT TO NEU YORK. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 96 (Nintysix) Empty Oxygen Cylinders for credit. These empties have been shipped per B*I.S.N.Co T s s. s.’’BARPETA' on November 3rd to Bombay thence via American President Line s.s.’’PRESIDENT GARFIELD' on November 18th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, Encl.lV; Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. ltd. (incorporated IN ENGt-ANO.) BRANCHES! HEAD OFFICE: 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LON DON E C. 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: “ GRAY ' cooes used: — ENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR. AHWAZ (FOR BANDA R-SHAHPOUR.) BUSHIRE. BUNDER-ABB AS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE L/847. Bahrein, 19th November 39 9 The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Mr. James D. Franz. We enclose herewith a certificate relating to the above seaman ex the T/V. 'MARIDAL”, and shall be pleased if you will endorse and return it to us at your convenience. Yours faithfully, Enc.1.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, ;Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. November 20, 1939. NO: PA-566. POWERS -OF-ATTORNEY . HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, THE AGENCY, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Will you please authenticate Mr. Lipp’s signature on the two substitute Powers-of-Attorney attached. We are also attaching copy of a recent letter to our Home Office in New York which gives a list of powers now in force. Yours very truly, tited. Attachments:(3) DKW:LA.| Awe11 t November 20 f 1939 ■ ^ Nr/.^-675 , ?0 ViLR -Q F-ATTu RN KY . Mr. Wm. Kunstadter, New York. Please refer to your letter No.71 of September 28, 1939, on the above subject. We are returning by slow mall both copies of cancelled powers for Messrs. Davis and Devles as requested In your letter. letter; The two new powers received with your (1) California Texas Oil Co., Ltd., in favour of Messrs. Lipp, Keith, Anderson, Deane and Brown, and (2) California Texas Oil Co.(Overseas) Ltd., in favour of Messrs Lipp, Keith, Anderson, Deane and Brown; have already been registered with the British Political Agent at Bahrein. We are also returning by slow mall both copies of the cancelled powers issued by California Texas Oil Co., Ltd., and California Texas Oil Co.,(Overseas) Ltd. Attached to this letter you will find copies of substitute Power-of-Attorney for the Standard Vacuum Oil Company issued to Messrs. Anderson and Brown. (Continued on page 2)THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED e&amp;' No.PA-558. Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, November 16, 1939. POWERS OF ATTORNEY. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, “Jus- We are attaching two Powers of Attorney as follows: (1) California Texas Oil Co., Ltd., in favour of Messrs. Lipp, Reith, Anderson, Deane and Brown. (2) California Texas Oil Co., Ltd., also in favour of ^viessrs. Lipp, Reith, Anderson, Deane and Brown. Will you please register these two documents and return them letting us know at that time the fees payable for this registration. Yours very truly, DKW:LA. Chief L The Bahrein Pet lCKI Representative, &gt;leum Company Limited ENCLS: 2 Powers of Attorney.-£i a No. 3Sie-5/3 To Political A ncy, Bahrain, the 2nd December 1939. The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. 1 Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No. PA-558 dated the 16th November 1939. 2. Please send to this Agency the sum of Rs. 31/- (thirty one only) representing: the charges for registration of the documents forwarded with your letter referred to above, which is m^de up as under:- Court Fee Stamps - ifc. 5 - 0 - 0 Copying fees - *21-0-0 Linking fees - f , 5-0-0Enel The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited (J Awa li , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. Dear Sir: REFERENCE OUR TBB-395S. RETURN OF 11 EMPTY ACETYLENE CYLINDERS FOR REFILLING AND RETURN. I enclose herevdth Certificate covering return of 11 (Eleven) Empty Acetylene Cylinders to New York for refill ing and return. These empties have been shipped per B.I*S.N. Co’s s. s. Tt VARELA” on November 21st to Bombay thence via American President Line s.s.”PRES. MONROE” on December 2nd to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account Yours very truly, /SKSM THE J Chief Logs BAHREIN PE epre sentative, COMPANY LIMITEDThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT BAHREIN. NO.PA-593 Dear Sir: I enclose herewith Certificate covering return Awali RETURN OF 23 EMPTY ACETYLENE CYLINDERS FOR CREDIT TO NEW YORK Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, cernher 4, 1939 of 23 (Twentythree) Empty Acetylene Cylinders to New York for credit. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co’s s.s.'VARELA” on November 21, 1939 to Bombay thence via American President Line s.s.'PRES. MONROE' on December End to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our accountEnel The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO.PA-595 HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. Pear Sir: TBB - 3124 RETURN OF TWO DEFECTIVE R.S.A. A.C.UNITS TO NEW YORK FOR CREDIT. I enclose herewith Certificate covering two Frigidaire, Model R.S.A. Portable A.C. Units which are being returned to New York for credit. These have been shipped per B.I.S.N.Co’s s.s.'VARELA” on November 21, 1939 to Bombay thence via 'PRESIDENT MONROE' on December 2nd to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. ^ Yours very truly, /SKSM Chief^ftSial Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Enel. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. Dear Sir: RETURN OF EIvPTY CALOL INDUSTRIAL GAS #2 CYLINDERS. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 12 (Twelve) empty Calol Industrial Gas #2 Cylinders to U.3.A. for credit. These empties have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line M.S.'TOSARI' on December 1, 1939 to San Francisco. Please return the Certificate duly attested at ygur convenience debiting charges in connection to our feccount. \ Yours very truly, /SKSM “ j. TblaCk Chief LCfc? vL Representative the Bahrein petroleum company limitedEnel. The Bahrein petroleum company limited \wal i Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO.PA-600. v U /o December 7, 1939. ' ' ' ■ * T v v ‘ HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. Dear Sir: RETURN OF EMPTY ANHYDROUS AMMONIA CYLINDERS TO SAN FRANCISCO FOR CREDIT. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 19 tNineteen) Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to U. 3. A. for credit. These empties have been shipped via Silver Java Pacific Line M.3.'T0SARI' on December 1, 1959 to San Francisco. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. a Yours very truly, ' 2 /SKSM ,ACK Chlef-TTcicrfl Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED * m No. PA-598 A w a 1 i Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, December 6, 1939 Fees for Registration of Powers of Attorney His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, The Agency, Manama. t Dear Sir, A 73 We acknowledge with thanks receipt of your letter No.2112-5/3 of 2nd December and the enclosed registered Powers of Attorney. We enclose herewith our cheque to value of Rs.3l/- * as requested. ) 17 . 0 Yours very truly, ;k Chief Local/Representative, The BcOirein Petroleum Company Ltd, JSB:LA. Enel: 1 Cheque - Rs.3l/- 1 &lt;P5 m p# c4ri 11 riMHf &gt; ^THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED . * c »vN c -0° NO.PA-616. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S POLITICAL AGENT, MANAMA - Bahrein Island. Dear Sir: RETURN OF 9 EMPTY FREON CYLINDERS. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 9 (Nine) Empty Freon (Dichlorodifluoromethane) Cylinders to U*S.A. for credit. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co*s s.s.'BARALA' on December 11th to Bombay, thence via American President Line s.s. Tt PRES. BUREN’’ on December , 30th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. / SK3Mk THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED \ NO.PA-617. Awa 1 i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, 23 OK. 1939 December ?2, 1-839* 77? HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, L A N A M A - Bahrein Island. Dear Sir: RETURN 0? 20 EMPTY ACETYLENE CYLINDERS. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 20 (Twenty) Empty Acetylene Cylinders to U. S. A. for credit. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S^N.Co’s s.s. Tt VITA” on December 20th to Bombay, thence via American President Line ’’PRESIDENT VAN BUREN” on December 30th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our ac count. Yours very truly,NO. PA-618. December 22, 1939. HIS BRITANNIC 1LUESTY T S POLITICAL AGENT, M ANA U A - Bahrein Island. Dear Sir: RETURN OF 21 EMPTY ANHYDROUS AMMCNIA CYLINDERS. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 21 (Twentyone) Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to U.3.A. for credit. These empties have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line m.v.'DJAM3I' on December 21st to San Francisco. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our Account. Enel. / SK3M. Yours very truly, Chief, _ THE BAHREXlfFE BEaCK Representative LEUM COMPANY LIMITED.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. ivy NO.PA-619 December 22, 1939. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, MANAMA - Bahrein Island. Dear Sir: RETURN OF 20 EMPTY CALOL INDUSTRIAL GAS ^8 CYLINDERS. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 20 (Twenty) Empty Calol Industrial Gas '^2 Cylinders to U.3.A. for credit. These empties have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line m.v.'DJAMBI' on December 21st to San Francisco. your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Please return the Certificate duly attested at Yours very truly, Enel. / SK3M[ ✓ i The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awa 1 i , Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. NO.PA-656. January 16 , 1940 . HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, MANAMA. Dear Sir: RETURN OF 51 EMPTY ETHYL FLUID DRUMS. I enclose herewith Certificate in quadruplicate covering fiftyone (51) Empty Ethyl Drums for return to suppliers. These have been shipped per B.I.S.N.Co’s s. s. T *VARS0VA” on Jan. 14th to Bombay, thence via ’’PRESIDENT HAYES” on January 27th to New York. Please return the Certificate in quadruplicate duly attested at your earliest convenience debiting charges in connection to our account• // /* LtsO . / SKSM Yours very trul M. H. LIPF Ag* Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Ends .4the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No« PA-661* January 22, 1940. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ POLITICAL AGENT Bahrein. Dear Sir, We enclose signed certificate of residence in respect of Mr. W.R. Gentry. It would be appreciated if you could counter sign and return to us. Yours very truly. Acting Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM C CMP ANY LIMITED. Enel DAGSiKSthe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No. PA-662. January 22, 1940. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AG-ENT, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We enclose signed certificate of residence A ' in respect of Mr. J.E. Creecy. It would be appreciated if you could counter sign and return to us. Yours very truly. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Ends DAGSSiKSthe Bahrein petroleum Company Limited ? Awali t Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No* PA-677» January 28, 1940. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrein* Dear Sir, We enclose signed certificate of residence in respect of Mr. J. Domercq, Jr. It would be appreciated if you could counter sign and return to us* Yours very truly. Enel: DAGS:KS. Acting Chief Local Represent at ire THE BAHREIN PETROLEIH COJPANY LIMITED:The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited s- Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. NO.PA-685. February 3, 1940. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, MANAMA- Bahrein Island. Pear Sir: SHIPMENT OF 45 DRUMS OF U.O.P. H INHIBITOR I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 45 (Fortyfive) Drums of No.4 U.O.P. Inhibitor to U.S.A. These are being shipped per B.I.S.N.Co’s s.s.'VARSOVA' on February 4th to Bombay thence via American President Line 'PRESIDENT POLK' on or about February 14th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our Account. 2 / SKSM Yours very truly, SS . M. H. LIPP Ag. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel,THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awal i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, '7 ^ NO.PA-687. February 5, 1940. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. De ar Sir: OUR REFERENCE T3B-4183. RETURN OF 13 EMPTY ACETYLENE CYLINDERS FOR REFILLING AND RETURN. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 13 (Thirteen) Empty Acetylene Cylinders to New York for refilling and return. These empties have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co’s s^.’^ITA” on January 28th 1939, to Bombay thence via American President Line s.s.'PRESIDENT POLK' on February 15th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Ag. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COLIP ANY LIMITED. /SKSM EnelTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, February 8, 1940. No. FA-692. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrein* Dear Sir, We enclose signed certificate of residence in respect of Mr. M. H. Lipp. It would be appreciated if you could counter sign and return to us. Yours very truly. M. H. LIPP Acting Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED: Enel: DAGS :KS■ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED -Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No. PA- 715. February 15, 1940* HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrein• Dear Sir, * I am enclosing herewith a declaration signed by Mr. M.H. Lipp, General Manager of The Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd., covering damage sustained by Bapco IY one of the Company's barges and would request you to be good enough to countersign returning to us. Enel: JSB :KSTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO.PA-736. February 29, 1940. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: OUR REFERENCE TBB-4241 RETURN OF TWENTYSIX EMPTY ACETYLENE CYLINDERS TO NEW YORK FOR REFILLING &amp; RETURN. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 26 (Twentysix) Empty Acetylene C 3 r linders to New York for refilling and return. These cylinders have been shipped per B.I.S.N.Co's s.s.'BAMDRA' on February 25th to Bombay thence via American President Line s.s.'PRES.GARFIELD' on March 14th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. /SKSM Enel.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Enel Awali , Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf NO.PA-735. February 29, 1940. His Britannic Majesty * 1 s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sirs: RETURN OF THIRTYFOUR CANS OF BUTTER. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 34 (Thirtyfour) Cans of Butter to New YorA. These cans have been shipped per the B.I.S.N.Co’s s.s.'BAMORA' on February 25th to Bombay thence via Anerican President Line 'PRES.GARFIELD' on March 14th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, /SKSM Ch THE BAHREIN ACK Representative, ?R0LEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Enel THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf i i* 0 NO.PA-734. February 29, 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: RETURN OF SIX EMPTY OXYGEN CYLIN DERS TO NEV/ YORK FOR CREDIT. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 6 (Six) Empty Oxygen Cylinders to New York for credit. These cylinders have been shipped per B.I.S.N.Co’s s.s. ”BAM0RA rT on February 25th to Bombay thence via American President Line s.s. tf PRE3. GARFIELD” on March 14th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. /SKSM Yours very truly, Chi THE BAHREIN ial Representative, tOLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, March 5, 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Manama - Bahrein Island. Dear Sir: TBB - 4251 RETURN OF 518 EMPTY OXYGEN CYLINDERS. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 318 (Three Hundred and Eighteen) Empty Oxygen Cylinders to U.S.A. for refilling and return in accordance with our requisition TBB-4251 referred to above. These empties have been shipped per the Silver Java Pacific Line s.s* TT E0EGH SILVERCLOUD” on March 1st to San Francisco. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Encl.l Yours very truly, Chief THE BAHREIN jACK Representative, ’ROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awal i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, March 5, 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, MANAMA - Bahrein Island. Dear Sir: RETURN OP 22 EMPTY ANHYDROUS AMMONIA CYLINDERS. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 32 Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to U.S.A for return to suppliers. These empties have been shipped per the Silver Java Pacific Line T, H0EGH SILVERCLCUD” on March 1st Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly. Enel.1THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, March 6, 1940* His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: OUR REFERENCE TBB-4328 RBTUAN Off 12 StiPTY ACSTYT.KTPTcyLIWDERS TO NE'.V YORK. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 12 (Twelve) Empty Acetylene Cylinders to New York for refilling and return in accordance with our requisition TBB-4328. These cylinders have been shipped per the B.I.S.N.Co’s s.s. Tt BANDRA w on March 4th to Bombay thence via The American President Line, 'PRESIDENT MONROE' on or about March 23rd to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Enel. /SKSM. Yours very truly, Chi THE BAHREIN jal Representative, LOLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.the Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali # Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No. PA-748. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S POLITICAL AG-3NT, 3alire in. Dear Sir, We enclose signed certificate of residence in respect of Mr. CJ.1. Cutbirth. It would be appreciated if you could counter sign and return to us. Yours very truly. Chief -Loc^l Representative TH3 S^^IirPSTROIOTi COMPANY LTDTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A W a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, March 10, 1940 No ♦PA-752# H. Weightraan, Esq*, I.C.S* His Britannic Majesty f s Political Agent, Manama, Bahrein Island. Dear Sir, I herewith enclose a declaration signed by Mr. W. P. Anderson on behalf of Mr. M. H. Lipp relative to the Company’s barge known as n BAPC0 5 ,f and would request you to be good enough to countersign and return same to us. Yours very truly, Chief The Bahrein P lCK Representative, iroleum Company Limited. RESW:LA. Uc Ends :1No .486 Political Agency, Bahrain. 13th March, 1940 f ( tG £&gt; V. To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Oil Company, Limited, Bahrain . Dear Sir, Will you please forward the sum of Hs.10/- to this Agency on account of fees on +,wo powers of attorney registered on the 17th February, 1940. Yours faithfully, C/L for Political Agent, Bahrain. /C IfThe Bahrein petroleum Company limited Dear Sir, We are attaching two original Powers-of-Attorney one given by California Texas Oil Company, Limited and the other given by California Texas Oil Company (Overseas) Limited to Mr. Julius 0. Fifer. Will you please register the same, and return them to us at your convenience together with a note of the fees payable for registration? Yours very truly, .Ends: 2 3All. AOM Mr Ml AM&lt;&gt; Vs TO UK AIMiMKSsKlt lo TIIK Cl &gt;M I’.WV ANGLO-IRANIAN OIL COMPANY, LIMITED. TKI-KI.RAI'HIC AlIDKKSS ■■ AXGI.IKW ' ABADAN, NO. 427/23 DATED . KHUZiSTAN, IRAN February 1940 H.B.M'3 POLITICAL AGLNT 3AHKAIN. AGENT, Sir KHAN SAHEB HaJI YOUSEF BIN flHIvED ^iNQO, C.I.E^. B.E. ,K.T.N. bold Title Deed Registered No .369 - Tapu No .33 for the year 1353 covering property mortgaged to us by tne above named as security for certain loans. The Title Deed includes one plot of land shown as containing colfee shops whereas the Deed of Mortgage made on 20th March 193 d and registered in the Agency Books under No.2 of 193^ states that two buildings leased to Petroleum Concessions Ltd. have been erected on the site and these have also been mortgaged to us. »Ve shall be glad if you w ill Kindly inform us whether any action is necessary on our part to amend the Title Deed to bring it into line with the Deed of Mortgage we have the honour to be, For ANGLO-IRANIAN OIL CO. LTD Your obedient servants, // GENERA L MAN AGER .No. pSt -6/3 Po3.iuical Agency, Bahrain. 21st T'sei’ch, 1940 To The Mviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. I fenscrgndum. In 1938 Kiv^n ^hib v H 9 uf bin Ahmd Kanoo mortgaged come oi' his properties in Bahrain to the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Limited. 2. The Title Deed No.389 - Tapu No.33 of 1363 - includes one p::ot of land shown as containing coffee shops, whereas the Deed of mortgage made on the 'Oth Varch 1938, states that two buildings leased to Petroleum Concessions Limited have been erected cn the site and have been included in the mortgage 3. ‘'Quid you please let me know if any action is necessary on the part of the Angl-Iranian Oil Company, Timiteh, to have the Title Deed amended so as to bring it into line with the Deed of mortgage.03 vcy,-) No.571/5/3 Political Agency, Bahrain. 27th March, 1940. To The Chief Local Representative! The Bahrain Petroleum Company f Limited, Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No.PA-756 dated the 14th March, 1940. 1 return herewith the two Powers of Attorney duly registered. The following charges have been incurred on this account: Copying fee Registation fee fc . 21 - 0-0 To«l-tei?H£§ 3. Would you please refund this amount to me as soon as possible. ¥ Nj Yours faithfully, , for Political Agent, Bahrain.No.653-5/3 Political Agency, Bahrain. 4th April, 1940. To The Genera1 M&amp;nager, AprI o-Iranian Oil Company, Abadan. Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No.4P7/23 dated the B7th Pebruery 1940. 2. As the title for the land includes any buildings which r&amp;ay be erected upon it, there is no need to amend the original title deed for land mortgaged to your Company by Khan Gabib Yusuf bin Ahmad Karoo. Yours faithfully, (A- for Political Agent, nhrain.c^' e&amp;’- THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED it w a 1 i , a / Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, PA - 830 April 9, 1940. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear 8ir, FILS jj/&amp;35 AGMCY ^GRtiEviMT we are attaching the original Agency Agreement between this Company and Holmes-Naught on &amp; Co., Karachi. Will you please register the same and return to us at your convenience together with the note of the fee payable for registration. Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. Rncl:Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENOI.ANO,) BRANCHES! HEAD OFTICE: 122, LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON, E C. 3. telegraphic address; ' GRAY ' cooes used: BENT LEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE ^*^'NTLEVS SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH. AM ARAM. KUT. KHORAMSH AHR. AHWAZ (FOR BANDAR-SHAH POUR.) BU5HI RE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SH ARJ AH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. L/305 . Bahrein, 17th April, ig^O. The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, SHEIKH MOHAMMED KAKA We enclose herewith a declaration in duplicate signed by the above in the presence of the writer, and shall be obliged if you will kindly countersign and return same to us in due course. The above man is now employed by us on our Tug 'RAS TANURA ,t , and is unable to present himself at your office, as the Tug 'RAS TANURA” is plying between Al Khobar and Zallag. This declaration is required by Messrs. Anglo- Iranian Oil Co.,Ltd., who were this man^ former employees. Yours faithfully, WU A S Enc.2. 4 O' ^ Aa—VNo. &lt;fO -5/3 The Political Agent* Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: — The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company, Limited, Bahrain* f ■ in original and has the honour to send him aXX^KXXXthe undermentioned document (/) duly registered. The following charges have been incurred tn this accounts- Copying fee R$.7/-/- Registration fee h$.2/8/ - The Agency, Total ru. 0 / 8 /^ BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. D , ted 23rd April, 1940. -']? I?e 2 Iei’ence to previous c^&gt;rrespondence: PA-830 dated the 9th April, 1940. * Description Of Enclosure, X Name and Date. Subject. Agency Agreement between the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited and Holmes-Naught on * &amp; Co., Karachi. Registration of documents. l ’ 1IP^aCRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; CO. LTD. 4 ' (INCORPORATED IN EN9L.AND.) BRANCHES! VA HEAD OFFICE: 122, LEADENHALL STREET. LON DON, E C. 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS; “GRAY” CODES USED! BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH. AM ARAM. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR. AHWAZ (FOR BANOAR-SH AHPOUR.) BUSHIRE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SH ARJ AH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE no L/323. BAHREIN. Bahrein, 23rd April, 19 40. Dear Sir, fjtr SHEIKH MOHAMMED KAKA Reference our letter No.L^SOB of the 17th instant, kindly return to us the declaration forwarded to you in duplicate, as the above now informs us that he re quires one month’s notice pay from the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co.Ltd. P.L. No. 0-5/3 dated 29th April, 1940, issued to Gray Tackenzie, enclosing declaration Jheikh TT ohammed I aka. rl*' UC‘THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, March 23, 1940 No. PA-769. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrein. Dear Sir, Vie enclose signed certificate of residence in respect of Mr. D. K. Wallace. It would be appreciated if you could counter sign and return to us. Yours very truly Enel: DAGSJKS.the Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, March 23, 1940. Bahrein, Dear Sir, We enclose signed certificate of residence in respect of Mr. R. M. Brown. It would be appreciated if you could counter sign sind return to us. Yours very truly. Enel: DAGSiKS.the Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, March 24, 1940 No. PA-775. HIS BRITANNIC MATESTY*S POLITICAL ACrENT, Bahrein. Bear Sir, We enclose signed certificate of residence in respect of Mr. J. P. Bergeron. It would be appreciated if you could counter sign and return to us. Yours very truly Chief THE BAHREIN PETROLEiLI COMPANY LTD: Enel: DAGSsKSTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED No. PA-815. HIS BRITMNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, - r Bahrein* Dear Sir, We enclose signed certificate of residence It would be appreciated if you could oounter- Awali: Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf in respect of Mr. W. C. Field. sign and return to us* Yours very truly Chie THE BAHRE _ Enel: One. DAGS:CDSmmmm THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali: Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. / t 1 ZZi April 4th, 1940, No. PA-814. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, B a h r e in. Dear Sir, We enclose signed certificate of residence in respect of Mr. G. H. Everett. It would be appreciated if you could counter sign and return to us# Yours very truly, Chie THE BAHREIN Representative, tOLEOM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel: One DAGS: CDS.A p THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 1 i * t * Li Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf NO.P^-822. April 6 , 1940. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Manama - Bahrein Island. RETURN OF SIXTEEN EMPTY ANHYDROUS AMMONIA CYLINDERS FOR CREDIT. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of 16 (Sixteen) Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to U.3.A. for credit. These empties have been shipped per the Silver lava Line M.V.'BENGEALIS' on April 6 th 1940 to San Francisco. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account# Yours very truly, Chie TEE BAHREIN &gt;al Representative, LOLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel. /SKSMTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED vV O N c&lt; ^ NT 0 '*’ Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf April 16, 1940 ■ • L T 0, PA- 841 ; His Britemnic Majesty’s lolitical A^ent, Bahrein* Dear Sir: As requested we send herewith Rs, 7. 8 . o being your fees for the attestation of Mrs* D* F# Kellenberg*s application forms for amendment of her Passport* Yours very truly. DAGS:STHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED NO:PA-847 \ Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, April 17th. 1940 A w a 1 i . His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. Sir Our Ref. Sh.Notice Nos.4-17,4-18,4-19 Return of Empty Cylinders to New York. I enclose herewith three (3) Certificates covering return of : - 15 - Empty Acetylene Cylinders. 2 - Empty Liquid Chlorine Cylinders, and 1 - Empty Nitrogen Cylinder. to New York. They have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. ’’VARELA’* on April 15th to Bombay thence Via The American President Line ’’PRESIDENT VAN BUREN’’ on or about April 26th to New York. Please return the Certificates duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in this connection to our account. Yours very truly MI Enel. 3./ it THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i . w / \ „ X * 1 ' Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, KO:Pa-858. u April 23, 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of one Zeiss Ikoflex Camera, Lens No.1990995 to London. It is the property of Mr. D. S. Hammond, 227 North Woodside Road, Glasgow , was received here after he had left this Company’s employ and is accordingly being returned to him per Registered Parcel Post on April 23rd. 1940. at your convenience, debiting charges in this connection to our account. Please return the Certificate duly attested, Yours very truly MI Enel. 1.aio. 847-5/3 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: i The Chief Local Representative, The Bahmin Petroleoii Company Limited, Bahra ii, * and has the honour to send hin^J^hp^iPtVi^undermentioned document ( /) duly attsisted. A sum of hs«5/- being the attestation fee iz&amp;y kindly be remitted as soon as possible• The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 2?th A P ril &gt; 1940 ' Keterence to previous correspondence: Desvnptidn df Enclosure* Name and Date. Subject. Attested application for passport of Mrs. Kennedy.The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments tor — Personal Department, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. \ . and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document /s) tor arranging payment as soon as possible. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated r:9th April, 1940. Reference to previous correspondence: Desiript'idn df Enclosure* Name and Date. Subject. Bill for iis.10/- a/c Vre. M.Thornburg and N.A. Janke.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED PA - 864 H.B.M’s Political age: Baiirein. A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, April 27, 1S40. FILB ^835 HEGIoTHATION 05’ DOCUMaNTB Dear Sir, &gt; \ Receipt is acknov/ledged of your connmiication No.807-5/3 of 23rd instant enclosing original agency ^greeiuent betv/een The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited and Holmes-Naught on &amp; Co. Karachi which has been duly registered. As requested we hand you herewith cheque for Rs.9-8-0 in payment of charges incurred on account of this registration, and your receipt, in course, will oblige. Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COLPANY LIMITED. AttachmentHis Britannic Bahrein. Sir, I obtai„ Authority from your .1 Agent i. I pv Bahrein, I,!ay 18 th. 1940. goodself in favour of Mr. Mohd Ibrahim, on August 10th 1939, authorizing him to arrange sale of my one house at Amritsar. Since that time my Special Lawful Attorney - Mr. Mohd Ibrahim could not sell the house for me and I am now informed that he is able to dispose it off but on his presentation of the Letter of Authority referred to above to the Law Courts at Amritsar, he has been advised by legal authorities that they are unable to accept this Authorization as valid for the following reasons : 1) Its time has now expired. &amp; 2) It should have been attested by the Registerar at Bahrein. Kindly advise me, at your earliest convenience, your ruling on this so that I could undergo necessary steps for obtaining the correct Authorization to suit our demand. For your information, I am attaching herewith the said Letter of Authority which is recently sent back to me by Mr. Mohd Ibrahim, for the purpose. Thanking you in anticipation of your valued orders. I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant RAHMAT ULLAH Purchase &amp; Stores Dept., Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited A W A L I - Bahrein.-—I r~ ■.» t hC e&amp;'' THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, May 4th. 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Our Ref. Sh.Notice No.4-31 Sir, Return of Defective Purox Liquid Air Containers. v 1 enclose herev/ith Certificate covering return of two ’’Defective Purox - 15 Liter Liquid Air Containers to New York. These have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. ’’YARSOVA” on April 28th to Bombay thence Via The American President Line S.S. ’’PRESIDENT HARRISON” to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your earliest convenience, debiting charges in this connection to our account. Yours very truly, lCK Chief irtfc&amp;L/Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI. Enel. 1.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED / S ^ Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, A w a 1 i , NO:FA-875. May 6 th. 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, Our Ref. Sh.Notice Nos.4-55 &amp; 4-36 : Return of Empty Cylinders to San Francisco I enclose herewith two (2) Certificates covering return of : - 22 - Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders &amp; 2 - Empty Oxygen Cylinders. to San Francisco. They have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V.'H0EGH SILVERSTAR” on May 3rd. 1940. Please return the Certificates duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, THE BA. ITED MI. Enel. 2.The Bahrein petroleum Company limited A w a 1 ii Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf May 9, 1940. FILS 800.15 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, With reference your letter No.847-5/3 dated April 28, 1940 and letter No.856/5/3 dated April 29» 1940, we send you herewith our cheque No.3546 for Rs.15/- in payment of attestation fees as desired. Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLECM COMPANY LIMITED. AttachmentGray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. ltd IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE BUSREH, 122. LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON, E C. 3. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR. AHWAZ (FOR BAHREIN. No. L/354 KOWEIT. GRAY BANDAR-SHAH POUR.) BUSHIRE. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. Bahrein, 7th kay, 19 40 The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, We are sending Sheikh Mohamed Kaka to your office for the purpose of signing the attached declaration which is required by his former employers Messrs. Anglo Iranian Oil Company Ltd. Kindly return the declaration to us duly counter signed. Yours faithfully,Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) HEAD OFFICE: 122, LEADEN HALL STREET. LONDON.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: /■^BENTLEYS COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BRANCHES: BUSREH. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ (for BANDAR-SHAH POUR) BUSH I RE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LI NG AH. BAH REIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. hC3/^ 87&gt; Bahrein* 9th May. 192 40 The political Agent, Bahrein* Dear Bir, *i/e enclose herewith the sum of to. 2 / 8 /- being declaration fee for Bheikh Mohammed Kaka. Yours faithfully, Encl:- SB.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, May 26th. 1940. I His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Our Ref. Sh.Notice #5-11. Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of one 'Westinghouse S-990285 CLS-1320 Compressor equipped with 220 Volt Motor”, to New York. This has been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S. S. ’’VARSOVA” on May 20th to Bombay thence Via The American President Line S.S. ”PRES. POLK” to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in this connection to our account. Yours very truly, MI. THE Chi BAHREIN BLACK Repre sentative tOLSUM' COMPANY LIMITED Enel. 1THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali » Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf May 30th 1940 No* PA-917♦ H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrein* Dear Sir, We enclose signed certificate of residence in respect of Mr* J* McFarlane* It would be appreciated if you could counter sign and return to us* Yours Tory truly Chi&lt; THE BA_■The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Avail f Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf May 30th 1940. No. PA-916. H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We enclose signed certificate of residence in respect of Mr. D. Gheno. It would be appreciated if you could counter sign and return to us. Yours very truly Sncl^O' v c° THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. NO:PA-930. June 8 th. 1940. His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, Bahrein. Our Ref. Sh. Notice No.5-8 : Return of Empty Cylinders to San Francisco. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of twelve (12) Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to San Francisco. They have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line M.S. 'TARAKAN' on June 4th. 1940. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, Chief THE BAHREIN PE l 1 Representative [OLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel. 1THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED NB:PA-929. Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. A w a 1 i , June 8 th. 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir Our Ref. Sh.Notice No.5-7 : Return of 4-1/2” Breaking Substitutes to Los Angeles. I enclose Certificate covering return of : 75 - 4-1/2”, 16.60# type IF Heat Treated Alloy, Breaking Substitutes. to Los Angeles. They have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line M.S. tt TARAKAN ,f on June 4th. 1940. Please return the Certificate, duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, J. S. BLACK Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI Enel. 1 .rranslation of a letter dated 5th June 1940 from Ramadhan, ^ bin ^uhamad ^adiq ^azeruni to the Political Agent, Bahrain. I beg to state that on the 4th Rabi I, 1351 I made a vvill which was registered in the Agency under ^0.13 of 1932 on the 12 th &lt;^uly 1932. 1 should be grateful if you would kindly consider that will as null and void and cancel it as I have made another will on the 22nd Rabi II, 1359. A *C • U. E.No.112?~o/3 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:*'- The Personnel Popart,!lento Bahrain Petroleum Company Lind ted, Bahrain *. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undsrmentioned document tne remark that she should sign on page 3 of her passport v/hich 4 until she docs so is jfnvalid• The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated l^th June, I940* #&gt; &gt;&gt;«&gt; w ***** Reference to previous correspondence: Descnpl'idn dj Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. American passport No*45966 of Jewell Minty Chambers Ariaendiuent of passport. 2 . Carriage cartificate together vith application for amendment of passport an triplicate.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED NO:PA-957. A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. June 20th. 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Return of one 54” Quadruple Sir, Link Chain to New York. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of : 1 - 54” Quadruple Link Chain, Part #A-66-108L for Ingersoll-Rand XVG Compressor. to New York. It is being despatched today per Parcel Post to New York for return to Suppliers for Credit being wrong part supplied. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, Chie THE BAHREIN P BLACK fal Representative 'OLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI. Enel. 1./V Please note that an appointnent has been made for you with His Britannic liajesty’s Political Agent ^ ■ on to carry out Notarial work requested. Please attend at his office at the appointed time with necessary cash to pay fees. ? 19^-0 in order PERSONNEL DBPARTt SNT — JSB'.KS.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i» Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, July 7, 1940 PA - 979 FILE 8&lt; His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, / //£? Bahrein. \ ^ ) Dear Sir, We enclose three copies of our Note of Protest covering possible damage to Barge Bapco II in an accident during June. Vie should appreciate your confirming the signature and authority on two of these copies returning same to us in due course• The third copy may be retained for your files Yours very truly, CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Attachment.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a X i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, July 7th, 1940 NOTE 0? PROTEST I, W.P, ANDERSON, Acting Manager, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited and representative of the owners of the steel barge called the rt BAPC0 II' hereby certify that on the fourth day of June 1940, said barge, towed by the motor tug 'HAS TANURA', having departed from the Port of A1 Khobar, Saudi Arabia on the fourth day of June en route for the Port of Zellaq, Bahrein Island, which destination was not reached until the sixth day of June, and having on board a cargo of 5,612.73 barrels crude oil, did during said voyage run aground and fearing damage I now note my protest to serve and avail me hereafter as occasion may require, reserving to If the to extend the same at will. THE BAHREIN PETROLM' COMPANY LIMIIED I confirm the above signature and authority. For ManagerTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED ( 13 ' J. A w a 1 i , © Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. NO:PA-992. July 15th. 1940 His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent. Bahrein. Sir, Our Ref. Sh.Notice #6-15 &amp; 6-16. Return of Empty Cyls. to San Francisco. I enclose herewith two (2) Certificates covering return of : 21 - Empty Calol Industrial G-as #2 Cylinders. &amp; 37 - Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders, to San Francisco. They have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. ’’TOSARr* on July 14th. 1940. your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Please return the Certificates duly attested at Yours very truly Chief Local Representative. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI. Enel. 2.V The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, July E4, 1940. PA -8 H.B.M’s Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein Island. Dear Sir: Thank you for your letter No.1391-5/3 of 22 nd July 1940, returning the enclosures to our letter No. PA-992. The certificates are returned herev/ith for attesting, having been duly signed by the declarer. Yours very truly, ’ 6 . A. r5MTSl)Y Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY L INI TED Certificate of original (in duplicate) returned duluy countersigned under P.L. No•1436—5/3 dated 28-7-40. ;£«£&gt;'■ ^ o” /-v the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awall: Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No. PA-16. Political Bahrein. Dear Sir, We enclose sigied certificate of residence in respect of Mr. N. E. Matthews. It would be appreciated if you could counter- si gi and return to us. Yours very truly, Enel: THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTDTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf N0:PA-14. July 29th. 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Our Ref,Sh.Notice 6-3 &amp; 6-4 : Return Sir, of Bmpty Cylinders to New York. I enclose herewith three (3) Certificates covering return of : - 7 - Empty Acetylene Cylinders. 3 - ,f Freon n &amp; 3 - M Liquid Chlorine Cylinders. to New York. These have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. ’’BAMORA” on July 23rd. to Bombay, thence Via first available American President Line boat to New York. Please return the Certificates duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, —i R. A. KENNEDY Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI. Enel. 3. '£ua~sua&lt;) J/. 7. c *THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED &gt;SS / L i2 Sir, Our Ref. Sh.Notices Nos.7-9 &amp; 7-10. Return of Empty Cylinders to San Francisco.; I enclose herewith two (2) Certificates covering return of : - 8 - Empty Calol Industrial Gas #2 Cylinders. &amp; 15 - Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders. to San Francisco. They have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. ,r H0EGH SILVERDAWN' on July 27th. 1940. Please return the certificates duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. MI. Yours very truly, T. A.' KEMKET Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN FETROLEmi COMPANY LIMITED. H Enel. 2.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, August 27th. 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Our Ref. Sh.Notice No. 8-6 : Return Sir, of 2-3/4 tf McCullough dun Perforator and Parts. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return to Los Angeles of : - 1 - 2-3/4 Tf McCullough dun Perforator and parts for 2-3/4 Tt , 3-1/2” &amp; 4-7/16” McCullough dun Perforators. which have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. ”3ILVERBEECH” sailed hence on August 24th. 1940. * Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, R. A. KENNEDY Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI. Enel. 1 .THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, / J 157/ l August E7th. 1940. Vi- l r&gt; His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Our Ref. Sh.Notice No.8-7 : Return of Empty Anhydrous Ammonia C y linders. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return to San Francisco, of : - 27 - Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders. which have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. 'SILVERBEHCH” sailed hence on August 24th. 1940. x Please return the Certificate, duly attested, at your earliest convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Ypurs very truly, R. A. KENNEDY Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED MI. Enel. 1 K lTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED J NO:PA-65 A A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, August 27th. 1940. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. / Hi 5&lt;P Sir, Our Ref. Sh.Notices Nos.8-11 &amp; 8-12. covering I enclose herewith two Certificates/return of : - * r 3 - Defective Tank Cleaning Machines. 1 - Defective R.S.A. Air Conditioner Unit. to New York. These have been shipped per S.S. 11 STEEL WORKER ' 1 on August 22nd. 1940. Please return the two Certificates, duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. I MI. Enel. 2. Yours very truly, R. A. KENNEDY Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED $ t S&amp;AS***A~*t 3 * J'ifO y 11 /IThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited A w a 1 i , Bat NO:71. 0 ‘ ' &gt; His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. m Sir, Our Ref. Sh.Notices Nos.8-9 &amp; 8-10. Return of Empty Cylinders to New York. r I enclose herewith two Certificates covering return to New York of : - which have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s 3.S. ’’BAMORA” sailed hence on August 27th. 1940, with transhipment at Bombay via first available American President Line Steamer. Please return the Certificates, duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. 9 - Empty Acetylene Cylinders. &amp; 22 - Empty Freon Cylinders. I Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM R. A. KENNEDY. f Chief Local Representative EIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. HI. £ Enel.The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited A w a 1 5 , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, September 8 , 1940. - 97 File 801 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, MAN A M A. i*' Dear Sir, V/e enclose herewith three copies each of two ITotes of Protest made by Mr. ? T .H. Lipp in connection with recent accidents to our marine equipment. Would you please certify the signature of Mr. lipp on all six copies and return them to us at your convenience. Yours very truly, R.A. KENNEDY, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM CO., LTD. Attachments:-fr-f 0 ** ' ' THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED iWali '• Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, IJO. EA-H5* Sept^aber 14, 1940. s political iigent, Bahrein* Dear Sir, MR. M. H. UPP We enclose herewith passport application foi£k&gt; on behalf of the above and it would be very much appre ciated if you would complete where marked. Charges should be deducted from our deposit. Yours very truly, 'V THE R. A. KENNEDY Chief Local Representative BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LED:THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. NO.PA-155. Awali, Sept.23, 1940. H.B.M’s Political Agent Bahrein Island, PERSIAN GULF. File #855 POWERS-OF-ATTOHRZy Dear Sir, We are attaching the original Power-of-Attorney given by The Texas Company (China) Limited to Messrs^.M.H.Lipp, W.P.Anderson and J.T.Deane. Will you please register, and return to us at your convenience together with note of the fees payable for registration. Yours very truly Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM CO.LIMITEDNo.1851-5/3 Political Agency, Bahrain. 2nd October, 1940 To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Reference your letter No.rA-135 dated the 23rd September, 1940• &lt;&lt;* «*-« 2. The Power of Attorney is returned herewith duly registered. Registration fee (fis*14/-) has beer, debited to your account with this Agency* Youre faithfully, / A for Political Agent, Bahrain.. ,r Y'*’ COPI 1 D (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) ALL LETTERS TO BE ADDRESSED TO THE EASTERN BANK LIMITED. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS EASTERTIDE. imm The Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, W« anclese herewith a Declaration signed by Mr* K*T. Nereyane Iyengar, a neinber of eur Staff, and duli r witneaced by us. V# shall be nuch obliged if yeu will kindly hare this document authenticated and returned te us* This Deolnratien is required by the Postmaster, Bombay, before making payment on certain postal cash certificates jOwned by Mr.Wronger, in the name of his miner sen and daughter, referred te in the decument. Thanking yeu in advance Manager•the Bahrein petroleum Company limited x &lt;eP ^rO' C *\^' A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. NO:PA-163. October 1st. 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, Our Ref. Shipping Notice 9-10 Return Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return to San Francisco of 37 Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders which have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line M.Y. 'POELAU-BRAS' sailed hence on September 26th. 1940. Please return the Certificate duly attested &amp;L your earliest convenience debiting charges in connec ^*.on to our account. Yours very truly, '»&amp;. XT Chief Local Representative. ME BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel. 1* No. f' -5/3 si Political *Vgency f Bahrain# 6 th October, 1940* To :he Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Vetroleuni Company Linitert, Baiii*ain # Bear air, Ihe enclosure to your letter No .FA-163 dated the 1st October 1940, is returned herewith, foi* pauor signature by the declarer. for l/S. Political Ase^t* Bahrainthe Bahrein petroleum Company Limited PA-166 A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, October 3, 1940, File 801.5 His Britannic Majesty f s Political Agent, B a h r e in. Dear Sir, We enclose herewith a Note of Protest made by Mr. M. H. Lipp in connection with an accident to our oil barge n BAPC0 IT'. Y/ill you please certify the signature of Mr. Lipp on three copies of the Protest and return them to us at your convenience. The fourth copy is for your files, should you require it. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Attachment:THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 1, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, October 1940. NOT! OF PROTEST I, M, H. Lippi General K&amp;ntger of llie Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited and repreeentatiTe of the owner* of the steel barge called the 'Bapeo II* hereby certify that on the thirtieth day of September 1940, said barge whilst pulling away from the terminal at the Port of A1 Khobar, Saudi Arabia, loaded with a cargo of approxi mately 5,644 barrels of orude oil destined for the Port of Zellaq, Bahrein Island, sustained damage. The damage appears to be a tear in the starboard side plate, amidships about 2 feet from the bottom of the barge and is 1/4** wide by 1-1/2' long with a bad dent extending from the tear about one foot in length. occasion may require, reserring to myself the right to extend the same at will. I now not# ay protest to serfs and ayaH ms hereafter as ^iginal signed sy n* K UPP. y.Arjem THE BAHREIN PETROLEQK CON?ANT LII.TITFD I confirm the above signature end authority. HIS BRITTANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENTPRINTED IN U. S. A MEMORANDUM From THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED BAHREIN ISLAND. PERSIAN GULF To H.B.M* s Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein. We thank you for your letter No.1875-5/3 of 6th October 1940 The attachment to our letter No,PA-163 is returned herewith duly signed by the declarer. ^ 7 ‘ /cALL LETTERS TO BE ADDRESSED TO THE EASTERN BANK LIMITED. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: EASTERTIDE. ilhe (tastrrn (incorporated in England. 9th October 9 ^40. URQEMT « The Political Agent, Bahrain. Bear Sir, Mm enclose herewith 2 Aeclaratione signed by Mr. K«T. Kdreyana Iyengar, a menber of onr Staff, and duly witnessed by us. We shall be much obllgad If you will klndlj hmr. th. doevawnt# wuthwntiMt.* wd rwturn than to us* th. neoaasuy f.« of R».8/- for both docunonte le sent mm herewith. These declarations are required by the Postmasters, Karachi and Bahrain, before waking payment on certain postal cash certificates ••uat hy Mr. Xysngur, in th. nan. of hi. minor sons ref.rrod to In th. docuaents.Enel. 2. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf X NO:PA-186. October 13th. 1940. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahre in. Sir, Our Ref. Sh.Notices Nos.10-4 &amp; 10-5 : Return of Empty Cylin ders to New York. I enclose herewith two Certificates covering return to New York, of : - &amp; 3 - Empty Liquid Chlorine Cylinders. which have been shipped per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. 'BAMOR.v” sailed hence on October 7th. 1940, with transhipment at Bombay via first available American President Line Steamer. Please return the Certificates, duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges in connection 17 - Empty Acetylene Cylinders. to our account. Yours very truly, XU • w Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM C CMP ANY LIMITED. MI.The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf A w a 1 i , NO:PA-187 October 14th. 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein, Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering return to New York of : - which are being shipped in one box per B.I.S.N. Co.’s S.S. 'BARPETA' sailing on or about October 15th. 1940 to Bombay thence Via ’’PRESIDENT GARFIELD” on November 6 th. to New York. at your earliest convenience, debiting all charges in this connection to our account. 1 Generator and 1 Starting Motor. Please return the Certificate, duly attested Yours very truly Chief Local Representative IHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED MI Enel. 1.fU THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED No. FA-189. Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. October 15, 1940. A w a 1 i, H. B. M’s. Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I am enclosing original powers of attorney granted by The Bahrein Petroleum Company to Messrs. M.H. Lipp, W.P. Anderson, H.N. Phillips, and G-.A. Kellenberg, together with one copy of each. that these are true copies of the original and return them to me, together with the originals at your earliest convenience. It would be appreciated if you will certify Yours very truly, XL# XL« AAXiU.Hi.W.U'.*. Chief Local Represantative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDV No. 1999-3/3 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain* in original together with one copy each of and has the honour to send him/^35H3Q«Cthe undermentioned document ( s ) duly attested. A sum of Hs20/- being the fee for sealing and attesting has been debited to your deposit account with this Agency. Thb Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 23rd October, 1940. Reference to previous correspondence: His letter Ho.PA-189 dated 15th October, 1940. Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Power cf attorney granted to Mr. M.H. Lipp. 2. w »t W ft rt M W.P. Anderson. 3. N rtf? rt rt ?i H.N. Phillip.. 4. w ?« « rt rt G.A. Kellenberg.\ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf AWALI. N0.PA-203. October 27th. 1940. His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, BAHREIN. OUR REF. SHIPPING NOTICE #10-6, RETURN OF 4 MONROE CALCULATING MACHINES. I enclose herewith a Certificate covering return to New York of 4 Monroe Electric and Hand Calculating Machines which have been shipped to Bombay on October 7th. per B.I.S.N.Co*s•, S.S. 'BAMORA' and thence via first available President Line Steamer to New York. Please return the certificate duly attested at your earliest convenience, debiting chirg&amp;s in this connection to our account. VASU. Yours very truly, R. k. KENNEDY7 Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel. 1THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf Awali. NO:PA-212. November 4th. 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. OUR REP. SHIPPING NOTICE #10-17 RETURN OF EMPTY ANHYDROUS AMMONIA CYLINDERS TO SAN FRANCISCO. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of :- 24 - Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders, to San Francisco. These have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. 'HOEGH SILVERSTAR* sailed hence on October 31st. 1940. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. RNKiVASU. Enel. 1/?^ No. 2128 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. in original and has the honour to send him axKTOOOf the undermentioned document ( s ) . The agency* BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 14th November, 194°. His Letters N o.&amp;» knrM cS¥eS &gt;n 6 th e November, 1940. Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Substiture Power of Attorney - 2 . 3. 4. Philip C. McConnell. Russell M. Brown. Y/ard P. Anderson, dated 15-2-40. m if ftThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited A w a 1 i Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No. PA-220. November 9, 1940 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I attach two substitute powers of attorney issued by Mr. Milton H. Lipp to Messrs. Ward P. Anderson and Philip C. McConnell together with a notice of revo cation. Would you kindly annul these and return to me as soon as possible? Yours very truly Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LTDTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A W a 1 i Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, 9th November, 1940. I, Milton H. Lipp, Attorney-in-Fact, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, desire as from the 9th November, 1940 to revoke the attached two substitute powers of attorney issued in the names of Ward P* Anderson and Philip C* McConnell and regis tered by you on the 17th February, 1940. MILTON H. LIPP Attomey-in-Fact THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a X i Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, 9til November, 1940 I, Milton H. Lipp, Attorney-in-Faot The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, desire as from the 9th November, 1940 to revoke the attached two substitute powers of attorney issued in the names of Ward P. Anderson and Philip C. McConnell and regis tered by you on the 17th February, 1940. / MILTON H. LH&gt;P Attorney-in-Fact THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDthe Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, PA-225 3q (o November 9, 1940, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein. Dear Sir: I attach two substitute powers of attorney issued by Mr. Milton H. Lipp to Messrs. Aard P. Anderson and Russell M. Brown together with a notice of revocation Y/ould you kindly annul these and return to me as soon as possible? Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LTD.c^ C ? c the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, 9th Noyember, 1940. I f Milton H. Lipp, Attorney-In-Fact, The Standard-Vacuum Oil Company, desire as from the 9th November, 1940 to revoke the attached two substitute powers of attorney issued in the names of Ward. P. Anderson and Russell M* Brown and registered by you*The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ^wali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, 9th November, 1940. I, Hilton -I. Lipp, attorney-in-Tact, The Standard-Vacuum Oil Company, desire as from the 9th November, 1940 to revoke the attached two substitute powers of attorney issued in the names of 7/ard. P. Anderson and Hussell M. Brown and registered by you.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED PA-221. Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Awali, November 10, 1940. Political Agent, Bahrein Island, File #855 Pr.-.5IAII GULF . PO’TIRS -O F-ATTOIHEIY Dear Sir, Te are attaching herewith substitute Power of Attorney authorized by Milton Hickethier Lipp, Attorney in Fact; (1) Ward P. Anderson (2) Philip C. McConnell In both cases you will find one original and two copies, will you please register and certify the copies and return to us at your convenience together with note of the fees payable. &gt;urs very B. A. KENNEDY Chief Local Representative The Bahrein Petroleum Co.,Ltd. Attachments.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED NO.PA-232. Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, Awali, November 10, 1940 Political Agent, Bahrein Island, PBR3IAI T G-UL?. File #835 P0'SR3-OF-ATTORNEY Dear Sir, '^e are attaching herewith substitute Power of Attorney authorized by Hilton Hickethier Lipp, Attorney in Fact (Standard-Vacuum Oil Company); (1) T .7ard P, Anderson (2) Russell M. Brown In both cases you will find one original and two copies; will you please register originals and certify copies, also enclosed are two original Powers-of-Attomey from Standard-Vacuum Oil Company for registration: (1) M. H. Lipp (2) I. T. Deane Please return all documents at your convenience together with note of fees payable. Yours very truly, AttachmentsThe Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Oil Company Limited, Bahrain* i y return herewith and has the honour to iiteK3r}0©&amp;5o?k the undermentioned document ( s ) duly registered and certified• U The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 23rd November, 1940• Reference to previous correspondence: His letters Nos:rA-221 and PA-222 dated 10th November, 1940 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1*Substitute Power of Attorney (one orgls &amp; 2 copies) 3 2.Substitute Pov^er of Attorney (1 Crgl: and 2 copies) } 3.Substitute Power of Attorney . (1 Orgls and 2 copies) 3 &amp;fr&gt;A 4.Substitute Power of Attorney (1 orgls and 2 copies) 5.Power of Attorney (orgls) 6 .Power of Attorney (orgls) Yard P. Anderson Its .17/-/- Phillip C. MeConnell fo.17/-'- Ward P* Anderson Rs.10/8/- Hussell M. Brown us. 10/2/- M.H. Lipp J .T • Deane ns* 6 /-/- Hs. 6 /-/« Total Rs.67/-/-The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited !$&gt; Aw all. Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, November 20, 1940 PA-242 File 801.5 Damage to Barge 'Bapco l w His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: We enclose herev.ith three copies of a Note of Protest made by Mr. M.H. Lipp in connection with damage caused by the recent bad weather to our oil barge w Bapco 1 H . Will you please certify the signature of Mr. Lipp on i three copies and return them to us at your convenience. Yours very truly. DR. R. A. KENNEDY Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. Attachment: cc Acctg.(2)THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED NO:FA-241November 20th. 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Our Ref. Sh.Notices Nos.11 -2 &amp; 11-14. Sir, I enclose herewith two Certificates covering return to Nsw York of : - 40 Drums - Chemicals. and 1 Box containing G.E. Turbine Parts. which have been shipped per S.S. 'WESTERN QUEEN' which sailed hence on November 18th. 1940. Please return the Certificate, duly attested, at your convenience, debiting all charges in this connection to our account. MI. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel. 2.tSi THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No. PA-263. December 2, 1940 His Britannic Majestys Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I attach hereto two Notices of Agency issued to Mr. Thomas Colin Homes Naughton by Mr. M. H. Lipp and Mr. Floyd W. Ohliger on behalf of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited and The California Arabian Standard Oil Company respectively. two Notices of revocation, one signed by Mr. Lipp and the other by Mr. Ohliger. Will you please cancel the two Agency appointments and return to me as soon as possible. It is desired to cancel these and I attach Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LTDt. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. i • in original and has the honour to send hing^g$C$Ofof the undermentioned document ( s )duiy cancelled. The agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 4th December, 1940# Reference to previous correspondence: His letter Ko.PA-263 dated 2nd December, 1940* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. T,vo notices of Agency with two Notices of revocation. Subject.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. NO:PA-261. December 2nd. 1940. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Our Reference : Sh. Notice No.11-39. S ir, “ I enclose herewith Certificate covering return to New Yorlc of : - 1 - Foxboro Potentiometer Pyrometer Recorder No.76123. which has been shipped per S.S. 'ANNISTON CITY' sailed hence on November 28th. 1940. Please return the Certificate, duly attested, at your convenience, debiting all charges in this connection to our account. Yours very truly, R. A. KENNEDY. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI. Enel. 1* ■ .. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. December 2, 1940. PA- 262 Pile 801.5 TO ’’blipco ir* Hie Britannic Hajesty’s Political A^ent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, 7fe enclose herewith three copies of a Note of Protest made by Hr. M. H. Lipp in connection v/ith damage caused by the recent bad weather to our oil bar^e '3APC0 11'. 77i 11 you please certify the signature of Hr. Lipp on all three copies and return them to us at your convenience. . A*' »• &lt; J '’Yours very truly Attachments:Enel•4 The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited A w a l i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO: PA-512. January 10th. 1941. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, Our Ref. Sh.Notice No*12-13. Return of Empty Bthyl Fluid Drums. I enclose herewith Certificate in quadruplicate covering return to New York of : - 12 - 55 Gallon Capacity, Empty Ethyl Fluid Drums. &amp; 17 - 10 Gallon Capacity, Empty Ethyl Fluid Drums. which have been shipped per S.S. n PUERT0 RICAN n sailed hence on January 5th. 1941. duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges in this connection to our account. Please return the Certificate in quadruplicate MI.Enel.2. The Bahrein petroleum Company limited N0:PA-31l Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, January 10th. 1941 A w a 1 i , His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent Bahrein. Sir, Our Ref. Sh.Notice Nos.12-11 &amp; 12-12 : Return of Hmpty Cylinders to New York. I enclose herewith two Certificates covering return to New York of : - 4 - Empty Preon-12 (Dichlorodifluoromethane) Cylinders. &amp; 9 - Empty Acetylene Cylinders. which have been shipped per S.S. 'PUERTO RICAN' sailed hence on January 5th. 1941. at your earliest convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Please return the Certificates duly attested Yours very truly THE* BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED MIEnel« 1. v. s/-' c^V * 0 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, NO:PA-318. January 12th. 1941. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. 9/ ( P Sir, Our Ref. Sh. Notice No. 12-9. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return to Los Angeles of : - 1 - Empty Acetylene Cylinder. &amp; 1 - Empty Oxygen Cylinder. which have been shipped per Silver Java Pacific Line M.V. 'BOSCHEONTSIN' sailed hence on January 8th. 1941. Please send the Certificate duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Touts very truly. A / -2?U£. «t M. H. LIPP. ACTING CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED NO :PA-517. A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. January 12th. 1941. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Our Ref. Sh.Notice Nos.12-4, 12-5, Sir, 12-6 of 1940 and 1-1 of 1941. I enclose herewith four Certificates covering return to San Francisco of : - 26 - Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders. 10 - Empty Calol Cutting Gas Cylinders. 3 - Empty Carbon Dioxide Cylinders. &amp; 33 - Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders. which have been shipped per Silver Java pacific Line M.V. 'BOSCHFONTKIN w sailed hence on January 8 th. 1941. Please send the Certificates duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our v ^ accoui)^. Tours very truly, M M. H. LIPP. ACTING CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. MI. Enel• 4# : ty * •; 9 / / V&gt;\ &amp; '-rtC' THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awal i , Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, /?&gt; NO.PA-359. January £ 6 , 1941. *# I tJ HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrein. Sir: OUR REF. SHIPPING NOTICE NO.1-12. RETURN OF TWENTY EMPTY ANHYDROUS AMMONIA CYLINDERS TO SAN FRANCISCO. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of Twenty Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to San -Francisco. These have been shipped per the Silver Java Pacific Line, M.V.'HOEGH SILVERDAWN' sailed today. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. i Yours very truly, ~^ 7 . M M. H. LIPP Ag. CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED,4 m the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awal i , Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. NO.PA-340. January 26, 1941* HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrein, (' Sir: OUR REF. SHIPPING NOTICE NO.1-10. RETURN OF FIVE EMPTY CALOL INDUSTRIAL GAS #2 CYLINDERS TO SAN FRANCISCO. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of Five Empty Calol Industrial Gas No. 2 Cylinders to San Francisco. These have been shipped per the Silver Java Pacific Line, M.V. 'HOEGH SILVERDAWN' sailed today. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. SKSM/- Encl. Yours very truly, Ag. CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE; THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.C.12.37. TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS: Lord Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) A. Agnew, Cr i-B&amp;H- :r0/V 6. .S R. Cayrol, D.S.O.. D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser, C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy H^STeMulS) ?CL/CAA. 3/2309 CONFIDENTIAL BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 23rd February, 1941. R. W ’lers J. Sk. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, INCREASES OF CAPITAL We enclose herewith certified copies, in duplicate, of a Resolution authorising an increase of Capital of the following Companies Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd. from £400,100 to £500,100. Petroleum Development (Trucial from £150,100 Coast) Ltd. to £170,100. We shall be grateful if these increases can be registered in due course in accordance with the usual Bahrain procedure. ACMThe Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, N0 # PA-593 February 26, 1941 HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT BAHREIN. Sir: REF. OUR SHIPPING NOTICE NO.2-18 RETURN OF 15 EMPTY ACETYLENE CYLINDERS TO NEW YORK. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of Fifteen Empty Acetylene Cylinders to New York. These have been shipped per the s.s. 'EXCELLENCY” on February 25th to New York. Please return the Certificate duly attested at your convenience debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly Enel•1 Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROIEUM COMPANY LIMITED cc Acctg. (2) S/HouseThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. March 5, 1941. POWER OF ATTORNEY No. PA-404. H. B. M’s. Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I attach hereto one true copy of the Substitute Power of Attorney issued by Mr. M. H. Lipp, Attorney in Fact, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, to Mr. P. C. McConnell also of this Company. As Mr. P. C. McConnell is very shortly proceeding to the United States on vacation, it is desired to revoke Mr. McConnell’s Substitute Power of Attorney as from March 6 th, 1941. It will be appreciated, therefore, if you will kindly cancel the attached document and return it to this office in due course. f l Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. T,THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, February 12, 1941. File No•835 POV/ERS OF ATTORNEY Agent, We are attaching hereto Substitute Powers of Attorney authorised by Milton Hickethier Lipp, Attorney in Fact (The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited) for the undernoted individuals Ward P. Anderson, Robert Cameron. /?/ 26 S In support of Mr. Lipp’s issuance of these Substitute Powers of Attorney, we attach Mr. Lipp’s own Power of Attorney dated 19th October 1938 from which you will see, upon referring Clause 10, that he is authorized by the Board of Directors to make such substitutions. In both cases you will find one original and five carbon copies. Will you please register the original and certify the copies? We are also enclosing three Powers of Attorney issued by the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited to the undemoted individuals:- Milton Hickethier Lipp, - ^ Harold Newell Phillips, Ceorge Anthony Kellenberg, appointing them Attorneys in India. Will you also register these three Powers of Attorney? Please return all the attached documents at your convenience together with a note of the fee payable. iVery truly yours, Chief Local Representative, TW! BAHREIN PRTROLW COMPANY LTD.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED l.f' V Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. March 27, 1941. File No. 835 POWERS OF ATTORNEY H. B. M f s. Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We attach hereto six copies of a Substitute Power of Attorney authorized by Mr. Milton Hickethier Lipp, Attorney in Fact, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, for Mr. Leslie A. Smith active for the Sheikh dom of Bahrein. We also attach, for your perusal, Mr. Lipp’s own power of attorney dated 19th October 1938. Under Clause 10, Mr. Lipp is authorized by the Board of Directors to issue such substitute powers. Will you please register the original and certify the five carbon copies to be true copies of the original. Kindly return all the attached documents at your convenience together with a note of the fee payable. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LTD.No 606-5/3 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Chief Loc?*l Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain * and has the honour to send hinsaOMODOtf the undermentioned document ( s ) duly registered and certified* The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 2nd April, 1941* Reference to previous correspondence: His letter No.PA-437 dated the 27th Tarch, 1941. Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. One original and five Power of Attorney. duplicate copies of a Substitute 2 . Mr. Lipp's 1938. own power of attorney dated 19th October, Details of fees charged to Bapc* account Copying fee Registration fe Attestation fee Linking fee e (Rupees thirty five only). Rs .4- 8—0 ^ hi. 2 - 8-0 v' Its • 12 — 8—0 fo . 15 - 8-0 ni.35- 0-0the Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. NO.PA-454. April 8 , 1941 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. w Sir: OUR REFERENCE S/NOTICE #3-7 SHIPMENT OF 89 EMPTY ANHYDROUS ANMONIA CYLINDERS TO NEW YORK. I enclose herewith Certificate covering return to New York of : 89 Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders which have been shipped per the B.I.S#N*Co f s s*s*'SHINKUANG' sailed hence on the 7th instant. Please send the Certificate duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account# s truly. sksm/- Enel# R. A. KENNEDY, M.D. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED /uSvi*jtZ&gt;The Bahrein petroleum Company limited A w a 1 i Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, June 5, 1941 PA-514 His Britannic Majesty’s Political -^ent, Bahrein. Sir REF. OUR SHIPPING NOTICES NO.5-17 &amp; 5-18 RETURN OF 42 EMPTY ANHYDROUS AMMONIA &amp; 18 ACETYLINE CYLINDERS TO NEV; YORK I enclose herewith Certificates covering return of 42 Empty Anhydrous Ammonia and 18 Acetyline Cylinders to New York. These have been shipped per the B.I.S.N.Co’s S*S.'Barala rt on June 4, 1941 to Bombay and thence to New York. Please return the Certificates duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. Yours very truly, EWG:MD Attachment cc Acctg.(2) Storehouse (2) JTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. June 12, 1941. ty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We attach herewith the original and duplicate Power of Attorney of Mr. Colin Reith which we shall be pleased if you will cancel and return to us in due course. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN 1STR0LEUM COMPANY, LTD JA: jg Attachments:The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, June 30th, 1941, 1 X No. PA-560. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT Bahrein. Dear Sir MR. 0, BJOHKLUND '’Deceased. We enclose herewith 3 copies of the cremation certificate for the above duly signed by Messrs. Lipp, Anderson, Kellenberg and Smith of this Company, and by Messrs. Lorentzen, Tellefsen, Larsen and Sveva, Norwegian Officers of the Motor Barge, Caltex II who were present* We should appreciate your certifying one copy of this certificate in the usual manner to allow us to ship the remains from Bahrein and return same to as soon as convenient. memorandum by Dr. Kennedy giving the history of Mr. Bjorklund last illness so far as it is known to us. We also enclose for your records a copy of a Yours very truly, // 1/ ^ tfyfi M. H. LIPP jf Chief Local Representative, TIE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Ends: 3 copies of cremation certificate, 1 copy of Dr. Kennedy’s memorandum. TEBiCDS.The remains of OLE BJORKLUND were placed in the Awali Crematory for cremation at 1 0 15 p.m. (standard time) on June 21, 1941 by the following persons M. K. LIP? Kr. LQKaiTSiIN i. Jl. SVi-VA ‘.7. P. AIIZHRS01T I. B, vX.ITH Go A. The Ashes were removed and placed in a Bronze Urn, with the neune, and place and date of death, stamped on the Metal Bottom, beginning at 5*45 a.m* (standard time) on Juno 22, 1941 by the following persons n. lipp I. 3. SLITH Go A. KHLLS1BKRG Awali, Bahrein.Awali, Bahrein. pm The remains of OLE BJORKLUND were placed in the Awali Crematory for cremation at 1.15 p.m. (standard time) on June 21, 1941 by the following persons K. H. LIP? Kr. Lonarr^N L. T XLEFSSJ I. LABSSir K. SV3VA Z. P. A1IIERS01T I. B. SMITH , Go A. KSIA^HKiBG . , The Ashes were removed and placed in a Bronze Urn, with the name, and place and date of death, stamped on the Metal Bottom, beginning at 5.45 a.m® (standard time) on Jane 22, 1941 by the following persons I. 3. SIXTH . a® A. K iLXii’lD'i'TRGTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED I't? A w a 1 i Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. June 30, 1941 No.PA-561 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent BaJirein. Sir REF. OUR SHIPPING NOTICES NOS.6-19, 6-29, 6-30, 6-32 f 6-33, 6-54 &amp; 6-56. I enclose herewith Certificates covering return of the following: ' #6-36 - 5 ' Calol Gas #2 ' These have been shipped per S,S. 'FLORENCE LUCKENBACH' sailed June 29th, 1941. Please return the Certificates of the Ethyl 'Fluid Drums in quadruplicate and one each of the rest, duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges in this connection to our account. S/N #6-19 - 11 Empty Ethyl Fluid Drums ' #6-29 - 1 Armature for Hobart Generator ' #6-30 - 180# John Crane Packing Size 1” 6-32 - 41 Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders 6-33 - 5 ' Freon-12 Cylinders 6-34 - 6 ' Acetylene ' Yours very truly CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWG:MD Attachments cc Acctg.(2) Storehouse (2THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali: Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrein# Dear Sir, We enclose herewith two Forms of Application for a U# S, Passport completed by Ur, W* P, Anderson and sigied by Mr. M# H, Lipp as identifying witness* Would you kindly certify the signatures of Messrs. Lipp and Anderson and return the forms to us tomorrow for certain as Mr. Anderson will be leaving for U. S# A# towards the end of the month and his new passport has to come from Baghdad* Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED* Ends: Two Forms Two Photographs* ^ A 1 —*' W- iliGray, Mackenzie &amp; Co.Ltd. INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE: 122. LEAD EN HALL STREET. LONDON,E.C.3. TEUESRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BU S R E H. AM AR AH. K UT. KHORAMS HAHR AHWAZ for BAN OAR-SHAHPOUR| BUSH I RE RAS TAN UR A. BUNDER-ABBAS. LING AH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. M U SCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE L/623. No. Bahrein, 7th July, 41. &gt;(! ' The Political Agent, BAUHsnr. Dear Sir, '■ We attach hereto list of the contents of pe rsonal effects shipped by us to Few York per B.I.Vessel with trans shipment at Bombay to American President Line steamer. To enable transhipme t to be effected at Bombay, it is necessary that the attached list is approved by you for transhipment and despatched to the Bombay Customs, and we shall therefore be glad if you will do the necessary in this connection. For employme nt your information, Mr. N.T.Langham is in the of Messrs. Petroleum Concessions Ltd., at ^atar. Yours faitAif ully, tor 1Political Agency, Bahrain the 9th July, 1941 • Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Girc, Pl- 3 as -2 refer to yocr letter Ko.1/623 dated the 7th July, 1941. 2. The certificate asked for is endorsed to the list enclosed *hich in returned herewith. It is requested that in fut&gt;r-e such lists should be sent to me in duplicate to enable me to keep a copy for my files. 3. The fee for tiixS certificate is Rs.2/8/- and I shall be grateful if you would let me liave this amount at your convenience. Yours faithfully, tor Political Agent, Bahralr ,Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) HEAD OFFICE: 122. LEADEN HALL STREET. L0ND0N.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BRANCHES: BU S R E H. AM AR AH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ for BANDAR-SHAH POUR BUSHIRE RAS TANURA. BUNDER ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. M U SCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. L/655* Bahrein, 15th July, 19 41* A, The Political ^gent, BAHTIN. Dear Sir, We enclose herewith copy of a letter received from the Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd., together with a Certificate in duplicate, which we shall be glad if you will kindly endorse and return to us, retaining one copy for your records. This certificate is required by Messrs. F. S. Kerr Co., of Bombay, to enable them to obtain delivery of the cylinders. Yours faitnfully, Ends:COPY OF LETTSR RECEIVED BY MESSRS. GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; CO. LTD FROM THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM CO. LTD., BAHREIN. No.GM-964 dated. Awali, July 13, 1941. Messrs. Gray, Miackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., BAHREIN. Dear Sirs, We have today received a letter from Messrs F.3. Kerr Company of 125 Esplanade Road, Bombay, requesting that the shipment of 101 cylinders Butane, shipped per ss.'Barpeta' on June 20, 1941, be navicerted by the Political Agent at Bahrein. We should inform you tnat Messrs. Kerr Co. undertake in their Butane purchase agreement to make their own shipping arrangements from -frahrein, and so we are requesting you to handle this matter on their behalf, and suggest that you should charge Kerr &amp; Co. a fee for handling this work: Details of shipment are as follows: 101 Cylinders - Nett Weight Butane 2,828 lbs. Gross Weight 5,234 ' Product manufactured by: The Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd., at Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Yours faithfully, 3d/- W.P.Anderson for Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd.es 1 ?/ &gt;- CERTIFICATE OF ORIGIN DETAILS OF IMPORT . LILOR PRI&amp;GAZ - 101 empty cylinders. Received here from Bombay ex ss. ,, Pronto n v. 6 . on 1st June, 1941. DETAILS OF SHIPMENT . 101 Cylinders Butane. Nett Weight 2,828 lbs. Sc*oss 5,234 ” Shipped to Bombay per ss. 'Barpeta ' 1 v.292. Product Manufactured by* Declared before ne this 16th day of July, 1941. The Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd., at Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf for GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; CO. LTDTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, covering return of 30 empty Anhydrous Ammonia, 7 Acetylene, 2 Freon, 1 Nitrogen and 1 Hydrogen Cylinders to New York. These have been shipped per S.S. 'Puerto Rican' on August 11th, 1941. Please return the certificates duly attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in this connection to our account. TEE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. August 12,1941 PA-636 REF.SHIPPING NOTICES NOS.7-25 &amp; 8-5 RETURN OF EMPTY CYLINDERS TO NEW YORK I enclose herewith certificates Yours very truly CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE Attachment cc Acctg.(2) Storehouse (3)2 -/ c / No. /Si 1 ? of 1360 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 22nd Rajah, . , &lt;oCjUU XVO.J O.U , August 14, 19- H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain, I enclose herewith a letter from Haj Khalil Ebrahim Kanoo, a Bahrain subject addressed to the Good Year Tyre and Rubber Export Co., Akron, U.3.A., for favour of attestation. The facts mentioned are true. Adviser to the Government. Y.G zTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No. PA-623. Eis Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, V/e are attaching hereto four copies of a substitute power of attorney for Mr. J. T. Deane which we shall be pleased if you will register and return to us at your convenience. The power of attorney of Mr. M. H. Lipp is also attached, which please return to us after it has served its purpose. &gt; M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LTD.The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Chi«f Local Representative* ^he Bahrain Petroleum Coiirpany* Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) registered and attested. duly V The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dat8d -y3rd Augunli f 1041. - Reference to previous correspondence: His letter No .PA-623 dated 3rd August, 1941. Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. One original and three dup! .icate copies of a Substitute Power of Attorney. % 2. Mr. Lipp , s c\vn power of at- Forney dated 19th October, 1938 Details of fees cha] 'Ked to Baoco account. Copying fee Rs. 10— 8—0 Registration fee Rs • 2—8—0 Attestation fee Rs. 7-8-0 Linking fee _ jfo.10— 0—0 Totdl #30-8-0The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Z /7 HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrein* Dear Sir, Would you kindly certify the signature of Mr, F* E, Brisson, one of our American employees on two copies of the attached documents 'Revocation of Power of Attorney', Mr. Brisson, signed this document in the presence of Mr, G, A, ^ellenberg, our Personnel Manager, Please deduct your charges for this service from our deposit with you. Yours very truly. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, c.c. BNP ) LAS ) TEBjCDS, Ends:No.1647-5/3 Political Agency, Bahrain* 20th August, 1941 To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company limited, Bahrain* Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No*PA-639 dated the 16th August, 1941* 2. In order to attest the signature I have to certify that Mr. Brisson signed the document in my presence. Unless, therefore, he appears before me and signs the document in ny presence, I an afraid, l/h*. 1 not be ab? L e tc attest the signature. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, BahrainThe Bahrein petroleum Company limited Axall: Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, August 21st v 1941* No. PA-654 . HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, B ah r e i n« Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No. 1647-5/3 and our letter PA-639* Tiis will introduce Mr. F. E. Brisson who will sign the document again in your presence to enable you to attest the signature* Please deduct your fees for this service from our deposit* Yours very truly. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED* TEBiCDS.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. July 6, 1941. No .PA-568 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, With reference to our letter No.PA-514 dated June 5, 1941, enclosing certificates of origin for attestation covering 42 Empty Anhydrous iimmonia and 18 Empty Acetylene Cylinders which we were returning to the United States. Certificates were duly returned and forwarded to New York as usual. The cylinders were shipped by B.I.S.N.Co’s S.S.'BARALA' on June 4, 1941 to Bombay for transhipment. We have now received advice from our shipping agents Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co.,Ltd., that tranship ment permission has been refused. I enclose here with two additional copies of the certificate of Origin. Will you please return the certifi cates duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges in connection to our account. On receipt we will forward to Bombay for completion of transhipment formalities. very truly , . H. LIPP CHIE®'BOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWG:MD Attachment cc Acctg. (2) Storehouse (2) 7/7/V03°: The Bahrein petroleum company limited i »- / Awali: Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. August 23rd, 1941• No. PA-655 ♦ HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGS0NT, Bahrein* Dear Sir, This will Introduce Mr. R. S. Wilson, who wishes his si&amp;i&amp;tures on a document to be attested by you. Kindly deuuct your fees for this service from our deposit with you* \ ^ 0 * ** 0 •*. J . 4 Tours very truly. M. H. LTPP Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN FETROLECMDOMPANY LIMITED* TEBiCDSTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, September 27,1941, No.PA-695 REF. SH.NOTICE mTmi' W EMM 1 __ NIA CYLINDERS TO SAN FRANCISCO His Pritannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. covering return of 23 empty Anhydrous Ammonia cylinders to San Francisco. These have been shipped per S.S. ’’VAN CLOON' to-day. attested, at your convenience, debiting charges in this connection to our account. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED ETO: MD Attachment cc Acctg.(2) Storehouse (2) Sir I enclose herewith certificate Please return the certificate duly CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVEThe Bahrein Petroleum Company limited i Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bfeiirein. Dear Sir, We attach hereto one copy of the substitute power of attorney for Mr. Leslie A. Smith and shall be pleased if you will cancel this and return to us in due course• Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Attach: fix. * . 3u&gt;s-/ &gt;\A cn fy 0 IM-X- 71 ^ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We attach hereto power of attorney of Mr. M. W. Thornburg dated September 5, 1939, which we shall be pleased if you have cancelled and return to us in due course. Yours very truly, //• M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Attach: f'k' /V»: &lt;}l 0The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. PA-790 POWERS OF ATTORNEY 0. A&gt; KELLEN3ERG November 12, 1941. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I attach hereto two powers of attorney issued by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited to Mr. George Anthony Kellenberg, covering the ^haikhdom of Bahrein and India for purpose of revocation as Mr. Kellenberg will soon leave Bahrein for the United States. kindly cancel the attached two documents, returning them to this office in due course and charging us in usual manner for any fees which may be incurred. It would be appreciated, therefore, if you will _ M. H. LIPP. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW :Jag Attach:Awall, Noyamber 12, 1941 PA-790 P0WER3 OF ATTORNEY 0. A&gt; KELLENSSRG His Britannic Itiejeety’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear air, I attach hereto two powers of attorney issued by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited to Mr. George Anthony Kellenberg, covering the Sheikhdom of Bahrein and India for purpose of revocation as Nr. Kellenberg will soon leave Bahrein for the United States. kindly cancel the attached two documents, returning them to this office in due course and charging us in usual manner for any fees which may be incurred. It would be appreciated, therefore, if you will Yours very truly k. H. UPF. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. uftlUiNM- oivaHtD BY H.L1PP- 3* :Jag Attach:1 Attachs: the Bahrein petroleum company limited Awali Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, October 7th, 1941. No. PA-712 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We are attaching hereto six copies each of three substitute powers of attorney for Mr. Beave Crow, which we shall be pleased if you will register and return to us at your convenience. The three powers of attorney of Mr. M. H. Lipp are also attached, which please return to us after they have served their purpose. Yours very truly, M. H. LIPP. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.A wall No. PA Cotober 7th, 1941 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We are attaching hereto six copies each of three substitute powers of attorney for Mr. Beare Crow, which we shall be pleased if you will register and return to us at your convenience. The three powers of attorney of Mr. M. H. Lipp are also attached, which please return to us after they hare served their purpose. Yours very truly, ORIGINAL SIGNED BY M. H. LIPP. M. H. LIPP. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Attachs:No * 2311/5/3 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Preseats his complimeuts to s— The Chief Local Representative, B&amp;hrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. and has the honour to send him 3o€R9Sdtf the undermentioned document ( s.) « • n- -la* The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated Novemberi^l941 • Reference to previous correspondence : His Letter No.PA-712 dated 7th October, 1941. Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject 1. Six copies each of three substitute powers of attorney for Mr. Beave Crow. 2. Three powers of attorney of Mr. H.H. Lipp. ^etials of fees charged to Banco account . Copying fee Registration fee Attestation fee • Linking fee Total 3. Two powers of attorney duly cancelled forwaixifid with your letter No.790 12th November, 1941. Rs.21/8/- 8s .45/-/-j ^ ■ 83.111-8' dated L. H \rTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED O ^ 0 Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. December 8, 1941. PA-833. POWERS OF ATTORNEY Major R. G. Alban, O.B.E., His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We enclose new Powers of Attorney and those they supersede as follows (a) Power given by the California Texas Oil Co., Ltd., to M.H. Lipp, W.P. Anderson, B. Crow, J.T. Deane, R.M. Brown, J.O. Fifer for the Sheikhdom of Bahrein expiring 31st December 1945 and superseding similar powers granted to the above named, except B. Crow, expiring on 31st December, 1942. (b) Power given by the California Texas Oil Co. (Overseas) Ltd., to M.H. Lipp, W.P. Anderson, B. Crow, J.T. Deane R.M. Brown, J.O. Fifer for the Sheikhdom of Bahrein, expiring 31st December 1945 and superseding similar powers granted to the above named, except B. Crow, expiring on 31st December 1942. (c) Power given by the Texas Company (China) Ltd., to M.H. Lipp, W.P. Anderson, B. Crow, J.T. Deane, for the Sheikhdom of Bahrein expiring 31st December 1945 and superseding a similar power granted to the above named, except B. Crow, expiring on 31st December 1942. We would appreciate your registering the new powers, recording the revocation of the old powers, and returning all to us at your convenience, and charging us in the usual manner for any fees which may be incurred. M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited December 8, 1941. PA-832. POWERS OF ATTORNEY Major R. G. Alban, O.B.E., His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Manama. Dear Sir, We enclose two new Powers of Attorney given by the Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd., to Milton Hickethier Lipp and Harold Newell Phillips for the Sheikhdom of Bahrein, expiring on 31st December 1945, and also the powers which they replace expiring on 31st December 1941. We would appreciate your registering the new powers, noting their replacement of those expiring, and returning them to us at your earliest opportunity, and charging us in the usual manner for any fees which may be incurred. M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.C/ISO2 No. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Preseats his compliments to :— The Chief LoclI Represent Live, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. The relevant f ts as aet ilea oelo% have been debited to your Deposit account vath us. The Agency, Reference to previous correspondence : Cnief Loc.-1 Representative’s letters No. PA-d32 tnd PA-ol3 a ted the dtn Decemoer U41 Description of Enclosure and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) Name and Date. Subject 1. Five nev&gt; powers of attorney £ fter registration. 2. Ei^e old pov, rs of ottoiney £fter c .ncellation. Details oi foes cnar, 4 LQ Registration fee 12 d 0 (court fee mps) Copying fee 62 0 0 74 3 0 Rupe s Seventyftou* na /The Chief Locel Representrtive, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) /\ / S The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated 14th January 1942 Reference to previous correspondence : letter Mo. PA-864 dated the 27th December 1941 from the Chief Local Representative,The Bahrain Petroleum Co.Ltd Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject S ix copies of Subst One substitute powelr One power of attorns itute Power of Attorney duly registered of attorney, cancelled. y Registration Fee Cppying fee Linking fee Details of fees charged (6 copies) 15- 0- 0 5 - 8 - 0 15 - 0 - 0The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. December 27 ,• 1941. POWER OF ATTORNEY Major R. G. Alban, O.3.E., His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Manama. Dear Sir, We enclose Mr. Crow’s Power of Attorney as registered at your office on November 15th, 1941 for revocation as from 23rd December, 1941. We also enclose for registration six copies of a new substitute Power of Attorney in favour of Mr. Crow. The Power of Attorney in favour of Mr. M.H.Lipp under which the substitute power is issued is attached for your scrutiny before registering the new power. We would appreciate your recording the revoca tion of the cancelled power and registering the new power, returning them to us as soon as possible. Please debit our account in the usual manner with any charges incurred. V Yours very truly, -/V' ■ M. H. LIPP. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Attachs:r 3 The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, January 11, 1943 PA-890. POWERS OF ATTORNEY Major R. G. Alban, O.B.E., His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, &lt; we attach copies of Messrs. M. H. Lipp and H. N. Phillip’s Powers of Attorney as registered at your office December 31st, 1941 (Vol. 5 pages 186-193), Dec. 31st, 1941 (Vol. 5 pages 160-165) respectively. Will you please certify the enclosed as true copies returning them to us as soon as possible. Please debit our account in the usual manner with any charges incurred. Yours very truly, M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LTD.i &amp;'■ ^rO' The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. 13th January, 1942. PA-896. POWERS OF ATTOENEY His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, BAHREIN. Bear Sir, l ^ We enclose Messrs. J.T.Deane, B.Cameron and W.P.Anderson's Substitute Powers^jof Attorney as registered in your office on August 23rd 1941, March 25th 1941 and November 11th 1940 respectively for revocation as at 31st December, 1941. Six copies of each of the new powers for Messrs. J.T.Deane, H.N.Phillips and R.Cameron are also enclosed for registration. The Power of Attorney in favour of Mr. M.H.Lipp under which the substitute powers are issued is attached for your scrutiny before registering the new powers. We would appreciate your recording the revocation of the cancelled powers and registering the new powers, returning them to us as soon as possible. with lease debit our account in the usual manner harges incurred. Yours very truly, M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED cc-Audit.■I ■ T 180-5/3 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to :— The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. and has the hnno jr to send him a U(1 ^ 3rnlsn tioned document ( s ) i v The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated 31s_t January,_ 1942 • Reference to previous correspondence : His letters No.PA-890 and P.A. 8S6 dated 11th and 13th January respectively. Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject substitute 1. 3/Powers of Attorney in favour of Messrs. J.T-Deane, R.Cameron and W.P.Anderson, duly cancelled. 2.6 copies of each of the new powers of Attorney in favour of Messrs. J.T.Deane, H.N.Phillipjt and R.Cameron, duly registered, linked and attested. 3. 2 copies of powers of Attorney in favour of Messrs. M.H. Lipp and H.N. Phillip, duly attested. Details (&gt;f fees Registration fee Linking fee Attestation fee Copying fee 4. 1 Power of Attorney in favour of te.7- 8-0 8—0 is .42— ^—0 g.23- u-0 ts.80- 8-0 Mr. H.H. Lipp.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, February 9, 1942, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Our Shipping Notice #1-25 : Return of 12 Smpty Carbon Dioxide cylinders to Bombay I enclose herewith two certificates covering return of : 12 Empty Carbon Dioxide cylinders to Bombay. These have been shipped per M.S. 'ARENA' which sailed from Bahrein on February 5th. 1942. 539* imaii Itvm please return the certificates duly attested at your convenience, debiting charges to our account. Yours very truly, M. H. LIPP Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. EWG:MI Attachment 2. c.c. Acctg.2. Storehouse.2vjk* v THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 1, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. February 4, 1942 FILE 835 PA - 938 re. POWERS OF ATTORNEY 2^ A ri V • l V 'V A H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We acknowledge receipt of your letter #180-5/3 dated 31st. January 1942 enclosing 1. The duly cancelled originals of substitute powers granted by Mr. M.H. Lipp, under his power of attorney dated 19th October 1938, in favour of Messrs. W.P. Anderson, J.T. Deane, Robert Cameron. 2. Tie duly registered, linked and attested original and five copies of each of three substitute powers granted by Mr. MJJ. Lipp, under his power of attorney dated 17th October 1941, in favour of Messrs. J.T. Deane, E.N. Phillips and Robert Cameron respectively. 3. One duly certified copy of each of the powers of attorney for the Sheikhdom of Bahrein granted by the Board of Directors of the Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd. on 17th October 1941, in favour of Messrs. M.H. Lipp and E.N. Phillips respectively. ( r 4, The original power of attorney for the Sheikhdom j-s. of Bahrein, granted by the Board of Directors of the Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd. on 17th October 1941 in favour of Mr. M.H. Lipp, which had been forwarded for your scrutiny when registering the substitute powers mentioned in 2.I The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. February 17, 1942. No. PA-970. File 835 POWERS OF ATTORNEY His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir We enclose six copies of Substitute Power of Attorney authorized by Milton Kickethier Lipp, Attorney in Fact (The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited) for Ward P. Anderson, Manager Operations, for registration. Substitute Power of Attorney, we attach Mr. Llpp’s own Power of Attorney dated October 17th 1941 from which you will observe, upon referring to Clause 10, that he is authorized by the Board of Directors to make such subs titutions. and debit our account in the usual manner with charges incurred. In support of Mr. Lipp’s issuance of the Please return all copies at your convenience, M. H. LIPP. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LIMITED. // Attach: cc- Acctg. 2 Inves. &amp; Sys.2 _ 3&gt;7 No. -3 3^ -5/3 Political Agency, Bahrain, 24th February, 1942. of power of Attorney in favour of Mr. W.P. Anderson, forwarded under cover of your letter No.PA-970 dated the 17th February, 1942, and shall be glad if you will p ease have them signed by the Attorney in Fact and the witnesses and forward the same to this Agency for registration. To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, I return, herewith, the six copies Yours faithfully, \ for Political Agent, Bahrain I ,A.P.A. The attached document has been executed by Siadi bin Yusuf in favour of Ahmad bin Jasim to whom he owed Rs.950/-. Siadi requests that the document may be attested by the Agency. May the signature of the Qazi be attested pi?C. 12.37. f TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES: BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED . DIRECTORS: Lord Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) A. Agnew, C.B.E. R. Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser. C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy J. A. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) R. W. Sailers J. Sklirc . P/CA.3/2868 CONFIDEHTIAT. BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 7th March, 1942. H.B.M. T s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, INCREASES OF CAPITAL We enclose herewith certified copies, in duplicate, of a Resolution authorising an increase of Capital of the following Companies:- Petroleum Development (Qatar)Ltd from £600,100 to £660,100. Petroleum Development (Trucial from £178,100 Coast) Ltd. to £190,100. We shall he grateful if these increases can he registered in due course in accordance with the usual Bahrain procedure. We forward herewith Rs.5/- being the registration fees. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on hehalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITEDNo .427-5/3 Political Agency, Bahrain. 10th March, 1942. The undermentioned documents are forwarded to the Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain, duly registered, with reference to his letter No .P/CA .3/2868 dated 7th March, 1942. • Resolution dated 20th November, 1941, for increase of capital from £.600,100 to £.660,100 2. Resolution dated 20th November, 1941, for increase of capital from £.178,100 to £190,100. tor Political Agent, Bahrain. /v *6A * A Tt \ . p * HEAD OFFICE: 122. LEADEN HALL STREET, L0ND0N.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS- GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEYS COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEYS SECOND PHRASE CODE. Grav, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: BUS R E H. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ (for BANDAR-SHAH POUR) BUSHIRE. « 1 /% / *«AS TANURA. BUNDER-ABBAS. LING AH. BAH REIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. M U SC AT 2 ^/ IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE n 0 . L/20^:. Bahrein, 14th Larch, 19 42. A The Political .tgent, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, We enclose herewith Certificates of Origin in respect of shipments of cylinders of Butane shipped to Bombay per the ss. M Barala n and tne 'Pronto' and shall be glad if you will endorse same and return tne certificates to us as soon as possible. Yours faithfully,504 No j4ee-5/3 Political Agency, Bahrain* 19th March, 1942• To Messrs* Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co*, Ltd*, Bahrain* Dear Sirs, Please refer to your letter No.L/202 date 1 the 14th March, 1942. 2 . I shall be grateful if you will forward as* 5/- on account of the endorsement fees for the service rendered* Yours faithfully, ' Vj, for Political Agent, Bahrain.The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, February 28, IS42. PA-987. Av . J His Britannic Majesty’s Political Bahrein. Agent, Dear ^ir, With reference to your letter Nof 334-5/3 of February 24, 1942, we regret that the substitute Power of attorney in favour of Mr. W. P. Anderson has inadver tently been sent to you unsigned. Y/e are now returning the document in question duly signed for favour of necessary action. Thanking you. C THE BAKH3IN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.5~7 No.638-5/3 The Political Agent, Bahrain presents his compliments to and has the honour to forward the undermentioned documents i- c * The Agency, Reference to previous correspondence* His letter No .PA-970 and 987 dated 17th February and 28th February, 1942, respectively. 1. Substitute power of Attorney in f/o Mr.^.P.Anderson duly registered and linked. 2. 6 - copies of above duly attested. 3. Mr. M.H.LipJiJg Power of Attorney dated 17-10-41. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Bahrain Dated 24th March, 1942. Details of fees . ^ Registration fee fis.2- 8-0 Linking fee '2- 8-0 Attestation fee Rs.12- 8-0 Copying fee ts.14- 0-0 te.14- 0-0 Rs.31- 8-0C.12.37. TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS: Lord Cadmaw, G.C.M.Oi (Ckmirmon) A. Agoow, C.-S.-E,- (^. 4.C CfH-J.nrs R. Cayfol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser. C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) I. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy h A. Meny (frmrii) H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skl-os P/CA.3/2873 CONFIDENTIAL H.B.M.’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 14th March, 1942. COPIES OF RESOLUTIONS We shall be grateful if you will kindly return a copy each of the Resolutions authorising increases of Capital of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, sent to you for registration under our No.PCL/CAA.3/ 2735 dated the 25th November, 1941. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED MANAGER EPA.No./43/5/c Politicel /gency Bahrein, . ^ The 2br(5 March 194 C 25 * To The Manager, * Petroleum Concessions Limited Bahrein. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No.P/C// g/2873,dated the 14th March 1942, I 'm to inform you you that the Resolutions referred to in your letter; quoted ehove to n rff — ere not trcceshle.K. ^ ' thrr ':. T ,. -n r ^-.r-ci pH t'jOU^ 111 kindly send f copy of these resolutions '3Wh U-c necessary action will he taken afiaaisdittpiy* icurs faithfully J d For Political Agent,Bahrein•* THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, March 24, 1942. 7. C/O (Zto? His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. We enclose Mr. J. T. Deane’s Power of Attorney as registered in your office on the 28/1/1942 for revocation as at March 23rd, 1942. We would appreciate your recording the revocation of the cancelled power and returning same to us in due course. Please debit our account in the usual manner with any charges incurred. Yours very truly, M. H. LIPP. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.'MA; THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED ^ Awali Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. 24th March IS42 A*- No «PA-47 iH£ BRITANNIC LAJESTT’S POLITICAL ACLI.T t Bahrein. Lear Sir: Further to our PA-987 dated February 28th 1942 We shall be very grateful if you would let us have Mr. W. P. Anderson’s Pov/er of Attorney duly registered as early as possible. Chief Local Representative Tm BAIRS IN PETROLEUM CCMPAITY LII;JTED IICC/YABalnea in- 26th March, 1942. A The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain- Dear Sir, Substitute Power of Attorney forwarded with your letter No-FA-46 dated the 24th March, 1942, is returned herewith duly cancelled- 2- Please acknowledge receipt- &lt;5 Yours faithfully, Ima- Political Agent, Bahrain.the Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Await, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. March 2, 1942 5-? RETURN OF EMPTY CYLINDERS, OLD TANK CLEANING MACHINES No,PA-991 &amp; ENGINE PARTS His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir I enclose herewith 8 Certificates covering return of the following to New York: 20 - Empty Acetylene Cylinders 3 - Old Butterworth Tank Cleaning Machines 79 - Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders - large 1 - Full Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinder with defective valve 14 - Empty Oxygen Cylinders 6 - Small Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders 1 - Box - 5 Crankpin Bearings for Fairbanks Morse Diesel Engine 3 - Empty Freon Cylinders 3 - Empty Nitrogen Cylinders at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. These have been shipped per S.S. 'MOBILE CITY' which sailed from Bahrein on February 24, 1942. Please return the Certificates duly attested Yours very truly M. H. LIPP CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMETED EWG: MD Attachment cc Acctg.(2) Storehouse (15)THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, March 3, 1942 OUR SHIPPING NOTICE #2-14 RETURN OF EMPTY CYLINDERS PA-997 TO NEW YORK Political Agent, Manama. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of: 1 anpty Cylinder, Calol Industrial #2 Gas 1 Mpty Butane Cylinder 2 Eiiipty Propane Cylinders to New York. These have been shipped per S.S. 'Mobile City' which sailed from Bahrein on February 24, 1942. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. Yours very truly, * / THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWG:PJG. Attachment cc. Acctg. 2 Storehouse 2 [Iji/iAA** jri • ■M&gt;iThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. March 5, 1942 PA-4 £~ f(? S-fi/ifX- His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I am attaching hereto a certificate of residence in my name which I would appreciate having attested by yourself and returning to me at the earliest opportunity. Kindly debit our account with any charges in this connection. M. H. LIPP. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Attach:TO VHOM IT MAY CONCERN ; March 5, 1942• This Is to certify that Mr. M. H. Lipp, General Manager of The Bahrein Petroleum Company, Limited, has been resident In Bahrein since 1936. “??7- // M. H. Lipp General Manager THE BAHRAIN PETROLSUM COMPANY LIMITED. t*mm~ •JF***'- rTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. PA-7 6th March, 1942 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith original and one copy of certificates for attestation, relative to our employees Dr. B. A. Kennedy, Hi chard R. RohMns and Norman A. Janke I hereby certify that the statements contained therein are true and correct. Please debit our account in the usual manner for any charges incurred in this connection. Yours very truly, // ri M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Representative. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. ■Cs 3 (V;Awali, 6th Ilaroh, 1942. TO WHOM IT I4AY CONCERN This is to certify that Dr, Roger Anthony Kennedy, Chief Uedical Officer of this company, has been employed in Bahrein since 1937, Q r# Kennedy is a British subject. t??- M. H. LIFP General Onager THS BAHREIN FSTROLSUL: COMPANY, LTD. F\tt £ %r £l&gt;. 'jr. S JT*. pJLod Am*; ^ ^ *TO 'HOM IT ?/AY COI4Ql^ This is to certify that Mr* Richard R. Robbins, an American citizen, has been an employee of this company since 1936. ^ 7 ^. // • Um H. LIl^P General Manager, THS BAHKSIN FSTHOLSUI/' COMPANY, LTD. tAwali, 6th March, 1942* TO WHO!.. IT ^iY OONOERN This is to certify that Mr* Korraan A* Janke, an American citizen, has been an employee of this company since 1936. M. H. LIFP General Manager THE BAHRU IN JETROLISUK COMTANY LTD. X (&amp;**** - ■ * I jm:3W is~&gt;VA THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A. w a 1 i, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. March 26, 1942 PA-56 -KEftjRN OF IMPTY CYL3NDEBS TO NSW YORK His Britannic Majesty^s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir t of: I enclose herewith Certificate covering return 18 Bnpty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to New York. These have been shipped per S.S. M Steel Mariner' which sailed from Bahrein on M&amp;rch 17, 1942. Please return the^Certificate duly attested, at your earliest convenience,/debiting charges to our account. Yours very truly, ' rSa ’ MC:PJG. Attachment cc. Accounting (2) Storehouse (2) W. P. ANDERSON CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMIT32) - k- Vrr LThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited A w a 1 i Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, March 29, 1942 RIJIUEN OF HMFIY CARBON PA-61 DIOXIDE CYLINDERS \ His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith three Certificates covering shipment of: to Bombay which are being shipped per Tanker ?, Capt.A.F.IUCA3 ,, sailing on or about April 3, 1942. Please return the Certificates duly attested at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. 21 Qnpty Carbon Dioxide Cylinders Yours very truly, CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED MGlPJGr. Attachments Accounting ( 2 ) Storehouse ( 2 ) cc.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awali, 3 Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, March 28th, 1942. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I attach substitute Power of Attorney for myself recently registered in your office for revocation. This is not required as I brought back with me full powers under seal. I would appreciate, therefore, if you will kindly cancel the attached, returning same to this office in due course and charging us in the usual manner for any fees which may be incurred. Yours very truly, W. P. ANDERSON. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Attach:608 *0.68*5/3 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to *- -fv ’ilie Chief Local Kepresentative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain* and has the honour to send him sxnjqc the undermentioned documentsduly cancelled* The Agency, Bahrain* Dated 5th April, 1942* Reference to previous correspondence His letter n©.PA-58 dated 28th Iterch, 1942. Cancelled substitute powers of attorney in favour of Mr* 7.P. Anderson.C.12.37. TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN V-6 t, COOES: BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE 76. PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS: Lord Cadman, G.C.M.G. rd Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) Atm.., Grft.E. R. Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser, C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenklan (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy JrArMewy (f—nrh) H. G. Seidel (LLS.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros &amp; RECEIPT^&gt;\v BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF P/5 P/CA.3/2905 3^ ^ Persia^ 30th March, 1942. H. B. M,*s Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir, REGISTRATION OF DOCUMENTS With reference to your No.543-5/3 dated the 25th March 1942, we enclose herewith one certified copy and one uncertified copy of each of the Resolutions concerned. We shall be pleased if you will return us one copy of each duly registered. In this connection, we note that we have already sent you the fee of Rs.5/- which was acknowledged in our peon book. Will you please inform us if you require 1 another Rs.5/-. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED MANAGER Encls^ iAA/; ' ^ epa. &lt;;•‘i'he agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain. \ and has the honour to send him xxnfija/ the undermentioned documents.&gt; duly registered^ The Agency, Bahrain. \ 'Jated 5th April, 1942. N Heference to previous correspondence His letter No .P/CA .3/2905 dated 30th torch, 1942 1. P.D. (T.C.) Ltd., Hesolution dated 21st August,1941. 2. * ^ ) ' 17th July, 1941.The Bahrein petroleum company limited Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. April 8, 1942, RETURN OF ONE BAILEY RATIO No.PA-85, CONTROLLER TO NEW YORK His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, Manama* Dear Sir, of: I enclose herewith Certificate covering return 1 Bailey Ratio Controller to New York. This will he shipped per S.S. 'ENSLEY CITY TT sailing about end of April 1942* Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. Yours very truly. W. P* ANDERSON CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE ETO:MD THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Attachment cc Acctg. (2) Storehouse (2) ^ Ctt-t-rfb ^ 9. 4-. \&gt;cJ&amp;oL clTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a I i Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, April 6 , 1942 PA-79 RSTCPN OF MPTY ACID CARBOYS TO BOMBAY His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, to Bombay. These have been shipped per Tanker ,T CAPT.A.F.^JCAS ,, which sailed from Bahrein on April 6 , 1942. your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at Yours very truly W. P. ANDERSON CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWGrlPJC. Attachment cc. Accounting (2) Storehouse (2)the Bahrein petroleum company limited iEPA-147 . Avail, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, May 4, 1942* SHUMENT OF EMPTY ACID CARBOYS TO BOMBAY. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering shipment of: 290 Bnpty Acid Carboys to Bombay. These will be shipped per Tanker W CAPT. A. F. LUCAS” sailing on or about May 10, 1942. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE EWG:MD THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Attachment cc Acctg.(2) Storehouse (2) H.Q Registration and copying of dociuaents, fees etb. II 1. -(a) No spelific rules governing the copying or registration fees have been expressly applied to Bahrain. Under s.78 -(a) and (c) of the Indian Registration Act (the Act is not applicable to Bahrain and can only be used as a guide), ouch fees shall be fixed by the Local Government. But P.A. is, also, a Consul under Article 75 -(iii) of the Bahrain order in Council and as such it is one of his functions (Chapt XXIX, para, 8 (iii) to make or verify copies of documents and certifying the same to be true iiiisimn.■; and if there are no rules i s.S:/- II ii made, or fees fi^ed, by the Local Government, we can charge tno fees tabulated in the Consular Instructions (Chapter IX, annexe 2) according to which the following fees are chargeable (1) Item No.102: Pee for making or verifying a copy of a document, if not exceeding 100 words, exlcusive of fee for certificate (seeNo.74| S.-/2/6 (2) Item No.103: If exceeding that number, for excry subsequent 100 words or fraction thereof /3) Item No.74: See No.(l) above. P 0 r certifying to a copy of any document or part of a document if not exceeding 100 words (JfJ Item No.75: if exccdding 100 words, for any additional loo words or fraction thereof -(b) There is no objection to persons registering documents sending spare Copies alongwith the original and wo need not insist on making the copies ourselves as there is no provision for it. But if wc are asked to attest correctness, we have to charge foes a B mentioned under l-(a) above. s .5/« S.V-2 ?| 2* Powei's of attorney in general are not mentioned in the documents registration whereof fcs compulsory under s.17 of the Indian Registration Act; but a power of attorney to recover rents of immovable property for the donmo's benefit or a power of attorney giving the donee aohargc upon the property requires registration as explained in a note to the aforesaid section on p. 40. So powers of attorney which do not, fall under the second category need not be registered. Please also peruse note to s.l marked A on p.3. 3. If three copies arc made, one for the Agency, one for the Company and one for the Bank; it is essential that all the three copies should be attested and stamped, provided the copies are made by us. But if tne Copies are sent by the Company and we are not asked to attest them, we need not bother. The Bamc can have an unstamped copy, if they agree to it, but the Bank will not be at liberty at all times to inspect a document in the register because, for instance, a will or an authority to adopt cannot be inspected by any body before the executant dies unless fl it an agent of the executant (s.57-(2) read with c. &gt;52&gt;(1)- (A) of the Indian Registration Act.) The question of powers of attorney has been dealt with in para 2 above and substituted powers of attorney should be treated in a similar manner.No•958-5/3 Political Agency, To Bahrain, the 28th May 1942. The Chief Local Representative, » The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Before Mr. Jackson left Bahrain he recorded a note that your Company had made verbally a number of en quiries from him concerning copying fees, registration of documents etc. I understand that the questions you asked were as follows. 1(a) On what scale are copying fees charged by the Agency? (b) Is there any objection to persons desiring to have documents registered sending spare copies to be posted in the Agency Register in order to save the cost of copying fees? 2. Is it essential that Powers of Attorney executed in England or the U.S.A. should be registered in the Agency in order for them to be legally valid? 3. If 3 copies of registered documents are made (i.e. one for the Agency, one for the Company and one f or the use of the Bank) is it legally necessary that all 3 copies should be attested and stamped? It was suggested that as the Bank were at liberty to inspect the registered copy of a document in the Agency it would be sufficient for them to receive an unstamped copy, 2• The ansv/ers to these enquiries are as follows 1(a) The authorised scale of copying and other fees is as follows: for the first 100 words and as.8/- for every subsequent IOC words or fraction thereof. (ii) Registration fee Ps2/8 per document. (iii) Linking fee Rs2/8 per document. (iv) Attestation fee fe2/8 per document. 1(b) 'ihere is no objection to persons desiring to register documents sending a spare copy to be posted in the Agency Register. Such document will how-, ever have to be attested and the attestation fee of Rs2/8 will have to be paid. 2. There is nothing under the law in force in Bahrain which require^ that Powers of Attorneyexecuted in England or the U.S.A. should be registered at the Agency in order to give them legal validity. »vhether a document is com pulsorily registerable is a question which can only be decided by reference to the substantive law of the country in which it was executed. I regret that I do not know whether Powers of Attorney are^under the laws in force in Great Britain and the United States of America com pulsorily registerable. ' if each of the 3 copies of a registered document is to be legally valid it must be attested and stamped. It is unlikely that the Bank would accepc an unstamped copy since such a copy would have no legal validity. Moreover the Bank are not at liberty to inspect documents in the Agency Begister since such documents can only be inspect- e i one executors or by the presiding Oxiicer of a Court of Competent Jurisdiction. Certain documents included in the Register e.g. a will or an autnority to adopt .cannot be inspected by anyone prior to the death of the executor. Yours TrulyThe Bahrein petroleum Company limited A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. May 5, 1942 RETCEN OF EMPTY ANHYDROUS PA-154 miWIA CYLINDERS TO NEST YORK His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of: 30 Bnpty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders to New York. These will be shipped per S.S. ,f Ensley City' sailing during May 1942. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. WG'.PJG. Attachment Yours very truly, CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED cc. Accounting (2) Storehouse (2) - cLJLJcj y Vh- L .V ^ \r~- THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering return of: to Nev; York. These will be shipped per S.S. M 3nsley City w sailing during May 1942. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account• A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. May 10, 1942 PA-162 RETUEN of empty anhydrous AMMONIA CYLINDERS TO NEV/ YORK 10 Bupty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders Yours very truly W. .F. ANUElKSUN CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED MG:PJC. Attachment cc. Accounting (2) Storehouse (2)th hrein petroleum company limited Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. May 19 til, 1942. PA-178 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein. Bear Sir, It is requested that Mr. ¥. P. Anderson’s signature on two copies of each of the attached letters may he certified, and the copies returned to this office. A third copy of each letter is also attached for your files. Please deduct your fee for this service from the Company’s deposit in your office. ¥. P. AFJEKSON, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LED. AA#ali, 19tn, 1942. TO IT HAY GOaC., ^: This is to certify that Hr. Charles is an employee of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Li:riite&lt;l. Ur. ^ntelhart has ueen in Bahrein since November, 1939, occupyln£ the position of Head Mechanic, and is now returning to tho United otates on leave* AA;B TH3 BAH 1 KIN X LIMrCKI) *. P. UA1IAO,;, t OPillflSla ♦ * *'*5.# Hi Certified that the signature narked 'A' above is that of Mr. w.p.Anderson. for Political Agent, Bahrain.A^ali, May 19th, 1942 This is to certify that ? lr. Ralph festhrook MOooMAM is an employee of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. Mr. Mossman has “been in Bahrein since Novemhur, 1939, occupying the position of Chief Metallurgist, and is now returning to the United States on leave. A ibAwali, May 19tii, 1942. Mr. H. II. Mangold, The Texas Company, Lagos, Nigeria. Lear Sir, This will introduce Mr. Ralph Westbrook MOSv^&amp;AN, an American employee of this Joinpany who is proceedi ng on leave to the United states. Would you please purchase for Mr. Mossman transportation by Pan American Airways system from Lagos to New York, and afford him any other assistance of which he may be in need. Mr. Mossman is being given an additional copy of this letter to present to Pan American Airways re presentative i-- Lagos, should you be absent from Lagos on his arrival there. Yours very truly, -a. p. axe .30;;, n op^yAT ions AA:3 co- Pan American Airways Representative, Lagos, Nigeria. certified that the signature marked ’A* abtsve is that of Mr* ' .p .Anderson* \ V \May 19th, 1942 Mr. B.H. Mangold, The Texas Company Lagos, Nigeria. -ear Sir This will introduce Mr. Charles BNCSLHAST an American employee of this Company who is proceeding on leave to the United 3ta.tes. ffould you please pur chase for Mr. Jingelhart transportation hy Pan American Airways system from Lagos to New York, and afford him any other assistance of which he may he in need. copy of this letter to present to Pan American Airways representative in Lagos, should you he absent from Lagos on his arrival there. Hr. lingeihart is being given an additional Yours very truly P. -NIK i3CN, UANA3.-; •. OPX U. XO, - ^ An jB cc - Pan American Airways Representative, Lagos, Nigeria. Certified that the signature marked •A 1 above is that of .Anderson for Political Agent f Bahrain*C^V d THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. May 19, 1942# SHIPMENT OF EMPTY ACID CARBOYS No.PA-179. TO BOMBAY. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate covering shipment of: 110 Einpty Acid Carboys to Bombay. These will be shipped per Tanker M CAPT. A. F. HJCAS M sailing on or about May 20, 1942. Please return the Certificate duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. Yours very truly. CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWG:MD Attachment cc Acctg.(2) Storehouse (2) iN. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 1&gt; Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. April 30, 1942 PA - 157 FILS 835 PCWSRS OF ATTORNEY His Britannic Majesty’s Political i^ent Bahrein. /o/3 Dear Sir, We are enclosing herewith an original Power of Attorney granted by the Board of Directors of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, on Hth December, 1941, for the Sheikhdom of Bahrein in favour of Mr* W.P. Anderson and expiring on 31st December, 1945. We shall be glad if you will register this Power and return it to us at your early convenience, charging us in usual manner with any fees that may have been incurred. In order to avoid the necessity of copying the Power into your register we are enclosing a copy for retention in your files Yours very truly, cc. Acctg. 2 Imres .&amp; Sys , IaCIola.Cu+. W,p. ANDERSON •CHIEF LOCAL. REPRESENT AT IVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED\ \. i. ^4 No.992-5/3 Political Agency, Bahrain. Date 6 th June, ‘X 3 s - The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to : — The Chief Local -Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. and has the honom to transmit to him the undermentioned document A sum of cis. 2 / 8 /- has been debited to your deposit account. Reference to previous correspondence His letter No .PA-137 dated 30th April, 1942 No. &amp; date of enclosure Power of Attorney in favour ~jof Mr. Ward Payne Anderson. - &lt;!^4 Subject Registration of documents.Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE: 122, LEADEN HALL STREET, LONDON.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS. GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BUSREH. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH I RE. RAS TANURA. EL KHOBAR. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAH REIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. M U SCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. L/422, Bahrein, 3rd Juno, 19 42 in The Political Agent, \ po H 7 3 ? Dear Jir, We enclose herewith two Certificates of Origin for snipments of 75 cylinders Eutane and 14 cylinders Butane to be made per the “Pronto' to Bombay, for favour of endorsement and return to tnis office as early as possible. Yours faithfully, For G Co.,Ltd. Manager. L PM.No, 984-5/3 Political Agency, Bahrain. Date 4th June, *942 7^ The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to ;\ Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain . and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document (s) rluly endorsed. A sum of ns.5/- may^be forwarded to this office on account of the endorsement fees. T X Reference to previous correspondence Their letter NO.IV422 dated 3rd June, 1942. No. &amp; date of enclosure Subject 1. (Jertificate of origin dated 2nd June, 1942, re garding contents (Butane) of 75 cylinders 2. Certificate of origin dated 2nd June, 1942, regarding 14 gas cylindei|s Attestation of Certificate of Origin. \ a s ( j ,^ 7THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, June 1, 1942. FILE 835 PA - 202 A re REGISTRATION OF DOCUMENTS a* ♦ / -^7 ^ — His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We thank you for your letter #958-5/3 dated 28th May 1942, answering the queries which we raised with Mr. Jackson concerning the registration of documents. It seems that our present practice of registering all powers of attorney, irrespective of whether they are original or substitute powers, is the most satisfactory course to pursue. Chief Local Representative cc. Acctg. 2 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Wjm / . L fj | No,984-5/3 7 5 ^ Political Agency, Bahrain. Date4th June, 1942 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to : — Messrs- Gray, Ifeickenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him the^mdenpentioned document (s) duly endorsed. A sum of us.5/- ma^/be forvyarded to this office on account of the endorsement fees. Reference to previous correspondenoe Their letter No.1/422 dated 3rd June, 1942. No. &amp; date of enclosure Subject 1 . Certificate of origin dated 2nd June, 1942, re garding contents (Butane) of 75 cylinders 2. Certificate of origin dated 2 nd June, 1942, regarding 14 gas cylinder^ Attestation of Certificate of Origin.4 ' u S' ?) ($ fc&lt;J fv* PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. 15tli June, 194£. Dear ^ClfVtyit^Lf With reference to our conversation this morning, I enclose herewith the Priority Certificates which you so kindly agreed to endorse. ar Will you please return the two sets marked w Original w and 'Duplicate** and retain the set marked 'For P.A.'. The messenger bringing these docu ments can wait and bring them back if this is any convenience to your peon service. Yours sincerely. Ends. E.B.Wakefield, Esq., I.C.S., H.B.M.’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Certificates endorsed and submitted for signature pi. May charge &amp; 6/- urgent attendance fee pi. f' - J 15/6/42f'ri LIST OF PRIOHITY CEHTXFICAT 33 ?ROM P.D.q . QATAR SUBMITTED TO THE POLITICAL AGSNT BAHRAIN. ON THE 13TH JOWB. 1942 . COPY, COPY. ■■ |i . pp j Q’RTT^Y’ j ORDER NO. | DATED | DES ^ T ?^2JL 0F I CERT: NO. I REMARKS j j EQUIPMENT | ALLOTTED 1 Q/832 22 . 5.40 Spare Engine &amp; Winch Parts for Internatiom Gummins Diesel Truck j.'] '3^//- £ 11 Q/889 12 . 11.41 Laboratory Equipment for Drilling Fluid Re search« Q/892 19. 5.41 Chains, Sprockets and General Spares for Drilling Rig Q/ 899 28. 8.41 High Pressure Valves and Fittings for Oil Well Head Connections Q/901 24. 9.41 Laboratory Equipment for Geological and Drilling Fluid Re search. L/t-S Q/ 904 24. 9.41 Spare Pinions and Bearing for Drilling Rig. Q/ 908 26. 1.42 Casing, Cementing shoes* Landing Head, Wire Lines, Valves, 'Well Head Fittings. //-a 4£^7/nT-State the importance of this installation to the defense of the APPLICATION FOh PRIORITY DSUTW Of OUBF.1R (To be mibmitted in duplicate) i • The Information given below pertains to the following equipment: .?4?T?.«3?.pnm4TIOT«TCWW5.5rt3Bt.T80Cr pl» 0 «a with the JJSAS JW3S JJSSSMBIOJn:.GOSEQSiXIClH’’S^rt Department; shipment of which is desired on .^15^ .... A* If this equipment is desired for filling a contract with the Awy, Nary» Air Force, or other Agency of the United States Government; Nome of Government Supply Arm or Bureau is , Project or Contract Number la • •. Contract was placed with Equipment is to be used for B* If this equipment is desired for filling a contract with the Army, Navy, Air Force, or other Agency of the Local Government: Name of Local Government Supply Am or Bureau is Project or Contract number is Contract was placed with Equipment is to be used for C» If this equipment is desired for use for Defense purposes but is not being supplied tinder contract with either United States or Local Government: Location where equipment is to be Installed Equipment la to be used for D, If this equipment is desired for purposes other than those listed above: Location where equipment is to be installed • •*i4T4$9 •9TOT• • • Name of Customer is .• Nationality of Customer la Business of Customer is • •.• . WiVl’QWQfT ••••••••••••«••••• Equipment is to be used for !• (This information is VERY important if equipment falls into Group LTD., TRANSPORT FLEET C or D l) ,- 2 - Local CrOTenmusnt or to the economy of your Country, or any other ' facts outlining the importance of the installation PFTOLro (QATAR) LTD. t .T9. ^ .9LT^ . W???. ??WI4TI9 N .W.Wn«.Q&lt;JTOWm.T5WW5.?OT-m5«..... RESIDKRT IK PERSIAN GOLF * Ke certify that the facts herein set forth are believed to be true and correct. Date. 16 - rt Vltness C t In /’ \ Name of Ctampany FOR AND ON BEHALF OF PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED. (Sgd.) E. r. Packer, By Name '•'WkfcW Title Form PR-1 No.1063-36/l-B Dated 15th June 1942. Certified that the equipment specified above is urgently required for the operations of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, an undertaking which has been declared essential to the prosecution of the T far •State the importance of this installation to the defense of the APPLICATION FOR PRIORITY DELIVERY OF ORDER (TO b« submitted in duplicate) r The information given below pertains to the following equipment: .. J^UIPlJKNT TOR ^DRpXDJG ^ELUn) RESEARCH placed With tha department; shipment of which is desired on • .^7^ ^HIPPING .SPACE ^AVAILABLE......... A* If this equipment is desired for filling a contract with the Army, Navy, Air Force, or other Agency of the Ohited States Government; t Name of Government Supply Arm or .Bureau is Project or Contract Number is Contract was placed with Equipment is to be used for If this equipment is desired for filling a contract with the Array, Navy, Air Force, or other Agency of the Local Government: Name of Local Government Supply Arm or Bureau is Project or Contract number is Contract was placed with Equipment is to be used for If this equipment is desired for use for Defense purposes but is not being supplied under contract with either United States or Local Government: Location where equipment is to be installed If this equipment is desired for purposes other than those listed above: Location where equipment is to be installed . Name of Customer is vW . M4T4?] .LTP» BL (This information is VERY important if equipment falls into Group It is covered by our order number dated Nationality of Customer is Equipment is to be used for Business of Customer la • • .9y7?WS*IOTr CONTROL TOR DRUXIMJ OIL WELLS Equipment is to be used for C or D l)•COPY, Loeal Ck&gt;T«mment or to the econony of your Country, or any other facts outlining the Inportance of the Installation f^ (W) ^LTD •, DECLARED 4N ENDERTittCTUC .9^ .K???? .^.??T?M.99Y^WW.TOTO^.?QinTQ41 RESIDENT IN PERSIAN OtJLF We certify that the feots herein set forth are believed to be true and correct* Date .. . / . 4 . V.. «Hi and on BSetttjr^r CoBipany PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED, OSjtf.) E. Name V. Packer. aeeaaaeeaeeee *-# &gt; rave TiUe ?onu PR-1 No. 1084-38/l-B Dated 15th June 1942. Certified that the equipment specified above is urgently required for the operations of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, an undertaking which has been declared essential to the prosecution of the War®State the importance of this Installation to the defense of the A m J CATT O N FOR P^IOHITY DEUTOnr OF ORDER (To b« submitted in duplicate) The infonaation given below pertains to the following equipment: CHAINS, SPRflCOTS AND GMERAL SPARES FOR DRILLING RIG It is covered by our order nuiaber ..?/???. dated placed with the 7 ?^. 1^7. S^rt Departomt; shipment of which Is desired on ..™?T.??????».??«7.5T«f^. A. If this equipment is desired for filling a contract with the Any, Navy, Air Force, or other Agency of the United States Government; Name of Government Supply Arm or Bureau la • Project or Contract Number is Contract was placed with • Equipment ia to be used for B. If this equipment is desired for filling a contract with the Amy, Navy, Air Force, or other Agency of the Local Governments Name of Local Government Supply Arm or Bureau is Project or Contract number is Contract was placed with Equipment is to be used for C. If this equipment is desired for use for Defense purposes but is not being supplied under contract with either United states or Local Government: Location where equipment is to be installed Equipment is to be used for D. If this equipment is desired for purposes other than those listed above: Location where equipment is to be installed .7K Name of Customer is PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (CATAR) LTD. E. Nationality of Customer is Business of Customer is Equipment is to be used PETROLEUM DETOOttOTr # SERVICING OIL WELL DRILLING RIG IN USE fo wntf Wfaomh* ‘(qatah)* itd.* (This information is VERY important if equipment falls into Group C or D l)$/892 - 2 - (' 5 &lt;o: COPY. Local OoTernment or to the economy of your Country, or any other facte outlining the importance of the installation PETROLEUM DESTELOPMUTr (QATAR) LTD, DEDLARKD AN UNDERTAKING ESSENTIAL TO THE PROSECUTION 0? THE WAR UNDER DEFENCE REGULATION NO,2 OF 1942 ISSUED BY BRITISH GOVEH&amp;OTT THROUGH POLITICAL RESIDENT IN PERSIAN GULF We certify that the facta herein set forth are believed to be true and correct. FOR AND ON Company PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED, {Sgd.') E. V. Packer. By Name Manager. »Al-if&gt;ilN. Title Form PR-1 No. 1065-36/1-B Dated 15th June 1942. Certified that the equipment specified above is urgently required for the rperations of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, an undertaking which has been declared essential to the prosecution of the War. .State the importance of this installation to the defense of the e e e e e e e T APPLICATION FOR PHIORITY DELIVKHY Of ORDER (To b« submitted in duplicate) COPY. The information giyen below pertains to the following equipment: •• HIGH PRESSURE VALVES AND FITTINGS FOR OH WELL HEAD CONNECTIONS It is covered by our order number • • • ?/???, dated 2 .®.Vi .^ 7 ??.^ pl» 0 «d with the KVrt .WJ. Department; shipment of which is desired on . • • AKT; AVAILABLE A. If this equipment is desired for filling a contract with the Army, Navy, Air Force, or other Agency of the United States Government; Name of Government Supply Aim or Bureau is Project or Contract Number is Contract was placed with Equipment is to be used for ., B. If this equipment is desired for filling a contract with the Army, Navy, Air Force, or other Agency of the Local Government: Name of Local Government Supply Arm or Bureau is Project or Contract number is • • Contract was placed v/lth Equipment is to be used for C. If this equipment is desired for use for Defense purposes but is not being supplied under contract with either United States or Local Government: Location where equipment is to be Installed Equipment is to be used for D. If this equipment is desired for purposes other than those listed above: Location where equipment is to be Installed • • • Name of Customer is .... TOTCOTK .(.QA T M). &lt;OTU Nationality of Customer is Business of Customer is Equipment is to be used for . WWv WM 7PK JWTOWR fifft E. (This information is VERT important if equipment falls into Group C or D l). *- 8 - COPY Q/899 Local Government or to the economy of your Country, or any other facte outlining the importance of the installation PyTRCLTO^ DETO.OPMFTTl' _ j QATAR) # LTD. ^ DECLARED # UNDERTAKING ESSpfPlAL TO THE PROSECUTION OF THE WAR UNDER DEFENCE REGULATION NO . 2 # 9 F 1942 # ISSUED # BY # BRITISH^ GOypjljftOTT ^ THROUGH^ POLITICAL RESIDENT IN PERSIAN GULF ■* We certify that the facts herein set forth are believed to be true and correct. B*te is - i&lt;w Witness , Name of Company roe awo on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED. (Sgd.) E. V. Packer. By Name Title ’ - Form PR-1 No. 1066-36/1-B Dated 15th June 1942 Certified that the equipment specified above is urgently required for the operations of Petroleum Development (4iatar) Limited, an undertaking which has been declared essential to the prosecution of the War. v*) State the importance of this installation to the defense of the e e • » e • e / APPLICATION FOR PRIORITY DgLJVEHY OF ORDKR (To be submitted in duplicate) The information given below pertains to the following equipment* LABORATORY TOnWMT FOR GEOLOGICAL AND DRILLING TOHD RESEARCH COPY. It is covered by our order number ...... dated NEW YORK placed »lth the ,/ Report Department; shipsgent of which is desired on • •. A* If this equipment is desired for filling a contract with the Army, Navy, Air Force, or other Agency of the Chi ted States Government; Name of Government Supply Arm or Bureau is Project or Contract Number is Contract was placed with •. Equipment is to be used for If this equipment is desired for filling a contract with the Army, Navy, Air Force, or other Agency of the Local Government: Name of Local Government Supply Arm or Bureau is • • • Project or Contract number is Contract was placed with •. Equipment is to be used for If this equipment is desired for use for Defense purposes but is not being supplied under contract with either United States or Local Government: Location where equipment is to be installed • * Equipment is to be used for D. If this equipment is desired for purposes other than those listed above: Location where equipment is to be installed .. I Name of Customer is ... J5TOWWWPC ♦ W4Jf45i .TO Nationality of Customer is ••.... Business of Customer is Equipment is to be used for .WPP. J&amp;mm . S. (This information is VERT important if equipment falls into Group C or D l). B. C.3 is APPLICATICf? /OH PRIOBIYY r)FXIYT!HY OK ORD?'.P, (To b« srtaltted in duplicate) COPY. The Inforoation given below pertain* to the following equipmenti tffm. ?mm. m. pmmp. m pjwwk*. m. / It le covered bp our order number •••••• ,Q/. 9 P.*. t dated YOnK placed with the •. tQW* PEtTUlTWW, 'Report IJepartjnent j ahlpment of which 1 * desired on 4. If this equipment la desired for filling a contract with the Angr, Mary, Air Force, or other Agency of the tfolted States Government; name of Government Supply Arm. or Bureau la 'Project or Contract Humber Is contract was placed with ^ulpaisnt la to be used for B. If this equipment Is desired for filling a contract with the Amor, Navy, Air Force, or other Agency of the local Governments Name of local aovarzsaent Supply Am or Bureau Is Project or Contract number Is Contract was placed with fquipmant la to be used for C. If thia aquipment la desired for use for Defense puipoaos hut Is rwt being supplied under contract with either United states or Local Government: location where equipment is to be Installed Equipment le to be used for D. If this equipment is desired for purposes other then thoee listed above: Location where equipment Is to be Installed •. • • fVSWAffSfSiW.SP??i • • Name of Custmer is Nationality of Cuatomer Is Business of Customer Is JW73WRW?. Fqul^aent Is to be used for SERVICING OIL WELL DRILLING RIG IN BSE WITH PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT* (.1ATAR) LTD. (Thie Infomation is VERT important If equipment falls Into Group C or D t). Stats the importance of thia Installation to the defense of the* * &lt;4/904 COPY. ' / # / Local Government or to the economy of your Country, or any other fact* outlining the importance of the installation ptooleum DEraopmrr^,( Qatab^ pECLApjp^ an^ undertaking ESSENTIAL TO TOE PPD3ECUTI0N OF THE WAR UNDER DEFENCE REGULATION NO.2 OF 1942 ISSUED BY BRITISH GOVERNMENT THROUGH POLITICAL RESIDENT IN PERSIAN GULF / ^e certify that the facts herein set forth are believed to be true and . so^ct. ■V— Ji Name of Company FOR AND ON BEHALF OF PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED, (Sgd.) E. Y. Packer: By Name ^tte^^' ■I ‘ I 'V n A PH-1 NO. 1068-36/l-B Dated ISth June 1942, . —. ' Certified that the equipment specified above is urgently required for the operations of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited f an undertaking which has been declared essential to the prosecution of the War. 3:\ Political Agent, Bahrain. L Ev gwJi V an- APPLICATIOl? TQU PHIOitlTY D?XXYFI^ CY CRPFJK v COPY (To bo submitted in duplleato) ^ The information given below pertains to the following oqulpeient: CASING, CKMIWTINO SH01S, LANDING HEAD, WIRE LINES, VALVES, WELL HEAD EITTINGS 0/908 26th JWTARY, 1942 It la covered by our order number ••••••••••••••••••» dated •••••••••••••••• .NEW YORE pl*o.d with the .. .1^. /report '•p.rtm.at; FIRST SHIPPING SPACE AVAIT,ABLE shipment of which la dealred on A* If thla aqulpment la dealred for filling a contract with tha \my. Navy, Air Force, or other agency of the Tftiited statea Govemmentj Name of Government Lhapply Aim or Bureau le Project or Contract Number la Contract was placad with Equipment la to be ueed for B. If thia equipment la dealred for filling ® contract with the sjmy, Nevy, Air Force, or other Agency of the local Government! Name of Local Government Supply Arm or Bureau la Project or Contract number is Contract was pieced with Equipment la to be used for C. If thla equipment la desired for use for Defenae purposes but la not balng supplied under contract with either United States or Local Government! Location where equipment la to be installed Equipment la to be used for D. If thia equipment la desired for purposes othsr than those Hated above: ^ * QATAR, PERSIAN GULF Location where equipment le to be installed «**••«••••••••••.••••••»• , ’ PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LTD. Name of Customer la Nationality of Customer la PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT Business of Customer Is , DRILLING OIL WELLS Kqulpwent la to be used for (Thla imfoimation la TfRY Important If equipment falls into Group C or D I) • Stats the importance of this installation to the defense of the o o a • seen N Looal CoT©mw«nt or to the economy of your Country, or any other facts outlining the Inportanec of ths installation ••••••••••••• PFTRDmJM D^VKLOPMOT (QATAB) LTD. DECL/JRED fiN UNDERTAKING ESSENTIAL TO THE PROSECUTION 07 THE WAR UNDER DEFENCE REGULATION NO.2 OF 1942 ISSUED BY BRITISH GOVERNMENT THROUGH POLITICAL RESIDENT IN PERSIAN GULF ftc certify that the facte herein eet forth are Believed to be true and correct. \ s' ' ^ J. / ' x7 \ Date /^&gt; FOR AWD ON BE fiWfoV Ca 'P'V PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED. (Sgd.) E. V. Packev, By •fcMrtfife Nana Title W 4 n Fona PR—1 No. 1069-36/l-B Dated 15th &lt;Tune 1942. Certified that the equipment specified above is urgently required for the operations of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited f an undertaking which has been declared essential to the prosecution of the Wjp*.0 ^ \c9 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, 0 ^ (St? June 14, 1942 -V R ECEIPT^ PA-224 RETURN OF EMPTY CARBCN DIOXIDE CYLINDERS 132-? •• ••Y \ \t*i 'kl&lt;4k- His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith 3 Certificates covering shipment of:- 9 - Bnpty Carbon Dioxide Cylinders &amp; 1 - anpty Nitrogen Cylinder to Bombay, which have been shipped per Tanker S.S. w Ceylon M sailed on 14th June, 1942, Please return the Certificates duly attested at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. Yours very truly. r. P. ANDERSON CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWG:PJG. Attachments. cc. Accounting (2) Storehouse £o\, . ^‘Jut at- -fico ? JL- i\_ 0 L 4 AsLs 6 ^+. &gt; Yii / 6 . 7 /t/- '.J ' hVL LL L :\y n-6ii-TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN JO 1 / CODES: ^ BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASt PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS: Lard CidmiiT ■ C.H.O. -fC(iuiiiimrr) Agni-ii, e.P.e. f 9 // - ^ Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) ' . Fraser, C.B.E. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy J. A. Mewy (French) H. G. Seidel (U.SA.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros 0 P/CA.3/3107 CONFIDENTIAL BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 11th July, 1942. H.B.M. 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, INCREASES OF CAPITAL We enclose herewith certified copies, in duplicate, of a Resolution authorising an increase of Capital of the following Companies Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd. by the creation of 60,000 'B' Ordinary Shares of £.1 each. Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd. by the creation of 10,000 M B W Ordinary Shares of £.1 each. We shall be grateful if these increases can be registered in due course in accordance with the usual Bahrain procedure. K We forward herewith Rs.5/- being the registration fees. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED EndsNo*1247-5/3 }° J Political Agency, Bahrain. Date 15*th July, l 942 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to : — V J ^ \ The Onager, The Petroleum Concession* Limited, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document (s) Reference to previous correspondence Hie letter Ho.P/CA.3/3107 dated 11th July, 1942. of enclosure Subject l.Copy of Resolution d^itedl 6 ti capital of the P.D.(Q) 'imi^' April, 1942 for increase of ed, duly registered. 2.Copy of Resolution dated 161h April, 1942, for increase of capital of the P.D.(T.C.)LiDilt«d, duJy registered.Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE: 122. LEADEN HALL STREET. LON D 0N.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEYS COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BUSREH. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH I RE. RAS TANURA. EL KHOBAR. BUNDER-ABBAS. LING AH. BAH REIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. N REPLY PLEASE QUOTE L/483. No. Bahrain, July 1st 19 42. The Political Agent, Bahrain. ■ J Dear Sir, M.T. 11 RAS TANURA 11 We enclose herewith Qrew List of the above tug in triplicate, and shall be pleased if you will countersign this list and return two copies to us at your earliest convenience. The tug is proceeding to Basra today, and the reason for our request for countersignature of the % crew list is to avoid the possibility of any difficul ties with the Passport Authorities in Iraq. Y 0 urs faithfully,Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co . 7 Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE : 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEYS COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH AM A RA H KUT KHORAMSHAHR A H W A Z BUN DA R-SHAH POUR BUSH IRE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DU BAI SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE no Bahr ain, 11th July, jg The Political Agent, Banrain• Jear Sir, ye enclooe here.vith Certificate of Origin for 14 Butane cylinders, shipped fro.a here per S 3 . 'Barpeta 11 V.301 to Bombay and snail be glad if you will kindly have same endorsed and returned to us as early as possible. Yours faithfully, frcr ‘Ml ft-**- /O. O'A'ZZG ik.h Gray, Mackp;nzie «&amp; Co. Lto. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: BUSREH BUNDER-ABBAS The Political agei.t, Baiirain. Jear ^ir, /e enclose nere.vitii one Certificate of Origin covering 14 cylinders Butane, shipped from here per ss.'pronto' V.lo to Bombay, for favour of endorsement and return to this office as early as possible. Yours faitnfuily,CERTIFICATE OF ORIGIN Bahrein Island, June 2, Persian Gulf. 1942. V/g hereby certify that the fourteen gas cylinders to be shipped in the S.S. w FRONTO H today to Ihe Natural Gas Company Ltd., Bombay, were forwarded empty to us by that Company and that the cylinders have been refilled with Butane, manufactured at Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. THE BAHREIN P3TROIEI3M COMPANY^ I MI TED, ^.P. ANDERSON, MANAGER OPERATIONSZZ£ Gray, Mackknzie &amp; Co. Lm. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: head orricc : 122 LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON. EC.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH BUNDER-ABBAS AMARAH LINGAH KUT BAHREIN KHORAMSHAHR KOWEIT AHWAZ DUBAI BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR SHARJAH BUSHIRE MUSCAT RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE ^anrain, ±lth July, jg 42. ^ \ i X The Political Agent, Bahrain. Bear Sir, tfe shall be obliged if you will kindly treat our letter L/517 of today's date as cancelled, as the Certificate of Origin in question has been duplicated. Yours faithfully,THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, July 11, 1942 PA-274 RETURN OF EMPTY CARBON DIOXIDE CYLINDERS His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith 2 Certificates covering shipment of:- 3 - Empty Carbon Dioxide Cylinders to Bombay, which are being shipped per Tanker S.S.'Ceylon' sailing today. Please return the Certificates duly attested at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to sour account. Yours very truly, THE CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWG:PJG. Attachments cc. Storehouse Accounting (2)Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE : 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. EC.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH AMARAH KUT KHORAMSHAHR Ahwaz BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEA SE Q UOTg „o L/ Bahrain, 18th July, 19 42. The Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, We enclose herewith one Certificate of Origin covering 50 cylinders Butane, shipped from here per ss. M King Yuan ' 1 to Bombay and shall be obliged if you will kindly have same endorsed and returned to us as soon as possible. Yours faithfully, MSGray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) HEAD OFFICE: 122. LEADEN HALL STREET. LONDON.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. tM BRANCHES: BUSREH. BUNDER-ABBAS. AMARAH. LINGAH. KUT. BAHREIN. KHORAMSHAHR KOWEIT AHWAZ DUBAI. BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR SHARJAH. BUSH I RE. MUSCAT. RAS TANURA. EL KHOBAR. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. k/ 3 Bahrain, 20th July, 19 42. The Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, We enclose herewith one Certificate of Origin covering 27 cylinders Butane to be shipped per s.s.'E-Sang M to Bombay for favour of endorsement and return to this office as early as possible. Yours faithfully, MS.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED i/J A w a 1 i Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. July 29, 1942 PA-321 SHIPMENT OF EMPTY CYLINDERS Sc CARBOYS His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith 3 Certificates covering shipment of:- to Bombay, which are being shipped by Tanker. attested at your earliest .convenience, debiting charges to our account. 2 - Empty Nitrogen Cylinders 2 - M Carbon Dioxide Cylinders Sc 250 - ' Acid Carboys Please return the Certificates duly Yours very truly W7 P. ANDERSON CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE TEE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWG:PJG. Attachments cc. Chief Acct. ( 2 ) Storehouse (3)THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. August 10, 1942 PA-340 RETURN OF EMPTY CYLINDERS TO NEW YORK His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. f) rt\ H' Dear Sir, j l We understand the Certificate of Origin attested by you during March 1942, under reference our letter'PA-56, covering shipment of 18 Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders, has been lost in transit. I therefore enclose a copy of this Certificate for endorsement and return at your earliest convenience. Please debit all charges to our account. Yours very truly, CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWGiPJG. Attachment cc. Chief Acct. StorehouseNo .1447-5/3 Political Agency, i: &gt;ahrain. 16th August, 1942. To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, In reply to your letter No .PA-340 dated the 10th August 1942, I regret to have to iiiforai you that I cannot sho^ tie endorsement on the copy of ths? Certificate of Origin in question as hewing been signed in March when the document was presented to me in August. 2 . I suggest therefore that you send me alfrtsfc copy of the document with the original endorsement shown on it, which I will certify as true copy of the original. Yours faithfully, 3 f; l tor Political Agent, BahrainHis Britannic Majesty’s political Agent, Bahrein. A &gt; 7 - Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No.1447-5/3 dated August 16, 1942, I enclose herewith a true copy of the certificate of Origin, as suggested by you. Will you please certify as true copy of the original and return at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. Yours very truly, W. P. ANDSRSON CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWGiANM. Attachment cc. Chief Acct Storehouse7 A w ^ i Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltij. , Ml KI r% I ^ I 5 {i« (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE : 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEYS COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH AMARAH KUT KHORAMSHAHR Ahwaz BUN DAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BUNDER-ABBAS LI NGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE U bS Bahrain, 30th August, 19 42. Dear Sir, We enclose herewith two Certificates of Origin covering 50 and 11 cylinders of Butane, shipped per ss.'Baroda” and one Certificate of Origin for 30 Butane cylinders went forward per ss.'^arala” to Bombay and shall be obliged if you will kindly have same endorsed and returned to us at your earliest convenience. Yours faithfully, For GR MS. Enel: 3 Certificates.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i PA-387 RETURN OE EMPTY CARBON DIOXIDE CYLINDERS * 6 Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, August 31, 1942 His Britannic Majesty^ political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith certificate covering shipment of:- 6 - Empty Carbon Dioxide cylinders to Bombay, which have been shipped per M. S. w Nederland w during August. attested at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. please return the Certificate duly Yours very truly w. p; immsw' CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWG-iANM. Attachment cc. StorehouseThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 3Z Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. September 8 th, 1942 PA-407 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. Bear Sir Would you kindly certify my signature on two copies of each of the attached letters, and return the certified copies to this office as soon as possible. An additional copy of each letter is also attached for your records. Please deduct your fee for this service from the Company's deposit in your office. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. AA:B Enc.2 letters (3 copies each).T9 *\m e l jai TMs Is to certify that Hr. George 3. kindle is a member of the Staff of The Bahrein Petroleum Jom- pany Limited. Mr. Windle has been in Bahrein since February, 1941, occupying the position of Be search and Development TecJtniician, and is now returning to the United States on leave. THS BAHBSIK Awali, September 3th, 1942. UM dpkpAKY 150).THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Mr, R. H. Mangold, The Texas Oompany, LA003, Nigeria. Bahrein Islanix ifc sian Gulf. September 8th, 1942. Tear Sir, This will introduce Mr. George S. Windle, an American employee of this Company who is proceeding o *■ loave to th© United States, Would you please pur** cshase for Mr. Wiadle transportation by Pan American Airways system from Lagos to New York, and afford him any other assistance of which he may be in need. Hr. windie is being given an additional copy of this letter to present to Pan American, Airways representative in Lagos, should you be absent from Lagos on his arrival there. Yours very t] THE BAHREIN wTp. Ai-HERSON aa.b co«?an Ameriaa;i Air- ways Representative, LAGOS, Nigeria. LIMITEDThe Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Dear Sir, 1 enclose herewith 4 Certificates covering shipment of:- 28 - Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders 3 - Empty Liquid Chlorine Cylinders &amp; 2 - Empty Ereon F-12 Cylinders to New York, which have been shipped per S.S. 'Coloradan” sailed during September 1942. Please return the Certificates duly attested at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. THE CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWCrlPJCr. Attachments cc. StorehouseBahrain. Dear Sir, We enclose herewith Certificate of Origin covering 30 cylinders Butane, shipped from heie per s.s. ’’Pakhoi' to Bombay and shall be obliged if you will kindly have same endorsed and returned to us at your earliest convenience. Yours faithfully, MS. Bncl: 1 . Li*.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, August 23, 1942 RETURN OF EMPTY CARBON DIOXIDE CYLINDERS His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith 3 Certificates covering shipment of:- 9 - Empty Carbon Dioxide Cylinders to Bombay, which have been shipped per S.S.'Capt. A.F.Lucas” sailed during August, 1942. Please return the Certificates duly attested at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. Yours very t W. P. ANDERSON CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWG:PJG. Attachment cc. Storehouse /.^fl Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE : 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. EC.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH AMARAH KUT KHORAMSHAHR Ahwaz BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DU B A I SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE r , Bahrain, 26th September, 19 42. (4 Dear Sir, We enclose herewith Certificate of Origin covering 28 cylinders Butane, shipped per ss. 'Barpeta'’ Voy.303 to Bombay and shall be obliged if you will kindly have same endorsed and returned to us at your earliest convenience. Yours faithfully,\ • ef»' ic,\* flO° the Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, October 14,1941, OUR SHIPPING NOTICES #9-12.9-13. 5'-T6.'9-£6 &amp; 10-4. RffTTON 6 f E.'Fi’Y CYLi^DEkS, PARTS k ElViPTY 2THYL FLUID DRtJK , D0 tlTs^A, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein* Dear Sir, I enclose herewith Certificates covering return of the following to New York; 10 Empty Anhydrous Ammonia Cylinders on 7 ' Acetylene Cylinders ) ' 1 ,f Chlorine tf j 4 Camshafts (Engine Parts) tf 3 Empty Liquid Chlorine Cylinders M 1-55 Gallon Empty Ethyl Fluid Drum n These have been shipped per S.S*'STEEL RANGER” which sailed on October 8,1941. Please return Certificates of the Empty Ethyl Fluid Drum in quadruplicate and one each of the remaining Certificates duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges in this connection to our account. SH.N. #9-12 « 9-13 9-16 9-26 10-4. EWGjMD Attachment CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED cc Acctg.(2) Storehouse (5)THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 3 Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, PA-745. October 20, 1941. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear ^ir, We attach hereto an Affidavit by Mr. Eric Hale Mooring Master, regarding the accident which occurred while loading the S.S. 'Anniston City' with fuel oil. We shall be obliged if you will have this original Affidavit duly notarised and copies certified and return to us. J Please debit our account with the cost involved. Yours very truly, A/' M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Attach: 1 Original Affidavit and 5 copies.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. October 27,1941* No.PA-754 OUR SHIPPING NOTICE #9-5 RETURN OF 15 EMPTY CARBON DIOXIDE CYLINDERS T 6 BOMBAY His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Manama* Dear Sir, I enclose herewith two Certificates covering return of: to Bombay. These were shipped per S.S*'BAMORA' which sailed from Bahrein on September 12,1941. attested at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. 15 empty Carbon Dioxide Cylinders Please return the Certificates duly Yours very truly CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD EWG:MD Attachment cc Acctg. (2) Storehouse ( 2 )1 &lt; r!' THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, November 3, 1941. UUR SBJPrlNG NOTICE #10-5 RETURN uF IQ EMFTY CARB(JN DIuXXDE CYLINDERS TO BOMBAY. His Britannic Majesty’s political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith two Certificates covering return of: 10 empty Carbon Dioxide Cylinders to Bombay. These were shipped per S.S.’ , BAM0RA n which sailed from Bahrein on October 10,1941. Please return the certificates duly attested, at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. M. H. LlPJb' Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 3,3 c&gt; ■ raiTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 7 ^'' A w a 1 1, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. November 4, 1941. 3^/ PA-774 FILE 801.5 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We enclose herewith three copies of a Note of Protest made by the undersigned in connection with damage caused to our Oil Barge w BAPC0 I w on November 1st 1941. Will you please certify the signature on all three copies and return them to us at your convenience. Kindly debit your charges to our deposit account quoting this letter number as your reference. Yours very truly, m. n. ijirr Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Attachment cc. Acctg. 2e^' 3 The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, November 19,1941* [m, ■ )&lt;jh ?•&gt;*» RETURN OF EMPTY CARBON DIOXIDE CYLINDERS: His Britannic Majesty’s Political .Agent, Bahrein* Dear Sir, I enclose herewith two Certificates covering shipment of: 6 empty Carbon Dioxide Cylinders to Bombay which are being shipped per T*V. n CALTEX #2' sailing to-day. Please return the Certificates duly attested at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. Yours very truly, CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWCr: MD Attachment cc Acctg.(2) Storehouse (2) I 5 ' r .v r ar U . it [V0 33J Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co.Ltd (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE: 122, LEADEN HALL STREET, L0ND0N.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. BUS R E H. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH I RE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAH REIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. No. L/1106. N REPLY PLEASE QUOTE BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. RAS TANURA. EL. KHOBAR. Bahrein, 24th November, 19 41 The Political Agent BAHREIN. Dear air, .Ve enclose herewith a Certificate of Origin in connection with shipment of 101 cylinders Butane shipped to Bombay per ’’Barpeta' on June 20th, 1941, and shall be much obliged if you will have same attested and returned in duplicate to this office at your earliest convenience. Yours faithfully&gt;3V osanncAK of origin Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. November 23, 1941. Ne hereby certify that the contents (Butane) of the 101 cylinders shipped in S.S. 'BARP3TAF on June 20, 1941, to Messrs. F. 3. Kerr k Company, Bombay, were manufactured at Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. November 16,1941• PUR SH.NOTICE #11-17 SHIPMENT OF 4-5/4'' SLOTTED CASING TO PAKANBAROR,SUMATRA . His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Manama. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith Certificate in triplicate covering shipment of: 25 Joints (750 Ft.) - Casing, Kobe Slotted, 4-3/4' O.D. x 16#,A.P.I., 1-1/2' Slot, 120 Mesh, 6' Centre, 8 rows to Pakanbaroe, Sumatra. Above is being shipped per S.S.’’ADHIA”• Please return the Certificate duly attested at your earliest convenience, debiting charges to our account. CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED EWG:MD Attachment (3) cc Ac ctg. (2) Storehouse (2)I. A. As regards the fees to be charged on the document brought by Mirza Abbas Irani according to Consular Instructions, please see section 104 Part IV of the Table of ^ees submitted herewith Also please see your note at p.269 File 5/3 III submitted. V 5 &gt; ACT ^ ^ 4 - / ' ^5-w ^7/ UL^ y ^ /t £y S’A ' \ /C/- w v ( 7 &lt; ^ r #A - ^ ^ //» // ///^</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00032e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1175</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00032e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1175</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 5/3 III Registration of documents.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-18T12:17:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (364 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are mainly arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after their relevant covering letter, and terminate in a set of notes (folios 356-365). However, folios 345-355, dated October - November 1941, are out of chronological order, as they follow papers dated 1942.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 366; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-365; these numbers are written in pencil, and are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the registration of documents by the Political Agency, Bahrain.The papers consist of correspondence between those applying to have documents registered and the Political Agency, Bahrain. Most of the correspondence is from oil companies, particularly the Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO). The documents submitted for registration are principally certificates for shipments of oil, cylinders, and equipment, but also include title deeds, powers of attorney, passport applications, certificates of residency, and certificates of employment.The last correspondence item is dated 26 September 1942. The end date in the date range is supplied by an entry in the notes on folio 365.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Notarial instruments</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00032e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>