<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00014c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T14:05:19.671Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Previous File : Next File . f flirt General Heading Sub-head Notes:^’bth ovetaber .1937. (5 1938 I (o Si (^O With ref«^®2i©0 to my despatch 0.317 o ? the 19th la&amp;t,l have th® honour to tjpaasaiit herewith a t.r^TUilatio * of a bill embodying an amendment to Article 43 of the L&amp;w inflicting ’©aalties ou Smugglers, patted by the j ajlis on the ^Oth March 1934,a translation of which was enclosed In Sir } 9;,imXt Roare 1 l despatch Jo.393 of tii® 24th August 1934. This bill was Bub- mi tied to the MaJIia oa t e 31st January last and passed on the 24th February by the Judicial Cemmissiou of the a^iifc which glree it the force of taw. 2. It will be observed that the amended Article differ* from the original only in the fact that the manttf&amp;c tore of gun powder is made subject to the grant of pcrnission by the Ministry of War and not,as formerly,by the polioe Department. X sei sc idiiig copies of this despatch to the secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs jje part mast llo♦ 213,to !T1 b 'ajesty*® Ambassador at pt^puio.84 and to His Majesty’s Consular Officers in Iran Mo. 36. I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir Your most obedient humble servant, (Pigned) HU*, feymour. t Honourable, ony ddeu M.6* » etc., etc., eto., The Foreign Office, L. JlK)I,S.^.l. (o Si (^O/ . (z) ■% { &gt; ilo.017 ■ ‘(TI7/I6/37) 6260 L ,r . ■ 19th August, 1937 Sir, With reference to Sir Reginald Koare’s despatch Mo .393 of the 24th August 1934,1 have the honour to transmit to you herewith a translation of a M 33©finition 5 ' of Article 45 of the Law Inflicting penalties on Smugglers passed hy the Majlis on the 20th March 1934. This 'Definition' was approved on the 18th March 1937 and appears to have the force of a law. It will be seen that it extends the penalties on smuggling prohibited goods from those who import prohibited goods to all those who subseque: tly deal in prohibited goods which they know to have been illegality imported. 2 # It will be remembered that the original Article 45 of the Law dealt both with prohibited imports and prohibited exports. The present 'Definition' refers only to prohibited imports. 3. I am sending copies of this despatch to the Secretary to the government of India in the External Affairs Department Ho.l45,to His Majesty's Ambassador at Baghdad. Bo .64 and to all His Majesty's Consular officers in Iran, Circular Despatch No.25. I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, (Signed) s.J* Seymour. The Right Honourable, Anthony Eden M.C-,M.P., • etc*, etc., etc., THE FOHKIGB OFFICE.OF A mFIhrnOu OF PAR .GKAIH £ OF AP.TIOLF 45 OF THU LAW ILFLICl'I^G BL I0ID£E1^ OK SHLGC-LLKS , AP “ROVFL OA THSi 27 th ESFAiiD, 1315 (16th March 19£7). Single Article. paragraph 2 of Article 45 of the Law inflicting .mi’-inhr'ieut on enugglers,approved o the 29th E^fand,1312 (£0th March 1934} applies also to cases where persons transfer,or take any part in the transfer ence of,goods whose import is prohibited from one place to another inside the country for the purpose of trade or business,while knowing that such goods have been imported in contravention of a prohibition.r.Z. 3261/36. EXTRACT T'ROivi DIaRY Oi' THE BRITISH RESIDEHCY &amp; CONSULaTE-GEHERAL, BUSHIRE, i? ; OR THE MONTH OR MARCH, 1936. 45. ClJBTQi.^ GUaRD ^ ORCE . This force, which was originally organised for the suppression of the smuggling of contraband goods, was recently amalgamated with the Amnieh and the authorities of the latter Department took over charge of the men and the offices. The reason for this action, it is said, is that the Amnieh Force is more efficient and better disciplined. 46 . THE CbSTOivE BREVE Nil VE DEi'ARiSxENT . The officials of this Department have been able to seize the following dhows and contraband goods at the under-mentioned places I. BU SHIRE IQ„N, DISTRICT AltJ bUxi-FORTS: 319 bales piece goods 11 bags sugar 2 bags tea 4 cases soaps and perfumery 2 smugglers’ dhows II. UN THE CAIB IblAND : 10 packages tobacco 6 bags sugar 2 bags chillies 2 bundles ropes 4 cases sundries 1 dhow also the Nakhuda and crew of the last mentioned dhow. Reports received state that the smuggling of contraband goods is being actively carried on through the Iranian ports into the interior of the country via Farrashband and Firuzabad. During the month under report two caravans of smugglers were intercepted one at a spot between Xangan and Daiyir (some 115 miles south west of Bushire) and the other/other somewhere in Tangistan by the Arnnieh guards. The smugglers’ guards put up a resistance. Their casualties consisted of 9 killed and 2 wounded while the Amnieh losses were 10 killed and 4 wounded.EXTRACT PROM DIARY OP THE BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE-GENERAL BUSHIRE FOR THE MONTH OP DECEMBER 1935- 166. THE CUSTOMS PREVENTIVE DEPARTMENT : !• During the month under reference the officials of this Department seized 6 hales of contraband cloth with the smuggler concerned in Bushire Town and some 15 hags of sugar in the suh-ports. 2. In order to curtail the activities of local smugglers the Director of Customs has arranged with the Police Authorities to issue no Passport or any other travel papers to ten citizens of the town who are known to he smugglers of contrabands.Smuggling continues actively in the Tangistan and Dashti ports, especially of sugar. These ports have almost ceased to buy sugar from the Bushire Sugar Monopoly C ompany. About the 15th of October, one of three smugglers dhows landing contraband cargo at a Dashti port, was attacked by Customs Guards. One Guard was killed and the smugglers drove away the rest and took their goods to Firuzabad by mule. During October the Preventive Department succeeded in seizing the following goods in Bushire and suburbs: 16 bales of cotton piece goods and crepe de chine 5 bags soft sugar £ dozen Japanese shoes 1 dozen playing cards They also arrested 3 smugglers who owned 5 bales of cloth and fined one of them Ts.1206. He paid the fine and was released. The fate of the others is not known.Smuggling continued actively through the Tangistan ports. On the 1st August a smugglers' dhow with 20 bales of crepe de chine, 2 rifles and some 500 rounds of ammunition arrived at Dilbar (Tangistan Coast). Before she could unload her cargo she sprang a leak. The people of Dilbar salvaged the goods and took them away. Ghulam Hussain Karam, a Tangistani outlaw, took the ammunition. On the 17th August 3 smugglers' dhows discharged 60 bales of piece goods, at Lavar another port in the Tangistan Coast. The goods were taken into the interior via Farrash Band and Firuzabad. A quantity of contraband piece goods has reached Ahram a village 32 miles south east of Bushire, presumably through the Tangistani ports. From Ahram the goods find their way into Bushire town and are sold to local drapers at very low prices under-selling the wholesale dealers. During August officials of the Preventive Department succeeded in seizing some 33 bags of sugar, 2 dozen under shirts, 4 dozen Japanese shoes and one smuggler.P.Z.5674/35. /, Extract from Diary of the British Residency and Consulate General, Bushire, for the month of July, 1935. 101. CUSTOMS PREVENTIVE DEPART!,IBM 1 . LINGAH. Reference paragraph No.95 of Diary for July 1935. It is reported from Lingah that the smuggling is being carried out on a large scale at port Jezza between Kalat and Chiru in the Shib-Kuh Coast. At the beginning of July, the report states, 2 or 3 sailing boats having bribed the Customs Guards began discharging their cargo at Jezza when a launch, hired by the Mudir of Customs at Muqam (another port in the Shib-Kuh Coast) was sighted on her way to Lingah. The Guards suspecting she might be carrying an Inspector signalled her to stop and reported that they had seized a boat full of contraband goods. The Mudir took the cargo in his launch and also one sailing boat without any crew, to Lingah. A description of the goods is given below:- 45 bags soft sugar 25 bags loaf sugar 34 boxes tea 40 bundles imitation silk cloth 13 bundle piece goods 5 cases haberdashery 20 bags cementm P.Z.5674/35. \ Extract from Diary of the British Residency and Consulate General, Bushire, for the month of July, 1935. 95, THE CUSTOMS IBEVaLITIVE DEI : AKTL-li^ITT. During the month under report the officials of this Department seized 11 hags sugar and 10 pieces contraband cloth in Dashti and in Halilah. This quantity is only a fraction of the contraband smuggled into the country with the connivance of the Iranian officials. On the 83rd July a non-commissioned officer and two private guards of the Amnieh (the Hoad Guard Force) were arrested, and handed over to the Military authorities here, for having taken bribes and connived at two dhows discharging their cargoes of contraband goods in a port on the Shib-Kuh Coast. It was reported that the non-commissioned officer and his two guards not only allowed the contraband goons to be landed but beat off tha Customs guards who interfered. These men, being Government officials and having abetted in the smuggling of contraband goods, will probably be shot.extract from Diary of the Britten Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, for the month of June, 1935. 85. THE CUSTOMS PREVEUTIVE DEPARTiiiBrT . During the month the officials of this Department seized the following in the town and neighbourhood and in down Gulf ports:- 2 smugglers 2 smugglers’ dhows 20 bales cotton piece goods and crepe de chine 23 boxes tea 18 camels belonging to smugglers 72 bags sugar 2 bundles hides. 86. THE I RADI AT? NAVY AND PREVBI^IVE MEASURES . The gun-boat ’’Chahrokh” succeeded in catching 2 smugglers’ dhows in June. One of them had the following goods on board:- 20 bags sugar 10 boxes tea 5 bales cotton fabrics and the other a sum of Rials 170,000 of Iranian silver money which smugglers had sent out to buy Rupees with. It is reported that srmgglers can buy Rupees in Fao and in other Arab ports at the rate of Rials 290 per hundred while the rate of exchange for Rupee in Bushire is Rials 600 to 620 a hundred. The smuggling of silver coin is reported to be vigorous in the Gulf p o rt s. In the first week of the month a band of armed smugglers attacked a party of Customs Guards and killed one of them when they tried to intercept a caravan carrying contraband goods out of Bul-Khair - a port on the Tangistan Coast./{ a \ I : , (SJ) Extract from Diary of the British Residency and Consulate General, Bushire, for the month oi April, 1935. 59. x x x x (3) During the month under reference the officials of this Department seized the undermentioned contraband:- 30 pieces imitation silh. 1 box cigarettes. 1 bale cloth. 1 empty dhow said to belong to smugglers. 60. THE IRAhTAlI HAVY Ah T D PK3V hNTIV E_ MEASU£1^.3:.. ABout the end of April, the sloop 'PALAUG' caught a smuggling dhow off Tangistan Coast. She was carrying a few pieces of contraband cloth and Tomans 300 and Rupees 200 in silver. 61. THE Ml]-IT ARY AND PREVENTIVE MEASURES. On the 29th April the troops in Dashti intercepted a gang of smugglers in Khaki (60 miles south of Bushire). In the fighting which took place between them the troops killed the ringleader of the smugglers, arrested 6 of them and seized 470 bags of contraband sugar which they had kept hidden there evidenttyfor despatch to the interior of the country. The troops had a non-commissioned officer killed.P.Z.1046/1935. (5f) Extract from Diary of H.B.M. ’s Consulate for Khuzistan, Ahwajd for the month of December, 1934. 335. CUSTOMS Reference paragraph £60 of diary No. 10 of 1934. His Majesty the Shah has ordered that all the Preventive Departments of smuggling must be transferred to the control of the Customs Department and in future the Customs Officials have the right to inspect houses suspected of containing smuggled goods after they are fully satisfied that such goods exist. This will stop complaints of the public against the irregularities committed by the Inspectors and all classes of the public will benefit. 3' P.Z.1046/1935. Extract from Diary of H.B.M.»s Consulate for Khuzistan Ahwaz for the month of December 1934. 338. STOGGLlhG It is reported that about 45 camels loaded with sugar were caught, entering Persia, by the Amnieh guards on the Perso-Iraq frontier and were handed over to the Customs. Smuggling is daily increasing in the Province despite the drastic measures adopted by the Government to prevent it.P.Z.7888/34. Extract from Diary of the British Residency &amp; Consulate- General,Bushire, for the month of November,1934, 133,Economic Condition. 1. No appreciable improvement has taken place in the economic situation and with the exception of a few daring individuals who have taken to the smuggling of contraband goods rest of the inhabitants of the hinterland and town remain in a poverty stricken condition. His Excellency the Governor with a view to alleviate conditions approached his Government to instruct the Revenue DepartmentjBusnire, to supply cultivators with free wheat seed and to recover the value from them after the harvest. 2. Statistics kept by the Police Office,Bushire, show that 6,000 of the population of Bushire and district have migrated from their homes during the last seven months (22nd March 1934 to the end of October) and have gone abroad in search of employment. These people, it is reported, have gone to Ahwaz, Abadan, Mohammerah, Kuwait, Bahrain, Shiraz and other towns in the interior of Persia.P.Z.7888/34. Extract from Diary of the British Residency &amp; Consulate General,Bushire,for the month of Novemher,1934. 134 134. Local Government. The Customs Preventive Department. 1. During the month under review the officials of this Department succeeded in seizing 138 hags of contraband sugar in Bushire and in the sub-ports./ / P.Z.7888/34. Extract from Diary of the British Residency &amp; Consulate- General,Bushire ,for the month of November,1934. 135 135. The Persian Navy and Preventive Measures. 1. About the end of November the gun-boat 'Shahbaz” caught three smugglers” dhows carrying some 600 packages of contraband sugar and piece-goods. Two of the dhows were set fire to and the third was left at Delvar. The smugglers took shelter on shore, and fired on the gun-boat. Two of the former are said to have been killed in the fighting.Extract from Diary of the British Hesioency ana Consulate General, Bushire, for the month of September 1934. 108. INSPECTION . About the middle of September a Committee of two, namely Aqai Ahmad Khan Framarzi and Aqai Froogiiizadeh, arrived at Bushire ana are carrying out inspections in the Customs offices of complaints about smuggling ana charges brought against private indiviauals for smuggling. The usual report is saia to have been given to the inspectors about tnere being hardly any traue, taxes too high and what trace there is ruined by smuggling competition and that the end is near at nand. No results are expected from these reports.Extract from Diary of the British Residency ana Consulate General, Bushire, for the month of September 1934. 'Vo. 109. LOCAL GOVSl-^llJ^NT . THE CU3TC1..3 P.lLVSNTI'i/E DEPAriTI\SI'IT. During the month under reference the officials of this Department seized some 56 hags of contraband sugar and a negligible quantity of tea which were being smuggled into the town and neighbourhood.?•2#7003/34 EXTRACT FROM PERSIAN GULF INTELLIGENCE REPORT FOR AUGUST 1934 . 30. New Cons true tio-n. It is reported that the Customs Officials at Bunder Abbas have stated that a number of small craft will shortly be available for anti smuggling purposes. They will be given certain definite areas to work in and will be responsible for that area. 31. It is probable that the 3 motor Vedettes ordered from the Cantieri Naval! Riuniti of Palermo which are expected to be completed between February ana April 1935 are for this purpose. Particulars of these vessels which were laid down in toy and June are;- Displacement Length Beam 20*9 metres. 28 tonnes. 3.85 metres.p.s.7003/34. eg) 3£G^T. * ,, , * * * * 34. Anti« 3 mu^;linu; . some idea as to the difficulties the Persian Navy are experiencing in stopping smuggling may be gained from the following story. 35. jx Bahrein motor dhow with a cargo of tea and sugar reached a small port on the LUghu coast recently. While the Nakhuda and some of the crew were bargaining with the local annich (road guards) as to the price to be paid, a Persian patrol vessel was sighted. The amnich, fearing that their unofficial role as smugglers* agents would be discovered and condemned, promptly terminated the bargaining by opening fire on the Arabs. Some are reported to have been killed.■■MiTHE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop ^5 of the under-mentioned paper. ^ ^ Foreign Office, |«7^ i 3 , 193 U. 1. Ojc. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. W.Vv,35 ) His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of of smuggling In Psrsla 9 prevention Reference:- Tehran despatch No. 11 of 8th January 1934. / \ Persian Law against Smuggling, passed by the Medullas on 20th March, 1934. Copies also sent to:* Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. (No. 182). His Majesty's Charge d*Affaires at Baghdad. (No. 62). All Consular officers in Persia (Circular despatch No. 15).V 1 Art: 1 . Toute personne gai fraude un oTs^et constituent une source de revenue pour I’Etat ou un des d^rivls du dit objet et (que les dits revenue aient ete approuv4s par une loi speciale ou qu’ils aient ItI prlvus et approuves expresslment dans le budget de l f Etat) sera condamnee non seulement a la restitution du bien fraud!, ou si ce bien n’existe plus au remboursement de son prix, mais aussi au paiement d’une amende plcuniaire Igale au double des revenue lludle et &amp; un emprisonnement correct!onnel de 3 mois &amp; 2 ans. Art: 2 m Toute tentative de fraude entralnera outre la saisie de I'objet fraud! et 1'application de la moiti! de I’amende pecuniaire sus&amp;entionee, la condamnation ^ un em/prisonnement correct!onnel de 2 mois a un an* Art; 3 « Si deux ou plusieurs personnes sont coauteurs d'une fraude, non seulement I'objet fraud! sera saisi, mais encore chacun des fraudeurs sera condamn! a 1'emprisonnement pr!vu par 1'Art. premier et solidairement au paiement d'une amende plcuniaire !gale au double des revenue destinls It 1'Etat. La peine h infliger &amp; chacun des complices est !gale &amp; la moitie de 1'amende pecuniaire appliqule &amp; 1'auteur principal et a un emprisonnement de 3 mois &amp; un annee* Art; 4 . L'unite de 1'objet de la fraude sera dlterminee, pour les cas od les lois y afferentes n'ont pas fix! cette /unite. \ft ft ft , ft •'' .ft ' ' v • '••' J Ul ■'' '- 1 ■ ‘ l ^ v. u v* ...ft iu oo 3w _ ■ O - .. .'' • • X M ; j ( ■ , , . . - - ■ O •:&gt; » &gt;•. ■ J i.. o •xi o;^ uV; &gt; w i-ftft;.’ i vJ' : ’I ..H -1 : v,.....'. U • ., ftftft...-. M a 5 fti ‘ft o' V.. u ±&lt;0 w . 'X . ft. ’ . J- „ /ft ift i : &gt; V .ft -fti.. jftft X ft . * ft ft _ ; , f ftftft Xfti'ft ftft i&gt;.. •• © ■ $ a . 3 *i -ic i J • t (13 ixxfXI3|S&lt;|^‘'X9VTi/O^ . RiQj'it &gt; v c ; .. t ; ■ ' • ■ ' , • ■ ■ ioX ^j ' . . ■ . ! s . ■ ., i * f . • • p ' i. , • t , t 4-X... v ft V ' V i L ■ I ft v) ■ t &gt;•■/tJ ^ ft •■ ftii-ft 'V - Ail ft’Q’.. ft fi-. ft; ,: ; ft, ( ' ft n \ a i j ft -ftTI.; _) ;i .ali &gt;o‘i J. ..L'.i i\i X ' S.Lft: ft 'ft x . 0 ftjft , J r x-ii x-'ftB' ft/l / ./.ft! : M.ft. ft; ft 4 ft- ft •*).3 ioi. ;ft ; ft-) , aft-- ft -a j ft aft-ft f:on'o -viyucoftA) t*c ft.; . . , ■• ft - •• ■' »a&gt; ac Xu JftG / i. .ft: ^ ; ft,.. ?j.-. ift s j i\j fft j i ... X ■, : ft al6ino#I slftvtyo as I ft I spp ft-ft X&gt; r.jjxc/- 7 ' / . . . c •' , ( .ft; all t mi/jU;O f X 91 a / ftX. X ,. ft.; IX ft ft J ft x. . ft'. O *1 ('ft ; yi' f ft q Q. r • ■ ft CXI ob , Xx ft-xfto\ //ft % ^ o . . j . N .. . '. ' /•; ; •. • ' • - ' . &lt; / : • : . ft O 1 ' .' . • • J . ftr .,■. ; .■■; 'i . ; i , ft ; .• •. : . . ft . Jt^BottacmX^q^e esu A $@ 0001 /. 006 ^ K • ’ ^ ^ ' ' / ftl.rXv )fto ft .,r u 8 ft ft-/ uxftft ftX . 5.0 fft Xuoo: Vi J 5 b Jxx XdX'x''. / ... §&gt;I .... . • . ft ' ft ft. ft-ft ,ft 3 Q oft- t X x. . J t X aft j /’Xii: j vj9 'V/ftto ft : 5 . aft ... ,ft1 —*» 1 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^6- ^ jw and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop U of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ^ , 193#-/. Reference to previous correspondence : it F.o. ^ I ; Description of Enclosure. 7 K &gt; Name and Date. Subject. Jbv^C Tl’m ^ Clmf British Legation, Tehran, JO JAN ‘1934 8th January 9 His Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Persian Lav of 7th March, 1929, relating to the punishment of smugglers* Referenee:- Tehran despatch No* 601 of the 28th December, 1933* Persian Lav dated 16th Eafand, 1307 (7th March, 1929) relating to the punishment of Gsiugglers* (Copies sent to: His Majesty's Ambassador at Baghdad* No* 2* The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* His Majesty's Consul, Ahvaz* No. 2. No. 2. ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER N0 8 22 FEE 1934 FROM SECRETARY, POLiru L AHD RftnRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICELAW RATING- TO THb OF aMUGOLi^S. (Sanctioned by tixe Royal sign Manual and approved by the Mejlias on the 16th Bsfand 1307 (7th Mareh, 1929)* ££ ixl H- H- ui ^ I &gt;: oa —1 CM —» -- o o ui ui £ £ H £ 23 UJ H CCS ZD CO CO o O UI c 2 co £2 © z car Uu AR'i-ICLiv 1 : Any one guilty of smuggling any commodity, or substances derived from any commodity, which is the object of Government revenues, whether the said revenues have been approved by a special law or definitely provided and approved within the General State Budget, shall, in J addition to returning the property or the price thereof, be condemned to the payment of twice the revenues that the Government would otherwise have derived, and to correctional imprisonment of from three months to two years, . . / ^»-i«uL Tu&gt;h fiz £ Persons guilty of-lnitiating smuggling shall, { in addition to the confiscation of the goods and the payment of half the above-mentioned cash penalty, be liable to condemnation to from three months to one year correctional imprisonment. Mote:- Those persons who are unable to pay for the property or the oash penalty shall, in addition to the above imprisonment, be imprisoned one day for every Toman for which he is in default. The total duration of such imprisonment must not, however, exceed ffcte years in any case. AKTICLK II; The unit of smuggled goods, if not determined by relevant ^aws, will be determined in accordance with the Regulations of the Ministry of Finance; and the penalty provided in Article I consists of twice the revenue which is appointed as the share of the Government from the smuggling of every unit or fractions of every unit. In any case, the amount of the fine for the first unit of the smuggled goods or fractions thereof will not be less than five Tomans. /Note:-- 2 - Notes- In reepect of goods derived from the smuggled goods, the double amount provided above is proportional to the original unit of whatever substance the derived goods consist of, and will be determined in accordance with regulations of the Ministry of Finance. ARTICLE III : Any one of the officials in charge of collecting Government revenues can carry on inspection in suspected places with the object of discovering smuggled goods. Inspection in houses of private persons must be / effected by special officials who have been given authority j in the matter by the Ministry of Finance, in the presence of a representative of the parquet (primary court) or his representative, or the local police officer or his representative, or the local head-villager ( hedkhuda ). Inspection in houses of private persons will not be allowed between sunset and sunrise. Inspection in suspected places and houses which are suspected must be effected in the presence of the owners of the said places and houses, or, in case of their absence, in the presence of at least two i witnesses. MTIGLi; IV ; After discovery of a case of smuggling, it is the duty ol the officials investigating mxem the discovery to pack up the smuggled goods and to seal them with a wax deal. Any one other than the oompetent officials breaking the seal or tempering with it shall be dealt with under „ Article 113 of the Penal Law. AR^IGLL V; The officials in charge of the collection of revenues may, with the approval of the (local) provincial or sub-provincial officer, compromise with the smuggler and permit him to pay the fine and return the smuggled goods, or the price thereof if the actual goods do not exist, and to be exempt from criminal prosecution in the Courts of Justice, provided that this compromise,in the first place, /shallrs - 3 - Csi\ shall not be made more than once in the case of one individual and, in the second place, that the smuggler shall have had no previous conviction* The Customs Administration is also authorised to make a compromise, subject to the above two conditions* The collection of the amounts which have been guaranteed to be paid, in accordance with this Article, shall be the duty of officials appointed according to special regulations by the Ministry of Finance* The said officials may, in macs&amp;x conformity with the provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure pertaining to the execution of orders emanating from Courts, collect the amounts guaranteed, regardless of whether the guilty persons are, according to certain Laws, justiciable by special courts. ARTICLE VI ; Kxcept in cases where a compromise is allowed, asmentioned in the preceding Article, it is the duty of the officials in charge of discovering cases of smuggling, after confiscation of the smuggled goods and the preparation of a proces-verbal * to send in the dossier to the competent authorities for necessary action. \ ARTICLE VII: Any one smuggling arms, or importing or exporting goods whose importation or exportation is prohibited shall, in addition to confiscation of the property itself, be liable to correctional imprisonment for from six months to three years* ARTICLE VIII s Those who directly or indirectly have the duty of discovering smuggling or of prosecuting or punishing the perpetrators thereof, and who themselves smuggle or participate or assist in that offence, as well as the competent officials who, knowing that smuggling has been committed, refrain from prosecuting the perpetrators or compromise in a manner contrary to the conditions laid downin Part one of Article V, shall be considered as embezzlers of GoYemment property and condemned to penalties mentioned in Articles I, II and III of the Law of the 16th Azar, 1306 (8th December, 1927). ARTIOhiS IX : The accomplices of smugglers shall receive the same treatment as is applicable to the smuggler himself under this Law, but the cash penalty to which those who assist the perpetrator shall be liable shall be half the cash penalty to which the real perpetrator is liable, and their imprisonment will be from three months to one year. ARTICLE X : The officials in charge of collection are bound to furnish, against the collection of the price of the smuggled goods or the cash penalty, receipts on which stamps have been affixed for the amount of the payment collected. ARTICLE XI: The Law assigning penalties for smuggling sanctioned on the 22nd Lsfand 1306 (15th March, 1928) and the provisions of Article I, II and III, and the latter part of Article^ IV, and Articles VI, X and XII of the Law assigning penalties for the smuggling of opium sanctioned on the 16th Mordad, 1307 (7th August, 1928) and Article V of the Amendments to the Law levying taxes on tobaccos sanctioned on the 27th Hout, 1503 (17th March, 1926) as well as its second Note, and Article IV of the Law authorising the Sugar and Tea Monopoly sanctioned on the 9th Khordad 1304 (30th May, 1925) are hereby revolted. ARTICLE XII: This Law shall be put into force as from 20th Esfand 1307 (11th March, 1929) and the Ministries of Justice and Finance are charged with its enforcement. (Extracted from the Official Gazette of of Finance No* 117, dated 25th Esfand, March, 1929)*2 T On the 26th March 1934 and taking advantage of the ’Id Holidays, the Mutasarrif of Basra, Tahsin Beg Ali , accompanied by Dr.Ibrahim Akif Alusi, Director of Health, Basra, Sami Beg, Accountant-General, Basra; Abdul Wahab al Haama, Deputy Director of Customs; Abdul Jabbar Khaderi, merchant; ITuri Thabit, Journalist; Mr.Gabriel, Lawyer (Shaikh’s), paid a purely private visit to Kuwait. The i Shaikh who was in camp with his family placed his Palace at the disposal of the p^rty. The Shaikh, it seems, did not invite the above guests in the first place, but in answer to an urgent personal message from the Mutasarrif that he would like to run down pnd see Kuwait, the Shaikh answered thrt he was welcome to do so, provided he came unofficially. The Mutasarrif and party left again on 28th March 1934, after mutual calls had been exchanged between him and the Political Agent. In the opinion of the writer, the Mutasarrif’s visit had something to do with ’Iraq’s anti-smuggling policy. The Mutasarrif certainly made public remarks as to the unwisdom of accusing Kuwait, when his own country was entirely to blame. imm(e) A curious but unconfirmed report reached Kuwait on 20th March to the effect that the ’Iraq Government had appointed a certain Shammar tribesman naT7ie ^ Sudaid al Shammari to try and deal with certain ’Iraqi smugglers, who, with great boldness were conducting their operations between Kuwait, Kerbela and Ke j ef. It was said that Sudair had been given the equivalent of Rs.5,000/- per annum, and had to produce and maintain a party of 60 horsemen and camelmen with the money. It was further said tha.t in the first engagement which he had with smugglers his party had been roughly handled, and scattered, while he himself ('Sudaid”) had been severely wounded in the thigh. The writer personally thinics the story is a myth. i *P.Z. 3485/34. No. 4 of 1934. Extract from Diary of the British Residency &amp; Consulate- General, Bushire, for the month of April, 1934. 49. LOCAL GOVERNMENT . The Customs Preventive Department. During April the officials of this Department succeeded in seizing 85 hags of contraband sugar in the suburbs of Bushire. P. The gun-boat 'Karkas' caught a smugglers dhow on the Shio—Kuh coast but after she had unloaded her cargo of contraband goods. She was brought to Bushire. 3. Smugglers are still persistent in their traffic. In order to deter the Bushire smugglers the Military arrested over a dozen of them last year. They were kept in detention for close on a year: their petitions for the investigation of their crimes were ignored. They were released on bail in April after two of them had died. Their families had bored all the Ministries; the Majlis in Tehran and even His Imperial Majesty the Shah himself with their petitions.P.Z.2672/34. Extract from Diary of the British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, for the month of March 1934. 37. Reference paragraph No.25 of February 1934. It is reported that the Commission of Inspection having visited three towns in Dashti and Tangistan and instituted enquiries about smuggling left for Shiraz during the first week of March.2672 / 34 . Extract from Diary of the British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Dushire, for the month of March 1934. 39. LOCAL GOVBRKMEITT. THE CUSTOMS PREVENTIVE DEPARTMENT. The officials of this Department succeeded in seizing 6 pieces of imitation silk, 3 hags of contraband sugar and 16 rifles in the Shib-Kuh Ports: a negligible quantity of opium in the town and a boat carrying 300 bags of contraband sugar at Dilum. The Mudir of Customs who seized this boat placing her under the orders of two Customs Guards directed the Nakhuda to report himself at the Bushire Customs Department. The Nakhuda, however, set sail for Kuwait where he made himself scarce. The guards, however, reported matters to His Excellency Sir Shaikh Shmad bin Jabir Al-Sabah, the Ruler of Kuwait. His Excellency sent the boat and the guards, with some monetary aid, to Mohammerah.P.z. 2755/54 CONFIDENTIAL. No.4 of 1934. EXTRACT FROM THE KUWAIT NEWS FOR THE PERIOD FROM THE 1st TO THE 31st MARCH 1934. 21. MOVEMENTS. (I) British. (i) Mr.Edmonds, C.M.G., etc., of the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Lieutenant-Colonel Ward, C.M.G., C.I.E., D.S.O., Port Director, Basra,arrived by Imperial Airways on the 22nd and returned to Basra by next day f s westbound plane. Mr.Edmonds had several discussions with Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.E., Political Agent, or the smuggling question. Mr.Edmonds was put up with Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.E., while Colonel Ward stayed with Mr.Chisholm, for the one night theywsre here.P.Z, 2257/34. EXTRACT EROM DIARY OP THE BRITISH RESIDENCY &amp; CONSULA'TE G-ENERAL, BUSH I RE FOR THE MONTH OP FEBRUARY, 1934. 29. D &amp;C A L 'GOVERNMEN T. T11E-QUSTQM3 PREVENTIVE JEPARIT.gNr. At the beginning of the month a proclamation was circulated in all the Persian G-overnment Departments in Bushire and the countryside to the effect that if any Persian official is found helping smuggling he will be shot if proved guilty. This it seems has had no effect whatsoever in the deterring of officials concerned. See para. 25. Two officials were sent to Ganawah and Dilu on inspection duty and also to find out by which means smuggled goods get to Behbehan. During the month under reference the officials of this Department have been able to seize only 58 bags of sugar in the suburbs of the town and beyond.P.Z. 2257/34. EXTRACT T ^0M jIARY OF 'THE BRITISH RESIDENCY &amp; CONSULATE OENERAL, BU3HIRE, FOR THE MONTH OF FEBRUARY, 1934. 25. INSPECTION . On the 12th February a Commission of Inspection of Governments offices arrived at Bushire. It is composed of the undermentioned 1. Sartip (Brigadier General) ABUL HASSAN XHAN (President) 2. Colonel AKBAR MIRZA 3AHHEMANI (of the Amnieh Administration). 3. Colonel KHUDA YAR KHAN (of the Ministry of War). 4. Aqai MIFTAH (a young Oxford graduate) of the Ministry of Justice. 5. ABDUL HUSAIN KHAN SAEI-ASLANI. 6. ISA KHAN ILAHI (of the Ministry of Finance) 7. Major NAZMI (of the Police administration). The eighth member of the Commission named HASSAN KHAN DEBIR-I-A f AZAM ASAYESH died at Bandar-Abbas and the Assistant Governor, Bushire, Aqai ABDUL SHAKOOR MIN was elected in his place for the time being. The second day after their arrival the Commission posted a printed notice in the town inviting complaints against Persian officials in Bushire. Many anonymous reports were submitted but unlike the previous Commission which came to Bushire in March 1931, this Commission would not take cognisance of such reports nor verbal complaints without substantiating evidence. Having inspected the different Persian Governments Departments here the Commission left for Dashti and Tangistan. They arrived at Delwar when a dhow was landing her cargo of smuggled goods. The Mudir of the Customs, Customs Guards and the Amnieh Guards were watching and conniving at the smuggling. Twentyeight persons consisting of smugglers and Government/Grovernment officials found aiding the former were arrested by orders of the Commission and brought to Bushire. Here also several smugglers were arrested and interrogated in the Police Court. Fifteen of those found involved in the smuggling were put into prison. The Commission then returned to BORAZJAN where they are instituting enquiries in connection with the onward traffic of smuggled goods. It is stated in Bushire that the Commission will proceed to Khuzistan after they have finished their work here.P.Z.1006/1934. Confidential cS) Extract from Diary No.10 of 1933, of the Political Residency and Consulate General, Bushire, for the month of October 1933. * * * * * 112. Local Government . - Customs Preventive Department . The following contraband goods were recovered from smugglers during the period under reference: 15 oz. opium; 16 cases matches; 4 cases confectionary. 99 bags crystal sugar. 3 boxes tea. 19 pairs of shoes. It is reported that there is much smuggling through the ports on the Tanghistan Coast. Husain Rustum, a Tanghistani chief who was recently appointed by the Persian Government to help in the suppression of the traffic, came to an arrangement with the local Mudirs of the Customs and Amniah guard Commanders by which smugglers can carry their goods through into the interior towns after paying 60 or 70 Rials for each bag of sugar or a box of tea, etc. jj # The Persian Navy . - On the 8th October the gun ooat 'Shahbaz' brought in a dhow carrying 250 goats for Bahrain. Fifty of the animals were in excess of the correct number shown in her manifest and customs papers. The Nakhuda was fined and the 50 goats confiscated and sold by public auction.COPY (TS 5734/5754/91) British Legatl Tehran* October 11th, 1930* V Sir, I have the honour to transait to you herewith a copy of a report from Hie Consul-General at Bushire dealing with the question of smuggling in the Persian Gulf, together with a copy of the letter from the Commercial Secretary referred to therein* 2 * Customa statistics are notably unreliable but it is interesting to note that Colonel Blsooe's information points to ; n appreciable decrease in the smuggling from the Arab to the Persian side of the Gulf, a traffic whioh ha© undoubtedly contributed very largely to the pro&amp;nerity of the Arab coast in the past* 5* I agree with Colonel Biscoe that it would be advantageous for him to be accompanied by Mr*Probationer Vice Consul Blanch on hie forthcoming tour of the Arab ports, and I should be grateful if I might be informed as soon as possible by telegraph whether the suggestion meets with your approval. 4* Copies of this despatch are being sent to the Department of Overseas Trade and to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India* I have, etc., (8d .) R.H.OLIVE. The Right Honourable Arthur Henderson, M.P., The Foreign Office*COPY .C.A, 6/IA. British Legation, Tehran, May 2nd, 1930, Sir, I haye the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your Printed Letter No*64/946 enclosing a copy of your despatch No.Overseas Tr^de (B) 4 to the Department of Overseas Trade, dated Si nd April 1 ist, on the subject of the possible market for British goods on the Arab side of the Gulf. 2 . I suggest that it would be useful to know what proportion of the goods shipped to the Arab ports of the Gull are smuggled into ersia, it being cownon knowledge that this contraband trade h? s assumed formidable propor tions in recent years. A study of the Import e of these Arat rorts during the last six or se en years, so as to include the two years prior to the introduction of the 1 ereian Sugar and Tea Monopoly in May 1925, should give a valuable indication of the rapid Increase in smuggling from the Arab to the Persian side of the Qulf. I are unaware, however, whether goods intended for Persian consumption are invariably declared on entry into the Arab ports prior to transhipment, 3. I should also be glad to learn whether in your opinion the prosperity of the Arab side of the Gulf, and therefore its power to purchase British goods, does not very much depend on the continuance of causes which now i K;e smuggling into Persia so extremely profitable. 4. Copies o this despatch am being sent to the Department of Overseas Trade. I have, etc., ( 8 d.) B.R.LXNGBKAN. Officer 1/c of Commercial Affairs. The Honourable Lieut-Col*H.V.Blacoe, I.A., etc., etc., etc., Bushire.British Rculdsney and Consulnto-Oanural. n fri&amp;htre, 10tli Septoafrer 1930* Sir, Kith mfewnce to p*T*gvnyhti 2 and 3 of lottor Ha*0*Ah 6/1A of m? f^nd Inst from tho Offioer la ahargo of Corns ^rolnl Affairs, the enelowad ingles, giving In the one o&amp;m the r l^ie of totel ismorte, a« woll ae thooo of too and sugar, for Bahrein, Kuwait and Muscat during the years 192&amp;-93 to and in the oth*?r, tlwg actual oeroentage of total imports r^r*seated hy tea »nd sugar, will X think ho of interost to you* T^oeo figure* show that oraotiof lly no snuggling now t«,k ©8 rlaooa from either Kuwait or Musowt, a fact which it confirmed *y reports X hawo r^eeiTed from both placoa* 3. A s regards Bahrein, there. h^S boon a fairly ectiwe contrebanli trade zeroes the Calf to Persia of recent years hut \ X m told that this is on the decrease owing to tho Increasing difficulty of getting cargoes fVOft the coast into the interior? in any oeao there is no Justiflostion for the assuaietioa thst the rholo prosperity of these Islands is attri utehle to emugglingi tho figure# shew that in Bahrein* s tsyerage yearly laroorts of close on £,2,0 -O .O'/O, sugar and tea account for hut £160, 90, B&amp;r&amp;ly a vital factor of prosperity, even if it were nil smuggled into Persia, which of course it Is not* 4* UM # s rnvoy ^traordinsry ©ad Minister Pleni t*o tenii ry et tho Court of Porsls, rmm7 . 4* It must be realised that Bahrein Is becoming to an increasing extent the entrepot for He 3d ^nd the greater part of Worth Baetem Arabia, and that this port has lately, for reasons vshich it is not necessary to enter into here, to a Tery considerable degree usurped the position formerly held by Kuwait, and a large part of her tea and sugar imports go to supply the needs of the interior of Arabia. This accounts for the increase in sugar and tea imports of recent years, probably more than smuggling. 5. In any review of the economic condition of the Arab Coast, the only factor which really need be considered Is the Pearl industry. Bahrein alone exports annually some 1 ^ to 2 million pounds worth of pearls, probably more, since pearls safe always undervalued, and in good years the export may actually amount to as much as £5,000,000. In my opinion smuggling from Bahrein - carried on in the main by Persian merchants - cannot in the light of the facts be considered to constitute more than an unimportant and spasmodic trade, of i&amp;leh the extent is apt to be considerably exaggerated on account of its notorious character and imaginative appeal. 6 . While the present moment, owing to the slump in the pearl market, is not particularly opportune for the development of British Trade on the Arab Ooast, it is to be hoped that in the ordinary course, conditions will shortly improve and it would seem desirable to carry out a general preliminary survey of the market, so that when the purchasing power of the Arab principalities is regained, British and Indian merchants may be ready to profit by it.?♦ I would therefore suggest if you see no objection, that Mr,Blanch should accompany ae on a tour of the Arab porte which I propose to undertake in the 'Patrick Stewart ?t about the end of October, lasting approximately 3 weeks or a month. He could riollect Information from the Political Agents, make personal enquiries from local Indian and British liras and would be more qualified at the end of the tour to reoly to trade enquiries from the Department of Owerseas Trade etc., and would obtain a wider outlook of trade possi bilities in the Persian Oulf. 8 , ;s Mr.Blanch will be transported free of dharge no additional cost will be involved. 9. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Department of Oversea© Trade. I have, etc., (Sd.) H*V,BISQOE, Lieut-Oolonel. Political Hesident in the Persian Oulf and His Majesty’s Gonsul-Oeneral for Pars, KhuzistanUnder Secretary i. ( Ju Secretary of State ... Committee /V Smuggling in the Persian Gulf. Under Secretary Secretary of State... G c. SEEN BY SIR A. HIRTZEL. ^ &amp;JUN1929 SEf* yOLWCAl COMMITS Previous Payers 3287 2000 12.28 FOR INFORMATION. The earlier history of this question is given in the India Office memorandum of October 1928 - B. 408 - flagged 'G M below. vYith this there should be read the extract below from Tehran despatch No. 89, dated 16th February, reporting conversations between Sir Robert Clive, the Senior Naval Officer and the minister of Court in February last on the question of contraband. The present despatch is a palinode by the Senior Naval Officer as regards Arab responsibility for smuggling in the Dabai sector. Apart from this, it goes to confirm the statement made at an earlier stage by Sir Lionel Haworth (compare paragraph 9 of uhe Indie*. Office memorandum) that the areater part of the smuggling done was done in Persian ships/■ It ,, 1 ships, and was under the control of Persian interests. While the Senior Naval Officer's information comes from an Arab source, and must therefore be taken with some reserve in so far as it exculpates the Arabs, it goes on the whole to support the conclusion already reached in the light of the information available to us that the suppression of the smuggling nuisance is a matter essentially for Persia herself in the first instance. It is regrettable that Captain Boyes on the incomplete information available to him should have committed himself so far as he did in the discussions with Taimourtache, for the impression JLu left by his remarks on the Minister of Court is not likely easily to be effaced. &gt;OLmcAL .coiiiurm Uja 1928 l % y- xy «Extract from Tehran despatch No. 89, dated loth February. ... 6 . As it seemed possible that in the course of our interview there might arise the question of contraband, I asked Captain Boyes for any information he could give me on the subject. It appears that at present the biggest centre in the Gulf for smuggling is Bahrein, but the traffic from the island is carried on almost entirely in Tangistani (Persian) vessels, and not in Arab dhows. These vessels sail as a rule four or five together. If an armed customs launch is seen, the leading boat takes a different course to act as a decoy. If it is then pursued, as appears usually to be the case, by the Persian customs boat, the remaining vessels quietly pursue their way to trie Persian coast, there to land their contraband goods. 7. From Dabai, on the other hand, the contraband traffic is entirely carried on by Arab dhows. The above facts were explained to Taimourtache, who expressed great interest in the matter.E l 19^9 I British Legation, May 7 th 192 g . /N His Majesty’s Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Simigglinf* in the Persian Gulf. Reference: paragraph 7 of Tehran despatch no. 89 c) of Fehruaiy 16th, 1929. From the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, II.Jl.S. 'Triad' at Bombay, to the Honourable the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. April 10th, 1929. Ko.’dS/E/^/l[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [PNL412/1016/34] 2664 I No. 1. March 18, 1929. Section 14. Sir R. Clive to Sir Austen Chamberlain.—[Received March 18.) (No. 110.) Sir, Tehran, February 27, 1929. I HAVE the honour to report that during his stay in Tehran I arranged for Captain Boyes, senior naval officer in the Persian Gulf, to meet Commander del Prato, of the Italian Naval Mission. 2. Captain Boyes will no doubt report fully to the Admiralty, but I have thought it well to transmit to you a copy of the report which the military attache to this Legation has sent to the Director of Military Operations and Intelligence at the War Office. 3. I also enclose a record of the conversation which Mr. Havard had with Major Dezan, another officer of the Italian Naval Mission. 4. Copies of this despatch and of its enclosures are being sent to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India and to His Majesty’s High Commissioner for Iraq. I have, &amp;c. R. H. CLIVE II Enclosure 1 in No. 1. Major Woodward to Director of Military Operations, War Office. Memorandum. THE following information regarding proposed Persian naval forces has been gleaned from Commander del Prato by Captain Boyes, British senior naval officer, Persian Gulf:— Navy. Two vessels of 1,000 tons each, internal combustion engines, probably armed with two 4-inch guns and two machine guns. These vessels may also be used for surveying. Revenue Service. Four gunboats of 250 tons each, internal combustion engines ; armament, one 50-mm. gun and two machine guns. The above are being built in Italy, due to arrive in the Gulf middle of 1930. At Mohammerah. A floating dock to lift 2,000 tons. A floating workshop. A barrack and training school to take 200 men. Nine Persian officers are being trained in Italy and are to come to Persia at the end of 1930. A naval mission of Italian officers and petty officers is also to come to Persia. As the Persians know nothing whatever about naval matters, Prato is experiencing some difficulty in his dealings with them. The items in the current budget relative to the navy are:— For purchase of new and repair of old vessels and expenses in connexion with foreign naval officers, 400,000 tomans. There are two items “credits for sending students to Europe” under the military and general budgets respectively, but this money will have been earmarked already. Under the circumstances it appears an ambitious programme with the funds available, and will take some years to complete. R. F. WOODWARD, Major, Military Attache. Tehran, February 17, 1929. [744 s —14]Enclosure 2 in No. 1. Minute by the Oriental Secretary. MAJOR DEZAN, one of the Italian naval mission, told me last night that he was . very pessimistic as to the ability of the Persian Government to put a stop tof^e smuggling going on in the Gulf. He said he was sent down to Bushire to make a report, and he was told the matter was most urgent. He came back and submitted his report of the 15th January, and has since heard nothing further, and he thought he might hear nothing further for quite a long time. He told me that when he was in Bushire he enquired how much smuggled goods (sugar) had been captured during the last year; the total amount was 2,000 sacks, whereas the Government is supposed to be losing a revenue of 400 tomans a day. He thought that the means at the disposal of the Government for preventing this trade were quite inadequate, and one of the chief reasons he had for being despondent was that the smugglers and the crews of the preventive vessels were all friends, if not even relations; it was, therefore, difficult to expect the crews to do their very best for the Government at the expense of their friends, and, moreover, if they went too far they exposed themselves and their families to revenge. On the other hand, the Persians were not seamen and had not the means of manning these boats with any other material. February 20, 1929. G. T. HA YARD.Minute Paper. ■'S 2759 go) Department. ■II The Year 1927-28. The year was unfavourable for trade as there was still no trade with Najd. Although the imports and exports show higher rate than that of the last year, considerable quantity of the imported goods remained unsold, partly owing to unsettled state of the country round Kuwait during the winter months, which hampered such trade with the hinter land that does still exist: and perhaps more so, to the increased efficiency of the Persian Preventive Service which has practically stopped the smuggling of sugar and tea to the Persian Coast. Consequently many people left Kuwait for Bahrain, Jubail and Qatif to seek employment: and even a few merchants transferred to Bahrain and are carrying on trade there. The pearling season was considerably better than those of the two previous years. The number of oysters was not large but the yield was fairly rich. The pearl market had also improved but was far from good. j.*(x' cn a $*~*&lt;*m. j-Date. Initials. To • Cinder Secretary lu ' * * / ik Secretary ot State... Committee 2( Under Secretary Secretary of State... £: L. ru^ yyi C - c. SY SIR A. HIRT 7 £L 2 2 MAR 1929 M COMMITTEE Previous Papers: Persian complaints of smuggling in the Gulf: Attitude of His Majesty’s Government. Copy to 2877 1000 6.28 FOR INFORMATION. The^history of this question is given in the India Office memorandum, &lt;3 B. 408, flagged^below. In his telegram No. 93 of 20th February Sir Robert Clive suggested that it might be possible to assist Persia in the matter by allowing her to have a Consul at Bahrein; by a guarantee that Tamb and Abu Musa would not become depots for smuggling; by allowing her, if she so wished, to buy gun boats in Great Britain, and possibly by a special agreement authorising her to search ships suspected of smuggling outside the three- mile territorial waters limit. The instructions sent to the Minister by the Foreign Office in their telegram of 14th march, of which a copy isnow submitted, represent the result of official and private discussion with this Department. From our point of view they are entirely satisfactory. They have been repeated to the Government of India, who will thus be acquainted with the position. Sir Robert Clive's despatch of 2nd February on P. 2169/29 on -this subject is now a little out of date, but both it and the memorandum prepared by the Minister on the smuggling question, of which a copy has been obtained privately from the Forei^i Office, are of interest. The answer to the point raised in the is briefly that the Persians cannot reasonably expect us to go out of our way to meet them by making concessions on the higji seas until they have put territorial waters in order. The opinions which have since been expressed by the Gulf authorities and the Government of India still further emphasise, moreover, the very awkward reactions on our relations with the * t Arab Rulers of any special concession to Persia in the matter. 9 / 1 SEEN 3 - w^ [This Document lg the Property of H is Britannic Majesty's Government, and should be (E 1218/2/34) returned t o the Foreign Office if not required for hoc.].. P To PERSIA. 2242 Cypher telegram to Sir E. Clive (Tehran)-j &gt;9 Foreign Office, 14th March, 1929. 5.40 p.m. No. 108. Your tolo.-TcUn No. 93 (oi tins 20tli NolDruouy• Possibility of offering British assistance to Persia in her contraband difficulties). Government of India’s objections to allowing appointment of Persian consul at Bahrein have 00 on fully explained to you in a letter sent by ba.g February 28th. It is definitely undesirable that His Majesty’s Government should themselves permanently undertake such obligations as 0 . guarantee that Tamo and Aon Musa shall not become depots for smuggling. It might be feasible to give the Persian government an assurance, as part of the general settlement, that the /nab sheikh who owns the islands will take the necessary measures to prevent smuggling on a large scale from them into Persia, but you should make no statement on ah is subject to tne Persian government at the present stage. When the neg 0 1iations have proceeded further, His Majesty’s Government will be prepared to consider a recommenda tion from you that some such assurance should be offered for bargaining purposes and as a special concession. A special agreement regarding territorial waters giving Persia the right of search in certain areas outside the three-mile limit would give rise to so many2 •* many difficulties that you should not yourself raise the subject. If It is raised by the Persian government, you should abstain from conmittlng yourself and state merely that the proposal Is ono which you will refer to His Majesty's Government. I fear that In these circumstances the less said about the possibility of offering Persia British assistance in her contraband difficulties the better. Repeated to India No. 17.i [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [E 1016/1016/34] f o 6 ° February 25, 1929. Section 2 . No. 1. Sir R. Clive to Sir Austen Chamberlain.—(Received February 25.) (No. 72.) y ' Tehran, February 2, 1929. I HAVE the honour to report that the Minister of Court at my last interview again referred to the vast smuggling trade in the Persian Gulf. The customs authorities, he said, estimated at 4 million to 6 million tomans, i.e., somewhere round £1 million, the annual loss to the Persian Treasury. This is probably an eNaggeration, but no one denies that the traffic is enormous and on the increase. 2. In a private letter to Sir Denys Bray of the 9th December, a copy of which , ^ y was sent to Mr. Oliphant, I enclosed a brief memorandum/on this subject in which I / ^ pointed out that the Persians were determined to take such steps as were possible to check this traffic, and added that if we could in any way assist them without laying up too much trouble for ourselves with the Arabs, 1 should be very glad. 3. The Resident at Bushire, to whom I also sent a copy of this memorandum, has written to me privately that he does not propose to enlarge on the subject until his views are asked by the Government of India, but that his views would be that the Italianised Persian navy would probably be a lesser evil than interference on our part, a,s the Arabian coast sheikhs were already exasperated at what they consider our failure to support them in the matter of recent Persian interferences, and any attempt to restrain their actions in the interests of Persian excise would be likely to have far-reaching results. 4. It is in this connexion that the Persian counter-draft Slavery Convention presents an obvious difficulty. Taimourtache has proposed that there should be reciprocal right of search of Vessels of the other country of under 500 tons, and has told me privately that in practice this would give His Majesty’s Government what they want, while the Persian right would be a dead letter. It would obviously be dangerous to take this remark of the Minister of Court too seriously, and the Resident at Bushire, in his telegram No. 66 to the Government of India of the 27th January, made the following observation on the question of reciprocal right of search : — “ Difficulties seem to arise in the case of a large number of Arab dhows flying their own flag under our protection. There will be strong temptations to the Persians, especially in their present attitude, to harass these under cover of slavery. ’ ’ I agree that this would appear very likely to happen. The Italianised Persian navy, in their eagerness to find contraband, might be tempted to hold up dhows on the pretext of searching for slaves when they were really searching for contraband. It would be necessary, therefore, to make it clear to the Minister of Court that no illicit interference with Arab dhows would be tolerated should His Majesty’s Government be disposed eventually to admit reciprocal right of search in a new slavery convention. 5. On the other hand, this wholesale contraband trade by dhow T s claiming our protection does, in my humble opinion, justify the Persians in wishing to extend their police control outside the 3-mile limit. 6. Copies of this despatch are being sent to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India and to His Majesty’s High Commissioner for Iraq. I have, &amp;c. R. H. CLIVE. [716 bb—2]TUtg 5^ &gt;V (E 10X6/1016/34) Dear laithwaite. In accordance with your request, I enclose a copy of Clive's 'memorandum' on smuggling mentioned in paragraph 2 of his despatch No,72 of February 2. He does not appear to have sent us a copy of his covering private letter to Bray, but this 'memorandum' is evidently the important document. He also sent a copy of it privately to Johnston, A*' &amp; J,Gr, Laithw&amp;ite, Esq, ,(E 1016/1016/34) I have not had any detailed discussion yet on Gulf questions, hut we must realise that the Persian Government will take any steps in their power to check the vast smuggling trade from the Arab coast and Islands, which according to Teymourtaohe has its organising centre in Bombay, There is no doubt whatever that from Bahrein and Labai in particular it is a well organised traffic on a very large scale. If any means could be devised to help the Persians in this matter I do not say they would be grateful - as gratitude is not in the Persian make-up - but we can certainly put them under an obligation and to that extent strengthen our meagre bargaining counter in other respects. The Persian point of view as I understand it is some thing of this sort :- The British say to us hands off the Arab Coast of the Gulf and any islands claimed by the Arabs on the ground that they have treaties and Conventions with these Arab Sheikhs - in other words they claim a sort of veiled protectorate. We com plain of the organised smuggling. The British say we are very sorry, but this is really no concern of ours, H.M* Ships cannot be expected to do police work for a foreign country and by what right can we interfere. If you want to stop smuggling you had better take the usual precautions. The Persians say, in that case we will buy gunboats which we cannot afford, hire Italian officers and start a navy. If this navy materialises what is to happen to the Slavery Convention, Lighting and Buoying in Persian waters, Henjam/Henjam, etcetera? We cannot have it both ways. The navy probably will materialise to a limited extent, but if we could genuinely help them over this smuggling business without laying up too much trouble for oneself with the Arabs, I should be very glad* I do hope therefore you may be able to look into « this question. I realise the difficulties but we do want to retain all we can in the ^ulf and I feel that a complete non-possumus attitude will not be understood by the Persians and certainly won't help matters.! r|&gt;i i T — i. ^. ■—■■■■wnii -o [Tfaiia PocumBiit is the Property of His Britannic F^tg^ty^-Qo^eit&gt;nrent, and should be returned to the Foreign Office J!t rpt required for-nfRcial •rom 'un;.2. J, 184 Decypher Sir K. Clive (Tehran). , 20th Pebru.ary, 1923. D. 5.50 p.m. 20th February, 1929. H. 9.00 a.m. 21st February, 1929. Mo. 93* Your telegram Mo. 59/ Subject to Persian Government’s meeting our essential requirements in the Gull we could; firstly allow Persian Government to have Consul in Bahrein. Secondly guarantee that Tamb and Abu Musa would not become depots for smuggling. Thirdly allow Persian Government if they so wish to buy gunboats m Great Britain. Although I did not have this in mind, any such agreement as that referred to in my telegram immediately preceding would I imagine be highly appreciated by the Persian Government, but I quite realize this may be very undesirable. Addressed to the Foreign Office, repeated to India No, 53. (Too)This Document la the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] COPY . A ' 774/19/34) Cypher telegram to Sir H. Clive (Teliran). Foreign Oil ice, 19th February, 1929, 12.45 p.rn. No. 69. Your telegram No. 67 (ol the 11th February. Persian negotiations). I approve your proposed action. You realise pre-war debt of £490,000 will have to be repaid and necessary arrangements will have to be made therefor. I appreciate desirability of adding to the credit column anything we properly can, but doubt whether we could promise a 'helpful attitude in Persian Contraband difficulties.' What form do you suggest this attitude should take, and what cun we really do except possibly allow Persia to buy gunboats iron firms in Great Britain? It is clear from Government of India's telegram No. 1732 S. of September 4th that we cannot undertake strict control of tea and sugar exported from the territories under British protection on the Arabian side of the Gulf; and you will be careful to say •nothing to the Persians that might raise false hopes or be misunderstood. Repeated to India No. 12.1 / ' / - Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] FiiOM iM Decypher. Sir E. Clive, (Tehran) 11 th Februar:/, 1929 D. 6,00 p.m. 11 th February, 1929 E. 9.00 a.m. 12 th February, 1929 No. 67. M il V I* »l »« H li W U tt ft H It H H It M H fl tl ft It Your telegram No. 53 and my telegram No. 66 of February ilth. Bahrein QueGt/ion cerbainly present's createsu difiiculuy and I am at a loss to find a way acceptable to Minister of Court of saving the Persian face. I can (?only) suggest submitting to him balance sheet on following lines, subject to your approval. Credit : Basidu. Three wireless stations (one to oe leased to us). Non-agression clause. Helpful attitude in Iraq settlement (your telegram No. 44). Ihtto in nis ne gotiations with Anglo-Perslan Oil Company Limited. Debit i Hen Jam. Tumb and Aau (?Abu) Musa. Bahrein. Certain claims, e.g. Persian railway syndicate. Debt (this to be transferred eventually to credit). Telegraphs, Duzdap railway, slavery convention, and ligliting and buoying should hardly figure on either side as they are, or should be, mutually advauts-fseous. If i could add to cre dit side 'helpful attitude in Persian co ntraband difficulties', this wdul&lt;l ‘be of great assistance. Meanwhile I will defer saying anything about banre^n beyond suggesting that press campaign should cease. Yhen presenting balance sheet I would explain vny hi© piopOoal is impracticable.—i ^ \ ( 2 ) I hope I may he authorized as soon as possible to mention Shatt-el-Arab proposals and inform Minister of Court, if only in strict confidence, of proposed abolition of judicial agreement, Regarding debt, I consider it would be well that I should now address a letter to the Minister recaptu- lating debt and Persian promise to pay, and adding that I will later address him on the subject of other claims. Addressed to Foreign Office, repeated to India, No, 40,A i_ — — MkI f F- -fl “SVSO /OJ^j , Xo. ‘S / : Ccri^v-L\4 ^xX^Ti^yii C^yx^ciy ^ ^G-iss^lz cr^ 9 U We spoke of smugg'Hig in the Gulf, I said that while Ills Majesty 5 s Government sympathised with Persian government it was extremely difficult to assist theme His Majesty’s Ships could obviously not do police work for a foreign country. He agreed and then enquired whether Ills Majesty’s Government would he ready to sell to Persia one or two gun boats, I said I thought Persia v r as buying them from Italy* He said, no ; , they were only buying sliallow draft customs boats, I did not pursue the subject. l i(P. 6536/28) m AW AX WITH Extract from Intelligence Summary No. 22 for the Period ending November 3rd, 1928. AW* Persian Gulf. 20. anu^ling . - The Customs Department are considering the construction of preventive stations at points along the coast of the Gulf, providing berthing facilities for preventive service craft.3144 b lb 1028 **UT AWAY WITH v\&gt; V* CONFIDENTIAL. INDIA OFFICE, p^gg. Persian Complaints of Smuggling in the Persian Gulf. 1. The relevancy to the Persian attitude towards the independence of . , ircin and of the Trucial Sheikhdoms of recent Persian complaints about Y V _ 1 * _ „. A. ^ I ) ^ i r-» /-»/-'v 4- f 1 1 /■» A &gt;»0 1 'v iJahr the prevalence Mr of smuggling to the South Persian coast from the Arab littoral and from the Persian Gulf islands makes it desirable briefly to set out the recent history of this question, and the result of the investigation made by His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India of the extent to which assistance could be given to Persia in the suppression of the contraband traffic. 2. On various occasions during the past year His Majesty’s represen tatives at Tehran and the Political Resident have emphasised that the problem is one of very serious dimensions, and the Belgian Administrator-General of Customs informed Mr. Parr, in the summer of this year, in connection with the Tamb incident, that the Sheikhs on the Trucial coast were all associated with smuggling, and that “his people are at their wits’end how to cope with it.” The serious development of the trade apparently dates from the imposition by Persia in 1925 of a monopoly tax on all consignments of tea and sugar imported from abroad. The situation is rendered difficult by the fact that the Persian Government have practically no means of coping with it on the sea, and ven^ inadequate means for dealing with it on the coast, the corruption of the local officials being a serious factor, while the fact that the motor launches possessed by the Customs administration, although they carry an automatic gun, are not armoured, places them at a disadvantage in dealing with armed smugglers. 3. A formal request to His Majesty’s Government to assist them in suppressing smuggling on the Gulf has not so far been made by the Persian Government, and there is no special reason to suppose that such a request is likely to be made in the course of the forthcoming negotiations. Active steps, in fact, are apparently being taken by Persia to deal with the problem in other ways, and there is reason to suppose that the Persian Government contemplate the purchase of half a dozen Italian vessels, and the engagement of an Italian Naval Officer for preventive service in the Gulf. As will be seen from what follows, the matter has, however, been brought to the notice of His Majesty’s representatives on various occasions, both by the Minister of Court and by the Belgian Customs officials. 4. The importance to Persia of the suppression of the traffic was mentioned to Sir Robert Clive by the Persian Minister of the Court at the beginning of the present year, in connection with the Persian claims to Bahrein, and Sir Robert Clive then suggested to His Majesty’s Government that it might be possible to dispose directly of the Persian claims to the island if it was possible to meet Persia in regard to the prevention of smuggling from Bahrein to the Persian coast. On the 27th January Sir Robert Clive reported an interview with the Administrator-General of Customs, in which M. Molitor had stated that during the past year the Persian Government had been hard hit by the smuggling conducted from Koweit, Bahrein and Dabai, and that all the reports received from his agents insisted that to take effective measures for the cessation of this illicit traffic British co-operation was necessary. The only practical suggestion which the Administrator-General could make, however, was that the resident British authorities in the ports mentioned great deal by having ships’ manifests inspected, and the cargoes supervised.” 5. In the light of the Minister’s representations, which assumed particular importance in view of the desirability of disposing of the question of Bahrein in direct negotiation with Persia rather than through the League of Nations, the question of possible action to assist the Persian Government was carefully investigated by the Admiralty and the Government of India. The results, however, were not such as to show that any effective assistance could conveniently be given to Persia, the objections to action being partly of a general political character, and partly based on grounds of practicability. Teh. Desp. 137, Mar. 23 1928, P. 1975. Teh. tel. 2Tt5, Aug. 14. P. 4368/28. Teh. tel. 236, Aug. 8 1928, P. 4219. Teli. tel. 13, Jan. 15, P. 296/28. Teh. Desp. 53, Jan. 27 1928, P.879. “ could help a loading of theAdm. to F.O., Jan. 25 1928, P. 409. Tel. from Pol. Res. to G. of I., Mar. 31 1928, P. 2005. Tel. from Viceroy to S. of S. for I., 1782 S., Sept. 41928, P.4783. Viceroy’s tel. 1782 S. Sept. 4 1928. P.4783. 6. On the question of action by His Majesty’s ships, the Admiralty, who drew attention to the fact that the Navy had no power to take action against persons infringing Persian smuggling laws, stated that it would be contrary to the policy hitherto pursued for the Navy to take any active steps in civil operations such as the prevention of smuggling. The only action which could, in their view, be taken without a departure fro^ precedent would be to report cases in which smuggling appeared to bt taking place which came under the notice of His Majesty’s ships. They presumed that this would be unlikely to be ol much assistance. 7. The matter was very carefully investigated by the Political Resident and by the Government of India. The result of its examination by Sir Lionel Haworth was to indicate that assistance to Persia was not merely politically undesirable, but unlikely to produce any result of value. 8. The political objections seen by the Resident, with whose views the Government of India agreed, were that assistance could be given only by applying to the Arab rulers of the Arab littoral pressure which was not justified under the treaties between His Majesty’s Government and those potentates, vis-d-vis whom His Majesty’s Government had no sort of right to interfere; that any attempt to ap)ply such pressure would react very adversely on the position of His Majesty’s Government on the littoral in question ; and that at a time when the consolidation of the British position in that area was more than ever important, the arguments for action of such a character in the interests of a Government which had done nothing to meet us on any point were not convincing. 9. Apart from the general political objections set out above, the Political Resident stated that to force the rulers affected to adopt the preventive measures which would be necessary if anything was to be achieved would be difficult at Bahrein, except at considerable expense; still more difficult at Koweit; impossible at Dabai, unless the whole policy of His Majesty’s Government on the Trucial coast was altered, and completely impracticable at El Katr (close to Bahrein), except by an increase in the British Naval force in the Gulf, after the manner adopted in the case of the arms traffic, and its employment for the purpose. As for concentrating action against Bahrein, Sir Lionel Haworth reported that smuggling took place not only from Bahrein, but from the entire length of tile Arab coast, and that the success of measures against the Principality would only drive the trade to other ports, over which no effective control is exercised by His Majesty’s Government. A final objection to action on the part of His Majesty’s Government was that the greater part of the smuggling done was done from Persia in Persian ships, and not from Bahrein ; that it would be stopped to a great extent if Persia could spend money for,patrolling her own coast; and that the real difficulty was that all the Persian Khans were interested in smuggling, that the Persian Customs officials were bribed, and that the country of Tangistan was out of Persian control. 10. The Government of India, in expressing their agreement with the views of the Political Resident as set out above, add that vis-d-vis Persia “it is not our business to control harmless exports like sugar from our Arab Protectorates, and Persia’s apparent expectation to the contrary . . . has, as far as w r e know, no basis in international usage.” Summary. 1L It appears quite impracticable, in view of the difficulties set out by the Indian authorities, and the objections of principle seen by the Admiralty, for His Majesty’s Government to lend any effective assistance to Persia in dealing with the problem of smuggling. The political objections to the application of pressure to the Arab rulers of the Gulf are very strong in present circumstances, and they are reinforced by the practical difficulties to which Sir Lionel Haworth draws attention. It is to be regretted that it is impossible to assist Persia in this matter, for an offer of help by His Majesty’s Government, if indeed it was likely to produce any effective result, might form a useful lever for bargaining purposes. But the objections to action appear to be insuperable. India Office, J. G. L. 1st October 1928.(un) i t it &lt; 19. /'reventlve ^ervice . Patrol vessels of the Customs Department have had more than one conflict with Tangistani smuggling craft, in which the Tang is tail is came off Pest. Occasional disturbances also occur on the island of Bushire between troops and bands of smugglers. Small detachments of 15-20 men have been installed at various small Tangistan and ^hib Koh posts to assist in prevent work. GULF PORTS.Minute Paper. HUT AWAY WITH (to^ Register No. P. SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMEWT. Dated 192 , Rec. Date. Initials. • SUBJECT. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee 2^. K//V Persian Gulf. Possibility of effective action by His Majesty’s Government to stop smuggling to Persian Coast. Under Secretary Secretary of State... Views of Political Resident. / . \lu/) Dip Copy to ^ ( %o ri'&gt;.v Ah— 1 SEEN BV SIR A. HIRTZEL 2 7 AUG 1928 Previous Papers :— 2069d 2000 6.27 FOR INFORMATION. Legation telegram No.144, referred to by Sir Lionel Haworth, referred, in connection with the Tamh incident, to the fact that smuggling from the Trucial Coast was a lucrative and well-estatlished business which caused the greatest difficulty to the Persian Customs authorities. The question of smuggling has already been raised by Persia in connection with Bahrein. Sir Robert Clive, in January last, rsdfcsed the -queation whether satisfaction could be given to the Minister of Court on the prevention of smuggling from Bahrein to the Persian Coast (Teheran telegram 1515 of 13th January P.263)• The matter was examined hy the Admiralty and by the Political ^ Resident. The conclusion reached was that there was nothing effective to he done. I The Admiralty, without departing from precedent, could not go beyond reporting cases where smuggling was apparently taking place which came under the notice of H.M. ships and indicated that they had no powers to take action against persons infringing the Persian smuggling laws. The Political Resident reported (telegram dated 31st March to Government of India, P.2005) that the greater part of smuggling was done from Persia itself and not from Persian ships , and would be stopped to a considerable extent if Persia would spend money for controlling her own coast. He did not think that anything could be done on the Arab Coast without running serious risk of alienating Arab feeling in return for an inconsiderable result. No action appears to have been taken on a suggestion made by us to the Foreign Office that the Persian Government should, by a rescript from the shah or in whatever other manner was proper, give us powers to search, on their behalf, Persian vessels plying between Bahrein and the Mainland on the analogy of the action taken by them in connection with theMinute Paper Department j I 1 the arms traffic in the Gulf. In July the Resident, in submitting his general recommendations on the points likely to be considered by the Persian Gulf Sub Committee, expressed the opinion that 'if we tried we could not stop smuggling except by armed force as in the case of arms traffic as smuggling takes place from places spread over 600 miles of Coast and not only from Bahrein'); telegram dated 10th July, P.4302). We have not had the despatch from the Consul at Shiraz referred to by Sir Lionel Haworth in his present telegram nor have the Foreign Office, but presumably it takes the same objections to action as are stated above. On the main proposition stated by the Resident-that there is no reason why we should do anything to help Persia unless Persia adopts a more amenable attitude towards usr there is no dispute. The chances of an arrangement with the Persian Government on the lines suggested in his second paragraph are probably extraordinarily small in their present temper, but the possibility of a bargain with them under which we should, as suggested in the first paragraph of the telegram, adopt a more active policy, is one which can be considered in the course of the forthcoming negotiations. It seems unnecessary to take any further action on the telegram, copies of which have been sent to Foreign Office, Colonial Office, Admiralty and Air Ministry.r B3/PEB/'W-W? 4- 4 5 4 (126 2 n (i un i ' 2 5 AUG 1928 C 9 Q. v 0 F__T S if.JL.G-B..-J &gt;. M (\U^ (CGPixiS CIP.CULATED) Frois Political Resident in the Psreicn Gulf to Govsnunsnt of India# and repeated by former to Secretary of State India© Dated Shiraau 18th Auguet# 1928, Received I8tfc August# 1928# 12.45 a. mo (f tr 1 , 00 $ •*\]?&gt; 225_T 0 Legation telegram No. 144 to yon# laat paragraph. U ’ v *\\^ While it is doubtful whether we could at any time take effective measures to stop smiiggling to Persian coast (in this reference see Consul at Shiraz Despatch No. 51 to Legation dated June 29th# 1926# especially paragraph No. 9 and paragraph No. 10)# it is quite clear that it would be an act of political folly to attempt to do so while Persia is attempting to drive ua out of the Persian Gulf# and we are consequently depending upon the Arabs for our position in these waters© If# however# Persia admitted our paramount position in the Persian Gulf as stated in my telegram 209 T p then it would be worth our while to take measures which# even if as unsuccessful as I think they must be# would have at any rate some effect on smuggling# and would show our goodwill to Persia© Rut Persia cannot have it both ways. They cannot drive us out from the Persian coast and# at the same tim* y use our position which, still exists on the Afcab coast for their purposes. Can we not persuade Persia that it is to her own interestinterest d both for Custcros revenue and for protection against Russia^ that we should hold the position that we have held in the past in the Persian Gulf* If they understand that we are firm in the maintenance of our necessities (sic) in this respect 0 it ma 2 ^ assist* They can never themselves be a naval powers and a continuance of their present policy must drive us into definite opposition to thenia which can only harm theme They want political power in Persian with the Gulf in our hands* we can assist them in t-his^ but if they oppose ue 0 as they are now doings they change the situation* Persia has neither gratitude nor honesty* but her politicians^ if unscrupulous* are clever men who will see the truth of the above* Report on question of ownership of Tunb follows* Addressed to Indian repeated to Secretary of State for India* 225 T 0 and Tehran* X 50«</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00014c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3766</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00014c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3766</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/50 'Persian Gulf: Smuggling'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-01-02T22:00:27</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (110 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 112; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains extracts from the diary of the British Residency and Consulate-General in Bushire that relate to smuggling in the Persian Gulf. In addition to these extracts, the file also contains a limited amount of associated correspondence between British officials and the following documents:Copy (in French) of the Persian [Iranian] Government's law for the repression of voter fraud (folios 36-54)Copy of the Persian Government's law relating to the punishment of smugglers (folios 57-60)'Persian Complaints of Smuggling in the Persian Gulf' an India Office memorandum from 1928 (folio 106).The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Smuggling</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00014c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>