<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000166_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:19:55.013Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CONFIDENTIAL. No. 1799-' of 1933. a • '• w The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to '’he Ajrent, Muscat, The p oli ti e?»l n *he 'olitical \frent, Afront 0 Bahrain» Kimait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (// for infor^ntior only . British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated .AS?;. SffZWi&amp;tK. AS33* Reference to previous correspondence ; Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. ^ral Kimiteo of Meetinft held at the India Off! ce on Monday,&lt;?th 1 ^ 53 , *• Subject. ^oreiifn Oonoular Reurenentation in the Aroian (’ulf. \/kSU*S» ' ^ 9 /'.p/ /\/ /f ^ Minutes of me e ting held at India Office on Monday,, 9th October, to consider the question of foreign consular representat i on in the Persian G-ulf . There were present Mr, Laithwaite (in the Chair), Lieutenant Colonel T.C.Fowle, C.B.S,, Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, and Mr. K.R.Johnstone, Foreign Office. Mr, Laithwaite said that the meeting arose out of Bushire despatch No.847 S of 20th July to the Government of India on the subject of foreign consular representation in Bahrein. The Government of India had. since intimated that they saw no objection to the discussion of the points in issue by the Political Resident during his leave in this country, but that they wished to be informed of what took place at the discussion and consulted before any decision was taken. 2, The question had arisen in connection with the possibility of an American request to be allowed consular representation in Bahrein; but it seemed desirable not merely to deal with this specific point, but also so far as possible to endeavour to reach agreement on certain broad principles as regards foreign consular representation in the Gulf States. The question was probably a live one in Bahrein and Koweit only, (the position of Muscat being of course special) though it might arise in Qatar in the event of oil being developed in that principality/principality. There was no likelihood at tlus stage of the question of foreign consular representation arising in the Trucial area. 3. The meeting first discussed the question of the action to be taken in the event of the American Vice-Consul at Bushire repeating his visit to Bahrein Showing signs of consular activity or raising the question whether there would he any objection to his performing consular acts in that Principality. The Acting Political Resident had suggested that it might be sufficient on the first occasion, if the Consul were to show signs of such activity, for the Political Agent to draw his attention to the Exclusive Agreement of 1892, between the Sheikh of Bahrein and H.M.G-* If the question were then to arise of the Consul performing some specific act at Bahrein, such as the solemnisation of marriage, which was not within the powers of the Political Agent, the Political Agent might reply that as a matter of courtesy he would raise no objection on that particular occasion provided that a request for the act was made by the person concerned through the Political Agent. The Political Agent might add, should circumstances appear to necessitate this, that the question of future procedure would be referred to H.M.G. 4. The general sense of the meeting was in favour of action on the lines suggested by the Acting Political Resident, with the modification however that it would be undesirable that the American Consul should be allowed to perform in his consular , capacity any special act even as a matter of courtesy. 5 ./3. 3* The meeting then turned to consider the possi bility of laying down general principles applicable in tne case of a owe it and Bahrein and possibly Qatar, The India Office suggested these might be as follows:- (a) that we should oppose any attempt to establish foreign consular representatives;. (b) that we should if necessary arrange for the ruler concerned to inform us that he ?/as strongly opposed to their estab 1 ishment; (c) that if any foreign Power were to raise thepoint we should explain our special Treaty relation with the States in question, and the objections of the local ruler, adding that we were not prepared to bring pressure to bear upon the ruler in the matter, but that we would gladly give our fullest good offices to any of the citizens of the interested Foreign Powers who might find themselves in the Sheikhdoms concerned and would instruct our representative to look Softer their interests; (d) that in the events referred to in (c) above it might be possible by friendly arrangement with the foreign Power concerned to agree, feat should that Power consider a mere offer of good offices in general that _ insufficient„/4cts which are normally consular acts such as the solemnisation of marriage should be performed as a matter of courtesy (but not as Consular Acts) by the Political Agent, whose action in the matter would be recognised by the interested foreign Powers, 6* Ilr, ^aithwaite referred to the previous history of this question. Ahe position of Puscat was special. It was an independent State with foreign treaties of its own and it would not be possible for us to take exception to a request by an interested foreign Power to establish a consulate at Muscat. The meeting agreed. 7. The Sheikh of Koweit was precluded by his Treaty engagements from receiving the representatives of any foreign power save with the approval of There had been considerable correspondence between 1924/k 4. 0) 1924 and 1S32 as to the possibility of appointing Persian, Iraqi, or Saudi consular representatives in the Sheikhdom. Tne Sheikh had taken the strongest exception to any such proposal and it had been necessary to overrule him before we could undertake even to offer our good offices to Persian subjects in Koweit. (We had in this connection informed the Persian Government m 1924 that the appointment of a Persian representative even in an honorary capacity would be contrary to the Agreement of 1899 between the Sheikh and H.M.G. ana that any departure from this agreement infavour of Persia would create a precedent which would prove embarrassing in the event of any other Powers proposing to appoint representatives.) When a suggestion was made at the beginning of 1930 that an Iraqi Vice Consul should be appointed at Koweit, Sir Francis Humphrys was similarly instructed to reply that H.M.G. were not prepared, having regard to the Agreement of 1899, to sanction the. appointment of foreign consular representatives and the matter was not pursued by the Iraqi Government. The Saudi Government had raised the question in 1932 with sir Hugh Biscoe, but had dropped it on their attention being drawn to the fact that the grant of consular status/d&gt; 5 status to their representatives would make it difficult for us to refuse a consular concession to the Persians. political Resident and the Government of India had been definitely opposed in 1928 to a proposal, made with the oeject of reconciling Persia to the abandonment of her claims to the Islands, to establish a Persian Agent in the island for face-saving purposes and had reported that such a proposal would have to be forced on the Sheikh with bad reactions a long the Arab littoral. The appointment of any foreign consular representative would make it difficult to refuse a similar.concession to the Persians and the Saudi Government aid it seemed probable that the objections of the sheikh of Bahrein to any such proposal would be no less definite than those of trie sheikh of Koweit. 9. Colonel Fowle expressed his general agreement with the suggested principles and with the course of action outlined above % He said that the sheikh of Koweit h the past and would still be very strongly opposed to any foreign representation in his State. The same was true of the Sheikh of Bahrein. Apart from any general political objections to the establishment of foreign representation such 8 . In tiie case of Bahrein the representation would have to he forced on tiie/*2) the Sheikh. If the Sheikh was definitely oDstin&amp;te, while we might overrule him as we had in Koweit, as regards the grant of good offices to foreign subjects, it would be most difficult, if not impossible, i.oi Uo to oblige him to accept xoreign rep re sentative s. i xlh-.. o o nnstone said that he thought the Foreign Office would not, in the light Oi- trie Resident's remarks, be disposed to dissent from the principles -under u isc u s s i on. It c o u Id no t, ho we ve r, be overlooked that while we might shelter behind the Sheikhs in refusing to accept foreign representatives, we should be Quite unable to convince foreign Powers that the Sheikh was not in fact acting under our instructions. This might lead to some difficulties. 11• Colonel Fowle admitted that this might be the case. But e ven so it made no difference to the facts. The objection oi hie locaa. rulers was real and sincere. In any event foreign Powers could not get behind our statement. 12. As' regards principle (d) above hlh___Johnstone stated that there appeared to oe three particular consular acts in regard to which difficulty was most likely to arise between 'the Political Agents at Bahrein or Koweit and foreign nationals, namely the solemnisation of marriages, the/I -tne registration of births and deaths and the granting of extensions to visas. As regards one lirst and second ~ apart from any exceptions v/hich foreign Governments might be inclined to make in the case of marriages, similar to the recognition accorded in English common law to marriages in uncivilised countries contracted in any solemn form - it would in an; Cctse De necessary to obtain the consent of the foreign Government concerned to the opening of registers of marriages, births and deaths recognised by them. And as regards the e xtension of visas, this 1 unction also couia clearly only be Ublegated to British Political Cfficeri with the consent of the foreign Government concerned. 13. The general sense of the meeting was w0 , ulci k, 6 J^st, subject to acceptance 01 the general principles suggested above by higher authority in the departments concerned and oy the Government of India, to cieal with specific incidents as they might arise. i INDIA OFFICE. 13tli October 1933.CONFIDENTIAL. - \ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gridf presents his com pliments to l, ^Y\e ^©litical Agent Bahrain t * P* Hie Political Agent, Kuwait ^ 3 a rr Tie Political Agent, KuBCat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment for information and comment •» if any* \ British Consulate-General,(received under India Office SVinted Letter Nq.P.%. 7583 / 33 )„ Cepy 0 Ho* r, 6143/5755/91. TORTSIGtt OT?l?ICT2 t 71st Hovenher, 1933. Bir 9 / ^ jf With reference to Mr. Laithuaite T s letter No.P.Z^ 6349/33 #f the 14th October to Mr.Johnstone. enclosing the provisional minutes of a meeting held at the India Office on Monday, the 9th October, to consider the question of foreign consular representation in the Persian Gulf, I am diree + ed by Secretary Sir TT@hn Simon to request you to inform Secretary ^ir Samuel Hoare, tthat,, with the reservations set out below, he concurs both in the particular course of action whi di is recommended in paragraph 4 of those minutes in the event of a visit of the United states Vice-Consul at Bushire to Rahraih, and also in the general principles to be followed in dealing with the question of foreign consular representa tion in this region, which are enumerated in paragraph 5 of the minutes. 7. 'here are, however, two points to which I am to request vou to invite Sir Samuel Hoare’s attention. While concurring in the view expressed in naragradi 4 of the minutes that the United S at os ice—Consul should not he allowed, even as a raa^ + er of courtesy, to perform any special acts in his consular capacity. Sir Simon considers that in Practice, eiren if the ^ice—Consul is allowed to perform such acts on the express understanding that they are not to be regarded as done in his consular capacity, it may subsequently be found difficult to refute the contention that they were in fact The Under Secretary of State, con sular/ India Office.6./ consular acts* It will, therefore* be better not to allow him to carry on any of^icl 1 activity whatever in 'Bahrain or Kuwai t. 3, Secondly* in connection with conclusion (d) in nara^ranh 5 of the minutes of the meeting, consideration has been /?iven in this deuar+ment to the question what measures -ould have t 0 be taken in order to establish on a proper lepal basis the services to be performed by 'British political officers for foreigners in the Arab B+ates of the Persian Oulf* supnosing that, as postulated in conclusion (d) , any foreign Power were not content with a general offer of the good offices of His Majesty’s Government and it became necessary to raake some detailed arrangement on that subject with the Power in question e Taking the different classes of consular services in order; the exercise of civil and criminal jurisdiction in so far as Bahrain is concerned is already sufficiently provided for, in principle, by Article 8 (p.) of the Bahrain 0 Council* 'Mie position will be the name in Kuwait .... if and when the nroposed revised Kuwait Order in Council is issued« p - A® regards ordinary consular assistance and urotection, the legalisation of documents and the registration of births, deaths and marriages, it will he sufficient if instructions are issued by the Secretary of Sta^e to the officers concerned emoowerinr them to perform the services in question. The recognition, however, by foreign courts or authorities of auy registers which may be opened under these instructions raus + of course depend uoan the local law of the forelyn country con cemcd o~3~ 6 a m here rsnainB the question of the celebration of marriages. Sir John f5im 0 n conniders it undesirable that the Political Agents at Bahrain and Kuwait should perform marriages between foreigners, ''he celebration of marriages by British officers is under the fbreipn Marriage Act and that Act only apnlies where one of the parties is a British subject* Although it may be legally possible to provide, by Order in Council under the foreign Jurisdiction Act, for formalities of marriage far foreigners subject to British jurisdiction, Sir John Simon does no + consider it necessary or desirable to endeavour to legislate specially for the nurpose of marriages bv these officers between foreigners, to whom the Bahrain (or Kuwait) 0rder in Counci 1 applies. In the first place, it in doubtful whether, for instance, such a marriage celebrated by the Political Agent at Bahrain between two Hhited Crates citizens would possess increased validity in TTnited States law owing to provisions for such marriages having been made by Order in Council, Again, TT nited States law, and indeed the laws ©f most countries, contain principles similar to the English common law marriage, under which marriages celebrated by a minister of religion or nor, yerhe In countries where there is no local form available are recognised as valid. Since, therefore, in all probability no special legal provision by Fis Majesty’s Government for such marriages would increase ♦heir vaiiditv in -^he eves of foreign governments, it seems best to leave them to be celebrated in one of the forms referred to above. 7. finally, as regards the registration of marriages, the Secretary of State sees no objection to the '’olitioal Aftent keeolnr a ren-inter for the marriages of fbreigners in 'Bahrain, in which he will record the Particulars of marriages reported byttm ’by the parties to have heen celebrated between then and the manner of their celebration* %&gt;p;i strati on of this hind is merely a record of what has taken place and is in no wav a celebration of marriage. Nor, as stated in paragraph 4 above, would such a register add any validity to the marriage or pur port to do so, but it might assist in the proof of a marriage if the question whether it had been celebrated arose at a later date* I am, ftir p Your obedient servant, (naj Mendel* LC CimD^NTIAL. POLI TIC AL AGEN CY, No. SIS • KIMAIT. Dated the 28th December 1935. From Lt.-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.E., I.A., Political Agent, Kuwait; To Tlie Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf , B u s h i r e . Foreign Consular representation in the Persian Gulf. Sir, ; ! /ith reference to endorsement No.l938-S, dated the 19/20th December 1935, forwarding a copy of Foreign Office despatch No.F-6143/5255/91, dated the 21st November, to Secretary of State for India; I have the honour to say that I have no comments to make. I have the honour to be, Sir , Your most obedient servant, a Lt.-Colonel, Political Agent, Kiiwaitn • V CONFIDENTIAL. No. 7 The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian (xulf presents his com pliments to 1. TVe Political Agent,Bahrain. 2. The political Agstofc,Muscat. 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- ment British Consulate-G-eneral, BUSHIRE. Dated.• Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. India Office letter ho. P.£.7583/33 dated the 15th Beceiaher 1933 to the Foreign secretary to the G-overnraent of India. Subject. Foreign consular representation at Bahrain.3opy. P.Z. 7583/33, 15th December 1933. Air Hifail. Sir, iith further reference to the Government of Inaia # s Express Letter Ho.F-218-11/38 aatefl 5th August on the sutjact of foreign consular representation at Bahrain, 1 aa directed by the Secretary of State to refer to the record of a meeting at the India Office on 9th October, at which Lieutenant-Colonel fowle was present, copies of which were sent to the Government of India and to the Political Lesifient hy the air mail of 21st October, ana to the Foreign Office letter of 21st November, No. H.6143/5255/91, of which copies were sent to the Govern ment of .iodia and the Political Besident by the sea mail of 23rd Novamber. v . I 2# subject to the reservations contained in the Foreign Office inter of 21st November, and to the observations of the Government of India, the Secretary of State is in general agreement with the conclusions of the matting of 9th October. If the Government of India share this view I am to suggest that the necessary instructions in the matter should be issued by them to the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, to whom a copy of this letter is beigg sent uirect. I am,oir, four ebeuient servant, sd. JwO.Walton. Foreign secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi.' u ■fy If % JocliuenLial • p fl « ^ ^ ^ x GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTE /ax’) Oi \ ■' [N. B % — This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed, as if it had been so despatcheds] — From olitieal Besicient, Bushire. ■ B T® lolitieal a ©nt, Bahrain, iolitical Agent, Kuwait. / La . iVflb &gt; oi 1934. Dated 31 st January JSH 4 .* g M SuoAect; Foreign Consular representation in the Persian Clulf. Beierepce correspondence ending with isushire printed Lette^Ko*46*3 dat^i the 2.1st January 1934. ^ xhe Coyernment oi Inuia concur in the views expressed in paragraph 2 of Secretary of otate tor Indian letter No. p.„. 75d3/33, dated the 15th Lece&amp;har 1933. 3. In the event of the nce-G nsul for the United States of America visiting Bahrain or Kuwait, please take action as detailed in pax-a^rapfe^ijof the Final Minutes of the LeeUi* held at th^ Inuia Office on the 9th uctoD8x last ic^py ^ j&gt;J 'forwarded to you unuer iiesidency Printed retter ho. 1792- - of 1st Kovemher 1933), subject to the modiiicati^ns DCFP—1566S&amp;P—(M*182l)—27 0-32—2^0,000. explained/2 - J explained in paragraph 4 of those iinntes anu in paragraph 2 of Foreign Office letter Ho.E 6145/5255/91 dated the 21st November 1953( copy forwarded to you unaer x^esiaency Printed Letter No* 1958-6 aated the 19th December 1955)* sd. T.C.Fowle, Lt.-Colonel, Political xxesiaent in the Persian Sulf. Major, for Secretary to the Political jaesiaent in the Persian cult*Telegram G.T.C. From Political, Kuwait. To Britconsul, Bushire. No. 72. Dated the 23rd February 1934. Private Secretary and third Secretary, American Legation, Baghdad, arrived Kuwait yesterday, returning today. They report that Minister proposes tour Gulf Ports next month, probably starting from Kuwait 10th March. I -POLI 'ICii- I'-A / r p ^ L ^ 0 * I b ' Telegram I.?.0.1927. From Resident , Bush ire. To Political, Kuwait. No. 238. Dated the 27th February 1934. Addressed to Political Agents, Bahrain and Kuwait f -lAj Repeated to Ambassador Baghdad. My telegram dated the 23rd instant, NoC226 to Muscat, copy of -hich was sent to you by post. I* Grateful if you could (1) Meet mnerican Minister, who leaves Basra by slow mail May 3rd (which does not stop at Kuwait) and give him appropriate meal (2) arrange for Shaikh to receive his informal call on his return journey from Muscat. II. I will be very pleased to see His Fxcellency here. -RESIDENT-Telegram I.F.Q. 1927 From To No* Dated Poll tic-31, Kuwait* Britconsul, Bushire* 75. the 27 th Februaiy 19 34. Your telegram of 27th instant, No.238. Instead of May 3rd, presume March 3rd is meant -POLITICiiL-Telegram From To No. Dated the I.F* 0.Ex.1927. Resident, Bushire. Political, Kuv/ait . Nil. 28th February 193 4. My telegram 238. For May 3rd, read March 3rd. -POLITICAL-CONFIDENTIAL. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. The Political Agent, Bahrain, 2. Tne Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. ^ ate&lt; ^ SSrd^sfcmiHrjrl^CA Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. j, -&gt;1 Telegram Bo. 22^, dated the 23ra Feoruary-1934, to the Political Agent, Muscat. Purposed visit of the American Minister to Musest and the Persian Gulf.\/ Telegram R.30 From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Muscat. Copy by post to Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Kuwait. Ho• 226• Bated 23rd February 1934. . Q My telegram Bo. 202. Following telegram Bo. 10 of 21at February AJabassador Baghdad begins. United States Minister proposes to leave Basrah Marhh 3rd by el^jg; mail due to arrive Muscat about 12th and leave Muscat by slow mail on 15th. Please telegraph urgently whether Sultan can receive His Excellency’s official call between these dates. He would also wish to pay informal visits to Shaikhs of Kuwait and Bahrain on return journey. Ends. Please wire urgently if this is convenient to Sultan• ResidentTelegram From I.F.O. lx.1927 Political, x ^uv/ait. To 1. Brit consul, Bush ire; 2.Political, Bahrain. No. 81. Dated the 1st March 19 34. Shaikh informs me that ^imerican Minister hopes to visit Bin Baud from Bahrain. American Missionaries here confirm quoting as authority their colleagues in Bahrain. Holmes also says he got same news from Saudi Minister in Pgypt. Addressed Bushire, repeated Bahrain. -POLITICAL- \No. 281- S of 19 34 CONFIDENTIAL. -V T-he Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Politiccl Agent, Kuwait* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment/s). * ^ ■ ' ' - ■ — — i ✓ x Reference to previous correspondence: / Bushire telegram No* 238, dated the 27th .February, 1934® British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. !• Political A, telegram No. li March 19 34 1* Political Ag telegram No. 16 March 19 34 3. Political Agent, Bahrain’s telegram No. 171, dated 4th March 1934.Telegram From Political Agent, Bahrain To Political Kesident, Bushire ho. 166 -dated 1st (received 2nd) March 1934 i/t? \ Your telegram of 27th February ho. 238. I understand Linited States Minister has Jess been in touch with Mission and wishes Doctor DAME to arrange and accompany him on visit to RIADH . Dame is now in ^ATAR and I only ho^e that fact will not make Minister ask to go to Qatar, * understand Minister lias his son and Secretary with him. Political *Telegram R.27. - yr0ifl Tolitical Agent, Bahrain 0 - 0 Political Resident, Bush ire. No»167. Bated 3rd (received 4th) March 19 34 0 My telegram of 1st instant, N 0(&gt; 166. Minister has declined &amp;y invitation to stay on ground tliat he has promised to stay with Skinner. Mrs.Skinner did not admit on evening of 2nd Mky (2nd March?) knowing of his stay with them. 2. Both Mission and Skinner apparently knew of his coming here but kept it to themselves and latter has I gather been in touch with Q,usaibis to taxe him across. «friole business seems most odd. - Political -Telegram R. Fr om To Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. Secretary of State for India, London. Government of India, Foreign and Political ,Department, Hew Delhi. -H.ltt’s. Minister, jeaaa. No. 171/ Dated (and received ) 4th March 1934. IMPORTANT. &amp; Your telegram of 4th March. I gather Saudi Representative at Baghdad told American Minister that Bin S&amp;ud i 8 likely to leave for the Hejaa on the 15th liar oil so Minister is trying to arrange visit to hi&amp;dh at once instead of on return tr ip. ^olx tical V i \Telegram - G. T, G From - Political, Kuwait. To - Political, Bahrain. No. 76 , Dated - 14th March 1954. Grateful if you could give me advance information of American Minister’s departure for Kuwait when known.Telegram - G.r.C . From Political, Kuwait. To Political, Muscat. No. f00' Dated The 16 th March 1934. Following for American Minister begins Delighted put you up on March 26th also your son and Moore# onall meet you on arrival. Have fixed things up with local mission. Dickson. Ends.CONFIDENTIAL. ♦ No. 248-S of \ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf presents his cem ents to The Political Agent, Kuwait. Bush ire Printed Letter No. 281-S of 1934, dated the 4th 1. Political Kedidehts telegram No. 278, dat^ed the 6 th March To His Majesty’s Secretary n ci of State for India, London, p etc. 2. Political Residents telegram No. 279, dated the 6 th March 1934, to His Majesty's Secretary of Sti te for India London, etc# iUnericen Minis ter ’ s visit to and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated Reference to previous correspondence : March, 1934# Description of Enclosure, a Name and Date. Subject. Riadh.tlA \i&gt; Ml) ,f. /Vo- • ^Tri'^v GOA^KNMENT OE INDIA, .,'Onl'iuentiai .Department. ^ _ EXPRESS LETTER [ iV.jS.—TMs is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save tele graphic expense and undue use of the icires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. ] i From Political, Bahrain. TO:- ' resident, 1fv Bushire.. To Repeated:- Political, 7 Kuwait* Ko. Dam im urc m . . * telegram February 10th,dB. Mr*Lnabenshue mentioned casually in conversation that he ha&lt; asiced kmia Hiiiani to accompany him oxi this journey as he (Ir. inabenshue) had Known him for some time end he thought tii&amp;t he might be useful in liiyadh. Re could not pay for him and Amin Bihar could not bear the cost hi: self. \ Z* On another previous occasion Amin lihani f s booKs had been mentioned and I asked whether he thought they were altogether accurate in their statements. r.Knabenshue said that he (Amm Rihani) had got into trouble teftfe-he-was-depertedt with the Syrian Government ana he was deported over bitter criticism of tae French policy in the nebanon ana Jahal ] ruze. He (; r.Knabenshue; thought Amin ! iii&amp;ni m the wrong over it ana told turn so* B. Ir.ICnabenshue thinks that mu Rihani will shortly receive ^ /pemission MGIPO*-Sl—61(CSP)DCF—(G-1227) —2I-3-30—4,CO,0 CO. mtKSBSt2 . permission to return to Syria. Political Agent,Bahrain. (aJv- Political Agency, BaHrain, tiie 14th Marcii 1934. t Will you kindly refer to your telegram No:9b dated tiie I4tii Marcii about me Unitea States T Minister. 3. Mr.Knabenshue left Baiarain tins morning (l4tii Marcii) for Muscat, but 1 do not imow by wnat Siiip de will return from Muscat. Directly I Imow I will inform you. 3. Mr.Knabensiiue was unable to arrange ins visit to Riyadh on this occasion but hopes to do so next autumn. Lieut-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson,G.l.E., Political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram G.T.C* From Polltioa] To Political, Kuwait. No* 230. Dated the 22nd received the 23rd March 1934. journey Your telegram 14th March, No.96. American Minister left Muscat March 21st on return -political-IN REPLY REFER TO FILE NO 866.16 JSM/ * American Consular Service American consulate General, Baghdad, Iraq, December 21, 1934. DEPARTMENT OF STATE Dr. C.S.G. Mylrea, Kuwait, Persian Gulf. Dear Dr. Mylrea: The Consulate General is required to submit an annual report on the automotive vehicle census of Kuwait. Since there appears to be no proper official in Kuwait to whom a request for information may be addressed, I am taking the liberty of asking you to fill in the enclosed questionnaire and of returning it to me. While accurate figures are desirable, estimates will serve the purpose if nothing else is available. In either event, I will be most grateful for your assistance. Very truly yours For the Minister Resident and consul General, J dMnj) £ fhAjux- ames^T^MooBe, jr. Enclo sure: questionnaire.The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon’ble the Political .Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R 3 : and has the-honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). for information* POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Bated the 6th ^ruary 1955. Reference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. 1.Letter Ho.Nil, dated 21.12.34 from Mr.J.G.Moose, American Legation,Baghdad, to Dr. C*S.G.Mylrea,O.B.E., American Mis si on,Kuwait. Figures re: automotive vehicles in Kuwait. 2*Letter dated 1st January 1935 from Dr.C.S*G.Mylrea,O.B.IS*, Aiaerican Mission,Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. 3.Demi Official letter No.C-yr dated the 6 th February 1935, from Polltical Agent, Kuwait, to Mr.J.S.Moose,American Lega tion,Baghdad.Baghdad, February 11, 1935. My dear Colonel Dickson, I wish to thank you for your reply to the question naire I sent to Dr. Mylrea in regard to the number of motor vehicles registered in Kuwait. This will enable us to complete the automotive census of our district. Should this office be called upon for any similar in formation, I will tal© the liberty of communicating with you directly on the subject. The Minister is at the moment recovering from a strenuous duck-shooting expedition, but is otherwise cheer ful and in good health. I am beginning to be rather excited over the prospect of leave in the United States this summer. It will be the first time in the States in five years, and I am looking &gt; forward to it with great anticipation. With kindest regards to Mrs. Dickson and yourself, Sincerely yours Colonel H. R. P. Dickson, H.B.M. Political Agent, Kuwait.*1 4 CO FIDE' TIAI. No. 608-S A ^he Political resident, his compliments to t- Persian ^ulf presents The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Kuwai t The Political Agent, '.lusc&gt;. t and has the honour to transmit to Mm a copy of the mentioned documents#, for information only. under Persian half Residency, Bahrain. Dated the 20th March, 1948. Reference to previous correspondence Nil Description of enclosure. Name &amp; Date Subject Government of India E.A.D. &amp; C.R. New Delhi, Letter No. P 26(1)-A T/48 dated the 3rd March, 1948. V.*' Indian Representation in the Persian Gulf. ML. uH’ / &lt;y k vA 'IP &gt; o . V 1♦ V . _ T ^ Becrived ur.der Ciovermnent of India. E , n a f r N «J letter No. F 26(l)-AVVT/48 d.ted thi 3^ M^rch i948 addressed to torrimonwealth Relations Office, London, coried' Commlssior-r in India, “igh Commas?oA e r for j «ia, i.ondon and Political Resident, Bahrain. ism Sir, I ans directed to refer to paragraph 3 th#» Government of India's telegram to the Secretary of State for Indi s , Ko. 4581 d.ted the 13th Jure 1947, Ld to your letter No. txt. 1893/47 dated the 16th September 1947 and f ay _ t 5? st the views of the Government of India regarding their future representation in the Arab States in the Persian Gulf are as follows. 2 . K^ait. As His ^jesty's Government h ve alreadv ird?-! s , the irtention of the Government of India that Indian interests in Kuwait should be supervised by 4 . a u Consulsir post to be established at Basra It has ’ not however been possible as yet to establish Indian ance U for thf preset ^^ propossl must be h( “ ld ^ hv H-if’ j :i ' r ^ In vd?,w of the objections pointed out by His Majesty's Government the Government of India are a reeable that their representative in Bahrain should be ■ ira&lt;3e A £ ftnt “ nd not Consul. They would, however, f an ass o r ~ n &lt; &lt;“ that the Indian Trade Agent will ' be able to supervise all Indian interests, and to exercise in r R a hrA?n SU nh r v, fUnCt o°* S in re 8 P ect °- Indian nationals, h?e B f^ 1 1?nc' 1 *??? n ’ i a J ar and the facial Coast, and th’t hiStfunct^ns will not be confined to matters relating 4. MiisciJ. As previously stated, the Government of India propose to be represented at : uscat by a non-career consuiar oificer, and they are glad to note th;t their the Tre°tv P n° J . c0Rsul4r representative in Muscat under tne ire.ty cn 1939 is recognized. They propose that their representative at Muse t should be designated elth-r Honorary Vice-Consul or Consular Agent, and that he should work; under the supervision of the Indian Trade Agp t rt Bkhrsin. 5. The Government of India do not propose to ask permission to establish a separate consular court at .siuscit. It is, however, their understanding that so long f “?n r Vf r r nalns ?'■ ^ h * CoBBBonwealth, Indian nationals r ; 11J . ‘ I* &gt; 83 hitherto, to have recourse to the British Courts in the Ar.b States. 6 . The Gov mm nt f India will be glad to be informed as soor. as possible th. t they may preceed with the Implementstiom ot the &amp;rr ngements proposed above for representation In Bahrain and Muscat. p°py of this ietter has been sent to the high Commissioner for the United Kingdom in India, to the Indian high Commissioner in Lor don and to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.^ , v v r.r;- v $ Yi (/(b No.654-S The Hon'ble the Political Resi presents his compliments to:- The Political Agent, BAHRAIN , The Political Agent, M USCAT The Political Agent, KUWAIT and has the honour to tra.nsmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN Dated the 24th March, 1948. REFERENCE to previous corre s pondence R esidency Printed Letter N 0 .SO 8 -S dated the 2Cth March, 1948. Description of Enclosure N^g_*nd „Date Subject Telegram No.Misc.46 dated 11th 'H March 1948 from United Kingdom () GULF AGENCY BUILDINGS High Commissioner, New Delhi. )(Telegram G.T.C. From United Kingdom High Commissioner, New.Delhi. To Commonwealth Relations Office, London. No.698 Repeated Political Resident, Bahrain. No.Misc 46 Dated Tlth and received 12th March, 1948. IMPORTANT i Your telegram No.846 March 6 th. Gulf Agency Buildings. 2 . Government of India have intimated informally (and will confirm in writing) that they are agreeable to transfer of Kuwait premises on April 1st. 3. They wish to appoint consuls at Bahrain and Muscat s^nd before considering proposition further would therefore be grateful for views of Political Resident in the matter of providing accommodation for them. Can existing properties be devided in order to house both British and Indian representatives suitably ? If not what would Political Resident suggest ? 4. Pending decision on paragraph 3 above Government of India agree that His Majesty’s Government may undertake upkeep of buildings and equipment frbm April 1st, any necessary financial adjustment to toe made later. ’LB’ - UKCOM9 Te' 1 epram From To No. 710 n**»A G.T.C. Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Arent, Kuwait. 271 Dated the 27th received 28th Mar ch. 19^-8. My Printed Letters 608-S and 65^xS Gulf Agency Buildings. When replying to Government of India ^ 1 / , letter F. 0 6 (l)AWT / 4 8 please make suggestion regarding reply to be riven to paragraph three of United Kingdom High Commissioner’s telegram Miscellaneous 46. HAY BR.- /1 BLITZ 1 AUGUST 13 n 'YOU*RE MEMBERS OF A VERY DIRTY RACE l' KUWAIT OIL FIELDS - HELL HOLE FOR INDIAN EMPLOYEES. to Under-Paid- Ill - fed and Insulted 1 — WHITE BOSSES In the vast, grim, burning of Arabia, the West struck oil, and today Dahran in Saudi Arabia, and Kuwait, a post of great strategic importance in the Persian Gulf, are declared to be the richest oil fields in the world. According to a statement by Mr. A.W.Southfield, Assistant Managing Director of the Kuwait Oil Co.Ltd., the hitherto- marvelled giant Texas Oil fields ’are but a pigmy in comparison to the Burgan Oil fields of Kuwait*. The oil fields in Kuwait are controlled by the British and Americans, who have a fifty-fifty share and is practically a new concern having started actual operations only in earlu 1945 . However, all this does not interest us - but we are certainly interested in knowing what our Government intends doing for the welfare and well-being of the thousands of our countrymen, the f ) flower of our intelligentia who are recruited in hundreds % 4 bvery ’day Xh”T^oraSy'’dH“ 1 tO't-/ Salaries and tempting promises. First class technicians, stenographers and Clerks are k recruited on one-fourth the salaries offered to the same category of White Man, and perhaps no description of the colour prejudices and colour bar that exists can be offered in adequate terms. Everyone has heard of South Africa. Well, Kuwait is easily worse and threatens to be worse still. We have no represen tative of our Government there, and all disputes between the management and the employees ]aave to be settled by His Britannic Majesty’s Political A ent, and that worthy is an autocratic imperialist who cares a jot for the under-dog and is nothing but the Company’s man. Let me enuraerate a few instances of the Management’s attitude towards Indians as a whole and show in what hellish conditions our men are carrying on there. As if to show to the world that the most generous treatment is being meeted out to Indians, a Clerk is recruited in Bombay on Rs/210/- a month, rising to Rs.2A0/- in 3 years time, a Steno grapher on Rs. 245/- a month rising to Rs*275/- again 0 in 3 years time and a first class technician on Rs.190/- a month flat, for two years. Technicians are not graded, with the result a Diesel Mechanic or an electrician draws the same salary as a Mason Carpenter ±03CKX±fe3a:isaxiE:csxix or even a Dhobyi The same class of Englishmen, who have lesser abilities thaim the Indian Clerk is paid £45 a month to start with and can go upto £90 in three years. Both Indians and Englishmen, with the exception of the Indian technicians get free food and free quarters. The Indian technicians The type of food and quarters given to the Indians compared with those fiven to the European, has to be seen to be believed. The I n dian food was so terrible that, early in April 1943, the Indian Clerks went on a complete strike. The Management of the Mess was then handed over to them, and now the situation has partially improved though no butter, bacon, ham, or fruit such as the white man enjoys, are h issued to them. .get 50 percent allowance in lieu of food \Whenever members of the Indian Clerical Staff, which is known as the ’Junior Staff’ as against the white staff which is knox-m as the ’Senior- Staff’ ask for some butter, better rice or tinned fruits, they get this remarkable answer ’the Ministry of Food, London, has directed that the ’Junior Staff’ are not allowed butter, etc I We rediculed this statement and pointed out to the Management that this was impossible in view of the fact that rice etc. was not a product from London. Butter came from Australia and New Zealand, and rice from India, and where on earth the Ministry of Food, London, stepped in, no one could say. The Indian is generally considered an inferior being. A Senior Staff man even if he be ignorant and utterly useless(as many of them are) orders the Indian Clerk around, makes him stand to attention while speaking, and in a few 6 ases, orders the ClerFs under him to address him as tSIR”. Some of us who felt miserable and could not put up with the daily insults have lefit the company for good. Hundreds of others would have followed suit were it not for the fact that they have to support families, wives and children. In almost all the cases the men employed, threw up jobs in India enamoured of the high salary offered, and plumled for the Oil fields of Kuwait, prepared to undergo any climatic hardships. In Kuwait, during summer, the temperature is 130 dig.F* in the shadeand in winter belox-j- 50 dig.F. not to mention the violent and strong sandstorms that blow frequently. e If he protests against the treatment he received, he is summarily sacked without even an enquiry. Afraid of losing his job and having to rot, looking for one in India again, he sticks on in the most terrible and humiliating conditions. Into the Senior Staff mess or Club no Junior Staff man is admitted and they will never alloxj you to go anywhere near their quarters. ’You are a terribly dirty race’ so one snob told me, for which I licked him. I knew the result would be my being sackedj but he did not seem to have the guts for it. Hox/ever as matters begin to take a grave turn later, I decided to resign and return to my homeland so as to let our Government knoxj what is really happening thei there. In the company’s busses, there is a notice, which runs, ’First five rox&lt;rs for Senior S + aff; the Junior S x aff to sit behind. That was in the early stages when they had transport difficulties. Now, however, no Senior Staff man travels with the Junior Staff, as the Company has plenty of transport at its dispos ^ disposal. The technicians are huddled like cattle in cattle-wagons and moved from place to place. \ A detailed memorandum, signed by all the Junior S aff, is noX '7 with the Central Government in New Delhi and we are waiting for a reply. When will this exploitation end and when xd.ll an Indian be treated as an equal to another race^ Why does our Government allow such emigration, especially when a glaring disparity is made in regard to x./ages and treatment betx^een^a European and Indian? Will our Government ever avrakeV Will they ever stop t 1 is humiliation; N r ill they send immediately a competent representative(for Heaven’s sake, a strong and upright man and not a white man’s stooge) to the Gulf to enquire into the conditions of thousands of our countrymen? BOMBAY. AUGUST 13CONsTDSMTIAL. /VC No.R/57(^l). The Political Agency, Kuwait• Dated the 26th August, 1948. To. The Secretary to His Excellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain . Subject:- Activities of Hr. Harid Mian. M^O RANDOM: Reference paragraph No.240 in the Fortnightly Intelligence Summary No.14 of 1948 of thCs Agency. 2# Enclosed herewith are two extracts dealing with Indian Representation from an article on conditions in Kuwait published by the Indian Paper ’Blitz 1 . 3. The article is written in a hysterical tone and although unsigned is presumably inspired by, if not from the pen, of Harid Mian# The Kuwait Oil Company itself subscribes \ to this paper for Indian welfare, but this will presumably now cease. Political Agent, Kuwait. MBCOPY TOP SECRET Commonwealth Relations Office Downing Street. February 25th, 1949. Pol.Ext.6393/49 Dear Rogers, Will you please refer to the correspondence ending with Gibson's letter No.17356/48 of November 10th, 1948, to the High Commissioner for India about Indian representation in the Persian Gulf, a copy of which came to you. We have now received the enclosed reply from the High Commissioner and we should be glad to know whether we can confirm that the arrangements suggested by him are acceptable and, in particular that the Trade /gent at Bahrain and the Consul at Basra may correspond direct with the appropriate departments of the Bahrain and Kuwait Governments on matters of a routine nature. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) R.W.D.Fowler T.E.Rogers Esq., M.B.E., Eastern Department, Foreign Office.V ^ i COPY TOP SECRET (Residency classification) P0L.FXT.630S/49 OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INEI/i EXTERNAL DEPARTMENT INDIA HOUSE,ALBWYCH, LONDON, W»C•£• i^XT .68*4*10. February 8th, 1949, To: The Under-Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street, London, S.W.l. Subject:- Indian Re present ion in the Persian Gulf . Sir, I am directed by the High Commissioner to invite reference to correspondence resting with your letter POL.EXT *17356/48 dated November 10 th, 1948, on the subject of Indian representation in the Persian Gulf area. 1. Bahrain and Kuwait 1. The Government of India, having given their most careful consideration to the points raised in the letter under reference, maintain that there would have been no departure from precedence if India’s representatives were given the right to deal directly with the respective Shaikhs in continuation of the practice when the Political Agents, appointed and controlled by the Government of India, exercised this privilege. The Government of India, However, do not wish to press this point in view of His Majesty’s Governments’s assurance that the Indian Trade Agent in Bahrain and the Indian Consul in Basra (in respect of Kuwait), would be permitted to perform ell normal consular functions and to work independently of Ris Majesty’s Political Agent. While therefore, the Government of India agree to the stipulation that their officers will not have direct access to the Rulers of Bahrain and Kuwait, they trust that there will be no objection to their corresponding direct with the appropriate departments of the Bahrain and Kuwait Governments on matters of a routine nature. bfc kS &lt; i 2. The Government of India would therefore, be grateful if His Majesty’s Government would take the necessary steps to approach the Ruler of Bahrain to obtain his agreement to the establishment of an Indian Trade Agency there. His Majesty’s Government will, no doubt, explain to the Ruler the scope of the Indian Trade Agent’s duties viz., that he will exercise consular functions in respect of Indian nationals and be charged with maintaining and strengthening the friendly economic and commercial connexions that have long existed between India and Bahrain. As has already been agreed to by His Majesty’s Government, the Indian Trade Agent at Bahrain will supervise Indian interests/- 2 - interests in Qatar and the Trucial Shaikhdoas, and His Majesty*s Government will, no doubt, issue the necessary instructions in this connexion to their political Resident in the Persian Gulf * 3* The Government of India would further be grateful if His Majesty’s Government would similarly approach r ^ ^ the Shaikh of Kuwait to permit the Indian Consul in Basra, m- ' Y‘ ru . *’ ’when appointed, to exercise, in respect of/the Indian Trade 4 , -^' Agent in Bahrain. j - ( /w T II. Muscat 1. with regard to Muscat, His Majesty’s Government is requested to seek the agreement of the Sultan of Muscat under the Treaty of 1939 to the opening of an Indian Consulate there. It is the intention of the Government of India to appoint, in the first instance, a non-career Vice-Consul/Consul at Muscat. III. I am to say that the Government of Indie will be grateful for the earliest possible action on the pert of His Majesty’s Government in regard to the arrangements arising from the matters set out above. Yours faithfully, (Sd) P.N. Haksar Secretary, External Department.TOP SECRET Tiie Political Agency, Kuwait. 0/56(13/5) 27th Parch, 1949. Dear Residency offer at this stage. We presume, however, that paragraph three should read ' approach the Shei&amp;h of Kuwait to permit the ladian Cossul in Basra, when appointed, to exercise consular functions in respect of Indian nationals in Kuwait'. 3. Please confirm that this is correct. v The Persian Culf Residency, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL Kim'dii tteceirt j*y r e /?$ D fl Telegram El.T.P From Prodrome, Bahrain To Political, Kuwait No.103 Dated and received the 13th April, 1949. Priority. TOP SECRET. i.r Your letter 0/56(13/5) of March 27th. Passage reached us corrupt but should probably read ' to permit Indian Consul in Basra when appointed to exercise in respect of Kuwait same functions as are proposed for Indian Trade Agent Bahrain x 'hese functions are defined in second sentence of paragraph 2 of High Commissioner’s letter If you see no objection please approach Shaikh accordingly and report result.loS' Telegram From To No. Enclair Prodrome, Bahrain Political, Kuwait 110 Dated the 20th received the 21st April, 1949. My telegram No. 103. Please expedite reply. HAY. asr.From Kuwait to Bahrain G.N* JacKson, Esq., No, 0/99(13/5) JAVTNG-. Jated 25th ^pril, 1949, Your telegram No. 103* '' 2. I have spoKen to SheiAh who has no objection to arrangements proposed. Indian Consul at Basra may deal direct with Departments of Kuwait Government on matters of a routine nature.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000166_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/315</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000166</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/315</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 13/5 'Foreign Consular representation in Kuwait (and Persian Gulf)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-04-12T22:44:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (68 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 68; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains papers of the Political Agency, Kuwait, relating to foreign consular representation in the Persian Gulf.Papers dated November 1933 to February 1935 include:correspondence of the Political Agent, Kuwait, with the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and the Political Agent, Bahrain, and copies of correspondence sent by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, relating to the visit of the United States Minister at Baghdad to Bahrain, Kuwait and Muscat, and his intended visit to Riyadhcorrespondence between the Political Agent, Kuwait, and the United States Consulate General, Baghdad (James S Moose), and Dr C S G Mylrea, of the American Mission, Kuwait, concerning the annual report on the automotive vehicle census of Kuwait, to be submitted by the American Consulate GeneralPapers dated March 1948 to April 1949 consist of correspondence relating to Indian consular representation in the Persian Gulf. The file does not include papers for the period March 1935 to February 1948.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Consuls</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>American Consulate General</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ambassador to Iraq</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>District Magistrate, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Riyadh</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Consular services</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000166#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>