<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000eb_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T02:45:33.191Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/ (Vi To No • l n 26. Political Agency# Bahrain. Dater] the 15th May 1926. The Pension Officer 9 Baghdad. Subject:- Pension to Abdur Rehnan . Menorandun . Tn continuation of ny Menorandun No.749/246 dated the 26th March 1926# I forward herewith one copy ®f ' Yoklana I7 or7!^ ,, duly filled in by Pensioner Abdur Rehnan together with his letter in arable A addressed to you. Major, C.I.E.# Political Agent# Bahrain.OFFICE OF THE CIVIL TREASURY, BAGHDAD. oXUI ♦♦ ♦♦ » \A-o ♦♦ To J' Mr. Abdul Rahman bin Hossan, —— C/o Britla !i Ylaa Council # Bahrein* Memorandum* I forward herewith a cheque for Re* 378/~ being the arrears of your pension from 1st March 1925 to the end of May 1926 less bank's commission charges* Please acknowledge receipt* 3DUUDI J*ti*OUFI for TREASURY OFFICER /S Copy to:- The British Vice Council^ Bahrein reference pensions Officer memo*Mo*2211 dated 12th June 1926* Copy to Pensions Officer, Baghdad for information reference his aborequoted memo*/0JL6 No. /lfl/7 of 1920. The Political Ap:©ncy&gt; Bahrein. Data,! the 9th November 1926, To The Pensione Officer# Bap'hrlacl« Subject:- P ension to Abdul Rehman bin HasBan . ?,!eno rand um . With reference to your metiorandun No. 1059 dated the 10th March 1926# I forward herewith one copy of w Yoklama Porn' duly filled in by the pensioner. political Ar,® t, &gt;a' re in.OFFICE OF THE CIVIL TREASURY, BAGHDAD. Telephone No. “Serai 29.” svfo.- y 10/5 T)a/e 16 th D^eember, 1926 To • Jl Mr* Abdul Rahman bln Haas&amp;n, C/o Bri tiah Vice Couno11, Bahrein* Memorandum* I forwrrd herewith a cheque for Re* 100/5 beilng your pension for the period from let June 1926 to the end of September, 1926 leas bank*a commisaion charges* Please acknowledge receipt* Please note that no receipt ( stamped ) has been received from you for payment of your pension made by this Treasury* Please Bend same for thie and all previous payments in order to enable me to send your pension regularly in future# otherwise your pension will be stopped. SB. J.H.OUFI for TREASURY OFFICER Copy for information to:- ls British Vice Council, Bahrein. The Pensions Baghdad. ^ ZZZ*. I » f k &amp; - 'l for TREASURY OTFICBR \ k tOp^CX^CpLWo. IfSy / 16 / 7 Of 1927. The Political Agency# Bahrein, i^atecl the St^^Deoeuber 1927, To The Pension Officer, Baghdad. Subject: Pension to Abdur Re^iDan/bjn Haasan . Meniorandup . in continuation of my nenorandun Wo.13/16/7 dated the 0 th January 1927, j forward herewith two copies of Yoiclama forns duly filled m by Pensioner Abdur Rehrnan together with his latter in arable addressed to you.ManorAndum Copy oi a No.l3/l6/7» dated the January 19&amp;7, iron t.he x J olj tical A^ant# Bahrein# to the Treasury Officer » Baghdad, Subject:- Pension to Abdur Rehnan bjn Jhasoan , Reler-enco to correspondence ending wi thy our nonorandun i'io.Si.OBj dated tlie 15th Decinber 19&lt;i0 addreosed to Abdur Reiman bin Hassan, I forward herewith a closed cover received from Pensior Abdur Rehnan to your address. ier no. .2/16/7 of 19£8. The Political Agency# Bahrein. Rated the 16th February lOi#, Copy forwarded to the Pension. Officer, Pensions Depart- nent, Baghdad with reference to his endorsement do.sip, dated £l/£3rd January iosq, with the remark that the required y Oil’ll ana torus will be furnished duly completed by the pensioner when received from his Department. Political Agent# Bahrain.»o. /*-/ 16/7 of 1928 The Politioal Agency Bahrein, 25th March 1928. The Treaeury Officer, Civil Treasury, Memorandum* Reference your Memo.Ko. 694 dated tne 11th ieoruary 1928 to the address of Mr.Abdul Rahman bin Hassan, copy forwarded to me for information. 1 forward herewith a cover addressed to you by the Pensioner. Political -r.gent .BahreinNo of 1928 The Political Agency, Bahrain. To Tlie Treasury Officer, Civil Treasury, Baghdad. Moraorandura. A cover containing a 'yoklana” forr» and receipt from Pensioner Abdul Rahman bin Hassan is forwarded here with. Please acknowledge receipt. Political Agent, Bahrein'v'i TO, Mr. Abdul Ha.iman bin Hasson Bahrain ft* ' c ' i;u ' *&gt; Reierence ray memo Ho # 694 dated 11/2/2S. Please send stomped receipt for the cheque of Re* 415/1^ forwarded under my above quoted memo in order to unable me to remit your pension regulary in future other-ice payment will be descontinued. y. -M. &lt;3?# A For Treasury Officer Copy ^r informc tion to. Political Agent Bahrein. Treasury OfficerNo . r A 6/7 Of 1929. Tho Politicai Agoncy, Bahrain. DatocI the January 1929. To The Treasury Officer, Civil Treasury, Baghdad. \ , ^ x^enorandura . Reference your memorandum No.29*7, dated the 8th December 1928 to the address of Hr. Abdur Rahman bin Hasean, copy forwarded to me for information. I forward herewith a cover addressed to you by the Pensioner. ’ A, ci Political A^ont, BahreinIOFFICE OF THE CIVIL TREASURY, BAGHDAD. Telephone No:— “SERAI 29.” •i/$7 37/19 N° Date To \ r iV 3^r Abdul Hahm'm t^ln Ha»san o/o Britia}. v^lo# Council Bahrein* « Y^ ® Jykl\ fj — .juJI J1 / ora ; 1 I forward herewith first of .Exchange for R*. 162/1 pees one mndred sixty two anna* thirteen only) on the Eastern Rank. Ltd. Bahrein being your pension for the period, fr0m lst tspt ‘ 190 ' r * tolE,t April 1929. less Bank's Cor*: issiofc charges rnd strtnips* I'lonse 3snd your stnopei receipt for the above amount to this • rer. ury at your earliest convenience. Asstts Treasury Officer Copy for information to, The British Vies Council Bahrein for I eoeury Officer* * i /( 'I u&gt;t A ^&gt;'&lt;^'f^^&lt;^j M)'m /yj* &lt;^jv &amp;&amp;'^»4y*'j&amp;'&gt; ^ ^&gt;i£AUu;j! ^ ^ J’W^V ^ ii&gt;»^ ^&gt;ja, ^ o£?&lt;££&gt; Letter dated 6th Muharram 1347- i.e. 13-6-1929 from f Abdur Rahman bin Hasan ,Penioner,Hasa to Captain C.G.Prior,H.B.M T s Political Agent,Bah rain. After Compliments, p I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter dated the 24th Dhul HAjjah 1347-i.e.5.6.29 together with the letter and /! cheque sent with it^from the Treasury Office^ about my penion. I am very thankful to you for the trouble you have taken in getting the English letter translated to Arabic. 1 have endorsed the cheque and sent it to my agent Abdul f Aziz al Qusaibi to receive the amount on my behalf. Enclosed please find a reply to the T.O. which I request you to kindly forward to him.No. of 1929. ^3 The Political A;ency # ahrein. Dated the m Jane 1939• To The Treasury Officer, Civil Treasury, Baghdad# Memorandum . Reference your Memorandum No.2167/37/19, dated the 15th May 1929 to the address of Mr. Abdur Rahman bin Hassan, copy forwarded to me for information. I forward, herewith, a cover addressed to you by the Pensioner. — y c , Captain 4p' Political A^ent, Bahrein*No. 177*1 of 1929. The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the December 1929 The Treasury Officer, Civil Treasury, Baghdad* Memorandum. I forward, herewith, a pension form filled by the Pensioner AbduT Rehman bin Hasan, duly countersigned by me together with a letter addressed to you by the Pensioner. /o. C ' ^ ST Ol Political A^ent, Bahrain*No. of 1930. Tho Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the ; j { April 1930. 'fhe Treasury Officer, Civil Treasury, Bagdad. Reference correspondence ending; with rny mesnorandiiiii Ho.1779 dated the ^7th December 1939. I forward, herewith, a cover addressed to you by the Pensioner Abdur Rahman bin Hasan. a 0 y k/i. Political Agent, Bahrain,v--*r; 11/ f'rrf y Ho. W of 1930. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 23th. May 1930. The Treasury Officer, Civil Treasury, Baghdad* Memorandum . Reference my Memorandum No.611 dated the 8th April 1930. Pensioner Abdul Rahman bin Hasan informs me that he has not received his pension for the last six months and requests that it may please be expedited. Of Political Agent, Bahrain,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000eb_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1500</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000eb</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1500</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Miscellaneous 16/7 Pension to Abdur Rehman – Civil’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1930</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-12T18:48:43</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (51 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 54; these numbers are written in pencil, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 4-53; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence relating to pension payments made by the Pensions Department of the Iraq Government, to Abdul Rahman bin Hassan, a resident of Hassa [Al-Aḥsā’]. The file’s principal correspondents are: the Political Agent at Bahrain (Major Cyril Charles Johnson Barrett); representatives of the Pension Department and Treasury Office of the Iraqi Government in Baghdad; Abdul Rahman bin Hassan.The correspondence includes copies of a ‘Yoklama’ (pension) form, completed by Abdul Rahman and sent to the Treasury Officer in Baghdad at roughly six-monthly intervals, and covering letters (originally sent with cheques) by the Treasury Officer in Baghdad to Abdul Rahman. Correspondence between the two parties was relayed from the Iraqi Government in Baghdad to the Political Agency in Bahrain, then from the Bahrain merchant Abdul Aziz Al-Gosaibi to Abdul Rahman in Hassa.Much of the correspondence, including all letters sent by Abdul Rahman, is in Arabic.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Abdul Rahman bin Hassan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Pensions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Civil Servants</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000eb#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>