<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000270_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T06:31:55.945Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">- - - ' • —No. ??&lt;?■- 8/7. Persian Gulf Residency, .Bahrain 7^ April, 1947. From The Secretary to the Hon’ble the^ ^ Political Resident in the Persian Gulx, Bahrain To The political Agent, ^ ^ ^ v v'- V 7 Bahrain Kharita from H.E. Field Marshall the Right Hon’ble Viscount Vifavell. Sir, I am directed to forward, herewith, a copy of letter No.D.1853-Pt/47 dated the 25th March 1947, received irom the Government of India in the External Affairs Depar tment, with its enclosures (1) a Kharita in English, announcing tne termination of His Excellency«s Viceroyalty, ana (2) a copy of the Kharita for record in your office. 2. I am to ask you to make a translation in Arabic of the Kharita, and to deliver it along with the Kharita on the first suitable opportunity to His Highness. 3 A cooy of your translation should be sent to this office for record, along with His Highness’ reply to the Kharita with an English translation in duplicate. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Confidential- BAHRAIN BGnElPT. D Ae K«...No. D.1853-Pt/47 From To The Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department The Hon’ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Dated New Delhi 3, the 25th March 1947. Sir, I am directed to forward herewith a Kharita from His Excellency Field Marshal the Right.Hon’ble Viscount Wave11 to His Highness the Sultan of Musfat and Oman His Highness the Shaikh bf Bahrain His Highness the Shaikh of Kuwait announcing the termination of His Excellency’s Viceroyalty, and to request that you will sand ±h it to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman / the Shaikh of Bahrain the Shaikh of Kuwait t ■ with a suitable translation in Arabic. 2. Should any reply be seht by Their Highnesses to the Kharitas, I am to request that you will forward it to the Government of India with an English translation. S. A copy of each Kharita is enclossed for record in your office. I have the honour to be, ' Sir, Your most obedient servant, • • (Sd.) R.E.R. BIRD Under Secretary to the Govt.ofIndiaTo His Highness Shaikh Sir Salman bin Hamad A1 Khalifah, K.C.1£ Ruler of Bahrain. My esteemed friend, On the termination of my Viceroyalty I write to bid Your Highness a cordial farewell. Admiral Viscount Mountbatten of Burma will succeed me as Viceroy and Governor General of India. 2. It has been a matter of much gratification to me that during the times of danger and stress through wliich, with the help of God, we have safely passed, the ties of friendship between the British Government and Bahrain have not only been maintained but strengthened. 3. I recall with gratitude the loyal and unfailing co-operatior which Your Highness has afforded to the British Government at all times and it is my sincere hope that the future will briag f increased prosperity and happiness to Your Highness and the people of Bahrain. Although the affairs of Bahrain will no longer concern me officially I shall continue to take a personal interest in all that concerns the welfare of Your Highness and the Islands of Bahrain. I remain, v/ith much consideration, Your Highness 1 sincere friend, (Sd.) Wave11 F.M. Viceroy and Governor General of India Delhi 3, 20 th Me^ich 1947.No.94. Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated 5th May, 1947. From: The Political Agent, Bahrain. To : The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Kharita from H.E. Field Marshall the Right Hon’ble Viscount Wavell. Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No.778-8/7 dated the 7th April, 1947 and to state that the Kharita has been delivered personally by me to His Highness the Ruler, together with its translation in Arabic. 2. I forward herewith the Shaikh’s reply along with two copies thereof and a copy of the translation of the Kharita. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Agent, Bahrain.# -■*** n iW&amp;M iTo-Wl* 4i£^e '* &gt; «* !, w sc $ ■tiiftfci, i'»i ■ jjlu ^',‘ IC.-. I'iniain ■ «&gt;g-5«31 j ■' il «*«aH illu^alt 4 Ai,» 2g»~j£j ^ ^ LmI ^ ii-J i J j^wiAijg !«*f j ^ Ic^bw,,.,. .»^JI l^. na. M &gt;^J —f*JJ ^ •;; cJJUvS aJJ^J V U I %il P Lm L*i&lt;W C..,n%«' &gt; :' : -1 ^W51--^-3 ^ ^Lwjl J iU.'sC-H U *^ From To THE'PALACE BAHRAIN. Bahrain, May 1, 1947. Sulman bin Hamad AlKhalifah, Bahrain. His Excellency Field-Marshal Right Honburable Viscount Wavell of Cyrenaica and / .Vinchester, G.C.B., G.M.3.I., G.M.I.S., G.M.G., M.C, After compliments: We h.ve the honour to acknow ledge your letter dated 20th March, 1947,, written from New Delhi, which we have just now received. We greatly appreciate your references to the friendship which has existed between us and our ancestors and the Government of Great Britain and we look forward to the continuation of this ancient friend ship in the future. we are grateful to know that you will continue to take an interest in all that concerns us in Bahrain. We thank you for your kindness and consideration tow rds us during the years of your viceroyalty and we offer you our most sincere good wishes for the future. May God preserve you. Salaams. IftXaafcA A* Sulman bin Hamad AlKhalifah© now. The Shaikh's reply to the Kharita has been received May forward it to the Secretary to the P.R., as requested by him, please? DFA. * ' p. f) 's y&amp;lsy*^*^**^* s « 1 &gt;\ VI \ bk^ ^mum</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000270_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1889</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000270</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1889</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File C/3 Papers regarding reception of H. E. the Viceroy of India and Kharitas — From the Viceroy to the Shaikhs'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-03-24T18:46:57</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (15 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are loosely arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file; the correspondence related to the reception can be found between folios 2-8, and the papers related to the Viceroy's Kharita can be found between folios 9-14. A set of files notes can be found at the back between folios 15-16.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 17; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-9; these numbers are written in blue crayon, and are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence — in Arabic and English — between Shaikh ‘Abdullah bin ‘Isa al Khalifah [‘Abdullāh bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah] and Percy Gordon Loch, the Political Agent, Bahrain. The correspondence is concerned with inviting the Political Agent to a reception in honour of the Viceroy of India; the dates of this correspondence range from May to November 1934.The file also contains an official document referred to as a Kharita (see folio 11) dated 20 March 1947 from Archibald Percival Wavell, announcing the end of his term as Viceroy of India, along with an Arabic translation of the Kharita. The translation (see folio 12) was prepared in order that it may be transmitted to the Ruler of Bahrain, Sulman bin Hamad Al Khalifah [Shaikh Salmān bin Ḥamad Āl Khalīfah], and his reply — in both Arabic and English — dated 1 May 1947 can be found on folio 14.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh 'Abdullāh bin 'Īsá Āl Khalīfah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000270#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>