<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000292_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T06:44:11.066Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">2 ^ traitslation. Agenda for the L°&gt;th meeting of ran amah jyaladeyah which will be held on rhursday the 7th shawal 1354 ^2-1-1936;. l;. Budget of income and i^penditure of ranamah Baladeyah for the months of Kajab and sha*ban 1354. 1. ihe income of Kajab is Rs.5106-6-6. xhe income of Kajab lafet year**.5905-15-3. b. ihe expenditure of Kajab is Rs*3532-7-0. rhe expenditure of Kajab last year is. 2349-0-3. 2 . income ol Bha'ban is. # ,P 5 # 43 rhe income of bha‘ban last ydar is “.5229-10-9.* b * e; ^ en ^J ure of t&gt;hfe»ban is fo.3692-7-6. ihe expenditure of sha'ban last year.2529-8-6. 2,). old Medicines and i/rugs. It is known that most medicines become useless after a long time and would be harmful too. i n Bahrain there is no system whereby a period should be fixed for medicines, un many occasions people bought old medicines ft-om the market some of whom were harmed by such medicines, what steps would the Majlis recommend for putting a check on this ^ 3). Artesian well of the warden. * since late the Saladeyah have been deepening their - artesian well in the garden and the water consequently has become adequate now which was not anticipated, rhe total feet dug are 300. now the garden enjoys sufficient water. rhere ' were pipes by which water used to be drawn from the well of ' Barahat Khawajah to the garden but as water from this well i s ' no longer required, it is necessary that water from our well should be extended to the small g al * ens situated in ^ Qf ' the /imerican Hospital. -i, 0 + ,• + , ' ha “ 13 the opmion of the Majlis about removing the pipes from their present nl- Piesent place and fixine them on the new site. 3 ' ) ‘ Baladeyah worries. J it has been noticed bv -i &lt; &amp;1Cecl the ^alaaeyah that they snend a considerable amount ^ ^ spend ure amount in paying for the co^t n-c . ^ 00st of repairs donp th,,r 0U - - « - th . ; I ^ • * B ^.Si opinion of the Majlis about buying one or two new lorries and thus saving the cost of repairing these old and unserviceable ones, it is a fact that the aaladeyah are in a great need for lorries and as the present lorries have been in use since a long time, they are no more fit for aaladeyah work. 5). rhe jjeath of the aear. it is regretted to announce the death of the bear which was so kindly presented to the aaladeyah warden by Major Prior, it fell sick and expired on 25th Kamadhan. 6;. Heading reports of the inspecting committee.My dear Frior, i am desired to inforn you th t the bear which yoj presented to the mlacleyoh uordon here some foir years a^o has died recently* \ copy o' the relevant extract of the minutes of the mlndeyah on the subject ' re attrehed herewith* xours sincerely, %'Or c.w.prior, i.\. f uepu ty aeeretary to the Government o India in the foreign and Political apartment, new nelhi.4 '4 !S Translation of Agenda for the ISth meeting ol Manamah Baladeyah to be held on Thursday the 21st Shawal loo4 i.e,16/1/1 ( 1936)• 1;. Filling up a Poolt Reference the minutes of the meeting which was on 22na Jamad Awwal 1354 regarding the contract made with the contractor in connection with filling up the pool. The period fixed with him has expired ana the po&lt;U has not been filled up completely. A r hat is the opinion of the Majlis ? 2) . Drilling Machine. At present the machine is^ free as the drilling has been completed. Apparently it is shprt oi some necessary tools in case the Baladeyah wish to use the machine again. ?;ould the Majlis approve ordering these requirements or else the machine may be kept m store . 3) . Plants for the Baladeyah Garden. The Baladeyah garden is in a great need. ior various kinds of plants. Should the Baladeyah import the same, from outside so that the garden would be lull Ox charming and useful scenes ? 4) Li ^ads Surrounded with walls * | Most people do not care to surround their lanes with walls O 1 * repair the walls which are in a ruined, state which are used for dumping all sorts oi wastes and garbage The Baladeyah are taking great pains in this respect. /Jhat is the opinion of the Majlis ? 5) . Crude Oil. The Baladeyah are in need for crude oil for use on the v/ater pools etc. r : 6) . Sale of Meat During ^amadhan. The sheep slaughtered by the Baladeyah during the month of ^amadhan are 77 in number. \ loss of iis.211/b/~ has been sustained. j►rRAiiSLATiUJu. Minutes of the 17th meeting of man amah ualadeyah held on ihursday the 17th Dha*ban 1354, ihe Manamah ualadeyah meeting was held under the * presidency of the member naji muhammad bin L^barak al i^adhil, % acting president and in the presence of the members, ihe following members were absent due to indisposition of health l.uaji rJialil bin xbrahim al mua ^/yad and S.naji abbas abul f^asim bhirazi. rhe undermentioned two members were also absent as they were busy:- Haj i ±brahim bin r^aha r imad ahmadi and uaj i rajhanmad al ijarazi. previous meeting discussion took place over the following: 1). Departure of the president. left for bar Dhaharan for the purpose of hunting, ne will be away for a few days and sends his compliments to the members of his Majlis, ne has appointed naji Muhammad bin Mubarak al padhil to represent him in this meeting. 3. mring these six months, though there was* an increase in the expenditure and a decrease in the income, the naladeyah have i earhed a sum of H.B290-7-e. a sum of Rs.2260/- approximately was spent in excess for which there is no previous account, rhe after reading an I confirming the minutes of the rhe Secretary stated that the president shaikh jmhammad rhe Majlis prayed that he may be in good health. 2). Budget of expenditure and income of Manamah rsaladeyah for six months. 1. income Rs.28418- 1 - 6 . bast iear... .Rs. 29076-15- 0 . 2. expenditure.. .Rs.20127-10- 1. Last Year F . 18837- 1 - 8 . 4. a sum of Rs. 23969/15/9 is available in the Bank and in the !- the treasury upto the end of uamad ihani 1354. Last year there was a sum of Rs. 11318/11/7 in the Bank and in the treasury upto the end of jamad rhani 1353. decrease in the income is fc.1820/-. '4 xhe Majlis approved of these./2- C 1 ^ 1 ' h l f 3^ Combatting Malaria. ihe secretary submitted the question of combatting malaria by taking the necessary steps in filling the water pools and covering the open water cesspools and also in washing the v/ater pits and the water pots in which water is kept for considerable periods in the houses as uncleanliness in the houses is a strong cause for the spread of diseases. ihe Majlis discussed this matter minutely and decided as followss- a. The Baladeyah should ask the Government to include an item regarding malaria in the programme of the schools. b. ihe Baladeyah should order from agjrpt or other countries enlarged photos to be promulgated amongst the public so that they may take the necessary steps to combat malaria. c. rhe Baladeyah should issue an ‘Alan urging the public to have their houses clean. Li d. rhe Baladeyah should write special letters to those who keep cows in their houses urging them to cleans their houses; every day. 4;. Lights of the streets during the month of Kamadhan. The Secretary suggested to the Majlis of keeping the lights of the streets till dawn during the month of Kamadhan. The Majlis decided that the lights may be kept on till after the morning prayer. 3). sale of meat by the Baladeyah during the month of Kamadhan. ihe secreteny submitted the question of the sale of m at during the month of Kamdhan as usual. x h e Majlis approved this. b). Suggestion of the membersi- Haji All bin Muhammad nanoo has put up the following suggestions*- a. The Baladeyah may ask the government to have a police^n to stand at every entrance of a street and also at every junction* of four roads in the town so that no collision by cars etc, may ! happen. b - ihe Ualade y ah fill up the water stream which-extends | from the fort to the Baladeyah garden as it spoils the beauty of ' the road. 6 ion of the structure which stands in the midst of liielgrave Koad opposite the gate of Baladeyah garden. rhe l.'ajlis approved all these suggestions and decided that ^ the naladeyah should write to the idovemment asking them to let a policeman stand at each of the following places 1 . rpace of the Qusaibi situated in the southern part. 2. At the bower court. 3. At the compound which is near the artesian well of mgbil. 4 At the customs house. 5. at nota of Ali Abul. naji Salman bin Ahmad Karnal suggests as follows w ^ a. The Baladeyah should consider the question of the bakers who raised the price of bread to double its price these days. The Majlis, after discussing this ratter at length, decided that the Baladeyah should keep an eye on the bakers and also watch the price of the flour. shaikh ishaq bin Abdur Rahman al Khan -Sir-seBts as follows- a. bvery boat which carries soirit and kerosene oil and every inflarnable material should anchor not less than one mile away from the coast. f b. carriers should be made for the electric wires in the town so as to prevent any harm being done by their falling down on the ground. After discussing these suggestions, the Majlis decided that firstly the boats carrying inflamable materials should anchor near Zurruwan buoy and the « 0 vemment may be informed accordingly, and secondly, carriers should be made for the electric wires but this suggestion should be communicated' to the Government first. ii 9 * 2 bKhaliLbin. ibrahii^^ i -^. ja:a d _ su gp:e sts as f 0 i low jij _ i a. The Baladeyah may order some vaccine and that one day in the week may be fixed for carrying out vaccination. b. Kepairing rrior Koad and sprinkling A^bater on it for one month. C. nemoving certain date palms which stand in the way to Adhari. ihe i.ajlis, having discussed the se suggestions, decided that they have approved of the the Baladeyah should write to 1 st and 2 nd suggestions and that i&gt;p.nolmes the radical officer toi -4 to fix one day in the week for vaccination in his place (.Hospital; for men. vaccinating the women will be done by the Baladeyah mid-v/ife. rhe Adviser said that no vaccine is to be ordered as the uovemraent should supply it,but the Baladeyah is to encourage the people for vaccination. ihe Majlis thanked him very much for thi$. negarding the third suggestion, the .yaladeyah is to write to the government about it. naji Muhammad bin namad al vadhi suggests as follows :- a. xhe Baladeyah should reclaim the roads and rain water ways in the streets and narrow lanes. b. ror the coming year, the yaladeyah should considei bringing a specialist in road reclaiming. ihe Majlis approved of the first suggestion, ihe second suggestion will be considered at the beginning of the new year. 7) . Reading reports of the inspecting committee and the Accounts Committee»- rhe Majlis approved these reports. 8) . The following letters received by the Baladeyah were read:- (a)Letter p 0 .832/8 dated the 14th shaban 1354 from the Adviser to the Bahrain government reminding the yaladeyah of the correspondence on the subject of mosquitoes which cause malaria and that this is due to the stagnant waters m the houses, in the pots and in the cesspools against which necessary steps should be taken. xhe Adviser also suggests that the following persons should attend in case the yaladeyah wish to hold a meeting for this purpose:- Dr.Holmes. u r .L&gt;ajne. up.Thoms* ur.Bhandarkar. They should attend the meeting and give their opinion. ! if the steps which are to be taken necessitate expenses, the government would probably help financially, provided^ ' ^aj lis takes active steps. rhe Majlis thanked the adviser for this and referred to '1 their previous report on the subject of combatting malaria.*r\ 'f, ^b)Letter n 0 .828/8 dated the 14th instant from him too regarding cleaning the narrow lanes, ne suggests that the contractor should be wanned to perform this work satisfactor ily as the lanes are dirty. rhe Kajlis decided that the contractor should be warned to perform his duties satisfactorily and keep the town clean always. (.c )Let oer dated the 14th shaban 1354 from Ibrahim iMunoo joint requesting that the/roof of his house and of the shops of uaji Abbas bin Muhammad sadiq Kazeruni may be removed as it covers the balcony of his house. rhe matter has been referred to the inspecting committee. (.d)Letter dated the 13th instant, from Abdullah bin abdul /ahid irani requesting the r.ajlis to have the boundaries of his land fixed by another inspecting uommittee according to the Baladeyah rules. ihe Majlis accepted his request. ie)Letter dated the 24th shaban 1354 from &lt; Abdur Hahman bln Muhammad al Mutawa* regarding the repair to the wall of his house. This was referred by the r.-ajlis to the inspecting Committee. ^f/Letter dated the 15th instant, from naji Khalil bin ibrahim al Muayyad asking the Majlis to accept his excuse for being absent on account of the indisposition of his health, ihe Majlis accepted his excuse. 9i. rhe meeting was dissolved at 5.30 Arabic by the order of the Acting President. -4TRANSLATION. zt ^ Agenda for the fOth meeting of £ an amah Baladeyah which will he held on Thursday the 6 th rhul mada 1354 (30.1.36;. 1;. Reclaiming the Roads of the rWwn. Ten extra labourers are required urgently to work in reclaiming and levelling the roads and the streets within the town. 2;. Building Biaces for throwing the waste. The waste pans which are in the town are built of mud and very frequently get ruined on account of the damp weather Apart from this they are unsuitable. rhey would be better and stronger should the Baladeyah build them with stones and cement, what is the opinion of the majlis about this &lt; 3) . Filling the second portion of the water pool. '/hat is the opinion of the rajlis about making limits ‘ • for the sedond portion of the water pool which has not yet been filled and inviting tenders for filling it. 4) . Repairing a portion of the ground of the ganden and getting it planted. In the Baladeyah garden there is a ground situated in the west, it is unreclaimed and spoils the scene of the garden. it would have been more useful should the Baladeyah reclaim it and plant flowers on it. а) . The new lorries and their cost. in accordance with the report of the Majlis which was held on the 13th shawal 1354 to the effect that the Baladeyah should ask for the prices of lorries from the agents of motor cars at Bahrain and submit the same to the Majlis, the Baladeyah obtained quotations from the Agents of Ford, Chevrolet and Pharco at Bahrain, v/hich will be read to you. б ) . Contract made with the contractor about filling the pool. In accordance with the report of the Majlis which was held on the 21 st Shawal 1354 regarding the expiry of the period agreed to between the Baladeyah and the contractor to ^ fill the water pool which has not been filled completely, I the committee appointed to inspect the place have carried out l ta * •23 • 0 | their inspection and they did not reach to a final finding as all of them have different opinions. ihe matter has not been settled, what is the opinion of the Majlis ? ?)• Expiry of the period of the inspecting comnittee. fhe inspectiong Committee have finished their term and they are to be thanked for their services, another Committee should be elected. 8). Heading reports of the inspecting committee who carried out inspections on certain places. r ;■ ■MM D.O. No. y Dpr.EIPT - C ^ V. Rec&amp;iPT No (^X Bahrain, Persian Uulf. 29th January 193d. 2*0 Dear Cole, Keference your D.O. Ho. 32-P/2 dated 27th January 1936. We have ordered a supply of dry vaccine from -rt-merica which Dr. Holmes recomnends. Yours sincerely, Captain G. A. Cole. I.A.. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.ifa -V-* x'RANSTATION. Minutes of the Bth meeting held by the manamah aaladeyah on ihursday the 7th ohav. r al 1354^2.1* 1936 rhe Man amah aaladeyah meeting was held under the presidency of shaikh Muhammad bin sliai-'h * isa bin ’All al nhalifah and in the presence of the members of whom the following were absent owing to indisposition of health and businesss- Haji nuhanmad bin iv-ubarak al radhif, naji Muhammad j bin nasan al uarazi and naji Husain *Ali xateem. after reading and confirming the minutes of the previous meeting, discussion took place over the following;- 1) . The secretary submitted the account of income and expenditure of the naladeyah fro two months namely najab and sha'ban 1354 which are as follows j income of najab Rs.5106-6-6. bast year Rs.5905-15- Kxpenditure of najab.. .Rs. 3532-7-0. 4i ' Rs. 2349-0-3 income of bha’ban Rs.4812-^15-6. M ' Rs.5229-D-9 expenditure of oha 1 ban. Fs. 3692-7-6. M •• Rs.2529-8-6 ihese figures were passed by the Majlis and signed by 6 * the ^resident. 2) . uld medicines and drugs. rhe Secretary stated that it is known that most of the medicines would be of no use after some time and some of them would be even dangerous. in Bahrain, no period is recognized for medicines and there is a great deal of old medicines m the market and sold to the public. Ag a result of these medicines the health of certain people was badly affected. vhat is the opinion of the rajlis about checking this matter v I-he Majlis, after going through this question fully, - decided that the government may be asked to pass their orders to their medical u’ficer to carry out an inspection on the places where useless medicines can be found. • L.HMBMHRHi ^*#r- 3;. i'he Artesian well of the garden. rhe Secretary stated that the saladeyah have started | deepening the artesian well of the .garden and that, by the &lt; grace of vod, adequate water has cone out which was not expected, rhe total feet dug are 300. now the garden enjoys sufficient water, in this connection the Decretory I suggested that the water coning from the Ahawajah well nay | he discontinued and the pipes may he removed from their | present place and used for watering the sma 1 ! gardens I which are in front of the American mission from this well, rhe Majlis thanked him for this ano approveo discontinuing the water from Khawaj ah well and watering the small garden 4;. Baladeyah lorries. The Secretary stated that as it appeared that the Baladeyah are spending a considerable amount on the repairs done to their lorry cars which are old and soon go out of order, he suggests to the :.:ajlis to buy one or two lorry cars and thus get rid of the expenses for the repairs of these old and unserviceable lorry cars. xhe Baladeyah are,in fact, in a great need for lorry cars. The present lorry cars have been in use since a long time and are no more suitable for ualadeyah work. rhe Majlis approved this suggestion and sanctioned the purchase of (.lorry cars;, but before this is done, the ‘ r otor uar Agents in Bahrain may be asked to supply quotations which should be submitted to the Majlis. 5). Death of the bear. rhe Secretary stated that the Baladeyah regret to announce the death of the bear which Major .prior very kindly presented to the Barden as a momento. ±t died on 25th pamadhan after it had fallen sick. The Majlis regretted its death but has not yet decided anything as sufficient beasts are not available in the garden.6 ). Reading reports ol* the inspecting uo ni dll of which were approved by the majlis. 7). The follov;ing letters and petitions rec baladeyah were read over:- la)Letter No. 962/8/- dated the 13th Kamadhan 1354 from the Adviser to the Bahrain government saying that tne Government are willing to give the sea piers oo the ualadey ah as saying that nojone should be given the plot of land which is near the power House as compensation as it may be required in future. xhe Majlis agreed to this and decided that nasan bin Hibail should be compensated with another plot of land in lieu | of the portion which has been cut off his house according to ,, the opinion of the inspecting uo uittee. '•c^'Letter no.If'/8/1354 dated the Ifth namadhan 1354 from iir.bteele,btate hmgmeer, Bahrain, enclosing a statement shov/ing the requirement^of the ice machine .and asking for f Vd)Letter from naj i • Ali bin mhammad nanoo and naj i Kalman bin 1 Ahmad Kanal, two members o' the majlis, asking the Baladeyah to have mercy on the people. xhe Majlis thanked them for their attention and approved their request. compensation if they require them for stones, juss etc enclosing a list of the donations given for the eastern mosque g perusal of the Majlis. lc)Letter wo.538/12/1354 dated the 27th bhawal 1354 from him permission to order them. xhe Majlis approved this.^eJLetter no.247 cUoted the 2 Sth uamadhan 1354 from the CDhara* 'vaqf department at Bahrain, informing the aaladeyah that they have reverted the water stream as they were going to build the foundation of the uama 1 Mosque, ihe Majlis agreed to this. ^f;Letter dated the 20th Ramadhan 1354 from 'Abdur Kahman al bhaiji, neac ulerk of the baladeyah informing the Majlis about the period he spent in the service of the baladeyah which is five years and requesting^;that he may be given the compensation the payment of which was deferred, vide the decision of the najlis held on 14th mharram 1354 based on Articles 72 of the £&gt;aladeyah lav/ and (b)that he may be paid for five months on account of the five years 4 past services according to article 69 of the lav/, ne also informed the jviajlis that the pay for three months which he received was refunded by him. After this had be°n read, the Majlis referred this question to the Accounts committee so that they may refer to the the previous reports and 1 a? see the reason for the recovery by the naladeyah of the amount paid to him. tg) Letter from s e th r.ahrajmal rfansraj dated P8th oha , ban 1354, requesting that he ''ay oe all owe d to make a pavement m front of his office on government Road similar to the pave rnent macie fbr the 0 ffi ces on barre t KO ad. The Majlis allowed him to do so. (h)Letter dated 5th instant from haji Yusuf bin ‘Abdur Kahmai Rakhroo saying that he wishes to buy the narrow lane adjacent to his property in nua f im as the tenants of his property are amoved with it. he requested that inspection may be Vi rnade 0n t;:e lane 80 that i^s price nay be estimated if the Baladeyah wish to sel 1 it. rhe raH.i- referred this questio to the inspecting committee. U)Letter dated S7th Kamadhan 1354 from Salman bin ‘Ahmad Kanal enclosing a sample of paper sent from B rypt. After examining it, the ITajlis did not approve it and therefore cided that one of the presses in Basrah may be asked to* - supply the form of printed paper required. Kj ^Letter dated the 7th bhawal 1354 r ror the mernner naji Muhaui’iad bin r^ibarak al r'adhil apologizing for his absence owing to his illhealth. rhe Majlis accepted I his apology, and ^rayec that he may recover. 8). The meetirxg was dissolved by the order of the president at 6.00 Altaiic time.THAITSL ATI ON . Minutes of the 19th meeting of : anemah iialadeyah held on Thursday the 21st shawal 1354(16.1.36;. The Man amah Baladeyah meeting was held under the presidency of shaikh i^hammad bin shaikh * Isa bin *Ali al I Khalifa.li and in the presence of all the members except the following v/ho were busy and could not attend j- l.Haji msain bin • Ali Yateem. P.naji Ibrahim bin *Ali al Maskati. 3.HaJi 'Ali bin *Abdur Hasul Kanguni. After reading and confirming the minutes of the previous meeting, discussion took place over the following:. 1;. Filling a water pool. xhe Secretary submitted the question of the contract made with the contractor the period of which has passed and he hj© not filled the pool completely. After discussing \ this question fully, the Majlis decided that this matter should be referred to the Accounts committee and the inspection committee so that they may inspect the pool and express their opinion about it. 2). The Drilling Machine. The drilling machine is now free as the work has been completed but it requires some necessary parts in case the Baladeyah wish to use it again. vould the Majlis sanction the purchase of these parts or the machine may be kept in the godown. The Majlis discussed this matter and decided that keeping it in the godown is of no use. xhe Secretary should estimate the necessary parts and also to see if anybody wishes to buy the machine and how much he offers for it. These should be submitted to the Majlis during its next meeting. 3;. plants for the Daladeyah garden. variou ihe secret/ r- stated that the garden is in need for s kinds of useful plants, bhould the Haladeyah order these from outside.rhe 1 'ajlis agreed to it but decided that first the natter should be referred to the Accounts committee so that they may allocate a sum of money for this purpose. 4 ). surrounded lands. rhe secretary stated that many people do not care to get their lands surrounded v/ith walls nor repair the ruined walls of their lands. Lands not surrounded with wal! are used by the public for wastes and the Baladeyah are undergoing great dificulties on account oz this. rhe Majlis discussed this matter end decided that the Baladeyah should warn the owners of such lands three times, if they do not comply with the order, the Baladeyah should do the necessary repairs and send s bill of the expenses to the owners for payment. 5;. Crude oil. rhe Secretary stated that the Baladeyah are in need for crude oil for use on the water pools etc. ihe Majlis | decided that the Baladeyah should write to the Adviser requesting him to get a supply from the Bahrain Petroleum company. 6 ;. Sale of meat during the month of ttamadhan. rhe Secretary stated that the sheep slaughtered during the month of Kamadhan were 77 in number, rhe loss cornes to Rs,211/6/-. rhe Majlis passed this. 7;. ihe following letters received by the Baladeyah were read overs- UJLetter jmo.115 dated the ISth shawal 1354 from naj i balman bin Ahmad Rafnal and ohaikh ishaq bin Abdur Kahman al Khan drawing the attention of the Baladeyah to the fruit market which is dirty and damp, rhe I'ajlis thanked them this 8 jiq ^©ciceo 'that 'ths 8 Isdsvrili should siboutj i - it to the Adviser as it belongs to H.E.Shaikh sir Hamad. (b)Letter dated the 6 th shav’al 1354 from shaikh Ahmad bin shaikh Kuha mad bin 'Isa al Khalifah asking that his property which is occupied by the ■’inawis may be vacated.ihe Majlis decided that the ^aladeyah should inform the government that the crmer wants his land to be vacated and, as the baladeyah and the government allowed them to live on the said property in the past years, therefore the Majlis solicits the approval of the government to the vacation of the property and also order for its vacation. (.cJLetter rgo.519/54 dated the 12th ohawal 1354 from the Adviser to the Bahrain 'government asking the unspecting committee to inspect on the Joint passage of the house of ■Abdullatif bin Mubarak al nhair - * -nd the house of the client of ‘Abdul vaheii bin dasim ^arata as the former alleges that the client of ‘Abdul walrit has erected a building on this passage and thus blocked it up. rhis matter was referred to the inspecting Committee. td)Letter dated 20th yhav/al 1354 from ‘Umar bin 'Abdur Rahman bin ’Abdul vahhab al Khalifah asking the Baladeyah to give him compensation in lieu of the shop which was demolished by the Baladeyah and also to give him the amount of the rent, ihe MajJLis referred this to the Accounts Committee. (.eJLetter from bu It an bin • Abdur Rahman bin • Abdul v/ahhab al Khalifah, requesting the Baladeyah to dismantle the haillvj which 1 Abdur Rahman bin bhaikh ‘Ahmad al rihza* has erected^ m rent of his shop. rhis was referred to the inspecting Committee. i,f)rho member Haji ’Ali bin Muhammad nanoo submitted to the 1 ■'ajlis 34 rupee coins saying that the Bank have refused to take them from him as they were considered by the :;ank to b&lt;r' bad rupees and thus not accepted, after examining them, 3 | tee Kajlis asked the o e cretary to show then to the adviser ^ for his opinion and then they should be returned to their ' owner Haji 'All. 8 ). ihe meeting was dissolved at 6 o'clock Arabic by the r order of the President.Agenda for the 21st meeting of Han amah Baladeyah which wil-1 be held on ihursday the 20th iliul ^ada 1354 (13.2.1936;. 1). Account of expenditure and income of Han amah ealadeyah for the month of Kamadhan and yhawal 1354:- 1. income of Kamadhan, .H'. 3479-7-6. Last year.. .R c .4351-14-0- 2 . expend. M ' f ». 3517-5-6. w n Fs. 2719-13-0- 3. Income of yhawal.... ‘*.5143-12-6. ’* ” Rs.3683- 3-0- 4. expend.'* ” M . 4160-12-6. M ' Ks. 2571-15-0- 2;. to thank the members for their suggestions. I rhe Government thank the members for their suggestions which they put up durinr.f the meeting which was held on 17th Sha'ban 1354 and they will gradually be put into effect. been ordered from America from the best quality. a s regards; I the second matter, at present a police-man is madeto stand NS 3;. Leprosy. Luring several meetings, the qu:£tion of persons suffering from leprosy was put up for discussion but the Baladeyah have obtained no result out of these discussions. This disease is contagious and to neglect it would be dangerous to the public. The order rests with you. 4), Filling up water pools. i - ur i n 8 several past meetings, it was decided that the water pool situated between the property of al v^usaibis and Lespers Office south of rrior Hoad should be filled up but As regards the question of vaccine, a sufficient supply has near the Customs ^ouse as a trial. t is very dirty and nasty smell emanates from it. it, was decided in the previous meetings that it should necessa; be filled. necessarily ! • An electric li iit in the garden. This year the Baladeyah have reclaimed the -round their garden and had flowers of various' kinds planted There is 'Iso adequate water which has been granted by • grace of -od. how the garden lacks nothing except one 1 how the garden lacks nothing except one thing rlC liSht * ' rhis wil1 not cost the Baladeyah ' water which has been granted by the ground of namely an electric light. This wimuch; as they have a pole for the light to be fixed on it K and there is only a short distance for connecting the F* wires. rhe power of this light may be similar to those of the streets, ihis is useful in case the isaladeyah some day may require lights in the garden. 6 ). To read reports of the Accounts committee and the inspecting committee.jevknd Manufacturers of Motor Vehicles. Yours 25-P/2. BY APPOINTMENT ^ T 7 (3 LEYLAND MOTORS LIMITED, Head Office and Works. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE: OURS jap/ES ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO BE ADDRESSED TO THE COMPANY AND NOT TO INDIVIDUALS CUSTOMERS' VEHICLES DRIVEN AT OWNERS RISK ONLY • ♦ * TELEGRAPH 1C ADDRESS LEYMOTORS, LEYLAND TELEPHONE: LEYLAND 81400 (16 Lines) Leyland, LancashIRE The Political Agent, Political Agency, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, 23rd January 19 36. ia We thank you for your letter of the 15th January and are pleased to note you are interested in motor lorries and trucks. As the largest manufacturers of heavy commercial vehicles in this country, we have a wide range of chassis at your disposal, and we are enclosing leaflets describing the various goods machines from 3-tons payload capacity up to 12 -tons payload capacity. Xf you require chassis or complete vehicles to he shipped to Bahrain we feel we can meet your requirements from a general point of view, and we hope that you will let us have full details so that we may quote you for a suitable vehicle. Operating in tropical parts of the world necessitates modifications to standard chassis and in Persia we have found it necessary to incorporate these in order to ensure satisfactory operation. Different chassis require modifications in different directions and we feel no useful purpose will he served in endeavouring to give you them at the present time, hut we shall be only too pleased to set out full details against any specific enquiry. Assuring you of our attention at all times. p.p, We are, Yours faithfully, LEYLAND MOTORS KT' ENCLS. Sales Managerdear Belgrave, I am at’sirec by Colonel Locn to forward to you the enclosed pamphlets concerning LeyInna lorry cars ana trucks in case the Manamah Balaaeyah are interested in them. Yours sincerely, C. talrymple Belgrave esquire, iidviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. i\ a id I If s 'No. i&amp;qQ— / of 1354 Office of the adviser to the Government, Bahrain Oated 26th ^il saad 1354 No. /&amp;qci~ Office of th i'ebruarji 19, 1936. H.B.M's Political 'gent, Bahrain. Memorandum: I have received a letter from shaikh Mohamed bin Isa al Khalifah, in his capacity of President of Manama Municipal Council, asking the Government remove the occupants of the village of Adilabad (locally known as Zulmabad) from the ground which they now occupy as he claims that the ground is within his Tt oehat Tt of Mahoos, which he states belong?to his son *k-hmad bin Mohamed. as the persons concerned are all foreigners, Persian and^I think some ex slaves, I refer the matter to you. this demand involves the question of feudal rights and^Sehat'. M.Y Adviser to the Government v- y&lt;. '53 xRA.Iibijrt.ri^ » Agenda for the 22nd meeting of the ©aladeyah which will be held on xhursday the 4th x'hul *‘ijjah 3.354 v27.2.15 35;. !;• inspections carried out by the ualadiyah. on 20th rhul ^ada,vl9.2.36;, the ^aladiyah carried out sanitary inspections on 20 restaurants) coffee-shops) bakeries and soda factories the owners of which were taken to the oourt with the charge that they kept dirty water and did not observe cleanliness and did not care to have the food which they offered to the people made in accordance with sanitary measures, ihe court passed various sentences against them, ^ each according to the nature of his offence. 2;. Making limits for the water pool. in accordance with the decision of the majlis v/hich was held on 6 th i^ul ^&gt;ada 1354 regarding filling the second portion of the water pool, the naladiyah made limits for the portion in question and invited tenders for filling it by contract. 3;. erecting a place for the ice machine. as the new ice machine will shortly arrive, it is necessary for us to build a place for it in accordance with the opinion of the ^tate engineer. 4;. iooIs for the filling machine. m accordance with the decision of the majlis held on 21st j&gt;hawal 1354 v/hich says that an estimate should be made | for the tools required for the drilling machine and submitted j to the Majlis, the x&gt;aladiyah have obtained quotations which will be read to you in detail, xhese tools are necessary for the machine and the order rests with you. 5;. Crude oil, cast week the ualadiyah received 5 kegs of crude oil from the Bahrain petroleum company which ha« been obtained from them by the adviser, xhe Adviser is to be thanked for his kindness towards the Baladiayh.6 ) . instructions regarding combatting malaria. ihe Baladiyah gave to each of the members of her majlis a copy of a report regarding combatting malaria which the adviser forwarded to the ualadiyah in order to study it and take steps to act in accordance with it. ^his matter \ should be discussed. 7) . contractor for the bokerage of sheep. xhe period of the contract shall expire on 30th •.hul nijjah 1354. should the ^aladiyah invite tenders as it would be possible that the ualadiyah may get a higher offer than the previous one which was Rs.1500/- per annum. If so, what would be the opinion of the Majlis about the period r Should it be one year or three years r 8 ) . ro read the following reportss- deports of the xnspecting committee. &lt;,b&gt; reports of the committee appointed to distribute the donations to the relatives of the victims of the house of Muhammad xayib.iranslation of the minutes of ..ianamah oaladiyah 20 th meeting ’ held on xhupsday the 6 th ihul Qada 1354 ^30.1.36; xhe sittiag of the waladiyah was held under the presidency of ohaikh muharnnad bin shaikh l lsa bin k Ali al fvhalifah and in the presence of the members, Amongst the absentees was naji iviuhsin bin Ahmad al xajir on account of some business. After the minutes of the last meetin ' were read and confirmed, discussion took place over the following: 1 ) , Kepairs of road in the town.. a proposal was made by the secretary that the oaladiyah was in urgent need of eirploying ten labourers for repairs and levelling of roads, it was approved by the Majlis and passed that 16 labourers in place of ten should be employed in addition to the present workmen and they should be under the supervision of the CDecretary* 2 ) . erection of dumps. it was proposed by the oecretary that the dumps in the city are made of clay and are not suitable and always get spoilt on account of dampness, the Baladiyah make them with stone and cement, they will be more strong and fit. xhe Majlis discussed the matter and at length asked the secretary to get the number of dumps and submit his report to the committee of Accounts. 3;. ro fill up the second portion of the water pool. ihe secretary proved that if the Majlis approved ,the saladiyah snould limit the second portion of the water pool which is still unfilled, and invite tenders for its filling, ihe proposal met with the approval of the Majlis. 4) ‘ cultivation^ l0n ° f the « al ^iayh gai^en suitable for a proposal was made by the secretary that a portion of land in the western side of the saladiyah garden is tmlooked for and it presents an ugly sight to the garden. x f the Baladiyah make it fit for cultivation, it will be a nice scenery and will yield profit, xhe Majlis approved of it unan Lnously. ■■ .'b- ijrlr r rnmw5). wew lorries and their prices. ihe secretary submitted catalogues and nrices of motor lorries in sahrain in accordance with the decision of the Majlis held on 7th shawal 1354. xhey were from three agents of different firms. A. *rom I’ord Agent. xhe Agent states that motor lorry # with box having capacity to carry 2 tons, 1S36 model, will cost Rs.3200/- but without box of the same model the cost will be Rs.2413/8/-. models at two years will not be but slight, u. rhe Agent o ^argo informs that a lorry without box having capacity to carry two tons will cost Rs.2400/-. rhe Majlis discussed over the matter and came to the decision that it was out of question to order a rargo car as it is not used in Bahrain. i. 0 rd and Chevrolet cars are generally used now. as opinions of members differed in b. From the Agent of Chevrolet. ±he A -ent states that the value of a lorry with a box having capacity to carry two tons, model 1935, will be Rs.3100/- if the orddr is for two but if only one is ordered, the value will be R3.3150/-. ns regards one without box of the same model, the value will be Rs.2300/- if the order is for two but if for one only the cost will be Rs.2350/ ne farther states that he has not received the price list o l 1930 model but the difference between the year. cast votes and it was approved, xhe Majlis decided by 9 votes with the votes of the ^resident to buy one lorry only with box and leave the consideration for the second car for next ghe Model. connection with these two makes, the resident proposed to take votes after two members aaji uasan bin •Abdul aziz al ajaji and naji a Vi bin Muhammad nt to buy one lorry only with on for the second car for next i\anoo had taken leave not to ng the model of the lorriesr- rs ^0 whether ^ord or Chevrolet as hev the btate engineer) possesses experience in machines and their capacity, rhis being done the order will be made by the tsaladiyah. xhe Adviser approved of this. 6 ). undertaking of contractor to fill up the water pool. rhe Secretary put the minutes of the meeting held on 21st shawal 1354 in connection with the termination of the period agreed upon with the contractor within which the filling up was not completed, un inspecting the place by the appointed committee, the matter was discussed v/ithout arriving at any definite conclusion. -i-he Majlis asked the commit bee the reason for not filling the water pool completely by the contractor, xhe committed admitted that the place 'was not filled up completely and farther stated that the porlion filled up already has not been done according to the level required, xhe Majlis asked for the appearance of the contractor and when he came they demanded from him the reason for the delay in filling the water pool completely within the period specified in the agreement, xhe contractor pleaded that he was sick for about anonth and that was the cause of delaying the work, ne asked apology from the mJUs which S was accepted and the time extended till the end of xhul najj 1354. xhis further grant of time will allow him to fill up the place completely in accordance with the agreement. ri e will be paid Fs.300/- on that date and after 15 days a further sum of Rs.300/- will be given him. 4 ie committee will inspect the place fortnightly. ± f the period which is the end of xhul najj expires and he has not filled up the place as required, the naladiyah will take action according to the terms of the agreement. I 7). .termination of the period of office of tho „„ committee. lce 0i tfle J-nspecting rhe secretary informed the majlis that the period 01 office of the inspecting committee has expired and passed a vote of thanks for the refonns they have done/~N - during their time for the benefit of the public. xhe President suggested that another com ittee be formed. j.he result of the election was as follows:- 1 . naj i ivuhsin al iajir. 2 . naji iiusain l Ali i^adhum. 3. uaji nUSain *Ali yateem. 4. x.aji Ahmad bin i-ohsen ballum. 5. r^hwajah mir uaud nobein. 8 ;. Heading the reports of the inspection committee about inspection carried out on certain places. rhe Majlis approved of the opinion of the inspecting Committee• 9). ihe following letters received by the j^aladiayh v;ere re ad:- i.a; copy of letter ^o.K.i. dated the 8 th January 1936 from Hlasmiter engineering company addressed to the estate engineer,Bahrain, saying that the price of the new ice- machine with its accessories should be paid at the arrival of the invoices and bills of lading, to the .u a stern uank according to the usual commercial rules. fhe iuajlis approved of this. vb; betoer dated 4th xhul ^ada 1354 from xiaji ‘Ali bin •Abdullah and wasim dhirawi, saying that as they intend to build the north-western portion of their amarah which was formerly property of shaikh rvhalifah bin caiman al baali-ah, they suggest that saladiyah should open a straight road passing through the Ajnarah from the north oo south leaving the western portion adjoining the office of ^usaibis and the shop of shaikh iviuhanmad bin Abdullah al Khalifah. xhey further add that shar/al xujjar is narrow and, if this suggestion is accepted, it will enable the saladiyah to widen the road from the southern side in thj Amarah and to remove the waq^shop bringing the shop of ohaikh iwuhammad bin Abdullah in one line of the road. xhe Majlis discussed the subject and decided that the matte should be referred to the inspecting committee for their opinion. IC) Letter dated 4th xhul qada 1354 from uaji ibrahim al -ua-yyad inviting the attention of Khalil bin ike tial ad iy ahto the drivers '/ho want to learn motor driving, ne suggests that at the outset, before spending money for learning driving, their eyes should be inspected by an eye-doctor and should be allowed to learn driving only after passing the eye examination, xhis will save the necessity of spending money and energy and will be better for them than to learn driving first and then become unsuccessful when exmained by an eye-doctor. ihe Majlis thanked him -nd decided that the oaladiyah should write to the government on the subject, vd) Letter dated 29th ohawal 1354 from several people who occpuy places on warrettnoad inviting the attention of the Laladiyah to the flour mill erected in the market in aarrett road which during the day and night is at work and causing inconvenience in many respects which is set forth in their letter, xhe Majlis discussed this matter and then decided that the baladiyah should write to the owner of the mill and mforrn/of the inconvenience which the neighbours conrolain against. nex.ter dated the 2 nd xhul .^ada 1354 from the member iia Ji ibrahim bin Muhammad Ahmad i inviting the attention of the naladiyah to the cemetaries the gates of which were seen by him to be kept open and dogs etc passing through, xhat it is bitter that they should be closed and not opened except on the evening of every Friday and also Wien there is any need ao so. ihe «ajlis decided that mie gates but the gates should be bolted but not locked, ihe ualadiyah shall take steps to kill the doirs. ' ^ Lette1 ' d&amp;ted 4th shav,al 1354 ^om naji xusuf a l ^ailam asking the Baladiyah to let him know the sice of the porti cut Oxf his prope rty situated in wior xioad so that he may demand compensation from the Government, .he x.ji is decidei tnat the si ze may be ascertained and then intimated to him Letter dated 2nd xhul ,ad a 1354 from ^harnad bin xusuf requesting the a aladiayh to collate the buildir •Was Hummanof his house which has been cut for the purpose of v/idening mharraq road, xhe Majlis referred this matter to the inspecting Committee for favour of enquiries. 10 ). ihe meeting was dissolved by the order of the rresident at 7,00 Arabic time. /'b ■j ;Translation. ^3 Minutes of the 21st meeting of Manamah jaladiyah held on ihupsday the 20th rhul ’^ada 1354 vl3th rebruar,. 1236;. &lt; L : ihe meeting of m an am ah ualadiyah was held under the presidency of of the m*esident ohaikh Tjjhamnad bin shaikh ‘isa bin ‘Ali al nhalifah and in the presence of the members of whom naji ali bin Muhammad nanoo and naji ^usain bin • a 1 i ( xateem were abs 4 owing to some business. After reading and confirming the minutes of the last meeting, discussion •&lt;- took place over the followings- 1 ;. xhe secretary submitted the accounts of expenditure and income of manamah naiadiyah for the months of Hamadhan and shav/al 1354, as show# below income of Hawadhan R?.3479- 7-6. nast year * s. .Hs. 435 ^_ » expenditure - Rs.3517- 5-6. •• n Rs.2719-13-0 1 1 income of ahnv/al f _ _ _ meome o a snav- al • .R?.5143—12*”6. n expenditure “ Rs. 4160-12- 6 . »• Rs. 3683- 3-9 Rs. 2571-15-0 j.hey have been passed by the Knesident and approved by the Majlis. r;. fhwaxing the members for their proposals. ihe Secretary stated that the Government are grateful to the members for their proposals which they put up during the meeting held on 17th ohaban 1354 which will be put into effect gradually, ^he woverment have placed an order for a sufficient quantity of vaccine from America of the best quality. a s regards the second question,about detailing a police man on the roads, at present one pfclice-man has been detailed at the customs as a trial. ihe Majlis thanked the adviser and the ^overrunsnt fi&gt;r their care. 3;. Jbeprosy. ihe oecretary has put up for discussion the question of people suffering from leprosy as the saladiyah have not received any result during the past meetings, ihe i.aTlis discussed this matter with the *dViser who .anted that thetown and outside may be burnished to the (doveminent anti then the matter will be considered* xhe iviajlis agreed to this. 4 ;. filing up '. r ater pools. ihe Secretary stated that the ylediayahj in several past meetings, decided that the water pool situaoed near the sea between vespers wf'£ce and the property of a 1 '^jusaibi, south of rrior Koad may be fi led up but this has not been done yet by their owners and the place in question is very dirty now and nasty smell emanates f rom It. ihe Majlis decided that it should be filled up as decided in the past meetings and that their owners may be asked to take early steps to fill it up. 5;. An electric light to be installed in the garden. ihe secretary stated that no electric light has so far been installed in the .aaladiyah garden and someday there may be a need for the same, what would the ncajlA say to installing an electric light as the ±jaladiyah have a pole for it and the voltage will be as those of the streets. ihe majlis approved this suggestion and agreed that a light may be fixed on the pole for Mch one switch plug may be provided. 6 ;. t 0 read reports of the Accounts and inspecting committees. All items have been approved by the Majlis. 7). ihe following letters received by the aaladiyah vere read:_ (.ay better iMo.lf33/8 dated ~he 16th j-hpl mada 1354 from the adviser to the Bahrain government saying that nis bxcel ency shaikh namad has agreed to reoair the fruit market. a s regards the other market which is being occupied by copper smiths, -is Excellency will discuss with the Adviser about it. xhe thehked nis excellency shaikh namad and the Adviser for their care.Letter 1 ^ 0 .394-6/58 dated the 15th instant from uaptain ^r.A.Cole, Assistant Political ^gent, Bahrain, saying that he has been desired by Colonel .uoch to thank the Decretory for the kifld assistance v/hich he afforded in making arrangements for the ceremony which the Political j*gent, Bahrain held in honour of the anniversary accession of nis excellency ohaikh cjir namad on 11th tjanmary on the rolice oports ground. xhe Majlis thanked the political -ngent. kc) better uq. 11^6/8 dated the 8th instant from the Adviser tc '^he Bahrain Government forv/arding a copy of a. report concern ing combatting malaria issued by the i edical section of Beirut university, ne invites the attention of the ealadiyah » to the first part of the report which deals on public roads and hopes that steps may be taken to put it into action here.* ihe Majlis thanked the adviser for his kind attention and asked the Secretary to have the instructions written and a copy sent to each member so that they may study them, xhe matter will then be decided in the next meeting. ^ vd; Letter from the member naji -uha^mad bin naamad al Qadhi drawing the attention of the Baladiyah to Barrett ^oad which nas now become one of the important rdads as : o reat many « customs cars pass through it. rha , the/l*ail line there harrass the passersby and suggest that the government may be asked i remove them. j.he Majlis agreed to this and requested the Adviser to have the rail line removed and placed somewhere else which would not stand in the vay of motor cars and the ! passersby. xhe Adviser said that the Government weregoing to remove them from that place ,nd the .ajlis thanked him for&gt; better ^ mSaln bin • Ali rhawadi asking the naladiyai to give him compensation as he alleges that the * a ladiyah some years past cut off his house, xhe , ajlis asked the se has ever been cut stnd if saladiyah to ascertain if his hou tnere is any record about it. VjLott,, fro. the ^ ^ ^ ; ^ ^ 8e MaJllS disso ^d at 6 o.cloch by order of president■ms pgr*.' ! —— 7s&lt;5r -6 Agenda for the Man amah t&gt;aladiyah meeting which will be held on rhiirrsday the 13th ihul Hijjah 1354 (If.3.36) xranslation. 1; to give on contract the brokerage of sheep. in accordance with the decision of the .uajlis which held its meeting on 4th instant in connection with giving the brokerage of sheep on contract, the ^aladiyah have issued an Alan inviting tenders and its period expired. 2) To widen ohara 1 al xujjar street. as the Majlis, in the last meeting, postponed discussion over the letter of the Adviser, it may now be put up for reconsideration. 3) to collect house tax. A S the Majlis, in the last meeting, postponed discussion over the letter which the Political Agent sent to the Adviser* it may also be put up for reconsideration. 4) nusain bin All al xhawadi. in the meeting held on 20th Thul Qada 1354, the Majlis asked the tialadiayh if there had been any report about cutting the house of the above person. The Baladiyah have now traced reports about the house in question which are dated in the year 1350 and which will be read to you. 5) Extending water to the small gardens. ihe laying oi pipes for 'water from the warden artesian well to the two gardens has been completed and the two gardens are getting enough water, xhe aaladiayh have fixed six water taps outside the big warden for supplying water to the public. &gt;one side was made for the male and another for the female, all the residents of that quarter draw water from trie warden artesian well and are thankful to the oaladiayh for this philanthropic act. &lt;5; Kesidents of hotas vupen lands surrounded with walls;. xhere are many hotas in the town in which several unknown people are living in huts, un several occasions theaalachgrah as well as the public have been annoyed by the dirt which they cast within and without the hotas. as the residents of the hotas are unknown people, x suggest that the ovraers of such hotas should be held responsible to the xsaladiyah for the following;- 1 .Cleanliness S.naladiayh tax, as the aaladiyah did not recover •any tax on some of these hotas. oabmitted for the opinion of the majlis. 1) ro read reports of the inspecting committee who made inspections on certain places. -mmmw r+J% I’KANSbAxlOIvl Minutes of the 22nd sitting of the uianamah Baladiyah held on Thursday the 4th xhul nijjah 1354 (27.2*36). ±he manamah baladiyah sitting was held under the presidency of shaikh ^hammad bin ohaikh * Isa bin ‘Ali al j^halifah and in the presence of all the members, after reading the minutes of the previous meeting and confirming it discussion took place over the following*- 1 ;. inspections carried out by the .baladiyah. ±he secretary submitted a report about the inspection which was made on the restaurants, coffee-shops, bakeries and soda factories, xheyapproved this action. 2;. Making limits for the water pool. # xhe secretary informed the Majlis that the ualadiayh made limits for the second rater pool and invited tenders to fill it up by contract, in accordance with the decision of the Majlis v/hich held its sitting on 6 th xhul v*»ada,1354. xhe Majlis approved this action. 3;. milding a place for the new ice-machine. , , that xne secretary stated/t:ie new ice-machine will arrive shortly and that early steps may be taken to have a place built for it in accordance with the opinion of the state engineer, xhe Majlis decided that the committee should inspect the place with the state engineer. 4;. Tools for the drilling-machine. ^he secretary submitted quotations for the tools which are necessary for running the drilling-machine, vide the report of the Majlis which was held on 21st ohav/al 1354. ihey are Rs.1313/-/- approximately excluding expensesuf ordered; from outside, .he Majlis approved/oubordered that the wovemment are to he asked first if they approve/ordering the tools for the running of the machine as the machine is owned jointly by the government and the aaladiyah. 5;. (Jr»ude oil. . lhS ° eCretary stated th at the aaladiyah during last week received five kegs of emde oil from the Bahrain■■I ' . -»• '•* ^ ■g* i petroleum company which was obtained from them for the tfaladiayh by the Adviser. j.he ^resident and the iv;ajlis thanked the adviser for his care towards the Baladiyah. 6;. instructions for combatting Malaria. ihe secretary stated that the Paladiyah sent to each member of their Majlis a copy of a report concerning Cbmbatting of Malaria, vide the decision of the Majlis which was held on 20th ifrul .^ada 1354. ihis matter should now be discussed and necessary steps may be taken to put this report into action, xhe Majlis discussed this question at length and decided the following:- (a)rhe Baladiyah should support the report made in the meeting which was held on 17th sha'ban 1354. vb;rhe naladiyah should ask for the quotations of a stuff called Paris green; from the firms v/hich deal in it and then a quantity may be ordered. kc )rhe paladiayfr should make efforts in filling the f water pools. vd)rhe naladiyah should combat mosquitoes by using oils and materials which kill the germs which are to be found in the water pools etcetra. vejwhen the necessary water pools have been filled, the paladiyah should consider the question of precautions to be observed in houses. 7;. contractor for sheep brokerage. ihe secretary submitted that the period of the contract made betv/een the baladiyah and paji Abdullah shall expire on 30th instant, should the saladiyah issue an ‘Alan r** about this V rhe Majlis decided than an • Alan may be issued. 3;. xo read the reports. 1 . ihe reports of the ^nspectiong committee were read, ihe Majlis approved all the items of these reports. rhey also approved the payment of Rs.5.00/- now and a further Rs.500/- after 15 days. 2 . ihe report of the oomittee for distributing donations to the victims of the house of Muhammad rayib was read. ihe Majlis thanked the '-onmittee for their services. 9). ihe following letters received by the aaladiyah were read:- U) Letter doted 1st .h„l y ,d, ft™ sh .i kh ^ „ ahln ■nasan al iv hunji drav/inr^ the attention o:f the resident and the w.ajlis to the ^osque of -^bn ^harib or the mosque of the late jauqbil al iftakair as it has no waqf e-nd no allowance and that there is nothing for its upkeep except two ruined small houses, ihat as there is a sum of Rs.536/6/- in the ttaladiyah treasury on account of balance of the donations given for the victims, he requests the president and the members to have this amount spent on repairing the house a which belongs to the mosque and that this is/Philanthropic act. xhe majlis discussed this question fully, xhen the member naji Khalil al mayyad suggested that the .baladiyah B I may enquire from the ^adhis whether it is admissible to have j this amount spent on the mosque and on receipt of a reply from the ^adhis of ^hara* , the Majlis can discuss the matter.*' ihe majlis approved this suggestion. vh.)Letter no.8/1354 dated 3rd instant from the ndviser to the Bahrain government mentioning about the proposed improvement in the manamah market which will result of widening the road which extends between the Amarah of uasim and Ahmad al ohirawi'and the property of ^usaibi, and that he inspected the plans of the properties involved and found that the road lying betv/een them was a public road and not a special property, ne also said that the matter is for the baladiyah to decide. n e also suggested that the bhara• al xujjar street may be v/idened as it is one of the important streets in the market, ne also suggested that the road v/hich extends from north to south may be widened. A he majlis discussed this matter at length and then decided that it may be postponed to the next meeting so that the Lajlis may see the title deeds of *usaibi and bhirawi. uiscussion would then take place. , ^c; setter « 0 .675/11 a datec’ 3rd instant from the superintend, ent, band apartment saying that the -dviser desired him to send the enclosed plan to the baladiyah, showing the road which lies between the property of *usaibi and the nronert. property?2- of Ali bin Abdullah and al ^hirav/i. ne also drav/d the attention of the ualadiyah to the fact that the road is a public road, ihe wajlis examined the plan and thanked the adviser. vd; netter -.0.134^/9, dated the 3rd instant from the Adviser too, saying that time has come for the baladiayh to adopt a « usual system for supplying water to'houses belonging to the is public as/prevalent in all the tovus. ne also refers to the artesian wells in Manamah most of which were drilled by either the government or the ^aladiyah. ihat in future it would be possible t,o collect all the water in one place which may be driven by power to a reservoir and then distributed to all parts of the town,but that this cannot be done at present, ne suggests! that for the time Deing, the naladiyah can get supplies of water from the public wells from which water can be drawn easily and without causing shortage to their water in return for an amount to be paid, monthly or annually. The Majlis agreed unanimously to this useful project and they asked the -ecretary to enquire from -asrah or naghdad about the amount of tax levied for supplying water to houses, ve; better dated the 3rd instant from ^uhammad al Abdul ^ziz al Ajaji asking the naladiyah to allow him to lay pipes for the purpose of drawing water from the well of Baladiyah garden and that he ^prepared to pay to the naladiyah 20% of expenses/ the re-drilling only. The Majlis discussed this question fully and decided that 20% of the exonses of th drilling of the well may not be taken from him but that he may be allowed to draw \ water from the garden well at present on the condition that the width of the pipe through which the water runs from the well to his place may be one inch, and that he should pay a tax of p,, ..nth until tt, „„ teen put into ep,,,^ information .tout the amount of tax has been K„„„ outside. of i if; rranslation of letter «o. 62/ i ./2 dated from uolonel cordon -och,c.i.a., political the 16th February 1936 *gent, Bahrain, tot&gt;tiG adviser to tlie tsalirain -'overnnen't^ v/nicli has ..een sent to the waladiyah by the Adviser, 1. ne ^Political Agent;refers to a letter which he received from the vJyahrain; government under ^o*S61/S dated the £2nd bha-ban 1354 regarding house tax the payment of which has been remanded by the waladiyah. 2. rhat in the past he did not agree to the system of recovering house tax from tenants instead of from landlords but that in view of the special circumstances prevailing in Bahrain now, there are certain reasons which support this system, i&lt;or these special circumstances he ^Political Agent^ hesagree^ to the recovery of house taxes from tenants instead of from landlords subject to the consideration laid dovm in paragraph 4 of his letter, parapgrah 3 to 9 of his letter. ihe Majlis postponed discussion over this question till the next meeting. ^.g^ Letter no.751/11 .a. t. dated the 24th j-hil (q)ada 1354 from the Adviser to the Bahrain government in reply to Baladiyah-s letter iMo.581 dated the 27th ahawal 1354 saying that the government think of opening another road which may connect with the present Adhari road, rhe Lajlis thanked him and decided that the naladiyah should write to the Government enquiring as to v/hich side the road may be opened. kh; better no.1275-8 dated the 22 nd i^ul y a da 1354 from him too, referring to the 1st paragraph of -^aladiyah's letter no.580 dated the 27th bhavval 1354 regaa’ding boats which carry petrol or oil anchoring in the sea more than one mile off the coast, and that this rule has been in existence since , a good many years as reported to him by the uirector of customs and rort officer. ihe Majlis thanked him and the director of customs for his care. UJ better no. 1303/3 a dated the 27th bhul Qada 1354 from him too, in reply to naladiyah s letter r: 0 .537 dated the 24th xhul ^ada 1354. ne says that he agrees that persons who learn motor driving should first go to the -octor. ne was thanked by the ■ iwajlis.(J) setter dated the 28th ihul '^ada 1354 from nusain bin Muhammad ahmadi in reply to aaladiayh• s letter rjo*639 dated the 24th instant inviting the attention of the mnicip&amp;l Majlis to the fact that it is difficult to change the site of the machine as the site on which the machine is erected at present is his own property and there is no other place suitable for it, | ihe reasons for the difficulty is that there are a good deal of tools in the ground which cannot be removed and that he spent I much on the erecting of the machine in its place, xhat if he were to change the site, it would also be necessary for him to change all the tools which are being buried in the earth. i&lt;or these reasons, and as he incurs a loss, he requests the. . ajlis to looK minutely into this question. Vk; Letter dated the 3rd xbul “ijjah 1354 from Lhawajah ibrahim between the shops of naji abbas i^azeruni and his house as he complains that it harms him and requested that inspection may fhe Majlis directed that the inspecting committee should inspect the machine while it is working and see whether it is a nuisance to the neighbours. ^unoo requesting the Majlis to stop the work on making a roof be made on it again. ^he Majlis decied that the work may be stopped and that the committee should inspect it again. M U) -he -ecretarystated that one of the tax collectors of the ctors of the market, nbdur nasul rurani, by name, has from his post, -he Majlis accepted his reo^aoxon ana aecided that another man may be appointed in his place according to the from his post. xhe Majli opinion of the iiecretary. 7.00 O'clock Arabic.iKAl'J b Lirt. ±' XUfJ q t -&amp;1. (3 Agenda for the 1st meeting which will be held on Thursday the 3rd ivuharra^i 1355 &gt;,26.3.1936). as this is the first meeting to be held in the year h ive the v/orks of all the people crowned with success. I 1;. rudget for the expenditure and income of ^anamah / rialadiyah for the month of ±hul ^ada 1354. [ 1* income Rs.4414-3.6. j_,ast year Hs.3584.4. j-n pursuance of the decision of the meeting held on loth xhul nijjah 1354, the ^aladiyah have given the contract ior* sheep brokerage to Abdullah bin naji ihrahim al Qassab Lor a sum 1500/- for a period of one year with effect security has been received from him. 3;. i n pursuance of the decision passed during the meeting held on ith xhul nij.jah 1354, the oaladiyah have invited tenders for filling up the remaining water pool and the period of the notice has expired but nobody has offerred to take up the contract of filling it up. ,,h a t is the opinion of the aiajlis about this ? Electric energy for the ice-machine. 2 . expenses. . .Rs.4702. 1 . 0 . 2), contractor for sheep brokerage. 1355, we pray ^od. to make this year a prosperous one and to from the 1st of uuharran. a sun of ft.1000/- on account of6;. projects and inprovenents in the tovm for the new year, vaj .videning the road of ohaikh namad from north to oouth, vh; Making straight roads in ^udhaibiyah before the erection of any building there. kcj extending the warden water streara to the Lea. v.d; increasing the number of lights in the streets and bazars. , ^e ; mil ding dumps v/ith stone and cement. \fj Purchase of 20 wheels for carts for the use of ualadiyah. 7;. Termination of the period of office of the inspecting committee. xhe period of office of the inspecting ^oLmittee has expired and they are to be thanked for their services, nhotherl committee is to be elected. 8). neading reports of the x^dget Committee and the inspecting committee v/ho carried out inspections on certain places.Translation. &amp; Minutes of the 2oru meeting of Manamah Balaaiyah nela on thursaay the 18th liml Hijjnh 1354 (12.3.36) The Manamah Balaaiyah meeting was hela unaer tne presiaency of the ^resicent Shaikli Muhammaa bin Shaikn T Isa bin T Ali al Khalifah and in the presence of tne members oi whom the following were absent as they were busy:- i Haji Hasan bin Vbaul ziz al Ajaji ana Shaikn Isna^ bin ’^baur Rahman al Khan. After reaaing ana confirming tin minutes of the previous meeting, aiscussion took place over the following:- Ij. io give on contract sheep brokerage. The Lecretary submit tea the minutes of tne meeting hela on 4th instant on the subject of the question of ^making; a contract between the ialaaiyah ana liaji ’Abaullah bin Ibrahim al ^assab. The Balaaiyah issuea an f Alan on the subject ana its period has expirea. The Majlis ueciaea that a fresh contract may be maae between tne Balaaiyan ana ; j Abaullah for a periou of one year only. 2;. To wiaen Shara’ al Tujjar. The Secretary resubmittea the question of wiaening tne Sna^a ? al Tiljjar street ana the raaa which extenas from north to south situatea between the property of al Qusaibi ana ! Ali bin iibaulian ana al ^hirawi. The Majlis aiscuseea .v tnis matter at length ana by a majority of votes aeciaea ^ that wiaening the roau from north to south is not important as it is wine enougn at present, r.s regaras Snara* al Tujjai^ II is important to wiaen it but this question may oe postponeu for the present until the question of compensating tne waqfsnop is consiuereu. Two votes from Haji Knalil ai Muayyaa and haji Husain ^ili Kauhum were against this decision. They were of opinion that the roau from nortu to south ana Shara al Tujjar beginning from the waqf shop ana enaing in the nmarah of Haji Yusuf Kanoo may be wiaenea on tnis occasion. 3J. Recovery of house tax.The Secretary put up for uiecussion the letter of the Political ..gait aduressea to the Aaviser on the subject of Manamah Balaaiyah(house; tax. , fter it naa been reau again, the ^resiaent ana tne members came to know tnat the Political Agent, in the past, ciu not agree to tne recovery of Balaaiyah tax from tenants insteau of from lanuloras as shown in paragraph 8 of nis letter. Seconaly tne Political Agent suggested that it was in the interest of the Balaciyaii to consiaer tne question ol levying Balaaiyan tax on Manamah houses afresh. After reaaing tnis, tne Majlis aeciaea:- 1. The Balaaiyaii shoula write in aetail to tne Aaviser about ihe previous reports in connection with taxes. 2. at tne beginning of tne new year the Balaaiyan snouia consiaer levying tax on houses afresn by the Committee. 4). Husain bin^Ali al Lhawaai. The Secretary reaa the report of the Balaaiyan aatea in the year 135U about the house in question. The Majlis decided tnat the person in question is not entitle to anything. This is similar to the report of the Majlis which was held on 3oth Muharram 13hU. 5;. Extenaing water to the small garaens. The Secretary stateu tnat tne Balaaiyan nave completed the work for extenaing water from the garatn well to the two gardens ana they have also proviaed six taps for supplying water from outsiue tne big garden. Tne people of that quarter are getting comfort on account of tuis charitable action of the Balaaiyan. Tne Majlis consented to ana approvea tne cnaritable action of Balaaiya. 3;. Resiaents of notas (open lanas surrou^aed witu walls). Tne Secretary saia that there are many T notas T in tne town occupiea by certain unknown people who live in huts. The Balaaiyah have exercised great pains as they throw rubbish insiae ana outsiue the notas. The owners of ■ such hotas shoula be hela responsible to the Baiauiyah for (a) cleanliness ana (2 ) Baiaaiyah tax. The Majlis disapproved this suggestion but ueciued that taxes shoula be recovered by the Balaaiyah from tne tenants of such hotas.di tc 7;. Reaaing reports of tne Insepcting Committee. The Secretary reao the reports of the inspecting Committee which were approved by tne Majlis. 8). The following letters received by tne Balaoiyah were read (a) Letter No. 1398/8 dated 15th fhul Hijjail 1354 from tne Adviser to the Bahrain Government regarding the question ol opening a road wnich snould extend from Shara T ai Tujjar (bn the eastern side of the property of Shaikh Muhammad bin T Abdullah bin T Isa al Khalifan and tne property oi al ^usaioi He stated that he insepctea tne place in question and he is of opinion that tne roan which extends from north to soutn is not of much importance and no great benefit can be achieved therefrom but he desires that Shara al Tujjar may be widened. The Majlis thanked him and then decided the same as is mentioned in paragraph no.3 of these minutes. (b) Letter No.1394/8 dated the 15th Thul Hijjah 1354 from him suggesting therein that a moveable wooden shade may be iixed in the midst of a road, as a trial, under which a police-man should stand for tne discharge of his duties. Tne Majlis unanimously approved of this suggestion (c) Letter dated tne 18th Thul &lt;,ada 1354 from Muhammad bin Salman bin Sa^r asking the Balaaiyah to give him the contract of brokerage on dry fish such as* T um , small fines and ury fishes etc wnich are imported from outside. The Majlis re jected hisre^uest and decided tnat eve$one is free to do whatever he likes with his property. No.290 (djLetter/dated 1st Thul nijjah 1354 from Shaikh f AbduLlatil bin Sa’au, one of the Gauhis of Shara f Court requesting tne Baladiyah to,remove the light wnich is in Belgrave Roan and to fix it at the head of the water stream to the north as it is of little use in its present place. If it is fixed on the new place, it will give light to junctions of two streets. This request was referred by the Majlis to the Inspecting Committee. (e)Letter no.209/9 dated the 3rd fnul hijjah 135* from Haji Knalil bin Ibrahim Kanoo requesting tne Baladiyan to limit his land which is situated near his garden in the vicinity ofthe Fort. The Majlis referred this matter to the Secretary. (fjLetter dp tea the loth Thai Hijjah 1354 from T Abaur Eanman^ bin Muhammad al Mutawa f in reply to BaladiyaJ^s letter I No.651/54 dated the 1st dhul Hijjah 1354. He requested the ^resident ana the Majlis to give him a larger amount than that which the Committee had fixed for him. The Majlis decided that he should be paid Hs.lOO/- in addition to tne amount has already been fixed, thus making a total of as. oUU and that the Baladiyah should pay him this amount in two instalments; as. 300/- to be paid during tiiis montn ana ris.3U0 wnen tne BalaGiyah cuts his nouse. (gjBill ho.Y.B/69/54 dated the 17th Thul Hijjah 1354 from the State Engineer, Bahrain, for a sum of as.103/11/9 on account of wages for repairs done to parts of tne ice-macnin by the Petroleum Company. The Majlis decided tnat the amount should be paid. (h) Another bill No.Y.B/70/54 dated the 17tn instaht from the €-tate Engineer for a sum of as. 74/8/8 on account of wages for repairs done to parts for the ice-machine by the Petroleum company. The Majlis decided tnat tne amount should be paid. (i) Letter from the members Haji Hasan al’njaji ana Snaikn T Ishaq bin T Abaur Rahman asking to be excused for not being able to attend the Majlis. Their excuse was accepted. (jJThe member haji Muhammad bin Kama'd al Qaahi suggested that the Balauiyah bye-law may be revised ana printed. The Majlis approved of this suggestion but decided t~at first a committee composed of members of tne Balaaiyan should hold sittings in tne presence of the Secretary and revise the bye-law. After submitting it to the Government, it should be printed. 9). The meeting was dissolved by the order of the President / at 6.3c Arabic time./£&gt;/ ' dE? I Translation of the ^genua for the ^na meeting of Manaman Balaaiyah which will be helo on Thursday tne 17tn Munarram 135b (9.4.1935J 1) . Budget of expenditure ana income of Manamah Balaaiyah for the month of Thul hijjah 1354. They are as follows after having been examined by the Accounts Committee income Rs.6773.10.7. Last year Rs.67U7.2.1. Expenditure.. .Rs.8u37.15.9. With tnis amount a siun of Rs.2054.10.3. has been included on account of naif of tne amount spent on Colonel narrett T s Road ana also another sum of ks.222.14.0. on account of deficit in tne sale of sheep. j_ast year T s expenditure was us.4313.4.0. 2) . The Contractor who undertook to fill up the water pool. ihe period has expired whereas the water pool nas not be filled up completely. .*hat is tne opinion of the Majlis ? M 3) . Contractor for the sale of ice. Ahmad al-Baqlawan, tne contractor for tne sale of ice, is indebted to the Ba±aaiyan for a sum of money on account of expenses spent on tne ice machine wuen it was under his contract, he refuses payment oi tne amount. 4;. To fill up the otner water pool. The Balaaiyan again invited tenners to fill up the water pool ana the period of tne notice expiree ana noone has responded to the call of tne E^alaaiyah. An at the opinion of the Majlis ? 5). To widen Telegraph Roan. There are three houses standing in tne sain roan. The question of cutting some of these nouses for tne pupose of widening the roan may be considered.Translation. tog ( Yo^ Minutes of the Balaaiyah 1st meeting hela on Tnursuay the 3rd Muharram 1355(^7^. 3.1936j. Tne Marmmah Balaaiyan meeting was nela unaer the presiuency of tne Presiaent Shaikh Muhammad bin Shaikh T Isa bin f Ali al nhalifah ana in the presence of the members, haji f Ali bin Muhammad ivanoo ana Haji Husain bin f Ali Yateem were absent on account of some business. After reaaing ana confirming the minutes of the previous meeting, aiscussion took place over the following^- 1;. The Secretary submitteu the account of expenditure ana income of Manamah Balaaiyah for the month of Thul Qaaa 1354. Income Iis.4414/8/3. Last year, Expenditure its. 4702/1/-. ” ” .its. 3584/4/9. Bs. 3084/12/-. ; / ■■ I- This was approvea by the Majlis after it xiaa been passea i 1 by the Presiaent. 2&gt;. Contractor for sheep brokerage. The Secretary stated that the Balaaiyan gave the contract for sheep brokerage to ’Abaullah bin Haji T Ibranim , ? al -iassab for its. 1500/- for a period of one year commencing from the first of Muharraip 1355 ana thatothe Balaaiyan nave ' received a sum of Rs.1000/- from him as a security. The Majlis approvea of this. 3). To fill up the water pool. r ihe Secretary re-submit tea the report of the meeting hela on 4th Thul nijjah 135^ in connection with filling up . of the secona portion of the water pool ana statea mat the Balaaiyah issued an T Alan inviting tenaers ana tne perioa has passed but noboay has come forward to take up the contract, fhe Majlis decided that another T Alan should be issued. i 4 4;.Electric energy to be consumed by the ice-machine. Ihe Secretary re-submittea the suggestion of the adviser which was postponed curing the meeting nela on 24th Eabi T Than! 1354 to the effect that the Balaaiyan should pay Annas 3/- for each unit of entrgy by the ice- machine instead of Anna l/- etc. Ihe Majlis discussed this |■ I question fully anu decided tnat the matter snouid be referred to the Accounts Committee to deal with. Secondly, the Baladij should write to the Adviser revesting nim 10 reply to Baladiyah's letier ao. 317/54 dated the 3otn Jamaa Awwal 1354. The Majlis would then pass a decision on the matter. 5). A car for road reclaiming. The Secretary suggested that it would be better for the Baladiyah and the expenses would be less should they buy a car for the purpose of road reclaiming. The Majlis disapproved this suggestion as the car in question is not suitable for reclaiming the roads of the town but it is useful for the wide roads. 6^'. Projects and improvements to be carried out in the town during the new year. The Secretary suggested the following six items. a. To widen Shaikh Hamad road from north to south. b. To construct straight roads in ^udhaibiyah before the erection of any building. c. Extending the garden water stream to the sea. d. Increasing lights of the streets and bazars. e. Bui].aing dumps with stone and cement. f. To purchase 2u wheels for the use of Baladiyah carts. The Mjlis discussed these proposals and at length decided that:- As regards items(a) and (bj, the inspecting Committee should inspect the roads and express their opinion * about them. Item no.3 approved. Items (dj,(e) and (f) were I y i referred to the Budget Committee. 7j. Termination of the period of office of the inspecting Committee. The secretary stated that the period of office of the Inspecting Committee nas expired and they are to be . thanked for the general improvements which they cairied out. The President elected a new committee of the following members : ~ l.Haji Muhammad bin Hamad al *aani. S.Haji T Ali bin C ; •&gt; - Muhammad Kanoo. 3» haji Muhanmau. Janial khuiiji* 4-. haji f Aii bin ’Abdur Rasul Kanguni. 5- Haji T Abbas Abul .^asim Shirazi. 8;. To read reports of the accounts Committee ana the Inspecting Committee. a. Report of the Budget Uommittee in connection with tne leave pay of ’Abdur Itaiiman al bhaiji was read. b. Report of the Inspecting Committee in connection with the erection of a place of the ice-machine ana providing it with water was read. The Majlis approved all these reports. 9). The following letters received by the Balaaiyah were read:- (aj Letter No.1434/8 dated 21st Thul Hijjah 1354 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government in reply to Balaaiyah T s letter No.678/54 dated the 15th Thul Hijjah 1354 sayihg that • the Government have approved tne purchase of parts required by the drilling machine. The Majlis thanked him. (bj .setter No. 1491/28 dated 29th Thul Rijjan 1354 from him too, informing the Baladiyah that the Jafariyah Wa^f CounselI decided that the word (Waqf• J; should oe auoed to the Balaoiyah number plates fixed on shops ana houses belonging j to Jafariyah Waqf. Re asked the Baiadlayu to do this. The Majlis agreed to this. (cj Letter dated 24th Thul Hijjah 1354 from the Ja f fariyah Shara T ^adhis requesting the Baladiyah Majlis to afford assistance to a number of people from T Ihzayan T village who received damages on account fire. The Majlis ueci that they should be afforded help ana given a sum of its.9u/ I * from the Baladiyah treasury. This amount should be paid to them at the rate of Rs.15/- for each house. A hey are six houses. {&lt;1) Letter dated the 24th Thul nijjah 1354 from tne waohis of the Shara f Court in reply to Baladiyah ? s letter No.580/§4 dated the 15th Thul ^aaa 1354 regarding the balance of tne amount of donations given by the uonors for the relatives of the victims of the house of Muhammad Tayib which is i 4 n ♦ J .dec s. 9u/- HIll in , f &lt;!J3^ kept in deposit in Manamah Balaaiyah treasury, ine amount shoula be distributed to those who are present ana are known. That this is in accordance witn Sdara! rules. The Majlis thanked the Shara T M.adhis. (e) Petition dated 18th Thai Hijjah 1354 from ail butoners requesting the President and the Majlis to reduce the slaughter fees by the Baisdiayh arid to treat them on tne same lines as in Muharraq. The Majlis discussed this matter fully and then decided that the question of the extra fee levied on them concerns the Government who have transferred it to the Baladiyah to be spent on tne mid-wife. The Balaniyah should inform the Government of this matter. (fj netter from Muhanna bin Muhammad nu Hammud and Muhammad bin Abdullah Fakhriddin requesting the Baladiyah to reduce the tax levied on their houses. The Majlis decided that this matter should be referred to the Accounts Committee who will look into the question of house tax. ig) Letter dated 3rd Muhamram 1355 from Jasim bin Muhammad Kanoo asking that his brother ’Ali bin Muhammad may be excused for not being able to attend the Majlis on account of some business. The Majlis accepted his apology. 10). The Majlis has been dissolved at 6 Arabic oy the order * of the President.c^cn^co Translation. ( \Z~) Agenaa for the 4th meeting winch will be held on Thursday the loth Safar 1355 (i.e., the 6th May 1936;. l;. Baladiyah budget for the year 1355. The Budget committee composed of the following persons held a meeting:- 1. naji Khalil bin ibrahim al Mua T yyad. E.Haji f Ali bin Muhammad Kanoo63Haji Muhammad bin Hamad al ^adhi. 4.Haji Munsin al Tajir. 5. Shaikh ishaq^ bin T Abaur Rahman. o.Haji Hasan bin Abdul T Azi al 'Ajaji. 7.Haji Muhammad al Darazi. Q.Haji Husain T Ali Kaohum. They decided the budget of tnis year to be as follows For income Ks.55,150/-. Last year it was Ks.52,08o/-. For expenditure. .Hs.51,365/-. ' ” n Its.44,090/-. This will be read to you in detail. 2/. Tax on leased houses. rented s*; The committee found it desirable that taxes on/living place which are situated in the market and in the town should be tne same and decided tnat Baladiyah should recover taxes from tenants of such places at the rate of one Annas' and a half per rupee with effect from tne montn of Muharram 1355. The kxKicotg tax on living houses is-fc’TT'remain as before. . ..T 3;. Barbers. The Committee decided that the Balaueayh should keep an eye on the barbers and give them lisences in which they are to J be warned to observe cleanliness in return of which they should pay a tax of Its.2/-. The poor class barbers who move from here ana there in the market and streets will have to pay no fee but their names will be recorded by the Blaaiyah and they are to give an undertaking that they will observe the required terms. 4;. To fill in water pools. The Baladiyah have started buying stones for filling the water pool and work will be put in hand very soon. 5). Widening roads and corners of the town. 1. Telegraph roaa, near the property of Khuohoori Sayegh. 2. The roaa which lies between the house of Mohd Iain a Bastaki and the Jiouse of ^han 3hai Bohra. •House of Haji Matruk al Tannak situated in Shara T Muqbil. •House of heirs of ^in nadhi situated south of Barahat bin Haoid .East-southern corner of Haji Mohamad al Hama., al *adhi T s house. •' ' ' ' Muhamad bin Yusuf Lori T s house. 6 6 ) To read reports of tne Budget Committee.Translation. Minutes of tht 10th sitting of Manamah Balaaiyan hela on Tuesaay ths 9th Jamaa Awwal 1347. Item No.6. A letter was resubmitted from Shaikh Muhammaa bin 'isa al Ehalifaii in which he requested that the Persians may be turned away from the land which belongs to his son Ahmad and w^io were placed there by the Baiadiyah in accordance wit a the promise made by Major Laly. The Majlis discussed this question iully and then decided that, as the land belongs to the above-named person .'A^mad bin Muhammad), they should be made to leave it and go to another place. L^ji f Abdullah al M.usaibi suggested that tney may again occupy the lane which is situated neai Maitham, in the vicinity of ’Ain Haifa. Taking the above into consideration, the E Mailis decided that an inspection may be carried, out on the land and a committee lor this purpose composed of the following persons has been appointed:- Haji T Abdullah al , t usaihi. Haji Khalil bin ’Ibrahim al Bakir and the Adviser. 'Then they inspect the land and give their opinion about it, the Secretary should let the Political Agent know so that he may himself inspect it also and decide what he thinks. Minutes of the 11th sitting of itonamah Baiadiyah held on Tuesday the 23ru Jamaa Awwal 1347. \km Item uo.l. The Secretary submitted that the Inspecting Committee composed of the following members Khan Bahib Haji ’Abnur Ranman bin Muhammad al Layani, the Agent of ohaikh Mubarak Haji^ ’Ali oin ’Ibrahim Kanoo, haji ’Abdul ’Aal bin Giianim, Khawajali Isha 4 Hisqail Swery, Commandant Park, Haji ’Abdullah al H usaibi and haji Khalil bin Ibrahim al Bakir,carried out an inspection on Thursday tne lltn jamsd Aw.al 1347 on the land which is situated near ’Ain Halta to see whether it is suitable Minawis for tne Persian /to shift to it from tneir present place, vide the decisj.on of the Majiis which neld its meeting on 9th Jamau Awwal 1347. After considering the matter careiully, it has been found desirable to let tnem occupy the new land in question . On Monday the 15th Jamadel nwwal 1354 (?J oolonel Barrett inspected the said land and approved that it may be occupied by those people but he suggested that it would be better for tne Balaaiyah to write first to Shaikh ^uha.iuad bin Shaikn T Isa | bin T Ali al khalifah informing him that as the land belongs to his son, he(his son) can m % do whatever he likes with it and is entitled to recover monthly tax from all the occupants of tni 3 land. Should they refuse to pay any such tax, he would have the right to sue them and then order them to shift to the new land wnich is situated near T Ain Halta. After discussion, the Majiis unanimously approved his (Colonel BairetVs) suggestion, and the suggestion of the Committee The President, however, remarked that nobody Auld occupy the new land before Shaikh Muhammad himslef has seen it lest it may be his own property.f&gt;J&gt;/ r 1/1349. (land Dept) JiUI AjsVO Uj l ■ - -' '•*,' ■ c t •/ : ^ • ■ ■. /'' 4 ^ t ' It is hereby notified:- ^he registration of all sales or gifts of immoveable property within the municipal boundaries of Manaman and Muharrak and the town of Hedd is compulsory. i he registration of all sales or gifts of cultivated or uncultivated property in any part of the island* of . . 1 ■ ’&gt; i f ' '• -• L i . - 4 f y in is compulsory. ihe seller or giver will be responsible for the regis tration and will be responsible for payment of registration fees • ^0 4^ * and tT 'BEA ALKHIYARI’ 1 are considered as sales insomuch as this law applies but need not be registered until after the expiry of the period specified. Applications for registration of sales or gifts must be made within six months of the signing of the sale document. Any seller or gifter failing to comply with this order 0 - i will be liable to punishment by the Courts and any such sales or gifts will be considered invalid. I’rom this date any alteration made in sale deeds, mortgage or gifts deeds or powers of attorney will not be recognised unless the alteration is sealed or signed by the parties in this transaction. * ijiy Fees for registration of sales and gifts will be l^charged at the following rates, on the sale price in case of a sale and on the valuation of the property in case of H &gt; HViWV I./- ni 3 - \. *• Up to rupees five hundred. Fixed fee of rupees five only. 1 vi &lt;Jk. % wOiUl* B. From five hundred to two thousand rupees. ‘•j . ( . U.o c. A t rupees one per cent and part thereof, i’rom two thousand to ten thousand rupees. -nt rupees two for every fitfe hundred rupees and part thereof, having charged for the first, two thousand rupees according to 3. From ten thousand to twenty thousand rupees, ^t rupee one every five hundred rupees and part thereof, having charged for the ten thousand i rupees according to o. For upwards of twenty thousand rupees, U&lt;U D. E. F. At annas eight for every five hundred rupees, » . i * ^vi 111 ll i*i\ I hi having filiarged the twenty thousand rupees according to D. ' \ i - For copy of a sale or a gift deed, Rupees five fixed fee for each copy. Bahrain subjects as v/ell as foreign subjects having objections to sale or registration proclamations issued by the Land department should submit their objection to the Land department direct and not according to the present practice, by which the foreign subjects apply to the Agency. ■‘•he ^and department after the expiry of the proclamation concerned will refer all such objection^to the respective courts for decision. ihe objectors will be considered as plaintiffs and full court fees will be realised from them. hjc l ! UjthwJti i , v v ' ?. ^ ^ •j&lt;*&lt;A! X) No claim between private individulas for immoveable property will be heard by the courts if it is shown that the property claimed has been occupied for ten years or more without payment of rent or without a definite permission from the person who claim it. iflafe Government has the ri 0 ht to claim its property in any part of the Bahrain islandfeven though it has been unlawfully occupied for sixty years, according to this the time of limitation for claims between private indi viduals is ten years but the time of limitation between the Government and private individuals is sixty years. -&gt;d/ C.D.Belgrave. adviser to the Government.translation. Agenda for the ^anamah Baladiyah meeting v/hich will be held on Thursday the 30th L a far 1355(21.5.36). #++#****#* 1) , Budget of account of income and expenditure of Manamah Baladiyah for the month of I%harram 1355. income Rs. 4,096-13-4. Last yearns income. .Rs. 3,527-8-3. Expenditure Rs.4,302-14-3. M ' expnds. .Rs. 3, 306-2-4. 2) . fo thank His Excellency Shaikh Hamad. His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad has been pleased to give the B a ladiyah a special grant of Rs.5,000/- for the purpose of filling the marsh. suggest, for the approval of the Majlis, that a committee of six members may go to His Excellency and thank him in the name of the Baladiyah. 3) . A lorry car for the Baiadiyaji. Last year the Majlis decided tha.t a lo'-ry should be bought- and the Baladiyah placed an order for the same on 8th Thul Qada 1354 but the lorry has not arrived so far. The Baladiyah is in a great need for two lorries. What would the Majlis think of ordering another lorry. 4) . Poor people to be exempted from B a ladiyah tax. The B u( 3g e t C omm ittee found that some per.ple owe Baladiyah taxes and they are unable to pay. On making sure that they Sj. e really poor, the Committee waived the taxes due from them. 5) . Tq widen important roads. Every department has a special duty and the dut$r of the Baladiyah is to observe cleanliness and t£ widen the roads. The ^aladiyah should, therefore, consider two points 5- Firstly widehing Belgrave road from north to south, ^econdly, wid^Lng Eujjar road which is the centre fo^ business to-day. 01 eoljnit™^ ati0n 0f the peri0d of 0 flce of the inspecting •tlie period of office of the inspecting Committee has expired and they are to be tanked for their services, toother Committee is to be elect'd. 7). To read the reports of the Inspecting Committee. V. n -m,' t'3? 4-! itans lat ion of agenda for the ^ an am ah Baladlyah meetin,?' v/hich will be held on r hursday the 28th h a bi A^wal 1355 CIS. 6^36) | 1). ii.iS• Shaikh Hamad's Road. -i-he ^aladiyah have commenced cutting the houses whic§ are situated on Doth sides of bhaikh * i ar.iad load so as to make it wide* J-ovday this Road has become unique in the town but there is one house bulging into the road still and giving a bad shape to the Road. If this house is not cut, the road will still possess a bad shape as though there has been no improvement at all. what is the opinion of the Majlis about this ? 2). Making the scene of the roads beautiful. At paragraph 6 of his letter No. 194-8 dated the 11th ^afar 1355, the -dviser, suggested that trees may be planted on both sides of the roads so that they may present a nice scene. The -aladeyah have provided trees for this pnrpose but they naturally require enclosures so as co protect them from outer exposures. Expenses which may be incurred in this connection may be debited to the account of road reclaiming, ■feat is the opinion of the i-ajlis about this ? 3) • °ale of ice* To read the accemts of eependiture and l»co,» of «. lee -acMne fro„ 25th S.f„ to 23rd Rabi *,,1 13K . 4;. Land of Shaikh Abdul ./ahid. fta Finance ^itta, not decided anythin!! .boat •tad the boundaries of the land of Shaikh * 1,1 ,,hid but they hay, referred the natter to the f,, disposal. • i. dtscus, the question of buyin* a l.r^ for the 3 .i,dey. 6; . '0 read reports.traHsutiou. (a? Hgenaa for the 7th meeting which will be held on (Thursday) the 12th Rabi Thani 1355 July 1936; 1J• Car Stand hear the Customs House. There is no doubt that the number of cars has increased especially taxi cars and buses. The car stand lias consequently -become too small for them, ii/hat would the Majlis think of choosing another place wnicii would suitaoly hold tnis increased number of cars so as to avoid danger and to afford comfort to the public. 2) . Place for ^ashing Coprses at the Cemetary. The place for washing corpses at the cemttary is in a state of ruin, it would be a charitable act if the Baladiyah take steps to repair it before it falls down- 3) . Lights in the Streets and Markets. Tome of the places in the town and in the market require lights. The Baladiyah, this year, have allotted a sum ol money ior the purposes ol lixing lights in the streets, it would be useful if they order 18 lights from abroad and lix them on the places which need them. 4) . To Widen the Roads. One of the important projects of the Baladiyah is the widening oi roads, ine Balaaiyah should, tnereiore, attend to the important places in the town wnere cuts should be mane such as the road which is situated to the west of Mespers T s Office from north to south, .all know that thi^/an important road. There!ore, the Baladiyah should attend to tnis road as they do to others. 5) . Combatting Malaria. All people are aware that malaria has had very ban ejects in Manamah and the people and doctors have had to face great diiliculties. The BaladiyaL, assisted by the Government, took very active steps to combat malaria arm its germs at Lana mail. Through the help of the Government, the Balauiay.x iiIlea up the marshes which are situated outside the town ana useu the oils ana other liquids which aestroy the mosquitoes.By taking this action, tne Balaaiyaii were able to cause the decrease in tne number of deadly cases of malaria. The reports of the doctors show that there has been an improvement in this end. This item may be considered as an extract from a report concerning the project of f Combatting Malaria at Manamah by tne 13a 1 aniyah’ 6). To read reports.— ! K'S/7 • 1 Td o Jj^rOI j*j,K &lt;u* jUJI i—J^JI oKlri•^ t i-^ 1^-i mLaJI jJLj ^l ■)! ,^I»«4^3-*? I • ^ 4 aa#J^JT • J&lt; U«# Col;it J^Jl C^?&gt; Ly^jp ^ JuoJlj iijUJI i-dsJI ^iu&gt;^ ♦ ^ gjj\ mW PyLiJl W^L AtXyl ^jl rjjL-^cJl ^&gt;-1 £yL4Jl&gt; jJljli ^yLAi) 4j£* yt&gt;j # ^pb ^jLAJl ij Jfa j£* -*** • cjl &lt;&gt;4 pi • AgJ UJl *JL»J^ JS^A A^Jp • £&gt;1/^ Jt&lt;?w Mj$L&gt; jL£j'*4 d J hi^ ij4 Cl) jUOI 4 jUJI 4 0* • I r*a^11^ q;&gt;J 1 Mi — A JJ* Oy.^?- Ai jJJIj l^bJl ^*1^ ^UJl i ^ a ^Ai)l ^ L^JLJ ^&gt;U3l L^Jjj^ ^L&gt;^VI a 1a ( ji)j J^^Jl 11^ • * ^ j\y£)\ '.\+*-&gt;£ c-rU^-^Jl *-J Lii? iiJJ J L^ • dUJ^ w* c^* • ^ iii'il ^ ^J1 jl^-iVl JOP*L*fl s i)l Jtls, ^I-mJIo'.^ c. bJI f-^ 1 ^ Jl ^Jl ^U-i-il t-M Otr :, ^ Jl ^/•• a *- ,, ^ **Ui ,1^ i»JU^1 jL&gt;-iVI^ ^ *i-vVl 6 1 O* cr-^ 1 W 1 ^ ^Ir 411 • *j4 JZ\ ^ o&gt;\y tji&gt; 'J' • gj^ 1 gw i 'rooj/jil jyy xr ji&gt;- TO plili c.lJ,ijy ^v 1 -' y; 1 -^ 1 J-' s^Jo rfl^ljl cl^kdOJ JUI *U»*1 ^ *tT5» •»-*. U 1 ^ u -J;'&lt;-'&gt;jU^-tu-l^'v^aJj Jp Jj^Aj L^ljl p«^ JouA* ‘o' 1 ^ 1 i^UJI jlip^-UJI 5^1 ^ f &gt;l« oi'J'. ■ i {r iJ1 '-^ t&gt; f^' • is ju_i ♦ ~ll)l ^-kAMu* V,*&lt;JJltJI JjUiJjJ-*- JiJ' JH o' C )jMp V v I * J N, U r r y *i f ^'“J s -wJ—* * It 'O ^ ^ *^VC ^5 • ^HrS - -t. tj&lt;JL-^ x ^ • ^ % \~*-i : ’ J ^J * A— I - : 1^? wl wL. • r_ • ^ ijJ, . w '*■ ^ J c-^J Vj '. 'j^ • T S*. 4j I JJ^ . ^J-i,-- V J • U , “ *- M &gt; A • - -' ►'» * r*^ • A y Ai».c - IVJ ^ 'w ^ HI ,-x. ^ ^ ^ J -i:-. ^ yl.«JC J ^px t »UJ^ IUJ« • «-H ■JV'kKi Vr5 -J: - ' ILLpl ♦ '-jj IUJ4-J _ IUJ-, s-s, _ IL Jg l^j ^ ‘^V - ,LJ - • - e -yg ?i t M t rr^yr^4&lt;»7 V*. iUrJ^ ^ i'i*. lu ^*1^ — iV-te^i r^s ^s-, M ^ ;jr i 0 J fuv-! ^■» ' ^ I ■*») - !' v |(j - i * j j .» ^ tv-?j ,j^j Vj '•-„yv 1 t i *~c i H&gt;i • S.!^:u:ly_, i.lj.; 'Va^ . ^ - t ' J ’T'*v&gt; *L'.X _ f 17 i,_ r^jift, -Itj* 7\7\r7/ ^'V ' j * L '- - -J’-S ~Wv ^ '. “* J -'-‘ • ;._x u &gt;j 0 y , Jr ’ VX’; *'&gt; '-^- lw **C '-&gt;*'' * !j y.’i **»-^' fJUJt^j i.' u *o ‘■i, : -’-ii/ ^i jj'i** . ,N * -J . | - ~ ‘ i’ * / A M i. .• , ^ ^ s.,J^ K J c*.^* 'JaIxva • ^k; . V4 -x! ‘‘l ,. . jf^Ji f .• t - c r, IUU. W f. -J’.j ( l 0 J1 i \ / No. Sl^/g of 1355 Office of the Adviser to the G-overnuEnt, Bahrain i^ated 21st R/*hany 1355 July 11, 1936. H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- \ ^ith reference to your memorandum No. 262/B‘/2 dated 1st July 1936, I have instructed the secretary of the ^anamah Municipality to send you the minutes regularly in future. M.Y.— ^ I .•, #il IU^ , ft- «3b ,U v f 0 ' » i ' i *‘ i • J-wlU- H *c Iv.clv **■ JJ -I^ &amp; « ' LfrL ^ ^ Jy 1^ JUv-*O^L» !( ^»vt IL h .U C K,. v^.xLI lU^-, ^ *- , V ,u ^ J l &gt;- ' * 4|Mb iu |ki lu *’ * _ _ ^ - i «.U «LC A_rr T 1 --V, &lt;, °'’' ■&amp; au^, iM^f $'W INFc v ^-1 047! o-^' +&gt; ‘x ^ I *£,, tut^ ^ lli-4U»0 ili . V''* c-'^ u * 1 * iu * . »•*-}* . L» ‘ l C~v^ '*'- &lt;Jti li ^ Ly-^ * -^L. **• u 3 _ c^v&gt;“C. %***** vf7: 'Vs #7J */ '*tT ^ ^ AI V \ ) • 7 I li^V **c - • C sS-Vv llTt l‘A, - ^ ^ *i»** V L ^ c* Hi. *'*' Lj A' ■’■ j ‘ *! i4U^ • j — iU^L Jo«^ *£~r&gt; jJyr-' * - Hi-tj +Z* *\j Lu. iL.^di«r&gt; Ctt^ iU^L^ *i» * O ^ '*+**'‘- c _ , lU^tU^ lU^. rO^-^-C^O * IL ^ ILy ^ i ^ ^ ^ x ^ i &gt; ’ J vjj ^w ^ 'K. ' ' ^ Hj ^ ; 1^ . v!^ i *o*-s ' ,v 'V 1 ^ ^ A ® #jLI iU X^ *u^H. U ; Wu ^ lUjii •&lt; *&lt;1 i' it-j ^v. *^U v _ ^ J JLu tUL i l f JL v j ^ »^J -r wijJ -'4*i'^j * ^4^1 t^L *, if\.C-&gt; ‘ ^-*■‘•0 1124,0 IO;L-*^ j-^*' v. K. \j tilf t *'-*♦&gt; ^ N, * ^x -(? Agend a of the 10 th sit t ing on t he 25th Jamadial Awal,15 55. 1. 2 . 3. 4. Tax on huts . It has been dicided hjr the committee of budget that taxes on houses for rent will he one anna and a half per rupee on the rent and the Majlis held on 16th Safar 1355 confirmed that. There are huts of date leaves monthly rent of which is Rs.2/- and even less. Does the dicision include the huts laso ? If not, some taxes should he fixed on huts monthly the/rent of which is less than Rs.2/- so that the tax may he at leat annas three per month. Shailoh Hamad Road . The above road has been widened by cutting some fcBX houses and removing some electric poles from the diddle. Row it requires levelling. If Baladiah would ask the Bahrain Petroleum company through the Bahrain Government for the for two days truck,/the turning of the ground would be sooner. After that the coolies could level the ground. Artesian well of late Ra s hidA1 Hamar at Qadhebiah. Many people living in Qadhebiah complain that the water of the above well is dirty, and they drink water from it. The water is in a reservoir which has been roffed on the top. They say that there are many dead animals kxk in it and even they are to drink water from it. If Baladiah would raise the roof of the reservoir, clean it and keep it open it would be better. Drains and latrines . The drains and latrines of the city is in a bad condition and the dirts which are collected in them are very harmful. In civilized countries it is a practice that whenever digging or cleaning a drain, latrine or well in any place of the city, permission from the Municipality is obtained. The Government physician, Dr. Holmes has pointed after seeing some cases of suffocation while digging of cleaning . 7/hat is the opinion of the Majlis sbout this? Reading of the decision of the inspecting committee and the committee. 5t The nineth sitting held on Thursday the 11th Jamaial Awal, 1355. The sitting of the Majlis of Baladiah was held under the presidency of Shaikh Abdullah 'bin Shaikh TT sa A1 TChali^filic,officiating president, with all the mem^bers present. Among the absentees was Kaji kuhammad al Hamad A1 Qadhi on account of sickness and Haji Mohsen bin Ahmad Al Tajer on account of some personal business. 1. Boring In s truments . The Secretary infromed the committee that he boring instruments ordered for by the Baladiah have arrived, and their delivery will be taken from the Customs. The Majlis ap roved of this. 2 . Stray/ houses ( huts). The Secretary submitted that thsfere are many land ov/ners v/ho allow people to build huts in their proper ties v/hich present^ an ugly sight of the city. Moreover they do not pay any tax tothe Baladiah for the dirt and rubbish they are increasing in the city. The Baladiah is tire^of this. The Majlis is to take this matter in to consideration. The Majlis discussed the matter. The Majlis decided that ixndisrdxshEsidTnut Baladiah t-HtI will prevent landlords from renting -t-heir property to people unless they build good loo 1 ing Barastis and huts as is the custom. 3 # flame of the new western road . The Secretary informed the Majlis that in view of the new road v/hich is between the Hota of Ali Abul and the madhouse which has been completed, the Majlis should keep a name for it. The Majlis decided that the road should be named ,f Shaikh Muhammad bin T Tsa Al Hhalifah road”. 4 . House of Haji Jasem al T a itoon . The Secretary submitted that the above house was cut according to the decision of the Majlis held on the 12th Rabial Thani 1355. What is the opinion of theMajlis regarding payment of the money sanctioned? The Majlis decided that the money sanctioned should he paid, 5 • V/orlc of the Baladiah and proposals . The Secretary informed that in view of excessive work of Baladiah at present there is no necessity of new proposals until the work becomes light. 6, Reading of the decisions of the inspecting committee dated the 2nd Jamadial Awal 1355. 7. Reading of letters addressed to the Baladiah. A. Letter from Haji Muhammad bin Husain A1 Darazi dated the 9th instant informing that he has intended to go to Qatif leaving Haji Abdun Habi bin Muhammad Husain Arayed in his place during his absence. The Majlis accepted it with pleasure. B. Letter dat r d the 10th instant from Haji Abdul Husain bin Abdul Karim Busheri, contranctor of Baladia for cleaning. He wants the refund of Rs.600/ kept by him with Baladiah as security for cleaning. The Baladiah decided to refund the money from the deposit. C. Letter dated the 9th instant from Amar bin Abdur Rehman Abdul V/ahab as v ing for compensation for his shop which was demolished in the Colonel Barrett Road according to the decision of the Majlis held on the 21st Rabial Thhni 1351 . The Majlis decided that the matter will be looked into as to why the payment of the compensation has been delayed so long. D. Letter dated the 10th instant from Haji Sultan bin Abdur Rahmab Abdul Wahab A1 Khalifah, informing that Shaikh Abdur Rahman bin Ahmad Al removed Mehza T has not the varendah infront of his shop. The inspecting committee in their report dated the 14th Safar 1355 stated that Abdur Rahman must remove the varendah as he had no right to make it in tire front of the property' &gt; v m 'WSJ of another. The Majlis decided that Sultan should file a suit against Ahriur Rahman in the ^'ourt. E. Application from some of shopkeepers of the market asking BaladiaCto sprinkle water infront of their shops. The Baladiah has decided that water should he sprinkled in the market in hot days including ±k* even the the places where watercar cannot pass. F. Letter from Haji Muhammad A1 Hamad Al Qa-.^hi asking excuse for not attending the Majlis on account of sickness. The Jiajlis accepted his excuse. The Majlis dispersed hy order of the Officiating President at 3.30. Arabic. I ■I) r © © ^ Jj VI I i Jl ,^1^1 ^ • irooi^ J^VI 1 • &lt;jg^lr»Jl ^ c ^!;lk (r —1 Ck ^ (T &lt;y r*#^ c^JeoJl Jl jS~&gt;J\ C ^P pjU &amp;;1 *^ &lt; • ' x +*+ • viUJlt f- j/ aJI a^ ji^il (V^ Ch tj* —. w t^JJI &lt;j£*tl)l ij* t—ty 1 * * ^4 J ^1 ^JkJLjJl ^ ♦ ^L*Jl !• • dU JJ JL?-L&gt;- ajLc^I.&lt; 4^:11 ^ J JfJl «J • AL^b £♦ 4-^y 1 * • iJLjA aJ ^ /,! t/is-Jl * ^L?Ji ^ ^y jaJI c^IajJI j-|p X(f- (j'.J** (j* —C* v^a!?^! ij {/&gt; a^^L— ic^i+H (&gt;• MvyJU^ • A-jb^^y *U-U I r © I i&gt;* ^LJl £ty T 1 p.UL a^JI • cu^Ji vii) a^Lm &amp;y eU J^y^Jau; ^1 ^ai—»)1 ^ • J * r j*j*^ -M 1 0*^1 Ck O^-^ 4 *' — vi- Ajl^J ^Ul jJJJI a^jJI jJ *^&gt;-l ^ •V’ L^-^i^l d*^'^ I r d « 2&gt;»1 1 g;b&lt; 2S^A ^1 Uy &gt; • ^ ^ fbl J-*?&gt; J cT^J • M^xJl ^y JA^JI ^4JI ^ &lt;^«c o* jbxU r UI ^ o l i&gt; u 1 ^ iA-* a-^ — ^ • MJU J^**Jl J*^l-&gt;l j i;UJl |*W^^ d •UJLj Jjr-JI At-^^ d* • a^» La u£*i^ ^yJJl ^ X&gt;«4J1 A_*4 V i~A?J\ jy+&gt;- A#A^ JJL^t ^j^UJI «W&gt;J1 py V&gt;, A^^ ^ • a*&gt;m» ^y v_il^-&gt;jl • tj ip J- • * 1 ^i ^j, ui^ ^Jij fciut mUaJI iTranslation of letter No*3b9 dated the 28tii Jamadial Than!, 13bb corresponding with the Ib.^h September 1936 from tne Secretary, Manamah Municipality to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments. I beg to inform you that a proposal was made by Muhammad Al Hamad Al Oadhi, a member of the Majlis in the sitting held on the 26tn Rabial Thani 135b lor widening the Shaikh f Isa Road beginning from the northern extremity joining with the Goremment Road and ending at the house of Farukh. He stated that in fact it had become necessary to widen this road in view of the importance attached to it on account of greater number of vehicles passitg through it. The Majlis appreciated the proposal and agreed to widen the road alter an inspection by the inspecting committee. On Sunday the 19th instant an inspection was held by the committee consisting of Haji Haji * • ? Khalil bin Ibranim Al Muayed, Mohsen bin Ahmad Ai Tajejand Haji Ibrahim bin Muhammad Ahmadi.Shaikh Ishaq bin Abdur Rahman Al Khan and Haji Salman bin Majed Al Jishi were absent on account of their private work. The Majlis has decided that tne road should be at least 40 feet wide and cuts should be effected as under:- 1. b feet to be cut off from the western side of the Agency straight from north to south. 2. 3 feet to be cut off from the land of the Government Hospital straight from north to south. 3. b feet to be cut off from the houses of the Bahrain Government and its building from the eastern side, straight from north to south. 4. After this the road will surely be 40 feet broad. 5. The Majlis held on the 23rd Jamadial Thani, 135b has confirmed this. I send this for at your information. Usual ending.mmmmsa '■'V' rv }i» (&amp;J Agenda for the 11th sitting of the Majlis oi BalaQian ai ted Thursday the 23ru JaLiaaial Thani, 13ob. (io.j.b^j. 1 . Compirttive statement of income of Balaaiah for four months5- Last year. A. Income of Safar. 7204-9-11. 5o09-7-0 expenses ” 4710-5-9. 40^8-2-9 B. Income , Rabi,I 7785-12-0 50uo-i2-0 expenses ' ' 0088-5-3 2922-13-9 c. Income, Rabi,ii 7U5U-I4-0 4783-8-0 Expenses ” ” 7239-5-0 3o75-0-3 D. Income Jamah,!. 0325-15-0 5092-13-0 Expenses ” 8844-1-7 2989-11-0 Fire. As worksnops in Bahrain has^^increasea ana tne town is full of workshops ana garages at present, it is absolutely necessary to take precaution for the prevention of fire ana such other inciaenis. &lt;«e have the last instance at the garage of Khalil Kanoo. It is necessary for every owner to use nana lire extinguisher which is light for removing in garages, petrol goao.vns ana places where machines ana batteries are repaireu. Whoever wants to open a place like those should take permission from Balaaiah ana alter that he himself will be responsible for his place. 3. Maa house . In foreign countries the Municipalities take all possible care for lunatics as well as for tneir asylum ana convenience. In Banrin the house is very conjestea ana hot. The rooms are closed ana not good for health. Undoubtedly it will not help them in any way to recover ana to remain in rest. What is the opinion of the Majlis about sending the inspecting committee to look into their requirements?4. Planting trees on ti+e roads . • In accordanct- with tnc resolution passea on tne 27th Rabial Awal 1355 to make an estimate of plants to be planted and the value of ca^es lor the protection of the plants, the estimate nas oeen made lor two roaas, Shaikh iiamau Roan and Shaikh I/Iuhammao. Roau. Vne nuiubei Ox plants reuuirea is 28J ana the cages lor their protection will co^t Rs.l.8.10 each, if maae new. 5. Place fo r the new ice macnine . The place for tne new ice machine has been uuilt. ihe machine has been placea there ana working successfully. Tne Ma’lis is to visit the place for their satisfaction. tj. hew Fo rd lorry of Balaaian . On the 13th instant the Baladiah has receivea the new Ford lorry. It is just wh&amp;t Balaaiah wanted including the colour. It is of green colour and working at present. 7 . hxpirv of the time of t he inspecting uommi otee_ . have The Inspecting Committee ftas passed a long time in their offices. Thanks to them for tneir works rendered. It is necessary to appoint another committee. 8 . Reading of tne decisions of tne Inspecting Committee ana the committee.lOtn sitting of tne iiajlis of Jialaaiaii Held on I'Hursday ttie 2btn Jamaaial Awal,13bb. The Majlis of Baladiah, Manamah was held unuer the pres/ldency of Shaikh Abdullah Din f Isa Al Khaliiah, the acting President and the members were present. Among the absentees, Haji Hasan Al Abdul Aziz Al Ajaji and Muhammad Al Hamad Al Qadhi did not appear on account ol private work. Haji Ali bin Muhammad Kanoo on account ol his journey from Bahrain and Shaikh Isha^ bin Abdur Rahman a! Khan on account of ill health. Haji Salman bin Majed Al Jishi and Haji Husain bin Ali Kadhem were absent on account of private work. After the reading of the decisions of the previous Majlis and their confirmations, discussions started as follows 1. Tax on straw houses . The Secretary stated that there are houses of Saaf (date leaves) rents of which are less than Rs.2/-. Will the Baladiah charge tax on them at the rate of one anna and a half in the rupee or make a fixed rate of at least annas three on such houses? Ihe Majlis unanimously agreed that a house,monthly rent of which is less than Rs.2/-, should be charged annas three as Baladiah tax monthly and not less. Hence Baladiah will not accept tax less than annas three. 2. Shaikh Hamad Road . The Secretary informed that the road has been widened by cutting some houses and removing some electric poles which were on the road. Now it requires to be lavelleo. If Baladiah would ask the Bahrain Petroleum Company to lend their machine for scraping the ground , it would be nice, and then tne ground could be lavelled. The Majlis accepted this and asked Husain bin aII Yatim to request Mr. Skinner about it. Mr. Husain yatim immeodately spoke in tne phone to send the machine andand nelp Balaaiaii. Mr Skinner readily agreed ana tne Majlis thanked him. 3. Artesian well of late Rashid Hamar at ^uahebiah . The Secretary informea that the inhabitants of ^udhebiah complain about dirty water of the above well as they drink from it. The water is m a reservoir wnich is closed from all sides ana roofed. There are many dead animals in it. It would be betier if Baladiah would The Majlis accepted this and decided that a committee should inspect it first and khwa give their views. 4. Drains and latrines . The Secretary infromeu that tne conditions of drains and latrines in tne city are very dirty and extremely harmful. It would be better if permission would be taken from Baladiah at the time of digging or cleaning drams and latrines and wells at any place in the city. The Governement physician, Dr. Holmes pointed out that there were some cases of suffocation in tne city.on account of that, 'hat is the opinion of the Majlis ? The Majlis discussed on the matter and then decided that every one living inside the Baladiah limits should take permission from Baladiah before cleaning of tne places mentioned above especially for draifis, wells and latrines wnich are deep. 5. Heading of tne reports of the Inspecting Committee dated tne 23rd Jamadial ^wai 13b0. Tne Majlis agreed to tnis. 6 . Reading of letters addressed to tne Baladiah. i* Letter dated the 21st instant from Haji Ali bin Muhammad Kanoo saying tnat he intended to go for a change for two months and that ne appointed Muhammad bin iibdullan Juma his agent. The Majlis accepted this. B. From Haji Salman bin Majed Jishi for his absence on account of urgent work, me Majlis accepted his remove cleaning it. excuse.c letter dated the 24th instant from ShaiTch Ahdur Rahman h^n Ahmad A1 lehza T enclosing a copy of a letter addressed to Baladiah under his sig nature on the 18th Rahial Awal 1355 in connection with the verandah (Dalcajc) infront of the shop of Sultan hin Ahdur Rahman Ahdul Wahah A1 Khalifah and other things mentioned in it. The Majlis^the Secretary to produce the decisions passed in connec tion with Dakalc in the year 1353. The Secretary submitted the decisions and the Majlis read it. The Majlis confirmed the decision passed in the sitting held 4n the 7th Rabial Awal 1353. The Baladiah is to inform Abdur Rahman and Sultan accordingly. D. Letter dated the 24th instant from Shaikh Abdul Latif bin Saad, one of the Qadhis of the Sharatfeurt as-^cing Baladiah to turn their atten- to the artesian well near the Juma Mosque, the flow of which is very weak. Necessity requires a reservoir for the Juma Mosque. Could Baladiah make the well deeper so that the water will increase for the benefit of the public. The work will be a charit 1 ble one. The Majlis decided to refer the matter to the committee of budget.for their views. E. Letter dated the 24th instant from Mr. Muhammad Fhalil, Superintendent of the Land Department in connection with his conversation that took place with the Secretary Baladiah regarding the mosque of Abu Abham • He informs that it was Jafariah Waqf Department that put a lock on the said mosque and closed the door infront of it. The Majlis discussed over the matter and decided that the Inspecting Committe should inspect the Hammam and inform their views.No.10/603 F. Letter/dated the Slat instant regarding the Llidwife of Baladiah and her leave, and to pay her Rs.869/2/- being leave pay for three months and a half including cost of passage for the journey etc. The Majlis decided that she should be paid the amount according to the agreement between her and Baladiah. The Acting Presr'ent proposed that on account of heat the sitting of Baladiah might sit after one month from the date of this sitting. The Majlis approved of this. Khalil bin Ibrahim A1 Muayed proposed that write to the Sunni '7aqf Department to could Balad-’ah/repair the mosque in which Shaikh Jasem A1 Mehza f prays ? The walls of the mosq.ue are in bad condition and at any time may fall down. The Majlis ap roved of this. The Baladiah is to inform the said department about repairs. The Majlis dispersed by order of the Acting President at 3 0 T clocTc.^ / Agenda 1 'or tne 12tn sitting of tne Majlis of Baladian held on Thursday tne 8 th najao, 13bt»* 1&gt; Repairs of two piers . In accordance with the decision of the Majlis held on 22nd Jamadial *wal 13b4 regarding repairs of two piers in front of Government road where gutch ana stones kept , the Baladiah wish to repair them at present* 2* Income of the dug al Henmi for one year * Last year the Baladiah made a special place ior the sale of Henini water which cost Hs*837-1-0. The income received during the period of one year oating irom Ibth Jamadial fhani 1354 to 15th Jamadial ‘fhani 1355 is Bs*978-7-9. 3* tot Payment of the price of the new lorry (Ford ). * * * 4 5 In the 11th sitting the Majlis was informed about the receipt of the lorry. What is the opinion of Baladiah regarding the payment of the pricef 4. Building of Baladiah shop . The Baladiah has a shop in ^u^ al Hawawij which needs repairs in order to be rented. 5. Reading fcfcE of the reports of the committees. Sd/- Muhammad Saleh Shutar.11 til sitting of tiie ^ajlis of Balauiaii, nclci on Tiiursday, tiie 23rd «Jamaaial liiani, 13bt&gt;. file Majlis of Balaaiaii, Manamaii lie la unuer tne presidency of Shaikii -abaullaii bin Isa Al Kdaliian, Acting- Presiaent ana all tne members being present except Haji MuHammad ^.1 Hamaa a! i^aain on account ot ill-nealtn* A fter tne reading of tiie minutes of tne previous meeting and confirmation discussions took place as under 1 . Trial balance of expenses and incomes of Balaaiah P four months. A. Safar Income Rs.7204-9-11 uast yea r Rs .bU09-V-b ' Expenses ' 4Vlo-b-9 i? tt 4008-r2-9 B. Rabi.I Income 7 V 8 b-12-0 tt it bObo-12-O ' Expenses oo88-b-3- it ft 2922-13-9 c. Habi.fi Income VObO-14-O it it 4788-8-8 ' expenses 7239-b-0 ft it 307b-0-3 D. Jamaa 1. Income b82b-lb-b m tt b093-13-b tf expenses 8344-1-7 tt it 2989-11-6 It was attested by tne committee of accounts. The Acting President sealed it and members of the Majlis confirmed it. 2. Fire . The Secretary informed tne question of worksnops, garages etc. and petrol godown and places lor repairing mac nines and bauery etc. It is absolutely necessary to take necessary precaution to prevent accidents ana fire etc. Coula Balauian compell mentioned all owners of places axxxkaM above to use hand fire-nxtmg- uisuers wUicii are lignt for removing from one place to another. Secondly one who wishes to open a place mentioned above should obtain permission from Baladiah. The Majlis approved of tms ana decided that all steam owners of sucn places must place^nand iire-extinguisners and tins full of sam. ine places for repairing machines kerosene or etc. shoula not be near/jpetro godown out in aTranslation of agenda for thelSth meeting to be held on Thursday the 1st Thai Qada 1355(14.!• 37). 1) . Rain water and the destruction of the roads. Some of the roads have been destroyed ov/ing to the rains which fell last month especially a portion of Shaikh Sir Hamad Road and Shaikh ktahaamad Road t which became full of water and nobne could pass. The Baladiyah did their best and made the place dry and elevated it with 'Fashti 1 stones to the height of one foot. We will have to thank the Bahrain Petroleum Co., also for kindly helping the Baladiyah by having stones carried on their lorries from the shore to the place until the road became suitable for passage. This is one of the roads damaged by water. 2) . Baladiyah Office. fr-ost of the lower walls of the Baladiyah building are in a ruined state and thus dangerous. It would be suitable i'he B a i a diyah tatfie early steps to have them reoaired. 3) . The huts which spoil the view of the town. In past years the Government and the Baladiyah disallowed the erection of huts at the northern side of the city front - from the western to the eastern side - . The M ajlis should, therefore, stick to this decision and order for the removal of any hut erected on Government road and Prior Road. 4) . Bakers in the markets. fn view of the increased number of bakeries in the markets and the use of flaming fire which causes fires, the Majlis should consider this point. 5) . Car stand in the middle of the market. Phe Baladiyah should fix a special place near the market or in the middle of the market to be used as a stand taxi cars as too many cars stop in front of shops and thus for Mock the way. It is desirable to cars as in other modem countries. -ix a special place for such Nowadays our town has I■''“N ZW advanced, the things have increased and the work became wider to such an extent that it is necessary to enact further rules. 6) . Expenses and income in connection with the ice-machine Income fc.8322/7/9. Expenses.. .Rs.5392/11/9 approximately besides aother odd expenses spent by the Government which have not yet been adjusted, such as pay of attendeants of the machine etc. for this yean. 7) . A new pier for stones. I find it necessary to construct a new pier on the sea-shore, near the western pier for ^uss’ as the placing of stones on the sea road,as is at present,spoils the view of the road and blocks the way, especially the bi^ motor-c ars. 8) . To read certain reports. *********,!'* * \Minute of the 15th sitting of Manamah Baladiyah Majlis held on Thursday the 20th Tha’ban 13556th Nov., 1936). 1) . Income of p 'aladiyah for six months ^.43110-10-0. Last year f s ' 25418- 1-6. Expenditure of Baladiyah for six months....' 39818-13-9. Last year’s ' 20127-10-1. Taeh in Bank and in Treasury unto the’ end of Jamad Thani, 1355. ' 23140-14-1. Last year ' 23969-15-9- 2) . The bringing of water on carts from f Al Sunaidiq. The Police have prevented water carriers from bringing water from al Sunaidiq as the wheels of their carts have- destroyed the public road and because they are apt to collide with the large cars owing to the narrowness of the read. After discussion by the Majlis, they decided that this •prevention should bettopped but that the Baladiyah should consider widening the road from near the garden of Yusuf bin Abdulah al Lhatur and that the Committee should carry out an inspection on the water place and on the widening of the road. The cut should be effected either from the southern side of Haji Yusuf bin Abdullah al Lhatur’s garden from east to west or from his ’jubar’ which is situated to the south side of the road. He should be compensated with a piece of land adjacent to his garden but if this is not possible, he may be paid for the portion which is to be cut off and which will be debited to Government. 3) . A letter from Haji f Ali bin Abdullah Abul. The Secretary put up the letter over which discussion was adjourned during the last meeting, '•‘•he Majlis went into this matter fully and then the President decided, to which the members approved, that Haji Ali is to be informed in writing as to why he sent the letter to the Baladiyah without any address. If he did that through an oversight, the Majlis will pardon him but if he did it purposely, the Baladivah can make another arrangemnt with him.4) Lights in the street during Ramadhan month r ihe Secretary asked the Majlis if they considered keeping the lights in the streets on during the nights of Ramadhan, as usual. This has been anuroved. 5). The holding of sittings during Ramadhan. The Secretary said that normally no sitting is to be held during Ramadhan. Ihe Majlis decided that no sitting is to be held except for urgent matters, t). Reports of the Committees. Ihe Secretary read the reports dated 10th and 15th instoN 1 he report dated 10th instant was sanctioned by the Mailis. That dated 15th instant in connection with the construction of the wall of Thawardas Janimal’s amarah has been the subject of different views. Some adhered to the went report of the Inspecting Committee, others / against itahd&lt;de manded that the wall should be demolished, according to the Baladiyah laws. There has been a lengthy discussion and ■ argument. Thereupon the President suggested that the whdle Majlis should inspect the place in question together with the Secretary and then every one can say what he thinks. The final decision will be subject to the majority of votes. 7). Owing to the fact that the time is up, the President j i , suggested that the Majlis should disperse after the reports over the suggestions of Baladiyah are completed and the report* v of the Committees had been read. Reading the letters is to be adjourned till the next meeting. The Majlis dispersed at 5 O’clock Arabic.TRANSLATION. z.r 4 Agenda for the Manamah Baladiyah meeting which v.i 1 .' 1 - Le held on Thursday the 15th Thul ^ada 1355(28th January 1937) 1*. ^ ^ * + * l). Statement of income and expenditure of the Baladiyah for four months, i.e., Rajah, Sh^ban, Ramadhan and Shawal 1355. 8 . Income of Rajab.... DS .6310-2-7. Last year. 5106-6-6. Exoenditure ' .... ** 7913 -6-0. ' ' ft 3532-7-0. Income of Shaban... 5552-7-10. ” ' ft 4812-15-6. Expenditure ” ... Tt 6048-11-10.” ti 3692-7-6. Income of Ramadhan. ft 7814.11.0 ” ” tt 3479-7-6. Exoenditure ” . ft 5010-13-9. ” ” tt 3517-5-6. Income of Shawal... ft 6237- 7-0. ” if 5143-12-6. Expenditure ,f . . . tf 5194-9-4. ” ” tt 4160-12-6. A ■v 2) . Completion of the opening of Barrett Road. During previous meeting, it was decided to open this road which should run to the southern side. The LajliHJ B is to take up this question. I * 3) . Sale of keroseh oil in the markets. In accordance with the suggestion of the member rla.ii Muhammad al Hamad al Qadhi about the question of the mP sale of kerosene oil in the markets which is a great cause } for the occurence of fires, the Baladiyah should look into this matter. 4) . Baladiyah Garden water stream. The Paladiyah have already spent a considerable amount of money on the water stream which they have continuously been cleaning but this trouble by the Baladiyah and the spending of money go in vain as the stooning of water in the stream is not due to dirts but it is due to the fact that the stream itself is not properly dug. It is low in many places and high on other places which causes the stoppage of water. The Ralediyah have always been incurring two losses: by opening it and cleaning it and by reclaiming the road which gets spoilt % 9 on account of opening the stream. If the Baladiyah spend K| on it once fo^ all and debit the espenses to some fund, it [ would have been better. Now a great portion of the stream f has been uncovered by the Baladiyah pending the orders of ff the Majlis.* J 5) . Two lights for- the new Car Stand. The new Car Stand, near Prior Road i lights on two poles. 6) . Increase of lights in some streets. I find it necessary at present to have two lights fixed on the pole which is near the place of Haji v usuf Fakhro and on the pole which is near the Baladiyah Gardens on the south side. 7) . Reports of the Committee. hMinutes of the 16th meeting of Manamah Baladiyah held on i'hursday the 1st 1‘hul Qada 1355^14.1.37,). Meeting held under the presidency of Muhammad bin Mubarak al Fadhil, on behalf of the president who was sick and in the presence of the members. Three of the members were absent due to some reasons. 1 ) . Rain water and the ruinine of raads. The Secretary reported that he repaired a portion of Shaikh Sir Hamad Hoad and Shaikh Muhammad Hoad which were flooded l with rain water, and that the Bahrain Petroleum Company assisted in the matter. The Majlis thanked the Baladiyah for their efforts and the Bahrain Petroleum Company for their kind assistance. 2) . The building of Baladiyah. The Majlis decided that early steps may be taken to jpovl iw- ^ have the lower v/alls of Baladiyah office repaired. 3) . The huts which spoil the visv- of the town. The Majlis decided that no huts should be built on the city front on the northern side from east to west and that no timber, reeds and date branches should be accumulated on these roads. That no one should store such articles in a walled place without the instructions of the Baladiyah. The Adviser referred to the decisions passed in the previous meetings that land-lords who own properties situated on the Covernemnt Hoad should not erect a building without first t ing submit/a plan for the proposed building to the Baladiyah for inspection who have the op^tion of approving it or otherwise, ihe Majlis decided that this may be adhered to and that an 'Alan should oe published dealing eTthis subject. Ctae of the members Haji Aii bin Muharnnad ^anoo submitted two suggestion. First that the Adviser may be asked whether the Government are willing to let the small pier which is situ; to the east of the new Customs Building be used for timber which comes from abroad and then distributed to various pl s The Advise agreed to this suggestion. Secondly, that lane251 ,2^ landlords who own properties on Government iioad ma^^ be permitted to build, as far asltfiey can,like the usual buildings of the town using materials such as stones, lime and cement and that the Baladiyah have the only right of objecting to the type of such buildings so that they may not be in such a way that they spoil the view of the town, ihe Majlis and the Adviser approved this suggestion. Al*- Bakeries in th e towr&gt;&gt; Tne question of the bakeries in the bazars was put up by the Secretary. She Majlis decided that bakeries should not be made in the bazars under roofs made of reeds and date- palm sticks. Those which are in the town and made into huts are also affected by this decision. Bakeries should only be made in places built with stones, mud and lime and the roofs should be high from the surface of the oven over which two plates of 'chinku’ iron should be kept. 1'imber for the use of one or two days should be kept in the bakeris at a time and no fire should be kept in the oven at night. Any negligence will render the offender liable to be produced to the Court for punishment accroding to law and he will be prohibited by the Baladiyah from plying this profession any more. An 'Alan is to be issued by the Baladiyah giving therein one month's time for compliance with this order after the expiry of which the Baladiyah shall arrest defaulters and take them before the Court. As regards the question of keeping kerosene oil in the bazars raised by the member Haji Muhammad al Hamad al Wadhi, the Majlis postponed this question till next meeting. —th e market.. The Secretary suggested that a car stand may be made for the motor cars of those who come marketing and pointed out a Place near the Hawawij market for the purpose and suggested a a shop situated there property of the Baladiyah may be emo ished. fhe Majlis decided that the Inspecting Cormdttee2 r&lt;/ &gt;o 6) . £x pe nditure and income of ice. Income Rs.8822.7.9. Expenditure... .F5.5392.11.9. appr. rhere are other expenses made by the Government such as salaries of those who attend on the factories etc which have not yet been paid. 7) . A new pier for stones. The Majlis accorded their sanction to the construe tier! of a new pier on the sea shore, northern side, near the pier which is being used for lime, to be used for stones. The Majlis requested the adviser to have the Government accept the expenses for filling up this place as an act of help towards the Baladiyah, to which he agreed. The Adviser asked the Majlis to have a committee of experts estimate the cost of filling up this place and then the Government informed accordingly. 3). Becit a l of reports. The Majlis approved the reports dated 20th Shaaban 25th Shaaban, and 29th Shawal 1355 which were read over by the Secretary. the tenure of the Inspecting Committee. The following persons have been elected as members of the new Inspecting Committees- 1. Haji Mihsin bin Ahmad al Tajir. 2. Haji Ahmad bin Muhsin bin Sallum. 3. Haji Muhammad Jamal K^unji. 4. Haji Ibrahim bin IHihammad Ahmadi. 5. Khwajah Mi r Baud Roben. 101* —Big,,fpllowing let£&amp;r£ received ari( j r ead oveT ^ Xl) Utter Wo.963/23 dated 10th Ramadhan 1355 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government intimating that H.E.Shaikh Sir Hamad passed his orders for the payment of Ps.2000/- from his persona! purse and Pi. 2000/- from Government funds to the victims of the fire. He(Adviser)said that this amount or a part of it should be paid to the poor people whose shops and belongings were burnt by the fire, not according to the real valued the goods lost but according to the state of poverty of the persons whose goods were destroyed and who have no other me ans fo r i iv ingThe Majlis thanked His Excellency the Shaikh and the Government for this donation and decided that the Finance Committee should distribute this amount and the Secretary is to record the number of the victims and submit the same to the Committee. tb)Letter No.782/6 dated 24th Shawal 1855 from the Mviser saying that H.S.Shaikh Sir Hamad has agreed to let the triangular piece of land situated between the Amarah of Haji Abdun Nabi bin Ahmad 3 u sheri and Prior Road be used as a Car Stand for taxi cars. This is being used temporarily and the question of its sale to the Baladiyah is under discussion. The Majlis thanked His Excellency and his Adviser for their kind efforts. (c) Letter No.1137/8 dated 28th Shawal 1855 from the Adviser suggesting that the maximum speed for cars within the limits of the Baladiyah should be 30 miles instead of 20 miles outsid the town and 20 miles inside the town in all the roads situated between the houses. That, if this suggestion is passed by the Majlis, he will do what is necessary to control th? speed of cars by making police tricks. The Majlis approved' his suggestion. Haji Ali bin ^bhammad A^noo, one of the members, suggested that kilometres may be used for the speed of cars instead of miles as now-a-days most of the cars in •Bahrain used kilos. The Adviser and the members agreed to this. (d) ijetter dated 8th Shawal 1355 from Shaikh Ishaq bin Abdur Rahman al Khan, one of the members, suggesting the following:» 1. The introduction of a complete fire brigade. 2. A special pipe should be fixed on every artesian well for the use of the fire brigade. 3. The creation of a fire Tarig-ade staff. not b * • oi&lt;i 5 - “•ouK KVfSKiJ; £“ r 1 ?* 1 * r a. -oof made high and plastered with cement^to ^ he . floor b e connected for the puroose of washing n! plP6S arS to be The ulajlis approved all the above. As regards items Nosisi zss Nos*l and 5, the Adviser said that order for the same has been placed and one fire brigade and three ’chabrahs' for the fruit market will arrive shortly. As regards item No.3, it is necessary to have a trained fire brigade staff. (e)Letter dated 12th Shawal 1355 from the member Haji Khalil bin Ibrahim al T/uayyad suggesting the following ten itmes 1. Opening of the Royal Road v/hich may extend to Has Rumman Ro a d. 2 . Repairing Prior Road. 3. Electric poles should be fixed on Prior Road and Ras Rumman Road. 4. Electric poles should be fixed in the midst of the roads and not on the sides. J! 0 , draw attention of the Government to make sides for -u iairag Road both on the northern and southern sides. 6. flfhile going, motor cars should use Prior Hoad and while comins?- they use Sovemment Road. coming* 7. To widen Shara Tujjar Road. 3. To expedite the study of the lavra. 9. To ask the 3 0 vernment to make four wings for Miharrao Pier +wa on northern side and two on southern side. y 05113 *2 ^er, two 10 ‘to sir onf 11 ' 3 ° n th ® Wing ® rnentioned in 9 above for the people The Majlis thanked him for these suggestions Re. item 'o.l. the Baladiyah decided to connect R a s Rimman Road with %ra Road instead of the Royal Palace Hoad. 2. The Baladiyah have taken the necessary steps. ' 3. i'he Majlis approved. '4. The Majlis disapproved. 5 * Thls wiU be done the road is complete. ' 6 . Russes of the Bahrain Petroleum Co., should use Prior Hoad for their coming and going. Other cars should use Government Road. ” ?• The Baladiyah at present have to sufficient funds for cutting the huge buildings situated on both sides of this Road but they are prepared to demolish the waqf shop situated there whan they find another suitable shop in lieu of it. pi257 7? ^ He* item No*8. i'he Majlis approved. n rt n 9« ^ajlis and the Adviser approved. M ' 10. The Majlis approved this but it cannot be carried out till the road has been completed. Ce) Letter dated the 19th Lha'aban 1355 from Haji Sulaiman al Hamad al Bassam inviting Baladiyah's attention to fix a light near Abdur Razzaq's iiosque in Mahalat Fadhil. i'he Majlis decided that the Inspecting Committee should inspect the °7rt and submit their report* (f) Letter dated 29nd Shawal 1355 from Haj i Mihammad al Nakhudha asking for condensation in lieu of the portion of land usurped by the Baladiyah for Has Rumman Road which he claims to be his property. fhe Majlis decided that he should produce the title deed of this land in the Baladiyah and after investigations,the Majlis will pass their decision on the matter. (g) Letter dated the 10th Shawal 1355 from Ibrahim bin 'Ali al Jodar compalining against one ’Ali al Kumaish that he pretends to be a broker for cows appointed by the Baladiyah for this purpose and collects fees from buyers of cows in Suq al Arba'a and gives a lot of trouble to the people. The Majlis enquired from the Secretary .whether the Baladiyah appointed this individual ts broker for cows to which the Secretary replied in the negative and added that/it is proved that this man actually behaved in • this way, the Baladiyah will complain against him to the Court. 1 he Majlis agreed. (h) Petltl0n fl,om sever al persons who have places in the market requesting the Baladiyah to make a roof for the way over their Places, the Majlis decided that the Baladiyah should first ask the owners of the properties sitauted on both sides of the way to r a roof for their properties, if they did so, well and good otherwise the Baladiyah will do it and recover the charges from * them as usual. (i) Letter dated the ISth Shawai -p . aWal 1355 fr0L1 Za ^ Haidar al Banna informing the Baladivah th e + . ' “** “* a '-* 1 ' M« house p « r on ,piece of land adjacent to his house and that this piece of land has recently been sold and he fears that the buyer may construct a building on this land and thus block the passage of the drains i'he Majlis decided that Zayer Haidar has no right to this but the owner of the land has full liberty to do whatever he likes with his property. Zayer Haidar should, therefore, change the site of the drains. (j) Bill No.42/55 *.B. dated 27th Rajah 1355 from the State Engineer asking for payment of P?.653/10/- on account of cost of construction of the new ice-machine and pay of caretakers. 1‘he Majlis ordered for the payment of this amount. 11). After the recital of the above reports etc the member Haji Khalil bin Ibrahim al Maa'yyad requested the Majlis to say a few words in connection with *Kindness to Animals’ project and requested the members to have this humanitarian project brought into existence. He stated that he met the Secretary of the Society of L 0 ndon and India, in the Baladiyah office where the Baladiyah B e cretary was also present. I'he Majlis unanimously agreed that such a society may be made and thanked Haji Khalil or his kind attention in supporting this good project. The Adviser suggested that the Society which is going 1 t0 be made in 3 ahrain may communicate with those of London and India and that he will have the instructions received from the secretary of the Society translated and sent to the Baladiyah. &amp; 3. The Majlis dispersed at 7 o’clock A ra bic by the order \ of the Acting President.■MM*TRANSLATION* Agenda tor tne 19in meeting of Manaman Balaaiyan i/Iajlis to be held on Thursday tne Idtn nhul Hijjan 13bb(2t).2.3Vj 1) . PLACING OF FULL WOOD ON GOVhRNMENT ANL PRIOR ROaDS . The President postponed the question of fuel wood during tne past meeting. This question may now De discussed again. 2) . G OST OF TEL NEW IQh MACHINE. The total cost of tne machine and tne expenses incurred thereon whicn has been paid by tne Government vide their letter No.1380/8/ dated 9th ~hul hijjah 13bo is ns.SbVb/?/-^ The Baladiyah shall pay this amount according to tne Government’s letter No.587/8 dated bth Jamad Thani 13b£ as agreed upon. 3 j. EXPENSES ON OPENING MUHARPulQ ROAL AT RAS Kim AN. A sum of Ks.7804/13/9 has been spent by tne Baladiyah lor the above road which has been remitted by the Government by a cheque and credited to Laladiyan’s account. Tnere are still minor expenses on this road sucn as re-building of women’s ’matam’ which hashot yet been completed. / 4J. THh MIXING OF BARLEY FLO U R WITH nilL AT FLOUR. Tne above question is put up again for discussion as it was adjourned during the past meeting. 5) . SHOPS OF T KL HEIRS OP SHAIKH ABLUR RAHMAN BIN ABDUL NAHiiAB. Regarding tne reports of Baladiyah on tne subject of compensating them, a report dated 2btn Lhul . t aca 1351 and another dated 26th Safar 1352 were traced and will be read over to you. 6) . HEALING OF REPORTS.M ZB TRANSLATION Minutes of tne ivtn meeting of Manamaii Balauiyan meeting nela on Thursday tiie Ibtn Lhul 13bb(88.1.3V) ihe metting was nela m tne presence ol tne Presiaent ana the members of whom Haji Hasan al Ajaji was aosent owing to his illness. Ij . Account of income ana expenaiture for * months. These accounts are for tne months of Rajaby ona’ban, Ramaanon ana u hawal 13bb. ■‘■hey nave been examinea by tne Budget Committee ana passea by tne Presiaent ana the members. 2) . Completion of opening Barrett Road. The Secretary statea that it nas been aeciaea in the past meetings to have this roaa opened upto to tne southern siae of the /town. The majlis aeciued tnat tne Budget Committee shoula inspect the places to be cut and to state the amount of compensations. 3) . Sale of kerosene oil in tne markets. The Secretary made a reference to the suggestion of tne member \ Kaji Muhammad al Hamad al ^adhi on the subject of tne sale of kerosene oil m tne markets which causes fire. Tne -ajiis, after going through tms matter, aeciaea that/seller of kerosene oil should not use fire in his place, nor smoke in the place where there is kerosene oil, nor to store more than the quantity fixed, he should also put on the uoor of his shop a sign boaru bearing the expression T Smoking not aliowec r . The guarus who watch the market at night are not to make fire in tne market. The Balauiyah should first issue a notice to the sellers of kerosene oil and then write to tne Government and tne Amir asking t^em not to aliow the watchmen to use fire m the markets and that whoever does not comply witn this order will be reported to the Government. 4). Balaaiyah Garden water ch a nnel. Tne Majlis aeciaea tnat tne Balauiyan shoula inform the Government about the state of tne Balahiyan garaen water channel requesting them to ask the Bahrain Petroleum Company to send one of tneir engineers to inspect tne water stream ana give his aavice about it. thebj. Two liffii t s to be put at tiie new Car Stand. The Secretary pointed out the necessity of having two light points put on two poles at the new Car stand on Prior Road. The Majlis approved this and decided that the Baiaaiyah should ask the hlectric department to do tne needful. SJ. Installation of more light points m tne streets. The Secretary mentioned that two places require light points; one is near the building of Haji Yusuf Fakhro ana the other on the pole to the south side of the two amall gardens in the vicinity of the American nospital. The Majlis approved that light points may be installed accordingly. 7J. To read report s of th e C ommittee. The Secretary read out the reports dated 13th nhul ^aua 13bb and the Majlis accorded them with their approval ana decided that the Government should be informed accordingly. 8j. The following letters receiveaby the Balauiyan were reaa:- (aj. NQ.4/bb dated 9th instant irom the State Engineer asking the Baladiyah.to shift the old ice machine which is at present st the Power house to the new place where the new ice machine is. The Majlis agreed to this. (b) . No.b/5h dated 13th instant from the State Engineer suggesting to the Baladiyah to appoint someone to oe run ana to do all the repairs to the ice machines wno may he held responsible etc. The Majlis decided that the Baladiyah shoulai lirst ask the .engineer about the amount of pay required by such? man ana secondly during winter time when the machineaare not at work who will pay his salary. On the receipt of a reply from the nnginner, the Majlis will decide the matter. ( c ) * Letter dated 27td Shawal 13bt&gt; from Mir tjutbuddin, fuel wood broker infomring the Baiaaiyah that certain fuel wood sellers whose places were burnt out on the Bna Ramaahan QAe a sum ol Ks.43/lb/10 on account ot luel wood brokerage aue to the Baladiayh. The Majlis aeciaea that enquiries snoula first be made in tins connection . If it appears tnat they haa paid the brokerage to tne broker, then the latter snould in turn pay it over to tne Baiaaiyah; if otherwise tne brokerage £*7? O' citea above snoula be waved. (d) . Letter dated 12tii Lhul ^aaa. 13bb i’rom Saliii bin Abdullah bin Salih applying i'or a contract ot the iruit market lor a period of one year for a sum of hs.oJO/- only, etc. The xmajlis decided that the fruit market snoulo not be given on contract. (e) . Letter dated 13th Dhul i^ada 13bb from Salih bin ’Abdullah al Omani applying to take the contract of brokerage for the piers of lime, stones and sana against a sum of its.60/- per annum. The Majlis refused to give the places on contract to anybody. (f) . Letter dated Ibth instant from naji Aodun Nabi bin! Ahmad Bushin asking for permission to make a balcony for his property on Government Road. The ^ajlis allowed him to oo so. (gj. Letter dated Ibtn Lhul Qada 13bb from ’Abuur Razzaq bin Shaikh f Abdur iiatu^an T Abdul d'ahhab asking for compensation in lieu of his shop used Barrett hcao and alleg ing that he holds a letter from the Balauiyan in this connection. The Majlis decided that he should produce tnis letter for inspection. (hj. setter from Haji liasan al ’Abdul Aziz al ’Ajaji apologizing for nor being able to attend the meeting. His apology has been accepted as he was sick. 9. The member Haji T Ali bin Muhammad Kanoo suggest-' ed that tne balance amount available in the Baladiyah^s treasury in the name of the victims of 10th Munarram 13b4 may be spent on the eastern Mosque which is in urgent need for repairs, ihe Majlis refused to accept this suggestion as the Baladiyah have a letter No.216/1334 dated 24th Dhul Hijjah 13b from the ^adhis saying that the amount should be distributed amongst those who had received previous payments. 10. The Secretary read out the report sent by Captain A.R.Watson of 1 the society of prevention of cruelty to animals’ through the Adviser. Tne Majlis thanked the Captain for his report. 11• The Majlis dissolved by the order of the ) Presidnnt at 6 o’clock ^rabic.Minutes ot tiie Ititn sitting 01 Hanaman Balaaiyan neia on Tiiursaa} tne 29tn Dhul Qada 13bb(11.2.1937) The Majlis nela tneir meeting m tne presence ot tne President and all tne members. They discussed tne loiiowmg:- 1 ). Jjisjp_ec t i_ons_ c_9Trj_ed_ _oAt. - D XA n A .AiA c l 1 J. a . n n A report nas oeen suomittea oy tne Secretary aoout tne sanitray inspection carried out on oakeries during tne montn wmcn was accorded witn approval. 2y_. Tax i lar es. 'me Majlis decided tnat tne Budget committee snouid study tne tares ol taxi cars ana give tneir opinion wmcn will oe submitted beiore tne Majlis lor sanction. 3). Th e mi xing of w heat _llo_ur witn barley fl our. The Secretary reported tnat there are in the town some persons who deal in flour but they mix barley ana wheat when they want to have it ground at the mill in Bahrain. The ^ajlis discussed this matter and then adjourned it till the next meeti 4;. Re-publishin g 3 ; som e of the i mportant Bal aaiya n _^Ala_ns_._ The Secretary stated that the Balaaiyah had published several ’Alans about the tranquility of the public ana observance of Baladiyah rules and that tney will attract attention if they are re-publishea. The Secrttaryms asked to read such -Alans to the Majlis ana the following were reaa:- Nos.35/l3bh, 36/l35b, 38/l3bb, 38/13bb, 39/l3bb, ana 40/13bb. The Majlis approved all of them except No.38/1355 which prevents tne public from placing building materials on We streets and roaas for more than 10 days whether tne building is under erection or not. The i-^ajlis discussed this matter anu decided unanimously that if the work is going on, the owner of such a building can place building materials on the streets or roans near his place in a way that it will not prevent the passage of motor cars and passers-by. 5j. Husain bi n Haji T Ali bin Nasrulla h. Regarding the sum of ns.600/- said to be deposited in his favour in tne Balauiyah treasury on account of compensationI for a piece of land belonging to bis grandfather tne late Hasan bin Nasrullab, which was asurped by the Balaaiyah, a search was made in the records of the year 1343 onward, but no mention of the said amount has been found. No mention was also lound in the proceedings of the meetings. ihe Majlis asked for the prodoction of the record oi proceedings for inspection. This has been done but still nothing has been found in favour of the abovementioneo person. The Majlis decided that he has no right to claim any money etc. from the Baladiyah. 6 j. Kind treatment to animals* The Secretary stateu that such a society may be brought into existence. The ^jlis decided that tne Govern ment may be asked to form such a society. 7). To read reports. The Secretary read out the reports dated the 19th and 20th instant to which the Majlis approved. The President saia that the Baladiyah should enquire from Shaikh T Abdullah bin T lsa al Khalifah about tne price of the piece of land which is being used as a car stand and which belongs to the heirs oi Salman bin Duai T j and also about the price of snops which are under his supervision if he desires to sell them to the Baladiyah. On the receipt of a reply from him, the Majlis is to consider the question. 8;. The following letters received by the Baladiyah were read: (so* Letter No.M.M./b/hb dated 26th instant from the State Bngineer to the Bahrain Government which is a reply to Balaoiyah f s letter No.628/l3bS dated lYth instant about the pay of a mechanic for the ice-machine. His pay is to be paid by the Baladiyah and the Bahrain Government. The Baladiyah is to pay him as long as the ice-machines are working and one month alter they nave been stopped. His pay for the remaining months is to be paid by tne Bahrain Government. The amount ol tiie pay is hs.IbO/- per mensem anu he is to be proviuea with free quarters anu entitleu to 6 weeks leave each year witn leave salary and passage from India and back together with medical care etc. ‘ihe Jajlis approv223 li (b). Letter No.208/l35b datee the 23th instant from liaji Abcul ’Aziz al ^usaibi ana brotners in reply to Balauiyah’s letter No.649/13bb aatea the 20th instant enquiring irom the Baladiyah about the question of timber saying that this word is construes to mean all kinds of timber . He requests that the position may be explained to him. The member Kaji Khalil bin Ibrahim al ^lua’yyaa tiitreupon came ior^vara ana stated that the Baladiyah did not decide, in the meeting held on 1st instant, that fuel wood should not be put on Government Hoad and Prior Road, but they decided that aate-palm sticks, reeds and ’karab’ only should not be put on the said roads. Kaji \ ’Ali Kanoo ana Kaji Husain bin ’All Kaohum corroborated his statement. The Secretary ,then read out item 3 of the report in connection with the question of timber after which tne President suggested that the matter should be postponed till next meeting. 9. The member Haji Muhammad bin Mubarak ai Fauhil suggested that before publishing any ’Alan, the Baladiyah should submit a copy thereof before the Majlis for correction,atleration etc./ and then issued His suggestion was met with approval. 10. Tne member haji Hasan al 'Abaul 'Aziz al 'Ajaji suggested 'J that the Baladiyah should get their ’Alans printed at the press ana then distributed amongst the public so that tne people may read them. His suggestion was accorded with approval. (c;. Letter dated 11th instant from Abdullah ana Ibrahim sons of Muhammad imlaih asking for compensation in lieu of their shop which was demolished for Lharkh Hamad Roaa ana that the piece of land given them by the aalaaiyan is not enough for his family. The iwajlis decided that the Budget Committee should inspect report* (d) . From Kaohum al Sindhi asking for compensation in lieu of the portion cut off his house for Shaixh hamau Road. The Majlis decided that the Budget Committee should inspect and report. (e) . From Haji Muhammad al Kakhuaha replying to Baladiyah’s letter No.o33/l3bb of 13th instant requestingMB ^6 1 h tiiat a committee may be nominated to inspect his lana. Tne Majlis deciaea that the Budget Committee shoulu inspect the 1 -i lana and make enquiries about it. (f). From Khan Sahib Haji Yusuf bin Ahmad Kanoo,CIE, in reply to Balaaiyan T s letter ho.ooB/lBbo enclosing a plan for an upper building on his property situateu on Government E Hoaa. Ihe Majlis approved of the building accoraing to the plan which he submitted. i* 11. The meeting was dissolved by the oruer oi the President at 6 o^lock arabic.ZW z°v r —» Translation of agenda for tiie SOtii^itting ^nicn will be held on Thursday the ^8tn Dhul Hijjah 1355(11.3.37). 1). i ncome a.na expenaiture of Mananiaii Jlaniyah i'or Uie montn of hhui ^aoa 15bb. 2). Banarnah Bakers. As the ^ajlis, in the past meeting, postponed tne aiscussion over tne question of Baharnan bakers wno sell yellow bread at more than 16 loafs of breaa per ruba*, the matter is re-submit tea. 3j. d a ter pipes for arawin/; water from the gara^n of T Abauiian bin ^abur 'to the Lunat i c Asy iuia* The distnace requires oOO feet of pipes one inch in aiameter at a cost of iis.2u0/~. 4) . The frilling Machine., In accordance with the orders of the Adviser, the machine is working on tne aovernment artesian well at Budai^i* in oraer to make it deeper. 5) . Trees for the Baladiyah ^araen and tne roads. The Adviser has ordered from abroad various kinds of trees which arrived lately, ^e has been kina enough to present about 19b trees for the garden ana the roaas. 6;. To read reports. 7). expiry of the period of the Inspecting oonmittee. Income RsJ2454/l2/3 plus Is.bJOU/ granted by the Government for the filling up of the water pool. La&amp;t year’s income was Iis.4414/8/6. Expenditure Rs.7203/15/-. nast year T s. •^•4702/1/-.2-72- (2^ Minutes of tne latn sitting of Manainah Balaaiyali ^eid on ihursday tne 14tn Dhul Hijjan 13b0(,2fath February Ido/;. 'fne meeting was helci under the preseiucncy of ouaikn Muiiammaa bin 'Isa al Khalifab ano in tne presence of tne members. Five members were absent uue to work ana illness. After the minutes of the previous sitting was reaa ana approveu, discussion 'went on about tne foilowing:- 1). FLAGIKff DF Firan WOOD OH QOV ^ri ldifflf r ROxiB aNL PRICR AQAlaL 'iJae i»iajlis discussecx tue above question ana aeciaed unanimously that, as aecidta in tne meeting iiela on tne 1st Lhul ^aaa lobb, fuel &lt;vooa, sued as reeas, aate-palm sticks ana T karab T , ’iazam’ snoula not be placea on tne above two roaas. Exception is, nowever, maae for tne wooa used for tne builaings and boat builuing etc. Tne Ealaaiyaii are to issue a notice in continuation of Notice No.32/13bb da tea 2utn ^nul v t aaa 13bo explaining tne uiflerence between tne meaning of 'fuel wooa’ and T timber T . Hie Secretary recited the draft notice which is to be published and it was approved by the Majlis. E). COST OF THE NSfi ICE MACHINE .. • The cost and freight from London . of the ice machine is Rs.657b/7/- paid by the Government. Tne jaladiyah will nave to reimburse this amount m accordance with the agieement maae, nde Government f s letter No .8/587 of bth Jamad lhani ISb^t. me Majlis approved this and tna.ikea the Government for their iclp to tne Baladiyah. 3J. EXPENDITURE INCURRED ON THE OPENING OF Whii _MGHaRRA^ LOAD. The Secretary stated that a sum of ns.7804/13/9 has been incurred on the opening of the above roaa by paying compensations, cost of building ana wages of workmen lor levelling tne road. This anount has been recovered liom the Bahrain Government. There are, however, some more expenditure on the above raoa in connection with the re-builaing of the women T s T Matam T which has not yet been completed. Ihe Majlis thanked the Baladiyan for their efforts in opening this important road in a little time and at such a small cost.4). THE MIXING OF ^'KEaT FKOUR WITH 3AI ; 1EY FLQUH. The Secretary submitted the question of flour which was postponed curing the last meeting, discussion arose over this matter. It has been aeciaed that it is forbidden to have wheat mixed with barley ana that the decisions passed in the previous meetings of tiie Balauiyah on this subject are to be upheld, and that the Baladiyah have to effect observance of them. One of the members, Haji Muhammad al Kamau al Qahhi, suggested that the Baladiyah may apply this decision to the wheat which has already been imported as well as that which may be imported in future if it is mixed with barley more than half the quantity as the wheat which comes to Bahrain now is mixed with barley more than half. The Majlis did not approve this suggestion. b). SHOPS OF THE HEIRS OF SHAIKH aBDUB RAhMAB BIN ABDUL WAHaB The Secretary stated that the Baladiyah have found a report dated the 25th Dhul Qada 1351 and 26th Safar 1352 about the giving of compensation to T Umar arid his brother T Abaur hazzaq sons of Shaikh f Abaur Rahman bin Aooul ..aiihab. The ^ajlis discussed this matter and then decided that the Accounts Committee should inspect the place cut, their shops and the shops built by the Baladiyah, and submit the result to the Majlis. 6). Reading reports. The Secretary read over the report dated 1st Dhul Eijjah about Mespers’ place. The Majlis approved the report. 7;. The following letters received by the Balaaiyah were read over:- (ay. Letter dated 14th Dhul *ada 1355 from Haji Husain bin Muhamrnaa Ahmadi requesting that the passage belonging to Muhanmiad bin 'All Haji may oe pulled down as it is erected on his property which he purchased from Muqbil al Dhukair in accordance with an undertaking letter which he has. After reading tnis letter, the Majlis decided that he should be told to take his case to the Bahrain Court. (bj. Petition from a number of Baharnah bakers requesting the Baladiyah to allow them to make yellow bread 2o loaves of which may weigh one ruber since such bread is sold to the villagers most of whom ask for such a number of loaves. AccordngjJAgenda for the 1st meeting which will be held on iliursday the 26th Muharram 1356 CBth April 1937). 1)« The ^ew ^e ^r*. This is a first meeting during the new year 1356 which we hope it will be a prosperous one for the country and the • ! •daladiyah. hast year was so and we should not forget the v/orks j done during that year for the improvement and the progress of the 1 country in which the Government and the Baladiyah took great parts. The President, his deputy and the members made great efforts in this end. H is hoped that during this year many of the projects which were incomplete during last year, may now be completed and that other projects may be added to those of last year which may he worthy of mention and deserving to last. and SXPENDI TUHE FOR THB iDITTH OF DHUL HIJJAH InConie Rs.9474-1-4. Last year's income... .Rs. 6773- 10 - 7 . Expenditure... 6299-12-3 ' ' expenditure.' 8637 - 15 - 9 . m msm qi m mmm , JjlCOme P-• 82866 - 11-11 I&gt;ast year's income... .E'.57398-3-7. Expenditure' 69402-9-10. ', ' expenditure' 47620-0-4. *rom the above it will be seen that the Baladiyah has made a profit of Rs. 13464-2-1. this year. 12-i-i2ASH CAP ITAL OF THB BALADIYAH. Cash available in the Bank and in the Baladiyah's Treasury upto the end of 1355 Rs.33182-6-7. Last year's.. .Rs.29496-4-8. QF ACCOUNTS tuv The above statement will be snbmitted after it had been checked by the Accounts Committee and passed by them. mt_0FF3R. OF THAijKS TO THE FTWUJr? COMTTmim? ^ account of the expiry of last year, the Finance ommittee should be thanked for their inspection of the accounts e t “ ri0S ^ •««. th. T r amparticularly grateful to them for the kind attention which they paid in every meeting held for the inspection and the classifica tion of the accounts. 7). CONTRACTOR F OR SHEEP BROKERAGE. The period of the contract expired on SOth Dhul Hijja 1355. Should the Baladiyah issue an ‘Alan on the subject ? S j. SUPPLY OF WATER TO THE UJ2TATIC ASYLUM. Pipes for water supply from the well which is in the garden of Haji ’ ABDiILLAR EXIT JABUR t.o the lunatic Asylum have been lajld. 9) . THE DRILLING MACHINE. fhe Clover ment well at Budayi’ has been deepened and f consequently more water is coming out than the quantity required. rhe ^dviser has ordered that the machine should be used for boring a well on the ground of His Highness Shaikh Hamad in order that water may be obtained for the cleaning of the/fruit market , fish-market, meat market and also for supplying water to the mosque of Shaikh Qasim al Mihza’ as well as for precaution against fires (God forbidJ. 10) . To read reports of the Committees.% Agenda tor the 2na meeting oi Manaman Balaaiyaii Majlis wmcli will be held on Thursday the 11th Sai’ar 1356(22.4.37). 1) . BUDGET OF THE YEAR 1356. The Budget Committee composea of the following members held a meetmg:- haji Khalil bin Ibrahim al Mua’yyaa. Haji f Ali bin Muhammaa Kanoo. Haji Muhammaa al Hamau al ^aahi. Haji Muhsin bin Ahmad al Tajir. Shaikli f Ishaq bin ^bdur Rahman. Haji Hasan al T Abdul f Aziz al ’Ajaji. Haji Muhammaa bin Hasan al Darazi. Haji Husain bin f Ali Kadhum. TheVdecided the budget of this year as follows For income hs. 78000/-/-. Last year ! s Ks.bblbO/-/-. For expenditure.” 77140/-/-. ' ” Tl b!36b/-/-. These will De read to you in detail. 2) . RECORD ROOM. The office requires one room to be used as a record room for the Baladiyah. It should De situated on the north side of the oflice and adjoining to it. 3) . RESIGNATION OF ONE OF HOUSE TAX COLLECTORS. The tax collector, Muhammad Sai f d al Afghani has tendered his resignation owing to his inability to perlorrn his duties on account of his illness. The Baladiyah accepted his resignation lor a period of one month trom the date of the resignation and they have appointed two persons to work m his place during this period. Both are paid the same pay which Muhammad Sa^d used to get. 4) . COLONEL L0CH T S DEPARTURE. Colohel Loch will i- leave Bahrain about the enu of this month. I suggest that the Baladiyah should hold a-party ih his honour before his departure. This will have a good efiect as his honour has rendered very valuable services. L’hat is the opinion of the: Majlis about this ? b ). To read reports.TRANSLATION* ZOZ /%14~ Minutes of tne 20tn sitting of Manamah BaladijaJa Majlis dela on Thursday the 28tn Lhul Hijjan 135b (11th March 193V) The Klanaraan Baladiyai:i ^ajlis he la their meeting unaer the presidency of the Presiaent Shaikh Muhammad bin t^sa al Khalifah and in the presence of tne members. Two members namely, Haji Ibrahim bin Muhammaa Ahmaai ana haji iiiiuhsin bin Ahmad al Tajer were absent owing to some business. After the proceedings of the previous meeting had been reaa and confirmed, discussion took place over the following:- 1;. Account of income ana expenaiture for Dhul ^aaah 1353. Income hs. 12454/12/3 incluaing Government's grant of Ks.5000/- for tne purpose of filling tne marsh. Last year T s income was Iis.4414/8/6. Expenaiture Rs.7203/15/-. Last year T s Rs.4702/1/-. They were approved by tne -accounts Committee, sealed ana passed by tne Majlis. 2) . BAHARNAH BAKERS. The Secretary submitted tne question of bakers the discussion over which was postponea at tne previous meeting. The majlis, after going through the matter fully, decided unanimosuly that tneir request should not be acceded to but they must follow Balaaeyah f s rules about the sale of bread at 16 loaves per ruba, i.e., fpur pounas. 3) . WATER PIPES FROM THE GARDEN OF HAJI ABDULlAH BIN JABUR T O'^E'TiJNATnr''' A57LQMT The Secretary statea that the distance requirea for extention of water pipes is 600 feet. The width of tne pipe should be one inch. The cost comes to Rs.200/- only. The Majlis approved of tne purchase of pipes ana their extention. 4J. THE DRILLING MACHINE. The Secretary statea that the Balaaeyah nave started deepening the Government artesian well in accoraance with the orders oi tne Adviser. The Majlis approved of this. 5). TREES FOR THE BALADIYAH GARDEN AND THE ROADS. The Secretary stated that the Adviser has been kind enough to present about 19o trees lor the gardens and tneO- /r\ 301 ana tne roads. All tnese trees nave been importea from outsiae. The Presiaent and tne Majlis tnanked tne Adviser for tms gift# b). TO READ REPORTS. The Secretary read tne reports datea tne 18tn hhul Hijan 13bb wmcn were confirmed by the Majlis# The member haji f Ali bin Muhammad Kanoo objected to the builaing of the heirs of Shaikh T Abdur iiahman al T Abdul ttahhab which is adjacent to the Sahnaf Mosque saying that the building in question is higher tnan the roof of the mosque and that the drains of the mosque have been blocked on account of that and that it is possible that the rain water may fall on the walls of the mosque and thereby damages it. The Majlis discussed this question and then the President suggested that the whole Majlis shoula inspect the place in question and then decide. 7J. EXPIRY OF THE TERM OF THE INSPECTING- COMMITTEE. The Secretary statea that the perioa of ofiice of the Inspecting Committee has expired and that they are to be thankee in for the improvements and general projects/which they took part. The President elected another Committee of tne following members:- 1. Haji Muhammad Din Mubarak al Faahil. 2. Haji f Ali bin Muhammad Kanoo. 3. Haji Muhammad al Hamaa al Qadhi. 4.Haji Husain T Ali Kaohum. b.Haji Ibrahim bin T Ali al Mascati. 8J. The following letters received by the Salaaiyan were read:- (a) Letter No.184/8 dated 24th Lhul Hijjah 1355 from the Adviser in reply to Baladiyah T s letter No.631 of 18th ultimo regarding the pier of stones. He suggested that tenders may be invited. The Majlis approved of his suggestion. (b) . Letter dated 3rd March 1937 from Rev. Van Peursem on behalf of the American Mission, in reply to i3alaaiyah f s letter about the corner of their ^ta 1 which has been cut by the Baladiyah. he stated that he authorised the Balaaiyah to do the cutting but that he wants tne Balaaiyah to give him the small corner situated to the east side of the Hospital for inclusion in the Hospital. The Majlis decided that tne Inspecting Committee should inspect tne place.(c). Letter dated 27tn Diiul Hijjali 13bb trom naji oalman bin Ahmad Kamal inviting Baladiyah T s attention to the question oi Japanese cement. He saia tnat cement less insight tnan wnat is usual nas been imported into Bahrain ana sola in tne markets at the same rate at wnich full weignt cement is sold. He considers tnis to be fraud. The Majlis discussed tins fully and also they discussed the question of sugar which is imported m less weight ana sold as full weight, and then they decided unanimously that the Baladiyah should issue a notice prohibiting the import ana sale of cement ana sugar m Bahrain if they are not oi the following weight Cement, one cwt or 112 lbs. per bag* Sugar, 2 cwts per bag. The Government should be informed of this. (d) . Letter dated 23rd Lhul Hijjah 135b from haji Khalil bin Ibrahim Kanoo asking the Baladiyah to pay him a sum of AS.lbO/- being the difference in the cost of motor lorry tyres. The Majlis decided in accordance with their decision aatea tne 22na Rajab 13bb to the effect tnat he should be paid Rs.75/- only. (e) . Letter dated 20th Lhul Hijjah 135b from Muhammad Kawoosh requesting tnat he may be given the contract of fruit market lor _ 'll the period of one year. The Majlis reiusea his request. (f) . Letter dated 2oth Lhul Hijjah 13bo from Husain bin ’Ali bin Nasrullah in reply to BalaaiyahJs letter Ho.739/3oo m connectior with the land which he claims. He stated that he has witnesses V from among the members of the former Majlis to tne eilect that a sum of Rs.600/- has been fixed for him as compensation. The Majlis upheld their decision dated 29th Lhul Qauah 13bb. (gj. netter dated 21st Lhul Hijjah 13bb from Muhammad bin Rashid al Mehri on behlaf of his father Shaikh Qasim al menza 1 complaining that Knalifah bin Hammaa al ^allaf has sold a piece of land adjoining the land of Shaikh jasim to Haji Yusuf bin Abdur Rahman i^akhroo ana that the seller has cut a part of his land ana added it to that which he sold. The nuajlis decided that he should be told to refer his case to the Government. # (hj. setter da tea 28tn i&gt;dul Hijjaii 138b trom Abuun Noor bin Muhammad Bastaki saying tnat ne wisnes to maice a shaue in tront2U di 3 of his shop situated on Barret Road* Tne Majlis aeciaea tnat he rnay be allowed to make a shade as othershave done on the same road. (i) . Letter dated 2Utn Dhul Hijjah 13bb from Hamad al Sulaiman al Roaq ana T Abdullah al Hamad al Zamil enclosing a plan for tne building which they propose to erect on G-overnment Road. The Majlis approved ol tne building in accordance witn tne plan (j) . Bill No.8o/5b/T.B. dated 26th Lnul nijjan 13bb from tne State Lngineer asking lor payment of £.8.10.6 and as. 2l/b/- on account of cost of certain requirements for the old ice machine The Majlis passed orders for tne payment of tnese two amounts. (k) . The member Haji Ibrahim bin Muhammad Ahmaui has written apologizing for his absence from the meeting on account of some business. The Majlis accepted his excuse. 9. In connection with the question of fixing eltctnc light points in places by Haji Sal man bin f Abdullah al Zaya.ni, the member Haji Khalil bin Ibrahim al Mua f yyad stated tnat the Baladiyah and the public do not know whether this person alcbne is authorised to do so or other people can do so too. Also about the question of the rate of fixing light points as the matter is not quite clear. The Baladiyah should therefore make enquiries to this end from the G-ovemment or from the State engineer. The Majlis approved of his suggestion. 10. The meeting was dissolved by tne order of the President at b oclock Arabic.-I'lQ Translation of letter No.79/1356 datea 2oth April 1937 from the Secretary, Manamah Balaaiyah, to Colonel Loch, Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments. I understand from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government that you will call at the Balaaiyan Office to-morrow i morning at 3.00 0 T clock Arabic (9.30.A.M.) to say goodbye to the President of Manamah Baladiyan ana the members of the Majlis, on the occasion of your leaving Bahrain. will be waiting for you at the time fixed. Me hope that you will bring with you Captain Hickinbotnam ana your Assistant. We, therefore, nave tne honour to receive you and Usual Ending.I 7). Contractor of sheep Drokerage. The Secretary stated tdat the period ot the contract expired on the 30th Dhul Hijjah 13^b ana enquired whether the Baladiyah should publish a notice. The Majlis agreed to this. b). To extend water to the Lunatic Asylum. The Secretary stated that the Balaaiyah has completed the work | on extending water irom tne well 01 Haji ’Abdullah al Jabur to tne Lunatic Asylum. The Majlis approved ot this. 9) . The drilling machine. The Secretary stated the Baladiyah has completed the work on deepening tne Government well at Budaya’ ana that the Adviser nas ordered that an artesian well should be bored on the property ol H.H.Shaikh Hamad situated near the Baladiyah lor tne supply ol water! lor cleaning the new truit market, tne ush-market and the meat market and also lor supplying water to Shaikh Rasim’s Mosque and as a precaution against tires God toroid. The Majlis agreed to all j these and thanked tne Adviser. 10) . Beadamg reports ot Commit tees. The Secretary read tne reports dated SVtn ana iibtn Dhul HijjahJ 4rtn and 19th Muharram which were approved by tne Majlis. 11) . Trie tollowm^ let ter s received by tne Balaaiyah were read over: - (a) . Letter irom Munammaa Salin al Shatur, Secretary ol Manama Baladiyan applying tor 3 months’ leave m order to take his lamily to Bagnaaad to visi l tneir relatives. He preters to leave on otn Rabi al Awwal 13oo i.e., alter holding receptions in honour oi the | Coronation of tne King ol Great Britain. The acting president and the members agreed to his request and to the payment oi leave salary | to him. Tne acting president suggested that the Head Clerk should act lor the Secretary during his absence. This has been approved. (b) . Translation ol a letter from tne Bahrain Petroleum Co., # to the Adviser to tne Bahrain Government containing a report from Mr.Boone, an engineer ol the Company regarding the water channel wnicn extends irom the Garden to the sea. The Majlis agreed to the report and decided that tne Committee should carry out an inspection on the channel and order iw(c). Letter No.110/d dated 18tn Muharram 13bo from the Advise to the Bahrain Government saying that it' a member of the Balaaiyan Majlis fails to pay Baladiyan tax, it would be better for him to resign from the membership of the Majlis. The Majlis agreed to this. (d). Letter No.74/8 dated Ibth Muharram 1356 from the Auviser to the Bahrain Government saying as follows:- The corner of . &lt;Z ( i^r&lt;x L Government-noad has been repaired by the maae in the Government House and the cutting of a part of the wall. The Political Agent agreed to the cutting of the south-western corner of the Agency which is situatea behind the new Court but that he does not agree to the cutting of any other Government building either from the agency compound or from the Hospital compound. The Adviser snail make arrangments to remove the water reservoir so that the roaa which extends from Has Rumman to the Government Roaa may become wide. The Majlis approved of all these and thanked the Political iigent and the adviser. (e). Letter No.40/20 dated oth Muharram 13bo from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government inviting 3aladiyah f s attention to Baladiyah ! s ’Alan No.3bb/44 dated 29th Dhul Hijjah 135b and saying that it has been wrongly issued as it is not the business of the Baladiyah to forbid the import of anything to the country but it is for the Government only to do so. The Baladiyah can only fix the weights ana measurements of certain goods within the limits of the Baladiyhan The i&lt;iajlis discussed this matter fully and then decided to approve of what has been pointed out by the Adviser. (i)* Letter No.1/6 dated 4th Muharram 13b6 from the Director of Customs and Port Officer referring to Baladiyah T s ’Alan No.35b/ 44 in connection with the import of cement and sugar and inviting Baladiyah f s attention that it is not the lookout of the Majlis to forbid the import of anything into Bahrain but that it is for the ‘Government to do so. Regarding the question of the sale of cement at 112 pounds a bag, whether this is nett weight or not. Regarding sugar. It would be better it the kind of sugar is specified and whether the sale is nett or By bags. etc.The Majlis discussea tnis matter fully and decided that the v/eight of the goods relerred to above should be fixed and to iorbid tnet**- n+iu (L ^ tis{c&lt;u&lt; ^ sal«yless than the weight fixed within the limits of the Balaaiyah. As regards prohibiting the import of the same Irorn abroad, this rests with the Government. Secondly, about weight and kind oi goods j The cement should be 11B lbs nett weight. Sugar, i.e., Java sugar should be 2 cwts a bag. dated 13/1/37 (g) . Report/from Captain A.K.^atson, of the Society of India for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, about the Slaughter House of Manamah. Captain Batson, accompanied by Muhammad oalih al Shatur, 5 Secretary, Manamah Saladlyah, saw the way of slaughtering animals. | He liked the way of slaughtering and the cleanliness of the place especially the instant washing of blood with water. He saw the puffing of animals before they are skinned, i.e, the butchers put their mouths in a hole in the animal T s thigh and then exhale by their lungs strongly. He suggested that a bellows may be ordered specially for filling the animals with air and that a hand pipe may be used for drawing water from the sea for washing the place. The Majlis thanked him for his observations and approved his suggestion about ordering two pairs of bellows. (h) . Letter dated 24th Muharram from Shaikh Ishaq bin f Abdur Rahman al Khan asking the Haladiyah for permission to extend a pipe j from his artesian well to the seashore on the eastern side for the benelit oi the public. The Majlis approved of his request and thanked him lor his Charitable act. (i) . Letter dated 3rd Muharram 13bo from f Abdullah bin Ahmad Y^ asking lor compensation in lieu ot the portion cut off his house u situated at yudhaibiyah m the year 13b3 in accordance with the resolution oi the Majlis dated the 22nd Salar 13b3. The Majlis decided that the inspecting Commitcee snould inspect tne place and report tne result. (j)* Latter dated 2otn Muharram 13bb irom Ahmad bin Yusuf al Mahmid, one oi the Baladiyah clerks applying for ie*r leave and leave salary due to him as he intends to marry. The Majlis decided I that leave cannot be granted to him at present as the Secretary is shortly proceeding on leave but il he wanted leave for 10 days to enable him to marry, this can be granted* him otherwise ne can |wait till the Secretary returns from leave ana then get leave (k). Letter dated 21st Muharram 13b6 from Haji T Abdun Nabi bin Aiunaa Busniri drawing Balaaiyaii’s attention 10 the corner adjacent to the f Jafariyah Washing House* ana saying that he heara that the American Mission asked the Balaaiyah to include this corner in the Hospital, he added that tnat this corner is used as a passage for water from the f Washing House T . He requested the Baladiyah to confirm its ownership to the ’Washing House f . The Majlis decided that the corner should form a part of the ’Washing House’. 12. The meeting was dissolved by the order of the acting president at 4 o’clock Arabic. BM■ —33W Translation of tne age no a tor tne 3ra meeting whicn will be he Id on Thursday tne 10th Babi al Awwal 1356 (20.3*37) 1). Budget ol tne montn of IJutiarr a m 1356 . Income fis.5670-10-10. Last year T s.. .ns.4126-13-4. Expenditure ” 4988- 1- 9. M M ,f 4302-14-3. 2_). Interlerence ot members witn tne administrative alTairs oi tne BaTadiyahT Some ot tne members of tne Maj lis mteri'ert wi the administrative ai'tairs of tne Balaciyah which they have no right to do. But every member has tne right to put his suggestion officially to tne Majlis in matters concerning the welfare of the town. 3). Letters and suggestions. The Baiadiyah law uoes not permit that tne letter whicn is to be read before tne Majlis ana any suggesyion by any member, be submitted one aay before tne Majlis nola their meeting, but they shoula do so at least three aays before tne meeting is convenea so that tney may be incluuea in the agenda. 4 j . Connecting Nai f m RomL with Telegraph Boac. M.- , I find that it is in the interest ol tne country to connect Lai f m Boaa witn Telegraph iToaa. ns there are some places in the market situated in tne way of tne roaa, it woula be well if the Balaaiyah cut tnem so as to connect these two roads from east to west. 5;. The walking of the ice-machine. The new ice-machine started to work on Friday the 3rd instant and the Baladiyah has taken over the income of ice as usual. 6) . Putting the previous resolutions into effect. As there are some resolutions which have not yet ssr been put into effect, 1 finu that it is the duty of the Baladiyah to put tnem into effect without further discussion 7) . Heading tne previous reports.ip* 1-MM.7. Letter No.566/54 dated the 14th January 1936 from the Secretary, Manamah Baladeyah. Agenda for the Meeting, A.F.A. Submitted lor your perusal t 15/1/36 % 1 l 10. setter no.564/54 dated the 13th January 1S36 from the secretary, Manamah ualadeyah. A..P. A. Minutes of the meeting. Submitted for your perusal ■ „ f ^ v36 4 i' * x ThanKs. I thinK that we might let the Adviser Know that it would be advisaole for him to consult Dr Holmes before ordering vaccine as we have found that the Karachi vaccine gives better results than the Basrah vaccine and that there is now a dry preparation which ieeep= is believed to Keep. A d.o. would be b^st. 25.1.36 Yf. A.P.A. uraft submitted. ^ 27/1/36 Qtt ' 27//- issued D.O.I' 0 .3 -i*'/2 dateo the 27th January 193S to the Adviser^ to the Bahrain (government, Bahrain. better ho. 591/54 dated the 27th’January 1936 from the Secret-H Manamah Baladejiah. ' J A.P.A. Submitted for your perusal, rlease see item 5. i fear that the Majlis may sanction the purchase of a lorry from the local Agents before we receive Leyland pamphlets. /J r4 4 /S 47 ► Letter No.JGP/ES dated the 23rd January 1936 from Leyland Motors Limited. Adviser's attention to be drawn to these with referencej to P.A’s orders. Please submit file. 1 think the question of buying new lorries came up in a Municipal meeting. ti.A.C.-10/2. 48 49 A.P.A. Ihe felative file is under submission to p.A. i P.A. ordered that we should send these nay land pamphlets to the Adviser but we should not make any recommendations. Draft D.O. is submitted. (Jv 13 / 1/36 Iky D.O* no.53 dated 13.2.36 to the Adviser issued. \J Letter no.1299-1 dated 19.2.1936 from the Adviser^Bahrain^ pay up with pps. 'j'. A. . 19/2. H.M. A.P.A. Please see item 7(b) at page 38(file F/2 Vol.ill). 20.2.36 xliere is no record of this case nor of local custom ^ e. ards sehat. i understand that the persons living in zulmabad were removed there from some site in Manamah oecause of their filth, do far as ± know this happened m the time of Major Daly, fhe ground they now live onknown as Ailmabad belongs to Shaikh Ahmad bin Muhammad bin •Isa al Khalifah. If the inhabitants are unwanted tenants ! presumably he has a right^to remove them, if they are ^ undesirable foreigners Wno ostensible means of subsistanc they can be dealt with under Section 109 Criminal wocedure Code and then removed from Bahrain under Section 2Cii..36On the 25th February I discussed this case with the Adviser. It is not clear why shaikh ^ahammad bin f Isa writes in his capacity of President of the ^anamah Municipal Council, unless it is that the people now at Zulmabad were placed there from the Municipal area. I gather that he has a document similar to other hibbas of the ground in question and that it now belongs to his son, Ahmad. It might be useful to take the line of dealing with the matter with the son (he is if not mental at any rate somewhat peculiar). 2 . I understand that shaikh ^“uhammad has also made a gift of a large tract of land near Yatim T s garden td his son Khaiifah (the one who works on the Court) and that some question may arise of ejecting Baharinah from holdings in that area. 3. It seems to me possible that this case of Zulmabad is being brought with a view to establishing a precedent for the ejection of persons who live on lands belonging to Shaikh Muhammad and his family so that it will be necessary to be very careful in dealing with the question. 4. .We should look up the papers of ^ajor Daly^ time and see when these people were transferred to Zulmabad from the municipal area and h what circumstances this was done. One point is to discover whether at the time u haikh ^uhammad or any of his family made any representation about it (was Shaikh Muhammad then President of the Municipality) and another point is that if these people have been there for aotim than ten years without a protest, they have, according to Bahrain Customs. . 7 vik, _ „ % squatters rights. 5. I do not think that we need be hasty in this matter if and when it comes to an head it is likely to rai&amp;e the whole question of the interpretation of numferous hibbas. 27.2.1336(3£f ■ 7 4 S* setter ho»646/54 dated 22.2.36 from the ^resident of * a Manaraah j^aladiyah. A • ir* • A • &gt;r Ke para 4 of r.A'S note dated 27.2.36. i made a search in v.u. files of Major ^alys time hut have not been able to find any papers about the transfer of these people to uhulmabad. bhaikh Muhammad bin ^sa al jtvhalifah became rresident of the Manamah naladiyah about uune 1929 at the time of Major xrior. ^ 7.3^36 A.P.A. ^( p ara 1 of r.A»s i\otej . We Hive no record of the ownership of this land and the only information we have is the letter(Page 51) from bhaikh Muhammad bin ‘Isa, ^resident of Manamah baladiyi to the Adviser, i am sorry ± have no knowledge about this hiba or ownership. A(para 4 of P»a 1 s note). * According to the Bahrain government ‘IIAim ho: 135 dated the 19th March 1924, persons v/ho, at the time of the ' issue of the *Ilan, were living and in actual possession of an open Government land,which is situated within the Baladiyah limits, for an uniterrupted and undisputed period of ten years or more could be considered as having acquired tlufVlght of ownership. We have no record of any representation by either bhaikh Muhanmad or his family, when these people were transferred bhaikh Muhammad was not ^resident of the Man amah baladiyah. 7.3.36a 0 %I should be glad if I.A. would asK Shaikh Ahmad hin Muhammad 8/4 to come to see him . He shd then enquire from him how he holds the land in question, and whether he has any documents. He will probably say that he has,and possibly may produce, an hibba - if so, I snd liice to see it. I.A. shd also say that in any case persons who have been in possession of land for more than ten years,as these men have, are by local custom entitled to retain it. This remark shd not be pursued,but made in a general way to see what he will answer to the suggestion. I shd liKe I.A. to spea^ to me before sdnding for Shaiish Ahmad. 16.4.36 a.P.a/P .a. Shaikh Ahmed bin kohd came and told me that he has documents (Hibba) from the late Shaikh Isa to show the transfer oi this land to him ana will send them if found with his father’s servant -Mohd bin Saleh. He added £hat the local custom entitles to retain the lanu. by the occupants who have lived more tn&amp;n 10 years if it is not owned by anyone. Jhr Z&amp;/4/26 0.0.NO.68/121 .P. dated 19.4.36 from the .adviser. a.P.a./P .a o I Para NO. 1 of my my above Note. Shaikh 'dimed bin Mohd informed me that the *Hiba papers 1 are with his father. He, however, sent me a minute of Baladiya, Manama copjf of whi (Exhibit A) together with its translation (Exhibit B) are submitted below for your perusal. Keference D.O. letter. Proclamation NO.653 of 1347 ie available at page 42 (File 6/17 P.I). A copy of EiiKiX Proclamation NO.l of 134y duly obtained is submitted below. fa “^6/ 4/36F/ 2 . 133* Letter L 0 . 34/55 dated the 18 th Man amah Baladiyah. ay 1936 from the S ecre tary, Agenda for the meeting. A.P.A. Submitted for your perusal. 20/5/36 137. Letter ^ 0 .126/55 dated the 3rd June 1936 from the Secretary Manamah ^laaiyah. 138. Letter ^o. 145 dated the 15th dune- 1936 from the 5 e cretary, Manamah Baladiyah. 141. Letter Lo.178 dated tne 30th June 1936 from the Secretary Manamah Balaaiyah, Baiiiain. Submitted for your perusal. Since tne last two months we have not received any minutes of the meetings of the Baladiyah. Subject to your approval, we may ask tne Acting Adviser to instruct the Secretary of Baladiyah to send the minutes and the agendas regularly in future, There is no meeting this week. A.^.A. May be filed ? Agenda for the meet! g. Submitted for your perusal. May bn filAd ? Agenda for the meeting. Draft submitted. 0 .^5 /^\ F/2. III. 238. Letter No.582 dated 12th January 1S37 from the Secretary, Man amah Baladiyah, Bahrain. A.P.A. Sending agenda for the municipal meeting. There is nothing of importance in the agenda. May be filed ? (V-, 1§/1/ 37 V&gt; L It' 242. Letter No.592/1355 dated 16.1.37 from the Secretary, Manamah Baladiyah. Minute of the meeting. Submitted for your perusal. May be filed ? 247. Letter No.6l8 dated 26.1.37 from the Secretary, Manamah Baladiyah. A.P.A. Agenda for the meeting. Submitted for your perusal. May be filed C * . k % 27.1.37 ' K 251. Letter No.637/1355 dated 1.2.1937 from the Secretary, Manamah Baladiyah. ^[ .P.A. Minutes of the meeting. Submitted for your perusal. / 4 ° 'Z 0.2.37 'r i</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000292_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1923</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000292</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1923</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File F/2 III Miscellaneous correspondence with Manama Municipality</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-09T16:40:50</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (378 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 378; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Additional foliation sequences are present in parallel between ff 2-359 and ff 360-366; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains meeting minutes of the governing board of the Manama municipality, and their translations. Covering letters of the meetings follow a set of Arabic and English transcriptions of the meetings which cover a wide variety of municipal and/or administrative concerns. Some letters from the Political Agent, advisor to the Government of Bahrain, Charles D. Belgrave, and the Land Registration Department, are also included in the file.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Manamah Municipality</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Municipal ordinances</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000292#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>