<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00033a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T23:28:31.357Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(&lt;£&gt; 2 h- \ K X P H £ L E T T g Prom Political Resident| Persian Calf, Cuap f Shir&amp;£« To Ret&amp;xandiLTi, LO^ DO;; &gt; Repeated Foreign, N£V. DEUII , Political, jj,ui;u,Iii. ^ dated the 30th August)1944* IMir.aln J&gt;ih»rrr,ci) ,-erodro ie . Copy is enclosed of a note dated 25th August 1944 by Major T. Hickinbotnam, I^olitical Agent, Bahrain* In view of the conflicting technical opinions as to the suitability of the Muharraq aerodrome it is requested that future policy in regard to it nay be ascertained from the Air Ministry and communicated to me* 2* The advantages of utilising Muharraq in preference to the mainland require no stress. Sd• GEOFFREY PRIOR Political Resident, Persian Gulf for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.In Karachi on the 17th of August Mr. Lloyd-Taylor the B.O.A.C. Regional Director showed me the minutes of a meeting of the Middle East Air Transport Board held in Cairo on the 4th of August. It v/as recorded that Air Vice Marshal Betts had stated that the U.S.A.^.C. wished to construct a large aerodrome at Dhahran capable of accomraodat- ing heavy aircraft. The Air Vice Marshal intcn-dod that short supplies of essential materials would render this impracfcic- ♦ able. Ke further stated that experiments carried out at Bahrain showed that the landing ground there was unsuitable for heavy aircraft at present and that owing to atmospheric conditions it would not be possible to render it suitable in the future. 2. Mr. Lloyd-Taylor was perturbed by tils reoort which he considered ill founded as he had already had experiments carried out by Mr. Atkin the Corporation's engineer, who was present during my conversation with the Regional Director, which had proved to the satisfaction of both of them that though not at present suitable for the heaviest aircraft it would be a matter of little difficulty to make ^ the landing ground into one of the finest in the world. 3. This is the first intimation that I have had that the R.A.F. are dissatisfied with the Muharrak ground and that experiments had been carried out. That the heavier bombers showed a tendency to sink when taxi-ing with a full load of petrol is a fact feiawt I have always been given to understand that the resurfacing of the landing strips after the war would be simple and would remove this present dis advantage. Until my interview with Mr. Lloyd-Taylor I understood from conversations itfcfchx which I had had with Ik Sir Frederick Bowhill and Air vice Marshalls Collier and Davison that the Muharrak ground was ideal for post war aviation. It is therefore somewhat sjirorising to learn that not only will it not be ideal but is in fact a complete failure. 4. In view of the :L ^urtHnee to Balirain of A.^L^vHcffesstatement it is desirable that the A.O. C-in.C.Middle East be asked for further information in particular regarding the nature of the experiments carried out by the R.A.F. A.M. Sir Keith Parks* attention could be drawn to the view4 of the B.O.A.C. engineer regarding the improvement of the ground surface and he might be asked what exactly was meant by M atmospheric ' conditions. 25/8/44-On the evening of the 30th September 1^4 Air Goa.mooore Whitney Straight, M.C., D.F.C., accompanied by Group Captain Carey, called at the Agency and discussed the use of the | Bahrain landing ground by heavy aircraft. Air Commodore Whitney Straight said that it was now Intended to post 24 squadrons of He'll faxes at Shalbah and that they will be flown continually backwards and forwards to India. Unfortunately the landing ground at Maharraq was net sufficiently solid to permit of its beingused by Kali faxes whose weight per square inch of tyre was greater than any other aircraft. The possibility of improving the surface by the use of wire mesh had been considered and would be very satisfactory but unfortunately wire mesh was very hard to cone by and might not be immediately available. In the mean time two experts were due to arrive on the 2nd October who would make a careful examination of the landing ground. They would also examine the Has Tanurah and Dhahran landing grounds. 2. Air Commodore Whitney Straight stated that he would very much like to land at Has Tanurah end Dhahran with a view to examining those landing grounds to see whether they would be suitable for his purpose. I explained that permission would have to be sought from the Saudi Government and that I would set about doing so first thing the next morning. I asked whet tar he had considered Qatar peninsula, forgetting the absence of water there. But he did not appear to be particularly interest ed and I do not think that we need expect any move in that direction. 3. On the 1st October the Air Commodore left for Sharjah. Owing to the absence of the local Government officials at Dhahran permission to land there and at Has Tanurah . s con siderably delayed. However it did not matter for I le rnt from the Air Liaison Officer that the Air Commodore had changed his mind and now had no desire to land in Saudi Arabia, prefer- ring; to leave the work to the two experts. (Id) T.H. 2-10-44.Talegra^. &amp; i/38 S(Pad) From. Political Kasident Persian dull, Bahrain, To. Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated tb Government of India, Nev Jelhi. Copy to Political Agent, Bahrain. No. T/3G3 Da :;ed the 23rd Novenber 1944. TOP SBCxuiT Your Express letter No. Ext.4779/44 October 30t^ 1UARD. I agree with viefjs expressed in para- heard graph 3 r d). I have/nothing so far to suggest that Bahrain could not bundle much larger numbers but cannot of course exp ress opinion regarding its suitability for very heavy bombers. Ibadan has parallel runways which could be developed witnout interfering with each other but there has been sone difficulty over fog or dust. 2. Everything points to fact that Ameileans are solely concerned with improving their post war position and ray view is that Dhahran can only be developed at expense of Bahrain. RESIDENT /■ G Oh d I jj.v.X iAL Soi C/535 Oi'fi'a '&gt;'■ the Political Resident, in the Perdian Gulf, Jump, Bahrain. dated the 23rd November 1944. Copy forv.aried with compliments to:- The Political Agent, Bahrain,HTDIA OFFICE, External Department T From: EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL ) I’OP SECRET Secretary of State for India. To: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Government of I n dia, External Affairs Department, and Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated: No. : 2^ October 1944. Ext.V779/M-. I i Please refer to Jedda telegram 157 of 10th May, copy forwarded under EXT. 2156/44 of 19th May 1944 (not copied to Bahrein), regarding American request for permission to construct airfields in Saudi Arabia. 2. On October 3rd A.O.C. laddie East telegraphed stating that message had been received from Washington by local U.S.A.A.F. authorities requiring them to arrange immediately for the provision of Very Heavy Bomber Airfield at Dhahran, and that . reply had been sent to Kashin,.ton on A. O.C. 's advice requesting that proposal should be put as firm requirement to British Chiefs of Staff. Until such proposal as received no action is being taken by British authorities either at Washington or London. 3. Meanwhile, matter has been considered here provisionally under following heads:- (a) Our transport interests. Air Ministry consider that it would be advantageous to have large relief aerodrome of this kind provided it did not add to our maintenance difficulties in the area. Same relief could, however, possibly be afforded at perhaps less cost by Americans developing Abadan. As regards Bahrain, trouble is at present being experienced with use of runways by heavy aircraft, though by use of steel planking it is hoped that airfield will be fit for use by heavy aircraft by February next. To provide full length V.H.B. runways however, at Bahrain, would be major undertaking of many months and airfield would meanwhile be largely out of commission. (l aln replying separately to«jour express letter No. C/209 of 30th August regarding future use of Muharra.q aerodrome) (b) Constructional aspect. Owing to other liabilities in Middle East and Persian Gulf region at would probably be imp ossible for British Authorities to construct airfield at Dhahran of type proposed and Americans would have to do it themselves and at their own charge. (c) The American case. The Americans can probably make a good military case for building a heavy bomber airfield at Dhahran though it is doubtful whether they could justify prevision of V. II. B. airfield. The northern route via the Azores and Persian Gulf is being developed and will be much more heavily used than hitherto. It is possible, however, that development of Abadan may suit them as well for /practicalC T-i E T 10 e IITDIA oppici;. EXTERNAL DEPARTMllTT EXP^RS i LETTER (AIR MAIL) rs P'om: Secretary of State for India. Tp: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, i peated to: Government of India, External Affairs Department and - Political Agent, Bahroin. Dated: 2J$1' ITpvemher, 1944. . » No« Dxt. 52 28/44 . s v ^0 a Your express letter No. C/209 of 30th August regarding future use of Bahrein (Muharraq) Aerodrome. Matter has Been referred to Air Ministry, who comment as folows:- There is an underlying element of truth in Political Agent’s note of 23th August in so far as the natural runway at Bahrein has shown that in its present condition it will not stand up to continuous use hy aircraft with a., heavy wheel landing. Bahrein is, however, of such importance that we have already taken action to send out a supply of pierced steel planking which will go far to strengthen the runway and it is probable that in the near fujure we may decide to put down concrete. Bahrein is recognised as a vital link in our Imperial lino of communications and is likely to bo developed further from time to time. It is therefore possible to allay completely the Political Agent’s fears expressed in t c last sentence of paragraph three of his note in whicii he mentions the possibility of Bahrein being 'a complete failure .Lf Please see also my express letter BXT.4779/44 of 30th October, 1944. The issue of the above has been duly authorised. (Sgd.) R.crtffwa&gt; TiMtauu (Thia telegxum is of paxtioular seoreoy aud sbouia be retained by the authorised recipient and n^t ptisaeu mj W 5Z&gt;V&gt;/52/&lt;} Sxt. 2D9&lt;Sh5 cti'tm ivkcial (oiviXi Axa/tfinn) Ti?2-i mcmw iwige w jjmul . go, 179 D* 12..J5 p.ia* May ini, May 2nd, 19^5* Repeated to Washington oaviog idkl U,X^ in Saving tl • ^G;v£T SPACE \ My telegra So,9790 of 1%4 to Washington (airfield at Gofibine&lt;i Gldefs ^f StaiT have norar decided that in order to serve needs oi Fa^liasteru mr it is nt3Ce3o.&lt;ry for the bnited States forces to aoquure tuid construct a militai y air base at Dhairrun* situation has changed since jUst year (see ay telegram He .60 of 1944 ) when we thought that existing routes i^uld be capable of handling flow of aircrait to Par iiast, Ooutinuance of German wax has postponed British and United States deployment in Par Baetertwfchcatre and we are now obliged to iiove laiger ^uuntitios oi aircraft than oan be ootiveniently acoommodated at Bahrein and Abadan* 2. Your United States Colleague is being instructed to renew request to Xtei Sand for porridssion to constxuot airfield at and you should support his request when asked to do so, using arguments in paragraph 1 above# (Copies sent to Mr# Armstrong) OTPOUTWARD 'm&amp;uSUi.. EXT *209^45 G- U A E D (This t6legi&amp;a&gt; is of particular secrecy and should be retained by the aut loiised reoipxent and not passed on,) ai^8ClAL(QIYIL AVIaTKXO cnJiaK mLmmL^magLmjmL H o, 180 2ndi«Lay, 19^5 D, 10.35 e-tW# 3rd Ma/p 191*5 Repeated saving to: - Washington No, 1*03 nx,E, K.in No, or XXX daOHRT GUARD My imaediately preceding telegram. If questioned by the King about post-mr civil aviation aspect you should reply that construction of ioilitaiy airfield does not, (repeat not), confer aiqr right of civil use. Please see also last sentence of first paragraph of ray telegraia No,bO of 1944*~ 1 *A ($) 13/15 Telegram. S(^AD) From. Political Agent, Bahrain. To. Political Resident, at ohiraz. No. 484 Dated the 29th August 1945. For Pelly. Understand from BIRGR constructions on DHAHRAN Air field has begun and approximately 900 half 1800 Italians being employed. Allcard tells me four ships with equipment arriving shortly and work which will include 5 mile runway expected to be finished by January. POLITICAL 7 ' LR.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [*v. £, This is an ORIGIN AL MESSAGE, sent hy pnsf t 0 sar e telegraphic expe. se aid undue use of the ,vires, hui mtended to he treated, o&lt;i receipt, with the same ejpedotvn ,z&gt; &gt;f a had hren telegraphed. To sa e time a-d formalities it is warded a d si v ed as if it had been so despatched.\ TOP SECRST- Frgm Political Agent, Bahrain, at Shiraz. To Political Resident at Shiraz. P 13 DcrVu, 31st August, •? T have received a telegrani froin Bahrain saying that the American Vice-Consul, fhahran- has informed the Assistant Political Agent that the construction of the Dhahran Air Field has begun. Approximately 900 Italians are stated to be employed. Gray Mackenzie’s agent states that four ships with equipment are due to arrive and that the work will include a five mile runway expected to be completed by January. 2. For information. Political Agent, Bahrain. s 6 MFP— 40QS&amp;P—(M-480 - 26-7-34—2.00 * 0.81/38 0 lb Telegram S 3 From Political Rcirident at Shiraz. To India Office, London. Repeated Government of India, New Delhi. H.M.Minister, Jedda. (India Office please pass). No. T/418 Dated 1st September 1945. Correspondence ending with India Office endorsement No. Ext. 3470/45 July 21st. 2. PoliticaJ. Agent Bahrain has heard from American Vice-Consul Dhahran that construction of Bhahran airfield has begun and that approximately 900 Italians are to be employed. Bahrain agent of Gray Mackenzie states four ships with equipment are due to arrive and that work whi«h includes five mile runway is expected to be completed by January. GALLOWAY TOP SECRET Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Camp, Shiraz, No. C/231 1st September 1945. 0opy forwarded with compliments to tlhe Political Agent, Bahrain, ^ with reference to his Express Letter No. P 13 dated the 31st August 1945.EXT. 3956/45 vy 2 ^his telegram is of particular secrecy and should be retained by the authorised recipient and no*; passed on^ {cypher? SPECIAL (CIVIL AVlAIIQJf) FROM J-ffiDA TO POHLIGN OFFICE Mr*Grafftey Smith D: 1.4° p.au 10th August, 1945 No&gt; 359 8th August, 1945 R: 4.45 p.m* August, 1945 Repeated to Washington Saving M.E.Min's Office* t * co^nmriAL Washington telegram Wo*4909* My United States colleague and General Giles cocmanding American Army Air Forces Middle East visited Riyadh August 4th to August 7th in order to complete the agreement about construction of airfield at Dhahran* f * / W rX ^ 2. Agreement now recorded in exchange of notes respects Ibn Baud* s terms in paragraph 3 enclosure in my despatch No* 90* I suggest that State Department be asked by the Embassy at V/ashington, or War Department by our Military- Mission, for copy of lay United States colleague's note* I have seen the original but it was shown to me confidentially by Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs* The following details therein are interesting. 3* Airfield of maximum of five miles by five miles area and of base capacity of 500 persons extendable to 2,000 persons will be located in area known as Damman tracks, approximately 26° 20 north and 50° 10 east, 4. Americans propose to use about 3#000 imported /labourersV* labourers etc., to construct it including 500 Americans and 1*500 Italians. 5. An intermediate emergency airfield at Lauqa, approximately 29°56 north by 45°7i east will be constructed. 6. Navigational aids, meteorological services etc. will be installed at the airfield at Lauqa, and at Hafar- al-Batin, approximately 28°25 north by 45°35 east. 7* Airfield with all immovable installations, becomes Saudi Arabian government property on conclusion of the war with Japan. Privileged use by American farces ^^rp^undec. 7 as proposed originall^7 3 years ^grp.undec. ? after J ^/grp.undec*^ if the United States Government so decide. 8. General Giles assured Ibn Saud that use of airfield by British ^ Hit ary aircraft was automatic by standing Anglo-American agreement. 9* Permitted route of flight from Cairo passes Maan and follows Saudi-Iraqi frontier and then frontier of Koweit neutral zone through point named above avoiding Nefud Sesert and in general avoiding any large slab of Saudi territory. Foreign Office please pass to Washington as ipy telegram No. 44* ^Repeated to Washington telegram No.8321j7 '(This telegram is of particular secrecy and should he retained by the authorised recipient and not passed on) (CYPHER) SPECIAL (CIVIL AVIATION) FROH JEDDA TO FOREIGN OFFICE Mr. Grafftey Smith No. 595 29th August, 1945. D. 10.00 p.ra. 29th August, 1945. R.11.22 a.m. 30th August, 1945. Repeated to Washington, M.E.Min Saving IMPORTANT . &gt; ; , «// , ' - ' Confidential. My despatch No. 112 Space. % I have been informed confidentially by the Deputy Minister for Foreign Affairs of the two recent developments in Aierican civil aviation policy here. 2. United States Legation lias presented the Saudi Arabian Government with the draft of an agreement for reciprocal civil aviation facilities. No English text was presented and my informant was very vague about the details; but I understand that the United States draft is the standard raodel as presented to the Egyptian! Govern ant and others. You therefore presumably already nave the text. 3. So far as I could gather, the draft accords such.rights to United States aircraft to set down and pick uo traffic in Saudi Arabia as are 'normal in international civil aviation'. t 4. No monopoly is (2 grps. undec: ? apparently requested). 5. The second development reported is the form of applica tion by T.W.A. representative, Nicholls, now in Cairo to negotiate air services in Saudi Arabia. T.W.A. flew the Saudi Princes from New York to San Francisco and back and had already proposed to Emir Faisal in June last a concession to operate lines in Saudi Arabia or the formation of a joint or Saudi Arabian Company, offering considerable training facilities. Now T.W.A. have been granted Civil Aeronautics Board certificate to fly from six points in United States to Ceylon through Egypt, Palestine, Transjordan, Iraq, Saudi Arabia, Yemen, Asir Oman and Bombay and they press for negotiations with the Saudi Arabian Government. 6. Copy of T.W.A.'s letter which was received by the Saudi Arabian Government through the United States Legation ,,oes to you by air bag. 7. Saudi Arabian Government are flurried by these approaches and have asked for advice. Their attitude remains as slated ini my telegraa No. 323, to take advantage of any benefit offered froa (grp.undec) source and to spend no (repeat no) money themselves. 8. I suggest that consideration of T.W.A. application should be postponed until after the decision regarding the United States Govern ent's draft agreement, and that this decision should not be taken without consultation with neigh bouring Arab States to insure uniformity of action. I reminded the Deputy Minister for Foreign Affairs of His Majesty's Government's general views expressed in the enclosure to my despatch No.36. 9. The matter is likely to sleep until after Ramadan i. e. for ten days at least. If you have any observations or advice to offer or if you wish to sponsor competitive applications by British interests please telegraph before September 8th. 10. By all appearances the United States Government pro poses to proceed'with the construction of ''military' air field at Dhahran despite the termination of hostilities. f Foreign Office please pass to Washington as my telegram No. 47. (Repeated to Washington as telegram No. 9008) (Copy sent to Mr. Armstrong). 0. T. P.V ifl 1 / GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. 23) i m aowxiiiaiTiAX, . EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B .—This is an ORIGINAL message tent by AIR MAIL which provides a meant of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and it cheaper than the telegraph. It it intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition at if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It it authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] ^•rsian ttuif Residency, JMq,. 17 . -3 * To Repeated jrtsmmi Bushire, Date&lt; i&amp;&amp;M^ ) t}le 16th Januar3r . His Majesty 9 s Minister, Jedda . —^ H,M• Secretary of State for India, The India Office, London * The Secretary to the GoTemment of India in the External Affairs Department, Nee Delhi * The Political Agent, Baara in* my Anglo-I ran ian Oil Company, Abadan, hare addressed me stating that in the erent of landing ground at Dhahran being brought into use for commercial aircraft, they may wish to consider the establishment of refuelling facilities necessitating the erection and operation of bul* storage there, and hare enquired whether there are any existing concessional restrictions which may preclude their taking such a step* 3* Grateful for any information you can giro for eammunioation to the Company* Sd* (TSOFPtW PRIOR* Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested * &gt;r Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf* NHL* Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. . N«.—^9. Date.lld^k S. 44. MFP—1015 S&amp;P—(M-1870)—9-2-39—20,000. {Signature) (DesignationOur reference R. 6301/45• 16th October, 1946. Dear Balk,/ill. What v/e now know of the performance of the Tudor II has compelled us to revise our ideas as to the Staging Posts that will be used on the India, Far Rastem, and Australian routes when these aircraft come irito operation early next year. It is clear that Bahrein, the contemplated stop in the Persian Gulf area, is inadequate for the Tudor II, and cannot be made adequate except at very great expense and after considerable delay. We believe, however, that the airfield at Dhahran is probably suitable for use by Tudor II aircraft with little, if any, constructional alteration and while it is inconvenient from a traffic point of view, we have little alternative but to consider its use if the Tudor II is to fly the India route by the target date. ' , ,/e would now ask you therefore to take formal steps to obtain for us the rights that we shall need at Dhahran:- (^i) The right of transit over Saudi Arabiah territory and uhe right of tecnnical stop on a route between Cairo and Karachi, either direct oi* via Lydda and Baghdad or Basra. (This latitude in respect of the actual route is necessitated by uncertainty as to the adequacy of the intermediate airfield). (ii) Third and Fourtn Freedom rights, in respect of traffic between Dhahran and U.K. territories and . J % / (iii) F. G. B.al:v/ill, 2sq. , roreigi Office, Downing Street, S.1.(iv) That U.S. aircraft should be allov/ed Fifth Freedon lights at the airfield subject to the right of the Saudi Arabian Asveminent to cancel the peimission at six months' notice. It is presumably in accordance with these provisions that T. ...a. have concluded an operational agreement with uhe Saudi Arabian ^veinment for a peiioa of tvio years in f ' , respect of their service between uairo and Bombay, as ^ ^ r reported in Jedda Telegram No. b9 Saving or the lltn July 1946. It seems clear from this correspondence that it rests with King Ton Saud to grant the use of this airfield to British ' aircraft, and that we should be jusitifed in asking for the same teims as have been granted to American airlines. I ought perhaps to add that .;e aould certainly not agree to any of the absurd conditions referred to in telegram No. 68. ... Saving from Jedda of July 11th. ^ *' Vv ' ' Two final points, First, the route from the U.K. to Austrdia is to be operated in parallel partnership by B.G.A.C. on behalf of the U.K. and Qantas on behalf of Astralia. Je do not yeo know u.efinitely whether Cantas will want to use Dhahran but if they do, the Australian Government will no doubt wish us to secure the necessary permission for them. Presumably, this matter could be taken up separately at a later stage if necessary. India also in due course may want to use Dhahran. Secondly, B.O.A.C. want detailed information about Dhahran. airfield. ,7e are telegraphing to the C.A.A. Cairo for tnis in the first instance, but if he fails we may have to ask you to telegfaph uraffity Smith. Yours sincerely (Sgd) L. J. Dunnett. P.S. I am sending a copy of this letter to Miss Holdgate (.dominions Qfficej and to France (India Office).* • 5 . r IITOIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.l. f! N ovembe r, 1946. We have seen a^tipy of your letter to Balkwill N 0 .R. 63 OI/ 45 of 16th Octob&lt;2r7 in which you request the Foreign Office to take steps to obtain rights for British aircraft to use the Dhahran airfield. 2 . I am not clear whether this indicates a general intention for all B.O.A.C. services to use Dhahran instead of Bahrein in future. If so, we should be glad to know, so that the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may be informed and may be given an opportunity to comment on the local and political consequences. 3. We have also heard that B.O.A.C. may cease to use the flying boat base at Bahrein, as their present flying boats become obsolete, and that the R.A.F. will shortly cease to station personnel there. 4* We cannot of course question the views of the experts on .•the technical capacity of the Bahrein airfield or mooring facilities, but from the political point of view it would be a pity if Bahrein were to be side-tracked altogether in favour of Dhahran by the main civil aviation route. 5* I am sending copies of this letter to Balkwill (F.O.), Miss Holdgate (D.O.), and Low at the Air Ministry, L.J. Dunnett Esq., Ministry of Civil Aviation, Ariol House, Strand, W.C.2. Vouv’c v**ne\QrK&gt;%', . H ^ *= S U.)NALDS®|\ N \\i/ o i-iXP rJ^SS L^TT^ii From To Repeated Dated No. Secretary of State for India. Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrein. Government of India, External Affairs Dept. 12th December, 1946. Ext. 8289/46. Reference your express letter No. 1023 - S of 16th November, 1946. Use of Dhahran and Bahrein airfield by B.O.A.C. 2. Copy of ma rginally noted correspondence M.C.A. letter dated 25.11.’46.) is forwarded for your Ext. 7974/46 dated 28.11.'46.) information. I will M.C.t.. letter dated 9.12. *46 ) keep you informed of any further developments. The issue of the above has been duly authorised. Sd. F. A. K. Harrison. confidential No. 48 - S. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. the 6th January, 1947. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, Bahrain. u • A • M • Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. 8 ' ( 4Y DateExt 7974/46. • Ministry of Civil Aviation, Ariel House, Strand, Temple Bar. 2466. Ext. 344. London, W.C.2. 25th November, 1946. Reference : - R.27007/46. Dear Donaldson, Many than}f«'' for your letter of November 11th, Ext. 7540/46, 'about the use of Dhahran airfield. 2. The question of using Dhahran instead of Bahrein arises only in connection with the Tudor II. It is the present intention that B.O.A.C. flying boats should continue to pass through Bahrein. Unfortunately the land airfield at Bahrein has neither the bearing strength nor length to be suitable for Tudor II aircraft and if we are to get these aircraft through to India, we have no alternative but to use Dhahran. 3 . as it happens, however, we are seriously considering the question whether a large airport should be constructed at Bahrein. Dhahran is certainly not ideal. The trouble is that the construction of an air port at Bahrein would be extremely expensive, and we may have difficulty in persuading the Treasury. We will, of course, let you know as soon as we have made up our minds on this project. If, as a long term project, we decide to press for an airport at Bahrein, I hope that we should have your support. 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to the recipients of yours. » Yours sincerely, Sd. L. J. Dunnett. I E. P. Donaldson, Esquire, India Office, Whitehall, S. W. 1. Copied.Ext 7974/46. India Office, Whitehall, 'London, S.W.l. 28th November, 1946. # dated 16th Nov. with enclosure. Dear Dunne tt, Thank yoj* / Tor your letter No. R.27007/46 of the 25th November about the use of Dhahran and Bahrein by the B.O.A.C. •* 2. From our own point of view we would certainly be in favour of the construction of a large and up to date airport at Bahrein if financial considerations do not preclude it and you may count on our support on general political grounds if you decide to press for this. You may also like to rally the Ministry of Fuel and Power in view of the oil interests in the area. 3. I enclose in this connection a copy of an express letter just received from the Political Resident. It would appear that although a flying boat (Sunderland) service will continue to pass through Bahrein after the withdrawal of the 1 C class flying boats, this may nevertheless involve a reduction in the present scale of facilities for the carriage of air mail and passengers from Bahrein, v^e should be grateful for any further information you can give us on this point in order that we may, if possible, be able to reassure the Political Resident in the matter. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter to Balkwill and Low. Yours sincerely, Sd. E. P. Donaldson. L. J. Dunnett, Esquire, Ministry of Civil Aviation, Ariel House, Strand, W.C.2. Copied. G. A. M.Ext. 8289/46. I 3^-f Temple ^&gt;ar. 2466. Our reference - R 27771/46/ii. C. A. 1. Dear Donaldson, ill you ui^ase refer to your letter to Dunnett Ext. 7974/46 of 28th November about the use of Dhahran and Bahrein by 3.O.A.C. ;.ith regard to the question raised by the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, in paragraph 3 of his letter of 16th November, as to what provision there will be for carriage of air mail and passengers from Bahrein when the 'C' class flying boats are withdrawn from the route, I am afraid that B.O.A.C. have not yet reached a definite decision regarding the passenger traffic emanating from the Persian Gulf generally. We will, hov/ever, keep this matter before us and endeavour to let you have some definite information shortly. As to the air mail from Bahrein, there should be no difficulty about this, as accommodation will be available on the 'Hythe 1 flying boat services passing through the station. Yours sincerely, Bd. .... E. P. Donaldson, Esquire, India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.l. Copied. Ministry of Civil Aviation, Ariel House, Strand, London, Vv.C.2. 9th December, 1946. G. A. M •Extract from t he Ministry of Ci vil Aviation Middle East Summary No. 5 Oaiz 24. The Saudi Arabian Government has agreed in principle to the use by B.O.A.C. of bhahran airfield but have asked for further information about the services which we intend to operate. The Far Eastern Survey Party will visit Dhahran to confrim its suitability for \ use by Tudor II aircraft. SECRET No.269-S Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. The 11th February, 1947. Forwarded with compliments to :- The Political Agent, Bahrain. BR. Confidential. ft*.... BAHRAIN RECEIPT. ZlA: Date t.?jA DateThe Hor^ble the Political Resident in the lL2aC/gg., Persian Gulf presents his compliments to - THE POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN . and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents* OFFICE OF THE POLITICAL RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULF, aboard H.M.S* 'Wildgoose”, At Sea, dated the 30th March 1947. Reference to previous correspondences 1 ) 2 ) DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURES f 37 Foreign Office telegram to Jedda No.5 Saving dated 3rd March 1947. Jedda telegram to Foreign Office—' No.459 dated 22nd December 1946. 3) Foreign Office telegram to Jedda No.441 dated 14th November 1947. SUBJECT: CIVIL AVI A TION RIGHTS AT DHAH RAN AIRFIELD. NPG. rE / 5. mr - j V^5) COPY ' ' ' ’ Ext 495/47 (This telegram is of particular secrecy and should be retained by the authorised recipient and not passed cm). m CHAIR. CIVIL AVTATXSJ DISTRIBUTION FROL FOREIGN OFFICE TO JEDDA No. 5 . Saving* 3rd March 1947. Repeated to: Cairo, No. 11. Saving. Y/:V/: 7:7/: tf:W:V/:W IMPORTANT. SP7iCE Your telegram No. 459 (of Aviation rights at Dhahran airfield). December 22nd: Civil * j e require ft&gt;r aircraft of B.O.A.C. and associated companies operating on the services specified in paragraph 2 below the rights - (a) to fly over Saudi Arabian territory. (b) to land at .Dhahran for refuelling and maintenance; (c) to set down at Dhahran passengers, mail and freight taken cn in United Kingdom territory as well as the right to pick up passengers, mail and freight at Dhahran for destinations in United Kingdom territory; (d) to pick up or put down at Dhahran passen era mail and freight originating from or bound for destinations other than United Kingdom territory. In accordance with the Bermuda principles, we would propose that this ri^ht should be subject to the provision that the capacity provided on the services operating through Dhahran would be relatedp0\ ^ wmm 9il.j ^neblao LsoJt^ tlc4 3il.'i sXcPut ^*1’*’ — cl Iflfliilt &lt;v-inch?* Cxrrrr *&gt; f ^ iwB9L&gt; #• 3T the traffic requirements between United . ^ Kinpdaa territory and the points of destination of the service. This would mean that the capacity available for picking up traffic at Dhahran for destinations in other than Tkiited Kingdom territory would be limited to fill-up space. 2 The services for which we require rl^its at Dhahran are the trunk services between the United r ingdcm Australia and the Far Bast. The total frequency is not expected to exceed three times daily but w® suggest that this' estimated figure should not be disclosed now unless you are pressed to give details, uhe route ^ Saudi Arabian territory either from Cairo or lydda direct, or via Bagdad or Basra, to Dhahran and would go thence to Karachi and points beyond. t The tern 'United Kingdom territory', wherever used, is to be interpreted as including, in addition to the homeland, any territory which is under the sovereignty, suzerainty, protection, mandate or trusteeship ox he. United Kingdom. • L. 'in view of the fact that Saudi Arabia is not a signatory of the I.C.A.N. or P.I.C.A.O. documents, we should wish to have the following additional assurances.- (a) that any charges levied on United Kingdoiu aircraft for the use of the airport and ancillary facilities at Dhahran would not be higher than tne charges levied on airettift of any other oointry 01 ^. those paid by Saudi Arabian aircraft engaged in similar international services (b) that fuel, lubricating oil and spare parts taken on board United Kingdom aircraft in Saudi Arabian territory and intended solely for use by United Kingdom aircraft would receive treatment in respect of Customs duties, inspection fees and other charges not less favourable than that accorded to aircraft of any other country o** Saudi Arabian aircraft engaged on similar intemati .nal services. (c)/(c) that aircraft in transit, and fuel and lubricating oil and aircraft spares and stores retained cn board United Kingdom aircraft would be exempt from Customs duties inspection fees and similar duties or charges. 5. , By 'associated companies' in paragraph 1 above, we have chiefly in mind British companies such as Skyways operating charter flights in close association with B.O.A. C. or a British Commonwealth Company such as the Australian Q.E.A. operating in parallel partnership with 3.G.A.C. If Saudi Arabian authorities raise objection to the addition of these words, we should not wish to prejudice our chances of obtaining the rights we require £&gt;r 3.0*A.C. by pressing at this stage for tne inclusion of the words in question* 6* It is possible that B*0*A*C* may need some accommodation at Etiahran, in which case they would presumably have to arrange for its erection themselves* As, however, this is by no means certain you may feel it would be best not to refer to it at this stage in L [jQ * the formal application to the Saudi Arabian Government# ' ?• »/e are not clear what you have in mind in your reference to rt (b) Saudi Arabian conditions”* As / explained in paragraph 4 of y telegram No. 441 conditions referred to in your telegram Saving No* 68 are quite unaccepta le. Apart from claiming reciprocal rights Saudi Arabians should impose no conditions, although you could point out to them that the provision in paragraph 1 (d) above will insure that any local air services which may eventually be started by Saudi Arabia would be protected fran undue competition by our aircraft on trunk routes* This is an important limitation which, we voluntarily accept*@ ip COSY Ext 8556/46. OUT&lt;//iBD TELEGKAI&gt;I. Z^his telegraui is of particular secrecy and should be retained by the authorised recipient and not passed cn./ *Y. 102444 3/802. From Foreipgi Office to Jedda. No. 441. 14th November, 1946. Repeated to Basra No. 62. Bagdad Ho. 999 Cairo No. 1957. SPACE. CITIL AVIATION . D. 1.15 p.au 15th November, 1946. My telegram No. 418 /llth October: Civil Aviation in Saudi Arabia/ Bahrain has no adequate airfield for the Tudor XI which it is hoped to introduce early next year on the routes from the United Kingdom to India, Australia and the Far East. It is thought that airfield at Dahahran would probably be only suitable alternative. 2 * Please therefore ask the Saudi Arabian Government for the following rights at Dhahrans ( a ) of transit over Saudi Arabian territory and of technical stop on a route between Cairo and Karachi, either direct or via lydda and Bagdad or via Basra. * Actual route depends on adequacy of inte mediate airfield: ( D ) Third and fourth Freedom in respect of traffic between Dhahran and United Kingdom territories: (c)/(c). Fifth Freedom in accordance with Bennuda s pxinciples, in respect of 'fill up' traffic within the capacity required for traffic between point* of origin and destination* We should expect to be accorded the same times as the Americans (see paragraphs 3 and 4 of your telegram No* 69 Saving) LAX 4* You should make it clear if necessary that^ we could not agree to conditions referred to in your telegram No* 68 Saving. imCOPT Ext 8556/47 Code R. % From Jedda to Foreij^n Office , Mr* (Jrafftey Smith. D. No. 459. 22nd December, 1946. R. Repeated to Cairo SAVING. CIVIL AVTATICN DISTRIBUTIOII 12.45 p.nu 22nd December, 1946. 6.20 p.m. 22nd December, 1946. SPACE Your telegram No. 441. Saudi Arabian Government are in principle quite willing to offer ua faci ities similar to those enjoyed by the Americans but they request the statement of our needs under paragraph 2 (b) and (c) of your telegram inder reference in simple language and in specific terms of (a) our requirements for the air service contemplated and (b) Saudi Arabian conditions. 2. Text of the Bermuda resolution is no less legalistic and involved in the Arabic translation than in the original, and Saudi’s are by nature alarmed by present at ic3H of any demand in the /^rp. undec. ? lan&amp;iagef of general principles. 3. Please fumish me with precise and factual definition of our requirements for their consideration.j J ifixtract from M.C.A. under India Office Middle 3ast Summary No.7 (Received endorsement No. ifixt.975 dated 2nd May 1947) SAUDI ARABIA . 101 . the U.K ciated The Saudi Arabian Government have been notified of . requirements for the rights for B.O.A.C. and asso- companies operating on the services specified below;- ^ \. right to fly over Saudi Arabia (freedom one) ii) The exercise of freedom two, three, four and five at Dhahran. The services for which these rights are required are the tranK services between U.K. and India, Australia and the i?ar aast. The route would enter Saudi Arabian territory er-rier from Cairo or Lydda direct or via Baghdad or Basra to Dhahran and would go thence to Karachi and beyond. Additional requirements include assurances from trie °audi Arabian Government that charges levied on U.K. aircraft for the use of the airport at Dhahran and for fuel, o! Jpd spares taken on board in 3.A. territory, would not be higher than those levied on aircraft of any other country or on 3.A. aircraft engaged on international services. ** ** ** ** ** 122. q A proposal for a M.S.A.T. Board service Cairo-Baghdad- Basra-Bahrain has been discussed with B.O.A.C. who do not agree with the proposal on the grounds that (a) it is im- Board services at a time when . ?. 3 difuculty in substantiating a H raison d’etre’* for existing ones and (b) a service Cairo-Bahrain which would cater for passengers to and from the U.K. would impose an unacceptable additional strain on U.K. - Cairo service which is already severely taxed, due to recent reduction in frequency. ■ x. Aitern ative proposals for serving Bahrain by a l lying boat service are under consideration by tne Corporation. CONFIDENTIAL . No. 895-S. Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, the 13th May 1947. RHL. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, i / !*•... . OEIPT. /&lt;, *r, • &gt; •• .••»••*•••••»&lt; iD.O. So. 1872-S mmajmi i ttM 30th October, 194? K to my dool-official latter ho.1808-8 dated the 17th October, 1947. 2. 1 father that the B.O.A.C. are atill encountering many difficulties at Dhahran. There is no accommodation there for their staff or pass engers and owing to the Saudi Arabian Government's senseless quarantine restrictions there is little or no direct communication beteeen the B.O.A.C. staffs et Dhahran and Bahrain and messages between the two places have to be sent via Karachi. 3. I understand that there is a proposal afoot that the B.O.A.C. land planes should use Buharraq aerodrome instead of Dhahran. I an told that the hunarraq aerodrome will easily taka the aircraft in •question but that the Air Ministry are anxious about the wear and tear of their perforated steel plates. Surely it should be possible to reach some compromise on this point and extricate to* BeOoAmCm fro» th« uncomfortable and hualliatlne position which they at present occupy at Dhahran ? Sd/- W.R. Hay, P» Donaldson. Esquire. CosuBonwealth Relations Office. King Charles Street. Whitehall. umiL, §tVii •LB* EQj2§2Sz§ ^ giBg*AN BAHRAIN , the 30th October, 1947 Copy forwarded with compliments to:- 1) H.iPs Minister, JEDDA , with reference to Residency Endorsement^o.l847-S dated 27th October, 1947. [. Y'V 2) The Political Agent, BAHRAIN , Confidential, BAHRAIN R^EIPt. v ( 7 1 56 /^ V 'LB*COPY . EXT 2530/47 Ministry of Civil Aviation, Ariel House, Strand, W.C 2 Temple Bar 2466 12th November, 1947. ' ^ Ext. 616 V' /&gt; :he route Our reference H.43741/47/B.0&gt;A.1 . J A ^ - Dear Hallows, I am writing with reference to your letter Ref: Ext 2437/47 'dated loth November 1947 to Garran, dealing with the use by B.O.A.C. of the aerodrome at Dhahran. 2. Following a proposal by B.O.A.C. Headquarters to route the U.K./India service through Bahrain in pref erence to Dhahran, we asked the Air Ministry whether they would be prepared to permit B.O.A.C. to operate these York services through Bahrain, on the understand ing that the Corporation would provide the necessary personnel for handling services and that no additional commitments would fall on the R.A.F. 3. The Air Ministry, in reply, stated that there w was little doubt that the runway at Bahrain would deter iorate rapidly if t .ere were extensive operations of this type of aircraft, and that in wet weather particular ly, the danger of deterioration would be more marked. They pointed out that during a period when aircraft with tyre pressures of 60 lbs per squsre inch operated through this airfield, fcjtsHak the -natural surface was badly cut up, and caused rapid deterioration of the P.S.P. In these circumstances, their view was that B.O.A.C. would be taking considerable risk in operating Yorks at Muharraq. 4. We have informed the Corporation of the Air Ministry 1 s recommendationsknd, while we have not yet had their considered views, it is understood that the Corporation are unlikely to change/from Dhahran to Bahrain despite the lack of passenger handling facilities and the other difficulties at the former place. 5. It has been reported that Margil (Basra) airfield, which has been undergoing repairs, will be available for services with effect from 15tn November, from which date the York services to India will operate through that airfield in the eastbound direction. Whether or not it will also be possible to route the west-bound services via Margil, depends on an approach which is being made to the Iraq Government, to lift the ban on aircraft from India operating through Iraq territory. Yours sincerely, sd. J.Macpherson. P.3. I am sending a copy of this letter to Low. R.I.Hallows, Esq., Commonwealth Relations Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.lCOPY. ( This telegram is of particular secrecy and should be ) ( retained by the authorised recipient and not passed on.) CYPHER/OTP CIVIL AVIATION DISTRIBUTION. FROM JEDDA TO FOREIGN OFFICE. Mr. Llark D. 8.00 a.m. October 24th, 1947 No. 344 ’ October 23rd., 1947 R. 5.40 p.m. October 24th, 1947 Repeated to Civatt Cairo and Washington. / . SPACE ’ ^'' CONFIDE! TIAL. ^ Washington! telegram No. 5745 to Foreign Office. B.O.A.C. use of Dhahran. I understand messing facilities are being provided on instructions of Minister of Finance but that there acute shortage of housing at Dhahran and that United States Ai Force have scarcely sufficient for their own needs. Aramco who are anxious to encourage the develop ment of Dhahran as civil air port are pressing Minister of Finance to proceed with erection of necessary buildings but this will take time and cannot help B.O.A.C. in the present difficulties. Foreign Office please pass to Washington as my telegram No. 8 ( Repeated to Washington )</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00033a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/523</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00033a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/523</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 13/15 Air base at Dhahran’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-04-16T08:12:26</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (45 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 45-46) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover, and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-39; these numbers are also written in pencil, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence, but they are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence relating to the construction by the United States of an airfield at Dhahran in Saudi Arabia. The majority of the correspondence in the file was received by rather than sent from the Political Agency in Bahrain. Correspondence comes from the Political Residency, officials at the India and Foreign Offices, the Secretary of State for India, and the British Legation at Jedda.Correspondence from mid-1944 to mid-1945 documents the United States Air Force’s desire to construct an airfield capable of accommodating ‘very heavy bombers’ at Dhahran, in order to maintain military supply lines to the Far East theatre of war. This is in response to Britain’s airfield at Muharraq in Bahrain being inadequate for the use of larger aircraft, to the concern of British officials. Details of the extent of the American airfield, construction of which began in August 1945, are given in correspondence from the Political Agent to the Political Resident (ff 14-15). A confidential telegram from the British Legation at Jedda confirms an agreement reached between the United States Army Air Force and the Saudi Government for the construction of the airfield (f 18).Post-war correspondence, covering the period late-1945 to 1947 documents the use of the Dhahran airfield for civil aviation purposes. This includes British Overseas Airways Corporation’s (BOAC) negotiations with the United States to use Dhahran for their Avro 688 Tudor II aircraft, being introduced on the air route to India, and which are too heavy to land at Muharraq (f 26). Correspondence between Ministry of Civil Aviation and India Office officials in late 1946 discusses the redevelopment of Muharraq to accommodate heavy aircraft, though acknowledging that there would be ‘difficulty in persuading the Treasury’ of such a project (f 31).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Overseas Airways Corporation</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>United States Army Air Forces</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00033a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>