<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001a9_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T09:18:13.365Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SIR ALFRED FAULKITER pointed out that there was no likelihood whatever of Mosul Oil Fields Ltd. constructing an independent pipeline to Haifa. If Haifa were to he the Mediterranean terminal, the Company would obviously make some arrangement to benefit by the existing pipeline system - pumping stations, roads, etc. - of the I.P.G. THE CHAIRMAN suggested that something might be done by drawing the attention of the British Chairman of Mosul Oil Fields -G-td. to the economy which would be effected by taking advantage of the existing I.P.C. pipeline facilities. This would furnish a sound economic argument which could be reinforced by the s ecurity argument which had already been alluded to. SIR EDGAR LUDLOW-HEWITT thought that the proximity of a pipeline to the Turkish frontier would be a strategic attraction to Turkey. He suggested that we should point out to the French the advantage of utilising the existing I.P.C. pipeline from Haditha to Tripoli for the transport of Mosul Oil Fields Ltd 03 oil 9 as they would thus have only one pipeline to protect,, He quite understood the reluctance of the I*p.C a to co-operate with Mosul Oil Fields Ltd 0 9 until oil was definitely found in the latter's area 9 west of t he Tigris. SIR FRANCIS HUMPHRYS said that until drilling was completed it was impossible to say v/hether oil was likely to be found in oommercial quantities west of the Tigris. The matter was very speculative and he had, at present, no grounds for optimism. SIR ALFRED FAULKNER said it was obviously impossible for His Majesty's Government to protect a pipeline via 5- 6 - Aleppo, which ran through French territory. had used this argument in his discussions with Viscount G^schen, Chairman of Mosul Oilfields Ltd. THE CHAIRMAN observed that the present situation seemed far too speculative to render any satisfactory agreement between the two Companies possible. Until Mosul Oil Fields Ltd. had definitely struck oil and the quality of that oil had been proved, the I.P.C. could hardly be expected to commit themselves to any arrangement. MR. STARLING mentioned the possibility of the Italian group ultimately securing control of Mosul Oil Fields Ltd. by buying up shares at present held by the British group. He asked what the effect of this would be on the position. THE CHAIRMAN replied that, in his view, such a development would not necessarily be to our disadvantage, since the Italians would probably prefer that the terminal of the pipeline should not be under French control, and might therefore be all the readier to reach some agreement by which that terminal should be at Haifa. The question of the security of a piepline along the northern frontier of Syria was then further discussed. SIR EDGAR LUDLOW-HEWITT pointed out that the French forces in Syria were amply sufficient to protect the pipe line against any ordinary risks, from e.g. marauding oands. The only real dangers would be either a war between France and Turkey or the peaceful absorption of northern Syria by Turkey. SIR FRANCIS HUMPHRYS pointed out that in either event the situation would be extremely serious for the Iraqi Government, as Mosul would be threatened from its West flank.iuh. oiAhLllNii pointed out that the 'iurhish Governuient would have a considerable interest in protecting the pipeline, since TurKe^, under the Treaty of angora, is to receive for a period of years a percentage of the royalties paid to the Iraqi Governrixent in respect of all oil won in northern Iraq. IKE CiiaIIilh-i.ll felt considerable doubt whether the dangers to the pipeline wnich had been referred to were lihely seriously to affect the situation. Sir Edgar Ludlow-Hewitt had explained that the urench could deal with ordinary dangers. In what he regarded as the unlixely event of hostilities between Turxey ana Syria, or of the absorption of northern Syria by lurhey, Turxey would, as ivir. Starling had pointed out, iiave every interest in maintaining the safety of the pipeline, moreover, as the pipeline would be an international interest, in which Italy, Germany, and other countries would ail be interested, it was improbable tnat a belligerent wouud court trouble with the countries concerned by seriously interfering with it, even if local hostilities should break, out. CAITaIK fiCOnE said that in certain circumstances it might be an advantao© to have three oil terminals on the Mediterranean coast, which a separate line from Mosul would involve. The I.f.C. line to Haifa would only have a capacity of four million tons of oil, which was a little over half our war requirements. Unless the I.r.C. line to Haifa was doubled, an arrangement wnereoy the B.Q.D. used the former’s line would not increase the output at Haifa beyond four million tons. A third terminal delivering another four million tons would meet the full Admiralty requirements, and leave a balance over. He suggested that if a recommendation was required as to tne strategic value of alternative pipe lines the opinion of the Chiefs of Staff Committee or the - 7 -The ideal Joint Planning Sub-Committee snould be asmed. solution for the Admiralty would be lor all Mosul Oil Fields Ltd. oil to be brought to Haifa independently ol the I.r.C. If this were impossible there might be certain advantages in an independent line ending at Alexandretta, which might be preferable to Tripoli. aIH COMMODORE PIERSS pointed out that the present pipe line bifurcated at naaitha to Tripoli and Haifa respectively. If mosul Oil Helds Ltd. snould arrange to utilise the I.P.C. pipeline system, they might eitner join the I.P.C. line east or west of Haditha. This was an important point because if east of Haditha it would be possible in war to divert B.O.D. oil to Haifa and in peace, if oil were developed in large quantities, there would still be the possibirity ol inducing the company to mahe use ol tne Haiia line. On the o + her hand, id tne junctioxi were made west of Haditna, there would be no possibility at all of any B.O.D. oil following any but the Tripoli route. It was important, therefore, to secure that if the I.P.C. pipeline system were used by Mosul Oil lields Ltd., the Mosul Oil Fields' line should join the I.P.C. system east of Haditha. Him CHaIjaMaB said that it was clear that the Sub-Committee unanimously agreed tnat the ideal solution would be that the Mosul Oil tie ids oil snouid ue bi ought to Haifa, an cl a^ the possibility ox an independent pipeline to Haiia seemed excluded, tne oest practicable solution would be an agreement between Mosul Oil Fields Ltd. and the I.P.C. lor the use of tne latter’s pipeline, under which the bulx of the oil should be brought to Haifa. The Sub-Committee were hot however, as to the relative advantages of the various alternatives other than Haifa. Captain Moore had drawn attention to tne possible advantages IT om theAdmiralty point of view, if it should prove impossible to secure the transport of the bulk, of the oil to Haifa, of an entirely independent pipeline system, preferably with an independent terminal- This was a new point of view, which obviously would require careful consideration by the Service Departments concerned, and he suggested that the Joint Planning Sub-Committee should be asked to give an opinion as to which of the various alternatives other than Haifa would be preferable from the point of view of His Majesty’s Government, in order that the policy to be followed in further discussions with Mosul Oil Fields Ltd., might be framed accordingly- CONCLUSION. THE SUB-COMMITTEE AGREED:- (a) that the most satisfactory practicable solution from the point of view of His Majesty’s Government would be that the oil produced by Mosul Oil Fields Ltd-, should be conducted to Haifa- (b) That the Secretary of the Committee of Imperial Defence should be asked to obtain an opinion as to the comparative strategic value of the following alternative alignments, if the transport of the oil to Haifa should prove impossible s- (i) from Mosul to Tripoli via the existing I.P.C. pipeline, point of junction being east of Kaditha; (ii) from Mosul to Tripoli by the existing I.P.C. pipeline, point of junction being west of Haditha; (iii) an independent pipeline from Mosul to Tripoli; (iv) an independent pipeline from Mosul to Alexandretta- - 9 -(THIS DOCUMENT IS T 'HE PROPERTY OF _H IS_ BRITAH NIG MAJESTY'S G-QA^RNMENT) . SECRET* M.E.(0) 95. - COPY HO. C OMUTT EE OP IMP ERI A L DEFE NCE. ST ANDING ORF ICIAI. SUB-COM MITT EE FOR QUEST IONS CONCERNI NG T EE MIDDLE EAST* MOSUL OIL FIELDS, LTD. , AND THE BRIIISH OI L DE VE LOPMENT CONCES S ION IN I RAQ. PDOPC MED F IDETiII TS FROM THE MOSUL AREA TO THE ME D ITERRANEAN. Note Uy th e Se cretary . 1. The Mines Department of the Board of Trade have brought the question of the proposed pipeline from the British Oil Development Company 1 s concession near Mosul' in Iraq to the Mediterranean^ to the notice of the Committee of Imperial Defence. S# The attached memorandum by the petroleum Department has* at the direction of the Secretary of the Committee of Imperial Defence* been referred for consideration in the first instance by the Official Sub-Committee for Questions Concerning the Middle East* as to whether there is a case on strategic or other grounds for action by His Majesty's Government to influence the choice of alignment of the proposed pipeline* and* if so* what action is most likely to be effective. 3. This paper has also been circulated to the Oil Board for information. (Signed) G. HIND * Secretary to the Sub-Committee. S* Whitehall Gardens* S*W* 1* * 14th June* 1933. •Vc .1 . I f % ' | c I'losul Oilfields Limited and the British Oil. Development Co ncession in Iraq. Memorandum ~by Petroleum Department* 1 • Introductory. On 20th April s 1932 5 the Iraq Government granted an oil concession to the British Oil Development Company Limited over the western portion of Iraq. The con cession is for a period of 75 years and covers an area of about 40,000 square miles, comprising all Iraq lands situated west of the River Tigris and north of the thirty- third parallel of latitude. A special law confirming the British Oil Development Concession was passed and published in the Official Gazette on 29th May, 1932. This is reckoned as the date of the commencement of the Concession. The Company (for details of present allocation of capital see paragraph 6 below) must be and remain a British Company registered in Great Britain and the Chairman must be a Britisn subject. There is, however, a large foreign interest in the Company. The concession cannot be assigned to another company except with the consent of the Iraq Government, but there is nothing in the concession to prevent foreign capital securing a controlling interest. 2. The area east of the Tigris (apart from the Transferred Territories) is held by the Iraq Petroleum Company, under a revised Agreement dated March 24th, 1931. The Iraq petroleum Company has already drilled a number of successful wells in the neighbourhood of Kirkuk and has commenced the construction of pipelines to the Mediterranean with an approximate annual capacity of some 4 million tons. The Iraq petroleum Company’s pipeline runs from Kirkuk to4 to Haditha on the Euphrates where it divides, one 'branch running 'by the Northern route through French Syria to Tripoli; the southern 'branch runs through Iraq and Palestine territory via Ruthah 3 terminating at haifa* These pipelines are due, under the concession, for compleoion in 1935, hut such good progress has been made that it is thought they will he completed v/ell in advance ox the stipulated date. 0h ligations of the British Oi l Devel oP 1 ?*-h_ Q under thei r concession. 3 . The British Oil Development Company has undertaken ohligations which may he shortly summarised as follows:- (a) To commence a detailed geological survey in three different districts within eight months of tne date of the Concession. This is now being carried out. (h) To start drilling within 18 months (i.e. by November 29th, 1933) with a minimum of 3 drilling rigs and to increase the number to 9 rigs within one year of oil being struck. (c) To make arrangements for the transport of one million tons of oil per annum to the Mediterranean and within Vi years (i.e. by November, 1939) to commence the regular transport of oil. Not less than one million tons to be exported in any one year (provided that it can be made a'vailaole with reasonable diligence on the part of the Company and is of '’merchantable quality”) • The Company has the right under Article (6) to fix the alignment of the pipeline. (d) To pay annual dead rents on the following scale until the commencement of regular exports: On the 1st January, 1933 £100,000 (gold) ,t it t* » 1934 £125,000 ' u tt u ' 1935 £150,000 '3 . On the 1st January 5 1935 £175,000 (gold) w •» » »* 1937 £200,000 ,r and of a similar amount on the 1st January in each succeeding year. (The 1933 payment has already been made) . (e) Royalty at the rate of 4/- per ton until a date 20 years after the commencement of regular exports, thereafter to be revised every ten year's by reference to the profits of the Company in the preceding period. Minimum royalty £ 200,000 per annum conditional on the oil obtained being of ’’Merchantable quality”. The Iraq Government is entitled to 20 per cent. oj. all petroleum v/on, free of cost at the well head, but no royalty is payable in respect of tnis oil and the Government may not export such oil although it can sell it back to the Company at a price to be agreed. (f) Certain payments in lieu of taxation of profits. Petroleum prospects of the terri tory covered^ the Concession. 4. Little definite information is available oi the prospects of this territory as geological surveys have not yet been completed and no test drilling has yet been cameo, out except at Qaiyarah on the west bank of the Tigris. Here the Iraq petroleum Company put down two test wells while they were prospecting and obtained a production of heavy oil of poor quality at shallow depths. It remains to be seen whether deeper drilling will reveal the existence of better quality oil at greater depths. The possibility of the existence of favourable oil structures in this large area has, however, always been recognised, although the preliminary surveys carried out by the Iraq petroleom Company indicated that the area east of the Tigris was the4 . ■■■■■■■■■■■ more favourable. A memorandum prepared by the Iraq Government in November 1931, stated that the northern portion of the area* north of a line drawn from Jebel Sinjar on the Syrian frontier to Baiji on the Tigris (about 30 miles N.E. of Tikrit) contained practically the v/hole of the known structures west of the Tigris. The southern portion of the area v/as stated to contain one or two structures in the vicinity of Hit, but these were not classified as being promising for production. It was stated, hov/ever, that it was possible that oil structures existed betv/een the Tigris and Euphrates rivers but no definite information could be obtained until a geophysical survey had been carried out. The British Oil Development Company has sent out a geologist of repute from this country and his report is at present awaited. Modification of frontier between Syria an d Iracp, 5. A point which will affect the area of the British Oil Development Concession is that a Commission of the League of Nations has recently reported on the question of the irontier between Iraq and Syria and a modification has been agreed to in the neighbourhood of Jebel Sinjar. The Commission did not succeed in putting forward a unanimous suggestion, but the majority of the Commission recommended an adjustment of the frontier line which would have the effect of causing it to run along the crest of the Jebel Sin jar range and v/ould award to Iraq a larger extent of territory in what has been hitherto regarded as French Syria south oi Jebel Sinjar. ihe Council of the League of Nations has accepted tne recommenda tion of the majority of the Commission but no attempt lias yet been made to delimit the new frontier on the ground. In the event of this territory proving to be oil bearing (which must, of course, depend upon geological surveys and test drilling still to be carried out), the value of the British Oil Development Concession will be increased, as they will(R) 1i) 5 automatically acquire some additional territory west of the old frontier line and nearer the Mediterranean. tered in 1928 with a nominal capital of £82 &lt;,500 5 the original directors being Sir Edward Manville (Chairman) 9 Sir Edward Mountain (Chairman of the Eagle Star and British Dominions Insurance Company) - (Sir E.Mountain subsequently became Chairman of the British Oil Development Co.) } the late Admiral Lord Lester Wemyss, V/.R. Brown, General Sir A.Mola (Italy), and three representatives of the Italian Azienda Generale Italiana Petroli, and E.C.Simmons (Solicitor). In addition to the British directors, British interests were represented by industrialists and financiers such as Sir Alexander Walker, Sir Robert McAlpine, Sir John Latta, Sir Charles Barrie, Sir Edward Iliffe, etc. Mr. W.R.Brown v/as a co-director of Lord Inverforth in the British Union Oil Company. At some stage, but when it actually occurred is not clear from the information available, German and Pranco-Sv/iss interests v/ere also included. The German interests v/ere stated to be represented by Pried Krupp, A.G.Vereingigte Stahlwerke, A.G. Gute Hoffnungshuette and Otto Wolffe and Company, and the Prench-Sv/iss interest by a Prench-Swiss group composed of the Swiss Bank Corporation, Messrs. Paul Girod and Jules Bloch. The capital in 1931 was stated to be held in the following proportions: 6. Constitution of the Company. The British Oil Development Company was first regis- British 52 per cent Italian 24 per cent. German 12 per cent. Pranco-Sv/iss 12 per cent. 100 per cent.nio) Form ation_o_f Ji osu 1 Qil fi elds Limited. r 7 . In December 193d ? a nev/ company v/as formed known as 'Mosul Oilfields 5 Limited*'' to acquire the shares in the British Oil Development and to carry on its operations. The Company had a nominal capital of £1,000,000 in £1 shares. In March, 1933, the Board of this Company was reconstructed and the Foreign Office was informed by the Company that the Directorate v/as as follows - Viscount Coschen (Chairman) , Other Britis h Dire ctors (5): Sir Edward Mountain (Deputy Chairman) , Admiral Lord V/ester Wemyss, Lord Glenconner (Director of Hambro T s Bank), W.R.Brown (Director of British Union Oil Company) and Sir Alwin Dickinson (formerly the representative of the British Govern ment on the British Phosphate Commission) as Managing Director. Italian Directors (3): Professor Allessa ndro Mar t el1i , Gr. Uff. Arnaldo Petretti , and Gr. Uff Vittorio Amoretti (Azienda Generale Italiana Petroli). German Directors (2): Herr Thomas Brown and Herr M.Hirschfeld. French Director (1): M. Paul Girod. Iraq Government Director (1): Jafar Pasha, a total of 13. In a recent communication to the Under Secretary for Mines, it was stated that the present allocation of capital is British 52 per cent. , and Foreign 48 per cent. 8. When the announcement of the appointment of the nev/ Board was made in the Press, it was stated that a development and exploitation programme had been approved by the Board, who v/ould concentrate on the work of bringing production to the near-by ports of the Mediterranean at an early date. Foreign Interests in Mosul Oilfields Limited. 9. As indicated above there are Italian, German and French interests in the Company v/hich hold 48 per cent, of the capital. As the Italian Directors represent the Azienda Generale Italiana Petroli (A.G.I.P.) a Company in which the Italian Government hold a controlling interest, it may be 6.Pmhipmipi; mmmmm assumed that that Government is actively concerned in this venture. Italy has practically no native supplies of oil and is knov/n to he anxious to secure control of supplies outside Italy. Unless the British Oil Development had secured their concession in Iraq there was a likelihood that the Italian Government would have opposed the entrance of Iraq to the League of Nations. 10. The German Government is not so concerned to secure control of oil supplies as to obtain orders for pipe-line and other plant for her iron and steel industries. The German Directors on Mosul Oilfields Limited represent those industries and it has been stated in the Press that the German Government has guaranteed half the German shareholding on the understanding that Germany secures 38 per cent, of the orders for plant. So far as can be ascertained 5 the French Government is not interested in the finance of the Company. A company in v/nich the French Government has a shareholding holds nearly a quarter share in the Iraq petroleum Company, but it is the policy of the French Government to encourage the import of crude oil into France for refining and it may be regarded as sufficient that French industrial and financial interests should secure a shareholding in Mosul Oilfields Limited. His Majesty^ Government and Mosul Oilfields Limited. 11. Lord Goschen, the recently appointed Chairman of the Company, has approached the Petroleum Department to inquire whether the British Government would v/ish to secure an interest in Mosul Oilfields Limited. He states in his letter of the 8th April that he is anxious that it should not be possible for the Government in the future to say that they have not had full opportunity for consideration or possible action.12 . dh jSr' This question is under consideration 5 hut meanwhile the effect of the alignment of the pipeline appears to he one deserving serious consideration. 13. On the assumption that the area included in the British Oil Development concession may prove to contain Oilfields capable of a substantial production of oil it would he in the national interest that the oil should so far as possible he transported to a British port of ship ment rather than to a foreign port in French Syria s which is the alternative. 14. With this object in view an attempt was made by His Majesty’s Government at the time when the British Oil Development concession was being negotiated to secure the inclusion of a provision in the concession, similar to that which was inserted in the I.P.C. concession, which would have given the Iraq Government a voice in the align ment of the pipeline and the choice of terminals. At that time, however, the Iraq Government v/as apparently more con cerned to secure immediate revenue in the shape of a substantial dead rent and also a share in the oil which might be produced. The Iraq Government considered that it could not obtain these conditions and in addition a control of the alignment of the pipeline. Further, at the time this concession v/as being negotiated final preparations were being made for the admission of Iraq to the League of Nations. The protraction of the discussions v/as con sidered inadvisable as there v/ere suggestions that if the concession were not granted the Italian Government, which v/as very interested in the B.O.D. , might oppose the admission of Iraq to the League. The High Commissioner in Iraq therefore advised that the proposal for the inclusion of a provision in the concession should be dropped but suggested that at an appropriate time His Majesty’s Govern ment migirit use their influence with the British interests9 F * concerned to secure the transport of the oil to a British port. It is considered that the time has now arrived when His Majesty’s Government should consider what action 5 if any* they should or can take. Once the Company have made their plans or surveyed a route it will obviously he diffi cult to secure any substantial modification of those plans to meet the viev/s of His Majesty’s Government. bvents are likely to move fairly rapidly as Mosul Oilfields 5 Limited^ cannot afford to continue for long to make the heavy dead rent payments 5 which will amount to £750,000 by 1st January, 1937, and carry out their other obligations under the Concession, without making every effort to secure a sub stantial production of oil. If oil is found its transport to the Mediterranean must be provided for before it can be disposed of. 15. Considerations affect i ng the pipeline routes . Tv/o alternatives will present themselves to the Company, either to construct their own pipeline, or to come to some arrangement, as they are entitled to do under their Concession with another Company for the conveyance of the B.O.D. output. The only Company v/ith which an arrangement could be made would be the I.P.C. It is not easy to say what is likely to happen because a great deal depends on the quantity of oil which may be forthcoming. The basis of the concession is a minimum export, after 7i years, of 1 million tons per annum and unless a production on this scale is forthcoming the Company is hardly likely to v/ish to keep the Concession. In the further consideration of the matter it v/ill therefore be assumed that a reasonable production of oil v/ill be secured. 16. In the absence of external influence the Company v/ould probably be inclined to align its pipeline by the shortest route to the Mediterranean. This v/ould run for the greater part of the v/ay along the Turco-Syrian boundaryto Alexandretta. There is a railway which it is understood is Turkish under French management from Nisibin nearly to Alexandretta and the distance, as thecrov; flies, from Mosul to this port is about 385 miles. This question v/as raised in a talk v/hich Lord Goschen had with Sir Alfred Faulkner and it seems clear from that talk that the Company has definitely had this route under consideration. It was suggested to Lord Goschen that a pipeline along such a route was particularly open to attack in normal times from local tribes and during an emergency would be difficult for British forces to protect. Lord Goschen admitted that the pipeline would run through wild country but there was, he thought, a safeguard inasmuch as under the Angora Treaty between Iraq and Turkey the Turkish Government participates in the royalties on oil secured by the Iraq Government. (The Turkish share is 10 per cent.) But he added it has not been determined that the pipeline v/ill be laid to Alexandretta. Sir Alv/in Dickinson has informed Sir Alfred Faulkner that the Company have a provisional estimate for the cost of a pipe line of S million tons per annum capacity by this route and it amounts to from £2-J to £3 million. The actual cost may prove to be rather more than this, but a rough indication can be obtained from the estimates of the cost of their pipeline made available by the I.P.C. This pipeline, v/hich consists of tv/o pipes, each of a nominal capacity of 2 million tons per annum, represents a single length of pipe of 2 million tons capacity of 1,150 miles. The latest estimate of the cost is about £8 million. Until the actual route of the B.O.D. line is knov/n it is not possible to estimate its length but assuming that it goes to Alexandretta it v/ill probably be betv/een 450 and 500 miles. On this basis a cost of between £3 and £4 million may be assumed as likely. 10- 11 - '&gt;jn ^ Company were to build a pipeline of their own from Mosul to Haifa the distance would be about 620 miles and the cost might well amount to between £5 and £6 million. It ie a iso believed tnat the operating costs on this route might be rather higher than by the Alexandretta route. The provision of an additional amount of money of this order would be a serious consideration and it is evident that it would require considerable pressure or some substantial compensation to induce the Company to forego the advantage of taking their oil out by the shortest and most convenient route. The French are likely to offer every facility to the Company in order to secure the pipeline terminal at Alexandretta. Possibil ity of using the I.P.C, Pipeline . 18. This represents the second alternative for Mosul Oilfields, Limited. As pointed out in paragraph 2 oi tiiis : omorandum, the I.P.C. have already under construction oi pipeline system with a nominal annual capacity of about 4 million tons. Jntil the wells in the I.P.C. oilfield have been fully tested on a continuous production for an extended period it is impossible to say definitely how much oil will be available. The potential production is undoubtedly large and more than 30 wells have been drilled and temporarily shut in. those in Persia, and the be the same, namely the [f the wells are similar to oil producing horizon appears to vAsmari Limestone, there should be no difliculty in obtaining a sustained production of probably more than 4,000,000 tons per annum judged by the initial tests which have been carried out on the wells already brought in at Kirkuk. Indeed it may be assumed that unless the I.P.C. were fairly satisfied as to this, they would not have consented to embark on the heavy capital expenditure at present being incurred in constructing their pipeline.ranm ■■■ X M 19. The capacity of a pipeline depends, however, partly on the viscosity of the oil and partly on the pressure which can safely be applied at the puraping stations. It is possible that the I.P.C. might be able to increase the v,. nominal capacity of their lines by boosting up the pressure at the pumping stations. In this connection there is, however, another factor to be borne in mind. The A.P.O.C, are developing the Transferred Territories Oilfield and they have secured an option to construct a pipeline to the Mediterranean for the transport of the oil from this field. Instead of constructing this line they may endeavour to make an arrangement with the I.P.C. Having this possibility in mind, His Majesty’s Government secured an assurance from the A.P.O.C. that if they should make such an arrangement they will ensure that for a period of 10 years any oil so transported shall be Gciken to a Palestinian port, i.e. , by the southern portion of the I.P.C. Pipeline. Several wells have been drilled in the Transferred Territories Field and one of these has for some time been meeting all the internal requirements of Iraq. 20. If an arrangement were made with the A.P.O.C. it may mean that the I.P.C. could not accommodate any other Company’s oil in their southern pipeline unless they were prepared to lay an additional line of pipe. With a pipeline system already established it is possible that an additional line could be laid along this route at a cost which would not be in excess of that which Mosul Oilfields would incur by laying a new pipeline direct to Alexandretta. For a pipeline system involves a good deal of expenditure on ancillary plant such as pumping stations, telephones. - 12 -- 13 - •K and either some form of railway or good roads to convey material for repairs and ordinary upkeep. 21. The relations between the B.O.D. and I.P.C. have not hitherto been cordial and it may not be an easy matter for Mosul Oilfields Limited to come to terms with I.P.C. The B.O.I). were very active two years ago when the I.P.C. were endeavouring to secure a revision of their concession with the Iraq. Government and made difficulties before the Permanent Mandates Commission at Geneva. They also threatened the I.P.C. with legal proceedings. On the other hand* the I.P.C. at one stage regarded the B.O.D. as interlopers and they were very annoyed that having themselves been 'tied up' on the alignment of their pipeline, involving them in a substantially increased expenditure, the B.O.D. were given full discretion as to the alignment of their pipeline. 22, At the same time the I.P.C. might be prepared to come to an arrangement if only to give them some measure of control of the production of Mosul Oilfields Limited, and thus help to eliminate competition. On this matter their attitude may be influenced by their view of the nossibilities of securing a substantial production from the B.O.D. concession. Sufficient information is not at present available for a definite opinion to be expressed by the Petroleum Department on this point. Until further drilling takes place the information possessed by the I.P.C. is probably rather better than that which Mosul Oilfields Limited have because they had for a number of years exploratory rights over the whole of the territory embraced in the B. 0. D.'• concession. There is no doubt that they regard their own area as very much better than that oi the B.O.D.Attit ude or III s Murie gty s Government . 23. Under nresent arrangements) in an emergency His Majesty’s Government would be aoie, subject to taking the necessary measures of protection) to control the disposal of the whole of the output of the rich oilfields in Persia held by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company and the quarter share of the output of the Iraq oilfield) held by the Anglo- Persian Oil Company in the I.P.C., with some measure of control over the other quarter share which must come via Haifa. The oroduction from Persia could be expanded vory quickly, and it is probable that this will also be the case with the I.P.C. output. Doubtless ouher sources of supply will also be available to this country, but the requirements of the Empire during war-time will be so great that any supplies which are under British control will be very valuable. In practice control of the pipeline terminal virtually means control of the oilfield served by the pipeline. 24. It is lixely that there will be refineries at Haifa which would mean that fuel oil and other refined products would be available. The harbour at Haifa, when the work which is now being carried out there is completed, will be a very good one with special facilities for the berthing and loading of oil tankers. So far as is known neither Tripoli nor Alexandretta possesses anything like such gooa facilities, and at Tripoli the I.P.C. are proposing to make their shipments by means of submarine loading lines. 25. It is therefore for consideration whether tnere is a case, on strategic or other grounds, for action by(tes DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC liAJESTY'S GOVERNlfflNT.) \y SECRET. M.E.(O) S4th MtfJ* COPY NO.__._J COivCvilTTEE OP IIvlPERIAL DEFENCE. STMDINO OFFICIAL S T JB- COMMITTEE FOR QUESTIONS CONCERNINO THE MIDDLE EAST. A meeting of the Sub-Committee will be held in Conference Room 'A”, No. 2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.l, on Monday, 17th July, 1953, at 3.30p.m. A G E N D A. 1• PROPOSED PIPELINE FROM THE B R ITISH OIL DEVELOPMENT COMPANY T S CONCESSION NEAR'MOSUL TO THE MEDITERRANEAN. Memorandum by the Petroleum Department. (Paper No. M.E.(O) 93 - already circulated). 2. TPANS-DESERT RAILWAY FROM BAGHDAD TO HAIFA. Memoranda by the Secretary of State for War and the Secretary of State for Air. (Paper No. M.E.(O) 92 - already circulated). Copies of Despatches received by the Foreign Office from Baghdad - to be circulated. (Sgd.) G. HIND. Secretary to the Sub-Committee. 2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.l. 13th July, 1933.B 12 b Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted :— i ■ &gt; i / S / Letter the jrom Reference to previous correspondence: ^Office of the sr q 3 , A copy has also been sent to the Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonieb. Admiralty Air Ministry Foreign Ofnc* India Office fclrr* ,h ; i » »■ War CtW dAR /A, Colonial Office, Downing Street lu a. t', x (R9720) Wt 18117/2750 IN WEEKLY L 21 MAR 1935 from secretary, politic/ SECRET DEPT. IKBIA OFFICE iy./ tUiaitfinHtfl H&amp;SP Gp 1121955 J ?opy n ONFIDENTIAL f B 9 Hlgii Oomissioner for Palestine, Jerrisalem* 16 th pel) rua ? 1955» I have the honour to report that on Wednesday, the 22nd January, I flew to Haifa to perform the ceremonial opening of the Kirkuk-Halfa pipeline of the Iraq. Petroleum Company* after a series of signals from the tanker ’British Fusilier which was waiting in the hay to receive the first outflow of oil, I pressed a switch that set in motion the appropriate pumps * 3. There were present at this ceremony some three hundred visitors, prominent among whom were lord Stanhope, Sir William Gowers, and other guests, both official imjl representative of associated Gil Interests, as well as the French and United States Consuls-General in Jerusalem* 4. At a luncheon which followed this ceremony Sir John 0adman delivered a speech, in the terms of the draft of which a copy is already in possession of the Colonial Office, and then presented me with a silver howl as a memento of this occasion. 5. In response, I made a speech of thanks and congratulation of which the text is enclosed for your information* o (. / o I was met on arrival by Sir John Cadman, and The Right Honourable Sir Philip Gxmliff e-Lis ter, G.B.3 His Majesty’s Principal 8e for the Coloni6, The arrangement of this function was admirably planned and carried out, the Iraq Petroleum Company having spared neither trouble nor expense* 7. On the 24th January the final ceremony in connection with the inauguration of the jjipelines was held at Amman, in the form of a reception and luncheon party given hy Sir John Cadman, at which His Highness the Amir Abdullah was the guest of honour. 8* His Highness was accompanied by Their Highnesses Amir Talal, Amir Naif, and Amir Jemil, and among the other guests, who numbered rather more than a hundred, were Lord stanhope and other official visitors from Europe, Lieutenant Colonel Cox and other British officers and officials, Ibrahim Hashem Pasha and some sixty other trans-Jordanians, official and otherwise, as well as officials and organisers of the Iraq Petroleum Company. 9. At the luncheon party Sir John Cadman addressed the Amir and the rest of the company in a speech, and presented His Highness with a gold casket in honour of the occasion: the Amir briefly replied. I transmit copies of both speeches herewith for your informations that of Sir John Gadman differs in certain minor particulars from the advance text which is in possession of the Colonial Office. 10. The Aeiit conferred upon Sir John Caiman the title of Pasha, 11. After luncheon His Highness proceeded with Sir John Cadman to inspect the Imperial Airways Liner Syrinx, which then 3eft to return to Ramlef^ aerodrome. 12. I am informed by Lieutenant Colonel Cox that the ceremony was well organised and passed off very successfully*IS* A sad eircujnstance ol* these celehx*ations has been the death of Lady Waley Cohen, who had come to Palestine for the occasion with Si3? Robert ^Yaley Cohen, the senior representative of the Shell Company. They had an accident while motoring near Jerusalem on the 16th January; though her injuries were slight, complications ensued and she died early in the morning of the 24th. 14. I am sending copies of this despatch to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Baghdad and His Majesty’s Consul-General at Beirut. I have, &amp;c., (Signed) Arthur Wauchope. • High Commissioner for Palestine.■HMMRMi MM OIL ON SHIFTING SAI7DS» Speech of the High Comnii sal oner ♦ I look upon it as a great compliment that you have asked me to open the pipe line officially to-day, and it was with great pleasure that I accepted the invitation to he present, so that as High Commissioner I may extend the warmest welcome to Sir John Caduan and the many distinguished strangers who have come from far and wide to he present at this gathering to-day. I thank Sir John for his all too kind words as to myself, and I cordially endorse what he has said as regards the most happy relationship that has existed throughout the difficult period of construction, and the good feeling which I am confident will always exist between the Iraq Petroleum Company and the Government of Palestine and Trans-Jordan. I need not dwell upon the tremendous task that has been achieved, but I must congratulate Sir John and all those who are responsible for its successful issue on the foresight, energy and skill that enabled them to overcome all obstacles and achieve that success, and accomplish it many months before the date originally anticipated. I asi confident that the opening of this Pipeline will prove of the highest value to Palestine and the neighbouring countries; of value to the country in which the oil is won to the countries through which it flows, and not least of value to the countries from whose ports it is distributed to the world market. A.sAs High Commissioner I am happy to think that the Port of Haifa already contains the sea loading terminals which we have seen in operation to-day and that in the not very distant future our new Harhour will provide sheltered facilities in a specially contracted dock for the export of crude oil, and perhaps later on for the export of refined oil., The construction of the long pipe line, and the road alongside it, has already had good results, and those I am sure will continue this good influence in the future, We are told to pour oil on troubled 7 /aters; Sir John Cadman and the Iraq. Petroleum Company, ever moving with, or even in advance of the times, are metaphorically pouring oil on the shifting sands of the desert by giving employment and helping to maintain order among the Bedouin and the semi-nomadic people of that region. The Company has set a fine example to us all, and shown that with energy and good will success can be achieved in spite of all obstacles; and I feel confident that both the construction and operation of the pipe line will not only enlarge the scoTpe and activities of the Iraq Petroleum Company, but will also further the development and prosperity of the people of Trans-Jordan and of Palestine. I heartily congratulate dir John Gadman, Hr. Dimkley, Hr. Stuckey and their colleagues in this country, on the success of their undertaking and wish them all good fortune in the future.Speech to he delivered by Sir John Gadiaan to His Highness The .air ^bdulla -Aqman, on January 24th, 19 3 5, .our Highness, Your Excellencies and Gentlenen, 0n o£ the Iraq Petroleum Company and the associated groups and Companies whose representatives are o J jC) 9 I should like to express our very warm appreciation of the honour done us to-day by the presence hlB (Ii £hness the Amir &gt; accompanied by so many of the statesmen and personalities of his capital and country: thus to receive His Highness and so distinguished a gathering has been a privilege and a pleasure which we shall long remember. Our meeting to-day should be taken as marking the close of the period of Construction of a great enter prise, and the beginning of that of Operation. Although xrans-Jordan is neither the source of the Oil, nor can provide its outlet to the markets of the world, yet the territories of His Highness the ..mir have provided us ' rath an indispensable corridor, the use of which was granted to us by the Government nearly four years ago. t ore than 200 miles of our main Pipeline, with over so miles of waterlines, now lie buried in the soil of this country; and two major Pumping stations in the desert, one reserve station beside the Jordan, the Depot at Mafrak, and three water-supply points, lie also within its foandones. All of these (essential links in our chain as they are) as well as our office in Amman, we hope for many years, to maintain, and to be able to give employment, good conditions, to a considerable number of the subjects of His Highness. j t . * ’ Looking back over our operations in this country over the last three years, we realise that we have many reasons— ■MM wmmm ■HMHPai reasons to “be grateful and satisfied. Te have worked throughout - even in districts hitherto almost entirely uninhabited - in conditions of law and order which could scarcely have been improved; and we have learned accordingly, fully to appreciate the remarkable achievement of the Arab Legion (supported by the prestige and states- ■* manship of the Ruler) in creating and maintaining a state of affairs so different from desert conditions which prevailed in former years. Not only in the desert, but in the populated province of Ajlun, and in our relations with Government both on the spot and at the Capital, we have been fortunate indeed to find a spirit of active and enlightened co-operation, not only in questions of law and order, but in those affecting public health, the many others. Relations between the Comijany and the Government have been maintained from first to last upon a basis of mutual respect, comprehension, and helpfulness; for this we are very greatly indebted not only to His Highness himself, but to His Excellency the High influence (with that of the British Resident in Amman) has always been used on the side of co-operation and support. strangers; working together, for month after month of strenuous and exacting work, we found willing helpers and sincere friends of proved good-will, from the Palace of His. Highness himself down to the humblest tent of fellah and beduin. Commissioner for (Palestine and) Trans-Jordan whose acquisition of land, the recruitment of our personnel, and He came to Trans-Jordan three years ago as companions; and we remain surrounded, I believe, by Atmamm At the same tine it is a source of much satis faction to the Company to feel that it has been able, in a period of great economic depression and general unemploy ment, to make a very considerable contribution to the prosperity of the country, by offering employment to thousands of its inhabitants, and by obtaining necessary services within the country in all cases where this could be done at the required scale, quality, and speed. The voices, indeed of those who considered that they, instead of others, should have been employed have been raised from time to time; but it may be said with confidence that within the limits imposed by the necessity of finishing the work v/ith essential speed and economy, every preference has always been (as it will always be) given to the local employee. In the field of the skilled artisan and technician, we have indeed been obliged to import fairly freely (but most often temporarily) from neighbouring countries. This necessity is already less as construc tion is complete, and we feel no doubt that future years will give us the supply which we need of skilled and specialised men from this country itself. The manner in which the people of this country have learned to adapt themselves to new methods and thus to render efficient service to the Company, may be taken as a good omen for the future. The development which Northern and North-Eastern Trans-Jordan has witnessed through the construction of the Pipeline has been indeed remarkable. In the great road which crosses al Harrah - the lava—strewn desert — from side to side you have probably the finest as well as the most costly highway in the country and one for which, but for our enterprise, the country migfrt have waited for manyc^D &amp; many years. Along this road, the Company f s telegraph line carries, hy mutual agreement. Government lines which will serve to link Trans-Jordan with its eastern neighbours. At the same time, the Company^ water drilling operations, successfully carried out at several points in waterless desert, have shown what can he done by such means towards supplying that essential element of which Nature has been too sparing. I wish every success to the water-finding programme which I understand the Government, under the wise direction of His Highness, has already taken in hand and If the Company can be of any assistance to the Government in this connection I am sure they will be only too willing to help. In the Times of Ignorance, in the days of the Caesars, the Ptolemys, and the Greeks - of the Egyptian and the Nabatean empires - there was found a high culture and a royal Government east of the Jordan, with a prosperity still attested by the marvellous ruins of Petra, Amman and Jerash. It is in this country of ancient fame, and under the rule of a member of a House so greatly venerated in Islam, that the most modem progress is to-day encouraged: with results already full of hope for the restoration of wealth, the maintenance of good order, and the advance of the state to a place, among the peoples of the Near East, of which both ruler and subjects will be proud* Your Excellencies and Gentlemen, before I ask His Highness to accept from me a small souvenir of his presence amongst us to-day - a token of our high regard for his person and Government - I will ask you all to join me in wishing long life, health and prosperity to the Ruler of this country. His Highness the Amir Abdulla.■■Ml Ml J mm His Highness The Amir’s Speech in Answer to Sir John 0adman, Amman Ceremony - 24th January, 1935, Gentlemen, I am very pleased to he present Y/ith you at this ceremony which is being held for the formal inauguration of the Pipeline, We have all heard the eloquent speech delivered by Sir John 0adman, the Chairman of the Board of Directors of the Iraq Petroleum Company Limited, regarding this great enterprise which has been accomplished. Sir John Cadman has explained in detail the Company’s operations, the material assistance and the developments resulting therefrom and he has also mentioned the co-operation of the Government with ?/hich the Company was able to carry out its difficult operations even in the vacant areas and the uninhabited desert under conditions of law and order. He ended in appreciating the mutual friendship between the Government and the Company from the Amir’s Palace to the humblest tent in the country. All that gives the utmost satisfaction, I feel, hov/ever, that it is my duty not to forget in an occasion such as this, the good part played by the people of ny emirate in extending a sincere and contented hand towards the enlightment of the fatigues of this great undertaking and making tne task of bringing it into being less difficult than was expected. I have the full confidence that the good hand hitherto extended by Trans-Jordan towards this great enterprise will continue with the will of God as long as the good relation exist between the two parties. II am pleased to refer, in this connection, to the distinguished qualities of Mr, 3.Y. Packer the representative of the Companv in the capital of my country, and to particularly say that he has been an honourable representative to whose tact and good character a deep effect is credited in the good understanding and co-operation prevailing between the Company and my Government. I accept with hearty thanks the souvenir offered now to me as Amir of Trans-Jordan by Sir John C adman and 1 pray God that he may lead us in the paths of success.INDEXED In any further communication on this subject, please fjuote No.^r T —not to any person by rtame, bdt to— /. —V and address- 'The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. nan ► u THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^2^ an d&gt; by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop&lt;=^c? of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 193 . Reference to previous correspo7idence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. y-ATHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT i \ r EASTERN (Iraq). * f.j ,, i ! 1090 I I * J ^ L January 28, 1935. CONFIDENTIAL. r ; f Section 1. [E 624/33/93 J No. 1. Sir F. Hum/phrys to Sir John Simon — -(Received January 28.) (No. 36.) ^i r &gt; Bagdad, January 17, 1935. I HA\E the honour to report that the pipe-line of the Iraq Petroleum Company connecting the oil-field at Kirkuk with the Mediterranean port of Haifa was officially opened by His Majesty King Ghazi on the 14th January. 2. A fortnight prior to this event Sir John Cadman had arrived at Bagdad from Abadan to take personal charge of the arrangements for the ceremony; he and Lady Cadman and their two daughters were my guests during their stay in Bagdad, and Sir John was able to make many interesting and useful contacts with the Iraqi politicians, members of the Diplomatic Body, and senior British and Iraqi officials, who. were present at the parties which were given at the Embassy in his honour. 3. On the 30th December Sir John paid a flying visit to Tehran in one of the company’s aeroplanes to be received in audience by the Shah. On his return journey his machine was unfortunately compelled by bad weather to make a forced landing between Hamadan and Kermanshah. Happily, neither the aeroplane nor its passengers suffered any injury and, after a short delay in Hamadan, Sir John was able to reach Bagdad on the 5th January without further mishap. 4. On the 12th January some thirty-five distinguished guests of the company, the chief of whom was Lord Stanhope, representing His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom, arrived in Bagdad from Europe in two specially chartered passenger aeroplanes. British oil interests were represented by Major the Honourable Thomas Cochrane, Director of the Anglo-Saxon Petroleum Company, and Lieutenant-Colonel H. R. Medlicott, Deputy-Director of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company. M. Paul Bastid, President of the Foreign Affairs Committee in the French ^Chamber, and M. Robert Cayrol, director of the Compagnie francaise des Petroles, were the principal representatives of France, while Mr. G. H. Siedel, director of the Standard Oil Company of New Jersey, represented the American holding in the company. 5. Lord Stanhope accepted my invitation to stay at the Embassy during his visit, and Colonel and Mrs. Medlicott were the guests of my first secretary. The other members of the party were accommodated in the Maude Hotel, which had been exclusively reserved by the company for this purpose. 6. On the same evening, King Ghazi dined at the Embassy and had an opportunity to exchange views with Lord Stanhope and the other principal British members of the party whose acquaintance His Majesty had particularly desired to make. 7. In all, over 250 guests were invited by the company to attend the opening ceremony, and elaborate arrangements were made for their transport. The majority of the guests from Iraq travelled to and from Kirkuk by a special train, while those who came from Europe made the journey in the aeroplanes in which they had flown to Iraq. Lord Stanhope accompanied me in my private aeroplane. One of the outstanding features of the day was the large part played by air transport, no fewer than fourteen aeroplanes landing on the company’s aerodrome at Kirkuk. 8. The ceremony itself is described fully in the enclosed copy of the Iraq Times, which also contains the full text of Sir John Cadman’s speech and the King’s reply.f) I need only add that the programme was carried out from beginning to end without a hitch and in a manner which does great credit to the efficiency of the company’s organisation and personnel. The arrival of His Majesty in one of a flight of five Hart Audax military machines was particularly ( 1 ) Not printed. [306 ee—1]2 . impressive, and the maimer in which the Iraqi pilots handled these fast machines called forth universal admiration. 9. the next day King Ghazi entertained some of the senior British and foreign guests oi the company, and the members of the Iraqi Cabinet, at a banquet at the Qasr-al-Zuhur. Unhappily, the King was overcome by the excessive heating of the dining-room and was obliged to leave the table after ^ the third course. As His Majesty has been in indifferent health lately, and had already carried through a long and tiring programme at Kirkuk, it was considered inadvisable that he should attend the reception at the British Embassy which took place later in the evening. This was unfortunate, as His Majesty particularly wished to bid farewell to the distinguished foreign guests who had participated in the ceremony and were due to leave Bagdad for Syria next morning. 10. On the 16th January Sir John Cadman and his guests left by air for the official opening of the second sector of the line from Haditha to Tripoli. 11. Sir John Cadman may well be satisfied with the unparalleled engineering feat which has been achieved by the Iraq Petroleum Company under his inspiring guidance, and completed without a hitch one whole year earlier than had been thought possible. It is, indeed, a magnificent piece of work which will confer lasting benefits on this country and which should emphasise the identity of the interests of Great Britain and Iraq in future. The friendliness and good-fellowship displayed at the recent ceremonies has afforded welcome proor that responsible Iraqis of all shades of political opinion are proud to be associated with Sir John Cadman and his splendid team of engineers in the successful completion of this remarkable enterprise. 12. Among the most interesting comments by Iraqi statesmen and business men which I heard during the celebrations was the J desire that the earliest opportunity should be taken for increasing the output of Iraq oil to the Mediterranean, and I understand that the Kirkuk oil-field, measuring about 51 miles in length and an average of 1-| miles in breadth, which is probably the largest structure of its kind in the world, would be capable of exporting not less than 20 million tons of oil annually, if markets could be found for such a quantity. In any case, it seems safe to assume that additional pipe-lines will have to be constructed to the Mediterranean in the not far distant future, and I need not emphasise the effect which a railway fro m Bagdad to Haifa would ' have in determining the direction of future pipe-lines from the point of bifurcation at Haditha. It is significant that Yasin Pasha informed me at the opening ceremony that Iraqis would much prefer that these additional pipe-lines should go to Haifa rather than to Tripoli. The extra distance of about 90 miles, however, which is involved by choosing the Haifa route must weigh heavily with the company unless some cheaper means of transport can be provided as a'set-off against the extra cost of the pipes. 13. I am sending copies of this despatch to His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran, the High Commissioner for Palestine, His Majesty’s consul-general at Beirut and the Department of Overseas Trade. I have. &amp;c. F. H. HUMPHRYSTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOYERNMENT (No. 20. Confidential.) Sir, Bagdad, January 9, 1935. WITH reference to my despatch No. 5, Confidential, of the 4th January, 1934, I have the honour to inform you that the Iraq Petroleum Company paid in full the annual royalty due to the Iraqi Government on the 1st January. The amount paid this year in sterling was £678,000. 2. The payment due by the British Oil Development Company to the Iraqi Government has not yet been made, but they have a period of three months’ grace. 3. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Department of Overseas Trade. n o EASTERN (Iraq). January 21, 1935. CONFIDENTIAL. Section 3. [E 432/432/93] No. 1. Sir F. Humphrys to Sir John Simon.—(Received January 21.) I have, &amp;c. F. H.' HUMPHRYS. [306 x—3]I ’vV' o,* » Any reply to this letter should be addressed to the Director, Petroleum Dept. PETROLEUM DEPARTMENT ^ .©&gt; Telephone: Victoria 9310. Telegrams : Minindust, Part, London. (Mines Department), r / i Dean Stanley Street, Reference No.:-P.D. 236/6 Millbank, Westminster, London, S.W.l. 18th January, 1934. Dear Walton, In reply to your letter of January 15th, regarding the Iraq Petroleum Company, I enclose a note which I hope will give you the sort of on the telephone, there are no published documents dealing with this matter. Ihese special arrangements between the groups in the Iraq Petroleum Company are of a strictly confidential character and we only learn of them privately through our close touch with the oil companies. information you require. As I explained to you Yours sincerely J. C. Walton, Esq., C.B., M.C», India Office, King Charles Street, S.W. 1. EA *»K (1) The Iraq Petroleum Company . - The Turkish Petroleum Company (now the Iraq Petroleum Company) was formed in 1912, when the Deutsche Bank became associated with the National Bank of Turkey and the Anglo-Saxon Petroleum Company (Royal Dutch Shell Group), in order to press certain claims to oil rights in Bagdad and Mosul, including those attached to the Bagdad Railway Concession. The chief rival of the new company at that time was the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, which had for some time been in negotiation with the Turkish Government. In 1914 an agreement was entered into providing for the reconstitution of the Turkish Petroleum Company, from which the National Bank of Turkey withdrew, the new participants being the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, 50 per cent.; the Anglo-Saxon Petroleum Company and the Deutsche Bank, 25 per cent. each. This agreement also provided that the three groups should give undertakings not to be interested directly or indirectly in the production of oil in the Ottoman Empire in Europe and Asia (excluding Egypt, Koweit and the Transferred Territories), except through the Turkish Petroleum Company. This agreement was signed by the British and German Governments, and by the groups concerned. As the Turkish Petroleum Comoany was then predominantly British, this arrangement had the effect of securing the whole of this area to interests which were predcBiinantly British. After the war American and French interests were admitted into the Iraq Petroleum Company and the arrangement as regards non competition between the groups composing the Iraq Petroleum Company was confirmed in an agreement between the groups, entered into in 1928. This was a private agreement between the groups with which the British Government was not associated. Under this agreement a line was drawn round Arabia, Palestine- 2 - -jfi. x f and Asia Minor, which excluded the Sultanate of Koweit and the Parsan Islands, but included Bahrein, and an area was v x thus defined within which the various groups constituting the Iraq Petroleum Company agreed that they would not seek for or obtain oil concessions otherwise than through the Iraq Petroleum Company or its nominee. On the admission of French and American interests the share capital of the Iraq Petroleum Company was distributed as follows Percentage. Anglo-Persian Oil Company. •• 23.75 Royal Dutch Shell 23.75 French Group 23.75 American Group (1) 23.75 C. S. Gulbenkian 5.00 100.00 As the Royal Dutch Shell is 60 per cent. Dutch and 40 per cent. British, the British shareholding in the company now only represents about 33} per cent. The Iraq Petroleum Company is still technically a British company, as in article 32 of its convention with the Government of Iraq the company must be and remain a British company, registered in Great Britain, and the chairman must at all times be a I British subject. But the position is different from a British point of view, from that which formerly obtained when the company was British in fact as well as in name. (1) In 1932 the American shareholding in the American group (Near East Development Corporation) was held in the following proportions:- Percentage . Standard Oil Company of New Jersey 41 Standard Oil Company of New York (now the 2 / Socony-Vacuum Company) 41'o Gulf Oil Corporation of Pennsylvania 16 2 / 3x THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT EASTERN (Iraq). CONFIDENTIAL. ’520 October 1, 1934 Section 6 . [E 6097/1752/93] No. 1. Mr. Ogilvie-Forbes to Sir John Simon—(Received October 1.) (No. 558.) „ 7 gj r Bagdad, September 20, 1934. IN his despatch No. 257 of the 9th May, His Majesty s Ambassadoi trans mitted copy of the drilling return of the British Oil Development Company tor the month of April. Owing to the absence on leave of the company s local manager and the unwillingness of his substitute to supply this information without specific authority, I have been unable to obtain copies of similai month v returns since that date, but I have now received from the acting British consu at Mosul a report on the present stage of the company’s undertaking. 2 At Qaiyarah, the headquarters of the oil-fields, there are three wells. No 1 was drilled by the Germans during the war, and is still exploited to produce bitumen for sale to the Public Works Departments, who are now erecting a small refinery close to the British Oil Development Company s camp for r efining t e bitumen. No. 2 was drilled about 1928 by the Iraq Petroleum Company m the course of their prospecting, and has been filled up, and would need redrilling to exploit. No. 3 was drilled by the British Oil Development Company, and is mudded down. , ^ • , 3. Other wells are being or have been drilled at various points lying west of the Tigris, within a radius of some 35 miles of Qaiyarah. Of the three s at Najmah, No. 1 is complete and mudded down; No. 2 is being drilled by percussion, and is all but complete and ready to “ come in ’’ any day; ™ being drilled by American rotary drill (Sullivan type), and has reached a depth of 800 feet, or approximately two-thirds of the depth anticipated to be required. 4. At Jawan are one well and two projected wells. No. 1 is being drilled by percussion, and is half drilled. Of the remaining two, one is being piepaied for the erection of a large German rotary drill, and has got as far as concrete platforms and about one storey of the derrick; while the other is being prepared for percussion drill, and has got as far as concrete platfoims. 5. At Habbarah, an emplacement is being prepared tor a large German rotary drill similar to that at Jawan, and has reached about the same stage. 6 At Sadid, another emplacement for a German rotary dull is being ^ 7° A well was completed last winter at Mishrak, but though the geological indications were all correct, the oil had disappeared, probably through centuries of seepage, and the well is being demolished. TT , T -n 8 The German drilling machinery is from Hanell and Lue, Dusseldort, and the firm, being under guarantee, is sending out selected German drillers to work it. Two or three have arrived, and the remainder, to the number of thirteen, are expected soon. , .. . , ,. . ri-u- 9 The companv have not shown much activity in the direction ot building or road-making. This is but prudent at this early stage of their operations. No information is available at present as to the prospects of marketable oil being found in commercial quantities, but I hope to be able to report on this point . 10 X am sending a copy of this despatch to the Depaitment of Overseas^ *' ia ^ e ' I have, &amp;c. G. OGILVIE-FORBES. [231 a—6]MHHPIW COPY (B 4999/194/93) GTH/MP K - '' 45 1037/44/34 ■■■ Sir, I have the honour 'go inform you that the first oil from the Iraq petroleum Company 1 3 fialds in Iraq arrived through the •Dine-line at ( P.Z. i F&gt; 1 A / i Consulate General,. \ w' ! i C— 1 i 1^54 J Beirut, 24th July, 1924, on the evening of 14th July 0 2. a On the 18th July the French High Commissioner visited Tripoli to be present at the official opening of the pipeline* 2o It is stated that the first oil tanker will arrive at Tripoli on or about the 7th August* 4 0 l am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty 1 s High Commissioner at Jerusalem and to His Majesty*s Chargd d'affaires at Baghdad* I have etc« &amp; (Sgd) G*To Havard* Consul General® The Rt 0 Hon® Sir John Simon, G»C«»St&gt;lop K*CoY*0«* OaBcE*^ MaP»^ H®Mo Principal Secretary of state for Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office, London*r. Notes. Minute Paper. Register No. P. z. 4484/34 SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT Dated 19 . Pec. Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State... BRITISH OIL DEVELOPMENT COMPANY'S CONCESSION IN IRAQ,. &lt;&amp;££SVW- C . Copy of to FOR INFORMATION. SEEN POLITICAL COMMITTEE. 1 3 AUG 1934 Previous Papers :— i 5041 2000 1.31 It will be seen that the British Group in the B.O.D. Company were unfortunately unable to raise their share of the dead rent payment due to the Iraq Government last January, and that the money was put up by the Italian Group, apparently on condition of the transfer to themselves of additional shares and voting power in the Company. The Italian Group has thus succeeded the British Group in the position of majority shareholders in the Company, but it is just possible that the British Group may be able to regain its former predominance if and when it finds itself in a position to repay the money advanced by the Italian Group. I understand that the British Group attempted to obtainfinancial assistance from His Majest; Government .but that this request was id down by the Foreign Office and the Board ( ide. According to Sir Francis Humphrys, tl &gt;t of the trouble is that the Company ur &gt;ok to pay far too high a dead rent for i .d which was not only undeveloped but tl potential wealth of which was a matte guesswork. h./i.c.^ m * OJ&gt; - SEEN ^®j|TICAL CONI MITT EE.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOYERNMENT EASTERN (Iraq). f P. ’J . ' 14 g J May 29, 1934. CONFIDENTIAL. * ’T :r i s . - * f Section 2. [E 3S16/1752/93] No. 1. Sir F. Humphrys to Sir John Simon.—(Received May 29.) (No. 267.) Sir, Bagdad, May 15, 1934. WITH reference to my despatch No. 190 of the 12th April last, I have the honour to report that a Mr. L. C. Patterson; a British director of the British Oil Development Company (although his name is new to me), has paid a visit to Bagdad on behalf of the company, and in the course of a conversation with me he confirmed that the additional money required to enable the dead rent payment due to the Iraqi Government on the 1st January this year to be made was supplied by the Italian group. 2. He also informed me that the consideration obtained by the Italian group for providing the extra funds was the transfer to themselves, from the British and French groups, of additional shares and voting power in the company, which has thereby given them the largest international holding in the company. The distribution of the shares now seems to be as follows : — Percentage. British group 42 Italian group 46 German group 12 The method whereby this has been done is not clear, as Mr. Patterson informed Mr. Wheatley, the adviser to the Ministry of Economics and Communications, that the redistribution is only temporary, and that he hoped that the previous balance would eventually be restored. If this statement is correct, it is possible that the additional money advanced by the Italian group is being regarded as a repayable loan carrying voting power until such time as it is repaid. The position of the French group is also obscure, but it appears certain that at the present time the Italian group has succeeded the British group in the position of majorityj shareholder in the company. 3. Mr. Patterson informed me that he feared that the company would have the greatest difficulty in finding the necessary cash to meet the dead rent payment due to the Iraqi Government on the 1st January next, unless oil in sufficient marketable quantities is found in the meanwhile. Success in this direction seems doubtful, although the company intend to accelerate their drilling programme and to set up three new drilling rigs in September. Machinery for these rigs is being supplied by the German group as satisfaction in kind of their share of the dead rent payment made last month. 4. Mr. Patterson asked me whether I thought that the Iraqi Government would be likely to come to the assistance of the company in the matter of the next payment either by reducing the amount to be paid or by extending the period of grace. I said that I thought that the present Government would certainly decline to help in the manner which he had indicated, as they were too fearful of criticism in Parliament and outside. If a really strong Government came into power before the end of the year and could be convinced that a moratorium or a reduction of the dead rent was in the interests of Iraq as well as the company, it was possible, though unlikely, that some help might be forthcoming. I remarked that the root of the trouble was that the company had undertaken to pay far too high a dead rent for a field which was not only undeveloped, but the potential wealth of which was still a matter of guesswork, although I sympathised with the company’s difficulties and would do my best to help them. 5. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Department of Overseas Trade. I have, &amp;c. F. H. HUMPHRYS. [106 ff—2]any further comiriunicaticm oi^fl^ajlibject, please quote no. ^ and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. presents his corni THE Under-Secretary of State fo l iplirnents to VdLj. c ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop \su) of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ls&gt; , 193 Reference to previous correspondence : f.o . UU e 'mo ^ ^ Description of Eiiclosure. 3 d Name and Date. Subject. 'COPT (w 1915/1758/93) NO. 148. British (259/1/24) CONFIPFimAL, Bagdad* 15th Uaroh^ 1954. 3ir # I have the honour to inform you that the British Oil Development Company have begun to eubmit periodical progress reports to the Iraqi Government and that their manager at Mosul has agreed to supply my Commeroial secretary tTith copies. 2. A copy of the first of these reports is enclosed and copies of future reports will be forwarded to you os received. I have. etc.. (sga) p.h. Huupmrra. 5he Bight Honourable Sir John Simon. G.C.S.X*. K*C.V.O«. etc.. etc.. etc.In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. £ / and address —not to any persott by name, -but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. l ‘ V • ' . THE Under-Secretary of State tor Foreign Affairs presents his ONFIDENTiAG 512 concluded, and the cost of the arbitration proceedings themselves. Although 1 see no reason to suppose that the Government is not financially in a position to put the Habbaniyah Escape works in hand, even in the face of these contingencies, the Cabinet may well think it prudent to avoid a decisive step in the matter of the Habbaniyah on account of them. ^— 6. I have sent a copy of this despatch to the Department of Overseas Tp^uc. I have, &amp;c. F. H. HUMPHRYS.In any further communication on this subject, please quote N°- £ \cvi. and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. /L &amp; 6 t 'i c iv 602 i954 A' THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs'“presents his compliments to k i ~ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. f Foreign Office, * &lt; 5 ^ , 1931^ Reference to previous correspondence : f .0 . JU&amp;u e '■ , ° \ l&lt; ° K'S ^i 0 ^- x L Description of Enclosure. to r 1 Name and Date. Subject. v\^ v\. rSOLOWRE IN WEEKLY LETTEK I ,; 4i Sj n FEB. 1934 ! .yay 8WRETARY, POLITICAL AN! | SECRET DEPT. INDIA 0F5 *t ‘ 2 6 JAN 1334 1 l l lHD^OFf!C£l Similar letter sent to to X 14-6130 8931 (b) C.qTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT Sir F. Humphrys to Sir John Simon.—{Received January 15.) (No. 5. Confidential.) gj r Bagdad, January 4, 1934. WITH reference to my despatch No. 8 05^_ConfidentiaI, of the 21st December last, I have the honour to inform you thatTthe Iraq Petroleum Company paid in full on a gold basis the sums due from them to the Iraqi Government on the 1st January. , . 2. On the other hand, the payment due from the British Oil Development Company has not yet been received. 3. I have sent a copy of this despatch to the Department of Overseas Trade. EASTERN (Iraq). January 15, 1934. CONFIDENTIAL Section 2 [E 326/326/93] No. 1 I have, &amp;c. F. H. HUMPHRYS.r-’ In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. £-]CjJ0 ^ir- &lt;fJ - and address —not to any ftrson by name, tgit to-^- “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. SEC THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents hi Cz(L 4'C*— c^sCqs compliments to , and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, f •, 198--. ifip. 'o J,1 /) v Reference to previous correspondence : J Description of Enclosure.7 THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT EASTERN (Iraq). CONFIDENTIAL. [E 7930/84/93] Sir F. Humphrys to Sir John Simon.—(Received December 27.) (No. 780. Secret.) Bagdad, December 13, 1933. ’ LORD GLENCONNER, who was appointed general manager of the Mosul Oil-fields last July, arrived in Bagdad on a tour of inspection on the 15th November and left on the 8th December. While in Bagdad he had several interviews with Rustam Beg Haidar, Minister of Economics and Communications, and Nuri Pasha, on the subject of the operations of the company, and, particu larly, in regard to the payment of the instalment of dead rent, amounting to £125,000 gold, equivalent to about £190,000, in accordance with article 10 of the convention, which is due on the 1st January. 2. Lord Glenconner informed me that the company were not in a position to raise fresh capital on the London market until the value of their concession had been proved; in other words, until oil of a marketable quality had been struck. Three rigs had been erected in the Mosul Province and drilling had already reached a depth of about 120 feet. He said that he had arranged for a cable to be sent to him from London each week reporting progress, but it was, of course, open to doubt whether oil would be struck by the 31st March, on which date the period of grace for payment of next year’s dead rent to the Iraqi Government would expire. 3. Lord Glenconner informed me that he had spoken very frankly to Rustam Haidar about the company's position, and he said that, if the prospects of the company did not greatly improve by the 31st March, they would have to default over payment of the dead rent unless they were granted an extension of time. This would mean, under article 15 (i), that the Government would have the right of cancelling the concession. Lord Glenconner told me that he had informed Rustam Haidar that, if an extension of time were granted, the company would be prepared to work at least twice as many rigs this year as they were required to do under the agreement, and he said that if the concession were cancelled he did not think that the Iraqi Government would find any other foreign company who would be willing to conclude an agreement on such onerous terms as had been accepted by the British Oil Development Company. 4. I pointed out to Lord Glenconner that it was possible that, if there was default over the payment due next March and the concession was cancelled, the Government might employ foreign experts at their own expense to drill in selected areas west of the Tigris, and if oil of a suitable quality was discovered they might put up the concession for tenders again in the hope of obtaining at least equally favourable terms, after pocketing a year’s dead rent from the British Oil Develop ment Company and taking over all their gear for nothing. 5. The question of a pipe-line to the Mediterranean was also touched upon in my conversations with Lord Glenconner, who told me that his Italian and German colleagues on the board were in favour of constructing a pipe-line to Alexandretta. The cost, he said, was estimated at about 3 millions and the Germans hoped to obtain the bulk of the contract for the pipes. I told him that my personal opinion was that the country through which such a pipe-line would pass was one of the most potentially disturbed areas in the Middle East and that the security from a British point of view was nil. I thought that it would be in the ultimate interests of the Mosul Oilfields Company to come to an arrangement with the Iraq Petroleum Company for the use on commercial terms of their pipe line to Haifa, and remarked that wherever oil might be struck in his company’s concessional area it should not be very costly to join up with the Iraq Petroleum Company’s pipe-line, which was liable to be duplicated if the world conditions of the oil industry permitted. I have, &amp;c. F. H. HUMPHRYS. [991 dd—1]■■■■■MM!In any further communication on this subject, please quote N »- 11VWV \~^&gt; 'o and address —not to any person by name ) but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. O j A £i O i r O (/Ia c THE Under-Secretary of State for For^igs ^re^ents his compliments to Q V . and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop A-A-o of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 193? . \/\ -Q^ / O'. ’ -pO Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER NO. 5iJ 21 DEC. 19S5 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SEC-El DEPT. I M QU OFFICE I4—6130 8931 (e) Similar letter sent to VaS , 0 .Copy (E T441/V36/93 wo. 2£2s {%89^/ii) 23rd Wov«mb^r # 1933i&gt; X Sir y ^'ith r^rerence to my despatch TiOo ^29 dated November 21et f I have the honour to report that, according to a telegram received in the Bagdad office of the ’Iraq Petroleum Company* the stringing and welding of their pipe-lines from Lirkuk to the proximity of the Mediterranean terminals was completed at 3*30 p»m.j on November 19th e The telegram added that work on the puraping stations is proceeding satisfsctorilyo The Company are to be congratulated on putting through a work of this magnitude with such efficiency and despatch* 2* I have sent a copy of this despatch to the Department of Overseas Trade* I have, etCo ; (Ligned) F v Hc Humphrys., The Right Honcuiable &amp;ir John Simon, GcCokoJ*., e »c {&gt; jf etCo 5 etc etCoindexed In any further oommunication on this subject, please quote % ^9/ z ■ / ess —not to any person by name, burt to— i &lt;' f and address- “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. i 1 93 2 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs prese and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop&lt;j£&lt;7 of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 1932 . '/424 its .. tiF I - F/tX- Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. a a ^ &amp;cX' . ■ fib* 0C1 1932 t) 6H(jL0t»aE IN ,,LEK' Y LETTER •- '■ Similar letter sent to FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND 14 - 6,30 7441 ( 2 ) frr\\ SECRET DEPT. IN'.IA OFFICE VJ.O \ &lt;L.O-Monday 17th Octoher ? 1932 Your Excelleney, You are no doubt aware that this Company has obtained from the Iraq: Government the grant of an oil concession covering all the lands of Iraq on the west Bank of the Biver Tigris north of the thirty-third parallel of latitude. assurance that in due course they may be privileged to receive from your Government facilities for the survey of a proposed pipeline. The projected route would be from the neighbourhood of Mosul to the My Directors would be glad to have your Mediterranean coast at either Alexandretta or Tripoli I have, etc.. Secretary ■Excellency r he Minister for Foreign Affairs, Quai d T Orsay ParisMonday 17th October» I932n lour Exoellency, You sirs no douht sw&amp;ro tha&gt;t tli5.a uoi2.p8j5.y ^-'-3 obtained from the Iraq Government the grant of an oil concession covering all the lands of Iraq on ^he west B&amp;nh of the River Tigris north of the thirty- third parallel of latitudeo My Directors would be glad to have your assurance that in due course they may be privilege^*, to receive from your Government facilities for the survey for a proposed pipelineo The projected route would be from the neighbourhood of Mosul following the Turco- ‘Syrian frontier to the Mediterranean coast at either Alasandretta or Tripoli® I have &gt; etc ®, SECRETARY « ; tTceilenoyc, :&gt;.a Minister for Foreign Affairs, Angora^ TurkeyCommunications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State.. Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. and the following Number quoted : 96301/32. ! 6 -3 , l * .v ^ ^ fll \\[^ Sir, With reference to the letter from this Department of the 20th February, I am directed by &lt;10 Sir, 0 -£r 18 do . Cad^ 8 * 10 ' l938j 18. 38; If 1 &gt; THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, INDIA OFFICE. Secretary Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister to transmit to you, for the information of Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare,| copies of the notes exchanged between the Iraqi Prime Minister and Sir John Cadman embodying the settlement of the recent dispute betv/een the Iraqi Government and the Iraq Petroleum Company in regard to the payment of dead rent and advance on account of royalties. I am, Sir, Your most obedient servant. —Iraq Legation, 51, Queen*s Gate hardens, London, '• 16th February, 1932. My dear Sir John, 7ith reference to our conversation to-day wiien you mentioned to me the difficulties experienced by the Iraq ietroleum Company in its dealings with the Iraq Customs Department, and other taxation questions, 1 wish to assure you that I will remove the cause of these difficulties. I also wish to assure you that the Iraq Government will sympathetically consider any unexpected difficulty which may arise in the future in the course of any operations with milch the Company is connected. Yours sincerely, (Signed) Nuri Said. To Sir John Cadman, G. 0.1.0., B. 3cP.Z. 1 Q ^ T b/7 ; i93^: V«.' •-V V./ 18 th f8 Druary # ~“1^5^ ^ % dear Kuri, With reference to our conversation to-day .with regard to the amount of £ 409,000 (gold) due to the Iraq Government on 1st January, 193£, as desired by you the Iraq ietroleum Company agrees to pay without prejudice to either party the sum of £578,000 in full discharge of the above-mentioned obligation* 1 accordingly request you to instruct your bankers to present a sight draft for £409,000 (gold) on the understanding that the Iraq i etroleum Company will authorise its bankers to pay the sum of £578,000 abo ve -me fit i oned • Yours sincerely, (3igned) J ohn Cadman* To His Excellency Ihiri i as ha. TB 12 b Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted :— 30f/*&gt; Subject • ^ Rejerence to previous correspondence Letter /»^ the Colonial OJjice of the jrom (R9720) Wt 18117/2750 10,00C(2) 12/31 H &amp; SP Gp 112I^L^GRAM from the High Coiunissloner of Iraq to tha ^ Secretary of State for the Colonies* v S Catea 2nci January, 1922- IRecelvea Colonial orrice 3,35 p.ia„ 2nd January, 1932) cs c* c: c? ^ c: IwlPOiTi'AN'i', No, 1, Article n Iraq Fetrole’no company Supplementary AiSreement dated 24th iiarch 1-31 and Aaireeiiient. 1155 of same date Iraqi «50''&amp;rauen: hr .a received telegraphic advice from Eastern Bank L.ondov %ux Iraq Petrol hum C ompaity acting on legal advice positively refuse to pay gold. They will pay 409.000 pounds (sterling) out only against oms. Iraqi Govertiaent sent ollls to London at Company's request for 400.000 pouiius gold and 9,000 pounds gold. On advice of Eastern Bank iaatructiona have now aeen given that these bills should not be presented,, Iraqi Government will be grateful for legal opinion as to precise sum in sterling .which the company should We asked to pay as the equivalent of 409..000 pounds gold Could you obtain and send this by telegram, Iraqi Government are perturbed at this turn o. events and say that it is likely seriously to embitter relations with the Company. They ha « no indication of nature of legal advice given to the Company and would be grateful for advice of H M Government, as to what course they Should pursue, it should he remembered in thic connection that Iraqi Government would have recourse to arbitration under Article io of print!pal agreement and not to British courts.mmMinute Paper Department f °Mr It MOSUL OIL FIELDS CONTROL ACQUIRED BY ITALIAN INTERESTS Y ie i- i- o it a &gt;f n in o d i. h n e n 0 f 1 i I It was officially Enounced last night that Sir Edward M. Mountain and Mr. L. C. Patterson have resigned their directorships of Mosul Oil Fields and its associated, concern, British Oil Develop ment Company. The resignations have been accepted. Mr. F. W. Rickett, who secured the recent Abyssinian concession, was closely associated with the original promotion of the British Oil Development Company. Mosul Oil Fields, Limited, a private company with an authorized capital of £1,850,000, was registered in 1932 to acquire all the shares of the British Oil Development Company, which was granted a concession of about 45,000 square miles from the Iraqi Government. According to the 1935 Stock Exchange Year-book, Viscount Goschen, the chair man, was supported on the board of directors by,, among others, two Italians, one Frenchman, and two Germans. The new board of directors, omitting Sir Edward Mountain and Mr. Patterson, consists of 13 members, and includes five Italians, one Frenchman, and two Germans. The Press Association was in formed that Italian interests have acquired sufficient shares to have control in both companies, which were formerly managed by British interests. . Sir Edward Mountain refused to make any comment last night on his resignation. The B.O.D. Company had long dis cussions this year with the Iraqi Govern ment regarding the building of a £3,500,000 railway from their oil wells at Quaiyarah to Tel Kuchuk. Sir Edward Mountain was deputy chair man of Mosul Oil *Fields and B.O.D. Company, and is chairman and managing director of the Eagle Star and British Dominions Insurance Company. The official announcement of' Sir Edward Mountain’s and Mr. Patterson’s resigna tions states that “ no other resignations have taken place recently.” Mr. William R. Brown, another director of Mosul Oil Fields and the B.O.D. Company, denied the suggestion last night that he also had resigned. “ I have not yet resigned,” he said, “ but I am considering what steps I shall take. Some time ago a meeting was arranged to be held in London. It was cancelled, then held a day or two later in Paris. I am one of the original directors.” k. i r t 1 &gt; ■&lt; i t &gt; &gt; i t I S t 1 &gt; 1 d g 3 g S t t r e d s n P o e e y r s t r ITALIAN INTEREST IN MOSUL OILFIELDS STATEMENT BY MR. F. W. RICKETT Mr. F. W. Rickett, who recently ob tained an oil concession from the Emperor of Abyssinia, last night made a statement about his position in relation to Mosul Oilfields and its associated concern, British Oil Development. The resignations of Sir Edward Moun tain and Mr. L. C. Patterson from the boards of these companies were an nounced on Monday. Mr. Rickett was closely concerned with the formation of British Oil Development Company, the shares of which were acquired by Mosul Oilfields in order to exploit a concession obtained by the B.O.D. Company in Iraq. I have had no connexion with the manage ment of either of these companies for the last two years (Mr. Rickett stated). I withdrew when it became obvious to me that the control, which I considered it was absolutely essential should remain British, would pass into Con tinental hands. My only interest now is that of a large shareholder. It is, of course, a vital condition of the concession that the company owning it must be British, have a British chair man, and have its offices in Great Britain. This doubtless explains Lord Goschen's retention of the chairmanship of these foreign-controlled com panies. Mr. William R. Brown is, it is under stood, also retaining his scat on both boards at the request of the original British shareholders, of w'hom he was one, as otherwise these would be entirely without representation. The new boards include five Italians, one Frenchman, and two Germans. Commenting yesterday on the reasons that led to his resignation from the boards of Mosul Oilfields and the B.O.D. Company, Sir Edward Mountain stressed the continued cordiality of his relations with the companies concerned. His resignation, he said, was entirely due to his appreciation of the fact that the recent strengthening of Italian interests in the com panies, as a result of their payment of the dead rent on the concession, should be proportionately represented on the board of directors. ¥ I f c f I 1 1 1 c 1 h r F t s &lt; c I 1 1 2956 6000 7 34-/ wmmmrnmmmmmmmmu &lt;§&gt; &amp; t ^ f (THIS DOCUMENT IS THS PROPERTY OP HIS BRITAHNIC lAATLSTY* S GOVYRiHIRKT'). SECRE T, «(0 ) 24 th Mt r . P. ' AL COPY. COPY HO. y COMMITTEE OP IMPERIAL DEFENCE. STANDING QFPICIAL SUB- COMl^ ITTSE POR QU ESTIONS CONCERNING THE MIDDLE EAST. MINUTES of a Meeting of the Sub-Committee held at No. 2 3 Whitehall Gardens-, S.W. 1. 9 on Monday, July 17th, 1933, at 3.30 p.m. SUBJECTS - 1. PROPOSED PIPBLIItS PROM THS BRITISH OIL DEVELOPMENT COMPANY 1 S CONCESSION NEAR MOSUL TO THE MEDITERRANEAN. TRAILS-DESERT RAILWAY PROM BAGHDAD TO HAIFA. PRESENT: Mr. G.W. Rendel, C.M.G., Counsellor, Foreign Office, (in the Chair). Captain H.R. Moore, D.S.O.,R.N., Director of Plans Division, Admiralty. Colonel K.D.B. Murray, C.B., D.S.O., General Staff, War Office. Air Commodore R.E.C.Pierse,D.S.0, , A.P.C., Deputy Director of Operations and Intelligence, Air Ministry. Mr. R.A. Grieve, O.B.E., Assistant Secretary, Treasury. THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT: Lieut.-Colonel Sir Francis H. Humphrys, G.C.M.G., G.C.V.O., K.B.E., C.I.E., His Majesty’s Ambassador at Baghdad, Sir Alfred Faulkner, C.B., C.B.E., Under-Secretary for Mines (for Item 1.) Colonel P.J. Mackesy, D.S.O., M.C., General Staff, War Office. Mr. P.C. Starling, Director of Petroleum Department, (for Item 1.) Mr. E.P. Donaldson, Principal, India Office. Air Vice-Marshal Sir S.R.Ludlo'w- Hewitt, K.C.B., C.M.G., D.S.O., M.C., Deputy Chief of the Air Staff. Mr. O.G.R. Williams, Assistant Secretary, Colonial Office. Group-Captain A.T. Harris, O.B.E., I A.P.C., Deputy Director of Operations and Intelligence Designate, Air Ministry. Mr. J.C. Sterndale Bennett,C.M.G., &gt; M.C., First Secretary, Foreign Office. Mr. W.L. Gore 11 Barnes, Third Secretary, Foreign Office. Lieut.-Colonel N.G. Hind, M.C. , Secretary to- 1 - (S) 1. PROPOSED PIPELINE PROM THE BRITISH OIL DEVELOPMENT COMPANY’S CONCESSION NEAR MOSUL TO THE MR. RSNDEL, v/ho 3 in the absence of Mr. Parkinson was acting as Chairman, wished to express his regret, which he felt sure was shared by all the Sub-Committee, at the impending departure of Air Commodore Pierse and Colonel Murray, who were attending the meeting for the last time. He extended a welcome to their successors. Colonel Mackesy and Group Captain Harris. THE SUB-COMMITTEE had before them the following paper:- Memorandum by the Petroleum Department. (paper No. M.E.(O) 93). THE CHAIRMAN explained that this memorandum dealt with the question of the transport to the Mediterranean MEDITERRANEAN. of any oil which might be obtained by the British Oil Development Company under their concession from the Iraqi Government. A new Company known as Mosul Oil Fields, Ltd. had been formed to work the Concession. The Company were apparently contemplating tne construction of a pipeline from Mosul to Alexandretta along the northern frontier of Syria. This alignment did not seem, however, to have been finally decided on, and another alignment v/as possible. A]_ternatively they might come to an agree ment with the Iraq Petroleum Company for the use of the latter’s pipeline system. The question for discussion was what solution would be most advantageous from the point of view of British interests, and what action, if any, could be taken by His Majesty's Government to ensure that such a solution were adopted. The matter was, however, one of great difficulty, and it was not clear how His Majesty’s Government Could intervene. SIR ALFRED FAULKNER explained that recent develop ments had rendered this question even more difficult. Mosul Oil Fields Ltd. had recently suggested that HisMajesty’s Government should assume a financial interest in the Company. After careful consideration a decision had been taken against this suggestion. The question had also been considered whether the Anglo-Persian Oil Company could take a financial interest in the Company 9 but their participation was ruled out by the agreement under which this area was excluded from the sphere of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company’s operations. A third possibility had been the assumption of a financial interest in Mosul Oil Fields Ltd. by the I.P.C. or some other agreement between them. Sir Alfred Faulkner had approached Sir John Cadman with such a suggestion^ but after a talk with Sir Alwin Dickinson 9 the Managing Director of Mosul Oil Fields 3 Ltd. 9 Sir John Cadman had stated that the I.P.C. was not at present prepared to take a part. Whether some arrangement would be possible in future might depend to a considerable extent on whether oil were found in paying quantities. The fact that His Majesty’s Government had been unable to take any financial interest in Mosul Oil Fields Ltd. would make it all tha more difficult to approach that Company with any suggestion that they should meet the wishes of His Majesty’s Government in such a question as the alignment of their pipeline. Opportunities might 9 however^ present themselves later of influencing the policy of the Company through its British Chairman, and he was anxious to know the views of the Sub-Committee and particularly of the Deforce Departments on the importance which they attached to the issue. THD CHAIRMAN recalled that the question of influencing the Company’s decision in regard to the alignment or iheir pipeline had been fully discussed over a year ago. Her quoted a despatch of May 5th, 1932, from Sir Francis Humphrys, which gave the reasons why it had then 'been impossible to secure any control over the choice of the alignment. Sir Francis Humphrys had, however, at that time suggested the possibility of an agreement between the B.O.D. and the I.P.C. for the transport of the former’s oil over the latter’s pipeline. SIR FRANCIS HUMPHRYS thought that the fact that neither His Majesty’s Government nor the I.P.C. would finance Mosul Oilfields Ltd., did not preclude that Company from negotiating for the use of the I.P.C. pipe line. He pointed out that the proposed alignment from Mosul to Alexandretta would lie close to the Syro- Turkish frontier, which was a potential battle-field. The Turks made no secret of their aspirations to regain Aleppo and northern Syria, which he regarded as not improbable some day, either as the result of war or even by peaceful methods, as there was a large Turkish population in this area. The French might well prefer that the pipeline should go direct to Tripoli, which, although longer, was a safer route than via Aleppo to Alexandretta. THE CHAIRMAN remarked that there appeared to be some divergence of view as to the extent of the danger of Turkish expansion in this area. He did not wish to question Sir Francis Humphrys’ views, but there were other authorities, such as H.M. Ambassador in Turkey, who did not consider it at all probable that Turkey would seek to expand to the south of her present frontiers. It was possible that the French might not regard this danger as a very real one. It would certainly be extremely difficult, if not impossible, for His Majesty’s Government - 3 -- 4 . mmm to draw tne attention ol tne irencii Government to sucn a danger; and ii the,y did so ; the irencn Government would only suspect their motives and would be umiuely to be inlluenced. 'me discussion having reverted to the question ol the possibility ol an agreement between Mosul Gil Fields Ltd. and the i.r.G. for the use by the former of tne latter 1 s pipeline, Sin ALlnim, FaULKLILH pointed out that the German group had participated in Mosul Gil Fields Ltd. on the understanding that 38 per cent, of tne plant required for any pipeuine constructed by the Company should be bought in Germany. The uerman group were therefore lihely go favour the construction of an independent pipeline and to ox^pose any pipeline agreement with the I.F.C. Uixii, CiL^lru/iGh pointed out that tne Italian group would probably u-lso prefer an independent pipeline, since they nau participated in tne formation of Mosul Gil lields Ltd. in opposition to the groups represented on ihe I.P.C. inis opposition oi interests would probably militate against an,) pipeline agreement between the two companies. CaPIaIL mOGhE said that the Admiralty would definitely preier that the B.O.D. pipeline should tane tne southern route and terminate at Haifa. The first reason was that the measures ol defence necessary for the I.P.C. pipeline would probably cover the two. The second was that a measure such as this would tend lor the development of Haifa, on which the Admiralty placed considerable importance. The iuear solution would be that the B.O.jj. Company snouad buiud tneir own pipeline to Haifa.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001a9_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2882</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001a9</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2882</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 17/21 ‘Iraq. Oil in – ’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-19T09:04:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (89 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate reverse chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 89; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains papers relating to the oil concessions and operations of the Iraq Petroleum Company and the British Oil Development Company in Iraq.It includes:Papers concerning payments due to the Government of Iraq from these companies.Papers of the Committee of Imperial Defence Standing Sub-Committee for Questions Concerning the Middle East, dated 1933, concerning the British Oil Development Company’s proposed pipeline from its concession near Mosul to the Mediterranean.Papers regarding the official opening of the Iraq Petroleum Company’s pipeline connecting the oil-field at Kirkuk with the Mediterranean port of Haifa, on 14 January 1935.The papers include India Office minute papers, correspondence, and three newspaper cuttings from
                           The Times. The correspondence is largely between Sir Francis Henry Humphrys, HM Ambassador to Iraq (HM Representative, Baghdad), and Sir John Simon, Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. Other correspondents include: the India Office; the High Commissioner of Iraq; the Colonial Office; Sir John Cadman, Chairman of the Board of Directors of the Iraq Petroleum Company; and the [British Government] Petroleum Department (Mines Department).The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Oil Development Company</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Committee of Imperial Defence, Standing Official Sub-Committee for Questions Concerning the Middle East</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Kirkuk</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Colonial Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Iraq Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>The Times, British newspaper</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Division</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mosul</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Haifa</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Oil</topic></subject><subject><topic>Pipelines</topic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Iraq</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001a9#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>