<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002f7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T08:33:21.561Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">■■ ■ v Telegraph Section, Colonial Office, Church House. Telegram Section, /Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street. War Registry, admiralty. Duty Signal , War Ofri^o^ignal Office, MonWrl5e House ijinexe. Message Control, German Section, Foreign Office, Horrgc. Herewith co-&gt;y of telegram No. from * ^ for repetition ^in cypher* to_ i_ FOREIGN OFFICE. (Date) Telegram Section. * Delete when inapplicableTills telegr ua is of particular secrecy unu should be „ . mm tf 7. The i Inister for Foreign Affairs sent for «ae on 1st April to make urgent request for assistance in getting certain ^*r material which Government required to enable them to deal with the insurrections which ioight take place as a result of strong measures they were taking against Communists* ' he Government, he said, wanted six fighter bombers, thirty armoured cars, one thousand each Bren^ Tommy and 3ten guns, three thousand rifles, four hundred field wireless sets* similar appeals were being made to United states and ndlan Ambassadors and a telegram had been sent the night before to the Burmese mbassador. New jelhi* 2* The inister agreed that I should first consult the Head ol the services Mission anu the two mbassadors in oraer to co~orulnatc action* I therefore arranged a meeting with General Bourne and the two Ambassadors at which General Bourne explained that the inister's list bore little relation to the Army 1 ! real requirements as he conceived thera* 12 agreed that it was necessary for the matter fi^st to be threshed out between the Minister of defence aw*. General Bourne* The United tates and Indian mbassadora said they would gladly consult their Governments ab jut the ^possibility of supplying any Material which might not be available frota United Klngdm sources* d. I tolu the Inister for Foreign affairs the result of our meeting, ana he at once arranged for ■ inister of defence to see General ie* \u a result ef that meeting, detailed requirements are now beinp worked out by Burmese ana Mission experts. Meanwhile the Burmese are now pressing fer nson Aircraft, and General Bourne has telegraphed both to tendon and ingapore about this# His discussions with the dnister of Defence and the Burmese Government's request for aircraft have been reported by the Mission to the '^ar office ano. ir Ini to try gp* undec* j messages contained in my telegrams Nos. 279, 285, 286 an I tp ingapore .rll J /(uy telegr ..a u*. 895Bangiwn telcgr.ua N«. 296 to Foreign ufflc e. “5828 1948 («y telegTciia if®* 296 to you), vs regards the &gt;ilce of ?iny aircraft that nay be available, I think there is umch to be #1 s*id, in view of the special circumstances, for keening it as low as )os dble. 4. The Oevemment, who were inclined to panic last - eek, are now taking the situation more calmly. But the Inister for Foreign affairs told me today that the situation was still threatening and called for immediate action, iieveral police posts in the country districts had been aver-powered by the Communists ^vh® had seized the occupants* rms ana in the egu aistrict villages were being surrounded and forced to surrender licenced weapons. Ministerjiaid that the situation around Pegu c Ilea for a military operation and Govern!tent were anxious to deal with it at t?nce before trouble spread. 6* The ]fillister tola me that the Burmese mbassador in London had been instructed to acquaint you with the situation. 6. a more detailed re &gt;ort follows by bag. 3 i G.R.O. for transmission to U.K. High a</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002f7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2221</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002f7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2221</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 7/50 'Supply of war material to Burma'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-27T22:52:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 7; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Copy telegram sent by HM Legation Rangoon [Yangon] to HM High Commissioner, New Delhi, regarding a meeting with the Burmese Minister for Foreign Affairs, and requests for military equipment to deal with possible communist insurrections.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM High Commissioner to India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Burma</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Weapons</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002f7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>