<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001e7_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-02-04T14:11:54.406Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">N WAR Allotted to External Departnient * £ O From To WORD COBS Political Resident Secretary at State for Conraonwealth Relations Bated Bahrein 19*15 hours? 30th September* 1947 Received 04*00 hours^ 1st October* 1947 IMPORTANT ' -***».*.. :t ^»*»*W*w* Wo* UlPl Following for Hay» Acoousits New Delhi have telegraphed your English leave salary certificate was despatched High Commissioner for India London on August 20the 1— nu« p. h SV /A' n L 1Wt. 25044/P4666. 9/46 C.N.P.Co. Ltd. 51-7260 Charges to pay s. d. RECEIVE^ at Central Telegraph Office, E.C. I No. POST OFFICE ^yerpp^STAMP * v uf i* Prefix. Time handed in. Office of Origin and Service Instructions Words i-*/ * . 35 TELEGRAM From By 1^5 10.5 CH I BLOCK 14 — To By ^LOMS COMHONHCALT!I’ RELATIONS OFFICE KING CHARLES 'sT _ N 1 HTEil AuL LONDON SH- 1 = ' PREFER 4.30 SECOND = HAf + ■ CT SH 1 4,M) . For uee repetition or douWuT words telephone “TELEGRAMS ENQUIRY” or call, with this form B or C at office of delivery. Other enquiries should be accompanied by this form, and, if possible, the envelope. cT1 , . -5' } Wt.*2S044/ P4444. 1/46 G.N.P.Co. Ltd. 51-7260 Charges to pay s. d. POST No.. OFFICE OFFICE STAMP RECEIVED at Central Telegraph Office. E.C. I TELEGRAM M / Prefix. Time hantfsd in. Office of Origin and Service Instruction. Words. a. ^ From, By i m M — 84 10/23 CHiDEOCK 20 To' HALLOWS COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS OFFICE KING CHARLES STREET WHITEHALL LONDON $N 1= CONFIRM NOON SECOND HIGH WOOD SUGGEST 3 PM SECOND C4CC!A = HAY | ) - rtL .ITf Hrtr + 3ne 'TELEGRAMS ENQUIRY” ©r tall, with this form B orC | at office of delivery. Other enquiries should be accompanied by this form, and, if possible, the envelope. CPUSH'*iuZ INWA Allotted to External Department COWPIDSMTIAL CODH! Px*ora / To Dated Received Government of India J^xte^nai Afrairs and Commonwealth Relations Department. Secretary of State for India New Delhi 23,30 hours, 14th July 1947 22.40 hours, 14th July 1947 54.95 Your telegram No.9020 of July 12th. Hay’s departure! 2. We have no objection.DEPTL. No j3rt.l36SA7.t. DRAFT TELEGRAM No ftPtZQ. From .. .Sacr.et ary... of. .Stato -fo-F- India To ..(Joyerment...of.India., Bxtftrml Affairs &amp; Cornmomveglt i Relations Department jRrpcafrrLlr* It is proposed to put Sir Rupert Hay on deputation 7th July - 20th July for purpose of disc ussier; here in Realty O' ' connection \vith the/persian Gulf/. ^ Hay s** ^ elects to consume leave during this period of duty. Please telegraph v/hether you agree. DESPATCHED O (10858) Wt. 21358—P172 20m. 8/46 G.S.St. Gp. 620I // , © J/ External Department. NOTES FOR REGISTRY. REGISTER NO. / 2 v&gt;i /utyij Hil 194 Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary ^ — Secretary of State - Committee . . Under Secretary Secretary of State Perusal FOR USE BY DEPARTMENT ONLY.4v&lt;y. «&lt;&gt; O) Colonel 1 raser. ^ v ' ^ ^V.. wT Lieutenant-Colonel Rupert Rsp, Political Reaident in the Pers3.an Gulf, on whom a K*C«X.£« iiaa been conferred in The King’s Birthday Honours, will be returning to this country on short leave at the end of this month. He is due to arrive about 28th June and will be in or near London until about the middle of July whe i he goes to Ireland. If arrangements could be made for him to be dubbed at an Investiture while he is in this country it would be very convenient. I hope that in ary case some opportunity could be ta.:en for Colonel Hay to be received by The King before his return to the Persian Gulf since, as you know, the Rulers of the Gulf States attach a great deal of importance to ceremonial matters of this kind, and, on political grounds, I hope that arrangements can be made accordingly. ( ip •, J.- . Donaldson. 14 *vi. 47 ‘</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001e7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1202</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001e7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1202</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 1368/47 'Col Hay, Political Resident, Persian Gulf: leave and deputation 1947'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-03-02T09:30:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (16 folios)</extent><extent>The file's contents are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 19, these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of a letter, telegrams, and notes between officials of the Government of India, India Office, and the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations regarding the deputation of Lieutenant-Colonel William Rupert Hay, Political Resident in Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Deputations</topic></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001e7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>