<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000195_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T15:54:57.632Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE 'Sri IOR NEGI ^ / (D 5th June 1914# 6 The Governor here keeps raising the question of a Persian representative at -asqat# It appears that tier© ~ r as an article in the Habl ul Matin about a aueotlon of a Persian shoplceeper belnR beaten at asqat by a fanatical 'utawwah. This was a fact and the Governor tells me that the matter attracted the notice of the 'Inister for ^orci '.n Affairs at Tehran who has wired asking His Fxcelloncy whether it would be better to get a Persian representative at Masqat or ask the Fn^lish to protect Persian nationals, in fact, take charge, at the instance of the Persian Governraent, of Persian interests® I don't serious/believe there is anything in all this# X am doubtful if anyone at Tehran has bothered his head about Persians at Msqat and could of course enquire from inister on the subject, but, before doing so, I should be glad of a lead from you on the subject. Co far as i can ascertain such a suggestion was never mooted in your time but ^ossibly Kia Excellency ^ay have occasionally talked about it in his private conversations with you. There is some fascination about the idea o the Political Agent, Masqat, assuming charge of Persian in terests at Masqat, but both Sultan and France would no doubt object* Benn mi^it perhaps make capital out of th# suggestion by telling His Highness that it was suggested and that, , if we found His Highness oorresnonding with Persian Govern ors on matters &lt;!bf political interest - and of c mrne the % foolish nan dooo this - w© night think serlous^of the 'he Hon'ble Lieut-Ool Sir P#Z # Oox, K»O.I.E.,C»S,I. nr ' r Foreign secretary, Sirala. —matter and inforra him one fine day that, at the request of the Persian Government, v;e proposed to treat Persians as British subjects and that ho »ould not possibly object# 'ftiis should terrify him if he realised its significance. But the whole subject bristles with difficlhltles and, beyond telling His Excellency that it is a difficult question, I find myself a good deal embarrassed by his constant queries. Can you give rae any guidance? It is just within the bounds of possibility that this mad notion may come up officially and I should like to have omnE general notion of how to treat (i) the proposal that we should assume charge of Persian interests at flaoqat. (ii) the appointment of a Persian Consul at Masqat. lo^/P(Confidential) 3^: eusHiRt Ksnstnc^ ' .1 . „ , _ „ #«w(n and ^otitta) Stptlwttil Rtft Wo 'H . _ q 7- lu.Siml*. ! CCvnOfNtKl RECOROS. 1.1 11 -fc.... 11 $ 'zJuly /h^ h^rr yv \niH- Please refer to your demi-official letter dated the 6th June 1914, to the address of Sir Percy Cox on the question of the appointment of a, Persian Consul or representative at ^askat. In view of pact history the relations of the Sultans of Maskat with Persia can perhaps, hardly 'be regarded in quite the same light as his re lations with other foreign pov/ers, hut in any case the presence of a Persian representative could only prove a source of inconvenience and it is considered that we should do our hest to discourage thethe idea. To this end I on desired to sa^ that there are two arguments which could he used with effect either with the Governor of Bushire, or the Cen tral Govern-nent. firstly, that we are in a position to intervene much more effectively in behalf of Persian subjects at Maskat in case of serious need, than any 'Consul' of theirs could he, and that they might just as well use our good offices as they have done in the past. Secondly, that whereas they have no treaty or arrangemen' vitl the Sultan providing for the reception of representatives from one State to the other, and whereas the Per sian Government and the Governor of the Gulf Ports, have consistently refused to accord any 'Consular' or other official recognition to Muhammad hin TahnoonTahnoon, the Sultan's Agent at Lingah the Sultan might naturally be expected to object to receiving a Persian representative unless Persia recognised his, and the Persian Governnent would find a Maskat 'Consul' merely a centre of petty inconvenience and intrigue. T am to suggest that you should,if necessary , express your views on the question to the Governor at Bushlre, and to His Majesty's Minister at Tehran,on the ahove lines. Tt is perhaps hardly necessary that the Sultan should he communicated with on the subject for the present, hut you will no doubt explain the position to the Political Agent, in order that he may know what line to take should necessity arise. I To . /I J/ Major S.G.Knox, Cl.I.E. , ( ^ ^ Officiating Political Aaenl-. in the Persian Gulf #Oonfidential• Docket Telegram. Prom Knox, P.R. Buohire. To Benn, P.A. Masqat. D.O. Dated 3Cj#7.14* Enclosed please find copy of a confidential D.O. from Grant, in reply to one of nine asking what line to take in the matter of a possible, though most unlikely, attempt to appoint a Persian Consul to Masqat. It is a pet hobby of our Governor here. Grant puts the position very clearly and no doubt the Foreign view will be useful to you, should the necessity arise.18.7.14. 3^ &amp;Cj Dear Mr. Grant, I am much obliged to you for your D.O. of the 3rd July on the question of a Persian Consul or representative at ^asqat. I shall act on the lines indicated should it prove necessary and am letting Benn know the line we are to take. Yours sincerely, S.G.Knox. ____3£ TE^GRAH. 'R' . From, Townley, TOLniBter, To, ' Knox, Resiftent. No: 196. ^ated 15.9.14. . (3) !!lninter for Foreign Affairs states yon will not agree tnat British Representative at Masqat shall protect Persian subjects who are said to loe hardly used.'by people and authorities at Masqat. please let me have some information on the subject . Persian Grovermient say they will send a representative to Masqat if the British representative there is not allowed to protect Persians. 'Townley,'Bus hire, - ^ 17th September 1914. /%4_^ l/eJidZ' There is a curious little intrigue behind the question of your telegram No. 196 dated 15th September 1914. Some con- 5 iderable time ago - I should think about a year - at our inFtanoe the Sultan of Masqat relieved certain irlanders of a Persian island near Lingeh of the money with which they had - it was obvious and clearly proved — come to purchase arms• Ever since the Muwaqqar—uci—Dauleh came to hear of it, he has been moving heaven and earth to get hold of that money ( tor local improvements*.). After trying my predecessor, the late Mr Lorimer, who warned me while I was in Masqat of the attempt, His Excellency tackled me on the subject immediately I arrived. As a good Political Agent, Masqat, whose main object in life was to discourage the arms traffic, I would not hear of the pro posal and of course it would not bear discussion 4ny way. A Persian subject commits an offence against the local laws and proclamations o„ a foreign country an the authorities of that country, arrest, try and fine him, why should a Persian Govern or get the fine? I urged Eis Excellency to retaliate on Masqat arms smuggl rs when I would give all assistance I could in re lieving them of their spare cash. In the course of my arguments showing why I regretted that I could not fall in with the views of His Excellency, I perhaps unguardedly let slip the remark that, even if I could bring my self to accept His Excellency's views, it was by no means certal that His Highness would consent to listen to my remonptrances, &lt;L that subjects of a Mohammadan country, other than those of Watiy States in India, were considered in Masqat as subject to the Sultan* H.S. Sir W.B. Townley, K.C.M.Q-. H.M , s Envoy Extraordinary &amp; Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of Persia, TEHRAN.Sultan 1 s own Jurisdiotion and that we did not interfere. By treaty and ordinarily in practice this view is probably correct. In our treaties with Masqat, a clear and raUier quaint distinction is drawn between British subjects and those of other Christian nations on the one hand arid subjects of Kis Highness the Sufctan or those of any non-Christian nation on the other. The one have ex-territorial rights, while the others are ordinarily treated as subjects of His iiigi^ness t, 10 ultcv . to all intents and purposes. On the other hand, His Highness the Suitan is bound by his own engagements to pay attention and to seek the advice of th6 British Qovernment in all important matters. I expected something of this kind and accordingly asked for Simla views /i on the subject. The following is what I received but demi-officiaily and confidentially:- M In viev; of past history the relations of the Saltans of 'Masqat with Persia can perhaps, hardly be r garded in quite 'the same li^ht as his relations with other foreign Powers, 'but in any case the presence of a Persian representative could 'only prove a source of inconvenience and it is consider6d txiat 'we should do our best to discourage the idea'. ' There are two arguments which would be used with effect. ' Firstly, that we are in a po ition to intervene much more 'effectively in behalf of Persian subjects at Masqat in case 'of f erious need, than any ''Consul*' of theirs could be, cuaa 'that they might Just as well use our good offices as they have 'cone in the past. Secondly, that whereas they have no treaty 'or arrangement with the Sultan providing for the reception of 'representatives from one State to the other, and whereas the 'Persian Oovemment anc 1 the Q-overnor of the GKilf Ports, have 'consistently refused to accord any 'Consular' or/ other 'official recognition to Muhammad bin Tahnoon, the Sultan's 'Agent at Lingeh ; the Sultan might naturally be expected to 'object to receiving a Persian representative unless Persia 'recognised his, and the Persian aovemment would find a 'Masqat 'Consul' merely a centre of petty inconvenience and intrigueintrigue' I hope that these renarkB may be of use to Your Excellency in discussing the matter with the Minister lor Foreign Affairs, The latter will only stir up a deal of trouble and possibly let himself in for a humiliating rebuff. If the Sultan undrr- Btanda the matter in its true light, he will certainly refuse to admit a Persian representative and Bersia is in no position to compel him to do bo.Telegram.P. From - Knox, Resident, Bushire. To - Minister, Tehran. No. ^35/1124. Dated 21-9-i4» 3&gt; ,0 1 @ m Your Excellency^ 196 dated 15th September re garding proposal to send Persian Representative to Masqat. Position has been entirely misrepresented to Minister for Foreign Affairs: I am in possession of the views of the Governmont of India on the subject and pro pose sending them to Your Excellency by letter which, if possible, please await. I have only heard of one case in which a fanatic Mullah beat a Persian merchant for smoking in the street contrary to a local edict by His Highness. In that case, the British Consul addressed a remonstrance to His Highness and my experience of 3 years as Political Agent, Masqat, has certainly not led me to believe that Persian subjects in Masqat are badly treated. We should certainly intervene and give good offices In case of serious need and such good offices are /likely to be far more effective than any protection a Persian representative could afford. Presence of such representative could only prove inconvenient. Sultan would almost certainly insist on reciprocity and Persian Government would find Masqat Consul merely a centre of inconvenience and petty intrigue. Knox.# v ' v? n- I* Ho . at, of 1914. Forwarded to the Qovemment of India In the Foreign and Poiluioal tepartment, for information. By Order, ] A B Second AssIrtaut to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushlre, yi September 2&amp;id 191^-• List of Papers (1). Telegram from Minister llo. 19^ dated 15th September 1914. (2), Telegram to Minister Bo. 235/H24 dated 21st Sep tember 191 4 '* w * V3s r ® Telegramo Ro Prom Minister Tehrano NOo 2slio201o Dated 2^o9»14. Your telegram No. 2^^-1124o Minister for Foreign Affairs asks that British reprsent— ^ r-^—4/ ative at Mas oat may be instr ucted to une Jnip of^looo o n p^v.^i-p n-p Persian ^ubgLects o His Highness says that Sultan not being entirely independent could not ask/V for reciprocity wj^ere a Persian Consul appointed &amp;.t Mus cat. His Highness adds however that the Persian g -overn- ment do not intend to re-establish the Agency in Muscat whifcLh was abolished years ago. Townley.Telegram P, From '^es ident o To Foreign. No. Dated 28.9»14o Following from Minister, begins,, 'Minister for Foreign- Affairs .......... -years ago'. Endso I would be glad of instructions as to reply to be sent and venture to suggest ad interim reply as follows, begins ' Your Excellency's telegram No.^o/ dated 26.9,14 I have referred question raised by His Highness to Q-overnment of India and hope in due course to receive instructions that our own represent ative will continue to exercise in the future as in the past his good offices on behalf of Persian subjects when appealed to and in all cases of ^eriou? hardship or oppression, and I doubt not that His Highness the Sultan will be powerfully influenced by such represent ation' . Ends. Our representative at Muscat would have to exerci?© such good offices with caution for fear of his action being resented by His Highness, and mis—represented^his foreign colleagues. It might be worthwhile to lay some stress on Sultan's independence being guaranteed b: Great Britain and France in view of remark of Minister for Foreign Affairs, Previous telegraphic correspond ence which does not materially effect i* question goes to you by post. Knox. 9// 3 ©Telegramo P* Prom Minister Tehrano Addressed Foreign Office t Repeated BushirWo Noo 203o Dated 30th September 1914 i J U IS After an exchange of telegrams with -British Consul G-eneral Bushire, I was able to give Minister of For eign Affairs certain assurances in regard to protect ion of Persian subjects at Masqat, but His Highness still maintains that the latter are very much oppres sed o He requests that instructions may issue to our Consul at Masqat to take over charge of Persian in terests. His Highness says that if this proves im possible, French Q-overnment will be approached and if they also refuse, the Persian G-overnment will find it self obliged to re-open their Masqat Agency. Townleyo Above telegram repeated to Foreign under NOo 1172 of October 2nd 1914«.H ¥ Telegramo Po From Foreigno To Residento NOo 831-So Dated 2nd October 1914o You are authorised to inform Minister that you have received instructions of the nature indicated in your telegram No«3,152 of September 28th« But you need make no allusion to question of Sultan's independence when replying Tehran, ForeignTelegram. From - Knox, Resident, Bushire. To - Minister, Tehran. No. 242/1177. Dated 4-10-14. i Your Excellency's telegram No, 201 dated 26th Sep tember 1914, I have referred question raised by His Highness to Government of India, who have instructed me that our representative Masqat will continue to exercise in the future as in the past his good offices on behalf of Persian subjects when appealed to and in all cases of serious hardship or oppression and I am to say that I doubt not that His Highness the Sultan will be power fully influenced by such representations. Knox. Telegram. From - Knox, Resident, Bushire. To - Foreign, Simla. No. 1176. Dated 4-10-14. Your telegram S. 831 dated 2nd October complied with. Knox.K l leleeram P. ^ ' OA 0 From Foreign , Xo Secretary of State , repeated Bushiro for guidance Kos 864S. Dated 7th October 1914. Your telegram of the 5th October .Persian Agent for Masqat • Pleae see enclosures to Cox* letter dated Qth)^ July to Hertzel • On the 2nd October , the Resident was authorised by us to inform H.U.*s Minister that w when appealed to and in all cases of serious oppression or hardship , our Consul at Masqat was being instructed \ . to use his good offices ; we did not doubt that such representatior would be willingly attetoded to by His Highness ' . Regarding recent alleged/cases of oppression Resident will be further instructed by us to cause enquiry to be held but , as H»H« has hitherto ordinarily dealt with Persian subjects himself , we hope that Minister will persuade Persian Government to accept above solution H.H. and his subjects would resent complete withdrawal of Persian nationals from his jurisdiction and French Government would probably misunderstand our action • Foreign • Telegram P. From P*R« , Bushire • To Foreign No: 1193 . DatedC^th October 1914. Your 864S of 7th October . Alleged recent cases of oppression . In regard to proposed enquiry , am I to take action • Knox .31' /a , ,o v Telegram. Po From Foreign, To Bushire 8 No, 881-So Dated ll o 10ol4o We did not at present contemplate the judicial enquiry indicated in ^ r our telegram dated October 9^^ No, 1193- It would appear to suffice if you- ascertfl&gt;in i iform— ally the nature and ext nt of thie allegod recent cases of oppression at Masqat of Persian oubjects, either from the Muwaqqar-ud-Dauleh or from Benn, :Je will consider the matter further on receipt of a report from you to the Government of India, Foreign eTelegramo Po Addressed Foreigno Repeated Masqat» No. 1224 0 Dated 13th October 1914„ Your 881-S of the 11th. I suggest that Political Agrnt should sound Sultan as to his attitude towards pre sence of Persian representative« Do you see any objection? I hopf that Sultan will object, as strongly as we do, if he does, I should see my way better,, (To Masqat only):- I am sending you a letter on this subject by next mail,. Please take no action pending its receipt, even if Foreign agree to above suggestion KnoXo 3f 10^) * / ©6 ^ Confidential. Docket Telegram. Prom Knox, P»R. Bub hire. \ To Bean, P.A. Masqat. D.O. Dated 13-10.14. In oontinuation of my telegram No dated P October 1914, regarding alleged oases of oppression of Persians by SuJ^tta of Masqat, my idea was that, if Foreign consent to your sounding Sufrtan, you should be frank with him and let him know proposals of Persian Government in all their nakedness and explain to him that their first propo sal is to place Persians under British protection; failing that, French protection; and if neither of the two Oreat Powers consent to the proposal as likely to produce con tention between them, and certain to give offence to Sul tan and seriously affect his independence, then to appoint a Persian Agent who is certain to make use of such position as he has to intrigme against His Highness. You could, I think, tell His Highness that we are tho roughly opposed to the whole scheme, that we do not believe that Persians are at all seriously oppressed, though there was certainly a silly fanatical case against them wnen that Persian shopkeeper was beaten for smoking. It is not so much that the man was particularly badly treated but that the case sounds bad and is particularly open to Persian misrepresentation. Bven according to the Abbathl tenets, it seems to me that, if a foreigner wants to earn hell by smoking, why should a good Abbathi Moolah interfere especially with his will and pleasure,/if it leads to an attempt, rather difficult to rebut, of foreign interference in Mas qat. The case requires delioatie handling and His Highness should be cautious and take action only with your advice. Though@ Though I would prefer to see His Highness handle the en- quiiy into alleged Persian grievances himself, I am afraid that the Persian authorities would immediately reply that the Persians were afraid to speak their mind before him and I am inclined to think that it will have to be yourself who should make this enquiry. There is a very large Baluohi element in the population and it mostly comes, originally if not immediately, from Perso-Makran and is therefore technically Persian, but, Judging from their behaviour in their own country, I should say that these are the last people in the world who would care to be submitted to Persian rale. For instance, I suppose both Ali Musa and Nasib are technically Persians. Genuine Persians are, I think, few and far between and even they do not, so far as I know, desire a Persian Agent or even British protection. The first would certainly fleece them. I think that all this trouble is (flue to the Midhat-us~ Sultaneh, Deputy Governor of Lingeh, inspired by the Mu- waqqar-ud-Dauleh, Governor of the Gulf Ports. Neither of these, though they pretend to be Anglophile, are at heart favourable to us. They are, when they are not thinking of their own pockets, by way of being patriotic Persians. They have, of course, no idea of building anything up but imagine that they will do themselves good by undermining the British position in the Gulf, and they are very hostile to Arabs and Sunnis e I should like to know if His Higiiness learnt anything of what the Midhat-us~Sultaneh was doing when he was twice staying in Masqat in my time. Did he make any overtures to His Highness and in what guise did he put forward the idea of a Persian Agent, if he ever discussed sach a plan? Having got so far, ask His Highness point blank if his sentiments are ours and does he want a Persian Agent? 1 presume that, on no accounts does he want Persian interests placed in the charge of either British or French Consuls? If he is emphatic in his denunciation of anything of the kindIt- © kind, tell him that his best way will be to let you conduct an imormal enquiry into these alleged Persian grievances by seeing individual Persians of standing living in Masqat and see what they have to complain of if anything. The only real grievance that I know of is this wretched slavery and I also know well that the initial fault lies with the Perso ft -Baluchi Chiefs, who are bom slave tradvrft, as well as arms- defers and smugglers of every kind. The British take a real interest in this question and do their best to put a stop to it, and the Sultans of Masqat have also, on the whole, followed an enlightened policy in this ra^peot. A report on the whole question should come in in due c^urcie and you can safely assure His Highness that we rhall give the matter a sympathetic consideration from the poinb of view of his interests and endeavour in every way to support the principle of his independence, which is likely to be seriously affected, and of the maintenance of his au thority, apt to be undermined, if t-he Persian project succeeds.{&lt;5&lt; ] ®&gt; Telegram, P, From Foreigrio To Bus hire , repeated Masqat, No, 914-S, Dated 15,10,14, There is no objection to the Sultan being discreet ly and informally sounded in the matter of the Persian representative at Masqat as proposed in your telegram No 1224 dated 13th October last. Foreign,To, Reoeate^l No: Dated T3 T ICGHAM. ' P ' F tot ^ i , Foreign ■- c 'v P.R. in P.Gr. 967.S. Si87xS. 24. 10.14. We have received the following addressed to Foreign Office by Townley with reference to my telegram Vo: 864.S. of 7th: October last . Begins Your telegram No: 256 . I have made a communication to Minister for Foreigi Affairs in the sense of Viceroy's telegram l T o: October 7th: and have fcsKMx received an answer expressing satisfaction of the Persian Government at the instructions issued fey to Resident Masqat .Fnds, In these circiuistances it wou] d he unnecessary for Political Agent to sound Sultan as proposed in your telegram No: 1,224 date^ October 13th: if he h-s not already done so . 'Foreign '. T^^egram , Knox , Bushire to Berm Masciat , J ated 25.10.14. &lt; Demi Official . please cancel my confidential Demi Official docTcet telegram of 13th: October unles you have alre^tly taXen action thereon . You need maXe no communicrtion . Knox. Repeated by post to Political Afent , Masqat , froni Bushire 'under date 25-10-14 •&lt;3^ • ® Telagraa. From - Benn, Political Agent, Masqat. To - Resident, Bushire. Derai-Official. Dated 26th October 1914. Your demi-official telegram of 25th OctobBr 30 Words. I have cancelled your confidential docket telegram referred to and have made no com munication. Benn, Consul, Masqat9 ~ * Telegram 0 P To Fore ign, No 0 I'V't IS Dated October 1914 No action has or will be taken by p e A. Masqat in regard to concluding paragraph of your telegram of October 24th No, 967-8. Kn oxCopy &gt;7 ,v '~- H0;260. T E H r. A N , OotobeT 22. 1914 SSsDI mvcy 11 {ur ' £ - 25^- ^ P' 1 ' 1 '—— ' I L' 1 ■ ^1 ,AL nL^/.iJS. '' Six» I have 'the honour 'to 'tx&amp;nsml't 'to you hezewi'th in oonfixmation of my telegram No.307 of todays date, Oct. 16 oopy of a memorandum whioh,in accordance with the in - structions contained in your telegxam Ho.256 of the 15th instant,1 caused to be handed to the minister for Foreign Affairs on the 16th instanttupon the subject jf the po • sition of Persian subjects in Muscat,and their protection by the British Resident. Ala-ue-Sultaneh has since caused me to be informed verbally that the Persian Government are much gratified at the early attention paid to their request, and that they have no doubt that the good offices of ihe British Besidant will suffice to secure for Persian sub jects in Muscat the fair treatment of whioh they stand in need. I have the honour to be, with the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, 84/ W Donley The Bight Honourable Sir E. Grey,Bart. ,K.G. ,K .P. , etc etc eto&gt; Uemoxandum. Cii '.Townley to H.H.the AlA-ua-SultaneJi. Datdd Oulh»k t th© i5th Ootobtx About 15 days ago H .H .the ^inlBtex fox Foxelgn AffalXB zepiesented to His tiaJo^ty'B Mlnl&amp;tex that the Pdielans xesldont In Husjat aire muoh oppressed and xe^uested that the nxitirh xepxesentatlve at that place cilght be Instxuated to take chaxge of I ex elan Intexests there. Six li.Townley did not fall to bilng the xequept of the PexBlan Government to the favourable attention of fix Sdwaxd Orey tr nd he now hae Buoh plee^suxe In Informing H.K.Ala-us-Sultane^ that he has xeoelved Inst ructions to bring to the knowledge of the pexelan Government that the government of India have instructed their repieEentatlve at i .us cat to exeroise his good offices on behalf of Persian cubjecte when appealed to and in all cases of seriouB hardship and oppxeBPion # and that they have no doubt that the Sultan will be gladly influenced by such xspresentations. The Pritish Lepresentative in Muscat has also been told to oause an enquiry to be made regarding alleged xeoent oases of oppxession. Six v s .Townley feels sure that the ax angement made will be quite satisfactory to the Fexsian Oovexn- ment,and confidently anticipates that the Kinistex fox poxeign Affaixs will be no longs troubled by com plaints on the eooxe of oppxession fxom Persians residing or trading in bus^at.r 7 lo r ^] CONFIDENTIAL. Docket Telegram. From - ;nox, { in t e absence of the Resldentf), Bushlre. To - Benn, P.a., :aaqat. \i No .Of. &amp;W- IS Dated ^ November 1914. Forwards.for information, copy of Minister's despatch No. 2fl0 dated 22nd October 1914, to Sir Edward Grey. It would appear clear from the above that His Ma jesty's Minister still expects that an Informal enquity will be held by you into alleged cases of oppression at Masqat and indeed orders contained in Foreign Department telegram N0.88I -S dated 11th October 1914 have not been cancelled. It is not clear from our records whether this telegram was repeated to you or not, so a copy is enclosed herewith. The cancellation, however, of the orders regarding the sounding of His Highness on the question of the des patch of a Persian Representative together with the other possible solution discussed in the previous correspondence makes it no doubt somewhat difficult for you to find an excuse or explanation to His Highness of the reasons for holding the informal wnquiry that has been directed. Before doing si, therefore, I shall be glad to have your views as to the best method of approaching Hid Highness in the matter, as it seems essential that the sultan be first consulted.¥ Docket '^'cle^rain. No. 306. Confidenti«.l. .. ■ ,..u Dated 7/12/14. From......... Benn To Knox ( in y'bflence of Resident) \ L 3/ t^jzs&amp;A Your docket telegraia Ino . 444 dated 26th. NoveaalDer 1914« Knuuiry into alleged illtreatment of Persian subjects. In viev/ of cancellation of orders vgariing the sounding of His Highness on question of posting; a Pcrsiw.n representst/ive to Mascat,! am at present at a loss to knov^ hov/ to find an excus -se or explanation for holding the informal enquiry desired by His Laj esty's Minister. It seems to me that we must either consult His Highness in a straight forvmrd way and obtain his consent or ignore him and xkxx k* i^ Ixssxkxx risk his displeasure v /hen he discovers, as he is bound to do, that the enquiry has been held. There can be no doubt,I think, which of the two courses is preferable,namely the former# I am inclined to think that if the proposal was properly and tactfully suggested t© His Highness,he would not resent the enquiry, as the result would no doubt enwble him tt rebut the charges made against hi*. As far as I know His Highness is very well disposed towards the Persians. He considers the few Persiwn so Idiers he has anoxic his troops as the best and most reliable men he possesses and it would be entirely ijainst Ms interests not to conciliate them. I have heard of no case of ill-treatment of Persians except the one you quote of Sayad Mehdi,Isfahani,which occured 9 monthfi a^o. I understand that besides His Highness* Persian soldiers, the nuiaber of Persian subjects in Mascat does not ex ceed 15 to 20 and that these are not residents but temporary trac -ders who come and ^o in connection with the small business dealings they have on this side. Witr CONFIDUITI ALi. Docket Telegram, From - .nox, ( in the absence of the Resident),3uBhlre. To - 3enn &gt; .A., -a^qat. No • Cf* • Vf' Jated ifiDaco bor 191 v. Your confidential docket telegram Wo,30G. in quiry into alleged illtr^atment of Persian Subjects. I aha11 be glad if you will approach His Highness, a- you suggest and represent that the reasons for hoii— ing the enquiry are representations made at Lehran, as a result of which, you were directed to hoXd an mqu 4 ry. If unavoidable yau might add that th'?8e representationc seemed likely to lead to proposals which were unpalata ble to His Majesty's Government and, in their opinion, likely to prove equally unpalatable to His ^i^hness. bhomld ilis Highness press you as to nature of these pro posals you couli say that we do not vish to create bad blood between His Highness and the Persian authorities by disclosing them and in any case you are precluded by your instructions from doing so. It would be veil to lay stress on the point you put forward that you have every reason to hope that the re sult of the enquiry will be to show how entirely un founded the inputationsof the iersian Government are.34. y L 3) From Benn Masqat. To Knox Bushire. No. 12 Demi official. Dated 7.1.15. Your docket telegram 479 Gf. dated 16th December and confidential letter 492 dated 22nd December. I have inter viewed Sultan of Masqat on both subjects and found him quite ready to fall in with my view's esnecially with regard to latter about which he is formulating his views in writing as desired. As regards former he asks for few days to con- i sider matter. My reports will follow in due course. Benn Political Agent. t!TolegrarA.Co.cia. From - Trovor, Muscat# To - Political, 'uacat. No ,2153• Dated 5th December 1920 Your letter dated 4tli OctolJer &lt;'3011 • u;0 Tr or -t rndia su*-est that as negotiations and settlement were ^ # for the benefit of His Highness, expenditure is- lepatimate charge against state Revenues. Do you see any objection Trevor.Tele 'Tan 0 o o de• From - Pol tioal, ' msoat, • =» . To - Trevor, joushire• No.2430. Dated 6th received 7th Decor^er 1920• Your tele ;ram dated 5th Decoriber 2153. We acted as mediators that is neutral to both sides and by Arab customs sue 'expenditure is incumbent on us. woth sides l^enefitted to say not/' ing of us and presumably I c^uld nave recovered half the anount from the Tram. -itber side would certainly refuse. .political.(g) From - To The Political Resident in th^ Persian Gulf. The Foreign Secretary to the Govemnent of India, Foreign and Political Department, DELHI. t Memorand-um No s« Dated yth ^ecember 1920. Your Memorandum no.i714-E # A # dated 28nd Novemher 19S0. Political Agent Ltuocat telegraphs as follows' begins. We afctatf ! as mediators that is neutral to both sides and by Arab customc . ouch expenditure is Incumbent on us# Both sides benefitted tc i say nothing of us and presumably I should have recovered half the amount from the Imam* Either side would certainly refuse ends. i think that as we were acting as mediators it would appear rather moan and create bad improsBion if we were to / Mil the state for expenditure incurred in entertaining tho various parties at the meeting# in the circumstances I would recommend that the expend iture should be borne by us# Lieut-Col# Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, He96 © Imam. This definite depnrture occurred when Sultan bin Ahmed usurped the power from his brother Said bin Ahmed who had been elected Imam. The latter retained the title of Imam till his death, but no temporal power. The ru'e of Saltan and of his son Said which lasted from abont I7v)0 till 1R56 marked the growth of sea power, foreign conquests, the most important of which was Zanzibar, and the removal of the capital from Hnstaq in the interior to Muscat on the coast, and foreign treaties and interference, almost entirely British, The removal of t &gt;e capital to the coast cut off from the in enor has been stated by some as the beginnim: of the loss of hold by the Sultans oYcr the interior, and as such as an impolitic move. This is however open to question. It is more probable chat the Saltan knew they could hope better to control with outside power and this outside power they obtained i'roji their sea power and their foreign possessions. It is a fact however that from the death of Saiyid Said the power of the Saltans over the interior became more nominal than ever. Attacks could only be warded off by bribery, no revenue was obtained, travel was dangerous and there were saveral attempts by the Omani tribes to set up Imams of their o^n. 1 n attempt had actually been made in 1819. In 1^68 Azzan bm Qais an elected Imam actually ruled in Muscat, and though latter ejected, many similar attempts were'made during the reign of Turki and the earlier years ot the reign of Faisal to depose the Sultan, who may have said to have been saved only by our support. Finally in 1913, after an elaborate conspiracy of several years fostered by the famous blind Ibadhi mullah Sheikh Abdullah bin 11 u maid as S&lt;ilimi, the Oman tribes rose in a body elected Salim bin Hashid -al-Kharusi as Kir n.am and by 191) had obtained complete control of all Oman proper where t ley organised a Government. It will thus be seen that for more than 60 years there has been active opposition to the ruling louse by the Oman tri'aes. The causes Oi. t us opposi tion may be briefly summarised as follows: (1) ^Religion. —According to the Ibadhi religion their ruler must be elected. The Sultans who had not undergone this formility were therefore userpers. (2) The personal diameter of the St alt ins This deteriorated at an alarming rate, and the repeated assertion of the Omani tribes that they were unfit to rule does not lack jusl moat ion. (3) The character of the Saltans'rale.—Thxs was corrupt to a degree, and the element of personal control and touch by the ruler himself which with the Arab will pilliate even the worst forms of corrup tion, was completely absent. (4) Foreign interference —'Wu* appeared in the eyes of the fanat [ &lt; 'a 1 and ignorant Omanis to be directed against their most ehens.ied rights such as the importation of arms and slaves. In these the Sultan acquiesced without consulting his subjects accepting large sums of money for his acquiescence, not one p?nny oi wlucli money the Omanis ever saw- At the same timaour policy in Zmzibar lost nothing in the telling. Several of the reasons why the Sultans were unable to cope with the ^bel- lion are con-am-d in these. But to them may be added three ^ ' o ; 9 t of Zanzibar and its revenues, the loss of sea power owing to the ntroducbon ot steam, and finally and most important of all the effects of British mdncnce. When cinsiderinar our policy in Muscat ant 1 Oman this last point n 1 '- 1 ^ never be lost sight of. A brief perusal of the treaties and engngemon s with the rulers of Muscat will show 1 tot our inlluence I im boon interested, has p.id no regard to the peculiar political ,,lo the country and its rulers, and by bribing effete Sultans .'o ® measures which benefitted none but ourselves, and permitting them to mi.i CllTTD'vrirhout proiest luis done more to alienate tke interior and to prevent the Sultans from re-establishing their authority than all the rest put together. In other words it has been support wrongly applied, in money ani not in essentials, interference in external arfairs which must have seriously reacted upon internal peace and no palliative except money which was thrown into the sea or worse by those into whose hands we put it. The result uas that we were retluced to the absurd position of supporting by armed force under our treaty obligations a ruler against whom most of his subjee.s were in open rebellion, who was theoretically independent and yet who would be driven into the sea in a day if it were not for us. The immediate causes of the 1913 rebellion were an outbreak of religious fanaticism coinciding with the stoppage of the importation of arms. 2. Events from Colonel Benn's first meeting with the Oman Cliiefs in 1915 till Major Haworth's meeting with the same in September 1919. m ♦ In January 1915 the Imam accompanied by Sheikh Isabin S ilih-al-Harithi and many Oman Sheikhs attacked in force our defenees at Bait-al-Falaj guard ing Mattrah. The attack was beaten olf with serious loss to the Omanis who learnt their lesson there once and for all. The Imam however remained in indisputable possession of the interior and a constant menace to the coast towns which he would probably have taken had it not been for tne certainty that he would be driven out in a few days with the advent of a British man-of-war. In May Lieutenant-Colonel Benn, the Political Agent, sent a circalar 1c t r to the Oman Sheikhs asking for a conference in which peace n i^ht be arrange! betweea the Sultan and the Itnam. Tin's did not meet with a very warm res ponse in the interior ; but after considerable correspondence a meeting was finally arranged nnd took place at Sib on the loth September 1 15 between Colonel Benn and Sheikh Isa as the representative of the Imam's party. This meeting was ent'rely abortive. In the Sultan's mind was the para mount idea that he would eventually recover his authority in the interior, in the minds of the representatives of the Imam their unassailable position as conquerors and their moral position as Ibadhis obeying the dictates of religion. The two most important points demanded by the Sultan were the return of the S^mail forts and the recognition of his temporal supremacy ia Oman. These were categorically refused by the Omanis who demanded that the Sultan should reform his government according to their ideas that they should be given subsidies, arms and so on. No reconciliation was possible and the negotiations were broken off. From this date till 1918 no further steps were taken towards a settlemen'. The Imam backed up by the two great Chiefs Sheikh Isa bin Salih-al-Hari^hi, head of the Hinawi confederation and Sheikh Hamiyar bin Nasir-al-Nabhani, head of the Ghafiri confideration consolidated his power in Uie interior. On the other hand the Sultan's Government sank from bad to worse, because involved in hopeless debt and reached an unparalleled degree of ineptitude. In March 1918 during the absence of the Sultan four relations of Sheikh Isa's came down into Muscat and were seized by Saiyid Nadir who was acting for the Sultan and imprisoned. This resulted in letters from Sheikh Isa to the Sultan and the Political Agent asking f-or their release. The Sultan in return insisted on the return of the valuable gardens seized by the Orranis, and the Po'iticaLAgent declined to interfere except on these lines and the matter was dropped. In the meantime the Political Agent Major Haworth had realised the imperature necessity of taking drastic measures to preserve the Sultan's Govern ment on the coast from complete financial and actual collapse, and a loan to pay oPP the Sultan's deb s and arrangements to obtain the services of an experi enced Customs official were made. Our victories in the great war now made the occasion a suitable one for again approaching the Omanis with a view to a settlement and the Political98 A^enfc Major TTaworth addressed n very strong letter to the leaders in March 3 919. Coneiderable correspondence resulted and finally Sheikh Isa met the Political Agent at Sib on the 15th September 1919. By this time it had been realised, and the realisation was more than confirmed at the meeting, that the recognition of the Sultan in the interior was as impossible as that he should reeonquer Oman by force. His own territory was on its last legs, lie only stood at all with our support. The best means was therefore the reeognition of the status quo and the terms discussed and which it seemed might eventually form the basis of an agreement were that the Sul&lt;an— (1) should remove all restrictions on entry lothe town of the coast. (2) reduce the zakat on goods coming from the coist towns to the ♦ interior to 5 per cent. (3) return fugitive from justice. (4) release the four Omani prisoners. And tl at the Omanis— (1) should guarantee not to attack the Sultan's territory or interfere in his Government. (2) should guarantee the safety of travellers and freedom of trade. (3) should hear and decide cases against Otnanis. (4) should return fugitives from justice. (5) should return the valuable gardens belonging to two of the most important of the Sultan's subjects seized oy tne Omaais, 3 Events from October 1919 to October 1920 including the final settle- went.—The situation therefore on my arrival in October was - (1) The reform of the administration of the territory controlled by the Sultan had to be taken in hand. (2) An agreement was to be arranged if possible throngh the mediation of the Political Agent between the Imam s party and tue Sultan. It was at once clear that these two matters were closely bound together. In the first place the strengthening of the Sultans administration ^ou c inevitably result in a decrease in the comparative power of the Omams In the second place an agreement and the establishment of peace would enable the reform of the administration to be proceeded with with more rapicaty. Tiie reform of the administration was therefore tackled with vigour, and Sheikh Said bin Nasir al-Kindi a prominent mullah of the Ibadhi sect resident in the territories of the Sultan, and greatly respected m Oman, was ^ntl^me to Nizwa, the seat of the Imam, to endeavour to obtain ratification of the teims discussed at Sib. Though at the commencement of Sheikh Said's mission circumstances Feemed favourable, it very soon became evident that the influence ot the ' Mntawwa 'or fanatical party would be strongly against the return of gardens, which were mostlv in r their hands and from which the mul abs derived a lucrative income. The leader of the opposition party was ^asir bin Rashid- al-Kharusi, the brother of the Imam and his ah in Rnstaq. The mission was more than once on the point of success, but finally after i months of negotiations and intrigue the Imam in February defini e j rt ive to Sheikh Said and Sheikh Isa to rati I y the terms. The possibility of this unfavourable result had been foreseen for some time, Brd a definite plan of action prepared to meet the emergency. The Umania bad been given a fair field and plenty of favour. They had been moved with99 honeyoi words. They had refused peace (v-vin^ to ignorance and religious prejudice it is true, possibly as well owing to the lukewarraness of the chief protagonist in the cause, Sheikh Isa, but actually because the Omanis thought that we were not backing the Sultan with any degree of enthusiasm and that therefore they could go as far as they liked with impunity. The Omanis were therefore to be shown that our support of the Sultan was a reality, and not only that but that the Sultan was capable of retiliating very effectively on the Omanis by taxing their produce heavily when it came down to the coast for export. Reliable information from the interior showed that owing to the long stoppage of the import of arms and ammunition the Omanis had largely lost their olfensivepowor, and ware by no means enthusiastic for the Imam whose puritanical fanaticism was making lite intolerable, and the exactions of whose brothers had raised a storm of protest. The mom mt was therefore opportune for changing from a weark defensive to a vigorous offensive. It was pointed out that if certain steps were taken which involved no use of force by us, it was extremely probable that the Omanis would S3e reason. Even if they did not do so for sometime it would not matter as affairs would eventually automatically adjust themselves with the increase of the Sultan's power following on the reform of his administration. The following events therefore took place on the refusal of the Imam to ratify : — (1) The negotiations were broken off by mo in the most insulting fashion. (2) A British advisor to the Sultan appeared. (3) The Sultan accompanied by me went on an official visit to His Excellency the Viceroy in India leaving the British adviser in '♦charge of the State. (4) A British warship, in pursuance of our enagements to support the authority of the Sultm on the coast, proceeded to Masnnah and Sur where the authority of the Sultan had been defied and inflicted punishment at the former place with good results. The position of the Imam was at the same moment greatly weakened by the sudden death of Sheikh Ha niyar bin Nasir-al Nabhani, the most powerful chieftain and his staunchest supporter, whoso successor was an inexperienced boy of 11. These events created consternation in Oman only to be increased on my return from India by the publication of notices by the Sultan's Government imposing a penal zakat of 25 per cent on all dates and 50 per cent on pomegra nates brought by the Omanis to the coast towns, instead of the customary 5 per cent. Tae proclamations announcing the imposition of this penal tix were very carefully worded, making it perfectly clear even to the Omanis that the tax was imp sed as a punishment owing to their refusal to give up the looted property and to come to terms. * v Coincident with the publication of these notices (in M &gt;y) a very significant incident occurred. Nasir bin llashid-al-Kharusi who had been suffering con siderable trouble from Ahmed bin Ibrahim, the ruler of Hazm just within the Sultan's territory, laid siege to Hazm. A small expedition was organised by the Sultan's Government and Nasir bin Bashid was compelled to retreat wil.li every appearance of ignominy, most of his men deserting him, and might even have lost Bustaq. Such an incident would have been unthinkable six months previously. Prom this moment events moved rapidly—it may almost be said according to plan: Sheikh after Sheikh approached the Imam pointing out that they were powerless to resist the penal tax which seemed to be imposed simply100 owing to the greed of his brother, and praying him to return the gardens and come to terms. The Imam dominated by his brother proved obdurate and dis content grew. Finally Sheikh Isa, whose last letter I had torn up and refused to answer, addressed me himself on 29th June. I seized the opportunity to write a strong and lengthy reply emphasising that the British Government was entirely behind the Sultan in this matter, and that f w^ould neither meet him nor discuss any thing with him till the looted gardens had been first returned. ^ I took the precaution of allowing the contents of this letter to leak out before it was sent. There is little doubt that this letter dispelled any remaining doubts that the Omanis may have had. On 21st July the Imam Sheikh Salim bin Kashid-al-Kharusi was murdered at Khadra. The immediate cause of his murder was stated to have been an insult to one of his guard. The real reason of his death, which •was confirmed from many sources, was that the tribes were practically in open revolt against his rule and that of his brother, which was a combination of utter religious bigotry combined with shameless selfishness and oppression and a complete disregard of politics or government, all of which in addition to their inherent disadvantages were resulting in all sorts of trying restrictions from the Sultan's Government, which they were powerless to resist, culminating in the penal zakat. Oman was now without a leader and the greatest confusion prevailed. The 'Walis of the late Imam were driven out immediately by the infuriated tribes men and had to flee for their lives. Many tribes sent tentative offers of alle giance to the Sultan's Government. Sheikh Isa began to collect men in Sharkivah, and on the other side the Sultan's Government made a determined effort to regain their hold over Oman. The situation was now extremely interesting, and provided the British Government could preserve an attitude of strict neutrality, one of two results both equally favourable to a satisfactory settlement would be bound to occur. Either the Sultan's Government would regain their hold over the interior—this would settle affairs for the moment, though it would inevitably lead the Sultan into difficulties later—or the Oman tribes would retain their cohesion against the Sultan in which latter case their leader could only hope to consolidate his posi tion satisfactorily by coming to an agreement removing immediately the penal zakat, It was peculiarly fortunate that at this critical moment the British adviser to the Sultan was on leave in India. It was therefore possible for the Sultan's Government in entirely Arab hands to act without suspicion being raised that we were behind them. I kept conspicuously aloof, well knowing that the Omanis, if they did not come into the Sultan, would approach me to mediate. Semail was the objective of both parties, but Sheikh Isa who had meantime secured the election of hisfatl er-in-law Mohomed bin Abdullah-al-Khalili, chief of the powerful Beni Huwaha tribe as the new Imam, succeeded in reaching Bemail 24 hours before the Sultan's men, and the tribes naturally followed him. • He immediately addressed himself to me through Sheikh Said bin Nasir-al- Kindi asking for an agreement. I replied that till the gardens w T ere returned I would not meet him, but that when that had been done I would mediate. To show more strongly my complete indifference I stated that I was going to India for a month, and with the permission of Government went. Even then Isa'spath was by no means smooth. The new Imam being a Hinawi and the father-in-law of Isa raised the suspicions of the GhafirK Ahmed bin Ibrahim on behalf of the S iltan took Rustaq and would have held it but for the sudden desertion of the Boni Ghafir tribe to the new Imam. Immediately the Rustaq situation had resolved itself in Isa's favour lie acted with great policy, as indeed he was compelled to by the insecurity of his C11ITD101 position which depended for its consolidaticm on Ihe romovil of the penal zakat. He obtained the return of the guard ens from the Imam, wrote to me (then in Indian) that he had done so, and asked for a meeting. This was finally arranged and took plaee at Sib from the 23rd to 26th September 1920. It is worthy of note that on this occasion, as a mark of the complete change in the political situation and in the attitude of the tribes caused by the new policy, Isa sent in letter after letter asking for a meeting and actually waited for me 20 days at Klioz ; while on previous occasions exactly the reverse had been the case. On the 21st Captain Thomson of the l-ll7th Mahrattas proceeded with an ( scort of 50 men ot the 117th to Sib by naiive sailing boat, to the house of the Wali of Muttrah at the edge of the gardens which had been fixed as rendezvous. Tents were erected close by for the entertainment of the Sheikhs. Within a few hours of my arrival from India on the 22nd, accompanied by Captain Pearson, Commanding the detachment of the 117th at Muttrah, Captain Menon, M.O.,ar.d the Consular dragoman, I embarked in a native sail ing vessel for Sib, arriving there the afternoon of the 2^rd. A message was s-ent immediately to Sheikh Isa who was at Khoz only 2 hours distance. Early on the morning of the 24th Sheikh Isa accompanied by over twenty Oman Sheikhs and three hundred camelmen arrived at the rendezvous When they had dismounted and entered the tents I paid the customary visit on them as their host remaining about 10 minutes. The first meeting took place an hour later and lasted some two hours. The question pressed by me was the authorisation of Sheikh Isa. It will be remem bered in this connection that on the occasion of the last meeting he was not fully authorised. Finally, he having stated, and his word having been confirmed by other Sheikhs, that he was fully authorised by the Imam, it was agreed that the terms if arranged would be signed by him and the Sheikhs present in my presence, and that they would then take the document away and obtain the signature of the Imam and of any other Sheikhs whom I might name. After the middy meal a further long meeting was held to discuss the actual terms. There were present at this meeting only Sheikh Isa, Said Nasir-al- Kindi, the Consular dragoman and myself. Twelve extravagant terms were put forward by the Omanis :— (1) That the independence of Oman should be recognised, (2) That the z itat should be reduced to 5 per cento (3) That the Omanis should be free and safe in the Sultan's territory. (4) That the British Government should not help their enemies (pre-- sumxbly meaning the Sultan). (5) That nothing should be done against their religion (G) That passports should not be needed for them. (7) Tliat they should be allowed to purchase cartridges. (8) That the Sultan should subsidise them. (9; That all documents such as passports, etc., from the Imamfshould be- (Countersigned by the Political Agent and not by the Sultan. (10) That Eashid bin Uzaiz should not bo allowed in Oman. (11) That Sheikh Said bin Nasir -al-Kindi should be guaranteed safe'y m the Sultan's territory. (12) That the Sultan should return fugitives from their justice. As against this they proposed to promise: — (1) Not to attack the Sultan's territory or to interfere in his Government. (?) To allow freedom of trade and travel in Omam102 the terms they proposed to exact from the Sultan all except (2) and (3) and (12) were clearly absurd. By a mixture of argument, cajolery and threats and the final statement that if they were not prepared to accept the terms originally agreed upon I would leave at once, they finally agreed to ask ing only (2), 3) and (1^) from the Sultan. Terms (10) and (11) were put in by Sheikh Said bin Nasir al Kindi only owing to personal enmity and were soon disposed of. (1) was pointed out as being absurd—if we were mediating in an agreement they could rely on our not backing the other side unless they flagrantly broke it. (5) tfas pointed out as a sine qua non. (6) and (9) were pointed as equivalent to asking for exemptions of formalities which had to be undergone by the whole world, and as implying no disgrace but which even British citizens had to put up with in other countries. (&lt;) was pointed out as impossible owing to international agreemert and it was added that in any case permission to import could not be given till we were sure by experience of their good intention^. (1) was categorically refused and it was explained that as they had got practical independence what more did they want. (8) was laughed at. 'Finally the following terms were arranged. The Sultan's Government would:— (1) Beduce the zakat on all goods comiug iato the coast towns to 5 per cent. (2) Guarantee safety and freedom for Omanis in the coast towns. I (3) Remove all Irestrietions on the entry of Omanis into Muscat and Muttrah. (4) Heturn fugitives from their justice and'not interfere in their internal affairs. (N ote .—The word; here used was ' dakhiliy: t-a-hum,' which is very im portant as it means no more than it says, their internal affairs, and the Sultan cannot argue should he choose to do so that there is any derogation of his supreme authority. On the other hand the Omanis are at liberty to regard it as complete independence. Both sides are therefore satisfied.) The Omanis would— (1) Eemain in peace with the SuKan, not attack the coast and not interfere with his Government. (2) Permit freedom of trade and travel in Oman and guarantee the safety of travellers. (3) 'Would return and not protect fugitives from the Sultan's justice. (4)) Would hear the claims of traders and others against Omanis accord ing to Shara. It is amusing to note that the terms asked from the Sultan was originally only three, (2) and (3) being combinefl. When the Omanis found that they had to concede four terras to the Sultan they were somewhat upset, but the situation was saved by splitting the second term into two. As regards the fourth term conceded by the Omanis, hearing by the Shara was inevitable as they have no other courts. It will almost certainly be necessary in this respect to warn British subjects that they should be careful to claim on waraqas' (documents) not on account books which would not be accepted. On the morning of the 25th Sheikh Isa and some twenty Sheikhs came to write out the terms and sign them in my presence. Immediately a most difficult point arose. Sheikh Isa insisted that the peace should be between the Sultan on the one side and the ' Imam-al-Muslim' on the other. This I refused for obvious reasons. In the first place it meant the open recognition by ua of another ruler. In the second such a peace would obviously he103 resented if not disowned by the vSultan. Every argument was used, tiiat there were millions of Muslems to whom their Imam was not Imam, that this was a political not a religious matter and so on. All to no avail till by chance I was able to quote to them the Hadith of the peace made by the prophet Mohomed at Hudaibiyah a yeir before tha conquest of Mecca between him and the people of Mecca. In the document he originally described himself '' Mohomed rasul allah The people of Mecca replied that this was absurd, if he was the prophet of God there was no question of making peace with him or not. The prophet saw the force of the argument and described himself plain ' Mohomed bin Abdullah'. This direct appeal to their religious history carried the day, and the word Imam was omitted from the body ot the document which simply read as conditions arranged between the Sultan's Govern ment and Isa bin Salih on behalf of the Oaa ani tribes. I explained to them that I had no objection to any one signing for or as an Imam-al-Muslimin. The document was written and the signatures affixed and in tbe evenin'' the Sheikhs departed for the interior to obtain the signature of the Imam, and of the Sheikhs of the Beni Eiyam the Beni Ghafir and the Abriyin. Before their departure I took a copy of the document signed and certified by Sheikh Isa and took the precaution of warning him that the penal zakat w ould not be lifted till the document was returned. The signature of the Imam was obtained on the 28th September and fie document returned to me on the 7th October signed by the remaining Sheikhs. The Imam also sent three letters addressed to his three Walis in Semail Muawal and llustaq, authorising them to hand over all the gardens to the agents of the owners. D In the meantime I had obtained a similar document from the Sultan's Government. Both parties are being given copies of the documents certified by me. The peace was proclaimed on the 8th and already dates and Oman^s are pouring in. An enormous boom in trade is anticipated, and the merchants are prej aring to go into the interior. Whether the peace will lost cannot be foretold, but it should lost at least for some time. Both sides are tired and desire the resumption of normal inter' course and trade. Both sides have got what they want. The Omanis may say they have complete independence, the Sultan may say they only have dominion homo rule. The Sultan is relieved of the expense and responsibilitv of ruling a turbulent and rebellious interior which hated him, while he has lost no revenue as the only revenue he ever got was the 5 per cent zakat on the cojst. The Omanis manage their own affairs under their theocratic Govern- ment wiiich is possibly the Go\einment best suited to their peculiar conditions though such Government would be impossible in contact with the outer world. The strongest prop to the maintenance of peace is the strengthening of the Sultan's Government. His finances are now in order and the State is now paying its way. There is a skeleton, quite sufficient, of an administration. With a small levy corps to give him actual and visible man power it is probable that the Omanis will think twice before they break their word. The position of the Political A^ent in the future will be of some delicac^ He will inevitably be used as an intermediary over delicate questions and the ^reatc-t tact and patience will be necessary, TV^ith the minimum pf inter* ference aad an occasional hint much will be however smoothed Over. •Not printed. Copies of the agreements in Arabic* with English translations are attached. In the name of God the cornjpassionate, the merciful, This is what has been agreed upon in the settlement between the Govern- m nt of Sultan Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal and Sheikh Isa bin Salah bin Ali- al-Hrathi on behalf of the Omanis who sign their names here through themaHms-' f ^ mediation of Mr. Wingate, I.C.S., Political Agent and His Britannio Majesty's Consul, Muscat, who is authorised by his Government in this respect lo be a mediator between them. The conditions are stated as follows. Four of them concern the Government of the Sultan and four of them concern the Omanis. Whet concern the Omanis are these :— Firstly. — On all commodities brought from Oman of all kinds to Muscat, Matrah, Surand all the coast towns uothing more should be taken than 5 per cent. Secondly, —'For all the Omanis there should be safety acd fieedom in all the coast towns. Thirdly. —All restrictions on entry to and exit from Muscat, Matrah and all the coast towns should be removed. Fourthly. —The Sultan's Government should not protect criminals who flee from the justice of the Omanis and that they may be return ed to them if asked for and that the Sultan's Government should not interfere in their internal affairs. The four which concern the Government of the Sultan are stated as follows:— 4 . Firstly. —All the tribes and Shaikhs should remain in peace and amity with the Government of the Sultan and that they should not attack the coast towns and should not interfere in his Govern ment. SecondlykW travellers to Oman on their lawful business should ba tree and there should be no restrictions on trade and travellers should be safe. Thirdly. —All criminals and evil men whoilee to them should be turned out and should not be protected. Fourthly.— claims of merchants and others against the Omanis should be heard and decided as is just according to the Sharah. Written at Sib on the eleventh day of Moharram, one thousand three hundred and thirty nine Hijrah, corresponding to twenty fifth day of Septem ber, one thousand nine hundred and twenty. I have completed what was completed by Sheikh Isa bin Salah on my behalf in these conditions. Written by Imam-al-Muslamin Mohammad bin Abdullah with his own hand. I on behalf of the Tmam-al-Muslamin Mohammad bin Abdullah-al- Khalili and on my own behalf agree to the conditions written here with the authorisation of the Imam-al-Muslamin. Written by Isa bin Salah with bis jown hand. (Signed) Sulaiman bin Hamyar-an-Nabhani (with bis own hand). „ Zahair bin Ghusn-al-Hinawi „ „ »&gt; &gt;» Mohsin bin Zahran-as-Siyabi . Hamaid bin Mussullam-an-Nidabi , Saif bin Salim bin Amir-al-Habasi „ „ ^ &gt;» Khalaf bin Nasir bin Mohammad-al-Moawali (with his own hand). »» it &gt;» I pi105 Thumb impression of Mohammad bin Sultan bin Mansur-al-'Wahaibi. (Signed) Mohammad bin Saif bin Said-al-Jabri 'with his own hand). ,, Sultan bin Salim a^-Rahbi (with his own hand). ,, Khalfan bin Mohammad bin Salaiman-al-Hidabi (with his own hand). „ Thani bin Harith-al-Jabri (with his own hand). ,, Hamdan bin Sulaiman bin Saif-an-Nabhani (with his own hand). ,, Muhanna bin Hamid bin Mohsin-al-Ibri (with his own hand). „ Nasir bin Hamaid bin Hashid-al-Ghafiri and his son Mohammad bin Nasir (with his own hand). „ Abdullah bin Hilal bin Zahar-al-Hanai (with his own hand). This official document of agreement was brought to me which is the best sort of settlement between Sheikh Isa bin Salah on our behalf as written above and the Government oE Sultan Saidd Taimur through the mediation oE Mr. Wingate, I C S., His Britannic Majesty's Consul at Muscat, as is written also with special authorisation. I write these lines with my own hand and thank God for it. Written by Saif bin Ali bin A^mir A1 Maskari with his own hand, I n the name oj God the compassionate, the merciful. Seal. This is what has been agreed upon in the settlement between the Gov ernment of the Sultan Saiyid Tairnur bin Faisal and the Omanis, by the acting Wazir Saiyid Mohammad bin Ahmad authorised by His Highness the Sultan through the mediation of Mr. Wingate, I.C.S., Political Agent and His Bri tannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat, who is authorised by his Government in this respect to be a mediator between them. The conditions are stated as follows. Four of them concern tha Government of the Sultan and four of them concern the Omanis What concern the Omanis are these:— Firstly. —On all commodities brought from Oman of all kinds to Muscat, Matrah, Sur and all the coast towns nothing more should Ue taken than 5 per cent. Secondly. —For all the Omanis there should be safety and freedom in all the coast towns. Thirdly. —All restrictions on entry to and exit from Muscat, Matrah and all the coast towns should be removed. Fourthly. —The Sultan's Government should not protect criminals who fl'je from the justice of the Omanis and that they may be returned to them if asked for and that the Sultan's Government should not interfere in their internal affairs. The four which concern the Government of the Sultan are stated as fol lows :— Firstly. —All the tribes and Sheikhs should remain in peace and amity with the Government of the Sultan and that they should not attack the coast towni and should not interfere in his Govern ment.106 Secondly.— travellers to Oman on their lawfal business should be free and there should be no restrictions on trade and travellers should be safe. Thirdly. —All criminals and evil men who flee to them should be turned out and should not be protected. Fourthly, —The claims of merchants and others against the Omanis should be heard and decided as is just according to the Sharah. Written at Muscat this fourteenth day of Moharram, one thousand three hundred thirty nine Hijrah, corresponding to twenty-eighth day of September, one thousand nine hundred and twenty. Sealed signature of Taimur (H. 11. the Sultan of Muscat and Oman). (Signed) Mohammad bin Ahmad, with his own hand, on behalf of the Sultan. CUFrD—36-22-11-20- GCPSProm - The Secretary to tlie Goyernmant of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To « The Hon'ble the Political He si dent in the Persian Grulf, Budiire. r • — • - • ^ ' • • « Memorandum No® vr B # A d * Dated Delhi # the / y January 1021 # Tour memorandum No«341**S r dated the 7th December 1920^ In riew of youf further representation, the GoYemment of India are pleased to sanction the expenditure of Hs»3 # 278-ll«-8 incurred hy the Political Agent at Maskat in connection with the meeting at Sib with Shaikh Isa and other Omani Shaikhs* It is understood that the expenditure will be met by yCT|i|^ar|#Tir«tTg re appropriation. ' '# Sd* Denys Bray, Secretary to the Governspent of India* Attested* Superintendent, Foreign and Political Department* Copy to Finance Department, for necessary action* if inffWMm .mm/r Copy of a menoranclum no«55- 7 ^ # A# dated 1-th January 1921 from the Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department, Dolhi tc the Mon'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, In-.hire. Your merorandim no.541-3 dated the 7th December 1020. In view of your further representation, the Government of India are pleased to sanction the expenditure of $ 3 # 278-ll-B Incurred by the Political Agent at Muscat in connection w*th the meeting at Sib with Shaikh Isa and Othor Om-ni Shailrhs. 2* It is understood that the expenditure will s br met by reappropriat ion• Copy forwarded to the Political gent, uscat for information with reference to his letter no•2011 dated 4th October 1920# 10. -S The Residency, Bushire, 27th January 1921. By order, Captain. Assistant Resident.iin- n * ■ * 0* BlSHiKk NSIL ^ - 5-} ?-AL /• ,%y It no.Sb : • /• • From i Tlie Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foroirn and Political Department, To The Hon'hie the Political 'Resident in the Perrian Gulf, Bushire. Dated Simla, the Sir, 1921. I am directed to inform yon that His Majesty's Secretary of State for India hes requested thtt his appreciation of the services rrndered by l!r. R.2.L. ling-ate, Political Agent, I. f askat, in the settler ent of the Oman negotiations and the inanrrration of administrative reforms in the ,T aFkat State • V X may be conveyed to that officer and to request that Tr. 'Yingate may be informed accordingly. I have the hononr to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 7v Hl\*y&gt; Deputy Secretary to the Government of Indiaj i ii IV ♦ v (A TO:- Undated(Peed: 22/7/14) Mr(Major) Mnox, H.B.M's Consul-General , B u s hi r e • le A.C. , I be, to represent to 3^011 that T am. an Ottoman Turk but a friend of the exalted British Government today and am proceeding to Masqat/on a special business. My object in addressing this letter to 3^ou is to in form you tf my friendliness and to state that T desire to represent to you certain circumstances concerning the politics of your exalted government in this Hilf and in Arabia. If you attach any importance to this my repre sent ati on, you may send me a letter at Masqat and I will come to you after the receipt of your orders^ on t] condition that your exalted government appreciate^ my services and friendliness. If you desire to send me a letter askin_ me to come to you,you may forward the same through the Consul at Masqat or under the care of Saiyid Hashim,Officer of the Arms' Warehouse at Masqat, and your order should be kept confidential between me and you. Address:- Muhammad .Am.in Beg, the Turk, Y. r ith Saiyid Taimur, M a s c a t . I desire to pay you my respects urgently for the Tp nefit of your Government. I am awaiting an early ans wer from you:and if you delay(this),I will write to the Governor-General of India. ^ f ./i T.T. /[4fa y/A 111 k 1 I \. : &lt; i IS (0-6) 196--4,000--7-13--(K2*) (Continuation of Note, Precis or Draft.) Spl—Resident Persian Gulf 2 * .Oonfldentlal » Docket Telegram# From Knox f P.R. Bushlre* To Benn, P«A# Masqat* D«0« Dated 2l|.7.14. Letter undated received 22nd July 1914 from Muhammad Arain Beg» I am Inclined to believe that this is the Turk who is drilling the Sultan's armyj Please first of all interview Saiyid Qasim whom the writer names and see whether he knows anything of the man or what his aims and intentions are. Then, if you think fit after your x± Interview with Saiyid Qasim, approach Saiyid Taimur and get him to send for the writer in your presence and ask him what he wants to tell me. If he is very reticent in Saiyid Taimur's presence tell Saiyid Taimur that he may possibly have some news from Iraq md that, in any case, no new® relating to Masqat or its dependencies will be dealt with except through His Highness and appoint a time with Saiyid Taimur for Muhammad Amin to come and see you* Tell him that I cannot decide whether it is worthwhile his coming to see me, unless he takes you into his confidence. I doubt if he has much to tell you but one never knows. Let me know please in due course resiilt of the interview. 3^ y. 5Confidential« Docket Telegram. From*•••••••««#• Benn To .Knox D.O. Dated a /8/14 BliSHiRf RESIDENCY ^ Your Confidential Docket Telegram of 26th.July about iLahomad Xmin Beg,Turk. Sayad Q,asim eaye he knows nothing about him except that he ie a friend of the Sultan and a Mason and lives Im His Highness. He recently sent £ 30 m ]ay money order to Constantinople. Sultan gave'icllowing history of the man this morning He first came to Mascatin his fxtfuxn father's time fMiom Beyrout. With his passport &amp; other papers were found i^^gg^emasonry dip lomas. Sayad Taimur took the latter and being/to learn Something about masonry semt for Mahomad Amin, with the result that the latter arranged to have S.Taimyr made a mason. Mahomad Amin went to Karachi to arrange this &amp; S.Taimur obtained leave from hi his father on some excuse £ followed M .A. to Karachi where he was initiated as a Mason. This was while Mr.Holland was Consul in Mascat. After the ceremony S.Taimur &amp; Mahomad Amin returned to Mascat. M«A, received a present of money and after staying a month or so left for Constantinople. After Sayad Faisal^ death, S.Taimur invited M.A. to return to Mascat &amp; promised him service. M.A. came but became very aaxtmia seriously ill. H.H. sent him to Basra for change if air &amp; he m only returned to Mascat a short time ago. He is not the Turk who is drilling the Sultan's army. 5. After giving me the above history,H.H. sent for Mahd.Amin. He was introduced to me r given a chair and treated with consider- abiie respect. I asked him, with reference to his letter to you, what it was he wished to tell you. After some hesitation he said it was a long story &amp; he would like time to/dthink it out &amp; write a note about it. He mentioned however that it had to do with Bin Saud of L T ejd and Said Talib, and concerned certain events which had occurred at Basra &amp; which were ixximtx inimical to British inter ests. Finally he said he would prefer to write a note about it &amp; hand it to H.H. for delivery to me. Though H.H. offered to let the man com e &amp; see me (as suggested by you),M.A, said he would prefer not to do so. H.H. said he would send M.A.* a Note over to me as soon as he received it. 4. It struck me that the man was axxxx an aristocratic beggar who lives,at present, on the charity of H.H. &amp;■ that he is anxious to make a bit by selling * information. e( i I must tell you that throughout the above interview H.H. act- my interpreter as I speak no Arabic,though I understand a ± little. I had not my dragoman with me nor did I send for him as H.H. had assured me that Mahd.Amin spoke excellent French, but on the man*s arrival I found that he did not know (or pretended n not to know) a word of the language. M.A. is living here as H.H.*s guest. 5. asConfidential. Docket Telegram, Prom Knox, P.R. Bushire. To Benn, P.A. Masqat* D.O. Dated a. 8.14. Your D.O. dated 2.8.14. Muhammad Amin Bey Turk. Many thanks. I will await note referred to in para 3. P.IS. I have since received a furious letter from Uuhammad Amin , saying that I have entirely destroyed his credit with Syud Taimur and asking what the latter can poosiTtly know of 'haute politique' • ae is )friow going to lay his information 'before the 'high authorities' in England . I am afraid it is hardly likely to do him f or them , much good •'Oateci 10th August 1314 • TO:- L Mr: (Major)iinox, British Consul (Teneral) B u s h 1 re A.C. , I beg to s^ate that I have submitted the letter I promised to the Consul at Masqat and that I submitted it,as I advised you in my letter,through His Highnes.s the Sultan Saiyid Taimur,so that you may know. My signature in that letter was 'M.A.N,' i.e.Muhamm.ad i^min Beg,so that it may not be charged by arothe^ b.and. Sir, you should not be negligent r as you'^ Government is in war and they (the enemy) are waiting for an oiDT )or— tunity. I think that the Authorities of the Britisji Government fully understand the end (of th^pe affai-rs). During my travels and my intercourses with the offi cials of the (TurkishK'overnmntt, I have learned some thing which concerns the British. Government:but I am. unable to utter or write one word of it unless I re ceive the(British)Government's word of honour.and will then disclose the same to your Honour and to the other authorities concerned in those politics,because I am an Ottoman Turk and concerned in those politics. If the Government of Great Britain desire (to undent an. the intrigues of the German government,they will surely be disclosed on the condition that they should ask me and undertake to accept my proposals:and I will then exp^lain something to your government which may protect: them against enemies. Being now at Mas oat, I am. unable to represent those facts. I would point out to you that my friendliness for the British Government is natural,because when the late Vazir aiami 1 Pasha enjoyed due respects with the BritirL Government,it is natural for this servant,Muhammad Amin Beg, (to aspiiire)to become known to all the autho rities of the Government. I was one of the favourites of the Vazir Kamil Pasha and have inherited friend^.i-S (0-6) 196--4,000--7-13-(K2*) Spl—Resident Persian Gulf 2 ? (Continuation of Note, Precis or Draft.) @ ; ness for the British n-overnment from that statesman . I hope you will not neglect this as the end is impnirt- ant for you. This is a secret petition I make to you, and I await a private answer,after the approval of the British r overnment,at Mascat. Tour reply should oone through Saiyid Abdu l Qader Zawawi ,who is my confidante and I am. prepared to explain to .you all what you ma^ n command,out of regard for your government. Sincere friend of the British Government. (signed)Muhammad Amin Beg. p ^ - .0.9 Should the matter require,I will proceed to Bu- shire or even to London,on the condil^tion that my pro posals are accepted and a promise is obtained from the Government for helping me. &lt;A l I A*^ o Usv^eL, VuC ^ i 1 ^ ^ ^ v ^ (sr A yu ^ o A'— *Absolutely Confidential. r atecl 3rd /u^ust 1914 ( Oi £ TO:- A.C. ^ j or Knox in- On the 2nd -August a reply to my letter was re ceived from you by H.B.M's Consul at Masqat and he formed H.H.the Sultan•Sai3^id Taimur,of my nommunicci- tion with you. You must have known,however,that my re quest for a reply through the Officer in charge of ' the Arms * Warehouse ,Saiyid Qasem.,or the Consul at Mas- cat indicated that the matter was confidential:and I had stated that I would come to you at Bushire if re quired. How could it be (desirable)that the Sultan should learn the facts which concerned the interests of the Governmenti I held an important position in the confidence of the Sultan and was receiving special mo netary consideration: but in consequence of what has been done by your Consul.vis the communication of r .he facts to H.H. the Sultan,the latter's confidence in me has been lost and he has done me a great deal n:' harm. It is not possible that the British ^overn^ejit should agree to do any harm, to an honest man like As regards the affair which I had promised to you.!' shall submit it to you through the Sultan by the noxt mail. This has been forcibly taken from, me and the British Government has lost much of the secret infor mation which I had in my memory owing to the fact 'hat proper principles have not been observed. I shall communicate them to the Head of the English in London, I hope you will accept an expression of my esteem find if you desire to send an answer,it should be confined to me and the Political Agent at Mascat and his fa;:thf^ dragoman. (signed)Muhammad Amin Beg. E^S., I trust that British Government will ensure ny tection against any harm. ro-BU SHiRE RES^F-'-^ C. (O- i CONnDtNllAL 1/ Telegram ?. 7rorn General brigade, Karachi. m o Intelligence Officer, Persian Gulf. TTo.232 W. Dat^d 23.9.14; Reed. 23,9,14, 1-30 p.m. ********* ^ Gregson has sent T'uharj'iad Arnin Beg, a Turk, to Knox, His statements have reference to the ^urks in the Persian Gulf, 'but without local knowledge it is impossible to know how nuch to 'believe at present. The Turk is here thought to 'be a Pan-Islamic Agent, Please inform Knox on 'behalf of Gregson who has no cypher yet, ' General Pri^ade ' 'To,669 ^o P,R. Copy forwarded for information. Pushire, 23.9.14, ■t jf I ihe nan nay ne be sincere and well meanin-r, anu his information is, I daresay, fairly accurate and well founded. But he does not know much beyond the wild dreams that t ese inveterate schemers the Arabs and SurHs are always tryin- to hatch. I think he g hould be rewarded in moderation, 'pour oncourci ager les autres ' but should like to know your opinion. I should be clad to help:r.if necessary and suggest Rs ICC. I will send him back to you with Mir Aslam as sson aa i-osnole, b but in these days of Mfn interrupted posts, it is not easy. I have left instructions that they are to be '.iver any reasonable funds they may reruire. I am a bit hurried as I am off to Bahrein and W uwait and work keeps pouring in. Shall we see. you up the Gulf soon. Kii dest regards from us bot}i. tYours sircerely.. nfidential From No. 218 of 1914 Url IS' P^ajitlcal Agency and His Britannic Majesty^ Consulate e ' 1 ' i— -HSScat. 0 J f&gt;-^ H. ^ _ COIitiolKim LieuFTTJblonel R.A.S.Benn, C.I.S. Political Agent and H.B.M.Consul Mascat To. Major S.G.Knox, C^.I.E. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire Dated Mascat 20th. September 1914 * Sir, Is reference has been made in recent correspondence from this office to the presence in Mascat of certain Turks, I have the honour to submit herewith for information a complete List showing the names of and a few particulars about the more import -ant individuals of Turkish nationality who are now,or who have recently been, resident in this place. 2. A copy of this letter with its enclosure is being for warded to the Hon'ble Secretary tct the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. I gave the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lieut.Colonel Political Agent and H.B.M.Consul MascatConfidential No £20 Mascat, 21et.September 1914 iwy dear Gregson, Knox, in reply to a request made to hla fey the CoiamisB •loner In Slnd, has asked me to lurnlsh you with detail b re garding ' Mahomad Amln Beg 1 ® eon, JaiBal-ud-dln # Turk t *ho h*s come from Maaoat 11 • There has been no Jaaal*ud«dln 9 son of Lahoaad Amln Beg # ln T/'ancat but tfahoraad Amin Beg himself Is well known^here* He left iiaBOat b^ the mall of 14th.September and It Is possible that he chang ed his name on arriral in Karachi. Or it may be that lilt real name is Jamal-ud-din and that he assumed the nam© of Xahoaad tm Amin in Hasoat* But I think the latter is unlikely. He is a great friend of the Sultan and has been here for about two months. 1 enclose two extracts from correspondence which has passed Klcul about this man between myself and the Kesident. I have no thing more to add except that the correspondehce about him was the result of a request made by Mahomad Amin to the Resident in Juky last in which he desired to •represent ...certain oir» cumstances concerning the politics of your exalted Goyemmi^nt in this Gulf and in Arabia * He then gave his address es • Mahomad Aain ^eg, the Turk, With 3aiyad Taiiaur t Ka8qat '. Knox instructed me to see the man in the ^ultst^s presence and I did so. Mahomad Amin promised to embody what he had to say id a note for submission to the Resident # but he never fulfilled his promise. K.S.Ikhlas-ud-din who goes to you by this mail knows the -aan well and will be able^. perhaps / to suppliment what I have recorded here. Yours sinoerely 9Telegram. P, From General Karachi. To Intelligence Officer, Persian Gulf. * No, 240 W. Dated Sept. 27th; Reed 9-20 a.m. ********* Please infortn Knox from Greg son that Director C.I.D. reports that Fuhamrnad Amin Turk is kno\Yn to ?iave 'been employed on political missions from Turkey to the Amir f and ask him to take precautions that Muhammad An in re turns 'by the M DwarkP M , and to instruct police to see that he does not leave the ship at I'asqat. 'General Karachi'Secret. CONfUKAhAL htamos. i The I'einlT^ I am desired to forward for your information a copy of an extract from the Karachi Intelligence Diary .of the 19th September 1914 in which reference / » is made to the reported German Mission to Afghanistan. f Reference is also made to one Muhammad Fowad, a Turkish Military Instructor to the Sultan of Muscat. Presumably this man has no connection with the Fuad who sent the intercepted telegram to the Sultan. But we should be glad to know about him, and how long he has been in Muscat. A copy of the extract has been sent direct to Lt. Col. Benn. I also enclose a copy of telegram^No. 224, dsted the 24th September 1914, from the Political Agent, Muscat about the intercepted telegram for the / Sultan. In the circumstances explained it has been arranged to allow the telegram to be delivered to the Sultan, aro «S f VI IT TELL I GrETTCE SUT.H.IARY Instructions regarding War Diaries and Intelligenoe Surarnaries are contained in Field Service Regulations t Part II,and the Staff Uanual^respeotively. Title pages will be prepared in manuscript. Hour.Date. Place• 6-0 p.m. Summary of events and information. Remarks and. references to Appendices. EXTRACT FROM KAHAQHI IHTDLLIOKITOE DIARY OP 19th. Report from Mr .Sregson.G .I.E.. (Persian (Tulf C.I.D.) ! t j f T The Turk stopped on the 17th,who came from the Persian C -ulf on the B.I.S.S., I'VDumra' is Muhammed Amin Beg,formerly a Turkish military instructor to the Afghan jtropps at Kabul. He is disposed to talk and said, that if he could see the highest {authority here he could make important disclosures. On being told that he could J speak freely to Mr .(rregson, showed a number of cipher messages he had, said to be jfrom the Turkish authorities at Busrah. Spoke of the mission from the German Empo- irar to the Amir being conducted through Turkish Agency and proceeding via Persia. iQuestioned regarding other persons connected with the mission mentionecfinDdul Wahab »fa relation of Abdul ^ami) also formerly a military instructor at Eabul. Spoke al- jso of Abdul Majid and Tewfik Shikri (though he did not know they were under deten- jtion here) and of Mahomea Fowad t a Turkish military instructor to the Sultan of Mus- I cat. T j A policeman disguised as an Indian seditionist was placed in the Same cell jwith Abdul Majid and endeavoured to elicit sympathy in his (supposed) trouble with {the Indian authorities but could obtain nothing but; praise of the British Indian iGrOvemment from Abdul Majid. The latter evidently saw through the ruse. r Two other Turks who were Bushire as undesirables turthfey I t t Mr.Gregson is of opinion that Muhamed Amm is himself one of the mission and that his story about the mission proceeding through Persia is de signed to conceal the real facts. His role as an informer appea red also prearranged for the eventuality of his being arrested by V the British authorities. His story and papers are being examined v/ith a view to obtaining furth er information, about to be deported to 4re being detained pend-ConfldentiRl 'fe BUSHiB? 'p.ta:0ENty Bta ■. -/w CUKFiOtNl Docket Telegram. ?rom Political Agent To Knox Resident Bushire ITo235 • ^ated 4th,, October 1914 Please refer to your Docket telegram ( deMi-official) of 9th. August regarding Hahomad Amin Turk.and subsequent correspondence ending with my Docket telegram Ho.221 dated 21st.September. As you know,Mahoma^went from here to Karachi and was sent back from there oy the authorities. I happened to go,on board the up mail by which 'ahomad Amin was travelling and he spoke to me. He said he was going back to Bushire to see you and then propos ed going on to Basra, He was full of professions of Uyalty to to the British Government# During a visit I piid the Sultan yesterday I referred to the Note which Mahomad Amin had promi 8 ed t^ 0 that Mahom- ad Amin had left it with him. H.H.handed it to me and I enclose it herewith in original with a translation. When I remarked tia that it was not signed H.H.showed me (though not for perusal) a large packet of letters written to him and signed by ^ahomad Am- 4 hand and asked me to compare the/wrting of the H 0 te with that of the letters . I found tnat/they were identical. The Sui^an's remar.o about Mahomad Amin gave me the impression that H.H.was not wen pleased with him and H.H. frequently ^ used the word 'Liar,Liar' with reference to him. ix. x 8Uegeated that H.H. had not much confidence in the man to which H.H. replied 'No.no *ot that; but I am interested to know what he will do in Bushire. What he will tell Major Knox H.H.them added - I have shown you Hahomad Amin's letters. I hope that Major Knox will Be good enough to let me know what he tells him at Bushire '. This rather disposes one to think that H.H. is afraid that Maho- Aaun 13 going to make some disclosure about H.H. It would be interesting torf know if he does so. 0 'Trensl atlon ol* an AralDio During my stay at Basrali and association wlul^ one of t^e prominent men there I got acquainted vrix^ certain political matters which I st^te for your considerationfor information). It is not unknown to politicians that x^he Ottoman peoples split up into two parties after securing constitutional govern - -ment. One of the parties is Ittihadi (Unionist)and the other and greater is ijfaste ItilaXlC ?). The Ittihadis(Unionists) are inclined to republic and the Itilaf , iB( ?)to the maln- -tenance of the CaJiphate as every sane person cldarly under- -stands that the various elements of the Ottoman peoples have rallied to the one word 'maintenance of the empire and the Oaluphate', This is especially true in regard to the Ara'b ela- -ment and two-thirds of Anatoli ans,who are rigidly in favour of the maintenance of the Caliphate. The number of the republicans is thus much less than the Khllafatls(yoyaliBtB). To look to the Muslim element outside the Ottoman empire,there are about ft50 millions of men in Asia who desire the maintenance of the Caliphate and^therefore#supposing that the Ottomans were strip ped of the halo of the Caliphate,the Jluslims would naturally ere ate (11 legible) another Caliph and would rally to his standard but this would be attended wlxh harm at the present time. For instance,at the time of the Caliphate of All bin Talib(The fourtlh successor of the Holy Prophet) the Muslims were all of one com- -mcn belief (faith) and there was no seism whatever .After All,the Muslim peoples split up into various sects,each of the sect^ zealously following the views of its own founder. Thus,some followed the then Caliph,while others oppose him,the various sects setting up their own Imms. Of these the greatest sect was the Shia^ who adored All bin Talib and millions of them opposed the (next)Oaliph and formed a distinct body.In those old times,ignorance and fanaticism were greater than what9)11 they are t»o-day and the founders of religious sects took advantage of the ignorance of the peoples. Although igno- . -ranee still exists yet in comparison to former times there is now much more general enlightenment. During these three years past,many men have 'been trying to secure the iridMxtPcx title of Khilafah for their names. They are (})The Khedive A^has Pasha of Egypt (S) Husain Pasha the Sharif of Mecca (3) Saiyid ^Calib Bey the Naqih of Basrah (4) Imam Yahya of Sanna*a, Yemon,(^) Idris ? # yemen (6) Bin Saud of Najd. With the exception of Saiyid Talib none of these aspirants has any serious hold on the minds of those concerned. Saiyid Talih is a native of Basrah which town is in the neighbourhood of Persia,and the majority of the Persians, » being ShiaB,love Ali and his descendants of whom Saiyid Talib is one,as he is descended from Hasan son of Ali. Some of t,he most prominent men in Persia have promised to accept Ms Laia*t (a]legiance)in case occasion should arise for so doing.Secoi dly, tl (Musi im) Indians and all the (Mu lim) inhabitants of Asia have an undescribable regard for the KlaabaJ-:!' office of Maqlti) . TMb statement is boime out by the fact that numbers of Zuwwar(pilgrims )most!y Indiana and Bohras preferably go through Baghdad for no other purpose excopt for visiting the (shrines of the)ancestors of Saiyid £ Talib,who,too,has made a long tour in India in recent years with the object of enlisting support for his candi- -dacy for this title or designation.At that time he was enabled to arrange that in the event of the Ottomans per- -sisting in their efforts to do away with the Caliphate and establishing a republic,the people(Muslims of India) should certainly accept his Eaiat f al legiance)aa Khalifah - But there cannot be two Khal ifahs at a time on the earth nor in one illegible ^country 1.for Bin 3aud is a rival claimant for this (honour) and this fact became clear to Saiyid Talib who undBrstend^ that he could not free himself from the rivalry of Bin Saud,and so bethought himself to try and get some other distinotion.Thus,taicing advantage i •*® iv of t»^e Goverrmefnt* b 0nga^emen't In 'the Balkan W^^lne Beoret»ly negotiated with Eir. aaud,flind,&lt;?Xter securing the reina of ' tl'e (Turlcish)i:amBor the au^orities hy bribery,in- -duced Bin Saud to taJce poaseseion of Najd and A1 Haaa to- -gether with the surroundirgB and properties and b tores there without a stroke or oppo8ltion(or! the part or the garriBon) • At the same time,in order to safegurad. himself against (tl'© action of , )tho Turkish Govemifient,3alyid Talib adopted a device in respect of Shaikh Muharak a«-3ubah of Kuwait and Sirdar IthaZva.3 ICh?ai{of Muhacnaerah)giving it out to the Qo- -verniient that being Ms neighbours these two Shaikhs were ready to help him,If .rovex^mer.t so deeireB,by men and money in re-tajting A1 Kaes- and that thig had been definitely agreed upon between t) em. Ix» was on ol is aocotait that,as an act of friondel ip f Saiyid TaZlb endeavoured to secure for these two 3hal £hB the dictinoticn of t»he First 01 ass Order of Mejidi and virtually sreoeeded therein. The appointment of Sulaiman 7 Pa«ha as V/ali and troops at Commander ol/Ta^rah was due T j O uhe problem of Najd and the % insurrenotlon of Bin Sand as well as to the actions of Saiyld Talib Bey, Thiis appoint^aent was made at a Lime when the Central Government had many important problems to deal with,and the Wall was entrusted with secret Instructions and was to have a free hand in al3 matt/ers# As a matter of precaution,he was escorted by a sufficient force•Before the Wall's arrival at Basrah,3aiyid Talib ordered the local house-proprietors not to let a single house on rent to the Iftali within the town of Basrah .The object of this was that, in the event of the least opposition being shewn by the Wall,he may be easily killed outside the tov«r as was the x case of the murder of the former 0ommand'3r,F6rid Bey .Thus, he made the Wall to dwell in the house of KhazpJ Ehan(Cfhler of Muhammerah)which is situate on the bank of the large Easrah river some Jaancx 3-J hours 1 distnace from Pasrah, There a body of x»he Shaikh^s men was stationed a guard® 33 for t/^e prot&gt;ec-tion of Ifcls life. Laterthe ounrincly perBuaded ■tire Wall to 'beleive 'Umti t^e problem of Bin S^ud liad arisen as a surprise to the Qovemment and tfc^t the ma^itery in the Qulf was formerly lBlam , B # , but when the (iovemment gave up her position and the British Government was granted the privilege ? the alfaire of the peoples came to 'be neglected and they 'became disloyal to the government,'but that it was not necessary that the Government should sond her forces to fight Bin aaud,but he(3aiyid Talib)would with the Oovemmert's approval # mai:e the bei3t arrangement and thereby enlist Bin Saud's loyalty and that if the latte-r» proved refractory,then the former would himself raise a force with the help ol the other chief b and fight for the Government# When the Wall saw this attitude of Salyid Tol ib,oppoB(ld as it was to former^s opinion about the latter,he Informed the Porte of this and,as result,the Government entrusted Salyld Tallb with this task on getting this intimation and then the position of Bin Saud with respect to the Uovemment was disouseed and settled by meanB of two agreementB of Which one wae ordinary(public)and the other secret.You may have 'been acquainted with the subject matter of that(open agreement). In accordance with the secret agreement the Government recognise the independence of Bin 3aud as ]| Wall and Ooimuand- -ant in Najd with.the condition that a31 the ooastB,with their independent 3haliihB,e'rtendlng up to Yemen end Hazramaut are to be attached to (or under)Bln S \ud vinder the Ottoman flag with secret aid from Goveinment. Wnar Saiyid Tallb succeeded in dealing with the pro- —b3 em of Bin S'lud ir thiB way,he aociUired great pow «r and in— —fluence in the whole of A1 Iraq,. The Go vemment, however, re a*- -llzed the effect(or nature) ol tie aotions of Saiyid Talib and his close ocnneation with the Wal 1,alter the prcblem of the bojxiT./ardirient(or fight)of Az-2u'Dalr(near Basrah) and a flood(of protests or oomplalnt8)went forth from Easrah.Salyid Ta3i'b prouised to the WaJl ^at in o^e the Ctovern- -ment did anything undesirable to latter the former would try and find means for the Wall's rescue. But finding that Salyid Tallh 'broke his promise to him the Wall was obliged to t^ke action -igalnst him through Constantinople.This action was in connection with an important matter con- -cerning Saiyid Talib and the German Qovemment and in rivalry of (opposition to)the Prltish (iovemment and It is was a thing which in the interests of the two parties oon- -cemed and to the disadvantage of the third .This was a very important thing and of the nature of the general poli- -cy of the (European )Powers. Every day that Qovemment (the German Government?) was giving something to the Wllavah (Wall's administration or province) and to Salyid Talib and they were awaiting an opportunity .find. Yours Sincerely. (sa) Miiu Ra Nun 3 j'.h.K.I pom ,0 region, ^squire; C.I o: u Superintendent of PoXloe t 0 n BpeciaX Duty, Under the Oovermaent of Xndia f y oreign a epartt Karachi• To The Deputy Secretary to the uorernment of Xndia 9 ioreign department; diala. Dated Karachi the 26th: September 1914 Sir X ha've the honour to report that I rceumed charge of my dutlee on the 15th: ^eptemher 1914- # atntt officer K rrt-chl .^rlgt-de eeked for aeeletance re garding Inquiries about certain Turke from the Persian OuXf who had been detained In Karachi, The reeuXt of ny Inquiries are summarised beXow end here been cofftmunloated 1 rem time to time to the XocaX officers concerned* '\ A party of nine European Turks appear to hare ooXXected In k*2k*t and shortly after the outbreak of war to hare Xeft In different directions, some returning to Basra and others proceeding to Xndla. One portion of this party was headed by C oXoneX Kurl of the Turkish army from Basra and consisted of (2) AbduX *ahlb # (j) bahib, and (4) teehdl; with the exception of AbduX %ahlb # who is now probabXy in CabuX, aXX theee persons returned to itesra. IsmalX Bey snd I ohammad Jfuad are stiXX in Xaskat ( vide Xlst beXow). Of this party Mohammad •'uad, AbduX Vahib, and ohammad Amin B ey have aXX at one time or enother been employed in C abuX* Whether or not these persons constitute an organised mission is to some extent a ques tion of conjecture, ^here is howsver something tangible against Mohammad Am in Bey, AbduX ^ajld and Tewflk t»hukrl. \ On arrival in Karachi Major Dickson H.* . Generall l The pftrtleulara nt prewertt known retarding •aoh of the Turks Is as follows:- ^ w (1) kohwmmmd Fusd Is sn instructor of ths hizum J alaXl at ^ s» 4s «» 4» i askst. This man is l&gt;sXiSTSd to haws fonuerly bean an instructor of ths ^mir's army in C aoul. Hs arriwsO in Las- kat during ths early part of this ysar and still there* (2) Ismail jbsy, this xaan is a guest of the Sultan of i^as- «t«»m»e»m&gt;fl»e»e»e»efre» kat and his father is a doctor in Bagdad. He arrited from Constantinople on the 20th July and is still present in &lt;*askat« (3^ Abdul ^ahifc arrived in *askat on the 29th July froa i&gt;asra t he was on three months 1 leave from tabul where he is an instructor in the Hatoitoia ^ar college* He is a nephew of Colonel KahMUd t^ami late instructor of the H atoibia College C abul f who ie at present residing in Peshawar* Colonel Kahmud &amp;ami was expelled froa CaOul in the conspiracy case of December 19Ahdul ^shih arrived in Karachi on the 6th: august end left for Peshawar on tnel^th august and in the absenee of any information to the contrary is presumably in Ca^ul at present* (4* Colonel ^turi arrived in ^askat on the 29th July, with » m» ss «» «a es es a» ei Abdul *ahlb from £ asra* ne was a gusst of the bultan. He returned to i*asra on the 16th* august. (5i «ahio bin l^ajab arrived in askat on the 29th J uly, Aeooiiipanied (3) and (4)» (6&gt; i endi bin i^ahib arrived in ^asaat on the 29tii J uly and is one ef Colonel Yuri's party* . (?) /bdul k a J id k amil* (d) trewfik iihukri. These two men arrived in ^skat from B asra on the 9th: Auguet and left for Karachi on the 12th A ugust* They stayed with Uayyid Abdul Kadir ^awawi, 4 hey made inwuiries about liaskat and Oman in connection with a book tt »i ^ilad-ul- Kae' which they are bringing out in parts. The book is a sort of guide to different countries. they have visited &amp; ombay together and tewfikht profetsftd to have eoples of trantlAtions of olphor mes sages received by various Turkish officials. Considering the difficulties such a mission as described would have in crossing Persia and Afghanistan it seemed most probable that if there was sny propaganda at all on foot, it would be via British India to ^abul. Inspector ^han ~uhib Ikhlas* ud-din at Maskat reported about the mission on the 29th: August. Xhese reports were submitted to Colonel ^enn, C •!.£ and Aajor ^urphy, Military Intelligence Officerin the i^er- sian ^ulf. X find on inquiry that in all probability i^oham* mad Am in i^ey and Abdul ^ajid Kamil were the originators of the rsport that the Oerman Turkish mission was proceeding via Persia to Cabul. ac my Inspector^ informant was in very close touch with both of these men during their stay in kas* ^at. Abdul *ajid and his servant Tewfik Shukri have so far completed a tour in India, itarachi, Bombay, Bhopal, and Delhi having been visited end they were on their way back to the ^erslsn tH*lf when 4)iey«weee detained in Karachi. The Ueeident in the Persian Gulf may possibly be able to prove these conjectures to be ill-founded. In deal- ing with spies end emmissaries it is hardly possible to obtain evidence of any Judicial value and the above conclu sion is founded on the assumption of an alleged ian-Xslamic movement in India, Persia and babul either with or without. Cerman or Turkish support • it is quite possible that the whole thing is a creation of ^ohammad ^min Jbey and Abdul • *ajid. The fact that Atodul J^ajid ^amil had a copy of his own pamphlet • &gt;'axaih.ul.aoudan ,l is itself significant. The tesident in the iersian ^ulf has been asked to return Kohammad Amin -bey to Xaraohi and on his arrival further inquiries will be made. ^ have also interviewed two Arabs under orders of deportation as undesirables. (1i Ahmad iaik ibn Usrian and \&lt;i .4 *•&gt;!.*', 1 ibn ii«ktaeh ! rois ^ eoopcttmia. Ihey apparently were stowaway and were disembarked on the arrival of the stealerIn Kumehi. ^ do not oonoldor thwa In any way oonnootod with tho ^urks montioned nbove. I haw not ^oon nblo to tr^oo ^*mlr their n&amp;tlTo place out undorotunA it to bo in 'ittxk* 5. N *ho doportation of *ark» to tho ^oroian ^uif may possibly upnot th« politioal situation, for it ia oonooiYablo that daportets on arrivaX in the Cuif would gain oonoiderable local sympathy by representing the fact of their deportation hawing been ordered without their country being at ear with Great ^ritian. tn mary respects detention in tui India prison is preferable to deportation aa it stops the propaganda en* tirely, and i« the c&amp;se of foreigners their absence is not likely to cause any notice as they are taostly travellers who more frot* place to place and are not In consequence wissed, I hare offered to prevent the embarkation at ports in the - ersian tSulf/of Saropean foreigners, whose entry into British India has been prohibited by Government, in the saiae raanner that Afghans are at present prevented from entering / into India porte« The commissioner in i *ind J r. ^uoas approved of my action, as many benefits of the prohibition were Lost wvar tacii undesirables landenl in f arachi. I am tiucing i^xaeuiate etepa to put this into effect. 1 have the honour to be, »ir. four most obedient servant, mm Superintendent of folice, Un Special l&gt; uty.15th October 1914. Thanks for your secret letter ot the 26th September 1914* I see that Benn 's reply to you of the 4th October is a good deal fuller than anything I can give you about liuhaomad Puwad. I did not know anything about the man in Masqat, and it would seem from Benn's re ort that he oaate in March last # viz, w.ien I left Masqat. A.E.Grant, iSsquire, I.C.S., Deputy Secretary, For ign aid Political Departnent, SIMLA. rjj: ,0^- p l«. SuSHifle lltSlDtllCTo; ,: ■ —7 CTrmTri f?~ (p r (U. Tip ^SeiifejiteraiDer 1 1914. In continuation of ray demi-official letter of the 2Gtli September 1914, I em desired to forward, for your 110 information, o copy of a further extract from the Karachi Intelligence Diary of the 20th September 1914 rr jar ding one Mahouimed /inin, Be^; to whom reference was made in the extract which was forwarded with my above mentioned letter. 1 To Major S. G. Knox, C. I. E., Offg. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, . 1SECRET e -1 — Extract from Karachi Diary. 11IT1LLIGE1ICE SUMMARY. -J Hour, Bate Place• Sumnary of events and Information, 20th Sept.1914. S.O.p.m* Mr.Crre^Gon, O.I.E» # reports that further lengthy etatenent has heen made by MahommecL Amin Beg, and that he is sending the individual under escort to Colonel Knox, Bushire, who is in a better position to verify the nan's statement. Mr. Gregson reports that he has nov; arranged for a system of spies on all steamers trading to the Gulf, Remarks and refer- encesto Appendices.euswKt Mi 41 No: ^ C-180 of 1914 Poiic 0 Department. Dyilnspr.Genrl. of Police's office. From, Bto Karachi, ' a.ated 15th OctolDer 1914 C0Nf\^i ' - ^ W.L.B.SOUTER,Esquire, C.I.E., Deputy Inspector General of Police for Sind . The Political Resident,Bushire. To, Sir, I have the honour to confirm my cypher )telegram of date in Muhammad Amin Beg, Turk. | which I inquired j whetherjthe Turk, Muhammad Amin Beg, lately sent 'back to Karachi 'by Major Knox should 'be arrested. It will 'be remembered that on ahout the 17th ultimo this individual was sent up to Major Knox from Karachi with a letter from Mr. Gregson and returned here on the 7th instant in charge of one of Mr. Gregson*s men named Mir Islam. There is nothing in Major Knox's letter to Mr. Gregson warranting Muhammad Amin Beg's detention; 'but 'before taking any action in the matter I should 'be glad to 'be favoured with your views. I may mention that amongst the man's papers are two documents purporting to 'be copies of letters' addressed to the Resident intimating that he had certain important information to give him. I have the honour to 'be Sir Your most obedient servant Dy: Inspector General o 7^ - ' ice for Sind. iCOmTX'TI .r.T,. c % Ko: 3~/ ^ of 1914. BRITISH RKSIDSPCY AlIX) COI'SUIKTE O:I-ERAl BUSKIRB. Rrom L't-Coionei S.G.Knox, C.I.E. Offg; political ReBide it in the Persian gulf. 1014. The Kon'^ie Sir P.Z.Cox,K.O.I.E.,C.S.I. Bahrain, Sir, I have the honour to forv/arcl herewith copien of correspondence as quoted in the nat^in on the subject of the ) detention of one Muh&amp;nmad Secret letter I'o: C.ISO D/-15 .10 \ 1914 ' ^ ,m ^ n the Sind police, fr: -yj: i.g . police sind to \ P.R. in p.a. &gt; llo: C. -\o95.D/-30.10.14.fr: P.R. in p.G. to Dy: I.G.police, Sind.) -hia individual towards the middle of last juiy ad'a^: sed me stat.mg that he had inportant secret information to convey to rae and asked for a personal Interview . The tone of J - ■&gt;, tter aid not inspire confidence and I forwarded a 0f A^n letter t0 tJie rr, -- ;! - tlca - A £ ent , Hasciat, who saw ilijhariuaad .MM&amp;a Beg m the presence of His Harness the Suitan of -TiS-.at . Muha^iad Ainln Beg was evidently much disconcerted hy fils method of jrocefture and eventually wrote to me' somewhat Intemperate letter?! saying that I had completely destroyed crof.lt v/.i,„,i the Siiitan and asked what the latter cou^d be. supposed to K ow of ■■ haute politique -■ He announced his intention to lay his Information before the authorities m Si- a a and L o ndon. The ^ out In ai Agent , '-urqat records the following opinion about hiia 'Stayed hert? as a iniPRt /-.-p tt guest of His Highness and Is a friend of Syud Aodui Kadlr -n &lt; ^ . Said io have been once in the detective service of Abdul Harald, Sultan of Turkey, at Constantinople. mm f(s) ^2^ ^^ visited ^ar.q.at several times during the t: e 0: 0 the late Sultario Travelled with the present Sultan in India is a keen Hason and was ret pons ihle for laaRinj the present Sultan one. Appears to he an aristoctatic beggar and lives on the charity of His Highness , ' Muhammad Amin Beg , in his endeavour to 'brinj to t&gt;© notice of the authirities at Simla and London V e secret information of vhich he was in possession reached Karachi and was immediately taken off the steamer and detained on suspicion. His alleged status of secret informant was assumed to 'be a pose and he was told tht he could communicHte his information to :ir: Gregson. The latter, unaole to gut .je the truth of Muhammad Amin's allegations , sent him on to me whe . he was dulj? examined and produced certain items of Information , alleged to be translations of cypher telegrams passing oetween the local authorities at Basrah and Snver Pasha, the Turkish Minister of War. These- were duly communi cated to the Foreign and Political Department but they contained little that was not known to us already and merely confirmed former impressions , chiefly that the Turkish authorities were trying to win Bin Saud over to their side and anticipated an outbreak of hostilities between their country and Great Britain . It is porsiole that Muhammad Amin may be genainely anxious to sell some true scraps of information that he has picked up _ for a consideration - to the British Go ,v,ra) lent but attaches more value to the Information than it x„ &lt;■•1 h . Tfc. e t s f as I have raid, no Information on the records of this P.e £ idency to warrant his detention, though it would ho well if h e were watched while in India' a! no douht he will be under the stringent precautions now taken in the case of all Foreign suspects . I have the honour to be. Sit,Extract from c- letter No,' 417 deted 30th October 1914 from E . G-. Or egs on , Esquire, Superintendent of Police on Special Duty under the Government of India in the Foreign end Poli tical Departnient, to the Deputy Secretary to the G-overn- ment of India in the Foreign and Political Deportment. x A Muhammad Amin Bey has returned from Bushire, nothing connecting him with a Turkish mission was c scertatned , Bi^t B j note furnished me b;^ Mr Isemonger 'onder cover of his derai official Criminal Intelligence Office No, 1413-P.T. dated Simla the 30th September 1914, shows t at Muamm d Amin Bey visited India as long as 1909&gt; when he was re— garcffed as -n emis arrr from Turkey to Indie nd Afghanist n. This information was forwerded to the Deput^^ Inspector Q-enor^l Police, Sind , and I understand the Local G-overn- r ment has passed orders on this case. The conclusion I came to in my previous report has been confirmed the information received in Mr Isemonger's note and the further perusal of Abdul Majid's papers. There were nine Turks who foregathered at Masqat, five of whom I classed as emissaries, because they were intimately con- nect d with Indie . nd K bul, These are (1) Mu mm- d Amin Bey, (2) Abdul Wahib (3) Abdul Majid (4) Tewfik Shukri, and (5) Muhamme.d Fue.d , Militarrr Instructor at Masq t nd formerly of Kabul 0 The remaining four are more connected with the Gulf end Turkish Arabia, They ,re (1) Ismail B^y in Masqat, (2) Colonel Nuri in Besr^.h, (3) Sahib bin Naj b in B- srah, nd (4) Melidi bin S^ hib in Basrah„ Of tJ;e pfc.rty connected with Indie, ail ere in jail ex- oept Muhc.mmed Fuad , who is in Masqat, - nd Abdul Wahib, who is tr-veiling in India. He is in the Amir's service^ and 't present on leave, was last reported in the Punjab Secret * Abstract as being on his Wc y to Pes hew-r.Dtoket telegrajt , M jj , 6 Confidential Dated A/l/15. Fr«* Benn, Kascat T« Kntx, Bushire ( in kliBence ef Resident) Please refer te my telegraa, fte.5 ef 4th«January 1915 regarding Ali Ghalia bin Mahtnad. This aan oame here frea Basra about 4 nenths age to organize a pol ice force for the Sultan and has now been summarily dismissed to as]c and ordered to leave Mascat at once. He came to for my good offices and to protest against this treatment which he said was due to Intrigues of Sultan's younger brother and Fuwad^he Turkish In- struotor of His Highness* troops. I explained to him that not being a British subject or entitled to British protection all I could do ti for him was to refer him to the Local Grorernaient• As a British sub, -Ject had filed a suit against him for debt I took the opportunity during a visit I was paying to Sayad Kadir ( acting in the absence corns of H«H*) to mention the faot of the man having/to mam represent his case to me and I said that in view of the faet that a suit was pend ing in my oourt against the man I hoped he would be detained until the debt was paid. Upon this Ali Ghalib settled his account* Nadir against Sayad/said that there was no charge of misconduct/the man but that he had been found unsuitable for the work of organising the Police. The following appears to be the man^ history as given to zae by him self and derived from other sources;- He is a Turkish subject of Arab parentage whose family resided in Bagdad. He himself has been long resident in Basra,where he was employed in the Police. Ho was persuaded to desert from the police and seek employment ip Mascat by/1 one Ifuri Beg who is now said to be in Basra ( This is pvobably the Colonel luri mmntioned at No.5 of enclosure to my letter No,216 of 20th.September 1914)• Ali Ghalib,who has been styled ** Sffendi ** while in Mascat,arrived here 4 months ago and was at first given a subsistence allowance by H.H, and later was entrusted with the organisation of a local Police force. The Rev.Mr.Barney of the Arabian Mission here wrote to k±m me on behalf of the man stating that he was well known to him andTelegram. Oode. From - Benn, P.A. , l asqat. To - Foreign, Delhi. Repeated - Basrah and Bushire. No.90. Dated 1 -4-15. Your telegram of 29th Faroh Uo v 87. Sultan of ea. ^ l asqat informsme that Ismail is entering into 'Kurulhair's articles as a Storekeeper and resident of rasqat. Addressed Foreign, repeated Basrah and Bushire. Benn. *•f si 0 Telegram, From, Benn, Muscat, To, Foreign, Simla. Repeated, Basra &amp; Bushire* Dated, 29. 3. 15. No: 89. P. Reference my letter No 219 of 29th Spetember, 1914, with which I forwarded a copy of my No 218 of the same date to the P.H. and also my telegram No 224 of 24th September, to Foreign, a copy of which was sent to the P.2.with my No 225, dated]? 24th September, regarding Ismail Bey Turk. Alos see appendix to the report submitted by Gregson, No 417 of 29th October to the address of the Foreign Dept of the GoveriiLient of India. Ismail Bey (be oil board the Sultan's ship the Nur ul Bahr, which is enroute to Bombay for repairs &amp; due there about the 2nd April;he is brother of the Sultan^ Turkish ? and has been very ill for some time. the object of thisbtrip is stated to be for the good of his health. His deperture was not? mentioned to me by the Sul tan. During the past six months nothing suspicious has come to my notice, moreover some little time ago the Sultan assured me that this man wa above suspiciono Benn#</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000195_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/432</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000195</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/432</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Persian representation at Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1914/1921</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-18T15:12:22</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">per</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (119 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The main foliation sequence commences at the first folio and terminates at the final folio; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Three other incomplete foliation sequences run alongside the main sequence between ff. 1-37, ff 39-56 and ff 58-117; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled and can be found in the same position as the main sequence. Fold out folios: 74-75, 87-88.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file includes correspondence between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Political Agent at Muscat. There are also correspondence with Walter Beaupré Townley, Minister to Persia; Muhammad Amin Beg [Muḥammad Amīn Beg], the Turk; the Commissioner of Sind, Karachi; Edward Gelson Gregson, Superintendent of Police, Karachi.The file consists of three sections of correspondence:Folios 3-37 concern Persian representation at Muscat raised by the Governor of Bushire following a report of an attack on a Persian shopkeeper at Muscat in
                              Habl ul Matin [Ḥabl al-Matin] in 1914-1915;Folios 39-56 concern issues to do with the uprising and the Treaty of Seeb [Sīb], 1920, and includes a 'Brief survey of causes and history of the rebellion of the Oman tribes under the leadership of their elected Imam Sheikh Salim bin Rashid-al-Kharusi [Salīm bin Rāshid al-Kharūṣī] till 1915'Folios 58-115 concern Ottoman Turkish subjects, among them Muhammad Amin Beg, in Muscat and their possible influence on the Sayyid Taymūr bin Fayṣal Āl Bū Sa‘īd, the Sultan of Muscat, and includes 'List of Turks who are new, or were until recently, resident in Mascat (f 75-76) and extracts from Karachi intelligence Diary' 19 and 20 September 1914.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Financial administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>Treaty of Sīb (1920)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000195#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>