<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000295_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:57:37.652Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">File No. 2/14Translation of letter in.505 dated the I'th use enter 1935 from nhan tJahib niisain bin ass an • Amad, i-n. charge current duties of the Kesidency agent, atariah, to the political Agent, uahrain. After compliments. i received a letter addressed to you from shaikh sultan bin salim, KUler of Kas- el-Ahaimah which i enclose for your perusal. i beg to inform you that the shaikh of nas-el- khaimah asks for your help in deputing an experienced man to vaccinate the people against smallpox which has spread m all the tov/ns of ,/the x'rucial coast, if it becomes very cold, most of the people who suffer from smallpox would die. rhe order rests with you. usual isnaing.Translation of letter dated the 15th Kainadhan 1354(11. IP. 35; iron, bnaikn oil loan oln balin 5 Killer of Kas-el-jiliainish ^ to the Political Agent, rahrain. After CQinplimente. i write this letter to inform vou that smallpox has spread in. iias-eH-nhaimah. As these parts are in need 'or a doctor and, as you are aware, the people of these parts are ooo poor to travel for medical treatment, i feel compelled to ask for your help and request you, for the sake of ^iendship, to a end a doctor to vaccinate (the people; against this spreading epedimic before i£ brings bad affects. u su al iin d i ng.Telegram From To No. Dated the 24th Enclair, Political Agent, Bahrain, Health Officer, Basra, 317 December 1935. * IMPORTANT . , Grateful if you would send 400 repeat 400 doses small^pox vaccine next slow mail. Kindly ask Ship T s Doctor keep in ice chest and hand to Dr. Holmes at Bahrain. Political. ** * ■ -Telegram Enclair, Prom Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi, To Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Repeated Political Resident, Bushire, Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Muscat. No. A 119 Dated and received 28th December 1955. X X X X X X Flight may have to avoid Sharjah owing^ to wm—mwap Telegram Enclair, From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Imperial Airways, Sharjah, No. 319 Dated the 29th December 1935. $ ( 3 ) Please hand following to Khan Sahib Husain begins Please telegraph whether there is unusual amount of small pox at Sharjah ends. Political. / t1 Telegram From To No. Enclair, Political Agent, Bahrain, Imperial Airways, Sharjah, 320 Bated the 29th December 1935. Please hand following to Khan Sahib Husain begins Vaccinator Sattoor is proceeding Sharjah slow mail Baroda please send by launch urgently to pas al Khaimaho Please also telegraph whether he is required to work at Sharjah on his return if so more vaccine will / be sent. He is being paid by Government Ends. / / / Political. / * * * r \ '•Printed9 - - -1 Telegram G-.T-C. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. Ho. 321. Bated 30th December 1935. Residency Agent telegraphs smallpox along Trucial Coast is increasing. In response to revest from Shaiich I am getting vaccine ana arranging to sena Vaccinator to Has A! AhaimaU. Dioai Hira Ajmai! arid Umm A1 qaiwain are also affected and I am arranging for further supply of vaccine to be sent to Sharjah. *ould it be possible to spare anyone from Bushire by next slow mail to help carry out vaccinations. Will this affect your tour ? political•2/14 Telegram **&gt;* From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Health Officer, Karachi. No. 322. Bated 30th December 1935. Please send urgently oy Airways to Residency Agent Sharjah one thousand doses smallpox vaccine auo. send bill to Political Agent, Bahrain.^ (yVU. 'S&amp;Q * * * n &amp; Telegram From To Repeated to Political Resident, Bushire, Political Agent, Bahrain, Air Officer Commanding, R.A.F. ’Iraq, No. 1051 Dated and received 30th December 1S35. /I ,&amp;■ f ' Last sentence of Air Officer Commanding’s telegram No.AJ19.of December 28th please ascertain immediately from Residency Agent and telegraph me the number of cases ana deaths smallpox during the last week* If smallpox is confirmed Residency Agent should arrange with (_!_£__) (and?) Station Superintendent to isolate Rest House as far as possible from town. Britconsul.14 y zbtck^ ^ 3(1 h ^ Telegram R/E7 From Political Resident, Bushire, lo Political Agent, Bahrain, No. . 1052 Dated 30th (received 31st) December 1935. / My telegram of to-day No. 1051. Any outbreak of infectious disease on Trucial Coast is obviously of importance especially at Sharjah and Dibai at Aden (?) latter on which slow mail calls and at former both slow mail and Imperial Airways. This being so, both you and I should receive immediate information. If outbreak has actually occurred how was it that Residency Agent did not telegraph you. Britconsul® ** *2/14 Telegram G-.T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Political Resident, Bushire, No. 323 Dated the 31st December 1935. 4 lour telegram of December 30th No. 1051 crossed my telegram of 30th No. 321* I am instructing Residency Agent to telegraph figures both for Sharjah and other places and if smallpox severe at Sharjah to isolate Rest House. 300 persons have already been vaccinated at Sharjah and further supply of vaccine is being sent* Guard of Rest House were vaccinated last year but I have issued oraers for vaccination of any new guards* Political.* * * * 2/14 t Telegram Enclair From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Airways, Sharjah, No. 324 Dated the 31st December 1S35. Please pass following to Khan Sahib Husain begins Please telegraph for Residents information number of cases and number of deaths from smallpox at Sharjah in last week* If smallpox is severe you should arrange with Station Superintendent to isolate air station from town as far as possible. Any of / . guard not vaccinated last year should be vaccinated, at once. One thousand doses vaccine ordered from Karachi to be sent by air. Please telegraph if more required. Please telegraph who is carrying out vaccination in Sharjah. Vaccinator for Has al Khaimah will be sent by air mail of January first if vaccine from Basra received in time otherwise by air mail of January fourth. Please try to get figures of cases and deaths for other places mentioned in your telegram of December 29th o Political.Telegram G.T.C. Prom Political Resident, Bushire, To Political Agent, Bahrain, No. 1053 Dated and received 31st December 1935. IMPORTANT . Your telegram No. 321 of December 30th. Difficult to supply anybody from here could, not Bahrain Government supply vaccinator or alternatively could you not send your compounder? Please supply urgently details asked for in paragraph 1 of my telegram No. 1051 first for Sharjah and then in due course for other places on Trucial Coast. Britconsul*b (S&gt; Telegram Enclair From Air Officer Commanding, Hinaiui, To Political Resident, Bushire, Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain, ... Senior Naval Officer, Persian G-ulf Division, No. A129 Dated and received 31st December 1935. For your information am sending medical officer to Sharjah by Imperial Airways to-day to vaccinate all personnel of Rest House and any others who require it and also to investigate cause of outbreak. * * * * h♦ * * 2/14 Telegram From To No. Enclair Political Agent, Bahrain, Airways, Sharjah, 325 Dated the 31st December 1935. Important Please hand following to Khan Sahib Husain begins Air Officer Commanding is sending Mddical Officer by Imperial Airways to vaccinate all personnel in Airways station and any others who require it and also to investigate cause of outbreak. Please meet him at landing ground and assist him Ends. Political.%D 2/14 Telegram Enclair From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Political Resident, Bushire, Repeated Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi, Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, No. 326 Dated the 31st December 1935. Important . Air Officer Commanding T s telegram a/ 129 of December 31st Have instructed Khan Sahib to assist Medical Officer. As regards investigation no objection provided Medical Officer does not attempt to enter private houses unless asked to do so. Smallpox is endemic on Trucial Coast and is more likely to become epidemic in winter owing to crowding in towns. Outbreaks usually appear in cycles of something like five years when immunity given by last outbreak has become reduced. Political. * * *1st Jaauary \ V'i Dear Li*', &gt; 0 I encxose a co y oj. a tele rara f]o.3Jb datea tue 31st Docember 1D35 uo the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Guii and repealed to the Air Oiii v&gt;r Gor^^iUiCiin^ • • and the Senior Naval Oiiicer, Persian Gulf Division, about your visit to Sharjah, 3, I have instructed Khan Sahib Husain bin Hasan ? \mad who is carrying on the duties of the Residency gent ■ to assist you and he will do ail he can to help you. 3, I do not know what lorn ox investigation is meant, but 1 am sure that you will app reciate that c&amp;^e should be taken not to at .QKiut to go into houses, unless asked to do so* 4, The action that I have tauen so far is to send,a \ vaccinator (named Sattoor), who will bo on the aeroplane with you, to ^as al Khaimah with OOu doses ox vaccine. Alter ^as al Khaimah, he is going to /gman, Hira, Umm al ,awain and Dubai. 5, I have ordered a further luQQ doses 'irom the Health Officer, Karachi, to be sent by air, ior the use of the vaccinator. 6* Khan Sahib Husain reports that some 300 persons have already been vaccinated in 3h. rj h, and I resume that any of the Airways . tation Stall, who ha&amp;nat boon vaccinated recently, have been done. / 1 , AS- \ The i edicai Officer of -oyai ir lorco &gt; roceeuing to Sh rjalu G/o. Imperial irwa s Liu ten, Bali rain.All the guaTQ ixmx most if not all the Station employees were vaccinated last ye r, but 1 telegraphed instructions that any new guards should be vaccinated at once and also that, if the outbreak in Sharjah is severe (I have not yet received the numbers of cases), the Station Superintendent should be asited to isolate the Station xrom the tom as iar as possible* 6. ihen you are at Sharjah, please do not hesitate to telegraph to me il there is any way in which 1 can be ox help to you. Yours sincerely, xwcmst and appears to break out into epidemic iom in cycles ol aomotluiif like live ^©o,rs , when the immiiij given bj the last epidemic has weakened* It is doubtful whether it is possible to oiler an explanation ?:or # u outMreak ocmrtuig ? w ^ specific «*oment* 7# Such outbreaks are most likely so nap pea x» «ne -inter owlru- r,o cjowdlag ia tno towns* e&gt;* ihe old fanatical hostility to vaccination has largely died away, but now the diJfiieulfcy oxpctioncod by -anciantors is thrs if there is no epidemic men simply e^y timt tstore is no mnllpox about - ii tncre is ?n epidemic, they often think that ¥-.cciaation bring on real snail pox* Inis is probably due to choir regarding our vaccination m like tneir own system oi inoculation with puss from smallpox cases* It is Inc a res tin.; to iind that in some places, notably Dubai, the people themselves impose a kind 01 isolation of smallpox cases, as soon is they appe r, by sending the pc non a ai-.ee to! awa y. oxitioal- bsU I ^ ^ jahrain*j 2/14 Telegram Prom To Repeated to No. Gr.T.C. Political Resident, Busiiire, Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi, Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, Political Agent, Bahrain, 1 -« Dated and received 1st January 1936. Important . Your telegram of 31st December A 129. In addition to his telegram No. 326 Political Agent, Bahrain has telegraphed that under his arrangements 300 persons have already been vaccinated at Sharjah, further supply of vaccine is being sent, guard of Rest House were vaccinated last year but that he has issued oraers for vaccination of any new guards. Britconsul. * * *2/14 Telegram From To No. E Political Resident, Bushire, Political Agent, Bahrain, 2 Bated and received 1st January 1936. •V w You might have included in your telegram / / x No. 326 information given in my telegram No. 1 which is based on your telegrams Nos. 321 and 323 to me it was essential for Air Officer Commanding and Senior Naval Officer to know what measures had already been taken. Britconsul2/14 Telegram From To Repeated No. Enclair Political Agent, Bahrain, Osmonde Care Airways, Sharjah, Khan Sahib Husain Care Airways, Sharjah, 1 Dated the 2na January 1S36. Letters for you are coming by to-day T s aeroplane containing general information about smallpox on Trucial Coast and details of what has been done in this outbreak. No objection to your investigating cause of outbreak proviaed you ao not attempt to enter houses unless asked to do so. Khan Sahib Husain has instructed been to meet and assist you. Political.. * * * i i I! (I f 4Printed2/14 G.T.C. Political Agtnt, Baiirain, Political Resident, Bushire, Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi, Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, 2 Dated the 2nd January 1936. u \l A Your telegram No. 1051 of December 30th. Husain reports Sharjah 100 cases 12 deaths Ras al Khaimah 30 and 4 Umm Al Qawain 80 and 4 Ajman 15 and 7 Hira 30 and 2 Dibai 50u and 60. Precautions taken to safeguard station. Osmonne Medical Officer Royal Air Force arrived Sharjah December 31st returned January 2nd he vaccinated personnel of station not already done. Political. Telegram From To Repeated No. ^1 , •' 4 » 32 -- D.O. o Janutiry 193b. M '.Vill you kintily rolur to your tolo b ~tuii dutod tho 1st January 193b about tko outbreak ol sioali^ox on the frucial Coast. ^ I eor^y taat I did not include the measures taken in my telec^am No.326 dated the 31st December, but did not do so as I |~a?e them in a deei-oificial letter rio.l~3/H d^ted the lot January (co.iy enclosed) and in my express letter Bo.2-2/14 dated the 1st January 1936 which was to have been handed to the Medical Oiiicor on the aeroplane. 3. I'nlortunatuly owing to his aeroplane passing through earlier than was expected, it did not reach him, but I have since had it sent to him at Baghdad, as he '■eturned there by the next Westbound aeroplane, unknown to me till he had passed thnnigh. I should explain th t yie 30c vaccinations at Sharjah moatioaed ia my tole»jrfa'Ko.J23 dated the 31st Doocaber v.'erc done by the Sa^eriaueadent oi the Ktstioa. I do not yet itaow .here his oritfiaai supply oi v?iCoiae came irom, but I had a fuHIier 1000 do^es sent to Sharjah (whe-e it arrived on 1st January) by air from Karachi for use m «11 the places ^fleeted. *&gt;• I am instructing Khan S*hio Husain m future to let me have news oy telegnm of a u y outbreak. I do not yet know when this outbreak first started, but he reported ^ it by letter as soon, I should judge, as it became severe according to frucial Coast standards fhe Honourable Lieutenant Colonel P.C. rowle, C.B*i*;., Political ^esiaent in the Persian Gull, Bushins. / m- Telegram From To Repeated No. 2/14 G.T.C. Political Agent, Ban rain, Political Resident, Bushire, Air Officer Commanding, Hinaiai, Dated the 4th January 1936. Crateful if I might have by air mail copy of Osmonde f s report on smallpox outbreak at Sharjah. Political. *****2/14 Telegram G-.T.C* From Political Resident, Busnire, To Political Agent, Banrain, No. 12 Dated 4th (received t&gt;th) Jauuary IStSo. p\ Gorresponaence ending witn Banrain telegram No. 2 of January 3rd. For information® Trucial Coast smallpox* Relevant Health authorities ana Imperial Airways informed of situation ana measures taxen* Britconsul* ***V)€&gt; NCCRPORATI NG:- . EPH EN LYNCH &amp; C9 LYNCH BROTHERS, L T P GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; C9 and GRAY, PAUL &amp; C9 Telegraphic Address;- 'mespersV Codes usedi- Bentley’s Complete Phrase Code. Scotrs Tenth Edrtiorr. • The Standard Shipping- Code. A;B.tTS*,E^tidh^ Be^Tk.rr'i Dear Captain Cole, In reply to your D.O. IT©. the 30th ultimo, I have to inform you that the Vaccinator left for Sharjah by the Eastbounb Service of the 2nd instant. Yours sincerely, / Captain G. V;. Cole, Bahrein.Telegram G.T.C* From To Repeated to Political Resident, Busnire, Air Oflicer Commanding, Hinaidi, Political Agent, Banrain, No. 2b Dated and received otn January 1936» Reference Banrain teiegrarfl No. 3. If you nave no objection grateful if you would send copy of report referred to ootii to Banrain and Busnire. Britconsui* * * *^ °j © G*!T»C# Political He si dent, Bushire, Political Agent, Bahrain, 28 Dated the 7th January 1936, Tour telegram No# 2 of January 3rd. Please send weekly telegraphic report on Mondays stating number of new cases and deaths. Britconsul# * ** j ^/' } ( i - ftranslation of letter Ho: 13 dated the 5th January 1936 equivalent to the 10th ahauwal 1354 from Khan sahib husain bin xtasan *A£iad, in charge current duties of the residency Agent, sharjah to the political Agent,uahrain* / After Conpliments, •5m Reference your letter HojL dated the 1st January ji I yl936 concerning the vaccinator named Sattur, who is to V&gt;' vaccinate at nas-al-nhaimah, uni-al-Qaiwain, Ajman,Hira, Sharjah and uibai* 2. i beg to inform you that the vaccinator arrived on 2nd January 1936 by the airmail aeroplane and 1 took him to my place at Sharjah. As the sea was very rough on account of the heavy wind, the launch c&amp;uld not leave for Kas-al-Mhaimah. therefore, he vaccinated some of the Sharjah people on Saturday the 4th January till midday, when the sea became quiet and the wind subsided, and then left for Kas-al-Khaimah at once. 3* ihe 1000 doses of vaccine arrived from Karachi and 1 telegraphed to you accordingly on the 2nd January 1936. I gave shaikh sa*id bin maktum, Ruler of Dibai, some of the said vaccine and he ordered his brother, shaikh Hashar bin Maktum and his cousin, shaikh uum f ah bin fhani and one of his men, who know vaccinating, to do vaccinating, fhis dhey did and were very thankful to you for your kind ness. all 4* I have informed/the irucial shaikhs that you have sent a vaccinater with medicine in order to vaccinate against smalipox ; free at the cost of the government, and that he will visit their states when his work at Kas-al- Khairaah is finished# 5. -ihe vaccine will not be sufficient and, if you be consider fit, it would/a good thing if you order for more from Karachi.g &gt;^ xhere are people at bharjah and at Ajman who know vaccinating. I will issue them with little medicine from time to time, and they can do the work of vaccinating, ihe Shaikh of nas-al^haimah is prepared to placx two of his men, uasim bin kalban and Muhammad bin ^Abdul *Aziz, to learn the work from sattur so that later on they can do the work themselves. usual Ending.Telegram Enclair From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Health Officer, Karachi, No. 10 Bated the 8th January 1936. please send urgently by Airways to Residency Agent Sharjah further supply of one thousand aoses smallpox taccine ana send bill to Political Agent, Bahrain* Political. *** / \iTanslation of letter jso: 16 dated the 8th danuary 1936 equivalent to the 13th Shauwal 1354 from Khan 1 i asan ’Amad. in charge current duties of the Kesidency Agent,Sharjah, to the Political Agent, Bahrain* After conpliments, i enclose a letter which jl have received from shaikh Sultan bin balim,Kuler of Kas-al-Khaimah in reply to your letter no *2 dated the 1st January 1936, in which he egresses his grateful thanks to you for sending the vaccinator.to his town,and hope it will reach you safely, usual landing. ■translation of letter dated 11th Shauwal 1354 !&lt;??ivalentto 6th January 1S36 from Shaikh sultan bin Dalim,Kuler of t Khm-mah to Lieutenant Colonel Cordon Loch,C. i.b., Politic Age nt r Bahrain* After c omp 1 ime nts 9 1 was very pleased to receive your letter Uo:2 aated the 6th shauwal 1354 equivalent to the 1st January 1936 and feel very thankful to. you for the care and trouble which you have taken in sending sattur for vaccinating and saving the people of the evil, fhe people are always indebted to those persons who do them an act of kindness* usual Ending*COPY Reference 3S14/17/36. Station Si ok ^strters, f Royal Air Force, Hinaidi, ^iraq, 3rd. January, 1935. The principal Medical officer. Air Headquarters, British Forces in f lraq, HIHAIBI, 'Iraq. Sir, I have the honour to submit the following report on my visit to Sharjah on 31.IS*35. Upon arrival, it was found that the imperial Airways Rest House at Sharjah is separated from the outskirts of Sharjah Town by about a mile and a half of open desert country. The Rest House is a converted fort in which live five or six Englishmen (employees of imperial Airways), as members of the permanent staff* The rest of the personnel is entirely native, and numbers about sixty, nearly all these natives live in a settlement of their own just outside the barbed wire surrounds of the Rest House and aerodrome. They are not, however, forbidden to enter Sharjah Town when and as they please. I, personnally, vaccinated the entire native staff and such of the English staff as had not been success fully vaccinated during the last year. Upon enquiry, it was deduced that the only native personnel with which Imperial Airways passengers would come into contact, were the bearers employed in a domestic capacity in bedrooms, dining rooms etc. These bearers live in the Rest House. I also interviewed the Native political Agent for Sharjah and obtained from him the latest figures of small pox incidence and mortality in the neighbouring towns. The figures are appended herewith Town. Population. Small pox C&amp;ses (approx.) Deaths during previous week. SHARJAH. 3,000 100 13 DUBAI. £15,000 500 60 RA3 AL KH1IMA 30 4 UMMAD ^GWAIN. - 80 4 AJMAH. •m 15 7 HEERA. - 30 a 0 The nearest of these towns to Sharjah is Dubai, which is about 15 miles distant by road. The actual source of the infection is unknown, small pox is endemic in the Truoial Oman, and it is seldom that there are not a few cases in one or other of the towns. This, coupled with the fact that (in Sharjah, at least) there is no form of sanitation, there is filth, squalor, and overcrowding everywhere, and vaccination is not rigorously practised, is sufficient reason to account for the seasonal epidemics of small pox in this area. jIII P.T.O.ContdThe following two recommendations are therefore made with a view to minimising the risk to those visiting Sharjah Rest House (a) That all personnel employed at the Rest House should be made to live in the immediate vicinity, and forbidden to enter Sharjah Town (or any infected town) unless the nature of the duty makes it imperative. (b) That, conversely, the inhabitants of Sharjah should not be allowed to approach the Rest House. £t the moment, a large number of people are coming from the towns to the Rest House to be vaccinated by the Station Superintendent. If a general vaccination station is to be started, it should be situated at a considerable distance from the Rest House, and the vaccinations should not, preferably, be done by a member of the imperial Airways staff. V*'-**'” I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Signed) a* H. OSMOHD, Flight Lieutenant, R*A*F*M*S.i Telegram Enclair, From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Kuan bahih Husain Care Airways, Sharjah, No- 13 Dated the 11th January 1936* /^\ lour telegram eleventh Doctor Holmes will come by Imperial Airways this evening eleventh returning Monday but please telegraph urgently what Shaikh Mohammad T s illness is so that he can bring suitable medicines. Political. * * * * v i li-J!'&amp; 5 ^ 2/14 We should tell K*S. Husain to let Sattur train the two men of whom he writes, if Dr. Holmes thinks him capable of doing so. Dr. Holmes Do you think Vaccinator Sattoor capable of training two men on the Trucial Coast to vaccinate persons? P. A. No. I think it would be better to train the men here anti sena them down. B.H.. 10/1 I instructed Dr. Holmes on 10th January to inform Khan Sahib Husain that the two men should not be trained oy Sattur, but to inform the Shaikh that if he woulu. send „ them to Bahrain for a month Dr. Holmes would train them properly in the Hospital. D.J ..S 10/1 G.L. , 12/1 Gr.A.Q ii. • U • 12/lThe Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to;—- The Honourable the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated J J ' GUa Ty 1936 L Reference to previous correspondence : Political Agent, Bahrain’s telegram No.3 dated the 4th January 1936. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. NO.5012/32/P.M.0. dated the 4th January) Outbreak of Smallpox at 1936 from the Group Captain, Principal Sharjah. Medical Officer, British forces in ’Iraq., with enclosures.Telegram Enclair, From Political Agent, ^a.-i.r&amp;in, To Health Officer, Karachi, No. 21 Dated the 16th January 1936. Please send urgently by Airways to Residency Agent Sharjah further supply of one thousand doses smallpox vaccine and send bill to Political Agent Bahrain. Political.translation of letter no.34 dated the 15th January 1S36 equivalent to the 20th shauwal 1354 from nhan bahib msain bin uasan ^Amad, in charge current duties of Agent,bharj ah, to the Folitical Agent,Bahr After uonroliments § reference your telegram no.is dated the 11th danuary 1936. jjoctor uolmes arrived at oharjah on the 12th January by the airmail aeroplane. ± made all the necessary arrangements for him and accompanied him to Jibai. Ke called on shaikh ba‘id bin Maktum, u.B.K., Kuler of Dibai for balams and then went to the patient* shaikh mhammad bin Ahmad Dalmuk, examined him and treated him on the same day. During his stay the Doctor used to go to the aerodrome and come to Dibai for treating the patient, ne also did vaccinating work at Dibai only. i enclose a letter to you from bhaikh sa'id, in which he expressed his gratitude for complying with his request. usual ending.jiranslation of letter dated the 20th Shauwal 1354(i*e. 15th uamary 1936) from Shaikh Sa*id bin maktum, Hiler of wibai to the Folitical Agent,Bahrain* After compliments, regarding the request which l made,through your agent &amp;han sahib nusain bin nasan r Amad , asking the government to send their ovm Doctor, I write to thank you for your kind help in sending Doctor nolmes* 1 am also grateful to the government. rhe Doctor arrived and very kindly treated shaikh Muhammad bin Ahmad, whom x hope will be cured through his treatment. ?»e are all very thankful to him for his treatment and for the vaccination work which he did to al}. the people without exception, ihe people are very thankful to him for his treatment, x request you to convey the contents of my letter to the nigh Government for whom x pray for prosperity and g^ory. usual Ending.SHIV No. H. q A / u 1 From, To, MUNICIPAL CORPORATION, ., KARACHI. i L January 1936 Dr. B. P. BILLIMORIA, l.m. &amp; s,, b.^y., d.p.h , (London) Health Officer, KARACHI. Sir, The Political Ag Bahrain 2 \ m 936 - n ‘~'* With reference to your two telegrams dated 30th ^ecemher 1935 and 8th January 1936 signed Political 322 and Political 10^ respectively, I have the honour to inform 2 /ou that 1290 doses i.e. 129 tubes-Belgaum Vaccine Lymph has so far been despatched by Airways as instructed by you to Sarjah. Bill amounting to Rs 161-4-0 at the rate of Rs 1-4-0 per tube of 10 doses is enclosed herein. I therefore request you to kindly remit this amount at an early date and oblige. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant X^C-^eo / Health Officer / ^/bc(jjyf \r cy Translation of letter to. 43 dated the 18th January 1936 from k. a msain bin nasan 'Amad, i n charge current duties of the Kesidencv Agent, bharjah, to the Political Agent, aahrain. «esicency After Compliments. 1 enclose a statement showing the details of cases and deaths by smallpox on the xrucial towns for the period from 12th to 19th January, the statement shows also the number of those who have been cured. topy forwarded to the secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian uulf, tsushire. usual snding.1* BY AIR MAIL . RI&amp;IS T ERKD . No. /2/14. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21January 1936. From To The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Health Officer, Municipal Corporation, K A R A C H I. Sir, With reference to your letter No. iL 9 a/ 4/36 dated the 11th January 1936, I have the honour to enclose 0 Draft drawn in your favour for Poipees( 161/4/-) one hundred and sixty-one and anna© four only in settlement of your bill dated the 10th January 1936 in respect of 129 tubes Belgaum Vaco ine T ,ymph. Please acknowledge receipt. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Bahra in.i-ranslation of letter no*62 dated the 26th January 1936 equivalent to the 1st -whul ^a* dah 1354 from Khan bhaih nusain,sharjah to the rolitical Agent, Bahrain* by smallpox on the xrueial uoast for the period from 19th to 26th instant, and also those who have been cmred* 2* ± beg to inform you that Shaikh numaid bin ohaikh ^ashid bin Ahmad bin bultan the son of the Killer of Biba died today at oharjah of smallpox* ihe market was closed by order of the shaikh, sultan bin Saqr who is the cousin of the deceased. 3* j/he shaikh ordered that persons suffering from smallpox should be removed ouside the town, as it is the custom of the irucial '-oast to keep the patient out side the town for a period of 40 days - until he is cured- and then make him return* rhe Shaikh stopped this practice for the reason that the people are poor and cannot afford to build good houses which can protect them against the severe cold weather. 4* rhere are many people who have not been vaccinated on the irucial Coast as the vaccine which was received was not sufficient. If you consider fit you may order for vaccine to be sent from Karachi weekly. Decision rests with you. copy has been sent to the Secretary to the Honourable the rolitical He si dent in the rersian v^ulf, sushire.Telegram Ea clair From To Repeated - No* Dated Political Agent, Bahrain. The Health Officer, Karachi. ■Residency Agent, Sharjah. 41 27th January 1936. Please send to Residency Agent Sharjah by Air Mail one thousand doses smallpox vaccine weekly till further notice addressed Health Officer Karachi repeated Residency Agent Sharjah (who should telegraph to me directly supply can be st opp ed)• Political,—. 6 ) fro No. 300-2/14. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 30th January 1936 From Lieutenant Colonel Cordon Loch, C-I*E., political Agent, Bahrain, To he Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Cull, Busin re • Smallpox on the iracial Go_ast Sir. I have the honour to enclose a copy of a letter Ho.5* dated the 16th January 1936 from Doctor Holmes, I.M.D., Medical Oiticer in Charge, Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain, who visited Dubai and Sharjah at my direction to attend Shaikh Muhammad bin Ahmad Dalmuk and to enquire into the progress of the smallpox epidemic. 3 # I understand from Doctor T&gt; . Holmes that Mr l.C* Janes, Station Superintendent, Imperial Airways Station, Sharjah, has visited Dubai, Ajman, Hira and Khan on the Tmcial Coast in order to vaccinate the people. This work is most creditable to Mr James from the humane point o- view, but I would propose to write to him informally and, while expressing appreciation of his efforts on behalf/-•&lt; of behalf/these poor people, to request him in future to telegraph to me to ascertain whether there is any political objection before he undertakes such activities outside the Imperial Airways Station. I do not, of course, know what view his Company takes of such work with its attendant risk of bringing infect ion into the Station. S. I am reporting to the Health Officer, Basrah, jC ■ 7 the difference which has been noticed between the ijcisrcdi find the Karachi vaccine, and am arranging xor furtner supplies to be got from Karachi, as requested. ^ ic.lose a translation of a letter dated 4. I one the 15th' January 1936 from Shaikh Sa»id bin Maktum, ■^ler of Dibai, expressing his gratitude for the help afforded to his relative and his people by Doctor Holmes, to whom I am sending a copy. 5. I also send a translation of a similar letter ol thanks dated the 6th January 1936 from JV\ Shaikh Sultan bin Salim, '^hiler of ^as al Khaimah for ■ s sending a vaccinator. s. . , i y\ I have the honour to be, /■' .'y ' Sir, 7 MV. v ' \ V Your most obedient servant, I \ \ \ ■/', i Lieutenant Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain. I 1 L i ST ;S • A; : \ h r\ ■. v V / AD,0.No.3ol-2/l4 1 idose a translation ox a letter dated the January 1936 irons 3fcaikh id bin t.aktuSj ^uler ox Dubai, in which he expresses his thanks ior the help which you have ^iven him and his people. I. should like to add my own thanks for the prompt way in v/hich you acceded to my request to you to visit the iTucial woast * Doctor Holmes, I.M.D* . fictoHa Memorial Hospital Bahrain.Telegram From G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain, To Political Resident, Bushire, Repeated Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi, Copy handed to Senior Officer, Persian Gulf. No. 51 Dated the 3rd February 1936. Smallpox week ending 2nd February Dibai 21 cases and 4 deaths Sharjah 17 Hira 2 Ajman 4 and Ras al Khaimah 2 all cases. POLITICAL.a \M ' ^7 ^ Dh. h. p. bilimoria, , r -M. &amp; s f , B.HY„ d.p.h. (London) Health Officer MUNICIPAL CORPORATION, C?1 f KARACHI. X# o r\ vW y J * January 1936. No, H. 9A/10/36 To, The Political Agent, Lahrain. I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your telegram dated 16th instant and to - - inform you that 25 tubes of Vaccine Lymph - - - containing 250 doses have 'been despatched hy - - Airways to Residency Agent, Sharjah. I enclose herein a hill amounting to Rs 31-4-0 being the cost for the same at the rate of Rs 1-4-0 per each tube and to request you to kindly remit the amount at an early date along with the amount - - asked for under this office Ho.9A/4 dated 11th instant. Kindly return all wooden covers enclosirg in the lymph tubes as they &amp;re required to be sent to the .Director of ''nccineT' ‘^.gaum.V^^\j&gt; ^4 'ue_A Translation of letter no.67 dated the 2nd February 1S36 from h. S, Hu sain bin jkasan * Afiad, In charge current duties of the Residency Agent, sharjah, to the Political Agent, Bahrafh. After Compliments. 40 with reference to my letter n 0 .13 dated the 5th January 1936, i enclose a receipt for Rs.70/- received by the Nakhuda of the launch which carried battur, the vaccinator to Ras al Khaimah. U.E.TRANSLATION. Received from Khan Sahib ms a in bin nasan *Amad the sum of Rs.70/- on account of hire of the launch which carried sattur, the vaccinator to R a s al Khaimah. -Dated: 8th January 1236. Thumb impression of xusuf bin uasim al uokhi.\ Subject: Smallpox on the Truelal Coast. /f* -deference paragraph 2 of your letter No. 300-2/ 14 of 30th January 1936. P 2. I approve of your suggestion to write to Mr. Janes. 3. A copy is 'being forwarded to the Government of India and the Air Officer Commanding Iraq Command, Baghdad. Sd. T. C. Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf- Attested. •o ■IK */ ^ f No. 4/142 (m) The Secretary to the ''Tfon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Air Officer Commanding Iraq Command, BAGHDAD, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRB. IL Dated | J February 1936 Reference to previous correspondence : This Residency Telegram Ho. 12 of 4th January 1936. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 1. Letter Ho. 300-2/14 dated the 30th January 1936 from the Political Agent, Bahra_in, with enclosures. 2. Memorandum No.^1 dated the February 1936 to the Political Agent, Bahrain. No. J)ko Subject. Smallpox on the Trucial Coast. Copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain. —-Copy forwarded fco the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department No. wiigii reference to this Besidency Telegram 11 of 4th January 1936. By order, od. C.G.L. Byan. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Golf. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bush ire J F© br-tt&amp;ry • • •1936’ Smallpox on the Trucial loast 1 . 2. L tter Ko* 300-2/14 dated Political Agent, Bahrain, ; emorandum No* ^31 ‘dated Politioal Agent, Bahrain. List of Papers. the 30th January 1936 from the iwith enclosures* the February 1936 to the 'Ho. 341 Copy to the Politioal Agent, Bahrain.Dk. h. p. bilimoria, L.M. &amp; S., B.HY„ d.p.h. (London) Health Officer tg) MUNICIPAL CORPORATION, KARACHI. / ** r 0 February 1936. To, Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge with thanks the receipt of a Draft for Rs 161/4/- on account of cost of 129 tubes Belgaum Vaccine Lyinnh received with your letter Ro.264/2/14 dated Janu ary 1936, and to enclose herein stamped receipt No.32284 dated 4/2/1936, for the same. I have the honour to he. Sir, ’ Your most obedient servant. r ^Health Officer.This receipt will be merely evidec of payment cf the money ORIGINAL KARACHI MUNICIPAL CORPORATION. CHALAN (Head Office). To the Municipal Accountant. Sir—Please receive the amount as noted below for credit to the Budget Head as specified hereunder: — nlf) PARTICULARS. Head of account to be credited. Amount. No. Head. Rs. a. X P -V' y ** / | / j v ^ ' J' r ' *, Amount (in words) Rupees Countersigned / ( ^ Dept. ^ it rcm Q t' l —~ Remitter. Received Rupees (in words) Receipt No.__ * t- — : ' ■ 1 .dated t 1 M : Municipal Accountant. This receipt is not valid unless countei signed by the Municip.il Accountant who is in chaige of the Municipal Treasury.Dk. H. P. BILIMOPvIA, l.m. &amp; s t , B.HY„ D.p.H. (London) Health Officer No, He The Political Agent, Bahrain. . .1o\ MUNICIPAL CORPORATION, KARACHI: Pehrurry 1936. ne:= 'O.kin To, Sir, - ' :/ ( I have the honour to enclose herein a hill amounting to Bs 1^5-0-0 on account of supply of 100 tubes of Vaccine Lymph to the Residency Agency, Sharjah. I therefore request you to kindly remit the amount to this office at an early date. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant. t/vvvV) Officer. r _ = -4- 1KARACHI MUNICIPAL - 0 O 0 — CORPORATION The Political Agent, Bahrain. D r# To, The Karachi Municipal Corporation. BILL . ) Rupees one hundred On a/c of 100 tubes of vaccine ) Lymph to Residency Agent Sharjah ) and twenty five a t Rs 1/4/- per Lymph .Rs 125-0-0 ) ) only. Total. Rs 125-0-0 ) Municipal Office. Karachi. 10th February 1936. I/VVV1/)rm* W&gt;i-&amp;2£» Vi e/CiV^—i^i/ A* Ac&gt; iranslation of latter uo.lll dated the S3rd February 1936 from fAan t&gt;alub tiusam bin aasan 'Amad, j. n charge current duties of the residency agent, oharjah, to the r 0 litical agent, Bahrain? After ^onpliments • 1 encxose a statement showing the number of cases and deaths by smallpox on the irucial towns from the 16th to the 23rd February 1936. .he number of those who have been cured is also shown. copy sent to the o e cretary to the Honourable the political resident in the rersian trulf, mshire. U.^j.InTelegram Gr.T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Political Resident, Bushire, Repeated Air Officer Commanding, Rinaidi, Senior Officer, Persian Gulf, No. 73 ^ated the ^5th February 1936. Smallpox week ending 23ra February Sharjah 1 and 3 Himriyah 1 and 1 cases and deaths. Dubai 6 Has al Khaimah 2 all deaths. Political./07 o9 D*0*No#598-2/14 2 r /fch i ebrua ^y 1936* Just a line to say how much I appreciate the help that you have given to the unfortunate people both of Sharjah and of Dubai, Ajman, Hint and Khan, by carrying out vaccination* I am sure that the Shaikhs and thei^ people are most grateful fo’r all tliat you have done fo v ‘ them and 1 am glad to hear ths-t the epidemic seems gradually to be subsiding. 3* It would be useful if you would kindly let me have a bHei account of your work, mentioning especially the numbers of vaccinat cabled out at each place, 'ind whether you found any difference in the results obtained fn&gt;ra the vaccine received f^om Basrcdi and from Karachi* 3. fhere is a small point which I must mention in connection with this work - I should bo glad if on any future occasion you would telegraph to me to find out if there i s any objection, before you engage in any activity :u,,a as this outside the Airways Station area* . l.C. Janes, ^srpAire, Imperial Airways Station, Sharjah* ij /i .1* /h-t * V59S-,i/l4 lot The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:—-- 1* The hbroign Lecnsta^ bo the Grovemrauut oi Inoia # Hew 2* rhe Honour ble the politic ! T&amp;aidant in the Persian Gruii, Buehi^* 3. Thu Air* Oificu^uommaadiii^, BHfcishruorces in Head^uaH ~s, Ilinaidi* and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gule. Dated...jjy|j|..j^j^ Pho Honourable the political losident f s mer.iorr.auun dr.tod tlio 13th Pel&gt;ni&amp;ry 1936# Reference to previous correspond Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Demi-oiiiciai letter Ho.396-2/14 dated the 26th rubmary to •«»G. Jraiue, — Imperial Airways station. the 26tli rebruary 19tk; to •&lt;•0. Janus I prucial Coast* aailpox on the \Translation of letter wo. 168 dated the 3rd march 1936 from i^han bahib nil sain bin nasan Arnad, m charge current duties of the Kesidency Agent, bhagah, to the Political iigent, Bahrain. After compliments Keference my letter wo. 112 dated the 23rd i&gt;’ e bruary 1936. i beg to inform you that oattur, the vaccinator, has finished vaccination work in the other towns and the vaccine has not come from Karachi, rlease let me know whether oattur may now return to nahrain. usual ending.Telegram Telegram Enclair, From Political Agent, Bahram, To Health Officer, Karachi, Repeated Residency Agent, Sharjah, No. 82 Dated the 7th March 1936. Plea&amp;e send urgently to Residency Agent Sharjah by airways one thousand doses smallpox vaccine and send bill to Political Agent, Bahrain. POLITICAL.mmm Telegram En Clai^. F^om Political Agent, Bahrain. To Khan Sahib Husain bin Hasan: jAmad c/o Imperial Ainmys,Sha^j ah. No. 84 Dated 8th Marsh 1936. ^ You-^ letter 168 of thin! Ma^ch. Sattu-^ should proceed again to Rasal Khaimah and aftarwar*ds Dubai when vaccine onie^ed in my teleg vc am 8^ of seventh has been -received aaa please telegraph to me directly vaccine can be stopped aaa please acknowledge. -political-Printed ir FromJ . / ’’V^Ju ^ O / vrT. *..^ %. . gi^ Translation of letter imq. 177 dated the 8th j^arch 1936 from K an sahib nusain bin Hasan ‘Amadj ± n charge current duties of the Kesidency Agent, bharjah, to the Political Agent,Bahrain. After Compliments. i enclose a statement showing the number of cases and deaths by smallpox on the frucial coast from fnd to 8th Jiaroh 1936. ihe number of those who have been cured i s also shown. i have received a repitition of your telegram no.82 dated 7th March 1936 addressed to the wealth Officer,Karachi. Usual ending. y i K 'G.T.CODE. Political Agent, Bahrain. Secretary to Resident, Bushire. Senior Officer, Persian Gulf,H.M.S. Powey, with the request that he will please give Political Resident copy. Air Officer Cdmmanding, Hinaidi. Dated 10th Marchl936. Smallpox week ending 8th March Sharjah 7 and 3 Kira 1 and 3 Ras al Khaimah 50 and 12 cases and deaths. Dv/hai 8 deaths. - POLITICAL TELEGRAM F rom T6 Repeated No. 86 r .—Confident; iai. &amp; d D.0.NO.75S-2/14 18th f.'a-ch 1230. daled the 24th December 1935, as a njsuit oi which you kindly sent down a supply oi vaccine fo~ saallpox* njpoHed to me that the vaccine has given poo~ tactions and an high p-opoHion ol no reactions, as compared with those given by vaccine obtained i'*om Ka-^iohi, though used unde** simila** conditions and by the same vaccinators* I am letting you kno^ of this not, I am sure you will understand, in any spirit of criticism, but in case the information may be of use to you* I mu w**iting now to say that it has been Doctor fhomas fhr^fnn M rj nw *.B. Ch. B. ^*i* D * U • , Su^eon and L'edical Officer, poH; of Basrtdi. # “ public fiealtn Oificer f B- srah, fTELEGRAM - G.T.CODE. Prom - Political Agent, Bahrain. To — Secretary to the Honourable the Political Redident, Bushire. Repeated Air Officer Commanding, f Iraq Command Hinaidi Senior Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S.FOW! No. - 94. Dated - 18th March 1936. Smallpox week ending 15th March Dubai 2 deaths Hira 1 case Has al Khaimah 15 cases and 4 deaths. % POLITICAL - \— t? TELEGRAM Prom. To No . Dated ENCIAIR. Political Agent, Bahrain, Khan Sahib Hussain C/o Imperial Airways Limited, Sharjah, 95. 19th March 1936, Please telegraph whether Sattur still at Ras al Khaimah and v/hether he has vaccine. POLITICALPrintedNo.793-2/14 / Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21st Ma-ch 1936, To The Sec-’*eta*y i;o the Honoumble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushi^e. Bxpenditu^ incu^-^d in connection with the s mallpox epidemic on the Tmcial Coast (15UG) * Memorandum. With ^fe-^ence to the fi-^st pa-ag^-aph of you-^ telegram Wo.1053 dated the 31st December 1935 •regaling smallpox epidemic on the Tmcial Coast, as it was impossible to spa^e the Compounder from Bahrain and as,the Bahrain Government had no vacc incat or available, an arrangement was made for* a local vaccinator to go. 2. A statement is attached showing the expenditure *V-«&gt; *** incurred and I revest that the amount may be refunded. L Captain, for Political Agent, Bah-ain,7 10-1-36. 25-1-36. 30-1-36. 4-2-36. 10-2-36. 25-2-36. STATEMENT SH0 v XNO THE EXPENDITURE INCURRED IN CONNECTION ' ITH THE SMALLPOX EPIDEMIC ON THE TRUCIAL COAST (1936) Air paeeage from Bahrain to Sharjah to the vaccinator Advance of Pay to the Vaccinator &gt; Oott of Vaccine from Karachi Re. 72-0-0 ft 50-0-0 ” 161-4-0 ” ” M « 31-11-0 Launch hire to take Vaccinator to Raa al %eimah 70-0-0 Cost of Vaccine from Karachi 126-5-0 Total Re. 511-4-0 further Charges (approximate) Coet of vaccine from Karachi Balance of Pay of Vaccinator V;.V* Note ! - The Vaccinator wat promised Re. 100/- for the trip provided the time aid not exceed one month. For the extra time, it ie hoped to arrange with him for He. 50/- a month. Cost of deck passage with food from Sharjah to Bahrain .... 1 . Rb. 125—0—0 R-a-o N.B . Vouchers will be forwarded if required. -- • - . - *vI shall he greatfull if yon will kindly send a sum of Hr 10/__ f Rupees Ten Only ) to my family hy Yusuf S*ater who is employing in Moharra% Custom. The said amount is accepted to deduct from' my salary;. Thanking you yerey ranch, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Moharaed oat nr —y/&gt;+ TELEGRAM - ENCLAIR. Prom - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Residency Agent, Sharjah. No. - 102. Dated - 24th March 1936. Please expedite report on smallpox week ending 22nd March. - POLITICALTELEGRAM G.T. CODE. Prom Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushi^e. Repeated Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi. Senior Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S.Fowey No. 104. Dated 25th March 1936. Smallpox week ending 22nd March Has al Khaimah four cases and three deaths. - POLITICAL - / *TELEGRAM From To G.T.CODE. Political Agent, Bahtin. Pol it teal Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushi• Repeated - Air Officer Commanding, R.A*F. Hiuaidi. Copy given to - Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gmlf Sho^eham. No. - 108. Dated - 29th March 1936. Smallpox week ending 29th March Dubai 6 Sharjah 2 Ras al Khaimah 10 deaths. - POLITICAL - (No - 872-2/14 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:—&gt; fhe Senior Naval Office^ Persian Gulf Division E*M*S* ShO'-ehsjn JUPAin. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated. 28Lth .M&amp;2S&amp; . 1v13.Ga ... Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. feleg^am No*108 dated the 29th Ma^ch 1936 f-om the Political Agent, Bahrain, uO the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Smallpox on the i^cial Coast.Dh. H. P. BILIMORIa, I..M. &amp; a., B.HY., d.p.h. (London) Health Officer /5f MUNICIPAL corporation, KARACHI. ^“*March 1936 To, Sir, I have the honour to enclose herein a hill amounting to Rs 50/- on account of 40 tubes of Vaccine Lymph ; 'to the Residency Agency, Sharjah in response to the telegram dated 7.3.36. I therefore rquest you to kindly remit the amount to this office at an early date. I have the honour to he. Sir, Your most obedient servant.4P1 Memorandum : Expenditure incurred in connection with the smallpox epidemic on the Trucial Coast, /M 50 Reference your memorandum No, 793-2/14 dated the 21st March 1936. 2. The expenditure should have been included in your report of anticipated excesses and savings in the budget appropriations for 1935-36, due to reach this office by February 5th. As this was not done, the necessary pro vision could not be made in the budget for 1935-36, In the circumstances, the charges should be adjusted tem porarily against your Office Allowance grant for 1936-37. 3, Please report the total expenditure actually in curred and expected to be incurred in connection with the smallpox epidemic, so that steps can be taken to obtain the necessary provision in the budget for 1936-37. The proper head of account under which the expenditure should be readjusted will be intimated to you in due course.lelegram. Enclair. From - - Hussain, Sharjah. t 0 - Political, Bahrain. Ho. - HiI. Bated - 9th received 10th April 1956. Your telegram. 84 of 8th March. Sattur has completed at has-al-xthaimaj:i t-me vaccine had received from Karachi ordered in your tele^ra 82 of 7th March and now returned to Sharjah. Duhai not necessary at present. Ho cases and deaths this weeh ending 5th April. Only Ras-al-Khaminah 2, 1. Hussein. Telegram. Enelair. Prom - Politic Laj 1, Bahrain To - Residency Agent| Sharjah. Ho. - Bated 115 fa^L 11th MertWti x9oo . Your telegram &amp;&amp; dated 9th '***#&amp;&gt;• ' Return Sattur hy next available steamer. Political.■ : n IS? Telegram. G.T.C. Prom - Political, Bahrain. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated - Air Officer Commanding, Rinaldi. jhi \ / No. Senior Naval Officer,Persian Gulf H.M.S.Shoreham. - 114. Dated - 11th April 1934. / Smallpox weelc ending 5th April itas-al- Khaimah Two eases and one death.y 86-2/14 No. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:—• The Soc^ta^y to the Honourable the politicaj. riesident in the Persian Bushido. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). \ The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gdle. Dated... .]£. ApHL • 1936 v ■ Reference to previous correspondence : /&gt; t V) !,:erao'-andum Ko.723 dated the 21st Ma^h 1136. Description of Enclosure.Deferred Foreign Telegram. lj ordinary, 'arachi, dated 50tii March 1936 political Agent, • — ReSftK.S^V,. Bahrein. w “Karachi Bhafi o^ iiealth declared Karachi free from plague from twenty eighth March'. “quarantine ^. No. » ^ J of 1936. Port Health oiTpeer^Kiamari. Karachi, dated ^ | March 1936. Copy posted in confimation :.B.B.S., Health Officer of the Fort, Karachi. To, The Political Agent, . Bahrein.(w) jljb cjp Ho« of 1355 Office'of tba Adviser to the Government, Baiirain. Dai e d, M&amp;haraa 17, April-S,.-JL936. 1 X xJiJ'.J The Medical Officer, Bahrain. Memorandum: ** The Manamah and Mijharraq Baladiyas have asked lae to request you to appoint one day in every week for vaccinating. They say that the people regard vaccination, by you, y oursel f, as being more effective than vaccination by any of your assistants and they ask that you should appoint one day a ween for this. As regards Muharraq, I think myself that Dr. Bundarkar could satisfactorily, but carry out this work if you could spare the time it might be a good plan if you could inaugurate the proceedings at Muharraq. Both Baladiyas agree to take measures for reporting all cases of small pox to you and they are issuing an alaan on tnis subject once. Sd/ G. Dairy mple Belgrave. Advisor to the Government.I it me d late. Dr. I understand that smallpox has become or is becoming epidemic in Muharraq. Will you kindly let me know if you have any information about it and also whether the disease is sufficiently widespread to make it necessary for us to notify the Resident that smallpox is epidemic in ^uharraq. S. Are there any signs of it elsewhere? Holmes. 7 . 4 .'' 936 . P#litissil Agomt. There kave cases of SMall-pex in M&amp;karraq fr®F tke last three I do mot tkiak that there kas beem a great imerease tke muisker. of eases recently,hut tke death of ©f ©me *f tke A 1 Khalifa from tke disease Bay kave led t© people talking about Small-pax more, Tke Resident may be inf armed* There are ©eeassisnal reports of tke disease frtm tke villages. I fekeive m© official reports fr©B tke G«vt: ®f lakraia. 7.4.3^s dwt' 'rrh.tMajor Rooney will be coming over either on the mail arriving here about the 12th or the 19th ^pril. Please have the draft list of instruments ready by the time he comes so that you can consult him on the choice. 2. Please also have the papers ready so that you can shoi/v him the repairs that are being done to the Hospital. Dr. Holmes. 11.4.1936. Ajv.\?A — ^ cfcybb^yyy \ L-^i \ 3^t£&gt; fe 2 j ^ ^ &gt;^c^C^3Sut^ \ L^Wi.U\ Translation of letter no.254 ciateu the 14th April 193- from K.^. Husain bin Hasan T ^mau, xn charge current auties of the Residency Agent, Sharjah, to the Political -gent, Bahrain. y After Compliments. With reference to your letter ^5.350-2/14 eaten tne February 1936 regareing the wooden cases in which vaccine was sent to me, 1 beg to inform you that I nave been able to collect 86 cases only which I sent to you by the hand of Sattur. i could not get the others which were despatched to Baraimi at the request of the shaikhs npr those which were sent to the places in which Trucial people were living. Usual ending.I'm J Translation of letter No.255 oaten the 14th April 133o irom Khan Sahib Husain bin Hasan the Residency Agent, Sharjah, After compliments. I beg to inform you that when niunaB arrived at the irucial Coast he started vaccinating the people at Ras al Khaimah, bmm el (^aiwain , Himriyah, T Ajman, Hira ana Sharjah. All the Shaikns ana the people of these towns became very grateful to the (British; Government ana to you for the help which you afforded to them ana which savea the lives of their subjects from the aanger of smallpox. The Shaikhs and the people are also grateful to Sattur, the vaccinator, for carrying out the work in a most satisfactorily manner and for his valuable efforts which met their satisfactior 2. | \IA Sattur, the vaccinator, informed me of your jyt telegram No.115 aated the 12th April 193B instructing him to proceed to Bahrain by steamer. Sattur, however, showed me the aeroplane ticket for the return journey to Bahrain, he is coming to you. Usual ending.U^fe^^t3-db^ 2^. ^ 6C&gt; A\cAaS^\1&gt;1jv &gt;^^3 U ^csw^y &gt;V^-A^-si l^b Translation of letter ^0.284 dated the 29th April 1938 from K.S.Husain bin Hasan f Amad. in charge current duties of the Residency Agent, Sharjah, to the Political ^gent, hadrain. After compliments. Reference my letter No.255 aated the 14th April 1936* 2. After the departure of Sattur from Sharjah by aeroplane, the Superintendent of the Rest House at Sharjah informed me that the ticket which Sattur had was not available for the return journey ana that, therefore, I should pay a sum of Rs.72/- • On the 22nd April 1938, I paid Rs.72/- to the Superintendent of the Al est House whose receipt is enclosed tor your perusal. / . 3. It is request^hat you may kindly remit to me this amount for which i beg to thank you. Usual Ending.Ho.1185-2/14 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th May 1936 To '/ i The Secretary to the 1 ;'f ; • •, Honourable the Political Resident Memorandum* Reference your memorandum Ho.731 dated the 31st March 1936 V\ 2. I am enclosing a complete and final statement totalling Rs.935/- (Rupees Nine hundred and thirty five) only, for the expenditure incurred in connection with the smallpox epidemic on the Trucial Coast. 3. This sum will be charged temporarily against this Office Allowance grant for 1936-37 for the month of May 1936. • '/ d ■ i 4. Regarding the item for Rs.72/- on account of V A ( \ return air passage. The Residency Agent, Sharjah, was V instructed to arrange a return passage by sea but owing to lack of sufficient care he arranged the return by ' \ air by mistake. / A .id f \ \ \ ■ \ A \ Captain, ji for Political Agent, Bahrain. Yv / 'v ASTATEMENT SHOWING THE EXPENDITURE INCURRED IN CONNECTION WITH THE SMALLPOX EPIDEMIC ON THE TRUCIAL COAST (1956) Air passage from Bahrain to Sharjah to the Vaccinator Cost of Vaccine from Karachi 'j Rs. 72-0-0 ” 161-4-0 ■X If ff ft ” 31-11- Launch hire to take Vaccinator to Ras al Khaimah \ 70-0-0 Cost of vaccine from Karachi f A 126-5-0 ; M; ft if if ?»jS 50-9-0 !W Pay of Vaccinator for 3A months @ ^.lOOZ-p.m. H 350-0-0 Air passage from Sharjah to Bahrain to the Vaccinator ” 72-0-0 Postage on empty wooden boxes of vaccine j returned to Karachi ' fC 1-3-0 —j . ! 935-0-0 Total RsThis receipt will be merely evidence of payment of the money ORIGINAL KARACHI MUNICIPAL CORPORATION. CHALAN (Head Office). To the Municipal Accountant. Sir —Please receive the amount as noted below for credit to the Budget Head as specified hereunder: This receipt is not v^lid unless counteisigned by the Municipal Accountant who is in change of the Municipal Treasury.This receipt will be merely evidence ol payment of the moI his receipt will be merely evidence of payment of the mo‘i'elegram.Gr.T.G. From - Brit consul, Bushire. To - Political, Bahrain* No. - 359. Dated - 7th May 1936. ' V, ^ f My telegram No.28, January 7th. f r \ last report received v/as your telegram Ko.114, April 11th. . continue weeky telegraphic report till further instructions. Brit consul. Pt .4ju- The telegram is hadly mutillated. I have asked Telegraphs for repit it ion.Telegram - From - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Re sidene y Agent, Sharj ah. Repeated - Political Resident, Bushire reference his tel*3oy of Fo: 134 May* \ \ t fr Dated - 9th May 1936. fl) Your telegram of 9th A^ril Smallpox aaa Report telegraphically if there are further cases and deaths. In future continue sending weekly telegraphic report on Sundays until further instructions. Political-Telegram. G.T.C From - Political, Bahrain. To - Britconsul, Bushire. No. 137. Dated the 11th May 1936. My telegram No*134 dated 9th May» No cases and deaths in Trucial Coast since 9th April. PoliticalT '—~—- Telegram From To No. G.T.C. Political ^ Buehire, Political Agent, Bahrain, 577 Dated and received 14th May 1936. Trucial Coast free of smallpox. Please discontinue weekly reports. •) BRITCONSUL. P.A. N.S. Abdur Razzaq who is proceeding by this mail to Sharjah he informed to discontinue weekly reports please.Hoi •r 2/14 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th May 1936. From The Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Health Officer, Municipal Corporation, Karachi• Sir, ■ , • TT • O iC 1 With reference to your letter Ho:H.9A/10/36, dated the 22nd January 1936, I have the honour to inform you that a parcel containing 88 wooden covers of lymph tubes lias been despatched to you by this mail. 2* The Residency Agent, Sharjah, informs me that he could not get all the empty wooden covers as they were lost in different Shaikhdoras on the Trucial Coast. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain. f'VTelegram, G.T.C. Prom - Political, Bahrain. To - Britconsul, Bushire. No. - 144. Dated the 18th May 1936. Following from Political Agent, Bahrain from Sharjah begins ' Infom Resident that 14 cases smallpox reported from R&amp;s-al-Khaimah May 17th” Ends. PoliticalTelegram. G-.T.C. From - Political Resident, Bus hire. ~ Political Agent, Bahrain. - 394. - 19th May 1936. I?? To No. Bated A Your telegram No.144 of May 13th. I have informed Air Officer Commanding and Senior Naval Officer. Please obtain confirmation and telegraph as soon as possible. Britconsul. Telegram. En clair. From - Political, Bahrain. Adaressed - Residency Agent, Sharjah. Repeated - Hickinbotham C/0 Warship Deptford. No. - 145. Dated - 2(J)th May 1936. Political Agent T s telegram May 18th reporting 14 cases smallpox at Ras-al-Khaimah May 17th Resident asks to obtain confirmation and telegraph as soon as possible. m R«A. Sharjah, repeated Hickinbotham c/0 Warship Deptford. Political.Telegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Political Resident, Bushire, Repeated Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi, Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf No. 149. Dated the 23rd May 1936. Your telegram No. 394. Following from Residency Agent, Sharjah. During last fortnight Ras al Khaimah town 3 Fahlain Uraibi and Shamal villages 11 cases no death and no fresh cases since five days. POLITICAL.Tmaslation of letter No*359 dated the 23rd May 1936 corresponding 2nd Rabial Awal 1355 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah to the Political Agent, Bahrain. the 20th May 1936, I have already sent a wire yesterday that saying/during the last two weeks there were 14 cases out of which 3 cases were in the town of Ras-al-Khaimah and 11 in Fahlin, ’Araibi and Sbamal - villages of Ras-al-Khaimah. There was no death during this period and at the same time no fresh case occurred during last five days. 2. The Shaikh of Ras-al-Khairnah has asked me to send him some vaccine if possible. H e wishes to keep it with him and give whoever wants to get vaccinated. If you consider it proper, please send me some medicine for After compliments With reference to your telegram No.145 dated vaccination in compliance with the request of the Shaikh Bsual -Sliding.Telegram Fr om To Repeated No. 2/l 4 G-.T.C. Political Resident, Bushire, Political Agent, Bahrain, Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi, 424 Dated and received 28th May 1936. ^0 Your telegram No. 149. Chief Quarantine Medical Officer, Arab Coast does not propose to declare Ras al Khaimah infected with smallpox. Britconsul' JTo. 1455-2/14 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 30th May 1936* To The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. sb! a Memorandum * Reference my memorandum Ho. 1185/2/14 dated the 6th May 1936. 2. The new Residency Agent, Sharjah, has incurred a further expenditure of Hs.40/- (Rupees forty only) on account of car hire to Ras-al-Khaimah to collect informa tion about the sniallpox. 3. I am remitting him Hs.40/- in settlement, but will you please let me know if the amount should be charged temporarily against this Office Allowance grant forTelegram* G.T.C Prom - Political, Bahrain, Addressed - Political Resident, Bushire, Repeated - Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi and Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. No. - 161. Dated - 5th June 1936. Following from Residency Agent Sharjah dated the 5th June begins ” Smallpox Sharjah two cases 0 Ends. &gt; Politicalo iTelegram From To Ho, Dated En Clair Political Agent, Bahrain. Residency Agent, Sharjah. 162 8th June 1936, Reference your telegram 5th June smallpox Please inform me at once if there are fresh cases. -Political'Printed i: From-v ' Printed in England. (Sept. 1935.) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED in ENGLAND) (Message Forms 5/-171.) From. '+ V a. O t* 0 2^0 No. of Words- JN... -Date /_ Time * ‘ ,—.— To ; ' ^ ” tZ K'K^r^ ’ : F** ' 'v ^ /'f :* Cl/ C - e b s S-- .a. F(w). MARK YOUR REPLY IS' No enquiry respecting this Telegram can be attended to without the production of this Copy.' \» ’ 2t‘Z) Telegram G.T.C. Prom Political Agent, Bahrain, To Political Pesident, Bu&amp;hire, Repeated Air Officer Coam^rding, Hinaidi, Copy sent to Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, No. 173 Dated the 16th June 1936. Residency Agent Sharjah reports on June 15th smallpox Sharjah one case. Dubai imported from diving banks two cases. POLITICAL.■ \V No. ~I7u2 o4 V ol Bated the /(^^June 1936 To The Politioal Agent, BAHRAIN. 'Jo. 145d'‘2/l4 dated Heference your letter No the 30th May 1936. 2. The expenditure of Bs. 40/- inourred hy the Besidenoy Agent, Sharjah, on account of car hire to Ras-al-Bhaimah should he debited to this Residency and included in your monthly advance statement. The payee’s receipt should he obtained from the Residency Agent, Sharjah, and forwarded to this office in support of the charge. By Order, Secretary to the Poli^Bdal Resident in the Persian Gulf. I,rom * Hon^Xe the Political Kesideot in the Persian anIf* To * The Foreign secretary to th© Oovemmaat of 1 emorandiJiii ho* Bushire, Bated the ^ June Expenditure in connection with the smallpox epidemic on the Irucial Coast* .Uefereuce eorresponaenc© ending with this Residency’s endorseaent ho* 553/4/14S dated the 15th February l$3$. 2m A total expenditure of Bis* 955A was in* curred by the Political Agent* Bahrain* on account of the cost of vaccine and the pay and travelling expenses of the vaccinator employed in connection with the recent smallpox epidemic on th© fruoi&amp;l Coast* 5* In the absence of any specific provision in the Budget to meet these charges, the Political Agent, Bahrain, has been instructed to debit th© expenditure to his Office Allowance grant for the current year. /The extra expenditure will be met* as far as possible* \by re-appropriation from probable savings in the current year’s budget of this Residency* and proposals in this connection will be submitted to the Government of India when the financial position is reviewed in November next Ompy Sent ToJ?Z*~*T ^ Sd.) C. C. L, for lolltioal Resident In the Persia” O-ulf.i No * 1805-2/14. 7ti~’ Political Agency, Bahrain the 9th July 1936. 110 To The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire• Memorandum. / Reference youjr* memorandum No. 1230/4/142 dated the 14th June 1936. 2. A receipt for Rs.40/- is enclosed as desired. for Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain.TELEGRAM - G.T. Code. Prom - Political Agent,Bahrain. To - Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated No. 267. Air Officer Commanding,Hinaidi. Senior Naval Officer, H.M.S. Shoreham Dated the 29th August 1936. Residency Agent, Sharjah reports on 29th August smallpox Sharjah one case Dubai one case. POLITICALPrinted in ! Front- No. of ToTELEGRAM Prom To Repeated G. T. CODE. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushice. Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi. Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, H. M.S. Shoreham. No. 279. Dated the 31st August 1936. Residency Agent, Sharjah reports on 30th August smallpox Ajman 3 cases. POLITICALLetter aated the 11th Jarnadial Than! 1355 (29.8.35) from Shaikh Rashia bin Humaia, Ruler of jijnian to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments. \ My object of writing this is to inform you that iksii I want meeicine for vaccination against smallpox. 1 hope that you will send me ten bottles. u sual uncling. !it, Telegram G.T.G. Prom Residency Agent, Sharjah, To Political Agent, Bahrain, No. 585 Dated and received 8th Sentember 1956. 9/ n m in Your letter No. 2272. Brother of Shaikh Said would not be prepared to go to Ajman where Shaikh and two others were trained by Janes. Please inform me if I can issue to Shaikh. Ajman ten cases and one death. Telegram G.T.C. Prom To No. 308 Dated the 8th September 1936. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, Residency Agent, Sharjah, Issue all vaccine to Ajman. PoliticalG.T.C Telegram G.T.G. From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Political Resident, Buehire, Repeated Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi, Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, No. 309 Dated the 8th September 1936. Residency Agent reports Ajman ten cases of smallpox and one death.Telegram From G.T.C. \ Political Resident, Bushire, fpo Political Agent, Bahrain, No. 628 Dated the 10th September 1936. My telegram No. 629. Residency Agent should arrange isolation of Rest house and aerodrome with Shaikh and Station Superint enden t. BRITCONStJL. I /TELEGRAM G.T. CODE. Prom - Political Resident, Bushire. To - Political Agent, Bahrain. No. — 629. Dated 10th(received 11th) September 1936. Sharjah Trucial Coast infected with smallpox 8th September?, Sharjah 10 cases 1 death aerodrome Sharjah being isolated. - BRITCONSUL -G.T.C. 2/14 Telegram Fr om To No. Dated the Political Agent, Residency Agent, Bahrain, Sharjah, 315 11th September 1936. Arrange with Shaikh and Station Superintendent for isolation of rest house and aerodrome from smallpox infection. Political.Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Bushire, To Political Agent, Bahrain, No. 660 Datedlthe 21st September 1936. Please wire number of cases and deaths of smallpox at Sharjah Trucial Coast for the week ending 19th September and send similar weekly reports until further instructed. Britconsul. Telegram From To No. Dated the G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain, Residency Agent, Sharjah, 539 22nd September 1936. Please wire number o^ cases and deaths of smallpox at Sharjah Trucial Coast for week ending 19th September. Similar weekly reports should be submitted until further orders. POLITICAL^ ^ ^ 5,'; * Telegram From To No. Dated the G.T.G. Political Resident, Bushire, Political Agent, Bahrain, 667 22nd September 1936. vaccination / o Your telegram No. 309 of September 8th. Please telegraph whether arrangements for desirable and if so what you propose. Britconsul.&amp;) ,4 * * ❖ ❖ Telegram G.T.C. Prom Political Agent, Bahrain, To Political Resident, Bushire, Repeated Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi, Senior Naval Officer, H.M.S. Shoreham, No. 343 Dated the 23rd September 1936. To Political Resident only . Your telegram b60. Residency Agent reports no further cases or deaths after those reported in my telegram No. 309 September Rth. POLITICAL.TELEGRAM # I.W. CODE. Prom To No. Dated Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. 344. 23rd September^.1936. V* Your telegram 667 of 22nd September. Propose that I send 20 tubes of vaccine (sufficient for 200 persons) to Residency Agent by Sunday f s air mail and that you replace these for us. Consider it desirable that Residency Agent should have vaccine available as Shaikh of Ajman recently applied for vaccination of his own free will, and there are several vaccinators trained by Holmes on the Trucial Coast. POLITICALTelegram Prom To No. G.T.G. Political Resident, Bushire, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, 679 Dated the 25th September 1956. Your telegram No. 344. Your proposal approved. Please arrange with Political Agent Karachi to replenish your supply. /y* Rritconsul.$ $ $ $ Telegram From To No. Dated the Enc la ir, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, Captain Hickinbotham, Karachi, 553 26th September 1936. IMMEDIATE . Please bring 20 tubes of smallpox vaccine. POLITICAL.I itrf®;. — fir“- Telegram O-.T.G. From Residency Agent, Sharjah, To Political Agent, Bahrain, No. 651 Dated the 27th September 1936. 4'1 Weekispp* ending September 26th smallpox nil, ■4wTELEGRAM - G.T.CODE. From - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated - Senior Naval Officer, H.M.S. Shoreham Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi. No. - 362. Dated — 28th September 1936. Smallpox. Residency Agent Sharjah 1 s report for week ending 26th September is nil. - POLITICAL -Telegram From To Repeated No. ■^ated the G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Resident, fiushire, Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi, Senior Naval Officer, H.M.S. Shoreham, 385 7th October 1936. Smallpox Trucial Coast week ending 4th October Nil. Political. ^ — ■PrintedTelegram G.T.C. From Political '’esident, Puehire, To Political Agent, Bahrain, No. 721 Dated the 12th October 1936. h' My telegram No. 629 of 10th September. Shar^ah^Trucial Coast now free of smallpox Britconsul.Telegram From To Ho. 395. G.T.G. Political Agent, Bahrain. Residency Agent, Sharjah. Dated 12th October 1936. Your telegram Ho. 678. October.:12 th. Please discontinue reports. POLITICALTelegram From G.T.C. Residency Agent, Sharjah. Political Agent, Bahrain. Ho. 681. Dated 13th October 1S36. Your telegram Ho. 315 September 11th. Please inform me whether isolation of Rest-House should still continue. ABDURAZZAQ. Agent, Bahrain, Agent, Sharjah, Telegram From To Ho. Dated the 14th *#*$$$* G.T.C. Political Residency October 1936. Your telegram No. 681. NO. Polit ical.—' L„/H. P. BILIMORIA, l.m. &amp; s., b.hy„ d.p.h. (London) * Health Officer. *5 J ^ ICIPAL CORPORATION, KARACHI. &lt;J ^ OctoLer 1936 To, Sir, wo. g. The Political Age Behrein V' 7 With reference to your Telegram dated 26th September 1936 addressed to kr.Hickin Botham, I have the honour to inform you that 20 tubes containing 200 doses of vaccine lymph have been despatched to you by Air ^ail on the 29th ultimo. Bill amounting to &amp; 25/- at the rate of Ss 1-4&amp;-Q per tube is enclosed herein. I therefore request you to kindly remit this si amount at an early date end oblige. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant IfJealth Officertranslation of letter No.807 dated the 25th November 1936 from the -Residency Agent Sharjah, to the Political Agent Bahrain. Aft er Compliments. I beg to state for your information that on 20th November 1936 a case of small pox occurred at IXibai. •Usual Bn ding.Telegram rr.T.T. Prom Political Agent, Bahrain, To Political Resident, Bushire, Repeated Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi, Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, No. 472 Dated the 28th November 1936. Residency Agent Sharjah reports one case of at smallpox/Dubai November 20th. Polltical.Telegram QIC. From Political, Bahrain. To No.100 Britagent, Sharjah. Dated Dated 10th April, 1940. Dr. Holmes arrives by flying boat to-morrow. Please meet him. Tell Sheikh of Dubai to collect people for vaccination.No.101 Dated 10th March, 1940. Can you borrow or purchase 5000 doses smallpox vaccine and send by air mail to Station Superintendent is Sharjah. This/urgently required as there is beginning of smallpox outbreak at Dubai.'To.697-2/14 Political Agency| ^hrain* 10th April, 1940 To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government iiahrain * Memorandum * The Hesidency Agent, Sharjah, Informs me that there have been six case? of small-pox in Dubai* Dr. Holmes is proceeding by air to-morrow to investigate and carry out vaccinations. for Political Agent, Bahrain 'Telegram From GTC. Political, Bahrain. To Britagent, Sharjah. No.105 Dated 11th April, 1940. 25 tubes vaccine arriving by air to-morrow for Dr. Holmes.L Telegram En Clair. From Britconsul, Basra. To Political, Muscat. Unnumbered. Dated 11th April, 1940. Vaccine left Basra by air today. Much regret consigned you in error© &amp;&gt; Telegram GTC* From Britconsul, Bushire. To Political, Bahrain. No. A 149. Dated the 13th April, 1940. Your telegram No.102 April 11th. Please ask Holmes to report by telegram progress of outbreak0.0 .No.708/2/14 Oated the 13th April, 1940 Very many thanks far your aid over the vaccine question. It vias extremely good of you to send it so very promptly and I hope it did not earn you too many grey hairsl 2. I expect I sliall hear* shortly from you whether it is to be replaced or paid for. Yours sincerely, I' /' Wolatan /eld-Forester, Esquire, Kis Majesty*s Consul, / Basra* lb!Telegram GTC From Political, Bahrain. To Britagent, Sharjah. No.108 Dated 13th April, 1940. Following for Dr. Holmewe: Begins r *P}eas= report by telegram (reporting to Bushire) progress of small-pox outbreak ,r Ends.Telegram GTC. From Britagent, Sharjah. To Political, %hrain. No.239 Dated 14th April, 1940. f Addressed Bahrain, repeated to Bushire. Your telegram No.108 April 13th. Following from Dr. Holmes begins r *No fresh case reported in Dubai. Two cases in Khan. All classes are sucked vaccination , i Ends.* Telegram GTC From Britconsul, Bushire. To Political, Bahrain. No. A154 Dated 16th April, 1940. Addressed to Sharja, .repeated to Bahrain Your telegram No.239 April 14th. Please report any signs of spreading of small-pox immediately.Telegram. Code. G.T.C. From. Political, Bahra in To. Britagent, Sharjah No. 115. Dated. 16-4-40. Your telegram 239. Please repeat last five groupstelegram From To G.T.C. - Residency Agent, Sharjah. Political Agent, Bahrain. No- 215 Dated(and received) 17th April 1940. / Your telegram No.115 dated April 16th. All classes are sucked vaccination. BRITAGENT//y/. Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain,Persian Gulf, 18th: April 1940# To. H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I heg to forward a statement on my receit visit to Sharjah and Dubai,in connection with the outbreak of small-pox there. I arrived Sharjah on the 11th: and left on the 17th:April. I carried out vaccinations morning and evening from the 11th: to the 16th: April.All cases offering,including those with good previous marks,were vaccinated. Others vaccinated were Employees of the British Overseas Air Corp: their wives and families. Employees of the Anglo-Tran Oil Co: Employees of the British Air Ministry. The Port Guard. The Shaikh of Sharjah f s servants and guards. In all 837 vaccination were done in Sharjah,and 1386 in Dubai, giving a total of 2223. The surplus vaccine was distributed to the Govt: Hospital,the British Agent,the Shaikh of Sharjah and Shaikhs Said,Juma and Rashid of Dubai. There were 4 cases of small-pox and 9 contacts in the isolation camp.These cases had contracted the disease about 22 days before I visited the camp on the 15th: April.The contacts were vaccinated. A report that two cases had occurred in Khan proved to be false. The vaccine from Busra was badly packed and arrived with 9 tubes broken and three empty. About twenty two days having elapsed since the last fresh case I see no cause d&gt;f anxiety of any epidemic starting now. The first cases appear to have been from among pilgrims retunnning from the Hadj. t- L' c I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant cer&lt; Quarantine Medi / Copy forwarded to the Hon'ble the P.R. Bushire under p ' L i NO. 764-2/14 dated the 18th April, 1940. r i 1C/ jtfo.243-28/1. TO The Memorandum Reference telegram No .A 154 dated the 15th April 1940 from the Honourable the Political Resident on the subject of Smallpox. 2. I beg to inform you that as soon as I heard about the smallpox in Dubai I asked the shaikh and he said that there was none. I did not rely on his information but made enquiries myself and telegraphed to you immediately I dis covered the cases. 3. Pew days ago 1 heard that there were few cases of smallpox in Abu Dhabi brought by arrivals from Haj j and informed Doctor Holmes. All the rest of the Trucial Coast is free from smallpox at present. i-X&lt; 4Lt No. '77^ British Consulate D. y f i 1st May, 1940 Basra Your letter No.708/2/14 of the 15th April last regarding vaccine. Thornton, the Port Health Officer, from whose department the vaccine was obtained, tells me that he would prefer it to be renlaced rather than paid for. Will you therefore kindly arrange for a similar quantity to be sent to me for transmission to the Port health Benartment ? The following incidental exoenses were incurred by this Consulate in connexion 11-4-40. Telegram to Bahrain ID.Pil rerouting desnatch 855 19-4-40. Freight &amp; clearance fee - Imperial Airways 250 ID.1-085 Will you please let me have a refund at your with the desnatch of the vaccine :- The relevant vouchers are attached &amp;// early convenience?— -—6&amp;&gt; INVOICE BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION. (Incorporated in England.) Teleplione : Office 06.385 BASRAH Stn. Sup&lt;It. ResitJence 06.357 Engineering 06 ' 25 «Hi s Britannic Majesty's consul, BASRAH. 15 th April 1940. No._ B/37# Clearence agency fee on one parcel twenty five tubes Vaccine, Basrah- Bahrain, S.E. 236 , 11th April I 940 including Customs Forms and Revenue Stamps = 8* / OFFICIAL RE CEIPT, j Payment of this account will be acknowledged by issue of the Company’s official receipt : • kindly notify us should any other form of acknowledgment be proffered.INVOICE BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION. (Incorporated in England.) Telephone : Office 06.385 BASRAH Stn. Supdt:. Residence 06.357 Engineering 06.250 His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, BASRAH. ! No 11th April 1940 js/ji. 1KD3 £ s. d - Freight Charges# C/N# 382952 , One Parcel twenty five tubes Vaccine, Basrah- Bahrain, S.E. 236 , 11th April 1940, 0.080 Kgs# @ l/5d* per Kilo# 0 # 1 . Statistical fee 0 , 0 . 6 . / (One Shilling and Eleven Pence Only) (Original Copy of C/N.382952 attached) E.y&amp;^O. Excepted^- ' ^ 0 . 1 . H./ \ OFFICIAL RECEIPT.] Payment of this account will be acknowledged by issue of the Company’s official receipt : — -1 kindly notify us should any other form of acknowledgment be proffered.ol V r' \ HEGISTBHED AIR I^AIL , K®. *2/14 v/ / Political Agoncy, Bahmin. 9th May, 1940• From The Political Agent, BahraIn« To The Health Officer, ^ The Karachi Municipal Coi^oration, Sir, I have the honour to request that 25 tubes smallpox vaccine m^y kindly be supplied direct to His Majesty*s Consul, British Consulate, Baam - •Iraq, as early as possible* The cost will be met by me and it is •therefore requested that the bill should be addressed to the undersigned and not to His Majesty's Consul, Basra* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Political Agent, i3ahrain- $*!D.O.N©. ^ «*2/14 9th liSay, 1940* Please refer to your demi-official letter Po»779 to fir * ^eightimn# 2 * 1 have asicad tne Health ufficer t Karachi to supply you direct with ‘d&amp; tubes smallpox vaccine and trust these will reach you shortly* 3 * * nm erjeiosinr- a draft for I.D*1-083 to cover th. incidental charges incurred by yea. Would you please acknowledge receipt? 4* we are very grateful to you for ycur assistance in this matter* Yours sincerely, T© Wo Is tar; we Id-Fore c te r, ..squire, His Majesty*a Consul, ^SNTranslation of a letter No. 299 dated 1st May 1940 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah to the x olitical Agent, |alirain. After compliments, I request you to kindly issue orders for the remittance of Rs. 16/4 to me. This is the value of 5 tins of petrol used in the car which was put in the service of Dr. Holmes when he came to Sharjah^for vaccination on 11th April 1940. 1 also enclose a receipt six. for Rs. 2/- being the value of 2 bottles of spirit used in the hospital at Dubai and at Sharjah during vaccination. U.E.Received from 1.3. Sayid Abdul R&amp;za^ the sum of Rs* 2/- being value of 2 bottles of spirit. Sd. Muhammad bin Abdul 'abi, for Mirza Hasan &amp; Bros. 'No. -19/94 The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident presents his compliments to / The Political Agent, Bahrain, \ I I and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated Reference to previous correspondence : Bahrain memorandum No*979-2/14 dated the 15th May 1940* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Sanction Order No.34 dated the 25th May, 1940. Sanction for journey performed by air to Sharjah and back by Dr. R. Holmes, I.M.D., M.B.E.Sir, f ^ --J^iave the honour to acknowledge receint of a hank draft for the sum of ID.1-083 in full settlement of expenses incurred in connexion with the despatch of anti-smallpox vaccine to Sahrain. I have the honour to he. Sir, The Political Agent, Bahrain.* # 400—4-^0. F'O. H. ^ From, To, VVl MUNICIPAL CORPORATION, KARACHI. U /°1 24th Maynl940. Health Officer, KARACHI The Polidsioal Agent, B a hr in. Sir, With reference to your No; 916/2-14 dated 9th May 19 40, I have the honour to forward herewith a hill for Hs. 34-1-6 being the charges for 25 lymph tubes and postage, sent to His Majesty*s Consul, British Consulate, Basara-. Iraq on 14th May 19 40 and to request you to kindly remit the amount at an early da te. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant,Telegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain. Britconsul, Buahire. No. Bated the 24th December, 1941. yr 7 ’ Ledical Pj icer, Trucial Coast reports one severe case at Dubai oP smallpox imported Prom Kuwait 22nd December. Patient has been segregated and supply oP vaccine is being arranged. -Political7 7 Telegram G.T*C. From British Agent, Sharja* To Political Agent, Bahrain.(P.O.T.C?) No. 876. Bated the 23rd received the 24th December,1941. Medical Officer, Tracial Coast reports a severe case of smallpox has been imported from Kuwait yesterday morning* Patient has been segregated by Dubai authorities. Medical Officer requests Bushire may kindly be informed and arrange supply of 500 doses t smallpox vaccine by air mail until Dubai declared free from smallpox. -Britagent- The foregoing copy is forwarded to the the (Quarantine Medical Officer,. Bahrain, for information and suitable action? Bushire is being informed telegraphically as requested in the telegram. The Agency, Bahrain. The 24th December,1941. /^Political/Agent, Bahrain.POLITICAL AGEJTCY BAIIBAIK The 3x*t:l January, 1942# To The Superintendent of Vaccination, Karachi Municipal CoT*por*ation KARACHI. Sir I have the honour to request that you will kindly supply 500 doses of smallpox vaccine lymph to the Residency Agent, feudal ('oast, Sharja, as early as possible* The vaccine } suitably packed, should bo handed over to the Station Superintendent of the British Overseas Airways Corporation, Karachi, with the request that he ;ill have it delivered to the abevementior Officer. X \similar quantity my please be sent to the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, also through the Airways. Your bill for the cost will be paid when it is received. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant £ c frLrTfCJH. fce/YT /lAel&amp;AY/y 1 WmmmMS.74-2/14 of 1942 Political Agency, Bahrain. Tha 15th January,1942 To The Residency Agent HARtTA. i box containing 300 doses smallpox as soon as possible. Presumably this has been received. 2 * Please intimate me if and when a further supply is required. 2* i lease acknowledge receipt. al Agent, Bahrain. for Political AgentTelegram G*T.C. irr0m Brit consul, Bushire. 1,0 Po 1 it i cal, Bahrain. No, A/30 Dated 17th January, 1942, Please send oy the next opportunity enough calf lymph to vaccinate 300 persons against smallpox.''elegram From To Fo. 22 GTC. Political, Bahrain. Pritconsul, Bushire. Dated 20th January, 1942. Your telegram Fo .A.30. Vaccine for 200 persons being despatched by next up mail. Balance will follow on receipt of supply from Karachi.4 No.111-2/14 Political Agency, Bahrain. 19th January, 1942. From To The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Superintendent of Vaccination, Karachi Municipal Corporation, Karachi• Sir, I have the honour to request that you will kindly supply 500 doses of small pox lymph to this Agency as early as possible. The vaccine suitably packed should be handed over to the Station Superintendent of the British Overseas Airways f Corporation, Karachi, with the request that he/have it delivered to this office. A' I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Political Agent, ahrain. | IIm elegram GTC. From Political, Sharjah. Fo Political, Bahrain. TTo. 86 Bated 22nd January, 1942* Medical Officer, Trucial Coast reports urgent need for vaccination in Bubai• Ho lymph has arrived since January 12th and stock is now-exhausted. Grateful if you could expedite supply.CONDITIONS. 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose ; but in such case the amount paid for transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4 The aboye mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. N0T E~C°d e words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters, i he use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging, — ‘ ~ must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company 1 s Branches.' T'— Reference your memorandum No.74-2/14 dated LSth January 1942. 300 doses of smallpox vaccine lymph have been received. 500 doses were received from the Superintendent of Vaccination on the 12th January. 2. Reference paragraph 2 of your memorandum, please refer to my telegram No.876 dated 23rd December 1941 in which I forwarded the Medical Officer,Trueial Coast’s request for 500 doses of vaccine per week until Dubai is declaimed free from smallpox. The request still stands. I sent a telegram No.86 today re-affirm ing it. 2? Residency Agent,.Sharjah,TO PREVENT MISTAKES ATTENTION IS CALLED TO THE IMPORTANCE OF LEGIBLE WRITING. Priced in England, .mg. 1940. (23,200 pads.) No. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) , ' Charge. OFFICE STAMP AND DATE. Clerk’s Name, No. and Circuit and Time forwarded. Official Instructions No. Words Time Instructions to be Signalled. To Superintendent Vaccimtion runieipal Corpox^tion Address &amp;a nehi My telegram 28 January t^entyfourth stop Please despatchweekly by air five hundreddoses smallpox lymph to Hesid ncy Agent Sharjah until further instructions Political 35 No.191-2/14 Copy forwarded to the Residency Agent, Sharjah, for information with a request to inform this office telegraphically when Dubai is declared free from small-pox. I request that the above Telegram may be forwarded subject to the conditioni printed on hick of this term to no bound. Signature of Sender- Address (Not to be telegraphed) ..Telephone No.„„: .— ( —^ P.T.O.CONDITIONS. 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose ; but in such case the amount paid for transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. NOTE.—Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging, must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company's Branches.2 oo- 7-41 Zfl MUNICIPAL CORPORATION. KARACHI. Dr. H. K. SHAHANI, D.P.H. (London), Ag. Assistant Health Officer, Superintendent of Vaccination Registrar of Births &amp; Deaths. To, The Political Agent, Bahrain, (Persian Gulf). a' v Sir, / re:~ Simply of V accine' Lymph. With reference bo your iJotb/^/’/ dated instant and a telegrair dated 13 th instant, I have the honour to inform you that two parcels containing 500 doses each were sent on to Quorantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, and Residency Agent, Sharjah respectively, the receipt for which may please he acknowledged. The Bill amounting to Rs.133-7-0 for the same is sent herewith for an early payment please, Enel: 1 Bill. :- v ,*V w BM/- I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Superintendent of Vacc: ^Municipal Corporation Karachi..No. -2/14 of 1942. To Political Agency, BAHRAIN. The 10th February, 1942. TT'tr The Superintendent of Vaccination, Municipal Corporation, 'ARA- : riI. Sir, I have the honour to enclose a Bam Draft for Re.133/7/- (One hundred and thirtythree -/?/-) in payment of the bill received with your letter No.H.9A/2/42 for the vaccine lymph eupplied by you. Please acknowledge receipt. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient serve [K\ \ Bahra jAIR miL. . 2ftH ' # ' * &gt; ttefOLlflCAL ^GEr^Y, * K % . BAHREIN* -'* v ji/fit c t*~- j 3. To * ’ * URGJjTT. * The Superintendent Vp coin Depot Lehore. Sir, I hf ve the honour ta .request you to kindly despathh in the first instance 2000 doses £&gt;f small vaccine lymph addressed to the. Station Superintendent of the British Overseas /irways Corporation,Karachi, a. nd there a. f ter 500 doses weekly should be despatched to the above address until further instructions. The cost of the vaccine suppled will be remitted to you on receipt of your bill. I have etc.. For Political Agent, Bahrein. 1) Copy forwarded to the Station Superintendent,. British Overseas Airways Corporation,Kerscni, for information,with a' request that the vaeying, on receipt may please be despatched by airypBj the Residency Agent,Sharjah. 2) Copy to the Medical Officer,T.Coast,Sharjah,for information.DEPAR FMENT BRA SCH. Class for telegrams^ Draft L» tter } NLAND s immediate Expre ss ' Ordisary Memo -aadum Tel&lt; framT FOREIGN : ]S^ 0t Immediate Important Ordi nary Withoni priority To be issued on leaned ©a 'J'q 1st Remind a? * 1 # Snd Reminder # 3rd Reminder Heading : Case or Diary No. If post copy of telegram requirec Date of despatch of above List of enclosures Dated (Code word for telegrams.) S 5. MGIPC-—S2—1916 (S&amp;P) MFP- (M-i49! )-13-ll-40--60,00e PadsThis receipt will be merely evidence of payment of the moneyNo /2/14, Pphrein, The 25th Merch 1942. To The Superintendent Veccine •Sepst Lahore. Sir, I have the honour to invite your attention to my letter No.585/2/14,dated the 4th March 1942, end to rrvuiHjt whether the vaccine lymph ordered P&amp;e- has been supplied as direc' An kxe urgent reply will be greatly apprecia ted. I hvve the honour to b etc. /’• ^00 or Political Agent,BahreinBahrain (Persian G-ulf). Sir, Mo: H_ 7 l-T / of 1942 . Munrcl^al Office, Karachi, ^ 1Q4-2. Re: Vaccine Lymph Bill of Rs.155-5-0, I have the honour to invite your attention to this Office No: H.9A/13/42 dated fth February 1942 in connection with the above subject and to request you to please remit the amount of the above bill immediately so as to enable us to close the Accounts of the year. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Superintendent of Vaccination, Karachi Municipal Corporation. V 4 JSA.27/2.£ 2, 2/14 P r Politic?! Igcncy- Eehrein, The P4th Mprch 1942. To T^e Superintendent of Vrccinction Municipal Corporetion,K?r?chi. Subject:- V ?ccine Lymph Pill for &amp; 11:5-5-0. \p T h-ve the honour to refer to your letter No. H. 9 //I 0 ,doted the 4th Mrrch 1942,end to stote tte that your letter No.H.9^/12/42,dated the 7th *1 February 1942, together v dth the bill for 8s 135-5-0^ has not been received in this office. 2 1+' is therefore reauested that you will please send me a copy of th£t letter^together with the bill showing the details of vaccine lymph supplied. I have etc., h. For Political Agent,Bahrein.IU ' ^ &lt;^7 Stereo. A. D. P. H. (T. V.) No. 3 V Form No. 4. No. To u, i : 47 DPH—4,100—16-4-40-SQPP Lahore. Telegraphic Address—'* Vaccine. ” Foewards s \ tubes (one gramme each) of vaccine lymph sufficient for esses with 3 insertions each. The vaccine must be kept in a cool dark place and used as early after receipt as possible. I t should be shaken up well just before actual use. The result should be inspected about 7th day, and the return submitted at once t o the Superintendent, Punjab Vaccine Institute,- Lahore Murree No. of tube in series. D&lt;\te of despatch. Date of receipt. * Form of vacrinntion, primacy or revaccination. Date of use. Names of persons using the vaccine. Total number of persons vaccinat ed. Total number of inser tions originally made. Results op Inspection. (a) (6) XJ m d 9 to 00 « S'o cu-S 0 &gt; d N Ao. of persons with 1 vesicle. (d) («) to {9) a *» £ tn a 0 . to &lt;r 5 ® ’Sf d eo No. of persons w th 0 vesicle. | Unknown cases. Total number o' in sertions in unknown cases. Total number of suc cessful insertion.-’. ■’A Primary Revaccination . - — ( i ' - Piituary Revaccination .. — — Primary Revaccination .. Primary — Revaccination .-. — ■ - - Primary — Revaccination ._ I I 1 Primary /' Reva 9 cin. 1 tion u ~w £ Remarks. Ccn^ LM &lt;Xsia~^&lt;jz /t—^ -Cc2L V! i H To, The Political Agent, Bahrain, (Persian G-ulf), 0 No:H.9A/13 Of 19 1 12, Municipal Office, Karachi, 16th March 19^2, 12 .73 l£$ 1 Sir, 7 ' ?? - re:- Vaccine Lymph Bill of Rs.135~5~° « Reference this Office letter No:H. 9A/13/4-2 dated Ath ’.aarch 19 ^ 2 . Please expedite remittance of the amount of the above Bill at a very early date as the accounts of the year are to be closed. Please treat this as urgent. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ■ bm/- 16 / 3 . 1 Superintendent of Vaccination, Karachi Municipal Corporation.2°ez receipt. Telegraphic address- 'VACCINE”. Bill No.1020, dated 20.4.1942. The Political Agent, Bahrain (Persian Gulf) (Supplied to Station Superintendent, Br.Airways Corporation, Karachi)- Dr. To t he Punjab Vaccine In stitute. Lahore . _ March, 1942. 60 gramme tubes of V.L. @Re.l/ each. Add it i-enal. .. Rs.60-0 Additionalpostage for above ... 0-13 (Rs.sixty-/13/- only). i. ot al.. . Rs.60-13 Sd.Illegible, Superintendent, Punjab Vaccine Institute.No: R. of 194? 1 Municipal Office, I have th© honour to invite your attention to this Office No: H.9^/l3/^2 dated 2&gt;th April 19^2 in connection with the above subject and to request you to please arrange to remit the above amount immediately as the yearly accounts have to be closed. I have the honour to be, Q * v&gt; Jw' JL 1 p Your most obedient servant * 7 . *. rU jsa.27/4. Supdt. of Vaccination. \ \ VV K ! *■0 No: H. ^ f / / ^ 0 f 1942. Municipal Office, The Political Agent, Bahrain (Persian Gulf.) Kara ch y&gt;, 1942 . Sir, R £F??IX- j , / No (@ 6 5 \**Ys ^ Persian Re : Bill of Vaccln^^yi^&gt;hr ifgr Re.l^n/o/- I have the honour to acknowledge with thanks the receipt of a sum of Hs. 135 / 5 /-. being the charges for 1000 dozes of Vaccine lymph supplied to you. — .t The official/receipt No: Zh S J Dated //for the same is herewith enclosed. JSA. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 0.u.^U‘ V| Superintendent of Vaccination, Karachi Municipal Corporation.J deceived the mm tpecified on the reverse on- V.1 Signature of witness to be taken -when the pages is illi terate or not known to the post office, and in all cases when hatf- ment is made by a village post man or to a pardanashin lady on her own signature. ±2- Siynaiure of witness. Date %—•—— P-Tt.dovdov) .c; tt3*a. u v,. t-Vj r'C'JJAL 1 l0n i Karachi s IfP f fme/M'* if‘payee uumh-impressian yf paypfi. at/lOn X! H n &lt;’* k'f*' ’ ' The Post Office is not responsible for the payment of a money order to a person other than the rightful payee, if such wrong payment arises out of incorrectness or incompleteness of the name or address of the payee as written by the remitter. If the payee of a money order cannot be found, the amount of the order will be paid to fhe remitter. FOLD HF.RS* “FOLD HERH n tmvees of money orders. fTelegram From To No. 138 GTC. Political, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushire• Reference my telegram December 24th 1941. Medical Officer, Trucial Coast, Dubai, reports that Dubai is now declared free from small pox.ACKNOWLEDGMENT (INDIAN POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS DEPARTMENT.) Pu nja b Vacci ne Institute, naia. ' Xw- pf pawM-xne—isup. Sell ore, Punja An onu. nf or&amp;»r (*n figure*) Us — At. [in -r^.) Rupees six ty -/l5/-, and addrttt of the remitter (in full). ISam^stm^ of the office of issue. \3( -Poli tical Agent. Bahrai n. I f I'Z- FOLD lu Heceited /fie tJm specified on the reverse on Signature of witness to be taken when the payee it illi terate or not known to the post ohiee, and in all cases when pay ment is made by s, village post- pmn or to a pardanashin lads on her own signature. Data. Signature of witness Punjab Vaceige Institute Signature (t« snk) of payee or thumb-irip res si on of payee Tl:e Post Office is not responsible for tbs payment of a money order to a person other than the X'gbtful payee, if sncb wrong paj?n:enfc arises cut of incorrectness or incompleteness of the name or address of tbe payee as written by the remitter. If the payee of a money order cannot be found, the amount of the order will be paid to t!i» remoter.I Telegram Fpom To No,649 Dated 29th July, 1942* Political, Bahrain* Medical Officer, Trueial Coast, reports six small-pox cases at Dubai, one serious and five modified* He requests that Bus hire be informed and 500 doses of vaccine lymph supplied weekly till epidemic abates* No.1355-2/14, Political Agency,Bahrain. Copy forwarded for information to 1. 'Che Adviser to the ^cr/emment of Bahrain, Bahrain. 2. The Quarantine I’edical Of leer, Bahrain. for~^^!t^ tical Agent, Bahrain. i^Y rS' * &lt; ' 1- The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose; but in such case the amount paid for &gt; transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. NOTE.—Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging, must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company's Branches. CONDITIONS. m '9 the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the superintendent, Punjab Vaccine Institute, Lahore. Copy by post (Air ail) in. eonfiraation. 500 doses of small-pox vaccine lymph may kindly be despatched each week until further notice, to the Station Superintendent of the British Overseas Airways Coipor^ition, Karachi, for transmission to the Hesidency Agent, Sharjah. 2. The cost of the vaccine ¥4ill be remitted to you on receipt of your bill. Copy forwarded for information to (i) Ibe Station superintendent, British Over seas Airways Corporation, Karachi, with a request that the vaccine on receipt may please be despatched by air freight to the Residency Agent, Sharjah. (ii) The Residency Agent, Sharjah,-with reference to his telegram No.643 dated the 29th July, 1942. 'Kindly despatch 500 doses small-pox vaccine lymph to British Overseas Airways Corporation, Karachi, for transmission to Residency Agent, Sharjah.' No *1354—2/14 Political Agency, Bahrain. 1st August, 1942.c t a te ^ e £ rain ^o*A/526, dated the 2nd July, 1942, from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. CIBCULAH . Dubai infected smallpox. Copy forwarded to 1. The Air Li&amp;ision Officer, Bahrain. 2. The ITaval Officer-in»Charge, Ba hr a in fer information. Fo.1361-2/14 Political Agency, Bahrain 2nd August ? 1942. for Poll Aerjant, Bahrain.Telegram Prom To Ko# 41 Dated 13th received 14th August, 1942* Ambassador, Baghdad* Political Kesident, at Bahrain* r Owing to reported outbreak of small* P°* in Dibai Iraq Government require that all travellers proceeding to Iraq from that area by land sea or air should carry anti small pox vacination certificates countersigned by appropriate authorities* Such certificates should be more than 12 days and less than three years old* NCJ ■;o. C/641 I $. 4- v CORNWALL IS • Office of the Politic-?' 1 ' esicVnt in the Persian Gulf. C r. up , B a hr sin. It th / u L ;us t, 1 • if Copy for' arced to the Political Agent, Bahrain.JJ &gt; Copy at &amp; telegram no *41 dated 13th Ai% w » w 1942 9 then His Excellency the British Ambassador* n&amp;jgdactt to the Hon , ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain* owing to reported outbreak of smll-pox in Dubai,Iraq Government require that all travellers proceeding to Iraq from that area by 2and sea or air should carry anti sroa 11-pox vaccination certificates countersigned by appropriate authorities* mch certificates should be more than 12 days and less than three years old* Copy forasn&amp;ed to s*» X* fhe Adviser to the Government of Bahrain 2* the uarantinc Medical Officer, Bahmin 3* Kes^rs* Gray Mackenzie ^ Co*, Ltd*, Bahrain 4* 11 British Overseas A irways Corporatioj 6* Heaidency Agent, ^larjahf for information and necessary action* Ko *1454-2/14 Political A, political Agency, Bahrain. 17th August,1942* for Political Agent, Bahrain*No*1459-2/14 Political Agency, Bahrain. 17th August, 1942* To The Residency Agent, Sharjah. Memorandum. 1 forward herewith a box containing 500 doses of small-pox vaccine lymph. Presumably the consignment has been sent here in error by the superintendent Punjab Vaccine Institute, Lahore, vide this office indorsement No.1354/2/14 dated 1st August 1942, a copy of which was sent to you. Sd/- R.I. Hallows, for Political Agent, BahrainCONDITIONS. 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose ; but in such case the amount paid for transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. v f . NOTE.—Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging, must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company’s Branches JmmTelegram From To Ho.186 enclair. Political, Bahrain. Vaccine, 'Lahore. My 1364 August first. Ho more vaccine required. Ho.1524-2/14 Political Agency,Bahrain. 29th August, 1942. Copy forwarded to the Vaccine Institute Lahore, mation. Superintendent, Punjab by post, in eonfir- for Political Agent, Bahrain.29 . Letter No, 43 dated 19-1-36 from K.S. Husain, Sharjah, Issued telegram No. 29 d. 22-1-36 to Secretary, Bushire. 30, Telegram No. A/234 d. 25-1-36 from A.O.C. Hinaidi. Reference 25 , A T lhat places does Mr Janes visit ask doctor Holmes. We should send copy to F. 15 . with covering letter saying where Mr Janes has gone. T B T We should report this. G.L. 18/1 ^e.A*. N«;\ Fr. Hplmes says that Mr Janes visited Bibai, Hira, Ajman and Khan. Frait for approval submitted. This refers to bad supply of vaccine ^ :noni Basrah. w e obtained a direct 5 / supply of '400 doses of smallpox vaccine from the Health Officer, Bahrah, for which we have not received a bill. The first supply of vaccine was made to us by the Health Officer, Basrah, through His Maiesty f s Consul, Basrah, in connection with the destitute pilgrims free of charge and it is possible that he may not send his bill Tor the present supply. In the circumstances should we report the matter please ? Reference 26. P.A. to see who may wish to write to Fr. Holmes. Copy of correspondence be sent to P.^. ? Reference 27. A The remittance may be made by Mt6. ?/a *7/1 Reference 28. Orders contained in A.P.A T s office note dated 23-1-36 on pre-page noted. Is it necessary to reply to H.A. Sharjah please? Reference 29. Submitted for P.A T s perusal who may also see docket No.20.V' •% We should ascertain from A han ^ahib ^usain whether it is not possible to stop supplies of vaccine going to ^harjah. I think that we ordered a weekly supply from the Health Officer, Karachi, and we must see that it is stopped as it costs a great deal of money. A £ A* &amp; 24.2.1036. ? m. Letter No. 112 d. 23-2-36 from the Hesiaency Agent, Sharjah. W ■ Please asK Dr Holmes if he has any vaccine to spare and if it is the new stuff (powder) whether Sfe&amp;tur Knows how to use it, 2. If not, we shd telegraph to Karachi for a further 1000 doses by the next aeroplane, and repeat to Sharjah. We shd also tell K.S.Husain that Sattur shd go to afterwards Has al Khaimah and/Dubai again, =x£ag=al=Ka. k 7. 3.36 Issued telegram No. 82 dated 7-3-36 to Health Officer, K a p aC hi Repeated Residency Agent, Sharjah. X*35 SLm 'il /?»/ n 1 b/T&gt; 0 61 /a/ J£/ h SI) V)\1 K D9 Letter No. 254 dated 14th April from R.A.Sharjah, Translation of letter No.255 dated the 14th April 1956 from R.A. Sharjah. Translation of a letter -No.284 of 29-4-36 from A.A.bnarj Sattur, the Vaccinator left Bahrain for Sharjah on the 3rd January and returned to .naiirain on oxie x9th April He worked 3 months and 17 days including two days for journey going and coming. 2. It was arranged'Tfo pay him Rs.loO/ - for the trip, provided the time did not exceed one month, for extra Xx time, it was. hoped to arrange with him to pay Its.55/- a month* ° • His statement pla.ced below, he wants As*haw//- at it he Orate of Is.lGO/- a month. 4. About his return passage to Bahrain. On the lith April, v/e telegraphed to R.A.Sharjah to send Sattur oy steamer. R.A .acknowledged tne ooiogictm and stated that Sattur had a returned ticxet and now in P.U.C. 61 he a&amp;a states he has j^aid Rs.72/- to Su^dt, Rest house Sharjah for return ticket. Draft to Bushire submitted for approval pi. Vi Issued letter No.1161 dated 5-5-36 to it.A. Sharjah. Issued Memo. No.1185 dated 6-5-36 to the Seciy: Bushire. 62 . Telegram No. 359 dated 7-5-36 from Brit consul, Bushire PA. ' l' ^ “The last report from B.A.Sharjah is dated 9th April, No further repo its received* Draft telegram submitted for approval, eJl (A - 4- Issued telegram No.134 dated. 9th May 1936 to h.A.Sharjah repeated to Political Resident, Bushire.Telegram dated the 10th May 1936 from R.A. Sharjah Draft telegram to Bushire submitted for approval pi. l“b Issued telegram No. 137 dated 11-5-36 to P.H. Bushire. We have to return empty wooden covers of vaccine supplied to the Trucial Coast hy the Health Office,Karac Draft submitted for approval please. if ! hi v/ Ji.'' s. ? v/U “/&lt; ~ (x '&lt;1 A. P«A, A special Vaccinator was sent from here(please see page 9) • An expenditure of Hs.93o/- was incurred on this head( page 156) please. 3 tL /i' IL/V Issued letter No.1326 dated lo-5-36 to the Health Officer, Karachi • Letter No.314 dated b’-b-36 from the if.A. Sharjah. 64. V' 7%- lelegram dated 18th May 1936 from P.A.Bahrain from Sh&amp;rjah.p.186 Issued telegram No.144 dated the 18th May 1936 to Bushire p. 187 Telegram No.394 dated the 19th May 1936 from P.R.Bushire p. 188,• 189 lEelegram dated the 22nd May 1936 from R.A» Sharjah. Please see P.R f s telegram No.394 asking for con firmation of 14 cases from Ras-al-Khaimah. R.A.Sharjah now reports 3 cases at Ras-al-Khaimah and 11 cases Pahlaink Araibi and Shamal villages. Should this telegram be repeated to p.R.Bushire please? Issued telegram No.149 dated 23-5-36 to P.h # Bushire, A.O.G., Rinaldi 6b S.N.0.P.G-. Letter No.359 dated 23—5—36 from the ii.A, Sharjah# — We have closed our small pox account and the final statement sent to Bushire. Should we enquire from M*0. if he have any vaccine available, but there will be no Vaccinator at Ras-al- Kh&amp;iaah. 'f' - **/&lt; fe leg ram No .424 dated the 28th nay 1936 from f .R. Bushire. Letter No.365 dated the 27th May 1936 Irom H.A.Sharqah. We will remit Hs.40/- to R.A.Sharjah and enquire from Bushire to whom to debited. Draft submitted for approval. *7 ^9 Issued letter No.1446 dated 3Q-5-36 to the R.A. Sharjah. Issued Memo. No.1455 dated 30-5-36 to Secretary, Bushire. Issued letter No.1494 dated 4-6-36 to it.A. Sharjah. Telegram dated 5-6-36 from the R.A. Sharjah. Issued telegram No.161 dated 5-6-36 ta k.R. Bushire, A.0.0. Hinaidi and S.N.O.r .0./ Jtf^ (2t^iin. H- /^e. (dexU&lt;JU t W 16 ^ 1 (XI ^'- Ml ^ 1^- ri “ (fet 2 7-' 1'VK‘v. A?2 -u, . j-/ JJ. z-ifirf. 0 . &lt;d-c&lt;^&amp;A ' f Q 3 /yu^~ 0 ^ A«&gt;. // 7 /£--£.- ^-f iL ^. R ef.122 gnd Igo . We telegraphed to the Superintendent Vaccination,Knrc'chi, on* 1-2-42, that he should supply by air 500 doses of small pox lymph to the Residency Agent, Sharjah, until further instructions / but it seems that he has not able to do so.Perhaps they do not stock the vaccine as a Vaccine Depot. Dr.Steel says that the Vaccine Depot.Lahore, stock the vaccine as a supplying Depot and it rill be ouicker to get the vaccine from Lahore instead of from Yarvada- May ask Vaccine Depot Lahore to supply the vaccine. Draft submitted for approval pi. yC^ ujivu25' * 7 /Ca^Li/^c - i /K ' H f^/z 3J- 2-if z. pfo 1 a ■ l\Ayi^ (^VUiu e^tJ/ti- Av , /■/. ^^// 3 &gt; a^/ &lt;/, 3 , Va ^^ /&lt;U^*-Csbu &lt; ^ ^V. T 4 — N ‘°- ' Cf ^ U - /z £&gt; ^g r&gt; i;:0 - -he letter referred to in the p.u.c. bps not been received in this office.This office only received letter No. 9/71742, together with the bill for Its 133-7-0, vine page k^i and the amount was remitted vide page.Tf May ask the Municipal Corporation Karachi -to sena us a copy of their letter No.9/712/42 of 7-2-42, together with the bill showing the details of lymph ' supplied. D.F.A. submitted. • . M-126. In February last we asked Municipal Corporation by telegram page289 to supply weekly by air vaccine to Residency Agent,bhargah, but it appears that they have only supplied twice to. Sharejah and thereafter nothing, ns the Municipal Corporation is riot a supplying Depoti under instructions from Dr.Steel,we have placed an order v.itn the Vr ccme Depot.Lahore, on March 4th. Nothing so far is heard from Vaccine Depot.Lahore,|May issue a reminder. D. F. A. submitted f\ ^yyM // (/LsC&lt;^S~^ifi/&amp;U&lt;A. /^O /'ejfci a» • / 4 / . rf/l/te/tfZ £*/%t , /{vjlcJ^ / 3/ % Re f.ISO .Refers to page 304 and states that 40 tubes of vaccine were despatched to Sharjah through airways on the 12th March and thereafter ten tubes weekly are being.to the same address. May file. Ref*131 .Refers to page 307. Fds bill for 100 doeses vaccine supplied to Sharjah. May remit the amount of £s 135-5-0 by debit to Dubai hospital contgs pi. j^r 24/4/42, Ref.131 . Accountant, for action Di U 24/4/42. (jLi^SdGX tfL M./oit *j ±‘-&lt;1-^ A— /X ' Ref.132. Refers to page 300. The bill represents cost of vaccine supplied to the M.O.T.Coast,Snarjah,vide our order at page 300, May remit the amount by debit to Dubai Hospital contingencies pi. 10/5/42 43 ) //S A i^-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000295_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1070</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000295</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1070</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2/14 Outbreaks of smallpox, cholera and other diseases on the Trucial Coast'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-10T16:16:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (402 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes at the end, on folios 367-403. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 404; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Two additional foliation sequences are present in parallel between ff 3-364 and between ff 368-383; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence and telegrams between the Political Agent at Bahrain; K S Husain bin Hamad, in charge of the Agency at Sharjah; the Political Agent in the Trucial Coast; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; and Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo; regarding outbreaks of smallpox and other diseases on the Trucial Coast.The file mostly contains documents regarding a smallpox epidemic in the Trucial Coast: weekly statistics and telegrams showing deaths by smallpox in 1936, in English and Arabic.The file also contains requests for supply of vaccines, vaccinations, quarantine measures, requests for the intervention for Dr Ralph Holmes, Medical Officer at the Victoria Memorial Hospital, and reports from Dr Holmes' work in Sharjah.There is correspondence in Arabic with English translation, with the Residency Agent at Sharjah and with the ruler of Ras-al-Khaimah, Shaikh Sultan bin Salim Al Qasimi.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Medical Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Yusuf Bin Ahmed Kanoo</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Ra's al-Khaymah, Āl Qāsimī dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Sharjah</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Statistics</topic></subject><subject><topic>Infectious diseases</topic></subject><subject><topic>Smallpox</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000295#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>