<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001c8_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T05:27:41.885Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">The Bahrein petroleum Company limited fa*! l/h lo No,PA-454 Bahrein Island, Persian G ulf, April 10, 1936. His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Sir: We are interested to know if marine borers, especially teredos,are in existence in the Persian Gulf and we would very much appreciate it if you could furnish us any infomktion you may have as to their presence in this region. Yours very truly, Gr, W. R. SMITH Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDNo. 1142-28/3' Political Agency, Bahrain, the 3rd May 1936• Sir, I have the honour to inform ycu that I have received an enquiry from The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain, who are interested to know if marine borers, especially teredos, are in existence in the Persian Gulf* I should be obliged if ycu could furnish me with any information you may have as to their presence in this region. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. 'V \ To X ^ * Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, H.M.S. Shoreham at Bahrain.3 v . © NO. 371• H.M.S. «SHOREHAL' M , at Bahrain. 5th Way 1 Sir, In reply to your letter No.ll42~B8/£ of 3rd May, I have the honour to inform you that I have already received an enquiry from the Bahrain Petroleum Company regarding marine horers. 2. As far as is Known these are not existent in the Persian Gulf but I have advised the Company to maKe further enquiry from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. I have the honour to he. Sir, Your obedient servant, The Political Agent, Bahrain. CAPTAIN• SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER, PERSIAN GULF.the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, May 8, 1936 Dear Captain Hicklnbotham: „ TT * 81,1 attac hing copy of a letter received from • r. L. Dobree of the Basra Port Directorate relative to marine borers which I thought might be of interest to your office. For your information, Mr. A, A, Weymouth, our Paleontologist, has definitely determined that teredos ( ankia Mnima) do exist in the waters around Bahrein. They are not particularly abundant but they would be v ';ry destructive to wood of almost any kind, especially piling if it is not particularly protected. Yours sincerely. End: 1. Captain T. Hickinbotham, The Agency, Bahrein.HEADQUARTERS, PORT DIRECTORATE, BASRAH, IRAQ. iiMd 1 No. 19/AD57 17th April, 1936. The Bahrein Petroleum Co.Ltd., Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, Dear Sirs; MARINE BORERS - PERSIAN OTLF Referring to your letter of the 10th instant, I regret that I have very little positive information to give you in reference to this matter, but from experience it has been found as follows:- 1. In the salty water of the estuary secondhand pitch pine piles which have been used for temporary works have been attacked by marine borers and piles 12' x 12' have collapsed within a space of about five yesrs. 2. The Semaphore Station was erected with teak piles 12' x 12' in 1917 and the structure is now showing serious signs of attack by marine borers, but, as the structure is no longer required for navigational purposes, it is proposed to with draw it at an early date. 3. In the fresh water of the Shatt-al-Arab marine borers have not made their appearance, and the Margil Wharves wh-'ch are constructed in teak piles chiefly 12' x 12' from 1917/18 are still in good condition. 4. The new Jetty at Bandar Shahpour constructed about 1925/26 I understand was of creosote oregan pine but I have no Information as to whether it has been attacked by marine borers. I regret that I am unable to state the actual type of marine borers but they are undoubtedly of the teredo specia. Samples can be seen at this office by your representative should he wish at any time to call on my Chief Engineer. Yours faithfully. (SOD) H. M. DOBREE, for PORT DIRECTOR &amp; DIR _ CTOR-GEMERAL OF NAVITATION.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001c8_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1721</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001c8</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1721</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 28/18 Marine borers'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-05-30T00:14:33</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (9 folios)</extent><extent>The documents in the file are arranged in chronological order. There are notes at the end of the file (folios 6-7). The notes refer to documents within the file.</extent><extent>The foliation is in pencil in the top right corner of each folio, and is encircled. The numbering starts on the cover with 1, then 1a, 1b, 1c and ends on the back cover, with 8.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO) representative and the Political Agent at Bahrain on the presence of marine borers in the Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001c8#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>