<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000335_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:02:32.260Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">15 MESOPOTAMIA. Appointment of Sir Percv Cnv aq « m*ml f, f Commissioner ; Instructions o£ His Majesty s Government. / manee CommUCee of the Cabinet, not as formal W approved b !l the otherwise, hut as a general indication, f the lines upon which he is authorised at hit discretion i ■ per %' lal ' 0&gt;'&lt;lance, of His Majesty's Government.) DRAFT INSTRUCTIONS. I.— Original draft as subm.tted to the Cabinet, 5tii August 19^0 &lt;=- delay as « a deoi.ion ha. b„„ J. „ jj' xou are aware that a tpWmm lino ^ a |. n ess eiitiai factors. (i) A spontaneous demand for Feisal is forthcoming from a sufficiently renrp .... Q1 se ^ a i. i y e \ Q dy; of public opinion in Mesopotamia ; (ii) ohenr Feisal is prepared in principle to accept Great Britain as Mandatory 1 ower and to agree to a form of Mandate on the lines already drafted for communication to the League of Nations, or such modification of it ^ His Majesty s Government can advisedly approve. (in) French susceptibilities can be overcome. Supposing that the demand is forthcoming, Sherif Feisal accepts in principle and the question of irench susceptibilities is disposed of, your duty will be to 'et forthwith into personal touch with Feisal, either in Haifa, Cairo, or some neutral own in Liuope, and proceed to negotiate with him a document which shall form the basis ot the working relations between himself and His Majesty's Government. It is possible that Sherii l^eisal. by the light of his experience with the French Government m regard to Syria, may, while accepting the principle of a Mandate and Great Britain as Mandatory, press for the expression of its terms in treaty form. Should this prove the case. His Majesty's Government will be prepared to entertain the proposal. Should the negotiations above referred to lead to the desired result, you should then proceed to Mesopotamia with Feisal, or, failing that, precede him by a short period in which to prepare the ground for his coming. As to the form of government which it is proposed to set up, it is common ground that it is to be predominantly Arab; but, in view of the change in the situation arising from our acceptance of Feisal as Head of the Arab State, it is considered that, subject to the safeguarding of our obligations and interests as Mandatory, the government must be as completely Arab as possible. That is to say, that it must be composed as far as, or as soon as, practicable, of Arab Ministers for each Department of State, responsible to the Arab Ruler, each assisted by a British expert as Secretary, such experts to be considered employes of the Arab Government. It is recognised, however, that for the present special considerations attach to certain Ministries which cannot be overlooked, e.g., the Ministries of War, Foreign Affairs, Finance and Justice. As regards the Ministry of War, it must be clearly laid down in our agreement with Feisal that his Minister of War has no connection with or control over the British garrison in Mesopotamia, which must remain, for the period of the Mandate, under the direct authority of the British Representative. The Arab Minister of War will simply be concerned for the present with the organisation and distribution of indigenous formations of a military or semi-military character, calculated, w r ith the assistance of such British instructors as may be necessary, ultimately and gradually to replace the present Army of Occupation, o 2179 60 8.23As regards the control of the future British garrison, it is recogmsed that m Mesopotamia, as in other parallel cases, the authority of the chief cm representative must be supreme, and accordingly as High Comm.ssioner you will be ex-officio Commander-in-Chief, and will be the sole channel through which the General Officei Commanding will communicate with the Arab Government on the one hand and His Majesty's Government on the other. It will be understood, however, that your position as Commander -in-Chief will carry with it no authority for intervention in matters of military detail. , . TT . „ As regards the conduct of Foveign Affaivs, His Majesty s (jovernment as Mandatory is responsible for them. It is possible that difficulties may be laised on this point by Sherif Feisal, but the principle must be maintained until the Arab State qualifies for admission to the League of Nations. . . The representation of the Arab Government in foreign states by the British representative should not be a source of difficulty, it being accepted in principle that, as the Arab Government progresses, promising Arab officials may be attached to British Diplomatic or Consular representatives abroad with a vievv to learning their duties, and thus qualifying for diplomatic employment later on. It is rather your own position in relation to the Head of the Arab State in regard to the handling of Foreign Affairs which presents some difficulty. There can clearly be no Arab Minister or Ministry for Foreign Affairs. These must be conducted as a branch of the British Residency or Agency, and prima facie all external correspondence must be conducted by the British representative. The Ruler should, of course, be consulted by you in all important matters, and for purposes of routine communication a trustworthy go-between acceptable to both parties should be appointed. Ministry of Finance. —So long as a British Force has to be maintained in Mesopotamia wholly or partly at the expense of the British Exchequer (and that is likely to be the case to a gradually decreasing degree throughout the period of Mandate), it is essential that His Majesty's Government should be in a position to exercise effective supervision over the finances of the country. The appointment of a British Minister of Finance would no doubt be a more satisfactory arrangement, but as this may be regarded as incompatible with the principle of truly Arab government. His Majesty's Government will be prepared to accept an Arab Minister of Finance, provided that a British Financial Adviser is appointed with adequate financial powers. Apart from this, and to strengthen the hands of the High Commissioner in local supervision of finance, His Majesty's Government are prepared to appoint to your staff a representative of His Majesty's Treasury who will act as your financial adviser until such time as the Arab Government is in a position to offer, and His Majesty's Government to accept, a fixed annual contribution to the cost of the British garrison. Ministry of Justice. —It is recognised that the precise measures necessary for safeguarding the obligations and responsibilities of the Mandatory Power towards foreign subjects need careful consideration, and it is not possible to deal with the subject here. His Majesty's Government will await your suggestions after discussion with Sherif Feisal. It is considered prima facie that Sherif Feisal must function as a constitutional ruler, with an Elective Assembly, but this essential point must be a matter for discussion in the negotiations with Feisal. Meanwhile it is not considered necessary to suspend the measures already inaugurated in Mesopotamia for creating elective machinery. In conclusion, it has been decided that, as High Commissioner of Mesopotamia, you will be directly responsible to the projected Department of the Middle East, and will receive the instructions of His Majesty's Government through that Department of State. II.—R evised draft. In pursuance of the Anglo-French Declaration of November 1918 and other pro nouncements, His Majesty's Government have decided, now that peace been concluded with Turkey, that there shall be as little delay as possible in the creation of an Arab State in Mesopotamia.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000335_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B347</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000335</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B347</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Mesopotamia. Appointment of Sir Percy Cox as High Commissioner: Instructions of His Majesty's Government'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1920/1920</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-19T12:24:16</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (2 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this sequence commences at folio 124, and terminates at folio 125, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between folios 7-153 of the volume; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This printed report published by the India Office contains two sets of draft instructions approved by the Finance Committee of the Cabinet for Sir Percy Zachariah Cox's personal guidance as High Commissioner for Mesopotamia to give effect to the policy of His Majesty's Government. The first set is an original draft, dated 5 August 1920, while the second set is a revised draft.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Iraq</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight Percy Zachariah Cox</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000335#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>