<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000a1_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T08:56:51.833Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Telegram From To Repeated P. Political Resident, Bushire H.M's. Minister, Tehran, No. 170. Government of India, ) „ 1 Qflf7 Secy, of State for India, j N0 ‘ P.A., Bahrain, (Separately), No. 1289. Dated 31st Decemher 1928. I have received letter from Governor of Bushire on the subject of the Bahrain passport system, gist of which is contained in my telegram immediately following. Letter did not call for reply and I have so far made none. We may expect condition of stalemate, which -ill however inconvenience Persians more than Bahrainis. JOHNSTON'. Telegram From To Repeated Code. Political Resident, Bushire. K.M’s. Minister, Tehran, No. 171. Government of India, Secretary of State for India P.A., Bahrain (separately) | No. 1288. No. 1290. t Dated 31st December 1928. Persian Government does not recognise any State of Bahrain, considers Bahrain the legal property of Persia and is not prepared to adopt any formality for bahi. a in islands oesides this. No other document will be issued for travelling to Bahrain beyond Ilm o khabar and Bahrain inhabitants who arrive with foreign passports will not be allowed to enter Persia. JOHNSTON. Post copy for information to Political Agent, Kuwait . 4 , * 'Muscat. for Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.,/ S' DateTelegram p, From Politioal Resident, Bushire. To Government of India, Delhi, No, 22, Repeated Secy, of State for India, • ' Dated 10th January 1929. A.s regards Muscat claim I agree with action proposed. I am however awaiting reply from Political Agent, who was instructed to report after discussing matte] with Sultan. Political Agent, Muscat, informed me as regards retaliatory passport measures that he considered Sultan would have no ohjaction hut as number of Persians in Muscat was insignificant, practical effect would he small. Political Agent, Kuwait, reported that question was being considered by Shaikh, who asked time to give definite answer, but who for some reason did not appear to regard proposal with favour. No difficulty should be experienced in obtaining letters from Trucial Shaikhs as desired but as diplomatic measures are not understood by them ( vide para. 13 of enclosure No. 3 in No. 1 Admiralty to Foreign Office, of November 12, in Persia Confidential Series Nov. 15, Section 1 ), I am inclined to doubt whether request for such letters is advisable especially in view of effect already produced of Bahrain measures. Political Agent, Muscat, has been requested to expedite reply. I am visiting Kuwait myself this week in H.M.3. 'TRIAD' and hope to be able to reply furthe] on my return on January 17th. The foregoing refers to your telegram No. 2637-3 of December 4th. RBSID3NT. Kuwait Post copy for information to Political Agent, Bahrain . - Muscat. for Under Secretary to the Political Resiuent in the Persian Gulf.Telegram yrom Political Ke&amp;lcent 9 isuehlre. J0 Oovernnant of Inula, tforei^a and ^oilticul Department * jpiew Delhi. Repeated H.M's. bcicretary of otate for Inaia, London. ho. 36. Dated ICth January 19^9, ihe Bhalich of A.u^alt Is not aiurloue to impose passport measures and to press him *ould seem now unnecessary. Political Agentat Muscat will submit report after return of «ultan ana wazir, both expected about 2Prd January. foregoing is in continuation of my telegram of 10th instant, no, 22. - HKl&gt;li)KKT. Political A^ent. M uacat. J os copy to tli e Political Agent I baJirain . for J^oliticjil Agen t, huwai t, information. for Under ^Secretary to ithe Political Resident in Jie Persian Gulf, Bush ire, January 1928. fTele gram j j . From Gove rnrnent of India, foreign and Political Departnent, new i;el3ii. H.M’s. Secretary of State for India, Lond on. TTex^eated J , olitical Keoident, i^uehire- llo. 140-S. Dated 11th (received 12th J January 1929. m In special c ircurrs tances explained in Buchire telegram Ho. of December Slat, we think practice if giving certificates of identity to JPersian residents of Bahrain and Kuwait for journeys to places other than Persia might be allowed to continue. To discontinue custom would not seemingly help in matter now in hard, viz. emphasising that Bahrain is not Persian port. Some such arrangement seems to be rendered (desirable ?) in view of our insistence on excluding Persian like other foreign representatives from Bahrain and Kuwait. Reference is to your telegram of 14th December, ho. 3632. - PORKIOH . Political Agent, Muscat^. Dost copy to the Poriffcal~ Agen tV hahrain .3M British Kesidency &amp; Consulate-Creneral, Bushire, the 25th February 10 Recently a Kuwait subject named Ibrahim^T5XYT~Ali here arrived/from Dabai under Certificate of Identity issued by the Residency Agent, Ghargah. ne came to Bushire to lodge a complaint against the Residency Agent ( I have sent you a separate letter by the man himself abput his case) • 2. Cn departure for Kuwait Ibrahim bin Ali attempted to leave on his Certificate of Identity as issued from Dabai. The man was prevented doing so by the Persian Customs authorities who are in charge of Passport arrange ments, on the grounds, that he should take out an'llm- 0 - Khabar', Kuwait being, according to Tehran regulation, a part of Persian territory. The man was made to miss his steamer by this action of the authorities. £. Ibrahim then complained to this Residency and was advised un-officially to take out a *llm-o-Khabar' for Kohammerah and leave the ship at Kuwait - this to avoid awkward duestions• He did not do so however but has I understand asked for and obtained an ’Ilm-o-Khabar’ to Kuwait, and has gone out to the steamer today. 4. Action of this sort on the part of individuals naturally pleases the Persians, and helps them in justify ing their claim to Kuwait especially when they get no protest from the Kuwait authorities. As you doubtless know the Ilm-ro-KhalJar, is the document issued all over Persia to persons who desire to travel within the Persian Umpire from Province to Province. Lt-Col J.C.fore.,D.S. 0 . Political Agent, Kuwait.7 Bahrein recently put their foot down and now refuse to allow any one from the Persian side to land unless he jiskxsx a passport visaed ty British Consul. L'uscat has also made a protest quite recently . /V 6. i give you the above at length as 1 think you ought perhaps to discuss the matter with the Ruler. I am aware of course that you sometime hack reported that ^ the Shaikh did not seem inclined to move in the matter, but I think it is as well that he should fully realize the difficulties his subjects are put into when trying to return to their homes. ^• ^nly today an~other difficulty arose over the question of live Kuwait ship-wrecked sailors whom 1 am repatriating to their homes.The Authorities refuse^to allow them to go on board ship without the •llm-o-Khabar*. in their case also if the authorities are adamant 1 shall in the interest oi the Shaikh of Kuwait advise them to take passage to r.ohammerah and get off at Kuwait., ^hat does the Shaikh himself really want? V'e are trying to safe guard his interests at this end, but does he wish them safe guarded in this way. t at a fersian fort with your ueruiricate or identity or wiTdi the Shaikh’s fassport (if sucn were issued) has his documents impounded and is given the rersian -ilm-o- Khaiar' instead^being forced to pay for same, ne probably will be unea into one bargain ror not being m possession oi tne rersian consul’s visa at Basra. possesses li he makes no move he merely strengthens the fersian case and claim to Kuwait. °’ course you realize that any Kuwaiti arrivingD.O. 110.1^*9 OOIlFIDgNTIAL Kuwait 12th Marsh 1929. O'o In reply to your deal-official letter of 25th February, I h ve told Shaikh Ahead about Ibrahle bln ’All, and he seeae to realise quite well what happens to hie subjects In Persia* He tailed a lo$ of platitudes about the sl^n of following Bahrain's lead in talln* retaliatory aeasures* I did not actually surest that he should on this occasion, and do not purpose doing so unless the Resident wishes ae to, as he has already had our advice - and not taken it* . are ri&amp;ht In one thin* you say in paragraph ft of your letter aaaely that the Shaikh’s Passport (if such were Issued) would be iapounded. A Kuwait nerchant who has a lot of deal* inf,s with Muhaiaarah and 'Abbadaa as well as with Basrah told ee only the other day that they wanted to impound his Certificate of Identity issued by me, but he eventually persuaded them not to as a personal favour (he now uses it for everywhere except Persia, for which country he has to use Persian papers)* The interesting thing about his case was that they apparently asked him why he had a Certificate of Identity signed by a British official and not one Issued by hia own Ruler, and told him that if he had the latter he would have no trouble. The merchant does not know whether this was the particular official's personal view, or an ’'inspired” one, but the point is certainly interesting* Lieut*-Colonel H* R, ?• Dickson, C.I.3., Secretary to the Hoxi'ble the Political Resident In that ?&gt;«ral*A Gulf. B U S h 1 r S. Persians belni, trying people to deal with, but showed no As a matter of fact I am not at all sure that you1 ^W*-s r i&amp; 7 4r4&gt; Telasraa. rT)m To No 2283/3 Dated 23ru July 152 . P. (Sovernaient of India, Simla iolitioal .iesiuent 'Triad', jrima facie proposal is noa unotijectionabla. er.its in the fora sugge tea would perhaps be sufficient * r * ’urneyi’lnside the I eraian flulf. in vie. of our exolusiie control of ai.reins external relations it a^etis certainly necessary to insist &gt;n end .recent oj lOlitisal gant for Journeys outside the Gulf whether to mpira destinations or to foreign countries. Before we address Secretary of state regarding Bahrein ' '-1 it seems necessary to consider the probability of a similar request from «* lkh of Keweit ^see correapo^i.n^ -ce anOing with my endoraomant&lt;75/9/27 228 ^ Wiich shoula proauma dy be dealt with similarly simoe in passport matters the position of both states seats identical. The latest proposal by Kuwait was for the introduction of regular passports.Bould it be possiol* and suitable for Bahrein at any rate for Journeys outside Gulf?. foreign. for information^ P ° Bt t0 ^ olitical ^nt at 3 j n c * : “ T * i^ai'rett, Lieut.-Cotonc 1 olitical efficient in the ^crBian Gulf,*1 TELEGRAM. TO. Resident Buahire. FROM. Political Kuwait. NO. 464. Rated 19/6/29. c° f your No. ?9b. Rated 12th August. for Sheikh does not wish issue pascports slX present. Decision not to prejudice any future desire his part to reopen question. Political.Telegram (I*D , # 0*C,) No From To Resident, Bushire, Political, Kuwait, 1024. Dated and received the 19th October 1929. Circular. Afghan Foreign Office Kabul has announced capture Kabul city on October 10th and of Citadel on October 13th by brother Nadir Khan. Habibullah reported to have fled. Grand National Assembly to be summoned as soon as possible select future ruler. Re si dentConfidential Ho. 160-W. of 1050. British Heaiclency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 7th April 1050. From ^he Secretary to the honAhie Uie Political heaident in the Persian Gulf, To The Political A^ent, uuscat. The Political Agent, Jiaiirain. he Political Agent, Kuwait. Gir. 1 am directed to inform you that in the treaty which is at present unaer negotiation with the Pereian Oovcmifitnt it la proposed to inaert a non- aggresolon clause under which each of the nigh Con tracting Parties would agree to respect the territorial independence of the oilier. A copy of the clause, as at present drafted, is attached herewith for your in formation and while it nay be subject to verbal modification in the course of the negotiations the purport of it nay be r&amp;garded as sufficiently fixed for the present purpose. You will notice that in this clause the Persian Govermaent undertake to resect the territorial Independence of the British Governmant, and, fur titer, of those territories for the protection of which the British Govcrnncnt are responsible and of the Heads of Gtates in special treaty relation with His Britannic Ma^eoty. Among these Heads of states is B ultan of Huscat. the Shaikh of Baluraln. In tills clause, as Bh aliih o/ Kuwa it' originally drafted, it was considered tltut it would sufficesuffice if a reciprocal undertaking was given by hie Uujeety'B Government to reepeot the territorial integrity of yeroia: but the iJ i?rBian oovermaent pointed out that thin would Inpose unilateral obli gations on Persia since the states unoer special treaty relations would not liave to give any reciprocal undertaking to respect the territorial integrity of Persia. You will see therefore tluit'in the clause as now drafted the addition has been made 'in his own nane and in the name of those states and 'territories to which this article refers': that is to say, it is proposed that liis uajesty's oovermaent should give an undertaking on behalf of the Sultan of Muscat phalkh of Baiirain r to respect the territorial inacpend f^ml idi o/ Kuwait ence of Persia. in order to enable them to do this, it is considered cieolrabre that they Bhould obtain the requisite authority from the rulers concerned. 1 an therefore to request that you will obtain a Bahrain authorising Hin iiajesty*e uovsrnnent to sign Kuwait the non-aggresalon clause, in t^ie sense of the draft which has been coiomunicated to him, on hin behalf. Vhe Kon’ble the Political Hesident would be glad if you would obtain U*e requisite undertaking with os little delay as possible and ifii'orm him by telegram when it lias been signed: considerable progress, it 1b believed, is being made with ti« Persian negotiations and it is essential that the formal assent of the rulers concerned should be obtained as soon as possible. formal letter from the * I * * 4 tjult an o f unsea t or Muscat Q&gt;£isor“ r lml kh' oT I have the honour to be, :Ur, Xour moot obedient servant 4 Captain, for Secretary to the Political itesioent in the Persian Gulf.Draft of second paragraph of Article I of proposed treaty between Great Britain and Persia, ^Saeh of the High Contracting Parties, in view of the obligations incumbent on them as members of the League of Nations, and in view of the Multi- -lateral Treaty for the denunciation of Har signed at Paris in August 1928, and in view of the ancient ties of friendship existing between them, undertakes in his own name and in the names of those states and territories to which this article refers, to respect the territorial independence of the other High Con- -tracting Jarty, including the territory for the protection of which that High Contracting Party is responsible and of the following Heads of States in special treaty relations with His Britannic Majesty* Government. LIST OF H^DS OF 3TATB3• The Sheikh of Kuwait. The Shaikh of Bahrain. The Shaikh of HI Katr. The Sultan of Muscat. The sheikhs of Abu Dhabi, Dabai, Ajman, Sharjah, lias el Khaimah and Uma el qaiwain.4 7N r Eetter From - To »K Political Agent, Kuwait. H.E.Shaikh Ahmad al-^abir as-Suba^, Ruler of Kuwait. 0 . S • 1 • ,0.1. -J • , No. 210. Dated 16th April 1930 (17th Dhil Qa , dah 1348). CONFIDENTIAL After Compliments. I am directed by the Eon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to inform Your Excellency that in the friendly Treaty which H.M.Government are at present negotiating with the Persian Government, it is proposed to insert a non- &lt;j;ression clause, under which each of the High Contracting Parties ( i.e. H.M.Government and the Persian Government) will agree to respect the territorial independence of the other. That is to say the Persian Government will undertake to respect the territorial independence of the British Government, and of those territories for the protection of which the British Government are responsible, and of those Heads of States who are in special treaty relations with H.M.Government. Among these heads of states is Your Excellency as Ruler of Kuwait. H.M.Government on her part will among others give A an undertaking on behalf of Your Excellency as Ruler of Kuwait to respect the territorial independence of Persia, also similar undertakings will be given by H.M.Government on behalf of the Sultan of Muscat, the Shaikh of Bahrain and other rulers in the Persian Gulf. Before H.M.Government proceed further in the matter however it is considered fitting and necessary to inform Your. Excellency of the above facts, and to ask whether Your Excellency agrees to authorize H.M.Government to sign the proposed non-, ^ression Clause on behalf of Yourself as Ruler of Kuwait. In order that Your Excellency may have no doubt as to what is meant exactly,5am directed to enclose for your information a translation of the proposed Draft para graph in the treaty to which the foregoing refers.As R.M.Government would like Your Excellency^ formal assent as soon as possible, so as not to delay the putting through of che treaty, I am directed to request that a very early reply my be given me .to this letter. Usual ending. K Lieut-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait.Draft of aaaond paragraph of Article I of proposed traaty between Or eat Britain and ierela. aofc of tho Eigh Contracting P&amp;rtioa, in view of the obligations incuusbont on thm aa aeabors of the Teague of Setione, and in view of the lulti- •lateral treaty for the ^enunciation of 'Sar signed at laris in August 1928, and in view of the ancient ties of friendship existing between thea, undertakes in his own naise and in the names of those states and territories to which this article refers, to respect the territorial independence of the other High Con* -traoting Jtarty, inciifcaing the territory for the protection of whioh that High Contracting Party is reap noible ) and of the following Heads of States in special treaty relations with His Britannic Kajeety f i Bovernment, LIST OJT H5AD3 Q1 3TATX8» The Bhelkh of Kuwait. The ihalkh of Bahrain. The dhaikh of K1 X&amp;tr. The Buitan of Muscat, he uheikhs of Abu Dhabi, Labai, Ajaan, Bharjah, \ps el Khaiaah and Hjeoi el v&amp;lw&amp;in*Translation of a letter From - H.E.Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah, C.S.I.,C.I.E#, Ruler of Kuwait* To - Lieutenant-Colonel H.R # P.Dickson, C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. Dated the 19th Dhil Qa’dah 1348 (18th April 1930) After Compliments* I have pleasure in acknowledging the receipt of your letter No*. 810 dated the 17th instant, and note the contents of the proposal as submitted by the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, for inserting a non-aggression clause in the friendly treaty which R.M.Government are at present negotiating with the Persian Government, and under which both the High Contract ing parties will agree to respect the territorial independ ence of the other party* Also that the Persian Government for their part will agree to respect the independence of the territories for whose protection H*M*Government are responsible, and the independence of the Heads of those States who are in special treaty agreements with H*M. t Government. Further I note that I, your friend, come under the category of these Hoads of States, and that H*M.Govern ment will un&amp;ertrJce on behalf of myself, your friend, to respect the territorial Independence of the Persian Govern ment. Lastly note that they have considered it fitting and necessary to inform me about the above facts and to enquire from me whether I agree to authorize them to sign the suggested non-aggression clause on behalf of yuxoc myself, your sincere friend. I have now to say that I have understood the translation of the draft of the suggested clause in the proposed treaty, which is referred to above and I consider it suitable, and I hereby state that I have no objection to H*M.Government signing the above mentioned clause on my behalf.I am grateful for H.M.Government*s favours, and thank H.E. the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire and Tour Excellency, and express my gratitude and pray for the progress of you both* Usual ending* ■Telegram (R) From Political, Kuwait To - Resident, Bushire No. 215• Dated 19th April 1950. Your 160-3 of 7th April. Shaikh has sent me formal letter authorizing H.M. G-overnment to sign non-aggression clause on his behalf Anglo- Persian Treaty. Letter by post. Political. \ / /Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated the 19th April 1930 Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Diokson, C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. • I 11 j In continuation of my telegram 5 No. 215 dated 19th April 1930 and in reply to your confidential despatch No.1603 dated 7th April, I have the honour to forward for your in formation and record, '] (a) Translation of my letter No. 210 of 17th Dhil Qa’dah 1343 (16th April 1930) to H.E. the Shaikh of Kuwait with enclosure. (b) Translation of H.E. the Shaikh’s letter jj -yi^fLated 19th Dhil Qa’dah (18th April 1930) / to my address, intimating that he authorizes H.M.Government to sign the non-aggression clause, on his behalf, in the sense of the draft communicated to him. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait.Jm B. Telegram From To No. 869 Bated 28th Beeember 1932. Political Resident, Bushire. political ^gent, Bahi*ain. Taimjurtache, Minister of Court has Been dismissed by ohah, it is rumjured in connection with Anglo-rersian Oil Company affairs. Besident. lost copy forwarded to the Political Agent, JLuscat, Political Agent, Kuwait, for information. By Order, for Seer tary to the Political Besident in the Persian Culf.ft - ! . 7 *t !-■. £/ V. f iH Confidential. No. 502-S Of 1933. British Residency and Consulate-General, BTTSHIRE. I he Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment ( 6 // for information. Dated 12 th May 1953. Reference to previous correspondence : Bushire printed letter N©,329-S of 4th April, 1933. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. i Subject. Mohammerah letter No. 346 of 27th April 1933. Extract paragraph 128 of Moh&amp;mmerah Diary No. 8 of 1st May 1933. Restriction on travel of Persians to Kuwait.v ioj-ConitflSW, April 27 1 Id33. /)v0 / r vlft Dear Residency, Please refer to your Ho. 373-S dated the 20th February 1933 to Chancery. The Police authorities in Mohanmerah have received instructions from Tehran not to issue permits to Persians who wish to proceed to Kuwait. This was reported in this Vice-Consuiate Commercial Report paragraph 4 sub-paragraph (cy. At the time it was thought to be oii account oT txie reason given in tne report, but Turtnur enquiries u.eaa me to believe that ACT restriction has been imposed to prevent smuggling of contraband goods from Kuwait to iersit and that the instructions emanate from Tehran. Yours ever, VICE-CONSULATE. The British Residency, B u 8 h i r e •if*.;Extract paragraph 128 of Mohammerah Diary No.8 of 1st hay 1933. *■****•* 128 . Persians •proceedin g to Kuwait . The Police authorities at Mohammerah received instructions from Tehran to the effect that Persian subjects are not allowed to proceed to Kuwait and that no permits to travel there were to he issued after the close of the Persianjyear 1311( 20th March 1933). The restric tion is believed to have been imposed owing to the extensive smuggling of contraband goods from Kuwait to Persia by Persians. ****Copy to liuahire . Conridential . L'.O.Ko:C/275. /i7f whip —i Political Agency, I^Jirain, tiio 15th/uly 1&amp;33 d •' ■ My dear Colonel,■ X was able to find out yesterday afternoon that the Governor of Bushire had embarked on the ♦Barpeta* at Lingeh. The possibility of the Governor of Bnshire being on board had been mentioned to the Shaikh that morning and he agreed that it was most unwise to allow him to land, should he by any chance wish to do so. 2. In the evening Belgrave and I discussed the matter and it *as decided that the best way out of the difficulty was to arrange that the Chief of the Bahrain State Police should go on board this evening (6 P.M) and be ready to inform the Governor politely that it was regretted that it was not possible for him to land. This message would only be conveyed to him should he show any inclination to do so. At the same time to prevent any popular demonstration by the Persians,Beigrave and liucooll thought it a good opportunity to restrict the ever increasing swam of visitors to ships in harbour. For come time past,Captains of the slow mail steamers have complained bitterly that crowds,which swarm on to their ships will one day breais: down tne gangway, so Beigravc lias prepared a notice for the Shaikh*s signature to tne el feet that from today no casual visitor can leave the shore without a permit to do so. o. These are the arrangements that we have made and we hope that there will be no incident. Yours sincerely, he Persian Gulf. /. Bushire. The Hon’ble Lieut-Colonel Gordon Loch,I.A., yfS Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, ^ ’H- e c w -British Consulate, D.0.No Confiden Lial. Basra, Iraq. 50th August, 1955* There is a rumour here to the effect that (a) Persians from Abadan and/or Mohammerah go to Kuwait by native craft and holding permits issued by the Persian Authorities and not vised by any British Consulate, and that such permits are recognised by the Shaikh* s Government and the people allowed to enter the territory; (b) Y r hen a person wants to go to Abadan and/or Mohammerah from Kuwait, by native craft, the Shaikh’s Government issue permits for the journey, these permits being recognised by the Persian Authorities and the people allowed to enter the country. and, Could you let me know whether there is any foundation for this story ? I am sending a copy of this to Chauncy at Mohammerah. ^ Lieut.-Colonel H.P.P.Dickson, C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. id PYC Tf-V' 1D.O. No. 2/15/loG British Vice-Consulate, fcohuafueraa, f A/o- ^epteijbei o, 1,,,^. A Ir'oiJ-ilo- noi J IT, ^ ^• L.H. Hurst, Esquire, His Majesty's Consul, Basra. Dear Hurst, Please refer to your Demi-Official letter No. 1604 of August 30, last to Dickson. 2. Enquiries about the visas for Kuwait from private sources have elicited the following Until 30th Isfand (20th Varch 3933) the Police authorities at Kohamnerah used to issue permits (Jawaz) to * *■ Persians to travel to GJulf ports including Kuwait, but it appears that early in 1312 (April 1933) the local Police authorities received instructions fron 'Tehran to the effect that Persians are not alio ed to proceed to Kuwait nor a~e they allowed to travel by slow nail. The obiect of these restrictions is two-fold. i) to stop tae extensive smuggling of contraband gooas from Kuwait to Persia by Persians, ii) to discourage Persians fron proceeding to i ecca for pilgrimage via Kuwait and i'ejd. As far as I know no permits are, at present, issued to Persians to proceed to Kuwait and the permits granted by the Shaikh of Kuwait are not recognised by Customs authorities here, but Persian Subjects arriving by slow mail are allowed to land on payment of a small sum of money (presumably in lieu of permits). 4. Prom the foregoing it will be observed that rumour (a) is correct but that the Persian authorities have at present ceased to issue penults for reasons of their ovn, and tnat rumour (b) is incorrect since though the Shaikh of Kuwait may issue permits the Persian authorities do not recognised them. 5. I am sending a copy of this letter to Dickson. Yours ever, - ' i ______Comp-WTIAI Ko. 314. HaRaSjL POLITICAL AGENCY, XUYAIT. Dated the 13th September 1933. LIy dear Hurst, Reference your Confidential D.O.No.1604, dated the 30 th August 19 33. 2. Persian generally have been forbidden to visit Kuwait by en order from Tehran issued, I believe, last Kerch. is 3. The order, however/evaded in the case of (a) an occasional merchant or well to do person, who comes over by native craft to do a bit of business or to see a friend or relative; (b) the inhabitants of the many small hamlets on the Persian side of the Shatt-al-Arab, who come to Kuwait in oKall boats to dis pose of vegetables, fruit end market garden produce. 4. As the category mentioned in 3(b) above are visitors for a day or a night only and like fishermen, are to be encouraged than otherwise, I propose not to take them into account here. b* As r0g6rds3(a): Such visitors cannot get a visa to their passports from the British Consulate, Kohamerah, even if they tried to do bo, as the Persian authorities refuse to make any passport val,id for Kuwait on the ground that Kuwait forms pert of Persia. To get out of the difficulty such persons get a Ilm-o-Khabar or small slip of yellow paper from the Police or Passport authorities, no doubt, by . L.H. Hurst, Esquire, His Majesty’s Consul, BASRA.— 2 — by a bribe, Tihioh permits them to go to Kuwait and return. On this paper are the words written in Persian and French, permitting the holder to proceed from one Persian port to another, and return if necessary. 6. On arrival at Kuwait it has been the practice to allow the holder of an Ilm-o-Khabar to land on payment of a snail fine, as the Shaikh does not wish to discourage legitimate traders, by making things too difficult for them at this end. The mans Ilm-o-Xhabar is, however, col lected from him and sent to this Agency Passport Office for record, where also the small fine is taken. 7. Should the individual desire to go back to Mohammerah, he gets a paper from the Shaikh’s Secretary (compulsory for everyone desiring to leave the town) to me, in which it is stated that so and so, a Persian subject, desires to proceed to Mohantmerah• 8. I then issue a Certificate of Identity for the journey to Basra, and the traveller gets back to Mohammerah from there as best as he can, with the assistance of his Consul, who, I believe, makes him take out proper passport costing a considerable sum of money. 9. Under no circumstances do I issue a Certificate of Identity for Mohammsrah as the holder would have it torn up on arrival and be fined for having it. 10. There are a few cases, no doubt, and this is ad mitted by the Shaikh to be so, of Persians slipping into Kuwait by dhow after dark, and landing unbeknown to the Passport Control authorities. Uuoh persons hang on to their Ilm-o-Khabars, which come in handy for thoir return journey. 11* Up to a short time ago the local Passport officials did not send in the collected Ilm-o-Khabars to me as regular ly as I should have liked, but as I suggested there was a certain amount of illicit traffic in them especially whenwhen Persians were returning via Basra, I got the Shaikh to put the .'.latter right, and norc they all cocic to me, 12. In this connection, X believe, I am right in say ing that travellers going back Tzia Basra can get out of having to take uut a Persian Passport from their Consul there if they can produce their original Ilm-o-IChabar, hence the efforts made to get back these documents frcm the local authorities here even though they held certificates of Identity issued by me for Iraq. 13# The Shaikh tells me that the only document that he ever gives to travellers going to Persia is a sort of 'Nationality Certificate’* to the effect that the bearer is a subject of Puw&amp;it, but this is done only in the case of Arabs, The total number of these is under ten per annum. 14. I em sending a copy of this to Chauncy at Moharam erah, Yours sincerely, t .an™ mots. I have just received a copy of Chauncy* s D.O. 2/15/706, dated September 8th, to you. He nuts the matter very clearly and brings out the interesting point which escaped me, that Persians returning to I'ohammerah from Kuwait, without documents, are allowed to land on payment of a small fee. No,215 of 1933. Copy, with compliments, to Lt.F.C.L. Chauncy, H.B.M’s Vice-Consul, Moharamerah, with reference to his endorsement No.2/15/707, dated the 8th f’eptamber 1933.(2^ . I .JY “• 5 ^ Telegram Cypher. Resident, Bushire. Tolitical, Kuwait. 895. Dated the 11th October 1935. Addressed to Unseat, Kuwait, Kohainiaerah and Bahrain, who will send by this Air mail to Residency Agent (Shargah). Bor information and to enable you verbally to counter rumours if necessary. On October 9th Kudir of Customs Persian Easidu boarded dhow and inspected her papers in our waters. He was arrested and is detained on Lupin pendin- reference to Tehran. -RESIDHMT-ARABIC LETTER. POLITICAL AGENCy, PERSONAL . KUWAIT. Dated the 12th October 1933. To His Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait. After compliments, I have the honour to inform Your Excellenc that on 9th October a Persian Mudir of Customs, boarded a dhow and inspected her papers in British waters at Basidu. He was immediately arrested, and is now detained on board H.M.S. Lupin pending a reference to Teheran. I write to inform Your Excellency of this privately in case exaggerated or false rumours should reach abfcut the incident. Usual ending.Telegram iTrom Resident, Bushire. To Political, Kuwait. No. 905. Dated the 14th October 1933. Pollowing from Secretary of State for India, 2528, October 13th begins. Addressed Government of India foreign L Political Department, 2527, repeated to Bushire, No.2528. BASIDU. Regard it as most i iportant to keep I.Iudir incident out of press if possible, and would be grate ful if any possible steps to secure this, ctrould be taken if necessity arises. -RESIDENT- *CONFIDENTIAL. 0/88 Of 1932♦ Office of the Political hesident in the Persian Gulf # H* l • . Shoroham, Henj ass• ^ v' ; British Consulate-G-eneral, ' ■\\\,xxxx*xxxxxxx*i*WKmxn. xxxxxxxx $1 b ' J \ e '&lt;K ' The Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- 1« The oeoior Laval offleer,Persian Gulf ^lvi3lon,!Uh«:i«^horehatiu 2* The Political Agent, Bahrain. 3. The olitleal Agent, Kuwait. \/ 4. The clinical Agent, ikueaat. 5. His Majesty's Consul, Kerman. 6. His Majesty’s Tice Consul, Mohaosierah. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). Dated, 16th oeptcaber 1933 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. y-n Subject. Telegraa Ho«5 flour series) daueji 13th Jeptember 1933 Iron ^la Majesty's Ohargd d'Affaires, Tehran. Resignation of Persian Government.CONFIDENTIAL. 689—S of 1935 'lA The Hon’ble the PoHtica) Resident in the Persian (xiilf presents his com- pliments to .4 1. The Political Agent, Kuwait 2. The .political Agent, Bahrain 3. The Political Agent, Lius cat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copj of the undermentioned docu ment (jjf). British (lonsulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated September 1935 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Extract from Tehran News Circular No.12 fcr the period Iranian representation ending 10th August 1935. in Saudi Arabia. Tvv* 5 ’Cl^ Extract from British Legation, Tehran, News Circular lfo.12 for the period ending' 10th August x935. 1. IBAKIAII DIPLOMATIC mj COHSULriit R-,PIk.S£jJTATIOK X (iii). Iranian representation in Saudi Arabia will be in the hands of the Iranian Legation in Cairo.No. Is 35/6 The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent* P u w a i t • ith and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. 7 - the request that he will kindly let tie Kor/hle the ^jli tic-il hesidert have full inf on ation about the case British* Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRB. Dated er # IS Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. • Subject.Copy of a Demi-Officic1 letter 'o. 375/39-1/1 - cel the 17th August 1935 from Kis lajesty’s hinister ac Tet.,van to Dieutenant-Colonel C-oraon Loch, J.-.D,, offg. Dolitioal Hesicient in the iersian ^ulf. ould you please refer to my letter to ?o.le ac. 375/35-2 of the 5th July about the orse of an Iranian Jubjeot resident in Kuwait. 1 . /e have nov; had a further enquiry of the same type from Hotamedy, who has asked if we can find out why the Kuwait authorities had seized there a boat belonging to an Iranian named deyyid ibdullah Ku tamed of Bandar Rig. Apparently the incident took place c urin e t he month of 1 herd ad• I should he very grateful if you could ask Dickson for any information he may habe about the caseI, Saiyid Abdulla bin Saiyid Bihzad, have now sold to Salih bin Taqi half of the balam, which originally bought from him, for the sum of Rs. 160/- which amount I have received in full* The balam has therefore become the property of the said Salih, and I have no claim to it, whatever* D/- 27th Jamad I, 1354. Sd/ Saiyid Abdulla Saiyid Bihzad Yfitness Witness Ali bin Abdul-Karim Abul. Ahmed bin Abdul-Karim Abul. Witness, Witness, Sayed Mundeni bin Sayed Khalifa. Mosa bin El-Shaikh Muhamnad El-Mazidei. Witness Husain bin Sultan rSSX GOMJFJ; •j L No. C-294. r rhe Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments tq The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. L Ul Dated the 8th October 1955, — Reference to previous correspondence: Budiire Printed Letter No. 1842 . dated the 9th September 1955, 85/6 DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. 1.Letter No.C-290, dated 2Gth September 1955, to His Excellency the Ruler of Kuwait. 2.Translation of a letter No. R-4/2250, dated the 28th Jamad Thani 1554, (27.9.55) from His Excellency the Ruler of Kuwait, Alleged seizure of a boat belonging to Saiyid Abdulla Mutamed of Bandar Rig (Iran). Y \Copy of a confidential letter No.C-29 0, dated 26th September 1935, from the Political .agent, Kuwait to His Excellency the Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments, I have the honour to inform Your lilxcellency that according to a letter from His Majesty’s Minister, Teheran, received by me through the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gu&amp;f, Bushire, one Saiyid Abdulla Mu tamed of Bandar Rig (Iran) has represented to the Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs that a boat belonging to him was seized by the Kuwait authorities, in the month of Khordad (May-June 1935). 2. His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran has, it seems, been approached by the Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs, who have asked for infoimation on the matter. 3. I myself know nothing of the incident referred to above, and should be obliged if Your Excellency would put me in possession of real facts about the matter to enable me to pass on the information to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, who has asked for same. Usual Ending.Translation of a letter No.H-4/2250, dated the 28th Jamad Than! 1354, corresponding to the 27th September 1935, from His Excellency the Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait* •Tamad Thani 1354 (25.9.35) , regarding the complaint of Saiyid Abdulla Mu tamed of Bandar Rig to the Iranian Ministry of Foreigi Affairs, in connection with a sailing boat, I beg to explain below, for your information, the manner how the abovemontioned boat came to pass into the complainant’s hands: registered Ho.200. It belonged to a Kuwait subject named Salih bin Taqi who some 7 years ago sold half of it to the said Saiyid Abdulla Mutamed for a sum of Rs.300/-. The other half remained with the seller as his share; and the boat was run by both parties in partnership, each being entitled to half of the net income it brought in. By mutual arrange ment Saiyid Abdulla was himself appointed Nakhuda, but a short time after the above transaction took place, he dis appeared together with the boat, and for five and a half years, he neither returned to Kuwait, nor did he write anything to his partner here.at all. Officially, the boat still appears on our Register of Craft owned in Kuwait, in the seller’s name, and in the original document of ownership, it still remains the property of the seller. Salih bin Taqi (the original owner) got hold of him, and demanded from him his (Salih’s) share of the boat’s income for the past years. A dispute arose between them on this point, and Saiyid Abdulla claimed that the boat yielded no income at all. Then some friends offered to arbitrate After Compliments. In reply to your letter No.C-290, dated the 27th The boat is of the balam type, and bears the Eighteen months ago Saiyid Abdulla came to Kuwait' v ’ i. S'T • 2 •* 5*0-^*- arbitrate between them, and they (the partners) agreed to &lt;sg&gt; ! dissolve their partnership, so that one only of them should possess the boat. They (the arbitrators) therefore fixed a price of Rs.200 for each half share of the boat. The first owner then sold his share to the abovementioned Saiyid Abdulla Mutarasd at the price so fixed, and the latter undertook to pay the amount by instalments. He, the Saiyid, however, once again left Kuwait and once again failed to return. Moreover he never sent any money to the seller, as promised in spite of the seller’s repeated requests, passed to him by means of passengers proceeding to that destination (Bandar Rig). The boat also did not come to Kuwait. She remained plying for hire between the Iranian ports and the Shatt al Arab. Three months ago, however, another boat which also belonged to Saiyid Abdulla Mu tamed by chance arrived at Kuwait. Its nakhuda was Saiyid Abdulla’s own brother. Salih bin Taqi, therefore, at once lodged a complaint demanding Rs.200/- being the price of his half of the boat mentioned above. Saiyid Abdulla’s other boat was therefore detained by the Town Magistrate shaikh Abdulla al Jabir, who passed orders that Saiyid Abdulla should come and pay the debt he owed his partner, -u few days after these events (in Jamad Auwal 1354 - August 1935 - ) Saiyid Abdulla himself arrived and sold back his half of the boat to Saleh ibn Taqi for Rs.160/-. He gave a Sanad to this effect, which bears the names of certain reliable merchants who witnessed the transaction. For your information, the Sanad is enclosed herewith in original. Please return same after having gone through it. Usual ending. !■? VNo.451* British legation, (231/5/36). Gulhek, 1st October, 1936. C opies to:India No•228• All Consuls Circ.Des.No.37. Sir, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a translation of a law passed on the 9th July last, providing that smugglers who resist arrest by the force of arms shall henceforth be sentenced to death. Smugglers in possession of arms who surrender without resistance, are to have their sentence reduced by two degrees, which means life imprisonment or a lesser sentence at the discretion of the judge; and unarmed persons in the company of armed smugglers are to te sentenced to a term of hard labour ranging from three to fifteen years. 2. Article 3 of the law provides that smugglers in the possession of arms are henceforth to be tried by a military court. In so far as British subjects are concerned, this article clearly runs counter to safeguard No.3 and I have therefore thought it well to take the opportunity to review the present position with rggard to the safeguards in general. 3. Paragraph 6 of Sir John Simons desja tch No. 451 (£.24£3/ 1622/34) of the 6th November, 1933, concludes that 'it would probably be held that the so-called 'safeguards' do not constitute an international engagement in the sense that, in so far as they are embodied in provisions of Persian law, the Persian government, are not entitled to change them without the consent of the foreign Governments concerned'. Paragraph 7 then continues 'It should not, however, be infered from this that the safeguards are wholly without value or effect. His Maj es ty * s / The Right Honourable Anthony Eden, MC.,MP., etc. , etc., etc., The Foreign Office.Majesty’s Government would, I am advised,, be entitled to contend that although the Persian Government may have the right to alter the provisions of this law in matters which concern the safeguard*, they are bound, unless and until the law is thus altered, to observe its provisions rigidly, and consequently to apply the safeguards fully M . But if even at the date of that despatch it was to be presumed that the Persian Government had the right to rt alter the provisions of their law in matters which concern the safeguards', subsequent events have considerably increased the difficulty of adopting a contrary attitude. In the first place a considerable volume of legislation has been placed on the statute-book in the interval which has radically changed the situation since the assurances were given; and the Persian Government thus have ample precedents on which they could rely in the event of any protest with regard to the present law. More important still in this connexion would appear to be the expiry of the Tariff Autonomy Treaty, since it was held in paragraph 4 of Sir John Simon’s above-quoted despatch that 'the strongest argument which His Majesty’s Government could probably make for the internationally binding character of the safeguards would be based on the fact that they were signed on the same date as the Tariff Autonomy Treaty and on the contention that they were thus really part of the consideration for that Treaty'. Thus though the expiry of that Treaty would hardly seem to be a conclusive factor in the situation, it would yet appear to have shorn away the main buttress of the contention that the safe guards formed part of a binding international agreement. 4. In s o far as it is relevant to cite the view of lawyers in Tehran, I would also mention that in a memorandum prepared early this year by Naitre Raphael Aghababoff, a leading Armenian lawyer here, on the subject of the juridical situation of foreigners /foreigners in Iran, it is stated the safeguards rt sont considereea par le gouvernement de n f avoir aucune valeur legale et ne sont pas reconnus par les outorites iraniennes'• This may undoubtedly be ta^en as being the view of the average lawyer here. It is true that when an employe of the Anglo- Iranian Oil Company was arrested at Abadan early this year, an appeal to the safeguards by His Majesty* s Vice Consul at Khorramshahr apparently carried some weight with the Governor* but I think that the conclusion to be drawn from this is that, just as new regulations take some time to penetrate to the provinces, so do old ones linger on for some time before they are recognised &amp;s extinct. Leaving aside for the moment the merits of the case, I do not think that an appeal to the safeguards in Tehran today would have the slightest chance of success • 5. Taking all the above into account, I presume that you would not desire His Ilajesty’s Legation either to protest against the provisions of Article 3 of this law or to intervene should a British subject charged with being a smuggler in the possession of arms, be tried before a military court, I should, however, be grateful for your instructions on this point and also in due course on the wider question of the present validity of the safeguards in general, 6. In conclusion it is perhaps of interest to notice that this law was not passed by the Hajlis in the ordinary ?ray. It was approved by the judicial committee of the Majlis and was then promulgated over the signature of the Prime Minister and the Minister of Justice. Theoretically the laws enacted by this simplified procedure are supposed only to enter into force experimentally and if the Minister in charge of the Department concerned finds them defective, he should report-4- back to the Majlis. Actually he does so but rarely. It is interesting to note that even important and lengthy laws, notably the Penal Code and the Code of Criminal Procedure, have been passed in this simplified way. 7. I am sending copies of this despatch to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India No.228 and to all His Majesty^ Consular Officers in Iran, Circular despatch Ho.37. I have the honour to be with the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedieit, humble servant, (signed) N3VILE SUTLER.LAW INiXIOTIiiG THE DEATH PENALTY ON AIMSD SMUGrQLERS (Passed on tde 9tli July 1936) ♦ Article 1 . ^ny armed person smuggling, or helping to smuggle, goods or monies tne expert or import of which is prohibited, or goods in regard to which there exists a Government monopoly, shall be punished in accordance with Article 2. article 2 . A. Persons who carry arms while engaged in smuggling and use their arms to resist the forces of the Government shall be sentenced to death. Persons who carry arms while engaged in smuggling but who do not resist the forces of the Government when pursued and surrender themselves, shall have their sente-ice reduced oy the court by two degrees. 0. Persons who associate with and assist such persons as mentioned in Section A., but who themselves carry no arms, shall oe sentenced from 3 to 15 years imprisonment with hard labour. persona Article 3 . The trial of the^abeve-mentioned shall take place before a military court. he mark: The trial of the person mentioned in Gecticn J. shall be within tne competence of a military court, if the trial of tee principal criminal is possible and if he is tried in a military court. Otherwise the trial shall take place in a ccmracn (civil) court. (Signed) Jam, Prime Minister. AChsen ^adr, (Minister cf JusticeCONFIDENTIAL. No. 424 -S of 19o7. X The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait,^ The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Poritical Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (*)• British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated ^7• Reference to previous correspondence: hesiaency Printea Letter No. 268-S, dated 24th March 19L7. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. India Office Letter No. P.Z.x;970/19o7, hated 11th May 1937 to Foreign Subject. Iranian rights of inspection and search of Arab dhows.* ^9) P.Z.&amp;97u/ o7 INDIA OFFICE 1 . WHITEHALL 11th May, 1^67 My dear Baggaliay, Would you Kinuiy rei'er to Colonel Fowle f s letter to tne Government of Invia aatea tne Z4th March, anu Major Hay f s reply uatea tne 14th April (copies of v»nieh were sent officially to the Foreign Office on the Zdru April No. r.^.ZoOi;, o7 ana the 6th May No. P.Z.Z970/o7) about tne Persian Goviernment f s rights of inspection ana search of Arab Dnows. You will have seen that tne Resident suggests, ana tne Government of Inaia agree, that tne Suitan of Muscat ana tne Shaikhs of Bahrain anu huvvait snoula cancel the existing proclamations which give Persian vessels rights of search outsiae Persian territorial waters. If tnis suggestion, which seems orima facie sound, is adoptee, I presume tnat the repeal of tne proclamations would nave to be notified officially to the Persian Govern ment - or at any rate tnat it would somenow come to their notice (there would not oe much puint in doing it otherwise). You may thexefore wish to inform Beymour of tne proposal at txxis stage, in case ne has any observations to offer. I am sending a copy of txxrs letter to Beal. /*&gt; Yours sincerely, (Sa.) M.J. CLaUSON H.L. BAGGALLAY, EB(^., FOREIGN OFFICE.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 605-S of 1937 n&gt; &amp; J/4. AV. TT R s /' The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1, 3. Tile Political Agent, The Political Agent, Tne Political Agent, Kuwait, Bahrain, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.. t&amp;e.. WXfr .. AUS.VS t. k . 1937 • Reft rence to previous correspondence: Foreign Office Despatch No.204 of tne 3ra June, 1937, to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. (Busnire Printed Letter No.521-S aatea tne 8th July ldd'7) Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Despatch No.295 dated the 31 st July 1937, from His Majesty’s Minister Tehran to Foreign Office. Iranian Government’s rights of inspection and search of Arab ohows.Copies tos INDIA No. 130 BUSHIRE No. 60 ai»t July* 193?• Sir, I btive received your de«g&gt;fttab m* 204 of the 3rd June and have the honour to autbmlt the following observations on it and the proposal in the note by the Honourable the Poli tical Hesideat in the Persian Gulf enclosed in it to the effect that steps should be taken to cancel the Muscat proclamation of 1896 t substituting for it an authority confined to His Majesty’s Ohips to search /j»ab dhows, and that Dahrelni and Koweiti roo- l&amp;aetlons on this aau« subject of the right to search for area should be einilarly cancelled end redrafted# 2# It would seem fx on paragraphs 2 and d of air ?. Fowle’s note that he ie not seriously oonoerned as regards possible Iranian action in ahrelni or Koweiti waters under the powers coufen ed by the two latter proclamations, but that he has serious misgivings that Iranian warships, by abusing these powers, and using those already conferred by the Muscat proclamation, will interfere with Arab dhows cm the High Seas. At the date when Sir ? # Fowls’s note woe written, last February, there was much reason for such misgivings in view of repeated oases of high-handed action by Iranian warships in all kinds of waters in the Persian Gulf, 3, since tnsn, however, 1 have mad, strong protests to the Iranian Kin later for Foreign Affairs and have discussed with him and his officials the latent dangers. In May - see my telegram Ht* 6b of the 23ad Kay, a member of ay staff was in formed y the inistry of foreign Affaire that orders were being The Right honourable /issued Anthony Aden, M,C«, M«p c , etc,, etc,, etc,, 'Hie Foreign ffice, .1,/ \ CONFIDENTIAL. . V'\ v No. 259-S of 1942. ^ A m The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, v/ The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Muscat, The Publicity Officer Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). British Consulate-General, BITSmRE. Dated.. 18th. February.. 1942. Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. TEXT OF THE TREATY OF AIJ THE U.S.S.R. AND GREAT ER LIANCE BETWEEN IRAN AND ITAIN, AND ANNEXES 1, 2 &amp; 3.His Majesty The King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and the Presidium of the Supreme Council of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics on the one hand, and His Imperial Majesty The Shahinshah of Iran on the other: Having in viev/ the principles of the Atlantic Charter jointly agreed upon and announced to the World by the President of the United States of America and the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom on the 14th August, 1941, and endorsed by the Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics on the 24th September, 1941, with which His Imperial Majesty The Shahinshah declares His complete agree ment and from which He wishes to benefit on an equal basis with the other nations of the World and: Being anxious to strengthen the bonds of friendship and mutual understanding between them and; Considering that these objects will best be achieved by the conclusion of a Treaty of Alliance: Have agreed to conclude a treaty for this purpose and have appointed as their Plenipotentiaries; His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India; for the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland: SIR READER WILLIAM BULLARD, K.C.M.G., C.I.E., His Majesty's Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipo tentiary in Iran The Presidium of the Supreme Council of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics; His Excellency ANDRE ANDREEVITCH SMIRNOV, Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics in Iran, His Imperial Majesty The Shahinshah of Iran; His Excellency ALI SOHEILY, Minister for Foreign Affairs, who having communicated their full powers found in good and due form, have agreed as follows: ARTICLE I His Majesty The King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and the Union of the Soviet Socialist Republics (hereinafter referred to as the Allied Powers) jointly and severally undertake to respect the territorial integrity, the sovereignty and the political independence of Iran. ARTICLE II An Alliance is established between the Allied Powers on the one hand and His Imperial Majesty the Shahinshah of Iran on the other. ARTICLE III. (1) The Allied powers jointly and severally undertake to defend Iran by all means at their command from all aggression on the part of Germany or any other power. (2) His Imperial Majesty The Shahinshah undertakes: (a) To cooperate with the Allied Powers with all the means at His command and in every way possible in order that they may be able to fulfil the above undertaking. The assistance of the Iranian forces2 forces shall however be limited to the maintenance of internal security on Iranian territory. (b) To secure to the Allied Powers for the passage of troops or supplies from one Allied Power to the other, or for other similar purposes, the un restricted right to use, maintain, guard and in case of military necessity, control in any way that they may require, all the means of communication throughout Iran, including railways, roads, rivers, aerodromes, ports, pipe-lines and telephone, telegraphs and wireless installations: (c) To furnish all possible assistance and facilities in obtaining material and recruiting labour for the nurpose of the maintenance and the imrprovement of the means of communication referred to in paragraph (b): (d) To establish and maintain in collaboration with the Allied Powers such measures of censorship control as they may require for all the means of communica tion referred to in paragraph (b): 3. It is clearly understood that in the application of paragraph (2) b), c) and d) of the pregene article the Allied Powers will give full consideration to the essential needs of Iran. ARTICLE IV (1) The Allied Powers may maintain in Iranian territory land, sea and air forces in such number as they consider necessary. The location of such forces shall be decided in agreement with the Iranian Government so long as the strategic situation allows. All questions concerning the relations between the forces of the Allied Powers and the Iranian authorities shall be settled so far as possible in cooperation with the Iranian authorities in such a way as to safeguard the security of *the said forces. It is understood that the presence of these forces on Iranian territory does not constitute a military occupation and will disturb as little as possible the administration and the security forces of Iran, the economic life of the country the normal movements of the population and the application of Iranian Laws and Regulations. (2) A separate agreement or agreements shall be concluded as soon as possible after the entry into force of the present treaty regarding any financial obligations to be borne by the Allied Powers under the provisions of the present Article and of paragraphs (2) b), c) and d) of Article 3 above, in such matters as local purchases, the hiring of buildings and plant, the employment of labour, transport charges etcetera. A special agreement shall be concluded between the Allied Governments and the Imperial Iranian Government defining the conditions of any transfers to the Imperial Iranian Govern ment after the War of buildings and other improvements affec ted by the Allied Powers on Iranian territory. These agree ments shall also settle the immunities to be enjoyed by the Allied forces in Iran. ARTICLE V. The forces of the Allied Powers shall be withdrawn from Iranian territory not later than six months after all hostilities between the Allied Powers and Germany and her associates have been suspended by the conclusion of anan armistice or armistices, or on the conclusion of peace between them whichever date is the earlier. The expression ''Associates” of Germany means all other Powers which have engaged or may in future engage in hostilities against either of the Allied Powers. ARTICLE VI . (1) The Allied Powers undertake in their relations with foreign countries not to adopt an attitude which is prejudicial to the territorial integrity, the sovereignty or the political independence of Iran, nor to conclude treaties inconsistent with the provisions of the present treaty. They undertake to consult the Government of His Imperial Majesty The Shahinshah in all matters affecting the direct interests of Iran. (2) His Imperial Majesty The Shahinshah undertakes not to adopt in His relations with foreign countries an attitude which is inconsistent with the Alliance, nor to conclude treaties inconsistent with the provisions of the present treaty. ARTICLE VII. The Allied Powers jointly undertake to use their best endeavours to safeguard the economic existence of the Iranian people against the privations and difficulties arising as a result of the present war. On the entry into force of the present treaty discussions shall be opened between the Governments of Iran and the Governments of the Allied Powers as to the beat possible methods of carrying out the above undertaking. ARTICLE VIII. The provisions of the present tre a ty are equally binding as bilateral obligations between His Imperial Majesty The Shahinshah and each of the two other High Contracting Parties. ARTICLE IX. The present treaty shall come into force on signature and shall remain in force until the date fixed for the withdrawal of the forces of the Allied Powers from Iranian territory in accordance with Article V. In witness whereof the above-named Plenipotentiaries have signed the present treaty and have affixed thereto their seals. Done at Tehran in triplicate in English, Russian and Persian, all being equally authentic, on the twenty-ninth day of January one thousand nine hundred and forty two.w '+ ( 7t yT British Legation, TEHRAN. 29th January 1942. ANNEX 1. Monsieur le Ministre, With reference to Article 6, paragraph 1, of the Treaty of Alliance signed today, I have the honour, on hehalf of His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom, to assure your Excellency that my Government interpret the provisions of this clause as being applicable to any peace conference or conferences held at the conclusion of the present war or other international conferences. Consequently they consider them selves bound not to approve anything at any such conference which is prejudicial to the territorial integrity, the sovereignty or the political independence of Iran, and not to discuss at any such conference anything affecting the direct interests of Iran without consultation with the Government of Iran. His Majesty's Government will further do their best to secure that Iran will be represented on a footing of equal ity in any such peace negotiations directly affecting her interests. I will avail myself of this opportunity to renew to Your Excellency the assurance of my highest consideration. (Sgd.) R. W. BULLARD. His Excellency Monsieur Ali Soheily, Minister of Foreign Affairs, TEHRAN. Ill Translation. ^ No.4952. I 9th Bahman 1320 (29th January 1942) ANNEX 2. Monsieur le Ministre, With reference to article 6, paragraph 2, of the Treaty of Alliance signed this day, I have the honour on behalf of the Iranian Government to assure Your Excellency that the Iranian Government would consider it contrary to their obligations under this clause to maintain diplomatic relations with any State which is in diplomatic relations with neither of the Allied Powers. I avail myself of this opportunity to renew to Your Excellency the assurance of my highest consideration. (Sgd.) ALI SOHEILY. His Excellency Sir Reader W. Bullard. K.C.M.G., C.I.E., His Britannic Majesty's Minister, TEHRAN.British Legation, TEHRAN. 29th January 1942. ANNEX 3, Monsieur le Ministre, I have the honour, on behalf of His Majesty^ Government in the United Kingdom, to transmit to Your Excellency the following assurances 1) With reference to article 3 (2) of the Treaty of Alliance which has been signed today: the Allied Powers will not re quire of Iran the participation of her armed forces in any war or military operations against any foreign power or powers. 2) With reference to Article 4 (2) it is understood that there is no pro vision in the Treaty which requires that the Iranian Government shall bear the cost of any works which the Allied Powers carry out for their own military ends and which are not necessary for the needs of Iran. 3) It is understood that Annex 1 will remain in force even if the Treaty ceases to be valid, in accordance with the provisions of Article S, before peace has been con cluded. I avail myself of this opportunity to renew to Your Excellency the assurance of my highest consideration. (3gd.) R. W. BULLARD. His Excellency Monsieur Ali Soheily, Minister for Foreign Affairs, TEHRAN.CONFIDENTIAL. O' No. C/1 of 1942. CONFJJy 14 T- The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, s.s. Nearchus. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. .3,9^h February 1942. Residency demi-official letter No.257-S, dated the 18th February 1942, and enclosure. PERSIA-BAHRAIN QUESTION.CONFIDENTIAL: D»0« No»257*mS • The Residency, Bushire, I8th February 1942. I forward herewith a copy of a note on the Persia- Bahrain question which I handed to Bullard on my recent vl sit to Tehran. I also discussed the question at considerable / length both with Bullard and Squire. Bullard was of opinion that the Persian Government’s attitude only caused a certain amount of inconvenience and that it was undesirable to use our present position in the country to press them too far. He considered that the recognition by them of British endorsements relating to Bahrain on travel documents would amount to a for mal abandonment of their claim to sovereignty. I urged that an attempt should be made to persuade the Persian Government to accept such erdorsements for the duration of the war on the same condition as that on which they have agreed to the res toration of direct telegraphic communication between Bushire and Bahrain viz., that each party should agree that the facil ities granted would be for the duration of the war and would not imply any change in the attitude of either to the Persian cla m to Bahrain. I gathered that Bullard con + emplated representing the whole matter to the Foreign Office but I have not yet heard that he has done so* 2. With regard to the note itself there are a few points that require amplification or correction. 3* With reference to the second sentence of para 3, it would appear that at any rate so far as Bushire is concerned Muscat and Kuwait subjects are ordinarily allowed to land pro- O.K.Caroe Esquire, C*S.I.,C*I.E.,I.C.S., / vided Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, ^ New Delhi.provided they have travel documents properly endorsed by the issuing authority. Muscat subjects have to pay the cost of a *Shahadatnama 1 * and Kuwait subjects the usual visa fees. The Shahadatnama is apparently a kind of Identity certificate issued by Persian Consuls to foreigners wishing to enter Iran who have no travel documents or whose travel documents have been issued by some authority not officially recognised by the Persian Government. 4. With reference to para 4, in ew of what is stated in the last preceding para, so far as (b) is con cerned, representations to the Persian Government are only required in respect of Bahrain subjects. 5. With regard to the foot-note to para 4 the position is that the Sultan of Muscat and the Shaikh of BahraL n issue their own passports aid Kuwait subjects are granted Certificates of Identity by the Political Agent Kuwait. 6. With reference to para 6 I agreed after dis cussion with Squire to v/ithdraw my suggestion on the ground that the Persian Government cannot be expected to forgo the right to make prior enquiries about foreigners of ordinary standing wishing to visit their country on private business. It appears however from para 3 above that the prpctice already exists of grantii^g Muscat aid Kuwait subjects visas or thiir equivalent on landing. It will, I think, be better not to make say formal request to the Persian Government that thisprivilege may be accorded to Bahrain subjects as it is possible that it will be granted in practice if the Persian Governmeit concede (b) in para 4 in respect of Bahrainis for the duration of the war.-3- A further consideration is that the Political Agent Bahrain is drastically restricting the number of Persians entering Bahrain largely to meet the wishes of the Bahrain Govemmert , and it would be impolitic therefore to press for the unrestricted entry of Bahrainis into Iran. 7. I am sendii^g a copy of this letter to Peel axi Prior, and without its enclosure to Bullard. Sd. W.R. Hay.Hot# on Rtwlf of XT»lan attitude towards Bari rain mo far &amp;» tic4VcX facilities ar&lt; oono a rnad » am the ircralan Gortin^cnt oxain Bahrain a* tfiair tarritory 9 they rafua# to reootpalaa any mention qX Bahrain by a British authority in a British i&gt;aaaport and insist on tr^atin^ Bahrain subjecto as if they were Iranian aubjcot&amp;t with the following resuite* (a) It ie neoetut/y to ^ive Fritiah aubjecta Tiaitintf bouth rereia and Bahrain tuc vuML^ortB* ib; It ia io^oaslbie lor BritiaTt aabjecta Ber^anentiy residing in Bahrain to visit rersla at aXl f as no endorses*snt on a passport by tha loiiticnl i^ent t Bahrain* is recognised* and in any case they cannot obtain a visa* This is *axt: oularly inconvenient in the case of of fleers subordinate to ne» as it aeons they cannot visit ae in Bush ire • (o' So Bahrainis can visit lersia as they are not in possession of Xeralan Identity oertif iostes* Two Bahrainis not long ago (Z think since the entry of our troops into Iran) were arrested at Khorramshahr on this account* 2* (a) is a nuisance and is liable to give rise to V dlfflottltifte e*g* If a British subject wishes to pass throng Iran on a journey from Bahrain to Persia or vice*versa* when the Ira^i authorities have to be asked to give an exit visa on a passport which bears no entry visa* (b) can be overoooe in practice since the entry of our troops into iersla at any rate eo far as Bushire ie concerned* by soaking a special request to the local authorities to perolt entry without any travel document at all* This however is a most unsatisfactory state of affaire* (o) prevents Bahraini aerahants* seamen* sto** visiting Isrsla on their lawful occasions* and cannot be overcome* except in very special oases* In the saru* asan-or as (b)* / Blsabllltlee3* (a) and (bJ ^Xao to Uuaoat and Kuwait* X have not haard of ttuaoat or Kuwait oubjeota being arrefeted on iraralan soil for not being in poaaabaion of itral&amp;n identity aertlfioataa ox for being in poececalon of travel doouznente not recogrtlaod ay tha i'araian Govexniaent but X imagine thie might well ea# 4* X would atrongiy urge that the yerelan Government ahouid be aefcud at any rate for the duration of the war to reoogniee the de faoto position in the Arab Statea bordering the lerelan Gulf ani to inutruot their offlolala (a) to aocept Brltlah travel doouoente oontaining British endora«aente 9 etc*, relating to theae States provided they are in order in other rcapeote and (b) to allow eubjecta of vhaee Gtatea to vialt rarela provided they are in poeueaelon of valid travel dootnenta granted by the British or their own state authoritles** 5* There la still the difficulty that persona visiting Far ala from the Arab States by sea cannot just obtain Feralan visas at any rate without a delay of several months* The reraian Government might be asked In such oases to grant visas on landing, provided the travel documents are otherwise in order. * X cannot say off«n*nd to that extent these States issue their own travel documents.Kuwait Receipt No .jrj_C &gt;_Dated 7-Z. MM'L ' :.r- Telegram q From political Resident, Nearchus. To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. T/324. ^.ated 21 received 2 .na April 1942. Following is a repetition of Tehfcan telegram 80 begins: Addressed to Political Resident — in the Persian Gulf repeated to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs Saving. Prime Minister has asked me to express his thanks to British Authorities for having captured at Kuwait a man who had been sent by Nasir Qashqai to buy 300 rifles there, saving to senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf ends. 2. Please elucidate. Resident.■■ oeutiou. rile No. Heading. NOTES. Serial No. DEPT. Pros. 19 . Nos. BRANCH. aPolitical Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Mearchus C/422. Dated 25th April 1942. 2 . Your telegram T/b24 April 21st paragraph 2 I regret I am unable to comply with your request. I have never heard (bP the individual nor of the incident and His Highness* Secretary assures me that the Kuwait Government are equal}/’ z 1Telegram From To No.97. Code. Britain Khorramshahr. Political Kuwait. Dated 6th and received 9th September, 1945. A Persian army deserter by name Yusuf Akhund absconded to Kuwait via Iraq about 30 days ago with 30,000 Tomans Persian army funds. Grovernor has asked me to request your good offices to secure his return to Persia. I have explained position regarding extradition but it occurs to me that absconder will have entered Kuwait without proper travel papers and if you can put him across border for this reason, notifying me in advance governor could arrange to pick him up in Iraq. Should be grateful for any help you could give. MB. —BRITAIN— AtfL. &lt;Telegram Q. From Political Agent, Kuwait. To H.M. Consul, Khorramshahr.' No.841. Dated the 12th September, 1945. Your telegram No.97 September 6th. deserter. Persian 2. Shaikh has been asked to detain the man and the stolen money if in Kuwait and I will inform you of the result. 3. I should not be able to take the action you pro pose v/ithout referring to the Political Resident. LES. POLITICALc H.M. Consul, Khorramshahr. Political Agent, Kuwait. 9 V' ■ £ 8 ) Telegram Q. From To No.104. Dated the 6th and received 7th October, 1945. A* Your telegram No.841. Has anything more transpired regarding deserter ? LES. - BRITAIN -Translation of letter dated 9.10.45 from Head of the Public Security Hept., Kuwait, to Kib Richness the Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments, I have the honour to inform Your Highness that since perusing the letter received by you from the Political Agency regarding the man named Yusuf Akhund, an army deserter of the Persian Army, I have made careful investigations about this person, but we did not find him here. It may not be forgotten that if this person had actually arrived here, he would undoubtedly be found. It ix seems that he went somewhere else and had not come to Kuwait territory. Usual Ending.Telegram From To No.924. Dated the 11th October, 1945. *&gt;0 Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty f s Consul, Khorramshahr. Army deserter. Your telegram No.104 October 6th. Persian His Highness denies that the man is in Kuwait. LES. POLITICAL -'N The Hon’ble t?ie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. His Britannic Majesty’s Ambassador, TEHRAN. 2. The Political A 6 ent, KUWAIT. and has the honour to transmit to him a undermentioned document. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 16th ?:ay, 1947. !L Reference to previous correspondence : Description of enclosure : Number and Date Memorandum No. 924-S, dated the 16th May, 1947, to the Senior Air Staff Officer, Intelligence, Air Headquarters Habbaniyah. Subject Persian Consul at Kuwait.mm. No. 924 - S. PERSIAN GULP RESIDENCY, SAdHAIR. trie 16th .'ay, ly47. A To The senior Air Staff Officer, Intelligence, Air Headqmrters, iiA JUAht If AH. MhkOIJINLUk reference Appendix ‘‘B 1 ’ of Iraq Comnand Intelligence Review fio. lb for the period ending the Lth ii&amp;y, 1^47 • fc. As there is no Persian Conmlate in Kuwait, the Political Resident would be glad to know the source of the report that Abdul Hasan Riazi has been appointed First Secretary, Sd. J• Croning• for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, G, A«1,SECRET. ij’romi To ; Dates Ref : 3*1.0. Air Headquarters,^ Iraq. Tne Political Resident, Persian Gull' Residency, BjUIRAIH. r —— - 31st Hay, 1947 . S.48b0/Air Int. •Vith reference to your memorandum 924-3 of 15th Hay, 1947, the source of the report was Intelligence Summary No.15 of 20th April, 1S47, issued by the British ''Military Attache, Tehran, to whom an enquiry has been ad dres sed. No. 1092-S. 3d. J.L.HJNTBR - Capt. for Senior Intelligence Officer, Ai r Headquarters , R.'A.J?., British Horces in Iraq. Persian Gulf Residency, Bahra in, the 5 th June 19 47 . Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, K U A 1 T . with reference to Residency Printed Letter No. 925-3 dated the 15th Hay 1947. ,&lt; ij'rom : a.i.O., Air Headquarters, 'Iraq. io : The Political Resident, Persian Gulf Residency, hAHRAli, . Pate : June 19 th 194 7. Ref: o#4850/2/Air Int. Persian Consu late Appo i ntmen t• /'.‘V With further reference to your memorandum 924-3 of 15th Kay *47, the error arose out of faulty transliteration from a Persian newspaper by a translator who failed to note a small final 'h'*, the only difference in Persian between Auwait and ouetta. A corrigendum is included in Review i^o.19 issued by this H.q,' 3d. h.A. Praser - V7/Cdr. Senior Intelligence Officer, Air Headquarters, R.A.P., Eabbaniya, Brit ish P or ces in ’_Iraeg. Extract from Iraq Command intelligence Review bo• 19 - Ject ion 1. JM on-operat ional intelligence for period ending 19 j une 1947 . APPEbPIX *5 * Movement of Official s f or Persia . x x x x x Corrigendum to Appendix *3* Review Ko.16 - ABDUL HA3AH R1AZ1 to be Pirst Secretary to the Persian Consulate at Quetta, not Kuwait.Telegram From To Repeated En Clair. H.M’s Charge d f Affaires, Tehran Foreign Office No.1088 Washington. Moscow. British Middle East Office. Political Resident, Bahrain. 'h No. 63 Dated 23rd and received 24th October, 1 0 Question Resolution last night by majority of Open. My m No.1083. Majlis and Oil 102 to 2 differs considerably from draft reported in my telegram L isiderably different ■ nts (a) and (b _ w __ ially unchanged except that exploitation in (b) should read sale of oil products. A new provision is then added prohibiting negotiation of oil concessions in any form and the creation of oil companies with a foreign interest. 3. (c) is modified into a formula on the following lines. The Government may open negotiations and take the necessary measures keeping Parliament informed in all questions where the rights of the Persian people about the country 1 s national resources have been prejudiced and especially as regards the renewal of the South Persian Oil Concession. 4. Qavam in a statement made just after above resolution had been proposed said that he had been obliged to sign exchange of letters to save the people at a time when assassinations were occuring in Azerbaijan and when Tehran was practically encircled. Any patriot would have done the same. He urged that the measure should not be hastily passed without reference to the competent Commissions and that Majlis should leave the door open for further negotiations with the Soviet Union. Foreign Office please pass to Washington and Moscow as my telegrams Nos. 99 and 119 respectively. modifying 2 various - CRESWELL N o.1836-S PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN. the 26th October, 1947 Copy forwarded with compliments to:- The Political Agent, KUWAIT The Political Agent, BAHRAIN . , LB ICONFIDENTIAL No, 1858 -R , , t^ 16 Hon'ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, presents his compliments to*- 9 The Political Agent, mvaii c . The Political Agent, ' 97-7' BAHRAIN and has the honour to transmit to him a mentioned document(s). copy of the under- PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN Pated the 28th October, 1947 . REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPO^nEKCF. Residency Endorsement No.l836-S dated the 25th October, 1947 . Description of Enclosure, Number and Date 1. Commonwealth Relations Office, London telegram No,14047 dated the 25th October, 1947, 2. Commonwealth Relations Office, London, telegram No.14049 dated the 25th October, 1947 Subject MAJLI S AND OIL QUESTTfiTJ ttj IRAN 3. Commonwealth Relations OiDice, London, telegram No.14053 dated the 25th October, 1947. R6c&gt;/£;6 a ly/19I Telegram fi.IKDK. (CfiFHLR TLLEGKAW - O.T.P. - SECRET) From Commonweslth Relations Office, London, To Political Resident, Bahrain. No.14047. Dated and received 25th October 1947. . mmm Confidential. Following frors Tehran to Foreign Office No.1082 dated October 22nd repeated Bahrain Lo.GQ. Begins. Uy telegram 1072. kAJLIb AND OIL QUESTION. Prime Minister’s report is to be submitted to Chamber today. Last night the Lajlis met in secret session and according to a reliable source a draft law covering four points was proposed for discussion in open session today. (a) The Qavam - Ladtchikov letters to be considered null and void. (b) The Persian Government to carry out during the next five years geographical exploration of North Persia oil bearing areas ( mut ) it shall then be authorised to discuss exploitation with the Soviet Government. (c) fts Persia considers terms of Anglo-Iranian Oil Company concession inequitable and does not approve of itr renewal in 1933 (sic) on these terms* it is duty of Goverinaent to open negotiations with H.E.G. on this subject. (d) As Bahrain forms part of Persia it is duty of Government to enforce its rule there. 2. This story has no?*' appeared in the Press and articles supporting it have explained that the Majlis should take the opportunity presented by submission of Prime Minister’s report to re-define Persian foreign policy so as to disapprove allegations that Government and Mp^lis should be- 2 - should be informed of adoption of on anti-Russian attitude* 'Journal de Tehran” says a general revision of Persian foreign relations is necessary especially with Russia and Ureat Britain so as to safeguard Persia*s national rights and basic principle of equilibrium between influences of Persia* s neighbours. It adds tiiat Government and iwajlis are confident that this policy Y/ill be approved by U.b*A. and also by ii.M.G. which ventured on a courageous policy of recognising India's sovereign rights and by Soviet Government which is always ( ? ^r. omitted ) rights of weak countries at United Nations* ' 3. Tudeh newspaper 'Kazm” on the other hand rejects ?/hole project as a childish manoeuvre which barely conceals one-sided intention to repudiate Qavam - Sadtchikov Agreement. It says there is clearly no serious intention to implement ( three ^rouos corrupt ) dealing with A.I.O.C. and Bahrain which are quite unconnected with other issue. See my immediately succeeding telegram. Ends. - CECKO - NPG.CONFIDENTIAL. Following from Tehran to Foreign Office No.1083 dated 22nd October repeated Bahrain No.61. Begins. MAJLISS AND OIL QUESTION. It is clear that draft proposal has taken this form in the hope of forestalling Russian resentment by maintaining that there is no discrimination against them; and that it is not main purpose of Persian Government to carry out its 'duty** under (c) and (d). 2. On the other hand this latter part of ( omission ) may come to assume major importance and Persian Government, if it accepts obligation of opening negotiations with H.M.G. over (gffliggjr 9 fl) -Iranian Oil Company's concession, would tnen be prevented by public opinion from concluding them except on much more favourable terms than those of present concession. I assume therefore that H.W.G. would have no intention whatever of agreeing to open such negotiations and that they would insist upon validity of 1933 ( omission ) and continuance of concession on its present terms until 1993 3. You may wish me to make some statement to this effect to Persian Government if this resolution ? is .L-gflgged l would be glad of instructions In due course. Meanwhile it is important that any comment made by the B.B.C. and British Press and by Embassy Information Depart ment here, should be in a uniform line. For the moment I imagine that little (gx, pmtt) jL be said except to repeat the facts of the,1933 renewal of ?L Anglo -Irani«n oil Company Concession, of its expiry in 1993 and of absence of anyITelegram From To No.14053 Dated and received 25th October, 1947 S.INDIV. (Cypher telegram - O.T.P - SECRET) Commonwealth Relations Office, London Political Resident, Bahrain. I MPORTANT . Confidential. Following from Tehran to Foreign Office No.1089 dated 23rd October repeated Washington Bahrain No.64. Begins: My immediately preceding telegram para 3 If official text goes no further than this formula I no longer think action proposed in first sentence of para 3 of my telegram No.1083 necessary or desirable.. Ends.Telegram From To No. 7,39. Cypher Political, Kuwait. Repgu, Bahrain Dated the 10th November, 1947. My telegram No.1886 9th November. Water supply. 2. Persian authorities are permitting Oil Company water-tankers to bring water from Abadan only on condition that each craft carries one Persian Mav&amp;l rating to ensure that the crew do not land hore. as the water is absolutely essential it does not seem possible to protest. Politicalf&gt;th August, 1948 CONFIDENTIAL J y] sv b |yV^ Dated Dear Andrew, ReferenceX**#^conversation of a few days ago on the subject of Kuwait and Iran. Iran has recently even more vehemently than before, voiced her claims to Bahrain (Note: Incidentally, it is significant that Radio Moscow in Persian keeps reminding the Iranian Government of this claim to Bahrain, and accuses the Government of insincerity in not pressing the matter more vigorously). On the other hand the Iranian Government never mentions any claim to the territory of Kuwait. Local Iranian Government officials in Khuzistan province, when this is mentioned, merely laugh and say they have none. Telegrams for Bushire etc., to Bahrain are refused. But telegrams from Bushire to Kuwait for trans mission to Bahrain are accepted. This again seems to prove that Iran has nothing^against Kuwait, then why do their'little ’’pin-pricks” still exist, such as, passports must not have ’’Kuwait” on them if it is desired to enter Iran? Why are K.O.C. aircraft based on Kuwait refused permission to land in Iran? In view of the fact that H.I.M. the Shah has just concluded a most successful visit to Britain, and becausethere is now a strong government in Iran, surely all this can be negotiated and abolished once and for all. Why are such things (perhaps not very importnat in themselves, but still very irritating and unfair) allowed to drift on without any action taken to have them discussed and righted? Has the P.R. ever put this up to H.M. Embassy, Tehran? If so, what was the reply? Would the present not be an opportune moment to bring the matter up? I am writing to you in a private capacity as a British subject and retired officer. Yours v-wuw S R.McC. Andrew, Esq., Kuwait.KUWAIT ttb C '\^ 5th August, 1948. Andrew, Reference our conversation of a few days ago on the subject of Kuwait and Iran. Iran has recently even more vehemently turn before, voiced her claims to Bahrain (^'ote: Incidentially, it is significant that Radio Moscow in Persian reminding the Iranian Government of this claim to Bahrain, and accuses the Government o.f insincerity in not pressing the matter more vigorously). On the other hand the Iranian Government never mentions any claim to the territory of Kuwait. Local Iranian Government officials in Xhuzistan province, when this is mentioned, merely laugh and say they have none. Telegrams for Bushire etc., to Bahrain are refused. But telegrams from Bushire to Kuwait for trans mission to Bahrain are accepted. This again seems to prove that Iran has nothing against Kuwait, then why do their little ’’pin-pricks* still exist, such as, passports mus ; not have n Kuveit ,, on them if it is desired to enter Iran? Vhy are K.O.C. aircraft based on Kuwait refused permission to land in Ira i? In view of the fact that H.I.M. the Shah has just concluded a most successful visit to Britain, and becausethe'’^ i3 now s strong government in Iran, surely all this can be negotlct^d and abolished once and for all. Vhy are such things (perhaps not very importnat in themselves, but still very irritating and unfair) allowed tc drift on without any rction taken to have then discussed and righted? If so, what was the reply? Would the present not be an opportune moment tc bring the natter up? Has the P.R. ever put this up to H.rf. Embassy, Tehran? I am writing to you in e private capacity as a British subject and retired officer. Yours F.McC. Andrew, Esq., Political Agent, Kuwait.KUWAIT 5th August, 1948. Dear Andrew, Another point I would like to bring to your notice unofficially is the following. During my lieson visits I have ascertained that Liany Senior Staff employees of Bapcc, I.P.C., Qatar, Arainco and K.O.C. etc., would very much like to be c ble to visit Iren on vacation as Lt is within easy flying distance, and th^ climate on the Iran plateau is cool and agreeable in such interestin . centres such as Shiraz, Ispahan Hama ban end the capital Teheran. The main dif■iculty is the Iranian visa which is certainly not forthcoming easily to anyone working, through no fault of their own, in Kuwait or Bahrain. Csn this matter not be taken up with the British Foreign Office in order that, the position be explained to and clarified by the Iranian Government, so that foreign employees of oil companies work ing in the Persian Gulf, eve not penal!s-d bee use of territ orial claims which do not directly concern them. It iaight be suggested that special tourist visas (valid V months) he authorised by the Lupe ial Government. The advantages to Iran are that foreign capital would be spent in the country *nd that increased trade would follow. Incidentally, fruit and vegetables could be flown into Kuwait from Iran much more easily than from Cyprus or Bagdad Yours R.McC. Andrew, Esq., Political Agent, KUWAIT•i 1 he Agency, Kuwait , Dated the 11th August, 1948. CONFIDENTIAL . No.K/51 (3/4 &amp; 23/10). My dear Colonel, I enclose copies of two letters I have received from Colons?. Underwood on the subject of our relations with Persia. present attitude are of course more evident to members of the Oil Company here in ixuwait, within easy reach of Persia, than in Jahrain, end particularly to those who have connections reopening the questions at this moment depends on factors of which you and the Foreign Office will be the best judge: the Persians may seem short-sighted in their policy over tourists, but there are no doubt other factors, and the most beneficial act on their part as far as Kuwait’s economy goes would un doubtedly be the resumption of free expert of foodstuffs. 2. The inconveniencies resulting from Persia’s Yours sincerely His Excellency Lt-Colonel A.C. Galloway, C.I.E., O.B.E., Political Reside n t in the Persian Gulf Bahrain. MBR.W. Andrew, ^squire, Political Agent, KUWAIT si h~ / O Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No. F./51 (3/4 &amp; 23/10), the enclosures to which I find interesting. 2. I note they are personal and they seem to me to contain a considerable amount of hot-weather dementia At least that is the most charitable view T can nut on them. 3. There is possibly a case for reviewing the Kuwaiti - Persian situation, though T doubt it, and, if the Oil Company wish to make a representation I will consider it. They should not be prompted.■ K/14P No.(9/l/4P) his Majesty’s Pol. Resident at Bahrain presents his compliments to Political Agent, KUWAIT ' and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents., for record. British.. .Residency, Bahrain, PERSIAN GULF. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Name and Date. Subject^ Tehran letter dated 17/3/34 to Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs. Tehran despatch No.232 dated 4/5/34 to the Foreign Office. PERSIAN CLAIM TO THE ARAB LITTORAL. Xx Foreign Office Blue Print No.1 dated 24/9/34 3479a 34340 (8)copy Copies to: FOREIGN OFFICE. No.131 INDIA. No.56 BUSHIRE. No.53 17th March, 1934 My dear Minister, Your Excellency may remeinber that on more than one occasion during the past year you yourself or members of the department over which you now preside have expressed to Mr. Malletsome uncertainty as to the precise nature of the relations between His Majesty*s Government in the United Kingdom and certain Arab principalities situated on the southern shore of the Persian Gulf. In order to dispel this uncertainty I have been authorised to draw the attention of Your Excellency to the following treaties and agreements, of which the texts are enclosed 1. An agreement dated January 23rd 1899, with the Shaikh of Kuwait. 2. An agreement dated March 13th, 1892, with the Shaikh of Bahrain. 3. A treaty dated November 3rd, 1916, with the Shaikh of Qatar. 4. A treaty dated March 19th, 1891, with the Sultan of Muscat. 5. An agreement dated March 20th, 1891, with the Sultan of Muscat. The texts of the agreements with the Shaikhs of Abu Dhabi (dated March 6th, 1892), Debai, Ajma n , a n d Shar&amp;ah (dated 7th March, 1892) and Eas-ul-Khaimah and Umm-ul-Qfcwain (dated March 8th, 1892) were comnunicated to your Excellency's predecessor in Mr. Parr’s note No.228 of September 7th, 1928. • r ' edition there are other, less important, treaties and agreements between His Majesty's Government and the Govern ment of India and the Rulers mentioned in the two nreceedine paragraphs. &amp; In general terms the position's that all these Rulers have placed the conduct of their foreign relations in the hands of His Majesty's Government. I should be happy to think that, at any rate in the cases of Kuwait, Muscat and Qatar, it was owing to lack of information to which I have alluded in my opening paragraph that certain notes and semi-official communications received from Your Excellency in recent months (notable No.18103 of Mehr 29th 1312 (October 21st 1933)-) have contained expressions indicating a refusal to admit the right of His Majesty's Legation to make representations to the Persian Government on behalf of the Arab principalities. But if, as the reference in Your Excellency's note No.18103 to the correspondence between His Excellency Mizra Fathullah Khan Pakrevan and Mr. Parr in 1928 suggests, such a hope would be X illusory, I shall be hapny to explain to Your Excellency the views of my Government. His Excellency Mirza Seyyj:d Begher Khan Kazemi, Minister for Foreign Affairs. (signed) R.H. Hoare.COPY No.232 Copies to : INDIA No.95 BUSH IRE fio.93 Sir, British Legation, TEHRAN. 4th May, 1934 With reference to my despatch No.131 of March 17th last enclosing a copy of a letter which I addressed to the Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs communicating to him copies of certain treaties and agreements between His Majesty^ Government and the Government of India and certain Arab rulers, I have the honour to transmit to you the accompanying translation of a reply from Mirza Bagher Khan Kazemi. 2. This letter is couched in such oracular language that it is not easy to discover its exact meaning. Kazemi quotes from his note referred to in Mr. Mallet’s despatch No.506 of October 31st Last, a note in which he appeared to have admitted that there had at least been private conversations on the subject of our relations with the Arab rulers, but at the same time he now appears to deny that either he or any of his staff ever suggested that the Persian Government were not already in full possession of all information regarding those rulers. Mr. Mallet recollects most clearly that on various occasions last summer Anurshirvan Khan Sepfhbodi and Shayesteh, after emphasising the private nature of their enquiries, asked him about the agreements governing our relations with the Arab rulers. It was indeed as a result of these enquiries that Mr. Mallet|tcT~~^ you his telegram No.246 of September 30th last. Mr. Mallet’s recollections of his conversation with Kazemi on October 15th on the same subject is set forth in his despatch No.506 of October 31st last. 3 « t Whether or not, either privately or officially the Persian Government made such enquiries is, however, of no great importance compared with the fact that in my letter of March 17th I gave Kazemi d6cuments which evidently have caused him some embarrassment. The mere sight of them has apparently been sufficient to compel him to remind me of a series of notes in which the Persian Government have insolently asserted that they cannot admit any sort of intervention on the part of His Majesty's Government in regard to the Arab rulers on the opposite shore of the Periian Gulf. From this Kazemi goes on to reassert not only the Persian claim to Bahrain, but apparently to other places vaguely referred to as’etcetera*. 4* Kazemi letter appears to me to need a sharp retort, and if you approve, I propose to reply in the following sense The Persian Government assert that they cannot take cognisance of our treaties and agreements with Arab rulers. The only effect of^persistence in this attitude will, in fact, be that it will be impossible for the Persian Government to make any form of communication to 'these xxiJizx rulers who have entrusted their foreign relations to His Majesty's ■ Government. Such a self denying ordinance is clearly a matter of no concern either to us or to the rulers. On the other hand we are by treaty bound to represent to the Persian or any other foreign government that may be concerned any matter which the ruler of one of the Arab principalities in exclusive treaty relations with us may request us to raise with that Government. The mere fact Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I., etc,, etc., etc., The Foreign Office. /that the Persian2 /- A that the Persian Bovernment does not recognise our right to do so cannot in any way effect our duty towards the Arab ruler concerned and we should be failing in our treaty obligations to the ruler concerned if we did not bring to the attention of the Persian Government any , matter such as those regarding which we have had, in the course of the past year, to make representations. We are equally bound to insist on proper satisfaction being given and a refusal to grant satisfaction must raise serious issues. * As regards the question of Bahrain, His Excellency must surely be fully aware of our views as to this entirely preposterous claim. Moreover, the phrase ’’lands and places such as Bahrain, etcetera, which are inseparabl parts of Persian territory’’ appears to indicate some wider pretensions of which His Majesty’s Government have not hitherto been apprised. His Excellency may wish to make his meaning clearer on this point. 5. I am sending copies of this despatch to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India (No.95) and to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (No.93) I have the honour to be with the highest respect Sir Your most obedient, humble servant, (sgd) R.H. HCARE.COPY 124 Trmslgtion : From the Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs (Department Furope and America) addressed to His Majesty's Minister. No*5849 dated 10th Crdibehest, 1313 (30th April, 1934). My dear Minister, Your Excellency's esteemed note of Esfand 26th, 1312 (March 17th, 1934) together with its enclosures has been duly received. With regard to the statement made in your note to the effect that the members of the staff of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and myself have informed Mr. Mallet that information and confidence (sic) regarding the exact nature of the relations between the British Government and the Shaikhs of’the southern coast of the Persian Gulf was lacking, I have to state that this has caused much surprise to since such a statement has never been made to Mallet either by myself or by the staff of this Ministry, but on the contrary, in the course of an interview which I had with him on Mehr 24th 1312 (October 16th, 1933) when he was acting as Charge d*Affaires, I explained and pointed out to him most clearly and categorically the definite viewpoint of the Imperial Government in the matter. Moreover, during the last few years the definite views of the Imperial Government have been clearly expressed in numerous official notes e.g. in Note No.11024 of the 30th Murdad, 1307 (August 21st, 192P), in Note No,13018 of the 29th Shahrivar, 1307 (September 20th 192$ and in Note No.18103 of the 29th Mehr, 1312 (October 21st,1933). I now once more emphasise (sic) that your Excellency will, no doubt, admit that the Persian Government, in respect of conventions and agreements with which they have not been concerned or to which they have not been a party either individ ually or as a party to a multilateral instrument, have no obligation what^jrfever to recognise such treaties and agreements as official or to consider them valid so far as they concern this Government or to give effect to them. The agreements to which Your Excellency alludes are of such a nature. Therefore there exists no obligation on the Persian Government in respect of these agreements and if'any agreements, concessions, and obligations are laid down in these treaties and agreements which may be contrary to the interests and rights of Persia or may have a prejudicial effect on these rights and interests, my Government do not consider or accept them as being of practical value as evidence from a legal point of view (sie^ against Persia, Furthermore, not only does the Persian Government consider those of the agreements, treaties and concessions in question which relate to lands and places such as Bahrain, etcetera, which are Inseperable parts of Persian territory, to be neither official nor valid, but it considers the conclusion of such instruments by a third power to be contrary to the principle^ of friendship, and protests strongly and vigorously against such a step which violates the rights of sovereignty and suzerainty of Persisg in her own territory and waters. Yours sincerely, (signed) Bagher Kazemi.COPY THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S GOVT.. (E 5955/2240/91) No. 1 Sir R. Ho^re to Sir John Simon - (Received September 24) September 24th, 1934 Section 1 (No.416) His Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and has the honour to transmit herewith a copy of his note to the Persian Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs, dated the Pth September, on the subject of the treaty relations between His Majesty's Government and the Arab rulers of the Persian Gulf. Tehran, September 8, 1934. Enclosure in No.l Sir R. Hoare to Persian Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs. Gulhelc, September 8, 1934. M. le Gerant, I DULY communicated to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs a copy of the letter addressed to me by his Excellency the Minister for Foreign Affairs on the 30th April last (the 10th Ordibehesht, 1313) on the subject ofthe relations between His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom and the Arab rulers of the Persian Gulf. 2. I have now received Sir John Simon's instructions to reply as follows to the assertion of the Imperial Government that they cannot take cognisance of the treaties between Great Britain and the Arab States in question : The only practical effect of persistence in such an attitude by the Imperial Government will be that it will render impossible any form of communication from the Imperial Government to the Arab rulers who have entrusted the conduct of their foreign relations to His Majesty's Government. Such a self-denying ordinance is clearly a matter of (poncern to the Imperial Government rather than to His Majesty's Government or to the rulers concerned. On the other hand, His Majesty's Government are bound by thejr treaties with the said rulers to represent to any foreign Government, whether it be the Imperial Government or any other, any matter which the ruler of any xjtofts of the Arab states in exclusive treaty relations with His Majesty's Government may request them to raise with the said Government. 3. It follows that the fact that the Imperial Persian Government refuses to recognise the right of His Majesty's to do so cannot in any way release His Majesty's Government from their duty towards the Arab ruler concerned and they would obviously be failing in their treaty obligations to him if they did not bring to the attention to the Imperial Government matters such as those i^flfich in the course of the past year have been the occasion of representations. 4. Finally, as his Excellency Mirza Bagher Khan Kazemi thought fit in his note to mention Bahrain, I am instructed to emphasise once more that, in the view of His Majesty's Government, the Persian claim to those islands is entirely inadmissible. avail r.h; hoare.—- 26/6/3/a n FST^ICTED 14th September, l°4p. Dear Fastern Department, ^ '7 n) t&gt;*r 'Jo Your letter F . H0X7/6579/P4 the 0 ' ! st A n pu s t about Persian visas for* the employees of the Kuwait Oil fomne^ r . We have not approached the Ministry o^ ^oreifrn Affairs ws we thinV that this might do more harm then crood and we are reasonably certain that they would not relay rv^e erist- in? restrictions even though, as you sav, their claim to F U wait has not bean raised of late. In these circumstances we see no alternative but to continue^ and ie recessarv extend, our practice of issuinp r a separate passnort ^or* travel to Persia, which the holder would, &lt;5f course, present to the Perc-i^n Consul at Basrah. We have iust secured a verbal undertaking -^rom the Ministry, and are awaiting written confirmation, that the Persian Consulate-General in Tondon will in future bo authorised to grant visas to British subjects without reference, on the basis of reciprocity. Tf this works smoothly we shell e S v the Ministry to send similar instructions to Persian Consuls in Bagdad and Basra, on the*srounds that manv of our travellers make their first application ^or visas when they are in Tran. This might help the Kuwait Oil Company, but vou win o^ree that it would be premature to sav anv^hins to them at. present. r ' • Bahrain. We are conyin^ this letter to the Political ' r ‘pnr!pncv Yours ever, CBA.KCFry.N »2S Files 6/2J 6/10} 6/14; 3/4 v/ ay Telegram From To No. Code Politioal Kuwait Prodrome Bahraiu 166 Dated the 21st July, 1949. / - RFSTRICTrD , .nufc/V V&amp;e2 . l/» 'V/* ^33. A*iT&gt; t:u ft 4-t U ? S for ^ i S • 17 ■ V, U 3^ ..q# +. (oo U 4^ . He. w Beferenoe enclosure to your C.S No. 248/12/49. 2. Tour letter No. 20/32/49 and Chancery letter referred to not received here. 3. Iranian Airways have not yet as far as I know got His Majesty^ Government's approval to oper ate a scheduled service here. Position has been explain ed to their local agent. To get it they will have to apply to the Ministry of Civil Aviation as a foreign air line to use an Airfield that is for the purpose of civil aviation to be regarded as United Kingdom territory. This would appear to entail admission of our position &amp; here which the Iranians have hitherto refuded to recog nise. Once this is recognised the whole question of visas from Kuwait to Iran should be simplified 5 but until the Iranians do recognise our position there does not appear to be much to be said for a modus vivendi in which they, rather than we, are Interested to make their airline pay and to encourage their tourist trade. Procedure des- ^ HU ih orlbed in Tehran Chancery letter No. 26/6/3/4 of Sept., 14th, 1948 is cumbersome, but I do not thinK we should allow the Iranians to escape the consequences of their attitude to us in Kuwait for the slight advantage now offer ed. Oil Company personnel are at present using Cyprus and the Lebanon as summer resorts. asr. JACKSON\z£ PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. \jjj R6th May 1949. ' u(t (Zo) I forward herewith a copy of a letter from the Tehran Embassy to Eastern Department and should be grateful for any comments you may have to make on the second para. Galloway in a letter on some other subject made a reference to the ; i ^ 'long-standing question of Kuwaitis at Khorramshahr' or something of the sort. I know nothing personally about this question. Would you kindly refer me to any correspondence there may have been with the Residency about it. 2. The Embassy is I think wrong in stating that the Persian Government regard the subjects of all the Gulf Sheikhdoms as their nationals. They only claim Bahrain as part of Persia. Elsewhere they refuse to recognise our position. 3. Do Persians visiting Kuwait first obtain any kind of visa or laissez-passer and if so ftfom what source ?British Embassy, C OPY (256/5/49) Tehran. CONFIDENTIAL. 10th May, 1949. Dear Department, There are two questions about Bahrain and Gulf Shaikhdoms generally on which we should be grateful for guidance. Either through lack of continuity or because we have packed up a number of files, we have been unable to find adequate precedents in our archives. The first concerns the protection of subjects of Gulf Shaikhdoms vis-^-vis the Persian authorities while in Persia. The Political Agency at Kuwait recently asked the Consulate at Khorramshahr, at the request of the Shaikh of Kuwait, to as sist hi some of His Highness’s subjects who owned landjin Khuzis- tan and who were being subjected to vexatious demands from a local official. In the last few days a representative of the Kuwaitis in question has called at the Embassy and, in reply to his requests for help, we have put him in touch with a suitable official at the Ministry of Justice, without specifying the nature of his business or actually arranging an interview. As the Persian Government presumably regard all subjects of the Gulf Shaikhdoms - and a fortiori those in Persia - as Persian nationals, to take any official action on their behalf would, we think, be to court a rebuff and might possibly do more harm than good to the aggrieved parties. The second question concerns the formalities to be ob served by Persian nationals entering the territory of the Gulf Shaikhdoms. A Persian official on anti-locust work recently arrived in Dubai from Bandar Abbas to establish contact with a Pakistani anti-locust party and asked whether the Poli tical Officer Trucial Coast had any objection to his visiting one of the locust breeding areas. The Political Officer saw no objection but requested the Persian official to call at the Agency. On finding that his only travel document was one valid for travel 'from one port in Iran to another,' the Political Officer informed him that in view of his work he would be allowed to remain but that he must report again before departure and that for any future visits he should have valid documents. The Persian Gulf Residency have asked us to take the matter up with the appropriate Ministry. Presumably no contravention of the immigration regulations of the Shaikhdorns should be allowed to pass unchallenged, parti cularly where acquiescence might imply derogation of the rights of His Majesty’s Government and of the Rulers. It may, however, be necessary for the exact form of action to vary according to the circumstances. Thus a traveller of no importance might be deported; the master of the craft in which he travelled might be imprisoned or fined; while, as in the case of the Persian official referred to above, the offence might go unpunished provided, that the offender was made to realise the nature of his offence. It seems to us an open question whether official action should be taken in Tehran after each offence. In the present circumstances we see no reason why this should not be done. It is, however, highly improbably that such action would ever result in the Persians conforming to.our requirements since to do so would very seriously weaken their claims to the territories in question. /The Eastern Department, Foreign Office, London, S.W.lThe principle involved in this question is likely to come up in a concrete form before long in the following way. The Anglo-Iranian Oil Company have arranged with Hunting Air Surveys limited to carry out an aerial survey of the Dashtak- Sarneh region of the Persian coast next winter, which wil] involve basing the aircraft at Sharjah. One of the conditions on which the Persian Government have agreed to the project is that the Persian Air Force officer shall accompany every flight. The Political Resident has informed us that he sees no objection, provided that the Persian Officer obtains a visa or it is made clear that he is visiting Sharjah with our con sent. As we have said, it is most improbable that he will ap ply for a visa and presumably we shall have to devise some procedure which will save faces on both sides. We are sorry that we have to bother you to go over ground which must obviously have been fully explored before, but we see no alternative. We are sending a copy of this letter to Bahrain. Yours ever, Chancery.No. C/209(3/4) 20th August, 1949. Dear Sir Aupert, v Please refer to your letter No. 248/3/49 dated the 26th May, 1949. para of the Tehran Chancery letter. I have caused an extensive search to be made for any correspondence with the Residency about the question of Muwaitis at Ilhorramshahr; but have not yet been able to find any. Perhaps the Consul at Khorramshahr could find it. 3. r ost of the Persians who come here do so without any papers at all. They are allowed to land and to remain if security is given for them by a merchant of standing in Kuwait. ohters carry 2 I have no comments to make on the second recognised here. Yours ever, Sgd. C.N. Jackson .2. Sir Rupert Hay, KCI2., C3I Politicl Resident, •» _ e rs ia n Oul f Re si;en c y, Bahrain.The Persian (rulf Pesi dene B^-hraih. (141/20/49) 9th August, 1949 Dear Agency We enclose a copy of a letter ^ dated 19th July addressed by Tehran to Eastern Department. ./oald you please send any comments you may have direct to the Department with copies to us and fehran? Sir Rupert ’ s letter referred to forwarded vour letters ' r o. C. 119(6/2) of 20th Pay Political Agent; iOJ'./AlT.British Embassy, TEHRAN. IffiSTRIiTED. 19th July, 1949. (382/1/49) Jear Department, A report recently appeared in the press to the effect that the oheikh of Kuwait was sending his eldest son to Tehran in the near future. Comment suggested that the visit was connected with the possible recognition of Kuv/ait by the Persian Government. A week later it was reported that the 3heikh T s son would not proceed until after the end of Ramazan (July 27th). and Bahrain will doubtless inform us if there is any serious possibility of any of uhe Bheikh’s family coming to Persia. It seems to us just, possible that personality might be sent there to follow up the opening talks on Iranian airways reported in Dir R. may's letter No. 20/32/49 of the 11th .Tune,to Kr. B.A.B. Burrows. V/e are sending a cony of this letter to Bahrain. The whole story may be a mare's nest Yours ever, Eastern )epartment, The foreign 0 f f i c e, London, 3.;/.lcimPEmAL The Political Agent, ••••••. Kuwait. ( 23/74/49G ) For Information. With the compliments • of the Political Resident. ...,11th August. • 0 1949.COPY 1 CONFIDENTIAL . G.29/50/49 / (Dear Wright), Please refer to my despatch No.257 of the 18th July about the rumours of impending Persian action against the islands in the Persian Gulf. You may have been surprised at the Shah*s statement that the Ministry of Foreign Affairs initiated some such move, but what I have heard since suggests that it is in fact the case. I have reason to think that the Ministry are giving a good deal of attention to Persian Gulf questions, possibly| as a result of the off-shore oil project, and it would not surprise me if their objectives were something like this; (a) The two parties to stand on their respective posi tions as regards Bahrain. (b) Persia to recognise the Ruler of Kuwait and the other Sheikhdoms. (c) The Shaikhs to drop their claims to Abu Musa and Tamb (d) Kuwait and the other Shaikhs to agree, with the advice and concurrence of His Majesty’s Govern ment, to the appointment of Persian Consuls. In case the Persians make some definite move on any of the above points, it would be helpful if I could have an indi cation of your views. (Aj6 As regards Kuwait, I feel that there is something in the air. After the appearance of Iranian Airways in Kuwait, as reported by Hay in his letter to Burrows No.20/32/49 of f the 11th June, there were rumours about the Shaikh's eldest son coming to Tehran (see Chancery letter 382/1/49 of the 19th I July) and it is now announced that the Shaikh's Minister of | Finance has arrived in this country and is making a pilgrimage I* to Meshed. I am sending a copy of this letter to Hay. J.H. LE ROUGETEL. British Embassy, Tehran. 26th July, 1949. M.R. Wright Esq., C.M.G., The Foreign Office, London, S.W.l.f ^eaBcfm3 .a»3*trl9T . v fuT» ii^^2 9^\oa\e&lt;5. o f (J-rfgiivV 'T.yea) 9rf ^^o . 0V1 .io^sqesJb Y'tn ot aa^sx 0 ! enj .ranta^B noitos ists'isH sntbcieqiul lo sTijornui 9 ^^ ^-joda .ICuO as tarred srf.t it aba^Xai: J’a:&gt;'v^ &gt; tad'8 2 1 rlsd j 9dJ ds boaiiqaus noed sv/sri zsm voY !f 9onia bissrl svarf I d.sffw dud v • ' + ' v; * t &amp;ild&amp; ot aoaa9a s^eri I .9330 /Kii ;*oq .e io l taaup HuO ast -asi ot aottaaits lo Isab boos s t^stoaq I to 9Toda.ro arid lo dluaea s a* .ai-ud 9&gt;ftl satddamoa aaaw aevldoetdo aterid l.t an eataqujg -taoq oyritooqaea ‘ttorft 10 ba^da of a-^ida-'q owd eriT ( 3 ) .nlsarisH abiagsi as aaold oo-f bns 1 Ib'-uX ‘Jq isfjjH arid aatir oosa od staae^ (d) .emobrWtjsrie asrido has sau! udA od a tialo id arid 007 b -d grbUis^B oriT ( 0 ) dmsT e ' lt ? 99 , td 3 od erivisriS aarido arid bna ddswuX (b) -a^e^oO. 2 ^dea^B add *3:o adnaa^uoaoD bos aolv s .-ruaao) astpaaq lo da ^dat^qs. odd od .dnan odd ‘io ^as 10 evo.T! adtattob 9702 S/fB.-n aasieiaq odd aaso at -tmt ns evsrf M ioo I It Cir^t ^ M hluow tt , 2 Jntoq ^ods .2i f /9iv iuo^ xO aotdBO 4 at snlritf^oa el 9 Trtct Iasi I .UsiruX ,A 4 o'^\^\ao 8 ft^“ nsl-TBir *&gt; 9»«&lt;M9qq8 «dJ as.+lA .ais 9 rij 10 i \^,\0F .O i awoiTUci od 1 add 9 1 add id vbH yd bedaoaaa * * ri^ 9 i a «rii%o 6 i!\f\daf rif et 0 o«oi 91 aw aisrfj t anii'; rii: X adi id .1 arid lo ^Vv^SS 7addal YiaoasdD eos) HBidaT od andnoo iop -lad-'uai... 2 ' d-&gt;ft£riA arid dsrid baoauoaris wo a pi *• t ' bas ' ' r v r • ; • :q b SOtHB. el f-ae ;a+ ,,00 Z™ nt .herizs'i od . v'bH od aaddal at rid 1o ^qoo a gntbaas ns I . I3T:IOUOA 5,1 .H.L ?. • . 1 . ) . .pa.: drf' ta.. . h t 9omo asiaioq adT f aobaoJ .1. v,8</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000a1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/174</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000a1</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/174</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 3/4 Relations with Persia'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-01-07T14:28:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (135 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 137; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Two previous foliation sequences, both of which are written in pencil (the set from ff 1-136 are circled, the set from ff 4-122 are not), have been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns Britain's relations with Persia (also referred to as Iran in some of the correspondence). It includes the following:cases of Persian customs authorities reportedly inhibiting (and in some cases preventing altogether) the passage of persons travelling between Persia and Kuwait, allegedly because of the Persian Government's claim that Kuwait is part of Persian territory;a copy of a non-aggression clause, written in 1930 and taken from a draft of a proposed treaty between Britain and Persia;copies of correspondence between the India Office and the Foreign Office regarding whether or not the rulers of Muscat, Bahrain, and Kuwait should cancel their respective existing proclamations that give Persian vessels rights to inspect Arab dhows outside Persian territorial waters;a copy of a draft of Iran's 1942 treaty of alliance with Britain and the Soviet Union;copies of correspondence dating from 1934 between the British Legation, Tehran, and the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs [Sir John Simon], regarding Britain's response to the Persian Government's refusal to recognise certain agreements between Britain and the Arab rulers of the Gulf, which give Britain the right to represent the latter in their foreign relations.Other subjects of correspondence include the anticipated revision in (1947) of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company's concession of 1933 and the presence of Iranian Airways in Kuwait.The principal correspondents are the following: the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Political Agent, Kuwait; the Secretary of State for India; the British Legation, Tehran; the India Office; the Foreign Office; the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs; the Commonwealth Relations Office; the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Sabah [Shaikh Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ].</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commonwealth Relations Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Iran, Pahlavi dynasty</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Iran</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Customs policy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><subject><topic>Tripartite Treaty of Alliance (1942)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000a1#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>