<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000912.0x000004_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T13:29:05.513Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">THE MUNTAEIK. The tribal league which may be said roughly to occujoy the Euphrates from Chabaish to Darraji and the Shatt al Gharraf as far north as Kut al Hai is known as the Muntafik.* The link between the units of which it is com posed is of the loosest kind, being no more than a common recognition of the paramount authority of the Sa’dun. This family, which claims descent from the Prophet and is therefore related to the Sharif of Mecca, migrated from the Hijaz to Mesopotamia in the early part of the 16th century. According to local tradition, the southern borders of the ’Iraq were held towards the close of the ’Abbasid period by two large tribal groups, the Bani Malik (in the dialect pronounciation Bani Malich) in the Shamiyah under Ibn Khusaibah, and the Ajwad further north on the Gharraf, under the Al Wathal. The name of the first ancestor of the Sa’dun who approached their territories is generally given as Shabib. It is said that Kis son, Mani‘, took to wife a daughter of the ruling house of the Bani Malik and was presently involved in a feud between that tribe and the Ajwad. The scale turned in favour of the latter. The Bani Malik were defeated with considerable loss in a battle in which Mani‘ was himself killed, and forced to make their escape into Najd, taking with them Manias son, Shabib, who was the grandson of their owm Shaikh. After three years of exile, they were reinforced by some sections of the ’Ataibah, one of the most powerful tribes of Central Arabia, and felt them selves strong enough to take revenge upon their rivals. Legend relates that Shabib ibn Mani‘ came up to spy upon the camping grounds of the Ajwad whom he found at the wells of Safwan, a well-known watering place on the borders of what is now Kuwait territory. On his way back he took note of the stages of his journey and returned to Najd with a careful report of every halting place, Wird, ’Azlb, Fallahah, Qirb al ma (water, waterless, sown land, near water) and so further, until he had completed the tale of the road. Armed wdth the information he had gained, he led the Bani Malik to Safwan. where they overthrew and almost exterminated the Ajw r ad, sparing onlv a handful of men and 40 women, or according to another version of the story, 40 women with child. The remnant, whatever may have been its composition, took refuge in the Hawlzah marshes, but returned after a short period to the ‘Iraq where they were joined by the Budur, who are a section of the Buwalah ’Anazah, the Shuraifat, a tribe of Southern Arabian origin (Qahtan), and the Juwarin, long settled in Mesopotamia. Shabib, by virtue of his relationship with the Al Khusaibah and his military powers, had assumed the leadership of the Bani Malik, and to him the Ajwad addressed themselves with proposals of peace. He demanded for the killing of his father, no payment of blood money, but that he should be accorded the honours of overlord, that they should kiss his hand wdien they approached him, and that he should not be required to rise in response to their salutation. To this stipulation, wLich was regarded as an instance of high generosity, they agreed, and the Bani Malik and Ajwad, united under one chief, made so formidable a combination that they attracted a third ally, the Bani Sa’ld, a tribe of the Jazlrah. These three formed and still form the Muntafik league. The three divisions as avc know them are not tribes but tribal grouns. The Bani Sa’ld, w T ho are by far the smallest, appear to be the most co-hesive. Their district lies as yet beyond our sphere, in the desert between the Tigris and the Gharraf. Though they own some cultivation on the tail of the great canals, they would seem to approach the Beduin more closely in their mode of life than is the case with the other tw'o members of the league, and their con stituents have the character of sections of a homogeneous tribe rather than that of independent units gathered into a confederacy. The Ajwab are the least compact. Their country is on the Gharraf and on the Euphrates above . and below Nasirlyah; they are therefore mainly in * The word should probably be written with a Qaf, Muntafiq, (’ittifaq-agreement'. 194 F, &amp; P. I), s 22 thcjiostilc zcmo. They are riverain Arabs of the Shawiyah * type, half- settled cultivators and half-nomadie owners of flocks. They spend the late winter, spring and early summer in the desert with their sheep, leaving some ol their number m the reed villages by the rivers to till the fields. They have no camels but use donkeys as their transport animals ; the presence of large eads of donkeys is as distinctive of Shawiyah encampments in the desert as is that of grazing camels indicative of the proximity of Beduin tents. By ie Beduin they are regarded with not over tolerant contempt, and though some of the Shawiyah, notably the Budur, are bold fighting men, no true nomad would intermarry with them. They have been dubbed felicitously in English, Donkey Beduin. J The Ajwad seem to have lost almost entirely the sense of confederacy. A member of one of their component tribes, if asked to define himself, would invariably give the name of his tribal unit, though when questioned more closely 1m would admit that his tribe formed part of the Ajwad as opposed to the Bani Sa id or the Bani Malik. In former times, when the Muntafik coalition was much more completely under the control of the Sa’dun than it is no\v, the latter appointed the family of Manna‘, Sunnis of Hijazi origin like themselves, as inferior headmen over the Ajwad, for which reason the group is sometimes known as Ajwad al Manna'. The Manna', who are said ff Harb stock, occupy a titular position as chiefs. If a capable member ol the family happened to be available he would be the natural leader in battle, and m an assembly of Ajwad Shaikhs, Zamil al Manna', the present Bead ot the house, would be given the highest place, but they have no execu- ive power or tribal jurisdiction. The Al Wathal, once paramount, are still m existence, but they have fallen into unimportance. i ■? an 1 1 ^alik, though less homogeneous than the Bani Sa’id are more closely kmt than the Ajwad. They are mainly cultivators (Eilih, Harrathah, Jladhi) and Ma dan, men of the marsh who live by fishing, by the weaving ol reed m^fs and by the breeding of buffaloes. Just as Zamil al Manna' is nominally leader of the Ajwad, so Badr al Bumaiyidh is chief of the Bani Malik, but whereas the Al Manna' are not ’Iraqi tribesmen, the Al Bumaiyidh ai ’. ie P a F amo ? nt clan of a strong tribe of the Bani Malik, the Albu Salih, to winch their real authority is restricted. Outside the limits of the Muntafik league there are large bodies of the Bani Malik on the lower Tigris and in the Hawizah of common origin with the Bam Malik of the Euphrates. It is piobable that at one time all were part of a single entity.! Such dismember- ment accompanied by re-grouping, is the process which governs all Arab tubal evolution Mithm the Bani Malik are two ancient and powerful federations which have from time immemorial been at strife, the Bani Khaiqan and the Mujarrah. There is some doubt as to whether either are of Bani S T? k ’-n WUC £t may aCC0Unt forthe secular feud which exists between mem4 Ilie Bam Khaiqan are at present gathered under the hold of the Al tnhf f Cla r - 0l f 0n - e ° f their lar S est sub-tribes, but the Mujarrah are split into a number of inferior groups and have no common head. M- ThC mf t0ry ° f the lea £ ue is inseparably linked with that of the _dun. The very name of Muntafik, as used in the ’Iraq, refers only to the inte^l ! la , VeS and . de P endants &gt; who are reckoned to be an integral p a rt of it. INo tribesman m the ’Iraq would call himself Muntafik h -b ml £ ht ase the word lf he were in Mecca or Damascus, where his own fZ W ° Ul A b f. un hnown, while the fame of the Muntafik would be am Inn to every Arabic-speaking community. The position of the Sa’dun, a latter ol considerable importance is Southern Mesopotamia politics, has been rntentionn? \ * r lr and partly Turkish official ignorance or n 1 ’T dlll f i° f their f lation to tb e tribes. It must be borne succT lid f tl ^ bG ° ng t ^. tbe 1 social order of the desert and have not the ih the loca ! lnfli J ences which have affected the tribal population of the naq, who are, like themselves, immigrants from Arabia, but usually o an e a rlier date and as settlers on the soil have been brought into »3a ruling imm’grants J l he I3aui Khaiqaa are said to be originally Ajwad and tbe Mujarrah to be Bani Sa’id.3 more intimate contact with Mesopotamian tradition. The Sa’dCin have preserved the characteristics of Beduin Arabia. They are Sunnis and Ahl al Ba ir, people of the camel; their dirahs are in the Hamad west of the Hai or south of the Euphrates, where they have dug or reopened wells in their accustomed camping grounds. Here they repair after the early rains, and here they assume their natural part as independent chieftains of the desert. The Iraq tribes, who acknowledged them as overlords, differ from them in every particular. 1 hey are Shi’ahs, settled or half-settled cultivators and marshmen, whose link with the desert people has long been broken ; socially inferior, but strong numerically, and stronger still in their hereditary hold upon the land ., r ., Muntafik league under the Sa’dun remained until the time of Mid-hat Pasha, in 1871, almost independent of Turkish rule. From the middle of the loth century onwards, however, they seem to have paid tribute to the lurks. The first mention of this tribute is in 1747, when the BesideUt at Basrah reported that the Muntafik were in rebellion against the Turks because of the tribute imposed on them. In 1769 they again rebelled under their Shaikh Abdullah on account of arrears of the tribute which the Turks had attempted to exact.^ In 1776 the Muntafik helped the Turks to defend asrah against the Persians under Karim Khan, but were defeated and presumably submitted to the Persians during the 3 years of the Persian occupation, which ended in 1779. In May 1787 the Sa’dun Shaikh Thuwaini entered Basrah with a large force, took possession of the towm and the Turkish cct and imprisoned the Musallim, but was expelled from Basrah by the Pasha of Baghdad in October 1787. . Between 1797 and 1802 the Muntafik formed the chief bulwark of Basrah against the Wahhabis. In 1798 they marched with the Turks into Hasa against the Wahhabis, and in 1801 the Shaikh Thuwaini, already mentioned, led an expedition against the W r ahhabi Capital, but was murdered not far from Kuwait. Between 1810 and 1817 the Muntafik seem to have been in open rebel lion against the Pasha of Baghdad. In 1813 ’Abdullah Pasha of Baghdad marched against the Muntafik chief, Humud al Thamir, but was defeated near Basrah, cajitured and put to death. Upon this the Sa’dun greatly extended their powci and ruled uj) to Samawah. Baud Pasha of Baghdad attempted about ^ ^ iea h U P the tribe by nominating a rival chief in opposition to Humud, but the intrigue failed, and after the deposition of Baud Pasha in 1831, Humud s son, Majid, regained the old independence and ascendancy of the Sa dun. In 1850 the Muntafik districts were once more torn by feuds' in which the lurks feebly interfered, laris ibn ’Ajil being finally recognised as the principal chief. From this time onwards the Turks began getting a firmer hold over the Muntank by constantly changing the Shaikhs and setting them one against the other, increasing on the occasion of each change the tribute payable by the tribe. Ihus between 1851 and 18o3 the nominal tribute was increased from 200,000 to 310,000 Shamis, and the regular system of farming out the country by auction to the Shaikhs seems to have begun. In 1863 the Wali of Baghdad, Kamiq Pasha, attempted to break the tribal power by taking away altogether the Muntafik lands south of Qurnah, together with the Hai lands, and turning the Sa’dun Chief into a regular Qaimmaqam whose powers were to be much diminished and restricted to Suq al Shuyukh. A Tufjkish VTuhasibji w 7 as put in to rule the country with him. The Chief, Shaikh Mansur, rebelled against these restrictions and tried to engineer a general Arab rising against the lurks, on the express ground that the Turks w r ere attempting to interfere in the internal administration of the tribes. The Wali was forced to withdraw from his new policy, but it was'noted by the Resident at Baghdad that, if the Turks had had the strength and perseverance to carry it out, it would have been approved by the Muntafik tribes, who had suffered much oppression at the hands of their chiefs. In 1864 and 1865 the two principal chiefs, Shaikh Fahad and Shaikh Mansur, were stili in a state of veiled rebellion asaiust the Turks, owing to the attempts of the latter to break up the tribal system. Shaikh Mansur finally\ 4 took refuge with the Dhaflr, while his brother Nasir was in 1866 granted the lease of the Shaikhship, having outbid Shaikh Eahad. Shaikh Nasir was received into special favour by the Turks and he seems to have fallen under the influence of the Great Wali. of Baghdad, Mid-hat Pasha, who about 1871 induced him_ to abandon the position taken up by Shaikh Pahad and Shaikh Mansur and to welcome Ottomanizing influences among the Muntafik. This was the first downward step, and Nasir Pasha, great as his name is (he founded Nasiriyah), seems really to have been the betrayer of the Muntafik to the Turks. An attempt at a regular Turkish land settlement was made. The Sa’dim were bribed into accepting the change, by being converted into regular landowners from their position as tribute-receiving ^ chiefs. The tribes” lost their status as landowners and became tenants, and the whole of the arable laud of Nasiriyah and Suq al Shuyukh was parcelled out, by Tapu registra tion, then for the first time introduced, between the Sa*dun and the Turkish Crown. In 1872, Shaikh Nasir was employed by the Turks in settling the newly conquered districts of Hasa and Qatif, and as a reward for these services he was appointed Wali of the newly constituted Wilayat of Basrah in 1875. He proved too powerful, however, owing to the conjunction of the Waliship with the Chiefship of the Muntafik, and was exiled to Constantinople about 1877. In 1881, while Nasir was a prisoner in Constantinople, the whole of the Muntafik tiibes lose in rebellion, partly it seems owing to collisions between them and the Turkish troops stationed at the newly built cantonment of Nasiriyah, and partly because attempts were being made by the Turks to enforce the new land settlement and to make the tribesmen pay landlord’s dues to the Turkish Crown and to the Sa’dun. This rebellion was never properlv put down, but the Turks seem to have given up collecting the new land taxes and to have given considerable power to Falih Pasha, eldest son of the deported Isasir, who thereupon resumed to some extent the Ottomanizing policy of his ici l n er • In the meanwhile the Muntafik became divided in allegiance between fea dun I ash a, son of Shaikh Mansur (who was thus nephew of Nasir and first cousin of Falih), and Falih himself. Apparently at the time Falih was regarded as the Ottomanizer and Sa’dun as the exponent of the old tribal principles. Sa’dun Pasha, in consequence of his hostility to Turkish influence was at this time a friend of the Shaikh of Kuwait. He maintained himself ?g a ; 1 ^ iahh mainly by plunder and robbery. He first came into prominence m 1900, when he raided Ibn Eashid in order to please the Shaikh of Kuwait Ibn Bashid threatened reprisals on Kuwait, and marched to attack Kuwait tG 7* m 17 ' -n 11 ? was .confronted by the forces of Shaikh Mubarak of Kuwait and of Sa dun Pasha, with some Turkish troops, and was finally persuaded to with draw, on the promise that Sa’dun Pasha would be hunted down. Sa’dun Pa&lt;dn thought that he had been deserted by Mubarak in the course of these neeotia- ^nno 1 and hG a 1 nd Mubar , ak s,3em never to have beeu on good terms again In iOOS he caused a great disturbance among the Muntafik by practising extortion on the Jazirah tribes, presumably those which owed allegiance to Shaikh Falih A small Turkish force was sent against him and together with the Colonel wn« massacred by him at Shatrah, but in 1904, he was taken back into favour of cue lurKs. Between 1904 and 1908 the Muntafik continued to divide their alleeiance between the two cousins, Sa’dun Pasha and Falih. In the spring of 1908 Fahh died,_leaving no son of any age or force of character to succeed him so that Sa dun become clearly predominant in the tribe. In 1908 Sa’dun seized the opportunity of the revolution and came out as a strong supporter of the Com mittce of Union and Progress. He was therefore favoured by the oflicMs' while Fahh s family was thrust into the shade. Sa’dun’s championin-of the cause of the Committee gradually brought him into conflict with Saivid Talih of Basrah, who, after flirting with the party of Union and Progress, had be&lt;uin to promote the opposing Arab movement. Confident in the support of Ue Union and Progress officials, Sa’dun Pasha began to exercise great tyrannv among the Muntafik ; he put many of the minor Shaikhs to death, and ex-tended5 move and more his system of blackmail and extortion. Finally in ]910, Nazim Pasha, Wali of Baghdad, adopted the policy of governing the whole of the Muntafik country through Sa’dun Pasha, whom he practically appointed Mutasarrif of h asiriyak. He supported him unreservedly and would listen to no complaints against him. Great discontent against Sa’dun Pasha, fomented by the party of the sons of Falih Pasha, developed among the tribesmen, who, in March 1911, took advantage of his defeat in an expedition against the Dhafir to rise against hiim The whole country was in an uproar and in June 19ll, a Turkish Commission was appointed to enquire into the cause of the rising. It appeared ^ that one of the main causes was that Sa’dun Pasha, acting as^a Turkish official, had attempted to carry out the Turkish policy of disarmament among his own tribesmen. This had naturally made him intensely unpopular. The commissioner, however, was understood to “ attribute the Muntafik troubles to the fact that the arable lands of the tribe are in the hands of a few powerful Shaikhs, who oppress their fellow-tribesmen and keep them at variance, and that the proper remedy is a thorough-going partition of the lands.” This was a rare instance of penetration on the part of a Turkish Committee of Enquiry and there is little doubt that they had hit the right nail on the head. At the bottom of all the Muntafik troubles is an agrarian difficulty such as has stirred men’s minds from the time of Tiberius Gracchus to the time of the Irish Land League. Sa’dun Pasha, with his son ‘Ajaimi, had been seeking to maintain himself in the neighbourhood of Xasiriyah against his rebellious tribesmen. But on the assembling of the Committee of Enquiry, the Turks withdrew all official support from him and, entirely reversing their policy, sought to enter into direct relations with the tribesmen and to jnepare the way for an individualistic regime and for the last step in the smashing of the tribal system. Saiyid Talib, Naqibzadah of Basrah, who had not yet appeared in open opposition to the Committee of Union and Progress, nor openly espoused the side of the Falih family against Sa’dun, was sent by the Turks to try and get hold of Sa’dun Pasha. He managed to decoy him on board the gunboat “ Marmaris ” near Suq al Sukyukh and immediately took him off in confinement to Basrah and handed him over to the Wali, leaving ‘Ajaimi and Sa’dun’s other sons at large. This act of treachery on the part of Saiyid Talib was never forgiven by * Ajaimi and threw him permanently on the side of the Committee of Union and Progress and against the side of the Arab Party under Saiyid Talib, insihte of the way in which Sa’dun Pasha had been treated by Turkish officialdom. xn July 1911 Sa’dun Pasha was sent in confinement to Baghdad and was thence removed in August 1911 to Aleppo where ho died suddenly on 25th November 1911, as was officially reported of “ apoplexy and heait failure,” but, as was generally believed, of poison. ’Ajaimi remained at large in the neigh bourhood of Nasirlyah as an outlaw. During the interval between Sa’dun Pasha’s capture and death the sympa thies of the whole Muntafik trible (including even his enemies, the Falih family) seem to have veered round in his favour, presumably because he was no longer in the position of an Ottoman official but was obviously out of favour with the Turks. After the death of Sa’dun Pasha the Muntafik country was administered from January to November 1912 by a Military Mutasarrif, Farid Beg, who was a staunch adherent of the Committee of Union and Progress and was therefore on friendly terms with ’Ajaimi. ’Ajaimi, as already explained, was on the side of the Committee out of hatred of Saiyid Talib, the betrayer of his father, who was new drifting more and more into opposition to the Committee and was intriguing with ’Ajaimi’s cousins and rivals, the members of the Falih family, Mizyad Beg, ’Abdullah Beg and others. In October 1912, when a reactionary movement against the Committee was^ threatened in Con stantinople, a telegram was sent by one of ’Ajaimi’s relations to say that ’Ajaimi was ready to march on Constantinople to frustrate any attempt at reaction, In the same month ’Ajaimi attacked and robbed his cousin Mizyad Beg (probably with the connivance of the Mutasarrif, Farid Beg) of a very large sum and came into conflict with Mizyad’s brother, ‘Abdullah Beg,6 The Committee of Union and Progress had been temporarily overthrown r in November 1912, and Saiyid Talib was paramount at Basrah and in favour with the Wali, who was a creature of Kiamil Pasha. ’Ajaimi was declared an outlaw, owing to his attack on Mizyad; the Ealih family was received into full official favour, and the Ocmmittee partisan, Earid Beg, was removed from his post at Nasiriyah. ’Ajaimi, irritated by these events, threatened an attack on Basrah in November 1912 and there was a panic in the town, which Saiyid Talib had helped to put in a position to defence. ’Ajaimi was, however, dissuaded from pressing his attack and retired. In January 1913 the Committee resumed power, by a coup d'etat culmin ating in the murder of Nazim Pasha and the removal from office of Kiamil. The partisans of the Committee were immediately installed in power in Basrah and ’Ajaimi once more found himself on the side of the Turkish officials, while Saiyid Talib was in opposition. Finally in June 1913, Saiyid Talib stood forth at Basrah threatening open rebellion against the Turks. The Committee then evolved the scheme that ’Ajaimi’s old friend, Earid Beg should he sent from Baghdad to be Military Commandant of Basrah and if possible arrest or kill Saiyid Talib, while ’Ajaimi with his tribesmen should help against Basrah from the desert. ’Ajaimi’s hands were set free by a reconciliation patched up by the officials of Samawah between him and the Dhaflr tribe. He advanced against Basrah and Saiyid Talib’s assassination was expected at any moment, but Saiyid Talib suddenly got in the first blow and had Farid Beg assassinated in open day in c Ashar. ’Ajaimi then retreated and is said to have complained subsequently that he had not been properly supported by the Turks. During the whole of 1913 the Muntafik country remained in disorder, ’Ajaimi was now apparently officially recognised as Shaikh of the Muntafik, but was unable to control the tribes. He worked in concert with Ibn Bashld against the Dhaflr. In April 1914 the Wali visited Suq al Shuyukh and saw ’Ajaimi and a new plot seems to have been concocted against Saiyid Talib, who had meanwhile been growing in power at Basrah. In May 1914 adher ents of ’Ajaimi began to drift into Basrah and Saiyid Talib was once more in danger of assassination but he took so firm an attitude that the Wali banished ’Ajaimi’s adherents from the town. ‘Ajaimi remained, hanging about not far from Zubair, until war broke out in November 1914, when after some show of indecision, he threw in his lot with the Ottoman Government. The tribes have n(frer acquiesced in the degradation in their status from landowners to tenants, nor have the Sa’dun been able to enforce to the full the rights they acquired from the Ottoman Government. With the weakening of the central authority since the beginning of the constitutional era in 1908, and the general deterioration in local administration which followed on the Italian and Balkan wars, the official sanction for which the Sa’dun bartered their old tribal prerogative has proved a broken reed. For several years before the British Occupation the tribes had refused to pay rent, and their attitude is one of extreme unvillingjiGss to be drawn back into the state of subserviency which was imposed upon them. At the same time the prestige of the Sa’dun chiefs, combined with the sedulous preaching of the Jihad by pro-Turkish Saiyids, and the yet stronger inducement offered by the immediate rewards of war, whether they took the form of loot or of Turkish subventions, brought the Muntafik league out against us in 1914. The work of pacification &amp; began with the occupation of Nasiriyah and Suq al Shuyukh in July 1915 and in spite of the proximity of hostile influences, has made fair progress ; 'but no finai settlement of the Muntafik district can be reached until the rival agrarian claims of Sa dun ail tribesmen have been adjusted.■ —' : ■ &lt; 6&gt; : 7 AL SA’DCTN. Table I. ’Abdul Muttalib. ’ Abdullai. I Muhammad the Prophet. Fatimah. Ahn TJlih. I ’Ali-Fatlmah. Husain. I Zain al ’Abidin. Umm Kulthum. Muhammad Baqir. 'Abdullah. ’ Abdullah al ' Araj. Ja’far al Hujjah. ’Ali Muhammad. Tahya al Nashabah. Muhammad. Amir 'Dbaidallah. Ya’qub. Yahya. Muhammad. Amir Ahmad al Qasim. Amir Bashim Baud. I^hid. ‘Abdul Wahab. 'Ali. 'Ubaidullah. Muh_anna al 'Araj. A Qasim al Fulaitah al Yatim. _Hashim. {Al Hawashim descevded- from him.) *lsa Shaihah. Jammaz. Ob. A.H. 704. Mansur. Ob. A. H. 726. Qasim. Muqbil. ‘Atiyah. Hadaf. {From him are dejcended the Al Hadaf.) Malik. i Nughaimish. (6) Mani\ 1 (6) Shftbib. (7) Shabib. {Migrated to ‘Iraq.) {Al Shabib.) Barakat. {Migrated to Hatolzah.) _ Salih. (Al Salih, i.e., Al NijriSj Al ‘Ali, Al _ Hamadah, Al Sabti.) (Migrated to Tunis ; his descendant is •) ‘Ali al Maghribi. (1) Thamir. (Al 8a’dun.) 1 (2) ‘Aodullah. (Al Muhammad.) Thuwaini, 1c. in Najd 1801. Najm. (3) ‘Abdul Mun’im. (Al Fodhav.) (Table 3.) (4) Rashid. (Al Rashid.) (TabU 3.) Mughamis. (Al ‘Aziz.) (TabU 3.) -Saqr. LAI Saar.) (Table 3.) Humad. (Table 2A.) Muhammad. (Table SB.) Mansur. (Table SC.) Rashid. (Table SB.) Nasir. (Table SB.) 'Abdul Muhsit (Table SB.) Salih. Table SG.) The only people who are correctly called Al Sa’dan_are the descendants of Thamir (1) The descendants of ‘Abdullah (2) call themselves Al Muhammad after ‘Abdullah’s father. They are now few iu number. The descendants of ‘Abdul Mun’im (3) are called Al Rodhan. The descendants of Rashid (4) call themselves Al Rashid al Badr to distinguish them from the descendants of Rashid ibn Thamir. The descendants of (6), (6) and (7) are sometimes lumped together as Al Shabib, but (7) are the real Al Shabib and (6) is seldom included. ‘Abdullah. (Table SR.) ‘Ah. (Table SI.) cI*II—I—HA NT SA’Tr» DIVISION</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000912.0x000004_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/20/63</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000912.0x000004</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/20/63</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'The Muntafik. Al Sa'dun, Bani Malik, Ajwad, Bani Sa'id, Bani Huchaim'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1917/1917</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-03-09T10:20:29</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (87 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 89; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume contains details of the Muntafik [Muntafiq], a confederacy of tribes in the Middle East, which is made up of tribal groups including the Bani Malik, Ajwad and Bani Sa'id. The volume opens with a historical outline of the development of the group before providing further details about members of the confederacy.There is a map on folio 18 which outlines the divisions and locations of the Bani Malik, and there are genealogical tables for Al Sa'dun between folios 7-17. Folios 19-87 contain lists of the tribes represented under the Muntafik. For some tribes, there are brief notes relating to their location and how they are viewed by other members of the confederacy and by the British.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Muntafiq (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Banī Mālik (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl ‘Ajwad (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Banī Sa‘īd (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Sa‘dūn (Family)</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Cairo Intelligence Department, Arab Bureau, Basra Branch</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Middle East</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Tribes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000912.0x000004#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>