<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000394_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T19:34:45.058Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I, /I ln ' - ^ &lt;v 1. - &lt;v 1. - '''Conf idential No.C/TC-202. Political Agency, © Bahrain, 25th November, 1950 / I have approved the draft Concession Agreement handed to me by Messrs. Garrett and Lower today. I have taken note of the differences of this draft from the draft Agreement which we approved in May last. I have initialled each page of the draft approved and am sending it back to Mr. Garrett with this letter. 2. As instructed in my telegram No.31 of 4th May, you should not witness the Abu Dhabi conmercial concession before re ceiving the reply required from the Shaikh to our letter concerning the Political Agreement. P.D. Stobart, Esq., M, Political Officer, Tn Sharjah.Telegram G.T.C Fr*^ Political Sharjah To Political Bahrain No ISO fit 26th Oct.1960. Your C/TC 182 sea bed. 2, Arab assistant was present at signature of all proclamations. The actual document used was in each case physically that forwarded under Bahrain letter C/S 81 of 8th June 1949 of which a carbon copy should be on your file. 3. Meanwhile, I will try to retrieve Shaikh’s copies if still in existence. Political9 Confidential. &lt;V£&gt; C- ffC ■* f &amp; 3. HL ^ *? ?- ^ src* Political Agency, Bahrain, 24th October, I960. j 1 ^ © v ^ f Please let me have, as early as you can, five copies of the Arabic text of each the sea-bed proclamations issued oy the ohaikns of the Trucial Coast, exactly as signed in original, pointing out any differences or clerical errors you can discern in the texts. P.D. Btobart, Bsq., Political Officer (Trucial Coast), Sharjah.© / \ k\ Conf idential. .0629/2/50 Dear pelly, British Agency, Sharjah, December 6th 1950. As reported in my telegram No.164 of 4th December the sea-bed concession agreenent between the Superior Oil Company and Shaikh Shakhbut bin Sultan was signed by the Shaikh on the one hand and Mr. R.J, Garrett on behalf of the Company on the 2nd December 1950. 2. I flew to Abu Dhabi with Mr. Ali Bustani in the early afternoon of the 2nd December. Mr. Garrett and Mr. Lower who had travelled in the same air craft, retired to the guest house while I presented myself to the Shaikh and obtained his seal to the letter accepting the conditions laid down in your letter No. C/TC-68. The original, a copy, and a draft translation of Shaikh Shfikhbut»s letter of acceptance are enclosed. 3. You will notice that Shaikh Shakhbut refers to 'your letter No.C/TC-68 dated the 2nd December 1950' whereas your letter was originally dated the 18th April 1950. It seemed to me incongruous that a Imtter dated in April should contain a reference to an agreement signed in the following December, and with the Shaikh's full understanding and approval I altered the English and Arabic dates of your letter to the 2nd December 1950 = the 22nd Safar 1370, respectively, initialling the manus cript alteration. Both the original of the letter, now held by the Shaikh, and the copy held here have been so altered. I hope you have no objection to my having done this/..•• C.J. Felly, Esq., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain9 / - 2 - (j) this; if you have none, perhaps your own copy of the letter might be similarly amended, 4. After obtaining the Shaikh’s sealed reply to your letter, I joined the Company’s representatives in the Guest House and together with Mr. Ali Bustani checked the various copies of the agreement. Everything appeared to be in order, in conformity with the text you had initialled. 5. Vie returned to the Fort in a body, ai,d the Company’s interpreter read the agreement through to Shaikh Shathbut. He expressed himself satisfied end retired for five minutes’ prayer. On his return, I asked him if he had any questions to raise or if there were any points in the agreement which were not quite clear to him. He replied that he had no queries and was ready to affix his seal to the agreement. All six copies of the agreement were thereupon sealed and signed, and witnessed by me. 6. The Company’s representatives, who had brought a suitcase of paper money with them, then mode payment of fis. 1,500,000/- under Article 4 of the agreement. The Shaikh was ready to sign a receipt for the money without seeing it, but I asked that it might be produced for my own satisfaction and this was readily done, 7. A further sum of Es. 60,000/- was paid over to be shared among the members of the Rulers ’’Representation Office” (see Article 1 (e) of the Agreement). As Zaid bin Sultan was absent in Buraiml, his share was accepted and signed for by Shakhbut. It appeared to me that this payment was more in the nature of a gift than an advance for services rendered or to be rendered. 8. My part in the proceedings being at an end I withdrew, but I learnt later that a gift of &amp;. 3000/- was made by the Company to the brothers’ mother Salamah bint Buti and that the brothers themselves were expecting further gifts in kind.3 9. jwfore^ieavlnc Abu Dhabi oft the 3rd December, I was given a signed and seeled copy of ^agreement which I shall keep in the archives here until X receive other instructions from you. Mr. Garrett told me before he left that he would deliver a further copy to you on his return to Bahrain. Yours sincerely, H.D. Michell tTranslation of letter &lt;fc;ted the 2nd December 1950 corresponding to the 22nd Safar 1570 from .Shaikh Shakhbut bin bultan bin Zaid, Ruler of Iftiabi 9 to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments, I have the bonour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter Bo. C/TC-68 dated the 2nd December 1950 equivalent to the 22nd Safar 1370. I inform you hereby th t I agree that my concession with Superior Oil Company shall be subject to all the conditions which you mentioned in your letter. Usual EndingTV*POLITICAL AORSKMENT BETAKEN HI3 MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT IN TH5 UNITED KINGDOM OP GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND AND THE SUPERIOR OIL COMPANY REGARDING THE OIL CONCESSION AGREEMENT WITH THE SHEIKH OP ABU DHABI This Agreement dated the 15th day of Aprll t One thousand nine hundred and fifty le made between Hla Majesty's Government In the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland (hereinafter called 'His Majesty's Government') of the one part and The Superior Oil Company, acting as agent for a company (hereinafter called 'the Company' which expression shall where the context so admits be deemed to Include Its successors anchor assignees) to be formed by the above-named company of the other part. Whereas upon the aforesaid agent concluding with the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi (hereinafter called 'the Sheikh') an oil agreement (hereinafter referred to as 'the concession') certain responsibilities will devolve on His Majesty’s Government, the agent has agreed with His Majesty’s Government as follows, notwithstanding anything contained in the ooncession:- 1. The Company, any transferee Company or Companies and any subsidiary Company or Companies that may be created in connexion with the Company’s operations under the concession shall, except with the prior consent in writing of His Majesty’s Government, be and remain a British Company registered in any of the countries of the British Commonwealth of Nations or an American Company incorporated in the United States of America, of which no more than 49 per cent of the capital or voting power shall be directly or indirectly controlled by persons other than British subjects or United States citizens. The obligations and benefits of the concession shall /not be 2.not be transferred to any other Company without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty’s Government* The employees of the Company in Abu Dhabi shall at all times so far as is consistent with the efficient carrying on of the undertaking be British subjects or United States citizens or subjects of the Sheikh. With the consent of His Majesty’s Government, which consent shall not be unreasonably withheld, persons of other nationalities may be employed if in the opinion of the Company they are required for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking. The importation of foreign labour not of United States or Suropean origin shall be subject to the approval of the Political Resident, Persian ij-ulf, which approval shall not be unreasonably withheld. One of the superior local employees of the Company shall be designated chief local representative of the Company in Abu Dhabi. The approval of His Majesty’s Government shall be required for the person so designated but such approval shall not be unreasonably withheld. He will be ordinarily resident in Abu Dhabi and will be responsible for the Company’s local relations with the Abu Dhabi authorities. These local relations shall always be conducted through the Political Agent at Bahrain or his representative on the Trucial Coast, except as regards routine oil business, which may be transacted through the official Representative of the Ruler referred to in the concession. Subject to the terms of the concess} undertakes at all times to pay wishes of the Sheikh and to thepolitical Agent ond the Political Be©ident f Persian Ot*l£V' Tho oonpany also undertakes to recognioe the Jurisdiction exorcised in the Trucial State© under the Tracial State© order in Council* 6 * The right given to tho Company by the concession to utilise moons of t^moportation ^ air shall be subject to any regulation© regarding civil aviation in force in Abu Dhabi* 7 * The Company shall not construct any landing-ground without the prior consent of Hi© Majesty*s Government and the Sheikh and except in accordance with the terms and conditions of such consent which ©hall not be unreasonable and any landing-ground so constructed shall be used only in accordance with ouch terms and condition© as may be laid down by Hi© rnjeoty s Government and the Sheikh which ©hall not be unreasonable* s 6 * The Company shall not have tho right to use or occupy t and shall not include in the areas selected for the purpose© of its operations* any sites which may have been selected by or on behalf of the Shel’ch or Hie B&amp;Jeoty f 3 Government feu* defence purposes* for aerodromes* aeroplane or seaplane bases or for wireless and telegraph installations or in connexion with the development of harbours* provided that with tho consent of Hie Majesty's Government which shall not be unreasonably withheld the Company £*011 have the right to use for the purposes of It© operation© such harbours a© nay be developed by the Sheikh or Hie Majesty*a Government if there is not reasonable harbour accommodation available elsewhere* 9 * Telegraph* wireless and telephone installation'-)* ^.f any* maintained by tho Company shall bo for use only /inin its business ana. as nroviSM in the concession amfi shall be bo const rue tee and operated that their operations shall not interfere with the operations of each \virelese f tolesraph or telephone installations as may be established by the Sheikh or Hie Majesty f 8 Oovemnent# 10* If and when the Oouoany oonoidero that it is desirable to erect a refinery at Abu Dhabi f it will examine with Els Majesty f s Ooremuent the qaeation of the type and eapaeity of the refinery* 11* The Company undertakes to do nothing to prejudice the fixing of the exterior boundaries of the sea-bed area appertaining to Abu Dhabi and not to dispute with the Sheikh or His Majesty^ Goremment regarding these boun&amp;arx ea* Until the fixing of the oen-bed boundaries the Company will refrain from drilling operation© or other works permanently affecting the soa-bsd or oub-soil in any area or areas which the Sheikh or His Elajesty’s Oorertaent may define* 12* The Company undertake to comply with all reasonable requirements of His JJaJesty f s (hnremnont affecting navigations fishing and. pearling in the waters of the Persian Gulf* 13* In the ©rent of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of either of which His Majesty f 8 Goverapent shall be the sole judge) His Majesty’s Ooverrra^t shall have the right of pre-emption of all crude oil and products thereof produced under the agreement between the Company and the Sheikh in accordance with the terms of the schedule hereto* 14* The Company acknowledges the special treaty relations now existing between Bis Majesty*a aovenment and the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi and the rights and obligations devol ving therefrom with regard to the Sheikhdom of Abu Dhabi* /r13* I?!)© ^persons ana eorapanlos deoignatod ac agents In the proamble of this Agroement are hereby given the right to assign their rights, privileges and obligations under this ^greeraent to the Ckxrrpany 5 and they s’^all InTora His Majesty’s dovemuent aocordingly* £he Goriww shall speelfioally asmiae all these same righto, privil^ee and obligations# Upon ouch aecignment the persons and oompenieo aforesaid deoignatad as agents shall be discharged from all liability hereunder# 16* The concession may, at the request of His Majesty’s Cknrem vant, be terninated by the Sheihh on the ground that the Company has failed to observe any of the * terms of this ^greeient between the Company and His Majesty’s Government, and In the event of notice of mi h termination being given the arbitration provioi ne of the concession email apply if the Company considers that termination is not Justified# IK rraass whereof Mr# Hichaei Robert Wright, C#ri # o,, on behalf of His ISaJosty f a Government * and Mr# adwln L*smith, on behalf of the Superior Oil Company, have hereunto sot In the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of which Hi© Majesty’s Oovemnent shall be the ©ole Judge) ~ (1) His Majesty's Government shall have the right of pre emption of all crude oil gotten under the Concession granted by the Sheiidb to the Company and of all the products thereof and shall have the right to require the Company to the extent of any refining capacity it may have in &amp;bu Dhabi to produce oil fuel that shall * their handa# gim scsirau above £8£am&amp;JiSl Pre-emption Clause. /complyV • eoraply with the A&amp;almlty 8|&gt;eoifieation© at the tirao provided thiit Aba Dhabi oli be of a suitable hind and quality for this purpose* (2) She Cofi3i&gt;aiur shall us# its utcicot endeavours to Increae© so far as reaconably possible uith ead.sting facilities the eup &gt;ly of oil and/or products thereof for the Government to the extent required by the Oovonnent* (3) The Oorapany shall with every reasonable expedition and so as to avoid damurrage on the vessel or vessels eongciged to convey the sarie* do its uti^oat to deliver all oil or products of oil purchased by t e Oovernnent under their said right of pre-emption in the quantities at the time and in the naimer required hy the Government at a convenient place of shipment or at a place of storage In Abu Dhabi to be determined by Hi© Majeat f e (kwaranent* In the event of a vessel employed to carry any such oil or products thereof on behalf of His Majesty being detained on detfttVTCg# at the port of loading the company ohall pay the amount due for demurrage according to the terms of the alerter party aitf/or the rates of loading previously agreed with the company unless the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Ofmapany* Any dispute which tasy arise as to whether the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company ©hall be settled by agreement between His Majesty f s dovennent and the Company# and# in default of ouch agreement, the question shall be referred to two arbitrators# on© to be chosen by Hi© Majesty f a Govemaont (or the Political Resident) and the other by the company# with power to appoint on lanpirc in case of disagreement# such arbitration to be held in E^lund and to be doomed a reference to /arbitrationarbitration under the provisions of the Arbitration Act of 1889 (52 and 53 Viet. c. 49) of the United Kingdom Parliament, or any statutory modification or re-enactment thereof for the time being in force. (4) The price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty’s Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery as the same shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last preceding subclause. To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company shall furnish for the confidential information of His Majesty’s Government, if so required, particulars of the quantities, descriptions and prices of Qatar oil or products sold to other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty’s Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of such oil or products. His Majesty’s Government shall be at liberty to take control of the works, plant and premises of the Company in Abu Dhabi and in such event the Company shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf of His Majesty’s Government. Compensation shall be paid to the Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty s / GovernmentOovemFaont of the patera oo»ferred by thia aubaatiae# /uny aueh compenjetlon ahall be settled by agreement between Hlo Liajeaty’a OoYemriarjt and the Company or* in default of agreer^mt* by arbitration in the manner provided by suboltmae 3* Signed and delivered by the eaid Michael Robert Wright on behalf of His ? 1ajerity , a Government# Sirned end delivered by the said ^dirin L» Smith on behalf of the Superior Oil Company# In the pr isonce ofs</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000394_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/4/10</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000394</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/4/10</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 0629/2 Correspondence regarding the land beneath the sea outside territorial waters'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1950/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-03T10:48:33</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (25 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in reverse chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 27; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding oil concession grants for land beneath the sea beyond the three mile territorial limit. The correspondence is principally between the British Agency at Sharjah, the Political Agency at Bahrain, and Shaikh Shakhbut bin Sultan Al Nahyan [Shakhbūṭ bin Sulṭān Āl Nahyān], the ruler of Abu Dhabi.The file covers the oil concession granted by Shaikh Shakhbut to the Superior Oil Company (California) for the subsoil beneath the sea beyond the three mile territorial limit. It includes the political agreement signed by the British Government and the Superior Oil Company on the 15 April 1950, wherein the obligations of the former are stipulated.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Superior Oil Company</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Abu Dhabi, Āl Nahyān dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Trucial Coast</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000394#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>