<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000067_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-08T10:22:04.338Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">-- ■ j -— ^ k&gt;&gt; 9 7 No. 5/17/33/49 —X British Consulate, (j&gt;s Muscat, December 7, 1949. PROMULGATION OF FRESH NAVIGATIONAL INFOrNATION. With r^ferenc# to yc5ur circular letter No. III-P.G.(3)A Rfttert the 16th November 1949 to all shipping companies and copy to me, I have to inform yon that there is e grs flashing light at Muscat^which it is understood is maintained by the Basra Port authorities at present.and Alwr-two oil leading lights - one red light on this Consular Clagstaff am^juiother light behind the Consulate on the hill'/are still maintained by the Government of India. The maintenance charges for these two lights are about Rs. 27/- a month. 2. If these lights are necessary which it is believed they are f it seems that they should be taken over by your service and maintained by it. I should be glad of your views. Your I am* Sir* obedient Servant, The Secretary, P.G. Lighting Service and Supetintendent of Lights and Buoys, His Majesty's Consul, iftiscat. ‘RAHRAiN x copy to The S.N.TT^.G., Bahrain The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.(V) Bahrain. 91^.9 No.III-»P0(3)/1 To all Companies concerned -ii±Li/S&gt;£*2*li Dear Sirs, PROMUL GATION OF FRE SH NAVIGATIONAL INF ORMATION Except within BASRAH PORT limits, there 1$ at present no organisation for the speedy promulgation io all concerned of new navigational information arising in the PERSIAN GULF. It has now been arranged that the Secretary, Persian Gulf Lighting Service, should undertake the co-ordination and distribution of this information. Commercial companies are therefore requested to send him(with a copy to the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf) details of any new navigational marks erected, old marks changed or removed, or other navigational information discovered, which does not fall within BASRAH PORT limits. In order that it may be of full value it is essential * that a report be made of all new information at the earliest possible moment. As far as oossible, the above information may please be given in the form below:- Subject Position- Latitude Longitude Details Authority reporting _ „ This letter is issued according to instructions fro the Senior Naval Officer. Persian Gulf, contained in his letter No.P.G.88/102A9, dated 11th November \$b9.MOW.21/^9/139 MINISTRY OF WORKS, POLITICAL RESIDENCY BAHREIN. 30th April, 1949 The Secretary, Peraien Gulf Llghtimr Service, Bahrein. Reference your letter PG/HPA/1/1 to Muscat dated 26-4-49. I am sorry to have to inform you that the Ministry Of Works forman eleotrition in Muscat is at uresent on sick leare in India. In any case he is not capable of undertaking the type of work you require doing. May I suggest that the work be let out contract by H.B.K s Political Agent ae when the Ministry Of Works forman does return he will have ouite a lot of re-pirs and alterations to do. We have Just had to send to Bombay for an engineer to carry out work for ourselves at Muscat. May I also propose that P.G.L.S apply to Ministry Of Transport London for official Ministry Of Works services. Then we could claim extra staff. As ve are under staffed and over worked at present and shall be for the summer I am afraid we will not be able to complv with any but the most minor requests. ^ X icc. Copy H.E. Political Kesident, Bahrein. Copy to Political Agent, Muscat.^ St fr/ tjp z/ci /. 'the *^*k&lt;&gt;n* JJS iartto ^Q/H P A/1// 'a/&lt; Mm . Ut/ ati Sst/ip 7 26th April, 1|9* x*. To, H#B«M *8 Political Agent and H.M f s Consul, MUSCAT. Sir, After the last' cruIse of the P.G.L.S. to Muscat the Inspector of Lights reported the following:- A. The lime mortar of the curbing along the pathway LEADING TO THE LIGHT HAS FALLEN OFF IN SEVERAL PLACES. \ B. The pathway itself is strewn with a large quantity OF BROKEN STONE PROBABLY WASHED DOWN BY THE RAINS, WHICH MAKES THE ASCENT TO THE LIGHT VERY DIFFICULT. C. There are small pits on the pathway that need to be FILLED WITH LIME MORTAR. D. The concrete foundation of the light has also cracked AND REQUIRES CEMENT GROUTING. AS THIS IS AN IMPORTANT NAVIGATIONAL LIGHT IT IS DESIRABLE TO KEEP IT IN GOOD REPAIR. In THE CIRCUMSTANCES I SHALL BE GRATEFUL IF YOU WOULD KINDLY INSTRUCT THE ASSISTANT Resident Engineer of the Ministry of Works at Muscat to arrange FOR NECESSARY REPAIRS AND CLEARING OF THE PATHWAY. The bill in this respect may please be forwarded TO THIS OFFICE IN TRIPLICATE FOR SETTLEMENT. IAVE THE HONOUR TO BE S I R, cc: The Asst. Resident Engineer, M.O.W., Bahrain ) For information and The Asst. Resident Engineer, M.O.W., Muscat ) necessary action. BM/AIO'SA BKITISH INDIA STEAM NAVIGATION CO., LTD. (£) \l; (Inoobporatbd in England.) S.S. W B A R A L A' 388 His Britanic Majesty 1 s Consul Muscat. , i Voy. ISo. 18th March, 294 9 Dear Sir, LEADING LIGHTS. This is to inform you that as I was on the point of entering harbour this morning, solely depending on the Leading Lights, the white upper one was suddenly extinguished. Fortu nately I Just had turning room so ; was able to lie off until daylight but I do wish to indicate the very serious results which might result from such an unusual action. I shall certainly not risk arriving before daylight in future whereas there can be no doubt of the advantages under fine weather condition of being able to do so. Relevant times are Time of sunrise 0610 Hrs. L.M. T. w Light was extinguished 0537 Hrs.L^r /i 3 I am. Dear Sir, Yours faithfully. y Master. lA\A~&gt; ^ |3 j L t*.INDIA OFFICE RECORDS microfilm</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000067_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/328</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000067</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/328</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/7 Lighthouse and leading lights'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-23T22:08:17</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">mis</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (8 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in rough chronological order, from the rear to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 10; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 4-9; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence concerning repairs required at Muscat Harbour. The papers consist of numerous reports of lights not working and other needs for repair and replacement. Also included in the file is the proposal to make the Secretary, Persian Gulf Lighting Service, responsible for disseminating navigational information in the Gulf.Correspondence comes from: the Government of Iran; the British India Steam Navigation Company Limited; the Persian Gulf Lighting Service; the Political Residency, Bahrain; and the Political Agency, Muscat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Lighting Service</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Harbours</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000067#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>