<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024102474.0x00000b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T11:55:47.213Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No. 1115 of 1870. P olitical D epahtment. Jacobahad, 2§th July 1870. Memo : The accompanying letter in original, from. Captain IIarrison r No'. 36 of I870 r dated 7th instant, and Political Superintendent's letter to Captain Sand eman, No. 1100 of 1870, dated 20th idem, are forwarded to the Commissioner in Sind, in reply to Iiis Memo : No. 437 of 1870, dated 20th instant. 2. The favor of either a copy of Captain Harrison's or the original being^ returned, is requested, as the Political Superintendent s Office Establishment is quite inadequate to the work that devolves on it. B. PHAYHE, Colonel., Political Superintendent, U. S. F. No. 36 of 1870. From, T he P olitical A gent, K helat. n To, T he P olitical S uperintendent, F rontier U pper S ind. Khelat, 1th July 1870. Sir,. I have the honor to report foryonr information that Sirdars Ala Deetiab Ivoord and Wudderah, Adum Khan left Seebee a few days ago, and are now settled at Murrow. ' 2. The Sirdar's brother, Kadur J&gt;oenab, and bis son, Yar Mahomed, having come to Khelat to settle preliminaries for the Sirdar's visit, called upon me yesterday afternoon, and in the most natural manner alluded to the subject noted in my Diary of the 29th ultimo, Their statements were such that Itliink it necessary to record tlie same for your Information and tliat of liiglier authority. * 3. Sirdar Ala Deenali'g brother and son state that a few days before they left Seebee, Shaban Murree arrived, bringing a letter from Captain Sande- man for Sirdar Moolah Mahomed's son, and that the substance of it was as follows, viz : that he wanted to know what arrangements had been made by Captain Harrison tor the benefit of the Sirdars in Beloochistan. That he and other Officers had directed Captain Harrison to bring the Khan into the plains this cold season, and that Sirdar Moolah Mahomed had better attend with the principal people of his tribe, as negotiations would be entered into in which he, Captain Sandeman, would stand security for the good conduct of Sirdar Moolah Mahomed, and that the English Government would make the Khan give good security to treat the Sirdar properly. 4. My informants state this letter was at once taken to Kandahar by Wuzeer Khan, Sirdar Moolah Mahomed's Vukeel, and that Shaban Murree had told them to trust Captain Sandeman implicitly, and that everything would be properly arranged. 5. Were these statements correct, or reliable, I should naturally claim the protection of Government against interference with duties that they have entrusted to me. My object, therefore, in recording this conversation is that Captain Sandeman may have an opportunity to contradi ct these statements, and thus enable me to counteract the evils that must arise from rumours of this kind. G. His Highness, T am glad to say, is still incredulous, and attributes this report to some underhand intrigue. Having however heard the same thing from three or four different sources, he is so far anxious that he has sent mes sengers to Seebee and Kandahar to ascertain how these reports emanated. 7. As previously stated, I am sceptical regarding these statements, further, I nm of opinion that no Government official would interfere in the manner described, as the Supreme Government have expressed their opinions so clearly in letter No. 1194, of 2Gth August 18G9 by the Secretary to the Government of India, and in Resolution No. 3039, Political Department by the Government of Bombay, under date 21st September 18G9. At the same time, as His Highness has always placed the greatest trust in the English Govern ment, I think it most desirable that the statement made to me should be contradicted. I have, &amp;c., C. w. HARBISON, Captain, Political Agent, Khelat.■ No. 1100 OF 1870. Proin, To/ The Politica] Superintendent, Frontier Upper Sind. The Deputy Commissioner, Dehra Ghazee Khan. Sm, Jacobahad, 20th Jw/y 1870. I lia\ e the honor to acquaint you that a few days a^o I received from Khelat, in the Diary of Captain Harrison, the Political A^ent, a remark that an English Officer had been corresponding with the family of Sirdar Moollah Mahomed l^aisanee, at Seebee, on matters connected with the restoration of the family to their social position in the Khelat State. 2. In forwarding that Diary, as usual to the Commissioner in Sind, I re marked that the same report had been been brought to me by His Highness the Khan's A akeel at Jacobabad, on nearly the same date as Captain Harrison had received it at Khelat (29th June last), and as at that time I had no idea that there was any truth in the report, I contradicted it, and said that it must have emanated from one of the Khan's own people. &lt;&gt;. That report, which has not yet been returned to me from Kurrachee, was followed a day or two since by the accompanying letter from Captain Har rison to my address, No. 86 of 1870, dated 7th July. 4. Today the Vakeel of His Highness the Khan at Jacobabad waited upon me, 'uith the intelligence that two messengers had come to his house here, and stated that they had brought two letters from the son of Sirdar Moollah Mahomed, from Seebee, and asking permission to bring them in. I accordingly ga\c permission, and the letter to my address having been opened, it announ ced that the A akeel, Wuzzeer Khan, mentioned in Captain Harrison's letter as having carried your communication to Kandahar to Sirdar Moollah Mahomed, had been arrested on his way back at Quetta by the Khan's Naib there, that he had a letter in his possession to your address from Sirdar Moollah Mahomed, and that he hoped application would be made for his release. 5. This letter was read in the Vakeel's presence, and I merely acknow ledged its receipt, without entering upon any notice of its contents. 0. Although J believe with Captain Harrison that the version of your alleged communication to Sirdar Moollah Mahomed and his son, given by the Khelat informants, is neither'■ correct or reliable,' yet I cannot but express my regret that you should, under present circumstances, have addressed either the Sirdar or Ids sons at all.7. It is true that the Sirdar himself is in Affglianistan, and bis sons aro refugees in the independent Affghan territory of Seebee, and therefore not in Khelat territory at all; still, had you consulted me on the subject, which I think you will admit you ought to have done, as the principal Political autho rity for Khelat affairs on the Frontier, I should have informed you that no proper opportunity of again advocating the cause of these Sirdars would pre sent itself until next cold season, when, according to the invitation of the Commissioner in Sind, despatched to Khelat in April last, Ilis Highness may be expected to come to the plains to confer with Sir W. Merewether and our selves, about the final arrangements for settling the Murrees and Boogtees, and other important matters, which I am convinced no amount of correspond ence will settle satisfactorily. 8. Before therefore forwarding this correspondence to the Commissioner in Sind, with a view to a suitable communication being made to His Highness, the Khan of Khelat, through Captain IIarrison&gt; I await your reply to this let ter, now forwarded. * I have, &amp;c., (Signed) K. PHAYRE, Colonel, Political Superintendent, Frontier Upper Sind. p. —The letter from Sirdar Moollah Mahomed's son to your address is enclosed. I forgot to mention that on my asking the Seebee messengers why they came here, instead of going direct to you, they replied that under instructions from you, Shabhan Murree had told them to bring any reply they might receive to Jacobabad. I can scarcely imagine this to be true, but it as just as well that it should be contradicted. (Signed) H. PHAYKE, Colonel, Political Superintendent, Frontier Upper Sind. No. 461 or 1870. P olitical D epartment, Commissioners Office, Kurrachee, Is^ August 1870; Memo. In reply to his Memo. No. 1115, dated 25th instant, the Political Superin tendent Upper Sind Frontier is informed that his further report will be awaited. Meanwhile, copy of a telegram sent by the Commissioner to Captain Sandemauon the 18tli January last (when Colonel Phayre was in Bombay) is for warded for information, and to show that Captain Sandcman had been told so far back that he should hold no communication with Sirdar Moollah Mahomed Haisanee. 2. The original letter No. 36, of 7th July 1870, from Captain Harrison, is herewith returned, as requested. W. L. MEREWETHER, Colonel, Commissioner in Sind. No. 1158 of 1870. P olitical D epartment. From, The Political Superintendent, Frontier Upper Sind. To, The Commissioner in Sind, Kurrachee. Folitical Superintendent's Office, Jacohabad, \Qth August 1870. Sir, I have the honor to forward the letters noted at margin, received yester day, from Captains Harrison 1. Letter No. 52 of 1870, of 5th August, from Capt. Harrison, i Political Agent, Khelat. iXna oanUCman. 2. No. 519, dated 10th August 1870, from Captain Sandeman 9 j reft aJn from offer- to Colonel Phayre, Political Superintendent, Frontier Upper Sind. ing any comment, unless called for, upon Captain Harrison's endeavour to give a personal turn to my ofhcial criticism of his report No. 29 of 1870 ; a criticism both called for and warranted by facts, which of themselves prevent the questions at issue, from beinj; lowered into the arena of invective discussion. 3. Owing to want of clerks I have not retained a copy of Captain Sandeman's letter, and should therefore feel much obliged if you will kindly return tiie original, or favor me with a copy. I have, &amp;c., R PHAYRE, Colonel, Political Superintendent, U. S. F.No. i&gt;2 of 1870. From, TrtE P olitical A gent , K iikl.vt. To, The Political Supertxtexdent. U pper S ind F rontier. ^ „ Khelat, §th August 1870. S ir, I licavo the honor to acknovrledge the receipt of your letter Xo. 1110, of the 21st ultimo, reviewing my report Xo, 29 of 1870, and commenting upon my conduct in such a manner as requires refutation. Answer to your Srd para. T was first informed of the taking of Beyla and the inauguration of a new Government by His Highness. Being aware of the responsibility lie had undertaken, 1 have anxiously watched the progress of that province; that a new Government has been inaugurated appears to be recognized by the Commissioner in Sind. Major Ross in his letter Xo. 104 of 1S70, calls it the change ol Government,' and Sir AV. Merewether requests His Highness' favorable consideration of the subject referred to. Sluigassee \\ ullee Mahomed reported to Sir TT. Merewether and myself that he had recovered all the property he could, but that the major part had been carried oH to Kurrachee. As no subsequent complaints were made, it may be surmised that the report was truthful, the term 'conciliatory policy' was used last year, and from a re-perusal of para. 10 of report No. 54 of 18(59, and copy of letter from Shagassee Wullee Mahomed appended to letter No. oo of 18()9, L think the expression may be considered appropriate. Hearing His Highness' reports supplemented by occasional letters from Major Ross, and other people that I trusted, gave me sufficient infonnatiou to venture upon giving an opinion, knowing that, if incorrect, the Commissioner in Sind was in a position to point out any error I might have made. Letter 1—A of 1870, of 31st may 1870, from Major lloss, acknowledging having perused my letter No. 11), may show that my statements are to some extent reliable. Para 5. —Behaviour of Khelat troops on first going to Beyla may be Petition forwarded by the Collec- verified by reference to letters marginally noted, tor of Kurrachee under the Com- a , K l the people by whom the plundering was missioner in Sind's endorsement No. . , . „ . .. . .. g of 1870. committed ascertained. I p to the present tune Political Ajjout■ Cwadur's 1 —a of ] have never heard of the fight between the •ilst Mav lb/0. 0 Khan 's troops and Janotes, the suggestioncontained in yonr para, prevents my entering into any historical sketch of the country. I have no doubt that Major E /Oss will be able to give any information required. This Officer's letter supports my statements regarding newspaper reports. p ara g .—I was not awai'e that Major KoSs, having reported Sirdar Faquir Mahomed for some disrespect in a letter, could be looked upon as ' a serious and unfortunate dispute.' His Highness wrote to Faquir Mahomed and told him always to address Major Ross. With respect to Sirdar Faquir Mahomed's threat to resign, was chiefly to compel the Khan to give him assistance, in case of futher aggression by the Persians. lie is at Khelat on most friendly terms with His Highness, and has every intention of returning to his Xaibship. From the 7thundfollowing paras —It is implied that I knew for what reason Captain Sandeman went to Kahun, and that I declined to give His Highness the information required, with the view of bringing Captain Sandeman into dis repute. My culpability rests entirely on the understanding or otherwise of a verbal conversation. Considering over what you have written, and what I remember, it appears to me that in the excitement of the interview, points stated by you, must have escaped my notice. Had I understood your conver sation, as stated in the letter under reply, nothing would have been easier than satisfying His Highness' ' alleged curiosity,' to exonerate myself from the im putation of falsehood. I respectfully beg to state what I understood, and to further ask whether or not my actions have been in accord with what I sup posed I heard. On your return from Knsmore, I went at once to you, stating that I heard Captain Sandeman had been to Kahun, and asked if he had any political powers; that I thougt he was only to treat with the Murrees and Ehoogtees in matters connected with his own districts, and not called upon to interfere in their disputes. Your answer to this, as far I remember, was, that if the Khan could not look after those tribes, Captain Sandeman had a right to do so. I certainly never remember having heard the object of the visit until the present moment, and I think this may be conceded, as I certainly should never have written my letter No. 23, had l known Captain Sandeman s reason for going to Kahun. With reference to para 10, I availed myself of Sir . Merewether's presence at Jacobabad to allude to the subject, stating that I had asked you what political powers Captain Sandeman had in Beloochistan, &amp;c. Para 11—Would appear to imply that I was afraid to speak at Jacoha- bad, and re-opened the whole question directly I arrived at Khelat. I respect fully beg to contradict such an injurious statement. Having spoken to Sir W. Merewether and yourself, I considered the matter settled as far as I was concerned. His Highness'allusion to the subject was quite voluntary ; as several people were present, the matter was treated as described, but not iu a wayto prejudice His Highness mind in any way. Having been ordered to keep a Diary, 1 thought this allusion showed that His Highness wanted to know what was voiu? on in the Murree and Bhoogtee country—hence the entry. O &lt;3 Para 12.—At the latter end of last year, I received and took copies of all the correspondence regarding the exploring expedition. His Highness also favored me with copies of the correspondence that passed between you and him on the subject. As this expedition never took place, I concluded that all arrangements pertaining thereto were void ; no subsequent correspondence was received, and I only heard a day or two ago that a sanitarium and post was being built. Para 14—Does not appear to call for remark, being merely an expres sion of opinion regarding the present attempt to defend Cutchee, and an inten tion to express a policy on this subject on a luture occasion. Para 15.—The remarks in this para, can be met in 16. Para 16.—I have always alluded to the Government Resolutions quoted as per margin with the greatest confidence, iiH G d~* lg'rwH 0 h a ' d am u ' der the i^P^ion that 1 have acted Bombay Government Resolution No, strictlv according tO the policy defined. I 30*39, dated 21st September 1869. J ® , i i i i i. iji should be sorry that it should be believed that I am influenced, as you imagine, or that I would support the Khan, whether right or wrong. I am really not aware that His Highness thwarted you last year. Naib Mahomed Khan wrote saying, that you considered that the sub sidizing the Murrees had failed, through want of co-operation on His Highness' part. I thought it just to represent what His Highness the Khan had to say in a demi-official, and regretted that what I represented had not met with your approval. I still further regret that you have lost all confidence in me, self-respect necessitates my suggesting that higher motives than that ot partizanship, obliged me to bring forward what I considered a dangerous interference on the part of Captain Sandeman. Had a rebellion been organized, I should have been the person blamed. I have no personal ill- leeling against Captain Sandeman, and hope that he may continue to earn the good opinion of his Government, at the same time not intecfere with Beloochis- tan politics, as he is supposed to have done. Paras. 17 and 18—1 have certainly always considered that if subsidizing was attempted, that the most suitable manner would be to let the recipients Kee that it was indirectly through the Khan, the acknowledged head of each tribe in Beloochistan. Para 19.—In letter No. 42 of 1870, I ventured to state my reasons for supposing that the English Government would not interfere regarding Sirdar Moolah Mahomed and the other Chiefs situated 300 miles away iroin anyone. I have to express opinions; on the present occasion, I concluded that the Government policy for years past warranted the statement. Para 20. The 14th para, of report under review having been approved of by you, no further comment is necessary. Para 21. The Murrees have for years past committed raids, so I fear nothing that can be done will put a sudden stop to their predatory habits. It it was of course a great disappointment to me that they should have com mitted a raid in Cutchee, just as I was informing ^Government of the satisfac tory results during the past nine months. Having answered your numerous queries, I would most respectfully solicit that these appendices, viz., your review and the reply, accompany my report, as there are allegations that must cflPect my character, not only as an official, but as a private gentleman. I have, &amp;c., C. W. HARRISON, Captain, Political Agent, Khelat. No. 519 of 1870. From, T he D eputy C ommissioner, D hera G hazee K han. To, S ir, T he P olitical S uperintendent, U pper S ind F rontier. JDhera Ghazee Khan, \Qth August 1870. I have the honor to acknowledge receipt of the correspondence noted in the margin, and in replying to the same, Copy of Political Superintendent Upper _ _ .. , Sind's letter No. 1838, dated 30th December I shall endeavour to place you in poSSCS- .Tx^Uror^ sion of the true facts of the case; but iu ''^Ei'tract^om' Captam Harrison's letter No. O^er *0 do SO, it is necessary that I 42, dated 22nd July 1870. should briefly pass in review the political Copies of correspondence from Beloochistan « , ■, . .i Sirdars at Kandahar to Captain Sandeman position OI atiairS OU this DOmer at tlie time Sirdar Moolah Mahomed of Sarawau dated 20th July, to the Commissioner in Sind. t k f ^ th MlirrCC dan, and Political Superintendent Upper Sind's No. u , iioo, dated 20th July 1870, to Captain San- -^-Jiich circumstance alone led to the cor- deman, Deputy Commissioner. , . , , i • . - i respondence which has been mterccpted by Captain Harrison's orders. I use this expression advisedly, for I have every reason to believe, as I will show hereafter, that the Khan of Khelat himself was fully aware of all I was doing, and was secretly glad at it. 2. The intercourse between our Officers and the powerful Murree clan, as you are fully aware, has only existed during the last few years. Prior to this, since the days of Sir Charles Kapier, our position towards this clan wasany thing but friendly, and until very lately no member of it was suffered to visit British territory. If you remember, so lately as last spring, when I visit ed you at Kusmore, the Murree Sirdar's nephew and followers were imprisoned by a Sind Post, simply because they were Murrees, and I understood you to say that the I osts had until recently all been furnished with a standing order that no Murree was to be allowed to cross the British border. 3. On the Punjab side, although the restrictions against Murrees visit ing our territory was not so stringent, still the feeling against them ivas anv- thing but friendly, and the policy since annexation confessedly was to isolate them as much as possible from all intercourse with us. 4. It is unnecessary here to enter upon the reasons which led to the inauguration of a new policy in dealing with this clan. It is sufficient to my purpose to note the fact, and that it was successful, but at the same time to make it entirely so, on account of the former treatment the Murree clan had been subjected to, it was necessary that at first until they thoroughly believed in our friendly intentions towards them in our intercourse with them, we should treat them as considerately and delicately as possible. 5. Just prior to Moollah Mahomed's taking refuge with this clan, it had been decided that a friendly expedition should visit their hills. You had in formed them of this, and if I mistake not, you had notified to Sirdar Guzzen Khan, the Murree Chief, that you would then arrange with him for the protec tion of Cutchee, and I know he had hopes that the 600 Eupees per mensem, which you had on account of the Murree inroads into Khelat, considered it necessary to withhold, would be restored to him. G. Suddenly orders came that the expedition was not to take place, and instead of meeting the Murree Chiefs as they expected, urgent business called you to Bombay. 7. Directly I heard this, if you remember, I telegraphed'to you that a determined effort was being made to break off our connection with the Murree clan, and that such was truly the case, the events which happened on your re turn from Bombay abundantly showed ; for it was proved that one of your own Native officials had deliberately endeavoured to break the peace of the border, and which for a time in a measure he succeeded in doing. 8. Any thing like a real disturbance in the Murree hills does not, on ac count of the geographical position of Sind, affect the peace of the Sind border as it does that of the Punjab border. The hills from Sukkee Srewer to the liojhan are inhabited by the Murree clan, it is therefore a matter of far more real importance to me than it is to you, as far as your border policy is concerned, that the influence possessed over the tribes should be of such a na ture as to determine and lead their councils. Peeling, therefore, the importance that would be attached to the breaking off, as it were, of our engagement tomeet the Murreo clan, and knowing how easily they are disheartened, and more especially being aware of their impulsive nature and the advantage that might be taken of the turn affairs had assumed, I told the Chief that I would keep my engagement, and meet them as proposed, and this led to my visiting them at Khan with, as you yourself have expressed it, your ' full approval.' 9. Such being my position towards the Murree clan, the arrival of a Sir dar of the position and influence of Moollah Mahomed of Sarawan, was an event of great moment to me, more especially as the Murrees in writing about him, made most reasonable requests. 10. The clan sent a deputation to me to say that by their customs they were bound to receive the Sirdar. That he had asked them for aid against the Khan, and they asked my advice as to their action. They told me at the same time that the Khan had no real quarrel with the Moolla, that the whole affair between Captain Harrison and the Sirdar was brought about by the Minister, Wullee Mahomed. They said £ ' admit ' the Sirdar to an interview, and he will prove to you he is not in rebellion ' against the Khan of Khelat.' 11. Such statements and requirements made by our hill friends ap peared to me very reasonable, and I at once communicated with Sir William Merewether (you were at Bombay), and asked permission merely to see the Sirdar, and satisfy myself if the Murree assertions regarding his quarrel were really true or not. It is unreasonable to assert that the Chief of Sarawan's arrival in the Murree hills was no business of mine, seeing that it kept my border in a turmoil, and placed me, with regard to the Murrees, in a most awkward position. 12. Sir William Merewether on receiving my letter at once telegraphed to me not to receive the Sirdar. I sent him word to this effect, and I advised the Murree Chiefs to tell Moolah Mahomed to wait patiently, and not to again resort to arms. This they promised to do, but as they seemed to have great faith in both Sir William's and your own treatment of Moolah Mahomed, and put stress on the statement that you did not know of the Khan's real feelings towards him, I said that I would do all I could to convey this to you, and if you remember at Jacobabad, this I did. These negotiations resulted in the Murree clan refusing the Sirdar help, and feeling he could get nothing from me, he left for Kandahar. All I did was to assure him that it was no un kindly feeling that prevented my seeing him, and that if an opportunity offered, 1 felt sure that both Sir William and yourself would aid in re-establishing peace between him and the Khan. I took pains to show that this matter rested entirely with you, and that I was only interested in him as he was a friend of my allies, the Murree Chiefs.13. The other day, when I went to meet the Murree Chiefs at Maree, if ^ on remember, it was in the hope and belief that you also would be present * —ill health alone prevented your being so. I had written to both Sir 'William and yourself about opening up the trade route between this and Kandahar, and not only you, but Sir William also, had promised to give me every legitimate aid in your power. 14. My letter to Sirdar Moolah Mahomed's son was in reply to a com munication from the Murrees about his father. I advised him to tell his father to wait on patiently, and as I feared the return of the Sirdar to Kahun, I discouraged the Murrees from holding out hopes of aiding him, did he do so. J n my reply I made it appear that I was principally writing to him about the Kafila route from Kandahar to this, and I saw no harm in doing so. In fact, to have driven the Sirdar to desperation, or to have refused a reply, would have been unwise, and might probably have led to his return to the Murree hills, which I wished to avoid. Besides, it would have conveyed to the Murrees themselves the impression that we were unreasonably harsh in our treatment of the Sirdar, for after all he had in no way directly offended against the British Government. In fact, all he asked was, an opportunity of proving that, in having acted as advised by British Officers, he had been ruined. He declared most positively that all he did at first, and which his intercepted letter to me also affirms, was to abide by Sir Henry Green's advice. Had you come to Maree, all this would have occurred in your presence, and this itself must com ince you that, in acting as I did, the position was not of my seeking, but was forced on me. 15. But the most extraordinary point is, that I believe His Highness the Khan was not only fully aware of all I was doing, but secretly and in his heart approved of it. 1G. Shortly after I arrived at Maree, an Agent direct from himself ap peared in my Camp. He brought a khillut with a letter (a copy I forwarded to you) to the Mazaree Chief, Emam Buksh Khan, who is closely allied by marriage to the Murree Sirdar, and this the Khan is fully aware of, with a message to myself, to say how very pleased the Khan really was at the efforts that had been made to reform the Murrees, and I certainly understood, if I had so desired it, that the Khan himself would address me to this effect. The Khan's Agent asked for help to purchase Camels, &amp;c,, for the Khan, and told us that it was His Highness' intention to visit Gundava, where he hoped to meet us all. To me it is most strange how the Khan under these circum stances asked Captain Harrison who Emam Buksh Khan was ? More espe cially as this is by no means the first time the two Chiefs have interchanged compliments, and Emam Bux's close relationship to the Murrees, must have been known to him. Moreover, the Khan's herd of Camels not unfrequently have obtained at the Khan's request shelter from the depredations of the Murree clan in the Mazaree country.17. As the Khan's Agent bad come to my . Camp with a letter from Khodadad. himself to the Mazaree Chief, I told the latter to ask what was the Khan's real feelings towards Moollah Mahomed. The reply was that given by the Sirdar himself, and I was further assured, if I wished it, that this fact would also he written to rae. Other circumstances transpired which led me to think that the Khan Is not a free Agent, and that ullee Mahomed directs matters, and that Captain Harrison is not aware of the Khan's real sentiments, who is afraid of his minister and unable to speak out, but would willingly do so did an opportunity offer. Of course it must rest with you to communicate or not this impression to Captain Harrison. I would be careful at present not to let the minister know the Khan s Agent had been to me. 18. Captain Harrison appears to me unduly to dwell on the fact that I have no official connection with Khelat. I have clearly the position which the executive charge of 100 miles of British territory, running parallel to the Khelat border gives, while the interests of Khelat and the Punjab border are so bound together that, even if the Government desired it—which we know full well it does not—it would be in practice an impossibility to separate the two, seeing that the British clans and Chiefs are nearly allied by marriage to Khelat subjects. 19. Whether the Government will approve of my efforts to open up the old trade route with Kandahar, and this I am not quite in a position to state, but I believe it will. Before reporting the matter officially, I was waiting to see what news would come from Kandahar, and what would result from open ing out the trade as far as Moondai. A good commencement has already been made, as several Kafilas have traversed the hills in safety. It must be evident to you, as it is to me, how mistaken the statement is, that the opening out of these trade routes would injure the Khan, and in writing as His High ness has done on the subject, I doubt if he has considered or knows the objects aimed at, which must result, should they be successful, as much to the promo tion of his own interests, as they will assuredly do to those of the British. 20. I can assure you that you only do me justice in expressing the opi nion that you feel sure I would in no way desire to act in opposition to your implied wishes, as Chief Political Authority on this border. I have explained how I came to reply to Moollah Mahomed, and had you been with me, and heard from the Khan's Agent the real state of affairs, I doubt not you would have felt with me that, under such circumstances, no harm could result, more especially as great benefit had accrued from not allowing the Sirdar to return to the Murree hills. Doubtless the Khan's real knowledge of what was go ing on enabled him to assure Captain Harrison that the stories told him were' neither correct or reliable.' It is equally untrue tl&gt;at the messeugers were directed to return by way of Jacobabad. I have purposely avoided noticing the attempt to fasten on my intercourse with the Murrees as having caused the raid on Phoolajee. You have clearly refuted it, and well I know that such intercourse has often greatly tended to prevent bloodshed. 21. In conclusion, I would desire to tend to yourself my most sincere and grateful thanks for the considerate and generous way in which you have dealt with this matter. I believe you have arrived at a true conclusion in esti mating that this agitation has been brought about by design, and in the hope of getting the additional Es. 50,000 once more placed at the Khan's disposal, to be spent by his ministers of their own pleasure and as they may consider right untrammelled by us. I trust my conduct will ever deserve your confi dence, and by continued efforts I hope to prove that, like yourself, I have but one object at heart, viz. the promotion of Imperial British interests on this border, which I shall allow no provincialism to interfere with. I have, &amp;c., EGBERT SAN DEM AN, Captain, Deputy Commissioner, Dhera Ghazee Khan, No. 523 of 1870. Political Department. Commissioner's Office, Kurraclhee, 25M August 1870. Submitted to Govcrhmcnt, in continuation of former correspondence. Captain Har rison s letter needs no comment, but I would offer the following remarks on Captain Sandeman's letter No. 519, dated 10th August. 2. In this letter Captain Sandeman not only acknowledges that he hag repeatedly communicated with Sidar Moollah Mahomed, since I desired him not to do so, but actually proceeds to try and justify his direct disobedience of my orders conveyed last January by telegram, and more fully afterwards in a demi-official letter. Copy of the telegram is annexed— ' From the Commissioner in Sind—Nowakote, via Hydrabad. ' To Captain Sandeman—Dhera Ghazee Khan. ' 18th January 1870. ' Received your's of 13th. Moollah Mahomed Raisanee should on no account be allow- ' ed to come to you. Colonel Phayre has been desired to hold no communication with him. It would therefore be manifestly wrong that he should be communicated with - by ' authorities on your Frontier. Further by post.'3 Captain Sandeman is a very intelligent, and energetic Officer, and lie has de servedly gained high credit for his zeal, but he has forgotten that zeal should be guided by discretion; and in this instance, Carried away by the plans in which he was immediately most interested, he has acted in a manner that is not only most unjusti fiable, but very disrespectful to myself, in that he had pursued a Course diametrically opposed to ihe one I had laid down, as the only one that should be followed, and which being strictly binding on the Officers on the Sind Frontier, should be respected by the neighbouring ones in the Punjaub, 4. Captain Sandeman is an Officer of the Punjaub Government, and not under my orders, but since I had the opportunity of seeing him last November, when he was passing through Sind, I have freely, and fully communicated my views to him, as to the management of affairs on the Frontier of Sind, and especially in connection with that portion of the Punjaub Frontier placed under his charge, so that there might be harmonious action by all. He was not therefore ignorant ot my wishes or of the- policy that was to be observed from the Sind border. His deliberate action in opposi^ tion to both is therefore the more marked, and unbecoming'. 5, The ' belief' expressed at the latter part of the 1st para: of Captain Sande- man's letter, that ' the Khan of Khelat himself was fully aware of all I was doing, and ' was secretly glad at it,' is simply belief, wholly unsupported by a' particle of evidence to warrant it, and therefore should not have been put forward. It is not even proba ble, that His Highness the Khan would \Vish, that an Officer about whom he knows nothing whatever, and who was serving in a distant part of the country from Khelat, should engage in matters so nearly affecting his, the Khan's, interests, especially as he was aware that the British Officers on the Sind border were restrained from interfering, and such arrangement not only was the most suitable for him, the Khan, but met with his entire concurrence. G. Captain Sandeman's knowledge of border history as displayed in the 2nd para : is very limited, indeed appears confined strictly to the period since he came himself to the border. Sir Charles Napier had little or nothing to say to the Murrees, excepting during his hill campaign, when communications were held with them through Captain (after wards General) Jacob. From the time, however, when General Jacob returned to the Frontier in 1847, intercourse with the Mui'rees was at once re-opened, and though broken at intervals by their misconduct, never ceased as supposed by Captain Sandeman. The Murrees, by the excellent information they gave in 184-7, were greatly instrumental in bringing about the severe punishment inflicted on the Boogtees in October of that year. 7. Gamin, the Murree Chief, until he died, visited Jacobabad when he wished, as also others. But though there was no absence of conciliatory measures, still the distance of the tribe from Sind, and, I believe myself, difficulties put in the way by the inter mediate lying Boogtees,, who were jealous of the other tribe, prevented their coming to Jacobabad so often as they might have done. The anecdote related about the imprison ment of the Murree Chief is doubtless quite correct, excepting that part where it is stated they were imprisoned, because they were, Murrces. This is a mistake. There was, and I conclude is still, a standing order on the Frontier, that all armed men crossing it without a pass, or some previous communication from the Chief of the tribe to which th ey be longed, were to be seized and sent into Jacobabad. This is a very necessary order, consi dering the wild rices on both sides of the border. It is well known in the hills and appreciated too.8. Whatever the former policy may have been on the Punjab side, I will answer for it, that there was no desire on that of Sind to isolate the .Murrees. They were always wel come if they choose to come. The fact was, they could do no injury to Sind, and excepting as regards their harassing the trade in its passage through Cutchee, there was no reason for any particular attention being paid to them. With the Punjaub it was different, assisted by a portion of the Boogtee Tribe, the Shumbarrees and Mussoorees, the Murrees were able to make successful forays in that country. 9. Captain Sandeman deserves every credit for checking this state of disorder, and no objection would have been raised to his proceedings, had he confined himself to merely using the Murree, and Boogtee horsemen he had been allowed to take into service, and to • simple intercourse with the Murree and Boogtee Chiefs, without interfering in other matters affecting the Khelat State. 10. Instead of any expression of regret on Captain'Sandeman's part, at his having acted contrary to pronounced wishes, and at having produced inconvenient embarrassment with His Highness the Khan of Khelat, he, in paras: 5 to 14 inclusive, adduces at length his reasons for having followed so unbecoming a course, and this too even while acknow- 1 edging (vide 12th para :) that he had received my telegram, directing him not to receive the Sirdar. The real reasons for the Sirdar's exile from his country, or what he supposed were the real reasons,.for he only went by the statement of the Sirdar, should have been nothing to Captain Sandeman. He had no right to listen to them, having been told not to receive, or communicate with the Sirdar. This course he should have followed, and no other. 11. The whole of Captain Sandeman's letter shows a totally mistaken view of his position, and a tendency to interfere with affairs, which are entrusted to the charge of other Officers. 12. He seems also to consider by his 18th para, that he has some official connection with Khelat, which would be warrant for his late proceedings. I am surprised he should state so, for it is not once, but many times, he has been distinctly informed, that political relations with the Khan of Khelat are in the hands of the Political Superintendent on the Frontier of Upper Sind, and the Commissioner, and that all matters from the Punjaub relating to the Khelat State should invariably be conducted through the medium of the former Officer. 13. With regard to the trade route with Kandahar, Captain Sandeman should, I consider, take no action in that scheme, until his proposal has been submitted officially and duly discussed. It may appear to Captain Sandeman a very simple arrangement, but he forgets that drawing Kafilahs direct from Kandahar to Dhera Ghazee Khan will greatly injure the Khan's interests, by changing the route of so much trade, which would otherwise traverse his country, but which entirely avoids it by going eastwards from Pisheen. I am always ready to advocate, and assist in, opening out every possible trade route, but the Hung should be done with discretion, and all interests properly weighed before final steps are taken. I told Captain Sandeman that to press the matter now was premature, that as the hill people quieted down, and became civilized, the old route would re-open of itself, without any irregular stimulas being applied. 1 1. Captain Sandeman, in the 22nd para: of his letter, while saying he would in no way desire to act in opposition to the implied wishes of Colonel Phayre, as Chief Poli tical aut hority on the border, fails to recollect that he had acted in direct opposition to my clearly expressed wishes, as Chief authority in this nrovince.15. The concluding para : of Captain Sandeman's letter is very objectionable in matter and tone. In respect to the former, without any but chance knowledge of the affairs of Khelat, he takes upon himself to endorse an idea, which has been hastily assumed by Colonel Phayre, reflecting very strongly on His Highness the Khan of Khelat. In respect to the latter, I have only to draw attention to the last line. 1G. All that Captain Sandeman writes, and all that has occurred, only proves more clearly what I have pointed out before, but especially last January, that it is of the utmost importance, while the fullest cordiality exists between the Officials on the Sind, and the Punjaub Frontiers, the utmost care should be enjoined on the latter, that they engage in uo measures which may in any way affect the political relations existing between the British Government and the Khan of Khelat. Captain Sandeman has exceeded due limits in this respect, and I would beg that measures may be adopted to prevent a recur rence of such very embarrassing procedure. W. L. MEREWETHER, Colonel, Commissioner in Sind.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100024102474.0x00000b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/22, ff 88-96</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024102474.0x00000b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/22, ff 88-96</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No.523 of 1870 from William Lockyer Merewether, Colonel, Commissioner in Sind, Commissioner's Office, Kurrachee [Karachi] to His Excellency the Right Honourable Sir William Robert Seymour Vesey Fitzgerald, G.C.S.I., Governor and President in Council, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1870/1870</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-29T16:06:27</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>9 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Letter enclosing correspondence relating to Captain Robert Sandeman and his actions in communicating with Khelat [Kalāt] Sirdars in direct violation of Government instructions.The letter itself contains Merewether's comments on Captain Sandeman's letter of 10 August including the acknowledgement by Captain Sandeman himself that he had disobeyed Merewether's orders and his attempts to justify his actions, and including a copy of the telegram from Merewether instructing the Captain not to communicate with Sirdar Moolah Mahomed Raisanee [Sardar Mullah Mohammed Raisani]. The letter goes on to discuss Merewether's opinions of the Captain; his frequent communication with him on border matters; statements made by the Captain, particularly in relation to the Khan of Khelat, for which there is no evidence or justification; the Captains apparent lack of historical knowledge of the border regions; Captain Sandeman's statements and justifications for his actions and his 'mistaken view of his position including that of having a formal connection to Khelat whereas he should be passing any Khelat affairs through Sind; a proposal made by the Captain in relation to trade routes from Kandahar; and Captain Sandeman's actions in affecting the political relations between the British Government and the Khan of Khelat.Enclosed with the letter are the following correspondence:Memorandum No.1115 of 1870 from Colonel Robert Phayre, Political Superintendent, Upper Sind Frontier, Jacobabad 25 Jul 1870 enclosing letter No.36 of 1870 from Captain Harrison and letter No. 1100 of 1870 from himself to Captain Sandeman to Sir William Lockyer Merewether, Commissioner in SindLetter No.36 of 1870 from Charles Henry Harrison, Political Agent, Khelat, to Colonel Robert Phayre, The Political Superintendent, Frontier Upper Sind, 7 July 1870 reporting on a visit by Kadur Deenah (brother of the Sirdar Ala Deenah Koord) and his son Yar Mahomed in which they alluded to a subject that he had noted in his diary on the 29 June and giving Colonel Phayre their statements that they had received a letter from Captain Sandeman asking what arrangements Captain Harrison had made for the benefit of the Sirdars in Beloochistan [Baluchistan] and informing him that Captain Harrison had been directed to bring the Khan to the plains to meet with Sirdar Moolah Mahomed and the principal people of his tribe and that he (Captain Sandeman) would provide security for the good conduct of Sirdar Moolah Mahomed and the British Government would ensure the Khan treated the Sirdar properly. Captain Harrison goes on to ask whether the information contained in the statement is true, and asking that Captain Sandeman be offered the opportunity to contradict them as he (Captain Harrison) would need to undertake work to counteract the evils of such rumours. Captain Harrison also reports that the Khan believes the reports to be some kind of underhand intrigue on the part of one of his enemies and has sent messengers to ascertain where the reports eminated.Letter No. 1100 of 1870 from Colonel Robert Phayre, Political Superintendent, Frontier Upper Sind to Captain Robert Sandeman, The Deputy Commissioner, Dehra Ghazee Khan [Dera Ghāzi Khān], 20 July 1870 informing him that he had received the diary of Captain Harrison, Political Agent at Khelat which contained a remark about an English officer having been corresponding with the family of Sirdar Moollah Mahomed Raisanee in regard to matters connected with restoring the family to their social position in Khelat state and that a similar report had been brought to him by His Highness the Khan's Vakeel at Jacobabad. Colonel Phayre note's that he had initially assumed it to be a fabricated story until he both received Captain Harrison's letter (No.36 of 1870) and received a visit from the Vakeel bringing with him two letters, one of which was addressed to Captain Sandeman from Sirdar Moollah Mahomed and discussed his application for release and expressing his regret that Captain Sandeman had addressed correspondence either to the Sirdar or his sons (as was alleged) and requesting an explanation of his actions, as well as an explanation for why the letters had been instructed to come to Jacobabad and not to the Captain himself.Memorandum No.461 of 1871 from William Lockyer Merewether, 1 August 1870 stating that a further report from the Political Superintendent is awaited and enclosing a copy of a telegram sent to Captain Sandeman in which he was told not to hold any communication with Sirdar Moollah Mahomed Raisanee (telegram no longer enclosed).Letter No. 1158 of 1870 from Colonel Robert Phayre, Political Superintendent, Frontier Upper Sind, Jacobabad to William Lockyer Merewether, The Commissioner in Sind, Kurrachee [Karachi], 16 August 1870 referring to letters No.52 of 1870 and No.519 of 1870 and mentioning his official criticism of Captain Harrison's report No.29 of 1870 which he feels was appropriate and warranted by facts.Letter No.52 of 1870 from Charles Henry Harrison, Political Agent, Khelat to Colonel Robert Phayre, Political Superintendent, Upper Sind Frontier, 5 August 1870 regarding Colonel Phayre's comments of his report No.29 of 1870 and stating that His Highness had informed him of the taking of Beyla [Bela] and the inauguration of a new Government and reporting that he had received correspondence from the Commissioner in Sind in which the new Government had been recognised; that Shagassee Wullee Mahomed had reported both to Harrison and to the Commissioner in Sind that all possible property from Beyla had been recovered and that there had been no subsequent complaints made in regard to missing property; and stating that other information stated in his letter had been taken from correspondence with Major Ross and others and that had there been any error the Commissioner would have corrected it. The letter goes on to speak to other comments made in relation to his influence with the Khan and suppositions made based on Government policy before requesting that this correspondence be included with the forwarding of his report as the Colonel had made allegations against his character as both an official and a gentleman.Letter No.519 of 1870 from Captain Robert Sandeman, Deputy Commissioner, Dhera Ghazee Khan to Colonel Robert Phayre, Political Superintendent, Upper Sind Frontier, 10 August 1870 giving a review of the political position of affairs on the border at the time Sirdar Moolah Mahomed took refuge with the Murree clan and explaining the circumstances which led to his correspondence and claiming that the Khan of Khelat was both aware of, and secretly glad at his actions. The letter contains statements in regards to the history of the British Government's relations with the Murree clan and allegations of arrests and policy against them (both of which are refuted in the letter from Sir William Merewether with which the correspondence is all enclosed); his correspondence with Sirdar Moollah Mahomed and his intentions being simply to avoid causing the Sirdar to take any actions as well as his relations with the Murree clan; his official connections to Khelat; trade routes from Kandahar and his belief in the correctness of his conduct.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024102474.0x00000b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>