<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001a2_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:44:12.969Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">' X \ L. X. 1 JU jL J» &lt;5 ) I 1 wT 1 ^ »4^5l&gt;J u—i- I L -4 l, i^-Xl V JJl jJ JJl 1J 51 v ^ j U l I -^L&gt;J I *—■_&gt;• I—^ &lt;5 —— -4 1 . &lt;«) &gt;Ji... &gt;• 1 —&gt; ^&gt;-1 l—^—‘-j*— f !&gt;—^ 3 --^ 4 w c, 1 4 J &gt;J jl UJI J I 1 f 4 J I X d JJ iU iJ 1 ---&gt;. L_^ j—:— ij ,*L_.) g. ‘JIlj-JI I ♦ '.-j (oj—I—«J=&gt; -jrrj* j-s' O-* ,L_kJI J. c-L ~JU ; 5 A i jL-JI 0 I U 0 . . .1 »4^ &gt; ,&gt;^1 ' J tl- 4 J S : L 5 * J r'.- 3 ^ ' tj—' _J I Oj —* I ) j ^* ^3 tj 3 ,VI o 1 Jl -3- connexlon with their exercise shall be conducted through the British Authorities in the Persian Gulf, or as Kis Majesty's Government may direct. ARTICLE 6 . His Majesty's Government and their duly appointed representatives shall have the right to send wireless communications from, and receive them at, any wireless station operated under the present Agreement, whether on tneir own behalf or on behalf of others, and to levy charges in res pect of such communications. ARTICLE 7 . His Majesty's Government may charge (directly or through their duly appointed agents) such landing and housing fees ana other charges for the use of the aerodrome and services connected therewith as they see fit. His Majesty's Government shall pay to the Shaikh (directly or through their duly appointed agents) a fee of Rs.10 on account of each commercial aircraft using the aerodrome. ARTICLE 8 . His Majesty's Government shall have the .sole right to supply fuel and lubricating oils (directly or through their duly appointed agents) to users of the aerodrome. The rates chargeable / for1 J * L-«5' 1J—^ ^ 5 » 1 L&gt;*J I ^ uJ -i—JV ^ 0 ^;yLJJ ^i.U-iJL-iw.^1 o o * °—^5 d J&gt;-—. j j i -&gt; d — £-1 ^ o—.j&gt; J&gt;-^'- 1 =^ , o!&gt; J - j I jO_i- * lS I I Jj' ^ 1 J ^ l_; Jjl jVlj C C 1 Ja—1^,‘H o 5j | *J I O 1 1—J» -« &lt;J I—Is ‘ I j_Xft J—^ 1 d I j J L-li. y I I— i^» ^ 1 ^^' d ^ ^ C &gt;J- -yy \ 5 I ( \ ) ) * « J U I : +-&gt;-y~ ~ — -n u y** u** ^ J Ctf—*i J— l * ^ dI—^—&gt; Lw J I —^ ^ ^ (Jr*' okju- d J I—M J-&gt;-1 &lt;&gt;• — *3 ^ ' d j ft ^ jCiiu^ ^ I—jj-. j- ^ ^ J • }tz*V\o*~ a S ^ ° 1 1 ( 1 ^ r 31 ^^ I J—^ ^ 1 J 1 i — N;i ' * ^^ d^UjVUJ—ft ^ -y Uk-i 1 0 1 w regulations in force in Sharjah relating to the entry or departure of persons or the importation or exportation of goods, the authorised person may give such orders and take such steps as he may consider necessary to prevent the contravention I or further contravention of the laws or regulations concerned and in par ticular to secure that any person or freight unlawfully embarM in Sharjah shall be disembarked again and that any aircraft from which any person or freight has been or is likely to be unlawfully disembarked, or any other aircraft belonging to the same operator, shall remove such person or freight from the territories of Sharjah again. 11. All aircraft and the persons on board shall conform with such orders under Article 10 (ii) or otherwise as may lawfully be given by any authorised person. 12. Any authorised person shall have the right of access at all rea sonable times to any aircraft for the purpose of exercising his powers and carrying out his duties under these Regulations. 13. (i) If any aircraft fails to comply with these Regulations or if any act is committed in, or in * L-ji* /respect ofShaikh for the purpose of these Regulations; (c) ’’territories of Sharjah” means the territories of the SheiKh of Sharjah together with their ter-, ritorial waters; (d) ’’the Chicago Convention' means the Convention on International Civil Aaiation opened for signature at Chicago on the 7th December, 1944.mam J_4J ■' 4 , .ll 4 J 1 ,\y l Cjsw l ,—J L-1 p L — » 0 /- L-4J1 I ij &gt;U Oi5^*— **•* J * «J‘^' ' vJ J Kr I j i —^ &lt; Jj» recert World Wnr, His Majesty^ Governniant will pay you rent for this land et 600 rupees a month for so long as they require the land, ills Majesty* s Government will also pay you for 2 head guards and 36 guards for the protection of the camp at 86 rupees a month ^or each head guard end 66 rupees a month for each guard plus 16 ruoees ns a living allowance for each man. This cost of living allowance shall be subject to reduction if the cost of living i falls.H8S*-’ Telegrams : AIRGENAHOH. BJOtOEK HABBANIYA. Telephone : HABBANIYA. Extn /3/3/s~j&gt;/p~A\0 THE CHIEF ENGINEER, DIRECTORATE-GENERAL OF WORKS, AIR HEADQUARTERS, ROYAL AIR FORCE, HABBANIYA. IRAQ. v. M«5« 19. &lt;_ N Q v eaip. e r, 19 pi &amp;c. All letters on the undermentioned subject should be addressed to the Chief Engineer at the above address and should quote :— Our Ref. : W/X5 .3/SJH• Your Ref. : (013/^/49/51) SUBJECT : SHARJAH AIRFIELD , -/«?/- j. m H. Political Agent, Political Agency, Bahrein. Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge your letter dated 14th. Noveniber 1951 and to thank you for the information contained therein. I am. Sir, Your obedient servant, 'O (Arch-G. Gull an. Group G apt ain) CHIEF ENGINEER. ROYAL AIR FORGE. AIR HEAP QUARTERS. . IRA1. .(C13/3/56/51) POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, 4th December, 1951. Your letter (1389/47) of the 28th November about the Sharjah Civil Air Agreement. 2 . Wilton is writing to Shaikh Saqr in terms of the enclosed draft about the faci lities for despatch of telegrams. I will send you two certified copies of the letter as soon as I receive them from Wilton. 3. With regard to paragraph 3, the Shaikh has asked Wilton how to give the Air Navi gation Regulations the force of law, since he has never promulgated a written law in his lifeJ We are preparing and sending down to Wilton a suitable draft Alan. (W.S. Laver) C.U. Le Quesne, Esq. The Residency, Jufair.DRAFT. To Shaikh Saqr bin Sultan al Qasimi, Ruler of Sharjah. After Compliments: In connection with the Civil Aviation Agreement signed by you on 15th November, 1951 I am to inform you that you may, in any one calendar year, send telegrams free of charge, irrespective of destination, up to a limit of two thousand words, through the Civil Telegraph Station established at Sharjah. Usual ending.y /s/J/s'V'* 7, 1 © (C13/3/54/51) POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, 4th December, 1951 Your letter (0436/39/51) of the 17th November. 2. For the avoidance of any possible dis pute in the future, I think it would be ad visable to insert 'irrespective of destination” after 'free of charge' in your letter to Shaikh Saqr about the free despatch of telegrams. Otherwise your draft letter is quite satisfactory Please send me three certified true copies of the letter after you have delivered it. 3. With regard to paragraph 3 of your letter, we will send you shortly a suggested draft Alan. (W.S. Laver) A.J. Wilton, Esq., Political Officer, Trucial States, Sharjah. I*- — 11389/47. s/3/&amp;'3/er/ British Residency, Bahrain. 28th November, 1951. -h-'h -M' /^-CT I II I h I 3?)), ^ With reference to your despatch No. 33 (C 13/3/51/51) of November 2I|.th enclosing copies of the Civil Air Agreement recently signed by Wilton and the Ruler of Sharjah, I enclose a copy of the despatch which Sir Rupert has sent to the Foreign Office. You will notice that we have passed on your requests for photostat copies of the Agreement and for the preparation of a new map. 2. We should be glad to know what agreement Wilton made with the Ruler regarding facilities for the despatch of telegrams free of charge to which the correspondence resting with our * letter 1389/34 of August 28th refers. 3- I presume that Wilton is now requesting the Ruler to issue the Air Navigation Regulations as an f Alan. 4. I am returning the map^enclosed with your despatch. trWm iWMv, (C.M. Le Quesne) W. S. Laver, Esq., The Political Agent, Bahrain. -I*-/- vo 4ho. 132 (1389A6). COKFIDSM UAL Sir, I have the honour to refer to my despatch No* 126 (1389/Vl-) of October 27th and to enclose herewith the original copy of the Air Agreement and exchange of letters concluded between His Majesty*s Political Officer in the frucial Coast and the Ruler of Sharjah together with the Air Navigation Regulations annexed to the agreement* I should be grateful if in due course you could provide me with six photostat copies of these documents* In addition to the original copy of the agreement and the exchange now of letters which I/enclose 9 two additional copies were signed and these have been retained by the Ruler and by the Political Officer* 2* Ifce map attached to the letter from the Political Officer to the Ruler was that enclosed with General Ttepartnontfe letter p ni. 13 / 20 '(/‘lu 8- W 75?6/3/$02 of April 29th, 1949. this raaPt however, does not sho* the extension to the airfield to which we secure the Ruler*s agreement in 1950. I suggest therefore that a further map be prepared showing the present extent of the airfield and that the Ruler be aaiced to substitute it for the out of date map which he at present has* In the event of your approving this proposal, I should be grateful if I could be supplied with six copies of the revised map* I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir, Your most obedient Servant, The Right Honourable Anthony uiden, Ssquire, M*C* , M*P., His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affaire, London, 3*W*1* (W*R* Hay)0436/39/51. British rncy, Shor^ah. 17th H c vr ■ :ab c r, 1951. Please, refer to ny desj tch ho.9 rf 15th a .gv . r. 2. v/hen the P;ul r signer' the Air Ayr^enent he remind eh :-is of tl i. concession by which he is t© be j &lt; r litter to send 2000 words a year by telegraph fr e of charge, and I said that I would write him a further letter on this subject. I enclose a draft letter which I shall send if you see In this connection please see paragraph 6 of residency letter 1389/29 of 18th July forward* ‘ to me with C 'li amts sli i G13/3/34/51 of 25th July, tnc paragraph 3 of my letter 0436/24/51 of 13th .august. •rant of the facility has b&lt; n settled, , no I should he grateful if you could give me your approval for the letter to be sent. 3. article 14 of the Agreement states that the he ulaticn annexed to the agreement shall be given the force of law in the territory of the Shaikh. The Shaikh is a little hazy about hew to achieve this result, nrv r havin. pronuloatei a written law in his life, and having n© precedent to work ©n. Have you a simple example of a form cf wor : s used in Bohrcin to give legal force to a document such as this which is already dn f ted? I have su as ted that when photostat copies cf the ^';r&lt; meut i nd its Annexes have b-on made, cc ies of the latt r should be avail&lt;ble for inspection at the -irfiel* , tea nthc-r with z cc y of some siarle proclamation by the Shaikh that they are to be c nsic red part of tlx law of his territory. 4. The 74 rifles and 7400 rounds of ammunition have been hair ad ov&lt; r to the Ruler. (-*i • J. Wilton) ,7.0. Lav^ r Bsquira, li.I-I. Peliticcl x. -ent Bahrain. , 3 / 3 / 4 -/^ 13/3 / Iff i' 7 -Draft. Shaikh Saqr bin Sultan al ^asini, Rul: r of Sharjah. After compliments, In connection with the Civil aviation Agreement signor; by ycu on 15th he v^.h'-.r 1951, I am to inform ycu that you may, in any one calendar y r ar, send telegrams free of charge up to limit of two the use no words, through the civil tele: raph station established at Sharjah. Usual ending.9SB5*p- f is/s/bjf ^ 1 y i ) D«spstch No.33. (0X3/3/80/51) POLITICAL AGENCT, BAHRAIN, 84th November, 1981. #•-/ ^ 1 - _J5 31r 9 I have the honour to report that the Sharjah Civil Air Agreement, which replaces the Agreoaent of the 22nd July, 1932, was signed by the Ruler of Sharjah and H.M. Political Officer or the 16th November, 1961. I enclose the top copy of the Agreement, together with e signed copy of H.M. Political Officer's letter (04 cj 6/36/51) to the Ruler and the Ruler's reply con cerning the special position of the Royal Air Force. The Ruler and H.M. Political Officer both possess signed copies of all these documents. 2 . 'I should be grateful if Your Excellency would be so good as to ask the Foreign Office to have photostat copies made of these documents. I should be glad to have four copies; one copy I need for ray files, and the Chief Engineer, Air Headquarters, Habbaniya, has also asked for a copy. 3. I venture to draw Your Excellency's attention to the fact that the map supplied to the Shaikh of Sharjah, as an attachment to the Political Officer's letter to him about priority for Royal Air Force air craft and the renting of the Royal Air Force Camp, , n* p lllzx shows the airfield as it was before the extension was ' * carried out In 1960. ify only copy of this map is S Cm*-**/ enclosed for ease of reference. The other map enplt^sed in Your Excellency's letter to my predecessor No.^l/10/49 of the 7th fc§ay, 1949 (see paragraph 2 of that letter) is also transmitted herewith; this map indicates the extension which was then proposed. I venture to sug gest, for Your Excellency's consideration, that the Foreign Office be requested to provide me with four or five copies of an up-to-date map showing the extended airfield, one of which could be substituted for the map in the Shaikh's possession and one be placed on the files of the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, and of this Agency. 4. I should be grateful if you would return the two maps in due course. X have the honour to be. Sir, Your Excellency's most obedient servant, (W.S. Laver) H.M. Political Agent. His Excellency the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. -M</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001a2_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/939</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001a2</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/939</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File No. 13/3-ii. SHARJAH AIR AGREEMENT (Aerodrome Facilities at Sharjah).'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1951/1951</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-23T21:04:15</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (36 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>The main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 36; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-35; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises a signed copy of the Sharjah Civil Air Agreement with accompanying air navigation regulations, and an exchange of letters between the Shaikh of Sharjah (Shaikh Saqr bin Sulṭān Āl Qasimī) and the Political Officer on the Trucial Coast (Arthur John Wilton).Also included in the file is correspondence between the Political Officer on the Trucial Coast and the Political Agent at Bahrain, which concerns the following: an agreement for free facilities for the despatch ingof telegrams, which are to be granted to the Shaikh of Sharjah; information on how to publicly announce a written law in Sharjah.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Sharjah, Āl Qāsimī dynasty</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>RAF Sharjah, British air base</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Sharjah</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001a2#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>