<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00009f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T17:05:10.098Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">-r By Air Mail. (9 . I . 13.41 «s.\ rerun nj. ed with the compliments of the Secretary, Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to... ba^Mdi.^v.*^ ^ NiJV ,4, 'll Tire injrcigrr -S ecfetary, ^uvenmi^lll of India. The Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf (11807) Wt.27899/P.287 2,000 9/39 A.&lt;fc B.W.Ltd. Gp.685ii,xt.716b/4:l ±1 • © (Cypher) V' biX.ioiT. LirJtr.j.t'ix.itiu.T^Lii hO.^. I'i-iOia XU- TC h.9.10. p.iii. 7th November, 1941. i-,Q. 998 7th November, 1941. Repea tea to Cover riment of India No. 14216. Ba^haad ho.1139. //// inlijjiA'H . Ily inmediately precedii% tele^ran. Followiiie, is text of araft Regulation. Begins. 1 any person to whom this Regulation applies who is in the employment of persons carrying on any essential undertaking shall, whether or not he is bound by contract to ao so, continue in the en^loyment of those persons in such capacity as they may from time to time specify, unless the becretary of ntate or some person acting with the authority of the secretary of btate consents to his leaving that employment proviaea that corjsent under this Regulation to a person leaving his enp)loyment shall not be efusea, unless the Secretary of ^tate or, as the case may be, -he person acting wrth his authority is satisfied that the employers are willing to continue the employment on reasonable terms. 2. The persons to whom this Regulation applies are British subjects or British protectea persons to whom the Regulation is applies by a airection of the decretory of otate or some person acting with the authority of the secretary of Btate, being persons employea in Persia or in any such other foreign country or territory, in which for the time being His Majesty has no jurisdiction, as may be specifies in an orcier of the Secretary of State. 3. In this Regulation the expression 'essential undertaking' means any unsertakirg specifies in an orser of the Secretary of State as an undertaxing the carrying on of which appears to the Secretary of State to be essential for the prosecution of the war.SijGRKT Ext.7190/41 OUTWARD TELEC^AIvi (This Document is the property of His Britannic Lajesty^ Government, and should he kept under Lock and Key)* (CYPHKR) DLPARTDLNTAL NO. 2* PROk PORLIGiN QPPIGH TO TEHRAN. No* 997* D. 9*05 p*m. 7th November, 1941* 7th November, 1941. Repeated to Government of India No* 14215 Bagdad No. 1138. Ii .a. KDIATE. SECRET. Your telegrams Nos. 839 (of 24th September) and 1028 (of 22nd October). Proposal now under urgent consideration is that a Regulation shall be made by Order-in-Council under the i&amp;nergency Powers (Defence) Acts 1939-1940 under which departure of personnel in Persia of Anglo-Persian Oil Company and Imperial Bank can be prohibited under penalties enforcible in the Courts of the United Kingdom for disobedience. Text of draft Regulation is given in my immediately following telegram. Please telegraph immediately your comments. Text is being discussed here simultaneously with representatives of the Company and the Bank. 2. Regulation applies to Persia, but can be extended to other countries such as Iraq by Secretary of State. It is proposed to delegate to you power to specify the undertakings in Persia whose employees will be affected, but that you should inform me before specifying undertakings in addition to Anglo-Persian and Imperial Bank. It is also proposed to delegate to you the power to apply the Regulation to employees of specified undertakings. This means that you will have to issue a formal order under Regulation specifying the categories of employees of British nationality to whom the order is applied, or else mention them by name•/name. If your order specifies categories, which is perhaps the preferable alternative, A.I.O.G. and Bank should not only furnish you with descriptions of the categories, but also with list of names in each category, and you should make them responsible for seeing that each of the individuals concerned is personally notified. You will have to take steps to ensure that your orders specifying'the undertakings and the employees are brought to the knowledge of the companies and persons affected in a manner which will be easily susceptible of proof in court. 3. When, as the result of your orders, the Regulation becomes applicable to certain employees, they are forbidden to leave their employment without your consent, but it is stated that you shall not withhold your consent unless you are satisfied that the company is willing to offer them terms of employment which you consider reasonable. You are in this way made responsible for seeing that employees who are retained as the result of your orders receive reasonable terms and your power to let them leave Persia is the means by which you can bring pressure on companies to grant reasonable terms of employment. Employees detained by your orders^should know that they can appeal to you as regards conditions of employment. Naturally you will not keep in Persia any employee whom the company are not anxious to retain. 4. The penalty for disobedience to your orders under the Regulation is not specified in this particular Regulation, but you will have to see that the following '/X note is brought to the attention of those concerned: u Any person who on returning to the United Kingdom is convicted of having left his employment in contravention of this Regulation will under Regulation 92(1)♦of the Defence (General) Regulations, T 1939, be liable, on summary conviction to imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months or to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and such fine, or on conviction on indictment, to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding five hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and such fine. 1 '^ X' 1 745 9/41. (£7042/68/34) (CUHl^) . j?'KOk rU.LuiOi. TO . OkOiO^T. 1 , 0 . 1052 . 19th November, 1941. u.10.40 p.m., 19th November, 1941. iiepeatea to Government of India, Ho. 14871. Bagdad ho.1174. hhh IMPORTAI^T. k telegram ho.997 (of hovember 6th. proposed Regulation prohibiting departure from Persia of personnel of ^nglo-Iranian Oil Company and Imperial Bank of Iran) . As the result of consultation here with Company and Bank, it has been decided to abandon proposal that the formal Order to be made by you under hegulation should either specify categories of employees, or mention them by name. Order will ins lead apply to every British subjecl aid. British-protected person who may be employed by the Company or the Bann in Persia. 2. Company and Bank have jointly prepared a draft letter which, if you agree, you should address to their General Managers in Persia. 1 will telegraph to you the text of this draft. This letter will oe sent by you after Order in Council has been issued, and General Managers will be responsible for maxirig- copies and bring a copy personally to the notice of each British subject or British-protectea person in their employment, who will be required to sign an acknowledgment, for transmission t^ you, in the following- terms: ”1 hereby acknowledge having received a copj of His Majesty's Minister's letter dated , together with a copy of Regulation ho ' 3. Meanwhile, Order in Council is being held up pending receipt of your observations. Please expedite your reply.OUTWARD T5LEGRAM. (This docuraent is the proj^erty of His Briti-nnic Majesty’s Goverrjaent, and should be kept under Lock and Key) . (K 7042/68/34) With the Compliments of the Under Secretary of State ,CYPHER) for Foreign affairs. SECRET. lEPARHSI TAL EC .2 . FROM FORE IGF OFFICE TO TBHRAR . “ D.ll.SO p.m.20th November 1941 20th November, 1941. 3 3 3 i) Jiy telegram r r o.l052 (erf Kovember 19th: Proposed regulation prohibiting departure from Persia of personnel of Angfo-Persian Oil Company and Imperial Bank of Persia). Following is draft letter to General Manager Abadan; (Begins) You have been informed on several occasions that His Majesty’s Government regard the operations of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company in Persia as of vital importance to the Rational interest and that the employees of the Company in Persia can best serve the Rational interest by remaining at their posts. I have now to inform you t'at His Majesty's Government have issued regulations by an Order in Council under the Emergency Powers I r ence Act 1939-41 regarding essential undertakings in Persia, and t,,at in virtue of t'e powers conferred on me by t v at Order I have scheduled as an essential undertaking the Company's operations in Persia. I accordingly enclose a copy of the said Order in Council. You will observe that under this Order no British subject or r^ibis' protected person may leave t^e Company's employment, either during or on completion of an agreement, without my prior consent. Any employee so detained by my Order has however the right of appeal to me regarding his or her conditions of service, and any employee who leaves t * 1 -e Company's service without my consent is liable to prosecution as under: ' Any person who on returning to the United Kingdom is convicted of having left his employment in contravention of this Regulation will under Regulation 92(1) of the Defence (General) /(General) Regulations, 1939, be liable, on summary conviction to imprisonment for a term not exceeding t^ree months or to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and such fine, or on conviction on indictment to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years or to &gt;» ' a fine not exceeding- five hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and such fine”. /“*\ 4 ! YOU are requested to bring this Order in Council and t u is letter to t^e attention of your British and British- Indian employees, and to obtain from each individual concerned a -written acknowledgement t’ at this has been done; these acknowledgements should be forwarded to me. I have been much impressed at the manner in which so many of t v e Company’s employees have continued to perform their duties under difficult conditions, and I am confident that in future all will show t r e same spirit and devotion to the Rational Cause. Similar letter with consequential amendments would be addressed by you to the Chief Manager of t v e Imperial Bank. (INDIV)Ext.7673/41. OUTWARD TELEGRAM (E 7759/68/34) © DEPARTIvlEITTAL NO.2. (CODE R) RRQL: PQREION OFFICE TO TEHRAN . No.1094 2/th Nr-erober 1941. D.2.45 p.m. 27th November 1941 Repeated to Government of India No.15257 Bagdad No.1195 Your telegram No.1203 (of the 24th November. Proposed Regulation prohibiting departure from Persia of personnel of Anglo-Iranian Oil Company and Imperial Bank of Iran). f.v An Order-in-Council has been made today November 27th in the terms of my telegram No.SOa/of November 7th). The Secretary of State has also today made an order under the said Order-in- Council. Latter is numbered No.SSAC of the Defence (General) Regulations. You should now at once make a formal order in the t.*-NAs set out in my immediately follow--ig telegram and cause copies of your order to be sent to the Anglo- Iranian Oil Company and the Imperial Bank with a request that your order IMMEDIATE. should/Ext. 7673/41. QTTTV7ARD TSLSG-RAIv! PROM RQRRIGN OPRICE TC TSHRAIT. II o. 109 ^ 27th I\ /ember 1941 D. 5.25 p.m. 27th November 1941. Repeated to Government of India No.15258 I.'y immediately preceding telegram. Text of Order is as follows:- Whereas His Majesty’s Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs by an Order made on the 27th November, 1941 under No. 5$AC of the Defence (General) Regulations made by Order-in-Council dated 27th November, 1941, has ordered (1) that the An.glo-Iranian Oil Co. Limited and the Imperial Banh of Iran are undertakings the carrying on of^ which^j-s essential for the prosecution of tly N tfar: (2) that His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran, or, in his absence, any person Bagdad No.1196i r*»' (Hi \ o ♦ .v (Gener* to imp] fine n&lt; impris&lt; to imp: a fine impris&lt; Y&lt; t^is 1&lt; Indian conceri these { I many oJ their c t^at ii to the Si addresi INDIV: vho with his authority may he acting on 'is Majesty's Minister's enair, is aut orised to direct to what persons the aforesaid Regulation shall + PP-7 and to consent to persons to whom the said Regulation applies leaving their employment and to satisfy himself t h ^'t •when he refuses consent to a o&lt;Hon ’ leaving his employment, the employers are v/illmg to continue the employment on reasonable terms; „ o . J°'f I &gt; Si r Reader Bullard, His Majesty s Minister at Tehran, do hereby B^ti-h ornf^ f ltlsh ^hjects and all Br., ti^h protected persons, who are in one employment in Persia of the Ann-lo- Iraman Oil Company Limited or of the -a'n'r'+'h' Bar h : of iran, are persons to r ° ihe^said Regulation ilo.SSAC of the Defence (General) Regulations apolies. M /ClCONFIDENTIAL. No. 172-3 of 1942. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. ^th”February Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Dnte. 1. Political Residents telegram No. 218, dated 7th February 1942. 2. Political Resident's telegram No. 219, dated 7th February ^ 1942. Subject. DEFENCE REGULATION.79/65 Telegram 'Q' From Political Resident, Bushire. To India Office, London. Repeated Government of India, New Delhi. No. 213 Dated 7th February 1942. Your telegram 901 January 16th. 2. A draft regulation is submitted in my immediately succeeding telegram. 3. Political Agent Kuwait has recommended application of proposed regulation to Kuwait Oil Company after discussion with General Manager. 4. I have included Muscat within scope of regulation in case occasion may subsequently arise to apply it to any undertaking there. 5. I propose that on the issue of the regulation letters under paragraph 5 of your telegram should be handed immediately to European British employees of the undertaking raentioned in 6. Political Agent Bahrain reports that Canadian employ ees of Bahrain Petroleum Company are acutely conscious of their personally which had not received the approval of the Canadian Government, I would sug, ; est therefore that before the regulat ion is applied in practice to them and notices are served on them the approval of their government be obtained. 7. I am not at present fully satisfied that it is national status and would resent any affecting them necessary/• 2 — necessary or desirable to ap^ly the regulation in practise to Indians and should like to postpone my recommendations on this point for a month in the course of which X hope to visit Kuwait and Bahrain and examine question on spot. 8. Reference paragraph 4 of your telegram penalty of one year's rigorous improsomnent has been included in Article 3 of draft regulation to invoke Fugitive Offenders Act so as. to legalise arrest of offenders in India. Article 16 of the Bahrain Order in Council and corresponding articles in other Orders in Council allow for trial of offenders at Bombay. - BRITCQNSJL - R.B.T. 7/2.Repeated Government of India f New Delhi No. 219 Dated 7th February 1942. To Telegran From «Q»« Political Resident| Bushire India Office, London. 79/65 This Regulation shall apply In the territories of tne Shaikh of Kuwait, the Shaikh of Bahrain, the Shaikh of Qatar and the Sultan of Muscat and Oman (hereinafter referred to as the territories) and shall be applicable therein to all •uritisL subjects and British protected persons employ in the territories by the Kuwait Oil Company, the Bahrain Petroleum Company, Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, and in any other undertaking in the said territories which may be specified in an/ order of the Political Resident in the Persian -fair as an undertaking essential for the prosecution of the war 2. (1) Any person to whom this Regulation applies who is in the employment of persons carrying on tie undertakings ment- ioneu in Article 1 of this Regulation or any other undertaking specified by the Political Resident in tie Persien Gulf as an undertaking essential for the prosecution of the war shall, whether or not he is bound by contract to do so, continue in the employment of those persons in such capacity as they may from time to time specify, unless the Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf consents to his leaving that employment, provided that consent under this Article shall not be refused unless the Political Resident in tie Persian Gulf is satisfied that the employers are willing to continue employment on reasonable terms. (2) The powers conferred on the Political Resident by paragraph (1) of this Article may be exercised within their respective spheres of jurisdiction by the Political Agents at/fUU. at Kuwaiti Bahrain and Muscat subject to the control of cue Political Basldant* ^wwn. ^ k 0^^ Article 2 of this Regulation e» shall be liable to apprehension and trial and to a penalty of rigorous or simple inpr son- aent which may extend to one year or to a fine which may extend to 3000 rupees, or both. on board any vessel leaving territory where ho is employed shall be presumed to be contravening the Regulation, and tha onus of rebutting such presumption shall be on him. in Council, 1. 36, the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, the Qatar Order in Council, 1939, relating to criminal matters shall applyt in so far as they may be applicable, to the trial of offences against this Regulation. 6. This Regulation shall take effect i:ru ediately on publication. Any person to whom this Regulation applies found - BRIICONSUL R.E.T. 7/2.O' K- \,RV|W:' Confidential . \ The Residency^ Bushire, the 10th February, 1942 a 9 letter No.C/139, dated the 2nd February 1942. I forward herewith a copy of the reply I have sent to Curtis. 2. I have already submitted my proposals to His Majesty*s Government and the Government of -f n pit India - vide my telegrams Nos.218 and 219 ox the 7th February 1942, copies of which have been sent to you. I had no opportunity to consult you regarding details but if you have any important comments or suggestions to make please telegraph them. Bahrain.ConfIdentic!♦ The Residency y Buanlre, tto XOth February 1^12* D « 0 • HQ • l^ 1 l!!^k “ A Please refer to your demi-OJC/icial letter Ro*L*GOLC- 2. lou have no doubt seen a copy of Wakefield 1 s aer.i- officlal letter Ko*0/139, dated tiie 2nd February 19^2, to me. Ly emu present vlev/ is ti'.at provided tne Bahrain Petroleum employees it will be better not to apply any form of conscrip tion to them. If the other British subjects to whom conscrip tion is boInc applied protest it can be explained to then , their case replacement is not possible whereas it is in the case of Aniericons and Canadians, end Cb) that it is in accordance with the law in force in the United Kingdom, and that no such law has yet boon introduced in America or Canada. Argument (b) of course only applies to luropenr. British subjects and not to Indians. 3 # x propose to examine the whole question further when I visit Bahrain early In 1.arch end will then confirm or revise ny views.. The matter of imueciiats l*nporta-»co is Lo apply conscription to the European BritisU employ oa u--© Oil i^omp.anies. 22/41, dated the 20th December 1941. Curtis Esquire, Additional Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, Extern 1 Affairs iapartment, hew ieihi. Yours sincerely, sd. W.R.Hay.CONFIDENTIAL. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, L/T Nearchus. 'ithhp 0 onsn hd 1 Hih. Dated 4th March 1942 . Government of India telegram No.1562, dated the 1st March 1942. Lf Amendment to Defence of India Rules.M ■III**'s. Telegram © Repeated From To Government of India, New Delhi Minister, Tehran. No.98. Political Resident, at Kuwait. India Office, London. Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr. No.1562 Dated 1st received 2nd March 1942 IMMEDIATE Your telegram No.116 of 26th February 1942 Following is draft of Notification No.1256 OR/42 which will appear in the Gazette of India March 7th. In exercise of the powers conferred by Section Two of the Defence of India Act 1939 (XXXV) of 1939 the Central Government is pleased to direct that the following further amendment shall be made in the Defence of India Rules namely. 2. After Rule 81(a) the following Rule shall be inserted namely 81(b), provision with regard to Defence Regulation 58 AC. domiciled in any part of India leaves any employment in contravention of Regulation 58 he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with fine or with both.' for war injuries to employees of the Anglo Persian Oil Company of whatever nationality in Persia is we think a matter for His Majesty*s Government and/or the Anglo Persian Oil Company. A copy of the Indian War Injuries \Scheme 1942 will be sent to Tehran by air mail. f 'If any person being a British subject 3 Application of a scheme of compensation FOREIGN -CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/56* The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents hi compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned Persian Gulf, Bahrain, British Consul ale-G enerah BU SHIRE. xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx Dated, 8th March 1942. kft/Zs. Reference to previous correspondence : it Residency Printed Letter No. 172-S, date d 7th February 1942. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ■ India Office telegram Np&lt; Draft King * s Ragulation 3990, dated 4th March 1942. regarding employment in essential undertakings.79/65. Repeated From Telegram To Political Resident, at Bahrain. Govermient of India, lii.A.h., New L*.^**. Q • India Office, London. No.3990. Dated 4th received 6th March 1942 Your telegrams Nos. 218 and 219 February 7th. I approve draft Regulation subject to the follow ing amendments. In Article 2 (2) for “subject to control of the Political Resident* 1 substitute “subject to such instructions as the Political Resident may from time to time issue to them** • 2 of this Regulation shall be liable on conviction to a penalty of imprisonment not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding 6500 or to both such imprisonment and f ine**. Words “to apprehension and trial at Bombay md“ have been ommitted because action suggested in paragraph No. 4 of my telegram No.901 January 16th would have to be taken by legisla tion in India, and not by Regulation in Persian Gulf. You will no doubt consider in consultation with the Government of India whether it is sufficient that the provisions of the Fugitive Offenders Act are attracted by scale of punishment provided or whether it is desirable that notification similar to that in Government of India's telegram No.1562 which it will be observed only covers limited class of British subject domiciled in India should be issued so as to cover offenders increased so as to conform with maximum penalties enforceable in the United Kingdom against those who infringe the Regulation applicable to Persia. This is desirable since it is proposed if possible to punish in this country people who disobey your Regulation (see paragraph ^o.3 of my telegram No.901). (b) Order of articles should be altered so that Nos. 4 and 5 become 3 and 4 and No.3 becomes No.5. (c) Article 3 (now 5) should read as followsi “Any person contravening the provisions of Article fv^V * against this Regulation also. Maximum penalties have beenH'1 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain, ^ The Political Agent, Muscat, 0 ^ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (/). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain Dated yth March 1942. Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed Letter Eo.C/56, dated the 8th March 1942. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. / Political Resident’s tele grain So.T/96, dated the 9th March 1942 . Regulation relating to essential under takings*79/66. y ’ (f)* .. Telegram 79/66. &lt;*• From Political Besident 9 at Bahrain. To uovernment of India* Hew Delhi* Copy by nlr mil to H.U** Sooratary of State for India, London. Ho.T/96. Dated the 9th March 1942. ^ \ a. India Offloe telegram ho.dVOO March 4th* J^egal experts of Government of India will no doubt advise whether existing proyieione in Oroere in CounoiX of. Article 16 of Bahrain Order in Council and of Fugitive Offenders Act are sufficient to cover trStyl in India of offenders against the proposed Regulation. 5. Meanwhile X propose to issue regulation without awaiting a decision on this point* Po Government of India agree T • - R&amp;&amp; UDhilT •■■■■■■■■■■■■I0 \&gt;l J l CONFIDENTIAL. v No . 0/119 of 1942. 1 £ +■ L,} JO |M &gt; The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, The Political Agent, The Political Agent, Kuwait, Bahrain, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^* British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp, BAHRAIN. Dated .. ^ th ^ March. 1942. -• ^ Reference to previous correspondence: ^ Besidenoy Printed Letter Ho.0/97, dated the 9th March 1942. “ jj \ &gt;p % % Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject. Government of India, External Affairs Depart ment, telegram No.1822, dated the 12th March 1942. Regulation regarding essential undertakings.Telegram Q. From Political Resident, at Bahrain Government of India, New Delhi To Repeated Secretary of State for India, London Political Agent, Cuwait. / Copy given to Political Agent, Bahrain No.T/141. Dated the 19th March, 1942 I Reference India Office telegram No*3990 Liarch 4th and my telegram T/96 'larch 9th copy to India Office by air mail. of Bahrain Petroleum Company and Petroleum Concessions Limited. Both are anxious that Regulation should be applied to Indians at the same time as to British European employees. Indian employees can give a month's notice and are difficult to replace. I also discussed this question with Management of Kuwait Oil Company who had no strong views either way. 3. On the whole I am in favour of applying Regulation to Inians provided they are first given dearness allowance. This matter is under consideration at Bahrain and it is h oed it will be settled within two or three weeks. At Kuwait Company have allowed Indians to purchase rations at pre-war rates. Some dearness allowance in addition is I think desirable but number of men concerned is small, and it is not n cessaty + delay action pending a settlement of their case. British and Indians should be served simultaneously to emphasise similarity of treatment and avoid possibility oi wholesale resignation by Indians. I see no harm in holding up issue of Regulation for short time until question of dearness allowance 2. I have discussed Regulation and letter with Management I also agree that it will be better that n^ .ces on is s ttled / 5 /5# Bahrain Petroleum Company are now very lukewarm the proposed Regulation and would I think like to see It dropped. v They expect a good deal of protest from malcontent portion of their British employees (amounting to about 20 per cent.) based on fact that o&gt; nscription is not being applied to Americans and Canadians accompanied probably by some*mlingering. Malingerers can be dealt with by deportation to India and conscription there but there are real practical difficulties in arrest and detention of Ffcropean British subjects as use of Bahrain Police or Indian troops would probably lead to violence and there is no other Instrument wU ch can be employed. I consider however that we must proceed with issue of Regulation and that these difficulties must be faced. - Resident.e**'* s° s&gt; THE BAHREIN PETROLE a COOTHENTIAL No. PA*28 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. OMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. March 16th, 1942. Bear Sir, 7/e have to advise you that it has 'become necessary to terminate the Foreign Service Agreement of the above-named member of our Staff for being in toxicated. while on duty as Mooring Master. Arrangements are being made for Mr. Hale to leave for India by the first opportunity, and we shall be glad, therefore, if you will issue the necessary Exit Permit, to enable him to leave Bahrein. Yours very truly, '7??. //■ M. H. LTPP7 Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. A* C* $9 ^ ^ dtf JUbcrtk , ^ , a.3 - /i- /?o 2..the Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali: No. PA-725* Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Vf* October 12th, 1941, HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S POLITICAL ACHNT, Bahrein* Dear Sir, S2CIT PERtvIIT W.C. MERWOOD. Mr. Merwood called on you recently and obtained the enclosed Exit Permit* Unfortunately he apparently did not make himself very clear. Full details of his case are as follows Kerwood has completed his 30 months contract with this Company, and has proved himself in every way a very desirable employee. has been employed as an Operator in our Power Plant a f a I ' eter He is now entitled to a vacation. We have thS ! i f he wil1 tatce hiE leaTe in either India or South ,..ica, we should be very glad to have him return to Efehrein for ' f -^ h e r wf°!J 1Ce * Ife feels * however, that he must return to the Un ted kingdom as he states his presence there is required for some business. We have infoimed him that we cannot re-emoloy bfenf^t r ! h6 TJhited *hat he is liable'to be enlisted in India for service in His J%jesty»s Forces, Would you, therefore, please amend the enclosed Frit aSom viaTd, Mr * IlIerwood t0 proceed from Efehrein to the United Kingdom via India on or about October 25th, 1941, Yours very truly, A*) ' 4 ^ &amp; 'A?. V % \ Sncl; One* / / TEB:CDS* U M. H. LIpp Chief Local Representative, TEE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. &lt;SPertnit issued under Regulation No.2 of 1940 b v the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf—The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. November 4th, 1941. Awali, L~ % PA-771 Mr. W.C. Merwood His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. Pear Sir, Further to my letter No. PA-725 of October 12th, 1941. Mr. Merwood has now decided not to return to the United Kingdom, hut instead to take his leave in India and Ceylon. A passage has been obtained for him on the flying boat due to leave for Karachi on November 6 th. Would you kindly issue an Exit Permit to enable Mr. Merwood to leave by this flying boat, also the usual certificate to facilitate his return to Bahrein upon com pletion of his leave. It would be much appreciated if these documents could be delivered to Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Coy. tomorrow (Wednesday) morning, so that they may be handed to Mr. Merwood before he leaves. THS BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY T.TMT Tan •Gw** / si/#:CBRTIFICATS an employee of the Bahrain Petroleum Conpany Limited, Bahrain is proceeding on short 0 ■ ^ leave to * , He is due to return to duty with the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain on expiry of his leave and it is requested that he may be permitted to proceed from accordingly. Bahrain, Dated the 1942. for H.B.Iv^s Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential No# C/339 The Agency, Bahrain, the 20th March 1942 To B# Crow Esquire, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited Awali# Dear Sir Will you please^r^er to Mr. Lipp f s con fidential letter No.PA-28, dated March 16th, 1942 about the dismissal of Mr.Hale? 2. An Exit Permit in favour of Mr.Hale has already been sent to you. I shall be obliged if you will let me know as soon as the information is available to you the date of Mr.Hale* s departure from Bahrain, the name of the boat on which he travels, his port of destination and probable date of arrival. If Mr. Hale is travelling to India by air advance in formation of this fact would be welcome. Yours faithfully Politic Agent, Bahrainl+f&gt; Confidential* No .C/341 The Agency, Bahrain the 21st March 1942. To The Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. Memorandum ' the difficulty which the Bahrain Petroleum Company ex perienced in securing the return of employees who left Bahrain on leave ; and he showed you a cable he had just received from England about a certain Mr.Merwood. The wording of the cable was as follows t- w Merwood secured transportation India South Africa thence United Kingdom arrived January 21, report today and prepared return Bahrain if required.* 2. You asked roe to let you have details of the case so that you could, if you thought advisable, find out how Mr.Merwood was enabled to leave India. ative, Bahrain Petroleum Company, informed the Agency that Mr. Merwood was taking leave in India and Ceylon, and that a passage had been obtained for him on the flying boat due to leave Bahrain for Karachi on November 6th. He asked that an Exit Permit might be given to Mr.Iferwood, and also a certificate in the usual form to facilitate his return to Bahrain on the expiry of his leave. 4. An Exit Permit was Issued, and also a Certi ficate of Return (copy enclosed)• 5. The Manager of the Bahrain Petroleum Company informed Mr. Merwood that the Company would not re-employ On March 16th Mr. Lipp complained to you of 3. On November / himM © - 2 ~ him if h« returned to tho Dbltod Kingdom{ and it » a3 on hia aaaurance that he would not go there that the Company asked the Agency to issue a Certificate of itetunu 6. Possession of the Certificate of Beturn probably enabled Mr. Merwood to escape military conscription in Indiej but it would be intereating to know how he secured a peaaage to South Africa* Political Agent 9 Bahrain*CERTIFICATE # No#2193. Mr# W#C# Merwood an employee of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited* Bahrain is proceeding on short leave to India and Ceylon# He is due to return to duty with the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain on expiry of his leave and it is requested that he may be permitted to proceed from India and Ceylon accordingly. Bahrain, Dated the 5th November 194i. For H#B#M#'s Political Agent, Bahrain#CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/205 of 1942. I ($ M' The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp. BAHRAIN. Dated... 22nd _ March _ 1942. £ &amp; Reference to previous correspondence : -VO! Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject. Demi-official letter No. DO/CM.5/2877, dated the 17th March 1942, from Mr. E.V. Packer, Petroleum Concession Regulation relating to 3 the conscription of Limited, Bahrain. labour in essential undertakings. Political Resident’s demi- official letter No.C/200, dated the 21st March 1942.CONFIDENTIAL Petroleum Concessions Ltd. Bahrain DO/CM.5/2877 Persian Gulf. 17th March, 1942. Dear Colonel Hay, The following perhaps may be of interest in connec tion with the subject discussed this morning (17th March.). 1. Composition of P.C.L. &amp; P.P.Q. employees P*C.L. &amp; P.D.Q. comprise: (a) British on formal agreements, usually for 3 years. (b) Americans, on formal agreements, usually for 3 years. (c) British Indians, clerical, artizan, and domestic types, on Protector of Emigrants contracts, for periods varying from one to three years. (d) British Indians, clerical, artizan and servant types, recruited in Bahrain on ordinary letters of engagement. (e) Portuguese Goans, recruited in Bombay on similar conditions to those laid down in Protector of Emigrants agreements. Their agreements, however, are not signed by the Protector of Emigrants, and they are not entitled to protection from him, presumably because they do not come under the Indian Emigration Act. (f) Certain employees, British Indians, but not recruited under the Protector of Emigrants arrangements as they belong to professions excluded from his control under the Indian Emigration Act. (g) Miscellaneous, Iraqis, Koweitis and Saoudis. (h) Locals, Bahrainis and Qataris. Categories (a), (c), (d) and (f) are affected by the scheme under discussion. Although in theory the above categories could pre sumably be retained indefinitely under the new measures, in practice it would be necessary to arrange some sort of leave programme. Leave is not catered for in any of the agreements but it has been the Company T s practice to allow leave after three years* service. In Bapco to date it has generally been given on the understanding that the man is2 iv is returning to work. In practically every case leave will be taken by Indians in India. (British and Americans may go to South Africa if their wives are there or to any adjacent country, if families do not come into the question). It would seem advisable in any scheme which is being pre pared to include consideration for leave after 3 years as and when an opportunity arises and some machinery to ensure that the employee taking leave will return to his location. The principle that leave is not a right should be maintained. As regards locally recruited Indians under the new scheme, it would be necessary for the Company to decide whether they should be granted leave in Bahrain or whether the Company would accept the cost of their passage to India and return. The Company’s chief difficulty with Indians in operating the new scheme will be in coping with the mal contents anxious to get away who refuse to work or adopt a policy of passive resistance. Under paras 3 and 4 (copy attached) of their agree ments (3 and 5 artizans) it might be possible to reduce their pay by half. In Qatar as free food is not a right the line could be taken that active and passive resisters who will not work shall not eat at the Company’s expense. Grant of long or local leave could also be made dependent upon satisfactory work and behaviour. Yours sincerely. Sd.E.V.Packer. Enel. Lieut.-Colonel W.R.Hay, C.I.E., BAHRAINEXTRACT FORM OF AGREEMENT IN RESPECT OF CLERKS AND OTHER SPECIAL CLASSES OF EMPLOYEES Provided that the Employee shall perform his duties diligently and to the satisfaction of the Company and shall observe all the conditions of this Agreement, he shall receive a salary during the period of his service on Bahrein Island and the Company*s concession areas in the hinterland at the rate of Rs. a month for the first year. Rs. a month for the second year. Such salary to be paid at the latest on the 15th day of the month succeeding that in which it was earned. The salary of the employee shall commence from the date above mentioned, which will be the date of his engagement in India, and except in the event of his dismissal or as is stated in clause 9 read with clause 10 shall cease on the date of his return to the place of his recruitment in India. The employee shall be entitled during illness or other forced idleness during his employment on Bahrain Island or the Company*s concession areas in the hinterland to a minimum wage of not less than half of the monthly pay on which he is engaged. EXTRACT FORM OF AGREEMENT IN RESPECT OF ARTISANS Provided that the employee shall perform his duties diligently and to the satisfaction of the Company and shall observe all the conditions of this Agreement, he shall receive a salary during the period of his service on Bahrein Island and the Company’s concession areas in the hinterland at the rate of Rupees per diem and not less than Rupees P e ^ mensem, such salary to be paid at the latest on the loth day of the month succeeding that in which it was earned. The employee shall be entitled during illness or other forced idleness to a minimum of not less than half of the monthly pay on which he is engaged.CONFIDENTIAL Office of the Political Resident D.Q. NO.C/2QQ in the Persian Gulf Camp, Bahrain, 21st March, 1942. Please i^fer to your demi-official letter No. DO/C!'.5/2877, dated the 17th March 1942. 1. The proposed Regulation will not prevent the Companies concerned from granting such leave to their employees as they consider desirable. 3. If any employees fail to return from leave there will be machinery for punishing them in India or the United Kingdom but not elsewhere. 4. If a Company can show good reason for discharging a man it is most unlikely that consent will be refused. 5. Malingerers and passive resisters will undoubtedly constitute a difficulty but ways and means can probably be found for dealing with them. 6. If you require any further elucidation I shall be glad if you will come and discuss the case with me again at some suitable time. Sd. W.R. Hay. E. V. Packer, Esquire, Petroleum Concessions Ltd. BAHRAIN.\ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL) IN.B. This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] It is authenticated by the signature of a No. C/211. Camp, BAHRAlB, Dated the 23rd Karel. 1S4&amp; Camp, Bahrain, Dated the 23rd Marct. 19S&amp; To The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Fe'v Delhi, Repeated - The Political A^ent, Bahrain, y A copy of Bahrain memorandum Uo.C/o41, dated the 21st March 19*2, is forwarded herewith. may he ascertained how Merwood was permitted to leave India. Although he is a man whom the Company can ill afford to spare and has applied from the United Kingdom for permission to return the Company are refusing to re-employ him in case others may follow his example. 3* As it is, his success in managing to leave India and reach the United Kingdom is likely to encourage others to attempt the sane. It is accordingly requested that every effort may he made to prevent European British employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company on leave in India, from leaving the country except to return to employment at Bahrain. It is requested that if there is no objection it Sd. W.R. Hay. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Attested. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. {Signature) S. 44. MFP—1048 S&amp;P—f 11 - 2042 )— 17 - 12 -^—20,000. {Designation)CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/233 Of 1942. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. 2. 3. The The The Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muacat, ¥ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Ca mp* Bahrain. Dated.. 26tJ»..;4areh,1942... Reference to previous correspondence : To 1. Political Resident *s telegram No.T/141 of 19th March 1942. To 2. Residency Express Letter No.p Q/232 of 26th March 1942*^ 1* To 3. Residency Printed Letter No. C/138 of 19th March 1942. % ' s? 1 yf?'- '1 r i mcf- jj / Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject. m No* 1 ’ 942 ; 1. India Office telegram 5260 of 22nd March 2. Government of India tele_ No.2302 of 24th March 1942&lt; $ 3. Express Letter No.C/232 of 26th March 1942 to the Political Agent, Bahrain. 5 to 1.* 3.only. ^ * V A Industrial ConscriptionGovernment of India* ! T ew Delhi* ? To political Resident, at Bahrain. ^ • Bo 2302• ^ 1 Dated and received 24th I.larch, 1942*^o\ Your telegram T/143 of Iferch 19th. 2. The essential Services (Maintenance) Ordinance 1941 empowers Governments to order persons engaged in oer*a n emplovments to remain so employed and provides for safeguards for the regulation of wages and conditions of service. Copy follows hy air mail. - Foreign. W.L.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Confidential Department EXPRESS LETTER [N.B. This is an ORIGINAL message sent by ALR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save lime and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a rcvanMk officer of ^DeparUnen,^ 0ffice of the p olitlcal HeSidSlt March 1942 is forwarded herewith,for your very early comments. 3. I should he glad to know whether the Jurisdiction the Political Agent, Bahrain, possesses over foreigners has ever been exercised in respect of U.S.A.subjects. sd. W. B. Hay. Political 'Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Pers ..an Gulf. S. 44. MFP—1048 S&amp; P—(M-2042)—17-12.37—20,0(0. {Signature) Designation)79/65 T^lfigraa Q. Incici Oi l ice, U&gt;i:idon. Political Resident, i t Bahrain, Government of Incile, K.A.D., Hew r-tihi. From To Hepe^teU Mo,5^60 D^tcd ^nd deceived L4th iarch X94; . Mo.T/14i of March 19th paragrcph Ho*5. Caiiaai&amp;n Government is beAii^ consulted regarding ep^llcction of Rtguli tion to Canadians* /s regards Americans we understand B*A.P*C#0* Head Oil ice have consulted * f* U.8.A* Governaient as to possibility of legislation to Compel their posts. This se ms all to the go d but it *ou!ci be unuesirtble to rely solely on action by the U.S.iU Government because — (a) legisl. tion by them could presumably only provide for trial ana to punishment on arrival in U.l.A. after leaving their employment iX Bahrain* This by itself would appear ineliactive. (b) that we should not ap ear to be giving up jurisdic tion over foreigners which we possess in ail Persian Guxi States except Muscat. M* It hv.s th ref ore been sugiosten tn^t a further lieguiv tion should be ne.de applying the provisions oi tne Regulation which you 4 re now making to ail f oreigners over whom we possess jurisdiction. This would of course include U.; .A. nationals employee by Oil Companies t.t Bahrain and Kuwait; and before Reguli tion could be »aue it would be nocoasary to obtain the consent of the U.S.A* Government. d, I should tit* glad of your vie%is ana those of the Government of Iiiui . the Conpany | s employees who are U.S.A* nationals to regain at - iufi U 4 DU, -GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, .Departmknt. EXPRESS LETTER Confidential [N, B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and, undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sane time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.'] Befarence your *£xpress Letter No. C/232 dated the 26th March, 1942* 2* The jurisdiction which the Political Agent, Bahrain, possesses over foreigners has been exercised on several occasions in respect of U.S.A* subjects. Both civil and criminal jurisdiction have been so exercised. n 3. In regard to India Office telegram No. 5260 dated the 22nd March 1942 the following comments are offered *- (i) The action of BAPCO Head Office in consulting the U.S.A. Government about the possibility of legislation to compel U.S.A. nationals to remain at their p ~ ~ presumably taken in consequence of Lipp’s cable _ (copy enclosed with my confidential demi-official letter No. C/139 dated the 2nd Febmaiy 1942) • From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Besldent, Camp Bahrain. No, Doled m . C/373 28th March 1942. s. 5. MFT— 400S&amp; P— (M-480)—26*7-84—2,00,000. (ii) A- 2 - (ii) Extension of Heguletion to cover all foreigners over whom we exercise jurisdiction is excellent proposal provided that three conditions are fulfilled: (a) Such extension should be with the approval of the U#S.A* Government (b) Such extension should be made simultaneously with or after, but not before, application of industrial conscription to Canadians (c) Imerican employees of CASOC on mainland should be treated in similar manner. In regard to (c) attention is drawn to the following American CASCO employees should be treated same as Americans Bahrain under any enforced regulations otherwise dissension will result as exchange personnel certain categories now common practice and we dependent their crude supply n Fulfilment of condition (c) prime facie appears difficult but unless it can be fulfilled I think extension of Kegulation in manner proposed would do more harm than good. Extension of Kegulation as proposed would bring within orbit of conscription Goanese, Iraqis, Kuwaitis and Saudi Arabians. I see no harm in this. passage in Lipp»s cable of 31st January.* Political Agent, BahrainNo. C/246 CONFIDEN The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 3. The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(^). British Consulate-General, BU8HIRE. Dated...27th March ,1.^42 Ganp, Bahrain. .^•Bldency Printed Letter ’'o.C/97 of . r™ ; 9th HlAT&amp;i ,1942 • Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject. Government of India telegram No. 2299 of 24th 1942. Industrial ConscriptionTelegram Q. From Government of India, New Delhi. To Political Resident, at Bahrain. No. 2299. Dated and received 24th March 1942 Your telegram T/96 M&amp;rch 9th. 2. Provisions of Fugitive Offenders Act 1881 are attracted by sc&amp;le of punishment provided in Regulation and no further Statutory nUe is required in British India to authorise rendition of fugitive offenders against Regulation. - Foreign. W.LjoJi- G- l ^ J ote on a discussion hoM at the Agency at 11 a«fiu on Thur8day 9 Search 26th f regarding the grant of an allowance to Indian employ ees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company to compensate for the increased coet of living. Presents- The Political Agent 9 l^r.C.P.Belgrave, Adviser to the Bahrein Government. &amp;r«%r*Campbell 9 Manager f dray Mackensle d Co. Manager 9 Baatarn Bank Limited. Kr. ^.V.Pecker, Manager« Petroleum Concessions Ltd* Mr.F # ^.Ohliger f Manager, California Arabian Standard Oil Company. Mr .Ward P.^nderaon, Manager, Bahrain Petroleum Co* hr.B.Crow (Bahrain Petroleum Company) . The Political Agent opened the dissuasion by giving information about the prices of foodstuffs now as compared with September 1939, by describing the system of price control in Bahrain and by touching on soma of the factors which affected local prices. The Political Agent further gave information about the amount of stocks of food at present in Bahrain and explained that the most important factor in replenishing stocks was that of shipping space. The question of using native craft to a greater extent was discussed, but Messrs. Belgrave and Campbell pointed out that, owing to the monsoon, import by dho%s is not posalbLs during the 5 months June to October inclusive. After this preliminary talk the conference took up the question whether an increase in wages was justified. It was generally admitted that the cost of living had risen but the majority of the persons present took the view that the wage scale of Indians was already so generous that a rise In the coot of foodstuffs, clothing material etc. did not in any way affect their ability to pay for the necessities of life. Mr .Gunn was strongly opposed to any Increase in pay being given to persons earning mere than fc 900/- a month. Hr.Belgrave said that he had not consulted His Highness the Shaikh and could therefore not speak authoritatively but he thought His Highness would probably agree to give an allowance to employees of the Bahrain Government on a low rate of pay provided, of course, that they were not in receipt of rat Iona (the Bahrain Police- 2 ~ lollce «*g. are given ration®) • Mr •Ward Anderson and Mr.Ohliger urged that the wage® given to their employees in the past left a very cona id arable margin above a H living wage*’ i*e. the minimum wage neceaoory to mipport a man and hi a family* Mr.Chliger said that some years ago the daily wags of unskilled labour was 10 annas* This rate had gradually been raised until now it was Re*l/-,and Re*1/2 for persons who had been in the Company's employment for a year or more* He said that this rate, in spite of the increase in the cost of living^conatituted still a living wage and , while he admitted the responsibility of mi employer to see that employees received e living wage, he sow no reason why higher wages should be paid gratuitously* £* At this point of the discussion Sir* Gunn showed the recently Conference a copy of a cable which he ha^recelved from the Directors of the Eastern Bank in London* The wording of the cable was os followsf- The Directors wish me to emphasize to vou, and through you to the whole of the staff, that the Bank cannot be ex pected to provide them with full relief fro® the higher cost of living and that under present olrcumstnnces a fall in the general standard of living must be accepted by every body as part of the burden of war* * kr* Gunn took this cable to mean that no help was to be given to the Bank's employees to enable them to meet the higher cost of living, and it was necessary for me to point out that his Directors had only taken objection to providing employees with 'full rallaf *• The implication was, X said, that the employee should be given some relief from the higher cost of living* 3* lh*»Ward Anderson denied strongly that his Company was under any obligation to help its employees to meet the Increased cost of living* He pointed out that the wage given to the Company's employees had not been determined by consideration of their living expenses and should not In any way be tied down to this factor. He said that if for one moment the principle was admitted that there existed a basic connection between wages and living cost; every increase in price would be reflected by a / demand- 2 - demand on tho part of aap^qyaea for an Ineraaaa In pay* Ha said that the question we were now discussing was not concern ed with the grant of a living wage since It was admitted on all sides that all classss of the Company'e employees were in receipt of a living wage* V'het we were discusslng 9 he eald v was the question whether y because living costs had In creased* there should be a compensating rise in the pay of employees* and he denied emphatically that the Company was under my obligation to compensate Its employees for the reduction in their savings which was the result of the rise in prices* 4* X said that the matter must be considered from a psychological as wall as from an economic view point* In dian employees at Abadan and Kuwait had been given an Increase of pay* and Indian employees In Bahrain would want to know why they were not being similarly treated* European and Ameer lean employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company had been given a bonus to compensate them for the increased cost of living and other employees might well ask what Justification existed for this d lacrlmlnation* Further* I gave an indica tion of what was proposed in regard to Industrial conscription (although 1 asked persons present at the Conference to keep this matter confidential) and 1 pointed out how much better it would be for all concerned if this measure were preceded by e sympathetic gesture on the part of the Company* 5* Mr*Ward Anderson admitted the relevance of these observations but said that he was still opposed to anything in the nature of a 'dearness allowance 91 which employees would expect to be increased If living costs rose still fur ther* Mr*Ohligar was equally opposed to raising the basic wage of employees sines it would be impracticable to bring wages on to a lower level when prices again became normal. Several members of the Conference thought that* if any allow ance were given to meet the Increased coat of living, it / should■ t r siiould be termed a ^bonua'. I opposed this suggestion since the tens’bonus'has a misleading significance and employees who hod asked for an allowance to meet the Increased cost of living would be dissatisfied* Eventually it wee agreed that if any additional allowance were given it should be termed a 'war allow- ance' f * Thlj term wt*s unobjectionable from all points of view siiiCt; -t» did net constitute a change in the basic wage scale nor* at the same time, would it give employees Justification for demanding a further increase in pay when living costs again in creased* 6* 1.embers of the Conference emphasised the Importance of price control and in this respect I was able to give them the necessary assurance* 1 said that I thought a further rise in price/ inevitable but that this rise would be in the future^ m it had been in the past,proportionate to the rise of pric^fin India, and i added that price control in Bahrain would ensure that local factors e«g* increase of wages or short supply would not affect ^ the price level. 7* 2 asked members of ths Confsrenea, other than those representing the Bahrein Petroleum Company and the California Arabian Standard Oil Company, whether their interests would be a&lt;lv«rs&lt;ily lasted if the Oil companies raised the wages of their employees* They all replied in the negative* Either they had given alroftvl^ a^aal^ increments or they were prepared to do so in future* 8. It was generally agreed that if a war allowance were given to Indian employees a similar allowance should also be given to Bahraini employees* 9* Before the Conference broke up Sir*Ward Anderson said that he thought that a number of useful points had emerged in the course of the discussion and that he would 1st me know as soon as po i^iblo, after further study of the case, what his Company had decided* Ponhcfll* ./ * id// - G-^, / f. The Food Controller has prepared the following table showing the amount of money spent tyr members of various communities in Bahrain earning wages of RslOO/- upwards on foodstuffs* Arab Christian Hindu Prewar * -/13/9 -/15/9 - 10/6 Present * 1 / 10 /- 8 I 1/14/- { 8 1/4/- { Increase * 95 %CONFIDENTIAL. The Hon’ble the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1 . 2 . 3. The Political Agent* The Political Agent, The Political Agent, Kuwait. Bahrain. Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the document^). undermentioned British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp|Bahrain ■ Dated. 3T6tmttttrT942V Reference to previous correspondence : S A* Residency Printed Letter No.C/246 of 27th March 1942. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No.C/283 of 31st March 1942 to the Joint Secretary to the Government of India', External Affairs Department, New D^lhi. Essential Undertakings•Jani'identlal . Ofrice of the Political resident in the Persian Gulf* Cajttp f 3ahrein» D*o»rro.c/a 83 # Det^d the 31at starch t 1942« le'ise refer to T^ctemal Affhlrs Department telegrsiia Ho.2299, dated the 24th ^larch 1942* °* If I understand the position correctly the 'ugitive Offenders /jjt only authorises the rendition of offenders for trial, '’liia rne na tliat offenders will have to be sent b&amp;o&amp; to the Gulf for trial which Is noat undesirable ef«penultimate sentence of my telegr n No.T/141, dated the 19th .torch 1942, or, under Article 1G of the Bahmin Vder in Council (and correspondin 0 Articles of other Orders in Council), tried in Bombay ^hich my well be Inconvenient. In the latter case too the Gulf authorities will be more or leas responsib le for conduct the prosecution which will lead to lo # delays in the present at&gt; te of communications. 3. In view of the above I am inclined to rc-c ;u.K&lt;nd the enactment of special legislation to allow for the arrest and trial in India of offenders against the proposed regulation. I Jp'i-V As pointedout by the India Office in their tel ^raai'tfo.3990, dated the 4th llarch 1942 a notification on the lines of tb^at described in rxtern&amp;l Affairs Department telegram No.l§62, T dated the 1st torch 1942, will not be wide enough. It i© essential that all classes of british subjects to whom the proposed Regulation is applied should b« covered. The most lively type of offender to be met with is the uropean British subject who fails to return from leave in India or who during the course of his leave there tries to obtain a passage to the Mi 1 ed ingdom cf. the case of lerwood vide my Kxpress Letter ?To.C/211, dated the 23rd larch 1942. Yours sincerely, sd. W.R.Hay# H.uSightman Esquire, CIE. ,ICS. f Joint Secretary to the Govern ment of India, 'jctemal Aff^lra^rtawA,His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, 3AB3AIN Dear Sir, CON-991 CONFIDBNriAL The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited 0 Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. March 31st, 1942. Awali, Mr. D. HALE With reference to your Confidential letter C/339 dated March 20, 1942, we have to inform you that Mr. Hale, accompanied hy his wife and daughter, expects to leave Bahrein today hy the 3.S. 'AURIA' for Karachi. The Steam ship Agents inform us they are unahle to divulge when the steamer is expected to arrive in India. We understand from Mr. Hale that he proposes to proceed to South Africa where he has prospects of employment. linary action in this case, hut we believe that the action taken will have the necessary beneficial moral effect. We regret that it became necessary to take discip W. P. ANIXEPSON, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LEDcompliments to 1. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. \J 3. The Political Agent, liuscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(^). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp, Bahrain. Dated .. 2nd April ,.1942 * Reference to previous correspondence : ^ ^ To 1 &amp; 3. Residency Paitited Letter ITo.C/233 of 26th March 1942. &amp; ik ' • ' b: V ^ To 2. Residency Exnress Letter No. L ' C/232 of 26th March 1942. (As- . r-. &gt;. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Political Resident’s tele gram No.T/203 of 2nd April 1942. Essential Undertakings.79/65 Telegrsja q # From Political Resident f at Bahrain. Secretary of State for India, London. Govemnent of India* New Delhi. To f epeated Govem-nent of I No.T/203. Dated the 2nd April* 1942. Your telegram No.5360 March '2nd. Political Agent Bahrain hae frequently in the past exercised jurisdiction he possesses over foreigners in respect of U.S.A.subjects. From this point of view there would there fore be no objection to proposal in paragraph 2 of your tele gram but it would certainly be desirable first to obtain the consent of the U.S.A. Government as you suggest. 3. Peal difficulty arises however from position of CASOC on Saudi Arabian mainland. In telegram sent by/BAPCO to their New York office in January on subject of corlscription n following passage occurs* beginsi \ In view of this I consider it essential that any legislation enacted In America should cover both SAPCO and CASX employees and that CASX employees should be subject to same action in Gulf if they attempt to leave their employment as 3APC0 employees. . 4. If U.S.A. Government apply legislation to CASX latter requirement might be met by issue of Regulation which would empower Political Agents Bahrain and Cuwait to take action within their limits against CASX employees leaving their employment against the terms of such legislation. It is unlikely that CASX employees leaving their employment against the ^American CASX employees should be treated same as Americans Bahrain under any enforced regulations otherwise dissension will result as exchange personnel certain categories now common practice and we dependent their crude supply.** Ends. / Management 1 s- 2 - llaria^ement wishes woiild be able t,o maice “their ge“t»&amp;w^,y except* through one of these places. 5. I presume that proposed Regulation covering foreigners will not be proceeded with unless it is decided that Regulation already under discussion covering British subjects will be applied to Canadians. 6 . I am assuming throughout that any legislation in U.S.A. Y/ould he subject to limitations described under (a) in paragraph 1 of your telegram. 7. Subject to the consideration in paragraph 5 I think all the Companies concerned v/ould welco ie the proposed Regula tion covering foreigners provided difficulty in reaoect of CASOC can he overcome. I should like however to discuss whole question with llanagers of BAPCo and CASOC and should be ^ glad to know whether I may do this. resideutThe Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Polltioal Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Polltioal Agent, Husoat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^. British Consulate-General, Dated... Gamp, Bahrain, Residenoy telegram No,T/224 dated 8th April, 1942 Essential undertakings.CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/. 8b of 194;;. The Hon’ble the Political Pvesident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent t Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain, v/ The Political /gent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). To Bahrain •only. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp, BAHfUlJ . Dated.. Wth ; jyrU, . CC4ff^v Reference to previous correspondence : Resiaeiicy printea Letter Ro.cA^-tl, ' ^ 1 $ uated the 8th April 194L. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Political Resiiient's telegram No.T/l 67, dated the iLth April 194^* Political Resident's Telegram No«T/£68, dated the lith April I94L. Conscription of labour.79/65. H -70; Telegram 3 , From To Hepeatod Copy to No.T/JsT. Dated the lith April 194^. Folitioal Desideatf at Bahrain. Government of India, New Delhi. India Office, London. Political Agent, Bahrain. Your telegram No.^336 April 10th. &lt;£• Bahrain Petroleum Company have sanctioned war allowance of Rs« 25 per menth for Indian clerical and technical staff and per month for artisans and per month for domestics. These allowances appear adequate. 3. Company have now received 14 resignations from Indian staff including 4 on April 11th. Dome of these resignations have heen acknowledged and the more recent ones have heen pigeon-holed for the time being. Under their contracts Indians are entitled to leave their employ ment at a aonth # s notice and unless Begulatlon is Issued within this month it does not appear possible legally to insist on their remaining in the Company*s service. Steps might be taken to prevent them leaving the Island but penalties ag last them under the Begulation could not be enforced and their presehce on the island might well prove an embarrassment. 4. It seems unlikely that arrangements can be made to cover Americans within one month and Company*s Lagement are anxious that proposed Regulation should oe issued at once. Bo far as British European subjects ©re concerned it is proposed to make it clear in the letter Issued under instructions contained in paragraph 5 of India Office telegram No.901 January 16th that a similar measure of conscription has been applied to the Anglo-Persian Oil / CompanyGoffiL&gt;aQy aud other ooaoeriiB and Ooiayany's Uanagemeat do not eryeot much trouble with their ej^yloyees of this class if this is done, 5 # They expect more trouble from their In iaa employees who they think may be adversely affected by the failure of the Oripps Mission, I doubt this but Indians of the non-martial class especially those coming from the east of India are no doubt anxious for the safety of their families and wish to return on this account, 6 . -difficulty with Indians must be faced and so far as they are concerned I do not think it will make any difference whether conscription is applied to Americans and Canadians or not, I should like to be in a position to inform them that similar measure of conscription has been applied to Indus tidal oonoema in India, I have received from the Government of India a copy of Ordinance XI of 1941 making provision for the maintenance of cert in essential services but have not been given details of any industrial concerns to which this Ordinance has been applied. Wjlxi tne Government of India kindly telegraph the names of a few of such concerns ? 7. In the light of the above remarks I recommend the immediate promulgation of the [Regulation and its applica tion to British Buropean and Indian subjects. 8 . Please see also my immediately succeeding telegram. - bssid:ht79/6l&gt; fc 86/14 7 l Telegram i'rom To Hepe&amp;ted Copy to S. Political Roeiuentt at Bahrain. Goverr.i.ifent of India t ^ew Pelhi Secretary of btate lor irdia, London, lolitioal ant, Bahrain Bo. T/268 Bated the 12th April 1942. By immediately preceding tele &amp; r*m. 2. Company are anxioue not only that conscription be applied to their existing employees but that measures enoulc be t»ken to enable them to make up their deficienc ies. They state that they h&amp;ve he arc that the Haifa re* finery is at present largely run by British mixitary personnel. They are at present short of 55 staff personnel and they fine it impossible to obtain recruits from Treat Britain anc aery difficult from America ana Canada. They eould much preier European British subjects to Americans and Canadians as their general policy is to employ as many British as possible anc ie»er practical ciiixculties arise over their terms of eiuployment. 3. There are precuimbly a cumber ot oil experts serving with the forces who could be required to enter the Con^any*s employment. it would however probably take a long time to obtain recruits from this source even if Leience authorities were willing to release them. events in Burma have pre sumably thrown a large numoer of employees of Burma Oil Company out of work. if they see no objection would the Government ot India ascertain whether it would be possible to make up the Bahrain Petroleum Cocipany’s deficiencies from this source ? if a favourable answer is received details of the ty e of expert required will be telegraphed. KJK. • ResidentC©/&gt; ^ 7 ive-t* h 7*-A. T^olAyo.^ 79/65. ')r /—&gt; T e l egraa ^'om To Bepeatod No. 6641 q. Secretary of State fbr India, London. ir olltloal Bealdeut, at Bahrain Govemmont of India, New Lellil. Dated and received the 14th April 194^. IMPORTANT Your telegram No. T/203 of April 2nd. »*! I am advised thfit It would he ultra vires tne Order in Oouncil fbr you to make Regulation elther prohibiting en^loyees whether British or foreign in oauni Arabia from leaving their employ- meat there, whether with British or foreign Company at providing for their punishment in Kuwait or Bah rain if they did so in contravention of a U.S.A. B.gulation applying to Saudi Arabia. U.S.A. em ployees In Saudi Arabia can be dealt witu oni, by O.S.A. legislation and in U.S.A. Courts, though a r egulation made by you oould cover any persons actually working in Gulf Shaikhdoms whether alloy ing Company is px'incipally operating in Saudi Arabia &gt;r not. Hence proposed regulation cannot apply to '.A.o.O.u, employees except those who may from time to time be working In Bahrain. I lease discuss matter with local Managers in light oi loregoiug. Subject to results of this discussion, U.8, Govex-nment might then be asked la; to legislate ior U.S. employees working in Saudi Arabia aixl (b) to raise no objection to you legislating by regulation for U.S. ejui^loyecs v. orbing Tor oil /Oil Oompany la Kuwait and Bahrain Petroleum Oompany.including 0.A.3.O.C. in so far as it operates in ? Bahrain . If T J.S. Government ished to cover by their 1 ' islation cases under '(b) as wefel there would appear to be no objection* Ag regards paragraph £ of Govern ment of India telegram ;* 0 , 3835 we feel it would be more appropriate for formal approach to U.3. Govern ment to be made through ills Majesty’s Kabas y at Wash ington though there would of course oe no objection to Government of India discussing matter with Solonel J ohnson. 3. A s regards regulation for British subjects Canadian Government h've no objection to its animation to Canadians on understanding (a) that United Kingdom a uthor it ies consider continued employment of triose Canadians in present jobs is important to war effort and that they cannot reason ably be replaced ; (b) that if for special reasons f^nadian. Govern- ir at asks that a Oanadi an employee be allowed to leave permission will be granted. You will presumably satisfy yourself as to (a) in each case. 4, Your telegram d 0 . T/344 of April 8tn and Govern ment of India telegram fl 0 . 3836 of April 10th. In view Q- satisfactory reply from Canadian Government I feel that to avoid f urther delay Begulation should be made and notices served on all British sub ,6 0 .8 including Canadians and Indians as soon as possible unless you feel exclusion for present of .Americans will cause serious iL^missipa /i . If you agree please telegraph Then /-3^. CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/421 of 1942. y*' $«». y &lt; &lt; v 18 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. 5. The Political Agent, Muecat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. L.T .ifearchus, At Sea. Dated. loth April 1942* * Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed Better Io*0/53t&gt; of 12th April 1942* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Gorernnient of India telegram No.2835 of 10th April 1942. • India Office telegram No.6641 'p of 14th April 1942. 3. India Office telegram ho.6716 of 14th April 1942. 4. Political Resident’s telegram No.T/306 of 16th April 1942. 5. Draft letter to Oil Companies• v Essential Undertakings - 7 &lt;r&gt; { f 7vI I I r * rTelegram s. From Government of India, New Delhi. To Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Political Resident, at Bahrain. No. 2835. Dated 10th, received 11th April 1942. Your telegram No. 5260 dated March 22nd and 1olitical Besldent’s telegrams No. T/203 amf T/224. ^ 2. We agree in general with suggestion in 'fv r v paragraph 2 of your telegram No. 5260. on the other hand we apprehend that it moght he grave error to promulgate regulation applying to British and British Indian subjects only before arrangements are made to cover Canadians and Americans. So far as latter are concerned we propose to take up question with Presidents personal represent tative in India in e xpectation of accelerating decision. Meanwhile Political Resident ean no doubt ensure that Indian employees mentioned in his telegram T/224 do not leave Bahrain. - Foreign.Telegram From To Repeated No, 671*5, 3. Secretary of State for India, London Political Resident, at Bahrain. Oovernment of India. Dated 14th ; received 15th April 194J. IJk.OHTA; t . Paragraph 4. argent. Peel to Hay repeated Caroe. Our t lei-ram No. 6641 of April 14th. You Hu.il no doubt maice regulation as veteran aum.5.. Political Resident, in nearchuB. Secretary of ‘-tate for India, London. Government of incia. Sew lelhi. £&gt;0 • T/506» tated trie 16th April * 1942. lour telefcr&amp;in 6641 April 141: • 2 . Both Bahrain Petroleum Company and California Arabian Standard Oil Company oppoa. inscription at present Bta fc e of their American ec^loyeeo on fcrour,is that ia) Americane already earring Company in foreign land anc unhealthy climate would intensely resent legislation less favourable than that existing in home country and (h) further recruitmert from America * 0 ttM tocome imposs- Telegram From To Reptsateh *) ible is a serious consideration *itn Bahrain Petroleum Coaaany who are short cf staff cf .rtf telegram ho. /A-7^ ■ T/i:68 April liith. 3 . Bahrain Petroleum Company would only welcome conscription of 'merioun employees ii la ) similar measure were applied by Act of Congress IZ other American industrial concern^t hone and - -roa4*nd lb) provision were made for conscription in C.3.A. of ^ ^ recruits for service %ith Comp&amp;riy in Bfehrai^. 4. Califcrnis Arabian Standard Oil Company * l P^^ at are not in favour of neasurt in ory oircumstai.ces »* ' lr ' ey ar8 able to obtain i-eplacementE they require tloggli » i tL difficulty and they doubt deterrent affect of jenaltlaa h coulu only be onf ore td in U .S % A» b. Brirair. Petroleum company oppo* 6 conscription oi Canadian, on same grounds as stated in paragraph *• At * ,r * ,#nt- 2 - *} ^ they have to rely on Canada for replacemente to a considerable extent and three Canadian recruits axe awaiting transport in New York. They would prefer to xkksl± recruit from elsewhere cf* paragraph *i of niy telegram fio»T/ / 268 April ILth and would gladly see all their Canadians replaced except for about six persons who will stay on whether conscripted or not# 6. Canadian Government have in any case limited tie efficacy of Regulation in respect of Canedians by stipulations mentioned in paragraph 3 of your telegram and on the whole i am inclined to recommend that idea oi applying it to them should be dropped at any rate until a similar measure cm be applied to ioaerican subjects. Situation is further complicat ed, by fact that Company are now recruiting from £outh Africe and six South Air leans are already on their way to Bahrain. 7. Bahrain Petroleum Company aleo fear tiat applica tion of Regulation to Indians may affect recruiting in India# hven so 1 consicer Regulation should be applied to Indians to prevent wholesale resignations due to panic e^c* 8# 1 am not issuing Regulation/until 1 receive final instructions whether Canadians should be ak included or not# if they are to be included please state whether injlettsr to Manager of Bahrain Petroleum oo/ipany i may say that Regulation has been made witn approval oi Government of Canada# 9. 1 presume tt^t I may in any case state t .at Regulation has been made with approval of Government of India (as well as of his liaje&amp;ty's Government). Please confirm. -RESir&amp;NT. W.L.DEPARTMENT. BRANCH. Bile No. INLAND: Immediate Class for telegrams imporunt Express Kxp ~&lt;5rdfc nary To be is-oued on 1st Reminder 2nd Reminder 3rd Reminder Heading : Case or Diary No. i If post copy of telegram required Date of despatch of above List of enclosures Serial Xa \ Letter Draft ^ssuBagmBx FOREIGN: j Ko Dated Id . I mportan t HOIl’ble the POlltiC&amp;l ^Ordinary _ | Rceidwit in Uxe IcrBien U ulf Without priority ! Issued on To - The Chief hoc&amp;l RepreBentatiT« # The hahrs-in Petrolown Co.Ltd., Bah re in# The Man ager 9 Tetr^ leum ConcesBions Ltd. # Bahrain# The Manager* Petrolejun j. eTelopment C^&amp;tar) limited#* Bahrain# The Ueiieral Kariager* The Kuaait cil Co#htd# 9 iUroait# (Code word for telegrams.) 7C S. 5. L. 0. k Son#, CaL—No. 723R iG-fci9j-n-7-4U -60,09» Fads. Dear Sir* ^ou will appreciate that His Majesty’s aovernment regard the operations of the Company in ...•..#••••• •e-* vital importance to the National interest and that the employees of the Company in can best serve the National interest by remaining at their poets# 2 # i am now to inform you that with the approval of His ajest *8 Govern me r t, 'X ,trT covernn ent of India 1 have mad e a Defence Regulation* No of 194i* regarding essential undertakings in •#••••* which i eridose a co y# -43 lou will observe that under this Regulation no British subject or British Protected person may leave the Company^ employment either during or on completion of an Agreement without say prior consent, or that of the Political Agent, •••••••• Any employee so detainee by my order or tu&amp;t of the Political Agenti has however the right of appeal to me or the Political Agent regarding his conditions of service. 4. Any employee who contrwenea the provisions of this Regulation shall be liable on convic tion to a penalty of imprieonmunt not exceeding two years or tc a fine not exceeding Ks.6,fc00 or to both such imprisonment and fine. JL«egal provision exists for the arrest and trial in India of offenders against this Regulation, and any person who or. returning to the united Jtingoom is convictea of having left his euploy- V ment in contravention of this Kegaiationwiil . i under Regulation 92 [ i; ea the Pefenoe ^General) Regulations, 1939, be liable, on suamiury convic tion to imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months or to a fine not exceeui&amp;g one hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and such fine, or, on conviction on ino ictment, to impr leonmemt for a teim not exceeoing two years i or to a fine not exceeding five hundraa pounce to bq a u ch izrrprisonmen t and such fine# &amp;• You are requested to bring this Regulation and this letter to the attentioroi all your British employees and also of all your Indian eu-ployees who are British subjects or British Protected per&amp;ona, and to obtain from ^acho r o v DEPARTMENT. BRANCH. Draft Letter M emorandum INLAND: Immediate Class for telegrams important' Ex pr ess Ordinary To be issued on | 1st Reminder ‘2nd Reminder 3rd Reminder Heading : Case or Diary No- If post copy of telegram required Date of despatch of above List of enclosures Telegram FOREIGN: j N 0 Immediate Important Ordi nary Without priority | Dated Vila No Serial No. 10 Issued on To (Code word for telegrams.) S. 5, L. 0. 4 Son*, CaL -Mo. v&amp;R (G-(i9i-11.7r40—60,069 Pads. each inciyiou&amp;i. coiicerned a written acknowicdgmer,t that thifc ha* been done* These aoknowlecemente should be forwiirded to tr,e Lciitical A^ent t C. The position of your employees to whom the Regulation applies will now be the same as that of British subjects and protected persons e ploy ed by the Aa^lQ-lrari&amp;n Oil Company* ae ti.et of incus trial workers in Great Britain whose export knowledge or wuose technical skill has been requisiticueu by the Government for use in the procaction of armaments or for other purposes connected with the far and as thet of the (urployete of certain important incuntrial concerns in india* such as .. * • * ••«•••••••••••• to which the B-seent Lai Services — t , Urn t- (Ixaintenance) Orciirance 1941 has been applied, luperisl interests render it vital that the activities of Cii Companies shculd be maintained and ail vuo contribute to this end are playia^ theii part in ti^e present iNar •CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/427 of 1942. &lt;?tp I he Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agunt, The Political Agent, The Political Agent, Kuwait, Bahrain Muscat* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docement British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated...^^..^.?.^?:. 4t_ Sea. L.T. Nearchus, Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed Letter No.C/421, dated the 16th April 1942. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Political Resident*s telegram No.T/316, dated the 17th April 1942* Essential undertakingsONFIDENTIAL. No. C/435 of,1942. v*' The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to % 1. Political Agent, Kuwait. 2m The Political Agent, Bahrain.r 3. The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (^). British Consulate-General, BUSH IRE. Dated... .April r l$42.&lt; fcearchus, at, Tamh, s M X?' ttUir .-S'’ - Reference to previous correspondence: ResidenyyPrinted letter No.C/421 of 16th April 1942. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Government of India, t.legrei No.3043 of 17th April 1942. i Es 5 ent ial Undents ki ngs.1 79/65. From GoTernflient of Xndia # Mew Delhi* Inciia Office, London. Political Resident, on Hearchus* To Repo&amp;tod Ho.£04a. Dated 17th received 16th April 1941. Up telegram No.16.55 April 10th. £« Hatter has been discussed with Presidentta personal representative who advises tlu t there is little inoiedlate prospect of U.S.A* legislation likely to assist in solution of difficulty at Bahrein. He has however definite authority in natters affecting American personnel of both ! I B.A.PtC*0. and C«A«6.0.C. which should serve the purpose and has asked for our co-operation to auJte this effective. objection to issaediate promulgation of new regulation aa affecting British and British Indian subjects. Possibility of obtaining unemployed men of B.O.C. is being investigated. Will Resident please telegraph types of experts required ? In view of the above we withdraw our 4 . Reference paragraph 6 of Residentts telegram Mo.7/167. Following ere some of 16 concerns to which industrial conscription has been applied In India s Company, Calcutta. 5. Paragraph 5 of Resident's telegram Mo.T/i66. 6. Above was drtftea before receipt of your telegr&amp;m No.6&amp;65 and 6671.py. A\ l^jo y 1 '^' ImV Telegram Q. From Political Resident, on Nearchus. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No.T/323. z' 0 kM Dated and received 21st April 1942. A M3 / Last sentence of paragraph 3 of my telegram No.268/T April 12th. Please telegraph types of ?experts required by Bahrain Petroleum Company. Resident.Conf Idffltial No. C/507 . Political Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd April 1942 To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited Awali. Dear Sir At a discussion with the Political Resident on the 12th April 1942 you mentioned that the Bahrain Petroleum Company were at present short of 33 staff personnel and you asked whether it would be possible to obtain recruits from among the employees of the Burma Oil Company whom recent events have presumably thrown out of work. You further stated that, if necessary, you could specify the type of expert you require. 2 . The Government of India are taking up the matter, and have inquired what types of experts are required by your Company. Will you please let me have this information as soon as possible. Yours truly, \iilr ^ ToG° 9^ 00N-14. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. 25th April, 1942. / s His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Reference your letter No. C/507 dated 1942. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited require as soon as possible the following staff employees, who should he suitable as citizens in the British-American community here (Awali):- 6 - Apprentice Refinery Operators. / S / S' s 3 - Experienced Power Plant Operators. s 3 - Chemists for Oil Refinery r work^ 2 - Combination Welders, one^vh.th^tinsmith / experience1 1 - Boilermaker'for Oil^Refinery work/ 1' - Garage mechanic 'with good experience r 3 - Machinist/mechanics for'Oil^Refinery work.' 1 - Electrician with good general experience. V- Petroleum Engineer. / x 1 - Metallurgist for Oil Refinery inspection work/ / x / 3 - Accountants with good general office experience. / x / 2 - Good'male'Stenographers suitable / for handling confidential correspondence and files. 1 - Experienced Storeman. Prospective employees located in India should contact our Recruiting Agent, Mr. C. I. Graham, 'Caltex House', Ballard Road, Ballard Estate, Bombay who will review the qualifications, arrange for physical examinations, advise men of wages they willCON-14. 2 25th April, 1942. receive and subsequently arrange transportation to Bahrein. Prospective employees other than those located in India should contact the Company at Bahrein, who will make the necessary art angements. This procedure is necessary in order to avoid duplication of requisitions we have already placed in India, South Africa, England the United States and Canada.' good prospects of obtaining approximately six men within the next month or two from South Africa, which accounts for the above not totalling 33 as mentioned in our discussion with the Political Resident on the 12th April, 1942 _ , your information I should advise that during February the Bahrein Petroleum Company contacted, through their representatives in London, the Petroleum Board for assistance in securing the services of surplus technical men made available by events in the East. ' These efforts avail any men out of a total of 27 requested with qualuicaoions of those indicated above. We are continually interested in men of similar qualifications, and will welcome applications from such men at any time. ,, , The Company will be very grateful for any assistance uhat you or uhe Honourable Political Resident are able to render in this connection. W. P. Anderson. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. f JL- C/W c(.Telegram From To Repeated No.254. Q. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, on Nearchus. Government of India, New Delhi. Dated 26th April 1942. Reference your telegram No.T/323 dated 21st A^ril and para 5 Foreign telegram No.3048'dated 18th April. 28 experts now required as follows. 6 Apprentice Refinery Operators. 3 Experienced Power Plant Operators. 3 Chemists for Oil Refinery ' u ork. 2 Combination elders, one with tinsmith experience. 1 Boilermaker for Oil Refinery work. 1 Garage Mechanic with good experience. 3 Machinist/mechanics for Oil Refinery work. 1 electrician with good general exoerience. 1 Petroleum Engineer. 1 Metallurgist for Oil Refinery inspection work. 3 Accountants with good general office experience. 2 Good male .Stenographers suitable for handling confidential correspondence and files. 1 Experienced Storeman. Other experts making total of 33 previously mentioned are being recruited .from South Africa. 2. Prospective employees located in India should con tact Bahrain Petroleum ComDany*s Recruiting Agent Mr.Graham Caltex House Bombay. Prospective employees located outside India should contact Company at Bahrain. 3. Bahrain Petroleum Company add that Petroleum Board London were asked for similar assistance in February without result. Political.V Telegram 3 From Political Resident, on Nearchus. Political Agent, Bahrain. No.T/360. Dated 25th received 26th April 1942. Following is repetition of Government of India External Affairs Department telegram No.3183 April 22nd begins. Resident's telegram No.f/306 dated Rpril 16th. 2. Government of India strongly recommend that Canadians be included in Regulation. Otherwise Canadians will enjoy privileged position as against other employees since British and British Indian subjects will be covered by legislation and Americans to certain extent by arrange ments adumbrated in para 2 of Government of India telegram No.3048 dated Rpril 17th. Individual Canadians can then be dealt under para 3(b) of India Office telegram 6641^ ??S 3. They think it would be unwise to assume Bahrain Petroleum Company will be able to obtain any replacements from Burma since employees of Burma Oil Company rendered surplus by developments there will almost certainly be required at Abadan. 4. Gubject to above Resident may say that Regulation has been made with aporoval of Government of India. Addressed Political Resident repeated Gecretary of dtate for India. Resident.7 V&gt;\* c^*‘ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. CON-17 April 29, 1942 4«i~ His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: In connection with conversation exchanged, please find hereunder a list of enqployees who have resigned from the Company's service together with the expiration dates of their notice periods* NAME OCCUPATION NOTICE EXPIRES HOME DISTRICT Megh Nath Clerk May 4, 1942 Nawashaher M. Paul Chemist May 6, 1942 Boakhali T.K. Dass Stores-Clerk May 7, 1942 Jullundur J• Menezes Compounder May 9, 1942 Goa C* D* Souza Fitter May 11, 1942 Goa Jaswant Singh Turner May 11, 1942 Sri Ganga Nagar Nasrullah Khan Mechanic May 15, 1942 Jullundur K« S. Ismail Khan Special Foreman May 21, 1942 Karachi Abdul Hamid Fitter May 26, 1942 Gujrat Eazal Karim Waiter May 27, 1942 Jammu State In connection with K. S. Ismail Khan's resignation adequate internal re-arrangement has already been made to cover his duties* Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. fyrW k t' ■ *Telegram From Q. Government of India, New Delhi* To Political Resident. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. No.3430. Dated 30th April received 1st May 1942. Political Agent Bahrain’s telegram No.254 April 26th. 2. All technical personnel from Burma already absorbed. Company's recruiting agent will presumably advertise for non technical personnel required. Foreign.Confidential &lt;TS I No^C/STZ. To Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd May 1942. The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Awali. Dear Sir, &gt;&lt;t v Reference your letter No.CON-14 dated 25th April 1942. 2 . I have received information from the Government of India that all technical personnel from Burma have already been absorbed. In regard to non-technical per sonnel your recruiting agent in India will presumably advertise in order to secure your requirements. Yours truly, el Ct Political Agent, Bahrain.^ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Coiifi den al. Dbpabti! EXPRESS LETTER B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the mres, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as {f it had been telegraphed. To save ± time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Carap,Mu&amp;cat.. (To Kuwait &amp; Muscat)• From To Political Resident, Bushire, at Muscat. The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Political Agent, Muscat. Subjects Industrial Conscription. C/484 of 1942. Dated 29th April, 193 42• ^ * • ,j ' Reference correspondence ending with my telegram ITo.T/360 dated the 25th April 1942 (Residency Printed Letter Ko.C/474 dated the 25th April,1942). /p* 2. A copy of India Office telegram No.7425 dated the 25th April 1942 is enclosed. &gt; ^ 3. The following addition should be made in the draft Regula tion forwarded under Residency Printed Letter No.C/183 dated the 19th March 1942. In Article 1, after 'Bahrain Petroleum Company' insert^ 'Petroleum Concessions, Limited'. ^ ^3. 4. The following changes should be ms^de in the draft lett^^ * to Companies forwarded under Residency Printed Letter No.C/421 dated the 16th April,1942, which will now be issued by you instead of by me. (a) Paragraph 2. ' (i) For 'I have' substitute 'the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has' S. 6. MFP—1407 S&amp;P-(M-2339)—25-5-37—300,000.- 2 - /tro (ii) At fcta end of existing paragraph add 'At the request of the Canadian Government, who were informed that it was proposed to enact this Regulation, the Political Resident has undertaken that ix for special reasons the Canadian Government asks that a Canadian employee be allowed to leave, permission will be granted'• (b) Paragraph 3. (i) For 'without my prior consent, or that of the Politi cal Agent •.«' substitute 'without the prior consent of the Political Resident or the Political Agent'. (ii) For 'by my order or that of the Politicetl Agent' substitute 'by order of the Political Resident or the Political Agent'. (iii) For 'appeal to me or the Political Agent' substitute ' appeal to the Political Resident or to the Political Agent'. (c) Paragraph 5# 5. (i) For 'all your British employees and also of all your Indian employees who are British subjects or British protected persons' substitute 'all your employees who are British subjects or British protected persons,' (ii) For 'forwarded to the Political Agent, ...' substitute 'forwarded to me'. (d) Paragraph 6. . After l*such as' insert 'Caltex India!s installations at Bombay, the Calcutta Tram/ways and the Burmah-Shell Oil Storage and Distributing Company,Calcutta,' I shall issue the Regulation very shortly and shall notify Attested. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* sd. Y&lt;. R • Hay. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* you by telegram of its issue* On receipt of such notification you should exhibit a copy of the Regulation (and issue the draft lettefr (To , - , , Bahrain to the Comoanies, ensuring that all Canadians are included among &amp; Kuv/ait . ' only). those on whom notices are served) 6. To Bahrain only . Reference paragraph 2 of India Office tele- gram No.7425 'dated 25th April 1942. Please report in due course tne arrival of the employees from South Africa. 7. To Bahrain and Kuwait only . Please acknowledge by telegram receipt of this Express Letter* Vi/d)l 79/65. Telegram 6 « Inula Of!Ice, London. Political Resident, on Nearchus. Govt mm nt oi India, New Delhi. From Tp Repeated No.74&amp;5. Dated fe6th received i;7th April l94fc. Your telegrams T/S06 of April 16th and X/516 of April 18th and Gov rment of India telegrams Nos* ZO-8 and 2183 of April 17th and April Ifcnd. Paragraph 8 of T/306. scope of regulation will automatically include Canadians along with all other British subjects, end I agree with Gov* rnment of India that ? in. order to avoid discrimination as far as possible it will be best to include them among those on whom notices are served. If in any case Bahrain Petroleum Company do not wish to retain a Canadian employee, they have onxy to ask you to let him go. Effect of Canadian Government t s second stipulation is that if neither you nor Company agree to his departure he e;n ? appeal to Canadian Government. Your letter to Managers should ? contain following passages were informed that it was proposed to enact this regulation the Political Resident has undertaken tint if for special reasons Canadian Gove rnment asks th ! t a Canadian employee be allowed to leave, permission will be granted'. gV fc. Paragraph 6 of T/306. As regulation wi apply automatically to South Africans it will probably be thought desirable that position should be explained to Union Government. You should therefore ? not serve notices 'at request of Canadian Government, who on South African employees until you receive instructions to do so. Please inform me of their arrival.0 )o*v - Z - 3. /.a regards Americana, if in the light of p&amp;r&amp;gr.-pha k to 4 of your telegram T/tSO€ ? A^rll 16th. Government of India still consider it desirable that any fora of conscription should be applied to them or any other step taken in their regard, I assume I shall be kept X'ully informed •4 79/63 Telegram From To Repeated Mo.T/332. Dated the 3 . Political Resident, at Huscat• Secretary of State for India, London. Government of India, New Delhi. 29th April, 194'. Your telegram ^o.7425 April 25th. 2 . Should notices be served on all Canadians or only on those to whom stipulation (a) in paragraph 3 of your tele-Tam No 41 applies 7 Discrimination in the serving of notices is un desirable and it is preferable that stipulation (a) should only be observed in the enforcement of the Regulation. -Resident. Office of the Political Resident ! T o.C/485. in the Persian Gulf, Camp,Museat. Dated the 29th April,194^“ Copy forwarded to: The Political Agent, Bahrain./ The Political Agent, Kuv/ait. The Political Agent, Muscat, reference Hesidency x.L.No.C/484 of 29th April 1942. v —* c 0Telegram Q. From Political Resident, on Nearchus. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. Political Agent, Kuwait. No.f/455. Dated 7th received Sth May 1742. Essential undertakings. I have made today May 7th urgent Regulation No.2 of 1942 with following addition in Article 4 viz. insertion after '1939, of ’’and the Muscat Order in Council, 1939,'. 2. Please take action indicated in paragraph 5 of my Express Letter No.0/484 April 29th. Resident./or DSPENCB RBGfULATION NO, 2 OF 1942. X* This Regulation shall apply in the territories of the Shaikh of Kuwait, the Shaikh of Bahrain, the Shaikh of Qatar and the Sultan of Muscat and Oman (hereinafter referred to as the territories) and shall be applicable therein to all British subjects and British protected persons employed in the territories by the Kuwait Oil Company, the Bahrain Petroleum Company, Petroleum Concessions, Limited, Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, and in any other undertaking in the said territories which may be specified in any order of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf as an undertaking essential for the prosecution of the war, 2, (1) Any person to whom this Regulation applies who is in the employment of persons carrying on the undertakings mentioned in Article 1 of this Regulation or any other under taking specified by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf as an undertaking essential for the prosecution of the war shall, whether or not he is bound by contract to do so, continue in the employment of those persona in such capacity as they may from time to time specify, unless the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf consents to his leaving that employment, provided that consent under this Article shall not be refused unless the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is satisfied that the employers are willing to continue employment on reasonable terms. (2) The powers conferred on the Political Resident by paragraph (1) of this Article may be exercised within their respective spheres of jurisdiction by the Political Agents at Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat subject to such instructions as the Political Resident may from time to time issue to them, 3, Any person to whom this Regulation applies found on board any vessel leaving territory where he is employed shall v be presumed to be contravening the Regulation, and the onus of rebutting such presumption shall be on him. / 4.- 2 - 4. The provisions of Part 112 of the Kuwait Order In Councll f 1935, the Bahrain Order In Council, 1913, the Qatar Order in Council, 1939, and the Muscat Order In Council, 1939, relating to criminal matters shall apply, In so far as they may be applicable, to the trial of offences against this Regulation* 5* Any person contravening the provisions of Article 2 of this Regulation shall be liable on con viction to a penalty of imprisonment not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding % 6500 or to both such Imprisonment and fine* 6* This Regulation shall take effect immediately on publication* t (.♦ i^Tuid) «v*R*Hay Lt*—Col«, C*2*l£* » • Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* 7th May 1942*No +C/625 • Political Agency, Bahrain, the 8th May 1942* AO The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain* Dear Sir, You will appreciate that His Majesty’s Government regard the operations of the Bahrain Petroleum Company in Bahrain as of vital Laportance to the Rational interest and that the employees of the Company in Bahrain can best serve the National interest by remaining at their posts* 2* I am now to inform you that with the approval of His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has made a Defence Regulation, No* 2 0 f 1942, regarding essential undertakings in Bahrain, of which I enclose a copy* At the request of the Canadian Government, who were informed that it was proposed to enact this Regulation, the Political Resident has undertaken that if for special reasons the Canadian Government asks that a Canadian employee be allowed to leave, permission will be granted* 3 # You will observe that under this Regulation no British subject or British Protected person may leave the Company’s employment either during or on completion of an Agreement without the prior consent of the Political Resident or the Political Agent, Bahrain. Any employee so detained by order of the Political Resident or the Political Agent has however the right of appeal to the Political Resident or to the Political Agent regarding his conditions of service. 4 # Any employee who contravenes the provisions of / this- 2 - this Regulation shall be liable on conviction to a penalty of imprisonment not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding Rs 6 f 500 or to both such imprisonment and fine. Legal provision exists for the arrest and trial in India of offenders against this Regulation, and any person who on returning to the United Kingdom is convicted of having left his employment in contravention of this Regulation will under Regulation 92 (1) of the Defence (General) Regulations, 1939, be liable, on summary conviction to imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months or to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and such fine, or, on conviction on indictment, to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding five hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and such fine. 5. You are requested to bring this Regulation and this letter to the attention of all your employees who are British subjects or British protected persons, and to obtain from each individual concerned a written acknowledgment that this has been done. These acknowledgments should be forwarded to me. 6 . The position of your employees to whom the Regula tion applies will now be the same as that of British sub jects and protected persons employed by the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, as that of industrial workers in Great Britain whose expert knowledge or whose technical skill has been requisitioned by the Government for use in the production of armaments or for other purposes connected with the War, and as that of the employees of certain important industrial concerns in India, such as Caltex Indian installations / at 1 : V\ \at Bombay, the Calcutta Tramways and the Burmah-Shell Oil Storage and Distributing Company, Calcutta, to which the Sssential Services (Maintenance) Ordinance 1941 has been applied. Imperial interests render it vital that the activities of Oil Companies should be maintained and all who contribute to this end are playing their part in the present War* Yours truly, &amp; Political Agent, Bahrain.• , © I/O Political Agency, No •C/626* Bahrain, the 8th Uay 1942* The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, You will appreciate that His Majesty's Government regard the operations of Petroleum Concessions, Limited, in Bahrain as of vital importance to the National interest and that the employees of the Company in Bahrain can best serve the National interest lay remaining at their posts* 2 . I am now to inform you that with the approval of His Majesty's Government and the Government of India the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has made a Defence Regulation, No* 2' of 1942, regarding essential undertakings in Bahrain, of which I enclose a copy. At the request of the Canadian Government, who were informed that it was proposed to enact this Regulation, the Political Resident has undertaken that if for special reasons the Canadian Government asks that a Canadian employee be allowed to leave, permission will be granted. 3. You will observe that under this Regulation no British subject or British Protected person may leave the Company's employment either during or on completion of an Agreement without the prior consent of the Political Resident or the Political Agent, Bahrain. Any employee so detained by order of the Political Resident or the Political Agent has however the right of appeal to the Political Resident or to the Political Agent regarding his conditions of service. 4 . Any employee who contravenes the provisions of / this- 2 - this Regulation shall be liable on conviction to a penalty of imprisonment not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding Rs 6,500 or to both such imprisonment and fine* Legal provision exists for the arrest and trial in India of offenders against this Regulation, and any person who on returning to the United Kingdom is convicted of having left his employment in contravention of this Regulation will under Regulation 92(1) of the Defence (General) Regulations, 1939, be liable, on summary conviction to imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months or to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and such fine, or, on conviction on indictment, to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding five hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and such fine* 5* You are requested to bring this Regulation and this letter to the attention of all your employees who are British subjects or British protected persons, and to obtain from each individual concerned a written acknowledgment that this has been done* These acknowledgments should be forwarded to me* 6* The position of your employees to whom the Regu lation applies will now be the same as that of British sub jects and protected persons employed by the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, as that of industrial workers in Great Britain whose expert knowledge or whose technical skill has been requisitioned by the Government for use in the production of armaments or for other purposes connected with the War, and as that of the employees of certain important industrial concerns in India, such as Caltex India 1 s installations 7 at • 7at Bombay| the Calcutta Tramways and the Burmah-Shell Oil Storage and Distributing Company, Calcutta, to which the Sssential Services (Maintenance) Ordinance 1941 has been applied. Imperial interests render it vital that the activities of Oil Companies should be maintained and all who contribute to this end are playing their part in the present war. Yours truly, Bahrain.Ho.C/627. O'® * ^ n Political Agency, Bahrain, the 8th May 1942. To The Manager, Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, You will appreciate that His Majesty’s Government regard the operations of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited in Qatar as of vital importance to the National interest and that the employees of the Company in Qatar can best serve the national interest by remaining at their posts. I am now to inform you that with the approval of His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has made a Defence Regulation, No. 2 of 1942, regarding essential undertakings in Qatar,, of which I enclose a copy. At the request of the Canadian Government, who were informed that it was proposed to enact this Regulation, the Political Resident has undertaken that if for special reasons the Canadian Government asks that a Canadian employee be allowed to leave, permission will be granted. 3. You will observe that under this Regulation no British subject or British Protected person may leave the Company’s employment either during or on completion of an Agreement without the prior consent of the Political Resident or the Political Agent, Bahrain. Any employee so detained by order of the Political Resident or the Political Agent has however the right of appeal to the Political Resident or to the Political Agent regarding his conditions of service. 4. Any employee who contravenes the provisions of / this/Mf - 2 - this Regulation shall be liable on conviction to a penalty of impriaonment not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding Rs 6,500 or to both such imprisonment and fine* Legal provision exists for the arrest and trial in India of offenders against this Regulation, and any person who on returning to the United Kingdom is convicted of having left his employment in contravention of this Regulation will under Regulation 92 (l) of the Defence (General) Regulations, 1939, be liable, on summary conviction to imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months or to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and such fine, or, on conviction on indictment, to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding five hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and such fine. 5. You are requested to bring this Regulation and this letter to the attention of all your employees who are British subjects or British protected persons, and to obtain from each individual concerned a written acknowledgment that this has been done. These acknowledgments should be forwarded to me. 6 . The position of your employees to whom the Regula tion applies will now be the same as that of British sub jects and protected persons employed by the Anglo-Iranian Gil Company, as that of Industrial workers in Great Britain whose expert knowledge or whose technical skill has been requisitioned by the Government for use in the production of armaments or for other purposes connected with the War ? and as that of the employees of certain important industrial concerns in India, such as Caltex India's installations / at— 3 — © nr at Bombay, the Calcutta Tramways and the Burmah-Shell Oil Storage end Distributing Company, Calcutta, to which the Essential Services (Maintenance) Ordinance 1941 has been applied. Imperial interests render it vital that the activities of Oil Companies should be maintained and all who contribute to this end are playing their part in the present War. Yours truly,Confidential&gt; No, C/601 , Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th May 1942. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain, Dear Sir, !&gt; In your letter No.CON-14 dated 25th April 1942 you mentioned that you expected some employees recruited in South Africa to arrive within the next month or two. Will you please inform me as soon as any of them arrive, intimating at the same time which of them are South African British subjects. Yours truly, Political Agent, Bahrain.PA-155 May 5th, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, The Agency, BAHREIN. PHEINMaY STAFF Bear Sir, During the last few months this Company has 'been endeavouring to obtain from South Africa men who would be suitable to work as Operators in our Be finery. Messrs. Caltex (Africa) Limited of Cape Town have lined up six men who are willing to come to Bahrein, but a notification has just been received from them indicating that they are unable as yet to obtain Nxit Permits to enable the men to leave South Africa. As you are already aware, our Befinery Operating Staff is nearly down to a bare minimum and if there is any thing you could do to assist in our endeavours to obtain the necessary Exit Permits from the South African Military Authorities at Pretoria, it would be greatly appreciated. Yours very truly, AA:B ¥. P. AHDSBSON, Chief Local Bepresentative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD.V GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER ns [N* Z&gt;,— This is an ORIGINAL MTiSSAGTZ, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Confidential. FfiOM To Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. C/620. Dated 7 th May 1942. ii!t • X enclose a copy of a letter No.PA-153 dated 5th May 1942 from the Chief Local Representative, the Bahrain Petroleum Company with the request that such action as is possible may be taken to obtain clearance for these men from South Africa. Political Agent, Bahrain. s. 6. MFP—1206 8&amp;P—(M-l 723)—4-2-36—200,000.5 / 2 -&gt;1 CONFIDENTIAL . No. c/543 , fa t fa ^ % X r H ^ #J. .4 % ^ ' The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to com- X* His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India f India Office f London* 2* The Secretary to the Government of India in the Rrternal Affairs Department. Hew Delhi* 3. The Political Agent, Bahrain. 4* The Political Agent, ifuscat* 5* The Political Agent, Kuwait* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Consulate-General, BIT SHIRE.VjjMlM SUM. STAkk IfiUSi following aogulation, »ado by tho lolitioal Rob id ent in tho f oroian Uulf and Uoroby doolarod to bo urgent p is publiohod for general inforaation. Sd. W.R. Hay. JUT. nroarcliuo*, 7th hay, 1942. lolitioal Resident in tho Persian Gulf. Regulation made under the Persian Gulf States IJtosrgenoy) Order in Oounoilp 1939. ■ i ' ■ 111 Ho. 2 of 1942. 1 # This Regulation shall apply in the territories 0 of tbo Uhulkh of Kuwait, tho Shaikh of Bahrain, tho Shaikh of ^atar ash tho Sultui of Muscat and Oman (hors Inaf tor referred to as the territories) and shall be appllo&amp;ble therein to all British subjects and British protected persons employed in the territories by the Kuwait Cil Comp an the Bahrain Petroleum Company, ietroleum Concessions, Limit petroleum Development Katar) Limited, and in any other undertaking in the said territories which may be specified in any order of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf as an undsrtaking essential for the prosecution of ths war. 8. (1) Any person to whom this Regulation applies who is in ths employment of persons carrying on ths undertakings . mentioned in Article 1 of this Regulation or any other undertaking specified by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf as an undertaking essential for the prosecution of the war shall, whether or not he is bound by contract to do so, continue in the employment of those persons In such capacity as they may from time to time specify, unless ths / Political/Jj . 8 . Folitiotil R**LC ent In I eroian Gulf consents to his IseTing that employment, provided that consent under this Article shall not be refused unless the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is satisfied that the employers are willing to continue employment on reasonable terms* (2) The powers conferred on the Political Resident by paragraph 11) of this Article may be exerolsed within their respective spheres of jurisdiction by the Political Agents at Kuwait, Bahrain and muscat subject to such instructions as the political Resident may from time to time issue to them* * 3* Any pereon to idiom thie Regulation applies found on board any veeeel leaving territory where he ie employed shall be presumed to be oontravenlng the Regulation, and the onus of rebutting sueh presumption shall be on him* 4* The provisions of Part 111 of the Kuwait Order in Oounoll, 1936, the Jtahr&amp;in uroer in Counoil, 1913, the &lt;«atar Order in Council, 1939, and the muscat Order in Counoil, 1939, relating to criminal matters shall apply, in so far as they may be applicable, to the trial of offences against thie Regulation* &amp;• Any pereon contravening the provisions of Article 2 of this Regulation shall be liable on conviction to a penalty of imprisonment not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding Rt*6,600/» or to both such imprisonment and fine* 6. This Regulation shall take effect isuaediately on publication* UT. *li•arohue', 7th Kay, 1942. Sd. W.R. Hay. tlofcl RaaUant In tha faralan Bnlf.jlZ-lP CONFIDENTIAL . No. C/544 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- pliments to 2. The Political Agent, Muscat. 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Consulate-General, 1 The Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ BUSHIRE. on L.T. Kearchus Dated... .7th. May. .1942 * Reference to previous correspondence : Political Resident’s telegram No. T/455 dated the 7th May 1942. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. India Office telegram No. 8073 dated 6th May 1942. Essential - Undertakings. 2. Political Resident’s telegram No.T/456 dated 7th May 1942.79/85. 8 . Telegram From To Repeated No.8073. Dated 6th received 7th May 194k, # Inula Office, London* Political Resident, on Nearchue* Government of India, Me* Delhi, ^•i c Your telegram No*T/38JB April £9th. Notices should be served on all Canadians NPG* • RLTAXANDUM •79/65 T«l«gram From To Repeated No. T/456 Dated the 7th Hay 1942. Political Resident, on Neardiue Secretary of State for India, London Government of India, New Delhi / ^4 Essential i Undertakings. I have made today 7th i!hy urgent regulation .-t i'i No. 2 of 1942 in accordance with ay telegram NS. 219 l 1 February 7th as modified by your telegram No. 3990 / March 4th with following two additions (a) Article Z. M Petroleua Concessions, Limited, 11 has been inserted after ♦•Bahrain Petroleum Company,' (b) Article 4. 'andW Iluacat Order in Council, 1939,' has been inserted after *1939,♦•• HJN. - Resident -CONFlDSNTxAL . AxS MAxL. VIvvn^- '&gt;( ic i © GOVERNMENT CP xNDxA. External Affairs Department. PH LEimiix- Prom - Foreign, New Delhi. To - Britconsul, Bushire. (Bipeated Political, Bahrain.) if No. P.761-N/41. Dated tihe April 1942. -ji. Your Express letter No. C/211, 23rd of March 1942, 2. Notification No* 13 m.P.(D.C.), dated the 19th of September 1939, made it necessary for male European British subjects •ordinarily resident in British India* to obtain a written permit before proceeding from British India to any destination. Merwood not being ordinarily resident in British India was not required to produce a written permit before departure. The notification to which reference has been made was replaced by Notification No. 13/M.P. dated 13th November 1941, of which a copy is enclosed, which applies to all male European British subjects for the time being in India. Thus no male European British subject with the exception of those categories for which the notification makes special provision, can now leave British India without a written permit, it will therefore not be possible for any other European British employee of a Persian Gulf oil Company to emulate Merwood's discreditable Odyssey. The issue of the above has been authorised. Additional Deputy Secretary to the Govt, of indi* S.R.*CIVIL D3EENC5 EEPARTMENT. NOTxPjlCATiON. New Delhi, the 13th Novemher 1941. No. 13/lJ!.P.- m exercise of the powers conferred by clause (a) of sub-rule (1) of rule 25 of the Defence of India Rules, and In supersession of the Notification of the Govern ment of India in the Defence Co-ordination Department No. 13/M.P. dated the 14th October 1939, the Central Government is pleased to order that no male European British Subject as defined in clause (a) of section (2) of the Registration (Bnergency Powers) Act, 1940 (i of 1940), who, for the time being is in mdia and nas attained the age of 16 years but has not attained the age of 50 years, other than a Government servant proceeding out of India under the orders, or with the permission, of Government, or an employee of the British overseas Airways Corporation Limited proceeding- 2 - l^l out ol India on duty, shall depart from British India for any destination HXtSS outside *ndxa gSSl 2Se?%» autfloriw ol a wltten pemlt eranted hy the Commander of a Military Dlot r iLo, ^(independent) Area Commander or the commander, Delhi XJte Area. Sd/- C.J.V. Lillie, Deputy Secretary to the Government of IMDxA.No.C/557. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 29th April 1942. To V. S. Wild Esquire, Awali. Dear Sir In reply to your letter of 21st April, I have reason to believe that it will be very difficult, and perhaps impossible, for you to take the journey you propose later this summer. If you would care to dis cuss the matter, I suggest that you telephone to me when you are free and I shall be glad to see you. Yours truly,CONFIDENTIAL . No. 341-3 of 1943« The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Now Delhi. 3, The Political -Agent, Bahrain ./ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (4). British Consulate-General, BUSH IRE. Dated.... ?•. A?.’}. Reference to previous correspondence : No. 2 only. Bahrain Prrroae Letter No. 0/630, detod 7th May, 1941. ^ (* IIS Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Residency telegram No. 801, dated i2ta Lay, 1943 to H,M # 8 Secretary of State for India, London. Subject. Exit permits for South Africon recruits of Bahrain Petroleum Com pany.86/3. ’ Telegram Q* From Political Resident, Bushire. To H.M # s Secretary of State for India, London. Copy ‘by air mail to Government of India. post to Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 801 Dated l^th May, 194^. Bahrain Petroleum Company who are seriously short of staff have been endeavouring to recruit men from South Africa. Messrs. Caltent (Africa) Limited of Cape Town have recruited six men hut so far have heen unahle to obtain exit permits. Company have asked for assistance in obtaining permits from South African military authorities at Pretoria. If there is no objection could Union Govern ment kindly be approached. JA. - Resident.0 G 0 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 11 ‘b CONFIUSNIIaL CON-34 Avail, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, May 11, 1942 ,$£/Cl ^ Vi &gt; His Britannio Majesty^ Political A^ent, Bahrein. (D Dear Sir: Further to our letter CON-17 dated April 29th, the services of the following men are required by the Company at least until suitable reliefs can be obtained and brought to Bahrein. The Company will endeavour to do this* Jaswant Singh Nasrullah Khan Abdul Hamid Fazal Karim Turner Mechanic Fitter Waiter Three further resignations have now been tendered by:- David Baptiste - Stores-Clerk B. C. Desai - Chemist Illam Din - Met erman These men’s services are also required until reliefs can be found# All the above-mentioned employees have been referred to Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942, a copy of which has been sent to them* Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ^O- COMTIimTlAL can-35 Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, May 11,1942 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. / Dear Sir: Reference is made to the last paragraph of h * our letter #C0N-17 of April 29, 1942. It will be appreciated if an exit permit is granted in favour of K. S. Mohd. Ismail Khan to enable him to leave Bahrein on or about May 21, 1942.; MANAGER OPERATIONSTHE BAHREIN “ UM COMPANY LIMITED A»all, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, CPNglDENTIiiL May 14, 1942 CON-40 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein* has been stopped working by the Company Doctor for a period of at least two months. Vazirani has requested permission to go to India on unpaid special leave and take the necessary treatment down there* Since we are unable to utilize his services here until he is cured, we have no objection to his doing this, although the necessary treatment is available in Bahrein through the Company’s facilities free of charge* If it is in order for him to leave, please issue an exit permit at your earliest convenience to enable him to leave by the next sailing which is expected shortly* We require Vazirani’s services and wish him to return to work as soon as he is medically fit to do so. Yours very truly ^ ' W* P. AttBEESON Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. PA-171 May 16, 1942 A# His Britannic Majesty* s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir N« K, PAUL This employee has requested to be allowed to proceed early on his Foreign Service Vacation in order to assist his family to comply with evacuation orders received by them in Noakhali, We have replied to him today as per copy of letter attached* If this is in order, we shall be glad if you will kindly grant permission for him to proceed to India immediately. W. P. ANUEKSOfl Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. Attachment© i A.vall, ni kay 16, 1942 kr. M. K. 2aul, Bahrain• laup 2&gt;ir: V.a rafar to your lattar dated April 28, 1942 containing your re cast to prooaad on your Foraigs Sarvioa Yaoatlon aa soon as poaaible. as you know, you ara not due foreign oarvica Vaca tion at this tine, but it has bean Uacidad to rrant your raquast on condition that you promise to return to our service innedlately on expiration of the vacation granted. Kindly confirm your understanding and acceptance of these conditions in the place provided belo*. Passage has been booked for you in a vessel expected to sail today or to-tfiorro* to India. You will be &gt; ranted 64 days leave in India at half- pay. as providsd for in the Coispany Vacation Plan. On returning to work for this Company, with continuous service, you will be paid a sum equal to leave-pay. Your leave expires st your home on ugust 4. 1942, and on your raportlng to our Agent in Bombay, *r. C*1. uraham, Callex House, Ballard Estate, on iuigust 10, 1942 and provided you pass a physical examination by the Company appointed doctor in Bombay, you will be re-engaged on a throe year agreement as a Clerk at Re.235/- per month plus temporary bousing allowance. Please note that failure to report to our Bombay Agent on the date indicated will lead to forfeiture of welting period pay. and promise to return to the service of The Bahrein Petroleum c.c. Personal File His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Personal File Bahreh. Mr. H. N. Phillips Mr. C. I. Graham, Bombay. THE BAHK£IM PdXKOL&amp;UM COMPANY U’D Yours very truly I confirm my understandingacceptance of the above'In exercise of the powers conferred uoon me by $2(2) of Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942 I hereby consent to K.S. Mohd. Ismail Khan leaving his employment with the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited.No♦C/671 ♦ To Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th May 1942. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, M. D. Vazirani . Reference your letter No. CON-40 dated 14th kay 1942. 2. I encloae an exit permit in favour of M.D. Vazirani. I also enclose (in duplicate) a notice to be served on Mr. Vazirani, one copy of which should, I suggest be kept by you after Mr. Vazirani has signed it in acknowledgment of receipt. Yours truly,Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th May 1942. To M. D. Vazirani, C/o the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. It is hereby brought to your notice that the grant to you of an exit permit to leave Bahrain ie not tantamount to the grant to you of permission 4./or under $2(1) of Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942 to leave your employment with the Bahrain Petroleum Company. If on the expiry of your leave you fail to return to Bahrain to resume your work for the Bahrain Petroleum Company you will be liable to arrest and trial in India and, on conviction, to a penalty of imprisonment not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding te 6500 or to both such imprisonment and fine. &amp;1 C Political Agent, Bahrain.C.12.37. ' TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS DIRECTORS: Lord Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) A. Agnew, C.B.E. R. Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser, C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy J, A. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (OS.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros LIMITED BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 11 til May, 1942. Political Agent, Bahrain. / Sir, DEFENCE REGULATION NO.2 OF 1942 yp ' I JO Lll*) We have the hohour to refer to your letters Nos. C/626 and C/627 dated Bahrain, 8th May 1942. We enclose a copy of a telegram (No.596) to our London principals and our General Manager in the Near East, Haifa, which was despatched after reference to Mr.E.B.Wakefield. 4 . ' 0 ' Reference paragraph (5) of your Memos. 626 and 627, the written acknowledgements will he forwarded in due course. ~ T/3 . We have the honour to he Your most obedient servants, For &amp; on hehalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED Enel. EPA.&gt;r THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED CON~.FXDENTI.AL CCN*-50 x. /' r ■C: fc Await, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. May 18, 1942. His Bfitannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. R. H. Goody - Asst. Surveyor Address - Karachi Dear Sir: The above 'CT' employee has given one month* s notice of his resignation. We have referred him to the Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942. This man’s services are required until a suitable relief can be obtained. Yours very truly ^c. H. P. ANDERSON Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. C-H- ^ A b&gt; L«A-No.C/696 , Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21st May 1942, To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain, Dear Sir, I enclose in original an application v;ith enclosures (return requested) from Fazal Karim. The application is a genuine one in the sense that the applicant’s mother is really ill and he is genuinely i anxious to see her• 2 . X understand that the applicant is a domestic servant. If that is so, I think that it would he unfair for me to detain him here on the ground that his continued employment in the Company's service is essential to their operations. If you are prepared to let him go altogether, I will give him an unconditional exit permit; if you want him hack, X will give him an exit permit and also, at the same time, a legal notice that he must return within 2, 3 or 4 months (as you may decide) on pain of prosecution under Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942. 3. Y/hen returning the enclosures to this letter will you please let me have your views on my suggestion. Yours truly, ^/Political igent Bahrain.■,\&gt; v No,0/463. / To /2 1(4 Lf- Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, L.T. tNearchus’, At Sea, the 24th April, 1942. The Political Agent, Bahrain, MEMORANDUM X forward herewith details of one of the Panes employed in the sardine factory at Bandar Abbas. As his pay is several months in arrears he is seeking employment elsewhere. g. I am asking His Majesty's Consul Kerman to veriiy his antecedents. If a favourable answer is received I may recommend to the Government of India his appointment as Assistant Engineer Persian Gulf in place of hr. ..urtaza. 3. In case however this proposal falls through would you please ascertain whether the Bahrain petroleum Company would have any use for his services and if so how much they would be willing to offer him. Sd. W.R. Hay. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Attested. for Secretary to the Politico! Resident in the Persian Gulf.Tehran, Iran. October 2nd, 1941 The writer, Ditlev Petersen, age 40, a Danish citizen, married and with a wife and son residing in Tehran, is seeking employment as an operating engineer. I have had many years experience in the operation of Deisel, steam, refrigeration and electrical generating equipment. For your information I hold a Danish First Class Steam and Deisel License. For the past two years I have been employed by the Iranian Government as chief engineer of the Bandar Abbas Canning Factory. My contract still has one year to run but due to the fact that the government is several months behind in my pay the contract is no longer valid and I am desirous of making a change. Prior experience has included eleven years as operating engineer in the Helsingor Water Works in Denmark. Five and one half years v/ere spent as engineer in Malayan rubber and cocoanut plantations, fourteen months of this time were spent as manager of a rubber manufacturing plant. The remainder of the time I was in charge of five engineering plants connected with rubber manufacture. During this period in Malaya I joined the Joho^e Volunteers, served three years and was given an honourable discharge. I am willing to go anywhere to a position where my engineering ability may be put to good use. The Scandinavian Club Avenue Shah, Tehran.IMfe No.C/706 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 23rd May 1942 To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir I forward herewith details of Mr. Petersen, a Dane who was until recently employed at the Sardine Factory at Bandar Abbas. 2. Steps are being taken to verify Mr.Petersen*s * antecedents. Assuming that the result of these in quiries is satisfactory, would you please let me know whether you would have any use for Mr.Petersen*s ser vices, and, if so, what terms you would be willing to offer him. Yours truly, Politics _ &gt;nt, BahrainAwali 19th May, 1942, The Honourable £• B* Wakefield, His Britiannic Majestic»s political Agent, Bahrein. Dear sir, in accordance with Section 1, article 2. of defence Regulation No.2 of 1942, I herewith beg to apply to you for permission to go to India, on special leave to attend to my mother’s last days. On April 25th I received the herewith attached cable from my relations advising me of mother's dangerous illness confirmed ny letter. I am an Ex-Service man and Served in the 2nd 112th Bombay Infantry, for five years and for 4 years in the Bahrein police. Under these sad circumstances I trust that you will be able to grant my request. I promise either to return to Bahrein as soon as possible or if desired to serve in India in any way in my capacity as an Ex Soldier. Fazal Karim. DOQuraemts attached. fPrinted in England. Feb. 1941. Pattern A. 450,000. TELEGRAM.INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND. TELEGRAM.\ NO 6NQUIRT RESP6CTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OP THIS COPY. The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named : - Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. Printed in F.neland NOV. 11)40. 1500 pads ) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) 5/-168 Clerk's Time Circuit. Name. Received. KN96/Z MIRPUR (JVU) 13 23 0 KR LC FAZALKARIM BECOMISSHAL AMERICAN PETROL COMPANY BAHREIN YOUR MOTHER DANGEROUSLY ILL REACH KARAMDIN MARK YOUR REPLY '%g Smne'uaCBahrein, April 26, 1942 The Personnel Manager, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd,, Bahrein. Dear Sir: I have today received a telegram from my home in India to the effect that my mother is dangerously ill and asking me to come home immediately. As I will be completing two years service on May 8, -1111 n i ■ w 4'wanmuj'mi i/ihp' 11 1942, I should be very thankful if you would kindly grant me whatever Foreign Service leave I have earned so far. On completion of this leave I am prepared to come on a fresh Contract, Commending this matter for your kind consideration and thanking you, I remain Dear Sir Yours obediently. #490 - Fazal Karim,THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Aw all, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, April 27, 1942. Mr. Fazal Karim, Bahrein. Dear Sir: We are in receipt of your letter of April 26, 1942. Owing to pressure of work, we are unable to grant you the leave you request. Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD./M Bahrein. April 27th, 42 The Personel Manager, The Bahrein Petroleum CO I.t^ ., Bahrein. Dear Sir, Owing to the had news of my Mothers illness and my presence is required to he at home in India I am compelled to resign my joh and leave Bahrein as soon as possible. So I the undersigned heg of you to except my one months resignation from to-day and arrange to send me to India as early as possible and oblige. I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant 490. MLTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 4 -Awall Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. April 28, 1942• Mr, Fazal Karim #490, Bahrein, Dear Sir: We are in receipt of your letter dated April 27, 1942, in which you tender one month’s notice of your intention to resign from our service# Details of available steamer sailings will be communicated to you on expiration of this notice period# You are reminded that all the terms and conditions of your Foreign Service Agreement will remain in force l while you are in Bahrein# Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED KG:CTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. May 11, 1942 Mr. Fazal Karim, #490 Bahrein* Dear Sir: Further to our letter dated April 28, 1942. We refer you to Section 1, Article 2 of Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942, a copy of which has been given to you. It is laid down therein that you may not leave the employment of this Company without the prior consent of the Political Resident or the Political Agent. Yours very truly, TEE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Aw all, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. PA-191 May 26, 1942 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: fj- Kl~ Reference is made to your letter No. C/696 dated 21st May, 1942. We have found it difficult recently to recruit satisfactory Waiters and Cooks in India for service in Bahrein, and we are prepared therefore to grant special unpaid leave of absence to Fazal Karim on condition that he returns to Bahrein within three months of his departure. Fazal Karim* s previous request for leave was made in April, at a time when we were receiving numerous similar requests from employees of occupations that could not be spared, and it was considered advisable to restrict exceptions to absolute minimum. As you are satisfied that Fazal Karim* s case is a genuine one, we are quite prepared to adopt your suggestion as stated above. We return herewith the enclosures as requested. We shall be glad if you will kindly issue the necessary exit permit and legal notice as soon as possible to enable him to depart by the first available Attachment:Ho.C/730 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 28th May 1942. To Dear The Chief Local Hepresentative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. F Sir, Fazal Karim* Reference: Your letter No.PA-191 dated 26th May 1942. I enclose an exit permit in favour of Fazal Karim. I also enclose (in duplicate) a notice to be served on Fazal Karim, one copy of vvhich should be kept by you after Fazal Kan im has signed it in acknowledgment of receipt. Yours truly, r. Political Agent, Bahrain.Political Agency, Bahrain, the 27th May 1942 To Fazal Karim, C/o the Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain* It is hereby brought to your notice that the grant to you of an exit permit to leave Bahrain is not tantamount to the grant to you of permission under $2(1) of Defence Regulation No*2 of 1942 to leave your employment with the Bahrain Petroleum UjiflU'* tHrOV+L* y&lt;ru,v Company. If w-the expiry leayou fail to return to Bahrain to resume your work for the Bahrain Petroleum Company you will be liable to arrest and trial in India and, on conviction, to a penalty of imprisonment not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding Rs 6500 or to both such imprisonment and fine. Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram Q From India Office, London* To Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain* Copy by post to Government of India. No.9466. Dated 27th received 28th May 1942. .ii&gt; / P Your telegram No.801 of May 12th. United Kingdom High Commissioner in South Africa has been asked by telegram to approach Union Authorities as suggested. KetaxandumNo.C/734 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 28th 1942. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. / Refinery Staff . Bear Sir, With reference to your letter No.PA-153 dated 5th May 1942, X have received information from London that the United Kingdom High Commissioner in South Africa has been instructed to approach the Government of the Union of oouth Africa with the request that exit permits may be granted to the men concerned. Yours truly, Political t Agent, Bahrain,The Bahrein petroleum company limited Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, Awali, ( May 27th, 1942. PA-194 Application for Employment D. Petersen. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. Pear Sir, ✓ i Reference is made to your letter No. C/706 dated May 23, 1942 enclosing application for employment from Mr. Pitlev Petersen. We should however prefer to have some more par ticulars of Mr. Petersen and it would therefore he appreciated if you would have Mr. Petersen complete the attached foim of application for employment giving detailed answers to each question asked and return it to us together with a recent photograph of himself if he has one. Upon receipt of this information we shall he able to judge if Mr. Petersen would fit into our organization and what terns we could offer him.No.C/747 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 1st June 1942 To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum . , yr • »^ Please refer to your Memorandum No .C/463 dated 24th April 1942. 2. The Bahrain Petroleum Company would like to have more particulars of Mr. Petersen before they decide whether they can make use of his services and what pay should be offered to him. They have asked, therefore, that he will fill in the enclosed form and also send a recent photograph of himself if he has one. Political Agent, Bahrain.Wo.C/748 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 1st June 1942. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I I enclose a copy of an application from Mr.Mangha Ram. Will you please let me know what the terms of Mr. ^angha Ram’s employment are, what his work is, and whether he was recruited in India or Bahrain. Yours truly, A 1, r Political Agent, Bahrain.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited © Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. May 27th, 1942. PA-196 S' Mr. W. A. SMITH His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. @ Dear Sir Please refer to your letter No. C/601 of 6th May 1942. So far only one employee of those the Company is attempting to recruit in South Africa has arrived in Bah rein. This was Mr. ¥. A. Smith, who arrived hy the tanker 'OHIO” on May 19th, 1942. Although Mr. Smith was recruited in South Africa, he had, we understand, only Been there for a short time. He was horn at Liverpool, England, on March 26th, 1917, and before going to South Africa he had been employed on tankers in this part of the world. further details of his career can be obtained if you require them. scrutiny. ¥ould you please return it to this office. Mr. Smith’s passport is attached herewith for your W. P. ANDERSON, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD AA:B Enc.I*|0 No.C/757 . Political Agency, Bahrain, the 3rd June 1942. To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Mr. W.A. Smith . Reference your letter No.PA-196 dated 27th May 1942. As Mr. Smith is a British subject by birth, Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942 is ; automatically applicable to him. If you see no objection will you please take in regard to Mr. Smith the action already taken in regard to other employees in accordance with para 5 of my letter No.C/625 dated 8th May 1942. Mr. Smith's passport is returned herewith. Yours truly, VH 1 Political 1 ^Agent, Bahrain. t© The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited / “7 I Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, May 31,1942 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Sir: #282 JASWANT SINGH - TURNER This employee has applied to us for special leave to escort his wife to India. In the absence of a Doctor’s re commendation for this step, we refused to grant the special leave, and Jaswant Singh tendered his resignation (vide our letter No#Con-34 of May 11th)« Since then Jaswant Singh has again applied for special leave, and a second opinion given by a lady doctor recommends her return to India, We have therefore informed Jaswant Singh that we are prepared to grant him two months special leave of absence to escort his wife home, and we shall be grateful if you will kindly issue the necessary exit permit and legal notice at your early convenience. We enclose herewith a copy of our letter to Jaewant Singh for reference together with his Passport No, 1931 of 9th May, 1938, which please return with the above-mentioned documents. Chief Local Representative Attachment: THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD.n v iiay 31,1942 Mr. Jaawant Singh 0 282, Bahrain. Taar Sir: Consequent cm Uf• Barney's report on your wife's present condition of health it has been decided to grant you special unpaid leave of absence for teo aonths to enable you to escort her to your home in India Phis leave is granted on condition that you are back in Bahrein not later than teo aonths from the date of your departure from here, and that all expenses in connection with this special leave are for your ovn account. Furthermore, you will be required to withdraw your resignation and work a period equivalent to your absence after the expiry of your current foreign Service Agreement• You should acknowledge your understanding and acc ptanos of these conditions in the space below. fce have applied to the Political Agent for the necessary permission for you to leave Bahrein, and you may sail by the first available vessel after this permission is received by us. 1 hereby acknowledge ay understanding and acceptance of the above-mentioned conditions. Yours very truly, TK&amp; BtSitelH PifliiOJUaU COMPANY LTD KGJC c.c. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein Mr. C. I. Graham, Bombay, Mr. J. 0. Fifer Personal File. JAJft/vNT SINGH ?282No♦C/758 * Political Agency, Bahrain, the 3rd June 1942. To The Chief Local Representative,^ Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Jaswant Singh - Turner . Dear Sir, Reference your f rn letter No.PA-201 dated 31st May 1942. I enclose an exit permit in favour of Jaswant Singh. I also enclose (In duplicate^ a notice to be served on Jaswant Singh, one copy of which should be kept by you after Jaswant Singh has signed it in acknowledgment of receipt. Passport No.1931 is returned herewith. Yours truly, Political Agent, Bahrain.Political Agency, Bahrain, the 3rd June 1942. To Jaswant Singh, C/o The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. It is hereby brought to your notice that the grant to you of an exit permit to leave Bahrain is not tantamount to the grant to you of permission under §2(1) of Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942 to leave your employ ment with the Bahrain Petroleum Company. If within two months of your departure you fail to return to Bahrain to resume your work for the Bahrain Petroleum Company you will be liable to arrest and trial in India and, on conviction, to a penalty of imprisonment not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding fis 6600 or to both such imprisonment and fine.&lt;b~ .q&lt;r Pergonal and Confidential * Ho#928/6• ^oiglo* Iranian Oil Co.Ltd#* Abadan, 19th April, 1942. My dear Chaunoy, With reference to your Ho.l07-K, dated 15th April, 1 confirm having teleghoned to the efxect that the applica tion of the Order-in-Council to our Indian employeeg had not ao far affected the recruitment of further Indian personnel in India. Ae you may know, we are at present in the market for considerable additions to our Indian Artisan strengn, ana this is one of the questions that Pattinson is dealing witn during his present visit to India. Up to now, the limit ng factor to our recruiting efforts has been our inabili-y to obtain the release from National Service in India of sufficient men with the requisite degree of skill, but we are hopeful of obtaining certain priorities in this connection now. aid at no time so far las there been any indication or suggestion that the Order-in-Council is likely to afiect matters adversely. vhen Pattinson gets back, I will let you know what his latest impressions are in this connection. Yours sincerely, sd. G.H.S.Gobey. M£jor Chauncy, H. b.M* s Consul, Khorramshahr. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf, Bushire, with reference to his telegram No.T/273 dated the 15th April 1942. IH ilMBBn sd. P.C.L.Chauncy. H. . f s Consul, Khorraroshahr. Bated 22nd April 1942. Ho.400-S• British Residency &amp; Consulate-Genera. Bushire, the 18th May 1942. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to* 1. O.K.Caroe Esquire, CSI.,CIE.,ICS., ^ secretary to the Government of India, iS Exterrial Affaire I&gt;ei)artment, Hew Belhi. 2. E.B.Wakefield Esquire, ICS., * Political Agent, Bahrain.^ 3. Major T.Hickinbotham, OBE., Political Agent, Kuvrait. with reference to Bushire telegram l-o.T/318 (to i.only) and Residency Printed letter Bo.C/4J7 oi 1/th^pril 1942 (to 2.and 2.only). t^ r ^The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali: Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, June 6th, 1942• No# PA-210 * HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT, B a h r e 1 n« Dear Sir, Further to our letter No* PA-197 __ _ 30th, 1942, enclosed herewith please find 3 slips acknow- f sp.to? lodging receipt of a copy of your letter No, c/625 to the Company dated May 8th, 1942 and copy of Defence Regulation 4 &gt; /ciT No# 2 of 1942# These slips are signed by the following British employees of this Company V- : Mr. W. A# Smith Mr# G. Bumble A new employee who has recently arrived from South Africa, Who returned on June 3rd from leave in India Mr# R. A# Darroch - Who returned on June 1st from leave in Palestine Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN FETR0L20M COMPANY LIMITED Ends: Three slips.No&gt;C/783• Political Agency, Bahrain, the 7th June 1942. To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. Memorandum . Keference your Memorandum No.PA/Est/1/297 dated 7th June 1942. 2. I enclose a copy of Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942 from which it will be seen that up to the present Oil Companies only have been declared to be undertakings essen tial for the prosecution of the War. Political Agent, Bahrain./-N Subject:- Grant of leave to Indian employees of Kuwait Oil Company. \Ay Hic ki n b°tham who was here a day or tv/o ago told me that the Kuwait Oil Company were unable to make up their minds on what terms they should grant their Indian employees leave. I gather that these employees are normally engaged on a S ye 5 r ^f°? tract whicil makes no provision for leave and that they are only granted leave in India on the expiry of their contracts if they undertake to renew them for a further period. (lAi 2. As a result of the recent King's Regulation Indian employees are forced to continue in the Company's employment on the expiry of their con tract. In some cases it will certainly be desirable to grant such employees a month or two's leave in India and I gather that the Kuwait Oil Company are contemplating the grant of this leave either without pay or on half pay. 3*^ My own view is that as these employees are being forced to remain in the Company's employ ment leave should be granted them on reasonably generous terms, say one month's leave on full nay for each year's service but 1 should be glad to ; know what policy the Bahrain Petroleum Company and Petroleum Concessions Limited are follow^np- in this respect, ~ 4 * . I 1 am sending a copy of this letter to Hickinbotham. virould you kindly send him a cony of your reply. To E- B. Wakefield, Esq., I.C Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram Inter/S. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain* No.1068. Dated and received 8th June 1942. 4' uU My memorandum No.C 463 April 24th. Petersen to whose employment there is no objection from security point of view is not now required as Assistant Engineer. Is he required by Bahrain Petroleum Company? Britconsul. ✓Telegram Q. From India Office, London. To Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy by post to Government of India. No.10224. Dated and received 9th.June 1942. My telegram No.9466 dated May 27th. High Commissioner has reported that Union Authorities have now agreed to issue necessary exit permits• RetaxandumFrom Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. No.421. v Dated 12th June 1942. j, ip Your No.1068 June 8th. Company ask for further particulars of applicant. Please await my letter of June 1st which will arrive very shortly. / p.iU 1 Political. i \No, C/804 , 198 int) To Dear Sir, Political Agency, Bahrain, the 12th June 1942, The’ Chief Loic^al leiitaliive, J ^ The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Refinery Staff . Reference my letter No.C/734 dated 28th May 1942. I have received information that the Government of the Union of South Africa have agreed to issue exit permits to the men whom you propose to employ. Yours truly, f Political Agent, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 309-3 of 3.942• The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1 * 2 * The Political Agent, Kui»it# The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the document^). undermentioned British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated...l$.th..WWr. .iWg... !• Government of India letter No *D*2477-H/42 of the 16th April 1942* 2* Buehire letter No«379-S of 16th May 1942* Essential Undertakings.Confidentiale Air Mail* ft t&gt; D.O.Ho.D.2477-N/42 External Affaire Department, Sew Delhi* The 16th April 1942* Please refer to your demi-official letter *0/283 dated the 3let March 1942* 2# I am desired to say that you are oorreot in assuming tnat the Fugitive Offenders Act only authorises the rendition of offenders. An offender against the Regulation arresied in Inaia would, after the requirements of Sections 6 and 7 of the Act had been fulfilled he sent to the Court having jurisdiction to try him. So order under Article 16 of the Bahrain Order in Council (or corresponding Article of other Orders in Council) would he legal until the offender was within the jurisdiction of the Chief Court of the Persian Gulf* 3 We are advised that it will not he feasible to undertake legislation in India on the lines of the notification *i, in Foreign Telegram No.1562, dated the 1st Maroh 1942, to within its scope British subjects not dcmioiled. On the other hand it has been suggested that Section 9 of the Foreign ouiis- diction Tot, 1890, Sight *** P ro n d % cove ^ f °'rnh l rorM Authorise Bahrain, Kuwait and Orders in Go uncil * whioh + ^“ :i t^^ rise the trial forthwith by the Bombay High Court or other British Indian* Court 1 of*11 person subject to the Order In Council who was found in British India after com; itting an offence against the Order. But this is a mattsr which you might raise with the Secretary of State* 4. It is, however, relevant to note that while such legislate t; u ld do aw with the necessity of th ‘ Gulf, it could not reliers the Gulf Authorities of ^he res ponsihility for briefing the prosecution. 5. Do you not think that the mere fact that an oilman transgressing the regulation would be returned to Bahrain trial - and probably *ome part of his sentence - would in itself be a considerable deterrent ? Yours sincerely, sd. C.A.G.Curtis. To The Hobble Lt .Col.W.R.Hay, CIS., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Confidential * D.O No*379-8* The Residency, Buehire, the 16 th May,1942. .Xu P '* t% Please refer to your demi-oflicial letter Ho.D.2477-N/ 4 2. dated the 16th April 1942. O Reference naragraph 3. Unless British subjects domiciled India !ho offend against the recent King's Regulation already fall within the scope of the notification described in Foreign telegram H 0 . 1562 ,dated the 1st March, I would suggest that it amended so as to include them* 3 . With reference to paragraph 5. The return of an oilman gLeTl^Mulf ^Pslf^eSgr^^o T/l^ofthe* 19th March* concrete cases arise. yours ainoere3yfTim Bahrein petroleum Company Limited ■ Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, PA-208 June 4, 1942 His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: #4506 - .u^angha Ram - Tailor Reference is made to your letter No.C/748. Mangha Ram is employed as a Tailor, 'GSU' classi fication, on a daily basis at the rate of Rs.2. 4. 0 per working day. He was recruited locally in Bahrein on 25th May, 1941. This employee has made no official application for special leave or discharge, although he has offered the opinion that Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942 is not *— 'h . /o ^ applicable to him. If Mangha Ram tenders his resignation, we are prepared to release him, provided he has your permission. He can be replaced locally. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED PA-221 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein* Dear Sir: Further to our letter No .PA-208 of June 4, 1942, Mangha Ram has definitely expressed his wish to resign as soon as possible. In the absence of any instructions to the contrary from you, we presumed it was in order to accept his resignation and permit him to leave our service* We have accordingly done this. Chief Local Representative THE BMREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD.No .C/841 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th June 1942 To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. Grant of Vacation to Indian Employees Dear Sir ^*'79 I have been asked by the Political Resident to inquire from you (a) on what terms vacation is normally granted to your Indian employees, and vacation for your Indian employees in view of the new conditions created by Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942. x*or example, on termination of his contract an Indian can no longer leave his employment; do you propose to give such an e/nployee vacation in India, and, if so, how much vacation would you give him, on what terms (i.e. on full pay or half pay) and who would pay his return passage? J l .^ 2. In regard to (a) the Information required apoears to be contained in (6) of Mr.Lipp*s letter No.Con-955 dated 18th Feb ruary 1942. Will you please confirm that the statement there made is still correct. 3 . In regard to (b^ I shall be grateful for an answer to the Resident’s query at your early convenience. (b) what policy you propose to pursue in regard to Yours truly, r Political Agent, BahrainNo«C/842 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th June 1942. To The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, I have been asked by the Political Resident to inquire from you (a) on what terms vacation is normally granted to your Indian employees, and vacation for your Indian employees in view of the new conditions created by Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942. i’or example, on termination of his contract an Indian can no longer leave his employment 5 do you propose to give such an employee vacation in India, and, if so, how much vacation would you give him, on what terms (i.e. on full pay or half pay) and who would pay his return passage? 2. Will you kindly let me have the information required at your early convenience? (b) what policy you propose to pursue in regard to//rg) No,C/843, Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th June 1942, To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, jo ff! Reference your letters No.PA-208 dated 4th June 1942 and PA-221 dated 14th June 1942. It is confirmed that Mangha Ram is permitted to leave your employment. Yours truly, Political Agent, Bahrain*-//? vjV 6 &lt;&gt;0' THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 5 (i- loV Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, 8th June, 1942. FOREIGN SERVICE AGREEMENTS His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Herewith 6 copies of the current Foreign Service Agreement used hy the Company in the employment of British Indian personnel, as requested. Encs: 6. cc - AA. BC: JA Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Foreign Service Agreement Service Date. Contract. ENTITLED TO BE RETURNED TO (Name of Employee) THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. (Name of Company.) MEMORANDUM OF AGREEMENT made on the day of 19 between THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, hereinafter called the “COMPANY” of the one part and^ hereinafter called the agreed as follows:— ‘EMPLOYEE” of the other part, whereby it is COMPANY hereby engages EMPLOYEE and EMPLOYEE hereby I £ . agrees to serve COMPANY as ^ in I erm or Agreement P „ r • i I I i n and place of the Zone ot Operations, as hereinafter denned, for a period of Service. three (3) years from the date EMPLOYEE shall report for duty at than^ EMPLOYEE shall report for duty not later THE COMPANY shall provide the EMPLOYEE with free transporta- 2 tion. and food or an allowance in lieu thereof from Out passage. the place of recruitment in India to . 3 Salary. PROVIDED that the EMPLOYEE shall perform his duties diligently and to the satisfaction of the COMPANY, and shall observe all the conditions of this Agreement, he shall receive a salary at the rate of Rupees per diem and not less than Rupees. per mensem, such salar}’’ to be paid at the latest on the 15th day of the month succeeding that in which it was earned. The salary of the EMPLOYEE shall commence from the date on which he is engaged in India and except in the event of his dismissal or as stated in Clause 12, shall cease on the date of his return to the place of his recruitment. The EMPLOYEE shall work six days in each week and during 9 hours on each day work to the satisfaction of the Company and also work reasonable overtime and on Sundays when called upon to do so by the COMPANY for which he shall receive payment at the rate of the ordinary wages above specified. BEFORE his departure from India to take up his employment, the 4 COMPANY shall make to EMPLOYEE on application, an Salary advance not exceeding half a month’s salary, such sum to be Advances. deducted by the COMPANY in two equal instalments from the first and second full months salary of the EMPLOYEE. The COMPANY is not bound to make any further advance to the EMPLOYEE at any time. (a) 5 Physical Requirements. EMPLOYEE shall furnish a statement from the Company’s Doctor showing the results of a complete physical examination and certifying that he is in proper health and physical condition to perform the duties required of him in the Zone of Operations(b) EMPLOYEE agrees to receive at bis own risk and at the expense of COMPANY and from a Doctor in Zone of Operations designated by COMPANY, such inoculations and vaccinations as shall be specified by COMPANY. WHILE EMPLOYEE is in the Zone of Operations, COMPANY shall 6 either furnish him free quarters through available facilities Quarters. which EMPLOYEE shall be required to utilize, or grant him an adequate allowance in lieu of free quarters. COMPENSATION will be paid in all cases of disability from injury 7 (including occupational diseases and death; when the injury injury. shall proximately cause death) arising out of and sustained in the course of employment and in determining the amount of such compensation the COMPANY will be guided by the Workmen’s compensation Act of India and in no event shall the COMPANY be liable for the payment of compensation in excess of that provided in said Act for a disability of the nature suffered by EMPLOYEE. WHILE in the Zone of Operations, EMPLOYEE shall be entitled to 8 receive free medical care and hospital treatment (with diet) Medical care. through such facilities as COMPANY shall have available in all cases of sickness or injury, except when such sickness or injury is directly due to intoxication or to the use of alcoholic liquors as a beverage, or to the use of stimulants or narcotics, or to unlawful acts, or immoralities, or to fighting, unless in self-defence against unprovoked assaults, or to other encounters such as wrestling or scuffling to injury received in any brawl or in any disreputable resort, or to self-injury wilfully inflicted, or from venereal disease, or from non-compliance with COMPANY’S health regulations in which case the employee will be provided only free medical attendance. THE EMPLOYEE shall be entitled during illness or other forced 9 idleness unless due to causes listed in Section 8 to a mini- Sickness pay. mum wage of not less than half of the monthly pay on which he is engaged. COMPANY may at any time . . month’s written notice cL^yupon to EMPLOYEE and notice - visions of Section 14 terminate this agreement upon one (1) or one month’s salary in lieu thereof in event of such termination the pro- (a) shall apply. COMPANY may at any time terminate this agreement without notice i! . . . and in event of such termination the provisions of Section lermination by ^ -v , . Company with. 14 (b) shall apply. out notice. COMPANY may at any time terminate this agreement for Cause and 2 . . . any one of the following shall be deemed a cause: lermination by x , • it Company for Insubordination, intemperance, use ot narcotics, venereal disease, Cau9e - self-injury wilfully inflicted, non-compliance with Company’s regulations or instructions, dishonesty and misconduct. In the event of such termi nation the Company shall repatriate the employee by providing him with free passage with food or an allowance to the place of his recruitment in India without prejudice to any claim that they may have against him for debt or damage. EMPLOYEE may at any time terminate this agreement upon one (1) Termination b month’s written notice to COMPANY and in the event of such Employer 0 y termination before the completion of 12 month’s service the • provisions of Section 14 (c) shall apply.3 14 Termination allowances. Notwithstanding anything in this paragraph 14 to the Contrary, EMPLOYEE must depart from Zone of Operations at the time specified by COMPANY to be entitled to Transportation or Vacation (a) Upon the termination of this agreement at the expiration of the term of service described in 1, or upon termination of this agree ment by Company on one (1) month’s notice, COMPANY shall furnish or tender EMPLOYEE Transportation, and food or allowance to EMPLOYEE’S place of recruitment, and in addition pay or tender EMPLOYEE a sum of money equivalent to salary for travel time and allow EMPLOYEE a Vacation in accordance J with COMPANY’S Vacation Plan for Class II-B Employees in | Foreign Service, as in effect at that time. (b) Upon termination of this agreement by Company without notice, COMPANY shall not earlier than 7 days nor later than 15 days, from the date of such termination, furnish or tender EMPLOYEE Transportation and food or allowance to EMPLOYEE’S place of recruitment and in addition, pay or tender to EMPLOYEE a sum of money equivalent to salary for a period of one (1) month and for Travel Time only (without any vacation or allowance therefor) (c) Upon termination of this agreement by EMPLOYEE, EMPLOYEE shall pay all expenses of this Return Passage and shall receive no salary for Travel Time and he shall forfeit any privileges to which he may have been entitled by reason of his employment hereunder. EMPLOYEE agrees to comply strictly with all regulations and *5 t instructions issued by COMPANY. Company s Regulations, EMPLOYEE agrees at all times to conduct himself in such manner 16 as not to bring discredit upon himself or COMPANY and to Employee/ abide by all general or local laws of the locality in which he is working. EMPLOYEE shall not engage directly or indirectly in any other employment, service or business whatever nor shall he take part in local politics. EMPLOYEE shall not, during the term of this agreement, or thereafter, impart any one information relating to the business or^ affairs of COMPANY to any one except to those employees of COMPANY who are entitled to receive such information. If EMPLOYEE shall absent himself from his work or duties without permission, he shall not be entitled to any wage or salary or to any allowance whatsoever for such day or days of absence. COMPANY shall ownership be entitled to the sole benefit and the exclusive _ ownership of any invention or improvements in plant, Patents 0 ' 8 and machinery, processes or other things used in the business of the COMPANY which may be made or discovered by EMPLOYEE while he is in the service of COMPANY and all patents for the same and EMPLOYEE shall do all acts necessary or required by COMPANY to, give effect to this clause. upon the request or with the consent of COMPANY EMPLOYEE continues in COMPANY’S Foreign Service beyond the term of service described in continuance of such service. If 18 Extension of Agreement. effect during t, this agreement shall remain in 19 Repatriation. COMPANY guarantees the repatriation of EMPLOYEE. EMPLOYEE shall not bring his family to the Zone until he has satisfactorily served a period of in the Zone of Operations and then only consent of COMPANY. 20 Family. of Operations three months with written4 21 Definitions. The following terms when used in this agreement shall have the meaning indicated Zone of Operations: “ ” or any other locality to which EMPLO\EE may be transferred for service during the term of this agreement. Transportation: tickets or fare on railroad, boat, motor or caravan of the customaiy^ class and over the most direct route as designated and selected by COMPAN\ together with k food allowance of Rupee One (Re. 1) per day for allowed Travel Time provided meals en route are not included in transportation. . travel The period of time required by EMPLOYEE to reach a particular destination when travelling via the route and means of transportation and in accordance with such itinerary as shall be selected and designated by COMP A N Y. P al t the fees paid or to be paid to the Government in respect of the emigration of the employee or his dependents shall be borne or recovered from the employee directly or indirectly by deduction from his remuneration or otherwise howsoever. ^ If any difference or dispute shall arise to the true intent of this agreement or any part thereof or in any way connected with or Arbitration. arising our. of the same, the decision of which is not herein- . . before provided for, the matter shall be submitted to the arbitration of the British Government Officer exercising judicial powers in r—r — ■ —f—. — an d the decision of such officer in the point shall be final and conclusively binding on both parties. IX M IINESS whereof the parties to this agreement have set their respective hands on the day and year first mentioned above. Signed and delivered in the presence of Signed and delivered on behalf of the said THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. % {Signature of Agent) Signed by the said employee. In the presence of Protector of Emigrants Bombay.i V ;) :i loUj \ It, hi 2o &gt;s&amp; U Telegram From India Office, London. n To Political Resident, Buehire. M ^ Repeated Government of India, New Delhi. If No. 10100. Jated 6th received 7th June 1942. Your telegram No.T/456 of May 7th and last ^sentence of my telegram No.6641 April 14th*- —' Z 3 * Order in Oouncii was made on ^29th May to provide for ^punishment in ^Un ited Kingdom of persons contravening sluj ireiK.aii Gulf Defence Regulation requiring persons to continue in their employment. Copies being sent to you and Political Agents by air mail. \ No. 550-&amp;. -Secretary of State for India. - British Residency &amp; Consulate- General, \ Bushire, the 8th June 1942. \ Copy forwarded, 1 . The 2. The 3 ! The Political Agenti Muscat, with reference to Residency Printed letter No.C/544 of 7th May 1942. I 3 ' r\ mmyW Tmii— AAwali, Bahrein Islands Persian Gulf. 16th. June, 1942 Dear Sir, T have been informed by my employers, lirein Petroleum Co. Ltd., that on completion of my current 2 t in November this year they are prepared to release me heir employment. I also understand that they are writing immediately to confirm this statement. volunteer for service v/ith the Fighting Forces and apply for an emergency commission. My training and experience as a rgdip and telephone engineer fit me for one of the signalling units • in either the Army, Navy or H.A.F. and T should like to know whether in view of existing regulations, it is possible to leave the oil industry and join up. Actually I am in no way an oil technician and although I am employed here as a telephone engineer the scope of the job is limited and does not offer enough activity to make full use of my ability. That is the reason for the termination of my service with this Company. five months ahead I am writing to you now so that my subsequent movements may be planned m advance and unnecessary travelling or waiting avoided. If it is possible for me to join up T i-iiro make my application through your office before Under the circumstances I wish to Although the time for my departure is Yours faithfully,2 &amp; Q THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED I. .'V Confidential. i Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, 16th June, 1942. CON-93. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, The above-named member of our staff has informed us that he is shortly approaching you as he is desirous of joining the Army on the expiration of his Agreement with this Company. maintenance of our Telephone service, which, however, does not keep him fully occupied. As we will be able adequately to make arrangements for his work to be taken over by our Electrical Department, Mr. Skerrey has been informed that we will be unable to offer him re-employment on the expiration of his foreign Service Agreement. This Agreement will expire on 27th November, 1942. Mr. Skerrey is at present in charge of the THE BAHREIN EETBOIEUM COMPANY LIMITED. W. P. Anderson. Chief Local RepresentativeI ^ / /' THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED © Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Awali, PA-225 June 15, 1942 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein# Agent, U Dear Sir: #5950 RASHID AHMSD, TAILOR. - INDIAN This Tailor, who was engaged locally, has expressed a desire to resign from our service. We do not wish to retain him, and can replace him locally. We therefore propose to release him, and shall be glad if you will confirm that this is in order. His conditions of emnloyment are similar to those of Mangha Ram, vide our letter ?fPA-208 of June 4, 1942. Yours very truly W . P. ANDERSON Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD2^ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein* Dear Sir: f lb Further to our letter No.PA-210 of June 6th, •V ^ JlJLcu. we enclose herewith signed receipts for a copy of your fol letter No.0/625 of May 8th, 1942, and copy of Defence sp -/CjT Regulation No.2 of 1942 from the following three British Indian employees, who arrived from India on June 16th, 1942: K. S. Menon - New employee C. Alberts - Returned from leave #135 - Sohan Singh ' ✓ Attachments:3. Yours very truly, W. P. *NDhRSON Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD./V h 1 VH3 No,C/858« To Political Agency, Bahrain, the 20th June 1942. The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Reference your letter No. PA-225 dated 15th June 1942. // 3950 Rashid Ahmed, tailor, is permitted to leave your employment. Yours truly, f PoliticalUAgent, Bahrain.Illl^ His Britannic Majasty*s Political Agent, Bahrein. CONFIDENTIAL CON-100 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. June 20, 1942 Dear Sir: GRANT of VACATION TO INDIAN iflfiPLOY&amp;gS We have for acknowledgr — p/q&gt;ii ia Mr. Lipp's letter No.Con*955 dated February 18, 1942 regarding the amount of leave granted is still correct. This however only refers to Artizan and Domestic employees who are still privileged to receive l-l/6th days per completed month of Foreign Service, but only if employee has satis factorily completed the period of his Foreign Service Agreement in the zone of operations. Vacation is granted at one-half pay with the second half payable on return for further service with the Company. Vacation granted to Clerical and Technical Employees of the Company is at the rate of 2-l/3rd days per completed month of service on the same conditions as outlined in the previous paragraph. ments or make suitable internal re-arrangements to enable us to release an employee, it is the Company’s intention to arrange for its Indian employees to proceed on vacation on the expiration of Agreements, this of course subject to transportation being available. In some cases naturally it may be necessary to hold them for some months. We shall in all cases endeavour to grant the whole of the vacation earned at the rates previously mentioned. Employees in the C &amp; T group will be provided with a second class passage or allowance equivalent thereto back to India, similarly on return to Bahrein. A &amp; D employees receive a deck passage to India and also on 1942. In regard to question return to Bahrein, W. P. ANDERSON Chief Local Representative mE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD sl c ' INo,C/868 &gt; Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21st June 1942. To C.E. Skerrey Esquire, C/o The Bahrain Petroleum Co*,Ltd., Av/ali. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter dated the 16th June, the Company have confirmed that they are prepared to release you from your employment on termination of your contract on 27th November 1942. 2. I shall be glad to assist you in obtaining an Emergency Commission in one of the Services. Will you please let me know whether you have a decided preference for the Navy, Army or Air Force. If your preference is for the Army it is presumed that you would be willing to accept an Emergency Commission in the Indian Army. 3. To enable me to take further steps on your application will you please let me have the following particulars about your self. (1) Date of birth. (2) Whether British subject by birth, domicile or natural isation. (3 ) Educational qualifications. (4) Technical qualifications, with details of experience. Yours truly Political t, Bahrain.D»0.No .C/879 * c*2nd June 1942* Subjecti- Grant of leave to Indian employees of the Kuwait Oil Cocipeny. Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No.494-86/29 dated 16th Way 1942. 2. The position in regard to Indian employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited is as follows. Artijrn and domestic employees receive vacation at the rate of one and one-sixth days per completed month of foreign service subject to the employee having completed the period of his Foreign Service Agreement in the zone of opera tions. Vacation is granted on half pay, the second half of the pay being payable if the employee returns for further service with the Company. Clerical end technical employees of the Company are treated similarly except that they earn vacation at the rate of two and one-third days per completed month of service. 3. Asked about their policy in regard to vacation for their Indian employees in view of the new conditions created «h. M—t King' a —I*—;— Company l»v. rapUM .. follows:- 'Provided we can get satisfactory replacements or make suitable internal re-arrangements to enable us to release en employee, it is the Company's intention to arrange for its Indian employees to proceed on vacation on the expiration of Agreements, this of course subject to transportation being available. In some cases naturally it may be necessary to The Hon'ble „ _ „ Lieut.-Colonel W.H.Bay, C.I.s.. Political Resident in the F Bu shire. ersian Gulf, / hold2 - 9-H © hold them for some months. e shall In all cases endeavour to grant the whole of the vacation earned at the rates pre viously mentioned. Bmployees in the C &lt;&amp; T group will be provided with a second class passage or allowance equivalent thereto back to India,similarlyon return to Bahrain. A &amp; D employees receive a deck passage to India and also on return to Bahrain.' 4. 1 nave not yet received a reply from Petroleum Coi&gt;- cesbione Limited to my enquiries in this matter. 5. As desired I am sending a copy*of this letter to Hickinbotham. Yours sincerely, T * sent under Printed Letter No.0/880 dated 22nd June *42\'\ &lt;!&gt;■ ^o' The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited PA-237 Awall, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, June 20, 1942 His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: GURCHARAN SINGH #283 -TUHN5R The above employee’s Foreign Service Agreement with this Company expires on July 5, 1942, and is there fore due to proceed on vacation by the first available steamer on or about that date. Adequate arrangements have been made in our organiza tion to take care of his work while on leave, and as his services are required on completion of vacation, we have offered him re-employment. YJe shall be grateful therefore if you will kindly issue the necessary exit permit and legal notice at your * early convenience. Gurcharan Singh’s Passport No.1932 dated Mount Abu 9th May, 1938 is enclosed herewith, which please return along with the documents requested. Yours very trulyj W. P. .rkNDERSON Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD, Attachment:THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED ^ His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein, iawali, y Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, June 20, 1942 Dear Sir: ABDUL LATIF #97 - ASST, REFINERY OPERATOR The above employee’s Foreign Service Agreement with this Company expires on July 5, 1942, and he is therefore due to proceed on vacation by the first available steamer on or about that date. tion to take care of his work while on leave, and as his services are required on conqpletion of vacation, we have offered him re employment , We shall be grateful therefore if you will kindly issue the necessary exit permit and legal notice at your early con- venience, Abdul Latif’s Passport No,1759 dated Calcutta 6th December 1932 is enclosed herewith, which please return along with the documents requested. Adequate arrangements have been made in our organize- W. P. ANDERSON Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTDrolitioal Agency, Bahrain tha 23rd &lt;fan* ISH2« (1) Abdul Lat»ii} (2) Gurcharan Singh, C/o The Bahrain Petroleum Co.,Ltd,, Bahrain. \ ‘ It la haraby brought to your notieo that tho grant to you of an axlt paralt to loavo liahrain ia tantamount to tho grant to you of pomiaoion undar 2(1) of Dofanoo Modulation Bo«2 of 1042 to lottvaifO*^ aent with tlwi Bahrain P*trolou&amp; Co^aisy# If on the n*» V-. . piry of year leave you fall to return to Bahrain to mm* your work for tha Bahrain retrol«Ma Cmpmy you '111 he liable to arrest and trial in India and f on comriotibn f to a penalty of laprleaxuaeat not exceeding t»o years ^ to a fine not exceeding laBSOO or to both such l&amp;prieonaent; ; v,e®d fine*No.0/896 . Political Agency, To Bahrain, the 23rd June 1942. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, GURCHARAN SINGH - TURNER ABDUL LATIF - ASST. REFINERY OPERATOR. Reference your letters No.PA-237 and PA-238 dated June 20, 1942. I enclose exit permits in favour of the above. I also enclose (in duplicate) notices to be served on Gurcharan Singh and Abdul Latif, one copy of each of which should be kept by you after Gurcharan Singh and Abdul Latif have signed them in acknowledgment of receipt. Passports Nos.1759 and 1932 are returned herewith./iAi %\b this Company expired on June 5, 1942, and he is therefore due to proceed on vacation by the first available steamer* Adequate arrangements have been made in our organiza tion to take care of his work while on leave, and as his services are required on completion of vacation, we have offered him re-employment• ISe shall be grateful therefore if you will kindly issue the necessary exit permit and legal notice at your early convenience. Ali Ahmed*s Passport No* 7507 dated Karachi, 28th May 1938 is enclosed herewith, which please return along with the documents requested* Yours very truly, W, P. ANDERSON Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. Attachment:No,C/908 , Political Agency, Bahrain, the 25th June 1942 To The Chief Local Representative The Bahrain Petroleum Co,,Ltd,, Bahrain, Dear Sir Ali Ahmed - Refrigeration Mechanic , Reference your letter No,PA-242 dated 24th June 1942 2, I enclose an exit permit in favour of the above. I also enclose (In duplicate) a notice to be served on Ali Ahmed, one copy of which should be kept by you after Ali Ahmed has signed it in acknowledgment of receipt. 3. Passport No.7507 is returned herewith. Yours truly, Political Agent, BahrainPolitical Agency, Bahrain, the 25th June 1942* To Ali Ahmed, C/o The Bahrain Petroleum Co*,Ltd*, Bahrain* It is hereby brought to your notice that the grant to you of an exit permit to leave Bahrain is not of Defence Regulation Ho*2 of 1942 to leave your employ ment with the Bahrain Petroleum Company* If on the ex piry of your leave you fail to return to Bahrain to re sume your work for the Bahrain Petroleum Company you will be liable to arrest and trial in India and, on conviction, to a penalty of imprisonment not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding fe 6500 or to both such imprisonment and fine* tantamount to the grant to you of permission under $ 2(1) Political Agent, Bahrain.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ^ V CONFIDENTIAL ' ^wali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. June 24, 1942 ic Majesty’s Political Agent, Dear Sir: D. VAZIRANI .n&gt;* 'V 6/ ^ 't S-#A. We refer to our letter #C0N-40 dated 14th May, 1942 on the subject of special medical leave granted to the above employee. Since his departure, information regarding his work and general attitude has come to hand, which has decided us to dispense with his services* The arrival of new employees from India has enabled us to fill his position, and we propose to write to him in India and inform him of his dismissal* With regard to the legal notice served on Vazirani before his departure, we shall be glad if you will inform us what steps, if any, you wish us to take to cancel this notice* We shall appreciate an early reply to enable us to contact Vazirani as soon as possible* Yours very t W* P* ANDERSON Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD,Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited PA-247 Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. June 28, 1942 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent Bahrein. Dear Sir: #4283 - NIAZ ALI - TAILOR - INDIAN This Tailor, who was engaged locally, has expressed a desire to resign from our service. Me do not wish to retain him, and can replace him locally* We therefore propose to release him, end shall be glad if you will confirm that this is in order* His conditions of employment are similar to those of Mangha Ram, vide our letter #PA-208 j 4, 1942* uxiieA iA?uax .Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD*toy 5*1 No»C/950 « Political Agency, Bahrain, the 1st July 1942. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, 2 . Reference your letter No.PA-247, dated 28th June 1942. Niaz Ali, tailor, is permitted to leave your employment. for Political Agent, Bahrain.&lt; 5 ) / 9 No*C/951 &gt; Political Agency, Bahrain, the 1st July 1942• To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Reference your letter No.CON-110 dated 24th June 1942. 2. I enclose (in duplicate) an order permitting Mr.M.D. Vazirani to leave your employment. Please send a copy of the order to him and obtain his acknowledgment. f fbl^PoiAtical Agent, Bahrain.1^111 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 1st Jhly 1942* I hereby revoke the notice dated 16th May 1942 . * served on M«D« Vazirani in exercise of the powers conferred upon me by $2(2) of Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942, and consent to Vazirani leaving his employment with the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. f t' ' for Political Agent, Bahrain.e^*‘ A / / C^V° ^ C0N-1B5.^ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A $ ^ u r % 4&gt; 14% s/ \ Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, ? !V^ $ l » 2nd July, 1942. Ifis Britaimic Majesty f s Political Agent, BAHREIN. / % A N«- Dear Sir, R.S.HOWEY - Agreement Expires 19/8/42. F.D.C.McLEAN - M w 3/8/42. R.C.DOWIE - ' M 28/8/42. The above men, who are at present employed as Refinery Operators, have been advised that we shall be unable to offer them further employment on the expiration of their Agreements. This decision has been made in view of the curtailment of our operations, which makes these men surplus to our requirements. We understand that The Anglo-Iranian Petroleum Co., Ltd., are in need of Operators for their Refinery at Abadan and you may, therefore, wish to advise them that these men would be available shortly in case they would like to contact Howey, McLean and Downie regarding offering them employment at Abadan. If you require any further information regarding the record and experience of these three men for transmission to Abadan, we shall be pleased to supply it. Messrs. Howey, McLean and Downie have all expressed a wish to return to England, but they have been advised to approach you for the issuance of the necessary Exit Permit to enable them to leave Bahrein. W. P. Anderson. Chief Local Representative. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.C/973 Political Agency, Bahrain, 5th July 1942. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir * Reference your letter No. CON-125 Dated 2/7/42. Please send the passports of Messrs.R.S.^owey, F.D.C.McLean and R.C.Downie and also let me have the informat ion regarding their record and experience. Yours truly Political Agent, BahrainBY AIR MAIL. From ^ j r - r' c aovsaniiiiE cf india. External Affairs Dep|ytiaWt. m X P E A 3 J L K T TEE. 3lM 'irk i JQo-0 Foreign, New Delhi. / —, To i J, \ ^ Britconsul, Bush ire. s (Repeated Political, Bai rain/fcoweit) .D.4157-N/42. Dated the (June 1942. Your demi-official No.3 r ?9-3 May 16th. Following is draft of notification No. 1470-OR/42, which will appear in Gazette cf India 20th June. Begins. in exercise c£ the po^ r ers conferred by section 2 of the Defence of India Act, 1939(XKXY of 1939), the Central Government is p3fi ased to direct that the following further amendment shall be made in the Defence of India Rules, neTj'iy j- After rule 81 B cf the said Rules, the following rule shall be inserted, rpmelys- 'Provision with respect to Regulation No.2 of 1942 made under the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939. 81.C. If any person baiqg a British subject domiciled in any part of Iniia leaves any anployment in contravention of Regulation No .2 of 1942 made under the Persian Guif States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939, he shall be punish able with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with fine or with both.' Enis. ISSUE OF THE ABOVE HAS BLEN AUTHORISED. i Addl. Deputy Secy, to the Govt, of India.d!'*! is Awali, Bahrein Islands, Persian Gulf« 1st. July, 1942. H.B.M. Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, dated June 21st. 1942, requested. ■Replying to your letter TTo.C/368 I enclose particulars about myself as I have since had a talk with Squadron Leader Chase, A.L.O. Bahrein, on the prospects of joining the R.A.F. and he suggests that an enquiry might be sent to his Headquarters, Iraq, regarding my suitability as a signals officer. Subject to your approval, he has offered to forward my particulars and application forms direct in orderto obtain an early reply. I understand that an interview will be necessary in the event of my application being successful. I am very eager to follow up this opportunity and therefore request your permission to make my application through the A.L.O. At the same time, T am perfectly willing to follow any other course you may prefer. Yours faithfully,1. Date of Birth - May 12th. 1909. 2. Nationality - British Subject by Birth. 3. Education - All Saints’ School, Coventry, 1915 - 1921. King Henry Vlll. School, Coventry, 1921 - 1925. Coventry Technical College, (Part time) 1925-1932. 4. Technical Training and Experience - ^ British Thomson Houston Co. Ltd., Coventry, 1925-1930. Apprentice, electrical engineering. General Electric Co. Ltd., Telephone Works, Coventry, 1930-1937. Four years factory experience, manufacture and testing radio, manual and automatic telephone equipment etc. Three years engineering and sales departments, specification and estimating telephone exchange equipment, supervisary control gear, repeater and carrier systems, etc. Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd., Bahrein, 1937-1942. Telephone engineer responsible for construction installation or maintenance of followings- 250/500 C.B. lamp signalling and magneto exchange. Aerial Cable routes. Open line routes. Submarine cables. Phantom circuits. Subscribers apparatus including safety type equipment for hazardous areas. Signalling devices for Oil P.efinery. Fire alarms. Air Laid Sirens. Short-wave radio transmitters, P./T and W/T. crystal controlled, Low and Medium pov/er. ^ Communications Peceivers, P/T and W/T. Directive and resonant antenna systems. Audio amplifying equipment. etc. Associate Member Institute Padio Engineers, 1941.• • • • • • TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN C.12.37. J X iM'i , ,-v f x CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE -* PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED « DIRECTORS: BAHREIN C. S. Gulbcnkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) W. Fraser, C.B.E. PERSIAN GULF L. M. Lefroy It-A. Many (French) H. G. Seidel (OS.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros P/CM.5/3098 4tli July, 1942 CONFIDENTIAL H.B.M.’s Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir ^5 &lt;jl j^&gt;. (^4.A- j^. yto LEAVE - INDIAN PERSONNEL 1. General Principles (a) Leave in the A.I.O.C., I.P.C. and all our subsi diary and associated Companies is omitted in agreements and it is left to the discretion of the Management as to whether leave is granted, the amount, and the conditions in which it is taken. Sometimes a bonus in lieu of leave is granted. (b) Another general principle is that home leave is granted on the completion of three years’ foreign service provided this service has been satisfactory. (c) Leave is usually allowed when it is expected that the employee will return and serve a further period. (d) When leave is granted after less than three years’ service there are special circumstances justifying the exceptions made. (e) If leave is granted to an employee not returning for further service, it is in the form of a gratuity or bonus covering the amount of leave assessed and the employee is struck off the Company’s• • # • ♦ • 2 P/CM.5/3098 (Contd.) strength with effect from the date he arrives in India, i.e., although he is in effect drawing leave pay he is no longer an employee of the Company, Reference (c), we believe Bapco and Casoc do not accept any obligation as regards leave for employees terminating their services on completion of a three-year agreement (or lesser agreement). It is understood also that they pay half leave pay only in advance and the remainder on return of the employee from leave. Leave is given on completion of three years and on termination. 2. Particulars &amp; Conditions of Leave (a) Scales of Leave ; Clerical and certain technical personnel of the same status classified as“monthly paid'up to date have been assessed for leave at 2-1/3 days per month of service. Other categories, artizans, servants, etc., known as 1 'daily paid? 1-1/6 days per month of service. (b) Indians working in Qatar get three days with pay every six weeks to visit Bahrain when work permits. In Bahrain Indian employees get a holiday on Friday with pay, when work permits. (c) Long leave (vide (a)) commences from the date of arrival at the place of recruitment but this is frequently extended to the home of the employee even in cases of where recruitment took place in Bombay. This is a generous gesture as rail journeys in India are usually long and expensive. (d) Passages: Monthly paid are given a 2nd class passage by steamer and train with food or food allowance for the journey. Daily paid get deck passages by steamer and 3rd class by rail with food or food allowance. Legitimate and reasonable travelling expenses such as porters, passport fees, vaccination and inocula tion fees, tonga hire are usually recognised.P/CM.5/3098 (Contd.) Families : When Company has given formal permission in writing for an employee to bring his family the Company pays one passage each way in three years for the wife only. Passages of children are not paid. 3. Fixed Leave Regulations The Company at this juncture would not wish to be tied down to any fixed leave regulations. If any standard leave procedure is under consideration which would result in leave being regarded as a right and included in Protector of Emigrants* agreements it would be necessary for reference to be made to our London principals. It is possible that some of the above provisional leave regula tions would not be approved. We believe that the present situation does not warrant or necessitate the introduction of any new or fixed leave procedure as far as we are concerned. s' ^^ U 4. Reference your No.C/842, the answer to para (a) is included in the above information. As regards (b), we propose to give leave governed by the conditions outlined above after three years’ service. It might happen, of course, that in making a leave programme and fitting in reliefs certain employees might have to go a month or two early and some late. As explained above the Company to date have been in the habit of paying full pay for leave, but they do not regard themselves as under any fixed obligation to do so. Return passages would be paid by the Company in cases where the Company has renewed agreements or the employees are returning under existing agreements. You may be interested to hear also that to date we have made a practice of paying full leave pay in advance. You may think this inadvisable under the new conditions. Bapco hold half the pay until return and this constitutes a strong incentive to the employee to report back to duty. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED ^UaI' ^ Uc X / f.U. t^-c/ l c&gt;ui ?u*-yu'i~ MAHAGERTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED OOKFILEHTIAL Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. CON-136 July 7th, 1942. Mr. R. S. Howey His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. P.D.C.MacLean R. C. Boimie. Bear Sir ¥ith reference to your letter C/973 dated July 5, 1942 we enclose herewith the passports of the above-named employees of this Company. Also attached is a copy of an application form completed by each of these employees which gives de tails* of ^experience prior to entering our employ. R. S. HOBB Y Joined this organization on Bebruary 3, 1940 and was working for 1 year as a Pumper on the loading fac ilities at Sitra, for 1 year as an Operator in charge of a shift at the SO 2 Plant (Kerosene Treating) and for the last 6 months at the Crude Oil receiving terminal at Zellaq.. F.P.C. MACLEAN Joined the Company on January 20, 1940, and has been employed as an Operator on Coking Units and also as Operator on Gasoline Reforming Unit. R. C. POWEB Joined the Company on February 10, 1940. He worked for 1 year as a Pipefitter on Coking Units and sub sequently to that period has been employed as a Pipefitter in the Refinery Maintenance Department on maintenance work. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. AA B Enc.3.P.P’s. and 3 Forms.Application and Service Record - - g. o. 307 GO 307 9-37 FULL NAME (please p, Address 21st Oct. 1939 HOWEY, Reed Stone'banks SOC. SEC. _ACCT. NO- TKe Anchorage, 14. Ot^erlum Road Un rth Shields jl aintenancc^Sngineer. Yield Me ctiani c. HFiriHT 5 FT 9 IN WEIGHT 9 ? t. IQbS. .PHONE. FOR EMPLOYMENT AS IN CASE OF EMERGENCY NOTIFY. DATE OF BIRTH : Mo.. June .DAY. 29th,- 1912 IMPORTANT BE SURE BIRTH DATE GIVEN IS CORRECT MALE cXfEMALE □, SINGLE QL MARRIED □, SEPARATED □. DIVORCED □. RENTING □, BOARDING □. (OWN HOME □, BUYING HOME □, WHERE? AGES OF WHOLLY DEPENDENT CHILDREN. RELATIONSHIP AND AGE .OF OTHER DEPENDENTS. PLACE OF BIRTH_ North Shields f InrHand.. ARE YOU AN AMERICAN CITIZEN? IF NOT , T O O + TJ-Y*T + Cl T -n OF WHAT COUNTRY ARE YOU A CITIZEN? LUJ-j l.yl CCi b—1. Ueti-IA. DATE OF ARRIVAL IN U. S. A- .DATE OF FIRST PAPERS. . DATE OF SECOND PAPERS. LIST ALL PHYSICAL DISABILITIES. DO YOU OBJECT TO GOING TO ANY PART OF THE COUNTRY? IF SO WHERE AND WHY?. EDUCATION: LIST ONLY HIGHEST REGULAR SCHOOL ATTENDED PLUS ADDITIONAL COURSES TAKEN SINCE LEAVING SCHOOL NO. OF YEARS NAME AND LOCATION OF SCHOOL GRAMMAR. HIGH. COLLEGE. ETC. FROM TO GRADUATED AVG. GRADE SUBJECTS OF SPECIALIZATION. DEGREES. MARINE AND PILOT LICENSES HELD. ETC. MO. YR. MO. YR. YES NO 4 Marine School of South 1 929 [193; 5 Technical. Junior and Shields Intermediate Engineering —(evening classes) Machine .Drawing u — Li Mathematics. » WHAT FOREIGN LANGUAGES DO YOU SPEAK?, PREVIOUS EMPLOYMENT (list last job first) FROM TO NO. NAME OF EMPLOYER AND LOCATION - INCLUDING MILITARY SERVICE - IF ANY (for MARINE DEPARTMENT NOTE VESSEL’S NAME: FLAG: OWNERS; SAIL. RECIPROCATING, TURBINE. DIESEL/ POSITION HELD NATURE OF WORK OR MARINE RATING REASON FOR LEAVING MO. YR. MO. YR. YRS. MOS. 3 193 3 3 1 9 1 Lawther Latta &amp; Jo. Ltd., niiliter St. 3rd En&amp;r. 1st Class London, E. 0. 3. BOT Exam. 9 193' f 1 I93e 5 G.T. Bowring &amp; Co. Ltd., 52 Leadenhall Jr. 2nd Dental. Street, London. Engr. 7 1 9% 7 1937 4 British Tanker Co. Ltd. Britohnic &gt; $rd, 4th, Domestic. &lt; House, Finsbury Circus, E.CJ 2.5th &amp; } un JSiIl££ 1.116 ^rs LIST OFFICE MACHINES OPERATED. WHAT experience have you had in OPERATING AND SERVICING MOTOR EQUIPMENT^ have you ever worked FOR THIS COMPANY BEFORE?. fsgOTnfrfclass Board of Trace Motor Certificate WHAT .DEPT.?. REASONS FOR LEAVING. THIS SECTION NOT TO BE FILLED IN BY APPLICANT , - —== INTERVIEWED BY DATE APPEARS TO BE BEST QUALIFIED FOR REMARKS EMPLOYMENT STATU s REGULAR □ TEMPORARY □ PART TIME □ EXCEPTIONAL PROSPECT □ ORIGINALLY EMPLOYED BY.Application and Service Record - - g. o. 307 GO 307 9-37 Full namel 12 / 9/39 MacLean, Fitzroy Donald Campbell SOC. SEC. _ACCT. NO._ (please print) Address 41, Day'brook EoadT s Llorcen, S. 1. 1$'.° .phone Liberty 1526 FOR EMPLOYMENT AS. 5th LnrineeF, Standard^ r._ .WEIG IN CASE OF .EMERGENCY NOTIFY 82 s . TA ^elville St.. Oreefibck Scotland 168 DATE OF BIRTH s MO._ January 11th vp 1904 IMPORTANT BE SURE BIRTH DATE GIVEN IS CORRECT MALE iS. FEMALE □. SINGLE X MARRIED □, SEPARATED □. DIVORCED □, RENTING □, BOARDING □, (OWN HOME □, BUYING HOME □, WHERE? AGES OF WHOLLY DEPENDENT CHILDREN. RELATIONSHIP AND AGE _OF OTHER DEPENDENTS PLACE OF BIRTH. Oreenock, SCOTLAND. ARE YOU AN AMERICAN CITIZEN? IF NOT LPltiSh _ OF WHAT COUNTRY ARE YOU A CITIZEN? DATE OF ARRIVAL IN U. S. A.. .DATE OF FIRST PAPERS. DATE OF SECOND PAPERS. LIST ALL PHYSICAL DISABILITIES DO YOU OBJECT TO GOING TO ANY PART OF THE COUNTRY? IF SO WHERE AND WHY?. EDUCATION: LIST ONLY highest regular school attended plus additional courses taken since leaving school NO. OF NAME AND LOCATION OF SCHOOL FROM TO GRADUATED AVG. SUBJECTS OF SPECIALIZATION. DEGREES. YEARS GRAMMAR, HIGH. COLLEGE, ETC. MO. YR. MO. YR. YES NO GRADE MARINE AND PILOT LICENSES HELD, ETC. 9 Belville Place School, E: .gh&lt; sr Greenock. 3-rac Le. H Z 00 WHAT FOREIGN LANGUAGES DO YOU SPEAK? PREVIOUS EMPLOYMENT (list last job first) FROM TO NO. NAME OF EMPLOYER AND LOCATION - INCLUDING MILITARY SERVICE - IF ANY (for MARINE DEPARTMENT NOTE VESSEL’S NAME: FLAG: OWNERS: SAIL. RECIPROCATING, TURBINE. DIESEL) POSITION HELD NATURE OF WORK OR MARINE RATING — D REASON FOR LEAVING Q hi re MO. YR. MO. YR. YRS. MOS. Aug .19 Dec, 24 5 3 J&amp;G Kincaid &amp; Go. Greenock 1 .pp. Engine CD •i REQUI McMurchy &amp; Greenless Glasgow &lt; th n hi Lambert and Bros. London &lt; :th U &lt; a. w&gt; Jan. 31 June } 31 _ 6 P. 0. S. N. Co. London &lt; th hi K O Jlv. Oct , 36 3 3 J. Hay and Son. Glasgow 1st 1 and 2nd 3 Ingrs . s .1 an. 37 1 Dec , 38 1 11 Messrs. Lines Bros. Morden, 3.W.19. Plant Meci ianic. LIST OFFICE MACHINES OPERATED WHAT EXPERIENCE HAVE YOU HAD IN OPERATING AND SERVICING MOTOR EQUIPMENT? HAVE YOU EVER WORKED WHAT FOR THIS COMPANY BEFORE? WHERE? DEPT.? FROM TO. REASONS FOR LEAVING THIS SECTION NOT TO BE FILLED IN BY APPLICANT INTERVIEWED BY DATE APPEARS TO BE BEST QUALIFIED FOR REMARKS EMPLOYMENT STATUS REGULAR □ TEMPORARY □ PART TIME □ EXCEPTIONAL PROSPECT □ ORIGINALLY EMPLOYED BY— NAME POSITION DEPT. LOCATIONGO 307 9-37 Full name (please print) Application and Service Record - - g. o. 307 COFI nAT F 50th Aug. 1939 DOME BoDert Oraig SOC. SEC. _ACCT. NO.. Address. l_A^l rirf=&gt;i 61 Ashliank Itoad. jPu n fee , icotland. .PHONE. FOR EMPLOYMENT AS. ^ I K jlnginoer IN CASE OF .EMERGENCY NOTIFY. I2i S^ e DATE OF BIRTH : MO- Decem'ber 29 til. 1913. IMPORTANT BE SURE BIRTH DATE GIVEN IS CORRECT MALE (XfEMALE □, SINGLE &amp; MARRIED □, SEPARATED □. DIVORCED □. RENTING □, BOARDING □, (OWN HOME □, BUYING HOME □, WHERE? AGES OF WHOLLY DEPENDENT CHILDREN. RELATIONSHIP AND AGE .OF OTHER DEPENDENTS— PLACE OF BIRTH r DATE OF ARFN1AAL IN U. S. A.. Dundee, Scotland. ARE YOU AN AMERICAN CITIZEN? IF NOT OF WHAT COUNTRY ARE YOU A CITIZEN?. No, Great Britain .DATE OF FIRST PAPERS. DATE OF SECOND PAPERS. LIST ALL PHYSICAL DISABILITIES. Nil DO YOU OBJECT TO GOING TO ANY PART OF THE COUNTRY? IF SO WHERE AND WHY?. EDUCATION: LIST ONLY HIGHEST REGULAR SCHOOL ATTENDED PLUS ADDITIONAL COURSES TAKEN SINCE LEAVING SCHOOL NO. OF YEARS NAME AND LOCATION OF SCHOOL GRAMMAR, HIGH. COLLEGE, ETC. FROM TO GRADUATED AVG. GRADE SUBJECTS OF SPECIALIZATION. DEGREES. MARINE AND PILOT LICENSES HELD. MO. YR. MO. YR. YES NO 9 Blackness School, Dundee 1 919 1 TU ro 00 ] ^h] ic Technical Course of 3 Arbroath High School, 1 930 1 233 I tigi er Technical Engineering 3 Dundee Technical College, 1 933 1 236 Te&lt; ihni cal M ' s 0 &lt; xEe} ;e 5 — — - kJ WHAT FOREIGN LANGUAGES DO YOU SPEAK?. Hindustani PREVIOUS EMPLOYMENT (list last job first) FROM TO NO. NAME OF EMPLOYER AND LOCATION - INCLUDING MILITARY SERVICE - IF ANY (for MARINE DEPARTMENT NOTE VESSEL'S NAME: FLAG: OWNERS: SAIL. RECIPROCATING, TU RB1N E. Dl ESEL&gt; POSITION HELD NATURE OF WORK OR MARINE RATING D REASON FOR LEAVING Q bl MO. YR. MO. YR. YRS. M0S. Feh, 38 . iUg. 39 1 7 Bonar Long &amp; Co.Ltd. Electrical Engrs. Kaintnce . Employed alt Dens Works, Princes St., Dundee Engineer present. 5 Apl, 36 &lt; )ct. 37 1 7 India Jute Mills, Serarapore, Bengal I iechanical Slump in l Jute Manufacturers India. Si ipervision ► Jute Trades 0 Mar, 33; £ar. 36 3 Thomson Shepherd &amp; Co.Ltd.Seafield Maintnce • Received l Jute Manuf acturerS^s , Dundee, 8 cotian( L Engineer. 3etuer sitn. Jan, iar7 ~33 — IT Douglas Erazer &amp; Sons. Ltd. Westhum Pn( cry. App. 1 X- X 1^. ! amny ±ei u rii stri ot, _ LIST OFFICE MACHINES OPE WHAT EX PER 1 E OPERATING ANC JL Civ U-LXC -_IX.L£ ) -L1J.C7C;-L 0 • JTU. L/X Wlx U1X , U J.LXXXU. • -L X- u uox . Drawing Office printing machines, etc, Slight knowledge mce have you had in of motor j)etrol engines. SERVICING MOTOR EQUIPMENT? HAVE YOU EVER WORK FOR THIS COMPANY BE REASONS FOR LEAVING THIS SECTION NOT TO BE ED f&gt;T WHAT FILLED IN BY APPLICANT INTERVIEWED BY APPEARS TO BE BEST QUALIFIED FOR REMARKS EMPLOYMENT STATUS REGULAR □ TEMPORARY □ PART TIME □ EXCEPTIONAL PROSPECT □ ORIGINALLY EMPLOYED BY. NAME POSITION DEPT. LOCATIONy' \Av\ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED PA-273 Awali, ^ Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, , July 11, 1942 V His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. \ Dear Sir: We enclose herewith signed receipts for a copy of your letter No.0/625 of May 8th, 1942, and copy of Defence Regulation No.2 of 1942 from the following three new British Indian employees, who arrived from India on July 8, 1942: 0. Benignus P ,K. Sukumaran Qm Ratnam Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. Attachment: 3The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali Bahrein Island, July 12th, 1942. No. PA-279 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. Bear Sir, Rurther to our letters No. PA-197 of May 30th, and No. PA-210 of June 6th, 1942, please find enclosed herewith 5 slips acknowledging receipt of a copy of your letter No. 0/625 to the Company dated May 8th, 1942 and copy of Befence Regulation No. 2 of 1942. These slips are signed hy the following Canadian employees of this Company:- Mr. YJ. A. Goodyear who has recently returned to Bahrein from leave in Canada and the U. S. Mr. H.Y.L. Bourhis New employee who arrived from Canad.a via the U.S. on June 26th and India. Mr. P. H. Hull - do - Mr. J. M. Langdon - do - Mr. G. A. Lowles, Jr. - do - W. P. ANDMRSON, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COiiPANY LIMITEB.,v /'1 tot® Extract from 'Gazette of India' dated June 2G, 1942. No.1470-OR/42. - In exercise of the powers conferred by section 2 of the Defence of India Act, 1939(XXXV of 1939), the Central Government is pleased to direct that the following further amendment shall be made in the Defence of India Rules, namely After rule 813 of the said Rules, the following rule shall be inserted, namely:- '81C. Provision with respect to Regulation No.2 of 1 , 1942 made under the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939.- If any person being a British subject domiciled in any part of India leaves any employment in contravention of Regulation No.2 of 1942 made under the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with fine or with both.'Ho.C/1040 . Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th July 1942. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited Bahrain. Mr. R.3. Howey F.D.C. MacLean R.C. Downla. Dear Sir, Reference your letters No.CON-125 dated 2nd July 1942 2. Consent is granted to Messrs. Howey, MacLean and Dovmie leaving your employment on the expiration of their agreements with you • 3. None of these gentlemen is willing to accept employment with the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, and all wish to return to England where their technical skill and experience con be utilised to the full in the National War Effort. 4. Exit permits to leave Bahrain will be granted to these gentlemen on their depositing with the Company or with me the sum of fe 2,000/- as a guarantee of their intention to return to the United Kingdom. On confirmation of their arrival in the United Kingdom the deposits would be released in their favour. This plan, to which all three men concerned have agreed, was suggested by one of them himself, and facilitates the issue by me of the exit permits asked for. 5 . I shall be grateful if you will communicate the substance of this letter to the three men concerned; and you will, I hope, give them such assistance as you are able to facilitate their journej to the United Kingdom via South Africa. 6 . The passports which you sent will be returned after examination in my office. Yours truly, Political Agant, BahrainHo.C/1038 , Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th July 1942, (ns To C.B. Skerrey Keq., C/o The Bahrain Petroleum Co.,Ltd,, Bahrain. Dear Sir, / 1 * - p * ^ In your letter of July 1st you informed me that you had had a talk with Squadron-Leader Chase about the prospects of your joining the R.A.F. as a Signals Officer, and that he was willing to take up the matter direct with Air Headquarters. 2. I am glad that you have made contact with Squadron^. Leader Chase, and I suggest that you should make your application for a Commission through him, as this will save time and corres pondence. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter to Squadron-Leader Chase for his information. Yours truly, PoliticalAgent, Bahrain AHo&gt;0/1039 . Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th July 1942. To The Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain. Memorandum. v * I enclose for your information a copy of my letter No.0/1038 dated 14th July 1942 to Mr. Skerrey. As you probably know, Mr. Skerrey is a wizard at anything to do with radio trans mission, and I hope that your Service will be able to make use of him.Telegram 3. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No.1348. Dated 12th received 13th July 1942. Following is repetition of India Office telegram No.12285 July 10th begins.~ Addressed Political Resident repeated Government of India. - * to\ LIy telegram No.7425 April 25th paragraph No.2. Union Government to whom oosition has been fully explained I of have no objection to application of Regulation 2 of 1942 to Union nationals recruited in Union for employment Bahrain Petroleum Company subject to 3 conditions first two of which are same aj3 ; ** k •'I s' those agreed unon in case of Canadians (see paragraph No.3 of my telegram No.6641 April 14th) third condition is that in the event of Union nationals not having been made aware of Regulation prior to their recruitment permission to leave will be granted to them automatically. 2. Unless you see any objection please (omission) communi cation to ? manager containing passage on lines of that in para- graph No.1 of my telegram No.7425. He should also be informed of third condition and asked to instruct Caltex and any other agent who may recruit for company in Union to advise men before recruitment of existence and terms of Regulation and of second Ucondition rti a cle Union Government. Company’s London represent ative has been notified of foregoing with request that he will inform New York. 3. Notices may then be served on Union nationals emoloyed by (omissioh) when they arrive at Bahrain ends. II. if you see no objection please take action accordingly. Britconsul.C.12.37. TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN I Ml 'S'fl [4T- CODES: BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE @ ii(i ^ PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED PERSIAN GULF dated the 8th May, 1942, forwarding Defence Regu lation No.2 of 1942. operations in Qatar will involve certain reductions in staff in Qatar and Bahrain. We shall be glad if general permission can be given us to terminate employees* services where considered necessary. preferable to making a separate application for each individual case. If, however, a fixed pro cedure has already been evolved to cover discharges initiated by the Company and approved by the Political Agent, we shall be glad if we can be informed. DIRECTORS: BAHREIN C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy J. A. Pte rry- -(French)- H.G. Seidel (US.A.) R. W. Sellers J. sT P/CM.6/3116 13th July, 1942 CONFIDENTIAL H. B. M.*s Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir Reference your Nos. C/626 and C/627 As you are aware, the suspension of oil From our point of view this will be Yours faithfully. For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED MANAGER Copy sent to P.R. under P.L.No.C/1068 dated 19th July 1942.No.C/1040 . Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th July 1942 To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. fcr. R.3. Howey F.D.C. MacLean H.C. Downle. Dear Sir, Reference your letters No.CON-125 dated 2nd July 1942 \6 dated 7th July 1942. and CON-136 dhted 7th July 1942. 2. Consent is granted to Messrs. Howey, MacLaan and Downie leaving your employment on the expiration of their agreements with you. 3. None of these gentlemen is willing to accept employment with the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, and all v/iah to return to England where their technical skill and experience can be utilised to the full in the National War Effort. 4. Exit permits to leave Bahrain will be granted to these gentlemen on their depositing with the Company or with me the sum of te 2,0C0/- as a guarantee of their intention to return to the United Kingdom. On confirmation of their arrival in the United Kingdom the deposits would be released in their favour. ^This plan, to which all three men concerned have agreed, was suggested by one of them himself, and facilitates the issue by me of the exit permit« asked for. 5. I shall be grateful if you will communicate the substance of this letter to the three men concerned? and you will, I hope, give them such assistance as you are able to facilitate their journ&lt; . to the United Kingdom via South Africa. 6. The passports which you sent will be returned after examination in my office. Yours truly, id. E.3. Wakefield. Political Agent, Bahrei: ipare copyfor A.P.A. for information. \■HPMI — — A-n l 1 * IOjjC/1065. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 19th July 1942, To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. hjtf Dear Sir, ^ I / Will you please refer to my letter No *0/626 dated 8th ^ J A), I?* Hay 1942 with which I enclosed a copy of Defence Regulation Ho.2 of 1942. /'J-O- 2. I am now to inform you that, at the request of the Govern ment of the Union of South Africa* who have heen informed of the terms of the Regulation, the Political Resident has undertaken that if for special reasons the Union Government ask that a South African employee he allowed to leave his employment with the Company, per mission will be granted. 3. The Political Resident has also agreed that in the event of any Union national not having been made aware of the terms of the Regulation prior to his recruitment, permission to leave his employment with the Company will be granted automatically. 4. I shall be obliged if you will instruct Caltex (Africa) Ltd., and my other agent who may recruit for you in the Union, to advise prospective employees of the existence and terms of the Regulation as wall as of the undertaking referred to in the second paragraph of this letter. 5. Notices may then be served on Union nationals as soon as they arrive in Bahrain and their written acknowledgments forwarded to me in the usual way. I am, Tours truly, * ^ Political 4,3Bnt, Sahrain. Coov sent to P.H. under P.L. No.C/1066 dated 19th July 1942.Ho.0/1067 » Political Agency, Bahrain, the 19th July 1942 To The Manager, Patroleu* Conceaeions ltd., Bahrain* Bear Sir, Beference your letter Ho .P/CM,6/3116 dated 13t 1942. 2. There is no objection to your terminating employees' service? ee and when this course is considered necessary. I suggest, however, that you should send me periodically lists of employees who are being discharged so that I can give formal consent to their lecving their employment. If you will kindly send me such lists in duplicate I will return one of them to you with the r.ecessarv consent endorsed on it. Yours truly. ^ Political ;ent, Bahrain . Cooy sent to F.• under P.L.No.C/1068 dated 19th July 1942.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED goi^teential CON-160 Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, July 19th, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. Tear Sir, Reference is made to Captain R. G-. Dixon's letter to Mr. A. Ayto D.0.No.C/1062 dated July 18, 1942 regarding Messrs. Howey, MacLean and Downie. He take this opportunity of confirming that a sum of not less than Rs.2000/-/- each would he due for payment to these employees covering salary for the period of their Travel Time home and subsequent leave, and that this money will not he paid to them until their arrival in England. He are requesting our Agents in England to com municate with us before paying the salaries of any of these employees should our Agents receive a request for settlement of the amounts due before Messrs. Howey, Mac- Lean and Downie arrive in England. AA:B TEE Chief Local Representative, BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD.On March 16th the subject of industrial conscription was discussed at a confernece at which the following were present The Political Resident, The Political Agent, Mr. Lipp, Mr. Russell-Brown and Mr. Crow. Mr. Lipp said that the Company did not favour conscrip tion of British subjects because of the Element of discrimina tion involved. He thought that there would be - or at least there might be - mass opposition from British subjects on the ground that they were not being given a square deal., their treatment being less favourable than that accorded to Americans and Canadians. Mr. Lipp said that if British subjects did object to the proposed Regulation he would be helpless to deal with their objections and could merely refer them to the however Political Agent. Mr. Lipp agreed^that the proposed Regulation would be useful in preventing employees who took leave from refusing to return. The most difficult problem would arise if a British subject desired to leave the Company*s employment and was not allowed to do so. The course that he would then adopt would undoubtedly be to 'sit down on his work' be slack and inattent ive to his duties and insubordinate to his employers. There is no provision in the Regulation providing for the punishment of persons refusing to work; and even if such provision were made (which would be inadvisable at present as being provocat ive of even greater hostility from British employees) there is no means in Bahrain for detaining British employees in gaol. If an employee refuses to work it seems that the only solution would be for the Political Agent to deport him to India and to arrange for his military conscription on arrival at an In dian port. There might, however, be difficulties in deporting such a man as there are no facilities at Bahrain for arresting and detaining in custody British employees. Matters would be aggravated if 15 or 20 persons Simultaneously downed tools. Since the conference took place two possibilities for dealing with this situation have occurred to me (1) that / AgentAgent should he given authority to call on the gunner detachment at Awali to arrest and detain persons whose conduct was likely to interfere with the Oil Company^ operations; or secondly that military conscription for European British subjects should be introduced in Bahrain so that anyone who refused to work for the oil Company could be conscripted as a soldier and would automatically become subject to military dis cipline. The suggestion was also made that, in order to prevent the feeling among British em ployees that the Company was deliberately dis criminating against them, they should be inform ed that the Company was in no way responsible for the Regulation which had been prepared entirely by H.M.G. and had already been applied at Aba dan. To sum up, Mr. Lipp agreed that certain advantages would accrue from the application of the proposed Regulation (especially as the Com pany's power to dismiss employees would not, in practice, be affected by it) but he was very apprehensive of the effect which would be caused on those British employees, 20 ^r 30 in number, who were at all times intractable. The question whether the Regulation should also be applied to Indians was also dis cussed. Mr. Lipp thought that if it was applied to European British subjects it should also be applied to Indians. About 400 Indians are em ployed by the Company and many of them, especially turners and fitters, were difficult, if not im possible, to replace. I expressed the definite opinion that if the Regulation was applied to Indians it should only be applied after the / question _‘J question of giving a rise in pay had been decided. If the Regulation were applied before any rise in pay had been granted to meet the increased cost of living in Bahrain the Political Agent might find it difficult under the terms of the Regulation to refuse consent to Indians wishing to leave their employment• The matter is to be discussed further by P.A. with P«R. before positive action is taken. 17/3/42. ^ ^ Cu o{f^ caCc ^ // 7 /f/^ IJl No- 7 '/^/, S ' 4i -c . . l*Sam . Do we know this man’s age ? — E.B.W. 17/3/42 P »A « He is 39 years of age; his date of birth, as entered in his passport, is 23-12-1902. K.V.H. 17/3/42 (i) Exit permit may be issued Cii) What are the age limits of compulsory military service for Eur.Brit.subjects in India ? (iii) Whom did we telegraph to in Karachi on previous occasions when we wanted somebody to be conscript ed ? E.B.W. 17/3/42.V Ref.your note dated 17/3/42. (i) Exit Permit has been prepared and will be sent to Bapco to-day. (ii) A copy of the rules regarding compulsory military service are not obtainable in the office; but according to fram the Registration Ordinance, 1939, (copy attached), male European British subjects between the ages of 16 and 50 have to register themselves in India. It can be surmised that they can be called upon for service in an emergency. (iii) Intimation of the date of departure from Bahrain and the probable date of arrival in India, the name of the boat, and destination were telegraphed to the Government of India, New Delhi, who arranged with the appropriate authorities for contacting the individuals concerned. Precedents are in file 12/19-11, put up to you in connection with Conscription of Labour. I 0 \ ^ O . S \.)K . L~^ € V &lt;A CZ -l' e tL 1i u M ^ i V tA^-v . V- S- U^t’^oC - I take it the propo'sed legislation for industrial conscription will cover cases of employees who have given notice before its introduction if they are still in the island. Pending further developments in regard to Industrial Conscription I suggest the writer be invited to the Agency and the importance of his work be explained to him and that an attempt be made to persuade him to stay voluntarily. I can see him if you so desire. I know him fairly well and I have always found him a reasonable person. 23/4/42 &lt;fY 70 ) 2P(, extract from r’.A.’s note dctfile 12/19-Hi r nn extra copy of draft i^^. should oe prepared, and sent to A.F.A. lor information, me passports should also be sent to A• P• A• for examination, v/heT.ner they are in order for a Journey to the U*K. Vxa Africa, ana saosequenu retux-xx (with any necessary comments) Xu the 1.0. f</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00009f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/750</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00009f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/750</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 28/57-III Volunteers for National Service: Conscription of Labour, etc.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-08T21:17:22</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (254 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 238-256) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 257; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional mixed foliation/pagination sequence is also present in parallel between ff 3-256; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains copies of correspondence and other papers relating to the introduction and application of Defence Regulation No. 2 of 1942, issued under the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council (1939). The Regulation stipulated that British subjects employed at the Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO) and Petroleum Concessions Limited (PCL), whose operations were considered essential to the war effort, could not leave their post without the permission of the Political Agent at Bahrain. The file is a direct chronological continuation of ‘File 28/57 II Volunteers for national service’ (IOR/R/15/2/749). The principal correspondents in the file are: the (officiating) Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Lieutenant-Colonel William Rupert Hay); the Political Agent at Bahrain (Edward Birkbeck Wakefield); the Chief Local Representative of BAPCO (Milton H Lipp; Ward P Anderson).The file includes:copies of correspondence dated November 1941, relating to the introduction of a regulation under the Emergency Powers (Defence) Act (1939-1940) in Persia [Iran], prohibiting employees of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company (AIOC) and Imperial Bank from leaving their jobs without prior official consent (ff 3-13);copies of correspondence, papers, and file notes, dated from March 1942, detailing discussion between the Political Resident, Government of India officials, Political Agent at Bahrain, and BAPCO and PCL representatives, over the drafting and implementation of an emergency regulation to be made under the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council (1939). The correspondence discusses: the applicability of the regulation to Indian as well as ‘British-European’ employees; the allocation of leave to Indian employees; opposition of BAPCO and PCL to conscription; employees’ likely response to the Regulation; questions of jurisdiction over Canadian and United States employees; punishment of offenders under the regulation; copies of Defence Regulation No. 2 of 1942, dated 7 May 1942 (ff 102-103, ff 117-118); letters to the managers of BAPCO, PCL and Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited (PDQ), all dated 8 May 1942, informing them of the implementation of the Defence Regulation (ff 104-112);correspondence concerning shortages of staff at BAPCO, including lists of staff whose contracts have expired or have resigned, roles required to be filled, and efforts to recruit employees from the Burmah Oil Company and from Caltex (Africa) Limited, in South Africa;correspondence relating to individual BAPCO employees, either applying for temporary leave, including compassionate leave, and reassignment. The correspondence includes: applications for leave; assessments of the individuals’ importance to operations; employment records; correspondence relating to the granting of exit permits by the Political Agent; notices informing employees due to depart Bahrain on leave of their duty to return to Bahrain after their leave has completed, or face arrest and conviction under the Defence Regulation (f 155);notes and correspondence dated from March 1942 relating to the increased cost of living in Bahrain, due to the rising costs of foodstuffs, and the possibility of granting additional allowances to Indian BAPCO employees (ff 56-60, ff 68-71).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company, Chief Local Representative</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Concessions Limited, Manager, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>National service</topic></subject><subject><topic>Persian Gulf States (emergency) Order in Council (1939)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Recruitment</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Employees</topic></subject><subject><topic>Conscription</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00009f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>