<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024066926.0x00005d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T01:54:00.542Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024066926.0x00005d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/157, ff 288-292</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024066926.0x00005d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/157, ff 288-292</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter no.278 of 1856 from Commander Felix Jones, Resident in the Persian Gulf, to Henry Anderson, Secretary to the Government of Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1856/1856</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-03T00:37:32</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>5 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter and its enclosures relate to arrangements to despatch a captured vessel, found carrying twelve slaves and under Turkish colours, to the Turkish authorities in Basra. The enclosures are as follows:1. Letter no.258 of 1856 (folio 289) from Jones to Lieutenant Giles, Commanding Officer of Honourable Company’s Corvette
                           Falkland, dated 28 August 1856, containing instructions to tow the captured Turkish vessel to Basrah [Basra], with its cargo, for its handover to the Turkish authorities via the Basra Political Agent;2. Letter no.268 of 1856 (folio 290) from Jones to Commodore Richard Ethersey, Commanding Officer Persian Gulf Squadron, dated 30 August 1856, informing Ethersey of the plans to hand the Turkish vessel over to the Turkish authorities at Basra, as per the existing agreement with the Ottoman Porte;3. Letter no.262 of 1856 (folio 291) from Jones to Captain Arnold Kemball, Political Agent in Turkish Arabia, dated 28 August 1856, informing Kemball of the decision to despatch the Turkish vessel to Basra. Enclosed with the letter is a copy of letter no.261 of 1856 (folio 292) from Jones to the British Consular Agent at Busreh [Basra], dated 29 August 1856, with instructions for handing the vessel over to the Turkish authorities.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024066926.0x00005d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>