<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000032_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-26T14:04:21.745Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">■;her communicution on this subject, please quote No- E /j-t- s —not to any person by wawe, out to— Ifi anj further 1 communication on this subject, please quot /A and address- “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. rv. C. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreigitr^A^uga^preients his compliments to 1 .S ^ -J StoJ3L t _ii. a. ' and. bv direction of the Secretary LI —and, by direction of the Secretary of State, ansmits herewith cop of the undermentioned paper. For 'eCfpi Office, 193^ Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. 33. f u6&gt;o Name and Date. Subject. o Lvo^Jl Similar letter sent to 14—6130 10950 ( 2 ) 2'. MAY 1 Hob ofr- ENCLOSURE III y/cEKLY LETTER I* 0 - 2 2 3 OMAY 1935 Mil fiFfinETAiiY, PfiLITICAL AND 3 ^ % DEPT, INDIA OFFICE (2/0 , i' SENT UlL-Q COPY * ( E Jc478/2£/34) J * &lt; 6 ? 1 ' £ mm \ ! Q “I H i \+s kJ \^S y Prince balar-ed-powleh, Abul Path Kirza, Qajar (Salar-ed-Dowleh), commonly (though incorrectly) called Prince Salar-ed-Dowleh tbe third son of the late Muzaffar-ed-Din, Shah of Persia, has for many years been a source of trouble and anxiety to His Majesty’s Government and the Persian Government* He has successively headed revolts against Mahomed Shah (his brother), Ahmed Shah, (his neohew) and the nresent Shah; and His Majesty’s Government have twice been obliged to arrest him when he was passing through territory under their control in order to foment trouble in Persia. The first time was in 1919, when His Majesty’s Government were the oower in military occupation of Trans Caspia, and the second in 1927, when they were the power exercising mandatory responsibility in Iraq. 2* After his arrest in 1927 the Tince agreed to proceed to Haifa and not to leave witnout the permission of His Majesty’s (Jovernment, and also to refrain from intriguing against the Persian Government. At the same time the Persian Jovernment undertook to pay him a monthly allowance and this allowance was continued until September 1933, when the Persian Government announced that they could pay it no longer. as a consequence of the discontinuance of this pension, His Majesty’s Jovarnment informed the Prince that he was absolved from hie undertaking and free to leave Palestine. 3. A few months later the Prince proceeded to Jgypt and is now living in Alexandria, where he is understood to be in great financial difficulties. As a result, no doubt, of these difficulties he is claiming damages from HisHis Majesty’s Ooyernment for wrongful arrest and consequential losses and may even attempt to prosecute his claim hy legal action. It is unnecessary to enter into details here and sufficient to state (a) that His Majesty’s Government do not admit any liability whatsoever towards the Prince and (b) that it is unlikely that any such claim could be entertained in the ;Siglish Courts. 4. As Salar-ed-Dowleh is of a restless disposition, it is quite possible that he may leave Sgypt before long, even if the Egyptian Government do not oblige him to do so. If ae were to gain admission to any territory under British control he would inevitably become a source of embarrassment to the local authorities, not only on account of his claims against His Majesty’s Government, but also on financial grounds owing to his extravagance and constant indebtedness and on political grounds owing to his doubtful relations with the Persian Government. 6. It is therefore important that he should not be allowed to enter territory under British control, especially India, Palestine, Transjordan, Cyprus, Aden and the minor Arabian States and it is desirable that all consular officers and passport control officers should be warned in this sense. 6. The same objections do not apply to other members of Salar-ed-Bowleh’s family, but especial care should be taken to see that they are not given visas unless it is certain that they are in possession of adequate means, and in the case of grown-up sons visas should not be given without reference to the Foreign Office. (Signed) H.L. BAGGALLAY. 15/4/35.Passport Control Department, t M y: 48817 ] V Foreign Office, Mug 20, 1935. For official use only. Abul Path MIRZA, Qajar (i.e., Prince Abul Path, Qajar) ; also known by his title of Salar-ed-Dowleh. The above-named is the third son of the late Muzaffar-ed-Din, Shah of Persia, and is at present residing in Alexandria. Neither lie nor his family should he granted a visa for any territory under British control without reference to this department H. E. SPENCER. To His Majesty’s Consular and Passport Control Officers. (V/19/1935) 7939—2 nS38—6</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000032_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3492</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000032</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3492</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/86 ‘Persia. Prince Salar-ed-Dowleh.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-25T16:05:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (10 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 12; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence relating to the Iranian prince Salar-ed-Dowleh [Abulfath’ Mirza Salar-ed-Dowleh Qajar], the third son of the former Shah Mozaffar ad-Din Shah Qajar, who lived in exile in Alexandria, Egypt. The file contains: a British Passport Control Department memorandum dated 1935, stating that visas should not be granted to Salar-ed-Dowleh or to members of his family; a note on Salar-ed-Dowleh, written by Herbert Lacy Baggallay of the Foreign Office, detailing his involvement in revolts against the Persian monarchy, and his subsequent movements and actions; letters in French dated 1941 from Salar-ed-Dowleh, requesting assistance from the British Government to travel to India, Palestine, Jeddah, or South Africa.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Abulfath' Mirza Salar-ed-Dowleh Qajar</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Visas</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000032#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>