<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-26T10:08:51.156Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">V Allott ed to External SECRET / 12689. D E C Y P H ER, _ OF T S L E G From Govt.of India* External Affairs Dept.* to Secretary of State for India. Dated Simla* 02.46 hours* 17.8.41. Reed. 09. 30 hours 3 17.8.41. 4529 . Addressed to His Majesty's Minister- Tehran No.260 and His Majesty's Ambassador repeated to Secy.of State-for India and British Consul at Meshed. 2. Syed Mohamed Razi left India on August 14th. He will travel as an ordinary pilgrim via Zahidan* (?Meshed) and Tehran to Iraq* He will return to India 'by same route after spending two or three months in Iraq and Iran (Persia). instructed to keep in touch with you and follow j oui instructions. Government of India will he glad if arrangements are made to ensure that (7during; hio journey to Iraa he is not unnecessarily held up in Iran (Persia) on account of visa or other f o rma1ities. 3, Government of India have paid Syed Mohamed^ Re^i Rs.4000 for his entire expenses and he has o; warned that he must not ask for more money from British representative in Iran (Persia) and Iraq. ieni\. i r yPILE COPY; . /493T '* Allotted to External 1941 SECRET^ 12553. Prom ~0 E C Y P H E R QP g E E E G- R A M Government of India* External Affaire Department* to Tehran and repeated 'by former to Secretary of State for India. , °/8' b‘K . Simla, 08.00 hours* 15th August* 1941, Dated Received 09.30 hours* 15th. August, 1941. 4280, XXX ^77' Addressed to Tehran No.259 repeated to Secretary Of State for India No.4280. Your telegram No.596 of August 9th . Function of special officer v/ln oe vo collaborate with the Press Attache in distribution of material received from India and in other matters of special interest to India* Impression gained by Vhealer was that Press Attache v/as already so fully occupied that assistance from India in dealing with considerable quantity of raw material would be valuable. Government of India also understand she has not time to tour in provincial areas which may well become of equal or greater importance than Tehran particularly to India.f SECRET w /) \j JSAP/IR/808 To : Mr. Clauson Sth August, 1941 Pnom : Mr. Pearson With reference to telegram No. 4042 from tne Government of India to Teheran, repeated to hondon, dated 5.8.41. which suggests that the Government o. India propose to send Captain Hardinge as_ a repres entative to organise the distribution in Persia ox propaganda material produced in i dia, I understana Lord Bearsted spoke to you on the telephone regarding this matter today. 2. We have telegraphed to Mr. Greenway, our renresentative in the Legation at Tehersn, staging that we are in entire agreement with the^suggestion and consider it essential that Hardinge is put m ^ touch with Greenway on arrival so that they can worK together on parallel lines. 3. We would, therefore be most grateful if, when you telegraph to the Government of India, yov would be so good as to ensure that instructions are given to Hardinge to contact Greenway as soon as he arrives at Teheran.From Genreirament of India 3 ‘ixc. Affi'S. Dopto to Tehran &amp; reptd, oy the former to o»of S. fov India* Dated Simla* 09.55 hours, 5th August, 1941. Received 11* 00 hours, 5th August, 1941, 4042&gt; v ^ XXX Addressed to Tehran 240, repeated to Secretary of State for India Ho.4042. The Government of India are anxious to send a representative to organise distribution in .Iran of propaganda iiiatena,! produced in India* They propose siibjecu :o your concurrence to send Captain Hardxnge of 10th Baluchistan Regiment to Tehran v/ith cover as Language Officer. (c. f. your telegram IVo* 545 duly 26th.) „ Ear dingo is fir.su class interpreter yn Russian., and German and also knows Trench very well. His experience in Indian Army would enable him to geu on well with Sikhs and other Indians. Do you. concur? RECd. POL. DEPt. 6 AUG :941 INDIA OFFICE# Allotted to External &gt; a A A SIICRET* 19 4 1 10793. n b n Y p H E R From n P T E L E G .R A M. Govt, or India, External Affairs Dept.*to Becy.of State for India* Dated Reod. Simla, 10.35 hours, 18,7,41* 03.30 hours, 18th July, 1941. XXX 56S5. Addressed to Secy#of Statelier India, repeat edTSnister at Tehran No. 216 and Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Gar telegram No, 180 dated June 25do. and ^ resulting telegram repeated to you, Vice Consulates Iran. 2 Proposals that follow arise from the fact that le must anticipate demands in future from military authorities for trained officers for service in L '- s® £ r areas. If we are to he in the position to lend qualified officers with experience of current affairs io in essential that we should plan at once to place as many Officers in training as cadre limitations, fanjuacia imoli cations and Iranian suspicions will permit. V/e -ip.f'ntrriise that actual volume of existing work does nou iustlfy ell the appointments hut considerations s-cated above must outTieigh this factor. We hope to reduce -possible difficulties (?with) Iranian Governmenb hy^ ^ only 'filling uoots already (^recognised) or hy creating posts not requiring recognition. 3. After P ■BiAllotted to Ext.Dept. SECRET 7484 D ECIPHER Off TEIE5RAM , From Govt .of India, Ext .Affrs.Dept 0 to S,of So for Indiao Dated N.Delhi, 17.07 hours, 26th May, 1941. Reed. 12.00 hours, 28th May, 1941. ^ X X 16 . Crornbie from Gonsalves* Reference my telegram No.4 dated 8th May. Four more copies of In ^'department al Cypher supplied to General Staff Branch from our reserve and also one each to Bombay and bind. No copies left in our reserve new. Please include six copies for our reserve along with the twelve copies indented for by (General Staff Branch^FILE COP-Y jJl.otted to Extern al Depar ■O V I' /JLj JV 1 A ~T r~ 40 i o 941 SECRET ® fO ijji tUu iosoa. I&gt; E C Y P H E R OP. TE LBG-RAM. . From Goveranssnt of India, External Affairs Department, to Secretary of State for India# Dated Simla, 16.53 hours, 16th July, 1941. Reed. 16,45 hours, 16th July, 1941. IKfCSTAET ♦ ■ ■» ■■ &lt; M-W ' ' XXX 5588. Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated to Tehran tel©gran No.212. Continuation of our t elegram No.3540 of July 14th ly anign Water schemes. We can offer inHrecCi€itely teem of &amp; European irrigation engineers with Indian assistant for projects menticned in Tehran telegram • as 265/577 of June 27th. One of these has experience of domestic water supply projects. 2. Though it is not entirely clear from Tehran telegram quoted we assume that Tehran water schttnfc is, IfTre Tehr an-XAzvin ' and £‘arun ;, soh ©me s, still in planning stage and that no question is lilaely to arise in near future of it reaching stage of execution involving possible conflict with any plan for exerting economic pressure on Iran*/ . 5. There are heavy demands from military authorities m Frcndncial Irrigation Departments for personnel and we &gt;sn only keep this offer open for a few days. Officers loncaroed ask for 50 per oeait addition to present pay (payable- &gt;ar-ii.y in India and partly in Iran) with free don from doublU? hcom# Tax piis Outfit nlloweinQe medical attendaiicc furnished icca^mpdation' free passages reasonable travelling allowance* » . ? and generous leave- We presume period would be cne year in the fir at inst ance • : ‘ ' - 1 4. Though terns are stiff we ceocmmend acooptanoe since we are satisfied officers concerned will constitute particular efficient party both from purely technical and other points 01 'view- ' At' the-sare time it must be remembered that they will not be working in ideal ‘Circumstances and that‘they will be involved in considerable expenditure in providing for their families in India 0FILE f • 'V r .Hi i 4l 08 ,a' Allotted to.SxfrernaX Dent* D E 0 Y. t P H E K OF F3?om 19 41 T E LT: G~~g a m SiECEET. '10436. fat h,l « Govt, of India, Dept, of Extei-»rial Affairs p to Secy»of State for India. • Dated Simla, 22.00 hoars, 14.7,41. Reed. 11,45 ho-ups, 15.7* 41. XXX 5540. Addressed to Seoy.of State for India,repeated to ’Tetiran No.(V 210 )•, Your tel epyam No, 8005 dated J uly 10th. Tehran*^ Kasvin water scheme. 2 . We have one two excellent irrigation engineers in view, and pai^tloularly since work is proposed to he done on irrigation project in Karun River area, ^■ J ^ G inclined to ihlnh that men with long experience ox oxg irrigation works in India are likely to 'be of more value in Iran than representatives of United Kingdom fxivx. Further it will he easier for ns to Utilise men whom we know for Intellig^noe and propaganda purposes. RCCd.POL.DCPt. 18 JUU941 INDIA OFFICE- Yx'U.'\'As\\-&gt;.\i^v + [Cypher] DEPARTI/MTAA MO . 1 B 4 1 FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIG-M SIMLA. S NoJi5! Ullard D ‘ 6,40 P*' 1, 13th July&gt; 1941 * 13th July, 1941. R. 7.30 p.m. 14th July, 1941. Repeated to FOREIGN OFFICE No.452. [][][] Your telegram No.180. I am of the opinion that the Consul at Ahwaz does not need a Vice Consul and that the Vice Consul at Bandar Shapur (If Iranian (Persian) Government agreed to the creation of post) would be of little use. i’-V \ r T 1 . ill nv i /I A A Q sT t UOc. © !(B)Ext.l+Olrf/kl' (CT’her). DEP,^R r ' r HlfJAL NQ.l. EROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN SIMLA. . ullard D. 3.00 p.m., 9th Julv, 192J.. No.298. 9 th Ju- ^_1941. R. A. 40 a.m., 13 th July, 1941. Repeated to ^0 EIC-K OFFICE No.417 Kerman No. - Your telegram No.180 (telegram No.3122 to India Office'). His I a je sty’s Consul at Kerman holds that the re-opening of the Vice Consulate at Bandar Abbas would not be justified either by economic -warfare work or by x&gt;olitical advantages. He suggests, however, appointment of a Vice-Consul at German who could act for him (?gp. omitted: and who) could be detached for periods of duty at Bandar Abbas concession (sic). This would have the advantage of not requiring the agreement of Iranian (Persian) Government, He maives a very good case which, for reasons of economy, I am not rex^eating to you in full, and I agree.Pile iuu\L^' &lt;? \^ T,&lt;n°! . (E 360f7/36d’^54)1 PORPIGN OFFICE S.W.l. lltjh July, 1941. tM^r ( |n&gt; t, &lt;2t-*rtS0ujK^ ^ro. Ov ^ K t nJL**. *■ w ’Y} I enclose a copy of a telegram from Tehran suggesting that the Government of India should send an Indian army officer to Iran as a language officer. &lt;L ^ en. We wish to support this proposal.which no doubt will also appeal to the India Office^, as being a useful contribution to the policy outlined in our telegram No. 262 to which Sir Reader Bull'aFcT's telegram refers. We therefore hope very much that the Government of India will see their way to putting it into effect. V (jwvl c. w. R.T. Peel, Esq., C.B.E., M.C./ [This telegram is of partlqip.^^sr^precy and should be i.hoi^feed'Krdcipi rut and not passed on]. y 5Q 7Qg£4 ctmental (secret) . retained by the an [CYPHER] FROl-I TEHRAN TKOF^RIIGhJoFFICE Sir R. Bullard. D. 7o00 p.m., 30th June, 191-1. No. - Undated R. 1.1-3 p.m., 3th July, 191-1. Repeated to Foreign Simla No. 270. 3 3 3 SECRET. Your telegram N o. 262 parag raph 2 (e). I suggest that Government of India should send an Indian army officer to Iran (Persia) as language officer. To judge from our latest experience Iranian authorities would insist on residence in Tehran and would watch him closely but in first place he could cultivate British- Indian community, which is considerable. Experience of Sikhs desirable as most Indians here are Sikhs and some of them anti-British.A. “ ^ OUTWARD TELEGRAM ' 2 ^ jU J 0 [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be &lt;5^ 1 1 (E3503/3U.7/3i,) Repi - U11UB ^ [CYPHER] kept under^Lock and Key.] 5 SK rrza eanM No. 3U7. ^ ssey RTMENTAL No. 2. FROM FollutN OFP^i-Tb TEHRAN. 4th July, 1941. 'tf' 2^Z. v Your Karvin water scheme]. D. 4.-5 p.m., 4th July, 1941. 0 j\ four telegram No. 335 [of I3th June: Tehran - /J &lt; Henry Boot and Sons Limited, who were engaged on reclamation scheme in Greece until recently, would be interested in developing plans for this and other public works in Iran (Persia) if way is made reasonably clear and if they are assured that Shah desires that British engineers should undertake them* Department of Overseas Trade recommend this firm in preference to that mentioned in your telegram. Messrs. Boot state that they have good men available, but before pursuing matter further require to know: (a) Any general information regarding scheme including geographical details and any preliminary surveys; (b) financial arrangements proposed; (c) travelling arrangements for two or three experts* Firm also enquire whether His Majesty’s Government would be willing to subsidise fairly considerable preliminary expenses, which would include insurance policies in favour of dependants of engineers* This might be arranged. Please telegraph fullest possible infom headings enumerated above REOd. POL. DEPt atibi?4iAid&lt;&amp;4t INDIA QFFfrF[Cypher] hEPARH-EFTAL NO. 2 FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN SIMLA., Sir R. Bullard No. 265 27th June, 1941 D. 5.0 p.re. 27th June, 1941 R. 4.45 p.m. 29th June, 1941 Jungle. Repeated to Foreign Office Ho. 577 . TTTTTT Your telegram No. 170. There are two projects. First is water scheme fo** Tehran. For this old G-overnment plan exists, second is hie irrigation and water scheme for Tehran - Kazvm F? territory - ] construction of five mile [? group undec.J. There is also third scheme, viz % irrigation involving barrage works on River Karim. For second and third schemes no plans exist; it is to make the plans that experts are wanted, 2. Ministry of Civil Administration v/ant to know whether experts can come and when they will be able to inform une Shah of the formation of local company. Matter is urgent.PILE COPY fo r cs iq 331^9, . plotted to eternal Depertrnen- -EXT 3903 19 41 SECRET 9859 0 DE CYPH ER , OF TELEGRA , H. From Covernmant of India, External Affairs? to Secy,cf State for India* Dated Simla? 09*50 hours? 1st July? 1941* Received 05,50 hours? 8th July, 1941, XXX 5262, Addressed to H.M.Representative Tehran telegram No#189 repeated to Secretary of State for India and Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (? lour telegram No.266) June 28th Imperial Bank of r ! rf Persia.' Your telegrajn does 'not taka into (? account) p 0B gihllity of introducing through bank Isrger number cf (? British) (? agents) (c.f. paragraph No.4 our telegram No»147 __June 10th). C-overnment of India would be grateful for your vievs on this point. REOdl POL.DEPt. -9JUL1941 INDIA OFRCE[This telegram is of particular secrecy and should be Ffegt ^TOreigk office. ?/ ' &gt;vc / Sir R. Bullard. No. - Undated h*) D. 7o00 p.m., 30th June, 191-1. R. 1.1-3 p. m., 3th July, 1911. Repeated to Foreign Simla No. 270. SECRET. Your telegram No. 262 paragraph 2 (e). I suggest that Government of India should send an Indian army officer to Iran (Persia) as language officer. To judge from our latest experience Iranian authorities would insist on residence in Tehran and would watch him closely but in first place he could cultivate British- Indian community, which is considerable. Experience of Sikhs desirable as most Indians here are Sikhs and some of them anti-British.OUTWARD TELEGRAM 1 [This Document is the Pro perty of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be kept under Lock and Key.] With the Comp! : men':s cf ■* bo E.5445/112 /54 Under T - / t*te foi* At raM^S- [CYPHER] m DEPARTMENTAL NQ a 2. 'FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO TEHRAN. No, 541 ‘ D&gt; 5 p.m. 2nd July, 1941. 2nd July, 1941 c 0 0 0 0 Your telegram No 0 343 [of 17th June: material and personnel for aircraft factory in Iran (Persia)]. Material for 12 Hurricanes Mark II with Merlin XX engines will.he supplied 0 First shipment (a small stock of raw material) was due to leave a few days ago. 2. Enguiries are being made regarding provision of personnel as necessary and further telegram will follow.COPY (r EXT 3780 1941 3ECRS¥. Allotted to External Dept* n ^ n Y P H‘ E R OP T B L £ G- R A.M 9377 Froin Political Resident in the Persian Gulf** 3^ S. for India* Dated Bahrain 12,15 hrs, lat Jui^l^l* Received 19 t 00 brs» 1st July, 1941«, XXX IMPORTMT, T/230o Addressed to Govt of India E.AcDeptp Sind.a repeated to*S. of for India, Your telegram No* 3122 dated June 26th. Reopening of Vice-Consulate at Bandar Abbas is fully justified by extra work entailed in Navy Certificate system# As regards Khoramshahr Daub any certainly rscpiires help but does not need (?another) Poltioal Officer. Someone who could take charge of Office and cyphers and deal with Navy Certificates is all that is required but he must be Europeano 2# It is not practicable to post anyone to Bandar Shahpur and this place can only be handled from Ahwaz which is one hour s distance by rail* In actual fact King has ucss work ^oorrup'?/ group) Denbeiiy and reopening of post ccaild scarcely ce justified by y/ork alone though additional officer in this area would be very useful for shipping and strengthens Govt* India s position in this area#% &lt;»-SeAjc Bw^f FORE TON OFFICE, .^- *-- 27th jvnvy 1941. (E 3303/3117/34) ^ XT ^ Important, .... L &gt;. ~. K 3732 Dear Mr. Boob, 19 4 1 ! Vith refrarence to my letter of the 22nd June, about the Tehran-Kasvin vater scheme, I have been asked to let you knov that we are anxious to make all possible progress ■with this matter. We should therefore be grateful if you could let us know as soon as possible the points on which you would like further information. VftJbwt. ft VO. 6 jvx&gt;-6jl^cc C. Boot, Esq Thornbridge Hall Ashford,, near Bakewe DerbyshiAJJ A'bte ci. to External Dept^ CcT| SSCRST. 9205. n K C Y ? H a 'R Qg Y From Govt of India, External Affaire S. of S. for* India. Dated Simla 00.25 hre, 26th June^l94l. Received 06.15 hr a, 26th Jnno # 19-i--i. A M Dept* to X X X IMPORTANT. 'vipp Addressed to Minister ari rehran No* and Secretary ox state fu A mdia. ^ T v , ith te glad of your opinion as to Poss-Mf ^op.-iu-ng «!-.« officers from India of Vice-Consuiat.s at (a) Sandai ATD'oas (D) Mashed (c) Ahwas. In vas» ot jt - f A with knowledge of Russian might he useful. In -as., of (Mr) it might he 'better to post^assis^en^ at TOi rir-rcimah fihir 2. for opening as Chief por What wciad he Iranian reaction to reques of new Vice-Consulate at Bandar Shahi-m t and railway terminus of Southern Irauf T, ■* *Infiltration of British Agents into Middle East countries.. 1. Iran. foreign Office telegram to Tehran No.262 of June 8th .which was repeated to India) said that the suggestion was under consideration that, in order to report on and if possible to obstruct all German activities in Iran, we should increase the number pf British subjects employed by us on political worn in -i.ran: in fact, have csfucourse C 'infiltration', more or less on the German model. The Minister was ashed for his views and recommendations on the personnel required for this purpose, under the following heads (which were not intended to be exhaustive). The Government of India have now asked that action on these proposals should be deferred until they send a further telegram after considering how the organisation could be controlled and financed throughout Iraq - Iran - Persian Gulf - Afghanistan. (a) The attachment of extra staff to the Tehran Legation or to British Consulates in Iran, or the opening of new Consulates. The Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf has questioned the value of this suggestion on the grounds . that the Legation already has an enormous staff; that untrained officers attached to the Consulates will be useless except as cypher clen^s; and that since Consulates are closely watched, new ones in areas where our interests are few would be suspect and achieve nothing, even if Iran agreed to them. , Be.suggests, however, that the Headquarters of the Consul, Shiraz, should be transferred to Isfahan; and that the Vice-Consul at khonamshahr should be given an assistant to do the routine work of the post since at present he is too hard, pressed to do any political work. . (b) Employment by British firms trading in Iran of extra personnel at K.k.G's expense. In this connection the Government of Iijdia have asked K.M./f 1 ta^H should act as nationals and Government of (c) H LI.Minister at Tehran to approach the head ‘Oj. the Imperial Bank of Iran with a view to his instructing the British managers, of branches in oouth rers^a that they and othec: European employees of the nank observers of the activities of Axis of their sympathisers in Iran. The India hope that, in face of the vital • need for improving intelligence, the Bank may oe willing to relax their policy of remaining aloof from any form of political or intelligence activity. The Government•of India add that their suggestion might involve the employment at their expense of extra staff by the Bank. It, -,-S understood that efforts are being made to supply material to enable Messrs. Hawkers Aircraft Factory at Tehran to resume production. There were originally lb British technicians attached to the factory, but only 6 now remain. To restart uhe Factory, 4 more would- be needed immediately and ^ more very soon. T e Political Resident comments, with regard to (b) as a v;hole, that British firms with concessions to lose will not expose themselves to any risk and the real identity of any extra personnel will quickly become apparent, especially in the case of the-Imperial Bank; and that permanent members of the Bank are unlikely tc tale any active part in intelligence work as tne cancellation of their permis de sejour would lose them their posts. He adds that the Anglo-Ireman Oil Co. &lt; have very few useful people and are Liern.edly unc o-operativ e. The starting of i*t* subsidised lorry or ’bus service (e.g. the extension of the Nairn line; betvveen Bagdad and Tehran, or between Tehran and India, or both. (d) The offer to the Iranian authorities of the service^ of CL-frii* hritisn Cotton expert^, or some other expert^, on favourable terms or free of charge. The Political Resident .considers that this is a good line and that a cotton expert at Isfahan could be very useful. He observes that tne Germans■w» have had excellent results from subsidising mining prospecls etc., and that even if the expert knew no Persian, good results could be obtained by attaching to him a Persian- ^speaking Indian. His viex is that Indians are inconspicuous and that more use could be made of them. The Minister at/Tehran has reported that, in connection with the large Tehran - na$vin water scheme, ^the Iranians are proposing to form a local company which would invite some prominent British specialist with two assistants to come and draw up flu. scheme. Two German specialists in Iran have already bean preparing plans for barrages etc., but there is good reason to .believe that the Shah does not want the work to go to the Germans and would like to interest the British. The minister, who has been asked to furnish names .of possible specialists, suggests that a representative of hessrs. Hughes and L.C.D.Caster, who carried out a water and drainage scheme for Athens, might be sent from Egypt with two first class assistants if the local company were to offer suitable terms. He further suggests that, if the salaries offered by the company were inadequate, it would be worth while to make up the difference officially. . • .. ' . ; ’ . I* The Government of India have telegraphed to Tehran to to ask for details of the scheme in order to enable them to select men in India if required. The Foreign Office are also looking fcr suitable experts. (e) The appointment of a permanent Inspector of Consular Buildings,anfc Assistant Director of antiquities, Language Officers, Archaeologists, Naturalists, etc. The Political Besident remarks that Language Officers will meet with difficulty, and that the French have a monopoly of archaeology. (f) The employment by the British of Armenians, especially lorry owners, who may be able to circulate more freely, than British subjects. The Political Resident says that the Isfahan Armenians are believed •to be under German influence. Ke sugg sts that use might be made of: (1) Calcutta Armenians(though they would be in/^ I in danger of conscription if of Iranian corn parents). (ii) Jews with a stake outside Iran y of . whom potentially useful colonies exist in Lieshed and also in Basra, which would 'fea convenient centre. (g) The dispatch by the Government of India of specially selected pilgrims to Meshed. The Government of India have been asked for their views. 2. Afghanistan . Suggestions similar to, though less detailed than, those in foreign Cffice telegram No.262. have been put to the Government of India in India Office telegram No. 6668 of June 12th. This telegram expresses the view that any opportunity offered by the Afghan Government for introducing British subjects into the country should be s fctzed, and that this policy should not be limited by considerations of expense or ty the rigid restriction of our economic activities to the ereaH east orjiKabul - handahar line. Beference is made to: . . * tk&amp; . (i) The question of/.employment by the Afghan Government of British road engineers, and (ii)The desirability of attempting to introduce agents on the pretext of helping with bridges on the Herat - Kandahar road. 5. Irac. India Cffice telegram No.6955 of 18th June passed on to the Government of India a suggestion made by the Middle Hast Linisteri-al Committee that suitable British officers with political or military experience in India or the Middle Hast . ight usefullube employed in the Bagdad Nmbes y ^ to/ yto report^and to obstruct German activities. The Government oi India were asked to put forward names of men in the following two categories who would be suitable and could be made available for this purpose:- (i) Serving or retired British officers, either in India or the United kingdom; ^ (ii) Shia iioslem officials now in India who could be used for propaganda purposes. -he Government of India have suggested postponing the consideration of (i) until the system of liaison officers for me into ininf contact between the local military commanders and the civil officials in Iraq has teen established. They say that they are at present unaware what their commitments will be under this system and what liaison officers will be required. ^ (Kith regard to ^ii; the Government of India say that they will be able to find Shia koslem officials for' the urpose^ indicated, but suggest that this also should wait until the chief liaison officer is appointed and candiscuss Vvith the Ambassador how many of these officials are reouired and where they should be located. keanwhile H.l.Ambassador at Bagdad has emphasised the v ^1 great importance of establishing some organisation which will enable him. to establish and maintain contact Y/ith the tribes and the influential Shaikhs in various oarts of the country. would be done by appointing experienced pelitical officers who know and have gained the friendshi' Ox chief tribal leaders and by the generous employment of x.oney. The political officers would keep tne Embassy informed oi local politxcal.developments and events, establish close and fxiendly relations with the tribes, make propaganda and discourage the activities of enemy agents. As a first step the Ambassador with the support of the C.C.C. has asxed 'for authority to appoint zor this work two experienced political lecturers whose land settlement contracts . ith the Iraci Government have just expired and whom he intends to attach to the British military forces in Berth and South Iraq/Ukdar Secretary o f State for Foreign Affairs Dear Hi £*? 3^ Q%*sryJL- tyMl. y, y-0-4. Z/Z/jr/is/yst* $0 It waa very kind of you to take the trouble to call at the Foreign office to dlacuaa the aueetloo of the proposed Tehran&lt;-Ksavin 'fater Scheme. I promised to confirm the substance of our conversation in writing in order that you may consider and let ua know whether there are any pointa on which you would like further information before you ta*e a decision in the matter. According to a report which we have received from Hia 'ajeaty^ Inlater at Tehran* which I must as: you t&lt; keep conflcentlal for the present, the Germans have had two specialists in Iran preparing plana for two barrages, a tunnel, etc., in connexion with the large Tehran-Kaavln Vater scheme. There ia good reason to believe that the Shah ould like to interest the British In the scheme and, in order to obviate political complications, the intention apparently ia to fora a local company who would invite some prominent British specialist with two assistants to go to Iran to draw up the scheme. Our linister has been asked to furnish names. %e feel that this ia an opportunity to strengthen British influence in Iran which should not be lost and we propose, as soon as we hear from you, to telegraph to the Minister asking him to try to obtain such further Information as you may require. Boot, Esq., Vours sinoorefy ThornbricUre H«n OVERLE.Y PRICE■HU wmmammm Copies of the relevant correspondence are attached. This Department is at present engaged in collating it in order to get a complete picture, but we cannot submit until we have received the further telegram promised in paragraph 3 of the Government of India*s telegram of June 21st, which may well provide matter for discussion in the Middle East Committee. The Foreign Office telegram to Tehran of 8th June and similar telegram to the Government of India of June broaching this suggestion of infiltration on the German model, were sent in accordance with recommendations of the M.E. Committee. I have not yet seen the reply from Sir R. Bullard to the F.Q. As regards paragraph 2 of the Government of India*s telegram it is not quite clear to me v/hat sort of 'organisation” they have in mind, whether it is an extension of their Foreign Information Bureau or a 3.0. organisation or a combination of both; but no doubt their further telegram will elucidate this.&amp; E 0 X P H E R , . OF T S L B 0 R A M From Govt of India ? External Affairs Dept, to So of S. for India. Dated Simla 19.35 hrs 21st June ? 1941« Received 22.45 hrs, 22nd June,1941. x X X 504 7, Addressed to Tehran 170 repeated to S. of 8. for India. (VYour tel. No. June 131 . To exiatle Govt of India to select personnel in India if i required please cable main details of Tehran Kasvin service project at sufficient (?length) to enable ub to determine what experience and qualifications will he necessary. Quote references if any have appeared in engineering periodicals or publications* RECd. POL, DEPt.I 2 4JUIH41 INDIA ©m§£FILE (50PV r - I A i 1 - fi iU \bW^ . A34otted to Exteinml Dgptc Copjea Ciroulatedo D E 0 Y P H E R u F, T /EXT 3578 SECRET g? 8978c O rinU J li E G Prom Govt 0 of India, External Affairs Deptc, to Secretary of State for India. Dated Simla, 19c50 hours, 21st June, 1941 o Received 22o45 hours, 21st June, 1941 o / XXX b.a, repeated Tp-RlPTAWT. 5048 c Addressed to SecycOf State for India 3 to Bus hi remand 'Tehran, No c 171c FQx-eign Office telegram to Tehran No * 26 2, June 8th and connected correspondence« 2c We are anxious to fit these projects into a larger picture and to consider how the organisation should be controlled and financed not in Iran alone, frit throughout Iraq Iran - Persian Gulf - Afghanistan (corrupt group),, We would ask therefore that action until we telegraph a gain 0 should be deferred RECb. rC#^. DEPt.I l\ JUN ^4i INDIA OFFICE99 ! / [This telegram is of-particular secre cy a mi should:t' retained by the authorised recipient and’ not pa^se&lt; 'parsed on]. [ Cypher ] DBPARiiiliiM'AL (S^CKdT) FROM ‘JEHRM TO FOREIGN OFFICE D s 3.00. p.m. 17th June, 1941. R* 9,00o a,in. 19th June, 1941, Sir R. Bullard No, 545. June 17th, 1941. b b b b b b Your telegram No. 261. Secret. Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs who had received direct from London, information in first paragraph, is pleased at the hope of raw material in these difficult times and is anxious to re-start factory as soon as oossible but asks for date of first delivery as that would strengthen his position with the Shah K 2* I have no doubt that if hope of Hurricanes was abandoned the Shah would be strongly tempted to turn to the Germans who would offer better terms than we ever did. The Shah might prefer the Americans as material develops but dollars are short and exceedingly difficult to release. At present ’there are twenty-five Rearwin training machines which have been in Tehran for four months and for lack of American experts are not yet unpacked, Tomahav/ks have reached Bandashahpur and one pilot and two riggers to erect them have reached Tehran. 3. As to British aircraft personnel. Mr. Knight reports as follows. Personnel on production origrnally numbered eleven of whom two left eighteen months ago ana were not replaced. The remaining nine reduced to two viz. Mr. Knight and one welder~fitter 0 In addition there are four employed on maintenance inspection, of whom two could ,sic] desires i)ut most if make a TO probably be borrowed for production. India to absorb all sjj^ as their contracts expire, not all would remain if material released, beginning with construction of Hurricanes with material described in your telegram under reference Mr, Knight in addition to welder fitter and the two men he could hone to borrov/ would need (A.) Immediately (1) machine shop foreman ^foreman. _(6]_ insp ecto r v' ^ v In a ddition to inspector who would be one of the two men fbn5e borrowed) 7 electriciarw. 4® I am sure that maintenance of factory is worthy of a struggle. Unfortunately the ask is more difficult now that the group have nearly all gone. The attraction of war work in India was too much for them once the hone of receiving Hurricane material disappeared. J \n £ 1 7/it/ 7 /^ With the Compliments of the / Under Secretary of Stato for Foreign Affairs 17 JUN 194t a- E XT SECRET , [Gy er] ^\V ^ DEPARTMENT AL to.2. y\'^ Vdjn FROM TEHRAN TO FORE IGiV ©SSICE—— Sir Ra Bullard Nq» 335. June 15th, 1941. D. 8.55. p.m. 15th June, 1941. R. 6.45. p.m. 15th June, 1941. Repeated to Foreign|i~^ elhi No.226. Cairo No.51. h h h b b h Germans have had two specialists here preparing plans for two barrages [grp.undec.] one tunnel etc. in connexion with large Tehran-Kasvin water scheme. There is good reason to believe that the Shah does not want the work to go to the Germans and would like to interest the British. To obviate political complications however it is proposed to form a local company who would invite some prominent British specialist with two assistants to come and draw up the scheme. I have been asked to furnish names. 2. This is a. great chance to introduce British instead 55U of German infl uence (your telegram N o.262). 3. - The firm of Hughes and L.C.D. Caster was carrying out water and drainage scheme for Athens. Their representative Mr. Sisson is perhaps in Egypt. Could he come with two first class assistants if local company offered suitable terms? b Enqu^iry is confidential for the present. &amp; V-' ’ ,r l 1 (' * i \ IS JUN 194, ' • \ x * j' ^ \\ 4V EXT SECRET ?) ysyP. Allotted tc^xt^nEt D^pai^.sntl ' , CO 1 Prom Dated Received 8616 trui^a, 4x ue-. ' DBCYPHER OF TELSSR ,A « • CU Government ox India, External Affairs Dept., to Secretary of State for India. 'v&lt;we£&gt;-&gt; Simla, 21.58 hours, 15th June, 1941. 16.00 hours, 15th June, 1941. '&lt;J6 XXX 2878 . Personal. Prom Caroe for Peel. Prior reports that on May 20th Bullard issued a circular which suggested inter alia that Russia and Germany had come to an agreement regarding Middle East, and advised that all British subjects who had np special .reasons for remaining in Iran should be encouraged to proceed on leave to India. Minister, after being informed by Foreign Office that as far as they were aware no such agreement existed, subsequently issued a revised circular containing instructions that British subjects with nothing to keep them in Iran and (? some) with children might as v/ell go to India. [12. I am passing above on for your personal ^ 1 information,, (? Prior) has protested against Minister’s 1 instructions but I do not press for any representation to be made as they will presumably be modified in (? light) of Foreign Office te legram Noo262 of J une 6th. IrECd. POL.OEP-n j7 'OIM li&gt;DIA OFFICEFro^-% Govt o of India, Dept, of External Affrs, g to Secretary of State for Indiao Dated Simla, 21.55 hours, 14th June, 1941. Received 09.50 hours. 16th June? 1941. XXX telegram mrr~ v 2866. Following from British Consul, Bushire, No.627, June 11th. Beginss Your_ „ 281^ June 11th. Plan is an exceXTerft one (v DUtrf ‘foreign Office have produced it i’ive years too late. It is not possible now to acquire British subjects with intimate knowled^a of Persia and Persians, and without it they will be of little value. Since objects of infiltration auoear also to be conflicting, e.g. * information and jro pacsiria? double staff will be required* 2» To,take points in details (a) Legation already have enormous staff. Untrained officers attached to consulates will be useless except as cypher clerks. Since consulates are closely watched new ones in areas where our interests are few would be darkly suspect and achiev nothing, even if Persia agreed to them. I think, I £ however, headquarters of the Consul, Bhiraz ? should I lu obviously be at Isfahan and not hhiraz as at presentsO Khoramahahr could do with an assistant to fake the routine of post Off his shoulders since at present id hard pressed to do any political work. I &amp; (B) British firms with concessions to lose I Q will not expose themselves to any risk and_real [ identity of'any extra personnel will quickly become apparent/.eo FILE COPy- E XT SECRET^) fp.i 5342 L 1 q 4 1 Allotted to External D epa rtment; . I ^ r I L~ From Dated Keoelved B589“ D E C Y. P H E F OF T B LEG g A M . Govt*of India&gt; External Affaire Dept., to HJ.I .Minister at Tehran and repeated by the former to Secretary of State for India. Simla, 22.46 hours, IGfch June, 1941. 01.30 hours, 12th June, 1941. XXX 2813 . Addressed to Minister at Tehran 147 repeated to British Donsul at Bushire end Secretary of State for India. As part of our Intelligence organisation in peripheral countries we arc anxious if possible to make use of European personnel of Imperial Bank of Iran as observers of activities cf. Axij nationals and their sympathisers in Iran, including ^ro-Kashid Iraqis and pro-Axis Iranians. 2. The area in which we are particularly interested comprises the following towns in which Imperial Bank branches are located via., Meshed, lahiden, Shiraz and Bushire, f/e shoul d be grateful if you would take up this matter with head of liiiperiel. Bank of Iran in Tehran with the idea that he might issue suitable instructions to British managers of these branches. The latter could pass any information to Consulates for transmission to us. 3, We are aware that it has been the policy of Imperial Bank of Iren to remain alQof from local politics of all kinds end it is probable in ordinary circumstances they would-be unwilling to take any part in collection of intelligence. We feel however that in present circumstances need fox' improved intelligence is so vital to (? interests) of the Empire end India that the Bank may be willing to relax, vheir ordinary/* - 2 - V Z 'such arrangements would be on the lanes of those in the Foreifn Office tgjgggjP to Tetean and ndght inSiude enPoyrrent^ the Bank of ex„ a personnel at to teOT if the Bank agree(s) OTd if so, if you would be good enough to issue complementary instructions to ConsulateGConcerned.^v. p^l OUTWARD TELEGRAM With the Cemplimen of the Under* Secretary of Stat for Foreign Affai [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be ^ i ^ M/i kept under Lock and Key.] W ***) KupJt juk m f c ^ ^[This is 0 o/ ^parficular^ s ec recy and should he ^ retained by the authbldrs e d i-e 6 ip i^nt and not passed on]# ^ ^ U^. “ /EXT '4~t ,E. AvP.^/G M ' ' ' 0 TpA'RP:Er?I.-.L (SECRET). *1*^1 f)&gt;' [Cypher] ^ UeAs t~Jt Yt+J^L kic~l fc. 9”® * ER0i : . i '4l iige; Td tehrak . D. 5 o 50 n.m# 3th June, 1941 262 .StZ' l W’June, 1941 la^. a&gt; fc: h^*^Repeated to India No. 6459 kee^ ' q. , itt a# a. a. a, a. a. a ( L 1 * |M ^ ^ SECRET . tt. Suggestion is now under consideration that, in order i W^vt^to report on, and if possible to obstruct, all German aJL-J activities in Iran (Persia;, we should ^ increase number of British subiects employed by us on political work m Iran; . , o co h j_ n pj_]_-t ra -t3_o n »» more or less on CjUtt/fcisy. «(■ L*. i- ^ in fact have recourse the German model. ' Tycu~ Please telegraph youi 1 views and recommendations on personnel required for this purpose. four report should cover the following points: (a) Should extra personnel be attached to your Legation, or to British Consulates, or should new Consulates be opened? (b) Should British firms trading in Iran be asked to employ extra personnel at His Majesty s Government s expense? If so, which firms? Position of Anglo— kt 'P Iranian Oil Goirroany, United Kingdom Commercial Corporation and Tehran Aircraft Factory is Using considered sepai-ately. (c) Would it Ue possible to start subsidised lorry or bus service (e#g» extension of Nairn Line) between Bagdad and Tehran, or between Tehran and India, or both? (d) Would it be worth while^offering Iranian _ authorities the services of a British cotton expert, or some other expert, on favourable terms or ffee oi charge? (e) If we wish to arrange further infiltration, we might send out a permanent Inspector oi Consular Buildings, language officers, archaeologists, naturalists, etc. Have you any further suggestions \ Would Godard like an English Assistant Director of Antiquities? (f) Could Armenians he usefully employed by ns in Iran? It is understood that many of them, being Iprry owners, are able to circulate moi’e ireely tlimn British subjects. (g) Government of India are being asked^to. consider desirability of sending specially selected pilgrims to Meshed. Do you see any objection? ft* RECo. POL* Mate] HJUN1941 INDIA OFPW!5. I aiu most anxious, as you know, to do, every- thinn- uossilole to counter German activities in Iran, . and J 'feel that the infiltration of suitable personnel on the lines proposed above or on any other lines vou can suggest is a necessary part of any scheme which we. shall be able to devise for this nurpose. *'■ i f jXt&gt; Ext,3217/41 No, of groups 534, Cypher telegram from Secretary of State to Government of India, External Affairs Department, dated 12th June, 1941. XXX HOST SECH3T. ExPOfllANT, 6668 Prom Peel to Caroe through Viceroy's Department. Repeated to Fraser—Tytier, 169. Most secret. It is clear that events of next six months in Middle East may be of critical importance and we have recently been in consultation with Foreign Office on urgent and vital necessity for countering Axis activities in this area. Foreign Office, with a view to thwarting Axis intrigues as far as possible are now urgently investigating steps in Iran to strengthen intelligence and other secret activities largely under guise of commercial intercourse - for example by subsidising British business ventures and by using agents as commercial representatives or advisory experts on German model wherever opportunity occurs. We realise difficulties in pursuing similar policy of infiltration in Afghanistan but we feel that general line to take now should be to seize any opportunity offered by Afghan Government for introducing British subjects into the country and that we should not allow this policy to be limited by considerations of expense or by rigid restriction of our economic activities to area East of Kabul-Kandahar line. We should be grateful if you could consult with D.I.B. and let us have an early expression of your views and any suggestions for accion on above lines. We are glad to see from your telegram No.2613 of 3rd June, which we have taken up with the Foreign Office, that Government of India are already thinking along somewhat similar lines. D.I.B. will no doubt have shown you information from secret sources regarding Axis intrigues with Bose and Faqir of Ipi. Foreign Office are most anxious to be assured that everything possible is being done to deal with situation. In light of above we should be grateful for further information and comments of Government of India in regard to two following cases; (a) Road engineer for Afghan Government (reference Government of India’s Express Letter No.F.141~F/41 of 24th March to Kabul). How does this particular matter stand? On information available at this end it seems to us that Government of India might well have adopted Fraser-Tytler's suggestion that they should find part of pay of Forestry expert and road engineer in order not to lose opportunity offered of introducing British experts into Afghanistan. (b) Helmand Bridge and bridges on Herat-Kandahar road (correspondence ending with Katodon 153 of 16th May). We have not seen full correspondence between Government of India and Kabul regarding Helmand Bridge but it seems that British tender was •touch too high to bo accepted' (see Fraser-Tytler's d.o. letter of ^2nd March to you). In order to prevent this most important contract from going to Germans, did Government of India consider whether it might not have been worth while to subsidise Gammon out of Afghan Fund? As regards other bridges, we recognise importance of strategic considerations, subject to your views on Prime Minister's remark reported in last sentence of Katodon 153. On the other hand Fraser-Tytler reckons that bridges could not possibly be finished before winter of 1942-1943 at earliest and in present emergency we doubt whether there is much to be gainedby taking- too long a viev/ of future developments. As it is gQsduring critical months ahead to intorforo with uoriiian plans in every possible way, would thero not bo much to be said for using the pretext of assisting with these bridges to secure a footing for ourselves and to oust Gorman influence from this important area? It would no doubt be possible without much difficulty to spin out time before and during construction on one excuse or another and local Afghans could be kept sweet by judicious expenditure in right quarters. We should be glad if you would consider matter again from this point of view and let us have your views. (</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3517</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3517</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/106 ‘Persia. Infiltration of British agents.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-06-14T22:05:04</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (52 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 54; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence, some marked Most Secret, discussing ways in which British agents could be deployed in Persia [Iran] and other countries in the region (Iraq, Afghanistan) to counter German influence during the Second World War. The correspondence discusses: how British firms operating in Iran could recruit employees to act as agents; the redeployment and use of existing consular staff in Iran for intelligence purposes; the use of British (or European) engineers on Iranian water irrigation schemes, to counter German influence in that area; the distribution of British propaganda in Iran. The file’s principal correspondents are: the British Ambassador at Tehran, Reader William Bullard; the Foreign Office; the External Affairs Department of the Government of India.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Spies</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Military intelligence</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>