<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002e3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-27T12:14:09.290Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">o O' - ^7 From To jjctt 0 H Officor Comriianding, No. 8 (B N Squaaro.n, Khormaksar, Aden. t ’ , * fc political Agent, liuscat.- 'Copy to A.K.Q.j 'fo^ information). \ A© 24th May, 19 57. 8s/29/l/Air. i c IN TEH COi.m.iAlsL AND BEVELOPUli^lj FLIGHT - 19,^7. ) m, * I have the honour to form- ^e^isWr-e-d- / if L post, keys (3 in number) to the Petrol Store at LA3IRAH ISLaND. These were picked up by the Officer Commanding the Inter Co mand and colonial Development ' Flight, 1937. g, it is requested that you acknowledge receipt of these keys. I have the honour to be Sir, Your obedient Servant, Squadron Leader, Commandin ho. 3 (B) Squadron, q. A. Hhormaksar, _ _ Aden. bONo. 84 / 40- C © Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate Muscat the 24th June 1937. Prom To Sir, Major K.P. watts I.A. Political Agent Sc H.B.M* u Consul Muscat. The Officer, Comziianding Mo. 6 (B) Squadron, Khormaksar, Aden. ( Copj to Air Officer Comi-anding Air forces in Iraq Baghdad. ) Inter Command Development PliMit 1937. iwith reference to your letter No.8S/29/l/Air dated the 24th May 1937 I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of 3 keys to the Petrol Store at Masirah island and to request instructions regarding their disposal, as nothing is mentioned in the letter under reference. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant, Major, Political Agent Sc H.B.M's Consul, Muscat.rv A v. (*~ PTom; - To; - ^ % Late; - vv Ref;- Sub j e ct; - - Store to Royal n retention. The Political Officer, Muscat, Persian Gulf. ■Util July, i§37. 8 4/3 6/15/Air. Petrol Store - Masirah Islands Bequest you hand keys of Masirah petrol Pilot Officer - Adjutant, f o £ Officer Commanding, Ko, P 4 (Bomber) Squadron, Royal Air Force, Shaibah. Copy to A.K.^. , Hinaidi.) C-849/4Q of 1937 Ho Bio Political Agent and His Majesty*» Consul, Muscat presents ixis compliments to I• 1, The Officer Commanding 84(B) Squadron, R.A.F., Shaibah, Basrah. 2. The Air Officer Commanding, British Forces in Iraq, Hinaidi. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the under mentioned document (s) Political Agency and H«B*K* s Consulate Muscat• Bated July. 1957... Reference to preTious correspondence (To i -O. Reference his memorandum No.84/36/l5/Air dated 12.7.37. Description of Enclosure Name and Date Memorandum Ro.C-848/40, dated 28th July 1937, to The N.C.O. in Charge, Royal Axr Force ^est House Muscat. Subject. Petrol Store-Masirah Island.y 2033/557/17/S. 21st August, 1937. R. A.F. Petrol Store - Umm Rasas. It is requested that you will notifj'' this unit as to what action you have taken on the letter dated 2Rth April, 1937, a copy of which is attached. AGU&gt;-k ——^ x' / Squadron Leader, Commanding, No. 203 (^R) Squadron, R.A.P. The Political Agent, Muscat.prom;- Commanding Officer, Ho. 203 (FB) Squadron, at Muscat. To: - The Political Agent, MUSCAT. Date; - 28th April, 1937. H. A# 151 * petrol Itore - TTrnni Rasas. — ■ ■■ * — 1. The Petrol Store at Umm Rasas, opposite the flying boat anchorage, is in need of repair. The foundations are becoming undermined, particularly at the corners, apparently by the action o^ the wind, and the walls are cracking, due to sinking. 2. The Head Man of the village was asked whether he could effect repairs, and he said that the matter must be referred to the WALI. 3. Would you be so good as to enquire whether the WALI will put the repairs in hand.Translation, W From - Saiyid Said bin Taimur To « Shaikh Khamis bin Hilal al-Mij^li After complimenta* Bearers are officers of the British Government, leaving for your side. They will deposit with you some drums containing oil, which We want carefully kept and protected from damage and a receipt given for then. They will also deposit with you a small hoory which We want kept and protected from damage. Further, We have heard that the godown in which oil is stored is partly ruined. We want you to order its owner who receives the rent to have it repaired so that nojri dampness should get through to the oil. Dated 25th Rajah 1356 (2-10-37). Usual Ending. 'f.O. ^ . - \r iX k yU ^ IaAu? L*xa**- u A' f k CK&gt;From ■' j - i No. C// of 191/3? Maj or H. ^ • Ya t tS f ! • A« f Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, To The Officer Coiuiaanding ftOSi/.B.) Squadron, hoyal hir Force, Basrah. British Agency and Consulate. Muscat, the 2^th October igj/Zl. iiovai Air Force retroi, Store- Uaaa Hasas. ^ ^yoaAiugJM. Reference your xnemoranduia No.2o35/b57/i?/b, dated the 2ist August 1937. , 2. X mentioned the matter of the re^lr to the petrol store at UBsa Rasas to His Highness the Sultan on the iirst owortunity after my return to Muscat from recasts in India* His Highness has accordingly issued the necessary instructions to the Sheixh of Masirah, and the letter was despatched by the dhow which conveyed Royal Air Force stores to Massirah Island on the 3rd October 193/* 6i Maj or, political Agent &lt;sc Consul, Muscat* S. G. P. I.—247 P. A. &amp; H. B. M. Consul Muscat—6-12-11. 500.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002e3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/91</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002e3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/91</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 2/15 ANNEX PETROL DUMP &amp; LANDING GROUND AT MASIRAH.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-31T22:03:32</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (13 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 15; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file includes correspondence between Royal Air Force commanders and the Political Agent at Muscat regarding: the deposit of petrol containers; the delivery of three keys to the petrol station at Masirah Island; and the repair to the petrol store at Umm Rasas, in Oman.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Umm Rasas</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Masirah</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002e3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>