<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000003591.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T15:28:19.147Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000003591.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Or 13006</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000003591.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Or 13006</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Compendium of alchemical treatises in Arabic, Persian and Ottoman</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1513/1764</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-12-03T16:42:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">per</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fas</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ota</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. 159+i</extent><extent>Material: PaperDimensions: 215 x 150 mm leaf [168 x 112 mm written]Foliation: British Museum foliation in pencil; Arabic foliation in the purple crayon typical of Lebanese bookdealers of the 19th centuryRuling:
                           Misṭarah; 19 lines per page; vertical spacing 11 lines per 10 cm (ff. 113r-158v: 29 lines per page; vertical spacing 17 lines per 10 cm)Script:
                           Naskhwith
                           nasta‘līqtendencies and some titles in
                           thuluth(ff. 113r-158v:
                           naskh)Scribes: Qudrat Allāh al-Marandī al-Ādharī (ff. 3r-112v) and Muḥammad ibn Sulaymān al-Mawṣilī (ff. 113r-158v)Ink: Black ink, with rubricated, yellow and green headings and overlinings in red (ff. 113r-158v: black)Binding: British Museum bindingCondition: Some worm damage, foxing, and tears towards the fore edge. Folios 19, 21 and 24 have been replaced.Marginalia: Extensive marginal corrections, conjectures, glosses in Arabic and Persian and other evidence of collation and textual study (ff. 113r-158v: very few)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises two manuscripts. The first (ff. 3-112) was the notebook of the Qudrat Allāh al-Marandī al-Ādharī, who copied into it thirteen alchmical texts between 919 AH/AD 1513 and 925 AH/AD 1519, first at Fez and then Damascus (see colophons on ff. 11r, 14r, 57r and 66r). The second (ff. 113r-159v) was copied in the 18th century, beginning with ff. 113r-158r copied in 1177 AH/AD 1764 by Muḥammad ibn Sulaymān al-Mawṣūlī in Algiers (see colophon on f. 158v).The volume contains 16 alchemical texts:Anonymous,
                              Risālah nāfi‘ah fī ghāyat al-naf‘ wa-l-nafāsah lam yu‘raf muṣannifuhā(رسالة نافعة في غاية النفع والنفاسة لم يعرف مصنّفها) (ff. 3r-11r);Khālid ibn Yazīd al-Umawī (خالد بن يزيد الأموي),
                              Risālah li-Abī Hishām al-Amīr Khālid(رسالة لأبي هشام الأمير خالد ) (ff. 11v-14r);al-Ṣafadī, Khalīl ibn Aybak (الصفدي، خليل بن أيبك), Extract from
                              Kitāb al-Ghayth al-musjam fī sharḥ Lāmīyat al-ʿAjam(كتاب الغيث المسجم في شرح لامية العجم) (f. 14r);al-Ṭuġrāʾī, al-Ḥusayn ibn ʿAlī (الطغرائي، الحسين بن علي),
                              Kitāb tarākīb al-anwār(كتاب تراكيب الأنوار) (ff. 14v-57r);Democritus (ذومقراطيس), Untitled alchemical treatise (ff. 57v-66r);Jābir ibn Ḥayyān (جابر بن حيان),
                              Ayn fuṣūl az ba‘z̤ kutub ustaẕ Jābir(اين فصول از بعض كتب أستاذ كبير جابر ) (ff.66v-67v);al-Rāzī, Fakhr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn ʿUmar (الرازي، فخر الدين محمد بن عمر), Selections from
                              Kitāb al-Mulakhkhaṣ(كتاب الملخص) concerning physics (ff. 67v-76b);al-Rāzī, Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn Zakarīyā (الرازي، أبو بكر محمد بن زكريا), Selections from al-Rāzī’s
                              al-Kutub al-Ithná ‘asharah(الكتب الإثنى عشرة) (ff. 77r-91v);Ibn Waḥshīyah, Aḥmad ibn ‘Alī (ابن وحشية، أحمد بن علي), Extracts from
                              Kitāb fī Maʿrifat al-ḥajar(كتاب في معرفة الحجر) (ff. 91b-96b);Anonymous, Excerpts from a commentary on the poem of ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz b. Tammām al-ʿIrāqī (عبد العزيز ابن تمام العراقي) (ff. 96v-98r);Anonymous, Excerpts from a commentary on the alchemical poem
                              Shudhūr al-dhahab(شذور الذهب) (ff. 98r- 110v);al-Sayyid al-Sharīf al-Bukhārī al-Naqshabandī (السيد الشريف البخاري النقشبندي), Excerpts from the
                              Risālah fī al-Ṣināʿah al-falsafīyah(رسالة في الصناعة الفلسفية) (ff. 111r-112r);Anonymous, Cancelled page of Persian alchemical poetry (f. 112v);al-Maṣmūdī, Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad (المصمودي، محمد بن أحمد),
                              Kitāb al-Wāfī fī al-Tadbīr al-kāfī(كتاب الوافي في التدبير الكافي) (ff. 113r-158r);Anonymous, Fragment of a treatise on practical chemistry (f. 159r);Anonymous, Instructions for producing perfumes (f. 159v).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Alchemy--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><subject><topic>Chemistry--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000003591.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>