<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000ff_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T13:44:51.017Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">D.O.No.952-17/28 The 23rd March, 1948 Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No.Ext.2971/47, dated the 2 nd January, 1948, regarding a 16 H.P. Austin Shooting Brake for my office. As I have now been fcble to obtain a 2 shooting Brake from the local agents, I very much regret that I am unable to confirm the order placed by you on the Austin Motor Export Corporation Limited. I am very sorry to have troubled you over this matter, and am grateful for your assistance in the first place. F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., Commonwealth Relations Office London. Copy tos Messrs. Austin Motor Export Corporation, 279-283, Oxford Street, London.. with reference to their letter No.VQIJ/Pm, dated the 24th December, 1947, to the Under Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, London.© —.7 “i l _ HU5TIN MBTyP EXPPBT CnPPBPHTigW LIMITEn (proprietor^: THE AUSTIN MOTOR. COMRANY LTD. BIRMINGHAM) 51 telerhone; MAYFAIR 7620 TELEGRAMS AUSTINETTE. TELEX, LONDON AUSTINETTE LONDON ENGLAND cooes: BENTLEYS PLEASE ADDRESS ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO THE CORPORATION A QUOTE REFERENCE 151 CHAIRMAN .. P LORD MANAOINO DIRECTOR A. C. R WAITC DIRECTORS O W HARRIMAN. A C. HERRING A.O.TOOKEY B J HCGARTY HEAD OFFICE A SHOWROOMS 479 - 48 3 OXFORD ST. LONDON W1 ENGLAND works: LONGBRIDGE BIRMINGHAM 15 OUR REFERENCE (3Lit/4D/teY. YOUR REFERENCE St.764/48. PLEASE REPLY TO LONGBRIOGE WORKS BIRMINGHAM The Under Secretary of State for Commonwealth delations, Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street, Whitehall, LQ-TDON. S.W.l. Dear Sir, SAT' ?&gt;1 j o b i^u) 1/4 2 ^th March, ^ 4C1 - I^DEXEP We thank you for your letter dated the 23 rd March from which we note that you wish to cancel the order for a l6-HP. Shooting Brake for Sir R. Hay, Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf. V/e regret to receive this intelligence but we have complied with your wishes and duly cancelled the order. Yours faithfully, AUSTIN MOTOR EXPORT CORPORATION LIMITED. r A 2/4d) Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office i. » 'r\n\/ ■ I ^7 -ill octoa 'go Externa l Department(B) iux WORD CODE INDEXED FROM : POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN G-ULF D. Bahrain, 16.A5 hours, 22nd March 1948 R. 16.20 hours, 22nd March 1948 A/2 04 .^ telegram _ . ,A 189 dated March 15th. Purchase of Austin shooting Drake. 2 * As new Austin Utility Wagon available locally I nave purchased it. Please disregard my telegram under reference and ask Austin’s to cancel order for shooting brake, o* Reference to my Express letters Nos. 541-30/2 ib ruary 24th and J 01 - 30/19 March 11 t h - disposal of Buick and mouor cycle. lew Delhi have replied that I should refer matter to you. As I have received good offer for Buick I am selling it at once and also motor cycle. No distribution(XA05i2(5/ij His Britan Bahrain.i o (XAO 51 2( 5/U7)) Dear Residency, Please refer to Major Pettiprrew^ nemorandum Ro*l649- 30/19 of the 23rd July, 1947 about the method according to which Government cars were operated under the Government of India rules. As from 1 st April, 1948, we should like your official cars, with the exception of the Head of Mission car allocated to the Political Resident, to be operated according to the Foreign Office Car Code. ix copies of the Circular No. 01*0 (XA 5 /O /1 ( 11 )) of the 1 5th April, 191*6, with enclosures are sent to you herewith for this purpose and we should be grateful if you could circulate them to the Agencies. Six copies of the Chief Clerk 1 s circular No. 052 of the 22 nd KSarch, 1947, are also enclosed for your information. Although special conditions in the Persian Gulf do not admit the application of some of the principles contained in it, at any rate for the present, we should like you to see it as showing our policy at normal posts. Should you see any difficulty in introducing the arrangements set out in the Car Code, could you please let us know and we will see whether any modification is necessary for the Gulf? Unless we hear from you, however, we shall presume that you see no difficulty in its introduction on 1 st April# We propose that no change should be made for the present in the manner in which the Political Resident's car is rur or how the costs are borne. Yours ever, Sstablishment and Organisation Department. His Britannic Majesty's Political Residency, Bahrain.( &amp; U-7b }# j&gt; / ij-L G * T#C# jnd^xhP Political Resident, Bahrain. Government of India, New Delhi. Reference my express letter No.541*36^2 /j/j February 24th. Telegram From To No. A/181. Dated the 11th March, 1948. 2. May sale of Buick please be sanctioned in current financial year. 3. The second-hand motor cycle purchased from Army stocks in 1946 is unserviceable. May its disposal also be sanctioned at best possible price. = REPGU = NO. 701-30/^.14. PERSIAN GOLF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated the 11th March, 1948. Copy forwarded to H.M’s Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, London, with reference to this Residency express l etter No. 541-30 /2 d ated the 24th February, 1948. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.Bxt.72VVt 16th March, 19W /6/j Dear Sirs, With reference to your letter ( 2 / 2 *fl/JH of 9 th iiareh regarding the 16 h*p, shooting brake ordered ty the Political Resident in the Persian Ciulf, the Political ^ Hesident has requested that your bill for the supply of this vehicle may be presented before 50 th .-'arch even if delivery is impossible hy that date* i am to request that the bill may accordingly be forwarded to this Deparfcdent for transmission t-&gt; the i.olitioal Resident* Tours faithfully. ^ K. HARRISON The iUistin iiotor Kxport Corporation, Ltd*, Longbridge Works, Birmingham.' ' -V ^ d) rixf HOWARD TELEGRAM TO COMMOMVS^LTH RELATI(j)|sQ OFFICE tw IT! 7 ALLOTTED TO EXTERNAL DEPARTMENT (B) WORD CODE FROM : POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULP D. BAHREIN, 15.20 hours, 12th March 1948 R. 18.10 hours, 12th March 1948 No. A/1 80. ♦ Your express letter Ext.246/48 dated, J5rd February. Austin shoot brake, 2, Please reguest presentation of bill before • 31st March, even if delivery of car impossible before then. 3. Please let me know as soon as bill received. No distribution.V X 8 •' \ XX S“ r P V\cVXH V&gt;t30K. ” K '\f ’Af HUSTIW NBTHP EXPORT CnBPPPHTIHW LIMITEO (p.RORRieTOR 5 : THE AUSTIN MOTOR COMPANY LTD. BIRMINGHAM) 1 ^- tclcphonc : MAYFAIR 7620 TELEGRAMS AUSTINETTE, TELEX, LONDON AUSTINETTE LONDON ENGLAND COOES : BENTLEYS PLEASE ADDRESS ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO THE CORPORATION l QUOTE REFERENCE tfl L P LORO DEPUTY CHAIRMAN J GIBSON JARVIE DIRECTORS G W HARRIMAN. A C. HERRING A .O.TOOKEY. 0 J. HEOARTY HEAD OFFICE &amp; SHOWROOMS 4 79 - 48 3 OXFORD ST. LONDON W-l ENGLAND works: LONGBRIDGE BIRMINGHAM OUR REFERENCE YOUR REFERENCE CM/4D/JH PLEASE REPLY TO LONGBRIDGE WORKS BIRMINGHAM iJCT. 2 -* 6 /48 . 3 ^ The Under Secretary of State for mw- Commonwealth Relations, /i^Q^Yirr* Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street, Thitehall, LC^DOU. S .77.1. Dear Sirs, ?Te thank you for your letter dated the 4th inst. , with reference to your order for a 16 H.P. Shooting Brake for t e Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. lie regret to state that production of this model has been temporarily suspended owing to the urgency of producing Ambulances. We now fear it will be June at the earliest before we can execute your order for a Shooting Brake for Lt. Colonel W.R.Hay. Yours faithfilly,Z.*4 1 &gt; L£TTliIH. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. _ INDEXED From , REPGU, BAHRAIN. To FOREIGN, NEW DELHI. No.641-30/2. Dated 24th February, 1948. Reference correspondence resting with your Memorandum No.F. 50 -A/ 4 S, dated the 17th June, 1947. 2. As the old Buiek car Is constantly off the road for repairs and is in an uneconomic running con dition, it is requested that sanction to its sale to the best advantage of Government may please be ac- corded as early as possible. = REPGU = The issue of the above has been authorised. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. v Copy to His Majesty^ Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, London, with reference to India Office d.o. letter No.Ext.153 6/47. dated the 24th July, 1947. “ ^9 CSLp £ tf 1 . /fit/i 7 &lt;, &gt;7* /p. ) &amp; *9 fr'Pb ' V 7 ^/ V d) l/U HUSTIN MOTOR EXPORT CDBPDBHTIDN LIMITED ^proprietors : THE AUSTIN MOTOR. COMPANY 11 O. BI PM INC HAM j TELEPHONE; MAYFAIR 7620 TELEGRAMS AUSTINETTE, TELEX, LONDON 'AUSTINETTE LONDON ENGLAND CODES BENTLEYS PLEASE ADDRESS ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO THE CORPORATION &amp; QUOTE REFERENCE Chairman .. P LORO MANAOINO DIRECTOR A C- R WAITE DIRECTORS G W HARRIMAN. A C HERRING A O TOOKEY B J. HEGARTY HEAD OFFICE &amp; SHOWROOMS 479 - 48 3 OXFORD ST. LONDON -W1 ENGLAND WORKS: LONGBRIDGE BIRMINGHAM YOUR REFERENCE u / *4. EXT.14^/48©C s A CiVi/ 4D/d O PLEASE REPLY TO LONGBRIDGE WORKS BIRMINGHAM Tue Ufiaer Secretary oi* State for Coirmonwealth Relations, Commonwealth Relations Office, ^ Downing Street, II^ Whitehall, c &gt;/ ' —■— London.S... »1. rd January,1948. Dear Sirs, We thank you for your letter dated 21st instant regarding a 16HP. Shooting Brake for the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Gn looking into this matter we assume that it refers to a IbHi. Shooting Brake ordered on tne 3 ra June,!&gt;4, ^.y the IndiaX Office over the signature of Mr. Harrison, who also signs the letter to wnich we are now reply ing. We understand that the vehicle is to be snipped to Lt.Col. W.R. Hay, C.S.I., C.I.E. Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrein, and we note that you particularly desire it to be invoiced to you before tne of March next, being tue end of your current financial year. Altnough proauction of this new model is benind scnedule we will endeavour to supply and invoice the car to you towarns the end of March, and it will be snipped unpacked witn right-hand steering and kilo speed ometer . Witn reference to price will you kindly note tuat we reserve tue rignt to invoice the car at the price current on the oate of aespatch, and we snail be pieasea to give you a aiscount of 10 ^ off tne English Retail Selling Price. Yours faithfully, AUSTIN MOTOR EXPORT CORPORATION LTD% (y COPY rOR n:G!'TRATIOM INWARD TELEGRAM ALLOTTUP TO EXTERNAL DEPA RTMENT (B) BN GLAIR r FROM: POLITICAL RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULF / TO: C0MM01R7EALTII RELATIONS OFFICE D. Bahrain 1100 hours, 16th Jan., 1948 R* 0950 hours, 16th Jan., 1948 No•A37 Harrison from Hay, Your letter Ext.1273/47. Austins ' 1 ^ « V # shooting brake for Residencyo Two. Grateful for action to ensure delivery of vehicle and presentation of bill current financial year. Funds will lapse if bill not paid by March 31st. l-bA'*. F.7-AA?. GOVERNMENT OF LNDIA. n a) r~ uu l I I H MINI STRY . , DEPARTMENT OF EXTERNAL AFFAIRS AND COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS. From INDEXED A Delhi (3), the. •rW-t-nl' z: ‘M*-? 4 • \ .kg KTMXKK SECRETARY to the* GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, /| MINISTRY JiEfARTMKST OF EXTERNAL AFFAIRS AND COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS, % To The Under Secretary oT State for Gonunonwealth Relations, King Charles Street, Whitehall, Lond.ofi S.W.I. Subject :■ Cars for consular posts in Persia a 3^T, MW Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with your letter No.Ext.2059A?, dated the 2 nd October 1947, I am directed to forward herewith, for information, a Letter from His I r iajesty T s Consul General ” General for Khorasan No* 1342/V/94 , dated the 2$th October, 1947» 2. Letter to - do - No.F.7-A/47, dated. copy of the marginally noted communications* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedieit servant. for Secretary to the Government of India* lyl \o Copy, with copy of enclosures, forwarded for information to the (1) Ministry of Finance in continuation of this Ministry T s endorsement » dated the loth October 1947 snd with Reference to Finance Ministry 1 s u.o.No.2303-(EA CR)/47, dated the 22nd December 1947, and (2) Accountant General, Central Revenues/Auditor General of India in continuation of this Ministry’s endorsement No.F.7-A/47 dated the Igth.iiitU^r 1947.4 ./ «•••• No.13Wv/94. From Subject British Consulate-General, Meshed 2#th October, 1947c Lt. Colonel E.H* Gastrell, H.M T s Consul-General, Meshed* The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations • Department, New Delhi * Purchase of Cars for Consular Officers in East Iran - Khorasan Consulate-General (including Zahidan Consulate) Sir, I have the honour to refer to the correspondence UGO resting with my tele gram Ho. 997 dated the 9th August 1947 re ; orting the purchase of the vehicles sanctioned in tne Government of I n dia, External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations Department ilemorand um No * F*7-A/47 « dated the 12th abdtx February 1947^ and to state that because all efforts *tT 7 ■ a r± “ct pui'cliast-: Uiem in India at the Indian Government controlled rates were fruitless, the vehicles were obtained in Iran entirely through the good offices of the British Embassy at Tehran, It is further appreciated that His Majesty 1 s Ambassador agreed to clear these four vehicles under his Diplomatic Privilege and that no Persian Customs nor Monopoly tax duty was levied on them. 2. The official Persian Zone prices quoted for delivery at Persian Gulf port at Khorramshahr were as follows (i) For Consulate-General, Meshed* (a) For Consul-General, Meshed One Humber Super Snipe Saloon Car £. 863 / 3/0 or Rials 138,110 (@ 160 to £) (b) For Consul-General, Meshed, instead of Vice-Consul, Meshed/ Birjand (ii) For Zahidan Consulate. (a) For Consul,Zahidan One Villys overland Jeep • Station Wagon @ Rials&gt; 130,000. One Jeep Station Wagon @ Tials 130,000 (b) For Vice-Consul, Zabul/Zahidan totalling Rials 5J#,11Q# 3* The allotment of Rupees 40&gt;000/- would have produced only Rials 393&gt;$00 @ Rials 984-50, the official rate of. exchange - per Rupees 100/- and could net have met the cost. Arrangements were therefore madewith the help of the Imperial Bank of Iran, Meshed to convert this sum of Rupees 40,000/- into Rials at the officially authorised T, Free Market TT R a te of Exchange prevailing and thereby I obtained Rials 503 . 768 . The result^was that there was Gain by Exchange of Rials 109,968 (or Rupees 11,170/- @ Rials 984-50$) which has been credited to the Khorasan Consulate-General Monthly Cash Account for 1st to 14th August 1947 at Item 3 on the receipt side. One Jeep Station Wagon (5 Rials 130,000L m In addition to the actual tlost of trie fo u g_ vehicles landed at port a furthdir *dxpendituife oi ^ial., ^ 20 , 092-40 cents was incurred in the sending,for c ' lia 7 H lt f d brtngin? of them the 1200 miles to ^eshed, J___ to -amaan and 2109 to Zabul viz:- , . i) Transport of Consular and Embassy mot**-' to Khorramshahr, i i ) Subsistence allowance ,to Drivers for the period 11; on §uSy away from headquarters, iii) Salary of temporary drivers engaged ; iv) Incidental charges at the Persian Gulf port on clearance and other small items connected witn r ; their clearance, destination, v) Petrol ana oils used in the vehicles from the port to/ 5. The position is summed up as follows:- Expenditure incurred. . . .. (a] dumber Car” O^3/3/0 credited to Kooros i-ros. London through Monthly Cash Accounts vice items 2 &amp;, 3 for 6 cc ^/1947 respectively converted @ 15 pence to a Rupee and r&gt; • 11 o ono / ^ Rials 984-30 per 100 Rupees Rials 113,3- ) 2-4P (b) Three Jeep Station Wagons @ Rials 130,000 each .... (c) Miscellaneous expenditure vide paragraph 4 ..Rials 390 , 000-00 Rials 2Q«092-4Q Rials 323,3^4-83 or Rupees 53 &gt; 1 / at ' Rials 9^4-50 per 100/- the offical Rate of Exchange of Rupees. There has.been therefore^an^Excess^ of .Rui?ees^1^3^|^/ ■ s^^inst which it i 3 - requested that you wi±l ^ind±y (i) the credit of Rials 109,968 Jor Rupees 11,170 @ Higsl 984-50^) on account of Gain by Exchange (v^ae p©.i agr^ph 3 above) to be utilised and (ii) that remaining Rupees 1995/3/- may be adjusted from the Savings under C • 5• T, 0ther Charger- Maintenances Grant of Truck and Lorry under hhorasam Consulate-General budget grants for the year 194/-48 which shows a saving of Rupees 3,496/8/- on the 14 th August 1947 when the accounts were closed vide instructions contained in simx y enclosure to the Government of India, Expres s -Letter No.F.19£-A/4 7, dated the 17 th July, 1947 q _ I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- E.,H, Gastrell, 0 O 0F.^-a/L.7- GOVERNMENT'OF INDIA. OF EXTERNAL AFFAIRS AND COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS. j K 31XA Ijl j * A'ew (5), the 1^4^ /From The UNDER SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, - v Department of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations, II ISTRY .^cxxxxxxxx To His Britannic Majesty^ Consul General for Khorasan, M e s h e d» Furchase of cara for eoasular officers in the East Iran* Sir, With reference to your letter No*1342/V/94 t dated the 26th October 1947, I am directed to oay that, in continuation of paragraph 2 of the memorandum from the late External AXTairs Department No.F. 7-A/47, dated tne 12th February 1947, the Governor General is pleased to accord ex post facto sanction to the additional expenditure of a $.13 ,165/8/- vide details iven in the margin already incurred on Consul General Meshed* Consul General Headed instead of Vice-Consul, Meshed/BIrj and• 1 Humber Super Snipe* the purchase of a car Saloon Car at Rials | 1133G2.45. One Willy*s overland Jeep Station Wagon &amp; Rials 130,0u0 for His Majesty’s General, Consul^ Meshed and a jeep station wagon each Consul Eahidan - do - ♦for His Majesty’s f Vice Consul Sabul/Etiu-hidan - do - ♦Consul, Zahidan, Vice Miscellaneous expenditure Total Rials 20092.40 523394.85 » ♦Consul Zabul and Vice- t or Rs* 53,165-8-0 ♦Consul Birjand. They t Deduct Amount sanctioned RS* 40,QUO—0—0 ♦regret that they cannot Excess expenditure Rs. 13 . 165 - 8-0 t —*agree to tne credit of Rials 109,968 (or Jd.11,170) on account of gain by exchange referred to in paragraph 3 of the letter under reply being utilised towards the above expenditure as it is against the rules to 'utilise such.receipts to cover expenditure* A Government• moiety of the expenditure will be borne by His Majesty I have the honour to be, Sir, Your isost obedient servant, s Unuer Secretary to the Government of India*&amp; /f p f. @&gt; Outward Telegram from Commonwealth Relations Office EXTERNAL department Ext*2907/47 EN CLaIR 2k* POLITICAL RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULP. (Sent 00.45 a.m. 10th Jan., 1948) No.70 Your d.o. letter 2183-30/20 of 17th October. Travelling allowances. Your proposals approved. 2 . Your express letter 2182030/19 of 17th October. Cars should be maintained in accordance with Government of India until end of current financial year, after which Foreign Office rules will apply. Copy to: Foreign Office A. G • Mr. J.M. Fisher. Mr. Kordik.V * I iiw/ J«ii :Vfe&gt; rnsmn'iovoO Copy No. 45 - 20/3 (§) British Consulate, Khorramshahr. Dated the 20th Novemher, 1947« \ ^Dear Finance Department, We.forward herewith copies q£ the marRi nally 1. Telegram No.110 dated 8.9.1947 to Foreignmoted New Delhi from H.M. Consul, Khorramshahr. Jccrre^nnaenoe 2. Telegram No.9463 dated 11.11.1947 from • )regarding ^/Foreign, New Delhi to H.M. Consul.Khorramshahr. )the refund customs duty to the buyer of the old Buick car, which is self explanatory. 2. We shall be grateful if you will kindly sanction the refund of the sum of Rials, 22025/- telegraphically as this case has been pending since a long time and the buyer has been worrying us for an early settlement. Yours ever, . CONSULATE The Finance Department, Foreign Office, LONDON.(Copy) Copy of telegram No. 9486 dated the 11th November 1947 from Foreign, Nev/ Delhi to H.M. Consul y Khorramshahr repeated to Political Resident, Bahrain and High Commissioner for India, London» Your telegram 110 September 7th. Refund customs duty to buyer old Buick car. Please refer the matter His Majesty’s Government. If they sanction refund Government of India will meet their share by debit to accounting India through His Majesty’s Government.r EX*! r - .0 date3‘ the 8 th September, Khorranishahr to Foreign, i / \ Reference your memorandum F.267/A/46 January 20th to Repgu Bahrain. Buick car was sold to local merchant for 2 Rials. 56500 equivalent of Rs. 5738/14 and proceeds credited to Govt, in 6 uriTreasury account for February. At the time of sale buyer was given surety car was free of customs duty. After lengthy correspondence with Persian Govt, it has now been decided by authorities concerned that we must pay customs duty of Rials. 22025/- equivalent of Rs. 2237/3. I shall therefore be grateful for refund of Rs. 2237/3 to buyer. 2. As Governiaent of India Treasury has been abolished arrangements should be made to send rupee draft in my favour at very early date.f* * HU 5 TIN MBTBP EXPOBT CPPPgBHTiaW LIMITED 31 RRORRICTORC THE AUSTIN MOTOR COMPANY LTD. BIRMINGHAM TCLtPMONE; MAYFAIR 7620 TELEGRAMS AUSTINETTE, TELEX, LONDON AUSTINETTE LONDON ENGLAND cooes : BENTLEYS PLEASE ADDRESS ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO the CORPORATION i QUOTE REFERENCE L. P LORO MANAOINO DIRECTOR A C R WAITE &lt;STI3. A O. TOOKEV O J HEOARTY OUR REFERENCE VGW/PM HEAD OFTICE &amp; SHOWROOMS 479 - 48 3 OXFORD ST. LONDON W1 ENGLAND works: LO NGBRIDGE BIRMINGHAM YOUR REFERENCE m t T281374 i ICE PLEASE REPLY TO LONGBRIDGE WORKS BIRMINGHAM 24th December, 19^-7• Under Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street, London, S.V/.l * ^ Dear Sir, L* —s\ O -*• !*1 */ 19 //e aoknov/ledge receipt of your letter dated the 13th instant and have booked an order for one 16 HP Shooting Brake to be shipped to: C. J. Felly, Esq., O.B.E., The Agency, Bahrein. The prices quoted are as follows Ex Works £565. 0. 0. Less 1Q$ Diplomatic Rebate £ 5o« 10. 0 . £ 508 . 10 . 0 . Plus C.I.F. Charges Unpacked Bahrein £ 69 . 0. 0 . £577. 10. 0. The above are subject to any variation which • may occur up to the date of delivery. We will endeavour to effect delivery within 4/6 weeks of receiving remittance covering the pur chase of the vehicle. Yours faithfully, THE AUSTIN M0TQ/ EXPORT CCRPORATION LTD., / -D.O. No.*?/.? -17/28. * \ INDEXED EXT ■&gt; ' '1 &lt;— K^L ^ 3 POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. The 26th November, 1947. In addition to a car for this Agency, the Government of India sanctioned the provision of a station wagon or truck. The latter has not yet been ordered, but I should now be grateful if, as you did for the Residency, you would ask the Austin Motor &lt; Company, Limited, Longbrldge, Birmingham, to supply me with one Austin Sixteen 'Shooting Brake', and if you could have it shipped to me in Bahrain. I should also be grateful if you could ask the firm to give the usual 10 per cent diplomatic discount. 2 . I hope this will not be too much trouble for you. R.I* Hallows, Esq., C/o Commonwealth Relations Office, King Charles Street, WHITEHALL, London.Application of certain Foreign oervice xiegulations to the Persian Gkilf Recently two instances have occurred which have made it necessary to consider whether certain Foreign Office Regulations should be applied tq the Persian G-ulf as soon as possible and not at the time of the Foreign Office assumption of responsibility next April, The Regulations in question are those governing the maintenance of motor-cars and the drawing of travelling allowances, As the ministerial staff in the Persian Gulf posts is on deputa tion from the Government of India and the Government of Pakistan, it is clear that they will have to be paid their allowances in accordance with the old Government of India Rules, or according to any new ones made by the Goverrment of India or Pakistan. With the superior officers the case is complicated by some of the officers being on contract to the C.R.O. (subsequently to the Foreign Office) while others are or will be career Foreign Servants. Colonel Hay, in his letter at flag A, has suggested that officers might be allowed to draw travelling allowances under the Indian Rules until 1st April next, thus giving time both for ary anomalies in the Foreign Service Regulations to be noticed and for the officers themselves to study the new Regulations. The P.R. stresses that this procedure should only apply to journeys on tour and that for U.K. leave, first appointment and termination of service, the Foreign Office Rules should apply. Tne arguments in support of this contention may be summarised as follows: (a) Auditing. The Accountant-CJeneral, Central Revenues, is responsible for auditing the Persian Gulf accounts and if Foreign Service Regulations are introduced now, he will have to be furnished with copies of them and given an agreed date from which the accounts of certain officers should be dealth with according to the F.S. Rules. As it is doubtful whether this could.be arranged by the end of the year, the advantages of introducing a new system for a few months only seem rather uncertain. (b) The clerical staff in the different Agencies and in the Indian Treasuries in the Gulf would also have to accustomthemselves to new regulations, and at the same time maintain a dual accounting system. (c) The Foreign Office will presumably between now and 1st April, 1948, have to review the entire system of allowances payable to superior officers in the G-ulf, e.g. the G-ulf posts will have to be included in the Foreign Office List of unhealthy stations and permission granted for paid recessing for approved periods and at approved stations, etc. The Foreign Service Regulation No.7 - Travelling Allowances • is simple in application and need only be considered in the present connection in relation to journeys on tour. Under Section 8 the payment of the fare of the officer, and, in certain cases, his servant, is envisaged and under Section 10 a subsistence allowance is granted to meet the expenses of food and sleeping accomnodation when not included in the fare. This subsistence allowance is 'at the rate in force 1 * at the time for the country or countries in question. The Government of India Rules are rather more complicated, making as they do provision for railway journeys which will not be normally obtain in the Gulf. The Regulations applicable are:- a conveyance or horse allowance (when specially sanctioned by the Govemident of India), a mileage allowance, a daily allowance or the actual cost of travelling. Without going into details the principle behind them is that an officer receives either double the cost of the fare for himself and party, or else an allowance to cover incidentals when transport is provided by the State. As far as the maintenance of motor-cars is concerned, the Government of India principle is that an individual officer receives a motor-car on charge, pays its running expenses and is reimbursed for the journeys for which he uses it on the public service. The Foreign Uffice system is to make an allocation of motor vehicles to the Head of a Mission, who then assigns them to his subordinates who pay at a fixed mileage rate for using the vehicle for pleasure, but its petrol, maintenance, etc. is provided free. (The Foreign Office Car Code is at flag C and the Government of India Rules at flag L). /A possibleA possible solution would be in the case of:- (a) Travelling Allowances . To apply the Foreign Service Regulations for journeys outside the G-ulf in the case of officers serving on contract and to maintain the Government of India Rules for officers touring within the Gulf area. Admittedly an anomaly will occur in the cases of career Foreign Servants, but if they are to draw their local advances of pay from the Indian Treasuries it will be better for their claims for travelling allowances to be submitted in accordance with Government of India Rules, and ihE different entitlements (i.e. Government of India as against Foreign Service Rules) to be adjusted at the presentation of the last India Office Budget. As far as I can discover, the Foreign Office fix subsistence rates in accordance with local conditions, and they will have to decide tnese rates either on the evidence supplied by tais Office (i.e. on the basis of allowances already sanctioned by the Government of India;, or by despatching an officer to the Gulf to inspect and to report. A solution of this point is of some imnediate importance, as all officers, career or contract, will presumably be required to do some tours between now and April 1st, 1948. (b) Motor-cars . The Indian Gar Code might be maintained until April 1st, 1948, when presumably all vehicles in the Gulf will come under the Foreign Office Car Pool in matters of maintenance and supply. The Political Resident refers to the Foreign Service Regulation No.7, paragraph 3(a), laying down that he must obtain the authority of the Secretary of State before going on tour. I think this matter need only be taken up with the Foreign Office il it is decided to apply Foreign Service Regulations en bloc during the current year. (Sgd.)A.H. Reed, 26 / 10 . This question is to sane extent connected with the general question of payment of officers and auditing arrangements, papers regarding which are now with A.G. /FromFrom the administrative point of view I think the simplest solution would be (1) In regard to cars, to maintain the G-overnment of India Code until next April, when it should be replaced by the Foreign Office Car Code. (2) In regard to travelling allowances generally to accept the proposals in Sir R. Hay’s letter of 17th October. This arrangement would be the most convenient from the practical point of view though on the other hand the Foreign Office might see some difficulty in agreeing that Indian rules should be applied to Foreign Servants. On the financial side it seems likely to work out to the advantage of the political officers concerned and the Treasury might querry this, but it would be pointed out to them that it is only the continuance of previous practice and in any case the only practical arrangement. * It will be necessary to obtain the agreement of the Treasury and Foreign Office to Sir R. Hay's proposals in his letter of 1?th October. If you agree, we could write enclosing a copy and making the best case on the lines above. Alternatively it might be quickest to call a meeting, having previously circulated copies of Sir R. Hey* s letter. For ary comments, please. (Sgd.) F.A.R. Harrison, I am inclined to agree with Mr. Harrison on both points, but the Treasury may be sticky about Travelling Allowances. I had a similar question in regard to Lord Mountbatten's special staff in India and after some fruitless discussion, the Treasury decided that their won rules should apply. The arguments put forward by Mr. Hallows (which did not exist in the case of the special staff) may, however, induce them to agree. Incidentally the Travelling Allowance Rules in the C.S.R. have long been out of date except /forfor civilians paid from Arn^y estimates. Their place has been taken bry the Supplementary Rules issued by the Government of India under the Fundamental Rules. The Record Department should have a copy. (Sgd.) R.S. Brown, 3/11.•«.* H/q, £U^EIGN OFFICE, 8, Carlton House Terrace, S.W. i. 27th September, 19U7. /^74 ' ^'“T Dear Harrison, I am sorry there has been such a delay in replying to Donaldson’s letter to Gardener, Ext* 1628/1+7 of the 12th August regarding which Car Code should be used in'the Persian Gulf. I take it that the official cars will principally be used by those officers who have accepted a contract with His Majesty’s Government under the terms of your telegrams Nos.9123 and 9340 of the 16 th and 20 th July respectively 'to the Political Kesident. As you may remember the second telegram set out our conditions of service which will now presumably have replaced the former rules under which these officers operated. We agree the refore that their transport system should also be operated according-to Foreig n Office rules as from the date of the change-over. It is of course for you to decide which Car Code sh ould apply but we shall undoubtedly - apply the Foreign uri'ice uode with effect from the 1st April next. Yours sincerely, (J. Mi Fisher) F. A. K. Harrison, Esq.., Commonwealth Relations Office, King Charles Street.Commoruvealth Relations Office, King Charles Street, Y/hit ehall, S. W. 1. Optober, 19V7- Sir, I am directed to refer to Government of India letter NO.F.7-AA7 of 21st April, 1947 and connected correspondence about the provision of vehicles for consular posts in Persia and the Persian Gulf. t 2# His Majesty* s Government in the United Kingdom agree to bear a moiety of the cost incurred up to 15th August, 1947 in respect of the provision of vehicles for all the posts mentioned in paragraph 1 of the Government of India* s letter under reference, but since His Majesty* s Government have a continuing interest only in Khorramshahr, Meshed and Bushire, they are unable to accept any share in expenditure at posts other thin those incurred cater 13th August, 1947* 3. I am to add that His Majesty* s Government wish the arrangements for the purchase of vehicles for Bahrein, Kuwait, Muscat and the Trucial Coast to stand, and to confirm that His Majesty*s,Government, will bear their cost. 4, Copies of this letter arc being sent to the Government of Paid.stan and the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. I an, Sir, Your obedient Servant, K. HARRISON The Secretary, Ministry of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations, Government of India.(11178) Wt.21321/P.248 6,000 (2 sorts) 7/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 1 It ts requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S. W'M. P. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.WA.0 In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. XA 051 / 3 l|K 20 a( 5 / 47 ) and address— not to any person by name Z05~9 Foreign OFFfcE. S.W.1. 22nd SepteniDcr, 1947* but to— ** The Under-Secretary of SI Foreign Office. .^-*Eondon, S.W.l. Sir I om directed t&gt;y Mr. Secretary Be vin to refer to your letter of 2 nd June BXT969/47 regarding the nromsion of transport tov consular posts in Persia. 2 . With regard to the division of expenditure on vehicles between the Government of India and His Majesty’s Government, I am to say that it is agreed that costs should be divided in respeco of ro-QiT’smsh ihr, Meshed and Bushire, but that His Majesty s Government is unable to accept any share in expenditure at the remaining posts after 15th August, ‘5 ; 47&gt; i.e. the date on which the Government of India ceases to represent His Majesty’s Government at these posts. 3 . jt is also agreed that arrangements for the purchase of vehicles for Bahrein, Muscat, T.uwait and the Trvicial Coast may stand. 4. These proposals have the approval of the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty s Treasury* I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant The Under-Seeretar Commonwealth HeINDIA OFFICE, P.Z. WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. I. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State in Council ,to enclose, for the information of the Government of India, a copy of a letter from the Foreign Oliice regarding the appointment of for at 2. I am to enquire whether any objection is seen to this appointment and am to request that, if there is no objection, it may be recognised by the Government of India. 3. If it is considered that there may be any objection to the appointment, the Secretary of State would be glad to be informed by telegraph at the earliest possible date.(xa 051 / 3 UK 20 a( 3 A 7 ) ) i^Ok-ilGXi OFFICE, EX1 a f Carlton House Terrace, ■&gt; • ; i • 1 • lith Au*jiust f 15&amp;7* tsar llltfliin. i lease see a letter addressed to tile Foreign CfTice by the India OiTi e, their re^erenee m• 969/U7 of 2nd uime, and copied to the rroaeury* ““ ,l111 It concerns a oevensaent ojl India proposal that the cost or supplying a nuzober 01 vehicles ^hioh they have sanctioned ror certain consular posts in Persia should be shared between India and United Kingdom revenues according to hitherto existing arrangements* The foreign orrioa is asked whether it conours in the proposal* The posts concerned *nd the vehiclee authorised are as lollops / \ iUiorratshar (one 2k/30 b*p* Baloon Car) Eanaan (one station wagon) Bandar bbas* (two trucks 4 x U# 8 cwt*} Meshed (on 24/30 h«£* saloon ear) ahldan ^abul Birjand Bashirs on 1 21^/30 h*£* r one station wagon) one station wagon) one station wagon- one car or station wagon) V Our view is that as we are only taking over Khorraiashar, ashed and Buaftire, we should agree to fiv&gt; proposed division ol coots for those three posts, but that we can scarcely promise to share the cost of care for the romolning posts which we shall not take over if the expenditure ie incurred after 13th August-, 1947# l*e«, the date on which the Jovemaent of -India ceaeea to represent His Majesty's oovenssent at at these posts* i^ention is also zaade of five Persian &lt; uir posts on the itrab Shore, the administrative anc rinanei &gt;a responsibility for which is to be entirely taken over by His Majesty's oovement as fros 1st ^ril, 1947* C»H* ^lliraaa, dsoi*. Thm/ \rha Oovarnasat or India hava already sanotioaed the purchase oT vehicles for these posts, aucL the India omoe propose that the arran&amp;araents should be allowed to stand, provided that the b'orel^n cfries and Treasury concur# This applies tot The i erslan Otar Reside my Bahrein (one station-wagon) Jhe Political Agent, Muscat (one oar) * ' Bahrein (one (Jar and one truck) * * * * Kuwait (one car j The Political Officer, 'racial ;oast- (one pick-up trade} ^ x v r sun ably the cost of transport for these posts should be borne on the India office Vote, wo do not therefore feel that we are In a position to criticise the requirements# .'Aay we have your views on these two proposals? Yours sincerely. (3,a # Yore ton)MM IWARD“ T f~e&gt;( faAPUujt^. BAM “ jk^plmo x+© EXT ' ^.M/a plotted to Extern al PeDartmajat^ - -(H ^ '13369o Frou. To B^tptd*to Dated Received Government of India* External Affair's and Commonwealth. Relations Department* political Resident in the Persian Oulf Secretary of State for India* New Delhi * 22.30 hours* 1st August* 1947* 12U05 hours* 2nd August* 1947. /tea Tour telegram A/5Q2 2 8ndjL^ e ^, 3 a e ®? e |l?h '** of State for India, Eo^dS^a^el-egram 5n8^2§tb July. Please see our telegram No^O? of 26th Ju.-j to India Office repeated to you and India Of i telegram Ho. 9606 of _mbJu^alao jepeatedtoyou air mail regarding aeparate Indian Brit. fooo ^7 by air mail regarding separav* Consular representation in Febiuary ah* accorded in our memo No*P7-A/47_ _da^ed Ig^D ^ 1 1947 in respect of pro^iil^n^f vehicle for Kerman Sd B^der A^bas Consulate should now be considered imperative* i»the appointment of 2 . I am to enquire whether any objection is seen to this appointment and am to request that, if there is no objection, it may be recognised by the Government of India. 3. If it is considered that there may be any objection to the appointment, the Secretary of State would be glad to be informed by telegraph at the earliest possible date. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Foreign Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Government of India. 500 11.30i ;ra r- p V .Lifcwir x From INDEXED The Hon f hie the Political Hesider. in the Persian Gulf, Baurain. To 1* ■» M. The Secretary of State for India, India Office, London. 1 emorandura No .1649-£0/19. Dated Bahrain, the 2crd July, 1947. Keference paragraph 4 oi Government of India memorandum No.F.jd***A/47 dated the 12th February, 1947, a copy of which was forwarded to you under Government ox -India memorandum W O.F.7-A/47 dated tne 21st April, 194 7. 2. The Government of India have since instructed that proposals for the sanction of maintenance grants for the cars sanctioned for the Residency and for tne agencies at Bahrain', J uscat and Kuwait should he submitted to His .ajesty's Government in accordance with your telegram no.7378 dated tne 7t h June . 1947, addressed Government of ' India and reueated to me. Before making proposals, instructions are requested d-fr-f to whether the cars are to be maintained in accordance with the Foreign Office car code, or in accordance with the Government or India rules of 1912 (Finance Department Ho.^50 S.A. dated the 15th July, 1912) a copy of which is enclosed. Political iresident in the Persian Gulf. SV/A&lt; Copy to ; _l• political ii^ent, iiuscat, v/ith reference to this Residency memorandam 30 .665-30/19 aated the 20th : arch, 1947 • 2• Tne political Agent, Kuwait, with reference to this Residency memorandum ho.655-30/19 dated the 20th .arch. 1947. • ’ 3. Tne Political .agent, Banrain, with reference to this residency memorandum jo.668-30/19 dated the 21st arch t 194 /'« \ — ■■ for guidance.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Finance Department Simla, the 15th July, 1912. •r RESOLUTIO N. The Government of India have, for some time, had' under consiueration the question of framing rules to regulate (a) the purchase and maintenance of motor cars supplied at the public expense for the use of Government officials other than heads of provinces and administrations, and (b) the grant, of travelling allowance to officers using such cars. The matter was referred to a departmental committee 5 and other careful consideration of the Committee's report the Government of India, with the approval of the Secretary of State, are pleased to issue the rules appended to this resolution for the information and guidance of local Governments and Administrations. 2. The Government of India have decided not to lay down any general rules on the following points until some experience has been gained of the operation of the rules now published ( 1 ) the insurance of cars; ( 2 ) tne valuation of cars on change of incumbents; (3) the submission of periodical reports of the mileage run by a car, as compared with the mileage for/Which travelling allowance is claimed, as a check on any excessive use for private purposes: (4) tne regulation of the grant of conveyance allowance to officers to whom cars are supplied at the public expense, mainly for use at head-quarters.-Hales for expense fo: provinces. I.- Th« Government State. Su very stron perfoi mci a car: and a Local Go’ necessity : II.- Th&lt; car which ] expense * - (i) Ho possess thi Government (ii) A ; use of the apply only no case sh; others for (iii) Che by the Gov( below, the shall bear regards amt continued t (u) The j i ] c Note ns .50 or ai provided tt connection entitled tc charges on setting up (b) rU Vi C (iv) The careful silj car. nil c ’‘minor ’ 1 rep reported tc frame detai on such rep damage whic careless ha will be for this respon enforced at rest upon oAPPENDIX 'Hales for the purchase and maintenance of motor cars at the public expense for the use of Government officers other than Heads of provinces• I.- The supply of a motor car at the public expense to a Government officer requires the previous sanction of the Secretary of State. Such supply will be allowed only in exceptional cases and on very str ong grounds. It is not sufficient to show merely that the perfoi mce of an officer^ duties will be facilitated by the grant of a car: and, in submitting a recommendation to the Government of India, a Local Government or Administration should clearly Justify the necessity for the supply. II.- The following are the conditions governing the use of a motor car which has been supplied to a Government officer at the public expense :- (i) No person shall be permitted to drive the car who does not possess the certificate of qualification prescribed by the Local Government for the purposes of these rules. (ii) A Local Government may permit the officer to make a reasonable use of the car for private purposes. • Such permission will, however, apply only to ordinary movements within the officer's station; and in no case shall the car be used on long runs foi? recreation or lent to others for private use. (iii) Charges for the maintenance and upkeep of the car will be borne by the Government and by the officer respectively, in the manner indicated below, the general principle^being that the officer using the car shall bear tnose of its running expenses which are largely uepenuent as regards amount on carefulness or management and which affect the continued efficiency of the car ;- (a) The officer using the car shall pay the cost of petrol, tyre renewals, manor repairs and renewals, lubricants and illumi- nants, as well as all occasional storage charges and all petty charges incurred otherwise than at the periodical overhauling and annual varnishing of the car. Not©:- Minor repairs and renewals are those which cost less than xiS.30 or are not connected with the prescribed periodical overhauling provided that if a new component costing more than Rs.15 is used in connection with a minor repair or renewal, the officer shall be entitled to charge to Government its actual cost but not any workshop charges on account of the examination of the defective car and the setting up of the new-part. (b) All other charges shall be paid by the Government, including wages of chauffeur and cleaner, the cost of uniform of the chauffeur, and all charges incurred in connection with the annual varnishing and the periodical overhauling. (iv) The officer will be expected to bestow the same amount of careful supervision on the car as he would do in the case of his private car. All cases of damage or accident involving reeairs (other than 'minor' repairs) or involving claims by third parties must be promptly reported to the controlling authority. Local Governments will further frame detailed rules as to the authority which may sanction expenditure on such repairs. The Oxi.icer will be held personally responsible for any damage ^nich nay 00 caused to the car by negligence, or by rough or caieless handling or by accident due to these or similar causes. It be foi txie Local Government to determine in each instance how f^r this responsibility shall be enforced. A similar liability to be' enforced at the discretion of the Local Government in each case will rest upon officers in respect of third party claims„ III. • • • • •- 2 - I EXT-; rposes III.- Controlling officers will take steps to see that t rules are generally observed. If in any case it is found t privilege of the reasonable use of the motor car for privat is systematically abused or any.of the other rules is constifcntly infringed, the matter should be reported to the Local Government which will take v such disciplinary action against tne officer concerned as it—considers desirable and may deprive him of the use of the car. le above {9=“ IV.- Each Local Government will maintain a register of the mileage run from month to month by the various cars supplied to officers under its control and will, for this purpose, obtain a monthly report from the officers concerned, showing the readings of the milometers attached to trie cars. Vo- The travelling allowance of an officer to whom a motor car is supplied under these rules vail be regulated by the ordinary rules in part XI of the Civil Service Regulations and not by special rule 1(h) under Article 9S9 of those Regulations, provided that - (a) If an officer travels more tnan twenty miles by Government motor car in a day, he will draw for the first twenty miles the mileage allowance ordinarily admissible unuer the regulations ana for the remainder three-fourths of the mileage allowance so admissiole; (b) if a journey by Government motor car is combined with a road journey by ordinary conveyance, the officer so travelling will draw the mileage allowance ordinarily admissible for the first twenty miles or for the portion of the journey performed by ordinary conveyance, whichever is greater, and for the remainder three-fourths of the mileage allowance so admissible; (c) if a journey by roaa, wholly or partly by trie motor car, is combined with a journey by rail or steamer, the officer so . _travelling will draw the allowances admissible under article 1065 (iii) of the Civil Service Regulations modified in respect of the roud journey, whether made by the mtor car or otherwise, with reference to rules 5(a) and 5 (b) of these rules; (d) the travelling allowance of chauffeurs will continue to be regulated by rule I(j) under Article 999 of the Civil Service Regulations. VI.- Officers to whom at the date on which these rules come into force motor cars have been already supplied at Government expense will continue to use them on the existing terms and Subject to the provisions of rule 1(h)'under Article 999 of the Civil Service Regulations, until the cars now used by them have been worn out. The use of new cars supplied after such date to such officers will be regulated strictly in accordance with the rules nov/ promulgated.OUTWARD TELEGRAM External Department &lt;&gt; From OYHDSR (O.YoPc) Secretary of State for India To Government of jjndia, Ocinmonwealth Hei^ioina Sc Sxtemal Affairs Department Repeated to Political Resident in tb.e Persian Gulf Despatched 17 o 30 hours* 7th June 1947 IMPORTANT a—T.IWlI HH II / «*- &gt;MMHI » No &gt;7S78 e S^GRKT My predecessor*a Despatch External Wool dated 4th March and your Secretaries letter dated SOth April Noo 15HBPG/47• Persian Gulf administration^ 2. H.M.G. agree that 1st April 1947 should he regarded as date from ishieh transfer of control becomes effective? but since J.K 0 revenues will bear cost of administration Political Resident's budget as well as proposals for additional expenditurec, re-appropriations* etc* will require my sanction which P*Re should now seek direct (with copy go Government of India) instead of through Government of India, 5o It would seem appropriate that formal announcement should be made by Political Resident to all the Rulers notifying change which has taken effect, • please telegraph if you concur in draft /text/r: text contained in my ixjsiiediately foil owing* telegram* ✓ 4 0 HoM 0 Go gratefully accept Govemment of India’s willingtioss tc continue to maintain st&amp;lf and JberriceB as HofeUG-J'a agents on the ^ unde^stending detailed in. paragraph 5 of Grichtcfii’s ' Xettero Question of transferring subordinate staff is being separately examined* 6 * H»M.Go note Government of India’s desire to establish Indian Consulate at Bahrein but feel some difficulty in reaching conclusion until relationship of India to British Commonwealth and future status of Indian nationals can be more, clearly defined* (In any case li.M* ’s exequatur could not be issued in favour of a British subject holding tae King’s Commission)*, Meanwhile H*M.G. would welcome further indication of Govexnment of India’s intentions regarding scope of proposed Consul’s functions in relation to Indian nationals^ ©eg* would they expect that Indian Consul would exercise in respect cf Indians extra-territorial jurisdiction conceded by the Sheikh to the British Crown? If notj&gt; could not Indian interests in Bahrein be equally well supervised by officer designated Trade Agent* whose appointment would not raise difficulties regarding Treaty position and influence cf Political Agent which were seen by Government of India themselves in relation to proposed IKS*, Consulate? (see Government of India telegrams No®3556 dated 5th May 1943 and No*4865 dated 26th April 1944* KoM®G® are glad to note Government of India’s willingness to transfer buildings end movable property not required for Indian representative at an agreed valuation and look forward to receiving list of property available for transfer in due course* — /Copies to; -OUTWARD TELEGRAM Cioi to &gt;us7 A3BtcUS ? 8c US.for Bu.rfna 0 Asst*Us, for- Burma, PSoto ss« PS.to US. PS.to Parly.US LVo Turnbull. Mr. Joyceo Reeldent Clerk, tot- Foreign Office (Hr. Pyrnan'o (Mr. * Treasury (Mr. Helsby). 14* of w« (Mr. Barker) 9 Gardener).&lt; iji f w- o -vr - \y[ Copy of Memorandum Jo,F.265-A/46, dated the 12th April 1947 from the Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Afiaigjifl Dep'^tmisftjt to His Britannic Majesty’s Gpnsul GenersfL fogXT Khorasan, Meshed. $102^4 Subject:- Maintenance gfant fqr Cwt. Chevrolet trubk. .supfrjJtgd to 1 H.M.’s Consul at Zahidan. Reference your express letter No. HcT\ H37-A/62 dated the 30th September 1946. 2. Sanction is accorded to the continuance for a further period of one year with efiect from the 1st March 1947 of the maintenance grant of Hs.3,500/- p.a. for the truck supplied to His Majesty's Consul, Zahidan. A provision of Rs.3,500/- has been included as a fresh charge in the budget estimates of the Zahidan Consulate for 1947-48. o • • • •F3?om Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* To Secretary of State for India* Repeated to Government of India, External Affairs &amp; Comnonwealth Relations Dept. Dated Bahrein hours, 22nd July 1947* Received 03»40 hours, 23rd July, 1947* Reference External Affaire and Commonwealth Relations Department letter So. P7 A/47 April 21 st&lt;&gt; 2« Grateful for information as to ■whether in changed conditions sanction for purchase of car and truck for KERMAN and BANDER ABBAS Consulate and BUSHIRE Vice-Consulate is still effective* 3* An order has been placed for car for RUSHBiK Vice-Consulate but no order luis b^en placed for car and truck for KERMAN and BANDER ABBAS Consulate*Draft Letter Form B. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State in Council to enclose, for the information of the Government of India, a copy of a letter from the Foreign Office regarding the appointment of as at 2. I am to enquire whether any objection is seen to this appointment and am to request that, if there is no objection, it may be recognised by the Government of India. 3. If it is considered that there may be any objection to the appointment, the Secretary of State would be glad to be informed by telegraph at the earliest possible date. 1 am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Foreign Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Government of India. 500 11.30FILE COPY D.O.No.1568-30/27^ 1 ' / ^ tXf PERSIAN GUL BAI IDENCY, The 10th July, 1947. ftiArt is^ (loA Will you please refer to the correspondence resting with my demi-official ^25^ letter No.889-30/2 dated the 16th April, 1947, oiTUie subject or Hurntrer 'Euper Snipev ' 2 . I now enclose cop ies of the 1. Telegram No.98-A/Camp/46 dated ) marginally noted the 17th April,1946, from ) correspondence, Foreign, New Delhi. ) and should be 2. Residency Express Letter ) grateful if the No.1050-30/2 dated 5-5-47. ) sanction of His 3. Lemorandum NO.F.50-A/46 ) Majesty*s Govern- dated 17-6-1947 from the ) ment could be Government of India, New Delhi ) conveyed for the 'retention of the Buick until the arrival of the Austin 16 H.P. Shooting Brake — in this connection please see your letter No.Exl. 1 O / a m j ^ — — - - —- — — k?-. da ted the 14th June 19477 to Hay. F. A. K. Harrison, Esquire, India office, LONDON. 3V/AG.T.C Telegram G.T.C. From Government of India, Simla. To Political Resident, Bushire No.98A/Camp/46. Dated 17th received 18th April, 1946. Your telegram No.551 April 6 th. 2. Government of India sanction replacement of Political Resident«s car by purchase of new Humber 12 , 000 /- at cost not exceeding Rs. *1200. Your proposal for disposal of present car should be made to them again when new car arrives. S. Expenditure should definitely be met from current year’s grant. FOREIGN * as signalledCopy of Express Letter No• 1050 *-2072 dated the 5th Liay, 1947, from the Politicar'-lnrsj'deht ih the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, to the Government of India, New Delhi, Reference your telegram No.98A/Camp/46, April 17th, 1946, Supply of car for use of the Political Resident. 2, The new Humber car has arrived and has been taken into use. 3. Regarding disposal of the Buick car it is requested that sanction of the Government of India be conveyed for the retention of this car until the arrival of the station-wagon purchase of which was sanctioned by the Government of India under External Affairs Department memorandum No.F.7-A/47 of February 12th 1947, If this proposal is approved the expenditure on the maintenance of txhe Buick will be met from within the sanctioned grant of the Residency under Head 'B-5 Other Charges - Maintenance of Motor Cars”.Copy of memorandum NO.F.50-A/46 dated the 17th June, 1947, from the Under Secretary to the Government of India, Department of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations, New Delhi S-, to the Hon'ble the Political ResJjient .dja^tfoe Persian Gulf, Bahrain, EXT r -• 1 fl Subject : Retention of the old Buick caiV 'j Reference your express letter No,1050-30/2, dated the 5th May 1947. 2. As the expenditure on the maintenance of the old Buick car will be debited to the Bahrain Residency budget and will be borne in full by His Majesty s Government o in view of the assumption of direct control of the political administration in the Arab States of the Persian Gulf by them with effect from the 1st April 1947, it is requested that His Majesty's Government may be approached direct with regard to the proposal contained in the express letter under reference. SWAV- •&gt;. HU5TIN MBTQB EXPOBT CaPPaPHTiaN LIMITEQ (PROPR.ETOR5 THF AUSTIN MOTOI^ COMPANY LTD. BIRMINGHAM) HEAD OFFICE &amp; SHOWROOMS 479 * 483 OXFORD ST. LONDON W1 ENGLAND WORKS: LONGBRIDGE BIRMINGHAM YOUR REFERENCE LONGBRIDGE WORKS BIRMINGHAM ip 4 The Hinder Secretary of State for India, India Office, Whitehall, London. S.W.l . 19 th June, tXT ,1 3 a I9&lt;^&gt; )\* i’ Dear Sirs, We thank you for your letter dated 14th instant, ordering one 16KP. Shooting Brake for H.M. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. We nave nad much pleasure in booking your firm order, and confirm the remarks contained in our letter of the 10 th instant, regarding delivery wjciGxi we stateo. tnat it would probabj-j oe early in 1948, before we courd allot a car. Yours faithfully, AUSTIN MOTOR EXPORT CORPORATION LIMITED. fo X. ufi1273/47 !? 4 June, 1947 /leraen, I am directed to acknowledge iPeceipt of your letter reference MSD/lCW 10th June, regarding the supply of an Austin 16 h«p» Shooting drrice for H.M. Political heeident in the Persian Gulf, and to confins the order. I am. Gentlemen, Tour obedient Servant, F. A ^ U APRISON The Austin Itotor Export Corporation Ltd., 479-4#3 Oxford St., W.1.y- Ext, 1195 A 7 3rd June, 1947 Gentlemen, I am directed to state that H.IL Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has requested that an order should be placed with your Company for the supply of one Austin 16 h.p. Shooting Brake. Bj asks if you could arrange for it to be shipped to him at the following address: tit. Colonel W.R. Hay, C.S.I., C.I.E., Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrein, Persian Gulf. at as early a date as possible. The Brake is required as an official vehicle, and I am to enquire whether your Company would be prepared to give an official or diplomatic discount. Payment will be made in due course by Colonel Hay direct. Would you kindly state whether you will be able to provide the vehicle requested and if so at what da.e delivery may be expected. I am. Gentlemen, 9 Tour obedient Servant, F. A. K. HARRISON The Austin Motor Co. Ltd., Longbrid-e, Birmingham.J Td.Tvfo.: 'Whitehall 1234 Your Reference fh f ft TREASURY CHAMBERS. 11 GREAT GEORGE STREET, LONDON, S.W.l. 12th June, 19L7, Treasury Reference X«. J?*..i.4;Q/Q4:.. Dear Donaldson, T-vthank you for sending me a copy of you r letter to the Under Sec retary of Stt.^e, Foreign Off ice, dated 2nd ‘iQA7 j ahnn-h -t-Vio oupply r&gt;-p ^o-r^, ^ for consular posts in Persia and state that we are in agreement with the proposal you make. Yours sincerely. E*P. Donaldson, Esq. , India Office.!)? Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. 1947. yA D.O. No. 1166-30/19 ^DEXEl ' I 4-C^y ^,1119 IS\ UVv Please refer to Government of India's letter No. F.7-a/ 47 dated the 21st April, 1947, paragraph 2, on the subject of cars for Consular posts in Persia and the Persian Gulf.. / 2 . I should be most grateful if you could order on A. behalf of this Residency one Austin 16 Shooting Brake from The Austin Motor Co., Ltd., Longbridge, Birmingham, and if you could arrange for it to be shipped to me in Bahrain. I am reluctant to bother with this chore, but feel that you are in a position to get more expeditious delivery than the Austin agents here. 3. I should also appreciate it if the firm could be asked to give same 10$ Diplomatic Discount as was allowed by Rootes on my Humber - vide your letter EXT.6556/46 dated 30th September, 1946. / !/V' i'Al A F.A.K., Harrison Esquire, India Office, London*DRAFT LETTER Ext, 969/k7 © The Under Secretary of State, ^ ^ Foreign Office, ItA****' ^ S.W.l. \ Sir, X? I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to the correspondence /h r ll**** &gt;■ £}hu*( resting with Foreign. Offiee/ letter No,K2268 9 /265/ 234 dated 22nd January, 194^, about the supply of cars for consular posts in Persia and to forward a copy of a letter from the Government of India dated the 21st April, 2, It will be seen that the Government of India have sanctioned the supply of vehicles to the consular posts in Persia mentioned in paragraph 1 of their letter and propose^ that the cost should be shared between Indian and U.K, revenues * according to the hitherto existing arrangements for the division of diplomatic and consular expenditure in Persia, I am to enquire whether the^Fareign icuij: concur) in this proposal,5 3* With regard to the positfon the Arab Shore r of the Persian Gulf referred to in paragraph 2 of the Government of India* s letter, the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs will be aware that expenditure in respect of the Persian Gulf Residency and of Koweit icr shared between H.M* and the Government of India, while the Government of India v -V have hitherto borne the entire cost of the Political Agencies at Bahrein and Muscat and of the post of the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, The Government of India have now agreed, in principle, that/responsibility for the adminictmtion -ef these ^xjsts should be taken over by H.M.G# as from 1st April ^1947• ^ Lord Lis towel would, hnweyar, propose that the arrangements for the purchase of vehicles sanctioned by the Government of India should stand* It will follow that H,M,G« will bear the cost involved and that the vehicles $ Ju i/s u themselves will be taii&gt;wu turw yp H.M,G, r J * ^^3 /£ 4t- * *~ CM ' ^ ‘' u *' 4. A cony of this letter is being sent to the Treasuiy. x etc. E f. COHAIOSOMr 'i Please see the Government of India 1 s letter of 21st April below. The posts for which the Government of India have sanctioned the provision of vehicles fall into two categories:- (1) The consular posts in Persia, and (2) The posts under the Political Resident on the Arab Coast of the Gulf. As regards (l), the Government of India are apparently content that the cost of the vehicles should be shared in accordance with the existing arrangement for the division of diplomatic and consular expenditure in Persia* As regards (2), it’has now been agreed with the Government of India that the administrative responsibility for these posts and the expenditure involved in running them Should be transferred from the Government of India to H.M.G. as from 1st April 1947• H.M.G. will therefore have to meet the entire cost of the vehicles unless they wish to-oell thorn baelc %e the Government of InliaJOn the assumption that the purchase of the vehicles is necessary, which there seems to be no reason to question, the best course seems to be to allow the purchase of the vehicles to go forward and for H.M.G. to bear the cost. This will fall on the India Office vote. Agreement of the Treasury as well as of the Foreign Office will, however, be necessary. 0/40 1947 &lt;4 A draft letter to the Foreign Office is submitted. 9 (xrrM^r .N0.P.7-V47. i- &lt;A 4“ ‘t From H\3 mVo ui.miM* mil Hb «rv?4 n /•# To The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, The Under Secretary of state for India, India Office, London. Dated New Delhi 3, the 2 . 1 ^ April 1947. Subject:- Cars for consular posts in Persia and the Persian Gulf. Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with ,0 f/'vO the express letter from the India Office No.Ext089/46, dated the 24th October 1S46, I am directed to enclose a ^ copy of the marginally noted communications for information and with Memo, to the Hon’ble the Political ixesfaenfin the Persian Gulf No.F.7-A/47, dated the 12th February, 1947. ^ e 5°. to His Britannic Majesty's Consul 7, dated the 2 . General for Khorasan No.F.7-A/4 12th February, 1947 3. Memo, to the Hon'ble the Political Resident Mar£h e Gul ' 1: No « g »'i , -A/47, dated the 5th the request that the concurrence of His fl/kjesty's Government to bear a moiety of expenditure on the provision of vehicles sanctioned for the following posts in respect of which expenditure is shared equally by His Majesty's Government and the Government of India according to the present arrangement for diplomatic and consular expenditure, be obtained and communicated to the Government of India at an early date:- Khoramshahr Consulate Kerman Consulate Bandar Abbas Consulate Meshed Consulate General Lahidan Consulate Babul Vice-Consulate Birjand Vice-Consulate Bushire Consulate- 2 - V - In this connection a reference is Invited to the concluding sentence of Col. Burnett's demi-official letter to Harrison I o/4fNo i P.40(5)-M.E./45, dated the 17th July, 1945 and para 3 of Harrison's demi-official letter to Pyman of Foreign Office No.Bit.3617/45, dated the 21st August, 1945. 2. The vehichles sanctioned by the Government of India for Persian Gulf fiesidency at Bahrain, Political Agents, Muscat, Bahrain and Kuwait and the Political Officer, Trucial Coast will no doubt be taken over by His Majesty's Government in view of the proposed transfer of the administration of the Persian Gulf on the Arab coast from the Government of India to His Majesty's Government. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. 15/4/47 cOo NT) From - The Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, To - The Hon 1 tie the Political &gt; /• Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum No.F.7-A/47. Dated New Delhi 3, the 12th February, 1947. Subject:- Cars for Agencies and Consulates. Reference correspondence ending with this Department express letter No.F.7-A/47, dated the 26th January, 1947. 2. Sanction is accorded to the supply of following vehicles at Government expense to the consular officers in the Persian Gulf and the officers on the Arab coast of the Persian Gulf at a cost not exceeding As.10,000/- in the case of a car or a station wagon and As.7,000/- for a truck:- Consul, Khorramshahr One 24/30 h.p. saloon car. Consul, Kerman Persian Gulf Residency •••• Bandar Abbas Consulate • • • • Political Agent, Muscat ... Political Agent, Bahrain .. Political Agent, Kuwait ... One station wagon. One station wagon. Two trucks 6 Cwt„, 4x4 (Morris or Humber) One car. One car and one Truck One car. Political Officer, Trucial Coast One’Pickup truck' 3. A provison of Rs.68,000/- to meet the expenditure on the purchase of the above vehicles has been made as a fresh charge in the budget estimates of the various posts for the next financial year. 4. The above mentioned vehicles will be maintained according to the rules appended to the Resolution of the Government of India in the Finance Department No.250 External Affairs, dated the 15th July, 1912. Proposals for the fixation of maintenance grant for these vehicles in the light of these rules should be submitted to the Government of India in due course for their sanction. The/,- 2 - / * . 5. The officers concerned may be directed to initiat their own arrangements ior the purchase of vehicles in each case subject to the monetary limits prescribed in para. 2 above. /■&gt; 8d/-(P.N. Krishnaswamy) Under Secretary to the Government of India. Copy lorwarded to the Finance Department ior comnunication to the Accountant General, Central Revenue 2 . The sanction has been given with the concurrence of the Finance Department vide their U.C. No.332/F.0.(EA)/47 dated the 7th February, 1947. By order, etc., Sd/-(P.N. Krishnaswamy) Under Secretary to the Government of India.* (sLaa, H&amp;j From - The Under Secretary to the Government oi' India in the External Affairs Department, To - His Britannic Majesty’s Consul Genexal for Khorasan, Meshed. Memorandum No.F. 7-r»/47. Dated New Delhi 3, the 12th February, 1947. Subject:- Cars f or Consular officers y r\ ftefer-nce correspondence ending wit^ your telegram No.21, dated the 24th January, 1947. 2. Sanction is accorded to the supply of following vehicles at Government expense to the consular officers 0 / in Persia at a cost not exceeding Rs.l0 f 00/- per car or station wagon:- Consul General, Meshed ... One 24/30 h.p. saloon car. Consul, ^ahidan ... One station wagon. Vice-Consul, ^ahidary/abul One station wagon with reinforced springs. Vice-Consul, Meshed/Birjand One station wagon. 3. A provision of Bs.40,000/- to meet the expenditure on the purchase of the above vehicles has been included in the buget estimates of the next financial year - Bs.20,000/- under Khorasan Consulate General and Hs.20,000/- under Zahidan Consulate. 4. The above mentioned vehicles will be maintained according to the rules appended to the Resolution of the Government of India in the Finance Department Mo.250 External Affairs Department, dated the 15th July 1912 (copy enclosed). Proposals ior^jrie fixation of maintenance grant for these vehicles in the light of these rules should be submitted to the Government of India in due course for their sanction. 5. It is requested that steps may be taken to iHfciafc initiate arrangements for the purchase of the vehicles by the officers themselves subject to the monetary limit prescribed in para. 2 above. On/ . i n- 2 - Cn the arrival oi the vehicles, the two Chevrolet 4 trucks supplied free oi cost by the British Embassy, Tehran, for the use of the Consul General and the Vice. Consul, Zabul may be returned to the Embassy. 3d/-P.N. Krishnaswamy) Under Secretary to the Government of India. Copy forwarded to the Finance Department xor communi- cation to the Accountant Genersl, Central Revenue. 2. The sanction has been given with the concurrence of the Finance Department vide their u.o. no. 332/F0(EA)/47 dated the 7th February, 1947. By order, etc., 3d/-(P.N. Krishnaswamy) Under Secretary to the Government of India.From - Thp Under Secretary to the Government ol India in the External Affairs Department, To - The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum No. F,7-a/47 Dated New Delhi 3, the 5th March, 1947. Subject;- Vehicle for Bushire Consulate. Reference correspondence resting with your express letter No.286-30/19, dated the 3rd February, 1947. The Government of India are pleased to accord sanction to the supply at Government expense of a car or a station wagon to the Consul Bushire, at a cost not exceeding Rs.l0,000/- (Rupee ten thousand only). The expenditure involved on this account should be 3 met by reappropriation as far as possible and any portion that cannot be so met may be included in the statement of Savings and Excesses. The vehicle should be maintained according to the 4 rules appended to the Resolution of the Government of India in the Finance Department No.250 External Affairs, dated the 15th July, 1912 (copy enclosed). The proposal for the fixation of maintenance grant for the vehicles in the light of these rules should be submitted to the Government of India in due course for their sanction. 5. Arrangements for the purchase of the vehicle may be made by the Consul, Bushire, himself subject to the monetary limit prescribed in para. 2 above. Sd/-(P.N. Krishnaswamy) Under Secretary to the Government of India.© 6 . Sanction is th^r^for* 3 alac requested to [Maintenance grant at the following rates for the current financial year 1946-47, for which a statement of details of estiraateri expenditure is also attached:* Muscat . ... fo. 2*000/- Ker roan ... 7, o00/ - Bushire ... Fi.6,400/- Bfforts will be made to meet as much of the expenditure involved as possible from the sanction^ budget grant for the cur}- nt financial year and the balance vhich cannot b* so met will be included in our statement of savings and excesses to be submitted to the Government i India in Nov tuber nojft.' - RBPGU - The issue of the above has been authorised, Sd/- Illegible Secretary to the Political Resident in the J Barsian Gulf,EXT Dated t r 'T'otT’‘ay» i946 ' ?rQm To Lt.Ggl. W. His Britannic JLL ill)an f 1 • P• o• f ajGonsu 1, The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire. Bubiect: Maintenance grant for the Consulate J Truck at Ke.ni.n. Sir, I have the honour to refer to yo r telagrau No,V 456 dated the 16th March, 1946, and to fa ward herewith detailed estimates for the maintenance of the 15 cwt. truck supplied fO£ the use of this Qonsailate* 2. The estimates have been prepared on the basis of actual expenditure incurred in maintaining the truck since its arrival here in Juno test, 3. The roads in this consular area are in a very bad state of repair andthe war and tear of both tyres and tubes and machine parts has been very great, bince the Kamo sax handed over charge to the local government, the roads have not been maintained at all. A trip to Yezd and back involves a distance of 468 miles and tours to other outposts of this consular district involve equally long distances on bad roads. This will explain my estimates of a minimum of Es. 2,300/- towards cost of spare pa 'ts an ! 'yres ar.d tubes. 4. A sum of Bs.1,300/- has been as tin at xift awards cost i of petrol and oil on a basis of 48 gallons of petrol and 7 litres of oil per month. This allows for a tour to fezd once in two months only. Another important factor is that the cost of pe trol he-c ii about 70% higher then elsewhere, as Kenaan has no bulk storage facilities. 5. The cinema van driver here is being paid at Rials. 2,800/- per month and this is also idle minimum rate as paid bv the Umbassv. I have estimated a sum of Fi.3,700/- towards the pay of driver and his daily allowance when touring out side the station. Any reduction in this item of expenditure is not possible as it is impossible to get a driver on less pay- . 6 . The maximum economy possible has been exercised in making the estima te and I request that the Government ofIndia be approached to sanction MiQ t of h. 7,500/- for the maintenance of : t^-« 0 omiulate truck from June, 1945, when it was receivec hare* I have etc. Sd.R.Gr.xxlban. H.B.ir s Consul, Kerman.IARMY EQUIPMENT BRANCH, Any further communication on this subject should De addressed to— The Under Secretary of State for India, Department, India Office, f~&lt; London, S.W.l, and the ioHowing reference quoted:— 10116il5/ARIb Telephone :— Whitehall 8140. I.Q.-jExt. No.- Telegra lieta dum, London. Mr. Booth. jyQEXED External Affairs Dept., . Olarcnoe Houoo. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S. W.\ .2. January, 1947. XT P6 19+ 7 Reference your note attached, I have today received a letter from the Ministry of Supply on this subject, and am attaching a copy of this letter (Ref.12/Overseas 1132 dated 31.12.46.) for your information. It will be seen from the explanation given that the Buicks are being retained in use and consequently are not now available for disposal. 7GC It is considered most unfortunate that^Minlstry of Supply was not aware of the true position of the cars in the first instance, but in view of the explanation given it does not seem that this matter can be pursued further.Room 2005, (oft Thames House South# Our Reference 12/Overseas 1132 Ministry of Supply, Your ' 10116/12/AR1(B) Millbank, S.W.I. 31st December, 1946. Dear Sirs, Provision of Motor Vehicles for Eastern Persian C o nsulates .'' I refer to your letter of October 23rd last. Our Disposals Mission in the Middle East have now advised us of the present position in respect of vehicles at Shaiba, Iraq, earmarked for offer to the Government of India for use by the above Consulates. Since our latest communication, the matter has been referred by the Disposals Mission to the Bagdad Office, who have mentioned details of available vehicles to the political Resident, Bahrein and have invited him to inspect and select any he considers suitable for the requirements of the Government of India. It has transpired, apparently, in the course of correspondence that no Saloon Gars are actually available for disposal, the two mentioned in our previous letter being still in use and not included in surplus declarations. The matter has apparently resolved itself into a direct transaction between the Bagdad Outstation and the Government of India representative and it is evidently thought that it can safely be left to these representatives to settle details. Yours Faithfully, P. S0UTH7.ELL O.D.2.4 G , A • *4 yWUMM UL D.O. Ko. 1X65 - S. T P£FSIAK GULF BAHRAIN, the 17th Ajecenber 9 1946, My dear Harrison, *111 you please refer to your express letter No, text•7089/46, dated the 24th November, 1946, to Foreign, with a copy to us, about a car for the Political resident ? £. «e at once took the matter up with Disposals Mission, Cairo. In reply to a telegram of ours of November 8th, Mitchell telegraphed us on November 18th that Disposals Office, Baghdad, would tell us when we were to send a representative to view the cars, ^e then telegraphed to Disposals, Baghdad, asking them to wire us when the represen tative should go. There the matter rested till the 10th of this month when, in answer to sn urgent reminder to Disposals, Baghdad, we got a curt telegram to the effect that there were no buicks available, We have since received from them a list of vehicles available, consisting almost exclusively of hesvy duty vehicles, none of which are of any interest to us; no mention is made of the Rulcks, 3. In the circumstances, there appears no alternative but to pursue the Humber Super-Snipe again, although Colonel Hay does not consider it up to the standard required for a Residency car especially as the Petroleum Concessions, Limited, representative here, to quote one Instance, Is pro vided by his Company with a Pullman limousine Humber, From Footes letter tc you No, JGC/Vt? of the 4th r ovember, 1946, it appears that this order is still registered with them. I should be grateful if you could have this confirmed and could also endeavour to get a firm delivery dste from them. 4. be cannot help feeling somewhat aggrieved that the Bulcks should have apparently been sold in this way above our heads. If you agree, perhaps you would consider representing the facts to the inistry of Supply and sug gesting that they should inquire into their fate, 5. X am sending a copy of this letter to Duke, Yours sincerely, Sd. C. J. Pelly F. A, K, Harrison, esquire, India Office, London,from To lo.F.70-1/46* Tho Soorotary to tho OoTepnment of Indio In tho Srtornol Affairs hopartnant, His Britannie Majosty's Ambassador XxtraordInary and Flonipotontii TEHRAN (Illl H G '46 Dat«4 H«v Dalhi 3, th« II IU~ Daoambar 1946. Subjaett- Taking oaar by Gorernment of Station Wagon auppliad to Col. Oastrall. Tour Bxcallanay, With rafaranea to tha Enbassy'a danl-official lattar Mo.3/361/46, datad tha Slat October 1946 which has bean treated as official, I an directed to convey tha sanation of tha Goveraaent of India to tho taking over by than of tha Station Wagon of It. Col. K.M.Gastrell, O.B.S., at tho doproclatod value of Rs. 6,600/- approved by your Excellency. Tha Govarnnant of India also approve of tho sale of tha Station Wagon at Rials 60,000 which should be eraditod in full to tha Govarnnant of India account with the Treasury Officer, Tehran. Tha anount of Rs. 6,600/- referred to above and tha expenditure of Rials 8,179-40 incurred on minor repairs to tha Station wagon before Its sale should be debit ed to tha head '36-External Affalr*-B-Charges on account ef Diplomatic and Consular Services in Irsn-Brltlsh Embassy Tehran - B.6-Other Charges.' Tha Accountant General, Central Revenues is being asked to pass the eredlt to the extent of Rs. 6,600 to the Controller of Mllitdry Accounts concerned and to adjust it against the Embassy's grant under the above mentioned Sub-head. The sun of Rs. 1,404/- being the difference between the orlglanl cost of the station wagon and Its depreciated value will be refundable by Cel. Gastrell to the Accountant General,Central Revenues. I have the honour to be, Excellency* s Your/most obedient servant, $d/- PeNeKrishnaswaay. for Secretary to the Government of India*| UtfiS O 4 'V' I V ' •f ^ c h a J Copy foywoy4o4 to Lt# Col# l*H#Oastoollt 0^1#1#| vltli tho roquost that ho may kindly yofttad th# aaount of Ha #1,404/- at anwrly data to tho Aoooontant Oonoral, Contyal Hevenuoa, vho would pass the e rod it to tho Controllor of Military Aocounta OoMomod* gyxfrttraxtfai^ % Copy forwarded to the Finance Department for communica* tion to the Accountant General f Central Revenues in continuation of this Department endorsement HO.F.70-A/46, dated the 10th May 1946. The credit for the amount of Rs. 6,600/- should bo passed on to the Controller of Military Accounts concerned and expenditure adjusted against the budget of the Tehran Embassy under 'SS-B.A-B-Charges on account of Diplomatic and Consular Services in Iran — B* 6 —Other Charges*. Similarly the refund of Rs.1,404/- when made by Col. Gastrell should be passed on to the Controller of Military Accounts, concerned. 2. The sanOAion has been given with the concurrence of the Finance Department vide their U.O.Ho. dated the 1713/FO (EA)/ 22nd 1946. November * By order, etc., Sd/- P.N.Krishnaswamy. Under Secretary to the Government of India.i icv no ^ S s' / ^ Personal from Hay for G-alloway repeated vYeightmaru^.— Reference enclosure to India Office expres^ letter Ext.?o8&gt;^^^. of October 24th^ Disposal of venicles at Shaiba. 2. Rootes unaole to deliver Super Snipe Humber ordered for Residency till next year and there is ^ ^ ^ ^ little prospect of its reaching Bahrain before JuneT' In circumstances if G-overnment of India agree I should like to purchase instead one of the two^Buic:&lt; Straight Eight De Luxe saloons reported as in excellent condition at Shaiba, !&gt;fr If you see no objection please ask Tandy to talce first opportunity of verifying condition^ of ^ ^ r r ^ ^ these cars and if possible to ascertain their price. /// ^Our Ref: 12/0* Seas/1132. Your Ref: 10116/7/AR.1(b) MINISTRY OP SUPPLY, 0.D.2, Room 2005, Thames House South, Millbank, S.W.l. 9th October, 1946. Dear Sirs, _^ • * * &lt; I refer to our letter of July 19th last, and I am now able to give you more definite information about availability of vehicles needed to meet the requirements of the Eastern Persian Consulates. I understand from our Disposals Mission in the Middle East that certain vehicles at Shaiba, Iraq, have now been selected for offer to the India Office. They are not exactly identical with your requirements, however, the position being as follows:- Station Wagons. None available for immediate use, but 10 Morris H.P.Pick-Ups (SIC) in good condition are available instead. Saloon Cars. 2 Buick Straight Eight De Luxe 30 H.P. are available in excellent condition. Other saloons would require overhaul. 8 cwt. &amp; 15 cwt. Trucks. Suitable vehicles in good condition earmarked in Chevrolet, Ford, Bedford, or Morris. Many of these are available if they should be required in place of Station Wagons or Cars. India Office, Army Equipment Branch, Whitehall, London,S.W.l. /It.It is suggested- that representatives of the consulates should be asked to view, and select suitable vehicles, since most of the places where they are required are within 2k hours travelling distance of Shaiba. Matters will be further simplified if you will write direct to the British Stores Disposals Mission, Forest Hills, Sharia Walda Pasha, Cairo. (Col.F.Mitchell) indicating your views on the above proposal, and nominating representatives in ^‘Sia who would undertake the selection. The representatives could then contact the Mission's Out Station at Shaiba, which would be responsible for the final transaction. Yours faithfully, (Sgd.) P.SouthwellARM! EQUIPMENT BRANCH, Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State for India, Department, India Office, London, S.W. and the following reference quoted :— \ 10H6/11/AR1B Telephone :— ' Whitehall 8140. I.O. Ext. No, T elegrams &lt;, Retaxanuum, London. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.l. External Department, India Office. (it October, 1946. /% 3* ^ *d’' 0 A _v, £ hJ* Vehicles for Eastern Persian Consulates. A copy of Ministry of Supply letter 12/0*seas/1132 dated 9#10.46 is passed to you for information. It is considered that if you have not already arranged the procurement of vehicles for the Consulates, you may wish to make use of those offered in the attached letter. //&gt; You will observe that although the vehicles are “second-hand' they are reported as being in good condition. Before acknowledging the Ministry of Supply letter it would be appreciated if you will inform me whether or not you intend to pursue the matter further with the British Stores Disposals Mission, Forest Hills, Sharia Walda Pasha, Cairo. - im flu m Z m station wagons. This matter may please t&gt;e e 9 Ui£uiii%#d with w ▼iew to keeping 'down the requirentnt of vehioles to the minimus# T ♦ 5 # , The GeYernnent of India hare also decided that the r ehioles to be supplieq weald be maintained according to the Rules appended to their Finance Deptt# Resolution No. aaO-E./u, dated the 15th July 1912# THE MSUh OF THE sBOTE «A 8 aUThavIai^. * * ^ * * 3d/f F.N. Krishnaswamyt 11 Uhder Secretary to the Gort.of India# Copy, with enclosurV,' forwarded to His Britannic Maje8ty 9 s Consul General for Khoranan with the request tliat CrOYermient of India may please be informed whether cars and station wagons if offered for sale by Agents of the General Rotors Ltd,, at Bahrein will be acceptable to hist and the consular officers in his juriediotion# ***** ♦»»* * 9 * t * fi V ♦ * ^ + t e * a t • « * * 1 A l * + A 4- 4 * ♦ t rsj k ♦ » * * «»«♦ *«*♦» * ♦ #,•*»*• »»♦* ♦ .) 6 ?:C D jE COPY. s 2&lt;Y tyvoO A cortex iW . -*^‘S ^ u ^ | S/ S 43 JN.j F.166-A/45. By air y&amp;LU Thf llnaor Secretary to the Oort, of India in thjjb External Affaire Department, Hie Britannic Majesty*e Consul General for Khoraean, Meshed. Mated Simla, the 7th September 1946. Subjects* Care for consular poets in Fereia# Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with your dead official letter Ho. 624-V/94, dated the 35rd May 1.46 ahich has been treated as official referenoe» 1 am directed to say thkt the Goremment of India hare decided that the motor transport to be provided to their consular officers in Persia and the Persian Gulf diould be imdrtkined according to the Bulee appended to the Government of India, Finance Department Resolution NO.250-&amp;.A. dated the 15th July 1912. The Chevrolet trucks supplied free of cost by the British Embassy. Tehran to you and Vice-Consul, Zabul eould therefor# be rruiintainea according to these rules and para. 1 of the External Affairs Department letter No. F. 155-A/46, dated the 28th March 1946 should accordingly be considered to have been modified to this extent. I m also to convey the sanction of the Government of India to an expenditure of B». l,200/« being incurred on the purchaae cf a new set of tyres and a new battery for each of the two trucks mentioned above. The expenditure of k. 2,400/- should be Diet from within the •anctioned buuget ailotm nt for the current financial year. If, at the time of regular supply of vehicles to you and the Vice-Consul, ^abul, these tyres and batteries are atill serviceable, they should be rmmoti freau these vehicles and used further for new vehicles. I have the honour to be. Sir. Your most obedient servant, SQ/- P.N. Krishnaswamy, Under Secretary to the Gcr erment of India. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARV'S letter N °. DATE RECEIVED 66 11 : 0-9-1946cf^Wl (cx (E) xt^02l/kS &lt;1 fy'tr sjfd July, 1%6. v ill you please refer to paragrarii 4 of say letter No. :xt.^4.5CV46 ^ of 9th July on the subject of vehicles for consular posts In it’ersia? _i/_- V / n i 1 e nclose a copy of a demi-official letter from the Foreign Office No,X/'5K/3^/20(a)2) from which it appears that they will accept the res.onaIbility of 16th July. ) for obtaining the vehicles for he Ackiitional CojibuI for / Indian Affairs at Tehran. 3.h.Kapur Ssq « 9 External Affairs Departo^snt, (&gt;ovemment of India, New Delhi. toar9 ^^ARMSOM. Foreign Office, London, S.VV.l 18th July 1946. (XA5K/34/20a( 2)) A r ' Dear Harrison, Thank you for your letter Ext,4150/46 of the 29th June, We have not heard a word from the Embassy about an additional truck and station wagon to be added to their pool, but we have written asking them to give us the information we shall require before we get Treasury sanction for the extra vehicles. We shall be happy to do all we can to help them get the vehicles. Meantime the additional Consul for Indian Affairs will be entitled to draw on the existing pool for his needs. Yours ever. F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.July 1946. Jet. 415QA6. ^e«A {'ix^AAX V ill you xiloajBo vei'or to your d«o« latter $&lt;&gt;• l mi55/^/k5 of the 3rd June 1%6 # cm the mibjoct of voliioleR for oonsidar poets in Perciaff ’This !iris oroBaed our licproBs Letter Ho* Sxfe* 332iiA^ ol* 31 et Hay* 2* As ro^ardo station wagons and trucks thore is a uholoe between no?? vehiales and scoona-hand onoc. The situation in this oountry for ncr.? vehioiles is that there vmulcl be a delay of some six raonthe ran t!ic placing o on order before the veliioleo vxx&amp;d bo abr.dl^ble Bron productiorw If the Cavernpent of fndia vdsh to prOdure ne^.-? vohiales ( which we are advised •■ould be better on the vAidle) we current that you otiould place a firm -.lenfthJ' through the Itinh Cards- ioner (India Store Oepm'traent)# on the Ministry of Supply, P*V*2* # Adelplii, London, giving full det: ils of roqtdresfatmts, vis* type, moke and quantity of vehicles required* 3* If, on the other hand the frov rram.ut of India would prefer recori itionod v- x ^ i :lcloc ( hioh ore of course cheaper and vxmld have a fair resnoininf; railer^e) it a^jpearr, that these oould only be made available iYom stocks in this country if they are oortifled os not available in India* If therefore, you arc prepared to take these and if all or sorae rxc still not availidjle in Inlia, perhaps you would £'ive ur full letails as above of veiiicaler pot availabio, so that xm enn furnish the India i torc Department with the neoossaxy oertificate /and B*IC* Kepur, Hsq*, ?hctomal Af; airs Department, New Delhi.. * DRAFT LETTER EXT. 4150/46 m) B.K. Kapur, Esq., External Affairs Department, New Delhi. Will you please refer to your d.o. letter No. F. 1557^/45 of the 3rd June, 1946, on the subject of vehicles for consular posts in Persia? This has A4. 7 ^ crossed our Express Letter* Ext. 3324/46 of 31st tlay. t Qhevrolet station wagons might new be available , Jkt, Wt' loei&gt;i11y in The situation in this country for new vehicles is that there would be a delay of sane six months from the placing of an order before the vehicles would be available from nprf production. , ' « // Hm §/( wvd* frfpuc^M (jlvuL l** osU dtok** 4 * If it-appeara to you preferable te order thorn 4a UftolA vt(U% (*&gt;* ^nglanri -we are nfhM y™' should place a firm demand through the High Commisskrer (IM India Store Department), on,the Ministry of Supply, F.V.2., Adelphi, London, giving full details of . , • • t requirements, viz. type, make and quanity of vehicles required.J .YHCO si (W /C tlfc* ^ /fc $/ tsruL* f^M* 3* It a pooi-a uiiQ^ ^econditioned vehicle s (which axe of course cheaper and would have a fair remaining mileagey could only be made available frora stocks in this country if they are certified as not available in India. If therefore, you are prepared to take t ■ ^ x ■ ■ c. • c ~ -• these and if all or some are still not available in India, perhaps you would give us full details as above of vehicles not available, so that we can furnish the India ^4 —m At '^r? /,&gt;——4.^ ■&gt;» *&gt;»••* ft»«u Store Department (torongh wcwUd of nour&lt;3e . 4jW m ■ ^ £&gt;* } plhne. an order at. the snme tirne)/with the necessary certif icate^ ( / Ji Jn*** ’ *0+ /&amp; Sfi J U-kiJf , 4. With reference to paragraph 3 of your lette 1 am sorry that Tehran wets % as a matter of misprintec discovered the mistake and it-had-been corr-eoted in t iiwe» have asked the foreign Office to accept the responsibility for the truck and station wagon for the additional • * • • Consul for Indian Affairs at Tehran, (which yrc~-H$0r was now\his -title^l^your IfeT^ 23 ( 9 )—• to/to Tehran dated 18th Hay, 1%£) but we would / CLAAi suggest that you should/include them in |pMD orders you place aek^hey can always be cancelled later if the Foreign Office agree to supply them.DRAFT LETTER Ext. 4150A-6 R. W. Urquhart, Esq. , Foreign Office, S.W.1. 29 JUN*# Dear Urquhart, Will you please refer to your letter of 22nd January, No. K 22689/265/23^- about the supply of vehicles for Consular posts in Persia. The G-overnraent of India are purchasing cars for the Consul-General, Meshed and the Consul, Khorramshahr, and we are endeavouring, with the assistance of our Army Requirements Branch, to obtain the other trucks and station wagons required* One 15 cwt. truck and one station vsagon is required for the Additional Consul for Indian Affairs at Tehran however, and the Government of India say M the British Embassy, Tehran, however/s ■» however, propose that these vehicles t * should be carried on the strength of the Embassy in general, so that other Members of the staff, who also live out of town or have to go on tour, could also use them'. We should/be glad to know if the Foreign Office are prepared to include one 15 cwt. truck and one station wagon in the list of vehicles which they are endeavouring to obtain for Consulates in Persia* Yours sincerely, ft A, IL HARRISON//• Mr, Hanp^on^ War Staff (i. a t jor Branch) 9 The Government of India letter below goes some way towards clearing up the muddle about vehicles for the East Persia Consulates, The position seems to be: - (1) The Government of India are buying two Humber Super Snipe Saloon cars for the Consul-General, Meshed and the Consul at Khorramshahr through the India Store Department, (2) The trucks supplied to Meshed and Zabul - Zahidan by H,M. Embassy, Tehran are on loan until they are supplied with proper vehicles. (3) The other Consulates did not require this particular type of vehicle. (4) The list of requirements flagged at X still stands with the exception of the^ cars for Meshed and Khorramshahr and for the Additional Tehran and ^he station wagon and 15 cwt. truck for the Additional J for Indian Affairs at Tehran which are to be 'carried on the strength of the Embassy', (it is not clear where Sir Clarmont Skrine is to obtain his car, though we know that he is to have one), ( 5 ) Although we told them that station wagons are in short supply, the Government of India ask us to continue to try and find sane, expressing a preference for military type Humber wagons with four wheel drive, (6) Since the vehicles for the 'Additional Consul for Indian Affairs,Tehran' (for his exact designation see Ext, 376^46 on Collection 29/104) are to be used by other Members/.Y HO'') Members of the Embassy staff, the Government of India suggest th^y should be included in the Foreign Office list of requirements, A draft to the Foreign Office on these lines is below. (I am sorry that in our letter at Ext. 2426/46 mention should have been made of the Indian Vice-Consul, Bahrein. I did correct it, but apparently not in time). (7) The Governnent of India have not taken up the point made in our express letter at Ext. 3324/46 about obtaining reconditioned trucks from surplus stocks in &gt; y India. It seems probable that the two letters crossed. / ^ Perhaps, however, the War Staff would go into the matter again »vith the Minis try of Supply and if necessary with the appropriate authorities in India. A revised list of requirements is attached. OV-'-' 9 INDEXED E XT 4 I 50 &amp; * FILE ouPY External Affairs Department, &lt;©&gt; the ^ June New Delhi, D»0«No* Fal55—A/4:5« Subject i— GiiHo .F OR LN 7946 J&gt; 6&lt;v * /iw Ar~&lt;U.c£S&lt;~ Will you please refer to your demi-official letter to Burnett No. EXT.2426/46, dated the 10th April 1946 ? I am desired to say that 15-Cwt Chevrolet (: 2?4-/ trucks (reconditioned) were supplied to Meshed and Zabul free of cost by British Embassy, Tehran, out of the surplus stock of the Polish Refugees, only for so long as the regular supply of vehicles is not made to them. Such trucks were not required by any of our other consular officers in Persia and the Persian Gulf whose requirements were intimated to the Foreign Office by the Minister Resident, Cairo, in his telegram No. 24 saving of the 20th April 1945. + We shall, thererore, oe grateful if you will KT'ffdly continue to make efforts to obtain the station wagons and trucks required by the consular officers in Persia and mentioned in paragraph 3 of your demi- official letter under reply. I am to enclose a copy of correspondence which 1. Letter to His Majesty’s Ambassador^ has been exchanged with the Tehran No. F.155-A/45, dated the 3rd April 1946. 2. Letter from do ,No. 102, Tehran Snbassy, and to say i that an order for the t supply of two supersnipe i i Qlg' ’ ‘ ’ ’ saloon cars (for the dated the 1st Pay 1946. j Consul General, Meshed and Consul, Khorramshahr) will be placed shortly with the firm concerned through the High Commissioner. I am to request that in your attempt to find station wagons for our officers the preference expressed by the Tehran Embassy for the military type of Humber station wagon with four-wheel drive may kindly be borne in mind. 3. It may be mentioned for your information that no vehicle is required by the Indian Vice-Consul, Raht-ai n . One 15 cwt truck and one station wagon were required by the Indian Vice-Consul, Tehran who is properly designated as 'Consular Attache’ for Indian affairs, Tehran. The British &amp;nbassy. /TehranTshi’o.n, howevei , pi’oposs ijlistj tjliss© vsiilcXss should be carried on the strength of the Embassy In general, so that other members of the staff y •“ ve 0U 't of town or have to go on tour could also use them. This requirement of one ’ fr?^n 11 wa Son and one 15 cwt truck for the Indian Tn thP 0 ^Pil e o??? raa n y J therefore be Included v^hlcies^ 61211 0frlce list of requirements of Sir Cla^KM; 3 letter 18 bel ”« S9nt /U. icc^r** S.p« Donaldson, Esquire. India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.l.v . . . '© '• 4 • ' dopy of memcr andum fT'ora His Britannic ?lg i esty’ qv * '■ donsul General for Khoraam, He shed No. 186/7/cl, dated the 8th February 1946. Subject:-Maintenance gfant for 15 Cwt. Chevrolet.Truck supplied to tiia Majesty’s donsul 4t Zahidan. / Reference paragraph 3 of your memorandum No.F.251/!/ 45 dated the 12th December l94o. 2. It is proposed that the grant for the maintenance of the 15 Gwt/dhevrolet Truck supplied to His Majesty's yic donsul, Zahidan be fixed at Rs. 3,500/- per annum details of which ar e givan. below: - (i) Pay of driver D f\s.l20/- per mensem Rs.1,440 (ii) Dear Food Allowance at the current) rate admissible to the Zahidan ) clerical staff § Es. 123/12 (&amp;.125) ) .R5.1,500 per mensem. ) (iii) For repairs and livery c$ driver 560 Rs&gt;3,500 3. In addition a sum of Rs.650/- is to be paid to the Persian dustoms Authorities at Zahidan as Customs duty on the truck, and it is therefore requested that an ^ddiidon al grant to cover this expenditure may kindly be sanction ed and funds provided in the current year’s budget. 4. It is also recommended that if you see nc objection the proposed grant referred to in paragraph 2 above be sanctioned with retrosoective- effect Nith effect from the 2nd August 1945, the date Major Sakqr took ever as donsul Zahidan.3 From - The Under Secretary to the Grovernment of India in the External Affaire Department* To - His Britannic Majesty's Consul General for Khorasan, Meshed. /^ Memorandum No. F.155-A/45. Dated Simla,the 30th April, 1946. Subject:- Supply of motor vehicles to Consular posts in Iran and thei r maintenance. /i Reference your memorandum No.303-V/94 dated the 2nd March 1946. r ~~ 2. The Government of India are pleased to sanction till the 28th February 1947 a maintenance grant of Rs.3,500/- per annum for each of the 15 Cwt. Chevrolet trucKs supplied to you and the Vice-Consul, Zabul. For the truck of the latter officer no driver should be engaged until such time as the post is actually filled but a cleaner may be engaged on ft&gt;.65/- per mensem (ho.20/- basic pay and hs.45/- dear food allowance @ 225%) and this amount may be paid from the maintenance grant sanctioned above. 3. The expenditure involved should be met from the sanctioned budget grants of the Khorasan Consulate General and the Zabul Vice-Consulate. ( Sd/- P.N. Krishnaswamy ) Under Secret ary to the Government of India. (Puri)Copy of Memorandum No* 186 V/ 81 dated the 3th February, 1946 from Hia Majesty 1 a Confor^nprasan, Meahed to the Secretary to tne G&lt;)vernment/5t/fnfia tne External affairs Department, New Delhi.) 2927 Subject Maintenance grant for 15 cwt. Chevrolet.Truck supplied to His Majesty* fg^y sul aj t Zahid^n. Reference paragraph 3 of your memorandum No.F*251/A/45 dated the 12 th DeceSer,1945* 2. It ia proposed that the grant for the maintenance of the 15 cwt. Chevrolet Truck supplied to H.M f s Consul, Zahidan, be fixed at fls.3,500/- per annum details of which are given below (i) Pay of driver 1 Rs*l20/~ p.m* ffe* 1,440 (li) Dear Food Allowance at the current jj rate admissible to the Zahidan 0 &amp;• 1,500 , clerical staff 3 fe* 123/12 (Ks.125) p.m{ (iii) For repairs and liv^ery of driver Rs* 560 fe. 3,500 3* In addition a sum of Rs.650/~ is to be paid to the Persian Customs authorities at Zahidan as Customs duty on the truck, and it is therefore requested that an additional grant to cover this expenditure may kindly be sanctioned and funds provided in the current year’s budget* 4. It is also recommended that if you see no objection the proposed grant referred to in paragraph 2 above be sanctioned with retrospective effect with effect from the 2nd August 1945 the date Major 3aker took over as Consul Zahidan.FILbW jX m From bo S’ &gt;ticrotary in the Ex To His Britannic EXT j l ] i m to ^ C&gt; of Indiit SOTO Affairs Dapartaanto Ti Majesty's Aabasaador Extraordinary &amp; Plonipotontiar L i. h r * a» 'b/J: tt.O. % Datod uubjectSupply of motor vehiclaa to Consular Ofxl ~ 1 * “ Simla,tlM April, 1946. is to Ci cors in Persia and tbs I^rsian Gulf, Your Excellency, end Ko. ^ith reference to the correspondence with the Embassy's compliment -1- ^ , dated the 6 tb February a«v ww4 ^ liKontary*memorand un v 19- &gt;46, I am 4 POfc E'o. directed to forward herewith a copy of demi official letter from Mr. Harrison of the India Office No. Ext 1617/46 dated the 9th March 1946, together with enclosures and brochures. The Government of India would be glad to know whether your Excellency considora any of the oars offered by the firms as suitable* for the conoular officers in Persia and the 1 eraian Gulf for whom motor transport is to be provided by this Department, and to be furnished with the particulars of the type of motor vehicles for which an order may be placed with a supplying firm, { have the honour to be, lenoy 9 s most obedient servant rit£c £/V V , ^ - P.N. KRISHNASWiHIY ) to the Government of India. 0 /YI think the letter below is self explanatory. Before pressing the Array Equipment Branch to pursue their enquiries with the Ministry of Supply, it would be as well to ascertain whether the vehicles are still required. A list of the requirements of the Consulates in Persia maintained by the Government of India is flagged 'X' on the file. / • C5 (3^. %.I 'tzb J DIL'^T LSTTSR Lieut.Col.R.R.Burnett 9 C.I.E.,O.B.E., External Affairs Department, Government of India. W 1946 Dear Burnett, Will you please refer to Harrison^ letter No. Ext. 1617/^6 of 9th March about oars for the East Bersian Consulate. ^#We have now received a copy of the Government of India*s letter to the Consul- General at Meshed Mo.P155-A/5 f 5 of 28th March. Wvc. It appears from enclosure^(that 15-cwt. trucks are beincr supplied to Meshed and Zabul from Tehran feu that 'rnT^nrod 0 twpjr - or the other Consulates maintained by the Government of India x , S. — — WJ . in iterslal ■ ^ehieir-j uhioh the Amy Equipment Branch of this €CiXki Office are/endeavouring to obtain.through ot ^ military* Supply^ «r?f one l^cwt. truck and one station waggon for the Indian Vice Consul, 4*i, two 8 -cwt. trucks for Bander Abbas, /fourfour station waggons for I^ishire, and one each for Birjand, ZaHidan and Kerman. These requirements were taken *frera-the list given in 'Cairo telegram to the foreign Office- No.24 Saving of 20th April, 1945 (a 1 ’ co'py of which was enclosed in Harrisons •letter to Duke of the 22nd June^ No. Ext. 2841A5). ^f,Y&lt;e should be glad to know whether you still wish us - 1 c -©orftinue to press for the supply of these vehicles, * - Yours sincerely, ^V&lt;n r P 5t)N ^LDSOlTtUgratm: (Shipping) 'SHIPMINOER, TELEX, (Inland Transport) &lt;r TRANSMINRY, TEbcyv, ..unwun. inistry of War Transport, Telephone: ABBEY 7711 EXTN. 2/3, Fitzmaurice Place, Your Referenda and the following reference quoted :— be addressed to:— THE DIRECTOR GENERAL Any further communication should ZV. 16/3 2A (address as opposite) f 2290 | -&gt;) Berkeley Square, London, W.l. T?a. coa J.Iarch, 1946 I94R Dear Harrison Would you please note that after 4 the 31st March 1946, this Department will cease to be responsible for the allocation to Government Departments of surplus W.D. vehicles which are reconditioned and made available by the Ministry of Supoly for re-issue. Any further applications for these vehicles should therefore be submitted to Mr. G.H. Bryan, Ministry of Supply, F.V.3. (Disposals), Great Westminster House, Horseferry Road, S.W.l. A list of those applications which remain unfilled either wholly or in part when this Department ceases to be responsible for allocations will be sent to the Ministry of Supply at the t;nd of this month. Any further correspondence about tho se applications should therefore be directed to the Ministry of Supply. F.N.Harrison, Esq* India Office, G.D.Arnjy Equipment Branch 1Q116/7/AR1 (b) 2 fMarch # 1946, Inistry of Supply, DD/P73 (DI3), Adelphi, ^ Strand, w.C. 2 . *i &gt;r 'Vehicles for fijastern Persian Consulates So far we are unable to trace a reply to our letters 10 ll 6 / 4 /\R 1 B dated d.2.46 and 10116/6/AR1 (b) dated 14.3.46. It would be appreciated if an early reply may be received as we are being constantly pressed for the information called for. Copy to: Army Ltcternal Affairs Department, India Ofi ice.F-JLtt ,gR iiilL £xt 'tfotyUC . lu -9 W.O. I larch, I9i|6, March e.xr Burnett, ill you please refer to your letter D. 0 . No. Fl5i&gt;-«/45 of 15 th Deceraber last about airs for the Kast Persian Consulates ' On receiving your letter we wrote again to the -roreifin Office and I enclose a oqpy of their reply, ^s the —^ Forei^i Office were clearly unable to give us any dated 22 nd January; further help we have had to do what we could ——■——“■ ourselves. The inay Equipment Brandi of this Office have now taken up with the iinistry of Supply the procurement of trucks, ana, the sLQ)])ly of secondhand cars in this country being esdiausted, the ociety of Motor Manufacturers and Traders at our request circuXirised their iiieiabers about the supply of new Ckits which might be suitable. I enclose copies of the V ~ — . . —■ replies to this circular 1. from jpmstrong Siddeley* s dated 21st February 2 . from Rootes dated 22 nd . ebruary 3« from Jaimlors dated 26th February 4* from Jaguar C.ors Ltd. dated 25th February ) Government of India consider any of these cars suitable, assiane they will take steps to place an order with the firm concerned through the India itore Department keeping us in touch so that we may lend any possible assistance. 3* * will let you have a further letter about the truck as soon as a reply is received from the Ministry of Supply. Yours sincerely. Lt.Col.H.R.Burnett, O.B.M., External affairs f-epartment^ A. K. HARRISONmm THE DAIMLER CO LTD TELEPHONE. 4161 (NINE'LINES) TELEGRAMS: DA1MLER.PHONE, COVENTRY. The India Office, Whitehall, LONDON, S.VY, 1. BY APPOINTMENT TO HIS MAJESTY THE KING —EJLELTOPY _&gt; V T 146a COVE NTRY LEAS E REPLY TO EXT )KP MANAGER. 94 P OUR pEE WEH/JOB. &gt;1 26th. February, 1946, o Dear Sirs, Reference No: Ext. 584 / 46 . We are advised by our friends. The Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders Limited, (Overseas Department) that you are interested in the purchase of three Saloon cars of from 24 to 30 horse-power for the use of Consulates in East Persia. We believe that our new 27 H.P. six cylinder chassis with suitable bodywork would meet your requirements, and the list price of the chassis in this Country is £1200. The price of a suitable body would be approximately £1,000, and from these figures we should be pleased to quote you an export price based upon a net ex works discount of 15 ^ from list. We should, however, prefer to receive from you an enquiry of your exact requirements so that we can put forward our quotation, and to assist you in judging the suitability of our products we are sending you herewith a brief specification of the chassis, together with a coachbuilders drawing of the Hooper Light Limousine, and a photograph of a similar body but with four windows instead of six. We believe that the body could be modified to exclude partition, and if necessary the occasional seats, and at your request we shall be pleased to go more fully into the matter. Delivery should be possible by approximately the middle of this year, provided the order is placed without undue delay. Looking forward to hearing from you in the early future. urs faithfully, COMPANY L] — - 2 7 FFR1946 ’ TTie Company’s new'products are sold and the Company's work on Service and Repairs is done under the terms of its published Conditions of Sale ' which are current at the time of the transaction. Shop-soiled, ex-demonstration and second-hand cars are sold under special ' Conditions of Sale ' which can be had on application. OMP^NY LIMITED W. BSSSSi of'ffi4SS^tonditicTELE PHONE S HEAD OFFICE &amp; WORKS COVENTRY 88681 (lO lines) TELEGRAM S t) AG UA R' COVENTRY CODE: BENTLEY'S 2*m&gt;. J A G 17 A R » n RLE ^OPY / IdJk^ecJc^ mU v ~ (i^ RECTORS AM LYONS [f 14 * « (p) fr N T R LTD T W.OAFFERN o» i »XA. »AAA H. N GILLITT A WHITTAKER , GCNi *al Our R e f. PEH/JL. 25th Februar:; 1946• The India Office, Whitehall, LONDON. S.W.l. Dear Sirs, Reference Extension 584/46. We have been informed by the Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders Ltd., Piccadilly, London 7/.1, that you are desirous of receiving particulars about three Saloon Gars for eventual use by the Consulates in East Persia. We are accordingly forwarding you herev/ith a copy of our latest brochure which gives full details of specifications and performance of our current production models, the 1 ^. 2 &gt;&gt; and 3 j litre Saloons. We imagine the last named model would be the most suitable for your purpose, and we feel sure, it would, by reason of its outstanding performance, reliability and elegance meet your requirements to the full. V/e would add that our 3^ litre saloon is now appearing in small numbers from the finishing line, and we would be very pleased to receive the favour of your orders in the near future• Referencx^Lxtension 683/46. We understand mefFeover, that under the above ref&lt; you are interesteeKin a large 'convertible” type car H.M. Political^fgent at Koweit. ?nce, use by &lt;o o We Imtfe pleasure in announcing that alth 6 ugh we are concentrating on saloon models for the tnm*e being, we shall into jsfroduction with drop head coupes o^all three Chassis si^s in the late Spring, and we trusJi^Lbat one of these models .1 likewise meet with your appro^ Assuring you of our best attention at all times. Yours faithfully, for JAGUAR CARS LIMITED. Yb* : 9^3 Export department.r 1 33 L jM^ COPY BY A**OINTM£NT ^ RipqreS' | M &lt;»TTRT«»DlVI 6 ION t)F ' ^ HUMBER'HILLMAN • SUN BEAM - TALBOT COMMER • KARRIER DEVONSHIRE HOUSE * PICCADILLY * LONDON • W-l THC LAU QUCCN Of HO»*«»AY TELEPHONES ■ GR0SVEN0R-340H)8Linis) CABLEGRAMS • ROOTESMOTI- LONDON CODES - A- B-C • 5 T -» A 6™ EDITIONS PRIVATE • BENTLEYS ' I ' JB/MM , 22.2.46. 7our“Ref: Ext. 584/46. In^ia Office, WHITEHALL, LQHDOid. S.W.l. Dear Sirs, The Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders here has advised us of an enquiry you have put to them for 3 SALOON MOTOR CARS of 24/50 h.p. 8 STATION WAGONS for use of Consulates in East Persia. Also under Reference Ext. 685 / 46 ;^ a’’convertible 1 'type of car with approximately 50 h.p. for H.M. Political Agent at Koweit, Persian Gulf. Against these enquiries we would submit our HUMBER vehicles, catalogue of which is enclosed. Ext.584/46 . Either the HUMBER SUPERSNIPE SALOON or the PULLMAN LIMOUSINE could be proposed against require ment for the 5 Saloon cars. Special prices we would quote India Office would be - HUMBER SUPERSNIPE SALOON to standard specification, ex-Works £595 HUMBER PULLMAN LIMOUSINE £1050. Delivery . Against receipt of an order within the next four weeks, delivery could be indicated as follows - PULLMAN - approximately mid-July.We take it that Left-hand Drive vehicles would be required? STATION WAGONS . We are sorry, but we are unable to make any proposal with regard to this type at present. By about next September or October it is hoped to have developed a standard Station Wagon body on the HUMBER SUPERSNIPE Chassis, but we regret it.is too early yet to be able to supply any specifications or to indicate a price. REF; EXT. 685/ 46. We are afraid we can offer y nothing to comply with this request for a^convertible type and so we are hoping that one of the standard HUMBERS may be acceptable in this instance. Yours faithfully, ROOTES LTD. J. BYFIELD. Export Division.wmmmmmmmmmmmmzmm* ( CONTRACTORS TO H M. GOVERNMENT - ' ILE COPY \KMSTR()\(i YinWIKV-HOIORS IIMIIIH- WCTURERS OfV'^&amp;RO ENGINES AND HIGH GRA V i Our Refj AS/TT* • I r A r Zjat* February 19U&amp;* — ; PHONE COVEN! MANUI ~e wires E“7/wSIDARM COVENTRY GRADE MOTOR CARS J* India Office, Whitehall LONDON, S. ~fo 1. Dear Sirs, Reference Nos Ext, 58Vif6, We have received notification fran theSociety of Motor Manufacturers and Traders Limited, that you are requiring under the above reference, three Saloon oars, and eight Station Wagons, for the use of Consulates in 3ast Persia,, where we have officially appointed agents, who are in a position to render service. We are enclosing herewith, two copies of our current catalogue, which describes our new 16 h,p, 'Hurricane' Coupe and 'Lancaster' Saloon, the price of which, although not yet officially announced, is expected to be approximately £775* 0,0, ex- ,v orks Coventry, to standard specifioatiorw This is the only vehicle in production by us at the present moment^ We have every reason to believe, that this model will be very suitable for the purposes stated, and therefore, await your further instructions, which ;eive our immediate and careful attentiorv Yours f hfuji; for A&amp;ISTR0N&amp; SIDDELEf : 400RESS ALL COMMUNIC *4 T TO INDIVIDUALS// A SALOON WITH EVifiY GOOD FEATURE / A STYLISH COUPE WITH HIGH PERFORMANCE These two fine cars - entirely new in design - embody every worth-while feature known in motoring. # New frontal appearance - unmistakably Armstrong Siddeley, but completely modernised. # New chassis - low and of immense strength. # New suspension - giving remarkable comfort over bad road conditions. # New engine - giving exceptional power and flexibility. # New coachwork designs - modern and pleasing in appearance - practical in use. Finally, many advanced, yet proved details which set the highest standard of comfort and convenience ever known in motoring.The “Lancaster” saloon has many features designed specifically for safety and comfort, including air con ditioning, de-misting channels under screen, excellent visibility, instrument panel with concealed illumination, directly in front of driver, adjustable steering column and front seats, ample leg and headroom. Swivelling draught-free ventilators. Left—General view of driving position showing excellent visibility. : uusnuuuru iulkcf. Top right—instrument panel showing air con ditioning unit. Bottom right — comfort able individual type front seats. Concealed illumination for controls.Conveniently placed ashtrays. Left—Attractive safety type door handles. Exceptional rear seat comfort is illustrated on the opposite page, and the rear of the car showing attractive lines and ample luggage accommodation is shown below. For safety and con venience an auxiliary rear light is located inside the bottom compartment of the luggage boot and is automatically switched on when door is lowered and the normal rear light obscured. Top left—Swivelling draught-free rear quarter windows. Bottom left and centre—Rear views of car showing clean lines, large rear window and ample luggage space.* FOUR SPEED SYNCHROMESH GEARBOX AS ALTERNATIVE TO SELF-CHANGE nr &gt; i GENERAL VIEW OF THE INDEPENDENT FRONT SUSPENSION # HIGH PERFORMANCE 6 CYLINDER 16 H.P. ENGINE. # UNDERSLUNG FRAME OF GREAT STRENGTH AND LOW CENTRE OF GRAVITY # PERMANENT MECHANICAL JACKING SYSTEM % EFFECTIVE SILENCING SYSTEM ON RUBBER MOUNTINGSINDEPENDENT FRONT SUSPENSION SYNCHROMESH OR SELF-CHANGE GEARBOX STROMBERG DOWNDRAUGHT CARBURETTOR ADJUSTABLE STEERING COLUMN STROMBERG DOWNDRAUGHT CARBURETTOR &amp; A.C. AIR CLEANER Attractive Small Tool Container.The “Hurricane” Coupe is stylish and practical, combining exceptional comfort and roominess \^h high performance. The three position drop-head is easily operated and is completely weatherproof. All the detail refinements of the “Lancaster” are included in this model. Above—view of interior with head fully lowered. Left—alternative position of drop head. Adjustable front seats, the backs of which tilt forward for ease of access to rear seats.SEATING Comfortable accommodation for five persons. Individual sliding type front seats, adjustable over range of 6'. Recessed footrests at rear of front seats for comfort of rear passengers. Rear seat with side arm rests and centre folding arm rest. UPHOLSTERY Light toned soft leather in colours to harmonise with exterior schemes, edged with piping. Cushioning pleated laterally. Pile carpets to tone with upholstery. FEATURES Effective air conditioning controlled by switches on dashboard. Windscreen de-misting. Front doors recessed to accommodate inside door handles. Chromium plated interior and exterior fittings. Safety glass throughout. Swivelling draught-proof ven tilating light at front edge of front door windows. Rear quarter lights are also of swivelling draught proof type. Chromium plated metal door window frames for increased visibility. Polished walnut interior woodwork. Concealed dual screen wipers. Concealed self-cancelling trafficators. Interior driving mirror, with which is incorporated a small illuminated timepiece in full view of all passen gers. Ash-trays to front and rear compartments. Glove box in instrument panel. Rear blind operated from driver s seat. Ample luggage accommodation in rear luggage boot. Adjustable sun visors (passenger’s visor incorporates companion mirror). Single control sun roof. Two interior lights over rear passengers seats con trolled by two 2-way switches. Hand pulls to rear compartment. Floodlit switch panel with push button control. Concealed hinges. Licence holder. Bumpers front and rear. Ignition key also locks driver’s door and luggage boot doors. BODY COLOURS : BLACK . NAVY BLUE 4-6* TRACK4-6* TRACK SEATING. Full accommodation for five persons. Individual sliding type front seats, adjustable over range of 6'. Back rests on front seats arranged to tilt forwards for ease of access to rear seats. Recessed footrests at rear of front seats for comfort of rear passengers. Rear seat with side arm rests and centre folding arm rest. UPHOLSTERY Light toned soft leather in colours to harmonise with exterior schemes, edged with piping. Cushioning pleated laterally. Pile carpets to tone with upholstery. FEATURES Three position drophead roof in mohair to harmonise with exterior coachwork. Zip fasteners to close aperture between roof fabric and top frame of windows, making the car completely weatherproof. Front doors recessed to accommodate inside door handles. Chromium plated interior and exterior fittings. Safety glass throughout. Windscreen pillars in light alloy and chromium plated door window frames give excellent visibility and absence of blind spots. Polished walnut interior woodwork. Concealed dual screen wipers. Concealed self cancelling trafficators. Interior driving mirror with which is in corporated a small illuminated timepiece in full view of all passen gers. Ash-trays in front and rear compartments. Glove box in instrument panel. Ample luggage accommodation in rear luggage boot. Adjustable sun visors (passenger’s visor incorporates com panion mirror). Floodlit switch panel with push button control. Concealed hinges. Licence holder. Bumpers front and rear. Ignition key also locks driver’s door and luggage boot doors. TURQUOISE BLUE . GREY . MAROON . FAWN 4 6*'TRACKC H A S S I S ENGINE Six-cylinder monobloc, bore 65 mm, stroke 100 mm, capacity 1.991 cc., R.A.C. rated H.P. 15.72, water cooled with detachable head. Overhead valves operated by rockers and push rods from chain driven camshaft. Hydraulic Tappets. Pressure lubrication through filter to crankshaft main bearings, connecting rod big ends, camshaft bearings and overhead rocker gear, by submerged gear pump driven from camshaft. Oil intake through floating feed pipe. Counter balanced crankshaft, including vibration damper, supported in four steel-backed white-metal bearings. Four-point engine mounting on rubber to eliminate vibration. STROMBERG downdraught carburetter with automatic choke, fed by A.C. mechanical pump. A.C. air-cleaner and silencer. Cooling by centrifugal water pump. Ignition—LUCAS Coil and Distributor with automatic control. LUCAS Starter and Dynamo—the latter driven with water pump from crankshaft, drive being adjustable. Oil Filler Cap on rocker cover. Dip stick for indicating level. GEARBOX (Synchromesh or Preselective Self-changing) SYNCHROMESH Four-speed gearbox in Unit- construction with engine. Synchromesh in second, third and top gears—Single helical type gearing. Oil filler plug at side of box—which also determines oil level. Single dry-plate clutch (Borg and Beck) enclosed in flywheel. PRESELECTIVE Four-speed self - changing gears with pre - selective control on steering column. Centrifugal clutch automatically taking up drive. FRAME Frame underslung at rear and designed to give the car a low centre of gravity with consequent stability and road holding capabilities.p E C I F SUSPENSION FRONT. The road wheels are independent and torsion bar springing is adopted. The hubs are fixed to top and bottom articulated arms having unequal centres, thus giving a constant track and consequent lack of scrub and wear on the tyres. The top articulated arms are of the wishbone type and function as levers for the shock absorbers. The lower articulated arms are attached to the torsion bars. REAR. Half-elliptic, of generous length giving excellent resilience LUVAX-GIRLING Hydraulic dampers with pressure recuperation are fitted to guard against pitching and excessive deflection. REAR AXLE Incorporates Hypoid bevel gears ensuring a silent drive. BRAKES GIRLING Self-compensating. Pedal gear fitted with oil-less bearings, obviating the need for constant lubrication. Foot brake to all four wheels. Front wheel brakes operated hydraulically. Automatic adjustment. Oil tank is carried on dash and master cylinder is adjacent to the brake pedal. “Pistol” grip type handbrake operating rear brakes only. WHEELS AND TYRES Disc wheels with five stud fixing, spring-on type hub cap fitted, masking the stud fixing. (Wire wheels can be fitted if desired, at extra cost.) Track Front 4' 6'. Rear 4' 6|'. Turning Circle 37 ft. Wheelbase 9' 7'. STEERING Worm and nut (Burman-Douglas). Self-centring, light and positive action. Double arm two spoke steering wheel, giving good vision of the instuments. Adjustable steering column. (Licenced under Patents Nos. 417418 and 494902 Bluemel Bros. Ltd., Douglas). FUEL SYSTEM Petrol tank is located at the rear and enclosed. Large filler cap is accessibly placed for ease of replenishment and is designed for quick filling. Capacity 12 gallons. One gallon is “reserve” and controlled from the facia board by means of a solenoid switch. Feed to Carburetter is by mechanical pump. CAT I ON COOLING SYSTEM Cooling by pump and fan. Radiator filler located by lifting bonnet. AIR CONDITIONING Effective air conditioning equipment is installed. Heating and circulation of cool air controlled by switches on the instrument panel. JACKING SYSTEM Two permanent mechanical type jacks are fitted, one on each side of the car, and located alongside the frame underneath floor of driving compartment. By turning back carpet and lifting small trap-door the jack is exposed and the operating handle (which is carried in tool kit in door of boot) can be connected and the jack is immediately ready for use. EXHAUST SYSTEM Effective silencing system carried on rubber mountings permitting expansion, and preventing vibration to the chassis frame. ELECTRICAL SYSTEM &amp; EQUIPMENT 12 volt system with 53 amp. Lucas Battery located under bonnet. Two Lucas combined side and head lamps with dip-switch control. Rear lamp and “stop” tail lamp are incorporated with rear number plate which is fully enclosed. Side lamp failure is indicated on the instrument panel by an amber warning light. An auxiliary rear light is located inside the lower compartment of the luggage boot, and this automatically lights up when the door is lowered and the normal rear light is obscured. This light also illuminates the interior of the spare wheel and tool compartment. Trafficator control, horn button and dip switch are in centre of steering wheel. Twin-toned electric horns. INSTRUMENT PANEL Speedometer, Oil and Petrol gauges, Ignition warning light and side lamp failure indicator, on panel directly facing driver. Controls for Starter, Lights, and Petrol reserve are neatly grouped on right hand side of panel. Concealed illumination of controls, operated by a push-button on and off switch. Radio equipment can be installed as an extra, and provision is made to accommodate the receiver under the bulkhead and the controls on instrument panel. TOOLS Small tools are accommodated in a rattle-free container which is carried in a box and located under the instrument panel. Spare wheel is carried in lower section of luggage compartment and the wheel brace, tyre pump and jack handle are carried in the door of this compartment.PRINTED IN ENGLAND BY EDWARDS THE PRINTERS LTD. COVENTRY In consideration of your purchase of Car No. having Engine No. we hereby warrant to you that if within twelve months from the date of delivery of such Vehicle new to you you return immediately on discovery any part of such Vehicle which you allege to be defective to us at our Works carriage paid properly packed and clearly marked for identification with your full name and address and the Chassis and Engine numbers of such Vehicle, together with a complete des cription of the claim and the reasons therefor, such part will be examined and should any fault claimed be found, such defective part will be repaired or a new part will be supplied in exchange and the part so repaired or such new part will be delivered to you free of charge at our Works provided that you satisfy us or, in the case of the part in question forming part of the proprietary equipment supplied by us with the Vehicle, the manufacturers or suppliers thereof, (i) that such fault was due solely to defective materials or workmanship (ii) that such Vehicle has not been let out on hire or used for motor racing and (iii) that the Vehicle has not been fitted with an unsuitable body and on condition that any labour cost involved in the removal or reinstatement of the part in the vehicle is payable by you. If more convenient to you any proprietary equipment supplied by us with the vehicle may be returned with the above particulars direct to the Works or nearest Service Depot of the manu facturers thereof, but in such event, the make, model and date of delivery of the vehicle must also be supplied and the repaired or new part, as the case may be, will be delivered free of charge at the Manufacturers’ Works or nearest Service Depot. This warranty, the benefit of which is non-assignable, does not extend to tyres, covers and tubes, and is given on the terms that it expressly excludes all warranties, conditions and liabilities whatsoever in respect of the said Vehicle and all parts and articles thereof and therein (including tyres, covers and tubes) implied by Common Law, Statute or otherwise and is in lieu of all other warranties given by us or on our behalf in respect thereof. Our decision on all questions of fact arising under this warranty shall be conclusive and binding. The use on the said Vehicle of replacement parts not approved by us will absolve us from the necessity of fulfilling any obligation under this or any other warranty or condition in respect of the said Vehicle or any part thereof. Tyres : Attention is drawn to the fact that tyres, covers and tubes are specifically excluded from this warranty and that no warranty, condition or liability is accepted in respect thereof, accordingly any representations with regard thereto should be made direct to the makers. I.—Delivery is made at our Works, Coventry. &lt;yj /9 l 2 . —Chassis and Cars are only sold subject to the terms of the Company’s Guarantee, which is instead of, and expressly excludes, any other Guarantee, statutory or otherwise. 3. —All goods are sold upon the express condition that they are not to be exhibited at any Exhibition held in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland without the previous written permission of the Company, other than any Exhibition held by the Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders, Ltd., or approved by that Society for exhibition of motor goods by its Bond-signers. The purchaser agrees that in case of any breach of the provisions of this clause the purchaser will forthwith pay to the Company the sum of £250 for every such breach as liquidated damages, which damages may be assigned to any person. 4. —The term “Agent” in relation to our chassis goods or selling organisation is used in the business sense of a Dealer who purchases the goods of a Manufacturer for re-sale by himself as Principal, and not in the legal significance of the word. The person and firms therefore whom we style Agents for Armstrong Siddeley Cars, have no authority to incur any debt, liability or transact any business or to give any warranty or representation as to quality, or delivery of goods or otherwise on our behalf. 5. —Brief descriptions of our products are published in lists etc., for the information of intending Customers, but we do not guarantee strict adherence to detail and reserve the right to make such alterations in design, price and construction as we consider desirable. ARMSTRONG SIDDELEY MOTORS LIMITED, Head Office and Works, COVENTRY TELEPHONE . COVENTRY 4061 LONDON SERVICE DEPOT TELEPHONE . COLINDALE 5431-6 THE HYDE BRANCH OF HAWKER SIDDELEY TELEGRAMS . . “ SIDARM, COVENTRY” EDGWARE ROAD . HENDON, N.W. 9 TELEGRAMS , “SIDARM, PHONE, LONDON” AIRCRAFT COMPANY LIMITEDFiLE COPY LW/WJ 19th February, 1946. J.A.K.Harrison Ssq., UH)IA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON. S.W.l. Dear Sir, We acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 14th February advising the Government of Undines desire to purchase, as soon as possible, three saloon cars of 24-30 h.p. and eight station wagons for the use of Consulates in East Persia. Whilst crc unable, the time of replying to this 1 -toer, to advise you of the names of British manufacturers in a position to supply the type of vehicles you require, we would, however, state tnat this enquiry has been circularized amongst our Members. This will give interested manufacturers an opportunity of communicating with you direct. lours faithfully. L. M. 0 y OVERSEAS DEPARTMENT.'b. U, **/*/4/® fy.0. % Ik^FArMary, 1946 . f%l | ( ■;' •■■: iiliy/ I m dirooted to infona you that the (rovemnoat of India are anxious to obtain an soon aa poaaiblo three saloon oars of 2^}0 hup. and eight station wagons for the use of Consulates in %ast )&gt; arsis* The eorutar/ of state would bo grateful for your advice aa to which atanoffceturers in this country night be in the best position to execute this order at as early a date as possible* Z aa, Sir, Tour obedient Servant, F. A. K. HARRISON The Secretary, The Society of Motor Manufacturers, US, i iooadilly.Army Equipment Branch INDIA OFFICE, Address any reply to—The Under Secretary of State for India, as oppo- WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.I. site, quoting on the outside of the envelope a weM as in the text. Telephone ; Whitehall 8140. Telegrams 10016/5 (arib) “RETAXANDUM, LONDON.” , February, 1946, External Department, India Office, Lor ~ u s.w.i. ’’B' Vehicles for Eastern Persian Consulates Copy of personal letter from Major-General L.H. Williams, KBE, CB, l.C, Director of Warlike Stores to Col.A.B. Craddock CIE, OBE, War Staff, India Office in reply to letter No # 10ll6/l/ARl(B) dated 28,1.46, requesting assistance in procuring vehicles for the Eastern Persian / Consulates, is forwarded for information. It is presumed, owing to non availabilitg of Cars and Station Wagons from Army surpluses, you will take necessary steps to place demands on the Trade for these vehicles. The request for the 8 and 15 cwt. Trucks is being represented to the Ministry of Supply, and their comments will be communicated as soon as these are made known. Ml jolt, ary iAzpeu. uiucn*..From: Major-General L.H. Williams, K.B.E., C.B., M*C Director of Wax-like Stores* The War Office, Metropole Buildings, Northumberland Avenue, LONDON, W*C* 2* 57/Vehs. a/ 2342 (Ws 6 b) 4th February, 1946. Dear Craddock, Thank you for your letter No. 10116/1 /aRIB dated 28th January, 192*6. I am afraid that the Army is not throwing up ary surplus saloon cars or station waggons at present nor is it likeiy to do so for some time to come. Your only source of supply, as far as I can see, is new production. In regard to trucks 8 and 13 cwt. I suggest you get in touch with - G.H. Bryan, Esq., DI/PV3(DIS), Ministry of Supply, Adelphi, W. Tel. GERard 8 o 8 l Ext 2494 who, I am sure, will realize the high priority of this commitment. In the meantime, I am sending a copy of your letter to Mr. Bryan. Yours sincerely, (Signed) Col. a.B. Craddock, C.I.E., O.B.E., War Staff, India Office, Whitehall.Co fas £ HP«a.Col.A.B.CraQ&lt;ioclc ,CIE. ,OBS. , v-^ r f / ^gj, c&gt;4&gt;»^ /&gt;?&lt; HPtRtiSorj »ar Statt, ~ &lt;;», Dear «^C, January* 194^* caa 3o. 'B' Vehicles for Kaatem peraian Consulates. I wonder whether you couIU use your good offices to assist the Government of India in obtaining sone wry urgently required vehicles for the ; .astern Persian Consulates. I attach a list of the requirement and of the distribution proposed at Annexure 'A'. Although to the layman this would at first sight appear to be a Foreign Office responsibility* it is actually that of the Government of India You are aware of the staff car position in India. Their requirements have never been met* with the result that we are still obtaining staff cars from you for straight military requirements there. There are no suruluses. The Foreign Office and the M.W.T. have done their best to effect procurement to meet this coanitment but have been unsuccessful. I believe that the War Office may have some surpluses to their global needs which they intend to hand over to the Ministry of Supply for disposal* although the F.IA.2 cupboard appears bare at the moment. If this is the case* we shall be very grateful if you could use your knowledge of the War Office situation and your close /relationships Major-General sir L.H.Williams* KHE. *CB.*1C.* Controller of ordnance . ervicea and Director of Warlike Stores* War Office (Room 109)# Q.M.G. House* Whitehall Place *S«W.l.relationships wUh the iiinistry of . apply to induce latter to consider giving a priority to this important requirement before disposing of any Class 1 surpluses that there may be to purely civilian use as opposed to an essential Government coamitment* I apologise for troubling you in this matter but I am not sure whom I should address on the subject* If it is quite off your plate 9 perhaps you would be so good as to give me the benefit of your advice* Tours&gt;— FOREIGN OFFICE, SJN + 1. 22nd January 1946 Dear Donaldson, Your letter EXT 7034/45 of the 5th January. I have, since receiving it, talked with hoth you and Harrison and with Hart (F.V.2) of the Ministry of Supply. This is the case as I see It. Pending the supply of new vehicles, we have done our utmost v/ith the help of the Ministry of War Transport to scrape up suitable second-hand cars. We asked that India should do the same, well aware that she does not build new cars, but believing nevertheless that there must have been in India as elsewhere, a certain reserve of vehicles which could be combed through. We accept , wi thout much surprise, your assurance that nothing iWTttw can be done in India. We have, ourselves, exhausted the second-hand car possibilities in this country. I wish that we could solve the problem by simply adding East Persia requirements to our long and urgent list, but it 13 the responsibility of the Government of India to supply cars to these posts and I do not think it would help much if we took it over. As I think Harrison now agrees, it would be best if your Colonel Craddock could include East Persian require ments in his purchases of cars for India. Consuls concerned are likely to get cars much faster in that way, than by getting into our list. It would be unfortunate if the impression were /toto get around that we v/ere not willing to he helpful. I hope you will correct it if you encounter it anywhere. I do fear that people abroad^ sometimes work on the assumption that there is a full supply .of. new cars here, on which we can drav/ at will. You at least know how very different is the case at present. I am sending a copy of this to Tehran. Yours sincerely, E.P. Donaldson, Esq.. , India Office, Whitehall, S. . 1 •li&amp;XA OTmtf WHITBHALifts.W.l. 5~ January, 'm) Dear Urquhart, ill you pleaui« refer to your letter of 12th September Jo* 1^028/265/^34 about the sup. iy of eu*s for oonaiilar o&amp;ts y^Kaat 1 enclose a copy of a letter frern the kjvcrnaent of India / from wtiich you will see that there seema very little hope of dated suitable ears being suppliad from there* Cara are not manufactured 13 th i* 1 Ir* ia, Uiou £&gt; h they re assembled from liiported .arts; thus, any Decenber sent to ^aat Persia by the Govemiaent of India would have to be imported Aran this country in the first lace* hilc we fully realise the difficulty of obtaining cars in the J«iC* , we should be grateful if the Foreign office would reconsider the possibility of including the requirements of the vast Persia Consulates in their lists* As the Government of India point out, it is H*ihUG*s interest aa much as that of the rOV'. rmaent of India to aee that these Consulates are adequately provided with transport* and this the Gov* rniaent of India with the best will in the world are simply unable to 00 in present circumstances* Could we Join with you in an abroach to ar .Transport to secure the supply of the vehicles needed? I chits sincerely. * ur iUhart, q* Foreign Office S.W.l. SW-r ^ ^ . If034 BtXBflNAL AiifftlaS DffBMffMSNT, NKW DELHI 3, THE aSCEMBEH 1945. 131 r%tU Please refer to your litter No. Sxt.4622/45, d«ated the 26th September , €Lb out oars for consular posts in Persia. 2. The attitude of tne Foreign office to the provision of transport for consulates staffed from India is disappointing and is also difficult to understand. As you know, India does not produce cars and has no independent sources of supply, and the end of the war has in no way affected the position, except that such old cars ag were to be found in the country are older still l we have tried the Arny , but they hold out no hopes, on the grounds that the disposal of military vehicles is controlled by the London Munitions Assignment Board and that no cars are likely to be surplus,as ail types are in short &gt; supply. As for your suggestion that the Government of India might place orders for cars direct tnrough the India Store Department, or issue licences for import through agents, it is difficult to see how this would help. As you point out, quick results are not to be expected by this method, and the prevailing shor- tags in the United Kingdom, which the Foreign Office have given as their excuse for omitting the south and Sast Persian consulates from their scheme, would not be remedied by the adoption of the procedure you suggest. 3. We hope very much, therefore, that you will still find it possible to persuade the Foreign Office that since these are, after all, His Majesty's Consulates, it is in His Majesty's Government's interest as much as in the Government erf India's to sen that they are provi ded with adequate transport. 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to oastrell. noi-. 1 F. A. K. Harrison, Ssquire, India Office, LONDON. nd-’*—0 H IUsjol/u- COPY. (K.16271/265/254) * » / ^mOi 4. Am* / / ✓ F: : .;:3 V '• -LA 2 4|Dei r M45 t&lt;P X ***“ Ca«nfiKm«nti i’QKEiaN OFFICE, S.W.1. 6 th October, 19^-5* y&gt;± bj,y De^x Chancery, Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affain Your letter No. 110 of 21st August to the Office of the Minister Resident, Middle hast, which they forwarded to us. 2. A Circular dealing with official cars and an Official Car Code are in preparation, and they broadly speaking agree with your proposals. This Car Code should reach you shortly and help with your problems. Yours ever, Consular Department. The Chancery, ClX^yoJt. /s/oJvju-V). / (£) DRAFT LETTER Ext *462 2/45' 2 ^ SEP 1945 Lt.Col* R,R*Bumett, Joint Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Dept., New Delhi. SeotA. l 2 xvx*xcjfcC / Will you please refer to j^our letter No.F.40(5)-ME/45 regarding cars for 1 u Consular posts in Persia, j You will LavtT since have seen a copy of Our letter to the Foreign Office No .Ext #3 617/45 of 21st August, 1945, which was forwarded to you by air mail on 25th August, and I now enclose fNo.K.15028/265/234 of 12th September ) a copy of their reply. You will observe that they find themselves to 1.0. ih (UyJbJt) unable to include the transport requirements of these Consulates in their own supply lists, owing to^the current shortage in this country, swr£ JU ■■ mie IHJ. 2 Q Wrfft' . AN ,. ^P'l r„ -Jw D ( 'SaSfSaHHlHfeHbAAAMBnJLMM * k f' -•xor. y . 11 * Secretaiy, External Department Gars are not manufactured in India, although they are assembled fran imported parts. India has, therefore, to rely on ttuports from the United Xingdon, U.S.A. or Canada. Exports from the U.K. are subject to Board of Trade quota for the present. Up to the end of the Japanese war it has been impossible to find shipping space for any quantity of civil cars fran this country, owing to the very great pressure for military cars. With the change in the situation with regard to shipping space arising on the cessation oi the war, it would be possible to ship substantial quantities of civil cars to India during the next three months, but unfortunately the manufacturers have diverted the bulk of their export quota to other destinations, on information furnished by us as last, that it was unlikely that we should be a ^le to ship^any civil cars to India. V7e are, however^/pressing the Association and individual firms to make available as large a quantity as possible in the irmediate future and we have advised the G-overnment of India to issue import licences freely. With regard to purchases in i .S.A. and Canada, tlie position is conplicated by exchange difficulties. The Canadian G-avemment lias made a substantial allocation of cars for India and the Govemnent of India have been advised. The demand for cars for civil requiranents is far in excess of the supply and a sbiiilar system is working to that in this country, i.e. the cars are allocated for essential civil requirements, e.g. doctors, nurses, etc. The G-overment of India will have a similar, if not greater, difficulty than the U.K. Government in finding the cars required for consular posts in Persia. But it may be that they will be able to meet* the requirement from surplus Army cars, or alternatively we might put the case specially to the Board of Trade to obtain priority allocations* If it is de. ired to adopt this course the Government of India should either place the orders direct through the India Store Department, or issue import licences for import through agents and advise this Office, in order that the question might be taken up with the Board of Trade. * - —- * ~° A - ' ‘ t ijjppf ’ t aca^ r i *2 H .^i . A . ixO o_Lbnl I'm*: ^Gr. .far (K F.J FlL£: Copy (K 15028/265/234). ^ Dear Harrison, S/ V • ». J EXT 4622 FOREICtH OFFICE, S.7.1. 12tn September, 1945. Your jlettej 1 S4-6 3617F45 of the 2 1st August to Pyman 1 ^So'uttn^supply of cars i'or 'uonsular posts in Persia. 2. We are afraid that we cannot Undertake to do what you ask in your second paragraph* Cars are also in extremely short supply in this country and we are not within sight of obtaining enough for our ovm normal requirements abroad. Assuming tnat tnere were no cars at all in India suitable for service in Persia when External Affairs wrote on 17th July, the position must have changed with the cessation of hostilities in the Far East and the consentient reduced need for vehicles for military purposes. 3. In view of this recent change in the situation we hope that the External Affairs Department will be able to take a more optimistic view of the X^ossibilities of supplying vehicles for use in Persia. Otherwise, if they wait for help from here I fear they will be sadly disappointed. (R.*. Urquha F.A.K. Harrison, Esq. , India Office. R£c ». t-CL. DD*t. I ' SEP me Iw f.ij dkixo ( .T l y-T ?/ - Will you please refer to your demi- official letter to Duke NoJUt.2Q41/4 £l dated 22nd Jun e , 1945, about cars for Consular posts in~Fersia? 2. The car supply position in India is at present extremely difficult and we should have great difficulty in fulfilling the needs of the Grovernment of India posts listed in Minister Resident, Cairo’s telegran of 20th April to the foreign Office. Sven if we managed to find the requisite number of cars ana station wagons and secure agreement to their export, they would all | be secondhand and their condition would probably be such that they wpuld have an extremely short life in Persia. Supply from India, if possible at all, would tnere- fore be most uneconomical* 3. We would strongly urge therefore that these requirements should be included in the list of cars to be supplied by the Foreign Office. The Foreign Office is ( .T l y-T 36 - presumably under which- 2 - EXT ?61T .a probao (a# maintained and these wbulcTprobably be suitable for our posts! ajr^o. It^femains to settle the financiap. implications] and we would suggest that n am ArEfange- ment would be for the cost to be divided equally between the Government of India and His Majesty's Government under the normal arrangement for diplomatic and consular expenditure. aszi^z,.K i7.jyj.ro St- (vjo e*t , ..' [COflfe R] FILE COPY ~|{&gt;e — rA /^ V-4.C n FILES WH* \\ 0“^ ^ FROM '^'1 SIDMT : S OFFICE CAIRO TO FOREIGN 3691 D. OFFICE V\ \ S’ .1,20 a.m. GMT 20th July 1945. No. 706. | '— * iFth 'July 1S^5^[945 JR. f.2.55 p.nu BST 20th July 1945. Repeated to Tehran. 999999 Your telegram No* 8] Saving paragraph 4. It is suggested that it should be pointed out to the India Office that the cars supplied must be new cars from the United Kingdom as there are now only very ancient second hand cars available and therefore their requirements should be added to those already submitted by us m my telegram No. 24 Saving. I [Copies sent to Sir E. Grigg and Mr. Armstrong]. BESo. 4Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State for India, Department, India Office, London, S.W.l, and the following reference quoted:— INDIA OFFICE, } WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.l. Telephone :— Whitehall 8140. I.O. Ext. No. Telegram# :— fctetaxandum, LondonDear Harrison, My letter K 6325/1691/234 of 25th April ahoat- g ara fo^- Consular posts in Persia. I enclose copies of telegrams which have passed between the Resident Minister at Cairo and the Foreign Office, from which you will see that we are progressing slowly. We assume that the Government of India is already dealing with the transport requirements of the Indian Vice-Consul at Tehran, Khorramshahr, Meshed, Zahidan, Meshed, Bushire and Bandar Abbas and Kerman. F.A.K. Harrison India Office» 14 JUN 1945 ! INDIA OFFICE!hhhhhmmhi HHHIHfl! C opy. ..PC 8286/3372/250) (The text of this telegram must first be paraphrased if communicated to persons outside British or* United States Government service or if retransmitted in a cypher system other than O.T.P.). / (GY PHER) ^ FILES. (MIIflSTLR RESIDENT) CAIRO TO FOREIGN OFFICE Sir E. Grigg. D. 9.15 p.m. GMT 23rd May, 1945. ho. 487. 22nd May, 1945 R.12.35 a.m. DBST 24th May, 3 945, Following for Crombie from V/ardley. My saving 24 of 24th April. Please make the following urgent amendments Shiraz 1 truck 8 cwt 4X4 (Morris or Humber) to read priority 1 not (repeat not) priority 2. This makes two priority 1 trucks for Shiraz. Isfahan 1 truck 8 cwt 4X4 (Morris or Humber) to read priority 1 and not (repeat not) priority 2. Bandar Abbas 1 truck 8 cwt 4X4 (Morris or Humber) to read priority 1 not (repeat not) priority 2. This makes 2 trucks 8 cwt 4X4 (Morris or Humber) priority 1 for Bandar Abbas. 2 . The total should now read as follows:- 34 vehicles 24 priority 1 10 priority 2. 3. The necessity for up-grading the priority of these trucks 8 cwt 4 X 4 is caused by the recall of three jeeps on loan fran Paiforce by the 31st May. IIskenderun 1 2i./30 h.D. saloon. IRAQ Mosul, Bagdad Basra 1 24/30 h.p. saloon. 1 24-/30 h.p. saloon„ 1 24-/30 h.p. saloon. ETHIOPIA Harar has been supplied with one car from the United Kingdom. 2. Discretionary powoi does not include re placement. Are any of the above cars replacements? 3. On receipt of your reply we shall seek Treasury authority for any necessary replacements and for the additional transport required for Kermanshah, Tabriz, Shiraz, Isfahan, Ahwaz and Basra As a number of posts are staffed and run by the Government of India, copies of this corres pondence have been sent to the India Office for necessary action.* External Affairs Department, New Delhi, YV't\ i ^ * T 1 C'i ' M \\ strike one forcibly regarding the position of Consuls in that country. Our excuse ioi wriu ng to you on unis subject is that at. tne present moment the majority oi tne Jonsula apcoi-iui ■ *i.tb in Persia, to be exact I think the numbsi is Service, and 'we have for generations pscn ^ interested in tie functions and opportunities oi Consular posts in Pe-sia. 2, I made the personal suggestion to Bullae, ti-at trie meicher of his staff cnosen for paying periodical visits to Consulates mignt perhaps be tne A ditional Conseilor found from tne ( # Indian Seivice, if only because Consular duties in Po-sia in tne present circums jeve h ■ ely aii adaiinistrative complexion »nd Indian Service officers are accustomed to administration^ I 1 1 link he was well disppsea to tne suggestion, whicn mi nt be taken further as soon as we are in a oosition to appoint a successor to liacann. fhe su estion ha m fact been ma b in Igui^g s time bum it was impossible to carry out then for the reason tin t he wiiei t collecuj on* with- 2 - 3. There is a fu tner aspect of^tris question v.nich anyone accttstoiasd to conditions in the hink i as of importance* There must be a considerable difference of emphasis as between to« '* ^ a ^ x x ^ Gonsilax duties in couno) les such as Pe - sia ano in European countries or icr. Lj a country such as Peisia, particularly at tne present, time u .en txxe.re is so mucr Y^ork of a quasi- acministrative character to be put trr ouyn, a Consul, wxo ooes not know tne waole of ms District ax-d villages and t.ie tribes, is unlikely to be able to achieve much. While this point will probably be accepted, it is obvious that it nas not been possible to do anca as yet to p:&gt; ovioe Consuhoi officei s witn tne .xieaiis to tour. In most cases in r • sia those Consuls who went from Ixx: ia o. 5finally imported tneii omi cars widen are now wearing out aim, t sy a e unable to # obtain spare pa.* ts. In one case tmt Bullard himself mentioned to me,that of Fletcher now Consul en al Aiiwaz, great assistance was offered by toe Co-xmanaer of PAID Wxxo made a station-wa sJ on available, but while I was in Teheran its x eturn was Meanwnile it appeals tnat the Pussian colleagues of His ,hjesty T s Consuls in Persia have' everythin* they want including in many cases jeeps. I am unable oo vouch for either stoiy, out I was told of a case of one Consul in Persia who hat to call recently on tx_e local Governor Cent.m l in a drosnky, aid of anotne] w*.o found himself com eilec to ask his Russian colleague for transport. It is not easy for us in 1. to take this tatter ug to cover tne Consulates ataffSfrom Imia, since in such case ths Finance De pa -1.^ent wo aid .i eas onabl v # decl ^ ne t o make a. contribution exc&lt; gt in compliance with neral principles laid down by His L-ajesty’s Government, ana it seems to us Uxau one wnolo'N ^ In any further oounnunioution on this subject, piease quote No. and address —not to my person by name, but to— '' The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, 3.W. 1. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents compliments to and, by direction of the Secij^ary of St* transmits herewith cop Foreiq?i Office, of the under-mentioned paper.£*K HslC*I‘ t-*. [ X 8066/799/504 ] Circular. Foreign Office, 9th December, 1943. Sir, B\ Order-in-Covincil dated the 20th May, 1943, the Foreign Office and Diplomatic Service, ^^Consular Service and the Commercial Diplomatic Service were amalgamated so as to form a smgle F’oreign Service, which eventually will be recruited through one examination, will be subject to a single code of regulations, will be differentiated as to salaries by grades rather than by posts, and will come under a new Pensions Scheme. All these matters of administrative detail are now under consideration so that they may be ready for publication before recruitment on a permanent basis begins again after the war. By the amalgamation of the Diplomatic and Consular Services, the Foreign Service of the United Kingdom has at last adopted a system which has prevailed in almost all foreign countries for a considerable time; and public opinion here has welcomed this change as being timely, indeed overdue. 2. During the nineteenth century and up to the outbreak of war in 1914, the Consul was-, generally speaking, regarded simply as the official in charge of local British interests in an important foreign city; he negotiated on their behalf with the local authorities; he reported occasionally on trade and on political matters. But it is probably true to say that a Consul regarded his main functions as those of being the leader of the local British community, and of seeing that his office effectively discharged its notarial and administrative duties of a routine character. The history, traditions and atmosphere of the Consulate were, naturally enough, quite different from those of the Mission. , 3. To-day the Consul and the Consulate in those countries where His Majesty’s Missions are located find that they are playing an increasingly active and important part in the Mission’s work, and in fact have become part of its regular machinery. In due course, diplomatic, commercial diplomatic and consular posts will be interchangeable, and members of the Foreign Service may be called upon to serve in any of these three categories. In the meanwhile, it is desirable that members of the Foreign Service, in whatever capacity they may be serving, should adjust their outlook as fully and as soon as possible to the significance of the change involved in the amalgamation of the Services. 4. I am enclosing in this despatch a memorandum submitted to me by a friendly critic who was at one time temporarily employed under the Foreign Office. He writes about the Consular Service in the United States, with the work of which he was familiar; but the warning conveyed in this memorandum should be applied wherever diplomatic and consular staffs are working side by side, so that we may see a speedy disappearance of what he calls “ the gulf which separates the members of the diplomatic and the consular corps and which prevents a free exchange of knowledge and ideas between the two.” 5. The Order-in-Council of the 20th May last decreed, at any rate in principle, the abolition of this gulf. I rely on you to do all in your power to ensure that by means of corporate effort and mutual understanding the gulf shall prove to have been abolished not merely in principle, but—and this is far more important—in actual practice. The Mission’s staff must keep in close contact with their colleagues serving in consular posts, and all officers alike should feel that, beinj, equally members of the Foreign Service, they are all members of a single team under the direction of His Majesty’s Representative. His Majesty’s Career Consular Officers. (42/1943) 12199a [*26331—8]2 6. 1 he sphere of diplomacy nowadays includes trade and finance, labour and agriculture, cultural relations, &amp;c., in all parts of the country in which the Mission is stationed. This brings the Consulates at once into the picture as ready-made (but perhaps insufficiently appreciated) instruments of national policy. 7. This linking-up of the Consulates with the Mission in turn results in emphasising the representative character of the Consul as the symbol of the United Kingdom. He is, as it were, the Ambassador or Minister in parvo; and as such fulfils, within his district, many of the functions of the diplomatic Mission 8. It will hardly be possible for Consuls to fill adequately the wider role which ina^K0 conditions require of them if they are not kept in personal touch with the Mission. The Heau*of the Mission should make it his aim, if possible, to visit every year all career consular posts under his supervision; if he is himself precluded from going, then his Counsellor or Head of Chancery might go in his place. Such visits are, in fact, becoming more and more one of the regular functions of a Mission, and are sometimes usefully combined with an official call, in which the Consul should take part, on the local authority and with a reception given to the local British community. In some countries such visits can be easily arranged. In some they will involve rather long absences, in which case I w r ould not wish to insist on an annual visit. If in one year only 50 per cent, or 75 per cent, of the consular posts can be visited by the Mission, then the remainder should have prior claim for a visit in the following year. But, on the other hand, 1 think it is essential that the career Consuls should visit the capital at least once a year, when suitable arrangements should be made for their lodging and entertainment. Consuls should also try to exchange visits from time to time with their colleagues in other posts T should certainly support applications for any increased expenditure involved in these activities; and, in the case of His Majesty’s Missions, they may mean an increase of staffs. 9. Closely connected with consular work on its economic side is the work of the Commercial Diplomatic Officers who are now equally members of the Foreign Service. Their function is of course a double one. In the first place, they must assist and prepare the way for British trade, and, to that end, must maintain touch with local industrialists and importers, the British Chamber of Commerce (if any), local British interests and business visitors from the United Kingdom. In the second place, they must act as expert economic, commercial and financial advisers to the Mission, and, therefore, maintain friendly relations with local officials in the Ministries of Commerce, Finance and External Affairs. In his capacity as expert adviser to the Mission, the senior Commercial Diplomatic Officer at any Mission will probably continue, as in the past, to supervise the commercial side of the work of Consular Officers, calling upon them for reports as may be necessary. It will accordingly be desirable that when, as is directed in paragraph 8, Consular Officers make their annual visit to the Mission, the senior Commercial Diplomatic Officer should take the opportunity to discuss commercial matters with them. 10. Finally, since international diplomatic relations tend more and more to hinge on economic, commercial, financial and social questions, it is of the utmost importance that not only those members of the Foreign Service who may have specialised in commercial work, but all officers, whether, serving in diplomatic or in consular posts, should have knowledge of the economic problems, both local and general, which confront our own country and upon the solution of which our national prosperity will depend. It is for this reason, among others, that the need for amalgamating the Foreign Services impressed itself upon me as being of real urgency. Under the terms of the amalgamation, all new entrants into the Foreign Service will take a common examination in which a knowledge of economics will, of course, continue to be required. All newly recruited officers will be given an opportunity for practical study of the industrial and commercial life of the United Kingdom, of social conditions and of labour questions so as to fit them for their future tasks; and as soon as possible they will be sent to serve in commercial diplomatic and consular posts. 11. It may not be immediately practicable to transfer Diplomatic Officers to consular work, and vice versa; but I should be glad if you w r ould consider this possibility with regard to the staff at your disposal and the posts under your supervision. As you will gather from what I have said above, the future heads of the Service are likely to be chosen from men who are experienced in3 all branches of the Foreign Service officer’s work, and service in a consular or commercial diplomatic post should therefore be regarded as something natural and desirable. If you have diplomatic secretaries who you think might benefit by a few months' employment in a consular post or Consular Officers who should be given a few months’ spell of work in the Mission, T should be glad if you would consider the possibilities of such an experiment and inform me of your views. It would be an advance in the direction indicated by the amalgamation of the Services. I am, Sir, * Your obedient Servant, ANTHONY EDEN. [Enclosure.] A Note on the Future Organisation of British Diplomatic and Consular Functions in the United States of America. I. IT was probably never the case that a diplomat could conduct the business of his country successfully without a shrewd understanding of the political forces within the country to which he was accredited; but there was a time when these forces were concentrated in the hands of a comparatively few individuals, all of them of about the same social standing and living within reach of the Capital. To-day, with the widespread growth of popular education and a changing outlook, this is no longer so true. Even in totalitarian nations it is very evident that the riders have had to pay great attention to the attitudes of their public, although they are in a position to suppress minority dissensions From now on, the opinions and actions of foreign Governments will be largely unpredictable and unaccountable to anyone without knowledge of the life and thought of the people. This is particularly true of a democratic country like the United States; but unfortunately the pressure of work in the British Embassy at Washington, the unrepre sentative character of the Capital, the vast size of the country and the great differences between its parts, have all conspired to prevent His Majesty’s Ambassador and his immediate staff from obtaining the necessary knowledge by their own first-hand experience.* The study of newspapers, together with conversations with leading Americans and formal reports from Consuls all help, but, taken alone, they do not suffice. 2. 1 may perhaps be forgiven for mentioning my own experience during the past three years in which 1 have been privileged to work at the Foreign Office. 1 am profoundly grateful W my colleagues for the good nature with which they have listened to my amateurish efforts to make available to them any knowledge of the American scene that I may happen to possess, and 1 hope they will forgive me if 1 say that I have found it practically impossible to give them a realistic picture of American thought and life. This has surprised me, for never before have I had the opportunity to work with men of such high average intelligence and intellectual integrity, but I had not expected to find such widespread ignorance of the very texture of the American type of civilisation—a civilisation so different from our own and so deceptively hidden under what looks like a common language. In stating this I am. of course, partly.confessing to a personal failure; but I have come to believe that it is almost impossible to give anyone a real grasp of a human situation which is quite outside the range of his experience. How far a given individual can transcend his personal experience is a function of his own imaginative capacity, but for almost everyone the limits, are fairly narrow. What can be done with reasonable success is to bring * It is the case that the present Ambassador travels widely round the United States. But an official tour by a leading foreign representative is necessarily something of a quasi-regal tour; and, however many people he talks to, His Majesty’s Ambassador cannot by this method really experience the customary attitudes (as distinct from logical thought) of the districts through which he travels. [26331—8] B 24 others up to dnte on a situation of which they have a real background of understanding. During m\ mie in the Foreign Office I have listened to endless discussions about probable American h\h ions to this or that, often based on what some prominent American has done, said or written m on a vote in Congress or a Gallup Poll. It has been borne on me that, for most of mv colleagues, the Americans are not real people of flesh and blood with a life and a culture of their own; tlle - y eme rge from these discussions as thin abstractions, or shadows, to be classified as anti-Dntish pro-British, isolationist or the reverse, idealists or materialists; they are cardboard figures, good or bad. The absence of a vivid experience of the richness and quality of life, as it app ies o Americans, too easily results in an over-emphasis, or misunderstanding of particular trait which happens to have attracted attention at the time and it prevents a shreW stable judgment concerning American affairs. I write with great diffidence of men who have a far wider and deeper experience than I of foreign affairs, but I trust that they will grant that this situation is the inevitable outcome of circumstances which have prevented British diplomats from t gaining much knowledge of America outside of Washington and, possibly, one or two nearby H cities British officials stationed at Washington do, of course, show an intimate acquaintance with the personahties and mechanisms of government in so far as these are concentrated at the Capital, but they display the same difficulty in assessing those broad movements, attitudes and traditions throughout the Continent on which events in Washington so often depend. 3. If this be granted, it appears that a new, or an increased need has arisen for our Embassy at W ashington and the Foreign Office in London to become acquainted with the life of America throughout the Continent, This involves two things; first,, a general background knowledge of American life on the part of some British diplomats in Washington and London; secondly, some means tor keeping these men au courant with immediate popular developments. The’second cannot be accomplished without the basic understanding to build upon. It is true that diplomats are only directly concerned with foreign affairs; but the impulses of a people concerning their foreign relations are an integral part of their total conditioning and way of life, the one cannot be understood without the other. In what follows I venture to make a few suggestions as to how a knowledge of America might be brought to our Embassy and so to the Foreign Office in le long run. I assume that this problem will be of first importance in the future, and that its solution would justify a fairly radical departure from tradition as well as a moderate increase of expenditure. U. i' 4 ' Si ring th j past tw ° years 1 have visited th e United States three times on behalf of the foreign Office, and on each occasion much of my time has been spent with the British Consuls stationed in that country. In another memorandum I have given my impressions of the excellent work being accomplished by the Consuls. Quite apart from their technical office work, thev are performing two related functions; they are representing their country to a wide variety of Americans and, at the same time, they acquire an unrivalled knowledge of the traditions, customs, occupational and other attitudes, and political trends in their respective districts Taken collectively the British Consuls in the United States have precisely that intimate acquaintance with the life and thought of the country which is lacking amongst the members of the Diplomatic Corps. 5. But the really important defect of our British organisation in America, as I see it, lies in the gulf which separates the members of the diplomatic and the consular corps and’ which prevents a free exchange of knowledge and ideas between the two. This gulf, which is not confined to America, is perhaps more evident to the Consuls than it is to the diplomats; it is almost invariably the case that when two groups with unequal privileges and prestige are associated, it f is the less fortunate group who.are more conscious of the distinction. To the Consuls, the senior diplomats are remote and lofty beings who are unapproachable on terms of easy familiarity, whilst .i senior Consul will avoid placing himself in a position in which he could be snubbed or ^ cold-shouldered by a young diplomat. It is no answer, even if true, to remark that the Diplomatic Corps have no feelings of indifference with respect to the Consular Corps. The Consuls on the average, were not born with thinner skins than anyone else, and if their almost universal beliefs have no counterpart which can perpetuah diplomats are depriv own work, whilst tl outlook, and they ai direct their observat 6. The immedi 0^o relation with oi knowledge and ideas it will be many years then, the traditional itself. A similar pro country. The brand of executives; but e own headquarters ai result that the branc have the effect (whe of wffiat is going on i for its Diplomatic a Department official this very difficulty \ known this situatior promoting visits to headquarters by the actual conditions am in the alternating rol be maintained. Eve for the headquarters managements, and, 1 their welcome or sta realise how much it result, what attitude success comes when of holding his organis of easy fellowship wdi understanding of his immediate subordina United States is esse similar lines. 7. I am sugges should make a habit diplomats at Washin way, and when he addressing meetings, senior Consuls during should get on to easy in America to-day w&lt; any former Ambassu' the visitor should str allowance could be a his host’s American would be physically visit should be for t consulate, the distric m5 have no counterpart in the other corps, then that only emphasises the defects of an organisation which can perpetuate such an unfortunate misconception. The final effect in America is that our diplomats are deprived of what might be a magnificent source of information relevant to their own work, whilst the Consuls suffer from a sense of injustice which threatens to warp their outlook, and they are deprived of a knowledge of affairs at Washington which would serve to direct their observations in their own districts. 6. The immediate and pressing problem in America, I submit, is to bring the two services tf^to relation with one another so that the work of both may benefit by a free interchange of knowledge and ideas. It is the intention to amalgamate the two services in the near future, but it will be many years before the men trained under the present system have all retired, and, even then, the traditional gulf between a consular and a diplomatic appointment will not disappear of itself. A similar problem is met with in any large commercial enterprise with brunches over the | country. The branch houses and the headquarters staff are manned from the same common pool of executives; but even so the managements of the branches easily get out of touch with their own headquarters and then develop states of anxiety about their standing, with the inevitable result that the branch managements instinctively elaborate a series of defence mechanisms which have the effect (whether intentional or not) of depriving headquarters of any realistic knowledge of what is going on in their outlying stations. The American foreign service has a common corps for its Diplomatic and ConsulUr Officers; nevertheless, some years before this war the State Department official then in charge of consular appointments told me that he was experiencing this very difficulty with respect to his Consular Officers. The only way in which I have ever known this situation to be handled successfully by commercial enterprises is by deliberately promoting visits to the branches on the part of the headquarters executives, and visits to headquarters by the branch executives. In this manner each party learns something of the actual conditions and work of the other, and the two sets of men become personally acquainted in the alternating roles of host and guest. Only so can an easy exchange of knowledge and ideas be maintained. Even with these arrangements success is not always easily or quickly attained; for the headquarters staff are naturally in a position of authority with respect to the branch managements, and, human nature being what it is, the latter are not always sufficiently sure of their welcome or standing when they visit the central office, nor does the central office always realise how much it has to learn or how far out of touch it is getting from its branches; or, as a result, what attitudes of anxiety or resentment the branch managements are building up. Real success comes when the senior official of the firm—the managing director—realises the importance of holding his organisation together, and regards it as one of his essential functions to be on terms of easy fellowship with his branch managers. This not only gives the managing director a realistic understanding of his own organisation, but he sets a pattern of behaviour which is copied by his immediate subordinates. The problem of co-ordinating our Embassy and our Consulates in the United States is essentially no different from this, and, I submit, its solution must be sought on similar lines. 7. I am suggesting that the Minister and the members of the Chancery at Washington should make a habit of visiting the Consuls at their posts, and that the Consuls should visit the diplomats at Washington. The Ambassador has not the time to visit his Consuls in the ordinary way, and when he does make a tour his energies are absorbed in attending functions and addressing meetings. Nevertheless, it would be essential for the Ambassador to get to know his senior Consuls during their visits to Washington; even more important in some ways, his Consuls should get on to easy terms with him. For it is a regrettable fact that hardly any of the Consuls in America to-day w’ould claim to be on terms of easy, informal relationship with the present or fl any former Ambassador or Minister. When a diplomat visits a Consul, or vice versa, if possible the visitor should stay with his opposite number rather than be put up at a hotel. An expense allowance could be arranged to cover this. Naturally the visitor may wish to see one or two of J his host’s American friends, but the visit should not degenerate into a round of parties which &gt; would be physically and financially exhausting as well as a waste of time. The purpose of the visit should be for the visitor to see something of the work of the office and, in the case of a consulate, the district: to get to know his host, partly by spending the evenings with him and5 * 6 his wife, and for the two to exchange “ gossip ” (i.e., news and views) about their respective work. In this way the Consul would learn something of the problems and negotiations going forward at Washington, and the diplomat would hear and see something of the character and attitudes of the Consul’s district. In practice, neither would be able to convey much to the other until each V had visited the other man’s ground; for, as explained above, a realistic “knowledge by description ’’ cannot be built up from nothing, it must stand on a foundation of “ knowledge by acquaintance.’’ For the reasons already given the Ambassador should make every effort to have his senior Consuls to stay with him in rotation at the Embassy, from time to time. 8. There might be a temptation, which should be resisted, to whittle this programme dovl to the appointment of one official, stationed at Washington, whose function it would be to visit the Consulates in turn, bringing them news and views from Washington, and taking back to Washington accounts of the districts. This, in effect, is what 1 have been doing for the past two years, stationed at the Foreign Office. I hope that I have been of some slight use, bvit, speaking broadly, this work has not been very successful. As explained in paragraph 2, it is almost impossible for one so-called “ expert ’’ to bring to others a realistic picture of a complex human situation unless the latter have some ground work of direct acquaintance. Secondly, the “ travelling ’’ official, by the very fact that he is always travelling, can take no very responsible part in the diplomatic w r ork at Washington. The periodical appearances of this man at a Consulate would do very little to break down the gulf which exists in the Consul’s mind between himself and the Embassy. The only cure for this is for the Consul to visit Washington. But the Consul himself will be in no better position than the “ expert ’’ in trying to tell his story unless he is speaking to men who have visited at least some, of the districts—the visiting must take place in both directions. The conference of Consuls which the Ambassador convened at Washington last January performed a useful function, but this is no substitute for the kind of visiting I am suggesting. Consuls, cannot be handled en masse with sufficient leisure and informality for the purpose under discussion. 9. If a reasonably close and informal relationship were built up between those holding consular and diplomatic posts in America it would then become possible for each to impart to the other much useful news by correspondence between visits. I hove read a number of consular reports to the Embassy, and some of them are very good so far as they go, but they stop short of a realistic description of the life and thought of their districts. This is quite inevitable, for anyone who has lived abroad knows that it is practically impossible to write a description of the scene around him to a friend at home, unless the latter has some acquaintance of the district ; on the other hand, how delightful it is to write and receive a gossipy letter if, both parties have some common knowledge of the ground. Two things are needed for successful correspondence of this sort; a state of friendship or fellowship between the two correspondents, and a common basis of experience on which to build. To-day the Consuls and the diplomats in America lack both these requisites. Consequently, the consular reports are formal documents largely concerned with what Americans think or do about us, or about some political or economic . question. These are important matters, but in the absence of the relevant background of daily life such reports merely re-enforce h false picture of Americans as consisting of a bundle of apparently unrelated opinions and activities, dissociated from the texture of their daily circumstances. Written accounts of human situations are best when they are least formal and approximate to intimate letters between frjends. Such letters convey much to other people who may read them, provided the latter have a sufficient knowledge of the topics; this is why collections of letters, and informal diaries, give such excellent pictures of past times. 10. When a real relationship between the Consuls and the diplomats in America has been built up, other ways will disclose themselves in which the two groups can collaborate to their common advantage. But the basis of all teamwork is human fellowship. This is beginning to be realised by the more progressive of the large commercial firms, and it has always been recognised by diplomats in their dealings with foreign Powers. No Ambassador in his senses would omit to cultivate human relations with the leading politicians and officials in the country credited; he would recognise that he and they could not conduct friendly both parties belonged in some sense to one “ social system.’’ Similarly our VI K V Consuls and diplomats cannot work together unless they constitute one “social system. The same sort of problem has been met in the relations between our fighting services and between our departments of State at home. It is a fundamental characteristic of human nature that the whole man partakes of each activity in which he is engaged; there is no such thing as a purely economic man, official man, social man, &amp;c.; there are only whole, indivisible men acting in the light of all their instincts and capacities . Relationship cannot be confined to one narrow aspect of human nature. 11. I am aware that the proposals submitted above would greatly add to the already heavy &lt; *^frdens of His Majesty's Ambassador at Washington and would necessitate an increase in his uiplomatic and consular staffs. If it is believed that effective teamwork between these two groups is of secondary importance, then the proposals are not worth considering. My case rests on the belief that, in the United States at least, successful diplomatic work must be based on a knowledge of the American civilisation, where political action has its roots; and that any attempt to ignore this must result in a lack of shrewd and stable judgment both in our Embassy at Washington and in the Foreign Office at London. If this is true, then the effective co-ordination of our Diplomatic and Consular Officers becomes one of the most important tasks that any future British Ambassador to Washington can undertake. It would not be accomplished in any short period of time and its benefits would only develop gradually; for Consuls and diplomats cannot change their attitudes overnight, nor cap either side learn to work together without much practice. The result would be to build up a body of Foreign Service officials with a real working knowledge of America. As these men begin to be available for appointments in the Foreign Office we would be spared the situation in which we have found ourselves in the past. When I first came to the American Department of the Foreign Office, soon after the beginning of this war, apart from myself, a complete novice and an accidental intruder, North American affairs were handled in the department by one officer in the second room who had never crossed the Atlantic and a head who had been stationed at Washington a number of years previously and had never been back since. With the exception of one or two Consuls, at that time not employed in the North American Department, I have never met, in the Foreign Office, a single official who could seriously pretend to an adequate understanding of the life and thought of America, as distinct from the highly artificial society at Washington. I make this statement advisedly and I have weighed my words with the utmost care. III. 12. Throughout this memorandum I have deliberately confined my remarks to conditions in the United States, for I cannot pretend to be acquainted with the work of opr Embassies and Legations in other countries. It is possible that in many places it is less difficult for our diplomats to become acquainted with the character of the country. We share a European tradition and the size of these countries is small as compared with that of the United States. The States cover a vast continent and may be said to consist of 48 semi-sovereign countries. Although they spring from Europe, Americans have developed a civilisation of their own which is emphatically not Europeaffin type. Besides this, a Spaniard and an Englishman may not be greatly affronted by their mutual ignorance of each other. But it is a significant fact that Americans and, to a lesser extent, the British do resent each other’s failures of understanding; whether they admit it or not, both peoples assume a cousinly relationship and make heavy demands on each other. These' things, combined with our need for closer relations with the United States, probably call for a more highly developed foreign service in that country than elsewhere. Nevertheless, if the general trend is towards a greater popular interest in politics (including foreign affairs), it does seem probable that there will be a growing need to evolve some more systematic ways of studying foreign cultures than has been required in the past, and I venture to suggest that the proposals outlined above may. have some relevance to our Foreign Service in other parts of the world.No. 102. British embassy, TEHRiN. 1st May, 1946. U.$&gt; Lord, 1 have the honour to refer to your despatch No. Fal55^/45_Qf 3rd April, in which were enclosed copies of the tenders oi members of tiie Society of Kotor Manufacturers and Traders for the supply of saloon cars and station waggons for His Majesty’s Consular posts i ast Persia. 2. It is considered here that tne Humber 'Supersni^e' saloon is the best car for Consular touring in Persia, it is unfortunate that the specifications of the oupersnipe with station waggon body are not yet available, but it is probable that this also would be found to be the most suitable type of its kind. Left-hand drive would desirable. 3. xhe use of British makes, however, has the one disadvantage that spare parts are not yet readily to hand in rersia. it should therefore be stipulated that an adequate supply of duplicate parts should be furnished with each machine. 4. in these circumstances i have the honour to recommend that orders of aupersnipe saloon cars and station waggons should be placed with Messrs, nootes, by the orovernm^nt of india at the earliest opportuni ty. 5. i should add that the military type of number station waggon with four wheel drive is particularly excellent for touring if it can be obtained. i have the honour to be* My Lord, lour Lordship’s most obedient humble Jervant, 3d/- Illegible The Governor-General hi India, External Affairs Department, Government df India, New Delhi. RCS/ l- 6.4 6.EXTERNAL Secretary of State for India Government of India, External Affairs Department &amp;\tX May, 1946 . Donaldson’s letter to Burnett No. 21+26/1+6 of 10th April. Trucks for East Persia Consulates. 2. It is understood from Ministry of Supply that it might now be possible for reconditioned trucks to be made available froii surplus stocks in India. Station-wagons are still in short supply here but it appears from B-ishire Express Letter to you No. 538-30/5 of 1st February that Chevrolet station-wagons may no’, be obtainable locally. 3 . I should be glad to receive list of present requirements of trucks and station-wagons for obtaining which you still wish for assistance froia here.r ^■2 W / 'Of, \ From \ The Secretary to the CrOvernmen + ^ Tndio iecreuary uo uie uwvoxriimwii in the External Affaire De 4 To -His Britannic Majesty’s Ambassador Sxteao and Plenipotentiary, Iran, Tehran. Dated Simla, the /0/fr May 1946. Subjectj-Proviaion of a motor transport at (rovernment expense for the use of tne \dditional dounsellor, Tehran. Your Excellency, I am directed to invite reference to par‘\graph 6.\(5l of Colonel Castrell’s derni official letter Fo.dV'&amp;3/4b» gated th e 19tii Deceniber_194b and the enclosed extract irorii ur ularn.ont Iknne’s note dated t he 5th February 1946 and to state that the Grovernment of India have decided tHatuHe Additional Counsellor, Tehran should be provided with motor transport at Government expense in the same way as Consular officers in Persia and the Persian (rulf subject to the following conditions (i) the Additional Counsellor will have to surrender mileage allowance for journeys qualifying for travelling allowance, and (ii) he will pay a contribution towards the cost of running and maintenance of the motor tr ;nsoort in respect of journeys not qualifying for travelling allowance. These conditions will be reviewed on the introduction of a car code which His Majesty’s Government propose to issue regarding the supply of motor transport by them to their Consular pffleers in Persia. I am to request that the amount of contribution whioh 3ir Clarmont Gknne should pay under condition (ii) above may be suggested for formal sanction. 2. The station wa^on wnich 3ir Clarmont haa already ordered- will on its arrival in Tehran be treated as (rovernment p.vned and its cost, including customs duty, freight and otnar incidental charges will be borne by Crovernment. 3. As regards Colonel (la sir ell 9 s station wagon, which, it is presumed, h*s been left by him in Tehran in the hope that it will be taken over by Government in pursuance of the policy mentioned in paragraph 1 above, the Government of India agree to take it over only at the depreciated value which, in your opinion, could be fixed for it in July 1945 when the scheme for the supply of motor transport to Consular officers was accepted in principle. I am to request that the depreciated value of the car in July 1945 may kindly ue intimated and arrangement made for the supply of the car to a Consular officer of the Government of India who needs it most and whose requirement has already been conveyed to you. 4. The expenditure involved in the sanction conveyed in para graphs 2 and 3 above should as far as possible be met from the Budget allotment placed at your disposal in 1946-47.RLE^QPY 2 ° V.aX Xi A 1 ofl M.atno^n^^! No.303- 4, dated ! ,T egiried, iSjlS. frtan His Majesty 1 a Oonaul-^eneral for er Secretary to the G-oyeriJ f fairs Department, Simla. X^t&gt;V Subject:-Supply of motor vehicles to Consulsr posts •in Iran and their maintenance. tfpuld you please refer to your telegram No.2lA/C41P/ 46 of 14th February, 1946, to Hif=« ! aieaty’ s \mbasaador T&amp;irtn? 2. For the maintenance of these two trucks it is recommended that the same maintenance allowance aa that recommended for the maintenance of the i tor truck supplied by the Government of India for His Majesty 1 a Consul, Zanidan, in my memorandum No.l86/7/8i dated the 8th February, 1946, should be sanctioned. 3. In the case of the truck supplied to Kia Majesty’s Vice-Consul,,Zabul-Zahidan, a driver will not be engaged until such time aa the Government of India post an officer that post. Ido however propose that ^ clean e 1 ' should / be engaged in the meantime on ic.65/--osr mensem (Rs.20/- basic and # &amp;.45/- dear food allow^ice r 3 8s.225%) and thia amount paid from the amount sanctioned for the driver. b8 no , t i?^ d in m y memorandum N 0 .I 86 /V/ 8 I dated the 8tn February, 1946, that I have not recommended that a cleaner should oe engaged as well as a driver because present rate of pay of motor drivers and cleaners in Iran is fantastically high and I conaider that a -cod driver' should be able to drive and service a small truck or car without assistance. IN INDIA W’S LETTER RECEIVED 10-b~1946 . r</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000ff_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3693</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000ff</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3693</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/114(1) 'Supply of transport vehicles for consular posts in Persia and the Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-26T22:12:29</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (201 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 202; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the supply of cars for use of consular officers in the Persian Gulf and their maintenance. The file contains a promotional leaflet for Armstrong Siddeley cars (folios 157-166).The file contains correspondence between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Political Agency at Bahrain, the Foreign Office, the India Office, the British Embassy at Tehran, the Government of India, the British Consul for Khorasan at Meshed, the War Office, the Commonwealth Relations Office, the Ministry of War Transports, the Treasury, the Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders, Armstrong Siddeley Motors, Rootes, Jaguar Cars, Daimler Co, and Austin Motor Company.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commonwealth Relations Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Transport</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>War Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Treasury</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Cars</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000ff#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>