<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024102474.0x00001f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T11:55:47.213Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Political Depautmext. From, The Political Superintendent, Frontier Upper Sind. To, ■ The Commissioner in Sind, Kurrachee. Political Superintendent's Office, Jacohabady 2itli August 1870. Sir, In forwarding the Khelat Diary from the 8th to the 14th instant, I have the honor to observe, with regard to the 2nd para., which alludes to the disincli nation of the Khan to leave Khelat this winter, that, in this I think, he is quire right for the reasons stated in my report of the 6th December last. Since 1865, the same result has annually taken place from like causes, and therefore Captain Ilarrison's attempts to lay the cause of the Khan's unwil lingness to leave Khelat at Captain Sandeman's door is quite untenable. 2. The 4th para, of the Diary refers to Lus Beyla affairs, and having just read your letter to the Bombay Govermenfc dated 1st instant, published in the ' Times of India' of the 18th idem, 1 learn that the facts of the Jamote affair confirm the remarks made in the 5th para, of my letter No. 1110, dated 21st July last, to Captain Harrison's address, regarding the omission of all mention of those facts in what purported to be a narrative of events from January to June 1870, and it now appears from Colonel Marston's report, and from what Captain Harrison states in the present Diary, that the Khelat Government fail to inform the Political Agent of all that goes on, although they profess to do so. 3. Colonel Marston in fact shows that during the period for which Cap tain Harrison reported ' perfect quiet in Beloochistan,' (which was correct so far as his information went) the Jamote Chief was actually in arms with three or four hundred of his followers ' with the intention of attacking the Khan's Agent at Beyla, Shagassee Goolam Jan.-' I trust, however, that since the attention of Khelat has been called to this practice of omission, improve ment will be the result.( 2 ) 4. Referring to the last para, of the Diary which states that &lt;f during the past week quiet has prevailed in His Highness' territory, and nothing has occurred to authorize the * Friend of India! in its issue of the 28th ultimo to state that anarchy is wasting Khelat, and that raids occur every fort night,'' I beg to report that that statement is no doubt greatly exaggerated, so far as the past few months are concerned; but to show, on how utterly uncertain a basis the peace and quiet of His Highness' territory at present rests, I have just received a report made by the Naib of Bagh, that notwithstanding the Khan s outpost arrangements in Eastern Cutchee, the Murree leader, Kurrum Khan Bejuranee, has just swept that border for fifty miles from near Mittree to Chuttur, carrying off ten thousand sheep and goats, and killing three men. 5. The force employed was 1,100 horse and foot of the most notorious border plunderers, so that the Murrees were evidently determined to effect their object, in spite of any Khelat troops that might venture to oppose them. None appeared however, so far as I have been able to learn, owing to the strength of the Murrees. 6. This fact effectually disposes of recent attempts to show that the quiet which prevailed for a time, rested on any sound basis, and just as this Murree raid speaks as to the actual state of affairs on the Khan's Eastern border, so docs the Jamote ebullition speak for the Western. There are elements of mischief and discontent in both, which though latent for a time, for want of opportunity, or one cause or other, will assuredly break out into action, unless they are removed by good management. I have, &amp;c., E. PHAYRE, Colonel, Political Supdi, U. S. Frontier. Diary hj the Political Agent, Khelat, from Slh to lith August 1S70. Until Wednesday morning heavy rain fell, and the Cupota river close to our camp, usually a dry bed, came rushing down at a terrific pace, the large body of water gave it a very grand appearance; such a fall has been rarely witnessed by the oldest inhabitant. On Wednesday morning I called upon His Highness, and when his Durbar had been dismissed, I asked what his plans were this cold season, lie replied that it'had been his intention, not only to have visited Cutchee, but other distant parts of his territory, but that under present circumstances, he could give me no definite answer. That as Azad Khan had returned to Kharun,( 3 ) it was necessary to find out whether he wished to be reconciled, or had re turned in an unfriendly mood towards his Government. That Sirdar Faquir Mahomed being here, he wished to make every ar rangement to place matters on a satisfactory footing at Kedj. Lastly, that re cent events connected with the Sirdars at Kandahar, had given rise to so ma ny rumours in this part of the country, that he could not decide upon any course of action at present. At the same time, should the English Govern ment wish to meet him in Cutchee, ho would certainly arrange to do so, though circumstances might render a protracted visit in that part of the country inadvisable. On F riday, the 12th, His Ilighness forwarded for my perusal letters just received Jrom Beyla, substance of which I communicated for the information of Government, pointing out that I had received no information corroborating the statements made in the ' Times oj India ' of the 27th July. His Highness called upon me on the same evening, and on my talking over the matter with him, he said that his Shagassee had strict orders to report every thing, however un favourable; that he should always inform me of what occurred, and that he was positive nothing had taken place to warrant the statements that had been made. In the same issue of the paper, above quoted, an extract from the ' Sindian ' of the 23rd July, states that a panic had seized the Chieftains and peo ple of Khelat, in consequence of His Highness having demanded documentary evidence regarding their possessions to certain Jaghires, and that this had been done under the tuition of a British Official in Sind; this allusion probably refers to myself. Bearing in mind the instructions of the Commissioner in Sind, as con veyed in the &lt;ith para, of his letter No. 206 of 1869, I have not interfered in any way whatsoever. Dost Mahomed Moozharee of Jellal Khan had possession of a Jaghire (crown land), and not being able to show any Sunnud, his right to the same had been in abeyance for some time past. He arrived at Khelat the other day, and on presenting the requisite Sunnud, the Jaghire was restored. Other doubtful cases are being enquired into, as also all Jaghires held by Ze mindars or Sirdars, on the understanding that they should keep up a given number of Sowars for the Khelat State. Those who have been under obliga tions of this kind to the Khelat Government, have either evaded their respon sibilities, or performed them in a perfunctory and unsatisfactory manner. The effect of this enquiry, has been, that when the Khyeries were in difficulties at Poolajee, His Ilighness was at once able to place forty Belooch Sowars on duty at their village. O i On the 13th I had the honor to forward translation of a letter from Deen Mahomed Gitchkee, residing near Bumpoor, to Bahi, Khan of Kedj. which showed that the portion of this tribe, who had succumbed to Persian rule, were any thing but satisfied. I, also on the 13th, thought it advisable to report at once certain information that His Highness had given me, viz. that the Persians were collecting their forces, and that the Ameer had been obli ged to send troops to Purrah.( 4 ) From the 2iid Instant the following Kafilas have passed through Khelat— 131 donkeys from Kandahar, with fruit, cloths, and other commodities for the Bjmbay market; 4 camel loads of tobacco and hemp from Mustoong con signed to Baorh. o o Several Affghans are passing through here en route to Mecca. Daring the past week qaiet has prevailed in His Highness' territory, and nothing has occurred to authorize the 'Friend of India ^ in its issue of the 28th ultimo, to state that ' anarchy is wasting Khelat, and that raids occur every fortnight.' C. W. HARRISON, Captain Political Agent, Khelat. No. 540 of 1870. Political Department. Prom, The Commissioner in Sind, Kurrachee, To, The Political Superintendent, Upper Sind Frontier. Commissioner 1 s Office, Kurrachee, 30th August 1870. I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt to-day of your letter No. 1199, of the 24th instant, and with reference to the 1st para, thereof, to inform you, that after most careful perusal of the portion of Captain Harrison's Diary alluded to, I can find no reference in the slightest degree either to Captain Sandeman, or his proceedings, so why you should go out of your way to say Captain Harrison had attempted ' to lay the cause of the Khan's unwillingness to leave Khelat at Captain Sandeman's door,' I cannot understand. Ilis Highness the Khan states he is perfectly ready to meet the British authorities in Cutchee at any time they may choose to appoint, but under existing circumstances, such as the uncertainty with regard to what is about to take place Seistan-wards; the return of Azaud Khan to Kharun; and the necessity of arranging something for the better management of his Mekran Districts, His Highness thinks it very desirable he should be absent from the Capital of his Kingdom for as short a time as possible. This is very natural and proper, and it would have been in better taste had you abstained from alluding to the assertion, made by you in December last, that the Khan had been a quasi prisoner in his Citadel of Khelat since 1865, and that he shrunk from visiting his districts. Sir,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100024102474.0x00001f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/22, ff 146-147</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024102474.0x00001f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/22, ff 146-147</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No.1199 of 1870 from Colonel Robert Phayre, The Political Superintendent, Upper Sind Frontier, Jacobabad to Colonel William Lockyer Merewether, Commissioner in Sind, Kurrachee [Karāchi]</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1870/1870</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-29T16:30:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Letter forwarding the Khelat [Kalāt] Diary for 8-14 August 1870 and highlighting certain items which he wishes to draw attention to.Firstly the Khan of Khelat's disinclination to leave Khelat during winter, which has not done since 1865 and which the Colonel states that Captain Charles Henry Harrison (Political Agent at Khelat) has attempted to blame Captain Robert Sandeman as the cause of the Khan's decision.Secondly the references to affairs in Lus Beyla [Lasbela] and the lack of information which suggests the Khelat Government have been failing to inform the Political Agent of all that occurs there.Thirdly regarding a report received by the Colonel that members of the Murree tribe had plundered a border area of about forty miles, and that they had used a force of about 1,100 men to do so.The conclusion to the letter uses the recent report to demonstrate the unsettled nature of affairs in Khelat.Enclosure to the letter:'Diary by the Political Agent, Khelat, from 8th to 14th August 1870' reporting on the Khan's plans for the cold season in which he had intended to visit Cutchee [Kutch] and other distant parts of his territory but that as Azad Khan had returned to Kharun it was instead necessary to find out whether he wished to be reconciled with Khelat. The diary entries also discuss reports in the Indian press of an incident at Beyla [Bela] which neither the Political Agent nor the Khan had received any information about; an enquiry being undertaken by the Khan into Jaghires within his state; and reporting on Kafilas passing through Khelat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024102474.0x00001f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>