<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x00016c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T15:31:35.173Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">VOCABULARIES ENGLISH AEABIG PERSIAN TURKISH ARMENIAN KURDISH SYRIAC [Compiled on behalf of the Admiralty and the War Office) ADMIRALTY WAR STAFFVOCABULARIES Pronunciation Consonants. ’ = a slight stop, as in the middle of the compound word sea-eagle ‘ = a weak aspirate pronounced in the tlmoat dh like th in this gh a guttural r h a strong aspirate kh like eh in loch q a guttural h r to be distinctly pronounced s emphatic s t emphatic t th as in thing z emphatic 3 zh like the s in pleasure Other consonants pronounced as in English. Vowels. a pronounced as a in about a as in far e as in get e (Turkish) as e in father e (Turkish) as in met e (Syriac) as a in gate i as in hit as ee in seen 0 as in go o as u in fun u as in pull u as oo in pool ti as u in tu Diphthongs. ai pronounced as i in mind au as ou in out HES.I i</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x00016c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/52</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x00016c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/52</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Vocabularies: English, Arabic, Persian, Turkish, Armenian, Kurdish, Syriac'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1912/1922</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-12T19:10:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">per</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">tur</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">arm</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">kur</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">syr</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (90 folios)</extent><extent>Words are listed in alphabetical order (in English) until f 74 where numerals are listed. From ff 76v-90 'questions and answers' are arranged by theme.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 92; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: the volume also contains an original pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume contains vocabularies for the following languages: English, Arabic, Persian, Turkish, Armenian, Kurdish, and Syriac. It was published in London and was compiled by the Admiralty War Staff, Intelligence Division, on behalf of the Admiralty and the War Office during the First World War.As well as providing translations of common words from English into the listed languages, the volume also contains a brief note on pronunciation, basic numerals, and commonly used 'questions and answers'.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty War Staff, Naval Intelligence Division</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>War Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Reference materials</topic></subject><subject><topic>Vocabularies</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x00016c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>