<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000049_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-06T10:36:20.084Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">IBo. No. 455. India Steam Navigation Co., Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) 'BAKP E TA' Voy No. 275 . Muscat, 14th.September 193 9- The Political Agent, Muscat. Dear Sir, J Will you please forward the enclosed two letters for me hy the next Slow Mail Steamer. Thanking you. I have on hoard four R.A.P. ratings from the Iranian coast Tfciich please arrange to send to Karachi hy the next Slow Gulf Mail as per instructions received from the Naval Officer,Karachi» j Yours faithfully,^ COMMANDERTelegram From To Repeated to No. Dated -*qr - Government of India, &amp;.A.D*, Simla. - Political Agent, Muscat. - Political Resident, Bahrain. - 1491 - September the 14th, 1939. MOST BIMKDIATE. Sergeant Turvil and three other ranks of R.A.F. being crew of aircraft which crashed recently near Jask have been picked up by steamship Barpeta and are due to arrive in Muscat 11 p.m. today September the 14th. Kindly arrange accommodation and despatch to Karachi by first available steamer.« T E L EGRAH. Telegram From To Repeated to No. Dated - Cypher. - Political Agent, Muscat. - Government of India. ^ A.H.Q. Iraq, Habbaniya. Political Resident, Bahrain. Embarkation Commandant, Karachi. - 320 - September the 15th. 1939. I N P 0 R T A N m . Your telegram 1491 of September 14th. Pilot and crew of LS527 arrived September 14th. Pilot informs me that the machine was a complete wreck. Codes held by him could not be found and may or may not have been destroyed. Party leaving for Karachi by mail September 16th Embarkation Commandant will please inform R-A.F. Karachi.T T -] L G R A I. T . Telegram From To No. Dated - Cypher - Political Agent, Muscat. - Political Resident, Bahrain. - 321. - September the 15th, 1939. /-v Government of India telegram 1491 September 14th. Pilot informed me that personal kit of himself and crew v/as left at Galak 78 miles west of Charbar together with some salvaged equipment. Possibly Consul Bunder Abbas might be able to obtain possession of the equipment and kit.Tele^rara From To No. Dated Received Air Officer ConEnanding British Forces, Iraq. Political Agent, Muscat. S. 353. 15.9.1939. 15th September 1939 . Following received from Aircraft Depot, ^rachi Begins. Request you delay departure from Muscat of Down Mail Steamer pending arrival of Steamship Barpeta with four airmen of crashed aeroplane from Charbar. Request you make necessary arrangements for airiren to be transferred from steamship Barpeta to Down Mail sjbeamer for passage to iCarachi. Advise expected date and time of arrival at Karachi Ends. Request you take necessary steps.T -i: L II 0 R A I T Telegr^im From To Repeated to No. Dated -Inter-departmental. -Political Agent, Muscat. -Political Resident, Bahrain. -Government of India and Embarkation Officer, Karachi. -330 -17th September 1939. My telegram No. 320 dated 15th September addressed Government of India. Owing to possible complications at Charbar R.A.F. details will leave by next mail,which does not call at a Persian Port. Due Karachi September 26th. Following for Embarkation Commandant. Please inform R.A.F. Aa o p y. V 5 Bo. No. 455. British India Steam Navigation Co., Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Sm 'BARPETA'* Voy. No.. 275._ Muscat, 14th. Septr. 1939 . _ The Senior Naval Officer, Karachi. Dear Sir, 4 On receiving your radio message at 18.-30 hours, 12/9/L9 while on my voyage from Oharbar to Muscat I immediately altered course to steam along the coast between Charoar and Jask showing lights on the shore side and sending off detonators hourly to attract the attention of any one on shore. Before leaving Charbar I had heard that men were at a place called by them ’'Galatn’', so on reaching tne Longitude of Galag on the chart I steamed into nine fathoms of water, sent off detonators and as no reply anchored until daylight, I tnen steamed into 4 £ fathoms of water and again anchored and sent away a life-boat to see if we could get any information re: these men. Owing to a large surf which ran from about f to 1 mile from the beach it was found impossible to land and aX 11.00 hours the boat returned. As I was heaving up my anchor to proceed and pick ^ 2 p jny boat we saw flashes of light about 3 miles inland, naving no daylight signalling lamp I sent off another detonator to let these men know,the had been seen. I picked up my boat and returned to the anchorage . We then sighted a white flag on top of the only building visible also what looked like three men on top of this building.Yours faithfully n 0 P Y. Bo. No. 455. British India Steam Navigation Co., Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) S.S 'BARESTA* Voy . No. 375^ j Pa^e. 2 . 193 - | I sent you various reports during this time. At dusk we again saw flashes of light and were soon in touch with these men by morse. They stated that they were R.A.F.men stranded and required help immediate ly, would I send a boat(two men slightly injured). I told them in reply to be on the beach at daylight when another attempt to take them off would be made. My boat left the ship at dawn and was soon outside the surf but it was impossiole to cross this as the boat would have been smashed up. The men were seen on shore and signalled to.After a time &gt; the boat managed to go inside the first line of breakers and my Third Officer,Mr.N.C.E.Little,swam through to the shore with a line and lifebuoy. The first man could swim and with help managed to get on board the boat but the other three men had to be brought out oy tne 3rd.Officer and two lascars, named. Valla Pema and Jairam Earron, wi th the help of line and buoy. The boat arrived out to the anchorage at 09.40 hours when T left for Muscat informing you T had done so. My Chief Officer,Mr.C.P.0’Kill in charge of the boat. Third Offleer,Mr.N.C.E.Little,who swam on shore,and the two lascars, Valla Pema and Jairam Narron,did splendid workjand I am pleased to say the whole boat’s crew. j - Time first message received;13.00,12/S/39;men rescued, 09.00,14/9/39;left for Muscat 09 .47 , 14 / 9/39 #NAVAL AND SHIPPING. \ IX, A. BRITISH NAVY. (1) Movements of H.M*s Ships. Prom To Previous number. 166 .SECRET, Office of the Senior Haval Officer, Persian Gulf. 25rd February 1940. No.5 Sir I have the honour to inform you that from 9th March 1940, the Office of the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, will be disembarked at Bahrain. It is requested therefore, that all correspondence which will reach the Senior Naval Officer on or after that date may be addressed as follows:~ The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, and enclosed in an outer envelope (even if not confiden tial or secret) addressed to:- The Naval Officer-in-Charge, H.M.Naval Base, Bahrain. No mention should be made of a ship 1 s name. Mails for the Commanding Officer, H.M.S.'Sho.'eham', should be dealt with in the normal way. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant CAPTAIN SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER PERSIAN GULF. H.B.M*s Ambassador, Baghdad. H.M.Minister 9 Tehran. „ , The Flag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Navy. The Hon.The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. The Air Officer Commanding, British Forces in Iraq. The Assistant Secretary, Government of India, Simla. The Captain-in-Charge, H.M.Naval Office, Colombo. H.M.Consul, Basrah. H.M.Vice Consul, Khorramshahr. The Principal Sea Transport Officer, Bombay. The Sea Transport Officer, Karachi, The Political Agents, Bahrain, Muscat and Kuwait. Officer Commanding, R.A.F.Base, Basrah. B.S.&amp; T.D., Basrah. The Commanding Officers, H.M.Ships of the Per Division*Telegram TELEGRAM. © From - Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Addressed to - Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Repeated £o - Politic al Agent, Muscat. No. - 1302 Z. Dated - October 27th, 1940. K.M.S. Gnat accompanied by Admiralty Oiler 'Oiler Slavol' will call at Muscat for night of November 1st en route AdenSECRET. No. C/584. Muscat, the 30th 1940. To His Highness Saiyia Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Your Highness, I have the honour to inform Your Highness that His Majesty's Ship 'Gnat' accompanied by Admiralty Oiler 'Slavol' will call at Muscat for the night of November 1st. Your Highness 1 s sincere friend, His Britannic sty's Consul, Muscat.October the 30th 1940 From Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. To His Britannic Majesty f s Consul, Muscat. After Compliments, Reference your secret letter No.c/584 dated the 30th November 1940 (presumably 30th October 1940) . We thank you for the information contained therein. Your sincere friend. Sultan of Muscat and Oman.Telegram From To No. Dated - XX - Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. - Political Agent, Muscat. - 0915 Z. - October 31st, 1940. My 1302/27. Regret engineers do not now permit of this visit but ship will pass as near as possible if in daylight tomorrow Friday.SECRET . No. C/592. Muscat, the 1st November,1940. To His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Your Highness, Reference this Consulate letter N 0 . C/584, dated the 30th October 19^0. 2 . I have now been informed that H.M.S. '’Gnat' will not be able to call here but will pass as close to the coast line as possible during day light. Y 0 ur Highness’s sincere friend, His Britannic Majesty's Consul, /icg or, Musc at.Telegram From To Repeated N 0 - Dated TELEGRAM* - I.D. - Senior Naval Officer, Per - Political Agent, Muscat. - H.M.S. ,, Lawrence ,, , H.M.S. “Falmouth”, H.M.S. ''Parvati’', y Commander-in-Chief, East Indies, ^o. 242, and Flag Officer Commanding, Royal. Indian Navy. - 1438 Z. - January 8 th, 1941. S.S. 'Warialda' hired collier will arrive at Muscat a.m. Friday to coal H.M.S. 'Parvati'. 2 . H.M.S.'Lawrence” report Warialda's E.T.A. Muscat to Political Agent, Muscat repeated authorities addressed above. A TELEGRAM. Telegram - I.D. From - H.M.S. 'Lawrence'. To - Political Agent, Muscat. Repeated to - Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. 'Falmouth', H.M.S. 'Parvati', Commander-in-Chief, East Indies, and Flag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Navy, N 0 . - 0541 Z Dated - January 9th, 1941. 'Warialda' E.T.A. Muscat 1000 G.M.T. January 10th.TELEGRAM. Telegram From To Repeated No. - En Clair (by hand). - H.M.S, ^arvati'*, off Muscat. - Commander-in-Chief, East Indies, Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, S.N.O.R.S. - H.M.S. 'Lawrence'. - Political Agent, Muscat. - 1045 Z. Dated - January 11th, 1941. Muscat P.M. 11th January departure Warialda S.T.A. Kuria Muria P.M. 14th January. .TELEGRAM. /V Telegram - 'S'* From - S.N.O.P.G. To - P.A., Muscat, No. - 0742 Z Dated - January 19th Date reed - January 20th Request Naval Interpreter Golum All now on leave in Muscat may be sent to Khor Quwai in next up slow to join Seabelle.TELEGRAM. Telegram From To No. Dated - 'S' - S.N.O.P.G. - Political Agent, Muscat. - 1353 Z - February 17th, 1941. My 1232 Z/17 please inform Master s.s. ,, Pronto ,, he will be intercepted in Straits of Hormuz by ship requiring potatoes consigned to a secret address. Bequest departure signalled from Muscat be marked ^Important' in order that I can warn interception ship. M.O. Please given this letter to the Master and please issue the 'Important' telegram re departure as soon as you come ashore. T.H./18-2,41.CONFIDENTIAL . ? 0 litical Agency «Sr H.B.M’s Consulate, No. C/182. Muscat, the 18th February,1941. To The Master, s.s. ’’Pronto f *, Off Muscat. Dear Sir, You will be intercepted in the Straits of Hormuz by ship requiring the potatoes you carry consigned to a secret address. Yours faithfully, Major Political Agent 8c Consul, Muscat.Secret (yV i&gt;0 - C/114 of 1941. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Secretary to the Political Reeident in the Persian Gulf, huehire • 2. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 3. The Political Agent, Muscat, * 4t and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). ^ or i n f orTOa tion and guidance. British Consulate-General, I — 3aip^ | Bahrain. IBtK MMrOhi* *1941; Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1 # Telegram Ro.0742 Z of 8th March 1941 from the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf* Cash advances to It Commander Manson. 2. Bxpress letter No.C/ll3 of 16 th March 1941 to the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf.Secret* mm To:- Embassy, Bagdad, liinieter, Tehran (R) P*R*t P»G* Prom:- S*N»0«,P*G» TOO:-0742z/8•3*4l« IDG HELID 67/18 GrB*46* Political Resident’s telegram T/49 of 26th February, Appreciated if you would make any necessary advances of cash to Lt •Commander Hanson when he is in your area, and communicate details to me. Recovery from Officer will be made here but suggest inter departmental recovery be made in London*[N.B.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communieation more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to e re ^ * on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time an o o via e formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature oj a responsible officer of the Department.-] ^ ^ ^Utical *«»idtnt in the jereian Gulf, Bahrain* 79 . 16th tsaroh* 41# No *&lt;yus or wu. , w Dated _j ^ji,: the To - The senior TJoral ''ffleer, Jrerel&amp;n Gulf DlTlaion* Reference ~~ your tele^ruo Mo•0742 S, dated the 8th Varoh lG4i# Zasxtiy adYaneea required in nor area will toe made, Aa yai are recovering locally from the Offioer, eimpleet oouree for return of any advances made would be for you to return It to me or to the Political Agent oonoexned by rupee cheque* Please eonlina# Attested. sd. C.G.Prior. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. sd.J.Croning' for Ssoretary to the Polltloal Resident in the Persian Gulf. (Signature) s. 44. MFP—985 S&amp;P—(M-1597)—27-11 -36—10,000. (Designation)Telegram From To No. Dated TELEGRAM. I D. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Air Officer Commanding, *Iraq, Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Agent, Muscat, and Political Agent, Kuwait. 0609 Z April 3rd, £941. if® I am proceeding to Khor Kuwai today in H.M.S. Lawrence returning to Bahrain about April 9th. Correspondence and all messages should continue to Bahrain. faTELEGRAM Telegram -I.D. From - Commander-in-Chief, East Indies. To - Political Agent, Muscat. Repeated to - Political Resident, Bushire. - Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf No. - 1835 Z. Dated - April 25th, 1941. I shall be passing Peninsulai* in H.M.S. at about 12-30 G.M.T. 25th April. Regret I will not have time and should not enter harbour but I shall pass close to show the flag. Request you inform Sultan (Originator's number to S.N.O. 51).Telegram - X&amp;l I.D. From - Political Agent, Muscat. To - F.O.C.R.I.N., Bombay. No. - C/356. Dated - May 7th, 1941. Your telegram 1210 Z May 6 th. Can supply 7000 gallons water a day. Please repeat quantity required. Only about six tons small coal unbagged available. TELEGRAM. Telegram - 'I.D'. From - F.O.C.R.I.N., Bombay. To - Political Agent, Muscat. No. - 1210 Z. Dated - May 6 th, 1941. Could approximately 30 tons coal be supplied to one of His Majesty’s Indian Ships at Muscat about May 15th also tons fresh water. Request amount of coal available.TELEGRAM. Telegram - I.D. From - Flag Officer Commanding, R.I.N., Bombay To - Political Agent, Muscat. No. - 0957 Z. Dated - May 11th, 1941. Political Agent, Muscat from Flag Officer Commanding R.I.N., Bombay, Your 2104 May 7th. Ship v/ill not repeat not visit Muscat. secret. N°. 239-S of 1941. tu\ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1 . The Political Agent, Kuwait. 2 . The Political Agent, Muscat, v ^| ’r-i ' -4 and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document British Consulate-General, BUSHIEB. Dated 3$th .Aj&gt;rll,_}941. Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed Letter Uo. 0/114 of 16th March 1941. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter flo.311 Af 19th March 1941 from the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Subject. Cash advances to Lieut.Commander Manson.Secret office of Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf* H.M.Naval Base, Bahrain. No.311. 19th March, 1941. Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No.C/113 of 1941 dated 16 th March, 1941. The message to which you refer was only repeated to you for information since at present I am not sure that Lieutenant Commander Manson will be able to visit Bushire• 2 . 1 agree that any advances which you should make should be refunded to you or the Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient servant, sd. Cosmo M.Graham Commodore Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain.Telegram From - GTC. • Naval Commander-in-Chief, East Indies. To - Political Resident, Bushire. No* 1352Z* Bated 16th received 17th July, 1941. Vice Admiral G.3. Arbuthnot, C.3., B.S.O., assumed command of Station East Indies on July 16th in succession to Vice Admiral Leatham. - ADMIRAL COLOMBO - No. Jd^-33/2, British Consulate-General, Bushire. Dated the July, 1941. A copy of the above mentioned telegram is forwarded for information to:- The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty*s Consul, Bandar Abbas, His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman, His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Xhorramshahr.Telegrp k B S Fr#M Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. To Political Agent, Muscat. No. TOO 280725 /z Dated 28th, received 28th Ju MOST IMMEDIATE Most Secret. For information. tomorrow July 29th from daylight to noon approximately, please arrange any meetings which seem desirable to you with Sultan’s representatives. No gun salutes will be fired.DEPARTMEN T/OF FICE. Serial No. File No. Letter Draft Memorandum . Telegram No. 1. Date of despatch. Z. List of enclosures. After compliments. I shall be very grateful if | I may bring the Officer Commanding H.M.S. Capetown and any other officer he may bring ashore to see you tomorrow morning at 1000 hours • After that it may be possible to arrange with the Officer Commanding for you to look over the ship if you so desire. 1. Date of despatch. Z. List of enclosures. Usual ending Sd.R.E.R.Bird Assistant to His Britannic Majesty’s Consul Muscat. /S 5 (Small) B. P 6767/A /S-79—25-6-42—50,000 pads. }Telegram From To Repeated NSC A.P.A*, Muscat. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Political Resident, Bushire. © No.C/915. Dated the 30th July 1943. / Visit of cruiser was very much appreciated by everyone including Sultan*s uncle the Minister of External Affairs whom I took on board. - BIRD -V Wire file. Telegram N.S.C. From Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf To Political Agent, Muscat. No.TOO 271551/z Dated 27th, received 28th December 1943. For your information only. H.M.S• DANAE will arrive Muscat at daylight 1st January for visit of a few hours. Visit subject to U-boat conditions so do not take action until p.m. 31st December. Salute will not repeat not be fired. - Navycharge Basrah - i—Telegram N.S*C. From Political Agent, Muscat, To Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. No.C/ ' ’ a TOO 291030/z Dated the 29th December 1943. J'S Your TOO 271551/z January 1st is Proclamation Day and I will be occupied whole morning with political formalities. Can visit be postponed by one day ? If not, please warn Commander that a salute of 31 guns is being fired at 0900 hours January 1st in honour of British Government. - Political -—IX-A/1 Telegram N.S.C. From Political Agent, Muscat. To Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. No.C/1668 Dated the 30th December 1943. Your TOO 300646/z 2. State is firing the salute on account of Proclamation Day and 'DANAE’* should be warned it is not for her. 3. Sultan has already been notified that owing to War no salutes will be fired by His Majesty*s ships entering Muscat harbour. PoliticalD.O. No.C/1669 Muscat, the 31st December 1943. I Hela.B• 'iVAJW.n is wxpectoa to visit S&amp;LSC:it oax T Iy tomorrow morning. &lt;jwing to the war she will firs no salute. His Highness Saiyid L'aiu bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscut uad Oman.f mmmmw*' use Senior Naval Officer, Paraian Gull'. Flag Officer Commanaing* Royal Indian Navy. Coramandtr in Chief, East Indies. Flag Officer, Bombay Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. K.M.I.S* INVESTIGAX OR Political Agent, ilascat. N.O.I.C. Hormuz. Political ^ 4 gent, Bahrain. N.O.I.C• Bahrain. Political Agent, Kuwait N.O.I.C. Karachi. Consul, Bandar Abb&amp;s. Commodore, Aden. Too B50830 2 Dated 25th and Received 26th January, iD ^±6 IL'TOKTANT Cortf idential. Telegram From To Repeated Proposed (mut) cruise of-H.M.I.S. Investigator in Persian Gull 1 Flag Officer Commanding Royal Indian Navy 1 s 171158 not to all addresses. \ Arriving Places Departing. January 26th January 31st February 5th February 10 th February 13th February 16th February Uth February 23rd February 27th March 1 st March 3rd March oth March 6 th March 8 th March Bth Marcn 15th Khor Ruwai Bahrain Basra Abadan Kuwait Bandar Shapur Bushire Bahrain Chax*ak &amp; Ling ah Hengam nhor Kuwai Bandar add as Khor Kuwai Jash Muscat ^ Karachi. January 29th, February 3rd, February 10th, February 12th, February 15th, February 18th, February 21st, February 25th, (mut) March 2nd, March 5th, March 6 th, March 8 th, March Dth, March 12th, N.O.i.t. Jfcarmuz pass to H.M.l.o. Important. Investigator. 167 ImportantSSCRliT LA 1 KXPRLoS LKTXi^R. From Foreign, New Delhi, Resident, Persian Gulf. (Repeated - Prodrome, Baghdad). No. D 165-ME/45. Dated the 8 th January, l'J45. It is proposed that H.h.I.S. iNVESriGATOR which is being converted as training ship xor Joys of Royal Indian Navy should carry out instructional cruises, each lasting from two to three months, in Persian Gulf and elsewhere. First cruise will commence Karachi and in view of sheltered state of waters and smaller risk of enemy attack will take place in Persian Gulf and will probably include inter, alia.. visits to Bushire and Basra. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, has been requested to signify his concurrence. Grateful to know at very early date |hether * you see any objection to proposed cruise. Issue of the above has been authorised: (3d.) H Dayal Under Secretary to the Government of India.Telegram NSC From Naval Officer in Charge, Hormuz. To Political Agent, Muscat. Repeated Naval Officer in Charge, Bahrain. Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf. Too Dated and Received I9th February, 2945. Confidential. Departure Khorkuwai H.M.S. Muscat 0600 Z tomorrow 20th.a No. S- 2 y£ 20til. February, 1^46. To i*aiyid aiiibab bln Faisal, Minia+er for locternai Affaire, Muscat* Alter Compilmente. With reference to our conversation of £lay before yesterday, i have the honour to inform you that I have now received a further communication that H.M.S. '^ea * Belle' with the Senior Naval Officer on board is expected to arrive informally lit Itescat at 10 a*m. today* I hope, there* fore, ♦ ha-* he will be able to call on you •t ll a*m* and not 10 a«m* as suggested* Usual lading. His Britannic kaje&amp;ty^ Consul, Muscat. mNo. 442 of li&gt;46 \ IO Dated^^th March, 1^46 Saiyld Shihab bin Faisal, Minister for External Affairs, Muscat After Compliments • I.have the honour to inform you that H.M.S. '‘Investigator** of the Royal Indian Navy ax'rived at Muscat this morn ing. I regret my inability to inform you earlier. ! ♦ is expected that she will leave Muscat on the 12th March. Usual Ending. His Britannic Majesty's Consul MuscatTelegram From To Cypher. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Commander- in-Chief, East Indies. Repeated 4 Admiralty. Political Resident, Bushire. Naval Officer in Charge, Hormuz. Naval Officer in Charge, Bahrain. Naval Control Service Officer, Abadan. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain. H.M's Consul General, Basrah. H.M* s Consul, Bandar Abbas. _ Air Officer Commanding British Forces in Iraq General Officer Coramanding-in-Chief. Officer Commanding R.A.F. Station, Basrah. Officer Commanding R.A.F. Station, ^haibah. Area Commander South Iraq. Area War Shipping Administration. U.S. Naval Officer, Basrah. No. 1426 Z Dated 31st March, received 2nd April, 1945. RESTRICTED t Intend to move my headquarters to Banrain on 1st April. Request signals and correspondence may be routed there from that date. S. T.O.P.G. YG CONFIDENTIAL No. 318-S Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire, 3rd April, 1945. Copy fpr^varded with compliments to The Political Agent, Muscat^/ H.M's Consul, Khorramshahr..r-N Tole^r?.'! NHC From Navol Officer Charge Karachi To Political Agent, ?fuscat* Too 171207Z Dated and Received 17th June, 1945. Following is a repetition of m' r 171701 ^idrassed to Flag Officer Commanding Royal Indian Navy repeated Common~ or in Chief East Indies, Senior Naval Officer, Persian*Gulf, Flag Officer, Bombay, HJM.S. Bahadur, H.M.I.S. Lawrence, H.TM.S. Madras H.i % Malaya, Chamak from Naval Officer in Charge, Karachi begins fi^TQ view .of unfavourable weather off Karachi intend to oail K*M. 1*3. Lawrence and H.M.I.C. Madras on R.1D1R training cruise as follows 5- Arrive 22nd June 27rd June 26th June Place Karachi Khor Fakhan Muse at Karachi Lo ave 19th June. 22nd Juno. 24th June. H.iLI.t* Laurence to act as Radar targotV endsNSC Telegram From To Naval Officer In charge, Karachi. Flag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Navy Repeated Commander in ohief, East Indies. Flag Officer, Bombay. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Senior Naval Officer, Abadan. Senior Naval Officer, Basra. Political Agent, Muscat. H.M.I.S rt BAHADUR. ' HIMALAYA” »' ^KARACHI 11 ' MADRAS' ' 'CliAMAK' Too 200S02Z Dated and Received 20th July, 1945. Restricted. Intend to sail 'KARACHI^ and 'MADRAS' on RADAR training course as follows Arrive Place July 30th July 31st August 5th August 9th 2 . Karachi Abadan Basra Muscat Karachi. Leave July 23rd. July 31st. August 1st. August 7th. 'KARACHI'* to act as RADAR targetNSC Telegram From Naval Officer in Charge, Karachi. To Repeated Flag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Navy, Commander in Chief, Fast Indies. Flag Officer Commanding, Bombay. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Senior ' T aval Officer, Abadan. Senior Naval Officer, Basra. Political Agent, Muscat. I . .I.S. 'Bahadur'’ 'Himalaya” 'Chamak” Too 2303002 Dated 23rd and Received 24 th July., 1945. Departure 'Karachi” and 'Madras' in accordance with my ^ 0 ( 00502 . 2. 'Karachi' call signs for July FISH - GIG wireless telegraphy 9 OBOE GEORGE FREDDIE. Call sign*for August- ANALYSE wireless telegraphy 9 UNCLE ONKEY CHARLEY. 'Madras' call signs for July:- PROMOTION wireless telegraphy 9 OBOE i SUGAR* Call signs for August:- MAPLE •wireless telegraphy UNCLE NIC®-ELS. SUGAR. 3. Holding XC MERSIG and FOXO. 4. 'Karachi' continuous watch on port’s- wave for four hours from Karachi shifting to 500 kilocycles per second, 'iadras# continuous watch group V.5. Expected time of a' rival Abadan I500Z July 30thV *\ NSC Senior KaVol Officer, Persian Gull, at Bahrain, Political Agent., Muscat. Telegram Prom • To Too 241440 Dated and Received 24th July, 1945. IMPORTANT Restricted. I y .1.3. H MADRAS” ...T.A. Muscat 25I200Z to land two ratings seriously ill. - SNOPG -Telegram From To Too 2814452 Dated 28tl July, 1945. NSC Politicsl Agent, Muscat. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, at Bahrain, ■ f 9 Your signal 241440 of 24th July. Agency Surgeon reports as' follows . Both ratings suffering from intestinal Otasis. quite well. A.B. Nelson’s condition Mich improved. Grateful if you uould inform H.I .l.S. ,, I j adras ,, ,.r. Ra'Via Rao is - POLITICAL -Telegram From • To Repeated Too 030803Z Dated 3rd and NSC SBiaApr Senior Nav^l'Officer Persian Gulf, at Bahrain, Naval Officer in Charge, Karachi. Staff Officer (intelligence), Bombay. Flag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Navy. Commander in Chief, East Indies. Political Agent. Muscat. Resident Naval Officer, Shatt-el-Arab. Flag Officer, Bombay. Received Ath August, 1945. Arrival Bahrain 3rd August H.N.I.S. ,, KARACFI W B.M.I.i. u ADEIS 1 ’Telegram From To Repeated Too04030IZ Senior Naval Officer Persian 9ulf at Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. Naval Officer in Charge, Karachi. Staff Officer (intelligence), Bombay. Flag Officer Commanding Royal Indian Navy. Commander-in-chief, East Indies. Flag Officer, Bombay. I 4th August, 1945. LJEDIATI; Departure H.M.I.S. 'KARACHI' and N.LI.I.S. ' T ADBAS' estimated time of 1430 6th. Telegram From To Repeated Too04030IZ - NAVTCHARGE BAHRAIN -IIHBiHMBiHHMHI \ Telegram ^NSC Yrcri Naval Officer in Charge-, Karachi. Political Agent , Muscat. Repeat d Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Naval Headquarters, India. Flag Officer, Bombay. Too 280527Z Dated 28th and Received 29th August, i.945. Kindly confim ti at H.l.l.S 'Karachi' and 'radras' can call at huscat on or about September 7th and September 20th.NSC Telegram From Naval Officer in Charge, Karachi* To Flag Officer, Bombay. Repeated Naval Headquarters India. Political Agent, Muscat. Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf. Commander in Chief East Indies. S. Naval Store Officer, Bombay* Too 050702Z Dated 5th and Received 6 th September, 1945* Intend sailing H*M.I.S* H Kaifachi t1 and ^Madras” as follows:- Arrive Place Leave - Karachi September 7th. September 9th Bombay September I2th. September I 6 th Muscat September I7th. September 20th Bahrain / September 21st. September 23rd Abadan September 23rd. September 24th Basra September 26th. September 28th Bahrain September 29th. October 2nd Muscat October 3rd. October 5th Karachi - Both ships off loading 10 tons naval stores in ?Bombay .Telegram From NSC Flag Officer, Bombay. To Naval Officer in Charge, Karachi. Repeated . Naval Headquarters, India. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, political Agent, Muscat. Commander in Chief East Indies Station. Too IIII53 ADMIRACIRC Dated Ilth and Received I2th September, 1945. IMPORTANT Intend sailing H.M.I. Ships 'Karachi** and 'Madras’* for Karachi P.M. I2th September to discharge stores. Programme in your 050702 is amended as follows:- tA C&gt;*- Arrive Place ****** •• • • Bombay • • I2th September. I5th September Karachi • • l 6 th .September. I 8 th September Muscat • ♦ I9th September. 22nd September Bahrain • • 23rd September. 25th September Abadan • • 25th September. 26th September. Basra • • 28th September. 30th September Bahrain • • let October. 4th October Muscat • • 5th October. 7th October Karachi + • —NO.S.1317-9A Dated 6 th. Octobi r, 1945 V My dear friend, I write to inforia Youi* Highness that two Warship* - H.H.I.S. 'Lindias” and h.M.I.S. Tt K&amp;rHchl tT - are expected to arrive at yuccet on the 7th Octet-r and to depart the following day Your Highness’ sincere friend, His Highness 3aiy5d S»id bin Taimur, ^~l.tan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat•■■■■■■■El ■ i:o.s 1640 - 9/1 From. To. K.I.Hallows, Esqulro., Pol^icel Agent, Muscat* The Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, Bahrain Political Agency, Muscat listed the 20tb December, *45 ■ to I h&gt;- ve 4 be honour to reh er to your signa.l 2/,i46;C of Ju3y 24th, end tc forward trie atUcheu bill submitted by the Agency Medical Officer, iuseat, for favour of diriosal. I have the honour to be. Sir, four most obedient servant, — for Political A^'ent, Mu scat ,Telegram. GTC From. Political ^.gent, Bahrain To. political Agent, I'uscat ho.lo Qrted the 9th received the loth January, 1946 K. '.Ship Falmouth with Air Staff Liaison Officer Bahrain on board arriving I.'uscat morning January loth leaving . same day. Political Resident has telegraphed no objection. PoliticalTelegram. GTC From. Political Agent, ' us^at Political Agent, Bahrain To. No.G 23 Dared the 11th January, 1946 Your telegram ho,lo dated 9th January . Grateful if you will telegraph names and ranks of Commander of hkS Falmouth and Air Staff Liaison Ox ^cei. political.Telegram. Enclair From. political Agent, Muscat To. Senior -Javal Officer, Persian Griilf, Bahrain. No.C 24 Dated the 12th January, 1946 Your telegram No.llo953D of 11th January. Grateful if you will telegraph whether B-iS Falmouth will fire salute to country on arrival. politicalEnclair Telegram. From. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain To. Political Agent, Mudcat. No. o51H3D Dated and received the 5th February, 1946. H.MS. Shoreham will visit Muscat arriving P.M. 13th February. Leaving P.M. 17th February. Shoreham will not repeat not fire a salute. 051143 D SNOPG.Telegram. BTC From. Political To. ’ Political No.C 74 Dated the 6 th February, 1946. Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf has telegraphed that H.M.S. ’ , Shoreham ,, will visit Muscat from I3th to I7th February. 2. Sultan is leaving on tour to Sur on 9th February returning on I 6 th February. 3* If you see no objection, grateful if Senior Naval Officer could be informed and asked whether Sloop could bring Sultan from Sur to Muscat on I 6 th February. Agent, Muscat Resident, Bushire - POLITICAL -Telegram. GTC From* Political Resident, Pushire To. Rep. No. 232 Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain Political Agent, Muscat Dated the 9th received the loth February, 1946 ^ lut Your telegram 1134D February 5th. Sultan of Muscat is leaving for Sur February 9th and is due to return to Muscat February 16th. Could you kindly arrange for H.MS. Shoreham to bring Sultan back from Sur to Muscat on February 16th Prior.■ M Telegram. GTC From. Political Resident, Bushire To. Political Agetit, Muscat No. 249 Dated the 11th received the 12th February, 1 y&gt;&gt; bov* Ic) • My telegram 232 February 5th. Senior Naval Officer regrets will be impossible as Shoreham has to escort gunboats from Masirah to Karachi. Prior.T§legmffi. Enclair From. Political Agent, fluscat To. Headquarters British Forces, Aden No.C 91 Dated the 14th February, 1946* Important. Unclassified. Please pass to Has al Hadd. Grateful if you would send following message to Sultan at Sur repeat Sur. Begind. Sloop will arrive SUR dawn 16th to bring Your Highness to Muscat. Grateful if launch is sent Has al Hadd for Kahn Bahadur Abdul Haiy who arrives there 17th. Best wishes. Consul. Ends. Political 141555DTelegram. Enclair From. To. No.o51 Dated the RAF Ras al Hadd Political Agent, Muscat 16th received the 17th February, 1946 Unclassified. Reference your C 91 dated February 14th Request complied with. l6o53oZ— ■ So. C / 250-9/1 The Political Agent and His Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, presents his rompliments to the Supply Officer, Royal Indian Navy, Bahrain. I 0 and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document(s), with reference to his No .B2/T3 dated the 8th hehruaiy, 1946» Political Agency and British Consulate, Muscat. Reference to previous correspondence; Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. RECEIPT (IN QUADRUPLICATE) FOR Rs OFFICER. .48/- FROM THE AGENCY MEDICAL muscat.Telee^ram, GTC From. Political Resident, Bushire To. Political A^ent, Muscat No.428 Dated and received tie 22nd March, 194^ parjigr: pli 2 of ny Express Letter 64-3 January loth, Please telegraph Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf repeating to^e giving as much notjce as possible of date on which Sultan will be ready to embark at Dnofar. PRIORp Telegram. Enclair From. Political Agent, Muscat To. Headquarters British Forces, Aden No. TOO 231005D ( 0 157 ) Dated the 23rd March, 1946. Unclassified. Please pass to Salalah. Follwoing for Sultan. Begins. Grateful if Your Highness would telegraph when you will be ready to embark at Dhofar. Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf would like as much notice as possible, wishes. Consul. Linds. 231005D PoliticalTelegram, Enclair x From. Headquarters British Forces, Aden To. Political Agent, Muscat No. TOO 240810Z Dated and received the 24 th March, 1946* Unclassified. From Salalah P 29 dated 24th March. Yours C 157. Thanks. I will be reedy to embark at Dhofar on the 3oth March or on any day from that day. Please telegraph the date of the arrival of the ship at Dhofar. Best wishes. Sa5.d. Ends. Too. 240810Z ADENTelegram. Enclair From. Commander-in-Chief, East Indies. To. Admiralty- Flag Officer Commanding, RIN Political Agent, Muscat Port Officer, Seychelles Port Officer, Tanga Port Captain, Dares Salaam CS Simonstoym CS 5 FOG Ceylon NOIC, Karachi Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain Cap i/c Kilinidini Inspector of Produce, Zanzibar. Commander-in-Chief, SA No. TOO 291230EF Dated the 31st March, received the 1st April, 1946. Unclassified. Intend follov/ing programme for Jamaica. ARRIVE PLACE LEAVE Colombo 12th April 16th April Karachi 22nd April 24th April Muscat - 25th April 1st May Seychelles 3rd May 6th May Kilinidini 14th May 14th May Tanga 16th May 16th May Zanzibar 18th May 18th May Dares Salaam 24th May 1st June Siraonstown CCO 291230EFHIS BRITAHNIC l&amp;JFSTT’S COSSDUTR, MUSCAT, HO.C.28S-9A- Dat^d 7th April, 1946. My dear friend, I have the Lomor to ini'orm Your Highnees that tie cruiser H.H.S. ‘’Jamaica” will arrive nt Wuncat on the 24th April and leave on the 25th April. Your Highness’ sincere friend, His Highness Saiyid 9nid Mn Tainiurj Sultan of Muscat and Oraan, boTelegram. Enclair From. Political Agent, Muscat To. Navycharge, Bahrain. No. C 194 Dated the 8th April, 1946. Following for Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Your signal 020939D April 2nd. Grateful if you would confirm that warship will not fire salute to country on arrival. 081145D POLITICALI ¥Telegram From To No. /b-O'Ca, / En clair. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. 131029D. &lt;(\ A VTs * Dated 13th and received 14th April, 1946. Your 081145D. Jamaica will not repeat not fire salute to country on arrival. 131029D -NAVYCHARGE-Telegram From To Repeated No. En clair. Naval Officer-in-Charge, Karachi. H.MS. “Jamaica'. Commander-in-Chief, East Indies. Admiralty FOONHQ Captain in charge Killindini Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Political Agent, Muscat. 201011 EF Dated and received 20th April, 1946 2.3/ 2.1 Jamaica sails from Karachi in accordance with FITM 43/46 as follows (a) 0900 IF Monday April 22nd (fc) Muscat (c) 12 knots (c) Broadcast V and 500 KCLS (f) 0700 DE Wednesday 24th April. Request you acknowledge. 201011 EF Navycharge KarachiTelegram From To No. Dated En clair Political Agent, Muscat. Navycharge, Karachi. C.215 21st April, 1946. Your signal 201011 EF received Muscat radio can contact Jamaica on VTS 2, 10315 KC or VTS 3, 5305 KC. If this required please signal Jamaica's frequencies and times (GMT) -POLITICAL-/ ■ &gt; ' Telegram. Enclair From. H.M.S.Jamaica To. Political Agent, Muscat No. TOO 220925 EF April. Dated and received the 22nd April, 1946. IMPORTANT. Your 211143 to Naval Officer-in-Charge Karachi Will contact Muscat Radio VT S2, 10315 KGS and VT S3, 5305 KGS at 0505Z (GMT 23rd April) 220925 EF JAMAICAPrinted at Karachi July 1945. 5/- ) L. it ■ 'EAR MR HALLOWS THE FOLLOWING MESSAGE FROM THE JAMIACA QUOTE TO POLITICAL AGENT MUSCAT FROM JAMAICA ETA 0700 GMT WE^NES^AY UNQUOTE. ' WE ARE CALLING HIM AGAIN AT 1530 MUSCAT TIME ^ THEREAFTER EVERY FOUR HOURS YRTelegram From To No. Dated En clair Political Agent, Muscat. H.M.S. rt Jamaica M at Sea. Nil. 23rd April, 1946. For Captain from Political Agent Muscat. Have provisionally arranged for you to call informally on Sultan at 0800 GMT (12 noon local time) on Wednesday Hope this convenient. -POLITICAL-Telegram. Enclair From. Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, Bahrain To. Political Agent, I uscat Rep. Political Resident Persian Gulf, at Bahrain No.TOO 261320 * Dated and received the 26th Hay, 1946. Important. Pass to Salvage Of leer Persian Gulf. B.H.S. Sborehan will arrive Muscat AM 30th with stores for Salvage party. 261320 SNOPG.No.C.413-9A POLITICAL AGENCr, MUSCAT, Dated 27th r fey, 1946. The Salvage Officer, A.S.V. «S&amp;lTiola w Muicat. Memorandum. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gu7jT ? hat informed this office that HJI.S. ,, Shorel!aM l, is due AH' to arrive at Muscat on the 30 th May, 1946. with stores for Salvage party. for Political Agent. MuscatmmTele-ran. Enclair or;. Connan^er-in-Chief, East Indies, To. K.-C.T.C. Ader Salviola, Senior laval Officer, Persian Gulf, 2.0. TOO C 4101? Dat 'd the 4th -eceived the 5th June, 1946. Deferred. Unclassified. Corr al der-ir-Chief l editerranean’s 3111C1 hay not to all. Expect Storr King v'ill be recuired to proceed to Muscat soon after arrival at Aden to to?* salvaged vessel clear of harbour 2. Salviola at Muscat report to Aden in due course date tug is renuired. 041017 JuneGTC Telegram. Political Resident at Bahrain Political Agent, Muscat 5th received the 6 th June, 194-6. Circular . Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf has intimated that peace time procedure for firing of gun salutes has been reintroduced from June 1st. From. To. No.T/231 Dated the^4 / n Telegram. Q iTom. political Agent, Muscat at Karachi To. Political, Muscat NO.K25 Dated the 9th received uie loth July, 194-6. Your cele.gram C })0c July 7th. Please inform Sultan of Y^arship's visit I have telegraphed Political Resident that there is no objection. Halloas.No.C 5G4-9/1 Dated the 17th July, 194* lo The Minister for Internal Affairs, After Compliments This Consulate has been informed that H*M.I .8 'Dhanush* training ship of the rtcyal IndiriG Kavy proposes to visit Khor al J&amp;ram on 31st August, 1946 in course of cruise. for His Britannic Majesty’s cons - . 1 ,Telegram . Q From. Political Resident, kahr&amp;in To. Political .agent, Muscat No.1466 Fated and rec:ived the 3oth December, 1946. Senior naval Officer Persian Oijilf expects to visit Muscat in His Majesty’s Ship ''i’’dgooee arriving am 7th January and leaving on January 9th. Salutes will be fired on arrival. REPGUTelegram* Q From, Political Agent, Muscat To, Navycharge, Bahrain No. C 565 Dated the 31st December, 1946, Please pass following to Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, begins, T have been informed by the Political Resident of your proposed visit to Muscat in H,M.S Wildgoose on January 7th. Grateful if you will telegraph E.T.A. to enable me to arragge exchange of calls. Ends. POLITICALTelegram, ^ EoC-f^.v. \ t From. Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, Warship Wildgoose, Bahrain radio To. Political Agent, Muscat Dated aook the 2nd received the 3rd January, 1947. Too . Oyr / 3 i . &gt; % ■ '&gt;0 Expect to arrive Muscat 1000D on Tuesday 7th January and will salute flag on arrival. SNOPG. &lt;y/3 7 .■HP Telegram, From. To. • No. 7 Political Resident, Bahrain Political Agent, Muscat / Bated the 3rd received the 4th January, 1947. Unless you have any suggestions to make to the contrary following courtesies will be observed on forth coming visit of Wildgoose. 2. On arrival ship will salute country. Shore battery will reply. 3. You will then go on board and call on Senior Naval Officer. Your salute will be fired as you leave ship. 4 # Senior Naval Officer will go ashore and return your call. He will then call on Sultan*s representative. 5 * Sultan*s representative will return call on board and receive cast away salute as he leaves ship; — HAYTelegram. From. Q Political Agent, Muscat Naval Officer-in-charge, Bahrain a « To. No.C 6 Dated the 4th January, 1947 Please pass following to S, .G. Your telegram No.Too 0713Z dated January 2nd Suggest following programme for your visit 2 . 10.00 Ship arrives and salutes country. Salute is returned 10.20 Consul arrives on board to call on S.N.O.P.G. 10.45 S.N.O. arrives on shore to return Consul*s call 11.00 S.N.O. accoppanied by Consul calls on Sultan*s representative 11.45 Sultan*s representative arrives on board to return S.N.O's call I have room to put up three persons if therefore 3. you and any of your officers would care to stay ashore during your visit I should be glad of opportunity to put you up. Can I make arrangements for Hockey and tennis etc., I have one British Empire Medal awaiting presentation 5 to Interpreter Golam Ali your Memo No.PG 193 of 12th September, 1946, refers. Would you care to make presentation on board during this visit. Ends. Political O41400DTranslation of letter No*63/2, dated the 5th January, 194-6, from the Secretary to the Sultan, to Consul, Muscat. X Reference your letter No.C.4—9/1, dated the 4th January1946. Saiyid Shihab will be delighted to receiveXthe Senion Naval Officer Persian Gulf, and return the visit to him on the date, and time given. U.EOffice of the Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf 'WILD GOOSE.' 23rd December, 1946. No. PG. 1B/5. THE POLITICAL AGENT, 1.1TJSCAT. THE POLITICAL AGENT, IGJWEIT. (copy to:- The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.) I beg to inform you that I expect to visit Muscat in H.M.S. 'Wild Goose' arriving A.M. 7th January, and leaving on 9th January. 2* I anticipate arriving Kuweit on 14th January and leaving on 17th January. 3 . Salutes will be fired on arrival. SENIQR NAVAL OFFICER PERSIAN GULF.Telegram G.T.C. From Government of India, New Delhi. To Residency, Bahrain. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain (Repgu please pass) Political Agent, Muscat. No. 523. Dated 19th and received 20th January, 1947 Follow'ng is proposed cruise of His Majesty’s Indian ship Danush. Arrive Muscat February 4th; Depart February 5th; Arrive Khor Kuwai February 6th, depart February 8th; Arrive Bahrain February 10th, depart February 12th. ?Arranging further details. -FOREIGN-Telegram GTC From Political Agent, Muscat To Hay, Steamship Nearchus, Bahrain Mo. C 33 Dated the 20th January, 1947 X sv. Reference Government of India telegram No532 dated January 19th. Cruise of H.IC.I.S DANUSH. In view of my probable absence and absence of Sultan I suggest visit should not repeat not be official i.e. no salutes, and Commander to call on Sultan's represent ative privately accompanied ( in the event of my absence ) by Mathews. POLITICALTelegram GTC From Residency, Bahrain To Political Agent, Muscat No. 88 Dated and received the 20th January, 1947 Foreign telegram No 523 January 19th. H.M.I.S DANUSH Please confirm there is no objection to proposed visit. Repgu# % Telegram GTC From Political Agent, Muscat To Residency, Bahrain No, C 36 Dated the 21st January, 1947. Your telegram No.88 January 20th. Following is repetition of this Agency telegram No.C 33 January 20th to Political Resident, Nearchus• Begins. % 9 5~ „ Reference Government of India telegram No. 523 dated January Mathews. Ends. PoliticalNo.C 51-9/1 His Britannic Majesty's Consulate Muscat, Dated the 22nd January,1947. To The Secretary to His highness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, Muscat . Memorandum. H.M.I.S 'DHANUSII' is expected to arrive at Muscat on the 12th February, 1947, and will depart on the 15th February. Further details will be communicated on receipt. for His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat,Telegram From To Rep No. 577 GTC Government of India, New Delhi Repgu Bahrain Political Agent, Muscat Dated the 21st received the 22nd January, 1947. Foreign telegram No, 523 January 19th. Programme of H.M.I.S. DHANUSH as follows: Arrive Bandar Abbas •••••••••# February Depart »» Arrive Muscat • ••••••• • it Depart «•••••••• # it Arrive Bandar Abbas •••••••• ♦ 17th• tt Depart ♦♦♦♦♦♦ •• ♦ ♦ t! FOREIGN(§) Telegram GTC From Government of India, New Delhi To Political Resident, Bahrain Rep Political, Jtfuscat No. 929 Dated the 3rd received the 4th February, 1947. Your T/24 January 27th. 2. H.M.I.S. DKANUSH is not repeat not fitted for firing salutes. Please arrange for formal call if Political Agent present otherwise private call. FOREIGNNo.C 85-9/1 His Britannic Majesty's Consulate Muscat• Dated the 8th February, 1947. To M e m o r a The Secretary to His Highness the Sultan of Musc'-t &amp; Oman, Muscat. n d u m. Reference this Consulate ‘Memorandum No.C 51-9/1 C'g' dated 22nd January, 1947. Visit of K.M.I.S. Dhanush will be formal but no salutes will be fired as she is not fitted for firing salutes. ■pSvr+.hm* dfttails will be communicated later. for His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat•✓ N /-'S Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, aboard S.Y. 'Nearchus' To Foreign, New Delhi. No.T/14. Dated the 23rd January, 1947. Your telegram No.523 January 19th. 2. No objection whctever from political point of view. Presume Royal Navy have been consulted separately. 3. I will telegraph further about courtesies at Muscat. - haY ~ NPG. No.C/15. Office of the political Resident, Persian Gulf, aboard S.Y* ,? Nearchus”, the 23rd January, 1947. Copy forwarded with compliments to - The Political /gent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Muscat. NPG._Telegram From To No. Enclair Commander KMIS. DHANUSK Political Agent, Muscat Too 171212C Dated and received the 17th February, 1947. Thank you for all your help during our stay in Muscat and I hope that we shall have another trip together. Please^c5eerio to every one for us and we hope that we shall be in Muscat again in the near future.Telegram From To No. Enclair Political Agent, Muscat HMIS DHANUSH nil Dated the 17th February, 1947. Many thanks your; sorry your visit was disturbed. Come again soon. Political 5?^33/94. li %]) Telegraro G.T.C. From To Repgu, Bahrain. political Resident, Aboard S.Y. ,, Nearchus ? ». No. 99 Dated 22nd January and Received 23rd January, 1947. Following is repetition of Government of India telegram 577 dated 21st January, 1947. Addressed Repgu, Bahrain, Repeated political Agent, Muscat. Begins: Foreign telegram No.523, January 19th programme IT.M.I.S. DANUSH revised as follows:- Arrive Bandar Abbas February 5th. February 11th. February 12th. February loth. February 17th. Depart Arrive Muscat Depart Arrive Bandar Abbas Depart February 23rd. Ends. presume that you will reply to Government of India. -REPGU- the 24th Jonu^ry, 1347• Copy forwarded with compliments to - The Political /gent, Be:hrt.in . The political /gent, b , with reference to Residency endorsement No.C/15 d ted the 23rd January 1347. NPGTelegram From To No. Dated 23rd En clair Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. 221656C and received 24th April. 1947. Loch Glendhu will salute flag on arrival. -NAVYCHARGE-y 9/1 &amp; 4/6 &amp; Telegram From To No. Nil Dated 26th received 27th July, 1947* En clair Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, aboard H.Ii.S. Wild Goose. Political Agent, Muscat. ' Loch Quoich H arrives Muscat a.m. 4th and n Loch Glendhu H arrives a.m. 5th. Ships are exchanging duties and personnel and will leave about 6th August. NCJJ 9/1 &amp; 4/6 Telegram En clair From Political Agent, Muscat. I To Political Resident, Bahrain. No. C/33S Dated the 27th July, 1947. Following is repetition of telegram teceived from SNOPG Wild Goose begins : '•Loch Quoich' 6th August. Ends. r - POLITICAL - Telegram From To Repeated No. En clair Political Agent, Tfuscat. Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, aboard 'Wild Goose' Political Resident, Bahrain. C/339 Dated the 27th July, 1947. Muscat. Please pass to SNOPG Warship Wild Goose from Political Agent Your telegram regarding visit of warships. Kindly confirm visits are unofficial repeat unofficial. ~ POLITICAL - NCJTelegram From To No. Dated 27th / 9/1 &amp; 4/6 En clair SNOPG, Colombo Radio. Political Agent, Muscat. TOO 271735 C received 28th July, 1947. Your telegram C 339. Confirmed that visits are unofficial repeat unofficial, NCJNo* C«416-9A and Z./6 ?// 6 The British Consulate, MUSCAT, Dated the 30th July, 1947 To The Secretary, to His Highness, the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat. Memorandum His Majesty*s Ships ’ ♦ Loch Quoich H and f, Loch Glendhu tt are expected to arrive at Muscat on the mornings of the 4th and 5th August respectively. The ships will exchange duties and personnel. The visits will be unofficial, and no calls will be made. Acting British Consul, MuscatTelegram From To No. Dated Important of 4th by G.T.C. Political Resident, Bahrain Political Agent, Muscat. A/546 and received 1 August 1947. Major Stewart arrives Muscat morning Loch Quoich ^. REPGUTelegram En clair From Warship M Loch Quoich ,f Bahrain To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 0850 S BG Dated and received 1 August, 1947. Expected time of arrival Muscat 0900 4th August. Major Stewart embarked. Intend to fire salute on arrival. POLITICALHo. C. 422-qA British Consulate, Muscat* Dated the 2nd August,1947 To The Secretary, to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat* Dear Sir, Reference ray letter Xo* C. 416-9A dated 30th July, 1947. 2* I have just received a message from H*ill*S* 11 Loch Quoich * at Bahrain saying Major Stewart has embarked for Muscat and that the ship will fire a salute on arrival here which will be at 9 a.m. on the 4th August* Acting Consul, Muscat*Mo. C. 435-9A HIS MAJESTY’S CONSULATE, MUSCAT. 12th August, 1947. To The Secretary to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oiaan, Muscat• Dear Sir, I have received intimation from the Senior Haval Officer Persian Gulf that he proposes to visit the following places on the dates shown.~ 28th August, 1947. 29th August, 1947. 1st September, 1947. (a) Khor Jararaa Muscat Dibah I have no official intimation as to the purpose of these visits but consider it likely that the visits to khor Jararaa and Dibah may possibly be T/ith a view to examine the possibilities of establishing a navigational light buoy. I will inform you in due course whether H.M.S. * Wildgoose ' will fire salutes on arrival in Muscat. Yours truly. His Ifejesty’s Consul, MuscatTo No. Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, aboard “Wild Goose' C/370 Dated the 12th august, 1947. /-s ' . I Your telegram dated August 10th. (a) Will visit to Muscat be official ? (b) Do you propose salute the country on arrival ? - POLITICAL - NCJ ■Telegram From En clair Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, aboard 'Wild Goose'. To Political Agent, Muscat. No. Nil Dated 15th received loth august, 194 r /• i&gt;i$r programme altered. Will visit you for a night on way to Colombo. Visit unofficial and salute will not be fired unless you wish it. Date later. - S N 0 P G - NCJMo. C/453-9A •V H.U's* Consulate 9 Muscat % Dated the 21st August, 1947# To /-\ The Secretary to Hie Highness the Sultan of .^fuscat &amp; Oman, Muscat* Memorandum 106 Reference roy letter No* C/435*9/l dated the 12th August, 1947* The Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf now telegraphs to say his programme hae been altered and he will pay an unofficial visit to Muscat only, at a date to be notified later* NCJTelegram From En clair Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, aboard '‘Vi'ild Goose To Political Agent, Muscat. No. TOO 211351 D Dated 21st received 22nd August, 194V. Arriving 1st and leaving on '2nd. Visit unofficial. Do you v/ish any salutes to be fired ? - SNOPG - NCJ (HU! c ^ v ^ £ 3Z( Too zn?si i Ary-* t CXX. 1 cxHo. C/460-9A A H.M's. Consulate y (i 9 &lt;@) Muscat* Dated the 23rd August, 1947. To The Secretary to His Highness tho Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, Muscat* In continuation of this Consulate memorandum No. C/453-9A dated the 21st August 1947, the Senior N&amp;’val Officer Persian Gulf intimates that he will arrive at flusoat on the 1st and leave on the 2nd September* The visit will be unofficial and no salutes will be fired. H.M’s. Consul, Muscat* NCJSir, I beg t« inf*rui you that, after the let Septeuber, 1947? 'the Seuior Naval Offioer, Persian Gulf, Captain R.J.R. Dendy, R^yal Na^/y, will be absent from the Gulf, in H.L*S* WILD GOOSN, at H.lhS. LOCH GLLinXTJ, Col:, ander H.L. Hayes, O.B.L. , Royal Navy, will be the only H*1I. Ship in the Gulf until relieved by H.1I. S. wRLH, Commander J.C.G. Kart in. Royal Navy. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf will continue to administer Naval affairs fro.: Colombo and will probably return by air to Bahrein and Habbaniyah in late October, or early Noi|Ouib«ar, before being superseded by Captain L.E. Porter, Royal Navy, as Senior Naval Officer. All correspondence on matters »f policy should continue 1 9 be sent to the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, in H.M.S. tyM) GOOSb (c/o Fleet Kail Office, Colombo) but minor matters can be UpfewNDd. to the Commanding Officers of H.li. S. LOCH GLLKDHLf «r K*K.S. \CluN for such action as is found to be necessary. I have the honaur to be Sir, Ycur cbedient servant9/1 Telegram En clair From - , Basra. ( ? H.M's. Consul General, Basra) To Political Agent, Muscat. No. Nil * Dated 10th received 11th September, 1947, Following from E.M.S. Loch Glendhu Loch Glendhu intends to visit following ports in September and October. NCJ Muscat 19th - 23rd September. Khor Fakkan 24th - 25th September. Bahrain 29th September - 2nd October. Khor Kuwai 3rd - 6th October. Bahrain 24th October. - DAVIS -Hgr C/ 494 - 9 A H. B. M's. Consulate, Muscat, Dated the 11th September, 1947, To The Secretary to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat, Memorandum Intimation has been received that H,M,S, Loch Glendhu Intends visiting Muscat from the 19th to the 23rd September, 1947, M's, Consul, Muscat9/1 Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Bahrain. To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 985. Dated 14th and received 15th September, 1947. Following is programme H.M.S. LOCH GLENDHU :- Ivluscat - September 19th - September 23rd Khor Fakkan - September 24th - September 25th Bahrain - September 29th. GALLOWAY9/1 &amp; 1^/3 Telegram From To No. En clair Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. 174 Dated 38th 1 'cccivcd 29th October, 19&lt;±7. ■■ I ■ ^Loch blendhu ,, E.T.A. Muscat 1200 D 3rd November Remaining few hours only and do not intend salute or official calls* POLITICALEn clair Political Agent, Muscat. Political Agent, Bahrain. C 466 30th October, 1947. Following for Loch Glendhu. I hope you and some of your officers will be able to lunch with me. /- Telegram From To No. Dated the mmmmm9/1 m Telegram From To No. Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat, 1085 Dated 30th received 31st October, 1947. Foreign Karachi Express Letter No. D 767/47-0 October 21st which is repeated to you states H.M.P.S. ,, Godavari ,, which may be accompanied by H.M.P.S. ,, Baluchistan H expects to arrive at Gwadur on November 15th and leave November 16th and asks that Sultan^ permission may be obtained. 2. On previous occasions we have only notified Sultan regarding Royal Indian Navy^ visits cf rqy telegram No. T/344 July ^th 1946 and I am inclined to think we should follow same procedure while Pakistan and India remain within Commonwealth. If you agree and see no objection to visit please take action accordingly and report.Ho. C/560-9A H. P. M's* Consulate, Muscat* Dated the 1st November, 1947* To Memorandum The Secretary to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat * Intimation has been received that H.M*S. w Loch Gl•ndhu ,, will be visiting Muscat on the 3rd November to drop mails* She will arrive about 12 noon and stay only a few hours. The visit is unofficial and so no salutes would be fired* H* B* M^sT Consul, Muscat* Jp ' &amp; NCJ9/1 Telegram Q From Political Agent, Muscat. To Political Resident, Bahrain. No. C 467 Dated the 1st November, 1947. }2l Your telegram No. 1085 October 30th. I agree and have merely informed Secretary to His Highness that H.M.P.S. Godavari and Baluchistan expect to visit Gwadur November 15th - 16th and asked him to notify Tfoli. I have also told British Agent to make usual arrangements. - POLITICAL - NCJNCJ »njp Telegram From To No. G.T.C. Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. 1091 Dated 1st received 2nd November, 1947. Postal and Residency mails and potatoes sent by Glendhu 1 ' but not duplicator. REPGU - n LochNo* C 566-9/1 H. B. M*s* Consulate, Muscat, Dated the 3rd November, 19^7* To Memorandum The Secretary to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, Muscat, Intimation has been received that His Majesty^ Pakistan Ship “Godavari' is expected to call at Gwadur on the 16th and will leave on the 16th November. She may be accompanied by H,M.P.S. 'Baluchistan'* It would be appreciated if the Wall of Gwadur could kindly be informed* H. B, M f s* Consul, MuscatTelegram From To No. G.T.C. Political Agent, Muscat. British Agent, Gwadur. C 47&lt;± Dated the 3rd November, 19^7 His Majesty’s Pakistan Ship •’Godavari” is expected to arrive Gwadui’ November 16th and leave November 16th. She may be accompanied by H.M.P.S. ’’Baluchistan”. Please inform vVali and make usual arrangements. POLITICAL0.546/37, mi Office of the Secrctf^y^ to the Sultnn of Muscat &amp;ocian, r '\ Muscat . \\&lt;Z3J The 5th. November 194 7 To, His Britaimic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat. 'J Memorandum Please refer to your letter No.C 566-9/1 dated the 3rd. November 1947. As desired the Wall of Gwadur has been informed of the proposed call at Gwadur of His Majesty’s Pales tan Ships •’Godavari” and ' Baluchistan”. / J' - Telegram From To No. 9/1 Q Political Resident, Bahrain, Political Agent, Muscat. 1177 &lt;s Dated l&lt;±th received 15th November, 19^7. IMPORTANT Your telegram No. C &lt;±67 November 1st. Visit of H.M.P.S. ,, Godavcri M . 2. Ship will visit Gwadur on date already Comission;. She will also now visit Muscat on November 26th repeat November 26th arriving at noon. H.M.P.S. ’’Baluchistan'* will not be in company, 1^0 - REPGU -9/1 Telegram From To No. Q Political Agent, Muscat* Political Hcsiaotit, Baliram* C 5Q^± Dated the loth November, 19V7. S’. Your telegram No. 1177 November l^th* Godavari. 2. I presume as this is first visit official calls will be exchanged and salutes fired. Telegram From To No. - POLITICAL - ******* Government of Paxistan, Karachi. Politic al Agent, Muse at. 873 Dated and received the 16th November, 19^7. Your telegram No. 1103 dated November &lt;±th. Visit of H*M.P«S. Godavari. 2. Muscat also is to be visited on the 26th noon. Grateful if Sultan could be ini'orrned« - FOREIGN - NCJTelegram From To Mo. bated the G.T.C. Political Resident, Bahrain. Government of Pakistan, Karachi. 1102 4th November, 1947. Your Express better i«o.D.767/47-0 October 21st. Visit of H.fcLP.S. 'GODAVARI” to Gwadur and Bahrain. 2. Rulers have been informed. * = HAY = PERSIAN GULP RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, the 4th November, 1947. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, BAHRAh, . The Political Agent, hu^CAi . CObrl! Li. i 1AL. No. 1891-S MTelegram Q From Political Resident, Bahrain. To Government of Pakistan, Karachi. Repeated Political Agent, Muscat. No. 1189 Dated 17th received 18th November, 19^7. ^ Your telegram No. 873 November 16th not repeated Muscat* Visit of H.M.P.S. Godavari to Muscat. 2. Muscat Government is being informed. 3 . As this is first visit please confirm repeating Political Agent Muscat that official calls will be exchanged and salutes fired* Telegram From To No. 9/1 G.T.C. Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. 1203 Dated 21st received 22nd November, 1947. (§) 33 Correspondence ending with my telegram No. 1189 November 17th. H.M.P.S. Godavari will not repeat not now visit Muscat. - REPGU - A A /* ^ III Telegram En clair From H.M.S. 'Wren 11 . To Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. No. Nil TOO 210417 Z Dated 21st received 22nd November, 1947. Naval Headquarters, Pakistan asks me to inform you that owing to quite unforeseen circumstances requiring ,, Godavari H to dry dock in Colombo early December, her intended visit to Muscat at which f, Godavari ,, was due to arrive 26th November must unfortunately be cancelled.■/•V Telegram From To No. Dated of your visit. 9/1 &amp; 4/6 En clair Political Agent, Muscat. H.M.3. Wren C. 525 25th November 1947. Your telegram of November 23rd. Glad to hear As it is first this year presume salute will be fired on arrival and official calls exchanged. Please confirm. POLITICALy 9/1 &amp; 4/6 TolGgram From To No. Kn clair H.M.S* Wren. Political Agent, Muscat. 0040 Z Dated 26th received 23th November, 1947 lour 250712* Confirmed. In addition I shall be conveying the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and wearing his flag* H.M.S# Wren - NCJT«l«gram En olair From H*K«S* n Hrmn n To Folitloal Agont, Uuseat* Oatod 6th rocoivod 7th Dooonbor 1947. Wo should rsry mush like to ontortoln all tho British and Ansrloans (and any others you think fit) in Muscat to a cocktail party 1800 to 2000 perhaps the evening of the day so arrive* Day however left to you to decide* Would be grateful if you will issue invitations and let ne know details when we arrive* H.M.S. WHEN Telegraa En clair Frora H.M.S* 'Wren' To 6th received 7th December 1947. Dated Estiaated tine of arrival at Muscat of H*M«S* Wren wearing the flag of the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is 0805 local tine Wednesday 10th December* H.M.S. WHENT-t.'yX. Progranm# of uff icial calls 10th DecambTi 1^47&gt; 0805 hours Vrsn arrives and aalutes the country. 0sluts is returned by Chore Battery, ^hip anchors. 0820 hours Consul goos on board ran and calls on tue Hon*bio the political Resident. 0840 hours 0855 hours v /•v 0905 hours 09o0 hours A, 1000 hours Consul disembarks. political Resident accompafiied uy Captain of H. r .'J. ren (Usembarks. As his launch passes Fort 4irani, tdie battery will fire a saluta of 13 guns. political Resident lands ana is met by Consul at the top of the Consulate steps and conducted to the duard of Honour, and then to the Consulate. Political Resident accompanied by Consul and Ca/tain of H. JT.S. ron calls on cai/id Shihab. Saiyid Shihab returns political Rosident , ( call at the Consulate. Consul goes on board H. '.S. ron to return Captain's call. Consul disemoarks and H.M.S. ren fires a salute of 11 guns. dTolo^r-im Sn clair From To No- Datod Political Agent, Muscat. H.M.S. Wren. C 554 the l&lt;ith December, 1947. Goodbye. Thanks for the visit. Come again soon. STE /ART: ! cA 1 M w' /^s . . Government of Pakistan. Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Commonwealth Relations. Express Letter. From - Foreign, Karachi. To - Repgu, Bahrain. Repeated - Political Muscat. y Wo. D.767/47-0. Dated the JLiXf October 1947. H.M.P. 6 . GODAVARI proposes carry out cruise in Persian Gulf in November, arriving Gwadar 15th departing 16th arriving Bahrein 20 th departing 24th. She may be accompanied by H.M.P.S. BALUCHISTAN. * * 2* Grateful for Ruler^a permission. authorised. Issue of the above has been (M.G.Dixon) Deputy Secretary to the Government of Pakistan. [RjJ£±L (tyf i / _With the compliments of the Secretary to The Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station. k/ jor a srswr a &amp; e; KFr-v Consul, M. JGAT, PiiRSX^N GULP.Telegram Fro m To No. Dated 21st En clair H.M.S. Wren, Colombo Radio Political Agent, Muscat. Nil 210503 Z received 22nd January, 1948* Your C 27 201310. Yes salutes will be firedJ A &lt;•** /■v Ho. C/63-9/1 H. M'b. Consulate, Muscat. Dated the 26th January, 1948. To The Secretary te His Highness the Sultan ef Muscat &amp; Oman, Muscat. Memorandum Visit ef H.M.S. Wren H.M.S. 'Wren' 1 Intends visiting Muscat from the 9th to the 14th February, 1948. The visit will be formal and she will salute the country en arrival. Her expected time of arrival will be intimated later. H. M's. Consul, Muscat. NCJD«0« No. C 87-4/6 H.M'e* Conciliate, Muscat. Dated the 7th February, 1.^48 with reference to my letter «o. C 63 -4/6 dated the ^January, 1948 l have now hoard that H.M.S. wren will arrive at 11 a.m. on Monday 9th. As it will bo rather difficult to get all the calls through in one mornir^ conmoncing at so late an hour i propose telegraphing to Aren suugoeting the following programme i- *onday Jth : 11 a.m. H. V.rcn arrives and salutes the country. 11.46 Captain lands and callo on tlio Consul. 12.00 Captain accompanied by Consul calls on Saiyid Shihab. Tuesday 10th z 10.16 a.m. Consul calls on Captain. 10.uO Saiyid Shihab calls on Captain. 10.46 Saiyid Shihab disembarks, salute of 13 guns. 11.00 Consul disembarks, salute of 11 guns. 2. Will you please let 'me know if these times are convenient ? Mr. Ali Mohaamod al Jarnali, Secretary to Kis Highness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, Muscat.(SOyA Plaase refer to your D.O.No.C 87-4/6 dated the 7th, Office of the Secrettry, to xhe Sul can of Muscat cc Oman, y £?.OC Muscat, 7^ m) *- g y y /l - ^ February 1948, The time/fixed for the official calls on the 10th, February 1948 on the occasion of the arrival of H.M.S. '^ren' are convenient. Major A. G, Stewart, His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, /z/'ufJ 4/6 &amp; 9A Telegram En clair From Political Agent, Muscat. To H.M.S. Wren, Navycharge, Trincomalee. No. C 59 Dated the 7th February, 1948. IMMEDIATE As it will be difficult to complete calls in one morning starting at 11 a.m. I propose suggesting Monday 9th starting 11.45 your calls ashore. Return calls morning Monday 10th. Please confirm you agree TOO 070745 Z POLITICALTelegram From / 4/6 &amp; 9/1 isn clair H.M.S. Wren. To Port Authorities, Muscat. No. 071405 Z Dated 7th received 8 th February, 1948. IMPORTANT ^ S /^&gt; r ( Your C 59 CPUPURT). My E.T.A. will be adjusted to arrive at 0900 repetition 0900 local time so suggest calls starting 0930 and returned either same day or next as you think fit.. NCJ/' ■ N D.O. No. C/88 - A/6 *wt British Consulate, Muscat* 8th February 1948* / / Will you please refer to your D.O* letter No. 128/2 dated the 7th February 1948. I have now heard that H.tf.S. ,, W^en ,, has adjusted her expected time of arrival so as to reach ?J!uscat at 9 *•«!• on Monday instead of 11 a.m. so as to be able to complete the calls in one morning. If Saiyid Shihab agrees that this is more convenient, I wonder if you would ask for his approval to the new programme I now attach. Mr. All Muhammad al Jamali Secretary to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat.INCJ Telegram En clair From H.M.S. Loch Glendhu. To EcM 1 s* Consul # Muscat. No. 260854 D Dated 26th received 27th February, 1948. If we do not arrive before mall steamer due 2nd March grateful if you can look after our provisions for us. 2. Further request Hajjl Abdul Rahman Hascan contractor be asked to supply 200 pounds beef on 3rd March. 3. Naval interpreter is being embarked at Bahrain.1 CONFIDENT TAJ. D»Q» No. C» 143'9/1 Political Agency, Muscat• 11th March 1948. Please refer to Your Express Letter No. 25S-S dated the 29th January 1948. 2. I asked the Sultan whether he wished the ships of His itijesty’s Pakistan Navy and Indian Navy to obtain permission before they paid visits to Muscat or whether he was prepared to let them carry on as under the previous arrangement. He replied that his relations with Pakistan and India would have to be reviewed and that pending such revision he would prefer that His ifejesty^ Pakistan and Indian ships should obtain permission before they visited his territories. The Honourable Sir Rupert Hey, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain.4/6 (yp dde Memoir Call of H.M.S. Loch Glendhu The Sultan said he would be glad to see Commander N.K. Tod F..N. at 10 o f clock on Saturday the 13th. The visit should be unofficial. The Sultan should see the Residency Surgeon at the same time. Initialled ’‘^.C.S.” 10th fferch 194S. ^rtM.Telegram Enclair From. To Mo. P ol i t n ca 1 A &lt; r Bnt, 111 s cat Captain, Warship HIS Loch HLendhu C 1QQ Dated the 10th March, 1948- Sultan would bo glad to receive, a visit from you on Saturday 13th and suggests 10 a.n. as time of call. Be would prefer the visit to be unofficial and no repeat no salutes etc., POLITICALLt/lt. Telegram En clair From Warship ,, Loch Glendhu M , Afloat. _ To Political Agent, Muscat. No. Dated and received 12th March 1948. Still too rough for work towards Sib. Have come to Matrah. Propose ship to remain here as shelter from Sharaal is better than Muscat. I will come by boat tomorrow to call on Sultan. CaptainTelegram Knclair From Consul, tuscat To Captain HMS Warship Loch Glendhu No. C 105 Dated the 12th Jferch, 194S Sorry you've had bad weather. Presume you v/ill land about nine-thirty. ' Consulgpgppr*-- - . - - - - jTelegram En clair From Warship H.M.S. Wren, Bombay Radio To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 101121 D Dated 10th received 11th April 1948. H.M.S. Wren expects again to arrive Muscat about 2300 B Sunday 18th. Suggest Commanding Officer calls on new Political Agent 0915 Monday, Call returned shortly afterwards. 2* H.M.S. Loch Quoich with S.N.O.P.G. embarked arrives Muscat 20th expected time of arrival not yet known. Ceremonial and calls will be discussed on Monday 19th if you agree.234.- 9/1 19th April 1943, Will Your Highness refer tc cur converbation of tho 13th April e&amp;noerning tho visit o£ h.M*e Ship# Wrsn and Looh Quoioh ? X propose to ask the Comma tiding Officer of Wren to telegraph Senior itevel Officer Pertitn Gulf aboard R.jtf.S, Loch Quoich suggesting the follo^iug prograTume of oalla. *ednfi 3 ,-to-» aist A aril» 0801 hours E«MJS, Loch Quoich ar-lutes the country (21 guns). His Highness' shore batteries ret :zrn the salute, 1000 hours Senior ^-ml Officer Parsiaa Gulf, the Commanding Officer of • Loch Quoioh and Consul should call upca Tour Highness, 1055 hours A mot or-boat belonging to Loch Quoich should arrive at the palace steps and it is suggested that Tour Highness eight find it z&amp;st convent ant tc use this beat and to return Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf call aboard 2Ur3»S* Loch Quoich at 1100 hours* / Would His Highness Saiyid Said bln T&amp;lnur, Sultan of Unseat and Oaan, Sosost.I Would Tour RighnesB be good enough to let roe know urgently whether these tines are convenient for the forsal calls* I regret such chart notice of the proposed programme but difficulties of comarunioatlon have tended to delay this information concerning the arrival of Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf* N R! ■ wmjtBkti) (Received under Printed Letter No.432 dated 4 th April 1948 from the High Commissioner for the U.K. in Pakistan). Ref. No.432. 4th April, 1948. TV \ The United Kingdom High Commissioner presents his compliments to the Honourable Minister for Foreign Affairs, Government of Pakistan, and, with reference to the correspondence ending with the Ministry 1 s letter No. D.295-IU/48 dated 20th January, 1948, regarding visits by ships of the Royal Pakistan Navy to ports in foreign countries, has the honour to say that the Sultan of Muscat has expressed, through the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, a wish that his prior permission should be obtained before ships of the Royal Pakistan and Royal Indian Navies visit Muscat. 2. The High Commissioner would accordingly be grateful if the Ministry would arrange for such permission to be obtained before any ship of the Royal Pakistan Navy visits Muscat. It is suggested that such requests for permission should be addressed by the Ministry direct to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, though the High Commissioner would be glad to be informed of all such requests made. i Minister for Foreign Affairs &amp; Commonwealth Relations, Government of Pakistan, Mohatta Palace, Clifton, KARACHI . vCOMMONWEALTH RELATIONS OFFICE, DOWNING STREET. r Pol.(Ext) 15938/48 CONFIDENTIAL Your letter No.48/D/28 of 13th April (referring to Sir R.Hay's letter No.633-S of 22n_d March) in which you ask whether it is desired that you should inform the Government of India of the Sultan of Muscat's wishes regarding the procedure to be followed when His Majesty's Indian ships visit his territories. / R.W. » 2. We do not think that any action is required by you at the moment. When the occasion of a visit next arises, the Govern ment of India/Pakistan will presumably notify the Political Resident who might then inform the* of the Sultan's attitude. 3. I am sending copies of this letter to Hay, Burnett4nd the Foreign Office. Sd. F.A.K. Harrison. Selby, Esquire, , Office of the High Commissioner for the United Kingdom, ^ New Delhi oCo CONFIDENTIAL PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY No.M/33 (33/138) BAHRAIN Dated the 14th May, 1948 Copy forwarded with compliments to:- The Political Agent, MUSCAT ' LB'Telegram From To No. G.T.C. v PolitiCcl Resident, Bahrain. Politics! Agent, Muscat. 538 Dated 18th and received 18th June, 1948. Collect 1 bag and 1 cover from LOCK QUICK due Muscat about 21st.Telegram From To En clair Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, Bahrain Political Agent, Bahrain Political Resident, Bahrain ( for information ) No. 2309312 Dated the 23rd received the 24th June, 194^ Regret must cancel visit Loch Quoich to Rfuscat except to drop mails owing to unforseen circumstances. TOO 2309312 SNOPG.Telegram GTC From To No. 557 Dated and received the 22nd June, 1943* Political Resident, Bahrain Political Agent, Muscat H.M.S. n Wildgoose rt proposes to visit Muscat from July 5th to July 8 th. Length of stay may be shortened. HayTelegram GTC From Political Agent, Muscat To Political Resident, Bahrain No* C 206 Dated the 25th June, 1948. Your telegram No. 557 June 22nd. Grateful to know if Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf is on board. PoliticalTelegram From To Emclair Warship Wildgoose, Bahrain Radio Political Agent, Muscat No. 2513132 Dated the 25th received the 26th June, 1948. E.T.A Loch Quoich Muscat 0900 local time 27th. Please arrange to collect ?feil. TOO 2513132Telegram Enclair From H.M.S. Wildgoose To H.M.S. Loch Quoich Repeated Political Resident, Bahrain No. TOO 270818 D Dated and received the 27th June, 1948. Please pass to Political Agent, Muscat, by hand. ' Intend saluting National flag on arrival at 0900 July 5th. Lieutenant Commander F.D. Cole will be temporarily in command of Wildgoose. ,l Wildgoose. TOO 270819DNo.C 286-9/1 Political Agency &amp; His Britannic Majesty Consulate, ? His cot , dated the 28th June, 1948, To The Secretary to His Highness the Muscat, Memorandum . Wildgoose has informed this Consulate Lhat she is due to arrive here at 9 a.in, on Mond^p the 5th July, 1948* and that she will salute the country &gt;n arrival. His Pritannic itejegty^ bonsul, Muscat.Telegram Enclair From Warship HI© Wren, care Navywireless, Colombo To Political ftgent, Muscat, No. TOO 141225 CD Dated and received the 14th July, 1943. E.T.A. Muscat 0800 local time Sunday 18th. No gun salutes. Calls if you consider essential but otherwise not since interval is less than three months since last visit. MartinTelegram Enclair From Political Agent, Lffuscat To Warship Wren, Care Navywireless, Colombo No. • C/224 Dated the 15th July, 1943. Your 141255 CD July 14th. I agree all suggestions. Political.I have the honour to inform Your highness that H.M.S. Viren will arrive at liuscat on the 18th July at 0800 a.cu and leave on the 21 st. Wren's visit will he unofficial. Your Highness 1 sincere friend, His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of I-luscat and Oman, Muscat,Enclair H.M.S. Wren, Colombo Telegram From To No* Tool40417 z Dated the 14th received the 15th September, 1948. Political Agent, Muscat For Ellison from Martin. E.T.A HMS Vfren at Muscat is 0800 repeat 0800 your time Saturday 18th. 2. Desire to pay official call upon you and suggest 0915 Saturday. 3. As this my last personal visit please arrange farewell call on His Highness the Sultan for me suggest A.m. Monday. 4. No repeat no salute on arrival BT 140417 Z asrNo. C 367-9/1 September 15th, 1948 I have the honour to inform Your Highness that H. ? .S ftren will arrive in Muscat on the 18th on an unofficial visit. She will leave on the 21st. Your Highness' sincere friend, His Highness Saiyld Said bin Tairaur, Sultan of fuscet and Oman, iluscat.A /S Telegram From To Enclair Political Agent, Muscat H.M.S. Y#ren, care Navywireless, Colombo No. C 250 Dated the 16th September, 1948. Your signal 140417 2 September 14th. Agree all suggestions. Ellison./-'v 'V Telegram GTC From Government of Pakistan, Karachi To Political Agent, Muscat c -4- • o s tf\ A i Dated and received the 17th October, 1948• Immediate V • Pakistan Warship Sind is due to call on Monday or Tuesday loth or 19th October at Gwadur. Government of Pakistan would be grateful if permission would be obtained for this visit and also for other facilities. Regret for not informing you earlier. ForeignHo. C 387-9A October 17, 1948 I hevo received a telegi* 6 Ta from the Government of Pakistan requesting me to Inform Tour Highness that His Majesty’s Pakistan Warship * Sind * desires to visit Gwadur either on the 18th or 19th October, and to ask Your Highness 1 permission for the visit and for the usual shore facilities* They express their regret for the short notice given, a regret which I can only share* I should be most grateful if Your highness would inform rae of your decisionas soon as possible for / transmission to the Government of Pakistan* Your Highness' sincere friend, His Highness Salyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of fHiscat end Oman, Muscat•I Telegram Inter 2 From Political Resident, Bahrain To United Kingdom High Commissioner, Karachi Rep. Political Agent, ffascat No. 14 Dated £hd received the 17th October, 1948 smEr - j’.it, A telegram has been received on the 17th October from Foreign Karachi asking that Sultan’s permission may be obtained for visit of Warship 'Sind” to Gwadur on October 18th or 19th and facilities arranged. I have replied that time is insufficient for this purpose and asked that visit be postponed or cancelled. HaySo. C 388-9/1 October 18, 1946 With reference to cry letter of yosterday about the proposed visit of a Pakistan Warship to Gwadur, I have the honour to inform Your highness that His Excellency the Political Resident has now suggested to the Pakistan Government that the visit be abandoned or post poned owing to the short notice. I entirely a^ree with him that this would be preferable and trust that the Pakistan Government will find it possible to alter their arrangements accordingly. Your Highness’ sincere friend, \ His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat.Muscat S/89 13th October 1948 IjV (JljL&amp;Sls | X - . V X '?/ Fleass refer to your letters Kos.C 387-9/1 and C 388-9/1 dated I7th and 18th October 1948. » We are glad to know that H.JS.the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has suggested to the Pakistan Goreroment that the proposed visit be abandoned owing to the short notice. Further we are to point out that it is not only owing to the short notice but there are several points to be discussed and clarified in connection with such matters and we consider that such visits should not take place before we have the opportunity to discuss them personally with H.E.the Political Resident on our next meeting. Mr.R.F.J&amp;lison, His Britannic Majesty^ Consul, Muscat\»*w m Telegram Inter 2 From Political Agent, Muscat To Political Resident, Pahrain No. 3 Dated the 18th October, 1948 Important • Your telegram Yo. 14. Vis3t of Pakistan Warship. 2. I received yesterday a separate request from Karachi in similar terms and passed it on to Sultan without other comment than apology for short notice. He has not yet replied and I trust matter will he droppedTelegram GTC From Political Agent, Muscat To Government of Pakistan ( No. C 269 ) Rep. Political Resident, Bahrain No. 6 Dated the 19th October, 194^• Immediate. Your telegram No. 404&amp; October 17th. Visit of Warship. Sultan would not object to her entering territorial waters but considers landing of Officers and men inadvisable. He feels that before Pakistan Warships visit Gwadur a ceremonial visit should be paid to him at T fuscat. Political/EllisonDespatch No* 2 British Cons-ulats^ I4ueoat* October 21, 1948* /f.wA I have the honour to invite a reference to ngr telegram No* 6 of the 19th October about the proposed visit of His Jlajesty^s Pakistan Warship n Sind w to Gwadur and to enclose a copy of a letter I have received from His Highness. 2 . I think the letter indicates not only the concern His Highness feels about the future visits of His Majesty’s Pakistan Ships to Gwadur and Muscat but also a distinct nervousness as a result of the somewhat marked tendency to encroachment shown by the Pakistan Government in recent months. 3. Kis Highness also displayed, when I last saw him, distinct signs of being offended at the action of the Pakistan Government in sending a Warship to Gwadur before paying a formal visit to Muscat itself. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, ii , m His Excellency Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE., CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. asr*Kg. 305(52/48) Britisli l^ency, G-waciur, rhe 6th October 1943• ^Yom To The British A^ent, i.vadur. The Political A^ent k His Lajesty f s Luscat. Jonsul, Sir, I liave trie honour to report that two warships appeared in the ^ast Bay of G-waciur in the afternoon of ord Gctooer ana ^inciiored near the mouth of the Bay. Taking than to oe RN Ships I went to visit than on the following mornin as per instructions contained in your Lemorandum No. 0-72-14/13 dateu the 19th January 194o out founa out that the ships were of the Pakistan ilavy - HIPS' Sind” and PUPS 'Peshwar'. The Captain of the 'Sind” (an Jnlish in an) received me nicely anu told me that his ships, were on a training cruise in the Persian Juif anu tiiat he had anchored there to refuel the 'Peshwar H . The siiips sailed for the Gulf on the morning of the day of my visit. I have tlie honour to be, ‘-dr, Your most obeuient servant,Telegram From To No. GTC Political Agent British Agent, C 276 Dated the 27th October, 1948. , i.fuscat Gv/adur Important. Your letter No. 305 October 6th. Please telegraph if Warships came within three miles boundary limit. Ellison. Telegram GTC From Btitish Agent, Gwadur To Political Agent, I4uscat No. 327 Dated the 2&amp;th received the 30th October, 1948. Important. Your C 276 October 27th. As far as I could judge Warships were outside 3 mile boundary limit. British Agent. — —Telegram From To No. Dated the 2nd Inter 2 Political Agent, ruscat Political Resident, Bahrain 12 November, 1°4^• Seference my telegram No. 6 October 19th. Visit of Y;arships. 2. British Agent Gwadur reports that warships 'Sind’ 1 and M Peshawar 0 anchored near mouth of East Bay on October 3rd. He called on Captain of Sind who said that ships were on training cruise in Gulf and had anchored to refuel 'Peshawar'. Ships sailed day later for Gulf. 3. They were outside the 3 miles limit. Ellison1 Telegram Enclair From Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, on board 'Wildgoose* 1 To Political Agent, -Muscat No. 251516 2 Dated the 25th received the 26th Nov 1948. From SNOPG. Please request His Highness the Sultan to do me the honour of dining on board hild’goose with four of his entourage on Wednesday 1st. 2. Request pleasure of company of yourself at the same party. 3. Official invitation on arrival when please supply list of names. If ’fcjor Gre &gt;nwood can be included in Sultan’s entourage I would he 'rateful. SNOPG. Enclair Political Agent, Muscat Warship Nildgoose, care Navj r charge, Colombo C 295 Dated the 27th November, 1948• For S.M.O.P.G. Thanks for invitation. Sultan pleased to accept. Details on arrival. K11ison.Telegram From Enclair Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, Gildgoos To Cable and VJireless, Muscat No. Too 271221 D Dated and received the 27th November, 1948. Please pass to Political Agent's office and His highness the Sultan. H. ,S /ildgoose arrives Muscat 0430 I'fT December 1st. Salute of 21 guns will be fired. Please set watch 500 Kilocycles at 0200 GMT SNOFGC 429(9A) * V' November 28, 1948. I h&amp;ve the honour to inform Tour highness that H.i.S. Viiildgoose will arrive in 'nacat on the 1st December at 8.30 am and will salute the country. I also wish to inform Your Highness that I will be accompanying His Ixcellency on his tour of the Batinah, and will be back on the 1 st in sha» allah. Your ] ig} nee s’ since^friend.NOTE BY P.A. kFmi DISCUSSIOK .I'I PJ^IDEIfr, Sultan does not particularly want them at Muscat, but would like a hint dropped if they ask again for permission to visit Gwadur that Muscat should come first. ltd. R.E.E. 6/126 tii December, li&gt;48. CCiiKIPLMTXaL (188/10/43) V Please refer to correspondence ending with riy u&amp;nuiabered telegram of the 17th Getc^ber, reg&amp;rclin^ tiie visit of a Pakistan war si ip to Gwadur. When the Political Ager* t. t aakcd the Bui tan 2 for permission for the *'o IKD*' to vi^It Cwadur, he remarked that he thought that the Pakistan Govern ent ought to arrange for one of their warships to pay a courtesy visit to v his capi tal before they sought permission for the visit of a warship to any other part of his dominions. 3. Turing y recant visit to i scat I asked him whe ther be wished us to suggest to the Pakistan Governnent that they should send a warship on a courtesy visit to «(urcat f and he replied that t! e less he su# of the P&amp;Kistan havy the better he would be pleased, but that he was still of the opinion that they ought to pay such a visit before they sought his permission for a visit to any other part of his territo ries. if therefore I again receive a direct approach from the * on this subject, I propose if necessary to bring this point to their notice. 4. I am sending copies of this letter to Burrows and Gillson / (’V.R. HAY) bir baiirence Graff tey amith, K.B.K., 0. l.G., United Kingdom High Commissioner for fakistan KARACHI.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000049_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/298</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000049</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/298</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/1 I Naval &amp; Shipping: Movements of HM Ships and Naval Officers'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-23T22:07:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (279 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order, from the front to the rear. At the rear of the file are internal office notes (ff 262-280).</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 281; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 266-281; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence concerning the movement of ships through Muscat. The majority of the file is made up of notifications of the arrival and departure of HM ships into and out of Muscat. These papers deal with the questions of gun salutes and official visits when appropriate. Other matters covered by the file include: the movement of naval officers; programmes for official tours (such as that of the Political Resident in December 1947, see folios 193-194); arrangements for injured servicemen during the Second World War (folios 4-14); requests for water, coal, interpreters, escorts, cash, and other miscellaneous things; and the question of new arrangements for the ships of newly-independent India and Pakistan when visiting Muscat and Gwadur.The principal correspondents are: the Political Agent, Muscat; the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; and Sultan Said bin Taimur of Muscat [Sa‘īd ibn Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd] or his Secretary. Other correspondence comes from: the Government of India, External Affairs Department; Flag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Navy; Air Officer Commanding British Forces, Iraq; Naval Officer in Charge, Hormuz; the High Commissioner for the UK in Pakistan; the Commonwealth Relations Office; the British Agent, Gwadur; and the British India Steam Navigation Company Limited.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner to Pakistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Officer Commanding, Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commonwealth Relations Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British India Steam Navigation Company Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000049#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>