<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000360_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T13:42:15.051Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">^cyiy&lt;*^Li*e+jh NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROMthe Government, Bahrain, Dated, 30th Dnl Haj 1346 ITo. Office 'tu. Adviser to The H. B, M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum H. E, Shaikh Hamad is anxious to increase ShaiMi Sir Isa bin Ali T s pay 'by Rs 1000/- from the first Maharam 1347. Will you please let me know if you approve, I personally am in favour of it. Captain, Adviser to the Government, Bahrain.IH«.C/192 •f 1928. Th« Political Agency, Bahrein,20th June 1928. Th« Adviser, Bahrein State, Bahrein. by him that it iii deairabl# te increase the allewance ef E.iiJ. Sheikh lea te R ».5000/- p.m. Sheilch Mehamad bin Sheikh lea has represented % te me fer some time that his allowance of Hs.SOOO/- is Quite inadequate to muintain him, cenaidering the heavy calls en his puru© made by hia mether and his family.One of his sens who had an allowance of Rs.350/- monthly feund this sum reduced by Hs.50/- last year. Sheikh Hehaned though the elder draws an allowance considerably smaller than his brother Sheikh .tbdulla,and if H.IS.Sheikh Hamsid desires to increase his allowance te Rs.3500/- monthly I am prepared to approve the proposal. Political Agent,Bahrein.Ho. / Office 5e oy t of 1347 the Adviser to the G-OTernment, Bahrain. Dated, 11th, Safar, 1348 The H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir In forwarding the returns for the year 1346, I would point out that they v/ere all drawn up 'by Mr. Belgrave 'before proceeding on leave to the United Kingdom, and I have simply filled in certain items which it was impossible to complete until the end of the Financial Year. I 'beg to remain Sir, Your Obedient Servant ——^ Captain, Ag. Financial Adviser to the G-overnment, Bahrain,IJo. of 134H Office of the Adviser tof the Government, Bahrain,' Dated, 11t h Dul Qaad 46 Ihe H. B. M'd Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to forward herewith the new Budget for the year 1347 and also returns and explanatory notes on the revenue and expenditure for the year 1346. 1347 Budget . This is the third Budget which I have had the honour to submit. Practically the whole of the State's revenue is derived from the Customs. Each year as a result of increased revenue, I have thought it safe to budget slightly higher than for the previous year owing to the fact of there being an increase in actual revenue. In 1345 a revenue of Rs. 7,50,000/- from Customs Receipts was estimated in the Budget. The actual collections amounted to Rs. 9,68,000/-. In 1346 a revenue of Rs. 8,50,000/- was estimated. The actual collections reached Rs. \e&gt;S r ^ i S&gt;oeA^For 1347 I have estimated Customs Receipts at Rs # 9 t 00 t 000/-. Unless the pearl season turns out a bad one I am confident that this amount will be reached, I hope that it will be exceeded. Again in estimating Customs Receipts at Rs # 9 f 00 f 000/- I am allowing a margin of Rs.l^^^j-* as against actuals of 1346, Although I have budgeted higher on the Revenue Side this year than for the previous Jjfears I would point out again that the margin between the annual revenue of the State and the annual recurrent expenditure of the State is a very slight one, about Rs, 75,000/-. Although the financial position is sound the State is spending at present nearly the whole of its annual revenue on recurrent monthly expenditure such as the allowances to the Ruling family which alone absorb more than half the whole revenue. The sum of Rs. E,00,000/- has been set aside during the past year to form the basis of a State reserve fund. This money is on Fixed Deposits in Bombay and produces interest at 4^. It is hoped that the fund will be added to yearly. The reserve fund has been shown on the Budget entirely separately. Apart from the Reserve fund the State com pleted the year with a credit balance of Rs.-3- Rs. ——» in Bahrain and Bombay and no financial liabilities whatever. The actual assets from 1346, apart from the expected revenue for 134® have been alloted in the new Budget mainly towards special projects such as the electric installation and the proposed road across the sea to Muharrat* The sum of Rs. ^^^^jt-.will be added, it is hoped, to the Reserve fund during the new year. I think there are no other items in the Budget requiring explanation. I have the honour to be. Sir Your Obedient Servant financial Adviser,Botes on Revenue for 1346• She total revenue eolleeted during tiie year 1346 from all sources was Rs. 12,40,055/-. Out of this amount 10,68,660/- was collected from the customs only. In the year 1345, the total customs collec tions amounted to Rs. 9,62,041/-. She increase in revenue, from customs, over the last year is therefore Rs. 96,619/-. The Customs Receipts during the three last years have shown a steady increase. 1344 Total Collections (Customs) Rs. 8,82,894/- 1345 ' 9,62,041/- 1346 ' 10,58,660/- (Dhe following trade report from information supplied by the Director of Customs explains the increase under various headings. ^Comparative statement of receipts (Customs) Steamers' Cargoes Rs Native Craft Parcels Duty Passengers Baggage Export Duty RS Cargoes Duty Import Yard Dues Miscellaneous year 1345 576,840/- 125,125/- 18,040/' 19,528/- 4,209/- 67,018/- 147,684/- 5! 143/- T5T 647,903/- 104,550/- 22,649/- 37,662/- 3,781/- 73,128/- 164,566/- 4,440/- Total Rs. 963,587/- 1058,679/- The above comparison will show an increase this year of Rs. 95,000/- which is accounted for by.- Commodity. Java 8c Beet Sugar Loaf Sugar Piece y-oods sundries Increase Rs. 30,000/- 27,000/- 38.000/ - Rs. 95.000/ - The rather remarkable increase in duties from sugar appears to be due to the decrease in thethe wholesale costs of the various kinds of sugar, duewas to trade competition. This cheapening market has tempted merchants to develop an export trade from this State to neighbouring Ports. The increase in Piece Goods and sundries is a direct sequel to a good pearling season, which has provided more money for expenditure upon luxuries. The HE collections indicate a satisfactorily steady improvement of 6^. The decrease in Hative Craft collections is accounted for by the reduction in fixed duties upon ghee and date-sticks consistent with the market value; and also to a considerable decrease in the movement of tobacco and dates, and to the practice of direct transhipment at sea. In general the trend of business indicates steady improvement and the relations between the Customs and the mercantile community are good. Revenue. Vehicle Licenses . The collec tions are about four times the estimated amount; and although the import of Ford cars has decceased, other large high pov/er cars (mostly fiats) have been imported. I fancy that the State has now absorbed its limit in this direction, though there is a like lihood that a number of the new Ford type may be imported next year. I think the collections in 1347 will not be so large as in 1346. Pearling Licenses The collections for 1346 are a little less than in 1345. This is due to the fact that licenses have appreciated the prudence of renewing their licenses promptly, without payment of the fines imposed for late renewals. The number of Licensed-3- Lieensed pearling craft in Bahrain is 507. Craft Registrations . For the same reason asjaboTe the collections for 1346 are a little lower than in 1345. The total number of crafts of all classes in Bahrain is 1414, It is however noteworthy that the industry keeps steady, and quite a number of craft are regularly built for sale to other ports. Dhere are 23 motor driven craft in this port; and the tendency is to build the larger type of extra-port joliboat and to equip it with a .British Motor Engine. This has proved dist#lnctly successful for cargo work between this State and mainland Ports and I think such construction will increase. Rent of Government Lands . There is a marked decrease in these collections due to the gift of a large number of dategardens to members of the dawasir tribe, who have recently settled in Budaiya the rents on which would therefore cease. passengers and cargo by steamers; but^is satisfactory to note that there does not seem to be any marked decrease in the number of n^ive craft using the port. Certain adjustments of Customs regulations have assisted such native craft merchants in their trading. . Ehe port is mainly served by the British India Steam Navigation Company, Ltd., whose steamers call here weekly with the upmail, and fortnightly with the down mail. It would be of assistance to merchants in their financial transactions if the downmail called here weekly, and I am of opinion that this is the busiest port in the Persian Gulf. r The British Tanker Co. Ltd's steamer calls here monthly General. This Port is served, both for -U:-4- monthly to replenish stocks of A.P.O.Coy Ltd's oil, which has a ready sale here in a large quantity. Hansa line steamers call here bimonthly with general European'cargo. The Strick Line Ltd T s steamers call here irregularly, generally about every three months with general cargo mainly of British origin. I consider that trade between this State and Britain would improve if this line could call here regularly direct from Britain. Their present tendency is to discharge Bahrain cargo at Bunder Abbas, for transhipment here, and naturally such cargo suffers badly from/ pilferage. There is a unanimous opinion among mariners that the port of Bahrain is dangerous to approach on account of (1) mntirriffl difficulties, reefs etc., and (2) the bad lighting of the port and its approaches. It is con sidered that (2) could be very greatly improved by (a) lighted erection of a powerful/heacon on the fesht A1 Djebal, whose light would carry atleast twenty miles and warn steamers away from the reefs and (b) by improved lighting of the port from the shore itself, which would enable steamers to make their anchorage at any time day or night. I am submitting a separate note on this point. Despite the increase of work, the Customs staff has not been increased during the past year; and the cost of the collection of the Customs and Revenue is fiire ^ni nnr per cent.Hotes on expenditure under budget headings for 124^ Allowances to the Ruling Family, About one half of the total estimated revenue is paid over yearly to the Ruling family through the Civil List and various annual allowances at religious festivals, etc. [Dhis amount does not include salaries which are paid to various Shaikhs^in addition to their allowances / who occupy positions in the such as Magistrates, Presidents of Courts, Amirs Etc. (Dhese payments are included under other headings. Protection, Judicial &amp;c. H. E. Shaikh Hamad does not ask any of the Ruling family to occupy positions entailing any work without giving to them generous additional salaries which they expect to retain after they retira from their public duties in addition to their Civil List allowances. A sum of Rs. 12,000/- spent on enlarging H. E. Shaikh Hamad l s house at Sakhir is not included -under this heading but under Public Works. The total amount paid to the Ruling family out of the State funds during 1346 was Rs, — The total budgeted amount of revenue of State was Rs. 9 # 90 # 000/-, and the actual revenue Rs. '—— In this connection I would mention that should it be considered suitable a note remarking on the heavy expenditure under this heading wouldwould be of assistance in preventing it from increasing. Almost daily requests for increases and new allowances are made and it is difficult to restrain H. E. Shaikh Hamad from approving of all of them. The Ehalifa family is rapidly increasing. There are literally scores of yo\mg sons 7/ho are not yet of age. Bo attempts are made by their parents to educate them with the idea of having to earn anything in the future. Hhen each boy marries his father presses for an allowance for him. If all of them are to receive allowances in the future, the Civil List will slowly eat up the whole of the revenue. Almost all the Khalifas own property but they drain it dry by squeezing out every anna of rent and by never spending money on keeping up their gardens. As a result the value of their gardens decreases. Protection . The second largest item of recurrent expenditure. The State forces consist of 108 Punjabi Police, 37 local Police, and 113 local armed watchmen. The Punjabi Police supply a guard to H. B. M's Political Agent, a body guard to !• E. Shaikh Hamad and posts at Muharrak and Rufaa. The balance are in Manama. The rest of the force is in Manama and in Muharrak. The whole force is under the Command^ of Captain 1. S. Parke assisted by an Indian Officer and two Amirs. Protection absorbs 17^ of the total budgetedbudgeted revenue but owing to the political and geographical position of Bahrain and the cosmopolitan population it is considered essential to maintain an efficient force. Reserve fund . Rs. 2.00.000/- . It has been possible to set aside two lacs during the year as the beginning of a reserve fund which will be added to as opportunity occurs. fhis item is shown under expenditure in order to simplify the accounts. Until now the State has had no Reserve Fund. At the end of 1344 the State owed large sums on account of sereral big contracts for public works. Everything has now been paid off and Jhe total assets shown at the end of the year are entirely free from any charges. Customs. There is little alteration in the expenditure on this department. The department collects the whole State revenue, except Court fees, and is in reality the revenue and Customs Department. It is under the direction of Mr. C. de (Jrenier and a staff of Indian and Arab clerks. The present policy is to increase the numbers of Arab clerks serving in the various departments but there is no com parison between the efficiency of Indians and Arabs. A comparison of the Revenue and the cost of maintaining the Customs Department will show that only 5^ is spent by the State in collecting the entire revenue. The financial well-being of the State depends entirely on the efficiency ofefficiency of this department. Judicial and Waqfs. During the year several Courts have been instituted or revived and a Waqf department has been re-organised. These feave resulted in increased expenditure under this heading, The Courts are as follows.- The Bahrain Court . The Adviser and Shaikh Salman bin Hamad A1 Khalifa. Petty Court . The Assistant Adviser and Amir of Manama. Shara Courts. . 1. Three Sunni Qaadis 2. The Shia Qaadi. Majlis Tijara . A commercial Court of 24 mer chant members under the presidency of a Shaikh of the Ruling family. Diving Court . During about 4 months of the year. Consists of 4 members and a Shaikh. Waqf Departments . (Shia and Sunnis) The Qaadis assisted by Clerks and Supervisors together with an advisory council. These Courts etc. entaii£^considerable expen diture in salaries and general upkeep. Tfie cost of maintaining the above Courts etc. is Rs. 27 f 600/-. Total Court fees collected during 1346 amounted to Rs. ^ PUBLIC WORKS . lo public works of outstanding importance have been entered upon this year but the following minor repairs etc. have been carried out. 1. Partial re-building of Police Station in Manama and Customs Clerks 1 quarters. 2. Extension and repairs to H. E. Shaikh Hamad 1 s private house at Sakhir. 3. Repairs to Customs Pier badly damaged by heavy se^.4. Gates and wall at entrance of Customs Pier. 5. Completion of new summer rooms on roof of Shaikh Hamad 1 s state palace in Manama• 6. Building of mosque at Idari spring. 7. Repairs to Rafaa and Sehla road and mending bridges. 8. Repairs to Budeya Road and bridges. 9. lew Road across Suk A1 Khamis. 10. Additions to Quarantine. 11. Rebuilding of Agency Pier. 12. Building of two new Shia Schools. 13. Repairs to old Persian Mosque at Suk A1 Khamis. 14. filling in of ^ea Spaces inside the Sea Road. The State has no Public Works department. All such work is carried out under the supervision of the Adviser and Mr. Mohomed Zhalil, the Super visor of the Land Department. Education . The monthly allotment to the Education committee was raised from Rs. 1000/- to Rs. 3500/-. Uew Schools have been opened in Hidd and in Rufaa and the Manama and Muharrakk schools have been enlarged. The teaching staff has also been increased. Two Shia Schools are now being started. These are the first Shia Schools in Bahrain which have been supported by the State. The Shia Community subscribed towards the building and the State doubled the amount that was subscribed. These schools are to be maintained by the State in the future.Municipalities, Since last year a Municipality has been established in Muharrak. It receives a monthly subsidy of Rs, 2000/- per month. This doubles the expenditure under this heading. Electric Installation and Manama Muharrak Road. not commenced. Land Registration and Settlement Department . !Ehe Land Registration Department has dealt with about 300 sales, transfers etc. during the year. It is satisfactory to see that the number of applications steadily increases and the public appreciate this branch of the Grovernment. The work of the Land Settlement Department which is also the Survey Department has been some what restricted owing to illness among the Indian Surveyors. It carried out a detailed surbey of the stretch of shallow sea between the islands of Manama and Muharrak, wkiek with a view to the proposed sea road between those islands. The Survey of the gardens in the Khalifa Estate case which has been going on for 86 years was com pleted. five villages together with their date gardens were surveyed and their water rights were settled and recorded. The work of the department although somewhat expensive will be of lasting value and will put an end to the incessant disputes usually between Arabs and Bahamas over boundaries and irrigation rights. The Department is well equipped with modern Survey instruments which have gradually been pur chased by the State.SctT.51 18th September*X926* Three copies of the uaderxaeiitioned letter together with their eucioaures are i'orwaracd to the Secretary to the Hon # toie to the Political Heeident in the paraian Oulf # Buahire, I have no reioarKe to aaxe except that the Budget allotment for education iB too email an«b-l am calling the attention of the Advieer to thie point* Letter Ho.124/52 of 1547 dated 11th Dul qaad 1546 Tdih safar 1547. from the Adviser t Bahrain State, with enclosure* political Agent 9 Bahrain. 4 XDr aft for approval. No.T. 51• 18th September,1928• if! x i Three copies . of. the under, i eat lone d lettei^are forwarded to to the Secretary' to the Hon 1 Die to the Political 'esident in the Persian GulfjBushire. I have no remarks to make except that the Budget allotment for education is too small and 1 am calling the attention of the Adviser to this point. Political A ^ent, Bahrain. P m % Letter Ho • 124/32 of 1347 dated ilth Dul Q^aad 1346 from i3th Safar 1347. the Aaviser Bahrain State, with enclosure.Ho. | $17 of i 928 British Hesictenqy &amp; Consulate-General, -7 Bushire, the .-September j.928. 2.7 ?rom The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf. To Sir, The Political A^ent, Bahrein• P In reply to your Ho.T.5i dated tthe i8th September 1928 forwarding the new Budget of Bahrein State for the year 1347 with the Adviser Bahrein State's remarks and explanatory notes on the Revenue and Expenditure for 1346, I am directed by the Hon'ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf to say,that the Budget seems very satisfactory but that with receipts under head Revenue Exceeding Estimates, a regular sum should be adued to the Reserve Pund, The aim of the State should gradually be to have a savin^ of at least one year's revenue as a Reserve to meet unforseen circumstances. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf lurther directs me to say that he agrees v/ith i^e that eaucution is the dominant interest. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, YwUr most obedient servant, / •e Major, * •Secretary to the Political Resident in the P w r s i a n Gu If,H». C 211 1928. Political Agency, Bahrein. The 19th Octebcr 1928. n m) To The Adviucr, Bahrein Government, Bahrein. Memorandum- ^ Please refer to the correapondenoe ending with your letter Ko e/^jL ^ /3^ The Hen'hie the Political Resident is of opinion that the Budget is very satisfactory tout in. ' f ' L the receipts under head ' Revenue ' exceeding the eatlmate a regular sum should toe added to the Reserve Pund. The aim of the State should toe to have a saving of at least one year's revenue to meet unforeseen circum- -stances. The Budget Estimate x'or Education is very small considering the income of the State and the fact that income so largely exceeds expenditure. The Political Resident considers that education is the dominant factor in Bahrain, vv^ Political Agent, Bahreinno. 'T'S?6 ■ ^1347 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 27th Shahban 1347 To H. B. M 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain, Sir, I have the honour to draw your attention to the alarming increase in Civil List and allow ances which will be apparent at the end of the Arabic Year when the Rex r enue and expenditure figures are submitted for your inspection. As Financial Adviser to the State I feel that it is necessary to point out the following facts and ask for your advice and assistance in the matter. The revenue of the State now exceeds the expenditure. During the last three years about 4 lacs have been saved increasing the State funds which are invested in Bombay to seven lacs. it is proposed that most of th^s money should be spent on the electrification of Manama and a road across the sea to Muharrak island. For the time being the financial position of the State is sound, but if the Ciiil List and allowances continue to increase in the proportion that they are increasing now in a few years they will absorb the greater part of the revenue.The Ruling Family is large and ever increasing. When each young Shaikhling marries he demands an allowance from the Civil List, When, occasionally, an old Shaikh dies Shaikh Hamad always allots his salary to his heirs. With I think^two exceptions,none of the Ruling Family make any attempts to earn their dvm living. Because they are of the Khalifa they expect to be supported from ( State Funds. Almost all of them constantly apply to Shaikh Hamad for higher allowances. Shaikh Hamad is very good natured and as the money is paid from State Funds, not from his privy purse, he does not discourage these demands. Every year the State incurs additional expenditure such as Eduuation, Municipalities, etc., and the revenue does not increase corres pondingly. At present there are no serious finan cial difficulties but it is necessary to con sider the future. I have talked to Shaikh Hamad on the subject innumerable times but he fails to appre ciate the necessity of keeping down the Civil List. When I speak about it is he always replies 'Inshallah* 'the Revenue will Increase' It does not. I believe that Shaikh Hamad agreed to make no changes in the Civil List without dis cussing it with the Political Agent. If this is so I should be greatly assisted if you would see your way to writing an official reminder-3- si either to him or to me. It would be of much help in modifying Shaikh Hamad's uncontrollable generosity, from Public funds, to those of his relations who are persistent enough in worrying him. Shaikh Hamad has no real idea of money values and it is difficult to persuade him to give suitable attention to the financial affairs of the State. I have only lately, with much difficulty, made him learn how many lacs of rupees are collected and spent each year. The Budget is submitted to Shaikh Hamad and sanctioned by him and he keeps one copy himself, but he recklessly dis-regards it^ considering that as long as there is cash in the Bank it can be spent on any purpose quite regardless of the projects which have been budgeted for. As regards his own finances I am certain that whatever amount Shaikh Hamad draws he will always think it insufficient. For three years I have managed Shaikh Hamad's own private money affairs, at his request. When I advise economy he reminds me that Shaikh Isa used to spend most of the revenue on himself. Shaikh Hamad fortunately, owes no money to anyone but he is spending every rupee of his income at present. Lately he has suggested that all proceeds from sales of property by the State should be paid to his privy purse, not to the Treasury. Personally I think this would be unwise and an encouragement to sell land at any price.I understand that in some Indian States a definite percentage of revenue is set apart for the Civil List. It increases and decreases according to the Revenue. I suppose each years Civil List is assessed on the previous year's revenue. I should be glad if you could give me any particulars of this system and inform me whether you think it would be wise to suggest it to Shaikh Hamad. At present Shaikh Hamad takes only a very slight interest in the revenue, knowing that his allowances are not directly affected by it, and the other members of the Khalifa family take no interest in it at all. I do not think that half a dozen of them know whether the revenue is ten or thirty lacs. If their salaries were directly affected they would co-operate more in increasing this revenue. One difficulty is that already the Civil List absorbs almost 45$ of the estimated revenue. The enclosed figures will show the position since I have been in Bahrain. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your Obedient Servant, Financial Adviser.Allowances. Total Revenue. 1344 1345 1346 1347 Rs. 4,34,875/- 4,34,324/- 4,34,8E9/- 4,68,324/- Rs. 13,500/- 26,770/- 27,770/- 87,770/- Rs. 4,48,375/- 4,61,094 4,62,599/- In addition to this the following were paid.- paid to Sh.Hamad for building a private house Rs. 12,150/- Fidawis. 1,695/- 4,96.084/- Eote.- Some additional allowances were only ordered during the current year and started some months before the year commenced. Rs. 10,62,331/- 11,91,810/- 12,40,655/- 11,00.000/- (These are approximate figures) In addition to these allowances the following sum is paid for presiding on courts and ucMaxp occupying positions as allowances. annually to Amirs, etc. members of the Khalifah family as salaries These salaries are in addition to their Amir ft of Rafaa Manama Rais Majlis Tajarah Magistrate, Bahrain Court ' Small Court Kaadir Sunni Waqfs Rs 2400/- 2400/- 2400/- 2400/- 480/- 600/- / 4/ /'! • &lt;^7 OS* No. of 1348 Office of the Adviser to the Government. Bahrain, Dated am 1548 of 1348 To H. B. M f s Political Agent Bahrain. i Sir I have the honour to forward herewith the State Budget for 1348 together with a summary of Revenue and Expenditure for 1347 with expla natory notes on same. 1348 Budget s This is the fourth Budget which I have had the honour to submit. REVENUE, Again this year I have increased the estimate of Revenue from Customs Receipts, which is the Stated chief source of wealth. Last year this item was estimated at Rs. 9,00,000/-. This year I have increased it to Rs. 9,60,000/- allowing a margin of one lac between the actual receipts for 1347 and the estimated receipts for 1348. It would be dan gerous to budget for a larger amount, as it is generally thought that trade prospects for the coming year are not as promising as at the begin ning of last year. This is owing to the dis turbed conditions on the mainland, the exclusion-2- ' r&amp;) exclusion of Persians from Bahrain except with proper passports, and the dull condition of the Paris Pearl market. The Pearl season so far seems moderately good hut diving has 'been adversely affected hy rough weather. Rents of Government Lands . This used to 'be a substantial source of revenue hut it does not appear this year as all the property in question was handed hack to the persons from whom it was confiscated. The Royalty from the Eastern ajnd General Syndicate, Ltd., is not shown this year as it is uncertain whether the license will he renewed. Other revenue . Under headings such as vehicle, 'boat, and pearling licenses etc. I have 'budgeted slightly higher than last year, keeping in mind the actual collections for 1347. Interest on Reserve . This includes interest on all funds in Deposit Account in Bombay, The interest paid is, on an average, 4% per annum. It is now proposed that the Reserve Pund amounting to three lacs shall 'be invested i .n Government of India stock paying b% interest. In the summary of cash assets over two in lacs is showa as lying/current account. The reason is that it was transferred from Deposit account to meet the first payment to Messrs, Callender 1 s Cable and Construction Co. Ltd,, on account of the Electric scheme. Including the Reserve Pund, of three lacs the State completed the year with a cash balance-3- balance of and a half lacs, an increase of over one lac on the cash balance at the end of 1546. Apart from the Electric Light contract the State has no financial liabilities. EXPENDITURE . The headings for recurrent expenditure are the same this year as last year but in Borne cases the expenditure has increased. I have only allowed a very slight margin for additional expenditure above the actual amounts on the paylists. Recurrent expenditure ^ 1. Allowances to Ruling Family. Al though the estimated revenue is budgeted at Rs. 44,000/- more than last year this item still total absorbs very nearly half the/revenue. Estimated Revenue from all sources. Rs. 10,55,000/- Allowances to ruling family, 1348 5,15,000/- The amount allotted to this heading in the new budget is Rs. 56,000/- more than last year. The actual pay lists amount to Rs. 53,000/-,, ✓ but as every year the budgeted figure has been greatly exceeded I have allowed Rs. 3000/- for unforseen demands. If the civil list continues to increase as it has during the last three years, it will in about ten years have the entire revenue of the State. I give below a comparison of the last four yea.rs. year 1344 Rs. 4,44,000/- 1345 4,34,000/- 1346 4,62,000/- 1347 5,15,000/-2. Protection , The allotment for pro tection is slightly less this year owing to a reduction in the strength of the Indiai Police. 3. Government Departments , The only noticeable difference under this heading is the reduction in the allotment to the Land Department, At present only one surveyor is 'being employed and until the end of the summer no more surveyors will 'be enlisted. Last year provision was made for eight surveyors all through the year. The appointment of two shia Qadis and a separate Shia Waqf Department, also the increased pay of the Sunni ^adis has necessitated more expenditure under Judicial and Waqfs, 4. Education , An additional Rs, 12,000/- has 'been allowed under this item for the develop ment of technical education and also for the expansion of the Shia School when the building is completed. The remaining items of recurrent expendi ture scarcely differ from last year. The excess of revenue over recurrent expenditure as 'budgeted this year is Rs, 31,000/- not a largfa margin. Special Pro.iects , The actual contract for the electrification of Manama is for L 20,607/17/8 Pounds Sterling, but an additional amount is needed for the inside work on the palace and on Government buildings. It is essential that the State should own a Government Launch, H, E, Shaikh has now to hire a launch when he requires one, as he presented his own to the Shaikh of Kathar two years ago #-5- I (S H. E. Shaikh Hamad wishes psca^t^S&amp;y to purchase a well 'boring machine for the purpose of agricultural experiments, Unforseen expenditure # The sum of Rs. 75,000/- appears a large allotment unier this heading 'but it allows for the return of the rents to the Khalid Shaikhs whose property was confiscated Toy the Government owing to their complicity in the Sitra murders. Compensation , This includes Government's compensation to victims of fires and other misfortunes as well as compensations ordered by the Courts in cases of illegal gifts of private property 'by H, E # Shaikh Isa which continue occasionally to come to light, I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Financial Adviser, Bahrain State.CrOTERMCENT OF BAHRAIN Budget for the year - 1348. Ctistoms Receipts, duty including, a. Supervision fees 'b Sales of forms c. Weight certificates d. Amendment fees e. Certificate fees f. Khanchi g. Hamali h. Pier fees i. Royalty charges. Total of alDove .. ## Rs 1 Taxes on Motor Cars, Drivers T Licenses [I Pearling Licenses J Boat Registrations Miscellaneous fees etc # Judicial Receipts I Interest on reserve II Loans Recoverable # Cash assets at 'beginning of year 1348, * Fixed Deposits, Bombay excluding reserve, Cash in Consolidated Fund,Bahrain ' Lloyd f s Bank, Bombay current a/c with Eastern Bank:, Bombay ## 9,60,000/- 5,000/- 55,000/- 3,000/- 7,000/- 10,000/- 15,000/- 27,098/- 2,00,000/- 1,10,238/- 35,259/- 2,04,981/- Total Rupees 16,32,576/- BL^= T L a0eS -r n0t ineluae Reserve, Rs, 3 ,00 000/- Three Laos, which is on Fixed Deposit, in Bombay, Sealed. Shaikh Hamad bin Isa A1 Khalifah. Deputy Ruler of Bahrain.JJotes on revenue collected. The following is a comparison of the total revenue collections during the last four years. 1344 — Rs 10,62,000/- 45 — 11,92,000/- 46 — 12,40,000/- 1347, t - 12,16,000/- The following is from information supplied 'by the Director of Customs. 'Comparative statement of receipts (Customs) Year 1346 1347 Steamers' Cargoes Rs 6,47,903. Rs 6,25,786 Native craft 1,04,560. 1000,091 Parcels Duty 22,649. '25.362. Passengers T Baggage 37,662. 53,990. Export Duty 3,781. 2 878 H.E.Duty 73,128. 78,066^ Miscellaneous 4^440. 5 145 Import Yard 1.64.566. l.esllg?! Total Rs 10,58,679. 10,59,445, 'The above comparison shews an increase for 1347 over 1346 of Rs 766/-. 'Steamers T cargoes shews a decrease of Rs 22.117/- this decrease is mainly due to * ' 1. decrease in the import of ballam rice bv ah out 5^ ^ 2. in Rangoon rice 'by about 10^ and 3. in coffee by about 20^. i 6 J - the wholesalers were well stocked; and in the last month of 1347 there was a slump in sale with a tail off in the demand from the mainland, probably owin^ to the present dis- i° nS ' ana eonse&lt; inently local merchants I fear tha+^hn®* I have no figures available, but • if 't-hat Dubai merchants are attempting to conrnete f0r the ^ ^orts, 'trade, there being no import duty, as such in Dubai. Native craft cargoes, shew a decrease caused bv 1. direct transhipment at sea, 2. the Manama Baladia tax upon imports of tobacco of 2fi. This tax is levied upon imports of tobacco whether Intended for import ed y f ^or^opr^^hfLni ci ^ft ° s-2- ny 'Parcels duty shews an increase of Rs 2,713/-, mainly due to an increase of luxury articles such as perfumes etc. 'Passengers Baggage shews an increase of Rs 16,328/-, due to closer superTision of Persian craft, which are now made to anchor closer to Manama Pier, and are inspected at sea, whenever possible, by the Passport Officer, who hires a launch for this pur pose. The necessity for a State Launch is therefore justified. Also, a large quantity of ghee is brought here from Busreh as passengers 1 deck cargo, and the duty thereon falls under this head. 'Export Duty shews a decrease due to slackness in export of^oystershells to Europe. This of course does not include pearls or specie on which no duty is charged. TT RE duty shews an increase of Rs 4938/- partly due to the concession granted to al Qaseyby to import a consignment of rice for H.M. The Sultan of Ha^d, all of which bags of rice were of special weights, and partly due to the secure situation of Bahrain for trade purposes. 'Miscellaneous includes an increase of Rs 600/- in supervision fees, due to facilities granted by the Customs for landing bulk cargo at private wharves under supervision, 'Import Yard Charges shew an increase. These charges are levied on the nature and size of the packages, and naturally vary considerably. Included therein is H. E. the Deputy Ruler's Royalty tax on Agents T Landing Oharges, amounting this year to Rs 6558/6/6 of which Rs 5538/9/6 were collected from the Agents of the B.I. S.H.Co. Ltd., and Ellerman Strick Lines (The Mesopotamia representing their collections of Rs 1,10,771/14/- in Landing charges. 'Cargo directly transhipped at sea, but within the f 6 ?! ? ? limit of the port, is not liable to any duty an ?: ^ ls . 3:ias a distinct effect upon Customs Receipts notably in the case of oil etc., brought here by British Taoker Steamers from Atadan.a 'l H et I already sub- mitted a note upon this point. 'During the year 1347, 118 steamers entered this port, and the collections were,- Steamers Import RE D Capital Total dlr ty yalue Co. ltd. 77 5,25,984/- 76,224/- 105,19,580/- 38.11.200/- 143,30,880/ 1Cline 20 46.381/- 1,842/- 9,27,620/ 92.100/- ? 7 -11 12.57=_ Ml 2.11.560/- S18. 6,25,786/- 78,0660- 164,19,020/--3 'The Port is mainly served 'both for passenger and cargo 'by the British India Steam Navigation Co. Ltd;, whose steamers call here weekly with the upmail, and fortnightly with the down mail. Also a weekly mail service with the mainland ports has been unof ficially instituted, and is carried on 'by a local motor launch. The chief export from Bahrain is pearls, whose value is only estimable, and does not appear here. It would be of great assistance to merchants if the down mail could call here weekly; but I understand the the Company 1 s chief objection to this is insufficiency of cargo for export, though this argument is fallacious if we compare this port with Lingah or Henjam, on the Persian side. 'Strick line steamers used formerly to land their Bahrain cargo at Bunder Abbas; but since the Persian Authorities have demanded full import duty on such cargom the steamers have called here direct from England, a procedure which greatly benefits local merchants. It is noteworthy that both the Strick and the Hansa Lines bring here more cargo from the Continent of Europe than comes from England, and the continental suppliers T invoices are in English, and their quotations are c.i.f. Bahrain. One can not help thinking that English merchants are losing a good market by not competing. 'Revenue. Comparative statement of revenue. Year 1346 1347. Vehicle Licenses Rs 6,673/- 6,161/- Pearling Licenses 68,350/- 67,025/- Craft Licenses 3,630/- 3 850/- G-overnment Lands 5,724/- *625/- Mi scellaneous 6,211/- 10,913/- 90,588/- 88,574/- 'This shews a decrease of Rs 2,014/- 'Vehicle Licenses she?/ a decrease of Rs 512/-. There are nearly two hundred motor cars in Bahrain and of these two lorries and one private car are of British make. The most popular car is the new Ford model. 'Pearling Licenses shew a decrease of Rs 1.325/- In 1346-7 there were licensed 531 pearling craft. This year there are 527 craft. Owing to a Govern ment concession to Khammos divers no penalties have decrease tlliS yea^, ™ hlGh would ^count for thi 'Craft Licenses, she?/ an increase of Rs 220/- The boatbuilding industry is steadily progressing and the tendency during the past year has been tfwards ttp ! ■ Bail; r a;:Ln ''^' llil ' t Joliboats equipped with British Thele .^fi neS Varyin§ from 25 t0 60 horsepower These craft are engaged in cargo work with the main--4- // © mainland, and also tawwasha work with the pearling fleets» Trips in such craft have 'been made from Bahrain to Kuwait and return, to Bushire and return, and to Dubai and return. I helieTe there is a great future for the Bahrain-huilt craft equipped v/ith a motor engine, hut I would prefer to see such craft also equipped with a sail. TT G-overnfliant. Lands shew a decrease of Rs 5,099/- due to certain grants 'by G-overnment of property formerly under its control. 'Revenue Miscellaneous shews an increase of Rs 4,702/- this account includes, 1. Baladia surtax of 2^ on tobacco 2. Sale of Divers account books, 3. Passport fees. 'The increase is mainly due to the Passport fees which have been collected during the past six months only. The O ustoms collects the Baladia Surtax on behalf of the Municipality of Manamah, but receivs^ no payment for this work. 'G-enerally, I think the steadiness of the above receipts shews that the prosperity of the State of Bahrain^ is maintained, consequent on a reasonably good pearling season in 1347. The relations between the Customs and the mercantile community are good.' REHTS OF GOVERIMSHT LAEDS. This includes Rs 10,000/- being Soyalty paid by the Eastern and General Syndicate, on their oil concession. The balance consists of rent from the confiscated property of the Khalid Shaikhs. kOAlS . For some years past the Government has lent Rs 15,000/- at the beginning of the pearling season, to Mohomed bin Subah, the headman of the Bin Ali tribe, a leading Narkhuda. Rs 6000/- was lent to Shaikh Abdul Latif A1 Dosri, the headman of the Dawasir at Budeya. Rs 4000/- was lent to Ahmed bin Khalifah al Gattam a relative of E. E. Shaikh Hamad, one of the few members of the Ruling Family who is in the Pearl trade. Interest paid on Deposit Account, Reserve Fund and other funds held in Bombay by Lloyd T s Bank and Eastern Bank. Salejg of Government Land. Proceeds from salei -5- fa sale of plots of grotmd in the neighbourhood of Maharalc and Manama for agricultural purposes. Miscellaneous Receipt s, Sales of divers books garden produce etc.Notes on expenditure 1347. General. Th@ total expenditure during 1347 was Rs 11,82,214/- which includes one lac transferred to the Reserve fund in Bombay. The actual expenditure in several cases greatly exceeded the 'budgeted amounts. item Budgeted amount actual expenditure. Allow: to Ruling family Rs 459,064/- 5,04,489/- Judicial Department 25,500/- 29,190/- Education 40,000/- 57,883/- Upkeep of buildings and roads. 10,000/- 24,835/- Unforseen 29,436/- 41,704/- These differences are explained 'below. There is tendency to consider that the Budget of the Bahrain State is elastic and that as long as the total estimated expenditure is not exceeded, small attention need be paid to over expenditure under various headings. Some time ago it was suggested by the Hon'ble the Political Resident that a budget should be made for three years in advance. This could be done but it would be quite impossible to adhere to it; at present it is only with very great difficulty that the actual expenditure is kept within a reasonable distance from the budgeted amounts. The following notes explain the various items of expenditure. 1 * Allowances to the Ruling family . Rs 5.04,489/-. This amount does not include the additional allowances made to those persons who hold paid posts as magistrates,magistrates, amirs, and presidents of Courts etc. The increase of Rs 45,425/- over the 'budgeted amount is explained in a separate note. An additional sum of ahout Rs 16,000/- was paid to H. E. Shaikh Hamad for additional building to his houses in Muharrak and Sakhir and also for purchase of a metal fish market. The present market, which is the private property of H. E. Shaikh Hamad has for several years been in a dirty and unsanitary condition. It was thoughtthat the State should assist in this matter in the interest of public health. The total amount paid to the Ruling Family from State funds during 1347 was Rs 5,14,569/- Customs Department. The Customs expenditure shows an increase of Rs 6,600/- over the previous year. This ie results from the following reasons. (1) automatic increase of increments of senior members of staff, (2j increase of staff to deal with passport work. Until the middle of 134?'the Bahrain Government did not deal with passports. (3) employment of several local youths from government schools as paid apprentices in order that they may be eventually substitutedfor some of the foreign staff. Secretariat . Ho appreciable difference between 1346 and 1347. The expenditure is about Rs 600/- less than budgeted amount. 4. Land Dep artment. Rs 16,042/-. This shows a saving of Rs 3,070/- as compared with the previous year. Ho new instruments were purchased in 1347 and fewer surveyors were employed. It is hoped that the registration of all the culti vated area will be completed during 1348. The superin- ■bendent of this department is at present on leave on his return at the end of the summer the survey work will be s resumed.~o~ f ci) V \ 5 • Judicial and V/alcfs , V/akfs. Rs 4,500/-. The Sunni and Shia Wakf Departments are at present supported 'by the State though it is hoped that soon the departments will 'be paid for out of the wakf proceeds. Sunni. The Sunni wakfs are still under the sole control of the three Sunni Qadis who are assisted 'by two clerks and one of the the Khalifah Shaikhs. Of their actiTities, if any, little is known. It is likely that in the near future a dif ferent arrangement will 'be made. The public are at last 'becoming restless at the mal-administrati on of the wakfs and the time is ripe for the introduction of an outside committee representing the general public, who will work in conjunction with the Qadis in supervising the v/akfs. The expenses of this department are 'born entirely 'by the State but when it is re-organised the expenses should be paid from the wakf funds. The Shia wakfs were previously held by the Shia Qadi until his sudden death some six months ago. After his death the wakfs were temporarily entrusted to Shaikh Mohomed Ali Medani^i executor of the late Qadi. For some months no Qadi was appointed finally two Qadis were chosen, Shaikh Abdulla and Aly bin Hassan. The latter, on his appointment, stipulated that he should have nothing to do with wakfs. After some months Shaikh Abdulla asked that the wakfs should be handed over to him. He was persuaded to agree to a committee of which he would be President, to act with him in administering thethe wakfs. The country people objected to the Qadis presidengy and appealed to Shaikh Hamad. Finally the G-oYernment decided that neither ^haiMi Ahdulla or Shaikh Mohomed Aiy should control the Wakfs. A committee was appointed consisting of six persons from the villages and four persons from Manama and the wakfs were handed over to their charge. A local merchant was chosen as treasurer hut no president was appointed in order to placate the feelings of the Qadi and Shaikh Mohomed Ali 'both of whom are satisfied as long as the other is not in control. The arrangement was successfully accomplished about a month ago and so far there has 'been no serious opposition. An attempt was made ahout four years ago in Major Daly's time to alienate the wakfs from the Qadi but it roused such furious opposition that the suggestion was hastily dropped. The expenses of this department, pay of clerk etc. are born by the State. Judicial Rs 24,690/- The amount of litigation in the Bahrain Courts seems to increase yearly. During 1347 1064 new cases were taken by the Bahrain Court and 282 cases by the Bahrain Small Court in addition to a large number of old cases. This item includes the pay of Magistrates, Qadis, Presidents, paid members, clerks and menials of the following courts. Bahrain Court. Bahrain Small Court. Sunni Shera Court. Shia Shera Court. Mejlis Tijara Diving Court Small Joint Court.——The only changes the«e were made during the year were in connection with Mejlis Ta^ara and the Dicing Court, The Mejlis Tajara now consists of twenty members, local and foreign merchants, under the presidency of Shaikh Hamud 'bin ^ixbah al Khalifah. Ten members sit on the Court once during the week and they attend in rotation. The Diving Court consists of three important merchants in the pearl trade, Khan Saheb AMur Rehaman Ziani, Haji Abdn Ali 'bin Rajah, and Haji -^ly 'bin Seggar, with one paid member, Khalifah bu Qhais. Unfortunately at the beginning of the diving season two of the merchants were unable to continue their attendance owing to press of work. The Diving Court is intended to function only during the off season. The court holds its session in the Bahrain G-overnment Court House in Manama and sits once a week. 6. State Protection. This item includes the Indian Police, Arab Police, Naturs, upkeep of prison, and cost of depor tations. ^he strength of the forces is as follows.- Indian Police. One British Officer One Indian Officer other ranks - 96 in all. Arab Police. One Superintendent other ranks - 41. Haturs. Two Amirs 128 ITaturs. The Indian and Arab Police are supplied with quarters, uniforms and rations. The Naturs are not permanent employees and only receive pay. Many of them are divers and are given leave during the diving-6- diving season, their places being filled temporarily, 7, Itoxicipalities, The G -overnment grant to each of the Municipalities, Manama and Muharrak is Rs 2000/- per month. In addition to this they share half the total receipts from vehicle licenses and the proceeds of the 2fo tobacco tax is divided between them. The Manama Municipality ended the year with a credit balance of Rs 149,000/- and the Maharaq. Baladya which has been in existence for about two years showed a credit balance of Rs 37,844/-. A reduction in the grants to Municipalities is being considered, this would most k likely consist of cancelling the tobacco tax. Medical . This item includes the Stated contribution to the pay of Dr. Holmes, the Medical Officer, pay of the Assistant Medical Officer in Maharak and Maharak dispensary, pay and upkeep of hospital boat and pay of the quarantine staff. There is an increase in expenditure of Es 2700/- over last year. This is accounted for by salaries of a male and female vaccinator for six months during a smallpox epidemic and cost of weekly supplies of fresh vaccine. ^he public were vaccinated free. In this connection I would remark that most of those who availed themselves of the vaccination were foreigners, the local population having a prejudice against vac cination. The G-overnment has lately been requested by tne people of Maharak to provide a government midwife for work in Maharak and also to arrange for a permanent Doctor in the town. Previously the Assistant burgeon went out in the Hospital Ship during the diving season. A temporary doctor has now been appointed to the Hos pital ship and the Assistant surgeon remains permanently-7- permanently in Maharak, 9. Education, A large increase in expenditure, exceeding the 'budgeted amount, is shown under this heading. In this respect I would refer to your letter Ho. G/211 of 1928 dated 19th October quoting the remark of the Hon'ble the Political Resident that the estimate for Education is very small considering the income of the State and that education is the dominant factor in Bahrain. The expenditure in 1346 was Rs 32,119/- -do- 1347 Rs 57,883/- A rapid stride has 'been made in this direction and the State T s expenditure has increased correspondingly. Ahout 658 'boys and 104 girls are now receiving secondary education, Beyrout Students, Eight students, three of them from the ruling family and five sons of leading merchants are being educated at State expense in the American University at Beyrout, The cost of the State, including travelling expenses, is about Rs 13,000/- per annum. The reports from Beyrout are very satisfactory. One boy, whose father was a local merchant, is being educated privately at a boys f school in Brighton. Girls School, Three years ago the very idea of a girls school was considered, especially by the people of Muharrak^to be immoral and irreligious. Owing to the activities of Shaikh Abdulla bin Isa, President of the Education committee, and one or two travelled and enlightened merchants a girls f school was opened in Maharak some eight months ago. The religious and conservative element disapproved intensely and the experiment was ^o^ed from the pnlpits of the mosques. In spite of thisjjehool thrived. The women of thethe Huling family gave it strong support and it is now girl attended 'by over 100/students, The teachers are the mother and sister of one of the Syrian masters in the 'boys 1 school at Maharak assisted 'by two local women, pupil teachers. The curriculum is simple, reading, writing, arithmetic, sewing and painting. The school is very popular. The Education Committee are now being asked to open a girls* school in Manama, which as a town, is more 'broad minded than Maharak. One of the arguments against the school which was put forward seriously, was that it would injure the girls 1 chances of marriage as their looks would 'be criticized by female relations of intending suitors who would report unfavourably on their appearance. Shia School. The new Shia School was opened on the day following the Eid al Fitr by H. E. Shaikh Rs 1100/- Hamad. The sum of Rs has been eeii allotted at present for the new Manama school and the small school at Suk Al Khamis. The management of the school is in the hands of a committee of Shia merchants under the Presidency of Syed Ahmed bin Syed Alawi. The Head-master is a young Bahsani who was educated in Baghdad, his brother, and three Irakis form the school staff. The number of the boys at present is 198, as many as the building will hold. The school is warmly supported by the Shia Qadis and all the local townspeople. Persian Schools. Owing to quarrels among the committee the old Persian School divided into two schools during the year. Both schools are supported by the Persian Government and are said to be a centre for PersianPersian propoganda in Bahrain, On seyeral occasions H. E. ^haikh Hamad has been compelled to complain officially to the P olitical Agent about the aggressively military demeanon^ of the scholars and their hahit of marching through the tovm 'beating drums and flaunting Persian gia flags in the faces of the arahs. Mission School, The American Mission have 'built a new school which is shortly to he opened. The standard of education reached 'by students at the mission school is very high and superior,at present, to that at the State Schools, Technical education. There is urgent need for technical and agricultural education in Bahrain, At presenu all masons, carpenters and engineers are foreigners; mostly Persians, The question of intro ducing some such education is now being considered, 10 • Contingencies, This item includes printing stationery, office furniture and transport, flags etc, A supply of stationery v/as ordered direct from London from a large wholesale firm, and the cost was found to be considerably cheaper than either Indian or local prices. 11, Reserve, Only one lac was added to the Reserve fund during the year owing to increased expenditure under various headings of the budget. Public 'Orks, The following new works were completed during 1347 in addition to the usual repairs on roads and Government buildings. There is no regular Public Works Department but building is done by local labour at daily rates -under Government Supervision, Customs import Shed. The entire shed was re- roofed with corrugated iron sheeting. Most of theclo the old material, which has 'been put up twelve years ago, was found to 'be rotten. The area of the roof is ahout 38892sq. ft. The work was carried out departmentally. Cost Rs. 14,215/6/-, Shia School. This 'building on the south side of the town, consists of four rooms with a wide •veranda round the outside. At present half of the school as planned has 'been built. It is hoped to complete the whole during the next year. The school is solid handsome structure and is the largest and most important 'building that has 'been 'built 'by the State and not 'by contract. Cost Rs 13,666/6/4, of which Rs 5,540/- was publicly subscribed, Maharak Pier, A special grant was made to the Maharak Municipality for building a foot passengers 1 pier from the head of the Customs Pier to the deep water. The pier consists of two loose waits of flat Murabba stone with a centre filling of loose fishti 1 coral stone. Passengers csn now alight on the pier at low tide instead of having to wade, or ride on donkeys, from their boats to the Customs Pier through shallow water and mud. The shore at Maharak, unlike the shore at Manama, consists of mud down to a very considerable depth. cost Rs 6096/- Married Quarters.Fort. The existing married quarters were all repaired and new ones were built. There is now accomodation for 48families. Each quarter is a two room building. Cost. Rs 6977/- Artesian wells. Three artesian wells were sunk by the Government during the year; one at the village of Zellag, one in the Fort and one in the Palace Garden. The last is provided with two very large cement tanks and cement irrigation channels, Cost, Rs 8009/- #-11- Other minor works were as follows.- 1. Fencing of Palace garden. 2. Widening of 'bridge ©n Idari Road. 3. Store room for Land Department materials 4. Construction of § mile mud surfaced road on Meni road. 5. Rebuilding a beacon off Budeya. 6. Rebuilding of bathing pool Umm al Mishum. Idari Water Channel. The work on the water channel was completed. ^he sides and bottom of the channel have been built of cement on concrete and this has resulted in a very great saving of v/ater. The work was paid for by the owners of the property which is irrigated from Idari Spring and the Government contributed Rs 2000/- as a return for the road which runs alongside the channel being put in order. Cost Rs 21,000/- Maharak-Manama Sea Road. This formidable undertaking has not yet been commenced. Applications has been made for the services of an Engineer from the Government of India to advise on the practicability of the scheme. The distance is about one mile, across the sea which at low tide becomes almost dry ground except for a channel of unknown depth some 800 feet wide which would necessitate a ferry or a bridge. A very powerful current rushes through this channel. The entire road would have to face the full strength of the shamal wind and heavy seas. The whole population of Manama and Maharak are intensely amcious that this road should be built. Electric Scheme t Manama. A contract has been made with Messrs. Callender's Catle and Construction Co. Ltd for the electrification of Manama town, TheiC the work is to 'begin in September, The power-house is to he 'built in a corner of the Municipal Garden, a very central position. The system is alternating current supplied 'by two engines which will 'be capable in the future of supplying Maharalc. The amount of the contract is £20,607/17/8. which has been set aside for this purpose in Bombay. ? i ► i v 1Conf identialo Bahrain. J) e 0. Ko • July 12th 1929• p 51 Dear Prior. ^ f % You will se^Trom the annual accounts and 'budget which I am sending separately that the item Civil List and Allowances to Ruling family has increased since the 'beginning of last year by over half a lac. The increase is due to various young Shaikhlings having married, and become due to draw allowances, and also extra grants of allowances to the Khalids and various increases. Previous years also show a steady increase. I think that the position is serious and that unless some action Is taken this increase will continue and in a few years the Civil List v/ill swallow the whole revenue. I have written many letters on the subject and I should like you to refer to them. The following correspondence explains the position clearly. Pw'O''' My D.O. of 17/1/27 and ,your reply of same date, - 11 letter of 13th Rejab 46. n /rl - n 30/2/B of 10th Muharram 46.-—*- n 326/29 of 26 Rabia Thani 46 .—p 21$ ' * 111/2/B of 12 Safar 46. —- P Your G/52 of 8/2/29 0/27 of 20/2/29 ^ My C. 1076 of 17th Ramadan 47 r Ja n C.986 of 27 Ramadan 47. / 2 f If it is considered that the position is satisfactory,or if for political or other reasons it is inexpedient at present to raise the question with Shaikh Hamed I would be glad if you would let me know and I will cease from worrying the Political Agent on the subject, but in that case large i .ncreases will certainly continue. I would point out that I am only pressing the matter because as Financial Adviser I consider that it is my duty to do so. It vrould be far easier to just let the matter rest and allow the Civil List to increase. If any action is taken a good deal of the blame will be put onto me. When my first budget was forwarded to The Resident, about 3^ years ago I reoieved a letter in return with a copy of theMuscat Civil List suggesting that it might assist me in detirminin^ the allowances here. The implication was that I, Shaikh Earned*s adviser, should decree my employees allowance and that of his relations« I think you will agree that for me to do this would be neither politic nor possibleo Any suggestions on the subject should come from another quarter. In case any action may be taken in the matter I make the following remarks and suggestions. In spite of constant intermarriage the Khalifa family is rapidly increasing. As each young Shaikhling marries his father expects that he will be given an allowance from the State* Not only does Shaikh Hamed recieve constant requests for new allowance^ but present holders are incessantly asking for more, usually on the grounds that their families are increasing, or their gardens not producing enough rents. With the exception of two or three members none of the Khalifa attempt to earn a living, they think any form of trade is beneath their dignity,and work in any of the Government offices is degrading. None of the persons on the Civil List, except the Shaikh's brothers, will perform any public services unless they are handsomely paid to do so. With a few exceptions the Khalifa family are lazy, almost illiterate, and entirely without public spirit. I myself very much doubt their genuine alliegance to Shaikh Kamed. In the past a member of the Khalifa family held certain prestige but in these days this has fallen away from them except in the case of the three or four big shaikhs. I do not think anyone is to blame except themselves. This is partly due to increase in education and travelling. The Khalifa are far behind the merchant class in this respect. The wealth of the family is very considerable, they own all the best date gardens in Bahrain, but few take the trouble to look after the cultivation and consequently the value of the property decreases. The cost to the State of supporting this family is Rs 5,15,000, at present. The largest allowance on the Gi il List is, rightly, that ofShaikh Hamed« I do not think myself that it is too much. Shaikh Hamed genuinely relies on me to protect his own interests ( as well as those of the State and in this connection I must tell you that for the last four or five months he has been constantly complaining to me that his allowance is too small. During last year his total income was Rs 2,25,000, of which Rs 1,81,000 was from State funds, fis 32,000 from his market property and the rest from garden rents. He should have recieved Ss 16,000 more from a tenant who unfortunately went bankrupt* His expenditure during the year was Rs 2,38,000, of which Es 25,000 was distributed as presents to his relations and to Arabs from the mainland, following the custom of the tribe who used to pay the mainland Arabs large amounts every year to ensure their support in times of trouble. Shaikh Hamed, though a man of simple tastes, is naturally improvident and extravagant. He has really no idea of the value of money. He is surrounded by relations and hangers on v/ho incessantly pester him for money. Shaikh Hamed, alone, is not capable of managing his private affairs. In this respect I help him as much as I can, but it is very difficult to control his household and other expenditure. It would be almost a whole time- job. With the income that he has it would be possible for him to live in far better style, and to save money, if his private money affairs were properly managed. The KJalifah family will naturally strongly object to any reduction in the Givil List. In my opinion this is immaterial as long as Shaikh Hamed approves. If his own salary was increased I think he might approve of a reduction. I suggest an all round reduction of 10^, excepting Shaikh Isa and Shaikh Hamed, the latter to recieve an additional Ss 500 per month. The reduction would include all allowances and salaries. This would effect a total saving to the State of about i?s 30,000 per annum. Another system would be to cut or reduce certain salaries.• 4 , This method would be more difficult for Shaikh Hamed as he would dislike picking out certain people for reductions® J?or example I ifhow that Shaikh Hamed considers the salary of Shaikh Abdulla to be excessive but he does not like to alter it if he did so Shaikh Abdulla would probably cause trouble• He has often mentioned this to me« I myself could pick out a number of persons who in my opinion do not deserve salaries, but I do not suppose tha-t Shaikh Hamed would agree with my opinion. Another suggestion is that the Civil List should be based on the revenue, a definite percentage. Another suggestion is that the whole amount should be paid to Shaikh Hamed direct and he should admiaister it, but I doubt if he would ever agree to this system. If this were done he could appropriate as much as he liked and pay what he wished to his relations. I think the people who would profit by this idea would be his/toft- servants and hangers on 0 I enclose a copy of the Civil List and allowances. It is difficult to explain who all the people are, many of them 1 have never seen, and some rarely visit Bahrain, living on the mainland. The persons drav/ing pensions are mostly ex servants of Shaikh Isa, old people who will probably not survive many years. I personally think that it is more important to check future increases than to reduce the present amount, I think Shaikh Hamed ought to guarantee that if a person dies his heir shall not draw more than a quarter the salary. At present people drawing salaries consider that the salaries pass automatically from father to son. Shaikh Hamed should promise that the present^amount shall not be increased and that any new allowances shall be made by reducing some present one. When a person dies^his salary,aaat or part ~of ,1 i-, may be allotted to a new applicant, but a certain proportion of it shall revert to the State. If my first suggestion is not adopted, and Shaikh Hamed makes an official complaint about his finances, I suggest that be should be told to employ a suitable paid secretary,Jo who is capable of running his private affairs.5 a foreigner, for managing his private affairs. After thisyiDEBTIAL . ef 1929, Political Agency, Bahrain fhe 20th July 1929• Fr«m Captain 0. G. Prior, I«A* y Political Agent, Bahrain T© ; The Secretary to the Hon*hie the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire« Sir, J. have the honour to forward in triplicate the budgef of the Bahrain State, together with a most interest - -ing review of the past years working hy Mr. Belgrave, the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. 2o There is much that I should like to say regard- -ing this budget, hut in the absence of a stenographer, it will, I fear, he impossible to do more than draw attention to a few points, This appears also to have been the practice in the past, and critical surveys have not been oalled for, 3, A disquieting feature is the fact that total revenue for the past year was less by some 26,000 rupees. This decrease would have been greater but for increased vigilance in the Customs department which enabled the amounts recovered from IskM passengers baggage to be increased from Bs 37,662 to Rs 53,990. An explanation of how this was achieved is given in the Botes on revenue collected. The collections this year have been dis- -appointing so far, and there is little doubt that the maximum of revenue at the present rates is being collected. Any i'K Any drop, uucto «m u dtox» in Ui« I ithioh would ia«Trit«tely •oour if, for iiwtiuKio, tho pife»«iit i&gt;4reot®r were replaced by seme one lenn qualified, ) would have » most eeriouu effect au tins ttxpenditwc iiaa fully kept pace with the increased revenue, una would tee very difficult to retrench. 4. It will be noticed that there io an item wention- -ed in the nntoo cm revenue called ' Manaua Baladia tobacco tax of 3 £ upon iaporta, * X have Uiuuueaert. thie tax with the Mrieer, who agrees with no that it in contrary to the troatiea which preooribe a &amp; ^ duty. It is alec objectionable in that it gives the Baladia the idea that they huve a position in tho Cuatneui which they are not entitled to and enable then to tax th«; root of the Inlands indirectly. I can find no trace of this tax ever having been sanctioned by tho -'igenoy, and so I ouggoot that it be out out of next years budget, the State will not suffer as the Advisor intends to pass thu lesa on to the Baladia { who already have mora money than thoy can spend and have deposits of over a It&amp;h.) and possibly to redxioe one or two other of their trailer taxes. 5. Regarding tho allowances of the Ruling fmily I have nuoh to say, and «a submitting a separate letter on the subjeot. As Mr. Bolgrave says, at tho present rate of progress they will soon absorb the entire revenues of the State. 6. The anount shovm for education is now 9®,000 rupees, a sum considerably greater Uum tliat usually spent by States with sinilar inoones in India. I hope that it will be found by reorganisation in the Shiah tfaqfs, ( which tore now under popular control ,5 to arrange for acre primary eduonticn being undertaken by them from funds hitherto misappropriated by the clerics who previously handledhandled then. I fchinic the Bahrain Oniroruei«iit Itavc wide a gireat alotHk« in aaxiding 8 boye nt » coat of K b 15,000/- ao fiur ITifXd «» Beyrout. I'heae fejo?# do not Appear to have baen oolootod by oxtasinntion theijr pwents arc woli ablo to pay for tholr own octucation thenoolTee, throo of tlio boyo hoSng th« oona of aoiaboro of ttoo ruling fwaily who are already in roooipt of allowanooo of P.# 6,000/- and Ro 3,600/- por moiisoh fro« the Ctate. Had m» aosi boon opont on a won qnalifiod head aaotor and a soionoo sauttr, one of the oxioting inoffioient lower middle oohoola oouid have boon aside into a really good oeoondary oohool and theoo boya educated in Bahrain. One at least has already aianaged to acquire a Baj&amp;ed '&gt;ra«rioan accent and I think thp State cmila have achieved goad reoalt with far lees expenditure by eending then to Bagndad. Hor in Boyrout, whieh uonomtratoa in^BEall h area the mat ujipieaojtnt attribute# of the levant, the place to which one would choooo to eeod a child at the a. most tBpreeeionablo period of hie life. 1. Sr. Belgrade deservoo great orodit for the transfer of the JShieh wacife froM the Ctadhie to a popular oora.iitteo. They have already aaado groat strides, and have dioooverod by personal touro that there are many Wayfo in outlying villages whose OAistonue was unknown. Kenbern of the oomittoe are aouaUy housed free in villages they visit, and the new arrangeaont has proved so satisfactory that there is little doubt that the Bunnie will soon bestir theasclvea ana take over their rfaqfo fra» the three ^adhis. «toen thio is done it should be possible to open primary sohools all over the island at no extra cost to the State. 8 * aiaottJit spent under tht head • Medical is. 1 consider, far too snail. I an told by tiiose who oiioula be in a position to know that the obot/etrioal barbaritiesgaESTIALj. f. :, ' fc'' f frem To 1929. Political Agency, Bahrain The 28th July 1929. Captain C. 6. Prior&gt; I.A. &gt; Political Agent, Bahrain. The Secretary to the Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to draw the attention of the Hon'-ble the Polltioal Keaident t© the serioua situation in Bahrain caused by the «v«r increasing oivii list, and the dangerous results that will ensue unless early an yigirous action is taJcen in the ^^ 2 # In his report on the Budget, Mr. Belgrave shows that the civil list during the past four years has risen as fellows:- 1344 Bs 4,44,000 1345 H 4,34,000 1346 B 4,62,000 1347 ^ 5,15,000 It will be seen that in the last year the civil list has grown by some 12 % and inspite Mr. Belgrade's persistent efforts an addition of over half a lakh has been inade to an already inflated civil list* The matter has come to a head now, because Hre Belgrave is again being pressed t© increase it and he has told me that his powers are exhausted and that failing definite action be obliged by the political authorities he willytomw to relax his efforts , v \7 whioh notkiag and mly isak© hi» iwaiUon «xtr«mtiy ditflouit. 3. St far th* teunt of keeping civil liat at a yeaacmabl# figure has h*tn born© by Mr. B«igrave # H« ha© oouaiatantly warnad the politioaX authoritiaa af the aituatian ami while doing hi a beat to ciieok increase a has pointad out that ha can not do aa without atrong aupport. ^ y l have on my fila a dami-official Ho« 6E7/S of 6th Daoambar 1^^6 in which Captain Hornar forwarded to ay predeoaaaor a liat showing the allowanoas of the Muscat ruling family and saying that ' this may help Belgrava in determining questions of allowances to the al Khalifa family** It is well known that Hr. Belgrave^ chief trouble lies in restricting the Shaikh*a generosity to himself and his sons, and I subnit that it is not for Mr. Belgrave, the Shaikh's paid servant to determine what his master may or may not take from the State funds, ana in suggesting that he should do so we have shirked our responsibility rudd have attempted to saddle Kr. Belgrave with an unpleasant duty which should oe borne f by broader shotilders which may well make his position untenable• 4 0 we can not divest ourselves of this re ponai- ability, for Shaikh Karaad loft to himself would rapidly eat up the entire revenues and the work of the past six years would be undone at onoe« fhe Bahrain allowances generous in the first place and only fixed as a temporary measure at 4.44,000 have now risen to 5,18,000, and, if other payments to the ruling family be considered, nearly, 5,50,000, These other amounts are an elusive total and include His Kxcellency^percentage on sheep and goats landed at Bahrain, free education at Beirut for three sons of the ruling family at a cost of nearly 5,000, additional sums for entertainment of visiting ShaikhsBbaifebB wnri other item wlilch m«&amp; tretiaed d«tectiv« to dlooover. SM» 5# lakiui la roughly thret- tiaes that paid by the JuuaoHt Sit»t« to tte ruling faaiiy &lt;UJu i6 aajre tton inaJLt' the Uadgetted inuocio lor the ye&amp;r, wd the time has ooraa to tnke action. B. His i&amp;o«lAenuy iifec ^uet ajxiroaoheu Mt. iteigjp&amp;ife for an inoreaae of hie &amp;i.iowui&lt;t&gt;«ti. yoa* Me toWi inuwut: w&amp;a a,as,000 of idtioh the tmotmt from the State wao 1 ,81 ,000, 32,000 frow b.Xu market property and the rent i'i'ora garden rente. Ke eheuXci have reoeived another 16,000 hat a tenant nent bankrupt, his expenditure during the year wau 54,30,000 of which J j 5,000 was distributed aa presents. Kr. Beiifrave pointed out to Bio i&amp;oolienoy that his inoaae frwa lialirain was ruugiUy the ssac that of the Viowroy's, hut His liatocileney who saw in- -oongruity in their relative pooitioas imediatcly said that tlie Vioeroy aliaoet certain^ had land in hnglitna. 1 quote this to show how little he roalXui.o what a drain he is on the State, and how little he does in return for Mo pay. Ho might perhaps he told tliat exoepting hio sons mmdaugnters, only six of King Oeorgo's relations are supported by the Utato. 6. Au regards the rest of the ai Khalifa the Situation is infiititely worss, I find that this horde of idle noubha receive 20,07^/per »«noo34 froa the atate. Shis does not inolude the suae paid to certain of wiea to aot as aagistrates, for the al Khalifa oansider that they should be handswely eoapensatod to give up the sloth that is their birthright, and will do nothing for the atate unless suitably remunerated. In Ma letter C £1 dated the aiot of January ISte? ay prsduoecsor iMpraed jau that all the members of the al Khalifa uonaidcred ta^asolvos entitled b? virtue of their birth to a share in tho loot of Bahrain.X wieh to point out* however, tlmt I a» not diaputlotf with them the aoat of the ex. Taut mrtiiy bones and the hoofs for thoy mro already the owners of praotiouily all the agrioultural lands in the ialando which they have looted trm the Bahrainao and from whioh they wring the last #» penny, and in addition to this they own very valuable bamar property and nsorlceto. la view of this, if we allow thcia to eat ap in addition 80 of the gross revenue, we are in siy opinion failing in our duty. Mr. Belgrave inforaa ae that out of the oivil list of 108 persons, aaay do not live in Bahrain and are perttonally unknown to him, and merely come here to receive their doles and retire. The prinoipal reoipionte are of oourtte Shaikh Haaad, *y«ary lfi,SOO/« and Shaikh Abdullah, 6,000/- and Bhalkh Muhamad, 3,600/- per maam.and ShaiJ^n Salman who draws 1,400/* por menuem. X therefore awOco three euggeatione. 7. An all roum reduction of ten per cent except for ahaiah Xea and ahaikh Hamad, ehose allowance of 1®,bOV/- ia eoKewluit email in comparison to the gthors. 6. To reduce certain ealarie». This would be difficult ae the first to be reduced would undoubtedly be Shaikh Abdullah's as Mo 6,000/- is out of all pro- -portien to the others. Shaikh mbdullah is undoubtedly the ablest man in the State, an action slight un- -settle him bow that he appears to have turned over a new loaf would not in my opinion be worth the trouble involved. 9. To leave the salaries as they are sad to cut out the Burner move allowances of 6,000/- to Uhaikh Hsoad, 8,000/- to Shaikh huhacuad and to «hai,kh ^sa^'^'' ' Shaikh Hsmad's pay might then be brought upto 1»,000/-. 10. The ®ain thing however is to get the Shaikh toto ri.«p«0t the undertaking he MWmi tiaw giTt „ aad as frequently 4i 8 re«arded viz. thut he should a not make^tnorCHBe without t^inc the advice of the Political Agent. He ahould aloe agree that in the event of the death of an al Khalifa hie nuns ohould only receive a quarter or half hie allewancee, and that for tne present that no further inoreaeee should be given without a a reduction elsewhere to pay for it. and alec, preferably W proclamation, announce that the State will not be bound indefinitely to pay aUe«aB««» to ncmberu oi the al Khalifa who do not work for it. At present the al Khalifa are breeding like rabbito and the unfortunate State hae to support a rapidly increasing brood of utterly idle and worthless Shaikhlings. U. 1 would have taken action before but I feel it is better that 1 should first refer the matter to the Political Resident as. so far as I ^ awaro. the Kosidsnoy have given no clear ana authoritative orders on the .ubioct. and it is obvious that I should have the full support of tho Bosidont if any action of aine is to be •ucoessful. I consider the situation is serious. last yoar the revenue showed a slight shrinkage, ana this year has opened badly, and it also appears certain that the polling season will not live up to tho hopes raised by the Khanchia; against this wo have an oxtra half lakh of unproductive oxpendituro to meet. 12. I should be glad if orders could be conveyed 0 me before ny departure to Karachi as it will be more productive of result though less pleasant for ae to dis- .. CU88 the matter with I goo Z iiave tb.® honour to Sir, Your Moct obedient serr&amp;nt Political Agent, BahrainTelegraja ( In Code ) „ From - Political Agent, Bahrain. - Resident, Bush.irtt 0 Uo', 9&lt;o2 • Dated 9th August 1929• P.1 My 9o-G and 94-0. Figures for first month and revenue 1346 76,207, 1347 70,113, 1348 65,071. Second nonth/ figures incomplete but will be even more unfavourable so situation is serious. Request telegraphic authority to suggest to Shaikh action outlined in paras seven and nine my 94-G, leaving decision to him. RrfTranslation of letter dated 13th 'Vbi I 1348 - 18th August iM&amp;xx 1929 from H.E. Shaikh Hamad hin Isa al Khalifah G.S.I., Dj. Ruler of Batirain to the Political Agent, Bahrai After Compliments, I^o acknowledge the receipt of jour letter No. 991 datea 17th August 1829 ( 12th Rahi II 1348 ) the contents of which are noted. I am very thankful to I.E. for your kind advice by which you try to mak- my Government follow the best. I have thought over this and I hopw I will be able to make reduction in expenditure between Rs 14000/ and Rs 15000/- in the year. I have no mind at all to increase any pay unless we are able to have a large income from several other sources such as Kerosine oil etc. Thus if we then want to give new pay to any or give a normal increment such action will not cause harm to our 1 -4 ViUli*' r v U • Hoping Qoa wixl luaa us to tne best.Uo. 320-^ of 1929 « British Kesidency and Consulate-(xeneral, iiushire, 6th August 1929. ? 0 The Political Agent, Bahrain, , I 'r . I-' Memorandiqm , Reference your letter ^lo* 94-G#, dated the 28th ■ July 1929• 1 agree that the Al Khalifa allowances, which aznourt? to half the total revenues of the State / have now reached a figure which should not he exceeded. At the same time the State is in a prosperous i condition with income far exceeding expenditure and leav ing a handsome surplus each year for investment. From my experience of other Arab States of similar type ranging from LaJ^ej to Kuwait^it is clear that the members of the ruling family regard themselves as equally entitled with the actual ruler^to share the booty : originally earned by the exertions of their common pro- ■ genitor. It is quarrels over the sharing of this booty, as they regard the State revenues, that lead to the regrettable series of fratricides which have always marked the history of these small States. It is a matter of sincere congratulation that Bahrain, under British guidance, appears to have passed this state of development, and that its rulers are realising that ■' 1 Ml they owe a duty to their subjects as well as to the members of their family. At the sarae time the idea that the revenues of the Ithe State are the property of the family does not appear^/ wholly to have vanished, and we have to realise this mentality, it is for us to guide the Kuler 'by advice and not to order him. We do not want to appear in the lime light. Luckily Shaikh Hamad though wealc^is susceptihle to the advice of the Political Agent which, he knows, has the support of the Political Resident. I authorise you to explain the position to which his heedless generosity must ultimately lead; to remind him of his promises to Major Daly regarding additions to the allow ance; and to say that 1 have noticed the increase in the civil list with serious misgivings. His allowances and those of his family are already fixed on a very generous scale, and he and the Al Khalifa, who in addition draw considerable revenue from private gardens and town property, must contrive to live on their present income. A ruler has duties to his subjects, as 1 am sure that His Excellency who has visited London must realise. His Majesty King George is particularly careful to live within his income and none of his family draw any inc&amp;mes except a fixed yearly stfun granted to them 'by Parliament. This sum ifi not susceptible of increase except with the consent of Parliament and such consent has never been asked for by His Majesty the King. In the same way the Al Khalifa must act. I trust that Shaikh Hamad will now make a start by reducing instead of increasing expenditure. In the first place he should withdraw the annual grant made to him self and various members of his family for the summer move, which should be paid for out of the monthly allowance he and his brothers receive. At the same time I must ask His Excellency to make no fresh allowances to the Al Khalifa^unless he can make some corresponding reduction in the total grant to the * familyyr - 3 - family either owing to a death or curtailment of the allow ance of another member. You should tell the Shaikh that^it is not my wish to interfere in the affairs of the State, but when i see a dear friend heading for ruin, jbtxsi^ it is my duty to warn him and to take measures to avert the catastrophe, and i feel sure that he will accept this advice. Lieut.-Colonel, if |i 1 ' -jl I Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (LCUC 5 11 . 1 i t siHo. 320-S, of 1929• British Kcsidcnoy and Consulate-General, Bushire, 6th August 1929. f3 m The Political Agent, Bahrain. j 1 ■ MemoranduBU Reference your letter no. 94-G,, dated the 28th July 1929. I agree that the Ai Khalifa allowances, which amoui to half the total revenues of the ytate / have now reached a figure which should not be exceeded. At the same time the State is in a prosperous condition with income far exceeding expenditure and leav ing a handsome surplus each year for investment. From my experience of other Arab States of similar type ranging from La^ej to Kuwait it is clear that the members of the ruling family regard themselves as equally entitled with the actual ruler to share the booty originally earned by the exertions of their common pro genitor. It is quarrels over the sharing of this booty, as they regard the State revenues, that lead to the regrettable series of fratricides which have always marked the history of these small States. It is a matter of sincere congratulation that Bahrain, under British guidance, appears to have passed this state of development, and that its rulers are realising that they owe a duty to their subjects as well as to the meinbers of their family. At the saiae time the idea that the revenues of the- 1' I the Btate are the property of the family does not appear wholly to have vanished, and ^e have to realise this mentality# It is for us to guide the Kuler by advice and not to order him. We do not want to appear in t.he lime light. Luckily Bhaikh Hamad though weak .is susceptible / f to the advice of the Political Agent vshich, he knows, lias the support of the Political Hesident. ; 1 authorise you to explain the position to which his heedless generosity must ultimately lead; to remind him of 1 his promises to Kajor Daly regarding additions to the allow ance; and to say that I have noticed the increase in the civil list with serious misgivings. Mis allowances and those of his family are already fixed on a very generous scale, and he and the Al IChalifa, who in addition draw considerable revenue from private gardens and town property, must contrive to live on their present income. A ruler has duties to his subjects, as I am sure that His Excellency who has visited London must realise. His Majesty King George is particularly careful to live within his income and none of his family draw any incomes except a fixed yearly sum granted to them by Parliament. This num. i£ not susceptible of increase except with the consent of Parliament and such consent has never been asked for by His Xlajesty the King. In the same way the Al Khalifa must act. I timst that Bhaikh Hamad will now. make a start by reducing instead of increasing expenditure. In the first place he should withdraw the annual grant made to him self and various members of his family for the summer move, which should be x^aid for out of the monthly allowance he and his brothers receive. At the same time I must ask His Kxcellency to make no fresh allowances to the Al Khalifa unless he can make some corresponding reduction in the total grant to the family Mi«*» 3 family either owing to a death or curtailment of the allow ance of another member. You should tell the Shaikh that it is not my wish to interfere in the affaire of the State, but when I see a dear friend heading for ruin, it is my duty to warn him and to take measures to avert the catastrophe, and i feel j sure that he will accept this advice. I 1 11 I I I « SI)/ C.C..T. 'Barrett, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. IllHO British Residency Bu Prom To The Hon'ble Lieut- Pol it ica The Foreign Secret in the Porei B Sir, I have the honour Adviser to the Bahrain, No. l60, dated 29th Muharam 4th Safar 1348(11 2. The finance of th -ed 'by a lac of rupees it will 'be in a positi the electric power sch 1348. 3. The State andits agesxx of education as iture to Hs 90,000, an American University at that no school nearer i equally good standing ' American University ha Middle '^ast, and it is a success. The Ixpenditure 0 largely on account of i ! Isa,and to the reston Khaiifah hitherto in e: (E (fvvwv'4 Hams-d realised that he his family indefinitel, that the time has now IHo # 33i-s # of 1929. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire,8th August 1929 Prom The Hon'ble Lieut-Coi. G,C,J.Barrett,C.S,I., CM.B,, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department,Simla, Bahrain State ^udget. */% Sir. ^ * 1 I have the honour to forward a copy of a letter from the Adviser to the Bahrain State to the Political Agent at Bahrain, giving cover to the State • No. 160, dated 29th Muharam Ij^S (7-7-29 ) : Budget for the Arabic year 4th Safar 1348(117-29 ) ' :: 13^8. 2. The finance of the State , whose Gash Balance has increas -ed 'by a lac of rupees tp Si lacs, are very satisfactory, and it will 'be in a position easily to meet the heavy claim for the electric power scheme which will fall on it in the year 134-8. 3. The State andits inhabitants have awakened to the advant- ageexx of education as is testified by the increase of expend iture to Ks 90,000, and by the sending of eight pupils; to the American University at Beirut as State scholars. It is a pity that no school nearer home, under British supervision, of equally good standing was known to the State authorities. The American University has a great reputation through out the Middle '^ast, and it is hoped that the experiment will turn out a success. The Ixpenditure on the Civil List has again increased largely on account of an additional grant to the old shaikh^ ^sa.and to the restoration of the allowance to certian Ai Khaiifah hitherto in exile. it is certianly time that Shaikh Hamad realised that he^continue increasing the allowance to his family indefinitely. Mr. Belegrave is impressing upon his that the time has now come when no grant should be rnadeto amember Ox the Ai ik halifah without a corresponding saving being shown either owing to the death or curtailment of the allow ance of another member of the family. At the same time it is satisfactory that the State is in a position to bear this heavy drain and still show a surplus. In other less favoured States in the Gulf it is the resentment of relatives at what they Egard as an inequitable division of the booty, owing to the Ruler's appropriation of the major share 01 the revenues, that leads to the regrettable cases of fratricide, which are a future of Gulf history. 4. It is hoped that the State will now turn its attention to the medical and sanitary problems whic, in spite of the excell ent work of and great improvements wrought by the Hunicpalitiee still remain to be tackled. 5. Mr. Bel egrave deserves great creoit for a suacessful years work. i I I have the honour to be Sir, Yo'ur Most obedient servant. Sd/ C. C A J, Barrett, Lt.^Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Copy forwarded to the Political Agent at ^ahrain for information. Attested; Sd/ J.Croning for Secretary to the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf Bus ire, 8th August 1929* eNo. SSl -S, Of 1929. British Resldenoy and Consulate-Qsneral, BuBtiire, 8th August 1929. From TO The Hon'ble Lleut-Col. 0.0.J,Barrett, 0.3.1., O .I .S., Political Kesldent in the Persian Gulf. The Foreign Secretary to the Ooverniaent of India In the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Bahrain State Budget 1 ; sir, ■ I have the honour to forward a copy of a letter from the Adviser to the Bahrain State to the Political Agent at Bahrain, m 29th Huharam 1348 ( 7-7-29i. fO, dated 41 . h ,^ far l3 ^ cover to s the 5tate Budget for the Armtoi* year 1348# 2. TU© finances of the State, whose Sash Balance haa Increased hy a lac of rupees to &amp;i lacs, are very satlsfastary, and it will foe in a position easily to meet the heavy cslaim for the electric power scheme which will tall on it in the year 1348* 3« The State and its inhabitants have awakened to the advantages of education as is testified hy the increase of expenditure to m* 90 f 000, and hy the sending of eight pupils to the American University at Beirut as State scholars. It is a pity that no school nearer home, under British supervision, of equally good standing was known to the State authorities. The American University has a great reputation throughout the Middle last, and it is hoped that the experiment will turn out a success. TheThe expenditure on the Civil List has aga increaaedj largely on aoeouint oi' an additional grant to Urn old Stoikh Sir Isa t and to the restoration of the allowfoicea to certain Al imlifa. hitlierto In exile. It in certainly time that shulkh Hamad rcalleed that he cannot continue increasing the alio usance b to hio fastily indefinitely. iir Belgrave i» lupreaoing upon tda that the time haa not? come v&amp;en no gra »t should be made to a member of the Al Khalifa without a corresponding aav* 1 ing being shown either owing to the death or curtail ment of the allowance of another member of the family• At the sari© tirie it is satisfactory that the State la in a position to bear this heavy drain and still Rhow a surplus. In other less favoured states in the Gulf it 1© the resentment of relatives at what they regard as an inequitable division of the booty* owing to the tier's appropriation of the major share of the revenues, that l^iuls to the regrettable cases of fratricide 9 vshich are a feature of Gulf history. 4. It is hoped tluit the State will now turn its attention to the medical and sanitary problems itiich, in apite of the excellent work of mid great iaprove rrents wrought by the liunicipalities, still remain to be tackled. 5* Mr Belgrave deserves great credit for a successful year* j work. I have the honour to be» Sir, Your nost obedient servant f SD/ C. C. J. Barrett, 1 iti cal :es ident in the ersian Gulf. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent at .Bahrain for information. Attested: for Secretary to the j^litical Kesident in the Persian Gulf. Bush ire, 8th August 1929, v CNo. S31-S, of 1929. British K«8la«H0y and ^onaulats-ieneral, BU8hir@| 3th August 1929* The Hon* ble Li®ut»Col. Q.C.J.Barratt, 0.3.1., political hwidmt 1b %lw persian gulf# The Foreign S©oretarj to the 0#yarnM6Bt of India in the Foreign and Folitioal Department, Simla. Bahrain 3tata Budget , sir. ^ fV' I have the honour t® forward a copy of a latter from the Atviser to the Bahrain State to the lolitioal Agent at Bahrain, t i 7-29). 60 &gt; Zm Jg48 ( 7-y-^ T 1 glviaj , OOVQr to 4th .:alar IMBJ11-7-39), . givxng oo*«i to y J0 Budget for tha Arable year IMS. 2. The finances of the State, whose Baah Balance has inereased by a lac of rupees to 8t lacs, are very aatisfaotory, and it will he in a position easily to meet the heavy elalm for the eleotrio power scheme which will fall on it in the year i54de 5* The State and its inhabitants have awakened to the advantages of education as Is testified hy the increase of expenditure to fa, 90,000, and hy the sending of eight pupils to the American tlniversity at Beirut as State scholars. It is a pity that no school nearer home, under British supervision, of equally good standing was known to the State authorities. Tha American University has a great reputation throughout the Middle ;ast, and it is hoped that the experiment will turn out a suocess. Thele .no-c of 1929 Office of the Pol itleal Agent,Bahrain. Bated Karachi 19th 8epetiaber,1929. Il Irom Captain C. G. Prior, Political Agent, Bahrain, 9 To C- . B 7 fto Adviser, ^ / ^ : ;• ' i Bahrain Government, Bahrain* Sir, \ I have the honour to forward a copy of letter Bo.331^. from the Hon*ble the Political Eeaident to the Goverment of Xndia t for your information, and to draw your attention to the remark in the oonoluding paragraph with which I heartily concur• I also enclose a letter Bo # i09-0 dated the 19th Sept ember whicVvX have eent to the fion f ble the Political Meeid- ent. Itt the statement regarding 'Al Khalifah hitherto in ex«iie N correct in the letter fio .33l /S qpioted above f I have the honour to he Sir, Xour most obedient servant. osl Political Agent,Bahrain, m 1lo{ The Agencyt Bahrain. Persian Gulf. I4th April 1930 f&gt;ha.iich Hamad is getting increasingly pressing for more money, and I am having some difficulty in coping with his demands -t the moment. We were discussing the budget, and I was pointing out what an enormous amount the al .Khalifa costthe State, when his eye fell on the item of Court fees. He than said that % in your duy, either the Joint Court fees, or the Bahrain court fees, I could not make out which, were paid over to him in cash, and th t you allowed him to apppropraiite them for him self. From what I know ol your regime, I should think this very unlikely, but I would be glad to hear if there is anything in what he says. Further, he is constantly saying th t at some time when he went to India, the Customs paid him 56,000/- on 1 just a chit from Father 1 and why, when the S'ltte is supposed to be so porsperoua cant he e|gt omney like that now. Did he ever mention this ? Do you happen to Know wh ;t his allowance was say, hust after the War, or about how much he got away with. ' ; '■ / / ■' : ■ ' ,, ' i. 7,liat ?/as his pay first fixed at, and when ? I cant find any thing to show what it was. Ee now gets I2,S00/- besides a considerable mount of squeeze, andsayi he cant possibly make ends meet on it J So Jotty to trouble you ' Tours sincerely . £ AConfidential. The Agency, Bahrain. .0 No. C/ 27th April 1930. Shaikh Hamad has again raised the question of his finances, and though the difficulty has been tided over for A I am certain that there is more unpleasantness in the offing, Before going into it I would like to refer to paragraph 3 of your despatch No» 43-S dated the I3th February which 'bears on the matter. 2. This paragraph reads rather as though Col. Barrett had been an enthusiastic supporter or x I slkx. rtrench- ment in this direction# As a matter of fact, as Hussell will tell you, he disbelived my forecast of a bad year, and it was only after two months pressure that he agreed to force a reduction on the Shaikh, ( in this connection please see my 94 C dated the S8th July 1929 ) in fact when he came here on the I4th of May he was actually contemplating giving the Shaikh an increase that he was clamouring for. 3. Then again in para 3 if his despatch No. 33I-S dated the 8th August 1929 to the Government of India, he stated that the increases in the Civil List were principally due to an increase in Shaikh Isa's grant. This,as I point- out in my I09-C dated the I9th September 1929, was not the case. Nor could either Belgrave or I understand who the al Khalifa in exilereferred to were. 4. My forecast of a bad year has been fully borne t out. I had anticipated a possible drop of halfi a lakh, but the slupp in the Pearl market has made matters worse, and we shall be a lakh down on last year for certain, and next year Belgrave will be obliged to budget for an amount not more than this years taseipts. An increase in taxation would cause great discontent as dozens of merchants are going bankrupt every month. My subsequent remarks regard-Page 2. ing Shaikh Hamad should be read in the light of this para graph. 5» For the last twommonths Shaikh Hamad has been bothering Belgrave about his money affairs, and making attempt after attempt to extract more money from him. After an interview in which Shaikh Hamad became somewhat heated, Belgrave informed me that the Shaikh was 6000/- overdrawn and that he would be glad if I would take up the J matter. I went out to Sakhir, and found him in a very jfc± 1 ■ tiresome mood. He trotted out all his stock arguments 1 When he v/ent to India, the customs ^aid him 56,000/- sim- ply on Father^ chit, without any questions asked, and why could he get nothing like that now ' ' In Major Daly's time he was allowed to pocket all cou% fees, and they should be paid to him now 11 and so on. I very much doubt ■ the truth of thatlast contention and have written to Daly to see What the practice really was and what his pay at tha' time was. •&gt; §i 6. He told me of the great demands on his purse, and I told him that he was so generous that if his pay was doubled he would still be hard up. I also brought to his notice some of the more glaring instances where he wasted money recently, quoting the gift of his fish market to Daij, a property which I believe brings in about 3oo/- a month. An argument that he never tired of was that you had said he should have more money and 1 why did not the Adviser produce it. 1 I had been warned that he would say this and consequently had brought along a copy of the letter in which I told him that you had indded said sns that you considered he should have a high^e polrportion of of the Civil List, but that the 5 lakhs could not in any circumstances be exceeded. 7. I then suggested that he should take the amount which have been cut from certain persons, but on hearing I3. that it only amounted to a few hundred rupees a month he took no notice of the suggestion# I then produced as a final suggestion, the proposal that he should lease a plot of land or a promontory that he has in Muharraq to the Government for the QustDhtine, at a rate of 400/- p.m. to 'be paid in this case a year in advance as he was so hard up# This idea he approved of, but the difficulty lies in the fact that it is inhabited by some of Shailch Isa's ser vants, and that although the State will give them lodging or ground elsewhere, he fears his father's displeasure. t However he finally agreed to accept the sum and any cutings that might become available. 8. Unfortunately we now discover that the Civil List will be 5,^07,000 this year in spite of the deductions^ some of which will not really take effect ttll next year, a and so there will be nothing available from cuttings at the moment. The Shaikh has, however accepted the 4800/- and I have written to him urging him try and keep his expendi ture within limits, pointing out that it will be a very bad year for the State, and that nexjr year it might be necessary to reduce the al Khalifa allowances even further if matters did not improve. I also said that 3300/- per annum would be available from cuttings, and that he could take this and still keep below the five lakhs, and add to it any further sume that be available by th deaths or otherwise of mem bers of the family. Of course, the whole trouble is that so long as Shaikh Isa remains with us, we shall be never able to give him a really solid incresase and I feel that we should cling to t,his five lakh limit as to the horns of altar. Once we exceed it, even by a little, we shall be faced by even more insistent demands for more money than at present. The quarantine site is not worth 400/- a month, but it seemed impossible to find any other source of income without addling it to the Civil List, am the sitePage 4. is the most suitable for our purpose as it has deep water up to the edge of it. 9* That is where the matter rests at the moment, 'but I have no doubt that hw will soon be clamouring for more. Yours sincerelyHis Britannic Ma Gamp Birjand, da Your Derni-Officic April, 1930 ^ Joint Court fees share 'being credited to Staj Bahrain Court fe^ in fact to stop peculataiiH,w&lt; were affixed to cases and c credit of the State• Just 'before I re on a visit to Bombay. He w Father. At that time the e Isa on al Khalifah. The Sh ^his was of course stopped Before the new regime I thi from his rather. At one time I we with him to arrive at what legitimate expenditure, ap? which he had to scatter abc ~ Hs 2000, but he was being i entourage, particularly a ; * his special confidant - Muj called, 12,50u is of cour frittered away because he to stop everybody begging compete with Sin Saud, not keep himself on the ^thron and supporters ,whereas Ha get up against us by fooli of Ham&amp;d he is completely and would be equally hard allowance were raised to sIfi, His Britannic Majesty's Consulate, Sistan and H/ Gamp Birjand, da' Your Demi-official letter No 45 of tlie 14th April, 1930.. Joint Court fees were divided - the Bahrain share heing credited to State funds. Bahrain Court fees were credited to State funds- in fact to stop peculataDcwe had Court fee stamps which were affixed to cases and cash paid into the Bank for credit of the State, Just before I reached Bahrain Shaik Hamad went on a visit to Bombay. He was provided with funds 'by his Father. At that time the entire revenue was spent 'by Shaik Isa on al Khalifah. The Shaik drew direct on the Customs. This was of course stopped when Shaik Isa was deposed. Before the new regime I think Hamad got about 40U(J-5000 Rs from his rather. with him to arrive at ?i /hat sum he really needed. His legitimate expenditure, apart from the usual , Bakshish f which he had to scatter ahout, did not exceed ahout Es 1500- Rs 2000, hut he was 'being considerably swindled by his h r^(p^4x^-x&gt; entourage, particularly a ^x'GimoniQue individual who was. his special confidant - Muhommed Bin Jabarul believe he was called. ^12,500 is of course a stupendous sum, and is frittered away because he has not the strength of character to stop everybody begging from him. He imagines he has to compete with Bin Saud^not realising that the latter has to keep himself on the ^throne' by such bribery of his subjects and supporters ,whereas Hamad is quite safe if he does not get up against us by foolish belaviour. From what I know of Hamad he is completely incapable of managing his finances and would be equally hard up / after a year or two, if his allowance ..ere raised to a lakh. Whatever he has j al-Khalifa At one time I went into all Hamid's expenses-a- and. Ills hangers-on will get out of hin^and it is pure waste or money to allow him more, What is really required is for Government to determine the total 'Privy Purse 1 * for the whole family and leave him to make the 'best division of it that he can. If this 'be not done the ever increasing family will 'become a seriojis menace as none of the younger members will ever do a jo6 of work as long as they can continue to live out of State Funds. A complete list of those drawing allowances and the proportion of the State revenues spent in this way ought to convince G-overnment that some limit should he fixed, and the degree of relationship to the ruling Shaik ought to determine claims. reasons why Government had to intervene and place him on the throne was that the revenue of the State was 'being squandered and not devoted to the interests of the people, and he would 'be unwise to run the risk of 'being found wanting in the same way. It might he good to hint to Hamatd that one of the Yours Sincerely, To Captain C.G-.Prior, Political Agent, Bahrain.p.A. . . Bahrain . The Jf.H. distated this d.o. letter the office copy of which is shown as rt signed', but he inadvertently forgot to sign this before leaving /otL tour. i now forward it on to save delay. [Secretary; Bushire, 6th May 1930.r tl\ Confiaential . Mn • P / i&lt;0 . \j j • Political Agencj, Baiirein., the 15tii February 1931 Prom, Captain C.G.Prior.jI.A., Political Agent, Bahrein. To, Tlis Hon T ble Lt Col.H.V.Biscoe., i.A., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Buskire. Sir, I have the konour to say that His Excellency Shaikh llaiaai recently sent a letter to Mr.Belgrave,his Financial Aaviser,requesting kirn to meet some of his debts amounting to over lis.21,000/-. His Excellency already receives some Rs.lS,000/- per mensem and since his private income,apart from allowances,has recently been increased by his leasing the site of the new uarantine station to the Government, .Jr. Bel grave was most disturbed at the sudden arain on the State finances and went ana saw His Excellency who had asked him to discuss matters with him. 2. in discussing matters with Shaikh Hamad he found that the situation with regard to the debt was not as serious as he had first suspected and that tne whole of the Ks.21,000/- was not payable immediately. A considerable portion of this debt is aue to the cost of building the new mosnue at Sakhir,in which,His Excellency naively said,he had hoped local merchants would2. would assist iiim and that ke had found that they were unable to do so. Vihy the sorelj tried, businessmen of Bahrein should contribute to a mosque which could only benefit him alone 1 cannot iraaginepbut the instance is typical of His excellency T s tangled ideas of finance. 3. Shaikh Hamad tola I.ir.Belgrade that when you ere here he had heard that you wished him to make economies m the State budget. He alluded,of course, to your conversation with him in jhich he eluded this . awkward topic with considerable agility, ilis Excellency | : t considered it would be better to forestall any possible interference from the Political Authorities by reducing expenditure himself,but it was soon clear that his plan by no means coincided with your views. His Excellency considered that the Al Khalifa allow ances should,of course,remain at their present figure having been reduced from Es.5,15,000/- to Rs.5,00,000/- [ last year but that economies should be effected in the rest of the expenditure,instancing roads as an example. In other words,on the only portions of the State budget. ^ l ■ Mr.Belgrave pointed out to him that no work had been done on the roads for two months,that he had already effected considerable economies and that the expenditure | for the Al Khalifa had been some as .-/9/- in the Rupee of the last 8 months revenues and that by the end of the year this disproportion would be much greater. 4. His excellency then suggested that a tax on tobacco should be imposed - an import duty,in fact - ana further suggested that auties should be imposed on coffee,on tea and on gramophones. Mr.Belgrave pointed out that the Customs duties were fixed by Treaty at 5^ and that in view of the low rates collected at Lubai I it would be prejudicial to Bahrein interests to raise any duties here. This impressed him,but His Excellency tii enin then suggested one or two other sources of revenue none oi tnen calculated to. toucli the pockets of kimself or tue rest ol tne a X ICkalifa,which ..ir.Belgrave countered by citing the almost universal financial difficulties of the Bahrein public• 5. if any attempt is to be made to balance the Gtate buaget during the ensuing financial year without drawing further on the reserves in India,which I consider unwise,it will be absolutely necessary that the allowances of the Al Khalifa should be reduced by at least 10^ commencing from the month of Muharram (May) - the beginning of the Arab year - or preferably earlier still. The Al Khalifa have heard rumours of a 20,* reduction at Muscat and are expecting 4 a reduction in Bahrein,and since commodity prices have fallen heavily they would even then be actually better off than they were a year ago. 6. I surest tkat in making this reduction tue allowances granted for specific duties such as the small allowances granted to the Heir Apparent and t.o of his brothers for judicial work should not be touched,as it is possible lis excellency contemplates an all round reduction in the salaries of State servant and it would be well to mark the uifference e£ those who draw salaries for work done and the i J l Khalifa who receive theirs for merely existing. 7. I also suggest that in the new financial year His Excellency should be asked to give up the practice of granting loans of large sums to prominent persons who happen to be in need of money. These loans runjs up to as much as Rs.15,000/-,without interest,of course and since usually no security is taken the money can only be recovered,if at all,with great difficulty. In mostnt 4. most cases there is not the slightest justification for the loans and 1 need onlj quote the cases of two ersian ohaikiis who have received large loans (one of whom is now aeaa and the otlier who nas no intention of paying') to show how little claim some of the debtors have on tiie otate iunds* 1 would further suggest tnat me opportunity should be taken of making a clean sweep o~ i\s•25,000/- odd ol allowances granted to various members of the Al Khalifa during the year, for Ids and the purchase of dates end their summer moves. 8. If you concur in my view that reduction in the Bahrein Civil List is urgently required I would be glad if you would give me some message or letter for Shaikh Hamad suggesting this,provided that he has not made some adjustment in the meantime of his own volition It would be convenient if this cornmunication could be so worded as to appear a continuation of your abortive conversation with him at the Agency,for he may otherwise feel that the Adviser has abused his confidence on being asked to arrange a temporary loan for him. I have the honour to be Sir, Your .lost Obedient Servant, Political Agent, Bahrein.#. c ^ UEQ/lVE &gt; V \\ / | -i r\ ; v 1 j ; ' h Y { 6i ^ 1 ' British Hesideney , a, •' , ' Bushire, 1st March 1931 • &amp; C^/jiA'/nyu^ vfith reference to your memorandum No. dated the February 1931. X forward you herewith a letter from colonel Biscoe to Shaikh Hamad on the subject of the State finances for delivery to him or not as you see fit. Colonel Biscoe adds that, as he has heard that some members of the A1 Khalifa only receive allowances of a few Rupees, the out proposed should 'be somewhat modified in their cases, so as not to cause undue distress. Captain G.G. Prior, Political Agent, . B A H H A I N. TlM'tl^ • ■ . 3 . •Q3 1 - - /// / NO. Ifio of 1931. / British residency iCsnsulate-General, Bushire, the February 1931. To His Bxcellenc^f Shaikh Hamad bin Is a Al-Khalifah ]^eputy Ruler of Bahrain# B a h r a i n f . After compliments, I trust Your Excellency is enjoying good health and that all is well with you. X greatly enjoyed my visit to Bahrain and the pleasure of seeing Your Excellency again. Unfortunately the visit Wf?s short and 1 had not time to discuss fully with Your excellency certain matters that were in a\y mind and I am therefore writing this letter and sending it through Captain Prior. Your Excellency will remember that in the course cf our conversation I impressed upon you the necessity for strict econon^y in the administration of the state at the present time* As in almost every country in the world Bahrain is going through an economic crisis and I under stand that during this year the expenditure has exceeded the income. Unless drastic measures •••measures are taken to reduce the expenditure the same thin^ will occur next year* It is clear that this state of affairs cannot continue indefinitely and that unless prompt steps are taken the present excellent order and administration will certainly suffer* It is not only in Bahrain that the necessity for the reducti of the expenditure has arisen. States all over trie world, great and small, and other states in the Persian Gulf are also 'being compelled to revise their budgets* -/hen 2 was in Bahrain a year^o 1 expressed the view to Your Excellency that the allowances of the ruling family should in no circumstances exceed five lakhs per annum* this statement was made on the assumption that the normal revenue of the state would be about 10 laichs, and the allowances would therefore amount to 50/* of the income# ?his is a very large amount, higher than in any other country, I believe*. If however the revenue falls, then the allowances of the ruling family will considerably exceed 50/*, and in such circumstances it seems to me essential that they should be reduced. I would therefore suggest that a reduction of 10$ should be made in all the allowances of the ♦* *•the Al-Khalifeh, commencing from the month of -vluharram, and would point out that since the prices of all food-stuffs have fallen heavily, they would actually be no worse off than they were before. Allowances granted for specific duties might be left untouched# I also understand that Your Excellency, with your well-known generos ity of heart, sometimes makes large loans to prominent persons who happen to be in need of money. However laudable and praiseworthy such actions may be in normal times, at a crisis such as the present, 1 feel that Your Excellency should, as far as possible, refrain from such generosity, and, further, that the special allowances granted to various members of the Al^Knalifeh during the year for 'Id# and the purchase of dates and their summer moves might suitably be discontinued. These measures will, I am afraid, be distasteful to so generous a person as Your Excellency, but 1 would not urge them upon you did 1 not feel that they were absolutely necessary, but it is essential that the state budget should balance, and I think it is for the ruling family to lead the way, and show their readiness to share in the burdens ..., /^s Confidential. No: Political Agency, Bahrain, the 15th March 1931 From:- Captain C.G.Prio^ I.A., Political AgentBahrain. To:- The Ilon T ble the Political Piesident in the Persian G-ulf.,Bushire. Sir, pH I have the honour to saj that your letter to Shaikh Hamad regarding the proposed reductions in the allowances of the A1 Khalifa by 10 per cent has been very well received. In fact it appears that the Al Khalifa were expecting an even geeiter reduction and were agreeably surprised to find that it is only to be 10 per cent. Of course they realise that if thai* revenues continues to diminish it may be necessary to increase this 10 per cent to an even larger figure. I enclose a reply from Shaikh Hamad on this matter, which explains itself. It will be seen that he approves of your suggestion to him. I have the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant, Political Agent, Bahrain, rNo:- 0/66. Dated:- 4th Jme 1931. Prom:- Political Bahrain, To:- Secretary Bushire• Please send 'by down mail copy of Shaikh Hamad's letter to Resident accepting 10fo cut in Givil List.Mo: Political Agency, Bahrain, the 10th June 1931. From:- Captain O.G.Prior I.A., Political Agent,Batirain. To?- ti The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. I would be glad if you would send me todajr,if possible,a statement showing the total amounts, receipts and expenditure,of revenue for each of the last SIX Arabic months. This should not,of course, include amounts of capital. Please also show separately the amount in reserve in India and elsewhere on the close of each of these months. Sir, I have the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant, Political Agent,Bahrain.Confidential . D.O.Ho:C/ J^ e t - i —1 j j. j , Political Agency, Bahrain,the 28th June 1931 Dear ¥ajor, i ■ . The X0% cut in the Al Khalifa allowances has 'been made but not without soire unpleasentness. It will 'be recalled that the cut was to begin pn the let ¥uharret»,the allowances being reduced at the end of the cjonth. shortly before the cut was due to be inac . ®ade I discovered by chance that Parke had written to dhaikh Hamad and told hi® that neither his nor ohaikh lsa»g pay would be effected by it. I was obliged to take up the matter with shaikh Hamad since without a reduction of his pay the cut weuld leose aueh of its value and the remaining Al Rkalifa weuld net unnaturally ebjeot to their pay being ■ ! ■: . ■ - reduced while hie was left intaot. The shaikh finally I ■' agreed but owing t® hie evident alarm at the probably results of the out in bis father's pay 1 did not press it I' and as matters stand shaikh Isa will continue to receive ; * his full pay. I asked Parke afterwards what he meant by sending such a letter to the shaikh since ho clearly had no authority to go behind a decision that had already been arrived at by Belgrave in conjunction with the Political authorities,and he could only say that he had not known that the cut was to take effect on Shaikh Hamad as well as the others. This ; I regrat to say^ I do not believe^ as it was quite clear from the correspondence that all would be out equally and I think he was solely moved by a desire to ingratiate himself with his employers. Yours Sincerely, Hen'ble Major T.C.Fowle.C.B.B. , /'Al/ itical Resi dent in tfc* WXliiHHi DEPARTMENT. BRANCH. File N«. Serial No, Ii7 Draft Memorandum Telegram Glass for telegrams Ordinary _ Express Urgent* Priority 'Clear Linef SCo be issued oa 1st Reminder 2nd Reminder 3rd Reminder Heading: Case or Diary No. If post copy of telegram required Date of despatch of above List of enclosures # Only for foreign TelegranuL fNot fo? Foreign Telegrami, Issued oh (Code word for telegrams.) MGiPC—SI—555(C3P)L0F—(G-?13)—6-9-30—50,000 Pads. m No. To Dated ■k • 19 (/ . ✓ /a JL / &amp; /O0oo' — -c/ ^ uj^ Jiw St^. f v. CuCt) ^ c\JU£S - v ^. J/Yt</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000360_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/129</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000360</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/129</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/2 II Bahrain Reforms: Finances of the Bahrain Government'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-02-01T00:00:59</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (138 folios)</extent><extent>The contents of the volume have been arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest items at the beginning to the latest at the end.</extent><extent>Foliation: The volume is foliated from the front cover to the inside back cover, using circled pencil numbers in the top-right corner of each recto. There is an earlier foliation system which runs through the volume, using blue pencil numbers in the top-right corner of recto pages.The following foliation anomalies occur: 1a, 1b, 1c, 1d, 1e.The following folios are foldouts: 11-13, 18, 19, 36, 46-48, 54, 85-89, 97, 105, 111, 112, 133, 134.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume’s correspondence and other papers concern Bahrain’s state budget, and the rising costs associated with the Bahrain civil list and the Āl Khalīfah family’s allowances. Most of the correspondence takes place between the Advisor to the Bahrain Government, Charles Dalrymple-Belgrave, and the Bahrain Political Agent, Colonel Geoffrey Prior. The volume is a chronological continuation of ‘File 9/2 II Bahrain Reforms: Finances of the Bahrain Government’ (IOR/R/15/2/128).The volume includes Belgrave’s budgets for Bahrain for the Hijri years 1347 (1928, folios 5-25) and 1348 (1929, folios 38-66). In these reports Belgrave gives great detail of the state’s expenditure on modernisation. For example, detailed reference of Bahrain’s education system, including the opening of a girls’ school, is given in the 1348 budget (folios 61-63).The remainder of the volume’s correspondence is chiefly related to Belgrave’s concerns over the continual financial increases being requested by Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah to Bahrain’s civil list. Belgrave’s concern was that these allowances took up too great a proportion of the Bahrain state budget, and because the issue was primarily a political one, he deferred the issue to the Political Agent, who in turn referred the matter to the Political Resident. There are several copies of the civil list included in the file (for example, folios 81-83). Prior and Shaikh Ḥamad discuss Belgrave’s concerns about the increasing expenditure of the civil list in August 1929 (folios 84-90), with Shaikh Ḥamad raising the hope that revenues from other sources such as kerosene oil might alleviate financial problems.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Khalīfah (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>State budget</topic></subject><subject><topic>Economic reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Political reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Law reform</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000360#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>