<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:59:34.467Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">f — • SEORET, POLICY IN THE MIDDLE EAST. III. THE ARAB MOVEMENT. Memoramlum In Lieut.-Col. Sir Mark Sykes, Hart., M P. The folio vying Memorandum is intended 10 serve as a general appreciation of the Arab situation in the Ottoman Empire, and to give an analysis of the various human, religious, and political factors of which it is composed. THE ARAB PEOPLE: The Arabs may be said to fall into four groups : (1) The Arabs of Arabia proper, marked green on the accompanying map ; (2) the Arabs of Meso potamia, marked yellow; (:&gt;) the Syrians, marked red; (4) the Arabs of Northern Irak and dazirah, marked blue. G roup J.—THE ARABS OF ARABIA. The Arabs of Arabia fall socially under two heads, the settled urban population and village population, and the Bedawin. Religiously they may be divided as follows :— The Arabs of llejaz who are Sunnis. The Arabs of Nejd who are Wahabis. The Arabs of the Gulf Coast who are Sunnis. The Arabs of Muscat who are Boudis. The Arabs of Yemen and Asir who are Shias. The Arabs of Hadhramaut who are Sunnis and Shias. In Arabia proper there is no sense of nationality but a strong sense of race, blood, and common language, something approaching the sense of unitv compatible with war which prevailed in Western Europe in the 11th and 12th centuries. In Nejd political power devolves on chieftains who dwell in towns and are more or less supported by the local outlying tribes. Feuds and wars are chronic and are not waged with any intention of out-and-out success. Thus Ibn Sand and Ibn lieshid have been at war for three generations, but with no definite result. The various tribes who support the rival families absent themselves from battle or change sides with very little compunction, or quarrel among themselves. The following incident will serve to throw a light on the peculiar and desultory nature of these hostilities : — During the present war Major Keyes, our representative at Bahrein, was asketf to send Ibn Sand some ammunition and war stores to Hofuf. lie proceeded to the coast, but finding that the Arabs between the coast and Hofuf were at war with Ibn Sand, he returned to Bahrein. Ibn Sand sent a message asking why the stores had not been sent, and on being told the reason' he replied that if the tribe at war with him were given the stuff they would send it to him in due course, as they were the ordinary carriers. This was actually done and the goods delivered, although the hostilities still continue. It will, therefore, be understandable that war or hostilities need not be a bar to nominal unity, such as the acceptance of the Sherif as paramount chief. S. 291. 16 KO9 The religious divergences are also not ol' intense importance, the old fanatic lire of Wahabi Puritanism apparently being on the wane. In Muscat the case is different, the isolation of Oman from the rest of Arabia being a strong factor in the situation. In Muscat there is a distinct quarrel, and the Sultan lias been ousted from his authority in the land by a pretender to religious supremacy. This is a purely local affair, and the exceedingly rigid and primitive form of Islam prevailing in Oman has no adherents elsewhere. However, the Oman Arabs, the Sultan included, have a strong sense of race and breed. In Yemen and Assir the large proportion of sedentary and village- dwelling Arabs, the long reign and prestige of the Imam, the large number of men he can raise and keep in the field tend to produce a more compre hensible situation. Yemen in fact is a nearer approach to a State in the European sense than any other part of Arabia. In the Aden hinterland and Hadhramaut the sedentary Chiefs are too widely scattered and too small to be of any great account. Turkish influence in Yemen is tolerated, the Imam doing little to support the Turks in war and collecting his own taxes. The Shiism of the Yemen Arabs has nothing in common with that of the people of Kerbella, which will be referred to later. The Imam claims to be commander of the faithful in his own dominions, and does not regard the Sultan as caliph; his relations with the Sherif of Mecca are fair, and, under given circumstances, there is no reason why he should not recognise the latter's premier position, though he would naturally not recognise him as caliph. In Hejaz the situation is influenced by the holy cities of Mecca and Medina, which are large towns which subsist on pilgrimage, the Bedouin sharing in the. protits ol carriage, traffic, and dues. The Sherif has a strong position in virtue of his character, lineage, linanchl resources,»and office, and few very bitter and no powerful enemies. His relations with the Imam of Sanaa, Ibn Reshid, Ibn Sand are good enough to enable him to obtain their recognition a^ paramount ruler, provided other circumstances are propitious. Between Medina and the cultivated parts of Syria the tribes Beni Sakhr, Shararat, and the clans around Kirak would no doubt fall into line with the Sherif owing to their bitter dislike of the Turks, from whom they have suffered considerably in the past. G roup II.—THE ARABS OF LOWER MESOPOTAMIA. (See map. Topographical Section, (Jeneral Staff, No. 25G3 Lower Mesopotamia, scale 1 1,000,000.) Section 1.—Population of banks of Tigris from Fao to Kurna, settled Arabs, Shia sect, living in villages, in position of tenant and landlord ; accustomed to regular administration. Landlords are mostly local and tribal notables. Section 2.—Population of banks of Euphrates between Kurna and Suk- es-Sheyukh, as in Section 1. Sertion 3.— Population of swampy area contained by triangle Suk-es- Sheyukh—Kurna—Gannet-Ali, excluding riparian population mentioned in Section 2, are primitive, predatory people, with little attachment to religion, and little political cohesion. Section 4.—Population of banks of Tigris and its tributary canals from Kurna to Aziziyah are semi-nomadic Arabs, mostly Shias in transition stage from pastoral nomads to sedentary agriculturalists, economically, socially in transition from tribal chief and clansmen to landlord and tenant. White patches on east and west of Tigris and of Shatt-el-Gharraf inhabited by pure nomads. Section 5. Area contained in rough polygon Museyib-Kerbela-Kasr Reheima (a point 10 miles west, of Bahr Shinafie), Tel Maaja (10 miles south of Samawa), I m Dukan (10 miles east of Samawa), .1 in Khor el Afei- Museyib. Urban population of Nejef, Kerbela, Meshed Ali, mixed Arab, Persian, Indian. Fanatical and factious. These towns are centres of intense Shia religious feeling. Rural population as in areas described in Sections 1, 2, and 4, according to circumstances, but influenced by above-mentioned towns.I he donnmint factor in this group lies in the nature of the Shiism which prevails. To understand this it is necessary to .recollect a little of the previous history of the country. Kerbella was the centre of Ali's caliphate and was not only the stronghold of the lost cause of the AJid house after Ali's death, but also the centre of a sect known as the Kharyites or anarchists who interpreted the doctrine of private judgment as not only applying to religious matters but also to ordinary law. This sect has disappeared in name, but in essence survives, among these Arabs of Mesopotamia. After ' 'h'.ith ol Ali lower Mesopotamia was in constant rebellion and the scene of many persecutions, both under the Oinayads and Abbassids. It was also the ieM)it ol all Sliia pilgrims to the shrines ol the Alid martyrs and saints ir contained. With the death of the tenth Imam and the spread of the legend that he liad disappeared to return again, the population became rebels against constituted authority, but with no policy, since their candidate was not to appear until the end of the world. ICver disorderly at the best of limes, when the Abbassid civilisation collapsed, these people sank into a complete anarchy and have never since recovered. They' bitterly dislike (liristians as such, Sunnis, whether Turks or Arabs, worse than Christians, and are hostile to Persians on racial grounds. This area, therefore, presents a separate problem ; its inhabitants are broken up among themselves, and have no natural atlinity to any external movement. It must also be remembered that to Indian and Persian Sliias the shrines ol Nejef and Kerbella are more than Mecca is to Sunnis, as Shiism is a passionate and sentimental creed, and its poetry and traditions are that of a tragically lost cause. The pan-Arab movement in this area can have little force, and the Sherif of Meccano following. During the early part ol the present war the Turks, with con siderable ability, worked up considerable enthusiasm among the people on the grounds of repelling infidels who desired to pollute the holy places. The liussian action at Meshed and elsewhere has had considerable influence on the minds of the urban peoples of the Nejef-Kerbella area. The only sign of interest in outside events traceable in this area was the telegram sent to Constantinople when Mr. Parker profaned the mosque of ()mar a few years ago. G roup III.—SYRIA. Coming to this area we find a situation extremely diiferent from that obtaining in the preceding two. The material and intellectual civilization of Syria is superior to almost any part of the Ottoman Empire, and in many respects conforms with that of Southern Europe—it is equal to that of Spain, Calabria or Sicily. The reason for this dillerence can be traced to several factors, (a) The fact that the Ommayad dynasty primarily replaced Christianity by Islam with considerable caution and restraint. (6) That Jerusalem has ever been respected as a place of Christian pilgrimage, (c) That the long years of the Crusades produced by constant negotiations, settlement and the temporary introduction of European law, a tradition of intercourse and interchange of ideas with Europe, (d) The French Jesuit policy of making much of the Arab literature both for intellectual, religious and political ends, (e) The constaul ebb and flow of pilgrims and tourists, (/j The development of the country bv means of French railways, {g) The temporary emigration to, and subsequent return of large numbers ol Syrian Christians and Moslems from, the United States of America. On the other hand wo have the reflection of \rabian poetry and philosophy coming from Arabia proper, without any intermingling of Persian or Turkish influence. The Ottoman Turks have impressed themselves very slightly on Syria, and have, as a matter of fact, made considerable use of Syrians in the Government of the country, and the officering of the locally raised army. The main influences in the country are Jerusalem, Damascus, Beyrut, the Lebanon, Aleppo. . •In Jerusalem the Christians and Moslems are brought together partly bv a lear of the Jews and partly by the constant intercourse necessitated by the tourist and pilgrim trailic. s. 291. a 2 .4 Damascus is a centre of Syrian Islam, and its people somewhat fanatically inclined, but there is a strong leaven of toleration among the leading Moslem cleP'V and a considerable bent towards French and English culture among the rising generation of the aristocratic houses. Mimlar to Damascus are Horns and llama, but in these latter places' fanaticism is more easily ronsed. Bey rut with the Jesuit College and the American Syrian 1 rostestant ( ollege is the mainspring of European influence on the Arab and Syrian mind, nas been the scene in later years of much fraternisation between Moslems and Christians and is the natural lountain of the idea ot Arab nationalism, i r \rab nationalism embracing Arabs ol Christian, Moslem, and Dmse origin The Lebanon is the stronghold of French political influence through the'hold of the Jesuits of Beyrut on the Maronites. It is the most progressive part of Syria, but there still survives a ceitain feeling of religious antago nism between Maronites and Druses and Maronites and Mohammedans dwelling outside the Lebanon, though among the better educated there have been considerable efforts to srille and mitigate this evil. The last area, that lying between Tripoli, Alexandretta. Marash, and Meskene, may be described as Aleppine Syria. Here there is a strong Turkish influence owing to the mixture ol 1 urkish and l\uidi&gt;h settleis, and the existence oi Armenians in many parts. ( onsequently there are Turks who pass as Arabs owing to the fact that they are of the second generation, and there is a reflex of the Armenian question which is apt to make the mob range itself on the Turkish side in political questions. G roup IV, The main factors in this group are 1)iarbekik-ur ka. N. J azirah. Mosul. Kerkuk. B aghdad. Diarbekir-Uria is Turco -Kurdo-Arab, and heavily implicated in the Armenian massacres, and therefore not really a part of the Arab movement. N. Jazirah is Kurdo -Arab nomadic and anti-Diarbekir. The Kurds are practically with the Arabs in this area anti-Turkish, and solar not implicated in the Armenian question. Mosul is practically solid for the Arab movement, and normally the relations between the Christians and Moslems are fair, and with good outside influences capable of fusion. Iverkuk is strongly influenced by the Kurds, but the Kurds of good education are on the Arab side. Baghdad and to the North is influenced by the fact that there is a strong Jewish or Shia element. The Shias are a cause of want of solidarity ; the Jews, 50,000 in number, are pro-Ottoman, an:l Committee of 1 nion and Progress; the remaining Arabs are on the Arab side, as also- are the Baghdadi Turks, i.e., Turks of pre-Ottoman times. CONCLUSION. On the above groundwork we have the Arab movement, which is natural, spontaneous, but unorganised. It has its origin (a) in the sense of breed common to all Arabs ; (b) the dislike of Turks, common to all Arabs; (c) its driving power originates in Svria, especially Beyrut. Its organisation includes military oilicers drawn from all parts, the notables of Syria, the clergy, the ('hristians of Syria. These persons have moved the Shenf of Mecca and spread the idea among the Arabian chieftains. The sentiments vary, but there are certain common factors. On the whole the Arabs are pro-Knglish and anti-French, but this anti- French feeling is chiefly due to fear of French financial exploitation. The Syrians favour and preach alliance with native Christians, but this has the tacit hostility of a certain element in the clergy. This feeling would be strongest in Aleppo, Baghdad, and Mosul.The groundwork of the movement is real, but nevertheless the movement is incapable of action except with strong active support. The German-Turkish policy is obvious, to foment the feeling between Moslems and Christians, exterminate the Christians, kill the Sherif, and capture the Arab Moslems by according national concessions at the psycho logical moment, while menacing with overwhelming force. If the Germans succeed in keeping France and England divided, they will capture the Arab Moslems for good and all, and we shall then be confronted with a real Jehad. If we settle with the French and support the Arabs, we shall establish a strong anti-Turkish block in the very centre of Islam. FINAL NOTE. The Indian Moslems are politically and racially against the Arabs. The Arabs regard the Indians with contempt on account of their poverty, physique, and ignorance of religion. The Indians being pro-Turkish are anti- Arab. This is an immense benefit to us in event of the Arab movement succeeding.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B219</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B219</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Policy in the Middle East. III. The Arab Movement.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1915</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-19T09:12:59</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at f 116, and terminates at f 118, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 116-118; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and won't be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Printed copy of a secret memorandum, dated 1915; a report by Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Mark Sykes, which is an overview of the human, religious and political dimensions of the Arab population in the Middle East. The report is divided into four sections, based on the four groups of Arab people identified by Sykes:The Arabs of Arabia, further subdivided into the Arabs of Hejaz, Nejd [Najd], the Gulf coast, Muscat, Yemen, and Hadhramaut [Ḥaḍramawt];The Arabs of Mesopotamia, further subdivided into five regions along the banks of the Tigris and Euphrates rivers;The Syrians, with brief explanation of the reasons underlying the complexity of the religious situation in Syria, including the historic interplay between Christians and Muslims, the French railways, Turkish influence;The Arabs of Northern Irak [Iraq] and Jazirah, divided into five main factors: Diarbekir-Urfa [Diyarbakır], North Jazirah, Mosul [Al-Mawṣil], Kerkuk [Kirkūk] and Baghdad.In his conclusion, Sykes lists the chief characteristics of the ‘Arab movement’, and in a final note, he draws attention to the contempt which Indians hold towards Arabs. The original memorandum included a map, with the regions populated by the four Arab groups indicated in green, yellow, red and blue.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir 6th Baronet Mark Sykes</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Mesopotamian Campaign (1914-1918)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>