<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000d5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T02:49:49.022Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">-jj'rom Xq xiie Hesidenoy ^-gent, Shargah (Japtain Ji.H. Gastrell, Secretary to the -tion'tde the Political -Resident in the Persian Ciulf, iJushire. rJO.324. Dated 21st June 1933. ^ V A. U. /f- ^ Tith reference to ray telegram dated 15th June 1933 on the subject of the visit to ahargah of Lady Willingdon 'by aeroplane Monnu^ l 'beg to state that 'before the arrival to ahargah of the said aeroplane 1 informed Shaikh Sultan Mr. Saqar, Huler of bhargah, ahout her arrival ; and he v;as ready to meet her. i then went to the aerodrome waiting her arrival. The aeroplane arrived and 1 met her there, ihen the Shaikh came and we all entered the aerodrome. The Shaikh requested her to come to his house and she acceded to his request, le all went to the Shaikh's house. V/hen we all seated the Shaikh ordered a salute of five A guns to 'be fired for her and presented her at the same time some pearls and a golden anklet, Indian&gt;Make, in which there was a diamond ^tone, 3^0 W as very pleased and when coffee was served she left the Shaikh's place when they had a horse race for her sake. 'Hien the Shaikh's ceremony was over she called at the Agency and 1 showed everyrespect suitable to her position. Afterwards we / accompanied her to the aerodrome and she saii that she was resting; it was dark too. She allowed us to go. 1 asked if she required anything we shall 'be obliged to be ^ her service. She thanked us for this. On June 15, 1933 / morning the Shaikh and myself went to the aerodrome to see her off but she had left before we reached there. u.Ji. j 1 /V.7J3. A■No.290 Dated 20th June 1934. i ^rom - iTie lesidenoy Agent, 3harjah. To Japtain A.^. Galloway, uador Secretary to the 'Ion'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire. After 'Jorapliments. 1 have the honour to report that on June 19, 19-34, a native of tne village Khan, who was in the service of tne Amir of tne village named Jarash Din Ali, killed the Amir, went to oharjah, reported the outrage to the Shaikh and sought refuge with him. But the Shaikh captured him, put him to prison, enquired from him as to who was his participant and came to the conclusion that with him there was a man called Muhammad 'bin Ihrahirr a native of ^atar and a memher of the Sudan trihe, who asked him to commit the outrage, that when he murdered the Amir he went to Muhammad hin Ihrahim and reported the news and that Muhammad ad'yised him to go to the ohaikh of oharjah. That is what led the Shaikh to kill the murderer and seize Muhammad 'bin Ihrahim whom they are now contemplating how to deal with. 3haikh ruhammad 'bin oaqar, the brother of the :{uler of Sharjah, is in the village of Khan and the question of selecting a successor to the murdered Amir is under coasideration. A copy of this letter has 'been sent to the Political Agent^Bahrain, u .1. n .5No. 3 /3 of 1934. British nesicLenoy &amp; Gonsulato General Bushire, 10^ Noveni *ber 19.54. To ~ ' ^ ^ C ^ ' '^•■^'V. U-.aA.;,, ' S' \ ' li ^ i.uju vii - i^p c^yU 1 \ - ' t\&gt;' ' ^ ' &amp;&amp;yp^vxji \ * ✓ j rr^o CT^yJcJ 1 1 Tie Residenoy Agent, SUarjah. After CJompiimenbs. The Officiating Political A.pent Bahrain has reported that Shaikh Sultan 'bin Saqar, T^uler cf Rharjah, informed him that certain Tefiouins of the KanaBir tribe looted the houses of some Arnb^ of ^as ul KUalnah residing at flharjah, that the Shaikh chased the marauders 'but did not recover the property they had t :iken a ^ay . The Shaikh had added that only he lately had recovered certain property which some Kanaair raiders had looted in a previous raid. Unless firm steps are taken to stop these raids they are likely to increase as the raideri fjain oonfideaoe. ?.. Please inform the Shaikh that the Kon # 'Sle the Political Resident L **v-w expects - in view of the presence of the air port in his territory - to take special measures to prevert incursions. Usual Ending. „ ?■ /wr „. Major, Secretary to the political '^osidc in the Persian ^ilf.STIk T V V -'ot No. 1V3- 3/9. Mo-l.'''-— doStt ' ( x&gt;\&lt; The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Secretary to tne Honourable Uie Political itesident in tne Persian Gull, BUSH IRE. Cr J and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ^). T he A gkncy, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. t Dated. Reference to previous correspondence : Bahrain P.L.No.lbb dated 24 :th April 193V. Name and Date. Dcscripiiun of Enclosure. W- Copy ol letter No.372 oated 28tii April 1937 Irom tne Residency Agent, Sharjali, to tne Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject. One ol the Agency guaras ot Sharjah raiaea upon by oedioins.n Translation of letter IIo«372 dated 118th Ajril Iij37 fro ■ the Residency Agent, ^harjah, to the Political A ;c it, Bahrain. A 'V rX After Cornpliments, 'Vith reference to ny letter Ho# 335 dated 'lot /^ril 1937, on the 22nd April 1937 Hamad yhi Haldcadli 1 c ncn returned after they had overtook the plunderers in a jlacc called A1 Hafeer, about 30 miles from Aibai and restored from them the rest of the effects plundered from -bhamo.e Cliaii Bag save the F g.8/-* The plunderers too : oath ,o 'Ir ' in .lakkadh 1 e men that they did not ta':e that noney fron lain; it is ^osr:ible that he lost it in the place - ^oro the incident too': place# Usual iihding#Hi No. l'/2-B/9. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:—• Tiie Secretary to tiie Honourable The Political Resident m tne Persian Gull', 3USHIRE' and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). Tjje Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated.MA. Jtet.l.VSX. Reference to previous correspondence : r r r n ') Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Copy ol letter No.367 dated 28tii April 1937 irom tne Resiaei Agent, Sharjaii, to tne Politica Agent, Ban rain, witii enclosures ncy Subject. Diving on tne Trucial Coast.lo. i/L Translation 01 letter No.367 dated k!8tn April 1^37 irom tne Resiaency ^gent, Lharjan, to tne Political Agenx, iiis .nrain. 0+ ***** * 'jim Alter Complintents. I have tne nunour to euDmit nerewitn a letter and a notice dated 24tn kunarraa 13b6(G.4.3y)dealing .vitn diving. 2. The state ot diving in past years was that tne aiver was a prey oi tne naichudha, gave him what he(the naickhudna) wisiied ana tooic him on diving willingly or unwillingly. There was also no specitic time lor diving during wmcn a diver should be held responsible i'or his woriu This action on tne part oi tne huler oi Lubai is considered to be an important step towards tne improvement ot' the conuition of divers ana the diving industry. Apparently next year tne people ol Lubai will adopt tne same practice now m vogue at Bahrain. Ana by so doing, the reiormation concerning the conuition oi tne divers will be completea. Usual i^naing.■■■■■ CONFIDENTIAL. X „T/61-4/13. 'jl 'fcf vSV ' zs/y/i? '~7~cruryi , The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to P^l The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and hasvthe honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated ..9Xh. .AugU -st • 1937 Reference to previous correspondence: I Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Ruler of Qatar 1 s letter dated the 22nd July 1937. „ ' ' 2. Political Agent, Bahrain^ letter / No♦C/579-4/13 dated 26th July 1937i 3. Adviser to the Bahrain Governments letter No. 729/SF-9A dated 31st July 1937. 3. 4. Political Ag4nt Bahrain's letter N o .T /60 dated 9th August 1937. ✓ if Zubarah. C 'Cst.ir- ^ ^ &lt;r ^-uonr-Copy of translation of letter dated the 13th Jamad A1 Awwal 1356 (22.7.37) from Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim A1 Thani C.I.E., Ruler of Qatar to Captain T. Hickinbotham Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments. I beg to inform you that some of my subjects who were in the northern villages went to Bahrain in the meantime. Most of them are divers and are bound to work in diving as now is the season. They are also in debt. It appears that they took a chance of the present situation in order to neglect their obligations since they are still in Bahrain and were not prohibited as others. This is against the existing rules to be observed in these con ditions. I beg to invite your attention to this and I shall feel highly grateful if you will pay due attention to this matter and order for the return of those whom I mentioned to my side. I like to report this to you as I wish to have the rights protected. Usual ending. Copy of letter No. C/579-4/13 dated tjre 26th July 1937 from the Political Agent, Bahrain to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government Bahrain. I have the honour to inform you that I have received a letter from Shaikh Abdullah bin Qassim A1 Thani C.I.E., Ruler of Qatar. He states that a number of his subjects who live in the northern villages of the Qatar Peninsula have come over to Bahrain. He points out that they, unlike other subjects of his, were not prohibited from entering BeOirain. He further states that a majority of them are divers and are bound to work during the diving season which is now in progress. He says that they are indebted to their Nakhodas and that they have merely come to Bahrain % in order to evade their obligations. I should be glad if you would investigate this matter and let me have a report.■21. 2* T&amp;ifi ib not the first tiM that diyars t'roia t utar ami otiier atates have Qom settled in iXihrain and there is a regular prooedure in Bahrain and in other diring state# for suoh oases as these, as on this point the diving law in all # » tiie aiving statM is the mom . If a uiTer, with- * out a 'barua froa his original nakhuda, diyes with ^ an ■&lt; n^ituaa, tliti new iia^iiuda ^ecoiaws res ponsible for the total debt of the aiv@r to his old nakhucia* If the diver obtains regular eaploy* laent asiiore, during the civiag season, he is res* ponsiole for paying ♦ , fasl-al-l&gt;arr ,, to his original nakhttda, but aeoorain^ to divisig lev and custom the original nakhuda has not the ri^ht to olaim thtt of the diver who zaay have gone to another country unless he is a slave diver* This condition however would not be in iishrain m l 1 have no reason to suppose that any of the people i.&lt; ^ slavws. 3« In the pe . .. v . to Bahrain the ^uler of v atar has sent the uiver's nakhuda or a representative to *jahrain with a letter stating who he is and the nakhuda has produced his diving book showing proof of the diver 9 s debt# If the uiver has been diving with a Bahrain nakhuda without s 'barua' the dethrais has paid the diver's debt to the atar nakhuda. The saw pro* cedure has been effective in cases of iiahrain divers who have gone to ,atar anu similar oases in L@an ana iLuwait^ I suggest that now or si end of the season *ihaikh Abdullah bin Jaiiia should send Jdad-* onemm xomom to Bahrain with a list of divers alleged to hare ooiae here frcm .atar and with their accoiints and the Bahrain uoveraiment .iii fiad out whether the aen have been diTing and with ti?ho&amp;u 5« lioriaally no oakhuda will employ a foreign diver without a ' baruaand I think it is unlikely in any case at this late date in th^ season that wmsy divers will find nakhudas. b* In this —mtiMi any divers, who have no nakhudas in ^atur, apply to the Bahrain Uovemaent Tor permission to dive they will to si, Tft—A to do so sad those who have will y .L. ^ca Oil ^arua aooU i.i l;ic v^u a ...y ; uu the jialu'ain Joveriiaent will put the ^fourth* on deposit pending a claim from a ^atar aaidiuda/* I have the honour to bo, JLr, Your most obedient servant 9 od/ 0. i^alrymple ^el^rave, j.aviser to the uoveruuieat._____ No. T/60-4/13. Offic e of the Political A ent y Bahrain on raceas at Karachi. Dated 9th August 1937* To dhaifch Abdullah bin Quaijn Al i hani | C 4 X • ^ Huler of Qatar, After Compliments, Referring to jrour letter of the 22nd July 1937 regarding the coming to Bahrain from your country of certain peraons aaid to be divers, 2, I am informed by the Bahrain Government from whom enquiries were made that certain persona and their families who claim to be Bahrain subjects have been given permission to come to Bahrain by Uia Highneas the ^ler, A few of these parsons are divers but the Bahrain Government are informed that the total number of divers who may poasibly be indebted to Qatar Nakhodas is not more than twenty. The Bahrain Government suggest that you should send a messenger y either now ar at the end of the diving aeaaon 9 to Bahrain with a list of divers who you allege have coiue to this side and full particulars of their debts. The Bahrain ok&gt;vem inent will then inveatigat and find outmmmm Wg—a——* 2. ^o. h out whether the persona have been diving and with whom* In the meantime should any divers 9 who have no Hakhodas in Qatar, apply to the Bahrain Government for permission to dive they will be allowed to do so and those who have Kakhodas will be released on Barua in the usual way the Bahrain Government will put the f, fqrth H on deposit pending a claim from a Qatar Kakhoda* Usual ftnding* Sd. T. Hickinbotham. Captain| Political Agent, Bahrain at Karachi*Translation of letter dated 26th Jamad Thani 1356 (3-9-37) from Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim al Thani, C.I.E., Ruler of Qatar, to Captain T. Hickinbotham, Poli tical Agent, Bahrain. your canqp at Karachi. I thank you for the interest you have 'bken in the matter of the persons about w^om I refer red to you. As to your statement that the Bahrain Govern ment informed you that some persons claimed Bahrain nation ality and the Ruler therefore allowed them to come to Bahrain. My friendI allow me to say that this is incor rect and that the Bahrain Government are mistaken in giving you this information. The persons whom I mention ed to you were my subjects and from Qatar. It is, however, possible that someone has whispered to them and misguided them that the debts they owed would be waived if they run away to Bahrain. On their arrival in Bahrain they were not prevented from landing but were received by the Bah rain Government who promised to grant them documents to enable them to go for diving which made them not to in terest themselves or care for the debts due from them or for what they did. This is, as you are aware, an inad missible and an undesirable act. The Bahrain Government, by so doing, have exceeded the limit and acted contrary to rules to be observed in such cases and encroached on the rights of others. I neither allow nor agree to such unusual deeds and do not think that you also agree to such things. I am sure that had you made enquiries inter the matter and investigated the correctness of the same, you would have corroborated my statement and it would have become clear to you that the action taken by the Bahrain I had the honour of receiving your letter dated 9th August 1937 (1st Jamad al Thani 1356) issued from Government/-Government was contrary to rules and usages to be observed and followed in such cases# The persons whom I mentioned to you have run away from Qatar and left their nakhudas in the working season and delayed them from doing their work in the season# They were responsible for carrying out the work in this time# They are considered as offenders by the diving experts then how could it be desirable for the Bahrain Govern ment to allow them, receive them and make them leave their nakhudas in the time of work and promise to give them documents to work at Bahrain while they knew that they were subjects of others and responsible for payments and for necessary duty. Is not there a contempt and insult to the rights of others? Should you tiling over and consider the matter you would find that the action of the Bahrain Government was inadmis sible, and an encroacheaeint on the rights of others# I am, therefore, informing you that I neither agree to nor permit such actions and I protest against them to you# I am certain that you are of those {Just and equitable persons who would observe the regulations and rules in force. Undoubtedly you will enquire into the matter and care for the preservation and res pect of the rights and observance/ of the rules. Usual Ending#'TVurtv ' ^ Bur' No..^7f 2 1. . No, c/562. e;'0'-t e resir v, ■2i-v-ii. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— ilie Honourable 'ttie Political Resident in the Persian Caulf. D and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gdlf. Dated 17s eptember 1937 Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Copy of letter Nb.C/661 dated. 17th September 1937 to the ■Kuler of Qatar. ZUBARAH.u CONFIDENTIAL. Ko. c/777-4/13 /» V. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Honoureble the Pol i to* cal sic ent 5 in the Persia:- ^ulfj 'Hush ire , and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). J r\ The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 14th Cctobe r 1937. Reference to previous correspondence : Bahrain Printed letter No,0/662 dated the 17th September 1937 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter ^ T o. C/775 dated the 14th October 1937 to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. Subject. Z U B A ^ A F.Yo. C/775-4/13 From Political Agency, Bahrain, 14th October 1937• To Captain T. Hickinbotham, I.A,, Political Agentj Bahrain. m he Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to refer to^your letter No. 729/3F-9A dated the 31st July 1937 and to state that I have received a communication from Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim al Thani, C.T.::., Ruler of 'jatar, to the effect that he has instructed the nakhudas to proceed to Bahrain with lists of the names of persons and the amount of debt of each. Pi should be grateful if you will instruct the port officials in Bahrain so that there will be no question of these persons being pre vented from landing. T have the honour to be. Sir, v our most obedf ent servant, Sd/- T. Hickinbotham, Captain, Pol itic ^1 Agent. Bahrain.5/- Conflcleutial ^3— 443 ^ h'-n-iy No. C/920-22/l.b. Political figency, Bahrain, the 20th December 1937• The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire J.enjoraiidur: . T forward herev/ith a copy of a confidential memo- ran(3um No» C/1115-19/1 dated the 16th December 1937 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah, together with its enclosures. 2. The question of Sir Bu Na*ir Island last rose in 1933 and T would invite attention to my predecessors confidential letter No, 0/209-15/2 -dated the 18th June 1933 and to the Secretary's letter No. C/200 dated the ^ 25th November 1933 sddressed to the Residency Agent, Shar- Jah. 3. T have nothing on record to show whether any con versation was held by the Political Resident v/ith the Shaikhs concerned, and I would request information on this point. 4. In ordinary circuir,stances I should be inclined to recommend that the present communication from the Shaikh of Sharjah should be ignored, and matters left to take their own course. As matters stand at present however, it is undesirable that Sharjah and Abu Dhabi should be preoccupied by the alarms and excursions of 'war' at a time when we want them to concentrate on oil matters. Unless therefore some definite contrary decision was reached in 1933 and communicated to the Shaikhs, I would recommend that action be taken on the lines suggested by my predecessor in paragraph 9 of his letter quoted above»o. 5. I should doubt v ^hether subjects of Sharjah have in actual fact begun to build on the Island, and should expect that they have been instructed to wait a while until the Shaikh can judge the probable result of the present piece of kite flying. T am, however, enquiring confidentially from the Residency Agent v/hether there is any indication of building having been begur or being likely in the immediate future. Political Agent, Bahrain- 3 ^ Copy of memorandum No. C/1115-19/1 dated the 15th December 1937 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. T beg to enclose, in original and translation, letter No. 90 dated the 12th Shauwal 1356 (i.e. 15-12- 1937) from the Ruler of Sharjah to the Honourable the Political Resident. 2. I should be grateful td know v/hether there is any objection to the Shaikh buildirg a fort at Sir Bu Nu'air for the protection of his subjects#Translation of letter No. 90 dated the 12th Shauwal 1356 (i.e. 15th December 1937) from Shaikh Sultan Mr Saqr, Puler of Sharjah, to the Honourable Sir Trenchard Fowle, F.C.I.E., C.B.E., Political Re sident in the Persian Gulf. After Compliments# I write to inform Your Honour that T have permitted my subjects to settle at my Island Sir Bu Nu f air and to build houses etcetera for them selves, the fact which makes necessary for me to build a fort for their protection. Usual Ending.D.O, Hot /l 4/7 if dated the ^ January 1938, My dear Weightman, Will you please refer to your Demi-Offocial letter NojC/9klO -&lt;Jii /l. b dated the iiOth December 1937. 2. Unfortunately the two letters referred to in .tare 2 of yuur letter under reference have been destroyed last year during •weeding' of the records, fill you please let me have copies as soon as possible. Yours siCncerely, H. tyeightman JBsquire, I.C.S. Political Agent* 3a hra in . u ionfldentlal. M No. C/8-22/1.13. ' v ' &gt;T ^ Political Agency, Bahrain, the 3rd January 1938. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. © Memorandum. ? i Tn continuation of my memorandum No. C/920-22/l.b dated the 20th December 1937, I forward herewith a copy of a report received from the Residency Agent, Sharjah. Political Agent, Bahrain,Copy of memorandum No. C/2-19/1 dated the 1st January 1938 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah. Reference your memorandum Wo. C/921 -22 /l .b. dated the 2Cth December 1937. 2. No Sharjah people have so far started building on Sir Bu Nu'air. 3. The Shaikh intends to allow his subjects to settle in the Island before the next diving season in T .:ay, but cannot do so before he builds a fort for their protection. 4. Although the Shaikh did not specifically ask permis sion to build the fort, he is waiting for a reply to see whether there is any objection to his building the fort.COPY, Political Agency, No. C/209-15/2 Bahrain, the 18th -Tune 1933. From To Lieutenant-Colonel Cordon Loch, T.A,, Political Agent, Bahrain. 'he Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Culf, Bushire. 3ir T have the honour to inform yon that luring my recent tour H.I.'.3. 'ovvey anchored off 3ir ^u T Ta'ir Island to shelter from the ind on the 9th June 1933. A lar^e number of dhows (over seventy) vere there for 'he same purpose. 2. The Shaikh of Sharjah's flag vas flying from a flag staff and there was a small hut at the base of the flagstaff. No signs of other buildings were to he seen. 3. On the 10th June the 3ha T .kh of Abu Dhabi said that he understood that buildings were being made t Sir Bu ir and asked that the Shaikh of Sharjah should be prevented from bulld- inj there. he matter had been the subject of a dispute during the time of Sir Percy Cox. 4. On the 11th - T une the Shaikh of Bibai m' de a similar pro test. 5. The Beside;.cy Agent informed me that there had been trou ble in the time of Sir Percy Cox and he had decided that in the interests of peace no buildings shoi Id be constructed. The matter had apain come up in the time of Lieutenant- Colonel Trevor, who had said that Government had no objection to the buildings being constructed. On hearing this the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi had written a threatening letter to the Shaikh of 3harjah, who then gave up the idea. There is no question about sovereignty, which admittedly rests with Sharjah. 6. In accordance with recent general instructions the Shaikh of Sharjah hoisted his flag on Sir Bu Tie * ir Island, and has apparently/-• - _ n apparently made this an opportunity for reverting to the plan of building there and creating a re- victuall1ng base fa the pearling f leets * 7, Tn each case (Abu Dhabi and Dibai) T sail that T haci no information, that T had seen no buildings except the hut at the flagstaff, but that T would report the matter to the Hon'ble the Political Resident, 8. T took an opportunity of telling the Shaikh of Shar- jah that I had heard that he was thinking of building and that I believed that the question had been raised in the time of Sir Percy Cox and T ieutenant-Colonel m revor. TT e said that he was not building now, but that he might do so in the future. 9, I do not know what took place in the past and sub mit the matter for your orders. On the meagre imorr at:.on before me, T would suggest that the 'Resiuenc^ -^eiio r V)e instructed to remind the ShaiSh of Sharjan t la ^ the ques tion of building on Sir Bu' &gt; a'lr Tslanu. _^ve rise ■ o un pleasantness in the past and to advise h5.r:i no . to do an/- thing v/hich would upset his relations w th ms '•- - _ ^ 10. I would only add that I think that the Shaikh of Sharjah is acquiring rather an higher opinion of himself than hard facts 'ould warrant, and it is not impossible that he may embroil himself in some, 'oolish course of action un less he is carefully watched. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, 3d/- Loch Lieut-Colonel Political A^ent,Bahrain.COPY. To No. C/200 of 1933. Office of the Political Resident In the Persian ^ulf, Camp Bahrain. 25th November 1933. The Residency Agent, Sharjah. Aft.r Comoliments. Co Reference correspondence ending with your letter No. 441 dated the 22nd Aujust 1933, regarding the inten tion of the Shaikh of 3harjah to build on the island of 3ir 3u I T a'ir. The Honourable the Political Re si lent /ill talk over the matter with the Shaikhs concerned when he next visits the Trucial Coast. Usual 3ndinj. 3d/- -J. Croning for Secretary to the Political Resident | in the Persian Gulf,J Gonfidentisl. D.O. No, m /I /7 dated the Februsry, 19oc, My dear Weightman, Please refer to your demi-official letter Bo,C/47- dated January 16th. 2. The Shaikh of Sharjah hae a perfect right to build on hie o*n island and his doing so ^ould not appear to amount to a breach of any of the existing treaties or engagements. In vie* of the Shaikh's present attitude Sir Trenchard is not prepared to discuss the matter verbally v^ith him at has apparently been done before, and he is txierefore refraining from making any re^ly to the Shaikh's letter of the 15th December. COF* Yours sincerely, H, Weightman Esquire, ICS., Political Agent, B ahrain , i1 Confidential. . a The Political A S e U ., Bahrain, Presents his compliments to : K&lt; 7^3 The Honourable 'the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp Bahrain, -1 i,; m a cody of the nnderroentionea document («) and has the honour to send him a copy ~r~rr t , • The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dited 12th February 1938. Kefcrcnce to previous correspondence: lahrain demi-official letter l!o.C/34 dated the 12th January 1938 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date, Subject. Translation of letter lvo.96 dated the 29th -Tanuary 1938 from the Residency Agent, 3harj ah. I urder at 3har,iah of one of the Shaikh of Sharjah's subjects. .Translation of letter No.96 dated 29tii January 1J38 from the Residency iigent, Sb-arjah, to the PolitiCc l ;.gent,3ahroi. After Compliments. Reference my letter No.3b datea 8th January 1938. On the 27th January 1938 Shaikh Majid bin Saqr ana tlpse who had accompanied him returned to Liharjaii without being successful in overtaking the mucierers of Salih bin Samhah. This is due to the fact that the iiwamir who .vent with him missed the way and took him to the interior of Oman whereas the culprits had gone by another way. Usual ending.mmam r\' .s~\ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. D epartment, EXPRESS LETTER m B -This is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save Ukgmplic ' ' expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. 1 o save time and formalities it is worded and signed as ij it hud been so despatched,] Fbom Political Agent, Bahrain, 0 To No, C/939 Political Resident, Bahrain. DaUA 2nd December 1940 A letter has been received aated the 25th 'hawwal 105P (25th KoveEher 1940) frorn Shaikh Abdu lis - ; bin ^assiift A1 Than!, Shaikh of Qatar, stating that he Intends to pro ceed on pilgrimage to Kecca. The date of his departure has not been Intimated. Enquiries are however being made by me and the result will be communicated. teqem Political Agent, Bahrain S. 6. MFP—400S&amp;P—(M 480)—26-7-34—2,00,000.5TV GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. D epartment. express letter receipt, with the same expedition as * save time and formalities it is worded and siyned as if it had been so despatched,] F rom Political Agent, Bahrain. ilj' To Political Resident, Bushire. ^ Doled • * C/974-l.a/5 15th December 1940 1' ^ In continuation of my Express letter No. C/939 dated the ^nd December 1940. 2. Information has now been received that the ?ule-. o^ Oatrr, Shaikh Abdullah bin A asim al Thanl has gone on pilgrimage to Mecca accompanied by the heir- apparent^Shaikh Famad^and some seventy members of his family and servants. He expects to be away approximately two months. The eldest son Ali is acting for his father. , , „ llC/ClU ,a^ Political Agent, Bahrain4 s. 6. MFP—400S&amp;P—{M-480)—26-7-34 2,00,000.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000d5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/240</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000d5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/240</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'14/7 (XVIII) and (XX) Arab Coast. Miscellaneous'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-11T00:15:17</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (61 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file. There are file notes at the back of the file explaining how the file is arranged.</extent><extent>Foliation: This consists of pencil numbers, located in the top right hand corner of the recto of each folio. The foliation sequence commences on the front cover and concludes on the last folio before the back cover.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials in Bushire, Bahrain, and Sharjah.Topics include:The visit of Lady Willingdon to Sharjah.A raid by Manasir tribe and murder of the Amir of Khan village.Diving on the Trucial Coast and measures to improve the living conditions of the divers. Includes translation of letters from Shaikh Sa'id bin Maktum, ruler of Dubai to the Residency Agent, Sharjah; and from Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain to Political Agent, Bahrain.The building of a fort by the Sheikh of Sharjah.A pilgrimage to Mecca by Sheikh Abdullah, Sheikh of Qatar (1940).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000d5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>