<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100040903645.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T19:30:00.218Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Confidential. r— i 4 S o B j i j ——- India 'n I; The Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to transmit the accompanying sections of printed confi dential correspondence. Foreign Office, , i A ■[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government,] i r B PERSIA. C 0 X E [ i)E i\ T F A L. [November 14.] Section 1. [51683] Sir L. Mallet to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 14.) (No. 921.) Sir, Constantinople, November 10, 1913. WITH reference to my telegram No. 559 of the 9th instant, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith copy of the draft protocol for the delimitation of the Turco- Persian frontier as initialled by the commissioners of the four Powers and recommended by them for the acceptance of their Governments. I should observe that the two Persian delegates affixed their initials to the draft as representatives of the Persian Embassy, as Ittila-ul-Mulk, who is to be first Persian commissioner, had not yet. received official notification of his nomination, and not as members of the Frontier Commission. I also enclose copy of the notes made by Mr. Wratislaw on the various meetings of the commissioners, and I think, except on one point, these notes will be found to afford sufficient explanation of the difierences, none of them of importance, between the present text and that forwarded to you in Mr. Marling’s despatch No. 883 of the 27th October. The exception to which I allude is the transfer for obvious reasons of part of article 1 4 and the whole of article 15 of the “ Reglement interieur ” to the body of the protocol, where it appears as article 8. It will be noted that the Turkish commissioners accepted our draft of article 8 and Annexe (B) relative to the rights of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company without insisting on a modification thereof in the sense of paragraph 7 of the Minister for Foreign Affairs’ note verbale of the 23rd September last, to the effect that the rights of the company should be maintained only to the north of the Elvend River. Provided the point is not raised by the Porte before the final signature of the protocol, the question as to the area of the company’s concession in Turkey will thus be left open. In the absence of any knowledge of the reply of the company to the letter from your Department of the 15th October, this appears to me to be a fairly satisfactory position. I shall be obliged if you will inform me by telegraph whether the present protocol meets with your approval, so that in the event of its being agreed to without modification by the Porte—and I have at present no reason to anticipate the contrary— I may be in a position to sign it as soon as my Russian and Persian colleagues are authorised to do so. A copy of the draft is being sent to Tehran by the Russian Embassy, and I would suggest that printed copies of it, if approved by yourself, should be sent to His Majesty’s Minister in that capital with as little delay as possible. I have, &amp;c. LOUIS MALLET. No. 1. ■ pi Enclosure 1 in No. 1. Mr. Wratislaw's Notes of Meetings of Frontier Delegates at Constantinople, November 1913. Constantinople, November 10, 1913. THE first meeting of the commission was held yesterday afternoon (the 3rd November) at the Turkish Ministry of Foreign Affairs. There were present besides myself M. Minorsky, Nazim-el-Mulk and Ittila-el-Mulk, on behalf of the Persian Embassy, and Behdjet Bey and Aziz Sami Bey, the Turkish commissioners. The two latter gentlemen displayed a quite serviceable knowledge of French. We read aloud the draft protocol, following the proposed frontier north of Mendeli on the reduced identic map as far as possible, the Turkish commissioners indicating the points on which they would have observations to make. At this afternoon’s meeting the Turks put forward their objections at greater length. They are as follows, beginning at the extreme north of the frontier near Ararat:— [1933 o—l] B &lt;n 5 DEC 191' Corv vc1. The Turkish commissioners consider that, instead of laying down that the water system of Yarym Kaya should be left to Persia, it would be better to les the Commission decide the line of frontier in this direction according to the status quo. Behdjet Bey explained that the protocol line is vague, and that the Ottoman Government does not understand whether certain villages existing in the locality will be given to Turkey or Persia. He added that if a locality called Sarnitch (not marked on our maps and consisting of a reservoir and pasturage) he awarded to Persia, the Turks will he cut off from their homage No. 37. 2. Kizil Kaya, or Belassour, is by the protocol to be given to Turkey or Persia, according as its position is found on the western or eastern slope. If given to Persia it will, according to Behdjet Bey, cut off the only carriage road between the Turkish towns of Van and Bayazid, which passes through the village in question. M. Minorsky, on behalf of his Government, declined to entertain either of these objections. The protocol line represented, he said, the status quo line of 1848, and indicated the maximum which could be conceded to Turkey. Sarnitch was not marked on the identic map, and the sketch map shown by Behdjet Bey could not be accepted as authoritative. 3. The Turks consider that the valley of the Abi Seri Gadyr (headwaters of the Biver Gadzr belonging to the Ushnon water system) should belong to Turkey as well as the valley of the Tchoumi Gueli, the basin of a river feeding the Lavene (Lahidjan). Both these localities should certainly be given to Persia, on the principle followed as far as possible throughout, viz., that the eastern watersheds go to Persia and the western to Turkey. It is further to be observed that in the case of the Tchoumi Gueli the Turkish contention contravenes a point they have already conceded, viz., that in that district the crest of the Kandil range is to be taken as the frontier. The fact, alleged by the Turks, that certain Turkish tribes at some seasons descend the eastern slope for pasturage does not, in our opinion, afford proof of Turkish possession. 4. With regard to Khan Guermela and the “ sixteen other villages ” of the Persian district of Nowsoud (Avroman) the Turks expressed fear lest some may have disappeared since the time of the first Commission, and that if the terms of the protocol stand the Commission may find itself obliged to hand over other innocent villages to Persia to make up the tale. To obviate this danger, if it exists, we undertook to recommend that the protocol should be modified as follows :— “. . . . laissant du cote persan le village de Khan Guermela et les seize autres villages qui du temps de la visite de la Commission de 1849-52 se trouvaient dans la possession persane.” 5. Both Turks and Persians, though for different reasons, drew attention to the vagueness of the frontier indicated by the protocol in the Zohab district south of the Elvend. ^ M. Minorsky and I agreed that the passage beginning “ elle coupe la riviere Elvend a un point,” and ending “ laissant a la Turquie le Nepthe Mukataassi,” requires amplification, and we propose to redraft it. Immediately preceding this passage there is also an omission, no mention being made of the frontier descending to the Turkish post of Kanobez. 6. The lurkish commissioners expressed a wish that the protocol should safeguard the proprietary rights of persons transferred from one sovereignty to the other. I see no objection to this. 7 -Fh e y a l so drew 7 our attention to the omission in the protocol of a provision (contained in the last paragraph of the memorandum of the Pussian Ambassador (Enclosure 2 in Sir G. Lowther’s despatch No. 352 of the 26th April, 1913) ), by which the Frontier Commission was to make an arrangement for the division of the water of the Ganguir Piver in Soumar between the Kelhour tribe and the inhabitants of Mendeli. This is presumably an accidental omission, and we promised to rectify it. The above Turkish objections are in the main the same as those raised already in the Porte’s identic note of the 23rd September, 1913. 1^ informed the other commissioners that His Majesty’s Government desired the insertion at the end of article 1 of the whole of the Anglo-Turkish Agreement of the 29th July, 1913, to which no one objected. As the Persian commissioners did not possess a copy, I gave them one. We all found the reduced identic map inconvenient to use owing to the omission oftilt tl, »g t» j, f K, _W%d rorPe; g f giTen stion, er of ^■*8, aol )e accept :ers of I Turkey as he Lavent e followed a and tk ! Tcliouii viz., tk The fact, le eastern e Persian appeared tand the '’ersia to protocol i autres dans la in to the i of the .a riviere requires ,ge there Turkish afeguari r, I see irovision bassador jy ^ r hich yater of tants of V it. v ready ^ lired the t of ^ did u°t so many names and the doubts which have been freely cast on its accuracy. My colleagues unanimously urged me to request that the original identic map might be photographed lull size in London, and a nmjiber of copies supplied for the use of the ^Commission. ; M. Minorsky tells me that the St. Petersburgh copy of the big map has been mislaid. He possesses a photographic reduction of it, but this is on too small a scale to be easily read, and the negatives have been unfortunately destroyed. The “ Reglement interieur ” is to be discussed to-morrow, and the Turkish commis sioners have undertaKen to submit their final observations on the protocol frontier the day after. A. C. WPATISLAW. November 4, 1913. Meeting of November 5, 1913. Ihe u Reglement interieur” was read and discussed at length. The commissioners adopted the following modifications of paragraph 3, article 1 — “ Le meme principe de parfaite egalite sera applique aux rapports entre eux taut des commissaires adjoints que des autres members des commissions remplissant des fonctions similaires.” Article 2.—Instead of “ La carte identique communiquee,” &amp;c., we propose to say, “la carte identique originale comnmniquee,” &amp;c., to prevent any possible confusion with the reduced map. Article 6 we propose should be modified as follows : “La Commission fera les arrangements necessaires pour les travanx du secretariat qui sera charge de la redaction des proces-verbaux et de tout autre travail que la Commission trouvera utile de lui confier. Les membres du secretariat assisteront aux reunions de la Commission.” Article 8.—We propose to add the following rules regarding the payment of the expenses connected with the erection of boundary works :— “ Les frais de construction seront approximativement fixes pour chaque etape par la Commission; la somme designee sera ensuite versee par moities par les commissaires ottoman et persan et sera depense sous le controle des Sous-Commissions prevues dans 1 article 9. La Commission tiendra une comptabilite en vue de la repartition finale des frais entre les deux Gouvernements. Article 14.—We propose to abolish the last paragraph of this article, as we consider it beyond our power to furnish unlimited copies of the identic map, while it is obviously not of the competence of the Frontier Commission to “ inviter les Gonvernements limitrophes k les distribuer parmi leurs fonctionnaires sur les frontieres. ” Article 16.—We consider that this article, if necessary, should rather be inserted in the body of the protocol itself than in the annexe containing the rules of procedure for the Commission. Behdjet Bey announced that he proposed to travel overland via Trebizond, Erzinjan, Diarbekir, and Bagdad. Should he not arrive in time, Aziz Sami Bey would act as .First Ottoman Commissioner in his absence as provided in article 3 of the “ Leglement interieur.” November 5, 1913. A. C. WEATISLAW. Meeting of November 6, 1913. The Turkish commissioners stated that they had taken the instructions of the Grand Vizier regarding the points raised by them in the meeting of the 4th November. Concerning Sarnitch (or Sarinj) and Kizil Kaya, they said that the Grand Vizier proposed to talk with the Russian Ambassador, who was to call on his Highness to-day. They would only remark that the road passing through Kizil Kaya was a route by which much Russian merchandise from the Caucasus reached the vilayet of Van, and that Russia was equally interested with Turkey in keeping the road open. •&lt; - 'M'-r-yWith regard to the district of Ab-i-Seri-Gadyr (Ushnou) and Tchoumi Gueli (Zahidjan) they suggested a deal. If the principle of the crests of the highest mountains were accepted for the above two localities, then apply it also to Khan Guermela in Avroman. ^ There is no equality whatever between the two sides of the proposed bargain. What the Turks propose to concede is almost uninhabited country, which does not belong to them, and the only value of which consists in occasional pasturage for nomad Kurds of theirs. The Khan Guermela district, on the other hand, is fertile and populated and is certainly Persian. If the crest of the main Avroman mountain is taken as frontier, Khan Guermela and its neighbourhood certainly, and probably Nowsoud, would pass into Turkish hands. Though on the western slope’they have throughout the negotiations been treated by the embassies as indubitably Persian, M. Minorsky and I feel that it would be a s very strong measure to transfer them with a stroke of the pen to Turkey at this time of day, though we think it might be advantageous to make some concession to the Turks in this region in order to settle the other disputed points. I therefore proposed the following as a possible modification of the passage in the protocol referring 10 this district :— • ... la frontiere continue a suivre la crdte magistrale jusqu’a sa ramification du cote ouest s’elevant au nord de la vallee de Dere Youli et laisse du cote persan les villages de Khan Guermela et de Nowsoud. La Commission decidera sur les lieux le sort des autres villages du sud d’Avroman en prenant exceptionnellement en considera tion les changements qui out pu se produire entre les annees 1848 et 1905 et les interets locaux. La frontiere rejoint la riviere de Sirvan ” the Persian commissioners accepted this, though asserting that they knew that the result would be the cession to Turkey of the sixteen Khan Guermela villages ; but the lurks stuck out for the principle of the highest crests, and we could not come to terms. The question is left open until our next meeting on the 8th (to-morrow is a Friday and a dies non) and I would suggest that the embassy should now intervene. This seems the only point left unsettled, unless the Turks spring some fresh objections on us on Saturday. At the previous meeting I had drawn the attention of the Turkish commissioners to Annexe (B) of the protocol (rights of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company in the transferred territories), which they had not read, and which they appeared to consider as not their concern. lo-day Aziz Sami Bey told me that he had ascertained that it was Iready accepted “ in principle,” but that he supposed that there was no intention of . company “ creating an oil regie in Turkey.” I said that there was no such intention. November 7, 1913. A. C. WBATISLAW. Meeting of November 8, 1913. It was agreed that Sarmitch (Saring) should be in Persia. With regard to Kizil Ip ay a, it was agreed that if a section of the Van-Bayazid road passing through or near that village should fall outside Turkish territory the Turks should have free passage for mei chandise and passengers through it, but not for troops or military convoys. .It was agreed that the districts of Tchourmi Gueli and Abi-seri-Guerdir should be given to Persia, but that the existing pasturage rights of Turkish Kurds in those districts should be maintained. We adopted a formula for the delimitation by the Commission of the district between Avroman and the Sirvan, preserving the Khan Guermela and Nowsoud to Persia, but foreshadowing advantages to Turkey not provided in the draft protocol. A fair copy of the protocol with the modifications proposed by the Commission is being prepared, and will, I hope, be initialled by the commissioners to-morrow morning. Behdjet Bey announced that for family reasons he would be unable to accoronaziv the Commission in its work on the frontier. Who his successor is to be we have not yet heard. November 8, 1913. A. C. WBATISLAW.[51491] No. 2. Sh' Edward Grey to Sir L. Mallet. (No. 534.) (Telegraphic.) R. Foreign Office, November 13, 1913. YOUR telegram No. 567 of 12tli November : Turco-Persian frontier. Mr. Wratislaw has explained changes in protocol, &amp;c., which yon may sign. I presume Persian Ambassador has authority to sign, and, if not, you should communicate direct with Sir W. Townley. There is a slight inaccuracy in line 5 of paragraph 2 of declaration of 29th July, 1913, which should read “longitude 47° 45V’ not “45°.” This is an obvious slip, as may be seen by reference to annexed map, and it may be more prudent not to suggest alteration in protocol. [1933 n—4] Cory tc 5 D&amp;C 19^3 j [This Document is the Property of Kis Britannic Majesty's Govemmeat,} PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [November 13.] Section 4- [51583] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Sir L. Mallet. (No. 533.) _ (Telegraphic.) R. Foreign O ffice, November 13, 1913. YOUR despatch No. 883 and my despatch No. 345. Anglo-Persian Oil Company write as follows :— “ It is understood that from Mendali to Hawizeh it will be left to the Boundary Commission to determine the true frontier. If, in course of demarcation, commissioners should find it expedient to concede to Turkey any areas to the east of the line which they may hold to be the status quo frontier, company suggest that it would be reason able to ask the Porte to admit that these areas should be' included in the transferred territory in which the company’s rights will be recognised and maintained, or, failing this, and as quid pro quo, that the company should have the right to lay pipes from any of their workings, present or future, within Persian territory, to a convenient position for export in Turkish territory.” (End of R.) As the Annex B to protocol is now worded, I understand that such areas would be regarded as transferred territory, and that Turkish Government have, inadvertently perhaps, allowed former restriction, confining transferred territories to country north of El vend, to lapse. Your Excellency should not mention the point to Turkish Government now, but if they themselves raise question of reviving earlier proposed restriction, your Excellency should strongly oppose such restriction, which would be most objectionable.Property, of His Britanmc Majesty’s Government] 1 PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [52590 Suction 2 No. 1, Sir VP. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November ]9.) (No. 394.) (Telegraphic.) R. Tehran, November 19, 1913. 4OUR telegram No. 402 of 18th November: Turco-Persian frontier. The Minister for Foreign Affairs has returned, and I will discuss the matter contained in the second paragraph with his Excellency as soon as possible. I very much regret that I did not understand that the signature of the Anglo- Turkish Shatt-el-Arab Convention was still confidential. It has formed the subject of comment here ever since a somewhat detailed account of the conditions it contains appeared in the press some months ago. I know that the Minister for Foreign Affairs at that time twitted the Cabinet with having refused us the lighting, buoying, and police rights in the Gulf that Turkey had accorded. [1933 t—2]ETfcis Document is tlie Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government,} PERSIA. 013 ls f oV6mlroT IS.j CONFIDENTIAL. Section 6 , [52466] No. I. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 18.) (No. 391.) (Telegraphic.) R. Tehran, November 18, 1913. MY telegram No. 389 of 16th November: Turco-Persian frontier. Persian reply to joint note has been received, and appears to me quite satisfactory. It makes the same reserves as to the navigation of the Shatt-el-Arab as were made to us verbally, and also expresses a hope that special attention will be paid to the question of migratoiy tribes in Zohab district. Stress is laid on the good results to be anticipated from arbitration of the Anglo-Russian commissioners on points about which the Persian and Turkish commissioners may be unable to agree. (Sent to Constantinople.) 1933 s—6 | 1 Copy v' | * 19 DEC 1913 J 19 DEC 1913[This Dooinnciit is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] ^ PERSIA. GOMFIDEXTIAL. [52296] Section 2. No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Sir L. Mallet. Foreign Office, November 18, 1913. (No. 544.) (Telegraphic.) R. YOUR telegram No. 578 of 17th November. I heartily congratulate your Excellency on the successful termination of these negotiations, which 1 attribute largely to your action in the past month. It is particularly gratifying that the Persian Ambassador has made no reservations. (Repeated to Tehran, No. 466, and St'. Petersburgh, No. 756.) [1933 . 5 — 2 ] r .. 15 ^ 19 PEC 1913 190EC1913 , ;[This Bocnment is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government,] ■v PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL [No^grbeigT .j Section 15 [52296] No. 1. Sir L. Mallet to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 17.) (No. 578.) _ (Telegraphic) R. Constantinople, November 17, 1$]'.). PROTOCOL signed to-day. Persian Ambassador making no reserves. [1933 r—15] 1 Copy tc ; ' 19 TEC 1913 ■ J. 9 DEC I?'' 4 k[This Document is the Property, of His Britannia Majesty’s Government.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL [56093] [December 12.] Section 1, No. 1. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received December 12.) (No. 413.) (Telegraphic.) R. 1 Tehran, December 12, 1913. MY telegram No. 411 of 8th December : Turco-Persian frontier. Persian Frontier Commission started to-day. [1967 m—1] Y 1 ' Nil Copy to fnd’a 9 JAN 1914CONFIDENTIAL. Sir L. Mallet to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received December 10, 9 - 30 p.m.) Constantinople, December 10, 1913. (No. 612.) R. (December 10, 8*25 p.m.) YOUR telegram No. 567 Turkish Commission is reported to have reached Aleppo. Instructions are being sent to expedite their journey so as to reach Mohammerah before 26th December. They ought to arrive in good time.CONKJDKNTIAL. i Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley (Tehran). (No. 481.) R. Foreign Office, December 9, 1913, 12*25 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 411 of Sth December: Turco-Persian frontier. May I understand that Persian Commission is now provided witb funds adequate for expenses, say, for three months, and that Anglo-Russian advance will, for the present, be unnecessary, except to provide boundary pillars ? Please inform Mr. Wratislaw, either through Bushire or Basra, of movements of Persian Commission. 11279—146]CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir L. Mallet (Constantinople). (No. 567.) R. Foreign Office, December 9, 1913, 12.30 p.m. TURCO-PERSIAN frontier. Sir W. Townley reports that Persian Commission shonld reach Mohammerah by 26th December (n.s.). Are you satisfied that Turkish Commission will arrive by date arranged ? Delay would of course be very inconvenient.CONFIDENTIAL. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received December 8, 1T5 p.m.) Tehran, December 8, 1913. (No. 411.) R. (December 8, 1*45 p.m.) YOUR telegram No. 477 of 5th December : Turco-Persian frontier. All financial difficulties connected with the departure of the Commission are arranged. In consequence of the Moharrem it will not he possible to get members off before Thursday. I am promised that they shall start on that date. They will go via; Bagdad, as the Ahwaz road may be blocked by snow, and will travel by motor part of the way. They should reach Mohammerah about 26th December.L*G i i is the Property of His BritaMfl^Majesty’s Government.! PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. £ Lf-QCfo L-rf&lt;rb $Oi [November 27.] Section 1, [53732] No. 1. Sir W. Towniey to Sir Edward Gh'ey.—(Received November 27.) (No. 401.) (Telegraphic.) Decode. f 4^ : Tehran, November 27, 1913. WITH reference to your telegram No. 470 of 25th November: Turco-Persian frontier. I have not yet received promised details of camp equipment, but have been assured that there will be no delay at Mohammerah, and that I shall receive list immediately. Persian Commission will be composed of Itala Mulk, first commissioner ; Mansur Sultaneh, assistant commissioner; Yamin Nezam, military adviser ; Mirza Abdurrazzak Khan, engineer, with two assistants ; Mirza Nasrullah Khan, secretary ; Dr. Hussein Khan, medical officer. I will continue to press for their immediate departure from Tehran. [1933 dd—l\ XCONFIDENTIAL. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 28.) Tehran, November 28, 1913. (No. 403.) Decode. J (November 28.) YOUR telegram No. 470 of 25th November: Turco-Persian frontier. Detailed list of camp equipment required by Persian commission telegraphed to India to-day. Am arranging with Treasurer-General regarding repayment. o r'- tr 5 DEC 1913 1 DEC 1913 ,-CONFIDENTIAL, Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley (Tehran). (No. 470) R. Foreign Office, November 25, 1913, 1'55 p.m. 'YOUR telegram No. 389 of 16th November : Turco-Persian frontier. I am still awaiting list of equipment promised on 18th November. Have you telegraphed this direct to India, and, if so, what arrangement have you made as to repayment? • • p Are Persian Government making necessary arrangements tor provision ot transport for their commission at Mohammerah ? _ . . Please take every possible measure to avoid delay in labours ot commissions owing to failure of Persian Government to supply what is required. (Repeated to Constantinople, No. 553, and St. Petersburgh, No. 761.) 2 € —&lt;/ [1177—419][Tills Document is the Property of His’Britannic Majesty s Government] PERSIA. [November 17.] CONFIDENTIAL. -&gt; [ 52062 ] No. 1. (No. 230.) Sir, Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey .—(Received November 17.) Tehran, October 27, 1913. I HAVE the honour to transmit to yon herewith copies of a joint note which the Russian Charge d’Affaires and I handed to the Prime Minister this afternoon upon the subject of the' arrangement reached at Constantinople settling in principle the long standing question of the Turco-Persian frontier, and of an aide-memoire in which we recapitulated the special matters calling for urgent attention outside the actual frontier question. We did not consider it necessary to communicate copies of the several documents bearing upon the question in our possession, because we had reason to know that the Persian Government is already possessed of all these papers. We enquired of Ala-es-Sultaneh, in handing his Highness the joint note, if the Persian Government had received copies of all the necessary documents, offering to supply supplementary information, should such be wanted. We pressed most urgently upon Ala-es-Sultaneh the advantage of agreeing at once to the arrangement reached, and we pointed out that Persia had secured a most satisfactory settlement of an old and thorny question that had often threatened serious danger m the past, and which might be counted upon to be a still greater cause for anxiety in the future, if this excellent opportunity for settling it was allowed to escape. . . Ala-es-Sultaneh replied that the question was at this moment receiving the serious attention of a special commission. His Highness added that it was true that Persia acquired a large portion of the disputed territory in some parts of the frontier, but he pointed out that in other parts she lost large tracts of territory that had been considered her undoubted possession for centuries. After some further conversation, he went on to say that the Persian Government was fully alive to the great importance of settling this century-old question, and gave us to understand that the arrangement would be accepted in principle, although it is probable that some reserves will be made m the reply to our note, which we are promised at an early date. _ The Prime Minister further authorised us to report that it had been decided to appoint Ehtesham-es-Sultaneh commissioner, with Ettila-ul-Mulk as assistant commissioner, and that a sum of 21,000 tomans (say 4,000L) had been voted for the expenses of the Commission. The fact that commissioners had been chosen and a sum of money voted for the requirements of the Commission would appear to furnish good proof that the Persian Government has practically decided to adhere to the arrangement made at Constantinople. We urged upon Ala-es-Sultaneh the great importance of the Persian commissioners reaching Mohammerah not later than the 15th December. His Highness took note of this, and asked when the British and Russian commissioners were leaving Constantinople. M. Sabline was in a position to reply that Mr. Wratislaw and M. Minorsky had arranged to sail from Constantinople on the 16th November. Ala-es-Sultaneh promised that the several points contained in the aide-memoire should receive early and favourable attention. LE Couvernement Imperial de Perse se trouve deja en possession de toutes les pieces relatives a la question de la delimitation de la frontiere turco-persane, qui, d’apres 1’avis des soussignes, pent etre a present consideree comme resolue en Les soussignes expriment le ferme espoir que le Gouvernement persan, ayant pns I have, &amp;c. WALTER TOWNLEY. Enclosure 1 in No. 1. Joint Letter addressed to Persian Prime Minister. M. le President du Conseil, Teheran, le 27 octobre, 1913. [1933 r—1][This Doctunent is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Goywamont. ] 1 PERSIA. 1 ''=&gt; r ~ Section 1. [November 6.] CONFIDENTIAL. [50457] '• Sir W. Townley to Sir Edivard Grey.—(Received November G.) TURCO-PERSIAN frontier. . My Russian colleague and I have again urged the point raised m your telegram No. 452 of 3rd November and preceding telegrams on the Prime Minister. His Highness explained that the Ambassador’s appointment as First Commissioner had been with drawn because the Turks have appointed a man of much inferior grade as their r irst Commissioner. We urged that Ittila-ul-Mulk should be at once given the necessary full powers to act as a commissioner, even if subsequently someone else is appointed First Commissioner. His Highness promised to endeavour to arrange this, and assured us that all would be arranged by Monday at the latest. (Sent to Constantinople.) [1933 /—l][Tills Document is the Property of His Britannia Majes: PERSIA. ■ [November 3.J CONFIDENTIAL. Section 4. [49780] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Sir L. Mallet. (No. 512.) (Telegraphic.) R. Foreign Office, November 3, 1913. YOUR despatch No. 883 of 27th October : Turco-Persian frontier. I approve the draft of protocol. It is of course essential that the whole of the London declaration of 29th July, 1913, should be embodied in the protocol, and that part relating to Shatt-el-Arab frontier should not be omitted, as previously desired by Russian Ambassador, whose Government have agreed to this line. As regards points (a), (6), and (c) in your despatch, I agree with you about (a) and (c), and I will leave (6) to the Commission. [1933 c—4] -* r Copy to tncna 2 a moV 1913[TMs Bocnmeiit tlie Prope rty of His B ritannic Majesty’s Government] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. v ^i U ‘S [November 3.] IT Secttion 3. No. 1. [50015] Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley. /TVleOTaohicO R. Foreign Office, November 3, 1913. ^ SIR L MALLET’S telegram No. 534 of 1st November : Turco-Persian frontier. If Persian Ambassador is left without instructions Commissions will not get to work by appointed date. You should urge necessity of immediate action. (Repeated to Constantinople, No. 513.) [1933 c—3][This Dociimeiit is the Property cf His Britannic Majesty’s Government] %J PERSIA. [November 3.J CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2. [49673] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley. (No. 450.) (Telegraphic.) R. Foreign Office, November 3, 1913. YOUR telegram No. 377 of 1st November: Tnrco-Persian frontier. It is a little difficult to appreciate the argument of Prime Minister respecting suggested Persian concessions in the centre. In Zohab Persia would, under the suggested settlement, obtain on the whole more than was awarded to her under the Mediating Commissioners’ line of 1852, though that line has been modified for Persia’s advantage, more especially so as to secure to her continued possession of_ Kasr-i-Shirin town. You should explain this to Prime Minister, and inform his Highness that I know of no unduly large concessions to be made by Persia. [1933 c—2][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] % : ^ J w PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [November 2.] Section 1, [49762] No 1. /Sir L. Mallet to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 2.) (No. 537.) _ (Telegraphic.) R. Constantinople, November 2, 1913. TURCO-PERSlAN frontier. Russian Ambassador strongly objects to attaching a map to the protocol on ground that line is more clearly described in protocol than in map, which is vague in some places. He fears that this may give rise to confusion and to possible difficulties with Turkish commissioners. British and Russian commissioners think that description in protocol is sufficient. In these circumstances am I to insist on map P [1933 6—1] ,•^7 Copy to 2 a nov 1913 B I[Tins Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] I HAVE the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 15th October, 1913, regarding the- reply of the Porte to the identic notes respecting the Turco- Persian frontier. My Directors note with satisfaction that the Turkish Government are prepared fully to recognise the rights of this company in any districts that may be transferred from Persia to Turkey north of the Kiver Elvend. This recognition, coupled with the right to construct pipe-lines in Turkish territory, should sufficiently safeguard the company’s interests so far as regards the oilfiefd in the neighbourhood of Kasr-i- Shirin and Chiah Sourkh. With respect to the country south of the Elvend, so far as my Directors can ascertain, there are at least four localities in which there are good prospects of finding oil. Three of these are Deh Luran in the south of the Pusht-i-Kuh, Tangi-Shashra in the hills east of the Gilan Plain, and, further north, Tangab, near the Tangi Gilan. The fourth, and by far the most important locality of all, is the Tangi Saumur and the surrounding hills immediately facing the Turkish town and district of Mandali. From all the accounts they have received, my board consider this tract is likely to be of great value as an oil-bearing district, and they attach a high degree of importance to j the maintenance in it of the rights granted to them by their concession. It has been | visited by Mr. Reynolds on behalf of Mr. d’Arcy and also by Mr Soane. The former was of opinion that probably the most valuable part of this oilfield may prove to be that which lies at present on the Persian side of the border, and if there were any likelihood of the transfer to Turkey of the Persian area, my Directors would feel it their duty to press strongly for the recognition of their interest in it. But from the War Office map and draft protocol, which I have been permitted to see, it is clear that from Kasr-i-Shirin to a point south of Mandali (Djebel Guarebi) the frontier-line laid down for the Boundary Commissioners to follow, as representing the status quo for which the Turks contend, will not seriously infringe any of this company’s rights. My board therefore are willing to agree to the restriction which the Porte wish to impose south of the River Elvend. It is understood that from Mandali (Djebel Guarebi) to Hawizah it will be left to the Boundary Commission to determine the true frontier. But if in the course of their demarcation the Boundary Commissioners should find it expedient to concede to Turkey any areas to the east of the line which they may hold to be the status quo frontier I suggest that it would be reasonable to ask the Porte to admit that these areas should be included in the “ transferred ” territory, in which the company’s rights will be recognised and maintained, or that failing an agreement to this effect the Porte should be requested, as suggested in the final paragraph of your letter, to grant the company, as a quid pro quo, the right to lay pipes from any of their workings, present PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2. [51583] No. 1. Anglo-Persian Oil Company to Foreign Office—(Received November 13.) (Confidential.) Sir, Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, November 12, 1913. or future, within Persian territory to a convenient position for export in Turkish territory. I have, &amp;c. C. GREEN WAY, Managing Director. [1933 n —2]PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [November l.J Section 2- [49673] No. 1. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 1.) (No. 377.) (Telegraphic.) R. Tehran, November 1, 1913. YOUR telegram No. 447 of 29th October: Torco-Persian frontier. Prime Minister informs me that the Persian Government is fully alive to the importance of settling the frontier question, and that it is not intended to raise any difficulties of a nature to delay the labours of the Delimitation Commission. His Highness assured me that the matter would be settled in a week, and gave me to understand that the arrangement reached would be accepted in principle. He said that he could not at present specify the points where Persia appeared to make unduly large concessions, but on broad lines she is called upon to concede much in the centre in return for advantages secured in the south and north. His Highness added that Persia was truly grateful to the two mediatory Powers, and fully recognised that it was entirely due to their efforts that it had been possible to reach an arrangement. Money voted is, he said, available, and more will be found. [1933 a —2] li i 21 NOV 1913[This Document ia the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Gover^^ent.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. | . [November 1.] Section 1, [50015] No. 1. Sir L. Mallet to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 1.) (No. 534.) (Telegraphic.) R. ^ Constantinople, November 1, 1913. IT has been arranged that preliminary meeting of Frontier Commission shall be held on 3rd November to discuss rules of procedure. Turkish commissioners have been appointed, but Persian Ambassador says that he has received no information as to who first Persian commissioner will be. Ittila-ul-Mulk will attend meeting on 3rd November as delegate of Persian Embassy. [1933 a—1] if✓ [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] PERSIA. f •&gt; \; j * ^ w y j O -.... [Oataber 31. j CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2. Ill [49536] No. 1. (No 533 ) '^ n ' ^ Mallet to Sir Howard Grey.—(Received October 31.) (Teiegraptic.) R. ^ ^ i Constantinople, October 31, 1913. MW? telegram No. 375 of 28th October : Turco-Persian frontier. be chie 1 !:' Persian frontfer^mm^ssioner. ^ &gt;erSlan Ambassador, who denied that he would He introduced to Mr. Wratislaw as members of Persian Frontier Commission the second and third Persian members of the Constantinople Commission. The former wou presumably be acting as chief commissioner, as he is senior to Itala-ul-Mulk I “'*” Mr ' &gt;■» .n—» Russk^steamer 11 Ainl:)assador states tilat the Persian Commission would leave by M. Minorsky is expected to arrive to-day. (Sent to Tehran.) [1898 hh—2] — C'O O’;' V[This Document is tlia Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] i j Q o U PERSIA. [ I. {jOctobbr 29.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2. [49098] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley. (No. 447.) (Telegraphic.) R. Foreign Office, October 29, 1913. YOUR telegram No. 375 of 28th October : Tnrco-Persian frontier. What arguments do you propose to use to Persian Government respecting their supposed cession of territory ? You should ascertain at once what locality is referred to and telegraph for information respecting any points as to which, after consulting your archives, you are in doubt, as expedition is most necessary. Will 21,000 tomans be really available and adequate ? If not, what action do you propose ? [1898 ff —2] \ i! 21N0V1813 DTP K /,&gt; f Co to indfa i «. 21 NOV 1913CONFIDENTIAL. Hi* L k : T vJ Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 16, 9’45 p.m.) (November 16, 1913, 8T5 p.m.) Tehran, November 16, 1913. (No. 389. Urgent.) R. YOUR telegram No. 459 Itala Mulk has been appointed Persian commissioner. His assistant commissipner and military adviser will be named at once and will proceed to Mohammerah direct from here. _ n i 21,500 tomans were telegraphed to Constantinople on Friday. Treasurer-Oeneral would welcome a loan of 10,0001. for expenses of Commission. _ Detailed list of equipment required for Persian Commission from India will be supplied on Tuesday. _ . . Persian Ambassador at Constantinople has been authorised to sign final protocol with reserve that Persia maintains her old rights of navigation on Shatt-el-Arab. Attention of Delimitation Commission has also been called to great importance of reaching a satisfactory solution of question of migratory tribes on frontier in Zohab district. We are promised an answer to our joint note and aide-memoire in above sense on Tuesday ; all the points raised in them here accepted. I pointed out that first article of Anglo-Turkish Agreement signed on 29th July declared navigation on Shatt-el-Arab open to ships of all nations, but I did not go more deeply into the question as I am not aware of nature of answer returned to the point i raised by Mr. Marling in his despatch No. 798 of 17th September with reference to levy of dues on Persian shipping by Conservancy Commission being possibly contrary to article 2 of Treaty of Erzeroum. _ _ . r • v Persian Government have raised navigation question because frontier line now follows the Persian coast instead of as formerly passing down the middle of the river. Final decision was reached to-day ; we have been pressing various authorities daily. (Repeated to Constantinople.) [1177—262]Put awry with CONFIDENTIAL. ‘I 3 S' &gt;/ Sir L. Mallet to Sir hJdward Grey.—(Received November 12, 7 p.m.) Constantinople^ November 12, 1913. (No. 567.) R. (November 12, 5’25 p.m.) RUSSIAN Ambassador is anxious that protocol on Turco-Persian frontier should be signed on Saturday. British delegate, who will call at Foreign Office on Thursday morning, will be able to explain a few changes which have been adopted. Actual text should arrive in London on Thursday evening. If you approve I should be glad of your authority to sign. I 1 II IS T 1 A v iV'- [A/ 14N0V1913- COPY TQ' INDIA '&lt;f A.j . r , j y j [1177—211] Ni&lt;-* 7 CONFIDENTIAL. •Si?’ hi (heard Grey to Sir W. Townley {Tehran). (No. 4f)9. Urgent.) lx. Foreign Office, November 13, 1913, 6*5 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 382 of 5th November: Turco-Persian frontier. Russian Government state that Persian commissioner has not yet been appointed, and that delay is due to lack of funds. I understood, however, from your telegrams Nos. 375 and 377 that money was available, and, if this so, you should urge that it should be telegraphed to Constantinople at once. Russian Government point out that money will be required in any case for erection of boundary marks, and they suggest that they and His Majesty’s Government should advance 10,OOOL in equal moieties for this purpose and for payment of Persian commissioner if funds are not otherwise forthcoming. I am considering this, but in the meantime you should strongly support your Russian colleague, who has been instructed to press urgently for appointment of Ittila-ul-Mulk as commissioner so that he may leave Constantinople by steamer of 18th November, and you should report the result of your action immediately. Russian Government also suggest that Persian Government should be induced to request His Majesty’s Government to furnish equipment for Persian commissioner from India. If this is desired by Persian Government, detailed request should be made at once, as time is very short. (Repeated to Constantinople, No. 535, and St. Petersburgh, No. 744.) Copy to !nd*a ^, fcftNOV 1913 [ 1177 - 226 ] - ' .V?.r W -CONFIDENTIAL. !I9 Sir Edward Grey to Sir L. Mallet (Constantinople). (N°. 534.) R. Foreign Office, November 13, 1913, 5’25 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 567 Mr. Wratislaw lias explained changes in protocol, &amp;c., which you may sign. I Foreign Office, November 13, 1913, 5’25 p.m. presume Persian Ambassador has authority to sign, and, if not, you should communicate direct with bir W. Townley. There is a slight inaccuracy in line 5 of paragraph 2 of declaration of 29th July 1913, which should read “longitude 47° 45',’’ not “45°.”' This is an obvious slip, as may be seen by reference to annexed map, and it may be more prudent not to suggest alteration in protocol. (1177—239]? i \'x Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government] \W fzfj PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. i •5 -V'’ t sisa* [October 29.] Section 1. [49098] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Mr. O’Beirne. (No. 727.) (Telegraphic.) R.~ Foreign Office, October 29, 1913. SIR W. TOWNLEY’S telegram No. 375 of 28th October : Turco-Persian frontier. Persian answer is not at all satisfactory, and I consider that Sir W. Townley, who is in possession of detailed information and all historical documents, should, in concert with his Russian colleague, endeavour, before written answer to joint note is sent, to dissipate Persian objections to settlement proposed, which is demonstrably favourable to Persia. Otherwise there will be delay, and it is doubtful if work can be started on date proposed. Ask Russian Government to instruct Russian Minister at Tehran to co-operate as suggested. (Repeated to Tehran, No. 446, and Constantinople, No. 501.) [1898 ff-1] |Cory to { l i t\ 0 « 1St3[This Docnment is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government,] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. rOctober 28 Section 1 [49098 No. 1. Tehran, October 28, 1913. and Sir W. Towniey to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received October 28.) (No. 375.) _ (Telegraphic.) R. TURCO-PERSIAN frontier. Your telegram No. 439 of 20th October. My Russian colleague and I presented a joint note yesterday to the Prime Minister, urged on his Highness the importance of the Persian Government agreeing at once to the arrangement made at Constantinople and losing no time in naming the Commission to represent Persia on the frontier. Ala-es-Sultaneh replied that the question was already occupying the serious attention of a special commission, and attempted to show that Persia was called on to surrender a large amount of territory that she had for long legitimately considered as hers. After some conversation the Prime Minister authorised us to report that it had been decided to name Ehtesham-es-Sultaneh commissioner and Ittila-ul-Mulk assistant- commissioner. His Highness also said that 21,000 tomans had been voted for expenses of the Commission, took note of the fact that commissioners must be at Mohammerah not later than 15th December, and promised us an early answer to our joint note. [1898 ee — 1] Copy t &gt;.r to uie’al J _ * *«r\'■* PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL No. 1. [48041] Sir Edward Grey to Sir TP. (Telegraphic.) Foreign Office, October 20, 1913. RUSSIAN Government appear to consider that some delay is attributable to inaction of His Majesty’s Legation in pressing Persian Government to agree to arrangement arrived at respecting r l urco-Persian frontier, and to settle necessary details for assembly of Persian delegates at Mohammerah in December. If you are only waiting for the text of the Turkish reply to the Anglo-Russian notes of 5th (18th) August, you should ask Mr. Marling to repeat to you the telegram which you received in a mutilated form. . # You are aware of the importance we attach to expedition. Please do everything to get everything settled with least possible delay. [1898 u—Lk| f: Copy to 14 NOV 1913In any further eomaiunisa- tion on this subject, please quote No '- and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for vv ^ ,r —■&gt; and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop\s^&gt; of the under-mentioned paper? Foreign Office, o * tQS Reference to previous letter: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject 3. ''vwv-v, ■ l to , 5!j&gt; f IvnJV- C 4 kUv . 9 w ' L r ! Oo. £ L Saxx-j^f ll'O $V~G ^ COPY .TO INDIA 1T F'S f cAN r 121 || ll 'i*lCypher telegram to Sir L* Vallet, (Constantinople) Foreign Office, November 8th, 1913* 8.0. p.m. No. 526. Your telegram No. 545. Flease Inform your Pussian colleagise that I find l identic Mf can be reproduced and ten eopliS pro vided, by the middle of December at an approximate cost of £230. An orde^ has been placed for this to be done, and In due course a statement of the cost will be furnished to the Fuselan Ooveroment, who T presume will bear half the cost. The maps will be se^t direct to Mohammerah.Copy Fomou OFFICE, rth Move'iber, 1913. Urge lit. (50546/1913) Sir: I am dULrected s i Secretary Sir V.. 'vey to acicnowledge the receipt of your letter of the 6th instant in Which you submit an approximate estimate of the cost of a photographic reproduction of what is known as the ’’identic map' 1 of the i utxo -Persian frontier. I am to state that sir E. Grey accepts your estimate of £230 for the supply of ten copies, pro vided you will undertake to deliver them not later than the 4th proximo, and on the understanding that you will furnish another 15 copies, if subsequently required, at un additional cost of £338* The original map is in the cus' ody of vhc Librarian of this Department and will be placed at your disposal on the morning of the 10th instant. c., (3 ± gned) W. Lang1ey The Secretary, Anglo-Engraving Company Lrnited Milford Lane, Strand, W.C..0646) MILFORD LANE, STRAND, W.C. 6th November,1913* Gentlemen:- We thank you for your esteemed enquiry for supplying photographic copies of sixteen coloured maps and 15 pages of writing* We would propose photographing each of these originals and making enlargements to the sizes of the drawings. We have pleasure in giving you as requested an approximate estimate for the work. To supplying 10 copies each of the 31 originals £230.0.0 and 25 copies of each 458.0.0 We would use isochromatic plates in order to get the varied colour matters upon the originals. Trusting we may hear further from you upon this matter we are &amp;c.. The Anglo Engraving Company Limited. The Librarian’s Department, The Foreign Office, Whitehall, S.W.Offy IH3 C ON FI DEN T1AI Sit Tj. Mallet to Sit JUdwaTd Grey.—(Received NovembeT 4, 6’ 15 p.m.) _ . _ . Constantinople, NovembeT 4, 1913. °' TURCO-PERSIAN Frontier Commission. (November 4, 6'30 p.m.) British Commissioner informs me that he and his colleague consider it most desirable that the Commissions should be supplied with photographic reproductions of the^ original identic map. Reduced map is of doubtful accuracy, many names being oinitted. Exclusive use of one original map by so many will lead to loss of valuable time, and I would suggest that, if possible, identic map in possession of Foreign Office should be photographed and a number of copies supplied. 01 ifIB t\ •iliC'' 0 1 of! [1177-73] H :Cil 1 • ij ■ Viv ''ifrIn any further comamn^a- tion on this subject, please quote No * and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. id x v\ VI. V ' T/te Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^ of the under-mentioned paper? Foreign Office, So /ucrve^-^k &gt; IF3' Reference to previous letter: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. /Co • ? 33 'i? r fee c^ySx, (xXLtui ■ Js^ Sll. ^ ri2 ] • * j 4 NOVfStoo'oy. i Cypher telegram to Sir L. pallet (Constantinople) ’H' Foreign Office, November 3rd. 1913, 6.30 p. n. Mo.513. Your despatch No.883. I approve one draft of protocol; it is of course essential that the whole of the London declaration of July 29th. 1913 should be embodied in the protocol, and iue:i part relating to Shatt-el-Arab frontier should not be omitted as previously desired by Russian Ambassador, whose v G-overnment have agreed to this line As regards points a, b,and c, in your despatch, I agree pith you about a) and c) and I will leave point b) to the Commission. i TO j mi[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Govcrajnpnt ] (-fb b b PERSIA. [November 3.j CONPIDENTIAL. 9 Section 1. [49780] No. 1. Sir L. Mallet to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 3.) (No. 883.) Sir, Constantinople, October 27, 1913. WITH reference to Mr. Marling’s despatch No. 877 of the 22nd instant, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith the draft of the protocol respecting the Turco- Persian frontier to be signed by the representatives here of Great Britain, Russia, Turkey, and Persia. The draft—the preparation of which by M. Mandelstamm, the first dragoman of the Russian Embassy, under the instructions of M. de Giers, in consultation with this embassy, has been attended with very regrettable and rather inexplicable delay— commences with a recapitulation, so summary as to be scarcely more than an enumera tion of the recent stages of the negotiations, and then (article 1) gives a detailed description of the line of frontier so far as it has been agreed on; articles 2 and 3 provide for the constitution of the mixed Demarcation Commission under a “ Reglement interieur,” attached as an annex (A) to the protocol; while article 4 confers arbitral powers on the British and Russian commissioners. Articles 5 and 6 provide that, when any part of the line has been demarcated, such part shall be deemed to be definitely settled, and the two interested Powers may establish posts in such parts. The remaining article (7) concerns the recognition of the rights of the Anglo- Persian Oil Company in the transferred territories, more detailed and specific provision for which is made in a second annex (B) in the terms of the draft article approved by you. This decision of the draft article is not, I am aware, precisely what was contem plated, but M. de Giers points out that the article, when drafted, was intended to be signed by Turkey and Persia only ; and as the exact terms of the remainder of the article are reproduced in the annex, I think it better to fall in with my Russian colleague’s views rather than lose further time in redrafting the whole article, so as to make it suitable for signature by the representatives of all four Powers. As to the description of the frontier line, there are, I think, but three points which call for note in that part of the frontier that concerns us, viz., two (a) and (6) in that part of it which is in the neighbourhood of Zohab, and one (c) concerning the lands on the Khaivin Canal. (a.) In the extreme north of Zohab the frontier line after leaving the River Tchemiz Zerischk was described in the Turkish note of the 12th July as follows :— “ ensuite en suivant la ligne du partage des eaux entre ce dernier et la riviere qui apres avoir pris sa source a Bend Berno prend le nom d’Arhouandol, &amp;c , but as this latter name does not appear in the Identic Map which is to form the basis of the geographical work of the Commission, it was thought better to adopt the description given in the present draft. (6.) A material point left open in the Zohab district is the identity of the Moukataa of Neft, and it was thought as well by omitting any mention of the astronomical indications of its position to leave the question to the decision of the Commission. I note, moreover, that in the map prepared at the War Office and enclosed in your despatch No. 331 of the 9th instant, that the line is not drawn in accordance with the Turkish contention, so that I conclude that His Majesty’s Government are not prepared to concede the point. (c.) By the last paragraph of the declaration of the 29th July, the fate of certain lands on the Khaiyin Canal is reserved for the decision of the British and Ottoman commissioners. This provision has been omitted from the draft protocol, as it seems impossible, when the delimitation of the whole frontier is being confided to the com missioners of the four Powers, to withdraw one part of it from their decision and reserve it for the verdict of two of the commissioners, especially when of those two commissioners one does not represent a Power directly interested. [1933 c—1] 14N0V1S13 to lr?a?a MOV 1S13Put away^vith. [This Dociment is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government ] 3 PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [October 16.] Section 2. [44872] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling. (No. 345.) Sir, Foreign Office, October 16, 1913. I HAVE received your despatch No. 820 of the 25th ultimo, in which you comment on the Turkish reply to the Anglo-Russian identic notes concerning the Turco-Persian frontier. I am in communication with the Anglo-Persian Oil Company respecting their interests south of the Elvend River, and I enclose a copy of a letter addressed to them on the subject.* I shall be glad to learn whether you and your Russian colleague have yet com pleted the draft of the final protocol, on which you reported that you were about to engage in your telegram No. 471 of the It th September, and, if not, how soon you anticipate that it will be ready. Owing to the delay which has occurred, I am afraid it will now be impossible to submit the draft to preliminary discussion with Mr. Wratislaw at this Office before his departure, as I should have desired to see done. With regard to your reference to “an obvious slip of the pen ” concerning the latitude mentioned in the identic notes of the 5th (18th) August, I understand that the latitude quoted is based on the meridian of Ferro, and it was in consequence of this that I addressed to you my telegram No. 456 of the 12th September. As to the last two paragraphs of your despatch, I agree that the large identic map should be used as a basis for the work of demarcation, but you should inform your Russian colleague that some doubt exists on the part of expert authorities in this country as to the complete accuracy of this map, and it will probably require correction in the light of surveys on the spot. For this purpose the War Office map enclosed in my despatch No. 331 of the 9th October may be of use. In order to avoid all confusion, I wish to emphasise the fact that my proposal to annex one of the two maps mentioned in my despatch No. 331 to the final protocol was that this should be done not as a definition, but merely as an approximate illustration of the frontier. I am, &amp;c. E. GREY. * To Mr. Greenway, October 15, 1!H3.■T-t' h tt, P» pertr „ Hia M^i,^ , PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. ^ # o &gt; i J [October 13.] Section 1. No. 1. . Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marlinq. (No. 338.) J Foreign Office, October 13, 1913. I HAVE received your despatch No. 830 reporting that the Grand Vizier has confirmed to the Russian Ambassador the assurances given to you thrice previously, that he agrees to the proposal that the British and Russian delegates for the demarca tion of the Turco-Persian frontier shall be invested with power to arbitrate, and not merely mediate, in the case of differences of opinion between their Turkish and Persian colleagues. This assurance is satisfactory, but, in order to be of real value, it must necessarily take some more binding form than a merely verbal one, and I presume that the grant of arbitral powers to the British and Russian Commissioners will be recorded in the final protocol to lie drawn up at Constantinople. I am, &amp;c. E. GREY. [1898 n—1]nais Document is the Property of His Britannie Majesty’s fifwsmmpnt. ] w r Jj q m.?} ^1* / PERSIA. ! [October 6.] CONFIDENTIAL. [45376] Section 4. No. 1. Mr. Marlinq to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received October G.) (No. 830.) Sir, Constantinople, October 1, 1913. WITH reference to your despatch No. 290 of the 11th ultimo, I have the honour to report that the Grand Vizier has confirmed to the Russian Ambassador the assur ances which he had given me on three previous occasions that he agrees to the proposal that the British and Russian delegates for the demarcation of the Turco- Persian frontier shall be invested with power to arbitrate, and not merely mediate, in the case of differences of opinion between their Turkish and Persian colleagues. I have, &amp;c. CHARLES M. MARLING. [1898 /--4] % Copy to too-- \t\i *1 i v W* mi ' « &lt; iT f : &gt; of His Britannic Majesty ] r i i PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [44169] No. I. Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 29 ) (No. 8J2.) Sir, Constantinople, September 24, 1913. I HAVE the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your despatch No. 293 of the 15th instant, instructing me to take steps to obtain the consent of the Turkish Government to the free movement of the escort of the Turco-Persian Frontier Commission on the Turkish side of the frontier. I would venture to recall to your recollection that this point is mentioned in the draft of the “ Reglement interieur,” which I had the honour to transmit to you in my despatch No. 777 of the 6th instant. I should be glad to know whether you consider it necessary that this point should be provided for in some other manner, and whether the draft in question otherwise meets with your approval. I have, &amp;c. CHARLES M. MARLING. [1870 ff —3] . 24 Cony to Endia ‘24 CCT1813fThis Docnment is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government! f) PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [41101] No. 1 Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling. (No. 456.) (Telegraphic.) R. ^ ^ Foreign Office, September 12, 1913. YOUR telegram No. 456 of 6th September: Turco-Persian frontier. What maps do you refer to in last paragraph ? Is the whole frontier line shown approximately on them ? The War Office have without difficulty prepared, both on the reduced identic map and on Colonel Maunsell’s map, a tracing of the frontier as described in the corre spondence, and if M. Minorsky has traced the line it would be useful for War Office to have a copy, and you should send it home at once. Our maps will be manifolded and sent out to Constantinople within a month. It would be desirable that they should be annexed to final protocol, with a statement that they show the frontier merely approximately by way of illustration. Colonel Maunsell’s map, which contains additional features, will be communicated to Russian Government. Meridian of Greenwich, and not that of Ferro, was basis of identic map, and should preferably be adopted throughout labours of Commission. Urge this strongly upon your Russian colleague. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 658.) [1870 m —2] Copy to t t v V V a I W S^-1 Tile Indian Government and War Office combined, by insisting on the appointment of •, Lieut enant,“Colonel 4 and a Major of Royal Engineers, seem to have reverted to their original idea of having a fresh elaborate map of the whole frontier region prepared. Should this prove to bo the case, is the legitimate work of the Commission - which I toko go bt, the demarcation of the frontier - to have the first claim on these officers' services? In localities where agreement between the parties is secured one where the Identic Lap is obviously sufficient for the laying down with practical accuracy ol the frontier lint, there seems no utility (from the point of view of the Commission) in preparing a fresh map which vouiu cause delay• I foresee the possibility of a conflict between my views on the subject and the instructions with which the Engineer Officers may come provided, and I should like to know eaactly how I stand. (Signed) A.C. Wratisiaw. Foreign Office, October 7th, 1913. i hir[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government,! PERSIA. [October 15.] i CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. [44672] No. 1. Porte to the identic notes of the British and Russian Embassies at Constantinople respecting the Turco-Persian frontier, a point is raised which involves the interests of (Confidential.) Sir, Foreign Office to Mr. C. Greenway. fidential.) Foreign Office, October 15, 1913. I AM directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to inform you that, in the reply of the your company, and on which Sir E. Grey would therefore be glad to receive your observations. Section 7 of the Turkish note runs as follows : — It has, nevertheless been considered desirable in the interests of your company to Sourkh or Shemiran, the Turks have never demurred to the use of the words “ cession but it appears to be their aim to deny that any “ transfer ” can take place south of the Elvend ; and Sir E. Grey anticipates that there may be great difficulty in establishing the contrary. I am to enquire whether you are in possession of information as to. the value as an oil-bearing district of the regions in question, and what degree of importance you attach to obviating the above-mentioned restriction of the area in which your rights are to be recognised. Should the Anglo-Persian Oil Company desire to guard against such restriction, His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires at Constantinople submits that the desired end would be attained by inducing the Porte to agree to recording in a formal protocol to be signed at Constantinople before the work of the commission begins, the draft article which has already been accepted by the Grand Vizier. The assent of the Porte to such a step might be obtained; but Sir E. Grey is dubious as to the efficacy of the article, even so inserted, for the purpose in view, inasmuch as it leaves untouched the Porte s contention as to the distinction between transferred and reacquired territory. Sir E. Grey would be glad to receive any observations that your company may have to offer on this point. Failing this solution, Mr. Marling suggests that, to avoid delay, compensating advantages might be sought for your company on the following lines, thougn Sir E. Grey is doubtful if the Ottoman Government would recognise that your company had any valid title to claim them: in return for the acquiescence of His Majesty’s Government in the Turkish desideratum, it might be requested that the Anglo-Persian Oil Company shall have the right to lay pipes from any of their workings present or future within Persian territory to a convenient position for export in Turkish territory. Sir E. Grey understands that there are valuable od strata in South VTestern Persia which could not be worked profitably unless such access to the sea is provided. On this proposal of Mr. Marling I am also to request your observations. 1 am, &amp;c. EYRE A. CROWE. “Pour ce qui est des questions touchant TAnglo-Persian Oil Company, mentionnees dans la note precitee No. 108, le Gouvernement Imperial reconnait pour Tetendue du territoire qui lui revient au nord de la riviere Elvend la concession octroyee jadis par le Gouvernement persan a cette compagnie.” The Porte thus desires to confine its recognition of the rights of your company to the territories which are to be admittedly transferred by Persia to Turkey; or, in other words, the Turkish attitude would appear to be that the line put forward by them in the regions south of the Elvend involves no cession of territory to Turkey, but is merely the recognition of the status quo —a contention which is largely confirmed by independent testimony. It has, nevertheless been considered desirable in the interests of your company to obtain the recognition by Turkey of the view that a cession of territory has taken place, and the phrase “ territoires transferes ” is with this object expressly used in the draft article providing for the maintenance of your company’s rights, in which you concurred by your letter of the 23rd September. In regard to such districts as those of Chia [1898 p—l][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Governm&lt;in£ ] [B] PERSIA. o CONFIDENTIAL [44672] bu# ^ FCopy to l odisil [October lj y V • * ^ » vy Section 1. No. 1. Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey. — {Received, October 1.) (No. 820.) Sir, Constantinople, September 25, 1913. WITH reference to my telegram No. 483 of yesterday and my despatch No. 817 of this day’s date, I have the honour to offer the following observations on the reply from the Porte to the identic notes of the British and Russian Embassies of the 18th ultimo, on the subject of the Turco-Persian frontier. Taken as a whole, I agree with the Russian Ambassador that the note is not unsatisfactory ; that it is to be regretted that the Porte, under the influence of its litigious-minded Armenian legiste Hrant Effendi Abro, should have thought it necessary to raise again so many disputable points, even though it agrees to leave them, with the exception of the question of the area over which the Anglo-Persian Oil Company’s rights are to be recognised, to the decision of the Dehmitation Commission. . I will not attempt to offer any remarks on those portions of the note which refer to localities north of the Shirvan, but will confine myself to the points in which His Majesty’s Government are more immediately interested, namely, those that are treated of in section 7 of the note and Section 3 of the memorandum. ' By section 7 of the note the Porte desires to confine its recognition of the rights of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company to the territories which are to be admittedly transferred by Persia to Turkey. It is to be presumed that the desire to exclude the company from the territories south of Elvend River does not arise from mere anxiety to prove that the frontier about to be demarcated is the status quo frontier. On the contrary, it would, as I suggested in Sir G. Lowther’s despatch No. 546 of the 19th June last, seem more to the interest of the Government to be able to exaggerate their acquisitions of territory rather than to minimise them, and it seems probable that the Porte has knowledge of some rich petroleum-bearing deposits south of the Elvend, and desires to reserve in its own hands the power to dispose of them to some other group from which better terms could be extracted than from the Anglo-Persian Oil Company. The company may perhaps be in possession of information as to the value as an oil-bearing district of the regions in question, and may attach importance to not allowing the area to which their rights are to be recognised to be restricted as desired by the Porte. If so, I submit that the desired end would be attained by inducing the Porte to agree to the insertion in the final protocol, without any qualifica tion, of the draft article, the acceptance of which by the Grand kizier wap recorded in the identic notes of the-18th-August. I do not think it will be impossible to obtain this if pressure is applied for the purpose both here and in London. If, however, the Porte appears inclined to insist, I venture to suggest that, to avoid delay, another solution which might secure compensating advantages to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company might be found on the following lines: We might agree to the Turkish desideratum, but request that in return the Anglo-Persian Oil Company shall have the right to lay pipes from any of their workings, present or future, within Peisian territory to a convenient position for export in Turkish territory. I understand that there are valuable oil strata in the Pusht-i-Kuh territory which could nou be worked profitably unless such access to the sea is provided. . The foregoing question is to a certain extent bound up vith the second point raised in section 3 of the memorandum as to the exact position of the Moukataa^ of Neft. It seems unlikely that this question can be set at rest until the Commission has examined it on the spot, but supposing that for some reason or other the Tmkish point of view were conceded, it could not then be contended that the line as altered in consequence thereof from that shown in the illustrated maps would be that of the status quo at the time when the D’Arcy concession was granted. Iheie would, m fact, have been a cession of territory for the purposes of the oil company, and, m accordance with international usage, its rights ought to be respected by the acqimmg Power. It will be within your recollection that the position of Neft vas brought up [1898 a—1]by the Acting Minister of War when the Russian Ambassador and I submitted to his Excellency and to the Grand Vizier the draft of the identic notes of the 18th August, and that Mahmoud Pasha contended that the River Neft is that marked in the original identic map as the Zelezerd, whereas the real River Neft is shown in that map to b^ a tributary, Cham-i-Neft, flowing into the Zelezerd from the north. The confusion seems to suggest that there are two places known as Neft, and it would remain for the Demarcation Commission to decide whether the status quo frontier would include that Neft which is on the Zelezerd River. The other point raised by the Porte in section 3 of the memorandum is a mere correction and has little importance. There is one other point to which I need call attention, viz., that which forms the subject of section 1 of the note. This section says that, as some of the astronomically noted positions mentioned in the identic note of the 18th August do not agree with the English map, it would be well to take the reduced map as a basis during discussion, and also for the work of demarcation. It is unfortunately true that an obvious slip of the pen has occurred in the only latitude mentioned in our note (besides that used in connection with the position of Neft), i.e., in memorandum (A), where the frontier is described as following the crest “ dans Textremite sud se trouve a peu pres a 62° 1' longitude et 39° 28' latitude/’ Longitude 62° 1' at this latitude is somewhere on the Afghan frontier, and should be corrected to longitude 44° 27' approximately. The suggestion that the reduced map should be used for demarcation purposes is, of course, impracticable, as it is on far too small a scale, and, moreover, is not exactly accurate. I anticipate no difficulty of obtaining the assent of the Turks to using the original identic map. I have, * e g ARLES M MARLING.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Go ve r»™p»H- 3 fcopy to ErstH&amp;i ^. *j&gt; WV *' * 1 PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [439471 No. 1. Section 1. Constantinople, September 24, 1913. Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 25 ) (No. 483.) ^ 7 (Telegraphic.) R» TURCO-PERSIAN frontier. .Turkish reply received this afternoon. It is a long document with a memorandum attached. It raises again a number of the disputed points in “ Russian” part of frontier, but leaves them generally to be settled by the Delimitation Commission. Points of more interest to ourselves are as follows :— In the body of the note recognition of oil companies is restricted to territory north of Elvend River. In the memorandum, frontier line from Sirvan to Mendeli is accepted with two observations— 1. It corrects line as shown in firman attached to identic notes of 18th August asserting that line should cross Elvend River at a point a quarter-of-an-hour down stream from its confluence with the Guilan River. This change seems of small importance. 2. It asserts that Moukata [group undecypherablej of [?] Neft {le., [?] Neft Meidan) is at a point 1 centim. [group undecypherable] ed on reduced map west from the point where longitude 45° [group undecypherable] cuts the Neft Sou (see my despatch No. 720 of 14th August). According to the original identic map this sphere of influence does not cut the above-mentioned stream at all. The alteration is of some territorial importance, but it might be of importance to the oil company if their rights were to be recognised south of the Elvend River. The note states that the Turkish commissioners have been appointed. The Russian Ambassador is inclined to accept the note and trust to our being able to make good our desiderata in drawing up the final protocol. Copy of note by messenger to-morrow, and copy to Tehran by post. (Sent to Tehran.) [1870 66—1][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Go-gernn»»'*3 ' PERSIA CONFIDENTIAL. [41683] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Hakki Pasha. SIR E. GREY presents his compliments to Hakki Pasha, and has the honour to inform His Highness that His Majesty’s Government have learnt with some concern and much regret that the Imperial Ottoman Government have not yet accepted the notes communicated by the British and Russian Embassies at Constantinople on the 5-18th August respecting the Turco-Persian frontier. Sir E. Grey would earnestly impress upon His Highness the urgency of such a step being taken without delay, inasmuch as it is essential, in the interests of economy and for other reasons, that the commission of demarcation should be in a position to start work at Mohammerah on an early date in December 1913. He accordingly would express the hope that Hakki Pasha would communicate with the Ottoman Government in this sense by telegraph. Foreign Office, September 15, 1913. fco 7v to Facial *4 aL [September. 15J^ Section 3-[42126] No. 2. bir W. Toivnley to Sir Edwqrd Grey.-—(Received September 14.) &lt;1 \llptj k . ; Tehran, September 14, 1913. of a Belgian military engineer strategical (No. 320.) (Telegraphic.) R. T U R 0 0 - P E RSI AN frontier. Persian Government propose to enlist services officer to assist their Commission, object being that he should safeguard position when the frontier in Zohab districths^Relimifedr Captain Wilson is of opinion that one of the Swedish officers now here would be more efficient, as he would have some know ledge of .Ri£Lnmm4ry r waidd be better fitted to advise in a mountainous country than W Belgian, and-. ehiiM !command Persian escort. ‘ VW • 7 c 1&gt; ^ It---* | YVe have not yet made an official communication to Person Government, as my Russian colleague is seeking explanations on certain paints about which he considers his instructions not sufficiently clear, but we have both spoken to Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs informally. Persian Government are in possession of copies of Anglo- Russian notes of 18th August, and are making necessary preparations. It is proposed to name Ehtesham-es-Sultaneh as first and Itila-ul-Mulk as second commissioner. I understand from your telegram No. 390 of 27th August that it is desired that we should secure from Persian Government formal declaration similar to that made by Turkish Government of its wish that representatives of the two mediating Powers should take part in work of delimitation. It would assist me to know if the Turkish declaration took any other form than that of the wish expressed in section 7, part 2, of the Turkish note of 9th July. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh.) - [1870 o -1] ' k 3 OCT!913,-' c Copy to India 3 OCT 1913 it[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [September 13.] Section 1, [41985] No - L Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey—(Received September 13.) (No. 778.) Constantinople, September 7, 1913. ’ WITH reference to your despatch No. 267 of the 20th ultimo and your telegram No 448 ol the 4th instant, I beg leave to submit that the main steps that have now to be accomplished before the Turco-Persian Frontier Commission can commence its labours are as follows : 1. To secure a satisfactory reply from the Porte to the British and Russian identic notes of the 18th August. 1 x 2. To obtain the assent of the Persian Government to the arrangements reached in virtue of the above correspondence and of the London Declaration of t e 29th Ju^ ^ on recor( j ^ agreement in some form to which not only Turkey and Persia but also Great Britain and Russia shall be parties, and to which shall be rSed iktructioBS, Ac., to the Delimitation Comnnssmne.s of the four Pmvers providing for arbitration powers being conferred on the British and ivussia commissioners. The agreement itself in whatever form it may be recorded wouU J p r esum^ include besides formal and of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company. Ag rds , j had a not The stages involving urgen^ \Yar and Mahmoud Pasha yesterday, but unsatisfactory interview with the Mr fi , hat we sha]1 get a satisfactory although the Russian that tlle Turks ma y raise some objections in connection *n f plrt of Ure Lontier, which will cause a little delay before M. de Giers can overcome them. j h &amp;c _ CHARLES M. MARLING. [1870 n—1] 1 V . X S-O' ^ A. 3 Copy to India 23 SEP 1913[This Document is the Pr operty of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. i S i 3 [41944] No. 1. Mr. 0 Beirne to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 12.) (No. 332.) (Telegraphic.) R. St Petersburqh , September 12, 1913. YOUR telegram No. 620 of 22nd August. Russian Government agree as to desirability of appointing Itila-ul-Mulk, but, while quite prepared to suggest his nomination to Persian Government, are of opinion that latter might be regarded on the other hand as of too junior rank to occupy important post of head of Commission. In this case Russian Government suggest that his appointment as “ adjoint ” to the Persian delegate might be insisted on, and that he might be allotted preponderant role directing labours of Commission. Russian Government do not think that this step could be taken before result of pourparlers between mediating Powers and the Porte has been communicated to Persian Government. With regard to question of money, Russian Government suggest insisting that Persian Government should immediately find the necessary funds and place them at disposal of Persian commissioners. Russian Charge d’Affaires at Tehran has been instructed to concert wdth Sir W. Townley in the sense of this latter proposal. [1870 m—1] , -rU 'A. \ A ' £ zesEPW’D, Copy to India 23 SEP 1913 ( C O' -j OcsCI™L^HenUs_the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [September 11.] Section 3, [41683] No. 1. .Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley. (No. 408.) (Telegraphic.) R. Foreign Office, September 11, 1913. YOUR telegram No. 308 of 10th September: Turco-Persian frontier. Turkish reply not yet received. Mr. Marling will telegraph to you when it is. We are pressing for it. [1870 i—3] /Y R 26 SEPSIS ,-y Copy to Ind'a 2,o SEP19 13[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL 4;. [September II.] Section 2, [41683] Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling. (No. 455.) (Telegraphic.) R. Foreign Office, September 11, 1913. SIR W. TOWNLEY’S telegram No. 308 of 10th September: Turco-Persian frontier. You should support Russian Ambassador in urging Ottoman Government to accept at once in writing frontier specified in notes of 18th August. As soon as you receive reply, inform Sir W. Townley. [1870 l—-2][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] u J • - soer- j j H U &amp;L £ PERSIA. [September 10.] • [ ^2, ^ ^ ‘ ] CONFIDENTIATi. ~ Section 2. [41567] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Mr, O’Beirne. (No. 656.) _ (Telegraphic.) R. Foreign Office, September 10, 1913. YOUR telegram No. 330 of 9th September : Turco-Persian frontier. Inform Russian Government that I am prepared to defer to their views provided the final protocol is made absolutely binding. I understood from Mr. Marling that Ottoman Government were prepared to agree to arbitration of British and Russian commissioners, in case of necessity, and all previous British commissioners have attributed failure to reach a settlement largely to absence of such powers. Russian proposal would practically attain same object, and if it is accepted I shall be satisfied. I presume two embassies at Constantinople will now co-operate in preparation of final protocol, and I trust this may be done without delay, so that protocol may be examined by British and Russian Governments before signature. Embassies will also have to satisfy themselves that Turkish and Persian delegates are furnished with full powers. Please ascertain precise date of M. Minorsky’s return to Constantinople, and whether he considers meeting there with Mr. Wratislaw, and, if so, when, to be really necessary. (Figures by post to Constantinople.) [1870 k—2] 26SEP19 1 .3 -VC' •; 4 '/ Copy to Endsa 23 SEP 1913»&lt;jr [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] i : &amp;€ at I CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. [41683] No. 1. Tehran, September 10, 1913. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received September 10.) (No. 308.) ^ (Telegraphic.) R. T U RCO-PERSIAN frontier. . ^ I am not clear from your despatch No. 207 to Constantinople (see your despatch No. 125) whether the Turkish Government have expressed in writing their concurrence in Anglo-Russian notes, and in what terms. Could you inform me on this point, as the Persian Government are sure to put the question ? [1870 k—\] ■ PERSIA. ^ L- &amp; s [September 10.] &lt; \ ;*26SEP19%/ tn cv - i Copy to India 2,3 SEP 1913r jr [This D ocument is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] YOUR telegram No. 650 of 7th September. _ _ I discussed matter to-day with Assistant Minister for Foreign Affairs, M. Minorsky, and head of Eastern section. # • r i,- j- rr i Russian Government entirely agree with you as to necessity ot binding iurKey and Persia to abide by results of work of present Commission. They think, however, that to submit to Turkey a convention such as proposed by you drafted in London would constitute anew phase of the negotiations, and would afford Turkish Government excellent pretext for indefinite delays. ^ ^ ^ They consider that a final protocol, signed by Turco-Persian rrontiei Commission, can be made absolutely binding to the parties. , x , If necessary, the delegates can be furnished with full powers, and protocol can be ratified by Turkey and Persia besides being countersigned by Russian and British Ambassadors. . . , ^ Protocol can contain clauses as binding as a convention, but as regards the provision for arbitration of Russian and British commissioners Russian Government think Turks may dislike the term “ arbitration.” It would be, they think, preferable to provide that in cases of difference between Turkish and Persian commissioners matter shall be finally decided by majority of four commissioners. As to proposed reference to a frontier line drawn on map as being final, M. Minorsky declares that, until commissioners have been on the ground, any line which they can draw upon a map must have portions dotted as being doubtful (apart altogether from Pusht-i-Kuh district), so that frontier is more exactly described by recapitulating the terms of the last Anglo-Russian note and annexes. Assistant Minister for Foreign Affairs appeared to hold so stiongly to above PERSIA. [September 9.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. [41567] No. 1. Mr. O'Beirne to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 9.) (No. 330.) &gt; (Telegraphic.) R St. Petersburgh, September 9, 1913. views that I could but agree to submit them to you. [1870 i—1] - Copy to India 25 SEP 1913mr put away with [This Docnment is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government,] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. U O &amp; o i '-3 I O [August 26.J Section 1, [38476] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling. (No. 267.) Foreign Office, August 26, 1913. I HAVE received your despatch No. 720 a of the 14th instant, enclosing the draft of a note to the Ottoman Government respecting the Turco-Persian frontier. The enclosures in your despatch apparently contain certain clerical errors, and if this is so it will be necessary to have the printed proof carefully revised. I accordingly enclose two copies in print, and have to request you to cause such corrections as may be necessary to be made. I gather that the position now is that the Ottoman Government have expressed in writing their concurrence in the Anglo-Russian notes, but I should be glad to know what steps are to be taken to give the arrangement arrived at binding force, and whether it is proposed that a preliminary treaty should be concluded between Turkey and Persia, prior to the demarcation, and a final treaty after the demarcation. If there is to be no preliminary treaty, I presume you and your Russian colleague are satisfied, in spite of past experience as to Turkey’s attitude in regard to this question, that the correspondence which has taken place will serve the purpose equally well in practice, though I agree with you that the form of the draft note is somewhat cumbrous and unsatisfactory. , You will no doubt report at an early date upon the form m which you and your Russian colleague recommend that the arrangement arrived at with the Ottoman Government should be brought to the knowledge of the Persian Government, and to what document the latter should be asked to adhere. I shall also be glad to receive a draft of the instructions which it is proposed to issue to the British and Russian commissioners. Commissions will be issued to Mr. Wratislaw and Captain Wilson, and, subject to any observations you may have to offer, it is proposed that they should be in general terms and contain a statement to the effect that the commissioners should act in accordance with instructions issffed to them by His Majesty’s Ambassador at Constantinople. I am, &amp;c. E. GREY. [1829 cc —1] s j ‘9SEP1S13 i &gt;' Y‘ ^ ^ '■ ’ Copy to India 19 SEP 1913 j[This DooaHient is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] (No. 446.) (Telegraphic.) R. Constantinople, August 29, 1913. YOUR telegram No. 437 of 28th August. According to understanding with M. Minorsky, actual delimitation will, to save time, be carried out not by commission only, but by one or more sub-commissions working sinraltaneously at different points, and 1 understand from Captain Wilson, who has just left for Tehran, that, considering limited number of each commission, appointment of secretary will much facilitate formation of these sub-commissions, and even that, without secretary, it may be impossible to form more than one. Captain Wilson appeared to attach considerable importance to it. Extra expenditure would be trifling as compared with that incurred by prolongation of work of whole com mission for a month or two. I believe Russian Commissioner would be inclined to bring secretary whether we send one or not. J PERSIA. 1, CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2. [39932] No. 1. Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 29.) [1829 2]PERSIA. % CONFIDENTIAL. No. 1. Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 29.) (No. 444.) (Telegraphic.) En clair. Constantinople, August 29, 1913. WILSON left for Tehran to-day. (Sent to Tehran.) [1829 3] Vy= rv £ i'i ^aSEP1913 M Copy to Lidia 10 SEP 1913[1071— 127J CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Mr. O'Beirne (St. Petersburgh). (No. 650.) R. y Foreign Office, September 7, 1913, 8 a.m. Mr. MARLING’S telegram No. 456 Please inform tlie Russian Government that I have been carefully considering the Anglo-Russian notes of 5th (18th) August about the Turco-Persian frontier, and the proposal that a final protocol indicating the settlement arrived at should be signed by the Turco-Persian Frontier Commission, which has not yet been formally dissolved, and that it should perhaps be countersigned by British and Russian Ambassadors. In view of the difficulties experienced in the past and the immense expense incurred by Russia and Great Britain upon abortive efforts at delimitation, I should prefer to bind Turkey and Persia by the most formal instrument, and I am therefore of opinion that a convention should be signed and ratified by both Powers as soon as possible, and that signed maps should be annexed to it. The convention should contain a clause to the effect that (except in the Pusht-i-Kuh district, where the status quo is uncertain and where it may be possible to make some concessions to Turkey) the frontier line laid down in the map is to be regarded as final, except that any claims for minor modifications which may appear expedient in the course of demarcation shall be submitted to the arbitration of the British and Russian com missioners, whose decision shall be final. Unless there is every guarantee that the work of the present Frontier Commission will be regarded as final, I hardly feel justified in sending it. I accordingly request you to suggest to the Russian Government, and to urge with some insistence, that M. Minorsky should, if possible, come to London in October in order to discuss with Mr. Wratislaw, Mr. Parker, and Legal Adviser the draft of a convention, based on Anglo-Russian notes, which will be prepared here at once in order to save time. Maps will also be provisionally prepared. M. Minorsky could at the same time discuss fully the “ reglement interieur ” of the Commission. Please inform Minister for Foreign Affairs that I should greatly appreciate it if he were to sanction this proposal; and I think presence of Hakki Pasha would facilitate assent of Turkey to such an arrangement. (Figures by post to Constantinople.) Copy to I nd' a ] 15. SEP 1913CONFIDENTIAL. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edicard Grey.—(Received September 7, 6 p.m.) (No. 303.) R, Tehran, September 7, 1913. (September 7, 7 p.m.) MY telegram No. 274 of 3rd August. Russian Charge d’Affaires tells me there has been a sharp skirmish at Tergavar in territory on Turco-Persian frontier recently evacuated by Turkey between Turkish regulars, who had crossed frontier, and Russian troops. Kurdish tribal chiefs appear to be at the bottom of the mischief, which Russian Charge d’Affaires anticipates will easily be arranged, as both Russia and Turkey are ready to withdraw their support from rival brigand chiefs, who have misused the same. [1071—120]CONFIDENTIAL. w / * J. Mr. O'Beirne to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received September 6, 9 p.m.) St. Petersburgh, September 6, 1913. (No. 326.) R. {September 6, 7'45 p.m.) TURCO-PERSIAN frontier. I spoke to Acting Secretary of State in sense of your telegram No. 647 of Russian Government seem convinced of the necessity of secretaries, and his Excellency informed me that they contemplated employing for their part Russian vice-consul at Bushire, if that could be arranged. ■ 8 SI? [1071—116] Cony to India ^SEP1913 L..CONFIDENTIAL. Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received September 6, 1T30 a.m.) / Constantinople, September 6, 1913. {September 6, 8 a.m.) YOUR telegram No. 448 of 4th September. I have discussed various points with the Russian Ambassador, who considers :— 1. As the line in the northern part referring to interests of Russia is described in the identic note with considerable exactness, it is useless and superfluous to trace it on the map, especially as the map is stated to be [in notes illustrative, and therefore not possessing authority of written description. 2. For the latter reason signature is also superfluous. In any case signature can obviously not be obtained till we have received reply from the Turks. When the Persian Government’s assent to the arrangement has been obtained and formally recorded in the final protocol or otherwise, maps might, if you desire it, be signed. 3. As Great Britain and Russia are invited to take part in the delimitation, they become pro tanto parties to it, and can therefore claim that the final protocol be signed by their representatives here. This is convenient and sufficiently binding, and preliminary treaty is therefore superfluous. Delay in obtaining Turkish reply is partly due to Ramazan and Bairam. We have repeatedly urged expedition on the Grand Vizier, who lays the responsibility for it to the Minister of War. I hope to see the latter to-morrow. At present we see no reason to doubt Grand Vizier’s professed desire to reach conclusion quickly. We have drafted a “ reglement interieur ” for the Commission (of which copies will be sent to you by post), but the Russian Ambassador is strongly opposed to preparation of instructions unless our commissioners take part, and hopes that the British commissioner will meet his Russian colleague in Constantinople for the purpose on the latter’s return from St. Petersburgh in about three weeks. As regards point 3 above, I might represent to the Grand Vizier that further copies of the map are required, and obtain from him for the purpose of mechanical reproduction one of the two copies in the possession of the Porte signed by himself, if you consider it indispensable and worth the cost involved.CONFIDENTIAL. &gt; ■ , w W ^ ; 1 &amp; ^ O j S?V Edward Grey to Mr. Marling (Constantinople). (No. 448.) R. Foreign Office, September 4, 1913, 11‘55 a.m. YOUR telegram No. 450 of 2nd September. I regret that original intention as to maps was not adhered to. Telegraphic correspondence of the last six weeks should have made it clear that the omission was not in accordance with the procedure I had authorised, and it would have been better if you had previously reported that you contemplated departing from it in this respect. Omission no doubt primarily affects that part of the frontier in which Russia is chiefly interested, but the settlement of the whole frontier north of Hawizeh is more or less interdependent, and, in the light of past experience, there is serious risk in dispensing with any safeguard against subsequent Turkish evasion. Advantage should now be taken of present conciliatory disposition of the Ottoman Government to secure assurance from them that all maps will, as suggested in your telegram No. 408 of loth August, be initialled as “ copies conformes,” and that this should be done before the Commission starts work on the frontier, and as soon as maps can be prepared, in order not to delay demarcation. You should discuss this point and those raised in my despatch No. 267 with your Russian colleague, and report fully. I gather that you anticipate a written reply from the Ottoman Government to the note sent in on 18th August (see your telegram No. 415 of 17th August), but I am not satisfied that arrangement proposed in second paragraph of your telegram No. 417 of 17th August will be satisfactory unless maps are signed and annexed to the final protocol, and even then it might be more prudent to have a preliminary treaty, as suggested in my above-mentioned despatch. All these arrangements, especially where they depend on concurrence of Persia, will take time, and should, so far as^possible, be taken in hand at once, as it would be inexpedient to delay until M. Minorsky’s return to Constantinople in October. to India \ \ f' j xa,SEP 1913 L r— [1071—98|CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling {Constantinople). (No. 450.) R- Foreign Office, September 5, 3913, 7 p.m. Mr. CHEETHAM telegraphs that Mr. Hubbard will be available for Frontier Commission, if necessary. Do you concur ? ■ ■■ ’'' ■No. 1. Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 27.) {No. 733.) Sir, Constantinople, August 21, 1913. WITH reference to my despatch No. 720 of the 14th instant, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith copies of the Russian and British notes on the subject of the Turco-Persian frontier from Mount Ararat to Djebel Guerebi, some miles south-east of Mandeli, together with Sheets 5 and 6 of the reduction of the Identic Map and a small sketch map of the district immediately south of Mount Ararat prepared at the Russian Embassy, intended to illustrate it. You will see that mutatis mutandis the notes are practically identical, the only discrepancy in the text which is perhaps worth calling attention to is in the substitution in paragraph 5 in the English text of “ le point nord du trace indique dans la declaration faite a Londres le 29 juillet ” instead of the Russian text of “ le point nord du trace britannique,” an alteration made for the sake of clearness, and agreed to by M. Minorsky. As regards the maps, M. Minorsky informs me that there is a trifling inaccuracy in Sheet 5, where the line in Serkale is shown as following the heights to the north of the stream, instead of the course of the stream itself as stated in the note. The inaccuracy is a trifling one, but it seems as well to place it on record in case the point should be raised in the course of the work of the Demarcation Commission. M. Minorsky might have corrected the error in the copies of the map he was preparing for this embassy, but as the Russian note with the map containing the error had already been sent into the Porte he thought it better to avoid possible confusion and to allow the error to stand. The variations between the draft note enclosed in my despatch above mentioned and the note as presented to the Porte have been made at the instance of the * urkish Minister of War in consequence of the interview between him and M. Minorsky, as arranged for when M. de Giers and I met his Excellency and the Grand Vizier on the 13th instant. They affect only that part of the line north of Zohab in which we take no special interest, and do not materially alter the original draft. At this interview the Minister of War did not press his point as to the identity of the Ab-i-Neft with the Zelezerd River, and it was understood that the point will be left to the Demarcation Commission on the spot. As regards the suggestion made in your telegram No. 411 of the 19th instant, that a statement explanatory of the agreement which has been reached between Turkey on one side and ourselves and the Russians on the other, should be prepared here to enable the two legations at Tehran to obtain the assent of the Persian Government to it, I have had some conversation with M. Minorsky on the subject, and we are agreed that as regards that part of the frontier which has been discussed at Constantinople any such statement could be nothing more than a recapitulation of the arguments used in the various notes which have been exchanged between the two embassies and the Sublime Porte. Copies of all these documents have been sent home, and will no doubt be in the possession of the two legations at Tehran. By far the greater portion of this part of the frontier, be., from Ararat to the north part of Zohab, is of special interest to Russia, and the Russian Legation at Tehran will no doubt be in a position to explain and defend against Persian criticism the various arrangements. Defence, however, seems scarely necessary, as, thanks to Russian influence, Turkey has been induced to recognise the principle of the status quo frontier, and to withdraw her troops from the districts west of Lake Urmia, a result which Persia could never have obtained by herself. As regards the frontier from Hawizeh to the sea, the negotiations which led to the declaration of the 29th July last were conducted in London, and it is to be presumed that His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran is as well informed as this Embassy of the manner in which the agreement therein recorded was reached. So far as I am aware, there is not in this case any more than in that of the northern part of the frontier [1829 dd —1] -'TTuVEc . B 1 -o \ 5 SEP1913 £ &gt; ! &gt;2 any reason why the Persian Government should be dissatisfied with the proposed line, but rather the contrary. Indeed the view of the two Governments has been that if by their efforts they have succeeded in bringing about in P ersia s interests a final settlement of this long-standing question, a settlement, moreover, which is far more** favourable to Persia than she could ever have hoped to have reached without their intervention, it is but reasonable that Persia should consent to some sacrifice of territory. It seems to me that there are, therefore, ample grounds to justify the transfer of territories we are agreed should be made by Persia in the Zohab region. It may be pointed out that in this region the only explicit cession is that of the districts north of the Kuretu Piver, for, although south of that point we maintain in the note of the 18th instant, in order to protect the interests of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, the view that the line as now laid down involves an actual cession of territory, it is not impossible that Turkey may, when the Delimitation Commission gets to work, be able in some instances to prove her assertion that the line represents the status quo frontier. As I have stated before, the actual reasons advanced for and against the line actually agreed on in this region are all to be found in the notes exchanged with the Sublime Porte. Even north of the Kuretu River where we are calling on Persia to make a definite cession, the Persian Government may be reminded that in the opinion of the mediating commissioners a part of the territory to be transferred by the contemplated agreement should, under the Treaty of Erzeroum (which is the basis of the present delimitation), properly belong to Turkey. The Persian Government will probably make a great point of the loss involved to them by the cession of Tchia Sourkh and the oil-wells now being worked by the Anglo- Persian Oil Company. There is, of course, a certain loss, viz., that of the royalties payable to Persia ; but it might be pointed out to the Persian Government that so long as Tchia Sourkh could not be connected with the sea by a pipe line—a condition impossible so long as the district remained Persian—any large development of the oil field and consequent increase of the royalties was impracticable ; and, further, that if, as seems likely to occur at no distant future, the oil-fields of Bagdad are to be worked, the market for oil from Persian Tchia Sourkh would be closed, and the present royalties, which I imagine do not amount to any large sum, would be correspondingly diminished. I have ventured to make these few short remarks on the subject of the transfer of territory in the Zohab district in the hope that they may be of some use to His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran, to whom, by the courtesy of the Russian Ambassador, I am sending a copy of this despatch direct, via Batoum, to-morrow. I rvC* CHARLES M. MARLING. Enclosure 1 in No. 1. British Note to Ottoman Minister for Foreign Affairs. M. le Ministre, Constantinople, le 5 (18) aout, 1913. PAR. ses notes en date du 18 (31) mars, et du 12 juillet, 1913, la Sublime Porte a bien voulu notifier a TAmbassade d’Angleterre son adhesion aux propositions russes concernant la frontiere turco-persane, exposees dans les documents suivants : la note du 9 (22) aout, 1912 (avec un memorandum y annexe); la note du 28 mars (10 avril), 1913? la note du 20 avril (3 mai), 1913 (avec un memorandum y annexe); et faide- memoire du 6 (19) juin, 1913. Je n’ai pas manque de porter la decision du Gouvernement Imperial ottoman it la connaissance de mon Gouvernement, qui a appris avec satisfaction le reglement en principe de cette question restee en suspens depuis 1843. Le Gouvernement britannique partage entierement 1’avis de la Sublime Porte sur la necessite de tracer sans delai la ligne frontiere sur les lieux afin de prevenir le retour a 1’avenir d’incidents de frontikre. Se reservant de communiquer ulterieurement a la Sublime Porte les noms des membres russes et anglais quiferont partie de la Commission technique, ainsi qu’il a etti pr^vu par la note de votre Altesse en date du 12 juillet, 1913, I’Ambassade d’Angleterre, d’ordre de son Gouvernement, tient a recapituler les principes de delimitation etablis dans la correspondance susmentionnee au sujet de la frontiere.rThis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majest/s Government.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. 5 e C Section 7. [31686] No. 1. Captain Wilson to Mr. Parker.—(Received Jidy 10.) (Extract.) My dear Mr. Parker, East India United Service Club, St. James's Square, S.W., Jidy 9, 1913. MANY thanks for your letter of the 7th July, and for the very kind support which you are prepared to give to my application to go on the Frontier Commission. Acting on your advice I went to see Sir A. Hirtzel at the India Office yesterday, and presented an unofficial application for the job in question. It remains to be seen how far employment on the commission would clash with my railway work, but I think that unless the commission should begin before the middle of November (and I can scarcely imagine the four Powers getting anything arranged before that), I could join the Southern Commission after going through Luristan (via Tehran), and after making the preliminary arrangements for the railway survey party. As regards the actual demarcation of the frontier, my impression is that up to the date when I left Bushire, no preliminary understanding had been arrived at as regards the frontier in the vicinity of Pusht-i-Kuh, and in particular regarding the Baksai- Saiyid Hasan-Ghurabah lands, and I anticipate a good deal of local difficulty here. The Turks seem to have right on their side, but the Persians are beati possidentes. As regards the two commissions, I should, of course, prefer the southern one, but I venture to express the view that (if the matter is not already res judicata) we could view with complacency the appointment of one instead of two commissions, mainly because there will probably still be mutual concessions to be made between Turkey and Persia in course of the local demarcation, and these are likely to be made easier if both portions of the frontier are dealt with by the same Turkish and Persian officials, than if the northern and southern sections are dealt with in watertight compartments, but I quite realise the possibly superior advantages of getting the work done as soon as possible. Yours sincerely, A. T. WILSON. [2987 k—7] &gt; v Copy to India 5 SEP 1913CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley 'Tehran), No. 400, and Mr. Marling (Constantinople), No. 449. (R.) Foreign Office, September 4, 1913, 5*25 p.m, RUSSIAN commissioner of Boundary Commission will reach Mohammerah about 15th December, and be ready to commence operations 1st January.COKKIDEN'TI.M. S O %j '.j j 5 u.5 Sir Edward Orey to Mr. O'Beirne (St. Petersburgh). (No. 647.) R. J Foreign Office, September 4, 1913, 5‘45 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 322 My impression was that officers in charge of survey parties could do, under general supervision of commissioners, such demarcation work as commissioners and deputy commissioners cannot personally superintend. With the assistance of native Indian clerk, I think British delegation should cope with correspondence, but if Russian Government are convinced of necessity for secretaries, notwithstanding disadvantage of swelling numbers of commissions, I will consider the proposal in last sentence of your telegram.CONFIDENTIAL ^ ! i I 9i5 j Mr, O'Beirne to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 3, 11 p.m.) St. Petersburgh, September 3, 1913. (R.) (September 3, 8 p.m.) M. MINORSKY is anxious to know whether the estimates of allowances for outfit, travelling expenses, Ac., submitted by consulate-general at Crete have been approved by Treasury ; also how long Mr. Wratislaw remains in England. Could you inform me ? U 5 SEP1S13 r 7 [1071-87]CONFIDENTIAL. Mr. O'Beirne to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 3, 10 p.m.) (No. 322.) R. St. Petersburyh, September 3, 1913. (September 3, 8 p.m.) TURCO-PERSIAN Boundary Commission. Your telegrams Nos. 641 and 635 j Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs sent M. Minorsky to see [group omitted: ? me]. Latter states definitely that he will be ready to commence operations on 1st January (n.s.), and that he will arrive at Mohammerah about a fortnight beforehand. As regards question of secretariat, M. Minorsky explained that he anticipates that deputy commissioners will be employed in work of demarcation while commissioners are otherwise occupied, e.g., in conferences with Turkish and Persian delegates, and he said that it would be very necessary that there should be a secretary capable of drawing up protocols of such conferences, and also of official diaries in French. Clerical work involved in making necessary copies would be considerable. He personally suggested, in last resort, secretary of Turkish Ministry of Foreign Affairs might be employed, although aware that this might be objected to by Persians. Acting Secretary of State asked whether it would not be possible to employ junior members of British and Russian consular services. [1071—731CONFIDENTIAL. O O 19.3 Mr. O’Beirne to Sir Edward Grey .— (Received September 2, 3’55 p.m.) IJJW) St. Petersburcjh, September 2, 1913. (September 2, 3 p.m.) (No. 320.) R. MY telegram No. 316 of 30th August. Instructions have been sent to Russian representative at Tehran to join Sir W. Townley in asking for customs immunity. The Russian Government are of opinion that similar step should he taken at Constantinople. \v ■ . , &lt; 09 — .J tG v A' ' * 3 SEPISI^i v.Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 2, 3'10 p.m.) f / , J j Constantinople, September 2, 1913. {No. 450.) R. (September 2, 1*45 p.m.) YOUR telegram No. 444 of 1st September. Intention originally was to trace the whole line as far as Mandeli on the map, but eventually want of time made it impossible. I regret that I omitted to explain this in my despatch No. 733 of When M. Minorsky returns in October I could get him to prepare it, or, if it is required earlier, I could telegraph to him at St. Petersburgh. We communicated to the Porte only sheets 5 and 6.CONFIDENTIAL. ’ 10ia~513] Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Ediuard Grey.—(Received August 24, 3*45 p.m.) (No. 313.) R, YOUR telegram No. 608 of 19th August. St. Petersburg!!, August 24, 1913. (August 24, 3'25 p.m.) In aide-memoire received to-day Russian Government express entire concurrence view of His Majesty’s Government in regard to desirability of communicating as soon as possible to Persian Government result of negotiations respecting Turco-Persian frontier, and of obtaining their adhesion to arrangements made and to despatch of Persian Demarcation Commission to Mohammerah without delay. Ministry for F oreign Affairs have forwarded to Tehran by messenger on 22nd August all the documents to be communicated to the Persian Government, and have instructed Russian Charge d’Affaires to concert with Sir W. Townley as to proposed communication. Russian Government have impressed upon Russian Charge d Affaires necessity of inducing Persian Government to make a formal declaration similar to that made by Turkish Government of its wish that representatives of the two mediating Powers should take part in work of delimitation. Russian Government hope that His Majesty’s Government will lose no time in sending similar instructions to Sir W. Townley.CONFIDENTIAL [1019—524] 'W' &gt;v._d Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley (Tehran). (No. 390.) V Foreign Office, August 27, 1913, 5 p.m. SIR Gr. BUCHANAN’S telegram No. 313 Yon should act in concert with your Russian colleague, and you should make arrangement with Persia, as has been done with Turkey, securing to British and Russian commissioners power to arbitrate (not merely to mediate) in any difficulties which may arise in course of delimitation. I understand that Mr. Marling sent you a copy of a further document communicated to the Ottoman Government, via Batoum, on 23rd August. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 631, and Constantinople, No. 433.) A/'' U 28 All • :CONFIDENTIAL. [1019—499] *V i ; „ Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 26, 2’20 p.m.) (No 433 ) R Constantinople, August 26, 1913. ' MY telegram No. 417 , last paragraph. ^ 26 ’ 1 M. Mmorsky thinks [? it] better to await further developments before coming to decision as to preliminary meeting of commissioner[? s] at Constantinople ; in view of progress that has been made this may not now he necessary. Captain Wilson of course would not be available.■ CONFIDENTIAL. i jSir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling (Constantinople). (No. 437.) R. Foreign Office, August 28, 1913, 5 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 430 , and your private telegram of 24th August. In view of other requirements of service, it would he very inconvenient to spare diplomatic secretary. Moreover, Mr. Wratislaw, whom I have consulted, agrees with me in thinking that such an appointment would be undesirable on account of expense, &amp;c., and not justifiable by reason of work to be done. One object in appointing a deputy commissioner as well as a principal commissioner was that he might deal with such confidential work as cannot be done by a native clerk, who will be attached to the commission and possess a knowledge of Persian. You should therefore inform your Russian colleague that a secretary from the diplomatic service will not be attached to the British delegation. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 634, and Tehran, No. 392.)In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No - 3? 77^/- • and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for Sh d t « and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop a » of the under-mentioned faper. Foreign Office, Cii-xy X ^ Reference to previous letter \-0- Description of Inclosure, Name and Date. Clt Ur. (Ia^ ^ Subject. * 22 AUG iSI3ipy* -ir ... Orey presents his co-rsplimonts to the imasisn Uh&amp;TfcjS d*i4‘istirea, aati. with reierenoe to Ms raoent en quiry, h&amp;s the honour to atete that, in tiew of the fnlu-iua mii reeponsilsie nature of the wait invoivod, the i riuoipai i.ritish OOMtissioner on the turoo-^orsian frontier con- miaaion (Llr. Wratislaw) will rsooivo an annual salary of i.bOO. faa thousand five htmdred pounds, end « personal outfit &lt;CfOv. allowance of Too hundred poundo. ha will elso receive ja20 * 0ne hundred and twenty pounds for trrrMlin,, wpoaooo to iohttMMrah froi» uondon, em&gt; of course ell travelling os- ponses while dewareating the frontier. ho will also receive t limited ouuptuory Mlowance, ofCOPY TO INDIA tUMMUKUltit^MtUtUifa'i 91 i3&amp;» ! §P.8RETAftY'S NftJife; Note by Captain Wilson for information and guidance \ of Survey Party which is to he sent to Mohammerah to join I / the Turco-Persian frontier Commission. tol/u pCjtvJUr Large scale maps of the frontier (l mile • 1 inch) prepared in 1849-52 are available, and much of the work of the survey party will consist in bringing these up to date, and marking the frontier, as decided on by the Commissioner?, on the map. The original 'triangulation record of the 1849 Commission is also available and will be brought by the Commission from England. It is important that in addition to the usual surveying gear the survey party should bring portable or semi-portable drawing tables, and drawing apparatus, to enable them in case of need to prepare fair copies in the-field of maps of portions of the frontier, which can be sent back to India for reproduction without delay. Tentage on a liberal scale should be brought, as hot weather will probably be experienced, as well as cold. Arrangements should be made to enable the survey partyto be split up if necessary into two independent sections. Khalasis should be brought from India to start with, but it will probably be found practicable after a time to dispense with most of them and replace them by local talent. The same applies to personal servants and saises Horses are obtainable, in time, locally but it will probably be best to bring them frqm India. Boxes and tents should be packed with a view to transport on mules, not camels, though the latter may be used occasionally. Uniform should be brought, both khaki, full dress and mess dress: Russians always wear uniform and the British delegation will probably find it expedient to conform. The Commission may last one, or two years, but further supplies of stores, clothes &lt;3bc. can always be obtained from India.respect nothing need he arranged for. The Officer Commanding survey party should arrange to he financially independent of the Commission: i.e. he should arrange to finance himself hy drawing Supply Bills on Bombay (which can always he cashed locally) and accounting for expenditure direct to India (Comptroller Indian Treasury) his hills being simply countersigned hy the head of the Mission (Mr. Y/ratislaw) . Any other arrangement will he fraught with inconvenience and involve much delay. (Signed) A.T. Wilson. Captain, August 15th. 1913.Note by Captain Wilson for information and guidance of the Officer Commanding the escort which is to he sent to Mohammerah to join the Turco-Persian frontier Commission, Tentage for men and for spare kit and gear on a liberal scale snould he brought, as hot weather will probably be experienced as well as cold. The horses of the escort must be brought from India but as the Commission will not last over two years and may take only one, there seems no reason to take them off the strength of the regiment. Persian saises can be obtained locally: officers will do well however to bring their own saises and personal servants from England, replacing them later on if desired by local talent. Poxes and tents should be packed with a view to transport on mules, not camels, though the latter may occasionally be used. Lances should be brought, if the regiment is a Lancer Regiment, and plenty of tent pegging spears, long and short, and tent pegs and swords for gymkhana purposes.The men should bring their own full dress and also the officer in command, and the men may reasonably be allowec a fairly liberal allowance of private baggage, in view of the special circumstances of the case. A good farrier (with his equipment)is an essential oart of the escort and also a good salutri (with his equipment). If it is desired to bring a few followers - lang^i, bhistis and even a sale,or two. I have no objection. It is not done in the case of consular escorts, but the conditions in this case are different. A supply of horseshoes and nails should he broug.i*-- many cavalry officers do not like their horses shod with Persian shoes. A fortnight's supply of compressed straw or hay, and cf grain, for the horses should be brought with the escort, as it is difficult to arrange at once for a local supply. The officer commanding escort should bring his own cooking utensils, cutlery, table linen, &amp;c. to enable him to mess independently, and a sufficient supply of wines and stores.arranged independently. financially independent of the Commission: i.e. he should arrange to finance himself hy drawing supply bills on Bombay (which can always be cashed locally) and by accounting for expenditure direct to India (Comptroller Indian Treasury) his bills being simply countersigned by the head of the Mission (Mr. Wratislaw). Any other arrangement will be fraught with inconvenience and will involve much delay. (Signed) A.T. Wilson.CONFIDENTIAL. (No. 419.) R. Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling (Constantinople). Foreign Office, August 22, 1913, 4‘45 p.m. WRATISLAW has had private letter from Minorsky in which latter, without definitely saying so, rather kicks at idea of beginning demarcation from south. We attach importance to this, as, apart from other reasons, it will be impossible to begin work in Azerbaijan region before spring, and it will facilitate transport, &amp;c., if work is begun at Mohammerah. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 622, and Tehran, No. 379.) f 1019-442][101ft-4321 CONFIDENTIAL. {No. 620.) R. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh). Foreign Office, August 22, 1913, 4 p.m. PLEASE communicate to Russian Government Mr. Marling’s telegrams Nos. 424 and 425 of 21st August, and ask that Russian Minister at Tehran may, if the Russian Government approve such a course, be authorised to recommend appointment of Persian delegate mentioned to serve on the Demarcation Commission. Suggest also that British and Russian Ministers at Tehran should take forthwith such steps as may be expedient to ensure that money will be provided for Persian expenses on commission. (Repeated to Tehran, No. 376, and Constantinople, No. 417.)CONFIDENTIAL. — / Mr. Mai'ling to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received August 23, 9*30 p.m.) (No. 429.) R. TURCO-PERSIAN frontier. My telegram No. 428^‘ Constantinople, August 23, 1913. {August 23, 5*40 p..m.) and your telegram No. 419 Following is upshot of Captain Wilson’s conversations with Minorsky :— 1. It is impossible for Minorsky to [group omitted : ? go] to Mohammerah with his staff before 15th December, and he desires 16th January to be the date of commencement. Russian Embassy, however, point out greater importance of demarcation in the north, so as to remove pretext for Turkish encroachments and possibility of frontier incidents (it would also admit of reduction of Russian detachments there). They therefore desire that it shall be understood that commission is free to arrange for commencement of demarcation north of Zohab as soon as the weather and other conditions permit. 2. Subject to approval of Russian Government, Russian delegation will be composed as follows : Commissioner, deputy commissioner, secretary, two cartographers, doctor, and escort of, in south, six men and officer, to be increased later in the north. 3. Wilson’s proposals for reciprocal arrangement in the matter of cartographical work and escort in the north and south portions are accepted. 4. Wilson will obtain tents and camp equipment for Russians from India. 5. Draft for “reglement” of commission is being prepared here by the two embassies, which they hope to get accepted by Grand Vizier and annexed to the final protocol of present Turco-Persian Convention. 6. Minorsky leaves for St. Petersburgh to-morrow. He begs that two copies of each of following documents may be sent thither for him : [? Reduced | identical map Mr. Parker’s memorandum of 7th December, 1907; translation of extracts from Dervish Pasha’s book ; Constantinople despatch No. 520 of 1912. Wilson leaves for Tehran as soon as possible. (Sent to Tehran.) [1019—460]Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received August 25, 8 a.m.) Constantinople, August 24, 1913. (No. 430.) R. {August 24, 8-50 p.m.) MY immediately preceding telegram M. Minorsky insists, and Captain Wilson agrees, on necessity of having secretary attached to both British and Russian delegations.Mr. Marling .to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 21, 7*30 p.m.) Constantinople, August 21, 1913. (No. 425.) R. (Aumi.ftt.9A TURCO-PERSIAN frontier. Persian delegates on Turco-Persian Frontier Commission have received no pay for some time past, and this suggests advisability of taking steps at Tehran to ensure that money be forthcoming for their expenses on Delimitation Commission.• -r*: ‘ ; CONFIDENTIAL. Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 21, 4*50 p.m.) Constantinople, August 21, 1913. (No. 424.) R. (August 21, 3’45 p.m.) TEHRAN telegram No. 291 of Persian Embassy and commissioners have been kept generally informed of progress of the negotiations and of the result now attained. They are very satisfied with it, and have already sent detailed and favourable report on the Turkish note of 12th July, as offering advantageous solution. We would urge that Ittila-ul-Mulk, one of the Persian delegates on the Turco- Persian Commission at Constantinople, should be appointed Persian delegate on the Delimitation Commission. (Sent to Tehran.)CONFIDENTIAL Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling (Co)isuuntinople). (No. 411.) R. ^ Foreign Office, August 19, 1913, 4T5 p.m. SIR W. TOWNLEY’S telegram No. 291 of 18th August has crossed my telegram No. 408 of 18th August to you. I am anxious to secure arrival of all missions at Mohammerah by 31st October if possible, as there will be, according to Captain Wilson, considerable preliminary work to be done there, and it is doubtful if commissions could even then start work from Diaiji northwards much before 1st January, which they should if southern part of frontier is to be completed before hot weather. In view of Sir W. Townley’s telegram, would it be possible to telegraph to him sufficient detail for preliminary identic communication from British and Russian Legations to Persian Government ? Great pressure should be exercised, if necessary, at Tehran to secure early and favourable reply, and arrival of Persian commissioners at Mohammerah by 31st October, but even if they cannot arrive till a few days later British and Russian missions will have plenty of preliminary work to occupy them there. It would also be well for you and your Russian colleague to tell the Persian members of the commission at Constantinople of the solution arrived at, and induce them to recommend its acceptance at once at Tehran. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 607, and Tehran, No. 371.)Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling (Constantinople). (No. 412.) R. Foreign Office, August 20, 1913, 1‘45 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 421 Attitude of Grand Vizier about arbitration is most satisfactory. You should aim at getting Turkish assent to exercise of such powers placed formally on record, perhaps in a clause to which both Turkey and Persia would agree. Captain Wilson suggests, as a means of avoiding delay in regard to those portions of the line where the frontier is doubtful, and cannot be established without further research, that two lines might be laid down on map for such localities, and the com mission might then proceed with the rest of the frontier, leaving the doubtful portions for final settlement at the end. You should discuss this proposal with him and M. Minorsky, but it should only be carried out in cases where delay would otherwise be serious, e.g., perhaps in Pusht-i-Kuh. I am sending you extra copies of the reduced identic map, as i wish to have one showing the proposed new line as soon as possible. (Repeated to Tehran, No. 373, and St. Petersburgh, No. 611.) [1019—389]CONFIDENTIAL Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 20, 8 a.m.) Constantinople, August 19, 1913. (No. 421.) R. (August 19, 9’5 p.m.) TURCO-PERSIAN frontier. Grand Vizier assures me identic note will be accepted practically without altera tion. Russian Ambassador sent it in last night and I am doing so to-day. His Highness is quite agreeable to procedure approved in your telegram No. 408 and to give British and Russian delegates on Delimitation Commission powers of arbitration. [1019-382]CONFIDENTIAL. jt r T a r o Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling (Constantinople). (No. 414.) Code. Foreign Office, August 20, 1913, 4'30 p.m. INFORM Captain Wilson that Dr. Young cannot be spared for Turco-Persian Commission. He should therefore submit alternative proposal.CONFIDENTIAL. [1019- 386] O h' &amp; ■ * -- i o Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St Petersburgh). (No. 608.) R. Foreign Office, August 19, 1913, 5*30 p.m. TURCO-PERSIAN frontier. Please communicate to Russian Government Sir W. Townley’s telegram No. 291 of 18th August and my telegram No. 411 of 19th August to Mr. Marling. \ c\ s'In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. and address- 3 o cj , L-Cj 3 - V - - ff The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. r/te Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop i ^ of the under-mentioned j)apery Foreign Office, , igig. 1/ Reference to previous letter Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. ' , V ZJjL-Q iwvc ib. c If C 12 ] Subject. •t AU3;:; • \&gt; •Telegram to LtCol Sir P. Cox, Bushire. Foreign Office, Aug. 16.1913. * Following from lilson. n Will you kindly ask Consul Mohaamerah to endaevour to loose house in , ohammerah for three months from Oct 1 for use of British Delegation on Turco-Persian Frontier Commission: should have accommodation for 5 iiiropeans if possible . Also # request him to buy or contract for 20,000 lbs straw to be eisii* TB r«rf ready at . ohammerah in storeor under cover by bov. 10. Kindly advance him necessary funds. Bnds.4 &gt; v M »ii uni 38492 j s « , . 120 AU G 19:5,1 ode Magrm to Uwtcnmt Ooloml sir p. cox (BuBhxre) Foroign Office, August leth, ms^ i.w r , ?a Following rro-i Wilson bogins: ^gga-£i^BiL lruntiBr C( CT ^ |H «| 7TT Should be grateful if you coulc lend ue clerk ■ by October. 15th. ••‘UFt know Indian uccountr and b® aWLe Epo&lt;ik Persian and to type. Puy ISO to SCO according to abilities with Travelling and Outfit Allowance. Work will last one to two years. In view of importance and difficulty of work of uc;a.usfutn * Boot clerk with experience in Terciu nay bo deputed. If Abdul Alim could be spared either on October l&amp;tli oy later he would suit us excellently. L CC°V to IN 01 A 22 AUG 1913 SECOET ;;;yc. nc 34[1019—205] CONFIDENTIAL. 91 2^ Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling (Constantinople). (No. 392.) Foreign Office, August 9, 1913, 5 p.m. I UNDERSTAND from Captain Wilson that the most suitable part of the Turco- Persian frontier to make any eventual further concessions to Turkey would probably be between Mendali and Hawizeh, in the region of Pusht-i-Kuh. It would be well, therefore, to allow for this by indicating that the line on the map as regards that part is only to be taken as the basis of the final demarcation, unless you see objection. As regards frontier generally, its seems advisable to get the Turks and Persians to accept the line on the map before the work on the frontier begins, and to sign the maps. That line will then be decisive subject only to such slight modifications as are shown to be expedient in the course of the demarcation, and much subsequent delay will be avoided. It is very desirable to secure to Russian and British commissioners right of arbitration, as distinct from mediation, in regard to any difficulties which may arise. Inform Russian Embassy that Captain Wilson will arrive at Constantinople on 19th August to confer with M. Minorsky respecting preliminary arrangements for commission. He can afterwards go to St. Petersburgh, if necessary, but must be at Resht by 16th September. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 587, and Tehran, No. 346.) * it ' ^ 1.1 A U i: U S o ,confidential. A Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 9, 6 p.m.) St. Petersburqh, August 9, 1913. (No. 297.) R. (August 9, 5 p.m.) YOUR telegram No. 574 Assistant Minister for Foreign Affairs told me on the 7th August that he was in consultation with military authorities, and would let me know as soon as possible their views as to advisability of Captain Wilson coming to St. Petersburgh. I have written to him again on the subject, but cannot obtain an answer till Monday afternoon. [1019—211]i! i! i §r * s C •:&gt; .J id i n nr E, I *U• S. 01u”b 16 St James SQ July 25tli 1913 My dear Sir Arthur Hirtzel, I return Colonel Hedley^ letter. I saw him this morning, and went over the whole ground in detail. I concur generally with his views, though I thlnlc that the cost of a party of the size he wants is likely to make the Govt of In&lt; -dla hesitate; and I am inclined towards a more modest surveying programme. He has not seen Parker yet, not have I. He is writing to you on the subject shortly. Sir F.A.Hirtzel K.C.B. India Office A-T W'Lsgw/ iSir A.Hirtzel Reference Mr Parser’s letter of July 2Pn&lt;! 0 I submit the following remarks, as requested. (1) 1 concur generally in the views expressed by Marling, an d in Particular in theview that Knowledge of languages and of local conditions should constitute the main qualifications for a Commissioner who should be( as I am) a civil official. (2) Subject to the views of Sir P.Cox and of the Govt of India I should, if desired by the P.O., be glad to serve under Wratisl -law as an Assistant Commissioner, with power to continue worK &amp; in case of his absence or illness, a very necessary provision, for which there are precedents. (3) I thinX that Sir P.Cox and the Govt of Indiawould taXe the v* view that if the principal British Commissioner is not to be an official nominated by the Govt of India, a Govt of India officer should be assclated with him. I presume that the survey staff escort etc are still to be supplied by India( who will no d&amp; doubt be aslced to pay half the cost of the Commission) As Mr Wratislaw is in Crete, not able to undertake preiiminay ary arrangements, and not entirely familiar with local necessities at the Mohammerah end, nor in touch with the Govt of India, I venture to suggest with great deference that in the event &amp;f Govt, being pleased to nominate me as Asst Commissioner, I may be officially Informed of the fact as soon as possible, and simultaneously instructed to maKe all preliminary arrangements for the Commission. Mr Wratlsiaw would then be relieved of b the preliminary worX of obtaining equipment, arranging details ofb the pavty etc with India, etc, which I am sure he would find it difficult to do satisfactorily without great delay, seeing that he is established in Crete with his wife and family etc. As regards the composition of the British C mmlss on, ny note &amp;f July 20th holds good m ut atls m u i&amp;aais lxsir A.Klttzel- I am not sure whether my views are desired re the suitability of Wratlslaw as a Commissioner- Govt of India will presumably have to contribute to expenses so matter may be considered pertinent. He Is now over 51 years of age-nearly 52 l.e. 5 years older that Colonel Williams was when first appointed as Commissioner. He is I believe not a particularly artive man, and, I gather from parsers letter that his health is not what it might be. I thinfc myself that he is rather senior for the Commission, which after all only has to demarcate and not to delimit; and the fact thet the British and Russian Commissioners only hold real ly a watching brief to prevent the Turks and Persian from quar* rolling may be held to make it less u rgent that there should be a very senior man as Commissioner. In other respects Wratislaw^ appointment would seem suitable /VvJM'W) K ffYV^ vv^U lv\ virtv^ * g ^ c^X ATW yS ft * V ^ i.#*- ’! V • w V' vV,y Po lltlcql Sec-Qtary&gt; I submit os requested the following note regarding the projected Turka Persian Frontier Commissions. I do 90 on the assumption that Government win be pleased to nominate me as British commissioner on the Southern Conran. (1 ) Nur:ibefr ^ of C o nrnl rpi . It i £3 propoeM that there should he two Commissions; Russia has apparently agreed to this, though not without some misgiving. i iLl-Jtorfr to commence r-nprn Zohsh . I would, suggest that arrangements he made hy tae Foreign Office for the whole pr vine© of Zohab to he dealt rith hy one of the C ramisalons, pref rahly the Southern. If the district is d alt with by both Commissions local difficulties will he inevitable. As regards the Southern Commission fran some points of view it w would he preferable to start r rora Mohamrasrah. ilJ. fan's of riom^l ^ 1 , oners. As soon as the rank of the Russian represe.itstive on the Southern, uomrai^ si on is known the Government of India may he . . , mint ry skoc to grant me the necessary temperary/rank whilst employed on the Commission, in orb-r to make me of equivalent rank to the Russian Commissioner. This would presumably have to he done hy a notification of the Govt of India In the Army Dept The c sesof military attaches appointed to Tehran and Egypt hy the Govt of India afford precedents for such grant of temp orary -ank. ' of CQ,mTiissio s. on July 17th the F.o. f sked for details of the technical staff 'hich it was proposed to attach to the Russian Comrai sioners hut gave no indication of what the views of HMG on the point were. I suggest that the Russian Govt he invited, in orde30 Indian cavalry under a selectee B order to reduce the size and cost of the Missions, and to prevent reduplication of wort, and possibilities of frction, themselves to appoint such topographical staff as is necessary on the Northern Commission, Great Britain mating her -self responsible topographical wort on the Southern Commission. If something of this sort is not done I fear the 3136 of the missions will he unduly swollen* (5) Topographic el. If not already provided for in protocols I would suggest that Turtey and Persia he invited, in agreement with Russia, to accept in principle the Identic map of 1838 as the topograph ical basis for demarcation as it has been for dramxnmiian, delimitation, the test of the Commissions being thus limited to bringing the maP up to date, and malo ng larger scale surveys of such portions of the frontier as are for any reason liable to cause trouble in the future, or are specially complex, e.g.Zohab, and the Said Hasan lan?s of pusht i Kuh. ( 9 ? British topogtraphlcai ^etjff On the assumption that suggestions (4) and ^5) aoove are aoprow tor xne S Commission ed I suggest that the British topographical staff /might swltably^e^nsis ^ survey of India of not over 9 years service a 3 Indian sub surveyors wiuu nwot&gt;asary xneiasj.s. (7) ttflcorla fq y tfowiffllsalons This is a point of some difficulty and much local importance. I vould suggest tn*t the itusBian Govt be Informed that with a^ vie- to avoiding Increasing unduly the size of the Commission tne/Brltlsn Commissioner win nKly tahe a small escort (fsay 10 or 12 sowars under a BJltlStl tlie main datir of protecting the Agio Russian party devolving of Russia, whilst vice versa In the south It might be suggested that the Russian escott should be a small one of the same size as th that proposed above for the British N. Commissioner, On th# assumption that the above meets with general approval I would suggest that the British escort should be composed ofselected British officerC preferably an accepted candidate for the Political Dept) vifl Date of Commencement of .ForK of Q Q. iMisslQ.flS.r This has not yet b^en settled, I would suggest that Jan 1st 1913 be specifically suggested to the Governments concerned, so as to give the dilatory Persian and Turk plenty of time. In any case it will take some time to collect escorts and men etc at Zohab from India ??)(A) E xpenses o f erecting Plllaxa. I would suggesttfthat an understanding on this point be arrived at beforehand. ztzuBftarziBadxfcfcatzEEEaxAiagztaxpiasadeHt fcfcexM®xBi*axa*fcxlla«x2*aKzjcz^fcfr0x8ii The cos', ml ght be adjusted on the spot by the British and Russian Commissioners and a moiety recovered from the Turkish and Persian Governments in due course. 9b (§b) Is the map or are the plllare, to be the test of th e boundary I would suggest that an understanding on this pol /t be arrived at beforehand. I understand that f wording to rece dent that map and not the boundary pillars are the authoritative test of wbruea boundary lies; this prevents fraud by removal of marks, but it involves more accurate topography, tl) Question of PosVoonemQnt. of wo?^ a yb 11 Tal functions^ of Russian 3M- Birltlsfr If it is possible for any understanding to be arrived at on thi fcfctigzjBaXnfc these points with Turkey and Persia worrc is likely to b&lt;greatly facilitated when the Commissions get to work af they will seldom be any here near the telegraph and if disagreements are not settled locally th re will be great delay ( 1 ^) Administrative arrange-! ents by the GQVt.._Qf British southern Commission. I would suggest that as soon as questions 1 to 7 abov have been definitely settled, I may be informed officially / as*® soon as I have been nominated British Commissioner^ ofl/ H13 of the decision of ©overnment as regards number of commissions place whence worX is to commence temporary ranK which it may be necessary to give me technical staff to be appointed( numbers and status) topographical work to be performed size of igratlltaxsxftxxD&amp;xIticBBK British escort af Southern Commn date of cmmencement of work and that I may be directed to submit to the Govt of India through the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf detailed proposals for giving effect to the orders and wishes of Government on the subject, and for the finances and accounts of the Commission etc. In oxbev that I may have time to prepare these proposals I beg that orders may be communicated to toe some time before I l^r leave England.''A Turae- Persian Frontier . 0 AUG 1913 3EC. I Vw’.Y’o H2&amp; Dear Sir Arthur Hirtzel, Captain Wilson came to see me on Friday and we also had the advantage of the advice of Major Crosthwait, an officer of the Survey of India, who has great knowledge of the Maps of Persia. We were all agreed on the following points: ' i' The 'identic Map* is certainly not afs+i sufficiently accurate to allow of the new boundary ^ &lt;X/fc and boundary posts being accurately shown on it. 2. It is essential that a map should be prepared on which it will be possible to show the boundary pillars accurately in position - otherwise a Loop hole is left for future dis^wsfrioB. To do this involves carrying out a triangulation through the whole length of the boundary and preparing a mapmap Tsased on this triangulation. Without triangulation it is not possible to prepare an accurate map, 5, We think that this work should be done by the Survey of India now that it appears certain that there will be only one Commission it would be best to start i from Mohammereh and work right through. The best time for starting work at Mohammereh is about October 1st, This is also the date for the commencement of the field work of the Survey of India, The Commission itself will probably meet on January 1st, It is important that the Survey should start work before the Commission meets and it is therefore suggested that the Survey of India should be asked to send the party to Mohammereh on October 1st or as soon as possible after that date. It is obviously useless for the Survey of India to send their officers and men to work in the field on October 1st and recall them to Mohammereh on January 1st. It would be more convenient to all parties to start survey work at Mohammereh on October 1st. If this is to be done the Survey of India should be warned as soon as possible, I think that the party should consist*4 * of 3 officers with a suitable number of surveyors, 4, It is estimated that the work will last two years if things go well, 5. The survey section would be quite distinct from the Political side of the Commission, We have received a letter from the Foreign Office asking us to take no action until the letter suggesting one Commission only is received from St, Petersburg, I have written this now in view of the necessity of giving early notice to the Survey of India, I return Captain Wilson’s note which you kindly sent me. It was of course written under the impression that there were to be two Commissions. Yours very truly,CONFIDEKTIAU 3 w &lt;j Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh). (No. 559.) R / Foreign Office, July 28, 1913, 7*45 p.m YOUR telegram No. 278 . / I agree with views of Russian Government. w Your Excellency should inform them of last paragraph of my telegram No. 356 ot to-day to Mr. Marling respecting communication to be made to Persian Government. ^Repeated to Tehran, No. 331, and Constantinople, No. 360.) CC pv 1 o \ n \ A j\UG ^ &gt;Y’S 31 2£ [902—713]CONFIDENT! AI, O Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling {Constantinople). (No. 356.) Foreign Office, July 28, 1913, 6*45 p.m. I THINK that for tactical reasons it would be a mistake to communicate to Persian Government text of declaration referred to in my telegram No. 550 / to St. Petersburgh, about the Mohammerah frontier, and I wish that signature should be kept confidential for the present. You should discuss with your Russian colleague the exact description of the frontier to be communicated and recommended to the Persian Government, informing me of text as soon as possible. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 557, and Tehran, No. 327.) |902—711]CONFIDENTIAL w '&lt;*J } I 9 i 3 J Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey—(Received July 27, 11 a.m.) /x’ x t~, Petersburgh, July 26, 1913. (I\o.278.) R. (July 26, ll’SS p.m.) I COMMUNICATED to Minister for Foreign Affairs to-day contents of your telegram No. 555/ , but before doing so had already received aide-memoire from his Excellency to the following effect, which virtually answers it :— Imperial Government desire to take advantage of present conciliatory dispositions of Porte, and to proceed at once to delimitation, if only of a portion of frontier, so as to create an accomplished fact and prevent possibility of fresh difficulties being raised by Porte. With this end in view Imperial Government propose to communicate officially to Persian Government result to which negotiations have led, and as soon as their adhesion has been obtained to propose to Cabinets of Constantinople and Tehran to form at,once mixed delimitation commission composed of Turkish, Persian, English, and Russian delegates, which should proceed to the spot towards end of summer, and commerce work of delimitation during fine season. It will probably be necessary to give up idea of two separate commissions for north and south, as it would be impossible for them to work simultaneously. From end of October to March snow renders roads in north impracticable, while in south heat would stop work of commission already [group undecypherable] April. One single commission should, therefore, suffice for whole frontier. Russian Government consider that principal English and Russian delegates should be chosen from members of diplomatic or consular services who have had most to do with frontier question. They therefore propose to appoint M. Minorski as Russian commissioner. Officers of general staff and of topographical corps will naturally be joined to commission to do real work of delimitation. Russian Government would like to know views of His Majesty’s Government with regard to present aide-memoire. 11 k Urs »■. 3 TO M T \ /\ SECfT 9 M 28 &gt; &gt; yoo—1-;68CONFIDENTIAL. %j Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received July 26, 8‘30 p.m.) St. Petersburgh, July 26, 1913. (No. 277.) R ( Jul y 2(j ’ 8 ‘ 20 P - M *) YOUR telegram No. 550 Minister for Foreign Affairs raises no objections. ! [902—681]CONFIDENTIAL. f ^ ^ i O ^2 Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh). (No. 555.) ((i s Foreign Office, July 25, 1913, 6‘25 p.m. Mr. MAILING’S telegram No. 353 . I am prepared to agree to views of Russian Ambassador and Mr. Marling, and I should like to know as soon as possible if Russian Government concur. In that event I would propose Mr. Wratislaw as principal British commissioner and Captain Wilson as assistant commissioner, with power to act in event of illness of principal commissioner—a provision which it appears desirable to make so as to avoid any possible delay. (Repeated to Tehran, No. 325, and Constantinople, No. 350.) |9()2- 644 c sec' \/ \r&gt;\N ,f_T ^ 'N ’ L G - 3l &gt;v 0 ^ , w ^ .\\ \ -• r ’confidential. bir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling (Constantinople). (No. 348.) R. / Foreign Office, July 24, 1913. SIR G. BUCHANAN’S telegram No. 274 V JJ &gt; U ^ You should see your Russian colleague and speak to him in sense of my memorandum of 19th June to Russian Embassy (see “persia” Print), using such arguments as you can in support of our view. If Russian objections are persisted in it will cause us great inconvenience and delay the whole settlement. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 553, and Tehran, No. 324.) 1902 -623]; !•' ■ CONFIDENTIAL Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received July 23, 10*30 p.m.) St. Petersburgh, July 23, 1913. (No. 274.) R. j {July 23, 1913, 7T p.m.) YOUR telegram No. 548 I have pressed Minister for Foreign Affairs for immediate answer. His Excellency took a note and promised to telegraph again to Russian Ambassador at Constantinople, whose views he has not yet received.CONFIDENTIAL ' ;~S3 0 Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh). (No. 548.) Foreign Office, July 22, 1913, L30 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 2C1 of 16th July : Turco-Persian frontier. Please inform Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs that I should be grateful if he could let me have a reply to your communication to him and to my memorandum of *19th June to Russian Embassy as soon as possible. This delay is causing very great inconvenience. (Repeated to Tehran, No. 317, and Constantinople, No. 342.)CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received July 13, 9*30 p.m.) St. Petersburgh, July 13, 1913. (No. 256.) R. (July 13, 7*30 p.m.) YOUR telegram No. 513 : Turco-Persian frontier. Minister for Foreign Affairs says Russian Ambassador at Constantinople has now received the Turkish reply, which he considers satisfactory. He is ready to proceed at once with appointment of officers to the two I commissions. 1 f He has given instructions for immediate answer to be sent to our former communication.confidential.CONFIDENTIAL. r Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received July 11, 6IS p.m.) Constantinople, July 11, 1913. (No. 329.) (July 11, 1*40 p.m.) TURC O-PE RSI AN frontier. y Russian Ambassador has received a reply to note of 3rd May, and I expect to receive corresponding communication very shortly. Russian Ambassador considers the note satisfactory as regards frontier north of Bane, but from point of view of interests of Anglo-Persian Oil Company wording of the note as regards line south of Kuretu River is objectionable, as it describes new frontier as being that of status quo. I propose to invite the Grand Vizier to employ different wording in his reply to us.Foreign Office, July 10, 1913, 5*40 p.m Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh) (No. 513.) R. Mr. MARLING’S telegram No. 324 I agree that frontier should as far as possible be definitely laid down by treaty and indicated on a map before work of commissions begins, and I think that work of commissions should, if possible, be confined to demarcation of that frontier in accordance with the line indicated on the map. But I think we should proceed as soon as possible with selection of British and Russian officials so as to avoid unnecessary delay, and I should be glad to know if Russian Government approve the idea of two commissions, and appointment of British and Russian commissioners to serve on both—a point to which we understand Turkey attaches importance. I am still awaiting Russian reply to our last communication respecting the southern part of frontier and Shatt-el-Arab. (Repeated to Constantinople, No. 317, and Tehran, No. 303.)] [902 22;CONFIDENTIAL. 'I ^ &amp; a - Si 913 Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received July 8, 5'45 p.m.) Constantinople, July 8, 1913. (No. 324.) R. (July 8, 5’10 p.m.) TURCO-PERSIAN frontier. Your telegram No. 309 Before [group undecypherable : ? agreeing to] commissions Russian Ambassador desires to await receipt of Turkish reply, text of which will probably be adopted as that of definitive treaty, the conclusion of which must be awaited before delimitation can begin. He fears that, if such text should be lacking in precision, differences of interpretation by the two commissions might arise, and he also suggests that it may be difficult to find sufficient suitable officials. He is not opposed to the suggestion in principle.i I CONFIDENTIAL. a.'yr, T r~n V -i ^ fi ViJ ^ i 9 13 j — Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received July 8, 8'30 a.m.) Constantinople, July 7, 1913. (No. 322.) R. {July 7, ll’SO p.m.) TURCO-PERSIAN frontier. Grand Vizier informs me that reply to our note of 3rd May is being drafted and will be sent to us at once. 9 JULISI[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government,! H , -9 L.U [A] PERSIA. [Jrme 19.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. ' . i ] 'W j 1 1 [27302] . No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Count Benckendorff. SIR E. GREY presents his compliments to the Russian Ambassador and has the honour to acknowledge the receipt of his Excellency’s communication of the 14th June, respecting the Turco-Persian frontier between Hawizeh and the Persian Gulf. Sir E. Grey has, in view of the communications which took place between His Majesty’s Government and the Russian Government in April and July 1912, read Count Benckendorff’s memorandum with considerable surprise. On the 11th April, 1912, Sir E. Grey telegraphed to His Majesty’s Ambassador at St. Petersburgh as follows :—- “Having regard to the wording of article 2 of the Treaty of Erzeroum, His Majesty’s Government are inclined to think that nothing more can be claimed on the Shatt-el-Arab for Persia than freedom of navigation, Turkey having taken great pains to assert her right of ownership over the entire waters of that river, while conceding such freedom. “ From the sea to where the mediating commissioners’ line strikes off from the Shatt-el-Arab, I do not think, therefore, that a fiontier more advantageous to Persia than the mediating commissioners’ line could be successfully claimed against Turkey. On the 16th April, 1912, Sir G. Buchanan reported that he had seen the Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs, that his Excellency concurred in the views of^His Majesty s Government, and that he would instruct the Russian Ambassador at Oonstantinop e to support Sir G. Lowther in regard to the frontier His Majesty’s Government had indicated to the Russian Government from Hawizeh to the sea. As His Majesty’s Government were careful to obtain the concunence o le Russian Government in the line suggested at an early stage of the negotiations, an as that line is more advantageous to Persia than the one allotted by t e me la mg commissioners in 1851, to which Persia then acceded, His Majest} s icveinmen are at a loss to understand why any exception on the part of any party s iou c e laise o it at this late period, when it has been placed before the 1 urkish Governmen o nearly ten months. The present declaration to be made y ui my in no _ Y invalidates or supersedes that clause of the Treaty of Erzeroumw nci secure right of navigation to the Ivarun via the Shatt-el-Arab, and Sn iiey ee s that the draft convention, already communicated to the Russian ‘ T • i ' latest form contains adequate guarantees, certainly in excess o am v ic existed, for international navigation on the Shatt-el-Arab. . rnffir.-nlm Si; E. Grey hopes that the Russian Government will not in regard to the proposed arrangements for the Shatt-el-Ara . _ ' , si r Tr Grev were communicated to the Russian Government seveial mon is ago , &lt; ' A TTj g was under the distinct impression that the Russian Governmen w i 0 f ]onm- Majesty’s Government in regard to the southern frontiei m w ic , y the magnitude standing association, of services rendered to navigation m genera , a otniilarlv^under- of their commercial interests, they are particularly intei es e , an Maiestv’s took to afford the Russian Government the full diplomatic suppoit of Hi S ^ Government in regard to the northern part of the fiontier, w no c pp on the eve of settlement in accordance with Russian views. Foreign Office, June 19, 1913. [2948 £-1] 26viUi 1 i f I[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] ASTATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. . [June 6.] CONFIDENTIAL. I q i ~“z Section 4. [20331] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Lowther. (No. 173.) Sir, Foreign Office, June 6, 1913. WITH reference to your Excellency’s despatch No. 360 of the 29th April, I transmit to you a copy of a minute by Mr. Malkin, acting assistant legal adviser, respecting the proposed transfer to Turkey of the territory now de facto administered by Persia in the vicinity of Zohab. I also transmit to your Excellency a copy of the Persian concession granted to Mr. D’Arcy in 1901. I agree with Mr. Malkin that in the agreement by which the frontier is defined the transaction should appear as a cession by Persia to Turkey of the territory in question, and your Excellency should aim at securing this object. The draft of an article to this effect will be forwarded to your Excellency forthwith, and, after discussion with your Russian colleague, you should seek to have a French version of the draft article embodied in the final agreement. I am, &amp;c. E. GREY. Enclosure 1 in No. 1 . Minute by Mr. Malkin, I HAD a long conversation with Mr. Greenway as to the provisions to be inserted in the treaty with the object of protecting the interests of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company in the transferred territory. The object is— (a.) To secure that Turkey will recognise and respect the rights of the company under their concession. ( 6 .) To prevent the Anatolian Railway from claiming that their alleged exclusive rights in the vilayets of Mosul and Bagdad exclude the Anglo-Persian Company from making their concession in the transferred territory. (a) can easily be provided for ; as to ( 6 ), please see the minutes on 33824/12 and 35252/12, and our despatch No. 405 to Constantinople of the 29th August, 1912. It would, I think, be necessary for the Anatolian Railway, in order to establish their case, to argue that the transferred territory formed part of the vilayets of Mosul and Bagdad at the time when their concession was granted. It would therefore considerably strengthen our position if in the agreement by which the frontier is defined the transaction should appear as a cession by Persia to Turkey of the territory in question, and not as a recognition by Persia of Turkey’s rights to it; and I would suggest that this course should be adopted. I have always understood from the papers I have seen and the conversations I have had on the subject that the arrangement proposed was that, as regards the transferred territory, Turkey should step into the shoes of Persia, recognising her obligations to allow to the company the rights granted to it under the concession by Persia, and being similarly entitled to the benefits thereby reserved to Persia (see the last three paragraphs of our despatch No. 405 to Constantinople of the 29th August last, referred to in our telegram No. 192 of the 21 st April), and this seems to me by far the most convenient and safest course. When, however, I mentioned this to Mr. Greenway he said that this was not the arrangement he had made with Sir L. Mallet, which was that the position of his company should remain unchanged in the transferred territory. I asked him to explain a little more what he meant, and, after some discussion and reference to the provisions of the concession, it became apparent that, in effect, what he wanted was that Turkey should confirm to the company all its rights in the transferred territory (including, e.g., the freedom from dues under article 7) and get none of the benefits, which should continue to go to Persia. I pointed out that [2950 /—4]it seemed unlikely that Turkey would consent to this, and that, even if she did, it was difficult to conceive of any arrangement more likely to lead to friction in the future, and to weaken the company’s position in the event of difficulties being raised by the Anatolian Railway or other persons holding concessions from Turkey, since in that case it would be to Turkey’s interest to support the other concessionnaires in their attempt to squeeze out the Anglo-Persian. Mr. Greenway seemed to appreciate this, and finally said that he would be quite ready to accept the arrangement I have outlined above—provided, of' course, that the company did not have to pay twice over. The practical point arises under article 10, under which Persia gets 16 per cent, of the net profits, and we agreed that this could be satisfactorily met by a provision that the company should not have to pay anything to Persia under that article on profits derived from wells in the ceded territory, such dues on profits being payable to Turkey, who should for that purpose have a right to inspect the company’s books. Mr. Greenway said that they were not making any profits irom these wells at present, but were merely keeping them open in the hope of a local demand arising with the construction of the Bagdad Railway. In that event it might be convenient to form a new company to work these wells, and he would like a provision specifically empowering them to be so inserted. Mr. Greenway said that it would have been impossible for them to lay a pipe-line to the Persian Gulf on the Persian side of the frontier, and if they had ever wanted one they would have had to get permission from Turkey to lay it on that side. He wanted it provided that the right conferred by article 2 should extend to laving pipe-lines through Turkish territory not included in the cession by Persia. This point has been raided by Sir G. Lowther (1 8111/13), and I think that such a provision should certainlv be inserted. J Enclosure 2 in No. 1. Concession granted to Mr. D’Arcy. [Enclosure in Sir A. Hardinge’s No. 16, Commercial, May 30, 1901.] , J^ TRE J e Gouvernement de Sa Majeste Imperiale le Schah de Perse d’une part, et William Knox D Arcy, rentier, demeurant a Londres, No. 42, Grosvenor Square (u-apres designe par 1 expression “le concessionnaire”), d’autre part, il est par ces presentes convenu et arrete ce qui suit, savoir :— ^ Article l er . mr ^ d *-v l So! '*h octwie concessioner* par oes presentes le privilege special et exclusif de rechercher, obtenir exploiter iTTW 6 emporter et vendre le ga Z ’nathetle petrole lasphalte et 1 ozokent, dans toute I’dtendue de 1’Empire persan pour une duree de soixante annees it d^eouler de la date des presentes. P P Article 2. des Semente fi, TsTw ^ ex « lusi f d’instaUer les “ pipe-lines ” necessaires Perslme ainsi one L I™ °j. P If' 6 ™ 8 desdits produits jusqu’au Golfe le droit de constrnire , m p nc em ® llts de distribution ndcessaires. II comprendra aussi d’accumulation et de d' ei . 1 , r ^. eulr t ? us P ult8 &gt; reservoirs, stations et services de pompes, jug“ess!dres! l ' SmeS et autres travaux et ^cements qui Waient Article 3. les Tlttf f at ] uite f nei ! t . au c&lt; [ ncess 'onnaire tons iuo-eront ^ P i P t a 1 Rtat que les mgemeurs du concessionnaire mfntionLs OuTnt P ,Tt ■ COnst ™ &lt; ; tl011 de ou partie des travaux ci-dessus sionnaire devra les-leb t ellaln . s [ultives appartenant au Gouvernement, le conces- ment imnXIaT leeorl f T Pr, f e q uitabl e et courant de la province. Le Gouverne- tous autres te-rains ^ a ? men i l au , concessionnaire le droit de faire acquisition de derproniStaires aL bpiments necessaires pour le m&amp;ne objet, du consentement p opuetaues, aux conditions qui pourront dtre arretees entre lui et eux sans qu’il*'V CONFIDENTIAL. i O Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey. —{Received April 29, noon.) Tehran, April 29, 1913. (No. 177.) R. (April 29, 1’40 p.m.) MY telegram No. 174 of 27tli April. The Russian Charge d’Alfaires so far confirms British consul at Tabriz’s informa tion that he says that 125 Cossacks with 5 officers have been sent to Sujbulak, whilst at the present moment Russian force there consists of about 650 men, as 500 men who have been making demonstration from Urmia, intended to overaw r e the Kurds, [?] are spending Russian Easter at Sujbulak. These men will return to Urmia to-morrow. The new force stationed at Sujbulak is intended to strengthen force of Persian Cossacks recently sent to Sullduz, but special care has been taken not to infringe conditions under which Turkish evacuation was agreed upon. COPY TO INDIA IQ] SEORiTABY’S NfiJd..[This Docmnent is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.! [B] PERSIA. •^CONFIDENTIAL. r « e [April 9.] Section 1, [16221] No. 1. Sir G. Lowther to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received April 9.) (No. 271.) Sir, Constantinople, April 5, J913. AS I had the honour to report to you in my telegram No. 181 of the 3 rd instant, on the subject of the Turco-Persian frontier, the Russian Ambassador has succeeded in eliciting from the Porte a reply to his note of the 9th ( 22 nd) August last, and M. de Griers has been so good as to communicate to me the text thereof. The Turkish reply, copy of which is enclosed herewith, consists of a note from the Minister for Foreign Affairs containing a qualified acceptance of the Russian demands, and an annex showing the cession of territory in the Zohah districts, which Turkey desires to obtain by way of compensation. The greater part of the note is occupied with the modification of the line north of latitude 36°, which are desired by Turkey, and as they do not concern us directly I need say no more than that they do not appear to be of much importance, and that M. de Giers believes that it should not be difficult to come to terms about them. In its eighth paragraph the note urges that in consideration of the complaisance shown bv Turkey in respect of the frontier north of latitude 36°, certain concessions (described in the annex) should be made to Turkey in the southern parts of the frontier, i.e., between 36° and 32° latitude north, and the Porte hopes that Russia will use her infiuence at Tehran to induce Persia to agree to these concessions. The Porte is ready to confide the actual delimitation of the new frontier, as described in the annex, to a joint Turco-Persian commission, to be formed in the coming summer. In conclusion, the note states that in the event of Persia not agreeing to the arrangement proposed concerning the Zohah district, the Porte would be obliged to “ maintenir comme par le passe fetat de choses et la situation existants sur toute 1 ’etendue de la frontiere.” This last phrase is ambiguous, but I think that it can be taken to imply merely that in the event contemplated Turkey would abandon the attempt to come to a definite solution of the frontier question, and would be content “ comme par le passe ” to leave matters in the same unsettled and unsatisfactory condition as has existed for the last seventy years; in other words, the Porte believes that it can trust to Russia’s (and our own) anxiety to see this question laid to rest, to induce her (and us) to put on Persia the pressure requisite to bring her to accept these cessions in Zohab. The annex, after attempting to justify the Turkish demands for cessions in Zohab on historical grounds, goes on, in paragraph 4, to explain that as, according to the Potsdam agreement, Kasri Shirin is to be the terminus of the future Russian railway which is to “ traverse Azerbaijan,” Turkey is willing to cede that village as also the town of Zohab to Persia, and “as compensation” should receive a rectification of frontier and the principle that both north and south of Zohab the territories occupied by Sunni tribes be ceded to Turkey. The annex then describes the new frontier to be traced in accordance with the above principle, and closes with the observation that the annual migration of these Sunni tribes must be regulated so as to prevent their traversing Persian territory. I have found it somewhat difficult to follow the line proposed by Turkey on the map, but M. Minorsky, who was present at the interview, between M. de Giers and the Grand Vizier on the 27th ultimo, when the latter explained his proposals verbally, has been good enough to trace roughly for me the more important parts of it on sheet 5 of the identic map, and I venture to hope that the accompanying copy^ of it with the line shown in red will be of use.* (The remaining part of the Turkish line can easily be identified on sheet 6 .) Starting from the north it will be noted that whereas as far as the Kuretu River the line verbally indicated to the Russian Ambassador by the Grand Vizier (see my telegram No. 169 of the 28th ultimo) was almost identical with the frontier suggested * Not reproduced. [2874 i —1] / a . • A4 [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. Section 4, [13342] No. 1 . Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edicard Grey.—(Received March 23.) (No. 115.) ^ (Telegraphic.) R. St. Petersburgh, March 23, 1913, YOUR telegram No. 204 of 9tli March : Turco-Persian frontier. Memorandum from Russian Government states that they consider that formula proposed by Hakki Pasha could serve as a basis for further negotiations. It would, however, be necessary for Ottoman Government to state clearly what compensations they intend to claim in zone situated between the 32nd and 36th degrees of latitude. Russian Government agree that negotiations should not be transferred from Constan tinople to London or St. Petersburgh. [2836 ^—4] L / * 24 Vifts t,CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh). (No. 204.) R. ... Foreign Office, March 9, 1913, 12-30 p.m. PLEASE make a communication in the following sense to Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs for his confidential information :— Hakki Pasha has been discussing informally here various questions connected with the assent of His Majesty’s Government to the proposed 4 per cent, customs increase. As the Russian Government are aware, the recognition of the frontier status quo, in the neighbourhood of Mohammerah, as described in the British note of 18th July, 1912, forms one of the desiderata put forward by His Majesty’s Govern ment. Hakki Pasha said that he recognised that the question must now be settled, and that the adoption of a definite line would be in the best interests of Turkey herself; but he said the whole frontier line was interdependent, and the south could not be settled and the north left undecided. He was informed that this was our view ; and that the Russian note of 1912 seemed to outline a very just and desirable solution. He then said that he would like to lay before the Grand Vizier, and strongly recommend the adoption of, a formula, which his Highness could put forward at Constantinople. The formula he is understood to contemplate is as follows:— “ 1. Admettre que la frontiere, dans toute son etendue, depuis le Mont Ararat jusqu’au Golfe Persique, se trouve dans les limites de la zone indiquee sur la carte ‘ identique.’ “ 2. Pour la partie septentrionale de la frontiere, depuis le Mont Ararat jusqu’a la hauteur du 36 e degre de latitude, accepter la ligne indiquee dans la note russe de 1912. “3. A partir du 32 e degre de latitude jusqu’au Golfe Persique, accepter la ligne indiquee dans la note anglaise du 18 juillet, 1912. “ 4. Pour les regions comprises entre les 32 e et 36 e degres de latitude, accepter le statu quo actuel, tout en offrant a la Turquie comme compensation dans les regions au nord et au sud de Zohab (ville) les districts occupes par les tribus Sunnites, ainsi que, du cote de Mendalli, quelques endroits a determiner ulterieurement. Les villes de Zohab et de Kasr-i-Shirine resteraient en possession dela Perse.” Hakki Pasha said that it w r as necessary to save the Government from adverse criticism, and that to do this the settlement must appear in the light of a compromise and not of a Turkish surrender all along the line. He also said that Turkey might ask for certain minor compensations in the north, but within the “ zone.” He asked if His Majesty’s Government would support Turkey in this formula. He v^as informed in reply that it would be impossible for His Majesty’s Govern ment to undertake to do this without consultation wdth the Russian Government, who were even more interested than His Majesty’s Government; but that, if the Grand Vizier replied to the Russian and British notes at Constantinople, and put forward proposals on the above lines, they would be examined there on their merits : vTdle His Majesty’s Government attached great importance to a final settlement of the whole question without further delay, and had therefore taken the opportunity of the informal discussions with him to emphasise this wish, they would deprecate trans ferring the formal negotiations from Constantinople to London. He recognised that this would be undesirable. The gist of his argument w r as that if Turkey accepted Russia’s wishes in the north, and our wishes in regard to the south, she ought to receive some compensation in the middle. (Repeated to Tehran, No. 115, and Constantinople, No. 132.)CONFIDENTIAL. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(deceived April 27, 12’SO P31.) Tehran, April 27, 1013. (No. 174.) (April 27, 3 p.m.) MY telegram No. 140 Following from consular officer at Tabriz, 26th April :—\ “Some 300 Russian Cossacks left here on 21st April for Soujboulak, and Shuja has informed me confidentially that a further force of Cossacks has proceeded from Urmia to the same destination. My Russian colleague, who confirms the above generally, informs me that measure has been decided upon on the recommendation of Russian consul in that place. The existing consular guard had already had a good effect on the Kurdish chiefs in those parts, but in view of continued unrest amongst the latter it w T as considered desirable that his guard should be augmented. My colleague added confidentially that Turkish Government, who, he said, had not ceased their activity in the frontier regions, had been notified of above step. The detachment sent from Urmia to Soujboulak would seem to be meant for a demonstra tion, as according to my colleague, the intention was that it should merely visit the d istnct. “ One hundredy^ossacks have further left here for Sullduz. _ Matters appear to he quiet in that district, and as far as I can gather, the mam object of measure, vith which the Russians, I believe, are not unconnected, would seem to be to supplement the Persian soldiers there by a better class of men.”Constantino'ple, April 28, 1913. (No. 208.) R. ^ ril 28 ’ 4 ' 40 RM ) TDRCO-PERSIAN boundary. The Russian Ambassador insists very strongly on expediency of send mg i the Porte at once his note (enclosed in my despatch No. 352 )Vithout waiting tor corresponding note from us, and, therefore, is very anxious to know whether the 18 C ° Paragraph 6 ' of the Russian Ambassador’s [?] note will be altered to bring it more into harmony with instructions contained in your despatch No. 405 ol 191^Sir W.Toicnley to Sir Eduard Grey.—(licccived April 27, 12'30 p.m.) (No. 174.) Tehran, April 27, 1913. (April 27, 3 p.m.) MY telegram No. 141 Following from consular officer at Tabriz, 26tlr April: “Some 300 Russian Cossacks left here on 21st April for Soujboulak, and Shuja has informed me confidentially that a further force of Cossacks has proceeded from Urmia to the same destination. My Russian colleague, who confirms the above generally, informs me that measure has been decided upon on the recommendation of Russian consul in that place. The existing consular guard had already had a good, effect on the Kurdish chiefs in those parts, but in view of continued unrest amongst the latter it was considered desirable that his guard should be augmented. My colleague added confidentially that Turkish Government, who, he said, had not ceased their activitv in the frontier regions, had been notified of above step. Ihe detachment sent from Urmia to Soujboulak would seem to be meant for a demonstra tion, as accordingt^my colleague, the intention was that it should meiely visit the 1&amp; ^One hundred/Possacks have further left here for Sullduz. ^ Matters appear to be quiet in that district, and as far as I can gather, the main object of measure, with which the Russians, I believe, are not unconnected, would seem to be to supplement the Persian soldiers there by a better class of men.” 1 &gt; * 28* ..... ^ &lt;VfrDVJ&gt; 1 G22] ; y ■4 CONFIDENTIAL Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Lowther (Constantinople). (No. 197.) D. Foreign Office, April 25, 1913, 6 p.m. AN agreement has been reached with Hakki Pasha respecting Mohammerah frontier. His Highness accepts our line, with slight alterations m noithein part. Details by bag. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 359, and Tehran, No. 205.) I [551—596] f j IfCONFIDENTIAL. (No. 204.) R. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petershurgh). Foreign Office, March 9, 1913, 12'30 p.m. PLEASE make a communication in the following sense to Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs for his confidential information :— Hakki Pasha has been discussing informally here various questions connected vdth the assent of His Majesty’s Government to the proposed 4 per cent, customs increase. As the Russian Government are aware, the recognition of the frontier status quo, in the neighbourhood of Mohammerah, as described in the British note of 18th July, 1912, forms one of the desiderata put forward by His Majesty’s Govern ment. Hakki Pasha said that he recognised that the question must now be settled, and that the adoption of a definite line would be in the best interests of Turkey herself; but he said the whole frontier line was interdependent, and the south our view-; and that the Russian note of 1912 seemed to outline a very just and desirable solution. He then said that he would like to lay before the Grand Vizier, and strongly recommend the adoption of, a formula, which his Highness could put forward at Constantinople. The formula he is understood to contemplate is as follows :— “ 1. Admettre que la frontiere, dans toute son etendue, depuis le Mont Ararat jusqu’au Golfe Persique, se trouve dans les limites de la zone indiquee sur la carte ‘ identique.’ “ 2. Pour la partie septentrionale de la frontiere, depuis le Mont Ararat jusqu’a la hauteur du 36 e degre de latitude, accepter la ligne indiquee dans la note russe “ 3. A partir du 32 e degre de latitude jusqu’au Golfe Persique, accepter la ligne indiquee dans la note anglaise du 18 juillet, 1912. “ 4. Pour les regions comprises entre les 32 e et 36 e degres de latitude, accepter le statu quo actuel, tout en offrant a la Turquie comme compensation dans^ les regions au nord et au sud de Zohab (ville) les districts occupes par les tribus Sunnites, ainsi que, du cote de Mendalli, quelques endroits a determiner ulterieurement. Les villes de Zohab et de Kasr-i-Shirine resteraient en possession dela Perse.” Hakki Pasha said that it was necessary to save the Government from adverse criticism, and that to do this the settlement must appear in the light of a compromise and not of a Turkish surrender all along the line. He also said that Turkey might ask for certain minor compensations in the north, but within the “ zone.” He asked if His Majesty’s Government would support Turkey in this formula. He was informed in reply that it would be impossible for His Majesty’s Govern ment to undertake to do this without consultation with the Russian Government, who were even more interested than His Majesty’s Government; but that, if the Grand Vizier replied to the Russian and British notes at Constantinople, and put forward proposals on the above lines, they would be examined there on their merits : w T hile His Majesty’s Government attached great importance to a final settlement of the whole question without further delay, and had therefore taken the opportunity of the informal discussions with him to emphasise this wish, they would deprecate trans ferring the formal negotiations from Constantinople to London. He recognised that this v r ould be undesirable. The gist of his argument was that if Turkey accepted Russia’s wishes in the north, and our wishes in regard to the south, she ought to receive some compensation in the middle. (Repeated to Tehran, No. 115, and Constantinople, No. 132.) could not be settled and the north left undecided. He w r as informed that this w r as de 1912. [409-200] ! COPY TO INDIA ! 9 13 I SECRETARY'S NS....UCONFIDENTIAL. Sir G, Lowbher to Sir Edward Gh'ey.—(Received March 9, 7 p.m.) (No. 135.) FOLLOWING from consul at Bagdad to-day : Constantinople, March 9, 1913. n (March 9, 1L50 “ Turco-Porsian frontier. &lt;c Mr. [word undecypherable] telegraphs to me that he learns that there is a contemplated move of Turkish troops on Persian territory near oilfields, and he begs make representations to the vali that the oilfields he not interfered with. On the other hand, [? report] here is that tribal difficulties have arisen between Zen jam, Turkish, and Knijabi, Persian, who have raided and counter-raided, and in the last raid three Turkish battalions at one of the guard-houses were killed. Neither I nor my Kussian colleague have any information of dispatch of Turkish troops from [? Bagdad]. “ Should I approach the vali on the question ? ” I have instructed the consul at Bagdad to approach the vali unofficially, and to / intimate to him in a friendly manner the undesirability of interfering with oilfields. [409-180][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government] PERSIA. [February 17.J ^CONFIDENTIAL. Section 4. I Q [7468] No. 1— Sir G. Lowther to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received February 17.) (No. 113.) Sir, Constantinople, February 13, 1913. WITH reference to my despatch No. 1060 of the 12th December last, I have the honour to transmit herewith the copy of a despatch which I have received from Dr. Scott, His Majesty’s acting consul-general at Bagdad, enclosing copies of a letter addressed by Mr. Vice-Consul Soane to M. Orlof, Russian consul-general at Bagdad, giving the southern limits of the territory of Shemiran in the north of Zohab, with certain particulars as to its ownership. The line given by Mr. Soane as delimitating the Shemiran district can be traced with a fair amount of accuracy on the map attached to the Foreign Office Memorandum 9033 of September 1907, to which he refers. Further details respecting the line in question, as also respecting the lines of the proposed cessions of territory to the east of Barau range and to the south of the Elwend River respectively, will no doubt be given by Mr. Soane with the new sketch map which, as will be seen from Dr. Scott’s despatch above referred to, is being prepared by him. In the meantime it might, I venture to think, be advisable that copies of the identic map should be forwarded to Dr. Scott at Bagdad for the use of Mr. Soane and M. Orlof. I have, &amp;c. GERARD LOWTHER. Enclosure 1 in No. 1. Acting Consul-General Scott to Sir G. Lowther. (No. 57.) Your Excellency, Bagdad, January 13, 1913. IN continuation of my despatch No. 964, dated the 11th November, 1912, I submit herewith three copies of a letter which Mr. E. B. Soane has addressed to M. Orlof, Russian consul-general at Bagdad, in connection with the proposed new Turco-Persian frontier. I had held this back hoping to be able to submit it together with the new sketch map Mr. Soane is preparing. His long illness, however, has prevented him up to the present completing this work. I have, &amp;c. NORMAN SCOTT, Captain I.M.S., Acting Political Resident in Turkish Arabia. Enclosure 2 in No. 1 . Mr. Soane to M. Orlof. Cher M. Orlof, Tohia Sourkh, le 19 novemhre, 1912. IL parait’que le fils de Mahmoud Pacha Djafe, nomme Ali Beg, sujet ottoman, est le proprietaire du terrain de Chemirane, lequel a ete, il y a longtemps, acquis par achat des anciens proprietaires (le tribu Charafbaini). A cause de cette circonstance les Kourdes le considerent comme territoire turque, appelant les limites de Chemirane “hudoud,” c’est-a-dire “ frontiere.” Referant a la carte incluse dans le Memorandum 9033, septembre 1907 (dont vous possedez un exemplaire), a voir la partie extreme nord de la chaine Bendi Bamou portant les lettres u Ben-” du mot “Bendi.” Entre cette partie de la chaine et sa [2804 r—4] C S MAR 1913 2 2 \ . 0/ 7 ) SECr^TARro H■- 1JnorU CONFIDENTIAL n 'U Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Lowther (Constantinople). (No. 120.) R. Foreign Office, March 3, 1913, 5*10 p.m. PLEASE telegraph, to me the substance of your Excellency’s promised observations (see your despatch No. 1060 of 12 th December) regarding the suggestions made by Messrs. Soane and Orloff on the subject of the frontier of Zohah, Bagcha, and Zatar./ ■ ' [This Documeat is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Governm ent.] ^ PERSIA. \ [February 1 .] CONFIDENTIAL. Sbctiok 2. [4847] No. 1. Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received February 1.) (No. 33.) (Telegraphic.) R. St. Petersburgh, January 31, 1913. YOUR telegram No. 80 of 30th January: Turco-Persian frontier. Minister for Foreign Affairs, to whom I spoke, still favours denunciation of protocol. On my pressing your views on him, he said that he would think the matter over and let me have an answer later on. [2804 a—2] • NACONFIDENTIAL. r c i ' l\Y' : ^ i S-» v Sir G. Lowther to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received February 18, 12‘45 p.m.) Constantinople, February 17, 1913. (No. 94.) R. {February 18, 9*40 a.m.) YOUR telegram No. 89 Turco-Persian bonndary communication made to-day by the Russian Ambassador and myself. Minister for Foreign Affairs assured me that he had been actively engaged on the subject, and promised a settlement within twenty days. I asked if I might so inform you officially. He replied in the affirmative. A similar answer was given to my Russian colleague. 1 COPY TO INDIA 2.L.&amp;L-..191.L, SEGUE f AliY’8 A [282—472] !iOONFTDENTIAl Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Lowther (Constantinople). (No. 89.) R. Foreign Office, February 12, 1913. MY telegram to Sir G. Buchanan No. 120 of 12tli February. When your Russian colleague is authorised you should make the communication to the Turkish Government. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 121.)OOVl'TDICNTlAL. r Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Lowther (Constantinople). (No. 89.) R. J Foreign Office, February 12, 1913. MY telegram to Sir Gr. Buchanan No. 120 of 12tli February. When your Russian colleague is authorised you should make the communication to the Turkish Government. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 121.)30|° CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh). {No 120 ) Foreign Office, February 12, 1913. ^ * SIR G. LOAVTHER’S telegram No. 83 of lOth February: Turco-Persian frontier. Ascertain from Minister for Foreign Affairs if he would send instructions to Russian Ambassador at Constantinople to let the Turkish Government know that it would he most desirable and in the true interests of Turkey if they were to agree without further delay to a definite settlement of the frontier question on the lines oi the Russian and British notes; and that Turkey would gam no ultimate advantage by further procrastination. , . -r* • n I am instructing Sir G. Lowther to take this step as soon as his Russian colleague is authorised to co-operate. ^ ^ n . AT OA (Repeated to Constantinople, No. 88 , and Tehran, No. 80.; ' I 13FEB1913 t&amp;rm'. 1282—319f. • yf. \ 1 [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Gove rnment] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. y \ [December 17.] Section 8. [53795] (No Sir, 253.) No. 1. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received December 17.) Tehran, December 5, 1912. NUMEROUS reports having reached me of late respecting the state of affairs at Kermanshah and in the neighbourhood, which has caused an almost complete cessation of trade, I yesterday made a serious representation to the Minister for Foreign Affairs. I pointed out that the Bagdad-Kermanshah route is one of the few remaining roads that are open for the importation of British goods into Persia, and I said that the disorders reported on it caused most serious damage to British commerce. I added that the Turkish Ambassador had spoken to me very seriously upon the subject, and had hinted at the possibility of the Sublime Porte having to insist upon the right to have Turkish caravans escorted by Turkish troops, since Persia’s inability to maintain order on her roads constituted a breach of her treaty engagements. It seemed to me, I said, that it might be difficult to find an answer to the Turkish argument. Ala-us-Sultaneh replied that want of money was the cause of the whole trouble, and that the treasurer-general declares that he is unable to supply the Governor- General with the funds of which he stands in urgent need, and that the latter had consequently sent his resignation to the Imperial Government. I replied that M. Mornard was somewhat justified in his hesitation to supply more funds to Farman Farma without a proper security that the money would be suitably spent, since his Highness’s notorious corruption had caused him to be deservedly distrusted. I suggested that it might be possible to find a less self-interested Governor-General. I have, &amp;c. WALTER TOWNLEY. [2729 r—8] i-o ^ 'A 9JAN1913 ) S'/-, DETh COPY TO P''!A 10 JAN 1813 SECRETARY'S N- 2In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote N °- 791/13. and address— ^he Under-Secretary of State, foreign Office, London. / (\\r^ V,; t 5] V ‘'i aM 7/?e Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under—Secretary of Stale for India, and is directed by SirE. Grey to transmit to him y the accompanying copies of a Sketch Map of the Province of Zohab. Jio. B q-i+ ® JAMsi} ^!yOFFlCE.t Foreign Office, January 7CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received January 11, 4*30 p.m.) St. Petersburgh, January 11, 1913. (No. 12.) R. ^ (January 11, 4 p.m.) CONSTANTINOPLE telegram No. 13 of 9tli January : Turco-Persian frontier. Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs has received similar information. COPY TOJNDIA 191.2... SECRETARY'S |; - ■ CONFIDENTIAL. r 1913 \ s N £1 J Sii W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received January 7, 2*35 p.m.) Tehran, January 7, 1913. (January 7, 4 p.m.) (No. 10.) CONSTANTINOPLE telegram No. 9 Following from consular officer at Kermanshali:— Report w as sent by Sinjabi, chief in charge of Kasr. It is probably only a tribal dispute on account of Persian raids into Turkish territory. I have sent a messenger to the vice-consul for information.” mtmmrn COPY TO INDIA | 9 O.- ; sir'll 1 ' ’'ARY'S U?...'h { ^ - „ *[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. i.J'' : [December 16.] Section 1. ^ ''—7 [53486] No. 1. Sir G. Lowther to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received December 16.) (No. 1060.) Sir, Constantinople, December 12, 1912. WITH reference to Mr. Mailing’s telegram No. 382 of the 20th September last and to Sir G. Buchanan’s telegram No. 342 of the 27th of the same month, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith the copy of a despatch which I have received from His Majesty’s acting consul-general at Bagdad, enclosing a letter addressed to him by M. Orlof, Russian consul-general in Bagdad, and of a report by Mr. Soane, His Majesty’s vice-consul at Kasr-i-Shirin, accompanied by a map, on the subject of the possible cessions of territory by Persia to Turkey in the district of Zohab. I would propose to defer my observations on these suggestions made by Mr. Soane and M. Orlof pending the receipt of certain additional information for which I have telegraphed to Bagdad, as both the question of the boundary of Shemiran denoted by the yellow line on Mr. Soane’s map and that of the exact limits of the Bagcha and Zatar districts to the south of the River Elwend would seem to require further elucidation. I would beg that, if it should be considered desirable to print the map annexed to Mr. Soane’s report, copies may be sent to me for the use of this Embassy. I have, &amp;c. GERARD LOWTHER. Enclosure 1 in No. 1. Consul-General Scott to Sir G. Loivther. gj r Bagdad, November 11, 1912. I HAVE the honour to submit, for your Excellency’s information, two copies of the enclosed documents. ‘ , 2. The last reference on this subject was my telegram No. 97 dated the ilth November, 1912. [ llcIVO &amp;c 'NORMAN SCOTT, Captain, I.M.S., Officiating Political Resident in Turkish Arabia, and His Britannic Majesty's Consul-General, Bagdad. Enclosure 2 in No. 1. Report by Vice-Consul Soane. Proposition 1. (Refer to sketch map of Zohab.) THE line here taken is based solely on the consideration of leaving the oil concession in Persian territory. Incidentally it leaves the Guran nomads their present winter pasturages in Kuretu, which they have illegally occupied, their hereditary pastures being to the east of the line proposed by the mediating commissioners. Against this proposition lies th e very small cession thereby made to luikqv, and the necessity of ceding a L*^V^S^-,some other place less suitable than the district of Kuretu. /ofr' '' 2 JAN IS rr n O V T n p ’ A a [2729 q—l] JAN 1913 I SECRETARY’S N 2 1Proposition 2. The line taken is fixed with the object of leaving the powerful and numerous Senjabi tribe undisturbed and undivided in their present and hereditary winter pasture. It involves the continuation of the frontier south from Kani Biz, on the Alvand (the present frontier), along its present line, as the Senjabi pastures are limited by that line, which is somewhere on the west slopes of Bagcha and Katar hills. This proposition leaves Kasr-i-Shirin to the Persians. It would be possible, were it so desired, to take the frontier-line along the green line (claimed by the Persians), thereby restoring to Turkey the west slopes of Agha Dagh, at present occupied by Persia. This would not interfere with the Senjabi to any serious extent. With this line of frontier a portion of North Juanrud, including Shemiran, would advisedly be ceded as compensation for the environs of Kasr-i-Shirin. Such portion should be bounded south by a line running from the south end of Bamu Mountain to Deshti Murd, meeting the Khani Shur Mountain and running north to the Sirwan along the ridge. By this proposition, in acquiring the Shemiran and Juanrud district and relinquishing the Senjabi districts, the Turks would obtain possession of— 1. Fertile and populated lands which have never rendered any benefit to Persia. 2. Sunni population (anti-Persian). Whereas against the acquisition of Senjabi lands there are the objections for Turkey of— 1. A hostile Persophile tribe (Shiah). 2. Settlement of the tribe’s subjectivity. 3. Disarmament of the tribes every autumn (a practical impossibility without open warfare). 4. Acquisition of lands absolutely desert in summer and autumn, with no popula tion whatever and no possibility of settlement. Proposition 3. . ^ ith the object of leaving the Senjabi winter lands in Turkish territory. For this purpose the mediating commissioners’ line must be taken to its junction with the Ahmnd, and. thence the frontier-line between the Kalhur and Senjabi to a point north i ^! nc a h hi the existing limit line. This proposition is open to objection, mainly that the question of subjectivity of the Senjabi would have to be settled. If they become Turkish subjects they will raid and commit brigandage in Persia m their summer lands near Kermanshah. If they are Persian subjects they will cause endless tiouble by their intrigues with other Shiah tribes just over the border during winter, and in any case the Turks will find it impossible to disarm them. This tribe cannot find any other winter grazing land than that thej^ at present occupy, and there is no solution in the proposal that they betake themselves elsewhere. The Gilan plain is part of the Kalhur territory, together with its lands of Wizhnan to south-west, and the incorporation of this in Turkish territory is open to exactly the tS 116 i ) :d ec ^ ons as ^ ie acquisition of Senjabi winter lands (which it also involves). I he Gilan frontier exactly doubles the difficulties considered under the Senjabi question, as the Kalhur are also a Shiah Persophile tribe, with their summer lands in I ersia and without any other place to occupy in winter save those in which thev are at present. Generally speaking, it appears that any cession of territory to Turkey is most preferably to be given from the lands containing Sunni (anti-Persian populations, which are only to be found north of the Zohab plain and Kuretu rivers), and that the anti-lurk (Shiah peoples to the south of these limits) are far better left in Persian t r rri D 0r ’F The adoption of proposition 2 meets entirely these considerations, saving ^ u Tv r i S u an \ leaving them Kasr-i-Shirin town and their Shiah tribes (Senjabi and Kalhur), which have their summer quarters near Kermanshah, and giving to the lurks a partially sedentary population (Sunni) and good land. The statements regarding the Guran pasturages in my original note on this question have to be modified, as at that time I was not aware of the circumstances of the occupation of theSir G. Ixncther to Sir Edward Grey .— {Received January 6 , 10'5 p.m.) Constantinople, January 6 , 1913. {January 6 , 9*30 p.m.) (No. 9.) R. TEHRAN telegram No. 3 Minister for Foreign Affairs says that no Turks have been sent to districts mentioned, and implied there was certainly no intention of doing so. He said that it was possible that there were disputes going on between Turkish and Persian tribes on that frontier. He added that the Turkish Ambassador at Tehran had refused to receive note of protest. (Sent to Tehran.) 7 JAN1913 rDt* 151—99roNFIDKNTIAI. T bir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey .— (Received January 6 , 10*15 p.m.) St. Petersburgh, January 6 , 1913. (No. 5.) R. j (January 6 , 9*18 p.m.) YOUR telegram No. 9 Minister for Foreign Affairs expressed thanks for instructions sent to Sir G. Lowther in yonr telegram No. to Constantinople. He has already instructed the Russian Ambassador to enquire into the matter.‘CONFIDENTIAL. Si?' Edward Grey to Sir G. Lowther (Constantinople). &lt; ' N °' Foreign Office, January 4, 1913, 2-30 p.m. SIR W. TOWNLEY’S telegram No. 3 of 2nd January. If your Russian colleague is instructed to enquire and to remonstrate, should the facts be as stated, you should support him. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 8.)</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100040903645.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/430/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100040903645.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/430/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 4880/1913 Pt 2 'Turco-Persian Frontier Commission: protocol of 1913'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1913/1913</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-07T22:04:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (248 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the section</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence, reports and maps relating to the 1913 Turco-Persian Frontier Commission, and the production of the
                           Protocole relative à la Délimitation turco-persane, signé à Constantinople le 4 (17) Novembre, 1913.The primary correspondents are: HM Consul-General at Teheran (Sir Walter Beaupre Townley); HM Consul-General at Constantinople; HM Vice-Consul at Kashr-i Shirin (E B Soane); the India Office Political Department; the Turkish Minister for Foreign Affairs (Said Halim); the Russian Consul-General in Baghdad (M Orlof); the Russian Ambassador to the UK (Count Von Benckendorff); HM Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Sir Edward Grey); and Albert Charles Wratislaw, head of the British section of the Commission.The file opens with correspondence regarding reported Turkish military build-up in Kasr-i Shirin [Qaṣr-e Shīrīn], disturbances on the Baghdad-Kermaāshāh route, local raids by Persian and Turkish tribesmen, possible concessions to Turkey in the Zohab [Zohāb] district, and the difficulty of reaching an agreement which would be acceptable to Sunni and Shia tribes in the Zohab region. A map of the Zohab region is included at folio 305.The bulk of the file concerns arrangements for the Frontier Commission, discussing: the push for a settlement; the composition of the British, Russian, Turkish and Persian commissions; the need to use surveying and triangulation to improve on pre-existing, inaccurate maps; the wording of the internal rules [
                           Règlement Intérieur] to govern the Commission; arrangements over work to be conducted by the northern and southern sections of the Commission; and arrangements to preserve the rights of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company in regions to be transferred to Turkey.Key items:Folios 224-29 Declaration regarding the frontier, signed by Sir Edward Grey and I Hakky Pasha, with four accompanying maps:Map No 1, Sketch Map showing Turco-Persian Frontier West and South of Hawizeh [Howeyzeh];Map No 2, Sketch Map of Muhammareh [Khorramshar] to indicate the Turco-Persian Boundary;Map No 3, Sheet No I, Map of Shatt-Al-'Arab &amp; Bahmanshir [Rūdkhāneh-ye Bahmanshīr] including Muhammareh [Khorramshar] &amp; 'Abbádán I [Ābādān];Map No 4, Sheet No II, Map of Shatt-Al-'Arab &amp; Bahmanshir, including Muhammareh &amp; 'Abbádán I.Folios 68-87 Copy of the
                           Protocole relative à la Délimitation turco-persane, signé à Constantinople le 4 (17) Novembre, 1913,plus: additional copies of the four maps detailed above; Annex (A),
                           Règlement intérieur de la Commission de Délimitation de la Frontière turco-persane; Annex (B) Statement by the Ottoman Government pledging to maintain, within the territories granted by Persia to Turkey, the rights and obligations granted to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Ltd by the Persian Imperial Government under the Convention of 28 May, 1901; also included are notes on the meetings of the frontier delegates at Constantinople, 4-9 November, written by the British Commissioner, Albert Charles Wratislaw.Folio 67 is a collection header sheet, giving the subject heading and a list of correspondence references found within the part, listed by year.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100040903645.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>