<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100054608681.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-29T09:13:53.067Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">&amp; !a jV O In any farther communication on this subject, please quote No. 35 285/285/16 and address, not to any person by name, but to— d^The Under-Secretary of State,” .(jb) Foreign Office, London, S.W.I. r&gt; \y‘ J /&lt; f ' Foreign Oeeice. S.W.I. January 10th 1921. Sir, .1 am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to, iax'orm you that the Government of the Soudan are anxious to re-acquire the services of Lieutenant-Colonel F.C. Balfour in the post of Assistant Director of Intelligence at Khartoum, Lord Curzon understands that Colonel Balfour he s applied to be released from his present appointment in Mesopotamia, and I am to request that no difficulties may be placed in his way. I am, +. Sir, Your most obedient, humble s e rvan t, ■' . .A \ LX j J a.’i i •• The tinder Secretary of State, India Office. 1 I(P. 6856) From Secretary of State to Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, 11th September 1920. Priority A. 1598. Do you approve of Balfour or Mackie taking over charge of Mesagent for a month ? Stephenson much in need of rest. From Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, 12th September 1920. )P. p856 2771 11087. Your telegram dated 11th September. Mesagent. No objection. From Secretary of State to Civil Commissioner, Baghdad p. 6856 2ird 8e Ptember 1920. 9 1956. Your telegram of 11th SectemW nns? nr charge 22nd September. ’ ' Vesagent. Balfour assumed From Secretary of State to High Commissioner. Mesopotamia, ^ ao , a 22nd October 1920. P. 6856 abonfm 1 ,: . My t tel ^am of 23rd September, 1956. Mesagent Stephenson about to return to duty here, have you any instructions for Balfour ?INDEX e0 la any further commumea' fcion on this subject, please quote piQ. /W- /1919, / and address— 7 4-^ The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. j-y'-tvrrajvw. fV iv r :t o ^ D ri v-4 THE Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Ojfice, ,2 , 1919. Letter Reference to previous correspondence from ^° re ^o n Office : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. / /?y n Subject. (Similar letter sent toCOPY. BO. 164. (4643). 'I \l s ? w ' r* r 25 ' SHE HESIttEBOSti V GAIKO. 21 at April, 191,}, Lord, V ith re fore iao e to my telegram So *508 of April the 5 th, I have the honour to aeud a eopy of a further despatch received from the Governor General of the Sudan regarding the pension contributions of Sudan Government officials lent to the Ae aopotamian Adminis tra tion. Xiith the despatch is enclosed a table showing the salaries on which the pension of each of the officials concerned would be calculate .1. I have the honour to be • with the highest respect, I^r Lord, Your Lordship*s most obedient, humble servant, (8gd) E. ALLEJ3BY. i, ■ 1 The Light Honourable 2arl Curson of Zo dies ton, 11. d*, G.C.8.I., G.u.I.K., etc *, etc., etc. : , j ! IH r • y — ifrT^ 80 YEKW 0 H OE:S»Al*S OFFICE, SUDAH aoVEMMEE!!!, KHABTOUK. Sth April, 1919. jn continuation of ray telograia Bo,lob of i»pril 3rci, and with refe renco to despatch Ho.olb4S/lOO/W9 of 6th October 1918 fron Officiating Civil Comnisaioner, Baghdad, and copy of letter :;o.r,b077, dated 19th December 1918, from the India Office, relative to the Pension contributions to be paid on account of officials lent the Sudan Government for employment in eaopotamia, I have the honour to inform you that the Sudan Government agrees to accept an • anual cash contribution at the rate of one sixth oi a-1 r, , as a . temporary measure, until the status of the liesopotamla Administra- , tion has been definitely settled, or for a total absence of six ^ years from the Sudan, whichever my turn out to be the shorter period. At the end of that period the Sudan Government will be prepared to provide a pension for the official calculated at one , forty-eighth fer ..oh y~f » f th ° ■'“**“ '‘ 1 “ J ” J to. been Boning for the tot to y»r. to h. r.noin.i in the I audan, IThis pension will Repaid on rds retirement from ■„o S ot*ia ferric. » nUn «*» «• 1,0 “““V 1 ited on is given in the attached tible. »,i, leares no hrori.i.n »r W period of e.rrio. »dor I tl. inoopotomi. hd.lni.tr.Uon euhooou.nt to the dot. .hor. [ n that time the neBopotanu.a mentioned. But it is presumed that by th Admitlstrotion ■All to. it. ponoion U» or 'HI '» “ * poeition to »b. provision for the further P-toon of «he»o officials» / f Bie His Excellency, The High G oimaio 3 io ne r, Residency, Cairo, 1 Jdittt MMeptunce toy the Sudan Government of the oontrlhutlon io sixth after a period of six years would involve considerable ln the 0Tont of the officials being retained in Mesopotamia ^long time or being permanently transferred. The annual cash contributions due from the Mesopotamia Admihistru^on to the Sudan Government under the above scheme would be as shewn in the attached statement. It is, or course, understood that these cash contributions shall be in final settlement of all pensionary liabilities of the Mesopotamia Administration in respect of the limited period of service pantianed. X have the honour to be, • Sir, Your Excellency’s most obedient servant, ( 3 ga) LEE S-JACK, Major-General, Acting Governor-General ox^tneaway Immediate and Confidential. (No. a ) 4-^' / c&gt; a — RefcvcncB to 'pvevtous correspondence . Foreign 0(j Ri-vjy r. The Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under - Secretary oj State . .for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of X telegram l , as marked in the margin. Foreign Office, fr' igtQ vy/r . &lt;CJ ‘-A Se- Similar tetter sent t-o ll/g. Xl ^ [ ^5 a ] -4^- ^ Ufa Jp( .f h /■ No, to air M.ffi Forei'ia office, Mmrch ( •). {Cairo), , 1819. 1 ?,St; p.ra. No. ;a? of B«««*or 3oth. (Pension of Sudan officials'aorvi.^ in . atar.ia). India office auk for reply. I gather from your despatch No. 841 of October 11th that Sudan Government, hnva no object Ion to accepting proposals of hovomtseit of India as tenDorary neaeure and I think that It would be desirable to adept tills r xlutlan. IX so whsfc rate:' of contribution do Sudan ■ G-ovemnent propose. If {ill .3 .Q/A),- 1 A Kf, O' LY, fl-jcyphor Iron Genarol Allenty (Cairo) April 5th B, 9.5 p. m. April 5th. H. 5.15 p. m, * 7th. Ho.508, (H.) Your telacrm No.364. PoHovdng fra;! Khartoum Begins: Souctaa Govsnanent agrosa to the acceptance of annuity of a month’s contrihutions, at rate of one- sixth of Sudanese salary, as a temporary measure, until the status of Mesopotamia is definitely settled, or, for total absence from Soudan of six years, which ever Is the shorter period. I am sending by post further explanations with statement showing annual amount due from Mesopotamia la respect of each official under the above scheme. 1a. f fhiy BOiat Is mnt'Lom$ avoid misxmders Landing as regards the pensionable paj of and does not affect the question of any actual emoluments which he may be receiving from the Mesopotamian Adminiatratiom I sliouid be gratefal i£ yoi would hina.i.y iuuoiia ale .'aiujest7*s secretary ox* bfate .for India aocordingiy« I bar 3 the ho near to he with the highest respect, „h/ Lord, Your horiohip^ , 20 st obedient, humble hervunt. (Signed)W J ^ V. 'S': b 0 ^' */• y Ary$ £m*t foj £&amp;£C4jC6 Hid p fa y f ^*v s+y JZ'tfEZy £**-4. a*+s6 a /? ^ /i&gt;i£Zt sA^—^s /a /U^A jfrfa ^,y. 7 f- £ /fa f&lt; fa‘ ft fal ‘ • . /r-xr-/ &lt; r 7* fi&amp;UsfaAty f 'Til*' 0*44 CcAf 7n ^fL&gt;rrU\*f r^i^^-AZZr 3016 1913 aP ju I t &lt;P Political Secretary, If the administration of Mesopotamia is taken over by His Majesty's G-ovemment the settlement of pensionary charges in respect of officers lent by the Soudan will be a matter of interest only to the Bouden end His Majesty's Government. We need accordingly raise no objection if the Soudan Government would strongly prefer either of their own plans. But as trie Government oi India are at present administering L, 6 o 0 ootamia, arid, as Lue method oi set clement oi pensionary charge at the time oi loon is one which has the rather important advantage of disposing of the matter immediately instead of when the officer retires, perhaps many years hence, when the Government of one or both of the territories concerned may have changed I think we might mention this advantage to the Foreign Office and say that in view of it the Secretary of State in Council, while not wishing to press the point unduly^would prefer that the Government of India's proposals should be adopted and be glad to learn, for communication to that Government, what rates of contribution the Soudan Government would propose. At/ ' J J/*■'(/'.y-'t-&gt;2 /liwi 2yi i l i WW p- Li. L In any further courmunica- tion on this subject, please quote w. and address— ^ .. The Under-Seaetaiy of State, y't Foreign Office, London. I. /f s ^7 *7 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents Ins compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of 'State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned djLs2A*&amp;{t paper^ iWMnittV ■*ii l iBttl-n'f!U»iri Mi Foreign Ojjice, I 4 ) , 19 ,1* Letter Foreign Oihc Re ference to previous correspondence : C. n69 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^ ^ (l , to /Uo* aw ti U^rmikw lottm-—Register No. i/V T ‘ * X, ’olitical Department. 1 jk Letter from 1 A ■°f‘ 1 y Dated JL0 * /- **** Eec. f XfY‘ 191 r. i Formally acknowledged — Date. Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary Secretary of State.... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State Council Table. Uty- Copy to ^ ^ ikr J(&lt;rr, 1&lt;[W ■ FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY.&gt;, \ •r-i/ v -'i. &lt; ■ ' . \ No. 63 or 1918. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. ESTABLISHMENT. To The Right Honourable EDWIN MONTAGU, Mis Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Simla, the 20th September 1918. Sir, We have the honour to report that, on the recommendation of the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, we have sanctioned for Mr. B. H. Bell, Sudan Civil Service, while employed under the Civil Administration in Mesopotamia, a deputation (duty) allowance of Rs. 300 per mensem in addition to the pay he would have received under the Sudan Government, vis., £E. 840 per annum. We have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servants, Q-C5.''1918 . SIMli A. ESTABLISHMENT. No. 63, DATED THE 20th Septembee 1918. Letter lo His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Emoluments at Mr. B. H. Bell, Sudan Civil Service, while employed under the Civil Administration in Mesopotamia. ~ i’, &amp; P. Dept. ^o. 4&amp;d—16-9-13—40.I' c r tv ^, In any further communica- tijn on this subject, please quote No. il- /1018, and address— The Under-Secretaiy of State, Foreign Office, London. THE Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents Ins compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. ik. Foreign Utfiee, kfy ■ , 1918. Re ference to previous correspondence : Name and Date. X 0j[£ CouJt-6 ■ 4.. ((jt- V Similar letter sent to Subject. .)1 i^ v '&gt; *91. 1x29931/ =/44) SffilGK 0 i s 1 July 25Ui, 1918, * * Xro® to you, herewith, a copy of ft letter India Office, enclosing, a despatch irosa of India, relative to the conditions of leave a«S pension to be attached to employment in Mesopotamia of officers of the unl '-iKhui Civil Services. stoould be pliwl to receive your observations the proposals of the Govern®*nt of India as contt.ioed in the last hb on the surf!* at ions conw.*u»« of the letter from the India office. 1 , 0 ®, with great truth &amp;oa res®*^* Your iso st obedient hustle servant, i Geasral I'!* ■-¥&lt; m * # § CU0#!3# # C*C»^*U* * *A ¥ Of 1918. SIMLA . TWWJgOHHJaf. .LWBLUMi 2‘ %.y 41ft FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT ESTABLISHMENT. No. 20, dauss thb 12th AmiL 1918, Letter to Bis Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Conditions of employment in Mesopotamia of officers of the Egyptian and Soudanese Civil Services. I, ft P, Dept, Pm»—No. 751—3-4»18—49. ■ iNo. 20 op 1918. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. ESTABLISHMENT. To The Right Honoubablb EDWIN MONTAGU, Hii Majesty'* Secretary of State for India. Simla, the 12th April 1916. Sir, We have the honour to refer to yoilr Secret despatch No. 26, dated the 31st August 1917, relating to the conditions in respect of leave and pension to he attached to the employment in Mesopotamia of officers of the Egyptian _ and Soudanese Civil Services, and we * No. 5210, dated the 17th November 1917. r a i * it enclose a copy of a telegram* on the subject from the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad. 2. We agree that the pensionary rights of the officers in question should be safeguarded, and that, with this object in view, a contribution should, as suggested by you, be made by the administration of the occupied territories in Mesopotamia to the Egyptian and Soudanese Governments on the analogy of the Indian Foreign Service Rules. The rate of contribution will no doubt be settled in consultation with the Governments of Egypt and the Soudan. We are also of opinion that the officers should continue to pay the pension con tribution of 5 per cent, referred to in paragraphs 10 and 19 of the annexure (“ Conditions of Service ') to the Foreign Office letter No. W.-138783—1, dated the 30th July 1917—a copy of which accompanied your despatch,—and that such contributions should be credited to the revenues of the occupied territories in Mesopotamia. 3. As regards leave, Sir Percy Cox considers that the existing rules applicable to other officers serving in the occupied territories should govern the case of officers from Egypt and Soudan. This seems to be equitable, and should, in our opinion, be accepted : no contribution on account of leave will then be necessary. 4. Mr. Bonham Carter being a pensioner of the Soudan Government, the question of safeguarding his pensionary rights does not arise; the question of the pension, if any, to be granted in respect of his service in Mesopotamia may be left over for consideration until after the war. ““n /an ■■■■■■■ 5- Our recommendations concerning the emoluments of Messrs. Balfour and Nalder in connection with their employment in Mesopotamia weve communicated to you in our telegram, dated 24th January 1918. We have the honour to be, Sir, Tour most obedient, humble servants,Telegram, No. 5210, dated the 17th November 1917. J’rom—The Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. Secretary of State’s despatch, 31st August, 26. As regards Bonham Carter, he is already drawing maximum pension which he could obtain from Soudan Government. Does not expect any addition if he remains in adminis tration of these territories after the war. Question as. to what pension he should draw for service in administration including service during the period of war may, therefore, conveniently he left open for consideration after the war. As regards Balfour and Nalder, their services out here during the period of war should count for pension in the same way as service in Soudan. A&amp; regards leave, officials appointed from the Soudan and Egyptian services must naturally come under same rules during the. period of war as other officials serving in these territories, i.e., they are entitled to one month force leave annually and subject to military exigencies and to leave on medical certificate under the existing rules hut not to privilege leave or to furlough. Their title to the latter should remain in abeyance till end of war. r ^ N &lt; t v ii &gt;3 r 41 .344 f'H [ 19! 8 f t-. ••v***#*.-.'* 1 / TELBGRM FROM VICEROY 24th' January 1918. Lf Rpcpived 25th January lC.30.a.m. ^ F.S. Your Secret despatch 26 dated 31st August 1917. We are considering conditions of leave and pension to be attached to employment in Mesopotamia of officers from Soudan and Egypt. The question of remuneration for Balfour and Haider has^to be settled. We recommended they should get pay of grade next above theirs in Soudan service plus duty allowance of Rs. 300 a month each'*' These terms were offered them and accepted* * tohr 4/,i 6a h ^ ~/lH fr l Jt~J ( iSjojty j44 In any farther commnnication on this subject, please quote ms saujeeu, piease No. 242363/W/44 and address, Foreign Oeeice not to any person by name, but to— January 11th, 1918 “ The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, Loudon, S.W.l. Sir: - With reference to your letter of the 22nd ultimo, relative to the proposed employment of Mr. Nalder in Mesopotamia, I am directed hy Mr. Secretary Balfour to state that he presumes that the salary and allow- ances of this official will he charged to Basrah Revenues and that your Department will recover from the Revenue Office at Bagdad the sum claimed in respect of his passage to Bombay. I am to add that Mr. Balfour cannot trace any statement of the actual terms of this appointment which was decided on the recommendation of the Mesopotamia Committee am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant The Under Secretary of State India Office.. ■I ^ \ / [This Document is the Property of His BritanBfc Majesty*s GcfvenimeKt, and should be returned to the Foreign Oi!ice / when done with unless required for official use.] n iTLjjjo •'Z q--&lt; &gt; j 3e cyph or . . 31 r . \ . '\fj.n; cate, ( Oair o) s Decerober olnt. 1917. D. 2 0 45.p,m a H. G.O.p.ra. No.1420. Decenter 31st. 1917 Following is renetition of telegram asked for in your telegram No,1264. Shall l)e grateful if you can lend for period of war 2 suitable men for following appointments* As President of a Chamber of Civil Court oi rirst instance for Bagdad Vilayet trie Chamber to consist of British President and 2 native members, a British lawyer knowing Arabic well and with experience or Egyptian Courts essential, he would also be a member of Civil Court of Appeal. Cecondly as members o:: Civil Court of first instance and to assist Bonham Carter in dealing witli Chari a Court a trustworthy Egyptian Mahomedan lawyer 0 Pay offered for both appointments Agyntian rates Of pay drawn by official plus rupees 300 per nonfli put I would consider liiyher rate if you consider this insufficient to obtain suitable men. Passage to and from s;ypt at Government expense. Addressed to high Cosaraissioner at Cairo repeated oo J ' 0i 3imla ;Secretary of Gtate London, .ml . J ill48) v; - 51 Foreign Office, ivate. December 27th, 1917. r My dear ShucMmrgli: - I send you, herewitli, a copy of a letter from the Treasury, relative to the proposed salary to he accorded to Major May. I imagine that May would have been receiving about £1,000 a year in the Sudan, but this point, as well as that regarding the receipt of retired.pay from the War Office, is one which I can elucidate later. So soon as we obtain this information we intend again to press the Treasury, for their con currence, pointing out that the salary proposed is a consolidated salary covering all allowances for incidental expenses, that the appointment is for the duration of the war only, and that the cost will in any case come out of Mesopotamian Revenues. Before doing so, however, I should be glad to hWTIC;* I—HI .Hi COPY. (241155) i ^ t f. icember 20th, 1917. Dear Sir Ronald Graham:- Would you be so good as to tell me, or ask someone in your branch to tell me, upon what basis the proposed salary of £2000 for Major May as Revenue Secretary in Mesopotamia was arrived at? (F.0.207465/W/44 of 2/11/17). I have tried to discover it from the India Office who refer me to you. Major May was only getting £350 a year from the Ministry of Munitions. No doubt this should be regarded as a nominal salary; but I should have thought that his Sudan salary ( which I do not know) ulus £240 as for transferred Indian officials ought to meet the case. The same basis would give Mr. Bowman (F.0.229142/W/44) £760, his Egyptian pay ulus £240 or £1,000 in all. I do not know whether Major May has any retired pay from Army funds, and though it has no bearing on the amount of salary appropriate I should be obliged if you could tell me Yours, he (Signed) J.H. Craig,x:- ' COPY. ■'(241155) , f f * *” • ^ XT 'Q’9-I ' lx \ tr ffTTTTVi rnorrji,—j~ u^ 1 ' l £Qi— &lt; ¥OIJS.]CTH— [Vi - ■) |December 20th, 1917. Dear Sir Ronald Graham:- Would you be so good as to tell me, or ask someone in your branch to tell me, upon what basis the proposed salary of £2000 for Major May as Revenue Secretary in Mesopotamia was arrived at? (F.0.207465/W/44 of 2/11/17). I have tried to discover it from the India Office who refer me to you. Major May was only getting £350 a year from the Ministry of Munitions. No doubt this should be regarded as a nominal salary; but I should have thought that his Sudan salary ( which I do not know) ulus £240 as for transferred Indian officials ought to meet the case. The same basis would give Mr. Bowman (F.0.229142/W/44) £760, his Egyptian pay ulus £240 or £1,000 in all. I do not know whether Major May has any retired pay from Army funds, and though it has no bearing on the amount of salary appropriate I should be obliged if you could tell me. Yours, &amp;c., (Signed) J.H. Craig.Jfc life.: • v V [This Pocnment is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s ^Tovernment and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done ^With unless required for official use.] 7k J6. * w X / &lt; r; . ?• 4 5 t* * £ILI]S. OIILY Dscypher„ Sir H # Uingate (Cairo) 'December 22nd, D. 9 o 10 p 0 m, Decerdoer 22nd. 1217. R. 9 a 40 o a e m o December 23rd s 1917. Nc, 1382 ©o®&lt;»!io*oeoc#ooooo : 1 # 0 U ^ f ^ ^ -a #' Your telegram Nc c 5785, 1. Is not available in Egypt or the Scudan. Temporary Captain E,M 0 Drower - formally in Khartoum - who is known to Mr 3 Os , 9 , u . a O o might be worth while considering in this connection. He is I believe new on the staff or Regimental duty in England. 2, Ministry of Justice recommends Sheikh Ahmed &amp;1 Amin, lie ia 31 years did, passed 12 years at Azhar and Cadis school, has sufficient knowledge of English and is considered promising, he would accept temporary post at 300 rcupees a month in addition to his present pay e&gt;f £16 Egyptian a month. Shall. I send him? He asks for advice as to whether he should, take wife and family with him. Would you pay their travelling expenses. Addressed t# Bagdad, Bent to Foreign Office and India 1382;' £52. L Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State to transmit to you, to be laid before Mr. Secretary Montagu , the annexed Statement, supported as far as possible by Vouchers, of Sums paid by this Office for Services chargeable to the Votes administered by your Department; and I am to request that the necessary directions may be given for the transfer of the Sum of Fifty-two Pounds to the Credit of the Vote for Diplomatic and Consular Services a l l^ e Office of His Majesty s Paymaster-General. A Receivable Order is enclosed. / am, Sir, Your most obedient, i The Under Secretary of State, [23 I^idia Office. humble Servant, 9v- 19 DEG 1817 yi mm 5°? m Station. Service. Amount. Observations. . v Cairo (September Quarter 1917) Passage of Mr. Nalder from Port Said to Bombay in connection with the 'administration of ' Mesapotamia. i'52.0.0. Reference. 1.0. letter to F.O. No. P.1977 of May 23rd 1917. Voucher annexed. I ■ vI C ] 141 . '44 In any iurther communica tion on this subject, please quote No. /191 • and^address— .Vhe Under-Secretary of State, ' Foreign Office, . London. D 4&gt; a ^W 1 W' , I'' •• - ' ^ Confidential. TtiF Under-Secretary of State for Foreign A Fairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India; and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop&gt;u &gt;0 of the under-mentioned paperi Foreign Office, , ||. , 191 y. Reference to previous correspondence : to Letter n Foreign Office : from ° Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject Atfm u UJ M 0 €£&amp;YYi£^!/}. ffi C/l U. ^8. cfo-(r]4- 'P-u-ii (Similar letter sent t&lt; •)it '' '-a^ /* &amp; % 1 f ^ COPY OF TEL3PRAM From Sir P. Cox Dated Slat October 1917. Pieceived 1st Hovember l.p.m. ^ r a 7T* 3&gt;^f ; 7 (P) 4736* Shall be grateful if you can tend . for period of war two suitable men for following appointments. First, as president of a chamber of civil Court of First Instance for Bagdad Vilayet the chamber to consist of British president and two native (s,a?). w British la\ryer knowing Arabic -well and with experience of Egyptian Courts. He would also be a member of Civil Court of Appeal. Secondly, as ,.iember of civil Court of-First Instance, and to assist Bonham Carter in dealing with Sharia Court, a trustworthy Egyptian Lohometan lawyer* Pay offered for both appointments Sgyptisn rates of pay drams by official plus rupees 300 per month but I would consider higher rate if you consider this insufficient to obtain suitable men* Passage to and from Fgypt at Government expense Addressed High Commissioner Cairo repeated Foreign Simla,, Secretary of State, London. 'i. j ; I rI t e&gt; COPY OF TFLSGRAH From Sir P. Cox Dated 313t October 1917. Received 1st Hovembar 10.30.a.m. ^ 4726. Reference to Secretary of. Stated telegram 29th October regarding Major May. Please see my telegram of 18tli May last Mo 1612 in which I urged that it was essential that officer selected should be physically active, able to tour freely and ready to associate with Arab agricultural element and be generally accessible. I trust His Majesty's Government can aaaure me that Major May possesses these qualifications. They will be especially important to him and to me now in connection with scheme in progress for increasing production in regard to which civil administration incurring considerable responsibility. Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Secretary of Stater for India. ,,- n O W- O NOV 1917 \ Vno- M 7 ( it DEPctdFrom Sir P. Cox, 24tth October 1917. (Addressed td High Commissioner, Cairo ; repeated to Secretary of State and Foreign, Simla.) (Received 25th October, 1 1.15 a.m.) 4569. I am finding considerable difficulty in finding suitable men for Subordinate Civil Staff. May I ask it you can assist me by loan of five trustworthy and competent Mohamedan officers of Egyptian Army, il possible, with previous civil administrative experience? Their duties would be similar to that of Mamurs under the Sudan Government. Pay to be fixed by you [? not exceeding] £ Egyptian 25 monthly. Term of contract one year extendable to two at our option and subject to power on my part to terminate earlier if work or conduct unsatisfactory or on suppression of appointment. Free bachelor cpiarters. Passage here and return passage on termination of contract at expense of this administration.•Zo^x+bS /\A/j ifif (1 ^ My dear Shuckburgh:- Your letter P.4270 of October 29th:- Revenue officer for Mesopotamia. The Treasury ask us privately how the pro posed salary of £2,000 compares with those of other higher officials in Irak. Have you any statement of the salaries allotted to the corresponding appointments? '/Ms ^ /{dt 1$. etsrtiy ('»■ foiy •18695. I. -480- l 000 - MINUTE. &lt; As regards the genesis of this appointment, Sir P. Cox, in his telegram No. 1903 of the 29th *flagged May 1917', stated his requirements in the following terms:- { H Vyhiat I need is the services of an officer of adequate weight and revenue experience as my ; Revenue Secretary or Staff Officer, to whom I can go for advice with regard to revenue questions and can give supervisory powers over the working ox both vilayets to ensure consistency of treatment.” The Secretary of State for India supported the proposal as a temporary measure; but the task of finding a suitable officer, with Egyptian experience, to fill the post has proved very difficult, and the Foreign Office are only now in a position to make a definite recommendation. I have discussed the matter with Sir R. Graham, who is satisfied that Major May is well qualified for the appointment. As regards remune ration, the amount proposed (£2,000 a year) is slightly less than what was given to Mr. Bonham Carter as Senior Judicial Officer, Bagdad, (£2,240 per annum*); but it is substantially more than the emoluments drawn oy the two (comparatively) junior Punjab civilians, Messrs. C.C.Garbett and A. L. Gordon Walker, who i at present represent the chief revenue authority in the Occupied districts, and will presumably be Major May’s principal assistants. We have no precise details as to what these two officers are actually drawing; but I understand from the Financial Department that Mr. Garbett probably receives at least Rs. 1200 per mensengand Mr. Walker at least Rs. 1100 per mensem^ plus the usual Mesopotamian *This amount was also offered to General Clayton, as Chief Assistant to the Chief Polit ical Officer - a post which he declined.Mesopotamian local allowance of Rs. 300 per mensem, their emoluments thus working out at Rs. 1500 per mensem (£1200 per annum) and Rs. 1400 per mensem (£1120 per annum), respectively. .Major May f s salary, &amp;c., will he chargeable to Basra revenues, the surplus balance of which goes to the Treasury, so that the Indian exchequer is not affected one way or the other. c 0 Leu cJ ^ j «Draft Paper. Department. Draft to F.O. IMMEDI ATE. Sir, , . In repl}^ to your letter of the 23rd October 1917, No. 198137/W/44, regarding the appointment of an officer to act as Revenue Secretary CivLL or Adviser to the •6hi.eC Commissioner, Mesopotamia, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to inform you that he concurs in the proposal of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to offer the post to Major May, formerly of the Sudan Financial Department^ and at present in the employ of the Ministrv of Munitions. As regards the emoluments to be offered to Major May, the question is one that has no direct concern for the Secretary of State for India in Council, inasmuch as, like other expenses of the Mesopot amian administration, they are payable from the revenues of Basra, the surplus balance of which is [ NMtn/- credited to the Imperial Exchequer. But -Lord-I i ngton- goo q. ■ no -r oaeon .tu-domirp- W the figure proposed (£2,000 per annum)/, provided it is made clear that the salary is a consolidated one, and must be held to cover any local or other allow ances1 ances 10 which hajar May might otherwise consider himself entitled, with the exception of travelling allowances at the authorised rates. ( It might also he explained to Major May that his appointment, and the remuneration attaching to it, must be regarded as provisional only and subject to reconsideration at the close of the war l/h' / h twyesn/t' HluC (J- Cry J ^ ^2 Aiuaj o yiCEf b&gt; i 1 &gt; .jiI / Telegram from Sir Percy Cox, Dated 28th October,1917. Received at India Office.. 8 p.m. CLEAR THE LINE. * 4671. Plesse see correspondence ending with your telegram 25rd 1315 of August regarding despatch of Holmes or other officer to my staff as Revenue authority. Time is pressing end I am in X- urgent need of the officer. If Holmes is appointed could he corns at once ? Kindly reply ’’Clear the Line” by 12 noon to-morrow if passible. Addressed to Foreiji,Simla, repeated to Secretary of State for India. Mfi. 7U Jjfiu-A. nd (tl- c i^UCi^ (i) Uz ft. B , a- lA^Vav&gt;— CaS\J ( /'-£*-''1'''- — iuUxyi ti IZur ' : &lt;n ' lyT.A.C. ^ O.P. Cx/,k^~- i CtA c^C-N P-- . -am i/l LA i v -: In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. 198137/W/44. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. $ £a , 000 Foreign Office October 2Sr*d, 1917. I Confidential. Wltli reference to my letter of the 1st instant, relative to the appointment of a Revenue Officer in Mesopotamia, I am directed, by Dm Secretary Balfour to transmit to you, herewith, a copy of a telegram from His majesty*s High Commissioner for Egypt, suggesting that Ha3or Lay,, now working in the ^ ministry of Munitions, would be suitaole for this appointment. The question has been submitted to Lord Curzon who concurs as to the desirability ox appointing major May to this post,and colonel Bernard, who hem. also been consulted, considers him to oe extremely suitable for this appointment. Mr. Balfour understands also that Major May would himself oe glad to accept such employment, ana in these circumstances hr. Balfour would propose, subject to the concurrence of Lord Islington, oo make him a definite offer of the appointment ana oo fix his salary and allowances at a total oi Two thousand pounds per annum. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, The under Secretary oi State, India Office. 1L I]J t C ] 1 Fn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Confidential. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned 1 paper. Foreign Office, e'jvXja^^'-eA. 1 ’ 1917. * Reference to previous correspondence : Letter from Foreign Jffice : 2 / Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. N 'L , d ; w 7 ; ^ ''v 0 CA: V'' M-jvj. ii'i Subject Similar letter sent to •)should be for official use. ert y of His Britaimic Majest y^ Governmeiit, and Foreign Office when done with unless required T1i r*, p r : cs 0 U FILES ONLY Cypher telegram to Sir H« hingate (Ramleh) Foreign Office c ' September 20th, 1917 lot 909, 9 C 30 p„m, Your telegram No, 664 (of June 22nd), (Administration of Mesopotamia) B I think Colonel Bernard is somewhat too senior for post. Can you suggest any other candidate, and man with from 12 to 15 years service would be suitable ^Cnrry to lutiifi i a' v ] s 11 Ojv i? Ito* -13 J Telegram from Viceroy, Foreign Department, Bated 28th A%ust, 1917, Received 29th August, 10*45 a.ra. Shuckburgh* Officers for Mesopotamia. Reference to India Office letter to Foreign Office P*2229, June 13th. How does question of appointment of Revenue Secretary stand? Is Senior Officer from India likely to be required? Wood. \o L\r O (Jc fa f to*In any further ooiiuuuuiea- rion on tlus subject, please quote No. w {(riotej /i9i7 »nd *ttr«s— The Under-Secretary of State ? Foreign O^ce, London. •i -v. A c ' .4 Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents is compliments to the and, by direction of the Secretary s of State, transmits herewith cop Uo of the under-mentioned paper Fn reig n ( ce, 4 Jj. Z# , IQU Reference to previous correspondence Letter to Foreign Office: iio. P.ZLf/Fp f- Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Si. ic s ’* 6 jur y/1* ' '&gt;|lliis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s GoverpmeEit, 2 nd shoiilci_be returned, to tlie Forei^a Office whea done with unless required lor official use.'j (166647/17) FIXES ONLY . Cypher telegran to Sir R 0 v/ingate (Ramieh), Foreign Office. August 28th, 1917. 6,30 p* No. 845. m.COPY OP &gt;EG ■*' From CoXj, Dated 22/8/1? Received at India Office Q 23 re Kindly inform me when Bonlvwn Carter may be expected *1 / INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.f.I. Jm 3/ August, 1917 • My Lord, In continuation of previous correspondence on the subject of the ILDIA SKCHET . NO. Co - civil administration of Mesopotamia, I forward for the information of Your Excellency’s Government copy of the o E•O.Lo.P.2493A, 12th July, 1 Mr.Bonham-Carter,12th v»nwi M ** 1 A+.Vl ** marginally-noted correspondence^- regarding the appointment of Mr. Edgar Bonham-Carter, C.M.G., Legal 14th ' rom F.O-No.1.158783, 30th w with enclosure. Secretary to the Sudan Administration to be Senior Judicial Officer, Bagdad / You will have learnt from Sir R. Wingate’s telegram ho.741 of the 15th July, 1917, copy of which was communicated to your Foreign and Political Department by the mail of the 26th idem, that two other officers of the Sudanese Service, viz Messrs. F.C.C.Balfour and L.F.Nalder, have also been appointed to oa am 1911 Mesopotamia. The actual terms of their appointment have not been communicated to me. I shall be glad to receive tha recommendations of Your Excellency’s Government as to the conditions in respect of lea.ve and pension to be attached to the employment of these officers, and of any other civil officers who may hereafter be appointed to Mesopotamia in similar circumstances. In ther - ( : I y ^fe! case of the present and any other officers who may be temporarily lent to Mesopotamia from the Egyptian, or the Sudanese, Civil Service, the simplest course would appear to be that a contribution towards the pension ultimately admissible from Egyptian or Sudanese funds in respect of the period of loan should be made by the Administration of the occupied territory in Mesopotamia to those funds during the period in question on the analogy of the provisions in Chapter AjJdx of your C.3.R, A suitable amount of leave might be given to them by the Mesopotamian Administration, so that the question of a contribution for leave need not arise* If you concur in these suggestions, I will submit them to the Foreign Office. Ho special arrangements as regards leave or pension seem to be required in the case of officers belonging to the Levant Service who may be temporarily employed under the Mesopotamian Administration* A copy of this despatch is being sent direct to the Chief Political Officer, Baghdad. Jh rs C-'T* Tin 7 tea 7JlCC,l\&gt;e 110 22 AUG 1917ot~ \ 103 •vo- In any further communication on the subject, please quote No. W.138783/17. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. iM 0 1811 2 i Foreign Office July 30th, 1917. Sir: - In reply to your letter, P.2493 A., of the 12th instant, relative to the conditions of leave and pension applicable to officers in the Egyptian and Sudanese Civil Services, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to transmit to you, herewith, the accompanying paper which contains the information required. Mr. Balfour understands that in regard to leave in the Sudan, Civil Servants are allowed three months a year dating from their actual departure from Cairo. I am to suggest that further details regarding conditions of civil employment in the Sudan could be obtained from: Sir A. ./ebb, K.C.M.G., Queen Anne T s Chambers, Broadway, O.. 1. I arm, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, 31 jul jgjA l Til % ^ The Under Secretary of State, India Office. x VV y /v\. oi c x ^ ^ ’• 11 i ® 17 ; L I v/ I lADDENDA. Paragraph 3.— (va) By members oi‘ the University of Wales, through the Appointments Board for Wales, University Registry, Cathay’s Park. Cardiff. Paragraph 8 .—-the Appointments Board for Wales before March 1 .* Information to Candidates. 1-—-Applicants for appointments in the above Services must be over 22 and Eligibility Widex J^ 5_Years of a»'e on OctohenJ of the year in which they stand for selection, for Service ' and have completed or be about to complete their University course. 2 . —Persons not fulfilling these requirements can only be accepted if they possess special qualifications or if they are required to fill special posts. 3. —Application for appointments should be made:— Channel of Application. (i) By members of the University of Oxford, through the Appointments Committee of that University ; (ii) By members of the University of Cambridge, through the Cambridge Appointments Board ; (iii) By members of the University of Trinity College, Dublin, through the Trinity College, Dublin, Appointments Committee ; (iv) By members of the University of London, through the Appointments Boards of the University oi- of University College ; (v) By members of the University of Edinburgh, through the University Appointments Committee, Edinburgh ; (vi) Candidates belonging to none of the above should apply direct to the Secretary to the Selection Board, Ministry of Finance, Cairo. 4. —Gentlemen desiring to become candidates will, on application to one of the Method of above sources, be furnished with a list of questions which they will be required to Applymg ' fill up and send in with their formal applications through the channels before- mentioned. A certificate of birth must be attached. 5. —Certificates and recommendations, to have any weight with the Board, Certificates must be given by properly qualified persons who have a personal knoAvleclge of the References, candidate. Recommendations from persons, however highly placed socially or politically, who do not know the candidate personally, are worthless. 6 . —As the selection is based on the general fitness and capability of the candidates as well as on their intellectual and other attainments, certificates and recommendations should not only deal wdth a man’s educational career, but also refer to his general character and qualifications. 7 . —ft shoiTld further be distinctly understood that no inquiry is made, nor is any information desired, respecting a candidate’s religions or political views. The Egyptian Government is not concerned with such matters, and they are not taken into aceount. 8 . —All applications must reach the Appointments Committee, Oxford, Date of before March 1 ; the Appointments Board, Cambridge, . before March 1 ; the l^pSions Appointments Committee, Trinity College, Dublin, before March 25 ; the Appointments Board of London University before April 1 ; the Appointments Board of University College, London, before March 1 ; the University Ap pointments Committee, Edinburgh, before March 15, _ by whom they will be forwarded to the Secretary to the Selection Board, Cairo, so as to reach him before April 15. Applications not forwarded through one of the Appointments Committees must also reach the Secretary to the Selection Board before April 15. 9 . A Committee appointed ad hochy the Ministries concerned sifts the records provisional of candidates, eliminating the less eligible, and leaving a number approximating to Selection, four times the vacancies to be filled.— 2 — Examination 10.— of candidates thus provisionally selected will be sent to the Medical xamma ion. ]^ oar( | j n L onc i on w ho will fix a date for the medical examination and inform the candidates when and where they must attend. Rejection on Medical Grounds. Final Selection. 11. —On receipt of the medical reports, the Secretary will inform by letter thoscy,. who are rejected as medically unfit. 12 . —The remaining candidates will be interviewed by the Final Selection Board which will meet annually in London in August. Notice of the date of meeting will be sent to each of these candidates. In.—The members of the Board will be furnished with a complete set of the candidates records, and each candidate will be interviewed personally. Service tn —Candidates will be asked at the interview whether they have preference EgyptVr 1 f° r service in Egypt or the Sudan. According to their statement they will be in the Sudan, placed either on the Egyptian or the Sudan list. Candidates are reminded that any subsequent change in their wishes cannot be taken into consideration. If no preference is stated, it will be considered that the candidate is willing to serve under either Covernment. Publication 15.—Tdie list of the selected candidates is published in the Times newspaper as of Successful S00 ! 1 U &gt; S possible after the meeting of the Board, and simultaneously the selected men Candidates, are informed of their success by the Secretary. Uonar P Year ■ 1 G -“' S ' lccessfnl candidates will be required to spend a probationary year at r 5 e,n - Oxford or (Cambridge at their own expense to study Arabic, and will communicate with the Professor of Arabic at either Oxford or Cambridge who will forward information as to the books required and the date of the commencement of the lectures, etc. 1 ‘ • -I)uling the probationary year candidates will further be required to attend courses of instruction in First Aid, elementary surveying, and such other subjects as may horn time to time be ordered by the Selection Board in accord with the U niversity authorities. Proficiency in subjects other*than Arabic is not obligatory. Lecturers fees will be paid by the Egyptian Government. It is desirable that candidates should be able to ride, and those who are not accustomed to riding should take lessons. A sound knowledge of French is most useful, if not indispensable, in Egypt. , . G knowledge of Military Drill, Musketry, and Care of E&lt;]uipment, is extremely desirable m the Sudan. ^ Arabic and Second Medical 18. —On the completion of their year of probation the candidates will be required to P as f »“ examination in Arabic, the results of which determine seniority. They Examinations, igl a so be re-examined by the Medical Board in order to ascertain if their state Approval Of or health is still satisfactory. ! he result of these two examinations will be laid Board!° n before the Selection Board for the current year, who will approve or reiect the probationary candidates. J 19. —The probationary candidates, after having been approved, will be mven mhti uctions by the Secretary as to where they should report themselves in either itgy pf or the Sudan, together with such information as may be necessary concernino' their outfit, etc. ^ o Candidates Eligible for Posts in Agricultural 20 ble if requir Candidates not selected by the Board, but recommended by them, are eliyi- ured for posts in the Agricultural Bank of Egypt.I o Conditions of Service. let H Sf f Board lee %i| Softie Police ey til ^ inded flat &gt;n- If do &gt; to serre '^paperas ectedinea 7 year at ' iniunicate fomnl it of tie to attend ibjectsas ffitl tie Egatory, ' are not Egypt [tremely •quired Tliey • eir state be laid ject tie » oiven a either cerning ■eeligi- (a) EGYPTIAN CIVIL SERVICE. - 1 .—Accepted candidates must be unmarried on arriving in the counh-v n„d will enter on a further period of probation for one year at 7 ea s t, or two vi’rs at most, in the Department to which they may be appointed. r y n!ess otherwise informed at the time of their selection they will be appointed to one of the Departments of the Ministries of Finance or Interior. , A ' l' 1 ' principal Departments of the former are those chamed with the administration of the Land Tax, the State Lands, the State Accounts, the Audit the Customs, the Post Office, and the Survey. 4.—Hie Ministry of the Interior comprises Departments charged with Public Security, Prisons, Municipal Services, Personnel, and the Press. ^ th , e M i ni . stries at Cairo certain high administrative posts are held by Englishmen of sufficient seniority. In the provinces Englishmen are employed as Inspectors and Sub-Inspectors. 1 hey have to supervise the work of the Native officials, to see that orders are punctually carried out, to report to Headquarters and to make enquiries and investigations if required. Inspectors and Sub-Inspectors ot the Interior are chiefly concerned with public security and the supervision of the administrative system, while the duties of Inspectors and Sub-Inspectors of Finance are principally in connection with the land tax and the sale and renting of State -lands. Ihe life in the provinces is in the main an open air one, and the work is interesting and important, and is carried on in healthy conditions. The climate, though somewhat hot in the summer months, is very agreeable during the greater part of the } eai. Rest-houses are provided for the accommodation of Inspectors, and travel I nig . allowances are granted. there are a few posts for yoiin°' English officials in the Accounts and Audit sections in Cairo. f •—The minimum rate of salary on appointment is L.E. 240* per annum. At the end of two years’ service, if confirmed in their appointments, officials will be promoted to a salary of L.E. 336 per annum. Further promotion must depend on the efficiency of the official concerned, but under normal circumstances an Inspector of six or seven years’ service would probably be drawing from L.E. 500 to L.E. 600 a year. There are a number of higher posts with salaries ranging to L.E. 1,500 whiclr are generally filled by promotion. 7. — Officials are liable to he transferred, when the interest of the service requires it, from the provinces to Headquarters, or vice versa, or from one Department to another, either on promotion or otherwise. 8 . —During the period of probation the services of an official may he dispensed with if he is not likely to prove a successful civil servant. In this case he will be given a sum equal to a month’s pay in lieu of passage money to Europe. Having passed the period of probation, he can only he deprived of his appointment on account of ill-health, misconduct, or suppression of post. 9. —Subject to the exigencies of the service, furlough (which may not he taken the first year) is given for two months every year on full pay, and a third month may he allowed on half pay. After fifteen years’ service, two and a half months full pay leave may be taken each year. Leave may be accumulated, but not more than three and a half months may be taken in any one year. 10.—All salaries are subject to a 5 per cent reduction for pension. Pensions are granted on voluntary retirement at the age of 55 after a minimum service of fifteen years ; also at any time after fifteen years completed service in the case of retirement from medical unfitness, on suppression of post from motives of economy, or by special decision of Council of Ministers. In these latter cases, if the service is under fifteen years, lump sum indemnities are given at gradually increasing rates, in proportion to the length of service. The rate of pension is based on the mean salary drawn during the last two years of service and is calculated at the rate of one-sixtieth for each year of service, with a maximum of two-thirds of the mean pay above-mentioned ; the pension in no case to exceed L.E. 800. Families of deceased officials enjoy certain specified rights to pension or indemnity. * L.E. 1 = £1 0s. 6d.It ! r (b) SUDANESE CIVIL SERVICE-. H,— A selected candidate, who has successfully completed his course at a University, will, on joining, be appointed Third Inspector with pay at the rate of L.E. 420 per annum, and will be considered on probation for the first two years of his service. During this period, if found unsuitable owing to ill-health or any other cause, his services may be dispensed with, subject to his being given two months’ notice of the intention to do so. In this case, he will be given a free passage to England, should he desire to go there, and a gratuity of fifteen days’ pay. If before the expiration of the above-mentioned two years’ probation the Go vernment decides that a Third Inspector shall serve a further period on probation before he is accepted as a permanent official, and the Inspector concerned accepts to serve for such further period on probation, it shall be open to the Government, during such further period of probation, to dispense with his services in the same manner and upon the same terms as during the first two years of the probation. On being selected, candidates will be required to sign a declaration to the effect that they accept the above conditions. 12.—Inspectors are guaranteed the following minimum increases of pay, pro vided that their services and conduct are satisfactory. A I bird Inspector is in addition required to pass examinations in Law and Arabic in his first two years of service before qualifying for increase of pay to L.E. 480. Third Inspector| 9 1 ,. 1 ••• - 1 | Alter completing 2 L.E. years service Second Inspector First Inspector- 4 6 8 10 12 14 5? 5? 5? 55 420 480 600 660 720 780 840 900 All promotions to appointments carrying with them more pay than L.E. 900 shall be entirely by selection. 13. —In most provinces, there is an appointment carrying with it the title of Senior Inspector ; such appointment will be held by the Inspector specially selected as Senior Assistant to the Governor of the Province. The Inspector so selected will, whilst filling the appointment, be Senior to every other Inspector of the Province. 14. —As vacancies occur, Senior and First Inspectors are eligible for selection to fill the appointment of Governor of a Province, which carries with it a salary of L.E. 1,000 to L.E, 1,200. 15. —All increases of pay are granted on, and dated from, January 1 . 16. —On first appointment, an Inspector will be stationed at Khartoum for a period of about three months or longer, and will there be instructed in his future duties before being posted to one of the provinces. 17. —An Inspector of a province sits as a Magistrate to deal with criminal and civil cases; he has also to investigate complaints, to supervise the collection of revenue, and the manner in which the Police carry out their duties. He will be compelled to lead an active life, and much of his time will be spent in travelling- on horse and camel back. 18. —If the exigencies of the service permit, leave of absence from the Sudan is granted (after the first year) at the rate of ninety days per annum counting from the date of an official's arrival at Cairo or Suez from the Sudan until his return to either of those places from leave, according to the route he takes. 19. —An Ordinance for regulating the pensions and retirement of officials is in force. A deduction of 5 per cent per annum is made from the salaries of all pensionable officials as a contribution towards pension. Voluntary retirement w ™with pension is permitted after 45 years of age, provided the official has completed twenty years service. The pension is calculated on the average of the salaries drawn during the last three years of effective service at the rate of one forty- eighth. of such average for each year of service, and shall in no case exceed two-thirds of such average nor a maximum of L.E. 800. In the case of retirement on the ground of ill-health or suppression of post, a pension is obtainable after twelve years’ service. Pensionable officials having less than twelve years’ service obtain a gratuity equivalent to one and a half months’ pay for each year of service up to seven years, and three months for each year over seven and up to twelve. 20.—The climate varies considerably in different parts of the Sudan, and is trying for Europeans, especially south of the latitude of Khartoum in the rainy districts. . lo the north of Khartoum, although very hot in summer, it is drv and comparatively healthy. 21-—There are at present very few places where an English lady can live in reasonable comfort. Candidates must, therefore, not be married or engaged to be married, and the Government will probably dispense with the services of an official who becomes so during his period of probation. On being selected, candidates will be required to sign a declaration to the effect that they accept the above conditions. 22 .—It is very desirable that selected candidates should arrive in the Sudan with a knowledge of the Government Regulations, and they are consequently advised to obtain a copy of the “Administrative Regulations,” which can be obtained from Sir Arthur Webb, K.C.M.G., Queen Anne’s Chambers, Broadway, Westminster, London, S.W., price 3/6. Note on the Employment of British Officers Attached to the Egyptian Army for Service in the Sudan Government. The Sudan Service will be recruited from civilian sources, subject to the employment of British officers serving in the Egyptian Army, under the following conditions •t A certain number of British officers of the Egyptian Army are employed for temporary service in the Sudan Government. Such officers will be, as far as possible, selected from those who have served at least tw T o years in the Egyptian Army. The Government may, at its discretion, occasionally retain for permanent service any officer employed under the conditions stated above wdio has shown special capacity for civil work and whose retention is eminently^ desirable in the interests of the public service; but the seniority of such officer shall be fixed in such a position as may be considered equitable compared with officials already in the permanent service. CAIRO. June 1913.^ ^ further commumca- p- 'tior ^'subject, please quote No. &amp; 5 ~P - 3 ^ / 1917 , and address— If The U :r-Secretary of State, brek jreign Office, London. ■v # P281°/ 7 \ 08 ^ H 2S 1° THE Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop te-c? of the under-mentioned Foreign Office, .1917. Reference to previous correspondence : to Letter ^ rom Foreign Office : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subj ect5, HYDE PARK SQUARE, W. 2 , July 31st, 1917, My Lord:- Some days ago I received from the India Office the formal confirmation of my appointment as Senior Judicial Officer Baghdad, and I gather that I am desired to take up my duties at Baghdad as soon as possible, I propose accordingly to leave England on the 9th August. Although the Gezira negotiations, for which I was sent to England by Sir Reginald Wingate, are not yet complete, they have reached a stage when my continued presence in England seems no longer necessary. As arranged with the India Office I propose to stop for a few days in Egypt on the way to Mesopotamia in order • to enable me to visit Khartoum and wind up my official affairs I have, etc., (Signed) Edgar Bonham Carter. * The Rigjht Honourable The Lord Hardinge of Penshurst, Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. ppy, (1506^3V ''A. TURNBULL, GIBSON &amp; INDIA OFFICE SHIPPING AGENTS. C : 3 S 0 H M o'.. - Telegraphic Address: Telephone No. “AFFRETER, ALD. LONDON. 1 ' AVENUE 5701 (3 Lines). 21, BURY STREET, ST. MARY AXE, And at LLOYD’S. LONDON, E.C. 24th July 1917. P.&amp; S.DEPT. THe Director General of stores, India Office. I Iks® Dear Sir, in reply to your enquiry regarding Mr.B.Bonham carter*s first class passage to Bombay, the P. &amp; 0. steamers in August will hej- From London . prom Marseilles , s. s. w M00LTA1T m about 16th August. about 7/lo days later, s.s. 'MALWA' ” 3Oth « ' 7/10 ' the fare being £50 'B” from Marseilles to Bombay and £l0-l0-0» by the P. &amp; 0. Special train London to Marseilles. The journey can be broken en route and Mr.Bonham carter could disembark at port Said and continue his voyage to Bombay by a later steamer. The free baggage iuLlowance is 3 cwts. and the one or two cases ot books could be sent with any heavy baggage to the steamer before she leaves London. We are, Dear sir, yours faithfully *4^- /GO Should Mr.Carter not have ma’’^^ cconmodation]) cost/£56. \ ‘go—- -•wSSM ——* -ir, ^fflf USSOPOTteJIA AmiMISTRATION COMITTEK 123 i%‘ Sir P. Gox^ Staff. 1 . TELEGRA M - Secretary of State to Viceroy and Sir PoCox, 20 June., 191? Foreign secret. My telegram of 23rd May 0 Officers for Mesopotamiac Clayton unwilling to accept and in view of political objections to his removal from Egypt at present juncture HoMoGovt. do not propose to press him further 0 - Wingate is being urged to find substitute with suitable qualificationso Failing that 8 can Cox make any suggestion? Is Dobbs available if health permits? 2 . - Foreign Office to Sir Ro Wingate D No 0 615 ? 20 June 191?o Your telegram Hoo 651 (of June IQth). General Claytono Can you suggest any other Anglo -Egyptian or Sudan official wita sufficient administrative kiiowledge ana capacity for post of Deputy Civil Commissioner in Mesopotamia and whose services will be immediately available? It is very necessary to strengthen Sir p 0 Cox's hands at the present moment by using means in our power and especially by providing him with &lt;s**pabla assistants* 3o Sir Ho Wingate to Foreign Off ice B No o 663, 22 June 191? 615 Your telegram No Storrs, who was he will shortly be quite m£uc 0 mm an invaluable - -■ — ■———~ » —— _ _ - — combination with him I would recommend employing Colonel Pearson whose long experience in the Soudan would provide the complemenuif) administrative knowledge of which Starrs is by training defieiento If this oroposal is concurred in I would arrange matters with Acting Governor General of the Soudan,, Pearson now draws pay £1,100 Egyptian per annum exclusive of all allowances. 4. Tun’.RSRAW - Sir Pc Cox to Secretary of State, Hoo2255, 22 June 191?, Reference to Secretarv of State’s telegra*a 22nd June„ Qfficeie for Mesopotamia, I welcomed appointment of General Clayton as my deputy because I was sufficiently acquainted wit i hi a work and qualifications to feel confident that he would.be a valuable acquisition and in order to fall in with the wisnes of HoUoGoy.. as indicated in SoOf S.’s telegram dated 30th March. But u ne is not comiao: I bee: I may be permitted to make ay own arrangements as hitherto o ft Dobbs is able to return (and as you know I should welcome him) it is for post of Revenue Commissioner or Secreoary that he is best fitted and in which he would have the greatest scope (vide my telegram of 18th May, Mo, 1612). _ , , Indeoendent of above s if Mr» Storr s services could oe.given me not as Deputy but as Oriental Secretary.it wouW be possiole to pay more attention during the war to questions affecting Arab interests and policy for which work his services would be most valuable. He would at the same time be a useful liaison with Egypt, 5. ' pgT.RfyRAHj - Viceroy to Secretary of State, 27th June 1917, Secret, Your tel, of 20th June, Substitute for Clayton, Apart from question of his health and personal inclinations we snould find it most inconvenient to spare Doobs who is Revenue oi , &gt; • &lt;• - Baluchistan, with prospect of succeeding Ramsay as Agent to j ie Governor General in December1917. X SIMLA. FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT No. 44, DATED the 25th Mat 1917. SUC BET. War. Copy. Letter to Ms Majesty's Secretary of State for India Puture administration and political control in Mesopotamia and Arabia9 No. 44 of 1917. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT, SECRET. War. To The Right Honourable AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN, Mis Majesty's Secretary of State for India* Simla, the 25th May 1917. SlRfl As promised in our telegram of the 27th of April 1917, we have now the honour to address you further regarding the policy proposed by the Committee of the War Cabinet for the future administration and political control in Mesopotamia and Arabia. 2. The proposal that India should be relieved of the administration of the occupied territories in Mesopotamia together with the whole Arabian littoral of the Persian Gulf, and also of Aden together with Hadramaut and, we presume, other areas at present under the political control of Aden, has our full concurrence. Not only shall we ourselves be glad, laden as we are with vast responsibilities in India itself and on its frontiers, to be relieved of this burden, but we readily recognise the advantages that will accrue from the bringing of the Empire’s responsibilities in Arabia under one central control. Nor have we any hesitation in endorsing the general policy outlined by the Committee for adoption in the occupied territories. There are however a number of considerations arising out of this policy to which we think it right to call specific attention. e. It seems doubtful whether it would in practice be wise to adhere rigidly to the geographical dividing line between the two Vilayets laid down by the Committee, and we offer the suggestion that the boundary eventually decided upon should as far as possible be tribal and not merely geographical, that it should, in other words, follow and not cut through the main tribal m ■4/ ¥1 L i , , y' • f2 limits in that vicinity. Our experience in India has been that it is desirable to have the whole of a large tribe definitely under one administration, and that anything in the form of dual control necessarily conflicts with satis factory tribal management. 4. We venture also to sound a note of warning against undue haste in the formulation of the precise system of indigenous rule to be established under our guidance in the Baghdad Vilayet. In the outlying parts of India the policy of recognising and strengthening the defacto ruler or rulers wherever possible has generally proved the most efficacious. In the Baghdad Vilayet j however, no such de facto government is apparent, now that the Turks have been removed; and it would, surely, be a grave error hastily to establish an administration that might prove ineffective and possibly repugnant to the majority of the population. To attempt to establish an Arab Civil administration while our hold on Baghdad is still insecure and while martial law must perforce remain predominant, would be fraught with danger. It js for these reasons that we urge the necessity for feeling our way slowly and cautiously, and that we endorse the suggestion put forward by Sir Percy Cox in his telegram of the 7 th April that, before any definite government is established, the whole problem should be examined by a Commission on the : spot. 5. Amongst other matters which the Commission might examine is the proposal to create a separate enclave out of the Shiah Holy Places. Of the soundness of this proposal we confess ourselves somewhat doubtful. True, a very similar proposal was advanced in the late Viceroy’s telegram of the 23rd September 1915; but the circumstances which prompted it exist no longer, and in the absence of any pledge or declaration on the subject, His Majesty’s Government are now free to consider the matter anew on its own merits in the light of present conditions. And in our opinion a wiser solution is to be found on the lines of Sir Percy Cox’s suggestion that Nejef and Kerbela, while remaining integral portions of the new administration, should be organized as independent townships under their own municipal government^ There is no need to apprehend that such a solution would not meet with the approval of the Shiah community in India, whose attitude is very different from that of the Sunnis in respect of Mecca and Medina. It would assure them that immunity from interference with the pilgrimage and the actual administration of the shrines which is their foremost concern; and given that assurance, they are too conscious of their own weakness not to welcome that sense of peace and security that would arise from the whole country being under our general protection. In this way too, the political embarrassment of a separate enclave would be avoided. 6 . The proposal to officer the new territories from a service to be amalgamated with that of the Soudan and possibly also of the Levant undoubtedly offers the best practical solution to an admittedly difficult problem. Nevertheless, the cadre even with these enlargements will remain small and as such be exposed to all the vicissitudes and objections that attach to small cadres, notably slow promotion alternating with unduly rapid promotion and the lack of a fair proportion of prize appointments. It seems, moreover, wise to recognise from the outset that Mesopotamia offers but few amenities, and that if a really good stamp of man is to be attracted, liberalIMP ratio^ i Salk ia tie erever ilajet i Turks lartial It is iftle le is leave concessions and generous local allowances will in all probability be called for. Without these or similar attractions it seems to us doubtful whether many of our officers now serving in Mesopotamia will willingly cut themselves permanently adrift from their career in India or will volunteer for any but a very temporary transfer to the new service* 7. Regarded as an ideal towards which we should gradually work, we see no reason to dissent from the proposal to discountenance the employment of Indians in the new administration and to draw the Asiatic element in the administration from men of Arab and Persian domicile or descent. But we regard this ideal neither as one capable of being realised forthwith nor as one which it w T ould be politic openly to avow. To discharge the whole body of Indian Moslems already employed to good purpose in the Basrah Yilayet and definitely to deny the administration the option of drawing further on this useful material, before the requisite number of clerks and petty officials of sufficient education are available locally, would seem bad economy and an unnecessary drag on ordinary administrative efficiency. To publish any formal orders rigorously excluding all Indians as such from employment in the new administration would clearly be impolitic ki the extreme. Such a course would not fail to rouse a deep resentment in India and to excite a strong antipathy against the Arabs, Indian sympathy with whom it should be our aim to foster. Much the wiser course will be to weed out Indians already in the service gradually and unostentatiously and to refrain from admitting any others to posts in the administration for which local candidates of reasonably similar qualifications are forthcoming. 8 . Even more invidious would it be, while publicly debarring Indians from a share in the administration, to proceed to call upon India for material assistance in other directions. This suggests the wisdom of refraining from any precipitate action in the undertaking of large irrigation schemes in Mesopotamia which would be beyond the scope of indigenous labour to con struct, or of indigenous cultivators to exploit. The inevitable tendency of any vast addition to the culturable area to act as a strong and rapid solvent of existing tribal organisms and institutions will doubtless receive due consider ation before any large schemes are initiated. The only aspect of the problem with which we ourselves are concerned, is to emphasise the possibility of the administration finding itself faced, however much against its will, with the necessity for drawing on Indian labour and Indian cultivators to carry out its schemes. Not only would this militate against the principles laid down by the Committee, but it would raise a fresh crop of difficulties, not the least among which would be the invidious necessity for debarring Hindus from a share in the advantages offered in this holy land of Islam to their Moslem brethren. At the same time in the actual carrying out of its schemes the it may be within the power of our Irrigation Department to render. 1 vfr*T r improbably, strong resentment. India has long been bound and must always remain bound to Mesopotamia by strong religious ties. Her commercial interests in Mesopotamia were considerable even before the war, and now that India has shed her blood in the conquest of Mesopotamia a large section of her population is looking forward consciously or unconsciously not merely to a very material development of those interests, but to securing in Mesopotamia a definite field for employment and expansion. It is clearly imperative that on the one hand nothing that can be avoided should be done to embitter this disappointment, and on the other that we should do everything in our power to mitigate it by compensations elsewhere. Any form of restriction on the free and natural emigration of Indians into Mesopotamia whether for pilgrimage or trade or other lawful purposes would inevitably arouse a storm of resentment far stronger, and we may add far more legitimate, than any resentment evoked by the restrictions imposed on their entry into the Dominions, and would be calculated to raise the cry that India had been used as a catspaw for the conquest of Mesopotamia. Partly therefore to divert emigration as far as possible into other channels and partly to satisfy in another form India s natural and legitimate expectations, we strongly urge that a definite field fop expansion may be found elsewhere. Such a field as we have already suggested in our Despatch No. 85 (Secret—War), dated 29th September 1916, would possibly be found most suitably in East Africa, and if German East Africa is to remain a British possession we earnestly hope that arrangements may be made not only to allow the free entry of Indians into it but to afford them special facilities for the establishment of settlements and the acquisition of land on reasonable terms. 10. It should, we think, be made clear that if India is to have no share in the administration of Mesopotamia, the trade which has«for so long existed between the two countries shall not suffer by the separation. Indian traders will naturally wish for an &lt;£ open door” into Mesopotamia, and, if this cannot be assured to them, we assume that the treatment accorded to Indian trade and industry will be at least as favourable as that received by any other portion of the British Empire. Further in the interests of Indian traders and artisans as also of Indian pilgrims, it would be desirable that an officer of the Government of India should be posted to Basra and perhaps also to Baghdad to advise the local authorities and communicate when necessary with the Government of India. 11. The administrative changes in the Gulf and at Aden now in con templation will certainly cause some uneasiness at the outset to the Sheikhs of Koweit, Bahrein and Katr, the Sultan of Maskat and Bin Saud, and in a lesser degree to the Arab chieftains under the control of Aden. But an opportunity will doubtless be afforded us to explain the matter to them in suitable terms through our officers, and there seems no reason for apprehension that any uneasiness they may feel at the change will be otherwise than transitory. 12 . A more important consideration is the need for ensuring that the division of the Persian Gulf into an Arabian and a Persian sphere, each under a separate control, will involve no loss of co-ordination in our Persian Gulf policy. These are two main aspects in which this consideration presses itself insistently to notice. There is first the possibility, indeed the probabilitynercial r&gt; s e tki *f tliii ifferta se fea age or itmeot itmeiiS itspaw as far [Dilia’s Africa ! IMf l them xisti raders .ndiaii ,er o liaa it aa m ia of a serious attempt on the part of Japan to secure a commercial and thereby a political foothold in the Gulf. With the disappearance of Turkey from the Gulf, and with it the elimination of German ambitions, coupled with that better understanding with Russia to which we may perhaps look forward, the Persian Gulf might have been expected to drop out finally from the region of high politics. Japan s designs in this direction, however, of which we have had more than one indication, threaten to introduce a new element into the case, which unless carefully handled from the outset on both sides of the Gulf in strict accordance with one uniform policy may lead on to far-reaching consequences. In the second place, there is the imperative need for perfect co-ordination of policy on both sides of the Gulf and in both spheres on land, with regard to the arms traffic, which though dead for the moment, is likely to revive in a more threatening shape after the war, when all the belligerent powers will find themselves in possession of large stocks of surplus arms of which they would gladly dispose. And in general, it will doubtless be recognised that it is essential for us to be kept fully informed of all important developments not only in the Gulf but also in Mesopotamia and the other areas now to be trans ferred from our administration, in order that we may be able to gauge the political situation in the Middle East. 13. As regards Southern Persia we are quite ready to accept an extension of our responsibilities, provided our position is clearly defined. Eor we are very conscious of the awkwardness and general inadequacy of the existing arrangements under which the Government of India has, as it were, been for many years past but a fifth wheel in the Persian coach, exercising responsibility without authority, and providing troops without an adequate voice in the direction of the policy. We beg therefore that before a final decision is made, we may be informed what the exact status of the Govern^ ment of India is to be in the extended sphere to be assigned to them. 14. Finally, we will deal briefly with the more important financial aspects of the case. We must postulate that, as the Government of India are to have no share in the eventual administration of Mesopotamia, they will not be called upon to make any contribution whatever towards either the civil or military expenditure of Irak/ We must similarly postulate that the Government of India will be relieved of all expenditure now borne by them in the Agencies on the Arabian side of the Persian Gulf which it is proposed to transfer to the authority administering the Basrah Vilayet. W T e also consider that, when once the control of Aden and its appanages is transferred to the Foreign Office, the whole charges, both civil and military, of these areas should be borne by His Majesty’s Government. We have not overlooked the fact that Lord Curzon’s Government, in their Despatch •No. 66 (Secret) of the 14th May 1903, offered, in consideration of being relieved of the Administration of Aden, to continue a contribution of £77,000 a year to His Majesty’s Government, /&lt;?., the average cost of the Aden Administration minus £100,000 contributed by His Majesty’s Government. This offer appears, however, to have been prompted mainly by a desire to be rid of Aden in circumstances quite different from those at present under discussion, and we do not consider tnat, having regard to the interests of the Indian taxpayer, we should now be justified in repeating it. If India is to be absolved from all administrative responsibility at Aden, she cannot, in our opinion, equitably be called upon to bear any share of the cost.f! i : ( ti I r r'- i 'Cj 6 As regards Southern Persia, possibly it is intended to make all the Consulates within the sphere of the Government of India, Indian Consulates on the lines of Bushire, Kerman, Sistan, &amp;c. If so, we should naturally be prepared to accept our moiety of the cost in the same way as we do in the case of other Indian Consulates in Persia. 15. The foregoing paragraphs were drafted before receipt of your tele gram of the 10th of May 1917. Although many of the points raised by us above have been anticipated in that telegram, and in some measure disposed of, we have thought it right to leave these paragraphs more or less as they were drafted in order that His Majesty’s Government may have on record the full considerations that prompted our telegram of the 27th April 1917. 16. As it has been decided that the present military arrangements are to be maintained as before and that the question of the military arrangements after the war must stand over until the situation is clearer, we need say no more on this subject at present than that we presume that, before any decision is finally made, we shall be given a full opportunity to study and discuss the strategic and military considerations which arise from the proposals so far as they affect Indian military policy and responsibilities. ’ We have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servants, (Signed) CHELMSPOKD. o C. C. MONKO. o W. S. MEYER. « C. H. A. HILL, m C. S. NAIR, n Q. R. LOWNDES, n G. S. BARNES. ft W. H. VINCENT* - 1 p' \r ''^“— ~ * SECRET. ■ 'W •p m tie e&amp;- O $.■ i£, ti i 3 i 7 J ' tele. MESOPOTAMIA ADMINISTRATION COMMITTEE. ay no far as . Note by Sir James Meston, K.C.S.I,, on the future system of government at Baghdad. In, the report of Lord Curzon’s Committee which was accepted by the Imperial War Cabinet at one of its last meetings, there are references to the future of Mesopotamia “under British control,” and to the desirability of “ an Arab State or congeries of States under the protection of Great Britain.” I do not know whether these expressions are intended to define with precision the future method of government in the Baghdad vilayat, and more especially over the Holy Places of Islam in that area—Kerbala, Najaf, &amp;c. On the assumption, however, that the exact degree of British control is not yet finally decided, I suggest that it would be well to ascertain the feeling of our Mahomedan fellow-subjects on the point. This would, of course, be done through the administrations immediately concerned, particularly the Government of India. In this note I merely put forward my own reading of the Moslem mind of India on the subject. My reason for writing is my belief that any protectorate by a Christian Power or group of Powers over the Moslem shrines in Arabia would acutely offend the deepest sentiments of our Mahomedan population. This is just as true of Mecca and Medina as it is of the shrines near Baghdad. But I understand that the British Government has defined its own relations with the Sharif of Mecca, now King of Hedjaz ; and I therefore refrain from alluding to that side of the question, except where it is inextricably associated with Mesopotamian affairs. All good Moslems are at one in reverencing Mecca, Medina, and the adjacent tract of country (the Hedjaz) in Central Arabia. The Shiah sect of Mahomedans reverence also, and with special devotion, the shrines at Kerbala, Najaf, &amp;c., near Baghdad. The historical reasons for this are well known; what I wish to impress is that Shiah sentiment in the matter deserves special consideration. The Shiah sect, besides being dominant in Persia, forms a substantial element in our Indian Mahomedans, and has been conspicuously friendly and loyal. In India, when the Sharif of Mecca’s assertion of independence was first made known, an attempt was begun to organize an agitation against him and his claims. The- Shiahs took no part in this outcry, although they disliked the Sharif’s action for several of the reasons propounded by the Sunni agitators. The Shiahs have all along been very unhappy about our campaign in Mesopotamia, and hate the idea of bloodshed in their holy land round Baghdad ; but they have never raised a voice in protest. They have withstood all suggestions for a Jihad (or Holy War), and have justified their opposition on strong theological grounds. They have no feeling against the Caliphate passing away from the Sultan of Turkey. In a word, they have been perfectly staunch to the British Government, and have never listened to any temptation to embarrass us. The strength of the feeling which was manifested in India against the Sharif—and which caused some astonishment outside India—was partly due to ignorance of the true position, but was also largely based on two objections deeply rooted in the Mahomedan mind. They loathed the possibility of war on the sacred soil of the Hedjaz, particularly if Christian forces should be involved; and they believed that the Sharif would be a puppet in the hands of the Christian Powers. The first sentiment is intelligible to us all; the second is based on an important tenet of Mahomedan faith, and the same « 361 40 6/17 nllld'il lawa—I2 tenet is applicable to the future of the shrines near Baghdad. It may briefly be thus explained. ...... The sanctity of the Holy Places is contingent on their being in t e custody of a Mahomedan authority or Power competent to protect them against violation. Their guardian would in time become, I fancy, the ex officio Caliph; and if he is unable (whether as Caliph or otherwise) to defend them by the sword of Islam alone, his failure will ipso facto mean the appearance of the last Imam, chaos, forcible conversion of the whole earth to Mahomedanism—ic brief, what we should call the end ot the world. It is thus unthinkable to the Mahomedan mind that the impotence of Moslem guardianship should be confessed by the establishment of a Christian protectorate or suzerainty over either the Hedjaz or the Shiah slirmes m Mesopotamia. &lt; . . What would happen in practice if Great Britain and its Allies did decide on such a protectorate, I cannot pretend to prophecy. The end of the world probably would not come ; but among our Moslem population an unrest and resentment would be engendered which no prudent Government would ^ provoke except under very grave necessity. An extra-friendly Mahomedan here and there would be glad at heart to see the shrines under honest and capable supervision such as we could ensure ; an acquaintance of mine actually dared to say so in a pamphlet which he wrote on the entrance of Turkey into the war; but he was met with a storm of obloquy, and it is clear that the Mahomedan world generally would not tolerate the suggestion. I have just happened upon a strong corroboration of this view in a quotation from an address by the late Lord Cromer. While expressing some delicacy in giving a definite opinion on a purely theological issue, he wrote :—* “ It is held that the due exercise of the spiritual power cannot be ensured unless the Khalil is placed in a position of assured political independence. Hence, although possibly the substitution of some Khalif other than the Sultan of Turkey might be effected without any great shock to Moslem opinion and sentiment, the recognition of “a Khalif who could directly or indirectly be brought under non- Moslem influences would be strongly resented.” In a matter of this sort it is easier to be critical than suggestive. It is possible, however, that the King of the Hedjaz may provide a way out. The Crown of Arabia might be acknowdedged in the treaties of peace as an independent Power, and given the ultimate sovereignty of Baghdad, subject to any terms on which the British Government and the Sharif may separately agree as to the actual form of administration. Many who know Arabia doubt whether the new kingdom will hold together for more than a few years, but it could be made to serve our purpose for the time, and the problems arising from its disintegration will come on us when we have more leisure to deal with them. Kor the moment, what I wish to suggest is that the assertion of any form of control, protection or suzerainty by Great Britain or her Allies over the Holy fMahomedan) Places near Baghdad should be postponed until Moslem feeling is ascertained. Jas. Meston. 21st May 1917.i 9 n /.,, v,&gt; h lio X TELEGRAM FROM SIR P, COX DATED 22ND JUNE, 1917, RECEIVED AT INDIA OFFICE 23RD JUNE AT 6. A.M. ))))))) (((((( t2255 Reference to Secretary of State’s telegram 22nd June. Officers for Mesopotamia, I welcomed appointment of General Clayton as my deputy because I was sufficiently acquainted with his work and qualifications to feel confident that he would be a xalaa valuable acquisition and in order to fall in with the wishes of His Majesty’s Government as indicated in Secretary of StateSs telegram dated 30th %rch. But if he is not coming I beg I may be permitted to make my own arrangements as hitherto. If Dobbs is able to return (and as you know I should welcome him) it is for post of Revenue Commissioner or Secretary that he is best fitted and in which he would have the greatest scope (vide my telegram of 18th May, 1612). Independent of above, if Mr. Storr’s services would be given me not as Deputy but as Oriental Secretary if would it possible to pay more attention during the war to questions affecting Arab interests and policy for which work his services •would be most valuable. He would at the same time be a useful liaison with Egypt. Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Secretary of State for India.131 [This Document is the Property o! His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] L Flics only* mm*.’ V’mr «»« I ——I &gt; namt-uu anuar;’ .mm Decypher of tele 3 ma from Sir D.wingate (Kamieh) c June 22nd. u 1917 .0 o e &lt;c 0 p o ili 0 June 22ndo1917 a j 40 mm N o»6 64 o Your telegr&lt;«ii No A ' 1C f. nU o If appointment of Financial Advisor to Chief P o1itica1 Officer c a j i e o mde sufficiently attractive I recomend your snaking offer direct to Colonel Bernard 8 secretary of Soudan Government, who is now in London. If Ms health permitted, Lis financial:, capacity and long experience of huveaue affairs in Soudan would ofm i55) is Document is the Property ot His Britannic Majesty*s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] Your telegram No. 615. atorrs, who was tempomrily incapacitated, now telegraphs that he will shortly he quite fit. His knowledge of Arab question might mke him an invaluable assistant to Chief Political Officer and in combination with him I would recommend employing Colonel .Pearson Whose long experience in the Soudan would provide the complimentary adiainistrative knowledge of which dtorrs is by training deficient. If this proposal is cencm red in I would arrange matters with Acting Governor General of the Soudan.# Pearson now draws pay £1,100 • - Egyp^Hoo per annurn exclusive of all allowances*k [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] ; / a f, K , i £* ,J O 4 mjs ONLY. Cypher 'belegrejra Yo Sir H. Wingate, (Kamieh) , Foreign Office, June 20th. 1S17. 7,0.p.m. No*616, Hie 3 opo tarni an Adrnlnl b trati on. War Office have selected temporary Captain M.W. Payne for immediate employment in the Soudan and . ^ have asked General Headquarters France to send home Lieutenants V.P-. Walley and G.H. Coihito, General Headquarters Salonica to send Second Liev.tci.an- M.W. Grey direct to ISgypt if servJ ces of these officerB can 1*3 spared. Lieutenant F.H. IMgliston is medically unfit. Addressed to Sir K. Wingate Ho.616 tindjir P. Cox. Copy to India, 0±J[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should b6 returned to the Foreign O ffice when done with unless required for official use.] (118846/L7) r'” £4 . 1 . ■ # g L. ''ITT j- J- l j. .j O Q]-ILV. C^qoher telegram to 8ir It, v dn.gate, (Kamieh), Foreign Office., June 20th. 1.917/8.30.p.m. No,619. His Majesty’s Government desire to attach to Chief Political Officer Mesopotamia experienced Revenue Officer to act as his Revenue Secretary or Adviser with functions extending both no Basra and Bagdad Vilayets, though in view of the policy of His Majesty’s Government to keep the two province distinct nothing would he done to prejudice their complete separation when the period of military occupation come to an end. Please inform me whether Revenue Officer with suitable qualifications would he available from Egypt or the Sudan c[This Document Is the Property of Hia Rrltannin and shocld be returned to the Foreign Office required tor official use.] ~ Majesty’s Governments when done with unless j'. r L v -J,. J O Oi\I .LY Decypher,- air R. Wingate. (Ramleh). June 18th,1917, D. 10. IGei'^^ne'18th, 1917. H. S.O.a.m. ^19th,1917. No. 651. u-eneral Clayton’s preference and personal and financial considerations dispose him to refuse an appointment in Mesopotamia but if it is considered necessary in the public interest he will of course waive these and carry out instructions. If it is decided to send him it will be necessary to safeguard hi^ right to revert to Soudanese Government service daring a probationary period and his pension rights, guaranteeing that service in Mesopotamia shall count to ppnsion on conditions obtaining in the Soudan Gov- V ^ ^tnent Service. ^Will salary offered free of income tax as Is the case with his present salary?v yj @&gt; 140 [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s GovernmenC and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] p t p 3 qi jjjy 1 X [1 , ‘ Decypher. Sir h. 'Ungate. (3walo.h) June 11th, 1917. D. 3,55.p.rn* June 11th,1917* 8.0.a. i. June 12th,1917., ^ No. 615. 'N, N \ s, M fa*3 Your telegram No. 570. Since appointment of General Clayton to Bagdad wa &gt; suggested Sykes has come and gone,.and I am hound to agree with latter that Clayton will he best possible successor to him as chief politico! officer to Anglo- French Mission. Importance of having a first rate man is obviously very great and (?Clayton,omitted)’s knowledge and experience renders him uniquely qualified for the post, I trust you will agree and in that case Clayton’s candidature for Bagdad appointment must be withdrawn. I cannot suggest a substitute for Clayton and provided Mr. Bonham Carter accepts judicial office this may not be so essential for the present. If Sir P. Cox desires and would find him useful Storrs could be retained at Bagdad where his knowledge of Orientals and Ngyptian experience would make him a valuable assistant. Balfour and Nalder are both executive Administrat ive officials and General Stack is now communicating to them new offer. Before they accept or refuse it, which as Soudanese Government officials they are I presume entitled to do, they will require to be inform ed of conditions of appointment. 1 , iWMc x etui ignorant 0.1 rsla.oiv© condiijioiia ^ living and salaries in ilesopotaifiia and Soudan but I think following conditions would be suitable* (A) . Appointment on probation for one year with right to revert to Soudan at the end of it if desired, (B) . Pension rights to be safe-guarded* (G). Hates of payment and allowances to be assessed according to next higher class of Soudanese Government payment to that drawn by them at present vis: Balfour 300 and Malder 580 pounds Egyptian. \ Climatejtravelling and forage allowances to be extra, jto these rates according to local scales* General Stack finds it impossible to send more than two officials in view of his reduced staff but suggests that War Office might be asked to' send to Mesopotamia as special service officers the under- « mentioned ex Soudanese Government inspectors* Captain LAW.Payne and Lieutenant EJlh/iugliston* A more experienced and senior officer is Major L,D, Spencer at present employed at War Office* If available he is well worth consideration for an appointment in Mesopotamia. J v[Tills Document is the P roperty of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, , and should be retnrp7ed to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] (116660/17) 0 FI 1113 ONLY \ h !u 3 3 7^ Cypher telegram to I3ir It, 'Wingate s (Ram^eh), For el gn 01 1 i ce ? June 13tli 1917, 11.30. p * m 0 No o 537 c r. -Mil «■*•''' **•«»• •JBfrjKT'Jfr'.' Your telegram No,616 (of June llth 0 ) (Almnlotration of Mesopotamia), Relative importance of two posts would not justify retention of General Ci.ayton as Chief political Officer to Anglo-French Mission, whose activities must he in abeyance pending further de velopments in Palestine. You should o^ier peso in Mesopotamia to General Clayton, and, if ne accepts, request him to proceed there as soon as POSbj.bxe 5 &lt;,b his support and assistance will he especially valuable to Sir PoCox an the present moment 0 I would suggest that Captain Lloyd if still xn E gypt v should replace Sir Me Sykes during latt&lt; absence* -i- ,o I' 1 ! r' '■1 I 'cnpytoV ; Draft Paper* B.Bonham Carter, Esq., C.M.G., he ., he ., he. kx- KKf'ihl' 7 - Xppio^e^ 01 Coto’^i 11 jutisn Department. Sir, / ^ v/^ I am directed by the S. of S. for I. to inform you, in confirmation of private communications that have passed between yourself, the I.O., and the F.O., that you hs.ve been appointed to the post of Senior Judicial Officer, damdad, at a consolidated salary of Bs.2800 a month, being the equivalent, approximately, in Indian currency of £22 / i0 per annum, with travelling allowances at the authorised rates. As you have been informed orally, (1) your functions will be confined to the Bagdad Vilayet; and ( 2 ), while you will doubtless be required to discharge the duties of a judge, your more important work, at any rate in the initial stages, will be to organise under the Chief political Officer (Sir Percy Cox) the judicial system of the Vilayet and to be his adviser on judicial affairs. Your appointment will ta.ke effect from the date on which you finally sever your official connection with ‘- 4 - the Sudan,‘on the understanding that you will proceed direct to Mesopotamia on vacating your present appointment inin the former country. During the interval between your doing so and the date on which you report yourself at Basra you will receive pay at the rate drawn by you in your present appointment. A further communication will addressed to you in due course regarding trie conditions in respect of leave and pension attaching to your employment in Mesopotamia. The Secretary of State will be glad to receive a formal intimation that you accept the appointment offered you on the above terms. It is understood that you will make arrangements to arrive in Mesopotamia by about*. the end of August 1917. You should report in due course to the Chief Political Officer, Basra, and to this Office, the exact date of your departure for'Mesopotamia from the Sudan, on vacating your appointment in the latter. /V-j j uhieh-b^an explained to you in conversation, i-t 1 -possible,—it^resent cl r^umstSlices, ■ be- t}ie-.p^P4^.nnneo 9'f your- •.sppQ^tment of Baghdacw * * *■ ^ *v^v. gpw vU.S. of S. Foreign Office. No.P.24f2&gt;4l dated/S 1917. Approved Pol Cun'ei., 11 JUL 1917 In continuation of previous correspondence repair ding the appointment of hr.Edgar Bonham Carter, C.1I.O., Legal Secretary to the Sudan Administration, to the post of Senior Judicial Officer, Bagdad, I am directed by the S. of S. for I. to forward, for the information of the S. of S. for F.A., copy of a letter which has been addressed to hr.Bonham Carter on th^ subject. Before inviting the C. of I. to make recommendations as to the conditions in respect of leave and pension to be attached to Nr. Carter’s employment in Mesopotamia, Mr. Secretary Chamberlain would be rdad to learn whether Mr, Balfour ha.s any observations to offer on these ooints. It would be convenient if precise information could be furnished regarding conditions in the above A resuectslattached to Mr. Carter’s■ 'M M l \ n-'C 14^ Whit shall, S.'.. 1. 15th June,. 1917. V ? I ”:rite to lot you kno?i that Lr, Bonham Carter called on [iolderness yesterday afternoon ■me,, discussed ^ith him the outstanding points in connection ^ith his proposed appointment in j esopotmda* Bonham Carter no^ unm ret ends that, at any rote for the present, nis functions ?ill be confined to the Baghdad Vilayat, and that his duties ^ill probably consist mre of organising judicial administration md advising on legal matters than of actual judicial fork, Bonham Carter is prepared to accept the post, temporarily at ail events^ on this understanding, md ^ill make arrangeffients to reach Mesopotamia about the and of August. I shall be telegraphing to the C■ overimant of India in this sense and a copy of the telegram '^ill be sent to the lorei^a Office in the ordinary course. /4 The Lord Hardinge of Penshurst, K, f.,Si ■i \\ 151 Whitehall, 1* 13th June, 1917, ? hear oir. With reference to the interview you recently had ^ith Lord Harding on the subject of your proposed appointment at Bagdad and your letter of the let June relating thereto, Mr, Chamberlain thinks it ifould be a good thing if you ^ould call and talk o?er certain matters connected ndth the proposed appointment with me * I should be happy to see you either to-morrow (Tkirsday) afternoon,^ or Friday afternoon at 3-30. Yours faithfully# ■ ) 1 ■ V 1 ' IT. 6^^ Kd|-:ar Boniriam Carter Isq,# C.f;.L,# b, Hyde Park Square, ^ m—I ^9 b Whitehall, S # U. 1* 13th June, 1917, A hear Lord Hardinge, -ith reference to your letter of 5th June regarding kr, Bonhaca Barter and his.&gt; proposed appointment at Baghdad, , r. Cha/aberlain asks me to say that ne proposes to invite i r, Bontiast Carter to discuss certain points in coimection with the proposed appoint^nent with Bir Thomas oldemess, I r, Chamberlain will let you know the result after the interview. Yours very truly -he Lord Hardings of Fenshurst. Foreign Office. ! 1 i \4 r 1 m-O I'nm Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Departmea^ SQlh March 1917. (Repeated to Sir P. Cox, Bagdad.) of Bagdad Ideas^ refer l ( ^ r;lln &lt; f ] tlie Mju'cIi. Civil administration statement of imen fon of mh j'*™ for ' introduS l'B fCC el ' fr ° ln . Same “’'■&lt;*, as we do not wish to uouuu Indian code. We are enqumng as to names. We have I'malnw selected frof^an e 1 ' 311011 a P point , lne ' 1 U , ot « ( 1 ( d™ty under Cox at Itagdad , ±10 ^ * lU ] 1g source, but should first like to hear his views on^th; u-oposal. Our object is to. supply Cox with staff familiar wiih TrabU anguage and customs, and with 'I'urkish administration and law i.etore leaving Dobbs said Ids doctor advised that his retuYn to Mesopotamia was impossible 3CUnn t0 Fi om Secretary of State to V iceroy, Foreign Department, 5th April 1917. (Repeated to Sir P. Cox, Basra.) Foreign Secret. My telegram of 30th March. Civil Administration of Bagdad. Lgypt can supply judicial adviser and two subordinate revenue ofheers. _ iNarnes will be communicated as soon as possible. When should they arrive? Also proposed to appoint General Clayton from Egypt as Deputy High Commissioner, Bagdad. Do you agree? Clayton would proceed at once. From Sir P. Cox, Sth April 1917. (Addressed to Foreign and repeated to Secretary of State for India and Political, Basra.) (Received at India Office, 6 a.m., 9th.) T. 1062. Reference to telegrams from the Secretary of State, dated 30th March and 8 th April. May 1 please be informed of names, ages, and number of years’ service of proposed Judicial Adviser and the two sub ordinate Revenue Officers ? I presume they are all Englishmen and belong to Civil Service. A competent Judicial Adviser is already available in Colonel Knox, who has had two years’ experience of local judicial needs and ideas, and as it is common ground that Irak Code is not to be introduced and as he is quite prepared to work on the lines indicated d)y His Majesty s Government, it seems superfluous, apart from Colonel Knox’s personal claims to consideration, to introduce another legal luminary. On the other hand, couple of capable junior judicial Officers who could assist huh over hauling Turkish codes would no doubt be very usetul. As regards Brigadier- General Clavton, his services would at any time be most valuable to me as well as to Government, but I suggest that his designation be not decided until Ills Majesty’s Government have had time to consider views of Army Commander and myself as conveyed in mv telegram 1019 dated 7th April. .From Sir P. Cox, Bagdad, 13th May 1917. (Addressed Foreign, repeated to Secretary of State for India.) £ Extras t^) (Received at India Office 14th May, 11 a.m.) 1612. Supply of officers for Mesopotamia. Firstly, Secretary of State’s telegram dated 21st April. In any case 1 think that Colored Knox would have done well for purpose now required, but as His Majesty’s Government seem to regard him as too much immersed in Indian codes to be a safe exponent of their judicial policy in the Bagdad Vilayet, and as I have undertaken to promote that policy, it is difficult for me to press further for his translation to Bagdad. To him, however, the decision means that he is deprived of all prospect of advancement in this country, and I trust that disappointment will be made up to him. I accept M*jjr Bonham-Carter, if His Majesty’s Government are satisfied as to his suitabdity, and request that he may join as soon as poss ible. ,VI 11 /&gt;l ‘ 1 ' ‘ 111 ^ i ‘ i ^ 1 -‘-‘o'From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 2Srd May 1917. (Repeated to Sir P. Cox.) Foreign Secret. Cox’s telegram No. 1012, 13th May. Officers for Mesopotamia. I think it probable that, when his telegram issued, Cox had not seen my telegram of 10th May emphasising necessity of maintaining separate administrative systems for Basra and Bagdad. Oiyen this po icy, to which His Majesty’s Government attach great impoitance ( ) retention of Knox as Senior Judicial Officer, Basra, and appointment of Bonham ( aitei to similar post at Bagdad, can scarcely be regarded as hardship to former, and (2) creation of joint revenue authority as contemplated by Cox does not appear necessary or desirable. Existing revenue arrangements should be reconsidered in this light. Meanwhile I am asking foreign Office to expedite appointment of Clayton and Bonham Carter, and am applying loi junioi officers from Egypt and Soudan, as desired by Cox. From Sir P. Cox, Basra, 29th May 1917. (Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Secretary of State.) (Received at India Office, 30th May, 2 p.m.) 1903. Reference Secretary of State’s telegram, dated 23rd May. Officers for Mesopotamia. As regards Knox. Hardship to him lies in the fact that Basra alone offers him no career in the judicial line, lie has a natural bent for judicial work, has made a practical success of judicial administrati on o f Basra, and naturally looked forward to prospect of advancement In the event of extension of our control to the Bagdad Vilayet. In existing circumstances 1 imagine he will apply to return to India, and will feel that his three years’ hard work in these territories has been wasted as far as his future career is concerned.(I) — Copy. PlH-95 7 -'//;■ 5, Hyde Park Square, W. 1st t3une, 1917 Dear Lord Hardinge:- Witli reference to tne interview which you granted me yesterday, when you did me the honour of offering me the appointment of Senior Judicial Officer Baghdad, at a^consolidated salary of Rupees 2,800 a month with travelling allowance at authorised rates, I write to confirm that I have much pleasure in accepting the appointment, assuming, as I understand is the case, the senior Judicial Officer Baghdad will he the senior legal official not only for the vilayet of Baghdad but for all the cohquered territory,- and that the duties of the appointment are not solely of a Judicial character, but include the organizing of a system of Justice, and the supervising of the administration of Justice, and that the appointment will carry with it the necessary powers to carry out those duties. In accordance with your request I write to explain in some detail the nature oi the. duties oo which I refer, and I can perhaps do so most clearly by giving some account of the Judicial oi'guriziUtion which has grown up in the Sudan. when I first went to the Sudan I was the sole British lawyer in the country, and I combined the duties of Legal Secretary to the Government and of judicial Commissioner. Gradually a Legal Department, under the general control of the Legal Secretary, has grown up comprising the following 1 K 'I(oo (l^j) (1) Tlie Higli Court of Justice, comprising a Chief Judge and a Bench of British Judges, and, subordinate to the High Court, a few minor judges either British or Egyptian in the more developed districts. In the less developed districts the judicial functions are performed by the executive officers. The Legal Secretary is a member of the Court of Appeal, but this arrangement was come to as a con venience to ensure a sufficient supply of judges to form a Court of Appeal in case of the sickness or aosenceof one of the Judges of the High Court, and I only sit as a member of the Court in an emergency. (2) The Mohammedan‘Law Courts, which deal with all cases between Mohammedans relating to personal status, such as questions of marriage or succession. These Courts comprise a Court of Appeal with a Grand Kadi and Grand Mufti, Province and District Kadis who form the Courts of first instance, and an inspecting staff. (3) Registries of titles to land under a Registrar General. (4) A legislative section, which is responsible for the drafting of laws and important regulations. (5) An Advocate General, who incidentally also acts as Administrator General of the unrepresented estates of Christians. (6) A Government lands office, which is responsible for all dealings with Government lands. This is not logically a branch of a Department of Justice, but has been placed under the Legal Secretary on grounds of convenience. The Legal Secretary is a permanent member of thetiie Governor Generals Council, and is responsible to tlie Governor General for all questions relating to the organization and administration of tiie various branches of the Legal Department, including the framing of the annual estimates of the Legal Department for submission to the Finance Department, and for all questions relating to the personnel of the Legal Department. He also advises the Government on the legal aspects of questions of policy. I do not suggest that the legal organization in Mesopotamia should be developed in detail on the same lines as in the Sudan. The establishment, for instance, of Mohammedan Courts of personal status is a question on which one cannot form an opinion except after full and careful studies of local conditions.. The point which I wish to emphasize is that it vail prove advantageous fo the judicial and legal system to be co-ordinated in one department under a responsible chief, who is in close touch with the lines of Government policy, and whose functions will eventually be administrative and not judicial. This arrangement is in force both in Egypt and the Sudan and has undoubtedly produced very good results in the latter country. Without affecting the independence of the judges, it has ensured tnat the judicial system and the administration of justice are in accordance with Government policy. It has prevented friction, whether between the judicial and executive services, or between the Mohammedan Law Courts and the Civil Courts, and it has facilitated the exercise of a necessary control over the Kadis of the Mohammedan Law Courts. It is obvious that at the start the legal staff in Mesopotamia must be very small and that the organization) Sr N) !62&gt; organization must be of the simplest character, but I trust that it is intended that the functions of the benior Judicial Officer at Baghdad shall include the organization of the judicial and legal system of the country, the supervision of the administration of justice and advising on the legal aspects of questions of policy, and' that the eventual development of a Department of Justice under the general control of the benior Judicial Officer is contemplated, or that, at least, if it is too early to lay down future lines of organization, that possibility is not excluded. May I add that, now the tranquillity of the budan seems assured, I am anxious to be employed on work more directly connected with the war, and that, even if the conditions of the appointment offered me should prove to be not in accordance with my views, I am at the disposal of the Government for the period of the war and a reasonable time after it. Again thanking you for the honour you have done me in offering me the appointment Yours very truly (bignedj Edgar Bonham Garter.India Office, London, 16th July 1915. Financial, No. 54. To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. My Lord, I have had under consideration the question of the pay for the period of x , 7 , rT the voyage to India which should be Officers transferred from Home J ° Civil Service to service in India: , i . ca ± t i t - x7 x , L , granted to oracers transierred irom (fuestwn of the pay to be granted ° for the pei iod of voyage. service under His Majesty’s Government in this country to service under Your Excellency’s Government. The practice followed in the past in this matter has not been uniform. 2. I have now decided, on the analogy of Article 185, Civil Service Regulations, to grant pay to the officer during the voyage at the rate last drawn by him in his appointment under His Majesty’s Government. 3. A note of this rule might be inserted, if you think fit, in the Civil Service Regulations. 1 have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) Austen Chamberlain.■I Ifc3 Draft Paper. Department &gt; In continuation of my letter of the 23rd T ’!ay, 1917, No. 1977, regarding the appointment of civil officers for service in Mesopotamia, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to invite reference to Sir P. Cox’s further telegram on the subject, No. 1903 of the 29th ultimo, eopy of which was communicated to your Department on the 31st May. As regards the position of Lieutenant Colonel Knox, to which Sir P. Cox alludes, Mr. Secretary Chamberlain sees no reason to modify the decision at which His Majesty’s O-overnment have-already arrived. Turning to the question of revenue administration, Mr. Chamberlain^ would wt object to - jto appointowat of an experienced ifl^Y ftZ. tompom-i?;/' 1 1 :na :7V.rtu&gt;g to act as Revenue Secretary or Adviser 4s-tiii- Wl tib/? CM Pf P n 1 - ~i ^ ^ 'i'' ^''f T. 1 CWl th functions o-xtonding both to the Basra and Bagdad Vilayets, pro^dedr-it io - p] ftn.r'jy understood that be ins the- policy of Ills Majesty’s Government to keep the revSnueUry^stems of the two provinces distinct, nothing must be * \ done to prejudice their compleue separation when the period of miliuor^ occupation comes to an encu c * ? t I am uo suggest that if this view commends itself to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, enquiry should be made of TT is Majesty’s High Commissioner, Cairo, whether a Revenue Officer with suitable qualifications is available in Egypt or the Soudan. Failing that, Mr. Chamberlain would propose to make application to the Government of India. This letter, as also my letter of the 23rd ultimo, Ho. P. 1977, has the concurrence of Lord Curson of Kedleston. w ■ . */l_ . N , 13 ) V (Received at India Office 30th May,) 1903, Reference Secretary of State’s telegram May 23. Officers i.or Mesopotamia* As regards Knox* Hardship to him xies in tii© fact that Basra alone offers him no aase&amp;p in the judicial line* He has a natural bent for judicial work, nas made a practical success of judicial administration of Basra add naturally looked forward to prospect of advancement control to the Bagdad vilayet In existing circumstances I imagine he will apply to return to India and will feel that his three years hard work in these territories has been wasted as far as his future career is concerned. As regards Revenue Administration. I have read Secretary of State’s telegram of May 10 and understand it but I would ask him to remember that for the period of the war there cannot be two Army Commanders in supreme control in occupied territory nor two Chief Political Officers, and that I am responsible to Army Commander and to Government for civil administration of both Vilayets. In the matter of revenue administration we have adopted in its entirety^the Turkish system which is the sane for both Vilayets* It is clearly opposed to interests of inhabitants and to principles of good government that identical questions arising in the two Vilayets should be handled differently. Ihat I need is the services of an officer of adequate weight and revenue experience as my Revenue Secretary or StaJf Officer to whom 1 can go for advice with regard to revenue questions and can give supervisory powers over the working of both Vilayets to ensure consistency of treatment. Dobbs would have suited me well As he is not available another officer of the same type is needed, and as revenue system of these territories idquite different from that of India and of Egypt it matters little whencewnence tne officer comes as long as he possesses right qualities. As regards present arrangements. Though as a matter of fact one member of my 'Revenue Board' is now running Basra Vilayet and the other the Bagdad Vilayet and they have doubtless separated for good - yet pending the appointment of Revenue Secretary asked for I have to maintain the institution 'Revenue Board' to ensure that there is no differential Treatment of identical problems. I hope officer will be nominated as soon asjposssible. j As fax as I can see some such supervisory post will continue to be necessary after the war with the same object in view but that is a question which can be considered by Commission. Addressed to Foreign repeated to Secretary of State* Cox*k n r . eference Paper. Political and Secret Department. Register No. M» 19893. 191 . Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 4th June, 191 ?. Proposal to grant Sir P. Cox temporary rank of 7 * Major-General. For information and any observations. (SD.) C.H.SELTOL 4. 6. 1917. Seen. Brigadier-General Clayton has not yet - so far as I know - been actually appointed to Mesopotamia; but we wrote officially to the Foreign Office on 23rd May last uring that his appointment should be proceeded with at once. On Political grounds, I support the Government of India’s present proposal. The rank to be granted would be M honorary' I take it, in the sense that it would bring with it no increase of emoluments. Sir P. Cox draws pay, not as a Lieutenant-Colonel, but as a Resident, First Class, in the Indian Political Department; and I presume the intention to be that he should continue to do so. (SD.) J.E.SHUCKBIRGH. 4. 6. 1917. m 'i i -iDraft Paper* &amp;pr. £ The Under Secretary of State&gt; FCKhIGh OFFICE, *No* 1612, dated 13th May, 1917. No. 1613, ” ' “ / INDIA OFFICE , MNITFHALL S.W.l. ^3 May, 1917. Sir, In continuation of previous correspondence regarding the appointment of civil officers from Egypt and elsewhere for service in Mesopotamia,, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to invite reference to the marginally noted telegrams* on the subject from the Chief Political Officer, Basra, copies of which were communicated to your Department on the 14th instant, Mr. Secretary Chamberlain would suggest that the appointment of Brigadier-general Clayton as Assistant to the Chief Political \ Officer (his precise designation being held over for future consideration) and of Mr. Edgar Bonham Carter, C.M.Cr., as Senior Judicial Officer, Bagdad, should be proceeded with without further delay. He considers that &amp; StJU. ^ ■lary of Rs. 2,500 a month (£ 2,000u E&gt; u I V (£2,000 a year), plug, a remunerative allowance similar in amount to that ^ drawn by various officers of tne Indian Civil Service and Indian Political Department serving in Mesopotamia, viz:- Rs. oCO a moiiun (£240 a year), would be * suitable romiiucrnrii-fi 1 y■ in the case of ootn these Officers.^/' I am to request that, if the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs sees no oojecuion, (urO ^ , the% A may now be approached wioh a ^ , • view to their immediate employment in Mesopotamia on the above terms; and that, if they accept the offer, they may be.directed to make arrangements with as little delay as possible to proceed to Basra and report on arrival to the Chief Political Officer. As regards the appointment of revenue officers, Bir P. Cox’s proposal for the creation of a J ' *-i * h- Uv joint revenuePbf the two Vilayets appears to Mr. Chamberlain hardly consistent with the policy of separate administrative systems which His Majesty’s Government have deliberately adopted. A telegram, of which copy is enclosed is being addressed to the Government of India Oil this point. Midh regard to the last paragraph CUJs^ didU- _ C^-7 luj (r*- To Viceroy, datedDraft Paper* paragraph of the Chief Political Officer’s telegran ?Tq. 1612, Hr. Chamber lair trusts that it may be found possible to comply ’ Ith fir P* Cox’s request for 4-6 youii^ \rabic-speaking officers from ^aypt or trie Soudan. I am to enquire in this connection, whether the two Revenue officers mentioned by Sir R. Ringate in his telegram No. 443 of the 16th ultimo, vis:- Hessrs. F.C.C.Balfour and L.p.llalder, would be suitable for employment on general political and administrative duties, if not required for work directly connected with the collection of revenue. If so, the further demand upon Sir R. t&lt;f ingat^’s resources would be correspondingly reduced. Should His Nxcellency, however, find it impracticable to ccmolv even with this ^educed demand , Mr. Chamberlain would be disposed, despite Sir P. Cox's criticisms, to press for the appointment of Messrs. Havard and Cowan of the Levant Consular Service, to whose transfer fPom Persia Sir C. Marling is prepared to agree. Tfr. ** I: Kj■ r. Chamberlain would be glad to be favoured with Yv • Balfour 1 s views . as to the remuneration of these gentlemen, and of any other junior officers appointed to Mesopotamia from Egypt, the Soudan or the Levant Consular Service. It has been intimated privately to this Department that hr. James Currie, O.m.G - ., late Principe-i- oi the Gordon College, Ifhartoum, and at present employed at the Ministry Munitions, would be willing, it approached, to take up administrative 1 work in Mesopotamia. Mr. Cnamberlain doubts whether any opening is likely to present itself at present for an officer of his seniority and special qualifications; but he would be glad to learn fir. Balfour’s views on the suggestion. Paruiculars ot Mr• Currie’s record are no doubt available to your Department. va. ( 5 l%x I^J\UZt+JL 3DRAFT TELEGRAM. SECRETARY OF STATE TO VICEROY, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla) to be repeated to Sir P. Cox. . (ZAFAiJDO BASRA). Despatched x 20465 I 468 1000 4/16 Foreign Secret. Cox’s telegram No. 1612. 13th Nay. Officers for Mesopotamia. I think it probable that, when his telegram issued, Cox had not seen my telegram of loth May emphasising necessity of maintaining separate administrative systems for Basra and Bagdad, given this oolicy to which His Majesty’s Government attach great importance (1) retention of Knox as Senior Judicial Officer Basra and appointment of Bonham Carter to similar post at Bagdad can scarcely be regarded as hardship to former and (2) creation of joint revenue authority as contemplated by Cox does not appear necessary desirable.^Revenue arrangements should be reconsidered in this light. Meanwhile I am asking Foreign Office to expedite appointment of Clayton and Bonham Carter and am applying for junior officers from Fgypt and Ooudan as desired by Cox. Addressed Viceroy repeated Cox. w(Received at India Office 14th May 11 a.m.) j. 61^. Supply of officers for Mesopotamia. (!)• Secretary of State ! s telegram April 21st. In any case I think that Colonel Knox would have done well for purpose no?/ required but as His Majesty T s Government seem to regard him as too much immersed in Indian codes to be a safe exponent of their judicial policy in the Bagdad Vilayet and as I have undertaken to promote that policy it is difficult for me to pi ess furtner for his translation to Bagdad. To him, however, the decision means that he is deprived of all prospect of advancement in this country and I trust that disappointment will be made up to him. I accept Major Bonham-Car ter if His Majesty ! s Government are satisfied as to his suitability and request that he may join as soon as possible. Referring to High Commissioner’s telegram 443 of April 16th. Present Revenue arrangements are that Revenue Departments of Bagdad and Basra Vilayets are in charge of two young Indian civilians, Messrs. Garbett and Gordon-Walker, respectively, who together form a Revenue Board assisted by Mr. Bullard, Levant Consular Service. The revenue work at out stations is done by the local assistant political officers under supervision of the Revenue Board. Special junior officers for revenue are therefore not now needed but what I do need is an efficient successor to Mr. Dobbs as head of Revenue administration, and I know of no one specially suited to the post. It is essential that he should be physically active, able to tour freely and ready to associate with Arab agricultural. element and be generally accessible. Mr. Dobbs knows what is wanted and I recommend that he be asked to suggest a suitable man. He should be of ■■■■■■■■—mm T &gt; tv no less seniority than Dobbs end would have general supervision over revenue administration of both Vilayets. Referring to Secretary of State’s telegram of 9th May. Harris is dead. Morrail cannot be spared from Bushire unless he can be replaced by another officer. The other two officers do not apparently know Arabic and will therefore be of no use for the present. They might be directed to study Arabic. Meanwhile should be glad of four or six young Arabic-speaking officers from Egypt or Soudan. Addressed Foreign repeated to Secretary of State.[P 1854] From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, IQth May 191 7. (Repeated to Sir P. Cox, Barra.) Your telegram of 27th April. Mesopotamia administration. Your despatch will be awaited, but His Majesty’s Government desire to assure you at once that they do not contemplate immediate establishment of an Arab administration on principles indicated in my telegram of 29th March. They fully realise that military situation requires that Army Commander and Chief Political Officer should have free hand, but what they are concerned about is that nothing that can be avoided should be done during military occupation that would prejudice subsequent introduction of above- mentioned principles, and in particular establishment of separate adminis trative systems for Basra and Baghdad. Subject to clear understanding on this point, Cox may carry on in consultation with Army Commander as heretofore, until whole problem has been examined and reported on by a Commission as he suggests. Such questions as administrative councils, permanent judicial system, regulation of Indian immigration, Ac., are reserved for consideration of Commission. Meanwhile only such minimum of administrative efficiency should be aimed at as is necessary to preserve order and meet needs of occupying force. Amendment of laws and intro duction of reforms should be kept within narrowest possible limits. Personnel both of higher branches and clerical establishment should be limited to immediate requirements, and should not ordinarily be drawn Irom India unless and until it has been ascertained that Egypt and Soudan cannot supply them. . t T i -m His Majesty’s Government accept Cox’s views regarding Holy 1 laces which coincide with their own. As regards irrigation schemes they entirely concur in last sentence of your paragraph 8 . Question of Persia must stand over till situation is clearer. Same applies to military arrangements alter war. Present arrangements will be maintained in meantime.^ ^ 'zul^/k r ,,^}- v / v' r ^'' % Privy Council Office, Whitehall, S. W. l. 10th May, 1917. Dear Shuckburgh, One of your Mesopotamia Administration Committee left the enclosed documents in Lord Curzon’s room at the House of Lords. Before you arrived the other evening,! asked Major Storr and some-one else who was in the room ; if you had considered the name of Mr. James Currie, C.M.G., for one of these Administrative posts in Mesopotamia. lou probably know that Mr. Currie, who is a personal friend of mine, was principal of the Gordon College at Khartoum, 1900 - 1914 . He is at present Head of the Training Department in the Ministry of Munitions. The other day I asked him incidentally if he would be willing, should he be approached, to take up work in Mesopotamia*, and he told me that he would go anywhere where he was wanted. He speaks, as you know, Arabic. Yours truly, J.S. Shuckburgh, Esq. Ta L^va, . yi ,Ml i ^ i / L Decyp-ier. 31r j?. nngnte. (Cairo) to sir ]?. Graham, Q. 8.55.p.ia. May 7th, 1917. H. S.O.a.m. I4ay 8th t igi7. Ho. - Your private tele [pram May 5th t Claytons present pensionable pay as Soudan A^ent is 1200 pounds Egyptian a year. T je also draws a monthly allowance of twelve pounds Egyptian as Directc 0 ! Intelligence Egyptian Aviry and he has recently been (? given) a special monthly allowance of ten pounds Egyptian by Egyptian Government.T.2406. In continuation of my T. 1254, 20th April. Following is result of analysis of Basra Vilayet. Personnel. About half perfectly indifferent. ve_jper, spnnsl. All leading officials were Turks and all principal subordinates in judicial, medical, customs, police and education. In last named all head men were Turks. Practically all posts requiring technical knowledge were held by Turks appointed from Constantinople and not by ,/alis. Natives of Nosul, Kurkuk and Sulaimanieh counted as non Turks otherwise proportion of Turks would be much larger. Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Secretary of State for India and Political, Basra. er 95 l nidi 7 I'idoBGRAM FROM SIR P. COX, BAGDAD,'DATED 30TH APRIL, Received at India Office 1st May, at 1 p.m.(V/. 83398/17). Dear Shuckburgh:- The proposal In your official letter P.1433 2.3 * 7 ) • of April that Clayton should now he inform ed of his proposed appointment and should arrange for his departure, seems to us to he rather pre mature. The policy and scheme have not yet been definitely approved either hy the Committee or by the War Cabinet, and. we are also awaiting the views of the Government of India. We ought, I think, also to be in a position to indicate to Clayton what his salary &amp;c. will be if he accepts the appointment. » In the circumstances, therefore, we are holding our hands.♦ [P 1762J From Viceroy, Foreign Department, 27th April 1917. (Received 28th April, 11.30 a.m.) Secret. Reference to your telegram of 29th March. Administration and political control of Mesopotamia and Arabia. Subject to following remarks, we readily accept general policy proposed by the War Cabinet. ' First and foremost, howevei, we would fully endorse the view of Sir P. Cov in the middle part of paragraph 12 and paragraph 13 of his telegram T. 1049 of 7th April. ’ Our hold on Bagdad vilayet is by no means secure yet. Any attempt to introduce civil administration while martial law must perforce remain predominant can only lead to confusion and inefficiency. War Cabinets conclusions contain no reference to military effects of their proposals, present or future. We presume there will be no alterations in the present practice of keeping Commander-in-Chief informed of all developments in the military situation in Mesopotamia. It should be remembered that India can now to a certain extent balance and check needs of Mesopotamia with the needs of other theatres in which she is interested and with those of India and her frontiers. If kept in ignorance of policy to be pursued in Mesopotamia and merely treated as a supplier of materials and personnel, there can be( no assurance that India’s resources will be utilised and developed to the best advantage. The same applies to Aden and the other potential theatres of war in the area to be transferred. It is, therefore, strongly urged that no change be made in the procedure now existing, but as there is no mention of intention in this respect, W T ar Cabinet’s orders on this point are required.- Turning to conditions after the war, we would point out that so far as we can see, India will have for some time to be responsible for supplying troops required for the defence and garrisoning of Mesopotamia. In an}^ case, she will probably have to provide reserves for all military operations. We would strongly urge, in view of these considerations, that some procedure be laid down by which India should be kept fully informed of all political developments which may necessitate a call for troops. Otherwise, it would appear that contemplated policy would be giving in fact to the prospective Government of Mesopotamia a blank cheque on India’s military resources. Turning to specific points raised in your telegram : (1) W T e readily accept decision that occupied territories should be administered by His Majesty’s Government and not by the Government of India. At the same time it must be recognised that India has shed her blood in the conquest of these territories in which she has already large interests, commercial, political, and religious, and that any restriction of free Indian immigration for trade and other purposes into Irak would cause bitter and legitimate resentment. Doubtless provision of a definite field for expansion elsewhere, preferably in East Africa as already suggested in our Despatch No. 85 Secret, War, of 29th September 1916, in recognition of her Avar services, would tend to satisfy India and check an undue flow into Irak, and we trust that steps may be taken to arrange for this. In any case, in view of pilgrimage and trade interests of India in Irak, it would be desirable to post an officer of Government of India to Basra and perhaps also Bagdad to advise local administration on such questions. ff tel V ' 4Ak.VL C&gt; ^y Ap } &gt; *!*■ £r*h i | . f ' '■ t''/ ' i i TELEGRAM from SIRP. COX, BAGDAD, DATED BOTH IPRXE t ; “T?l4.^ j Aitf- 5 Received at India Office 21st April, 1 0 .30 a.m. ' ( ^ ,c. m X • 1254. Secretary of State's telegram April 12th. Executive personnel, i.e. Deputy Wali, Muiessarifs, Putkmns(?) Mudirs, about 50 in number; half of them Turks. All have gone. (2) Administrative personnel* About 120 in number. All leading officials were Turks nukbering about 20; they have all gone. Remaining hundred were non-Turks of various demoninations. 48 remain* Turks were careful to take away in particular any officials who might be expected to be of use to us. Addressed Foreign, repeated to Secretary of State and Political, Basra.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] •O 2o5 lOS piit::; nmy ' yj 1Cr * jlr Tin 5 a *e. (Cairo). April 16th. 1917 . D ‘ April 16th.if-iv, ”• April 17th, 1917, No. 443, Your telegram No, 587 transmitting telegram April 3th from Sir p„ cox;- Judicial adviser Ifr. Ndgar Bonham Carter C.K.G. age 47, has been legal secretary to Soudan Government since September 1899. He venue officers, la*. P. c. C.IBalf our; age 32, joined Soudanese Government service November 1906. nr,L,F.Nalder ; ; age 29, joined Soudanese Government service October 1912. All these are Nnglish and members of Soudanese Civil Service. I nave not yet mentioned proposed, appointments to them. 4c,3 Addressed to foreign Office; repeated to Basrah.4 copy- Cypher Telegram to Sir c. Marling (Teheran) Foreign Office, April 4th. 1917. ll.o.p.m From Lord Hardinge. Decypher yourself with Mr. Scott Private and Confidential . His Majesty's Government are considering the creation of a new administrative service in the occupied territories in Mesopotamia, which will be under His Majesty's Government, and not under the Government of India. The intention is to amalgamate the Sudan, the Levant, and the Mesopotamian services in one service, but this will require time to arrange and organise. Meanwhile we are anxious to provide as soon as possible for administration in the Vilayet of Bagdad^ in order to avoid the setting up of an administra** tion of British Indian officials, who will subse- '•) quently have either to be absorbed in the new servico or replaced by officials without experience and training* * this purpose I should be very glad if y could spare one or two capable Consular Officers go to Bagdad as soon as possible. Knowledge of p least the elements of Arabic is of course ess^ but Persian will also be of great use* Cowan,. Hava:Havard, and Worrall have been suggested to me as suitable, and I should like to have your observations as to them and any others who appear to you fitted for the political work which will be mostly called for in Bagdad* I am aware that it is imposing con** siderable sacrifice upon your establishment in Persia, but the need is really urgent and I shall be most grateful if you can help* WmmlC Baghdad is governed by a pasha, assisted by a i council. The pasha and the higher officials in general come from Constantinople, but a very large portion of the other Turkish officials seem to come from the town of Kerkuk. They constitute a class quite distinct from the native Arab population, and they and the Turkish government in general are intensely unpopular among the Arabs, an unpopularity increased by their religious differences, the Arabs being as a rule Shi’ites, the Turks Sunnites. Besides the court of superior officers, which assists the pasha in the general administration of the province, there is also a j1i$ or mixed tribunal for the settlement of municipal and commercial affairs, to which both Christian and Jewish merchants are admitted. Besides these, there are the religious heads of the community, especially the nakib and Jewish high priest, who possess an undefined and extensive authority in their own communities. The Jewish chief priest may be said to be the successor of the exilarch or resh galutha of the earlier period.”X. r Telegram from Sir P. Cox Dated 8th April 1917, 3 Received at India Office, 6 a.m. (9th). Priority^ (2J,3) ^#7 U isgr Ill'll s!5 T )!7_J ” * # ^rij bis 1062. Reference to telegraias from the Secretary of State dated 30th March and 8th April. May I please be informed of names, ages and member of years 1 service of proposed Judicial Adviser and the two subordinate Revenue Officers ? IP presume they are all Englishmen and belong to Civil Service. A competent Judicial Adviser is already available in Colonel Knox who has had two years* experience of local judicial needs and ideas and as it is common ground that Irak Code is not to be introduced and as he is quite prepared to work on the lines indicated by H. M. G-ovemment it seems superfluous, apart from Colonel Khox , s personal claims to consideration, to introduce another legal luminary. On the other hand couple of capable junior judicial Officers who could assist him in overhauling Turkish codes would no doubt be very useful. As regards Brigadier-General Clayton, his services would at any time be most valuable to me as well to Cx8vt. but I suggest that his designation be not decided until H.M.Govt. have had time to consider views of Amy Commander and myself as ^ 3 ^;) conveyed in my telegram 1049 dated 7th April. Addressed to Foreign and repeated to Secretary of State for India and Political Basra./ ^*4 66 *, f !01 ■fV ^T' 4 From Sir P. Cox, 7th April 19J 7. (Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Secretary of State for India, and Political, Basra.) (Received at 1 ) p.m.) ^^ d [9. ^ cur telegram 416 S. of 1st April repeating Secretary of State s telegram ol 29tli March for the future administration of Mesopotamia. I beg to oiler following observations in regard to details :—- 1. No comment needed from me. 2 . 1 agree. . 3. Ruler will^be acceptable or feasible as I know of no outstanding personality who could fill part. An Administrative Council presided over by High Commissioner seems best solution, either one for each vilavat or a combined one for both vilayats. 4 (a). I agree that the territory should be administered in accordance with existing laws and institutions, and I am moreover convinced that there would be great advantage in having uniform codes for Basra and Baghdad and other Arab provinces under/fom-»- growp) rule or protection. The Iraq code has served its purpose well, but it is admittedly provisional and revocable on the conclusion of war, and whatever be the final political status ol Basra, there seems to be no essential reason why systems established in both vilayats should not be assimilated. It must be remembered that Turkish judicial system included final reference to Constantinople for which substitute must be found by creation of High Court of Mesopotamia with final appeal to Privy Council. Incidentally also the civil and criminal codes and land laws will require considerable amendment and adjustment of wording to make them interpretable at all. As regards substitution of AraI &gt;/ for Turkish personnel, there is not sufficient indigenous material available at present, but it can gradually be created. 4 (IP). Tribal system of government already adopted where suitable, and no objection to provincial and local councils. 4 (c). I agree in principle'f4U &gt;&gt; 4 (d). 1 agree in proposition, but for duration of war we must have some latitude, especially in regard to clerical establishments. (Ono grm 11 d/equire- / merits of Expeditionary Force and military administration cannot wait, and have to be met by the most expeditious means possible. o. Of course in principle it would be much more satisfactory to have the ^Basra and Baghdad Yilayats administered on one7(two groupi:) system both rin regard to principle and detail. But I know that on the one hand we cannot annex both, and on the other hand/An o group) annew^Basra makes it necessary to put up with certain disadvantages wdiich that course may involve. I feel convinced, however, that no attempt to differentiate funda mentally in regard to working principle/and details of two administrations will produce satisfactory results, and that they should be so similar as to be indistinguishable in the working. The difference would be one of technical political status and nomenclature which need not make itself felt on the spot. To attempt to run the two vilayats, which are from every point of v ' ew inseparable, on conflicting lines ami inconsistent with principle f' (nine groups^. 6 . No comment or objection. 7. Nejef and Xerbela should not be treated as an enclave cut off from advantages resulting to united Mesopotamia from enlightened Government, which advantage inhabitants anticipate with lively expectation and will assuredly demand. They should be organised as independent townships as far as municipal administration is concernec^/ while unable at present to form an opinion as to irrigation, river conservancy, navigation, posts, telegraphs and railways, they should come under united Mesopotamia administration controlled by High Commissioner. Limits of townships would be existing limits of sacred territory round shrines. Both towns should be represented on Mesopotamian Administrative Council which would combine Vilayat Councils of both Yilayats and would /; /„: t ,, t Baolid.ad. The divergent local and tribal interests of each vdayat would blend or fall into their true perspective m this Urancil and Indran iinmigration and cognate questions would be more easily disposed of since the rmlit of united administration to regulate such questions in aceoidance with need of whole country would be unquestionable The towns themselves, apart from precincts of the Holy Places have ■dwuvs been open to Europeans and would continue to be so m future, hut' auv officials which the Government or the Municipalities intend to idaee in residence there should be Mohammedans agreeable to communities plied conu iy^Q^irely concur. These are two vital matters and incalculable harm may be done by injudicious or inexpert handling of them. h) and 10 . No comment. ' x' r t ■ I [ | ;l m strongly of opinion that sphere of t government of IiKlia in l^rsia should include whole of present neutral zone plus farthest limit of Kerman shah and Ispahan if possible. 12. It will be seen from the foregoing that I generally accept and agree with the lines of policy contemplated by War Council. Hie task of carryino' it out if one of no little difficulty would be one of. great interest and' were I called upon to inaugurate it at the psychological moment 1 feel I could enter on it whole heartedly, and suppose, lor a moment, mat His Majesty’s Government did or were to contemplate entrusting me with task I should highly appreciate compliment and eontideuce which it would imply,'but I should let them know now, as the Government of India are already aware, that while anxious like anybody else to see the wai thiough in whatever sphere my services could be most useful!} employed, I have, never desired and do not desire to remain in this country after the war, and, moreover, I feel sure that new policy stands a better chance ii: it were j . inaugurated bv official who is going to remain and see it taku* shape. Both Army Commander and I, however, are strongly of opinion that when His Majesty’s Government contemplate formally introducing above principles during the existence of martial law, and while the military position of Baghdad, is as it is (namely, that we are in almost daily conflict with Arab t n 1 }e ^(ono group) •)head of us, and that unless determined Russian advance 1 tnoes O'lm group' hul-uu ul un, cmvi nxu. v.tw.-v,. .... — is made, of which at present there is no evidence, we. must expect severe liGitino- around Baghdad when enemy has had time to leco'vei and concentrate fresh troops against us), they are taking too much for granted, and are making demands upon us which may at . any time, and in many particulars, be incompatible both with the military interests at stake and the freedom of action of Army Commander, whose Chief Political Stall Officer 1 am. At same time His Majesty’s Govenijnent may rest assured that 1 accept their policy in principle, and that as long as l am here 1 will proceed on the spirit of it as far as possible and do nothing which 1 . can avoid eithei. m principle or in detail to prejudice its complete inauguration when the time comes. Army Commander desires me to convey similar assurance on his behalf. . . ^ . . 1 lb. For the present I recommend that Chief Political Officer be permitted to carry on according to his lights in consultation with Army Commander as heretofore, and that as soon as conditions permit, say at the beginning of next cold weather, a Commission of lirst-class men be spared to examine whole problem on the spot, and make detailed recommendations as basis on which future policy can be formulated. Premature conclusions arrived at now may do irreparable damage, and it is submitted that only greatest emergency can justify hasty decision by War Cabinet before His Majesty s Government are in possession of complete facts and details regarding Baghdad Vilavat.private* Piy private and secret telegram of April 2nd* Acting Govemor-Oeneral reports situation as regards administrative staff in Soudan is very serious* Establishment is now 13 below minimum required and in adequate leave and additional work during past 2&gt;i years is telling on present personnel many of whom will break dov/n unless they can be sent to Europe this summer* I have urged upon him the imperative necessity for supplying two he venue officials for Basra but I must make their despatch conditional on provision of a few special service ondicers capable of discharging administrative duties and, if possible, the addition of agricultural assistance requested in my telegram Ho* 24* Unless War Office can (?group emitted ? help) to this extent Governor General foels he v/ould not be justified in sending two officials, who must lie physically fit, to Basra,. 1 concur with Governor General ! s view and trust you will represent to War office urgency of the matter and necessity for forwarding without delay the special service oil leers, preferably those with previous Soudanese ex perience, required to meet pressing administrative needs* I am asking Governor General to telegraph numbers ioned- lately ro-qutrad ant If possible names*i l Z'] ^ *^rzz^? ^~1f-&lt; c^^C*-**'*^ Circulated to:- ord Cur z on, sir T. Hold ernes s^ • L^rd Milner, Sir A.Hirtzel, ' ^ ^(MV .Chamberlain, Sir H.Graham. Cypher telegram to Sir R.Wingate (Cairo). Foreign UXfice. March olst.1917. 10*0 p fl m. Fxom. Lord hardin/ce. Private and Secret, his Majesty's Government have had under their serious consideration the question o£ the future admin istration of the Vilayets of Basra and Bagdad, which has now become a matter of urgency owing to the occupation of Bagdad. Their view is that the occupied territories in Mesopotamia, although they are at present and must for the time being remain in military occupation, should in the future be administered not by the Indian Govern ment but by the Foreign Office on behalf of His Majesty’s Government. In view of the pledges already given and the political interests involved, the Basra Vilayet should remain permanently under British administration, but it would be too early as yet to determine the precise form of Government to be ultimately set up in the Bagdad vilayet, though they propose, if it be possible, to erect an Arab facade, while keeping a firm hold on the external relations and general administra tion of the vilayet. Further,the Bhiah Holy Places, Wedjef and Kerbela which will remain in the Arab sphere, will**«.-• — * i ^ r l will require special treatment. They also have in con templation to add the Ai’ah littoral of the Persian Gulf as far as Hadrarnaut to the Basra Bagdad administration, and to place the political control of Aden, the Hadramaut and the South Arabian coast under the direction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. The sphere of influence to he assigned to Cairo would include Western Arabia (the Hedjaz, ASir and the Yemen). if these proposals are carried into effect it is clear that a special service will have to be instituted to provide the necessary officials, and the idea is that recruits for such a service might be found by amalgamating the Soudan, the kesopotamian and possibly the Levant Consular Services, the system followed for recruitment being that of the Soudan Civil Service, This will of course require time to work out and to train young officials. Meanwhile it is urgently necessary, if possible, to establish the basis of some such administra* tion for the two Vilayets, before methods of Indian administration become stereotyped there, especially in Bagdad: Basra has now for so long been x'un from India that it is probably better not to upset existing arrange ments until the whole scheme is complete and in working order. The most urgent needs in the Bagdad Vilayet are for a judicial adviser and for one or two sub ordinate revenue officers, and though we are well aware how hai^d pressed you are both in Egypt and the Boudan,m 1 \ suitable olficiuls for those purposes, ./hut they want to do is to maintain, as far as possible,^system, both -in civil and criminal matters, and both as regards the substance of the law and official personnel, and to leave the existing land revenue system as far as possible undisturbed, while the tribal system of Government, the provincial local councils and the old official organisa tion (Turks being replaced by Ai’absJ should be maintained Tiie head of the whole Mesopotamian Service will, it is suggested, be an oificial with the title of Governor of Basra and high Commissioner for Mesopotamia who would have two high officers under him, one a Deputy Governor Of Dasra, and the other Deputy high Commissioner for Mesopotamia,residing at Bagdad, Sir P.Cox’s name ob viously suggests itself for that of Governor and High Commissioner, and a very capable assistant for the diplomatic duties of Deputy High Commissioner at Bagdad, will also be required. It has occurred to me that General Clayton, if he could be spared, would be eminently qualified for such a post, and I should be glad before you mention tne matter to him, to have your views as to tnis or* in the alternative* your recommen dations of any other Egyptian or Soudan official whom you think suitable. mCirculated to * - Lord Curson, sir T.Kolderness, Lord Iviiluer, sir A.Hirtzel, iur.Chant)erlain, Sir R.Graham. Decypher of teiegrarii from Sir K.wingate (Cairo). D. IS.15 p.m. H. 1.20 p.m. To Lord hardimre. April 2nd.1917. Li’ ivate and Secret . Your private and secret telegram of March 31st. I will supply judicial adviser and two subordinate revenue officers and will submit names as soon as possible, i/hen is earliest date they will require to take up new duties? General Clayton is a very suitable selection as deputy High Commissioner of Bagdad* Please infom me when I may mention matter to i am very short of qualified staff both here and in the Soudan but I appreciate paramount importance of obtaining best men available and will help in any way I can. I am delighted to know that a scheme that will secure general co-ordination and similarity in treatment of Arab affairs, is now being elaborated.[P 1315] From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department 29th March 1917. Foreign Secret Committee of War Cabinet has considered me future administration and Political control of Mesopotamia and Trabia and has reached conclusions of which following is summary but'In- MisT 6 * 1 ! em ( t ? rie8 t0 be administered not by Government of India, but In Ins Majesty s Government. l2 ' KuskA to .remain permanently under British administration : western and northern limits to be Nasiryeh, Shatt-el-Hai, Kut, Bedrai. R V , 1 rf g r d tolje an Ara,J state with local ruler or Government under Butish I rotectorate in everything but name. Thus it will have no relations Government ' 11 ° W T ^ C ° U ' Suls wiU be accredited to His Majesty’s (4) Behind Arab facade Bagdad to be .administered as an Arab Province )\ indigenous agency and in accordance with existing laws and institutions as lar as possible. In particular (a) Irak Code not to bo used but local juc icial sj stem maintained as regards both law and personnel, only substi tuting Arab for lurk ; ( 6 ) similarly with executive and administrative machinery, tribal system of Government, provincial and local councils &amp;c. to be resuscitated and maintained ; (c) present land revenue system not to be disturbed ; (d) employment of Indians in any branch of administration to be strictly discountenanced as inconsistent with above principles, and no Asiatics fiom outside to be employed unless of Persian or Arab descent or domicile. The same to apply as far as possible to Busrah Vilayet. (o) If Busrah is not annexed, head of whole Mesopotamian administration to be High Commissioner residing at Bagdad, Busrah being placed under a Governor subordinate to him. If Busrah is annexed, head of administration t° be styled Governor of Busrah and High Commissioner for Mesopotamia with titular headquarters at Busrali, but residing generally at Bagdad. Deputy Governor and Deputy High Commissioner at Busrah and Bagdad respectively to act for him in his absence. (b) British Civil Service to be amalgamated with that of Soudan and possibly also of Levant, recruitment being by same method and personnel inter changeable. British officers of Indian services, if required at first, to be lent temporarily under foreign service rules, and those now serving there to be permitted to volunteer for permanent transfer. (7) Shiah holy places to form separate enclave not under direct British control, care being taken not to include in it any important irrigated or irrigable areas. ( 8 ) Control of irrigation in both Vilayets to be under single British administration and similarly with navigation and conservancy of rivers. (9j Koweit and whole Arabian littoral of Persian Gulf including Oman to be controlled by Busrah. (10) Aden and Hadramaut to be taken over by Foreign Office. (11) South Persia including Arabistan and Pars to be sphere of influence of Government of India. Lastly. —It is regarded of utmost importance that administrative arrange ment s introduced into Bagdad Vilayet should from the very outset strictly conform to above principles. Please instruct Cox to this effect at once with special reference to Head 4, and telegraph with least possible delay any remarks you may wish to make on any of these heads for consideration of War Cabinet before they reach final decision.222 T rom Secretary of State to T iceroy, Foreign ])epartment, 30tli March 1917. (Repeated to Sir F. Cox, Bagdad.) Secret. Your secret telegram of the 26th March. Civil administration of Bagdad. Please refer to my telegram dated 29th instant for general statement of intentions of His Majesty’s Government. You may appoint at once four or five Assistant Political Officers. We propose to send also some junior officers chosen from Arabic-speaking staff of Egypt, Soudan or Levant services to fill other political posts and for revenue. We think it desirable also to appoint Judicial Adviser from same source, as we do not wish to introduce Indian code. We are enquiring as to names. We have further had under consideration appointment of a deputy under Cox at Bagdad selected from same source, but should first like to hear his views on this proposal. Our object is to supply Cox with staff familiar with Arabic language and customs, and with Turkish administration and law. Before leaving Dobbs said his doctor advised that his return to Mesopotamia Avas impossible. 3o tU fjiOo C, SQ), S Ctpril, ^ W? i) X,' /rvT &lt;\ 3o C&amp;jlaj C.3. ( 7). S'dfw-U \ telegram from Viceroy, Foreigi Dept Dated 2Mh March 1917, vy 1 V 1 Received at India Office, 10 p.mj UAJ.C! xr uiJ. i'iiclX UI1# ClvjL. Administration of Baghdad. Although paramount direct British Secret. Your telegram of the 17th March. feivil Your telegram of the 17th March. administration may not be contemplated it seems essential that apart from martial law which can nowly maintain order steps should be taken to overhaul and replace defunct Turkish adminis tration and to carry on work of civil Departments. For this purpose we understand suitable Arab personnel is not immediately available and that onus must fall for the time being at any rate on British Officers, The immediate requirements appear to be (1) to secure submission by political means of tribes between Kut el Amara and our front line and later between Kut el Amara and Nasiriyah and settle them on accustomed lands on revenue paying basis. Latter is of course mostly in Basra Vilayet but we mention|it to show full requirements; (2) to overhaul and replace civil Depts. of Vilayet of Baghdad* For (1) a few military Assistant Political Officers will be required and we propose to send such suitable Officers as are available from India. We have already sent Major Bailey of Political Ddpt., may we use our discretion up to say 8 more Officers ? For (2) an experienced Revenue Officer with a staff of 2 or 3 Officers acquainted with Arabic and if to Mesopotamia and his health admits we propose to send him. If not we propose Holme of Political Dept. . One or two Mfix* Officers from Egypt or London would be useful in this capacity. Further we propose to send Holland on completion of trade Beport to Basra as Cox’s Deputy, Wilson moving up to Baghdad in similar capacity. Addressed to Secretary as No. 389 S.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100054608681.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/516/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100054608681.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/516/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 4097/1914 Pt 5 'Mesopotamia: administration; personnel; loan of officers from Egypt and Sudan'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1921</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-10T16:27:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (225 folios)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This item contains papers relating to the hiring of civilian staff in Baghdad from Cairo or India following the British occupation of Iraq during the First World War.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100054608681.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>