<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000202_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T07:43:54.213Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">File 53/87 ~ii - Volume D,152 ( British Policy In Kuwait ) International status 2-6,36-48. of Kuwait. Iraqi conscription of 30-32,58,63-64,94-96. Kuwaiti Nasr bin All as Subah. Iraqi port in Kuwait bay 14-20,26-29,33-34,49-57,60-62, and Kuwait-Iraq railway, 66-83,85-91. proposed construction of, Iraqi port at Khor Abdullah, 97-100,104-5,110,112,114-124,126- proposed construction of, 163,165-191,194-196. Kuwait nationality 8-11,22-24,94-96.No. 557/1/58. HIS Majesty's Ambassador at SHIRE IE IDg faaJhs,**** - ' confident :;- f Bagdad •.ph presents his compliments to The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Embassy Bagdad* , 193.8. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. atch No. 162 dated 19th April to Foreign Office, London. Koweit - International Status. I 3479 13804 (2)p C '• i THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNI C MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT L EASTERN (A rabia). ,V CONFIDENTIAL. May 2, 1938. @ /$, I. , i S ection 1. eo is f :' d S t H l r 5 r. ds [E 2499/13/91] Copy No. 107 Sir M. Peterson to Viscount Halifax.—2.) (No. 162.) IJS y/z/Jl) My Lord, ' Bagdad, A pril 19, 1938. I HAVE the honour to report that, in the course of a visit which I paid to the Minister for Foreign Affairs 09 the 12th instant, the Minister raised the question of the international s tatus of Koweit. 2. His Excellency began by saying tlat the Persian Minister had more than once discussed with him the position of Great Britain in the Persian Gulf, and had implied that His Majesty's Government had no more right to exercise a protectorate over Koweit than they had to do so over Bahrein. He had maintained that Bahrein belonged to Persia, and he had suggested that Koweit might very well be claimed by Iraq. 3. Taufiq Suwaidi said that he had replied that the Iraqi Government regarded the Persian claims to Bahrein as a matter for settlement between Persia and Great Britain, and he had refused to be drawn into a discussion about * Koweit. Nevertheless, the seeds sown by the Persian Minister had evidently begun to germinate in Taufiq Suwaidi's mind. He had with him Volume XI of f ^ 1 1 Aitchesoris Treaties, and read out to me article 6 of the Anglo-Turkish Agreement (unratified) of July 1913, inviting my particular attention to the reference to the Sheikh of Koweit as an Ottoman Kaimakam which occurs therein. What, he said, did this mean? Surely it indicated that Koweit was not really an independent State, and was it not arguable that, since in 1913 Koweit had been technically a Kaza of the Basra Vilayet and as the sovereignty of this Vilayet had since then passed from the old Ottoman Empire to the new Iraqi Kingdom, Koweit now stood in relation to Iraq in the same position as it had stood in relation to the Ottoman Empire at the time when the Anglo-Turkish Agreement had been negotiated. 4. Iraq, Taufiq Suwaidi said, had in fact never recognised any change in the status of Koweit. The Iraqi Government had, it was true, in a letter written. / Q by Nuri Said as Prime Minister, recognised a certain line as being the frontier!' 0 ' . between Iraq and Koweit, but as this line was the same as that laid down in the Anglo-Turkish Agreement of 1913, the reaffirmation of this frontier could not be I held, he thought, to have brought any change to the status of Koweit which, judging from the agreement, seemed to have been that of an autonomous Kaza or Kaimakamlik of the Ottoman Empire. 5. The Minister explained that the matter was one of some importance in relation to the ideas which the Iraqi Government had already put forward ^ concerning the stopping of smuggling from Koweit through the control of the |^ /l Koweiti Customs (see Mr. Morgan's letter to Mr. Baggallay of the 15th March) ^ %0 and the extension of the Iraqi railway to Koweit Bay, in order to provide Iraq , /, with a port on the Persian Gulf (see my despatch No. 116 of the 30th March).^v'/ » He thought that in view of the Anglo-Iraqi Alliance, His Majesty's Government should see no serious objection in principle to these projects and it had occurred to him that a re-examination of the status of Koweit on the basis of the Anglo- Turkish Agreement of 1913 might reveal a way to overcome any political difficulties of a technical character to which it might seem that these schemes would give rise. 6. I said that the question was one which was largely new to me and I could not undertake to make any statement about the status of Koweit until I had had time to study the relevant documents. It seemed to me, however, that his Excellency was overlooking the Treaty of Lausanne. Under article 16 of that treaty, Turkey had renounced all rights and title whatsoever over Koweit and with that renunciation these rights had finally ended. There could, therefore, be no question of their having been inherited by any of the States which had been [305 b—1]2 set up in any part of the territory which, under the 1 reaty of Lausanne, had been detached from the Ottoman Empire. I made it clear, however, that this was a personal view given with all reservations, and I explained that I could give no formal or authoritative reply to the Minister's enquiries until I had referred to your Lordship for instructions. 2? h I 7. From such study as I have since been able to make of this question (please see particularly Sir John Simon's despat6li No. 865 of the 13th December, 1934), it appears that Koweit is recognised by His Majesty's Government as an independent Government under British protection (Political Besident s letter to the Sheikh of the 3rd November, 1914) and that from the point of view of international law Koweit's independence began from the date of the ratification of the Treaty of Lausanne (6th August, 1924). On this date also, Turkey renounced all rights over Koweit and these'rtghts, whatever they may have been, thereupon terminated and were not transferred to any other State. 8. I should be glad if you would inform me whether I may give oral explanations to the Minister for Foreign Affairs on the above lines, and I should welcome any additional arguments that it may be possible to put forward, with which to refute the suggestion that Iraq has acquired certain rights over the territory of Koweit. In particular it would, I feel, be an advantage to show that the Iraqi Government had in some way recognised both the independence of Koweit and the special relations between His Majesty's Government and the Euler of Koweit. Failing that, evidence of the recognition of Koweit's independence by other Powers would be of value. 9. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Political Resident m the Persian Gulf and the Political Agent at Koweit. I have, &amp;c. MAUEICE PETERSON.S&gt;f*7 Sxtract from H.A.F. Intelligence Summary, Iraq, for the month of March 1938, those opposing the treaty. The most important of these being Rustum Haiciar, whose speech was both calm and balanced. After sympathising with the Government for their awkward situation vis-a-vis the Treaty, which had been bequeathed by the late unlamented Government, he proceeded to condemn the Treaty because it endangered Iraq's future by jeopardising her position in her only outlet to the sea - the Shatt-al-Arab; Kuwait had been part of the Ottoman Empire but was not part of Iraq and afforded Iraq no alternative outlet. He concluded by suggesting that a remedy might be found by an exchange of notes with Iran and simultaneously an approach should be made to Iraq* s ally, Great Britain, and also Kuwait with a view to Iraq securing an outlet to the sea in this territory. 87, (*r 9 The Minister for Foreign Affairs was followed by xlot.- fr' 7 :, BC^ ^tfeH ^-elv ifla , | BUSHiRc r .-^'OENCY . j No.lfba&amp;futs. 2287/58, in, f . INDIA OPPIOE, WHITEHALL, S.W.I • PICORDS KcAA. ^ 29th April, 1938, I enclose for information a copy of the marginally noted correspondence about the line to ~ ~ ) 'be taicen by the oreign Office dated 31st March 1938 ) and enclosure ) Bagdad Embassy in oreign Office dated S6th April 1938 ) ) the event of the ' '{vsflst s^ M e I M JsIJllO Mb Iraqi Government reverting to the question of Koweit nationality. You will recall that you concurred in the terms of the suggested reply to Peterson. Copies of this letter (and enclosures) are being sent to the Government of India and to the Political Agent, Koweit. / cwas? Hon ! ble Lieut.Colonel Sir Trenchard K.C.I.E., G.B.E., H.B.M. 1 s Consulate General, Bushire.8 P.Z.8287/1938. FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.I (E 1450/13/91) 31st March, 1938. rv^ My dear Gibson, With ref^ence to correspondence resting with Foreign Office letter No. E 1383/13/91 of the 18th March on the subject of enquiries by the Iraqi Government ahout Bahreini (and Koweiti) nationality, I enclose a copy of a letter from Morgan in Bagdad in regard to the line to be taken in the event of the Iraqi Government reverting to the question of Koweiti nationality. We have gone into the question again with Beckett and our conclusions are set out in the enclosed draft of a letter to Peterson. We have also drawn attention to a point arising^out of the wording used in the Embassy 1 s memorandum to the iraqi Ministry for Foreign Affairs about Bahreini nationality. Will you please let me know as soon as convenient whether the India Office concur in this draft. Yours sincerely, (Sd. ) LACY BAG-GALLAY. P. Gibson, Esq.p.z. 2287/1938. Enclosure in Foreign Office Covering Letter dated 1st April 1938, copy E 1450/13/91) (810/3/38) British Embassy, Bagdad, 28th February, 1938. !&gt; My dear Baggallay, pl l With reference to the question of Bahrainis mentioned 7 in your letter E 7819/30/91 of the 26th January and previous correspondence. You will see from a Printed Letter No. 73 which we are sending this week to the Foreign Office that we have replied to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs about Bahrain! nationality. In view of the^€luctance of the Foreign Office (see Foreign Office despatch No. 865 (E 7283/1527/91) of the 13th December, 1934) to take up position publicly about Kov/eiti nationality, I have simply ignored that part of the Iraqi enquiry, for, so far as I know, we have had no complaints about Koweitis being conscripted in Iraq, and, therefore, no practical end is served (as it is in the case of Bahrainis) by replying to the enquiry. Should the Iraqis return to the charge about Koweiti nationality, might it not suffice to explain to the Minister for Foreign Affairs verbally that His Majesty^ Government have decided views about Koweiti nationality but, for technical reasons not connected with Iraq, prefer not to give official expression to them unless forced to do so by the emergence of some maoor issue? One could add that such a major issue did not seem to exist in the present case, and one could even, if you approve, say that His Majesty's Government, in view of possibilities - however remote- of claims to capitulatory privileges (one might even claim the sympathetic Baggallay, Esq. agreement/10 2 agreement of the Minister for Foreign Affairs on this point) 'by Foreign Powers, did not wish to disclose (unless for some very compelling motive) their position prematurely. I should be glad of your views on the above. Yours ever, (Sd # ) JAMES MOROAH.^. INDIA OPPIGE, WHITEHALL, S .W .I Z.2287/38. 26th April, 1938. v v . My dear Baggallay, With reference to your letter of the 31st March (No, E. 1450/13/91) in regard to the line to 'be taken in the event of the Iraqian Government reverting to the question of Koweit nationality, I am desired to say that we concur in the terms of the suggested draft letter to Peterson. Yours sincerely, (Sd # ) J. P. GIBSON. L. Baggallay, Esq., Foreign Office, S.W.IHo•©•1554-H/38• The undermentioned papers are forwarded to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Simla; The ^ May 19 58• A copy of memorandum from His Majesty's Ambassador&gt; Bagdad, Ho.317/1/38, dated the 30th March 1938, with end osure • No C3^FJ0£NTJAL RECORDS© Ho. (317/1/38) . His Majesty r s Ambassador at Bagdad presents his compiimeats to the Foreign Secreoary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Uew Delhi, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-menticned documen ts. British Embassy, Bagdad 30th March 1938 Reference to previous correspondence; Description of Enclosure Uame and Date Subj ect Despatch No.116 dated 7^ Koweit-Iraq railway 30th March,1938, to the Foreign Office, London (Copy sent to Tehran).Mo.116. British Embassy, (SI7/1/38). Bagdad. ^ 30th March, 1938. My Lord, I have the honour to report that early in March, the Minister for Foreign Affairs, during a conversation with Mr. Morgan, stated that Iraqi statesmen has recently 'been thinking a great deal about Iraq's position on the Shatt-al-Arab. The frontier negotiations with Persia had, he explained, brought it home to them that if access to Basra from the sea should ever be made difficult through trouble with Persia, Iraqi interests would be gravely prejudiced and, for this reason, they felt strongly that an Iraqi por t on the sea was most desirable. 2. Taufiq Suqraidi then pointed out that Koweit offered an obvious solution to this problem and he asked Mr. Morgan whether His Kajesty t s Government would be likely to agree to I permit the Iraqi Government to extend their railway through Kow^iti territory to the coast in Koweit Bay and to build a port there under their own control. He indicated that they would be willing to compensate the Shaikh of Koweit for the grant of these facilities, and he thought that they could reach agreement with His Highness, provided His Kajesty t s Government raised no political objections. 3. X have discussed this matter with Sir John Ward. He told me that the plan which he himself was reccmmending to the Iraqi Government was that the railway should be extended to ?ao and uhat the Iraqi Government should buy three... The Right Hon urable The Viscount Halifax, K.G., G.G.S.I., G.G.I.S., etc. etc. etc.three good 5,COO tons steamers with which to maintain a regular service between Fao and Karachi. He thought that this undertaking would 'be most profitable, since itwould save a day^s journey up the Shatt~al-Ara'b and would increase tourist traffic to the Holy Places in Iraq. He also thought that so soon as the Taurus route had been linked with Bagdad, many people would travel to Europe from India via Iraq, if there we^e a go d steamer service from Karachi to !Fao. He told me privately, that te had his eye on three vessels of the kind required which could be bought at a favourable price. 4. Sir vTohn T .Tard t s objects in makin; these suggestions to the Iraqi Qovemment were, of course, different from these which the Minister for Foreign Affairs had in mind when thinking of an outlet at Koweit. A port at Fao would not be free from the menace of Persian interference and, in order to maintain access to it, the Iraqi Governmant would still have ®ake sure of their control of the Rookha Channel. Indeed, from the point of view of freedom from Persian inter ference, Fao seems to offer but little advantage over Basra. 5. Nevertheless, the history of Great Britain fc s relations with Koweit suggests that there is little likeli- hood that the Minister for Foreign Affairs scheme for an Iraqi port in Koweit Bay would ever be welcome to HJs Majesty's Government and, subject to any instructions which Your Lord-ship may think fit to send me, I shall do my best to discourage X Taufiq Suwaidi from pressing his proposals and to persuade him to devote his attention instead to Sir John Tard's plans. I have the honour to be with the highest respect, My Lord, Your Lordship's most obedient humble servant, Sd/- Haurice Peterson.&amp;p7 nonf identlal The Hesldenoy, Buahire, tiie 24th May 1938. n.O.HQ.278-3 .rv vai n Gould you please refer to Petersoxi^ despatcn to ^ P'fU the foreign Office No.116 of 30th March, sent to mender GOTerniaent of India printed X»etter No#D« 1do4 - 'N/ / 3B of 4th May, on the subject of a port under Iraqi control at Kuwait connected with Basra toy an extension of the railway* This project of the Iraqi (lOTermaent raises some interesting ana important speculati ons. 2. In the first place, If the Shaiicn of Kuwait were to agree to the project, and His Majesty^ Government to object, can the latter blocic it ? The answer would appear to be defin itely in the affirmative under the Agreement of 1899 {Aitchison Vol.XI page 262) by which the Bhaikh ^binds himself, nis heirs and successors not to cede, sell, lease, mortgage, or give for occupation or for any other purpose any portion of his territory to the Government or subjects of any other power witnout the previous consent of Her Majesty's Government for these purposes.'* 3. In the second place would such a port ifuit the Shailch and His Majesty^ Government ? The answer to this question depends on what exactly is meant by Iraqi control. If by this is meant that there would be an Iraqi port, a sort of Iraqi enclave, in Kuwait territory, ; then the project is out of the question. If, however, all that is required is a Kuwaiti port, which would be run by Iraqi officials, but would politically be under the Shaikh, and therefore under His Majesty's OoTernment, then the project assumes another aspect. The details of any Ir Aubrey Metcalfe, K.C.I.B.,C.S.I.,M.V.O. agreement/ Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla.7./ -2- agreement to this would have to be carefulXy worked, out, but tiie Interests of all conoeriied migixi: be met by a Kuwait port Trust on whioh besides Iraqi members, there would be representatiTes of the Shaikh, and the Political Agent as representing His Majeoty^s QoTernment. There may be precedents for this sort of thing in other parts of the worId• 4 # would such a port suit the Shaikh ? financially f doubtless it would. The Iraqi Government would presumably give him a lump sum down for permission to establish this port, and thereafter some percentage of the Iraqi Customs dues. In view of the oil field which will probably be opened up shortly in his territory, a port and railway would be very convenient. o. Would such a port suit His Majesty^ Government ? quite possibly it might from xhe strategical, Maval ana Air point of views communication between Basra and the Persian Gulf would no longer have to depend almost entirely, as ix does at present, on zxie 3hatt-al-Arab and the Rooicha channel, while the terminus of the railway at Kuwaii: would be under the guns of the sloops of the Persian Gulf Division. ^rom the air aspect, if at any time the Royal Air Force wished to establish a base at Kuwait, the fact of the latter having the facilities of a modern port, including a railway, would be an advantage. l^om another point of view altogether tne Basra - Kuwait railway might mailo unprofitable such Kuwait - Iraq smuggling as still goes on, and 'Gnus lead to its complete extinction.I'l 7 # Whatever value the above arguments may have, I presume that before we actually discourage the Iraqi proposals the whole question will be examined by the various authorities concerned. * I am sending a copy of this letter to Peterson and Gibson. (flc- # sent under P.L.MO.279-S of 34/o/38.3679a INDIA OFFICE, POLITICAL T'T express letter (air mail). 'RUSHIRE F.ES'.DEN CY^ fipi ateEK-T. ^y ^/• 8 CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS i 0 (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From To Secretary of State for India Government of India, external Affairs Department, repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Oulf. Dated 17th May, 1338 Na P,Z.3139/38 Please refer to Fureigu Orrice letter of the 2nd May, No. E.20Sk/209k/95f a copy of which was sent to you by the air mail of 7th May, regarding the enquiry whether His Majesty's Government would be likely to agree to permit the Iraqi Government to extend their railway through Koweiti territory to the coast in !{oweit Bay and to build a port thei'asunder their control. I should be grateful if you tfould furnish me with your views after consultation with the .Political Resident in the Persian Gulf who is being supplied witn a copy of this letter, of the Foreign Office letter under reference, and of Bagdad despatch No.116 of the 30th March. h' 11 The issue of the above has been authorised. \ p (SgcL) R. PEEL*By Air Mail. p.z. 19 jT bushi^eresidency; /Vo &amp;f COJiFIDENTIAL RECORDS r iC&gt;. INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 11 Si AY 1938 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. Mr i A copy has been sent to ^ J*fL%K b ^ MaiL 4963 2000 7.36 Pbe-Fom^iL..Secre.tary, Gov-eynment of India. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.w By Air Mail. P.Z. I DUPLICATE. Air Mail of v bushire residency . Jy-J No Date CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS ginal sont by INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, iJUH % @) V ^ Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has 4963 2000 7.36 The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.P.Z. 3139/38 91+/209V93. POEEIGN OFFICE, S.¥. 1. 2nd May, 1938 Sir, I am directed Td ^viscount Halifax to transmit to you herewith, to 'be l^tad 'before the Marquess of Zetland, a copy of a despatch from His Majesty^ Ambassador at Bagdad regarding a recent enquiry from the Iraqi Minister of Foreign Affairs as to the attitude of His Majesty's Government towards an extension of the Iraqi railway system through Koweiti territory to the coast in Koweit Bay, and the construction of a port there under Iraqi control. 2. Lord Halifax considers that it is only natural that the Iraqi Government, realising the potential dangers of Persian interference with shipping in the Shatt-el-Arah and the Rooka Channel, should turn their thoughts towards an alternative outlet to the sea in Koweit. He realises however that the proposal in its present form is probably open to objection from the point of view of His Majesty's Government* Not only might it prove difficult to devise a practicable scheme by which the Iraqi Government should have the desired control of their own railway and port, while safeguarding the rights of the Sheikh of Koweit, but, even if this difficulty were overcome, the execution of such a plan might lead to a great extension of Iraqi influence in Koweit, and so make it increasingly difficult to maintain the integrity of the Sheikhdom. Moreover, in view of the great interest taken by His Majesty's Government in t he m aintenance of the Shatt-el- Arab, it appears doubtful whether it is from this point of view desirable/ Jnder Secretary of State, India Office. ' r , « / ^ &amp; /jf '' ' ^2 ^7 desiratae that the Iraqi Governraent shall develop on the coast of the Persian Oulf a port which might reduce the amount of shipping using the Shatt-el-Arab. 3. His Lordship therefore proposes to inform Sir Maurice Peterson that he approves the line suggested 'by His Excellency in paragraph 5 of his despatch, and I am to request you to inform me as soon as possible whether Lord Zetland concurs. U* In view of the more friendly relations at present existing between Persia and Iraq, and in view of the prospective settlement of the territorial dispute in the Shatt-el-Arab, Lord Halifax trusts that the Iraqi Government will not press their suggestion at the present time. It seems to him jbrobable however that some such proposal will be revived o^uiier or later, especially if the Persian Government construct p &gt; fortifications or mount guns in the neighbourhood of the whole position anew. Even if the proposal in its present form is open to objection, it might nevertheless be possible in that event to devise some alternative scheme by which the Iraqi Government, and perhaps also His Majesty* s Government, might benefit in an emergency. 5. Similar letters are being sent to the Admiralty, War Office and Air Ministry. I am, etc (Sd) G.W. BAXTERiiji? pTifiMIRE RESIDENCY. | - '''nO.iFlDEMTiAL RECOriDS | ,3464/38. SET. 3/1087/ (M.O.lj THE WAR OFFICE, LONDON, S.W.I. 16th Way, 1938. ^ y ' The Under-Secretary of tate for War presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India and is coismanded by the Army Council to transmit for the information of the Marquess of Zetland a copy of the document noted in the subjoined schedule on the subject of extension of Iraq.! railway system through Koweiti territory. Bate From Description 14 May 1938 War Office to Army Council letter Foreign Office No,0178/1087(M.0.i; Copies also sent to; Admiralty Air Ministry,dD 29 P WAR OFFICE, S.W.I. 087(M.0.1; 14th Mai-', 1938. J ^ Sir, p 1 I am commanded by the Army Council to reply to your letter No .i., S094/S094/93 dated 8nd May, 1938, and to inform you, for the information of Viscount Halifax, that the Council are in general agreement with the views put forward in paragraph 2 of your letter. 2, I am to say that although an extension of the Iraq Railways through Koweit territory might eventually prove a useful link with a through route via Baghdad to the Taurus oystem, free from possible interference Iran, the Council consider that this advantage would not he an adequate return , f or the decrease of trade in Shatt-el-Arah and the undesirable f e xtension of Iraqi Influence in Kowe it v /hich the project would involve. I am further to say that in these circumstances the Council agree to the line of action proposed by Sir Maurice Peterson in paragraph 5 of his despatch No.116 dated 30th March, 1938. 4. I am to add that when tae project for the construction of the Baghdad railway was under consideration, the question of a terminal port in Koweit territory, or its vicinity, was discussed by the Committee of Imperial Defence in Paper No.45 B of December 1904 and Paper No. 67 B of November 1905. I am, etc. , Sgd. A. E. WIDDO'VS. ler-Secretary of State, •reign Office, 3. W.l.■&gt;1 / u GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, ^ &lt;5 ■ Departmsnt, EXPRESS LETTER [N* B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had T so despatched*] (*- To Hie Hon T ble the political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire^ ^ ^ b J&gt;aM&amp; Qth June Sub je ot:- Iraqi Conscription pr a meiaber of the Ruling family of IDiwai t. i His Higtmess the Ruler has appealed for assistaose in saving from iraq^i Conscription, a member of his family, one ilasir bin Ali as-Sub ah, aged 22, a grandson of Shaikh Mohammad as-^Subah, the Ruler of Kumit from 1892 to 1896* 2. KTasir was born in Kuwait, his mother is a ICUV-aitiya, and his father and ancestors were born in Kuwait, but he has lived with his family in a house belonging to his fat lie r at 2iubair, Just over the Iraq, border, since 1925, and pert owns date-garden estates in Iraq, at SIBA, at which latter place he believes that in his absence he ^may have been registered as an Iraqi. 3. He is however registered at Zubair as a ICuwaiti, and holds a Kuwait; Certificate of Identity, and has just been offered an s. 6. mfp—1407 s&amp;p—(m-2339)—26-6-37—300,000^-2- &gt;■ I offered an appolntnEnt by the Shaikli of Kuwait* 4. The Iraqi Authorities, in spite of protests, continue to demand that he should join the AZmy on June S3rd, failing T^hioh he will, presumably be held criminally guilty in Iraq. In answer to his reply that he is a Kuwaiti, his lawyer was informed by the Ministry of Interior of Iraq, the.t^his family had been established in Iraq, 'before the Treaty of Lausanne', he would have to serve as an Iraqi soldier♦ The Mutasarrif of Basra, to whom reference was made by him holds, he says, similar views. 6. Nasir tells me that if he fail^ to carry out Iraqi Service he believes that his family, his elder brother and property in Iraq will suffea?, as he fears that political and not purely military and legal considerations are weighing with the Iraqi Authorities in this xsase. 7. it has been impressed upon him that he should stay in Kuwait, where he is now, until the matter can be cleared Upo Political Agent, Kuwait *GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AiR MAIL). [N,B.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a No. C/359 revomibk officer of the Department.] office of the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 3.S.V a RSOVA. m&gt; Dated the gist June _ | ^38 tnC v* Btom - Political Resident, Busiiire # on a.V.ARSOVA. To - His Majesty^ .Ambassador, Bagdad. Repeated H«M. Secretary of State for India, London. the Secretary to tJae Government of India in the External Affairs .Department, Simla. Y'R if fipynffBTflr Political i^gent, Kuwait. Subject s Iraqi conscription of a member of the Kuwaiti Ruling family. A ^ I enclose herewith copy of an Express Letter No. C-205, dated 8th June 1938, from the Political Agent, Kuwait, and would be grateful if representations could be made to the Iraq Grovernment on the subject. sd.t.c* ; fowls Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED fo* Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian (Julf. } !&lt; 11® (Signature) S/44. MFP—985 S&amp;P—(M.1597)—27-11.36-10,000. (Designation)53p I 3 3 r*' 1 Secret Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Crulf, Gamp Karachi* D&gt;Q&gt;Ho*G/395 30th June 1938» wv d !&gt; it Vl ^ .. CouXti-you please refer to India Office Printed / Letters hob .3139/38 of the 17tji May* and 3464/38, enclosing respeotiTely foreign Office letter of the 2nd May and War Office letter of the 14th May, and also to my letter So,278--3 of 24th May to Metcalfe, copy sent to the India Office and Bagdad under my printed Letter Ho.279-S of the same date* 2* In paragraph 2 of the War Office letter a reference is made to (a) a possible decrease of trade in the Shatt al Arab and (b) the extension of Iraqi influence in Kuwait. 3. With regard to (a). It seems to me that the volume of British trade entering Iraq will be unaffected^ all that will happen would be that some of it will enter Iraq through Kuwait instead of all of it going in through Basra. with regard to (b). I think that so long as sufficient safeguards are provided in any agreement made with the Iraq Ooverrment noli for the port at JEQiwait, this would/be a very serious objection, 4. neither of the objections mentioned by the '#ar Office are of a strictly strategical nature. It would be interesting to have their opinion on this aspect. 5. With regard to the foreign Office despatch. Shere is the possibility envisaged in paragraph 4 of the Iranian Government constructing at some future date fortifications or mounting/ .T. Peel, Ssquire, The India Office, London ; c &gt; /-2- 34 © Mounting guns in the neiglibouriiood of tiie Siiatt al Ara^# It might possibly be worth while, from our point of view, for this contingency to be forestailed by the construction of the railway in question since once the Iranian Govern ment had decided to fortify the Shatt al Arab they could place guns in position much quicker than the Iraqis could build the railway# 6* However the pros and the cons of the whole proposal may lie^I presume that, as suggested in paragraph 7 of my letter No.217-3, dated the g4th May 1938, (copy to Gibson under my Printed Letter Ho.279-S of same date), before a final decision is come to the matter will be carefully gone into toy all the authorities concerned# I am sending copies of this letter to Peterson and Metcalfe. * sent under P.L.So.0/396 of 30/6/38.A 4 By Air Mail. rRPfV^r^ nF o &gt;'0^NGV. ; J4&amp;. M P.Z. V3yH ii&gt;&amp; i CONFIDENTIAL BECORPS INDIA OFFICE, /? ' S y LONDON, ^5' T»—C Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to -i- 1 by Mail. of Indkr. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 4963 2000 7.36PPY DOWNING 3TRHI5T, B 1520/46/91) 2nd February, 1933. Mk ■£&gt;.96. Sir, 1 have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of Sir p. CQx's despatches Ho.876 of the 19th of December and Nob •874 and 877 of the 20th December regardirig the settlement of the Iraq-H© jd, Iraq-Koweit and itq jd-Koweit boundaries, and to inform you that I approve the proposals made in the two last mentioned despatches. 2. With regard to despatch Ho.876, your proposals relating to the Iraq-Neja frontier also are approved, subject to rectification of a small mistake which occurs in the concluding sentence of the second paragraph of Protocol Ho.1» The words 'Latitude 38 Kast' should read 'latitude 32 north' and, similarly, 'Longitude 50 north' should read 'longitude 39 east'. 5. When finally signed, two certified trans lations of the above agreements should be forwarded to me. One is for record in thia Department; the other would be transmitted to the Foreign Office, in view of the fact that His Majesty's Goverrment are to sone extent responsible both for Iraq and for oweit. I have etc., (Signed) DKVONBHIfiK. Acting High CommiaeionerV-J | &gt; 5 The Sealdency r« ■ w ( x v-. i t ■ zL: ^ ' J8 /46/91). Baghdad, the 20th December, 192 C.0.874. My Lord Duke, With reference to my two subsequent despatches dealing provisionally with the Irag-Hajd and Kuwait-Hajld frontiers. It would he convenient If we could at the same time arrive at a decision as to the frontier which we can advisedly recognise as between Iraq and Kuwait# I have the honour to suggest for the consideration of His Majesty 1 s Government that it would he reasonable for us to consider that the said frontier should start in the South from the point on the green line of the Anglo-Turkish Agreement of 89th July, 1913, where the Wadi-el-Audja intersects with the Bat in, and from thence follow the said green line along the Batin to its termination at the mouth of the Khor rubier just South of Jebel Sanam Safwan and Um-Qaor, leaving them to Iraq. I shall be glad to be informed whether the proposition meets the views of His Majesty's Government# I may mention that the question of the Iraq-Kuwait frontier has not hitherto been raised by King Faisal or his Oovernment and they will presumably accept our decision In regard thereto. I have, etc# (Signed) B.H» Bourdillon# for High Commissioner for Iraq# •ace The Duke of Devonshire, K.G., (KC#M.a. # cuc»V»0. f Secretary of State for the Colonies, Downing Street, London, S.f.l#1.4054/38 &amp; x ^ M 0 ! M.02976/38 00NPIDBNTI Sir, ADMIRALTY, S.W.I. 10th June, 1938. BUSWRERlsio^Fv // -7:. 5 ^ C0?JR3iriTiAtr l EC0FJ» _ V &gt; In reply to Foreign Office letter B 20y4/2094/93 of the 2nd May* I am commanded iDy My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs» that they concur in the view that the construction of a port in Koweit Bay under Iraqi control* coupled with an extension of the Iraqi railway thereto, would he open to objection on the ground that if such a project were executed, the Sheikhdom would tend to fall more and more under Iraqi influence. 2. It appears to 'be undesirable from every point of view that a British protected Sheikhdom should 'become dependent economically on Iraq to too great an extent. Furthermore, the development of the port would no doubt involve the grant of privileges which would tend to assiane a political character, such as freedom from Koweit customs control, etc., and it seems very unlikely that the Iraqis would agree that Koweit (a comparatively insignificant Sheikhdom) should have any considerable hand in the control of their new port. 3. Moreover, My Lords feel that the danger from Persia which the Iraqi project is designed to insure against could hardly he regarded as serious so long as the Anglo-Iraqi alliance is maintained. It is unlikely that . \ Persia would commit an act of aggression against Iraq while we were at peace. If we were at war it also seems to he improbable that Persia, left to herself, would adopt a hostile attitude, since we are the largest purchasers of Persian oil, and, in the event of supplies sr Secretary of State, reign Office, being/ S.W.I-2- st&gt; @ 'being Y /ithheld from ourselves&gt; we should almost certainly 'be in a position to ensure that no enemy po?/er obtained oil from this source. The resulting loss of revenue should 'be sufficient to deter Persia from any such hostile move. 4. The real danger to our supplies of oil from Persia would appear to he that internal disturbances, 1 inniii 'Mhi m iii probably fomented by our enemies, might break out in that country whenve were at war. In this event it would be necessary for us, if we were to continue to draw these supplies, to control that part of the country where the oil concession lies, and this would incidentally mean security of navigation in the Shatt-el-Arab. 5. My Lords would accordingly suggest that, provided the Secretary of State concurs in the foregoing analysis of the probable Persian attitude, it might be as well that His Majesty's Ambassador, Bagdad, should also be instructed, when he attempts to dissuade the Iraai Government from the Koweit scheme, to remind them of the value of their alliance with this country. 6. With regard to Sir John Ward's proposal for a port ^ at Fao, Their Lordships consider that this project would, from the point of view of this country, have none of the disadvantages of the scheme for a port at Koweit. Indeed it would appear to offer definite advantages since any development which would attract more trade to the Shatt-el- Arab is desirable hecause it is hound to result in a wider distribution of the heavy dredging costs and a corresponding decrease in the high proportion of these dues at present derived from the shipment of Persian oil. An increase in the traffic not related to the carriage of oil is all the more desirable in view of the possibility that the Oil Company may be obliged to develop a port in Persian territory (e.g. at Bandar Shahpur). Conversely, the development of an/an Iraqi port outside the Shatt-el-Arat), 'by taking away from the river traffic not connected with the carriage of oil* could only lead to an increase in the dredging dues levied on ships carrying that commodity; this in turn would further encourage the Persians to proceed ?d.th their project for a port at Bandar Shahpur, which, 'being on neutral territory, ?/ould he of much less use to this country than an Iraqi port for supply purposes in time of war. 7# finally, I am to enclose notes prepared 'by the Hydrographer of the Navy on the relative suitability of Koweit and Fao for development as a port. These notes also contain information ahout another possible site - the Khor Shetana - hut this is furnished solely as a matter of interest, and Their Lordships do not wish thereby to suggest in any way that the attention of the Iraqi Government should 'be drawn to this alternative, since, as explained above, the interest of this country appears to them to lie in persuading Iraq to retain her port or ports in the Shatt-el-Arab. Qm Copies of this letter are being sent to the War Office, Air Ministry and India Office. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd) S.H.Phillips.INFORMATION FURNISHBD BY THE HYDROGRAPHEH OF THE NAVY. KOWBITJ Has a few small artificial boat harbours but otherwise is undeveloped* It could* however, be developed, and dredging operations to open the Shweikh to the north—east and thus to the open sea might not be very costly* If this were practicable, wharves could be built on the south side of the Shweikh and ships of about 22 feet draught could be berthed at all states of the tide. This part of the harbour has good holding ground and reasonable protection from the Shamal (strong north-west wind). It also appears possible to build a breakwater in a north-easterly direction from Al Akaz to Fasht alHadaibah. FAQ: The width of the navigable channel here is about 2,000 feet and it is quite possible that, with a little dredging, wharves with depths of 20-22 feet alongside could be built, whilst just above Fao there is a pool where deeper draught ships could lie. The Inner Bar reach, below Fao, is dredged to 21 feet so that 26-27 feet would be the limiting safe draught for ships to enter, even at high water springs. KHOR 3HETANA: (Latitude 30 o 01 f N•Longitude 48 o 02 , B.) would appear to provide a suitable alternative port to Fao in Iraqi * territory. Little, if any, dredging would appear to be necessary to give facilities equal to those at Fao, and there is deep water in a sheltered position both north and south of Warbah island.sH- be entertained which could 3a ad to an increase in Kowei t of Xraqi influence or in any way undermine its position ae an Arab State in special treaty relations with us and under our influence and control* fhe issue of the above has been authorised# V C coUi tS X .)By Air Mail. p.z.itiW «_y BUSHIRE RESIDFNCY. Wo..- ^7—- o a fe..*0/^ CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS /7 INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, /2-. Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to S k A ^fC(r^~tAA' by Mail. The Foreign The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.365^ 5? IKDIA OFFICE, 'FHI TEH ALL, S.W.I Z.4484/58. 8tlri July , 1938 . Sir, / / / 2d 24th 1 - / sd 23rd le. I am directed 'by the Secretary of State for India to refer to foreign Office letter of the 2nd May, / Uo.E.2094/2094/93, 'and to forward, for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, a copy of ^ Pq &gt; / a demi-off icia.1 letter fr cm the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and a copy of an express letter 7 from the Government of india, communicating their views upon the suggestion that the Iraqi railway system might be extended through Koweit territory and that a port, serving as the terminus of the railway, might be constructed in Koweit Bay under Iraqi control. I am to state that Lord Zetland, after careful consideration of the views of the Political Resident and of the Government of India, fully shares the objections felt by the latter to this suggestion. His Lordship would view with grave concern the danger of the extension of Iraqi influence to the detriment of the position of His Majesty's Government in Koweit which, he fears, would be likely to attend railway and harbour development of the nature suggested. He therefore concurs in Lord Halifax's proposal to authorise His Majesty's Ambassador to do his utmost to discourage the Iraqi Minister for Foreign Affairs from * pursuing his proposals and suggests that Sir M.Peterson should/ e Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.■7 @ 2. should inform him, if necessary, that His Majesty's Government could not agree to them. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Admiralty, the War Office and the Air Ministry. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant , fSgd.) J. P. GIBSOND.O. Ho.C/463 i'ifS-J. Office of the Political Hesid In the Persian Qulf» Gampf Bahrain. 31st July 1*38. Could you please refer to my Jixpress Letter Ko. C/359, dated the Slst June 1938! on the subject of a certain Nasr bin Ali ae-Subah, whoa the Iraqis wanted to conscript. 2, i too* these thiiig» take tiae but I would be grateful if you could let me know how the matter stands. Nasr himself is still sheltering in Kuwait and, as pointed out in paragraph 6 of de Saury's letter of 8th June, is afraid that his relations and property in Iraq may suffer. Excellency Sir Maurice Peterson, K.C.M.a., His Majesty's Ambassador, all Cefy SW' &amp; Tt.ft.k Mo• Cjk bk. % i 1 / r/ 1&gt; By Air Mail. p. z .i^yi9M bushir ': residency vo $ie. ~ Date COuF.JI^TJAIL RECORDS A r« INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, i 0 1938 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. &lt;1 { A copy has been sent to A by Mail. IVJ. •'-Sear r Eh6^EQ£6ign^Seei 3 #toyT Q^ES$nm@B4 oLIaadia, The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.364975 /1938 A«M«Fom 541# Air Ministry Reference 3*46l02/S#6. i Air Ministry, Adastral House# Kingsway, W*C*2» 12th July, 1938. Proposed extension of Iraqi railway system through Koweiti territory to the coast in Koweit Bay and the construction of a port there under Iraqi control# Sir, I am commanded 'by the Air Council to transmit, for your infomation, the attached copy of a letter which has been addressed to the Foreign Office on the above subject. I am, etc. (Sd) Donald Banks. v ider Secretary of State, India Office, S.W.IL( 5/1938 Air Ministry, u ^ Adastral House, 41# Kingaway, \7*0«8 3KGRET. 12th J\ily, 1938. 5108/8*6. Sir, ^ With reference to Foreign Office letter No» 2094/2094/93 of the 2nd May, 1938, on the subject of the proposed extension of the Iracii railway system through Koweiti territory to the coast in Koweit Bay and the construction of a port there under Iraq.! control, I am commanded 'by the Air Council to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that they are in general agreemer^ ^ith the Amy Gouncil's view, as stated in their letter 0178/1087/(M.0,1) of the 14th May, that any extension of Iraqi influence in Koweit should he discouraged. 2* Moreover, the Council feel that the Iraqi proposal for the extension of the Baghdad-Basra Railway to Koweit is not unconnected with the substance of Sir —- f-%- M* Peterson 1 s despatch. No# 162 of April 19th, reporting certain Iraqi tendencies towards disputing the independent status of Koweit. That the Iraqi Authorities may be seeking for some means of claiming sovereignty over Koweit is disquieting, and reinforces the Council in their view that the Iraqi proposals for extending their railway to Koweit should be discouraged. In view, however, of the great increase in the strategic importance of our lines of communication through the head of the Persian Gulf, the Council suggest that it would be politic to frame the reply to the Iraq Government in such a way as to leave an opening for possible negotiations in the future. 3* I am to add that from a purely military point of view, the Council consider that aport at Koweit, * 'k^ 00 Basra, would possess certain attractions, and der-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, Whitehall, S.W.I@ 8. might v¥ell prove to 'be a valuable complement to plans for the reinforcement of Bgypt via Iraq and Palestine. If hov/ever there are to 'be any port developments in this locality in the future* it would he desirable that the port and the railhead should remain under the control, nominally of the Shaikh* and actually of his British advisers. In particular the possibility of Koweit eventually 'becoming an oil producing centre may lead to improvements in port facilities for commercial purposes, and in such an eventuality it would he most desirable for the strategic requirements to he borne in mind. 4* Copies of this letter are being sent to the Admiralty, War Office and India Office. I am, etc. (Sd) Charles Evans#■ ivjn 6S (5/24/38) rREC'D^NCY. Dcitc ^3 ^ 3^. COiVrlDE^TlAL RECORDS BRITISH EMBASSY, f bZ- BAGDAD. 10th August, 1938• QegcJz. t Reference Powle's letter J,0. No. C/463 of July 31st to Peterson. I ara doing iny best to extract from the Iraqi Government a reply to a Note which the Ambassador sent to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs on June 29th about Nasir bin Ali al Sabah, but it will be a long time, I fear, before this question is finally settled. His claim that he is not an Iraqi seems to be open to doubt and his established Koweiti nationality does not necessarily exclude the possibility that he is also an Iraqi according to Iraqi law. Such instances of dual nationality are quite common. If the Shaikh wants quick results, I suggest that he might consider paying the I.D. 50 which would buy for Nasir exemption from all but three months service (Article 6 of the Iraqi National Defence Law No. 40 of 1938). vU JTMA.N, ESQ., I.C.S ^^f iQf'i;orr' n . { E cg.:?;DENT;..L r.2CD;x3 * ... Political Agency, Confidential / . ^ __ 0 \ o M \ ^ Kuwfii't# D.O.NO.C-** o \ W ^ J Dated the 7th August, 1838 '&gt; s ^ j}, &lt;3 you please refer to your Printed letter N o .C/464 Of 31st July, 1938, 2^ In m y absence Nasir bin Ali as-Subah received a letter from his brother saying that he was assured by the Iraqi authorities that the only way to clear up matters was for him to return to Iraq and they would go into the matter of his nationality. He said that he would then be allowed to return to Kuwait# 3 # He therefore left for Iraq on the 20th July# ghtman IsQuire, I»C«Se, fficiating Political Resident, at Bahrein# 3 c66 .462. FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.I. 4145/2094/93) 15th August, 1938. ENCLOSUrSE IN OFFICi Si 7 AUG 1958 Sir, X J v - 0* -i In my despatch No.232 of 3rd May I sent Sir Maurice Peterson copies of letters from my department to the India / Office, Admiralty, War Office and Air Ministry regarding the enquiry made by the Iraqi Minister of Foreign Affairs as to the attitude of His Majesty's Government towards an expansion of the Iraqi railway system through Koweiti territory to the coast in Koweit Bay. I now transmit to you copies of the letters which have been received from these Departments in reply. You will see that in the letter from the India / I / Office there are enclosed copies of a semi-official letter on the subject from the Political Resident in the Persian L* Gulf to the Secretary for the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, and of an express letter from the External Affairs Department to the India Office. 2. It is clear from these replies that Taufiq Suwaidi 1 s proposal is, in its present form, quite unacceptable, although the creation of a port and railway at Koweit would not be without advantage from the military point of view, if satisfactory arrangements could be made for their control. In the circumstances I consider that your best course, if it is necessary to refer to the matter further, would be to confine yourself strictly to the proposal in its present form and to say that His Majesty's Government are not favourably disposed to a scheme on the lines suggested, since they do not see how it could function without infringing the rights of the Sheikh. You could then add, as suggested by the •.. E. Houstoun-Boswall, Esq., M.G. , etc,, etc., etc., Bagdad^f- the Admiralty in their letter, that in estimating the prospects of Persian interference with Iraqi trade on the Shatt al Arah, the Iraqi Government should not overlook the advantages which they derive from the interest of His Majesty's Government in the maintenance of free communications in the Shatt. 3. You should, however, endeavour to avoid having to reply to His Excellency at all and should leave it to the Iraqi Government to reopen the question. Since the enquiries of the Minister of Foreign Affairs appear to have 'been caused by the excitement which followed the passing of the legislation necessary to ratify the Frontier Agreement between Iraq and Persia, and with the passage of time this interest in what is, at most, a somewhat remote problem for Iraq, may now have died down, it is possible that the enquiries will not be renewed. I am, v /ith great truth. Sir, Your obedient servant, (For the Secretary of State)INDIA OFFICE, EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). POLITICAL D epartment. (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic j expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State for India ( Goverament of India&gt; External Affairs Department, To ( repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf f ( Political Anent, Koweit. Dated 2nd Septemberi ' iriao Reference your express letter of the 23rd June, iTo. P. 297-j}]/38. Suggested^ extension of Iraq Hailway to a port in Koweit. I should 'be glad to learn very urgently whether you and the Policical Resident have any further views to express i the light of the enclosed copy of a demi-official letter from 26th August.) the Foreign Oj^ficep with particular reference to the suggestions made in paragraph 13 thereof. No. P.2 •6034/58 Confidential. The issue of the ahove has been duly authorised. ^Sgd.) J. P. Q1B54/33 POHEIGi; OFFICEp S.W.I, i/2094/93) 26th August; 1938 g ntia l. i, Dear Peel&lt;, With Foreign Office letter E 4145/2094/93^^ the 16th August ? we have recently sent you a coiDy of a despatch to His Majesty*s Charge d'Affaires at Bagdad ahout the I proposals of the Iraci Government for a port under Iraqi control at Koweit? in which we tell him (as the result of interdepartmental discussion) that the Iraqi proposals are quite unacceptable in their present form and instruct him to say nothing more to the Iraqi Government on the subject3 in the hope that they will let it drop. 2. That despatch had scarcely left the Foreign Office when I received a visit from Colonel Sir John Ward5 (who is now not only the Director of the Basra port administration^ hut also the Director-General of the Iraqi Railways), who tells me that he has heard privately from Bagdad that one of the main questions which Tawfiq Guwaidy^ the Iraqi | Minister for Foreign Affairs 9 will raise when he comes to London early in October villi be this very question of a port at Koweit. The Minister will have with him Edmonds ? of the Consular service ? the principal British adviser to the Iraqi Governmentp but Ward has also been warned to remain in England for the visit. 3. The gist of what Ward had to say was this; His Iraqi employers 9 who are still obsessed; however unreasonably ? with fear of Persia ? are exceedingly anxious to secure an alternative outlet to the Shatt-el-Arab, and for this reason have turned their.eyes towards Koweit. Whether or not we are willing to let them have the use of a port at Koweit is a point on/ 1 Esq.j M.C ♦^ D @ 2. on which he has no information^ although he realises perfectly well that we are not likely to let them have anything in the nature of an ^ imperium in imperio r '« If? however5 we would like his help in riding them off the idea of Kov/eit ? he could, he thinks, divert their eyes to the Khor Ahdullah (i.e. the / Khor Shetana mentioned in Admiralty letter M»02976/38 of the 10th June). He, like the Hydrographer of the Navy, is of the opinion that it would 'be eas3^ to provide a good anchorage in this inlet, especially in that part lying to the north of Warbah Island. In fact, the expense would prolDahly 'be far less than the expense of developing Koweit, since, unlike Koweit, there is deep water right up to the shore. Finally the question of rail connexion would he unlikely to present any great difficulty. (A drawback from- the Iraqi point of view would probably be that Warbah Island, belongs to Koweit. If Iraq could secure this island by making territorial concessions to Koweit elsewhere, and so become the owner of the whole channel, she might have a really fine anchorage of her own. That, however, is looking ahead). 4. Furthermore, Ward is of the opinion, if I understood him rightly, that the capacity of the Shatt-el-Arab is reaching saturation point. Things will be eased a bit if he can dredge the channel to thirty feet, as he hopes to do when he gets the full quota of six dredgers which he has been aiming at for many years past, and which he hopes to do, notwith standing the pressure which is always being brought to bear on him to reduce the shipping dues, before much longer. But even allowing for this, some additional outlet may soon be necessary. The Anglo-Iranian Oil Company for instance are being forced inevitably towards the development of Bandar Shahpur, notwithstanding the additional loading facilities which/which they are ppoviding in 'the Sha'tt—el—Apab^ in 01 dei? oo deal with the increased outpnt xpoiti the new Pepsian fields which ai e now heing hrought into production. If; in addition the li^aq.i Petroleum Company were to find oil in the Basra district (for which they have now obtained the concession) or if fox 1 any reason e.g. danger to the Haifa pipe-line 9 it were decided to huild a pipe—line from the ICirkul-c or Khanioin oilfields to the Persian Gulfp the only outlet for such oil as could not he shipped from Fao would he through the Khor Abdullah or Koweit• 5. Ward would he glad of some indication of the sort of policy which we ourselves would like to see the Iraqi Government follow. This naturally does not mean that he can make them carry out our wishes whatever these may 'be ? hut he will, I knowp try to steer clear of anything which we regarded as seriously detrimental to our interests. 6. In these circumstances &lt;, it seems to me that the questiens which we have to ask our selve s are (a) whether we can? if we need to 9 prevent the development of either Koweit or the Khor Abdullah: (b) whether ? if we must accept such development P we would sooner see an Iraqi port developed at the Khor Abdullah, or see the port of Koweit ? developed either by our own efforts or those of Iraq, in some way which would allow Iraq the benefit of its use. 7. I do not think it is necessary to assume from the outset that the Iraqis could not use the port of Koweit unless they were given some degree of control over the administration of the port. That is what they have asked for as an opening gambit, but it is possible to conceive a suitation in which they might be willing at their own expense to build a railway from Zubair to Koweit (Ward is going to have a quiet, look at the country, but thinks that/7^ 4. thatj, apart from occasional flooding? there are no o'bstacles) ? and to improve the har'bo'ur facilities at Kov/e i 1 9 in retum (if they could get noting better) for a free customs zone; which would not need to 'be very large 5 and the right to use the port and railway free of charge? or on a services provided' 'basis., for a number 01 years. 8« In this connezion I think the Government of India are a little pessimistic. In their express letter ITo. F.297-11/38 of the 23rd June they say very rightly? in commenting upon Fowle's remarks as to the possible advantages of letting the Iraqis use Koweit? that his arguments ^have no validity unless 'Iraq control could be strictly confined to the technical 'management of a port and railway 15 ? and then proceed u in our ' li opinion such a condition would not be fulfilled? and this •'opinion is reinforced by the conversation reported in His ■% 'Majesty's Ambassador's despatch To. 162 of the 19th April '1938 (in which he reported that the Iraqi Minister for 'Foreign Affairs had suggested that Koweit should by right 'belong to Iraq as part o: r the former Vilayet of Basra)-' It may be that there is bound to be some danger in admitting the Iraqis to Kov/e it in any shape or form. But after all, it is for us to lay down the conditions on which the Iraqis may use Koweit? and if we draw up the conditions with sufficient care? I see no reason why they would obtain any serious degree of influence over the affairs of the Sheikhdom. It is admittedly possible that? if we draw up the conditions as carefully as all that? the Iraqis may lose interest in the Koweiti project? and prefer to build their own port at IChor Abdullah. But assuming for the sake of argument that other things being equq^we would rather see Koweit developed than the Ilhor Abdullah? the possibility of their not proving willing to use Koweit except on/TV 7? on conditions which we should think unsatisfactory does not seem to he a reason for not making them an offer. 9 # As to whether we do or do not want to see Koweit developed? we have already had a certain amount of inter-depart mental discussion and I think it would 'be fair to say that 5 from that discussion? three main points emerge (a) Everyone is agreed that we must do our 'best to keep Koweit as a p ied a terre for ourselves at the head of the Persian Gulf? and that for tils purpose it must remain under British protection and influence and free from the domination or influence of any other country. (b) N o one is anxious to sec anything done which might have the effect of lessening the volume of the shipping dues upon which the navigability of the Shatt-el-Arah ultimately depends? seeing that the Ghatt-el-Arah is a link of vital importance in our Imperial communications. (c) Insofar? however? as it is possible for such a thing to I 'be done compatibly with (a) and (h)? no one would 'be sorry to see the port of Koweit developed? and connected 'by rail with Iraq? in such a way as to provide an alter native channel of communication to the Shatt-el-Arah on one section of a route which is 'becoming increasingly important? at any rate potentially? not only for the despatch of reinforcements to the East? hut also for the despatch of reinforcements to the Mediterranean sea-board iO* i'o these three considerations I would add two more; (d) We cannot in the long run rely upon the use in full s ecu rity of the route through Iraq? unless the Iraqi Government remain not only our allies? hut our willing allies? and we must therefore do our best to meet their natural aspirations in matters to which they at any rate attach/(i)/ 6# attach importance and must? where we are inevitalDly forced to obstruct these aspirations&gt; do our 'best to provide them with an alternative form of satisfaction, (e) whatever arguments we may use to show that the Iraqi fears of Persia are groundless^ or ? even if not entirely groundless^ at any rate unnecessary so long as the alliance subsists, the Iraqis are hound to remember that sooner or later the day may come when they will have to stand on their own feet and may not unnaturally wish to take precautions against that day. 11. It is in the light of all these considerations that — —— the problem should, I suggest, 'be approached. What Ward had to say can to a great extent onl3^ he appreciated in the light of technical knowledge and it is difficult for anyone in the Foreign Office to know to what extent it need affect any of the views already expressed 'by the other departments concerned. Similarly, the Foreign Office is in no position to Judge ?/hether, if faced with the inevitable necessity of seeing an Iraqi port developed outside the Shatt-el-Arah, we ought to choose Koweit or the Khor Abdullah. But the fact that the Iraqi Government are apparently much more in earnest than we had hoped at first does, we feel, make it necessary to reconsider carefully the line which we are to take in discussing the question v /ith them. 12. We are therefore in favour of the whole question being considered further before Taufiq Suwaidi 1 s arrival early in Octoberl and I personally think it would be a good thing if we were to have a meeting - perhaps a Middle East (Official) meeting - before then. 13. I do not wish to anticipate too far the discussion at the meeting; but the sort of line we would like to see taken would be as follows:-1&gt; (1) Y/e should tell Ward that if the Iraqis pursue the ^ idea of a port outside the Shatt-el-Arah? for whatever reason ? we would sooner they developed Koweit than the Khor Abdullah (or vice versa ? as the case may he). (2) If the Iraqi Minister for Foreign Affairs raises the point we should tell him (if it remains the considered opinion of the other departments that we do not want an Iraqi port outside the Shatt-el-Arah if we can help it) s (i) that we do not think the Iraqis really need, such a port - the alliance? expenses etc. - hut that if they are really set on it we would not for a moment wish to oppose them and either (ii)(a) that although we cannot agree to anything which would infringe the political or administrative rights of Koweit, we would not he averse? for our part? to discuss an arrangement wherehy the Iraqis could have a free zone at Koweit? on the analogy of many similar arrangements elsewhere? the necessary railway and harbour facilities 'being provided either hy them at their ov/n expense or hy us and recovered from them through dues etc. in the ordinary course of business. or (ii)(h) that we regret we cannot? however? admit any foreign State to prcvileges of the kind for which they have asked in Koweit and therefore think they might consider the possibilities of the Khor Abdullah which we believe are very hopeful. A decision of some sort is necessary? because although the line already given to His Majesty^ Charge d ! Affaires to use in the event of the Iraqis themselves returning to the charge in Bagdad (that His Majesty* s Government do not see how the plan put forward could function without infringing the rights of the Sheikh of Koweit) is all right as far as it goes? it will/8. frill not 'be sufficient if the Tragi Minister for Foreign Affairs presses the question seriously here and says, in reply to any such statement 'Well let's consider how it can 'be made compatible with his rights'. L5. Will you let me know as soon as possible if you agree that a meeting should 'be held, without prejudice to any views you may wish to express at that meeting? 16. I am sending similar letters to Jarrett, Admiralty? doryton. Air Ministry and Mallahy? War Office? and copies to WebTb at the Committee of Imperial Defence and to Starling at the Petroleum Department Yours ever? (Sd) Lacy Baggallay.V 53/87 Telegram From political Agent, Kuwait. jo Political Resident, Busliire at Karaciii. KO.282. Dated 7th received Stii September, 1^38. Reference India Office letter of 2nd September P # 2,6034/38• ICy views will follow air mail. - POLITICAL. Telegram q. Fr as 'Political Resident, Bushire at Karachi. To Political Agent, Kuwait# jro,T/23CU Dated tne 8tli September 1938o / Your telegram jmo # 282 of 7tn September. Please telegrapn summary of your views immediat ely« - Hesidento. liT® L»9 ? t&gt;3/87 Tel egram q. jvom Political Agent, Kuwait, To political Resident, Busnire at Karacni. No. 287. Dated 9tli received lOtn September, 1938, . ...ft -f) 1 Your telegram 230/T of btn aepfcemDer# As Iraqis are inveterate intriguers only possible safe basis is last course given in paragrapn Oc 13, 2 (2 (14) Ue» expenses paid by us and recovered from tnem in course of business# 2 # In tills connection remeiaber (a) Ibn Saud may wish to use port also, (b) Natural development of new strategic road westward when Saudi bloclcade is raised* I think Iraqis anticipate above and consequently scneme* 3 # Best course is given in paragraph 13, 2 (2 (b)) but we could fall back if necessary on course mentioned in paragraph 1 above* 4« Shaikh nas in tne past spo-fcen of intention developing of local people port witn Britisn assistance and would welcome proposal on tnese lines, if British zone were available also to Ibn Saud, and rest of port to Kuwait* - POLITICAL,GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. Q§y eotrPlD'SimAL. Department. I EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). T.B.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a- means of communication mart expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a respotuibU officer of the Deparlmenl.] 0 f Q oe0 f ttie political Resident ^ m-zo in the Persian Gulf, ». c /636 of 1938, Camp, Karachi. J0 jferiaS' iOth September, L 38. rem - The Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 0 • His Majesty's Secretary of state for India, JiOBden. epeated The Secretary to the GoTernment of India, g' r - External Affairs Department, Simla. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 1 Your Express letter Ho»P.Z.6034/38 t dated tiie 2nd September 1938, regarding tne suggested extension of Iraq Railway to a port Ln Kuwait. V^n !, xt is apparent from previous correspondence ti£t Sir Trencnard B yS S fowle saw considerable adTantages in developing a port in Kuwait md connecting it by rail to Basrah provided that it could be issured that such development would not involTe the creation of an :raqi imperium in the Kuwait imperio, or an undue extension of Iraqi influence in the Shaikhdonu With this riew I renture to ixpress entire agreement* u The main objections hitherto taken to such a scneme have reen (a) the danger to the traffic of the Shatt al Arab aid hence to its continued existence as a navigable river as far as Basra, (Signature) ( ^) / 44. TP—1048 S&amp; P—(M-2042)—17-12-37—20,000. (Designation)-2- (b) the danger of the eoctension of Iraqi influence in Kuwait# In regard to (&amp;)• The consideratione set out In paragraph 4 of Foreign Office demi-official letter iio.E .4994/ 2094/95 of the 26th August 1938 (enoloaed with your isxprecs letter under reference) appear to dispel acor serious misglTings (b) If the course mentioned at the end of paragraph IS 2 (ii)(a) (faoilities provided by us and recovered in the ordinary course of business) were possible it would obviate all danger, and would be welcomed by the Shaikh, there might indeed be some Kuwait capital for investment in such a scheme. Even however excluding this optimum course, I still think that if the Iraqis are in fact determined to see an alternative port established outside the shatt, then from every point of view - strategic, economic and political, there are advantages in that port being established at Kuwait rather t.hari in the Khor Abdul laiu ( A ) Strategic# It would seem to be axiomatic tnat tnc strategic value of Kuwait would be greatly enhanced by harbour and rail development, and tnis opinion is confirmed by the Air b / Ministry lettef iao# S#45102/3# 6 f dated the 12th July 193B, on this subj ect # (B) Kconomic. It is equally axiomatic tnat tne develop ment of a port at Kuwait must have economic advantages for Kuwait state, even though the major portion of tne traffic were bonded for Iraq. It might even be anticipated that such development would galvanise the Kuwait Oil Company into a greater show of activity; there might,(with tne leising of the Saudi blockade), be an extension of trade with tiaudi Arabia (even /(eren though a port be developed at Has Tanura); and, aa a smaller matter, it might well possess some bargaining Talus of for tlie purpose A ne Date Garden cases* A particularly important point emerges here, partly economical and partly political. It is, 1 think, true tnat few if a^y thinking Ku.mitis even at present would willingly accept Iraq suzerainty, but the greater tne stake tne greatei the reluctance to lose it and anything tending to increase Kuwait prosperity should tend equally to stiffen resistance to any attempt at Iraqi domination. (It is immaterial tnat such prosperity might derive largely fran tne investment of Iraqi capital). (0) golitio&amp;l, Kuwait (i.e.British) terminal control of an important route to Iraq has obvious political advantages. It i8 t howeTer, clearly essential that it must be exclusire Kuwait (or British) control. If tiie Iraqis axe sufficiently a lamed by their apprehensions of Iranian closure of the Shatt it might even be possible to extract, as a preliminary to further negotiations, a total renunciation of any claims they may have felt disposed to advance to suzerainty over Kuwait. The further advance of the Kuwait project might then be secured by the formation of a Company, howsoever financed, guaranteed certain privileges including a free customs zone, but amenable to the executive and legislative authority of Kuwait. Details in regard to its direction would be for later consideration. Admittedly such a proposal cannot, from the Iraq point of view, nave the attraction which their own proposal possesses, but it does, alter all, secure for Iraq trade an alternative outlet to the sea which is /&gt;4- ia their ostensible object; and it is not, I suggest, inoompatable with the consideratio^s set out in paragraphs 9 and 10 erf the foreign Off ice letter referred to above, .'here Iraq OoTemment penetration might indeed be dangerous to the future of Kuwait, a public Company, even though it be largely finanoed by Iraq,could be controlled and P given due care, need introduce no greater danger tiian already ex let 8 in the propinquity of Basrah to Kuwait. sd. K. teigiitman. Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. At tea ted . for Sed^etary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.&amp; 23 Telegram From To repeated to Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla• H.M 1 s Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, iiushire, at Bahrain• Mo.1486 Dated and received 20tli September 1938. Your Sxpress iietter Ho#P.S.6034/38 of 2nd September• iix.tension of Iraqi ivail- -way Port in Kuwait. /1 . /V' /We are impressed with arguments / put forward by Foreign Office and by Weightman in / his Express Letter No.G/636 of 10th September in favour of scheme and agree tlat question should be reconsidered by Middle i^ast Committee. We also agree to your taking line suggested in paragraph 13 of Baggallay's letter of 26th August as explained ^ in (1) and (2)(i) and (ii)(a) provided you are satisfied that independence of Kwait can be fully safemiarded in any arrangement made with Iraq Gov- -ernment. Foreign ^ ^ ^ HaA w VAJ WWJLM! ■p.L . ^5.' dl- Xl.By Air Mail. p.z. U Wl 19 3^ ^1 i (^.. .^. j ~CO^rlO£NTlAl- B £CQBDS_ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, ^rt|o^ Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - 1 Sea 4963 2000 7.36 The Foreign Soorotary, Qovcrnmont of India. The Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf. rA .THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY f S GOVERNMENT. EASTERN (Iraq) SeptemlDer 19, 1958 , CONFIDENTIAL * Section U ^E 5477/2194 /937 Copy No. 97 Mr# Houstoun-Boswall to Viscount Halifax .-(Received September 19) - (No.438.) Bagdad, September 7, 1938. My Lord, I have the honour to report that when I saw the Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs on the 6th Septeraber he sai£i that he had 'been anxious to speak to me about Koweit, with special reference to the desire of the Iraqi Government to establish a port there, and he proceeded to elaborate the familiar argiimente about the vulnerabi 1 ity of Iraqi interests in the , ,» Shatt-e 1-Arab. It was thus fortunate that I had received^ / 1 ' jToup XordiEIp's despatch No.468 of the 15th August, which enabled me to inform the Minister that His Majesty's Government had given very close study to the proposal as presented to Mr. Morgan, and on another occasion to His Majesty's Ambassador, by the Minister for Foreign Affairs last March, but that the scheme on the lines suggested did not commend itself to them because it was felt that the rights o f^ the sheikh might be inf r in g ed the re by r' 1 al the lra(|i Government could zest assured that free communications in the Shatt would be maintained, as 1he interests of Iraq and of her allies were there identical. The Minister was clearly disappointed. He said that the Cabinet had considered the question several times lately, and that, indeed, the Minister for Foreign Affairs proposed to Iske up the question with your Lordship this month in London, as stated in my confidential^- letter to Mr. Baxter of the 23rd August, and in the enclosure to my despatch No.410 of the 29th August, He went on to say that tfeere had bg gn some suggestion of linking this questi on wi th that of the sheikh's properties in Iraq, but I think I was successful in persuading him that any such move would, to say the least of it, be very bad tactie s (the Director-General for Foreign Affairs also mentioned this to me last week and showed that he entirely shared my view). Saiyid Abbas Mahdi also said that his Government would proceed to elaborate some other scheme to secure an outlet to the sea through Koweit, for they were genuinely perturbed at the possibility of Persian interference with Iraqi trade on the Shatt-al-Arab and felt very strongly that it was their duty to do everything possible to obviate any such risk. He would write to me on the subject after consulting his colleagues, who would no doubt send further instructions to Saiyid Taufiq-al-Suwaidi. 2. I am sending copies of this despatch to His Majestv's ^ e ^ I * an an d to his Excellency the Governor-General 01 India, \ I have, etc. (Sgd.) W.E. Houstoun-Boswall,P.Z.6632/1938. FOREIGN OPFIOS, S.W. 1. B 5U77/209i+/93- 2Uth September, 1938- sir. With reference to Foreign Office letter E 5i7l/209U/9.5 of the 16th September I am directed 'by Viscount Halifax to transmit to you herewith forty copies of a despatch from His Majesty's Charge d'Affaires at Bagdad, from which it will 'be seen that the Iraqi Government have again raised with him the question of Iraq's access to the sea. 2. I am to request that this paper may be included among the correspondence to be circulated to the departments which will be represented at the forthcoming meeting of the Middle East (Official) Sub-Gommittee on the subject. 3« Copies of this letter are being sent to the Treasury, Colonial Office, India Office, Admiralty, far Office, Air Ministry and Petroleum Department. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd.) G. Baxter. cretary, ommittee of Imperial Defence.By Air Mail. RZ. IqT S^ / iQjfrf i o BUSHIRE RESIDENCY. au (- Date.....!. ST) COriFIDENTiAL RECORDS INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 7 OCT 1938 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - Sea Sic Fuiclgn Secretary, UovurmmmL ul Indi^ The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.36II®IA OPFICJ, WHITSHALL, 3. W. 1. Z.6526/38. 26th September, 193S. ■KDENTIAL. i ' : My dear Baggallay? % Would you please refer to your letter of the 26th August (E hS9k/20k-/93) regarding the proposed extension of the Iraqi raiIway systeai to a ^ort in Koweit territory. We have consulted the officiating .colitical Resident and the Government of India upon your letter and I now enclose copies of their replies. ¥e have reconsidered the matter in the light of your letter and of the views of the local authorities ? and? although we still dislike in principle any idea of a focus for Iraqi influence being established in Koweit territory? we are prepared to agree to the course suggested in jaragraph 13 of your letter, priy* excluding the alternative in (2) r tii , 4)(h) j but on the understanding of course that in any arrangement that may eventually be discussed the fullest possible precautions are taken to safeguard the political integrity of Koweit. The re/ igallay, Esq.;, gn Office. '*/cr 11 There are two points in Weightinan*s letter on which we should like to comment, (we doubt the advantage of trying to extract any bargaining value from our attitude on the port question in order to assist the settlement of the Date Gardens question. ( 1: And we are definitely opposed to , his suggestion that as a preliminary to further negotiations we might secure a total renunciation of any claims on the part of Iraq to suzerainty over Koweit, since we could not admit that any such claims had the slightest foundation in reality. I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Webb for circulation to the Departments represented on the Middle East Committee. Yours everj ifiSgd.) J p. GIBSON /'gu. By Air Mail. p.z. ^ lojf Ri ifiHSRE RESIDENCY No '■*?$. Date. ■ • • CONFiDENTlAL RECORDS INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 7 OCT 1938 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - ^ Sea Tlio FoiTjgn Sccrotary, Qovorpmnnti nf Tnrh'n The Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf. 2000 7.36fcNCLO»OKE IW FOHEION OFFfCfe OOVERINO LETTER OATEOL__I_ mi ms I 6S09 ^ ^ ^ NO DISTRIBUTION* )S09~ Cypher telegram to Mr. Houstoun-Bi 'Swa &amp;S Sl |g da( ) Foreign Office, 29th September, 1988* 6.0 p.m. No. 147. Your despatch No. 438 [of September 7th: Iraqi Government's wish for a new port on the . ersian G-ulf]. Sir J. Y /ard has asked to be given in confidence some indication of His Majesty's Government's views, since it will be useful to him to know whether, if the Iraqi Government pursue the idea of a port outside the Shatt-el-Arab, we would rather that they developed Koweit than the Khor Abdullah, or vice versa . 2 # You may speak to Sir J. Ward in confidence on following lines. Result of interdepartmental discussions shows that neither alternative need be ruled out on political grounds. Purely practical difficulties of building a modern port on Bay of Koweit would, however, be very great. At Koweit itself it would be very expensive to carry out necessary developments, which would include dredging on large scale, and building of a breakwater five miles long. A new port to the North of Koweit Bay would seem even less practicable, since ships must anchor three miles from the shore, and lighterage would be impossible in a strong southerly wind. On the other hand, Khor Abdullah appears from Admiralty charts, which are based on survey of 1911 and will require verifi cation, to be very suitable, with a deep water approach of at least 21 feet, and good anchorage next the shore. From Iraqi point of view, there seems every advantage in first examining Khor Abdullah, which is unquestionably more hopeful than anywhere in Koweit, could be developed at far less expense, and would be far closer to existing Iragi railway system. 3. Reply to Iraqi Minister for Foreign Affairs, if he raises the question, will be based on the foregoing considerations#&lt;S) 1 Knoloeure In Foreign Office Covering letter dated His Majesty's Ambasoedor at Bagdad present his compliments to H.M. 1 ® Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit to him the under~menti &gt;ned documents. British Embassy, 28th October, 1938 Bagdad. paragr 4th Mey, 1938, to Sir Maurice petereon Descripti n of Enoloeure, Heme and Date Subject. Note No.343 dat.d 89th June, 1938, to the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs Note No.13700/2792/100 dated let Octoher, 1938, from the Iraqi Mtnistry of Foreign Affaire. Koweitl nationality and Iraqi Military Law. Note No.634 dated 6th October, 1938, to the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Copies sent to Koweit)56/38 @ KJfCLOSUKE NO 1 IN BA&amp;DAD DESPATCH Ho.491 of 6th October f 1938. ^O. 343 ♦ Note Yerbale # His Majesty's txibm&amp;y present their complimemts to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs end have the honour to invite their attention to the following matter. 2. It has been brought to the notice of the Embassy by the Koweiti authorities that a Koweitl mimed Haeir bin Ali al Sabah, a grandson of Shaikh Muhammad al Sabah of Koweit f has been called upon to perform military service under the Iraqi Nati nal efence Law No,40 of 1938. 3* The Koweiti authorities claim that Nasir bin Ali is not an Iraqi subject and have requested this Embassy to make representations to the Iraqi Governxnt with a view to securing the withdrawal of the order com lunicated to him to Join the Iraqi Army for colour service on June 23rd* 4. In order that tiis matter may be investigated» His Majesty's Embassy request that they may be informed of the reasons for which the Iraqi authorities have decided that Nasir is liable for military service under the law referred to above. In the meantime» they would be grateful if the order referred to above could be held in suspense« His Majesty's Embassy avail themselves of this opportunity to renew the expression of their highest consideration. 1 Embassy, lad. ane, 1938.T ENCLOSURE NO.g IK BAGDAD DESPATCH No#491 of 6.10.38. Ministry of Foreign Affairs, }/2792/lOQ . Bagdad, Ist Ooto'ber f 1938. The Ministry of Foreign Affairs present their complements to Hie Britannic Majesty's Embassy f Bagdad, and, with reference to the Embassy's note Ho.425 dated 10th August, 1938, have al the honour to state that Nasir Ali/Batoah was called up for colour service on the ground th&amp;t he was registered in the census as an Iraqi. On 17th February, 1938, he protested against taxis registration. During enquiries about his nationality it was necessary to consider his father's nationality in order to give a final decision regarding his ■ * , • own. has As it/appeared that All's father resided in Iraq 20 years ago, and in order to give a decision as to whether the father is considered to be an Iraqi under Article 3 of the Iraqi Nati nality Law, and whether the son, who was under age on 6th August, 1924, acquires his father's nationality, the Embassy are requested to be so good as to reply to the /§.&lt; ^ * Ministry's enquiry contained in their note No.13118 dated 2nd December, 1937, and express their views regarding the date of the establishment of the Koweiti nationality. Mo reference is made in the esteemed Kmbassy's^Sote No.lQS dated 80th February, 1938, regarding the date on wh ch the Koweiti nationality was established. The Ministry avail themselves of this opportunity to renew the expression of their highest considerati n and esteem. tannic Majesty's Embassy, agdad.4 38. KHCWSURi; NO. 3 IK BAGDAD DESPATCH Ho.491 of 6,10,38, No. 53^ . Note Verfeale # His Majesty's Snbaosy presents its compliments to the Ministry of foreign Affairs and, with reference to their Note Verb«le Ho. 13700/2792/100 of October 1st, has the honour to inform them that the views of His Majesty # B Government on the question of Koweiti nationality are as follows:- The Bhaikdom of Koweit vme for a considerable period in an anomalous state of semi-dependence on the Ottoman Empire; His Majesty's Government have nevertheless been in treaty relations with the Shaikhs of Koweit since 1841; and Koweit finally be came completely Independent of Turkey and Koweiti nationality finally cam into existence on the same date as Iraq and Iraqi nationality. Hie Ma^eaty'B Etriba ay avails itself of this opportunity to renew the expression of its highest oonsiderstion. Ertbasey, A. Ob r, 1938.3679a m INDIA OFFICE, POLITICAL D epartment. (u)* EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). S' l(N.B. —This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State for India ( Ooverninent of India, External Affairs DeDartment, To I repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, ( and Political Agent, Koweit. Dated sth November, 1938, No. P. Z. 7136/38. I BUS H IRE RESIDENCY, w-- Xf/d/b^ r ft Confidential « Please refer to correspondence resting with Foreign Office telegranTilo Charge d ? Affaires 3 Bagdad., No,14? dated 29th September (copy to India hy sea mail of 6th Octoher ? to Bushire and Koweit by sea mail of 13th Octoberj India Office reference P,Z.6809/38) regarding desire of Iraqi Government for a new port on the Persian Gulf. I should be glad to have your views and those of Political Resident on enclosed copy of letter 9th October,,) from Foreign Office regarding wish of Iraqi closure• ) Minister for Foreign Affairs to discuss privately with Sheikh of Koweit possibility of establishing Iraqi port adjoining Koweit territory in the Khor Abdulla. The issue of the above has been duly authorised. 1. PEiE' Ii-j' ^ ^ , tn* Cm &gt;/1 5b L 'S33 1 FOREIGN OFFICE, &lt;2C94/93. S.W.I. 19th OctcTber, 1938. Sir, With reference to the recent discussion at the Middle East (Official) Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence regarding the desire of the Iraqi Government for an additional commercial outlet to the sea, I am directed hy Viscount Halifax to transmit to you herewith, for the consideration of the Marquess of Zetland, the record of a conversation on this subject at the Foreign Office with the Iraqi Minister of Foreign Affairs. 2, it will be seen that in this conversation Taufiq Suwaidi said that the Iraqi Government would examine the possibilities of Khor Abdullah, but that if they decided to develop a port on that inlet they might require certain concessions from the Sheikh of Koweit, and that they would like to be assured in advance that the Sheikh of Krweit would be prepared to agree to an alteration in the existing frontier, in so far as this might be necessary. It will further be seen that when it was pointed out to His Excellency that if the Iraqi Government wished the Sheikh to cede to them a part of his territory they would have to make an offer to compensate him elsewhere, he urged that he might be allowed to approach the Sheikh in the first place direct, .er-Secretary of State, .dia Office,,direct, and try to induce him to accept some reasonable arrangement. 3. . It will thus 'be necessary to consider what reply should be returned to the Iraqi Foreign Minister on this point, and the first question for consideration is whether, in view of the special relations existing between His Majesty's Government and the Sheikh of Koweit, there is any objection to informing the Sheikh that he is at liberty to discuss informally with Taufiq. Suwaidi this question of establishing an Iraqi port in the Khor Abdullah. It could be made clear to the Sheikh that he must keep His Majesty's Government closely informed of the progress of his conversations and that before any agreement is reached he would be expected to obtain their approval. 4. It appears to Lord Halifax that, provided that it is understood that any private approach to the Sheikh on behalf of the Iraqi Government is made with the knowledge and approval of His Majesty 1 s Government, and that any settlement which the Sheikh might wish to make with the Iraqi Government will have to be confirmed through the official channels, the most hopeful method of reaching an early settlement might be to leave the two parties to strike a bargain between themselvesc Lord Halifax sees no reason to suppose that any compensation which the Iraqi Government might offer, and the bheikh be prepared to accept., would be of a nature to which His Majesty's Government would have to take exception, but if that proved to be the case, it would of course be open to them to refuse to confirm the arrangement. On the other hand, if the Sheikh considered that the inducements offered to him were insufficient,insufficient, or that the Iraqi Government were bringing pressure on him to conclude an unfair 'bargain, he would naturally be able to inform His Majesty's Government accordingly, and request their assistance in the negotiations^ 5. I am accordingly to suggest that the Iraqi Government might be informed that it will in the first place be for them to state exactly what concessions they will require from the Sheikh of Koweit, and that if their requirements appear to be reasonable His Majesty's Government will be prepared to inform the Sheikh that they have no objection to his discussing informally with the Iraqi Minister for Foreign Affairs the question of the compensation which he would be prepared to accept. 6. Lord Halifax assumes that in the meantime nothing will be said to the Sheikh to give him an enhanced idea of the value which such concessions as he may be asked to make would have for the Iraqi Government. 7. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Treasury, Admiralty, War Office, Air Ministry, Mines Department and Committee of Imperial Defence. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,'his document is the property of his britannic majesty's government EASTERN ( I raq ). October 5, 1938. CONFIDENTIAL. S ection 2. ;E 5841/1982/93] Copy No. 115 [A mended C opy.] Record of Conversation with the Iraqi Minister for Foreign Affairs held at the Foreign Office at 6 p.m. on October 4, 1938. Present: Iraqi Minister for Foreign Affairs. Major Edmonds (British adviser to the Iraqi Ministry of the Interior). Mr. Baxter, Foreign Office. Mr. Crosthwaite, Foreign Office. Mr. Baxter enquired whether the Iraqi Foreign Minister wished to begin by discussing in detail the matters which formed the subject of the aide-memoire handed by his Excellency to Mr. Butler at Geneva, or whether there were any other matters arising out of that morning's conversation with the Secretary of State which his Excellency wished to discuss. The Iraqi Foreign Minister said that he would like to discuss in detail the subjects dealt with in his aide-memoire. Aerodrome Guards. As regards the question of aerodrome guards, Taufiq Suwaidi referred to the delay which had taken place in giving effect to article 4 of the annexure to the Anglo-Iraqi Treaty of Alliance. It was true that various proposals had been made since the entry into force of that treaty in 1932, but some of these proposals were not in accordance with the provisions or the intention of the treaty. Discus sions had taken place at Bagdad in 1935, and a certain measure of agreement had been reached, but there were still two outstanding points on which the views of His Majesty's Government had never been received. It was with a view to providing a solution of the whole problem that he bad now suggested that the aerodrome guards should be detached either from the regular Iraqi army (in which case the commanding officer would be a British officer attached to the British military mission) or from the Iraqi police. In either case, the Iraqi military or police forces would be placed under the control of the British Air Officer Commanding, and in addition, if the forces were to be provided by the Iraqi army, there would be a British commanding officer. He thought that a solution on these lines would be entirely in accordance with the treaty. Mr. Baxter drew attention to the provisions of the treaty article, stating that the special guards should be provided '' upon such conditions as may be agreed upon between the high contracting parties,' and that the Iraqi Government would ' secure the enactment of such legislation as might be necessary for the fulfilment of the conditions referred to above.' Various efforts had been made to reach agreement as to the nature of this legislation to be introduced by the Iraqi Government. The last proposals, it would be recalled, had been handed to the Iraqi Government by Sir M. Peterson in May last. It did not appear that the Iraqi Government had yet replied to that communication, and it was there fore only now that His Majesty's Government learnt that these proposals were unacceptable to the Iraqi Government. As regards the proposals now put forward by Taufiq Suwaidi, it was regretted that neither was entirely welcome to the British authorities concerned. The main difficulty was, to speak perfectly frankly, the problem of the control of these aerodrome guards. His Excellency had stated that they would be under the control of the Air Officer Commanding, but in certain respects these guards^ being part of the Iraqi military or police forces, would also be under the direct control of the Iraqi Government. It seemed to the British authorities concerned that this divided control might lead to difficulties and disputes between the British [430 e—2] b2 jfl! and Iraqi authorities, wJucn it would be in the best interests of both the British and Iraqi Governments if possible to avoid. His Majesty's Government, however, realised the difficulties in the way of f reaching an agreed settlement on the lines hitherto followed, and had therefore rl been giving active consideration to an entirely different solution of the problem, ■ which, if it proved practicable, would no doubt be welcome to the Iraqi Govern- 0 ment; that was that His Majesty's Government should waive their right to ask l|^ the Iraqi Government to provide special guards, and that the Royal Air Force '0 should themselves provide for their own ground defence without maintaining the l present levies or any other force composed of Iraqi subjects. Before definite proposals to this effect could be made, however, various practical difficulties would feS have to be examined. During a recent tour of the Middle East undertaken by P? the Under-Secretary of State for Air, a senior officer of the Air Ministry |p accompanied him to discuss this problem with the authorities in Iraq, but P, a unfortunately, owing to the international crisis, they had to be recalled when they had got as far as Palestine. But the British authorities would continue to consider the question as rapidly as possible. Taufiq Suwaidi said that this was an entirely new suggestion, and he could not say how the Iraqi Government would regard it. He would at once telegraph to Bagdad and might possibly receive some indication of the Iraqi Government's views in the course of a day or two. Registration of Land Occupied by the Port of Basra. The Foreign Office representatives regretted that they were not yet in a position to discuss this problem, and that if it proved impossible to give his Excellency a reply before he left London a reply would, in any case, be sent to him at Bagdad at an early date. Taufiq Suwaidi said he was sure that, if the Iraqi Government repaid the outstanding instalment of the port loan, there could be no objection to registering the land in the name of the Iraqi Government. He hoped that it might even be possible for His Majesty's Government to agree to his proposal without insisting hi upon the immediate repayment of the loan. Such a gesture on their part would fa be much appreciated in Iraq. jitati if®! % Koweit. (Tficaj fThe Secretary of State, in the course of his meeting with the Iraqi Foreign y 4 Minister in the morning of the 4th October, had told his Excellency that His L Majesty's Government would find it difficult to admit any Iraqi claim, if the L, Iraqi Government were ever to put forward such a claim, to sovereignty over 1 Koweit; and the Iraqi Foreign Minister had agreed not to insist on discussing tEis point, to which a reference had been made in the aide-memoire which he had ^ communicated as a basis for discussion.) &gt; . Ill Mr. Baxter referred to the reference in Taufiq Suwaidi's aide-memoire to ^ Koweit as a centre for extensive arms traffic and smuggling. He would like to ^ consider, in the first place, the statement that there was an important illegal traffic in arms into Iraq. Hitherto, he believed, His Majesty's Government had not U received any evidence to show that any such smuggling of arms was, in fact, W taking place. In fact, the British authorities in the Persian Gulf seemed to be || fairly sure that no arms were now entering Koweit, at all events by sea. He asked whether the Iraqi Government were able to produce any evidence to show % that smuggling of arms did, in fact, take place through Koweit. Taufiq Suwaidi replied that the Iraqi Government were convinced that arms smuggling from Koweit into Iraq had, in fact, assumed serious proportions, and nj he thought that the Iraqi Government could produce evidence of this. He was, |l| in any case, quite certain that arms were on sale in Koweit in large quantities lit and at very cheap prices, and that there was nothing to prevent anyone who ftsj liked from buying arms freely in the open market and trying to smuggle them h across the Iraqi frontier. , fic, il I iiiisf iitiii® iiM if ?Jfii H ill I sin I®|fl Ik ifos Major Edmonds added that, to his personal knowledge, as a result of his conversations with Iraqi tribesmen, it was quite a frequent occurrence for an Arab to buy a rifle in Koweit for £5 or £6 and to travel with it to Iraq, where® 10* Htkihe would sell it for about twice that amount. The fact was that Koweit had become a recognised market where Arabs, whether would-be smugglers or not, in tlf went to purchase arms. He was quite prepared to believe that the British ^ hadt authorities in the Persian Gulf were right when they said that no arms entered 1 of the Koweit by sea, but it was absolutely certain that somehow or other these arms were he Iraqil available for sale in Koweit. ^ Baxter said that His Majesty's Government would certainly be prepared 0 ?U to give the whole question their earnest attention if the Iraqi Government would, J ^taii i n be good enough to produce all the evidence in their possession, tiefou di| cil |j. At a later stage in the discussion. Major Edmonds suggested that His .st ^ Majesty's Government might be prepared to consider a solution whereby substan ce tial restrictions would be placed on the sale of arms in the Koweiti market. He ;ie s i; thought that in Muscat, before the war, His Majesty's Government had insisted be re I, 1 that all the arms available for sale in that territory should be collected and stored is Woil ^ in one special warehouse under Government supervision, and that the sale of these ' arms should be subjected to some form of Government control. He suggested that some such system in Koweit might be the most effective method of dealing with ^ ami; the situation which had arisen. Mr. Baxter said that this suggestion would receive further consideration. As regards other forms of smuggling, Mr. Baxter wished to point out in the first place that it was really entirely for the Government of a country to see that smuggling into its territory did not take place. The Iraqi Foreign Minister had put forward three suggestions. The first was for a customs union between Iraq m notj and Koweit. This did not seem to His Majesty's Government to be an acceptable issibletfl! solution, since such an arrangement between a large State like Iraq and a small iy case, If State like Koweit might be expected to undermine the independence of the smaller State. Taufiq Suwaidi said that he did not think that there was much foundation for this fear. He said that for many years now the Iraqi authorities had run the t it i |lti Koweiti postal administration. This had not, he thought, made any difference I wittaj to the political position of the sheikhdom, and he did not see why it should make i tkirAny difference if the Iraqi authorities also took over the Koweiti customs administration. Koweit would, of course, be offered a fixed annual sum in lieu of its present customs revenue. He thought that the Koweitis themselves would be very ready to accept such a suggestion. the™ Mr. Baxter said that the Iraqi Foreign Minister's second suggestion, that Lceto the northern frontier line of Koweit should be fixed further south so as to give raqi eg the Iraqi preventive services more space in which to operate, seemed also to be 3 unacceptable. This suggestion would apparently involve the cession to Iraq of g 0I1 | about one-third of Koweit, and it was difficult \o see what compensation could oire# be given to the sheikh elsewhere. I Taujiq Suwaidi said that, if the suggestion of a customs union between , Iraq and Koweit were found to be possible, it would not be necessary further to n eW || consider this alternative. tantife Mr. Baxter proceeded that, as regards the Iraqi Foreign Minister's third enu# solution, he understood that the proposal of combined preventive operations had '218wM already been put forward some months ago. The Sheikh of Koweit had stated on ulfsf® that occasion that he was willing to negotiate with the Iraqi Government when jjtslii he had reached an agreement with the Saudi Government regarding the raising of their blockade. These negotiations had been proceeding fairly satisfactorily of late. \m Taufiq Suwaidi interjected that he did not see what these negotiations between Koweit and Saudi Arabia had to do with Iraq. In reply to the question this. ® whether the Iraqi Government had any special measures in mind in connexion gejil with the proposed anti-smuggling agreement with Koweit, Taufiq Suwaidi seemed jt a# to think that it might be possible to induce the sheikh, who had no armoured' s0gi cars ' ( ^ c ' to contribute to the proposed joint preventive operations, to share the cost of these operations. It was pointed out to him that the sheikh would not be likely to agree to any such proposal. $ [«». 24 &gt;v Mr. Baxter informed his Excellency that His Majesty's Government had, in fact, received an expert report, from which it appeared that the Iraqi authorities might be able to give smuggling from Koweit a decisive blow if they were to take certain additional measures, e.g., control by aeroplanes and armoured cars, together with drastic measures against those organisations or individuals in Iraq who must be assisting in smuggling on such a large scale as had been suggested by his Excellency. Taufiq Suwaidi thought that the Iraqi Government had already taken all such measures as were in their power. There were numbers of armoured cars, troops and police engaged in anti-smuggling measures, and all this was involving the Iraqi Government in serious expenditure. The position apparently was that the Sheikh of Koweit would take no action whatever, because, of course, he had nothing to gain from doing so; on the contrary, he was, if anything, making a large profit, for a large part of the customs levied on goods entering Koweit (which might subsequently be smuggled into Iraq) went into his own pocket. From the Iraqi point of view it was an unbearable situation. Major Edmonds suggested that the difficulty might be overcome if the Koweiti customs tariff were increased to the level of the Iraqi tariff. The main cause of the smuggling was that the Koweiti tariff was so low. He thought that possibly the Sheikh of Koweit was precluded from raising it by his treaties with His l-Hw Majesty's Government. If it was impossible to agree to a customs union between the Sheikh of Koweit and the Iraqi Government, could it not at least be arranged that the two Administrations, even though remaining entirely independent, should impose the same tariff, i.e., the Iraqi tariff ? Taufiq Suwaidi added that in that case the Iraqi Government would no doubt wish to assure themselves that the higher tariff was being applied in Koweit in fact as well as in theory, and also that smuggling into Koweit was not taking place on a large scale. He thought that this difficulty might be overcome if an Iraqi customs official, perhaps one of the British officials attached to the Iraqi customs administration, could be attached to the Koweiti customs administration. Mr. Baxter undertook that this suggestion would be examined further. Iraqi Government's Wish for a new Port on the Persian Gulf. Mr. Baxter drew attention to the fear expressed by the Iraqi Foreign Minister lest there should be serious interference by Persia with navigation on the Shatt- el-Arab. He enquired the nature of the Iraqi Government's fears on this point. Surely they did not expect some hostile act on the part of Persia, at all events in peace-time ? Taufiq Suwaidi replied with references to the violent tendencies of Persian policy as directed by the present Shah. He referred to the difficulties that had already arisen with Persia regarding the Shatt-el-Arab, and to the use of that waterway by Persian warships. Mr. Baxter suggested that in time of peace it was improbable that Persian warships would commit hostile acts against Iraqi shipping using the waterway between Basra and the sea. Such an act of aggression seemed very unlikely, at least so long as the Anglo-Iraqi Alliance was maintained. In time of war, also, the Persian Government seemed to be unlikely to adopt a violently hostile attitude towards the British and Iraqi Governments, since they would be anxious to maintain the revenues resulting from their sales to us of Persian oil. On the other hand. His Majesty's Government fully appreciated the desire of the Iraqi Government to secure an additional commercial outlet on the sea. They had no desire at all to stand in the way of such a project, and they had carefully gone into the Iraqi Government's wishes. The information at the disposal of the British authorities concerned showed that Koweit itself was not suitable for development as a modern port, and such development would be very expensive; it would involve dredging on a large scale, and the construction of a long breakwater, in addition to the provision of ordinary harbour works. Any other place in Koweit Bay would be even less suitable, since at present ships could not anchor nearer than 3 miles from the shore, and when the south-east wind blew lighterage would be impossible. On the other hand, Khor Abdullah appeared froni the charts (which would, however, require confirmation, since they were based on a10^ IC^ ®®(irsurvey made so long ago as 1911), to be very well suited to development as a ^modern port. There seemed to be a deep water approach of at least 21 feet the uMsnwhole way, and a deep water anchorage next the shore. Khor Abdullah thus ^ siseemed to be much the best site from the point of view of the Iraqi Government. Its development would almost certainly be less expensive, and it would be nearer ady hi ^ ie I ra( li railway system. The Iraqi Government would, therefore, do well, in the r J st P^ ace ' examine the possibility of meeting their requirements by the con- Wagi) J struction of a port at Khor Abdullah. Taujiq Suwaidi replied that the Iraqi Government would certainly examine ioiirse [.the possibilities of Khor Abdullah,~But if they decided to develop a port on that ng^iinlet they might require certain concessions from the Sheikh of Koweit, and they )eriiig|,would like to be assured in advance, before embarking upon any expenditure, &amp;c., 5 own r, that the Sheikh of Koweit would be prepared to agree to an alteration in the existing frontier , in so far as this might be necessary. Wei Mr. Baxter suggested that first it would be necessary for the Iraqi Govern- mair. to decide exactly what they would have to ask from the Sheikh of Koweit. they wished the sheikh to cede to them a part of his territory, the small ties^island of Warbah and the navigable channel between that island and the open sea, unioii[ifthey would have to make an offer to compensate him elsewhere. For this purpose itboffljit be desirable that the Iraqi Government's offer should be made as 3iideBti attract ^ ve . as P 0 ? s ibl e to the sheikh; it would be well that the compensation offered should quite evidently exceed in value the territory which they were asking the sheikh to cede. 6Dt f|[ if*) ill , Taufiq Suwaidi asked if he might get into direct touch with the Sheikh of ragIlflt ,Koweit on this question. mm Mr. Baxter replied that His Majesty's Government would prefer that any Uotlfofficial approach should be made through them. ^ Taufiq Suwaidi urged, nevertheless, that he might be allowed in the first Me place to approach the Sheikh of Koweit, whom he knew personally, and discuss the matter privately with him. He was sure that this would be the best procedure for reaching agreement. He, as a fellow Arab, would know how best to put the gignimatter to the sheikh, and induce him to accept some reasonable arrangement. But oniP 16 would like to be able to tell the sheikh that this private approach was being ^jgmade with the knowledge and approval of His Majesty's Government. The alk 0 ^ 0 ^ P ro P osa l s would be made later, and through us if we wished. Mr. Baxter replied that he must maintain the view that any official approach be made through His Majesty's Government, and added that further con- ties tl Sera ^ 0n wou ^ gi ven to the proposal that a preliminary private discussion ,should take place between Taufiq Suwaidi and the sheikh, with the knowledge ; and approval of His Majesty's Government. tyf! Foreign Office, October 5, 1938. !ie imetf sp id if lioDi' elf? # i# orb'Confldentla 1 BUSH 1 P.^ Political Agency, no D,0.No.C-374 ofc xy : ff. 2&lt;r I Kuwait, y c6?iFio£ii Ti AL kilc6rD3 | 20th November 1938* ^K-c/ V ^ ' / Fuad Bey Hemza, Deputy Foreign Minister of Saudi Arabia called here soon after his arrival in Kuwait on the 16th« There had been sane alterations and confusion about the date, time and place of his arrival, but he put up in the end with His Hi^aness the Ruler, having first changed into Arab dress in the house of the Saudi Arab Trade Agent# He did not in the course of his conversation touch upon any Saudi-•Kuwait matters, but was obviously keen to find out if there was anything new in the wind about British policy for Kuwait# He, like my visitor of the night before. Colonel Hughes, the Australian Trade Commissioner for the Middle last, and Major Holmes, the Oil Concessionaire, had heard, and been rather impressed by the talk in Bagdad and in Basra about Kuwait becoming part of Iraq&lt;, Fuad spoke of Kuwait being likened, in Iraq, to the Sudeten land* He revolved round this for sometime while I said little in return to his openingso He left it finally, with the reminder to me that the Kuwaitis, and even Basrawis, were mostly Nejdis by origin and still so in their customso He did however say that he felt that genuinely progressive measures such things as for example infant welfare centres and mid wifery, were importanto Many Kuwaitis must be anxious for such benefits which Iraq,, and even Saudi Arabia now offered, e Hon'ble sir Trenchard Powle, K.C.I.B., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B u s h i r e.X u. »• 16$ @) and might be effected by Iraqi propaganda. He held that Kuwait was a key position and that if His Majesty's Government changed their position here it would have a wide and evil effect in this part of the world. He presumed they were not likely to do so. 3. Fuad then told me he expected to go to London as a delegate at the Arab-Jewish conference, for which he had little hope of an Agreement unless His Majesty's Government gave the Jews a hint, before it opened, that a marked change in Jewish policy was unavoidable. He thought the Arabs would agree to maintain the present ratio of Jews to Arabs in Palestine, and even to the periodic immigration of Jews to maintain that ratio, should the Jewish proportion fell below that of the Arabs. (He seemed quite vague about the respective birth rates, and infant mortality inspite of his views on midwifery). # 4. He will no doubt have many other and more formally expressed views to give His Majesty*s Minister at Jedda, now in iiiyadh, but I thought there might be no harm in recording briefly his conversation here. * 5. On the 17th Fuad lunched in the Agency, leaving for Hiyadh in the afternoon.1*1 Confidential , D.O.No.G- 37 RUSHiRE RESIDENCY. Wo Date. CONFIDSHTIAL RECORDS Political Agency, Kuwait. 25th November, A 0 ^ You will have seen my letter No.G-370 of the 20th November, 1938, about Fuad Hamza^ visit in which I touched upon the propaganda of Iraq officials and politicians, 2* So far there has been very little effect in Kuwait, Iraq propaganda in the past has always inclined Kuwaitis more towards us than usual, and perhaps the Iraqi politicians must be considered as, unwittingly, Kuwait's best friends. Also H.M.G-'s pronouncement recently given to the Sheikh and the Council have done good. 3. Nevertheless I foresee that if the news that Iraq hopes to obtain Kuwait and that 'the matter is being discussed', reaches the local inhabitants, a few may feel it wise to have atleast one foot in the Iraqi camp. The trend of events elsewhere, and the fact that we have recently had to refuse British Nationality and protection to some four thousand of the Kuwait inhabitants, might wrongly incline some Kuwaitis to believe that we are not much interested and would give way so resolute Iraqi advances. 4. In this connection I suggest that we should now pay particular attention to such practical benefits as we can give Kuwait, for example (a) The sending of Wajastf*Expert (Correspondence ending with your letter r No.C/776 of 13th October 1938 to India Office). ' (b) The provision of training facilities (My letter V No.0-335 of the 11th October, 1938, refers). ble Sir '^r en chard Fowle, K.C.I.E.,C.B.S., .tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E. 9-CA—&lt; 1/ '/c rBUSHIRE RESIOENCV . From No.......... Date Political Agent, Kuwai CONFIDENTIAL *REC0RD8 To, Political Resident, Bushire ( m No.C- 3fe&gt;- Dated End December, 1938 ^57 Reference India Office letter No.PZ/7136 of the 8th NoTemher, 1938. I do not see how we can object effectively to two distinguished Arabs holding private conversation about the affairs of their countries and their relations. makes his approach that we should make it entirely clear to the Sheikh that any such conversation is entirely private. recoil with alarm from the idea of (a) Entertaining him. (b) The subject which he proposes to discuss, and (c) The pere presence in Kuwait of an Iraqi politician of this, to him, formidable calibre who will no doubt be called upon by various Kuwaitis and make full use of his opportunity. The Sheikh will almost certainly try to put him off if he is not sponsored by us. I do think however that before Tawfiq Suwaidi It is my further view that the Sheikh will Political Agent, KuwaitTelegram $ From Political Resident, i^ushire. To Secretary of 3tate for india, London, Copy by post to Government of mdia, -wew -Jelhi. 11 11 n Political Agent, Kuwait. lio *2 Dated the 3rd January 1939. India uffice Express Letter ilo.P.Z. 7136 of 8th November. After consultation with Political Agent, Kuwait, i am of the opinion that provided the proviso in paragraph 5 cu foreign uffice letter of 19th October is followed we need not object to the suggested private discussion. Jiri tconsul s&lt;uJ' 5/' !'* t awAj 'SMILaL- GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. iibcb 3 rna'! Affairs Dmpaetmint, EXPRESS LETTER W BUSHIRE RESIDENCY No J Date CO.'JFIiZ.'JTIAL RECORDS [N* B,—This is an ORIGINAL MJESSAGU, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue me of the toires, but intended to he treated, on recdpty with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been §0 despatched.] From Foreign, NM DiSLHI, To Britconsul, Bushire,' Repeated to Political .Agent, Kamit. Hot F.297-N/38. Baled tile Decembe 155139 . Iraqi Government 1 a wish for a new port ^'1 on the Persian Gulf • Reference India Office Sxpress letter No.P.2.7136/38 dated 8th November 1938. 2. Government of India will be glad to receive your comnents as soon as possible. The issue of the above has been authorised Deputy Secretary to the Government of India ru. s. mfp—288 s&amp;p—(m-540)—27-7-38—300,000.£ 27 By Air Mail. P.Z. 4-j 3 19 INDIA OFFICE, Cui LONDON, c^7 Oc Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. / &lt;y / ^ C/ (■v .v-n A copy has been sent to X^eLc^. b y Mail. T4^-FnrP]'o-n (rovemment, of Tr .rli ?r The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 36819 Wt 8330/106 4000 + 4000 4.38 requested that in any further communi- t this subject the under-mentioned letter nber may be quoted, and the reply I to— Jnder Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S.TF. 1. 433/39 /IW- 0 INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.I. 31st January, 1939• Sir, With reference to Foreign Office letter of the 19th October, No. 6879/2094/93, relative to a conversation at the Foreign Office on the 4th October with the then Iraqi Minister of Foreign Affaire regarding the desire of the Iraqi Government for an additional commerical outlet to the sea, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that, after consultation with the Government of India and the Politjcal Hesident in the Persian Gulf, he sees no objection to the course of action suggested in paragraph 5 of the above-quoted letter. In as much, however, as the proposal for an informal disciission with the Sheikh of Koweit was made, partly on personal grounds, by Taufiq Suwaidi, who has now ceased to hold office, the Secretary of State would suggest that it is a matter for consideration whether the proposal to inform the Iraqi Government as suggested is affected by the change of Government. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd,) B.T. PSSL. Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office,1 QQqfitontiai. N0 .F.297-N /S8. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the (l) Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian (2) Political Agent, Kuwait ' for information. External Affairs Department, New Delhi. The 33^January 1939. Telegram to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London, No. 110 dated the 19th 1 \ ■; • January 1939. r' S v / 1 lit (n^) I MResidencv 1 . By order etc., Assistant Secretary to the Government of India ■110 „ Telegram P. No.110. dated 19th January 1939. From.Governor General (External Affairs Deptt..), New Delhi. T 0 -' .Secretary of State for India, London. (Coprby post to Political Resident Bushire and to Political igent, Kuwait), gXPRESS, Tour express letter No 0 p.Z.7136/38 dated 8th NoYember e proposed Iraqi port in Kuwait. K.fM We agree with Politicti. Resident's views communicated in his telegram No.2'of 3rd January. (N. IS.D,S,? t J.S. U.S.F. P.S.Y. &amp; 0. &amp; SECRSTiRY EXECUTIVE COmCIL). M„R.\ ,, A' By Air Mail. P.z. ^l+l 19jf! mamsm &amp; '1 BUSHIRE RESrDENCY. A/o o a te . CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to 1 ^ hyJ^Mail 3681 FuiuiMii l3y(jiuUi.y, QuvLiumuiL u£ ludm. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.m OFFICB '''I 'TtiSEItai OFFICE, S.W.I. /68/93) 9th February, 1939 Sir In my despatch NOo 587 of the ,20th OctolDer 1938 ? I sent Your Excellency a copy of a letter from my department to the India Office regarding the desire of the Iraqi ... - —i t -t-iit-i ii• ■iii .iirirrriirninTr'*'—nr—i»n—iww——— Government for an additional commercial outlet to the seao You will recall that in paragraph 5 of that letter it was rNl, III I _ . | proposed that 9 if the Iraqi Government desired to obtain certain concessions from the Sheikh in connexion with the establishment of such a port* they should 'be informed that it will in the first place 'be for them to state exactly what these concessions are, and that, if their requirements appear to he reasonable. His Majesty's Government will be prepared to inform the Sheikh that they have no objection to his discussing informally with the Iraqi Minister for Foreign Affairs the question of the compensation which he y /ould be prepared to accept. 2, I now enclose a copy of a letter from the India Office from Y /hich it will be observed that no objection is seen to this proposal. 3= Your Excellency will, however, see that the India Office suggest that, inasmuch as the request for permission to conduct discussions on the subject with the Sheikh of Koweit direct was made, partly on personal grounds, by Sayid iaufiq Suwaidi, it is for consideration whether the action ellency Maurice Peterson, KoC.M.G etc., etc 0 , etc©, etc 0 , Bagdad,llCj (g) action proposed is affected by the change of Government in Iraqt« It may indeed he well to leave it to the new Government to make it clear that they attach the same value to direct discussions with the Sheikh as their predecessors did, and subject to your views I am inclined to agree that you need take no action with the Iraqi Government, unless they again refer to the matter. If they do so, you may, however, speak to them on the lines of paragraph 5 of the Foreign Office letter mentioned above, 4, Should General Nuri al Said raise the question while he is in this country, I propose to speak to him in the same sense. I am, with great truth and respect. Sir, Your Excellency*s obedient Servant, (For the Secretary of State)(Mel tNQI OSURE IN FOREIGN OFFSCfe V —^ COVE «tlNO LETTER DATED '19. MAR Ml*' F' 7/58/93) L 1939 '39) British Embassy, B agdad• 22nd February, 1939. j My Lord ? With reference to Your Lordship's despatch No»73» (E 802/58/95) of February 9th, I have the honour to inform you that I agree with your view that ? unless the present Iraqi Government refer to the matter, it is not necessary for me to take any further action concerning the request made by Saiyid Taufiq Suwaidi in London last October for permission to conduct direct discussions with the Shaikh of Koweit regarding the modifications to the existing frontier between Koweit and Iraq which might, from the Iraqi point of view, become desirable if the Iraqi Government were to decide to develop a new outlet to the sea on the Khor Abdullah, 2 # The present Government have not, since they came into office, discussed this project with me and I do not expect that they will do so until the survey of this waterway which is now being carried out by the Basra port authorities, has been finished. I have the honour, etc., (Signed) Maurice Peterson. Right Honourable he Viscount Halifax, K.G,, G.C.S.I., G.G.I.E., etc., etc «, etc.,tt GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AtR MAIL). dentia l. [n.b. Thin is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated.., on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No 0/219 Political Agency, Kuwait, X Dated NewDdhi ' the 9th May, 19 39. 10 TJle Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject: - Projected, new Port works at the mouth of the Shatt-al-Arab. Eeference my His Highness tells me that he has received definite information and some details ahout the projecte d Iraqi port, the port preliminary surveys for which, partly on his terri- tory without permission, (see paragraph 56(c) of my Intelli gence Summkry Ho. 7 of 1939) are now, he hears, completed. T he Port, he says, is to he in the Khor AMulla and some of his land is to he acquired for it. T his information has reached him from Hajji Williamsor a renegade Christian sailor, and retired Oil Conffi'any employeT, who incidentally, from his own tales, has heen shanghaied in more ports than anyone else. I respectfully suggest that steps might now be taken to convey to His Highness some preliminary information ahout this proposed port, adjacent to, if not in, his territory, through an orthodox channel. rs 60 (Signature) s.u. (D Political Agent, Kuwait. MFP—1534 S&amp;P—(M.2835)—24-5-38—10,000.IXOj ■extract paragraph 56 (o) of Kuwait Intelligenoe Suninary for the period from let to 15th April, 1939. 56. IRAQ. . X x X X X (o) The Basra port authorities ifeve erected posts on Kuwait territory, along the shore of the BAHAITH BAY and the KHOR 3U8IYA, without permission from or intimation to the Kuwait authorities. This is understood to nave been done under the direction of Mr.Coster ^who was involved in the cutting of date trees on the Shaikh's estates witnout permission last summer) who, it is said in Basra, has been engaged on a survey 'at the request of the foreign Office'. X X X X X XI &gt;■ M*, Ho.0/187 of 1939• f Jhl Oogfidentlal Office of the Political Resident in the Persian £*ulf, ^amp Kuwait. 20th May 1939. To ?he Political Agent Kuwait* Subjects Iraqi Port in Kuwait territory Memorandum eferenoe your Express Letter Ho.0/219 of 9 til May. At an interview which had with His Highness yesterday, we informed him how the matter stood. Ho need for further action at present. ad, T.a.jhmss Political Resident in the Persian Uulf. Attested for 3e( . lit leal Resident in the Persian Gulf.c*. j S' - ] By Air Mail. !;;;: /^ ^ Sr-yjINDIA OFFICE, _J LONDON, Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to 'f- byMail. • •'-Sea-. * - c h 3681 u vui miCTt p£ Indra. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.\*&gt; .4852/39. JOEEIGiT OFFICE, S.W.I. 5116/58/93). 5th. August, 1939. ^ ' Dear Jarrett, Will you please refer to the correspondence ending s with our official letter E. 1817/58/93 of the 22nd March regarding the desire of the Iraqi Government for an additional outlet to the sea ? 2. You will recall that since this matter was raised last year, it has gone through the following stages. (1) 'When Taufiq Suwaidi , then Minister for Poreign Affairs, was in London in Octoloer, he was informed that the information at the disposal of the British Authorities concerned showed that the Khor Abdullah appeared much more suitable for developnent as a modern port than any site in the Bay of loweit. (2) Taufiq Suwaidi pointed out that if the Iraqi Government decided to develop a port on the Khor Abdullah, they might require certain concessions from the Sheikh of Koweit, and he enquired whether any objection would be seen to the Iraqi Government making a private approach direct to the Sheikh, with a view to reaching some reasonable arrangement with him. (3) After consultation with the Government of India, it was agreed that no objection need be raised to this procedure. (4) In view of the change of government in Iraq, it was, however, decided that the Embassy at Bagdad need not take the initiative in informing the Iraqis accordingly, and (5) meanwhile Sir John Ward was carrying out a new survey of the Khor Abdullah. j .Jarrett, Esq. , Admiralty.2. 3. Ward, who is now on leave, iias called at the Foreign Office and left the attached chart of the Khor ''''mtifflftfthf ibbbbwbwwo Abdullah which shows the results of the new survey. He ^ ^ - f . - l|j|| explained that he had throughout treated the matter as one of the greatest secrecy, in the first place because he wished His Majesty's Government to have a chance to consider any requirements they might have before the Iraqis began to take too lively an interest in the possibilities of the new port; in the second place because it seemed undesirable at the present stage to arouse the curiosity of the Sheikh o. Koweit. He had, therefore, specially asked General Kuri not to write to him on the subject and even his own subordinates had not been told the real reasons for his surveying operations. The explanation that he had offered for general consumption of the movements of his survey ship was that the Port authorities wished to test throughout the whole area the effects of dumping from the dredgers of the Fao service, and he had left definite instructions with his deputy at Basra, Captain Garstin, not to communicate his copy of the chart to the Iraqi authorities until Ward's own return to Iraq. 4. In brief, the survey had, Ward said, shown (a) that there is a channel never shallower than 19 feet at low water (i.e. some 29 feet at high water). fh^o is quite adequate for most of the ships that use the Persian Gulf. With a very little dredging it could be made navigabxe at all tides, and as there is no silt brought down to che Khor Abdullah from upstream, the dredging operations, once completed, would not have to be repeated, or at most woulu only have to be repeated at long intervals. (b)/3. ('b) that there are two good sites for a port on the right 'bank of the Khor Abdullah, one on the north, one on the south side of the Tin Kasr creek; the creek itself could, vilth the existing dredgers of the Port of Basra easily be made into an excellent basin: so far as he could judge from the air, the southern site was rather more suitable, but with the expenditure of some money the northern site too should prove quite adequate: Ward was not quite clear where the frontier reached the Khor Abdullah, but he thought that both the northern site and the creek itself were in Iraq, while the southern site was in Koweit. (c) That so far as he could make out, there should be no difficulty in extending the Iraqi railway system down to the Khor Abdullah, and that meanwhile there was a good surface for motor traffic. The examination had in fact settled once for all the question where Iraq should look, if she wished an outlet to the sea. 5. Ward further explained that before the completion of the survey he had himself inclined to the view that there was no very satisfactory site for a port on Iraqi territory. Hence Taufiq Suwaidi's reference to possible cessions from Koweit. Uov/ anything of the sort had apparently proved to be, strictly speaking, unnecessary, although if the site to the south of the creek turned out to be greatly superior to the site on the north, and if it was in fact in Koweit, the Iraqis might wish to secure it for themselves. Moreover, it would, of course, from the Iraqi point of view prove more satisfactory if such adjustments/(© 4. adjustments could be made in the frontier as would give them sole control of the channel, and thereby avoid the possibility of the same complications arising with Koweit in the future as had already risen with Persia over the Shatt al Arab. Ward added that so far as he himself was concerned he did not attach great importance to this second point, since so long as Iraq remained an ally of His Majesty's Government, they would no doubt ensure that Koweit 1 s interest in the water-way did not cause inconvenience. 6. General Nuri had shown considerable interest in the survey. Ward had, indeed, no idea whether the Iraqi Government was seriously contemplating any scheme that would involve expenditure on a considerable scale, but he was himself convinced that the site on the Khor Ab dullah. was in any case likely to play an important r61e in the future. If at any time the Anglo -Iranian Oil Company had to move out of the Shatt, the port of Basra might for financial reasons find difficulty in keeping up the dredging service on the existing scale, and if this was not done the channel would rapidly silt up and revert to its pre-Yv T ar state. The maintenance of the Khor Abdullah would be a very much less expensive task, and the time might come when all the big traffic in the Gulf would go either to Bandar Shahpur or to the Khor Abdullah, while only light craft would continue to use the Shatt. On the other hand, if the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company remained at Abadan, there^ was the fact that the Shatt was nearing saturation poi^nt, while it was only natural to suppose that the volume of Iraqi import and export trade would go on increasing. If oil is found in South Iraq the problem might become urgent. 7./5. 7. That however ? was in the future. Meanwhile Ward was confident that if additional, or alternative, port facilities were required in an emergency, he could arrange for them to he provided at very short notice indeed. The essential requirements could he supplied from reserves held at Basra and adequate communications could he provided 'by motor transport from Zuheir. 8. Prom all this the following points seem to emerge;- (a) We should note, for possible use in an emergency, that it will he feasible to provide facilities on the Khor Abdullah without much preparatory work# (h) We should try to get the facts ahout the frontier clear in our minds, and consider whether we ought to approach the Iraqis now with a view to getting an agreed definition of it, or whether it would he preferable to leave the matter alone for the time heing so far as they are concerned. (c) If the result of our enquiries is to shew that the more southerly of the two sites is in Koweit, whereas the more northerly is in Iraq, we should consider whether from our point of view we should wish Ward to advise the Iraqi authorities that this may he the better site provided that they can come to a political arrangement with Kov/eit such as would Justify them in developing it as their new port; or, alternatively, whether he Y /ould do well to take the line that as the northern site is unquestionably in Iraq, and as it should be perfectly practicable to develop a good port there, the simplest plan will certainly be to decide in its favour. (d) We should in any case consider whether from our point/6* point of view it would 'be preferalDle to arrange for Iraq, to have- sole control of the new port and its approaches? or whether we would wish her to share the channel with Koweit. 9» The position regarding the frontier seems to us very obscure . In the note of July 21st, 1932. from General Nuri to Sir F. Humphrys the definition given is as follows:- o.•to a point just south of the latitude of Safwan; thence eastwards passing south of Safwan Wells, Jehel Sanam and Urn Qasr leaving them to Iraq and so on to the junction of the Khor Zoheir with the Khor Ahdullah# The islands of 'Warbah* Buhiyan. •• appertain to Koweit 5 '. In a despatch which we have recently received from Bagdad? it is suggested that this definition should? in the interests of clarity, and by agreement with the Iraqi Government be expanded as follows;- ,f The 1 junction of the Khor Zobeir with the Khor Abdullah* shall mean the junction of the thalweg of the Khor Zobeir with the thalweg: of the north westerly arm of the Khor Abdullah known as the Khor Shetana. From the above mentioned junction of thalwegs to the open sea the boundary shall follow the thalweg of the Khor Abdullah. u 10. It is not quite clear to us that this expanded definition w±ll be sufficient to fix the frontier. It seems that the Khor zjobeir and the Khor Shetana form one channel, and are in fact both parts of Y /hat is known as the Khor Abdullah. Y/here then is the junction of their thalwegs ? It may be that the ivhor Shetana begins where the Khor Sabiyah (? or the Khor Bubiyan) joins the main channel. If this is 'so, it would seem preferable to make this clear in any improved definition of the point. Lior is it cl ear how the line from the point ^south of Safwan/Safwan' to the junction of the two Khor is drawn- In the 1932 definition it is said to run 'eastwards'' hut it is clear from any map that it does not run due east s or anything like it. The natural assumption would be that it is a straight line between the two points? 'but if the junction of the Khor is opposite the mouth of the Khor 3ahiyah&gt; a straight line from there to a point just south of Safwan •.oul.d apparently, owing to the hend in the Khor Zo'beiir? include a xoart of the left hank of the Khor in Koweit. So far as we know, however? no one has disputed that the whole left hank helongs to Iraq* 12* In spite of these difficulties, it certainly seems that* as V!srd believes? the Urn Kasr creek and therefore the site to the north of it, is in Iraq- What is doubtful? is whether the site on the south is in Koweit. j, 5' Ihother ? when we are clear ourselves as to where the frontier J : : : ;s? we sho«.ild approach the Iraqis forthwith with a view to securing its definition? depends? I think to a considerable extent| on our viewrj about points (c) and (d) above. 1/j., As far as point (c) is concerned? it will I imagine be common ground that we have no sort of interest in trying to prevent the JUr-gis from constructing a port on the Khor Abdullah if they wish tc do so.. ¥e gave the idea our sympathy last autumn and so tar a* I know, thero is no reason why we should change our views* On tre contrary&gt; Wv. shou3-d in princip&gt;le she?/ ourselves as sympathetic as possible towards their wishes to establish a new port- 15* At first sight it would appear that if the Iraqis can make an adequate port within their existing frontiers? this will be all to the good. For if? on the other hand, they want to construct their new port on what is now Koweit territory? there will have to be an alteration in the present frontier? and this is bound to lend to difficult, negotiations between Iraq and Koweit. But this brings us to the question whether there will not in any case have to be some, alteration in the present frontier in order to ensure that/(g) \ that in the Khor Abdullah 3 unlike the Shatt-el-Arat? Iraq shall have complete and undisputed control over the whole of the port area and over the whole of the waterway connecting it with the open sea. 16, ¥e thus come to point (d). We must make up our minds what part? if any, we wish Koweit to play in the development and administration of the new port. It may he 'best that Kov/eit should to some extent participate in any new schemes that may 'be devised in the Khor Abdullah. Or it may 'be 'best that Iraq, should 'be allowed to exercise exclusive control. The Iraqis will naturally wish for exclusive control? and it will he hard to persuade them to agree to anything less than this. 17. The first and most obvious objection to exclusive Iraqi control is no doubt the fact that the Iraqis would expect the Sheikh of Koweit to surrender, or at least to refrain from exercising, some of his existing rights over the water-way, and it would be difficult to find any quid pro quo that they could offer him for the necessary concessions on his part. If these were to include the cession of some part of his territory as well as of his rights over the waterway? the difficulty of finding any J^jiilLiL y. 0 quo would be very great indeed. Moreover, even if something suitable were found, it might not be easy to induce the Sheikh go accept the bargain. There may also be objections-to a Cxiange in the status quo either on strategic grounds, or on the grounds that it is in principle undesirable, in view of tne propaganda that has been going on in Iraq for the absorption Koweit, that Iraq should be enabled to acquire from the Sheikh any concession of potential value to her. In/In addition to this^ we may well ask ourselves whether 9, we can count indefinitely on the continuance of our present position in Iraq., whereas our relations with Koweit are p resumably on a more permanent hasis. Again, it is conceivalDle that Koweit might at some future date herself wish to establish a Koweiti port in the Khor Abdullah, and in any case might not wish to deprive herself for ever of the possibility of establishing such a port. Moreover, it may be thought that Koweiti participation in some kind of Harbour Board, (if the Iragis can be got to agree to that) may seem a useful guarantee for the future «&gt; 18. On the other hand, unless the production of oil in Koweit develops in a spectacular way, it seems unlikely that Koweit 1 s trade is by itself sufficient to justify the creation of a new port, even on a small scale, so far from the town. If there is not going to be a Koweiti port there in the foreseeable future, the Sheikh might well be reluctant to incur any expenditure or responsibility in connexion with the control of the waterway* Moreover, s-o far as our imperial communications are concerned, it is not clear what use a port in friendly territory would be unless a safe route to the Mediterranean could also be guaranteed. In fact, Koweit by itself would not seem to provide an adequate alternative to a friendly Iraq- 19. Complete Iraqi control of the new outleti to the sea would presumably be a great simplification frorft the practical, point of view and will probably be regarded as essential by the Iraqis. If we oppose their wishes in this respect, the political consequences may be very serious. 20, There is one further point which has occurred to us. Let us assume that there is a growing Iraqi port on/10. on the Khor Abdullah, and that the Sheikh, while maintaining his rights, is not himself in a position to construct a port of his own there, or make use of the waterway. The result would only too likely he the development of yet another source of grievance 'between the two countries, and those quarters in Iraq., who, for no particular reason except prestige already look forward to the annexation of Koweit, would then 'be a'ble to find persuasive arguments in support of their views. Taking the long view then, it is arguable that the Sheikh might 'be well advised, if he suffers thereby no real loss, to withdraw in time from this potential source of trouhle. 21. These are, however, all matters on which other Government Departments will have their views. I am accordingly sending copies of this letter to Shuckburgh o.x&gt; the Colonial Office, Peel at the India Office, Coryton at the Air Ministry, Mallahy at the War Office, Starling at the Petroleum Department, Weston at the Board of Trade, and Porter at the Committee of Imperial Defence. If they agree, I would suggest that the matter might oe considered at a meeting of the Middle East (Ofiicial) Sub-Committee some time 'before Ward returns to Iraq.* I understand that this will 'be early in September- Yours sincerely, (Sgd ♦) LACY BAG-G-ALLAY.P.Z.5504/39. Confidential jlKDIA OFFICE, VfiilTEILALL S.W.I. (ijioji') 8th September^ 1939 J By the air mail of the 11th August we sent you a copy of a demi-official letter from the.Poreign Office to the Admiralty Nd.E.5116/58/95 5 dated the 5th August; (India Office reference P.Z*4852/39) relating to the desire of the Iraqi Government for an additional outlet to the sea and the survey carried out in that connexion in the Khor Abdulla 'by Sir John Ward, You will wish to know that as the result of consideration here 'by the Departments concerned it was agreed that Sir John Ward on his return to Iraq should place the results of his survey of the Khor Abdulla unreservedly at the disposal of the Iraqi Government, and that discussions of the frontier between Iraq and Koweit in the neighbourhood of the Um Qasr creek should await further action 'by the Iraqi Government. 1 am sending a copy of this letter to Caroe and Galloway. » / 2- 4? 3 J: ''ble Major he Agency, | Bahrein. /id/s 7 Ho 30/1 5/59, /5%' HIS Majesty's Ambassador at Bagdad nresents his compliments to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the ^ Persian Qulf, Bushire, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. Bri tish.Ew!o.&amp;B.Q X. f A T o.... Bagdad. .L-.u Xl c6:ir t :z:c:^ Ricor.Ds ' 1.4th.Koyember 19^... Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 1. Bagdad despatch No.503 of 6th September,1939, to the Foreign Office, I London* 2. Bagdad letter (30/13/39) of 26th September,1939, to the Eastern Dept., Foreign Office,London. 3. Bagdad despatch No.668 of 14th November,1939, to the Foreign Office, London. Subject. Iraqi port on the Khor Abdullah, 3479 12360 [2)lio. 505. British Embassy, (50/11/39) Bagdad. 6th September, 1959• My Lord, With reference to bir Maurice Peterson's despatch No. 80 of February 22nd, I have the honour to inform you that, at an interview with the Prime I inister in the course of last month, the subject came up of the possible development mentioned by Saiyid Taufiq Suwaidi in London last autumn of a new outlet, to tne sea for Iraq on the Khor Abdullah. 2. General IMuri told me that the preliminary survey of this waterway, which had been entrusted to Sir John Ward.and the-Basra Port Authorities, would be completed during September. Mr. Loggin, the British Adviser to the Ministry of Communications, had previously told me in confidence that the Ministry of Defence were anxious to proceed with this project and had asked him to prepare plans for the construction of a railway extension to connect it with Basra. Mr. Loggin therefore anticipated that a formal approach would be made to me at any moment, but his anticipations have not as yet been realised. 5. I have since been told by Sir John Ward, on his return from England two or three days ago, that his survey is practically complete and only has to be checked. On the other hand, from official Quax*ters in London, he derived the impression that His Majesty's Government were not anxious to expedite the scheme. He was moreover confident that an emergency port could be got into use at short notice and that there was a serviceable track to connect transport with the Shaiba Road. 4. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Government of India. I have etc., (Sgd# ) BASIL MWTON. kight Honourable ^he Viscount Halifax, K.G. , G.G.S.I., G. 0*1. E. , etc. , etc. , etc.NO (30/15/39) British Embassy Bagdad. 26th September, 1939. Dear Department, ^ Our despatch No. 503 (30/11/39) of September 6th about the proposed Iraqi port on the Khor Abdullah. Sir John Ward has given us the enclosed copy of a report, the result of his survey of the Khor Abdullah, which he proposes to hand to the Minister of Communications and works today. He tells us that the explanatory charts are already in your possession. We have not yet been approached formally on the subject by the Iraqi Government. Yours ever OHANGERY. astern Department, PCP.SIC t N CFFICSECRST. Headquarters, Port Directorate Basra, 25th September 1939. No. C.58/ 59. The i-inistry of Gornrnns.&amp; Works Bagdad. Memo. You are aware that work has been going on for sometime in connection with the survey of the ^^hor Abdulla and I submit herewith a very brief report and a Hydrographical Survey of the Khor Abdulla from Urn Qasr to Warbah Spit. The survey has been carefully done in spite of the most unpleasant conditions which prevailed in the winter months during the stormy weather which made the task most arduous. It will be seen from a careful study of the chart that from a marine point of view the building of a Port just below Um Qasr Creek presents no great difficulty. The range and strength of the tides are, when compared with those in the Shat-el-Arab more difficult, neither is the surrounding country anything like so pleasant; but it is, in my opinion, infinitely better in every respect than Bandar Shapur upon which the G-overnment of Iran has already spent a very large sum and only one Berth to show for it. A proper port could be constructed at Um Qasr for a comparatively small sum - bearing in mind of course that Port construction is always a most expensive business, even the Port of Basra was a costly affair. There however, a port, with dolphins, short temporary jetties and the loan of pontoons and barges which could be made available from Basra, could be opened within a very short period of time. As will be seen from the chart a wide bar 2? to 3 miles long exists outside the Khor Shatona which carries 18 feet at low water with a rise of tide of 10 to 12 feet. This however is sufficient to enable vessels with a draft of 2? to 28 feet •r more to navigate with safety as soon as the channels are buoyed and marked which again presents no great difficulty. /IfIn-/ 0) If considered necessary one of the Port's large dredgers could, I estimate, make a channel with 20 feet at low water in 5 to 6 weeks clear working. A greater depth could be obtained over a longer period and it would not be the perpetual and most arduous task that dredging the Shatt-el-Arab bar has proved to be- I am of the opinion that once dredged it would remain steady for a considerable time. The dredgers would however be exposed to the south easterly gales and therefore could not work in bad weather, and it, is nothing to be compared with the 8hatt- el-Arab bar. In addition to the Bar already mentioned there is, near the upper end of Laskar Reach a shoal patch of 16 feet at low water, steep-to, almost in mid-stream; this would be buoyed or marked, also a short distance further up a shoal extends 3 cables out from Bahrah Point to the 3 fathom contour. This would also be marked and there is another steep-to shoal or obstruction which exists nearly in the middle of the channel approx: l-jSr miles below Um Qasr Creek but there is ample room for shipping. This would also be marked. The stream narrows to about -g- a mile in the Um Qasr reach which is ample turning space for ships at slack water. The bottom is not good holding ground but with the exercise of care ships anchoring with a good scope of cable should be quite safe. Heavy mooring Buoys could of course be laid in due course for vessels to make fast to. In my opinion 1rom a marine point of view there is no great difficulty in making Um Qasr into a very good port. The tidal range and strength of the tides will require ships to be brought in carefully and safely moored. Considering the position froma shore point of view, again I see no difficulty which cannot be overcome without vast expenses. There is a good 30 miles road running from Kobair on the same hard solid ground to within three quarters of a mile of the foreshore. This short stretch however is on ground /that-5- (l*fO/ that will become a quagmire in the rainy season, but a road could be easily made up and also wharves could be built from the Jebal Sanam Stone which is only 20 miles distant, A railway line could also in my opinion be quickly laid and without great expense. A railway bank from Shaiba to Jebal Sanam already exists. In all, 40 miles of light railway mill be required to connect up the quarry (i.e. from Shaiba to Jebal Sanam and on to Um Qasr) and additional 25 miles of proper track for direct connection between the Junction Shaiba and the Port at Um Qasr. All the ground appear to be well above spring tide level but an early survey should be made to verify this. The foreshore is unfortunately very shelving and extends approx. 300 ft. between the high and low water marks. Temporary Jetties of 100 ft. in length approx. will also be requjred, these with dolphins together with pontoons and Buoys available in Basra would enable the Port to be quickly put into commission. If rough estimates of cost are required then the railways should undertake the shore survey and my surveyors and engineers could prepare estimates of jetty construction, costs of dolphins. Buoys, Beacons, etc., etc. (Sgd*) J.G. WARD &lt;0olonel (Rtd.) Port Director and Director-General of Navigation.By Mail. __ . [BUSH' RE REBIOEN: (s 7//V INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to Zjl by g Mail Jftic Foreign Socrota ry, Goytniiiiigirrgrtmlia. The Political Resident in the Persian Gult.m Enclosure in Poroi gn_Qffinfi Covering T\In 0 E,q date i d. i 14th ^ tob er, 1939 . p.z. 6403. 1939. POREKGN OPMCE, S.W.I. 13th October, 1939. (E 6^0^58/93)- Secret, Dear Jarrett^ With our official letter E 6439/58/93 of the 20th September the Admiralty received a copy of Bagdad des^rtclT Wo. 303 regarding- the developments since the return to Iraq of Sir John Ward in the matter of the proposed new Iraqi port on the Khor Abdullaho I now enclose a copy of the report T ^hich Ward has submitted on the subject to the Iraqi Government» Copies of this letter are being sent to Sir John Shuckburgh, Mallaby ; Cory ton, Pecl 5 Weston, Starling and Porter. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) LACY BAGGALLAY. C.G. Jarrett Esq., Admiralty.- 4 %, cu n pMQMinp RE^OENCY x / / /4^ ; No- D r dt S 7601/58/93. lifiaENTIAL RECORDS CO i A 1 7886 j I9 21LJ PORSION OFFICE, S.W.I. 16th December, 1939. Sir, With reference to Foreign Office letter ** I' ^44- E 6450/58/93 of the 20th September I am directed by Viscount Halifax to transmit to you, herewith a copy of a despatch from His Majesty*s Ambassador at Bagdad regarding the proposed new Iraqi port on the Khor Abdullah- 2, It will be seen from this despatch that the Iraqi G-overnment have been favourably impressed by the results of the survey carried out by the Port of Basra authorities, that they have decided to undertake the construction of wharves near Um Qasr, which is to be connected with the Iraqi railway system, and that, in the opinion of the Iraqi Government, it would be necessary, both from the point of ■ view of navigation and security, to obtain for Iraq the sovereignty over both banks of the channel connecting the new moorings with the open sea.. It will further be seen that, on being pressed by Sir Basil Newton, the Iraqi Minister for Foreign Affairs stated that the concessions from Koweit which his government had in mind were the Warbah and Bubiyan islands* 3^ From the previous discussions on this subject, Lord Halifax understands that the Iraqi Government can in fact build on Iraqi territory a port of their own which would be adequate to their immediate needs and would have access to the/ The Under-Secretary of State, India Office. I(@&gt; h' 0 the sea through Iraqi territorial waters, without obtaining any territorial concessions from Koweit? although it might be necessary for a certain amount of dredging to be carried out in Koweiti waterSo On the other hand it is understandable that the State which controls the Mesopotamian plain should desire to have undivided control of at least one good means of access to the sea, and Lord Halifax thinks that on a long view it is likely that, if Iraq were given this access, it would make for steadier conditions in that part of the world in years to come 0 4o Undivided control of a waterway normally . pre-supposes the possession of sovereignty over both its bankSo At any rate it is difficult, as the experience of Turkey and Iraq in the Shatt-al-Arab has shown, to make good a claim to sovereignty over the whole of a waterway without possessing the sovereignty over both banks. But all the same the essential requirement of the Iraqi Government, or any other government in their position, must be the sovereignty of the waterway itself; and this general consideration is not effected by the fact that, in the case of the Khor Abdullah, if the port to be constructed on this particular waterway were expected to become a large one, they might require in addition, in order to allow for future expansion and for reasons of purely local topography, the cession of a small part of the Koweiti mainland near the point at which the common frontier meets that waterway (assuming, at any rate, that it meets it somewhere only a little south of the Um Qasr creek )o If Iraq could secure the sovereignty over the whole of the Khor Abdullah, the cession of the islands of Warbah and Bubiyan themselves would/would seem unnecessary from the point of view of navigation, and could only be justified on the s^ore of defence^ As regards defence, since these islands are, at certain times of the year anyway, under water at high tide, the military reasons for their acquisition by Iraq do not seem strong® In any case, strategic requirements would seem to apply with equal force, or rather with more force, to the whole of the mainland of Koweit from the point {wherever that may be) where the frontier meets the Khor Abdullah to the point of junction of the Khor Abdullah with the Khor Sabiya* The introduction of so-called defence requirements therefore involves further cessions from Koweit over and above those which could be justified on the score of navigational requirements alone^ Moreover, from the point of view of the prospective difficulty of retaining and exercising sovereignty over the waterway through a long term of years in the absence of sovereignty over the right bank, the acquisition of the two islands alone is insufficient. 5. But whatever the desires and deserts of the Iraqi Government may be, the Sheikh of Koweit is clearly under no obligation to cede to Iraq any part of his territory, except in return for what he may consider adequate compensation. If, therefore, the Iraqi Government desire to obtain concessions from him,they must accept his terms, although His Majesty's Government would no doubt, in view of their friendly relations with both parties, endeavour to facilitate a settlement satisfactory both to the Iraqi Government and to the Sheikho Copies of Sir Basil Newton 1 s despatch have been sent to the political Resident in the Persian//5'^ Persian Gulf and to the political Agent at Kovi/eit, as well as to the G-overnment of India, who may have observations to offer as to the nature of the compensation which the Sheikh might accept&gt; Until an expression of tb tr views has been received, it is clearly impossible to reach any conclusion on this point. But it seems to Lord Halifax probable that the question of compensation on any large scale will in any case present great difficulty,, 6. It therefore appears desirable that the concessions required from Koweit should be reduced to the minimum, and as there is a case for maintaining that it is at present unnecessary, in view of the special relations between His Majesty's Government and both the parties, and of the evident impossibility of any threat to Iraq from Koweit, for the Iraqi Government to take strategic considerations into account in connexion with the new port, it seems to Lord Halifax that they might be well advised to concentrate on their navigational needs onlyo As has been said above, these involve, essentially, only the cess on of the Koweit portion of the waterway, and since sovereignty over half this waterway is at present, so far as Lord Halifax knows, of no particular value to the Sheikh, and would probably not become of essential value (seeing that Koweit has other outlets) even if oil were discovered in larger quantities, it seems to His Lordship that some settlement agreeable to His Highness as well as to the Iraqi Government should not be impossible of achievement, possibly on the basis of a monetary payment by the Iraqi Government* I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,f . &gt; A ilff Confidential• Political Agency, . Kuwait. D.O. NO. 0/20 PUSmRE RE StDENOY:! January, 1940 /S'3&gt; 0 No .. /v.^r.Wr^rv.^-- Di - l - 4o • C ^fpercttftl/ records j SuIdJ ect ; - Proposed port on the Ktior AMulla. e£&amp;~*~r His Highness informed me on the 9th that some Iraqi engineers had proceeded to 'where you and I lunched with a European engineer ,f and were then and there driving stakes into the Khor SuMyah. I examined the man who had 'brought in the report at SuMyah, and found that the Shaikh had received a garbled version, ho Iraqi had 'been there, 'but I learnt that engineers were working on the Khor from some tents at Umm al Q,asr some five days ago, and it is possible that they entered Kuwait territory. 2. It would suit us if the Iraqis curbed their ardour until the case were at least settled in principle, but I think that we cannot protest as we are not, for one reason, sure of the boundary alignment. 3. It seems necessary to take an early opportunity of informing His Highness of the matter afoot. C^t^i / on'ble Lieut-Col. C.G-.Prior, GEE., 'olitical Sesident in the Persian G-ulf, at Kuwait.Telegrain. From. ttnn Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. Political Resident, at Kuwait. Political Agent, Kuwait. To. Repeated to No* 221. Dated 24th, received 25th January, 1940. Reference India Office Express Letter P.Z.7886/S9 of January 11th. Government of India propose awaiting your comments before replying. FOREIGN.(e&gt; w'i' Telegram Prom To Copy to N o .T/29. Dated the 25th January 1940. Political Hesident at Kuwait. Government of India, New Delhi. Political Agent, Kuwait. „ 15' O'- f ll'l Your telegram Ho*221 January 24th r Copy of India Office Expres-s letter referred to has not yet reached me. If it does not arrive before my departure from Kuwait (now 3rd February) I may not get it for some time. Please telegraph subject. RESIDENT.n /!7 Telegram Q From Government of India, New Delhi To Political Hesident, at Kuwait. iTo.247 Dated 26th received 27th Janaury 1,940. Your telegram l^o.T/29 January 25th. / Subject is proposed new Iraqi port on Khor Abdullah. India Office in their Express letter Ko.P.Z. 7886/39 'January 11th ask for Government of India views on Foreign Office letter Ho.7601/58/9S 16th December. Fore ign G.T # Copy given to P.A* Kuwait7471 Wt 23481/P 215 2000 8.38 INDIA OFFICE, 5? Political D epar 'ment. Date.' f5-i , H MM mm*-*- - 4 ' A — ' kfULsyuffc X7- EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). CONHDeNTIAL RECORDS (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State To Government of India. Ext. Affairs Dept. Bepeated to Pol. Res in the Persian Gnlf, : and Pol. Agent,. Koweit. Dated 11th Januaryl940 No. P.Z.7886/39 Please see foreign Office letter of the 16th December No. E. ?601/58/93 9 copy sent to you hy air mail on 22nd December 5 regarding the desire of the Iraqi Government to obtain territorial concessions from Koweit in connexion with the proposed new port on the Khor Abdulla, be glad to have your views at an early date. I shall The issue of the above has 'been authorised. 14 &lt;1. GIBSON /To. d /?&lt; i iOOKFIDfflTm.. Office of the PolitioaX Resident in the Persian Gulf, D,0.1T o .G/93. Camp, Muscat• Bated the 8th February, 1940 My dear Peel Please refer to your Express Letter No.P*2;•7886/39, dated the lith January 1940, regarding the proposed port in the iChor Abdullah* I haTe uome into the picture rather late in the day, and the first thing that strikes nae is that our attitude to the Shaikh has not been strictly honest, and that it is only within the past few months that any attempt has been made to consider his interests, which we have solemnly pledged ourselves to protect# 2* The project for a port in Kuwait Bay itself has fortunately been abandoned* The creation of a large and Important Iraqi pied a terra across the bay could only have resulted in the disintegration of Kuwait a© an independent State, with, as I shall show later, serious consequences for ourselves. It must be remersbered that the Iraqi attitude to Kuwait is essentially dishonest, as their tactics during the last two years have shown# They are perfectly aware that they have no claim whatever to Kuwait, but they are aware of our penchant for sacrificing our friends to our enemies, and hope that by making our flesh creep we may bring pressure to bear on Kuwait to agree to die quietly. 3# During the whole of the time we were considering the / possibility H,T.Peel Bsquire, G.B»B.,M»G», The India Office, London@) /6'&lt;J -s- possibility of using ICuwa.it 6ay no mention of the Iraqi proposals was made to the Shaikh# nor was any attempt xaa^e to reassure Mm regarding the yery disquieting rumours that must have reached him froui Ira&lt;i* If our intentiom? were honest and if we sincerely desired to protect his interest© wby did we keep him in the dark V Perhaps our object was to let matters go so far that there would he no recoiling for fear of arousing the ire of the terrible Iraqie (Baggallay's letter Ho#l 5116/56/93 of 5th August 1939 to Jarrett, para- b» \yi% 'h* graph /^)» and in the same letter (paragraph 3) though Iraqi surveyors had already 'been making free with Kuwait territory it was considered appropriate ^not to arouee the Shaikh 9 b curiosity• tt 4* It is unfortunate that the Iraqis were allowed to continue for so long without being informed authoritatively of Kuwait * £ rights and; very -unfortunate /that no one with knowledge of Kuwait affairs was present at Taufic| Suwaidi's conference at the foreign Office on October ^ hf 4th, 193S (Foreign Office Print Ho.B 584^/1982/93 of October 5th, 1938)♦ When Major Bdmonds suggested that Kuwait should levy the Iraq tariff (which would have been sfeioidal) and Taufiq Suwaidi suggested an Iraq official should be attached to the Kuwait CustomB administration, the only reply that was given was that 'the suggestion would be examined further*• The Iraqis did not fail to make capital out of this. The Shaikh has, as I have shown above, been unfairly treated in being kept in the dark, and there is no doubt that our failure to inform the Iraqis at the outset that they must gain their ends by negotiation made them raise their / voicesr ' ' ' -— : ■ , •; ■' ' - s voioas* air Basil Kewton 1 a letter (Ho#668 dated the i4th Hovamber 1939) to toe foreign Office was therefore doubly weloorse in that it put the isatter before the Irakis for the first time in its true light, and calling the Miniver•£ 'bluff had the iusediate effect of reducing his demands to reasonable proportions* 6# I now corse to the present proposals# iosjr extension of Ira&lt;li influence in Kuwait, no matter how we hedge it in^ wi)JL he a danger. They will abuse their position and by bluff from without and intrigue from within seek to undermine Kuwait until they realise their dream# They hare watched Herr Hitler*s tactics with interest and admiration and ■ adopted them for their own# So long as they derelop a port in their own territory, and ask for no conceasions from Kuwait, nothing can be said, but the moment they begin to ask for concessions it is, as Sir Basil lewton pointed out, extremely difficult to find anything that could be given them# Bubiyan the Shaikh would never yield, no matter what compensa tion was paid, for, apart from any question pf pride, its value as an oil territory is unknown# He could not accept money compensation for territory without serious lose of •♦face*# His Highness detests the Iraqis, who have behaved disgracefully In the last two years, and there is no doubt whatever that Bin Saud, witji whom he has recently strengthened relations, would resent any concession on his part as he . feels he has an underlying interest in what was his old home# fuad Hamsa pointed this out on his visit of 16th ilovember 1938 to de Oaury and said that if His Majesty's Government f&gt;&lt; ic&lt;£ ' changed their position here it would have a *wide and evil / effectaffect in this part of the world** Bin Saud ie as interested as the Shaikh in keeping the Iraqi® out of Kuwait and if the Shaikh makes any oonceeaion he will have to reckon with Bin ^aud. It will be remembered that Bin Saud moved troops to the frontier when the Shaikh staged hie 'coise back 11 Met m January and had the coup failed he would unquestionably have brought then in to support the AX Sabah. 7. If the Iraqis can develop the port without territorial conoeseions, there is of course nothing to prevent them, for the Shaikh would probably raise no objection to their improv ing the joint waterway so long aa he was not asked to cede hia rights# I should be very surprised if he made any territorial concession to enable theis to have the southern site mentioned, and I m extremely doubtful if he would agree to hypothecate his iright to the waterway r for, apart from questions of prestige, it would mean that any port developed by the Kuwait Oil Company for the oil which hae already been found would be at the mercy of the Iraqis. Hor does it seem to me that it is in our interests that Iraqis should have undivided sway# So long as Kuwait, or rather ourselves, have a half share in the Khor Abdullah, Iraq has incentive to remain on good terms with us. They cannot say that the K^wai t share in the Khor Abdullah can ever be a danger. ]far from an undivided Iraqi control of access to the sea making for steadier conditione in this part of the world, the Iraqis would become more intransigent than ever# 8. A word about ^ir John Ward, the protagonist of the scheme, may not be out of place. I have the greatest respect for his ability, drive and acumen^ Though his financial / methodsisethods would not be appreciated in more efficiently administered countries they are probably dictated by the circumstances in nfhich he finds hiajeelf • I must, however, dispel the illusion that he is entirely mindful of our interests# Ha# this been the ease he would aever have contemplated (without any assistance from Ira&lt;i$a project for 3 stealers to run from fao to Karachi, the first affect of which would be to destroy an important eervioe of the British India line• His idea unquestionably ie that if he can keep the Iraqis interested and involved in large soheises (which they cannot carry out without his drive and personnel) he is more likely to retain his position and power and that of the British element in the Port which he controls. Ho- where have 2 seen a mention of the fact that the British taxpayer is still apparently owed £ 170,00 for the Basra port and it seems strange that we should encourage the Iraqis to build a new port before they have paid for the old one. His stateraent that the Shatt has reached saturation point ie, I think, demonstrably untrue; had this been the case there should have been little difficulty in recovering the due to us. 9. To sura up (a) if the Irakis wish to build a port in their territorial waters m cannot prevent the% though anything that brings Ira^i influence nearer to K u wait is a danger to that State• (b) I do not think that the Shaikh will give territor ial oono«eeions of any kind no matter what financial induce- U J ', i ' ' iaont is offered. / (o)(a) I am 'very doubtful that he vdll make aay concession over his sphere of the watsrwa^r. (d) I think that he would he very ill advised to do so in view of the need fox a deep water port for his oil exports- (e) I consider that we have a lauoh better guarantee of Iracii good behaviour in the future if we control one hank of their outlet than if they have undivided sway* (f) Any concession by the shaikh to the Irakis whether spontaneous or dictated hy us will he bitterly resented by Bin Saud who dislikes Iraqi penetration as much as the Shaikh, and he will find zaeans of making his resentment felt, and finally (g) the Shaikh must be told at once what the Iraqis propose to do and be reassured that he is not going to be asked to make concessions against his will* I mm shall be able to do this when I return to Kuwait in March# I m sending oopiel of this letter to agroe, iewton mix Galloway • *«ent under Printed letter Ho.0/94 of the 8th February,1940•No. 20 5/4/40 . HIS Majesty's Ambassador at Bagdad nrpsents his compliments to the Hon'ble the Political Resident In ^ Persian Gulf, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. Bfitish. ..H^a s sy.. Bagdad. *1* Jin Dare... ,16.t.h..Pe.'b.ruary...., 19...40.. : R3^ Reference to previous correspondence : ly Bagdad despatch No. 30/15/39 dated 14th November, 1939. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Bagdad despatch No.72 of 16th February, 1940, to the Foreign Office, London. Development of a port at Um Qasr. 3479 18315 (4):mSk!Ai 7471 Wt 23481/P 215 2000 8.38 INDIA OFFICE, EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). 'r - &lt;!RE RESIDENCY. '/'/o'' iJEPARTlll^'iT? rr iuj&gt; ' COiiriOENTUL RECWDS JM* (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic Qbt-f- 'I expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it bad been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State To Government of India, External Affairs Department To- Repeated to Political Resident in the Persi n Gulf 11 to Political Agent, Koweit# Dated 16th February 1940. No. P.Z.7886/39. Reference my express letter'of the 11th -b ■ f5 '] January, No.P.Z.7886/39. Proposed establishment of Iraqi port on the Khor Abdullao Foreign Office are p ItPo anxious for early reply as Iraqi Government have again raised the matter. If your views can be stated conveniently 'briefly please communicate them 'by telegraph. 1 he issue of the above has been duly author!sed^ (SgcL) «!• m jjjjSSSS 55COPY OP TELEGRAM. From H.M. A mbassador, rogoitt lgn..Off ice ^om j o p. B agdad. Date No . 1 $/%MI ,110. Time despatched Addressed to Foreign Office !lo, IS/Savii^^ repeated to Politjeal Resident in Per«ian Gulf end Political Agent at Kowelt My telegram Wo.39. In the course of my flrct visit to General Kurl in his eapaelty as inister for Foreign Affairs he adverted to Urn ^,asr and pleaded for support in obtaining territorial concessions from Kowolt. Ihile not. proposing any territorial compenBation he hinted vaguely that economic satisfaction could be given and also that some coismon regime might be established similar to that of the Iraql-saudl neutral zone, ffhlle admitting that access to the port was not likely to be endangered by noweit he said that the Iraqi Oovernment ould be exposed to criticism if they failed to provide for thoir o«n control over the approaches and he offered to give any guarantees which AO welt or ate '-ajesty's Oovemment might desire in return. 2. I promised to telegraph again and said that might have some opportunity of discussing the question with the olitical Resident whom I hoped to meet shortly in Bahrain. At the same time 1 held out no hope that territorial surrenders would be made. I observed that the very fact of their being desired by the Iraqi Governmant would make them seem all the more important to the Shaikh whereas apart from the matter of appearances the only reason for th® acquisition of islands which he had himself described as barren was to meet a purely hypothetical situation. NKWTOM. fcajvL/0id-!■ V'C. ^ ^ (9462) Wt.47903/320 3,000 3/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 / ' ' y^'ra / &gt;7 Telegram En clair. prom Government of India, New Delhi To Prior, Taj Mahal, Bombay. No. 122-H. Dated the 25th February 1940. ,r • Khor Abdullah. Kindly supplement your demi-official letter with official letter to us stating your views. -FGRBIGN. W.L&lt;From To 'R, f y The Hon 1 ble Lieutenant Colonel CtG.Prior, CIE M Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. O.K.Caroe, Esquire, CIE» f Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. i/0 I 1 ^ Dated New Delhi, the 7th March 1940. sir, t-l'l ^ 1 I have the honour to refer to your telegram No.l22/K, dated the 1st March regarding the Khor Abdullah, and to express the following views t- 2. The matter must be viewed from two aspects: Firstly an Iraqj port on the north side of the Khor which would require no cession of territory by the Shaikh of Kuwait, and which would simply be a question of the Iraq Government improving and using t 1 the joint waterway for their own purposes. I do not think that Hid Highness would object to this, nor, provided that his rights were protected, would any objection be justified. 3. If, on the other hand, the Iraq Government decided that a po^ft on the south side of the creek, i.e. in Kuwait territory, would be the only one that would meet their requirements, then as has been accepted in Foreign Office letter No. E.7601/58/93, A / V/ dated the 16th December (para.5) the Shaikh of Kuwait is under no obligation to xbk cede any portion of his territory except in Tetum for what he considers adequate condensation. Further more, by virtue of the last paragraph of certain assurances given to Shaikh Mubaittk as^Subah in 1914 (Aitchison 1 s Treaties 1929 Ho. XLII) we have recognised that the Shaikhdom is an independent Government under our protection. 4. His Highness has not yet been officially informed of the exact nature of the Iraqi proposals and it is therefore difficult to say with certainty what his reactions to a request for/....for cession of territory would be. I feel sure, however, that If he is to be allowed no share in the port that he will not agree to any form of monetary condensation, nor would lis yield to blackmail in the shape of renewed attacks on the as-Subah estates in Fao. we may dismiss territorial compensation as impracticable, 5. The Shaikh has shown by his obstinacy over the Neutral Zone that he is extremely tenacious where Ms rights are concerned, and I do not consider that bis pride as an Arab Ruler would permit him to accept cash compensation for ceded territory, and Ibn Saud would be certain to resent any one sided concession in an area where he feels he lias an under lying interest* There is no doubt that Ibn ^aud wpdat moved « troops to the frontier in the spring of 1939 when His Highness staged his coup d' etat, and had it failed he would almost certainly have sent them to the sup.-ort of the A1 Subah. Since then they have further atrengthened their ties. 6* I do not feel that we should be acting in the interest of Kuwait in advising them to cede their interests in a possibJs pftrt in the Khor Abdullah* Oil has already been found in Jarge quantities and it is very likely that the Khor Abdullah may prove to be the most practical! route for exporting it* The best line to take appears, therefore, to be that / IH*' suggested in para* 4 of the Baghdad -mbassy letter No.668 of the 14th November 1939, namely that of providing a coianon interest for Kuwait in the construction and development of these the new port, on £ ek terms the co-operation of the Shaikh should not be difficult to secure* 7. As to whether the port is or is not required, I am not competent to judge# The view of leading ahippers is that far from having reached oaturation point| the 3hatt~al~Arab Is only marking at about 30 or 40 per cent of its capacity# If this is correct| and if as I believe to be the caee| His Majesty^767 &gt; Majesty's Government are still owed some £ 170,000 for Basrah Port, a new undertakiAg would appear difficult to justify* I believe, however, that a separate port entirely under Iraqi control, far from.making for more settled conditions would only make them mdre intransigent, and the ideal arrangement, if expert opinion considers that a port can and must* be made, would be for it/under joint British, Iraqi and Kuwaiti control. It should not be impossible to attain this positLom 8 # I am visiting Kuwait on the 17th of March and will take the opportunity to inform the Shaikh of the nature of the Iraq proposals, I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, — P-fl./chn s Telegraic S, 'STom To Political Resident, at Bahrain Government of India, Hew Delhi Repeated Secretary of State for India, London. Copy to His Majesty's Ambassador, Bagdad, and Political Agent, Kuwait. Ho.T/177. Dated the 13th March, 1940. I propose to inform Shaikh of Kuwait confidentially that the Iraq Government have in mind the creation of an emergency port in Khor Abdullah. As soon as proposal assumes a definite shape we will consult him officially as to his views if his interests are affected. This will i hope enable me to discover what Ambassador whom 1 have met at Bahrain agrees to the above. Shaikh's reactions are. - Resident - W.L.7 i W wj- ' ^ Gonfiiential Th^ Pa71 t.i r\xl h^r\c*Y ) {njj D.0.go.g/I05 i 12th. Haroil 1940 Kuwait, BUSH IRE REC'O'ENCY. Date c3;Ma£nt;ai. records' Will you please refer to my deml-official letter rro.C/20 of tiie 16til January, 1940 ? ] 2. It has 'been reported to me on reliable authority that some white painted, posts have 'been stuck into the grounl on ¥arba island. I 'believe these are new posts, and I had hoped to 'be ahle to ask ¥ard what was going on when he was here for a few minutes on the 2nd, 'but did not get the chance. 5. Ihile on the subject, there are two points which I should like to mention concerning this project, and which do not seem to have 'been 'brought out in the corres pondence up to date. One is that any ceding of Kuwait territory will cut into the Kuwait Oil Company *3 concession. Ihether Bubiyan is of interest to the Company or not I don f t know, for the geophysists have not yet heen over the island. The other point is that it is on the Port of Basrah f s survey only'that we are led to 'believe that the channel m.11 T3e in Iraqi waters (c.f. paragraph 3 of Foreign Office letter No.S.7601/55/93 of the 16th Dec ember, 1939). I think: we should accept that survey with suspicion as it is likely to 'be biased. 3. My own opinion is that it will he impossible for the Iraqis to confine their shipping movements to the Iraqi / rble 2Ut .-Col. CJ # G&gt; Prior, C.I.S., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, at Kuwait.Iraai side of the water way, even should they so try. I would, therefore, suggest that if the Iraqis cannot loe induced to drop the scheme, then the question of a survey 'by a joint comission should 'be considered.1 v c Telegrara S F yow Government of Indie, Hew Delhi. To Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Political Resident? at Kuwait. Ho.831 Dated and received 19th March 1940. Your Express Letter Ho.P.Z. 7886/39 16th February. Iraqi port on Khor Abdullah. Me have forwarded by air mail an yfi. - /yo olficial letter from the Political Resident in which he states he feels w ; e should not' be acting in the interests of -tiUY^ait in advising them to cede their interests in a possible port in Khor Abdullah and recommends that line suggested in paragraph 4 of Bagdad Embassy letter Ho.668 of November 14th 1939 should be followed. He expresses some doubt whether a new port is really required but admits he is not competent to judge of this and ends by saying that ideal arrange ment if expert opinion considers that a port can and must be Bsade would be for it to be under joint British Iraqi and Kuwait control. Finally he stresses probable resentmnt of Ibn Saud over concession in area where he feels himself to have underlying interests. Prior is visiting Kuwait on March 17th and will take the opportunity of informing Shaikh confidentially of nature of Iraqi proposals. 3. whilst we are unable to express any opinion /I opinion on whetner a new port is needed by Iraq to supplement Basra we feel strongly that such a port should not infringe on Kuwait territory. As ? pipint to decide ? principle in British interests as distinct from those of Kuwait we are entirely opposed to any ■ territorial cession in tnis quarter. The last 20 years have demonstrated Iraqi fickleness and we should not abet transfer of important point from a Shaikhdom (which with our feet in salt water we can always influence) to a State whose future attitude to the Empire is hard to predict. India will no doubt be called on to find ? forces to meet any threat in this region and is closely interested in maintenance of Kuwait as pied a terre. An Iraqi port on Khor Abdullah would inevitably tend to lessen the importance of Kuwait and might eventually eclipse it altogether. It is important for our position in the Gulf that Kuwait should be stable and free from Iraqi influence. 4. It follows that we are strongly opposed to any attempt being made to coerce the Shaikh of Kuwait into making any concession to the Iraqis. If case is taken with the Shaikh beyond confidential approach made by Prior (and we are averse from raising it) we think it should be made clear that Kis Majesty's Government will observe letter and spirit of third promise given 1*4 to Shaikh in 1914 vide document XLII at page 265-266 of Aitchison Volume XI. 5. A fortiori we should see great objection to /rv n€ to any direct dealing on this question betv;een Kuwait and Iraq in tne manner suggested at one stage by Iraq. 6- Finally we are impressed by ? comment that Ibn Baud in so far as we are in a position to appreciate his views would almost certainly resent Iraqi encroachment in this quarter and would prefer maintenance of Kuwait protectorate unimpaired to expansion of Iraqi influence. We recommend therefore on all grounds that project be dropped and if Iraq need a port they be encouraged to develop it within Iraq as safer course political circumstances ? of ( mut. ). | 1 r Foreign G .T. hi 0 *-Confidential . D.O. No. G/119 J Political Agency, Kuwait, 20tii March, 1940, o BUS?-VRE R ESIDENCY. AV' •. fv/gu-' ^ Dm CJivFiOENUAL RECORDS '■/'.fe' ■ ^ —' ' &lt; Tfill you please refer to Sir Basil Newton's Savingram No. 18 of the 27th February, 1940, on the subject of a port on the Khor AMullah? 2. It occurs to me that this desire to acquire the islands may not he for so hypothetical a reason at all. It is, I 'believe, more than possible that the Iraqis cannot conduct the operations of a port on the Khor AMullah without entering Kuwait waters. The desire to possess the islands on an excuse of defence ( or to meet internal criticism.may only he a blind to cover the facts; the real position being that by obtaining possession of the islands the Iraqis will automatically acquire rights over all the water, thereby achieving their object without admitting the weakness of their position, i.e. that they cannot operate a port without acquiring Kuwaiti waters. 3. I have heard that Sir John has been discussing these very secret plans with an American Missionary in Basra and, unless my memory fails me, has actually shown him plans. I, therefore, saw no harm in mentioning the case to Mr. Jameson when he was here a day or so ago. As I suspected he was fully conversant with the case, and he told me that it is possible that the Company might consider loading oil in the Khor Abdullah, and he thought that Kuwait would be ill advised to give up any of their rights in that area. Ma'ble Lieut-Colonel C.G.Prior, OIE., 'litieal Resident in the Persian Gulf, at Kuwait. i ITelegram From To Repeated S. Political Resident, at Kuwait. Secretary of State for India, London, Government of India, Hew Delhi# His Majesty's Ambassador, Bagdad. Senior Kaval Officer, Persian Gulf. Copy to Political Agent, Kuwait. F0.T/2C9. Bated the 2lst March i94c. ,n My telegram T/l77 March 13th. Khor Abdullah. 2. Another crop of survey marks is reported from Yfarba'* i therefore decided to tackle Shaikh without further delay and found him aware of Iraqi proposals which he viewed with suspicion. 3. He agreed that if project was carried out in Iraq, waters he could not object though he said new port y /ould affect Kuv/ait and draw away population. I enquired what his attitude would be if they asked for any territorial concession. He replied firmly that he would give them nothing at all. 4. I hinted that if large enterprise was at stake they might offer substantial 'assistance* 1 . The Shaikh's face darkened and he said he 'was not Debai or Sharjah and v/ould not sell territory nor did he need money'. All he wanted from Iraq, was that they should keep out of Kuwait. 5. J said that Iraq was interested in port as security measure . he waved this aside and said it was* 'all from Ward'. He could not understand why a British official and 'Sir' should be allowed to act like this. Ward had been behind all the troubles of cutting his date gardens for road and de Gaury and Fowle were aware of this. / 6 *@) -2- 6. As means of discoirery if project can be kept entirely in IraQ. waters he would like Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf to have channel examined by naval officer. • 7. We have only ourselves to thank for not discovering Shaikh's views earlier. Boundary has not been demarcated so we cannot say for certain where frontier runs at crucial point, i think it should be demarcated without delay and in meantime suggest Senior Haval Officer or failing him reliable harbour engineer (Ward who is moving spirit is not engineer)should examine^ project and give us candid opinion as to practicability. g # Ostensible reason given by Ward for new port is to facilitate reinforcements from India. Kuwait already handles large volume of trade including difficult loads for Oil company and has jetty, it could easily disembark military force and is only forty miles further from Basrah by good all weather road than proposed por.t. T&amp;is does not appear to have been considered. ■ - Resident. W.L.Telegram S from Political Resident, at Kuwait. Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Government of India, Hew Delhi. His Majesty*8 Ambassador, Bagdad. Senior Haval Officer, Persian Gulf. \ &lt; s&gt; Copy to Political Agent, Kuwait. Ho.T/2l6 Dated the 21st March 1940, ft* My telegram No .T /209 of March 21st. Knor Abdullah. 2• Jameson director of Anglo-Iranian Oil Company and i ^uwait Oil Company told me very confidentially that Ward had mentioned this project to him and asked if Kuwait Oil Company were interested. He replied that they might wish to use it but could not give definite reply. 3* He urged me to see that Kuwait's rights over this waterway were fully protected as Kuwait Bay had drawbacks and they might'find other cutlet preferable. 4. I have ascertained fard has also discussed project with American missionary at Basra. There appears no reason why he should not show details of project to Senior Haval Officer or failing him reliable harbour enginee who could give us unbiased opinion as to practicability of port and whether it can be made without infringing Kuwait territory. Engineer could easily be obtained without un due publicity from Alexandria Karachi or Bombay. 5. Wf should also endeavour to ascertain through him facts about necessity for new port. I apprec iate this is mainly matter for I-ran u raq Government bu t we have i- m) i?* TeXegr&amp;n From To Repeated Inter • Senior Faval Officer, Persian Gulf# Commander in Cliief, Bast Indies. No.705 Political Resident, Bushire. (HB Ho.0815 Z Dated 24tii received 25th Maxell 1940. b 1''° Political Resident*s telegrams Kos. 1/209 and. T/210 are 'being passed to you for inform ation. priTate letter of 17tlx March, addressed to you care flag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Havy, Bombay, refers. 2. I agree with. Political Resident's suggestion that naval authority, in which Shaikh of Kuwait has confidence, and/or qualified harbour engineer should he consulted officially on possib ilities of Khor Abdullah and harbour of Kuwait as alternative. Although in first instance the matter is a political issue I must warn you that in my judgment if hole and corner methods pursued up to now are continued any chance of accommodation between the two States and therefore the utilization of Khor Abdullah as a point of disembarkation may be jeopardized. Senior Maval Officer G.T. w- ft-i / if.Lfi-o. fa'- 5 4 ■ M MCONFIDENTIAL . No. 86-3 of 1940. (gp m' The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Senior Naval Officer, Perelan Gulf, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRB. Dated. ^/Y agi&amp;'Mftfoii' -mo.' y£(i &amp; ?A7-: Reference to previous correspondence: Senior Haval Officer Persian Gulf'e telegram 3TO.0815 Z of 24th March 1940. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. As fer list attached* Subject. Proposed Iraqi port on the Khor AbdullahList of enclosures to Residency Printed Letter No.86^-3 of the 26th March, 1940• f. Bagdad despatch Ho.503 of 6th September 1939 to the Foreign Office^ London. 2. Bagdad letter (30/13/39) of 26th September 1939 to the Eastern Department,, foreign Office, London^with /enoloQure 3. Bagdad despatch Ko.668 of l4th Koyember 1939 to the Foreign Office, London. 4. foreign Office letter So.E.7601/58/93 of the 16th December 1939 to the India Office. 5. India Office Express Letter No .IP. Z. 7886/39 of 11th January 1940. 6. Demi-official let No.G/93 of the 8th February 1940 to R.T.jPeel Esquire, The India Office, London. t(,i' 7. Bagdad despatch Ho.72 (205/4/40) of the 16th February 1940 to the Foreign Office, London. 8. Bagdad telegram No.l8/Saving of the 27th February 1940 to the Foreign Office, London. W.L.l053/630/|3 FOREIGN OFFICE, s.wa. 16th ilarch, 1940. Sir f With reference to Foreign Office letter E 7601/58/93 of the 16th Deoemter I am directed 'by Viscount Halifax to transmit to you, herewith, for the information of the Marquess of Zetland, the accompanying copies of a further despatch and telegram from His Majesty's Embassador at Bagdad regarding the proposed construction 'by the Iraqi Government of a new port on the Khor Vbdullah, 2, It will 'be seen that the Iraqi Government have again raised this question on two occasions, and that in speaking to General Nuri, Sir Basil Newton held out no hope that it would be possible to arrange for the surrender of any territory to Iraq 'by Koweit, 3 # Whether it would 'be likely to prove prejudicial to British interests that Iraq should obtain sole control of the Khor Vbdullah is a question which was discussed in some detail in paragraphs 16 to 21 of Mr. Baggallay f s semi-official letter E 5116/58/93 to Mr. Jarrett at the Admiralty, of the 5th August last. For the reasons given in that letter Lord Halifax is inclined to doubt whether, in the event of a breach in the present close relations between The Under-Secretary of State, India Office.4. •between His Majesty's Government and the Iraq.! Government, the retention 'by the Sheikh of Koweit of his present rights in the waterway would be of any particular advantage to His Majesty's Government, though it might of course prove useful to the Sheikh himself. On the other hand, any attempt on the part of His Majesty's Government to make use of Koweiti rights in the waterway to exert pressure on the Iraqi Government would 'be likely to prejudice relations between the Sheikh and Iraq, and would not therefore be in the former's interest. Lord Halifax feels, therefore, that apart from the general consideration, that it would probably, on the long view, make for more stable conditions in that part of the world in the future if Iraq, as the State which controls the Mesopotamian plain, had the undivided control of at least one good means of access to the sea, His Majesty's Government should treat this problem strictly on its merits: that is to say, in the light of their obligations to Iraq, as our ally, on the one hand, and to Koweit as a protected State, on the other. If their judgement is influenced by attempts to maintain a strategical hold over one territory or the other in circumstances which cannot now be foreseen, the consequences may recoil upon them in some totally unexpected manner and lead to trouble which the adoption of a different course might h^ve ^voided,4, These and the connected questions c^n, however, 'be considered further when the views of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and of the Government ~ t ilk* of India are received on Sir Basil Newton f s despatch of the 14th November last, 5 Copies of this letter are 'being sent to the \dmiralty, War Office, Ur Ministry, Colonial Office, Board of Trade, Ministry of Shipping, Petroleum department and Offices of the War Cabinet^ I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, fSd.) LACY EAGGALLAY■SBCRET. B!JSH'RE RESIDEiNCY M 0 t j tjb;. H*- ko • CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS' NO.0561/ME. Office of the Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf. 5th April, 1940. ft ^ Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge gratefully the receipt of your letter N0.86 -S of 1940 dated 26th March 1940, forwarding me copies of letters in connection with the proposed Iraqi port on the Khor Abdullah. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient servant. £ ^mv. CAPTAIN SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER PERSIAN GULF. Hon. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. BUSHIRE.(g) Telegram G.T.C From Political Resident, Bushire Politicg.1 ^ent, Kuwait. To ISQ.teZ Dated the 15th April 1940# It is understood-Barpeta has over 1000 tons cargo for Kuwait. Please let me know by mail length of time taken to discharge it. BritconsulPolitical Agency, Kuwait, 18th April, 1940 ip Will you please refer to your telegram // - tp No. 162 of the 15th April, 1940? tons made up of 10,474 'bags of rice, 1,100 'bags of coffee ana 715 paoKa^es ox general cargo. She arrived at a'bout 11 a.m on the 16th, 'but as she was a'bout 5 hours before her scheduled time she did not start unloading until a'bout 1 p.m. The cargo was evenly distributed in the holds, from one of which about 450 'bags were unloaded in one hour, making a total of ahout 10 hours work. The unloading was finished in the middle of the night and the ship sailed at dawn. There was almost a dead calm for the time sh^ was here. 2 The w Barpeta' carried for Kuwait 987 le Hon'TDle Lieut-Colonel C.G. Prior, C Political Resident in the Persian Gf Bushire , CIE., n Gulf, ^. n/s; Telegram s V* 01 ® Political Resident, Bushire. To Secretary of State for India, London Repeated Government of India, Simla. Copy by post Ambassador, Bagdad. Senior Haval Officer, Persian Gulf. Ho.207 Bated the 26th April 1940. /9w My telegram iro.T/209 dated 21st March paragraph 8. KHOR ABDULLAH» 2* On 16th April Barpeta unloaded over 1000 tons cargo in ten hours. Enquiries show that Kuwait is considered quickest port in Gulf for handling cargo. Britconsul l iM u VL-vJbt*-P.u./Vo-ii'-S ^|, iJbjLijyo AjjC ,. ■I 05/b7-ll ft 23. India Office P.2.6809/38, d/-7-10-38. iww—mmiinTimwiii File? Id* 3/11 Id.J.C. 3/11 Id.A.C.G. 4o 11. Id. T.G.S 1 . 4/11. in &gt;0 ■ ! 24. India Office P.L.P.Z.7S5t&gt;/^, d/-31.10.3b. —— File ? ' c Id. 15/11. Copy ms been sent to Kuwait. May be filed? P.R . As suggested pi.? Id. A.C.Q. 19.11. Id.N.I. 15/11. P.B . Tne facts summarised wnicn give rise to tne nationality question are tnat uas tr, born in Kuwait of Kuwaiti parents, but wJao purchased property in Iraq in 1925 and lived on it from tnat date, was called up for Iraqi military service. It appears tnat Nasir is registered in Kuwait as a Kuwaiti, ana in Iraq as an Iraqis tne question is wnat is Jilasir's nationality? Tne main point stands out clearly and tnat is tnat ne was Kuwaiti and still must De in our view, but nas ne by residence in Iraq become an Iraqi according to Iraqi Law? Tnis is tne only issue, ana it is lor tne Iraq Government to prove it. Tne Iraq Government nave been told tnat Iraqi and Kuwaiti nationality botn came into being on tne same date. Tnis being so tne Iraqis cannotsy s ; cannot correctly state iu tue proof tuey seeJ£ tuat tae nationality of tne parents of Sasir bears on tne question, for the latter cannot possible nave been lr Iraqis as there was no Iraq before - at tne earliest date - say 1922. 'ffiorer^Tnere was a practically autonomous Kuwait long before that date. The Treaty of Lou|sanne does not affect the question ot nationality as that Treaty limited boundaries only as from a certain date i© e. 1924, and did not concern itself witn tne nationality of the people subsequent to tne delineation of the frontier. THe probablity is that Haslr is of dual Kuwaiti- Iraqi nationality. P.R. — fr-cK^ p cry Perhaps P.A. Koweit will send his comments without being asked, if they are not in this mail may send a brief telegram requesting them? 25. H. 38 &lt;U:</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000202_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/541</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000202</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/541</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 53/87 II (D 152) British Policy in Kuwait'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-28T11:04:17</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (213 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.Circled index numbers written in blue crayon can also be found throughout the volume and refer to the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Condition: A bound correspondence volume.Foliation: The file's foliation sequence commences at the title page and terminates at the last page of text; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A second foliation sequence is present between ff 3-193; these numbers are written in pencil and blue crayon, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding British policy in Kuwait.Much of the correspondence relates to a proposal for the construction of an Iraqi-controlled port in Kuwaiti territory that would be linked to Basra by rail.The file also contains correspondence regarding the international status of Kuwait and discussions regarding an attempt by Nasir bin Ali as-Subah [Nāṣir bin ‘Alī Āl Ṣabāḥ], a member of the Al Sabah family resident in Iraq, to avoid serving as a conscript in the Iraqi army.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000202#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>