<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000128_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T03:31:22.511Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">P' v- / © Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES HEAD OFFICE : 122, LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON. E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH AMA RA H KUT KHORAMSHAHR Ahwaz BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DU BA I SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE L / 147. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Bahreinj ilth March, 19 45. The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, n / 3 I &lt; 2 .. ^ . us iM ^ INDIAN STAFF A GREEMENTS . We have been advised by our Basrah office that we are in future to have our Indian Staff sign agreements prior to their departure on leave, which agreements are to signed in your presence. We enclose herev/ith a copy of trie agreement and shall be glad to know if you will be agreeable to countersigning same especially in regard to clause 13 of this agreement. Yours faithfully, For GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; Co., Ltd Manager,flDemoranbum of Horeement ma ae o„ the between GRAY MACKENZIE &amp; CO. LTD.. called the COMPANY” of the one part and . ^hereinafter called the u EMPLOYEE ” of the other part whereby it is agreed as follows :— (1) The Company hereby engages the employee and the employee hereby agrees to serve the Company as a in connection with the operations of the Company in Iran, Iraq, and/or Persian Gulf for the period o f years from the date of his engagement in India and during such time the employee shall be under and shall obey the orders of his superior Officers in the employment of the Company. {2) The employee shall proceed to the Persian Gulf and shall serve the Company in any part of that country, Iraq and/or Iran as the Company may direct and when ordered to do so shall move from place to place either by land or by water. The Company shall provide for the employee when travelling on business of the Company by land the necessary horse or mule transport free of charge and by water second with a ■ class passage to his destination and in either case with free food or an allowance of Rs. 3 per day in lieu of food at the option of the employee. / (3) The Company shall provide for the employee free passage from the place of recruitment in India to Iraq, Iran or Persian Gulf and shall supply him during the journey with food or an allowance of Rs. 3 a day in lieu of food at the option of the employee. Passage means, for journeys by train, second secoivd a t j v i r( i class ticket; for journey by sea or river a ■ class passage. (4) Provided that the employee shall perform his duties diligently and to the satisfaction of the Company and shall observe all the conditions of this AGREEMENT, he shall receive a salary at the rate of Rs. i . such salary to be paid at the latest on the 16th day of the month succeeding that in which it was earned. The salary of the employee shall commence from the date on which he is engaged in India and except in the event of his dismissal or as is stated in clause 10 read with clause 11 shall cease on the date of his return to the place of his recruitment. ( 5) The employee shall be entitled during illness or other forced illness to a minimum wage of not less than half of the monthly pay on which he is engaged. (6) The employee shall be entitled to free medical attendance and free accommodation or an adequate allowance in lieu of free quarters. (7) The employee is prohibited from trading of any sort or kind during the currency of this agreement.4 -f \ I * l 2 (8) In the event of the employee becoming incapable to perform this agreement through ill-health brought on through cause beyond his own control his employment with the Company shall ipso facto determine. The Company shall be bound to repatriate the employee at the earliest convenient date after determi nation of his employment and to provide free passage and food or food allowance for the period of the journey in the manner provided in clause 3 and shall pay him his full salary up to the date of his arrival at the place of recruitment in India. The state of the health of the employee for the purposes of this and clause 9 shall be notified by the Company’s Medical Officer whose certificates shall be final and binding on both parties. ( 9 ) In the event of the said employee becoming incapacitated through illness brought on by causes within his control as to which the decision of the Medical Officer referred to in clause 8 and as therein provided shall be final or wilfully committing a breach of any of the conditions of this agreement or being guilty of gross misconduct or insubordination it shall be lawful for the Company to dismiss the employee with of; without notice his salary terminating from the date of such dismissal but the Company shall repatriate the employee in the manner provided in clause 3 without prejudice to any claim that they may have against him for debt or damage. (10) The Agreement shall remain in force for not more than three years from the date of engagement in India and is renewable by mutual consent of the contracting parties. The Company has the right to terminate the agreement at any time by giving the employee one month’s notice or one month’s salary in lieu of notice. The Employee has the right to terminate the Agreement by giving the Company one month’s notice but should his length of service in Persian Gulf, Iran and/or Iraq not amount to twelve months service in the Persian Gulf, Iran and/or Iraq he shall not be entitled to receive from the Company more than his salary for the period of notice or the cost of the return passage to India by the class to which he V would otherwise be entitled, whichever is greater. (11) If the employee shall desire to return to India on the termination of his employment with the Company the Company shall repatriate the employee in the manner laid down in clause 8 and unless he has been dismissed under ’clause 9, or if the agreement has been terminated under clause 10 shall pay his full salary up to the date of his arrival at the place of his-recruitment in India, provided that the employee avails himself of such means of return to India when required to do so after the determination of his employment. (12) No employee shall have right of remaining in the Company’s premises after the determination of his employment. If he does not avail himself of the passage offered to him by the Company at the first convenient opportunity after such determination he shall forfeit his claim to salary (if any) repatriation and food or food allowance during the period of the journey. (13) If any difference or dispute shall arise as to the true intent of this agreement or any part there of or in any way connected with or arising out of the same, the decision of which is not herein before provided for, the matter shall be submitted to the arbitration of the Officer-in-Charge of H. B. M.’s Consular Duties for or if he is not willing to act then■w 3 to that of such nearest Officer of the British Government exercising judicial powers or the Officer- in-Charge H. B. M/s Consular Duties for as he shall appoint and the decision of such officer on the point shall be final and conclusively binding on both parties. (14) No part of any fees or taxes paid or to be paid to any Government in respect of the emigration from, and return to, India or the entry into and return from the country of employment of the employee or his dependents shall be borne by, or recovered from, the employee directly or indirectly by deduction from his remuneration or otherwise howsoever. IN WITNESS whereof the parties of this Agreement have set their respective hands on the day and year first mentioned above. Signed and Delivered on Behalf of the said, GRAY MACKENZIE &amp; CO. LTD., Signed and delivered In the presence of 0 Signed by the said employee In the presence of PROTECTOR OF EMIGRANTS BOMBAY.Employee’s Name. Father’s Name. Name and Address of next of Kin, showing relationship with the employee. Designation. Salary per month. Allowances if any should be shown separately. Height. Age. Nationality and Caste. Distinguishing marks. Period of agreement. Date of appointment. Class of passage provided. Remarks.No. lolfl- 16/50. A Political Agency, The 19th March, Bahrain, 1945. To Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, Please refer to your letter No.L.147 dated the 11 th March 1945 regarding Indian staff agreements. 2. Under Article 12 the empl/yee is held to forfeit his claim to repatriation if he does not avail himself of a passage offered to him. By this I presume is meant 'repat riation at the expense of the Company' and I shall be glad if you will donfirm that the Company will at all times be responsible for meeting the cost of repatriation of its Indian employees. 3. There is no article in the memorandum of agreement which provides for compensation in cases of disability from injury arising out of or sustained during employment. I.consider provision for this should be made and suggest the inclusion of an article to read as follows:- 'Compensation will be paid in all cases of disability from injury (Including occupational disease and death; when the injury shall proximately cause death) arising out of and sustained ih the course of employment and in determining the amount of such compensation the Company will be guided by the Workmen^ Compensation Act in India and in no event shall the Company be liable for the payment of compensation in excess of that provided in said Act for a disability of the nature suffered by employee.' The above is a replica of Article 7 of the Foreign Service Agreement in force in the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. 4. You may wish to include the words 'or by air' after 'by water” at the end of the first sentence of article 2 . You also may desire to provide a more up to date means of transport than 'horse or mule”. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain.Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND! s HEAD OFFICE : 122. LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON. E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE bentley’s second phrase code BRANCHES: BUSREH AMARAH KUT KHORAMSHAH R AH WAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DU BA I SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE no. L/355* Bahrein.., 26 th May., 19 45. ( f \ \ * The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear sir, Referring to 19th March, commenting on clerical staff agreements we should perhaps point out that the form of agreement sent you has been drawn up by the Protector of Emigrants Bombay, and it is not in our power to make any alterations. As far as we know this form of agreement has been in force for many years. M. Co We require to know if you are prepared, in the terms of clause 13, to act as arbitrator in the event of any dispute £ We look forward to hearing from you in this connection at an early date. lours faithfully, For GRAY, MACKENZIE A Co., Ltd. / BaW’a Receipt ' your letter No.1067-16/50.A of * W f( 2 ) r -3SS? No. 2249-16/50. A. To Political Agency 9 Bahrain, The 31st May, 1945. © Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, . p ^ Reference your letter No. 1/355 dated the 26th May, 1945. 2. The answer to your question is in the affirmative* Yours faithfully, J for Political Agent, Bahrain,Bahrein. 23 rd Bebruary,1949. The M&amp;nagpr The Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., B a h r e i n t Respected Sir, as under; i^e the empoyees of your Company wish to request 1* We thank you for your irmreaaament given to us all. 2. The increment given to the employees is not according to the Jtules fixed bythe H|B|M»S.Political Agent,Bahrein. 3. The monthly payment rules fixed for the starting Clerk Qtt the Political Agency is fts.200/-/- Basic,Dearness Allowance Rs.110/-/- and House Rent Rs, 50/-/-(Single), House Rent Rs.70/-/- (Married) and every body is enjoying the same right equally.with them. 4* The present times are very hard and also gone very high even after War. The cost of lining for we Foreigners is gone to extreme and the Dearness Allowance given to us is not sufficient and veiy less than the Rules fixed by the Political Agency,Bahrein. 5* Regarding House Allowance we have to say that one cannot get a house for ahuman being to live in, on Rs. 50/-/- per month, as allowed to us by the Company and which is very unfair. In case of a single-man it is air ight to live two or three together in one house and pass a time* But it is v®ry impossible for a married-man with his family,to get a house,in these days on Rs.50/-/- per month. Therefore we request your honour to do JUSTIC E and be fair to grand your married Staff, the sum of Rs.70/-/-, accord!ng the orders of the H.B.M’S.Political Agency,which is some how to the point. 6. The above mentioned Terms fixed by the H.B.M*S.Political Agency are for the FOREIGNERS on the island, whether they are Locally engaged or come Trom outside. will be done in our case to save ourselves from difficulty and allow us to live a Human life. We put this humble application with a hope that justice We beg to remain,Sir, Tours most Obediently. Empiloyees of The G.M.&amp; Co. Ltd. Bahrein. cc. The H.B.M’S,Political Agent,Bahrein. ^ The India &amp; Pakistan Governments, India,Pakistan.V The Manager, The Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., Bahrein. \ 7 ' x. Bahrein. 10th March 1949. I ' ■ ■ ' Respected Sir, Refs Revision in the Scale of Dearness Allowance and House Rent. We have send you a humble petition on 23rd February 49, for the necessary revision to be made in our Scale,according to the orders of The H.B. M’S.Political Agent,Bahrein and should be allowed with a will,to enjoy the same rights, as alreacfy enjoyed by Agency &amp; Residency Staff,cn the island. The change from January 49,in the scale fixed for a starting Clerk with you is Rs*200#-/- Basic,Rs. 70 /-/-&lt;mly Dearness Allowance &amp; House Rent Rs.SO/-/- for Single &amp; Married both,which is not equivalent to the times and unjust. lou must remember,we all are Foreigners on this island and the * island itself is dependent in all respects on foreigns.Therefore the cost of living for us all is always very high and it is still getting worst. The Landlords of Bahrein are always trying their level best with a sharpen Knife in the hand to take the advantage of hard times and cut throats of poor Foreign Goats very easily, by increasing House Rents to Hundred Percent and even more than that. Foreigners putting such complains to The H.B.M*S.Political Agency are all go in vain.They are neither getting any reply nor have seen compalsary steps taken against,to stop mischief played by wealthy landlords of Bahrein. Hence it looks very urgent and needful,to think over again,with a open heart and allow the Terms &amp; Conditions of Agecy,to your foreign staff which are however to some point,to live at least a human life and work with^ an interest for your Company. At last,we request you to do needful and shall see that Justice is given to us at an early date. We beg to remain,Sir, lours Most Obediently. Employees of The G.M.&amp; Co.Ltd*,Bahrein. cos- The H.B.M’S.Political Agent,Bahrein. The India &amp; Pakistan Governments,India,Pakista#-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000128_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1561</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000128</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1561</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 16/50 A Conditions of employment of Indian staff in Messrs Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Company.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-15T22:08:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (10 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 10-11) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 12; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-7; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Two sets of correspondence between the Political Agency in Bahrain and the Bahrain office of Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Company, both relating to the rights and employment terms for Indians employed by Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Company in Bahrain. The first set of correspondence is dated 1945, and relates to an employment agreement devised by Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Company, with discussion focussing on repatriation costs at the end of employment, and compensation in cases of disability arising from injury at work (ff 2-7).The second set of correspondence comprises two letters dated 1949, sent by employees of Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Company to their employer (with copies also sent to the Political Agent at Bahrain, and to the Governments of India and Pakistan) complaining that a recent wage increment is not in line with terms established by the Bahrain Political Agency on pay for foreigners in Bahrain (ff 8-9).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited, shipping agents</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Conditions of employment</topic></subject><subject><topic>Labour disputes</topic></subject><subject><topic>Migrant workers</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000128#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>