<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001b6_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T11:03:17.181Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">ill /K-! t&amp;f - ■ . MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE IORNEG■GONFI D^NTI ;\L « No. C/ 253. vD 1 Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate, j Muscat, the 28th August 1939. w: From / jtt) &lt;*-9-39 To Captain T. Hickinbotham, O.B.E., Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. The Hobble the Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRS . Sir, I have the honour to re£er1? to my demi-official letter of 22nd August 1939 No.' C/248 and to enclose a copy of a letter No. 320 dated the 23rd August 1939 which I have received from Kis Highness the Sultan. 2. I understand that the Bombay Mint are prepared to undertake the work at His Highness's expense provided permission is granted by the Government of India. 3. I request that the Government of India may be approached and asked to authorise the Bombay Mint to under take the work. Khan Bahadur Ahmed Shubaili will act for His Highness in such transactions as there may be with the Bombay Mint. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Captain,I,A., Political Agent &amp; H.B.M 1 s Consul, Muscat.-v Copy in translation of letter No. 320 dated the 23rd August 1939 from His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman to Captain T. Hickinbotham. O.B.S., His Britannic Majesty^ Consul, Muscat. Reference our conversation with you on the 22nd August 1939 on the subject of minting a new nickel and other sorts of currency at Muscat. I shall be grateful if you will inform our friend the Government of India about our decision for minting a quantity of the new currency v/hich we intend to introduce in the country and request them to issue orders to the Superinte ndent of His Majesty's Mint at Bombay to mint the amount that may be asked for by Khan Bahadur Ahmed Shubaili on our behalf who is now residing in Bombay, and whom we have appointed asr 5 ccMMDsrrm . From To Offlot of tho Politlcal .Rtsideat in thi Ptrsian Gulf, Canp# Baiarain# The Hon* bit the Political Rtaident in the Persian Uulf» Cjc The Secretary to the Oovernment of India» SxternaX Affairs Department, Simla* Copy to Political Agent, Muecat. Memorandum 5o«C/423 of 1939* Dated the 17th September, 1939* Subjeoti Minting of currency for Muscat State* Copy of letter Ho»C/263, dated the 28th August 1939, with enclosure, from Political Agent, Muscat, is tnolosedU 2« It is requested that the Bombay Mint may be authorised to undex take work* sd. C.G, PRIOR* Political Resident in th» Persian Gulf* Attested* i c An-in for Secretary t o th for S^retary t o the political Resident in the Persian Gulf* V■ i ■ £From - Jhe Deputy Secretary to the u overlSment of India in the SxtemsiL Affairs Department, To - The Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memo random No # D-3629-N/39 # / Dated New Delhi, the October 1939 # SUBJECT :- Minting of currency for Muscat State, Reference your memorandum No # G/423, dated the 17th September 1939 # 2 # It has been arranged that the work will be undertaken at the Bombay Mint at suitable charges. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat may kindly be asked to instruct his Bombay representative to get into touch with the Mint Master, Bombay, giving full details of the coinage required. It is presumed that the Muscat State wi supply the metal for the coins # Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. i ^ • iff)'C/jrilfr ^CONFIDENTTAL. -u ^3 Ho No. C/738 of 1939, The Hon'bio the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Muscat, qc and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documentsfcj^. for necessary action. J 1 ' British Consulate-General, BUSH1RE. Camp, Ku wait. Dated ...l^tli. November, 1939 Reference to previous correspondence : Political Resident^ liemorandum Ko«C/423 of the 17th September,1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Memorandum No»D.3529-N/39 of the 24th October 1939 from the Government of Inc. External Affairs Departmen Subject. ia, t. Minting of currency for Muscat State.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001b6_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/465</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001b6</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/465</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Minting of currency in Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-18T15:12:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (6 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence is written in pencil, in the top right corner of the recto of each folio. It begins with the first item of correspondence, on number 1, and ends on the last folio of writing, on number 6.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence includes a letter from Saiyid Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr], Sultan of Muscat and Oman to Captain Tom Hickinbotham, Political Agent Muscat, requesting the minting of a new nickel and other sorts of currency at Muscat. Khan Bahadur Ahmed Shubaili, was appointed as an agent on the matter. Charles Geoffrey Prior, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, wrote to the Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla, requesting that the Bombay Mint may be authorised to undertake this work. Correspondents include Captain Tom Hickinbotham; Political Agent and HBM's Consul, Muscat; Charles Geoffrey Prior, Political Resident, Persian Gulf; Saiyid Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr], Sultan of Muscat and Oman.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Currencies</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001b6#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>