<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00029c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T05:59:57.491Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">FILE NO: F/6. Papers regarding the supply of ice by the Municipality to the Agency Staff.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN D.O. No. 490/8 August S, 1935. * ,' v v&gt; &lt;\v\V .y ■ * ^ Dear Cole, f I enclose a letter from the Secretary of the Man amah municipal council complaining that yesterday the ice cart was stopped and ice was taken from it forcibly by people belonging to the Agency. I had previously written to the Muni cipality telling them that your staff were to be allowed to buy the amount which you mentioned in your letter. 1 have just informed the Navy that we cannot supply any ice at all as there is a shortage. Yours sincerely, -v Caotain C.iuCole, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain.© 10th August 1935. Please refer to your deni-oiiioial letter Ho.490/8 dated the 9th August 1230. I have enquired hut cannot trace the aalefactors, nor did the police guari ohserre the occurrence. Could veu the non #io made the complaint come to the Agency and point out the persons rfio stopped them .orcioly? v - C(. A \ •&gt; C * deviser to^h^Bahre in^ovemnoat, ixUV Bahrain# /* mGOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. August 21, 1935. Dear Cole, The person who stopped the ice cart is reported to be your head farrash, Mohomed Shahdad. Yours sincerely, Captain G. A. Cole, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain.Statement of Muhammad Shahdad, Farraeh ^ashi, Political agency,Bahrain. The contractor usee to give me two ana a half blocks of ice for the Agency Staff. On 6th A ugust 1935, the servent of the contractor( i lo not know hia name&gt; who was in-charge of tne cart gave me two blocks only. I tola him that accoruxng to tne arran~juents x^e shoula givt me two ana a hall blocks. He torn me that he x^aa not had oraers from the contractor to give me more than two blocks, so he left the two blocks and went away. I ibia him tnat if he was not giving me two and a naif blocks he had better wait until tae Head Clerk comes ana speak to xxim about it, but he aiu not wait. 1 afinot stop the cart or interfere with it. 22na august 1935 L.T.f.of muhammaa SnahaaaTranslation of letter No.26/3/1357 aateci 24th July 1938 from the Secretary, Manamah Balaaiyah, to the Heau Clerk, Political . i | Agency, Bahrain. — hi V 3- A.C., To-day I have noticed your orders to^ the Baladiyah that you want 75 lbs of ice daily instead of 30 lbs., for the Agency Staff. This quantity is not small as I understand you get ice from the Jabal daily. Last year and the year before last no such request was made on behalf of the Staff. No other Government Office made such a request on behalf of their staff. Every one gets ice like others. As ice in Bahrain is not sufficient for the needs of the public, the Baladiyah cannot supply you with such a big quantity. U.E. UuL^A. &lt;*- VttCC iV' \uu&gt; hw. -4 - Hyt UCC,D.0.NO.222-F/6. The 28th July 1»38. Dear de Grenier, For some years now arrangements, which were made between Beigrave and Cole, have been in force by which this Agency Office has been able to obtain from 1£ to 2 blocks of ice daily for its personnel. For some reason the Secretary to the Manamah Baladiyeh has now written refusing to supply this and I should be much obliged if you would issue the necessary instructions to ensure that the previous practice continues. 2. It is a matter of considerable surprise to me that the Baladiyeh should have adopted such an attitude towards the Agency. Yours sincerely, C.C.L.de Grenier, Esquire, Acting Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. August 3, 193 In renly to your D.u. 140.3^3-1/0 of the 28th July, it is reported to me that no record exists nere of any arrangement having been made for the preferential supply of ice daily to the personnel of tne Agency Staff. 2. from enquiries I have made, it appears that in 1935 your present nead Clerk suggested to Captain Cole that mr ijelgrave should be re quested to ask the Manamah ijaladian to permit him to draw direct from tne Ice plant 1J to 2 blocks of ice daily for the personnel, to save the trouble of purchasing same at the Baladiah Ice shop where the demana is so great in the hoi weather that seven or eight police and a Havil- dar are daily required to control the crowd. The Baladiah Secretary was unable to do this, in fairness to other purchasers; but he arranged for one block of ice (56 lbs; to be issued from the Ice Plant as an act of courtesy t o your staff, for that season. 3. In 1936 and in 1937 ice was purchased by your personnel at the Ice Shop according to their needs and the quantity available. 4. The capacity of the Ice Plant is one ton in the morning and one ton in the afternoon. The sales in the hot weather could easily amount to five or six tons per day if tne Baladiah were able to satisfy all demands; but at present tne sales have to be adjusted in the hope of giving all purchasers a reasonable quantity; e.g. some of tne leading families can only buy between twenty and tnirty pounds of ice a day. 5. I understand, however, that your Head Clerk, having failed to obtain a supply of five blocks per day from the Banco, requested the Baladiah to supply him It to 2 blocks a day direct from the Ice plant. The Baladiah oecretary replied tnat he could not do this, in fairness other customers; but sanctioned the supply of one olocA per day direct from the Ice Plant. 6. I trust you will agree that tne situation has been treated as fairly as possible in this heat wave, and therefore the suggestion in parag raph 2 of your note does not arise. H. Weightman nsquire, I.C.3., Political Agent, Bahrain.^.-n, ^ &gt; A. i*v t \ il D.O. Letter No. 49C/8 datea tne 9tJa august X9oO from Mr. Belgrave. By a mutual arrangement tne contractor very kindly delivers the ice for the Agency wnile passing I enroute to the bazaar and this arrangement nus wonted^ smoothly from the time we^started getting ice. J All the ferrashes and Police state that they know nothing and that none of them is guilty of any xrtxdsxs misconduct in this regard. Until the date you were icmd enough to wriue to the Adviser about our ice we were getting Zf Dlocics a day (the extra blocx issued to P.A’s stall was being continued to the Agency by arrangement between Mr. Steele and Mr. Metcalfe). Since tnen we are being issued with 2 blocxs daily. It will thus be seen that in actual fact we are getting less ice - not more as alleged. May I suggest that the Municipal Council oe requested to issue two blocks ( reierence your letter to Mr. Belgrave) and not 94 pounds (wuicn is less tnau two blocks), as it is very diliicult to aistrioute the ice among so many of tne Stall. Issued (d.o.) letter dated the 10th August i9bo to Mr. Belgrave. Letter (d. o.) dated the 21st August 1955 from M*. C. Palrymple Belgrave. The statement of Muh^mmed Shahdad is atuacned.I £ vH3 % Qcidutitj lbs Lbs Lbs Lbs Lbs Lbs Lbs Ux Lbs Lbs Lbs Lbs\Lbs\Lbs ==s=s^=sr * wmmmmmm* * 1</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00029c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1933</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00029c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1933</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File F/6 'Papers Regarding the Supply of Ice by Municipality to the Agency Staff'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-10T23:21:42</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (86 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 42; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 4-14; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains an exchange of letters and documentation between the Manama Municipality and the Political Agency in Bahrain on a dispute arising from the supply of ice to the Municipality during 1935. Subsequent to letters with complaints by the Agency about the Municipality's staff appropriating of ice without permission, the file contains a number of papers and tables regarding the supply of ice and costs associated with it.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Manamah Municipality</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Ice</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00029c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>