<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002bb_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T07:48:30.225Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Previous File : ; Next File: No. File General Heading POLITICAL (EXTERNAL) DEPARTMENT COLLECTION Sub-head Notes: YEAR. 1939 . P.Z. This File contains the following papers :— 1 (Sfp. 19 P.Z. 19 P.Z. 19 P.Z. 19 P.Z. 19 P.Z. 19 P.Z. 19 P.Z. Papers may be removed from or placed within this File only by the Political Registry.CONFIDENTIAL C.B. 1892 (PLANS) ARABIA, INTELLIGENCE REPORT % STATE OF REPORT, DATED OCTOBER, 1941 Note .—The following applies to holders of Copy Nos. 1-125 only. This State of Report is identical in regard to plans, with , that issued with Notification No. 9, dated February, 1940, and is issued with the New Folder for plans only. The plans are to be transferred to the New Folder, which now becomes C.B. 1892 (PLANS). The State of Report dated February, 1940, is to be destroyed. The text of this Intelligence Report has now been issued as C.B. 1892 (X). Plan No. Title. Date. For use when mustering. tla r Feb., 1932 tlb 1 flc f ARABIA—General map in 4 sheets .. .. &lt; Feb., 1932 Feb., 1932 tldj l Feb., 1932 2 ARABIA—General map, showing communications, Jan., 1937 ' etc. 3 HODEIDA—View from S.E Feb., 1932 4 FUWWAH—Plan of landing ground .. Jan., 1933 5 MUKALLA and Environs—Plan of .. Jan., 1937 6 MUKALLA WHARF—Plan of Jan., 1933 7 MUKALLA Anchorage—Views of Feb., 1932 8 AKABA AND SHIHAIR landing ground—Views of.. Jan., 1937 9 SHARMA—Plan of . . Jan., 1933 10 RAIDAH and District—Plan of Jan., 1933 11 DOHA (A1 Bida) HARBOUR—Plan of Jan., 1937 12 SALALAH—Views of Feb., 1932 13 MURBAT BAY—Plan of Jan., 1933 14 MURBAT AND KHOR RORI—Views of .. Feb., 1932 15 BAHRAIN ISLAND—Plan of Jan., 1937 16 MANAMAH—Plan of Port and Town .. Jan., 1933 17 KHOR KALIYA—Plan of Naval Base Jan., 1937 18 KHOR KAWI—-Plan of Naval Base .. Jan., 1937 19 KHOR KAWI—Views of Jan., 1937 20 KUWAIT—Plan of Jan., 1937 21 MUSCAT AND MATRAH—Plan of Jan., 1937 22 JEDDA—Plan of Port .. Jan., 1937 * SYMBOLS CHART (referring to Plans dated prior to 1927 Jan., 1936). SYMBOLS CHART (referring to Plans dated Jan., 1936 1936, and later). * Not issued with Copy Nos. 126-375. •(•Not issued with Copy Nos. 363-375. (C 43041) 375 11/41SECRET. 6388/M.1.2. . Dear f\V.€. The War Office, ^ * WhitehiljQ / { SWI - X5t,li Iwav-oh^— In confirmation of our telephone conversation; can you arrange with the Admiralty for the issue to G,S. 'I 1 * at A.H.Q. , India, of a copy of Admiralty secret publication C.B. 1892 - ‘’Military Report on Arabia”? Para. 3 of Colonel Henderson’s d/o letter No. 42162/M.I.1. of 9th February, 1939, refers. Lt.-Colonel H.L. Davies, D.S.O., M.C., Military Department, India Office, WHITEHALL, • w • 1 • RECd. POL. DIPt. 1 7 MAh 1939 INDIA OFFICE ■nmHD.O. No. 42162/M.I.1 SECRET AND PERSONAL General Staff, India, New Delhi, the 9th February, 1939. Dear Lanee, x x XXX 3. Reference paragraph 4 of your letter of 19th January. Of the reports you mention ?/e hold C.B. 1885 only. Of the other two we should like to have a copy of C.B. 1892 if you can arrange it. I don’t think that C.B. 1959 will he of much use to us as all the information which we might require about Egypt and the Sudan will be contained in the Military Report on Egypt recently issued. x x x x x Yours ever, Sd. G.B. Henderson t Colonel L.E. Dennys, M.C., General Staff, War Office./isk COPY N9 9 lOR: ?S.\\V2)G0E This report is invariably to be kept locked up when not in use and is not to be taken outside the ship or establishment for which it is issued without the express permission of the Commanding Officer. C.B. 1892 (PLANS) ARABIA INTELLIGENCE REPORT (For Text see C.B. 1892 (X) ) I On all occasions of mustering, the contents of this C. B. are to be checked against the “State of Report,” Vide Article 38 of C. B. Form U.2D. (41) T91, 2146 6527,375 10/41■ Attention is called to the penalties attaching to any infraction of the Official Secrets Acts. This book is the property of H.M. Government. kuSMi® CONFIDENTIAL It is intended for the use of officers generally and may, in certain cases, be communicated to persons in H.M. Service below the rank of commissioned officer who may require to be acquainted with its contents in the course of their duties. The officers exercising this power will be held responsible that such information is imparted with due caution and reserve. i : I 111 ■W ■ jfp'! ■ 111 In$ # COPY No. 2 5 This report is invariably to be kept locked up when not in use and is not to be taken outside the ship or establishment for which it is issued without the express permission of the Commanding Officer. IOR: L PS 12 . 216 GB C.B. 1892 (X) (10/41) ARABIA INTELLIGENCE REPORT OCTOBER, 1941 SUBSEQUENTLY CORRECTED TO:— (For PLANS see C.B. 1892 (PLANS))CERTIFICATE OF INSERTION OF AMENDMENTS, ETC. Number of Correction. r- .* Authority. Initials. Rank. Date of Insertion. - CONFIDENTIAL This book is the property of H.M. Government. It is intended for the use of Officers generally and may, in certain cases, be communicated to persons in H.M. Service below the rank of Commissioned Officer who may require to be acquainted with its contents in the course of their duties. The Officers exercising this power will be held responsible that such information is imparted with due caution and reserve.$ @ ' ■ s) CONFIDENTIAL Attention is called to the penalties attaching to any infraction of the Official Secrets Acts C.B. 1892 (X) (10/41) ARABIA INTELLIGENCE REPORT OCTOBER, 1941 The following applies only to holders of Copy Nos. 1 to 125 of C.B. 1892. This book supersedes the loose-leaf text in C.B. 1892, which is to be destroyed by hre and a destruction certificate rendered to the Admiralty. The plans are to be transferred.to the new Folder, C.B. 1892 (PLANS), and mustered with the State of Report enclosed therein. Naval Intelligence Division, Admiralty. N.I.D. 2729/41.Introd notion CONTENTS Page 2 Section I.—Policy —(Notissued.) Section II.—Strategy and Tactics (1) (Not issued.) (2) Possible lines on which war plans would be framed (3) (4) (5) ( 6 ) (Not issued.) Section III. — Economic —(Not issued.) Section IV—Geography and Topography (1) Brief description of the country, location of frontiers and demilitarized areas (2) Climatic conditions, as affecting Naval operations (3) Transport facilities, including waterways, railways, roads and airways (4) Signal communications, W/T, L/T and cable Section V.—Base Facilities and Maintenance of the Fleet (1) (Not issued.) (2) Principal commercial dockyards and repair bases (3) Fuel storage . . (4) Supplies and storage of ammunition and other Naval material, including arsenals and armament factories. (5) Defended areas (6) Air Section VI.—Ports, Anchorages and their Defences AKABA BAHRAIN DOHA HODEIDA and RAS KETHIB . , JEDDA KAMARAN KUWAIT MUKALLA MUSCAT 16 16 16 16 16 18 18 20 25 27 29 33 36 40 42 No. la. No. lb. No. 1c. No. Id. No. 2. No. 3. No. 4. No. 5. ' No. 6. No. 7. No. 8. No. 9. No. 10. No. 11. No. 12. No. 13. No. 14. No. 15. No. 16. No. 17. No. 18. No. 19. No. 20. No. 21. No. 22. LIST OF PLANS General map of Arabia in four sheets. Outline Map showing Communications, etc. HODEIDA, View of. FUWWAH, Plan of Landing Ground. MUKALLA and Environs, Plan of. MUKALLA, Plan^of Wharf. MUKALLA Anchorage, Views of. AKABA and Shihair Landing Ground, Views of. SHARMA, Plan of. RAIDAH and District, Plan of. DOHA (A1 Bida), Plan of. SALALAH, Views of. MURBAT Bay, Plan of. MURBAT and KHOR RORI, Views of. BAHRAIN, Plan of. MANAMAH, Plan of Port and Town. Naval Base, KHOR KALIYA, Plan of. KHOR KAWI, Plan of. KHOR KAWI, Views of. KUWAIT, Plan of. MUSCAT and MATRAH, Plan of. JEDDA, Plan of Port. b 2 (C43043)2 INTRODUCTION 1. This report is divided into six sections, in accordance with the arrangement given in C.B. 3000 (38)—Manual of Naval Intelligence. 2. The following books and plans, the distribution of which is similar to that of this Intelligence Report, contain information supplementary to this Report and should be read in conjunction with it:— W/T Board List of Wireless Stations and Call Signs (C.B. Series). Submarine Telegraph Cables and W/T Stations in the Indian Ocean (C.B. Series). Ports and Anchorages (C.B. Series). Routes for Merchant Vessels on Outbreak of War (C.B. Series). Half-Yearly Return of War Vessels and Aircraft (British and Foreign) (C.B. Series). Quarterly Return showing Distribution of Foreign War Vessels and Aircraft (C.B. Series). Sources of Supply (Foreign Ports) of Coal, Oil and Fresh Provisions (O.U. Series). Dock Book (Foreign Docks) (O.U. Series). Sailing Directions. Military Report on the Arabian Shores of the Persian Gulf, KUWAIT BAHRAIN Q-^TAK’ TRUCIAL OMAN and OMAN—1933 (issued to Persian Gulf Sloops only). ^ Military Report and Route Book. The Arabian States of the Persian Gulf 1939.(C43043'' p3 SECTION I POLICY {not issued) SECTION II STRATEGY AND TACTICS (1) Not Issued &gt; (2) Possible Lines on which War Plans would be Framed ARABIA has no naval forces, but three important seas form the seaward boundaries of her long coast line, viz., the RED SEA, INDIAN OCEAN and PERSIAN GULF. The RED SEA with the SUEZ CANAL forms an important link in our maritime communication to INDIA and the FAR EAST, which remains secure as long as we have uninterrupted passage of the Canal and hold ADEN, combined with our dominant position in EGYPT and the SUDAN. We also hold SOCOTRA and the KURIA MURIA ISLANDS. On the other hand, the Italians have (or had until 1941) ERITREA, and the French have FRENCH SOMALILAND, both of which countries possess harbours at MASSAWA, ASSAB and JIBUTI. KAMARAN ISLAND, of which the status is not internationally recognized and upon which the Italians have cast envious eyes, may become important in the future. The anchorage is good and suitable for a large fleet. The questions of operations in the PERSIAN GULF is discussed in the Iran Intelligence Report (C.B. 1885). In relation particularly to the Arabian shore of this Gulf and the Gulf of OMAN, our relations with the Trucial Shaikhs and the other Arab potentates on this coast might conceivably demand a small combined operation at any time to maintain their position against rebellious tribes, not excepting those owing allegiance to Ibn Saud. Two fairly recent examples are represented by Ibn Saud’s encroachments into the KUWAIT area in 1928 and the rebellious attitude of the inhabitants of SUR against the Sultan of Muscat. A further potential encroachment into this coast may become evident if the Persian Navy develops. Again, the development of the Arabian coastal air route may call for protection of the aerodromes and fuelling bases. In the RED SEA it is possible to visualize a combined operation to bring pressure to bear upon the Imam of the Yemen, at his capital at SANA, to prevent repeated encroachments in the hinterland of the ADEN PROTECTORATE, by a landing at HODEIDA or some other point on the coast. Should it be desired to attack or exercise control upon merchant vessels trading with Arabian ports, three obvious focal points for trade are (1) The SUEZ CANAL ; (2) the STRAITS OF BAB EL MANDEB, which control the exits of the RED SEA, and (3) the STRAIT OF ORMUZ, which controls the entrance to the PERSIAN GULF. SECTION m ECONOMICS {not issued)4 SECTION IV GEOGRAPHY AND TOPOGRAPHY (1) Brief Description of the Country, Location of Frontiers and Demilitarised Areas [see Plans la, lb, 1c, Id and 2). ARABIA is essentially a desert country comprising an area of roughly one million square miles and inhabited for the most part by nomadic Bedouin tribes. It is bounded on the north by KUWAIT, IRAQ, TRANSJORDAN and PALESTINE, and enclosed on the other three sides by the sea, viz., the RED SEA on the west, GULF OF ADEN and ARABIAN SEA on the south, and the PERSIAN GULF and GULF OF OMAN on the east. The land surface of the peninsula enclosed within these limits slopes down steadily from the elevated mountain barrier, which runs down the whole length of its western side, parallel with the RED SEA, to sea level on the PERSIAN GULF, and the uniformity of this slope is only interrupted in the extreme eastern corner of the peninsula, where the mountains of the OMAN district rise to an elevation of 10,000 ft. above sea level. With the exception of this mountainous district and the similar district of the YEMEN, ARABIA is a barren country consisting of vast tracts of steppe desert, sand waste and mountainous wilderness. It is a country of insignificant rainfall (the YEMEN and OMAN excepted) ; here and there scattered oases or oasis groups are formed. The TAIF district, for instance, in the HEJAZ mountains above MECCA, the QASIM and JEBEL SHAMMAR provinces in CENTRAL ARABIA, and the HASA province near the PERSIAN GULF are among the best examples of such districts, while MEDINA, TAIMA, RIYADH, JAUF and WADI DAWASIR are a few among the many large oases which occur frequently throughout the country. The population of ARABIA cannot be estimated with any certainty, but may be taken to be about seven millions. SAUDI-ARABIA The two kingdoms of the HEDJAZ and NEJD, together with the districts of ASIR and HASA, form a personal union under the rule of King Ibn Saud, with the title of SAUDI- ARABIA. The chief port in the RED SEA is JEDDA, the seaport of MECCA, with YENBO, next in importance, which occupies a similar position in relation to MEDINA. Lesser ports are MUWAILIH, WEJH, RABIGH, LITH and QUNFIDHA. No definition is possible of the landward frontier between the HEDJAZ and the NEJD, and in any case the two countries are now united. The northern boundary is shown on Plan 2. The NEJD (“ Plateau ”) extends over about 800,000 square miles of CENTRAL ARABIA, with a population of about 1,275,000 arabs, negroes and half-breeds, the majority being Muhammadans of the Wahabite movement. The capital is RIYADH, but Legations are situated at JEDDA. The two chief ports in the PERSIAN GULF are QATIF and OJAIR on the HASA littoral. On the east, south and south-east, SAUDI-ARABIA is bounded by Trucial OMAN, the HADHRAMAUT and OMAN, respectively, but the exact boundaries are still under discussion. On the south-west, SAUDI- ARABIA borders on the YEMEN. THE YEMEN The YEMEN occupies the south-western corner of ARABIA between the district of ASIR and the ADEN PROTECTORATE, with an estimated area of about 74,000 square miles and a population of 3| millions. The country is ruled by the Imam Yahya, whose capital is at SANA and who is the head of the Zeydi sect of the Shiah Division of the Muhammadan religion. The highlands and central portions of the central plateau of the maritime range form the most fertile part of ARABIA. The chief port is HODEIDA with the lesser ones of LUHAIYA, MIDI, and MOCHA. The boundary with the ADEN PROTECTORATE is generally the Anglo-Turkish boundary demarcated in 1902-04, which commences on the extreme south-western point of ARABIA, just east of SHAIKH SAID, and runs approximately north-east to about NAWAH (see Plan 2). From this point a further line running north-east was drawn up at the same time, but not demarcated. A certain area east of the demarcated boundary around DHALI was reoccupied during 1928. By the Anglo-Yemen Treaty of 1934, it was agreed to maintain the situation existing in regard to the southern frontier of YEMEN, pending negotiations between the two parties, which should take place before the expiry of the Treaty, namely, 1974. No eastern boundary with the HADHRAMAUT is in existence.5) $ 5 (C43043) b4 THE HADHRAMAUT The HADHRAMAUT is a considerable coastal tract of fertile valleys in South ARABIA extending from the ADEN PROTECTORATE to OMAN. No western boundary is in existence, and on the east the boundary is with OMAN, which is described under OMAN. Inland the country is bounded by the Great Desert and the total area is about 82,000 square miles, with a Muhammadan population of 150,000. The most important coastal chief is the Sultan of SHIHR and MUKALLA, who lives usually at the latter port. MUKALLA is the chief port. Other ports of importance are SHIHR and QISHN. The territory is loosely under British protection and control by treaty. HAS A HASA occupies the whole of the PERSIAN GULF littoral of SAUDI-ARABIA, from KUWAIT to QATAR. Its chief importance lies in the fact that an oil concession has been granted to the Californian Arabian Standard Oil Co., an American concern, which has struck oil in an area south-east of QATIF. Both Ibn Saud and the company are anxious to develop RAS TANURAH as a port, both for marketing the oil and to avoid payment of BAHRAIN transit dues for imports into SAUDI-ARABIA. The British Government is anxious that the oil should be piped to BAHRAIN and refined there, as this not only gives us control of all oil found in this district, but obviates the loss of transit dues to BAHRAIN which would follow the establishment of a deep-water port on the HASA coast. The question is still in abeyance. MUSCAT and OMAN The Sultanate of MUSCAT and OMAN covers the south-eastern portion of ARABIA with a coast line about 1,500 miles long. Its western coastal boundary with the HADHRA MAUT is now generally accepted as being at RAS DHARBAT ALI in Lat. 16° 34' N., Long. 52° 49' E. In the PERSIAN GULF and GULF of OMAN the tertitory adjoins that of the Trucial Coast, though actual boundaries are difficult to define. In the GULF of OMAN the most northern coastal point is taken as KHOR KALBA. At the same time the tip of the RUUS AL JABAL peninsula lying to the north of a line drawn from DIBAH to SHA’AM owes nominal allegiance to OMAN (Plan 2). Inland the territory of the Sultan extends to the borders of the Great Desert, but of late years the Omanis of the interior have become virtually autonomous. GUADUR, a port on the BALUCHISTAN coast, and a small tract of country round it, also owe allegiance to MUSCAT. The country, much of which is arid and desert, reaches a height of 10,000 ft. in JEBBEL AKHDHAR. The population is chiefly Arab, with a strong infusion of negro blood from ZANZIBAR, which formerly belonged to MUSCAT, especially along the coast. The Sultan is an independent potentate who has commercial treaties with FRANCE (1844), the UNITED STATES of AMERICA (1833) and GREAT BRITAIN ; also a com mercial declaration (1877) with HOLLAND. Under the Anglo-French Declaration of 1862, H.M. Government and the French Government engage reciprocally to respect the independence of the Sultan. Under his treaty relations with H.M. Government, the Sultan is pledged never to cede, sell, mortgage or otherwise give for occupation, his dominions, save to H.M. Govern ment. His Highness has further undertaken not to grant oil concessions without the approval of H.M. Government. The Government of INDIA pays to the MUSCAT State a permanent subsidy of about £6,480, originally granted in 1861 as compensation for the abandonment of MUSCAT claims over ZANZIBAR ; this will continue so long as the Sultan fulfils his treaty engagements and manifests his friendship towards the British Government. While, however, the Sultan is in theory a wholly independent ruler, since the end of the 18th century British influence has been predominant in MUSCAT, and in practice the relations which obtain between its ruler and H.M. Government and the Government of INDIA very closely approximate to those which obtain between the Government of INDIA and an Indian State under the suzerainty of His Majesty. The present Sultan is His Highness Sir Saiyid Said bin Taimura, K.C.I.E., the son of the former Sultan, who abdicated in January, 1932. At the commencement of his reign he took over the internal administration of MUSCAT from a Council of Ministers and showed himself an able and active, if somewhat obstinate, ruler. In 1935, however, he absented himself from his capital (MUSCAT) and has since been living at DHOFAR, in the extreme southern area of his Sultanate, enjoying the life of a country gentleman and spending large sums of the impoverished State’s revenues. His uncle, Saiyid Shahib, acts as Regent, but the Sultan delegates little authority to him, whilst taking scarcely any interest in the welfare of the country himself. His conduct has led to much discontent in MUSCAT and the surrounding district.6 H.M. Government and the Government of INDIA are represented in MUSCAT by a Political Agent who is a British Officer of the Indian Foreign and Political Department and who acts as H.B.M.’s Consul. The last twenty years have seen the practical elimination of French and the consolidation of British influence in MUSCAT. Despite the fact that the Sultanate is independent, a very close degree of indirect control has been established ; the arms traffic has disappeared and thanks to the active intervention, both political and otherwise, of H.M. Government, a working arrangement has been reached with the rebellious tribes of the interior of OMAN. On the other hand, the financial situation is complicated by the need for expenditure on essential improvements and the problem of the attitude of the tribes of SUR remains a difficult one. The direct intervention in the affairs of MUSCAT of H.M. Government has been very definitely in the interests of the State, and, so far as those interests are concerned, it is desirable that it should be maintained. At the same time, so long as the treaties at present in force between the Sultan and FRANCE, HOLLAND and the U.S.A. continue to subsist, there can be no question of the establishment of a formal protectorate even should wider objections of principle not be held to militate against the acceptance of such a policy. From the narrower point of view of the interests of H.M. Government and the Government of INDIA there is no less advantage in a maintenance of the status quo, under which control in everything but name rests with H.M. Government. With the gradual elimination of British authority from the South Persian coast and with the adoption, for however long it may be maintained, of an active policy in the Gulf by Persia, the stranglehold on the Gulf, which the effective control of MUSCAT constitutes, has assumed an importance, more especially in view of British commitments in IRAQ, which it did not in the past present. Moreover, not only is effective, if veiled, control of MUSCAT the point d’appui of the consolidation of British influence on the North Arabian littoral, but the danger, in its absence, of active foreign interest in the State cannot be overlooked. The principality has recently acquired additional importance to BRITAIN for the three following reasons :— {a) The establishment of a “ recreational base ” at KHOR KAWI in the MUSSANDAM peninsula [see Plans 18 and 19). In view of the Anglo-French declaration of 1862, whereby both contracting parties agreed reciprocally to respect the inde pendence of the Sultan of MUSCAT, it was not possible to establish more than a recreational base. Even now it is possible the French Government may raise objections. In time of war, however, such objections could not be allowed to stand m our way in establishing a fully protected base here to safeguard our communications at the entrance to the PERSIAN GULF. The Imperial Air route to the East passes over the MUSSANDAM peninsula and also GUADUR, m BALUCHISTAN, where an aerodrome is maintained by Imperial Airways. J It is probable that the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company (or a subsidiary company) will obtain a concession to explore for oil in MUSCAT territory The Government of INDIA have expressed the view in 1928 that “ the maintenance of the independence of MUSCAT, KUWAIT, BAHRAIN and the Trucial Chiefs is necessary Our veiled protectorate over them suffices against European encroachments. So long as we do not alienate Arab opinion by attempting undue westernization, it suffices also aeainst encroachments by the WAHABI State. At need it can be more explicitly asserted ” § encroachments.^ 1106 ° f &amp; PerSian ^ added the P ossibilit y of Protection against Persian [b) [c) Trucial Oman AT 0f the PERSIA N GULF, from SHAAM to OJAIR is known as ins nrlu T.C, . A r lo '* thlscoastexlstseve n independent Shaikhdond namely RAS-AL QATAR l-heY t \ A p QAIWA U- AJMAN ' SHAR J A H. DEBAR ABU DHABI and ?«9n AR i Th tT ±} P rmci P allties are governed by Arab Shaikhs, whose predecessors in 18^0 and again in 1853 entered into Treaty relations with BRITAIN, whereby they contracted Foreign Po^ver ; notTo ceVeLermmmtg^fan^'oTiLTr sponge fishing or oil concessions without the approval of the British Government. P g ’ Actually, the Shaikh of QATAR did not join the Trucial Chiefs until 1916. In 1936 the Shaikh of KALBA (on the Gulf of mvrAxn t to the British Government, was accorded his independence’ and agrepd'to^nUrfntothe 1111168 contracts. He thus becomes the eighth Trucial Shaikh, g ™ 1 nt ° the Same7 (C 43043) The area between KHOR KALBA (some 5 miles south of KALBA) and DIBAH is otherwise independent. The tribes owe nominal allegiance to the Shaikh of SHARJAH, but they do not give it, and the Shaikh makes no attempt to exercise his authority in this district. (See Plan 2.) The Anglo-Iranian Oil Company has obtained concessions from the Shaikhs of RAS-AL- KHAIMAH, AJMAN, SHARJAH, DEBAT, ABU DHABI and QATAR to explore for oil in their respective territories. The concession in QATAR has been taken over by Petroleum Development (QATAR), Ltd. BAHRAIN The BAHRAIN group of islands, situated on the Arabian shore of the PERSIAN GULF, consists of two chief and a number of smaller islands. BAHRAIN Island is the most important and largest, being 30 miles long by 10 miles wide, with an area of 208 square miles. MUHARRAK, the next in importance, lies two miles to the north-east of BAHRAIN and has an area of 5J square miles. These two islands have now been joined together by an artificial causeway. / BAHRAIN is an independent Arab State under British protection, but is not a British Protectorate. The nominal ruler is Shaikh Hamad bin Isa al Khalifah, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., but the control of the administration comes under the Government of INDIA. The ruling Shaikh is precluded by his engagements with H.M. Government from receiving the representations of, or entering into relations with, foreign Powers, and from ceding, selling, mortgaging, or giving for occupation, save to H.M. Government, any part of his territory. He is bound to suppress the slave trade, to prohibit traffic in arms within his territory, and he is precluded from granting a concession for oil, or for pearl fishing, save with the approval of H.M. Government. The Shaikh has a British financial adviser, a State Engineer and a Director of Customs, all of whom are the Shaikh’s servants and paid from BAHRAIN funds. H.M Government and the Government of INDIA are represented by a Resident Political Agent, who is directly subordinate to the Political Resident in the PERSIAN GULF. In connection with the international status of the island, the last twenty years have seen the consolidation of British influence, but this has not affected the claim by PERSIA that the island is Persian. This claim has been constantly reasserted by PERSIA, and as constantly repudiated by H.M. Government. A factor which cannot be ignored is the rise of Ibn Saud and the Wahabi movement which, though at present has not affected BAHRAIN, may form a danger from a practical standpoint in the future. BAHRAIN has acquired increased importance since 1935, when the main Naval base of the Persian Gulf Division was transferred here from HEN JAM. It has also the largest natural aerodrome in the East and is a stopping place for Imperial Airways services on the IRAQ-KARACHI route. In addition, there is a large oilfield and refinery on the main island. KUWAIT r KUWAIT lies on the Arabian mainland in the PERSIAN GULF, about 50 miles S.W. of FAO and 80 miles south of BASRA. The boundaries are shown on Plan 2. In 1922/23 the islands of WARBA, BUBIYAN, MASHJANG, FAILAKAH, AUHAH, K-UBBAR, QARU and UMM-AL-MARADIN were attributed to KUWAIT. KUWAIT is, like BAHRAIN, an independent Arab State under British protection, but not a British Protectorate. The present Ruler is Shaikh Sir Ahmad-Al-Jabir-al-Sabah, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., born in 1885, and succeeded in March, 1921. He is precluded by his engage ments with GREAT BRITAIN from receiving foreign representatives, and from ceding, leasing, mortgaging, or giving for occupation, or any other purpose, any portion of his territory to any foreigner or foreign Power without the sanction of H.M. Government. He is bound to prohibit the import of arms into his territory, and although there is no slave treaty, he does much to suppress that traffic. He has agreed not to give a concession for oil, or for sponge fishing, without the approval of H.M. Government. The internal administra tion is conducted by the Shaikh, assisted in theory by an elected .Council of Advisers, consisting of 14 members, 9 notables and 5 members of the Shaikh’s family. The President is the Shaikh’s cousin. The Shaikh himself is the executive power and has the right of veto. H.M. Government and the Government of INDIA are represented by a Political Agent, who is directly subordinate to the Politcal Resident in the PERSIAN GULF. This officer does not hold His Majesty’s Commission as a Consul or exercise Consular functions, but holds considerable judicial and other powers under the terms of the KUWAIT Order in Council of 1935.8 The Shaikh, who is a strong man of considerable ability and personality, is well disposed towards H.M. Government and may be regarded as a very efficient Ruler when judged by Arab standards. In August, 1939, he assured H.M. Government of his and his people’s desire to place their services and resources at the disposal of the Government at any time they may be required. On a broad view politically the importance of KUWAIT is as great from the standpoint of H.M.'Government as that of BAHRAIN or of MUSCAT, and its absorption, or the establish ment in it of a dominating influence, by Ibn Saud, could not but react injuriously on our position in IRAQ, BAHRAIN and along the Trucial Coast. The desirability of securing that the Shaikh shall not escape absorption by Ibn Saud only to end by absorption by IRAQ, and the increased importance which this Principality, situated at the head of the Gulf, will assume as British control decreases in IRAQ, cannot be overlooked. KUWAIT lies across the main routes from HASA and NEJD to Lower IRAQ, and a force based in its territory could, to a large extent, control any future operations between SAUDI-ARABIA and IRAQ, as all land forces must follow the line of the few wells in N.E. ARABIA. Should the Royal Air Force be required: to withdraw from IRAQ in the future, an air base at KUWAIT might well prove an efficient substitute. Moreover, since the grant of an oil concession to the Kuwait Oil Company (half British and half American) in 1934, KUWAIT has assumed additional importance. From our point of view, oilfields in KUWAIT are strategically well placed and exceptionally favourably situated in that naval dispositions to protect the present source of supply in South PERSIA would in large measure afford protection to the sources of supply in KUWAIT. Should the A.I.O.C. output from ABADAN for any reason be interrupted, KUWAIT would be a convenient alternative requiring little diversion of shipping or change in protective dispositions. In addition, oilfields in KUWAIT would be more easily protected than those in IRAQ or PERSIA. It is known that the potential oil output of the area is very large and the company will erect a refinery. Practical work has, however, been discontinued since the outbreak of the war. In December, 1933, the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company negotiated an agreement to share on a fifty-fifty basis with the Eastern Gulf Oil Company in obtaining and exploiting a concession in KUWAIT. Sir John Cadman was understood to claim that he had the sanction of H.M. Government for this arrangement, although no trace of any record of such approval was found in the I.O. or F.O. It seemed desirable to give approval, as the American company had a much deeper pocket and were free from the difficulty which beset the A.I.O.C., namely, that they could not offer better terms to KUWAIT than they had already agreed in Iran. A certain amount of embarrassment was experienced in resisting American interests in KUWAIT, as the F.O. gave the American Government an undertaking which practically amounted to an open door arrangement in that area. This took place when Mellon was Ambassador in London. (Mellon’s family practically own the Eastern Gulf Oil Company.) (Incidentally this was a violation of the Red Line Agreement.) The two companies obtained their concession in December, 1934. The most important points were :— {a) A lump sum of Rs. 475,000 to be paid within 30 days. (b) Rs. 95,000/year until oil is found, after which the royalty should be Rs. 3 per ton or Rs. 250,000, whichever the greater. The Company to be free of duty in return for which Annas 4/ton to be paid. The agreement to be for 75 years. Political agreement was signed on 5/3/34 and contains a pre-emption clause. The area includes all KUWAIT territory, apart from the Neutral Zone. As a result of investigations it was decided to begin drilling at BAHRA, on the northern shore of KUWAIT Bay. Drilling was begun on 30th May, 1936, and was abandoned when 8,000 ft. had been reached without result. A new bore was opened at BURG AN, 35 miles south of KUWAIT, in October, 1937, and oil was struck in February, 1938, both the quality and pressure being good. Two other wells were immediately started. The company have been allotted and are developing a site on the shore of KUWAIT Bay at BANDAR SHUWAIK and also at KHOR KHADAMA, where there is comparatively deep water close inshore. KHOR KHADAMA was used by shipping in the Mesopotamia campaign (1914-1918), and was also the projected terminus of the BERLIN-BAGHDAD- KUWAIT railway.9 (C 43043) b* 2. At the moment it would appear that it is the policy not to export any oil from this area, and unofficial information has been received that the A.I.O.C. wish to keep this oil as a reserve in case things go wrong in Iran. Kuwait Neutral Zone Things are at a standstill, but it seems likely that the KUWAIT Oil Company and the Standard Oil Company of California will seek a joint concession. (2) Climatic Conditions, as affecting Naval Operations With regard to climate—in the PERSIAN GULF during the cold season fevers are most prevalent and the so-called gulf fever of the remittent type is very dangerous and convalescence can only be obtained by leaving the gulf. Cholera, plague and smallpox are frequent ashore in the native towns and villages. The hot season, from about May to October, is not apparently absolutely unhealthy. Men suffer from aggravated prickly heat, boils, etc., but if they are kept out of the sun and ventilation attended to there will probably be but little serious sickness. Work should not be done between 13'00 and 17 •00 if possible. Double awnings should be spread and the men may sleep on deck, where the dew does not appear to have an injurious effect. Absolute necessity alone can justify the exposure of men to the sun, and the wearing of sun-helmets must be insisted on, even under single awnings. Heat stroke and heat exhaustion are fairly common. Generally speaking practically no rain falls from May to September inclusive. Otherwise January, February, November and December experience considerable rainfall, but varying according to the locality. During winter the climate is very pleasant, resembling (in the south) a good English summer. Air temperatures of from 113° to 122° F. are recorded at places in the Gulf and in the lower reaches of the SHATT-AL-ARAB River during June and July. A sun temperature of 187° F. (shade 138° F.) was recorded at ABADAN in August, 1935. In the RED SEA the summer is perhaps, with the exception of the PERSIAN GULF the hottest of any sea in the world. In vessels proceeding southward during the hot season the great heat is often intensified by a light following wind of insufficient force to pass through the vessels and the almost complete saturation of the air deprives the wind of any invigorating effect. Near the coast the air is not so damp and the heat is somewhat more bearable, even though the temperature should be higher. In winter the climate is not unpleasantly hot. The climate of the GULF OF ADEN, though warm, is cooler than the RED SEA and generally healthy, there being no disease peculiar to it. The same remarks regarding precautions against exposure to the sun (during the summer) as given for the PERSIAN GULF apply. The rainfall in the RED SEA and GULF OF ADEN is comparatively small. It is greatest in the vicinity of SOKOTRA and gradually lessens through the GULF OF ADEN and. southern part of the RED SEA. The northern part of the RED SEA is practically rainless. For further details, including prevailing winds in the RED SEA, GULF OF ADEN and PERSIAN GULF see the official Pilots for these areas. (3) Transport Facilities Rivers There are no rivers in ARABIA which flow perennially from source to mouth ; but there are incipient perennial streams in ASIR, YEMEN, the Aden district, HASA, OMAN and NEJD and countless river-valleys (WADIS) which carry floods (Seils) after rainstorms. Those which originate east of the western watershed are mostly long and shallow, their bottoms being little depressed below the general level. The longest of these, the Rummah, whose course from the neighbourhood of MEDINA, through GAISUM to the SHAFT AL ARAB, falls 6,000 ft. in about 1,000 miles, is one good example. These rivers, though useless for transport, are not without importance, since at all times they carry water beneath their beds which can be reached by wells at varying depths, hence providing lines of possible commuaica- tion. Where, too, the moisture rises near or on to the surface are found chains of oases. The Wadis, which fall into the Red Sea, have as a whole deeply eroded beds, steeply inclined, and form an obstacle to'passage from north or south. Railways There is only one railway in ARABIA which is a continuation of the main Palestine line from DAMASCUS. It crosses the Transjordan frontier between RAMLEH and KALAAT (south of MAAN) and then continues in a south-south-east direction through TEBUK and AL ALA to MEDINA. The line is single track with gauge of 1 -05 metres and is not provided with sufficient sidings. The whole line up as far as MAAN has been out of action for several years.io Roads -There are practically no metalled roads in ARABIA. In and around the chief ports much has been done in recent years to improve the roads, so much so that motor cars, and light M/T are enabled to make considerable journeys inland and along the coast. This improvement has been mainly confined to marking out and rolling the existing camel and caravan tracks, which in many cases have followed the same course for centuries. The main roads or caravan routes, which are intersected by many cross-routes, are as follows :—Jedda-Mecca-Riyadh-Bahrain (950 miles) ; Jedda-Mecca-Riyadh-Kuwait (1,050 miles) ; Medina-Hail-Nejef (Iraq) (775 miles) ; Medina-Damascus (750 miles) ; Jedda- Mecca-Riyadh (450 miles) ; Jedda-Medina-Jauf (600 miles). A coast road, suitable for light M/T, exists from MUSCAT to SHINAS. A fairly good • road, suitable for all motor traffic, runs from KUWAIT to BASRA. In the rainy season such tracks and roads become quickly impassable for any wheeled . transport. Should it become necessary at any time to undertake military operations in ARABIA on a large scale the question of road communication would become a serious problem, as, for instance, that which confronted Lord Allenby during his advance from EGYPT into PALESTINE during the war 1914-1918. * ’ Airways The Imperial Airways Service to and from INDIA and the Far East calls four times weekly at BAHRAIN and DABAI for passengers and mails. For details of aircraft, owned by SAUDI-ARABIAN Government, see Section V—(6). Landing Grounds and Seaplane Anchorages [see Plan 2) The following list of landing grounds and seaplane anchorages is compiled from reports of air reconnaissances carried out by the Royal Air Force :— Place. Size. Position. Fuel and Remarks. Oil. TRANSJORDAN'— f AKABA 750 by 500 yards J mile north of head No Bay suitable for of Gulf. Black operating flying circle and corner boats and seaplanes. markings. {see also Section VI) SAUDI ARABIA (HEDJAZ)— DHABA Saudi-Arabian Mining Sydicate’s landing ground. WEJH 450 by 350 yards North of WEJH Yes in Village ; Markings. Town. YENBO 1,000 yard runway. North of Town ; Yes in small ground. Markings. Town. YENBO 1,500 by 750 yards North-east of Town; Yes Liable to flooding. Markings. RABIGH . . 800 yard runway North of Town No No report since used in 1916-17. JEDDA 800 by 450 yards North-West of Town; Yes in See also Section VI. Markings. Town. JEDDA — North-east of Town; — Under construction. TAIF Markings. Near old Turkish Not known Made base for Saudi Barracks, north- , ■ Air Force in Feb,, west of Town. 1935. TAIF — Another ground exists near by and is used by the South DISAN ID Arabian Mining Syndicate. 800 by 600 yards North-west of FARA- No Emergency landing SAN Group. ground. YEMEN— * KAMARAN IS. 600 by 700 yards 1 mile north of Town. Yes - . . S/P. Station. Three Circle and markings moorings. Landing HODEIDA .. — North - north - west No o/s Bay. See also Section VI. of Town—no mark- * Suitable for landing - mgs. but not maintained. See also Section VI.11 / Landing Grounds and Seaplane Anchorages [see Plan 2)— [contd.) Place. Size. Position. Fuel and Oil. Remarks. ADEN and the HADHRAMAUT PERIM IS 1,000 by 675 yards East of Harbour— Yes markings. RAS AL ARAH 800 by 500 yards 1^ miles south west Nil BIR MAHIJ JA— markings. Nil KHOR UM AIR API . . 800 by 450 yards J mile east of DAR UMAIRAH— markings. KHOR UMAIRAH . . 4 by 2 miles S/P. anchorage adja- Nil cent to landing ground. Nil BIR AM MAKHUUK 1,800 by 800 yards 3 miles south-west of Village. Land near circle marking. RASIMRAN . . 500 by 800 by 400 On shore near village. Nil yards. Circle marking. Yes ADEN 900 by 500 yards On Isthmus joining (KHORMAKSAR). ADEN to mainland. Aerodrome. ADEN 5,000 by 5,000 Sheltered harbour. . Yes at (Seaplane anchorage). yards. If miles east of town. aerodrome. SHUGRAPI . . 400 by 350 yards Nil Circle and corner markings. Nil AH WAR 500 by 350 yards 1 mile north-north- east of town. Circle and corner mark- ings. BIR ALI — Emergency S/P land- — ing north of bay. Nil MAJDAHAH .. 1,400 by 700 yards 6 miles east of BIK ALI. Circle markings. Nil MAJDAHAH . . — S/P open bay, 3 miles across. FUWWAH - [see Plan 4) 800 by 550 yards 5 miles south-west of At MUKALLA. Cor ner and circle markings. MUKALLA. Yes MUKALLA S/P anchor- — Bay east of town. age [see Plan 7). RIYAN 1,000 by 350 yards Two moorings. 5 miles west of From SHIHR. Corner MUKALLA. ,and circle SHIHAIR [see Plan 8) 570 by 230 yards markings. West of town wall. Nil Corner markings and boundary strips. raft regard th SHARMA [see Plan 9) Emergency S/P lan ding. Small coasting c between MUKAL LA and QISHN. No RAIDAH [see Plan 10) 700 by 550 yards 1 mile west of village. Corner markings. QISHN 450 by 900 yards East of town. Circle marking. No QISHN . . S/P anchorage . . Bay south-west of town. ANAD 960 by 30 yards. . Between ANAD and No \ NOBAT DAQIM. - BEIHAN 550 by 160 yards J mile north-east of Nil BEIHAN EL QASAB. Nil BIR UZIA 750 by 375 yards 48 miles north-west by west of ADEN. DAQQAM 600 by 160 yards 2 miles north of QARAD. Nil DAR MUFTARISHA 500 by 100 yards 4J miles south-west Nil of DAREJA. DHALA 1,000 by 150 yards 3 miles north of Nil DHALA. S/P. anchorage. Two moorings south side of Is. Emergency . landing ground. Emergency landing ground. Emergency landing ground. Emergency landing ground. Occupied aerodrome, 10 buoys. Political landing ground. Political landing ground. Political landing ground. Emergency S/P anchorage. Political landing ground. See also Section YI (under MUKALLA). See also Section VI. Operational landing ground. See also Section VI (under MUKALLA). Emergency landing ground. is as only good shelter Political landing ground. See also Section VI (under MUKALLA). Emergency landing ground. Emergency landing ground. Political landing ground. Operational landing ground. Emergency landing ground. Emergency landing ground. Political landing ground. B* 3 (C 43043)12 / Landing Grounds and Seaplane Anchorages [see Plan 2)— [contd.) Place. Size. Position. Fusl and Oil. Remarks. ADEN and the H A DM RAMAUT—contd. EL HAUTA . . 800 by 350 yards Nil Political landing ground. &gt;&gt; EL MASAWA 500 by 500 yards —• Nil Operational landing ground. HABIL EL JABR . . 500 by 130 yards 2 miles east of village Nil Emergency landing ground. ■&gt; HAIFIF 800 by 400 yards — Nil Emergency landing ground. KHUREBA . . 800 by 600 yards — Nil Political landing ground. Political landing LAUDAR 600 by 200 yards J mile north of Nil MIS-HAL village ground. 500 by 500 yards 1 mile east of village Nil Political landing MUSEMIR ground. 800 by 450 yards f mile north-east of Nil Operational landing NABIA village. ground. 550 by 300 yards —■ Nil Political landing NISAB . . ground. 900 by 300 yards 800 yards east of Nil Political landing SAUDA village. ground. 600 by 150 yards f mile north-north Nil Political landing SEIYUN west of village. ground. — — — Proposal to construct. SHIBAM 1,100 by 700 yards — Small emer- Political landing gency stock. ground. TARIM — — — Under construction. TURBA 325 by 70 yards 2 miles east of AM Nil Political landing TURBA. ground. Moth A/c. only. MUSCAT and OMAN SALALAH 1,000 by 1,400 by 1 mile north of village. Nil Operational landing [see Plan 12). KHOR RORI ... . . 900 yards. Circle with XII in -centre. Corner markings. ground. S/P anchorage . . 15 miles west of Nil MERBAT 1,040 by 250 yards MURBAT. mile east of village. Yes (see Plans 13 and 14) MERBAT Circle and corner markings. S/P anchorage . . Able to anchor close (sre Plans 13 and 14). to the north shore planes do NOT KHOR GHARIB 250 by 400 yards of the bay. SUKRA BAY. Circle Nil exist. and corner mark- KHOR GHARIB S/P anchorage . . mgs. Not suitable for F/B.s KHOR MILH .. Possible S/P an- chorage. No details. MASIRA IS MASIRA IS. . . S/P anchorage . . 493 by 440 yards 3 miles south of UMM Yes New landing ground RASAS. in place of UMM RAS AL HADD 895 by 840 by 500 1,000 vards west of Nil RASAS. yards. Cape. Circle and SHUWAINIYA Constructed by corner markings. R.A.F., no de tails available. KHOR JARAMA S/P anchorage . . — Yes R.A.F. supply tank. BANDAR JISSAH . . S/P anchorage .. Alternative to Yes at MUSCAT (BEIT EL FELEJ). R.A.F. landing ground main- MUSCAT. Circle and corner markings. MUSCAT. Yes See also Section VI. tained. MUSCAT (BEIT EL FELEJ). S/P anchorage . . R.A.F. buoys Yes SOHAR 1,200 by 800 yards 2 miles north of Fort. Nil Emergency landing SHINAS 1,380 by 450 yards Circle markings. South side of Town. Yes ground. R.A.F. maintained Circle and comer markings. I landing ground.13 B* 4 (C 43043) Landing Grounds and Seaplane Anchorages [see Plan 2)— (contd.) Place. Size. Position. Fuel and Oil. Remarks. PERSIAN GULF TRUCIAL OMAN RAS-AL-KHAIMAH 580 by 530 by 600 yards. Trucial coast. No markings. R.A.F. fuel barge in Creek. Yes R AS-AL-KHAIM AH S/P anchorage in Creek. Petrol dhow main tained. Yes SHARJAH . . 860 by 800 yards 1 mile south-east of Town. Boundary circle marking. Imp. Airways Rest House. Yes Night stop for Imp. Airways. DEBAI S/P anchorage . . Near SHARJAH . . Yes R.A.F. fuel barge. ABU DHABI 580 by 460 yards 1 i. miles south-east of Town. Circle and corner markings. Yes R.A.F. Store. YAS IS 750 by 500 yards South of Island. Suitable for Air craft with low pressure tyres only. Yes Emergency. YAS IS. . . S/P anchorage . . Yes at landing ground. S/P anchorage. Two buoys. DOHA (QATAR) (see Plan 11). 1,000 by 200 yards 2 miles north of Town. Circle and corner markings. . Yes in Town. See also Section VI. DOHA (QATAR), ' possible. S/P anchorage . . — Yes in Town. Customs aerodrome. BAHRAIN IS. 1,000 by 870 yards 2 miles north-north- Yes (MUHARRAK) (see plan 15). east of MANA- MAH (on MU HARRAK IS.) Imp. Airways. Marked landing ground. See also Section VI. BAHRAIN (see plan 15). S/P anchorage . . South-south-west of landing ground. Two buoys. Yes from aerodrome. See also Section VI. DARIN IS. (TARUT) 600 by 300 yards. . South end of Island. Not maintained. Circle and corner markings. No SAUDI - ARABIA (HASA) :— JUBAIL ' Landing ground used by Saudi Air Force and Oil Coy’s. No JINNAH IS. 500 by 600 yards Landing ground east side of Island. Idsed by Saudi Air Force. Circle and markings. No SAUDI - ARABIA (NEJD). Not known RIYADH . . 800 by 400 yards 24 miles east of 'RIYADH. Race course marked by whitewashed py lons. KUWAIT KUWAIT (see plan 20) 950 by 650 yards East of town. Imp. Airways stop. Rest House. Circle and markings. Yes Customs aerodrome. See also Section VI. KUWAIT (see plan 20) S/P anchorage . . In bay off town Yes at aerodrome. See also Section VI. Notes. (i) An emergency landing ground and two flying boat buoys will shortly be established at KALBA (on the west coast of the Gulf of OMAN), as an emergency landing place for Imperial Airways. (ii) Sites for landing grounds exist at MUWAIH and DUWADMI (in NEJD). (iii) Imperial Airways are proposing to establish a flying boat refuelling base on the lagoon at UMIN- AL-QAIWAIN.15 (C43043) B * Cables At the present time (September, 1941) cable communication is maintained between MUSCAT and BUSHIRE, BUSHIRE and BAHRAIN, and between BUSHIRE and FAO, thence to universal system. In the Red Sea, JEDDA is connected to PORT SUDAN and thence to the universal system There is extensive cable communication from ADEN and PERIM. Certain secret work is being carried out on submarine cables and when this is completed the position will be as follows :— PERSIAN GULF FAO—BUSHIRE (1). FAO—BAHRAIN (1). BAHRAIN—MUSCAT (1). MUSCAT—KARACHI (1). RED SEA JEDDA—PORT SUDAN (1). PERIM—ADEN (1). PERIM—SHEIKH SAYED (1). ADEN—PORT SUDAN (4). ADEN—PERIM (1). ADEN—BOMBAY (3). ADEN—PORT VICTORIA (SEYCHELLES) (1). ADEN—ZANZIBAR (1). ADEN—COLOMBO (1). Genera! Notes on the Arabian Wireless System The wireless system of Arabia centres around the two capitals of the Hedjaz and Nejd, namely, Mecca and Riyadh. The main link is, therefore, naturally between these two places and is' of the utmost importance, because for the greater part of the year the King resides at Riyadh, while the Foreign Office and other Government Offices are in Mecca. Thus all questions of international and internal interest are passed on this route. The remaining stations divide themselves into two groups'. those in the Hedjaz, controlled by Mecca , and those in Nejd, controlled by Riyadh. Apart from the internal system there are also external links working to Syria, Iraq, Yemen and occasionally to Port Sudan. In recent years there has been a considerable development in Arabian wireless communica tions and new stations and links are put into operation fairly frequently. This is due to the development of H/F apparatus, which is now taking the place of the old M/F equipment. During May, 1939, experiments were made between certain main stations in the use of R/T. These experiments were not very successful, chiefly owing to incompetence on the part' of the Arab operators ; on 24th June &gt; 1939, however, H.M. King Ibn Saud performed the opening ceremony of the R/T link between Mecca and Riyadh. It is not known to what extent R/T is now being used in Saudi Arabia. The main channel of communications is between Mecca and Riyadh and operates on both M/F and H/F. Since Taif is linked with Mecca by landline, traffic is also passed between Riyadh and Taif and then from Taif to Mecca by this means. The majority of stations in the Hedjaz are able to work direct to Mecca, but some of the northern ones, which still use a spark transmitter, work in a local group. Traffic for Mecca from this group is passed-either by Dhaba or El Weijh on H/F. The second group consists of stations imNejd, and is controlled by Riyadh. Of the stations in the Southern Hedjaz and Tehemah those of Jeizan, Dhahr and Kunfudah work direct to Mecca while Abha and Machlaf work either Riyadh or Mecca, all operating on H/F. It is not unusual for some of these stations to work Taif for onward transmission to Mecca by landline instead of direct to Mecca. The transmitters at Riyadh and Mecca are 6 kw. and manufactured by Marconi. Some of the H/F equipment was made by the Radio Corporation of America, the power of these being about 100 watts. It is possible that future apparatus may all be Marconi, as the engineers have expressed a preference for it. The receivers in use are very varied, Marconi, Eddystone and Philips are among the makes mentioned. The officer in control of the wireless organization throughout Saudi Arabia is one Ibrahim Silsila. The same man is likewise assistant director of Posts and lelegraphs. He is an Egyptian by origin.16 SECTION V BASE FACILITIES AND MAINTENANCE OF THE FLEET (1) Not Issued (2) Principal Commercial Dockyards and Repair Bases There are no dockyards, aircraft factories, commercial shipbuilding or repair works in ARABIA. ARABIA has no mercantile marine in the accepted sense of the word. Local motor and sailing dhows play an important part in the coasting trade. Hence the country is dependent on foreign carrying power for its trade both in peace and war time. This is especially the case regarding the import trade. ARABIA possesses no facilities for building ocean-going merchant steam vessels Local sailing and motor dhows are built at BAHRAIN, KUWAIT and other ports. In considering foreign ports in the area at which repairs can be undertaken, facilities exist at KARACHI and BOMBAY. In the area of the Red Sea there are two docks at Suez, a floating dock and seven gliding slips at Port Said and three docks and a patent slip at ADEN (for details see Dock Book). (3) Fuel Storage Oil fuel and coal are obtainable at ADEN, and oil at BAHRAIN. No fuel is maintained by any of the local Governments in ARABIA. Naval oil barges, holding 500 tons each, are based, one on BAHRAIN and another on KHOR KAWI. (4) Supplies and Storage of Ammunition and other Naval Material, including Arsenals and Armament Factories Although detailed statistics are not available, IBN SAUD has been able to obtain all the war material he requires as far as the financial resources of the country will allow. This is particularly so since the lifting of the arms embargo by GREAT BRITAIN and other countries in 1925. An embargo by GREAT BRITAIN still exists with regard to the YEMEN. The dominant position held in the Persian Gulf by H.M. Ships, combined with the treaty relations with the various Arab potentates on the Arabian coast, is a decisive factor in controlling the traffic in arms in this area. In past years IBN SAUD has received arms and ammunition from POLAND, GERMANY and the Government of INDIA ; aircraft from GREAT BRITAIN j petrol and benzine from the U.S.S.R., GREA1 BRITAIN and ITALY ; W/T apparatus from the Marconi Company (British). The Imam of the YEMEN has received arms, W/T apparatus and a tank from ITALY ; arms, petrol and benzine from the U.S.S.R. This is not a complete list, but so far as can- be estimated all the war material destined for ARABIA enters the country by sea, particularly via the ports of JEDDA and HODEIDA, which is the natural result of a long coast line and the fact that no countries engaged in the manufacture of war material on a large scale are situated on the northern borders. Arsenals and Armament Factories There is an arsenal at JABAL HINDI in MECCA and one at MUWAIL (between MECCA , an d RIYADH). DETAILS ARE REQUIRED of these and any other arsenals. Probably such weapons as swords and daggers are made in the*country. (5) Defended Areas So far as is known there are no modern fixed coast defences in ARABIA. The forts in existence are either unarmed or armed with old and useless guns. (6) Air The Saudi-Arabian Government possesses the following aircraft : Three Wapitis purchased in 1930. One Caudron-Renault Pelican ’ presented by the French Government in 1936. One Bellanca four-seater monoplane presented by the Arabian Mining Syndicate in 1937. Three Capronis presented by the Italian Government in 1937, the first instalment t of a promised gift of six aircraft.17 It is also proposed to purchase two aircraft for training and three other aircraft, to be called “ MECCA,” ” JEDDA ” and “ RIYADH.” Subscription lists have been opened in certain towns for this purpose, but are not meeting with a very rapid response. In addition to their gift of aircraft, the Italian Government have also presented the Saudi Government with a steel hangar which is said to be able to contain 20 aeroplanes. The hangar was sent out from ITALY in sections and erected by Italian personnel. The “ Air Force ” personnel consists of three Russians, eight Saudi-Arabian pilots trained in ITALY and a few Italians. The latter are paid by the Italian Government and are responsible for the aircraft presented by ITALY. They work on a system of six-monthly reliefs from ITALY. It is reported that the efficiency of the Saudi-Arabian pilots is low and that, since returning from their period of training in ITALY, they are dissatisfied with their low pay and general treatment and consider that they are regarded merely as chauffeurs. It is reported that a further 15 Saudi-Arabians are to be trained as pilots in their own country and that the experiment of sending them to ITALY for training will not be continued. The Air Force base has been located at TAIF since 1935. (C43043) b**218 SECTION VI PORTS, ANCHORAGES AND THEIR DEFENCES Notes. —1. Information is required in accordance with C.B.3000 (38), Chapter III, Section 5, to cover other ports for addition to this section. Any such reports rendered would be enhanced in value if accompanied by an up-to-date plan. 2. On no account should the navigational information given under this section be used without reference to the Official Sailing Directions published by the Hydrographic Department. AKABA (Lat. 29° 31' N., Long. 35° 00' E.) [See Plan 8 and Admiralty Charts 8a and 3595.) (1) General Remarks Gulf of Akaba The gulf of Akaba extends in a north-easterly direction for about 100 miles and varies in width from 7 to 14 miles. The entrance to the gulf is obstructed by extensive reefs surrounding Tiran Island, leaving two channels. The western channel is only two cables wide between the reefs, and the northerly wind and swell come down through it with great force at times. The eastern channel is about a quarter of a mile wide. The shores of the gulf are closely bounded by mountain ridges, which are continued to the northward on each side of the Wadi Akaba, a wide and desert valley, the water courses of which are dry for the greater part of the year. Along the wadi these ridges rise in many places from the plain like walls and the passes over them are extremely difficult. The gulf is subject to violent and almost constant northerly winds, which blow with considerable force. During April and May they are usually moderate and then an occasional change to southerly winds may occur as also during the winter months. These northerly winds raise a considerable swell and the gulf is consequently almost devoid of native craft. The shores of the gulf are steep-to and the only anchorages along the eastern coast.are at AKABA {see below) ; between Omeidar Island and the mainland ; at BIR AL MASHIYA, under a sandy point in about 5 or 6 fathoms ; at SHERM DHABA and at SHERM MUJAWAN, a snug cove with a narrow entrance with a depth of about 2| fathoms. All these anchorages except the last one are exposed to the southerly winds, which sometimes come on suddenly and blow hard. AKABA AKABA lies on the eastern side of the head of the gulf of the same name. The head of the gulf forms a semi-circular bay extending for some three miles north and northwest of the village. The shore is very low, and abreast of the village consists of sand. There is anchorage off AKABA village in 11 fathoms, and also at the head of the gulf. The importance of AKABA lies in its proximity to the following frontiers at the head of the Gulf of AKABA (a) SINAI-PALESTINE, which runs in a 335° direction from a point 254° 5 miles from AKABA village. (b) PALESTINE-TRANSJORDAN, which runs in a 010° direction up the WADI ARABA from a point about 310° 2-2 miles from AKABA. (c) TRANSJORDAN-SAUDI ARABIA, which runs from EL BURG point to MEDAWARA, some 80 miles inland. This frontier is not recognized by IBN SAUD, who claims AKABA as Saudi territory. (2) Port Facilities It is estimated (September, 1941) that the port capacity is about 100 d.w. tons per day. It is to be developed. Lifting Appliances Nil. W arehouses Nil.19 (C43043) (3) The Town AKABA was formerly a place of some importance, as it formed a depot for the supply of water and provisions for the pilgrims from CAIRO to MECCA, but now that the majority of the pilgrims from EGYPT use the sea route, it has lost much of this importance. The village is largely in ruins, as the result of bombardment in the war of 1914-18. It extends some 800 yards along the shore and is surrounded by groves of date palms. It consists of an old square fort, a few mud buildings chiefly occupied by fishermen, and some military huts on the eastern slopes overlooking the bay. The permanent inhabitants do not exceed 200 in number. The water supply is ample and the large deep well, which was formerly used for supplying the large pilgrim caravans, is in the fort. Drinking water of fair quality is obtainable from a well near Chatham Pier, while some good springs exist just north-west of the village. The amount of water available varies with the season. In summer it is reported that 5,000 men would be the maximum that could be supplied, while from November to April sufficient for as many as 15,000 men might well be obtained. . (4) Government Establishments The Customs House at the head of Chatham Pier is well built and used as a general purpose Government building. - Authorities The Commanding Officer of an Arab Legion post exercises function of Military Com mandant. The village headman is subordinate to him. (5) Commercial Establishments An unsuccessful attempt was made some years ago to establish industry to supply frozen fish, locally caught, to TRANSJORDAN and PALESTINE. Remains of refrigerating plant are still standing. (6) Aircraft Factories Nil. (7) Air Facilities. {See also Section IV (3) ) There is an emergency landing ground J mile north of the head of the Gulf, at the junction of AKABA-NEKHL and AKABA-GAZA roads. It has a black circle and corner markings. The bay is suitable for operating flying boats and seaplanes. (8) War Material Factories Nil. (9) Power Plants Nil. (10) Transport Facihties All regular traffic by cars and lorries has to go by the track up the main wadi to MA’AN (about 70 miles) and branch off from there. The construction of a new road and rail link is projected. (11) Signal Communications There is no telegraph or telephone system. A W/T station is sited in the Arab Legion posts, which is in touch with AMMAN and other stations. (12) Defences Nil. (13) Reconnaissance The most suitable place to land troops is along the shore for three miles to the north westward from the pier, where the beach is sandy and clear of reefs. Immediately inshore, there are some low sand hills and scrubs which would afford some protection to defenders, but about half a mile inland up the Wadi the land becomes flat and devoid of all cover, except occasional scrub. The shore for a mile northward from El Burg Point is also suitable for landing troops, but the plain here is commanded by the mountains further inshore. Southward of El Burg the coast is steep-to and unsuitable for landing operations. d**Q20 There is a mined jetty called Chatham Pier about 500 yards from the nearest point of anchorage. It extends nearly 200 ft. from the shore and stands about 1 ft. above water level, with 3 ft. to 4 ft. of water along its southern side. It could be rebuilt to take lighters and boats, but there is no stone available nearer than Farum Island, 8 miles away. The village is concealed from seaward by a line of date palms, but is commanded from inshore by mountains lying to the east and south-east. There still exist the well-concealed line of trenches built by the Turks during the war (1914-1918), to which they retired on the approach of a British man-of-war. They run roughly in an arc between the 652 ft. peak of Jebel Shahabi to Jebel Maaruf and they form a very strong defensive position, since there is no cover between them and the shore, and the mountains in rear are precipitous. There is a well of good water in Wadi Shallala. There are suitable camp sites on the plains to the north and south of the village. BAHRAIN (Lat. 26° 16' N., Long. 50° 33' E.) (See Plans Nos. 15, 16 and 17, and Admiralty Charts 3790 and 3792.) (1) General Remarks The State of BAHRAIN has suffered violent economic fluctuations during the last ten years. At first it enjoyed comfortable prosperity due to the pearl trade, then suffered a severe financial depression resulting in drastic curtailment of all activity and expansion, and finally an immense increase in revenue due to the development of the BAHRAIN Oil Field by the BAHRAIN Petroleum Company, Ltd. This company has now succeeded in making BAHRAIN the twelfth largest oil-producing country in the world, and, providing the oil does not run dry, a period of continuously increasing prosperity appears to be in prospect for BAHRAIN. Already among other Gulf States BAHRAIN is looked up to as being most progressive. The climate is not good and fevers, dysentery and malaria are rife in the spring and autumn. Venereal diseases are very prevalent. The climate is excessively damp and heavy, the maximum humidity actually occurring in winter, but even during summer it is damper than'any other part of the Gulf. A shamal blows almost continuously for 40 days during June and July, bringing constant dust-storms, whilst doing little to cool the atmosphere. From mid-July to mid-October the damp heat makes BAHRAIN most unpleasant for Europeans. The annual rainfall is about 3 in. BAHRAIN is of importance in that it is now the main base of the Persian Gulf Division. An officers’ mess, men’s canteen, swimming pools, gardens, coal, petrol and lay-apart stores, Clerk-in-Charge’s house and coolie lines have been built on ESSEX Point. Football, cricket and hockey grounds have been laid out, and a pier (one-third mile long) constructed, along which a Decauville track runs to the coal and lay-apart stores. A complete water supply and drainage system has also been installed. The construction of this base was undertaken by the Government at the request of the Naval Authorities. The white ensign flies from the flagstaff, which was transferred here from BASIDU. The sloops anchor in KHOR KALIYA, where is also moored a 500-ton oil barge. Buoys and beacons have been erected to assist navigation. This is always tricky at the bar, except , at slack water, as the stream sometimes reaches 6 knots. Passage in and out of KHOR KALIYA is undertaken regularly during dark hours and should not present any difficulties to a ship entering for the first time. KHOR KALIYA, eastward of the northern end of BAHRAIN, is enclosed by reefs extending off BAHRAIN, MUHARRAK and SITRAH ISLANDS, only leaving a narrow entrance at its south-eastern end available for shipping ; boats can enter the reef at the northern end. The middle part is occupied by a large sand shoal with 7 to 17 ft. of water in it, but there is considerable space around it with depths of 20 to 25 ft., affording fairly good anchorage, to some extent sheltered from shamals. The entrance channel across the middle of the bar between KASSAR DIWAN rock and SITRAH reef, is about 60 yards wide, with depth of 25-54 ft. (For full particulars see Persian Gulf Pilot.) The mercantile harbour lies northward of BAHRAIN Island. The anchorage, classed as “ D,” lies between the Jadam shoal and the island itself, and is- sheltered to the extent that ships can lie there in any weather and the holding ground is good. A considerable sea, bad for boats, gets up in the outer harbour during a strong shamal, but communication with the shore is- seldom interrupted and vessels ride easily at anchor. There is anchorage space for a number of cruisers with 19 to 42 ft. depth. It is open to observation and could be easily mined. There is unlimited anchorage if distance from the town is immaterial,The inner harbour, a bight in the reefs north-west of MANAMAH town, is about a mile in extent, suitable for small vessels and much better protected. Vessels of more than 15 ft. draught should not enter it. (2) Port Facilities The quayage consists of one pier and three small adjacent basins. The pier is 728 ft. long, has a breadth at the sea end of 141 ft., tapering to 68 ft. at the shore end. There is also a stone’pier in front of the Agency which is about 150 yards long and 10 ft. wide. At low water there is a depth of 1 ft. at the sea end of the former. The latter dries out 2 ft. The measurements of the basins are as follows :— Basin No. 1 .. 46 ft. wide and 49 ft. long. Pier 43 ft. wide. Basin No. 2 .. Of similar dimensions to No. 1. Basin No. 3 .. 49 ft. long and 128 ft. wide. There is a mole 320 ft. long tapering-to the head. The total quayage is 2,952 linear feet. Landing Places (a) Naval Pier, JUFAIR. Depth at end 5 ft. at M.L.W.S. (b) R.A.F. Pier : On north-west coast of KHOR KHALIYA. Depth at end 4 ft. (c) Customs Pier : MANAMAH. Depth at end 4 ft. M.L.W.S. (d) Agency Pier, MANAMAH. Dept at end | ft. M.L.W.S. There is one fixed hand crane of 5 tons capacity at the north-eastern end of the main pier. Radius clear of quay—9 ft. The customs department have two sheds, one on the main pier and the other behind the customs offices about 150 yards inland from shore end of the pier. A hand power-trolley system connects both sheds. The pier shed is built of corrugated iron with a ventilated roof and earthen floor, and measures 175 ft. by 67 ft. The customs shed is built of stone, with a corrugated iron roof, and is well ventilated. Its dimensions are 324 ft. by 97 ft. There are also two A.I.O.C. store houses built of corrugated iron about 1| miles west of Customs Pier, each having a capacity of 20,000 four-gallon tins of petrol. Harbour Craft In April, 1934, these consisted of the following :— Two iron barges (B.I.S.N. Co.), one of 30 and one of 20 shipping-tons capacity. Sixty-one motor launches and dhows. The average size of these is about 15 tons and they range from 10 to 70 h.p. (most are propelled by 20-h.p. Kelvin engines). Average passenger carrying capacity 45. 430 pearling dhows. \ Varying from 2| to 300 tons. 720 sailing dhows. Of all sizes. / ■ b At least 100 of these would be available at any given time. The Imperial Airways seaplane tender would be available at short notice provided it was not attending on LA. boats. The landing of stores would be difficult in the case of large vessels, a,s these have to lie from 2 to 5 miles off shore and discharge into dhows, though the introduction of motor dhows fitted with Kelvin engines has improved matters considerably. The capacity of the port is estimated at 500 d.w. tons per day. (3) The Town MANAMAH, the Port of the BAHRAIN Archipelago, is situated on the north and north-eastern shores of BAHRAIN Island. It has a sea frontage of approximately 1^ miles and a depth of about ^ mile. MUHARRAK, the second town of the State, and situated on MUHARRAK Island, is to be linked with MANAMAH by a causeway and a bridge. The length of the causeway is about 1,200 yards. The causeway has already been constructed. In addition to being the port, MANAMAH is also the headquarters of the various government and commercial offices, which are mostly situated on the north shore. On its northern shores are to be found the customs warehouses and piers and government establishments. The Shaikh’s town palace is situated on the south-west outskirts of the town. (C43043) b**422 To the south-east of the town is the wireless station of Cable and Wireless, Ltd., and the R.A.F. rest house and seaplane anchorage. Inside the town and to the south are the American church, a school and the quarters of the American Missionaries. There are three hospitals in MANAMAH :— [а) The Victoria Memorial Hospital, which is attached to the .Political Agency, and is under the charge of the Agency Surgeon, an Assistant Surgeon of the Indian Medical Department. - It has an outdoor and indoor department and has ten beds for men and two beds for women. It is not suitable for Europeans. The Agency Surgeon is also Quarantine Medical Officer for the BAHRAIN Government. (б) The Mason Memorial Hospital of the American Mission comprises a male and female hospital and has a staff of three qualified American doctors, one of whom is an eye specialist. Both these hospitals maintain in- and out-door departments and have : 45 beds in the men's hospital. 25 beds in the women’s hospital. This hospital can take Europeans in limited numbers in case of emergency, but venereal patients would not be received. The Surgeon in charge of the Mason Memorial Hospital is able to perform any major operation not requiring a specialist, but is not always present at BAHRAIN. (c) A hospital, erected and maintained by the Bahrain Petroleum Company for their employees and families. This hospital treats officers and white naval ratings. Water Supply Water for drinking purposes is imported from India for the civil population. For the Navy, a supply of 40 tons is maintained in the oil barge, which is kept full of distilled water by the visiting escort vessels. There is a large number of natural springs in the northern half of the island and a good supply of water from Artesian wells, but the water is slightly brackish and contains mineral salts. Water is tapped at an average depth of 250 ft. This might be used in Scotch boilers. The streets for the most part are drained and clean, while there is an organization to deal with rubbish. The population of the islands may be estimated at about 150,000, of whom rather over half are resident in the four principal towns as follows :— BAHRAIN ISLAND MANAMAH .. .. 36,000 BUDAIYA 10,500 MUHARRAK ISLAND MUHARRAK 30,000 AL HADD 10,000 BAHRAIN as a port and trade centre is the resort for people from IRAN, QATAR, TRUCIAL OMAN; and to a less degree from central ARABIA. Almost the entire population is Mohammadan. The language of the country is Arabic, though Persian and Hindustani speaking communities are found in MANAMAH. The exports include specie, rice, pearls, cotton piece goods and sugar, of which all except pearls are in the nature of re-exports. The pearl industry was important and flourishing, but of late years it has suffered severely from the decline of all luxury trades. For centuries the Persian Gulf has been famous for its pearls and at present is the centre of the industry, and the chief market in the Gulf is at BAHRAIN, where over 500 boats are registered. About 15,000 of the inhabitants of BAHRAIN gain a living by diving for pearls as well as many divers who migrate annually from IRAN and the Arab coast. The diving season lasts from about the middle of May until the middle of October, of which the chief season, known as Ghaus, is fixed by the Shaikh of BAHRAIN. The agricultural produce of BAHRAIN was formerly confined to dates, date juice and a small quantity of lucerne seed. Latterly, however, there has been an increasing demand for agricultural produce and the few experiments which have been made show that it is possible to cultivate successfully a number of trees, crops and vegetables which have not previously been grown on a large scale.23 (4) Government Establishments The offices of the Government, the British Political Agency and the post office are situated on the north side of the town. A new and up-to-date customs house has been completed and is situated immediately east of the pier. The electric lighting plant, the property of the Government, is in the north-east corner of the town. South of the town is the fort which serves both as police barracks and prison. New police barracks have been built in the vicinity of the fort and there are also police stations at MUHARRAK, AT HADD and BUDAIYAA. The strength of the BAHRAIN native police is at present 350 N.C.O.s and men. They are fully armed and militarily trained. (5) Commercial Establishments Oil In 1930 the Standard Oil Company of California acquired the oil concession, and it is now being exploited by a subsidiary company known as the Bahrain Petroleum Company. On the transfer being made, H.M. Government were able to make the following conditions :— [a) That the Bahrain Petroleum Company shall be a British company with an office in ENGLAND in charge of a British subject. [b) That one director shall be a British subject. (c) That a chief local representative approved by H.M. Government shall represent the company in BAHRAIN. (d) That as many employees as possible in BAHRAIN shall be British or Bahrainis. Large tanks have been built and the storage capacity on SITRAH Island is over 84,000,000 gallons. • A submarine pipe-line over three miles long was constructed to take the oil into navigable waters. The first mile of this pipe-line was built on piers above high water mark. Owing to the difficulty in finding a market for crude oil the company decided in 1935 to erect a rehnery which can now compete with approximately 20,000 barrels daily. The total number of producing wells at the end of the year 1939 was 66, three of these being in the “ fourth pay ” horizon. Total production for the year 1939 was 7,588,544 barrels of crude oil. Royalty paid to the Bahrain Government for the first half of 1939 was Rs. 15,49,278-12-8, and for the second half was Rs. 16,25,544-1-4. At the end of the year the company’s employees numbered as follows British Americans .. British Indians \ Bahrainis Others 192 67 374 1,878 399 Rehnery operating facilities were improved during the year by the addition of the following major units :— Polymerization plant. New oxygen plant. Gas oil stripper. Reformed gasoline lead sulphide plant. Inhibitor plant. Altogether 12 tanks were added at the rehnery. The following rehned products are exported :— Ethylized gasoline. Straight gasoline. Kerosene. Diesel oil. Luel oil.24 Repair Facilities The Bahrain Petroleum Company have a well-equipped workshop at their mam camp, which is several miles from the landing pier at SITRAH. Welding plants are avatlable but there are no facilities for casting. Small jobs, such as repairs to ships boats and auxiliary machinery, could be undertaken. Living and recreational facilities were considerably improved during the year. During the early part of 1939 negotiations for the unallotted area continued between the Bahrain Government and the Bahrain Petroleum Company, Limited, and Petroleum Concessions, Limited. After a careful consideration of the offers made by both companies, His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain announced his intention of granting a concession for the whole area, subject to the approval of His Majesty’s Government, to the Bahrain Petroleum Company. There are no commercial shipbuilding or engineering works, but there are many boatbuilding yards, most of the launches in the Gulf being built here. No coal. The A.I.O.C. have a quantity of kerosene and petrol available in tins. (7) Air Facilities [see also Section IV (3)) (a) For Aeroplanes A landing ground about 1,000 by 870 yards, which is used by Imperial Airways, is situated on MUHARRAK Island and consists of an area of hard sand. There is also a R.A.F. aerodrome which is 1,000 yards square and suitable for any type of aircraft. The approaches are al clear from north, south, east and 'west. Prevailing wind, north-west. An average stock of 70,000 gallons of aviation spirit is kept at Bahrain, also 15,000 gallons of lubricating oil. If necessary to remain the night, passengers can be accommodated in the Imperial Airways rest house on MUHARRAK Island. The R.A.F. is constructing a building to house officers and men near the landing ground. (&amp;) For Seaplanes ' ,, The Royal Air Force anchorage with four buoys is situated at the south-east of the town on KHOR KALIYA. Another anchorage, suitable only for Southamptons and smaller craft, exists at KHOR LUPIN to the south of the town. Seaplanes can alight anywhere in the inner harbour near the flying boats’ moorings or near the sloops’ anchorage. Shallow water can be seen from the air quite easily. (9) Power Plants Electric lighting plant consisting of two generating sets, each consisting of a 150-b.h.p. oil-driven engine, direct-coupled to a 100-kilowatt generator. (10) Transport Facilities [a) Railway Nil. [b) Roads There are numerous road tracks all over the island, the majority being suitable for motor traffic in fair weather only. There has been considerable road-making activity since the Bahrain Petroleum Company established itself in the State. This company constructs and maintains roads in all parts of the concession area and the Government can now confine its road work to areas in which the company is not interested. The following are the most important roads in the State :— (i) MANAMAH-RIFA. This is the most important road in the island and is maintained by the Bahrain Petroleum Company. It is fit for motor traffic in all weathers. From RIFA the road is continued to the oil fields at JEBEL AD DUKHAN. (ii) MANAMAH-MUHARRAK. This road, which links MANAMAH with MUHARRAK Island, runs for about 1,200 yards over the newly-constructed causeway. It is 32 it. wide and fit for motor traffic in all weathers. (iii) MANAMAH-BUDAIYAA. This road, which was recently constructed, runs across country and brings BUDAIYAA within 20 minutes’ journey by car from REN AM AH. There are motor bus services to and from the end of the MANAMAH-MUHARRAK causeway and a bus service to MUHARRAK, AL HADD and other villages in MUHARRAK Island is projected. There are also numerous taxis in MANAMAH.25 (c) Waterways Numerous launches and sailing boats ply regularly for hire between MANAMAH and MUHARRAK, and MANAMAH and ports on the Arabian mainland, PERSIA, IRAQ and INDIA. Normally, steamers of the B.I.S.N. Co. call weekly on their passage up and down the Gulf. The Strick and Ellerman-City lines make frequent calls, and the Hansa line one call a month. Regular calls are also made by Japanese ships of the MITSUI and YAMASHITA lines. (d) Normally the Imperial Airways four-times-weekly service to and from INDIA and the Far East calls at BAHRAIN for passengers and mails. (11) Signal Communications There is a cable to BUSHIRE, joining there with the ENGLAND-INDIA cable. BAHRAIN W/T Station is situated south-east of the town and is maintained by Cable &amp; Wireless, Ltd. {see Section IV). It has one mast, 105 ft. high, visible from the inner but not from the outer buoy, and a second mast is in course of construction. The telephone service is rapidly expanding and telephonic communication now exists over a large part of the island. (12) Defences There are no modern defences. There is no naval, military or air garrison, but there is a British-trained force of police consisting of Europeans resident at MANAMAH and at the oil camp at AWALI, numbering 200, who are armed with modern -303 rifles. Their purpose is to quell any disturbance which might be beyond the powers of the native police, and to defend the Island. (13) Reconnaissance. Information required. (14) Target Facilities Two “ Excellent ” Pattern II targets are available. Application should be made to the Naval Officer-in-Charge. DOHA (Lat. 25° 17' N., Long. 51° 33' E.) {See Plan 11 and Admiralty Charts 2837b and 2830.) (1) General Remarks DOHA is the principal (and the only protected) port of QATAR. The principality has achieved increased importance since the grant of an oil concession in 1935 to Petroleum Development (Qatar), Ltd. With the granting of this concession the Shaikh was guaranteed, by H.M. Government, protection against outside aggression by land as well as by sea. The other Trucial Shaikhs are guaranteed against aggression by sea only. In the event of naval assistance being required, this could be given only at DOHA. The harbour at DOHA is fairly well protected by reefs and sand banks and has a depth of 3-5 fathoms. The approaches are, however, difficult, as some ten miles east-north-eastward there are shoals of 1 £-1 f fathoms between which it is necessary to pass. It is essential, therefore, to sight the town in order to enter on a course which will clear these shoals. This is best done by approaching in the early morning, shortly after dawn. It is reported that a four-fathom channel exists to the southward and a survey of this area will probably be carried out in the near future. The development of the port as an oil base is dependent on deeper water for tankers being found. (2) Port Facilities „ There is a small Customs jetty, which small pulling boats Can go alongside at most stages of the tide. Landing of numbers would be a slow process. There are no facilities for dealing with cargo. There are approximately 300 pearling dhows, 40 other seagoing dhows and 70 fishing boats. The Shaikh owns the only motor dhow. \26 (3) The Town The town of DOHA was primitively fortified by the Turks, but abandoned by them in 1915, when they left behind three guns, 500 shell and 105,000 rounds of ammunition It consists mostly of stone houses and from the sea strongly resembles a Maltese village. Ihe only building of any size is the Shaikh’s fort. The population is about 12,000. Fairly good water is obtainable from a group of wells at MUSHAIRIB, one mile west of the town. In the event of troops being stationed in QATAR, the most suitable place would_be at RAYIN, seven miles west of DOHA. There is good water, and plenty of shade in the gardens attached to another palace of the Shaikh. There are no local resources for supplies. The climate is dry. (4) Government Establishments Nil. (5) Commercial Establishments Small boat-building establishments only. Small quantities of commercial petrol are available. (6) Aircraft Factories Nil. (7) Air Facilities (see also Section IV (3)) A marked landing ground, 1,000 yds. by 380 yds., exists two miles north of the town. There are no repair facilities. R.A.F. fuel, 4,000 gallons ; oil, 200 gallons ; poor and limited supply of water. Seaplane anchorage is possible in the harbour. (8) War Material Factories Nil. (9) Power Plants Nil. (10) Transport Facilities Roads fit for light M.T. exist (i) between DOHA and DHA’AIN, (ii) between DOHA and A WAIN AT BIN HASSAIN, (hi) between DOHA and KARA’ANA, with branch to UMM TAGA and (iv) DOHA to WAKRAH. Tracks extend :— (a) to SALWA WELLS (south-westerly corner of Peninsula), and (b) to ZUBARA (abreast BAHRAIN ISLAND). (11) Signal Communications Nil. It is probable that a small wireless installation will be erected when the oil company commences work. (12) Defences Nil. (13) Reconnaissance Information required.27 HODEIDA AND RAS KETHIB (Lat. 14° 48' N., Long. 42° 55' E.) {See Plan No. 3 and Admiralty Chart 14.) (1) General Remarks HODEIDA ROADS is an open anchorage, unsuitable as an advanced naval base. During the winter months, from September to May, the prevailing winds are from the south-west, accompanied by a heavy swell. During this period tho wind often blows with considerable force for four or five days, followed usually by a short calm of one or two days duration. When winds are strong the swell renders all forms of service boat transport very hazardous, and in these conditions it is advisable to use only native craft. During the summer months the winds are from north to west and are not so strong. RAS KETHIB, about 8 miles north of HODEIDA ROAD, is classed as a “ D ” anchorage, with 4 fathoms in the approach and from 4 to 6 fathoms in the anchorage. It is unsuitable for defence and visible from seawards. The anchorage which is accessible to small cruisers and destroyers, is 3 miles long by miles wide, with good holding ground. Extensive reefs protect it from the south and west, making it a suitable anchorage for the winter months. A considerable trade is carried out by dhows all down the coast. (2) Port Facilities The harbour consists of two projecting moles and a breakwater, and gives no protection to small craft during rough weather. The harbour has silted up considerably between the moles, and the only possible method of landing is by motor boat and skiff ; the best times are before 0800 or after 1600 owing to the strong north-westerly wind which blows during the day. The two jetties can just accommodate a skiff at low water. Dhows anchor off the jetties and produce is carried on the backs of labourers or slaves. The rise and fall of the tide is about 3 ft., but it is very dependent on the direction of the wind. In spite of the large amount of trade handled by the port, the facilities are very poor. All ships must anchor about miles from the town and stores are transferred in native craft to the shore. There are usually about 30 to 40 sailing dhows available for this work. The capacity of the port is estimated at from 100 to 150 d.w. tons per day. (3) The Town HODEIDA is a large town with a population of about 30,000. The more important buildings are on or near the sea front (with the exception of the Governor’s residence, which lies at the north-east corner of the town) and are built of mud bricks—-made without any binding material and very liable to disintegrate—or occasionally of stone. The remainder of the town consists of mud huts or small houses. It is generally, like all Arabian towns, dirty, insanitary and unhealthy. The country between HODEIDA and the mountains is sterile, until the higher ground is reached inland. Defences There are two forts, north and south of the town, both falling into ruins, but conspicuous from seaward. The southern one is in use for ceremonial purposes, e.g., returning national salutes. Water Supply Local wells are brackish and good water has to be brought from some distance. Lighting System There is no electrical supply for lighting. Lamps (paraffin) are laigely used foi lighting in the town. Government The town and adjoining coastal plain (the ‘ Tabama ) are administered by a Governor appointed by the Imam of the Yemen. Municipal Offices The Law Court and Municipal Offices are included in the same budding, near the southern end of the sea front. Next to this building is the Arab Government Rest House, and next to this again the prison, which is the last stone building on the front* \28 Hospitals A small clinic is run by a resident Italian doctor. This is suitable only for natives. Billetting Suitable accommodation for troops might be found in a large building at the northern end of the town. This was originally intended as a hospital, but is now in use as a banack for the local troop levy. (4) Government Establishments None. (5) Commercial Establishments Messrs. Gellatly, Hankey &amp; Co., Ltd., Shipping Agents. Messrs. Liverato &amp; Cie., Shipping Agents (Italian). Messrs. Cowasjee Dinshaw &amp; Bros, (of ADEN), Shipping Agents (Agent only). No engineering works or depots are known. (6) Aircraft Factories None. (7) Air Facilities There is a stretch of ground about 1 mile north-north-west from the town, which is suitable as a landing ground. This area lies between the hillock, 20 ft. high (on which stands a red blockhouse), see Admiralty Chart No. 14, and the shore, to the westward. The surface is smooth and hard, but small salt deposits indicate that it is liable to inundation during strong south-westerly winds. In these circumstances the surface is probably unsuitable for aircraft. Floatplanes and flying boats might sometimes use HODEIDA ROAD during the summer months, but in the winter it would be necessary to make use of one of the lagoons enclosed by RAS KETHIB peninsula. The southernmost lagoon is well sheltered from any sea and although not very deep it is reported to be suitable for use by floatplanes. The shores in places are liable to be dangerously soft. (8) War Material Factories None. (9) Power Plants None. (10) Transport Facilities Rail None. Roads There is a road to SAN’A which, though not very good, is passable for motor transport all the year round. The time taken for the journey is 13 hours by car and 24 by lorry. There are also passable car tracks to ZEIDIYA, MEDI, MOCHA and SHEIKH SAID. Sea Steamers of Besse,.Strick and Cowasjee Dinshaw lines call at irregular intervals. Italian, Soviet and Greek steamers also call occasionally, but only if they have cargo for HODEIDA. Air None. (11) Signal Communications W/T The W/T station at HODEIDA, formerly operated by Italians, broke down in December, 1933, and since then all external communication has been passed by the Italian operated W/T Station at SAN’A, to ASMARA. I29 LfT Telegraph connects HODEIDA to SAN’A, which in turn is in communication with the bigger towns in the YEMEN, also through SHEIKH SAYED by a cable to PERIM, and so to the Eastern Telegraph Co.’s cable system (1936). Cable None. (12) Defences The defences of HODEIDA are of a primitive nature In about 1932 the Yemeni Govern ment erected a chain of small towers round the town on the landward side. Further towers are placed on RAS KETHIB peninsula, one on the hill 26 ft. high and another near the northern end on the 52-ft. hill [see Chart No. 14). These towers are strongly built of brick and command the surrounding low lying country, but owing to the fact that they leave the only good water supply unprotected, their tactical value is small. The fort to the southward of the town is in fair repair and is reported to contain four old held guns, which form the saluting battery. Local Garrison Appears to vary considerably in strength. The local levy is ill equipped, with old rifles, but there is always a small number of troops from SAN’A present, who are as a rule equipped with modern rides in good condition. Strength, say, 300 all told. (13) Reconnaissance In considering suitable landing places for troops, the prevailing weather conditions must be taken into account. During the summer months troops could be landed at any time on the coast immediately to the north and south of the town. Apart from the rocks lying off KIDF AL MANE AH AH, there are no navigational dangers for boats. The beaches are sandy and gently sloping, and immediately inshore the ground is hat and even. If the defending force were sufficiently strong to prevent a landing in the immediate neighbourhood of the town, the most suitable landing beach would be that immediately to the south-east of KIDF AL MANLAHAH. Here the ground affords little cover, but by occupying the hill 20 ft. high, on which stands a tower, a commanding view and held of hre would be obtained over the low sand hills further inshore. The emergency landing ground or floatplane lagoon would at the same time be secured for refuelling co-operating aircraft. An alternative landing could be made to the southward of the fort, and the high ground abreast the beach occupied. In winter continuous communication with the shore could only be guaranteed in the neighbourhood of RAS KETHIB anchorage. Troops operating • against HODEIDA could be landed on the sandy beaches to the northward of DJEBANAH, where it is reported there are fresh water wells. Alternative landing could be made at RAS KETHIB, and an advance made along the isthmus supported from seaward. Although this isthmus is liable to inundation during strong south-westerly winds, it is said never to become completely impassable. The disused railway shown on Chart No. 14 does not now exist. JEDDA (Lat. 21° 29' N„ Long. 39° 11' E.) (See Plan 22 and Admiralty Chart 2599.) (1) General Remarks JEDDA is the principal port of the kingdom of SA’UDI-ARABIA, but, in common with the whole of the Hedjaz, it derives its main revenue from the annual pilgrimage to MECCA. Anchorage is available for large ships over an area about half-a-mile wide and 2 • 0 miles long in depths between 5 and 20 fathoms in outer anchorage, between the two outer lines of reefs, while smaller ships, destroyers or sloops, may proceed to the inner anchorage, and so lie about 1 mile from the town. JEDDA is administered by a Governor, and a military garrison is maintained. (2) Port Facilities All ships calling at Jedda must either moor in the inner harbour or, if of over 18 ft. draught, must anchor in the outer harbour. The inner anchorage is about 14 miles from the shore and the outer harbour about 3 miles. All transport between ship and shore must be done by craft of less than 3 ft. draught, in order to be able to negotiate the reef channels. There are about 150 dhows and about 12 small motor launches suitable for this work.30 The passage to the inner anchorage has recently been buoyed by the Saudi-Arab an Mining Syndicate who have also built an 80-ft. high beacon, which is visible for 12 mile,, on MISMARI reef some 10 miles to the south-east of the port There are no lights, however, and the port cannot be approached with safety at night. There is one quay about 100 yards long extending along the shore mth a small jetty nroiecting about 30 ft. seawards. The depth alongside the quay is about 4 ft. The Banque Mil ” have started the dredging of the existing channel for small craft between the inner road- stead and the quay. About l 1 miles north of the town the Saudi-Arabian Mining Syndicate have constructed a ietty fboutTsOO yards long, from the western shore of MANGABA Bay to a position oio oq'’cq' iq 39 0 09' 44' E. on the eastern side of the northern basm of the inner anchoragt . Vessels of 12 ft. draught can now load at this jetty, which carries a decauville rai way, oiry track and pipeline. At the seaward end of the jetty are a 15-ton and 5-ton crane. There are no other harbour facilities except those mentioned above, all transport of merchandise being done by manual labour. The capacity of the port is estimated at from 300 to 500 d.w. tons per day. (3) The Town The town of TEDDA is a haphazard collection of tall and often massive buildings of white-washed coral, separated by narrow tortuous streets and enclosed m a dilapidated coral- built wall, 10 to 12 ft. high ; the majority of the houses are m a very bad state of repair, borders the sea for about three-quarters-of-a-mile and extends inland on slightly rising ground to a depth of about half-a-mile. Population The resident population of Jedda is about 15,000, but during the pilgrimage season, i e during the first half of the Christian year there is an average additional floating population of 10,000 pilgrims. The foreign community is about 50 all told, grouped m the nine foreign missions—British, Dutch, Italian, French, Persian, Turkish, Egyptian, Iiaqi and Soviet and in the few British, Dutch and Italian commercial concerns. It includes a number of women. The resident foreign Asiatic and African colonies e.g the BntishMndian of some 400 souls and the British West African of some 500, are so closely meiged with the rest of the population as to be indistinguishable from it. Industries There are no industries in Jedda The population lives on the pilgrims and the small import trade There are practically no exports. The bulk of the town is residential. Lighting The present municipal system is by oil and petrol vapour lamps. All the leading houses have their own private electric lighting sets. Water The main water supply is drawn from rain water cisterns dug outside the town, but the water is brackish and impure. There are two Government-owned sea water condensers erected in 1928, with a combined capacity of 200 tons a day. There are tank dhows oi conveying distilled water to ships. A pipe line conveying fresh water (well) from inland has been completed, but at present •the water so brought is very Impure on arrival at Jedda. Sanitation This consists of a number of private cesspits under the houses and streets and one or two main drains which are said to reach the sea. The streets are kept tolerably clean. Hospitals There is one well-built but badly administered Government Hospital. Foreign missions maintain their own dispensaries. There is a Dutch resident doctor.31 Principal Buildings Many of the principal buildings are suitable for billeting troops. The Green Palace, Barracks and Aerodrome which lie to the north-eastward outside the town are also suitable. Extensive buildings, including offices, storerooms, workshops and living quarters, have been built by the Saudi-Arabian Mining Syndicate on the north shore of MANGABA Bay. about 1| miles north of the town. (4) Government Establishments The only military establishments are :— The barracks, which lie to the north-east of the town. This is a low square building, 70 by 50 yards, around an open court yard, which can hold about 200 regulars and all the military stores at Jedda. There are three muzzle-loading Turkish field guns for saluting purposes. The aerodrome {see paragraph (7)). Police headquarters and prison, which lie inside the wall on the north-west corner of the town. (5) Commercial Establishments There, are no commercial shipbuilding or engineering concerns or facilities for repair work. The average stocks of petrol and paraffin kept by the various British importing firms is about 60,000 gallons of each. There is no oil fuel available. Immediately north of MANGABA Bay are three tanks for diesel oil which are the property of the Saudi-Arabian Mining Syndicate. Two of these tanks have a capacity of 2,000 tons each and the other tank a capacity of 1,000 tons. (7) Air Facilities For Aeroplanes There are three landing grounds in the neighbourhood of the town, one to the north-east, one, which is a newer one, to the north just outside the Medina Gate, and one about 1| miles further to the north, which is used by the Saudi-Arabian Mining Syndicate (an Anglo- American concern working gold mines about 280 ft. inland). There are no repair facilities. The inner anchorage should be suitable for seaplane work. The shore reef to the north of the town is of flat coral type, which might easily be converted into a slipway. Flying boats could operate from and moor in the inner anchorage, but owing to the narrowness of the clear channel in an east-west direction, operating would probably be restricted in easterly or westerly winds. (9) Power Plants Messrs. Gellatly, Hankey &amp; Co.’s electric lighting plant. No others known. (10) Transport Facilities KHEDIVIAL mail ships and Italian coastal ships call weekly, and boats of Strick Line at rather longer intervals, of about a month. During the season numbers of large ships call to bring pilgrims. Roads There are no metalled roads, but desert tracks suitable for cars and light lorries run to MECCA, MEDINA and to the north and south along the coast. A sum of £50,000 has been earmarked, however, for widening and paving the road to MECCA, and it is expected that the work will shortly be completed. MECCA can be reached in 2J hours (40 miles) and MEDINA (200 miles) in two days when the track is in good condition. There are a few cars in the town and an increasing number of trucks and 12-seater buses, which are displacing the former more primitive forms of transport for the pilgrim traffic. Rail and Air There are no railways or air services. (11) Signal Communications (a) Telegraph There is one submarine cable to PORT SUDAN, run jointly by the Sudan Government and the Eastern Telegraph Company, and a land line to MECCA and TAIF, &lt;&lt;32 (6) Tdephone A telephone exchange serves Jedda and links it with MECCA and TAIF. (c) w/r M/F and H/F transmitters are in use (see Section IV). (12) Defences (a) There are no fixed guns or other defences of any description. The regular garrison normally consists of 40 men, including the police, who are armed ; but it is sometimes raised to 200 during the presence of the King. (b) The narrow reef passages could be quickly and economically closed by mines or nets. (c) The town is extremely vulnerable to gunfire by reason of its dense concentration and the flimsy construction of the buildings. Owing to the large use of wood, fires would spread rapidly. (13) Reconnaissance. Chart No. 8c. (a) Owing to the maze of off-shore reefs in the Bay of JEDDA, the approach of a hostile force would have to be carried out in daylight, and even if this could be accepted, the passage of boats ashore would be a long one, and would of necessity follow the few surveyed channels with a consequent complete loss of surprise. (b) It therefore follows that any surprise landing must be carried out outside the confines of the Bay, and for this purpose the coastline to the north possesses the following advantages :— (i) It is closer to the town, which lies towards the northern end of the Bay. (ii) It is free from the navigational dangers which to the southward stretch from the vicinity of IRK-EL-GHORAB reef to the KATAH KIDAN reef. (c) Northern Coastline. —From approximately 1 mile north of RAS GAHAZ, as far as SHERM UBHUR (a distance of 10 miles) the coastline consists of low coral cliffs alternating with sandy beaches. At a distance of 150-200 yards there is a continuous coral reef, the depth of water in-shore of it being not more than 3 ft. The reef itself is covered and breaks, though it is possible that lightly loaded boats could pass over it. Should this be impracticable, armed men could land on the reef and wade ashore, provided that strong winds did not make the grounding of boats on the reef a hazardous proceeding. Light stores could* be similarly handled. Alternatively boats of heavy draught can enter SHERM UBHUR (distant 15 miles from JEDDA), thus obtaining shelter, but it would probably be difficult to land troops dry shod. The rise and fall of the tide is about 2 ft. (d) The outstanding disadvantage of the northern coastline for a landing lies in the great depth of water off-shore, the few soundings available showing depths of 70 fathoms, ' no bottom.” Unless it were possible for troop-carrying vessels to remain under weigh while the disembarkation was in progress, they would therefore be obliged to anchor in the poorly charted area at the southern end of the ELIZA Shoals—a distance of some 10 miles from the coastline. This disadvantage also applies to the coast to the south of the town, though here a possible anchorage in shoal waters could be found somewhat closer in-shore. The approach to either of these shoals areas would require to be made during daylight except in the improbable event of considerable survey work and in the erection of navigational aids being possible in advance. (e) The Plain. —The plain in-shore of the beaches rises within a hundred yards to a height of above 15 ft., and is generally gently undulating. The surface is firm in most places except at the head of RUBA T’ASHARA, where to a distance of a mile the infiltration of the sea sometimes renders the ground sufficiently soft to prevent the passage of untracked motor vehicles. (/) The plain is covered with patches of low thorn bush and scrub, but only in rare places are these sufficiently thick to impede marching or motor traffic At these points good cover would be available for riflemen and machine guns. (g) Water and Fuel Supplies. —There are no signs of water on the plain. The dry scrub could be used for fuel. - (h) Landing grounds for aircraft could be quickly arranged, and in an emergency aircraft would have no difficulty in landing anywhere in the area. (i) The plain and beaches to the southward of the town were not visited, but it is understood that the characteristics are the same as those described above.33 KAMARAN (Lat. 15° 21' N., Long. 42° 36' E.) (See Admiralty Charts 543 and 8D.) (1) General Remarks KAMARAN Island is situated in the southern area of the Red Sea, close to the YEMEN coast and is about 12 miles long, 4 miles broad, with an area of about 22 square miles. The area between the Island and the mainland is 8 miles long by 3 to 4J miles wide, with good holding ground, and is suitable for a large fleet. This anchorage (Class “ A ”) is open to north-north-east winds only, which are infrequent and is otherwise well sheltered, fairly easily defended but not secure from seaward observation. The southern entrance is the usual one and is marked by buoys, making it easy to negotiate, but the depth in the fairway is only 6 fathoms, so that modern capital ships would have to approach from the northward along the recommended track shown on Chart 8D. The passage is clear and available for modern capital ships. The harbour is free from swell and, apart from the climate, would be suitable for the establishment of repair facilities, including large and small floating docks, and for an air station covering the necessities of an advanced naval base. The harbour is suitable for mining at both northern and southern entrances. Dredging is not necessary. Ships drawing 30 ft. could enter safely at either entrance during daylight. There are no lights. No improvements are in progress or contemplated. During the pilgrim season of approximately six months, about sixty ocean-going vessels call. The Island is extremely healthy, very dry and never excessively hot. Maximum tempera ture recorded during 1938 was 101° and minimum 62-l 0 . A strong wind, often developing into gale force, prevails throughout the cold season, October-April. During the hot weather a delightfully cool breeze from the north prevails after mid-day. Cyclones are rare, but a severe one was experienced during September, 1936. Dust storms are common throughout the hot weather. The cold weather is extremely pleasant and after sundown woollen pullovers are a necessity. The accepted average rainfall for the Island is given as 2-| in. : expected during November to end of February and during March. The south wind usually commences in early October and continues with calm periods of from 7-10 days till the end of April or even into very early May. The strongest wind, recorded in 1938, was force 9 and in 1939, force 7. KAMARAN inner harbour is well sheltered and coastal steamers anchored therein have no difficulty in discharging or off-loading cargo in all weathers. H.M. sloops also anchor occasionally in the inner harbour, but as the surrounding cliffs block the cool breezes, the outer harbour for anchoring is usually selected. May can be described as the windless month : between June and September is a period which can only be termed treacherous. Without the slightest warning the wind may suddenly increase to great force, probably 80-90 miles an hour—usually in terrific gusts of uncertain strength which might easily drive ships in the outer harbour resting on a single anchor, to -dangerous reefs on the coast line. Ships remaining for any length of time during the months of June, July and August would do well to drop two anchors. (See also Red Sea and Gulf of Aden Pilot.) The island was formerly a Turkish possession and has been in British occupation since 1915. It is not expressly mentioned in the Treaty of Lausanne. No settlement of the future of KAMARAN was effected at the time of the Treaty and none has been effected since, so that its political status remains undefined. It is at present administered by the Government of INDIA through a Civil Administrator who is under the control of the Governor of ADEN. The island contains a Quarantine Station for pilgrims on their way to MECCA from the East, through which about 66,1)00 pilgrims pass annually, and which, under an Anglo-Dutch Agreement, signed in 1926, is managed jointly by the Governments of INDIA and the DUTCH EAST INDIES. This covers the general supervision and control, including medical arrange ments of the station. The Administrator is invested with the powers of a Magistrate of the 1st Class and administers justice, with the assistance of a Kazi, for all cases affected by the Muhammadan laws. (2) Port Facilities The harbour has no wharves or docks, but there are :— Two stonework piers in the Quarantine area, about 100 ft. long and 12 ft. wide, with a depth of water of 6 ft. at the end. One arched pier in the Inner Harbour, about 150 ft. long and 6 ft. wide, with a depth of water of 4 ft. at the end. One stone pier in the harbour, 200 ft. long and 12 ft. wide, with crane at the end of the pier, where there is a depth of water of 6 ft. All are stone-work piers; are suitable for lighters and have light trolley lines on them,34 Lifting Appliances One crane—hand worked—on stone pier in the harbour. Lifting capacity two tons. Four ft clearance There is one small tug (not sea-going) employed for towing lighters for the disembarkation of pilgrims. Details I.H.P. 175, length 60 ft., beam 12 ft., draught 6 ft. and speed 9| knots. There are two pilgrim lighters of 32 tons cubic capacity and one dhow, fitted with water tanks, capacity 14 tons. (3) The Town The main settlement on the Island is the Lazaretto or Quarantine Station and adjacent KAMARAN Village, situated on the shores of the Inner Harbour on the eastern side of the Island. There are about 500 stone houses, and 150 matting houses enclosed by a shallow dyke. Most of the houses are stone built and in the Quarantine Station facilities exist for dealing with about 6,000 pilgrims at a time. There is a R.A.F. rest house and guest house with accommodation for about eight people. There is one small hospital on the south side of the harbour with 12 beds. It is not suitable for Europeans. There is a large ice-making plant capable of supplying up to 8 tons of ice per diem and a distilling plant capable of delivering 50 tons of water daily with tanks ashore holding a reserve of 200 tons. Condensed water and ice can be obtained by ships on application to the quarantine authorities. Good water is available from a well, situated about \\ miles south-south-west of KAMARAN native village and pumped by a windmill. A pipe-line to the main settlement has been completed, and water is now supplied from this source. The village and Quarantine Station are lit by electricity, giving power for electric fans. In addition to the Administrator, an electrical engineer (British) and a Dutch doctor, together with several Eurasians, live in the island. There are three villages in the island, with a total population of about 2,500, employed mainly in connection with the Quarantine Station. There are also a few fishermen. There axe fairly good recreational facilities comprising two football grounds, one hockey ground, several sites for matting cricket pitches, one hard tennis court (belonging to the Administrator) and a small bathing pool. There is also a rifle range with four trolley targets, with ranges of 100, 200, 300 and 400 yards. As regards supplies, there are no stocks of coal or oil fuel. 500 gallons of petrol is kept for use of R.A.F. machines visiting the island from ADEN. Chickens and eggs are obtainable locally, but vegetables rarely, except at certain seasons, when they can be bought from the mainland. Fish is plentiful and cheap. (4) Government Establishments There is no dockyard or repair base. (5) Commercial Establishments One small workshop, sufficient to maintain the two condensers, ice plant and lighting plant. (7) Air Facilities There is an aerodrome at KAMARAN about 1 mile north of harbour, of which the distinctive white circle shows up clearly from the air. It is 600 yards by 700 yards and has an excellent surface of hard sand. It is, however, liable to become waterlogged for a few hours after rain. There is no hangar but there are three permanent moorings for Vincent type aircraft. There is accommodation for personnel with the Administrator and stocks of petrol and oil. This landing ground is used by the R.A.F. There are no facilities for night-flying. KAMARAN harbour is suitable for use by seaplanes except at times during the winter months when a strong wind from the south blows into the anchorage. The edge of the coral reef is easily discernible from the air. There are three seaplane moorings. (8) War Material Factories None. (9) Power Plants Three identical generating sets, each consisting- of :—- (i) Prime mover—vertical, twin cylinder, Fetter “ C ” type heavy oil engine working on the 2-stroke cycle principle, developing 50 b.h.p at 375 r.p.m., direct coupled to (ii) Generator—continuous current, compound wound, with a maximum output of 136 amps and a voltage of 230. The plant is situated between the two prominent chimneys on the north side of the harbour.35 (10) Transport Facilities There is no railway. Communication by sea with ADEN and the adjacent coast is possible by the Cowasjee Dinshaw (small) coasting steamers once a fortnight which carry mails. Mails are also conveyed by R.A.F. plane once a fortnight when one is available. Roads are simply well-used tracks from village to village, and connecting points of cultivation. It is possible to take a car to almost any point in the island by this means. (11) Signal Communications There is no cable in operation. The cable connecting the island with PERIM and SALIFF (on the adjacent coast) has been out of use for some time but it is not known whether the actual cable is still laid. There are two W/T sets with two masts situated north-west of North Point : [a) Marconi type “ U ” C.W./I.C.W.—3 kilowatt—range, 300 miles ; (b) Marconi type R.M. 4B—range, 300 to 2,500 metres. Communication is possible with ADEN and ships. It is very vulnerable to attack. (12) Defences There are no defences. The Quarantine Station is garrisoned by one platoon of Arab levies from ADEN under the command of a native officer. These troops recently replaced the garrison of Yemen infantry. (13) Reconnaissance The extent of the sheltered harbour ensures the value of KAMARAN as a base but the approaches are in mineable water. Landing places in the Harbour (a) Under hospital on South Shore : shelving sandy beach meeting cliffs and steep ground rising to about 50 ft. (b) Pier on South Shore by ruined fo'rt giving access to flat ground with houses on foreshore and mound on which stands the ruined fort beyond. (c) Coal pier on North Shore : 15 ft. broad and with a least depth during summer (low) level of 4 ft. at the end only. There are steps and a 2-ton crane. Trolley lines run inshore to flat ground bounded on north-west by rising ground on which are situated the barracks, and on north-east by the workshops and another eminence on which are the administrative quarters. (d) Lazaretto Pier with hut and flagstaff on the end and steps both sides. Least depth (summer low level) 4 ft. at the extremity : gives access by steps to steep ground about 50 ft. high on which are the administrative offices and distilling plant. Quarantine Piers (| mile north of North Point) (i) Landing Places. —Piers enclose a sandy beach 400 yards in extent with 6 ft. (summer low level) 70 yards out shelving to 2 ft. close in. A trolley track runs round the beach with quarantine buildings scattered in background—those on the right front stand on slightly elevated ground with mounds to the southward and flat ground between rising very slightly to the main plateau. Small Bay, 1| miles north oj North Point, with Ruined Pier (i) Landing Places. —Sandy beach, 150 yards in extent with 4 ft. of water at end of pier, shoaling gradually. The pier is in ruins at the end and landing would be best effected by wading. Beach is flanked on either side by undercut cliffs about 15 ft. high. A ruin and tower stand in the middle of flat ground which subsequently rises steeply about 70 yards from the water to the main plateau 15 ft. above. An old roadway leads from the pier to the plateau between the ruin and the tower. Hamdieh Harbour, south-west side (i) Landing Places. —Small beach, coral and sand, 150 yards in extent close inside RAS HADI BIN MOOSA. Three fathoms water about 50 yards out, shelving to 2\ ft. close inshore ; bordered by steep rocky prominences on either side ; ground rising steeply at first in most parts, then gradually to the plateau. Considered generally the best beach.36 KUWAIT Lat. 20° 21' N„ Long. 48° 6' E. (See Plan No. 20 and Admiralty Charts 1213, 1214 and 22) (1) General Remarks Though situated strategically at the head of the Gulf the anchorage is a good one, being classed as “ A ” ; accessible to ships of all classes, partly visible from seaward at long range but not well suited for defence. The harbour is a commodious bay, 20 miles long by 10 miles broad at its maximum width, with good holding ground over the greater part. The outer part is exposed to the “ Kaus ” (S.E. wind) and the inner part or DUHAT KADHAMA to the “ Nashi ” (N.E. wind). Strong “ Shamals ” (N.W. winds) raise a nasty sea for boats along the southern shore. Ships can, however, lie safely in the harbour in any weather ; capital ships must lie north or north-east of RAS AJUZA, but lighter draught vessels can lie farther in, south of FASHT AL HADAIBAH. The approach is easy, through a deep channel 34 miles wide which could be defended. The depths in the harbour are from 10 to 16 fathoms in the entrance, from 5 to 9 fathoms in the middle and thence from 4|- to 5 fathoms deepening again to 54 and 6 fathoms towards its head which latter is shallow. DUHAT KADHAMA is suitable for a small floating dock. It will provide anchorage for large vessels but to reach it a bank, over which the depths are from 4J to 5 fathoms, must be crossed. It is one of the most important towns and ports in the Persian Gulf, being a big centre for the pearl fishing industry and for the trade of North and Central ARABIA. (2) Port Facilities There are no dry or floating docks. Numerous stone breakwaters have been built parallel to the shore to afford sheltered landings for boats. Most of the enclosed space dries about 2 to 3 ft. at M.L.W.S. Ships anchor 1 or 2 miles off the town and discharge into local craft. Landing at low tide is inconvenient as the beach dries out a considerable distance. The capacity of the port of KUWAIT is estimated (October, 1941) at 500 d.w. tons per day. The potential capacity is estimated at 1,000 d.w. tons per day. Landing Facilities The best places for landing troops are :— [a) At the Old Agency Steps. (b) At Kadhama Pier, erected by the Kuwait Oil Company on the north side of KUWAIT Bay. It is a cement pier, details of which are as follows :— Length .. .. .. .. .. .. .. 155 ft. (approx.) Width—Sea end .. .. .. .. .. .. 24 ft. 6 in. Shore end .. .. .. . . .. 12 ft. A hand operated jib crane, capacity 5 tons, is installed at the sea end of the jetty. Height from sea bed to top of jetty—sea end .. .. 9 ft. Height—shore end—from shore .. .. .. .. 1 ft. 6 in. Height to top of jetty from low water springs .. 13 ft. 6 in. ^approx.) Depth of water-—high water springs—sea end .. . . 7 ft. 9 in. Depth of water—high water neaps—-sea end .. .. 4 ft. The approach to the shore is shallow and the nearest a. boat drawing 4 ft. can close the old Agency breakwater at M.L.W.S. is about 100 yards. BANDAR SHUWAIKH is a small basin about 1-| miles south-west of the town of KUWAIT in which the depths are from 2--6f fathoms with a mud bottom. The channel to it passes eastward of ALAKAZ—a large reef lying about 1| miles westward of the southern part of KUWAIT town. There are two jetties at Bandar Shuwaikh. A concrete jetty on the foreshore 300 ft. long with a minimum width of 16 ft. has been completed. This jetty which extends seaward from the maximum high tide mark is 100 ft. from the road giving a total length of 400 ft. The end of the completed work does not extend as far as the low water spring tide mark, but it is used for unloading lighters as there is approximately 8 ft. of water at the head at high water neap tides. Proposals have been put forward to extend the'jetty by 32 ft. at right angles and raise the level 2| ft. There is also an old stone jetty approximately 300 ft. long built during the war (1914-1918). It is reported (October, 1941) to be in fair condition. There are no lifting or other appliances but with the assistance of the KUWAIT Oil Company facilities can be provided for the landing of weights up to 15 tons. Ships of 3,000 tons could here be brought to within 100 yards of the shore.37 From the foregoing, it can be realised that there is some difficulty in handling cargo except at high tide. The dhow owners are good seamen and unload cargo from ships in harbour in any weather. Preliminary investigations were made in April, 1940, by staff officers of A.H.Q., India and Middle East Command, as to the possibility of landing mechanised forces. The conclusion was reached that the practicability exists but that detailed investigations would be necessary to arrive at a correct time limit. There are 700 pearling dhows of all sizes in KUWAIT. Over 25 dhows are fitted with Kelvin and other engines, while there are 60 ' Booms ” of shallow-draught and extra beam, having capacity up to 100 tons each. The Agency owns a large motor launch, and a local contractor a small steam tug capable of towing his two 150 ft. iron lighters. There are 12 motor boats at KUWAIT of which two are Thornycroft, nine Kelvin and one Gardener, each capable of taking about 20 men with their equipment. (3) The Town The town extends for about 3^ miles along the shore and has a greatest depth of 2 miles. It has no .regular plan. The streets are irregular and winding, though many are passable for motor traffic. The bazaar (the best in the Gulf) and market place are south of the town on the edge of the desert. A mud wall, 15 ft. high encircles the town on the land side. It has four gates and towers at regular intervals of 200 yards. Its total length is 3| miles. The walls and towers are loopholed for rifle fire and in some parts there is a fire step, but both loopholes and fire steps are very dilapidated. Water Supply The extent of water available varies in summer and winter. In winter water collects after rain in hollows and remains for several months. Wells in some cases overflow. In summer water is confined to the wells ; many of these are brackish and a number dry up. The town of KUWAIT obtains its water from two lines of wells south-west and south-east of the town, but the water is of indifferent quality and Bedouins camp round the wells in large numbers during the summer. Therefore, the town mainly relies on water brought by specially fitted local sailing craft from the Shatt-al-Arab at Fao. Forty craft are always employed in water carrying. On an average six such boats arrive daily and bring approximately 35,000 gallons of water. If local craft were employed medical supervision would be necessary. Prominent buildings include the Shaikh’s palaces, the Diwan palace of the late Shaikh of MOHAMMERAH and the New and Old Agencies. The high ground of QASR-ES-SIRRAH or MISHRIF, 6 miles south-east of KUWAIT, is a good observation point. There is a ruined fort on top of it. There are no sanitary arrange ments, but the sandy soil readily absorbs sewage. In the last few years there has been an improvement in street-cleaning and in the disposal of refuse. The climate in the summer is hot but, except for short periods, very dry, and is tempered by sea breezes. The desert cools down rapidly at night. KUWAIT is the healthiest of all the Gulf ports and the absence of mosquitoes and sandflies makes it unnecessary to use mosquito nets. Tuberculosis and small-pox are the two most prevalent diseases, the latter being endemic all the year round. There have been no epidemics of cholera or plague for many years. A British surgeon is in charge of the Agency Charitable Dispensary and also acts as Quarantine Medical Officer. The dispensary is mainly confined to the medical treatment of native men, women and children. There is a hospital situated just south-west of the town run by an American Mission with a full medical staff. There is an Iraq Government Post Office in KUWAIT, but the stamps sold are Indian, surcharged “ KUWAIT.” Steps are being taken to instal a British Post Office. The popula tion of the principality, most of whom live in KUWAIT town, is about 55,000, of whom the majority are Arabs with about 10,000 Persians. This population increases to about 65,000 during the pearling season. In addition to the pearling industry the building of motor and sailing dhows is a flourishing industry. Gypsum mortar is manufactured in a large gypsiferous tract on the outskirts of the town by burning rubbish in shallow excavations. The only true local produce of KUWAIT is that yielded by the harbour fisheries, which are a valuable asset. The interior produces camels and sheep in abundance. (4) Government Establishments There are no Government buildings.3S (5) Commercial Establishments The offices of the KUWAIT Oil Company {see also Section IV, page 8) are near the American Mission. The company intends to erect more buildings and to make this area a concentration point in emergency, with a reserve of water and food. The Oil Company s water pumping station is at SHEWAIK, 2^ miles west of the town. The company has con structed a quay there and water is landed from lighters and pumped through a pipe-line to MAQWA. There is a small community—about 100 in 1939—of British and Americans, the majority being employees of the KUWAIT Oil Company living in KUWAIT. There are no other commercial, shipbuilding or engineering works except the small dhow building, electric light and ice plants and soda water factory, to which reference is made elsewhere in this section. Fuelling Facilities Stocks held at the beginning of 1941 were Petroleum Lubricating oil Aviation spirit R.A.F. fuel 20.000 gallons. 1,000 litres. 12.000 gallons. A fuel and oil store is maintained at the R.A.F. landing ground. (6) Aircraft Factories Nil. (7) Air Facilities {see also Section IV (3)) Imperial Airways have an agreement with the Shaikh for the use of the harbour near SHUWAIKH as an emergency alighting area and anchorage. This is the most suitable anchorage, as it is well sheltered from the winds. The R.A.F. landing ground, 950 by 650 yards, is to the east of KUWAIT, just outside the town walls. It has a circle and corner markings- and a fuel and oil store is maintained. R.A.F. unmarked emergency landing grounds exist at AL JAHRA and SUBAIHIYAH, just south-west of the oil wells area. A landing ground could be constructed fairly easily a mile south of MAQWA Camp and the country is such that many natural landing grounds exist all over the state, especially in the west, north and south-west and includes the following :— GRAN I WAFRAH .. RAS-UZ-ZOR RAS BARDHALK .. RAS SAFANIYAH A good landing ground. A good landing ground. Possible landing ground 1 mile north. Possible landing ground | mile north. Possible landing ground 3 miles north-west, sheltered seaplane anchorage. (8) War Material Factories None. 9) Power Plants Two electric light engines, one 50 h.p. and one 25 h.p. (250 volts D.C.)._ There is one ice plant of small capacity which is scarcely sufficient to meet the present demands of civilians, and a soda water factory, run by private enterprise under official control. (10) Transport Facilities There is no railway. The B.I.S.N. Co. “ Slow Mails ” between BOMBAY and BASRA call at KUWAIT weekly on their passage up and down the Gulf. There are 10 motor lorries and 70 touring cars available in the town for hire. The KUWAIT-IRAQ Transport Company maintain a regular bi-weekly service in each direction between KUWAIT and BASRA for mails and passengers. There are no metalled roads. Transport to the interior is normally by car and camel. Local roads, and those to the hinterland, are of sand and gravel, and are generally merely tracks, connecting groups of wells, it is easily possible to visit all the important points on the frontier by car, especially during the rainy season (October to March), when the sand and gravel surface of the hinterland improves. Camels in any quantity can be bought, but not hired. About 200 donkeys could be hired from KUWAIT and JAHRA.39 (11) Signal Communications There is a station owned and operated by the KUWAIT Oil Company. Correspondence is exclusive to that of a private enterprise. Frequencies employed are 3,000 and 3,750 kc/s, power 0-03 kw. Conducts a service with shipping and a fixed interior service. Telegraph line exists to BASRA. There is also another station, equipped with a 50-watt set, crystal frequency of 4,400 kc/s, operating frequency 8,800 kc/s. (12) Defences There are no modern defences. The Shaikh maintains a body of some 350 Bedouin mercenaries known as the “ Fidawiyah,” and can count on another 4,000-5,000 tribesmen for the purpose of defence against hostile tribes who might invade his frontier. This force has been improved recently by the introduction of a force of six Ford light lorries armed with Lewis guns, and carrying two gunners and ten men armed with rifles, which are capable of reaching any point on the frontier very quickly. Three more lorries are on order and it is intended to bring the strength of the force up to twelve eventually, together with two field wireless transport sets on lorries. The Shaikh holds a private stock of -303 rifles and about 250,000 rounds of S.A.A. in reserve. (13) Reconnaissance The question of how best to defend KUWAIT territory from an attack by land largely depends on the water supply. Apart from the wells directly outside the town walls, which have already been mentioned, the nearest supplies of water are at JAHRA, 20 miles to the westward of the town, and SUBAIHIYAH, 32 miles to the southward. These wells are on the main routes from IRAQ and HASA respectively. There are also some wells in the coast villages to the south-eastward. An attack on KUWAIT is almost impossible if these walls are denied to the enemy. Perhaps their defence would best be ensured by blockhouses and the use of armoured cars and aircraft. JAHRA, a large village at the head of KUWAIT bay and about 20 miles west of KUWAIT town, is a place of great strategic importance. Besides being on the routes to BASRA and NEJD, its wells are the last before reaching the waterless belt to the south-west. It is an important camping ground for Bedouins and a centre for NEJD and desert news. Its occupation is essential for the security of KUWAIT town and the KUWAIT-BASRA road. Billeting Facilities for Troops KUWAIT Town. A small party (say six signallers) could be accommodated at the New Agency. The Diwan Palace of the Shaikh of MOHAMMERAH is in ruins, but could shelter 40 men. The Shaikh of KUWAIT could provide tents for about 250 men at short notice, as was done for the naval landing party in 1928. The best camping site is on the east of the town, inside the walls and near the Agency and the palaces of the Shaikhs of KUWAIT and MOHAMMERAH. This site was used by the naval landing party in 1928 and is handy to cooking and washing water supplies. KUWAIT Districts JAHRA (20 miles west of KUWAIT). One brigade. Water from numerous wells. Arab fort, capable of defence. Possible landing ground. OURAIN (on southern border \ ~ of KUWAIT). SUBAIHIYAH (32 miles south of KUWAIT). WAFRAH (55 miles south of KUWAIT). Half battalion. Water from 10 good wells. One brigade. Possible landing ground. Numerous sweet wells. Two battalions. Numerous sweet wells. Possible landing grounds. Provisions Products are insignificant, consisting only of a limited supply of vegetables and a little lucerne at JAHRA. Supplies have to be largely augmented from abroad, principally BASRAH and the Persian ports. .40 MUKALLA (Lat. 14° 31' N., Long. 49° 06' E.) [See Plans Nos. 5, 6, 7 and 8 and Admiralty Chart 10.) (1) General Remarks MUKALLA (MAKALLA) is, next to ADEN, the principal port on the south coast of ARABIA. The anchorage is unclassified, being a shallow open bay, quite unsuitable tor defence, fully open to observation from seaward and accessible to any type of ship. It has a deep approach with 6 to 30 fathoms in the anchorage. There is a strip of anchorage off the town about 2 miles long and 5 cables wide, where a few ships could obtain temporary anchorage during the north-east monsoon. A ground swell comes in with the nortn-east monsoon, but the anchorage is stated to be safe then but untenable during the south-west monsoon. Ships could then find temporary anchorage off BANDAR BURUM, 13 miles to the south-west, where there is a similar anchorage but sheltered from the westward. The present Sultan, H.H. Omar Bin Awadh, is the chief of the independent rulers of the Hadramaut, who are all in loose treaty relations with GREAT BRITAIN. He is an Indian, and spends most of his time at HYDERABAD, where he owns property, leaving the administration of MUKALLA in the hands of a Wazir and a staff of grasping Indian Officials who have little sympathy with the natives. This state of affairs is causing considerable unrest amongst the Arab inhabitants, which is being sympathetically watched by the authorities at ADEN. (2) Port Facilities There are no piers or wharves accessible to steamships, although at high water dhows of about 50 tons are able to work their cargoes at the only existing wharf {see Plan 6) where troops and stores could be landed in ship’s boats. The depth of water alongside is not known, but would appear to be 6 ft. and below. There are no lifting appliances or docks. Harbour craft are limited to the local dhows. Steamships and cargo boats anchor about a mile off the promontory, where there is from 7-12 fathoms of water. From June to August, when the south-west monsoon is at its height, it is usually only possible to land merchandise at MUKALLA from dawn to about 1000 daily. After this time the wind and sea increase and dhows, etc., seek shelter in BANDAR BURUM. Landing in boats in fine weather would be possible on the small sandy beaches immediately east and stretching to the west of the promontory. (3) The Town Of recent years the population of MUKALLA has increased considerably and was estimated in 1931 at 10,000. The town is built partly on a rocky point between two bays and partly on the terraced slopes of a reddish limestone cliff. This rises to a height of 300 ft. and is defended by four towers. The western side of the town is protected by a wall extending from the cliff to the shore, possessing only one gate, which is closed at night and watched by a permanent guard. Many well-built stone houses have been erected, including the Sultan’s palace. This structure stands on the sea front at the western end of the town ; immediately behind it is the old palace, a large and permanent square building, which is now used as a guest house. Most of the inhabitants’ houses are built of stone or mud. There is a considerable number of mud huts and reed-matting shacks. The bazaar is situated on and to the west of the promontory. JEBEL AL KARA, about | mile northward of the north-western end of the town, is 1,300 ft. high, with a flat-topped summit. The main supply of water is conveyed to MUKALLA from AL BAKHRAIN (BOK HAREN) by a pipe line which empties itself into a reservoir near the guest house at the estimated capacity of 45,000 gallons per hour. There are two other reservoirs or tanks at BOK HAREN from which place water is brought in skins and sold in the town. There are other wells in the Wadi Wasit, chiefly used for irrigation purposes, as well as some in the town which are brackish. Firewood, bullocks, sheep, fowls, eggs, honey and some kinds of vegetables are obtainable and are moderate in price. Sanitation is probably non-existent. There is an electric lighting plant which supplies current to the palace and street lighting. There are no hospitals, post or telegraphic offices. A very considerable trade is carried on with INDIA, the SOMALI coast, the RED SEA p.nd MUSCAT. The exports are chiefly gums, hides, senna and a small quantity of coffee,41 A considerable coasting trade is carried on by the native sailing dhows, which vary from 100 to 400 tons, between the PERSIAN GULF and RED SEA, the greatest number arriving during the date season. During the south-west monsoon a considerable portion of the trade is diverted to BANDAR BURUM, which is a secure anchorage and in the future, as the commercial develop ment of southern ARABIA advances, it is quite possible that these two anchorages will become of great importance as alternative ports available for all vessels throughout the year. The climate in the bay is exceedingly warm during the middle of the day, and on the shore the heat is excessive, but land and sea breezes, with occasional showers of rain, mitigate it from October to April and often in June and July. The immediate vicinity of MUKALLA is particularly barren but about one mile inland, westward of the town, are large date groves and gardens with watch towers. (4) Government Establishments See under Sub-section (12) for Military Establishments. (5) Commercial Establishments There are no commercial shipbuilding or engineering firms. Fuel is available, but most of it is imported from SOMALILAND. A stock of aviation spirit and lubricating oil is maintained. There is no oil fuel stock. (6) Aircraft Factories None. (7) Air Facilities Landing Grounds (a) FUWWAH, 5 miles west along the coast from MUKALLA town, which can be reached by motor transport either by way of the sea coast when the tide is out or by inland track, 11 miles. The landing ground is 800 by 600 by 350 yards. The surface is all-weather gravel. It has a white circle and corner markings. There are no hangars or repair facilities. Fuel stocks (R.A.F.) are maintained. (b) RIYAN, about 15 miles east of MUKALLA, on the Makalla-Ghail Ba Wazir road. It is 1,000 by 350 yards and would be suitable as an emergency landing ground, operational base or for troop-carriers. (c) RAIDA, 100 miles east of MUKALLA, is the eastern-most landing ground in the KA’AITI territory with a good surface. 700 by 500 by 150 yards. There are no markings and no fuel stocks are kept. Seaplane Station Seaplanes could use either of the two bays east and west of MUKALLA promontory, where shelter in emergency, except during the south-west monsoon, is available {see Plan 5). (8) War Material Factories Believed none. Information required. (9) Power Plants Believed none. Information required. (10) Transport Facilities There is no railway or regular air communication. Steamships of the Bombay and Persia S.N. Co. frequently call at MUKALLA. Fortnightly visits are made by vessels of Messrs. Cowasjee, Dinshaw' and the Halal Shipping Company from ADEN during the trading season. Roads The only roads suitable for light M/T are—■ (а) MUKALLA to SHIHAIR (by coast via SHIHR), 35 miles. (б) SHIHAIR to GHAIL BA WAZIR, 15 miles. (c) MUKALLA to AL BAKHRAIN, 3 miles north. “ The construction of a road is contemplated (1935) . ” from SHIHAIR to TARIM in the upper HADHRAMAUT through the hill pass, which will mean that motor traffic will be able to run direct between SHIHAIR, MUKALLA and SHIBAM.42 There are also numerous well-defined camel tracks linking up MUKALLA with other ports of the HADHRAMAUT. They are generally broad and possess a good hard surface. It should be noted that there are no metalled roads in the HADHRAMAUT at all, and it is presumed that those already referred to would become impassable in wet weather. About 150 pack camels may be obtained for hire purposes for local work and about 200 to 600 camels for caravan purposes in the HADHRAMAUT. About 100 donkeys can be obtained for pack or water carrying. About 300 coolies could be hired at 10 hours’ notice and up to 1,000 with longer notice. In April, 1935, there were about thirty touring cars and fifty l|-ton trucks available at MUKALLA. (11) Signal Communications It has been reported that a W/T station was being constructed but no details are known. (12) Defences There are no modern fixed defences. The existing defences of MUKALLA are constructed to resist attack from the land rather than from the sea. On the cliffs above the town stand six stone watch-towers, chiefly for defence against Bedouin raids. These towers are kept in good repair, but are not manned or armed. The so-called regular garrison of MUKALLA does not- exceed 250 men, fifty of whom are employed on police duties in the streets. Some 400 irregular soldiers could be mustered in the town. The troops are armed mostly with old French Le Gras and German rifles. (13) Reconnaissance The approach to MUKALLA is open and clear of dangers. Landing could be effected anywhere along the sandy beach, which extends for some 12 miles to the westward of the town. Outside the gateway there stands a level plain which forms the entrance of a wadi running to the northwards inland, and which is used as the main road to and from the town. Immediately westward of this plain, the beach for about one mile is narrow and backed by steep cliffs, but further westward the foreshore opens out and gently slopes up to a low range of hills some 2| miles inland. The level plain would make an excellent camp site and it is used normally as a camping ground for camel caravans. The water pipe from AL BAKHRAIN runs along its eastern side to the tanks situated on the hill northward of the gateway. The plain has two narrow and easily defended exits to the north and northwest (see plan) and in all but the worst weathers, stores could be landed on the beach. In calm weather, landing could also be effected on the rocky shore between RAS MARBAT and RAS KODAR, but the beaches here are narrow and there is good cover for defending forces. MUSCAT (Lat. 23° 37' N„ Long. 58° 36' E.) (See Plan No. 21 and Admiralty Charts 2869 and 10C.) (1) General Remarks MUSCAT, with its sister port MATRAH, is the capital of the independent Sultanate of Muscat and Oman, situated at the south-eastern corner of ARABIA. At MUSCAT there are three harbours or bays :— Muscat Cove, at the head of which lies the town of MUSCAT. This anchorage is classed as “ E,” with 9 to 13 fathoms at entrance, shoaling gradually to 6 fathoms abreast Sira A1 Gharbi and to 2 fathoms at about a cable from the head of the cove. The cove is capable of defence but open to observation from seaward. It is 5i cables in length (to 3 fathom line) and 2| to 3£ cables in breadth ; open to north- north-west. Winds of any force between north-west and north-east send in considerable sea and swell, but the holding ground is good and vessels rarely drag. There is space for two sloops at single anchor, but three could be accommodated if sterns were secured to rocks on shore, which can be done in two places (see Plan 21). The prevailing winds throughout the year are north-west and south-east. South westerly and westerly winds also occur in winter and easterly in summer. Throughout the year about one-third of the days are calm. In January and February winds are boisterous and chilly and some rain falls. March to May fine, getting hotter. June to September very hot. October to December getting cooler, fine weather. Strong “ Shamals ” occur at all times of the year.43 Kalbuh Cove, to west of Muscat Cove, extends about three cables southward between the promontory terminating in RAS KALBUH and RAS AL BAZ. There are depths of 8 to 4 fathoms in the outer part of the cove, but this part is not used for anchorage, as it affords but little shelter. In the inner part there are depths of four fathoms to one fathom. Matrah Bay is again west of Kalbuh cove, with the town of this name at head of bay. The bay affords good shelter in a “ Shamal,” but is open to the ' Nashi.” The anchorage is off the north-west shore, three or four cables north-east of Arbak south fort. There is another small cove to westward between RAS KOWASIR and RAS AS SHATAIFI. It is open to “ Nashis,” and not used as an anchorage. At the head of the cove is the village of SHATAIFI. In brief, considering MUSCAT as a naval base, it has a good anchorage, but exposed to the “ Shamal ” and, to a lesser extent the “ Nashi,” at all times of the year. At present accommodation for personnel, piers, and other facilities are non-existent. The climate has been described as that of the hottest place in the world in the summer, though pleasant in the winter. It is a much drier heat than Bahrain and other Southern Gulf ports, and therefore fairly healthy. (2) Port Facilities These are very primitive. The only pier is the coaling one in Muscat cove extending from the coal sheds, with 4 ft. of water at its outer end. The coal sheds are now in ruins and no coal is stored. There is no inland communication from the pier. There are two wharves at MUSCAT :— [a) One, under Fort Mirani, 180 ft. long, with steps on south and east sides. There is a depth of at least 4 ft. at both steps. {b) Customs wharf, 200 ft.dong, which has no steps and is almost dry at low water. Landing can be effected on the foreshore in front of the Agency and also in Mughab Bay, which is sheltered during a ” Shamal.” Landing in boats in calm weather is also possible (i) in Matrah Bav, opposite the villages of RITAM, MATIRAH, MATRAH and ARBAH ; (ii) opposite the village of SHATAIFI, where sandy beaches exist. Harbour craft comprise about 58 lighters with a total capacity of 250 tons. There are no lifting appliances. The capacity of the port is estimated at 200 d.w. tons per day. (3) The Town The town of MUSCAT presents a picturesque appearance from the sea. The walls are on the western and southern sides, the eastern and part of the southern side being close-to, and even against, the face of the hills. The suburbs of mat huts occupy every available piece of level ground in the vicinity. MUSCAT is the capital of OMAN and though once important and prosperous, has been declining and falling into decay for a number of years. Trade has largely been diverted to the sister port of MATRAH, from whence starts the caravan route to the interior. The populations of MUSCAT and MATRAH have been (1933) estimated at 5,000 and 8,000 respectively and, counting the other small adjacent villages, the number is probably near 20,000. Date growing is the principal agricultural industry. Small quantities of a rough hand- woven cloth are made, chiefly for local use. There are no other industries. The chief exports are dried and salted fish and dates. Prominent buildings in MUSCAT are the Sultan’s palace and the British Agency and Consulate on the sea front. Southward of the Consulate is the Agency hospital of twenty beds (two of which are reserved for Europeans), in charge of which is an officer of the I.M.D. with a native sub-assistant surgeon. There is also a hospital maintained by American missionaries. Malaria and tuberculosis are frequent. Venereal disease is rife. Cholera, plague and small pox are infrequent. Sanitation is bad. Tanks for the storage of drinking water drawn from local wells combined with an aqueduct leading to the landing place southward of Mirani fort, represent the water supply. It can be supplied to H.M. ships alongside by stand pipe and is stated to be good. The tanks, however, become breeding grounds for mosquitoes, thus spreading malaria. Water can also be supplied to vessels at anchor in a water lighter of about 45 tons capacity. There are no billeting facilities. The nearest facilities for camping are at BEIT AL FELEJ, where there is ample flat ground. There is a Government of India Post Office in the Agency.44 (4) Government Establishments There is no naval dockyard or repair base. (5) Commercial Establishments There are no supplies of coal, but about 2,200 gallons of Diesel oil and 3,500 gallons of gas oil are kept. The Anglo Iranian Oil Company maintains a small depot of petrol and paraffin at a cove in RIYAM Bay. The average quantities of stocks kept are :— Petrol 6,000 gallons. Kerosene 12,000 gallons. Small stocks are also kept in MUSCAT. A supply of petrol and oil is maintained by the R.A.F. at the old coal depot at MAKALLA, approximately 20,000 gallons of petrol and 1,000 gallons of mineral oil. (7) Air Facihties (see also Section IV (3) ) The R.A.F. landing ground is at BEIT AT FELEJ, 4 miles west of MUSCA1 town, with which it is connected by road. There are a number of R.A.F. landing grounds in the territory of the Sultan and an Air Facilities Agreement exists which gives facilities to British aircraft. The harbour has a sheltered anchorage for seaplanes. Three seaplane buoys have been established north-west of FORT MIRANT A detachment of four airmen is maintained permanently at MUSCAT to attend to the wants of any aircraft that may call there. Stocks of oil and petrol are maintained. (8) War Material Factories None. (9) Power Plants A small electric light plant has recently been installed in MUSCAT, behind the Customs House. At present it is used only by the Customs and a few private individuals. (10) Transport Facilities No railway. MUSCAT is a port of call for the B.I.S.N. Co.’s subsidiary weekly mail service, and other companies such as Stricks, Ellerman City and Hansa lines call approximately monthly. A motor road now exists between MUSCAT and MATRAH with an extension inland to BEIT AL FELEJ, a distance of 5 miles. One coastal road is completed to the north as far as SHINAS, suitable for light cars only, and one towards SUR. This latter is only suitable for wheeled traffic for 5| miles (as far as RUWI). Inland transport is carried on by means of pack animals and is expensive and difficult, with only one pass, through the rugged hills surrounding the town, to the interior. (11) Signal Communications A W/T station exists at MUSCAT belonging to the R.A.F., which works with BAGHDAD and BASRA and with sloops. C. &amp; W., Ltd. Station. Telegraphy and telephony fixed, interior service. MUSCAT is connected by cable direct to KARACHI and to BUSHIRE, and is a “ repeater ” station. The Cable Office is just westward of the Agency. A private telephone line exists from the British Agency at MUSCAT to the MUSCAT Levies barracks at BEIT AL FELEJ. (12) Defences There are no modern defences of any kind. Old Portuguese forts exist at MIRANI (Western) and JALALI (Eastern) heads of Muscat Cove, on the eastern end of SIRA AL GHARBI and two on either side of the beach at the head of Matrah bay. JALALI is used as a prison. The forts are “ armed ” with numerous muzzle-loading cannon, only six of which are safe to fire, and these form the saluting battery at Fort Mirani.45 Small blockhouses command the approaches to the towns of MUSCAT and MATRAH from the land side. The forts, combined with the numerous strong points commanding MUSCAT and MATRAH, if manned by an intelligent enemy with machine guns and rifles, would make landing in boats on the beaches at or near these towns difficult, if not impossible, in daylight. The Levies are the only State Force. The composition is 150 men (mostly Baluchis) under the command of a retired British Regular Cavalry Officer with two ex Indian officers to assist him. Their chief duty is to form the Agency guard. The Barracks are at BEIT-AL-FELEJ* (13) Reconnaissance Bearing in mind that our more probable role would be that of a defender against attacking forces from the interior, the information has been given from that point of view, which would be equally applicable if attacking by land, although a sea bombardment would probably be the most efficacious. MUSCAT itself is hemmed in on all sides, its sea frontage by rocky and precipitous hills varying from 300 to 500 ft. in height. Even from the arms of the small beach, rocky eminences protrude into the sea. Full use has been made in the past of these vantage points, but the forts would now only be serviceable against small arms fire. Three passes give egress to MUSCAT ; a short road from BANDAR SIDAB, a footpath across the hills from RUWI entering MUSCAT from the south, and, lastly, and most important, the coast road from MATRAH. This road passes through two narrow defiles cut. through the rock, the first at the point of descent into MUSCAT (overlooking the town), the second at BANDAR ZAINAKI, between RIYAM and MATRAH. Given adequate fire power, either could be held by a very small force. The road to BANDAR SIDAB is short and passes into MUSCAT through a similar defile from the south-east. It represents, in fact, a back door that should not be overlooked. The only pass to the interior is via MATRAH and thence by a road that leads out through the hills southwards across a broad open valley to RUWI, where tracks diverge to the interior and the BATINEH coast road follows the Wadi to the sea. The northern end of this valley is commanded by BEIT-AL-FELEJ, the fort around which the Levies camp is situated. Also Levies picket posts on the WATAIYA hills command valleys on both sides from a flanking position. In the BEIT-AL-FELEJ valley and in the Wadi, which the coast road follows, are lines of karezs (small earth emplacements for a few riflemen) which would provide quite good cover in the open ground against advancing forces. It is in this valley that any forces bent on attacking MUSCAT or MATRAH would have to fight a decisive action. Moreover, since it is only to be entered by passes (even to seaward from DARSAIT) it is clear that the defenders have a considerable advantage. A landing on a small scale might be useful to block a retreat of the invaders, but if an attack on MUSCAT was the object, considerably superior forces and weapons would be necessary. Landing Beaches The three beaches at DARSAIT, WATAIYA, and the long sandy shore to the west, which is the beginning of the BATINEH coast, are all good sandy beaches with clear anchorages off them, but they would appear to be open to both the SHAMAL and the NASHI. DARSAIT has a mountainous hinterland, similar to MATRAH and MUSCAT ; on the remaining two the ground initially is open and undulating with plenty of scrub. They are normally unfrequented and surprise should be easy. Water Supplies There is water, and good camping sites, at WATAIYA, RUWI and BEIT-AL-FELEJ. Emergency Landing Grounds No possible emergency landing ground exists other than that normally used by the Royal Air Force [see Section VI, Muscat, paragraph (7)). (C43043) 375 12/41INDIA OFFICEIfiese SyrnboLs used, otl Maps, Plans and, Shetchesha\nng been approved by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty, will be used in all maps and plans issued with. Naval Inieliicjence Reports. They should- also be used whenever possible in the Naval service.Having been co-ordinated with accepted symbols in other services .they will be found, particularly suitably for combined operations BY COMMAND OF THEIR LORDSHIPS CJ^, /fyyU/VYa^ SYMBOLS CHART JANUARY 1936SYMBOLS USED ON MAPS, PLANS &amp; SKETCHES 1 st ' JazL-uarjr 1936. CONFIDENTIAL OA OB OC OD &gt;4/ ’vjo* ★ ® 12' O 6 ' a? © © L±J ■ D ■ B ■ M A w A b A R At o Ca£&gt;!e Landing 6 © ©B © M AnchorxLge cls classtfled, in 'Ports and Anchorages. Neural, Base Defended Port (size of largest gwv to be stated) Defended, Port (Defences uncertain) Steamship Horde British, Submarine Cables Foreign, Submarine Cables (NcdandWy indicated, in, Che circle) Railway, Double Track Railway, Single Track Railway, Under Construction, Railway, Projected, Telegraplt or Telephone (underground doe) Telegraph, or Telephone (overhead 'line) Power Station Gas Works Hospital Coal Depot * Bunkering Facilities ' Mine Oil Wells Fuel Oil Bunkering Facilities Oil Refinery Oil Tanks Cable Landing Place Lifting Appluvrvces o o © &lt;o P L A * ¥ /VWSA W/T. Station Radio Broadcasting Station M.N.B.D.O. W/T. Station Marine light Aerodrome (Name to be underlined in Red,, Blue or Black for Army, Naval or Civil) Untighted lighted 20 oM.C.S. &lt;E X Landing Ground, (Name ximderlined in, RedJBlue or Black for Amy,Naval or Civil) Seaplane Station (Name underlined in. Red,,Blue or Black for Amy, Naval or Civil) Seaplane Mooring Area (Name underlined in, Red.Blue or Black for Army, Naval or Civil) Aerodrome &amp; Seaplane Station (Name underlined in, Redjilue or Black for Amy,Naval or Civil) Airship Station- (Name underlined in, Red.Blue or Black for Army,Naval or Civil) Aerodrome and Airship Station (Name underlined in. Red,Blue or Black for Army,Naval or Civil) Airship Station &amp; Mooring Mast (Name underlined in, Red.Blue or Black for Arm}', Naval or Civil) Mooring Mast for Airships Hangar for Airships Airway Beacon Aerodrome with. Beacon Overhead, Power Transmission Line Airway Corridor Airway obstruction over 200 U (60 metres) above ground, (If the height of the obstruction, above ground level exceeds SOOff’ the maximum, height in, feet above sea level is given, thus : — X 545 fp) Limit of Area prolvibiteil for Aircraft Line of mines with, depth, in feet at Low Water Spiings Controlled, line of mines with, cable, to control station Mine Control Station Indicator Loop Indicator Loop Station Other seaward defences (type to be stated e.g.booms.nets etc) Disused Fort 20 -/ 00 “ Searchlig ht 3~6'Guns i ! &gt; Mag. r jT. Ex. T oR.F. F© i a A L©Sj ■ • (X /Examinatii© / A nchorage \ Searchlight (Number of degrees refers to the limits of illuminated, area,) Battery or fort where arc of fire is known (If scale permits and information, is available, shop e of fort is to be shown, in, black and red work sup erimp osed) Battery where position only is known Prepared, position for mobile artillery (Coast Defences) Magazine A D ' C T E.D.O. 7 F.C. I A - Visual Signal Station Port War Signal Station Telephone Exchange Range finding transmitter post Range finder Command, post or battery control post Anti-Aircraft gun or section A.A. Battery H.Q. Sound, Locator with, A.A.. Searchlight ■ Limit of Minefield Exartiination Anchorage M.N.B.D.O.Beach, roadway M.N.B.D.O.Pier Coast practicable for landing Entrenchments Demolitions Obstacles (Descrifition, of obstacle to be written, above the symbol) L.D.F. B.Bty. ’A’.Coy. L.T.W. Tsai. Defence Commander Extended, Defence Officer Fire Commander Administrative HQ Land, Defence Force oC.W.P. o o C W. P. oW A, P ©2 X T jb—✓_ r v Battery H. Q ■ Land Defence Company H.Q. Signal Company H.Q Landing Transport and. Workshop Company Land, Defence Platoon H.Q. Kite Balloon Coast Watching Post Coast Watching Patrol Water Supply One-way Traffic for M.T. (at roadJuMctCon) Turning point for M. T. Machine-gun post with, number of guns Land, mine field. Road, running under bridge Road, running over bridge Embankment Cutting Naval IrLtelHgence Division,AAmiralty - .</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002bb_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2160B</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002bb</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2160B</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 6/88 'Intelligence: Military Report on Arabia (C.B. 1892).'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-27T15:50:30</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (63 folios)</extent><extent>The Arabia Intelligence Report contains a table of contents. The maps, plans and photographs, which are listed below the table of contents, appear after the main text of the report.</extent><extent>Foliation: The file is formed of two parts. The foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover of the first part at 1 and terminates at the inside back cover of the second part at 65; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of two parts. The first part (folios 1-9) begins with a 'state of report' document for an Admiralty Naval Intelligence Division report entitled 'Arabia, Intelligence Report'; the 'state report' concerns the updating of the report in October 1941, and it includes a list of maps, plans and photographs that are contained in the report. There then follows a small amount of correspondence between India Office, War Office, and General Staff (India) officials regarding the supply of an earlier issue of the report, dated 1939.The second part of the file consists of the actual report, entitled 'C.B. 1892 (X) (10/41) Arabia Intelligence Report', dated October 1941, with appended maps, plans and photographs relating to Arabian Peninsula ports. The report is divided into four sections (six sections are listed in the table of contents, which lists sections one and three, most of section two, and one part of section five, as 'not issued', i.e. not printed in this edition of the report).The first section to appear in the report is entitled 'Section II: Strategy and Tactics'; parts 1 and 3-6 of this section have been omitted, leaving part 2, which has the heading 'Possible Lines on which War Plans would be Framed'.The next section, 'Section IV: Geography and Topography', provides an overview of the geography and topography of the Arabian Peninsula, including information about climate, transport facilities (including a table of landing grounds and seaplane anchorages), and communications.The third section, 'Section V: Base Facilities and Maintenance of the Fleet' (from which part one has been omitted), provides a summary of principal commercial dockyards and repair bases, locations for fuel storage, supplies and storage of ammunition, fixed coastal defences, and aircraft.The final section of the report, 'Section VI: Ports, Anchorages and Their Defences', proceeds through a number of Gulf ports in alphabetical order (i.e. Akaba, Bahrain, Doha, Hodeida and Ras Kethib, Jedda, Kamaran, Kuwait, Mukalla, and Muscat), describing each place's port facilities, anchorages and defences, as well as providing other information relating to matters such as government, commerce, water supply, transport and communications.Enclosed with the maps and plans is a symbols chart, which lists some of the symbols used in the maps and plans.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Anchorage</topic></subject><subject><topic>Landing places</topic></subject><subject><topic>Photographs</topic></subject><subject><topic>Aerial photographs</topic></subject><subject><topic>Plans</topic></subject><subject><topic>Maps</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty War Staff, Naval Intelligence Division</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Arabian Peninsula</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Naval intelligence</topic></subject><subject><topic>Topography</topic></subject><subject><topic>Harbours</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002bb#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>