<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100032671578.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T18:23:45.090Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">In any fui'ther communication on the subject, please quote V, 11276/141. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. liAmf^iate and Confidential. &gt; Sir:- * &amp; © \ In reply to j-our letter of one 13th instant P.927, regarding the Trans-Persian Railway, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to suggest that the interdepart mental Conference to discuss the question should, if convenient, meet at the Foreign Office on Thursday next the 19th instant at noon. Copies of two despatches which have recently been received are enclosed for consideration before the meeting of the Conference. In this connexion I am to point out that it would seem difficult to exclude from the discussion altogether, tne subject of a possible alignment east of Bunder Abbas seeing that this is one of the most important points in the Russian communication the answer to which is to oe considered by The Under Secretary of State, India Office.♦ Q (11276/14) the Conference. I am to observe that io is not intended that the Conference should take final decisions on this or other questions; its purpose is to make recommendations for the decision of His Majesty’s G-overnment. I am, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, /[This Document is tue Property of His Britannic Majesty’s GovenunentJ [B] PERSIA AND CENTRAL ASIA. CONEIDENTIAL. [10390] [March 9.] Section 2. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received March 9.) (No. 52. Very Confidential.) Sir, Tehran, February 18, 1914. I HAD a conversation with the new Russian Minister last Sunday upon the subject of the proposed Trans-Persian Railway. I found M. Koroslovetz very ill-supplied with the latest information about the doings of the Societe d’Etudes. He had apparently not been told that it is now proposed that the demand for an option is to be presented by the societe, instead of by the two legations, as was the original intention, and he had no knowledge of the proposal that, as soon as the option has been secured, a joint commission shall proceed to study the alternative routes south of Ispahan, with a view to arriving at a decision as to which route shall be finally adopted. I explained the situation to him, and told him that I had reason to believe that, in addition to a request for financial assistance which will be made to the societe when the request for the option is presented, the Persian Government is likely to raise some objection to what would appear to be the present intention, nameiy, to construct the line as it were in two or three sections, the Russian group having the predominant interest in the northern zone, the middle zone being equally divided between the three groups, and the British group having the predominant interest in the southern zone. I formed the above impression from a recent conversation which I had with the Regent, who is kept extremely well-posted in all the doings in Paris of the Societe d’Etudes by the Persian Minister in the French capital. His Highness on the above mentioned occasion said that it would not be at all satisfactory to Persia to feel that the zones of interest wmre to be accentuated in the construction of a railway which they had hoped to see built upon genuine international principles. He expressed his great surprise that His Majesty’s Government shoidd have, not only agreed to this plan, but possibly originated it, because it appeared to him diametrically opposed to the true interest of Great Britain in Persia, in that it would allow the neutral zone to come under the influence of Russia, doubled by France, in a manner which would serve to dispel the belief that, despite the fact that that part of Persia in which her chief interests are situated was left neutral by the terms of the Anglo-Russian Convention, she still maintains a paramount influence in that region. The Regent, who is a very staunch supporter of the Anglo-Russian understanding, in which he sees the only possible chance for Persia’s salvation, because under it His Majesty’s Government are able to address friendly remonstrances to the Russian Government, often speaks more like an Englishman than a Persian. On the occasion alluded to, his Highness spoke most earnestly in the sense that His Majesty’s Govern ment ought to take serious steps to protect British interests in the southern part of the neutral zone, which are, in his opinion, gravely threatened by the steady i penetration southwards of Russian influence. He cited the situation at Ispahan created by the Zil’s properties having been practically placed under Russian protection by being administered by the director of the Russian Bank, and pointed out that there are evident signs that a similar method for obtaining Russian control over villages to the south of Ispahan is being adopted. His Highness considered j that it is absolutely necessary for His Majesty’s Government to protect the interests of British subjects by coming to an arrangement with Russia and the Persian Government, under which a railway from Bunder Abbas to Shiraz and from thence to Mohammerah will be reserved for British capital. Such a bulwark would, he thought, do much to serve as a ring fence against Russian penetration. His Highness appeared to be fully aware of the objections entertained in India to the line passing through Kerman and on to Chahbar. He said that of course His Majesty s Government are the best judges of what is in their truest interest, but it seemed to him that very small risk to India would be run by agreeing to the line running through Kerman, [2063 i—2] -O' \ BH j 5 ..rather than Shiraz, whilst he was convinced that it would be much in our interest impOTtenceto die^fne tunning throtg^ KeVman, His Majesty’s Government woidd do ^sHi^hness asked that our conversation might be considered as strictly confidential. It was evident that the Regent was sincerely desirous in what he said of putting before ffirMa^tv^s Government what he considers to be a policy best suited to assist and protect British interests in South Persia. 1 w ° uW R ^ most heartily concur in the views expressed by the Regent. We are pe l ap. j stiiiea rshting stm whilst Russia carries out, under cover of the Anglo-Russian Convention what M S SabUne has defined as “ peaceful penetration A-^bu the situation appears to me somewhat different when that peaceful penetration is carried into a region in which British interests have long been paramount, by the old fashioned Russian dodge of extending protection to persons who can lay no sort of claim to it. j h &amp;c WALTER TOWNLEY. a[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government,] % 'uterest roulddo ^ their '1 1 [B] PERSIA AND CENTRAL ASIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [March 9.] Section- 1, [10331] Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received March 9.) (No. 58.) Sir, St. Petersburg]!, March 4, 1914. IT is clear from the Russian aide-memoire of which a translation was enclosed in my despatch No. 51 of the 27th ultimo that, should the request for the option be further delayed, the Russian Government will regard the original scheme of a trans- Persian railway as definitely abandoned, and will proceed with the formation of a new company for the construction of Russian railways in the Russian and neutral zones. So far as I am aware, His Majesty’s Government are not likely to oppose the immediate request for an option for the whole line, provided that its eventual alignment in the south is left open and not actually specified. I trust, therefore, that it may be possible for the Societe d’fitudes to apply at once for the option in the manner proposed and for the three groups, of which it is composed, to continue to ■work together, even should the scope of their enterprise be restricted for the present to railway construction in the Russian zone. It would, however, I think, tend to promote a better understanding between the two Governments were it possible to arrive at some compromise with regard to the direction which the alignment should eventually follow in the south. Their views on the subject are at present diametrically opposed ; as, while His Majesty’s Government advocate an alignment via Ispahan, Shiraz, and Bunder Abbas, the Russian Government are strongly in favour of the more direct route via Yezd, Kerman, and Chahbar. The latter is vetoed by His Majesty’s Government, who insist on securing certain strategic safeguards with regard to the route by which the line is to approach the Indian frontier, while the former is declared by the Russian Government to be absolutely unacceptable, because it would not only deprive the projected railway of its original character of a direct transit route between India and Europe via Russia, but would also bring it into dangerous proximity to the Bagdad system. For all practical purposes, therefore, these two routes are virtually eliminated, as neither Government is ever likely to modify its attitude of declared hostility to one or other of them. Under these circumstances it would be unreasonable to expect the Societe d’htudes to go to the expense of surveying two routes, which they know beforehand are certain to be vetoed by either England or Russia. The more rational procedure would seem to be for the two Governments to endeavour to arrive at an understanding as to the area within which the eventual alignment could be located without being foredoomed to be vetoed on one side or the other. The survey to be undertaken would then be confined to this area, which by the natural force of circumstances would be of restricted dimensions. The Russians are determined, with or without our co-operation, gradually to construct a railway from Astara to Tehran and Yezd ; and if the original scheme of a transit railway across Persia is ever realised, this is the route which it is bound to follow. They can, moreover, in spite of anything which we may do or say, extend that railway to Kerman. This fact seems now to be generally recognised ; and the Indian Government have apparently withdrawn the veto which they originally placed on the alignment being carried as far east as Kerman. Since, moreover, His Majesty s Government will never consent to a terminal port to the east of Bunder Abbas, the future alignment must be sought for in the country lying between Yezd and that port. As I had the honour to report in my telegram No. 23 of the 29th January, M. Zveguintsef informed me that there were many natural difficulties in the way of the construction of a railway between Yezd and Kerman, and that it might be possible for the Russian group to consent to an alignment running direct to Bunder Abbas at some distance to the south-west of Kerman. Though in speaking thus M. Zvegumtsef was but expressing his personal opinion, and though M. Sazonof strongly disapproved of such an alignment on the ground that it would serve to carry our sea-borne goods to the north of Persia, it has evidently been under consideration by the Russian group. [2063 i—1]i From the point of view of the Indian Government it is open to no strategical objections; and, as it is not very much longer than the Yezd-Kerman-Chahbar alignment, it does not, like the Ispahan-Shiraz route, expose us tc the charge of depriving the projected trans-Persian railway of its original character of a transit railway between Europe and India. I would therefore venture to submit that m agreeing to the request for an option without a precise specification of the xmthern route we should suggest to the Russian Government that both the Kerman-Chahbar and the Ispahan-Shiraz routes should be admitted to be unacceptable, and that me work of survey should be restricted to ascertaining the most direct and practical alignment between Yezd and Bunder Abbas. Our position would then be a much stronger one than it is at present, as we could point out that, m order to meet the wishes of the Russian Government we were abandoning the alignment which we considered the most advantageous to British trade and were consenting to one which would fulfil all the requirements of a direct transi t railway between India and Europe. Should the fear of seeing British goods competing with Russian goods in north Persia induce the Russian Government to oppose the idea of a direct railway between lezd and Bunder Abbas, the responsibility of the breakdown of the trans-Persian railway scheme 'would rest with them and not with us. It is I think very important at a moment like the present, when there are so many questions connected with Mongolia, Thibet, the neutral zone, and north Persia awaiting discussion, that we should not lay ourselves open to the suspicion of wishing to wreck a scheme which the Russian Government has so warmly espoused, from a remark recently made to me by M. Poklewsky, there would seem to be some reason to hope that the Russian Government would be more disposed to meet our wishes with iegard to Thibet were we to adopt a more conciliatory attitude towards the trans-1 ersian railway scheme. Whether this be the case or not, the questions enumerated above are all so intimately connected, that I should personally prefer to have to discuss them simultaneously with the Russian Government than have to deal with them separately. In a conversation which I had with M. Sazonof yesterday, his Excellency referred to the proposal which he had made last spring for a revision of our agreement with regard to the neutral zone, and expressed his readiness to make us considerable concessions in that quarter, though I do not for a moment believe that he is ready to go as far as M. Korostovetz intimated in a recent conversation with Sir Walter Townley. I am, however, strongly of the opinion that the sooner that we face this question of the neutral zone the better, and I believe that the time has come for a frank exchange of views between the two Governments on all questions in which they are respectively interested in Persia and Central Asia. If we deal with them simultaneously there is more room for a policy of give and take, whereas I very much fear that in treating them separately we shall have to give far more than we take. . In conclusion, I would only add that, however accommodating our attitude with regard to the trans-Persian railway, there would appear to be no probability of the realisation of that scheme for some years to come. The Russian Government are content to wait, provided that we do not render its eventual realisation impossible by the conditions which we attach to the southern alignment. _ The Persian Government will make the granting of the option conditional on a considerable advance, and that of the concession on a large loan ; and, judging from what Lord Revelstoke tells me, British financiers are by no means disposed to provide the necessary funds. It is also by no means clear where the capital required for the construction of the railway is to be found. We can, I think, therefore, safely risk approaching the subject in a conciliatory spirit. If, however, we wish to conciliate Russia, we must be careful to avoid doing anything to confirm the belief which is held in certain quarters here, that it is our intention to link up our future railways in southern Persia with the Bagdad Railway. It is for this reason that I should deprecate the raising of the question of the construction of a railway from Bunder Abbas to Mohammerah, which was advocated by the Regent in the conversation reported in Sir W. Townley s despatch No. 52, Very Confidential, of the 18th February, as such a railway would inevitably be linked up sooner or later with the Bagdad Railway at Basra. I have, &amp;c. GEORGE W. BUCHANAN. B f!*Ir EDIATE. Draft F.Q. I am directed by the 3. of 3. for India to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 9143 of the Nth inst. on the subject of the Trans- Persian Railway. The Marquess of Crewe has no objection to the questions discussed in the correspondence accompanying your letter being referred to an interdepartmental conference, but in view of their great importance, and the possible consequences to India of the decisions arrived at, he feels strongly that the possibility of an alignment or port east of Bunder Abbas - a matter upon which his views were communicated to Sir E. Grey in Sir T. W, Holderness’s letter of 12th Dec. last - should be excluded from the consideration of the conference. He would further suggest that the conclusions of the conference as to an alignment alternative to the Ispahan-Shiraz route should be subsequently referred for considera tion to the C.I.D.India. •/y In any further communication on the subject, please quote N o. 9143/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. mmeaiate. Foreign Office 6th. March, 1914. bir:- r 9 7 i - I -•* .. I &amp;m directed by Seeretary'-SnrlSdward Grey to transmit / to you, herewith, to be laid before the Marquess of Crewe copies of despatches exchanged with His Majesty’s Am bassador at St. Petersburg, relative to the proposed Trans- Persian Bailway. I am to state that in view of the extreme importance of the points raised in this correspondence and of the im pending arrival in this country of a leading member of the Russian group of the Societe d’Etudes . Sir E. Grey is of * opinion that a small interdepartmental committee, consisting of representatives of the India Office, Admiralty, Board of Trade, Director of Military Operations and this Office should meet at the earliest possible date to consider the questions at issue. I am accordingly to ask that if this course recommends itself Under Secretary of State, India Office. Copy to 'odia 13 MAR1914(9143/14). ^ itself to His Lordship a representative of the India Office rna y De ciesignated for the purpose# A similar letter has been addressed to the other De partments interested. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] [B] PERSIA AND CENTRAL ASIA. ^ CONFIDENTIAL. [9143] Sir G. Bvchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received March 2.) (No. 51.) Sir, St. Petersburgh, February 27, 1914. I HAVE the honour to transmit to you herewith, with reference to your despatch No. 434 of the 31st December last, translation of an aide-memoire which I have received from the Russian Government on the subject of the Trans-Persian Railway. I have, &amp;c. GEORGE W. BUCHANAN. [March 2.] Section 2. No. 1. Enclosure in No. 1. Memorandum. THE Imperial Government have not failed to give their serious attention to the copy submitted by the British Ambassador of Sir Edward Grey’s despatch of the 31st December of last year, on the question of the Trans-Persian Railway. Havino- weighed the proposals of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs contained in this despatch, the Imperial Government consider it necessary on their part to put forward their views on the questions touched :— 1. With reference to the question of presenting to the Persian Government a request for an option for the construction of the above-mentioned railway, it is now proposed that the request shall be despatched to Tehran directly by the Societe d’Etudes, by post, or through the Persian Minister in Paris. Following the receipt of this document in Tehran the petition of the company can be supported by the repre sentatives of Russia, England, and France separately. The Imperial Government are profoundly convinced that such action by the French Minister, having regard to the purely economic character of the matter, and that French subjects and capital are participating, cannot give grounds for the presentation of any demands whatsoever by anv other Power. On the other hand, the participation of the French Minister in the step specified appears to be necessary not only in view of the satisfaction of the just desire of the French group of the Societe d’Etudes, but also in view of the request to this effect, known to the London Cabinet, of the Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs, for whom it is essentially important that the undertaking shall assume in the eyes of the Persians an international and not only an Anglo-Russian character. 2. As regards the question of securing free access to the sea for the future Trans- Persian Railway, it must be noted that the Societe d’Etudes was not acquainted of any claims of the Persian Railway Syndicate to port construction in the region of the Trans-Persian Railway, and consequently in the charter of the said ompany, with which the British Government is acquainted, there are also references to similar construction, which is natural in view of the objects sought by the company. Moreover, t is impossible not to note that the fears of a political nature inspiring the British Government in this question are scarcely founded in view of the fact, as has been already pointed out, that in the southern section of the railway the British group of the Societe d’Etudes will have an overwhelming preponderance over the other groups. Should, however, this argument not appear sufficiently convincing to^ the London Cabinet, the following solution might be proposed, to which the Societe d Etudes perhaps , would agree, namely, that management of ports and their appurtenances in the south should be exclusively in the hands of the British group of this company. ^ From information in the possession of the Imperial Government, the Russian group has no objection in principle against entering into direct negotiations with the Persian Railways Syndicate, but it must first discuss this matter with the other groups, because these negotiations must be conducted in the name of the whole Societe d Etudes. [2063 6—2; Copy to 13 MAR1914As regards mention of access to the sea in the petition for an option which is to be presented to the Government of the Shah, the Society d’Etudes has already proposed to restrict itself in this matter to an absolutely general formula fully m accord with that which was put forward in the note of Sir E. Grey. But the Societe d Etudes, however, is desirous that the Bussian and British Governments should give to it due assuiances^- that the interests of the company in the question of free outlets to the sea will be properly guarded, the text of such assurance, from information m the hands of the Imperial Government, has already been communicated from Paris to the British group of the Societe d’Etudes in London, with y view to their considering it m conjunction with the British Ministry for Foreign Affairs. _ , - 3. With reference to the commission which is to survey the southern routes of the Trans-Persian Railway, the Imperial Government can only repeat that, for considera tions of a financial and other character, it is unable to charge the liussian treasury with expenditure on the equipment of an expedition to the south of Persia, and that the participation of a Russian and a French delegate in the said commission can take place only at the expense of the Societe d’Btudes, the representatives of which can at the most be given official character. As, under these circumstances, the French member of the commission will be in fact a Russian delegate, and the Trench Govern me nt will be taking no part whatever in this matter, there will be no grounds of any kind for fearing that any undesirable results will ensue therefrom. 4. The Imperial Government have already had the honour to inform the London Cabinet that the route of the Trans-Persian Railway—Ispahan, Shiraz, and Bunder Abbas—is to them and to the Societe d’Etudes absolutely inacceptable. It would seem, therefore, that any surveys of this route are superfluous, the more so that, with the restricted means of the Societe d Etudes, the labours of the commission must be completed as speedily as possible and all unnecessary expenditure avoided. Nevertheless, should the British Government still insist on a survey of ibis route, and if the Societe d’Etudes will agree to take upon itself tne expenditure incurred, the Imperial Government are prepared to include this route in the list of those meriting investigation—on the condition, however, that the commission shall be placed under the obligation of investigating also every other route, and that the results of such investiga tions shall be afterwards submitted to consideration. For due negotiations with the Societe d’Btudes on this matter it would be desirable to receive, as early as possible, from the British Government their proposals respecting the cost of the impending expedition to Southern Persia, as also the time requisite for the commission to travel along the different possible variants of the future direction of the railway. The Imperial Government would raise no objections to a representative of the British group of the Societe d’Etudes being appointed by the Societe d’Etudes itself on the staff of the party which is to verify the detailed surveys, already completed, of the northern section of the railway, believing that in due course, on the principle of reciprocity, a representative of the Russian group will take part in similar investiga tions of the route in the south. 5. Referring to the extract in Sir E. Grey’s despatch taken from his despatch of the 5th February, 1913 (No. 64), it must be noted that the views of the Imperial Government on the questions touched in it have been already communicated to the British Embassy in the aide-memoire of the 1st May, 1913, and these views have not up to the present undergone any change. The Imperial Government, however, deem it necessary to explain that the question of parity of tariff rates can only be decided after the whole length of the Trans-Persian route has been constructed, and not when only its northern section, within the limits of the Russian and neutral zones, is m existence. Having put forward its views on the questions touched by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, the Imperial Ministry for Foreign Affairs, in accordance with a request of the Russian group of the Societe d’Etudes, considers it necessary to draw the serious attention of the London Cabinet to the considerable delays which the enterprise for a Trans-Persian Railway is experiencing which are very sensibly affecting the interest of the Societe d’Etudes. The fundamental aim of this company is the creation of a great transit route between India and Europe via Russia, an aim which, at the very commencement sympathetically met by the British Government, is being ever increasingly relegated to an indefinite future, due apparently to fears of a political and strategical character, which it would appear should not exist in view of the friendly relations which have been established between the two Powers. In connexion with this3 'Btol* oowe^ !8 ^wily ^of| a nTreas® &gt;ia, and Hi ion can Aicli cann ernnientil an? kind li! i tne Loiff sotkiil of tlisni incurred, ii- aose meric d bedesmk tmereqi® ture dfflttK the settlement of the question of the northern section of the railway is being delayed, - as the latter, with the present state of the matter, naturally is dependent to a certain degree on the decisions which will be reached respecting the southern section. While in no way insisting on the realisation now of the enterprise of a Trans- |Persian route in its full extent, and being fully prepared to restrict the construction of F the railway for the present to within the limits of the Russian sphere of influence, the Imperial Government are of the opinion, however, that there are no longer any obstacles to the immediate request for an option for the whole route without specification of its direction towards the south. At the same time they consider, from the point of view of their own every-day interests, that the speediest possible laying of the line within the limits of the Russian zone is absolutely necessary in view of the undoubted successes which are noticeable in the construction of the Bagdad Railway. In view of this, the Russian Government propose, together with the Societe d’Etudes, to present now, by the above-mentioned method, to the Persian Government a request for an option for the whole line, together with the right to final surveys on its northern section, on the condition that upon completion of these surveys a treaty of concession to this section of the route shall be immediately drawn up, to be followed by a commencement of the actual construction. Should, afterwards, such a settlement of the question prove for any reason to be inacceptable to the Societe d’Etudes as at present constituted, it will be necessary to regard the original enterprise as upset, and to proceed with formation of a new company specially for the construction of Russian railways in the Russian and neutral zones, and the Imperial Government would of course in such an event consider themselves freed from any obligations taken by them in connexion with the exchange of opinions respecting a transit route. Simultaneously with this, instructions are being given to the Imperial Minister in Tehran to support the petition of the Society d’Etudes immediately upon receipt of such by the Government of the Shah. St. Petersburgh, February 12 (25), 1914. prmcip lar inWf 1, 8 WS 1 irnnesA laryot affeetC ^icki 3 is Wl1 p [This Dociimeat is the Property of His Britamiic Majesty’s Govemmpnt. ] PERSIA AND CENTRAL ASIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [February 5.] Skctton 4 [5382] No. 1. St. Petersburgh, February 5, 1914. Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received February 5.) (No. 39.) ^ &gt; (Telegraphic.) YOUR telegram No. 50 of 2nd February. M. Zvegintzof, whom I saw yesterday will consult Russian group with regard to suggested guarantee for facilities for railway. He quite understood that advance of 100,000Z. was an entirely separate transaction, but said that Russian group did not want syndicate to make this advance until railway option had also been obtained. This was one reason for their opposing concession. He made personal suggestion that this difficulty might be got over by requests for option and for mining concession being made simultaneously. On his asking whether I had heard anything more about terminal port, I read him first paragraph of your above-mentioned telegram. He personally saw no objection to Ispahan-Shiraz alignment being examined first. Same survey party would have to examine all possible alignments in turn, and to report on their commercial and practical possibilities, leaving all political and strategical considerations for discussion between the two Governments. Russian group regarded the Shiraz alignment as unacceptable on account of its length, and of its proximity to Bagdad Railway, but they could not veto it in advance. He trusted that His Majesty’s Government would also refrain from vetoing Char bar or Guetar # until after Survey Commission reported. I told him that I saw no prospect of your ever accepting either of latter, and enquired whether Russian group had insuperable objections to Bunder Abbas. He could not, he said, speak in their name, but lie personally held out hope of their possibly consenting to railway running direct from Yezd to Bunder Abbas and passing at some distance to the south-west of Kerman. Country between Yezd and Kerman did not lend itself to railway construction. Minister for Fo reign Affairs, to whom I repeated substance of above, spoke strongly against the suggested alignment on the ground that it would flood North Persia with our seaborne goods. Trans-Persian was to have been transit railway to India, but we were changing its whole character. We had better say so at once, and call it now by some other name. He had hoped that it would have drawn us nearer together, but, on the contrary, we were drifting apart. Russia was ready to give most solemn guarantees with regard to Indian frontier, and we should find, when too late, how unfounded were our suspicions of her. We had better give up all idea we had of asking for option. I reminded him that form which request for option was to take would leave the question of alignment in south quite vague. I was not pressing Yezd-Bunder Abbas alignment, and did not even know whether it would be acceptable to His Majesty’s Government, but grounds on which his Excellency opposed it were not calculated to encourage Anglo-Russian co-operation in Persia. His Excellency said he would discuss question of option with M. Raffalovit-ch, who had just arrived. Plis Excellency’s ill-humour may, I think, be caused by reopening of question of vacant Scutari command, referred to in my telegram No. 37 of 4th February. Present position of trans-Persian question is as follows : Russian group will no more accept Shiraz alignment than we shall accept Charbar as terminal port. They are, however, prepared to leave question of alignment open and want us to do the same. Though it seems waste of money for Commission to survey routes which are practically barred beforehand, we should be held responsible for breakdown of whole scheme were we to veto any particular alignment in advance. Suggestion of Yezd alignment offers possible compromise which we might adopt were the Commission to report in its favour. Were Russian Government then to veto it on commercial grounds, we could throw the whole blame on them. * Guetar is about 50 miles east of Charbar. Copy to . a mas 191 4 ;C 12 t In any further communica tion ion this subject, please quote No ’ and address— ' j The Under-Secretary of State, Foreiani Office, Ijondon. The Undersecretary of State for Foreign A fairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by' direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop A of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, lO ? I 9 I 4 . Reference to previous letter: f rt6.x3-iq 10- Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. ^ w E. A 4 _ v -' IA ■ -V\A^C^A^ Iax)- A A 0 ’ Subject. / 0 . A? - Vf • 0' if j . **4« 5558/14) ! ^ fijr: 6th, 1614. I aiily rucc&gt;iv^u your cleiv^tcli ho. 4 of the 8th* of J January lust .^avoeatine the ^loynent cf Persian forces to escort thy Joint Tcchnimu Oorrti#kicn of the TMi^-Perslyii Hallwoy Purvey, and I have consulted the Becretary cl ntata for India on the subject. I no¥ XtmmnXt to you herewith a copy of the reply of the Marquess of Crewe, who prefers the original suggestion that the escort should, he Hussion in the northern and British In the southern section. I would add that I agree with His Lordship's view but I do not consider the matter as urgent at this juncture. I am, with great truth and regard. Your most obedient, humble Servant, (Signed) E. Grey. Ur W. Icwnloy, K.CJU.G. tiC., &amp;C.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] [A] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [54973/12] [February 4.j Section 1. L ' ir &gt; , Foreign Office, February 4, 1913. HIS Majesty s Government liave had under careful consideration the letters which you addressed to this Department on the 9th and 20th December on the subject of the Trans-Persian Railway project. In your letter of the 9th December, while recognising that the attitude of His Majesty s Government had hitherto been to reserve complete freedom of action pending submission of the survey you were to furnish, you intimate that you do not now feel justified in sending a delegate to Tehran to negotiate, in concert with French and Russian associates, with the Persian Government; and, before proceeding further, you ask that indications may be afforded to you on the following points :—■ (a.) It would seem essential to learn whether His Majesty’s Government view with favour or disfavour the piospect of direct iuilwu^\ communication between India and Europe via Russia (b.) It would appear desirable to know whether His Majesty’s Government desire British'financial interests to continue co-operation in the Societe d Etudes in spite of such co-operation leadinp’ primarily to facilitating railway construction in Northern Persia only. (c.) In the event of His Majesty’s Government being already committed to support other applicants for railway concessions in the British and neutral spheres, it would seem essential to learn the scope of such concessions. (d.) In view of the possible advancement of conflicting projects for railway service in the British and neutral spheres, the British group would be glad to learn whether His Majesty’s Government have any suggestions as to a solution of the situation which may arise from rival claims in this portion of Persian territory. I am now directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to make the following observations on each of these points :—• (a.) His _ Majesty’s Government have already expressed themselves prepared to assent in principle to the project of a Trans-Persian railway: that assent is made subject to the following, among other, conditions :— That no part of the line or its connections shall be constructed outside the Prussian sphere until, and in such measures as, His Majesty’s Government shall consider it politic and feasible ; that the main line must pass through Ispahan by Shiraz, and if it, or any branch, is continued to the British sphere, it must reach that sphere at Bunder Abbas ; that His Majesty’s Government do not think that the time has yet come for a connection between Bunder Abbas and Karachi to be made, and as there must be no question pf ^ making it until His Majesty’s Government consider that the time has come w r hen it is desirable, the question of branch and local lines should be considered on their merits, and their commercial advantages should not be sacrificed to the project of through connection ; that His Majesty’s Government undertake no financial guarantee in regard to the project ; that the point where the line touches the Persian Gulf shall be referred to His Majesty’s Government wdien the surveys have been completed, and the arrangements for the maritime terminus, and for its control, shall be submitted to their approval ; that the question of the gauge outside the Russian sphere shall be submitted to His Majesty’s Government; that effective means must be provided, to the satisfaction of His Majesty’s Government, to secure British trade against differential treatment of any kind, direct or indirect, on any railway constructed under a concession obtained by the Societe d’Etudes ; that British control must predominate in the Southern or Gulf section of any Trans-Persian line, or of the branches, which may be made, and that this control shall not be invalidated by any arrangement wdiich may be made in regard to the percentage of other (i.e., non- British) participation in the undertaking. (6.) His Majesty’s Government raise no objection, regarding it as very desirable on general grounds that the British group should co-operate in the Societe d’Etudes, but they trust that such progress may be made in regard to a well-considered scheme [2804 ff—1]2 of^railway development in tlie south as will render possible an early, and if possible simultaneous, start in construction from the Persian Gulf. (c) That His Majesty’s Government are committed, and were so before the constitution of the Societe d’Etudes: that the concessions in question are the Bunder-Abbas-Kerman one in the British sphere (which would have to be purely British-controlled), and certain lines in the neutral sphere (other than the Mohammerah- Khorremmabad project) which, in view of the great predominance of British trade, should be preponderatingly British, though not without a substantial international participation both in construction and management. (d.) His Majesty’s Government would be prepared to recommend to the parties interested in the projects (other than the Mohammerah-Khorremmabad line) in the neutral sphere that it would serve British interests if they would join with the British group of the Societe d’Etudes, who, in consultation with His Majesty’s Government, might then arrange the degree and nature of the foreign participation in question. I am to express Sir E. Grey’s view that the arrangements for securing British control on certain portions of the line need not necessarily conflict with the principle of equal representation of British, Russian, and French interests in the undertaking from the northern frontier of Persia to the sea. In conclusion, I am to state that, subject to the acceptance of the conditions laid down, His Majesty’s Government are willing to support yonr Societe in the negotiations proposed at Tehran; but that they would recommend the substitution of the words “ d’un chemin de fer traversant la Perse du nord au sud par Teheran” for the words “sur territoire persan, &amp;c., &amp;c., .... par Teheran ” in the note which you propose to address to the Persian Government (see enclosure A in your letter of the 20th December). I am, &amp;c. LOUIS MALLET.L4 [This Docnmer ; is the Property of His Britannic Mi fsty’s Govermnent] PERSIA AND CENTRAL ASIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [February 9.] Section 1. [5786] No. 1. (No. 35.) Sir, IN Su G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received February 9.) ' r i , . St. Petersburgh, February 3, 1914. my telegram No. 23 of the 29th of last month I reported at length the convexsation which I had on that day with M. Zveguintsef, a leading member of the Russian gimxp, on the subject of the di’ans-Persian Railway and of the Kerman mining concession. I had not at that time received the confidential print with the India Office letter of the 12th December, and with your reply of the 29th of that month, so I was not aware that it was Lord Crewe’s wish that His Majesty’s Government should definitely state that they would in any case be unable to entertain the idea of an^ alignment debouching to the east of Bunder Abbas. Accordingly, when M. Zyeguintsef gave me to understand that the whole Trans-Persian Railway scheme which was to have cemented Anglo-Russian co-operation in Persia was about to break down in consequence of our attitude on the subject of the terminal port, I reminded him that, in the communication which I had been instructed to make to the Russian Government on the subject, His Majesty’s Government had stated that they did not wish to prejudge the work of the survey party, and that I was consequently under the impression that although an alignment terminating at a port east of Bunder Abbas would, in their opinion, be undesirable, the question would be left an open one until the report of the Commission of Investigation had been received. M. Zveguintsef replied that, if this proved to be the case, the Russian group would agree to the request for the option being made on the lines originally suggested, namely, for a railway traversing Persia from north-west to south-east, without indicating precisely its actual alignment. In reply to a question which I subsequently addressed to him, M. Zveguintsef said that should the Commission of Investigation pronounce in favour of Chahbar as the terminal port, and should we veto this recommendation, this fact would not necessarily prove fatal to the railway scheme. We might then, he suggested, propose that, instead of beginning the work of construction at both ends, building operations should commence in the north and should proceed gradually southwards till the railway reached Yezd, while the question of its further extension in the direction of India would be left an open one. What he wanted to avoid was the breakdown of this great Anglo-Russian enterprise. During the years that must intervene before the railway reached Yezd, Indian public opinion might view direct communication with Europe in a more favourable light; but if, on the other hand, His Majesty’s Government were now to declare that under no circumstances would they consent to an alignment debouching to the east of Bunder Abbas, there would hardly be any use in presenting the request for an option, or in sending a Commission of Investigation to survey the future alignment. In the course of our conversation M. Zveguintsef told me that he believed that the alignment most favoured by the Russian group would be one passing to the south-west of Kerman, without touching that town, as it was said that there were fewer natural difficulties to be overcome along this route than on any other one. As regarded the Kerman mining concession, M. Zveguintsef admitted that the Societe d’Etudes must respect existing vested rights. The Russian group did not wish to participate in the concession, as this would involve their participation in the advance of 100,000h, which the syndicate was to make to the Persian Government, and they had no intention of assisting that Government financially until they had obtained the option for the railway. It was not so much because they wanted to obtain the mining rights themselves, that the Russian group were opposed to the concession, but because they feared that, if the syndicate obtained it, the latter would be in a position to block the railway, should the alignment eventually agreed on pass through any portion of the concession. I told M. Zveguintsef that we could not allow the question of the concession to be hung up indefinitely, and that, with your assistance, [he Russian group ought not to find it difficult to come to terms with the syndicate.^ Hie objection which he had mentioned to their participation in the concession might, I [2044 i—l]thought, be got over by an ^houkTnot be Actually paid tffl the railway. If, o/the other. handTe Russ an group did not wish to partic.pate in the concession they mighf induce^ the syndicate formally to guarantee the granting of the necessary facilities for tte passage and working of the railway, should it pass through any part of then ““Tzveguintsef said that he would discuss these questions with the other members of the Russian group. , ’GEORGE W. BUCHANAN.^ facility F P a rt of | ^ernfflU [T^PocumenysJi^operty of His Britannic Majesty. flnv Pr ^ P , t ! PERSIA AND CENTRAL ASIA. [January 26. COX f 1 l DEXTIAI [3590] i No. 1. Section 3. isy\ o- ? W i ' -{Received January 26.) Si- 7 ' Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey. (No. 21.) y Sir ’ TNT A .,1 xl . Si. Petersburgh, January 19, 1914. of the accordance with the instructions conveyed to me in your telegram No. 18 of of the 13th instant, 1 spoke to the Minister for Foreign Aflhirs on the 15th instant on e subject ot the Kerman mining concession, and left with him an aide-memoire embodying the substance of what 1 had said. After consulting with the Russian group of the Societe d’fitudes, M. Sazonof sent me a reply in Russian, of which I have the honour to enclose a translation. As I considered this reply very unsatisfactory, I called on his Excellency vesterday and endeavoured to impress on him the great importance which you attached to a speedy settlement of this question. I reminded him that the Persian Mining Syndicate had applied for them concession long before the Trans-Persian Railway scheme had been put forward, and that then no objections had been raised by the Russian Government. His Excellency here interrupted me by saying that it was the invariable practice in the East that a company entrusted with the construction of an important railway should be granted the land on either side of it, and, if the Trans-Persian Railway was to be a financial success, it was necessary that the Societe d’Etudes should make good their claim. I replied that the Persian Mining Syndicate had prior rights which must be respected, and that 1 did not believe that it would be possible for His Majesty’s Government to withdraw the support which they had given them from the outset. In principle, no doubt, there was much to be said for his Excellency’s point of view, but it was preposterous to recognise the right of the Societe ci’Etudes to appropriate a strip of territory 200 kilom. broad wherever the railway might happen to pass, even supposing, as might be the case in our zone, that the said territory was already the property of a British company. The Societe could not be allowed to supplant British enterprise in this way, and if they attempted to do so they would not find much support for their railway scheme in England. The Persian Mining Syndicate, who, had it not been for the veiled and not very friendly opposition of the Russian Government, would have obtained their concession long ago, had made the Societe d’fitudes a fair offer, and I trusted that his Excellency would try and persuade the latter to come to terms with the syndicate and would at the same time withdraw his opposition. M. Sazonof replied that he was in a very difficult position. The Russian group of the Societe d’Btudes was strongly represented in the Duma, and were he to comply with my request he would be accused of sacrificing Russian interests. The concession, moreover, comprised a very large portion of the neutral zone, and Russia could hardly be expected to give us a monopoly in that zone. I said that the exact extent of the concession had been communicated to Count Benckendorff last February, and the Societe d’lEtudes had since been offered a third share of it in the neutral zone. It was, I thought, not fair to cause the syndicate to lose their concession on account of a railway whose alignment had not yet been settled and which his Excellency had recently described as “ Zukunfts-Musik.” M. Sazonof observed that he was afraid that the question of railways in Persia might end by sowing seeds of discord between England and Russia. There was a disposition on the part of the British syndicates interested in this question to look to the eventual connection of their projected lines with the Bagdad Railway. Russia, on the contrary, wanted the Trans-Persian Railway to serve as the great transit railway to India; but the realisation of this project, which depended on directness of route, was being blocked by the difficulties which we were constantly making about the alignment. I assured his Excellency that he was quite wrong in imagining that anyone in England contemplated establishing railway connection with India via the Bagdad Railway. The majority of our projected lines, like that from Mohammerah to Khoremabad, ran in a northerly direction, and on this account met with opposition from Russia. M. Sazonof remarked that there was at any rate one, to which his attention had been called, which was to run from east to west. As regarded the others, be did not suppose that Russia would be able to stop our building a line running [2013 cc—3 J ' i 1 ^ i ■ttmugb our own ,|*o.e fron b Jt. wh.to.or wonid regard Ui.eon.truet.on of . “ il f« ,. railway from A.k.M &lt;o| 5£CT!JSfSSn? S g~. a»5S—«r. w»- *- » -WSEfS *—i* ?F kp “”. K™sSi.““-o.”? conversation once inore which you attached to it. Finally, M. Sasouof more impressed on him the importan p ers i s ted in supporting the claims said that he did not see what was ^ b e done d you p^ to M Kh ^ iakol; and would of the Persian Mining Syndicate. P t(;nns w ; tll t | ie syndicate and to endeavour to induce the Kussian g™ I * of the concession . It was, however, a very withdraw their opposition to the g f t i lt pig efforts would be crowned with difficult matter, and he could not guarantee that success. 1 (fee ’GEORGE W. BUCHANAN. Enclosure in No. 1. Memorandum. THE Imperial Ministay for Fore^ Ke^tl^tpersan^tht the Russian group of the Socie e British Embassy of the 26th November, -id Lc,d« -i.h .he Persian SSt'SSftl »»“ Othc iullowing proposal made to it of a participaUon of one thnd of^ n0 | ay seeking in the neutral sphere macce ptable. Speaking generally, ^ m one participation in the mining enterprise o ! e of land (up to 100 kilom.) on each Societe d'fitudes in great difficulty m the acquirement of the capital necessaiy :S;V£”S And., within the S£*f a*TSnn‘S^1iriw.;%J. ,P Cgii.h group i, nlbt.cd mentioned right to a zone of land on each side of the ra.W the d b refuse to take a proportional part in the in Xn for ttegrant to it oJ- Syndicate intends to offer the Government of the Shah in return tor g the concession sought. St. Petersburgh, January 4 (17), 1914.In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. 5858/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. if latent ial. Sir:- fCo nv o', 4- p s.O I oia AW ^ —V 20 FEB 1914 — j ; ' ‘M&lt; • . _ India. 4 1 'u y Foreign Office /V 6 r\ o r : n 914 16th February, 1914. I i With reference to your letter of the 3rd of November last P.4461, and to my reply of the 26th of that month regarding the Trsjis-Persian Railway project, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith, to be laid before the Marquess of Crewe, a copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Minister at Teheran deprecating the employment of a purely Russian escort in the north and of a purely British one in the south to accompany the Joint Technical Commission in due course. Sir E.Grey would be glad to receive His Lordship's observations on Sir W.Townley’s despatch. I am. Sir, Under Secretary of State, Your mo st ob e d i ent, humble Servant, India Office.[This Document is the Property of His B ritannic Majesty’s Government,! “ ■ ' ——■ —; %RSIA AND CENTRAL ASIA. [Febrnary 9. CONFIDENTIAL. Section H, [5858] No. 1. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey—(Received February 9.) (No. 4. Confidential.) Si r &gt; , Tehran, January 8, 1914. IT is stated in a telegram from the Government of India to the Marquess of Crewe, dated the 16th October last (see Confidential Print Sections, “Persia,” [50005] of the 3rd November) upon the subject of the proposed Trans-Persian Railway, that it is strongly recommended that a purely Russian escort should accompany the Joint Technical Commission over the first part of the alignment, and that it should be relieved by a British escort at Yezdikhast or Shiraz. I would most respectfully venture to point out that there would appear to me to be serious objections to the adoption of this proposal, which I have not seen commented upon in any subsequent correspondence which has reached me. As I understand the idea of the proposed railway, it is to be a purely commercial enterprise, enjoying, of course, the full support of the two Governments interested, but divested, as far as may be possible, of all that may make it an object of suspicion as a political or strategical undertaking on the part of the two Governments. Were the Commission to be escorted by a force of Russian soldiers whilst passing through the district which is publicly recognised as being under Russian influence, and by British troops in the region where British interests are specially predominant, it would, in my opinion, create much suspicion in the Persian mind as to the genuineness of the enterprise being commercial, and would be calculated to engender serious opposition. There is no doubt that it would be well that the Commission should be escorted, although the road as far as Shiraz or Kerman would be perfectly safe, but I am very strongly of opinion that it would be most desirable that the escort should be composed of a Persian force, such as the Cossacks or the gendarmes, or of a composite force of the two, under Russian or Swedish officers, as the case might be. I have spoken to my Russian colleague in this sense, without telling him the reason for my doing so, and he entirely agrees with me that much possible opposition to the scheme would be avoided by the use of a Persian force, whilst the danger of a malicious attack upon the Commission would be greatly reduced. I have, &amp;c. WALTER TOWNLEY. [2044 II] _ T To. Co '' ' ’ 27 FEBCONFIDKNTIAL. Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received February 7, 10'15 p.m.) St. Petersburgh, February 7, 1914. (No. 40.) {February 7, 8 '12 p.m.) MY immediate preceding telegram M. Raffalovitch, who came to see me this morning, suggested that request for railway we have received should be made by Societe d’Etudes and sent either by registered letter direct to Persian Government or through Persian Minister in Paris. Reply of Russian Government to your despatch No. 434 of 1913 would be communicated to me in a few days. He expressed himself strongly against Bunder Abbas as a terminal port. With regard to mining concession, he said that syndicate must remember they could not lay claim to vested interests as they had not yet obtained concession, and that though they might have support of His Majesty’s Government they had to reckon with action of Russian group. Latter had never been told anything about concession when railway scheme was first started. . I replied that we equally had not been told till quite recently anything about Soci^te d’Etudes’ claim to 100 kilom. on either side of the railway, and that adoption of his proposed line of argument would make a bad impression on you. Societe ought to empower department to negotiate an arrangement with syndicate, as till concession was obtained no progress could be made with railway question. . Finally he said that he would be in London in a fortnight, and had no objection to discussing question with syndicate. He would consult French group on his way throug Paris and British group on arrival in London so as to be able to speak m the name ot societe. Syndicate was not a strong one financially, and he doubted whether Lord Revelstoke would care to co-operate with them by accepting a third share. Un my urging him to suggest some practical solution of question, he said that ifussian group would not oppose concession provided that they could safeguard interests of railway. They must have land on either side of railway to ensure its satisfactory working, and they might allow syndicate to obtain concession, provided that latter undertook to retrocede to soci^te portion of it through which railway might eventually pass sufficient for above purpose. _ Concession was of such enormous extent tha syndicate could begin mining operations m those portions of it Y h V ch h ^ e . n °y^ ly * be traversed by railway, and, though such an arrangement might h-eys ^van- tages, Eussian group were not to blame for being unable to mdicate preci^alignment It might bl advisable before he arrives m London to try and predispose Entish group in favour of some satisfactory arrangement with mining syndicate. 1 1CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh). (No. 50.) R. Foreign Office, February 2, 1914, 4T5 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 23 of 29th January : Trans-Persian Railway. We wish Survey Commission to first examine alignment from Ispahan to Shiraz and Bunder Abbas, as we consider that the terminal port should be there or in its immediate vicinity. Although we should be willing to receive any observations of survey party on commercial aspects of any possible alignment, we are not likely to agree, as at present advised, to any terminal port east of Bunder Abbas. There is no question of a loan of l,000,000L in connection with Kerman concession. The syndicate, when the concession is granted, would make an advance of 100,000Z. ; but this is a separate transaction, and has nothing to do with option of railway. You should explain this to M. Zuegintzof, and ask him to let you know with as little delay as possible whether his group would be satisfied if syndicate gave guarantees for facilities for passage and working of railway should it pass through any portion of their concession.Registry No. 434^/1914. o Draft. a?-*- .. A- ^ r4h -\ 'p-, CfM ,.4 , A.1 V Wi V* ' 6 . v^ ' ^ ^ Jk l ^ 1 gi i I :\ F. 0 ., 'V \ j I _•/ i 7^7 Your tel. No. 23 ( of 29 Jan: Trans- Persian Railway). Sir G.Buchanan, Tel No. \F* 0 . O^V^DLH^'-rL# , * V/e wish survey commission to first exa mine alignment from Isfahan to Shiraz and Bunder Abbas as we consider that the termin al port should be there or in its immediate vicinity. Although we should be willing to receive any observations of survey party on comnercial aspects of any possible align ment we are not likely to agree as at presort advised to any terminal port east of Bunder Abbas. v There is no question of a loan of a million pounds in connection with Kerman concession. The Syndicate, when the conces sion is granted, would make an advance of £loo,ooo, but this is a separate transactio n and has nothing to do with option of railway. You should explain this to M.Zvegintseff an fC ask him to let you know with as little de lay as possible whether his group would be satisfied if Syndicate gave guarantees for facilities for passage and working of rail way should it pass through any portion of their concession.) a 5J r' CONFIDENTIAL. , V U, f ■■ u ii . • v »r '&gt; ^ $ir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received January 30, 11 a.m.) St. Petersburgh, January 29, 1914. (No. 23.) R J (January 29, 9*30 p.m.) MY immediately preceding telegram of 25th January : Trans-Persian Railway. I had informal conversation with M. Zvegintzef to-day. He told me that the impression made by your despatch No. 434 of 30th December ( ggi last year was that His Majesty’s Government were irrevocably committed to Bunder Abbas as terminal port and that they would veto Charbar. Alignment by the former would be longer by about 140 miles, would be less profitable commercially and would render it easier for Bagdad Railway to eventually tap Trans-Persian. In view of attitude of His Majesty’s Government, many members of Russian group doubted whether it was worth while proceeding with request for option. I read him your telegram No. 176 of 1st March last year to show impracticability ^ of connecting with Bagdad Railway. He admitted this as regards railway from Khanikin to Ispahan, but maintained that our projected rail wav from Bunder Abbas to Ah waz could be linked up with Basra via Mohammerah. I said that we had never con templated such a connection, that as regards terminal port you had no wish to prejudge work of survey party, and that I therefore gathered, though you considered Charbar undesirable, choice was left open until their report had been received. There was nothing in my opinion to prevent our asking for option on lines proposed in your telegram No. 543 of 19th July last. He agreed provided that my view was correct. In that case he would prefer request, though addressed to Persian Government by the societe, should be presented through the two legations so as to avoid expense W of sending out representative of each of the three groups. As regards question of concession of port, he thought it would he sufficient were all reasonable facilities granted as you suggest. He would prefer that commission of investigation should be composed of representatives of the three groups, though latter would be free to select Government officials if they desired. Their recommendations would of course have to be ratified by the two Governments. I asked what would happen should they recommend Charbar and should we veto it. He replied that we could propose that work of construction should commence in y v north and proceed southward till it reached Yezd, leaving question of its further alignment open. Great thing was to prevent this Anglo-Russian enterprise breaking down, and by that time Indian public opinion might have changed. I then repeated to him what I had said to Minister for Foreign Affairs about mining concession, observing that if British vested interests were to be sacrificed to the Trans-Persian Railway that scheme would come to naught. He admitted that vested rights must be respected. Russian group did not wish to participate in concession, as this would involve participation in proposed loan of 1,000,0001., and until option had been secured they would not help Persian Government to obtain loan. They were opposed to concession not so much because they wanted mining rights, but because syndicate would be able to block railway were alignment eventually agreed on to pass through it. I replied that we could not allow question of concession to be hung up indefinitely, and that with your help it ought not to be difficult for Russian group to come to terms with syndicate. If they wanted share in concession it might be arranged that projected loan should be conditional on granting of the option. If not they might negotiate arrangement under which syndicate guaranteed to give all facilities for passage and working of railway should it pass through any portion of their concession. He said he would talk question over with his friends. I gather there is divergence of opinion among members of Russian group, and I do not know whether M. Zvegintzef accurately represents the majority. If views I expressed about terminal port are correct, I should like to be able to say so officially, and I should be grateful for any suggestions that might induce Russian group to come to terms with mining syndicate. |;121—406] COPY TO INDia, j k.'&amp;Jt.mmifi 'ii—r- 5 \ • 'v Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received January 26, 8 a.m.) St. Petersburgh, January 25, 1914. {No. 22.) ' (January 25, 4 p.m.) YOUR telegram No. 35 of 23rd January : Trans-Persian Railway. His Excellency expressed doubts as to use of asking for option for whole railway in view of our attitude towards it (see my immediately preceding telegram I reminded him that we had agreed to ask for option of railway across Persia from north-west to south-east without specifying alignment in the south. He said that he would like to discuss the whole question with M. Raffallovitch, who is expected here shortly, before replying.'This Doenmest is the Property of PERSIA AND CENTRAL ASIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [1429] No - L Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received January 12.) (No. 6.) a- r St. Petersbnrgh, January 12, 1914. I HANDED to the Minister for Foreign Affairs yesterday a copy of your despatch No. 434 of the 31st ultimo on the subject of the Trans-Persian Railway project, after giving him a brief summary of its contents. # The only point which M. Sazonof discussed in any detail was that of the participation of the French in the request for the option. The suggestion that the French Minister should join in the representations to be made by his Russian and British colleagues had, his Excellency said, really come from the Persian Government, who were afraid that, were they to comply with the request for an option addressed to them by England and Russia alone, Persian public opinion would reproach them with grantino' to those two Powers a concession that would result in the eventual partition of Persia between them. From what Vossuk-ed-Dowleh had said to the Russian Charge d’Affaires it appeared that the Persian Government would greatly prefer that the request for the option should be made in the first instance by the Societe d’Etudes, and that, as soon as this request had been presented, the British and Russian Legations should make representations in support of it. M. Sazonof expressed the opinion that this would be the best procedure to follow. ^ • j j j u Though questioning me somewhat closely with regard to the attitude adopted by His Majesty’s Government on the subject of the concessions of ports on the Persian Gulf his Excellency gave me no indication of what his own views were on the subject, or as towhether he would be satisfied with an application for the granting of all reasonable facilities to the International Company at the maritime terminus. On my referring to the Persian Railways Syndicate, M. Sazonof remarked that he feared that some of the lines which they wished to construct in a northerly direction from the coast would meet with opposition from the Russian Government. He also observed, during the course of our conversation, that his personal opinion was that, until^His Majesty s Government were prepared to link up the Trans-Persian Railway with the Indian railway system, nothing would be done beyond the construction of certain sections of it, and that the scheme as a whole was “ Zukunfts Musik.” I have, &amp;c. G. W. BUCHANAN. [‘Z013 m —9] Copy to India 30 JAN 1914CONFIDENTIAL. Su II da aid Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Peter shurgh). AT Trro , Foreign Office, March 1, 1913, 1 p.m TOUR telegram No 173 of 27th February : Khanikin-Ispaban Railway. Our advisers say that a line from Khanikin to Ispahan would probably not be feasible in the neutral sphere from an engineering point of view except at a prohibitive cost as the region is one of the most mountainous in Persia and the ranges have a marked trend from north-west to south-east. An alignment might be found within the Russian spheie, but would be costly, and the Potsdam Agreement makes such an align- ment impossible without Russian consent. S Ihis is a very important point which you should bring to M. Sazonof’s notice aa it appears to dispose m a practical manner of connection with the Bagdad Railway.CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh). YOUR telegram No. 236 of 28th June : Optio^fOT TSns-Sian^RaRwky. P ' M ' Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs has telegraphed to Russian Ambassador that he had not intended to send further instructions to Tehran, but that, now that the difference between His Majesty s Government and the British group appears to be settled, he sees no objection to an application for an option at Tehran You should therefore propose to his Excellency that, in the first instance, the two representatives at Tehran should be instructed to ask the Persian Government to grant to the Societe d Etudes an option for the construction of a railway traversing Persia from south-west to south-east. Details could be settled later by consultation between the two Governments and the societe. The two representatives must also be eventually instructed to inform Persian Government of the proposed despatch of an Anglo-Russian Commission to survey that part of Persia through which the southern part of the line will run with a view to recommend which alignment should be adopted, and to ask their consent. This step might be deferred till Persian Government have replied to application for the option but m any case it would be well that the two Governments should proceed without delay to appoint the members of the joint commission, so that it may be ready to begin woris as soon as Persian Government have consented to its despatch. (Repeated to Tehran, No. 314.) [^03—4961■■ — .i m ngwmww CONFIDENTIAL. 1 I 1 ^ e i Kjj ! 9, Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received January 22, 10 p.m.) Tehran, January 22, 1914. (January 22, l‘o0 p.m.) (No. 22.) R. YOUR telegram No. 11 My Russian colleague is without instructions^ but I took occasion, after discussing matter with him, of a recent visit to Minister for Foreign Affairs to ask his Excellency why the Persian Government desired that request for transaction of Persian option should be made by Societe d’Etudes, and if really serious importance was attached to this being done. Minister for Foreign Affairs replied that Persian Government consider it most desirable thnt this procedure should be followed, because they consider that it would help to make enterprise popular. His Excellency added that Persian Government had expressed on the same occasion hopes that Societe would make Persia a loan, or, at least, a considerable advance on some future loan. ' 24JAN1S14 [121—279]CONFIDENTIAL. t I J Q . Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh). (No. 23.) R. y Foreign Office, January 16, 1914, 3'45 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 15 : Trans-Persian Railway. I concur in the proposal of the Russian Government, and have instructed Sir W. Townley accordingly. (* 2U^ nsU [121—215]CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Buchanan to Sir hi dicard Grey,—(Received January 15, 10 p.m.) /at Petersburqh, January 15, 1914. &lt; No -15.) R ;, , T J 9 p.m.) Y()UR telegram No. 16 : Trans-Persian Railway. Minister for Foreign Affairs said he thought it would be easier for Persian Government to accede to request for option made by Society d’Etudes than to one presented to them by the two legations. As, moreover, German Government were aware that concession was to be granted to international company in which French weie repiesented, he did not think that it mattered much by whom request was presented. He would suggest that our representatives at Tehran should be instructed to confer together and to endeavour to ascertain whether Persian Government attached serious importance to request being made by societe, as it was only out of consideration for their position that he had moved in the matter. fy ^ \ 21JAN1914 ! •Tj [121—204]IZ__ ._^~aam.»..»il.ijyi. . n'™*'*'' CONFIDENTIAL. 7 (No. 16.) R. TRANS-PERSIAN Railway. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan {St. Petersburgh). ^otaat Foreign Office, January 12, 1914, 6 p.m. Russian Charge d’Affaires has communicated to us that Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs desires that request for option should be presented by Societe d’Etudes and not by two legations, and that Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs is disposed to meet his wishes. I should be prepared to join with Russian Government in asking societe if they would be willing to adopt this course, but I presume Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs has considered that the request will consequently be made by a group in which the French participate, and that Germany may therefore possibly raise objections. I should have preferred the two legations making the request, as had been already arranged, but I will not press this if it is likely to cause difficulties at Tehran. [121—137]rmsjoca-flieiit is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] 0 &lt;K PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. &amp;hi: :u [December 31.] Q! Seciion 1. [56211] No. 1. &amp;ir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan. (No. 434.) Eoreian Office T)eeemher 31 1Q13 ON the 27th September last the Russian Charge d’AffL; comr^cated a n^te explaining ^ the attitude of his Government on three points respecting the Trans- Rersian Railway project, and at the same time invited an expression of the views of His Majesty s Government. dne attitude of the Russian Government on the three points m question was as follows :— r (i.) fhey would agree that the request to be made to the Persian Government for an option should be presented by the British and Russian Legations at lehran instead of by the Societe d’Etudes itself, but they would prefer that the French Legation should join in the request. (ii.) They considered that the Russian and French groups were justified in wishing to include in the application to ihe Persian Government a request that r ^ ree access to ports should be fully guaranteed to the railway company. (hi.) They concurred in the wish of the Societe d’Etudes that a representative of the French Government should be included in the commission of investiga tion in the south, and, if such an arrangement should prove impracticable, the Russian Government considered that the Russian and French delegates on the commission might be representatives of the Societe d’Etudes who, in such a contingency, would meet the expenditure involved. 2. His Majesty’s Government have, in consultation with the Government of India, given these matters their careful attention, and I now have to request you to bring the following considerations before the Russian Government:— (i.) cl His Majesty s Government have grave doubts as to the expediency of the French Legation joining in the request to the Persian Government for an option. Other Powers are quite willing to admit and to recognise the special and predominant interests of Great Britain and Russia in Persia, where it is natural and reasonable that those two Powers should be concerned in such a request. But if a third Power were to be ostensibly and officially associated with Great Britain and Russia, it would be difficulty to resist claims of other countries to be placed on a footing similar to that of France. lor this reason His Majesty’s Government would deprecate the co-operation of the French Government in the step in question; and they are assured by His Majesty s Minister at Tehran that such co-operation would not, in his opinion, be of substantial assistance in securing the option. 4. The French Government have, however, recently communicated and recom mended a proposal of the Societe d’Dtudes for an alternative procedure, according to which an identic request for an option would be made by the British and Russian Legations, to be followed by a separate representation of the French Legation which, basing its action on the fact that the Societe d’Etudes is a French company, would recommend it to the Persian Government Provided the action of the French Legation is, so far as possible, treated as confidential and not made the subject of outside comment, His Majesty s Government recognise that the procedure now proposed would not be liable to the same objections. (ii.) 5. His Majesty’s Government would strongly deprecate any attempt to obtain from the Persian Government an assurance, as originally proposed by the Societe d’Etudes, that without a previous understanding with that body no concession for ports would be given to third parties at any points where the mam line or branches of the Trans- [1967 hh —1] Cc y YO c G JAN 1914 J ii.. .if m .^npigiBwrr ! i s -firct nlace, an exclusive assurance of Persian Railway may reach the c0 ^ DOS ition and prospects of the Persian this nature would manifestly F e J uc ^ Gover P nme nt are, and indeed were even before Railways Syndicate which ® led a in some measure to support. Such the constitution of the Societe d h-tud , P ^ of the 0 ln ; on that some arrangement being the case, His Majesty s Governme ; between the Societe d’Etudes and^; for the fusion of interests or at least essentiaL the Persian Railways Syndicate wid e • ^. tant cons ideration, I feel confident that 6. But apart altogether from this ^ 0 ^ 0 ^ the 29th August&gt; 19 o 7j to the Russian Government in the hgh y P political reasons, His Majesty’s Sir A. iSicolson, will ent.rely appreciate *at, ior p ^ ^ lication fm . Government could not acquiesce in, r ‘ eS c S omp ^ y . Subject, however, to the concession of a port to an m y rn . a * 1 d ‘ +he i ocat fo n of the^ort, and to such reservation reservation of conditions of control a Majesty’s Government would being expressly st^ed m the n^e ^^appMation,^ aU at such aoree to an application to the Persian iaov e maritime terminus as may eventual y e se e (iii.) 7m Majesty's Gov—»■ ^ be undertaken in the south, hold tha French participation in the ^ex^ahove uX (i), they consider such participation theb' opinion, be that from examine the possible alignments, H J V t h ere by be committed to accept wish to make on commercial aspects, but they ^ align . ^rtom tl point 0 “ otm”and political results has confirmed the ophfon of His Majesty’s^Government that an alignment terminating at a port eas Abbas would be^desmabl, ^ action respecting al^^^ enumerated in section (a) of the enclosure in my despatch No 64 of the iqi^ to vonr Excellencv. A. copy of this soction is enclosed for mcil^ y 11. His Majesty’s Government would be glad to attach a Bnt t lsP r ^P reS ^ ^ m to the survey party which is to examine the question of f 1?^. “h ed to section of the proposed railway, and, as Russian representative the commission in the south, f trust the Russian Government will accede to this proposal. ^ shoiiM commun ; cate a copy of this despatch to the Russian Minister for Foreign Affidrs. 1 ^ &amp;c E. GREY. Enclosure in No. 1. Section (d) of Enclosure in Despatch No. 64 to St. Petersburgh, February 5, 1913. U )His Majesty’s Government have already expressed themselves ^ he principle to the project of a Trans-Persian railway: that assent is maoe subject to the follow g, among other, conditions :— That no part of the line or its connections shall be constructed °? t3ld ® P P f ® i ^ b S 1 phe ^aUhe and in such measures as, His Majesty’s Government shall consider^ politma^feas^bi^e main line must pass through Ispahan by Shiraz, and i i , or , hesty ’s Government do not sphere, it must reach that sphere at Bunder Abbas, that 3dl3 } Abbas and Karachi to FUdf fKo hin^p has vet come for a connection between Bundebe made, and as there must be no question of making it until His Majesty’s Government consider that the time has come when it is desirable, the question of branch and local lines should be considered on their merits, and their commercial advantages should not be sacrificed to the project of through connection ; that His Majesty’s Government undertake no financial guarantee in regard to the project; that the point where the line touches the Persian Gulf shall be referred to His Majesty’s Government when the surveys have been completed, and the arrangements for the ^naritime terminus, and for its control, shall be submitted to their approval; that the question of the gauge outside the Russian sphere shall be submitted to His Majesty’s Government; that effective means must be provided, to the satisfaction of His Majesty’s Government, to secure British trade against differential treatment of any kind, direct or indirect, on any railway constructed under a concession obtained by the Societe d’^ltudes; that British control must predominate in the Southern j or Gulf section of any Trans-Persian line, or of the branches, which may be made, and that this 1 control shall not be invalidated by any arrangement which may be made in regard to the percentage of other (i.e., non-British) participation in the undertaking.—O 19! /i PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [56275] [December 29.] Section 1. No. 1. Sir E. Crowe to Lord Ernngton. (Private and Confidential.) Foreign Office, December 29, 1913. ,„u Li Si, w. Garstiu as to French co-operation n ^011 of a nature to enable the British group to B.A^n^ir.c-s.So, p—.—«* '*“ d “ this question. . , ra i se d in the letter of the president of the You will remember that the last) wi th regard to which he has the Societe d’Etudes, dated th Povernments were three. fc?“Sn«.S5 of ti. to. ” ”“«• ito -Mol. I —I “ “ This proposal appeared to ^ for have now suggested an alternative offer certain objections, but the Prencn wo procedure which^w^can^ee^ur way ^ applicatioa of a request that free access to ports should be fully guaranteed ^ “g^on^thm request in the form in which p We are still unwilling to admit the nciusionot^^ ^q ^ would be possible tQ M. Raindre’s letter orl ^ a Lich would satisfy the legitimate aspirations of arrive at a compromise m the matt , ^ wllic p we feel bound to adhere. the societe ^“^a^fwRh of the soeiete for French participation in the ““tkwe'^fSoTedhfag^on certain conditions which ought, we think, to be acceptable to the ^JX^ench Government a definite answer on the Before, however, we can give t ^ tbe Russian Government with regard three points raised, 'we mus gt may take some little time, and as to them, and this we are trying ^ mu ® ^ settled with the Russians before the f to toi™ tofS M P.too. **•.»“«“ »““« * b ” p “* ,OTl ' question. I am, &amp;c. H E. A. CROWE.[Ths Becmment is the Property cf His Brlasmc MEiestys Government.] 1 PERSIA. [December 13.] CONFIDENTIATj. Section 1. [56275] No. 1. Lord Errington to Sir E. Crowe.—(Received December 13.) (Private.) Dear Crowe, 8, Bishopsgate, London, December 12, 1913. SOCIETE d’Etudes. We expect shortly to receive an invitation from Paris to proceed there and explain the present position of affairs on behalf of the English group of the Societe inter- nationale d’Etudes du Chemin de Fer transpersan. It will be within your recollection that Sir William Garstin and I approached you privately last October in regard to the question of the diplomatic letter, the presentation of which to the Persian Government is still in contemplation. At the time you were good enough to inform us that negotiations were in progress between the Foreign Office and the French Government in regard to the principle and extent of French co-operation in Persia. May we enquire whether these negotiations have reached a conclusion, and whether there is any communication you can properly make to us in order that we may be in a position to continue discussions in Paris when invited to do so ? Yours sincerely, EKEtINGTON. [1967 n—l]) ^ In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. 56211A 3. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. if Immediate. Foreign Office December 29th 1913. U Sir: - I an directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 12th instant (P.4822), commenting on the draft despatch which it is proposed to address to His Majesty’s Representative at St. Petersourg respecting the three points raised oy the President of the Societe d’Etudes of the Trans-Persian Railway with the support of the French and Russian Gov ernments. Sir E. Grey has learnt with satisfaction that the Marquess of Crewe shares his views as to the manner in which tne first two points snould be dealt with, and ne is in general agreement with His Lordship's ooservacions regarding the last point He is accordingly disposed to concur with Lord Crewe The Under Secretary of State, India Office.(56211/13) ,v V • _ A .Ts ' - in the opinion that an addition to the draft despatch i: desirable to give effect to these observations, but he considers it important, in making this addition to show clearly that His Majesty’s Government have no wish to prejudge the conclusions of the proposed commission of investigauion ana oo emphasise tne fact that they have from the beginning of these negotiations declared that Bandar Abbas was the port at which British interests demand that the railway shall reach the sea. He has accordingly inserted in the draft the following sentence in suostit»ution for that proposed in your letter:- “They make this reservation in general terms as they do not wish to prejudge the work of the survey party or any observations which its members may wish to make on commercial aspects, but they think it right to state for the information of the Russian Government that the examination of possible alignments from the point of view of military and political results has confirmed the opinion of His Majesty’s Government that an alignment terminating(56211/13) at a port east of Bandar Abbas would be undesirable'. A copy oi the draft in its amended form is enclosed I am, Si r, Your most obedient, humble Servant,Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] _ ON tbe 27th September last the Russian Charge d’Affaires communicated a note explaining the attitude of his Government on three points respecting the Trans-Persian Railway project, and at the same time invited an expression of the views of His Majesty’s Government. The attitude of the Russian Government on the three points in question was as follows :— (i.) They would agree that the request to be made to the Persian Government for an option should be presented by the British and Russian Legations at Tehran instead of by the Societe d’Btudes itself, but they would prefer that the French Legation should join in the request. ( 11 .) They considered that the Russian and French groups were justified in washing to include in the application to the Persian Government a request that free access to ports should be fully guaranteed to the railway company. (iii.) They concurred in the wish of the Societe d’Etudes that a representative of the French Government should be included in the commission of investigation in the south, and, if such an arrangement should prove impracticable, the Russian Govern ment considered that the Russian and French delegates on the commission might be representatives of the Societe d’Etudes who, in such a contingency, would meet the expenditure involved. 2. His Majesty’s Government have, in consulta tion with the Government of India, given these matters their careful attention, and I now have to request you to bring the following considera tions before the Russian Government:— ( ■ •) 3. His Majesty’s Government have grave doubts as to the expediency of the French Legation joining in the request to the Persian Government % for an option. Other Powers are quite willing CONFIDENTIAL. u Draft to Mr. O’Beirne. (No, Sir, Foreign Office, November , 1913. [1379]to admit and to recognise the special and pre dominant interests of Great Britain and Bussia in Persia, where it is natural and reasonable that those two Powers should he concerned in such a request. But if a third Power were to be ostensibly and officially associated with Great Britain and Russia, it would be difficult to resist claims of other countries to be placed on a footing similar to that of France. For this reason Plis Majesty’s Government w r ould deprecate the co operation of the French Government in the step in question; and they are assured by His Majesty s Minister at Tehran that such co-operation would not, in his opinion, he of substantial assistance in securing the option. 4. The French Government have, however, recently communicated and recommended a pro posal of the Societe d’Etudes for an alternative procedure, according to which an identic request for an option would be made by the British and Russian Legations, to be followed by a separate representation of the French Legation which, basing its action on the fact that the Societe d’Etudes is a French company, would recommend it to the Persian Government. Provided the action of the French Legation is, so far as possible, treated as confidential and not made the subject of outside comment, His Majesty’s Government recognise that the procedure now proposed would not be liable to the same objections. (ii.) 5. His Majesty’s Government would strongly deprecate any attempt to obtain from the Persian Government an assurance, as originally proposed by the Societe d’Etudes, that without a previous understanding with that body no concession for ports would be given to third parties at any points where the main line or branches of the Trans-Persian Railway may reach the coast. In the first place, an exclusive assurance of this nature would manifestly prejudice the position and prospects of the Persian Railways Syndicate, which His Majesty’s Government are, and indeed were even before the constitution of the Societe d’Etudes, pledged in some measure to support. Such being the case, His Majesty’s Government remain of the opinion that some arrangement for the fusion of interests or at least for co-operation between the Societe d’Etudes and the Persian3 Railways Syndicate will eventually prove essential. 6. But apart altogether from this important consideration, I feel confident that the Russian Government, in the light of my despatch of the 29th August, 1907, to Sir A. Nicolson, will entirely appreciate that, for political reasons, His Majesty’s Government could not acquiesce in, and still less support the application for, any concession of a port to an international railway company. Subject, however, to the reservation of conditions of control and the location of the port, and to such reservation being expressly stated in the note of application, His Majesty’s Government would agree to an application to the Persian Government for all reasonable facilities at such maritime terminus as may eventually be selected. (iii.) 7. His Majesty’s Government, being closely * concerned in the investigation to be undertaken in the south, hold that the Commission should be composed of representatives of the Governments ; they would agree to French participation in the Commission, but, for reasons similar to those explained above under (i), they consider such par ticipation should be as informal and unobtrusive as possible. 8. The first alignment to be examined should, in their opinion, be that from Ispahan to Shiraz and Bunder Abbas. 9. In agreeing to the project of a commission of investigation in the south, to examine the possible alignments, His Majesty’s Government must make their assent subject to an express condition that they will not thereby be com mitted to accept the finding of the commission without further examination of its military and political results. They make this reservation in general terms as they do not wish to prejudge the work of the survey party or any observations which its members may wish to make on commercial aspects, but they think it right to state, for the information of the Russian Government, that the exami nation of possible alignments from the point of view of military and political results has confirmed the opinion of His Majesty’s Government that an alignment terminating at a port east of Bunder Abbas would be undesirable. [1379] , B 210. They also reserve complete freedom of action respecting all other points enumerated in section (a) of the enclosure in my despatch No. 64 of the 5th February, 1913, to Sir G. Buchanan. A copy of this section is enclosed for facility of reference. 11. His Majesty’s Government would be glad to attach a British representative to the survey party which is to examine the question of align ment for the northern section of the proposed railway, and, as Russian representatives will be attached to the commission in the south, I trust the Russian Government will accede to this proposal. 12. You should communicate a copy of this despatch to the Russian Minister tor 1 oi eign Affairs. 0PM i 15 ) I I (Enclosure.) (a.) His Majesty’s Government have already expressed themselves prepared to assent' in principle to the project of a Trans-Persian railway : that assent is made subject to the followino-, among other, conditions :— That no part of the line or its connections shall be constructed outside the Eussian sphere until, and in such measures as, His Majesty’s Government shall consider it politic and feasible ; that the’ main line must pass through Ispahan by Shiraz, and if it, or any branch, is continued to the British sphere, it must reach that sphere at Bunder Abbas; that His Majesty’s Government do not think that the time, has yet come for a connection between Bunder Abbas and Karachi to be made, and as there must be no question of making it until His Majesty’s Government consider that the time has come when it is desirable, the question of branch and local lines should be considered on their merits, and their commercial advantages should not be sacrificed to the project of through connection ; that His Majesty’s Government undertake no financial guarantee in regard to the project; that the point where the line touches the Persian Gulf shall be referred to His Majesty’s Government when the surveys have been completed, and the arrangements for the maritime terminus, and for its control, shall be submitted to their approval; that the question of the gauge outside the Eussian sphere shall be submitted to His Majesty’s Government; that effective means must be provided, to the satisfaction of His Majesty’s Government, to secure British trade against differential treatment of any kind, direct or indirect, on any railway constructed under a concession obtained by the Societe d’Etudes; that British control must predominate in the Southern or Gulf section of any Trans-Persian line, or of the branches, which may be made, and that this control shall not be invalidated by any arrangement which may be made in regard to the percentage of other (f.e., non-British) participation in the undertaking. ,1P. 4822. Immediate. India Office, S.W. 12th December 1913 a Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 50,005, of the 26th November, regarding the Trans-Persian Railway, and in reply to say that he acquiesces in the conclu sions of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs as regards points 1 and 2 enumerated therein, and has no criticism to make on the draft despatch to His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires, St. Petersburg, so far as it relates The Marquess of Crewe also concurs in the treatment of point 3 as Ear as it goes, though he thinks that it may require to be supplemented in the light of the letter from the War Office of 18th November, of which I am to enclose a copy for Sir E. Grey’s consideration. This letter conveys the formal views of the military advisers of His Majesty’s Government, which have the approval, his Lordship understands, of the Secretary of State for War; and the substance of the conclusion reached appears to be that the alignment via Kerman does not in itself involve any serious military danger to India, provided that the international line does not thereafter reach the water at any point east of Bunder Abbas. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff would strongly prefer that the line connecting Kerman with Bunder Abbas should be an inde pendent British line, but Lord Crewe observes that he describes this condition only as “advisable ’’ strategically, and he himself would not lay too much stress upon it, provided that British control is secured for that section. Lord Crewe agrees with Sir John French that it is important that the line (whether constructed by the Societe or by purely British Agency) should be already in existence when the international line reaches Kerman, so that there may be no excuse for an extension of the latter to the water east of Bundar Abbas. More important is the opinion of the military authorities that the interna tional line must not be so extended, that should such an extension take place, an increase in the strength of the army in India would be necessary, and that tne increase would be greater the further east the point of debouchment. Lord Crewe considers that the revenues of India would be unable to bear the increased expenditure. I am to refer to my letter of the 22nd July 1913, No. 2918, and to recommend that unless Sir Edward Grey is prepared to accept the conclusion of the Chief of the General Staff as final, the question should be re-submitted to the Committee of Imperial Defence. If it be accepted, Lord Crewe is of opinion that unless His Majesty’s Govern ment are prepared to relieve India of a responsibility that is beyond her resources, they would for this reason alone not be justified in accepting a terminus east of Bunder Abbas. Lord Crewe is aware that on considering the report of the Interdepart mental Committee of the 29th May 1913, Sir Edward Grey came to the conclusion that until the Technical Commission had examined the ground it to them. The Under Secretary of State, — — Foreign Office. f (0 ’rvdla S. 231. 19 DEC 1913was not necessary to consider the Russian alignment. The Russian alignment had Chahbar as its objective, whereas the Interdepartmental Committee, in accordance with the recommendation of the Committee of Imperial Defence, ruled out of discussion any port east of Bundar Abbas. Lord Crewe appreciates the considerations which favour postponement of a final decision on the alignment of the railway until the Commission have reported, and he understands that Sir Edwaid Grey is satisfied that the reservations to be communicated by Sir George Buchanan to the Russian Government leave His Majesty’s Government sufficient liberty of action at the proper time. But he is afraid that if the survey is allowed to proceed, and if the Commission should eventually recommend the Kerman-Chahbar alignment as the only one financially and commercially possible, it will be much more difficult for His Majesty’s Government to resist it. Lord Crewe would, therefore, ask Sir Edward Grey to consider whether the despatch which Sir George Buchanan is to communicate to the Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs should not state that His Majesty’s Govern ment would be unable in any case to entertain the idea of an alignment debouching to the east of Bundar Abbas. It is suggested that to paragraph 11 of the draft a sentence might be added somewhat to this effect: “ The examination of possible alignments which they have already “ made from these points of view has led them to the conclusion that an “ alignment terminating at a port east of Bundar Abbas would be opposed “ to their interests.” I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient Servant, (Signed) T. W. Holderness. IENCLOSURE. Sir, War Office to India Office. No. 0 164/2882. (M.O. 1). War Office, London. S.W., 18th November 1913. I am commanded by the Army Council to forward herewith in reply tp India Office better No. P. 2716 of 19th July last, a memorandum'^ « Memorandum by Chief of the General the Considered opinion of Staff, India, dated 5th September 1912. t | le . i nie± o± the Imperial General . A ^ Staff upon the effect on the defence of India of the alignment via Iverman of an international railway across Persia with special reference to the considerations urged in the memorandum of the Chief of the General Staff, India, dated the 6th June last. I am also to return enclosures! Nos. 1 and 4 to the above-quoted letter, as requested therein. I am further to regret the delay which has unavoidably occurred in replying to the India Office letter. I have, &amp;c., The Under Secretary of State R. H. Brade. lor India. t Memorandum on projected railway construction in Russian Central Asia 1913. Effect on the Defence of India of an Alignment via Kerman of the Trans-Persian Railway. 1. The India Office ask for the reasoned opinion of the Imperial General Staff upon the effect on the defence of India of the alignment via Kerman of an international railway across Persia, with special reference to the con siderations urged in the Memorandum of the Chief of the General Staff in India, dated 6th June 1913. 2. Before dealing with the precise reference made it may be pointed out that any discussion on this subject seems to be now of a somewhat academic nature seeing that the British and Russian Governments have agreed to a joint application to the Persian Government for an option for this railway on the understanding that when it reaches the Russian frontier of the neutral sphere a “ Russo-British Technical Commission ” shall be appointed to examine the two routes (viz., that via Shiraz and that via Kerman) and report to their respective Governments before an}?- decision is taken as to the continuation of the line through the neutral sphere. Since Russian commercial and strategical aims are clearly directed on an alignment via Kerman, and it is improbable that engineering difficulties on that alignment will be greater than on the alternative Shiraz route—it would appear self-evident that the Russians, with a free hand as far as Vezd in their own sphere, will so align and construct the railway within that sphere as to leave no room for discussion as to the route to be followed southwards. 3. The main points referred to the Imperial General Staff by the India Office may be summarised as— Firstly, the effect on the defence of India of an alignment of the Trans- Persian Railway via Kerman ; and Secondly, whether any, and if so what, increase to the Army in India is rendered necessary by such an alignment. S. 231. A 2 .4 4 The question of a railway from the Russian frontier Tehran aligned via Kerman may be treated from two main standpoints, viz . (a) that of a railway passing through Kerman ; and (b) that of a railway ending at Kerman. 5 As regards such a railway passing through Kerman, whether to link up with the ^Indian railway system at Nushki or Karachi, the Chief of tie Imperial General Staff is in complete agreement with the opinion against such a proposal expressed by the Chief of the General aaft m India. He is also opposed, for strategical reasons, to any proposal to permit such a radw'ay direct ^access to the L at a port east of the neighbourhood of Tinnrlnr Abbas. 6. Regarding a railway reaching but not passing east of Kerman or southwards to the sea east of the neighbourhood of Bundar Abbas, the Bine of the Imperial General Staff holds that the position is different and that no cogent military objection can be urged to the construction of such a me subject to certain essential provisos. . p . „ „ . £ . He is led to this conclusion by a consideration of the following factors. Kerman is some 350 miles from the Helmund m feistan and some GOO miles from Nushki. ,. „ •-&gt; Granting a possible rate of Russian railway construction of one mile per day—a liberal estimate, and one making every allowance for Russian potentialities -a Russian prolongation of the railway beyond Kerman would take approximately one year to reach the Helmund in bistan, or I years to reach Nushki. . . , . , The Chief of the Imperial General Staff is convinced that no war present day between two leading European Powers—whether the primary- theatre of operations is on the North-West Frontier of India or elsewhere- can be localised. Modern economic conditions and political considerations forbid such a possibility, and, in his opinion, render it certain that the pressure on India would be relieved and a decision be reached m hurope within a year of the outbreak of war. . T r He holds therefore that Russia could not develop strength against India 'from an independent railhead pushed forward on the outbreak of war from Kerman in time to be of use to her in a general advance upon India, kbit this oninion, based on the existing situation, is subject to the following 2/3rd at the essential provisos:— (а) that for strategical reasons it be recognised and acted on as a cardinal point of British policy that any extension by the Russians of the railway eastwards from Kerman or southwards to the sea east of the neighbourhood of Rundar Abbas, without express British concurrence, be treated as a casus belli ; and ^ (б) that before the railway from Tehran reaches Kerman, a British controlled railway shall have reached Kerman already from a port, similarlv controlled, in the neighb&lt; urhood of Bundar Abbas, and thus form the sole through continuation from Kerman to the sea. This has been urged for commercial reasons, is necessary from considerations of British prestige, and is advisable for strategical reasons. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff therefore thinks that should diplomacy fail to gain Russian acceptance of the more westerly alignment from Tehran vid Yezd and Saidabad to the neighbourhood of Bundar Abbas which from the strategical point of view is regarded as the one least objectionable, the Kerman alignment may be agreed to in so far as military considerations are concerned, subject to the express conditions referred to above. 7. Regarding the question of whether any, and if so, what, increase to the Army in India would be rendered necessary by the construction of a railway from the Russian .frontier vid Tehran to or beyond Kerman, the essential principle to be observed appears to be that the Army in India should be strong enough to delay any hostile advance sufficiently long to1 * enable the diplomatic economic and military resources of the Empire to be WelsewheTa “ ° 6r t0 rebeVe ^ P ressure ^ia and decide the The Chief of the Imperial General Staff thinks that no addition to the present field Army of nine divisions and eight cavalry brigades in India would be required so long as the conditions referred to in the preceding paragraph are observed, and provided these divisions and cavalry brigade! are fully organised, their training and equipment in all respects maintained at a high standard of excellence, and the state of peace preparation in India such as to ensure rapid mobilisation, concentration and the ready execution of the necessary plans of campaign. ^ 8 But should any extensions of the Tehran-Kerman Railway east of a north and south line through Iverman he forced upon us, he is of opinion that pro tanto an increase in the strength of the Army in India (as defined ui! 6 U ! d be ^ ce 1 ssa] A- Fo , r SUcil extensions would, by providing Russia with a third or (if the Alexandrov Gai-Oharjui project matures, and a line be constructed southwards through Khorasan) possibly a fourth— independent line of railway approach to the Indian frontier, render the defence of that frontiei a matter of such difficulty as to tax the military resources of the ifmpire to the utmost, owing to^ the enormous superiority of numbers which Russia would then be in a position to keep in the field. In this connection it must be borne in mind that even two vears would not suffice to produce an increase of any military value, i.e., one of all arms with British and ^ Indian troops in due proportion. Consequently any augmentation decided on would have to be made from three to five years in advance of such extensions. General Staff, War Office. November 1913.■ pwp/ ———4 ^ / r L y ( i, . i) k |t'f i'^A. !U4&lt;y- W -f H -' l f ^ - &lt;4 4^ s a (O cy army in India would be necessary, and that the increase would be greater the further east the point of debouchment. Lord Crewe considers that the revenues of India would be unable to bear the increased expenditure. I am to refer to my letter of the 22nd July, 1913, No. 2918, and to recommend that^the question should be^-submitted for final discussion to the Committee of Imperial Defence. Accepting the conclusion ****** Ghief of tSw General Imperial Staff, Lord Crewe is of opinion that unless His Majesty's Government are prepared to relieve India of a responsibility that is beyond her re sources, trey would for this reason alone not be justified in accepting a terminus E. of Bundar Aboas. Lord Crewe is aware that on considering the Re port of the Interdepartmental Committee of the 29th May, 19.ub, Sir Edward Grey came to the conclusion the.t until the technical Commission had examined the ground it was not, necessary to consider the Russian alignment. The Russian alignment had Chahbar as its objective, whereas the Interdepartmental Committee, in accordance with the recommendation of the Committee of Imperial Defence^ruled out oi discussion any port East of Bundar Abbas. Lord Crewe appreciates trie considerations which favour post-ponement of a final decision on the alignment of the rail way until ohe Commission have reported, and he understands tiia.t Sir hdr/ard drey is satisfied that the reservations to be communicated by Sir George Buchanan to the Russian Govern ment leave Kis Majesty's Government sufficient liberty of ac tion at one proper time. But he is afraid that if the sur vey is allowed to proceed, and if the Commission should even- yf/ tually re com lend the Kerman-ChoMar alignment as the only one imancially and comercially possible, it will be very diffi cult lor His Majesty's Government to resist it. Lord Crewe would, therefore, ask Sir Edward Grey to consider whether the despatch which Sir George Buchanan * C0: ^ nicate ^ the Russian Minister for Porei^ Affairs hould not soate that his Majesty’s Government would be un able in any case to entertain the idea of an alignment de bouching to the east of Bundar Abbas. It is suggested that to Para. 11 of the draft a sentence might be added somewhat to this effect: examination of possible alignments'sS they have already made from these points of view has led the to the conclusion that an alignment terminating at a pojt ea of Bundar Abbas would be opposed to their interests.” (sd) T.W.EIn reply please quote Ho.0164/2882 (K.0.1.) &lt;0 16546f ; War Office, 1913 J s - E CHE T. Whitehall, S.W. 22nd November, 1913. K The Secretary, War Office, presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for India, and begs to be furnished with a copy of each of the marginally 1 ‘ thP°Tnrti^ ? y the , C cl e L of | noted documents referred to in India ^ tne Indian General Staff ) dated 5th September, 1912. )Office Secret letter No.P.2716 dated 2. Memorandiun on projected ^ railway construction in Russian Central Asia, 1913 ) to complete V/ar Office records. H9th July, 1913. They are requiredThe Under Secretary of State for India. From s 'I The Secretary, War Office. -4 s 1 lemo, by Chief of the General Staff, India, dated 5th Sept. 1912. ^emo. on projected Hailway construc tion in Russian Central Asia 1913. Sir, 18th November,1913, I am commanded by the Army Council to forward herewith in reply to India Office letter No. P.2716 of 19th July last, a Memorandum containing the considered opinion of the Chief of the Imperial General Staff upon the effect on the defence of India Oo. the alignment via Kerman of an international railway across Persia with special reference to the considera tions urged in the Memorandum of the Chief of the General Staff, India, dated the 6th June last. I am also to return enclosures* Nos. 1 and 4 to the above quoted letter, as requested therein. I am further to regret the delay which has unavoidably occurred in replying to the India Office letter. s J * W . ' ' stv p- aV wt- ... J ' (V- - ” I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, ) t// 3. ^ , i ^ ISECRET. 7 Effect on the defence of India of an alignment via Kerman of the Trans-Persian Railway. 1. The India Office as?£ for the reasoned opinion of the Imperial General Staff upon the effect on the defence of India of the alignment via Kerman of an international railway across Persia, with special reference to the considerations urged in the Memorandum of the Chief of the General Staff in India, dated 6th June, 1913. 2. Before dealing with the precise reference made it may he pointed out that any discussion on this . | subject seems to be now of a somewhat academic nature s-eeihg that the British and Russian Governments have agreed to a Joint application to the Persian Government for an option for this railway on the understanding that when it reaches the Russian frontier o f the neutral sphere a w Russc-British Technical Commission 0 shall be appointed to examine the two routes (viz., that via Shiraz and that via Kerman) and report to their respective Governments before any decision is taken as to the continuation of the line through the neutral sphere. Since Russian commercial and strategical aims are clearly directed on an alignment via Kerman - and it is improbable that engineering difficulties on that alignment will be greater than on the alternative Shiraz route - it would appear self evident that the Russians, with a free hand as far as Yezd in their own sphere, will so align and construct the railway within that sphere as to leave no room for discussion as to the route to be followed southwards. ji ]I ^ 3. The mam points referred to the Imperial General Staff 'by the India Office may 'be summarised as:- Firstly, the effect on the defence of India of an and^ 111611 ^ 01 ^ rans '^ ers ^ an R&amp;ilway via Kerman; S^condl^r,whether any, and if so what, increase to the Array in India is rendered necessary by such an alignment. 4. The question of a Railway from the Russian frontier Tehran aligned via Kerman may be treated from two main standpoints viz.;- (a) that of a railway passing through Kerman; and (b) that of a railway ending at Kerman. 5. As regards such a railway passing through Kerman, whether to link up with the Indian railway system at Nushki or Karachi, the Chief of the Imperial General Staff is in complete agreement with the opinion against such a proposal expressed by the Chief of the General Staff in India. He is also opposed for strategical reasons to any proposal to permit such a railway direct access to the sea at a port east of the neighbourhood of Bandar Abbas. 6. Regarding a railway reaching, but not passing east of Kerman or southwards to the sea east of the neighbourhood of Bandar Abbas, the Chief of the Imperial General Staff holds that the position is different, and that no cogent military objection can be urged to the construction of such a line subject to certain essential provisos . He is led to this conclusion by a consideration of the following factors. Kerman is some 350 miles from the Helmund in Sistan and some 600 miles from ITushki. Granting fi,construction of one mile per day - a literal estimate and one making every allowance for Russian potentialities - a Russian prolongation of the railway heyond Kerman would take approximately one year to reach the Helmund in Sistan, or 1 2/3rd years to reach Nushki. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff is convinced that no war at the present day between two leading European Powers - whether the primary theatre of operations is on the North West Frontier of India or elsewhere - can be localised. Modern economic conditions and political considerations forbid such a possibility, and, in his opinion, render it certain that the pressure on India would be relieved and a decision be reached in Europe within a year of the outbreak of war. He holds therefore that Russia could not develop strength against India from an independent railhead pushed forward on the outbreak of war from Kerman in time to be of use to her in a general advance upon India. But this opinion, based on the existing situation, is subject to the following essential provisos:- that for strategical reasons it be recognised and acted on as a cardinal point of British policy that any extension by the Russians of the railway eastwards from Kerman or southwards to the sea east of the neighbourhood of Bandar Abbas, without express British concurrence, be treated as a 'casus belli”; and (b) that before the railway from Tehran reaches Kerman, a British controlled, railway shall have reached Kerman already from a port, similarly controlled, in the neighbourhood of Bandar Abbas, and thus form the sole through continuation from Kerman to the sea. This has been urged for commercial reasons, is necessary from considerations of British prestige, and is advisable for strategical reasons.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff therefore thinks that should diplomacy fail to gain Russian acceptance of the more westerly alignment from Tehran via Yezd and Saidahad to the neighbourhood of Bandar Abbas, which from the strategical point of view is regarded as the one least objectionable, the Kerman alignment may be agreed to in so far as military considerations are concerned, subject to the express conditions referred to above. 7. Regarding the question of whether any, and if so what, increase to the Army in India would be rendered lecessary by the construction of a railway from the Russian frontier via Tehran to or beyond Kerman, the essential principle to be observed appears to be that the Army in India! should be strong enough to delay any hostile advance sufficiently long to enable the diplomatic, economic and military resources of the Umpire to be brought to bear in order to relieve the pressure on India and decide the issue elsewhere. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff thinks that no addition to the present Field Army of 9 Divisions and 8 Cavalry Brigades in India would be required so long as the conditions referred to in the preceding paragraph are observed, and provided these divisions and cavalry brigades are fully organized, their training and equipment in all respects maintained at a high standard of excellence, and the state of peace preparation in India such as to ensure rapid mobilization, concentration and the ready execution of the necessary plans of campaign. 8. But should any extensions of the Tehran-Kerman Railway east of a North and South line through Kerman oe forcedforced upon us, he is of opinion that pro tanto an increase in the strength of the Army in India (as defined above) would be necessary. For such extensions would, by providing Russia with a third - or (if the Alexandrov Gai-Charjui project matures, and a line be constructed southwards through Khorasan) possibly a fourth - independent line of railway approach to the Indian frontier, render the defence of that frontier a matter of such difficulty as to tax the military resources of the Empire to the utmost, owing to the enormous superiority of numbers which Russia would then be in a position to keep in the field. In this connection it must be borne in mind that even two years would not suffice to produce an increase of any military value, i.e., one of all arms with British and Indian troops in due proportion. Consequently any augmentation decided on would have to be made from three to five years in advance of such extensions. General Staff, War Office. Hovember, 1913.! In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. 50005/13. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Foreign Office 26th. November, 1915. Immediate. Confidential. A) I l . _r v ' r Sir ■,y. V. secretary Sir E. G-rey has had under careful considera- K 'j | ^ e '^ er of the 3rd. instant resoectinp' the Trans-hersian hallway project, I dni now directed to transmit to you the accompanying drait 01 a despatch which, subject to the concurrence of the V 'y/ m Secretary of State for India, Sir 2 . Grey proposes to ad- dress to His Majesty's Charge d'Affaires at St. Petersburg}!; end. i am go furnish the following explanations for the in formation of the barquess of Crewe:- Point 1. The reasons for deprecating the formal association of the French Legation at Tehran with the of ficial request to be made by the British and Pussian Lega tions to the Persian Government for an option are explained m 1116 Under Secretary of State, India Office. Ot Y TO INDIA 't /k,tu M2/7 (50005/15). in n.o dralt; but the French Ambassador has lately made a fresh propooal, as described in the enclosed communication, - nc 0-rey is disposed to-concur in this procedure. Fo.urw n. Sir S. G-rey does not consider that Lord Lansdowne* s declaration of Lay 1905 v/ould cover a refusal on the part oi Kis Majesty’s Grovernment to assent to the con- cession of a port to an international railway company, as hkit declaration is expressly directed against the establish ment of a 'naval base', or a 'fortified port'. He considers that a more appropriate reference in regard to the attitude to be assumed would be to his despatch of the 29th. August, 19''/, to air A. hicolson, then His Majesty’s Ambassador at * bt. Petersburg}], - ; document which was presented to Parlia ment with the Anglo-Russian Agreement. Sir E. Grey con siders that, subject to the limitations stated in the draft, it would be difficult for His Majesty's-Government to refuse to agree to an application to the Persian Government for all reasonable facilities at the maritime terminus. Point 3. This section appears to correspond with the views of the Marquess of Crewe except as regards the agency through whom the survey is to be made. Sir E. Grey is not satisfied(50005/13). se.tisfied tnat Ills Majesty’s Grovernment could be certein that the British members of a survey party organised by the Society d’litudes would in fact represent the views of His Majesty’s G-oveminent and for this reason he would prefer a Government survey or As the main objec best alignment for rea does not consider that commission of investigation’’• t of the survey is to decide on the ching the 'ersian Gulf, Sir E&gt; Grey His h.iayesty’s Government could reasonably object to the survey going beyond Kerman* 1 am to state that Sir E* Grey concurs in the proposals of the Government of India in their telegram of the 16th* October tnat there should be a Russian escort in the north and a British one in the south. In conclusion, I am to express the hope that an early reply map- be sent to this letter, and if possible without the delay which would be involved in a further reference to the Government of India* I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,&gt; Registry No. 50005/13 Draft. Mr. (VBeirne. No. k- ^ c\ * (■ rsA4-* 2 £ 7L&lt;rv- - . 1 i ^ ri** i &gt;-’‘ F. 0., November ,/?a3 &gt; On the 27th September last the ■Russian Charge d’Affaires communicated a note explaining the attitude of his Government on three points respecting the % Trans-Persian Pailway project, and at the same time invited an expression of the views of His Majesty's Government. The attitude of the Pussian Govern ment on the three points in question was as follows:- 1. They would agree that the re quest to be made to the Persian Govern ment for an option should be presented by the British and Pussian Legations at Tehran instead of by the Boci^te d'Etudes itself, but they would prefer that the French Legation should join in the re quest. 2. They considered that the Pus sian and French groups were justified in wishing*' wishing to include in the application to the Persian Government a request that free access to ports should be fully guaranteed to the railway company. 3, 'They concurred in the wish of the Societe d'Etudes that a representative of the French Government should be included in the commission of investigation in the south, and, if such an arrangement should prove impracticable, the Pussian Government con sidered that the Pussian and French delegates on the commission might be representatives of the Societe d’Etudes who, in such a con tingency, would meet the expenditure invol ved. J N His Majesty*s Government have, in con sultation with the Government of India,Persian Government for an option. Other Pov/ers are quite willing to admit and to recognise the special and dominant interests of Great Britain and Bussia in Persia, where it is natural and reasonable that those two Powers should be concerned in such a re quest. But if a third Power were to be ostensibly and officially associated with Great Britain and Bussia, it would be dif ficult to resist claims of other countries to be placed on a footing similar to that of France. For this reason His Majesty's Government would deprecate the co-operation of the French Government in the step in question; and they are assured by His Majesty's Minister at Tehran that such co operation would not, in his opinion, be of substantial assistance in securing the option. The French Government have, however, recently communicated and recommended a proposal of the Societe d*Etudes for an alternative procedure, according to which an identicidentic request for an option would te made by the British and Russian Legations, to be followed by a separate representation of the French Legation which, basing its action on one fact that the Societe d 1 Etudes is a French company, would recommend it to the Persian Government. ■ Provided the action of the French Lega tion is, so far as possible, treated as confidential and not made the subject of outside comment. His Majesty’s Government recognise that the procedure now proposed would not be liable to the same objections. 2. His Majesty's Government would strongly deprecate any attempt to obtain frorr the Persian Government an assurance, as originally proposed by the Soci^te d'Etudes, that without a previous understanding with that body no concession for ports would be ■■'N (Ff prejudice the position and prospects of the Persian Pailways Syndicate, which His Majesty’s Government are, and indeed were even before the constitution of the Society d’Etudes pledged in some measure to support. Such being the case. His Majesty's Govern ment remain of the opinion that some arrange- |ment for -the fusion of interests or at least for co-operation between the Society d'Etudes |and the Persian Railways Syndicate will eventually prove essential. But apart altogether from this im portant consideration, I feel confident that the Russian Government, in the light of my despatch of the 29th August, 1907 to Sir A. Nicolson, will entirely appreciate that, for political reasons. His Majesty's Government could not acquiesce in, and still less support the application for, any concession of a port to an international railway company. Subject, however, to tie reservation of conditions of control and the location of the port, and to such re-inote of application. His Majesty's Govern ment would agree to an application to the Persian Government for all reasonable |facilities at such maritime terminus as may ■eventually be selected. Cfi 3. His Majesty's Government, being closely concerned in the investigation to be undertaken in the south hold that the Commission should be composed of represen tatives of the Governments; they would agree to French participation in the Com mission, but, for reasons similar to those explained above under (l), they consider such participation should be as informal and unobtrusive as possible. /0\ The first alignment to be examined should, in their opinion, be that from Ispahan to Shiraz and Bunder Abbas. // t In agreeing to the project of a com mission of investigation in the south, to examine the possible alignments. His Majesty's Government must make their assent subject to an express condition that they will not thereby be committed to accept-Ti 4 % 5 T tne finding of the Commission without further examination of its military and political results. They also reserve complete freedom of action respecting all other points enumerat- ed in section (a) of the enclosure in my despatch No. 64 of the 5th February, 1913, to Sir G. Buchanan. A cop^ of this section is enclosed for facility of reference. /ii, His Majesty’s Government would be glad to attach a British representative to the survey party which is to examine the ques tion of alignment for the northern section of the proposed railway, and, as Russian \ representatives will be attached to the commission in the south, I trust the Russian - overnment will accede to this proposal. /&gt;y. You should communicate a copy of this despatch to the Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs.Enclosure. (a) ills Majesty's Government have al.. eady expressed themselves prepared to assent In principle to the project of a Trans-Persian railway: that assent is made subject to the following, among other, conditions:- That no part of the line or its con nections shall be constructed outside the Russian sphere until, and in such measures as His Majesty’s Government shall consider jit politic and feasible; that the main line must pass through Ispahan by Shiraz, and if it, or any branch, is continued to the British sphere, it must reach that sphere at Bunder Abbas; that His Majesty’s Government do not think that the time has yet come for a connection between Bunder Abbas and Karachi to be made, and as there must be no question of making it until His Majesty's | Government consider that the time has come j when it is desirable, the question of branch i | and local lines should be considered on f | their merits, and their commercial advantages shoulds Should not be sacrificed to the project of jthrough connection; that His Majesty's Government undertake no financial guarantee in regard to the project; that the point mem the line touches the Persian Gulf shall be referred to His Majesty's Government when the surveys have been completed, and the arrangements for the maritime terminus, land for its control, shall be submitted to their approval; that the question of the gauge outside the Russian sphere shall be submitted to His Majesty’s Government; that effective means must be provided, to the satisfaction of His Majesty's Government to secure British trade against differential treatment of any kind, direct or indirect, on any railway constructed under a conces sion obtained by the Soci£te d*Etudes; that British control must predominate in the Southern or Gulf Section of any Trans-Per sian line, or of the branches, which may be made, and that this control shall not be in validated by any arrangement which may be I .- 'JLZT- RUSSIA. No. 1 (1907). « ^ Vv CONVENTION SIGNED ON AUGUST 31, 1907, BETWEEN GREAT BRITAIN AND RUSSIA, CONTAINING ARRANGEMENTS ON THE SUBJECT OE PERSIA, AFGHANISTAN, AND THIBET. Presented to both Houses of Parliament by Command of His Majesty. September 1907. L O N D 0 N : PRINTED FOR HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE, BY HARRISON AND SONS, ST. MARTIN’S LANE, PRINTERS IN ORDINARY TO HIS MAJESTY. v i 1i \ qi 1 Q 07 between Great Britain A Convention signed on August di, ' tlv ^ , . ^ and Russia, containing Arrangements on the suliject of Persia, Afghanistan, and Thibet. No. i. Sir Edward Grey to Sir A. Nicolson. Foreign Office, August 29, 1907. Sir ’ T ttavF to rlav authorized your Excellency by telegraph to sign a Convention with the A Ru S ‘L GO—nt containing Arrangements on the subject of Pers.a, ^ia regies of that country therefore been considered . a PP^°P^ possessed by Great Britain in the Gulf, the BritSrS Ko» -urn fcrmor. ‘Jg »al „ gi,, „« s“a‘ss asrsSss tz »= make further discussion affecti g noo-otiations leading up to the conclusion Russian Government have m he course of he neg^ ^ eoia l int erests of of this Arrangement explicitly stated t^t ^ ^ d I Majesty’s Government Great Britain in the Persian Gulf—a statement or which j j ^hfito mateR quite clear that the present Arrangement is not intended to rv i •, • ’ +&gt;,oPnlfand does not imply any change of policy respecting it affect the position m the Gu , Government think it desirable to draw on the part of Great Bntam His Ma esty govern ^ reaffiml aUy previous ':.r .;rg.iSS A ..a a» them. Government will continue to direct all their efforts to the preserva tion rfthe It Jus quo in the Gulf and the maintenance of British trade, in doing so, they have no desire to exclude the legitimate trade of any other 1 ower. ^ (Signed) E. GREY. Sir No. 2. Sir A. Nicolson to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 3.) St. Petersburgh, August 31, 1907. ' I HAVE the honour to transmit herewith the Convention which was si^ed to-day by M. Isvolsky and myself for the settlement of certain questions affecting the interest ° f ^ab^be’g leaved forward a note which I received from M. I svol *y ln T to a communication from me, of which a copy is herewith inclosed, on the subject of the entry of scientific missions into Thibet. T Vl Q TTO fST C* (Signed) ‘ ' A. NICOLSON.,1 His Majesty^heEttperor irfllfthe R™sf a S s S - d ° r Extraordinar y aild Plenipotentiarj. to Iswokky^Imis^r^fW^^relgii AffiRrs R ' SSiaS ’ MaSter of his Court Alexander ^ form, have agreed on the folio win” 0ll '' r tEeir Jud P owers . found in good and due Arrangement co?icerning Persia. the integrify amfTndepejfoemje^f^Pe ^ havi f g mutaall y en g a g ed order throughout that comltr^ P ’ ?? j mC f ely desiring the P^servatioA of establishment of equal advantages (,,1 l, l&lt; ' a ';' e ' d development, as well as the permanent Oonsiderine that eaJh S^ l l ? de and mdu . str y of aI1 other nations ; special interest in the maiute eTtl as ’ ^ or geographical and economic reasons, a aLilr n th nXVtomr e /^ P :f C V nd ° rder in certa “ Provinces of Persia fritiers if Afohanfstan T b e. P h ,° n 0f ’ ‘ he RuSSlan frontie r on *he one hand, and the avoiding all tuse ofconflfot hP T ^ the 0ther hand = aIld being desirous of Provinces of Persia * ^ een leir res P ec f lve interests in the above-mentioned Have agreed on the following terms :— si I. RrufI, 1 ™ u • Rl f ain . en ^ a § es n °t to seek for herself, and not to support in favour of Br tish subjects, or m favour of the subjects of third Powers, any Concess ons of a political or commercial nature-such as Concessions for railways 7 banks teWranhs tWigh Isfahan’ YeTd ra Kakhk C ' _ d ey °H- 3 liDe Sta - tillS fr ° m Kasr-i-Shilin, passing intersfction ofllmR,’, 1 k ’ T d A &amp;t a p0mt on the Persian frontier at thi • “i ;, 01 , oJ the Russian and Afghan frontiers, and not to oppose directlv or ndirectly demands for similar Concessions in this region which are supported bv the faZrefor^fo'b P U iS t T derSt00d that the above-mentioned placZareTnlded t! e regIon 111 Mdl ich Great Britain engages not to seek the Concessions referred to. IL Russia, on her part, engages not to seek for herself, and not to support in favour of Russian subjects, or in favour of the subjects of third Powers, any Concessions of a political or commercial nature—such as Concessions for railways, banks telegraphs of a Cafok an R SP ° rt ’q 1 T ranUe ’ &amp;C T be J. 0nd a line goi “g from Afghan frontier by way nT , • j . German, and ending at Bunder Abbas, and not to oppose, directlv tbeRV^V’ demauds lor similar Concessions in this region which are supported by in th B e rZ G ? verI ? me 1 nt - 1118 understood that the above-mentioned places ar e P included m the region 111 which Russia engages not to seek the Concessions referred to id the itual 3 oh rred' id able 111 . Russia, on her part, engages not to oppose, without previous arrangement with Ureat Britain, the grant of any Concessions whatever to British subjects in the regions 01 Bersia situated between the lines mentioned in Articles I and II. Great Britain undertakes a similar engagement as regards the grant of Concessions to itussian subjects m the same regions of Persia. . Concessions existing at present in the regions indicated in Articles I and H are maintained. IV. It is understood that the revenues of all the Persian customs, with the exception ot those of Farsistan and of the Persian Gulf, revenues guaranteeing the amortization and the interest of the loans concluded by the Government of the Shah with the “ Banque d Escompte et des Prets de Perse ” up to the date of the signature of the present Arrangement, shall be devoted to the same purpose as in the past. It is equally understood that the revenues of the Persian customs of Farsistan and of the Persian Gulf, as well as those of the fisheries on the Persian shore of the8 Caspian Sea and those of the 1 ' oste ^ n ^ ’with the Imperial ^an^of'^ereia^p^to^he^late 1 of^the^ signature of the present Arrangement. V. &lt; . • • • in iItp amortization or the payment of the In the event of irregularities occ ^“ ^ ^ p Banqne d’Escompte et des Frets interest of the Persian loans U p to the date of ' he si g natlire ° f de Perse ” and with the Impen nt of t p e necessity arising for Russia to the present Arrangement, and guaranteeing the regular service of the establish control over the sources o ^ s i tuat ed in the region mentioned in loans concluded with the first-nam ’ r Great Britain to establish control oyer Article II of the present Anang ’ reonlar service of the loans concluded with the sources of revenue guaranteeing the re^ in Artic i e I 0 f the the second-named bank, ^ situated present Arrangement, the British and Russ an Uoven . in agreement with hand into a friendly exchange of ^ al i interference which Atrwt “x;:s;is s p'»’S ^»- «-«—■ Convention concerning Afghanistan. ssz raswua peace, liave concluded the following Convention ARTICLE I. His Britannic Majesty’s Government declare that they have no intention of changng^he political status ^ e t0 exercise their influence in Afghani “in a pacific sense, and they will not themselves take, nor encourage A+Vhanistan to take, anv measures threatening Russia. • . &lt;» -i • , ^ The Russian Government, on their part, declare that they recognize Afghanis an s outside the sphere of Russian influence, and they engage that all their political relations with Afghanistan shall he conducted through the intermediary of His Bntann c Majesty’s Government ; they further engage not to send any Agents into Afghanistan. ARTICLE II. The Government of His Britannic Majesty having declared in the Treaty signed at Kabul on the 21st March, 1905, that they recognize the Agreement and the engage ments concluded with the late Ameer Abdur Rahman, and that they have no intention of interfering in the internal government of Afghan territory, brreat Britain engages neither to annex nor to occupy m contravention of that treaty any portion of Afghanistan or to interfere in the internal administration of the country, provided that the Ameer fulfils the engagements already contracted by him towards His Britannic Majesty’s Government under the above-mentioned Treaty. ARTICLE III. The Russian and Afghan authorities, specially designated for the purpose on the frontier or in the frontier provinces, may establish direct relations with each other tor the settlement of local questions of a non-political character. ARTICLE IV. His Britannic Majesty’s Government and the Russian Government affirm their adherence to the principle of equality of commercial opportunity in Afghanistan, and» Docmnent is. the Prona-tr of ffis Majesty's GrgyfirHjy&gt;A»i ] * 5 J r %j I ^ 1 PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAJ. ! r'‘ i o [September 8.J Section 2. [40084] No. 1. r L r Foreign Office to Director of Military Operations. IfH the ^Hary^perEtnTand isT'^ A , ff f rs P reseuts Ms compliments to Sis syrr ‘' e s~‘±t the v^ws^SMaiVstVsCn!' 6 ’ ^ ;' eply { ^ the ““i' P° in ‘ &lt;&gt;i difference between cobernTL the diS y * Government and those of the Russian Government is that G tWfe 8 “ e 5“ lectl0n which the southern portion of the line is to follow and that it refers. ^ qUeStl0n that tlle most important part of the Russian memorandum now pufwanr e andThe°R ^ however ,aware that His Majesty’s Government have put lonvaia, and tne Russian Government have accented n -nm-nnaol +n appointment of an Anglo-Russian Commission which should examine^o/the spot the rraTS*r ts - and vevoi i to the l tw ° onaeirStiv: ^ + 1 , ’ d 1 b F \ Gl ^ y . 1 . s r 111 consu Eation with the Secretary of State for India as to the composition of the British membership of this Commission. nrespr t tntl 01 ’ 6 b + ecome / + ; inneces s^T and, indeed, impossible to return any answer at piesent to the portion of the memorandum which concerns this question Soci^%ErT rand , mn m f r her insists 1 t] ? at each 0f the three constituting the Societe d Etudes should have an equal share of control over the southern portion of me, ms excluding the claim of His Majesty’s Government for the assignment of a pieponderating share m favour of the British group. As regards this point, there is reason to believe that the Russian group at any rate, have modified their view as to this requirement, and it is reasonable to infer that they have done so with the knowledge and approval of the Russian Government, e this as it may, a further meeting of the Societe has been arranged and will take place at Paris within the next few days, at which it is anticipated that this question will be discussed, and it would be useless to attempt any reply to this Dart ° ^ b ^,P lemoran&lt; ^ 1Im ’ EH the result of the discussion is known. -the part of the memorandum which concerns the enterprises of the Persian Railways Syndicate must also be submitted to further consideration, and it annears preferable, m any case, not to answer it alone. u -^icoEcm is to add that General Wilson will be informed as soon as it is decided to reply to the memorandum. Foreign Office, September 8, 1913. [1870 A—2][This Document is the Property of His Britannia Majesty’s Government.] [A] PERSIA. [February 4.J CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. [54973/12] No. 1. Foreign Office to Sir W. B. Oarstin. the Trans-Persian Raihvay project. 20th I)ecember 011 tlle object of ^ SeSTbTeS submission of the survey you wore to fnmicU • +• , co, ; luul etc non p^namg C 11 ^ to ’ concCTtbhth Tre'nch S ,^z zzzz/1 ates further ’ you p:-;— - primarily to facilitating railway construction in Northern Persia only. opeiation leading (c.) In the event of His Majesty’s Government being already committed to siimiort other tL^Z S o“Zce 0 s°“ n3 1D 11,6 Brlt,Sl ‘ a,ld neUtral Sphere8 ’ 16 WOuld seem essential ‘° lea ™ (d.) In view of the possible advancement of conflicting projects for railway service in the p,rit ; «ih and neutral spheres the British group would be glad to learn whether His Majesty’s Government have Persiaif territory 3,8 ^ a S ° lutl0n ° f the Sltuatl0n whic h may arise from rival claims in this portion of ^ 1 am „ now ^^ rectec ^ Secretary Sir E. Grey to make the following observations on each of tliese points :—• (a.) His ^ Majesty’s Government have already expressed themselves prepared to assent m principle to the project of a Trans-Persian railway: that assent is made subject to the following, among other, conditions :— That no part of the line or its connections shall be constructed outside the Hussian sphere until, and in such measures as, His Majesty’s Government shall consider it politic and feasible ; that the main line must pass through Ispahan by Shiraz, and if it, or any branch, is continued to the British sphere, it must reach that sphere at Bunder Abbas ; that His Majesty’s Government do not think that the time has yet come for a connection between Bunder Abbas and Karachi to be made, and as there must be no question of making it until His Majesty’s Government consider that the time has come when it is desirable, the question of branch and local lines should be considered on their merits, and their commercial advantages should not be sacrificed to the project of through connection ; that His Majesty’s Government undertake no financial guarantee in regard to the project ; that the point where the line touches the Persian Gulf shall be referred to His Majesty’s Government when the surveys have been completed, and the arrangements for the maritime terminus, and for its control, shall be submitted to their approval ; that the question of the gauge outside the Russian sphere shall be submitted to His Majesty’s Government; that effective means must be provided, to the satisfaction of His Majesty’s Government, to secure British trade against differential treatment of any kind, direct or indirect, on any railway constructed under a concession obtained by the Societe d’Etudes ; that British control must predominate in the Southern or Gulf section of any Trans-Persian line, or of the branches, which may be made, and that this control shall not be invalidated by an 7 arrangement which may be made in regard to the percentage of other (i.e., non- British) participation in the undertaking. (b.) His Majesty’s Government raise no objection, regarding it as very desirable on general grounds that the British group should co operate in the Societe d’Etudes, but they trust that such progress may be made in regard to a well-considered scheme [2804 d—l]2 of railway development in the south as will render possible an early, and if possible simultaneous start in construction from the 1 eisian (ju . , f , simu taneo Majesty - S Government are committed, and were so before he constitution of the Sdciete d’Etudes: that the concessions in question are the constitmioi in the British sphere (which would have to be purely Britfstctntrolled), and certain lines in the neutral sphere (other than the Mohammerah* Khorremmabad project) which, in view of the great predominance of British rade should “e preponderatingly British, though not without a substantial international -mrtioination both in construction and management. V Yd) His Majesty’s Government would be prepared to recommend to the parties interested in the projects (other than the Mohammerah-Khorremmabad line) m the neutral sphere that it would serve British interests if they would join with the British orouo of the Societe d’Etudes, who, in consultation with His Majesty s Government, might then arrange the degree and nature of the foreign participation m question. I am to express Sir E. Grey’s view that the arrangements for securing British control on certain portions of the line need not necessarily conflict with the principle of equal representation of British, Russian, and French interests in the undertaking from the northern frontier of Persia to the sea. In conclusion, I am to state that, subject to the acceptance of the conditions laid down His Majesty’s Government are willing to support your Societe m the negotiations 'proposed at Tehran; but that they would recommend the substitution ot the words “ d’un chemin de fer traversant la Perse du nord au sud par leheran for the words sur territoire persan, &amp;c„ &amp;c„ par Tdheran ” in the note which you propose to address to the Persian Government (see enclosure A in your letter ol the 20tb December). I am, &amp;c. LOUIS MALLET.rrom Viceroy, 30^ October 1913. of 4th October. Trans-Persian RaiLway'T 8eCret - Yo « ‘^gram presentation of P Note ^T^rs'ia^hiv™' 1011 p n,s , t ® r shmi W participate in importance to the argument hat We ^ not attach much French influence in Pe“o m,r fle f will tend to increase request would be difficult to justify ^ ” 6 3 reflIsaI to accef]e to the from Persian ^Ot^mmenTeu^aran tp^ to obtain an assurance which railway will eventinTlv hV contro1 of P ort or ports at claim to predominant shnrA i • nerearter, and to prejudice established position and interests in pLln Gulf‘justi^ ° r ^ M ° nr Sociltl flh^ethln o?T^cf C Tp t0 deC,ine t0 ac - de ^ request of to secure their representation Fre nch Government is reasonable. Acceptance of Fr 'repSatio/ however somewhat alters original character of Gomnnssion and in tT; ^“TnJXtcfv? ^ WOTld ^ Preferable to agre’e to Russian icinatne, and allow bociete to appoint Commiss on consisting of dele^ntes of three groups and to conduct enquiries at its own expense without dfS participation of three Governments. This would leave us a freer hand to object to an alignment unfavourable to us strategicallv or otherwise than if our Government were directly represented. We would urge however fha if this arrangement is decided on, steps should be taken to s^ure Ipnoint sympathv r w I ith 8 Tfd atlV? f a t gr0Up of a man acquainted and in y /a x Indian interests both commercial and strategical. adopted ^ e tV 0r0ngh - y a( l V0C i a i e th f whate 7 er method of'representation is bn? and no tn ^ qnir ^ should a PP^ ^ole alignment of Trans-Persian treatment of the K S t ? Uthern P^ion only. We see no reason for differential no, t on of th 6 northern section. In this connection please see concluding poition oi our telegram of 16th October.[Tins Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's GQ¥er nT ^ an ^ 3 [B] PERSIA. /la [September 22 ] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 15. [43384] No. 1. Mr. O’Beirne to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 22.) (No. 277. Secret.) Sir, St. Petersburgh, September 17, 1913. IN the Indian General Staff memorandum of the 6th June last on the subject of proposed railway ; and, on a review of these negotiations, the General Staff arrive at the conclusion that they afford evidence of inimical intentions on the part of Russia which cannot prudently be ignored. As the conclusion here arrived at differs funda mentally from the view of Russian policy held during the last few years by this embassy, in 1910, the plan at the Consortium was to build a railway across Persia connecting the Russian and Indian systems. Their main object was to secure the through traffic between Europe and India, and to anticipate in that respect the Bagdad Railway. As stated in the Consortium’s memorandum (print section 28970/10) the line’s “ importance- for transit was its very first consideration.” Therefore the Consortium proposed the alignment Yezd-Kerman-Nushki as being the shortest, and as touching the nearest point of the Anglo-Indian railway system. This alignment, it may be mentioned, was also favoured by Sir H. MacMahon. The length of rail to be laid from Yezd-Nushki was 810 miles, as compared with 1,341 miles Yezd-Bunder Abbas-Kurrachee. (Report of the Indian Interdepartmental Committee, print section 12,840/11, p. 17). The proposal, so far as the intentions of its promoters are concerned, finds the most complete justification in the words of the Interdepartmental Committee (ibid.) “ if the object of the proposed railway be taken as the connection of Russia with India by the quickest,, cheapest, and easiest route, this alignment seems to be preferable to either of the other two that have been suggested.” So much for the original Russian scheme, of which the most prominent supporters were men well known as ardent advocates of a closo understanding with Great Britain. In May 1911 His Majesty’s Government notified their assent_ m principle to the scheme of a through railway to India, but stipulated inter alia that it should be- brought down to the sea at Bunder Abbas, whence it would run to Ivuiracnee. 1 here upon the Consortium, supported by the Russian Government, proposed the alternative route Yezd—Herman—Chahbar ; and m the Russian preference for Chahbai overBundei Abbas, as the point at which the railway should touch the sea, the General Staff see strong grounds for suspicion. In reality the Russian promoters, reluctantly abandoning their original plan for the most direct alignment via Nushki, fell back on an alignment which, as regards directness, comes intermediate between the Nushki alignment and that via Bunder Abbas, and which, on the face of it, seems to possess strong com mercial advantages over the Bunder Abbas trace. Ihe new Russian scheme, in wine i the General Staff see. evidence of a strategical arriere-pensee, coincides as far as Bampur with that which had been advocated by His Majesty’s Consul-General at Lushire , 10 m Ttarvi-rvin. + 1-10 T?nacGn« T'nwnnsfid to deflect the line southwards to the sea at Giiaiibai in the Trans-Persian Railway scheme, it is stated that the General Staff’s military recom mendations must depend on their estimate of Russia’s present intentions towards the Indian Empire as revealed in the negotiations that have taken place concerning the I may perhaps be permitted to offer a few observations showing, as I think, that the attitude observed by Russia in the recent negotiations does not bear the construction placed upon it by the Indian military authorities. When the Trans-Persian railway scheme was revived by the Russian Consortium [1870 1 /—15] Copy to India 31 OCT 1913Societe M. Raffalovich, M. Goukassof, &amp;c., were certainly more concerned with the commercial aspects of the matter than with any political considerations, and it is exceedingly difficult to imagine that these gentlemen or other influential members ot the Russian group, such as M. Homiatof and M. Zvegintsef, toot their instructions from the Russian General Staff. The commercial reasons m favour of the Chahbar at£- againstthe Bunder Abbas truce (importance of the town of Kerman, nchness of the dfstrict, inferiority of Bunder Abbas as a port according to British sources of mfonnation, &amp;c.), are stated with obvious sincerity m a letter of the 7th March, 1913, from M Goukassof to Lord Errington, which was communicated by the group toll.Sazonof with the object evidently of enlisting his support. Finally the Chahbar truce com mended itself, presumably on commercial grounds, to the French group of the Societe d’Etudes, and was put forward by Sir E. Garstin on behalf of the British group (his letter to the Foreign Office of the 20th December, 1912, print o49 &lt; 3/12). So much for the two alignments proposed by the Russians. e now come to the statement in the Russian aide-memoire of the 14th May, 1913, to the effect that Russia will meet Great Britain’s wishes by refraining from railway construction near the Afghan frontier if Great Britain meets Russia’s wishes in regard to the Trans-1 ersian Railway. The General Staff regard this intimation as a highly significant threat. _ In order, however fairly to appreciate its significance it must be borne in mind that it is a reply to a direct request put forward by His Majesty’s Government in the embassy note of the 2nd (15th) May, 1911* In that note the British Government had_ signified their assent in principle (subject to certain stipulations) to a railway joining the Indian system at Kurrachee via Bunder Abbas, and, in return, they had asked that Russia should pledge herself not to entertain .... without coming to an undei standing with Great Britain any proposal for a line in the neighbourhood of the Perso-Aighan frontier within the Russian or neutral sphere.” But, in the meantime, His Majesty’s Government had appreciably changed their attitude. In the embassy aide-memoire of the 1st (14th) February, 1913,t a Foreign Office letter to Sir E. Garstin was communicated to the Russian Government in which it was said that “ His Majesty s Government do not think that the time has yet come for a connection between Bunder Abbas and Kurrachee to he made .... and the question of branch and local lines should be considered on their merits and their commercial advantages should not be sacrificed to the project of through connection.” The Russians considered, and not without reason, that the latest British communication meant the shelving for an indefinite period of the through connection project which was the very basis of the negotiations. Under the circum stances their reply to Great Britain’s request for a quid 'pro quo was as favourable as could possibly have been expected. They said that they would give the undertaking asked for when Great Britain met their wishes as regards the original scheme. So far indeed from being in the nature of an ominous threat this intimation constitutes a concession which may, in certain circumstances, be turned to valuable account. In short, the conduct of the negotiations from the Russian side may he summed np by saying that they sought throughout to secure through railway connection with India by the most direct route and under the most advantageous commercial conditions possible. It happens that the more direct the route the nearer it runs to the Afghan frontier. Bat that circumstance affords no better ground for ascribing political designs to the Russians than to the French or British groups of the Societe d’Etudes, and I venture to think that on a fuller consideration of the facts the India authorities will readify recognise that Russia must he acquitted of the unfriendly intentions which they attribute to her. I have, &amp;c. HUGH O’BEIRNE. * Embodying substance of Foreign Office despatch No. 129 of May 10, 1911. t » , „ ,, No. 64 of February 5, 1913.* ned i ate* In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. 46410/13. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. uir: - I ™ directed by becretary Sir E. Erev to state that tne French inibassador called on the 8th. instant and com municated a memorandum, of which a. copy is enclosed, regard ing certain points connected with the Trans-Persian railway project. As regards the French Legation at Tehran joining with the British and Russian Legations in presenting a request to the Persian Government for an option, bir A. Ni cols on in formed Monsieur Gambon crivately that he did not think His { Majesty’s Government would be disposed to agree to such a formal and public association of the three Legations: G-ermany was quite ready to admit and recognise the special and predominant interests of Great Britain and of Russia in Persia, but he felt sure that if a third Power were to be ostensibly end officially associated with Great Britain and Russia, e Under becretary of State, * *( 46410 / 13 ). (2*1) V. r.ubsid, Germany v/ouxg el so claim to be placed on a similar footing. oil A. i:icoxson t/iou lit, therefore, that the re- Q_u.es l SiiOUxc be presented by the F.ussian and British Legations alone. he added that the same observations applied also to the suggested French participation in the study of the alignment, monsieur Gambon seemed to admit the force of what Sir A. 1'licolson said as to French participation in the application to the Persian G-overnment, but His Excellency said that he did not quite see that similar objections should be raised as re gards £ French delegate on the survey commission, as French capital would be invested, and naturally the alignment of the railwa was of interest to those who 1 ere financially in- V terested. Sir A. HicoIson told Monsieur Gambon that of course the French Cfovernment’s memorandum would be studied, and that his own observations were merely personal. Sir E. Grey would be glad to receive the observations of the Secretary of State for India respecting these two points;( 46410 / 1 -). loiircj; and, as the British group of the SociStS d'htudes are being pressed by their foreign colleagues to address an ofiiciax letter to His Majesty's Government asking for con currence in, and official support of the above proposals, a step vhich the French and Russian groups would then adopt with reference to their respective Governments - it would xacilitate the ainal reply of the British group if they were sed at sxl 6srly data of the views of His Ms.lest'' 7 * s Gov~ eminent • In the meantime it is understood that the British group have addressed the letter, of which a copy is enclosed, to the President of the JocietS d'iitudes in Paris. As regards the port, mentioned in the French memorandum, I end terminal facilities generally in the south, Lord Errington and Sir ¥. Gerstin, who recently called at the Foreign Office, strongly urged - putting forward the suggestion in a strictly private and confidential manner, as best calcu lated to facilitate the position of the British group as to wards their foreign colleagues - that His Majesty*s Government should,( 46410 / 13 ). should, if possible, take the line that for political reasons coulo noo c.xlow any concession of a port to the inter- unner solely British control (so far as is practicable con sistently witn the maintenance of a. Persian fa.cade ): subject to tnis control, 01 course, every guarantee could and should be offered ior fair treatment and all reasonable facilities for the working and administration of the harbour, ware houses, etc. sir E. G-rey would also be glad to be furnished with Lord Crewe’s observations on this point. I am, dir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,* [This P€ Glim ant is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government] 1 PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL [October 23.] Section 2. [46410] Sir Edward Greij to Sir F. Bertie. (No. 640.) Sir, Foreign Office, October 23, 1913. THE French Ambassador called on the 8th instant and communicated a memorandum, of which a copy is enclosed,* regarding certain points connected with the trans-Persian railway project. As regards the French Legation at Tehran joining with the British and Russian Legations in presenting a request to the Persian Government for an option, Sir A. Nicolson informed M. Gambon privately that he did not think His Majesty’s Govern ment would be disposed to agree to such a formal and public association of the three legations. Germany was quite ready to admit and recognise the special and predominant interests of Great Britain and of Russia in Persia, but he felt sure that if a third Power were to be ostensibly and officially associated with Great Britain and Russia, Germany would also claim to be placed on a similar footing. Sir A. Nicolson thought, therefore, lhat the request should be presented by the Russian and British Legations alone. He added that the same observations applied also to the suggested French participation in the study of the alignment. M. Gambon seemed to admit the force of what Sir A. Nicolson said as to French participation in the application to the Persian Government, but his Excellency said that he did not quite see that similar objections should be raised as regards a French delegate on the Survey Commission, as French capital would be invested, and naturally the alignment of the railway was of interest to those who were financially interested. ; Sir A. Nicolson told M. Gambon that of course the French Governments memorandum would be studied, and that his own observations were merely personal. It is understood that the British group have addressed the letter, of which a copy is enclosed,! to the President of the Societe d’Etudes in Paris. &gt; As regards the port, mentioned in the French memorandum, and terminal facilities generally m the south, Lord Errington and Sir W. Garstin, who recently called at the Foreign Office, strongly urged—putting forward tlm suggestion m_ a strictly private and confidential manner, as best calculated to facilitate the position of the Bntisi group as towards their foreign colleagues—that His Majesty s Government should, it possible, take the line that for political reasons they could not allow any concession ot a port to the international company. Whatever the port was, it would have to be under solely British control (so far as is practicable consistently with the maintenance of a Persian Made ); subject to this control, of course, every guarantee could, and should be offered for fair treatment and all reasonable facilities for the working and administration of the harbour, warehouses, &amp;c. 1 am, &amp;c. E. GREY. * Memorandum by French Ambassador, October 6, 1913. t British Group to President of Societe d’Etudes [48108J. 1 | 1 I[This Document is the Property of His Britannic M^esty's Govemment.1 PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [October 22.] Section 2. [48108] No. I. -{Communicated Letter from British Group to President of “ Societe d'Etudes ” at Paris. to Foreign Office, October 22, 1913.) (Confidential.) M. le President, I HAVE the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated the 9th October, which reached London on the 14th instant, and which I found on my return from abroad. I am informed confidentially by the Foreign Office that the request was recently made by the French Ambassador in London for associating the French Government with the Governments of Great Britain and Russia in the diplomatic negotiations contemplated at Tehran on behalf of the “ Societe d’Etudes.” The suggestions made by the French Government would, we learn, appear to have met with serious objections on the part of His Majesty’s Government for general political reasons which have been explained to M. Gambon. The matter of the principles involved has, moreover, been referred to the Government of India. It is understood that the matter is still being considered and discussed by the French and British Governments. Under these circumstances I have no doubt your Excellency will agree that the forwarding of your letter of the 9th October, addressed to Sir Edward Grey, would hardly serve a useful purpose at the present moment, as it might tend to complicate the situation, which requires elucidation_ on the, part of the Governments concerned before the British group of the Societe d Etudes can usefully intervene to advance the interests of the “ Societe” as a whole. As soon as we learn the outcome of the present negotiations we will not fail to acquaint your Excellency, and consideration can then be given to the next steps required on the part of the u Societe d Etudes. ^ I am, &amp;c. ERRINGTON. [1898 y —2]pttt aNV y From Viceroy, 16th October 1913. Foreign Secret. Your telegram of 11th August. Trans-Persian Railway. We suggest British half of joint technical Commission should consist (1) of two engineer officers and (2) of a traffic officer, and that they should he assisted by (3) a commercial adviser, (4) an officer of Indian Survey Depart ment. We also consider it of great importance that (5) a representative of General Staff of Indian Army should be attached to Commission in some inconspicuous capacity to watch proceedings from the strategical point of view and be ready to give British members of Commission advice on points of strategy. A suitable escort of a medical officer, two Indian engineering- subordinates, with usual clerical and subordinate establishments will also be required. As to personnel we desire to make the following recommendations : — (1) Mr. Johns and Major Hopkins, R.E. Both these officers have a wide experience of Persia and have personally examined various alignments for railways in our sphere. (2) Major Anderson, R.E., an officer of long experience in Railway Department of Government of India. For (3) Cox strongly recommends Chick, now at Bushire. We concur. (4) Major A. A. McHarg, R.E., an officer of Survey Department. (5) Major Bainbridge, D.S.O. We propose to defer nomination of medical officer until the members of Commission and the strength of escort have been decided. As regards latter we strongly recommend, for the first portion of alignment, escort should be purely Russian and that it should be relieved at Shiraz or Yezdikhast by a British escort. There are obvious objections to an escort composed partly of British and partly of Russian troops. Strength can be settled later with reference to condition of country in which the Commission will work, and when we have fuller information as to precise scope of enquiry, e.g., whether it is probable or no that the party will be split up to examine alternative alignments. We are in some doubt as to whether it is proposed to extend Commission’s enquiry through the British sphere to Chahbar or only to Kerman. If the former is the case we desire to suggest for the consideration of His Majesty's Government advisability of British participation in survey of alignment north of Tehran. It might be advantageous to be in a position to offer criticism of alignments in North similar to those urged against our proposed alignments in South, and it would be well that we should have expert knowledge of relative conditions of alignment of line as a whole. Our proposals as to pay of personnel will follow.(4479C/13). Xrorn oaing created in the mind either of the Persian Government or of any foreign Legation at Teheran, Before taking any action in the matter. Sir E. Grey would Toe glad to learn whether the Marquess of Crewe concurs in the view above set forth. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,CONFIDENTIAL. 4 - 4 1 Sir T4 7 . Townley to &amp;ir Edward Grey.—{Received October 1, 10 p.m.) Tehran, October 1, 1913. (^°. 345.) / {October 1, 8*30 p.m.) YOUR telegram No. 422 I do not consider association of French Legation would be of the smallest assistance in securing the option for the Trans-Persian Railway. I think option will be attained without very great difficulty, but it is probable that Persian Grovernment will endeavour to secure some assurance of financial assistance. Co-operation of French Legation would not assist this. 1 ■ Copy to India 10 OCT 1913 [1119—19]__[This Document is the Property of His Britann^ Majesty’s Governmeiit.1 PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. \ [September 30. J Section 2, [44101] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley. (No. 422.) (Telegraphic ) Foreign Office, September 30, 1913. FRENCH and Russian Governments and groups of Societe d’Etudes demand that French representative at Tehran should join his British and Russian colleagues in presenting note applying for option for trans-Persian railway to Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs. Do you consider that this association of French Legation would enhance prospect of favourable reply ? [1870 g 2]N.B.—This Bonn must accompany any inquiry respecting this Telegram, Office Stamp. If th« Rfeceivet of an Inland Telegram doubts its accuracy, be may have it repeated on payment of half the T----nnmi l 'U its transmission, any fraction of Id. less than |d. being reckoned as |d.; and if it he found that there was any icnracy,yhe Jfmount paid for rep etition will he re funded. Special conditions are applicable to the repetition ot toreign lelegrams. ce of Origin and'Service Instructions. Lf In any further communication on this subject, please quote 44101/13. g rs f )i q No. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, Foreign Office Octoloer 1st, 1913 Immeu^ate. London. Sir: - O' Copy to India 3 OCT 1913 a- Tt/ w lth reference bo -Fereig-B—Qftlce letter of August 26th 1913 relative to the projected -rans- Perslan Railway, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward rey to transmit to you herewith copy of a let,ter from the President of the Society d'Etudes to the Chairman of the British group, communicated to this epartment by the latter offering certain observations on the draft of the note to be presented to the Arslan Minister for Foreign Affairs by the British and Russian Representatives at Tehran, asking for the grant to the Societe of an option to build the line. The Marquess of Crewe will observe that bnsieur Raindre, in the first place, appears to assume that the French Representative will join his British and -presenting this note, ano. 'i- 1 • Russian colleagues m presenting v.. x Grey is aware that in Lord Crewe’s opinion, expressed i.ocnsnigi ^ ^ letter 0 J the Uth ultimo (P.3160) this mode of procedure is to be recommended as being more likely ^ than The Under Secretary of Stave, India Office.(44101/13) - &gt; ;r - v ^ ' • ' v - . y\ than that originally contemplated to te favour ally received Toy the Persian Government because it emphasises the genuinely international character of the under taking. It has however, on the other hand, seen represented as not free from objection because it might tend to strengthen the political influence of ranee in Persia to the possible detriment of that exercised bv Great Britain and Russia. Sir E. G-rey is asking by telegraph His rajesty's Minister at Tehran to express his opinion on this point. ’'ensieur Baindre notes in the second place the omission from the draft of the paragraph contained m the letter which, as originally proposed, the 'ociete wa s to address to the Persian -inister for foreign Affairs applying for the option, wherein the Persian Government are asked for an assurance that they will not. Without previous agreement with the delete grant . fnr a -port on the main line or on any a concession for a pox u branch of the railway. , n , -roppive Mord Crewe's gir E. Grey would be glad to receive niu observations on this point.(44101/13) Thirdly, Monsieur p aindre demands that the Societe should itself te represented on the International Commission which is to examine and report on the alternative alignments proposed for the southern section of the railv/ay and suggests that this representation might he secured ty the presence of a Commissioner appointed hy the French Government. It is, in Sir E. Grey's view, nature.! that the Societe should wish to see their interests safeguarded in this way and logical that the French Government, whose financial interest in the scheme is equal to that of Great Britain and Russia, should wish to he represented on the Commission. The proposal might however he open to the same objection as that for the participa tion of the french Representative in the presentation of the note and I am to ask for an expression of Lord Crewe's opinion on the point. It will he observed that the French group of the Societe appear already to have approached the French Government with regard to the first and third of the above questions and to have assured themselves of the supportmm (44101/13) support of the latter before consulting their British colleagu.es, a fact which may make it difficult for TJ is Majesty’s Government to refuse their assent to the demands made in Monsieur Baindre’s letter. The difficulty will be increased by the fact that the 'Russian- group and the 'Russian Government themselves are in complete agreement v/ith the French Government and group as shown by a memorandum, copy of which is enclosed, communicated to this Office by the Russian Charge d'Affaires. It will be seen from this paper that, as regards the third point dealt with above, the Russian Govern ment suggest, as an alternative to the presence oi a representative of the French Government on the Commis ion, that the drench and Russian representatives should members of the SociStS, which should itself defray the expenses of the survey. I am to ask that, in view of the fact that a meeting of the Society has been fixed for a date early in October, Sir E. Grey may be favoured with a reply to(44101/13) to this letter with, as little delay as possible. I am. Sir &gt; Your most otedient. humble Servant,fiacnment is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.]^ PERSIA. CONPIBENTIAL. V ■? rw--* I O b' D [August 29.] Section 1. [38590] No. 1. Foreign Office to Sir W. Garstin. Sir, Foreign Office, August 29, 1913. WITH reference to Foreign Office letter of the 31st May, relative to the Trans-Persian Railway, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith the draft of a note which he would propose should be presented to the Persian Minister for Foreign /Yffairs by His Majesty’s and the Russian representatives at Tehran asking that an option for the construction of the line may be granted to the Societe d’Etudes.* I am to state that Sir E. Grey would be glad to be furnished with any observations which the British group may have to offer on this draft, and that he proposes, so soon as he has received them, to endeavour to obtain the concurrence of the Russian Government in its terms and to ask them to instruct their representative at Tehran to present the note to the Persian Government in concert with his British colleague. It will be observed that the text of the note is based on that of the draft, enclosed in your letter of the 27th May, of the communication which, as originally proposed, the Societe itself was to address to the Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs. I am, &amp;c. W. LANGLEY. * Draft note to Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs. [1829 ^—1]</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100032671578.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/416/1</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100032671578.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/416/1</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 4045/1913 'Pt 1 Trans-Persian Railway'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1913/1914</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-04T14:05:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (173 folios)</extent><extent>Papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume. Folio 79 is a collection header sheet, giving the subject heading and a list of correspondence references found within the volume part.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence and memoranda regarding the Société Internationale d'Études du Chemin de Fer Transpersan's proposed bid for an option to construct a railway in Persia.The volume contains communications received from the French and Russian Ambassadors to the UK, the British Ambassador to Russia, and the French, Russian and English representatives of the Société d'Études. It also contains internal communications between the Viceroy of India, the Foreign Office, the War Office, the India Office, and HM Legation in Teheran [Tehran].Topics discussed:whether to present the option request through the Société d'Études, or through the representatives to Teheran;whether France should play a formal role in negotiations;the establishment of an Anglo-Russian Commission to study the proposed alignment of track;granting concessions to third parties for port and terminal facilities in the south of Persia;potential alignment (routes) of the track: Ispahan -- Shiraz -- Bundar Abbas; Kerman -- Chahbar; Yezd -- Bundar Abbas [Eşfahān -- Shīrāz -- Bandar-e 'Abbās; Kermān -- Chābahār; Yazd -- Bandar-e 'Abbās];Anglo-Russian relations;the potential impact on the military defence of India, should Russia have rail access to any point to the east of Bundar Abbas;the application for a mining concession by the Persian Mining Syndicate.The file also contains a copy of the
                           Convention signed on August 31, 1907, between Great Britain and Russia, containing Arrangements on the subject of Persia, Afghanistan, and Thibet(ff 190-95).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100032671578.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>