<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000c5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T05:09:20.855Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">JLA ^ wrrvff fC** 9c ^ / *{f&lt;r^ { DiiO lo^ZL] From * Tho biker Secretary to th« OoveriiiSient of India in the eternal Affaire Department. To • Tne Additional Counsellor for Indian Affairs, British iwnbasey, Tehran. ' tU. !l\ kecuorundwn Ao. F.23(13)-*/46. ^ p| Dated dimla, the 23rd October 1946. ^ Subject:«Daily allowance to let ^rade officers itt. l .,nfriL.*.araifej Beference your Ma^iorunaum fiO.C/T-2/46, dated the 7th August 1946. 2 # Tae Uofernor Uerieral in Council, with the ap^rotal of His Majesty’s Uo?arnment, is pleased to sanction for 1st Grade officers serving in the districts of Khoras&amp;n and Kerman and in Tehran daily allowance at rates fixed by His Majesty’s Government from time to time for thoir officers of corresponding status, lor one year witn effect from tne 1st September 1946, subject to tue position be-%, reviewed in April 1947. ( 3d/- P*H# Krishnaswamy ) Under aecretary to tne Government of India.Please see Government of India’s Express Letter below. The Government of India support the recommendation of the additional Counsellor at the British Embassy, Tehran, that the concession already granted (see submission at Ext. 2090/45) to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Grade I Officers on his staff, to draw daily allowances at the enhanced rates when travelling on duty in Persia, Egypt and Iraq, should now be extended to Government of India Grade I Officers serving in East Persia (the districts of Kerman and Khoraslfli and in Tehran itself). These rates are identical with those fixed for Class A Officers by H.M.G. The concession!^ granted to officers of the Persian Gulf Residency was approved in our telegram No. 14573 of the 26th June, 1945* The Government of India in asking H.M.G.*s approval to their latest recommendation have requested that the new rate should have retrospective effect from the 1st September, 1946, subject to the position being reviewed in April 1947* It seems but natural and logical that the rates of daily allowances should be made uniformly applicable to all Grade I Officers of the ex-India cadre serving in the Persian Gulf and in East Persia. Perhaps the Financial Secretary would advise whether it is necessary to refer this to the Foreign Office, having regard to the fact that the Government of India have discretionary powers to sanction^without reference to the Treasury, items of diplomatic and Consular expenditure in Persia involving not more than £1,000 a year. &gt;7 A- Financial Secretary S.&amp; G. ke&amp;fetary For concurrence or any observations. Financial Secretary’s comments on the last paragraph v/ould be appreciated. ^7. &lt;5 • T / - x-By Fast Air Ll^il t» B hd i Government ojf India, Cxt ermy'^'f fail's Depar tment, Express Letter^ From Foreign, Simla, To ^enodotia, London,, No. F*25(1B)-E/46. Dated Siriila, the /(T^September 1946. Subject:- Daily allowance to 1st grade officers in East Persia. Reference correspondence ending with your telegram No.14573, aated the 26th June 1946. 2. Additional Counsellor, British Embassy, Tehran recommends that the concession granted to Government of India Grade I Officers serving in Persian Gulf to draw daily allowances at rates fixed by His Majesty’s Government from time to time for their officers of, corresponding status should also be extended to Grade I officers serving in East Persia. Government of India support the recomiendation and request that the concession be extended to Grade I Officers serving in districts of Kerman and Khorasan and in Tehran with effect From 1st September 1946 subject to the position being reviewed in April 1947. They would oe grateful if necessary approval of His majesty’s Government be obtained and communicated at an early date. The issue of the above has been authorised for Secretary to Hie Govt, of India,F *LE Bt Air Mail A *-x From - The Under Secretary to the Government of India JviuEX* r &amp; * n ^ &gt;a Slfcerna l Affairs Department* / To - The Hon'ble the Pol Memorandum No. F.27(12)-K/44. 1 j ^ Dated Simla* the .ialy ; 19fl5. Subject t m Daily allosanom to officers serving in the Persian Gulf. ------ f&amp;4S - -1- dent.in the Persian Gulf* i.n'. d&lt;3^0 Reference correspondence ending with Foreign telegram No* 103-8 /0/45 , dated the 2nd May 1945. )2L L /?. 2* The Governor-General-in-Council, with the approval of His Majesty's Government, is pleased to sanction for the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and grade I Officers serving ‘ in under the^Persian Gulf Residency, while travelling on dut I t travelling * w* immiNa* * asvwAVkwayw ^ naa^JkV ua.ce Persian. Sgypt and Iraq such rates of daily Majesty's Government fix from time to time similar status while travelling in those oo ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S LETTER DATE RECEIVED 9 1 7 a 0-8-1940 iV A allowance as His for their officers of countries* ( 3d/- p*N. Krishnaawamy ) Under Secretary to the Government of Indie*Please see the telegram from the Government of India below. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has suggested that the present rates of Daily Allowance admissible for him and Grade I Officers of the Persian Gulf Residency while travelling on duty in Persia, Egypt and Iraq are insufficient and proposed that the rates fixed by H.M.G. fof^officers of similar status travelling in these countries should apply to them also. According to Supplementary Rule 51 made under Fundamental Rule 44 and applied to the 'Political Department of the Government of India' (and so, presumably, to the ex-India cadre) by Supplementary Rule 17, read with Appendix 18, the Political Resident receives a Daily Allowance of Rs.15 while travelling in Persia, Egypt and Iraq and Grade I Officers Rs.10. These rates were fixed in 1934- and do not appear to have been revised since. The allowances fixed by H.M.G. for Class A Officers on 1st July 194-3 (Appendix H b to Estacode) are:- Egypt 35/- per diem in Cairo « 30/- ' ' elsewhere Iraq 40/- Persia 40/- »« 45/- if staying at the 'Park' or 'Durbad' Hotels at Tehran. The Government of India concur in the Political Resident’s proposal and in view of the recent rapid rise in the cost of living in the Middle East and the substantial difference between the rates of Daily Allowance granted by the Government of India and H.M.G., it is submitted that tnis recoranendation should be supported; a draft letter to the Foreign Office is attached. Financial Secretary S. &amp; G. Secretary j S &amp; &lt;x | 61 ^7 09. 'k f F 10672 : , ^ r- Ll9^5 J For concurrence or any observations. ^ 9 Q**. ^ J CKjfouuL- lAJi^k cdio.3 ^ i CM (LfVTK j htU TLvXw't-jJl HtMj JCf *** L^ir iu ^0/o ^ Kil 4/»v^iwvv/ t CVn-&lt;lIn doforonce-to the views of the Financial and O'* Departments, a draft telegram to the Government of India, approving their recomnendation, is now submitted.Bxt. 2090/4-5 / DRi\FT LSTTBR The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, S. W. 1. =ird herewith a slegram from 3nt of India, ces admissible ent in the I officers on ng on duty in at the rpose that the rates which are fixed by H.M.G. for officers of similar status when travelling on duty in these countries should apply to the Political Resident and other Grade I officers of the Persian Gulf residency. The Indian re gelations/regulations at present in force which date from 1934 provide for a daily allowance of Rs .15 in the case of the Political Resident and Rs .10 in the case of other Srade I officers, whereas it is understood that the allowances fixed by H.M.G* for Class ’A* officers are as follows : - 35 /- per diem in Cairo 30 /- per diem Elsewhere Iraq 40/- per diem \ Persia 40/- per diem 45/- if staying at the 'Park' or 'Durbad' Hotels at Teheran. Mr.Ameiy considers it reasonable that the rates of daily allowance should be/3. be eqiiated and would accordingly be glad if, provided Mr.Eden also agrees, the requisite steps may be tal^en to obtain the concurrences of the Lords Coninissioners of H.Li. Treasury. ^ A copy of this lettbr is being sent to the Treasury. IL L ^ ■NppapppiF1LI r DRV Kn. * JtF INWARD t-i &gt;: 20^0 1 TELEGRAM' v. 19 45 , Allotted to External 'T3emrt m9n^ Copies clroulated . WORD CODS TELEGRAM 14913 Prom To Goveriirrisixt of Hid ia^ Sxuei’no.l Ai fsirs Depertmant. Secretary of Stats for i.ndia. Repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire&gt; Dated Simla, 19,SO hours, Sad May, 1945, Received 02,45 hours, 3rd May, 1945, 103/B/C/45 Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Buahire, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf considers existing rates cf dally allowance admissible for him and grad© I officers of the- Persian Gulf Residency whilst travelling or. .d ity in Persia, Egypt and Iraq (?insufficient) and proposes such rates as H.M.Government fixes from tine to time for^their officers of simillar status v/ril t travelling m those countries may be sanctioned for irr and other i /officers ***** ..r _ 4 may r 45 Mnv\ I1^ Vs l' r \ “ won - The mder Secretary to the Govt, of India iii the External Affaire Department, 4 ' r i To - The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum No»1220“A/42» Me. Delhi, the If August 1942. '?TTO.TtfCT, Rented accommodation for the staff SWSSI* accompanying the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf on tour^ C!^, /q In suoersession of the orders contained ^ in paragraph of the memorandum from the Goyernmen of India ±n the ftctemal Affairs Department, wo p 145 -a/ 41, dated the 9th May 1S42, the -il^Srnt of India are pleased to decide that 4 no reduction on account of the provided for the staff accompanying the political * =sident in the Persian Gulf on tour should be made from their daily allowance so long as the present practice continues whereby the staff In question are allowed to draw full daily allowance for the first ten days of a halt and at half rates thereafter. Sd. V.B.Arte, Under secretary to the Govt, of India. 2778. JllfcsUu O' DA' LB'rom- The Under Secretary to the Government of ndia in the eternal Affairs Department, To - The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf • ft Memorandum No.F•145-//41. &gt;el i ,tne May 1942. s' Subject*- Leased accommodation at Bahrain and muscat for the staff of the Political Resident accompanying him on tour. Reference correspond nee ending with your express letter No •206-27/12, dated the 17th February 1942. 2# In tlie late Foreign and Political Department letter No. F.l6o-ii/36, dated tlie 7th August 1936, the Government of India accorded sanction to the Political Resident’s staff being provided with leased accommodation at Bahrain at a t rent of §•70/- p.m. for a period of one year in the first instance, as this sagption h s never been specifically renewed on the expiry of the year of its validity on the 7th Au? ust 1937, t e expenditure on renting accommodation for the staff in question has been irregularly incurred. The Government of India are. however, pleased to condone this irregularity and ti&amp;t of the fur her expenditure referred to in paragraph 2 of your # lemorandu® No.603-27/l2, dated the loth May 1941 being incurred without their prior approval* 3* They are further pleased to sanction (i) an expenditure not exceeding P«.l099/- p»a. on leasing accomrDodation at Bahrain for the superior staff accompany ing the Political Resident on tour till further orderj (ii) an expenditure not exceeding '.120/- p.a. for* leasing accommodation at Bahrain for the inferior staff accompany ing the Political Resident on tour for a period of one year in the first instancei and (ixi) an expenditure not exceeding 3 . 540 /- p.a* on providing rented accommodation at Muscat for the resident 8 staff till further orders, in accordance with the arrangement proposed in paragraph 3 of your memorandum of tne 15th May 1941 cited in paragraph 2 above. 4« The expenditure sa^tionod above should be debited to the office allowance grant of the Bushire Residency and should be met from the saqptioned budget ^rant of each year. 5. It is understood that the staff accompanying the Political Resident Qn tour draw daily allowance at full rates. This allowance is intended to cover ordinary daily charges incurred by a Government servant in consequence of ha absence from headuuarters and includes an element of living accommodation* The sanction conveyed in paragraph 3 above is therefore subjoc^ to the condition that the daily allowance drawn by each ( overnment servant, for whom rented accommodation is provided at Government expense, is reduced by an amount equivalent to the cost of such accommodation. Under Secretary^o Government of India.h mr Ko.F.361-i/34 From The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India* To His Majesty’s Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, Laadoru Dated New Delhi, the March 1935. Travelling allowance grants for the Persian Gulf Residency and its subordinate offices. Sir, With reference to my letter No.F.407-A/29, dated the 26th November 1929, I am directed to forward Letter from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No.2535, dated the 15th November 1934, with enclosure. Letter to the Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No.F.361-A/34, da^ed the T-S'V Marcn 1935. for information a copy of the papers noted in the margin regarding the travelling allowance grants for the Persian Gulf Residency and its subordinate offices. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. for Foreign Secretary to the Government of India.Copy of a letter No.2535, dated the 15th November 1934, from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. Revision of the fixed grants for Travelling Allowance of the Persian Gulf Residency and its subordinate offices. I have the honour to refer to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Memorandum No.F-407-A/29, dated the 26th November 1929, conveying sanction to the present fixed grants for travelling allowance of the Persian Gulf Residency and its subordi nate offices, and to submit in the accompanying state ment my proposals for revision of the grants for tne ensuing quinquennium commencing from the 1st April 1935. Xt will be observed that, with the exception of the Bushire Residency, the average expenditure during the past quinquennium in each case exceeds the present fixed grant which is inadequate to meet the normal expenditure on tours, transfers, leave and recess movements. The Bushire Residency grant was raised from Rs. 12,000/- to fe.22,000/- in consequence of the discontinuance of the hire of the despatch vessel, vide letter No.F.418-A/32, dated the 21st December 1932, from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. In the circumstances I request that the Government of India will be pleased to accord their sanction to the revision of the grants as proposed in column 9 of the statement.Ho, F. '361-k 1 34, From The Additiarial Deputy Seoretary to the Government- of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To The Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated Hex? Delhi, the March 1935. S Travelling allowance grants for the Persian Gulf Residency and its subordinate offices. Sir, . ^ With reference to your letter Ho.2535, dated the 15th November 1934, I am directed to say that the Government of India consider that the present system of fixed travelling allowance grants for the Persian Gulf Residency and its subordinate offices has proved to be a failure. It is noticed that the actual average expenditure up to the year 1925 was Rs.28,900 against a fUted grant of F5.11 S 10G and the actual average up to 1929 was Rs. 27,700 against a grant of Rs. 19,600. The latest years* average is Rs.42,300 against a sanction” ed grant of Rs.35,000. The reason for this appears to be that apart from transfer expenses which are heavy and fluctuating, the political conditions in Iran and the Gulf have been responsible for this. The system of fixed grants therefore serves no useful purpose. The Government of India have accordingly decided to abolish this system with effect from 1935-36, and I am to request thatthat in future provision for these charges may be pro posed in the budget estimates of the various offices on the basis of past average expenditure modified in the light of anticipated requirements. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your mst obedient servant, Sd. V. Harahari Rao, Additional Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.&amp; cii P POPV 1“ | S—.C* w w I ■ Fo. F.418-V 32 - v TJie foreign Secretary 't 0 'the Government Oi India in the Foreign and Political Department, To The Under Secretary of State for India* India Office, London. Dated Few Delhi, the 5/ December 19 32. Increase in the fixed travelling allowance grant of the Bushire Residency. •* X- X— X - * x» Si r, T/ith reference to my letter Fo. P.407-A/29, dated the 26th ITovernier 1929, I am directed to forward herewith a copy of the papers noted in the margin and to say that, for the 1. Letter from theHon'lie the Political Resident ; reasons explained in the Persian Gulf, Fo.2280 of 1932, dated the / 6th ITo vernier 19 32. { 2. Telegr^n to ---ditto-—- Fo.2607, dated the 19th Fovenler 19 32* 3. Telegram from -—ditto—- Fo. 766, dated the 22nd Fovenler 19 32. / 4. Letter from ----ditto---* Fo# 247 3 of 1932, ^ dated the 26th Fovgnler 19 32. ly the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the ] Government of Indiah 2607. Telegram E.No. 2607., dated the 19th Novr. 1932. From# • • • • .J’oroign, Few Delhi. To. .....••Political Besident, Bushire. Tour letter of the 6th November 1932, No.2280 of 1932. Necessity for additional grant for travelling allowance is not clear. Does it mean that you have to travel hy B.I. Hail steamers under altered condi tions more than in the past or that out of the exist ing allotment for Despatch vessel you have been spend ing a'bout Rs. 10,000 on the B.I. Mail steamer. Please furnish fuller details justifying increase in grant.... r — ' OJ Copy of letter No. 2473 of 1932, dated Bush ire, the 26th November 1932, from the Hon^hle the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, to the foreign Secretary to the Government of India, in the foreign and Political Department, New Delhi* Hire of Despatch vessel for the Political Besident, Bushire. With reference to my telegram No.766 of 22nd November 1932, sent in reply to your telegram No.'6607, dated the 19th November 1932, enquiring whether I have to travel by British India mail steamer under altered conditions more than in the past or that out of the existing allotment for despatch vessel, I have been spending Bs. 10,000/- on British India mail steamer I have the honour to state that in past years the Political Besident, in addition to his tours in the hired despatch vessel, also travelled in both British India mail steamers and His Majesty’s ships when visiting the various ports in the Persian Gulf. In the altered conditions, i.e. in the absence of a despatch vessel I will perforce travel by British India mail steamers and His Majesty’s ships even more than in the Past. 2. We have not spent Bs. 10,000/- on British India mail steamers out of the allotment for despatch vessel. 3. When the despatch vessel was at the Political Besident’s disposal the sum alloted for •’Hired Transport merely covered the hire of the vessel. Additional expenditure i.e. on account of Daily Allowance etcetera was/was debited to the Residency Travelling Allowance allotment of Rs. 12,000/- 4. In paragraph 2 of my letter No. 2280, dated the 6th November 1932 it was stated that the sum of Rs. 12,000/- was insufficient to meet the extra charges under the altered circumstances. In fact in the past three years it was necessary to reappro priate funds to cover normal excess expenditure under this head. 5. I submite a detailed statement showing the probable cost of my tours to the Trucial Coast and the Political Agencies by the British India mail steajners and/ or His Majesty # s ships.m Statement showing pro'ba'ble cost of Political ^Resident # s tour to the Trucial Coast and Political Agencies in the Persian Gulf* Politica l Res idents 1 3/5 fare from Bushire to Hen jam 'by British India steamer and iDack m Rs. 66/- Rs.212/ From Henjam to Trucial Coast in His Majesty f s ship* Messing charges on Sloop for 5 days ©Rs. 40/- 200, From Hen jam to Bushire By British India steamer Daily allowance approximately Rs . 25/ Cost of one visit*. Rs.437/ 2 visits to the Trucial Coast Cost of 2nd visit Rs.437/- Rs. 874/ Co nfid en tial Assistant. 1 3/5 fare from Bushire to Henjam By British India steamer and Back © Rs. 48/ Rs. 152/- Rs. 152/- Rs. 152/- Cost of one visit Cost of 2nd visit Rs. 304/ 2 visits to Kuwait Politic al R esid ent. 1 3/5 fare from Bushire to Kuwait By British India steamer and Back 25/- .Rs .80/- .Rs.150/ © Rs * 25/- 10 days halt Cost of one visit Cost of 2nd visit Bs. 250/- 3s. 250/- Es. 460/- Confident ial A ssist ant• 1 3/5 fare from Bus hire to Kuwait By British India steamer and Back Daily allowance.. Cost of one visit as. soA Bs. 114/- Bs. 1658/ CostfiiXt [ ?e©y From '-Che Foreign Secretary to the Government of Inuia, To His Majesty 1 s Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, London. Dated ^ew Delhi,the 26th Novemher,1929 Revision of the fixed travelling allowance allotments of the Persian Gulf Hesiaency and its subordinate offices. Sir, I am directed to refer to my letter Ho. 322-A,dated the 18th June 1925 and to report that the Government of Indio on the recommendation of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, have sanctioned the revision of the fixed travelling allowance allotment on the basis of past actu Is for 5 years, as shown below. Present grant . Hevised grant. Hs. Hs. Bushire , ... 8,400 12,000 Muscat 1,400 2,000 Bahrein 2,000 2,500 Kuwait 1,000 1,000 Mohammerah 1,000 1,200 Bandar ^bbas 1,200 2,400 Kerman 2,400 2,400 AhMaz 500 1,500 The revised scale will remain in force for a period of five years commencing from the 1st April 1930, at the end of which period the posa bility of modification will be considered. I have, etc. (Sd. ) for Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. f Ho. -k'. 407-A/29. ^7</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000c5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3635</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000c5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3635</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/59 'Bushire Residency: travelling allowances'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-19T08:57:14</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (32 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 34; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns travelling costs for the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf and its officesThe file contains correspondence related to:hire of despatch vessel for the Political Resident, 1932increase in travelling allowance grants, 1935accommodation for the staff of the Political Resident when in tour, 1942daily allowance of Political Resident and his officers when travelling on duty in Persia, Egypt and Iraq, 1945.The file is composed of correspondence between Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Government of India, Secretary of State for India, and India Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Expenses</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000c5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>