<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00028e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:00:40.755Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">This Document is the property of the Secretary of State for India. SECRET. B. 250a. Treaty with the Idrisi Saiyid. No. 33 A of 1915. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. SECRET. W;ir. To the Most Honour a blk the MARQUESS of CREWE, K.G., • His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Simla, My Lord Mahqi ess, i 1 With reference to your Lordship s telegram, dated the l ith Febnidry 1915 we have the honour to forward, for the consideration of His Majesty s Government, a copy oi a letteH trom » No. C. 343, dated the 1st May 1915. onr p 0 i lt ical Resident at Aden, with which he submits a Treaty signed by himself and by the representatives of the Idrisi Saiyid, for the ratiheation of the Government of India. 2 This Treaty does not appear to have been very concisely or very clearly drafted, but the terms generally coincide with what your Lordship approved in your telegram of the 28th December 1914. The idrisi, on his side, undertakes to make a pact of friendship between bmisefmidtbe British Government, to attack and to endeavour to drive the lurks from their stations in the Yemen and to extend his territories at their expense, and at the same time to abstain from any hostile or provocative action against the Imam Yahya so long as the latter does not join hands with t Turks. The British Government, on their side, undertake to protect his territories from attack on the seaboard, to guarantee ins independence in is own domain, and at the conclusion of the war to use diplomatic means to adjudicate between the rival claims of the Idrisi and the Imam Imther, they have no desire to enlarge their territories on Arabian soil but wish merely to see that the various Arab rulers live peaceably and amicab y “gether each in his own sphere. As a mark of appreciation of the work to be performed by the Idrisi Saiyid, the British Governmen have aided him with funds and munitions and undertake to give him fmthei assistance in the prosecution of his campaign against the Turks, in accordance with the measure of the Idrisi’s activities. Finally, the British Government agree as heretofore to give the Idrisi Saiyid full and free scope to trade and tiaffic between his ports and Aden. 9 The only point that appears to require definite qualification is the expression ' Arabian soil ” in Article 6, as this scarcely falls in with our position in Mesopotamia. If the words “ W estern Arabia were substituted for “Arabian soil,' this objection would be removed and oui mtentio would be sufficiently defined in the Treaty. 4 i t might also perhaps be urged that by allowing the Idrisi under Article 3 to 0 extend his territories and at the same time under Article o Laranteeimr Ws independence hereafter, we may be bringing ourselves into an Embarrassing position ns-a-ns other Arab Chiefs, but our position in R 3G39 c v the condition that the extension of the Idrisi s this nwtter is safeguarded b e ^ ^ TlirkSj and should he hereafter ^'‘re'huusd l a oo lision Cvfth other Arab Chiefs by an aggressive policy, rcould poinUo this condition and disavow h.s action. 5. Further, it might Un^ Sti^S-tV* of the pact of friendship which it is the object of the Treaty to consolidate. c t fnrtlier assistance in funds or munitions to the Idrisi is C. As any lurtlie . • measure of the Idrisi’s activities, our m Kir ^IdS;:; to be s«.ucie„u y safeguarded. 7 We think therefore, that, although the Treaty as drafted is open to objection on the’ground that it is neither very clear nor 7 ^' con ^ Se ’’ if the small amendment suggested in paragraph o above be f e ctea, adequately meet the requirements of the situation \ c 1 ^ therefore,'for authority to ratify it as it stands ^bject o his qua hcaUo^ To return it for extensive revision to our I olitical Resident endanger the ultimate success of the negotiations, and vvould at am rate involve undesirable delay. If Your Lordship agrees, we should be glad of orders by telegraph. We have&gt; &amp;c . ; My Loud Marquess. (Signed) Hardinge ot 1 ensulks i. Beauchamp Du e. R. W. Carlyle. S. A. Imam. W. H. Clark. R. H. Craddock. W S ATfyfr No. C. 343, dated Aden Residency, the 1st May 1915 (Secret). From Major-General T). G. L. Shaw, Political Resident, Aden, to the Secretary to the Government of India in the loreign and Political Department. In sending you by this mail three copies of the Treaty signed by me and the Idrisi Saiyid for the ratification of the Government of; India, I have the honor to state that the Idrisi representatives will leave to-morrow for their country. They appear to mean business. 2. There is little left to be said. Paragraph 5 is the most important one, and is in accord with the cipher instructions received from you. 3. Paragraph 7. The precise details of assistance in funds and munition is expressly omitted at the request of Saiyid Mustafa and is done to avoid wounding Arab susceptibilities. A receipt in full for assistance giyen has however been obtained. The concluding portion of this paragraph is very essential. Having begun a good work with so important a Chief, and one so inimical to everything Turkish, it will he necessary to prosecute the matter a outrance, but I was careful to insert the last nine words of the paragraph as showing the quid pro quo for which the Idrisi is responsible. 4. I would request that two ratified copies of the Treaty may he returned to me, one to he given to the idrisi and the other for this office records. Ibis ^ reaty of friendship and Goodwill is signed by Major-General 1). G. L. ^aw, the Political Resident, Aden, on behalf of the British Govern- meirt and by Saiyid Mustafa bin Saiyid AbduT ’Ali on the part of HisEminence Saiyid Muhammad bin Ali bin Muhammad bin Ahmed bin Idris, the Idrisi Saiyid and Amir of Sabia and its environments. 2. Its main objects are to war against the Turks and to consolidate a pact of friendship between the British Government and the Idrisi Saiyid, above- mentioned, and his Tribesmen. 3. The Idrisi Saiyid agrees to attack and to endeavour to drive the Turks from their stations in the Yemen and to the best of his power to harass the Turkish troops in the direction of the Yemen and to extend his territories at the expense of the Turks. 4. The Saiyid’s prime objective will be against the Turks only, and he will abstain from any hostile or provocative action against Imam Yahya so long as the latter does not join hands with the Turks. 5. The British Government undertakes to safeguard the Idrisi Saiyid’s territories from all attack on the seaboard from any enemy who may molest him ; to guarantee his independence in his own domain and at the con clusion of the war to use every diplomatic means in its power to adjudicate between the rival claims of the Idrisi Saiyid and the Imam Yahya or any other rival. 0. The British Government has no desire to enlarge its borders on Arabian soil but wishes solely to see the various Arab rulers living peacefully and amicably together each in his own sphere, and all in friendship with the British Government. 7. As a mark of its appreciation of the work to be performed by the Idrisi Saiyid, the British Government has aided him with both funds and munitions and will continue to assist him in the prosecution of the war so long as it lasts in accordance with the measure of the Idrisi s activities. 8. Finally, while maintaining a strict blockade on all Turkish ports in the Red Sea, the British Government has for some months past been giving the Idrisi Saiyid full and free scope to trade and trailic between his P 0 ^ 8 and Aden, and this concession the British Government, in token of the friendship existing, will continue uninterruptedly to maintain. 9. This Treaty will be held to be valid after its ratification by the Government of India. Signed this day Friday, the thirtieth of April 1915, A.D., corresponding with the fiftieth of Jamad Shani 135.1 llijia. (Sd.) (Sd.) (Sd.) D. G. L. Shaw, Major-General, (Sd.) Political Resident, Aden. H. F. Jacob, Lieut.-Col, (Sd.) First Assistant Resident. C. R. Bradshaw, Major, General Staff Officer, Aden Brigade. i . e ., Saiyid Mustafa bin Saiyid Abdu’l ’Am on behalf on the Idrisi Saiyid. i . e ., Sheikh Muhammad bin Awad ba Sahi.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00028e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B250a</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00028e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B250a</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Treaty with the Idrisi Saiyid. No 33A of 1915. Government of India Foreign and Political Department'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1915</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-03-31T18:21:42</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (2 folios)</extent><extent>The file opens with two letters about the Treaty and is followed by the Treaty itself.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 114, and terminates at f 115, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains a 'Treaty of Friendship and Goodwill' and is signed by David George Levigne Shaw, the Political Resident in Aden, on behalf of the British Government, and by Saiyid Mustafa bin Saiyid Abdu'l 'Ali on the part of His Eminence Saiyid Muhammad bin Ali bin Muhammad bin Ahmed bin Idris, the Idrisi Saiyid and Amir of Sabia and its environs. The document is also signed by Harold Fenton Jacob, First Assistant Resident in Aden. The Treaty seeks to unite the British Government and the Idrisi Saiyid against Turkish [Ottoman] incursions in Aden and Yemen more generally. Though the main focus of the document is the provision of diplomatic and moral support, paragraph 7 of the Treaty confirms that the British Government will support the Idrisi against Turkey through the supplication of 'funds and munitions'.The Treaty is prefaced by two letters: one signed by various government officials including the Viceroy of India, and one written by David George Levigne Shaw. Both letters provide their opinions on the Treaty.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Idrīsī Imām of ʻAsīr</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arms sales</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00028e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>