<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000912.0x00009e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T17:40:30.203Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">secret. Page 20 .—For first paragraph at top of page regarding Basidu T) 1820 - substitute the following :— asidu In 1820, a concession was obtained by the British from the Sultan of Oman for the occupation of a piece of territory on Qishm Island, and an important naval and military station was established on the north-east corner of the island. But this, as well as a station tried on the island of Han jam, being found un healthy, a move was made to Basidu, at the western end of the island. This became the headquarters of the Indian Naval Squadron, and a detachment of Indian troops was regularly maintained there until 1879, when it was removed to Jask, where it remained till 1887. The concession for Basidu was renewed by the Persian Government when it took over Qishm Island from the Sultan of Oman. History. Page 40.—Add the following at the end of the chapter : At the beginning of 1912, when the Persian Government was 1912 . much embarrassed by the action of Russia, a recrudescence of Ex - Sh . a activity on behalf of the ez-Shah took place. Recruits were col- b0lIl ° lected in Russian territory, and offered high pay, and large con signments of arms and ammunition were passed along the Russian railway for the ex-Shah. The ex-Shah himself advanced to Samana, Salar-ud-Dauleh re-occupied Kirmanshah ,and Shuja- ud-Dauleh again took the field near Ardabil. The Persian Government made energetic protests to the two Powers, and Russia was eventually persuaded to join with Great Britain in informing the ex-Shah that the Powers would not recognise him. Russian representatives at Astarabad conveyed the message, with reservations on the part of Russia, and the ex-Shah left Persian territory on March 2nd, 1912. Salar-ud-Dauleh, however, still remained. He kept most of western Persia in a state of disturbance throughout the year though he was decisively defeated by Ephraim (Yprim) Kha. n * Armenian, near Hamadan on May 19th. S170GSB9 In October 1912 Salar-ud-Dauleh suddenly appeared near Tehran and terrified the Government and the inhabitants* With the covert assistance of Russian representatives he made his way to Astarabad and there tried to obtain the assist ance of the Turkomans, but his partizans were defeated by Gov ernment troops and he attempted to make terms. The Persian Government was almost compelled, chiefly by Russia, to appoint Salar-ud-Dauleh to the Governorship of Gilan, but Salar-ud-Dauleh J s irresponsible conduct alienated even Russian support, and he eventually surrendered to a body of Per sian Cossacks, which had tardily been sent after him. He was deported in September 1913 to Europe, being granted a pension by the Persian Government. Throughout 1912 and 1913 the Persian Government were never free from the disquieting effect of rumours of the ea;-Shah’s return. During 1911, Russia had been growing impatient at the Russian Action independent policy pursued by Mr. Shuster, the American fin- in North R«'sia. ancier, whom Persia had engaged to reform her financial admin istration. Mr. Shuster had won the confidence of the Persian Majlis and people, and was gradually evolving order out of chaos. In November 1911, however, Russia seized the pretext of a minor incident in Tehran, over the seizure of Shua-us-Saltaneh’s property, to present an ultimatum, demanding an apology and the removal of Mr. Shuster’s gendarmes from the property. In default she threatened to send troops to north Persia. The Persian Cabinet, except two ministers, promptly resigned and no reply was then sent. Thereupon Russia sent 1,700 troops to Tabriz, 4,000 to Rasht, and 200 to Astarabad. On November 28th the gendarmes w r ere withdrawn, and a full apology was made. Russia, however, the same day, presented another ultimatum demanding t— (1) The dismissal of Mr. Shuster and Mr. Lecoffre (a British subject in the Finance Department at Tabriz). (2) An assurance that no foreigner should be employed in Persia without the consent of Russia and Great Britain. (c) The payment of an indemnity.The Majlis refused these terms, and many Persians agitated for resistance. On December 15th 4,000 Russian troops were concentrated at Kazvin, and an advance was threatened on Tehran itself. ' Disturbance broke out at Tabriz, Rasht, and Enzali between Persian Nationalists and Russian soldiers, thus aggravating the situation. The Russians repressed these outbreaks with great severity. In desperation, on December 24th, the Regent dissolved the obdurate Majlis, and accepted the Russian terms, hoping that the Russian troops' would be withdrawn. This hope, however, was not fulfilled, for in January 1912 Russia had seized the opportunity to place garrisons at the following places :—• Meshed ... .. 1,500 J Kuchan # # .. 800 J Gumbaz Kabud .. # 0 .. 400 ^ Astarabad .. 400 r Enzali .. _ .. c. 200 ■s Rasht-Kasvin . . .. 4,000 v-Hamadan ... .. 100 y Ardabil .. 2,000 1 Tabriz _ .. 6,000 rKhoi • # w* .. 1,200 &lt; Urumieh • , .. 500 (.Maragheh - .. 100 17,000 By the end of 1913 only slight modifications had been made in these garrisons giving a total decrease of about 3,000 troops.4 Russian Troops in Persia .—At the end of January 1014, according to latest reports, Russia had the following troops in Persia:— Place. Troops. Guns. Remarks. Meshed 250 Kuchan and Meshed-Gaudan road 200 Astarabad 880 6 Gunbad-i-Kabus 200 Barfarush 170 2 Meshed-i-Sar .. 210 Mahmudabad .. 150 Ardabil 2,000 Tabriz 2,000 14 Marand and Julfa-Tabriz road 800 4 Khoi 8,000 Urumieh 1,500 Sauj Bulagh 800 Rasjit 100 1 sotnia. Enzali 30 Depot. Kanjarud (30 miles from Rasht) .. 100 1 sotnia. Kazvin 2,826 8 Consular escort at Tehran, Isfahan, etc. 131 Total 14,200 82 On March 1912 certain agents raised disturbances at Meshed, nominally in favour of the ex-Shah. On March 30th the Russian Consul-General ordered the bombardment of the sacred Shiah shrine at Meshed, alleging that a mob of the ex-Shah’s followers had collected there. About 65 pilgrims were killed or wounded, and much damage done to the shrine, but those responsible for the trouble escaped with the connivance of the Russian authori ties. Turkoman raids, mostly from Russian territory, also caused much disorder in 1912 and 1913. The events of 1911, namely the rebellion of the ex-Shah and Russian ultimatums, had almost completely strangled Persia. At integrity 3 of the the beginning of 1912 her Treasury was empty, she had no mili- coun try. tary forces available to suppress disorders or to collect revenue, and there was no strong public man to be found to direct efforts at reform. Most of her troubles were ascribed to Russia, but Great Bri tain also incurred much odium for connivance.5 In March 1912 the two Powers made a small advance of £200,000 to the Persian Government on condition that Persia recognised the Anglo-Russian Convention, and devoted part of the advance to organising a Gendarmerie, {q.v.y This amount was soon dissipated in pensioning the ex-Shah and fighting against Salar ud-Dauleh, and the Persian Govern ment applied to the two Powers again for a large loan. However, until order had been restored, no financiers were willing to grant a large loan, without a guarantee from Russia and Great Britain, and without money Persia was unable to restore order. Hence she moved on in the same vicious circle. In September 1912, Sir E. Grey and M. Sazonoff, Russian Anglo-Ruasian Foreign Minister, conferred at Balmoral on the situation in Per- Polic y* sia, and apparently agreed on certain principles to guide their policy in Persia, namely the support of the Central Government, discouragement of the ex-Shah, the restoration of order by the Gendarmerie, and the exploitation of the country by railways. Difficulties, however, arose in putting these principles into practice. Many Russian representatives in Persia deliberately disobeyed the orders, which the Russian Government appeared to give them, and thus hampered all attempts to restore a sound administration. In 1912, M. Mornard, the Belgian Director of Customs, was placed in Mr. Shuster’s position of Treasurer-General. The Customs department then took over the whole financial ad ministration of the country, and, though at first M. Mornard appeared to be too Russo-phil to prove efficient, the Belgian agents also met with much obstruction from Persian Governors and other Persians steeped in venahty, yet eventually by 1914 the finances of Persia had begun to yield a regular income to the Central Gov ernment. Not little obstruction was met with from Russian, representatives in the North. Attempts were made in 1912 by the two Powers to find a new Regent in place of Nasr-ul-Mulk, who had fled to Europe, and also to collect a Cabinet to carry on the Government ; but not till February 1913 did they succeed in any measure. In the new Cabinet the Bakhtiari element had been entirely eliminated. The new Cabinet, on the strength o£ another small advance, made a promise, even without the approval of the Majlis, which was then non-existent, to grant a railway concession to each of he two Powers (see Communications). S170GSB6 During 1913 the Gendarmerie developed successfully, and the finances of the Government improved proportionately, so that by the end of the year there was not the same pressing need for a large loan. The two Powers were working fairly well in harmony, and serious disturbances were less numerous. In April 1913 Great Britain was able to withdraw the 39th Central India Horse from Isfahan, Shiraz, and Bushire, whither Persia. 3 * ° U they had been sent in October 1911 to re-inforce the consular guards. During their stay in the country, two serious incidents had occurred, which had nearly necessitated the despatch of an expedition into South Persia. In 1911 representatives of Great Britain and Russia visited xu^co^Persian the Turco-Persian Frontier and reported that Turkey had en- Frontier, croached considerably since 1905. In December 1912 a protocol was signed between Turkey and Persia appointing a Commission to sit in Constantinople and delimidate the frontier. This Com mission, under pressure from Great Britain and Russia, defined a line acceptable to both countries. In January 1914 a Commission consisting of British, Russian, Turkish and Persian delegates commenced demarcating the frontier from Muhammareh north- ' wards. During 1911 and 1912 the trade in arms continued brisk and Arms Traffla, our efforts to prevent the arms reaching Makran merely sent them further up the Persian Gulf, whence some still found their way to Afghanistan, and some tended to create disorders in southern Persia. In September 1912, however, an arms warehouse with strict regulations was established at Masqat, which was the only port where steamers from Europe called and the import of arms was not already forbidden. This materially limited the number of arms imported, though until January 1914 the French Gov ernment refused to recognise the justice of the Sultan’s rules. Exports from Masqat and Arabia continued throughout 1913 and 1914, and the blockade had to be mantained at full strength. Makran was still visited by Afghans in their search for arms, but not to the same extent as before Colonel Delamain’s expedi tion. In 1914 the headquarters of the Intelligence Officer, Jask, were moved to Bushire. /7 Page 43 .—At end of paragraph headed “ Western Frontier ” and ending with the words “ contested spot ”, add the follow ing :—- Note .—On November 19th it was reported from Constanti nople that a protocol in connection with the Turco-Persian frontier delimitation had been signed by the Turkish Grand Vizier and the British, Russian and Persian Ambassadors. The frontier fixed was said to be greatly in favour of Persia, which retained the disputed districts of Bazirgan, Targavar, Dasht (?), Margavar, Ushnu, Lavanavane ? (? Lahijan), and Marivan, and the southern extremity of the frontier formed by the Shatt- ul-Arab, as far as the mouth of the Khaiyin canal. The waters of the Shatt-ul-Arab remain under Turkish sovereignty; also all islands except Mahalleh and 6 dependent islands. Mu- hammareh continued to enjoy Persian jurisdiction, and the Shaikh will be maintained in possession of all his pronerties on Turkish soil. A special article states that the concession granted by the Shah and exploited by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company will be maintained in full vigour throughout the extent of territory transferred to Turkey. Page 60 .—Paragraph headed “ Lakes. Lake Urumieh ” after the words “ between the opposite shores ” in line 21, insert the following:— A Russian engineer has, however, obtained (1913) permission from his Government to arrange for a steamship service on the lake. Page 102 .—At the end of paragraph headed' Tehran,” add :—■ Note .—A sanitary council has now been instituted in Tehran. The members include representatives of several European Powers and of the Persian Ministry of the Interior : also several Persian doctors. The Council holds monthly meetings.mmm 8 Page 113 .—Lwt line but one, after the words “ not unhealthy ’* add the following :— J ’ Plague made its appearance in 1910, and so far has re appeared yearly, though not in epidemic form. Page 132 .—Lino 3. Following the words tant tribes are :—-J, insert the following : ' the most impor- . larg0afe tribe of tbe Kainat, numbering 8,000 to 10,000 famihea. , Military Report. .. rf 0 ? 6 135, after the P ara g ra P h on *• Armenians M insert Dashnatoutiun,” an Armenian Confederation was formed about 1894 In lurkey, as a secret society for defending Armenian ^ interests in countries where there are Armenian communities. ^ Pe S a th f re are IocaI committees at Tehran, Tabriz and Kasht. There is a central committee elected by local com- Genevar^’ Whl011 hSS head -' 3uartera 1,1 Emo P 8 &lt; n In -' PerS1 f\ 8inC0 Y P rim;K han, Armenian, in 1910, with a following of Armenian volunteers, helped the nationalists t° depose Muhammad Ah, this Armenian confederation has been an important factor m Persian politics. In 1912 its aims were (1) a reassembly of the Majlis ; (2) liberty of speech, etc., and the liberty of the press. Page 759.—last paragraph) reconstruct the second sentence as follows t—■ The tonnage of Persian gulf trade, which is almost entirely In -British ships, showed an increase of more than 10 per cent, in 19C8-09 over the preceding year. And after that sentence add the following t—9 The trade returns of the Persian Gulf for 1909-10 showed, 1,025 steamers of 1,327,318 tons and 2,811 sailing vessels of 83,573 tons called it the ports in the Gulf; of these 89-65 per cent, steamers and 4‘58 per cent, sailing vessels were British, 5-36 steamers were German, and about 6 per cent, of steamers and 12 per cent, of sailing vessels were Turkish. In 1910-11 there was an increase of 31 steamers. German trade increased about 5 per cent. The number of vessels visiting Persian ports in the Gulf was—• British 940 steamers and 156 sailing vessels. German 58 steamers. Russian 24 steamers. Turkish 7 steamers and 590 sailing vessels. Page 170. —After first paragraph ending “ to be found ” add the following :— On the Caspian Sea, where only the Russian flag may be flown, the number of vessels calling at Persian ports in 1909-10 was 2,542, an increase of 333 since 1908-09. There was a further increase of 213 in 1910-11. Page 170. For paragraph headed u Imports and exports ’' $ ubstitute the following :— During the year ending March 1910, the trade of Persia Imports and with foreign countries amounted to £16,279,049, as compared exp0r * with £13,974,021, in the preceding year. There was thus an increase of 2,305,073 pounds sterling or 16*49 percent. Of this total the chief contributions were :— Country. Imports. Exports. Total. Increase since last year. £ £ £ £ 4,531,619 5,250,461 9,782,080 1,500,000 British Empire 3,069,529 631,449 3,697,978 40,000 339,789 836,075 1,175,864 200,000 265,455 155,090 420,551 80,000 Italy 55,401 185,636 241,037 100,000 199,263 16,862 216,125 90,000 Austria Hungary 150,809 190 150,999 80,000 &amp;170GSB10 Germany thus rose from seventh to sixth place, displacing China, who dropped to ninth place below Afghanistan. In the year 1910-11 further changes took place in the pro portions of total trade to and from foreign countries. Russian trade fell about £150,000. British trade rose nearly £1,000,000. Turkish trade fell £70,000. French trade rose £100,000. Italy fell to 9th place and her trade decreased £100,000. Germany rose another place, and her trade increased £ 100 , 000 . Austria-Hungary rose one place with an increase of £50,000. Belgium and Oman came next above Italy with a total trade f £171,864, and £150,507, respectively. Imports usually exceed exports in Persia. In the years 1908-1911 the excess rose from £925,541 to £2,181,614. In 1911-12, British and Indian trade with Persia was reported to stand at 5.| millions ; Russian trade at 11 millions. The trade of South Persia was in 1914 still almost exclusively Trade of South- in British hands, though from 1911 onwards Germany, h? era Persia. means of subsidies, had been endeavouring to capture a large share of the trade. In 1911-12, out of a total trade of *1,601,551 to and from Bushire port, the proportions with foreign countries, were :— United Kingdom India .. Germany Turkey 1910-11. . 37 per cent. . 32 . 5 • H China (mcstly exports).. 4 1911-12. 43 per cent. 22 „ 7 „ » 8$ „ The trade of the Bushire Consular district is about equal to that of the Muhammareh and Bandar Abbas districts combined (vide Customs). The chief ports, in order of importance, are Bushire» Muhammareh, Bandar Abbas. Lingeh, Chakbar Qishm&gt;Minab, Dilwar, and Tahiri. These have an annual trade to the value of over £14,000. According to the trade report of Bushire 1012-13 there was a general revival of trade during the latter half of that period. The trade of Bushire (imports £,100,000, and exports £700,000, approximately) passed the record of 1907-08. The trade of other ports in 1912-13 was:—• Muhammareh 1,036,870. Bandar ‘Abbas £685,391. Lingeh, £ 389,589. Great Britain and India accounted for 70 per cent, of the im ports and 61 per cent, of the exports. 3. Resources. — Trade, Nushki Route. —On May 15th, 1914, it was reported from Quetta that the Nushki trade of 1914, had beaten all records by over five lakhs. Not the least satisfactory feature of the returns for the past five years was the steadiness of the increase. The figures are as follows:— 1909-10 « •M .. Rs. .. 23,99,449 1910-11 .. .. .. 26,87,227 1911-12 .. . . . . .. 37,56,334 1912-13 .. .. . . .. 46,40,170 1913-14 « «. .. 51,62,376 Page 173 .—After paragraph 6, insert the following t — According to a report made in 1913 by M. Brouard, a French engineer who spent many years prospecting in Persia, the distribution of minerals in the Northern and Western portions of the country is as follows. It is uncertain, however, as to what extent this report can be relied on:— Gold .—Alluvial and reef gold 30 miles west of Astaneh* Gold bearing pyrites in the neighbourhood of Tabriz and Zinjan, in the Kuh Sahand. The richest gold district is, however, along the Kalu River in Azarbaijan, the tract being roughly 120 miles long by 80 miles broad. Another important gold field is on the Jagatu River (east of the Kalu R.); and other deposits exist in the vicinity of Miandoab near LakeUrumieh, in the Sain Kaleh mountains of the same district and also near Hamadan. Copper is to be found in large quantities in the Shemran Kuh (about 6 miles north of Tehran), in the Kara Dag Moun tains, and at Miandoab. In the neighbourhood of Zinjan (on the road from Tehran to Tabriz) native copper ore is found in large reefs. Galena .—Large deposits exist on the northern slopes of the Elburz Mountains to the south of Resht: also on the road from Tehran to Ispahan, in a large stretch of Tertiary rock Native silver nuggets are also said to have been found at Ardebil, west of Astara. Iron.—Large deposits lie between Kazvin and Tehran containing as much as 70 per cent, metal with hardly anv trace of sulphur and phosphorus. . Manganese.—An extensive managanese ore body in the vicinity of Kirman. The pyrolusite yields an average of 40 per cent, metal. Turquoise.—A rich new turquoise-bearing bed is reported to have been discovered by M. Bronard on the old road from Tehran to Hamadan, in an old red sandstone formation near Saveh. Mercury. South of Zinjan native mercury and cinnabar have been found, close to the gold deposits already mentioned Borax .—Near Kirman. Asbestos .—Near Kirman. A ntimonv. Native antimony in Aragh, between Sultan- abad and Burujird. Bitumen.—A four-mile deposit of bitumen, 5 feet deep * nd &lt;i f f e T a ^ P urit Jb sported along the top of Tope Khazab in the i\uil 3/13 Bock Salt.—To the north-east of Tabriz. . J^nite.—15 miles south-west of Hamadan, an extensive bed 8™? ^ analysis 18 per cent, water and 56 per cent, carbon Another bed also reported near Tabriz. . Goal—A large coalfield between Kazvin and Tehran in the immediate neighbourhood of the iron body pre/iously men tioned. Another important coalfield with a great future beforeit is to English and it v price am Oil- Tied Russian I Tabriz b value tba The si in a souti immense Paqt* 1ml Theoi as the enb for Great which has sources of i %. Persia t are in a be trend of th Ahmadi ne at Maidai Shirinwhil ed at Whi; Ahmadi, ] places. Ir man, Mr, ] except in Astarabad, Vizier was sion it was sterling in P« cent, ui 60 years fro SUOGSR13 p' 13 ^ cated m ^{ l0 Gisakan Kuh, about 40 miles from Eushire. English coal sells at that port at from 40s. to 45s. per ton and it would be possible to sell Persian coal at one-half the price and yet make a profit on the transaction. Oil. — There are two distinct areas. extreme north of Azarbaijan, along the Russian frontier, the general trend being from the north-west of &gt;* 1 ^ Thl8 de P°sit is considered to - be of oreater value than the Baku fields of the Trans-Caucasus. The second area is from, and including, the Kuh Jahak in a south-easterly direction to the Persian Gulf. This field has immense possibilities. Page 174.—Delete information under heading “Oilfields ”. Insert the following :— JP 16 od reso urces of the country deserve special mention, as the enterprise has assumed an aspect of national importance u- . tain in connection with the urgent necessity which has arisen for earmarking and assuring ourselves of sources of supply of oil sufficient for the needs of His Majesty’s Oil fields. Persia abounds in petroleum springs ; but the richest sources are in a belt from the Diala River in Kurdistan, following the trend of the mountains on the southern slopes and plains, to Ahmadi near Bandar Abbas. Oil has been found in quantity at Maidan-i-Naphtun and has also been proved at Qasr- bffirin whilst surface indications of petroleum have beenobserv- ed at White Oil Springs (near Ram Hormuz), Qishm, Daliki Ahmadi, Rudan, Champa Kuh, Jask, and numerous other places. In 1901, the Persian Government granted an English man, Mr. D’Arcy, the exclusive right to bore for oil in Persia except m the provinces of Azarbaijan, Gilan, Mazandaran,’ Astarabad, and Khorasan. These were excepted, as the Grand Vizier was afraid of giving umbrage to Russia. In the conces- sion R was agreed to pay the Persian Government £20,000 sterling in cash, £20,000 sterling in paid up shares, and 16 per cent, of the annual nett profits. The concession runs for 60 years from the 28th May 1901. SITOGSHAd Concessio the acqui and the For guart also alloi The A are now 1 The Com square m examinee entirely I north-eas east of S conveved materials a difficult situated 6 inches i thence to 1.000 tons will enable White Oil fnl. withoi -i-Naphtra miles apar miles for t pressure w leakage. ' there is tel and the re the workii storage at hare a cap will he for hank near alongside only 18 fee cargo from expected th to a consid'14 An agreement was made between Messrs. D’Arcy and Concessions Syndicate, Limited, and the Bakhtiari Khans for the acquisition of the necessary land, erecting buildings, etc., and the guarding of the works and the projected pipe line.' Loi guarding these the Khans were to be paid £3,000; they were also allotted 3 per cent, of the shares fully paid up. The Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited, capital £2,000,000* are now the legal successors of Mr. D’Arcy and his associates. The Company’s concession covers an area of some 500,000 square miles and only a very small'portion has so far been examined. The Company’s production is at present obtained entirely from the Maidan-Naphtun area Iving 140 miles north- north-east of Mohammerah and about 30 miles east-south east of Shustar. From Maidan-i-Naphtun the oil has to be conveyed 150 miles by pipe line to the refinery at Abadan and materials have to be transported to the field by river and across a difficult tract of country by road. The pumping station is situated at Tembi, 2^- miles from the field. The pipe line is 6 inches in diameter as far as Wais (53 miles), and 8 inches thence to Abadan, and has an estimated capacity of about 1,000 tons per dav. The greater size of the pipe line from Wais will enable considerable quantities of oil to be carried from the White Oil Springs and Ahwaz, if the borings there are success ful. without reducing the quantity being carried from Maidan- -i-Naphtun. The pipe line is provided with gate valves 10 miles apart and stations have been placed at intervals of 20 miles for the purpose of keeping an hourly record of the pressure with a view to detecting and avoiding any loss by leakage. The line is patrolled from each of these stations and there is telephonic communication between the field, the stations and the refinery at Abadan. About 75 men are required for the working of the pumping station and pipe line. The total storage at the refinery, completed, and under construction will have a capacity of nearly 110,000 tons, of which 60.000 tons will be for crude oil. A steel jetty has been built on the river bank near the refinery having a depth of 25 feet of water alongside at low water spring tide. Tank steamers load to only 18 feet 6 inches at the pier and take the remainder of their cargo from lighters below the bar of the Shatt-ul-Arab. It is expected that it will eventually be possible for vessels to load to a considerably greater depth at the refinery.15 ♦ Tlie present workings are entirely unrter the charge of British subjects : the skilled labour is mainly recruited from India, while the unskilled labourers are, in accordance with a provision of the concession, largely Persians and no difficulty has hitherto been experienced in securing an adequate supplv. The agreements with the Khans for the policing of the field works and upper section of the pine line, and with the Shaikh of Mohammerah for the same work in connection with the refinery, and the lower section of the pipe lino, have been carried out loyally with satisfactory results. The material bene fits obtained by the peasants in the form of regular employ ment and medical attention have had a considerable effect in producing a condition of tranquillity amongst a hitherto disturbed population. At first a small guard of Indian Infantry was kept at the oilfields; this was withdrawn in 1911 as the Bakhtiaris were performing their guard duties satisfactorily. Under the terms of the agreement with the British Govern ment the Anglo-Persian Oil Company is authorised to increase its Ordinary Chare Canital by the issue of 2,000,000 additional Ordinary Shares of £1 each. These shares are taken uo by the Government and the Government in addition subscribe £1,000 in Preference Shares and £199,000 in First Debentures. In consideration of this financial support, conditions were made to secure that the Government had a voice, in the direction ot the Company’s general policy, and in the general supervision of the future development of the Concession. Vaqe 775.—Under paragraph headed 'Miscellaneous,' insert as first item (prior to “ the Castor oil plant'), the follow- mg:—-' Fisheries .—It is estimated that the annual value of the- Caspian Fisheries amounts to £3,153,000.Page, 213. Cossack Brigade.’ 1 At the end of the first paragraph delete the words “as follows ”; also delete from the Words “ In 1894 ” on the same page down to the word “ Kho- tasan ” on page 214, and substitute the followng In 1894 the Brigade consisted of 450 men. In 1899 the strength was raised to 1,300 men. Page 214.—Add at bottom of page : Persian Cossack Brigade.—On March 18th, 1914, Major Steel as^oHows^— PerSian C ° SSack Bri g ade wa? nominally organized 4 Regiments of Cavalry, of 2 squadrons of about 100 men 4 Companies of infantry of 100 men. 3 batteries (1 horse and 2 mountain) of about 90 men. 1 machine gun detachment (2 maxims).There were also 716 pupils at the Cossack School in Tehran. The infantry were armed with the “ 3 line, 51 1904 pattern, Russian rifle, the cavalry with the single loading Berdan rifle! The horse battery had 4 Schneider—Creusot 7 • 5 C. M. Q. F. guns with shields, as also had one of the mountain batteries. The other mountain battery was armed with one old and in! efficient gun. The training of the brigade was practically limited to parade ground exercises, and these were not good. The men were of good physique, but that was all that could be said for them. As a fighting force the brigade was negligeable, except against Persians, and its sole raison d’etre was as a Russianizino- influence. The Russian officers were wanting in energy, military qualifications, and social standing. Page 215.—After the first paragraph ending with the word information for Russia’ 2 add :— In December 1913, the Persian Government agreed to increase the strength of the Cossack Brigade from 2 ,400 to 4,500 men, with three or more additional Russian officers. The pay of the Brigade to be raised to the level of that of the Gendarmerie. In 1914, the Headquarters of the Cossack Brigade were, as always hitherto, at Tehran : and detachments of the Brigade were at Hamadan, Sinneh, Kirmanshah, Qasr-i-Shirin, Tabriz Resht, Sauj Bulagh. ’ Page 224.—At end of first paragraph ending with words “ throughout the provinces”, insert the table of ordnance, etc., attached herewith:—19 Enclosure No. 4. ORDNANCE AMMUNITION, ETC., PERSIAN GOVERN MENT, 1914. Table showing number and present distribution of the more or less effective ordnance in the possession of the Persian Government, dune 1914. Place or Corps. Schneider-Creu- sot. 75 wm, Utchatius (Austnan). Field (Q.F.) Mount. 7 cm. 8 cm. 9 cm. Maxims. In Tehran (reserve) 23 5 6 4 u 1 Gendarmerie 3 2 5 Cossack Brigade 4 4 • • Azerbaijan 2 *19 ’ 4 Astrabad .. 1 5 Resht and Enzeli : .. 4 Zendjan .. 9. Kirmanshah .. 2 Isfahan .. Kirman .. .. 1 • • Sulfcanabad Shahrud .. • • Khorasan and Seistan 2 Yezd Ears, etc .. 8 ’*2 'l Totals .. 82 16 1 73 | 21 20 23 The 12 maxim guns in the possession of the Gendarmerie ar of 8 mm. calibre and were obtamed m They are of the most up to date German pat tern and are complete with pack saddles for guns and ammunition and are on nVcrn rem f inin g H maxim guns are those mentioned on page ZKJ of the Military Report on Persia, 1911. It is doubtful whether half the guns (not with the Gendar merie or Cossack Brigade) are fit for service. It is reported that 2 of the Schneider mountain guns in reserve at Tehran are complete in every way, and efforts are now being made to obtain them for the Gendarmerie. One of the maxim guns, shown above as in reserve at Tehran, has been recently handed over to the 6th Regiment of the Government Gendarmerie at Isfahan.20 Importation of arms, etc., by Persian Government. I am informed by the Minister of War that the following arms and ammunition have been imported since those mentioned on page 227 of the Military Eeport on Persia, 1911 ; 1909. Russian 5 “ shot u (3 line ? ) rifles Cartridges for above Cartridges for Mauser-maxims 7,000 3,500,000 22,000 1911. Cartridges for Russian rifle Cartridges for Rebel rifle Cartridges for Mauser-maxims 1,000,000 300,000 1,000,000 1912. • 8mm Mauser-maxims for Gendarmerie with pack equipment complete .. • 8mm Mauser carbines for Gendarmerie Cartridges for above 12 6,000 1,000,000 1913. * 303 Lee-Motford rifles (from Government of India) .. •303 cartridges (from Government of India) ■303 catridges (taken over from Central India Horse at Shiraz, March 1913) 1,000* 3,70,720* 187,040 1914. cTl 16 ‘ P ® 1 : sian Government has decided to take 1900 Lee- Jimfield carbines from India for the Government of Pars, but tneir arrival has not yet been reported. si’f.afssansr sa, 0 'rsT 1 “i, ihi * 10U) *' SOb *‘ l ‘™ 1Ua * »»mport to Seistan. I'Lii co?rMt“i S Arms and Ammunition. Importation into Northern Pemo—On May 31$t 1914 it was reported that the Persian Government had been permitted Snnnn ’ T °r f duty ’ fr ° m Baku ’ 11 ’ 000 Mauser rifles and ciUU,000 rounds of ammunition (IST).\ 21 Page 234. —Paragraph headed “ Tehran,®* delete the last sentence, and insert as follows :— The force remains under the command of its own Chiefs, but draws pay from Government. In 1913, it was decided further to reduce the number of the force to 300. Page 236, delete the present entry against Kain and Sistan and substitute — *' Sistan and the Kainat. The forces in this province, which was separated, in 1914, from Khorasan, are in a state of transi tion. The budget for 1914 provided for the following establish ment :—■ Cavalry—• 250 horsemen. 150 camel sowars. Artillery—■ 1 artillery instructor. 58 artillerymen. Infantry—1 inspector 4 military instructors. 700 infantry. 700 M. L. E. rifles and 150,000 rounds of ammunition were imported from India via Robat, in 1914, for the use of this force. Page 237. — At end of paragraph headed “ Kirmanshah add the following :—- In December 1912 it was reported that the forces at the immediate disposal of the Governor consisted only of —“ 250 soldiers (armed with Wrendl rifles): and 250 levies and 100 Mujahids (armed with repeating rifles). The tribes, on the other hand, were reported to have thou sands of modern rifles. S170GSB22 Page 240. —At end of paraggaph which is headed “ Shiraz and which ends with the words “ by numerous desertions ad* the following :—• Note .—In October 1913, it was reported from Tehran that the Persian Government had sanctioned the formation of a small regular force of about 1,000 men for the Governor-General of Pars. Page 241.—Insert in 5th paragraph page S*1 after sentence ending “ Baluchis, who are now virtually independent. 11 Arms and Ammunition. — Kirman. —On* 24th May 1914, it was reported from Bushire that there were in Kirman pro vince four guns, seven centimetre calibre, and one nine-centi metre. Of the former one was in Rafsinjan, one was in Bam- The remaining breech loaders were unserviceable and beyond repair. The nine-centimetre gun was in Kirman city and was unsuitable for hilly work. Pages 242-43.—Delete paragraph headed “ Regular forces available to oppose an advance from Bushire. 11 Page 247.—kt the end of Chapter, insert the following In 1912 and 1913 no progress appears to have been made with the Reformed Army, and even the portions previously form ed have ceased to exist. On two Or three occasions during these two years the Cabinet brought out schemes for raising an army, but owing partly to an empty treasury and partly to Russian obstruction, nothing was done. Page 247. —Following the addition to end of Chapter V given on the preceding page, insert the attached article on “ Gendar&gt; merie. 1123 * Gendarmerie. Development. —In August 1911 three Swedish officers, under Gendarmerie. Colonel Hjalmersen, arrived at Tehran to take over the duty of re-organising the Persian Gendarmerie. The previous ‘ Road ’ and ‘ Treasury ’ Gendarmeries were amalgamated. In March 1912 Colonel Hjalmersen produced a scheme for the organisation of the Gendarmerie on a territorial system, in three commands of five battalions, with a total strength of 20 Swedish officers, 2,280 foot and 850 horse. The headquarters of the various battalions to be at Tehran .(2 Battalions). Shiraz, Kazvin and Isfahan. The force was to be divided into permanent garrisons of posts and moveable columns. At this time the strength of the Gendarmerie was 10 Swedish officers, 2 American officers, and 1,200 Persian officers and men. The organisation of the Tehran battalion was complete and that of the battalion at Shiraz in progress. Colleges of Instruction for officers and men were opened at Tehran (Yusufabad) in April 1912. In October 1912 a further re-organisation was approved. This new organisation held good in 1914. See table in Tehran, f In February 1913 the British Government advanced £100,000 to the Persian Government for the maintenance of the Gendarmerie in Ears. Military. — Gendarmerie, General .—On April 7th, 1914. it was stated in Parhament that the question of extending the Gendarmerie in Northern Persia was being amicably discussed between the British, Russian, and Persian Governments. Organisation .—The Kazvin, Tehran and Pars Commands were to be known as the 1st, 2nd and 3rd Regiments respec tively. Each regiment was to consist cf one or more battalions of trained men for duty on roads, with a depot battalion for training recruits. The strength of each battalion was about 300 to 400 men, and the depots had accommodation and staff for training 500 recruits. The 2nd Regiment at Tehran was to have a treasury com pany, strength 190, attached to it for collecting revenue in the Tehran district. N At the head of each regiment is a senior officer with full administrative responsibility. He is assisted by a second-in-command who is responsible for training and has an assistant for each of the mounted and dismounted services. Supply and Medical Services are organised under Persian officers ; the former under officers, who originally served with the Persian Army, the latter under Persian Medical officers, who have had six to eight years 1 experience in Europe. At the close of 1912 there were 21 Swedish officers and 2,892 Persian officers and men on the strength. The cost of the Gendarmerie in November 1912 was about £ 6,000 per mensem. At the end of 1913 it had risen to £ 20,000 or £25,000 per mensem. The following extensions of posts were made in 1913 In * ro g ressm1913 ' the north on the Meshed road to Samnan. In the west to Qum and Passangan, and to Sultanabad and Hamadan. Kirman- shah was to be taken over in 1914. On the Kazvm-Rasht road as far as Manjil, and on the Kazvin-Tabriz road as far as Smjan. The nucleus of the Isfahan Regiment was being organised at Tehran, and was to go to Isfahan at the beginning of 1914. In the south posts had been established on the whole Bushire- Shiraz road in December 1913, and northwards from Shzraz to Ahadeh in August 1913. The 4th Kirman Regiment arrived at Kirman in October 1913. Active 0 era*' In spite of lack of funds the Gendarmerie has been almost Wona&gt; uniformly successful. It has gained much experience from several fights with tribesmen, notably on the Bushire-Shiraz road, where twice in December 1913 and February 1914 near Kazarun, the inhabitants rose in force against it The Gendar merie, on both occasions, though hard pressed, held out till re inforcements arrived. In August 1913 the Gendarmerie had a fight with the Bakh- tiaries in Tehran, and succeeded in disarming the latter in Sep tember 1913, and again in March 1914 a party of gendarmes defeated some Lurs near Burujird. In February 1914 a party of gendarmes attacked a force of Baluch raiders near Bam (Kirman), and though obliged to break off the fight for want of ammunition forced the raiders to with draw from their position. Gendarmerie, Luristan.—On March 18th 1 914 Major Steel reported that 400 gendarmes under Major Holler had left25 Tehran on February 16th, with orders to establish itself at Buru* jird. The remainder of the expedition for Luristan, under Major Skjoldebrand, left for Burujird on the 8th, 10th and 14th March, The total strength of the expedition was— 6 Swedish officers. 639 infantry. 624 mounted men 2 mountain guns. 4 maxims. This force included the 6th Regiment which was destined for Isfahan, and also a squadron made up from the officers and non-commissioned officers schools at Tehran. This squadron was reported to be very efficient. S170GSB28 From the very outset the Swedish officers of the Gendar merie have done excellent work. They are keen perservering and capable : brave almost to a fault, receiving their first set back on that account near Shiraz in August 1912. They are thoroughly imbued with the offensive spirit, and have always sought out and attacked their foe. They are very friendly with the British representatives, who help them in every way, and have an influence in shaping their policy. They receive scant encouragement from the Russians, however, as the latter are jealous of their success. Their one fault is a want of knowledge of the people and the language, and this sometimes leads them to tactless or foolish dealings. By sheer good and 'loyal work, however, they have gained the confidence of and popularity with the Persian Government and the people. The Persian officers are not so satisfactory. If left to them selves they practise tyranny and extortion, and are apparently not a match for tribesmen, when left without Swedish leaders. ' At first some recruits of a poor stamp, the riff-raff of Tehran, were enlisted ; but later as the force became more popular, partly owing to regularity in the receipt of pay, better classes have been enlisted. Recruits for the 1st Regiment are not obtained from the neighbourhood of Tehran, but are mostly Kurds. Turks from Azerbaijan, with a few men from near Kazvin, and a few Bakh- tiaries. The 2nd Regiment recruits from districts south of Tehran including Yeramin. Neither regiment takes any men from the towns. There is no standard of height but a careful medical examination is carried out. The men are short, averag ing 5'4', but are generally thickest and sturdy and give the impression of being good material. There is no difficulty in obtaining recruits. A new system is being tried, and appears to be answering well, by which in some cases the men bring their own ponies. Several headmen have produced batches of recruits under these conditions. Men bringing their own horses receive 1 toman per mensem in addition to the usual pay of 3J tomans for the hire of their horses. Men of different classes are mixed indiscriminately and are liable for servica throughout Persia. They agree to serve for three years. Officers. Recruiting29 In Fars some success has attended the eff rt to enlist tufangchis and nomad tribesmen. At other places also, local enlistment is practised. The cavalry and infantry in Fars, in 1913, were both armed with a light German Mauser carbine, cahbre 8 millimetre, of which they had 550, with 400 rounds per rifle, and a reserve of 18,000 rounds. It is a very handy weapon and is sighted up to 1800 metres. The maxim gun is of the same cahbre. In April 1913 500 ? rifles and — ? rounds of ammunition were taken up to Shiraz from Bushire. The mountain guns are 7J centimetre Schneider (Austrian) guns. 300 rounds for these guns were taken to Shiraz in April 1913, and, in August 1913,200 shrapnel and 200 common shell were supplied by His Britannic Majesty’s Government. On this latter occasion some explosives for demohshing towers were also supplied. Gendarmerie, Fars and Kirman .—On 6th April 1914 the Resident, Bushire, reported that 900 cases of arms and am munition, of which 790 contained cartridges, had been imported in a German Steamer by the gendarmerie for Kirman and Shiraz. They were presumably all German goods. Uniform .—The imiform consists of a blue tunic for winter and garrison duties with a sheepskin waistcoat fer winter and duty on the roads, thin blue cotton trousers with khaki putties. In the summer men wear a khaki blouse and in the winter a thick blue cloth great coat for all duties including drill. A white lambskin cap is worn for garrison duties m the winter and there is a brown lambskin cap for service. Brown felt helmets are kept for summer use, but these have been strongly objected to by the mullahs and in consequence, by some of the men. Officers .—The officers school is situated in Tehran, there is accommodation for 40 officers. Officers are trained there for general service in any quarter of Persia. They are selected from good families and must be between 18 and 25 years of age. Before going to the officers school, officers have to serve for 6 months in the ranks at the ‘ school ’ of the Regiment. They then do 6 months on the roads and go to the school if found satis factory in every way. The course lasts a year and comprises gymnastics, fencing, simple tactical lessons, georgapny, mathe matics, and practical drill, manoeuvre, stable duties, etc., and S170GSB Armament. Uniform 1 raining.*11 ■KW? ,11 matter [ration oi t The non sccotnmoda horses. Th (hose ffho 1 Offing t&lt; Gendarmerie driEofthej lestmowmei fire to bear The four are organise! officer who w Army. The a mounted am The very bes Pa&lt;/e The Pers: Ilitary Rej existence wil the lack ofm The Govi vinces keep i toby theexi to such an e any satisfac no training, hare found i At the a is subjoined Thetota ‘greater def30 all matters connected with the interior economy and adminis tration of the Gendarmerie. The non-commissioned officers school is also in Tehran and Non-Commis- accommodation has been provided for 150 to 160 men and 200 S10ned oncers, horses. The course lasts six months. Men are selected from those who have seen service on the roads. Men .—Recruits are trained at Regimental Headquarters. Owing to the ever increasing road responsibilities of the Gendarmerie it is impossible to give the men more than about 4 months training before sending them out. They are in structed in drill, attack formations and musketry. The drill of the mounted gendarmerie is restricted to the simp lest movements and aims at no cavalry tactics but at getting fire to bear as quickly and efficiently as possible. The four machine guns at present with the 2nd Regiment detachment are organised into a battery and are commanded by a Persian officer who was formerly chief of the General Staff of the Persian Army. The ammunition has the pointed bullet. The detachment is mounted and the guns and ammunition are carried on mules. The very best men are selected for service with the detachment. Page 24k. — Insert .—■ The Persian Army, as described on pages 218 to 247 of this Military Report on Persia, has slowly but surely faded out of existence with the advent of the Government Gendarmerie and the lack of money for all save the most vital necessities. The Governors-General and Governors of the various pro vinces keep up just so many irregular troops as they are obliged to by the exigencies of the local situation, but the numbers vary to such an extent that it is impossible even to attempt to secure any satisfactory figures concerning these “ forces. ” There is no training, and all the younger officers of any ability at all have found service with the Government Gendarmerie. At the same time, the Infantry Regiments, of which a list is subjoined, nominally exist on paper. The total numbers of Artillery, Infantry and tribal horsemen nominally borne on the rolls of the Ministry for War, are 6095, 62,600 and 19,702 respectively. As long as these men used to receive their six months pay and were under more or less capable officers, they were always ready to respond to orders for embodiment, and there was never a greater deficit than from 100 to 150 men in the numbers of eachThe present number of the old “ Sarbaz ”, etc., which now (July 1914) form the “ garrison ” of Tehran are as follows :— Officers and artillerymen (employed in looking 264 after the old and useless artillery in the “ gun square ” etc. Demavend Regiment, employed as guards, etc., 270 at residences. Hamidan Regiment, employed as guards, etc., 112 at residences. Bands .. .. .. .. .. 120 Commissariat, etc. .. .. .. jg Guards of the Russian Consulate .. .. 41 Total .. 825 The following are the Guards at the Palace :— Imperial Guards 192, Zarand Regiment 151, Bodyguard 104, total 447. Pajrc 24:9 .—At the end of Chapter VI add the following :— The British Navy has for over a century undertaken the policing of the Persian Gulf, the suppression of piracy, and the maintenance of lighting and buoying. In connection with the Arms Traffic during 1908—14, there were usually four of His Majesty’s ships and four or five armed launches in the Persian Gulf or on the Mekran Coast. Vagt 255 .—At the end of the fourth paragraph ending with the words “ for extension ”, add the following :— Russian Officers in 1913-14 paid frequent visits to Kalat-i- Nadiri, and it was said they intended taking it over.Page 283. At end of paragraph headed “Aatarabad Bay , add :— u Note^—lt is reported that shoaling in the S.-E. Caspian is proeeedmg to a marked degree. At Chikishliar for example (N. of Astarahad Bay) steamers are compelled to lie 2 or 3 mile- further out than was the ease 5 years ago. (April 1913 ) • F ? ge J 92 /~ After Paragraph headed “ Entrance to Harbour 1 insert the following :— ^ ’ Lighting.—The following harbour lights have been hshed (1913) oa the Town Residency flagstaff :_one white lighi visible 13 mdes: one red light visible llj miles. Also the beacon on Ras-al-Marg in the inner harbour has been re-established» the beacon is 15 feet above the town. -* Page 29&amp;. Paragraph “ Shamals”, after the words “ their passage ashore add the following : Stores, provided the Shamal is not blowing can be landed at Bushire all the year round : but troops cannot well be landed between April and October on account of the extreme heat. A heavy swell sets in about a month below the monsoon. f &gt; l Page Jn 2 '~nJ ter y!' he sentenoe depth is about 9 fathoms (line 7), add :— A coal depot was established at Hanjam Island in June 1912 when 1,000 tons of coal were unloaded by using lighters, which were beached eastward of the Ras-al-Marg beacon. Page 312, Line 8.—Delete the sentence commencing “ The principal authority” and ending “Persian sovereignty”, and substitute the following:— 1 The principal authority here is the Arab Shaikh, all traie of Persian sovereignty has disappeared for some years (1911), S170GSB59 The above scheme has been carried out (May 1914) with the exception of Item No. 6, concerning the building of which nego tiations are being carried on with the Persian Government. A store depot has been established on Abbadan Island, the necessary land being leased from the Anglo-Persian Oil Com pany, which has undertaken to supply the oil necessary for lighting purposes. A lightship tender is expected to arrive in October 1914. In addition to the lighting arrangements already mentioned, beacons are maintained at Kuwait (Ras-al-Arz), Bushire (Ras- al-Marg), Jask, Hanjam, Basidu, Chahbar and Kubbar Island. The erection of beacons at Khor Kalijah and Halul are being taken in hand. Naval and Maritime.— Lighting and Buoying .—On June 16th 1914, His Majesty*s Government sanctioned noti fication being made to foreign consuls of the lights and buoys recently established in the Persian Gulf. These included light houses at Tanb Island and Little Quoin, buoys at Bahrain, Bushiro, Bandar Abbas and Jask, and beacons at Kubbar Island (Kuwait), Ras-al-Marg (Bushire), Ras-al-Arz (Kuwait), Jask, Hanjam, Basidu and Chahbar. The notification regarding lights and buoys in the Shatt-ul- Arab was postponed. Page 316.—After 1st paragraph add .*—* In December 1911, when the Majlis was dissolved by the Regent, its dissolution was already overdue as it had sat for its appointed time, 2 years. No opportunity had occurred for hold ing fresh elections. All through 1912 no agitation took place for a new Majlis, and Russia was known to be unfavourable to a Majlis being convoked. At the end of 1913, however, orders issued for the holding of elections, and the Majlis was opened at the coronation of the young Shah cn July 7th, 1914. Delete from line 10 to end of page and substitute The first election regulations were drafted In September 1906, and were followed by a later electoral law on July 1st, 1909. The present electoral law (1914) came into force on the 22nd October 1911. This provides for the number of represen tatives of the people and their distribution In the provinces and40 districts. The number of deputies is fixed at 136 (of whom 15 are for Tehran). The qualifications for electors are as follows: They must be Persian subjects, at least 20 years old, and maa have resided for at least 6 months in the electoral area. The following are disqualified from votmg Women, minors, “heretics’ 1 , fraudulent bankrupts, disreputable P« r9 °n 8 » criminals and persons who have been known to oppose the constitution. In addition, persons in military, police or genda - 'mploy Deputies (with the exception of the representatives of fJ d whom special provision is made), Persian subjects, be able to ' ead and write not under 30 or over 70 years of age, of good repu- tation and known in their electoral areas. Women, military and police officials, governors or deputy governors, e ro- thers P or uncles of the Shah, bankrupts, criminal, men of bad renutation^rwho are known to be opposed to the constitution are debarred from election. The elections ar ® ^ Anv number over half of the total number of deputies, presen fa Tehran, constitute a quorum. The’ duration of the Ma]l s is to be two years, and three month, \h\expmy of that period, the proclamation for new ekeW is Natural ^a' A—n, Tud srci Sam Amenian;. the Zorctriens, and the Jews have each one representative. r t this law was modified by the Electoral Law In January 19io . , , ^ vp a v ote a man must have o7£ 100and pay a tazoflO ehillinge per annum. ,, imo j i qi q mnch discussion took place regarding During 191 | arid f ® the pe r8 i a n Cabinet decided that the a Senate. In May 19 mberg 30 appointed by the Shah Stor be 0 e C Sed on ^ °f ^ a Senate.41 Page. 317.—Insert just above the paragraph beginning “ On the 31st August 1907 — That the affairs of the Persian Majlis are taking a turn for the better is shown by the result of the elections held in Tehran on February 1914. Most of the 12 deputies elected were Moderates, there was only one Democrat and among the remainder the ecclesiastical element was strongly represented—a satisfactory indication of the growing sobriety of public opinion m the capital. On the other hand the Russian Consuls are said to have obstructed the elections held in Azarbaijan and Isfahan dunng May and June and in several places the candidates had to be nominated instead of elected, as there were no means of holding elections. Page 317.—Delete from “ The two chief leaders ” to the end of the second ^paragraph “ second basis ” and substitute the follow ing “The urgent need for reform has been recognised for a long Foreign Officials time and various attempts have been made by the employment for^assas^nce^ of foreign advisers to improve matters. Monsieur Bizot, a dis- intervention in tinguished French official, was appointed Financial Adviser thejtdministra- in February 1908 and arrived at Tehran in March of that year. He left Persia after a two years’ stay, having entirely failed to bring about any improvement. The second Majlis decided m September 1910 to apply to the United States for Financial Assistants and to Italy for Gendarmerie Instructors. The American Government recommended Mr. Shuster but the Ita Government refused to accede to the Persian Government s request. Persia eventually applied to Sweden, and obtained th^ services of General Hjalmarsen, who arnvedm Tehran in July 1911 with two other officers. Mr. Shuster and ^ assistants arrived in Mav 1911. On May 30th and June 13th, 1911, various laws were passed by the Majlis pving Mr. Stater very full powers os an executive official and full control of all Govem- ment expenditure. Mr. Shuster was only eight months in Persia. He has published an account of the events which led to dismissal, in consequence of the Russian ultimatum to ersi S170GSB42 / November 29tla, 1911, in bis book entitled “ Tbe Strangling of Persia. ” The Persian Government finally accepted the Russian terms on December 24th, 1911, on which day the second Majlis was dissolved after a session of 25 months. Monsieur Mornard, a Belgian official, formerly Director of Customs, was appointed Acting Treasurer-General on January, 8th, 1912, and endeavour ed to carry out the mission Mr. Shuster had set before him. His functions were executive, and he endeavoured to introduce the much needed reforms in the finances of the country. He had a large staff of Belgians under him and conducted the financial administration nominally under the direction of the Minister o Finance, but in practice independently of that official He had representatives in all the provincial capitals, who collected the revenues independently of the local Governors. alter, when appointed, were obliged to come to terms with the Treasur er-General as to the salaries they and their subordinates would receive and the sum of money to be allowed to them for the up keep of their forces and other local services. This was called the provincial budget. In July 1914 M. Mornard resigned and left Persia owing to Russian action in opposing his collecting taxes in Northern Persia. On the 31st August 1907 the Anglo-Russian Convention was signed and the “ Russian ”, “ British ” and “ Neutral zones were created, and in March 1912 the Persian Government under took, as one of the conditions of a joint Anglo-Russian advance of £200,000, to act in conformity with the principles ol the Convention. One of the conditions of the Russian ultimatum of November 1911 was that “ the Persian Government must un dertake not to engage foreigners without the previous consent o the Russian and British Legations. ’ ’ One of the effects of engagements is that in practice the Persian Govemmen is n obliged to consult the Russian Legation before appointing dismissing any provincial Governor in the Russian Zone, and the British Legation has to be consulted m a like manner as to British Zone. Most of the Neutral Zone is at present treated as if it were the British Zone, but the situation is by no means a satisfactory one in this respect, and e w 10 e 9“ ~ of the “ zones ” is likely to be readjusted m the near future.43 In 1914 the foreigners employed by ■were as follows :—- American Austrian — Belgian British ~ Trench — German • • Swedish Swiss ~ the Persian Government 1 1 ~ 57 ~ ..4 - 10 .. 1 .. 34 1 Total .. 1°9 Page- $18, Line 24.—Delete from “ These officers who are responsible ” to the bottom of the page. Page 319.—Delete whole page down to “ Swarm round offi cials.” . Delete in paragraph “Nomad tribes” “ all of these being res- ponSble to P the 8 Governor of the Province’’ and “ ah of these being nominally responsible to the Financial Age t of the Province Paae 320.—Paragraph on “ Larger Provinces and Districts iThe words “ id Seistan ” a/&lt;«r “ Khorasao ' and .aaert er “Khorasan Meshed”, Sistan and Kain riand ”.44 Pagt 321.—Delttt paragraph “Administration of Justice as it now stands and substitute :—• “ Up to quite recently the dispensation of justice was al- Administration ways summary. It was, and still is, to a great extent admin- of Justice - istered by the Governors and their representatives and by the mullas and clergy, the former being guided by the ‘ urf,' the known or unwritten law, the latter by the shard’', the divine or written law based on the Quran. The most barbarous punish ments were in vogue and are still occasionally reported. The new regime, however, is endeavouring to put an end to this state of affairs. A legal code based to a certain extent on those of Europe is now under preparation, courts of justice have been established in some of the larger cities, while police magistrates, where the police have been started, deal with minor cases. Petty disputes are still settled by mayors and headmen. Page 322.—Delete the paragraph on Education and substitute the following i— There are many colleges (madraseh) throughout the country Education, supported by public funds in which students are instructed in religion and in Persian and Arabic literature as well as in a certain amount of scientific knowledge. There are also many schools for children, while private tutors are employed by all families of means. Education on modern lines is, however, in a lamentable state of backwardness and were it not for foreign enterprise, Persians would have few opportunities of obtaining that sound modern education for which they are exhibiting a very keen desire. The one exception among provincial authorities (whose indifference towards the institution by Persians themselves of means of educational development is deplorable) is the Governor of Sistan and Kain, Shaukat-ul-Mulk, whose enlightenment and public spirit are worthy of a full measure of applause and support. There are thought to be some 180 schools of various denom inations under Western supervision at work in Persia, with an aggregate of 10,000 pupils of both sexes and varying ages. Most of these schools are in the northern provinces, fewer being found in the centra) and southern areas. Of these schools the Americana45 have some 160 with 4,500 pupils (these schools are chiefly in small towns with native teachers). The American missionaries are working in Persia on the same lines as in Turkey and else where. Their best schools are in Tehran, Hamadan, Kirmanshah, Tabriz and Meshed. They are open to all comers. The Ame ricans are now urging the establishment of a college at Tehran at Tabriz. Great Britain has eight or nine schools with some 800 pupils: the principal centres are Isfahan, Yazd and Kirman, while funds are being collected for a college at Isfahan. The schools are almost restricted to Persians owing to the more pronounced religious fanaticism in the sphere of work of the English mission aries but a few Parsi and Armenian pupils are to be found in them. France has five or six schools with 800 pupils. There arc excel lent French schools under the Lazarist Fathers at Isfahan, Tehran, and Hamadan and Irench-Jewish schools (Alliance Israelite) in Isfahan, Tehran, Hamadan, and Kirmanshah. The Armenians have three or four schools with some 4,000 pupils. The Parsis have schools in Yazd and Tehran, maintain ed chiefly by their co-religionists in India. The Germans have one school with 260 pupils. This school, opened in Tehran in 1907, is subsidized by the Persian Government to the extent of £2,400 per annum. The German Government is supposed to contribute £1,000 per annum to its upkeep, but it has been stated that this obligation has never been fulfilled. Tehran schools .—The number of schools in the capital for boys is 78 and for girls 42 with 8,344 and 2187 pupils respectively. These figures include Armenian, Parsi, Jewish, Musulmanand foreign schools. These latter are (1) Alliance Israelite with some 250 boys and girls; (2) London Society for promoting the Gospel among the Jews, some 200 boys and girls ; (3) Alliance Frangaise 200 boys ; (4) St Louis (Catholic) 350 boys ; (5) the German schools 260 boys j (6) American High School for boys, 420 ; (7) American High School for girls; 300, half of whom are Armenians; (8) a Russian school of 100 boys. Page 322 continued.—Delete the remainder of page 322 and substitute the following paragraphs:— In August 1912, the Persian Government having failed to obtain the services of Police instructors from the Dutch Government succeeded in securing from Sweden a Chief Instruc tor, who has been followed by five assistants of the same nationa lity, as the service developed. The force in the capital consists S170GSB Police.4a of about 300 mounted and 1,000 foot police, while the organiza tion is now to be extended to other parts of Persia. The Tehran police are a fine body of picked men well organized, armed and equipped, and reflect the greatest credit on their Swedish instructors. For “gendarmerie” see Chapter V. Page 322—In 1914 it was intended to extend the system of Swedish supervision of police to the whole of Persia. For Gendarmerie see Chapter V, Page 323.—Delete the whole of the page, and substitute — Finance. The following loans were outstanding on March 20th 1913:— Russian Government .. 3,374,000 British Government 314,281 Russian Bank 976,100 Imperial Bank Gold Loan 1,250,000 Anglo-Indian Advance 140,000 Russian Government Advance 200,000 British Government Advance 200,000 British Government Advance for Gendar merie 100,000 6,544,1000 About £ 560,000 is^needed annually to serve these debts. It will be seen from the memorandum referred to above that the first annual statement of the revenue and expenditure of Persia is incomplete and can only form a base on which to found financial investigations. The gross revenue for the year ending March 20th 1913 is given as £2,040,000, and the payments by the Treasury amount to £1,598,000. The Government being in finan cial difficulties at the end of the year, it is evident that no part of this difference represented a surplus. Since then the Treasurer General has had to borrow from the Imperial bank of Persia which has now lent the Government £200,000 in current account, which is the limit laid down in the bank’s concession. The financial straits of the Persian Government are such at the time of writing (June 1914) that various expedients are being con sidered, including the sale of the Crown Jewels.’ 1On May 22nd 1914 the revenue returns for March 1915 and March 1914 showed an increase of over £400,000 or about 40% . These figures did not include the Customs Returns. The Minister at Tehran remarked that this satisfactory state of affairs showed that there was still economic life in the country. On May 24th the gross amounts of the Persian Customs revenue for the year ending March 20th, 1914, were reported to he as follows: Northern Revenues £683,000 or an increase of 12%. Southern Revenues £175,000 equivalent to an increase of 6% over the previous year. The total revenue amounted to £858,000 or an increase of 11%. Pages 324 and 325.—Delete the whole of page 324 and 325 down to the end of the paragraph on “ Crown Lands **. Page 326 .—Put a full stop after “ Increase ” in line 6, “delete from “ so that ” to the end of the paragraph on “ Expenditure ” substitute. The following table shows the gross customs receipts of re cent years. Place. 1009-10. 1910-11. 1911-12. Azarbaij:i^|(Tabrlz) 123,557 129,396 142,589 Caspian Sea ports— 33,405 31,843 Astara 32,089 Ghilan (Enzali) 135,522 143,195 226,954 Mazandaran (Meshed-i-Sar) 50,879 34,177 44 232 starabad (Bandar Gaz) 31,076 32,207 24,548 Khorasan (Meshed) 59.798 64,949 76,277 Southern ports.— 96,502 Bushire 82.222 65,723 Bandar’Abbas 33,407 39,189 37 568 Arabistan 40,905 61,497 64,364 Kirmanshah ?T4,265 II^SIO 91,711 Parcel post (Tehran) 20,013 43,223 24,445 Totals 723,733 763,271 861,053Pag* 327. mentioned. . -Ddete from paragraph beginning “As above • . ” to end of 7th line on page 328. Page 328.—Insert on page 328 below Bandar Abbas. Behbehan .. Agent. Page 330.—Delete present entry opposite Bushire and Jask. and insert the following :—- Bushire — 9 Indian Cavalry. Infantry, 300 men: from one battalion, the other wing of which was at Masqat in 1913. Jask —- One British offioor. 40 rank and file. Page 331—Delete present entries nnder Chahbar and Basidu and insert the following i— Chahbar —. 1 Indian officer. 32 Rank and file. Han jam—-7 7 Indian Infantry. Little Quoin — 7 Indian infantry. frnrrp 10 Ia ? ^ garrisons * Bandar Abbas, are supplied from one double company at Field Service strength. PPPage 338. Under heading ” Lynch Road “ insert on page 338 after paragraph ending “ of the peasantry.” On April 24th, 1914, it was reported that tho Persian Government had extended the time for the road conces sions held by Messrs. Lynch and Company to April 1921. This concession for constructing roads embraces the following roads:— Tehran-Ispahan. Tehran Burujird-Khurramabad- Muhammareh. Burujird-Isfahan. Isfahan-Ahwaz. The only work so far completed is Tehran-Qum, Qum- Sultanabad, and Isfahan-Ahwaz. Page 384 .—At the end of paragraph (a) ending with the words “ if required, a railway can be laid on it '* add the fol lowing :— In February 1913, it was reported from St. Petersburg that the Social6 des chauss£es de Enzeli a Tehran et de Julfa a Tabir had secured a concession for the Julfa-Tabriz railway, and the option on the extension from Tabriz to Kazwin had fallen to the Russian Discount and Loan Bank. The gauge is the standard gauge. The Julfa-Tabriz railway is, according to the above report, to be begun within two years and completed within six years, while for the extension of the line from Tabriz to Kazvin a time limit of eight years is fixed. Both works will probably be un dertaken with as little delay as possible. The branch extension from Tabriz to the N.-E.w shore of Lake Urumieh will probably be designed in such a way as to render possible the establishment of communication with the town of Urumieh on the other side of the lake. In conneotion with this extension a Russian engineer obtained permission from his Government in 1913 to arrange for a steamship service on Lake Urumieh. S170GSBPage 385, Line 3.—At end of parargaph (c) ending with the words “ is a level plain ”, insert the following: C(i) The Company for the construction of branch lines in RussianCentralAsiahave, in 1913, proposed the construction of— , (a) A line (presumably normal gauge) from the station ct Tejan on the Central Asian Railway (479 miles from Krasnovodsk) to Chacha on the Russo-Persian Frontier. The line would have a length of 59 miles. The projected line would traverse the richest portion of the Teien oasis, which exports at the present moment a consider able Quantity of grain as well as cotton, but Ihe Company reckons for their profits mainly on capturing the major portion of the caravan traffic between Meshed and Transcaspia and on diverting it from other routes, as the terminal point at Uiacfia would be little over 60 miles from Meshed by a caravan route used at the present time by both camels and mules. If it proved possible in the future to continue the line toMeshed itself the im portance of Askhabad as a commercial centre would be destroy ed. Paqe 385.—After paragraph {g) ending with the words “ difficulties in its construction” add the following paragraph . (jo i n May 1913, the Russian Government was reported to be about to construct a railway from Baku on the ^Caucasus line to Astara, on the Persian frontier. Ihis would fcim to the proposed Trans-Persian Railway. Trans-Persian Ratal/.—On March 17th, 1914 , it was reported that Imperial sanction had been given to the formation of a com- nany for the construction of a railway from Ahat, on the Trans Caucasus Railway, to Astara on the Rvsso-Persian Frontier. The line was to form the connecting link with the Trans-Persian ai - way. On May 26th, Lord Crewe stated in Parliament that the ques tion of the Trans-Persian Railway had not progressed muc . The Government, he said, had made it clear that any contm - tion towards India could not be made unless they ag^d ^nd that they were insisting upon exercising control m p51 Persian Gulf. Lord Crewe also said that from a Persian stand point, for trade development, the construction of lines inland* Cough Hne. C ° mmerCial W ° Uld be P referable - great Page 386.—After line 81, insert as follows * n J ™ e I, 913 [t was sported that the survey partv which bunt Lorn K ei ' Sla t0 i St !i ldy th ° route for new railway to be built from Khurramabad to Muhammareh had made vood nro gress, and it was hoped to complete the survey of The southern S?°ur™X try r mau] b y ‘ hs “O »* the yh^e sun ey party hope to complete their worh b y the end of the The country already surveyed is eminently suited for railwav oT£ u „t?h;m lT ide r^ difflcult y is “js O the northern section, both in respect to the character of the country and with regard to the inhabitants. The survey party is working on behalf of the Persian Railways Syndicate who, in March 1913, accepted the option offered by the On March 31st, 1914, it was reported in London that ^ p eraian Railwaya S^dicate an 0r .^ 3 nionths from the time when the state of tbo country shall permit the resumption o( the „„ rTC v „f tMr concession for the Muhammareh-Khurrumabad Railway survey Persia had also agreed to negotiate with the Syndicate ^or the separate construction of t h e fi rst portion of the line, namely co &lt; mpleted amUiare ^ ^ DlZfUl ’ the BUrV6y ° f which had bee “ Page 388.—After the first paragraph add the following “ (/) Gwatar to Kirman. This was reconnoitred and survey, ed during the cold weather of 1911-12 by Mr Johns anrl reported as follows :-The length of the C Ts 574 miles the ruling gradient 1 in 45, and the cost for a broad gauge Une t es ima ed at Rs. 8,16,43,000 and metre gauge at 6,23,92,000.52 There is no difficulty about water supply, but all labour will have to be imported. Bricks can be burnt on the coast plain, and at Bampur, while shingle can be got from the river beds ; otherwise the country is singularly devoid of building material. The Bampur plain is the only district possessing any traffic possibilities ; it is well watered by the perennial Bampur stream, as well as by numerous karezes' The soil appears fertile, and good crops of wheat, barley and beans are grown ; also, in the autumn, Indian corn pulse, cotton and rice. With a more settled form of government and better irrigation works, the cul tivated area could be enormously extended, for land and water seemed abundant. There is some export of wool and ghi, but the date groves only provide sufficient for local needs. Between the Bampur plain and the coastal ranges the popula tion is very sparse and entirely nomad, except in the main valley where there are patches of cultivation sometimes a mile in length. Grain, however, is barely sufficient for local needs, and the export of dates is inappreciable. The coastal ranges are the quite sterile as the flow of water ceases on nearing them, and below these ranges the only inhabited area worth mentioning is Dashtiari, where the Indian corn crop depends on a precarious rainfall and the overflow of the Kaju and Sarbaz rivers when in flood. Page 389 .—“ Communications by sea.” At end of the para graph which ends with the words “ every alternate week ” add the following :— Note .—In 1913, owing to a disagreement in regard to the Gov ernment subsidy, the Russian Minister of Commerce refused to renew the contract with the Caucasus and Mercury Company and has thrown the contract open to competition. The Russian Press considers that there is very little likelihood of its being taken up by any other company, and the prospect of regular Caspian navigation in the near future looks sufficiently black.53 Page. 390. After 3rd paragraph insert the following :—- On January 23rd,'1914, it was reported in London that the Hall Line of Liverpool had arranged with the Hamburg-Amerika line for a joint monthly service from British and Continental ports to the Persian Gulf. The Hall Line and Hamburg-Amerika vessels were to sail alternately monthly to the Persian Gulf. The latter were to load on the Continent, and proceed direct to the Gulf ; the Hall liners calling at Antwerp, and returning either to Glasgow and Newport or Glasgow and Manchester. 1 Page 392.—After paragraph (d) which ends with the word “ Hanjam,” insert the following ;— A oie.-—In July 1913, the British Treasury sanctioned the construction, by the British and Indian Governments, of the tele graph line Bandar Abbas to Lingah. KirmansMh to Qasr-i-Shirin.—On January 31st, 1914, it was reported from Baghdad that the telegraph line from Kirmanshah to Qasr-i-Shirin was nearly complete. (A 7 o/e.—This must refer to a repair of the line, which was probably destroyed bv Salar-ud- Bauleh in 1912-13.) 635. Azarbaijan .—In February 1914, it was reported that a telegraph line was to be built from Khoi to Maku in Azarbaijan. G. M. Frees, Simla.—No. S, 170 G. S. B—26-1-15.- 820—E.A. \</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000912.0x00009e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/20/237</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000912.0x00009e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/20/237</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'CORRECTIONS TO MILITARY REPORT ON PERSIA, 1911'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1915</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-27T22:52:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (53 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 53; these numbers are printed or written in pencil, and are located in the top centre of the recto side of each folio. The foliation sequence does not include the front cover. The back cover is missing.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume consists of corrections to the
                           Military Report on Persia(1911). This volume was produced in 1914 (1st series) by the General Staff, India.It contains corrections for sections on the country's history; geography; resources; army; naval forces; places of strategic importance and military notes; ports, harbours and islands; arms and ammunition; administration; and communications.Printed at the Government Monotype Press, Simla, 1915.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government Monotype Press, Simla, publishers</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">publisher</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Military intelligence</topic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000912.0x00009e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>