<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000361_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T13:42:50.402Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM /o^t. No . 48C-X.■ / ^ . &amp; A. / ... 'V Prom x w^' The Deputy Secretary to tie Government of India in the Foreign and olitical Department . To The Secretary to His Excellency the High Commissioner for Ira . . Dated Simla , the 13th September l •&lt;3 . roposed introduction of the Tapu system in Bahrain . Sir , In connection with the introduction of reforms in the administration of Pa lira in , the j olitical Resident in the fersian Gulf has suggested having the Islands accurately surveyed pre liminary to overhauling the e-. is ting revenue system and effectimg a registration of property. In short it is his intention to press the introduction of the Tapu System. ' Before they can consider any such innovation I am to say ti'iat the Government of India would be glad to be furnished , if His Excellency the High Commissioner sees no objection, with an appreciation of that system from the point of view of its suitability as a record of rights for revenue and otter purposes for introduction in an area where cultivation consists chiefly of date gardens. It must be borne in mind that Tapu would be a complete novelty in an Arab principality and that the chances of f inding et t icient and honest officials to work it would be problematical . I have the honour to be , Sir , Your most obedient servant, Sd/~ E. B . Howell , Deputy Secretary to the Government of India Copy to the Hon'ble the olitical Resident in -the ersian Gulf, for information.'THMi CD f U 3 )3NTTAL Th« ^ency II/2/24. From The Political Agent ,3ahrs in. To The Hon'fela th© litiof; 1 Resident,Bushire . r&amp;ndum Bahr in Hsforms. telegram Ho 239 of I9 /2/24. Proposed contract for Mr De Grenier is forwarded herewith. I do n^t cpiapatent to raaio any suggestions as to staff require for the technical work of surveying. I thinjc that an Indian officer 3.. u. with Tapu or Hevenue ^^x ^ )Qrierlce would be preferable .He would be of -i'liv; reat assist-nce to the Assistant political Agant,who ( if the propos i.^r. s aooepted by the Govornraent of India) would act as Revenue Adviser he Ruler &amp; wsuld carry out the praliraim ry records of landed prope 'i- a.A y,or rather supervise the work of th© officials engaged in it. GJ hi.. r Report withheld pending receipt of your further cormunic^tion. It was my intention to report by this mail that Mr Bower fs I had arrived «t the conclusion,that as long as Customs receipts maintair -a their present satisfactory,it would be inadvisable &amp; unnecessary to i censider an increase.The proposal was originally put forward when we h^d less experience of the results of customs reform than is now 1 o available . gtiiitx^K^jBBnEMx^*xxHM±n \ Ma^or .Political Agent.No.i^f/S, Of 1921&lt;-. ■S.v^L ■ fxt, f ■ BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERA BUSHIRE, 17th June 1924. To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. I ain directed to forward a copy of the undermentioned letter and enclosures for information and necessary action. Memorandum K0 .36 -X dated 15th April 192^ from the Government of India ( with two enclosures). By order Captain, Under ^Secr,e^ary rr to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.Copy of a Confidential letter to Khan Sahib Muharamd Shafi, .(araiehanvjala. 'fahsil, Gujrat Digtrict, Dingah i ^ost Office, Punjab, No ./jBO-X.,da tod 'elai.the lltti March I924. V/ith inference to your interviev/ v /ith I'x. Ho.;ell a short while ajyo, I am to aay that tlie Datirein State are in temiX)rary need of an Indian aevenue Surveyor dtti I 'evenua or tapu e^erienca in Iraq on a aalitry of R3.4OQ per mensem. The ai-ea to be surveyed is not very large (about 1R snuare miles) and com ifits in the ntin of date ^irciena and Luoem fields. It is not yet kno m ho.v long tee ;;ork .fill take, and the detailed terras of employment, which must be emoodied in a forrail contract, have yet to be settled. MaanrMle will you please say whether you wish to be considered for the apj/ointeisnt, and if so the date by viiich it .vould be possiole for you to proceed to Bahrein I am to add that in tse event of your accepting toe appointosnt it Wiy.it be nscessary for you to arrange for a Survey party to accompany you to Bahrain and advise as to its strength. Copy of a datji-offIcial letter fraa Khan Sahib IMiann&amp;d tabafi. Haslanwala.District Gujr&amp;t.fUnjab, to Major w.G.Neale, Additional Deputy Secretary to the Oovenrant of India in tfie Porei,??! and Political epartment dated Us yAth a'ui-ch 1^24. i .itii reference to your confidentiii-l No.ZpO-X.,of ferch 11th, 1924, and my subsequent interview with you at DelM on the 20th instant, I be«5 to say tnat in the case of its imturini;, I am prepared to take up the post provided its pay is fixed at 153.450/- p.m. and free quarters or an allo.mnce in lieu thereof is allowed. SupposingSupposing the area to ue surveyed ana recoraad is not more then 25 iniles I hop© .vitli a party of One senior survoyer ^ Hs.lOO/- p»r/i« ^ith iree &lt;• uarters. llxree surveyers ' 75^'' Ti:ire9 CMinsmon 25/- (Indian trained) to complete, within six months, a c^tp and a recorc? of rights on the bro^d linos of the Indian ilecoro of liiglifes »/ith sucri adc itions and alterations as may appear ;ar;mntod by the vsm&amp;Q of tlie place and trie land-holding system obtaining in Iraq and other Arabic Sjjeajiing countries • Should it he feasible, arran^iient mi^it be made for me to leave here, jita trie ^.rty and survey anuiimant in Augtet so as to 03 aola to camiance o^^tioas in ^optomer neKt. I^ctra ohainmen ^11 a coolies /ill, of course, have to be recruited locally ^iien needed. /^- o - ; ^yeesrsnt tiii dayof 1924,'betv/een hq Excellency Siiaik Eamad bin Isa A1 0.3.1, Deputy Governor of Balixain (hereinaf ter Jmovm as t Oxe Go v exigent ) on be- talf of the GoTerziment of Baliraiii, of tiic one purt»und IQian 3ciii'b ^ EuJbainmad Siiafi (hereinafter imam as tne Surveyor) of Uio o Uier Hierel^ it is agreed 'between the parties hereto as follows- |l) The Govenment shall employ the Surveyor to recruit and super y /ise the v/orl: of a survey party to siirvey the iniiaoitated islands h &gt;f the Bahrain State, ^[2) The abover gntioaod Survey party to consist of the following staff on the rates of pay hereinafter laid down vi^~ One senior surveyor # Hs ICQ per mensem. Three surveyors each € 3u 75 per luensen. Three chaixraen (Indian trained) t Rs ^5 ^ax iuenseia, [Z) The Govenment s3mll pay the Surveyor Hs4£0(fou.r hundred &amp; fifty) in Indian currency, in Bahi -ain, for his ttrvicts, therefor the surveyor undortakes- [4) To recruit the ahove survey party,and if ^ubsenuent}y foind necessarv to recruit furtiier siriiilar staff, to hring iAicti tc Bahrain so as to report there for duty botv/een the first and tenth of Hovonbex 1924,and to fully supervise their noxlt In Bahrain as lu ^' he required of Iiiui.TLe Surveyor further under- taiics to afford to the revenue Adviser to t}ie Govcr;u .ent such assistance as he nqy require in the matter of compiling a record of rights in landeu property in the areas surveyed,and generally to worh under the orders and supervision of the Revenue JUiviscr to the Gk.vtaai eut. (5) The salaries of the survey party detailed in para. 2 above shall 'be defrayed by the Government and the Surveyor and the survey staff shall not he entitled to any other pay or allow® ances except the pay mentioned in this agreement with the exception that- (6) The C-overmient will pay the actual cost of rail &amp; steamer pas sagesi thou t food-from the station in which recruited in India to Bahrain and, oneOizpletion of the worh,for the return journey,on the following scale- )art— a2. r the Surveyor 2nd. class throughout. For cJJ. other racsnbers of tlie iff 3rd class by rail and deois. paijaa^es 'by stealer, and, ) The goTemiient aoall provide adequate tentage for tlie party for the period of the Survey. ,and tjtoll provide necessary transport. ) The Government shall pay the surveyor and the staff herein mention- ~cd during tho mole term of their employment at the rates laid dtmn in Uils agreement out the Government shall not pay them for any period in excess of twelve days 'before reporting for duty in Bahrain a&amp;d in excess of twelve days after departure from Bahrain, both da^'s included ♦ t) 3t:rveyor siiall not while in Uie Service of the C-overnment carr oxi any tr-.ido on his own or »jiybody elseSs account or receive any rsnmneration for services rendered to tuxy other party without txre express ^auction of the Government in writing. CO) This a^j'reeiaent shall continue to t&gt;e in lorcc until its oeminatic liy the fact that the survey of the Islaoda has 'boon corfrpleted to t satisfaction of the Government, or by one full months written notice £:lven trj the Cfov ernnent. xn writing to the surveyor or by illness necessitating the absence of the Surveyor irom his duties 101 u period exceeding consecutive days. Sealed by the Deputy Go vernor of Bahrain in the presence of witness- Seal , Signed by the said Khan Sahib Sfamad iamfi in the ^ ese ' ce SignatureH' Ho, 497-3 of 1924. ^ | ; J r British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 50th August 1924. Copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain. By order, Subject . BAHRAIN REVENUE SURVEY. Foreign and Political Department Memorandum No. 36-X, dated the 18th August 1924, with enclosure.Telegram Pr om To Foreign, Simla^ Res id e nt,'Bus nir e - No . 36~x* Dated 1st i and received 2nd ) October 1924. My endorsement No. 3^-X . , dated 18th August. Revenue Survey at Bahrain* Owing to ill health, mt: Muhammad Shafi unable to accept. Kave wired Highcoma , Baghdad, to enquire whether 9 Iraq can supply staf f. Agent., Bahrain, for information, in continuation of this office endorsement No. 497--^ • i dated the 3^'^ August' J -,924« - Foreign No. SU -s . of 1924. British Residency and Cons ulate-G-enerai, B'oshire , 9th October 1924. Tlie foregoing is forwarded to the political BY ORDER Capt . , political Resident in the Persian Qulf. DJSOflfiB a ; ; J IflPliilr No. 58-S of 1925. British Residency and Consulate-General, Eushire, 7tli Ivlarcii 1925. Copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain. By order. Capt., Under Secretary to^ th^^jri^Tcal Resident in the Persian Gulf. February Letter Ho. 36-X. } dated the 12th 1925, from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department.The Political Agency, 1 , jj, Bahrain • Persian Gulf. j 1 COfiii 3fl: ifa Ka 3 /3. 28/4/25. From Major C.K.Daly C.I.E. Political Agent ,Bahrain, To The Surveyor General of India, Delhi, Staff for Survey in Bahrain State. it on \k 1 mu I have tii.e honour to refer to letter Ho 36-X of I2th Fehy, rom the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign 'i Political Department to the Hon f 'ble the Political Resident in the •ersian Gu -Lf ,on the subject of the engagement of staff for a sur- natir ey of the Bahrain Islands. It was suggested therein that I should lommunicate with you direct &amp; endeavour to supply you with fuxier ir sii .nformation. The matter has novr 'been considerably simplified by I) The fact that an Indian Official of the State who is a trained •9 '111 ^ surveyor &amp; has a guod v/orliing knowledge of Araoic &amp; oj . the Know distridt is now available to take charge of the whole Survey. [2) That financmal considerations are no longer so important as they were last year when the finances of the reformed state h r6 i]| i were not yet firmly established. The Staff it is now proposed to recruit from India, none of whom need have any knowledge of Arabic,though such a knowledge would be useful,and should preferably, though not absolutely necessarily,be Muhaiomedans, is a s follows- One senior surveyor 4 surveyors. chainsmen it is proposed to train locally before the surveyors arrive in Bahrain, rs5 '' S| The matter of pay of these surveyors may please be determined by you according pay ruling in India plus whatever increase you consider necessary to attract really good men-who are quit workers-s Second class passages both ways will be paid by . the be made here if you^) rill 'be so good as to fix the salaries. Provisionally a sum of ts 20,000 has 'been set ayide in a fund to meet the cost of the mrvey &amp; record of rights.The Ruler is prepared to increase this, md the necessary funds are available # up to a maximum of Rs SO,000 should it be absolutely neceaasry,but it is hoped tnat expenditure leed not exceed Rs25000 including the printing of maps etc. Lnstruments &amp; materials will be purchased by the State &amp; your advice as to the nature &amp; quantity of instruments etc to be or- iered would be greatly appreciated • The I5th October next would be the most suitable date by which the party should reach Bahrain. The climate from November to May is very pleasantly cool -rainfall very slight.Strong winds are rather prevalent. Dust storms are rare. The nature of the ground is flat &amp; except in the area planted with date palms the view is open.Date gardens &amp; lucerne fields have little detail. Date gardens are fairly continuous alon the coast for some I5vmiles with a varying depth of Si 'i to 1 mile &lt;5c away from the coast the gardens are in patches generally not of great extent. It is necessary for these patches to be geographical ~ly connected &amp; the uncultivated areas between to be mapped(though there is very little detail) as the cultivation is extending &amp; it will be necessary from time to time to add new cultivated areas to the maps for record purposes. No co/ntours will be required. The finished maps will require to be on a sufriceintly large scale to enable the land lecord Depart ment to record thereon ,to scale, the boundaries between individuc owners which are often not defined on the ground . The plans of the two towns of Kanarneh &amp; Muharraq will require to be on a large scale both for Land Record purposes &amp; for Municipal work. Great detail will not be necessary,the main desideratum being to haiaje all streets,open spaces 8c buildings of importance recorded to scale• Ordinary buildings of no particular importance would be sufficiently represented in blocks. No in strumental levelling will be necessary. The Town of Ma.yia.na.m ftVi contains afrofet 30.000 inhabitants &amp; ]Luharr«a roughly 20,000.It is suggested that some of the surveyors should start on the Town plans at once ,on arrival of the party,while others make the neceosary arrangements &amp; preparations for the other work, which I presume would entail the divis&amp;nn of the country into areas 'by theodilite? The area to be mapped will comprise that part of Manaaneh island ( the largest island) north of Jabel Dukhan. South of that is entirely uncultivated at present &amp; beyond fixin the position of a few small villages 8c saD.ient features it would be waste of time to record detail. The v /hole of the Island of Muharraq-which howver is very open &amp; contains very kittle cultivation or other detail. The whole of the small island of Sitrah which is very largely planted with date palms except the Southern portion in which the position of villages &amp; a few snal patches of date palms only need to be done in detail. It is desirable that the work should be donpleted ,if possible between 1st November atRdI925 &lt;&amp; May I5th 1926 (after whi date the damp heat is excessive &amp; work almost impossible) If the staff proposed is insufficeint for this purpose it should be increased,as the survey is urgently needed &amp; postponement of the work until the following cold weather would considerably increase the cost. If a draughtsman is necessary to finally make proofs for printing of maps, perhaps you would be so good a to arrange for his recruitment,but perhaps it might be possible for ^che finishing work to be done in India (cost being borne by Bahrain State) &amp; the maps printed tlu.re - The Ruler of Bahrain has agreed to accept any arrang -ments you consider necessary for t he proper completion, of the work within the limit of expenditure alreddy mentioned, I am personally proceed ing on six months leave &amp; the Ruler is accompanying me to England .My suceeserr has been asked by the Ruler to complete arrangements acting under your advice.I shall return early in November &amp; will personally assist the State Officials in the compilation of the record of rights while the survey .is proceeding &amp; shall be constantly on tour &amp; in touch with the surveyors while on their work,though of course fh« tftfVhnina.l suDft-rvi aroon will rftst with the trained Fmrvevor &amp;ad the senior surveyor recruited froiii India. j.lie only iruip oi Boiirain Islcinds # icnov/n to Lie, wiiiciL sliev/s ny detail ,is Map No.9I2 -s.06, Published 'by the direction of the irveyor General jbtf India in June 1906- Persian Gulf-Bahrain Island, sale I inch to I mile. I have the honour to be , Sir, Your Obedient Servant ■ ajor. Political Agent.Ho. 162-S Of 192b, ^riuish Residency and Consulate-General Bushlre, 16th May 1925. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to his memorandum l\ r o. 6/9/3, dated the 24th January 1925. By order, Capt. Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Sub.j e c t. ivevenue Survey of Bahrain Letter to the Government of India in the Foreign and -oliuical Department, ho. 160-5, of even date £ / r' iI1HHTIAL. Ne. 7^/3 1925. Political Agency, Bahrein. The 6th Septeraser 1925. iron T© Captain G«L#Uallam, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrein. The Hon*hie Lieut- Colonel 0«f* Crosthwaite, C3.S., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. HKY NU?: SimVEY OF BAHHF'IB ISLAKDQ Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with your endorsement 162-8 of the 16th Mfrnfa 1925 I have the honour to forward you herewith ^ oopjeyor correspondence which ha© passed between the Surveyor General in India and ay self on the ahove subject. The cosst of this surrey and the compilation Of a record of rights was originally estimated 'by Major Daly at from ^20,000 to ^25 ,000, with a maximam expenditure of r\$ 60,000 - It is clear however that if the proposals of the Surveyor General are accepted, they will involve a wotal expenditure of at least *0 ,000 on the s^urvey falone, il it lasts as long as six months. The large increase in the estimated cost of the survey is due to the fact that llajor „.)aly* 8 esuipkite was based on a survey staff of one senior surveyor and 4 surveyors only from India, while the Indian staff now proposed 'by the Surveyor General is -1 Officer 7 Traversers IS Burveyors 45 Initials. The employment of so large a staff will entail the lure of tentag and office furniture tmd large additional cost on passives and freiglit from India find transport arid rations for trie party during their stay in these islands - The party will also require the assistance of SO local menials, whose pay will be no anall add- •ition to the expenditure. In my opinion, after c ireful consideration of these proposals, the Bahrein State might well find it sell involYsd in a total expenditure of not such less than n ?580,000* In Tie^ of the fact that the Government of India have f now found it impossible to spare an Officer as Assistant Folitioc Agent in Bahrein to assist the Political Agent during the survey, I have had serious doubts as to whether the Bahrein State will 'be justified in afffHilffg expending: such a ori a BUrTey- a freat deal of the benefit of which will be lost from the fact that Major Daly single handed will not find it possible to devote siuch, if any, Of his time in the compilation of a record of rights and the settlement of several outstanding land boimdajj disputes contemporaneously with the work of e survey# X have considered several alternatives, suca as the reduction of the survey party to soiaplete the survey of the miilt island only this winter, and the postponement of tne survey oi Muharraq and Sitrah islands until next year- It does not appear to ne however that any decrease in the cost 'by the adoption of such alternatives, or of ony other modification of the Surveyor General*« proposals woiild be sufficj -ent to justify the risk of still larger expenditure in the even of a second survey party being required next year to cosplete th wo rk • BesidesBeside* time is now short- I doubt if the Surveyor General would 'be ready to consider any modification of his proposals, with a view to putting them into effect this winter. While mentioning his o«m proposals in regard to the staff require^, Major Daly quite rightly left the final decision in the hands of the Surveyor General, and at the same time gave liim full information in regard to the area to be surveyed. Under the above circumBtances 4 I am of opinion that the Surveyor General 1 s proposals must be either accepted ii toto, •r refused altogether. I have discussed the matter with Sheikh Hamad and we are tf opinion that in spite of the presence of unfavour- -able circumstances# it would be bad policy in a matter of this sort to hang back - It will be possible therefore to provide the necessary funds and to c urtail expenditure, if necessary, in other directions. I propose with your approval therefore to accept the Surveyor General's proposals and to make immediate prepara tions for the arrival of the party. I would add one condition to the acceptance, vis:- that if the work is completed to the satisfaction of the Bahrein Government before the expiry of six month®, the party s^ shall be returned to India at onoe, and the cost of their pay, hire of equipment etc. shall only be borne by the Bahrein State between the dates of their departure from and arrival back fei 'ir A India. I submit that there will not be sufficient time to refer the matter to the Government of India now without serious- -ly endangering the success of the survey by delaying the recrui ment of the party and their despatch from India.I request IMiljiiiiiwf therefore that, if you thirik fit, you will he so good mxx as to tolegraph to ne Immediately on receipt of this despatch, authorising me to accept the Surveyor General* s proposals and to proceed with the arrango- -isent e« I have the lonour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Captain, X • A* , Political Agent, Bahrein*COPY. TSLSGRAH. P«litioal , Bahrein. T« - Surveyor General, Sial.-u Ko. S3S Sated 25th July 1925. Solicit reply to my letter Ko. 37/9/5 dated 28th April as question of proposed survey is one of pressing importanoo to Bahrein State.Copy of letter No. 70/9/3 dated lith August 1925 from the Political Agent, Bahrein, to the Surveyor Oeneral, Siiiala. I have the honour to invite a reference to my letter Ho. 37/9/ 3 dated April 2Sth ms and t© request a reply at your earliest convenience* I shall he glad to know how the recruitment cf the Survey party is progressing, and what instruments, if any, it will 'be necessary for me to procure for the par pose of the survey. X X would suggest that the party he sent fully equipped witn instruments, as the time is now so short that it may not he possible for me to obtain them in time*♦ 4 ft Copy# telegram Bo. 19iS dated 1st Sept eraser 1926 from Surreys, Laadour, to the Politioal Agent, Bahrein. We can arrange for Bahrein survey as follows if you oable early acceptance of the arrangement® one officer seven traverser# thirty menials to sail early October and followed by fifteen surveyors and fifteen followers one month later AAA total oo et rupees thirty two thousand, for six months work in Bahrein from arrival of first party AAA In adiition steamer charges between seven and eight thousand and you will have to provide 80 local menials and free rations for nay forty five menials also quarters and office furniture AAA Ho tents have been estimated AAA Please cable if any tents or office furniture required and we will charge ten percent on cost and full freight of same AAA Cable reply t© Surveys Calcutta. Copy of telegram Bo. $3© date-i 2nd September 1925 from the t Political Agent, Bahrein, to Surveys, Calcutta. Your 1916 Presume party will arrive fully equipped and that total cost covers loan of all instruments required for survey please confirm. Copy of telegram Ho. 3847 dated 4th September 1 25 from Surveys Calcutta to the Political Agent, Bahrein. M «■«&gt; a* a* * Your 939 Yes estimate includes full equipment of instruments stationery and clo tiling.TEL S—G R A M . tmrn m i« m hi — ii m m ■m.-.am m m ■.mmmrm In Code# Pr®m - Resident # Bushire. . To - Political, Bahrein# No. 560 Dated 10th Septeraser 1928# » In view of the fact that no Asst# Political Ajfent can 'be posted to Bahrein consider it impossible for Major Daly sifle handed prepare record rights and settle numerous disputes that will arise* Also final estimate survey at Bahrein as compared with original estimate rupees 2»,000 will not be less than rupees 80,000 which sum however could be found by curtailment of other State expenditure. I am of opinion that Survey should be postponed. Government of India orders are solicited by telegraph as surveyor general must be informed immediately addressed Govt, of India reference correspondence ending with my predecessor*s letter No. 160 -S dated l€th Uay 1925 and repeated to Bahrein reference his letter No. 78/9/3 dated 6th September 1925.T E L E G R A . Fr«m - Mai lam, Bahrein. T« - Resident, Bushire repeated te Ferei^n, Simla. No. 970 Dated llth September 1928. Yeur telegram No. i60. If survey is postponed and Major Daly returns for one year only muoh of the value of his long experience in Bahrein will be lost to the State. In my opinion he alone can settle many of the intricate disputes in which land is tied up without tedious legal proceedings. Could Government of India possibly reconsider quostion of Asst. Pol. Agent and send one of the young officers now under training in Punjab or United Provinces to Bahrein for the winter,and so permit survey to be carried out? Addressed to Resident repeated to Foreign Simla.» r. Puri, 6 ■., j, earl3^ r ) ■ will study the situation ana can suggest necessary modi fications . As regards -ay z od allowances, I have arranged fche ustial special terms granted to s ua: eiaployed on suoli wo rk , as Tollows:- SUIEHIOIi Indian rate or ^ a;; jl in JepMtatlo- allowance of 25;^, I idj.a-' rate of Daily Allowance plus free transport, fr. 1-vl 'being allowed a usual Dotac'- :e clarge allowance of ?■:, 50/-^ »m un of it,:.' » Indian rate of pay plus a Tenporaip Ii:.cr0a c e o: i ay d d. 6/- per lease an^ free clo -ar and rations. Pension contri 'Dution is payaolo op pou 'J E3.12/8/- per cent. of the dap plus Deputati n and charge allowances and © .H; and Tenporary Increase to .,ienial^. Leavs 'bonus alll oe payable t^ the superior stai f at l/l 1th o.,. ^ap snd allowances subject to t : o ■ linimuni o^ pap and allowances for one month. I enclose hei ewith a copp of the estimate as prepared by us which amounts to mm32,00)/-. This d^es not include Bteame-;- fares, freight of cargo, cost or hire of tents anc furniture, wages of local :enials (vide para 2 above) and of extra coolies who may be occasional!, required for line clearing, also rations of aii menials, which will be s up plied oy - - ou. As regards the purchase of fstrm mits referred to in para 4 of your letter, I propose to supply all instru mnts free and have added.the usual percentage charge of 4^ of the whole cost to cover this ite mT ELE G RAM. In ctdg• Fr«m - Secretary 9 Buohire. T» - Political, Bahrein. N«. 580 Dated 15th September 1925. Telegram 042 N 14th September from P®reign repeate for yeur infermatien 'begins Yeur 5i0 Bahrein Survey. Ne A..P.A. available would deputation experienced Revenue Officer of Provincial service be of any uoe if so Govt, would consider whether it would be financially justified ends. Please furnish your opinion for Residents information •y to this com- its number, listin squishing be quoted. No. 500ji tt Sxtru^ir of JniiJia, SURVEYOR GENERAL'S OFFICE, 13.Wood Street, Calcutta September ^9 t&gt; From COLONEL COMMANDANT E. A. TANDY, RE., Surveyor General of India. To The Political Agent, Bahrain State. Subject - Typewriter required for the Bahrain Survey I hare the honour to state that the Surrey •Detachment ©bout to start for Bahrain will require a good portable Remington typewriter for its office work. Unless the State can provide such a typewriter for the use of the Survey Detachment I propose, with your approval, to arrange for sppjfc supply of a new typewriter with extra ribbons etc. and debit the cost to the State. To avoid delay^ X would request that your reply may kindly be sent by wire direct to the Director, Horthern Circle, Survey of India 9 Mussoorie (Telegraphic address, SURHORTH, Mussoorie). Detachment. Sir, I have the honour to be. Sir, your most dbedient servant.I I - will 1b a4 iitlon 'be grantod %ho unxml ietmhmnt ohnrgo allownnoe (apeclni which la :is. 5a/- per at proaent 4 flia wenlal staff will ba pali thoir IrAim rr.tea of pt^y plus h temporary inaroaae of is* C/- atvoh per nor^ern cxxo id.ll» in addition, 1)6 nllowod free rations or be giren en allowance in lieu ^hereof. (0), An outfit allowance of ra, 500/- will be grantoa to Hal Sahib Banak Chant! imrl anci Ha. 150/- to each of the lomr Subordinates. ?ho 45 monisla vvlil bo provided wl.tb a free issue of clothing. (d). The State will boar tho usual contribution for pension for the personnel aooordlng to rules In force at the time. (e). LeaTe bomiB to t ho superior staff at 1/llth of pay and allowances subject to the nlnlrmn of pay ana allownnoes for one raonth, (f) # Honoraria to the raenbera of the JetaclXiOnt for ap eel ally oeritorl oua servlooa* ^ho political Agent, Bahrain, haa intlaatea that 'ho aoat stil table titnte by which the Mfty shov.ld reach MiraSn 5 b the idth October 19C5 and m tine U short, I h&amp;w. In anticipation of the approval of tho &lt;^Ternner .t of India instructed the Director, northern circle to aasembl© the i-artjr to be ready to embark on the at ease r leaving Earaohl on or about the 4th Ootobar 19»i5. J. beg that, the aoremwent, of Inflie say be pleaaed to snr.otion J ho doput.otion of thm a .etnohBPnt to foreign sor^loo. for n period not, exoeeding one year, from suoh date as the farty la forraed. I woiaa State that those apeaiflo torna haw not as yet been aooeptert by the .mXer of Bahrain, but the Political Aeont . has glTen hla aaauraaoe that thorn will be no alfrloulty In reapeot of fnnda. A oopy of thla latter 1' belm .orvrrSed Mb with the re que at that I mj frill convey hie definite acoevtance b; t«legr«a. A further ooBwunloatlon wJ.ll follow on woelpt of his reply.g. In csonolxiQlon i would observo that the propooea deputation of the i^taohmant will reault in a Baring to the touiget allotment of t his Jepartment ao the pay and allowances of the officero and subordinates vrili be borne 'by the State. 7, X shall feel obliged if the sanction ot: the Government of Indie ooulcl be oonTey^a to ne by telegren at the earliest possible (into as the iteaaer /-gents require a fortnights notice for paeeages* I ha.T9 the honour to be t air # Your ipo ot obedient eerrent, 3d/- 0. a.Lewis, Ma J ox*» K« .*i.. For Purveyor General, of India. 3oo6z&gt;c*j^ ys , Oopy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for informa tion, in continuation of my No# 69£5/40.C14 dated 1st September 1925. The terms proposed in my previous letter were not sufficient ly comprehensive and it is requested that definite acceptance of the terms now detailed in the enclosed letteftpthe Government of India may be conveyed by telegram. Major, R*&amp;*» For Surveyor (reneral of India. l /-?/ Ov \ I Telegram PRIORITY. From Secretary BUBhire. T« Political Bahrein* No. 619 D^t^d 1st Oct« 25 Reference your telegram No. 1017 Are Ra 39,000 mentioned 'by you included in your figures wi Hs 80,000 in paragraph 4 of your letter No. 78/9/3 dated September? Or does it represent extra costs mentioned by Serveyor General in his telegram No. 3082 to you ?Telegram Ho. 10 IP. dated Secretary , Bushire. 'iority Your 619. Please see tele pram Ho,IP 16 froir Surveyor General to n© enclosure ir&gt; ray desratch No.78/o/^ 6th Septerbar Total eetir.ated cost of Rs .of?, 000/- payable to Government of India has no?? been raised to Rs.39,000/- by Surveyor General's telerrar. Ilo.^OPg. Latter sum may be taken as included in my estimate of R s .SO t OOO/- for total cost ct survey. Dallam /o/JTTelegram From To % ^ Government of India, Foreign and Political department, Simla. Resident, Bushire. No. 142-N. Dated 1st received 2nd October 1925. Your telegram Ho. 590. Begret no suitable Provincial Service Officer. Survey party has been cancelled. Ho. 269-S. of 1925. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 6th October 1925. A copy of the above telegram is forwarded for information in continuation of this office telegram ho. Lbc. dated the 19th September 1925. 2. The Hon'ble the Political Resident wishes you to forward to this office a copy of your let cer Imo. 37/V/o, dated the 28th April 1925, to the Surveyor-General, iTiO.ia, and of anv other previous or suleeouen ^ correspondence, no already forwarded with your letter i.o. •t./v/o, ciated ciit 6th September 1925. By order. 7q to Capt., Secretary to the Political Resident in the -Persian Gul-i.. To ?he Political Agent, BahrainNo. of 1925. Political Agency , Bahrain. Dated 12th October 1925, To $ The Secretary to The Mor^ble the Political HeQident in the Persian Gulf, Buahire . Memorandum . Reference your Endorsement No,*&lt;l9-Si dated ith October 1925. The copy of the letter referred to therein together with the copy of under noted correspondence on the subject is • forwarded herewith as requested. Captain*I•A*» Political Afcent&gt;Bahrain, Bahrain, cop, .f -nent of lndia iapartnent, of Education Health 4 Lands. %nm o fiat ed 18th September 1925 from the 'W W «» Agent.Bahrain. oop, o, Surveyor General»Calcutta to/ 0 ^ • GOYERHMEHT OB 1 BAHHAIN Ho. &lt;&lt;^1^ Of 1345 Office of 1 the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 12th, Safar, 1346 To The H. B. M 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that owing to the complete lack of control or supervision over wakf property in Bahrain, which has resulted in gross mis -management and in many cases, mis- appropriation of wakf funds.^edioated for the maintenance of schools, mosques and charitable purposes etc, hy the mutawallis and administrators. H. E. Shaikh Hamad has instituted a«* wakf depart- ment. ' The Department consists of.- hin Saad. and Shaikh Ahdul assisted hy Shaikh Mohomed hin Hashid Ai Khalifa and a olerk. Sye ^Hussein Ai n A|emi M^towa and two clerks. It is hoped that the Government will he ahlepz -2- atle to obtain a 'building which will 'be used exclusively for the department, hut in the meantime the Sunnis are occupying the Baladya Majlis and the Shias are working in Syed Adnan 1 s Majlis in Manama • ing all wakfs. When full particulars are obtained the department, will, where necessary, remove the present administrators and will undertake the collection and disbursement of the wakf. The internal arrangements are under the control of the Kadis themselves, . It is hoped that the installation of this depar-tment will result in a general improvement in the condition and upkeep of mosques and schools, most of whioh have, , without doubt, benefited not in the least from the monies dedicated to them in the past. The department is 'beginning by register- I have the honour to be. Sir, .... _ -3 .1 ^ 4- C5^ ■V'TTO Tr»+. Financial Adviser to the Government, Bahrain.No. 0/ L Ji) Of 1^27, EUB-M's Political Agency#Bahrein, /C Dated the August 1927, From Captain R.G.Alban, Political Agent#Bahrein, To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf» Bushire, Sir X have the honour to forward you herewith a cop^ in duplicate of a conmunication# received by me from the Adviser, Bahrein State, m regard to certain improvements instituted by Shaikh Hamad in the administration of Wakfs, I may say that this reform was demanded by public opinion after the conviction of the of the leading Mulla of Muharraq on the charge of embezzlement of a sum of Rb.3800/- and of certain equally disgraceful charges being brought against the sons of Shaikh Jasim bin Mehza chief Qazi of Manama, The new system is working smoothly and the r.ew qazia engaged wi it are keen and reliable men. x have the honour to be. Sir, Tour most obedient servant, \ A.:/ / Captain, Political Agent, Bahrein.lOHFIDMTIAL. No. 316-S. of 1927. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire , 12tli September 1927. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM . Reference your letter No. C.95., dated the 26th August 1927. The Hon'ble the Political Resident considers the reforms instituted by Shaikh Hamad in the administration of Wakf property most satisfactory and would like you to convey his satisfaction thereat to the Shaikh. By order, Secretary ^ Resi^ 611 '^ in the Persian Gulf.''1 ^6 jv^f^li. £ dl-au ^ a^** /3A6 - ' n,uC i 1 ^ Scfia^i^- To Captain R. U. Alban, Political ^ent, Bahrain. After ^alaane etc., I thank you l'ro y ' the bottorn of ny heart for inforning me of the approval of the Hon'ble the Political Uesiclent in the Persian Gulf, Colonel Haworth, concerning the HiformG 1 have inetituted in the matter of Waqf Properties and I hope that you will convoy my sincere thanks to the Political Resident for his kindness. U.S. Shaikh hamad 'bin Isa.GOVEHHMEIW 0? BAHRAII'J HO, 3^\^n- Of 1346 Office of the*Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dd,25th Hahi A1 Thany 46 To The H. 3. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, With reference to my letter Ho. 119/27 of the 12th Safar, 1246, on the subject of the newly formed TJakf Department, I now have the honour to Inform you of certain changes which have 'been made. Owing to the scandalous condition of wakfs in Bahrain the Government oonsiaered it necessary to take steps on the subject. Previously, during the time of Major Daly, attempts had been made to place wakis / private as well as public, under the direct control of the Government. This was unpopular and after Major Daly 's departure the wakfs which had Ijecn taken over were handed back to the Hutawallis. The condition of mosques is notorious. Mosques which are actually rich are kept in(o /, ^ page -2- in a ruinous and filthy condition. Muoh garden and market property has 'been dedicated in the past to schools. Th© schools do not exist. In most cases the wakf incomes are appropriated hy the mutawallis, the worst offenders in this respect 'being the old Sunni Qaadi, Shaikh Qasim Bin Mehza and his numerous sons and nephews, who occupy, hut do not function in, many paid positions in mosques and non-existent schools. These facts were so well known that foreign news -papers, Egyptian and Iraqian, oommentea on the subject. To remedy the conditions the Government appointed three new Qaadis as a Shara Court and Wakf Department. The Qaadis were provided with suitable staff and aocomodation. two clerks, and a Hathr or Inspector, Shaikh Mohomed Bin Eashid A1 Zhalifa. formerly a Magistrate on the Bahrain Court. The public were ordered to produce all wakf documents. This they did. The Qaadis were asked to record the documents by having copies made, and to inspect them and to enquire into the condition 4- n-p the various wakfs. They were and accounts of the vanuu authorised to r ..o,o m omtwoUl. .ho., -ort .ot satiofaotory to .t.rt . .. e t.t.t and 4- nil of which was carefully explained simple accounts all oi wm to them and their staff.page -3- After about two months it 'became perfectly olear that though provided with a oorapetent olerk and assistants they were absolutely inoapahle of running a department, keeping a register or aocounts. They allowed nothing to 'be written without 'being examined 'by each of them in turn, a lengthy proceeding, and usually only one or two of the Qaadis attended the office. They . effected no changes or improvements except the removal of one notorious Mutawalli, who was petitioned against, 'by the public. Public persons of standing complained to the Government of the uselessness and inef- fiolency of the department - which inoidentally oost a large amoimt of money to feeep up. They rightly pointed out that exoept for copying out ahout one hundred doouments nothing had been done, nor did it seem in the least likely that anything would he done in the future unless things were altered. After due consideration Shaikh Hamad called a meeting of fifty of the leading religious and civil notables, and the chief members of his own family. A speech was read fr0B Shaikh Hamad in which he laid do™ a new proposal. He suggested that there should be a 'Department of Education and Wakfs' under thePage -4- the direction of a Oounoil v /ith Shaikh Ah dull a Bin Isa as president. The proposal was received with unanimous and genuine approval, The three Qaadis were informed of the arrangement and suitable persons were appointed as members of the Oounoil, The Qaadis were told that they wiil- have the ohief say in ques tions of a religious nature, but that the work of supervision of property, repairs of buildings and accounts would be dealt with by the Oouncil, who were laymen and more experienced in such matters. All the three Qaadis appeared at the first meeting and their attitude indicated considerable disapproval of the new regime. They emphasawised the fact that being Qaadis. the chief exponents of religion in Bahrain, any decision or opinion of theirs should he treated as absolutely definite. They also drew attention to the fact that on their appointment they were told that in future the control of wakfs would be in their hands. After some discussion they seemed to acquiese in .he change. Shaikh Abdulla has sent for an Ofucial from the Ministry of Wakfs in Baghdad who will be acquainted with the system on which the department is worked in Iraq*#0 O/ ■■ page -5- The Department is intended to deal with toth Shia and Sunni Wakfs. Some of the mernbers of the Council are Shia and sorae Simni. The Shia Qaadi, Syed Ednan, has throughout expressed his entire approval of the ohange and has advocated it from the 'beginning. In my opinion the ohange was absolutely necessary if the Department was to 'be of any real use. The Q,aadis had an oppor^uniby of effecting great improvements, they were given every facility and the strongest support, but they did nothing. The new system has the entire approval of the lay population, the only opposition being from a few Mutawallis and religious persons who natural? resent any scrutiny into their aooounts and their adminis tration. It is hoped however that the new system will effect an improvement in the condition of Wakfs. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your Obedient Servant, Financial Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. N.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000361_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/130</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000361</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/130</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/3 Bahrain Reforms. Land Registration &amp; Record of Rights'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1923/1927</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-02-01T00:01:00</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (102 folios)</extent><extent>The volume's contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, starting with the earliest items at the front and finishing with the latest items at the end. The items in the volume deal with two specific subjects, separated chronologically by two years, and by a divider-title sheet on folio 79.</extent><extent>Foliation: The volume is foliated from the front cover to the inside back cover, using circled pencil numbers in the top-right corner of each recto. There is an earlier foliation system using blue pencil numbers, that runs through a small part of the volume, from folios 2 to 4.The following foliation anomalies occur: 1a, 1b, 1c, 1d, 1e, 3a.The following folios are foldouts: 32, 38-40, 43, 44, 54, 57-59, 64, 70, 74, 75, 80, 88, 97-99.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains correspondence and papers relating to the issue of land rights and ownership in Bahrain.The first part of the volume (folios 2-78) concern the organisation of a land survey in Bahrain. The Ruler of Bahrain, Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfa, with the assistance of the Bahrain Political Agent (Major Clive Day), arranged with the Government of India’s Surveyor General ( E. A. Tandy) for a team of surveyors to come to Bahrain to survey the populated parts of the islands. A letter from Daly to the Surveyor General, dated 28 April 1925 (folios 28-30) provides details of the extent and character of the area to be surveyed. The survey was originally intended to take place during the winter of 1924/25, but was eventually delayed until the following year. A large portion of the correspondence relates to the costs of conducting the survey (including manpower, equipment, lodgings in Bahrain, food rations and passage from India), which were far greater than originally budgeted for by Sheikh Hamad. A revised proposal from the Surveyor General of India to Daly, dated 1 September 1925, gives details of the various costs of the survey (folios 54-56). Negotiations over the costs continued right up until the departure date of the surveying team from India to Bahrain, in October 1925. There is a copy of the deed (in Arabic) for the plot of land adjacent to the Agency at folio 80.The second part of the volume (folios 81-99) concerns the implementation of a
                           waqfdepartment in Bahrain. The
                           waqfis a form of religious endowment under Islamic law, usually involving the donation of buildings or land for religious or charitable purposes. The correspondence relates to Shaikh Ḥamad’s introduction of a
                           waqfdepartment, to address the reported mismanagement and misappropriation of
                           waqffunds.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Waqf Department</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Surveyor General</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Khalīfah (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Land ownership</topic></subject><subject><topic>Economic reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Political reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Law reform</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000361#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>