<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00027f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:41:31.517Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">M !jir :: : m Mi ■ v--: i •- :.W 1 c: r;::: ■S.VZ / Te legram: - ZX.. No:- 553. Dated:- 12th July 1933. e’rom:- Recident Bushire. To:- Political Kuwait, Political Baiirain. Addressed Political Agent Kuwait and Bahrain. SAUDI Government have informed Minister JKDDA privately that they suspect that KHALID ihn HITHLAIN (AJMAN) proposes to e&gt;iter UEJD from KU/AIT vrith evil intent and is trying to obtain supplies at KU'A r AlT and BAHRAIN. Please ascertain whether KHALID or his agents have been trying to obtain supplies,and obtain assurance from Ruler that all preventive measures y/ill be ta»cen to check any activities of KHALTD cf his agents in KUWAIT or BAHRAIN directed against the SAUDI Government. Plea.se report by telegraph.(Vo % % Telegram: - XX. No:- 273. Dated:- 15th July 1933. Prom: - Political Bahrain To:- Resident Bushire. Rptd:- Political Kuwait. Addressed Bushire. Repeated Kuwait. Your telegram 553. (1). Local enquiries unable to trace any attempt to obtain supplies. (2.J. Ruler in interview readily gave assurance and added that he very much doubted that K(halid) who has been in Baghdad for some years would use Bahrain route.£ his shoes together and that he should or 11 a servant to do that for him, Ffcalid'e first coueln KAIP in in virtual imprisonment in Kejd, 5. The Ruler did not thin* it at ail lively that Bahrain ■would he used for either the buying of supplies or as a jumping off piece. Hs readily aacured me that he would do all in his poser to check any activities of KHALXJD or his agents {if there were any) in Bahrain directed against the Sa'udi Government, 6, Hi a Kxoolloney the Shaikh inforised m that it was well known that the 3a f udi king had enemies t especially his own crother # kli1if^iaAU,ana the latter’s son and his nephew (also named iJralid) and it might be tiiat Uaiiid bin kuhommad bin Hithlain was suspected of collusion with them, ?• 1 am sending a copy of this despatch to the Political Agent, Kuwait* X have the honour to be Sir, Tour Moot Obedient Servant, Political hfecut,Bahrain,^ ' i The Agency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. The 15th July 1933. &lt;• N Reference to previous correspondence. Bahrain Telegraai Ho:275 dated 15th July 1933. Description of Enclosure. A- Name and date. , “ : aV— Letter Ko:C/276 dated the 15th July 1933 from the Political Agent, Bahrain,to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,Bushire, Subject. Khalid Lin Muhammad Din Hithlain.- —^ -L&lt;m ftf 4 Telegram XX. From Xiniater, Jedda* To Folitioal Easidanty Bushlre f fio« 144. Eapoated Baoratar&gt; of State for Foreign Affairs, London, So. 134. B.K’s. Otaarge d*Affaires, Baghdad, Bo. Ill Dated (and received ) 11th July 1933. Saudi Governseat have ooasunleated to me privately information received hy them from a variety of souroee that KHALIL bln HIIHLaIH Is proposing to enter BXJJD from KUWAIT and with evil intentions and with encouragement of •others* and that he and his j party are trying to get supplies at Kuwait and Bahrain They ask that preventive Measures aay be taken. Somewhat similar warning preceded BIX ALA affair and mention of •others* may be attempt to Implicate King of Xraq&gt; 1 should like to answer what is possible to dispel Idea that if KHALIL is in fact up to mischief he oan make use of Kuwait or Bahrain. - Xiy&amp;n.l ^ 4 (To) Telegram ^ i'rom becretary of btate for ttie Colonies, Lonson. To Politi repeated ts K.k’s E. M • s ^ated 13th receiveo cal x\esident, Bushire. No. 10 Minister, Jedda. No. 88 Ambassador, Baghdad. No. 128 14tu July 1933 Important . This warning is very similar to that given hy baudi Government in the case of Ibn Bafada and in that case, warning proved to be correct, tnder international law there is general obligation to prevent as far as possible hostile activities being carried on against territories friendly with neighs -bouring country. All possible precautions should therefore be taken to prevent any such activities against Nejd, based at Kuwait and Bahrain and we rely on you to do your utmost to achieve this end. Foregoing has reference to Jedda tele- -gram to you, No 144 of July 10th. becretary of otate fot the Colonies.CONFIDENTIAL. No - 883-S of 1933 1 he Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf presents his com pliments to The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. £. The lolitical Agent, Kuwait. 3. The Political Agent, Bahrain. % and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment Residency Printed Letter No. 857-S dated 14th July 1933 144 ° British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. / Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Political Residents tele- -gram No. 23, dated 16th July 1933, to H.M's Secre- -tary of btate for the Colonies, London. Activities of Khalid Mn Hithlain.CONFIDENTIAL. S. Ao' ^ No - 992~S of 1933. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to / 1. 'Hie Political Agent, Bahrain, 2. Hie Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- meilt /^)/ for information. v\ British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated..9th. A;j^t. Reference to previous correspondence : aij / * ]J Residency Printed letter 1T 0 .883-S of 16th July 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No*218 dated the 18th July 1933 from His Maj esty’s Charge d T Affaires,Jedda, to the Foreign Office, with en closures. Khali d bin Hi thlain,Copy. Ho.PIS. TsotWsi) (■Sefieived under Jedda Printed letter Ho.PO' 7 B/s/81 of ) . /^vv-o.'O / J British Legation, Jedda. 18th July,1933. Sir, ^ G ■ J ' /Vo ' With reference to 3ir And rev; Byan T s telegram ho.144 of the 11th instant, relative to the reported intention of Tfhalid Ibrr Hithlain to enter Bejd from Kuwait, I have the ^ J . ‘ r io f S' honour to transmit to you herewith a copy in translation of a personal letter, addressed by ^hiad Bey Hamza to 3ir Andrew on the 8th July, in which the matter was first brought to the attention of the Legation. Sir Andrew subsequently spoke to ^ad Bey on the 11th July, the day before the Sa f udi delegation left for Jerusalem to resume the ^ransJordan negotiations, and described the action he had at once taken upon receipt of the letter. 2. ' T&gt; he Sa’udi Government evidently viewed the movements of Ibn Hithlain with feelings of considerable uneasiness, not unnatural in view of the part played by this young and warlike chief of the VAjman and his tribe in the rebellion of 1929, on the 15th July, the eve of his own departure for Jerusalem, His Kajesty’s Minister received the hurriedly-arranged visit of the official in charge of the Jedda office of +he Sa’udi Ministry of foreign Affairs, Shaikh Ali ^aha, who read in a stage whisper a message from the Minister for foreign Affairs thanking Sir Andrew for what he had told 'hiad Bey on the 11th and begging for further information as soon as it came to hand. y , 3. Hpon the receipt of Bush ire telegram Ho. 23 to the Colonial/ 'lie Bight Honourable, Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I., K.C.V.O., etc ,, etc., etc oColonial Office, I addressed an urgent Personal letter to the Amir Faisal, in accordance with an arrangement suggested 'by Sir Andrew, conveying the re-assuring news that the reports which had so alarmed the Sa’udi Aral Government appeared to he completely unfounded. A copy of this personal letter to the Minister for Foreign Affairs is also enclosed herewith* 4. Copies of this despatch and enclosures are being sent to His Majesty's Ambassador at Fagdad and to the Hon'ble the Political 'Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I have the honour t o be with the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, (Sd*) A.S.CALVEir*.TRANSLATION ^ 4: iT/v®;r 15/3. Ministry of Rorei^n Affairs, 15th Rahi-ul-Av;wal 135f. 8th July 1933. PERSONA -.. My dear Sir Andrew, 'Hie Government of His Maj esty the Kinp has been informed from various sources that Khalid Ibn Hithlain who three years ago was travelling between the territories of ’Iraq and Kuwait immediate!^ after the insurrection of al Luwayah, is now endeavouring to return from Kuwait into the territory of His Majesty the King. It is presumed that his coming has for its purpose evil objects which he is attempting to carr Tr out in accordance with the encouragement of others. It is understood that the man in question and his party are endeavouring to buy their needs and equipment in Kuwait and Bahrain. I therefore wish to communicate this infoimation to Your Excellency, urivately, trusting that you qould be good enough to take the necessary measures with the authorities concerned, to prevent the occurrence of trouble on the frontier. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) Fuad Hamza. His Excellency Sir Andrew Ryan, C.M.G., Jedda.J £ S Av/1 BRITISH LEGATION, •Xedda. 17th July,1933* Your Royal Highness 1 , '•/4th reference to His Excellency Fuad Be-' Harnza T s 2 C J.^v»; f personal letter H 0 .15/3 to Sir Andrew Ryan of the 15th Rabi- ul-Awwal (8th July) last, relative to the movenerts of Khalid ibn Hithlain, and to their subsequent conversation on this subject on the 15th Rabi'ul Awwal (llth July), Your Royal Highness will already be aware of the immediate steps taken by Sir Andrew to bring this matter to the attention of His Majesty's Government and other authorities ccrcerned. I am happy to inform Your Royal Highness that I now learn that Khalid ibn Hith&amp;&amp;in is understood to be at present near Herbela and that there are no evidences of any attempt, as his Excellency Fuad Bey would suggest, on the part of emissaries of Khalid ibn Hithlain to assemble supplies in ei 4 'er Kuwait or Bahrain or to engage there in activities against this country. Ail assurance has been given by the authorities in Kuwait and Bahrain uho have readily agreed to take every precaution to prevent any activity of this nature being direct ed against Sa’udi Arabia from those territories. With highest respects, (Sd.) A.S.CALVERT. His Royal Highness 'Hie Amir Faisal, T a if. Co py. No. 20 54/5/79. URGENT. ^R8C 1T AL.I# : 1 CONFIDENTIAL. No. 1069-S of 1933. 11 m The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. nv he Political Agent, Bahrain, k 2, 'Tie -Political Agent, Knv/ait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (ij/ for information. 4 c &amp; British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated, 22nd August 1933. Reference to previous correspondence : izi / ^-/'Residency Printed letter Bo.992-S of 9th August 1933. * ^SH i Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Translation of letter Ho. 25/3/33 dated the 20th July 1933 from the Saudi Ministry of foreign \ffai rs ,'*aif, to His Majesty’s Charg£ d’Af”aire|s, Jed da. Khalid ibn Hithlm.• 23*3/39 Sncloeure in Foreign Office Covering Note dated Kth pril 1939 # No.101 Foreign Office, . .1. 12th April, 1939. (X 2241/177/26) In my despatch No.86 of the 29th area, I informed you that the Amir Faisal had seen oir Lancelot Oliphant on the 24th ^ arch immediately after hie conversation with myself ! aiid had continued with him the diacuaeion of certain points arising out of the Prime Minister's letter of the 23rd inarch. 2. His Roysl Highness told Sir Lancelot Oliphant that he was very appreciative of the warm terms in which the prime Minister's letter was couched and then enquired, as I recorded in my despatch under reference, in what form, and how quickly Saudi Arabia might expect help should a situation arise in which the community of interests between esudi Arabia, and Great Britain led to their being laced with a common ene y. This is a point on which you will receive instructions in due course. 3. His Royal Highness then alluded to the phrase 'potential aggressors*’ which occurs in the sixth pa agraph of the frime inlster'a letter. He asked whether it was the opinion of the Foreign Office that, in the present unstable state of the world, some form of aggression might be exercised against Baud! Arabia. He was told that any act of aggression in ths near future seemed very doubtful. Indeed, Herr Hitler's recent activities could not have been welcome to those who Sir Reader Bullard, KCMO., GIF., frtc. , etc. , etc. , Jedda. had/2 . had hitched their chariot to hie star, and It was unlikely that any country which had done so would willingly undertake intensive activity in Arabia, But in Herr Hitler’s case it as no longer a question of dealing with a normal, logical man, and it was always possible that he might incite those whom he regarded as his friends to follow him even now. It might, however, be doubted whether Italy, if pursuing her claims against France, would simultaneously s iow any aggressive action in the Bast. It was not possible to aa* any more than this, 4, His Royal Highness then spoke of Koweit, and asked whether there was any likelihood of His Majesty's Government allowing its incorporation in Iraq, The answer was an emphatic negative, 5, His toyal Highness finally turned to the situation in the Persian Gulf, He was assured that, far from it being the policy of His Majesty’s Government to encroach upon the autonomy of the local dhelkhs. His Majesty’s Government had always been most careful to preserve their autonomy. He was rminded that hie brother, the Amir Saud, when he had visited Bahrein some fifteen months ago, had been impressed by the absence of any signs of dictation by His Majesty’s Government* He was also told, by way of illustration, that although His Majesty’s Government had met with considerable difficulty in establishing an air port on the Trucial Coast, yet later, when the Gheikh of oebal saw that the freedom of the chelkh of Gharjah had been in no wise diminished since the Imperial Airways service had been Introduced, this Ghelkh had himself pressed for the air port to be transferred to Debal« 6, His fioyal Highness seemed satisfied, and left after a conversation which had lasted nearly an hour. I am, etc,, For the Secretary of State, Ggd, LAC I BAGGALLAY.Bushire Printed letter No:857-S dated 14-7-1933. I iiave been able to extract the following information in regard to KHALLD bin HITHLAIN from the 1 Iraq Summaries of Intelligence for 1929/30. 1) . After DAIBAN bin HITHLAIN had been put to death by FAHAD bin JILUWI (son of the Governor of Hasa),NAIF bin HITHLAIN became Chief of the Ajman. 2) . The AJMAN revolted against*IBN SA’UD and KHALID bin HITHLAIN (NAIF’s cousin) led a number of raiding parties. 3) . NAIF surrendered to IBN SA’UD early in 1930 and KHALID then disappeared and was believed to be hiding in ’Iraq territory. 4) . I have given the above information to the Head Munshi in order to enable him to make further enquiries as he was not able to identify KHALID. P.A. May be filed? \ Head Munshi is still making enquiries pi. Bushire Printed Letter No:883-S dated 16th July 1933 S .No ’.A,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00027f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/464</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00027f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/464</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'11/4 ANTI-SAUDI ACTIVITIES'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-09T13:37:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (25 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. File notes appear at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover, and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns possible anti-Saudi activities in the Persian Gulf. It contains correspondence between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire, the Political Agent at Bahrain, and Charles Dalrymple Belgrave. In addition, there are copies of correspondence with Sir Andrew Ryan, Albert Spencer Calvert and Sir Reader Bullard of the British Legation at Jedda.The correspondence of 1933 (ff 2-20) concerns suspicions that Khalid Ibn Hithlain [Khālid bin Muḥammad bin Ḥithlayn] of the Ajman tribe proposes to enter Nejd [Najd] with 'evil intent' from Kuwait or Bahrain. Included are details of a meeting between the Political Agent and Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah who doubts that Khālid would consider Bahrain as a location for buying supplies or as a staging ground for an attack, but instead suspects that he might be acting in collusion with an enemy of ‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd [Ibn Saud], for example, his brother, Muḥammad bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān Āl Sa‘ūd (ff 3-6). In addition, there are copies of personal letters on the same subject between Fuad Hamza, [Fu’ād Ḥamzah], Ryan, Calvert and Amir Faisal [Fayṣal bin ‘Abd al-‘Azīz Āl Sa‘ūd] (ff 14-20).A copy of a letter, dated 12 April 1939, from the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to Sir Reader Bullard, concerns a meeting between Sir Lancelot Oliphant and Faysal regarding the potential threat to Saudi Arabia from Nazi Germany, the likelihood of the incorporation of Koweit [Kuwait] into Iraq, and British rule of the Persian Gulf (ff 21-23).File notes at the rear of the file (ff 24-26) include brief genealogical and biographical details concerning Khalid, as well as the Ajman tribe.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Khālid bin Muḥammad bin Ḥithlayn</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Subversive activities</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00027f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>