<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000396_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T08:09:22.767Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">4th July 0 The Director of Posts and telegraphs, Sind and Baluchistan Oircle, Karachi. You will recall that sometime a^o I approached you regarding the religious vagaries oi* the ost ' aster at Bahrain,!^ Bashiruddin. 2* This individual has somewhat curbed his missionary zeal,but his inefficiency remains and I am constantly receiv- ing complaints of his incapacity xrom all sides. The fact is that he is either in his dotage or else his religious interests occupy so much of hi3 mind tnat he is unable to carry out his duties will reasonable promptitude. is predecessors were,for example,able to close and hand over the mails ten minutes after receiving them from the Agency, but iT.Bashiruddin freu^atly takes two hours to perform this task,to the ^preat inconvenience of the Steajner Company 3. As you are aware ,Imperial Airways are now committed to the Arab Coast route and will be passing through Bahrain from the 1st October. This will inevitably lead to a great increase in the Air Hail work,work demanding rapid action and careful calculations* rurther,the Government of India are arranging with the Gro vernment of the Hedjaz-Mejd to allow their mail bags to pass through this Post Ofi'ice on its way to the outside world. This will also add difficulties to an already busy post. llr.Bashiruddin is ir my opinion not up to his present duties and any addition to them will probably cause a break dom. I understand that a predecessor of his,a ilr.Zafar Ilusain wishes irreturn here,and siiice he is familiar with the lan^ua^es required and knows the people I would he glad if he could he posted here, 4. There aru two more points I wish to mention. I understaad that the allowances here have been reduced from Hs.60/- and Rs.50/- to Rs.lB/- whereas in Gv/adurjirasni and !uscat they have only been reduced to .is # 40/- and Rs.30/-. This is apparently in addition to the 10/o cut applied to all Government servants* Since the cost of living has not decreased .these officials are unfortunate in receiviijg an additional cut not applied to other departments in the &gt;ulf, hut there appears no justification for the invidious treat ment meted out to Bahrain, and it will render it diiiicult to find the right man for a post viiiidi is becoming increasing* ly arduous and and responsible. 5. The second poin: is z minor one but one which affects the efficiency of the . ost Office, Xhe Postman ^ssa,is being pensioned,willy nilly,and a successor is being sent from India. I received petitions from the leading merchants of Bahrain urging his retention rud informed the Superintend ent of Post Offices of this by telegram and also in another telegram warned him that any successor must be able to speak Arabic ani Persian. To neither of these telegrams did he vouchsafe a reply. I believe ~ssa is being forcibly pensioned though still able to serve some five years more. e is a very useful man and gets on well with the local merchants. Since it is extremely unlikely that a man can be found in India who knov/s the necessary languages it would appear far wiser to retain him aslong as possible especially in view of the increasing work that will shortly fall to this Post Office 6. I realise that the Post Office is a separate depar' with requirements and an organizaticsi of its own,and I no desire to intervene in matters which do not CQnce^igmm* —, Agency, rhe Bahrain Post Office is,however,closely connected with this Agency and any inefficiency in it inevitably reacts upon us. As a natter of fact I kave yet to see an activity of G-overnmait in Bahrain which does not affect the Agency sooner or later,and though it has been possible to assist other departments in the past,this, assistance is based on mutual cooperation,and a lack of cooperation would render its continuance difficult. Political Agent ^Bahrain,Corr.-40. Indian Posts and Telegraphs Department (T © No. Staff.3-6. F rom The Director of Posts and Telegraphs, Sind and Baluchistan Circle. To GOifflDiiNTIAL The Political Acent, Bahrein. Numler of enclosures Dated Ka achi ; the 2nd August 19 32 # Sir, In continuation of my letter ^ r o .S taf f .B-6, dated the 15th July 1932, I have the honour to inform you that orders have since issued transferring Hr.Bashirudin from Bahrein and posting Mr.Zaffar Kussain as desired. 2. The allowances at Bahrein have been abolished altogether and instead a special pay at a uniform rate of Ite.15/- P.M. has been sanctioned for each member of the clerical staff employed at Bahrein Post Office by the Government of India, Revision of allowance has nothing to do % with the 10/2 cut which has been ordered temporarily due to financial stingency. 3. As regards the retirement of T jssa Ahmed, Postman, Bahrein, I am to inform you that, he had a service of about 33 years in the Department and on account of the abolition of a good-many posts of postmen in the Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, due to retrenchment, he had to be retired compul- sorily,under the retrenchment scheme. A local man has since been ordered to act in his vacancy and this arrangement will it is hoped be found satisfactory. I have the honour to be, * Sir, Your most obedient servant, 1 i' Ah—IS iT—1-11-28. -2,60.000. M. Director.D.O.No.Staff.Z-3 CONFIDENTIAL Office of the Director,Posts and Telegraphs, Sind and Baluchistan Circle, Karachi, 28th May 1931. Dear Mr, Hasomal, I am desired by the Director to request you kindly to convey a warning under registered A.D # cover to Mr. Bashiruddin that his religious propensities and activities at Bahrein are a source of anxiety and embarrassment to the local people and the Government. He must abstain forthwith from any further religious zeel and do his work quietly and peace fully, end not further, or attempt to further, the interests of his particular religious sect. If after the receipt of thit warning any complaints reach this office, this official will be summarily transferred without any T.A. either to or from Bahrein. Please acknowledge the receipt of this letter. Yours sinoarely, Sd.C.Dickens. Hasomal Esq., S.P.Karachi. ' vWi assisf wt 'ir.ctor 0fp0st3 &amp; telecaph 1 ? w«oa,mKiiiAu«;cLujttS PHS -1 December 14, 1935, \jQxOt ^ The Bahrein Postmaster has recently been doing considerable extra work for us and will probably continue to do so during the next few months. Would there be any objection to my giving him a cash Xmas present? I had in mind something like / rupees. We have never done anything of this sort in Bahrein and would like to have your personal views before taking any such steps.14th December l.&gt;55« Will you kindly refer to your letter dated the 4th lecember 13^5 about a present for the Bahrain ^ub-?ost Master. It is very kind of you to think of such a thing, but I am afraid the Government Servants' Conduct -'Uxes do not permit his accepting presents. hat you can do, if you wish to mark your ap reclition of his v.ork, is to vrite to me on the subject. I v lll then for\ &amp;rd your letter to higher authority and the fact that he has v *on the appreciation of your ^om^any v.ill be noted in his favour when any question of promotion may arise. 1 .A.Skinner Tsquire. The Bahrain Petroleum Company limited, Bahrain,INDiAIN POSTS ANO TELECRAPHS DePARTMEiYF. ft t Prom, The Superintendent of Post offices, . lower aind and ^ersi.-.n Gulf iUvision. To Hie Political ^ent Bahrain. Ko B-76 t^der a bad Sivd ^ated the 10 •8.46 _ oir 5 ~w&lt;i l^ve the honour to say that it is under contemplation to/srchMge in the charge of Bahrain post office, and according th • the rotation of charges the Director i-osts g id Telegraphs Karachi has heen pleased to approve the appointment'of Mr. Bewanchand, ( lately Sub Postmaster Bela ) as 3ub Postmaster Bahrain. Tile present officiating incumbent will continue at Bahrain, but vould serve as cler^ Jdahrain. According to our dex-&gt;artmental rules , only the sub postmaster in Chc.rge is entitled to free quarters and as such, Mr. Rahmatullah who is patting up there with family vdll require rented accomodation for himself ard his family. It is requested that all possible help, may kindly be rendered to ^r. Rahmatullah for procuring- a house. I have eLc.j 3 u : 3 a .i ? j _ t 3 h a a xr t. 1' ic. . © Political Agency, Bahrain, the 18th August 1946. To The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Slnd and Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad, Slnd. Meg^or^Wn, Reference your letter IJo.3-76, dated the 10th August 1946# As regards the appointment of B£r. Dewan Chand as Sub-Postmaster, Bahrain, I would like to polat out that an official with a knowledge of iirabic is essential for this appointment. There is a considerable amount of,work in this Post Ox Lice and the common language is Arabic. 3. ift/ith reference to your request to help Mr. Rahmat Ullah find accomodation, I Must point out that there is an acute shortage of accomodation in Bahrain and the rents are very high. I do not consider that it will be possible for Mr. Rah r nat ill ah to find accomodation for his family, and I therefore suggest that he be allowed to remain in his present quarters. It would be far easier for Mr. Dewan Chand when ho comes to find accomodation as I understand he will not have a family with him. oV- loV Political Agent, Bahrain. NO. cy^/j</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000396_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/183</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000396</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/183</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 3/9 Staff of Post Office'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-07-23T00:08:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (13 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged approximately in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: There is one foliation sequence that runs from the front cover to the back cover and appears in pencil, circled, on the top right hand corner of the recto side of the folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between the British Political Agent at Bahrain; the Director of Posts and Telegraphs, Sind and Baluchistan, Karachi; E A Skinner, Chief Local Representative of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO); and the Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad, Sind.The correspondence of 1931-1932 concerns complaints of missionary activity and inefficiency against the Postmaster at Bahrain, Mr Bashiruddin; a request to replace him with Zafar Hussain in light of an anticipated increase in mail volume due to the opening of Imperial Airways Arab Coast route; the allowances paid to the Postmaster; and the position of Postman occupied by Essa Ahmed [‘Īsá Aḥmad]. In 1935, there is correspondence concerning a request by Skinner to give a cash Christmas present to the Bahrain Postmaster in consideration of extra work due to BAPCO's activities. Finally, correspondence in 1946 concerns the appointment of Mr Dewanchand as Sub Postmaster at Bahrain and the retention of Mr Rahmatullah as clerk with questions of accommodation and Arabic language requirements being raised.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000396#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>