<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000007_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-12T15:08:22.890Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No.S/45 hiy I thank you for your letter No .8/8/Sl/ '49 dat ed the 24th July 1949 and the Pakistan Military Academy’s Confidential Report on Pahar* ce^jz. SouLJ- (r^i~ Mr # R # Andrews, His Britannic Majesy’ s Acting Consul, Muscat*&lt;■% V A, ( 2 &gt; S' !70. ASO/S. 2 Baluch. Malir Cantt. 17 Julrr 1 49, Sir, ii x Ref: your letter No.6/8/51/49 of 3 May / Hie pay of a 2/Lieut in the Paidstan Army is Ra390/- Basic Pay, plus Ra.40/-/- Dearness Allowance. Ap Salyid Paher hin Taimur is a 2/lt; in principle, he should also draw the same amount i. e. R^390/-/-. I feel thatRswSSO/- are hardly enough for a young single officer to meet all his expense® particularly 16031186 the cost of living at the present moment is very high and the economic conditions are not yet quite normal. I therefore, recommend that it would he quite fair if 2/Lt Saiyid Paher lin Taimur is allowed an extra allowance 'between the range of 'is. 50/- to R^70/- a month in addition to the normal pay of a 2/Lieut. Your letter dated 3rd May 1949, for unknown reasons, reached here during the 1st week of July thereby causing all this delay in reply which_ is much regretted. y Lt-Col., Cond:2n^Sh, Ihe Baluch R^t. (AD2ANGZEB EHAN). The British Political Agent, Bae British Consulate, MUSCAT. L- // ',£ 71 &lt;- a M. ,!Telegram From To V Political, Muscat * Foreign, Karachi* No,965* Dated the 25th July, 1949* Restricted* It is understood that ijaiyid Fahar bin Taimur brother of the Sultan of iiuscat, is now undergoing training as Commissioned Officer with 2nd Baluch RegtIklir Cantonment* Sultan wishes to know (a? when period of training vdLll end, and (b) what pay and allowances he is receiving at the moment* Grateful for telegraphic reply* PoliticalBahrain. (53/30/49) Dear Agency, Enclosed her«lth is the Pakistan Military Academy^ Confidential Report on officer Cadet GC-65 Syed Fahar Bin Taimur Alsaid for onward transmission to the State authorities. Yours ever, RESIDENCY.T~- ■1 6/8/51/49. The British Corsxilate, Ilufirat • May 3, 1949, Sir, Saiyid Phher bin Taimur, brother of Hie Highness the Sultan of Muscat, who is a Conuaissioned Officer and is at present undergoing training in your unit, has made several requests for money to His Highness* 2* His Highness has therefore asked me to find out from you what pay and allosanoes the bey is receiving, whether in your opinion they are sufficient for his needs, and if not what you would regard as the minimum allowance which should be made to him. 3# The Sultan feels that if Saiyid Paher is receiving the same emoluments as his brother Officers, he should be able to manage as well as they do. 4* I should be grateful if you would give as the required information to enable sw to inform His Higiinees. I am, The Officer Commanding, 2nd Baluch Regiment, Malir Cantonment, Pakistan.Sultan* s brothor Saiyid Falior bin Talnrur koops on nending hl^n tslsgraniG askin' 1 : for noro monsy# You know that Saiyid Fahor has roc'sntly complotod a course at the Pakistan l.filitary Academy, boon c©missioned and is at present undergoing training with the 2nd. Baluch Regiment at lielir Cantonment near Karachi. u. M. His Highness would be grateful if you would bo so good as to find out from the boy* 3 Commanding Officer what pay and allowances ho is receiving at the present moment. Also whether he considers them to be adequate for the boy*s needs and if not what ha would regard as the minimum allowance which should be made t© him. If Saiyid Faher is receiving the seme emoluments as other young men like him and they menage to live on their pay His Highness feels that his brother should be able to do the same. R.S.jSllison Esq., His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat. /o/fdifLOsi* f 2 please refer to your letter No.8 (2/8/51/49) dated the 5rd* January 1949. We are glad to know that arrangements are being made to attach F&amp;her to an Infantiy Unit. please convey our thanks to the authorities concerned. Mr. R. E. Ellison, His Britannic Majesty»s Consul, ^ Muscat.Sultan Muscat,No. 2(2/8/51/49) British Consulate, Muscat• January 3, 1949 With reference ta ny letter No. C 431(8/51) y^i •f the 7th December, I have the honour ta inform Yarn* Highness that the Gavernraent of Pakistan are naw making arrangements to attach Your Highness' brather Saiyid Pahr ta an Infantry unit an termination af his course at the Infantry School. Your Highness' sincere friend His Highness Saiyid Said bin Tairaur, Sultan af Muscat and Oman, Muscat.Telegram From To No. Enclair Political Resident, Bahrain Political Agent, Muscat 65 Dated the 31st December received 1st January, 1949 ft It, sfei ' ^ f.fy telegram No. 49. Following from Foreign Karachi. Begins. Your telegram December 6th. Arrangements will be made to attach A1 Saiyid to Infantry unit on term ination of Infantry School course.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000007_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/232</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000007</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/232</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/51 II MUSCAT STATE AFFAIRS. SAIYID FAHR BIN TAIMUR.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-19T22:04:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (9 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 11; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file relates to Saiyid Faher bin Taimur [Fahr bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd], younger half-brother of the Sultan of Muscat and Oman [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd]. The file concerns training received by Saiyid Faher with the Baluch Regiment, Pakistan, after having recently completed a course at the Pakistan Military Academy. The correspondence, which mainly discusses Saiyid Faher's pay and allowance, features the following correspondents: the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Sultan of Muscat and Oman; the Commanding Officer of the 2nd Battalion of the Baluch Regiment, Pakistan.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Fahr bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Wages</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military training</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000007#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>