<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001a2_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T05:53:48.324Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">The Residency, '0.0. TTo . 190-3» But?liire, 2nd June 19^9 . ^7-v'i /. - u Li: ' CJHA*. Bear Murphy. ^ / Titli reference to your deni-off ic'ial le tter, Ho . 63-C.lof the 14th 1929, regarding he Sultan's house in 'Oehra 'Dun, the Government of India's reply (D.O. ^o. 989/777X .. 25th April 1923) seems to have been very decided. Wh^ dii| the Sultan purchase 'Hhanroclc' in the name of Shubai 1 i, when he wo aid probably have got his wish if he had approached Governnent correctly ? '/lien T met TTis Highness at Muscat he appeared to be labouring under a sense of grievance against the Govern ment of India, and stated categorically tha^jhe wc i d return once more to Muscat and would abdicate in 1930 in favour of any person that the Government of India night select. Is his treatment in this case the min cause of grievance; and in the event of the Government of India's meeting his wishes, is the Sultan likely to reconsider his decision to abdicate ? I fear yo ir answer will be a negative w / but p i x he question an a ballon d T jtssai . I suppose there would be no difficulty, if Govern ment of India approved, in getting fttiubaili to transfer the property to T T ic Highness either in his own proper name or that of Mr T. F. ?. ^aeed. Yours sincerel ,r . C.C.t T . 'Rarrett. G.T 5 . Tfurphy, I. A., olitical Agent, Muscat, Karachi.35/37 Telegram P. Political Agent Muscat ,Karachi Political Resident Bushire . T/81 . Dated 19th reed 20th July 1929 . Following has heen telegraphed to me 'by Sultan of Muscat: Ihave received your letter arriving Karachi Monday to see you . Reference is to your D.D. letter No 19(^f June 2nd . Murphy . Telegram From To ^0 693 Dated 20thh July 1929 . political Resident Bushire » Political Agent Muscat ,Karachi . received ?♦ What was contents of letter Sultan has Reference is to your telegram T8U Resident.abandon his resolve to abdicate , a nodific'ttion of $oveypaent^ attitude -ith re ard to his h.iiise ^ould be u very useful prelmins ry # His Tijhners -iehes to leave the house to his son by his Turkish ^ife. K.3. Snub, .ili as ures me there 'fould be no difficulty about his transferring the house to H.H. if the (rovernment of India ay proved.Copy of letter dated ICth .Tulv ^ ip/) from Fa jor P.l r urphy, Ipliticf 1 A( : ;ent ' .3.Consul, 1' itc t, to H.H.Sir £ i^ r id Ifltur bin S.i.-.il, K.G.I.J., O.S.T,, Sultan of Vuacat , Cta&amp;n« Dehra Dun. . / A, C, Your Hi-hness. T trust Your Highneps is enjoying the best of health. I have received a letter fron Colonel Barrett re jiertin^ me to ask Your Yi jiness whether your decision to abdicate in 1950 has'been brought rhout to any extent by the •tvitide of the Government of glndia over the' question of Your Highness ? s house at Dehra Dun and in the event of the ^overnt- nent of India meeting your -ishes is Your Hijiness likely to reconsider your decision to abdicate.. '• ! '^' a ^ t nad to oe said and may you be preserved and salaams.ip - i m =4^ Translation of a leftter dated 14th Safar 1348 . . ' ' ' » . . ' I y r ci.i. Aft' r Coraoliraents. On the loth Jvly I received at t)ehra Dun your 1 -.i- -r ' d ted 10th July 19' 9 ' hich you h,d despatched from Karachi ' .-hich you ••'ere asked hy Colonel Barrett to entire from me. ' « o -ro- -rt rtr^ Hpvs not. cr.?. tliifc idea since more th. n c yeaxfc ^ - : ed it -ould he to the interef t of ooth &gt;• rties. Ko the reas n of my abdication is not due to the Ul- ^.tment of t^e Government, of India V d their attitude to-ards me and my Government. I cannot de y their support to my Government and their attention to my interests as I expect from them. Undoubtedly I am confident that they-'buld continue y erson lly abdicate. x request you to assure my friend Colonel Barrett of ny resolve to abdicate about .'hioh I ^ informed him verbally __ . ' r , I have e^i'lained o .in during his visit to 1 uscat this .e.-. n-r -v 1 oiv. bo is due to my illness non that the reason of my uo - l - o ^- pv - ■ tte^din 1 - the incumhent diitie? f'v prevents me from atxe Government. You have stated'that perhaps I have been displeased &gt;n account of the objection of the political M.tnoiities Govern ent of India -rith regard to my house at Dehra Dim. • No it is not the case and you are apare of my decision h.fore ^ ■I I the (rovernment -^ould tre .t me favourably in the case of the house at Dehra Dun and other matters. In conclusion I hox^e that the friendly relations between Ar.onfldan*, lfi.1 P.O. Mo. MV-H- of J-0S9 British H«aidenco' and Coneula e-ncticral, Buehire, 6tti August i929. Will you plcafjc refer to nlr ^'rcclci ick 2: -M Johnston 's confidential Mo. 94 -a. of 2nd April for- I warding Murphy's «o. 40-C. of Uie iBtti ma dh. During my visit to Muscat the t'ulton raiccd the subject of his abdication and remained adamant in his resolve in spite of all my efforts to persuade hiia to alter his views. Ho says he will return to Muscat once more and after that he will abdicate In favour of uny body the British oovernocnt may select. I said that His Kajesty's Government might consider his son tiaid who is still a boy to be too young to succeed, and suggested that the Sultan might retain the rule until Raid reached the age of thirty. Suit an rainur was however unyielding and repeated that irC ms Ka^euty's Government considered Maid unsuitable they could select somebody else. It is obvious, however, that j.e Kuitan Bir Denye Bray, K.C.l.l 7 ., O.B.K., Foreign r.eoretary to the Government of India, Simla*Sultan raimur personaily. He thinkB tlie Britiwh GoYcmraent care nothing for him and hie dignity (thio in epite of his official welcome to Kngland last year). . A little matter jparticularly irritates him. It is the pinpric&amp;D of life uhich bo often do. In 1920 llio Highneoe purcJiaaed a houoe in 3&gt;e Dun. He informf^ liurphy that he firot broached the aubject of the purcliaae to Captain ucCollum, vho was hio Vazier dej?uted by A. T. Wiloon from Iraq. lioCollum said there ehould be no difficulty about the purcliaae. He entered into negotiation® for the pur- chaae of the houee by instalment a and the receipt for the first inatalzaent was made in his own name. later received a verbal message from ttcCollum aent through one of his own servunto to the effect that the Government of India would not concent to his owning a house in JDehra Dun in hio own name and that he would have to put it in some one el8c*s name. As he had already paid a part of the purchase money he felt him self bound to complete the transaction and did no, pur chasing in the name of his i&gt;ccretary tihubaili. His Highness wishes hia son.by his mrkish wife to inherit this house; and fthubaili assures aurphy that there would be no difficulty about transferring the house to Ilia Highneas if the Governnent of India approved. His Highnesa informed me that although he could trust fUiubaili to carry out hio wisi^s, there is no knowing what difficulties lawyers and executors might raise in the future. His Highness does not mention the whole atory. It appears from the Hesiaency files that lie liad informed Wingate that he had found a suitable house at J)ehra T)un and- tfti ^ and that ^ingatc replied on the 15th October 1920 oivying: w nie Covernnent of India desire ne to inform 'Your Righneee that the general policy of the aovernmcnt 'of India is opposed to the grant of pemieoion to 'purohaoe land in India by independent rulero and tiiat, therefore 9 sanction cen only be given for the lease of a hou»e by Your Migliness at Dehra i)un or elsewhere.' There lias also been some demi-official cor respondence between Trevor and Howell. The last letter on the file i6 Howell's ^.0. Ho.989/777-&gt;:. # dated tlie 25th April 1923, in which he declined to help. Years have elapsed and Govermwnt nay perchance have modified their attitude towards r &gt;ultan Taimur. I certainly think Uiat his abdication next year would be unfortunate, especially as the Mtate lias been deprived by death of the services of Haiyid Uohammed, late Wali of xmttrah, the mo^t sensible roan on i he Btate Council. Uajor Kurphy d(^s not think that permission to hold his Dehra t&gt;un house in his own nane is tlie only or even the chief cause of the Huitan^s desire to ab dicate, but at ihe sarie tine he considers 'if iie Hultan 'is to be ijOrsuaded to abandon hlB resolve, a nodifica- ftion of Government's attitude with regard to his house 'would be a very useful preliminary*. I think it would be a &amp;ood move to grant the rul tan the permission he a till seeks — to hold the Dehra T)un house in his own name, — but i do not know how strongly Government hold to xheir policy of 1920. Is it any good returning to the charge - This small matter may possibly prove a starting point to induce the vain and idle puppet, as wingate called him, to a change of view, though the road must be long and difficult. In 1920 the Tultan was smarting under a serious defeat. Murphy lias a very high opinion of his abilities andand thinks that under fairer circunstancea he would have made an acUftirahle ruler# Hia childi&amp;h plcvi ii - neae aeeirus to hira the cloak of a deeper peraonality. The queation of tlie aucceaaion may have to be taken up shortly, I Uiink our beat courae ia to attempt to postpone it till we can see how young Said ahapes. There are some alight aigna of a rapproachemcnt with the interior, in apite of th® blood feud and the f ultan'a fear of aaaaa ^inatiendowing to joint fear of Win Baud. If young Haid turns out well, as 1 hope he will, there ia a poaaibility, though no probability ao far as 1 can aee, that he may at some future date reaume posaeasion ox tlie Arabian portion oi his great naneaake^ inheritance.X , ,v: I 336- d. o. ito.^t'. mm- v29 • ? f J . Foreign and Political Department, Simla; The September ^29. I am desired to refer to your D.0, l\o,517-S of 6th. August MW, regarding the Sultan of iiuscat^ revival of his proposal to abdicate. 2. However embarrassing the abdication might still be in the absence of a successor less immature than Said, the Government of India realise that it may not be possible much longer to prevent the Sultan from accomplishing his intention. 3. Said is apparently the only suitable candidate, but the Government of India would not without grave reason be prepared to contemplate a formal departure from the rule of election, broken though it was in the present Sultan's own case in the special circumstances of the tribal rebellion in the midst of which he succeeded to the Sul tanate. Gould Said's election be counted on? 4. If the Sultan abdicates soon and Said succeeds him, I am to suggest that the most satisfactory arrangement (though there might be difficulties over this in view of his being no longer technically a minor under Muslim law) v might be for the young Sultan at the outset to exercise power through a Council of Regency, as suggested in (7^ Cav Wingate's letter 1 ^0 .898 of 28th April 1920.5. Ve should also have to consider carefully the question of finance; for His Highness would probably claim a handsome allowance which, since his successor would doubtless be averse from a proportionate retrenchment of his privy purse, might go far to consume even the proceeds of the new Customs Tariff increase should it prove feasible. 6. The question of the purchase of the Dehra Dun house is being reexamined here as expeditiously as possiole, but should it be proposed to accede now, for the reasons you give, to His Highness 1 request, it would be necessary to consult the United Provinces Government, and this would take some little time. In the meantime I am to say you might consider the points raised above and let the Govern ment of India have your views. x O'; Lieutenant Colonel C.C.J.Barrett, C.S.I.&gt; C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. (With 1 spare copy)oonf identic x s \ * [uJL 3fi' 5W ] us cat I d til xiove oer 1^ 2^ &gt; »«* BUSHIP^ RfiefOCNCY. 'oU) Mc Hn.J.P'.t a^/^L - .'itii reference to your T.C.l , To.52E-i' ■J. i**#? forwarding a copy of Aclieson's T)•u•^-lo.i^ , . 334 of 2.4tJa aepteiaber and caJ.iin^ for my vrev/s# Tiie statement that tne rule of succession is 'by rigJat of ay election seema to r e to Toe based on misconception and is not 'borne oat historically* According to tiie tenets of tne ibadni sectjtiieir reiigiotis iiead is elected; but tiie gradual modification in tiie system of elect- -icn -.vnich nad taicen i-piace duni^ tne Yaaraban dynasty, appears to nave weakened tuie power and spiritual control over tne country wnicJa former Imatis iaad exercised* The contests for the succession ~ave birth to the xiinawi and uhafiri factions - a source of aunarcny whicn 1*o||p of the later rulers of Oew have been able to suppress and very few to control. In 1737, the imam t&gt;eif bin Sultan,finding himself hcvrd pressed by a co. petitor sou_.it the aid of tie rer^ians ..no soon overrun t.:: v/hole of Crnian* Jaced by a coj non danger,the vmanis elected a strong man^ u .~t bin baid, ti.e founder of tne present dynasty^ as jL.iam® On his deatn in 1763,the elective system once more proved ineffective when oaid bin Aumed was chosen chiefly because of his weaimess and imbecility^ bince i7o4,tne rulers of Oman have derived tneir authority through the support of one or other of the two political factions, Hinawi or Ghafiri,obtained by bribery or other causes»They have never exercised effective control over tne whole country nor have they assumed the title of Imam which is recognised as a religious and else- -tive dignity, ihe rule of succession may therefore be said to be by force of arms ratner tnan by election. me non 1 ble Lieut.uoi^u.u.J.Barrett % U* # b ^ * . x .--i . v.* . o . x • &gt; roliticai rtesident in the jt-ersian uuif j^usnire.rtior to oeayi-d xaionix's acce3sion .,(jovernj.aent's attitude was tnaftaey would view with, satisfaction the succession in iaaua. of one 01 tiie ues- -oendants of Saiyid baid provided ne were capable of presc-rTina mter- -nax order, conducting tlie (iovernnent of tne State and upholding existing relations between Muscat and tiie ari-xsh GoTe. -.nt tut t-it tjie succession must be settled by tne chiefs and people of the country', foreign secretary to Hesident dated June lodl; • xn o/tiier words / uoverniient reaognized tne de facto ruler after ne Jaad succeeded in estaoxisnxng nxmst-.-* In the case of Saiyj-d Xainur.the position was somewhat different. iOis tribes / botn Simmt and Lrhafir^ were in rebellion;ostensicly Rowing to tne Arms ,areaouse,and we were forced to recognize ni^even though he nad not succeeded in establisning himself ./ith the interior tnuea. sfith tne formation of a separate administration in the inte-icr,tie pooit-ton remaxns tne same to». ay» it seems to me tnat to introduce a system of election jmcn nas %een in abeyance for close on a hundred and fifty years would be a dangerous innovation^wmlst to call upon tne various members of tne Bultan's family to establish themselves by force of arms seems equally unthinkable. Az best it could merely result in a process of eiiminatio by assasination such as is taxing place at Abu Dhabi, .-resumapiy we could do would be to satisfy ourselves tnat aaiyid aaid is the most suitable candidate and the one wnose succession is most lilceiy to commend itself to the rignt minded portion of tne population, ^f tnis I thirus: there can be little doubt.ne is already acknowledged as heir apparent tnroughout the sultanate whilst ne is being addressed as such by Isa bin salen wno is avowedly well disposed towards nmu The administrtion of the country is being carried out, at pre Bant, by a Council of ministers who might be said to be tne equivalent of a Council of itegency. oaiyid said is now tne rresident of tnis Cioun- -cil,virtually acting as itegent for ms father. At the end of next year,tne possible date of the sultan 's %Ddi- -cation, saiyid said will nave been acting as x-resi .ent of tne uoun- -cil for lo inontns and will be approaching nis 21st oirt -aay. Wingate 1 s proposal appears to have been applicable in U2o when baiyid baid was 10 years olda The situation is certainly a delicate one. Whilst or: the oneiiand, tnere are cat ions of a rapproacnment ..xtn tne interior an:, a pocoi.ility that daiyid yaid may^at sone future date^reaune poasession of tiie Arabitoi portion of his ^reat namesake^ inlieri- -tance; on tne otner hand,tne gradual disintegration which has been talcing place OY/in^ to financial stringency and lacic of personal rule,might eventually result in the reduction of the btate to a r/iuscat - ii'iatrah enclave* ±sy attenptj.11^ tc cut^oaiyid oaid 1 s autiiority after he has as^ lj 3 q . tiie aul.«'e ..ouid, it seems to jae, not only I x imsJi /*rpu&lt;i and independent spirit of his subjects who looic for personal rule. The problem finance Jill need careful consideration, '.vith ^ ^u-'^ci . igcrous bultan instsulled in place of an absentee one, the cost of his tribal tours and enterti innent of ahei^chs ./ill inevitably be a consiberable ne.f item of expenditure. 1 v.ould the re-J -fore advocate the retention of present arrangements.as far as / pos^ible^ uatil such time as the new customs increase may permi't i&gt;j u iyi^ oaid to stcurt off his rule under favourable auspices. -t a v^ch a note givi ig details regarding the successions of previous Sultans,fs iii order to atrenstoea nis position,jae eat itJU^ned ru.0 aona in icey positions tarougiiout Oman,gave tnem civil poaer said con- -ferred on tnem tiie txtie ox beyyxds or j^nnces. . : ?J:ie results f iere \;Qrse tnan disappointing# jJuring nis lifetime Jxe iiad not only constantly to intervene to settle tneir quarrels itn eacn otner out ne nad even to defend iniiiself against tneir coja- 1 oined attacks upon nis o.m position^ * Tiie jiouse of beyyids' like tho. rei^ninc iiou-es of jsuto- •pe, nas become a recognized dynasty; but tne _radual increase in tne number of rival and aspiring Seyyids lias been one fer- source of intestinal -txi^ffeuds wiiicii nave arrested tne prosperity of tne ccmitryo On An22ied t s deatn, tne successful candidate \.a3 a roan of 11: ited capacity - Aimed 1 s second L.on Said - a iiian who bad played an undignified and passive part in tiie dissensions between tne late imam and nis sons beif and bultan, arkiwno subsequently sanK into a letn&amp;r c :ic state not far removed Trom imbecility. To quote Keute ; - a it ray be wondered at that the weakest of tne cc apetitors snould so easily w ^in tne pn^e &gt; 'eut CMl^tain subtle/ considerations must be ta-:en into account. Oman is a country in men sense of co men race is sub- •ordinate to sense of common clan or cc^.'ton ic^.ily * ^ere exists , in time of stress &gt; an unusual capacity to sinic tnese differences in face of a common x'oe a . ~ t is it is perhaps men nas distinguished the omani from tneir brother Arabs, rsut peace is tne testing time and tnen tne ./eaJcer tne central power tne L reat_r the scope for unlimited freedom of indivi - -dual action. In view of tnis it is pern .ps tne less curious tnat in time of tranquility and in the absence of danger from /itnout a candidc te snould succeed on tne strength of his weaicness rather than tne t of nis virtues'. St.id bin iUaiied was tne laet genuine elected Iiam of O i ..:an and alsctixe ia.it ruler o^tUat country to rearde in liusta^. The supreme power of tue «M«as M te».di^ to lose spiritual ar.d ^ain tem- -poral aspects. 'JSiere liad been a tiae, undoubtedly-dien tue sway ■ r * 1 11 - ; lts ; os^ue.tiie reli^ic-.irf centre of tte cou .t] y some, S Had at any rate figura tire significance as implyxiig tee control ofAtan. H ub was c. ..arng to be „ ^ the TOaiaiC33 of g Lii Mn ^ed -as increased by tee veryZaccessibility of bis position 1 at Hustaq vvnicb. proved n^no' leas tean bis protection. About 1784 / the temporal po.ver .&lt;as usurped by Said'a son .am.:, named irikciueTing bis usurption bad recourse to intrigue ano. deceit, but ne refr^ed from violence and Jus couduct may be excused on toe ground of bis father's incompetence and of tee impossibility of mar,taming tbe ascendency of tee family by any aiB reign, was disterbed by tbe efforts made by bis uncles beif and oultan to obtain tne mastery. .vio-r nameu's deate.tae Imam Abmed made a sbort lived effort to assert nimseif but oa^id Sultan soon made nimaelf master of tne country. In 1604 sultan was snot *iulst carrying ^ -ut operations at sea against the *ababis. i^or a time after nis ueate atable government ceased to exist but ^adar bin Self final- -ly auccscdtd in assertii^ biBself with tee aid of the Wahabis, uo? ...-.r was assasmated by his nephew Said. This | action p/of said'a/3 ^ was generally applauded arid accepted as a pro or of jiia capacity to ruie e caid died in lobe. At tue time of ius death his son xhu.,ai:* was tee de facto ruler in Muscat whilst his son aajid was ruling 'analbar and a maritime conflict between them ..as prevented and teeir claims adjudicated by the British uovemment. The claim of aiyi;. iuxxi to tne independent possession of sohar was negatived by Government at tne saiae time. xn lo.b xnuwaini was asaasinated by his son Salim who assumed tiie ouJLtanate,. In 1 ■■o Azaan bin -ais organized a re^eiiion and expelled Salim^ j-ii x /I Turici organized a rebellf on ^ , .vzjan ..as iciiled in the7^ attach on Liiiscali and iiirtri ajsuiaed tne t&gt;ultaiia ue^ in iwliUjji'L.iaa± seized tne po r wer on TuridL 1 * dentin and contrary to ^enerc;x expectation no disturbance of tLie jener^i peace tooJ£ piace© riie unusxai quiet tnat prevaiied subsequent to Saxyid xur- w&lt;w •kl's dentil attributed by the acting i^olijiical Agent^ to the uncertainty in tiie minds of the people as to whether Govern- -ment would, man tain tae policy of active support promised to Sayid Tur :i in 13^6 or not© a fiaiyid Abdul .^iz/brother of tiaiyrd Turi^i^who had made many unsuccessful attempts to obtain the sovereignty but had irfi* jc : frujtratidL 'ty our n terve^tion «iiote A '.cesiaent ciaii..iii^ the inheritance and asJcin^ ichat were tiie iij-tentions oi tfovern*' •Hsient and received a reply that tne interests of G-overni-'ent vie re chiefly concerned in tne man te nance of tranquility and ; ■ t ie prosperity of tne people under rule 15 o ^tnuir o n cnoice^ ' jfaiiin. to obtain a more definite explanation saiyid Abdul J Azia. *.rote a ratner remariiabie letter to tiie political Ajent •^x.earn tnat if the people of Oi.^n had regulations or even senae to understand tne advantages and honour and ease .1 ttOcrue to tneiu from, the chasing by them of rubers who would stren^tnen tiie pillars of their icin ^dom^improve then country,attend to the welfare of the people and endeavour to direct them for their o..n ^ocd^as is the custon a' 01 0 st otl.er 3f %l&lt;- peoples they would doubtless be in the greatest prosperity^ and peace such as is the desire of tne ^reat Government ^'but between tne desire of tne jan^lish government and tne condition of the people of Oman tnere is a ^reat difficulty^ for wbat are tne peo„le of Oman except miseraole animals who follow any one wno calls to tnern^ v/no turn wltn every breese^who are unillumed by tne lignt of learning and nave not through it sougnt the safety of a it: ong prop^ then how can one e.^ect tiiem to have tne icnov/ledge and ability to choose fit rulers* verily they ^niy flee from rulers and from laws as they would from a. lion^and truly tneir highest de£ilre is that one should rule nver them U10 is weak in intellect^poor in judc© lent and vit: - —— J, ^ v/itnout energy -alio , ill neitiaer cojuiuand nor forbid and so that eacJi one ; ay be a separate ruler and engage in strife and tJae spreading of discord tnat there snail be no one to stop them, that tne fttrOng raay oppress tiie weaK^tiien v/ili tiie land and its 4- stoc-K be ruined and suad are tneir doings at present© (uay God 1 s .rath not overtake them) I asJc how can tLere be ex- -pected from people in such a condition good deeds and the choosing of rulers fit to £uide tneDl• , . In lalS^on H-aisal's death^nls eldest son Tairiiur assumed the rule without protests ' .uOte&gt; OisJi^ln fcvCt^has been passing through tne sar:ie stages of evolution as tooic ^lace in -fene tcingctoma of tne eastern and vestern ivranxa duri: ^ tne middle aoes^when the systen. of election jraluaiiy underv/ent modificatxonline nistory of uiovis^too, could been written about a modern ^j:ati potentate^ ^y trea- -cnery or cattle ne soon destroyed all his icinsmen ..ho were or mignt be rulers , M xieTertheie£s M to quote Gregory M in a general assembic-ge ne is said to nave spoicen concerning the icinsmen wnom ne nad ninseif destroyed ' .v^e is me v /ho ha^remamed nice a pilgrim aiiong foreigners^and have no icinsmen t^ aid me if ad- -versity befalis me il uut he said thia not because he grieved ■ cunning at their ueath but vvith the, thought tliat ne ; Li^lit per- -naps find one still alive wnom he could icill , % o Tne present regime in tne interior with Shfiiidi Isa bin f c&gt;aleii and a puppet 1 am^may be 11 cened to t^ie i^ayora of the ±ulace during the regime of tne later l erovingian ivings.■ 35/135. P. SGcrstary of* Stiat.. ror India, London, Grovernment of India, !&gt;ew Delhi. No 3j74. Political Hesident, Bustiire. l T o 3 375. Dated 26tlx reed 27th November 1929. rr 'M + fr .1 n 'please see my Political despatch ' T o p 6143-133 November 23tli para 2. ?. Acheson's 1 - t* Barrett 7 334-N 29' of September 24th. Please let mo have your considered views on receipt of Residents leply. If Sultan ahdica^ed not only would he expest an allowance hut as matters stand arms traffic subsidy ceases with tenure of power hy him. ^-Should increase in tariff go through ; effect on Muscat finances would clearly he very serious and presS^ to postpone abdication may have .o he considered. Ahove refers to your Secretary's letter ol September 4th No F225-N. Secretary of State for India. ^ f j-.Confidential No. 68a-n of 1929. Britieh Hifuidency stnd Conuulai te-Gert eral, Butshlr®, 26th Peceinbtr 1929. - From The Hon'ble Lt.-Colonel 11. V. Bincoe, i^olitical l^eBicierit in tiie i'erKiuiii Gulf, To The Foreign Secretary to the Covernnrnt of India, New Delhi. Sir, I have the honour to solicit a reference Lo the eorreaponclence ending wi Ui telegram Ho. 5674 # dated uiie ! 6th Noyember 1929, from the Secretary of State for India to you, regarding the deaire of Hi* Highnean 4he Sultan of liurcat to abdicate. I have recently paid a vit it to Muacat wiiere 1 had the pleasure of making the acquaintance of Ilia llighneaa whom I hfjd not previoualy met, and was glad to find him looking well and on the wiiole in good apirita. 2. On my arrival in iiuaait I wan inforntd by iajor Tlurphy Uiat Ilia Highneaa liad returned to .'luacat early in NoTenber and had aince been taking greater intereat in the affaira of the atate tlian on any previoua occaaion within recent times. Ilia Hi guinea a had i^iid a viait in his &gt;acht to tiie Ratineh court anci anoUier viait t.A Cur and waa con templating a trip to Dhofar, and Major rurphy waa inclined to think that for the moment at any rate Hiu highneaa had giyen up hia intention to atxlicate. Mr honan, the a^ir, while agreeing that Hia llighneaa waa taking greater intereat i in atate affaira than forncrly told me thayie waa convinted that he waa a till firm in hia reaolve to afcxiictte at an early date and would Mention tlie matter to me during our interview/JO - 2 - intcrTieii. And having regard to the statenent made by Hia Highness to Colonel Barrett a fevr months ago I vient to see His Highness expecting to be confronted by something in the nature of an ultimatum: I am glad to be able to report, howeTer, that these anticipations were not fulfilled and that my interyieyr viith His Highness was on the vdiole satisfactory. 3, As already stated I found His Highness looking much better than I anticipated arid after complimenting him on his appearance and on the fact that he had been able to visit various outlying portions of his state, I turned the conversation to the subject of finance. The state financial year coincides with the calendar year; and Major Murphy had informed me that despite the strictest economy he anti cipated that the year would close with a deficit of Ks. 7P00 or 8,000, His Highness stated that in his opinion it was essential that measures should be taxen to increase the revenues of the state and expressed the very earnest hope that His Majesty's Government would obtain the consent of the French and American Governments wi thout further delay to the increase in the customs duty. I infomied him that I did not know exactly how the matter stood but that I agreed with him that it was essential that something should be done to enable the state to pay its way and would represent his wishes to Government. 4. His Highness then went on to discuss Sur affairs. He had himself visited Sur recently and endeavoured to arrivi at a settlement with Shaikh Ali bin Abdullah,the so-called Amir of Jaalan of the Beni Bu Ali tribe,who was still levy ing unauthorised customs duties at Sur and flying a flag which though of the Wahabi colours the Amir has always stated is not a Wahabi flag but his own flag. His Highness stated that he had informed the Amir that he had no desire to interfere in tribal affairs in the interior of the country but that the Amir must cease all interference in the 1. • • I &lt; ■ ■ ■the affairs of 'ur. The latter hoviever had refused to agree and the negotiations had proyed abortiye. his Highness expressed the Tiew that the Ainir thought thoTthe Gorernraent of India were not ready to support the authority of the Muscat state and was convinced that he could defy the Sultan with impunity. The bombardment by H.M.S.'Cyclamen' last year had very little effect. The ship had simply knocked down a small fort belonging to the Muscat stateafter it had been evacuated by the Beni Bu AJ.i # and had then sailed away, and after its departure the Beni Bu \li had resumed their occupation of the customs house and rehoisted the flag, I asked His highness what measures he thought should be taken and he stated that he thought it would have a good effect if the customs house were knocked down by one of His Majesty's ships. I then asked him whether the result would not be the same as before, namely, that after the departure of the ship the Bani Bu Hi would again impose their customs control at Sur occupying if necessary some other building for the purpose. His Highness agreed that this would probably be so and said that in his opinion it would be necessary for troops to occupy Sur for a certain period. 1 replied that in my opinion the Government of India would raa only agree to despatch troops in the last resort since the cost would be out of all proportion to the importance of the natter. After some discussion His Highness admitted the fo rce of this ano stated that in his opinion i^ would have an enor mous effect if air action Cwuld be taken in conjunction with a naval bombardment. The Beni Bu Ali were a very primitive people! the moral effect would be considerable! it would not be necessary for the aeroplane or the flying boat to cause any casualities but if it also dropped some bombs on the customs house while the ship was knocking it down it would impress upon the Beni Bu Ali that His Majesty^ Government on the present occasion meant business and couldI - 4 - could reach tlnein not only on the coast 'but also if necessary inland from the air. 5. His Highness then went on the say that before resortir(; to these drastic measures he thought that the negotiations that he had initiated might be continued though in a different form. In September last the Amir of Jaalan yisited Aden and submitted to the Kesident and Commander-in-Chief there a letter addressed to Colonel Barrett. In this letter the Amir claimed that the Muscat state had no right to interfere in the Ghafiri country: that if the Political Agent at Muscat wished to see him he should come to Sur for the purpose: that letters should come direct and not through the Muscat authorities and finally asked that he should be permitted to issue passports and also allowed to import 300 Mauser rifles. In short it virtually amounted to a demand to be recognised as independent of Muscat, and I have Just received a report from the Political Agent at Muscat that Shaikh Ali bin &gt; Abdullah has since his return been issuing printed travell ing permits purporting to be issued by the Government of Jaltlan and its dependencies. These permits have been signed and sealed by the Shaikh but have been distributed blank for all and sundry to fill in as required. A copy of Shaikh Ali^s letter was forwarded to the Political Agent at Muscat and he was told tiiat in case any further enquiries were made by Sur he should reply that no repre sentations would be considered unless submitted through the Muscat Governmentr Uo further enquiries have, however, beew made from Sur and the letter has remained unacknowledged. His Highness informed me that he thought Shaikh Ali was waiting to see what reply the British authorities were going to give tnd that this was one of the reasons why the discussions with him had proved abortive and the Amir had maintained his recalcitrant attitude. His Highness asked if I would send a reply refuting the claim to independence andKb j m n . B -J - b - il and calling on ttie vnir to ref*ain from interfering on the coast. I aBKed His Highneua to let me haire in writing the exact tenor of the reply he wished me to give and also eniiuired whether he would prefer that the reply should be sent through the Muscat State authorities. His Highness said he would do so and I am expecting a letter from him ^ on the subject shortly but stated that it would be prefer able that I should write to the Awir direct instead of through the Muscat authorities. I propose therefore on receipt of His Highness 1 communication to address a letter to the Amir calling on him to abstain from any interference at Sur and informing him that he lias no right to issue passports, etc. I am not very hopeful that this letter will have much efftect but it will, at any rate, fill in the time till a definite decision is arrived atjregarding the measures to be taken at Sur, and the \mir will have been seriously warned before more drastic measux^eb ar^ resorted to; also. His Highness will know that something is being done in the matter and will be encouraged to contain his soul in patience for a short time longer. XfteT we had concluded our discussion ot Sur affairs I asked His Highness sonwwhkt pointedly whether there were any other matters which he wished to discuss and to my surprise he stated that there were none and accord ingly after a few platitudes I took my leave. 7 # it is difficult to account for His Highness' apparent change of attitude and intention and 1 do not think that he has altogether given up his intention to abdicate. I am inclined rather to think that in view of the fact that a new Political Resident has come to the Gulf and one who has never formerly held the post ol Political Agent at Muscat or taken any part in Muscat affairs, and who may possibly hold the post for a somewhat longer period than some of his immediate predecessors. His Highness is disposed for the time being to adopt awaiting attitude, and to see whether the new Kesident will be able to do smnething to remedy his fancied grieTances, before finally and definitely abdicating. His desire to abdicate is, I believe, largely due to his alleged grieTances against the British Government and their . local representatives in the past. He thinks that an Opportunity offered for recovering inland Oman after the repulse by Indian troops of Isa Bin Salens attack on Muttrah in 191b and that it was the British government who refused to allow him to take advantage of it thus humbling him before Isa bin Saleh with whom and his family he has a long-standing blood feud, and he further considers that he has not been adequately supported over Sur affairs. If the two matters to which he attaches importance, namely, the re-habilitation oflthe finances of his state and the re-establishmen t of his authority on the coast can be settled to his satisfaction, I have hopes— though it is much too soon yet to express a definite opinion — that His Highness may take a renewed interest in the ait airs of his state and that it may be possible to ward off for some years at any rate the long -threatened abdication. 8 « Just as I was in the course of drafting this despatch I received a copy of letter flo. P. 6148 of the 28th November 1929 from the India Office to you and am glad that His Majesty^ Government are fully apprised of xht necessity for the increase of the customs tariff. I am at once consulting the Political Agent as to the possibility of increasing the taritf on goods other than those covered by the terms of the treaties with America, Prance and the Netherlands• bliouid this be feasible, I would strongly urge that the enhanced tariff should be brought into effect as soon as possible and that negotiations should then be opened with France and the United States to obtain theirtheir agreement to the Icry of a similar duty on any goode which may be imported from those countries. At present the state cannot pay its way: and even the Levy Corps which is essential for its defence cannot be main tained at full strength. With the additional ilinds thus obtained this could be done^while some money would be available to ^nable His Highness to entertain in suitable style and to show customary hospitality to fhe tribal Shaikhs in the interior, thereby increasing his influence and perhaps, in course of time, enabling him to gain some measure of authority. 9, As regards Sur, the British Government have always undertaken to maintain the authority of the Muscat State on the coast while refusing to be drawn into quarrels in the interior. It seems essential in pur suance of this policy to re-establish the authority of the Sultan at Sur. His Highness* suggestion that air action should be combined with a naval bombardment sounds, perhaps from a purely utilitarian point of ¥iew, somewhat ridiculous: I believe however that the moral effect would be considerable. I met the Senior tlaval Officer at Henjam on the 19th of December and discussed the matter with him. He expressed the view that there would be no difficulty in knocking do \*n the customs house estab lished by the Amir of Jaalan without damaging the rest of the town since it was an isolated building, and was also inclined to agree that the presence of a flying boat would have a great moral effect. 1 could consult the Air Officer Commanding if so desired and let you know his views. If, as I anticipate, my letter to the Amir of Jaalan has no effect then I suggest that the Sultan of Muscat should proaeed to Sur in his own yacht accompanied by the Political Agent on board one of His Majesty's sloops and, if possible, a flying boat. The Sultan would then open negotiations with the Shaikh of the Beni- b « 1 -'j Peni ^tu All and unlcae the latter Hgreeti finully to abandon all hie pretentions zo interference in Our affuira ilia Highneae would be at liberty to call on Hit) Jflajeaty'a ship and a flying boat ; through the Political A^-ent^to des troy the euatoms houae after diir warning. 1 belirve the tireacnce oi' tlje rultan supported by the arrjed naral and air forces of the British Government would finally con- Tince the Amir of Jaalan tiuit His Majesty v s Oovernmil nun, in earnest and that he mist abandon his irretentions to com plete independence of iuuscat (rjd must withdraw to his native hilln* 'he rultan, witn a state t)«at was at any rate solvent a a little monev in his treasury to finable him to raaintain his position as *n Arab ruler, and his author* ity to some extent re-established, and confident that he could rely on the support of His Majesty 9 * Government in the future, might chfin^e his whole outlook towards life, and continue to occupy the Muscat throne for raany years to corae. : ven if he did not do so and we were ultimately compelled to a^ree to his abdication, these measures would enormously tacilitate the task of his young arid ino^rien— ced son and enable him to commence his reign in more favour able circumstances than would a^ present be the cute. Both on account ol the position ol'huscnt at the entrance or the Gulf and of the projected air route it would seem essential to maintain the stability of the state, and I would therefore urge that we should strike while the iron is hot and that an early desision should be taken on these two questions. i i0, 2 on sei*.. ing a uopy of this dp 8, ;&gt;1, ch to IJ in WaJeaty 'b Rtcretury of :5tate for imitt. X have the honour to be, N Sir, Your most obedient servant, //V Lt.-Colonel, Political lesii ent in Uie 3eri4l ,ir) Gulf,- 2 - &amp; * 9 '''iT'-js m ' been elected. 'hie point i» brought out by a )riwer. Writn*; of tiie clian^eo initiated by llaifad i7B4—92 ( Guzett eer, Vol. X, p. 419? he otatea 'A tei^ency towax-ciB heredltar aoverei^nty waw confirmed under the lirnt 'loileru of the Al 3u Haidi line * and later deBcribes the regime an one of 'iraperfect heredity'. In his account of Azzan'w reign however he writea (p. 485j •nearly in hin rei^n Azzan tjeema to iiavtf been proclained M * Imam* by hiM x^rieeti^ eupi^ortero: but it doru not 'appear tnat Uic title, though often applied to him, 'ever received ti c needful ratification of tiie tribco 'ao a w)jole w . ''his view its borne out by the hiutory of uucat, fol since the death of Imam .Uxraad bin r&gt;aid 17B5, the la«t ruler who rms altio definitely regarded ao an liatim, not one of the Gultano of Uuneat haa been elected. It ic true ti.at Aluaad waa succeeded by raid, #ho, aa Lorimer aaya, was ll* genui^ine elected 1mm of Oman • He abdicated the Sultanate however after a few montna in favour of hia aon Hamad, but up to the tine of hia death which did not occur till long afterwarda in Uie reign of Haid bin Tultan, he continued to enjoy the title of Imam, which ^howa that from now on the Irnamate and the Gultanate were definitely •eparated. Up to lUimad'a reign the capital of Muscat waa RuatacjJ the elected Imaraa of Oman ruled there and maintained a considerable ncaaure of authority over the whole country, Muacat beinf, merely the i&gt;ort. Hamad, however, transferred the capital to i 'uacut, and since then tiie Bui tans of Huacat have no longer been recog nised a^J Irmms and their aulJliority over ill# tribes of the interior has steadily deaJLined. It1744-65 1783 |l - 3 • It may not bi? ainiBB to rttcorcl briefly In tabular form the nrthodB of sucueDKion In i-iusca t tiinav irnarn ,Ahmad. Tie v ted lutna. Imam Alunad. Haia bin \hrrsicl. 1784-92 1792-1804 1804-07 1807-b6 i8b6-66 1866-68 1868-71 1871-88 1888-1913 Hamad bin Said Hultan bin ^iraad Badar bin Haif Bald bin Sultun 'huwaini bin Saiu •lalira bin ^hiiwaini Azzan bin ^aio ''urki bin Raid J^aieal bin 'urlci l leu tea irium guyr. up iii« Sultanate after a few tnonth8, but retailed title of Imam. Compelled hir father to abaiuaWund k^Humrd tnronc . Succeeded by corniueBt. Uaurped throne c rightful heir* Hcu^j Hi^htful lieir. JJurdered Badar ana Beized throne. Mo election. f&gt;u«needed by heredity: no election. llle^itiria te liK&gt;n: murdered liiB fatiicr and took pouseue oion of tlirone. Succeeded by conqueet. Succeeded by conquest. Ruceeeded by heredity: election. no 1913 Taimur bin ^ainal. '^he abore chows that while in many cases oucceasion has been by conquest, e&gt;reri \thin a ruler jias succeeded peacefully he has not been elected. Moreover, the electorate are he tribes in the interior who for years pant have defied the authority of the Sultan, and do not acknowletige hira aw tirieir ruler., 'Ve can not c?ill on them to elect a new Tul tan anc: neither can we submit the matter to the votes of the commercial community of Muttrah or the petty nhnikhs on the coast. 'o sum up, I think it has been shown that the Sultanate, as apart from the Inamate, never was elective, and thnt until euch time an a ruler arire* who- -jdMik - 4 - wiio •Btiibi.l9h«« hio Hutiiority in tiic Interior laic uBsuneB tiie title of Imam rmnrt we eontucer the A qu ation of election. In yiew of the fact, already reported to Covemment, that the rultan did not in his interview with mc refer to the quetttion of abdication, it would nut Beera necc8»ary at preoent to conBioer tiie ([ueH .ion of the arrange went 8 to be nade when 3a id coraea to the throne.UCJ \ ** I- L '• -^0 Extract from personal letter dated 21st June 1930 from Colonel Biscoe to Major 7owle, Muscat. x X X X X X X X X X X If you can conveniently do so I think it would not be a 'bad thing when yoa go to Ranikhet if you went round via Dehra Dun and looked up the Sultan and made his acquaintance. If you can do this you might emphasise f to him that we have done much lately to restore his authority and prestige e.g. at Khassah and also hope to put his finances on a 'better 'basis and that it is now up to him to display more interest in the administra tion of his State and to spend a longer period at Muscat every year.'Jonfidcntia l. 77-u, ^uscat 20tii june ly3U. CCtc^. ^JZay\c£ •ath. regard to the Sultan. BUSHIR l residenc fin ■. W fob u* y* OONFjutNTiAi ftEOOBOS To As you know ne is not here now but in DeJira Dun. Thomas informs rue txj.at xie^tyne iiultan^ is again thinicing of abdication, m this connection please see murphy's D.O.^o.78-G.dated 15th November 1^2^. 'At the end of the next year the possible date of the Sultan's abdication 1 * etc. i have not yet met the oultan, and as even if he does not abdicate he will not return - according to Thomas - until ^ecemoer or thereaoouts^ 1 thinic it would be a very good thing if 1 were to ma-ice his personal acquaintance, i therefore propose when i go on recess,to visit him at Dehra Dun. Has this your approval? 1 could taice the Sultan an encouraging message from you? i would also,of course, endeavour to make myself persona grata with him. i presume i could draw my T.A.from Karachi to Dehra Dun and back in the same v/ay that murphy drew his T.A. from Karachi to Bombay when he went to see the Sultan off. (■[ tfl-vV} The Hon'ble Lieut.Col.H.V.Uiscoe^i.A., political iiesident in the Persian Gulf, iiushire. c , I£,0.N» # 334*S of 1930• British Residency, Bushire, the Sth July 1930* I tfi&gt; % , \ \ With reference to your D ■ I, 0,No. 77- C of 20 th June 1930, I am rather sceptical about Thomas 1 statement tlu t the Sultan is again thinking of abdication* Firstly, when I went to Muscat last ^scember Thomas told me that the Sultan intended to announce his abdication at his interriew with me* /s you know he neTer referred to the subject* Secondly, when I saw Thomas at Khassab last May, he told me that the 3ultan waa quite content with the existing arrangement, which amounted to rirtual abdication and would carry on under it as long as we liked. I think therefore that we may cuunt en bein^ able te maintain the status quo, and should work slowly ts try and improTe it by inducing the Sultan gradually to increase the time he spends erery year in Uuscat* I hare no ebjection to your going to Tisit the Sultan at Dehra Dun, in fact, as you will since haye seen, 1 thought of it myself and suggested it in my personal letter of the 21st June. You could proceed from Karachi to Dehra Dun and back on duty provided you can meet the expenditure inyolred from your own allot ment* If 1 can get orders in time^ you might announce Terbally to the Sultan the Gorernment of India decision regarding Themas, which I will communicate to you formally U- as seen as I receire 1 lium. Further UaJor T.C .W.Fowle,C.B.E.» Political igent * Consult MUSCAT35/135. 35/138. R. Telegram From To Unnumbered. Dated 30th reed 31st August 1930. Political Agent, Muscat at Dehradun. Political Resident, Bushire. I have seen Sultan whose reception of me was most cordial. He definitely accepts suggestion of Thomas* departure, hut equally definitely in spite of persuasion on m^ part, states that he has no intention of ever returning to Muscat. I will write from Karachi. JFowle. Telegram B. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Muscat at Karachi. No. 793. Dated 31st August 1930. Imn ortant Your telegram unnumbered of 30th August. That reason does Sultan give for . ahdication ? Is it Thomas* departure or any other specific cause 7 Resident. •r. 36^135, 33/15. 'd'o/l35, c 53/11 vate and jreraonal letter dated iat iiepteiaber 1930, froni the non. iit.-Gol. n.v.^J scoe, jfol. Hesident in the Persian tiulf, to is. b. Aov/ell, i^sq. , G.I3.1., C.i.ifi., iroreign L&gt;ecy. to the liovernment of xndia. * * '' '* ' -* * I got rather a thunderbolt from j?owle yester day In the shape of a tele gran to the effect that while the Kultan had no objection to Thomas 1 departure he himself did not intend to return to Muscat again. As far as 1 could gather from ?oiile , 8 telegram the sultan did not give Thomas* departure as a reason, but 1 am awaiting further details. It has of course been iv. the air for f a long time, but in Tie* of the fact (1) that he did not mention it to me when X saw him last liecember, and (2) that I have endeavoured to comply with the two specific requests that he made to tat regarding the Muscat finances and the »ur t 1 consider that he is showing base ingratitude. I shall probably write to him a letter myself emphasising all we have done for him in the last 9 months and hinting at the end that if he persists he cannot look forward to any very liberal allowance from the Muscat State. Shis may bring him to his senses, but of course one is dealing with a most unstable personality * fr ' 7©/-S i.tftirfyo ctA / ^ v-Wtfv. ^ If 35/135. 35/138. Telegram E, From To No. 804. Dated 3rcl September 1930. Political Resident, Bushlre. Governifient of India, Simla. of Thomas* replacement# Your telegram No. 2802-S of ^Ist August. Sultan has definitely accepted suggestion He has however informed Political gent^the same time that he does not inte d to return to I'uscat. I am awaiting detailedBreiort from Political Agent and will telegraph further regarding this decision, which is apparently unconnected with question of Thomas, and hope that it will he possible to get His Highness to reconsider it. Jilegret delav , which has been due to absence of Sultan from Dehra Dun. Resident# Post copy forwai^ded to the Political Agent, Muscat at Karachi. By order, for Secretary to the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire 3rd September 1930./ 35/135. •/ /(}? R. Telegrani From To No. K-28. Dated and reed 4th Septeiifber 1930. Fov/le, Karachi. Political Resident, Eushire. (.4? li Your telegram No. 7^8. During my several long conversations with the Suitan only specific cause which latter gave was ill health. As however hi? is fit enough to go tiger shooting this excuse hardly holds water. Ee did not mention Thomas* departure as a reason and I did not. got impression tr-at it was. ^hat I did gather i was that he heartily dislikes Muscat and its responsihilit -ies and much prefers life of a gentleman at large. I e said he was under the impression that we understood when he last left l.uscat it was never to return. Finally I suggested that proha ly you- v would like to see him at some convenient spot to which of course he agreed. Despatch follows. kh. Fowle./ c 35/135. 35/133. Telegram E. From Political Hesldant, Bushire. 10 Government of India, Simla. No. 803. Dated 4t , Q September 1930. Impo rt ant. * U \ Ky telegram of 3rd September Ho.304. Following from Political Agent Muscat^ 'begins:- 'During my several long conYersations despatch follows'.* Ends I propose to await Fowle's despatch and then to address personal letter to Sultan. I suggest that Kedgecock should now he appointed definitely to succeed Thomas hut Fowle has represented that as Muscat financial year ends 31st December it would he preferable that .ledgecock should assume charge early January. In view of delay which has occurred and necessity of giving Thomas at least 3 months notice I agree with this view. Eesident. Post copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Luscat at Karachi. By order, £■911 for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. % Busiiire 4th Septem -oer 1930.'J35/135. Telegram G. T. C. From Political Agent, 1 uscat at PCarachi r ^ Q HB Political Resident, Bustiire. N ot K-38. Dated 10th reed llth September 1950. ITy deini official Yt&amp;Z sent witL my despatcL Ho.F-51 'by yesterday's air .ail. Reference ^.aragrapti !To.ll of i-iy despatch. I have consulted Thomas whose views are as follows 'begins:- 'The snhsidies are paid into fehe Muscat treasury as part of the normal State Pievenues 'but are not specifically ear marked against repayment of loans. In reorganisation of finances following on loan Sultan of l.uscat in fact jave up i.ll 1 is claims on State lievenues, includi: ^ subsidies,, in return for personal allowance of E l 1C,000 per mensem, thougl this would ax-pear to re.^i ire regulariz- -ing in writing'. ISnds . I can find nothing- in m. files fr i 3ultan giving up claims to future subsidies in so man^ vord^ though this might 'be inferred from certain correspo^dei ce. Ixelereuce to the su^sld^es in ^ draft letter to Li- -.-i w Lt therefore he onitted. Fowle. liJtV Confidential# No.K/ 3 I of 1930. Political Agency &amp; Consulate. Recess Office at Karachi. September f?tli t 1930. //■f. - m aiflAL Ki * From, .,^,1 • • Major T.C. Fowle t C.B.E., Political Agent &amp; H .B.M f s Consul, Muscat. To, The Hobble Lt-Colonel H.V.Biscoe, political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject:- Abdication of Sultan of Muscat. Sir, I have the honour to submit this despatch in amplicext^on ^f telegraphic correspondence ending with my telegram l,o.K/28 of 4th September 1930. Impression of the Sultan. 2. I stayed two days in Dehra Dun most of which time ''as spent in the company of His Highness. It was the first time that I had met him. Various of my predecessors have given character a . studies of His Highness, varying considerably in their estimat&amp;i. Thus to Mr. Wingate the Sultan was incredibly weak, pompous and idle, not really extravagant, but silly about money, a ^ vain and idle puppet, and - as a ruler - generally useless, 'yVM-Vo (vide Mr. Wingate's letter No.898 of 20th April 1920 to Civil i Commissioner Baghdad; eonfidential note to Deputy Secretary /ft) I , .Foreign: undated; report of meeting between Mr. Wingate and His Highness dated Ambala: Sth September 1920). On the other hand Major Murphy stated; 'I have personally a .very High opinion of Saiyid Taimur's abilities and think, that under fairer circumstances, be would have made an admirable ruler'. ' /iN ' (itajor Murphy's D .0.Iio.T/40 of June 27th 1929). I incline ' decidedly to Major Murphy's opinion: probably the ten years which have elapsed since Mr. Wingate came in contact with the Sultan */;:2« Sultan have improved the latter 1 s character. I found him indeed a very pleasant personality: far from pompous or vain: on the contrary simple and unaffected, with a sense of humour,intelli gent and with abilities certainly up to the average, and probably above. Our relations throughout our conversations were most cordial. b S CMjLc *f&lt;SL ~cL «vv 'T-' ^ ^ I ^ if Mr* Thomas^ departure. 3. His Highness seemed to take. Mr. Thomas's departure philosphically, which was convenient. Unfortunately this philosophy was evidently based on the state of mind of benevo - lent neutrality described by Colonel Trevor in his letter No. 256 of 4th October 1921, (a state of mind I noticed in His Highness even before he made his declaration as to not return ing to Muscat):''His Highness's present idea is that he has now divested himself of all responsibility for the administration of the State, and thrown it on us, and that he can live at his ease in India on a comfortable allowance ' 4. His Highness's doubts on the change of Financial Advisers were apparently as to the qualifications of Mr. Thomas's successor, and once I was able to assure him on this point his mind seemed at rest. I enclose copies of letters A and B received from him (the translations are in the words of his •H t confidential clerk Khan Bahadur Ahmad Shubaily^, Letter A was received before I met His Highness, and is the one referred to me in my telegram of 30th August 1930. . Letter B was givei^by the Sultan after our conversation. In it, besides definitely agreeing to Mr. Thomas's departure,the Sultan states it is necessary chat the Adviser should take part in political as well as financial affairs. This was in reply to a question which I casually put to him as to whether he thought it advisable that the Adviser should only deal with financial matters. The question is not germane to this despatch, and will be dealt with in another in due course. The question of Mr. Thomas's departure having been settled, there remains that of the Sultan's abdication to be dealt with. Sultan's, i .i' , *i\ * «( 1 fc ^ ^ i Sultan^ abdication# 3. quoted in my D.O, to you No.77-^ Of Zot&amp;i 5. His Highness, as already reported telegraphically, announced his decision of never returning to Muscat. ''Then I ' / , expressed surprise at this decision, he remarked, (as stated in my telegram No # /(l^of ^ ^ that he understood we were well aware of his intention. It is true that Major Murphy referred to it in his D.O. No.78-C of 15th November 1928 773^, but after your interview with His Highness in December 1929, in which - though given a special opportunity to do so - he did not allude to his abdication it was concluded that he had probably abandoned the idea for the present. (Your letter No.^f^of 2-$^ ^ Ito Government of India). 6. I naturally used all possible arguments to induce the Sultan to alter his decision. I pointed out that - as he knew 4 well - both you and I had his interests at heart; that H.M # Government - on your representations - was doing its utmost to relieve the financial necessities of his State vide the scheme of raising the Customs dues from 5 ^ to ftxxft 7-^ that you haiaapplied to the Government of India for a moratorium of the next repayment of the State debt; that you had personally proceeded to Sur and induced the Amir of Ja^lan to lower his flag and promise good behavioue for the future, and so^forth. I pointed out that satisfactory as the Council of Ministers had proved, it was only a makeshift; that what Arabs really appreciated was a personal ruler, and that the person to fill that important post was obviously His Highness. My arguments were of no avail. The Sultan merely became perturbed and re iterated his protestations that he would not return to Muscat, giving ill-health as the reason. As he had made arrangements to go tiger shooting in ten days time, this reason - as pointed jf|' out in my telegram No./C2^ of /l3o 9 can hardly be held as valid. I asked him frankly was it because, when he was t - in Muscat he had not sufficient funds for keeping U p position properly,,entertaining Sheikhs, etc. He replied in in the negative. When I asked him what he thought should be done to fill his place, he replied that there were various individuals, including his son, Saiyid Said, who could be4. made Sultan. 7» The fact is that he has a 'complex 11 against Muscat and its responsibilities which he heartily dislikes, and nothing- as far as I can see - will remove this complex. Courses open to us. S. There is the obvious course^ of accenting the Sultan's abdication forthwith, and backing Saiyid Said for the Sultan- ship. (in this connection see Major Murphy's D.O.No. of|5th November 1929 to P.R.)* Saiyid Said is intelligent, tos- vW but still rather young for the responsibilities of the Sultanship. If we could postpone Saiyid Taimur's abdication, somehow or other, for another year, it would be a distinct advantage. 9. In this connection I suggest that it would be worti^fhile trnxtrj before any other action is taken, to try and draw the o Sultan down to earth from the attitude of benevalent neutra lity which he has adopted (see para 3 above), and I append a draft of a propos** letter to him for your approval, which explains itself. I have made it out as coming from me, but you may prefer it should come from you. It is possible that when the Sultan realizes that his abdication would bring him pecuniary loss he may postpone his abdication which is just what we want. In the meantime there is no hurry, as His High ness in any case is not due at Muscat till December, and we can await his reply. 10. Personally, as I have already stated, I like the Sulta n and have no wish to be hard on him, but business is business and if he does not choose to do his job, I do not see why he should be paid for not doing it. The allowance from the State, ^should, in my opinion, be the lowest amount which will keep him in very ordinary comfort. There is nothing new in the idea of reducing the allowance vide the Political Resident's letter No.256 of 4th October 1921 to Gowernment of India.11• In addition to hie personal allowance paid by the Muscat State the Sultan has two subsidies: one for the loss of Zanzibar and the other comjensation for cessation of the Arms Traffic. But both these subsidies are at present paid into the Muscat State treasury towards the repayment of the Indian Government loan of 6-^ laks. When the loan is paid off in about a year and naif the Sultan f if still ruling, will presumably again receive these subsidies. If, however, he has abdicatedjthen^, as I understand the situation, the Zanzibar subsidy will be paid to his successor, (as it is payable to the Sultan of Muscat* vide letter to His Highness Saiyid Thowainy Aitchison treaties volume 12 page 225), and the Arms Traffic subsidy disappears altogether. It is personal to the present Sultan vide Political Residents letter to the latter No.137 dated the 21st April 1923, and only while he has tenure of power vide telegram from Secretary of State to Government of India, repeated to Political Resident No.3675 of 26th Nove t ber 1929. % 12» If the draft letter mentioned in para 9 above meets with your approval, you ^ould let me know by telegram and I could send it from here. Major, Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat.1 Translation a letter dated loth Rabi awal 1249 from Hie Highneee Sir Saiyid Taimur bin Paieal, K.C.I .E.. C.S.I, f Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman at Srinagar to Major T.C.Powle, C.BtE., Political Agent and H.B /M* s Consul, Muscat. After Compliments# On the 6th August I have received your letter No f K.5 of 1930 dated the 31 st July 1930 despatched from Karachi, I () delighted with its arrival and read it minutely and noted % whatever you have received from the Resident!the instructions he has received from the Government of India to give us the impof'tant advice which is useful to our State^ particularly in the economical view to reduce the -budget of the expendi- ture of the Muscat State treasury^ 3n this case it is necessary . to change the financial minister and to employ in his place an officer with salary less than Xax what it is at present, Hiis pay must not exceed -tto* Rs.1200/- (one thousand two hundr^J with promotion in the six or three years up to Rs.1500/- (one thousand and five hundred). And the present Minister of Finance to the Muscat State should be given a notice to prepare to leave his post after three months and the new Officer will take the charge of the financial ministry on the 1st of November. The Government of India expects our confirma tion on this suggestion which is for useful benefit to the treasury of Muscat State. In reply I say^a letter forwarded by me previously to the former Consul before my departure from Muscat requesting the confirmation from our friend the Government regarding the service of Wazir Thomas the Financial A&amp;xxzsxxzx Wazir and Adviser, to be prolonged three years more the passed years, owing to our appreciation for his service^ and as we are well acquainted with his advices and he is an able in his duty. We doubt not that he is an agreeable to the Government too. With regret I say that I was not successful receiv/ the answer of my demand. Now I understood that this suggestion is the reply. In case that this suggestion is for the benefit to our State and will bring praiseworthy future to its treasury^ Iwhich is expected^ therefore we agree to accept this important h*, advice in view to the benefit comes to the Muscat State!there is no objection from our jPJLtKjbUKfcxJuLg* part in the matter, I have to inform you that Muscat State never can do without a good Officer in the financial office and Adviser like Yte.zir Thomas^of good experience and ability for his post. When we shall meet I will tell you verbally what is 6uitable and my desires ili/favour of this affair. f* 1 Hoping^ the everlasting friendship and unity among the both side always. £Letter dated Dehra Dun 4th Rabi al Thani 1349 from Sir Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal, K.C.I.E., C.S.I, t Sultan of Muscat and Oman, to Major T # C,Fowle f Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. . After Compliments. As we had mentioned in the end of our letter from Kashmer dated the 15th Rabi awal 1349 regarding the verbal conversation about the new Officer for the financial Ministry of our State and Adviser instead of ¥azir Thomas. As you understood from the conversation which passed between us in this particular, affirming the selection of an able and qualified person for that office and that he must employ hiiLself in the political affairs of the Council of Ministers. You under stood ^he important point of our ideas, which is that we aim for his cooperation in politics to help the President with his opiniovu In conclusion hopinjthe friendship between both side will continue always.Draft lettero lk &gt; To His Highness Sir Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal, K.C.I.3., C.S.I. Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman. After Compliments. Highnesses I informed the Hon'Tale the Political Resident as to Your / decision, which you recently conveyed to me verbally when I saw you at Dehra Dun, that you had determined never to return to Muscat, which of course means that Your Highness intends to abdicate. The Political Resident has directed me to reply to you as follows:- 2. He is of course much disappointed at the news of your decision which will be a great - loss to the Muscat State, and trusts that even now Your Kaxsaax Highness will reconsider your decision. If, however. Your Highness is determined to abdicate then a letter from you is necessary to this effect. 3. In connection with Your Highness*s abdication there is another matter as to which the Political Resident would like confirmation from you by letter: i.e. that Your Highness fully understand^ as doubtless you do, the financial consequences to yourself which must follow on your abdication. 4. Your Highness has three sources of income; (a) the Zanzibar subsidy (b) the Arms Traffic subsidy (c) your personal allowance from the Muscat State which at present stands at Rs.10,000/- per mensem. The two subsidies are at present paid into the Muscat State treasury towards repayment of the Government of India loan of 6^ laks, but when this loan is paid off in about a year and half %im&amp; then the subsidies will be freed for their original purpose. 5. On Your Highness^ abdication, however, you will lose both the subsidies. The Zanzibar one is payable to the Sultan of Muscat (and will therefore be paid to your successor)i and that for the cessation of the Arms Traffic is personal to you^ (vide Colonel Knox's letter No.137 dated 4th Ramazan ^541 ^' &amp; 1 and only while you hold tenure of power, and will therefore lapse altogether. As for the personal allowance which Your Highness now receives from the State. This Ix will naturally have to be much reduced, since the state will have to provide the new Sultan with a personal allowance to meet his expenses, and owing to its financial position cannot possibly afford to pay (t w o large allowances. The Political Resident ^ill be glad of a reply as soon as convenient to Your Highness, Usual Ending * 4i c^ v ISfS v The Political Agency.Muscat. ecese Office at Karachi. 8th September 1930. Ol Q&gt; C&lt;rhd£ With reference to my No.K/ of S . Muscat finances are rather complicated, but I think I am right in what I said as to the subsidies reverting to the Sulta^ provided he still remains on the throne^ after the repayment of the 6^ laks loan. Thomas however, arrives here tomorrow for dental treatment, and • without showing him my despatch (though I daresay he has had already heard all about the matter from the Sultan) - I will get confirmation from him, and if there are any corrections to be made will wire you. ^ I oXiyv^ I • C. 4^ To The Hobble Lt-Colonel H.V.Biscoe, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.•&gt;2« the qualifications of Mr* rhodaa' suoooooor t and once 1 was able to assure him on this point his aind seemod at rest* 1 enclose copies ol letters s and rec ived from him*'* 3. I do not thliUc It necees ry to forward coplss of these letters to the orernAent of India* in the first one the Sultan agreet* definitely to the ^overnacrit of Indian proposal that Kr* Thorns should be replaced by an officer on a smaller salary and in the second letter he expressed the view that he she Id * craploy hiraself in the politic' 1 affairs of the Council of ministers•* 4* The exact functions to be exercised by ^rArhooas* oucoesoor are ^ 1 think, a raattcr needing careful consideration and Z am not at all sure that It is desirable that he should \)e a mem* er of the Council of Ministers* Tr* Thomas was not originally a memVer but was subsequently appointed one* 1 will address the ovurnment of inaia later m on the subject. &amp;• Lhan, as already reported telegraphically t Ulo hl^j^ness infori ^ed ajor *owle tnat he did n t interid to rei to uscat* -lajor irowle expressed oonsidsraLle surprise at this decision and pointed out that Kis Highness had not mentioned the subject to me at our last a etin^t that efforts were being made to Improve the finances of the ^tate and to re-estalaish Ms ai^ijiess' authority at aur f the two reqj tnat he had speciiically iiade to me* xhe . ultan was howei unmoved by these a'r^umcnts and allseed the usual ground of 111»health* As however he imd made arran^ ements to go tit er shooting in 10 days' time this reason can hardly be regarded as valid, and Aajor 1 owle sums up the position by stating that he has a ••conplex' against Muscat and its responsibilities | which he heartily dislikes, and # In his o^lnlon t noth.nt; will remove this complex. He adds howeverinform Your &gt;ll^hnooB Umt the Oovernmeni of the lUtcd | tatee have already a^reod to tho propooed incroaue in the tariff ana 1 hope that the conaeot of tnc French ovf rmiK nt will be obtained in a ahort tlzae* j urtiiur X rqyaclf proceeded to our and interviewed ^haith i ll of Jaalnn and he agreed to rafrain from fly hie own flae at 'Iqa and wUl 9 I truot t adopt a store out 4 .caiTc attitude In future toward© Your lUi^hnooa* I also hope that It will bo poaaible to take etepo to improve the adainietration of the 3ur Cuatoma oo that the £ tate will derive aore revenue from the a in future# ; nfortu»ately the fall in the dollar exchange haa adversely affcotod the flnanoee of the State and* aa you know f for may years paat the adminiatratlon haa teen atarved and there haa been no poo&amp;ibility of effecting any is^provesieiita* ven If aotae additional revenuea are obtained from an inoreaee in the tariff and the ^ur Cuatoas tiiore ia no doubt whatever that for a Ion. tiae to cosao it will be neoeasary to exoroiae the moat atrin^ent aconoq^* It ie for thia rc ^uion tl »t tl^a 'ovemnent of India au^&amp;eated to Your iil^hnaaa uiat it would be preferable not to extend *r•*'hoiaae , contract but to obtain the serviced of an officer on a oonalderaily aimller aalary. X am glad to hear from iajor iowlc that Ycur ll^hneaa approve# of thia ;noaaure am 2 am oonfldcnt that the officer whom It la propoaed to appoint in i r ^iuotaao* place will worK hard and loyally to oerve the huacat utate* iriajor «owle however writea that Your•5* tour Highnoss laionacti him th t you did not intond to return to This oatte as a v«iy graat ourpriee to me* I am aware, of course* that Your Kighjiess had disouseed the question of abaioation with ajy preaecessorB / but as Your Highness nmde no reference to the matter in convereation with me X assumed that you had arrived at no definite decision in the matter and 1 hoped that if steps were taken to improTe the finaiioes of the lusoat State aiid to re-establish Your iUL^^mess* authority in those portions of the ^tate where it had been wealcenod that Your Highness would refrain from this step# If when you saw me last Borember it was at that time your definite resolve to abdicate then I think you should have mentioned the aatter to ae» I would li^e to ur^e you, frierui, to ree nsiaer this mtter since it will have most serious effects* firstly, at a time when every effort is bei^: aade to put the afTairs of Muscat on a ^ore satisfactory basis it will deprive the administration of the benefit of Your Highness' long experience and Your Highness will probably Ve replaced by a youn/&gt; and inexperienced ruler* ;ecor:dly, it will have the most disastrous effect upon the finances of the State at a time when, as 1 have already pointed uat 9 the most ri^id econoqy is essential* :8 you icaow / ine Arms Xraific subsidy of a*ltOO i OOO/- per an;i in at present paid by the Government of India to the Muscat State is persorjtl to Your Ui ^hnssa and i can hold out no hope that it will be continued to Your Ul^nnese 1 successor* Again, whoever nay be appointed to succeed Your ilit ^hness will have to be given a suitable oivil list befitting the uler of the atate to enable himhim to naintcilfi his position* It wiXX thorefore obviounly not Oo possible to i^ive Tour Hi^hnoss the allowanoe which you at prooont draw from the c &gt;tatc while in India, and I greatly fear that the sum whioh it would be possible for the £&gt;tats to gir* to Xour Highness would be a small one* Finally, thsrs are other mtters oonnoeted with the future administrr.tign of the State ro^ardin^ which it is essential that I should have the benefit of Your Hl-hness* Tisws and about which you will doubtless wish to be consulted. For the above reasons X would strongly urgs on ^our Highness that you should asJce no dsoision in Ihe matter at present but should come ai^d discuss the matter with me* X propose arrivinc at usoat on the 19th Sotstibsr and if convenient to Your Highness 1 suggest that you should come to usoat then and that we oho Id talk over the whole question and consider what is bsst to bs dons both for the State and for Your Highness* I desire to express the high oonsideration whioh i enterlain for Your Highness and to subseribe myself Your Highness*Confidential * D.O«No.505-S of 1930* British Residency, Bushire, the i6th September 193&gt;0 (yju^ Please refer to your letter J6io # K # 5i f dated 8th September 1930, regarding the abdication of the Sultan of Muscat* I enclose for your information a copy of a letter which I have addressed to the Sultan* I hope he will gather from it that he cannot expect to live in comfort at Dehra Dun and draw a large siiowance from the State, This is the only means that I see of bringing pressure to bear on him. If it were not for the financial aspect of the matter I personally woild see no objection to his abdication, but it is a luxury which the State cannot afford at the present moment and I entirely agree with you that we should try and fend it off* fife Major T.C.W.Powle, C.B.E., Political Agent,jriri * Translation of a letter dated Dehra ^un the 12th /3Vf Jamadi al Ula^( 6th October 1930 ) from His Highness Taiiaur • in : a 1 sal § Liul tain of 'iU scat and ' Ojjan ^ to the Hon'ble Lt.Colonel H.V.Biscoe, olitical Resident in the irersian Gulf, Bushire. . -e received your esteemed letter dated f the 16th bepteiaber 1930 { 22ndi Kabi 1 ath-Thani 1349), on the 30th September ( 7th Jamadi al Ula ) and noted its contents with much pleasure and consideration and under* stood what you mentioned therein. As the Political Agent, Muscat, ifiajor Towle informed you I had gone to Kashmir for a month, owing to the great heat of Dehra Dun and to the had state of my health. Towards the end of last September I went tiger shooting but without success. It was howeTei good exercise which the doctors advise me to take and I am very fond of shooting. As you know during my stay in Kashmir, I had some correspondence with Major Fowle and after my return at the end of August, he came and saw me in order to dis cuss the question of w'azir Thomas and it was mutually agreed upon that some other official and Adviser should take his place in the Finance Ministry of our State. My reason for a^reein^ to this was the improvement of the finances of the Muscat State. i As regards what you say about the favour which our friend the Government of India have been pleased to bestow, by making understandings with, and seekin ; the consent of the two friendly Governments of the United States of America and of France, with regard to thethe increase in Customs tariff of Muscat and 9 Oman, 1 thank the GoYernment of India for the efforts tb«~y are making to improre the Muscat State, and I also thank you for your efforts and hope that you will soon obtain the consent of the French Goyernment, as you hare obtained that of the United States of America* As regards what you say about your visit to our, the cf the and that you hare persuaded^ haikh/bani Bu 'Ali to refrain from agitation there 1 hope that he will fulfil hir under takings and thank you for your efforts* 1 trust that in future no further trouble will arise at bur that may necessitate the Muscat State troubling the Govermaent. I trust that Divine Providence will assist the Muscat State and that an improvement will be effected in the Customs revenue at Sur and that the State Treasury will be benefited thereby. I am certain that the difficulties are due to the present fall in the value of silver and the dollar exchange and this has brought about heavy losses in this country and particularly in tiie finances of the iuscat State, as pointed out by you. It certainly is necessary for the Muscat State to exercise econoiny, so as to bring about an improvement in its finances. I confirm what the Political Agent, ajor Fowle, wrote to you with regard to my determination not to return to uscat* The reason for this is that I am unable to perform the duties incumbent on me in the interests of my State and subjects owm to the ailments of which I have lon c been complaining. I would make it clear to you that this is not the first year that I left Muscat %.uBC&amp;t 'f&lt;i ti oiic iiiLsn..ion oi not rctLii'iij.n^ cincL you b&amp;vc doubtless read what your predeceBeore have left on record at uehlre Hesidenoy and at Uuscat Coneulate. Thie deciaion is not a recent one, but was nude several years ago and last year I announced it definitely to the Political Agent, Muscat, in reply to a letter of his and then confirmed it to him in an interview at ilarachi, as you know# If the ailments of which I complain had not disabled me I would certainly have carried on my duties in agreement with you. ^ajor iowle made every effort to dissuade me from this determination, but I could not force ny soul to its hard task. Finally he (Major Bowie) asked me to travel to Muscat for two or three weeks, but I did not a^ree to do so and in all the replies that i gave him I regarded him as your representative and of the friendly Government ( of India ), and he finally stated^as you have also done that an interview with you was absolutely essential and then he asked me whether it would be possible for me to go to Karachi to meet you. To this I agreed and am ready for an interview with you with all pleasure and aonour at Karachi at any time and hour which you like to fix. But I am not prepared to go to Muscat and I dropped you a hint about iqy intentions ana illnesses in the course of your visit to Muscat and our interview there in the month of November last. As regards what you say that in the event of my renouncing the rule of our State and abdicating, the authority will rest in the hands of a young ruler, devoid of experience; in my oelief and opinion, he ( ay successor) is fully qualified like his predecessors and with the help of the Government and assistance of intelligent men and the support-4- eupport of God, he will be able to effect ImprovementB in the State, arid to carry out the duties assigned to him and the undertakings towards the friendly Gorermaent of India* I do not claim anything which appertains to the Sultan of Muscat and •Oman. Any such thing belongs to my successor and we greatly hope that, as mentioned by you, jjQr successor wxll be given a Civil List suitable for his position. Jot aoyself I accept from the State only expenses to be ^iven to us monthly, as we nave mentioned to the Financial liinister of the Muscat State - Mr, Thomas, know that I cannot claim what I receive at present from the State. Rest assured that I am not one whose aim is to accumulate wealth for himself ( for selfish ends )• As regards the annual financial subsidy from the Government of India, mentioned by you, this is invariably given to my successors and he has a right to it* I hope that I shall arrive at an a^ reement with your wishes in this connection at Karachi. As reg: rds your visit to Muscat in November next, I hope that my s n Sa*id will have the honour of visitin^ you and of discharging the necessary duties of your reception, as has ibeen made known to him* I intend to proceed to Ceylon towards the end of this year or in the beginning of the next year, provided my health permits and have mentioned this fact to my friends liaj or Fowle and 2£r.Thomas. In the end I wish the continuance of the true friendship between both the parties ~ Government of India and Muscat State*I Miystr rj Conf i(ientlal &gt; JD.0 # No # 579-S of 1930. British Re8ldenoy» Buehire, the 20th October 1930. Sua-e^r I encloee herewith for your information a translation of a letter that I have received from the Sultan of Muscat. ^ ^ It would be humourous if it were not so annoying# It is» I think, rather a pity that you mentioned to him the . ^.possibility of my meeting him in Karaohii perhaps it would C i have been better if when he refused to come to Muscat you had merely said that you would report the matter to me. I have • &gt;-'1, , jyi. no intention of going to meet him at Karachi except in the last resort and I am inclined to think the best thing to do now would be to write to him on the following lines. To reiterate that the annual subsidy will cease if he abdicates and that he was distinctly warned by Knoj* that it was personal to himself and there is rut the least likelihood of the Government of India extending it and that 1 cannot for one moment admit his contention that it was not a personal subsidy. Secondly, that 1 cannot go to Karachi to meet him as it involves a protracted absence from the Gulf. Thirdly, that if he will not come to Muscat then the only thing will be for you and me to submit our proposals tegarding his allowances, etc, to the Gorernment of India without previous discussion with him and hint that in these circumstances decisions may be arrived at in his absence which he will not like# Please let me have your views on this# i • C • •» .Fowle, G • B«E«f Political Agent, Muscat I #...-2- I understand that the Sultan at present gets R8 «10|000/* a month. Is the whole amount remitted to him at Dehra Dun or does some ^o towards domestic expenditure at Muscat or elsewhere? You will see that in 1920 it was pro- posed to reduce it to Rs»5|000/- and this threat apparently had a good effect. It was actually reduced for three months in 1921, but the cut was subsequently refunded.Ur 35/135/ Telegram: From: To: No. Dated: Political Resident,Bushire at Kuwait. Political Agent, Muscat. T. 112. 2nd November 1930. DEMI -OFFICIAL. Please telegraph to me at Kuwait whether you agree with suggested reply to Sultan contained in my demi-official letter No.579-S, dated 20th October. Resident - Telegram: R. From: Political Agent, Muscat. To: Political Resident, at Kuwait. No. 91-C. Dated and received 4th November 1930. Your telegram No .T-112. I agree.I No. f. of 1930. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp, Bahrain, Dated the //^ November 1930. To His Highness Sir Saiyid Taimur 'bin Faisal bin Turki ,K.C .1 .E. , 0.3.1• , Sultan cf Muscat and ^man, My honoured and valued friend, I have received Your Highness 1 esteemed letter of the 12th Jamadi A1 Ula, 1349, and was pleased to learn that Your Highness had been well enough to go out tiger shooting. Your Highness writes that the state of your health prevents your perform ing the duties incumbent upon you and this is the reason that you are unwilling to return to Muscat• Last year, however, Your Highness had been for several months in Muscat and was able to travel to Dhofar and other places in your territory and in winter the climate in Muscat is very pleasant. I am confident therefore that a visit in the winter to Muscat could not possibly injure Your Highness 1 health and that with the sympathetic advice of L'ajor Fowle, the Political Agent, and the assistance of the new V/azir, you would not find the performance of your duties unduly difficult., JS~ -2- There is one matter regarding which Your Highness appears to 'be still under a misapprehension although I tried to make the matter quite clear to you in my previous letter. That is the question of the subsidy of one lakh at present paid to Your Highness 'by the Government of India, You contend that your successor has a right to t^iis. I would remind Your Highness that in 1923 Lieutenant Colonel Knox, then Political Resident, informed Your Highness in writing that this subsidy was personal to yourself and would not be continued to your successor. As I have no reason to suppose that the Government of India have in any way modified their previous decisicr: in this matter, Your Highness will readily ■ realise in what grave financial difficulty your abdication will involve the State since not only will the subsidy step but also, as I pointed out previously, it wil3 be necessary tc give a suitable civil list to Your Highness* successor # and make some provision for your own expenses, and I must 'tell you frankly that the State is not in a position at the present time to meet this expenditure. Your Highness states that your needs are simple and that you will not require a large allowance. Your Highness will however doubtless remember ■..lie't in 1921 owing to the fact that you did hot return to the State, it was found i—— it -3- necessfiry to reduce the allowance which you draw from the State and on that occasion Your Highness protested strongly against this reduction and said that you could not manage on the reduced allowance that was ther. fixed. Your Highness has suggested that I should come and meet ycu at Karachi. As you are aware, I have many important duties to perform in the Persian Gulf and many places to visit during the cold weather, and it is very difficult for me to absent myself for the period necessitated by a Journey to Karachi and back. In any case I cannot go to Karachi in the near future and the important matters which will have to be settled, should Your Highness not return, cannot wait till then. If Your Highness is unwilling to return to Muscat, the only - course open to me will be to discuss the important matters that will have to be settled, such as the al 1 qwvnoo t-hiut &gt; ic—^-e-te ftKftd Your successor^ etc., with the Council of State and the Political Agent, and to make my reeommendatioris to the Government of India without having the benefit of Your Highness* advice and without consultation with you except by letter, and in these circumstances it is possible that some of the decisions arrived at may not be in accordance with Your Highness* wishes or views .••views, a matter which I would very greatly regret. In these circumstances, I would urge Your Highness to reconsider your decision and instead of proceeding tc Ceylon to come to TTuscat as soon as possible. I shall be ready then to visit you there and v/e can discuss these matters together, I desire to express the high consideration which I entertain for Your Highness and to subscribe myself, Your Highness* sincere friend, It.Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.i| Confidential * K o .52 # T ©f 1930. Office of the Political Hesident In the Persian Gulf, I .G.T.S.r, atrlck Stewart 11 , At Sea f dated the Uth HoTeuiber 1930 From The Hon 'ble Lt.Colonel H^V.TUscoe, I.A. # Political Resident in the Persian Gulf To The Foreign Secretary to the GoTernment of indla f Sir, I hare the honour to invite a reference to oor despatch No.494 -3 of the 16th September 1930, regarding the desire of • 0 0 0 0 0 0 &lt;?!) His Highness the Sultan of Muscat to abdicate, and to forward for the information of the Goyernment of India, a fret translation of the reply that I have received from the Sultan, 2. It will be seen that His Highness persists in his intention to abdicate, but is well enough to go out tiger shooting and contemplates a journey to Ceylon, thoitsh he is ready to meet me at Karachi and discuss matters* Although he was distinctly informed in writing that the Government of India subsidy was personal to himself, he persists in contend ing that it was not, and finally winds up by maintaininc, that his needs are simple and that he can manage on a small allow ance, and he is still under the impression that tixe State can afford to maintain him in affluence in a foreign country with- out his doing anything to earn his salary, 3 ••••••••' f •2- 3. There is, of course, nothing new about this attitude, and though unfortunately 1 have not get the old reeords here with me on tour, a reference to them will show that as long ago as 1921 Hie Highnese refused to return to Muscat; and It was only when his allowance was reduced from Rs«10 t 000/* to R ».5 ,000/» that he consented to do so, and I do not think that anything short of similar measures will induce him to return to Huscat now# I have thertfore addressed him a somewhat bluntly worded letter in which I have reminded him of this incident and have hinted that if he does not chose to come back to Muscat it may be necessary to adopt measures which may be distasteful to him# On the previous occasion the reduction of His Hig;hne88 , allowance resulted in a protest which Colonel Trevor, the then Polltica: Resident, described as most intemperate, and It is possible that my letter may inake His Highness realise that it will be in his own Interest to return to Muscat for a short period at any rate. At any rate I feel that only the plainest speaking can disillusion His Highness# Personally, were it not for the financial aspect of the matter, I should view Kis Highness 1 abdication with indilf erence. His son Salyid Said Is now 21 years old, an age when were he a ruling prince in India he would certainly be invested with full powers; he Is virtually in charge of the administration during his father's prolonged absences and is shaping well* I believe that, with a competent officer to assist him in the administration of the finances of the State, and with occas.tocal advice and guidance from his Oi.itical A^ent, he would make at least as good a ruler as hlf father, if not better. Cm the other hand, ae the Governmentof India are aware, the financee of the State are at present in a TBoat parlous condition; the administrative services have been starved and the repayment of the GoTernment of India loau has had to he postponed* The State therefore cannot afford the additional expenditure which would be necessitated by the GultfrA*s abdication, and the renewed refusal to return to uscat has come at a particularly inopportune mosent* 1 thsrefore recomiaend that we should endeavour to fend it off for a few years longer if possible and, if arguments and persuasions are of no avail, should in the last resort use # financial pressure to ooiapel Saiyid Taiaur to return to Muscat. 5. X am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India* I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lt* Colonel political Resident in the Persian Gulf. f ''AI*. _ ConfidentiRl Office of the Political Resident in the Pereian Gulf, I.O.T.S.* atrick Stewart*, At Sea, dated the 12th HoTember 1930• f.7 $ In continuation of my despatch No»494-S of the 16th September 1930, 1 have the honour to forward for the iniormation cf His Majesty's Government a c^py of my despatch No«52«T of even date, and of its enclosure, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, on the subject of the intention of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat to abdicate. 1 have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. jnt^ '(s-c. Lt«Colonel 9 Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf* His Majesty^ Secretary of State for Indiat INDIA OFFICE, ISMSSSL*Translation . In the none of Ciod the 14)at Coinp&amp;Gsiouate and Lertiful. Trom To TAIMUR Bill FAISAL. 4 a/ Our respected friend Colonel H.V.Biscoe, Resident of the High British Government in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. After greetings and many salutations % In the best of the time we received with the hand of pleasure your honour 1 a esteemed letter irc .44 -T of 1930, dated the ilth l ovember 1930 corresponding to the 2ist Jamadi ath Thani 1349. V/e read it with great attention and care and your friend understood its contents to the end. Yes, as regards the question ol our coming to Luscat, just as your honour already learnt from our last letter and from what we spoke verbally to your Agent at liuocat^ 1-ajor Fowle, we have no wish to do so for the reasons which W e alrea^ expressed. And we inform your honour and we request you to submit it to our friend the Government of India that the fixed bounty of a Lakh of Rupees which they bestow upon us in lieu of the losses suffered by us we do not think that our abdication snould cause a cut of this financial aid. V/g have every hope ^npen d.m^ for the attention of the High Government at this time oTV financial danger to the Government of 1 uscat to continue this aid and to favour by changing their former view. The delli- ciency and the losses in finance of Muscat and the acute difficulties ensuing therefrom are not hidden from you. In view ox cne linancial difficulties oi our Government, 4he necessary expenditure for our successor and for ourselves should be made from that aid. And we inform your honour, just as youliientioned in your letter that our arguments and our rejection of the reduced pay in 1921 were in order. And no doubt that your Political Agent at Iluscat knows fully well as to what amount is sufficient for the expenses of the person of the Sultan of Kuscat to manage his affairs, and we do not doubt that the Headquarters of the Political Resident at Bushire are also aware of this important point. And as we mentioned, necessary simple expenditure would suffice during our abdication. It is not hidden from you that we have no income except what we receive from the Treasury of our Government. And no doubt that the allowance should be sufficient. Just as we mentioned in our last letter to iou we had explained to ^azir Thomas what would be sufficient for our expenditure, and it cannot be less than that, and we hope that he would explain it to you when he meets you at l^uscat. And we know your inability to reach Karachi as proposed by us and the Consul of M u sc«t, and we are sorry for our inability to come to Kuscat. As regards your proceeding there and discussing with the Council of Ministers and the Consul about fixing expenditure for our successor and for ourselves, undoubtedly that is your important business in this important arrangement. And your honour has mentioned that perhaps some arrangement may not be in accordance to our wishes. 'Ve say had we not been trusting and relying upon the (High) Government and their men in our affairs, it may therefore be that whatever is against our wishes (is) in the interests oi the both parties - our friend the (High) Government and the Government of Luscat, and (of) the preservation of this dynasty. And God willing, in the second week of December, we shall proceed from Derahdun for Ceylon. In the end (v/e say) we are # ever amongst those faithful. I^ated Derahdun, the 6th Raj ab 1349 {27th November 1930). i, 3d. TAIHUR. Received and translated on the Gth Dec. 1930. m.a.Scefr C .t-ji iConfidential # D«O.No.626-3 of 1930. British Residency, Bushire, the 8th December 1930. / 1 I enclose herewith a translation of a reply I have received from His Highness the Sultan, As you will see, he still refuses to return to Muscat and proposes to go off to Ceylon, Sayid Said said he would write to him urging him to reconsider this decision; I doubt this having any effect, but still i will await the Sultan's reply to Sayid Said before addressing Government. In the event of His Highness still remaining obdurate, I am inclined to agree with you that the best thing to do would be to ask Government to overlook his failure to return during the current cold weather, and then to inform him that should he persist in this attitude, his allowance will be reduced to, say, Rs.3,000/- a month forthwith. I do not know exactly what figure to suggest, but I want to recommend a sum that will more or less compel him to come back, Rs.3,000/- a month, of course, is more than adequate for his personal expenditure in India, but 1 do not know what his domestic expenditure is, i.e. how much it costs him to 8u t j t ort his three wives, children, etc, i Could you kindly make enquiries locally and let me know what sum, in your opinion, should be fixed? It should, I think, be such a sum as will just enable him to Major T.C.W.JPowle,C.B.£. 9 Political Agent and H.B.M* s Consul,■ -• iSJk 1 T- I.V^ I'/o -2- to subsist on an exceedingly moderate scale, but no more, Please telegraph to me what reply the Sultan ives to Sayid Said. edgcock leaves Basrah by the slow mail of the 21st Jecember. Howell has written to me expressing a hope that he will receive a friendly welcome in the Gulf and 1 assured him that this would be the case. pf 5 CONFIDENTIAL • iC2f ^ ^ „ . ./ Political Agency &amp; H.B.lPa Consulate D#O.No# \ 0 [)' C« of 1930* ' VMuscat,the 23rd December 1930. U, rtf* \k f A Owo fttou. 5ff'f^ 1^ oJ&gt;Y L * Your demi ofTicial No»626-»S of 8th. December 1930 Tor- warding a reply from the Sultan stating he was not going to return. Saiyid Said has just received a reply to his letter \0 i/ urging his father to return. In it His Highness absolutely refuses to do so# 2, I am glad you are inclined to approve of my suggestion re asking Government to overlook the Sultans not returning here this cold weather. It is of course a hand-to-mouth expedient, but I think the only one in the peculiar circum stances of the Muscat State, and if Government agree will tide us over a difficult year. 3. With regard to the •cut* which should be made in the Sultan 1 s allowance of Rs.10,000. This is a difficult matter. If Thomas had been here his views would have been of con- siucra assistance, as however he has vanished into the ■; ^-Ruba-al-Khali (vide my letter No.l04-C, dated the 19th ^ December 1930) I have had to get along without him. I could nave obtained information by sending my Interpreter confi dentially to the clerk of the Muscat Treasury (a Hindu), but since such enquiry would probably have got round to Saiyid ^ a ' na created a wrong impression, I thought it better therefore to approach Saiyid Said personally and privately, which I did. D 4. I explained that I had of course no desire to pry into His Highness' private affairs, but that the latter»s deci sion not to return to Muscat had raised an awkward situation and it would be best if we could have a frank conversation on The Hon*ble Lieut.Colonel H.V.Biscoe, I.A., -foxitical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. * tthe subject# Saiyid Said concurred, was most sensible, and the result of the conversation is as follows:- 5# Saiyid Said quite agreed in the first place that if His Highness would not return to Muscat he could not expect to get the full allowance which was settled on him on the condition that he would spend some months here every year» The question was how much should he receive# This again depended on what expenses His Highness had to meet from his allowance. 6# His Highness* matrimonial commitments are as followst- A* The wife in Muscat, mother of Saiyid Said# She gets Rs# 600/~ every month from the State# The Sultan also gives her an allowance# B# The Circassian in Constantinople, mother of one boy# The Sultan has divorced her^r|(She was too much of a handful, and according to one story I heard, not from ^ v Saiyid Said of course, tried to stab His Highness one night)# She has no further claims on the Sultan, but he sends an allowance for the maintenance of the boy© C# The wife in DHOPAR, with two boys and one girl# How far she is the actual 'wife* of the Sultan remains dubious# Anyhow she and her family are supported from the earnings of DHOFAR which as you know is a private estate of the Sultan^# No money, however, (according to Saiyid Said^is remitted to the Sultan from Dhofar^ the local revenues just about covering the expenses of the local administration# r , ' . - He probably has a ♦friend 1 or two in India, but cer- tainly no wife#1 7# The way the Rs.lO^OOO/- p#m. allowance is disposed of at present is roughly as follows:- R8 #3,000/- p.m# is sent to the Sultan, and Rs#7,000 p.m# is given to Khan Bahadur Nasib, to whom the Sultan is heavily indebted, the exact amount of the debt Saiyid Said did not know# Out of this Rs.7,000 Nasib gives - on behalf of the . Sultan •• Rs#2,000 as a sort of private allowance to various7 3, QK*' / members of the royal family, and to some others. What actually occurs is I imagine that Nasib advances to the royal family (and the others) cash and kind and then takes it out of the Rs.B^OOO. (Both the debt to ^asib and the family allowance are cu purely personal obligations on the Sultan as private individual^ A Mm not on the State)* The remaining Rs.5,000 Nasib takes towards Ms debt» 8» Having got so far we considered the question of how much the •cut 1 should be on His Highness 1 allowance. It seems advisable that he should receive sufficient to pay something towards his debts and towards his family allowance, thoggh not Sim much as he was paying before# If he was given RsoS^OOO per mensem for instance he could pay Rs.1000 p.m. towards each object and still have Rs.3^000 p.ijio to live on as at pre sent. In letting him have this allowance he would be made to understand that he would be expected to make some such payments. It would of course be feasible to pay him much less (say) Rs.3000 p.m., but in this case his creditors and family would have • I think - some cause of complaint against the State and against ourselves ( every one knows that we originate most lines of policy here). On the other hand by giving him a generous •vU (tc A. C, allowance we place the responsibility whioh it belongs, i.e. on the Sultan . When his family and his creditors come to us and the Council, as they will, complaining bitterly that owing to the ♦cut* in the Sultan's allowance they are not receiving from him what they did previously, we have our reply ready. H The Sultan is still receiving a very generous allowance. Living Q as he does incognite in India he can exist very comfortably on Ct ^e. much less than Rs.3,000 which he has been in the habit of /V spending on himself there. If he does not choose to economise in order to support his family and pay off his debts, we are sorry but that is nothing to do with us*. Personally I regard it as distinctly important that we shall be able to take up this attitude. 9. In point of fact considering that the Council will send the Sultan his allowance every month, and that the royal familyaa — ^ in - and Nasib - the chief creditor - exercise a good deal I in fluence over the Council, I think it is fairly certain that the claimants will get a pretty good alice out of the melon# / ' - 'i wrffiuuJ- Anyhow we can leave them to fight it out amongst themselves -ta t&amp;ert getting embroiled in the hurly-burly. 10# The State will of course get R8.5000 extra p.m. which will be most welcome in these hard times. -r 1 11. The above conversation I had with Saiyid Said was a purely private one, and naturally no action is being taiten pending your sanction. If you approve I can guarantee that the Council which H still-in Thomas 1 absence • consists only of Saiyid Said and Haji Zubair, will agree. 12. With regard to what action should be taken now. I suggest as followsw Snort of cutting off his allowance altogether, nhich is hardly practicable, I think we must give up any hope of getting the Sultan back. He has apparently in his letter given you carte blanche to arrange his allowance as you think fit. If you approve of the Rs.5,000 suggested above, then in your letter to Government asking them to overlook his failure to return, you could suggest this 'cut 1 which doubtless Govern ment will endorse. If they also agree to overlook his non return then the State retains the Arms Subsidy, gets Rs.5,000 from the Sultan's allowance, the present regime of the Council carries on, Saiyid Said gets more experience for his respon sibilities as successor to his father, and every thing in the Muscat garden is more or less lovely until next Autumn when '• on the Sultan still refusing to return to Muscat (which he will doj-his abdication can be officially announced. If Government d® not agree to overlook the Sultan's non-return then an entirely new, and awkward situation arises, which will have to be considered separately. I am afraid I have made this a long letter but as the matter was important I thought it best to go into the pros and con^s fully. (.( j\ i &lt;-■ I/ 5w1v kc 1 Bbc. ■ COOTIDBNTIAL. 7rom ]fo. P # 132-N/30 # liliyh' i The Addl. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf» ])rf ^ v If FoTember 1930 # I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Additional Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. ly / Dated Hew Delhi, the December 1930 # DESIKS GJ 1 SULTAN 01? MJSGAT TO ABDICATE. -o« Sir, I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your ^ letter Ho. 52-T«, dated the 12th November 1930, and to say that the Government of India concur in the recommendations nade by you and approve of the action taken* They will be interested to see what reply His Highness gives to your letter Ho. 44-T., dated the 11th (v ;ith 1 spare copy)■ i * c .s Conf idential# no.26, of 1931. British He «i( ency -e Consulate-Ceneral, Fuehire, the 12th January 1931* From - The Hon'ble Lt.Colonel H # V # iscoe,I•A. f Political Ueaident in uhe Persian Gulf To The Foreign Secretary to the Gorernment of India, Hew i^elhi. Sir, I have the honour to solicit a reference to the correspondence ending with .Foreign and Political department letter Ko.F. ia2-K/30, dated the 24th beceraber 1930, regarding the desire of the Sultan of Muscat to abdicate, and to forward herewith for the information of the GoTernment of India a translation of the reply addressed to me hy His Highness the Sultan* 2. It will be seen that His Highness* reply is entirely uncomproftising and that he refuses to return and has presumably gone off to Ceylon. This reply reached me on the 6th December, but as there were various points regarding which I desired to obtain the opinion of the Political Agent, and communications with Muscat are slow, it is only now that I am in a position to submit my views for the consideration of the Government of India* 3* The Sultan first mooted the question of his abdication when on a visit to Simla in 1920. it was at that time considered that his abdication would probably be mis interpretedi D &amp; -2- misinterpreted and fui ht have unfortunate repercussions on Moslem and Arab opinion at a somewhat oritical periods and further the heir-rpparent was then a minor. For these reasons efforts w«re made to induce the Sultan to return to Muscat and financial assiatance was eiren him to pay off his debts and set Mb house in order* In 1920t he recei ved a loan of Ks•6^50^000/* on the following conditioner t ,V 1) that he should reside in Muscat for three months eyery year. 2) that he should receive ks.lOfOOO/- a month through out the year conditionally on the ability of the rotate finances to meet the char e and on his good behaviour - vide J orei^n and Political i ^epartaent memorand a* No. 1496-hi-A, dated 6th October 1920 as modified by Foreign ana Political A&gt;epartiaent memorandum I^o.IVGe-E-Z^datec 1st iecember 192 • This arrangement has remained in force ever since, though it has at different times required a great deal of pressure to induce the Sultan to spend the specified period of three montns within the limits of his State, and he nas from time to time reiterated his desire to be allowed to abdicate. iiow at length however he has left the Stfte and definitely refuses to comply with one of the conditions on which the loan was made to him and to return for the three months. 4. The conditions whxch rendered his abdication undesirable ten years ago no longer exist. 1 doubt if the Sultan* s abdication would have any effect on Moslem or Arab opinion nowadays, since it is known that for the last ten years he has consistently been an absentee ruler and has taicenBFWl? -3* taken but little part in the to^ernment of his State, while the heir-apparent is now 21 years of age# 5. On the other hanu^ other reas ns^ of a financial nature, but almost equally cogtnt render the Sultan's abdica tion still very undeeirable and it could hardly have come at a more inconvenient moment. Trade all over the world is suffering from a period of acute depression and Muscat is no exoeption t while its revenue has been most adversely affected by the fall in the dollar exchange* I have not received the final figures of receipts and expenditure up to the end of the year, but x think it will be found that it is only due to the fact that the Government of Inaia have postponed the re payment of the instalment of the.loan that the State has been able to make both ends meet. The State has no reserves and the administration is starved. 6. Steps are being taken to try and remedy this state of affairs. Firstly, endeavours are being made to obtain the consent of the United States of America and the French Govern- ment to an increase in the customs tariff; secondly, recent improvements in the situation at 3ur make one hope that it will be possible to obtain an increase in the customs revenue from that port; thirdly, an officer on a lower rate of pay m.B been appointed as Financial Adviser, and it is possible that he will be able to affect economies or increase the income of the State cy closer supervision; fourthly» the repayment of the Government of India loan should be completed by the end of 193X. It will however necessarily te somejti le efore all these measures can be ^i^en effect to and their cumulative effect felt. It is improbable that tne negotiations with the United States of America and France will be concluded uefore the end of the current &gt;ear« While some increase has already takentaken place In the Sur cuetome receipts, the Muscat State will of necessity hare to ^o slowly In introducing reforms xti thai area; the new financial Adviser, who has just arrived} will obviously require time to make himself acquainted with local conditions, etc., ani finally there are still four instalments of the loan to be paid* abdication of the Sultan will affect the finances of the Jtate in two waysi Firstly, the State at present receives a subsidy of Hs.1,00,000/- per annum as compensation for loss of revenue from the Arms traffic. This eubsidy was personal to Saiyid Faisal, but in view of the fact that he died very shortly after it was rou c ht in, the Government of India continued it to Saiyid Taimur as a personal subsidy, Ko mally therefore it will prcsumacly cease on his abdication, and though having re ard to the special conditions under which this subsidy was granted and -he circumsLances oi the stste, i trust the 'overnment of India will not wholly rule out the possiijility of the con- tinuance of this subsidy for some further limited period if absolutely necessary, its lapse is a contingency which 1 have to take into account in submitting ray proposals* 8 * Secondly, the present civil list is Rs.10,000/- per mensem^and if the ruler of the iitate is to maintain his position adequately, I do not think it is excessive* This ^aiaouiio will nave to be paid to the Sultar^s successor, while Sai&gt;id Taimur would have to receive somt pension. Hot onl^, therefore will the income of the State be reduced by a large sum fvUt the abdication wiJl also involve further expenditure, which at the present time it frankly cannot afiord. 1or the above reasons it seems to me essential that the Saltan siioula not be allowed to abdicate durin^ the current year and tnat^ if possible^ further efforts shoulc ue ioad e * * *, • 5- made to iceep him, no ^iainaliy at any rate, on the t rone for two or three years more* 10* Z consider that the Sultan*a behaviour in leaTing Muscat without announcing hi a intention not to return, either to me or the Political Agent, was deplorable: as Saiyid .iaid said to me when i discussed the matter him ^ a prirate individual proceeding on a journey sets his house in order t afore he leaves; how much more should the ruler of a state do so*. Again, the finances of -he State are such that the Government of India nave had to postpone the repayment of the instalment of the loan and therefore it can rightly toe contended that it cannot afi ord to pay the Sultan Rs. 10,000/- per raenaeau ihe two conditions on which the civil list was fixed at K8.10 f 000/- have there fore been broken and the Government of India are, 1 think, perfectly entitled to aak the State to reduce it. !!• I have consulted the political A^ent as to the amount that should be fixed for Hie Highness during the period he remains in India, and ajor Fowle discussed the matter personally and privately with Saiyid 3aid. He writes as followai* ' X explained that i. had of course no desire to pry into fiia ilighnea8 , private affairs, but that the latter^ uecision not to return to Muscat had raised an awkward situation and it would be best if we could have a frank conver sation on the subject. Saiyid Said con curred, was most sensible, and the result of the converaation is as follows)- Saiyid Said quite agreed in the first place ••• —- 6— place that if iils Highness would not return to Muscat he could not expect to get the full allowance which was settled on him on the condition that he would spend some months here erery year. The question was how much should he receire* This ag in depended on what expenses His ^i t ,hness had to meet from his allowance* His Highness* matrimonial commitments are as follows:- (a) The wife in j&amp;uscat, mother of Saiyid Said, iihe ^ets Rs.600/- every month from the State* The Sultan also gives her an allowance* (b) The Circassian in Constantinople» mother of one hoy* The Sultan has divorced her. She has no further claims on the bultan, but he sends an allowance for the maintenance of the boy. (c) The wife in DHOJAR 9 with two boys and one ^Irl* How far she is the actual ^ife* of the Sultan reanains dubious* Anyhow she and her family are supported from the earnings of DHOffAR which as you know is a private estate of the Sultan's* 2»o money* however, (according to Baiyid Said ) is remitted to the Sultan from Dhofar, the local revenues Just ^bout covering theYj •xpenses of the local adminie trail on • The way tiie Ls. 10,000/- per mensem allowance is disposed of at present is roughly as followsi- He* 3 f 000/- per mensem Is sent to the Suiten # and xs.V^OOO/- per mensem ie Iren to lOian l ahadur Uasib, to whom the Sultan Is heavily indebtedi the exact amount of the debt Saiyid iaid did not know* Out of this 38.7,000/- Kasib gives - on behalf of the .iultan - R8.2 f 000/- as a sort of private allowance to various members of the royal family, and to some others, /hat actually occurs is 1 imagine that S^asib advances to the royal family { and the others ) cash and kind and then takes it out of the .8.2,GOO/-# (Both the debt to Kaslb and the family allow ance are purely personal otiligations on the Sultan as a private individual, not on the State) t The remaining i\s,5,000/- Nasib takes towards his debt. Having got so far we considered the question of how much the •cut 1 should be on His Hi^Jtiness* allowances* It seems advisable that he should receive sufficient to pay some thing t wards his debts and towards his family allowance, though not as much as he was paying before. If he was ^iven Rs.5,000/- per mensem for instance he could pay Rs.1000/- per mensem towards each object and still have Ks.3 f 000/- per mensem to live on as at present -tn . . . .• 8— In letting him hmve this allowance he would be made to understand that he would be expect ed to make some such payments. It would of course be feasible to pay him much less (say) ils.SfOOO/- per mensem, but in this case his creditors and family would have - I think - some cause of complaint against the State and against ourselves* Qo the: ^ c ruiiid by fivinfj him ^ ,,en^rou8 allowance we plaee the rf.fponplbllity where it bcloa ..i.e. on th^ .jAjLJt&amp;BL* hen his family and his creditors come to us and the Council, as they will, complaining bitterly that owinglto the 'cut* in the Sultan 1 s allowance they are not receiving from him what they did previously, we have our reply ready. 'The Sultan is still receiving a very generous allowance. Livin^ as he does incognito in India he can exist very comfortably on much less than the Hs.5,000//* which he has been in the habit of spending on hiaself there, if he does not choose to economise in order to support his family and pay off his debts, we are sorry but that is nothing to do with us**. Personal^ ly 1 refeara it as distinctly importait that we shall be able to take up this attitude. In point of fact considering that the Council will send the Sultan his allowance every month, and that the royal family and Nasib - the chief creditor • exercise a ^ood ci eal ...»12, -9- deal of influence over the Council 9 I think it is fairly certain that the claimant8 will get a pretty &amp;ood sixare. .^nyhow we can leave them to settle it amongst themselvee#^ I agree with the above views and would submit the following suggestions for the consideration of the overnment of India* Firstly, I recommend that they should condone the failure of the Sultan to return during this winter* It is too late to get him back now and 1 do not think that anything can be done this winter; I suggest however that I should be authorised to convey to him an expression of their displeasure at his action and his failure to comply with the conditions on which the loan was made to him, and to inform him that he would in future only get Rs.5,000/- per mensem instead of the r.s•10,000/- per mensem which he is getting at present* Secondly, I consider that during the coming summer efiorts should be i.mde iy the Political gent and rqyself - if - go *o India • to induce the Sultan to oome back next winter for the fixed period of three months* I am not very hopeful that .ve snail t)e successful, but it is at any rate worth trying* If these attempts fail, we can then consider the question of the oultan's pension, which I think should le less than Rs*5000A per mensem, and we can offer him the alternative of returnin or living in &gt;ndia on, say, Hs#3000/- per mensem or whatever sum may ue decided upon* s he will then have had a taste of living on ns*5000/- per mensem and will probably have been some what harassed by his creditors, there is the prospect that a still further reduction in his income may uluimabely brin,. him to his senses and may make him alwayo realise what he has consistently— -ipr. consistently failed to realise up to the present,namely, that the state cannot and will net maintain him in comfort and idleness. This should carry us on for another year during which it should toe possible to place the finances on a somewhat more satisfactory basis, and there is Just the possibility that it msy make the Jultan think that on Lhe whole a short sojourn in Muscat every year is a small price to pay for nine months confort and ease during the remainder of the year in India and is preferable to twelve months ot comparative penury. 14. I t ^ wi sending a copy ol this despatch to ..lis x lajesty's Secretary of State for India. A - M &lt; f'U'' ll/fl. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. JfThy^ Lt # Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent at Muacat for information. Attes ted ; Confidential^A.8sis tan t, British Hesidency and Consulate- General. Bushire, 12th January 1951.— •mumm ' »tl J 35/135, jli' xx Political Resident, Kuwait Government of India,New D^lhi f , ( copy 'by air mail to Secretary of Sta J .e r or ■y ~a *sz'''spl. '-t it T, 15 25th January 1931. * * * * * * * * * *■ * * I would also request early orders on proposal that Sultan's allowance should be reduced to Rs»5000/- vide niy letter No•26-3 of 12th. January* Hi -BESIKENT-■I n 7 35/135 R. fayf, TujJ -,y Grovernraent of India,^New-Delhi. Secretary of State for India. London. Repeated to Political Resident, Bushire. No. 521. ' Dated 22nd received 23rd. February 1931. Political Resident 's letter of January 12th. No.26-S. Sultan of Muscat. ^e propose to authorise Resident to take action suggested iDy him in paragraphs No. 1,2 and 13. Do you approve ? Foreign.mmrnmmm 35/135 Telegram -From Grovernment of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, New Delhi. Political Resident. Bushire Secretary of State for India. London air-mai, 27tli. March 1931 Dated 26th, received of State 's telegram dated Larch 24th No. 1043 Sultan of Muscat You are authorised to take action as proposed im paragraphs 12 and 13 of your despatch of January i2th. , No.26-S subject to reservation stated in paragraph 2 of India Office letter oi^March 10th. to Foreign Office.i • t- « | •• m COHFI iliilM r 1AL • lio.!?-! of 1931. From - Office of the Political Reeident in the Peraion Oulf f 8,8. ,, V /u RELA ,, # At 3ea f dated the 3l8t :vlarch 193U The Secretary to the iion'ble the Political Reeident in the Persian Gulf To The Political Agent, Sir, / fij-A •••••• JVith reference to your telegram ^o.30 t dated the 6th February 1931, 1 am directed to enclose a copy of India Z /^-Office letter No.1115/31, dated the 10th Jlarch 1931, and • iVl ^ -of Government of India telegram H0.893-.S of the 26th Inarch 1931. 2. It will be seen that the Government of India have authorised the action proposed in paragraph 12 of the Hon'ble the Political Residents despatch l&lt;o.26-S # dated the 12th January 1931 addressed to the Government of India, and I am to ask you to address the Sultan on the following lines. 3. His Highness should be infomed that in 1920, when the ^overrment of India agreed to assist him in the negotiate ions between his state and the rebels and in the continued reconstruction of his finances, they stipulated that His Highness should spend 3 months every year at Musoati the Sultan accepted these conditions. Last winter, however. His Highness did not return to Muscat; further he left Muscat without announcing that it was not his intention to return, and refused the Hon'ble the Political Resident's invitationIV&gt; -2- to c ma to Muscat to disouBs the yarious matters which must obviously be settled if His Highness persiBts in his desire not to return* I'he Government of India cannot but view with grave displeasure h^ s failure to adhere to his under taking to spend 5 months of every year in Muscat and his refusal last November to meet the Political Resident at liusont to discuss important matters that required to be settled. On this occasion t however, the Government of India are willing to overlook his absence from Muscat this winter and have agreed to continue payment of the Arms Subsidy for another year. 4# I am to request however that His Highness may be Informed that the examination of the finances of[the State undertaken by the new Financial Adviser have disclosed a serious state of affairs^ which is aggravated by the present trade depression. endeavours are being made to increase the revenues of the state, but meanwhile drastic economies are necessary if the budget is to be balanced* The allowance of Rs.10 ,000 per mensem fixed for the Privy Purse was contingent on the ability of the finances of the state to bear this expenditure and they are no longer able to do so* The Government of India after careful consideration have therefore come to the conclusion that in the interests of the state it is necessary that His Highness* allowance should be reduced to Rs.DOOO per mensem. it is hoped that His Highness, after giving the matter his serious consideration, will see the wisdom, both in his own interests as well as in those of the state, of modifying his decision and returning to Muscat next winter. Should His Highness persist in his determination to stay away from ...wmmm - -3- from Muscatt it will involve the state in further heavy expenditure and it may become necessary further to reduce his allowance next year* 1 am also to ask you to inform the Council of the reduction made in the Sultan*s allowance. 7. As regards the reservations mentioned in the India A Office letter above 9 the conditions accompanying the Sultan's allowance are contained in Governioent of India* s memorandum o# 1766EA # dated the 1st December 1930. It will be observed that in this letter it is definitely stated that nothing should be sfdd on these two points' for the present. Consequently, it is not clear whether these conditions were ever communicated to the Sultan. Colonel Trevor in 1921 cited this memorandum as his authority for according his sanction to a reduction in the Sultan's allowance, it is therefore presumed that they were. As, however, it has frequently been explained to the ultan that the amount of his allowance depends on the ability of the state to pay - vide Mr. ^ingate's No.564, dated the ^9th aarch 1921 • this is not a point of any great Importance. But the Political Resident would like to know, for his own inlorfoation, whether, in fact, these conditions were ever made known to the Sultan. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, ^ ii. * Cppt • » Secretary to the Political Resident ?n the Persian Gulf»■■■■■■■■ QONFIDBNTIA.L. No. F.40-N/1931. mmm r*m —**- ' -11 i j-^T 4^ i BUSHiRE FfESiDENCY. . 1^' to l*}-*- Dtu 1,3 M, 37 CCNflOWTIAL StflOWi A copy of the undermentioned ia per is forwarded to the Hon'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for information in continuation of Uie telegram from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department No, 893-S of 26th Karch 1931. By orcier, etc., Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. Ax- Foreign and Political Department. New Delhi; The April 1951. Letter from the Foreign Office to the India Office, Fo. 1220/267/91, dated the 16th I'arch 1931.64/rr^ K. Teleg am J'roin To Unnumbered Dated 28th. receivec 29th. April 1951 Major Ji'o v; 1 e , C av/n po r e ♦ Political resident, j^usliire. nl and i am Eiaving JC' My telegran no, a-2, i i leave here April 29th. i ^a^ive seen sultan ... interview with him at Lahore, where he has wired f^aiyid Said to meet him on my way to Karachi which i reach on May 2nd. and whence j. will telegraph. i shall be at Lahore from morning or Apii^ .'301h. to moi'ning of May 1st* Address care of station -master, Your telegram no. 260, \ i nk oaiyid 3aid is in iiarachi un .il about .he mid- -dle o May, vide my telegram no.ilS. ne virtually comprises council as Zubair merely follows hie leaa. j . venture to suggest there! ore that i could do necessary co nsultation in Karachi instead of in Muscat. j?*owle. Above telegram repeated to Political resident, G/o isritconsul, Mohammerah, under cur no. 275 dated 29th. April. I93i.. /£//f M No. /t &gt;//r of 1931. Political Agency &amp; H.B.K's Consulate, Muscat, Recess Office, Karachi, the 5th May 1931. bu S h;~e residency. R*t D»te. £ fm i/ CGNFlDcHTiAL mm The Secretary to the Hon^le the Political Reisident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. v Memorandum. V With reference to correspondence ending with my telegram Ko.Ml of 29th April. The circumstances in which the meeting at Lahore with the Sultan and Saiyid Said fell through are explained in the attached copy of a letter I wrote to Saiyid Said. If His Highness was 'very ill' I considered that he would not be able to transact business for some days, in which case I would simply be wasting my time at iJehra Dun. This proved correct as on return here I received a letter from Saiyid Said from Dehra Dun to the effect that H.H. was ill in bed with fever, and that he i would take up business with him when he was better, ky letter to Saiyid Said also touches on various important points connected with Muscat. 2. As stated in paragraph 1 of my letter to Saiyid Said I had several discussions with h.H. I renewed the favourable impression I received in my interview with him of last year (paragraph 2 of my letter of September 8th, 1930/. H .H. is decidedly 'all there', and if only he could be induced to take up the reins of Government would - in my opinion - make a good Sultan. On the main issue of our meeting, his return to Liuscat, he proved obdurate. - used all the old arguments at my command (vide paragraph | I\ms 2 of my letter quoted above),and added a new one. 'As a personal friend of his - which as a matter of fact I am - I asked his permission to speak plainly. He said he quite appreciated the fact that we were friends, and would like me to speak out. I said that we talked of his 'allowance from the State'; but where did this allowance really come from? It came from the taxes paid 'by his people. And what did he give in return? His ancestors in the Sultanate whatever mistakes they may have made, and every man makes mistakes, at all events stuck to their post, worked in it, and died in it. Every man whether he was a coolie or a Sultan had his work to do, and surely his - H.H's - work was-I ventured to .point out-in Muscat, and not touring about India leading a life of leisure. The Sultan took my homily in good part, and it seemed to make some impression on him. 3. . I gave him the communication indicated in your 1T0 .17 -T of 31st March, to which he said he would send a reply. Presumably Saiyid Said will bring it back with him here in a few days. He will also be able to inform me of the result of his conversation with the Sultan, which I will communicate to you in due course. Major, Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat.Cawnpor*• 29th April 1931. Dear Saiyid Said, I mat Hie Highness here and we had many conversations during the two days we were together. I Informed him of the deolslon of the Government of India to reduce his allowance to RsS^OO^of which I had already Informed you 9 and gave him a letter which I had been directed by the Political Resident to write to. him* 2» During the discussions 1 had with H«H« he stated that he was going to meet you at Lahore some time shortly. I suggested that as Lahore was on the way to Karachi»where I was returning*It might be comvenlent for us three to meet there. H.H. agreed,sent you a telegram accordingly # and left for Dehra Dun. Yesterday evening I received the follwolng telegrami Alsald very 111 cannot travel to Lahore will you come to Dehra Dun If possible to him his son coming here direct. Civil Surgeon# Dehra Dun Is of course not In the direction of Karachi,and unless H.H. wanted to see me especially It did not seem worth while spending time and money In going there after the long discussions urgent we had had here. I accordingly sent H.H. the following^telegram yesterday eveningj Much regret to hear of your Illness. We discussed matters fully here and unless you particularly wish to see me d/ In which case please sen me an urgent telegram I propose returning to Karachi 29th leaving here 15 hours. Am sending Salyld Said letter care of you. There Is of course ample time for H.H. to reply,but no telegram has come yet,and If one Is not received by 3pm. I shall leave for Karachi. H.H^ llness m\jst have been a sudden attack of something as he was quite well when he left here on Sunday. I sincerely trust you will flnpLhlm better when you reach Dehra Dun. Please Inform me how he progresses. 3* There are various points which I discussed at length with H.H. but which I would be grateful If you would also take up with him.\V^ a * First - pleaae Impress on him the serious flnanolal oondltlon of the State which I doubt If fully realises In spite of the ^tr^ss I laid on lt« There may be two opinions as exactly how serious this condition Is,but that It 1ft serious there Is no doubt whatever* You aHxtuliy have full knowledge with the flnflal crisis through which the 8tate Is passing,and which has necessitated economies In the Levy etc etc,and there Is therefore no need for me to go Into details In this letter# 4, There Is also the Important question of the Arms Subsidy,which - as you are aware - Is personal to H.H. so long as he remains Sultan. T The Q-overnment of India have,as I have already Informed you,agreed to overlook H.Hls absence from Muscat this Winter and have agreed to continue payment of the Subsidy for another year# This - as you ^ro^d ifhen I Informed you,and as H«H« also agrees - Is a generous act on the part of Government# But If H#H# persists In his determination no&gt; to return to tfuecat and the Subsidy Is thereby X lost I really do not know waht will happen# The State finds It difficult enough to carry on with the subsidy,what Is It going to do without' One result would certainly be that any allowance which the State could afford to pay H#H# would be reduced to a very small amount Indeed# 5. Another point Is that as follows# H#H# 1 s allowance of Rsl0,000-. used to be divided as follows# Rs3000- for H.H. himself,Rs2000- for yourself and the other members of the Ruling Family (paid through Naslb for some reason I am not quite clear about),and RS5000- for Naslb towards the debt which H.H. owes him. H.H's reduced allowance is Rs50'&gt;o. # This Is still a large one,and H.H. can us# the Rs^OOO- for his personal expenses,as he has been doing up to now,and^ still afford to give you and the Ruling Family the Rs2000- which he used to give. In fact H.H. definitely Informed me that this was what he was going to do. If In addition to this Rs20oo- H.H. wishes to pay something towards his debts,or soemthlng more towards the Ruling Family,he can • It seems to me — easily do so by cutting down his present expenditure t0 9; t ' hal/u o , J • Rs3000-. He lives ae &amp; private Individual and has no official entertaining or position to keep up. 6. Another question Is that of reduction In the allowances of the Rullnfc Family,which you had In mind. I did not discuss this with H.H.,but you may like to. It Is a somewhat delicate matter but In the present condition of the State all possible lines of economy must be considered,and the fact that H.H's own allowance Is being reduced to half should strengthen the hands of the Counell In this matter. I am addressing a few lines to H.H.,saying how sorry I am to hear of his Indisposition,anf hoping for his quick recovery. Please let me have a telegram to Karachi as to when I may expect you there. Yours sincerely, Sd/ T.C. FowleConfidential v i ¥ ' / yT » • • H0.257-S of 1931» Britieli Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 12th May 1931, I have the honour to forward herewith for the information of Hie Majesty's Government a copy of an Express letter addressed to the Boreign Secretary to the Government of India, on the subject of the return of the Sultan of Muscat to Muscat* 1 have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. Lt« Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,£ eee ' 9 '''' N - r - v y4? COiiPIDEM 'IAL. 7/3 / i'A/V No. of 1931 Political Agency &amp; Consulate, Muscat, Recess Office, Karachi, 12th hay 1931. The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian tiulf, -bushire. Memorandum . - ] Please refer to my telegram ]5o.21-K of ^th Lay 1931. The Sultan has at last agreed to return to kuscat under the combined influence of the communicaticn I gave him, my arguments when 1 saw him at Cawnpore, and those of Saiyid Said when the latter saw His Highness at Dehra Dun. H.H. told Saiyid Said that he would 'be very glad to see the Hon'ble the Political Resident at Iluscat in -November to discuss various important matters with him. I asked Saiyid Said whether CKc H.H. was coming to Muscat merely for/interview with the Political Resident or for the customary three months. Saiyid Said replied that H.H. was not definite on this point but that he - Saiyid Said - presumes it was for three months. H.H. was a sick man with a attack of stomach trouble and so Saiyid Said naturally could not press him on details. In fact it was only after two or three days pressing by Saiyid Said thai H.H. finally said he would return. He has sent no v/ritten reply to the communication I gave him, but presumably he will do so when he recovers. Saiyid Said had a telegram from him a few days ago to say that he was better. 2• The point arises as to from what date the H.H's reduced allowance should commence. Presumably from the 1st of lay i.e. as effecting his allowance for that month.2 He received tiie communication referred to above at the end of April. The Sultan's allowance from next November, when he returns to l.'uscat, will also have to 'be considered. i can discuss these two points (paragraphs 2 and 3 above) with the Political Resident when I reach Bushire if he so wishes. \' c ' Major, Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. 1a Ho« 310*3 of 1951 • British RealdenG^ &amp; ConBulate«GeneraX 9 Bushire, the 29th May 1931* To The Political Agent, Muscat* r Refereance paragraph 2 of your memorandum K0.26-K, dated the 12th May 1931. 2, The Hobble the Political Resident has decided that the reduction in the allowance paid to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat should date from lat May 1931,i.e. the cut should be made from payment due on that date*lb 0 -a- us in Urn past and wh/oh are oontlnaoua f and. which me •xpeot to b* oontlnued in the future to the Uueomt state and to cqr euooeeeer* (5) In regard to the ne^otiatlane between i^yeelf and the Political A ^ent # v &lt;ln^ate f at mbala in the /ear 1920f regarding return to ^ueeat from India am the •pending of two or three monthe there anuuaXXy* Yea I aeoepted that tes^oraril^ ana suffered the inoonvenionee of Journeying to Mueeat^ which ie not hidden from the preecmt heeioent aad hie predeoeeeore* . nd before the W be^inn^n^ of the laet winter I infer toed the Resident in zy Tarioue iettore,that I mum unable to return for reaeone which I explained to hiia in tsy laet answer: reasons Mhioh prevent me from returning# and fulfilling ay duty towards m Kingdom and qy eubjectst for sftiioh x a» sorry* Bor did X think that oorreepondenoe would eontinue on the subjeet after my final reply to the osid^nt and ^ter giving to hin and to «y euoeeseor full authority for the oonduot of the affairs of o^y State and its interoete. (4) X did not refuse finally the invitation of the resident in nay answer to him* but X infonaed you verbally during your vieit to ehra -un, where we net 9 that X was ready to tseet him at ^ araehi to discuss laatters with hisu I regret» however 9 that he oould not meet me at Karashi in November last owing to pressure of work f but X gave him full authority to tafcs decision in important affairs in whioh lay the advantage of the lusoat 3tats # as alludsd to by him in his letter*By Air Mrzavmr A JQI S S &gt;- K, ia a? ••••••• \i 1 A' : i^rom PolitloiiX Rcaideiit, Bu^hlre. To For«lgn 9 Slinla* Ho. 532-i of 1931. BUSHIH i, tit* 24th August 1931. Colonel Biacoe's Express Loiter 2 ?o*256-S of 12th May 1931* H- Sultan of luacat* I enclose herewith copy of a letter from the Sultan. It ie rery diffaee hut It is evident, ride para graphs 7 ana &amp; that Hie ui^hneee hai a^ain clanged hie mind, and announces his intention of abdicating* My comments will follow later* I am sending a copy of this letter, with enclosures, to His iiajcaty's Secretary of State for India, and to the Political Agent, Muscat* sit c^- Ae. f33-S .h. • i]( - ik MaJ or, Officiating Political Resiuent in the xersian Gulf. a ■9m No.558-3 of 1931. British Residency &amp; Consulate-Oeneral, Bushire, the 31st August 1931. The Hor^ble Major T.C.W.Fowle, Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Poreign Secretary to the Grovernment of India, Simla. I have the honour to refer to my Express Letter No # 532-S of 24th August 1931. * 2. At the beginning of this year a similar situation arose and was dealt with in Colonel Bi8Coe f s despatch No. &gt; /// 26-S of 12th January to the Foreign Secretary to the Govern ment of India with copies to His Majesty* b Secretary of State for India, certain definite proposals being made in paragraphs 12 and 13 of that despatch. 3. These proposals were briefly as follows: that the failure of the Sultan to return to Muscat last winter should be condoned,! and that His Majesty^ Grovernment should continue to pay the Arms Subsidy^paragraph 7 of Colonel Biscoe 1 s despatch}^but that an expression of the dis pleasure of the Government of India should be conveyed to the Sultan at his failure to comply with the conditions on whdch the loan was made to him ( i.e. that he should t-2- reside so many months a year in Muscat) f and that he should be informed that in future he would only receire Rs.5000/- per mensem PriTy Purse instead of the Rs^lOfOOO/- which he had been receiring up to then. That efforts should be made during the coming summer to induce the Sultan to come back to Muscat for the fixed period of 3 months next winter. 4. These proposals were agreed to by the GrOTernment of India in the Foreign and Political Department ( ride their telegram No*521-S of 22nd February;, and by His Majesty's Government ( vide Secretary of State for India's telegram Ho*1042 of 24th March to the Government of India, repeated to the Political Hesident 9 Bushire), subject to reservations contained in paragraph 2 of India Office letter dated March 10th to the Foreign Office. In this letter the India Office pointed out that the visit of the Sultan every year to Muscat for a stay there of 3 months was not one of the conditions on which the loan was given in December 1918. His yearly stay in Muscat was one of the conditions imposed in March 1920 in return for our assistance to him * in the negotiations with the rebels and in the continued re construction of his finances w ( P.G.13,page 48,paragraphs 35 and 36). It was on this occasion 1 also that the Privy Purge was fixed at Hs.lOfOOO, subject to His Highness' continued good behaviour and to the continued ability of the State finances to bear the strain'. In the opinion of the Secretary of State for India it was therefore undesirable to suggest that our power to take action on Colonel Biscoe*s proposals was directly connected with the terms of the loan.l(o^ 5# Accordingly in due course the Sultan was informed and his allowance reduced to H8.5000/* per mensem* 6. Measures were also taken 9 as suggested by Colonel Biscoe 9 to tiy and persuade the Sultan to return for the stipulated 3 months to Muscat next winter. With the approral of Colonel Biscoe, I took adrantage of the fact that I was recessing at Karachi from Muscat last April-May to have a meeting with His Highness up-country t at which I used all the arguments I could think of to induce him to agree to return to Muscat next winter. Saiyid Said, His Highness* eidest son, and President of the Council of Ministers, who was at Karachi for a change of air, also visited his father with the same object. i J he result of our combined 'attack' was that through Saiyid Said, His Highness stated verbally that he would return to Muscat, and on my informing Colonel Biscoe of this, he reported the matter to the Government of India and to the India Office in his Express Letter iio.256-S of 12th May. Unfortunately the Sultan has now again changed his mind. 7. The following comments occur to me. I think first, t it must be accepted that this is the Sultans last word and that no futther attempt to persuade him to change his mind would be of any use. In other words his abdication will have to be accepted. 3. There are three financial points in connection In fact, as Colouel Biscoe pointed out in paragraph 4 of-4- for the financial implications of Hie Highness 1 abdication his departure could be regarded with indifference. These three points are as followss- and (a) The Arms Subsidy; (b) The Priyy Purse for His Highness 1 successor; (c) The allowance for His Highness when the latter retires. 9. .Uth regard to (a), which was dealt with in para graph 7 of Colonel Biscoe's letter of 12th January already quoted. The Arms Subsidy 9 as will be seen y is personal to His Highness as long as he holds tenure of power ( Tide for instance telegram Bo,3674 of 26th .November 1929 from the Secretary of State for India to the trorernment of India, repeated to the Political Resident, Bushirei For the present year as His Majesty's G -overnment have condoned His Highness' absence from Uuscat last winter the State is continuing to draw the subsidy. ^Tien his abdication is finally accepted, however, this subsidy, by the letter of the law, will be lost to the State. The effect of a loss of Rs.1,00,000 per annum on the State in its present financial stress would be disastrous, and I can only echo Colonel Biscoe^ hope that Government will be able to temper the wind to the shorn lamb and not wholly rule out the possibility of the continuance of this subsidy for some further limited period. 10. With regard to (b) and (c) which Colonel Biacoe p commented on in paragraph 8 of his letter. As for (b), I think perhaps, that having regard to the present financialfinancial condition of the State, that something less than Rs.10,000 per mensem might suffice. In the Muso t budget, for instance, made up by Saiyid Said at a time when the ^ul:an was expected back at Muscat next winter, the sum of Rs*7000/- per mensem was allowed as His Highness 5 allowance for the period of his stay. This or perhaps eren less might suffice for his successor. 11. As for (c), I think the allowance should be cut down to the lowest figure to enable His Highness to live in reasonable comfort in India. I hare no personal prejudice against the Sultan; on the contrary, on the two occasions when I hare met him he has impressed me farourably, and after my last interyiew with him last April I wrote to Colonel Biscoe as follows^ * I renewed the favoarable impression I received in my interview with him of last year (paragraph 2 of ay letter of September 8th,1930}. His Highness is decidedly 11 all there', and if only he could be induced to take up the reins of CJovernment would • in ray opinion - make a good Sultan. n But as far from doing his full duty as a Sultan, he will not even perform the nominal task of residing for 3 months every year in Muscat, he has no claims on our sympathy. His statements as to ill health preventing him spending a few months of the cold weather yearly at Muscat are ridiculous. His real rfctsons are given by Colonel Biscoe in his letter llo.494-S of 16th Septeaiber ♦ 193(1, paragraphs 2 and 5, and are briefly that His Highness prefers to lead a life of ease in India on a comfortable income, supplied by the State, for which he has to do no work. An additional reason may be to avoid the Sultana, his first wife, and mother of Saiyid Said, a formidable lady ...lady with a temper and temperament of her own. She has made one or two attempts to leaye Muscat, where she llTes, and join him in his 9 exile* but has been hastily prevented from doing so l?y his express command. If we could make it one of the conditions of his abdication that the Sultana should also 'abdicate 1 and live with him permanently, His Highness might again chang^his mind, but I am afraid that j this is outside the sphere of practical politics. 12* In fixing the Sultan* s allowance we must consider his financial commitments* These are detailed in the quotation from a letter of mine given in paragraph 11 of Colonel Biscoe t s letter of i2th January and consist of two categories: family expenses and debts to merchants. I then recommended Rs.5000 ( which was approved of by Colonel Biscoe, paragraph 12 of the same letter), but that was when there were hopes that he would live up to his agreement to return to Muscat. The situation we are now considering is that he will no longer be ruler, and in that case, and considering the almost bankrupt condition of the State, I do not see why it should allow him more than about Rs.2000 per mensem, and even this will run up to Rs.24,000 per annum a sua which the State can ill afford to give. His Highness 1 family expenses, it will be seen from Colonel Biscoe* s letter, consist of an allowance to the Sultana, who already gets Rs.600 from the State, and to the son of the Circassian wife. His Highness in India lives entirely as a private individual, and preserves no sort of State whatever. ( In fact when I saw him off at the station after our last interview he was clad in Shorts', smoked a cigar, and had shaved off his beard. It is difficult to ...»hhohb -7- to a ay which would hare ahocked hia I bid eh. subjecta in Muscat moats- the f ahorta 1 , the cigar, or the abaence of the beard.) Thia being ao he can easily live on Ra.1500 per mensem Ra.500 over for the Sultana, if he likes to ©ontinue o her anything, and for the Circassians son. As for his debts to merchants they must make what arrangements they can w^-th him. 13. The question of His Highness' successor is not difficult. Saiyid Said, his eldest son, now about 22 years of age, and President of the Council of Ministers, which carries on the administration oi the litate in the .^l^an s absence, is the obvious choice. He has for the last two years has been to all intents the -.^ler, is ca c. le and popular with the people, by whom he is looked on as the Heir Apparent. He is a little on the young side, but is ox course of full age to become Sultan. 14. SUMMARY . The questions for consideration would appear .to be as follows:- (a) Whether GoTernment are prepared to accept His Highness 1 abdication ? The only alternative would appear to be to condone for another year his absence from Juscat (paragraph 3 above), and bo keep him nominally on the thronej (b) Whether, in case Grovernment do accept His Highness* abdication, they are prepared to approve of Saiyid Said as his successor ? ( paragraph 13 above). (c) Whether, in either case, aoTernment are prepared to continue the Arms Subsidy ? ( paragraph 9 above).id a A (d) What should be the Prify Purse of His Highness* successor ? ( paragraph. 10 above). Il l l«) wlxat » hou:Ld be the a;Llowance of ^ Sultan (paragraph 12 above)• 1ft. There is no immediate hurry and - suggest that the India Office might like to take advantage of olonel Biscoe* a presence in England and diecues the whole matter with him. I am sending a copy of this despatch to His &gt;; Majesty's Secretary of State for xnaia. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Major, Officiating Political Hesident m the Persian Gulf. •V ^ 'f ^/ s / v eafuj £ '5 i f h -BESIDENC^ No. J. 40-N/31. &amp;GN r fiOi ; . TUu dEGuHCf) The Foreign Seeretar/ to the Government of India, The Hon^hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated Simla the Jl f September 1931. Desire of the Sultan of Muscat to abdicate . — With reference to your letter No.558-S of 1931, dated the 31st August 1931, I am directed to say that the Government of India have decided that before accepting the Sultan of Muscat 1 s present reply as final it is advisable that either you or the Political Agent, Muscat, preferably the latter^ should once more visit the Sultan and put it to His Highness that^ if he persists in his intention to abdicate / (l) the Government of India will find tiiemselves constrained to advise the Muscat State Council that His Highness' allowance in India be reduced to is.2,000/- per mensem and (2) the Arms Traffic subsidy will cease. After His Highness has considered these prospects and all the arguments against abdication that the representative of the Government of India will urge upon him, his final decision should be recorded in writing and signed by His Highness. I am to request that action be ta^en accordingly and the result reported to the Government of India. I have the honour to be, Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, under P.L.No 660-S sir, of 9th Oct. 19 31, for information Your most obedient servant, ibreign Secretary to the Government of India. ^ i 1^ I £c )No. 163. British Residency &amp; Consulate- Greneral, Bushire, the 9th October 1931« To His Highness Sir Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal bin Turki, K.C.I .E. ,0.3.1. , Sultan of Muscat and , 0man 9 Jehra Dun , in which you express your intention of abdicating. I sent a copy of it to the Government of India and I received a reply in which they state that they would like a representative, either the Hon'ble ^he Political Resident or the Political Agent, Muscat, to have a personal interview with Your Highness and lay their views before you. Colonel Biscoe who - as you know - has been on leave is returning on the 22nd of this month. ^hen I have handed over charge to him I will return to Muscat reaching there at the end of this month. Colonel Biscoe will proDanly request me to visit Your Highness, and therefore - after having taken over charge from Captain Alban • I will most likely leave for Karachi on or about the 6th November, and can go strai^t on from there to see Your Highness at Dehra Jun. Please let me know if this is convenient, and l^y honoured and valued friend 0 ifith reference to your letter of 22nd July 1931 address ..w I V •2. * address your reply c/o Captain AXban at Uusoati who will telegraph me when he receiyes it* Trusting that Your Highness is enjoying good health and looking forward to our meeting, I subscribe myself, Your Highness* sincere friend, MaJ or, Officiating Political Resident in the Persian L ACCKginSMTIAL . D.O.No.661-3 a 1931. British Reeidency, Bushire, the 9th October 1931. ••••••• o v / Please see ray lta«660-S of today* s date forwarding Goyernment of India's reply to ny letter on the subject of the Sultans abdication. 2. As you will see they want another 'attack* to be made on the Sultan either by the Political Resident or the Political Agent, Muscat. I don't suppose that Colonel Biscoe will want to visit His Highness, so 1 imagine that the duty will probably derolve on me. If so, then after haTing taken orer from you at Muscat, and remained there a few day^B to get the hang of things, I would leave for Karachi^by the next mailj ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ * 3. Will you please inform Saiyid Said unofficially that Government, in reply to a letter of mine informing them of His Highness' intention to abdicate, have written to the effect that an officer,( who will probably be myself ), should have a personal interview with His Highness, and explain their views. (*hat these views are you need not tell Saiyid Said at present until I have had time to put the matter up to Colonel Biscoe.) You might also inform Saiyid Said that it would be of assistance if he could accompany me. 4. His Highness has a way of wandering about, sometimes to Kashmir and sometimes as far as Ceylon, and so I am v • writing him a letter, copy enclosed, asking him if he will kindly ... ^stp t . • Gr .£ . . .A Ibri n f Political Agent, M u s, c, a t..■ -2- kindly stand by at Dehra Dun for the interriew In SoTember, As you will see I am not at this stage informing him of Government's Tiews# If His Highness is n&lt;&gt;t at Dehra Dun but on his traTelBy and Saiyid Said has his latest address&gt; 1 would be obliged if he would write to His Highness to a similar effect. This will save time in case iny letter is delayed* 5, If His Highness remains obdurate and the State loses the Arms Subsidy, then I don't know what will happen. (f% i(/ 5^ v p,S . Ref .para 2 of niy letter to the Sultan, ' open his letter when received and wire whether he can meet me as suggested. N \f/rrf 2 7/flU eONROEHWL RtOOROS LOiJDON , S. :i. 1. 6th October, 1931. Dear Colonel Biscoe, I enclose a copy of a despatch we have received from Major Powle (together with copies of the various despatches, telegrams, etc., to which he refers in it) regarding the desire of the Sultan of Muscat to abdicate. You will see that he aiggests, in the last paragraph, that we might take advantage of your presence in this country to discuss the whole matter with you. I should be very grateful indeed if, the next time you are at the India Office, you could have a tali, either with Ytelton or myself, about this question. Yours sincerely,Telegram From To No 246 i-'ated 28th received 29th October 1931 Code. Political Agent, Muscat. Political Resident, Bushire. ! Your despatch No 661-S of 9th October. Please inform Fowle, Sultan waiting Savoy ^otel, Amhala. Political r</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001a2_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/445</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001a2</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/445</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Muscat. Desire of Sultan Taimur bin Faisal to Abdicate.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-18T15:12:27</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (198 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file. The front of the file includes a contents page arranged alphabetically.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation system in use is the sequence of numbers appearing in the top right hand corner of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence relating to abdication of Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal [Taymūr bin Fayṣal], Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Correspondence discusses how the Sultan had initially expressed a desire to abdicate in 1920 following the conclusion of the Omani rebellion and the Treaty of Sib. Correspondence relates to attempts by British officials to dissuade Taimur bin Faisal from abdicating including a reduction in his financial allowance from the Government of India. Letters discuss arrangements for his son Saiyid Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr] to rule through a Council of Regency and the tenents of the Ibadhi branch of Islam on election of their religious head. A letter describes how Saiyid Said bin Taimur became Sultan at the age of 22 following time as President of the Council of Ministers and de facto ruler for two years.  Other topics discussed include: finances, proposed increase of the Muscat tarriff and the Zanzibar Subsidy; the Sultan's [Taymūr bin Fayṣal] house in India; succession in Oman; and Bertram Thomas.Correspondents include Cyril Charles Johnson Barrett, Political Resident Persian Gulf; Gerald Patrick Murphy, Political Agent, Muscat; Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal [Taymūr bin Fayṣal]; Foreign Secretary to the Government of India.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman Āl Wasik Billah al-Majid Taymūr bin Fayṣal bin Turkī Āl Sa'īd</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Abdications (events)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001a2#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>