<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000317_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T19:08:20.950Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM Diary File Closedy/- Pile No. Pt PTTlSH INTEREST S, Diary Pile 1914. Closed.HO 1 Of 1914 X POLITICAL A'-HHOY, Bahrein, Bahrein news for the week ending 5rd January 1914. LOCAL OFFICIALS* 1* Sin Sp.ud Is said to be oozing to K&amp;tlf* GQNDXTIONf OF OOU^rjVf . 2m It ia reported that Shaikh Ali hin Ahmed le extorting thin^Q from the people Al-Bosaiba # a village in Manama where he has a date garden. Ha said to have demanded free 8upply#»of milk and donkeys. One Ateed bin Abdulla,gardener of Abdulla bin Juma in Behla was severely dealt with at the instigation of Faris,the servant of Shaikh All bin Ahned for not supplying him with donkeys. Some people said to have left 3ehla f^or fear of his oppression. 5. It is said that Shaikh lea has ordered the Hasanis of El HareeJ who lived in Manama to quit the place. Foreign Interests * 4. It is rumoured that the Hamburg-Ajnorika Linie intends plyinr their ateapr.erolbetween Bombay and ulf ports. The I ^rrohante and the general public are said to be pleased now 'J**- as they have been ^ruwbling of constant shutting out of cargo a./ by British Indi^ steamers in urachi and extoroitant freights be in.i?: oharged on nasa^nprere lurrago by the oor^any. 5. Selifan hi Adsoni 9 clerk of Shaikh Haseer bin Shaikh ^ubaral- arrived on the 27th December 191^ from Fuweit. It is said that his object is to enlist the ayrnrathy of the Arabs in favour of Saiyld 'alib I'aaha of Basrah. The people were indignant att the k&gt;i.n ,/ UX, request &lt;y* Jelman Al na«anl for asking/to take part with Saiyid Talib who is,they say, a drunkard,prof11^ate,ttielf and murderer and who rebelled a^ainut the Government mho- had elevated him to the high position he now holds* To body they sav would res pect &gt;aiyid alib in preference to the Supreme ' T ead of Islam. OnOn tho Arabs reporting the roatter to Shaikh lea the latter told the man to leave the country* He therefore sallied by 3.S.' 5, Kaaim Khadhairi of Basrah wanted to remove Captain vandaree of John .ofsoott'* fro® the ship but 3aiyld Talib of Basrah helped to keep him on. How the 3,S#John 0 f Soott^sald to have r^n aground at Katlf and it ie naid that the pilot end ¥ohamed bin Hasan Buaishey have both caused the 'John 0 f 3oott w to go aproundand that Captain I Mandaree wa« rourhly handled by them at Katlf• /^RIVALS and PFPAP'^JP^^ of ^« Reference diary 9 ?o#442 of 193^ S.B.^Sardlar' left on the 36th ult # She vae on the b»r while entering the harbour but no Gmmmm was ^onet 7. Saferenc® diary ? ?o»445 o»S • w narala** left on the 2Bth ult. 8. - On the Ist the flaiaburg-Aiaerlka Linie S.S. ,, !)inive w arrived from Lln?;ah and left the dame day for Oushire. 9. On the 2nd S.S^Baroda 1 * arrived from Bushire and left for Lingaii tho same day. MI3CnLLA !n :0US . I lt» On the 25th B^oeaber and lei January 1914 the Agency flap- staff wan dressed in honour of Chrlsteas and ^ew Year day^ #SECRET COMMERCIAL INTELLIGENCE ^Hinive* of the HaynhTjrfT-Ainerika Llnie arrived here from Europe on the 1st January 1914, and left the Baroe day# She landed the following cargo at Bahrein# FROM ANTFWRP . 550 double bags Sugar* 4 Cases dry colours. 50 ** Candles • 12 * Earthenware * 250 ' Vermlofclli FROM BUNDER ABBAS . 4 bags Henna 370 Total packages. BAHREIN Major, Political Agent, Bahrein. ?5rd January 19X4# AP.- t- do- L #0.QUARANTINE , ✓ , (summary of his inspection of steamers that called at Bahrein during the week ending 3rd January 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical officer, Bahrein. The s.s.^Barala' arrived from Lingah on the 27th December 1913, and left the next ciay» Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 78 passengers were landed. She was granted a free pratique. The s.s.''Ninive' arrived from Lingah on 1st January 1914, and left on the same day. After inspectionnB passengers were landed. She was granted a free pratique. The s.s.^Baroda' arrived from Buehiro on 2nd January 1914, and left the same day. After inspection which showed nothing suspecious 197 passengers were landed. She was granted a free pratique. \QUARANTINE # (Summary of his insDeotion of steamers that called at Bahrein during the week ending 27th December 1913 f furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. The s.s.^Baroda' arrived from Dubai on S4th December 1913 # and left the same evening at 7 p.m. Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 58 passengers were landed. She was granted a free pratique. The s.s. ,, Sardar w arrived from Bushire on 26th December 191.% and is still in Harbour. After inspection which showed nothing suspecious on board 850 passengers were landed. She was granted a free pratique.NO. 2J&gt;f 1914. POLITICAL AOKWOT, BAHREIN. Bahrein newa for the week ending 10th January 1914* LOCAL 0F1-TGIAL3 &gt; 11. Reference Diary Ho♦401 of 1915, Sheikh Hawed bin laa returned frow Linrmh by o.a.^Bankura' f and brought back 520 Hubaras. F0HI':i'^? INTER EST* 12. Abdulla bin Juna and Ahmed Yateem have bought in their 8ona , naraea the house aituated next to that of Moha^ed bin Amer and to the eouth of ^eanra &gt;ay Paul &amp; Cop ?T &gt;any f a build ing for a am of Ha .1800/- from Sheikh Abdulla bin Taa on condition that they would not reaell it to foreignera without permieaion. 15* The Turkiah Ounboat •Marraario* arrived at Fatr with, it ia aaid, stores and provialona for the ^arriaon. The Commani der of the Hinhoat ia aaid to have appointed a naid man at Katr to act aa a pilot. m he lunboat ia aaid to have brought a chief gunner for Katr to relieve the old one* AimVALS Am) DT^ P A H^ OF 14* On the 6th H.Iaf.S.'LAWSSNOE' arrived from the Persian ^ulf and left on the 7th. The ship waa relaying the red f?aa buoy and remained anchored there. 15. On the 4th S.^.TUNKOHA* &amp; 'OTOA' arrived from Dubai and Lincah and the former left on the 5th and the latter on the 8th both for ^uahire. 16. On the 6th S.S.^BAHAIiA'* arrived from Huahire and left for Dubai the aame day. OF H.B.^S R^^H^^-N^ A ^IVKG. . 17. Hef^rence Diary No.444 of 1913 the political Afrent re turned on the Bth inotant. MISOKLLATOOUS. ' ■ ■ J .-T T, ^ / 18. A piece of land, belonftin# to Raahid Doaeem 1 ahrani at Farik el -oaorra in Manama where poor people have been living for many years, ia beincr purchaaed by Sheikh Ahmed bin M 0h5ia 7for Sheikh Isa bin Ali al Khalifah. sheikh Ahmed bin Mehza it is aaid # has inatip^ted Rashid Doaeem to ^et the noor reai dents of the plot shifted. These people olaim to be tenants of Abdulla bin Hassan Dosari who is willing to purchase the ground for these poor residents. 19. Syed Abdulla Memoni a partner in a Memon firm trading with the Gulf has corae from Basrah to collect the firm's olaim from the late Mansoor bin Juma of Katif. The Political Af^ent is in correspondence with the Amir of Katif about the matter. 80. The public has recently experienced some difficulty in procuring meat for daily use. It is said Sheikh Isa bin Ali has 20 Rtibas ai Re.l per R&amp;ba (or 4 lbs) instead of Rs.l/s/- which is the usual rate. The privilege is also demanded by other Sheikhs and Fidawis. There is thus some dissatisfaction amongst the butchers who can ill afford to sell at the rate claimed by these Sheikhs owing to keavy Customs and other charges. The butchers consequently went on strike and re fused to kill for a week. Matters seem to be improving now but the Political Agent intends to raise the question with Sheikh Isa shortly. Major, Political Agent, Bahrein. L.D• 1 QUARANTINE . (Summary of hia inspection of steamers that called at Bahrein, during the week ending 10th January 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain* The 'Onda' arrived from Lingah on 4th January 1914, and left on 8th instant* 12 passengers were landed after inspection which showed nothing particular# She was granted a free pratique* The 3.S# 'Bankura* arrived from Dubai on 4th January 1914, and left the next afternoon* Inspection was made and having found nothing particular 161 passengers were landed* She was granted a free pratique* The S.S. 'Barala' arrived from Rushire on 6th January 1914, and left the same afternoon* After inspection which show ed nothing particular 337 passengers were landed* She was grant- ed^a free pratique* One death occured on 4th January 1914, due to old age*CONiTlDEOTlAt /o British TResicency 8? Consulate General, Vjr BusJarf[^^fidl2^BhssL:/ 191,4. \ ( Lia ~- i '.n the diary sent in by your Head Clerk for the week ending January 3rd-, there is mention of a rumour at the Hamburg- Amerika Linie working between Bombay and the Gulf Ports. Would you be so ' ind as to ascertain the source of the rumour, and let us know whether you think there is anything in it? lajor A.P.Trevor, C.I.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. / /Jf&amp;-1? II RAH.RFI15, the 18th January 19 34 Dear Chick, %/ nvT de^i-official of January IStia, 19 14• There wa® a. report ourront about th© Hawburg**Am8r Xk a Lini 8 oponing a Bombay service* The Elsslonnrle© aleo heard it. But I do not think: there is anything in it. Probably the wish is father to the thought - not th&amp;t people are specially fond of the Hamburg America Linie, but they find it better than the British India. The report as put Into the diary to show fa j/xhnyl. of public opinion. Poselbly the fact that a senior partner 1^ cnckhaus 1 firm is now out here has something to do with it t I r^.ould imagine thnt before euoh a line could really be started the Company would have to get a line running to Bombay and ret thops elves firmly Installedthere. ours Sincerely I. CHICK Esquire, B U B H I H E* !&gt; hm No. 19 14 Polltloeu. /j^wncy#Bahrein, Bahrein news for the week ending 17th January 19 14 CONDITION OF COUNTRY. . jjjgZ 21# It is rumoured that Abdul Aziz bin Saud has taken 3 cannons ARRIVALS and DEPARTURES of SHIPS , 22• On the 11th S^S.^BarJora 11 arrived from Lingah and left for Bushire on the 33th. 2S- On the 16th S#S.'Bankura* arrived from Bushire and left for Lingah the same day. Miscellaneous . 24. Lieut-Colonel W 0 G.Gray # the new Political Agent,Kuweit who was the passenger by S•£SBar3ora ,, called on the Political Agent on the 32th. 28. Rev. G. Boys, C.M.S. Missionary at Bagdad also a passenger by S^S.^Barjora 11 called on the Political Agent. 26. Shaikhs Hamed and Abdulla bin Isa bin Ali al Khalifa paid a visit to the Political Agent on the 11th and Shaikh Muhammad bin Isa bin Ali al Khalifa on the 13th. 27. Reference diary No.18 Shaikh Abdulla bin Hassan Dosiri informed Shaikh Isa that he was willing to buy the piece of Irnd for the poor people. Shaikh Isa said that Shaikh Ahmed bin Mehza asked him to take 3000/- from him for the ground. Shaikh Abdulla bin .lasean asked that the matter should be referred to the Shara - Shaikh Isa said he would into it. It is said Shaikh Ahmed bin Mehza has divided the place between from Hasa to Riadiu, Shaikh Isa and Hashid DoaeeM Major, Political Agent,Bahrein.aJARAMTmE . Euraraary of Inspection of steamers that called at Bahrein during the week ending 17th January 1914, furnished by the quarantine Medical Officer,Bahrein, &amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp; The S»S#BarJora arrived from Lingah on 11th January 19 34 and left on ISth inetant,Inspection was made and having found nothing particular 53 passengers were landed* There was one death due to chronic dysentry on 6th January 39 34. The ship was granted a free pratigue# The S«S#3ankura arrived from Buehire on 16th January 19 34 and left the same evening. One female passenger died at Bushire due to old age.During inspection one old Persian was found dead and concealed under thej^ bed clothings. The death Is supposed to be due to chronic diarrhoea and old age.Having ^ found nothing else particular 300 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratigae.No.4/9r/ of 1914. POLITICAL AGEMCY, BAHREIN. Bahrein news for the week ending 24th January 1914. &amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp; LOCAL OFFICIAL . 28• Heporte seem to shew that Shaikh Ahmed bin Mehza, the brother of the Chief Kazi and a factotum whom Shaikh Isa em ploye in dubious land transactions, has now got round Shaikh Hamed bin Isa and is acting for him in the same capacity. It is reported that he is going to evict a lot of poor people who have been ' b (patting 1 * on some land near the Basri bar^ar for many years. KATIF, 29. Rumour in Bahrein, accuses the Amir of Katif of being very grasping in the matter of bribes. It is said that Bin v Baud has appointed one Sa^#id Ali bin Suleiman to watch him. CONDITION OF COUNTPY . 50. It is reported that Bin Baud is having the guns at Katif put in as good condition as possible. ARRIVALS AND DKPABTURKS OF SHIPS . 51. On the 20th s.8. w Putiala w arrived from Dubai and left for Bushire on the 21st instant. 32. On the 21st s-s.^Barjora 1 * arrived from Bushire and left for down Gulf Ports the same day. E.S. ,, Markomannia H arrived from Lingah and left for Bushire the same day. S5. On the 23rd s.s.^Ferrara** arrived from Bushire and left for down Gulf ports on the 24th instant. 34. MISCFLLAKEOUS . With reference to diary $o.27 it transpires that the ground from which Sheikh Ahmed bin l^ehza was trying to evict some poor people ostensibly on behalf of Sheikh Isa, was sold to Shaikh Ahmed some two years ago for $ 1000/- . Shaikh Abdulla bin Hussani Dosiri is no? trying to buy it for the poor occupiers for15 f for If 1500/- and has enlisted the eytnpathiee of Shaikh Abdulla bin Isa on their behalf# try and recover a debt of t. 20p000/~ from Abdulla bin Hueeain bin Jurm of Katlf# The Political Agent ha© been in correepon- deno© with the Amir of Katlf who promleoe to enqplre Into the caee and enforce payment of the debt If proved but at present Eyed Abdulla is afraid to go to Katlf on account of the above- mentioned report® regarding the Aisir# Efforts are therefore, being T-ade to effect eoire amicable eettlement. ith reference to diary rio«19 £yed Abdulla Meraon represent ing the Karachi fins of Doealani &amp; Co. hac come to Bahrein to Major, Pol i t i cal'-flgwt, Bahrein.I&amp; (Summary of his inspection of steamers that called at Bahrein, during the wesk ending January 1914, furnished by the ^sarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein# The e#s* ,, Putiala tt arrived from Dubai on 20th January 1914, and left the next day# Inspection shewed nothing particular on board and 4P passengers were landed# She was granted a free prati- &lt;pe. The 6♦s• ,, Bar3ora ,, arrived from Buehire on 21st January 1914, and left the same day« After inspection 52 passengers were landed. She was granted a free prati qie* The s.s. MarVommania arrived from Lingah on Blet January 1914, and left the same evening. After inspection of the ship only 6 pas- B sengers were landed. She was granted a free praticpe. The s.s.^Ferrara' arrived from Bushire on 25rd January 1914, and is still in harbour. Inspection shewed nothing particular. She was granted a free prati que#'7 HO • 5 of 1914 * POLITICAL AOKWGX$ BAItRKIW. Bahrein newci for th@ week ending : lot January 1914» OOroiTIOn OF OOimTRY . ^ S)trcU ***-0 37 • A cold blooded atter^pt wa^ mdo at Manama to mu'lerj^yed 1 la a nan bin Mahomed In the early hours of the 28th January 1914» ^he Hyed was awakened feeling a knife beinr drawn aeroaa hie throat* He states he saw that his a assailant was a Kurd* and two or three Kurd is wore watching# Some Kurd i a have boon arrested on auBpssciaru Syed Husaaln is still alive, and there seems a prospect of his our- vivinf if no coniplicationa arise. FOR l 'T^ 58* Syed Talib Pasha of Basirah has written to Sheikh Isa, Bheikh Abdulla bin Jasira, Tusuf bin Ahmnd • anoo and others asking the© to raise subscriptians for purohasinp* warships for the Turkish aw. The Volte-faces executed by this individual are extraordinary, at one womont a deputy for Basrah, the next or^anizin^ fetation for autonomy of fluarah Vilayet and plotting a rains t the Turkish Valise, now a patriot* If sorfiethinr could be done to stop his mischievous aotivities with outside Arab Sheikhs it would be a rood thing p but^probably it^is impossible• f _ 39* (fn the 25th s»s M laroda' arrived from Dubai and left for ^ushire ,on the 26th. 40* On the 30th s.s. w Putiala* arrive from Bunhire and left for Linrah the same day* mi30 t :ll vmom. Al tu c &lt;*) dju* &gt; r - 41* Reference para 56. The ne^ociations for amicable settlement with Abdulla bin Juma havinr fallen throurh Syed Abdulla has at last plucked up courage to m to Katif, he hae been riven a letter to the Amir of Katif* 42* The Sheikh has Just got up a 42 feet sea ^oin™ launch from Bombay. The faot of his having a launch rather emphasises the absence of the Agency Launch* 43* Abdulla a correspondent of w A1 Foayad' has arrived and is a ruestmeet of Sheikh laa. He says that having heard in Kvypt that they were hol^lnrr meetinm of nobles in Koweit he went there, but found nothing of the kind# Ma lor, political Agent # Bahrein#Q UARANTINE (Summary of his inspootion of steamers that called at Bahrein, during the week ending 50th January 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrein. The s.s w Haroda M arrived from Dubai on 25th January 1914, and left the next day* Xaspeotion showed nothing parti cular on board and 82 passengers were landed, ^he was pranted a free pratique. The s.s. 'Putiala' arrived from Bushire on 50th January 1914, and left the same day. There was nothing particular found on board and after inspection BO passanfrers v/ere landed. She was granted a free pratique.2i Of 1914 Political Agency, Bahrein. News for the week ending the 7th February 1914. &amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;■&amp; 4RRTVALS AND DEPARTURES OF SH IPS . 44. On the 1st S.E.'Eardar' arrived from Ling-ih and left for Buehire on the 2nd. 45. On the 2nd S.E.'Barala' arrived from Debai and left for Buehlre on the 3rd. 46. On the 3rd S.S.'Barada' arrived from Buehire and left for down Gulf ports the same day. VISCELLAREOUS . 47 Shaikh Hawed bin lea bin All has sent 2 camels as a pre sent to Ehaikb Mubarak. 4B. Reference para 42. Ehaikh Isa is reported not to be very pleased with hie launch as the craft is an old one. 49. The Political Agent visited Shaikh Isa on the 1st February#qUARANTIHE , (Summary of hia Inspection of steamers that called at Bahreln # during the week ending 7th February 1914, furnish ed by the Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrein# The s.s# 'Sardar' arrived from Lingah on let February 1914 and left the next day. Inspection showed nothing parti cular on board and 54 passengers *rere landed. She was granted a free pratique# The s»3» w Barala n arrived from Dubai on 2nd February 1914 and left the next day. After inspection all the passengers for Bahrein (61) were removed to the Quarantine Gamp, where they stayed till the 5th instant. There was nothing particular found. The s#s. w Baroda w arrived from Buahire on 5rd February 1914 and loft the same afternoon. After inspection which showed nothing -sarticular except a case of ouspecicus Typoid, which was isolated, 247 passengers were landed. The shit) was granted a free pratique.-23 Ho. ^ Of 1914. POLITICAL AOmOY, BAHRRlIf • Bahrein news for the week endlncr 14th February 1914. jccplDI^IO^ QI r OOOHTRY» K/^TR 50. Owln# to the drought at Katr it la said the catties are heinpr aent to Haeaa for crraalnr and that Shaikh Abdulla bin ^Taoalm bin Than! haa ordered the people to fast for 5 days and then offer public prayers for rain. [ ARRIVAL3 4IID QLPAH^UHES OF 3tlIP3 , 51. On the 8th a.a. ' ankura' arrived frora Linsrah and left for BusMre the same day. 52• on the 13th a.a. M Barala w arrived from Bushlre and left for down ~ulf ports Lawrence' arrived with steam launch *^1^01^ and the former left on the 14th. The Persian 'ulf s.a# ;3oy f a 'Sardar' arrived in Bahrein frotn up nulf on the 14th and left the same afternoon. On leaving she fired a salute of 5 puna. MI3CELLA*IKOm3 . 55. Hewa was received by the Political Apent on the evening of the 13th instant of the sad death of Mr J.O. Lorimer, 0»I.^. f I«0.S. Officiating Political Resident in the Persian nulf» ^he fla&lt;r was hoisted at half mast and the Agency office was closed on the 14th aa a mark of respect to the deceased. The Hindu, liritish Indian ^uharamadan coBtFiunltlea and the prin- cipal men amonc? the Persian and Jewish residents in Bahrein waited on the Political A&lt;?ent to express their condolence with the 'ovem- roent at the lost of such a valuable officer anl with the relatives of the deceased at their sad breaveraent • -reat sympathy was shewn by all. he British subjects closed their shops and places of busi ness, as did a larro number of the Persiansand Jewish oommunities. Aa soon as word could be frot across from 'aharaq the Shaikh sent orders to have the fla^s on his flap-staff and Custom's office hoistedat half wast In W io v position t v 9? were Vopt for t^a rnst of the day. Shaikh Abdul la hln laa oallod In tho aftamoon to ojtnroBa his father's condolence (and bia own) with rovernnent and with Mr- In person to offer hla condolenoo» Shaikh ^ejbil, Yusuf 'anaiir# Tusuf Kanoo and other leading Arabs also called to express their condolence. The gentlemen of the .American Mission also called in the afternoon with the same object. r, h® sudden and trails news haa shocked everyone• 54# Reports say that All bin Abdul la and All bin ^Tbrahlra ayani are canvasinr: with pearl isorchants and others for sal© of the Persian Oulf Steam ^avlnation Gorm&amp;ny*® shares and that they have sold about He.50,000A worth of shares to Shaikh Isa who nromisr^ to buy roor© later. Tho latter statement seems rather doubtful as Shalfeh is not as a rule at all ready to part with money on new on tho 10th instant. They tooB 2 days enroute and stayed there a day and returned on Friday in a few hours in a stiff shaml. While there they interviewed in '»aud f s Amir and asked permission for the doctor to visit Katif etc In the Pearling season. The Aralr was very friendly and said he would be prlad to see the®. The Missionaries told the Political A^ont about thete exnedi tlon on Saturday after making the visit referred to above. Lorliser's famil: Shaikh laa Political Agent 9 Bahrein. |% QUARANTINE . (Summary of hia inspection of ateamora that called at Bahrein, during the weelt ending 14th February 1914 f furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrein* The s.a. H Rankura ,, arrived from Lingah on 8th February 1914, and left the same evening. Inspection showed nothing parti cular on board and 51 passengers were landed. Ghe was granted a free pratique. The a.s. 'Barala' arrived from Bushire on 15th February 1914, and left the same day. After the inspection which showed nothing particular on board 175 passengers were landed. She was granted a free pratique.NO. 7 Of 1914. POIiITIOAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Bahrein newa for the week ending 21st February 1914, LOCAL OFFICIALS * 56• Shaikh Fahed bin Jaesira bin Thani ha?? oorae to Bahrein to get narried and is staying at Shailch Isa's. 57* Messrs Haji i floods • POHKIGH IN^ERT^STS . 58• Two Germans, one Mr Oscar Blauert, a nev/ assistant of Messrs Robert ''onokhaus &amp; Co., and one a Doctor named (?) Deeds an Aroha- aolofiist who has been travelling in Persia come to Bahrein from Basrah on the 13th instant. Dr Deeds left for Oombay on the r7th» 59. Reference para 58. notices have been received in Bahrein from 3aiyid Talib stating that he has joined the Turks. A copy of one Df the notices is attached. c—' ARRIVALS AND DEimRTUHrCS OF 3HIPS . 50. On the 17th s.s. ^Barjora** arrived from Dubai and left for Bushire the same day. s.s. 'Rankura' arrived from Bushire and left for down nulf sorts the same day. ^ISCELLATTfiOUS . 31. Local report says that Captain ShakesDear will ro to Bin Pashid In Hayil and thence proceed to suez and that he has a caravan of 40 camels . 52. Shaikh Isa bin Ali al Khalifa and Shaikh ^uhammed bin Isa sailed on the Political Agent on the 16th to express their condol- snce with Government and with Mr Lorimer's family. 53. Reference para 54. Owing to the efforts of Ali bin Ibrahim 2ayani and others, a ridiculous amount of fuss was made durinf the recent visit of the s.s. f, Sardar H belonging to the new Persian ^ulf BRITISH INTERESTS. ^5 team£7 Steam navigation Gov., now bein^ floated. Every boat in the place vent off and it is reported that Shaikh Isa sent presents to the Daptain. Chief Officer and Chief Engineer. A .sood many people appear to have siascribed for shares in the new Coiimany headed apparently by Shaikh Isa who appears to have abandoned his usual mution* 54. Reference para 54 another sale of land on which poor people irere 'squatting 1 * has taken place. This tirrje Shaikh Hamed appears bo have sold the piot to a jew named Ishaq ^55. Shaikh Khalifah bin Ahmed, who had been given a p&amp;ece of grounrl near the around used by the boat builders on the west of the town, findins: it not larrre enough has got the Shaikh to force the ^oat builders to give him a piece of ground which they hadepreviously bought from Shaikh Isa and receive back what they paid for it. The boat builders have been seriously inconvenienced as they have no place near their houses where they can work. 66. The Political Agent called on Shaikh Isa on the 20th. Condition of Country. P.3. Reference para 37. Syed Hassan has recovered from his wound and was able to pick out his assailaali from among the Kurds who had been detained on; suspicion, inquiries into the matter are proceeding but it seems impossible that any corroborative evidence will be forthcoming.aK QUARANTINE . (SxiiDinary of his inspection of steamers that called at Bahrein, during the week ending Slst February 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. The s • s • 'Sardar** arrived from Bushire on 14th Feb ruary 1914, and left the same evening. Inspection resulted in nothing particular on board and 170 passengers were landed. She was granted a free pratique. The s.s. 'Barjora' arrived from Dubai on 17th February 1914, and left the same evening. After the inspection 39 passen gers were removed to the quarantine station where they stayed till 20th February. Nothing particular to be noticed. The s.s. f, Ban}cura M arrived from Bushire on 17th Feb ruary 1914, and left the same afternoon. Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 86 passengers were landed. She was granted a free pratique.NO, 8^ of 1914* POLITICAL AOEKOY, rJAHRF^IH. [ Bahrein news for the week ending 28th February 1914. 5: %% ' : i k kBiMkMk&amp;kh L ocal official . 67# Shaikh lea has given the ^Bushlrl Asara^ a sort of larjre aera ! in Manaim to hie eon Shaikh AMulla In order that he may maVe a ^i«ar there* # ■gO^DITIOH OF 0;.Um?HY. KATIF 68. Xt la reported that the Amir of Katif proceeded with 2B oamele to the house of Abdul llueealn bin Jum at night and arrested his. It 13 said that Abdul ? uesatn bin Juma with 13 other notables of Hasaa wrote a letter to the urks aaltlnp: them to come and that this letter was intei^j£ed and carried to nin Baud? henc^ thie action. kRHIVALl AIID DFFAnTlFinB. OF Snipq . 69. On the 23rd S.S. w Lindula n arrived fvor^ Dubai and left for uahiis on the 34th. 70• On the 24th 3.3. ^Budrie^ arrived from Dubai and left for ^ushire on the kj7th* 71 ♦ S.J. 'Barjora 1 * arrived from Buehlre and left for down 'ulf Porte. M13 0ELLAH IvOUij # W2. Shaikh Hasted bin lea called on the Political Agent on the 2Bth to offer condolence on the death of Mr Lorinert and to anolorlze for not calling with his father aa he was in the Interior at the tijne. 73. Reference nara 41 the Amir of Katif belnr unable to settle the claim of ^eesre Doealani against Abdulla bin Jursa sent an attorney of the latter with 3yed Abdulla Doaalani *3 repreoentatlve over to Bahrein to appear before Mejlia-Kl-Urf. The caee was heard by the 'ejlie on the 24th instant and the &lt;^xe^a»-part of 3ved Abdul la's claira waa tyunhcXir, The Arent had Juat made arrangements to pay up between 12,000 to 15 f 000/bo Syed Abdulla by making -dv noe salea of next year's date crop, when ha heard the news mentioned in para 68 above i and made himself scarce on the night of the 26th 27th. ,r he Political»olitioal Aswit however hoi)03 to rooover the money t^rour?h ths Amir ^ Katlf plus a sum of Rq»1000/- which pftyArent mve on undortaklnpr t ,0 par If he left without the Political Apent's t^orniaoion and before ,he settlement of the oaee* JJj-* On the arrival of the 3 .B, w Lindula w on the eveninr of 25rd .netant 9 All bin Ibrahim brolrar of esars Ho&amp;enthal &lt;vwA. the paasenrers •efused to go to quarantine and went off to Maharraq in epite of the doctor's orders* ^e was however sent to quarantine by the Shailch m the representation of the Political Awnt# When called before the flmikh he alleged falsely in the opinion of the Political A^ent, that .he Quarantine Isdloal Of floor had let 1^»«Hoff polnj? to quarantine, t la hopei-l that the Shaikh will fine hlsi. I Major, Political Asent, Bahrein. 'I I3! OfTARANTIME Summary of hia inspection of steamers that called at Bahrein, during the week ending 28th February 1914, furnished 'by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. ■ The S.S, w Lindula w arrived from Dubai on 25rd Febru ary 1914, and left the next day. Passengers remained in quarantine till 26th February. Nothing else particular was noticed. The S^S.^Budrie' arrived from Dubai on 24th February 1914, and left on the 27th instant. Passengers remained in quarantine till the 26th instant. Except a case of venereal . disease on board, there was nothing particular to be found. The S.S. 'Barjora' arrived from Bushire on 27th Feb ruary 1914, and left the same evening. Inspection showed nothing suspecious on board and 78 passengers were landed. She was grant ed a free pratique. .tHo. 9 - Of 1914. POLITICAL AOEHOT, ^AltRBIH 32. Bahrein news for the week endlne; 7th 'arch 1914. i nmuirion of oqipitry♦ hassa ^ ^atif 75 # Reference p^ra 68« There are various rumours about the reason for Abdul Huasatn bin Juma^ deputation ^roir. ^atif to llaasa# Some say that it is in connection with the olaira of Dosalani against him, nin Haud belnp: annoyed that he vot the oa ?e referred to the Bahrein MeJlis; others say that it is because Abdul Huasavn ie too influential at Katif and too pro-^ur^; others that a letter of his to the ' ur^s has been intercepted# It is said that he is not imprisoned in Tfassa, but is detain ed there at lar^e* 76. It is reDOrted that Bin 3aud has sent a few more men to garrison Katif and that he is keeping a strict lool^ out to ret news of any Turkish movements. It ia said that ho is cominr to Hassa shortly* 77. Apparently although the OJair Hassa trade route Is safer than it has been for years, many merchants are not attempting to increase their business as they are afraid of extortions by officials if they mafce too much money* ARK ivalb A t 1d DKPAH?IIRT%B op 3nip.3 . 78• On the 2nd S.3 # '^aroda'* arrived from Dubai and left for ^ushire on the 5rd# 79* On the 5rd 3.B# * uindula tt arrived from rmshire and left for * down ^ulf Porta on the same day. 80 • On the 7th 3 # S. ^Sardar* 1 arrived from down f! ulf p orts and is still in the ^arbour* Bl, MISOELLAflKOUS . All bin Ihrahln Zayanl Afont of the Peralan 'ulf Stea^ navi gation Oortpany tallce of brlnglnc up two aea rrolnf launches to trade with Katif and Katar» ^2-. Shaikh lea has i i sued a notice to the effect that the new ■ P mlanding rules will b® brought into foroa in on© rsonth'^ time in 30 far ae tbey effect shore arrangemento • 3hit)pini? £o y, *&gt;%ni.e&amp; * df^ents may take over landing sooner If they can* Y 3 Shaikh laa has left for a few days shoot In rr in the interior. Yfy - The Political Agent had a discussion vrith Bhailrh Abdulla bin Isa (on behalf of his father) on 1st ,f aroh about certain rinor alterations In the landing rules. Shaikh Abdulla agreed to then / but on 7th Tfarch Juat before goln^ to oarm Bhalkh Isa said he could not accept them# On the Ist Shaikh Abdulla Mn Isa called on the Political A^ent• w -J 'aJor, Political Agent, Bahrein. - y fiuv ^ 4 ^' uyj U- ^ ^ J / / J*i _ C ~^sl Lsf fSUTmnary of his inepeotior) of steamere that called at ■ Bahrein t during the week ending 7th Msroh 1914, furnished by the Quarantine ^edical Officer, Bahrein# The 3» 3. ^Baroda' arrived from Dubai on 2nd March 1914, and left the next afternoon. Inspection showed nothing particular on board and all passengers rerrained in quarantine ^ till 6th March. Nothing particular was noticed in the aarop, except one case of diarrhoea and two cases of Malarial fever* The -3. 3. 'Idndula' arrived from Pushire on 3rd March 1914, and left the same afternoon. After inspection 13-5 paosen- srers were landed. The ship was granted a free nratlque. &amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp; &amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&lt;&amp; 3If. 10 of 1914. POLmOAL A^IICY, BAHREIH. News for the week anding 14th March 1014. notmiTioyr o-- GOUHTRY . 95# Bin Saud aalfl to have writtan to Shailrh 'ubaralr; some say he told the latter that he may a^ree on hia behalf to all the oonditlona laid down hy the Turkloh ^overnoont if they will allow him to retain T 'a sa and Katif; others say that he authorized : Shaikh Mubarak to say that if Turkish ''oveminent will increase his allowance and not interfere with him In Hfejd he is nrepa^el to give back Fassa and Tr atif to the 'urke. 86. One of the nhailrh'8 relatives ^ubarak bin ?f oham©d bin Ahmed Al Khalifah aged about 18 years son of Shaikh Ali bin Ahmed's brother* died of amall-^ox on the 8th instant. FORK I 87 • 'ohmood Effimdi British Officer has arrived by the ^ . ^Budrie' from Basrah with 11 soldiers, who had run away from F'atr H# has also brought nrovisions for the detachment at Katr, and will proceed there when the wind is favourable* ARHIVAL3 A r fD D^ARTUHTyS OF SniPU . 88. On the Bth. Reference diary ^o.BO 3. 3. Tartar* left for Buahire and S. S. tt narala H arrived from Dubai and left for nushiro on the 10th# 89• On the 12th S.S. w Budrio* arrived from 'ushire and left for down lulf norts on the same day# &gt;. Sm w Hlfbatana' arrival fro^ ^urone and left for usblre on the 15th instant# 90# On the 13th ^3.*^aroda w arrived from ^ushire and left for down mif Ports the same day# Politinnl Ar^nt. rj «. b r» a 1 if 'ajogilARANTINE. Summary of his inspection of steamers that called at Bahrein, during the weel- ending 14th March 1914- furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. The S» S# w Sardar w arrived from Lingah on 7th v? arch 1914 and left the next day. Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 51 passengers were landed* She was granted a free pratique# The S# S. 'Barala** arrived from Dubai on 8th March 1914, and left the third day# 111 passengers were removed to the Quaran tine camp where they stayed till 12th March, There was nothing particular noticed after the inspection in the camp. The B# S• w Budrie w arrived from Bushire on 12th March 1914, and left the same evening# After inspection which resulted in nothing particular 102 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique# The S. 'Ekbatana' arrived from Lingah on 12th T r arch 1914, and left the next early morning. After inspection 12 -oassen- gers were landed. She was granted a free pratique. The S. 3. 'Baroda^ arrived from Bushire on l^th March 1914, and left the same afternoon# Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 20^ passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique#Ho 11^ POLITICAL AfSEHCX, Of 1914. BAHRAIN. Hews for the weak ending Slat March 1914, L OCAL OFFICIAL''' » 98. Tbe relations between Shaikh Jasin bin 'ehsa the chief Kasi and the Amir of Manama have been vary atrained of late, both T &gt;ar- tiea having made oomplainta and counter comlainta to the nhaikh against each other. Shaikh Jaaim bin ! | ehaa tall^a of aendinr in his reaimation, but probably if ha doea it will not be accented# Thara la nobody in Bahrein who would be ao efficient a Kaasi aa Shaikh Jaslia bin ^shsa* gQ^ DI'^TO^ OF CJIiHTR Y» Hasaa and Katif. 05• ^in Baud ia said to have written to Shaikh laa bin Ali A1 Khalifah inforainp: him that he intended to start from Ri&amp;dh with aoxne of hla foroea on the 12th Habi Thani and to halt between ^aaoi Katif. T Hn Saud la reported to have ?sent 150 nsore men to Katif, and to have put on a tax at Hasaa for Military ©xpenoes. 94. Baiyid Talib of Basrah ia reported to have aent a letter to Bin Gaud with HuhaTOned bin Haaaan Bualahery who proceeded to Haaaa on the 18th inatant. '-'uhan^ed bin nas«an atated that the 'urka have at prasant no intention of com in-* to t !aaaa and ''at if • 5. Mahmood Sffendi ''elasar? who arrived from ^aarah by tha S. r U ,, F?udrie H laat week with rroviaiona for detachment at Katr# hired a Persian boat for Ha. 150A to go to Katr. The Persian brought a aixiall boat and there was a dispute about it. ^ahsiood 'Tfendi alao had a diapute with ao^e turda for coolie hire. Katr 5) 96. There waa good rain / whio)'' waa very badly naeied / in Katr. ARRIVAL:! AND D-^ARTtmrq OF G^IPS. 97. On the llth 3.-1. 'Bankura' arrived from D $mi and left for Buahire on the 17th. 98. On the 17th S.S. ,, BaraaLa f, arrived from uahire and left for down -ulf Porta on the 18th.99* I• &gt;• w Palinuru3 ,f arrived on the afternoon of the l^th from Bunder A&gt;&gt;ba3 anl left for the neighbourhood ^ 'Has Tanura early oti the 20 th^ 100* On the 18th S* 3» w Sardar w arrived frora nushire and left for down 'ulf Porta the sai!?e evening. 101* I• lU 3« ^Lawrence** arrived with a buoy on the afternoon of the 20th and left to renlaoe the outer buoy on the of the 21et* 'TfsC'-'iLA.nKOTjr; . 102• Cantain Willian flood of the Salvation Army who had come here on the 2nd instant to oolleot eubaoriptiono left on the 17th for Buehlre# Political Apent, Bahrein. Major#QUARANTINE Summary of his inspection of steamers that called at Bahrein, during the week ending 14th ''arch furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. The S.S. 'Bankura* arrived from Dubai on 16th March 1914, and left the next afternoon- 86 passengers were removed to the quarantine camp where they stayed till 20th March. They were left off after medical inspection which showed nothin t suspecious. The S* S. 'Barala' arrived from Bushire on 17th March 1914, and left the next early morning. Inspection showed nothing particular on board; 46 passengers were landed. The i ship was granted a free pratique* The S» S. M 3ardar w arrived from Bushire on 18th March 1914, and left the same afternoon. Inspection showed noth -ing particular on board and 86 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique. li . I m v C.Ho. IS/ of 1'14. M- POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHHBIH, News for the week ending 28th llaroh 19X4, LOCAL OFFICIAL:; 103. Shaikh loa bin All Al Khalifah left on the 26th for the Island of Umnaaan on a 4 daya gazelle shooting expedition. COHDITIOK O tr COOHTRT s (Katif) 104• It is said that Mohammed bin Zeid has cor^e to Katif in Ooramand of about 1000 of Bin 3»ud f « men# t j 105# Local reporta say that shaikh ^ubarak invited the TW ali of Basrah to Kowait to arrange a settlement between Turks and Bin Baud; the Wall did not go but sent his Secretary to Koweit to hear what they had to say# ARHIVAL^ rVm OF mam . 106• On the 22nd 'Barjora*' arrived fron Linrah and left for Bushire on the 2^rd. 107• On the 27th 3.G. 'lankura* arrived from Buahire and loft for down Gulf Ports the same day. 106. BmBm •'John 0 3cott H and *Canara w arrived fron Basrah and Lingah on the 27th, and are still in the roadstead. 109. H.I.II.3. 'Palinurus 1 ' arrived on the afternoon of the 27th, and will return to survey tomorrow morning. ^IBO^LLANHOUS * 110. 'arious reports are current about the hapnenings at Owun Al 'TTavlir. U^nxyyi, UsC f'ajor, * Political Arent, Bahrein.Summary of his inspeouion of steamers that oalled at Bahrein, during the week ending 28th March furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein# The S.3. 'Barjora' arrived from Lingah on 22nd March 1914, and left the next afternoon* Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 93 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique. The S»3. 'Bankura* 1 arrived from Bushire on 27th March 1914, and left the same afternoon. Except a case of Liver abcess nothing particular was found. The ship was grant ed a free pratique. 35 passengers were landed* The S.S* w John Scott' arrived from Bussreh on 27th March 1914, and is still in Harbour. Nothing suspecious was found except that the ship was in a very dirty condition. 34 passengers were landed# She was granted a free pratique. The 3.S. 'Canara' arrived from Linpah on 27th March 1914, and is still in Harbour. There was nothing parti cular on board. ^0 passengers were landed. She was granted a free pratique. r 1 I ri!^ tya RAKTIHE. Sinnmary of bis inspection of steamers that called at Bahrein, during the week ending r 3Bd April 1914, furnished hy the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. The S. S* 'Virawa' arrived from Dubai on 139th March 1914, and left the next day. She had no passengers on board. She worked in quarantine till 1st April# There was nothing parti cular to note on board. The S.S. w Barjora H arrived from Bushire on 31st March 1914, and left the same afternoon. Inspection showed nothing parti cular • 4V passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique. The S. 3. n Persepoli3 w arrived from Lingah on 51st March 1914 and left the next day. She brought 19 passengers for Bahrein and who were landed after inspection. The ship was granted a free pratique- Ths 3m 3. 'Iiindula' arrived from Dubai on 5l3t March 1914, and left the next day. 85 passengers were removed to the quaran tine camp, where they will stay till the 4th instant. There was nothing suspecious on board. The S. S. 'Ferrara* arrived froia Rushire on Ist April 1914, and left the next morning. She had only one passenger for Bahrein. There was nothing else particular to be noticed. The ship was granted a free pratique.SUTnmary of his ina^eotion of ships that entered Bahrein during the week ending 11th April 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. The S*3• 'Baroda** arrived frotn Lingah on 4th March 1914, and left on the 6th instant. Inspection showed nothing particular on hoard and 112 passengers were allowed to land* Ship was granted a free pratique# The S.S, 'Bardar 1 * arrived from Linfrah on 9th April 1914, and left on the next day. After inspection which showed tiothing particular on board 103 passengers were landed. Ship was granted a free pratique. The S.S. 'Koweit** arrived frora Dubai on 10th A^ril 1914, and is still in harbour. She has brought 4 passengers from Dubai; they will remain in quarantine till the 14th instant* Nothing else particular to be noticed.! n TTARANTINK . Soimmary of his Inspection of oteamers that called at Bahrein, during the week ending 17th April 1914, furnished ■ by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. . T The S.S* w Iiindula tt arrived frora Buahire on 12th . /\pril 191 1 1 and left the same evening. Inspection showed nothing particular on board. 439 passengers were landed. The ahlp was granted a free pratique. ■ The S.S. 'Barala' arrived from Dubai on 13th April 1914, and left the next afternoon. 61 pasaengera remained In quarantine till the 17th Instant. Except a case of Ohronlc dya- entery there vfaa nothing ^articular noticed. The S.S. 'Baroda' arrived from Bushlre on the 14th April 1914. and left the aame day at 3 p.m. After Inanectlon which resulted In nothlns particular 71 pasaengera were landed. the ahlp was granted a free tiratlque. The S.S. 'Budrle' arrived from Bubal on 17th April 1914, and left the aame evening. 17 passengers were removed to the quarantine camp where they will stay till the Ust Instant. There was nothing particular on board the jhip.quarantine. Summary of his inspection of steamers that called at Bahrein, during the week ending 25th April 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. The S« S• 'Bankura' arrived from Lingah on 18th April 1914, and left the next afternoon. Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 308 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique. The S. S. ^Bahrein? arrived from Dubai on 18th April 1914, and left the next afternoon. 10 passengers were removed to the Quarantine camp where they stayed till the 21sit instant. There was nothing martioular to be noticed. The S. S. 'Sardar' arrived from Bushire on 20th April 1914, and left the same evening. She brought 165 passengers for Bahrein. All were allowed to land after inspection which did not show anything suspecious on board. The ship was granted a free pratique. The S. S. 'Barala' arrived from Bushire on 24th April 1914, and left the same afternoon. Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 816 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique.55 qriARASTIWE . Summary of his inspeotion of ships that called at Bahrein during the week ending 1st May 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein* The S*S« ^Bandra 1 * arrived from Debai on 2?th April 1914, and left the next afternoon. Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 102 passengers were removed direct to the Quarantine Gamp, where they stayed fctXl the Set instant• There was nothing suspecious noticed on inspection# The 'Bankura* arrived from Bushire on 29th April 1914, and left the same afternoon. After inspection which resulted in nothing particular 111 passengers were landed. % The ship was granted a free pratique♦% Ho. l^hz/of 1914. BAHREIN POLITICAL AGfENOT. News for the week ending 9th May 1914. PONDITION OF QOUHTHY ♦ 151• Two or three of the leading men of Haasa are now in Bahrein and staying with Shaikh laa hin Ali A1 Khalifah. FOREIGN INTERESTS . 152. Mr. Hoist of Mesara Robert Wonckhaua &amp; Co., arrived from Germany by S.3. * , Kioomedia ,, after ataying here a few weeks he will proceed to Ahwaz. He is reported to have received the Hamburg Amerika Companies 1 instructions about the new landing arrangements. ARRIVALS AND DBPARTtJRgS OF SHIPS . 153* On the 3rd 3.S. tt Barjora w and H Budrie w arrived from Lingah ahd Bushire and left for Bushire and Bombay on the 5th and 6th. 3.3. 'Budrie' run aground in the roadstead. 154. On the 7th S.S. 'Oolobaria 11 arrived from Koweit and is still in the roadstead. 156. On the 8th S.S. ,, Nipomedia ,, of the, Hamburg £merika Linie arrived from Lingah and S.S. 'Bandra' also arrived from Bushire and left the same day for down Gulf porta MI SCELLiANEGUS . 156. An Armenian named Mushal arrived here with samples of piece- goods and left for Bushire. 157. Mr. Hugh Langdale of the Anglo Persian Oil Company arrived from Mohammerah on the 8th and after inspecting the stocks of their Company's oil left for down Gulf ports the same day. Major# PoliticalT^ent,B a h r e i m■si ^ TTA l RANTINE * Gioinmary of hia inspection of ships that called at Bahrein during the week ending 9th May 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein# The G. 3. 'Barjora* arrived from Lingah on 5rd May 1914, and left on the 5th instant. Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 259 passengers were landed• The ship was granted a free pratique# The 3»S* 'Budrie' arrived from Buahire on I5rd May 1914 and left on the 6th instant late in the night. As she had run aground outside the harbour, inspection could not be made. The ship was reported to be quite healthy and 285 passengers were landed. She was granted a free pratique. The S#S« 'Oolobaria' arrived from Koweit on 7th May 1914, and 19 atlll In harbour. Inspection showed nothing parti cular on board. She was granted a free pratique. The S.S. 'W^omedla' arrived from Lingah on 8th Hay 1914, and la still in harbour. After inspection 60 passengers were landed. There \ia.a nothing particular to be noticed on board. The ship was granted a free pratique. The S.S. 'Bandra' arrived from Bushire on 8th Way 1914 -t the same afternoon. After inspection which showed nothingnothing particular on board 125 passengers were landed# The ship was granted a free pratique.l\0 .Vyjfr-7/ Of 1914. / /&lt;/■ 6/ BAHREIN POLITIOAL AGENCY. Newa for the weak endlnje- 16th May 1914. T i QQAIj OFFIOXAIjS # 158. Mana and Maktum sons of Raahld Maktum arrived fron Dobai and staying with Shaikh Isa bin All A1 Khalifah. OHSTOMS . 159. It is rumoured that Shaikh laa bin All A1 Khalifah has decided I? to farm the Bahrein Customs to Abdulla bin Hassan Qasibi and Ahmed ^ bin Salman for 6 lakhs per annum# 160 • It is reported that out of the consignment of 2000 bags of / rioe shipped in the name of Ahmed bin Salman^ 700 ba^s belonged to Shaikh Hamed. Shaikh Hamed gave orders that the 8000 bags be passed free of Customs duty and Mr. SaharaDirector of Customs a^&amp;ed why he should have brought rioe in others name, and why Customs duty should not be taken from thorn# Ahmed bin Salman reported this to Shaikh Hamed who was annoyed and is apparently trying to damage n r» MaharaJ• FOREIGN IHTBRE3T * 161. A relieved detachment of 1 officer and 24 Turkish soldiers arrived from Katar and left for Basrah the same day by S.S.^Sardar' ARRIVALS AHD DEPARTURES OF SHIPS . 163* On the 10th S.S. 'Sardar' arrived from Lingah and left for Bushire on the 11th. 163. On the 12th S.S, 'Barjora* and ^aroda 11 arrived from Bushire and Debai and left for down Gulf Ports and Bushire the same day and the latter on the 14th. 164. On the 16th S»S. H Barala n arrived from Lingah and is still in the roadstead. MOVEMENT OF H.B.M. RHTPRESKHTATIV;:' &gt; 165. The Political Agent called on Shaikh Isa bin All on the 15th 166. Captain T. H. Keyes, the new Political Agent, designate Bahrein arrived on the afternoon of 16th. Miscellaneous£37. Shaikh Abdulla bin Isa 15th. called on the Political Agent on1 nlTARAHTIHE . Summary of his Inapeotlon of shlpa that called at Bahredm during the week ending 16th May 1914. furnished 'by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein# r: The S. S# M 3ardar H arrived from Lingah on 10th ^ay 1914, and left the next afternoon• After inspection which resulted in nothing particular 64 nassengers were landed# The ship was granted a free pratique# The S» S. 'Barjora** arrived from Bushire on 12th May 1914&gt; . and left the same afternoon# Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 155 passengers were landed# The ship was granted a , free pratique.- The S. S» 'Baroda* 1 arrived from Dubai on 12th May 1914, and left on the 14th instant After inspection on board the 96 pas sengers for Bahrein were removed to the quarantine camp where they stayed till the 16th May 1914# There was nothing particular to be noticed amongst the passengers.HO. 80/^-7/ of 1914 * POLITICAL AGENCY BAHREIN. News for the week ending 23rd May 1914. nilSTOMS . 168. vide entry^in diary for week ending 16th inatant. Shaikh loa [tin Ali A1 Khalifah had actually approved of the contract with Abdul la Qasebi and Ahmed bin Salman for faming the Customs but on Major Trevor's advice he thought better of it, tore up the contract and sent for Mr. Haharaj to assure him of his confidence in him. There is general relief amocjng the merchants. ARRIVALS AND DEPARTTJHES OF SHIPS . 169• On the 16th S.S, 'Barala' arrived from Lingah and left for Bushiro the next evening. 170. On the 20th S.S* 'Sardar 1 * arrived from Bushire and loft the same day for down Gulf porta« 171. On the Slat R.I.M.S. ^, Lawrenoe f, arrived from Bushire with the Political Resident and left the same day with th© Political Resident and 'ajor A.P.Trevor. 172. On the 22nd 3.3* 'Baroda* arrived from Bushire and left the same evening for down Gulf ports. MOVEHH'MT OF REPH^SEKTAT IVS3 ♦ 173* The Political Resident arrived at daybreak of the 81st in the H.l.M.S. 'Lawrence 1 *. Shaikh Isa bin Ali A1 Khalifah visited him on board in the morning under the usual salute. The political Resident accompanied by Captain T.H.Keyes, who had taken over charge from Major A.P.Trovor, in the morning, returned the visit under the usual salute in the afternoon. The R.I.M.S. ^Lawrence' left at 10 rum. with the political Resident and Major a .P.Trevor on board. misokllaheous . 174. Reference No. 145. Shaikh Mejbel bin Abdurahman Dekhair who proceeded to Koweit returned on the 2Hnd. Ke has brought a horse for6 QUARANTINE* Summary of his inspection of steanera that called at Bahrein during the week ending 23rd May 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. The S»S. 'Barala' arrived from Lingah on 16th May 1914, and left the next evening# iHspection showed nothing particular on board and 93 passengers were landed# The ship was granted a free pratique* The S«S» ^Sardar** arrived from Bushire on 20th May 1914, and left the same afternoon* After inspection which showed noth ing particular 81 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique* The S*S« 'Baroda' arrived from Bushire on 22nd May 1914, and left the same evening* Inspection resulted in nothing parti cular and 172 passengers were landed* The ship was granted a free pratique*No* 21/^ of 1914. BAHREIN POLITICAL AGENCY♦ News for week ending 50th May 1914. ARRIVALS AND DEPARTURES OF SHIPS . 176# On the 24th S,S. 'Bankura' arrived from Debai and left for Bushire on the 26th. 177. On the 26th S.S. H Barala M arrived from Bushire and left for the down Gulf ports the same day. MISCELLANEOUS . Pea,rlS# 178. It is reported that over 50 lakhs worth of last seasons oatoh of pearls remain unsold. Captain, Political Agent, Bahreinu quarantine# Sunrmary of his inspection o# ships that called at Bahrein during the week ending the 30th May 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. The S.S# 'Bankura' arrived from Debai on 24th May 1914, and left on 26th May# 59 passengers were removed to the quaran tine camp where they stayed till the 28th instant# There was nothing particular noticed on board the ship# Except two cases of Malarial fever nothing else particular was found amongst the passengers who wore allowed pratique after inspection# The S.S# 'Barala 1 * arrived from Bushire on 26th May 1914, and left the same evening# After inspection which showed noth ing particular on board 85 passengers were landed# The ship was granted a free pratique#ffO. 22 [^V Of 1914» BAHHKIH POIilTlGALt AGENCY, Newa for the week ondinfr the 6th June 1914. OmiTOMSe 179• Reference diary No.lBO^ The 2000 baga of rice conaigned to Ahmed bin Salman were passed free of Oustoi^a duty by Bhaikh !lamed, 180 • said Bin Baud has aeked Shaikh lea not to oharge Ouetoms duty on 3000 baga of rice which have been shipped to Abdulla bin Hasaan Qaaibi« ARRIVALS AIID DEPARTURES OF oil IP 3 * 181. On the 30th S.S# w Bandra ,, arrived from Lingah and left for Bushire on the 51at« 182• On the 3rd ^Almeria* 1 of the Hamburg-Araerika Linie arrived from Lingah and left for Buahire on the 4th. 183• On the 5th 3.3• * Tmnkura** arrived from Buahire and left for down nulf porta the aame day. MOVmiEHT OF R 'PR '••^KIITATIVE. 184. The Political Agent left for Buahire on the 31at May return ing on the 5th June. Owing to Oaarah having been declared plague Infected he had to apend two daya in quarantine. The arrangementa for lat claaa paaaengera are adequate. Captain, Political Agent, Bahrein.70 * i g nARAIITINE . Summary of his inspection of ships that called at Bahrein during the week ending the 6th June 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. , The S • S# H Bandra w arrived from Lingah on 30 th May 1914, and left the next day. After inspection which showed nothing particular on board 66 passengers were allowed to land. The ship was granted a free pratique* The S. S« 'Almeria' arrived from Lingah on 3rd June 3-914, and left the next afternoon* There was nothing parti- ctilar noticed on board and three passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique. The 3. S» w ^anl^ura ,, arrived from Bu.shire on 5th June 1914, and left the same afternoon. After inspection which showed nothing suspecious on boari 120 passengers were removed to the quarantine to stay there till ?th June 1914. ,! ' ttll - 1171 H0# 7i^ of 1914 ' POLITICAL AGENCY, BATfRKIN, News for tho week endlnr the 13th June 1914, T.nnAT. aovEimwzwr . 186# Agha Mohammed Khalll # Reeidency Dragotnan who lo in Bahrein In connection with a marriage oornony has viaited nhalkh laa bin All A1 Khalifah and dined with hin?. The Shaikh baa treated him with great consideration. FORSI^H IWSKRKSTS . 187 • Two Turkioh Offioera, 2 soldiora and their Qazi arrived from Katar and left for naarah on the 9th• The Qazi is proceed ing on leave# The discipline amonr tho Turks in Katar seems to be very bad* ARRIVALS AND PEPA.HTURKS 3HIP3 . 188. On the 7th S»S# ,, HarJora ,, arrived from Dtfbai and loft for Bush ire on the 9 th. 189• On the 9th y.3# 'John 0 , 3cott n arrived from ? asrah and is Still in the roadatead^ 3.S. 'Pandra' also arrived from lushire. She missed the outer buoy in the mornin£: fog and went ashore to the Hast of Vfaharraq, but was got off within a few hours* She loft on the 10th for down Gulf ports. 190. On the 11 h 3.S. * -udri© arrived from Debal and left for Bushire on the 12th. MISOKLLAnROUS . 191. The anxiety caused by the state of the pearl market has now become acute. Reports have been received of the failure of three Parisian Banks connected with the larger pearl firms, and of the suicide of an Hungarian buyer who was Just about to start for Bahrein. Tho doings of Mon. Habib of 'essrs. ^oaenthals are eagerly canvased. m he solvency of a larrte number of brokers i depends on tho extent of his operations. The tightness of money consequent on this state of affatrs is reacting very^favourably on all busine3s / and there has been a regular epidemic of insolvency especially among the Jews. The || f71 ^TARANTINB,. Summary of hia inspection of ships that called at Bahrein during the week ending 13th June 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein# The S.S, 'Barjora' arrived from Dubai on 7th June 1914, 11 and left on the 9th instant. There was nothing particular noticed quarantine on board and 57 passengers removed in Camp till 11th June. Noth ing suspecious was noticed* The S.S. 'John O f Soott M arrived from Basrah on 9th June 1914, and is still in the harbour. All the passengers on board about 240 were removed in Quarantine Camp. After inspection in the camp they were let off on the 11th instant# There was noth ing particular to note# The S#3• 'Bandra 1 * arrived from Bushire on 9th June 1914, and left the next early morning. 39 passengers were removed in the Quarantine Camp and were let off after inspection on the 11th instant# The S.S. 'Budrie 1 * arrived from Dubai on 11th June 1914, and left the next evening# After inspection on board 13 passen gers were taken to the quarantine camp, where they will stay till the 15th instant.75 Summary of Ma Inapeotlon of steamers that called at Bahrein during the week ending 20th June 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein# I The S.S. w Baroda w arrived from Lingah on 13th June 1914, and left on the next day* After inspection which ehowed nothing particular on board 184 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique. The 3»S« ,, Fultala ,, arrived from Debai on the 17th June 1914, and left on the 19th instant at 9-50 p.m. There was nothing particular to be noticed on boards She did not carry any passen- - gera. The ship worked in quarantine till the 19th instant. . The S.S. w Bar3ora ,, arrived from Bushlire on 19th June 1914, and left the same afternoon# Inspection was made and having found nothing suspecious 79 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique. I i 1207 • no. 1914# POLITIOAIi AdEKOY, BAHREIN. Hews for the weok ending the 27th Juno 1914. &amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp; t ^ HAL oovkrnmfiht # 200* It is reported that the Sharif of Mfccoa haa written to Bin 3aud to the offoot that he wants to meet him at Marram 201# A quarrel between a Ifajdi and Abdul Habi ^a^i has been given fiotitioua in^ortanoe by the aotion of Abdullah Qasalbi and certain other Arabs who do not like the institution of a petition writer for the Agency Oourt and have been holding indignation meetings on the mabject• The Hajdi came to the Agency with a peti tion at 7 p•rru and as the Political Agent had guests, waa told to come in the morning. Later in the evening the Arab malcontents oollected all the Majdis when it was discovered that the petition had been incorrectly written by the Agency petition writer. After an excited meeting the Majdla were persuaded to .co to the shaikh and refuse to have anything to do with the Agency as Pin Baud had placed his subjects under the Shaikhs protection# Shaikh Isa who has evidently taken the Political Resident's warning to heart sent the petitioner to the Political Agent who with the assistance of Smgar was able to effect a compromise - much to the disgust of AMulla Qaaebi and the Dosaris# • g08. r, IOK IHTKHF/'T 202. 7 Turkish soldiers with their Officer Khader Kffendi arrived from ^atar and sailed for Basrah for medical treatnent. M^UVALi3 AND DEPARTURES OF 203. On the 21st H.M.3. 'Sphinx* arrived and left on the ^rd. 204. On the 22nd S.B* 'Barala' arrived from Debai and left for Buahire on the 23rd. 205. On the 23rd S.S# 'Baroda' arrived from Bushire and left for ^own Gulf ports on the same day. 206* On the 27th 3»3» 'Bankura 1 * arrived from Debai and is still in the roadstead. %17a OF U.B.U'B RFPHHSKNTATTyg! . 207 • Tiie Political Agent called on Shaikh laa on the 26th at his Sunder reaidonco in Manarm. | g|g^r.LANEQU3. . 208* Monday 22nd June being the day appointed for the celebration of His Majesty King Eoperor's birthday, the Agency, Customs and Shaikh 1 a flagstaffs were drassedy'ln honour of the occasion. M.S. ^Sphinx 11 which was in the roadstead, was also dressed for the occasion. The Political Agent received visits of congra tulation from Shaikh Isa and his sons, the local Arabs, Indian, Persian, Jewish and Christian CouimunltieB in the morning. The Chief Shaikh Jasim^attended with the Arabs for the first timo and delivered an eulogy of the E ?ritish Clovernnent^policy in tha Gulf. All the British and Foreign subjects closed their business premisses as a mark of respect fot? the occasion Captain, political Agent, Bahrein#quarantine Summary of his inspection of ships that called at Hit Bahrein during the week ending the 26th June 1914, furnished The S. S. 'Budrle' arrived from Buahlre, on 20th June 1914, and left the aarae evening. Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 17 paosemgers were landed# The ship was granted a free pratique. The S. S» ^Barala 1 * arrived from Dubai on 28nd June 1914, and left the next afternoon. 40 passengers were removed to the Quarantine station where they stayed till 25th June 1914. There was nothing suspeoious noticed amongst the paesengers. The S* S .^Baroda' arrived from Bushire on SS&amp;H IFune 1914, and left the same afternoon. After inspection which show ed nothing particular 77 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique*•! O . S 4^7&lt; t 7 of 1914. POUTIOAlt Aomox BAI !ta*. Sewa for the waotr anting the 4th July 1014 eksSf -V ''•W'; t ^haL novFa^W # 209# Owing to tho Indian maiiB bolnr aont alternate stsamw® the politioal A^ont only learnt In the ©vonlnr of July 4th that the O.S.I* had been oonfarred on Shaikh Isa bin All A1 Khallfah* Shaikh Isa had roooived a telegrar? of conrratulation fro^ Sir Parc^/ G0X&gt; by the previous mall, whioh he showed to All bin Ibrahin /.ayani who told him that it was frors one ' r 'iox In 'ODbay w and unin~ Itlllgiblo* Shaikh Isa did not mention the matter to anyone else* 210 • Shaikh Tiarad bin Mahommd Al Khalifah, coualn and brother-in- law of vhalkh Isa, who ha a already caused some trouble by his in- trirues with the all of Basrah hae arain been in trouble* ^ He orlored two of his Hasaawi servants to shoot the dciga of one 411 Al Ftsl and refused to obey Shaikh Isa when he ordered bin to send the aswawls to the Agency for enquiry and to attend hlneelf • Tueuf bin Ahmod anoo at length persuaded his to oome to the Agency# It appears, that he la now half wit ted and In very low water. T he Political Agent aocordin^ly accepted his apology and sent hii?! to Shaikh Isa to ask for forgiveneas# Sll» 3aiyid Abdullah, bin Ibrahim of Hidd has returned from liomh^f. or co'jwrm . Utt A fi^it between IpNM and Araba / the third within t m Imf*, took place on Saturday# IQmmn nr: 213. Abdul Latif Al endal the bearer of a firman from the Porte to Bin mud paeood through Bahrein on hie way from Hiadh to Basrah. tts states that Bin Saud is very pleased with the result of hie nogotiationa with the' 'urtish Government• arrxvalm 0'? .ivipa * £14* On the 5rd 'Minto* arrived and loft the next day# 215» on the 4th •Fox 5 * arrived and la still in the road stead# B,3« *llarala^ with nails arrived at 3 p«m# on the 4th beln^ ,gOARAiiSSlS- Summary of his inapeotlon of ahlps that called at Bahrein during the week andlng the 3rd July 1914, fumiahed by the Quarantine Medioal Officer, Bahrein# The 'Bankura' arrived from Lingah on 27th June 1914, and left the next day» Inspection showed nothing parti cular on board, and 158 paaaengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique. The S*S* ^Cheruskla** arrived from Mohammerah on S9th June 1914, and left on 2nd July 1914. After Inapeotlon the ship waa granted a free pratique. 3he had no paaaengera for Bahrain. One oaae of plague haa been reported In miaareh on S4th Juno 1914.No. of 1914. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHREIN. News for the week ending the 11th July 1914. &amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp; gnTffiTSN INTEREST . 318. It is aaid that the Turkish Gunboat 'Marmarla' with Salyid T alib, Wall of Basrah. Shaikh Sir Khaza'l Khan of Mohammerah and Shaikh Sir Mubarak of Koweit on board / will visit ttBsateast Katif where Bin Saud ia expected to arrive by 20th instant. 219. A Turkish soldier with mails for Qatr arrived from Basrah. tBBT 'JAJ.S A NO DEPARTURES OP SHIPS . 220. Name of ship Arrival H. M. S. 'Fox' 4-7-1914. S. S. 'Bankura' 7-7-1914. S. S. 'Bandra' 7-7-1914. lOTTOMmTS OF H.B.M'S R EPRESENTATIVE . 221. The Politioal Agent left on the 5th by H. M, S. 'Fox' for the p0arU&amp;% banks. miscellaneous &gt; 222. Lieut. W. Fitzpatriok, R.E. Assistant Engineer, Persian Gulf Section, Bushire arrived on the 7th. Pearls . 223. Messrs. L.B. Tom, Ernest Abraham, and G. Pack, pearl merchante arrived on the 7th. Some more .Hindu pearl merchants have also arrived. Departure 5-7-1914. 7-7-1914. 8-7-1914. 2^? Head Clerk, For Politioal Agent, BahreinggARAgllSS^ Suumnary of his inspection of steamers that called at g^ein during the week ending the 10th July 1914 f furnished by the Quarantine H edioal Officer, Bahrein* The 3. S* 'Barala' arrived from Hushire on 4th July 1914, and 1©^ 3am0 evening♦ Inspection showed nothing particular [ on board and 81 passengers were lended. The ship was granted a free pratique* The S» ,# ^3ankura ,, arrived from Bushire on 7th July 1914, and left the same afternoon# Inspection showed nothing parti cular on board and 58 passengers were landed# The ship was granted a free pratique. T cases of plague have been reported in Bussrah sinoe the S4th of June# The S. S# 'Bandra** arrived from Dubai on 7th July 1914, and left the next afternoon. 35 passengers remained in quarantine till the 11th instant. There was nothing suspeoious noticed. The S. S» 'Sardar' arrived from Lingah on 8th July 1914, and left the same afternoon. After inspection which showed noth ing particular 24 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique.8t» crmHF.T G0HMKRC1AL IRTELIiI GEHCR . 3. S. 'Nmantla' of the Hamburg-Amerlka Linie arrived here from Europe on the 15th instant and left the next day. She landed the following cargo at Bahrein. FROM HAMBURG . 1 Cases Earthenware. 67 Bales Piece Goods. 1450 Bags Crystal Sugar. 143 n Coffee. 70 double bags Coffee. 280 Cases Biscuits. 5 w Colours. 1 Case Gold thread• 27 Oases Glassware 7 n Hardware• 6 M Sewing Machines 8 packages Copper sheets. 14 Cases Accessories for sewing machines 2 tt perfumery. 2 H Lamp parts. 1 Case Bedstead. 1000 Oases Vermicelli 3 Cases Provisions. 1 Case Milk. 1 Case Musical wares 1 B Telescopes 6 Cases Miscellaneous. 3100 Total packages. tireln, Wth July 1914, Oaptaln, political Agent, Bahreinifs Summary of his Inspection of shlpo that called at Bahrein, the week endlnp 17th July furnished by the Quarantine Medi- uji offlo 01 *' Sahrein. The S.S. 'Barjora' arrived from Llngah on 10th July 1914, and left th8 next evenlnp,. After Inepeotlon whloh showed nothing particular on board 106 paaaengera were landed. The ship waa granted a free pratique. The S. S. 'Numantia' arrived from Lingah on 13th July 1914, and left the next afternoon. After inapootion R paaaengera were landed. There waa nothing; particular on hoard. The ahip waa granted a free pratique. The S. S. 'Bandra' arrived from Buahire on 17th July 1914, and left the aame afternoon. After inapootlon the paaaenpera ware moved to the Quarantine Camp where they will atay till 19th ^uly 1914. There waa nothing auapeoioua on board the ahip.n Summary of his inQpeotion of ships that oalled at Bahrein during the week ending the 84th July 1914, furnished the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein# The S* S. 'Sardar' arrived from Buehire on 18th July 1914&gt; and left the same evening# Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 18 passengers were removed to the Quarantine Gamp where they stayed till 80th July 1914. There was nothing suspeclous amongst the passengers# The Sm S» ,, Bar3ora f, arrived from Bushire on 21st July 1914, and left the same afternoon. 76 paBsengera remained In Quarantine till 24th July, when they were loft off after in- spoctlon# The 3. 3. 'Baroda' arrived from Duliai on 23rd July 1914, and left the same evening. 85 paeeengera were removed in the Quarantine Gawp, where they stayed till C5th July 1914, In apeotion showed nothing partioular amongst the paesengers.Sutmnary of aM inspection of ships that called at Bahrein during the week ending the week ending the JSlst July 1914» furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. Mi 1 mm : I The S* S* w Barala n arrived frora Duhai on 97th July 1914, and lef^ the next afternoon. After inspection on board 131 passengers were removed to the quarantine station where they stayed till Slat July 1914. There was nothing nartioular noticed amongst the paosengara except one oase of Malaria. |{ ill ill'] 1 ) I »: I ■ The S. S* 'Baroda' arrived froir Hu^Mire on S5lBt July 1914 ... * ' 1 and left the same afternoon. Inspection showed nothing partm- 111 1 ■ I oular. The Buasreh and Buahire Bills of health were olean, her after inapeotion 191 paaaengera were allowed to land on snore. V The ship was granted a free pratique.g jTAT?ANll^ &amp;•. Svxm&amp;ry of hia inspection of ships that oallod at Bahrein during the week ending the 14th August 1914, furnished bvthe Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein# i The 3. S. ' nandra' arrived from Dubai on 9th August 1914, and lai't the next aftoraoon. Inspection showed nothing parti- oular on bDard and 64 paaaengers wore removed to the Quarantine Oajap, where they stayed till 13th August 1914# Except a case of Septic fover there was nothing suapecious amongst the pas sengers • The S» ^Bankiara* arrived from Bushire on 14th August 1914, and left tho same afternoon# After inspection 117 passen gers were landed# Nothing particular to bo noted on board* he ship was granted a freepratique.yurahtiwe . 46 Sunmary of his inspection of steamers that called at Bahrein during the week ending the Slat Auguat 1914, furniahed by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. The 3,3. 'Sardar' arrived from Llngah on 15th Auguat 1914, and loft the next afternoon. Inapeotlon showed nothing parti cular on board, and 68 paaaengera were landed. The ahlp waa granted a free pratique. The S.S, 'Barjora' arrived from Dubai on 18th August 191^ y and loft the next afternoon# After inspection on board 57 pas sengers were removed to the quarantine camp, where they stayed t till 22-8-1914# There was nothing suspeoious amongst the pas sengers • The S«S. 'Bandra** arrived frora Bushire on 18th August 1914 and left the same day* After inspection which resulted in noth ing particular on board, 21 passengers ?/ere landed. The ship waa granted a free pratique#The Dumra, an extra boat, brought malla on the 28th. 265• Mr. Moerdyk of the Amerloan Miaaion has returned from India. 266. The greater number of pearling boats have left for the banks and there are apparently praotioally no divers left in Bahrein. Shaikh Isa has written to Hasa asking Bin Saud to urge those Hasa divers who usually serve in Bahrein boats to come to Bahrein, as many had refrained owing to news of the low advances being given for this fishing. Events in Basrah have fortunately reduced the usual influx of divers who retur^d^to their homes for Ramazan.I 1 quarantine Summary of Mb Inspection of steamers that called at Bahrein during the week ending the 28th August 1914, furnished Dy the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein, The S.S. 'Sardar' arrived from Bushlre on S5th August 1914, and left the next early morning. Inspection showed nothing parti- oular on hoard and only 2 passengers were landed. The ship wab granted a free pratique. - in The S«S» w Phlroo2i ,, arrived from Buahire on 26th Auguat 1914, II and left on the 28th instant. She had no paosengers for Bahrein. There was nothing partioular on board. The ship was granted a free pratique- The S »S» h Dumra w arrived from Bunder Abbas on 28th August 1914, and left the same evening. After inspection which showed nothing particular 4 passengers were landed. The ship was grant- ed a free pratique. i The S»S» 'Barjora* 1 arrived from Bushire on B8th August 1014 t and left the same evening. After Inspection which resulted in nothing partioular 28 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique.Mo .35/cj of 1914. POlilTIOAL AGHHCY, BAHHH1H. Haws for the weak ending the 5th Beptenher 1914. FOHKiGf? 887• H&amp;rr Marling, Agent of Messrs• Robert Wonokhaua St Go#, has returned from Bushire by sailing boat having been refuaed a pas- saga in ahips of 3 British lines ♦ He has inforaad his friends that the Wall of Basrah has caused two ships to be sunk on the Fao bar, and that a Consul General in Baghdad and Consul at Basrah have withdrawn to Abadan. This la all the news that has been received in Bahrein from Turkish \rabia but local in terest in events in those parts has died down. 0r r Hfarling also states that when the Mansaria' appeared near Foweit Sir Mubarak advised the Political A^ent not to fly his flag as long as she was in the neighbourhood. mMVMsBAm Ui^ARTUHES OP SHIPS . 268* On the 4th S.S. Pali tana arrived from down gulf ports and left for Bushire on the 5th• MI^GELLAH-'OUS ♦ 269♦ Shaikh Abdulla bin lea called on the Political Agent $ on the 2nd - 270• The Political Agent, paid a visit to Shaikh Isa on the 2nd, 271# Heferonce diary Mo.S65 Shaikh Isa returned from Sitra on the Slat August and left again for a few days shooting in the Interior# 272* The Political Agent called on Shaikh Ibrahim bin Mohamnod A1 Khalifah on the 5rd. Captain, Political Agent, Bahrein#102 quarantine:. oammary Inapaotlon of ahlpa that called at Bahrain during the waoJc ending tho 5th September 1914, furnished by the Quarantino Medical Officer, Bahrein. The S. 3. 'Palltana' arrived from Dubai on 4th Sep tember 1914, and is still in the harbour. Rxcept a caae of Septic fever there wae nothing particular to be noticed during the inspection on board, 109 pasaengera for Bahrein were reraovea in the Quarantine camp, where they will atay till 8th September 1914.lO(f No.37/^)6, of 1914. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHREIN. News for the week ending the 19th September 1914. &amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;§. parrTGW IHTSHKBT . 279&gt; The Turkish postal official vide entry Ho.S74 for period ©nding 12th oopteiaber has returned to Basrah. He merely oa?ne to enquire into the rumours as to the death of Bin Baud which have been prevalent in Basrah# RIVALS AND DEPARTURES OF SHIPS . 280. On the 13th S.S. 'Kasara** arrived from Bunder Abbas and left for Bushir© on the same day. MTSCELLANEQUS. 281. Reference diary No.276 for period ending 12th SBptember the total of specie ©XDorted should have been fifteen lakhs. r I fill lit C Captain. Political Agent, Bahrein.IbS (jUARA?lTItl!3. Svunmary of hlo Inspootlon of ablpa that oalled at Bahrein during the weok ending the 19th September 1914, furniahed ^he Quarantine Medioal Officer f Bahrein. The S.3. ,, Kasara w arrived from Bunder Abbaa on 13th September 1914, and left the next early morning. Inopection showed nothing particular on board and 21 passengers were landed. , The ship was granted a froe pratique. i .107 QUARANTINE. sunnnapy or hi, i n „p„ 0 tlon of ohlpo that oolloa at - till Bahrein during the week ending the 26th September 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrein. The S.S. 'Palltana' arrived from Bushire on the 19th Septem ber 1914, and left the next morning. Except a case of rickets, ■ 0 i i there wao nothing particular to be noticed on board. 85 nasaongera were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique. «&gt;64 quarantine. Summary of hla Inapootlon of ships that called at Bahrein during the weak * eK ending the 5rd October 1914, furnished / by the Quarantine Medloal Officer, Bahrein. The 3.3. 'Alavl' arrived from Buehlre on 28th September 1914, and left the next early morning. After thorough In- O spection all over the ohip f 17 paaaengero were landed# There was nothing suspeoious to be noted. The ship was panted a free pratique♦rOft Ko.40/1011.of 1914, BAHRSIH POIiITIOAIi AOHHCY. Hews for the weak ending ths 10th October 1914. LOGAL OFFICIALS * 292• Th® war la aarlously affecting Shaikh Igia f a Customs revanue and he is wisely reducing expenditure in all directions# 7 Ouotoms Glerfcs were dienisaed this week and returned to India. The Shaikh ia also considerably ourtaiting his hospitality to Bedouins# LOGAL GOVEEHMIIIT* 293* Shaikh Isa and Mis sons h^e''removed to 'aharraq for the Winter on the 7th. arrivals and departures of ships. 294. On th© 4th li«I«M.3. 'Lawrence' arrived frora Bushire with-f^ political Agent on board and left for Muscat the same day. On the J^th 3.g. * asara 1 * arrive- 1 , from ushire and left for down r Gulf ports the same day. On the 10th 3. &gt;♦ 'Olijrd&amp;ra' arrived fron Bunder hhas and left for Bushire the same day. movemsiits of his majksty's rbphestskt at ivb« 295# The Political Agent returned from Bushire on the 4th. MISOELLANSOUS. 296• On Me 5th Shaikh Isa, his son» and grandsons called on the Political Agent. 297. Reference diary Mo#291 for week ending 5rd October another man died of his wound in the hospital. 898. The One German in Bahrein has latterly been in a better position than the British Community as regards postal and tele graphic oommmi cat ions. Up till the arrival of the 3.S. 'Kasara' on the 9th he had received letters from Hamburg 8 days later than those received from England and telegrams from Berlin by sailing boats from Basrah 6 days later than those received by the Politi cal Agent from Oushire. Those telegrams are carefully concocted to suit the German policy in Turkey and have a bad effect on the Ignorant people here. Among other alarming reports the Aden's escapade\\c*&gt; p e was nagnifiad into Calcutta, Madras, Colombo and Aden 0n feorn ^ ar *^od and the mouth of the Indus occupied. As 0 ' - 0 voral mail bags having gone astray no Bahrein firms has he rd from their Bombay head-quarters for nearly six weeks, GOrUi ^ ora ^ e a l^rm; and some 25 Indians, despairing of a mail steamer, left for Karachi by sailing boat. oome ^ lakhs of rupees consigned to Bombay by the Kasara on the 9th w s withdrawn when the Baniahs failed to hear that the Kmden was accounted for. 299. ihe higher class Arabs remain supremely indifferent to all these ruwours* and are subscribing in the most generous way to the Prince of vfale'a Relief Fund. Over Hs. 11,000A has already been received. Considering the black financial outlook, in these Islands, whose pr03perity # depends entirely on the pearl market, this generosity is most gratifying. Kach subscription is accompanied \ by a letter expressing the good will of the subscriber, and all the Shaikhs and .azis have evinced tho^noat -^rat4fy4ng appreciaticr of the policy pursued by the British Government towards Bahrein. l Gar) tain, Political Agent, Bahrein.QUARANTINE. summary of his inspeotlon of aliips that entered Bahrein during the week ending the 17th October 1914# furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrein# The S,3. ,, Ohakdara w arrived from Bunder Abbas on 10th o October 1914, and left the same night. Inspection showed noth- ing particular on board except a uurn case among the crew, 39 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique. MMUtf i quarantine. Summary of hi 9 j.napeotion of at earners that called at Bahrein during the week ending the 23rd October 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein^ The S. 3. 'Ohakdara' arrived from r?uahire on 10th October 1914, and left the sane day# There wa3 nothing particular on hoard 2 passengers were landed* She ?/as granted a free pratique* The 3* S. 'Dusira*' arrived from Buahire on tho 23rd October 1914, and left the same day# Inspection showed nothing particular on board and pac?senders were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique.&gt;16 QOAKAHTIHB. Summary of hit, tnapoctlon of Bhlp3 that called at during th© woek ©nding the 6th November 1914^ furnished by the Quarantine nodical Officer, Bahrein# The o. S» 'Kasara' arrived fron Lingah on 5lBt October 1914, and left the same afternoon. Tn^eotlon ohowed nothing particular on board, and 5 paesengera were landed• The ehip 0 waB granted a free pratique. The 3. S* 'Dwarka* 1 arrived froi?i Huahire on the 31st October 19X4* and left the sane day. After inspection which resulted in nothing particular 30 passengers were landed# The ^hip was granted a free pratique. V The S. S. n Kasara** arrived from Bushire on 6th Hov ember 1914, and left the same day. Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 13 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a £rae pratique*//&lt;r QUARANTINE. Summary of his inapection of ahipa that called at Bahrein during the week ending the K5th November 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medioal Officer, Bahrein. The 3. 3. ,, Chakdara ,, arrived from Hunder Abhao on 7th November 1914, and loft the same afternoon. Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 42 passengers were landed• The ship was otut of Quarantine the same kxskxhk • morning.Summary of his inspection of ships that called at Bahrein during the week ending the 80th November 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrein. The S. s • ,, Dumra ,, arrived from Bushire on 20th November 1914, and left the same afternoon. Inspection showed nothing particular on board and 16 passengers were landed# The ship was granted a free pratique.Ml g nARANTIHP.. * Siimmary of hia inspection of ships that called at Bahrein during the T r eek ending the 27th November 1914^ furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. The S« S. 'Dwarka' arrived from Dubai on 21st Hovember 1914, and left the next day. Inspection showed nothing parti- o oular on hoaxed and 20 passengers were removed to the Quarantine oamr. where they stayed till 25th November 1914. There was nothing suspeoioua to be noticed. The S • S. w 3udrie ff arrived from Dubai on 26th November 1914, and left the aame day. After Inspection which reoulted A: in nothing particular except a case of Prostatis, 140 passengers were tal-ren to the Quarantine camp where they will stay till 29th Movoraber 1914. Four deaths are renortei to have oooured during the ships voyage, all due to old aw and dehlllty. The date of the last death heing 16th November 1914.\2£ INS , Summary of hla inspection of ships that called at Bahrein during the wee^* endinp* the 4th December 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. The 3. 3. 'Kerrara' arrived from Bunhire on 3rd December 1914 f at 4-30 and is still in the harbour* She had no passengers for Bahrein. There was nothing particular on board the ship except two cases of Malaria. The ship is granted a free pratique. miARAftT127 Summary of hia inspection of ships that called at Bahrein during the week ending the 11th Deoenber 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein* The Sm S. 'Ohakdara 11 arrived fron Bunder Abbas on the 5th December 1914, and left the sa^e evening. Inopection showed nothing particular on board and 23 passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free pratique. The S. S* ^Kaoara' arrived from Bushire on 5th December 1914, and left the sane afternoon. After inspection which re sulted in nothing particular 9 passengers we^e landed. The ship was granted a free pratique^.m gtTAR AMTINE . Summary of his inopection of ships that called at V. Bahrain during the week ending the 18th December 1914, furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. The 3». S. '•Bardar** arrived from Lingah on 14th December 1914, and left the next day. After inspection which resulted in nothing particular 15 passengers were landed* The ship was granted a free pratique^. The 3* 3 • w C}hakdara ,, arrived from Buohiro on 15th December 1914 and left the next day. Inspection showed nothing particular on board and B passengers were landed. The ship was granted a free Dratiquexquarantine. Summary of his Inapeotlon of ships that, o&amp;lled at Bahrain rturlnp; the woeV ending the 25th Deoemher 1914, furnished ty the Quarantine 'edlcal Off leer,Bahrain. The 3. S. 'Vita' arrived from Huahlre on 24th Deoemher 1914, at 9 .30 a .M. and left the same afternoon at 4*30 P.M. Inspection on hoard showed nothing particular and 83 passencera wsrs landed* After Medical examination on shore about 10 passengers were allowed on hoard. The ship was put In Quarantine till 29th December 1914.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000317_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/56</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000317</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/56</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File No. 4/1 Diary File 1914'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1914/1914</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-05-03T00:03:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (143 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The main foliation system starts at the title page and continues through to the sixth sheet from the back of the volume; these numbers are written in pencil and may be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Foliation errors: 1A, 1B and 1C; 77A and 77B; 110A and 110B.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains weekly news reports, weekly or fortnightly quarantine reports and occasional secret commercial intelligence reports for the period covering the week ending 3 January 1913 to the week ending 26 December 1913. The news reports and secret commercial intelligence reports were written by Major Arthur Prescott Trevor, Political Agent at Bahrain, or the Head Clerk on his behalf, while the quarantine reports were based on information furnished by the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. In addition, the file includes two letters between H G Chick and the Political Agent, dated 13 and 18 January 1914, regarding the activities of the Hamburg-Amerika Linie in the Gulf (ff. 10-11). There is also a page of handwritten notes on folio 35.The weekly news reports typically include information under headings: Local Officials; Local Government; Condition of Country; Foreign; Interests; Arrivals and Departures of Ships; Miscellaneous; Movements of HM's Representatives; Katif; British Interests; Arms Traffic; and Customs. Under these headings appear occasional sub-headings indicating location or topic, for example: Hasa, Katr (Qatar), Katif (al-Qaṭīf) and Pearling.The quarantine reports are a summary of inspections carried out by the Quarantine Medical Officer and record the name of the steamer, date and time of arrival, from where it has arrived, number of passengers landed at Bahrain, details of the quarantine inspection and whether a free pratique was granted. The quarantine report for the week ending 27 December 1913 appears on folio 6. The secret commercial intelligence reports focus on ships of the Hamburg-Amerika Linie landing and offloading cargo at Bahrain and give details of the nature and amount of the cargo and from where it has come. These cease to be included after 18 July 1914 (f. 84).Details include: rumour of Hamburg-Amerika Linie opening a steamer route between Bombay and the Gulf ports (f. 2); Turkish garrison in Qatar (f. 7); meat shortage in Manama and butchers' strike (f. 8); relations between Sayyid Ṭālib Pasha and Bahrain (f. 17); news of the death of John Gordon Lorimer (ff. 23-24, 26, 29); marriage of Shaikh Fahad bin Jāsim Āl Thānī in Bahrain (f. 26); tensions between Qāḍī Shaikh Jāsim bin Mahzā’ and the Amir of Manama (f. 39); arrival of Terence Humphrey Keyes, the new Political Agent (f. 60); visit of the Political Resident (f. 63); poor performance of the pearl market (ff. 71, 91, 93); movements of Dr Harrison of the Arabian Mission (ff. 74, 79, 89, 124, 126, 128); marking King George V's birthday (f. 77A); tension between Kurds and Arabs in Manama (f. 78); news of Britain's declaration of war against Germany and the initial progress and effects of the war (ff. 91, 95, 110A-110B, 113); issuing the date of the return of the pearling fleet (
                           al-quffāl) (f. 106); visits by Sir Percy Cox and Captain William Henry Irvine Shakespear (ff. 115, 118); and a case of bubonic plague (f. 128).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000317#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>