<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000c4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T02:43:13.020Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">From- The Residency Agent, ^hargah To - The Honlble the PoliticalRResident, Persian ^ulf. No.455 dated the 20th September 1927. t-h 'i With reference to your letter No.184, dated the 29th August 1927, regarding Musa 'bin Haidar who was kidnapped from Karachi and sold at ^ebai, I beg to state that on receipt of your letter No,33/^ated the 11th February 1927, I referred the matter to the Shaikh of Lebai ana asked him to help in arresting Ahmad bin Ghalib. The Shaikh and myself made every endeavour to trace the man in question but could not find him at Sebai. The Shaikh of Debai says that there are many persons by name Ahmad, Muhammad and Ghalib at Debai and he does not know which one of them he should arrest and it would be advisable if Haidar father of Musa or another person on his behalf comes to to identify Ahmad Ghalib or show his house so that the necessary acti'- should be taken in the matter. In my letter No,307, dated the 15th August 1. fc, I stated that if you see no objection Haidar may come to me in order to identify Ahmad Ghalib so that I may arrest him. In the month o£ August one of the inhabitants of Debai informed me that a man of Lebai by name Ahmad bin Ghalib wh is dealing in dates, etc., and importing same from Q^tif to Sebai has gone since the last four months to Q,atif and Hasa and now he is at Q,atar and will come to I^ebai shortly. I am on the look out for him and am awaiting his arrival as he may be the same man whom we want. I will report to you how the case stands in due course.4 No.2150-5/191. British Besidency &amp; Consulate General f Bushire,the 2nd October 1927. To The Superintendent of police, Headquarters, Karachi• 3 Sir, •With reference to the Borrespondenoe/ending with the Political Agent, Muecat, letter No.991, dat&gt;d the X8th September 1926, to your address, I have th^onour to ini'orm you that endeavours to trace Musa hin Haider have failed so far hut the search is heing continued. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient s jvant. Secretary to Captain, ■- le Political Resident in the Persian (xulr. * % *j t.M.N.No. 2 - 2 2. of 1927. British Residency and Consulate -General $ Bushire, the 2nd October 1927, To The Residency Agent, / Shargah. 5- A.C. I have received your letter No.455, dated the 20th September 1927, with regard to the boy Musa bin Haidar, and note that you are awaiting the arrival at Debai of a person who might be the Ahmad bin-Ghalib the master of Musa alias Balal. Your suggestion that Haidar, the father of the boy, should visit you to help in tracing the boy, cannot be carried out at present. Please therefore make energetic efforts once more to trace the boy as well as Ahmad bin Ghalib and report result to this office as soon as possible. U.E, Captain, Secretary to the Politicsu Resident n in the Persian Gulf. ^ ^ asJuJ LFrom To The Residency Agent, Shargah. The Hon'hle the Political Resident ,Persian Gulf. No.500. Dated 18th October 1927. A. C. With reference to your letter No.222, date., the end Octoher 1927, regarding Ahmad bin Ghalib who had kept with him Musa bin Haidar who had been kidnapped from Karachi, I beg to state that when I returned from Ras ul Khaimah to Shargah on the 4th October 1927 I enquired about Ahmad and found that he had not arrived at Debai as yet. un the 11th October 1927 a Baluchi informed me that Musa bin Haidar was in the house of an Arab. I sent a letter to the ueput^ Chief of Debai by two of my cousins who are helping me in the affairs of the Agency and the Baluchi in order to renaer the necessary assistance in the recovery of Musa from the Arab. My cousins and the Baluchi on their arrival at i^ebai went first to the house of that Arab and found that Musa was there and the house was that of Ahmad bin Ghalib. One of my cousins and the Baluchi sat at the door of the house and the other one named Abdur Rahman bin Kusain went to the Deputy Chief of Debai, delivered the letter to him and informed him about the case of Musa. •'■he deputy ohief sent two iidawis with my cousin to the house of Ahmad bin Ghalib, recovered the boy and handed him over to my cousin ^pdur Kahinan v.ho brought him to Shargah. I beg to forward herewith the letter of the Deputy Chief of Debai to my address intimating the recovery of i^usa bin Haidar as well as the boy's statement for your information. The boy is now at the Agency and am awaiting you- instructions Shaikh Said bin Maktum, Chief of Debai, returned to Debai on the 17th October 1927. Letter dated 17th Rabi II, 1346 (14 -10-27) from Shaikh Hashar 'bin iilaktum. Deputy Chief of Debai, to the Residency Agent, Shargah.! ki 1 A • G, I have received your letter and noted its contents. With regard to the boy who was with Ahmad bin Ghalib, I beg to inform you that I have now recovered him and am sending him to you by your cousin Abdur r.alman bin ..u-^ain. I hope you are keeping well. Statement made by Musa bin Haidar faqir Baluchi, aged about 16 years. Recorded on the 14th October i327. When I was at Karachi a certain Omar bin Ibrahim, Coachman, asked me to work as a servant for him at Ks.5/- per mensem ^ and I agreed to do so. After four days he said that he intend to proceed to Guwador in order to buy Ghi and then return to Karachi. We left for Guwador and stayed two days there. He then asked me to accompany him to Geh and Kasr Kand as the ghi was cheaper there. We rode on camels and went to Karawan where we stayed four days. Omar told me that he intendeT to go to another village so I should stay with one of the Baluchis of that town till his return. Two days after Omar-s departure the Baluchi said that he had bought me from Omar. I told him that I was a free born and no^slave tut he beat me and took me to Jask where he sold me to two Baluchis named Shah Sowar and Dadullah. These two Baluchis embarked on a boat from Jask and sent me to Jadam of Batinah W here they sold me to Muhammad bin Abdullah Dawwar in whose house there were many other Baluchi and Indian boys. I stayed with him at Wadam for two months. Ahmad bin Ghalib of Debai came to Wadam and bought me as it is said for Rs.1200/- and brought me to Debai where he engaged me as a boy in a diving boat. After quffal when Ahmad heard that Khan Bahadur the Residency Agent was searching for me he sent me at once to the Bedouins in the interior. At the beginning of diving of this year he brought me to a village on the sea shore named Umm Sakim, a dependency of Debai, whence he sent me t o diaing in a boat belonging to the people of 3ebai.On the 12th October 1927 the man of the Leputy Chief of Dehai suddenly came and recovered me from the house of Ahmad 'bin Ghalib and took me to the Government House of \ Shaikh Said 'bin i/Laktum and handed me over to the man of J^han Bahadur, the Residency Agent, who took me to the agent at Shargah. I beg H.B.M 's Government to be kind enough to send me to my father Haidar Faqir at Karachi.No. ^ W of 1927. ^ t British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the November 1927. /f To The Residency Agent, Shargah. A, C, With reference to your letter No.500 of the 18th October 1927, I am directed to ask you to send Musa 'bin Haidar to Bushire in charge of the Captain of the next steamer, 2. Before despatch of the 'boy to Bushire, please obtain his full statement regarding the house of Muhammad bin , Abdullah Dawar and present a copy of the same to the Hon'ble the Political Resident on his arrival at your place. A copy of this statement may also be sent to this office. U.E. o Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. / VI 4 ' 1 ^ ' i ^V No. of 1927 ' British aesidency and Conaulate-Geneial, liuehire, the K '' November 1927. To The Superintendent of Police, Headquarters, i Karachi. -y In continuation of this office letter No.2150-5/191 of the 2nd October 1927, I am directed to inforri you that Kusa bin Haidar has since been traced and is at present in charge of the Residency ^gent, Shargah. The boy will be sent % to Karachi in due course. A copy of his statement made before the Residency Agent is enclosed for your information. % I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, ■■PPI Captain, jtary Secretary to the Tolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf. KA.2si3 No. o ^ of 1927. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General. Bushire, the Novetober 1927. .From To Sir, The Secretary to the Hon'tole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf The Commissioner in Sind, Karachi. In reply to your letter No. S-152-30/A of the 18th instant, I am directed to infor .i you that Hyder son of .Fakir has since been traced at Shargah and will 'be despatched to Karachi in due course. 2. The Superintendent of Police Headqu&amp;rters, Karachi has already been informed of this fact in this office No.2424 of the 8th instant. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.The Residency Agent, Shargah. ■.he IIon f 'ble the Political Besident, Persian ^ • '-2. Dated 19th IToveinher 1927. ' — j I 'beg to u'• tir? tuat Captainthe Gecretary ^ instructed rae in his letter !To.24i, dated the 3th TTovem- 1 ? to send the hoy 7 'usa hin Haidar in cba'^e of ' 0 ^^itain of the mail steamer to Bushire and before ^io desn- tea to obtain his statement regarding the house f j ulicii.'i!i!-.cl bin IMi llah Da war and submit it jso you on 3. iiv i at jhargal 9 r ne st t jr 'nt of hoy 'us- is ^nclos '^ herewith. . St'ite:] mt made 'by '''usa hin Ilaidar Baluchi who v.as kidnapped irom Kai'achi aged ahout 16 years. Hecorcied on the 19th !Tovemher 1927. Z r hen J was at Karachi a certain Omar hin Ihrahim coachman came •md asked !;ie to serve him at Is.5/- per mensem and T agreed to do so. \fter 4 days he told me that he intends to proceed to Gwador in order, to purchase ghi :;nd hen return to Karachi. T 7e left r.ractii for Gwador where we stayed two days. Afterwards we went to Geh and Tasr Kand in the interior and thence to Kara wan. 7e styed 4 days •. t the latter -lace. Omar told me that as he intends to go to some other villages in the interi^or I should stay with a Baluchi at Karawan. As soon as Omar left the Baluchi told me that he had bought me from Omar. I said that I \ as a free born ana not a slave but he beat me and took me to Jask where 1 e sold me to two Baluchis n- med 3hah Sowar and Laaull ^h who embarked me on a boat and sent me from Jask to a town of Bati,nah called Wodam md from there they took me to a village in the interior called Tharmad where !:uhai.mad bin vod 11' - is living &lt; nd sold .-a to him. In hLa house there were many Baluchi/ and Indian boys ■ nd Iris /ho had boon idarr-pped by tlib Paluchis from TTekr- n ■ na soldto him. Ttii 1 e I v.as staying there the inhabit nts of Batinah used to visit fiutxammad Dawar's place and purchase 'Baluchi 'boys and jirls from hii . Gometi.Mes. T uhammad Da war ^ as taking some of the captives 'by camels to some other villages for sale 'but I do not the names of those places. I was sold 'by him at Tharmad to one \hmad ^oin C-halih en \ra'b of Deoai who 'brought me to ^ehai and thin sent me to the interior. During diving season he .as xxs sending me to the pearl fisi eries 'but on my return from- the diving of the present year wl ile I was still at '^ehai the messenger of the Deputy Thief of Dehai recover— ed Me :.nd handed me over to uhe i m oftl e Tl-^sidsncy ' genT at Shargah who took me to the \.gency. The statement was recoraed in ray presence. 3d.'v- old. : sa oi'^ bdul Jjatii .&lt;V3 A ^ / #/ y v Letter I'o.542 dated ±9th Nover ber 1927 from the Residency Agent ']hargah regarding 1 usa 'bin Haidar Baluchi. v 1 v. - • ^ • On arrival at Tnargah on the 22nd November the Residency Agent Ghargah brought the hoy ^'usa on hoard. Arrange ment has 'been made v /ith the hutler of the ship to feed the hoy at 's.S per diem. The 'boy may he handed over to the 3updt of Tolice Meadquarters T arachi on arrival at that pi oo, letter v .3 continuation of our letter &gt;T o.2424 dated the 3th November 1927 enclosing '^'usa's statement before the Resid ^ncy Agent Shargah pie- se. ijy n |&lt;ih / &lt;V3 /\ ^ Ho: S-152/30-A. Judicial Department. Office of tue Commissioner in 3ind. Government House, Karachi, | ! ove.noer _92 From, V/.F. Hudson 'Esquire, Commissioner in Sind. To, The Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf Busnire. Subject:- Slavery. Abduction of boys 1 or purposes of Si r, /2. if MOV. ^-•ation of my letter No; c^3-C, dated the 2nd March 1927, on the subject noted aoove, I hate tne honour to forward herewith a petition from one Hyder son of Fakir regarding the abduction of his son Muso. I su.-.li ve rlad to know as early as possible the result of any enquiries made about the boy. I have the honour to oe, Sir, Your most ooelient servant 4 ^or Commissioner in Sind, H .&amp;l fa -VH I*&lt;V3 A ^ Karachi 31st October 1927 3 v0Gt &lt;fe, //f r IIP The CommissionQr -in- Sind Karachi 1/ -a , Myder son of Kaitir and Mariam Y'ife o- Hyaer, oo^h mahomedanp,mkranis, residing at Karachi most raspocoially and humbiy be^ to placo the follovring few lines full 01 sour -ow and mourning and agany in our hearts, lor rodross o J our greivences of very long ardently hoping that this final request will receive its best, kind and favourable considerat: -ion . That since about 19 months we have been writing and entreating to your honour for helping us to got hold ot our son by name iyloosa who had been sold away naving kioriapped him by one Umer son of Ibrahim residing at Sadar bazar Karaclr to one arab by name Ahmed son of iiallid Shaikh at Dubai a port in Persian Gulf but 1 am execeedingly sorry no one came to my rescue and heljl to either proceed against the said Umer who sold away my boy without our consent and knowledge or to get mo possession of the boy through the help o. the British authorities at Duabi . it is most hard for the parents to pass a day of joy without the boy who is very dear to them and more precious that anything in the world .The reaching of matter to your ears should have moved as a man of family and children and should have at once come forward for the help but since 19 months nothing has been done at all Of course British justice is best known in the whole world and the thread of the justice is such that it brings any body within thb limit and dealt with according to law . I fail to see why a poor citizen living under British Crown is left uncared and accorded no help at all . I was promised for the help in letter No.,S-&amp;6 of 1926 dated 12th August 1926 but unfortunately that too was denied to me • I made several applications to your honour andy o. requested for some aid but nothing done • I went so far inrny applications to say that several persons have seen the boy with t the said arab Ahmed son of Gall id whonwouldbe ready to depose to that fact and those persons can be produced when required but then too nothing has been done • w e again as parents grew restle^ and approached your honour to kindly ,;rant us a pass port with a letter for help to any british Officer at Bubai but that too was not favoured . This shows that no poor person could be helped when need arsiee • w e are too poor to pay the freight and reach Dubai as 1 Hyder is a blind man and aleays begging for bread and the said wife of mine is always begging and thus alms suppon: me and my wife and sma^ll son with thnt • Vt /e snould be pi^i ; .an^- mercy shown towards us'and help given so that we may proceed to Dubai in search of our boy who is very dear to us and hand over the culprit in the hands of the British Officer . This should be taken bylast application which if not granted and ii nooning done I shall weep whole day and night in your name and shall - 50 on begging in your name and collect monoy and pay the froi'jit and go in search oi our boys • ^eing our just and kinu oiii or and alvrays bestowing benvolence and mercy for the poor and naedy as we are, we have every hope in your honour for help and hence approach you to kindly help us and do some needful . Wo pray that your honour will be graciously pleased to either write to the authorites at Dubai to get hold of boy and send him on hare or grant us a pass port and a letter to -tjceed there and search our boy and then inform the authority to help us to take possession of the boy • nope one 01 these t o prayers rill be granted at once and without any further delay as we can tolerate the loss of our dear son any longer . if'or this act of kindness 1 iiall ever remain grateful . left thumb impressionnof Mariem wife of Hyder . (IM a ' 9XA. We beg to remain, sir, Your most obedient servant i.e left thumb impression of Hyder son 01 FakirFrom- The Residency Agent, Shargah To - The Hon t 'ble the Political Resident, Per.aulf. With reference to your letter No. , 'the 8th Novemher 1927, regarding Fusa 'bin T Iaidar who was to 'be sent to Bushire through the Captain of the mail steamer, I heg to state that on the 9th November accompanied him to Kal'ba and ITujairah for the purpose of making peace 'between the Shaikhs of those places. After the conclusion of peace the S.N.O. left Kalha for I)a'ba and thence to Hen jam. On the 17th November the S.N.O. informed me that the Hon'tle the Political Resident is arriving at Dehai on the 21st November and so I left Henjam for Dehai 'by the mail steamer. The Hon*'ble the Political Resident arrived -Debai on the 21st November and I paid my respects to him on board. Then he left Debai for Shargah. I discussed the case of TTusa bin T !aidar with him and submitted the boy's statement to him. A copy of the statement is enclosed herewith for your information. The Hon # ble the Political Resident took the boy by ^C^lakdara ,, to Karachi. I was with the P.R. since his arrival at ^ebai till the 1st of December when I left by his permission at Khasab where I embarked on H.M.S. •♦Enterprise' and arrived at Debai on the 2nd December. Owing to a strong Shamal wind the man-of-war took me to Bandar Vbbas and then returned me to Shargah. I disembarked the man-of- war at Ras-ul-Khaimah on the 7th December 1927. T have stated this for your information. No. 551 dated 12th December 1927. a n a • u the S.N.O.' visited Shargah by H.M.S. 'Triad' and Ia ) 1927. Office of the Superintendent of Police Karachi Head Quarters. Karachi dated the DK ^ecemher 27. ^ rom, To. Sir, letter -ments The Superintendent of Police, Karachi Head Quarters. V The Under Secretary to the Political resident in Persian ^ulf. S.S.'Ghakdara'. Sohar. ihe I have tie honour to acknowledge receipt of your Mo # T.'69 dated 3rd ■ L; ecem'ber 1927 with its accomp^ni' and the 'boy named Musa hin ^yder. ^ v ^ I have the honour to 'be, Sir, j^our most obedient Servant, C. A.It. Superintendj^t of Karachi K-^ad Q.uart of Police erstelegram XT ^orn ^•^•G.Karachl. Political, Bushire 32 26th April 1927, Officer in Charge - T ask Telegraph Sub-Division reports arrival at Sadaioh of tv/o slaves with their owners ■v interior. Slaves will be probably shipped to Dubai. D.P.G.■ SiFrom To words Dated On morning of 1st instant a runaway slave woman 1 voni ^-i-'-■ Jagin ^Bashakardj came into concession and interviewed 0.0. Jask su'b-division claiming protection on grounds of having 'been ilitreated Dy Her owner. Owner arrived soon aTter with ten armed men whom he lext outside village. He was asked to o'btain written guarantee from Mustafa Khan that slave woman would not 'be ilitreated if surren -dered and in the meantime slave woman was handed over to Persian authorities for safe custody. Owner return ed with guarantee 'but Mudir refused to deliver up the slave and demanded / owner to interview him personally. This the owner declined to do and left with a threat that he would capture any Jaskis ne saw outside and failing this he and his party would attack the town during the night. Last evening a'bout 4 p.m. while our engineers son, his wife and -cheir woman relatives of u-overnment servants were on their way to old Jask ti they were captured 'by the Baluchis and carried off towards the hills there was also a herd of a'bout 80 goats which were included in the capture. On news 'being received l)y the O.'G. Persian troops he despatched 12 Nizamis to re lease Jaskis and a'bout two hours later personally follow -ed with six others. First 'batch of Nizamis returned ahout midnight without having seen the Baluchis but up to time of this report there is no news of the 0.0. Troops and his party. Remaining Nizamis have again gone out in search of him. Baluchis it is said stated that if the Nizamis came up with them they would be attacked without hesitation. Baluchis are fully armed with modem magazine rifles. Further report follows. Supdt. Telegram Dtjrf. 4 y Superintendent, Jask. ^ Director, Karachi. Copy .Resident, Bushire. 296 I/' reed 3r4 August 1927.VV /&gt;• 1 ?• From To words Dated Telegram Dt. Superintendent, Jask. Director, Karachi. Copy Heiident, Bushire, 28 {/ v 5rd August received ^rd August 1927. Oontinuation my 296/3. Mudlr has since released slave woman and Baluchis are said to have stated that h ® as soon#* 1 as she comes into their hands they will return the Jaskis and animals 'belonging 'to G-ovemment servants Supdt. From To Words. D a ted Telegram Dt. Superintendent, Jask. Director, Karachi. Copy Resident, Bushire. 132 j/' and received 3rd August, 1927. /n Continuation of ray 33/3 Last evening I sent Engine Driver to Mustafa Khan with request to render assistance release women folk and son of Engine Driver. Both Mustafa Khan and Mir Hoti left at midnight with small following to camp of Baluchis and shortly after tneir arrival Baluchis released Jaskis as well as the goats captured hy them. It is said that O.C.Persian Troops also &gt; ent to Mustafa Khan and asked nim use his in fluence release Jaskis but was told ne was taking action on my request, xxx • Baluchis stated that their grie vance was against the Mudir for refusing to release slave when requested to do so 'by the Officer in Charge Jask sub-Division. No further trouble is anticipated in connection with this case. Supdt.To Minister Tehran. Sir, I have the honour to report that on the 1st. August 19?7; a fugitive female slave fron Jagin (Bashakard) arrived in the Telegraph concession at Jask, and claimed projection from the Officer-i n-Charge on the grounds that her owne^illtreated her. 2. On the owrer8s arrival , a short while after, he v/as asked to obtain a written guarantee from Mustafa Khan,/to the effect that the woman would not be illtreated if, surrendered, and the woman herself was landed over to the Persian Mudir aBLtksxitlKx for safe custody, 3. The ov /ner duly returnee with the guarantee, but the Xudir refused to hand over the woman unless the owner came to interview him personally. Xkix The latter i&amp;fx declinea to do this, and left with a threat that ne would cap ture any Jaskis he met outside tne town. 4. On the afternoon of the 2na. Aug ust, the owner of the woman with his Baluchis proceeded to capture the ron k.a r of the I.E.T.D./Engineer with his wife and female relatives, v/ho were on their Y;a.y to Old Jask. A herd of 80 goats were also seized. 5. A pursuit v/as organised by the 0.0. Persian troops, and on the v/oman being released by the Mudir, the captured persons and animals were returned. No furtaex trouble is anticipate^. I -have etc. It. Col, P.R. in the P.G.To ITo, 2361. British Residency k Consulate General, Bushire f tlie 29 th Cctoher 1927. His Majesty^s Consul, Bunder AlJbas. Memorandum , j Heferenoe this office memorandum No,1912, dated the 1st September 1927, with regard to the delivery to their owners 'by the Officer Commanding, Jask, of 3 female slaves who had taken ' ■bast rt near the fort at Jask, your report on the subject, * C*// jgy order, Secretary to the Political Resident in^fe Persian Gulf, Captain,Telegram D.T. ' ^ From A.o.Jask. To ' Kes ident c/o ?&gt;, Bushire. No. of words 58. despatched . d received. 19th/20th llarch 1923. r wo slaves husband and v/ife have come into Jask from •^a^in complaining that their roaster has been ill-treating 'hem and they appeal for our assistance. Hatter has been referred to O.C.Persian troops as to vhat action he # intends taking on receipt of his reply it will be communicated to you. I r or information, file for the present. H.P.W 20/3/28 looted. A.A. 20/3/28. - rem- -i.*o.Jask # (copy to uri^rachi ) # To- Resident c/o ^Bushire. i. : o. of words- 36. ^ated 23rd 1'arch 1923. -y 58/19 O.C.Persian troops has not yet replied but am informed I'-orad son of I'ir Kustafa Khan came into Jask 21st and induced slaves return with their owner.r. A ^ /i /V/ ■- ..eg-: of 11? words or i5th August 1927 from the Superin- ^enlent Telegraph 3tation Jask to the Director Persian gulf sgi aphs Karachi. &gt; ^ x lays ago three Temale slaves with two children came into I J ask :.ro;a aa'breg and tooK shelter near the fort with the per- mi33Ion of the Ofricer Oouiiuanding Troops. The owners hearing of this sent in Tour armed men to the Officer 'Commanding last ^ eaing and demancLed the return of the slaves stating that it demand not complied with force would he resorted to to retriev them at the same time 25 armed men were waiting at Jikdar and another ten at Looran to advance in the event of armed resist ance 'being put up l3y the r.'izanis. officer Commanding without least opposition delivered up slaves and party left Jask wlth- •SjjH out any trouijle^ o * no.55O^ P Office of the director Persian Gulf telegraphs Karachi, the i6th August 19^7. Jopy forwarded to the Honourable the Political Resident in olie Persian Guli' Bu si lire fox^ iriformcition.* |Cv' v%. Director Persian Sulf Telegraphs, in Political Oharge of ^ekran ^oast./i* ' An /i /V&gt; ITo. 1912 British Residency &amp; Consulate General f Bushiref the 1st September 1927# To His Majesty's Consul, Bunder ^bbas* M eiaor^nriuttt The Superintendent Telegraph station Jask reports under date 15th August last that a few days ago 3 female slayes with 2 children came into Jask from Gabreg and took shelter near the fort with the pe^ission of the Officer Commanding Troops# The owners hearing of this sent in four armed men to the Officer Commanding on the evening of the 14th idem and demanded the return of the slaves threatening to use force in case of non-compliance. At the same time 25 armed men were said. _ to be waiting at Bkdar and another 10 at Looran to advance in the event of armed resistance by the military* The Officer Commanding on this delivered up the slaves without the least Opposition and the party left Jask withoutany trouble. Will you please discuss this affair with the Officer . Commanding, Bunder Abbas, under whom*' the Jask Garrison apparent views -ly is and see what/lie takes of the matter. Captain, y , secretary to the Political Resident mC Wy' Persian Gulf.No./ b'fyty/10/2. British Agency &amp; Consulate, Bandar Al^bas the 8th November 1927. To / The Secretary to the Hon'hle the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. „ &gt;/ : 1 Memorandum . ■ P ^ t Reference your memorandum dated the 1st September 1927. /V^ &gt;) 2. On receipt thereof 'by me at Karachi, I instructed the Head Clerk to call on the Officer Commanding, Bandar Ahhas, in company with this Consulate Munshi and discuss the incident demi-officially. The Munshi was also requested to try and obtain any available information in regard to this case confidentially. 5. ' xawar Hussain Ali Khan who had been spending the summer in the GINAU Hills arrived here on the 22nd September and my Head Clerk then interviewed him. The Officer Commanding stated that it was auite impossible for an incident of the nature reported by the Superintendent of Telegraphs to have occurred, without its having been reported by his subordinate at that place. He mentioned that about the middle of August some cattle and sheep belonging to the inhabitants of SKDAR had been carried off by some robbers and the Persian soldiers at Jask with the assistance of the KADKHUDA, MIH MUSTAPHA went in pursuit and recovered the animals. The Head Clerk suggested that the Officer in % Oharge of tne detachmeiiti migh.'t b© asked to make enquiries into the facts furnished 'by the Superintendent, I.S.T.D.^ A n rv A sV, -(2)- This, Yawar Hussain All Khan considered to oe unnecessary, and expressed the opinion that the facts had 'been distorted-. 4, The Officer Commanding then raised the question of British interests in regard to the ^lave Traffic to ^hich the Head Clerk replied that our inter vention in such matters was 'based on Treaties vvith Persia for the Suppression of that traffic# On xaWdr Hussain Ali disputing the accuracy of his statement the further Head Clerk added that^discussion was outside his sphere. The Head Clerk's impression was that the Officer Commanding was deliberately lying, as when in the first instance he arranged for an interview through the Consulate Munshi he enquired from the latter whether the appointment desired was in connection with the case of certain slaves at Jask. 5, i had intended seeing the Officer Commanaing personally on my return to headquarters, tut found on my arrival that he was absent at UIKAB. I only learnt of his secret and un expected return to Bandar Ahhas when he was ahout to emhark on S.3.'Bankura' on the 27th Octoher. 6- a member of this Consulate staff has since heard confidentially from the Customs Mudir at Jask that the facts of the case as reported hy the Superintendent of the Telegraph Station were q.uite correct. as rj ^ new Officer Commanding has not/yet called on me and I would suggest that the Governor of the Gulf Ports he requested to communicate with him on the subject. This is in view of the fact that orders have recently 'been issued prohibiting Officers Commanding from corresponding with foreign Consuls; further Jask being outside the jurisdiction of the Governor of Bandar Abbas it would be futile to addressj 's**\ ■ . . - - — - -—' -s : ' ]?r om To The Rcsic ency A{jent, Jlif rgt h. The Hon , 'ble the Political Resident, Persia Gulf • nd Consul Generc 1 for j^ars, etc, iSusl j _ 1 . 110.426. Dated the 19th August 1927. A.C. With reference to your letter l. r o.ll9, dated the 12th Juri' It 7, I beg to state that on the 19th lluharram 1346 (19- r /-' r/ y tl^.e BunniL community at Debai infomed me that the .'unnias oi Aou ^jliabi have traced a boy about \rhose nationality there was some suspicion and th t the Shaikh he d taken him fro: 1 them. I at once wrote to ■ The Shailch sent the boy with Khalaf bin Abdullah one of the not- ab3.es of Abu Dhabi Y »ho handec hi: to me on tlie r &lt; tj Augu: 19 /. I -was then at Debai vfhere I called the I unniae to come and see the boy. ^hev saA. him and on questioning him the boy said that he v.as a Bc.luchi born at IZasar Hand of Ile^ran, his father's na :ne tried for four days to convince the boy but he was insisting in his being a Baluchi. I thou ht that the boy was nfriad of the Arabs to say the truth so I too him to Shargah where I called the Bunnias of that place and forced the boy to go v.ith them and he did so. After two hours the Bunnias brought the boy bacv to me saying that he was abusing and using bad language to them ind that he v s a Baluchi. I beg to forward his stitenent here- \7i th for your inforn tion. I convened a neeting consisting of l yderabadis,Bunnias, Persians and Arabs in order to decide the question oi the nationality of the boy as to whether he is an Indian or a Baluchi. \ They investigated into the matter and it was found out that the boy was a Baluchi. I bej to forward herewith the decision of the meeting as well as the letter of the Bunnias of Debai to me in original, and a copy of my reply to them for your information. I beg to state that when I recovcrtdlnaian boys formerly and the Bunnias que tioneo them -bout their nationality they old thei at once and went vith then. Thib boy does noi w^nt f the Bunnias at all and always cries cnd wants to go bac : to Abu Dhabi as is st: te ^d in his st tement. 1 understend th- tthe boy is a Baluchi and not an Indian. He is -in custocy in the Residency Agency pending the receix)t of your instructions and arrival of one, of the Bunnia^s of Abu Dhabi to. recognise the boy. Statement made by I.uharnmad bin Ijaud a^ed about 14 years Orijinal olace Ilasar Hand under the rule of Hir Jan ::uhs.niriad and ITir Uawab. Dated 14th Safar 1346 (12th August 1927;. I'y father Daud is deed and I lived with my mother. Cne day four Be.luchi boys came to my mother and told her to send me with them to Charbar : nd on our return they will pay some money 8c my mother ordered me to go v/ith them. They took wheat and ghee on camels to Charbar and after si:-: days c journey we arrived there and sold the goods. hile we \vjre returning to Ilasar Kand we met on the road four armed Baluchi who suddenly fired on us and Icilled two camels. Cne of us ran away and the three others including myself were arrest by them and taken to Gharbar and thence to a town named V/etr under the rule of Jalal Khan where a Baltichi bought me on a boat and brought me and embarked me/to Seeb of Batinah and thence to Braimi where he sold me to a Baluchi named Iluhammad resident of Braimi. fter 10 days Luhar.imad handed me to a Bedouin who brought me to Abu Dhabi where Abdullah bin Khamis paid something to the Bedouin and took me from him. I v as living for the last two years vith Abdullah who was treating me like one of his eons and he was very kind to me. In the month of Safar a Baluchi came to me at nijht time and said that the Baluchis were dancing near the Shai cl^s house and asked me to accompany him there in order to see the show. When we arrived at the Bazaar of the Bunnias they caught me and asked me whether I was a Baluchi or a Bunni?.. I told them that I was a Baluchi but they did not believe and tore my clothes v .ith the object of dreesin^; me with their own clothes.As I did not agree they beat me with a cane on account of which I began to cry. By chance! r\ r - • i... jt- 7- the son of Shaikh Saqar 'bin Zaid passed that side and heard the noise. Ke came to the shops of the Bunnias and saw me there, :Ie tooic me from them : nt brought me to his father Jial 'Ji S' .qrr, Afjser £ few d-ys the Lhaii-h said that he had received a letter from the Residency Agent : bout me and he v.■ nt to send me to him. He sent me by a boat with T :rji I'halaf bin - in origin and not a Bunnia. I beg the ' i^jh Government to £;rant me a manumission certificate. I like to return to Abu Dhabi and do not want to go to Mekran where I may be arresred by the Baluchis and sold a£;j in. Translation of'decision of the meeting held in the Residency Agency vith regard to the boy Iluhammad bin Daud. The Residency Agent Shargah presented before us a boy who is said to be one of the Indian kidnapped boys. 'V/e made thorough enquiries about the boy and questioned him about his nationality. The boy said that his name was Muhammad, his mother 's n'Lme was Jatimah and his father's Jrud. Kis town is Kasar Kand of Ilekran. The Bunnie s of Abu Lhabi caught him by force and kept him in a godown ana beat him with a cane so that he may say that he was an Indian but he did not a rec .. . ccordinj to the enquiries made by usjjthis bo\ is a Baluchi and not an Indian because he has been for some time in the Residency Agency and he has no cause for fear and he clearly says that he is a Baluchi. B ted 18th Safrr 1346 (16-8-27). 3d. Abdullah bin Easan A1 l.adfj ' Abdullai. 'bin Hasan A1 Najjar Aea Ghulai Reza Aqa Hasih Lari Ghulai.. Abbas Ha j i Shai.:h Rez: Lari Saif bin Ahmad A1 Abdooli (by four persons in Gujrati). Letter 1:0.196, dated 11th August 1927, from nil ' ir Jus of I ebai, to the Residency Agent, 3ha-rgah. &gt;Statement made by Muhammad bin Davud of Kekran, Kasar Kand, aged about 15 years. Recorded on tlie S^tli October I beg to state that a year ago Mir Jan Muhammad, Governor of Kasar Kand, loaded four camels with Ghee and wheat and ' ordered me and four other Baluchis of Kasar Kand to take the consigments to Charbar for sale. We started for Charbar and on our arrival there we were suddenly attacked by foui Baluchi theives who killed those four Baluchis, my companions, took away the consignments, kidnapped me and brought me to Abu Dhabi. In Abu Dhabi they sold me to an Arab Abdullah Khamis by name for Rs.700/-. I stayed in Abdullah's house for one year. One day while I was passing from the Bunnias' shops in the bazaar of Abu Dhabi the Bunnias arrested me on the analogy that I was a Hindu boy and detainedjwith themselves for two days. The Shaikh of Abu Dhabi came to know of tms he sent his man to the Bunnias asking them to send me to him. I stayed four days in the Shaikh's house when a messenger who had a letter from K.B. Isa, R.A., Shargah, to the Shaikh arrived there. He delivered the letter to the Shaikh and the latter allowed me to go with the Residency Agent's messenger to Shargah. I stayed two months in Shargah when K.B. Isa received an order from the Residency to send me to Buuhire. I am a Baluchi born of Kasar Kand and have mother and a brother at Kasar Kand whose names are Jatimah and Shir Muhammad. I beg the High British Government kindly to repatriate me to Charbar where I shall arrange to go to my home at Kasar Kand. t ' (zu*An /i /V- // From - The Residency Agent, Shargah. To - The Hon'ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, No.506. Dated 21st October 1927, A.C. ^ r With reference to your letter No # 215, dated the 22nd September 1927, instructing me to send the boy Muhammad bin Daud to Bushire care of the Captain of the mail steamer, I beg to state that I have despatched the boy to you by the Captain of S.S. Bandra'and up to this date none of the Bunnias of ^bu Dhabi has come to recognize the boy. I am enquiring from the Arya merchants of Debai about the boy who is stated to be in one of the villages of Debai so that the necessary action should be taken with the assurance of the Shaikh of Debai for his recovery. I will report the circumstances to you in due course. j 3 .?. jiaqtyto ^ ^ zel . ft&gt; c/yanlr&amp;a iZixosCtiu GcciA. 071 ) viAs. (h a/O ^ ) ? 3o i* / / ^ v &amp; %(f^Jiushire, 36 th May 28 The Britisli Residency « Consul ate-General, lUSHIRE. a %- i - Dear Sirs, ¥e would refer you to our Debit Kote No. 954 of 10th November last in respeot of one deck ticket to ^arbar per the s# s« 'Bankura 11 V»163« We have to advise that ^e charged for 5 days food only at Rs.l/6/- per day, whereas it should have been for 7 days food at the same figure making a difference of Rs«3/-. nT e shall be glad if you will arrange to sr w th« sum of Rs.S/- at Exchange 360 equale Kre.10.80. Thanking you. Yours faithfully, Ih, fkt MESOFOUMt-1 PE'ttSM 0m ; *- ' • Agents.No.1070 of 1928. Brltleyt Residency &amp; roneulate-^eneralf Buehlre, the 7th June 1928. b To li«. a r 8 &gt; The Meaopotania Persia Corporation, LW, Buahire. Dear Siret With reference to your letter Ne.R/244 dated the 26th May 1928, I hare the pleaeure in forwarding herewith R..S/- in eettlement of the difference quoted in your ahore letter. Kindly acknowledge receipt. i Toure faithfully# registrar1° No. 5 3 ^ of 1927. British Residency and Jonsulate-^eneral, Bushire, the 1st November 1927. 1 To The Residency Agent, Shargah. A. C. please refer to this office No.166 of the 17th August 1927. I still await your report with regard to Murad son of Darak of Rudbar about whom you were asked to make a further search. U.E. Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 'c t\ ^ ^ % A ^ £ % * N ^ cj^Reference the kidnapping of I'urad of Hud'bar. i y 1 U.S. The Residency Agent 3hargah says that he has made every endeavour to trace Turad at Gharg-.h, Lehai md other placejhut he has not so far 'been successful. He wj.ll 'be on the look out and recover him if he is traced. P. U^/ vi h ^7 In ^&gt;4 /( -*5 An /i /Vi From To The Hesidenoy igent, Shargah. The Hon'lDle the Political Resident in the Persian Guir, Bushire. a n No.558. Dated 13th Decem'ber 1927. \.0. ^ith reference to your letter No.238, dated 1st Novernber 1927, regarding Murad 'bin Darak Rud'bari, I 'beg to state that I made secret enquiries a'bout Murad at De^bai and Shargah and its dependencies 'but could not trace him. I am of opinion that the petitioner has misrepresentr ed matter ahout Murad 'because if his statement was true he would have come 'by your instructions to me to show in what town of the Trucial CJoast and in the house of which one of the \ra'bs Murad was so that I may at once take action through the Shaikh for his recovery. U.B. =;&lt; fat cyak. nt&gt; /Yten^ -ex i&amp;i . % Ai$c&gt; r\S%AK^j ^ ah tki So /^l jjvlij / ^(sukasl ? % 7.^ .p* From To The Residency Agent, Shargah. - The Hon*'ble the Political Resident, Persian Gul No.504. Dated 18th October 1927. A. C. I beg to state while I was searching for Musa bin haidai at Debai, a Baluch informed me that a certain Muhammad Al - Q^ufaidi, resident of Debai , had bought a boy who had been imported from Braimi. I wrote to the Deputy Chief of Debai to recover the boy and deliver him to my cousin, Abdur Rahman bin Husain. '^he Deputy Uhief called the Najdi and asked him to hand over the boy but he did not agree and told him that he was a subject of Shaikh Abdullah bin Jalawi, Amir of Hasa, and that his affairs should be dealt with by his own Chief. The Deputy Chief was frightened when heard this from the ITajdi and told my cousin that he was unable to do anything in the matter. I wrote again to the Deputy Chief saying that the Chief of Debai has the authority to deal with the affairs of anyone who resides at D e bai especially those who are engaged in slave trade and that the Residency Agency as duty bound has to communicate with the Chief in such cases. ^he Deputy Chief then urged upon Muhammad A1 Qufaidi to hand over the boy. The ITajdi took back the boy from an old woman to whom he had sold the boy for Rs.300/- and handed him over to the said Deputy who also handed him over to my cousin and the latter sent him to me Igy©!* at Shargah. I beg to forward herewith copies of my letters to the Deputy Chief of Debai and his answer in original about sending the boy to me. I beg to state that the boy is a Persian aged about four years. He is of white complexion and does not know to speak Arabic but knows a little Persian. I asked him about his native place and name of his parents but he could not answer my questions. I have kept the boy with a woman to look after him in the hope that some Persians or Baluchis may come for him. I stated for your information.: ■ . -&amp;y 2 Letter ITo.489, dated 16th Rabi II, 1346 (13-10-27) from the Residency Agent, Sha^gah, to the Deputy Chief of Bebai. (9 i I 'beg to inform you that I am informed by a Baluchi that a boy had been imported from Braimi to Debai and that a certain lluhammad A1 Qufaidi of ITajd resident of Debai had bought him and he is still with him, ^ shall, be grateful if you will recover the boy and hand him over to my brother Abdur Rahman bin Husain, I hope that you will take immediate action for the recovery of the boy as the Najdis are cunning men and may conceal him. Letter tTo.493, dated 19th Rabi II, 1346 (16-10-27) from ^ J the Residancy Agent, Shargah, to the Deputy Chief of Debai, A. C, With regard to the boy who is with Muhammad al Q.ufaidi vide my letter lTo.489, dated the 16th Rabi II, 1346, (13-10-27) I am now informed by my cousin, Abdur Rahman, that Muhammad has not agreed to deliver the boy and has told you that he is a subject of Shaikh Abdullah bin Jalawi, My friend I communicate with you in my capacity as Residency Agent according to treaties which had been concluded for the prohibition of such nefarious actions which are contrary to humanity and it is improper that some people who live in your territory engage themselves in slave traffic !• and then say that they are foreign subjects. The Chief of Debai must take the necessary action in such matters and co operate with the Residency Agent in recovering every one who is imported your town for sale. I hope you will recover the boy and hand him over to me without fail. Letter dated 20th Rabi II, 1346 (17-10-27) from the Deputy Chief of Debai, to the Residency Agent, Shargah. 1 i/i /V/ A.C. i % I have received your letter and was acquainted with its contents. With regard to the 'boy who was with A1 ^ufaidi I recovered him and am sending him to you through your cousin# Ahdur Rahman. I hope you are enjoying the 'best of health. vextract of an artjc]e in the 'Mirpur-Khas Gazette' Jdtoa the :32nd XT ov^ber 19?7 The photograph of the small boy could not oe obtained as the ^ersjan woman aid not Ulow us to tike iiis photograph naving oeen frjrntened by some body. This small boy has now oeen nanded over to the Political Agent. 'Telegram Oode, From Hesiaent, Bushire. To Commissioner in Sind, Karachi. No. 24 Dated despatche d 7th January 1928. received. Your telegram No .l3960A, dated the 18th Deceiaber. Endeavours are heing made to photograph the 'boy and a copy will 'be sent to you when this has 'been done. Resi'w ent.*5 An I i No. I 2~ of 1928. British Residency and CJonsulate-^eneral, Bushire, the ? ^ ^ January 1928. The Besidenoy 'gent, Shargah. [I I enclose herewith a translation of a letter No.JM.129/ 6/6614, dated the 21st December 1927 addressed 'by the Superintendent of Police, Karachi, to the Gommissioner in Sind with regard to the kidnapping of tv/o 'boys. 17111 you please take energetic steps to recover the two 'boys and report result to this office. It is possible that the 'boy aged four referred to in the letter is identical with tie one at present in your charge. If so you should not find any difficulty in obtaining a copy of his photdgraph as he already seems to have been photographed by the 'Undus of Debai. U.S. 4. K o aptain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. * ^ v., ^ ^ ^ (U^ciA r t&gt;j-^ An i. No. ' 3 of 1928. \OU British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushira, the ^ January 1928. To The Residency Agent, Shargiih a.a. / Beferenoe your letter No.504 of the ISth Octooer last Tilth regard to the 1)07 aged atiout four who at present is ■being looked after 'byyou. A certain ^aji Hasan merchant of Lingah now living in Karachi lost a 'boy of that age in October 1926 and the authorities in 3ind have asked for a photograph of the child now in your charge. I hope tV s will 'be possible for you through some officers of a man-of- war next calling at your port or Dehai, or on a B .I. -boat. The Hindus at Debai might 'be able to help you as in an article sent 'by one of them to Mlrpur Khas Gazette (in Sind) he has mentioned that the Hindus wanted to take a to photograph of the child. Please send me four copies of the photograph as soon as you are able to accomplish tais. Also sea if the child answers to the name of Sheravi which is the family name of the parents of the Karachi missing child. Please treat this matter as urgent. U.l?. * % ( /- ^ Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf. _'7 No. Iof 1928. a &gt; &lt;7 British Basidenoy and CJonsulate General, ' Bushire, the / January 1928. To The Besidenoy Agent, Shargah. \.CJ. In continuation of this office letter No. 12^ dated the /itf January 1928, I am directed to inform you that the Commissioner in Sind has now telegraphed to th£s office that orti Dalumal Jashanmal who considers tie four years old hoy to he his missing son is proceeding to De^bai to identify. Should he claim the hoy to he his A son, please inform this office hy telegram. But ie doe^ not claim the child, then arrangements may he made to photograph the child as soon as possible. U.E. ^ ^ Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident ( *r|c in the Persian G-ulf. *\V v\ V 1 % &lt;V5 A n /j ^v. No. 13960-A Judicial Depar xtr From To Camp of the Commissioner in Sind, ^JtkrFebruary 1928. / , OS ^ ' 5, r. Hudson Esq.uire, C I I c Commissioner in Sind; The Political Resident in the Persian G-uir&gt; liushire. Su ^ eCt: ' 31 Eduction of toys for purposes of - Sir A % in continuation of my letter No. 13960-., dated the Hth January 1928, on the subject noted a^ove, I have the honour to forward herewith a copy of application aated tae 24th January 1928, fro. imalumal Jashanmal and to revest that the hoy in question, when traced, may kindly oe sent to Karachi. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, i For Commissioner in Sind«■. A -1 To, The rjOTomissioner in sind. -y Sir, While expressing with sense of gratitude the receipt of your Kind laemorandum No. 13960-A, dated the 14th January 1928, regarding adduction of my son Ghatu aged four years for the purposes of slavery, I respectfully 'beg to suhmit that I am unahle to proceed to Persian Gulf as ray 'brother's wife who had 'brought up my son and who alone can well identifjJ him is not in a position to undertake voyage on account ol her failing health. I have 'brought down my 'brother's wife from Tharushah to Karachi for identification purposes and I am prepared to give any amount of evidence that the 'boy 'by name Chatu is really my son and that he is the same 'boy who was kidnapped at Tharushah. As my 'brother's wife is unahle to accompany me and 1 alone shall not 'be ahle to identify the hoy and the place 'being very far off from sind 'being hahited hy Arahs, 1 respectfully request that you will he pleased to depute some reliable Hindu Police Officer from here to fetch the child or if that 'be not feasible, the Political authorities at Persian Gulf may kindly he asked to send the hoy through reliable Police guard as has 'been done in several other cases. For the above favour I shall remain highly grateful. Your most obedient servant Dhalumal Jashanmal of Tharushah now shop-keeper, rarachi Faiz Muhammad Tatehali Poad, v 24th January 1928. Serai Quarter, Garrikhata, Karachi.V m I Prom - 'J-lie ^Residency Agent, Shargala. To - The Hon'tie the Polltloal Resident, Persian 'ulf Mo.70 Bated 17th February 1938. i ■ . /t 't TLth reference to your letter No. 12, dated tie 13ta January 1928, enclosing translation of letters regarding the kidnapping of .two 'boys from Karachi, I '^eg to state that I made searches in the towns of the' T^ucial Oman for trie tv/o missing 'boys 'but could not trace them. I especially instruct ed my men to search in the village of J'umairah as stated 'by Naraindas Jethanand 'but could neither trace the nan nashid 'by name nor the 'boy. \ As regards the hoy of 4 years a^e whose photograpn is Required, he is not an Indian 'but a Persian. Narainoas has 'been mistaken 'because in the case of Fuhammad 'bin ^aud 'Baluchi he also said that he was an Indian 'but when I sent him to you vide my letter No. ^15,* dated 22nd S©p -eihn 1927 , it v/as found out that he was a 'Baluchi and not an Inaian. I am on the look out and will recover the missing hoy of Karachi as soon as I trace him. U.E.From - The Residency Agent, 3hargah. To - ^he Hon'^le the Political President in the Persian Gulf. No.66. Dated 17th February 1928. • A.. 0 • / ** With reference to your letter TTo.lij dateci the 1 t i January 1928, informing me that Faji ^Tasan a mere ant of Lingah residing at Karachi had lost a 'boy having the same age as the one who is with me and that I should take his photo and send it to you. T have through the Agent of the 3.1. CJo. at Dehai taken on four occasions the 'boy's photograph which had heen sent to Karachi for development and will 'be received 'back within 20 days. I will forward them to you as soon as they are received.From - The HGsidenoy Agentj To - The Hon '^le the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf. No. 69. Dated. i7th February 1928. A.O. j TTith reference to your letter No.W, a- tea the ifth January 1928, I peg to state that Dalumal Jushanmal has not yet arrived at Hehal to Identify the hoy who Is with me. The Indians who are here had seen the 'boy and stated that he was not an Indian hut a Persian. I will report how the case stands on arrival cf Dalumal Jushanmal for the Identification 01 boy.V JJ rr j n. Uo. W 0 f 1923. British l^eaidency &amp; Conaulate-General» mahiret the April 19ii8« i rora To The Hon'ble the Political eaident in the Perairn Gulf* The Commiaaloner in &gt;lnd # Karachi. 3ir# t&gt; rach: 4 t v ith r^/erence to correspondence ending vrlth your letter No. 1590-A dated the 10th torch 1928, on the subject of looys kidnapped from Karachi t i have the honour to inform you that prior to the despatch oi the child oi lour to i -arachl. it seeraj&amp; advisable to show his photocrf.ph to ^halunial and Haj i Hassan .vhirazl of Karachi and if any of them claim him, then arrangements could be made lor his despatch to Karachi, '^he Residency .{jent .^hargah has, under my instructions, got the boy photographed and on receipt of printed copies of the nhoto^raph, 1 will send one to you for necessary further action in the matter. 2 # The boy of 17 has not yet been traced but the Kesidency fr ent has beon as^-ed to corti; Ae • In nn I have the honour to be, TJlr, Your most obedient servant, Captain, /p 1 olitic;.l -esioent in the ersian ^ulf# 1 Cf - f% From - The Hesidency Agent, Shargaii. t To - The Hon'hie the Political Kesldent, Persian Gulf. No.234. Dated 16th May 1928. ; q t - f With reference to your letter No#64, dated the 15th April 1928, I 'beg to enclose herewith the photograph of the 'boy. As regards the 'boy aged 17 years I am on the look out for him and will take the necessary action for his recovery as soon as he is traced. I^report the matter to you in due course. U.E.IV 1*!r n f?7t No. 13960 - A Lp 5 \ x, vS®/A/V i Judicial department. Office of the Commissioner in Sind. G-overnment Eouse,Karachi, June 1928. From, G.A.Thomas,^S(iuire, C.I.J.,I.C.S., Commissioner in Sind,Karachi. To, The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gul^, Bushire. Subject:- Slavery Abduction of boys for purposes of - Sir, a V.C«- -r ^6- I have the honour to invite a reference to the correspondence ending with your letter No.673, dated 15th April 1928, on the subject noted above, and to enquire when the photograph of the abducted child, aged four, may be expected. ) 'fft, * I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. For Commissioner in Sind.Commissioner in SincL's telegram Ho. 13960-A, dated the -ori. Jim.- 1928 to the address of t Tout dated 17th adduction of slavery aaa to one to he 'boy aaa proceeding Shargarh 'boy aaa him facilities letter 1143 June regarding /CfQf 'boy * / 5 : ^ or passport issued o la lining of Dhalumal father He to Please is identify grant Gornmissioner in ^Sind , s Oi'fice Karachi, 19 28. Copy l3y post in coniiriiiation. j*, Head Olerk - Political Department h^t^scccusx i* rcsv*t~*m' ^ ,Telegram- Snclair. ?roin - Commissioner in Sind, Karachi. To - Resident, Bushire. Ho. 13960,A ^ated 23rd June 1928. Your letter 1145 dated 17th June regarding abduction of boy for slavery. Pasaport isaued to one Dhalumal claiming to be father of boy. He is proceeding Shargah to identify boy. Please grant him facilities. Commissioner ^ind.No. 132^ of 1928. British -^esidenoy &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, 24th June 1928. To The Residency Agent, Shargah. A.C. With reference to the correspondence ending with your letter No.234 dated the 16th May 1928, I am directed to inform you that the Hon^le the Commissioner in Sind has telegraphed to this Residency that a person 'by name Dalumal who claims to 'be the father of the hoy of four years age is proceeding to ^ehai to identify him. Please give him all necessary assistance and inform this Residency 'by telegram i$ the hoy is proved to 'be his son. Please treat this matter as most urgent. ~ Secretary to the Poli^iia^r^esident in the u ^ Persian Gulf • * ojl ^ syv y urr^ ^ y^ ^ '-ujsjj ^-A I /\ -1 * * i f \ i» ■ *• *f 1 Mr- 0 -~- Telegram From To No. EnClair Commissioner in Sind, Karachi Resident, Bushire 13960/A Dated 3rd received 4th July 1928. Continuation my telegram 13960 /A or 23rd June regarding adduction of 'boy for slavery. In case 'boy is handed over to Dhallumal Kindly inform me 'by wire also intimate date of departure for Karachi and name of 'boat. Commissioner in Sind. telegram - Code. -rom - Secretary, Bushire. -o - Commissioner in Sind f Karachi, lU). 7 91 -^ated the 19th July 1928. Your telegram of 4th July. 1 am still awaiting report from Residency Agent, Shargah, whether the boy proved to be son of Dhallumal. Reminder sent today. Secretary. I* r t •f \yj Commissioner in Sind^ telegram No .l3960-A, d^teg the July 1928 to the address of the Political Eesident^ Bushire. Continuation my telegram 13960 A of 23ra June regarding aMuction of l)oy for slavery aaa In case 'boy is handed over to Dhallumal kindly inform me wire also intimate date of departure for Karachi and name of 'boat • Coimnissioner Karachi, in Sind 's Office, joP July 1928. Copy 'by post in confirmation. RES/; : ; ! 0^&gt; s\\y /&lt;t f«(lEiy|o T •&gt; Offfv $. Head Clerk, Political Department. » pr a No. of 1928. British Eesidency and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 22nd July 1928. To The Residency Agent, Shargah. A.C. In continuation of my letter No.132 dated 24th June 1928, I am directed to ask you to expedite your reply 'by telegram if the 'boy is proved to 'be the son of Daluraal. The Commissioner in Sind has 'been telegraphing for i information. Please note that the hoy should not 'be handed over to Dalumal without orders from this Residency. The cause of delay in sending your reply may also 'be explained for the information of the r Ion f 'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. U.S. Ma J or Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. / fkl * %IFrom - The Hesidenoy Agent, Shargah. To - The Hon*hie the Political Hesident, Persian Gulf. No.389. Dated 23rd July 1928. A. C. Reference your letter No.132, dated 24th June 1928 with regard td^rrival at Dehai of Dalumal who alleged to he the father of the child aged four years for identification, I respectfully submit that owing to illness of my family and children T sent them to nas ul Khaimah for a change of climate on the 19th June 1928 and the said child and the woman who looks after him also went with them. On 15th July came to me Dalumal and three other Bunnias named Ganshamlal Thakerdas and Jethanand Lalchand residing in Shargah and Asanmal Pitamherdas of Deoai and Sf^id that Dalujial wanted to identify the hoy who was with me. I told them that there was no objection and as the hoy was with my family in Has ul Khaimah T would send for him, that Dalumal should stay in Shargah till the child*s arrival and that if he had no place to stay in I shall 5lve him a house. The said Bunnias replied that he will stay with them till the child's arrival from ^as ul Khaimah. I at once arranged a hoat and sent a man on my hehalf to Has ul Khaimah who brought the child to Shargah on the 22nd July 1928. I asked the Bunnias viz Ganshamlal, Jethanand and Dalumal to come to me and identify the child; the Bunnias turned up without Dalumal. I enquired from them about Dalumal who replied that the Bunnia Asanmal Pitamberdas took him to Debai but will bring him back to Shargah. They then heard that the said Asanmal and Narandas jethanand of Debai sent Dalumal back by the steamer to Karachi. I was really surprised of this action on the oart of the Bunnias for sending back the said Dalumal because Dalumal was a stranger and he had never visited the Oman Coast. Had the Bunnias not arranged? - i- l«i &gt; a &gt; Ba ^ this be (Daluipal) could not have returned to Karachi - ^ without identifying the child. The Bunnias* acoion is mischievous and their intention is to make you to cast suspicion upon me. I 'beg to forward for your information a document signed hy the members of the Majlis regaraxng the arrival of the child at 3hargah and their having seen him. I also send a copy of my letter to Asanmal Pitamher- das at Dehai together with his reply. You will come to know ahout this action from the letter of the two Bunnia^ viz Jethanand and Ganshamlal, in which they say that Dalumal came to Shargah from Dehai with Asanmal Pitauiher- das and returned with him to Dehai. He (Asanmal Pitamher- das) mentions in his letter to me that he searched for Dalumal in Dehai hut was unahle to find him and that the child should he sent to him so that he may send him to Karachi. There is no douht that Asanmal and !Tarandas have sent hack Dalumal to Karachi which action was undesirable and decision rests with you. U.13. On 15th July 1928 we the Bunnias Ganshamlal and Jethanand 'bin Lulu came along with Dalumal who came from Karachi to K.B. Isa hin Ahdul Latif, Residency Agent, in order that Dalumal should identify the child. The Khan Bahadur pointed out that the child had gone with his family to Has ul Khaimah hut he would send a messenger for him at once to 'bring him to Shargah. He asked Dalum^l . to stay in Shargah for four or five days until the said child arrived* ^e left IwB's house along with Daluflic-1 who was told hy us that the child will he brought. Daluiaal told us that he will go to Dehai and return to Shargah on 22nd July 1928. The child arrived from Ras-ul- Khaimah to Shargah hut Dalumal on his return to Dehai had proceeded to Karachi hy the mail steamer, ^e ttwtt were present in the meeting held hy the Khan Bahadur saw the child who was brought in the Majlis, with ourown eyes and the fault lies with Dalumal who did' not stay till the child's arrival to identify him. This is what has happened and the child is now suffering from fever which should 'be known. Sd. AMullah 'bin Hasan Najjar ' Tleza Mn Qasim Lari ' AMullah 'bin Hasan A1 Madfa Ghulam Husain AMullah ' Muhammad Heza Shaikh Husain Lari '* Ihrahim 'bin Isa ' Gansham Thakerdas ' Tikamdas Jethanand. Copy of letter No.381 dated 5th Gafar 1347 (23-7-28 from the Residency Agent, Shargah, to Asanmal Pitamherdas Dehai. G. On 15th July 1928 you and Dalumal came-'to me to identify the child who was with me. I informed you that the child had gone with my family to Has ul Khaimah. I sent for him at once and he was brought. Then I sent for 3eth Jethanand son of Lulu to come to me along with Dalumal hut Jethanand came and informed me that Dalumal had returned to Dehai with you. He should come now as soon as possible as the child is present. T T ^7 U • j • Letter dated 23rd, received 24th July 1928, from Asanmal Pitamherdas, Dehai, to the Residency Agent, Shargah. l.C. I received your letter of 5th Safar 1347 (23-7-28) informing me ahout the arrival from Has ul Khaimah of the child and asking me that Dalumal should come to you. I searched for him 'but could not find him in Dehai. I heard that he has returned 'by the mail steamer to Karachi ^ith regard to the child who was 'brought from Has ul Khai mah, if you wish to send him 'by this steamer, there are passengers going to Karachi and we could send him alongI irom Commissioner, JincU i^arachisub. To Kesident, Bushire. I«Oo 13 60 • Dated the 3rd ( received 4th ) august 1928. Please see Dhalumal*s petition to you dated July 16th concerning failure of Political A^ent Sharga to produce boy before Dhalumal for indenticication. Request early report as promised in your telegram Ho.322 of 3lst July 1928. Commissioner in Sind. \— (&gt; 1 Bahrein 1st August 1928 From M The Hon: Secretary Aryfj^Assocf^fon Dubai (Persian G-ulf) J To • &gt;...: s Consulate general &amp; Political Resident in x,he Persian- gulf. Bushire. Respected sir. Re;Kidnapped minor boy named Ghatoo I have been asked by Dalooraal Jashanmal,the father ol ohe above boy,who had been to Dubai to recognize and rec eive his son in accordance with the instructions contained in Your nonor's letter No:673 dated 15th April to the Conmiisioner-in-Sind, to approach your honor on his behalf as he could not himself write - English nor could get any one in Dubaiprepared and competent enough in English to prepare and place the full facts before your honor. That the said Daloomal arrived in Dubai on or about 13 July and saw the Residency Agent of Sharga and requested himt to hand over the boy to him but he was informed that the boy was away to Ras-el-khema. That the Residency Agent put obstacles and hitches and the way in which he was treated and conversed ,led him to infer that being a foreigner in a new place he would n(kt be able to get back his own son in Dubai,inspite of the instructions from your honor. Further I have been asked to approach your honor with a humble request that your honor will be pleased to order that the said boy be sent to Karachi,where the father ,would before the autl -orities,be able to prove that the boy is his son-specaally the lady who had brought up and nursed the said boy (as the mother of the boy died soon after his birth) will also be helpful and can ecjeily recogni; -ze the boy;although the external resemblance of the minor boy to his father in external appearance would satisfy even an on-looker that the boy ought tos be his son. If the said boy is sent back to Karchijkll the necessary witnesses required by the authorities,could easily be pro cured there from his native place in Upper-sind to cocroborate and^ lucjfrs) . ccs o cl 2nd contiued:- and recognize the boy and also the Medical inspection and opinion if necessary,could be easily procured in Karachi as in Dubai there is tte£~3E* no Medical-offic'er at all;hence the boy would, without any ^ un-necessary delay be handed over to his father,who has no other chiL except this boy and thus win the gratitude not only of the father of ^he boy but of the Hindoo subject of His Most Imperial Majesty in general as the poor boy will be saved from the yoke of the s-lavery and restored to his parents. Inmediate orders in the matter will highly oblige I have the honr to remain. Respected sir, Yours dutiful and loyal subject Vv\ Xv -^ N — C c i.e.Narandas.Jethanand. Secretary. .if j jl ; ■ p,3, Owing to some business concerns I have come to Bahrein hence ti.',- correspondence may kindly be addressed to me au Dahrein* 0 ^ 1 ^ Messers K x shindas .Haridas.and Coy: . \lo&gt; jrf»« (^-1... tuuh* . cuo a No. ( s'ql of 1928. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 19th August 1928• From The Hon^le the Political Heaid nt in the Persian Gulf. BUSHIRE. SO To The Commitsioner in Sind, Karachi. Sir, In reply to your telegram No.l390-A. dated the 3rd August 1928, I have the honour to forward herewith enclosed a translation of a letter No.389 dated the 23rd July 1928 from the Residency ^gent, Shargah, for your perusal. 2. It would appear that the best course was for Dalumal to come to me, if he thought that the Residency Agent, who appears to have acted promptly, and to have produced the poy for ident ification within a week of Daluma^s arrival at Shar^^ah, did not give him satisfaction, 3* Dalumal's attitude is not understood. ..hen the boy was distance, brought down to Shargah from RasralrKhaimah, a considerable^ by special arrangements, he, instead of staying and identifying him, quietly left for India. 4. Two courses are now open to me either (a) to order the Residency Agent, Shargah to send the boy to Bushire with a ian to look after him, and then get you to send Dalumal up here to identify him. or (b) to havejthe boy sent direct to you at Karachi, also in charge of a special man. 5. I can arrange to have either (a; or (b) carried out, as •V you desire, but would be glad ol an assuraace from you that t Daluoal has first deposited sufficient money with you to cover the expense that will have to be incurred in conveyinj the boy • V and a man to look after hims- (. curja. ^ (a) From Debai to Bushlre and back to Debal (with food) lb; From Debai to Karachi and back to Debai (with food) \ \ q ] Also maintenance expenses for say 15 days at Karachi for two persons^ Say Rs,300/- in all, ^ should be obliged if you will let me have as early reply as possible to this communication# In the meantime^ I ftrg instructing the Residency Agents ohargah, to keep the boy in his household till further orders, \ I have the honour to be, Sir, Your i ost obedient servant, [f Lt. Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. de. • fiVi .a . cud Ho. '/V of 1928. British 'Rpsidercy &lt;5: Oonsulate-G-eneral, Bushire, the 20th August 1928. To The Residency Agent, Shargah. A. C. i hc^ve received your letter No«S89, dated 23rd July 1928, on the subject of the 'boy claimed 'by Daluinal to he his Son, and have forwarded a copy to the ComiDissioner in Sind. In the raeantime you should keep the 'bpy in your own house pending further orders from me. On no account are * you to let the 'boy leave your house or go to any other family. Final orders will he sent you shortly on the subj ect. U.S. I - , Eajor, Political 'Resident in the Persian Gulf* % &lt; /(?&gt; bo&gt;dv.j&gt; —.'UTelegram Sn Clair. From Commissioner in Sind, Karachi. \ To 'Resident, Sushire. No. 13960.A. Dated the 5th (received 6th) September 1928. Your letter No.1561 August 19th regarding Ihalumal's son please send 'boy to Karachi 'by first 'boat in charge of special man and intimate 'by wire • Sufficient money has 'been deposited with me 'by lhalumal to pay deck passage with food and feeding in Karachi. Commissioner in Sind. J-elegra, D.T. From • Secretary Bushire. i To - Residency Agent, Sharcag Care C.C.Henjam. No.915. Dated the 10th September 1928. J y Reference my letter No. 171 dated 20t2i August. Please send the boy in charge of one of your own men and wire name of ship to Sommissioner, Karachi, by first ship^here repeating to Commissioner, Karachi. Identification will take place at Karachi. Send your bill of charge here. Secretary.% 7l r Telegram D.T. From 0*0., HenJ am. To Secretary, Bushire. Dated 11th September 1928. Reference your 'O.T. words 59 of date to Residency Agent Shargah. * Message will 'be posted via Muscat as up mail not touching Henjam. Oan I hand message to H.M.3. Triad now at T Ienjam. ^eply urgent please. ri n j • • Telegram D.T. From Secretary, Bushire. To Henjam Dated 11th September 1928. Your message of date. Please hand message for Residency Agent Shargah to H.M.S. Triad with my compliments and ask if the message can kindly 'be delivered 'by next warships visiting Dahai in ordinary course duty. Secretary. Jv • B . For information, type out and file. H.^.P.D. 12-9-28 A/C O, y't -fu*/-N i _ i'luk* . cju d ct j**' 1 7 . ♦ No. ' 8^ ot 1928. British Residency &amp; CJonsulate-General, Bushire, the 13th Septemher 1928. To The Kesidency Agent, Shargah A ^ In continuation of my telegram No.915 dated the IDth Septeinber the suhjeot of the 'boy who is claimed 'by Dalumal, T am to inform you that as mentioned in my said telegram, you should despatch the 'boy to the Commissioner .in Sind, Karachi, under the care of one of your relatives or men 'by the first down mail. 2. This person should produce the 'boy 'before the Commission er in Sind at Karachi, who will carry out the necessary :. identification in his office and before a responsible officer and issue orders. If Dalurnal fails to prove the 'boy to 'be his son, your man should with the Commissioner's permission 'bring him 'back to Dahai. i 3. ' T Vhen you send the 'boy you should send a telegram to the Residency repeating the same to the Commissioner in Sind. Tou should also send a letter to the Commissioner in Sind with your man, stating that you are ordered 'by me to send the hoy to him for identification and in case of Dalumal failing to prove,his claim, the 'boy will he returned to Dahai for further orders of this 'Residency. 4. The Commissioner in Sind has taken a considerable sum of money in deposit from Dalumal and your man should present your hill of expenses respecting the hoy and the journeys to Karachi and return to Dahai, to the said Commissioner, posting a copy to this Residency. U.S. (r Major Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 61 a w i —xrom - The Residency -gent, Shargah. ^ Hon'ble the rolitlcal Resident, Persiun Gulf. ITo. 442. Dtaed the 29th August 1928. — C. 'ith reference to your letter ilo i .7i dated the ^Qth August I am oDedient to your orders, i wili keep the cnild on the subject of the child^Ln house at ^har^uh and will not allow hi:.jio go to any other houses pending further orders from you. I beg to enclose herewith for your information a letter which has been received by me from a certain individual named Abdullah bin -vhmad a Persian subject in connection with the said child. 3 states therein that the child's father is in existence in I-inab and his name is Hasan bin Abbas of i.ehzabad and that a trader named Luhammad bin Rashid of Dabai know/^s the said child and his lather . I sent Sor -luham ad bin Rashld who came from Dabai and j- enquired from him. I forward his statement herewith for your information. r T e states in his statement that he has seen the said child on his father's shoulder in ^ab;;i market two years ago, begging from the owners of the shops, for his maintenance. He asked him about the child who alleged that his mother had died and he was a poor man and had nothing to maintain himself. He also saw him again in the market after three days and enquired about the child . He (child 1 s father) told him that he had kept him with a Persian woman of I&amp;bai to look after him. iuterwards t-.o other Persians resident of ohargah named Asad bin Hasrullah and Hasan bin X'undagar informed me that the father of this child was Hasan bin Abbas of 1'inab and that they had written to him and he will arrive shortly at Shargah. I beg to state that the completion of the child is as that of a Persian and not of an Indian sect. Letter dated the 10th Rabi ui Awal j.547 (i^Gth ^ugust 1928) from Abdullah bin Haj i -»xhi,iad -aj i Ali, to the Residency ^vgent, Shargah.xt . /XV.O tz d 1 7 I respectfully beg to state that I understi-rici tin t you have a child named Jafar in your house and the hindus are c-ieiiiain^ him I 'beg to state for your information that the uhild* s father is in existence and his name is Hasan bin *^bbas of Llehiabad^ Persia, and it is very likely that he may be at Hinab these days and will of course come to you» In addition there is a man here nameci Rashid who will bear evidence to the effect that he s seen the cnild with the said Hasan at the time when his mother was dead • You may enquire from Ra^hid who will acquaint you with all tne facts* Statement made by I-uhamrm d Kashid Hurrnudi, a traded o Da Dai, Recorded on the I2tii -'.abi 1, 1'34' (^- ] • When I was sitting in my shop in ^uidirah,bazar, , an old man named Hasan who had a child on his shoulders pusscd oy m^ shop* 1 askeC. the old mtm from where he got this child and he told^tia.t he v/as his son and his mother had died. I asked him what was his name (Child's name) , he said Jafar. Then he asked me for some money and I paid him Rs.0-3-0. He was begging from the shops and the child was on his shoulder^%rafter taree days 1 met tne same ola : :i ^ in the bazaar and asked him where was the boy. He told me that he had kept him with a Persian woman to look a^ter him. I said perhaps you have sold him to the Arabs. He said God forbid, he has not done so , but he has kept him with some people to look after him -or the sake of God. After that I neither saw the old man nor the child until RaM ul Awal (August) when I arrived at 3hargah I saw the child playing on the sea shore and identified him. J enquired from the Persiar shopkeepers about him who told me that he is in the Residency &lt;vgency. I told them I saw this child on hi^ father*^ ^ shoulders in Dabai^market about two years ago. And I swear^tne Almighty that he is the son of the old man Hasan bin Abbas without not doubt and^that of the Bunnia. The above statement was made in my presence. 3d. K.3. Isa bin Abdul Latif.No. (735of 1928. British Kesidenoy &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 16th September 1928. From The Hon*tie the Political iiesident in the Persian uuir f To The Commissioner in Sind, KARACHI . Sir, With reference to your tmtm telegram No.13960 dated the 5th September 1928, on the subject of the toy claimed 'by Balumal as his son, I have the honour tc 1 orward herewith,for your information a copy of a letter No.189, dated the 13th September 1928, which I addressed to the .residency Agent, Shargah instruct- ing him to send the boy to you for identification. 2. i also forward to you a copy of a letter No.442 dated the 29th August received from the .Kesidency Agent Jargah, subsequent to the despatch to him of my letter of the 13th September, as it may help you in the act of identification. I have the honour to be. Sir, Xoxir most obedient servant. ]olitical resident in the Persian Oulf. vjz p*/ «y rj A m . rxj n €t f 7 ?roin - The Residency ^gent, Shargah. (' Vj To - The Hon''ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf* No.465. -Uated 14th Septeraher 19 38. A. 0. I 'beg to state that I received your telegram Mo. 915 regarding the child that he should he sent with some one on my 'behalf to the Commissioner, Karachi, for the enquiries which had to 'be made there. I will do as directed 'but T submitted a letter No.442 dated 29th August 1928 enclosing a letter from a certain Persian 'Persian subject) and a statement form another Persian to the effect that the father of the child exists in Mmah and his name is Hasan 'bin Ahhas and that he has 'been asked to come to Shargah. I thought that my letter quoted ahove has not reached you ahout the claim of the Persians for the said 'boy. I postponed sending the 'boy to Karachi pending further orders from you. I was under the impression that I may perhaps 'be 'blamed 'by Your Honour later that as to why I did not report to you in this connection. I shall comply with your orders. U.S.t -0 i'J/JH* XI. rJU 1 CL Kj&amp;t' ' 7 Capt. Frank Cutler RN 1815 FOUNDER OP THE FIRM Of Catfcrrafmer 2?~'» WN, M„.CH»NT1 * * * VOL. CCXXaVIII. ALLAHABAD:! MONDAY, No. 21935. KIDNAPPED AND SOLD 0 - IN SLAVERY 4. Sind Mystery Solved MISSING BOY FOUND AFTER TWO YEARS &lt;■&lt;: \ Discovered in Persian Gulf A great stir has been created in Sind by the startling discovery that a Hindu boy who had been missing for two years was sold in slavery in the Persian Gulf. The boy has been restored to his father after a careful inquiry, but the public of Sind are not satisfied. A close investigation into the matter has been urged and it is even suggested that an organised gang is responsible for the crime. DEMAND FOR SEARCHING INQUIRY from our own correspondent. A K arachi, O ctober 18. BOY who was kidnapped from Nawabshah District and taken to the Persian Gulf was fomul working jl slave hv somr* i VJVg J// //-' ./J.KJ i 1 expressed his inability to send the boy to Sind. The father of the boy (Bhai Dhalumal) was then advised by t&gt;be Commissioner in Sind to I I i i 4 ^339 IHOn I UMaMMSl •pojtfv siCvmjn s* fw/J puojq 3m y ;/ 'mi £uu ssv(JCapt. Frank Cutler RN 1813 founder of the firm or CciffcrPofme/* 'OM(f D __ „ 1K . 0 »A VOL. CCXXAVTII. No. 21935. ALLAHABAD: MONDAY, OCTOBE kidnapped and sold IN SLAVERY Sind Mystery Solved MISSING BOY FOUND AFTER TWO YEARS Discovered in Persian Gulf A great stir has heen created in Sind by the startling isiovery at a Hindu boy who had been missing lor two years was sold m slavery in the Persian Gulf. The boy has been restored to his father after a careful inquiry, but the public of Sind are not satisfied. ^ A close investigation into the matter has been urged and it is even suggested that an organised gang is responsible for the crime. DEMAND FOR SEARCHING INQUIRY from our own correspondent. r Karachi, October 18. A-BO\ who was kidnapped from Nawabshah 'District and taken to the Persian Gulf was fouml working ^3 a slave by some Nagar Tatta II.a 1 . merchants. About two and 'half years ago, the boy was suddenly found mis sing from his home Tharushah village (Nawabshah district, Sind), and I3hai Dhalumal t'he fathoi- of the boy attempted in vain to discover his whereabouts. The police were informed and they instituted a thorougb search but were unsuccessful. Sometime after this incident certain Nagar Tatta Hindu mer chants trading in the JPersi.m Gulf found a boy, who looked remarkably Ijke a Sindhi, work ing as a slave there. Their suspi cions arousea as they had on a i &gt;re »Mous occasion discovered pin» her boy, undersmmarcircuar^ stances, who as it turned out was indnaipped from Karachi. Their suspicions aroused, they communicated with friends at Karachi and a description of the boy was published in Whe papers 1 he father of the boy seeing th3 advertisement communicated the circumstances under which hin boy had been kidnapped. CONSUL CONSULTED The matter was eventually brought to the notice of one of the British Consuls in the Persian Gulf. On inquiring into the rnafter, however, he discover I that an Arab residing in the Persian Gulf claimed to be lather oj the missing boy and, tfherefore» expressed his inability to send the boy to Sind. The father of the boy (Bhai Dhalumal) was then advised by ttac Commissioner in Sind to iprocoed to tl &gt;e Persian Gulf and identify fhe boy therei Bhai Dhalumal went to the Persian Gulf and got into touch with the British Consul, but returned d's- appointed and 'he complained thaf the Consul had not helped him. BOY BROUGHT OVER The Commissioner in Sind, however, assured him that if he undertook to ' pay the | passage arrangements could be made to have the boy brought down to Sind. Accordingly, the boy was brought over to Karachi under Goverment protection by the steamer which arrived on Monday evening. At this stage, however, a fur ther complication arose. An Arnh #0 Karoehi, Mr: Ishrafi, put in a counter claim stating that he was Ulie father of the boy. An identifica tion test was held and the rival claimants were examined before the boy was shown to them. The Arab on seeing the boy waiv- e.i his claim, bat B'hai Dhanumal was given charge of the boy on proving that the boy was his ron. The two incidents have roused the Hindu community in Sind and a movement is on foot to bring (pressure to bear on the aut/lioritics to institute a searching investiga tion into the matter. It is even suggested that kidnapping on a large scale is carried on in the Sind villages by an organised jransr. 'the pioneer Monday, October 22, b comment : Mysterious Movements in the Oil Industry— The Treatment ot Leprosy—The Australian Strikes much larger, perhaps nearer 500,000. There are numerous cases in which. the victims either do not realise their affliction or else consider it in their own interest not to disclose the fact. This is a dis tressing feature of the problem; the social stigma that attaches to the disease makes sufferers keep their secret to themselves. The dis- ■^T-cvvy n, cure is, there- [t/i leg') workers have been called in, which is an extreme step for an advanced Labour country like Australia. Perhaps no other na tion has siich a strongly organised Labour party; all the States have Labour Governments, and social istic legislation is widely practis ed, even down to State fried fish shops. If this strike is an exam ple of the way in which the eman cipation of Labour works, the rest of the world may be excused for doubting its efficacy as a solu tion of the industrial problems of to-day. Dalitodhar Sabha. The All-India Shradhanand Dalitodhar Sabha ii a Hindu Mission which has been doin^ excellent uplifi work among the depressed classes. Its annual report gives a just idea of its activities and their beneficial re sults. The S^bha has its head quarters at Delhi, and centres are established at R'ohtak, Khurja, Hathras, Bhivani and Ghaziabad Its objects may be summarised as follows: to ra:se the moral tone of the depressed classes and edu cate them: to eradicate caste hatred; am., to counteract mis sionary and proselytising work on behalf of other religions. A perusal of the report leaves one in no manner of doubt as to th6 utilitarian and moral effect of some of its endeavours. The Sabha has a number of active workers who have gone among the Chamars and Mehtars of these districts and have given them self-respect and an ambition to take their rightful place in- the scale of ? humanity. Particularly in rural areas the Sabha has been a strong champion of the rights of the oppressed. 1 articulars are given of a number of cases in which the intervention of the Sabha has led to official action and the cessation of the malpractices. Its educational, medical relief and protectionary work has also been admirable. It has opened a number of Pathshalas in rural districts for the primary education of the depressed classes. On the question of reclaiming and opposing conversions to other reli- gions 7 such action has, of course, been attended by a certain amount of friction. The Sabha is strongly Hindu, and as such it has unfor tunately come into conflict with workers in the cause of other re ligions. The social work of the Sabha is hindered Uy lack of funds, and an appeal is made for public support. This would probably be more generously provided if so much opposition was not roused on rchgiotrs grounds. Could not work for the depressed classes be mellowed with toleration? The Royal Tournament. Sir Herbert Greedy, the Secre tary of the Army Gouncil, is busy this month distributing the protit made at the 1928 lloyal Tourna ment, writes our Military Corres pondent in London. The cheque which has been handed over to him is for £27,000. The total sum taken in the fortnight's run was £57,000. fTince the Tournament has been staged at Olympia a sum of £172,000 has been handeu over to the Service charities and in all about a quarter of a million has been distributed. Up to 1926 the annual profit ranged from £3,000 to £14,000 and in 1927 there came an extraordinary leap. The profit that year was £25,000 and this year it is £2,000 better. The skill of the troops in he arena is excep tionally good and next year tlJ units to contribute the programme _ are M. Battery, R. H. A., The Lilt Guards, the bugle bands of tha rifle and light infantry battalions, units of the Koyal Marines, Royal Navy and lloyal Air Force and a regiment of the 1st Cavalry Brigade. If the attendance is as great in 1929 as in the last two years, the movement to a larger hall, which would have to be built ) will become a certainty. K w ulas iry 3S. nd sli- je, nt )r- th •e- lie Is, lie lv if 2d ot oe ^ -o -la !&lt;? 5011 , ^ pat* k ON&gt; rrom Judicial Department# Office of the Commissioner in Sincu Government House,Karachi i i ■jfih Octoher 1928. W. F. Hudson SscLUire, 0. I.E. , I. 0. S. , Commissioner in Sind, Karachi. The Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Bu shire. SulDj^ct:- Ahgucticn of a hoy for slavery,. Sir, u c 3 E E o 0 '3 0 e o u s v E u v '3 c 3 With reference to the correspondence ending with your telegram No: 1004, dated the IStrjC the subject noted ahove, I have t^o honour to i-pjorm you that the hoy has, to my satisfaction, 'been identifier as Bhallumal*s son and has therefore been handed ov^r to Dhallumal. 2, The Agent at Sharga sent the hoy down with ^.±^.5 cou ^j-j. a M u I Bahtran son of Hussain and a servant, tiie burner travelling second class. Abdul Ilahman has clai;Ti o ^ a s 1 .t of Rs 521 as expenses, details of which are shown in t^p accompanying statement, and also a^s for an ar 5 i tic - a ■ sum of Es 190/- to rn^et the cost of th^ir stay in Ka ' a ci -i ^vnd return journey to Dubai. 1 wo 1c in ohis. ccnn - ction Invi te a r Q ference to your 1.0tt o r I c. 1661, c c.e' L&gt;ii. 0 l-tn August 19 28 wherein it was asked that sufficient money should be deposited to pay expenses incurred in conveying the boy and a mar to look after him to Karachi, feeding charges for 16 days and the cost of the return journey. In my telegram No: 13960-A, dated the 5th September 19 28 it was intimated that sufficient money had been deposited to pay deck passages with food and feeding charges at Kar-chiKarachi. it was estimated that this would not exceed P.s 16 r /- an? this amount was d^positPd 'by Dhallumal. A passage with food for the Journey frou Duhai to , |P Karachi costs Bs 25 only and it was estimated tnat the actual expenses of the journey including incidental charges, should not exceed Rs 9 5/-. However the entire amount of the deposit viz., Es 160 has 'been paid to AMul Rahman, and I think you will agree with me that this is tl » | quite sufficient. The demand made is in my opinion un justifiably extravagant. 3. I would take this opportunity of thanking you for all the assistance rendered 'by you in this connection, I have the honour to he. Sir, Your most obedient s^rvanit, Commissioner in Sind. i' alosram lio. 13960-A, dat-Td the 10th October l^S, from the Commissioner in ''ind to the address of the II-on'Tsle' the lolitical Resident in the Frosian Gulf, Bushire. 1^. 13960-A your telegram 047 Septerober 26th aaa ^ oy did not come &gt;&gt;y this boat because it did not stop at Dubai aaa Residency A^ent har^ah should kindly he asked to wire to me ^riten 'boy has actually embarked and on what steamer /rf sceived o, 30^1 Commissioner Slnd Bommlssloner's Office. KarachiOctober 19?8. ^ost copy In confirmation. Head Clerk Political Department.f &gt; u* zi : rrj i »/ r 7 Translation. TO Shaikh Said bin Uaktiun, % Chief of Dubai. A^C. It may not be hidden to you about Muhammad bin Abduv Sahman al Kufaidi who deals in slares—Baluchic and others, that he is at prsent imprisoned. I request that he may remain in prison till an official comei to take him away and Khan Bahadur Issa will inform you about him. The object is send him orer to the Imam Abdul Aziz bin Saud for his punishment. This we hare written for your information. U.E. ^ated the 23rd October 1928. ltd/ L.H(aworth) Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. as 9 hi \ ftnu* ju _ rrj o fz. j^f&gt;r r 7^0 No. ot 1928. British Besidency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 4th Decemher 1988. n! To The 'Residency Agent, Shargah. n • j • In reply to your telegrajn No•579 dated 1st DecemlDer on tae subjeot or the illness or Muhammad Quraidi who is lodged in the Shaikh of Dahai's prison. I am directed 'by the 'lon'hle the Political Resident in tae Persian Gulf to inform you that the man may 'be released, and ordered to return to his own country of Najd. ile snould he warned in writing 'by you and 'by the .Huler of .Oahai that if he ever returns again to the Trucial ^oast, he will again 'be arrested and more severe measures will have to 'be taken against him. U.S. Major, Secretary to the Political 'Resident in the Persian Gulf, 0gr a^UUlT \ * / r~ b'v 'ojjl )\ ^ d ry — o c*-&gt; «m . nu 1 cl d&amp;f&gt;r r V From; Hesideticy Ageni^Shar^a^. Tc: The Hon'a'ble H.B.M's Political Hesident ^nd Ooi General in the Persian Gulf. No.546,dated 13th.November 1928-29th.Jamad Awal 1347. A/o. I 'beg to state that with reference to your letter No.i89 dated 13th.September 1928 to send the 'boy who is named Dalumal who is the son of the CJomissioner,Karachi,I sent the 'boy in question accompanied 'by my cousin with a special man,the hoy's caretaker,'by the steamer H Baroda rt to Karachi and informed your honour 'by wire on the 8th.October 1928,with regard to their de parture from Dubai. He reached with the boy and handed him to the Oommissioner in question,^nd as my cousin informs me - that the Identity investigations has not been made except that the boy has been handed to j.n old woman and gave my cousin the permission to return from Karachi to Dubai. Hence my cousin has forwarded details of expenses incurred on the boy such as expenses of pay for the duration of his appointment and expens es of the man who guaranteed to bring up the boy and expenses of tae voyage from Dubai to Karachi and the return to Dubai, and have not been paid except Rs.l50/-and he said to him that he would inform me as to what was paid to him,and demand the balance from Bushire Office. Inclosed for your perusal de tails of the expenses incurred on the boy in question and copy of my letter to the CJommissioner Karachi. '71 th the greatest respect I beg to inform your honour that when I received the boy from Dubai he was a mere infant and I engaged for aim a man who had a wife for his coring as washing, ^nd cleaning and paid for the boy's p^y montaly in the hands of the caretaker as the child without a caretaker will be in the worst state of uncleanliness and possibly perish. I request of your hon- our to favour me with the amount of expenses as I am unable to undergo this amount of expenses and from your kind favour to view the matter with a favourable eye. The total expenses amounts to after handing over to the Commissioner at Karachi shows a balance of Rs.610.10.0. U.S.- , iuahs\ a , rzy otatement of Account or expenses incurred on the 'boy who was. - sent to the Commissioner Karachi through Abdul Rahim 'bin Husain on 8th.0cto'ber 1928. 1st. The days the 'boy in question stayed at his Vakil's . house from 18th.October 1927 to 8th.October - 1928,total 348 days ® 8 as.per diem, Pay of caretaker of the 'boy from 18th.October 1927, to 8th#0ctober 1928,® Es.l5/-prr mensem, Second CJl^ss passage for my cousin Abdul Rahim bin -lusain who was sent v/ith the boy to the CJommi ssioner,Karachi , Passage^ ^ Tor the boyjof the man caretaker*,Deck with food from Dubai to Karachi Boat crossing fare from Shargah to steamer opposite Dubai, Received from the CJomraissioner,Karachi , through my cousin Abdul Rahim bin Husain, Balance Rupees Three hundred and sixtyfour,annas eight only. (Signed) K.B.Essa bin Abdul Latif, Residency Agent. Rs.174.0.0, 175.8.0. &gt; &gt; 120.0.0. 25.0.0, ±jl 20.0.0. Rs.514.8,0. 150.0.0. Rs.364.8.0. - A &lt;- Statement of Account of Abdul Rahim bin Husain from date of voyage from Dubai and stay at Karachi and his return to Dubai on 3rd.Nov ember 1928. 15th.October 1928. Arrived at Karachi,expenses of messing from 15/10/28 to 28/10/28,14 days ® Rs.5/-per diem Es.70.0.0. \Iotor Car hire to Commissioner,tv/ice, , 5.0.0. 1 Second Class passage from Karachi to Dubai with food, ,120.0.0. 1 Deck passage from Karachi to Dubai, , 25.0.0. Boat crossing fare from steamer to Shargah, , 20.0.0 . Rs. 240.0.0. Trr ire expenses to your honour from steamer 'Baroda' as o - ^ 4' /'&gt; Vn-rnobi - 6.2.0. regards boys voyage to Karachi, -LJL Rs. 246.2.0. / Total Bupees Two Hundred and fortysix and annas .two ■&lt; bi Bfied:K.3.S3SA BIN ABDUL LATH. R^SIDSNCY AGENT- / «*PA/s / • Copy of Residency Agent's Letter No.478 dated 24th. September I l3eg to stdte that in aocordance to the ooininancL of the Hon*a'ble Colonel Sir Lionel Haworth,H.B.M f s Political 'Resident ?=nd CJonsul-General in the Persian Gulf,per his letter No. 189 of 13th.Septemher 1928 that I should send the hoy to you,who is - clojumjixi aalled ^Dilumal' acoomp mied 'by one from our side for the pur- tdl pose of investigation of identity 'by your goodself,and ,, Daluinal M gives up his identity claim,the 'boy will return to Dubai for - the new orders from His Honour the Political Residentitherefore with great pleasure on your friend,the 'boy is sent accompanied with my cousin named AMul Rahim 'bin Husain with the serv mt - who from the date of his taking him over,he is the guarantor of 'bringing- up the 'boy in question. My cousin forwards to your honour the account of expenses incurred on the 'boy,and also expenses of the voyages from Dubai to Karachi and the return to Dubai. Your friend requests of your favour the amount of expenses to 'be paid to my cousin aforesaid. (Signed) K.B.Essa 'bin Ahdul Latif, Residency Agent. 1928,to Commissioner,Karachi.-» « i ^ I jry / t *•&gt; v B'rora- ' n he Residency '^ent, ohargah. 'o - rhe T Ion 1 ole the Political President, Persian Gulf. No. 607, dated the 12th December 1928. c* . .. . /i- 1 With reference to your telegram No.l2i3 regarding iluhammad Q.ufaidi I informed Shaikh Said 'bin Maktum ahout his request to release the said man on account of his illness and he obtained an undertaking from him and ordered hira to leave his town. I herewith enclose for your infor- m it ion a copy of the document which was taken 'by the said Shaikh from the aforesaid Muhammad. Translation of text of undertaking. I, Muhammad bin Vbdur Rahman A1 -';ufaidi give an undertaking to the said Shaikh Said hin Kaktum, CJhief of Dahai, and Khan Bahadur Isa 'bin Abdul Latif, Residency 'gent 'Crucial Oman, with regard to the irregular actions committed 'by me for which the Government of Dtfbai ordered me to go out of it. 1 am proceeding to Nejd and will never come back to the Coast(Oman) and if I returned I shall be liable to any ounishment that the Government may consider suitable to inflict upon me.^ . cju d ct kjef' 7 t ^ From The Hesidenoy Agent, Shargah. I 19 lon'ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf No.636, dated the 27th Decernher 1928» A.CJ. 'eTerence your letter Mo•289 dated the 4th Decemher 1928 on the subject of illness of Al-Qufaidi, who was in the prison of Shaikh of Dahai, I have the honour to stale that on receipt of your telegram No.1233 saying that oae saia man should 'be released from prison and ordered to leave Tor * T aJd, I at once informed the Shaikh and he did tae needful. I stated the facts to you in my letter No. 7 dated 12th December 1928, enclosing copy of the under taking taken from the said Muhammad to the effect that he should never return to Dahai. I hope that my letter quoted above has reached you. izf/i', \Secretary . SulDmitted, The Residency Agent states that ty Dalumal accompanied other 'banyas came to -^nr him on the 15th July 1928 and it was arrange^ 'by him to get the 'boy from Ras al Khaimah and the toy arrived at Sharqah on the 22nd July# But when he sent for Dalumal and other Banyas, the other Banyas of Dubai and Sharqah arrived and saw the 'boy but Dalumal did not come and on enquiry it was found that he had left for Karachi. In support of his statement,the R.A, Sharqah encloses statements of the Majlis and 'the Banyas. Tfs st ye/Ivr.n™ /W /Z'i&amp;.A 3 ct&amp;j-c* 'ycrf cuyx. qaxjy -A •xTv' sestef. 'fi-osia. x la ajj-ffv-* , 5V 7 may -tl co--'i.yy-u.a-cszijfi. ' '' ^ cq^ul o-lc ^ o^. ^ -tpoFrom To No.42. A. 0. The 'Residenoy Agent, Sliargah. ^ The Hon'hle the Political HesiaentJ, Persi.an Dated 4th 'Pehruary 1928. I l^eg to state that on the 13th Ifeoeiaher 1927 a Baluchi reported to rae that a 'Boom 'belonslng to the Baluchi s ca.- 'y- ing Baluchi hoys and girls for sale, had anchored between Hemriyyeh and Umm ul Qaiwain. I at once left Shargan. -y my motor hoat with a view to seize the Boom ana v/ent to Ajman, Ilemriyyeh, Umm ul Qaiwain and Has ul Khaimah u.it did not trace the Boom. In my absence one of tU' Agency ■Fidawis had found a Baluchi hoy in the house o' one of tae Arahs of Shargah and had taken him to l - - * ^ er two days the kidnapper of the hoy and the Arah named ^hal- Ai Hahhah had at sunset amhushed near f e Agency anl rekidnapped him. As my cousin, Ahdur Bahman, who was in charge of my house during my absence did not find the hoy after sunset, he at once ordered the ^idawis to search for him in the houses of the Baluchis residing at Shargah. As the hoy was not traced in the houses of the Baluchis ' e reported to Shaikh Sultan hin ^ar ahout the kidnapping of the hoy from the Agency and asked him to arrest \haid Al Hiihhah in whose house the hoy was • Th- J --- ^ 1 • arrested the said Ahaid. *he next day cousin was informed that the man who brought the hoy from B^oai uc Shargah for sale was called Bajah hin Muhammad of ^a'lan and had come to the house of Al Hahhah. He arrested and imprisoned him. He admitted that the hoy was at Behai. | My cousin sent a letter with a special Bidawi to Shaikh Said hin Maktum asking him to recover the hoy. The Shaikh , did every endeavour in the matter and recovered the hoy. The Shaikh 's letter to the address of my cousin is enclos&gt;?a herewith for your information. 1 received a letter from Snaiko. oultan . n .^aoar saying that the hoy had heen traced and was at the Agency I returned from Has ul Khaimah to Shargah, interviewed' the/. / is % . and pointed out to him that it was very strange that during his chief ship the Baluchi 'boy had 'been rekidnapped from the O on.vy. Tae ohaikh mentioned that the committers were ^alacais one of whom was in mj prison. I told the Shaikh J hat since olden times we used to recover Baluchi 'boys and girls from the Baluchis and Aral)s and no one had ventured to rekidnap them from the Agency. If Ahaid A1 Hahhah who is m citizen of Shargah, had not Joined hands with the Baluchis, tiiey would not have committed such an act. '-Qie Shaikh said that he imprisoned A'baid 'but he had escaped oo tae Bedouin tribesmen in the interior and did not know where he had gone. Ra jalp bin Muhammad A 1 ^a'lani is under custody at the Residency Agency and I will await your Mistructions as to his disposal. The Baluchi hoy requests that he may he sent to Muscat. Statement made 'by Eeza 'bin Pahmat Baluchi, a^ed ahout jears. Ha is originally from Kumazi under the rule of Mir Banian Baluahi. Recorded on the 17th Rajah 1346 (11 -1 -28 ^Then I was in my town a certain Khan* Muhammad Bachuh of Mand came to me^and said that he wanted to go to Basrah and required a servant. I accompanied him 'by land to Minah where v/e emhai ked a ooa and sailed for ^enjam and thence to TT mm ul Qaiwain. 'Prom the latter place v/e proceeded over land uo r&gt;ehai. After Pour days Khan Muhammad ordered me to accompany a certain Rajah Baluchi to Shart;ah. Taen I asked Khan Muhammad why he v/anted to send me to Shar^ah and was not going to Basrah as stated hy him he said that he was unahle to go to Basrah and that I should accompany Rajah to Shargah where he would find a joh for me. If I did not like Shar-ah I should return to Dehal.. I accompanied Rajah to Shargah and on,pur arrival there he took me to a house A wo wan who was m that house asked me v/hether I was a slave or free horn. I told her that I was. a free horn. She said that I Ijad heen kidnapped and so I told her not to' 1 # ^ woi; ' la ' n not purchase me. He/ took me to a .icase ci an olc man -.Those name I do not know and kept mc in a goaovm. At sunset they opened the 2 0( ^ 0wn snd- took me ou .. Two Arahs came there and looked at me am. then went away. T asked Ha Jab to permit me to go to ^' J - cre ■ u ''-' aid not agree. I ran to the door with the Intention of going out 'but the old man caught me. I snouted out and the Arahs came among whom was r Tilal 'bin LiaLimavi - Fidav/i 0° the Residency Agency^ On enquiring m ' 1 1 rcm 'hat place T had 'been kidnapped xiid: I inror -ed i him ah out my case. He took me to the Agency. The next day when I was sitting ahout sunset at the door of the Agency two men came and asked me to take'my clothes. ' I gc t up 'rom my place and went towards them hut they suddenly arrested me, closed my mouth with a cloth and took me to the house of the Baluchi at Dehai. After two days the 'Pidav/i of the Shaikh of Dehai as well as the Residency Agent's recovered me from Rajah's house and took me to the Shaikh and then sent me to Shargah. T 'beg H.B.M's Government to repatriate me to Muscat at I have no relatives at my own place ^nd I want to earn my livelihood there. Letter dated 29th Jamadi II, 1346 (24-12-27) from Shaikh oaid 'bin Maktum, CJhief of Dehai, to Ahdur 'Rahman 'bin Husain, R.A's representative at Shargah. • A.O. I have received your letter and was acquainted with Its contents. As regards the 'boy who was rekidnaiped from the Agency ^t Shargah and taken to the house of Cwaishah 'bino Masir, I heg to inform you that the hoy was 'brought 'Ralachi w io was unknown '/O them and was kept in that house. The Baluchi did ^not return for the hoy and they do not know where he had gone to. As soon as I received your letter through Hilal I recovered the hoy from the''v a &amp; house of Owaishah 'bin 4 '; Masir and handed him over to Hilal who took him to you. Letter dated 29th Jamadi II, 1346 (24-12-27), from Shaikh - Sultan tin Sa^ar, Chief of Shargah, to the Residency Agent, Shargah. A.O. iVS 1,f 3S-rds the Baluchi ahout v/hom you were informed 'by Ahdur Rahman 'bin Husain and ? r ulla Khalid, T 'beg to stiite that he is now under custody at the Agency. I am prepared to comply with any order that you may refer to me.Ho, ^ ^ 1928. of 1928. Britlah Residency &amp; Consulate-General. Bushire, the /H April i928 w To The Political Agent 5c H. B. M 9 s Consul . Muscat. Memorandum In December last the Residency Agent, Shargah recovered, from the house of one of the Arabs of that place, a Baluch youth named Reza, who had been kidnapped from Kumazi for purposes of slavery, by a Baluch called Rajab bin tfohamed of Yalan. A translation of Reza's statement is enclosed for your information from which it will be observed that Rajab even managed to kidnap the boy for the sec nd time after he had been taken charge of by the Residency Agent, iesidency Agent has been instructed to send him and the Baluch, Rajab, to you. The Hon'ble the Tolitical Resident will be glad if you will ask His Highness the Sultan of Muscat to punish Rajab for his offence. Please report result in due course^ As Reza asked to be repatriated to Muscat, the By Order Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Letter 110. 1179 dated the 6th October 1928 from ^ the Political Agent and H.E.I!.'s Consul, J'UBoat. - ' Punishment to slave dealer Rajab bin Muhammad Jaalani. Secreta ry r Submitter, The - J^uscat Govt sentenced Rajab bin Ttuharamad to 5 months imprisonment. They gave a lenient sentence on account of his health. The case is from flag 1/9 to 13/9 in file 5/191 which is submitted. May be filed ? * t^ja PR. q-. ((. ^ OS c4 vUNcuA.B•! 188 of 1927 British Kesidency ft Consulate-General, Bushire,the 22nd October 1927* o To Messrs.the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation,Limited BTJSHIRE. Dear Sir, I am directed to request the you will kindly sei&gt;d me a deck ticket,with food to Bombay for Ifirza Ghulam Husaij. hy to-morrow's Past Mail Steamer. Please send me a dehit note for the cost of the passage. Tours faithfully lial^ — British Hesidency k Consulate-General, Bushire.From To Office of the Commissioner of no . 'ZZ'tml. I - * T he COMMISSIONER of POLICE, BOMBAY; ^ 36 The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Bombay, S-*- November /p? 7 Sir, 7/ith reference to your telegran dated 24th October 1927,1 have the honour to inform you that I have incurred 1. One deck ticket from ) Bomhay to Calicut us. 10-0-0 ) expenses amounting 2. Subsistence charges ) to Rs.13/- as for 3 days during ) the voyage. Rs. 3-0-0 ) detailed in the j margin in connec- Total: - Rs. 13-0-0 ) tion with the repatriation of the Indian lad rirza G-ulam Hussein. I shall he glad if you will kindly remit a sum of rs .13/- to this office at an early date. I have the honour to 'be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. W] t^V tDy .Commissi i ner of Police Port. y- dc65 ^ V j kssy i /'MB wm No.A.B.1411 of 1927 British ReGidenoy &amp; Consulite-^eneral, Bushirefthe 2l3t i^ecem'ber 1927. Prom To The Secretary to the Hon'l^lc the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf• • / The Oomiaissloner of Police, B o m h a y • sir, \0 -ith reference to your letter No•12214/268, dated I the 22nd November 1927, I an directed to enclose herewith the sum of fis 13/- in Indian Ourrency Note and postage stamps, on account of expenses incurred 'by you in connoc- tion with the repatriation of rirza Qhulam Hup sain and to request the favour of an acknowledgement. I have the honour to 'be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Captain, Secretary to the olitical Kesident in the Persian Gulf.Gonfi dentj al. From, To ■'Wtwwr,-.' ■ ,£&gt;/ No; 13960-A, #• Oatt JWl .W- JudiciaJ Departm^riii. c ^ Office of the Goramissioner in Sind. Government House, Karachi, ^ December 1927 f. W.F. Hudson, Esquire, C .I. '3., Commissioner in 35nd. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushi re. bir. Subject;- Slavery Abduction of boys for purposes of yk a' t In continuation of my telegram No: 12$60-A dated 19th December 19 27 I nave the honour to forward, herewith copies of letter No: Jm-129/6 -6 399, dated the 14ta December 1927, and accompaniments from the Superintendent of Police, Karachi, Head Quarters on the subject noted above for favour of enquiry being made regarding the boy Muhammad Hassan son of Hajee Hassan who will probably answer to the name of Sheravi the family name of the parents. J have the honour also to request that you will be so good as to send co photograph of the boy in question if he is in charge of the Political Agency^. I have the honour to oe, Sir, Your most obecJent servant i For Commissioner in Sind,-SXC eilio zcvj' j /TU o! ^ s From To No.43. A. 0. The Hesidenoy Agent, Sh^r-jah. The Hon'^ble the Political P^sident, Persian Gulf. Dated 4th February 1928. I 'be^ to state that on the 14th January 1928 a Baluchi named Muhammad Murad informed me that he had seen u./o women and children who had 'been kidnapped from Hinah in tne aouse of a certain Hilal of Nejd. On asking him aoout the kidnappers he said that the kidnapper was I£uhira 'bin Muharak 'Baluchi who is well known in the towns of Kekran and Ilcas got a Boom and a jolly-hoat. TT e said that Muhim had le^Tt De'bai. T wrote to my agent at Deoai named Haji Yusuf 'bin Ao lullah, and sent the Baluchi to him in order to show him Tusuf the house. On receipt of my letter Haji/went at once to the Nejdi• s house, recovered the v/omen and sent them to me at Shar^ah. • ^ statement s are enclosed herev/ith. They 'beg Your Honour to repatriate them to Bandar Ahhas. Statement made 'by Zahra daughter of Ahmad of Minah aged ahout 19 years. Recorded on the 27th Pajah 1346 (21st January 1928). and myself My sister named Fatiah aged 7 year^were asleep at aome. Three Baluchis entered the house suddenly, arrested us, put us on camels and took us to a village called Priz. After 7 days some Baluchis brought the . woman Bihak and aer daughter. Muhim 'bin Mubarak Baluchi took charge (5f all of us, embarked us on a hoat and took us to De'bai where he kept us in the hoiise of an Arab of Nejd. After three days the Pesidency Agent's man came to Pehai and took us out of that house and sent us to the Pesidency Agent at Shargah. T 'beg TT .B.• s Government to send me to ^andar Abbas where I will meet my mother named Kanji and my 'brother, AhmacL who are residing at Minal3. Statemonti made 'by Bi'bak daughter of 'uhammad Tlud'bari aged alDout 27 years. Slie is from Oahur Hushkak under the rule of Mirza Khan of Rudhar. P^ecorded on the 27th Rajah 1346 (21-1-28). My hushand Husain Shah.war 'Rudhari and myself were sleeping at our home when we were suddenly attacked hy 10 Baluchi camel-riders. They killed my hushand and carried me and my daughter Jamilah off and took us to Mir Barkat. The latter did not agree to take us. They then took us to Muhim 'bin Mubarak Baluchi who 'bartered us for a rifle and embarked us on hoat and took us to the house of TTilal Mejdi at Dehai. After two days T Taji Yusuf, the Residency Agent's man, recovered us from that man's house. I 'beg K.B.M's Government to send me in company with Zahra to Bandar Ahhas whence I may 'be ahle to proceed to my own town. •*&lt;Bo, OO' 0 f 1928. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 3lf&gt;f IJarch 1928, From To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ^he ^irector # ?ersian Gulf Section, Indo European Telegraph Department t Karachi. \ iy Sir, y / I am directed to enclose herewith translation of a letter -*o«43 dated the 4th February 1928 and enclosures from the Residency -agent, '&gt;har^% regarding kidnapping of 2 Baluch women and children by Muhirn bin Hubarak Baluchi of l.'ekran and to request you to supply this office with a full history of this man and his antecedents to enable the Hobble the Political Resident to take further action in the matter. I have the honour to be, Sir. xour most obedient servant, Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident ^ in the Persian Gulf.No. 629/10/2. British Agency &amp; Consulate, lo To Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Memorandum. In accordance the instructions conveyed to him in your letter No.22 of the 25th Marhh last, the Hesidency A^ent at Shargah on the 20th instant sent to this Consulate by a sailing 'boat the two women, ZAHEA bint Yekshambeh and BIBOK bint Mahomed, with two female children who had been kidnapped at Minab and Rudbar recently by Baluchi and Rudbari tribesmen and taken to Dubai to be sold as slaves. 2. These women and children have been handed over to the Persian authorities with a request that they be safely returned to their homes, after enquiring into their cases. The father of the woman Zahra who had been to Dubai in search of his daughter and her young sister Fatma, accompanied the party to Bandar Abbas. 3. I have furnished the Governor with the names of the principal culprtits concerned, and requested His Excellency to have the latter punishedgi I have also suggested that the authorities at Minab and other places in that direction be instructed to exercise vigilence with a view to prevent the wholesale kidnapping of men, women and children which is reported to be rife in the Minab and Biyaban Districts. H.B.M's 3 Resident.s' No. 703/10/2, To British. Agency &amp; Consulate, Bandar Afbas, May 10,1923 The Secretary to the Hon'tle the Political Besident in the Persi-n CrUlf, B IT S H I E E . -rapRurouii. f 5 - /o II Reference my Memorandum wo.629/10/2 dated the 26th April 1928. ^ The Governor of Bandar Aohas has acknowledged receipt of the persons mentioned therein and states they have 'been disposed of satisfactorily. He adds that on making enquires from the woman Zanra 'bint Yekshamheh it was ascertained that her mother named C^anji and her young 'brother had also 'been kidnapped 'but had not 'been taken to Dubai with her. He requests that a watch 'be kept for their arrival and that in such case, they he restored and sent to Bandar Ahhas. His Excellency, in conclusion, expresses his grateful appreciation of the action taken 'by the Residencj Agent at Shargah. I shall 'be obliged if you would kindly issue instructions in the sense desired 'by the CJovemor. At the same time, I bm informing the Residency Agent ahout the B ■ ■ k * missing wom-.n and her son. A 'l-.i i a forf. j u _ .1 His Britannic MaJesty'sOeirsul and Assistant to ths^Resident ii. • c . .C's. P. P.-L (in) 479-1,000-3-28. ^ () NIo ^ iph Address : — Jii&amp;0-(£u W can felcowl} •qwrinttnl' Karachi. PERSIAN GULF SECTION. L- * A '^£ i? rrom f-w r &gt; * Persian Gulf Section ; \ 'i'he Regret a ry to the Kon'l^le the Political Resid e nt In the Persi an CJulf, i Bushire. . ^ To Enclosure No^iS-pKarachi, the June 192 ^ Sir, '' ■t&gt;' With reference to your letter No. 562 of '.larch 1928 (receive! on 5th April), I have the honour to inform you that Muhim 'bin Tfubarak whose hone is at Goorag or ±iris, is a well known slave-trafficker and gun-runner. 2. It is reported that he procures Baluchis, 'both men and women, and ships them to Dubai where he hands them over to confederates for sale. He takes rifles and ammunition in exchange for the slaves and on returning to the Persian coast, he sends them to Dost Mohamed Khan of Bampur, the latter paying for the rifles and ammunition with cash and a further supply of slaves who are in turn shipped to Dubai. :£Lrza Ahan of Kudbar also receives a supply of rifles and ammunition. 3. The slaves are embarked for Dubai from two places namely 'Bris and Sirik. 4 - It is reported that eight months ago, he 'borrowed Hs 4000/- from Mir 'Rarkat Khan for the purpose of financing his slave trading business. The loan was to be repaid, in cash and a supply of rifles and ammunition and from information received this debt has been discharged. 5. He has been at Banrpur and is at present at Biyaban in Mir Barkat's district. ^ stated that while the British ITavy wd.s engaged at noweit, he took the opportunity to ship his slaves across to Dubai as the chances of his heing caught were small.I 7. in this connection please also see the 1 ^ ^ mentioned telegrams: director Persian Uulf Telegraphs telegram of HI v/orx3 o. 27th July 1921 to the Political Resident Bus; ' m ; Mavarra's telegram of 74 words of 8th December 1922 ^o the Political Resident Bushire. 1 have the honour to be Sir Tour most obedient servant Persian Uulf Telegraphs, in Political Charge of Mekran Coast.From...D.P.G..Karachi. To Political, Bushire. Dated 9th Deer. 1922. Report for vreek ending 9th. One Sarfaraz brought four rifles from Dubai and iunded t; en at Sirik. Mohin Mobarak took nine young negro slaves in his dhow to Brisk for sale on Arab coast he is now reported to have fled to Bashakard for fear of Mir Burkat who was annoyed to hear Mohin's behaviour. Mir Burkat will arrive Jask shortly to celebrate narriage of late Mir HaJ^s son with Mir Hotis daughter Reported that Mirs Yaha Khan and Nagai Khan (Mir Yahya's uncle) will shortly leave Baiapur at request of Governor.'O Balitical Resident, Bushire . (Copy Senior ITaval Officer &amp; Intelligence Officer) Dated 27th July 1921. following telcgrura dated 26th instt received from Mr Navarra, ^sstt. r-updt. Jask Sub-Division. Begins. News Just received that Mohira Mobarak with his four slaves and his brother have embarked in his own dhow 22nd instant from Sarkand near BunJi for Dubai. He intends returning with arms, ^upposea do have 30 rifles awaiting him at Gwattar. Mir Abdullah and Mohamed Judgal have landed 20 magazine rifles and 200 rounds with each in dhow of Ghulam Kassim of Kar^agan about a week ago. They have been taken to Rudbar where some Afghans are supposeu to be trading in this lines. Lnds./\ ; a * No. (() |( of 1928* British Residency &amp; Consulate-Generalp Bushlre, the 2&gt;U Auguat 1928. Prom The Secretary to the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* To The Director» Persian Gulf Section* Indo European Telegraph Department 9 Karachi* Sir, I am directed by the Hon f ble the Political Resident ♦ in the Persian Gulf, to thank you for your letter Ko*235-P dated the 7th June 1928 and to say that any information of the slave traffic you mention that you can give us in advance will be gratefully received* I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most Obedient servant* Major, ^ Secretary to the Political Resident yc in the Persian Gulf*■ »o. 1612 of 1928. &gt; ■ x •' British Residency &amp; Consulate*General» ^/ Sef{: Bushire f the 2^ August 1928, &gt; Sir, I am directed to forward herewith for your information a copy of a letter No.235-P dated the 7th June 1928itogether with an Office Note dated the 23rd August 1928 from the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* I have the honour to bef Sir, Your most obedient servantp ^ Major, //? Secretary to the Pelltical a^eident in the Persian Gulf* 1*S. To The Senior liaval Officer, Persiajn Gulf. Hanjam®Copy of a Offloe ^ote 'by the iion , 'ble the Political Kesident in the Persian ^uir, dated the 23rd August 1928. 1 do not think the Consul at Bundar Ahhas can do anything of use at pre ent. That we want to do is to catch the man not to warn him. 1 hope in a short time to have a slave trade 'bureau and prevent ire service in running order in regular communication with the Senior Naval crficer and to catch these people red-handed. Thank D.P.G. for letter and say that any in formation he can give us in advance will he gratefully received. Send copy of letter under note and this note to R.N.0. for information.9 No. Of 1928. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 2n&lt;l June 1928. To The Residency Agent, Shargah. A. 0. \ In continuation of this office letter No.22-B dated the 25th March 1988 with regard to the recovery of Zahra, Bibolc and two children, 1 am directed to inform you that it has now 'been ascertained that the mother of Zahra named Ganji and her younger brother, had also heen kidnapped hut had not 'been taken to De'bai with her. 1 am to request you to 'be on the look out for them and effect their restoration 'by the assistance of the Shaikh on their arrival and report to this Residency in due course. Major, Secretary to the Political Resident . in the Persian Gulf.otatement made 'by AlDdullah son of MuharamacL,original place Bint of Persian Mekran, aged aT^out 30 years# Recorded on the 22nd DeoemlDer 1927, I was 'born at G-airun a dependency of 1 Bint under Dost Muhammad Khan, When I was 17 years old four Baluchis kidnapped me from Gairun and took me to Sadaich where they embarked me on a hoat which sailed for Batinah at once. Ihey sold, me at Batinah to another person who took me hy land to Dehai where he sold me to Muhammad 'bin Said who was dealing in diving. I used to work for him during diving season. Six years ago my master Muhammad died. I married a Baluchi woman at Dehai 7 years ago. Three years ago my cousin^'brought to Dehai and I kept him with myself. After the death of my master I was employed 'by Humaid 'bin Muhammad A1 Asam and I am now indebted a sum of Rs.850/- to him. Last year Muhammad 'bin Abdur Rahman A1 Cufaidi % v/ho is engaged in slave trade complained to Hashar 'bin Maktum that I was dealing in slaves and the latter imprisoned ! me till the 'beginning of diving season. He told me that either I should pay Rs.600/- or else he will take my cousin, f When I said that I had no money to pay he took my cousin and handed him over to the Al-Qufaidi. I went to diving and after my return I went to Shaikh Said and Shaikh Hashar and asked them to recover my cousin from Muhammad A1 Qufaidi 'but they did not pay any attention. I have now taken refuge at H.B.M's Residency and beg you to 'be good enough to recover my cousin from Muhammad 'bin Abdur Rahman A1 Qufaidi who has got a house at Debai and is living there. Left thumb^impression of Abdullah bin Muhammad. Tfyw* f ^wjfyuuuj pl^LQjL ^ ^ -MiWo. bof 1928. British. Residency h Consulate-General, Bushire, January 1928. Translation of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Residency Agent, Shargah, for favour of enquiry and report. Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the L y^ Persian Gulf. Statement made 'by Abdullah son of Muhammad of Bint aged a'bout 30 years. 'p /■ * - _From - Tiie Residency ^gent, Shargah. The T Ion , 'ble the Political Resident,Persian Gulf. No#287. Dated 13th June 1928. V.C. Jith reference to your letter No.6, dated the 8th January 1928, enclosing statement made 'by Abdullah 'bin LIuhammad Baluchi who alleged that his cousin was arrested oy Shaikh Hashar 'bin Maktum and handed over to Muhammad 'bin Ibdur Rahman U Qufaidi of Nejd. I 'beg to state that I was at Dehai when your letter reached me. I discussed the question of Abdullah's claim with Shaikh Said 'bin Maktum who stated that Abdullah 'bin i Muhammad used to kidnap Baluchi women and children from Mekran and that he had kidnapped a Baluchi woman and sold her to Muhammad 'bin Vbdur Rahman A1 Qufaidi. The latter after some time sold the woman to a Persian from whom I y recovered her. The Persian complained against Muhammad for the amount which he had paid on account of the cost of the woman and I recovered Rs.700/- from the latter and paid it to the former. Muhammad put forward a counterclaim against Abdullah 'bin Muhammad for the cost of the laluchi woman 'but as the latter was not able to pay the amount he mortgaged a boy with Muhammad for a certain period within which he was to pay the fimount. I asked the Shaikh to present Muhammad bin Abdur Rahman and the boy who v/as with him but he could not do sc as he was not present at Debai and had gone to Hasa. I v/as awaiting the arrival of the said Muhammad from ^asa. On his return to Debai I convened a meeting and summoned Abdullah bin Muhammad and Muhammad bin Abdur Rahman as well as the Baluchi woman, Amnah bint Muhammad, for whom I asked a Manumission Certificate and you sent one under your No»92, dated the 7th May 1928. Abdullah bin Muhammad admitted in the meeting that he with three other Baluchis had kidnapped from iu Mekran the woman Amnah and^boy whom he had claimed andsold the woman to Muhammad 'bin Vbdur Rahman. I 'beg to forward herewith the proceeding of the meeting and a document which Abdullah had given in connection with the mortgage of the 'boy for Rs.900/- on account of the cost of the woman which he had recovered from Abdullah. The hoy has heen kept with Shaikh Hashar 'bin Makturn till I refer the matter to you and receive your instructions on the subject. U.E. r* Proceedings of the Meeting. •■e the undersigned appeared in the meeting which was held in the Residency Agency 'by K.B. Isa 'bin Abdul Latif tne Residency Agent. Abdullah bin Muhammad Baluchi who alleged that his cousin was with Muhammad A1 Qufaidi of Nejd and Muhammad A1 Qufaidi attended the meeting also. On enquiry from Abdullah about the case of his cousin who was alleged to be with Muhammad al Qufaidi he stated that he acted as a broker for a Baluchi man v/ho had imported a woman for sale and sold the woman to Muhammad Al Qufaidi. Hie latter after some months sold the woman to a Persian from whom the K.B. Isa recovered. The Persian complained to the CJhief of Debai who recovered his money from Muhammad. The said Muhammad put^a counterclaim against him (Abdullah) to the Ghief of Debai and he was urged upon to pay the money which was not due from him. As he had no money to pay he mortgaged his cousin for Rs.900/- with the Ghief of Debai. lie said taat as the action taken by the Government Debai wab not according to Justice he proceeded to Bushire and submitted his complaint in this connection. We asked Muhammad Al Qufaidi to explain the case of the woman whom he had purchased through Abdullah bin Muhammad. He stated that he bought the woman from Abdullah himself and paid her cost to him and the Baluchi woman who is in existence could be questioned about the matter. vie asked K .B. Isa to present the woman. The woman whose name is Amnah bint Muhammad appeared before us. le asked her as to who has kidnapped her from fltekran. She said that Abdullah bin i il-uhammad was the man who kidnapped her from Mekran and / sold her to Muhammad A1 Qufaidi. The ^oy whom was claimed by Abdullah to he his oousin had al_so 'been kidnapped with aer from I^ekran for sale and was not his cousin. ^Te asked Abdullah as to whether the statement of the woman Amnah was correct or not. He admitted that he was one of the Baluchis who kidnapped the woman and the hoy whom was claimed by him. It has now 'been proved to us that Abdullah was the man who sold the woman and also mortgaged the hoy against the claim of Muhammad A1 Qufaidi. In our opinion Abdullah 'bin Muhammad Baluchi deserves punishment as he has acted against the orders of the British Government. Dated 14th Dhil Hejjeh 1346 (3-6-28). - 3d * Heza'tin Maslh^i^^ Salifatl JU(i S e • ^argah. Shaikh Rahmatullah bin Shaikh Eeza Larl Abdullah bin Hasan A1 Madfa* G-hulam Husain Zaita 'bin Lulu Tiku Gandanan. I Aodall ah l)j.n Muhammad 3aluchi, have mortgaged my servant Mubarak with Muhammad A1 Qufaidi for Rs.900/- which amount Is payable on 10th Dhll IIejjeh(10th June 1927). Then the time falls due I will return the goods which I have taken from Muhammad A1 Qufaidi and pay money for its balance if there be any without any fail or procrastination I have given this paper so that it may be known to anyone who may see it and I have asked the witnesses mentioned in this paper to give their evidence. Dated 1345 (1926-27). 2d Abdullah 'bin Muhammad Baluchi WitneSses.AMull^ bin Thani bin Khalaf. ' Sultan 'bin Muqrin. •— Tv(?&gt;OONJIDEWTIAT. . No. Of 1928 British Residenoy &amp; Oonsulate-G-eneral, Buahlre, the j^| is October 1928. I To Th® Political Agent and His Majesty*3 Oonsul, Musoat M emorandum # I am directed to forward therewith, for yo^ i^Qraation, copies of the marginally noted oommunioatione on the subJ eot of slavery oases on the Batinah and Truoial Oman ooast and to say that the Hon^le the political lesident wishes you to look out confidentially for the notorious slave nav © dealer AMullah 'bin Muhammad Eawar of ^adam and him arrested when opportunity aocurs either direat or with the help of the senior Naval officer who has instructioE on the matter. By order t 1. Letter No.287 dated the USth June from the Residency Agent 3harq.ah f to the Hon*hie the Politioal Ttesident. 2. Letter vo .32 dated the 20th sept, from the C.N.O. to the Commander in Ohief (Copy to Jpolitical 'Resident). 3. Telegram No.T.379 dated the 18th Sept. from the Resident, to the S^N.O. 4. Telegram No.1009 dated the 26th Sept. from the SNO. to the Resident. v? ft Uajolr, Secretary to the Political ^sldent In the Persian GilfOFFICE NOTES 557 -a/ /3 ^ f -tt ■ ^^ct &lt;* ' ^'■^du,. ^ ^ S gcrgtary &gt; Su 'braitted, ^he Record branch says the file 5/191 containing pp of this case is still in Shiraz in connection with the general slave question. T he gist of the reply sent by the R.A. is that the complaint of Abdullah 'bin Muhammad Baluchi is false and that he himself is guilty of selling a woman Aminah ( eventually manumitted) and for mortgaging a 'boy in lieu of a claim of R s 900/ due to Muhammad tin A^dur Rahman al Quf^aidi , and for falsely claiming the toy ( Mubarak £7y. The R.A # recommends that Abdullah b in Muhamm ad be punished^ W 2? ct^vc -- -Af Extract from letter NO. 44,E./32. dated the 16th August 1923 from the Senior Naval Officeri Persian Gulf, to the Political Resident jPersian Gulf. 7« There is another and more important side to the independent attitude displayed 'by the Shaikh of A1 Fujairah. '/hen investigating the reoent slave-running case ( Senior Naval Officer's letter NO. 43 E of17th July ^23 ) it was conclusively proved that the slaves were landed at Grherefa,which is the port of A1 Fujairah# evidence was atv the same time received that slaves are being landed there with moderate frequency and that it is in all probability the only port aaoiKitxkjcxaui on the Patinah coast now used for the purpose. The attractions of a port owned by an independent minded Shaikh obvious # This copy is taken for file 5/191, v&amp;cWct^Y ^ / 0*1, r )r~-' 1&gt;» v.©&gt; L Jfe - c.c. Ss. Telegram dated the H3rd April 1928 from the Coiumander, H.M.S. 'Crocusi ,, liubject:-Glare traffic in Uibaid &gt; Secretary &gt; $ There are no p»p® with regard to thia particular case» i5ut presumably the P.R, desireB to see the correspondence at present going on with rq^rd to traffic of slaves* This is on file 5/191, A* Xi« 25 -4 -28 File is with you. fut up to P.R. if required. K.P.W. 25-4-28 File is amongst p.p. below, we must first reply about the repatriation of the Indians. Before orders can issue about the disposal of the Baluchis their national ity Mtill have to be ascertained. J.C. 26-4-28 Indians might be repatriated and R.A.» Shargah, instructed to ascertain nationality of Baluchis ? P.R. R.P.W. 26-4-28 / ^l-uc .nr —mmr j* No. 111 of 1928. British Besldenoy St Consulate-General, Bushlre, the Hay 1928. To The Politioal Agent, Muscat* MemoranluiB . Two persons from Kusoat, originally Jedghas of Kuohatl, were arrested 'by the Besidenoy Agent, Shargah, at De^bai, 'bartering two 'beggar Indians to Bedouins. They were helreved to have already disposed of one other Indian in this way. The Residency Agent is 'being asked to send these two men to Muscat. The Hon^le the Political Resident hopes that you will T)e ahle to get these 2 men punis .ed suitably for their offence. PleaAa communicate result of your action to this office. By order. . Oaptain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. a^rom - Tie Re si den 07 Agent, Shargalu '^ le Hon •'hie Vie Politioal 'Resident ? Persian O-ulf. ^ated 2nd Kay 1228. a.a. I 'beg to state that on the 20th April 192S I reoeiYel an intimation from -y agent at 'De'bai to the effect that the ^Shai :h of Ahu Dha'bi had sent him t' o Indians one of V^e+n was from A j me re ; ad the other from Calicut of ^alahar. M hLiu Wo Baluohis had deceived thqfeIndians ^.nd Ifead. emTbarked them on a 'boat and taken them to Abu I&gt;ha'bl for sale and a - ^ ''hat the house 0' the Baluchis could 'be shown 'by the Indians. T wrote to .iy a^ent to ask the Deputy Shaikh of 'Dehai to render his a&amp;oistance li arresting the 'Paluchis. ■ In the me; ntime ' V toqus* arrives at ^harjah. Tien I -rent ashore in company the Oaptain to tho house of the Sh:.i&gt;li of Dehai I found the Baluchis and the ' Indians there. T enquired froi the Indians in the presence of the 'Baluchis ahout their case. They s:id that the ^ i luchis embarked them on a 'boat and tool them to Abu Dhabi- for sale. I then made enquiries fro? 1 the Baluchis and discover ^ed that they had played a trick with the Indians and had embarked them on a boat and intended to sell them. ^3 C?apt* in decided to imprison the Bal ichis in the *ort o n the Oover n ent of Debai and 'reop the Indians /ith r: j ajent at Debai. ^0 left for Abu Dhabi and the ^apta^n of •Crocus wired the matter for your infor lation. On arrival at Abu Dhabi &gt; r e asked the Shai':h and the notables of that place about the case o' the Indians. They said that a Baluchi 'brought them to ATSu IJSuilji jjid intended to sell them b.a^ as soon as the w heard the news they recovered' and sent - le. 1 ^o D3ha—• The statements of the Indians as .ell as the Baluchis are enclosed herewith. Statement made by TTawazi ^iyahi ^Tiotaaia. an inhabitant o^ AJmere, India, aged about 31 years. Be lordad on 7th Dhil-Oadeh 1346 (28-^-28) •i T an a poor man. 11 months .ago I le^t 1113^ to\ n AJmere with the intention of going on pil^riina^e. T travelled t&gt;y foot and rent to ^inC .■.'here I met with a Si'icli '^oy n^ed ^afar a^ed ahout 16 years, ^e joined me for ^oi to Eaj and e travelled together till ie arrived, at (xwadur 'lere a 'Baluchi _ .ve us free passag® to ir us-at. ^3 arri r e^ at Muscat and thence we travelled 'by land to Dehai. O'/in^ to earning our livelihood 'by hedging at the doors of the \rahs* i houses. .A. Baluchi v/hose name I do not 'know met# Safar and asked him from i.hat 'ulaoe he was. Safar told him that he was a poor mau and intended to go with his friend on pilgrimage. Tie 'Baluchi said that he had a 'boat 'by wnich he could take us to Kuwait and thence * e could go hy land to ^aj. ^ far i ifon-ed me that there was a man ho Intewd - j- ed to send us 'by his 'boat to Kuwait. T did not aj^G to jo vith him hut after two days Safar came an^ told me that he was going with them to Kuwait. T did not object to his f| a; doi.n^ so and he went away and I do not know any thing ahou J him up to now. After sometime a one-eyed Baluchi came to me and said that ny friend (Safar N h?u reached Fuwait n '--it I had rerained at Dehai. T sai' , that as my friend had ^one T would also like to jo to Kuv/ait. ^3 said t lat as it was too difficult for one person to travel 'by land from Kuwait to Mecca it was better if I could get a friend so that we may go* to Haj together. I met with a man of Malahar and 'both of us ' ent to the Baluchi, ^e embarked us on a 'boat which left at night tine. # Tn the mornihg • e lid neither see the Baluchi who was with us nor his friend who accompanied us to the 'boat. \fter two day c J we arrived at Vbu '^hahi here v/e disembarked and kept .vith a Persian r :1 o knew to speak Hindustani. 11 e enauired about our case and ve told him that we were Derwishes and intende^ to go to Kuwait and thence to ^aj. '^e informed ua that we had been imported for sale; we told him that we were free born persons. The Shal'h of Ibu Dhabi came to know about us -rcjid sent us 'back tc v 3 'Resiclenoy A^ent^s representative at D-3'bai. T 'be^ tlie Hiji G-over lent kindly to re^atriute me to India. Statement made 'by Alvi son oT Fuhammad an '.nha'bltant oT Calicut or M^la'bar aged alDout 26 years. 'Recorded on ?th Tfh.ll Qadeh 1346 (28-4-23). One year and aij'it aorths age T left :y native nl* ce with the intention of ^oing on pilgri -.ge. T arrived Karachi and from there I proceeded to Meier an :nd thence T sailed 'by a 'boat 'or De'bai here I stayed four onths. At the latter place T met ith TTawazi ^^iya. A one-eyed 'Baluchi came to us and said that he would send us to Kir/ait :.nl- fro i there we v/ould he ahle to jo hy land to Fecoa. T ,7e thanked hi for his favour ind one of his friends accompanied us to the 'boat which left for Abu Dhahi at night time. They landed us there and intended to sell us 'but no one 'boujht us. After a fe days they returned us to Dehai and handea us to the 'Residency Agent's man. I v 'ish to stay at 'Dehai until T get an opportunity to go to ^aj in company with 6he of the Arahs on whom T rely. Statement made 'by 'Rahmat son of Lai ir uh:w:mad o^ Jalgal trih i of Mekran, resident of rT uscat, aged aoout 40 ^ years. Recorded on 7th Dhil-Qadeli 1346. (28-4-28}. 'Four months ago T left Muscat for Basrah with a viev/ to pay a visit to my cousin at Mohammerah hut did not succeed as he had gone to 'B tghdad. I left for Dehai-and stayed for three months with one of my relatives named Abdullah. T o Indians ca.ie to me and sail that they anted t' ve them a hoat to JS/first to Kuwait and 'rc there they rould go- 'by land to Mecca- 1 took them to the shop of Hare on 'bin * Faair and told him that they intendAdto go to Kuv/ait and :.sVed him to jet a 'beat for them, ^e too'' them froi re : ; ,nfi T (3 b not kno\ hat had happene' to them.From - The Residency Agent, Shar^ah. To - The Hon'^ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. No. 236. Dated 16th May 1928. ^ith reference to your letter m O .84, dated the 5th Way 1928, and ttaxtluns the correspondence which were made 'by the Captain of H.M.S. 'Crocus'' a'bout tho t7/o men of Muscat and the Indians, I 'beg to state that I reported the matter to you vide my letter No. 192, dated the 2nd May 1928 enclesing their statements. i am sending the Baluchis with copies of'their statements as well as a copy of your letter 'by the mail steamer to the Political Agent, Muscat. Please send me instructions as to whether I should send the Indians to India or Bushire. 3 i os 9f ■&gt; if? ■No. Hb of 1928. British Sesidenoy and Oonsulate-General, Bushire, the Srd June 1928. 7^ (^) To The Residency Agent, Shargah. With reference to your letter No.236 dated the 16th May 1928, asking for instructions with regard to the ** repatriation of the two Indians, I am directed to inform you that orders have twice 'been sent to you once through the Captain of H.M.S. CJrocus and secondly in our letter No.84 dated the 5th May 1928 to repatriate the Indians to Karachi. Will you therefore have them repatriated to Karachi immediately if you have not already done so, and report to this Hesidency as early as possible that you have done so. / U.S. It Major, Secretary to the Political Resident f . £ in the Persian G-ulf. U^P ■mvt cm (lt.No. 7^ of 1928. Britisli Hesidenoy and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 28tA Norera'ber 1928. To The Eesidency Agent, Shar^ali a.a In continuation of my letter No,116, dated the 3rd June 1928, I am directed to enquire whether you repatriat ed the two Indians to Karachi as ordered. You should hare reported the action taken 'by you at once. 2. The Baluchis Harun 'bin Faqir and Rahnat 'bin Lai Muhammad Zadgali were handed over to the Muscat Govern ment who sentenced them to five and six months imprison- t ment respectively. TT 7 U • Jj • Major, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. \v&gt;^Cc 1 w. ^ r ■ *. 1 Statement o:' 'oula^nan 'bin Ali o... cl a' 1 out 50 a d Ms v/1''e Zcrlcnc toon. Our ancestors (forefathers) came from JasK and settled In 'atinah. , ' f c were 'born '.n .^atinah Tut do not l:nov. T wlich place exactly v.'l v . r ere ' orn. r e reside at '''alaj al C^ubail, near oohar. Jbut \e do not stay in one place and ^always ,:o from place to place' to earn our livelihood. T e had a son named natoo, a^ed aoout 9 years, une di;' ur ^on \.ent out to play in 7c..di ilhas;,rah. ne did not return, ne \r. s stolen 'by the ledums. This happened on th' Gt'i of Id al r.abir (5 years a^oj. /e searched for our * so i. 'fe vent tc Khan 'ih^rqah i d found our Lon with res ah bint Anad. '■e indentified our con. '''e did not jive an alarm. v 'e -rent to ''he Residency A :ent, l-'iarqr h, and asked hlr: to release our son. He replied that tfe should brinrj a letter from th- 'alyuz (Political !&lt;esident)» Ve have now come here and request H.i!.I rt s Consul, ruscat to help us in the recovery of our son. 'Ve are staying in iiatrah care of ''almoor Baluchi telephone peon. ' f e are poor and cannot stay longer* Recorded in this \;ency on JBCth December 1927.- . I k Letter Ko, of tne 213t 'eoGiuugr i iZl from t^e Muscat#. Slavery of ^uwoo boy, a^ed 12 aow # Secy. It la not otear wny the Real- I dency A^ent did nox taxe action when the father reported, to hira aoout tne Doy # A translation of SuXaiman f s statement may be forwarded to tne Residency Agenu witn instructions to recover the boy at once and report resuit to this oirioe,Mitn coj^y to r.A. Muscat? Attached dratt may issue please?*\ I No. 5' of 1928. British Eesidency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 7th January 1928. 3,\o, To The Residency Agent, Shargah. A. 0. I am directed to enclose herewith translation of a statement made 'by Suleiman 'bin Ali at the Muscat /gency with regard to the slavery of his son Matoo, and to enquire the circumstances under which action in this matter was postponed. T7ill also please endeavour to a recover the hoy at once and report the result to this office, at the same time forwarding copy of your letter to the Political Agent, Muscat. U.E. Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. no. ^4- The Residency, Bushire, 5 ^ January 1928. v. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, for information, with reference to his No.1603 of the 21st December last. A/^ Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. c t 1 4 1- The Residency Igent, Sharjah. The 'ijle the Politioal '^esidmt, Persian Cult*. ^ t d .149. Dated 16th April'1228. ' - l n Tith reference to your letter Mo.5, dated the 7th o iiuar v li^d, 3^1 closing a translation or a state ment made v 7 3ul iman 'bin Ali in the ^ourt o.' the Political l^ent, i- ^ re^a}-! to the slavery of his son ?Tatoo v/ho said to ba v.it \ Mesa bint Anad, ^e stated that he has reported i - — er o his son to me hut I did not take any action for his release. - ® l '^3 state that T h'tve neither seen Sul-i lan 'bin Ali nor I Vnow Kesa 'bint An ad. T have done my 'best in recovering Vie 'Baluchi hoys and jirls rvo the Ara'bs -in -i have reported to you -fter having done so. The (Statement made 'by Sul-'lman 'bin \li in the ^cency Muscat is not correct. The Vrahs of the Trucial loast ^ive n:jnes to men such as Kuha mad, Abdullah, Hamad, Hu a.lC., Salim, Sultan, Said and Ahdul Aaiz and to women such as Fatimah, Mary am, Ayshah, TThadiJah, Shamsah, Maimah and Malirah. I have never heard that the Arahs call a v.'cm an Mesah hint Anad. If Sulaiman 'bin Ali cm s^io 1 ' the house of Mesa in any to'.rn of the Trucial ^oast he should-come in order to guide me to the place so that I may take action v/ith the help of the Shaikh of the torn. Sulaiman has not mentioned in his st; tement the tov/n ./here Mesa 'bint Inad is living. T am sending ^ copy of this letter, acco vin^. to your instructions, to the Political *jent, Muscat. op. lvtjl ^//rvcx£&gt; . /b fiji ^ - a . ^ q fa ^ aq p a frn ma C Q qp/II ^1 bt hicraarrtiij .ia- 2®I —From To No.582. The Residency Agent, Shargah. The Hon'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Dated 28th December 1927. n • j • I 'beg to state that on the 7tn December 1927, when I disembarked H.M.S. 11 Biterprise' at Ras ul Khaimah Shaikh Sultan 'bin Salim, Chief of Ras ul Khaimah, informed me about the case of the two Baluchis who left Ras ul Khaimah with the intention of going to Kalba ' f were arrested by the Bedouins at a Ti 11 rurr called Bathn- ah which is a dependency of the Chief of 'Pujairah. T 7hen I went to my home at a village called Muaraiz of Ras ul Khaimah one of the aforementioned Baluchis came to me and made his statement which I beg to forward herewith. Ali bin Saif is a well known person and is the Headman of the Khawater tribe living in the interior of the territory of Ras ul Khaimah and^make traffic to the town of Ras ul Khaimah for the purpose of taking foodstuffs etc. % I wrote a letter No.548, dated 14th Jamadi 11,1346 (9-12-27) to the Shaikh of Ras ul Khaimah as per copy attached for your information and despatched it and the Baluchi with my son to the Shaikh in order to make enquiries about the other Baluchi who was with the Bedouins and endeavour to recover him. His reply in original is forwarded herewith for your information. I sent letter No.550, dated the 16th Jamadi II, 1346 (11-12-27) in reply to the Shaikh as per copy enclosed herewith for your information. 'lis reply in original is forwarded herewith saying that he will come to see me on the subject. In reply I mentioned in my letter No.572, dated the 23rd Jamadi II (18-12-27) that I expe^ A him to come as I intended to leave for Shargah. The c»^^ikh te saying Laat the BedoUj_n nas got a large 36number of followers ana that it would I db advisable if we ui not hurry in the matter and proceecWin a polite manner with them. I pointed out to the Shaikh that if there would 'be further delay in the matter the Baluchi would 'be sold and then it would 'be impossible to recover him. After a long conversation with the Shaikh he at last said that he would consult his 'brother Shaikh Muhammad 'bin Salim and some of the notables of Has ul Khaimah and then inform me of the result. Two days after my verbal conver sation with the Shaikh I received a letter from the Bedouin Ali 'bin Saif which is enclosed herewith in original saying that I should return the Baluchi who^Sf with me to him. I wrote a letter No.573, dated 25th Jamadi IT, 1346 (20-12-27), as per copy attached to the Shaikh of Has ul Khaimah enclosing the Bedouin's letter for his information. The Shaikh's answer to my letter, in original as well as a copy of my reply No.574, dated 26th Jamadi II, (21-12-27) to him are forwarded herewith for your informa tion. T .7hen I noticed that the Shaikh of Has ul Khaimah u &amp; glq not pay attention to recover the Baluchi from the Bedouin and heard that the latter intend;^ to send him to Braimi for sale I asked the Shaikhs of Hemriyyeh and Umm ul Caiwain to come to Has ul Khaimah in order to help me in pressing Shaikh Sultan 'bin Salim to recover the Baluchi. The Shaikh of Umm ul ^aiwain's letter is enclosed herewith saying that he . The two Shaikhs came and did their utmost in the matter and even told the Shaikh of Has ul Khaimah that if the Bedouin J -l A - 1*kjix not return the Baluchi they stape prepared to Join him in fighting the Bedouin Shaikh and his tribesmen. The * Shaikh then sent a messenger to the ^edouin asking him to s send the Baluchi who was with him but he did not agree. The Shaikh of Umm ul Qaiwain sent a messenger to the Bedouin advising him to send the Baluchi otherwise he would break his treaty with him. As soon as he received1 the message he sent the Baluohi with a letter which Is forwarded In original herewith. The statement of Shahbeh hln Shahln Is also enclosed. If the Shaikhs had not come to help me and had not used their Influence, the Baluchi, owing to the carelessness of the Shaikh of Has ul ft Khaimah would not have 'been recovered, Qawasira Shaikhs are very slack and have no sympathy and the Bedouins always kidnap free 'born persons from the interior of their territory 'but they do not punish them (Bedouins) for their nefarious action. I am of opinion subject to your approval that letters may he written to the Qawasim Shaikhs with regard to the activities of the bedouins in their territories. If you have no objection it would also 'be advisable if you write letters to the Shaikhs of T Jmm ul Qaiawain and Hemriyyeh thanking them for their assistance. Statement made 'by Khamis 'bin Ibrahim Baluchi of Sadalch, ruled hy Mir Barkat son of Ahdun Nahl, aged ahout 30 years. Becorded on the 15th Jamadl II, 1346 (10-12-27). Five years ago I went from l!ekran to Shargah and resided there. My cousin Shanbeh and myself were diving for Ali bin Junah of Ajman. ^7e decided to go to Batinah lo visit our relatives at the town of Sowalq,. On the 8uh Jamadl II, (3-12-27) we left Shargah and went to our Nakhuda t-li bin Jumah from whom v/e took Ils.50/ / '~ each in from advance and then proceeded jfcui Ajman to Umm ul Qaiwain. ./e then left ITmm ul Qaiwain for Ras ul Khaimah where we stayed with the Baluchis for four days. We hired tv/o camels from the Mazari* Bedouins who are making traffic to Kalba, (foi the purpose of obtaining their recLuirements) , lei j P.as ul Fhaimah and reached Tadi ^Tam after tv/o days, ^e noticed that a few Bedouins were walking in the valley in front of us. They reached the village of Bathnah a dependency of the Teadman of FujcLirah. At this place aa man came to us and said that it woul'd 'be 'better for us to halt at night time there and take rest, '^e came down our camels and went into a house there. H midnight 15 Bedouins armed with rifles entered the house, captured us and tied our hands with ropes and returned us 'back. In .the morning we found that the Bedouins were those v/hom v/e saw in the ^adi Ham. The Bedouins took us to their camps in the interior of Ras ul Kahimah. I was given to their Headman Ali 'bin Saif M Khateri and Shanhe^.vas given to the other Bedouins. Shanbeh was imprisoned 'but I was free.- After two days I got an opportunity and escaped from the house of the Headman of the Bedouins and after great difficulty I reached Eas ul Khaimah where I took refuge in the house of Shaikh Sultan 'bin Salim, CJhief of Has ul Khaimah. I wanted to see the Shaikh 'but I did not succeed. His servant Sorur sent a man with me who showed me the house of K.B. Isa 'bin Vbdul Latif at A1 Muairidh. Te are free 'born persons and not slaves. I 'beg H.B.M's Government to release my cousin from the Bedouins. Letter No.548, dated the 14th Jamadi II, 1346 (9-12-27) from the Residency Agent, Shargah, to Shaikh Sultan 'bin Salim, CJhief of Ras ul Khaimah. A ^ I 'beg to state that yesterday when we disembarked 'Enterprise' you informed me ahout the case of the Baluchis who left your town Ras ul Khaimah with the intention of going to Karba 'but were arrested 'by Ali 'bin Saif the Headman of the Khawater Bedouins at the village of Bathnah a dependency of the Shaikh of 'Pujairah. TJhen I went home I found one of the Baluchis has run away and has come to my house. The Baluchi informed me that his cousin lafdj Shanbeh 'bin Shahin i-&amp; still in the prison of Ali 'bin Saif and that on his arrival at Ras ul Khaimah he wanted to seeyou in order to represent his matter to you 'but he ale! not succeed. Your servant Sorur sent a man with him v/ho 'brought him to my house. I am sending the Baluchi to you * with my son so that you may hear his case 5nd I hope that you will do your 'best to recover the other Baluchi 'because arresting free 'born persons and selling them is against humanity. I trust you v/ill take the necessary action 'before 11 i 'bin Saif will 'be a'ble to sell the Baluchi. I await your reifcly. Letter undated from Shaikh Sultan 'bin Salim, C?hief of Ras ul Khaimah, to the Residency Agent, Shargah. A. 0 • I have received your esteemed letter and the message which you sent me through your son Said. I am taking the necessary action and your son Said has 'become aware ahout the matter. '^Te will acquaint you with the facts• A.C. Letter dated 16th Jamadi II, (11-12-27) No.550, from the H.A., Shargah, to the Shaikh of Has ul Khaimah. I received your esteemed letter 'but could not under stand anything from it. You had mentioned that my son would inform me ahout the case. My friend I have written you an official letter ahout this case as you are one of the Shaikhs who hafe got treaties with H.B.M's Government and such matters are also included in the treaties. Ky son informed me what you had told him verbally and I hope that you will do the needful in the matter. Ali 'bin Saif, Headman of the Khawater trihe, is resid ing in your territory, Eas ul Khaimah, and your connivance is not advisable. You know that the Hon'hle the Political I Resident writes always to all the Shaikhs of the Trucial Ooast to prevent the people who deal in slaves The actionof the Bedouins who are living in your side in arresting free 'born persons for sale is very undesirable and the Hon'tile the Political Resident will 'be displeased with you. I hope you will make every endeavour to recover the Baluchi from Ali 'bin Saif as soon as possible. Extract from letter undated from the 'Thief of Has ul Khaimah, to the Residency Agent, Shargah. x xxx As regards Mi 'bin Saif I will inshallah call on you and then we will discuss the matter.. Letter No.572, dated the 23rd Jamadi II, 1346 (18-12-27) from the Residency Agent, Shargah, to Shaikh Sultan 'bin Salim, Chief of Ras ul Khaimah. A. C. I received your letter intimating that you will 'come to see me in order to discuss the matter of Ali 'bin Saif A1 Khateri, I am awaiting your arrival as I intend to leave for Shargah. I.etter No. 573, dated the 25th Jamadi II, 1346 (20-12-27) from the R.A., Shargah, to the Chief of Ras ul Kliaimah. A. C. I teg to inform you that I have today received a letter from Ali 'bin Saif, Headman of the A1 Khawater Bedouin trihe, with whom the Baluchi is, demanding the Baluchi who is with me and enquiring whether I or you have kept the Baluchi 'because he thinks that our doing so is not according to justice. This is a strange thing, ^e are demanding the Baluchi from him and he is asking us to send him the Baluchi who is with us. Ali 'bin Saif isa proud man and I understand that the letter has iDeen written in your Island Za'atu T have nothing to do with the Bedouin hut I am addressing you as a ^ief who is in treaty with H.-R.W's Oovernment. Please peruse the enclosed letter and return and let me know of your views on the subject. Letter dated 21st Jamadi II, 1346 (16-12-27) from Ali Mn Sail: A1 Khateri, to the e.a., Shargah. A As regards my slave I teg to state that he has heen prevented to oome to me and do not know who has done so as I see that this has been against Justice. Please explain to me. I hope you will help in the matter of the one who is with you. I have asked xi Sultan hin Salim to communicate with you on the subject. I expect to receive your early answer. I hope you will not reproach me for anyt'iing which may happen between me and Sultan. / Letter dated 23rd Jamadi II, 1346 (18-12-27) from Shaikh Sultan hm Salim, Chief of Has ul Khaimah, to the R.'. Shargah. '{| I received your letter and was acquainted with its contents. As regards Ali hin Saif who is taking your permission to act against me I 'beg to state that if I desire punishment it is due to the fact that the slave took refuge at the Government House and you are aware ahout tHie matter. Letter Mo.574, dated the 26th Jamadi II, 1346 (21-12-27) Prom the Residency Agent, Shargah, to the CJhief of fes ul Khaimah.m* 8 \.G. I have received your esteemed letter intimating that Ali 'bin Saif intends to harm you on account of the Baluchi who has taken refuge at the Government House. You have not demanded the Baluchi who is with Mi 'bin Saif. Perhaps you have informed Ali 'bin Saif of the Khawater tri'be that the Baluchi has taken refuge with me in consequence of which he has written to me on the subject. I shall give shelter in my house to any Baluchi who has 'been kidnapped and it is my duty to do so, 'but owing to your carelessness the Bedouins always commit mischief and arrest Baluchis on the road and sell them at Braimi which act is not advisable. It is incumbent upon you to check every mischief- maker^. Ali 'bin Saif is a well known person and has got I date plantation at the village of Dhaid which was given to Shaikh Khalid 'bin Ahmad. Owing to the intrigues of Ali 'bin hi ^aif the village of Dhaid was taken from your cousin. In any case I want you to recover the Baluchi as you are a CJhief and responsible for all circumstances. If you procrastinate in the matter I will be obliged to report the matter to the Hon'ble the Political Resident. Letter dated 28th Jamadi II, 1346 (23-12-27) from Shaikh Hamad bin Ibrahim, CJhief of Umm ul Qaiwain, to the R.A., Shargah. |4F A. 0. I have received your letter and was pleased to know about the good news of your welfare and was acctuainted with its contents. As desired I will with much pleasure come to see you and will leave my place on Satuday. I have also informed Shaikh Abdur Rahman. Letter dated 3rd Rajab 1346 (28-12-27) from Ali bin Saif, to the Residency Agent, Shargah. A. 0I am sending you the Baluchi who came to our side. There is nothing 'between us and all my followers are yours and we should all 'be considered your own family. T7e are ohediont to your orders and we are under your protection. Te will not disohey you. I have 'been informed that the Shaikhs of the CJoast intend to move against me. G-od is aware th^t there is nothing 'betv/een us and God is against the aggressors. Bin Tasim will acqtuaint you with the facts. Statement made hy Shamheh hin Shahin Baluchi of Karawan ruled 'by Islam Khan, aged ahout 35 years. Recorded on the 4th Rajah 1346 (29-12-27). Since the last 8 years I was residing at Shargah and was diving in the hoat of Ali 'bin Jumah of AJman. My wife and children went to Khahurah of Batinah to spend the summer season there and I went to diving. As I did not find my family at Shargah when I returned from diving, I arranged with my cousin Khamis 'bin Ibrahim, to go to Khahurah in order to bring them 'back. Vfe went to our Nakhuda at Ajman and took Rs.50/- each from him and left for Uram ul Qaiwain tiienoe uo Ras ul Khaimah. ^Ve stayed four days at Has ul Khaimah with a view to get a sailing 'boat to go to Batinah 'but did not get one. Ttr e decided to go 'by land from Ras ul Khaimah to Kalha and thence to Batinah and so v/e hired two camels from the Mazari Bedouins who are making traffic to Kalha. In the morning we left Ras ul Khaimah and arrived at '/adi Ham which is on the way to Kalha. Te saw that a few Bedouins entered the Tadi 'before us and 'before our arrival at the village of Bathnah we noticed that the Bedouins had closed the way. They at once arrested us and 'beat the Bedouin who was with us, tied our hands with rope and 'brought us 'back. In the morning we found ourselves at the camp of tiie Bedouins who are living in the interior of Ras ul Khaimah. I was imprisoned hut Khamis was set free.rue Bedouins gathered together and divided us. I was given to the Bedouins and Khainis was taken 'by their Headman, Ali 'bin Saif. Khamis run away at night time after three days rom the house or the headman. They went in pursuit of Khamis 'but did not oatch him. They returned after two days and informed their Headman that Khamis had gone to the house of the Residency Agent at Has ul Khaimah. The Headman gathered the Bedouins and consulted with them that he would go at night time to the house of the Residency Agent and se r v a n t s kidnap some of his servants or/of the subjects of the Shaikh of Ras ul Khaimah. The -^edouins did not approve of his opinion. News was then received that the Shaikh of Umm ul Caiwain has come to see the Residency 'gent at Ras ul Khaimah. ^he Bedouins told their Headman that it would 'be very advisable if the Baluchi he sent to the Residency Agent. TThen the Headman heard this he released and sent me to the Residency Agent at Ras ul Khaimah. The statement was made in my presence. Sd. &amp; Sid. K.B. Isa 'bin Ahdul Latif.No. 3 5' of 1928. British T^esidenoy and Consulate G-eneral, 'Bushire, the Z-fTZ February 1928. v '^L To The (Thief of Umm -ul-Qaiwain Hemri3 r yeh. An • J * L I was ^lad to hear from the Presidency Agent, Shar^ah, of your v/elfare and of the help you gave in the recovery of the Baluoh Shambeh 'bin Shahin who had 'been detained 'by Ml 'bin Saif A1 Khateri. Please accept my thanks for % your trouble, and I hope you will continue to give your support in suppressing slavery as far as possible. U.S. t Lt-Colonel Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ^6 V '/cT - ^ ^ ^^ es, ^ u ^ 1. r' V - ' ' J &lt; , , ■ r &gt;-- u tMJ' ?_ _______ No. 3(, of 1928. British 'Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Busiiire, the 2-7February 1928. The Chief of Has ul Khaimah. A.O. • 0 I have received a report from the Eesidency Agent, Shar^ah, with regard to the Baluoh Shamheh hin Shahin who had' 'been detained 'by Ali 'bin Saif A1 Khateri. It appears you did not take sufficient energetic action to save this man from slavery. The Governments of the world are much interested in the question of slavery and the stopping of the sale of (Tod # s creatures and it is against the teaching of the Koran also that Muslims should sell a Muslim into slavery, so I write and impress upon you the necessity of your abiding 'by the terms of your treaty in this respect, and hope that no such instances will take place in future within your Jurisdiction. I shall 'be glad to receive your assurances in this respect. U.E. Lt-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. c.j Ul ^ ^ • s y * i (s . c , -fili _ | ■ MMNo. 3^ of 1928. British Residenoy and Consulate General, Bushire, the 2-7^ 'Pe'bruary 1928. rp The Chief of Shargah, k.n. i enclose herewith oopy of a letter written 'by me to the Chief of Has ul Khaimah with regard to the slavery within his jurisdiction. I hope that you yourself in your own jurisdiction are doin^ your 'best to check slavery as far as possible. U.S. Lt-Oolonel, Political Resident in the Persian Culf» c ^js Ail 11 No. 3 ^ of 1928. British Residency and Consulate-^eneral, Bushire, the February 1928. To The Hesidency Agent, Chargah A.O. c I have read with interest/your report No.582 of the 28th Deoemher last with regard to the recovery or the Baluoh Shamheh 'bin Chahin. 2. T send herewith letters addressed to the CJhiefs of T Jmm-ul-Q.aiwain, Hemriyyeh, Shargah and Has-ul-Khaimah; please arrange to have them delivered to the addressees U.'B. . Lfi Lt-r?olonel, Political 'Resident in the Persian Gulf. \ r -i ^rb^c) 'N/r- No.944/10/2.A. Of 1988. iirltish Agency &amp; Consulate, Bandar A'bl&gt;as, t^e 21st June 1928* ■r ■y *Sa - f\ \jp .y tVc(c-. To Tho Secretary to the Hon^lo tiie Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Busnire. iimarmtpm . I forward herewitii a copy of the statement of a slave 71R00Z bin jOWHAB of fekran ( Persian Baluchistan) who recently sought asylum at this Consulate and has since 'boon manumitted 'by the local authorities 2 # The freed slave Firooz requests that action may he taken for the release of his wife and children who are said to he with his late master Ismail hin Mubarak at G-URFA ( Batneh coast)* 3. Would you kindly request the Residency Agent at SHARGAH to take such action as may be possible, to restore FIROOZ'S wife and children. H.B.M^s uonsul and Assi ^.R e s i d e n t. to the M.A.S.£\ Statonont of FIROOZ tin JOWHAR of Mokran.Birth place Caravan (Persian Baluchistan) nano of mstor ismll tin »ful»rak of Giiurfa ( Batnoh) ajjo 45 yoarc. 'Rocordod on 7-6-1928# I was 'bom in tho house of my master '^alcksha it Caravan. ?hon I was a'bout 20 yoarc old my master ''aloksi^aj took me to Batneh and sold mo to my mresont master Ismail tin Mubarak. T married at Batneh and have had 8 children. I was serving my master as a Oardenor and my wife and children as servants at his house. I have 'boon serving this man for the past 25 years 'but recret to say that I my wife and children have 'been always ill-trented 'by him and no proper food supported to us. 1 Alxjut throe months ago, I loft my wife and children in the hou^o of my aforesaid master and escaped porsonall; to Shargah with a view to conmlain to issa Pin Abdul Lati Put unfortunitly Issa was not there. I then embarked in a Dhow with a view to come to Bandar Abbas, but I was transfered from one boat to anothi till I obtained a boat -'hich was riroceedinc to Hurmuz Island. Yesterday I arrived at Hurmusc and obtained a Jo 11; boat and have now come to bandar Abbas to complaint to n.B.'f's Consul i»o release me from all these difficulties md to grant mo my freedom and release my wife and children from tiio hand of my master Ismail so tliat no -body will interfere in our affairs in future. ooOoo--No. /V/ of 1928. British Eesidenoy and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 15th July 1928. To The Residency Agent, Shargah. A. ^ I am directed to forward herewith translation of a statement made 'by a slave Firooz 'bin Jowhar of Mekran who has taken refuge at Bandar Ahhas praying for the release of his wife and children who are said to 'be with his late master Ismail 'bin Muharak at G-urfa fBatinah) Please make enquiries in-'to this case, and if found correct, use your influence towards the recovery of his wife and children and report result to this office at an early date. U.E. kr Major, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.J'rom - The Residency xlgent, Shargah. To - Tlie Hon'TDle the Political *esilent, Persian Oulf No.465. Dated 19th SeptemlDer 1928. A. 0. T7ith reference to your letter No. 141 dated l r th July 1928 with its enclosure - a translation of a st'^teTient m^de 'by '^irooz 'bin Jowhar v/ho has taken refuge at H.'B.M's Consulate, bandar ihhas stating that his master Ismail 'bin TTubaralc is in Ghurfah f^atinah) and his wife and children are with his said master and praying for their release, I 'beg to state that I made enquiries ahout Ismail Mn Mu'barak in Ghurfah whi6h is close to Diha -Hi ilso in the Ghurfah rhich is a dependency of Fujairah, hut I could not ^trace him in these two places. If he is in the Ghurfah of Batinah, it 'belongs to the Sultan of Muscat. I am therefore of the opinion that the said Firooz should come here to identify the Ghurfrh ^nd to point out as to its locality under this Residency Vgency, necessary action can 'be taken and result notified to you.Mo. zior Of 1928• British itosidenoy &amp; (jonsuilate^cneral# / tl jsuahtra, the ^ovoniber 1928« To The jt &gt;oiltioal Agent &amp; H.B .lTs Uonsul, M us o a t* Memorandum&gt; I am dtreoted to forward to you therewith, the wife and children of slave Firuze Mn Jowher, who ire said to he with one Ismail ^in jsuharak of Qurfa (aitinah), for enciuii^r and report# Oopy of this aeworandum is heing sent to His Britannic Majesty^ Oonsul and ^jBsiatant to the Resident, Bandar Ahhas* By order, Or MaJ or 9 secretary to the jeolitioal Kesident Of(t in tie Persian uulf. the m^irginally noted letters on the subject of !• Letter !iO*944/10/2-A dated the Slst June 1928 from n.B.J ^s uonsul, Bitndar Ah Das to the Kesidenoy, mshire. 2» Letter rio* 46$ dated the 19th aepteri ^er 1928 to the i&gt;olitioal Resident, i^ersian Gulf# Oopy of the foregoing memorandum is forwarded to His Britannic Majesty's Consul and Assistant to the Resident, Bandar Ah has, for information.OFFICE NOTES. 35 Memorandum No»944/10/2.A«&gt; dated the 21st June 1928, from H.B.M's Consul and Assistant to the Resident, Bandar AlDhas. He. wife and children of slave Firooz/bin Jowhar of Mekran who are said to 'be with Ismail tin Mubarak of Gurfa (Batineh). S eoy « Translation of the statement made 'by Tirooz may 'be sent to E.A., Shargah, asking him to use his influenc for the restoration of Firooz^ wife and children*^ Draft letter submitted for approval please. ♦ 4-7-28. ic n . 7^.1 j ^ — 1 /Yo. ftf-/ ^ • 7* &gt;/• ' : 7' Letter NO. 465 dated the 19th September 1928 from the Residency Agent,Sha»qah. Ghurfah Replies that he can not locate &amp;Kstxa±fstkx where the master of the slave is said to 'be and suggests that the place may be under the jurisdiction of H.H. i the Sultan of Muscat, j ———' May forward forward R .A.'s letter together with i Consul &gt; Bandar Abbas 1 s letter Ho.i above,to the P.A. Muscat for enquiry and report, and the endorsement may be repeated to Consul,Bandar Abbas ? f7).QNo.1712/10/2 of 1927. British Agency &amp; Consulate, Bandar AlD'bas, Deceinber 21,1927. The Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. LIEMOBAITDIILI . I forward for the information of the Hon^hle the Political Resident a copy of enclosed correspondence received from the Consular A ^e ^t in record to the ahduction of an Indian Lad named Ram Singh, son of Jagan Singh 'by a certain Shanudh oin Hussain„ / 2. In the meantime, I am instructing trie Consular Agent to press for exemplary punishment should the alleged offence he brought home to the individual Shanheh, andalso to take steps to prevenu him from interfering with the 'boy. Assistant Rpsident-^f^i.i3. f s Consul Bandar Ahh '-S. A. J • D •Statement or Hamsingti son of Jagansingh now known as Aodull .h 'born at NANDEL• Date of 'birth not known, how lives in Mat Hut near the Telegraph q .u^rturs with Shanheh 'bin Hassan. Appearance an Indian. Age VL ahout 15 years. Recored on the 15th Decemher 1927. I was 'born at Nandel and when 7 years old I went to Bombay with a Gruzjer named Velji, father's name not known, and worked for Velji for 7 days in Bombay. One ^y, I met Shanbeh in Bombay near the docks (probably Victoria Docks or Carnac Bunder) Shanbeh asked me to go with him I went with him and worked for him for one month in Bombay, then he took me by sailing vessel to a place Cochin, I' .labar, there Shabeh clr-nged vessels and ^ came by_s iling vessel to Lingah. I was with him all the time, since then I have lived with Shanbeh. I used to y/ork and Shanbeh used to take ^ 11 my money. He used to beat me. One night last year Shanbeh came to me and wanted to sleep with me I complained to Shanbeh*s mother nd said I would report the m: tter to the Doctor nd she toll me not to do so nd that such thing would not happen again if he did I could report the m tter. I used go hungry 3 or 4 days bee :.sue Shmbeh was unable to feed me. One day Shanbeh's brother was V ken to the lockup :.nd I was to have been given as security to one man for Rs.10/- but the man refused, then He went to Nakhuda, Haji Abdullah bin Marhun and took loan of Rs.50/- on my name and informed Haji Abdullah that I will -o nd dive for pearls for him. I refused to dive and st-ted that I was willing to do boat work only. Last year Haji Abdullah took me to Jazirat-u-Sheikh(Island) there I worked for him for 4 or 5 months, then I returned and became a servant to Haji Abbas Ali the merchant. I servec him for 45 days and I left him; then I worked with Hali Abdullah's son named Kakee for 3 months; then I took service with Mr.ITagee, then after 13 d ys I left and took service with the IDriver with whom I have been for 4 or 5 months. I do not wish to stay here because Shanbeh is beating me every day. All the money I ^et he gambles aw y. flight before last I did not go to Sh nbeh• house and slept at the Drivers pi ce and at about 11 O'clock Shanbeh came for me and ; sked me why I h d not come home I said I was not going home, then'he w'nted to strikto me aith a noop iron. The Driver stopped him. I '.vent t) Pir T 3 ax aao told me to go to sleep and that he vould take me to Doctor in the morning. As Per bax lid not turn up I d d not come yesterday.3 1 Copy of letter No.640 dated the 14th December 1927 from the British Consular Agent ,Lingah to aovernor, Ling h. After compliments, I am obliged to 'bring to your notice the f oilowing incident. A 'british Indian named Ramsingh son ox Jag-.singh now called Abdullah, was ahducted 'by one ohanbch oin Hassan in Bombay about 6 or 7 years a.^o and brought to Lingah to serve Shanbeh as a slave. T]iio repiehensible practice of abducting children for ^xe purpose of slavery is, I am sure abhorent to you, ^ill please make full inquiries and punish the man Shanbeh severely should he be found guilty and please let me know wh;, t action has been taken. 0 q 0/ No.99 of ±923. •^ritioh Residency it Consiilate-^eneral, iiu«hire, the ^7th oi nuary i928. To 'i.B.]*' s Consul, - Bf?ndar bbas. / 1 enpra^urat 1 am directed to acknowledge receipt of your Memorandum Uo. l74r2/ir/2 dated the 21 st ecember 1927, 'ith reg- rd to abduction of lam Singh » by Wianbeh, and to inform you that the Governor of Gulf -^orts has also been addressed by this office on the subject. 2* -'oes the boy know anything rbout his parents and has he shown any inclination to return to -'.ndia? Il so he may be sent back to Bombay alter the enquiry is finished, and the Commissioner of 'olice, Bombay, informed of the f?cts t and of the boy 1 s depar ure. By order. Captain, secretary to the olitical Resident in the Persirn Gulf.i lb ■ ' 1 * 1? * Th ' 3 Oover nor of the Gulf P 0 rts, Bushire. | T ' 1 ' T ' on '^le 't-Colonel L. Haworth, f 'I.B.H's Consul General |or Fars, etc. J 'o.1848. Dated 1st Isfand 1306 (21-2-28). T have^e honour to state that on receipt of your J' *' ■' &lt;?1 '-■ 1S &gt; 7 the necessary steps on the suh.Ject I arw now T 'beg to forward herewith a copy of the cross- sxariU.nation v /'ilch the Boputy Governor, Lingah, had made J 1 tVlG - resence or the 'unshl of the Consular Agency. 9 - ^_ nation o uh.an'beh son of Hasaii) A.'b'bas I dated 23rd A.3ar 1306 (15-12-28). ^ What is yours and your father's name? Ky name is Shanheh, my father's is Hasan Ahhas ^ Kaoahi. T am a seaman and aged 40 years. I am a Miami ad an and a Persian subject. Q. ^an you read and write and have you got a seal^ I oannot read and write and have no seal. TTrvj . Jangi Singh I h ,. wha is the oase of Ah dull ah son of who has j complained against you 0 ^xpla-in. , T was formerly a -e-pe#. A few years ago I was scjju* employed as a or&amp;x in a 'boat hy which T proceeded to 'Bombay. T disembarked the 'boat &gt;t that place and employed myself as a fireman at P.s.18/- per mensem in one of the P. &amp; 0. Vessels. Afterwards I got a J oh in an Italian ship at 40 Francs per mensem and continued my services on the 'boat which was travelling between India and England for about 10 to 12 years. I have worked in all European | ships. 7 years ago I disembarked the ship at Bombay where I worked as a coolie. One day while I was walking I in the street of Bombay this boy who was begging in the streets asked me to take him with myself and look after I him. As he was a poor and had no one to look after him I kept him with myself for the sake of Gk)d. ^hen IR-./&lt; i wanted to return l^aclc to my native place the 'boy insisted' upon me to take him also and consider him as my own son and in return he would render service to me if he would 'be '•^'ble to do so. ^e 'both embarked a 'boat of Cutch which sailed for Charak where we disembarked and went to Lingah 'by land. The 'boy, Abdullah, has 'been with me since the last 7 years and have 'been supporting him v /ith all his requirements. Ke has now obtained a job and. has complained against me. I am a T)oor man and have no wife and children I used to spend on hi i and myself whatever I was earning. I have brjught him up since childhood but they have taken • him from me at a time when he should provide me. For the sake of God either return him to me or get whatever that I had spent on him refunded to me. Q* HoUJ much did you spend on him* K* I have spent whatever that I was getting during the last 7 years on him and'! have nothing now. dross 'Sxamination of Abdullah son of Jangi Singh lat d 25th JLzar 1306 (17-12-28). / / Q. What is your name and surname 9 Jangi Singh. A. I£y name is Abdullah and my father's is I am ori-inally from Nander and Hyderabad, now residing at Sabah' quarter of Lingah. I am aged 12 years, Muhammadan, British subject. I am serving the British Telegraph ^ Office and can read and write Marati. Q,. Taat is your case? Explain the matter. A. 7 years a^o I was at Bombay -nd walking about when I met with a certain Shanbeh who asked what I was doing. 1 told him that I was walking, '^e asked me whether I had any parent and in reply I' said that my parents were not there, '^e asked me to go with him and T accompanied him and stayed for more than one month in Bombay and was working, at that place. Shanbeh then found a Nakhuda for himself nd told me that he was leavins that )lace andT snould go with him. I agreed and went with him to Karaohi v /here we discharged the cargo of the 'oat //hioo. was salt. ^Te settled his account ulth that i i'-ia an.j employed himself with -mother one who left that olace at midnight. Shanheh was a and I was a hoy. ^e disemba rked at Bostaneh whence we proceeded to Lingah hy land. Q. Hov/ many years a^o you put up with tais man -nd siucj when? A. Since the last 7 years. Q,. 7ere you with him during the period of 7 years continually and did not go any where 9 Yes. Tio was paying your expendture' A. Shanheh was paying my expenditure and T was also working myself• What was u|ie reason that you left him 9 A. One ni^ht as it was rainy I slept in the house or the engineer of the 'British. Telegraph '^eaprtment. It 11 o.in. Shanheh who had a tin v /ith him came to the Engineer's, house and aslced why T was not going home. I saiJ I not want to go home as it was rainy and I would get wet. As soon as I said so he got wild and wanted to 'beat me. I asked the engineer to hear evidence as he wanted to heat me without any cause. The engineer cau-ht his hand and asked me to tell him the case. I told him that I was not Shanbeh*s son. Last year T was asleep one ni^ht when at midnight Shanheh took off my lungi and shirt. I did not say anything as then was night. In the morning I informed his mother of his action hut she asked me to^ forgive him this time and he would not commit such an act next time. Q,. T7ere you with him throughout the 7 years or left him for sometime? A. I was all the time with him and did not leave him. Gross Examination of Shanheh son of Hasan Ahhas, dated 26th Aaar 1306 (18-12-28)•0. Bxplain your name and surname. I n A. My name is Shanbeh son of Hasan A'b'bas Ka'baT3i. I am a araw and Persian subject. rJan you read and write and have you got a seal 0 I have not gqne to school. I am a o-iwv and have no seal Jangi Singh Ahdullah son of was summoned yesterday and was asked some iiuestions. He stated that last year at midnight you went to him 'and had a 'bad intention in mind about him. Is tills true or not 9 'Explain the matter in full. A. God forbid, I never had any had intention. T was considering him as my son. T adopted him as my son since childhood. They have taught him to aay such words in order to take him from me otherwise why he did not say such things 'before. Now that he wants to leave me he says such words. T hL.vo no tiling to say ir he wants to go away hut I only request that, the money which I had spent on him during my poverty and hardship may he recovered from him and paid to me.&gt;/ No. 104/10/2 (Special) British Age:cy &amp; Cona:late, Bandar AtTbas. Dated at Lingah, the 21st March 28. To The Secretary to the Hon , 'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. MEMORANIXJM . ) ' 1 Reference correspondence ending with my Memorandum No.284/10/2 dated the 28th February 1928. 2. I infer from the Consular Agent that no action has 'been taken against Shamheh, who is alleged to have kidnapped the hoy Ram Singh. The Governor has informed him that he would submit his report on the instructions received 'by him in regard to this case direct to the Governor of the Gulf Ports at Bushire. ' 3. I have personally seen the lad who on my questioning him expressed a wish to return to India. He stated that NANDEL, his native place was in the Poena district. H.B.M's Consul &amp; Assistant^t Resident.- ^ o thel«o• ( d &amp; 1 1 '2 • British Hesidency 6c Conoulate-General, Bushire, the April 1923. To H.M's Consul &amp; i-soistant to the Resident, Bandar Abhao. I emorandum. Reference correspondence ending with your Lo.104/10/ /2 (Special) dated the 21st ] arch 1928. 1 am directed to ask you to explain to the Consular Agent at Lin-ah that the ground we £0 on is not that slavery must be abhorrent to the Governor but that ander Treaty the import of slaves is foroidden. - tiic oxfice vill therefore await your further comwunication on the subject. By order, w Captain, Secretary to the Political .lesident in the ^ersian Gulf.f • 2-6 y. ij ■ ■ % No. 942/10/2. British Agency &amp; Consulate, B jidar AWas, June 21, 1923. To The Secret .ry to the Hon'hie th^ Political Eesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. iie.the kidnapped Indian lad -Ham Singh. Reference your Memorandum No.637 d;-ted the 13th April 1923. 2. The Consular Agent w ,s duly Instructed in the sense of the second paragraph thereof. 3. I enquired further into this c.ise on my recent visit to Lingah. In spite of Dr.Hill's iSurthor represent .tions to the Governor on the subject, .'bctK of;rici?.lly and personally, no steps whatever have 'been taken to punish the m n Shambeh. I found during uy short st „y in Lingah that there was nohody in charge of the dministration, .s the 1 Deputy Governor had departed for Butnire - ithcut pen i»s- ion and without making any arrangements for the perform ance of his dutiya during his absence. 4. As no useful purpose will he served hy further correspondence with the local officials at Lingah I would venture to surest that the matter he reported to higher authority at Bushire. The inattention of the Deputy Governor nd hisU| his utter disregard of the instructions conveyed to lilm from the Governor of the Gulf Ports in regard to this case may he hrou ht prominently to notice.No. ^' ^ of 1928. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 22nd July 1 j 28. To His ajeety 's Gonaul and AsBistant to the Resident, Bandar Abbas (at Karachi). I.emorandunu ^ ^ Your I.tsmp rand urn Ko*94fe/10/2 dated the 21st June i928» I am directed by the Hon 'ble the Political Keoident in tiie Persian Gull* to enquire what hcis, in the meanti me, liappened to the Indian boy Ram 3ingh, Is he still with ahambah or has been repatriated as desired by him? If he has not been repatriated, is there any reason why the Consular ^gent, Lingah, should not repatriate hiia at once? As the boy, who is obviously an Indian, demands this, there appears no reason why his wish should not be gratified. The danger of keeoing the boy at Lingah pending the Persian Governments enquiry as to whether they consider Shambah guilty or not of abduction is obvious. Probably the Persians will never decide this question, at any rate the chances of their doing some thing seem very far distant at present. The man Shanbah wants to keep the boy and will move ] heaven and earth to keep him. It is our duty to save the boy and 'get at' the man later if we can through the Persian authorities. iieply very urgently. Lla j o r, Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf# ofe fanTo British Agency &amp; Consulate, Bandar AtTbas. Dated at Karachi, the 27th July 1928 The Secretary to the Hon'hle the Political ^Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. MEMORANDUM. Reference your Memorandum No.^380 dated the 22nd July 1928. I infer that the lad Ram Singh was living in the house of the Engine Driver employed at the Radio Station at Lingah, also an Indian. The Consular Agent is now 'being directed to send the 'boy in charge of the Commander of one of the British India Slow mail steamers to the Commission er of Police at Bombay for disposal and to furnish that Officer with the facts of his case. A. J.D. His Britannic Majes^r^s. Consul and Assistant^jte^fhe Resident. ( on recess at Karachi ).^7. 0 4 ^ 1. 5 No. lll (3peGial). Dated St Karachi, the 31st Aug. 1928. British Agency &amp; Oonsulate, Bandar AtTbas. ^V^g/AN GO^S a The Secretary to the Political Resident, B U S H I a E . MSMORAKDUK . ^ • t / 'Reference my letter No.18(Special) dated the 27th July last. I have to report that the lad. Ram .Singh arrived here from Lingah in the S.S. 'Bajidra' on the 27th instant and was taken charge of 'by the Police authorities at my recuest. The facts of his case had in the mean time, 'been submitted 'by the Consular Agent to the District Magistrate, Karachi. I infer that 'both the Police and the General Secretary of the local ARYA SAMAJ who is interested in the 'boy, have 'been for some time past, engaged in making enciuiries with t he view to trace the whereabouts of his people, and that he will 'be sent on to Bombay shortly. * i His Britannic Majesty•s^tfcnsul and Assistant to the'^Resident, Bandar. Ah Das. recess at Karachi) . :yb ,(( vS llo./370ar 1928. l J ®litical .^ency and H. B. T-'s Consulate, Lluacat, the / 7M HoYeiaber 1928. '1 To The Secretary to the Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire&gt; lueinorandiaa* -» 1 forward, herewith, copies of the marginally — correapondence re^ardin^ the deceased Abeid bin Letter Ko. 7b1/119/28 dated Ist# August 1928, from) the Administrator-General, Zanzibar. )Baid and his sister ) Letter to Council tf Ministers to Hib Ilighnees the )Sunnurah bint Zaid Sultan of Liuscat and Oman, Luscat, Ho. 1058 dated- 7 11th September 1928, from Political Agent, Muscat .said to have been Letter Ho. 108 dated 10th HelPtmber 1928 from the ^kidnapped about 17 Council of Minister® to the Political Agent, ) Muscat, with enclosures* jycars ago and now in Shargah. I request that t.he Residency Agent, Shargah, may be asked to search for Sunnurah bint Zaid and if found her/ whereabouts may be intimated to me for communica tion to the Administrator-General, Zanzibar. i k rh J-ajor, 3», !\r i&lt;j\ ^&gt;1 Political ^\gent and Consul, ITuacat. 2 - xei&amp;a. ^ ^4 received \0 34^0 2%, |l,If'1 Copy ©f ai letter H#* 751/119/28 d^ted the iwo. August 1928, from the Administrator-General, Zanzibar, to the Political Agent, ruscat. I have the honour to inform you that the auove-naned deceased died at Halindi in Zanzibar town on or about the 23rd. June 1928 leaving movable and iiiimovable property It has been reported to me that the deceased has left a sister who is residing at 'tfuslimat V/adi Hawuli', Muscat, and is kn^wn to tiheikh jsasor bin i^halfan bin iUei el r.av;uli of ''Tharamid Tadi nawuli iJarke', Abdulazjz bin nohamed and ) jfithamed bin «tiif bin 8aleh Zamili botVof ruslimat. In the circumstances i shall be obliged if you will kindly cause enquiries to be made and let mo know if the alleged sister or any other heirs of the deceased can be traced at the address given above and if so shall be glad to know their names and relationship* If the sister died after the above deceased, i shall be interested to know the names and relationship ol her re Abeid bin iiaid khadim Kaya binti xaaellem bin nasud el jv '.awulia, deceased. heirs £££££££££££&amp;£&lt;£v Copy of a litter Ilo. 1058 dated the 11th Septeuber 1928, fr«m the Political Agent and H.B.H 'fc Consul, liuicat, to the Council of Hinifeteru to Ilia Hi^hne«» the Sultan of H ub cat and Oman, Huge at. mmmmm After cirapliemnts. I have the honour to forward herewith tranolation of a letter flo. 751/119/28 dated 1st. August 1928, from tne Adminiatrator-rJeneral, Zanzibar regarding Abe id bin Zaid Khadim Raya binti ITeellem bin Tiasud el Hawulia ^vho died at Malindi in Zanzibar on or about the 23rd. June 1928 leaving mivable and irmnovable property. T shall be obliged if you will kindly inform me whether any of the heirs mentioned are in lUiscat. This is what had to be said end may you be preserved. . aCepy of trknelation of a letter 7T o. 10r c: ted lOtii ov- rb^r 1''28, from the Cciuncil of r.inisterc to 'iis r ighnflos tae ult m of luBcat &amp;nd Oman, I ff UECfct # to ?,faJor (!• . ur \y t ' Political Agent snd .B,! f c Conaul, 1 uiscat. Af t er C orapl irnen te . n reply to your letter Do. 105G, (It. ted 11th -jepteinber 1928, corresponding to 25th Habi«T. t 1347, encloaing truneia- t; on of letter Uo. 751/119/28 dated lt,t. August 1928, v/hich hi..B been received from the Adwinietrator-General at Zanzibar Avith regard to the deceased Abe id bin Said tilave of Raya bint usallira al MuawXla unking uis to enquire about hia haira, v* beg to atate that we uoked the leading raen of the ruavil tribe to inform us about the heira of the afwreuaid deceased. '7s hrve nnvt receiTed an amswer stating; that tlie deceneed has got s sister named 'Jannurah bint I'nid who wan kidnapped by some robbere 17 ye sir o ?jnd who is 83 id to be now at Ghargah. They do not know of any other heirs bebides the oioter of the deceased and if she is not traced the estnte should go to the masters of the als^ve. The original letter sf the leading aouis men sf the J'uawil in forwarded herewith. £££££££p£££££ Gspy of tr«nisl&amp;tion of a letter d^ted 24th Rabi-TI., 1347 ( (9-10-1928) from Hamad bin 'aid al Ifuavrfli and Abdul Aziz bin Muhammad al Ruwuhi to the Council sf J inieteru to His Highness the oultan of H ub cat snci Oman. After Csmpliments. We have duly received y .ur esteeraed letter dated 27tn i&lt;«bi-I., l» r 547 (12-9-1928) enquiring about Sannurah bint 'Amid Hister of Abe id bin /'aid who died at Zanzibar. T Te beg to state that 17 years ago the thieves sf ,r uawil sold her although she was free woman and we understand that she is living at Bhargah. U'e do not know of any sther heir beeides her but if che is not traced then the eutate should go to the masters (of the deceased slave). Usual Ending. 31No. -2 0 f 1928. British IResidenoy and Consulate-General, ^ushire, the 1st December 1928. 1 To The Residency Agent, A.O. Shargah. I am directed to forward to you herewith translation of a letter No.1370, dated the 17th November 1928, with its enclosures^and to say that you should make full investiga tions ahout SunnJfah 'bint 2aid said to have 'been kidnapped ahout 17 years ago and now in Gharq^ah, and submit your report at an early date. ^ iat Major, • Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 11' f % u 1 - r ^ ^ IFroia The Hesidency Agent, Shargah. The Hon , 'ble tiie Political 'Resident, Persian G-ul^ ' -Lfeted 21st January 1929. To No.18. A. C. With reference to your letter JTo.286, dated the 1st ■Deceaber 1928, with enclosure, nanely translation of a letter froa the Political Agent and H.B.lf's Consul, Muscat, regarding Sannurah hint Zaid, sister of the late Ahaid hin ' Zaid who died in Malandi, Zanzibar. I hare the honour to report that I instituted search es at Shargah to find the said Sannurah 'but could not get at ner there. 1 then Made enquiries in the other Onan towns up to Has ul Klialniah; no-one inforiaed ae as to her existence anywhere there. 1 therefore heliere she is dead Decause ay secret and open enquiries did not throw any light at all her person. Decision in this case rests with you. U.E (h i. 2- ';i own Telegram K. J^rora The Senior JNaval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. 'TKIAD'. To Political Hesidect, iJushire. Time 0703. Dated (and received ) 15th December 1928. 7 ^ Tiber 11th. I Your message of Decembe** 'LUi'iJN' reports that Kesidency Agent has in his custody at Debai four slaves and crew of dhow and the Shaikh of JJebai has accepted responsibility for custody of dhow. flakhoda with six slaves escaped. xsa recommends that dhow should be burnt off JJebai in the presence of one of his Majesty's Hhips . if you concur this will be done. Kequest reply by wire asjto this, and. also as to disposal oi the four slaves and crew now in custody of isa. - S .^1.0. , ir*.(j . a Mb^ 0 2—J wmm tovh Telegram H. From Senior waval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. 'TKlAD'. To Political HesidBBt, liusiiii 4 e» Time 0907, Dated [ and received } 16th December 1928 i GLKAH 'rm urn . My 0703 of December 15th. The slaves were brought first from Mekran Coast to Wadum on Batinah Coast and thence to Dibai. The owner, tiakhoda and crew of ahow are all subjects 01 the Sultan of Muscat. The slaves nov^ in custody of Isa are two women and two children. - s . n . U. Seen •ro be resubmitted.% Town Telegram K. Froro Political Resident, Bushire. To Senior Naval Officer, .Persian Gulx , H.M.S. 'TRIAD', Henjam. No. 1263. Dated 17tii December 1928. Yes f 'burn captured dhow as propoaed. Residency Agent may 'be told to repatriate slaves. - residbwt.ii/- V(' PROM The Senior Nttirai OfTicer,Persian Gulf # TO The CottLuicUider-in-ChiefIndies Station. (Copy to Foiiticai Resident,Bushire^, DAT3. •. • •. 19th December 'J ^26. No. 35 Subuiitted, On 11th Deceiuber 1928 the Foiiticai Resident requisted the Senior muVul Or'iicer to ti.ke action upon a report iroui the Hesxaeacy Agent ut 3hu.r t ;«.h to the eiiect that a Slave Dhow and Jxaves hc-d been seized cvt Debai, a heavy shuuiai blowing at the tiuie which prevented iMediate action i'roiii bein^; taken # 3Mf 2 2.l2.2f /« s;an oOV&gt; 2. On 14th Deostaber 1922,tha «»3a,thar having modarated sufficiently,H.M. S, 'LUPIisi' visited Debai axid reported r- (a). Khan Bahadur Isa bin Abdul Latif arrived on board shortly aftarwards and informed me that the dhow referred to in his telegram of 12th Decembar was at prasent in his cuntody at Debai, together with the crew and four slaves (2 women aad 2 boys) but that the Nakhoda (who is a near relative of the owner of the dhow) with six slaves had escaped. (b). He axso -.ut'onued me that the Sheikh of Debai d-csoxciiiiied axl responsibility for the landing of the slaves,the dhow being owned in Sfadaiu and the owner and crew being subjects of the Sultan of Muscat. (c). He requested we however to impress on the Sheikh the necessity for his assistin-r him r Isa) in suppressing the Slave Trade in DeTrai. (d). Sheikh Saied of Debai,accompanied by Sheikhs Juma tuid Haskir, arrined on board in t^ e c.fternoon. (e). X pointed oufc to Sheikh Saied his responsibilities for suppressing the Slave Trade,to which he replied that we shouxd say that to the Government of Muscat where the dhow in Muestion belonged. I said we should do so, but that he was rospoiisible for its suppression in his o./n territory. (f). I then toxd him that ''LUPIN' was returninp; to Henjam and that he must be responsible for the custody of the dhow until one of H # M»Ships returned. He promised to retain t^e dhow as Ion': as we wished, but pointed out that unless he put them into gaol,he could not be responsible for the custody of the crew,with which I agreed,as I understood j .rom Isa that it would not be proposed to take ^ny action against them. (g). The threeFrom The Clerk in Charge Kenjan Stat-ion • To The Hon r Dle The Resident in The Persian Gulf • Eushire • Ko..'. ...V.. Dated Henjara 20tii December 1928 . ik. I have the honour to submit attached a receipt Iron Mr E Gilladary for Rs fifty on account of hire of Dhow to despatch your telegram no 1250 to the Residency Agent Shar^ah on the 13th instant • I shall thank you to remit the amount Rs fifty through the ■ Superintendent in charge Telegraph Station Bushire . I have the honour to oe , Sir , your most obedient servano7 No. 7 Of 1929. British Residency &amp; Consulate-G-eneral, t 'Pushire, 5th January 1929. To The Hesidency Agent, Shargah. A^CJ- The Hon'hle the Politioal Resident directs me to inform you that you should send the four slaves taken off the dhow that was hurnt 'by H.M's Man-of-¥ar outside Dahai, to Muscat. You should send them with a letter to the Political Agent, Muscat, explaining the matter in detail and send the 'bill for their passages to this office. vr l!ajor. Secretary to the Political Resident 4^?^ in the Persian G-ulf. -x*- . 4 , - '-sju 1 Copy 'to tHe Politioal Agent, Muscat, for favour of taking charge of the rescued persons and dealing with them as seems most suitable to him.From- The Ttesidenoy \gent, Sh-rgah. TonM^ie t ie Political Resident in the Persian Gul-f No-61dated the l r )th ^eoemher 1928. a He Terence my telegram No.^82 regarding the case of the oamhuq. and the 'aluchis arrested, I 'beg to state tnat on 4-12-28 trie secret Baluchi agents appointed 'by me to find out the importers of ^alucni 'boys and girls for sale in Oman n owns informed me that a Sarnbuq of one Nakhuda T 'uharamad 'bin Mi of Tadarn, subject of the Sultan of I'uscat has imported some Baluchi women and children for sale and that the SanTbuq was in Dahai uarhour. I at once asked assistance frorr the Shaikh of Jahai to arrest the oainbug. and take hold of kidnapped Baluchis. The Shaikh immediately sent his fidawis (guards) to the Samhuq 'but could not find the kidnapped persons. I therefore ordered my own guards as well as those of the Shaikh to make a search in the rn own.. ''hey found two women and two hoys in the house of an Arah. I obtained their statements which I enclose herewith for your information. 7ley stated in their statements that they were ten in .11 on hoard the oamhuy.. I therefore asked the Shaikh to get hold of the other six persons and also t!ie Samhuci. n le 3aaik:i detailed some of his Fidawis to search in the 'own 'but their action was unsuccessful. On enquiry 'being made it was found out that the Nakhuda ^uhammad bin Mi had imported the Baluchis from 7udam in the said boat. Tnen the searcn was instituted and the two women captured, ae took j io otie i six persons and ran away to the interior at mid ligat. .ae Shaikh sent for them from the interior but they conic not be traced. Owing to the Shaikh's assistance to us in this matter there arose a murmur among the Tabs that this -V;-ibuq. belonged to the subjects of the 3ultan of 'uscat md t vat the importers were his subjects of 'Mdam and under the ^ g protection of T.B.M'S Government and that tie coat s o 'li oe kept under custody of the Hesidency Agent. It then struck® me that the crew may probably run away from the creek, therefore 1 submitted a telegram to you on the M-12-2S.H.::.3. 'Lupin' arrived and I immediately visited the Captain ai i ^d u.n of t..j ja^e. Tae 3'nalkh also interviewed the Cap bain ana emphaclsed upon him to keep the boat pending arrival . ^ on ^ oenior ITaval Orricer /Monday 17-12-28, when the necessary .on '.vi 1 oe taken l)y him. In my opinion the hest course vhich has to he adopted in this matter is to 'burn the 'boat so that its news may spread among the inhabitants of Trucial Oman wOdSo and Batinah and they may refrain from this dangerous dealing, ^ae Town of 'Talchuda Muhammad 'bin Ali is ^udam, the woman -aryam hint ?aiz Muhammad has a son in the same Town and she knows his whereabouts. Decision rests with you. otatemeab made oy Mary am .Begum hint =. amuk -alucal aged ahout o/ y^birb, of town Boonu in Mekran under vhiefship of Din Mohammad Ahdi Baluchi. I was in my t/w^n Boonu and my work was shepherding, 's usual I took my son named Jumah with me as well as the cattle to the pasture and there I accompanied with eight other Baluchi children, hoys and girls. -'11 of us proceeded to the open pasture The cattle were grazing and we were sitting under a tree. *11 of a sudden one ^Tur ■'uhammad Baluchi approached us, who was riding accompanied 'by eight other persons. They captured us forcibly and carried us on the animals and took us to a village on the Sea called Park and thence they embarked all of us on a boat. There was with us Nawazan bin Nur T.'uiammad. The name of the Nakhuda was Abdur Eahman Baluchi of the village IBu-Abali, one of the villages of Batinah ^oast.They disembarked us in the said village and sold me and my son to a m3.n named Jabir bin I'uaamraad and 1 do not know where the others were taken to. I have been with the said Jabir for the last eight months. In this month Jabir intended to sell my son Jumah but I did not agree unless he sells both of us. le therefore embarked me in the Sambuci whose Nakhuda was Muhammad bin Mi of ' r udam. Tien I embarked the boat I saw there were in the 3ambuq. eight otaer persons, all Baluchis women and children. I enquired from th^m from where they ha^e embarked, taey said from udam. Samhuq. sailed and after ten days journey we reached Dahai. The Nakhuda diseraharked us at night time, yyseli and my son and ■laryam- aryam and her son were kept in the house of a man named uuharamad 'bin Said and I do not know where the others were taken to. The names of those who were in the 3am'buq are:- (l) Maryam 'bint Fai^ Muhammad (2) a 'boy Mubarik (3) a hoy Nuhi (4) a girl Tankuh (5) a 'boy Mahruk (6) a hoy Vbaidu. After two days stay at Dabai, there came to • the house of the said Muhammad the men of the Shaikh and those of Residency '-gent and they arrested me and my son, Maryam and aer son and taken us to ti fcne Agent -t Jabai. I 'beg to request the llig'a Gowernment to be graoiously pleaseito send me to Muscat, so that I may spend t t-ie rest of my life there with my son and he safe from the Baluohis. Statement made hy T.'aryam hint ^aiz Muhammad aged about 2^ years. — I am of the village Bahra in the neighbourhood of ''ampur under 'Oost Muhammad Khan. In the month of Babi I, (August 1928) I an^ my son named Pank left our town, intending to approach the sea side in order to proceed to Tuscat. Then we reaoaed tae mountain, we were pursued hy one Tfalishah Baluchi and tares others. Tiiey arrested us forcibly and took us to a town on tne sea side, the name of which I do not know, an.i then they embarked us in a 'boat going to Batinah to ^udam, they sold me to a man named Id and my son to a 3aluchi of 7;udam whose name I do not know-hut I know waere his house is and also ais date trees la the month of Jamadi IltOctoher 1928) the said Id sent me with Makauda Muhammad Din Mi of '.Tudam to DaDai, -'or sale. On our arrival at Dabai I was landed with the woman ^egum Dint Jamuk in the house of 'uhammad Din 3aid. After tvra days taere came to us the guards of the Shaikh and those of the Besiaency 'gent, arrested me and the said woman and took us to the Besidency ^gent at BaDai. I am a free Dorn person and my relatives are at Muscat. There names are 'Toor Muaannaa, 'all Muhammad, All Khan and Saild, Wao are employees o:- tie loiisulate at Muscat. I revest that the ligh Government may he graciously pleased to release my son from Tudam, for which act of kinlaess I shall ever remain grateful. G.H.No. 1'!-^ of 1929. British Residoncy * uonsulste-G-eneral. i X Bushir« , the J ^ TrJanuary 1929. A copy of the undGrmentioned paper is forward ed to the political Agent and riis Britannic iviajesty's Consul, muscat, in continuation of this office memorandum No.2517 dated the 29th Hecenher 1928. pf&amp; By Order, lc Major, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Translation of a letter No. 612 dated the 15th Decenoer 1928 from the Kesidency Agent, shargah to tae non'ole t ;G political resident in t ne Persian Gulf, Jus lire#A.CJ. ?rom - Tae Residenoy '^ent, Lin^ah. To - T10 r Ioa , 'ble tiiQ Politioal Resident, Persian Gulf. No. 619, dated the 19th Decernber 1928. ~ Reference my letter Mo.612 dated the IBth December 1^23 on tae subject of the Sarahug^, which imported Baluchis for sale, I be^ to state that on 17-12-28, at evening time, the Jenior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf arrived on II.M.S. 'Triad*. I at once went to pay m^ respects to hirn, who enquired from me ahout tie case of the Samhuc. I informed him of the facts. On 18-12-28 when T Iis Excellency the Commander in Tciief, East Indies Sq^u^dron visited T)al3ai and the Shaikhs came to Dahri to inter view him, the Senior ^Taval Officer took the 'boat out of L ^e creek and there it was hurnt, which action was guite appropri ate . In my opinion and subject to your approval^ x commendatory note may 'be issued to t le Shaikh of T)a'bai Tor t te assistance rendered 'by him in this connection. I think this .vill 'be useful for the future and your opinion is superior. I solicit instructions as to the disposal of the women and their children as they intend to proceed to l T uscat. /, l^h iT. i No. ^ Y of 1929. British Residency A Consulate-aeneral, / ,L iSushire, tue 4 ^etruary 1929. To 'N *1 Tae Saeilcii or Da'bai. ( Tarough the Residency igent, Shargah)• ATter Compliments. nth reference to the evil doings of Nakhuda Kohammed bin All of ./udam, who arrived at Dahai in a Samhuq on the 4tn December 1928, with some women and children, whom he intended to sell, and wnose Samhug was duly destroyed by tne Senior iJaval Officer, Persian Gulf, in the presence of the Admiral Commanding tne the Bast Indies Squadron, hy my orderr on the 18th December 1928- I write to inform your Excellency tnat I nave now received full details regarding t:ie matter from Knan Bahadur Isa Din Abdul Latif, this Hesidency's .gent at Snargah, and it gives me very great pleasure to write and tell y 0U now mucn I appreciate tne interest you snowed in the matter and the assistance you gave to the Residency Agent by seizing the Sambuq in question and handing it over to the Residency igent with the women and children. The practice of selling human beings like cattle especially ^aluchis who are 'hurr' is abhorent to God and must be detested by all right minded and God fearing men, and it is a cause for congratulation that you are determined not to allew such traffic in your territories. I trust, you will continue to work for the putting down of sued crimes and will always afford your assistance to our esteemed Vgent residing in your midst. J sual Ending. i G.H. iulitical Resident in tae Persian Guir.•//?/■ No. ILtiJ of 1929. British Residency and Consulate- eneral, Bushire, 21st July 1929. To The Political Agent, Muscat, at Karachi. , \ Slavs dealers at V/udam, Lemorandum . The favour of an early reply is requested to letters from this office Nos. 25and 138 dated 29th Deoemher 1929 and 19th January 1929 respectively. By order, 7' 7 for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000c4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/223</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000c4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/223</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 5/191 III Individual slavery cases'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1927/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-06-14T00:12:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (435 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence contained in the volume is arranged by subject, with twenty subjects in total included in the volume. Within each subject, correspondence is arranged in rough chronological fashion from earliest at front to latest at rear. The subjects themselves are arranged chronologically, based on the earliest pieces of correspondence included in each, from earliest at the front to latest at the rear. There is a handwritten contents page on ff.2-3, which lists the titles of these subjects, but not their corresponding page or folio number.</extent><extent>Foliation: The volume is foliated with a circled number in the top right-hand corner of each front-facing page. Cover (containing cover title), blank front page and 2 blank rear pages are unnumbered. Each of the subjects into which the volume is divided has its own internal pagination system, expressed as page number
                           xof subject number
                           y.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Twenty cases relating to individuals and small groups, kidnapped or transported from Baluchistan or India, to the Trucial Coast, in particular Dubai. Some of the cases are straightforward and involve the appearance or retrieval of slaves in the Dubai area, often initiated by the Sharjah Residency Agent ('Isa bin 'Abd al-Latif) and their manumission, plans for repatriation, and punishment of traders/kidnappers, where they are identified. Other cases are more complex, where the identification of slaves, their parents, or those who traded them, is more difficult. Of particular note in the volume:Subject 8, relating to a young Persian boy kidnapped from Sind and brought to Dubai, which stretches over 100 folios. Difficulties are encountered in obtaining a photograph of the boy for purposes of identification. The extensive correspondence in the case is in part also cause by obstructions and procrastinations of al-Latif. Subject 16, relating to two Baluchi men kidnapped by Bedouins in the interior of the Trucial coast. The case reveals tensions between the coastal Sheikhs of the Trucial region, and the Bedouin chiefs of the interior. Questions over the control how much control Sheikhs, who have signed treaties with the British, have over actions of Bedouins from the interior. Subject 20, account of the capture of a dhow carrying slaves at Dubai, and the burning of the dhow by the British navy, off the Dubai coast.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Dubai</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Baluchistan</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000c4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>