<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000177_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T21:24:44.181Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM wim mmGERMAN WAR: PERSIA A CJERMAN MONEY FOR PERSIA 0914*- I9I91JTelegram.... 3 . From...His Brlten/dc Majesty's Consul General, Ispahan Xo The Foreign, secretary to the Government oi India in the Foreign am Political Department, Simla { Addressed Teheran No J .. Lf . • . Dated the 6th August Reed, the 7th hy telegram Ho.5. I have refunded money to Kazeruni today, i delayed refundioc it lest enquiries should prove that th he hed had relatlo-s vith trigands recently captured hut nothing incriminating him has transpired.To* ooHis Britannic Majesties Charge d 1 affaires and special Connnissioner, Teheran* i^O 1* 5 ? . '~*Qo Bated the 7th May 1919„ Kazeruni* lixed deposit of balance of jds* 28,CoO expiree- on 27th March. Please wire whether in your opinion this sum should continue to be held on oenal: o± Kazeruni or whether it should now be refunded to him* This refers to my telegram dated 78th December last *7 ^ No. 377-0. Passport Office, Hew Customs House, Ballard Hoad, Bombay, 3rd Hay 1919# Prom The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, To Hov • i^: The/_Jecretary to the Government of India, x’oreim and Political Department, Oonf ident ial &lt;&gt; uu-i j «it _ ref (jrence to tl i; Dep rtmert letter Ho * 19v~u, dato-* 1 the 6th Pebruary 1918, I am directed to forward herewith a copy of a letter from the Custodian of Hnemy Pronertv at Bombay, Ho# C*^35E, dated the aBth -ipril 1919, and of its enclosure, in connection with the sum ot ns* 28,000 now held hy Government as security on behalf of Haji Mahomed Kazeruni of Ispahan, and to request the orders of the Government of India as to whetner tne amount should he redeposited in the Bank of Bombay and, if so, for what period* I am to ask that instructions may he communicated by telegram as the amount is now lying* idle with the Custodian of Bnemy Property* I have etc*, rt o For Secretary to Government*-- InniidentiglA 1 Yfirv urp:ent a IlOo 1-352 of 1919, Ballard Road, Bombay, 28th ,-pril 1919 o Prom E «0 IS aiit chell, o\\ ire, Oustodian of ULiemj property, Bombay, To The Secretary to the Government of Bombay Political Departmento Sir I have the honour to invite a reference to Government letter, Political Deportment, Ho. 76-0, dated Hath Joinery 1919, end to sttte that the balance of Ks. 28,000/- out of the sum of Its. 56,C0C/- deposited with aovemment ny Heii llahomed Xazeruni of Ispahan as secutity tor ns rpo&amp; behaviour was placed by me on fixed deposit for 12 months with the Bank of Bombay, as desired by the accountant General in his letter Ho. Dep.7-397, dated 16th Hebruery 1918, a copy of which is sent herewith. The period of the deposit expired on 27th Liarch 1919 and the amount is now lying with me without interest. I have as yet received no instructions as to whether the amount should be placed again on fixed deposit or whether it should be returned to the accountant General. 'The minimum period for which the Bank of Bombay is prepared to accept this amount on fixed deposit is six months and the Bank will allow 3i % interest only. 1 am to request that I may be favoured with very early orders of Government as to the disposal of this amount, I have etc*, 3d/~ H*0 J^kitchel], Oustodian of Enemy Property*Bombay, the loth February 1913d From The accountant General, Bombay, To The Custodian of Bnemy Property, Bombay. dir. Subject:- Opening si a personal ledger account. I have the honour to state that a sum of Bso06,000/^ was deposited in November and December 1916 in the Bank of Bombay by Hazi Ivlahomed Kazeruni of Ispahan as security to Government for his good behaviour. Out of this amount a sum of Fs* 28,00w was, under instructions from Government paid to him on 6tb November 1917, through his agents, Messrs Hazi Suit anali dhushtary and Go., Bombay, as a loan at 12 per cent interest per annum to be recovered half yearly. The remaining amount of its» 28,000 is in deposit with Government at the Bank of Bombay and it has been decided to treat this amount as a 'Fixed Deposit' in your name for one year at the Bank. 2* The Government of India have directed that the transactions connected with this deposit should, for the present be recorded in a Personal Ledger Account in which only interest on the local at 12 per cent realisable from Hsji Mahomed Kazeruni as well as that payable by the Bank of Bombay on the fixed deposit account may be credited. The Deputy Secretary to Government of Bombay, Political Department has intimated to me that the Personal Ledger Account referred to above should be opener in your name. 3, To enable me to clear the balance of As*28,000 originally credited to 'Deposits' I have the honour to requestrequest that you will please prefer a hill for the amount at this office for payment to you and pay the same to the Bank of Bombay who will treat it as a 'Fixed Deposit' in your name for one year* The interest on this deposit as well as that which will he recovered on the loan should he credited to the Personal Ledger Account to he opened in your name at the Bank of Bombay* I I have etc*, Sd/~ FJUG* Rehello# Deputy Accountant General.Telegram P. Prom His Britannic Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires and Special Commissioner, Teheran, 0 The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simlao Repeated Ispahan with reference to his telegram No. 105.) No. 71. Dated the 29th. Reed* the 30th • May 1919• Rupees twenty eight thousand should be • refunded to Kazeruni. His Majesty's Government having authorised the return of money or other securities deposited as guarantee of good conduct. This refers to your telegram No. 578-S.~ T ~™— /* 7 n iz Tele?rra.m- Fromo. o. o .The Secretary to the G-overnment of Indio in the foreign and Political Department, Simla, To 0 ......The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay fl No* 534-B. Dated the 30th Lay 1919, Your letter 3rd Lay,371-0* On recommendation of Special Commissioner Tehran Rupees twenty eight thousand should now be refunded to Kazeruni.T1 J- ■ ;UW - ^ ^ ^ H&gt; iab 7( f1, «?/ /^ \4- I Political bepartineni Bombay Castle, 19th Septern’oer 1918 Prom To J»E»C, Jukes, Esquire, Deputy Secretary to Government, The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, sir I am directed to refer to the correspondence ending with ray letter No, 190-C, dated the 6th February 1913, regarding the loan of Rs, 28,000/- advanced to Haji Mahomed Kazeruni of Ispahan out of the amount of Rs. 5S,000/'- deposited by him with Government as security for his good behaviour, 2, In the arrangement made with Kazeruni, the payment of interest on the loan at the rate of 12% per assuil was stipulated, and, as reported, in my letter No, 1387-C, dated the 6th October 1917, the Government of Bombay decided, at.the suggestion of the Accountant General, that the interest should be recovered in two half yearly instalments. The first instalment nas now fallen due, and I am to request the orders of the Government of Tidia as to how it should be realised. Messrsi Hajl Sultanall Shushtary and company of Bombay, Kazeruni's agent, are respondible for the payment of neither the loan nor the interest, and they have repudiated all liability in the matter. :,\h * a J KH I have etc* f f ‘Z'- 9 ' Sd/- J.E,C,Jukes, *' ’**'* , ^ ■• ^ * i ** i *' ‘ Dsrwty Secretary to- GovernmentTelegram, Prom-- The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. To—---— His Britannic Majesty's Charge d'ftfffeires and Special commissioner, T g H K A N„ No, 1328-W. Dated Simla, th® 2nd October'1918. Your telegram dated the 1st November 1917, 80. Interest is now due on loan to Kazeruni. Pleas® advise as to its recovery.Telegram. Prom..... The Secretary to the Government of India in the Pbreign and Political Department, To ..His Britannic-Majesty's Charge d'Affaires and Special Cdmrnissloner, TEHRAN . No. 1573-W. Dated atxiix, the 9th December’1918. Ivjy telegram dated 2nd October, 1328 W. Loan to Kazeronl. would be glad of a reply.. QQNPM ' M , . . N0« 1604*0 Prom To Political Department. Bombay Castle, 6th December 1918* A.F. Kindersley, Esquire, Deputy Secretary to Government, Bombay. The Foreign Secretary/ to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department. Sir, I am directed to request*that the Government of Bidia may he moved to pass early orders on the letter from this Department No. 1339*0, dated the 19th September last, with reference to the recovery of the first instalment of #.' interest due on the loan of Rs. 28,000 advanced to Haj i Mohamed Kazeruni of Ispahan. I have etc., Sd/* A»F» Kindersley, Deputy Secretary to Government,CDNFIDSNT.IAL «_ From..... The Secretary to the Govei’ament of India .in the K&gt;reign and Political Depattbment. To ...... A.F, Kindereley, E squire, Deputy Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department. Memorandum No. 1687-W. Dated Delhi, the 14th December 1918. Reference correspondence ending with your letter No. 1504-0, dated the 6th December 1918 regarding loan advanced to HaJi Mohamed Kazeruni. A' further reference has been made to His Britannic Majesty’s Charge d'Affaires and Special commissioner, Tehran, and his reply is awaited, Sd, Denys Bray, secretary to the Government of India, Attested. Sd/** A* Picachy, Superintendent, Foreign and Political Department.Telegram* P. prom s Charge d'Atfaires and Sj&amp;eclal Commissioner., Tehran, To The Secretary to the Government of India In the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, No, 215. Dated the 13th December 1918. Received the 14th December 1918, As individual has behaved very well since removal from the Statutory L'ist H.M's. Consul-General, Ispahan, recommends that Interest should be foregone and loan regarded as refund of half deposit. Falling that, and before balance is restored interest: should be deducted from deposit. I concur in above. This Is with reference to your telegram No. 1573-W, dated the 9th December 1918,Telegram**?. Prom... The Secretary to the Government of lidia, lii the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To H.B.M’s Charge d'Affaires and Special Commissioner, Tehran. NO, 2416**S» Dated 28th December 1918. Proposal that the loan be treated as a refund of half deposit and that the Interest thereon 1 be foregone is approved. Instructions to act accordingly are being sent to the Government of Bombay, This refers to your telegram. No. 215 dated the 13th December 1918 regarding loan to Kazeruni,routflDECTlAL . 7J Me. /?- w» A copy of the \rndormantioietf. papers Is fowarded to the Goverriment of Bombay, Political Department, for inforrr^tion, In continuation of the memorandum from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, No* 1587 W, dated the 14th December 1918, 2, It is requested that, with the permission of His Excellency the Governor, orders may be issued foregoing the interest on the loan granted to JJajl Mahomed Kazenmi and that the loan itself be regarded as a refund of the half deposit made by him. By order, etc,, sa|- W*. Deputy secretary to the Gove'mriient of India* Foreign and Political Department* DELE I: The k r January 1919* Telegram to Charge d*Affaires and Dpecial Commissioner, Tehran, No, 1328«W, dated the 2nd October 1913* Telegram to- ditto 9th December 1918* Telegram from ditto December 1918* Telegram to- ditto 28th December 1918* No, 1573-W, dated the No* 215, dated the 13th No* 2416-S, dated the ditto.Telegram from Viceroy, Foreign and P Department, to the Secreta* Dated 15th. October 1918. Received at I.O., 16th. 6 0 p.m. 6^tr. Your telegram of the 19th. September Bombay Government placed Rs 100,500 principal arid Rs. 1313 interest to order of Shirazi and Son on behalf of Itahadie with Hong Kong and Shanghai Bank on Sept. 27th. Addressed to Secretary of State andf ^ fr\. —« — i Jay?- Tele^raa - 1 * iron - JLs Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. 2ie Secretary to tlie uOYemiaent of India in tlie Boaei a and Bolitical Department, SiBLa, So. 123, Da, t e a uii.0 xo wii ie-cd. the 19til July IS18 Thorn 1 have no proof SadegMani is under suspicion' of dealing witli tlie enemy. Mot that lie is Believed tc have any syi'ipathy with enemy; he would simply take tr ; any Business vielUna r . cod commissi on, I propose tc ask kin to deposit caution uonej and si^: an undertaldng on pain of tsing { ?) This refers tc your tslogran !To. B88-S.1 T y further communication ^ -on abject, please quote 197566/34 ddress— 3 Controller, ^ 'oreign Trade Department. Telept^^: Oerrard 8640. iir. 2,^7 Eokelgn Trade DERAktefeT, J ^ Bridgewater House, St. James’s, S.W.l. August 1918. ^ - •f ft ■ Ml'ijv With reference to the letter from this Department of July 10th (190202/34) I am directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to transmit herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State for India copy of a telegram received from His Majesty r s Minister at Teheran. Mr, Balfour has no objection to the release to Ittahadie of £7,000 at present deposited in the Bank of Bombay, and proposes, subject to the concurrence of Mr. Secretary Montagu, so to inform Sir C. Marling. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, ^ humble servant. • » ' ; x,. The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, Controller. Whitehall, S.W.l.4-1 Telegram - P* Prom - The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay* To - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, uimla* Do 96-4£U D/~ the 25th (12*55 p*m.) R/~ the 25th (9*00 p*m.) fey 1918 ft appears that the money belongs genuinely to Ittihadie* Do third party has put forward any claim to it during the two years and seeing that the money is deposit offered hy Ittihadie himself it is extremely improbable that Government could be held liable in case of such claims. Please refer to correspondence ending with your en dorsement 633-1 dated the 31st lay 1916, Jn the circumstances we have no objection to return of money. This refers to your telegram of the 17th May, 536-S.mil. umiiiuwwh— wmiiBWW Ho.A.C-L-an-3-7781, dated Bon’oay, the 12th November 1917. From - .7.Alder, 2sq ., 1.0.2., Accountant-Gene :a al, Bombay. _’o - The Secretary to the Government of Bombay Political Department, Bombay. Re payment of Rs.28,000 to Haji Ltahammad Kazeruni. 7ith reference to Government Order (Confi dential) Political Department * 1-52 — 0•, o.ate^ - : e 24th September 1917, sanctioning a payment of Rs. 28,000 to Haji Muhammad Kazeruni out of the amount p£ Rs.56,000 deposited by him with Government as security for his good behaviour, I have the honour to enrmire whether Government desire to treat the payment as a loan or as a temporary refund of demosit. If the former, I request that the parti- . cular class of the Provincial Advance and Loan Account under which the loan may be allocated as well as the Budget provision for the same may be minted out. If however Government desire to treat it as a repayment of deposits, I may be informed whether the receipts on account of interest.may be credited to Government or to the deposit account. ' The amount was paid to Messrs. Haji Sultinali Shushtary and Co. on the 6th November 1917.— _____ . 4-4 Ko• 1198-V/*, fated Delhi, the 19th December 1917. Drom - The De'iity Dec etary to the Dovermpent of $ • India in the Foreign and Political Depart: lent, To - The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Denartrent. I sin directed to acknowledge the^ receipt of your letter Do.1573-0., dated the 13th November 1917 asking for instructions as to the treatment in the accounts of the payment of Pe.28,CDO made to Haji i.-uharTiad Kazeruni out of the amount of Ps.55,000 deposited by him with Government as security for his good behaviour. 2. As the loan of Ps.28,000 at 12 per cent to Mr. Ha3i luhammad Kazeruni was made out oT the money deposited by him and not from the general revenues of Government, the transaction cannot be treated in the Government accounts as a loan'made by Government It will be convenient for account purposes to record for the present all transactions connected with Kami Muhammad Kaz-wini ? s duoosit in a personal ledger account to be opened in the name of a Government officer (to be selecte for the purpose by the Local Government) in ydiich interest at 12 per cent realisable from Ha3i - uhamnad Kazeruni as well as that payable by the Bank of Bombay on the fixed deposit account may be credited. I am to sug est that, if His Excellency the Governor sees no ob3action, this course may be adopted.:• - ■'%{ - • s . ? V i, &gt; /l Teletya^ - E. | . &lt; . -, 1 i i &lt;3 J From - His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. To - The Secretary to tile Government of India in the Foreign ana Political Department, Delxii */ No 34. D/- the 19th R/- the 20 th February 19lb. JO flowing from Ahwaz 163 February loth. Deuaeehti Bombay refuses to trade with firm Naksivena on the ground that Mirza Mahomet Naksivena A 0 ertt Ahwaz is on Statutory List. So far as I am aware latter is not on List am is probably due to Ms connection with Amur Rahim Arab, n this is the case will you kindly issue necessary instructions t,o enable Naksivena resume business. fi£ 2 .* Naksivena is not on Statutory List and Amur Rahim is there by error am is to be removed as soon as possible.— ' ■' ' 6J % 4-&lt;3 • No. 2E3b. mimmT of India. DEPABKMW OF GOLIMEl 01 AND INDUSTRY. 191 . SIMLA, tLo 24bh April 1916. From Gr.S. ray, Fis^uirc*, I. C« S., UNDER SECRETARY TO THE OTIMMMT OF INDIA, To Ail Collectoro of Customs. Sir, I m direct ©a to infom you that ?! Abdul Rahim Arab® h&amp;e been removed from the Statutory List for Persia. A formal notification to this effect will issue shortly. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obeuient Servant, Q. S.HARDY. UNDER SECRETARY TO THE GGYEDMMENT OF INDIA. No .220*9 A copy is forwarueu to All Local Governments am Administrations. The Lftaai Foreinn and Political and the Army Department. The Director, Central Intelligence. The Director General of Commercial Intelligence. The Director of Statistics. Tlie Political Resident at Aden. By order, etc., E.P.Jones. for Unaer Secretary to the Government of India.Lbj 47 0 Telegram. P. From - Tii© Seoretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. To - Hie Britannia Majesty*© Minister, Tehran. No. 46b-S. Dated the 30th April 1916. Police warned BeLdneirhi not to trade with Naksivena. He has now been told that latter is not on Statuocry list. Abdul Rah'im Arab removed from Statutory list. Tlds refers to your telegram March 17th, 51.Any further communication should be .ddressed to— THE SECRETARY, at the address given opposite. The following number and letters must be quoted :— 27565/IS/S Letters will be dealt with more expedi tiously if they relate to one application only. rS rade, Vic, London . , 18345. Wt. 59250/652. 200,000. R. &amp; L., Ltd. 3/fr. WAR TRADE DEPARTMENT, 4, CENTRAL BUILDINGS, WESTMINSTER, S.W. 1. Your reference P2680 July 8th 1918. Sir, With reference to your communication of the 1st instant transmitting a copy of a letter addressed to hessrs. Klem.anta.ski, Sates and Co. , Limited, 21, Bury Street, E.C.3 regarding Messrs Haji Abdul Rahman Shirazi, of Bombay, I aim instructed by Lord Emmott to enquire whether the information contained in my letter qa. tne 17th ultimo is incorrect. gb/mrLr 18345. Wt. 59250/652. 200,000. Any further communication should be Iressed to— THE SECRETARY, die address given opposite. The following number and letters must quoted :— /- 27363/18/S Letters will be dealt with more expedi- r if they relate to one application only. ^5) &amp; L., Ltd. 3/17 i 7 WAR TRADE DEPARTMENT, 4, CENTRAL BUILDINGS, WESTMINSTER, S.W. 1. O f 0 Wa^.k^de, Vic, London Your reference \ e v v O s ' June 17th 1918. r / 1/ K 1 !=) i 8 m juMifcio I am instructed by Lord Emmott to transmit a letter which has been received in this Department from Messrs. Klemantaski, Bates and Company, Ltd., and to request that you will be good enough to reply to the same. The only information in the possession of the War Trade Department respecting Messrs. Haji Abdul Rahman Shirazi and Son is iJ‘im a report contained in a Customs Circular No.O. 1602 of 28.9.15., which states that it is an enemy- concern. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, he Under Secretary of State, etc., etc., etc., India Office.f &amp; Any 'further communication, op the subject, please quote No - 100202/34 and address— The Controller, Foreign Trade Department. ' ephone : Gerrard 861/0. Sir, (0^ ►ridcewater ' ' m He Foreign Trade Department, PoU St. James’s, S.W. 1. 1 trfk . July 1918. With reference to your letter, P.25C3, of the 11th ult., I am directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to transmit to you herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a telecram received from His Majesty's Minister at Teheran,from which it would appear that no further action is required for the present. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, for the Controller. The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, S.W.l. K-np^4 In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. and address— The Controller, Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, ^•'- v St. James’, S.W. J ^5 03 JSfi:.? 1^20(1 THE Controller of the Foreign Trade Department presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Trade Department, itr , mS - Reference to previous letter : Letter t0 Foreign Trade Department: U- l0 | ^ _____ P-5150S Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Td L (4 q ^ : (Similar letter sent to •)£=£/ y i, 3 t j_3 i cj j Telegram from Viceroy, Foreigi and Political Dept., to the Secretary of State for India. Dated 5th. June 1918. Received at I.O., 6th. 9. 0 p.m. Secret. Your telegram of the 1st. June. Jttihadi. £7 COO and not £1,000 is amount stated in Minister’s telegram 332 as received here and is presumably correct 1 Ifigure. Rs.105,000 is amount actually in deposit. K Mf Addressed to the Secretary of State and repeated to Tehran. zlsTELEGRAM FROM VICTTROY, FORKIG-K DEPART!ffilT 28th MAY 1910. (Received 29th 10.50 a.m.) Secret. Your telegram of 2nd May. Ittahadie. No objection. If desired we will issue orders for payment to Messrs Haji Abdur Rahman Shirasi and Son, of Bombay of Rs. 105,000-on Ittahadie 1 s behalf. Addressed Secretary of State repeated Teheran.* Uh ^ ^ O ■ 3 ' rrl„ S II f ■? ■&gt;\\ r \v/. &amp; Any further communication on the subject, please quote No . 178257/34 and address—■ 'b'7 Controller, Foreign Trade Department. Telephone: Gerrard 8640. *- Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, St. James, SW. 1 27th April 1918. Sir , V;ith reference to India office letter 1. 219 7 oi June 21, 1917, transmitting copies of correspondence v;ith regard to the firm of Ittahadie i’ils, of feheran, whose name v.as removed from the Black List for Persia on the terms stated in the accompanying copy of a telegram dated March no, 19xu, from His Majesty's Minister at Teheran, 1 an directed by ir. Secretary Balfour to transmit to you herewith, to he laid be lore the Secretary of State, for India, copy of a furtner telegram from Sir 0. Marling. LIr. Balfour proposes, subject to t.ne concurreuce ox -^ • Secretary Montagu, to inform fair 0. Marling tnat there is no objection to the release to Ittahadie of Llu00_at present deposited in the Bank of Bombay. I am, 3 ir, your most obedient, humble Servant, ♦ ^ ^ for GONfHOLLhh. The under-Secretary of State, , India office, (x :5 oliticai department), Whitehall, b. W. 1/ 12 COPY JMO. 20829/^4, f i;ecypher. Mr. Marling (Teheran) March 2u, 1916. u. 5.o p.rn. March 2u, 1916. n. 10.45 a.m. March 21, 1916. no. 182 (hi »' tw a I 4 ■ fe? o i^’iles only, x.iy telegr :.m no. 71. Ittahadie has signed .agreement and has instructed his agents to deposit with British authorities as guarantee i:18.,u00 in London and £7,000 in Bombay. Agreement provides that as soon as above sums have been deposited his name shall be removed from Black List and his other tunds nov detained in London and Bombay shall be released. Copy by bag March 28rd. Addressed to roreivn office sent to India.J&gt;' /W/&lt;'* fl 14 ti f f 'i '•w obfto i, &lt;, . . -lij ••' I / vJ :&gt; a r,/ i ' ; ? ’ (N #A a\ Political Department, Bombay Castle, 6th February ’16 L&gt; uU /C- |J ’2 ly to Brovernmen t, Bombay The Foreign 3ec T *etary to the G-overnrnent of Ii ! .ic, Foreign and Political Departinent, Delhi Sii*, V- As desired in Mr. Bray’s letter NoOIM. , dated the 19th December 1917, I ^ directed to state for the information of the Government of India that the Accountant General of SOT Bombay has been instructed to open a personal ledger account in the name of the Custodian of Enemy Property, Bombay, containing all transactions connected with Ha 3 i Mahomed Kaseruni’s deposit,, 2 . He reports however that, when the sum of ns. 56 , 000 /- was originally deposited, the amount was credited by the Bank in the Government account instead of being treated as a 'fixed deposit' in the Bank’s own accounts. He has now instructed the Bank to with draw the balance of Rs.28.000/- and treat it as a f ixe d deposit forgone year, and in accordance with the orders contained in the letter mentioned above, will credit the interest realised therefrom to Personal Deposits. I have, etc., Sd/- J.E.C.Jukes. &gt;4 M Deputy Secretaire to Government,V- i c; ■ i M{ fir-w^TDISiTIAL Gopyi^ A if' Political Department, Bombay Castle, 6tti February T 16 'W h.uA. ’ V From ^ J. B.C.Jukes f Esq. , (C- 1 Deputy Secretaiy to Boveriffiient, Bombay I^P° The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Delhi^ Sir, Y As desired in Mr. Bray’s letter No^U^S-V., x\ d? ted the 19th December 1917, I am directed to state fo ; the infcrraation of the Government of India that the Accountant General of «xe Bombay has been mstruc ea open a personal ledger account in the name of the Custodian of Enemy Property, Bombay, containing a transactions connected with Haji Mahomed Kazerum s deposit. 2 , He reports however that, when the sum of Rs. 56 OOO/- was originally deposited, the s i - aounfc was credited by the BanK In the aovernnent account WBtea of being treated as a 'fixed deposit' In the Ban* e W n accounta. He has net instructed the Banh o i draw the halance of Bs.28.000/- and treat it as a flxe d deposit for,/one year, and in accordance with the orders contained in the letter mentioned ahove, wi 0 a t-hPT'pfrom to Personal credit the interest realised t Deposits. I have, etc., sd/- J.E.C. Jukes. 1 !-•: 11918 Deputy Secretary to Government,It - *?''. 1 . (COPY) -iif. w#** 1 4 i i r\ © k a • 4 V‘' siB.V V, '‘‘v,^.' ' aa*'“ Telegram. . . - : ' v :■ $,#P ■ L x S9! e o 'From - The Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian ftulf and Civil Commissioner in Mesopotamia, Baghdad, To - - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign &amp; Political Department,Delhi. No * G&amp;3* Dated tfce 21st January 1918. 7 A Consul General I spadan enquires why Atdul HaJaim Arab figures on Persian Black List. Please telegraph reason if known. Addressed Foreign repeated Ispahan. iO r r , i 'A 19 WiAH '1918 Telegram. From - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign &amp; political Department,Delhi, To - - The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Civil Commissioner in Mesopotamia, Baghdad. (Repeated to Consul General, Ispahan). N0.95-W© Dated the 28th January 1918* Your 653, 21st. Abdul Rahim Arab was placed on Statutory List by His Majesty's Government in March 1916 presumably on recommendation of Minister. He has never been removed. Addressed Cox repeated Ispahan.* In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. please quote / ^ , t-lo ^ Si/Slf and address— The Controller, Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, St. James’, S.W. V4‘ v. &lt;« Mj A./ A t THE Controller of the Foreign Trade Department presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, transmits herewith cop y of the under-mentioned paper .5, Foreign Trade Department, 191&amp; Reference to previous letter: to Fetter Foreign Trade Department 'from ' ? s yi 7 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 'JL &amp;Y C^TAJLS2^&gt;S^ du bzJ'us-CZU ~1*T ' Mjlu-cDz-xI/cx • Subject. h &lt; SReSi &amp; (Similar letter sent to [ s j •)OPY No. 17095l/o4 Ellinger &amp; Go., Llanchester. 34 COPY Oi TELjpxRixi.l SENT TO : Tne Controller, Foreign Trade Lepertinent Lanoaeter House, London. on Tuesday Maroh 5th 1918. Referring 42078/-34 your letter May ninth 1916 Rahman Shirazi^3omoay ( cables us to receive ten thousand pounds from Credit Lyonnais London.Ifeve alvays received t for many years considerable sums to Rahmans credit in ordinary course business amounting to a fev thousands ! pounds, but this amount 10000 unusually large j also remittances previously have not come through Credit .Lyonnais /flease wire whether any objection to receiving money. ELL1NCER. E^LIHGER L CO. .Manchester March 5th 1918. *COPY Ho. 170951/04 2b, Oxford Street, JiiiiJCdESTSH. March 5th 191b. One Controller, Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, S.W. 1 Sir, V.'e have received a cable from Messrs. Haji Abdul Rahman Shirazee &amp; Son, Bombay, instructing us to receive from the Credit Lyonnais, London, a sum of £10,000, and to this effect we wired you this morning, as per confirmation enclosed herein. of this amount £1/2000 will be due to us from this firm to cover goods which we are about to ship on their account, and as we are expecting further large orders from them it is probable that the balance of this remittance is intended as cover for same. We have no reason tofdoubt 1 tnat this money is intended for other than the usual business transactions between us, but as we promised some time ago that in instances like the present in view of tne fact that we have not before received large remittances through this Bank, we deemed it right to ware you as we have done and we trust everytning will be in order. ''e are, Sir, Your obedient servants, (L-gned) Ellinger &amp; Co.i CO-T Ho. 10757^/o4 /'’'y . Foreign Trade Department Lancaster Louse, 1 * St.James' S. T J. 1 7th Larch 1918. Gentlemen, confirm the I am directed by Ur. Secretary Balfour to telegram sent to you by this Department of yesterday 1 s date informing you that there was no objection to your receiving the sum of £10,000 from Rahman Shirazi, of Bombay, through the Credit Lyonnais. I am, Gentle m n. Your most obedient, humble Serve it, (Signed) E. Uerton. for Controller. Uessrs. Eilinger 5c Co. , 28, Oxford Street, iLLJG FOSTER.\ GPY Uo. 107573/G4 j~ - jX» .':j jriiii * A • B 153 IB.16 Manchester R 74 CONTROLLER Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, St. James, SET. Referring 42078/34 your letter May ninth 1916 Rahman Shirazi ho mbay cables us to receive ten thousand pounds from Credit Lyonnais London have always received for many years considerable sums to Rahmans credit in ordinary course business amounting to a few thousand pounds but this amount 10000 unusually large also remittances previously have not come through Credit Lyonnais please wire whether any objection to receiving money ELLIRCER. \Copy. ■* $y Tel Prom - His Britannio Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, To - The Secretary to the^Jjovernment of India in the Following from Vice Consul Ahwaz. Begins. Abdul Hahim Arab on Statutory List is doing business with India through his brother Ali Arab and Mohammad Hussain Hagshina of Ahwaz. Letters correspondents are Haji Sayed kabdi Aulad Calcutta and Haji Hayed Mohamed Kamieruni Bombay. JMa. No. 88. Dated the 7th December 1917. Foreign and Political Department, Delhi 70 ICf \q(t.si onf i dent &lt; No* 27 - D* Govermaent of India* Department of Oommerce and Industry. Delhi, the 2nd January 1918. From To p« 0* Tallents, Esquire, Under Secretary to the Government of India, ill Collectors of Customs (except Chittagong) Sir, __ -ip-t-i-ftr 'Mn* 1484-D., dated the 18th With reference to my letoer imo* , December 1917, I am directed to say that 'Abdul Rabim Arab' who is on the Statutory List for Persia, is also known as 'Abdur- rahim Isfahan!' to which is some times added 'Mashhur Arab'. The name of his Calcutta correspondent should be 'Muhammad Mehdi Isfahan! wa Auladahu (M.M. I^ahani and Sons) and not as previously stated* I have, etc*, 3d. P. 0* Tallents, under Secretary to the Govermrat of Mia. No* 28»D* A copy is forwarded, in continuation of this Department . flm9nt No 1485-D., dated 13th December 1917, to the endorsement . ^ Madras, the Commission GoTernmants of Bo.!,.,. »« . Ooimr oial Iht.Ui- „ er in Sind and the Director General ot 501109 * f. &lt;= forwarded to the Foreign A copy of the correspondence is forward and Political Department. By order, etc., 34 . p. 0. Tallents, « rt-P India.Gopy of a memorandum from the Deputy Chief Censor, Army Head quarters, India, General Staff Branch, to the Cable Censors at Bombay, Oalcutta, Madras and Rangoon, to the Postal Censors at Aden, Bombay, Oalcutta, Karachi, Madras and Rangoon and to the Department of Commerce and Industry, No. 0-9136, dated Delhi, the 10th December 1917. Subject Statutory List R.im« The following telegram has passed through the office of the Cable Censor, Karachi : Prom - Peel, Ahwaz. To - Marling, Teheran. 0-12-17. Abdul Rahim Arab on statutory list is doing business with India through his brother Ali Arab and Mohamed Hussain Naqshina of Ahwaz Latters correspondents are Haji Sayed Mahdi Aulad, Oalcutta and Haji Sayed Mohamed Kazaruni, Bombay. C. OT of . confidential lett.r fro, 8. S. Hardy, B B1 nir., I.O.S., Hndar Hocrct.ry to «H. 8o«rn»nt of India, D.p.rt-nt of Co-arc. and Indnstry, to all Collectors of Oust™. (e»ept Chittagong), go, 1484-1)., dated Delhi, the 13th Decber 1917. I » directed to infor. you that it has teen brought to the „ T nr 4-1,-+ Abdul Rahim Arab, who is on notice of the Goyernment of India trough .V , tnrv List for Persia, is doing business with India through the Statutory -disi xor , his brother Hi Arab and «,h-.d Hu.aHn ^ latter'. »rr.sponde„t. are Haji S^ed Hahdi iul^i, Calcutta a. Haji Sayed lohamed Kazaruni, Bombay. No. 1485-D. 4 copy i. forwarded to the Credent, of B-ay, Bu^.BengH and Madras, to the Commissioner in Sma ana cO tne General of Commercial Intelligence. By order, etc., Sd. G. S. Hardy, Under secretary to the Goyernment of India.Copy of a memorandum from the Deputy Chief Censor, Army Head quarters, India, General Staff Branch, to the Cable Censors at Bombay, Calcutta, Madras and Bangoon, to the Postal Censors at Aden, Bombay, Calcutta, Karachi, Madras and Rangoon and to the Department of Commerce and Industry, No. 0-9B19, dated Delhi, the 13th December 1917. Subject Statutory List Birai. In continuation of my No. 0-9136, dated 8th December 1917, I forward, for information, copy of a further telegram wmcn nas passed through the office of the Cable Censor Karachi. From ** Haig, Ispahan* To - Peel, Ahwaz. 6th December 1917• 'Please warn All Arab and Mohamad Husain liaqshina ohao n oney continue to do bnsiness with Abdul Kahim Arab the, will be Plaoed on the Black list and let mo know result oi your warning”. Oeoy oi a memorandum fro. the Deputy Chief Censor. Army H.ad- uart.rs, India. Cneral Staff Branch, to the Cable Censors at lombay, Calcutta, Karachi, Itedras and Bongoon, to the Postal 'onsors at Aden, Calcutta, Itaaohi. Madras and Bangoon an » ^ Jepartment of Oo-erce and Industry, So. 0-9700, dateu e , iiOtli December 1917« Subiect Statuto ry List ^ - »ith rofarsuoe to my i»morandu. So. Cu91a6, datau 10th ece. e 191, the follows note has h.eu reoeiyed fro. the P.st^ Censor Bombay and is repeated for information i 'Abdurrahi. Arab is ^»o kn.™ aa Abdurr^i. Isfah^. » Whioh is sometimes added 'Mashhur Arab'. Im air.rd .tu. tn r, Calcutta correspondent she^d be M»h»»ai M.hdi Edine oi ais u . , vide Commerce and - - , . Aeeiadahu' (l*M. Isfabaui and bonsj, vi Isfahani wa Aulaaanu t M -u 1917. * n Wo 1699-0 . 1 ., dated 34th March i^i Indnst'nr Department u*o* •Uo. 167701/-34 rs The Controller of the roreiprn Trade Department presents his comuliments to the Secretary in the Political department, India office, and, wita reference to the communication from this Department of the 13th instant (166731/34} begs to inform him that the most recent reference to Abdul Rahim Arab in a letter from the India office is apparently contained in India Ofiice letter 1 • 4So4 oi iMovemoer 17, 1915, to the foreign office. foreign office, Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster house, St.James* S. . 1 18th February 1918.In any further communication on this subject, please quote * No. tmd address— The Controller, Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, St. James’, S.W. W k ; 9 \ 8 THE Controller of the Foreign Trade Department presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for ^hotio , and, by direction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, transmits herewith cop^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Trade Department, 191#. Deference to previous letter : \ _ (o t~l Letter Foreign Trade Department: 7 _ I Description of Enclosure. O n ' SL /54 Name and Date. Subject. filtq h/^Yr\ ^ V 4/ ya. r*r &lt;1 1^0 dS- %° jf3 M ^ ‘T*’ V^'rh, V [ l? J .)grf*''*'' ' •'-—V ^ 'A Q S (166731/34). * ■. 3 r:trv&gt;r.r?iv^’-.-.rr - ■ nw&amp;Mmmmm* * / G I 0 ! ^ - ^ i91 8 Cipher telegram to Ur C. darling (Teheran) foreign office # February 12th # 1910* U,p»£Q« Mo. .93, form. Your telegram Ko,. 91, t'hen the olack List was made Statutory in l arch 1916, Abdul HaMm Arab was retained therein by a clerical error., he should have been removed from the black List as a result of your telegram No. 72 of January 30th, 1916, the '-reply to which M# # 04 of February 3rd, informed you that Abdul had been blacklisted on the strength of Government of India despatch to you ho, 2o27 i, of October 19th, 1915, and that his name had now been removed. He will be removed from the ^atutary ^Ist as soon as possible*T. —' rki-iOE DEPT ’} 0 1 19 18 FILES ONLY. Decypher. Sir G.Marling (Teheran) February 8th&gt; 1918. D. 11 a.m. February 8th, 1918. R. 8 a.m. Februa^ 9th, 1918. No. 91 Forum • His Majesty’s Consul General at Ispahan states that nothing is known there or in India or Mesopotamia against Abdul Rahim Arab and recommends immediate removal from Statutory List. I know nothing against him, see my telegram No. 7 2 of January 30th, 1916 to which I can trace no answer.Coafidential . v* ', r v No# 1387-G# Political Departmeat# Bombay Oastle, 6th October 1917. / Prom J# So 0* Jukes, Isquire, Beputy Secretary to To Bombay, The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department. i 7 &lt;3 * iff Sir, / s In continuation of my telegram No.l30O-C., dated the 17th September 1917, I am directed to report for the informa tion of the (rovernmeht of India that, at the suggestion of the Bank of Bombay^ revised orders were issued, under which the Accountant General at Bombay was requested to pay the sum of Bs.28,000/# to Messrs, Haji Sultaaali Shushtary and Company on the terms mentioned in your telegram No«965-S,, dated the 14th September 1917, and to recover interest half yearly at the ^ate of 12 % per annum. 2, The need of secrecy regarding the concession granted to them has been/impressed upon Messrs. Haji Sultanali M Shushtary and Company. $ / I have, etc., Sd/- J. E. 0. Jukes, / Deputy Secretary to Government. p. i;o. s e c 9 NOV 1917 17 DEC '917Confidential. No. 1413-0. Political Department. Bombay Castle, 15tb October 1917. From J* E« C # Jukes, Esquire, Aoting Secretary to Government, Political Department, Bombay 9 if Tbe Foreign Secretary to tbe Government of Indi4, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with my letter No.l387«0., dated the 6th October 1917, I am directed to forward for the orders of the Government of India a copy of a letter dated the 8th October 1917 addressed to this of Bombay, relative to the terms on which it is decided to *’1 — — TT * • m •» h m •• . _ ^ ^ . _ affirmative to the first three points raised in the letter. the actual reason for keeping the matter secret, the loan being granted to Messrs* Kazeruni as a special concession* cannot be held responsible for the repayment of the loan or the payment of interest# The agreement being with Kazeruni, he must be the responsible party* 3* I am however to solicit the instructions of the Governs ment of India on the proposed reply and to request that at the same time informing Messrs* Shushtary and Company of / As regards the fourth point it is presumed that Messrs* Shushtary and Conqjany in acting merely as agents for KazerunipWpj ■ • ' ■ - loo Copy of a letter from Messrs. Haji Sultaaali Shashtary and C©* # Bombay, to the Deputy Secretary to Government, Political Department, Bombay, dated the 8th October 1917# have the honour to state that on the 19th ultimo, the G # I*D* called our representative and informed him that the Government had instructed the Bank of Bombay to pay to Hajee Mahomed Hussein Kazeruni of Ispahan a Loan of Rs.28,OOO bearing interest at 12 % per annum, and we may receive that amount as his agent, but to keep the matter a secret* About a week after thin, the CeI«D« again called up and informed us that we are to apply to the Accountant General for the above amount, and not to the Bank of Bombay* In this matter the said Hajee Mahomed Hussein Kazeruni of Ispahan has advised us to receive a sum of Rso28,000/**, but he does not mention that this amount is a Loan, bearing interest at 12 ^ per annum* - As we are to act in this matter simply as Agents, we require clear instructions from the above-named party, to . . _ lQu. his account, but owing to the receive this amount as a Loan, wgx&amp;rgxnnablyxigxE&amp;k instruc tions from the C.IJD*, we are unable to ask instructions from that party in this matter* In order to make our position clear, we respectfully request you to enlighten us on the following points, if you think it advisable, viz* (1) Are we allowed to ask the said Haji Mahomed Hussein Kazeruni by wire for instructions as regards the terms 'Loan” and 'insterest”? (2) After getting this point cleared can we enter this amount in our books, and to communicate the receipt thereof to the above-named party in letters in the usual business-like way ? (3) Gan we pass this amount on to the said Kazeruni ?(O After paying* him off this amount, are we to remain in W£ y responsible for the repayment of the principal amount 4' or its interest or not ? / A reply to the above in writing will highly oblige♦Telegram - p 0 From «• The Se ore tar; India To ^ His Britanni Tehran# No# 1056«S# Bated 25th October in the ] Department, Simla t Kindly telegraph what directions yon wish given to Shushtary# They wish to telegraph Kazemni for instructions to accept money on terms y#n mention and to pass amount on to Kazeruni, and enquire whether they remain responsible for re« payment of loan and interest after paying amount pk Kazeruni# This is with reference to my telegram 974-S#, September 19th# / No* 80# dated and reed# 1st November 1917* Your telegram 1056-S* Kazerun says he has telegraphed to Shushtari instructing him to receive money and place it to credit of Kazeru^s account with him# Shushtari may be informed that he is onsible for neither the loan nor the interest as Mazeruni Telegram R# From « His Britannic Majesty 1 s Minister, Tehran, To « The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla# all responsibility#Telegram - P. Prom *• The Secretary to the Groverament of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To « The Secretary to the (jovemment of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay* No* 1086-S* Dated the 2nd November 1917. Following telegram has been received from His Majesty 1 s Minister at Tehran, No.BO dated 1st November* Be gins * Kazeran says x x x all responsibility* Ends * Please act in accordance with the above instructions. This is with reference to your letter No.l413**C. of the 15th October./OS' (3 Copy. Confidential , No. 1387-C. Political Department, Bombay Castle, 6tli October 1917. Prom J.E.C. Jukes, Esquire, Deputy Secretary to Government,'Bombay To The Foreign xxx Secretary to the Government of India, In continuation of my telegram No.1300-0, dated the Ivtli. September 1917, I am directed to report for the informa tion of the Government of India that, at the suggestion of the Bank of Bombay, revised orders were issued, under which x me Accountant General at Bombay was requested to pay the sum of BSo28,000/~ to Messrs. Haji Sultanali Shushtary and Company on the terms mentioned in your telegram No. 965-3, aa ted the 14th September 1917, and to recover interest half yearly at the rate of 12 % per annum. ueeu secrecy regarding the concession granted to them has been impressed upon Messrs. Haji Sultanali Shushtary and Company. Foreign and Political Department. Sir, I have, etc.. 8d. J.E.C. Jakes, Deputy Secretary to Government.Confidential. No. 1413-4). Political Department, Bombay Castle, 15th October 1917. From J.E.C. Jukes, Esq., Acting Secretary to Government, political Department, Bombay, To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with my letter No. 1387-0, dated the 6th October 1917, I an directed to forward for the orders of the Government of India a copy of a letter dated the 8th October 1917 addressed to this Government by Messrs. Saji Sultanali Shushtary and Company of Bombay, relative to the terms on which it is decided to release to Saji Mahomed lazeruni half the amount of his deposit. 2. The Government of Bombay propose to reply in the affirma tive to the first three points raised in the letter, at the same time informing Messrs. Shushtary and Company of the actual reason for keeping the matter secret, the loan being granted to Messrs. Kazeruni as a special concession. As regards the fourth point it is presumed that Messrs. Shushtary and Company in acting merely as agents for laser uni cannot be held responsible for the repayment oi the loan or the payment of interest. The agreement being with Kazeruni, he must be the responsible party. 3. i m however to solicit the instructions of the Government of India on the proposed reply and to request that orders may be communicated by telegram. I have, etc., Bdo J.hod. Jukes, Acting Secretary to GcTernment.ment, Bombay, dated the 8th October 1917. We have the honour to state that on the 19th ultimo, the l.l.D. called our representative and informed him that the informed us that we are to apply to the Accountant Qenerai for the above amount, and not to the Bank of Bombay. In inis matter the said Hajee Mahomed Hussein Kaaeruni of Ispahan has advised, us to receive a sum of Bs.28,GGC/~, but he does not mention that this amount is a Loan, bearing interest As we are t-c act in this matter simply as Agents, we require clear instructions from the above-named party, to receive this amount as a Loan, on his account, uut owing- to the instructions from the G.I.D., we are unable to ask instructions from that party in this matter. In order to make our position clear, we respectfully request you to enlighten us on tne following points, if you think it advisable, viz: ^1/ mxq we allowed to ask the said Haji Mahomed Hussein Kazeruni by wire for instructions as regards the terms ^oan” and 'Interest* 1 ? {M} After ^erting this point cleared can ?/e enter this amount in our books, and to communicate the receipt thereof to the above-named party in letters in the usual business like way? (3) Can we pass this amount on to the said Kazeruni? Government had instructed the Bank of Bombay to pay to Hajee Maimed Hussein Eazeruni cf Ispahan a Loan of Bs.28,000/- hearing interest at 12$ per annum, and we aay receive that amount as his ag 0 -.it, out io keep the matter a secret. About a week after this, the C.I.D. again called us and at 12f 0 per annum. {4; Alter paying him off Shis mount, are we to remain in any way responsible for the repayment of the mmkviM principal amountTelegram - r. Cspy. From - The Secretary to the C-overnment of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To - His Britannic Majesty^ Minister, Tehran. No* 1056-S. Dated 25th October 1917. Kindly telegraph what directions you wish given to Shushtary. They wish to telegraph Kazeruni for instructions to accept money on terms you mention and to pass amount on to Kazeruni, and enquire whether they remain responsible for repayment of loan and interest after paying amount to Eazeruni. This is with reference to my telegram 974-S., September 19th.telegram P 3^^ ?rom - Eis Britannic Hajast^’s lainistar* Telircn. !To xhe Secretary bo the lovarment of India in the foreign and Political Department, Simla (Sepeated to the foreign Office with reference to 'Tehran telegram 'OoYSE^F^T. of the 7th Deoemher 1916)* Lo•67 9 dated the 6th reed* 7th September 1917* as lO zerimi is short of ready money he asks for permission to borrow half his deposit from us. Consul General Ispahan reports that he is under control and has been behaving correctly. Provided arrangement is kept secret so as not to form precedent I see no objection* Interest should be usual bank rate here at 12$. If you agree Bank of Bombay should be instructed by you to release to Shuster! on above terms the sura of Bs.B8,Caa * This is with reference to your telegram of the 1st December 1916, ho*940-3. !elegram P * ! rom - The Secretary to the Government of India &gt; in the foreign and Political Department, oimls , r o ~ The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department. :o.965-3*, dated the 14th September 1917. My telegram 1025-3., December 15aa l^lo. following ielagraa from Minister Tehran ITo.57, dated September 6t^. 3 e£i^s. .is Eazernni is short x ^ the sum of Bs«28 ,CCC • s . g: x x T7e agree. Xfyo^see no objection please inform Banli accordingly and reoe4pt action taxen. A M f«at MM* -m* —* v “ ii i ; : 1 oLO; I INDIA F O’DEIGN SECRET Ar; r ., i-&lt;£i.3P. No. y q i i 21 SEP 1917 , Raceiverf 24 OCT &gt;95telegram P. Irom - The Deputy Secretary to the Government of ''-'V # Political Department t To ~ fhe Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign &amp; Political Department, Simla. Do.ISOC-C• 9 dated 17th reed. 18th September 1917. Kazeruni. 1 have instructed Bank of Bombay to release on the terms laid down by His Britannic Ha jesty 1 s Minister at Bekran half the deposit to Shustari* Phis is with reference to your telegram ho.965-3. ? dated the 17th instant, felegram - P * Prom - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, ro - Eis Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. 21 o o 9 74-3. Dated the 19th September 1917. hs desired by you Bank of Bombay has been instructed to release half deposit to Shustari on terms stated. Phis is vith reference to your telegram 67, September 6tt[ S ] V v In any further communication cm this subject, please quote No S^88 and address The Controller, Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, St. James’, S.W, SC'S! 5 &amp; &amp; &lt;8 .V vmr j i THE Controller of the Foreign Trade Department presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for t and, by direction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, transmits herewith cop v of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Trade Department, C l Reference to previous letter: Letter Trade Department: 1, Description of Enclosure. 2.W tcjij Name and Date. Subject. “w c. ( rcJLjt^»-a_Iv. 9 'T7 (Similar letter sent to/IS' (W) k v \ fThis Pocnment is Pie Property of Mis B rit anmc Majesty^ Goverameist, an d shooM be return ed le the Foreign Office whea done witii imicss rc qmrci for oMclail tase.] ♦ % i -ft 'WS V :wiw PILES ONLY . Decypliar. Sir G. fiarlina; itsiierah), September 6th. D. 4,45.p.m. September 6th. 1917. H. 6.10.p.m. September 7th. 1917. Mo.300. 1917. Your telegram No.940S December 1st. last year. Kaaeruni (sic) is short of money and asks for permission to borrow from us half his orders. Consul General at Ispahan reports that he has been behaving correctly and is under control. I see no objection, provided arrangement is kept secret so as not to form precedent. Interest should be 125o usual bank rate here. If you agree, please instruct bank at Bombay to release rupees 28,000 to Shusteri (sic) on above terms. Addressed to India (? sent to Peking), liepeated t0 Foreign' Office'Wref^rence to Teheran telegram Mo.752 P.T. December 7th last year.——I Hu Minute Paper. ' i ^ Secret Department. 4) c/ ft/ //o 3// Dated Rec- 2 q To Under Secretary. Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary. Secretary of State Date. Initials. SUBJECT. 7L. l*Jc l CvDtfc. 2, —v Copy to -^5 - / Ttt-.TxJy IkfJr. 2/ FOR INFORMATION. p~Y I?r\Indexsd. ication ( o&lt;y 7S~/ In any further communication oa this subject, please quote No. and address— The Controller, Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, St. James’, S.W. 3* /\P i £&gt; * 5 191$. ter* Letter ^ Foreign Trade Department: Name and Date. /s F 1HL Controller of the Foreign Trade Department presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for 3 and, by direction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Trade Department, Deference to previous letter : Description of Enclosure. Subject jrStn^ V7 FEB 1917-——COPY. 1097S1/34 28, Oxford Street, Manchester. February 13th 1917. The Controller, The Foreign Trade Dept. Lancaster House, St. James. S.W. Sir, We confirm our telegram of this morning, as per copy enclosed, informing you that in accordance with the request of Messrs Haji Abdul Rahman Shirazee 4 Son of Bombay, we were remitting to-day by telegram to Messrs E. D. Sassoon 4 Co., of London, the sum of £1,000. As a payment to the latter firm on behalf of our Bombay friends has not been in the ordinary course of our transactions during recent years, it appeared to us that you might desire to be made aware of the payment. We are, Sir, Your obedient servants. (sd) Ellinger 4 Co. Enel. nger 4 Co., B, Oxford Street, Manchester.I ) (3 spy. 109751/34 13/2/17* -J-X.ii. From ELLIHGER &amp; CO. MANCHESTER. FOREIGN TRADE DEPARTMENT. LONDON referring your letter 42078/34 ninth May last acting on request of Rahman Bombay we are telegraphing Ed SASSOON London today remittance of one thousand pounds* ELLINGER. ,1 ptf iiQM411 In any further communication on this subject, please quote No IO&lt;j53&gt; and address— — * The Controller, Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, St. James’, S.W. Tlshl yilJsj 159 I 9 ) 9110 )0 m IHL Controller of the Foreign Trade Department presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for 'J 'K'd-vet and, by direction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. S Foreign Trade Department, Ilf ^ 1919. 7 Reference to previous letter to Letter | rom Foreign Trad^Department: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. &lt;d Co Subject. /3 WG.B. COPY 4S0W/M. . 28, OXFORD STREET, MANCHESTER. May 6th 1916. The Controller, Foreign Trade Dept. Lancaster louse, Westminster. S.W. Sir With reference to your letter of the 10th ult. No. 33467/34, informing us that Sir E. Grey is unable to grant us a license to ship goods to Haji Abdul Rahman Shiraaee St Sons, of Bombay, we notice that in the 'London Gazette' of the 2nd inst the firm of Haji Abdur Rahim Shirazi, Bombay and Shiraz, has been removed from the Statutory List, and we shall be glad to hear if this is the same firm as that mentioned above, and whether we are now at liberty to resume our business relationship with the firm without restriction. We are, Sir, Faithfully yours (Sd) Ellinger &amp; Co. Ellinger 4 Co, 28 Oxford Street Manchester.*: ^ J2J f^npv 4R07B/34. W . T. j .1245 ; V, M &gt; S' -w' ? / FOREIGN TRADE DEPARTMENT, LANCASTER HOUSE, ST. JAMES. S.W. 9th May 1916. i Mi Ah# fiflA ■t l. Gentlemen, In reply to your letter of the 6th inst., I am directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to inform you that the firm of Haji AMur Rahim Shiraai of Bombay and Shiraa which was notified in the London Gazette of the 2nd inst*: as a removal from the Statutory List of prohibited firms in Persia, is identical with the firm Haji Abdul Rahman Shirazee &amp; Sono of Bombay. This Department will accordingly now offer no objection to your resuming your business relationship with this firm. I am. Gentlemen, Your mo st obedient, humble servant, Messrs. Elliier Co., A 2R, oxford Street, Manchester. for the Controller130 109551. Telegram (en clair) from Mp. Ellinger, Man dies'ter. To Foreign Trade Department. Despatched 10.31 February 13th 1917. Received 12.36 February 13th 1917. \ui\ Hod 213 Mel Referring your letter 42078/34 ninth May last acting on request of Rahman, Bombay we are telegraphing Ed. Sassoon London today remittance of one thousand pounds. id) 0 'T&gt;'’ .tAlrf to-irmr^r f' Copy 131828/15. I 1917 FILES OLLY Telegram (en clair) from ^lr. Marling (Teheran) D. 12.46 p.m. R. 6.0.p.m. No. 337. September 15th 1915. Following King’s Regulation issued yesterday. Whereas it has been represented to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs that certain firms and individuals in Persia of enemy nationality'and well dis posed to His Majesty the King Emperor, and that trading with such persons is not prejudicial to the interests of His Majesty: I Charles Murray Marling, C.B., C.M.G., His Majesty’s Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to the Court of Persia in virtue of the authority vested in me by Articles 3 and 5 of the Persian Regulations Order in Council of 1901 declare that trading by His Majesty’d subjects with suc£ peroons is not anc. shall not be considered as a contravention of the King Emperors Regulations respecting trading with the enemy^by me on June 27th. last. Lists of such well-disposed enemy subjects selected at my discretion are kept at the Foreign Office in London and at His Majesty’s Legation and Consulates in Persia and licenses to trade with such enemy firms and individuals will be issued at those offices to which all enquiries as to such firms and individuals are to be addressed.In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. r le'tq and address— The Controller, Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, St James’, S.W. 744 i S S !7 ~i4 THE Controller of the Foreign Trade Department presents his compliments to the Secretary , and, by direction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, transmits herewith cop tj paper. 5 of the under-mentioned Foreign Trade Department, SC to , 19m 7 Reference to .etter Foreign r Frade epartment: from ous letter: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^ I I . Jnrtrv^ - 3^. R 47 . /^rNo. 11058. PERSIA. Decypher Mr. Marling (Teheran) January 6th. D. 11.30 a.ra. January 6th. /u R. 2.10 p.m. J anuary 7 th. I *«£■' No. 11 (K) Forum. My telegram No. 560. Imperial Bank of Persia who are anxious to get in as many Krans as possible for financing of moratorium etc. ask whether they may do business with persons in question to extent of selling drafts on London. They point out that this would only take money out of the hands of these people here where alone it could do mischief. They would only propose to sell in at present and in view of fact of German flight I can see no objection. In any case operation could be carried out indirectly in such a way that we could not detect it. t Addressed to Foreign Office, sent to India.0) 136 mam No. 11058/54. ? 9 i '7 Telegram Cypher to sir C. Marling, Teheran. Despatched P.0. 6.50 p.m. JanuEsry 27th 1917. No. 36. Forum. Your telegram No. 11 of January 6th 1916. Imperial Bank of Persia is now the only British Bank in neutral territory which is permitted to have any dealings with firms on the Statutory List. Unless therefore, the considerations explained in your telegram still hold good, or unless you see any other strong objection to such a course, please instruct Bank to cease selling drafts to firms and persons on the Statutory List.&gt;37 No. 10798 FILES ONLY . Decypher. Sir C. Marling (Teheran) February 2nd 1917. D. 5.15 p.m. February 2nd 1917. R. 8 a.m. February 3rd 1917. No. 47. Your telegram No. 36. In vie a oi Tinancial position in Persia I hope matters may be allowed to stand as they are for the present.opy. Fran - Hie Secretary to the Government of Bomba: Telegram 12'! ruvcCTimeno embay, Political Department, The Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department# No. 3183-0. Dated the 15th Please let us know if following telegram may be passed Mgoosiui, Bombay, to Ali Zayani, Bahrein, begins. Give Abdul Pahman Awazi 7,500. End of message. As Abdul Eahman may be Arab of same name shown in Persian Biack List telegram has been held up here. Telegram P# From - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To — The Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. No. 1085-8#, dated the 30th December 1916. Following enquiry has been made by Bombay Government 'Please let me know * * * * held up here.* Kindly let me have your views by telegraph. Letter. llo. 0 M Dated 19 JAiJ 1917 10 FEB 1917 ReceivedTelegram P* Frcm - Major A* P. Trevor, C,I*E, ^ Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To — The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, No, 52, Dated the 8th ^ January 1917, Reed, the 8th Political -Agent, Bahrein, reports that a clerk, the factotum of a Persian Merchant, Yusuf Khunji, local agent of tile ' Ja ' panese lin8 &gt; is the only person named Abdul Rahman Awazi. ±1 wire is allowed to pass he will try to watch this transac- Abdul Rahman Arab is the only one I find on Black List, This is with reference to your telegram No, 1G85-S* From - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To — Tlie Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, No, 48-S. Datea the 9th January 1917, Following from Trevor 52, January 8th, Begins, Political Agent * * * * 1085-S, Ends. Telegram may be passed and Trevor informed. This is with reference to your telegram 3183-C. December Bushire tion tr Telegram P 15th,Frcro To ~ Telegram P. The Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department* No* 6G* Dated the 9th Reed, the 9th January 1917. For Abdul Rahman in last paragraph of my telegram No. 52 please read Abdul Rahim. From - To --- Telegram P. The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, The Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department No. 52-S. Dated the 10th January 1917. Please read Abdul Rahim and not Abdul Rahman in the last0 h*' '%!■ JTelegrain - P. * ,, ^ Prom - Tlie Secretary to the Government of Bombay, relitioa! Department, To - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi* No. 3137-0. Dated and received the 9th December 1915. Is there any connection between the Kerman Firms Haji kuhammad Dilmagani and Haji Muhammad Nelinkani. Latter is Black Listed and Postal Censor suspects the two are identical. Will you kindly enquire and inform Government of Bombay. Peiearan* ?. Prom - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, - Hi s Britannic Maj e siy ? s Oonsul, Kernan. To (Repeated to Bushire). ’No. 1000-S. Dated the 11th December 1915. Following from Government of Bombay 3137-0 dated 9th December. Begins. Is there any x Government of Bombay. Bads. Please supply required information by telegram. LKCLGi UHE INDIA. FOREIGN SECRET A F.l’C Letlar. Ko. Q7 M Dated 22 DEC 1916 Received 27 JAN 1917Telegram - P* From - His Britannia i»iajesty ! s Consul, Kerman, To - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. (Repeated to Bushire). No. 333/51. Dated and received the 13th December 1915o Your telegram lio. lOGO-Bo neither names Jelinljani or Dilmaghani appear on latest Blacl List received from Legation under date July 6th. My previous enquiries failed to establish existence of any one named Welinkani. I understand that Mahomet Dilmaghani of Tabriz had some transactions with Ittahadie of Tehran who no longer figure on latest Black List received from Tehran* There is however no reason I believe to suspect him. He has an agent here called Ahmad who affects name Dilmaghani but is no relation To best of my knowledge he is harmless. The firm has some business relationship with Stevens H. M f s Vice Consul Tabriz.J 3 ’’ mo 9 i 7 IS'! Telegram. H, Trom - His Britannic majesty’s Minister, Tehran, To ihe Becretary to the •Government of India in the foreign and Political Department, No.153. Dated the 5th Reed, the 6th f . 'ui rn •••VT.y' V&gt; ..Tip December 1916. hour telegram No.94(M3. I see no objection. Telegram. T. from - The Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department, To - The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Depar tment. No. 977-S* Dated the 6th December 1916. There is.no objection to Shustari arranging the deposit as su ggested in your telegram No.3066-0., dated 29th November 1916o ind/a foreign secretary^ Letter - ^ 97 M Cated 22 DEC 1916 Received 27 JAN 1917Copy, r 11 s - 1 Telegram P, 19 IT £'4 November 1916, ■ 4 i Frcm - Hie Secretary to the Govermfentf' of Bombay' W I P ol i t i c al Dep artment # ^ To — Hie Secretary to the Government of India in tlie Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Dated the IQth Heed, the 19th No. 295i-C„ Is Bank of Bengal’s half of deposits to be paid into Bombay Branch bmk ? .Agent States Branch has no authority to receive deposits. This is with reference to your telegram 849-$,, of 6th November. Telegram, P* From - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign end Political Department, Delhi, To — His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. No. 903-S. Dated the 21st November 1916. The Agent Bank of Bengal Bombay states that branch has no authority to receive deposits. In these circumstances may the full deposit be paid into Bombay Bank. This refers to your telegram 141 of November 5th regarding Mahomet Hussein Kazeruni’s remittance. U r-civod on |. g J A M | p 1 7 with INDIA FOBEIGM SECRETARY’S Isttep. No. 93 M r - sd 8 DECTelegram P. **rom - ihe Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, To --- The Secretary to the Government of India iu tne foreign and Political Department, Delhi, No. 2981-0* Dated the 21st Heed* the 22nd November 1916* On the a7th Novemoer Sultan Ali Shustari and Co.^ sent oiieque for Es. 28,000/- on Hong Kong and Shanghai Bank on behalf of M. H. Kazeruni of Ispahan, to Bank of Bombay, and askea tne Bank to intimate its receipt to the Consul General Ispahan, but they have not done so. Foregoing is in continuation of my telegram of the 18th November 2951-C. Telegram P. Frora - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To --- His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran* No* 918'-S* Dated the 23rd November 1916. Please refer to my telegram No. 903-S dated November 21st regarding Ka^eruni. Telegram from Bombay Government No. 2981-0 dated 21st November 1916* Begins. On the 17th November * * * have not done so. Ends./€T6 Telegram P j*rua - The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, To — Ihe Secretary to tiia Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. No* 3060-C* Ify 398I-C of 21st November* On 20th Bombay Branch of ky telegram 918-8, November Bird* Bembay Government report 29th instant that Bank of Bengal Bembay Branch received on 20th Bs, 28,000/- from Shustari for deposit on account of Kaz&amp;runi* Shustari desires to withdraw sum to pay it into Bombay Bank. See my telegram 903-S of November 21st. Have you any objection ? Batea the 29th Reed, the 29th November 1916 Boik of Bengal received Ra. 28,000/- from Shustarti for deposit on account of Kasaruni of Ispahan. Shustari noi desires refund so as to pay it into Bank of Bombay. Is now Is there any objection ? Telegram R„ - ran - Hie Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign ^nd Political Department, Delhi, To — His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran, No. 940-S. Dated the 1st December 1916.Copy) |5''B a 1 i Oiii “ ills Brioannic iuaj e^ty 1 s kiiiister, Teiiran t To - The Secretar} 7, to the Government of India in the Foreign k Political'Department, l; f/l * ! £7/q Ct * r~ w —^ No. 136. Dated the 20th heed, the 21st K October 1916, 916 At the request of Itteiiadieh, nho had remitted upv/axcis ox 100,000 hs. to Abdul iahixian, Shirazi, at Bombay ^ars Trading uoiapany are?/ bills of exchange on Bombay for account of Ittenadieh* Latter psleads that as tne business was conducted with Abdul Lehman at Shiraz whose name has been removed from statutory list acid there was nothing to show that Company was involved he was justified in thinking that there was no objection. He says that if ks the bills of exchange are declined he will lose lojfge sum on exchange c.nd he asks whether you will allow acceptance of bills drawn by Pars Trading Company for his account up to October 4th since when he has discontinued similar transactions- Telegram. P, ~ The oecretar}- tc the GovenMient of India in the loreign u Political Departriient, Siml To - The Secretary to the Government of Bombay u t Political Department, Bombay. No. 6D6-S. Dated the 9th November 1916. « Minister Tehran tele^aphs,. * * Be 0 ins. At the recyaeot similar transactions# Ends. Acceptance of bills may be permitted. Minister informed, Telegram. L. a rom - Tne Secretary to the Government of Indie^ Foreign a Political Department, Simla l To - His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran# No. 657-S, Dated the 9th November 1916. Your telegram 166 October 20th. Acceptance of bills drawn by Pars Trading Company on ccocount Ittehadieh permitted. Bombay Governcient informed.Telegram, B* Fran - His Britannic Maje To — The Secretary to sty's I^Hnister, Tehran, tiie Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. No. 141. Dated the 5th November 1916* Heed, the 6th Your telegram No* 829-S* Money has been remitted and Ka&amp;eruni is instructing Shusteri by telegraph to pay it to Banks* Please inform me when this lus been done. Telegram* E, From - Tlie Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To — Hie Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department* No* 849-S* Dated the 6th November 1916* Your telegram 278I-C* November 1st* Minister, Tehran, telegraphs as follows* Begins. Money has has been done. Ends* and Remittance is to be paid half and half into Bank of Bengal Bank of Bombay* Please telegraph required report*u 19815 I 1573 500 11/15 Register No. R. &amp; S., No .W.T., 6775/ 1916. 191 . Referred to tlie Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 5th December Relative to an inquiry made by Messrs. Heyn, Franc and Company of Manchester, a.s to whether Mr. Mohammea Hussein Dedashty of Bombay is a suitable suoject with whom they could have business relations Dra.ft letter to the former. For concurrence in the draft letter, and any observations. (SD.) L.D.WAKELY. I concur in the draft letter. \J (SD.) A.iriRTZEL. 7. 12. 1516.■ '——- . Ut eference Paper. Political and Secret Department. Register No. R , &amp; S# f #T#62 84. Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 9th November, 1916 Business relations between Mr. M.H. Dehdashti and Bushire firm which has been placed on Statutory List. Letter from G. of I. &amp; enclosure. Proposal to send papers to Foreign Trade Dept, for information. For information or any observations. (Sdi) L.D.Wakely. 9.11. M L.J.Kershaw, 10 . 11 . Seen: no observations. (Sd.) J.E.Shuckburgh. (Intld.) A.H. 11.11.16.12332. I. 2457. 500.-12/1911. leference Paper. Letter No. R. &amp;, 3.W.T.4089. &gt; ***2*- Department. Bee. 191 ^ Referred to Political Secretary 4th day of August 1916 Li91 * ; trading with the enemy in Persia. uvGiidashti 1 s relations with Oho lam Ali and Mohammed Bagher Behbehani and Sons Bushire. Enquiry of Messrs. Heyn, Franc and Company. For information and any observations. (Sd.) L.D.Wakely. Please see papers flagged below. I think it would be well to inform Government of India. (3d.) A.Hirtzel. 7/8/1916.HEYN, FRANC &amp; C° MANCHESTER and BRADFORD. Telegrams: HEYN, MANCHESTER. Codes used: WHITELAW'S 400,000 WORDS ,1 202,599 ,, ,, 53,000 ENGLISH WORDS 500 MILLION WORDS i, 1,020 MILLION WORDS ABC Sth EDITION PARKER’S 1,000 MILLION WORDS BEITH'S B FIGURE CODE A1 CODE HAWKES PREMIER CODE LIEBER’ B CODE ROSS-MOSS CODE PRIVATE CODES. uc/ie'j tel &gt; July I0th/I6 . r 2/37 ! The India Office, Whitehall. LONDON. Dear Sirs, HAJI APDUR SHIRAZI. We have heard from the Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, St. James, S.W., who have written us as follows-: 'The firm of Haji Abdur Shirazi, of Bombay 4 Shiraz, ^was removed from the Statutory Lift for Persia on nMay 2rd last.. You should, however, apply to the ?f Irdia Office for inforraation as to the Bombay House*. We do not quite understand what they mean, but the information whicn we wish to ascertain is, as to whether we are allowed to trade and work: with the above firm*. Awaiting your report, We are, Dear Sir, Yours faithfully. 11 JUL ISIS . i &lt;fe .. ■emmBammm r) lV J Telegram-P. From --- The Deputy Political Eesident in the Persian Gulf, flT Bushire, PoTh e Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. No. 673. (Mdressed Basra, repeated Tehran). Dated the 13th (reed, the 14th) April 1916. t Until authority over the districts mentioned has been recovered by the Persian Government it would in my opinion be better to continue present arrangement with Indian Banks. This is with reference to Foreign Department telegram 41 S. r —p I u Telegram.! ; o ; -.g L. 1 ; ° From — The Hon’ble Lieut: Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.S.I., K # C.I.E., Political Pesident in the Persian Gulf, Basra, To------- The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. Nr '’700 A (Address eel Foreign&gt; repeated Minister and Bushire.) Dated the 15th (reed, the 16th) April 1916. Your 41 S. I think it would be premature to remove restrictions until recovery of control by Central Government is accomplished fact. Addressed Foreign; repeated Minister and Bushire. Received on 4 J U L 13 i U wiUx INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Letter. No. ^ 3 M E - ted 2 J UN 1916From K.BJvPs Minister, Tehran, To------ The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, S i m 1 a . No, 66- Dated, the 21st May 1916, Feed, the 21st May 1916, Your telegram No, 157 S. Imperial Bank of Persia inform me that their Agent in Bombay telegraphs Behdashti is not allowed to receive monies from that Agent in connection with remittances to Kawam in Shiraz, Please give Behdashti necessary permit otherwise V —* V .fa. no arrangement for financing Kawam* T e 1 e g r a m - P, From --- The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla, p 0 R.B.M’s Minister, Tehran. No. 226 S, Dated the 28th May 1916, Action requested in your telegram 68, May 21st has been taken.ternmaammssssamm COPY OF TELEGRAM. From Viceroy Foreign Department DkTKv 29 th June, 1916 % Received at London Office Please inform Pllinger and Company Manchester and Manchester and Liverpool Bank London that there is now no objection to their dealing with ffaji Abdur Rahman Shiraz i of Bombay m view of removal of films name from Black List, Addressed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to Tehran.(COPY). i I ^ “ % T « C. i I {&gt;• ;legram . Prom - T;hr55cretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, To - - The Secretary to the Government oT India in the Foreign &amp; Political Department,Delhi No,53Q-C. Dated (and received) the 29th February 1916. Please see your memorandum 158-W., dated 3rd instant. Government oT Bombay request instructions regarding renewal of deposits reported in their letter 2723-0. of 28th December 1915. One of which matures on 1st March 1916 and the other on 2ist March 1916.' .wiejit. iiii • (copy). No. 546 C. of 1916. Political Departraent, Bombay Castle, 3rd March 1916. From J. E. C, Jukes, Esquire, Deputy Secretary to Government, Bomtay, To The Foreign Secretary *go the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. Sir &gt; In continuation of rny letter Do.356 0., dated tne 8th Fehruary 1916, I am directed to forward here with, for the information of the Government of India, a copy of a report received from the Commissioner in Sind, N0.629-W., dated the 24th February 1916, in regard to the financial transactions of the Shikarpur merchant, Mohandas Chatandas. I have, etc., 3d/- J.S.C. Jukes, Deputy Secretary to Government .mu.Confidential No. 629-W» of 1916, Political Department, Office of the Commissioner in Bind, 24th February 1916. Ivl emorandurn. In continuation of his memorandum No.T,-87-W., dated the 2nd instant, the Commissioner in Bind has the honour to report that neither the Sind Criminal 1 nvestigation Department' nor the Sind Railway Police, in spite of sui exhaustive search carried out under the personal direction of Mr. Mayter, has been able to discover any trace of the missing box containing the papers relating to the enquiry into the financial transactions of the Shikarpur merchant, Mohandas Chatandas. The Commissioner accordingly submits the report due to Government from his recollection of the contents of the papers and his personal knowledge of the case. 9 ^ * The correspondence arose on the complaint of the British Vice-Consul at Kerman that the agent of the firm of Monandas Chatandas at Kerman had supplied an enemy agent with funds whicn he knew or ought to have known would reach the German emissaries in Persia andwould thereby replenish their diminished resources. The Commissioner was asked to enquire whether there was ah/ evidence to show that the ohikarpur proprietors of the firm had connived at the transaction, with a view to serious notice being taken of their conduct if they were found to be guilty of such offence 3. Immediately on receipt of the intelligence the Commissioner arranged that all the telegraphic and postal correspondence of trie firm should be censored, and confidential enquiries were set on foot. Every single one of the numerous censored letters and telegrams which passed between the firm and its branches in Persia showed that their monetary transac tions related to the remittance of money tShjUmrmih. # by the branches of the firm in Persia, In no single case was money sent to Persia £ho;a_lndiiJt. Tnei e was not the slightest evidence of complicity on trie part of tnis firm, or of any of trie otner j.ir,ifo of Shikarpuri merchants whose correspondence was also censored, of helping the enemy financially or of doing proprietors were constantly urging their agento 1 i sellanHHi sell goods for cash owing to the insecurity in Persia and to remit the sale proceeds to India without delay where it was wanted owing to the tightness of the money market. The procedure followed in remitting the money was to make cash payments'into the branch of the Imperial Bank of Persia at Kerman and to draw on the Bombay Branch or the Hongkong Bank, who are the Indian agents of the former bank, for the amounts in quest As already reported, the enquiries which the Comrnis- oiOiier uas made into trie matter have led him to the conclusion tiiao the transactions oif the Shikarpuri firms were purely harmless: this conclusion is supported by the personal enquiries made under the Commissioner’s orders at Chikarpur by the Collector and the Superintendent of Police. Mohandas Chatandas himself is the head of the Shikarpur trading firm of that name with branches in Bomba;/, Karachi, Bandar abbas, Kerman and Bemiavad. He is a trader, pure and simple, and is not suspected of any political leanings whatso ever I 'i{$3 xi.crixid.il 'Oj Laatandas, rvSPinan, (i • g» 'by Dialrial Tlianwai*- rnal, the managing partner in Kerman of the firm of &gt; Mohandas Chatandas) addressed to Chatandas, Shikarour, (the firm’s headquarters). This telegram was held up and has never been delivered: the text was as follows: Vemshid Hormoydiar has remitted Bombay rupees 6000 from Yezd Bank. In return has drawn on us Krans 25000 and we payed (sic) Bahimof Yedzi merchant. British Consul has written Shikarpur. Be aware.” This telegram obviously refers to the report by the Vice Consul at Kerman regarding the Kerman agent’s transaction, and the latter having been informed by the Consul that the matter was being reported, sent this telegram to acquaint the head of the firm at Shikarpur with the action which he had taken. The telegram appears to mean that one Jemshid Hormoydiar had remitted to Bombay to the credit of Mohandas Chatandas, apparently, the sum of Rs.6000 through the Yezd branch of the Imperial Bank of Persia: that the Kerman agent of Mohandas Chatandas was drawn on to the extent of 25000 krans, the equivalent of Rs.6000, by the said Jemshid Hormoydiar and that the amount was paid to Rahimof, a merchant of Yezd on behalf of the former.! _ i former. The Collector of Sukkur sent for Mohandas Chatandas at Shikarpur on the 24th ultimo and acquainted hiui w ith the consents of tne telegram and questioned idm as to his knowledge of the transaction: ne was anaole to throw any light on it. Whatever may have s he ,ii u^-^e object of tne transaction, so far as the firm * agent in Kerman was concerned it is quite clear that Mohandas Chatandas, the head of the firm, had no incriminating share in it. The firm is one of consider able standing carrying on transactions on a large scale, while the sum involved is comparatively trifling. It has been suggested that there may possibly be some signifi cance in the Kerman agent of tub firm electing to stay on in Kerman when advised by tne British Consul to quit. But the agent of at least one other Sindhi firm elected to do the same. These firms had considerable stocks of goods in hand and this fact must have been a powerful Incentive to induce them to stay in spite of the disturbed condition of the country. Moreover the Kerman^knew that he had been reported by the British Consul, and this would be a further reason for remain ing out of reach of the arm of the law 11 *wno the persons named in tne telegram are. • Art ah Jemshid horrnoydiar is reported to oe tne head of a trading firm in Persia and is also stated to he a prominent politi cian who took an active part in bringing about the recent revolution. Nothing is known of Rahimof, the \edzi mercnant. If further enpuiries about these nersons are considered necessary, they might be made from the British Consul who reported the matter from Kerman: he may also be able to throw further light on the transac tion so far as the Kerman agent of Mohandas Chatandas is concerned: but whatever may be the agent's complicity, the Commissioner is satisfied that the head of tne firm hirnself is not guilty of any discreditable conduct in this matter In connection with this case several other intercepted telegrams were forwarded by Government to the Commissioner unofficially for enquiry. Most of the telegrams had already been delivered. They all related to the financial transactions of Bhikarpur firms and these papers were also in the box which was lost. The enquiries which were instituted showed that the transactions to which the telegrams related wereSd/- W. H. Commissioner Secretary to Governnent, Political Department, Bombay. Lucas, in Bind.(COPY). Telegram. From - To - - ^ iie ° ecret ary oq the Government ol* India m tli&amp; Poreign &amp; Political Department,Delhi, The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay. N0.333-W. Date! the 17th March 1916. Your telegram 530-C. February 29th. Monev in question may he redeposited in Bank o:? Bombay in Mr * Robertson*s name as Secretary to Government, x J oliticai Department, Bombay, for further period of six montns m each case, pending appearance of rightful claimants(COPY). Telegram, ^ rom '' oeeretary t»o t»lie Gov8rnnient» of Bombay, Political Department, To - - Trie Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department* No.782-0, Dated 27th ) ) March 1916. Heed. 27th ) In order to enable me to carry out the orders contained in your letter N0.274-W. dated 1st March I recommend removal of Haji Abdur Hahman Shiraz! of Shiraz and Bombay from the Customs Black List. Please reply by telegraph.IN (COPY) Telegram - P. Prom - The Secretary to the Government of India in tine Foreign &amp; Political Department,Simla, To - - His Britannic Majesty^ Minister, Tehran Ho.65-8. Dated the 16th April 1916. Haji Ahdul Hahman Shirazi of Bombay and Shiraz has been removed from Persian Black list as interference is now considered unnecessary. His correspondence however will still be scrutinised.::onfiaentictl. No. J4 0. of 1916. British Residency and Oonsulate-Creneral, Bushire, 31st January 19±6r Nr on llajor j\ 0 P. Trevor, C.I.E., Deputy Political Resident, Persian Gulf, To The Hon ! hie Nr. A. II. Grant, G.S.I., G.I.E., Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. Sir, With reference to the telegram No. 35 (to Bushire) dated 30th January from His Pajesty f s Minister at Tehran which was repeated to the Government of ry 1. Telegram from Consul Bandar Abbas to Deputy Political Resident, No. 47, dated 31st Jam 1916. 3. Telegram from Denuty Political Resident to Consul, Bandar Abbas, No. mOl, dated 23rd January) India, I have the 1916. o. Telegram from Consul Bandar Abbas, to Deputy Political Resident, No* 53 dated 35th January 1916. 4. Telegram from Deputy Political Resident to Secretary to Government of Bombay, Political Department, No. 217 and to H. Us Minister No. ) honour to forward } } herewith a copy of the corres- 44?317 dated 25th January 1916. . Telegram from H. Us Mini5 5. Telegram from H. IPs Minister Tehran, No* 35, dated 30th January 1916. 6. Telegram from Deputy Political Resident to Secretary to Government of Bombay Political Department No. 258 dated 31st January 1916. ) pondence which i has passed on the subject of GO '■Zt;. &lt;: S § m CD f h 3 ^ - co a, ' e&gt; ' &lt;£ O T*' § ^ . ’ 3 2 7, I £5 © cj -’►-IQ CD O —- the drawing of telegraphic bills on the Hongkong and Shanghai Bank in Bombay by Messrs Dilmagani 6; Co. 3. As none of the Hi man Colony appeared to know anything of Dilmagani and thought the firm was identical with Welmakani I thought it advisable to telegraph to the Government of Bombay and His Majesty T s Minister on the subject. 3. His Hajesty T s Minister has replied (in the telegram mentioned above) that selling of bills in India through Tehran— ■ ■ nz. Tehran and Tabriz represents that Dilnagani is the correct the usual course of business, narie of the firm which is a well known and Tabriz Tabriz firm and that he is warning the Tehran branches that the firm will be blacklisted if they are not very careful with regard to hi man. d. I have not of course any knowledge of the usual method of selling bills on India in Kiman, via Tehran and Taoriz would seem a round about way normally when there is a branch of the Imperial Bank of Persia at hi man and also Hindu firms - possibly the rates- charged by these are too high. But under existing conditions it appears to me a matter for consideration whether it would not be possible to prevent altogether the sale of bills or telegraphic transfers on India from all places which are in the hands of rebels and out of the control of the Persian G-overn- nent. Buck places - e.g. Ispahan, Shiraz, Yezd and Kiman - are for the moment to all intents and purposes enemy county. I have, etc., Bd. A* 1. Trevor, major, Deputy Political Resident, Persian Bulf.113 Telegram S. D. From To ITowson, Bunder Abbas Trevor, Busliire. No. 47. Dated Blst January 1916. Heard that fin: of Dilnagani at Rinnan, who have branch at Tabriz recently sold telegraphic transfers totalling three lakhs of rupees on Hongkong Shanghai Bank, Bombay through Tabriz for Rrans at low rate of exchange. Presumably transactions were engineered by Crermans. Dilnagani is possibly sans person as Haji Mohamed Welinkani referred to in Linister T s telegraphic Circular A dated 1st January. Howson. Telegram In. cl. H r on Trevor, Bushir e. To Howson, Bunder Abbas. No. HOI. Dated Bbrd January 1916. Your 47. Cannot Nasrullah tell you definitely whether Dilmagani is the sane as Yelinkani or at least whether latter has branch at Rinnan ? Trevor.Tele gran ^3. D. Eowson, lunaer Abbas. Trevor, Busliire. From To No. 53. Dated 25th January 1916. lour .oClo Has r nil all, Indus, Russian Consul and Netli never heard of ' 7 elimkani. Howson. Tele gran P, Pron Tr e vo r, Bushire. T o P o 1 i t i c al, B omb ay. No. 217 repeated Tehran No. 44/217. Dated 25th Januar- 1916. Dilnagani of Kirnan is said to have sold throe lakhs Rupees lately on Hongkong Shanghai Bank through their Tabriz Branch. This transaction was probably on behalf of G-emans and firm Dilnagani is probably identical with the n Welinkani ? figuring; on Black List *'0 n if therefore transaction is completed as reported please warn Bank to that effect. Whether or not uilmagani and Welimkani are the sane is a point which I am submitting to His Kajesty T s Linister. probably a clerical error. (Following for Hinister only] According to Eowson, Bunder Abbas name T, Welimkani H unknown to Kirnan Colony and I think'it must be 'Dilnayanr* who have a branch at Tabriz. Please let me know whether this is so or not.Telegram K. Prom - Larling, British I r .inistor, Tehran. To - Trevor, Buslure. Repeatea - India. No. 35. Dated 30th received 31st Januarv 1916. Your telegrari 44/317. Selling of oills on India at Yirman through Tehran and Tabriz represents the usual course of business and rmch of it nay be legitimate. Dilnageni is cori ect none. Rmily is one set of Persian Sarrafs originating in Tabriz with which Sadeghiani and Ittahadie are also connected. To Black list Dilnageni would entail blacklisting then all. This would only render obtaining of money by Germans in Kirman a little slower and noro expensive it would not prevent it nnd would I eh informed by Imperial Bank of Persia seriously affect their business* I propose to get hold of these people here and in Tabriz and to threaten them with black listing if they are not very careful with regard to Kirman. addressed Bushire, repeated India* Marling, British minister.Telegrain P&lt;&gt; Prom Trevor Bushire* To Political Bombay. No. ^58. Dated Januarir 31st 1916. I am now informed by His Hajesty ! s Minister Tehran that n Dilmagani'^ is the Kerman fimNs correct name. He adds that at present this firm is not on the Black List but that he is about to issue a warning to its branches Tabriz and' Tehran threatening them that unless they are most careful with respect to Kerman they will be placed on the Black List. The reference is to ny telegram No. 217 dated 25th instant. Trevor.■ M i Copy • From - To ~ Telegram.. P. Tl:e Political resident in the Persian Gulf vrepeated to Bushire by post) T}j.e Secretary to the Government of India # Foreign and, Political Department, • elhi, No. 581 B. Dated 6th. Feed. 9th February 1916. As to Bushire letter 34 C dated 31st January I am very doubtful. I support suggestion made in concluding paragraph. It is almost entirely Bombay which is concerned it would seem wit.! in the power and competence of political authorities to exercise necessary control. It would be advisable that all drafts from Persia or telegraphic order for remittances should he subject to supervision by Political Department and those from enemy centre held up.Copy. No. 1426-?’. Government of India. Department of Commerce and Industry. Simla, the 5th April 1916. From S.H.Slater, Esquire, Under Secretary to the Government of India, To The Secretary to the Government of Bombay,Political Department. i&amp;y IS The Financial Secretary to the Government of the the endorsement from the Forei^p and. Political Department preventing transfers of money to places in Persia under enemy control. firm*and individuals in this country have been and are being used, often unwittingly, as a channel for remittances of enemy money to Germans in Persia* The recipients of such remittances are in most cases Persian subjects of firms, some of whom have been found to be acting on behalf of or in friendly relations with Germans. The Government of India consider it highly Punj ab. The Agent to the Governor General and Chief Commissioner of North-West-Frontier Province. Sir ( With reference to the correspondence ending with *, dated the 27th March 19141 ami directed to 2 . As the Government of Bombay are aware Hie Government of India understand that desirablep' desiracle t-hat steps should be taken as soon as possible to prevent such remittances from read in; firms of 9 individuals residing or carrying on business in the aacacs areas which are for the time being under enemy influence. Tlie territory which at present falls* u nd e i this d e s c r i p t ion c omp rises Ki rman, Ye ad and Shiraz with the adjoining districts. I am to request, therefore .that .with the permission of Ris' lonour^^e ' IFtherr - is no objection' ^v ^rpip y jp g C oupe; the Banks trading in the — r ^..— may be requested not to forth west Frontier Province accept, discount or receive for collection bills of exchange drawn by firms and individuals in the areas specified above. It is also hoped that any Indian firms who are l ikely to be approached in respect of such business may be warned not to enter into financial negotiations or transactions with such individuals of firms. 3. I am to point out that the above restrictions should be regarded as purely temporary and that as soon as any of the areas described above has been freed from German influences, instructions will be issued for the withdrawal of the restrictions in respect of such area. I have, etc., Sd. G-.S.Hardy, for Under Secretary/' to the Government of India*Telegram. P. From - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department,Simla, To — Trie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,Basra. Dated the 12th April 1916. Please refer to your telegram dated the 8th February 581-B. We have as a. temporary measure asked banks in Punjab, North West Frontier Province and Bombay Presidenc not to accept discount or receive for collection, bills of exchange drawn by individuals and firms in German-ridden areas, namely, Shiraz, Yesd, and Kerman with adjoining districts. Please telegraph whether you think these restrictions should now be removed in regard to any or all of these areas, in view of financial difficulties in Persia and of general improvement in situationkiy further communication the subject, please quote 51082/34 i address— The C ont roller, Foi i Trade Department. Telephone: Gerrard 864-0. Sir, oM f J i.fv Sj. ~\ wtt. 1480 19i6 Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, St. James, S.W. /£f April, 1916. With reference to the communication from this Department of the 23ra ult. (No. 28029), transmitting a copy of a telegram from His Majesty’s Minister at Teheran relating to an agreement concluded v/ith Ittahadie, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to state that he has been advised that the sum of £13,000 specified in the telegram referred to has nov/ been deposited in London as security for Ittahadie's future behaviour. Steps are accordingly being taken to remove Ittahadie’s name from the Statutory List and from the General Black List. I am, Sir, Your mo,st obedient, *&gt;&gt;»_ „ -•-* i \ r&gt; ... r-VX' pp- Y,--\ 1 H &gt;. ! » ‘ ■WWA-v* - '* e Under Secretary of State, India Office, Whitehall.Government Publications. TRADING WITH THE ENEMY (NEUTRAL COUNTRIES) PROCLAMATION, 1916. Additions to and Alterations in Statutory List of Firms in Neutral Countries with whom Trading is prohibited-Argentine Eepublic, Morocco , Netherlands, Persia*, Portuguese East Africa*, and Sweden At the Council Chamber, Whitehall, the Uth day of March, 1916. By the Lords of His Majesty’s Most Honourable Privy Council. Ma J e ! T fc 7 was Phased, in exercise of the power in that behalf conferred on Him by Section one, subsection one of the ad mg with the Enemy (Extension of Powers) Act, 1915, by a roclamatmn dated the 29th day of February, 1916, to prohibit all persons or bodies of persons, incorporated or unincorporated, resident arrymg on business, or being in the United Kingdom from trading with any of the persons or bodies of persons mentioned in the List contained in the said Proclamation : And whereas by Section one, subsection two of the said Act, it is provided that any List of persons and bodies of persons, incorporated or unincorporated, with whom such trading is prohibited by a reclamation under the said Act may be varied or added to by an r er made by the Lords of the Council on the recommendation of a becretary of State, such List as so varied or added to, being in the said Proclamation referred to as the “ Statutory List ”: And whereas there was this day read at the Board a recommenda- effect ° m tlie SeCrefcary of ' State for F° rei g n Affairs to the following That the List of persons and bodies of persons, incorporated or unincorporated, with whom trading is prohibited by the Proclamation dated the 29th day of February, 1916, should be amended by the variation and addition of the names set forth in the Schedule hereto. Now,^ therefore, Their Lordships, having taken the said recom mendation into consideration, are pleased to order, and it is hereby ordered, that the same be approved. Whereof the Right Honourable Sir Edward Grey, Bart., K.G., one of His Majesty’s Principal Secretaries of State, the Controller of the foreign Trade Department, and all other persons whom it may concern, are to take notice and govern themselves accordingly. Almeric FitzRoy. infL'\T )TE '~7^ nc * er the Enemy Proclamations of 25th June and to n 11 Novem ‘ :)e:r &gt; 1915, all Proclamations relating to Trading with the Enemy apply a 1 persons or bodies of persons of enemy nationality, resident or carrying on usmess in Morocco or Portuguese East Africa, and consequently it is an offence to _ a , e with any person or body of persohs of enemy nationality resident or carrying - usmess in Morocco or Portuguese East Africa, even thougu such person or body persons is not included by name in the above list, and the omission of the name of ny such person or body of persons from such list is not an authority or licence to trade with such person or body of persons.Mar. 23, 1916] THE BOARD OF TRADE JOURNAL government notices affecting TRADE. IMPORTATION OF CERTAIN ARTICLES PROHIBITED. By the KING. A PROCLAMATION. F.&gt;R Prohibiting the Importation of certain Ak^clib into the United Kingdom. ^^wSr^a^by Section 43 of the Customs Consolidation Act, 1876, it is provided that the importation ml^-oclama- gunpowder, or any other goods may be prohibited by Pio tl0 And whereas it is expedient that th^importatmn into the United Kingdom of certain goods should ^/prohibited as P Towf therefore, We, by and with Ahe advice of Our Privy Council, in pursuance of the said and of a o rr i ordain enabling Us in that behalf, do hereby proclaim, direct and o aS As^Voni and after the Twenty-se^nth day of March, 1916^sub&gt;ct as hereinafter provided, the impc/tation into the Uni g of the following goods is hereby prohibited viz. onoBsnr ; 8S 0 f Motor cars, chassis, moto^/cycles and parts and a - motor cars and motpr cycles (other than tyres) , g exception of the m/tor cars, chassis, accessories an P a which are at present exempted from impo^ ^ Section 13 (4) of/he Finance No. 2 Act, 1 91 °- . ^ Musical instruments^' including gramophones anc pian tg other similar ir/truments and accessories, componen p and records tlmrefor. , i. r an ^ Spirits and strong waters of all kinds excep Provided always/ and it is hereby declared, tlmt ? r ° unc | er tion shall not appl/ to any such goods which are ^p t ^ cfc licence given by jh on behalf of the Board j of Tra , to to the provision^ and conditions of such licence. TmDort This Proclamation may be cited as the Prohibition (No. 3) Proclaihation, 1916. ^ _g rgt . Given at/Our Court at Buckingham Palace, / j ne da/of March, in the year of our Lord One thousana „ hundred and sixteen, and in the Sixth year o GOD SAVE THE KING.1 Telegram P., No. 152, dated (and received) the 27th November 1915. From—His Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To The Secretory to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Please refer to your telegram No. 792-S It is stated by the Imperial » » d h^Tf f Yez T d + ttat they are satisfied that Sadeqh Affshar has definWely severed himself from Ittihadie connection, and they ask leave tn him. Hussein Dehdashtej, Bombay, is his agent in India. ^ Please let me have your views. Telegram ?., No. D. S.-106, dated the 29th November 1915. From-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department. Reference is invited to your telegram No. 416-P., dated August 5 th. The following telegram No. 152, dated the 27th November 1915, has been received from His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran :— “ It is stated by the Imperial Bank of Persia * * * * * please let me have your views.” The views of His Excellency the Governor in Council as to grant of authority required by the Bank should be telegraphed by you. 3 Telegram P., No. 281, dated (and received) the 30th November 1915. From—His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Kerman, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- ment, Delhi. I report for the information of the Government of India that bills of exchange for a large sum of money have been accepted by agent of Mohan das Chetandas of Shikarpur. He was aware or ought to have been aware that the money was intended for the Germans and has thereby replenished the exhausted funds of the Germans. Repeated to Foreign ; addressed to Commissioner in Sind, 4 Telegram No. 2543-C., dated the 1st (received 2nd) December 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. Your telegram 106-D. S., dated 29th November. Bombay Government have no objection to grant of authority required by the Bank. Ee^eivscl on * ^ r pf-l 1016with - r »« •* Jw’jv INDIA FGBEIG' 1 -CRETARY'S Letter. No. M Dated 17 ; 6 ;ARi9lBTelegram P., No. 119-D. S. } dated the 8rd December 1915. Prom The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, T 0 The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department. Following telegram, dated 30th ultimo, bearing No. 231, has been address ed to Comm’s loner in Sind by Consul at Kerman : Begins—1 report for the information of * * * * * * * * exhausted funds of the Germans. Ends. As soon as possible please obtain report from Commissioner, Sind. Government of India are of opinion that drastic action should be taken against the Shikarpur firm if there are reasonable grounds for believing that they have connived in above transaction. 6 Telegram P., No. 120-D. S., dated the 3rd December 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—PBa Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. Please refer to your telegram No. 152, dated the 27th ultimo. There is no objection to grant of authority required by Bank to trade with Sadeqh Affshar. No. 11-W., dated Delhi, the 4th January 1916 (Confidential). From—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To—His Britannic Majesty’s Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of Persia, Tehran. In continuation of the letter from the Government of India in the letter from the Government of BomW,, J’ureigii and Political Department, Political Department, No. 2923-C., dated the 28th I No. 2027-W., dated the 19th October December 1915. 1915, I am directed to forward, for in formation, a copy of the marginally noted paper regarding Ittihadie and Abdur Bahman Shirazi. 11 Telegram P., No. 226-D. S., dated the 11th January 1916. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department. Mohan Dass, Chetan Dass of Shikarpur When may a reply be expected to my telegram of the 3rd instant, No. 119-D. S. ? 12 Telegram P., No. 124-C., dated (and received) the 13th January 1916. From—The Secretarv to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. We have asked Commissioner in Sind to expedite enquiries regarding Mohan Dass Chetan Dass of Shikarpur. The above refers to your telegram No. 226-D. S., dated the 11th instant.( copy). No # 23u6d .dOuiDay Cas'tl6, “biiG SStdi Decsniber 1915 (Confidential). Pro v n - J.E.G. Jukes, Esquire, Deputy Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, With reference to the correspondence ending with Mr. Maffey’s letter No.1305-W., dated the 3rd August 1915, I am directed to state, for the information of the Government of India, that Messrs. Haji Abdur Rahrnan Shirazi and son were allowed to withdraw from the Bank of Bombay, on the 4th December 1915, out of the original deposits of two and a half lakhs of rupees, a sun ox Rs.50,478-0-8, being the amount of Ittihadie’s overnrait on them, together with interest at the rate of 2 per 3rd December 1915, amounting to Rs.511-11-1. To - - The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, cent. paid by the Bank from the 1st June 1915 to the balance of the deposits, amounting with Interest to Rs.2,00,260-4-3, has been re-deposited in the Bank in Mr. L. Robertson's name as Secretary to Government, Political Department, Bombay, as a fixed deposit bearing interest at 2 per cent, for a x further period of six months from the 1st September on 13 API PJ Igwiri INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Letter. No. M Dated MAR IN! 5No. 255-C-, dated Bombay Castle, the 25th January 1916 (Confidential). From-J F n Depttty Seoretary to tte GoTemmeiit of Bombay; ) To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. With reference to the correspondence ending with mv letter No 9 Q 9 Q.f', dated the 28th December 1915, I am directed to invite the attention' of the Governmentof India to th e&gt; Persian Black List, prepared by the Department of Commerce and Industry, m which the name of Shirazi Haii Abdur Bahman of Bombay and Shiraz appears, owing probably to the firm’s connection with the firm of Ittihadie of Tehran. In view of this, I am to request the instruc tions of the Government of India whether the Government of Bombay are to take steps to close down altogether the branch of the firm in Bombay or only to stop all its business with its Head Office in Shiraz In this connection I am to invite attention to paragraph 10 of Mr. Bobertson’s letter No. 354-P. W., dated the 21st July 1915, in which it was stated that the Government of Bombay were not interfering with the legitimate business of the Bombay branch of the firm. Business with the SMraz house of the firm except in connection with the remit tances for Ittihadie has hitherto been censored as “ legitimate ” business. No. 856-C., dated Bombay Castle, the 8th Febrnary 1916 (Confidential). From— J. E. C. Jukes, Esq., Deputy Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political With reference to the correspondence ending with my telegram No. 124-C., dated the 13th January 1916, I am directed to state, for the information of the Government of India, that the Commissioner in Sind has reported that the confidential box containing the case of the Shikarpur merchant, Mohandas Chetandas, was stolen on the 30th ultimo from the possession of the peon who was taking it to the Commissioner’s camp, where it had been sent for for the drafting of a report to Government. The Sind Bailway Police are investigating the theft. The Commissioner, however, adds that the enquiry which he had made in regard to the case had led him to the conclusion that Mohandas’s trans actions were harmless, and that he was proposing to report to Government in No. STl-W., dated Delhi, the 1st March 1916 (Confidential). From —Captain H. V. Biscoe, I.A., Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To—The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department. I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of Mr. Jukes* letter, No 255-C., dated the 25th January 1916, regarding the firm of Shirazi Haji Abdur Bahman of Bombay and Shiraz, whose name appears on the Persian Black List. 2. In reply I am directed to state, for the information of the Governor in Council, that the Government of India do not consider it necessary at present that the trade of the firm should be interfered with. The procedure hither to followed in connection with them should therefore be continued, but I am to request that their correspondence may be carefully scrutinised. 14 Department. this sense. 15 S. G. P, I., Delhi—No. 1061 F. &amp; P. D.-7-3-16-6...on. - A In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. tfoxq ' and address— / ♦'W' The Controller, Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, St. James’, S.W, THE Controller of the Foreign Trade Department presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for , and, by direction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, transmits herewith cop 14 of the under-mentioned / paper. V h V T ^ M V s *r ' . i -O Foreign Trade Department, a , 1916. Reference to previous letter to Letter p Foreign Trade Department Irom Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Aw A. f0 *• U,/&lt;{&lt;(&gt; Subject. bV M. 24 MAR 1916 X ^ ^ Uufy k-Ciftl I : ? §In any further communication on this subject, please quote n„. /tT4 2&gt;^ and address— The Controller, Foreign Trade Department, Lancaster House, St. James’, S.W. THE Controller of the Foreign Trade Department presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for 9 'K oLicX^ , and, by direction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, transmits herewith cop-CC^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Trade Department, i x &gt; 1916 - if! S'I • n Reference to previous letter: Letter Foreign Trade Department: from Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. L/T&lt;S&gt;Vv /VI A 1 J Cla*^ To JttcoLxJ-U /^rTO^ heJj S'. \ i-x t-r: i-ih x - / ' (Similar letter sent to [ 5 ]CThis Document is the Property of His B ritannic Majesty’s Government. and should be returned to the Foreign Offi ce when done with ^ ' 1 tmlrtcycr •VfW'l 111 ••Asi fAM AffSAinl 1 No• 71. (sic) Forum. (K). Ittahadie Persian Banker who was put on black-list as a result cf his money transactions with Germans has been brought as a consequence to the verge of bankruptcy. He has lately made several requests to me tor his name to be removed trom black-list and proposes that sum of some £20,000 of his impounded in India should be held as security for his good behaviour to be confiscated absolutely if he offends. I think he can do little n-nm at present and he has probably had his lesson. I would there fore propose that his name should be removed from black-list on his signing documents to the following effect. 1, Bum at present impounded in India will be absolute ly confiscated on the slightest indication that he is again helping the Germans, D. 11,55.p.m, January 29th.1916. K. 9.40.a.m,. January 31st,1916. 2. His Majesty's Legation shall he sole judge in the natter without any appeal. 3. Any commercial transactions on his part with foreign country or part of Persia in the nands of the enemy snail he regarded as helping the Germans, legitimate and 1 understand vnau be affected if lie went bankrupt 0Cypher telegram to Mr. Marling. (Teheran) February fith, 1916. D. 4.10.p.m. February 5th, 1916. No. 62 . Forum. &gt;f«' 'I' ■ 1, Your telegram of January 29th, 1916. Ittah-iile. Name will be removed from B.L. as soon as I hear that documents have been signed.27,0 ©nfi&amp;enti&amp;l* (inf) 3.2/6, Ho*2923~G* of 1915* £i . ? c~ j s/--. I O Political Department: Bombay Castle # 2Qth December 1915. /r Prom J* S.OgJukes, Bsquire f Deputy Secretary to Government, Bombay. To Tbe Foreign Secretary to the Government of India* Foreign and Political Department, Delhi* Sir ? With reference to the correspondence ending with Mr. Maffey f 8 letter ffo.l305~$., dated the 3rd August 1915, I am directed to state, for the information of the Government of India, that Messrs* Haji Abdur Hahman Shirazi and Son were allowed to withdraw from the Bank of Bombay, on the 4th December 1915, out of the original deposits of two and a half lakhs of rupees, a sum of Rs 0 50,478*^0*^8, being the amount of Ittihadle v 8 overdraft on them, together with interest at the rate of 2 ^ paid by the Bank from the 1st June 1915 to the 3rd December 4 4 1915, amounting to Bs*511**ll~l, The balance of the deposits, amounting with interest te Es # 2,0Q,260~4~3, has been redeposited in the Bank in Mr. L« Robertson 1 s name as Secretary to Government, Political Department, Bombay, as a fixed deposit bearing interest at 2 f 0 fer a further period of six months from the 1st September 1915* I have, etc*, Sd/« J, E.GJukes, / Deputy Secretary to Government* fioceived on 2 FE.B 'i d 1U with IKDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Letter. No. 2 M r-tni 7 ,! AN 1916, m Urgent and ConTidentlal. (COPY). No. 1960-C. of 1915. r r P n $' t t Prom 'Wi l v— Political Department, !Bombay Castle, lith Octouer 1315. To u* is# 0* Jukes, Esq*, Deputy Secretary to Government, Bombay, The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. Foreign and Political Department, Simla* Sir, I am directed to state that the following telegram from the Imperial Bank of Persia, fehBBan, addressed to Coffey, Ahwaz, is held up in the censorship: 'STS. Your bill Ettahadieh 12,000 paid, do not confiscate. Abdulrahim Arab pay them 10,000 on account Agha &lt; and to enquire whether, in the opinion of the Govern ment of India, it should be allowed to go on to its destination. I am to state that the telegram is in reply to a telegram from Coffey, Ahwaz, to the Bank at Teheran which was as follows: -^Referring to your telegram of yesterday, our mmw i mi i■ m - 0n 16 KiOV 1915 with !A FOREIGN SECRETARY’S 2P- NO. 5. M ^ PP n r T 1 o 1telegraph transfer Ettahadieh tahen from collection very probably enemies' money, it is on account of Mohamed Mehdi Samsar Isfaman. We intend to confiscate. Win you do so or leave it to us ? M This earlier telegram was allowed to go on, as from its contents it appeared that the Imperial Bank of Persia intended to have no dealings with Ittihadie, hut in view of the telegram now held up, the matter would seem to call for an explanation. I have, etc., SdA J. S* C* Jukes, Deputy Secretary to Government,(COPY). zzf Telegram - p. Prom - The Secretary to the Government of India in ^' e foreign and Political Department, Simla, To - - The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay. No. S.-1048. Dated the 16th October 1915. The intercepted telegram which was sent from Imperial Bank of Persia to Coffey at Ahwaz may be allowed to go on. This is with reference to your letter 1960-C,, dated October 11th.ho » ^ '/ m 9 From To 2he secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, ni;j isritaunic ivlajeaty’s iinvoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court ol Persia, Tehran. Sir, Dated Simla, the '7 i*r October 1915. With reference to the telegram from the Govern ment of India in the Foreign and Political Department, No.B.897, dated the 1st September 1915, 1 am directed to forward, for your information, a copy of the papers Letter from the Government of Bombay, &gt; noted in the margin. Political Department. No.1960-C. .dated 1 the ilth October 1915. Telegram to -Ditto-, No.S. 1048, 5 regarding telegraphic dated the 16th October 1915. correspondence between the Imperial Bank of Persia, Tehran and Coffey, Ahwax, relative to the payment of Rs.12,000/- to Ittlhadie I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- A. H. Grant, Secretary to the Government of India.ill Fr«m - Telegram - R. The Hsn’nle Lt.-Cel. sir Percy Cox, K.C.I JS.,C.8.1., Political Resident In the PerBian Gulf, Basra, The Secretary t® the Government of India In the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. N0.2118-B. Dated and reed, the 22nd September 1915 T® *1 learn that Germans in Baghdad are buying drafts e en Agent of Deutsche Bank in Kermanshah and transporting Krans from Kerman shah to Ramadan. This is their financial centre and Consular Agent here remits money by draft to Tehran and Ispahan. I am endeavouring to find out who is Agent at Kermanshah and broker here. This procedure would seem to indicate Germans stock of gold is running short. Sent to Tehran, repeated to Cox.' Above received from Ramadan dated September 2ist. *niMn,.ivir»i,i moii'ii. i - • Addressed India, repeated t® Bushireo ■ r/\j y 15 With. .......sECRETABrS t r&gt; ,, . .v m i . ■ , - :T.1915Put ci Vv wV \\ f India Office, 25th October 1915. Dear 01iohant, r •.. . letter Jo. 149257 of loth instant, I think io almost certain that Abdul Shirazi is our old friend Abdur Rahman Shirazi. It appears from para.2 of Mr.* Jukes’ letter ol 3rd August (copy sent to you with P.3278 on 8th September) that Abdur Rahman had dealings with Ellinger. nless there is reason to doubt the identity need we reply officially? Yours sincerely, (Sd.) A.Hirtzel.-t::- ..:: rL 1 k ■ •&gt;. .' »' I ^ ■ In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. 149257/15. and address— The Under-Sccretary of State, Foreign Office, &gt; London. 67 ? ^ 9 t ! O 1 r- i! * O 1 Foreign Office^'* October 1915. Sir:- I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to trans mit to you herewith a copy of the letter from the Parliamentary Counsel relative to the financial trans actions of a certain Abdul Shirazee of Bombay. Sir E. Grey would be glad to be informed as to the attitude which the Government of India have adopted towards this person and his activities. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, 19 OCT 1915 c. r * • Cnpv tr G-dja 12 NOV 1915 J:opy OFFICE OP THE PARLIAMENTARY COUNSEL, [149257) V'iHITEHALL. '1 D Dear Oliphant, Messrs. EUlnger Company of 28 Osford Street, luancheoter telegraphed to us the other day asking whether tuey might accept a bill drawn by Abdul Shirazee oif; Bombay, and we replied by telegram that the bill .should not be accepted. We have had a call from Mr. Ellinger in the matter and he has refused the bill on our instructions. He explains that the bill was drawn by Abdul Shirazee against the ship ment of Persian goods, the documents relating to which were sent to a Bank in this country and have been forwarded to him. The goods in question were shipped by a Persian, Abdul Shirazee merely financing the transaction. Mr Ellinger stated he is quite certain that Abdul Shirazee will have paid the Persian shipper of the goods, and that the only effect of his refusal to accept the bill is that Abdul Shirazee will have to refund to the bank in India the amount he received from them when discounting it. Mr. Ellinger pointed out that if the Government wishes to prevent money going into Persia, it must prevent shipments from Persia. Meanwhile, he suggested that no bills drawnby Abdul Shirazee, except against documents, should be accepted; but that so long as Abdul Shirazee was allowed to trade in Bombay, there was no object in refusing in this country to meet his acceptances against documents. I am inclined to think that, provided there is nothing against the Persian shipper whom Abdul Shirazee finances, it is difficult to ask people in this country to refuse to accept 'Uncelot Gliphant Esq. , Foreign Office.-Z3C @ accept nis 'bills accompanied 'by documents, so long as he is allowed by the Government of India to trade there freely. Perhaps you can discover whether the India Government have come to any definite decision as to whether Abdul Shirazee is to be allowed to trade freely, and if so, whether in your view people might be allowed to accept his bills, provided they are accompanied by documents. Yours &amp;c. , (Signed) Arthur T.TringvFrom Major A. P. Trevor, C.I.E., Officer on Special Duty in the Persian Gulf, Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- fS ment, Simla. I have received from the Consul a copy of your confidential letter of the 24th April to Ziegler of Manchester with regard to the dismissal of their German managers. Letter from German in Tangistan named Bohnstorff and another from certain K. H. M. apparently in Ispahan or Tehran, both addressed to an Austrian doctor named Biach now living in Shiraz has been intercepted by us mention money transactions through Stettlor and Sauer, Ziegler’s agents in Ispahan and Shiraz. Bohnstorff writes that the second letter was sent to him (stupidly ?) by Sauer who is apparently acting for German party as a forwarding agent. Addressed to Foreign Office; sent to India and Ispahan, Shiraz, Basrah,, Tehran. I shall have the abovementioned letter forwarded with my despatch No*. 244 of the 25th ultimo. No. Cf. 244, dated Bushire, the 25th June (received 6th July) 1915 (Confidential). From— Major A. P. Trevor, C.I.E., Officer on Special Duty (in the absence of the Resident), To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. His Majesty’s Foreign Office, London, to Messrs’ Ziegler &amp; Co., 2, Bombay Street, Manchester, dated 24th April 1915. I have the honour, at the request of Major W. F. T. O’Connor, C.I.E., His Majesty’s Acting Consul at Shiraz, to forward herewith, for the information of the Government of India, a copy of the marginally-noted letter which has been received by Major O’Connor from His Majesty’s Board of Trade. I have bad some correspondence with Major O’Connor on the subject dealt With in this letter and it appears that Messrs. Ziegler’s Manager at Shiraz is a German, a certain Herr Sauer, and that one or two of the firm’s other Mana gers in Persia are Germans. At the beginning of the war, His Majesty’s Consul, Shiraz, represented this matter to His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran, who referred it to the Foreign Office. Later on Major O’Connor addressed the Board of Trade on the subject and received a copy of tfie letter, herewith enclosed, in reply. It is to be hoped that Messrs. Ziegler &amp; Co. will now remove those of their Managers wffio are Germans; it is bad enough in times of peace for a British firm to be represented in a country like Persia by Germans, but in time of war it is intolerable. Copy of a confidential communication from the Foreign Office to Messrs. Ziegler &amp; Co,, 2, Bombay Street, Manchester, dated 24th April 1915. In reply to your letter of the 14th instant, relative to the present ppsition of your representatives at Tehran and Shiraz, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to refer you to my letter of November 27th last. The events of the last few months have confirmed him in the opinion that there are strong objections to any British firms employing German subjects in Persia during the present war. Since the date of your letter Sir E. Grey has received from Persia two telegrams emphasizing the unfortunate results of the fapt that certain of you v Managers there are of German origin. Telegrams Nos*S*708 and S*?1Q are in Manuscript- Please see page 3* ! India, Foreign Secretary No. M, dated o ^ or'r&gt; c St A iO13 Telegram P., No. 360 P., dated (and received) the 23rd July 1915. jp rom The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay, To The Secretary to the Government cf India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Please see endorsement from Foreign and Political Department No. 1207 W., dated July 16th, regarding German agents of Messrs. Ziegler in Persia. Until such time as they comply with the wishes of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs it would be easy to bring pressure to hear on the firm of Ziegler by stopping all their cables and letters in the Censor’s office In view of facts contained in Major Trevor’s telegram for- warded with your endorsement 1173 W., July 15th, this course would be perfectly justifiable. Correspondence of Ziegler with Persia already being carefully watched. Please let us have telegraphic instructions. Telegram No.725-S. is in Manuscript. Please see page 9* Telegram P., No. S. 729, dated the 26th July 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political , Department, Simla, To— Major A. P. Trevor, C.I.E., Officer on Special Duty in the Persian Gulf, Bushire (repeated to Sir P. Cox, Basrah, His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran.) Please refer to your telegram No. 270 C. of the 1st instant. It is suggested by the Government of Bombay that it would he easy to bring pressure to bear on firm of Ziegler by stopping all letters and cables ia the office of the Censor until such time as the wishes of His Majesty’s Govern ment are complied with by the firm. What views do you bold? No. 354 P.-W., dated Bombay Castle, the 21st (received 25th) July 1915 (Confidential). From—L. Robertson, Esq., Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. I am directed to acknowledge receipt of Mr. Maffey’s letter No. 1090 W* (Confidential), dated the 6th July 1915, on the subject of the restrictions placed upon the account of Haji Abdur Bahman Shirazi &amp; Son in Bombay* His Britannic Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz requests that the restrictions placed upon the firm in India may be relaxed. In particular Haji Abdur Rahman requests that the sums payable to him now detained in Bombay may be released. 2. In reply, I am to explain that the amount of money which the firm has been required to place on deposit in the Bank of Bombay totals Rs. 2,50,000 and not Rs. 1,50,000. These funds are not, in their entirety, the property of the firm. They represent sums remitted for the credit of Ittihadi, against which the latter firm has not drawn. 3. The circumstances attending the detention of the two sums of Rs. 1,50,000 and Rs. 1,00,000, which make up the total of Rs. 2,50,000, have already been reported to the Government of India in my confidential letters, Nos. 363 C. and 466 C., dated, respectively, the 5th and 17th June 1915, hut I am to recapitulate the facts tor ready reference. The former sum of a lakh and-a-half was remitted by the Chartered Bank in London to its Bombay branch for credit to the account of Shirazi, who had himself received from Ittihadi advice that the money should, on receipt, be passed to his credit. The second remittance of a lakh of rupees was made to its Bombay branch by the Eastern Bank from London. In this case, Shirazi received advice from Ittihadi that he was to expect a remittance of Rs. If lakhs on his account. Both sums were intercepted by the Government of Bombay and were similarly treated, being placed on fixed deposit for three months in the Bankof Bombay on condition that they 1)6 witHrawn only on the joint order of the Secretary to Government in the Political Department and of the firm of Abdur Rabman Shirazi &amp; Son. The deposit was made in the one case on the 1st June and in the other on the 21st June 1915, 4 On the showing of the Bombay representative of Haji Abdur Rahman Ittihadi’s total overdraft on them is no more than something between Rs. 40,000 and 50,000; and granted the accuracy of this account, and the claim of Shirazi to be re-imbursed this overdraft, he has no claim to the balance of the sums deposited, more especially as he has now ceased trading with Ittihadi. 5. The Governor in Council would propose accordingly that on expiry of the first deposit, the amount of Ittihadi’s overdraft on Haji Ab dur Rahman Shirazi &amp; Son together with the interest accrued on it should be handed over to the firm’s agent in Bombay. 6. The balance of the first deposit together with the second deposit should be held by Government pending the appearance of a rightful claimant to whom the money can be paid without endangering the public interest. 7. In view of the above proposal it does not seem to be necessary to dis cuss the denial of the principal of the firm of Haji Abdur Rahman Shirazi &amp; Son of any knowledge of the nature of Ittihadi’s transactions. 8. From the events that have transpired, it would appear that some other channel will be sought whereby money may be transmitted either direct to Ittihadi or through some third party in Persia. Tnis inference receives Confirmation from the fact that in tueir letter, dated the 8th June 1915, Haji Abdur Rahman Shirazi &amp; Son, Bombay, stated that they had received advice from Ittihadi of an expected remittance of Rs. 1,75,009. Of this sum only Rs. 1,00,000 has been received, this being the one lakh referred to in paragraph 3 above. The balance of Rs. 75,000 has not come to Bombay. 9. It would, therefore, appear desirable to institute enquiries in Persia with the view of discovering whether Ittihadi is receiving from other sources funds for supply to the German Legation at Tehran. 10. Finally, I am to add that, while commercial cables from and to Abdur Rahman Shirazi &amp; Son are carefully scrutinized in Bombay and explanations are asked of any doubtful transactions, every effort is made to avoid unnecessary interference with legitimate business. Telegram P., No. 345 C., dated (and received) the 27th July 1915. From— Major A. P. Trevor, C.I.E., Officer on Special Duty, Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Please refer to Foreign and Political Department’s telegram, 729 S. I do not yet know what, if any, action has been taken by Foreign Office on my telegram 270 C 4 , or whether Messrs. Ziegler show any signs of dispens ing with their German assistants. If the attention of the firm is again drawn to matter and they do not comply with our wishes within a reasonable time, pressure in the manner indicated by the Government of Bombay might have some effect, but only correspondence from their Shiraz and Bushire offices filter through this way. Repeated to Marling and Cox. Telegram P., No. 82, dated the 27th (received 28th) July 1915. From—His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment,- Simla. Please see Foreign and Political Department telegram to Bushiiei No. 729 S&lt;, dated 26th July.1 I® V A The firm of Ziegler and Company are doing all that we can require of them They are sending an Englishman to Tehran to take charge of their important office there and have offered to let me assume control over it for the time being. Repeated to Major Trevor and Colonel Sir P. Cox. TRieeram No.758 a. is in Manuscript. Please see page 10. l eiegrani Telegram P., No. 765 S., dated the 2nd August 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran. It is reported by the Government of Bombay that recent transactions tend to show that Ittihadi is receiving funds from sources other than Haji Abdur Rahman Shirazi. Is it possible to have enquiries made on the point ? Papers are being posted to you. No. 1-304) W., dated Simla, the 3rd August 1915 (Confidential). From—The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To— Major W. F. T. O'Connor, C.I.E., His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Shiraz. I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 105, dated the 24th June 1915, requesting that the restrictions placed on the account of Baji Abdur Rahman Shirazi &amp; Son in Bombay may be relaxed. 2. In reply I am to explain the circumstances attending the detention of two sums of Rs. 1,50,000 and Rs. 1,00,000, which make up a total of Rs. 2,50,000, which the firm has been required to place on deposit in the Bank of Bombay. These funds are not in their entirety the property of the firm, They represent sums remitted for the credit of Ictihadi, against which the latter has not drawn. The sum of one lakh and-a*half was remitted by the (chartered Bank in London to its Bombay branch for credit to the account of Shirazi, who had himself received from Ittihadi advice that the money should, on receipt, be passed to his credit. The second remittance of a lakh of rupees was made to its Bombay branch by the Eastern Bank from London. In this ease Shirazi received advice from Ittihadi that he was to expect a remittance of Rs. If lakhs on his account. Both sums were intercepted by the Government of Bombay and were similarly treated, being placed on fixed deposit for three months in the Bank of Bombay on condition that they be withdrawn only on the joint order of the Secretary to the Government of Bombay in the Political Department and of the firm of Abdur Rahman Shirazi &amp; Son. The deposit was made in one case on the 1st June and in the other on the 21st June 1915. 3. On the showing of the Bombay representative of Haji Abdur Rahman Ittihadi’s total overdraft on them is no more than something between R-s. 40,000 and 60,000 and granted the accuracy of this account, and the claim of Shirazi to be reimbursed this overdraft, he has no claim to the balance of the sums deposited, more specially as he has now ceased trading with Ittihadi, 4. The Government of Bombay propose accordingly that, on expiry of the first deposit, the amount of Ittihadi’s overdraft on Haji Rahman Shirazi &amp; Son together with the interest accrued on it should he banded over to the firm’s agent in Bombay and that the balance of the first deposit together with the second deposit should be held by Government pending the appearance of a rightful claimant to whom the money can be paid without endangering the public interest. 5. I am now to request that Haji Ahdur Rahman Shirazi may be informed that, in the circumstances, the Government of India regret t)iat they are unable to issue any orders m regard to the payment of any other sum than the sum ol Rs. 40,000 to 50,000 which is shown to be due to him. 6. Einally, I am to say that, while commercial cables from and to Ahdur Rahman Shirazi &amp; Son are carefully scrutinized in Bombay and explanation^ are asked of any doubtful transactions, every effort is made to avoid unneeeg* $ary interference with legitimate business.e cliaro, conlroli 10 , otl'er tb ] eon tlie poii m fte Foreki '8 Cod, St® No, lij, lsi' i tie accitl ig tne flet® e up a lilt rty ot tte Ss oW !(MR put IstJme# pfitlP y Wjr 1 j ! /eal^ No. 1305 W., dated Simla, the 3rd August 1915 (Confidential). Fr0m ~ T tica?C t0 ^ G0Vernme,lt of Ind - - foreign and Poli To-The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay. dated 1 thp m 2lt lr Tn t lt d loiK a0kn0 ^ 1 - ed8 P, the rece! I jt of yo«r letter No. 354 P.-W dated the 21st July 1915, regarding the representations made by Haii Ahdnr Babaian ot Shiraz m respect of sums held in deposit at Bombay. y J d 2. I am to say, for the information of the Governor in Council that the Government of India agree to action being taken in. regard to the* deposite on the lines proposed in paragraphs 5 and 6. of your letter. ueposits 3. I am to add that, as recommended in paragraph 9 of your letter under reply, His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, has been asked to conF tider the possibility of Ittihadi receiving funds from other sources. No. 1306 W., dated Simla, the 3rd August 1915 (Confidential). From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To—His Britannic Majesty's Envoy Extraordinay and Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of Persia, Tehran. J In continuation of tlie telegram from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, No. S. 765, dated the 2nd August 1915, I am directed to forward, for in formation,, a copy of the marginally-noted correspond ence relating to representa- ■d r - m . . . tions made by Haji Abdur Itanman of Shiraz in regard to the interception of certain remittances credited to their firm at Bombay at the instance of Ittihadi of Tehran. Letter from His Britannic Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz, No. 105, dated the 24th June 1915, and enclosure. Letter to the Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, No. 1090 W., dated the 6th July 1915. Letter from the Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, No. 354 P.-W., dated the 21st July 1915. Letter to His Britannic Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz, No. 1304 W.. dated the 3rd August 1915. Letter to the Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, No. 1305 W., dated the 3rd August 1915. No. 1307 W., dated Simla, the 3rd August 1915 (Confidential). From—The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To—The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department,. Bombay. With reference to your telegram, No. 360 P., dated the 23rd July 1915 , Telegram to Major A. P. Trevor, C.I.E., Officer on Special Duty I am diiected to forward, for - in the Persian Gulf, No S. 729, dated the 26th July 1915. Telegram from Major A. P. Trevor, C.I.E , officer on Special Duty in the Persian Gulf, No. 345 C., dated the 27th July 1915. Telegram from His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, No. 82, dated the 27th July 1915. the information of the Gov ernor in Council, a copy of the marginally-noted correspond- # ence regarding the removal of German assistants from the employ of Messrs. Ziegler of Persia. 2. In view of the assurance that the firm are endeavouring to meet the wishes of His Majesty's Government in the matter, the Government of India do not consider that action on the lines suggested by the Government of Bombay is at present necessary. Telegram R., No. 51, dated the 2nd (received 3rd) August 1915. T’o—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla.f vr Tele-raitt P., No. 416 P., dated (and received) the 5th August 1915. From—-The Secretary to the Government &lt;*£ Bombay Political Department Bombay, To-The Secretary to the Government o£ India m the Forergn and Poht.cal Depart- ment, Simla. r prman money Please refer to your telegram, dated the 31st July 1915. Transaction is objectiona^ “ “ * 8 “‘ ,or funds was recently intercepted by the Postal Censor. Telegram It., No. S. 792, dated the 8th August 1915. From-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran, latest information indicates that Ittihadi has adopted new name of Haji LutWi Tabriz! He asks to he addressed in that name at Tehran or Afshar at Tezd. Following names given in communication intercepted . 1. Mashhadi Ismail Salmasi, Kerman, 2 _ Haji Muhammad Welinkani, or his agents, Kerman, 3. Afshar, Yezd, 4. Ears Company, Shiraz, and 5. Sons of Aminuttijar, Ispahan. They will occur in connection with cheques. Letter was addressed to Mirza Muhammad Tacki Afshar, Bombay. Papers posted. Addressed Tehran; repeated Shiraz. No. 1369 W., dated Simla, the 10th August 1915 (Confidential). ^ rom The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Political Department, To—His Britannic Majesty's Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipoten lary at the Conrt of Persia, Tehran. In continuation of the letter from the Government of India m the Foreign Letter from the Government of Bombay, _ Political Department, and Political „ j Qn+u TnW 1Q15 onH PtiP.loftnPft. No. 964 C., dated the 30th July 1915, and enclosure. Letter from the Government of Bombay, Political Department, No. 1000 C., dated the 3rd August 1915. ... tv Telegram from the Government of Bombay, Political Depart ment, No. 416 P., dated the 5th August 1915. Telegram to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, No. S. 791, dated the 7th August 1915. No. 1306 W., dated the 3rd August 1915, I am directed to forward, for information, a copy of the marginally-cited correspondence regarding Ittihadi and Abdur Rahman Shirazi. . Telegram P., No. 97, dated (and received) the 7th August 1915. From—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran, _ , The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political ep To ment, Simla. ) . Please refer to your telegram No. 765 S. t There are so many channels for obtaining money through ^j. chants open to the firm in question that it is impossible to preve operations or to trace them.ID* 'na: e tter from l| Telegram P M dated the 16th (received 17th) August 1915. From—His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Please refer to Foreign and Political Department telegram No. 792 S. re Ittihadieh. Necessary steps (at ?) branches have been taken by the Bank, but they report that Afshar, Yezd, is a common designation and without further details is difficult to identify. Italian Minister appears satisfied that the dealings of Marobio with the firm are genuine and are harmless commercial transac tions on behalf of Italian firms. The well known Ittalian carpet firm of (Castelli at Tehran is represented by Ittihadieh. 115, ■MM*(COPY), Telegram p, s Prom - Tiae oecretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To - - The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay# Please refer to my endorsement No,1207~W., dated the j.6th instant* German money for Persia, The following telegram, dated 20th'instant, has been received from His Majesty's Secretary of State for India 'The following telegram was received * * * * with each other'. Telegram P*, No*S*710, dated the 23rd July 1915, Prom The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To - - His Britannic Majesty's Consul for Shiraz, Shiraz, (repeated to His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran)» Please refer to Foreign and Political Department telegram No*S*495 of the 7th April 1915* On the 20th instant His Majesty's Secretary of State for India telegraphed as follows 'There are indications * * * * * financial dealings with each other'.(COPY), Telegram F., No,725 S,, dated the 26th July 1915, From - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To - - The Secretary to the Government of 3a&amp;at±ai Bomhay, Political Department, Bomhay* Secretary of State telegraphs on July 23rd as follows ^Rahman Shirazi * * * * * Manchester Bank', The above is repeated with reference to my telegram No,S*708, dated 23rd July 1915,(COPY) Yjf4- Telegr&amp;n t No*75B S, 9 dated the 31st July 1915* From - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To - - The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay. On the 29th instant His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India telegraphed as follows 'Credit Lyonnais have been instructed * * Your reply on these points should be sent by telegraph to the Government of India. * * and who these people are**CONFIDENTI AL,. (COPY). No. 1189 C. Of 1915. Political Department, Bombay Castle, 19th August 1915. From J. E. C. Jukes, Esquire, Deputy Secretary to Government, Bombay, To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Sir, With reference to your telegram No.708-3., dated the 23rd July 1915, I am directed to forward, for the information of the Government of India, a copy of a letter from C. F. Prins, Tehran, to the Holland -Bombay' Trading Company, Bombav, who handeo it over to the Postal Censor, Bombay. I have, etc., Sd/- J- E. C. Jukes, Deputy Secretary to Government.(COPY) s C* F, PRINB p Teheran* Telegraphic Address; Prins Teheran, Teheran* 30th June 1915, Holland-Bombay Trading Company Ld,, Bombay Dear Sirs 9 Your favour of the 27th of May came so just to hand* Enclosed I beg to hand you a cheQue on the Hongkong Shanghai Banking Corporation for Hup. 43-15-0* Hope that you win not have any difficulties this time, I regret very much that my first cheque has not been paid* I do not know the reasons, but can only think that the Government wants to have the Rupees Market altogether in hand* The merchant, of whom I sent you the cheque, is doing at present very large business in exchange. It is the best business in fact* One can easily earn 10 to 15^, on account of Russia buying at present more than exporting to here, exchange is very favourable* By buying on Moscow and remitting from there to London and then to Holland and from Holland bank-notes are sent to has to come back again to here and this is done Sweden or Bombay* Here no news, 8.11 4is quiet* Business is very bad* to the middle of May. I am still here alone, my family Germany, one makes a net profit of 15%* Now the money A very good crop is expected* We had a lot of rain up is in the Hague* Yours faithfully.(COPY), Telegram - P. From - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department } Simla, To - - The Secretary to the Government of Bombay* Political Department* Bombay* N0.877-S. Dated the 26th August 1915* Attention is invited to your letter 1189~C* of the 19th instant. In regard to communications from Prins please exercise special watchfulness. This man does extensive business for the German Legation at Tehran, a fact proved by correspondence intercepted there.■ 9 (COPY), From 'M ,(V a aaftf) vlvvi/ ,sm To I^e Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, His Britannic Majesty’s Envoy Extraordinary ana Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of Persia, Tehran* Daued Simla, the 26th August 1915* Sir, In continuation of the telegram from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, No,S~71Q, dated the 2Srd July 1915, which was addressed to His Britannic Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz and repeated to you, I am directed to forward, for your information, a copy of a letter from C.F* Prins, Tehran, to the Holland-Bomhay Trading Company, Bombay, who handed it over to the Postal Censor, Bombay I have, etc*, Sd/~ A* H. Grant , Secretary to the Government of India*Confidential, (COPY). No. 1276 C. of 1915. Political Department, Bombay Castle, 26th August 1915. Prom J. E. C. Jukes, Esauire, Deputy Secretary to Government, Bombay', To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of Indi Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Sir, With, reference to the telegram from His Britannic Majesty's Minister at Tehran-, dated the 16th August 1915, which was received with Mr. Maffey's endorsement No.1445-W., da^ed the - August 1915, I am directed to state, for Oae information of the Government of India, that 'Afskar, Yesd' is the telegraphic address of the firm of Afshar Brothers, Commission Agents of Yezd. The -p +v.f. firm in Yezd is Haji Mahomed Sadia manager of the firm xn Afshar. The business of the branch of the firm in Bombay is carried on by Mahomed Sadiq's Mother, Mirza Mahomed Taai Afshar. I have, etc., Sd/- J* E. C. Jukes, Depfity Secretary to Government.(COPY). ~l so Telegram - R. From - The Secretari r to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department,Simla To - - His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran. No.S.897. Dated the 1st September 1915. Your telegram August 16th. Ittihadieh. Afshar, Yezd, is telegraphic address of Afshar Brothers, Commission Agents Yezd. Name of Manager is Haji Mahomed Sadiq Afshar. Business of Bombay branch firm is carried on by Sadiq's brother, Mirz Mahomed Taqi Afshar. Addressed Tehran, repeated Shiraz.f tf n erma i O ICutY). 1*0. ^64 - c. 01 ly 15. /j X c/ ioilucal Oepartm^at, Bombay Castle, 30tli Culy 1^15. To J. 1. C. Jukes, Esquire, Jeputy Secretary to Government, Bombay, TBe foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Sir, in continuation of ^ r. Bobertson*® letter ho. 354-F.W., dated the 2ist July 1915, I am directed to forward for the information of tne Government of India a copy of a translation of a letter in Persian intercepted by the Postal Censor, Bombay i have, etc., Bel/ m J.E.C. Jukes, Deputy Secretary to Goverraent, 11’Ow 2.t&gt;3 I’Tom to ieuran, i6tti rtajab 1336 uijri, i.e., 31st kay 1815. riaji Lautffalli Xabresi, Mir?.a Uuhanmad lackl Afahar, Bombay. 51 r. lue state of affairs la tue same as stated before. It Is a long time since no letter has been received from you which would have required a reply. But two days ago the Afahar (firm! of Yesd was informed telegraphically to grant you permission to caon the cheques of ittehadiyah and their agents. Ihe details thereof are as follows: a good round sum was sent by the firm of ittihadiyah to the firm of Hajl Abdul Hallman Shirazi and Bon in Bombay, and even the agents of ittehadiyah had sent 'Havalas* la kind of tiundii from Kerman and Yezd. Three days back a telegram came from the Haris Company etating that uaji Abdul Hahman has received an order from Government not to honour the cheques and letters of ittehadiyah and that consequently the amount of the above mentioned cheques will not be paid, inis has puzzled us the most, it seems that tue British are labouring under a misunderstanding in this matter, since ittehadiyah is a subject of a neutral state like Hersla, foreign policy does not in any way dictate that without any reason the earnings of the ittehadiyah should be stopped anu its credit and reputation should be allowed to suxxer. At any rate it is clear that the British have mistrust for the name of Ittehadiyah. Heuce the Afsnar at Yezd was tele graphically informed to give you immediate permission I toiT' to ioanage conjointly with Kaji Abdul Hatuitan to cash the cheques and the bills of our agents. 1 am waiting for the issue, as hereafter the name Ittehadlyah is likely to tx involve me into difficulties in Bombay, i have, from tills date, alterred the designation of my office in Bombay into Lautffalli Xabrezi. Very likely you will get in Bombay about a hundred thousand rupees on account of this firm. You should in no way use the name ittehadiyah in passing receipt, hay, even while telegraphing Lautffalli labrezi at fenran, you snould act accordingly or simply wire 'Received* to Afahar at Yezd. At that time Afshar will inform me and through his medium (?) will be sold. The object is that the name of Ittehadiyah should not intervene. The name a which might hereafter occur in connection with cheques are given below so that it may not be necessary to wire the same at length. Haji Abdul liahman has acted timidly in not cashing the bills. If he had any objection he ought not to have accepted the amount on our behalf. In any case 1 hope you will be good enough to honour the cheques drawn by us and cash them so that they &gt;ay not be dishonoured and may not entail lose on us. one hundred thousand (rupees) entrusted to you may be given. If any further particulars are needed please address Lautffalli Xabrezi at Tehran or Afshar at Yezd. Xhe following is tne list of names:- Mashhad! Ismail oalmasi, Kerman, daji khOmmaA welinkani, or his agents,Kerman Afshar, Yezd, Fars Company, Chiraz Sons of Amirmttljar, IspahanCUitfla^VIlAL . ICOl'Y). 1 fTs' NO. 1000-C. or 1915. iolitical Departdaeut, Bombay Castle, 3rd /unjust 1915. r’roizi J. N. C. &lt;iuke 8 , Esquire, ueputy Secretary to Government, Bombay, To ; : Ibe Foreign Secretary to the Government or India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Sir, I am directed to refer to the correspondence s ending with your telegrams Nos.708^ and 725 S., dated respectively the 23rd and the 26th July 1915. 2. I am to say that the telegrams from Mosers Abdur Hahman Shlrazi and Son to the kanchester ianK in Manchester were Intercepted by the Cable Censor in Bombay and were passed by the special officer with this Govern ment after investigation of to® facts, it appears tnat the Bombay firm had for years had an account open with the Manchester Bank, as well as with tne firm of ..euars Bllinger and Company in that city, and tod generally maintained a good balance in both these accounts, inis fact has been confirmed by toe Manager of toe National Bank in Bombay, who has shown every readiness to assist Government in toe matter and has satisfied himself of toe truth of this statement, it appears that dhiraai’s credit has suffered somewhat in Bombay through the action of Government in connection with toe i ersian remittances. Being hard pressed for funds, ne telegraphed for a sun of £ 3000 out of toe total amount of £ 37000 -standing to his credit in Manchester. Forgetful, according to nis own account, of toe fact that he tod recently transferred £1850£ 1860 from the Manchester Bank to Messrs kllinger, he applied to the Bank to pay the full amount to the national baiiK ox India in London for remittance to his credit with their Bombay branch. It was this application which drew from the bank the reply that funds were Inadequate for the purpose, uhlrasi then cabled to allinger to pay &amp; 1200 to the Manchester Bank and to the Bank to pay to the national Bank the full amount standing at his credit. 3. The next development was indicated by a second tele- gran from the Manchester Bank to Shirazl, wlxich was explained by a representative of the National Bank sent round to the Secretariat for the purpose. The National Bank in London refused to accept payment on Shirazi's account, on the ground that they preferred to have no dealings with him. The Bombay branch, at the request of Ohlr&amp;sl, inquired whether they might inform their home office that the Bombay Government had no objection to the remittance. On a consideration of all the circumstances the Governor in council was of opinion that the remittance might safely be allowed. While there was good reason to suppose that Shirasl needed the money for the purposes of his legitimate business, it was evident that its use could be more easily controlled by Government if it came to Bombay than if it remained in ianchester. The officials of the National Bank in Bombay were accordingly informed that Government had no objection to the remittance. In reply however they have stated that they have received instructions from their office in England forbidding them to have any dealings with the firm of Ghirasi in Bombay. In these circumstances the firm has been informed that Government cannot bring pressure to bear on the National Bank of India to undertake their business. 4. In conclusion, 1 am to say that a watch will be kepi, for correspondence addressed to 'Brins, Butch utorekeeper. --leheran’. I have, etc., -id/- J. £. C. Jukes, Deputy Secretary to Govenwent(COPY) Telegram - r. Krom - Tiie Secretary to tne Ooverniaeut, o£ India in tue r'orelgn and Political Department, Simla, To - * The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department. / Ho. 3-791, dated the 7th August 1915. Haji Latfall's letter to Afsliar should be delivered in ordinary course to addressee unless you see any objection. Transactions can then be controlled. Poregoing is with reference to your letter ho.964-C. of the 30th Duly- In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. /1915 and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 'T 'i j % ! J T'Jtc Under-Secretary oj' StdCtc fov Fovsigw siffciiys pvescwts his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for ^ -— and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop OLd of the under-mentioned Foreign Office, (JU^^ar^C , igiy Lettermmmm m Jopy. J. 25,666. 119458) levy Confidential . Sir:- BOAHD OP TRADE, (CO/MERCIAL DEPARUvIENT), GWYDYR HOUSE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 25th August, 1915 With reference to your letter of the 2nd. August (No,99777/15) respecting the fiitn of Messrs. B. Shamash Brothers and company of Manchester, I an directed by the Board of Trade to state, for sir E. Grey’s infomation, that they learn, as a result of enquiries which have been made by the Intelligence Branch of this Department, that the company in question are a Bagdad film of merchants and shippers established in Manchester in 1897 with an alleged capital of £50,000. No confinnation was ever received that the Company actually possessed this sum, which was, moreover, said to have been held in Bagdad, Although before the war Messrs. Shamash were able to obtain credit for £1,000 in Manchester, Messrs, seyds, it is understood, are now unable to rate them as the Company have refused to disclose their financial position to their Bank - a refusal which is contrary to Messrs. Shamash’s practice before the war, and cannot therefore be regarded otherwise than with .suspicion, I am to add that the Board have no infoimation as to any German proclivities on the part of the firm in question. I have, &amp;c., (Signed) Gamharn Roper. Che Under secretary of state, Foreign Office.—™ V f' I'-*' *&lt; \ O '■ i »...,&gt; i Telegram - p« ■2 h ~L ^2, *rf From - The Secretary to the Government ot India r in the Foreign &amp; Political Department, Simla ■HiS m d m 9q(jiiE siiqBJ j Ml yowofl Wo ol si II jdl ol To - Hie Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran® (Repeated to His Majesty’s Secy, of State for India). No® S-706, dated the 23rd July 1915 . The following intercepted telegram has bee^rom^ Lont&amp;no # To the Imperial Bank of Persia Sultanabad Persia, i75o Will you please pay Tavshanjian 1000 pounds® Newellc* Please inform us by wire whether you know who Tavshanjian is and whether cable should be permitted to go on« The name of the Manager of the Imperial Bank of Persia, London, is said to be Newell. ww* TXSEEasaPBrs; I Reived on 25 AIK ii a ' ’ C3 * .yith INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Letter. i; 0 . 30 HTelegram - P» Prom - His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To - The Secretary to the Government of India In the Foreign &amp; Political Department. No.79, dated and reed, the 25th July 1915. Please refer to your telegram No.706, dated 23rd 4. July. Firm mentioned is of New York, Its employes in Persia are all Armenians. It deals in carpets and is of good repute. It xul sells to Imperial Bank of Persia drafts drawn in New York on Barr's Bank London. Newell Is as described. It does not appear to he likely that they would he helping the Germans.Telegram • P* Prom *- The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign &amp; Political Department e To - The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department* No ®738~S*| dated the 28th July 1915, Reference is invited to your confidential letter to Home No*675-*C« of the 8th instant* The telegram to the Imperial Bank, Persia, Saltanabad, from Mr* Newell, London, reepecting Tavshanjian which was Intercepted may now be passed on. Mr. Newell is Manager, Imperial Bank Persia, London, and Tavshanjian is firm of New York with Armenian employes in Persia.Put r.wry witli [This Document is the Property of Eis Brilamilc Majesty^ Government, and should be returned to the Foreign OffifiE wiiep done with milesB required for official use.] f p ^ (3^ !2963 ! v_ ■ &gt;—&gt; : $4 is mmrsaty persta Decypher. Mr. Marling (Teheran) D. Nccn July 24th, 1915. R. 5.45.p.ra. Nc. _259. (R). July 24th. £ ^ . (/^ io Your telegram Nc. .180. Government of India have recently requested Imperial Bank of Persia net to have any dealings with firm mentioned which was attempting to get money for enemy through Bombay. Presumably therefore firm should be still regarded as tainted. 4 SA c r*o J put away With 3 Sit- From Viceroy, Sth August 1915. ff 2 777 Foreign Secret. Your telegram of 29th July. German money. Bombay Government Report P. dated 5th August : — “Transaction objectionable. Taki and Sadik Afshar are brothers work- j? ing in Bombay and Yezd respectively. Postal Censor recently intercepted fQ*. letter to former from Ittehadi appointing him as agent for importing funds g# in place of Shirazi.” Z o— From Viceroy, 23rd July 1915. (Addressed Tehran, repeated to Secretary oj State for India.) Foreign Secret. Following telegram from London:—“To Imperial Bank of Persia. Sultanabad. Persia. 175. Pay Tavshanjian 1,000L Newell,” has been intercepted. Please telegraph whether you know who Tavshanjian is and whether cable should A A**' be allowed to go on. Newell is said to be name of manager, Imperial Bank of Persia, London. *Z1 2L PERSIA. Flli^S ONLY . Cypher Telegram to Mr r Marling (Teheran) Foreign Office, July 19tlC 19rp r ! 4 r ’|) r p r m NO e 191 r K % I • V ‘ r %*i l 59 Secreto My telegram No„ 182 (of 14th r July, Monsieur Prins)r Following is substance of further letter dated 14th r June r 'Your wire 7thr June received and transfer to Shirazi noted' (Probably Hajji Abdur Kaiimen Shirazi is meant)r 'I confirm my telegrarru Remit nothing Shirazi, wire whether transferred', I have difficulties and at present I do not want anything to be remitted 0 Hope that you have passed on my wire. Be not too explicit , in informations, I do not want to know anything. You must not forget that I suffer and not the party who has written. One has to be a bit careful, I have no informations for you from here, (Here follow orders for sweets.. cigars etc,) 'Goods must all be sent direct go here and no longer through Ter Sarkissiantz, This fellow must have received previous parcels and kept them. It is better that telegrams are not signed ’ArB, ’ but any other name, 'Parcels should be marked Poste Restante Jnzeli Via Baku, Jnzeli, monsieur Prins, Mags,zin iiollvucialb, Teheran, perhaps your Russian colleasujgj at Baku regarding last, paragraph/* 20JU11915U .. v 'take action;&lt;* v, • % 1 PERSIA. (92i351/15) r Piles only Cypher telegram to Mr, Marling (Tehran). Foreign Office. July 14th 191j r 2.45 p.m N o. 1 32. Secret. Following is suhstance of intercepted letter dated 12th June from C.FrPrins, Tehran to his brother in Stockholm:- 'Do not give details in your letters and telegrams, I receive no wire of which British Legation does not get copy. I am doing here extensive business for the Legation (i.e. German Legation) hut nobody must know anything about it and if you send long wires and letters everyone will Know, Write in manner that no one under stands. English are too strong for Turks on Euphrates, Principal thing however is tnat Constantinople does no u fall. Everything turns round Constantinople , The:re are big intrigues go inn on here. , but I p e 1 i o v e no t nine, will happen here. People here are naturally on sine oi Germans hut not so much on side oi Turks, I should not be surprised if English and Russians do all possicle to induce Persia to declare war on Turkey, so that spectre of holy war disappears« Persia nowcvei fe^rs to come into conflict with Germany and that there will be difficulties with population and a complicated situation. All however will pass ca lmly buo still there is certain amount of danger. So long as halvesu ^6JUL|9J5 ismatter to do all this business &lt;1 ziir is not Ratherod and cooler weather sets in nothing will happen here, I receive my goods regularly from Englandr I will take care you receive money regularly from Amsterdam, If you have something special you must then write through the intermedia nnr of the ForMm. J iff ice,, Jji. Berlin, The:/ r send every thins for me,,. It is no smallSlE, In continuation of our telegram in the Foreign and Political Depart- ment, dated the 27th May 1915, regarding the transfer of enemy money for the use of the German Legation at Tehran, we have the honour to forward, for the information of His Majesty’s Gov- . No. 363 c., dated the 5th Jtine 1915. ernment&gt; a C opy 0 f a letter * from the Government of Bombay, on the subject. 'We have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servants,No. 363 C., dated Bombay Castle, the 5th June 1915 (Confidential). From L. Robertson, Esq., Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. I am directed to address you, in continution of my telegram No. 267 C. of the 25th may, on the subject of the transfer of enemy money for the use of the German Legation at Tehran. I am to explain that, when your confiden tial letter No. 819 W., dated the 20th May lyl5, was received, the particular transaction reported in my telegram was already under investigation, ha vino* come to notice in the Cable Censorship. 2. Before describing the nature of that transaction, I am to state what is known of the parties concerned in it. The Agent in Persia who apparently acts for the German Legation is one Haji Bahim bin Haji Lutfeali Ittihadi of Tehran, Yezd and Shiraz. This man, who will be mentioned as Ittihadi in the later paragraphs of this letter, has for very many years been the Agent of the Bombay firm of Abdur Bahman Shirazi and Sons. The principal of the latter firm, Abdur Bahman himself, has for some years been resident in Persia, where he is concerned in the directorate of the Shiraz firm known as the Pars Company. Ittihadi, who is actually the Managing Director of a large firm of General merchants and Commission Agents, draws very freely upon the Bombay firm of Shirazi in the ordinary way of business : his bills are. regularly honoured and he is often allowed very considerable overdrafts. Business of this kind, on a comparatively small scale, has been continuing, as before, ever since the war broke out. 3. To turn to the particular transaction now under reference. On the 18th May, the Cable Censor at Bombay intercepted a telegram addressed by “ Bahman Shirazi, Bombay ” to the “ Pars Company, Shiraz ”, which ran as follows:— “ Don’t sell sugar. Beceived 1,50,000 Ittihadi. ” Inquiries were at once made of the Bombay firm, who showed apparent readiness to give information. It was found that a lakh and-a-half of rupees had been paid to them on Ittijiadi’s account by the Chartered Bank on the 18th May. Inquiries from the Chartered Bank proved that its Bombay Branch had but iittle information on the subject. It had received on the 10th of May telegraphic instructions from its London Office to pay Bs. 1,50,000 to “ Abdul Abder Shirazi ”, Not knowing the name, the Branch called for instructions and after a somewhat unusual delay, received further intimation that the pay ment should be made to Abdur Bahman Shirazi. The Bombay Branch of the Chartered Bank had no further knowledge of the transaction. A significant fact, to which I am to revert in a later paragraph cf this letter, is that three cables on the subject had passed without attracting the notice of the Cable Censor. 4. When the money was paid over to Shirazi, the position of Ittihadi’s account was according to Shirazi somewhat as follows :— Ittihadi was over drawn to the extent of rather over Bs. 40,000. As against this, Shirazi held Ittihadi’s bills for £5,000 on the Credit Lyonnais in London, but he knew by experience that he would be unable to sell these without telegraphic reference to Ittihadi himself. Owing to the action now taken, it will, of course, be impossible to negotiate them. Shiraz was at once warned to honour no draft of Ittihadi pending the receipt of further instructions. By the evening of the 24th, when definite orders were finally given, bills to the extend of no less than Its. 80,000 drawn by Ittihadi on Shiraz were actually in Bombay; and the holders were clamouring for payment. These, it may be stated, have now been dishonoured. 5. The immediate need was to prevent the utilisation of any part of the I-| lakhs in the financing of operations in Persia. Messrs. Abdur Bahman expressed themselves as perfectly willing to obey any orders that might bef:fi* t ' 1 1 -r ! 1 issued, but stated that, in the absence of orders, commercial honesty would not allow them to dishonour Ittihadi’s drafts. They were accordingly served with a notice requiring them, on pain of prosecution for trading with the enemy, to place the sum of lakhs in deposit, to break off all financial dealings with Ittihadi and to dishonour all his drafts in future. At the same time they asked for permission to telegraph to their principal, Abdul Rahman, in Persia, and inform him that the Government of Bombay had forbidden further dealings with Ittihadi. As it was clearly desirable to impair Ittibadi’s credit in Persia, they were allowed to send the cable; and in pursuance of the same object telegrams regarding the dishonouring of one of the big bills still outstanding have since been allowed to go through. Subse quently on the recommendation of the legal advisers of Government, the notice already given was supplemented by a further notice drawing attention to paragraph 2 of Ordinance VI of 1914, the concluding words of which are clearly applicable to the case; warning Shirazi that further dealings of any kind, direct or indirect, with Ittihadi will inevitably be followed by prosecu tion ; and requiring him to place the sum of 1J lakhs on fixed deposit for three months with the Bank of Bombay, to be withdrawn only on the joint order of the firm and the Political Secretary to this Government. Copies of this notice were sent to the principal banks also. 6. I am to submit that, although this particular channel of remittance to Persia has apparently been securely stopped, there is nothing to prevent the stream following other channels. During the past few days, two cables from Ittihadi to the Credit Lyonnais, London, have been stopped in the censorship, in which he apparently asked for remittances direct to Persia. Abdur Rahman’s Bombay representatives gave information that such remittances are undoubtedly passing. Another possible channel would be remittance through Java ; and I am to say in this connection that a most unusually large amount of Dutch paper was negotiated in Bombay in the early months of this year. Finally, although one intermediary in Bombay has been laid by the heels, there may already be others in existence and there most certainly will be others when Shirazi’s uselessness is discovered. The Cable Censorship affords inadequate means of detection where influential banks are concerned. Cables, from London in particular, if transmitted in an authorised code, are passed with out question by the Censor. He could not attempt to decode the whole number without a considerable increase of establishment: even if he did so, a slight manipulation of names would render detection almost impossible. I am therefore to state the conviction of the Governor in Council that action to stop German remittances at this end of the line is not likely to prove wholly successful. Action in London is clearly necessary, if a satisfactory result is desired. It is obvious from their communication on the subject that the authorities in England have much fuller information regarding these transactions than has yet reached Bombay. They know the inter mediaries in the affair, as well as the principal banks concerned. In this connection, it may be mentioned that a recently intercepted cable indicates Messrs. B. Shamash Brothers and Company of 46, Bloom Street, Manchester, as being actively interested in the remittances. The Governor in Council desires strongly to urge that the full facts should be represented to the Secre tary of Slate for India, and that His Majesty’s Government should be urged to stop the stream of funds at the fountain head. Negotiations with the English banks concerned and, in particular, with the Head Office of the Imperial Bank of Persia coupled with a strict censorship of commercial cables to the East, are likely to effect infinitely more than could be accomplished in Bombay. 7. I am to add that a strict watch will be kept over the dealings of Abdur Rahman Shirazi and Sons, and that any further developments will be reported to the Government of India. FC1915 . SIMLA. FOREIGN AND POLITICAL SECRET. War. No. 51, DATED THE 24TH JUNE 1915. Letter to MU Majesty’* Secretary of State for India. Transfer of enemy money for the use of the German Legation at Tehran. F. &amp; P. Dep^ PrssB—No. 1109—21-6-15-1A’ 311X1(1 c G 0 P Y 0,1 No. 465 C of 1915 { put ■•'Political Department: ?B28 I Bo: -*py c Stle, 17th June 1915. From v... 11 ; ,f O c; iBOUXl 6 Deputy Secretary to Government, Bombay, To oreion Seeretar ov-rn ; o:t of India, Foreign and Political Department, St XL a. Q i r In continuation of Mr. Nobertson’s letter No.363-C., dated the 5th June 1915, I am directed to report for the inf 01 ion of the Government of India that a further sum of one lakh of rupees, intended for Ittihadie, has been intercepted in Bombay. The money nas remitted co the Bombay branch of the Eastern Bank by its home office for the credit of Abdur Barman Shirazi IS $, once reported the remittance, and orders have been given to place the money in deposit in the Bank of Bombay on terms similar to those imposed in the case of the remittance previously intercepted. I am to add that, shortly before the Eastern Bank;, received the cable announcing the remittance, Shirazi had given information . that he had b en warned to expect a. further remittance of 1-J lakhs of rupees on Ittihadie’s account. A careful watch sill be kept for the balance of Bs.75,000/-. 2. I am further to refer to ry telegram of the 10th instant, and to explain that the cable on which that telegram was based emanated from Teher cLi**! y jrded . s foil ons i %i.:ie name 'Akpavan 11 naF appeared as ,, AichavaIl ,, in oilier cOiiimunications, anct it is not* known which form is correct 3. Finally, I am to report for information that other cables intercepted by the Censor indicate that his majesty 1 s Government have informed the Manchester and Liverpool District Banking Company that it ”* s inadvisable for them to receive further monies on Shirasi’s account. The Bank t ' phed to Shirazi .to this effect. I have, etc., Sd/- J.E.C, Jukes, Deputy Secretary to Government.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote I'9'S No. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, F ''' ,is, ’ 0 Ena„„. pU* k ■-», 4- v , -■ - -CV&gt; r A- * r i &gt; 26 54 4-.'3» V.*' i o T'^ Under-Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for } , and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned faperS. Foreign Office, Copy to India 23 JUL1915 Letter Reference to previous correspondence : Foreign Office: —N copy 0.861?, 2/15 Your .xcellency;- OFFICB, July 16uu, 11,15. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of Your excellency's Note of the 28th ultiaio, relative to the payment by the Credit Lyonnais of a sisn of iwo thousand pounds to the account of Messrs, itta- hadie f’rferes in rehraji. In view of the circumstances neitioned in Your excellency s Note the action of the French Bank was fully justified, and 1 hasten to express iny regret that Your excellency was inconvenienced in the matter owing to a slight misunderstanding. His Majesty's Treasury have now been in direct correspondence with the representatives of the Credit Lyonnais in London as regards the question of remittances to Persia, and I feel sure that no similar misunderstanding His excellency Monsieur carabon,(UO.86122/15) mieunderstanciing will arise in the future. I have the honour to be, with the highest I consideration, Your Excellency's most obedient. humble servant,\ Date. Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary Secretary of State rinmmittee JLo (xr^r. Under Secretary Secretary of State ' &lt;0pyt ° FOR INFORMATION.[Tills Document Is the Properly of Hia Britannic Majesty's government, and v . should be returned to the Foreign Office when dene A with unless required for official use.] 1 No • 180c Sir Wc Townley’s telegram No. 35 (of 29th. Janu ary. Money for Germans). Several British houses or their correspondents have been recently buying cheques of H. Rahim H. Lutfali Ittihadie et Fils of Teheran. I presume that firm should still be regarded as tainted. If you concur I propose to prohibit payment of Ittahadie’s cheques in this country. This would be a strong step to take and would be only justifiable if the firm was really dangerous. We are now exercising over his cheques such supervision as is possible*Immediate and Confidential. •9 ! The Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Ajfairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of eg telegram, as marked m the Foreign Office, i ,MB~A f\ , ^ jf ! ,&lt;4 | 4 F^LES Decypher of telegram from Mr. Trevor (Bushire) (d. 3.40 p.m. r. 12.15 p.m. July 1st). Your letter confidential dated April 24th to Zeigler of Manchester regarding the dismissal of their u-erman inanagers copy sent me by Consul. Letters from German in Tangistan named Bohnstorff and another from certain K.H.M. apparently in Teheran or Ispahan both to Austrian Doctor Biach now in Shiraz intercepted by us mention money transactions through Sauer and stett- lor agents of zeigler in Shiraz and Ispahan. Boifen- storff writes that second letter was forwarded to him H stupidly” by Sauer who is apparently acting as (? loose) agent for German party. Addressed to Foreign Office, sent to India, , , , bniraz, Teheran and Basra.' iq &lt; In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. /I9I5 aiui address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, Londont. • Put away with.....l.fjj »O 1 1 W * I V : Xr-T. ■;•***» The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs presents, his compliments to the Under-Secret ary of State for ■— and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned, paper. Foreign Office, cU ^ ■ - to Reference to previous correspondence: Letter ^ Foreign Office y WWi Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ms U25JUN13%/ R t C E « r t 125 JUN 1915 ; ..ui 1 t ■i!! £ IA ^tslgsim ilar letter sent toiopy l.tSTWlS. li5\T Z14 WaatOH QFFXUii, June 24th, 1SJ15. Your ' xctdiency:- v.ita relareace to ®y „4ote of tue .list of 2,''« JonUfiry last, relative to the import into Persia of money iar tue uee of tae jeroaa Legation in lehran and of other enemy agentB in /ereia, I have the honour to state tuat it has coae to the Knowledge of l ie l ajesty’s I Government that a further remittance of Two thousand pouuus to Tohra^ ob uccoui*u ul mcuots. xttaiiahlt rreree has recently been negotiated throu«j:x the credit Lyomiais in uondun. I mould be grateful if Your excellency would again warn the crldlt hyomials that such tnuis*- actions are undesirable and likely Injuriously to affect the present situation In rersia. X have the honour to Uth wi th wiie highest consideration, Your excellency's most obedient, humble servant, is excellency Monsieur caaibon, &lt;■? i ! Foreign Secret. Money for German Legation at Tehran. Following cable from Ziegler, Shiraz, to Ziegler Company, Manchester, has been withheld:— “ We cannot remit exchange on London, we recommend specie, Tehran. What will be rate for insurance ? ” Consul, Shiraz, whom we consulted, cannot understand object of transaction, and suspects money intended for German Legation. Reference Ziegler &amp; Co. Please see Foreign Secretary’s letter 12 M., dated 25th March. We suggest enquiry regarding Ziegler Company, Manchester./ In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. 75803/15- Foreign Office and address— The Under-Secretary of State, June 14th, 1915. Foreign Office, % London. nonildentlal. Sir:- With reference to your letter P.1974/15 f of the 2nd instant, regarding the transmission of enemy monies ' to Persia, I am directed hy Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you, herewith, to he laid before Mr. Secretary Chamberlain, a copy of a private letter from the Manchester and Liverpool District Banking company Limited, reporting the result of enquiries regarding Messrs. B. Shamash Brothers and company. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, hie Under Secretary of state, India Office.i 3opy. (M) Private. (75803) THE FtANCHESTEH AMD LIVERPOOL DISTRICT BANKING COMPANY LBilTED. 75 f COfMiILL, LONDON-E.G. 7th, June 1915. Dear Sir:- E. Bhamash Bro mer.s &gt; In reference to the above, our Manchester Office write:- H These people hank with the Union Bank of Manchester For the last eight years we have had occasion to obtain references about them and they are rad have been reported as very straightforward people and perfectly .right for their business engagements* We trust this information may be helpful. Yours faithfully, (Signed) W. Fergusson. L. Oliphant, Esq., Foreign Office.1 .XciGaiV .6LQI em/l •euq SS.d •jol lo W iftruijft fplyirt ^tfrso^ tiamto^J iweif® ©Ida® M|H|MMi HfruiiiT amO mM i tg*l9¥ .fiiimtiiSiL lo cfnj/oooji no rmirimf oS OO0 f SI y-^ x aniabelwornfoa xe^tariomM rf«a#noM b&amp;numhhM bm mr.p,qM fmrds Jqieotn ijteSecreta:^0, In any further communication on the subject, please quote NO- 71142/15. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, ^ London. Confldentla-l . Foreign Office &gt; 'j June 10th, 1915. 21 43 ' Sir:- I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to ac knowledge the receipt of your letter of the 2nd instant P.1974 regarding the remission of enemy monies to Persia. The question of the financial transactions of Hajji Abdur Rahman Shirazi has formed the subject of semi official discussion between this Depart ment and Sir Arthur Thring, who has now informed the Manchester and Liverpool District Banking Com- 111 pany Limited^ that he thinks it inadvisable from : the point of view of national interests, for that Bank to receive any further monies on the credit of the above-mentioned firm f end that it would be well for the Bank to send a telegram to this effect3&gt;0S 71142/15. - ; &gt; 143 t to the firm in Bombay and Shiraz. I am also to state, for the information of Mr. | Secretary Chamber lain, that the Imperial Bank of Per- d sia have also instructed their Manager at Teheran, that, in view of the suspicions entertained that the Fais Trading Company .which is the firm of Hajji Abdur Rahman Shirazi place funds at the enemy*s disposal f f the Bank’s branches at Shiraz and elsewhere should discontinue negotiating the firm’s drafts until other- v/ise instructed. Sir E. Grey considers that no further action is possible in this country at preserrtybut would suggest, for Mr. Chamberlain’s consideration, that the surest means of preventing the transmission of enemy funds to Persia v/ould be for the Government of India to contin ue to exercise the useful pressure which they are now exercising on persons like Shirazi end on one benno in India. It seems to him that the business may be more easily( : ; ■ - ‘ easily suppressed at the Hermini'’ than in this country vdiere it is very difficult to discriminate noxious from harmless transactions. I am to add that enquiries are being made with regard to Messrs. Shamash of Manchester^ and that a further communication will he addressed to you on the subject. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,1 Foreign Secret. (Term an Legation. y for corifidentiallv. r From Viceroy, 21th May 191 3. I ^ j Q Your telegrams dated 11 tli anVhtW+n^Fa^— ^ We addressed Bombay Government Their reply dated 25th May is as follows : — “ Bank duly warned, but this does not meet situation. Abduf Rahman recently received from Chartered Bank one and a half lakhs lor credit ol Ittihadie. Abdut' Rahman’s attitude helpful. Under formal threat of prosecution for trading with enemy, has agreed put one and a half lakhs in deposit, and to break off all dealings with Ittihadie, and to dishonour his drafts Abdul' Rahman also warns that remittances now going direct from ^Manchester bank to Persia, (’able intercepted to-day indicates Shanysh ^Brothers of Manchester as intermediary. Letter follows shortly. r?L USD EPARTMENTAL , Cypher Telegram to Mr, Marling (Tehran) Foreign Office, May 25th, 1915, No, 124, 5,0,p,m, Following for Manager of Imperial Bank oi Persia from London Office, (R), In view of suspicions entertained here that Pars Trading Company place funds at enemy’s disposal you should instruct Shiraz and other tranches to discontinue negotiating firms drafts until receipt of further in structions. \ i2 &gt;s; From Viceroy, 12th February 1915. (Repeated to Tehran.) Foreign Secret. From information from Tehran and enquiries at Bombay it appears that arrangements have been made to supply German Legation at Tehran with 14,000/. enemy money in following manner. Money has been paid to Amsterdamische Bank, who have paid it to London Credit Lyonnais to account of a Tehran broker, Ittadin. Credit Lyonnaise will probably transfer money to Manchester and Liverpool Listrict Banking Company, 75, Oornhill, London ; this bank would, unless warned not to do so, wire either to Ittadie, Tehran or to Hap A bd i i\ r B ain n an in Slhraz, or possibly in Bombay. Haji Abdul Rahman promises to stop the money if sent to'Bombay, but it is desirable, if possible, to stop remittance to Tehran or Shiraz, as money will obviously be used for German propaganda. From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 'drd April 1915. Foreign Secret. Your telegram dated 12th February. Manchester and Liverpool Bank received 3,000/. on Jbth March and 1,000/. on 25th March from Amsterdam Bank for account of Abdur Rahman of Shiraz. They were not asked to remit money but merely notiiy him of receipt. On olst March they were requested to remit 3,000/. 1 understand that they will not do so, but they cannot be prevented from receiving money for him. Your telegram seems to suggest that he is British subject. If so, cannot pressure be put on him to request his foreign correspond ents to stop these remittances ? From Viceroy, doth April 1915. (Repeated to Tehran.) Foreign Secret. Money for German Legation, dour telegram of the 3rd April. Haji Abdur Rahman is not a British but Persian subject of Shiraz. He has however promised O’Connor to decline nirther facilities of this nature carrying through his account with the Bank. 1 ersian merchant of Tehran is real ofiender about whom O Couuoi is addiessmg Minister. From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 1 1th May 1915. , F ;™ s 'Ssf'”'1 Cm, ymi arrange witl, S—I and other banks not to buy his bills on MancliesU i an ^ •84 /'Vom Viceroy, 26th April 1915. Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Te Korean, Secret. Money lor German Legation. Your telegram of the ord April, llaji Alxlnr Rahman is not a Rritish but Persian subject of Shiraz. He has however promised O’Connor to decline further facilities of this nature carrying through his account with the Bank. Persian merchant of Tehran is real olTender about whom O’Connor is addressing Minister.JL any further communication subject, please q\iote . 35445/15. Idress— Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. r 1 i i O Ci ^ i i i D n v LU. list Mi '»!■ &lt; . t Foreign Office April 1st, 1915. Slr:- i 9 i 5 4 at a^ay &gt; With reference to my letter of the 26th ultimo, regarding the remittance of certain sums of money to the account of AMur Rahman of Shiraz, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you, to be laid before the Marquess of Crewe, a copy of a further telegram which he has addressed to His Majesty 1 s Minister at Teheran on the subject. I am to suggest, for His Lordship’s consideration, the desirability of making enquiries,through the ^ Government of India^of Messrs. Abdur Rahman of Bombay as to the objects to which this money will be devoted as l ^ it appears from the Viceroy’s telegram of 12th February that the firm promised to stop the money if it were sent to Bombay. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State, s India Office.t This Documen fr is ^ Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when don e with unless required for official use.] &gt; PERSIA, 1 POLTIIOAL, Cypher telegram to Sir A. Tovfnley (Tehran) Foreign Office, March 26th 1915,. 3,30 prm. No. 77. 1m My telegram No. 44 Oof 14th February. Money for Germany) Manchester and Liverpool Bank received on 16th March £3000 and 25th March £1000 from Amst erdamische Bank for account of Abdur Rahman of Shiraz. No request was made that they should rom.it the money bu^ they complied-with request to notify Abdur Rahman of receipt of these sums. You should endeavour to ascertain if there are any indi cations of Ibcal draffs in Shiraz against this deposit..(17793) ilQ distribution. Cypher telegram-“to sir Vif. Townley (Teiirf-in) Foreign Office, February 1915. 6 p.ji.. 0 Q | j | Viceroy's telegram of 12th February, i.oney for Oeman Legation. I have explained matter to Manchester and Liverpool IBank who undertake that money shall not be transmitted.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. fl Mid address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. f'T D J.. 4 Q X The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for Jl W ^ and, by direction of the Secretary ■* of State, transmits herewith cop it# of the under-mentioned papery _ Foreign Office, ^ » iQidT*. f r ' 1 ( : - Ai ’ LA 12 FEB 1915 Reference to previous correspondence: LetterJ from Foreign Office: f, T'F Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. 1 ^ XtT. / K&lt;rv~. S 2.&amp;I Subject. I (Similar letter sent to Cia ]PERSIA Oop7. POLITICAL Be cypher, Sir W. Tovmloy (Tehran) January 29th, 1915 D. 8*45 a.n* R. 11.45 a.m. No. 35 Conficiential. My telegram Mo. 381. I have learnt secretly that Prins is again en deavouring to bring in money for the Germans this time through^ the Amsterdamische Bank Credit Lyonnais in London, and the Imperial Bank of Persia to the address of firm of Tehran Brokers called Ittahadieh. A ques tion is asked in one telegram as to remitting portion of money (£20,000) to Bagdad. First instalment expected was £40,000. A tele graphic transfer of £3,500 to Ittahadieh has been received. Manager here refused business as being enemy money. n (yCopy. AL . :uE . 25, ABCHURCH LAME, LONDON, E.C (1^72) 29th January, 1915 Dear Mr. Oliphant:- The Chairman requests me to give you particulars of the following incident. On the 27th instant the Credit Lyonnais in London paid us £3,500 with a request that we should instruct our chief office in Teheran by telegram to pay the equivalent to Messrs. H. R. ittihadie et fils, Teheran. we telegraphed the same day to our Teheran office requesting then to effect the payment and we have received to-day the following telegram from Mr. Wood:- 'In reply to your telegram of yesterday £3,500 enemy money. Can you cancel the operation?' 1 have to-day returned the money to the Credit Lyonnais and explained to them that we cannot make the payment. I have also telegraphed to Teheran that the transaction is cancelled. Yours, he., G. Newell p f* •'* 7 f' ft f f;T C, ti th 12 FEB 1915 (Signed)(KO.UU71V15) 1 should be grateful therefore if four Excellency would be so good as to j^ive such warning to the credit Lyonnais as may appear desirable to put them on their guard against accepting any business of a siiailar nature in the future. I have the honour to be, with the highest consideration, four sy* s i sat, humble servant,ft . Copy to India ^ 8 JAN 1915 t tion on this subject, jples«r4 &lt;fuote »-W73^ juid address— / The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. r V'- S The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop -it? of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 7 &gt; m Reference to previous correspondence Letter *T rom Foreign Office: tS&amp;CC 'Tit Description of Inclosure. Cu-Uriu^. tit. /Vo, 3*^ p** L /v. ) Kame and Date. Subject.n. 10 py. 88135) n% V rll£ BAiiK OF PERSIA, 25, ABCHURCH LAliE, N LQIvlDON, E.C. 29th Decenter, 1914, I ' ? /f i j i Sir:- 1 have th6 honour t0 acknowledge the receipt of your confidential letter No.84884/14 of yesterday's date and as requested will at once iniona the Secretary of state for Foreign Affairs of any enquiry addressed to tne Bank here with reference to the transfer of money from Amsterdam to Teheran. I am, &amp;c., (Signed) G. Newell. llanager. 16 Under Secretary of state for Foreign Affairs.Immediate and ^mifidential. The Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of ^ telegram , as marked in the margin. Foreign Office, If iff 12 (? j igiff.CONFIDENTIAL. ‘Vi Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.— (Received December 20. 2‘40 p.m.) Tehran, December 20, 1914. (December 20, 10'20 a.m.) (N0 ’rr 1 has come to my knowledge that a Dutch shopkeeper here named Prins ha^ asked Imperial Bank of Persia for a quotation for ° ^ COn F rom another of money from Amsterdam to ^ f ^ 10,0001.] source I learn that sum 'X ll is moLed that mone/be^ransmitted first of all to money religious fervour is likely to remain lukewarm.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000177_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/480</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000177</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/480</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 3516/1914 Pt 3 'German War: Persian neutrality; German money for Persia'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1914/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-12-21T22:58:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (349 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 351; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-349; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume concerns German remittances to Persia, and the Foreign Office's efforts to stop and prevent these.The volume covers:Transmission of money from Amsterdam to Tehran, to be used for German propaganda during the First World War, via Imperial Bank of Persia.Various German attempts to remit money to Shiraz via French, Dutch, and British banks, for the use of the German Legation at Tehran.Correspondence intercepted and individuals suspected, at Bombay and in Persia.Black list of Persian firms with whom trading is prohibited (ff 209-211).Financial transactions between Persia and India.Black list of Persian individuals accused of trading with enemy firms (f 136).Restitution of sums confiscated after the end of the War.The volume’s principal correspondents are: Maurice de Bunsen, Foreign Office; Walter Beaupre Townley and Charles Murray Marling, British Ministers at Tehran; Edward Grey, Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs; L Robertson and John Edwin Clapham Jukes, Secretaries to the Government of Bombay; Arthur Prescott Trevor, Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; Alfred Hamilton Grant and Hugh Vincent Biscoe, Secretaries to the Government of India; Arthur Hirtzel, Leonard Day Wakely, India Office; William Henry Lucas, Commissioner in Sind; Foreign Trade Department; War Trade Department; Government of India, Department of Commerce and Industry; H C B Mitchell, Custodian of Enemy Property at Bombay; George Newell, Imperial Bank of Persia Manager; the Manchester and Liverpool District Banking; Heyn, Franc &amp; Co; Klemantaski, Bates &amp; Co.There are some letters in French, from the French Embassy in London.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>The Manchester and Liverpool District Banking Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Custodian of Enemy Property</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Blockade, Foreign Trade Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Amsterdam</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Commerce Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>French Embassy, London</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Bank of Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>War Trade Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commissioner, Sind</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Bombay</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>India</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Mesopotamian Campaign (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>International trade</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000177#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>