<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000015_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-08-10T16:15:03.493Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">® fej 1 &gt; v Bri t iah i*ibaaay , . v Tehraai 4, ril # 1947* HO. 131 (GW1747) V&gt;il* 1 ; k l Jt I have the honour to traxranit to you herewith* copy of a note which I have thle day addreaaed to the Persian Minister for Foreign Affaira regarding an attacic upon Ills Majeaty^ Oonaui at Herman and Mrs. Alban by armed robbers on the 38th February. 2* I mi awaiting full details from Mr* Consul Alban regarding the extent of the damage inflicted and It may be necessary, on receipt thereof, for me to aeeK. your ins true tions aa t the formulation of a claim for compensation. 3* I shall not fail to inform you of further developments in this matter. I have the honour to be with the highest reapect, Sir, . Your moat obedient, huable servant, ^ (Sgd) J.H.LiS BDUGiiTSL The ^ight Honourable Smest bevin, ..., H.M. principal secretary of iitate for i4&gt;reign Affairs, ioreii.n office, &gt;. ».l*II Telegram fro] Letter Under Seer Secretary o Under Seer Secretary o■■■ .mm P ’ U C ° Py V** ^.o.Mo.y^yd-M/sg . ! / .,; .. External Affairs Department, 7404 Simla, 'V-L- IS ^ Q O T IQ 3rd July 1939 iwy dear Seymour, ^ould you kinaly refer to the correspondence ending with letter from His Majesty’s Consulate G-eneral, Khorasan, to the Chancery, British Legation, Tehran, !k&gt; .1012-0/6, dated the 9th of August 1937 regarding Mulki Chand dahny 2. The gentleman in question recently came to see me and explained the present position of his case. It would appear that the case has now been going on for nearly ten years and that there is no reason why it should not go on for several more years. 4testions have already been asked about it in the Legislative Assembly and more questions will probably be asked at the next session of the Assembly. 3. I hold no particular brief for Mulki Chand who may well have intended to smuggle the gold which was seized by the Iranian Customs authorities. From the records of the case, however, it would appear that it was seized some 600 miles from the Frontier and that any proof of indention to \smuggle it was entirely lacking. Whatever may have been the merits of the case originally, there can be no justi fication whatever for its protraction over ten years and the inordinate amount of trouble and presumably expense to wnicn Mulki Chand has been subjected, /e shall be very grateful for anything you can do to obtain a reasonable settlement of the case as soon as possible. 4. he have also addressed you officially. Tours sincerely, dd/- H.A.F. Metcalfe. dir Horace Seymour, KCMGr., CV0., His Majesty’s Cnvoy Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary at the Court of Iran, TEHRAN. ister( 616/6/3.9 ) 7404 { 1939 ] T ehran. 1st September 1959. Dear Will you please refer to Sir A. Metcalfe’s letter No.F.276-N/39 of the 3rd July and your official despatch of the same number and date regarding the case of Mulki Ghand Sahny. I asked Squire at Meshed for details of Mulki Ghand 1 s latest appeal, and now learn from him th$t the Tamiz Court in Tehran has heard the f inal appeal and has three months' simple imprisonment, confiscation of the gold coins and return of the car to Mulki Ghand. /hile I fully aumpathise with your desire to avoid awkward questions in the Legislative Assembly, I feel that in the circumstances the final sentence is not unfair, and I do not think there are any grounds on which we could % reasonably press the Iranian (Government to have it modified. Moreover, I am quite sure that even if we had good grounds for further intervention, it would not be successful. Ao regards the points Ol detail raised in paragraoh 3 of dir A. Metcalfe's letter, I ought perhaps to point out that while the gold may have been seized some 500 miles from Gahidan, it was only about 90 miles from the Soviet and about 100 miles from the Afghan frontier, which serves to strengthen the case against Halki Ghand. confirmed the lower court's order, which Yours sincerely, Sd/- H. Seymour. 0.K.Caro internal Affairs Department, Government of India.Copy (E 6451/2083/34). ( 157/10/39 ) BRITISH LEGATION, l ISc59 TEHRAN. 25th August 1939. Dear Department, Will you please refer to our despatch No.62 of the 27th February, which dealt with our correspondence with the Ministry of Foreign Affairs regarding an incident in March 1933 in which a ous hired by Meshed Consulate-General was involved. 2. The Oriental Secretary discussed this case recently with Monsieur Intizam, who had had a reply from the Ministry of War. The Ministry maintained that the driver of the Consulate- General’s bus was to blame for the accident, and that he had been reported to the authorities and dealt with. They did not, however, say anything aoout the behaviour of the Sarwan, or his arbitrary commandeering of the bus, which were the main points of our complaint. Monsieur Intizam, when Finch pointed this out, said he thought we should get no further with the Ministry of War. matter any further, we have made our protest, and we should certainly get no change out of the Ministry of War. 3. In the circumstances we do not propose to pursue this Yours ever. CHANCERY. Eastern Department, FOREIGN OFFICE.COPY (E 3405/826/34) (203/4/39) BRITISH LEGATION TEHRAN. 29th April, 1939 Dear Baggallay, Will you kindly refer to our despatch No. 280 of the 5th August last, and previous correspondence, notsbly your telegram No. 48 of the 9th June, 1938, about the provision of exchange to deported Berber is? arrangements made in the case of the Berberis to cover all Indians who would be glad to leave Iran if they could get their capital out, (The suggestion actually originated with Pakrevan the Governor-General of Khorassan, and was endorsed by Squire, who asked how much sterling would be available at the official rate if such a scheme were introduced). position as we see it f and of a letter from Hay, written after Squire had discussed the question in Delhi, agreeing with our proposals. You will notice that we think the scheme, if introduced at all, would have to be limited to those Indians who are compelled to leave Iran through no fault of their own; i.e. either by order of the Iranian authorities, or by the force of specially hard circumstances. As such we think it would serve a very useful purpose. Owing to the limited amount of exchange available, however, it would be impossible to offer rupees to all those Indians who would like to leave. There has been no more talk here of a ’diplomatic* rate, and the prospects of one being introduced now seem remote. Would you kindly let us have your views? If you favour the scheme in principle we will again sound the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. Squire recently suggested an extension of the I enclose copies of my letter to Squire explaining the Yours sincerely, (Signed) Nevile Butler, H. L. Baggallay, Esq,COPY ' f ) - y ry l CONFIDENTIAL . &gt; ^ v ., t / \j External Affairs Department, D.Q. No .D.923-N/39 .■ ! NEW DELHI, ' The 25th March, 1939. Dear Butler, Please refer to your secret demi-official letter No. 203/2/39 of the 7th February, 1939 to Squire. I am desired to say that we have discussed with Squire his proposal that he should be permitted to take over Rials from British Indian Subjects, who are either expelled from Iran for no fault of their own or driven out by force of circumstances, at a rate profitable to both parties, and consider it a good one. We should be grateful therefore if you would kindly refer it to the Foreign Office and if they agree, discuss it with the Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs as suggested at the end of your letter. We should be glad to know the result in due course. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) Hay. To N. M. Butler, Esquire, C.V.O., His Britannic Majesty’s Chargd d'Affaires, British Legation, Tehran.(203/2/39) 7th February, 1939 $ Dear Squire, You will remember that in a postscript to a recent letter to me you mentioned the case of those British Indians who would be glad to leave the country if they could get their capital out, and discussed pakrevan's suggestion that we should supply the exchange. question of exchange for the Berberis last summer, whether he personally thought his Government would raise objection to or dislike an extension of that arrangement to cover further cases of persons obliged to leave Iran. He thought that there would probably be no objection, but that it would be hardly possible to give us anything in writing. I explained that my enquiry was entirely private, as there were considerable difficulties from our own point of view, even if we felt assured that the Iranian authorities would neither raise ncrfeel any objection. The main difficulties from our point of view seem to be: (1) The limited amount of exchange available, and the consequent necessity to restrict our distributions and discriminate between cases on their merits. (2) The possible desirability of continuing to sell some exchange at the official rate. (3) The possibility that a special 'diplomatic* rate may be introduced, which would be applicable to all exchange sold by the Legation. As regards (l), in 1938 the Legation sold £9,000 to the Iranian Government at the official rate on behalf of the Government of India. This was only half of the amount sold during each of the twc previous years, part of this difference I asked Intizam, with whom I had dealings in the being/ G. F. Squire, Esq., I.C.S’ .gp^ being doubtless due to the Berberis* money which was taken over at Meshed during 1938. £9,000 therefore seems to be a minimum estimate of the amount of foreign currency available. On the other hand there would obviously not be sufficient exchange available for all Indian traders who might wish to take advantage of it, and it might therefore be necessary to restrict the facility to those traders who are compelled by the Iranian Government to leave Iran through no serious fault of their own. However, under any such scheme, then, it seems clear that we should have to rely upon your advice in the first instance, especially as regards the selection of the most urgent and deserving cases. (2) above refers to the good-will of the Exchange Control Commission which sales of exchange at the official rate may help us to retain. But as there is considerable doubt on this point, it need not weigh very heavily on any decision that may be taken on the general question. As regards (3), the question of a diplomatic * rate was mooted some weeks ago, but it now seems likely that nothing will come of it. It is however a possibility which will have to be borne in mind, as it might be introduced at short notice, thereby seriously reducing the financial benefit to Indians who obtain exchange through the Government of India. We for our part are prepared to see other Indians helped in the same way as the Berberis. If you think that the sum available for disposal justifies the trouble, you would perhaps think it worth while discussing the question with the External Affairs Department when you are in Delhi in March. If the Department are in favour of the scheme we would refer it to the Foreign Office. If the latter approve, we should also, I think, have to tell the Ministry of Foreign Affairs what we propose to do and seek their oral or at least tacit acquiescence. (Signed) N.M.Butler.ei) (,- 34 )8/ei.6/«i) KHkiOi'i Ji-vic e.w.i isSrd May, 193 j. ■7 Vi j 1 1959 j la reply to y^ur letter ft j • is&gt;»S/ 4 / 3 d of the i. 9 th April, I write to let y &gt;u :&lt;aow that the foreign ffice have no objection to the sropOMl to extena the arrangements aade for the provl^i j« of exchange to deu rtc - oerberie to cover those Indiana who are c aoellt i to leave erbia through no fault of their .wu; i-e. by order of the Persian authorities or by the force of specially hard eircuaatances. te agree that the extension eiiouldl be Halted to Indians in this category# rather than aaie to cover all indians who would be glad to leave ersia if they could get their ca dtal out of the country* 2. or agreement with the proposal ia nadc \-n the understanding that it would ap ly only to drawings on the Covernaent of India and not in any way to those on the foreign/ • dutler $ . sq* , o • v * ^ Tehran.Please refer to your demi-official letter LioJP.Z.1779/ 39, dated the 5th April 1939# I forward herewith a copy of a notification by the Grovernment of India in the Home Department, No^Sl/lS/oo, dated the 29th March 1938, from which it will be seen that a delegation was made entrusting the functions of the Central Government under sections 3,3A and 4 of the Foreigners Act, 1864, (III of 1864), to Provincial Governments, with their consent. c R.T. Peel, Esquire, M.C., India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.l. (With 2 spare copies).Government of India, Home Department(Political) The 29th March 1938. NOTIFICATION . No.51/12/36. In mxkjrx exercise of the powers conferred by sub-section (1) of section 124 of the Government of India Act, 1935, the Cential Government is pleased, with effect yrtk from the 1st April 1938 to entrust to Provincial Governments, with their consent, the functions of the Central Government under section 3, 3A and 4 of the Foreigners Act, 1864 ( III of 1864), sections 16, 17 , 27 , 34 and 36 of the European Vagrancy Act 1874 (IX of 1874), section 7 of the Explosive Substances Act, 1908 (VI of 1908), section 5 of the Indian Passport Act, 1920 (XXXIV of 1920) and rule 2 of the Indian Passport Rules, 1921. SdA J.A.Thorne, Secretary to the Government of IndiaNo. 62. (167/6/39) Copy to India &amp;&gt;• ad Maahad to* 16 ■^rv«r: u 2$tBi£$uar y, 1939. 1939 l .. My Lord, t flth reference to Your Lordship 1 s despatch rio. 305 of the 22nd September last, (&amp; 5452/461/34), I have the honour to transmit herewith a copy of a further memorandum which I have received from the Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs regarding the incident in which a bus hired by His Majesty's Consul-General for Khorasaan was involved on the 1st March last* 2* Ag is to be expected in oases where the Ministry of War is Involved, this reply is unsatisfactory for a variety of reasons* Not hopeful, therefore, of obtaining a more satisfactory reply, but not wishing to give the Iranian Government the impression that I accept their version of the incident, I have drawn the attention of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs to certain aspects of the case in a further note, a copy of which is enclosed herein* I will not fall to keep Your Lordship informed of any subsequent developments there may be in this matter. A copy of this despatch is being sent to the Secretary to the Government of India in the rocternal Affaire department and to His Majesty's Consul-General for Khorassan at Meshed. I have the honour to be with the highest respect, My Lord, Your Lordship's moat obedient, humble Servant, (Cgd) H.J. Seymour The Mght Honourable The Viscount Halifax#ENCLOSURE NO. 1 IN TEHRAN DESPATCH No Proms No* I.M.P.A. (3rd pol. 51957/4486. 62. '1-988 Dept). To: H.B. t. Legation, tehran * q g Date: 29th Jdmiarypl^g^; The M.P.A. of the Imperial Covt. presents its compliments to H.B.M. Legation, and 9 in reply to the latter's memorandum No. 21 of the 1st Bahman 1317 (21st January, 1939) concerning the collision of the motor bus which was hired by the British Consul- General with that of Sarvan Vossough Zadeh, has the honour to inform the Legation that, according to information received from the competent quarters, the local Amnieh post has reported that the lorry of Partab Singh Hindi, which was carrying some articles and members of staff of the Consulate, collided with the lorry of one Mohammad Hindi, which was carrying Govt, ammunition under superintendence of Sarvan Vossough Zadeh and a number of soldiers, oecause of failure to blow his horn. i’he driver Mohammad had driven his lorry to the right hand side of the road in such a way that the right wheel of the machine passed up the bank, and Partab, who occupied the middle part of the road, struck Mohammad' lorry with the left side of his vehicle, with the result that the mudguard and other parts of Mohammad's lorry were smashed, and the wife of Ustovar Khusrovi, who was travelling in Sarvan Vossugh Zadeh’s machine, was injured by the breaking of the glass. Sarvan Vossugh zadeh protested to Partab, and stated that since his machine was smashed the latter must take the ammunition to Birjand, and forced the driver to return to Sedeh. As Mohammad's lorry was damaged, Saravn x Vossugh Zadeh forced the driver Partab to carry half of the ammunition to Birjand. On arriving at the latter place, he referred to the '‘mnieh post in order to prosecute the driver. But as the driver was obliged to take the members £ the Consulate to Meshed, the Consulate was told to get the driver to report himself at the Amnieh post, and in the meantime to name a guarantor in order that his file might be examined upon his return. The man, on his return, was handed over with the file to the Primary Court of the place. As regards the detention of the driver of the lorry and placing of a guard, it is stated that the driver was not detained, and as the lorry grrived at Birjand at 10 o'clock in the evening with half of the overnment ammunition in it, it was to protect these latter that a guard was placed upon it. (Sealed) M.P.A.— (g) ehi an &lt;iea pt-tch Ko_ d&amp;to 4 7 f 27th -euruarx to. m euruhrau 198S I939 iii» Majesty’s Legation present their eoapl i»enta to the Imperial I iniatry ol* foreign Ai. airs and have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of their meiaoranduia 0.61957/ 4466 of the 29th January*(9th Bahman# 1317) regarding the incident in whieh a hue hired hy Hie gaiety* a Consul- General for Ihoraaaan wae involTed on the let Larch* 1930 (10th &gt;sfand*1316). 2 . rhe imperial ; inietry of Foreign Affairs will appreciate that the version of the accident given in the memorandum under reference ia at variance with the account given hy those who were travelling in the hue hired hy His fcsweety’s Consul General and with the view of the Annieh officii who inspected the scene of the accident and reported that in his judgement hot* drivers were to blame. 3. However this may he* His Majesty’s Legation pointed out in theii notes Ho a. 109 and 380 of the 19 th March* 1936 (20th Lsfand* 1316) and 5th August* 1938 (14th frordad,1817)* respectively* that whatever may ha tha correct apportionment of responsihllit; /for tha1988T L 1939 1 ^ ■ ^ tor the accident^ the conduct of Sarwan Vo&amp;suq Zadeh on this occasion could not he justified# It is therefore with dlaappointaent that they observe that the aenoranduis under reference contains no expression of regret for the Oarwan’s conduct# nor indeed any reply to the eoaplaints which His Majesty’s legation felt bound to aake regarding his treatment of the occupants and the driver of the bus hired by His Majesty's Consul general and of the archives and effects of the Consulate-General# His Majesty^ Legation are unwilling to believe that his conduct has the approval of the Iranian authorities# Bar wan Vossuq £.adeh clsgrMy felt that his own conduct was unsuitable seeing that he attempted to secure from the members of the staff of His Majesty's Consulate-General a written statement that they had no complaint against him of any sort. 4. Although the version in the $ inlstry of foreign Affairs' memorandum under reference and that furnished to His fajesty's Legation by the Consulate- General differ in so many particulars# it is agreed on both sides that oarwan Vossuq Zadeh did in fact comaiendeer the bus hired by the Consul General# with ita driver to return to Sedeh# and then /to carryto carry a load of amaunition to Blrjjmd. It la presumably not contended by the Iranian oovemiBent that Iranian lae or regulations entitled the Sarwan first to constitute himself sole arbiter as to responsibility for the accident» and then to commandeer the bus without payment. His r ajesty’s Legation venture therefore to draw attention again to their request for the payment of Xtials 600, which was their careful and moderate assessment of the amount due to tne driver of the lorry for the services that he was compelled to render for the f arwan. 5* In the above circumstances His Majesty's Legation would be grateful if the Imperial Ministry of Foreign Affairs would cause further consideration to be given to this unfortunate incident.*3 k.® r\9^1779 kew Delhi, D..._ o.F.ol2-:y3^ 0 OT « / ' g, U? - areh &amp; . ^ rtati Iranian subjects to Iran. C£ V* XJ CL-&lt; please refer to your demi-official letter No.P.2. 660/39, February the 24th. 2. The Iranian gypsies concerned were not expelled in retaliation for the expulsion of British Indian subjects from Iran, but were deported under the order of the Punjab G-ovemment(who were probably entirely unaware oi the Berber! case) largely as a result of a riot which took place in the Hultan District in June 1938. During the course of the investigation in to this riot it was found that the gypsies had been responsible for numerous petty thefts, that live oi them were previous convicts, and that a large number ol them had either no passports at all or invalid ones. Deportation orders were passed ag&amp;inst 29 persons only but the band of gypsies concerned numbered about 60 parsons and it is possible that the remaining members of it accompanied 'die deportees to Iran. 3 . Xt will be seen from the above that these deportations 1 ere not in any way retaliatory and were therefore not in consistent with the policy indicated in paragraph 8 of our Express Letter to Meshed of 21st October 1938, No . F .238-N/38. As, however, their effect has been so salutary, we shall [rEOo.POI-.DEPt.~I nave 21MAR1939 INDIA OFFICER.T.Peel, Esquire, L r .C., India Office, Httiitehall, London.3.W.l. - 2 - have to consider whether we should not dejpart jcfrfe thgjt policy- if an occasion arises in future. / b —ACT NO. Ill OF 1864.' {In reprinting this Act Arabic numerals have been substituted throughout for the Roman numerals used in the Act as originally passed.) [12th February 1S64.~\ An Act to give the Government certain powers with respect to Foreigners. fAs modified up to 1st April 1915.] W HEREAS it is expedient to make provision to Preamble, enable the Government to prevent the subjects of 1 1 Short title, “ the Foreigners Act, 1864.” See the Indian Short Titles Act, 1897 (14 of 1897), Genl. Acts, Vol. IV. For special direction from Parliament to pass this Act, s- 84 of the Government of India Act, 1833 (3 &amp; 4 Will. IV, c. 85), Coll. Stats., Ind., Vol. I. For the Statement of Objects and Reasons of the Bill which became Act 3 of 1864, see Calcutta Gazette, 1863 p. 2163; for Proceedings reiating to the Bill, see ibid, Supplement, p. 581, and Gazette of India, 1864, Supplement, p. 41. „ The Act has been declared to be in force in the whole of BrUish India, except as regards the Scheduled Districts, by the Laws Local Extent Act, 1874 (15 of 1874), s. 3, Genl. Acts, Vol. II. It has been declared in force in— Upper Burma generally (except the Shan States) by the Burma Laws Act, 1898 (13 of 1898), s. 4 (/) and Sch I, Bur. Code; but its application to Chins in the Chin Hills has been barred by the Chm Hills Regulation, 1896 (5 of 1896), Bur. Code, and to hill- tribes in a hill-tract to which the Regulation applies by the Kachin Hill Tribes Regulation, 1895 (1 of 1895), Bur. Code; the Santh&amp;l Parganas by the Santhal Parganas Settlement Regula tion (3 of 1872), s. 3, as amended by the Santhal Parganas Justice the'Arakan 8 HUl’mttHct by the Arakan Hill District Laws Regula- B&amp;^^^’B^&amp;chistan Laws Regulation, 1913 (2 of 1913), s. 3, Bal. Code; Angul District by the Angul Laws Regulation, 1913 (3 of 1913), s. 3. It has been declared, by notification under s. 3 (a) of the Scheduled DistHcta lcL ?874 (14 of IsV Genl. Acts, Vol. II, to be in force in the following Scheduled Districts, namely . . QO See Gazette of India, 1878, Pt. I, p. 482. [Price annas three and six pies.']F orcigncrs. [act III .foreign States from residing or sojourning in British India, or from passing through or travelling therein, Aden West Jalpaiguri, the Western Duars, the Western Hills of Darjil ing, the Darjiling Tarai, and the Damson Sub-divi sion of the Dn. jiling District . . . . The Districts of Hazaribagh, Lohardaga (now the Ranchi District, see Cal cutta Gazette, 1899, Pt. I, p. 44) and Manbhum, and Pargana Dhalbhum and the Kolhan in the District of Singbhum The, Porahat Estate in the Singbhum District . The Scheduled portion of the Mirzapur District Jaunsar Bawar The Districts of Hazara, Peshawar, Kohat, Bannu, Dera Ismail Khan and Dera Ghazi Khan (Por tions of the Districts of Hazara, Bannu, Dera Ismail Khan and Dera Ghazi Khan and the Dis tricts of Peshawar and Kohat now form the North-West Frontier Pro vince, see Gazette of India, 1901, Pt. I, p. 857, and ibid, 1902, Pt. I, V- 575; but its applica tion in that part of the Hazara District known as Upper Tanawal has been barred by the Hazara (Upper Tanawal) Regula tion, 1900 (2 of 1900), Punjab and N.-W. Code) The District of Lahaul The Scheduled Districts of the Central Provinces The Scheduled Districts in Ganjam and Vizagapatam. The District of Sylhet . See Gazette of India, 1879, Pt. I, p. 434 ditto, 1881, Pt. I, p. 74. ditto, 1881, Pt. I, p. 504. ditto, 1897, Pt. I, p. 1059. ditto, 1879, Pt. I, p. 383. ditto, 1879, Pt. I, p. 382. ditto, 1886, Pt. I, p. 48. ditto, 1886, Pt. I, p. 301. ditto, 1879, Pt. I, p. 771. ditto, 1898, Pt. I, p. 870. ditto, 1879, Pt. I, p. 631. The rest of Assam (except the North Lushai Hills) . ditto, 1897, Pt. I, p. 299. It has been extended, by notification under s. 5 of the last-mentioned Act, to the following Scheduled Districts, namely :— Kumaon and Garhwal . . See Gazette of India, 1876, Pt. I, n. 606 I he 1 arai of the Province r of A s ra • ■ • • ditto, 1876, Pt. I, p. 505,boreigners. therein, without the consent of the Government; It is enacted as follows :— 1. 'Ihe following words and expressions in this interpreta- Act shall have the meanings hereby assigned to them, tlon * unless there be something in the subject or context repugnant to such construction, that is to say :— The words “‘British India” shall denote the “ British territories which are or may become vested in Her India ” Majesty by the 2 Statute 21 and 22 Victoria, Chap. 106, entitled “ An Act for the better Government of India ”: the words “Local Government” shall denote the “Local person authorised to administer the executive government in any part of British India, or the chief executive ohicer of any part of British India under the immediate administration of the Governor General of India in Council, when such chief execu tive oilicer shall, by an 1 order of the Governor General of India in Council published in the Gazette of India, be authorized to exercise the powers vested by this Act in a Local Government: the word “ foreigner ” shall denote a person :— “Foreigner.” '[(a) who is not a natural born British subject as defined in sub-sections (2) and (2) of section 1 of the British Nationality and Status of Aliens Act, 1914, or 4andr&gt;Gco. (6) who has not been granted a certificate of v ’ c * 17, naturalisation as a British subject under any law for the time being in force in British India : Provided that any British subject who, under any law for the time being in force in British India, ceases to be a British subject, shall thereupon be deemed to be a foreigner.] the 1 Cf. definition of “ British India ” in the Interpretation Act (52 &amp; 53 Viet., c. 63), s. 18, and the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), s. 3 (7), Genl. Acts, Vol. IV. 2 See the Government of India Act, 1858 (21 &amp; 22 Viet., c. 106), Coll. Stats., Ind., Vol. I. 3 For order authorizing the Chief Commissioner of Ajmer-Merwara to exercise the powers vested in a Local Government under the Act, see Gazette of India, 1876, Ft. I, p. 346. 4 These words were substituted for the words “ not being either a natural-born subject of Her Majesty within the meaning of the Statute 3 &amp; 4 William IV, Chap. 85, section 81, or a Native of British India ” by s. 2 of the Foreigners (Amendment) Act, 1915 (3 of 1915). If** Magistrate of the district.” V of 1898. “ Vessel.” Proof of being a foreigner. Government Foreigners. . [act hi the words “ the Magistrate of the district ” shall denote the chief officer charged with the executive administration of a district and exercising the powers of a Magistrate, by whatever designation the chief officer charged with the executive administra tion is styled, or, in the absence of such officer from the station at which his Court is usually held, the senior officer at the station exercising the powers of a Magistrate as defined in the 1 Code of Criminal Procedure : the word “ vessel ” shall include anything made for the conveyance by water of human beings or property : 1 2 Number.] Rey. by Act X of 1914. Gender.] Rep. by Act X of 1914. 2. If a question shall arise whether any person alleged to be a foreigner and to be subject to the provisions of this Act is a foreigner or not, or is or is not subject to the provisions of this Act, the onus of proving that such person is not a foreigner, or is not subject to the provisions of this Act, shall lie upon such person. 3. The Governor General of India in Council may order llla y Py writing, order any foreigner to remove him- an v foreigner •/ ? t/ # # o 7 # %/ o # -ir»i to remove self from British India, or to remove himself there- himseif. from by a particular route to be specified in the order; and any Local Government may, by writing, make the like order with reference to any foreigner, within the jurisdiction of such Government. Foreigner 3 * * [3A. (l) Whenever in a Presidency town the apprehended Commissioner of Police or elsewhere the Magistrate and detained of the District, considers that the Local Government ^ 0 ™?' ? ll0uld be m0Ved 10 issue an order under section 3 in respect of any foreigner who is within the limits of such Presidency town or of the jurisdiction of such Magistrate, he may report the case to the Local Government and at the same time issue a warrant for the apprehension of such foreigner. {2) Any 1 Genl. Acts, Vol. V. 2 Cf. definition in s. 3 (56‘) of the General Clauses Act, 1897, Genl. Acts, Vol. IV. 2 Section 3A was inserted by the Foreigners (Amendment) Act, 1915 (3 of 1915).1864.J Foreigners. (2) Any officer issuing a warrant under sub section (Z) may, in his discretion, direct by endorse ment on the warrant that if such foreigner executes ^ a bond with or without sureties for his attendance at a specified place and time, the person to whom the warrant is directed shall take such security and release such foreigner from custody. (3) Any person executing a warrant under sub section (1) may search for and apprehend the foreigner named in such warrant; and, subject to any direction issued under sub-section (2), shall forthwith cause such foreigner when apprehended to be produced before the officer issuing the warrant. (4) When a foreigner for whose apprehension a warrant has been issued under sub-section (1) is produced or appears before the officers issuing such warrant, such officer may direct him to be detained in custody pending the orders of the Local Govern ment, or may release him on his executing a bond with or without sureties to appear at a specified place and time and thereafter if and when required until such orders are obtained. (5) Any officer who has in accordance with the provisions of sub-section (4), ordered a foreigner to be detained or released on his executing a bond shall forthwith report the fact to the Local Govern ment. On the receipt of a report under this sub section the Local Government shall without delay . either direct that the foreigner be discharged or make an order for the removal of such foreigner in accordance with the provisions of section 3.] 4. If any foreigner ordered to remove himself Foreigner from British India, or ordered to remove himself refus ' lg 10 therefrom by a particular route, shall neglect or returning refuse so to do, or if any foreigner, having removed [[^nsetfter himself from British India in consequence of an removal, order issued under any of the provisions of this ma y Act, or having been removed from British India amuiotainJd. under any of the said provisions, shall wilfully return thereto without a license in writing granted by the Governor General of India in Council or by the 5Foreigners. [act m Governor General may order all the provisions of this Act to be in force in British India, or in any part thereof. Proviso. Every foreigner to report his arrival in India in certain cases. the Local Government under whose order he shall have removed himself or been removed, such foreign er many be apprehended and detained in safe custody, until he shall be discharged therefrom by order of the Governor General of India in Council, or of the Local Government within whose jurisdic tion he shall be so apprehended or detained, upon such terms and conditions as the said Governor General of India in Council or Local Government shall deem sufficient for the peace and security of British India, and of the allies of Her Majesty, and of the neighbouring Princes and States. 5. Whenever the Governor General of India in Council shall consider it necessary to take further precautions in respect of foreigners residing or travelling in British India or any part thereof, it shall be lawful for the Governor General of India in Council, by a 1 notification published in the Gazette of India, to order that the provisions of this and the subsequent sections of this Act shall be in force in British India, or in such part thereof as shall be specified in such notification, for such period as shall be therein declared; and thereupon, and for such period, the whole of this Act including this and the subsequent sections shall have full force and effect in British India or such part thereof as shall have been so specified. The Governor General of India in Council may, from time to time, by a noti fication published as aforesaid, cancel or alter any former notification which may still be in force, or may extend the period declared therein : Provided that none of the provisions of this or the subsequent sections of this Act shall extend to any foreign minister duly accredited by his Government; to any consul or vice-consul; to any person under the age of fourteen years; or to any person in the service of Her Majesty. 6 . Every foreigner on arriving in any part of British India in which all the provisions of this Act are 1 The provisions of s. 5 and the subsequent sections which were brought into force for a period of six months in the whole of British India pee Gazette of India, 1914, Pt. I, p. 1329), shall remain in force during the continuance of the present war, see Gazette of India, 1915, Pt. I, p. ^29. G7 • 804. J p oreigners. are for the time being in force under an order issued as provided in the last preceding section, from any port or place not within British India, or from any port or place within British India where all the pro visions of this Act are not in force, shall if he arrived nt a presidency-town, forthwith report himself to the Commissioner of Police of such town, or, if he arrive at anv other place, then he shall forthwith report himself to the Magistrate of the district, or to such other officer as shall be appointed to receive such reports, bv the Governor General of India in Council or by the Local Government of such place. 7. The report shall be in writing, and shall be Wh attobb signed by the person reporting himself, and shall ^ in the specify his name or names, the nation to which he belongs, the place from which he shall have come, the place or places of his destination, the object of his pursuit, and the d&amp;te of his arrival in such pre sidency-town or other place. The report shall be recorded by the officer to whom it is made. 8. The provisions of the last two preceding sec- Foreigners, tions shall not extend to any person being master ^g r s of or commander of a vessel or employed therein, but i f vessels or any such person shall be in any part of British India theSiTto in which all the provisions of this Act are for the report'’ time being in force, after he shall have ceased to be actually employed in a vessel, he shall forthwith cease to i&gt;o report himself in manner aforesaid. so em pi &gt;\ed. 9. If any foreigner shall neglect to report him- Foreig era self as required by this Act, he may be dealt with in ^ g r 1 e ect ^ g the manner hereinafter provided in respect of for- tLSves, eigners travelling without a license. “ay be dealt ° ° with in like manner as foreigners travelling without a license. 10. No foreigner shall travel in or pass through No foreigner any part of British India in which all the provisions indiT™ m of this Act are for the time being in force without a yithouta license. license. 11 11. Licenses under this Act may be granted by L ! cens ® b f the Governor General of India in Council or by any granted? ofForeigners. fACT ill 8 What to be stated in license. License may be granted subject to conditions and may bo revoked. Foreigner travelling without or contrary to the condi tions of license may be apprehended. Procedure upon appre hension. of the Local Governments, under the signature of a Secretary to the Government of India or to such Local Government, as the case may be, or by such other officers as shall be speciallv authorized to grant licenses by the Governor General of India in Council, or by any of the Local Governments. 12. Every such license shall state the name of the person to whom the license is granted, the nation to which he belongs, the district or districts through which he is authorized to pass or the limits within which he is authorized to travel, and the period (if anv) during which the license is intended to have effect. 13. The license may be granted subject to such conditions as the Governor General of India in Council or the Local Government may direct, or as the officer granting the licensfe may deem necessary. Any license may be revoked at any time by the Governor General of India in Council, or by the Local Government of any part of British India in which all the provisions of this Act are for the tune being in force and in which the foreigner holding the same may be, or by the officer who granted the license. 14. If any foreigner travel in or attempt to pass through any part of British India without such license as aforesaid, or beyond the districts or limits mentioned therein, or after such license shall have been revoked, or shall violate any of the conditionr&gt; therein specified, he may be apprehended without warrant by any officer exercising any of the powers of a Magistrate, or by any European commissioned officer in the service of Her Majesty, or by any member of a volunteer corps enrolled by authority of Government whilst on duty, or by any police-officer. 15. If any person be apprehended by a person not exercising any of the powers of a Magistrate and not being a police-officer, he shall be delivered oyer as soon as possible to a police-officer, and forthwith carried before the Magistrate of the district. Whenever any person shall be apprehended by or taken before the Magistrate of the district, such Magistrateummmmmm 9 1864.] Foreigners. Magistrate shall immediately report the case to the Magistrate Local Government to which he is subordinate, and ow^nment. shall cause the person brought before him to be discharged, or to be conveyed to one of the presi dency-towns, or pending the orders of such Govern ment to be detained. 16. Any person apprehended or detained under Persons the provisions of this Act may be admitted to bail ^] ) a p v re ^f nde&lt;l by the Magistrate of the district, or by any officer admitted to authorized to grant licenses, and shall be put to as bai1 * little inconvenience as possible during his detention in custody. 17. The Local Government of any part of British Removal of India in which all the provisions of this Act are for appScnded. the time being in force may order any person appre hended or detained under the provisions of this Act to remove himself from any such part of British India, by sea or by such other route as the said Local Government may direct; or the said Local Govern ment may cause him to be removed from such part of British India by such route and in such manner as to such Local Government shall seem fit. The Governor General of India in Council may exercise all the powers given by this section to any Local Government. 18. The Governor General of India in Council may by order prohibit any person or any class of persons not being natural-born subjects of Her Majesty within the meaning of the 1 Statute 3 and 4 William IV, Chap. 85, section 81, from travelling in or passing through any part of British India in which all the provisions of this Act may, for the time being, be in force, and from passing from any part thereof to another without a license to be grant ed by such officer or officers as shall be specified in the order : and, if any person so prohibited shall wil fully disobey such order, he may be apprehended without warrant by any of the officers specified in section 14 of this Act, and carried before the Magis trate of the district, and dealt with under the pro visions Governor General may prohibit persons not being natural-born subjects from travelling or passing through any part of India without a license. 1 See the Government of India Aet, 1833 (3 &amp; 4 Will. ^ , c. 85), Coll. Stats., Ind., Vol. I.Foreigners. [act hi visions of section 17 in the same manner as if he were a foreigner : and the Governor General of India in Council may order such person to be detained in safe custody or under the surveillance of the police so long as it may be deemed necessary for the peace and security of British India or any part thereof. Also the 19. The Local Government of any presidency or Local Gov- p i ace j n w hich all the provisions of this Act may, within their for the time being, be in force, may by order prohi- respectiye an y p ers0 ii or any class of persons not being jun ic ions. natlira i_hoTn subjects of Her Majesty within the meaning of the 1 Statute 3 and 4 William IV, Chap. 85, section 81, from travelling in or passing through such presidency or place or any part thereof, and from passing from any part thereof to another, with out a license to be granted by such officer or officers as shall be specified in the order; and, if any person so prohibited shall wilfully disobey such order, he may be apprehended without warrant by any of the officers specified in section 14 of this Act, and car ried before the Magistrate of the district, and dealt with under the provisions of section 17 in the same manner as if he were a foreigner; and the Local Government may order such person to be detained in safe custody or under the surveillance of the police so long as it may be deemed necessary for the peace and security of British India or any part thereof. officers a 20. It shall be lawful for the Commissioner of bear'd Vessel s Police, or for the Magistrate of the district, or for w°hethe? ain an y 0 ® cer appointed to receive reports as mentioned foreigners are in the sixth section of this Act, or for any police- on board, officer under the authority of such Commissioner or Magistrate, to enter any vessel in any port or place within British India in wdiich all the provisions of this Act may, for the time being, be in force, in order to ascertain whether any foreigner bound to report his arrival under the said section 6 of this Act is on board of such vessel; and it shall be lawful for such Commissioner of Police, Magistrate or other officer as aforesaid to adopt such means as may be reason ably 1 See the Government of India Act, 1833 (3 &amp; 4 Will. IV, c. 85), Coll. Stats., Ind., Vol. I.1864.] Foreigners. l ;u ably necessary for that purpose; and the master or Master of commander of such vessels shall also, before any of o! the passengers are allowed to disembark, if he shall passengers, be required so to do by such Commissioner of Police, 4ft Magistrate, or other officer as aforesaid, deliver to respecting him a list in writing of the passengers on board, them - specifying the ports or places at which they embark ed, and the ports or places of their disembarkation, or intended disembarkation, and answer to the best of his knowledge all such questions touching the pas- ' sengers on board the said vessel, or touching those who may have disembarked in any part of British India, as shall be put to him by the Commissioner of Police, Magistrate, or other officer as aforesaid. If any foreigner on board such vessel in any part of Foreigner British India shall refuse to give an account of his ^ 8 ^ 0 ^ nt objects of pursuit in India, or if his account thereof KSf, shall not be satisfactory, the officer may refuse to not to be allow him to disembark, or he may be dealt with in di^mblrk. the same manner as a foreigner travelling in British India without a license. 21. If the master or commander of a vessel shall Penalty for wilfully give a false answer to any question which by section 20 of this Act he is bound to answer, or shall make any false report, he shall be held to have committed the offence specified in section 177 of the klv of i 860 . 1 Indian Penal Code. 22. If the master or commander of any vessel penalty for shall wilfully neglect or refuse to comply with the by requisitions of this Act, he shall, on conviction be- vessel to fore the Magistrate of the district or a Justice of the Peace, be liable to a fine not exceeding two thousand ofXt. 1008 rupees. 23. Whoever intentionally obstructs any officer Penalty for in the exercise of any of the powers vested in him ^™ ting by this Act shall be held to have committed the ° offence specified in section 186 of the 1 Indian Penal klv 0 f i 860 . Code. 24. \Fines imposed under this Act how to be re covered.'] Rep. by Act X of 1914- 25. The 1 Genl. Acts, Vol. I. 11Foreigners. [act m, 1864.] Persons may 25. The Governor General of India in Council, from p™o Pted or the Local Government of any part of British visions of India in which this Act may, for the time being, be tins Act. j n f orcej ma y i exempt any person, or any class of persons, either wholly or partially, or temporarily or otherwise, from all or any of the provisions of this Act contained in any of the sections subsequent to section 5, and may at any time revoke any such exemption. 1 1 For exemption under this section, see Gazette of India, 1914, Pt. I, pp. 1329 nnd 1905. 12 CALCUTTA : PRINTED BY SUPDT. GOVT. PRINTING, INDIA, 8, HASTINGS STREET.EXTRACT from Baluchistan Weekly Intelligence Summary No.11 dated 17th March, 1939. 36. During the past three months Hazaras of Eastern Iran have 'been left in comparative peace. A fresh campaign against them appears, however, to have been started, as numbers in Meshed and Zahidan are again being closely examined, and lists of persons for deportation are being -repared.Extract from Baluchistan Weekly Summary No.8 dated 24th February, 1939. 48. A Sikh motor driver of Zahidan, who recently refused to lend his car to an Amnia officer for a trip to Zabul, was badly beaten by Road Guards when passing by the Amnia post to which the officer is attached. The matter was reported at the British Consulate, and Sikhs are said to have sent telegrams to Tehran asking for suitable action to be taken against the officer concerned.SECRET. P.Z.1095/39. BALUCHISTaR Extract from Weekly Intelligence Summary No.6, dated 10th February, 1939. 37. Saiyid Murtaz a, who was appointed Chief of the Hazaras in and around Meshed by the Iranian Government and given the title, of 'Salar Afkhami', is reported to have been imprisoned in Tehran. It is said that he was found in possession of incriminating documents. 38. The authorities at Zahidan and Meshed have ordered that all letters addressed to or suspected to emanate from Hazaras who have been deported from Iran shall be strictly 6? i censored.P.Z. 1102/39. Extract from Political Diary No. 12 for the month of December, 1938. British Consulate General for Khorasan, Meshed. Confidential . 367. T recently had an interesting interview with M. Pakrevan who was ready, as always, to talk. He spoke of the difficulty of getting foreign exchange and of trading generally. The trade agreement with Russia, he said, was defunct and was not being renewed while in their barter with Germany Iran suffered from the fact that Germany charged 50* more than the proper price for everything exported. Re did not know why the Russian members of the Trade Agency stayed on in Meshed as they had nothing to do. (There are still about 9 families staying in the former Russian Consulate). He told me with pride that the brigands of Dilbaran (para: 309) had now all been caught and that he hoped that they would be hanged at the scene of their last exploit. He also mentioned ruefully the unwelcome present recently made Iran by the Government of India (para: 300) . He did not think it fair that in exchange for a few families of perfectly harmless Berberis the Government of India should have seen fit to unload 65 families of gypsies all of whom were thieves. They had given endless trouble in Meshed and he had novr ordered their removal into the interior of the country.. .660,3 24th Febra^ry* 1939 Pmpa^p«i r 'h 309 of the lesaed olitienl Jt&amp;ry i or otjoor, 1936 re ort« trie arrival of some 69 Iranian gyyeiee fr&lt;»i India who stated to the Ofclef of oliee at ;«hidan ’that they had bean excelled in retaliation for the expulsion of British Indian s^bjeots froe fran**. The sWteoHsnt seeas to hare had a s*iatar^ effect on the ersiaas* bat it dote not s^aare vitn the policy indicated in paragraph 6 of your express letter to Meshed of 21st ctoner* 1936* Mo* F* 236 ~X/ 3§0 and ae e setter of interest ve should like to know what were the foots regarding the expalsion of theae gypsies* (SgdO R. peei ir H* A. Wetcalft * ^ovemttent of India f External Affaire Department*r 2. , 1932. ' f 1 ele^raui K., No, 224 # dated 23rd (reed. 24th) September 1938. From ....... H.M’s Consul-Greneral, Meshed. To ....... . Foreign, Simla. (repeated to Minister, Tehran, No. 37). 1 ^ ^ \\v * N ^ : ***1#) I'jT) 1 (*' f I VUM yC C\fA. /■V&gt;j ■ yt,. My despatch No. 66 of 23rd August to Tehran ( 193 to India). In spite of Minister at Tehran’s protests expulsions c.re being proceeded with. If no retaliatory expulsions are possible could not the Government of Inaia impose or at least threaten immediate Customs duty at Nokkundi on principal imports by this route making it clear that these are purely retaliatory measures. Believe that threat of duty on almonds, carpets and poppy seeds would be immediately effective in stopping further expulsions which otherwise appear inevitable. I have already suggested this in my demi-official No. 124 of 6th June (24 to Tehran). N., F.S., D.S.(F)., J.3. &amp; U.3.(F). M.b.H. t-Ci mV • V.3 u v c 47 Telegram R No. 47 dated 26th September 1938 From Foreign, Simlae To. Minister, Tehrano Reference Meshed telegram No* 37 September 23rd. Expulsion of Berberis* Government of India will be glad of your views on suggestion that retaliatory measures directed against Iranian im ports on Nek Kundi route should be taken* It is not yet certain that such action could in fact be taken but this would be examined if you think that it would, be effective. &lt;X F.S. D.S.F* J.S. U.S.F.) GLB»2011 , M.S.H. telegram XK., No. 77, dated (&amp; reed*) 29th September 1938* From Seymour, Tehran* To . . . Govemor-Greneral (External Affairs Department) Simla. EXPRESS Your telegram No. 47. I assume that no action likely to . antagonise Iranian Government is contemplated at present juncture. Subject to this I feel that if there were to be any retaliation it should be by way of action on lines similar to action taken by Iranian Government, i*e*, by expulsion of Iranians and that it would be unwise to introduce quite a different issue. Increased tariffs might result in counter retaliation here by same method and it is impossible to forsee where a tariff war would end. Hence while sympathising with difficulties of Berberis I would be reluctant to recommend trying to help them in manner proposed. N, s F.3.» D.S.(F)., J.S., &amp; U.S.(F) /(5) • • • • © GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, EXTERNAL AFFAIRS DEPARTMENT* EXPRESS LETTER * From - Foreign, New Delhi* To - His Majesty’s Consul General, Meshed* (Repeated Minister Tehran)* No* F. 238-N/38. Dated New Delhi, the 21st October 1938. Your telegram 224 September 23rd repeated to Tehran as No. 37. (2) Mter consultation with Minister Tehran and detailed examination here Government of India have decided against 'oroposal for retaliation by way of imposition of increased customs duties. For one thing as pointed out by Minisoer \ such action would introduce quite different issue and result in tariff war end of which cannot be foreseen. In addition there are certain technical objections which make this course in any case undesirable. (3) At same time we agree that expulsions to which your telegram refers call for more positive attitude than hitherto adopted, particularly in regard to two Sikh traders ^- nu the Punjabi who are among those expelled from Zabul and Zahidan. (4) Y r e have therefore drawn attention of Iranian Consul General g here to the matter. At personal interview on 12th October such details of expulsion as are available were given to him and concern of Government of Ineia expressed* Representations followed line taken oy iv\ Yeb 9 - Cao® te/v Minister/at Tehran vide paragraph 3 of Tehran despatch No* 154 of 14th September.- 2 - (5) Particular stress was laid on publicity and bitter feeling likely to be roused in India by these expulsions and consequent probability of deimnd for retaliatory action against Iranian subjects in India justice of which Government of India would find difficult to resist* (6) Monsieur Ansari professed ignorance of these parti cular cases but promised to make enquiries from his Government and at same time communicate the concern expressed by Government of India* (7) It is too much to hope that this action will have any decisive result but if only effect is to make Iranian Government more alive to consequences of arousing Indian resentment and therefore more hesitant about further expulsions something will have been gained* (8) Beyond this we do not feel inclined to go at present, ^here is plenty of scope for retaliation by way of expulsion of Iranians in India but for sake of general relations between Iranian Government and Government of India and His Majesty’s Government we are reluctant to embark on such course except as very last resort* le are not yet convinced that such course, even if adopted, would be effective and we cannot ignore possibility of counter retaliation by Iranian Government which would ruin large number of Indian traders in Iran* The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd/- G* C* L. Crichton, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India*-'7 Copy of express letter (Confidential) No. 1431 # dated the 29th September 1958 from Britconsul, Meshed* to Foreign, Simla. Fveference your letter No. F. 238-N/38, dated the 23rd August 1938 to Baluchi a tan. 2. Possibly the present situation has not been sufficiently explained. The total assets of the Beroeria have been deposited by them in Rials in the Meshed branch of the Imperial Bank of Iran in a separate account in the name of the Vice-Consul, Meshed. As funds are required for Covemnent purposes cheques are drann by Vice-Consul on this account and paid to Consulate Treasury and the equivalent in Rupees at current rate of exchange is sent to the Political Agent, Quetta, by supply bill for proportionate distribution to individual Berber is, for each of whom an account ic maintained by me. Tids satisfied all our account requirements. Political Agent merely cashes my supply bills and distributes proceeds in accordance with my instructions. It is not I hope proposed that any fresh instructions idmt it !»y be considered necessary to issue to Baluchistan should affect the arrangements made in Government account lushed. Any attempt to credit now to this Consulate/ the whole assets of the Berberis is likely to involve Government in loss owing to possible exchange fluctuations.in. r. r From To Uo. ?. 2S8-N/38. Th# UAdfir .^ecrtiiary to the Government of India in th* ijctonutl Affairs iieparteent. Tiu» Hon*bio tiie j^pett to tiie Governor General t Heeident and Uiiief Cosra liaaicner in Baluchietan* .iated hew jelhi» the ^ January 1959. SUBJhGTi- Ihcpuleion of ijer’oeria froj^ Iran, bir, I am dxi'ected to refer to tiie correepondenoe erding srith your ismmrafi&amp;m ho. C-10/58- K-lcK)8-- .6., dated tiie died Bepteuiber 1936* eiid to enoloee for infom* iion* |7j copy of the naurginally noted comtimication. 2. In modification of the procedure laid down in my letter foo. T. ri58-H/53 t dated the 25rd u^^uat 19.38, the Government of India have decided that the moii&amp;'/n of tire Berber!a should b© deposited with the Imperial Bank of Iren in the nao» of the fioe-Consul, Meshed, and utilised for Government purposes from time to time. A* ssoney ie withdrawn, the equivalent in Indian currency at the current rate of exchange should be remitted to the Political ^ent, ^uetta, by weefte of supply ^ills for diatribution to individual Herbaria• A aiaterauti t showing the amount of each supply bill and its distribution should be furnished by the Consul General. Ihe i olitical ^§©nt ehoulo credit the sale proceeds of the supply bills to a Personal Depositas Account vis, Section P. Civil Deposits - Personal Deposits - Berberis Accounts and imke the distribution &amp;press letter Aroxo fi'is Itjoaiy^a ffcneul ..o. 14al. a.^a tae 29w&gt; ,epbe.r;ogr from.V 1 - l, 660 Vfc &gt;- - 2 • from Uiio account by clxO&lt;vue» dram on The Political should maintain a detailed account shomn^ the amountc of supply bill# received and deposited in the Fer&amp;on&amp;i deposit i^occunt^ tii© Bar &gt;. i is to mom the payunanta are to be mde, the amounts paid \ am Xu* balivacs due to each. ' I have the honour to be. Sir, Your .noat obedient aervrjit. Id/- C.K.S. Sarma, Under Secretary to the Government of India,P.Z.7833/1938 CONFIDENTIAL, a* ' Extract from Meshed Political Diary for the month of October, 1938. 300. 69 Iranian gypsies expelled from India arrived at Mirjawa on October 12th. They were interviev/ed by the Chief of Police, Zahidan, on the 13th and informed him that they had been expelled from India in retaliation for the expulsion of British Indian subjects from Iran. The Police also made enquiries about them from M. Rafaat, the Iranian Passport Officer in Quetta, who paid a hurried visit to Zahidan on the 19th October, for v/hat purpose is unknown, had a long telephonic communication v/ith Tehran and r turned to India the same day. The gypsies have now been sent under escort into the interior of ttfe country. These expulsions have caused considerable excitement in East Iran. The Indians are, of course, delighted and report that Captain Sharifi has completely changed his tune. Since the arrival of the gypsies no more has been heard of the expulsion of the further 26 Indians mentioned in para. 277.No 3X8. (631/35/38). CS? 0 i &lt; . - Tehran, British Legation, His „ „ t sentative presents bis compliments to 23rd September, 19 38 . His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of deportations of .ierberis* Beference :— Tehran despatch No# 313 of 14#9*1938 # Despatch No, 158 of the 23rd September, 1938, to His Excellency the Governor-General of India* Simla,' “7 »» / * ot/ no, 16a. (631/36/80) iS53 j Copies to j F # 0. Ho. 318. Meshed. HO. 49. both ref. 621/23/38. British negation, Tehran. i33rd ssptenb^r* 1938. '-ty Lord 'nrqueast since I had the honour to address to Your Excellency ny despatch No. 1S4 of the 14th September* it has been necessary to continue to make a:«ost dally representations at the Ministry for F&lt;s*eign Affaire In the Mtt«S of the Berber is and the two Sikhs whom the Iranian authorities desire to expel from Iran* 2. 1 fear it has not been possible to shake the authorities in their decision to proceed with these expslslons. I bays, however» been able to secure promises that assistance will be given in the matter of the export of the capital of those affected. as regards this* an undertaking has been given that the men will be allowed to utilise their assets In the purchase of oorpetg cr other articles which are not s aovernaent monopoly, and then permitted to export these goods from Iran free of restriction. iis Majesty f s Consular officers at TMiiam and iiabul are in touch with the local authorities with reference to the details of the arrangements to befeade. 5. In the meantime I regret that the instructions which the ministry for Foreign Affairs promised to send arrived too late in one case - as indeed I anticipated would happen in paragraph a of my despatch under refermce. Ahmed All lel’t Iran on the 11th Sept saber. 4* His excellency The Kight Honourable The Marquess of Llnlitiigow. PUT. , 0. 0. X. , etc*, etc., etc., SIMLA*4» I am mending copies of thig dggpatch to His Majesty's principal secretary of state for Foreign Affairs and His Majesty's Con «ul-*Gtm oral for KhorasBan* I have the honour to be. My Lord Marquess, Your Excellency's most obedient servant, (-gd) ^iymwr.14 6130 17548c (4) /Im^ In any further communication on this subject^ please quote . n 0 . EE'frK'S ( 5-S-T3 and address- not to any person by name, but to— ' ‘‘The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London,?S.W. I. ^ INDIA DIRECT vt) -? f r ~(y'w r t) u&gt; /Ujb * 1953 j ^ L ^ &gt; - THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to 0ru^L(lcc and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop KJL# of the under-mentioned paper. - i93? • Foreign Office, Reference to previous correspondence : krJ' Su »7 jC Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 07 Ojor~i- rvx^r^ 1 Similar letter sent toCopy . /V (E 5883/5883/34). No. 462/15/38. 14th September, 1938. To: The Eastern Department, The Foreign Office, LONDON, S.W.l. With the compliments of His Majesty^ Representative. British Legation, Tehran(S 5883/5883/34) No. 462/15/38. 14th September, 1938. Would you please refer to Government of India ^ telegram to Tehran No. 17 of the 25th April, in which we were informed of the selection of Major J.B. Cunningham for one year’s language duty in Iran? 2. The authorities here have been causing considerable trouble in his case. First he was delayed for over two weeks in Bombay while they decided whether he should be given a visa. Then, on his arrival at Isfahan, the police at once raised difficulties about his residence permit and camera permit. We enlisted the help of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs but nothing happened. Matters suddenly came to a head a few days ago, when I learnt that Cunningham had been ordered to leave Iran within forty-eight hours. The police, in intimating this to him, stated that they did not know the reason. I at once made urgent representations to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, (the Minister is away in Geneva) and, being unable to get any sense out of the Ministry, saw the Prime Minister; the latter agreed that permission should be sent for Cunningham to come up to Tehran. This I instructed him to do, and he arrived on the evening of the 9th September. 3. 1/ Sir H.A.F. Metcalfe, K.C.I.h., C.S.I., M.V.O., Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla.3 I have since Cunningham* s arrival represented to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs that the police admitted &gt;&gt; they had nothing against him, and I have impressed on them the serious discourtesy with which he has been treated, but I fear there is no hope of getting him back to Isfahan. This is another instance of the suspiciousness of the authorities, against which we come up the whole time. 4. The only satisfactory feature is that the Ministry of Foreign Affairs have without delay managed to get the police instructed to issue a 'permis de s^our” for residence in Tehran. I am sorry for the quite pointless inconvenience caused to Cunningham, but I think that from the language point of view he will be as well off here. In any case, after what has happened, he had better live somewhere where we can keep an eye on him. 5. I am sending a copy of this letter to the Eastern Department at the Foreign Office. (Signed) Horace J. Seymour.Minute Paper. political Department. Expulsion of British Berberis and other British Indian subjects from Iran. The Iranian Government’s drive against certain families of Berberis of Indian and Afghan antecedents settled in Khorasan is described in the submission at P.Z.4063/38, which carries matters down to last June. The number of Berberis who finally left reached the figure of 137, of whom 98 had retained their British nationality. They realised Rials 286,400 bv the sale of their property, /pImt paib cw* ft tt&amp; Hu6l*2 CiUht&amp;j&amp;ThJibeavAiUtll*' fa ttleu* fca*' ohY'ia/aA- iu&gt; , In arranging their actual departure the Iranian cf.Minister at Tehran’s letter dated 5th Aug. at P.Z. 6190/38 enclosing authorities were more obliging than at an earlier stage; letter dated 22nd July from it became quite clear before the end that the Berberis’ Consul-General at Meshed. nonconformity with Persian dress regulations was the merest pretext for an antagonism due to suspicions of espionage, and ultimately to dislike of anyone not x impeccably Iranian. The Government of India were averse For the change A of attitude on to a serious dispute over a community which they had this subject vide the Consul-described as 11 British subjects in little more than name*.' General ’ s letter dated 13th June at P.Z.5272/3&amp; Meanwhile, however, at Zabul and Zahidan four further British Indian subjects received oral notice to quit and on 7th and 8th August six more, of whom four cf.para;3 of were Berberis and two were Sikhs, received actual the Minister’s *r- 7 — ^ u ^ letter of 5th expulsion notices. Of the six, all of August at whom are traders in Zahidan, five had served in the Indian Army and this was given them orally as the reason for their expulsion. Vigorous representations by our P.Z. 5190/38. x reported in Minister at Tehran to the Iranian Ministry of Foreign his letter of Affairs secured at the last minute the postponement of the 14th Sept, at P.Z.5990/58. orders of expulsion pending negotiations with a view to The Aide-memoii^ f « p enclosed there* a settlement of exchange problems in connection with the with gives the names and realisation of their property. This presumably means status of those aft^cWar 111 10 ' 000 08 that/that it still remains the intention of the Iranian authorities to have the orders of expulsion carried out, though the Minister is continuing his efforts to stop them.-s ,*0 1 ^jf*/^ ■ -C.W (E 5837/461/34). Dear Peel, 040 333 F j ^ fcjsJpa t oJS/Jz. $ . 'I, [ ^ FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.1. 13th October, 1938. You will remember that in your letter No. P*Z*4263/38 of the 16th July you suggested that the threat of a Question and Answer in the House of Commons about the treatment of our Consuls in East Persia might have a salutary effect on the Persian Government. 2. We referred this suggestion to the Legation at Tehran, and I enclose herein a copy of a letter now received from Seynour ir reply* He does not, you will see, think that this expedient would have the desired effect. 3. Our own view is that the Shah is sensitive to which he considers to be ridicule or insults rather than to 'public opinion”. But in any case, publicity is not a weapon which is likely to do any good unless it is used with resolution, and at the present juncture in hardly MAifc letter R.T. Peel, Esq., M.C. FNCL08URE IN AIR NO. (!•«, JJ II .1° • 5S ’ FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. IIS. .A OFFICE embark/embark upon a campaign of publicity against the Persians, however much their manners may call for such action.Copy * (E 5837/461/34), Ho.148/25/38 . I 7040 I ! S o 3 ^—— i British Legation, Tehran* 8th Septemher, 3-9384 My dear Lacy, I have delayed answering your letter to Nevile Butler of the 4th August, (E 4271/461/34), on the use of publicity in connexion with our grievances in East Iran, as I wanted to talk to Squire, who is now in Tehran for a couple of days* 2* On the whole I cannot believe that questions and answers in the House of Commons would be likely to relieve matters, and I would not recommend our lightly embarking on a policy of this kind of publicity. I do not see what exact objective we could place before ourselves: we covld give our version of various incidents: the Persians would deny that version, and we should I think get no nearer what is required - a civilised attitude towards the Consulates* 3* As a matter of fact publicity may be forced upon us in rather a different way — over thequestion of expulsions of Indians from East Iran. The Persians are taking steps to get rid of some more Indians, mostly Berberis but including two Sikhs who have a business of some value. We are doing our best to get these men left alone, but if they are expelled we must expect complaints in public from their friends in India* I have already cf pox* l iV privately warned the Persians of this prospect, but i/f^ whether we can stop the ex P ul8i0ne 1 do not yet know# CUxi/A Yours ever, (Sgd. ) Horace Seymour* Lacy Baggallay, Esq., The Foreign Office, S.W.l.No... 313 1 1,1 sL&amp;ilj 33/ 34) &gt;/ / i - British Legati on 6 .’ehran, 14th ^eptemWc His Majesty’s Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of deportations of British Indian subjects from Iran. Reference :— l&amp;i^c Tehran despatch 14o« &lt;*79 of the 5th ^ugast 1948. despatch to the Goverment of India Ho* 154 of 14th September,1936P.Z. 7156/38 EXTRACT FROM BALUCHI ST AIT WEEKLY INTELLIGENCE SECRET* ' SUMMARY NO.UP. DATED TTOCTOBER, 1938/ 39» Deportations of Hazaras from Iran have been reported in a number of past summaries. It appears from the numerous reports since received that it is the policy of the Iranian Government to gradually deport all Hazaras of British-Indian and Afghan nationality. It is further understood that the Government have decided that even Hazaras of Iranian nationality are not to be allowed to reside near the border in future. Orders have been issued warning such persons living in close proximity to the border to arrange to settle in the interior. The hazaras living near Turbat-i-Shaikh Jam (29 A-C/4), near the Herat border, are reported to be already moving to Laristan. Even Hazara officials will not, in future, be employed near the border. Two Hazara clerks of the Zahidan post-office, named Muhammad Atai and Barkat Ali, have recently, in pursuance of this policy, been transferred to Kerman and Meshed respectively. 40. In Zahidan it is believed that the deportation of foreign Hazaras will be carried out in small batches so as not to give ground for complaint by the Indian and Afghan Governments. About 25 more Hazaras are expected to be deported from Zahidan in the near future.Q P.Z.749 3/38. Confidentia l. i)xtract8 from Meahed Political Diary No.9 for the month of September 1938. SI ST AI T. 263. Certain Afghan subjects in Zabul were ordered A. to leave the country in August last. The orders were apparently only verbal but one expulsion, that of the courier of the former Afghan Consulate has been enforced. The courier was removed under an Amnieh escort. So much for the Saadabsd pact. A. A. B. 273. (Reference para. 242) Mullick Sardar Ahmed has been permitted to export almond kernels in order to obtain the foreign exchange necessary for the girders he is supplying. There seems no reason why British subjects expelled from the country should not similarly be allowed to export monopolised articles. 277. Captain Sharifi, the unpopular Chief of Police, Zahidan, returned from leave on September 28th, relieving Captain Jehanbin who returns to Zabul. Sharifi is understood to have said that there are still another 26 British Indian subjects to be expelled from Zahidan. He is believed locally to be the prime mover in the expulsion of foreigners.nit) r :w t ^ StP 1766. '7 f &gt;!&lt;*✓ J * ' ' 3 ? Telegram R No. 44 Dated (and reed.) 1st September 1938. From .Seymour Tehran. To HJI. Consul-General, Meshed. t-f ,1 7 1&amp; (Repeated Foreign, Simla No. 71.) STRESS. Your Despatch No. 66. I gave Under Secretary of state today aide-memoire containir^ short summary of cases and made verbal representations on the follovdng lines. Speaking personally and without instructions I foresaw that these further expulsions might lead to serious situation. Any action implying discrimination against Indians would be deeply resented and some of men now under notice of expulsion had been told that their military service was real cause for action against them. If this were true it was clearly discrimination against Indians. Bitter feeling would be aroused in India and demand might well arise for revision of attitude of tolerance towards Iranians in India. Surely it Was not v/orth while to risk such developments in order to get rid of a few men against whom so far I knew there was no accusation. 2. As regards further Berberis under notice I thought these would be resigned to leaving if arrangements could be made for them to export their possessions. emc. : i:i IA FOiit-urt ARY’G 0:tter No. 1(4 Dated 2 SL * Reoelvwl 1 o SL 3. Finally I asked that additional time should be givengiven before any irrevocable action was taken* 4* Under Secretary of State promised urgent enquiries*In any further communication on subject, please quote No. E 5084/451/34. and address, no/ to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. rs 6 INDIA DIRECT v (sk*oLq .93 Foreign Office. S.W.l. 3rd September, 1938. ft Sir, ^ With reference to Foreign Office letter No. E 2715/461/34 of the 20th May regarding the incident in which a bus hired for the transport of the staff of His Majesty’s Consulate-General at Meshed was temporarily commandeered by an officer of the Iranian Army, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to transmit to you, to be laid before the Marquess of Zetland, the accompanying copy of a despatch on the subject from His Majesty’s Chargd d’Affaires at Tehran. 2. Lord Halifax proposes, subject to Lord Zetland’s concurrence, to inform His Majesty's Minister that he approves the terms of the further communication which has been addressed by His Majesty’s Legation to the Persian Ministry for Foreign Affairs. I am, t ' ,• L. fc 1 . 5 Sl -••'‘938 INDIA OFFICE Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office.LONDON. S.W.I., British Legs!Ion 9 Ko. 278 , (351/17/38) Tehran* 6 th August 9 1938, My Lord, I have the honour to invite reference to Your Lordship^ despatch Ho. J.71 of the 19th May, (fc 2716/461/34), and to enclose herein copies of the — further note which, as there authorised by Your Lordship, I addressed to the Iranian Gowernment on the subject of the incident involving a bus hired by His Majesty^ Consul-General at Meshed. 2. After frequent reminders, I have at last — succeeded in eliciting a note, of which copies are also enclosed, in reply to my original representations. The terms of this note are entirely unsatisfactory; indeed no attempt whatever is made to answer the arguments put forward in my own note. 3. I called at the Ministry for Foreign Affairs on the 27th July, and saw Monsieur Intizam, the new Head of the Third Political Department. As he was no doubt unfamiliar with the case, I took with me and shoved him copies both of my own original Note and of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs Note in reply. I told him, speaking personally, that the Ministry for Foreign Affairs Note did not answer our points, that it left me with the feeling that an army officer in The Right Honourable The Viscount Halifax, K.G., G.C.S.I., etc., etc., etc., The Foreign Office, /last&lt;Sf Eaet Iran, howeTcr subordinate, would be allowed to get away with anything; and that we were bound to ask the Ministry for Foreign Affairs for a more adequate reply. I referred to previous talks with Monsieur Zanjanl on previous incidents, when I had warned him that inadequate punishment would lead to further incidents ending in serious ones, and I said that in the present case, though we had asked for very modest compensation and, orally, for an apology, our main anxiety was to be satisfied that the peccant officer’s misconduct should be adequately brought home to him and others, with a view to preventing similar Incidents in the future. I asked Monsieur Intlsam for his help in this. 4. Monsieur Intizam listened sympathetically, and undertook to try to get a more satisfactory answer. In reply to an enquiry from him, I said that I would probably send him a further written communication drawing attention to the omissions in the Ministry for Foreign Affairs Note. This I have now done, and I have the honour to enclose copies of my Note herein. I am aware that Your Lordship does not desire to make a test case of the present incident, and I have therefore endeavoured to word this further communication objectively. I trust that Your Lordship will agree with its terms, and with my decision to attempt to obtain a fuller and more satisfactory answer to our complaint. I am sending copies of this despatch to /The— - s - The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affaire Department, (No* 143), and to Hie Majesty 9 e Consul-General for Khorassan, at Meshed, (No* 41). I have the honour to he, With the highest respect, My Lord, Your Lordship 9 s most obedient, humble Servant, (Signed) N* M. Butler*Kncloeure No, 1 in Tehran despatch No, 278 of 5t h Auguat 19g8« British Legation, Tehran, 81 sc June,, 1.Q38# No, 864 . His Majesty 1 s Legation have the honour, under instructions from His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom, to invite reference to their note of the 19th March (No, 109), with regard to an incident in which a bus hired by His Majesty’s Consul-General for Khorassan was involved on the 1st March. His Majesty’s Legation have now received a despatch from His Majesty’s Government in which it is stated that the latter approve the representations which the Legation felt obliged to address to the Imperial Government on the above subject, 2* His Majesty’s Legation venture to express the hope that they may be favoured with an early reply to their communication.Enclosure No,2, In Tehran despatchJjo. 273 of the 5 th Au^ujst^—_ ^ Translation : Prom the Imperial Ministry for Foreign Affairs, (Third Political Department), addressed to His Britannic Majesty’s Legation, Tehran. No. 22115/2002, dated 3rd Murdad, 131? (25th July, 1938). Memorandum: The Ministry for Foreign Affairs of the Imperial Government, with reference to the British Legation’s note No. 109 of the 28th Esfand, 1316, (19th March, 1938), has the honour to inform the Legation that the contents of the memorandum in question were communicated to the competent quarters in due course. According to enquiries made of Captain Vossuq £adeh, it appears that the latter was ordered to take certain supplies to the Mukran Army Corps. When he was transporting these supplies in a motor-bus he collided with another car at a turn of the road near Sehdeh; the radiator, the front wheels and the front springs were smashed; also one man was hurt. As it was not advisable to leave the wounded man and the supplies in the middle of the desert, these supplies were, according to the agreement reached between the chauffeurs, conveyed to Birjand in the machine which caused the accident (zarib: literally - M which hit' - translator)• (Sealed) Ministry for Foreign AffairBritish Legation, Tehran* 5th August, 1958* MxJSSSi* His Malest/^ Legation have the honour to aehnowledge receipt of the aeaorandua from the Iisperlal t Ministry for Foreign Affaire, Ho* 22115/2008 of the 25th July (3rd Murdad), on the suhj eet of the Incident on the 1st March, (10th Eefand), in which a hue hired by His Majesty's Consul-General at Meshed vas involved. 8* His Majesty's Legation note that enquiries have been made of darwan Vossuq 3adeh, and that in hie report he has stated that the commandeering of His Majesty's Consulate-General's bus took place 'in accordance with the agreement reached between the chauffeurs'. According, however, to the report received by Hie Majesty's Legation, the commandeering followed directly upon a threat by Sarwan Voasuq £adeh to use force. He ordered his men to tie up the British-Indian driver of /HiaHI* Majesty'* Con*ulate-Grner*l’• bus with a rope, and the drlwer therefore had no option hut to coaply with the wlshea of Sarwan Vossuq iadeh* There was therefore no agreement between the chauffeurs which could be deemed to supersede the Iranian regulations regards the requisitioning of lorries, nor any voluntary agreement with Sarwan Vossuq Sadeh to act as the latter desired* S* Furthermore, Sarwan Vossuq Sade)^ s statement In no way answers certain other points mentioned in His Majesty* s Legation*s Note No* 109 of the 19th March (28th Esfand, 1516); in particular the points concerning the forcible emptying of the contents of His Majesty* s Consulate-aeneral* s bus on its arrival at Sehdeh, and the resulting Improper treatment of the archives of His Majesty*s Consulate-General* There was here again no question of agreement being obtained to this, nor to the subsequent further commandeering of the bus to return to the scene of the accident* There, it will be recelled, the drive ewae placed under arrest, as the party from His Majesty f s Consulate-General declined3 - to leare their driver bellina and sign a written statement to the effect that they had no complaint of any sort againat Sarwan Voaauq ?.adeh. Hi a Majesty'a Legation would observe that the mere fact that auch a atateaent waa demanded indicated a realisation on the part of Sarwan Voaauq Kadeh that hi a act ions had gone very auch too far. 4. There waa again no question of any agreement on the part of any member of the party from Hie Majesty's Consul at ©-General to the commandeering of their bus from the scene of the accident for the second time. Hia Majesty's Legation would point out that it waa this compulsory requisitioning of the bus, first from Sehdeh to return to the scene of the accident, and then from, the latter place to Sehdeh and thence to Birjand, that led to their request in paragraph 10 of their Note So. 109 of the 19th March, iddthBsfand, 1316;, for the payment of Hiala 600 for services actually rendered by the driver of the lorry under compulsion. In hia report Sarwan Voasuq Sadsh refers to Hia Majesty's Consulate-General's bus as 'the /machine4 machine which caused the accident 11 • His Majesty's Legation desire, however, to invite attention to the fact that the occupants of His Majesty's Consulate-General's bus were unanimously of the opinion that their driver was in no way to blame for the accident* Iven if their opinion is regarded as 'ex parte', it should be observed that the Amnlyeh official who Inspected the scene of the accident reported that in his views both drivers were to blame. Ke did not exonerate the driver of Sarwan Vossuq. Xadeh* a bus. Hut, as His Majesty's Legation previously pointed out in their Hots Ho# 109 of the 19th March, (28th Ksfand, 1316), whatever may be the correct apportionment of responsibility, it could not justify the conduct of Serwan Vossuq 2adeh on this occasion. 6. The Imperial Ministry for Foreign Affairs will hove noted that there la no comment in Garwan Vosauq Sadeh'a report on his action in detaining the driver of Hia Majesty's Consulate-General*s bus at Blrjand from 10,30 p.m. until midnight, on the arrival there of barwan Vosauq /Sadeh'a5 £«deh 9 B party. Nor ia there any comment on his action in placing a military guard orer the bus on ita arrival at Birjand or in arbitrarily detaining it under guard during the whole of the aubaequent day, the 2nd March, (Hth “ afend, 1316), until 6 p.m. 7. His Majesty’s Legation would be very grateful if the Imperial Ministry for Foreign Affairs would, in the light of the above, cause fresh enquiries to be Instituted and would inform them of the result In due course.aomaamAL . K)?9mor Greneral, Re»ident and Ghief Sommissioner in Baluchistan. La continuation of endorsement from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, No.F.238-N/38, dated the 10th August 1938, I am directed to state that in connection with the payments to be made to the Ber- beris on their arrival in India, it has been decided that the value of their property which will be taken over by His Majesty's Consulxte General for Khorasan will be credited in the Consulate account for the month in which the amount is actually received; the rupee equivalent being calculated at the rate of exchange for the month in which the transaction takes place. Dhe rupee equiva lent thus converted will be adjusted under a personal deposit account, viz. 'Section P-Civil Deposits - Persona} Deposits - Berberis Accounts' for the opening of which special sanction of the Government of India will be accorded. The amounts required from time to time for disburse ment to the Berberis will be drawn on cheques from the treasury by the particular authority in Baluchisten, who will be charged v/ith the administration of the personal ledger account, vide. Article 217, Civil Account Code, Volume I. The Government of India will be glad to know the designation of the official whom you would detail for the purpose and on receipt of this information detailed instructions will be issued.1719. Telegram R No.25, dated 22nd (reed 23rd) August 1938. From. .His Ma.jesty T s Consul-General, Meshed. To. .. .-..^Minister, Tehran. (Repeated Foreign No.188)* EXPRESS. My telegram No.24 of 21st July. One appeal from Zahidan of Ahmed Ali son of Juna Ali rejected and second notice served pn 14th. Could urgenc application be made for him to be given foreign exchange for his assets of the value of Frans 50,000 or permission to export goods to that value and for postponement of expulsion meanwhile 0 2. Six more British subjects traders in Zahidan of whom five have served in Indian Army were served with first notices of expulsion on 7th August and 8th August. Four of them were verbally informed that reason for their expulsion was their previous service in the Indian Army. Two of them are Sikhs who are not willing to leave. Anticipate serious repercussions in India if these expulsions are enforced. Despatch follows. (N. F.S. D.S.F. J.S. U.S.F.) M.R.I indexed In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. E 5086/49/34. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. INDIA DIRECT C^j r \co) Foreign Office. 3rd September, 1938. Sir, With reference to India Office letter No.P.Z.5872/38 .■■ky n of the 23rd August regarding the expulsion of Berberis from Persia, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to transmit to you, for the information of the Marquess of Zetland, the accompanying copies of two despatches on the subject from His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires at Tehran. 2. Lord Halifax shares Mr. Butler’s high opinion of the manner in which this matter v/as handled by His Majesty’s Consul-General for Khorassan. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office. ftfcfcD. PUL. 5 SEP 1938 INDIA OFFICENo 279 5th ^agast 9 1938.- His Majesty's presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Deportation of Berberia. Referenee:- Deapatoh Bo* 144 to His i&amp;xoellency the Governor-General of India, from Hi a Majesty's Chargtf d'affaires t Tehran* Copy also sent to iChoraasan ho* 42ao. a8u(44o/7i/s&gt;el British Legation t Gulhdk, 6th .agast, 19^8* ^..y Lor4 t 7. L With reference to my telegram ho, m of the 11th wane, I have the honour to transmit to lour Lordship herewith copies of &amp; despatch from His Majesty's Oonsul- Oeneral for Mho rasa an t (ho. 59 -l/4B of the k&amp;id reporting on the conclusion of the case of ^ht d-wpoliud Berberis, d*he number of Berber!a vho finally left reached the figure of lo7 t 98 of whom hud retained their British nationality, whereas the remainder had at least nominally become Iranian subjects, fhe sum which they realised as a result of the sale of their properties oame to a total of iii&amp;ls *86,400, 2 hie aaount has been de posited by them with Mr, bquire, I aid not fail to inform the Irani n Oo^emment that the estimate I had originally gi^sn them would be exceeded; i;he official ,«ith whom I spoke at the Ministry of foreign affairs did not show con cern at this - indeed I understand that the grevemor— General for i-horassau hed himself originally mentioned a figure of Rials 400,000 - and, in the absence of riy comment from the Irani n Government, I think th t there is reasonable ground for anticipating that they will not raise any objections, I think that it can be fairly said tht t the incident as passed off as satisfactorily ao could have been expected, &gt;11 the assistance that was possible was / afforded fhe Right ‘honourable, ! i'he Viscount Halifax, h.G., G.h.4.1,, etc,, etc,, etc,.— mm 1 111 m ■ m* ^ • &lt;1 afforded to the victims of the axpulelon orders, hot ^ through©at Hie kajesty^ Legation and Mr # dqaire h-ve been in mind the fact that these Berherie were, m the Government of India pointed oat in a telegram of the 4th kay, Uo* *1 to me), drifcish subjects In little more than n jee and that the Government of India were as a result averse to their being made a sei’icas bone of contention v ith the Iranian (vovemment* ^.t the same time His iaajQSty , s Legation felt sure that His |ftnj« 0 ty v 8 uovemment ~Jid the Government of IndiA would share the view tit t in the interest of British prestige it was highly desirable that the Lerberis retreat across the Irano-Indi m frontier should be in good order, and tfith a good prospect of their not becoming indigents in India. 4 # I £i&amp; sendin copies of this despatch to the decret ry to the Govemacnt of India in the dxternal affairs department and to His Majesty's Consul -General for ^hor-ssan. I h ve the honour to be. bith the highest respect. ky Lord, lour nordship's. most obedient, humble Servant, ( iigned) Jlcvil« Butler*ZQMimmiAL . MO 69-1/4JS h Oonsulato Gen oral Khoraaan, keahed* sand July 1936• sir, How that tha Berber la who formed the auhjeot of the oorreapondenoe resting with telegram ;Jo; 36 dated 3Uth July 1938 from the Qowrnment of India hare left Iran it may he of Interest if I attempt a Brief review of the whole ease* I have had several opportunities of talking to auhedar Joh&amp;med lUsuf nnci. Havildar ftek kohamed since their release from Jail as a result of which it has been possible to arrive at certain definite oonolusions as to the reasons for the action that the Iranian authorities have taken* *• when these two were first arrested in January last on leaving the Meshed Consulate they were examined closely as to their antecedents and present mode of life and were definitely accused of being British spies* The Iranians cannot, of course, understand any Oovernaent being so quixotic as to continue the payment of pensions to residents in a foreign oountry without demanding some definite service in return* Their assurances therefore that they only came to the Obnsulate to draw their pensions could not possibly be accepted and they were lodged in Jail. Fortunately for thea they na&amp; at the time of their arrest a considerable sum of money with them* This was placed to their credit with the Jail authorities To i* His Britannic Majesty's Charge d*Affaires, Tehran•tibrough whoa they were afcie to purchase any food and other necessaries that they might require* i’hey were not unooaziortaole nor unhappy in jail as they report at least loot) other prisoners in exactly the same plights imprisoned on mere suspicion without any definite charge 9 and with little hope of release unless they were In a position to pay handsomely for it* fhelr chief complaint was that they were unahle to communicate in any say with their friends outside* 5* oareful notes were taken Dy the secret police of all their friends and associates in the little colony at kalata Khuah and the neighbouring Tillages ana there can now he no doubt that the wholesale expulsion of the herberls of hrltlsh and Afghan nationality was the direct result of the information thus acquired* When matters came to a head and enabled me to make representations on Dehalf of the prisoners no great difficulty was felt in ordering tnelr release* The manner in which this was done was, however 9 typical. They were sent before a court and informed that they had obtained their sljjils (Iranian nationality documents) under false pretences ana were therefoxe sentenced to 6 months imprisonment* as they had already spent more than this period in jail they were released* Their friends meanwhile had given the jail authorities a bribe of 6,000 rials (£62-10-0) in order to obtain their release* when, however, this was effected by consulate intervention, they claimed and secured, a refund of ms orlbs, surely &amp;n alaost unique aoflleveaent even for the land of haji babe* 4o onoe the return of these J»rDeris with their raailies to Xnaia had beenccotpted I auat acknowiaage tiiat it^aJcraYan was most conciliatory and oven gonsrous in tulfllllng the conditions agreed upon* The ^erDeris sea urea a wery fair price fbr tneir land froh the (Jowemaient; the length or the negotiations gave then surrioient time to dlepose of their rloots and household property) and tinally this consulate has been allowed to t&amp;te thfcJLr capital Tot local use glring the^i rupees in exchange* Thnt the authorities should oare granted to a pack or 'unaeslraiaws' a concoction which the majority or respectable traders in £ast Iran would be only too glad to accept and tor fthioh indeed many of theft nave applied in vain is truly astonishing* and can* in my opinion only be attributed to the mot that the Iranians are again quite unable to believe that we can be »© ridiculously honest as to buy our rial requirements at the omoial rate* an indeed we do* when they could easily be* ana in Tact by most other foreign missions are believed to be o&amp;Vaindd unomdully »* Hide nore than htlf lr»t mile* (ittnaour Indeea r»o ll tact ay Argymn colleague jtsla otoo lass man the “blecx rale* lo ala naiionsis wao nave ^liallarly been expellee, from Iran). b * At tne s&amp;ae tlwe I ao not oonslaer tmt tne settlement or Ids case gives any grouna for unaue coapiaconoy. fne r&amp;ot reaalna tnat tne Iranian uovernamt nave witnout assigning any reason at all, ana In r&amp;ot wlinout legitlMste osuss sxpslleu &amp; wnole colony ol oarmlsss people enose only orrenoe i to quote xroa tneir own papers on tne euejeot of tne externeestron «uasla) is tftst tney are nationals of anotnar country. mat tne price enion tneyFrom..Britconsul, Meshed. To..........Minister, Tehran. (Repeated Foreign, Simla. No.168). EXPRESS. Four more British Indian subjects (two at Zabul and two at Sahidan) have been verbally ordered by the Police to leave Iran. All are retired non'-Commissioned Officers and three are Berberis. Vice-Consuls have been instructed to obtain Expulsion Orders in writing and to advise them to submit appeals. (N, F.S. D.S,F. J.So U.S.FJ M,R. ENCLOSURE IN r'OIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Latter No. ' 4 o Dated 4 AUG. Beoetved 2^ AUG ^12th July 1938 # from H.B.H’s Conaul General for Khoraaan, PitE COPV%* the Secretary to the Govemnent of India in the External Affaire Department, Bimla. of those now leaving Iran for India as 137. Of this number 81 are of purely British nationality and no question arises of their right to return to India. Passports or emergyncy passports are therefore being issued inhere necessary as a matter of course. 3. These British subjects however have* in addition certain other relatives, to the number of 17, who are not strictly members of their families ana who, as far as is known, have no claim to British nationality, but who are entirely dependent on them and vho naturally wish to leave ti e country with them. These consist in two cases of widowed toothers; in one of a widowed sister and her two children, in another of an old uncle aged 80, etc. I mentioned their case to Monsieur Pakrevan telling him that have Iranian passports issued to them as this would involve \txx In continuation of my telegram No. 156 of the ^ ~ w ' jllth July 1938 I have the honour to report that the L j 9 33 jqueation of the nationality of mi several of the persons ^ S'^ wishing to accompany the Berberis now being expelled from 2. In that telegram I reported the total number ments whicn the Iranian Government might care to give than to enable them to leave the country. lionaieur Pakrevan replied that it was quite out of tne question for him to of course I could not possibly give these people British passports though I should be prepared to visa any docu 0*5 him in endless complications with other departments and takebe.«... 2 - 0 . A i tosa J s rc? iH £&gt; 0 &lt;3 V C take months to arrange. He begged me to have all these people's names entered on the documents which I was proposing to give to the heads of families and said that he would instruct the Police to give them the necessary exit visas. I am therefore in these cases issuing Emergency Passports, valid for one month, in the names of the heads of the families and entering on the rmmx reverse of tne passports t;.e names of all their dependents whether of Iranian or British origin. 4. The case of the Berber is who have taken out Iranian sijjils and of their dependents is sxkxk even more compli cated. These total 7 with 32 dependents. It has not been possible in the short time at my disposal to verify all the claims that before they leak took out Iranian sijjils they were legally British subjects. Havildar Nek ‘luhararaad for instance was born according to his own statement in Afghanistan and is probably an Afghan subject. Our records show however that he formerly waa in possession of a temporary certificate of British nationality. As these people have all served in the Indian Army and as not only is it their and the Iranian authorities* wish that they a should leave the country but also very much to our advantage that they should do so, I have thought it better not to xoi| inquire too closely into their antecedents but to issue them ail, without distinction, with British .jaergency Passports. Once tney have reached India the question of their nationality is not likely to raise any difficulties and as they are men of considerable substance there is no likelihood of their becoming destitute. 5. I trust that the action I am taking will be approved U1 the iSaergency Passports are valid only for a single journey to India for one month and cannot, therefore, be used in any attempt to return to Iran. It would, however,&lt;55 -i- be poa^ible to nave tneee documents taken from such persons as cannot est ablish their claim to British nationa lity should the Government of India think it for any reason desirable to do so. In that case a separate list with such evidence as is txxssX locally available will be prepared and forward*!« 6. I m sending a copy of this despatch to His Britannic Majesty’s Charge d* tffairea in Tehran under Printed Letter No* 58; !CONFIDENTIAL 1 No.?„238-V38, From The Deputy Secretary to tiie OeTornraent of India in the j£xt$mal Affaire Department, Hie Britannic Majesty’a Coneul General for Khoraean, Dated Simla, the /0% Augaet 193B. dxpuleion of Berberie from Iran. Sir, tith reference to your letter Ho. 158, dated the 12th July 1938, I am directed to aay that the Government of India approve the action taken by you in ieeuii^ emergency passports to Berberie and their dependents whose nationality is doubtful. A copy of this letter is being sent to Hie Majesty 1 • iinieter* Tehran by dr Mail. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your moat obedient servant. Sd/- G.C.U Crichton, Deputy Secretary to the Govemr.ent of India. Copy forwarded to the Hon'ble tiie Agent to the Governor General. Heeident and Cidef Comiaissioner in Baluchistan, for information, in continuation of enaoraement from the Government of India, External Affaire Department, No. D. 2Q22-K/38, dated the let August 1938.Lt-Ol any further oouununicution on this subject, wiease quote ^ No - £ U(?3o / f£*f /3A-. and address —not to any person by yame, ywy to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. P 7 ) * • / J * 933 INDIA DIRECT &amp; IaaM^vI) /i THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ ^ ^ W and, by direction/td' the Secretary' of State, transmits herewith cop V of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 193 / Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject..0 2S6 f p. zri 5738 1938 British Legation, Tehran, 1th July # 19 38 His Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of itnglo-Iranian Relations: Boycott - Harnam Singh. 3 6 S' Reference:- Tehran despatch ho. 458 of 14th DecemberJ37 Despatch ho. 35 from His Majesty's Chargtf d'affaires to His Majesty's Consul- General for iQiorassan at Meshed, and enclosure. Copy also sent to India ho. 127.3 tFC I •M' 57,R. FI LE 00*1 | i ! =&gt;-=&gt;H 5273 i f ( 1938 ! Zi f-U&gt;. % 146Cr Telegram R No* 61 Dated 14th (reed* 15th) July 19^8 From Butler, Tehran. To Foreign, Simla* J^o ^Z) (Rfapoatod to ^eshed No. 40.) Your telegram No. 26. I have given Head of Third Political Section the figures in Meshed eeiegranu Nos. 20 and 21 telling him that CTOvernor-tronersl v Kiioraean. and His Majesty's Consul- General had made arrangements for departure of increased number of Berberis on above lines, though I dad not know for certain tnat you would sanction Mr* Squire taking ever .larger sum even if Iranian authorities were agreeaole* 2. This official told me this morning that after talk v/ith Minister for Foreign Affairs he was drafting a paper cn the subject for submission to Council of Ministers* 3. Cn the assumption that His Majesty’s Consul-General can suitably dispose of Jarger number of Krans, I trust he may be authorised to take whatever total the Iranian Government will sanction*, 4. Despatch referred to in his telegram No. 21 has not yet been received* HS.F* P.S.V, &amp; 0. SHOT, FI. CGDNCIL,)% 1464 . Telegram R Nc, 22 Dated 15th (reed. 16th) July 1935. From Bntconsu], Me shed ^ Tec .Minister, Tehran. (Repeated Foreign, Simla No. 165.) t My telogram No. 21 (to India No. 156). Remai ning Berber! 3 numbering one hundred and eight now leaving Meshed. Deposits received total two hundred and eighty six thousand four hundred Krans• (N. F.S. D.3.F. J.S. U.S.F. &amp; U.D,) GCR.¥ i LLjCi M. S I 3. I Zt~tO~X Conf IdentBl* »o.127-10/3. / . i O^.'J His Majesty’s Consul General at Meshed presents his compliments to the Secretary to the Government of Inoie Simla in the External Affairs Department/and has the honour to to him transmit^the undermentioned documents* British Consulate General Meshed* 13th June 1938* Reference to previous correspondenee: Description of Enclosure. Mame and Da&amp;e Subject Two copies of despatch Mo.48-10/3 dated the 15th June 1938 addressed to His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires* Tehran. M&amp;tion&amp;llty of Berberis, Kash miris and Kurr&amp;mis in East Iran* ENCLOSURE IN ' ' 0 !A FOREIGN SECRETARY'S Letter No. 1 33 Dated '1 JIJL Rec eived 26 JU 1^ No.48-10/3. Confidential. British Consulate Grener&amp;l for Khoraaan, Mehsed. 13th June 1938. Sir, 1 have the honour to report that in connection ait with the expulsion of the British Berberis of Kalata Khush the Grovemor General of Khorasanhx has propounded a new theory which is of considerable interest and may raise coraplicajed issues in the near future, if, as seems likely, the present anti foreigner complex is going to result in the open expulsion or gradual squeezing out of foreie£i nationals from Iran. 2. When the nationality Laws of 1929 first began to be enforced the Sijjil Officers in East Iran practi cally forced large numbers of the poorer people who in reality had good claims to be considered as British subjects, or British protected persons such as Berberis, Kashmiris, and K Kurramis to take out sijjils and so become to all intents and purposes Iranian subjects. In most cases the persons concerned were permanently domiciled in the country and it ms not entirely unreasonable to expect that they should be required to become Iranians. Those, who, like the Berberis of Kalata Khush, owned landed property considered it on the whole advantageous to tr emselves to acquiesce in order that they might retain their land. Others had not the courage or sufficient certainty as to their legal position to resist. 3. If.Pakrevan, competely ignoring this former attitude, has now begun to claim that such people are not legally Iranians at all inasmuch as both under the Tos- His Britannic Majesty^ Charge d’Affaires, Tehran. \2 - earlier law of 1929 and under its successor special orders of the Council of Ministers are necessary before a foreigner can become an Iranian subject. He pretends th t these Iranian documents have been obtained under false pretences and can have no validity. As this apparently means at present that there will be fewer difficulties in extricating the sijjil holding pensioners of Kalata Khuah, including the two that are in prison, from their unfortunate position I have thou^it it test to moke as little coraaent as possible on this volte face. If, however, efforts are subsequently made to expel others, especially Berber!s, from the country, the situation will require further examination. A few Berber!s near Knlata Khueh, who claim thet they also have a ri^it to be considered as British nationals, have indeed already heard of the new theory ?nd have made indirect approaches to me to allow them formally to adopt British nationality and return to India. I have, of course, declined to do anything for them and the next move lies with the Iranian authorities, but I have thought it as well to report the fact for your information. 4. I am sendiag a copy of this despatch to the Govern ment of Indua under printed letter No.127. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. G,F. Squire. .Confidential. No. 126-1/4 B British Consulate General for Khorasan, Meshed. 13th June 1938. From G.F. Squire, Esquire,!-C.3., His Majesty's Consul General for Khorasan, Mesndd. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the subject of the pro posed expulsion of certain Berbens iron Iran (vide -he correspondence resting with your telegram No.932 of tl o IGt; June). 2. As there has been a considerable exchange oi telQ ( gran» between myself and His Majesty's Charge d'Affaires at Tehran, copies of which 1 have not thou^t it nocessary to send to you, it may of use if I place on record briefly xn narrative form the developments which have taken place since the issue of His Majesty's Charge d’Affairos telegram No.34 of the 28th April 1938. 3. On the 5th May second orders of expulsion ^ere served on eight of the seventeen Berberis affected, requiring fcs* them to leave Iran within ten days. Protests here and at Tehran were successful in securing an extension ot ^ is period and meanwhile on the 25th May 1 paid a visit to K&amp;lata Khuah, a village situated some fifty miles from Meshed and the home of eleven of these Berberies, in order to obtain first hand information of the situ* tion. 4. I found that having regard to he way in which British subjects are now being treated in East Iran the Berberis would be willing to leave the country provided that jl they were able to export their capital with them and provided To The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla.also that they could take with them their par 0, rk B wiio, as rts^aKta reported in ;)aragrapii 2 of my deapatch No.35 of the 16th April 1938! had t?ken out sijjils. I accordingly au^josted to the Governor General that r compronjise on this basis should be effected and on his welcoming the proposal I addressed to him a letter of which I enclose the ICnglish version. M.Pakrevon had inquired from me how these Berber!s had obtained their Iranian nationality, said that he did not believe that they’ve a legally Iranian subjects at all, and expressed the opinion that it should therefore be easy for me to re-issue the nationality documents necessary to allow them to leave the country, on which the local authorities could withdraw their sijjils. I have reported separately on this aspect of the case in my despatch No.48-10/3 to Tehran (No.127-10/3 to you) of todays date. 5. On the 1st June I again saw H. Pakregan who informed rae that he had been authorised by his Government to come to a settlement with me on the lines of ray proposal. 6. The negotiations for the financial settlement have already been fully reported and it only remains for me to add that M. Pakrevan informed me verbally a few days ago that the property had now been valued and that my estimate of Rials 1,80,000 was more or less correct. Of this sum some 96,000 rials was included in the figures of 320,000 reported in my despatch No.35 of April ixxili 16th so that the total assets according to their own estimate might unount to 404,000 rials (vide my telegram No. 118 of the 31st May 1938), In this connection I should mention also that in addition to the monthly expenditure of Rials 20,000 which I had air ady reported in the same telegram I anticipate a considerable expenditure on the coniautution values of certain pensions recently sanctioned in the orders forwarded with External Affairs Departments letters Noa. F.182-N/37 of the 15th March 1938 and F.182-N/37 of the 30th August 1937. If these, together with the coHrmatation ofMirza Mohamed Khan'a pension recam ended in ay letter No. 463/P/17 of the 29th March 1938, materialise, this special expenditure will amount to a further 60,000 rials .u;roxi raately. 7. The second condition^, on wh.ch the Berber!s set even greater store, involves the release of Subedar Muhanmad Yusuf and Havildar Nek Muhannad from jail and permission for them to leave the country with the rest. 1 have received verbal assurance* from M.Pakrevan that my wishes will be met in this respect snd though I still await definite informstion, 1 am hopeful that in this matter also a satisfactory settlement mil be possible. 8. I am sending ft copy of this despatch to His Majesty's Charge d’Affaires at Tehran under printed letter No.49. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. O.F. Squire. His Majesty's Consul General for Khorasan, Meshed.Copy of letter No. 160, dated the 26th ?&amp;.y 1938 (5/3/1317) from His Britannic Majesty’s Consul General. Seabed to Ilia r.xceliency Monsieur Faicravan, latanchir 9th, Meshed. With referenco to our converaation tiiia morning on the subject of seventeen Berberis (British subjects) who have been wanned that they must leave Iran, I write to confirm the infor mation which I have just &lt;jiven to Your PJxcellency. 2. The village of Knlata Khush together with iialf the lands of the village of Bulbul and certain additional property was purchased some 20 years ago by certain military pensioners on their retirement from the Indian Army. When the Iranian Law forbidding foreigaers to own 1. nded property in Iran came into force in 1931 these pensioners saw no alternative to becoming Iranian subjects. A number of them therefore applied for and obtained sijjils and heve since then treated as Iranian subjects. As far as I have been able to ascertain i.uch people were freely accepted as Iranian subjects by the local Sijjil Department under the Law of 1308 without any proper formalities. 3. Twelve of the seventeen British subjects who have now been ordered to leave the country are the sons of these pensioners and naturally they are most reluctant to be separated from their \ parents. If, however. Your Excellency would oe reparod to arrange that their property should oe purchased from them at a reasonable price and also would allow those pensioners who have taken out Sijjils (they are eight in number) to leave Iran ndck J !■ ' \ Mitkim at the same ^ime they would all be prepared to go vo\lunta* rily and I would undertake on their behalf that they would Hmve Iran within one month of the date of acceptance of tins proposi tion. 1 should, however, add th&amp;t two of the above mentioned parents are Muhammad Yusuf and Nek Muhammad, who, it is believed A are in prison, and whose case 1 have already mentioned to Your Excellency, It is desired that these persons also should be allowed to leave Iran with their sons. 4. As regards payment for their property; it would not be necessary for me to ask for any fareit#! exchange for these persons provided that it was understood that the Sonsulate-Greneral would be at libertyto utilize the sums paid for their expenses.1426. Telegram 3 No.59. dated 9th (reed 10th) July 1938. From........Butler, Tehran. To..,.Consul-General, Meshed. (Repeated Foreign, Simla*) Your telegram No 6 20. Number of Berberis about to leave the country by arrangement with Governor - General presumably now exceeds total, of six by-nine given m your telegram No* 10* 2, ; Pisaso telegraph estimated figures of families of total number of persons leaving (a) of British (b) of other Berberis^ (N. F,S. D.S.F. J.G. U.S.F. &amp; U.Dj M.R.1434 . Telegram R lfo.21, dated 11th (reed 12th) July 1938. From........Consul-General, Meshed. To minister, Tehran. (Repeated to Foreign, Simla. No.156). EXPPFSS. Your telegram No.59. The six Berberis reported as leaving in my demi-official letter No.20 oi June 28th took sixteen dependents total 22. The remaining eleven are now expected to take 65 dependents total V6. Oth^r Berbe-is including dependents to cal Despatch follows. (N. 1o - D.S.F, J.S. U.S.F. U.D.)IT/DIA. oT groups) 1938 P_B CY PHER OF T £ L E G R A M g I From Government of India, External Affairs Department*to Minister at Tehran and repeated by the former to Secretary of State for India. Dated Simla, 9-6 p.m., 20th July, 1968® Received 20th July, 1938, 6 p.m. 3JL71. Addressed to Tehran Noo38, repeated to Secretary of State for India and Meshed. Your telegram No .61, July 14th. Berber!a. No objection to acceptance of Krans to the extent of 290,000 instead of 180,000 as X agreed in our telegram 932, June 10thJ.P. Gibson, Esq.,, India Office. Copies to: India Office, Foreign Office, Air Ministry, Admiralty. RSiia. pat fc t .r-:. - 5 JUL1938 INDIA OFFICE!(IIP INTRODUCTION. !• This report describes the Persian attitude towards the British, as experienced by Pour Royal Engineer officers, Lieuts. A.C.Lewie^ R«A*Lind3ell f C.C.Rosher and I.H.Lyall Grunt, during a LiOtor trip across Northern Persia .froiu ^est to 2ast in iiarch, 195d. 2. None of the above officers speak Persian, and the in 4 &gt;re&amp;sion 8 are therefore necessarily superficial. G&amp;ikRAL * Altogether we spent fourteen days in Persia, from 9th Uarch to 23rd March. Contrary to our expectations we received nothing but courtesy from both officials and civilians, all of whom knew our nationality and moat of whom knew our X'f°fesalon. I give details below of several incidents which, though trivial in thei selves, are interesting as they illustrate the manner in whicn Persians were often strikingly helpful when they might well have been otherwise.INCIDifllTo . rJlC3R0Vl to (y karch - 11 karch} • (a) The; Cuetoma at KHOaROVl . No ajjpareat dlxTerenco to British subjects. Tho cusiotAS crficlals were thorough t but not objectionally oo # enquiring particularly after tilKm, firearm® and money* (b) The Pol ic e Posts . Nc apparent difference to British subjects. There were chucks about every thirty miles, and at the entrance and exit to large towna, but the police were all courteous and copied down our passports as speedily as their literacy permitted. We failed to notice the check ±oing into KA2V1N, but a policeman followed us to our hotel and without any reproach took away, copied, and duly returned our passports. TKHSftAN . (11 March - 14 March). In TSIISRAN big preparations were being made for the Shah’s birthday celebrations the following week, and possibly some anti-foreign feeling might have been expected, but neither in the streets, the shops, the bazaar, nor in our hotel, did we see any signs of it. In fact we took photographs with impunity in the centre of the town, although this is forbidden. m noted in T4HSRAN that:- (a)/■ ■(a) All street signs and shop noises etc., were in Persian writing. Roman characters are forbidden in public. (b) The sub-title in the cinemas ivere thrown on the screen in Persian and Russian, but the latter were quickly blotted out. (c) A police permit was necessary to leave the town at all, and a special one to go to the CASPIAN 3i£A (off our direct route}* TKHi&amp;AN - CASPIAN C0A3T - 3HAHRU1) . (14 iiarch - 17 fcarch). On this circuit we met with nothing but civility* We inadvertently failed to stop at the 'IN' police post at DAMAGHAN and went on - we heard no more about it. Near SABZEVAP. * (Id Larch). A wealthy and well-educated Persian from TKHrSRAN, a 'cotton-inapector , , who was driving from IShiiRAN to M33HED, v/ss strikingly kind and helpful to us* Briefly the facts were these:- About 15 miles short of 3ABXKVAF we found that our back spring was disintegrating, and as dark was coming on we looked like being stuck* However, a passing car stopped and its Persian owner came to our help. With the aid of his chauffeur we got the car sufficiently mended to limp on into SABZ^VAR* The Persian, a man or charming manner and manners, and who spoke excellent French, insisted on two of us going in his car to lighten our loan, and drove slowly behind our car to make sure that all went well, when we got to SABZiiVAR, he fixed up our rocms in the local r garage—massls' (a garage with primitive/primitive sleeping accommodation) and refused to fe© on until his chauffeur had spent some two hours patching up our car* Meanwhile he had ‘dinner* with us, and professed himself charmed with the tinned faconachie and peaches, and chlorine-flavoured tea.* He went on towarda Mi£3HED a^ter dinner. The delay caused by helping us meant an unpleasant drive for him through the snow and darkness with Very little chance of getting help at such a late hour if anything went wrong. SAB&amp;S VAR - NISKAPUR . (ly March). On this stretch we wore twice in serious trouble, and in each case the first people to come along went right out of their way to help ua. They were:- (a) a lorry-driver and his mato, apparently Persians, and (b) a 'sous-lieutenent* in the Persian Air Force. (a). Ten miles 3A3T of 3.iB2iSVAR our back spring had again given trouble, and we were busy try in* to repair it when a passing lorry saw we were in difficulties and stopped. The driver and his mate insisted on helping us, nnd after an hour*a work they got the aprin{ temporarily mended, they refused a tip. We went on, but in another ten miles had trouble again, and it was obvious we would have to put in our spare spring. This we could not do without three Jacks; our only one was broken. However, the friendly lorry appeared instantly stopped, and the driver and his mate again dug out their tools. Then, borrowing two more Jacks from another car and lorry which passed, they laboured at the spring for four hours in a biting wind, politely refusing all help from us. ilventually they/they were successful, but again would not accept any tip. (b) Nearing NISHaPUR in dark, we failed to notice a poorly-marked diveraion, ana drove onto a broken culvert of which only a narrow atrip remined. It was obvious that we should need help to /et the car off* The next car to pasa, n crowded T:;H3R JI - bus, stopped, and a * aoua-l leu tenant' (his own description) in the Persian Air Force wearing a smart dark-blue service cap and dark blue mackintosh, came over to see us. He spoke a certain amount of French and rather less Sngliah, and on hia advice I accon^anied him in the bus to the next town, NI8HAPUR, twelve miles away, to get helj). He told me he was travelling to MKSIi&amp;D, with his wife, to ^oin his unit, and 1 told him who we were. Cnee in the town he made tilings hum. He bullied the police, who constantly saluted him, unmercifully in an unsuccessful attempt to get a breakdown lorry. Then he rang up the local Road Governor and told him to produce ten men with spades, planks, and rope, and to send me a written authorisation for their use. Not till this was arranged did he and his wife sit down to supper in the local cafe, inviting me to feed with them. Before going on with the bus, he ordered the police to stop the next WiSST-bound lorry and make them take out the breakdown gang, there being no local cars available. This they duly did some two hours Inter (spent tea drinking with the police) and the road gang soon ^ot our cur back on tho road* The Air Force officer had warned rae that the road- gang were state paid and should not be tipped; they did not ask for anything and the lorry drivers who had/had brought us out refused all offers i|46) 6. NI3HA1UR * KaoKaD (fcG Warch). (a) We took several photographs of the iiosque at Ciiiar Khayyaw' s torrib y two triiles '£•£• of lfI9HAJ?UH« A custodian who saw us said casually that cameras were forbidden, but maae no attempt to confiscate the films we had taken* (b) In kJSUHiiD we stayed witn the British Consul- General and were very surprised to learn that the Persian officials there are forbidden to apeak to the I3ritiBh, and that any Persian who speaks to a member of the Consulate staff is likely to get into serious trouble with the police. One incident showed ua how strict the financial laws are. A tyre manufacturer badly wanted to accept a cheque in sterling but did not dare. (£1 sterling is worth 3C rials in the country ami anything up to 100 rials outside). v/e saw a great many soldiers in the streets at ME .SHED. , 7 * TUR .HGT~I -SKDK JAM . (22 March). received a r^th^r curious and sv/stifying reception from the Persian Amy here; whether we were being protected or watched we a not cl earn*. The facta were these. We arrived at 1900 hours at TURBCT-I-3HI2IKH JAM, wiiere there is evidently quite e larpe garrison. Roughly a battalion was housed in huts outside the town, and there were also more barracks inside. The policeman at the police- check politely insisted on guiding us to the garage- naseis, a thing unicue in our experience. Arrived the re/there we were unloading the car when a very smart Army oi*flcer appeared, clicked his heels, saluted, and shook hands with each of us in turn. He could not, or would not, speak any langua^ e but Persian, and we could not make out what he wanted. After seeing us settled down for supper he tried to say something to us, possibly asking whether we were going out again. Palling to get any intelligible ruply he saluted and disappeared. Shortly afterwards two sentries appeared with fixed bayonets and spent trie night outside our rooms. The next morning I strolled a short way down the street to buy eggs without any sign of interference. Our departure after breakfast was supervised by the same officer who had received us, and with the same politeness. Near XARIZ 123 March). The ’Out* customs, 6 miles i£A3T of KARIZ, might legitimately have held us up on a technical point, but to our surprise they Suioothed the whole affair over in the politest way. On a custom's form at KH03R0VI, on entering PERSIA, wo had mistakenly declared, among other money, a g6 Cook's Travellers Cheque, which as a matter of fact had already been spent in IRAq. Consequently we had no exchange chit to explain its disappearance (this is obligatory in PERSIA). As money laws are extremely strict, we thought we were in for trouble when asked at KARIZ where it had {&lt;ot to. However, our true but unlikely explanation was instantly accepted, and after a cursory and polite examination of our suitcase, camei’as, and films, we were allowed to proceed.CONCLUSION 1. It is possible that in PERSIA, a country where roads are poor, distances great, and care infrequent there is a certain code of courtesy among road travellers which accounts for the willing help we always received. But quite apart from the Incidents already described we were always treated civilly in the so-called Jhotels* and , garage-massi8* in which we stayed, and neither in the villages nor on the road did we detect any anti-British feeling whatsoever; perhaps rather surprising in view of the extreme poverty everywhere apparent. 2. On the CASPIAN COAST the Shah has built several luxury hotels, and is building a new sea-side road, apparently in order to attract tourists. Foreigners who come under the latter heading are therefore probably encouraged officially. 3. Anti-British propaganda, except where British officials are concerned, is either non-existent or extremely ineffective.P.Z. 4657/38. CONFIDENTIAL. VO British Consulate General for Khorasan, Meshed. Extract from Political Diary for the month of May 1938. CONSULAR BOYCOTT . 147. The boycott has not been so much in evidence during the month, but that it has by no means been A. withdrawn is shown by the following incidents. The servant of a Miss Degner, the American Superintendent of nurses at the Shah Reza hospital was arrested and taken to task by the Police for having been to the Consulate with a note for Mrs. Hart on the subject of an appointment with a hairdresser. On his release he not unnaturally refused to bring a further message. No one else could be found in the hospital brave enough to risk a visit to the Consulate and eventually Miss Degner came herself in some agitation. The Governor-General has been politely asked if such attentions are really necessary. No reply has been received. The American Mission, which holds services in English once a month has recently received information that if Persian Christians are found attending the same services as members of the British Consulate they will be arrested. The Mission has therefore reluctantly had to ask us to stay away. '(E 3278/461/34) iw* ^ rs With the compliments of His Majesty* s Representative, N.M. Butler Esc., 0. r .0., H.L. Baggallay Esc., ff The Foreign Office. (Reference: Mr. Butler’s letter of 25th larch). British Legation, Tehran.X mtM ;i Copy . (E 3278/461/34) No. 148/19/38 Copies to: Sir. Baxter Squire 6th May, 1938. Dear Sir Aubrey, Y/hile Squire was here, the most burning subject that we discussed was that of the Berberis, but we did. also discuss the possible use of publicity in connexion with our general grievances in Khorrasan - see his letter to me of the 23rd March. We agreed that there was no immediate need to resort to this, but Squire was anxious that it should be considered as a method of countering further injustices in East Iran. 2. My general feeling is that publicity as regards the ill-treatment of Iranian subjects, v/hich we believe but cannot prove to be due to past or present connexion with the British, would probably do more harm than good, and similarly publicity as regards the persecution of our Consulates, where in addition we should advertise our unfavourable position. 3. In connexion with cases of the ill-treatment of British subjects, I think that an objectively-worded publicity stands a better chance, and might do good; and I do not think that this Legation should ask you to put an embargo upon it, assuming that you would. At the same time, I do feel that British Indian traders, the individual concerned, or the Consulate supplying the information, might be made to suffer. In effect, that when our publicity is brought to the Shah’s notice, as it would be by his press-cutting organisation, he will demand an explanantiont he will be told a pack of lies; quite Sir H.A.P. Metcalfe, K.C.I.E., C.3.I., M.V.O 3 ILL A.quite possibly he will see through them but equally possibly he will react against us, and more particularly against the villainous foreign officer who has misrepresented things. 4. Squire also raised the point whether question and answer should be shown in advance to the Ministry of Foreign Aflaifs, in the hope that they would thereby be frightened or shamed into giving redress. I don f t think that this would be done regularly, but it might be worth trying once to see how it works, if there were no objection! at yonr end. The Legation would , I think, have to try to convince the authorities here that the Answer had been drawn up in Delhi.* 5. If redress were given before the date set for the Answer, the Iranian Government might in certain circumstances, e.g., if military officers or senior officials were concerned, expect the question to be withdrawn. 6. Feeling as we do that these Consulates are in an exposed position, we hope that publicity would be used with a discretion not necessary as regards all countries; and seeing that the Foreign Office are interested in our Consulates in Iran generally, I am sending Baxter, who has succeeded Rendel, a co] y of this letter, as well as to Squire. (Sgd.) Nevile sutler.British Consulnte General, Copy . (E 3878/461/34) D.O. No. 13-21/1 CONFIDEXTIAL . for Khorasan, Meshed. 23rd March, 1938. My dear Butler, In deference to the opinion expressed in your telegram No. 16 of the 11th March 1938 we attended the Governor General’s evening party at the ,f Shir o Khorshid Club” on the evening of the 16th. (Iman Reza was not long in visiting the scene of these Muharram festivities with divine dis pleasure, as the whole 'building, which lies in the main street, only a few hundred yards away from us, was completely gutted hy fire on the morning of the 17th.’). But though there were enough foreigners present to make the way in which we were shunned hy Iranians, other than the Governor General, less embarrassing than it would otherwise have been, I cannot help thinking that we have missed an opportunity of showing that we are, at least, aware of the indignities which are put upon us by the Shah's representatives, an opportunity that will not recur for a whole year. But my reasons for having made the suggestion perhaps require amplification and as I have now held this appointment for close on 18 months it may be of interest if I attempt to put my views on paper* 2. I need not mention instances in which British subjects, unconnected with the Consulate have been maltreated without any justification, except to observe that in spite of your untiring efforts on their behalf there are very few cases occurring in Meshed in which redress of any description has been obtained and practically none which can be said to have been satisfactorily settled as a result of normal diplomatic representat ions/ N.M. Butler Esquire, C.V.O., British Legation, Tehran.t representations. But the cases which cause us so much anxiety are those in which insidious indirect attacks are made on us through the medium of persons in whom we are interested, either on account of their past services or y kjt'/UC*' IUl ca^u ^ tl't VtikiL h ctMsOCi*. L* th* fin'* r (fyv) dm ua(’ b&gt; '^ouk. TUa. /Ut. Ca&amp;lq Iuuul present connection with us but whom, by reason of their possessing Iranian nationality we cannot officially protect. 3. In the former category, I include such persons as Tv oh am ed Vakili and the two military pensioners mentioned in my demi-official No. 19 dated 22nd February 1938. The friendly representations made by the Minister on behalf of Mohamed Vakili produced in Tehran a promise of sympathetic consideration and in Meshed the wretched man’s immediate deportation. We cannot take up the cases of the two pensioners for fear lest a similar fate befall them. The irony of their case lies in the fact that in order to retain possession of their landed property they renounced their own nationality (British in one case and Afghan in the other) and took out Iranian sijjils. They had been sent for to draw their pensions for the last time prior to the submission of their applications for the commutation of their pensions to which the Government of India had already agreed in pr inc iple. Jabbar Agha and Qandam vide the correspondence ending with my 68(2l / lB) dated the 24th August 1937 were presumably only allowed to go because, not being Iranian subjects, the authorities were not quite sure to what lengths they might safely go, but Meshedi Ghulam, the third of this trio, has not been heard of since his removal in chains to Tehran and his relatives are probably correct in believing that he has been done away with; and this, in spite of Pakrevans assurance to me that he would be allowed to go free provided that he did not continue to live on the frontier.We have also to consider, in this connection, the position of our other pensioners who since leaving the Indian Army have settled in Iran and who are already encountering difficulties, owing to their past connections with the British Government. Those who are British subjects are always being sent for and pestered by the tolice while those who are Iranian subjects do not dare even to draw their pensions and are liable at any moment to imprisonment with all its unpleasant consecuences. 4. Almost more difficult to cope with are the cases of those Iranians (and their relatives) who are at present in our employ and who have, in many cases, served us faithfully for many years. I have already mentioned the case of the son of Mohamed All, one of our best ferrashes. This boy, who is doing his service as a conscript was publicly denounced on parade, and then imprisoned, for having dared to visit his parents in the Consulate where he was brought up. Many other cases of imprisonment of those who have been in our employment or are suspected 6? having dealings with us have occurred in addition to those which I have reported from time to time in my letters and monthly diaries (vide my demi-official No. 60 dated the 6th September 1937 about the Nokundar case; No. 78 of October 19th and paragraph 59 of my current diary). A single further instance will suffice. On March 12th, a servant of Mrs. Hotchkiss (the wife of one of the Amiranian geologists) who had come with a note to my wife, was, in accordance with the usual routine, stopped ny the Agent on ou r gatea and roughly questioned as to his business in the Consulate. The servant was frightened and complained to his employer who in turn wrote to Fakrevan. Pakrevan replied that he was sure that there must have been a mistake and that he had ordered an iramdeiate inquiry. At the psrty on the 15t.h evening, Mrs. Hotchkiss, somewhat tactlessly tackled her host again and Pakrevan explained blandly/NMMNKmIMVHVB 7 blandly in the hearing of us all, that on that particular evening the Police had been on the look out for a wanted man in the neighbourhood and had accosted her servant by mistakeJ d. I must also mention in this connection the propaganda which is now being carried on in the army in Meshed, and I as the country’s chief enemy (vide paragraph 50 of my current political diary). 6. The stock reply which has been given to me on more than one occasion when I have complained of interference with people coming to the Consulate is that I have been misinformed and that the authorities really cannot undertake to compel people to visit us against their will. Such point blank denial of the existence of conditions which are notorious makes the whole problem peculiarly difficult. But it now seems to me that we are not merely the victims of unfriendly and rapacious local officials. Promises of incuiry made to you at Tehran almost invariably result in the victims being dealt with more severely here and in our situation becoming worse. We must therefore, I think, conclude that the conditions under which’ we suffer are directly due to the Shah’s deliberate policy of trying by every means other than a direct request to compel us to leave the country, a policy carried out, it is true, with alacrity, by his zealous supporter Pakrevan. We realised before thrt the so-called Secretary’s activities here gave some grounds for looking on us with suspicion and also knew that Daly was personally unpopular but it was hoped th‘t with the departure of these two officers there would be a change for the better. So far from this ‘being the case, the past 18 months have seen a marked deterioration in the situation and though the anti-British propaganda and insidious attempts to undermine our position and to inlure our prestige seem so far to/to have had surprisingly little effect on the attitude of those who have known us in the past, it can hardly he doubted that the younger generation, especially the military, are being greatly influenced and that such incidents as the breaking into the Zahidan Vice Consulate in August l^st and the recent commandeering of our lorry near Birland are the direct results. 7. If it were only a matter of our personal inconvenience, I should be quite prepared to put up with it, but prestige counts for so much in the East and the more we submit to the undermining of our own position the less are we able to afford to our subjects the protection which they have a right to expect. Our British Indian subjects cannot understand our supineness and are rapidly losing faith in our power to help them in any way against the local authorities; and with reason. This is, in my opinion, the most serious aspect of the present situation and leads me to recommend that we should now take action to counter the existing boycott. 8. The question of what form our protest should take is not so easy to answer. We have tried the policy of good humoured tolerance and of dignified protest jn cases where anti-British zeal has led local officials to overstep the limit between covert unfriendliness and open insult, but with no success. A threat to close our own Consulates as a protest would be only playing into the hands of the Iranians. Coercion is, of course, out of the question. Appeals to good feeling, to verbal promises previously given, or to civilised usage seem to be even more useless in Iran than in other totalitarian states, as we have here to reckon not only with the ruthlessness of the dictator but also with the duplicity and guile which the Iranian has in common with other /other orientals, as well as the ineffable vanity peculiar to himself. Unfortunately the Iranians do not seem to want anything from us in the shape of a loan or other concession which we can use as a bargaining counter. It therefore seems to me that we must devise some method of retaliation which while in keeping with our dignity will touch them on the raw. It was for this reason that I suggested absehting ourselves from the festivities on the 15th as action of this nature would have % aroused widespread comment locally and would have I think had a good effect. 9. Gould we not perhaps turn to account our knowledge of how intolerant the Shah is of criticism and how press articles of the most harmless description rouse him to fury? The Indian Government have, I believe, suggested encouraging the publication in the press of accounts of the treatment often meted out to travellers. Actual publication, would not, in my opinion, do any good, as the Iranian Government would concentrate on retaliation rather than on redress of grievances but I do think that threat of publication would be a very powerful lever to employ. It might, for instance, be feasible for a fairly detailed question to be asked in the Legislative Assembly in Delhi about the handicaps wh? ch British pensioners, British Consulates and their employees, or British subjects in general, labour in East Iran and for a draft reply to be prepared detailing some of the indignities with whicn we ^re at present being subjected and the failure of diplomatic representations to produce any improvement, believe that if the Iranians were told that a reply in this sense was under contemplation and that it would inevitably arouse considerable press comment throughout India, such a threat would do more to bring them to a reasonable .frame of mind than any other action short of coercion in some form or other/V V io other thet could he devised. 10. I apologise for the great length of this letter hut I have thought it as well to make it fairly complete in itself. The remedy I have proposed is merely a suggestion which may not he practicable hut it might serve as a basis for discussion when we meet in Tehran. 11. I am sending a copy of this letter to Sir Aubrey Metcalfe under No. 65. Yours sincerely, (Signed) G-.F. Squire.NO DISTRIBUTION Decode. Mr. Butler (Tehran) June n, 1938. D. 5.30 p.m. June h, 1938. No. 76 R. 10.30 a.m. June 12, 1938. Addressed to Meshed No. 20. 3 Government of India f s telegram No. 952 to India Office. I told head of Third Political Department this morning that proposal as regards taking over of Rials was acceptable and repeated my request for adequate delay to allow Berberis to make their arrangements. He said this was intended. 2. I assume you will give them vis-a- vis Governor- General such assistance in this question of their arrangements as you can. Repeated to India No. 46 and Foreign Office No. 76 of June 11.• Code telegram to Mr. Butler (Tehran). Foreign Office, 9th June, 1958. 7.50 p.m. No. 48 (R). vvvvvvvvvvvvvvvv (^0 1^ Your telegram No. 70 [of the 7th June: expulsion of British Berberi subjects from Persia]. There are no objections of principle to plan suggested j S't i n Jour telegram No. 62, since Persian authorities approve. It is however necessary to obtain consent of G-overnment of India since they control accounts of His Majesty’s Consulate- General. They are being asked to inform you direct of their views (see India Office telegram to Government of India repeated as No. 47 to you). 2. If Government of India agree you may act as suggested on receipt of their reply.14 6130 16473 (4) oLajl^ In any further communication on this subject, please quote N »- £ 33,5- Mjj+ and address —not to any person by name, buy to— * “The Under-Secretary of State,” Fcn-eign Office, London, S.W. i. 4020 _ &lt;??8- ! ^ THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ £ s£i(Z ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, f , 19B/. Reference to previous correspondence : fo -eZ/icx £ Sjoz/uy/jL/.. y_ 4-oi ^ Description of E?iclosure. Name and Date. Subject.r NO DISTRIBUTION. (® Decode D, R. No. 64&lt; Mr. Butler (Tehran). 1st June, 1958. 5.20 p.m. 8.15 p.m. 1st June, 1938. 1st June, 1938. i p . Z . 4 ( 90 i w . L- p W , *._) My telegram No. o2. Head of third Political Department has adverted to subject. He said Ministry of Foreign Affairs was anxious to promote settlement, and was considering sympathetically method of payment suggested. He enquired total sum involved. I gave figure from Meshed of kraus :ne hundred and eighty thousand, and though stressing need for foreign exchange, he seemed to think this not too large. Addressed to Fvcretary of State for Foreign Affairs telegram No. 64; repeated to Simla, New Delhi, telegram No. 42 His Majesty s Consul-General, Meshed telegram No. 55.NO DISTRIBUTION. (T^) Decode. Mr. Butler (Tehran). 2nd June, 1938. D. 2. 22 p.m. 2nd June, 1958. ( P-Z ; R. 5o 20 p.nio 2nd June, 1938. t f-r*. * i A » 1 1 1 r\ p No, 65. My telegram No. • CO I learn Iranian Government are ready to agree provided amount involved does not exceed kraus one hundred and eighty thousand. Addressed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs telegram No. 65; repeated to Simla, New Delhi telegram No. 44, Ills Ivkjesty’s Consul-General hashed telegram No. 37.■I In any 'further communication on this subject, please quote no. e sso 1 / 49 / 34 . r p y 0 n and address— but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. not to any person by name Foreign Office. S.W.l. 7th June, 1938. 318! E 2798/49/34 of to-day 1 s date regarding the expulsion of British subjects (Berheris) from East Persia, I am directed 'by Viscount Halifax to transmit to you, to he laid before the Marquess of Zetland, the accompanying copy of a telegram from His Majesty’s Chargl d*Affaires at Tehran reporting a suggestion made by the Governor-General of Khorassan to His Majesty’s Consul-General at Meshed to the effect that the latter should take over the krans (i*e. rials) representing the property of the Berberis who are under order of expulsion and should arrange that equivalent funds should be provided for them in India. 2. A copy of Mr. Baggallay*s letter to His Majesty’s Minister of the 17th November, 1937, referred to in paragraph 2 of Mr. Butler’s telegram is enclosed herein. 3. Assuming that the Berberis in question are to leave Persia, Lord Halifax sees no reason to object to the proposed method of dealing with their assets if it has the approval of the Persian authorities. Subject therefore to Lord Zetland’s concurrence His Lordship proposes to inform Mr. Butler that there is no objection from this point of view. 4. So/ The Under-Secretary ofji India Office - 9 JUN 1938 INDIA OFFICEI v yuc. 4. So far as the accountancy aspect of the question is concerned, it is for the Government of India to say whether His Majesty’s Consul-General should obtain rials in this way for his official requirements# But I am to express the hope that provided His Majesty’s Consul-General does not acquire more rials at any one time than he needs for his current expenses, they will see no objection. The only condition Lord Halifax wishes to make in this connexion is that no loss by exchange should as a result fall as a charge to His Majesty’s Government in the annual adjustment of joint expenditure in Persia. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, La-—^ (h t ffUuJ'27th May, 1958. D. 5.10 p.m. 27th May, 1958. R. 9.50 a.m. 28th May, 1958. No. 62. 3 ^ ^ c ^ es P a ' tc ^ No. 166, paragraph 15. Governor-General has suggested to His Majesty's Consul- General Meshed that the latter should take over krans representing property of Berheris who are to be expelled and should provide equivalent funds for them in India. He said he was going to recommend this to authorities in Tehran who he thought would agree. 2. I am aware of general ruling about assistance for British subjects desirous of exporting money from Iran (please see Mr. Baggallay's letter to His Majesty’s Minister of [? grps. omtd.] it will be possible for you to make an exception in the present case. Otherwise position of those involved in expulsion is likely to be desperate. 5. Amount involved is estimated by Berberis at 180,000 krans or £2,250. I would suggest repayments in India should be made in gradual instalments in amounts corresponding to normal requirements of His Majesty's Consulate-General. Addressed to foreign Office No. 62, repeated to India no. o9 and His Majesty's Consul-General Meshed No. 35.to itie of public ?und 6 in a contrf.tv«nXion of iereiMn regulations vie cannot a gciier^l oxceition in favour of British Cov-m^ent servants. tn« % 6 ’*»ne time, »e Jo not wirfa to forbid &lt; ltogether !^n srron^eiaent ^hereby the Legation «nd Consol* te staffs wight tnke over ri^-lp for their personal use, from Frit inn Government servant?' in nerd of sterling or rupees. It is tml-rstood th? t* you point out in your letter, tne uu* * involved &amp;re never lively to be bif nor the c?&gt;een frequent. ach Cfi.*-? would, o* couree, depend on the personal willin # ness end c p^city of some member or members of the et ff to r&gt;u cnese end use the ri It* But v-.e muet meke it 2 condition that personal cheques nnd not of icirl bills of exchange should be used* It mi nt be «urge?ted to the Staff ^ t 'U'hire that they ^igiit sr. arrt ngement of this sort in the case of 5 ‘r. C«h n who, we agree, deserves special sympathy on the strength of his previous emoloyarnt in the Indo-vuropo^n fcleyr* &gt;h L*ejv*%rtment, althoughJ. u a »3, further communication / ^* on ^nis svibjecfc, ploase quote No. E 2798/49/34. and address— not to any pri son bi/ name but to— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. /'A J. ‘V 15 JIJN 1938X 8EC. r ;E t U Sir, &gt; I ifNDU DIRECT r5&gt; e^&lt;S. (r^~i Foreign Office. S.W.l. 7th June, 1938. fa *7 * ^ J With reference to Foreign Office letter No. E 2977/49/34 of the 28th May, regarding the expulsion of Berheri British subjects from East Persia, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to transmit to you, to be laid before the Marquess of Zetland, the accompanying copy of a despatch from His Majesty* s Charge znofzr i ue !ser d*Affaires at Tehran reporting his conversations on the subject with the Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs. 2. In paragraph 16 of his despatch Mr. Butler refers to the opinion expressed by His Majesty’s Consul-General at Meshed that the only action likely to be effective in preventing the expulsion would be a threat to expel from India an equal number of Persian subjects resident there. It appears from Government of India telegram to the India Office of the 4th May, a copy of which was enclosed in India Office letter No.PZ 3170/S8 of the 5th May, that the Government of India are disinclined to resort to such retaliation. Mr. Butler, too, in his telegram No.48 of the 29th April, a copy of which was sent to the India Office under cover of Foreign Office letter No. E 2549/49/34 of the 4th May, advances important considerations against such action. It is to be noted in this connexion that Mr. Butler's telegram was sent at a later date than his despatch under reference, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office. REGS. POL. DLPT. - 8 JUN 1938 INDIA ofFICE ———■ ■■ —Ml I I ■ ■ ■ i III ‘reference, and therefore presumably represents his considered views on the subject. 3. Lord Halifax is impressed by the considerations advanced by Mr. Butler and is himself of the opinion that it would be undesirable, in the present case, to take retaliatory action of the kind suggested against the Persian (zovernment. I am : Sir Your obedient Servantm l/iy Lord, *•*“•“* I have the honour to enclose copies of a despatch from His Majesty's Consul-General for Khorassan on the subject of the threatened expulsion from Iran of a number of Berberis,some of them of British and some of Afghan nationality. At the time v/hen Hr. Squire sent this despatch,formal steps had not been taken by the local authorities to carry out their threat,but on the 9th April Mr. Squire reported by telegraph that he had been informed by the Chief of Police at Meshed that the latter, Tinder instructions from the Governor-General of Khorassan,had issued formal orders for the ex nilsion. 2. I immediately telegraphed to the Government of India reporting the substance of Mr. Squire*s despatch and telegram above referred to,and invited attention to the correspondence which took place in 1935 regarding the threatened expulsion of Berberis in Khorassan and which terminated in Hie Majesty’s Minister’s despatch to the 1 bGO j2 Foreign Office Iio.419 of the 2nd October, 1935. I pointed out that the present case contrasted favourably with the circumstances of 1935,inasmuch as some explanation of the deeision^to expel had been given,and the local authorities had in the first instance offered to pay those affected the value of theiprproperty if they would agree to go quietly. I added that there was no doubt but that the local authorities in Khorassan are still nervous since the /Incident The Right Honourable, The Yiscount Halifax K.G. etc., etc., ,G.C.S.I., etc- 2 incident at the Meshed Shrine; that the Berheris proV-ihly do present in dress etcetera a contrast embarrassing to the local authorities,and that it cannot be argued that from the strictly legal point of view,the Government ore not acting within their rights. Nonetheless I agreed vTith Mr. Squire that the drastic action xvhich was being taken justified representations to the authorities in Tehran,and I was seeking an interview with the Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs. 2. in the meantime I telegraphed to Kie Majesty’s Consul-General for Khorassan to enquire whether the Berberis were appealing in accordance with the procedure promised by the ! inistry for Foreign Affairs - please see Mr. Seymour’s 2 (o'! GI despatch Ho.80 of the 2nd March,193?. This procedure was in fact that contemplated in article 12 of the law concern ing foreigners in Persia of which copies were sent to the Foreign Office by Sir Robert Clive in his despatch No.26o of the 30th May, 1931. I have since learnt that the necessary formal appeals were sent in on the 17th April. 4. On the 14th April I handed Monsieur Adi the aide- memoire of which copies are enclosed herein. After he had read it,I added some remarks. He would,! said,see that I had alluded to discussions in 1935. Monsieur Soheily and His Majesty’s late Minister had achieved a real Improvement in i;ast Iran, and in the particular case of the Berberis that had then arisen,they had succeeded in avoiding any wholesale deportation. 5* Monsieur Adi would be aware,from His Majesty’s Minister* s talk with him on February 27th - please see my ^'7^7 despatch Ho.109 of the 23rd March - that Mi*- Seymour felt that the situation was now less good. It would,I thou^it, /be«* 3 • be e very great pity if this deterioration were allowed to spread to British Berberis. 6. I was really apprehensive of the effect upon the Government of India,if on the top of the situation repre sented by Mr. Seymour,there followed the deportation of l a considerable number of British subjects without specific accusations actually proven. I mentioned that in the 1935 dossier I had found a record of a talk at Simla with the Iranian Consul-General in connexion with the possibility of deportation. 7. in these cii’oumstanees ,1 wondered whether come less drastic solution might not be found,and one involving less publicity than a deportation. I realised,as did His Majesty*s Consul-General at Meshed,that the wearing of their antiquated dress by these Berberis might be embarrass ing to the local authorities,and I mentioned Mr. Squired suggestion to the Governor-General of Khorassan that they might berhaps be persuaded to wear something more up-to-date. In any ease I asked Monsieur Adi to speak to the prime Minister,who is now acting in the absence of a Minister of the Interior,and with Monsieur pakrevan now in Tehran* Wholesale deportations were undesirable in principle;in this case deportation would mark a further deterioration in the situation in East Iran,and if Monsieur Schelly and His Majesty 1 s then Minister had been able to *woid it in the strained time that followed the affair at Meshed in 1935^ I was confident that it could ve avoided in these tranquil times,when incidentally the adjacent country,Afghanistan,had become a friend and almost an ally by Treaty. 8. Monsieur Adi promised to speak to Monsieur Jam and Monsieur P&amp;krevan. As regards immediate action we agreed / thatt«p that the first step was fox* the Berberis to obtain tirae by appealing in the m&amp;merpfcescribe&amp;. vers&amp;tion of the 27th February about the treatment of Hio llajesty’s Consulates in East Iran* Since that talk,a pensioner who hah been imprisoned and deprived of tlis employment at the Meshed Department of linanoe.aud on whose behalf we had asked the good offices of the ministry of Foreign Affairs last December,had been expelled under police escort to Salsawar where presumably he had no means of getting a living. This was most disappointing. £here had ale ) been an incident connected with the Consulate- General bus about which X had spoken to the Director-General of the political Department. (This was the incident reported (sCqj &amp; a y despatch Ho* 113 of the 24th March). Last, but by no means least,was the fact that the Soviet Consulate-Go’'^ral wan about to close at Meshed,which introduced a radical change into the position. 10. I reminded ?x. Adi that he had promised His Majesty 1 » Minister to apeak to the Chief of .police about the watch kept over His Majesty’s Consulates and to urge that local authorities should not in their zeal exceed what could sanely be regarded as a w juste milieu”. Had there been any reply from General Kukhtavi that i could convey to Hr. Seyraour in England and to the Foreign offices in London and Hew Delhi? 11. &amp;• Adi replied to the effect that withdrawal of the Doviet Consulate-General was indeed an important rew factor; he implied that it was a favourable one, and he said that he had judged it better to defer his talk with the Chief of Foliee until the Soviet Consulate-sen 9 I then reverted to His Majesty’s Minister’s con-had become a tiling of the past. 12. I asked M. Adi to talk to M« p&amp;kreran also while he was in Tehran. I thou^jht that the Berberis* case was a good illustration. Instead of proceeding at once to an order oi expulsion^ would it not have boon better if the local authorities had made use of the very ready good offices of Hr. Squire, asking him to use his influence to • eruuade the Berberis to be accommodating, i concluded by repeating that the Oovernment of India felt that hitherto tneir efforts to improve the atmosphere in saat Iran had met with very little response. 13. Subsequent to my interview with the Actirg Minister for Foreign Affairs I went to see the Afghan Charge d'Affair, ia vi.w of the fact that Afghan subjects were affected by the expulsion orde r, as well as British, fhe fhargi had no Information, either ea to the fact or as to the motive behind it; but as the Afghan Ajabaaeador Is now in Kabul, the news may have been telegraphed direct there from Meshed. 14. since ay talk with Konsieur Adi, I hare received further reports from Mr. fquire to the effect that the number of Berberis, British sub.eots, against whom aotioos of •xpulsion have been issued, is seventeen. The total number to be expelled, including dependents, is however for these notioes of e..pulaio a is a groundless suspicion that many Berberis are in secret British employ, and that the Governor-General. E statements about drees reported in Ms despatch of the 6th April ^e merely an excuse. 15. Mr. Squire-s reports show that, in addition to their agricultural pursuits the^-p S ’ tl0se are large fiook owners, and that some of them are „■&lt;» „ are men of oomparatire /substauc6. subst&amp;nce* Their total assets appear to aaou t to over 320,000 rials, equivalent to £4,000, covering houses, flocks, orops and other assets. Technically no land is involved, as on the introduction in 1931 of the law forbidding foreigners in Iran to possess landed property, the lands owned by these Berber^ were nominally sold to relatives who were Iranian subjects. If the expulsion orders are eventually proceeded with, it is manifestly unfair that those affected should not be allowed to export their capital. This is a matter which I Y/ill in that event take up with Honsieur Adi. 16. In his latest telegram, repeated to the Oovernment of India, Mr. Squire expresses the opinion that the only action likely to be effective in preventing this and future unjust treatment of British subjects would be a threat to expel from India an equal number of Iranian subjects resident there. I shall have an opportunity of discussing the case orally with him in the course of the next few days, and I propose to see Honai e\r Adi again before the breathing space provided by the formal lodging of appeals has expired. I am sealing copies of this despatch to the Secretary to the Government cf India in the internal Affairs Bepartmoat and to Kis Majesty’s Consul-General for Khorassan at Meshed. I have the honour to be, ISy lord, Your lordship’s most obedient, humble Servant &lt;-4* )-w-y. -r * iii ltiaih OOitaul&amp;'w# G iai*! ti^n Coiiaulati# Qeuvr&amp;l for hucriitt&amp;n, «nahe4* l^o 38- 1/4$ S . /, j 6th April 1»ZH. on April 4th from 30 to 40 jberheria, half of whoz&amp; wer« cf Afghan and the re^uaiDder of British nationality suriraoned to the Aanieh office in forbad froa their villages to the itast of tofihedf nei?r the . hah*3 e^taten of Varinan and were then told that they could no longer remain in Tran 'but that if thej 1 would agree to go quietly the Iranian Government would pay the value of their property which they should declare. The Berberia concerned declined the official terras and c&amp;ae in a body to their Gonsul&amp;tes for advic©• General on the 5th. #.pakravan told me that ay information was correct; that it had been dec if*-* be undesirables and that the offer of compensation h&amp;d been his own ide&amp;« as forcible expulsion was naturally resented and night create diplomatic unpleasantness. If th© terms offered were not voluntarily accepted formal steps for their expulsion would be taken in accordance with the i fi^ul&amp;txons that had been drawn up after the 1935 disturbances.(Circular .Despatch Wo 9 of aid teroh 1937). a.rakrevau explained that he had not, of course, seen the dossiers of the individuals but generally speaking the presence in the rural districts ox' a nuraber of foreign nationals who refuses I accordingly interviewed the Governor to expel certain Berberis who were considered Asked the reauon for this decision tooonpljr with th« Ir&amp;nl&amp;n r&amp;gulutionsi x’e^arding thw wearing of Trilby ftata and tho unveiling of woiaen w«8 a source of enlmrr&amp;ssftent to the administration and could no longer he tolerated* the Government set great store by the enforcement of their regulations and drastic action was necessary to overcome the obstinacy of the local peasantry* 4* I pointed out that the wholesale expulsion of these British subjects who are closely relatea to the Iranian numbers of their clan and who in many eases have now no other hones would be a serious step and as^ed whether some compromise would not be possible* It is understandable that the somewhat truculent defiance of the local dress regulations in whioh foreign nationals are reported to indulge is emterra*sing to the authorities and I*sited whether for example it would be possible to allow these people to regain on oondltion that in tne villages at least they adopted the prescribed costumes* i'&amp;icrev&amp;tt said that this mist depend on the dossier of each individual but admitted that the suggestion had not ooourrod to him and might be feasible. He promised to give it his considerat ion • Titero the matter rests for the moment* &amp;• I do not know* if, in fact, the question of dr ewe has any tiling to do with the real reason for the action proposed or whether it is only a plausible excuse* hut I aid not thin* it wise, in the absence of instructions, to mxe any definite protest against the decision to expel these persons from Iran especially as no definite * &amp; tepa to this end have yet been taken; but it does not sew to ae that such drastic action is in any w&amp;y justifiable* further, if the expulsions are permitted to pass without protest it seeaa notTo t • ur:3lively th&amp;t the polloy will be exUsnaect first tc* 3ert&gt;erlc in Soaked itselx % stid eubae^uccUy %o nil iixiUah subjects in this area* r '* I tniat therefore that it nill l&gt;e hOPL-l'Slo to rm(re if, clear V„&gt; the Iranian Oovemronf et fhr, outset thrt HUoh a course of action on their part would he nost unwise* a threat of publicity for the whole affair coupled if poeatble with e warning that retaliatory notioz with rafmrti to Iranian subject a in India would have to b* seriously oonniAored would probably have the effect of asking then proceed with oeution. If nothing in dona, on at least if ta« poltoy to be ourauod is not definitely decided upon until orders of expulsion have actually been passed it will then bo too Into for affective action, the feer of unpleanent couse(,uonceB aay prevent the authorities frcr. taking hasty action, whereas post f ft eto rate nation though It *ay prevent further expulsions can only .■sake the thole probleu more compileatad. * ~ *111 not, fail tc keep you irtforaea, by telegram if nececaary, of further developments, bat I have thought it as wail to report on the situation immediately as the Oovemer Uenwral expects hiaaelf to bo leaving for Tehran toaorrow and a timely earning my serve to ** situation. 6 * « i iJertdltjf a copy of tills despeteh to the Qcrertmmt of India under Printed Lett«r lio KOe j have th© honour to be, air, /our iooat ob©al©nt serY&amp;nt, Hla Uritannic i^je 96&gt; . s Charge d’Affairee^* TJKK^AR .Mail , fidential. * f p. Z WT!.7 A 4 External Affairs Department, A l Simla, , - - * / rt 1 . D.0.iio.F.238-N/3|. 9 T ,8 June 163 z,. Expulsion of Berberie of British nationality from Iran. hi- 3^81 Please refer to your demi-official letter No.p.Z.3170/38, dated the 6th Hay 1933,1 enclose herewith a copy of our letter to the Chancery, British Legation, Tehran, No .Z.369-11/35, dated the 6th September 1935 and enclosure as desired. To J.P.Gibson, Ssquire, Political Department, India Office, London, S.D'.l. S£tt&gt;. Ml. BEPt. - 7, JUN 1938 INDIA OFFICE OdL S c. t, )Copy of a letter No.?.369-N/35, dated ^the 6th September 1935, from the Foreign emd ] } olitical Department, to His Majesty's Legation, Tehran. ./ill you please refer to the correspondence ending with His /..ajesty’s Minister’s telegram Ho.62 dated the 29th August 1935 to His 'Hajesty’s Consul General 'Hashed regarding expulsion of Berberis. /e enclose a copy of a note recorded by the Foreign Secretary on the 31st August 1935 after an interview with the Iranian Consul General here.mm* Copy of^note recorded by the Foreign Secretary on the 31st August 1935. In my interview with M. Nourzad this morning, I said that we have been greatly concerned over the reported indiscri minate expulsion of British Indian subjects from Meshed, and would be glad if M. Nourzad could let me know how the matter now stood. M* Nourzad replied tnat on his addressing the Iranian G-overnment in the matter after his interview on the subject with Mr. Garoe some days ago, he was informed that only those persons were being expelled who had been implicated in the riots. I remarked tnat my information was that the Meshed police themselves had explicit^ admitted that no British subjects v/ere so involved, and that I believed that this view was accepted by the Tehran authorities also; if so I presumed no British y.Jbe//ec£ Indians Berberis at all would be »omooli-ed. LI. Nourzad then asked me two questions: (1) what were the numbers of British Berberi subjects in Meshed and neighbourhood, and (2) whether I heard of any fresh expulsions since his interview with Mr. Garoe. I replied the numbers were small, and on the second point that I had heard of no fresh expulsions, but that on the other hand we had not heard of the withdrawal of trie notices, and that we would be glad to receive an assurance that no fresh action was contemplated. I adaed that I hoped the matter could ( I now be regarded as satisfactorily settled, as otherwise the G-overnment of India would have to ask themselves why if their subjects were being expelled without reason from Meshed, they ; should continue to allow Iranian subjects in India as at present ) to carry on their normal occu &gt;ations without interference or || question. A copy of this note should be sent to the Tehran Legation. bd/- J.G-.Achison,\7 tc k ' ^ - */ Priva t e Seo^tary , ^ The Secretary of State might like to see this note about the boycott of our consulates in E. Persia, and also the paper below in regard to the incident of the commandeering of the Consul-General ! s bus. Difficulties have also, I think, been experienced in taking up the cases of aggrieved British subjects. Col. Daly, who was at Zabul (Seistan) and Meshed from 1929 to 1936, is now in London. (He returns to India on 19th May to take up the post of Political Agent, Western Kathiawar.) Perhaps the Secretary of State would like to see him. gg &gt;2r,Minute Paper (P.Z.3758/31). (P.Z.872/33) 'k’* a-A-tw Uf^nU i/' \U&gt; ^0 t &amp;y*t\&gt;l*lC4 ( P.Z.4765/37) (P.Z.80 &amp; 397/38) J53&gt;1 Department. Boycott imposed by the Iranian Authorities on relations of Iranian Subjects with H.M.'s Consulates. 5853 5000 3.37 The boycott, which is becoming increasingly vexatious in East Persia, is of several years' standing. It is directed against intercourse with all foreign representatives and not only against the British Consulates. In 1931 it was reported that the Shah had forbidden any intercourse between Persian military officers and foreigners - an order which was repeated with added emphasis in 1932 - while late in 1932 the Shah seems to have issued instructions that no Persian subjects, save in exceptional circumstances, should visit • any oreign Embassy or Legation.^, A succession of ! [ ‘ ' '** | irritating incidents resulting from these orders was reported by H.M.'s Consular Officers. The instructions were not even relaxed in connexion with the entertainment given by H.M.'s Consuls a year ago in celebration of the Coronation. The situation, thanks no doubt to the officious zeal of the local police, seems to be particularly bad in East Persia and notably at Meshed; for example, a Persian from whom the Consul General at Meshed had hired a garden for his family was arrested and charged with having dealings with the Consul-General a constant watch is kept on the Consulate-General and all callers are watched and questioned, even Persian ladies being followed by the police into their homes and interrogated; while some Persians who had been playing football in the Consulate grounds at Zabul were arrested, detained for 30 hours, and only released on giving security that they would not again enter the Consulate. Representations were made to the Persian Government by H.M.'s Minister last November and December (see the aide-memoires at 'X* an6 l v l wh-? « na Y which summarise the more importantIt P.Z.2787/38 important incidents complained of) and again in March, before he departed on leave (see the despatch at , Z I ). is perhaps too soon to say that Mr* Seymour's latest representations have had no effect. The usual Persian defence has been that the principal objects of their suspicions in the matter of contacts are the Russians, but that it is necessary to treat all foreigners alike. If that is so, the Persian case has now been weakened in Meshed by the withdrawal of the Soviet Consulate-General, and it may be that this will result in steps being taken by the Persian Government to check the excessive zeal of the police at Meshed. If, however, as seems probable, the real cause of the whole trouble is the acute xenophobia of the Shah, it is doubtful whether any improvement in the situation is to be expected* For years past the Persians have been very suspicious of the posting of political officers with military rank to the Consulates staffed by the Government of India. Obviously with the existing cadre of the Indian Political Service it would be extremely difficult to arrange that only civilians were sent to these posts. But the posting of an I.C.S. officer to Meshed has had no effect in mitigating the Persian boycott, as Mr. Seymour complained in the representation he made last November. (P.Z.80/38)Co(148/17/38) 22nd April, 1938 - i f! Dear Sir Aubrey, The Squires arrived yesterday evening; our bag has to close today which has consequently been a very full one, and there has been no time at all yet for a discussion with Squire of the East Iranian troubles about which he has written and telegraphed. I feel, however, that you may expect something from me by this bag, and am therefore writing the present letter before having had any detailed talk with him. 2. More particularly in his letter to me of the 23rd March, (No. D.O.13-21/i), and his telegrams about the Berberis, there are broadly three subjects raised:- (a) ill-treatment of Iranians at some time in our employ; (b) anti-British policy, with special reference to our Consulates in East Iran; and (c) ill-treatment of British subjects. 3. The persecution of those in category (a) causes us, as it does him, much anxiety, not to say indignation and exasperation. It is an essential part of the Shell’s policy to instil patriotism into his subjects, including the principle • T that Iranians should serve Iran. His.local officials are therefore no doubt fulfilling his wishes when by their persecutions they make it brutally clear, for the instruction of the present generation, that Iranians of the older generation who draw rewards for having served the foreigner now deserve to suffer. I believe that generally speaking we think it in our own interest that the Shah should pull his countrymen out of their recent slough of subservience to the foreigner, and that if ex-employees of Kussian Governments were made to suffer we might even regard this as wholesomeI Of/ Sir H.A.P. Metcalfe, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., M.V.O. New DelhiOf course we have an interest and a tradition to defend all who have served us well, hut in this matter we are unfortunately not, in the last resort, in a x^osi-tion to insist on redress; also I fear that we should delude ourselves if we thought we could 'shame” the Iranian Government into 'behaving decently. Therefore residing as these Iranians do permanently in Iran, it is extremely difficult to see what we can do for them, except in such minor ways as letting pensioners commute their pensions as speedily as possible, and continuing our efforts to get a less suspicious atmosphere. 2. As regards (b). Squire may well be right in believing that the boycott is directly due to a deliberate policy on the x^art of the Shah of using every means, except a direct request, to compel us to leave the country. At any rate I have no doubt that we are up against a definite policy of the Shah* s to curtail British influence especially in East Iran as part of his 'Iran for the Iranians'. 5. But, as we see it here, this policy is as much anti-foreign- Government as anti-British. For instance, notwithstanding the (CSijtt Pact of Saadabad and last summers Treaty of Friendship, the Iraqi Consulate at Kermanshah, and I think at Tabriz also, is under 4 quite as strict surveillance and boycott as our own. Whereas the new officer supplied by our Air Ministry to the Iranian Government to look after the Hawkers’ Aircraft factory here has been received very well; nor have the established British interests here much hostility to complain of. I think too that the breaking into the Zahidan Vice-Consulate (for which the soldier 'I i^ldvjwas severely punished), and the incident of the Consulate-General bus to which Squire refers, are capable of a less general and hostile interpretation. moIlien t the withdrawal of the Soviet Consulate- General from Meshed seems an important new factor. Adi, the Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs, as reported in my official despatch/despatch to the Foreign Office No* 156, of which a copy, under No. 77, goes to you in this 'bag, certainly implied that the Soviet withdrawal was a favourable factor for us, and Squire has mentioned to me a local comment to the same effect. On the other hand Pybus, our late Military Attache and veteran here, shared Squire’s view of the Shah’s policy to the extent of believing that the Imperial Government would not long resist the temptation to follow the Soviet example of reducing the number of foreign Consulates. My feeling is that the present position, complicated by ’’Indian” Consuls and their military titles, has possibilities of improvements, but is a delicate one, and that a threat of publicity would be dangerous. A threat, if made, would have to be carried out. 7. As regards (c) British Subjects, we are on stronger ground. I agree with Squire that it would be most undesirable that British-Indian Subjects should lose faith in our power to help them. I did, however, gather from the icnow ledge able Trade Assistant at Zahidan when I passed through there last December that the Indian community had not much to complain of, and that diplomatic-cum-consular representations had produced a fairly satisfactory state of affairs. And I doubt whether it is desirable that British Indians should expect very strong assistance from us if they take the risk of setting themselves in dress or deportment conspicuously against the new and dictatorial regime here. 8. It is on behalf of British-Indian subjects - these would include incidents not purely Consular, like the Consular bus, as well as the Berberis - that publicity of an objective kind (which we have already hinted at to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs) seems most hopeful. But I forbear to comment yet either on the threat of publicity or on retaliation. (Sd.) N. Butler.14 6130 16473 (4) r &gt; * rj jnication on this subject, please quo tny person by bnfmk, but ‘&lt;7 In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. and address —not to any t “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. f P 5/ 78 j I t ^ *&lt;r 1KD1A DtHOT 1 THE Under-Sec ret ary of Sta^e for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to J jC* and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop V of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ^ -Zf', 193 t. (laj^k r 4 3 c? 5” Reference to previous correspondence : Jo. stidz, 7 ^. S'+it/ ss-. tp . ^ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^ 1 Jo r- Similar letter sent to181 British Legation, 7th May, Tehran, 1938. His Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to f 1 His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Daportat ions from Iran. Referenee:- Tehran deep.£jo« 156 of ZZ/l/ZQ. Tehran deep* Ho.90 to G* of I* dated 7/5/38. Tehran tele* no*37 to G.of I. dated 7/5/33*In&amp;ia* | ia eoiuiluolou to toll mo. olour of the warnlog given to Meneiew i our&amp;oA la 1996 at Simla in eo&lt; aectton with a previous order of expulsion served on Berfeeris $ reoo^aising that la the rrosent o^e ootnpe^e at ion had been offered &amp;4 a reason given. 3. Monsieur Anaari said that, spoakin, without ar&lt;y knowledge of the subject,he felt cure that the dimculUee created by the levherie drees could be surmounted by their agree! .&amp; to ohaage It,and ho preeilsed to on what 1 had a&amp;ld to hi x to 2:etu»ieur Adi next day. days later,at a reception,he toi.d me that he had discharged his proaiee, arid that he felt eoufldent that a eatiefaertery so .ution oould be fouiid. ly conversation at the Ministry of Foreijv-# Affairs to-dsy.reported in my tele^am 1 o*37 t i»eke» it all to clear that this optlmima was ill-fou ded. 4. fh9 euggeetion An sgr telegraw o«34 that lan/^a^e simiiai* to that used by P,r• oheson to onoieur xouraad in 15136 should ax^ia be employed,was put forward largely with a view to safeguard other British subjects in Khormmmm in the future.about which Mr* Squire had expressed s&amp;rleue aisgivliigs. 6 . » feel that in my twe conversations with : ouaieur Adi already reported,In this talk with monsieur Aaeari 9 end the conversation at the Ministry for foreign Affaire to day,! have ge&amp;e &amp;e far as the levercmnt of India would wish. 6. i m sending copies of this despatch to Hla Majesty*© rineipal Secretary ©f State for Forelga Affaire and to His Majesty’s Consul-General for horaeean. 1 have the honour to be, By Lira. Bstrcue&amp;e, Tour AxceXlency* s most obedient Servant, i *) i *vlAe autler *From H.M. Ministi COPY OF TELEGRAM. To GOVEENMtHT....DB....IimiA.. No SL. L %1 . Y pate 7th..M.a y.» 1938, i * 'b -v j Addressed to Government of India, No. 37; repeated to Khorassan (at Meshed), No. 28. Copy hy bag to Foreign Office. ^ Your telegram No. 21. ^ I elicited from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs today that while decision on Berberis’ appeal had not yet been taken it is intended that expulsion reason was not the only one. Iranians in India if there were further expulsions ofy any further communication on this subject, please.quote ' ^ I No - 2 jy/ /ay//$&lt;{, . 1 Mid address—&gt; 10 / to any person by name&gt; but k&gt;--/ “ * be Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs pre compliments to ^ and, by direction of tbe Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop V of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ^4^ ,193 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. &amp; isO Name and Date. Subject. /Usfux^ f. SFifC ^/dept.'] I — - _ ;' r . u 1 17! MAY 1938 f ' INDIA OFFICE f l, : : : Similar letter sent toCopy. f'p. (E 2371/2371/34''. &gt; . J 4 '—v &gt; 1 l ■ Extract from Khorramshahr trade report for 1937-1938 . INDIANS . On the whole, the Indian Community engaged in trade in Khorramshahr and Ahadan have not suffered undue hardship. Considerable difficulty has been encountered in obtaining visas to enter Iran, restricted visas valid for one month only and precluding them from work, being issued by the Iranian Consul at Karachi. This has borne particularly heavy on men long established in business, who have been to their homes on holiday.FiLb copy 1 ! 9 ? ? | IT/CWP/CVD. (102 groups) (OOPIKS CIx^CULATICD ) 1831 (Pt. 1 of 755) D - JLILJ—P H E H OP T E L E G P A M . From Government of Jndia, External Affairs Department,to Tehran,and repeated by the former to Secretary of State for India. Dated Received Simla, 4-th May 1938. 2.15. p. m. 4th Lay 1938, XXX 'SlCoS IMPORTMT . Addressed to Tehran, number 21, repeated to oecretary of State and Consul-General, Meshed. Your tele; rsun No.34, April 29. Berberis. Government of India are averse to Beroeris being made a bone of serious contention with the Iranian Government as they appear to be British subjects in •3S little more than name; c.f. Daly’s note forwarded v/ith Tehran Legation endorsement of 10th August, 1935. They would, perhaps, be well advised to renounce their British nationality and become Iranian subjects. 2 * As &gt;' however, they are still British subjects Government of India are glad that a protest has been made. 3. With regard to threat of retaliation they would suggest that, if you consider it desirable, you should make the same vague threat to the Iranian authorities as Acheson made to tne Iranian Consul General in 1935, vide my letter quoted in paragraph No.4 of your telegram. .. Durr. 3 - 5 MAY 1938 INDIA OFrir*?,SECRET THK/MA, (80 groups) !Sd2o (COPIES CIRCULATED) DECYP H ER 0? TELEG RAM,, Prom Gc';’eminent cf India, External Affairs Department to Tehran and repeated hy the former to Secretary of State for India* Dated Simla, 4th M a y? 1938o Received 4th May,, 1938* 3 poim, XXX P.2 3^t/ Jg IMPOHTANT_ 756o Second and Last Part* This would perhaps be more effective than a repetition of the warning to Nourzad who In ary ease is under orders cf recall, f and has not come up to Simla, 4* If it were found necessary to implement the threat, the Government cf India would not contemplate the expulsion cf classes mentioned in the last paragraph of Squire p s telegram No,10, April 16th as this might be detrimental to the interests of Indian traders In Imho They might perhaps tatee action against Iran Gypsies who frequently give trouble in Indian 5o Government of India would deprecate any , argument based on the suggested commercial agreement, as they consider it unlikely that they will favour such an agreement in any case.2 W DISTRIBUTION* Decypher. D. 11.00 a.m., 29th April, 1958. R. 9.00 a.m., 50th April, 1958. No. 48. Addressed to India No. 54. My telegram No. 55. I have also spoken to Afghan Charge d'Affaires again. He was still by no means completely informed but was aware that fifteen heads of family took part in [grp. undec.]. He has so far taken no vigorous action here. As regards reasons for expulsion he said question of dress had also been quoted in case of Afghans; he thought there might be something in this but felt there was probably contributory motives also. He was unable to say whether any of these Afghans had previous connexion before his [grp. undec.] in India. 2. I have discussed with Mr. Squire suggestion of possible retaliation made by him. He still believes that threat of this is the only way to prevent expulsion of Berberis and that prevention is desirable in the interests of British prestige as well as necessary to prevent similar action before long against British subjects residing at laora. I agree that a serious threat of this kind might well prevent present expulsion orders from being carried out. But on other hand: (a) .to • • • 2. (a) The Berberis if left here as a result would almost inevitably find their lives made a burden. (b) Iranian Government are within their legal rights in expelling. (c) Iranian G-ovemment have this time given a reason, inadequate but plausible which Mr. Squire, Afghan Charge d'Affaires and I believe to be genuine though not the only or principal reason. (d) It might be difficult to adduce corresponding reason in cases of Iranians to be expelled from India and to make corresponding (and perhaps more unfavourable) offer to buy out their property. (e) Similar order against Afghans makes it incautious for us to argue either that action against Berberis is being taken as a result of their previous connexions with army in India or that British subjects are being discriminated against. (f) It is impossible to foresee ultimate effect of retaliation on general relations between Iranian G-overnment and G-overnment of India and His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom. 3. It is true that Iraqi Minister is convinced that it was his threat that was effective in connexion with Jews but subsequent information from other sources suggests that this was by no means the only reason for revocation of expulsion order in this case. 4. In view of the above considerations I am inclined to think the best step now to safeguard future might be repetition at Delhi of warning on the lines of that conveyedV to Iranian Consul-General in Trieste, please see Foreign and Political Department's letter to Tehran Chancery of September 6th 1955. Commercial agreement which has been tentatively proposed to you seems to offer additional material. Repeated to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs No. 48 and His Majesty's Consul Meshed No. 27. Kci-uJ- U. uc,J 3 2 8^. jJl'STRIBUTIQ i^ Decode and Decypher. Mr. Butler (Tehran). April 29th 195b. Do 11.0 u.m. April 29th 195b. Rc 6.30 p.m. April 29th 195u. No. 46. n R u begins. My despatch No. 156 nov/ on its way to you contains report of expulsion order issued (grp. undec. ] in Khorassan against 17 Berberis who are British subjects (though total number involved with dependents is 69) and also of rny representations to Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs. Similar order has been issued against a number of Afghan Berberis. 'R' ends. 2. His Majesty's Consul General at iliorassan considers only action likely to be effective in preventing this expulsion and others later would be threat of expelling from India a like number of Iranian subjects. Government of India having asked for my views on this suggestion I have addressed to them a report repeated in my immediately following telegram. 3. Report on Iraqian Minister's action in connexion with Jews referred to in paragraph 5 of my telegram No.54 to India was sent to you in my despatch No.140.NO DI S TRIBUTION Decode. Mr. Butler (Tehran). 29th April, 1933o D. 11.00 a.m. 29th April, 1938. R. 10.00 a.m. 30th April, 1938. No. 47. (t II HU IIII It till ft Hit II II .1 It II It II H It II It II It H Addressed to India No. 33. Your telegram No. 19. I have seen Acting Minister for Foreign affairs again. I enquired whether he had anything further to tell me and was told that he had spoken to Governor-General and that legal procedure must take its course. I then said that since my last interview I had learned that of seventeen Berberis affected five were pen sioners of army in India whilst other twelve 'were sons of pensioners. I feared that you were certain to suspect that action taken against them was due to this circumstance unless specific charges were brought and proved. 2. Monsieur Adi said apoeal would be considered by Ministry of the Interior and I therefore asked him to tell the Prime Minister what I had said about these men being British pensioners. He promised to do this without delay. 3. I added that I had just learnt of the informal suggestion made at Delhi of a commercial agreement between Iran and India. It would be the worst possible prelude to any such proposal if sixty- nine British subjects were expelled on a general orderwithout proven charges. Repeated to Secretary of State No. 47, His Majesty's Consul- General, Meshed, No. 26.(for India Office). Copies forwarded to Tehram ( \ r •y~» 4 V ' / ^ V U- %,A ' ? ..j- ^ • Telegram Rc, No. 50, dated 13th (reed, 14th) April 1938, From « &amp; ^ * » » * • Butler 9 ienictUo To Foreign,_ New Delhi (Repeated Consul-General, Meshed, No. td. '(r?o 'O x .lease see 1935 correspondence regarding threatened ^ expulsion of Berberis terminating in Sir h. hrsttcnbuli-Ji^Ci-.-v. % 'igtd 2^9.Despatc h 206, v Tin s Majesty’s Consul-General ior Khoiasan reports .hat expulsion order has been issued age.inst thL u y to^io.ty S.., , Afghan and British. Governor-General professes ignorance of • individual dossiers but has explained (a) that refusal to comply with dress and unveiling reforms has become intolerable embarrass- menu to administration faced with difficult task and (b) that at his intervention Berberis (who) had been offered cash value of their property there went quietly» 3. His Majesty T s Consul-General saggested Gove^nox General compromise on the lines of Berber is adopting ppi’bi.rit*-., costume. He considers expulsion unduly drastic and has suggested action here on their behalf* Present case contrasts favourably with 1935 from facts that some explanation has been given and compensation offered, 4 C CO &gt;- ^ ^ o; h- CU cc j&gt;- o &gt;- CO ° z CD z z ^ 00 cc o C\i TJ o — a. &gt; m T 3 .C tD Q&gt; . o ! cj c&gt; « S y -J Q QT '1 Also local authorities are undoubtedly still nervous; the Berberis probably do present an embarrassing contrast and Govern, ment are within their legal ri^rt. I agree nevertheless with His Majesty’s Consul-General and am asking for interview with Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs at which I would deprecate | wholesale expulsion referring to unfortunate effect in Indiaand would express hope that some compromise may be reached.^ Qtlo 5. i/xeanwhiie I have asked His Ifejesty's Consul-General whether Berber is are appealing in accordance with procedure pi omised b} 'll Ministry of Foreign Affairs ■’ see H« M v s Minister s Despatch a 0*^3^ of 1937 hut am also reminding him that under Iranian law 1931 regarding ownership of land by foreigners Berber is should have sold their property so that they were on weak ground in rui using compensation as they have* fil ! FeSc D.S.(F)*), J.S,, and T J e 8»(F). Mod .»Hcr&lt;X2&gt; r » * / Telegram R Ro a 10, dated (and reed) 15th April 1938, 1 rom &lt;9 &amp; c u — .Saulre, Meshedo To«*.o o» t c a •Ministe r ? Tehran f (Repeated to To reign ^ Ren Delhi. !To,91), RESS Reference my despatch Ho*30(80 to Delhi) and your telegram No,22 of April 13th* Notices of April ; 7th have been issued against 1? Berberis British subjects and v:ere served on April 9th c Appeals are being submitted* Total number to be expelled is 69 including dependants* Property affected is not landed property as you assume but houses, household effects, and numerous flocks, Nov; believe real reason for these orders to be groundless suspicion that many Berberis especially pensioners in our secret employment and Governor General 1 s statements to ne about dress mere excuse* Eleven Berberis affected reside in the same village and head of community is Subadar Mohamed Yusuf referred to in my demi-official No* 13 of March 22nd (No*65 to Delhi)* I mentioned his case to Governor General April 5th and asked for return of pension papers which were confiscated on arrest.. This request has resulted in more severe treatment and / -792 , and Iranians no doubt believe that papers are conclusive proof of cur sinister designs. Threat of expulsion from India equal number of Iranians preferably monopoly trade representatives or Calcutta tea dealers is in my opinion only action likely to oe effective in restraining unjustifiable treatment of British subjects. ■n n £cO, u ,3,7.. J.S, Tf.S.F.) 51! .R «&gt;* f p z i Ok r 803. Telegram R &amp; XX No* 31 dated 18th (reed. 19th) April 1933. From. ..Butler, Tehran. To Fereign, New DeIhi. (Repeated to Consul-Greneral j._eshed No. 24.) L : y telegram Nc. 30. I had already addressed representa tions to Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs on the lines therein forecast before receipt of Khorasan telegram No. 10. He promised to speak to Prime Minister and to Governor-General who is now in Tehran. In the meantime he agreed that first step was to obtain time by appeals in accordance -with prescribed procedure - in this connection please see para. 5 of my tele gram under reference. 2. Afghan Charge d 1 Affaires has no information about Afghans affected but as Afghan Ambassador is in Kabul news may have been telegraphed direct there from Meshed. 3. In my conversation I referred to general situation in Khorasan and tc withdrawal of doviet Consulate-General Meshed. Monsieur Adi concurred in this as an important new factor. (i\ T . F.3. D.S.F. J.S. U.3.F.) GLR812. Telegram R I\ T o*l-Saving, dated 19th (reed 20th) April 1938. From........Consul-General, Meshed. To. Minister, Tehran. (Repeated to Foreign New Delhi. No.95). EXPRESS, In continuation of my telegram No. 10. Of the 17 Berber!s affected 5 earned pensions or gratuities in Indian Array., remainder are sons of such pensioners. (No F&lt;S, DeS.Fc U.S.F)4 r p z or, Telegram R. Kc . 19 dated 26th April 1938, Frcm Foreign, Simla. To Charge d ? Affaires, Tehran. Reference last paragraph of Squire r s telegram 1C April the 15th. . Rxpulsicn of Berberis. 2. G-cvernment cf India will be grateful fc r your comments on threat suggested by Squire. This form cf treatment would appear tc be efficacious vide your Despatch copy sent tc India No. 62 of the 6th April 1928.Confidential * No.8(M/4B* His Majesty's Consul G-eneral at Meshed, presents his compliments to the Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents* British Consulate General, Two copies of despatch No*32 dated 6th April 1938, addressed Deportation of Britii Indian subjects from to His Majesty's Charge d'Affaires, Khorasan* Tehran* Meshed. 6th April 1938. Reference to previous correspondence:. Description of Endlosure. Name and Date* Subject.Confidant! al » British Consulate General, for Khorasan, Meshed. 6 th April 1936. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that on April 4th from 30 to 40 Berberis, half of whom were of Afghan and the remainder of British nationality were summoned to the Amnieh office in Meshed from their villages to the East of Meshed, near the Shah’s estates of Fariman and were then told that they could no longer remain in Iran but that if they would agree to go quietly the Iranian Government would pay the value of their property which they should declare. The Berberis concerned declined the official terms and came in a body to their Consulates for advice. 2. I accordingly interviewed the Governor General on the 5th . M. Pakrevan told me that my information was correct; that it had been decided to expel certain Berberis who were considered to be undesirables and that the offer of compensation had been his own idea, as forcible expulsion was naturally resented and might create diplomatic un pleasantness. Ifathe terms offered were not voluntarily accepted formal steps for their expulsion would be taken in accordance with the regulations that had been drawn up i after the 1935 disturbances. (Circular Despatch No.9 of 2nd March 1937). 3. Asked the reason for this decision M.Pakrevan explained that he had not, of course, seen the dossiers of the individuals but generally speaking the presence in the rural districts of a number of foreign nationals who refused to comply with the Iranian regulations regarding the wearing of Trilby hats and the unveiling of women was a source of embarrassment to the administration and could no longer be tolerated. The Government set great store by the enforcement /• 2 enforcement of their regulations and drastic action was necessary to overcome the obstinacy of the local peasantry* 4* I pointed out that the wholesale expulsion of these British subjects who are closely related to the Iranian members of their clan and who in many cases have now no other homes would be a serious step and asked whether some compromise would not be possible. It is understandable that the somewhat truculent defiance of the local dress regulations in which foreign nationals are reported to indulge, is embarrassing to the authorities, and I asked whether, for example, it would be possible to allow these people to remain on condition that in the villages at least they adopted the prescribed coatumes. Pakrevan said that this must depend on the dossier of each individual but admitted that the suggestion had not occurred to him and might be feasible. He promised to give it his consideration. There the matter rests for the moment. 5. I do not know, if, in fact, the question of dress has anything to do with the real reason for the action proposed or whether it is only a plausible excuse. But I did not think it wise, in the absence of instructions, to make any definite protest against the decision to expel these persons from Iran especially as no definite steps to this end have yet been taken; but it does not seem to me that such drastic action is in any way justifiable* Further, if the expulsions are permitted to pass without protest it seems not unlikely that the policy will be extended first to Berberis in Meshed itself and subsequently to all British subjects in this area. 6. I trust therefore that it will be possible to make it clear to the Iranian Government at the outset that such a course of action on their part would be most unwise. A threat of publicity for the whole affair coupled if possible /3 possible with a warning that retaliatory action with regard to Iranian subjects in India would have to be seriously considered would probably have the effect of making them proceed with caution. If nothing is done, or at least if the policy to be pursued is not definitely decided upon until orders of expulsion have actually been passed it will then be too late for effective action. The fear of unpleasant consequences may prevent the authorities from taking hasty action, whereas post facto retaliation, though it may prevent further expulsions, can only make the whole problem more complicated. 7 * I will not fail to keep you informed, by telegram if pm necessary, of further developments, but I have thought it as well to report on the situation imnediately as the G-overnor General expects himself to be leaving for Tehran tomorrow and a timely warning may serve to avert an unpleasant situation. 8 . I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Government of India under Printed Letter No*80* I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/-* G.F. Squire* To His Britannic iflajesty’s Charge d f Affaires, Tehran.14 6130 16473(4) r J i any further communication on this subject, pleaso'quote no. rj-j/s-/,A6/7j6 and address —&gt;toi to any person^y najhe, but to/- '• “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I P. z. 3572 1938 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ -TU and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, &lt;Jo , 193 S. Reference to previous correspondence Jo, ^-2T. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Similar letter sent toIn any further communication on this subject, please quote M v ' a No. E 2051/461/34. and address— not to any person by name but to— Foreign Office, s. w. 1. 3rd May, 1938. “ The Under-Secretary of State,' Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. Sir, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to invite reference to Foreign Office letter B 205 1 /461/34 of the 14th April in which was enclosed a copy of despatch No. 112 of the 24th March from His Majesty’s Charg£ d’Affaires at Tehran, regarding the commandeering by an officer of the Persian Army of a bus hired for the transport of the staff of His Majesty’s Consulate-General at Meshed. 2. As will have been seen from Mr. Butler’s despatch, the latter addressed in writing to the Persian Government a protest against the behaviour of the Persian officer responsible for the incident, and added a request for the payment of 500 rials in respect of the use by the military of the bus chartered by the Consulate-General. Furthermore he expressed orally the hope that an apology would be made. 3. Subject to Lord Zetland’s concurrence. Lord Halifax proposes to authorise Mr. Butler, if he sees no objection, now to address an official note to the Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs stating that His Majesty’s Government approve the representations already made in the matter by His Majesty* s Legation, and adding that, in the opinion of His Majesty’s Government, the behaviour of Sarwan Vossuq Zadeh calls for an apology. I am. Sir Your obedient Servant The Under-Secretary of State India Office.-I . r l SO^f- r Copy. r_E 2080/461/34) British Legation, Confidential Tehran 25th March, 1938 My dear Lacy 2 . East Iran shows signs of producing more trouble. Since the Minister’s talk about the boycott with Adi, Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs, and Jam, recorded 21^T- in despatch No. 109, there have been i) further police interference with pensioners, Iranian subjects, calling at the Meshed Consulate-General to draw their pensions; and ii) the incident of the Consulate-General bus recorded in my despatch by this bag (No. 112 of the 24th March). possibly other incidents that he thought it would be salutary to decline the Governor-General’s invitation to a function on the Shah’s birthday. I think that I have dissuaded him from M-rMi will -»-h8t in the enclosure to my despatch against the attitude of the military authorities generally, and in a private letter to me he speculates whether the time has not come for something like a show-down, Government of India coming to stay here on the 20th April for three or four days and he wants to discuss the position further with the Legation 3 Squire was impressed so unfavourably by these and that the Legation should protest being ready if necessary to tell the Iranian Consul General at Delhi to pack up. Squire and his wife, a welcome pair, are then. H.L.Baggallay Esq. The Foreign Office 4./4. My own feeling is that as long as Government of India attach real importance as they evidently now do, to the Consular posts in East Iran continuing to exist* we stand to lose by having a show-down, particularly since the Soviet Government have succeeded in making us close our Consulate- General at Leningrad and are about to withdraw all their Consular posts from this country except the one at Pahlevi. I told Laithwaite, when I was in Delhi, that I didn f t think the threat to expel the Persian Consul General from Delhi would be thought very fearsome. 5. Therefore, as long as the Government of India view remains what it is, and unless and until we or the Persians start some fresh general initiative, I think that we can only a) follow up the Ministers representations against insensate exaggeration of the boycott, and b) try to get the laws and regulations re requisitioning and other subjects respected vis 6 vis our harassed but by no means ingenuous British Indian brothers in East Iran. But I shall listen with interest to whatever Squire has to propound. 6. Meanwhile, if Government of India insist - reasonably as I think - on furnishing the Consular Officers to these Consulates, it seems less reasonable that they should risk losing the posts altogether by not overcoming the administrative difficulties as regards doing away with the military titles. It ~ -'Wll. is three and a half months since we asked for the agr&amp;nent for Captain Willoughby, Vice Consul designate at Zabul. By a pure accident it is now not needed for another two months. 7. This is to forewarn you of trouble that may come rather than to suggest any action, but it is perhaps worth considering whether Soheily should be told in the course of conversation that the deterioration on various points affecting Anglo-Iranian relations in East Iran is disappointing. Yours ever, (Signed) Nevile Butlere-^Y r''- r s ’o.r-. 1T0. 109 (148/14/39) 23ra j*&amp;roh f 19SS* Vy Lord, *Hh r«fer««c« zo Mr. ^eythour*# letter to His &gt;*a&lt;JfS3t7*» Oorisul-aener&amp;l for Khoraesfm of the EOth 'fovwater, (367/15/37), of which copies were sent to Vr. Hen del and to :nr H.a.F. Metcalfe, I have the honour to report that, immediately before hi® departure on leave of abeenoe, Hia Majesty** Minister called on the *otin£ Minister for Foreign Affairs and reminded his. of the conversation which he had had with U* Samiy shortly before the lattor *3 fatal illness, and of the aide- rneaoirea which he had left with the latter, on the subject of the boycotting of His Majesty's Consular Officers in Tran, -• &gt; - Adi said, however, that he had not seen these ai&amp;e-Biemoirea. j r. Seymour accordingly recapitulated the substance of hi a talk with M. ^amiy, and saiiC that since then he had hears of other incidents inducing the oaae of a soldier who had been punished for calling on his fa mlly who were consulate employees, nr. Seymour pointed out that other difficulties were being put In the way of visits to consulate employees: a vice-consul had been unable to obtain medical aid for a sick child and, to ; show to what ridiculous lengths things were carried, one Of Hi, Consular Offio.r, who had Juat left Iran | *** 6 aonUonwl that Curing the whole of hi, atuy he ha« not be, n ,bl# to get anyone to oome to teach hia Pereian. The Bight ftoao rable , The Viscount Halifax, • F.Adl 'C e • , LeV^eSeTe, etc., etc., etc.2. 3* 5?. Adi made the usual re&amp;arfca about the speoial difficulties resulting from the existenoe of Soviet consulates in Iran (Mr* Seymour unfortunately only learnt later, when he went to see the Prime Minister, that the Soviet post at Meshed was being withdrawn). M* Adi declared that surveillanoe was necessary, and must be the same for all* Mr. Seymour commented that even admitting this, and he did not think that M. Adi thought His Majesty's Consulates presented any danger, there was a 'juste milieu' in everything* It was unnecessary for rainor local officials to go far beyond wnat the central government could aesire and to give the officials of a foreign government the impression of being trea ted as pariahs* ^Adi promised to look up the aide-memoires which &gt;r* Seymour had left at the Ministry of foreign Affairs, and to epeu-c to the Chief of Polioe on the subject. He said that he thought that the main trouble was excess of zeal on the . pa rt of the local officials. 5. ^is Majesty's Minister then saw the Prime Minister, repea ted more shortly what he had said to M. Adi, and expressed the hope that M• Jam would prove sympathetic to the representations which he had made to the Ministry of Foreign affairs. Mr. Seymour said that he felt sure M* Jam J would wish the officials of a foreign government to be treated with the courtesy usual in suoh matters. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the / SecretaryS«or«tary to the Governraent of India in the External Affaire department. I ha ye the honour to be, with the highest reapeot, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient humble ServantINDIA DIRECT In an^^rtWTcoininuniculion on this subject, jiiease quote No. £' £(&gt;£/ / ylol / J^b. and address— not to any person by n/trne, but Jto — “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.\Y\ 1. ?A P- 7 •• 1 rx- 2669 1 L ifiaa THE Under-Secretary of State ifnr Aff^ rs presents his compliments to X^oul/Z&gt;^/ J) transmits herewith cop and, by direction of the Secretary of State, of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, A , 193 Reference to previous correspondence : H’* 0 - Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Similar letter sent to 14-6130 14007 ( 4 ) x.■■■■■■■ wo. 112 (351/8/38) ny 24th Jmroh* 1928. I have the honour to transmit to you horowith oopies of a £*sp&amp; toh from His Fi&amp;jesty’s Consul-6«n«rul for ^iom ssan reporting on the incident whioh ooourred on the 1st Faroh in whioh a bus hired for the transport of the staff of His ha peaty’s Consulate-Crwieral was temporarily commandeered by an officer of the ranian army. 2 . I felt it desirable to bring this incident immediately to the attention of the Iranian Government a nd I accordingly a rranged to see the Director-General of the political Section of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs on the 2oth March, when I handed to him the aide-m^/ioire, of whioh oocies are enclosed herein. &amp;. I^ohsen Buis read this and said that it seemed a bad case and that the local authorities would be aeked to report on it without delay. 2. I a s ed leave to ia&amp;£e two points: first ae regards the very modest estimate of lials 50C in respect of use by the military of the bus chartered by the Consulate-General. This insignificant sum was assessed carefully and exclusively in respect of services actually rendered by the owner to the military authorities in / the The hight Honour able The Viscount Halifax, a.o.s.i., e to •, etc •, etc.2-, &lt;g) the spirit t though Inevitably not withis the letter, of the Iranian regulaticme ns regards req aiultionlng of transport: the driver was entitled to payment, and also it was important that the Icoal authorities ehould be /VV^V£Vv(aMA. reminded whwer a r uestlon a rose of the oorreot procedure laid &amp;o*n by the Irfinian authorities themselves as the outcome of mimerous oonveraKtions In 1935 between r. ioheily and Hie hajesty^ minister f ihen r. Knatohbul 1- nu£es&amp;en. (Pleaae see paragraph 4 of the aide-memoire enclosed in Tehran despatch to the Government of India Office* A copy of the final paragraph of the Iranian reference la there nnOe, i&amp; enclosed herein*) The i&amp;peroved state of affair® noticeable in 1936 already showed a tendency to deteriora te as in another case, about which I had recently had to talk to M* ^en^ani, and i now asked M• hai»» help in «aicuring that the correct procedure as regards req uisitioning should be made fa»ailiar to and be observed by local authorities and military officers of all ranks, k. mia a f rreed that this was very desirable and pr omised his help* 4* secondly, x »aid that there was unfortunately the question of iarwan ^adeh’s behaviour. Granted taat he may have aeeraed placed in an awkward position, the Consular party had endee voured to help him, and his behaviour had been quite contrary to the treatment which a dexunOUte establishment and its property were traditionally entitled to enjoy. In all the circumstances, X felt that the aarw&amp;n owed an apology to His Majesty’s iiovermnent 1 s note of the 28th January, lt36, to whieh Coneulate-Creneral and I ashed M* Rai ® to transmit to the / ^tiliirActing Minister for Toraign Affair* my aamast hop* that an apology woulfi h« «afil* in an appropriat* manner# S • Hals man* no oommont, an6 prwaiaeO to t»a»© this on. 6. I#a*tly I said that as onfortonataiy tiioro had reoettly Peon some r#&amp;r*ttable oaourreuoe* in i^et ; ran, I felt bound to report this case to you. I greatly hoped to be able to transmit a satisfaotory reoly from the Ministry of foreign Affairs while His Majesty's minister wa* in IfivAm* 6. you will see from the above that I did not claim the full *\m of Rial* 1»000 *ngg**%*4 by \ r. : quire. Tn all the oiroumst&amp;noe*, and in view of the fact that the competent authority attached » ;«se of th* blame for the oollision to the driver of the Consulate-'General bu*, it aeemed best to a sfc for payment only in respect of the services rendered by the one bus that was actually commandee red. the auja of 500 rials represents a eharg* of *.baut rial* per mile, which I am a ovised is a felr estimate. 7. no request for an apolo^ is rmde In the aide- memoire. Without instructions froti you I would not have felt justified in making a written request for one, and in this case prompt protest seened mors important. I confine* myself to expressing orally the Hop* that an apology would be forthcoming, tfut in the light of past ex erience and of the fact that vhe Sarwan ws* assuring the sa fety of (government arms and munitions, I doubt very much whether the Ministry of tar *111 authorise an apology. I hope nonetheless that the recital in the aide-memoire ofvp) r, . j., •, SOI* ) British oon8ulate-'*eimr»l Tor ^iornBnnt .r'-s the 11th taroh 11 ^ir In continuation of ay toia^rnma TtoaiZ and 3 i/imp I have the honour to sub ait wy detailed report on the incident of March 1st, 1936. a. 'hen I left 'abul on tour for ahidim on February 27th i-y staff and wienie 1 eotabllahraent left for -eahed direct in two hired buses. The first bus, driver arteb 'in^h, carried liy Office Superintendent ( 3r. Thorias), the icoountnnt. ( Y. 'hulaa Tarwar) and his faaily, their servants and luggede «» well m those of the ■ttnohe. 'he second bus (driver ^uhau-ad laud} carried my he«d fermsh nnu the families of the subordinate eatabliBfcaent. Both buses we ovneo riven by .-ritish n-.U^cots. 3. On the morning jf nrch 1st nt about 9 a.ru., the leading bus was climbing into the hills about three niles north of the villaAe of ;ehdeh, 40 miles north of -irjnnd, when at a bend ^in the road it was run into by a bus coining from ashed driven by qm 4iha amad Khan, also a British subject, and carrying -arwan n} ^obsuq Tadeb, a regular officer of the 'Kabul Artillery, nn latiiyeh officer and his wife and child, 12 military other ivnks and n convoy of arms. be view of the occupants of artnb iingh •» bus 1b th»t their driver wrs In no way to blame for the accident. Vubasmed J han *b bus, ss is &gt;nly to be ex pected whore the Trsnlan military forces nr© concomed, was grossly ^vei'- loaded; It had apparently not been ins &gt;ected and )aosed by the eshed ^olio© in accordance with the Police rei;ulntions, /it His Majesty # s Tnvoy Extraordinary JBI 5t24 ^ 4» m. '•‘VW 4 ^ a ^ ^ 4 and Minister 'lent potent!ary at the ourt &gt;f Iran ''ehran.&lt;g)^ it ves an old and unserviceable machine f it had no proper brakes, and considering the gradient was proceeding auch too fast. 4. In endeavouring to avoid a collision iiha jmd rhan turned his bus into the bank, the impact caused the front vheel to come off and the bus rebounded into the road the back bumper coming into collision i*ith the rear part of rartab Singh's bus, which he had run off the rosd into the ditch in order to avoid a headon collision. fortunately no serious daaiage was done either to the buses or to their occupants but the gallant Captain, who in view of his rank and position might have been expected to have exercised a steadying influence, was so unnerved by the occurrence that be completely lost his head and his temper and rjroceeded to use most foul language, to lay the whole blame on Portab Mngh, and to demand that he should abandon his own passengers and return with him all the way to 'abul. This ^artab »lngh declined to do. He deiftanded that if he was to be held responsible for the accident the soot should first be examined by the comoetent authority, viz, the Maniyeh officer at Cehdeh. Ir. Chulam Carwar also Intervened and said that they could not agree to being turned out of the bus. The abuse which this protest called forth was such that *ay staff tnought it more dignified to retire and leave this irrespons ible maniac to do as he liked. It is significant that Uhsimriad Khan himself at first freely ad:aitted both to the r arwan and to art^b r ingh that the fault was his? and left to theuiselves the drivers of the three buses could soon have repaired the damage sufficiently to allow of the parties proceeding on their respective ways, this they offered to do and indeed set to work on Tiha /find Khan's bus. 5. Vossua fadeh, finding that oere abuse was insuffi cient, then resorted to force. He ordered his men to tie /up3. up artat) Singh antf they advanced threateningly upon him with a rope. Partafc Singh was thus forced to give way. The sarwan with sonae of his men climbed into his bus and Tartab Singh had to take them and his Passengers back to the village of ^ehdeh. i^uhara.aad Daud also brought his bus back. At Sehdeh the bus was forcibly emptied of all its contents and taken back to the scene of the accident. ’uh&amp;u.mad Khan's bus had by this time been sufficiently repaired. Half the load was taken off it and placed on Partab Singh's bus and both buses returned to the A.miiyeh Post at Hehdeh. 6. At nehdeh the ^arwan, who by this time had to some extent recovered his nerve and his tempert was less ofTensive. But he declined to listen to the Amniyeh officer» who was only an N.C.O, or to be influenced by the reconaj-iendatory letter from the Uovemor of ^abul which *r. Thomas carried. After imich argument he offered to allow the oorty to proceed provided that they left artab *Ungh behind as a prisoner and signed a written statement that they had no I f complaint against him of any as sort. Hiis was of course impossible. The Sarwan thereupon placed 'artab tUngh under arrest and co/iKiandeered his bus. $r. Thomas and r.ohulara °&gt; 0 rwar leaving their servants in charge of the luggage at Sehdeh returned in .uhaiamad Daud's bus to Birjand, which they reached at 6.30 p.m. 7. An immediate complaint was made to the Acting Governor and his help solicited. The two buses with Vossuq 'adeh's party arrived about 10.30 i.m., but 'artab singh was detained until midnight when on the Intervention of the garage owner he was released and allowed to go to the Vice- Consulate. A military guard was placed over his bus. 8. Negotiations hasted throughout the following day /Voamuq.VoBeuq Hadeb continuing without aucoess to &gt;ress 1 artab i&gt;ingh and the Consulate StaTf to acquit hi/a of any charge of improper conduct. This was declined and the civilian authorities in Birjand also failed to bring their uiilitary colleague to see reason. Eventually at 6 o.m., the \djutant of the local Amniyeh proceeded to the garage, ordered the military guard away, had the bus unloaded by coolies nnd handed it over to Tartab &gt;ingh. 9. Meanwhile the wretched luha ai/iad Khan was also in a difficult position. He had a painty of angry soldiery in his bus and dared not openly oppose them. He has therefore been forced to lodge a complaint against Partab ?3ingh for having been the cause of the accident olainilng nials 1,000 as damages and stating that the rife of the Axaniyeh officer also received injuries. These were apparently of an extremely trifling nature. Kepairs to his bus were completed and he has since proceeded on his way to ''abul. 10. I enclose herewith translations of the oorresoondena which has passed between the Vice- Consulate at Blrjand and the Governorste (I have appended my own notes where necessary] I tnyself arrived at Birjand on the 5th and the following morning called on the Acting Governor. He himself made no allusion to the subject and X therefore closed the interview by informing him that I was astonished at such an insult having been offered to members of nsy staff by an officer who should have known better and requesting him to take no further proceedings which would only aggravate matters pending instructions from Tehran. 11. the *th I left Birjand for hashed and stopped en route at Sehdeh. There I saw the Aimlyeh jf.0.0 who was quite polite. He informed me that he had since been to the scene of the accident and had reported that both drivers were to blame and that the Sarwan had taken it on himself /toto compel the vehicles to return to Mrjand, X also inspected the site ourself. It &lt;aay he that n artah ningh tvas partly to hlaiae for not sounding his hom # hut the comer though very sharp was not entirely blind and it appears to me probable that ha mad Khan*8 bus could not have negotiated It in any case at the speed at which he uust have been travelling. The question of rosponsibility is however an academic one which does not greatly affeot the question of Sarwan Voasuct Sadeh *8 behaviour. 12. It will be seen from the above account that I have no complaint to make against any official other than Harwan Vossuq Tadeh. The r'olice and Araniyeh officers at r&gt;ehdeh and Birjand did no more than their duty and the Acting Covemor t who is really the Head Clerk, did what he could in the iaatter. fossuq Sadeh however in w opinion behaved aborainably throughout. 13. An officer of his position should not in the first place have so lost his head after the accident and his oo unandeering of the bus as far as n &gt;ehdeh though understand able was auite inexcusable. Mad any approach to him been possible my staff would have been only too ready to have helped him at least as far as the ^mniyeh Post at nehdeh from where he could easily have made all necessary arrange ments. 14. His behaviour at &gt;ehdeh was even /oore outrageous. He declined to let the Amnlyeh tf.O.O, the proper authority to deal with the case, to have any say in the matter, appointed himself arbitrarily as oroseoutor and judge, placed the unfortunate Par tab iUngh under military arrest and co^iand- eered the Consulate bus to Birjand even though his own bus was by then sufficiently repaired to proceed (as it did indeed do with half the load). The fact that he offered to /allow■ 6 . to ^lS?) '*'*V I allow the Uonsulat© party to proceed on conditions showed that this eoiomandeering was quite unnecessary and that he knew it to be so, 15. Finally his retention of the bus until 6 p.m on March 2nd when it was only the assistance of the Araniyeh Officer which secured its release added gratuitously to his previously insulting behaviour, 16. I trust therefore that it will be possible to f&amp;ake strong representations against the high handedness of this individual in particular and of the jailitary authorities in East Tran in general. The incident which I now report is only the culimlnation of a long series in which /flilltary ofX'icers have been allowed to usurp the functions of the civil authorities and to ride rough shod# over their civilian colleagues in the iiatter of conuiandeer- ing of transport. 17. The incident has had a deplorable effect locally and Indian traders in jsirjnnct are asking what is likely to happen to them when even Oonsular representatives can be treated with such scant respect. 13. It is perhaps not for m to advise what re &gt;aration if any should be asked for but I venture to suggest that the minimum demand should be for a formal apology and a dniiaura sum of dais l f QQO as hire of the two buses from ‘&gt;ehdeh to Birjand and back (30 miles)* ('uhammed ^aud had to return also and to wait at Birjand for the rest of the party) ameJl we Ur as oomnensation for the loss of two days work. 19. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the decretory to the Government of India* External Affairs Department* flew Delhi, under Printed Letter Hoi526. I have the honour to be Hir, Your most obedient servant* s d/-0.;F. Squire. His ajesty's Sonsul-Oeneral for Khomsnn.// Ho. 39 Vice-Consulate &gt; Bitjaud. rtie 2nd iiarch 1938 The British Vice-ConsliUte at Birjand presents its compliments to the Farmandari of the Kainat and has the honour to report that at 7.30 a.m. on &amp;arch 1st, 1938, two 'buses containing the staff with XhiiSL^ their wives and children and property of the British Consulate-Ceneral, Peshed , left Birjand for Meshed. About one farsakh north of the village of oeh&amp;eh, a bus proceeding from Meshed to Zabul containing a military officer (Sultan Vassough ^adet an Amnieh officer and his wife and child, 12 soldiers and a heavy consignment of arms and ammunition, collided with on of the buses hired by the Consulate-Seneral (No. M.1709) driver Icrtab Singh. Itr. accident tooK place at a narrow bena and to avoid a head on collision driver Partab oingh drove his bus into a ditch and Muhammad Khan (a British subject) the driver of the aov.n-coming bus steered his bus on to a mound. Ttu result of this was that Muhammad Khan f s bus broke a front spring and sustained other minor damages to the front mud-guards and to r^ar bump r. The fact that this bus was able to proceed to Birjand, where it arrive^ last night, under its own power, proves that neither bus suffered serious damage. 2. The British Vice-Consulate is informed by the members of th &gt; Consulate-Ceneral staff who were travell ing on Partab Singh’s bus that Immediately after the acci-ent sultan Vassough Zaaeh ais-mounted from his bus ana used most foul language in addressing one of the members of the Consulate-General staff ana the driver i artab Singh. He threatened and compelled ariver The Farmundaii of the Kainat, Birj ana. IartabPartab Jingh to remove his bus i‘rom the scene oi' the accident and proceed to 3ehdeh where the property oi‘ the Cons ala V'-General was taken dov;n i'rom the bust which return ed empty to the scene of the accident and was loaded with the rifles and. soldiers and returnee to Sehdeh. Here Sultan Vassough Zadeh held an enquiry as a result of which driver Partab Singh was detained under guard, Hie two members of the Consulste-Cenerai staff (with a lady and a child) who were travelling with Partab Singh therefore left Sehdeh in the second bus with the women and children who were travelling in that bus and returned to birjand, and the incident was reported to you personally last night. 3. At about 10.30 p.m. driver Partab Singh arrived at Pirjand with Puhammao Khan’s bus. Ihe present position therefore is that the property of the Consulate General which was carried on lartao Singh’s bus is left lying at Sehdeh in charge of 2 servants and the rest of the staff are here. 4. The British Vice-Consulate in reporting this case draws the attention of the b'armandari to the fact that (1) the buses were removed from the scene of the accident by force, without an enquiry being held by the appropriate and independent authority; (2) that the bus of Partab Singh was finally commandeered oy the Militay officer to bring him £ad his party to Sehdeh and later to Birjand; (3) that the property of the Consulate-General has been left at Sehhbh without adequate protection; (4) that the staff who were to have reached Meshed today have been compelled by the arbitary action of this officer, to remain in Birjand. 4. The British Vice-Consulate therefore requests that/3 that the Farmandari will kindly order the release of the Consulate-Oenerul has whi.ch has been forcibly commandeered by the Military officer, so that the staff may proceed to Meshed.ba ted the 12th lafand 1516• Ministry of Interior, 1316 (2no March 1958) in forwarding a copy of the letter received in reply (to my letter) with its enclosure (I request you to ) please instruct the motor driver concerned to introduce himself to the Amnieh Office and to furnish the* security required, so that the passengers can return and reach leshed with their property. The 5rd March 1958 Khorasan 1 rovince Mo. 8782 (lovernorate of Kainat /ice-Oonsul In reply to your Mo. 59, dated the 11th Isfand acting Governor for Kainat. (Kafil -i -i’armand ari - i -Kain a t) id. iLhmed Naseh, Mr. -rhulam Muhiyud iiin, Janashin of the British Vice-Consul, BirJ and/r Tr ansXa Copy or letter No* 14738/Tf dated the ilth Ist'and 1316 (the 2nd tfaroh 1938) rrom the X ^auiieh Office to the Govemorate for the xainat 9 hirjaud. In reply to your No* 8774t dated the 11 th Xsfand 1316 (find Jbaroh 1'38) 1 have to say that this Cardan had no previous information of the case* &amp;s soon as your letter was received a report on this subject and for recovery of compensation for damages sustained was received from Garwan Vassal £aoeh officer in charge of the convoy of arms and ammunition t under No* 77, dated the 11 th Isfand 1316 (2nd liarch 1938), a copy of which is sent herewith* In these circumstances th*.s G&amp;rdan agrees with the views expressed Intd. G.F.S. Consul and has not come out at all* i lease issue instructions for the driver to refer owner of the garage it transpires that his lorry is in the garage and that no one has by the Governorate that the driver can on This is not correct* The driver had been to the garrage several times and had also given his state ment to the Birjand Police. furnishing security proceed to feshea and then return. Nut the driver since his arrival at Birjand is staying in the house of the .1 ana shin (representative) of the Vice to this Cardan for furnishing a security. In the end the Cardan has to add for your The ^nmieh placed no information that in addition to the fact that restrictions on the _ bus, but Taiwan Vassuq. this Cardan has not placed any prohibition 2*&amp;deh had left it loaded with a Military on the driver, on enquiries made from the guard over it* placed any restriction on its movementsrxaoalr.tlon. 16 He was asiced to sign several state ments incriminating himself and exonerating Vassal -adeh. He did in fact under compel- tion sign one state ment hut refused to sign the other. Ind. O.i’.a. Copy of letier Ho. 77, dated t;he llth Xsfana 1316 (2nd Marhh 1938) from Sarwan Vassu^ ^.adeh. ^he Hais-i-.jnnieht Birjand. At 11 a.m. on the 10th Isfaad 1316(lst March 1938) the motor bus con taing members of the Consulate staff and passengers oolliaed while travelling 6 kilometers off Sehdeh with the motor bus carrying Oovernment ai*ms and ammunitioni and militai’y escort, damaged the motor bus containing the arms and injured a person. The matter was reported to the mnieh post at 3ehdeh. As usual preliminary investigations were made from the drivers. Ihe driver at fault who was carrying members of the Consulate staff refused to sign the statement, as is evident from the examination of the scene of accident the bus carrying the arms collided with a hill and with •the circular bank of the w&amp;ter course which is on the right hand but the other automobile contrary to the rules was travelling on its left hand side and did not blow its horn in the bend. As a result of this accident, according to my duty, 1 brought to Birjand, the Government arms and ammunitions and escort with the injured person in the bus of the driver at fault, also the empty motor bus which was carrying the anas. Accoruing to information the driver at fault a&amp;o gone to the Biitish Consulate and refuses to pay damages ana compensation for medical treatment of the injured. The matter has been referred to the lashkar to which I am suborainate. 1 request that according to law the driver• i ’P &gt;S) ^ ' 7 the driver at fault may be summoued as early as possible and necessary enquiries may be instituted and arrangements may be made for the despatch of the Government arms* iid . Garwan Vassuo. Z&amp;deh, . Officer in charge of the convoy of arms and ammunitions*A'atecl the 14th Isfand 1S16 iiinistry of Interior. 5th ^rhh 1938. Province of Khorasan, Governorate for the Kainat. Vice-Consul. In continuation of my No. 8782, Gated the 12th Island 131u (3rcl March 1938) (lhave the honour to inform you that) according to a letter received from the minieh Office the defendant has gone to Meshed without attending the Amnieh Office and furnishing security. The driver cailying the military stores has claim for damages amounting to xslals 1,000 and a second Lieutenant (attached to oiTice) named Abhas Khomravi who was accompanied hy his wife has complained about the injuries received by his wife. In view of the above please instruct Partab Jlngh motor driver to return to Biijand as soon as possible to answer his complcinants. cd • iihemd Naseh Acting (Jovernor for the Kainat. Mr. dhulam Muhiyu Lin, jaaashin of the British Vice-Consul, Birj and.No. 46 British Vice-Gonaulate, BirjaiiO . The 6th March 1938 The British Vice-Cons jlate at Birjaud has the honour to inform the Oovernorate for the Kainat with reference to their letter No. 8838 t dated the 14th Isfand 1316 (5th March 1938) that the bus was personally handed over by the MJutant of the ^miiieh Office to i artab Jin^h who Informed him that he was at liberty to leave employment of the British Oonsulfcte-£»eneral at the time of the accident he will be directed to report himself to llrjand as requested. Ihe Govemorate for the Kainat, Birjana. however 1 artab Jingh was in the BIrj and19th l arch, 1938. HI» Majesty*s Legation feel obligees to draw the attention of the Imperial Ministry of Foreign affairs to the following incident which h&amp;a been reported to them by Hie ifajesty's Oonsul-ireneral for ^orasan. 2. r r. Squire, who hits recently been in 2fc&gt;ml, arranged for hie et&amp;ff and menial establishment to return direct from that town to Meshed on the 27th Jeebruazy (8th lusfand). For this purpose he arranged for the hire of two buses, the first bus carried the Office Superintendent to His Majesty's Gonaulate-General (Mr* Thomas), the accountant (Er. Ghulam ^arwar) with his family, and also their servants and Consulate luggage. ’The second bus oarried the head ierr&amp;sh at rr ls Majssty *8 Consulate- ueneral and xhe families of the subor dinate establishment, doth bu^es were owned and driven by British subjects. 3. on the morning of the 1st aroh, at about 9 a.m., the first bus -us reached a point about three miles / northnorth of th* vill&amp;ire of forty miles north of Birjand f when at a bend in the roa6 It wae run Into by a bus oomtng from Meshed, csurry- in^ Sarwan Voesuq .'iadeh, a regular officer of the uatbul Artillery, an i-saniyeh officer and his wife and child, twelve military other ranks, and a convoy of anas* Fortunately no serloua damage was done either to the buses or to their oooup&amp;nts* 4* iiarwan ossuq ^adeh, however, placed all the blame on the driver of the first of His Majesty's Consulate-General’a buses and demanded in abusive language that the driver should abandon his own passengers and return with him all the way to ;;abul. '?his the driver at first declined to do, claiming that if he was to be accused of being responsible for the accident, the spot should first be examined by the competent authority, ▼iz. the Mmiyeh officer at Sehdeh. The drivers of the three hu.ee set to work to put in order the bus whioh had carried Sawran Yossuq 2adeh, since it was clear that the damage toit, as well as to the other bus inTolred, could be repaired sufficien tly to allow of the parties proceeding on their reepeotire ways, iterwan Voaauq &lt;a6eh, however, insisted on commandeering the hue hired by Hie Majesty's Consulate-General, and eventually threatened the use of force, ordering his men to tie up the Britleh Indian driver with a rope, the latter therefore was obliged to comply with the wiefces of Sarwan Voseuq l^adeh, and conveyed him and some of his ien to the village of Sehdeh • 6. There the bue was forcibly emptied of all its contents and taken back to the scene of the accident. ossuq ^deb'e bus had by thie time been sufficiently repaired. n*lf the load was taken off it and placed on His Majesty's Consulate- Ceneral's hue, and both buses were driven to the 4®niyeh post at Sehdeh. 5f#rt th * **rwan declined to listen to the Asmiyeh official in charge of the post, or to be influenced fey the letter of recommendation from the C°*«rnor of 2ft bul ^ ieh Mr . ThoBa8 onmed. Aft er «uoh er^u^nt h. offerod to alio* th. party f roa HuMajesty's Consulate-General to proceed provided that th«y left the driver behind as a prisoner and signed a written statement that they had no complaint against him (the iiarwan) of any sort. This they naturally declined to do. Sarwan Voaauq 'adeh thereupon placed the driver of Kia Majesty’s Consulate* General’s bus under arrest and commandeered the bus. 7. The Consular officials, leaving their servants in charge of the luggage at ;&gt;ehdeh # returned in the other bus to Birjand. kn immediate complaint was made to the Noting Governor, and his help solicited. A few hours after the Consular officials reached Birjand, the two buses with Sarwan Tossuq ^adeh’s party arrived. This was at about 10.30 pm. The driver of His Majesty's Consulate* General'g bus w&amp; 8 detained until midnight. A military guard was placed over the bus. 3. WsgotUUons laat.fi thr ou^hout the following day (the 2nd V’aroh), uarwan Vo«au 9 2afi e h oontlnnin* to praaa without suooeaa for a fioounant / aoquitting1 s?&gt; lL+~ 5 acquitting him of improper oonduet* Eventually, at 6 the Adjutant of #uard to be removed and the unloaded. It wae then returned to ite driver. strongly to protest against the notion of Sarw&amp;n Vosauq ^adeh on thie ooo&amp;sion. The Iranian regulations transport were clearly explained to His majesty*s hegation in the la«t paragraph of a note from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs signed by M.Kaseml on the 7th Bah,mn 1314. They provide that the commandeering including the rate of hire shall be done through the Police (in towns), and through - ^ miyeh (outside towns). From the above account of the faots in the Jarwan ''oseuq not only th. bus of HIb ^Je 8 t y . 8 Consulate- •»« fcMk again, but ttiat at $«hAah *&gt;« fieollneC to let the *mnlyeh offioial, the proper authority to the local Hmnlyeh oaused the military 9. His Majesty’s Legation wish regarding the oomraandeering of motor | preaent case it will he seen that .^etierui frois the soene of the accident a;- far as Sehfleh, and then fn&gt;m that Tillage to the scene of the accident accident daai wi «* the oase. have a «*y oay i n / thethe matter. He appointed himself arbitrarily prosecutor and judge, placed the drlrer of His Majesty’s / Consulate-General's bus under arrest, and finally again command eered the hue from Sehdefc to Birjand. (on the occasion of this sec one cocimndeering, Sarwan Voaeuq Sadeh»s own bus had already been sufficiently repaired to proceed - as indeed it did do with half the load). Finally, on the 2nd March h© arbitrarily detained Hie Majesty 1 e Joasulttte-G.n.ral's hue during the »i»ole of the day up to 6 pa. i.'« The Iranian regulatione referred to above «how that the rate ’*&gt;j hire should have b&amp;en fixed through the A niyeh at hehdeh. larwan '° aau &lt;J «h having prevented this. Bis Majesty's legation draw attention to the faot that for the distance &lt;rf approximately 89 miles (from the eoene of the uooident to Sehd.h and then from iehfieh to the scene and buok again amounted to about 9 miles, * hilst t * oa ' to Birjand and Wok again amounted to about 80 mil,,; (the bus w&lt;ts aorspulaorily in the servioe of ^arwan Vossuq Uideh, in his o&amp;paoity as an officer in the Iranian ^rtny* In default of any sum having been fixed at the time through tiie Amniyeh, His Majesty's legation feel that in the present instance _ fbo the sum of Kials ir^f*** would be a proper charge for the forced hire of the bus of Hie Majesty's Oonsulate-General• 11» In addition His Majesty's legation^ to their freat regret feel compelled to point out that besides being o&amp;used very oonalder- able inconvenience by the delay which they were obliged to inour, oilioials of His Majesty's Consulate General were subjected to grave discourtesy, and that property belonging to the Consulate-General hati to left at Sehdeh under inadequate proteotion. 12 , different accounts have bean given as to the responsibility for the aocibent. Those who were travelling i n Hi a Consulate ttenerai, « b «* holfl the view that their driver wae in no way to bias* w^erea* the irmly,*, offioial who inspeoted the 80en ® of *he aooldent / sported* COPY Extract from the Translation of Hot© from Iranian Minister for Foreign Affairs to His Majesty 1 a Minister Tehran Ho.47160/3652 of 7th Bfthman 1314 (28tli January, 1936). ... • How the latter quarters state tnat inatruotions have been issued to the sections concerned to see that the saaie treatment which is &amp;iven to Iranian drivers is given to foreign drivers so far as the conclusion of contract, fixing up terms, taking steps through the police (in towns) and through the Aranieh (outside towns), fixing the rate of hire etc. are oonoei’ueo and also to compensate the losses, if any, which they may incur in accords noe with the rules in force.7108 Wti2012/PS&gt;0 1000 4.38 rmr. &gt;&lt;* * Reference PaperJ! Transferred to itea (pn^) Retford Department (Parliamentary Branch). Secretary, P. &amp; j. Dept,. E8 APR 1938 193 Extract from Official Report of the LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY Debates. Late 28 MAR 1938 193 . page Arrest of Mulki Chand Sahni of Peshawar, an Indian Trader in Iran. 1027. *Mr. Abdul Qaiyum: Will, the Foreign Secretary please state: (a) whether Mulki Chand Sahni of Peshawar, a trader in Iran, was arrested between Mashed and Zahedan on the 9th March, 1930; s (b) whether he was carrying a number of gold coins with him at the time; (c) whether these gold coins, as well as his car, were confiscated by the Customs authorities in Iran; (d) what is the amount of loss that he suffered; (e) whether he has been fighting his case in several civil, revenue and criminal courts since then and, if so, with what result; (f) whether Government will lay on the table the latest information about his case; and (g) whether Government have taken any steps to help him so far; if not, whether Government propose now to do something in the matter? Sir Aubrey Metcalfe: (a) Yes. &lt;(b) and (c). Yes, according to Mr. Sahni’s statement. (d) The value of the confiscated articles was estimated by Mr. Sahni at approximately Rs. 26,000. (e) Yes, he tried unsuccessfully to lodge an appeal in various Courts in Iran against the order of confiscation. In 1936 his petition was entertained by the Lower Court in Meshed. His car was ordered to be released, but the action of the Customs authorities in confiscating the gold was upheld, and he was also sentenced to six months’ simple imprisonment. (f) He appealed against the judgment of the Meshed Lower Court, but t e res ult is not yet known. Government have no other information. (g) Yes, His 'Majesty.’s. Legation and Consular Officers in Iran have been affording him every possibTe assistance, since the case against him was first instituted. Mr. Abdul Qaiyum; Is it a fact that according to the law then in force in Iran at the time of his arrest, he had not committed any offence, but that subsequently the law was altered and he was prosecuted and convicted? Sir Aubrey Metcalfe: I believe’ that to be a correct: statement of the case, and that particular feature has been pointed out very vigorously by His Majesty’s Minister at Teheran to the appropriate authorities in Iram. Mr. Abdul Qaiyum: Will Government do their best to help this poor man? Sir Aubrey Metcalfe: We have done everything possible: I discussed the case only the other day with His Majesty’s Minister in Teheran who happen ed to be in Delhi. He assured me that he would not relax his efforts on behalf of this gentleman. Mr. Abdul Qaiyum: Thank you very much indeed. ft •A i l ' *- MW 1938 )° l r Urfc &amp; r.O r A* For information, W. T. OTTEWILL NOTE. —A copy has also been referred to y Department. If the subject- matter does not concern the Department, it is requested that this reference may be returned immediately to the Parliamentary Branch.ty person by nam*, bu/ to— In any furtlier communication on thU/Subject, ulease quote No and address—wo&lt; to any “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. u .. &lt;■ vV C j THE Under-Secretary of State^'for “Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop ^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, // , IWif. Reference to jjf'evious correspondence : t yft- ^ iff Cls£c ‘l ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER NO. 7 1 7 FEB 1938 PROE SECRETARY, POLITICAL Am) SECRET DEPT.' INDIA OFFICE I 14 Similar letter sent to 6130 15844(4)(116/2/38) 14th January, 1938 Our aide-memoire (unnumbered) of the 18th December about the difficulties of Muhammud Wakili, a copy of which I sent you, seems to have produced some effect on the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. The acting Head of the Third Political Department has now stated that enquiries have been addressed to Meshed and that he hopes to send a reply to the aide-memoire at an early date. 2. As regards the general question of the 'boycott* I fear the outlook is far from hopeful. For the last year or more, up to about November, there was, anyhow in Tehran, an evident tendency for more Iranians to .''frequent foreign houses'. In the last weeks of last year there was a sudden tightening up of the restrictions, and it is clear that this winter we shall only be privileged to entertain a few members of the official classes. In fact we have now joined you in the ranks of the pariahs. There seems to be no discrimination against us as British: all the Legations are in the same boat. 3. We know of no real reason for all this, but I fear that the appetite of the cheap English press for juicy bits about the Shah may have been partly to blame together with authors like Robert Byron. It is tiresome and irritating to be treated in this childish way, and not very complimentary to the patriotism of the Persians themselves. But we can do nothing effective to stop it. (Sgd.) H.J. Seymour. G.F. Squire, Esq., I.C.S. His Majesty^s Consul-General for Khorasan, at Kabul.Copies to; Mr. Squire, Meshed. (Ref:D.O.No 86 (21/1) of 16.11.37), Sir Metcalfe, New Delhi. Mr. andel, F.O. Pi Z. 1 _ oi 7 | .j Aide-Memoire. There is an Iranian subject resident at Meshed named Muhammad Wakili. This man is the son of the late Haji Mirza Abbas Khan, formerly British Consular Agent at Meshed. Muhammad tfakili was formerly in the employment of His Majesty*s Consulate-General in that town. But some years ago his services were dispensed with, and since he left the employment of the Consulate-General he has had no connection with it whatever, except that he has received a pension of Rials 250 a month in consideration of his past services. Until the month of October last he was in the employment of the Finance Department at Meshed at a salary of Rials 300 a month. About the 3rd October he went as usual to the Consulate-General to draw his pension. On leaving he was arrested and taken before the police. His house was searched and every document written in English was seized, as well as the decorations granted to his father. He was placed in solitary confinement and charged with being a British spy. Nothing incriminating was found, and after thirty five days’ solitary confinement he was released. On returning to his post in the Finance Department he was told that he could no longer be employed because he had been in prison. In despair he went to the police and asked whether he would be again imprisoned if he were to continue to draw his pension, since he was now penniless and had no other means of support. It appears that he was given permission vi^it the Consulate-General to draw his pension, and he did/■■■■■ m did so on 15th November to draw his pension for the month of October* 2. Muhammad Vfakili is, as stated, an Iranian subject. His Majesty^ Legation venture however to put forward his case because his difficulties appear to have arisen solely from his former employment at the Consulate-General at Meshed. It is believed that it cannot be the intention of the Imperial Government that an Iranian subject should be deprived of his employment simply because he was formerly in the service of a British Consulate-General and now draws a small pension for his past services, and it is hoped that the authorities will, on reconsideration, allow him to resume the post which he previously held. 18th December, 1937Nn.488 (a&amp;.7/ as T 'a7) (Jonf iaentiw.1 British Legation, Tehran, 14th Teoeraber, 1^157 . His Majesty’s Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Ill-treatment of British subjects travelling in East Iran* * Reference — To External Affairs Dept, Govt*of India, *o*367/25/37 of 14.12.37. From -do- No.D.0.No.F.768-!f/36 of 23.11.37 Copy also sent to: H.P.Consul-General for Khorassan (No.84 of 14.12.37)mdJLUUL^ 14th Ueoembe*, 19^. — 1«M i&gt;«paaptaa ;at, Oa the receipt of pear Joafldential letter i&gt;*c • Ho« P 7^ - ll/^d of the ii^xd koTembex f about the «x- pexieriuee of British aabjeot* traTelUa^ la lxun # the Minister aarefully ooaBldered the eag^eetioa that pahliaitp should mw he given to inaideate of the hind reeently re ported by bqeixe* It would aert&amp;i&amp;ly he onl^ what the Ixanlaa aeverameat daeerre if there were atieh pahlialt^, hat in view of the very resent row over the ho oh *By trder of the ShfeUr’ 'mo *«*« ©«* deepateh to the Foreign cf?lee ho. 4BB of the 6th Bov ember, of whiah &amp; was enaloaed in oar deepa oh to yea !!©• of the same date^ , the Minister thinks that it would he hotter at present to awe the threat of pabllelty rather fch*a ptiblialty itself* fhe threat should he mm ef fee tire, withoat eaasing an explosion from the All-Si* hest, which might hare onfere&amp;een aon&amp;eqaenoea* /** The eternal Affairs Jeparhneat, The government of India, «ew Belhi*5* W* e^ujXode a csopy of th« whioh the ■udniste* la aoooxdintcl^ aezkiing to idl v Jnd^r-oooretary at th« Miaiatfy of ^oroiga Affairs 9 on the general ques tion of the ill-treatment of travellers in lran 9 and men tioning oases reported by Squire in the two despatches to which your letter refers* 4* We are sending copies of this letter and its enclosure* and also copies of your letter of thu £3rd November 9 to the foreign uffioe Mo* 45h and to £hora$saa Ito * B4* Yours ever. Jhanoaxy*go^y 1933 j D.0.HO.V.768-H/36. 'he 23rd November 1937 ght Ohanoery f iivite your attention to (SeapatoheB from His a,]e8ty 1 s Oonsul General for iliorasan, Hos. 85 anfi 86 Gated the 13th October and End November 1937 respectively, regarding ill-treatment of Bii tish 2. are thinking that it might perhaps he salutary for the &lt;*-ranians if publicity were given to incidents of this nature in the Indian press, without of course revealing the source of the information, but we would be glad to be furnished with the views of His Majesty’s rinister on the suggestion in the first instance. subjects travelling in East Iran fours ever, SXfEflUAL AFFAIRS DSPAHTFEITT To The Chancery British Legation Tehran.®it sa#5«ad th« a»ual trunmlt vl«&amp; ▼alic for flfio«n Cayo from aat« of Ills ontry int&gt; Xraft h&gt;»ro^i. He orooooa th« frontier at c&amp;out noon on t^i# 15th Ootober 19i&gt;7 aa tho 6ay of oritry t« not oountofi an one of the fifteen £aye v his transit Tisa was not due to expire until the atenta# of th^ Seth otoher. ven on a strlot ealoulatlon of hours it was until midday* t Tehran rr. ubairi fell ill &amp;ru; was therefore delayed for some hays and only reached Hashed on Thursday # the B 8 th rotober, at about 6 'e had hoped to be able to continue his Joiirney ths ?i*xl day to Herat and so had not applied for any extension of his transit Yisa* K* found, howeter, that no transport was leasing fbr Hsmt on the doth or 3oth nnc he, therefore* on the startling of the Both at about 10 o’clock (the prerlous day being riday and all offloss closed) presented himself at the Central Police station and ap tiled fo tax •xtwnal'm of hi# *r«n«u ▼!»». H« vf Q « lately |&gt;iiie»« unf #r * ur *«' 1 io * o» eratnyac. the pwiai &lt;t his ■*!«», k«Dt la o«%o&lt;ly / whilst{ In any further communication on this subject, please quote N( t /SPV and address —not to any person by name, Init to— ' The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I, |Ml&gt;iA UIBLCJ THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his V?'' compliments to ^ ^ compliments to ?A $ fu.dC**- an&lt; ^ , ^ direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, £ i , 193/ H 5 u- .1^ ■% Reference to previous corrcspo?idence : /o- XM.f * Kt 3T33 y 2.0 . Description of Enclosuix. Name and Date. Subject. J /t-rzeo*. JCopy (E 7496/584/34) N o. 567/15/57 Copies to Mr# Rendel m Sir H.A.F. Metcalfe. 20th November, 1937 Dear Squire, I had a go at Samiy to-day about the treatment of Consular Officers and quoted to him a good many of the recent incidents reported from East Iran adding also one or two from Kermanshah* I urged that, even if the Iranian Government thought it was still impossible to allow their citizens to frequent foreign Consulates freely, yet it must surely be possible to arrange that matters should not be carried to such ridiculous lengths as is still the case. I said that the situation at Meshed was particularly disappointing to me, as we had reorganised the post in order to avoid the suspicions (though unwarranted) which the i Iranians had felt in the past: the result had been that the Consulate-General was still treated exactly as before. I also tried the argument that the Iranians were doing very bad propaganda for themselves in this business: foreigners who lived in Tehran left Iran having enjoyed their stay and with every sympathy for the country. With what feelings, on the other hand, must the unfortunate foreign official who lived in the provinces leave Iran? 2. Samiy said that he realised the position and was sorry for it: but he thought it inevitable. It came from dre Esquire, I.C.S. , His Majesty*s Consul-General for Khorassan at MESHED.from the history of the past and from the nationalism 'which is raging everywhere'. The treatment of foreign consulates largely resulted from the behaviour of the Russians. The Iranian Government must see that propaganda and undue foreign influence in the provinces did not recur, and the representatives of all nations were treated alike. In fact the usual argument. I said this was all very well, but surely senior police officials were going much further than the Government would wish: it could not be their intention to frighten away harmless tradesmen, visiting ladies etc. After various repetitions of our arguments Samiy said that, if I would let him have an Aide-Memoire of actual cases he would speak to the Prime Minister: he seemed to agree that the senior police officials were exceeding their instructions, and he would see if anything » could be done. 3. I will let him have a note of the sort of cases we object to and we shall see if there is any result. He would I think like to help, to some extent anyhow, but it is doubtful whether he has much power to do so. 4. I am sending copies of this letter to Metcalfe at New Delhi and Rendel in the Foreign Office. (Signed) H.J. SeymourMr. Squire Mr. Rendel Sir H.A..F. Metcalfe AIDE-MEMOIRE Standing instructions have been issued to all officials in the provinces limiting the number of those who may accept invitations from foreign Consulates. In many towns it appears that these instructions are interpreted not only as prohibiting all non-official Iranians from accepting hospitality from foreign Consulates, but also as requiring that a strict watch should be kept on Consulates, and that callers should be questioned as to their business and in some cases even forbidden to enter the Consulate concerned again. 2. The following are some of the instances of such action by local authorities which have been reported to His Majesty 1 s Legation. At Kermanshah in February 1937, a weaver who has often visited the British Consulate to receive orders for curtains and other goods sent by British residents in Tehran and elsewhere, was told by the police that if he entered the Consulate again, he would be punished. Similarly in June last a man who came to the Consulate to buy some old tyres was summoned to the Police Station and cross-examined about the reasons for his visit. At Shiraz it is stated that no one may enter the Consulate without prior permission from the Chief of Police. At Kerman, when His Majesty’s Consul gave a reception on the occasion of the Coronation of His Majesty King George VI, a police officer was stationed in the road outside the Consulate and openlyopenly turned away a number of Iranians who had been invited to attend. At Zabul in February six Iranians who had played football with members of the Consulate staff were arrested, kept in custody for thirty hours, and only released on furnishing a security of Rials 2000 each that they would not again enter the Consulate. At Birjand the policeman appointed to watch His Majesty’s Vice-Consul caused him much inconvenience by following him closely and openly everywhere, even into the shops of Indian traders. At Meshed tradesmen have at times been forbidden to enter the Consulate General without special permission being given on each occasion. A constant watch is kept on the Consulate-General by a number of police agents. An Iranian ferrash*s wife who went to visit her sister in the town was followed into her sister’s house by three policemen who questioned her about her movements. In October two Iranian ladies from Shiraz, who are friends of the Iranian wife of a member of the staff of the Consulate-General and who had visited her in the Consulate-General, were followed to their lodgings by a detective who told them that if they entered the Consulate-General again they would be imprisoned at once. In August the owner of a garden near Meshed which had been hired for a month by His Majesty’s Consul-General, with the knowledge of His Excellency the Governor-General, was arrested and charged with having dealings with the British Consul-General. 3. It will thus be seen that in the majority of towns where there are British Consulates, not only is all social intercourse with members of the staff forbidden but Iranians who have ordinary and entirely legitimate business with the Consulates are liable to be closely examined and even punishedpunished if they enter a Consulate. In general it must he said that the local authorities appear to interpret their instructions in a manner which, it is believed, can hardly be intended by the Imperial Government.Notes for His Majesty’s Minister’s interview with Monsieur Samiy. 1 • The general boycott of all Consulates . We know that last No-Ruz a circular was sent to all provinces by the Ministry of the Interior, laying down that the only officials allowed to accept invitations from Consulates are Governors-General and Governors, Assistant Governor Chiefs of Police and Heads of Municipalities, These instructions were passed on to all officials, including foreigners in the employment of the Iranian Government, The instructions of course merely re-stated the existing position. The Coronation gave an opportunity to see how the instructions were observed. On our instructions our Consuls invited everyone they could think of. Everywhere these invitations made a stir. Every Governor telegraphed to Tehran for special instructions, and in every case the reply was that the previous circular must be obeyed. Everywhere the only civil officials who attended receptions were those formally permitted to do so. The only people who disobeyed the instructions were Colonel Bayendor, General Mu’ini, and the General Chief of Staff at Tabriz. Scarcely any non-official Iranians accepted their invitations. They were undoubtedly told not to. At Meshed the police telephoned to people invited to Mr. Squire's dance to tell them not to come. At Shiraz no one is allowed to enter the Consulate without the prior permission of the Chief of Police. At Kerman a police officer was stationed a little way from the Consulate to note who entered it and to turn away people not entitled to attend.(loO 2. Spying on Consulates and persecution of any Iranians who have any dealings with them. We have much evidence that a strict watch is kept on all Consulates, and that any Iranian who enters a Consulate is liable to strict questioning and often persecution. Most of our evidence is from East Iran, but the following has been reported from Kermanshah . (a) A local weaver has made many curtains etc., for the Consulate, to the order of British February in reply to a request to call at the Consulate with patterns for an order from the Legation, he said that he had been told that if he went again to the Consulate he would be punished. From East Iran we have the following evidence. ZABUL . Football has been played for many years in the Consulate grounds, and Iranians, friends and relations of the staff were in the habit of coming to play. Mr. Squire suggested in February that matches formerly played with subjects in Tehran and elsewhere. In (b) The man who gives His Majesty’s Consul Persian lessons asked to be allowed to come after dark to avoid being seen by the plain-clothes man watching the Consulate. (c) In June a man who came to the Consulate to buy some old tyres was summoned to the Police Station next day and cross-examined about the reasons for his visit the local military might be resumed. Next day six Iranians who had been playing as usual were arrested on their way outout of the grounds, kept in custody for thirty hours and * r only released on furnishing a security of Rials 2000 each that they would not again enter the Consulate. They were also told that they were to say they had been arrested for gambling. BIRJAND . His Majesty’s Vice-Consul has had to complain more than once that he has been much inconvenienced by the too close attentions of the plain-clothes policeman appointed to spy on his movements, who openly followed him wherever he went, even into the shops of Indian traders. MESHED , provides a number of bad cases. (a) There has been at times a virtual commercial boycott - tradesmen, artisans and workmen being forbidden to enter the Consulate-General, at any rate without special permission. This was lifted for the Coronation festivities. The photographer employed on that occasion received a special visit from a policeman, who said he needn* t ask for permission this time. (b) A constant watch is kept on the Consulate-General, and all callers are watched and questioned. Thus a ferrash’s wife (an Iranian) who went out of the Consulate-General to pay a visit in the town was followed right into her sister’s home by three policemen, who wanted to know her business. In reply to her remonstrances they explained apologetically that they were only carrying out instructions. (c) Similarly, on the 3rd October two Iranian women from Shiraz, friends of the Iranian wife of the Indian Attache, who were in Meshed on a pilgrimage, came to spend the day in the Consulate-General. When they leftleft a detective followed them to their lodgings and questioned them rudely, warning them that if they were seen entering the Consulate again they would be imprisoned at once. They had previously accepted an invitation to dinner later, but were so frightened that they returned to Shiraz at once. (d) In the summer Mr. Squire hired a garden for his family at a village named Naukandar, about 20 miles from Meshed, after informing the Governor-General of his intention and learning from him that there was no objection. On the 27th August Mr. Squire learnt that the owner of the garden, quite a poor man by name Kerbelai Akbar, had been arrested and charged with having dealings with the British Consul-General. Pour other leading men of the place were also arrested, although they had had no dealings with Mr. Squire. Mr. Squire immediately took the case up with the Governor-General and Kerbelai Akbar was released shortly after, the Governor-General explaining that he had been arrested on quite another charge. The case inevitably recalls that of the Headman of Talk in December, 1935.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000015_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3467</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000015</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3467</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/60(2) ‘Persia; Treatment of Foreigners; Position of British subjects, British Consular Representatives, etc.,’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-03-26T22:03:11</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">per</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (302 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 304; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence, reports and other papers concerning the ill-treatment of British subjects in Persia [Iran] by the Persian authorities. The file is a direct chronological continuation of Coll 28/60(1) ‘Persia. Treatment of Foreigners; Position of British subjects, and British Consular Representatives, etc.’ (IOR/L/PS/12/3466). The file covers: the treatment and deportation of British subjects (Berberis, or Hazara Khawari) from the Khorasan province of Persia into neighbouring British India (Pakistan); an incident occurring in 1938 in which a bus carrying British consular officials was commandeered by an officer of the Persian military; claims of discrimination against British subjects in Meshed [Mashhad]; a boycott imposed upon the British Consulate at Meshed by the Persian Government; correspondence describing the general attitude of the Persian authorities towards British persons in Persia; a ‘Report on the Attitude towards the British in Persia in March 1938’, written by Lieutenant Ian Hallam Lyall-Grant of the Royal Engineers (ff 134-142).The file’s principal correspondents are: Nevile Montagu Butler of the British Legation in Tehran; HM’s Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary, Horace James Seymour; HM’s Consul at Meshed, Giles Frederick Squire; Charles William Baxter and Herbert Lacy Baggallay of the Foreign Office; the Government of India.The file contains a single item in Persian, a typewritten letter (accompanied by English translation) from the British Embassy in Tehran to the Iranian Minister for Foreign Affairs, dated 23 April 1947 (f 5).The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Iranian Army</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Ethnic discrimination</topic></subject><subject><topic>Ethnic groups</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Iran, Pahlavi dynasty</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Meshed</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Khorasan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Foreigners</topic></subject><subject><topic>Deportation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000015#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>