<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000363_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T14:48:08.894Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">4987a 2000 12.30 Previous File. P. * POLITICAL (EXTERNAL) DEPARTMENT. 19 ^ 3 . SUBJECT: QrvtqLO ~ E U-V £ P YEAH, This File contains the following papers 19 &gt; a ' • 19 . P. 19 . P. 19 19 . P. 19 . P. llir Papers may be removed from or placed within this File only by the Political Registry.to lint fJ O u [Vo a . V* cqp.M * u (3 5827/6/34) £: * f J2L?2syv3 FILE COPY /?-7~. /Zas*j/^ ,4^9. i 4'r'^ i: 10 ^- No. 387. (45/179/43) /■\ Sir, With the ConMi of th« nts BRITISH \LSr T § tlieCTjci42j ' Tsmtsr.: Stats /O ^jo/yCoo^U. / vhxufa. Hfa tuyrt 'tfe / ^ &gt; 10th Sept'ember, iy43/^ a Ia.CWvUXa~ ( TViC AxO^O ' ^oUtX^ I^crrvft? ^«4^&gt;-*v7 ^ ^ ^ wfc )- 3 .^^- With reference to your telegram No. 523 of May 29th, authorising the grant of a further £10,000 to the Anglo- Iranian Relief Fund, I have the honour to forward herewith \ (*) q ~ statement of the position of the Fund on July 20th, ) y/ allocation of grants for the fourth quarter. a after the /t) 2. The fourth quarter’s activities would normaHy'T'*’ have been brought to a close on August 23rd, twelve months after the inception of the Fund. As, however, the quarterly accounts of receipts and expenditure now being rendered, the first of which was forwarded under cover of my despatcli^fj' No. 381 ( 816/31/43) of September 6th, are to fo-llow the l/W European quarters, it ha a been thought desi.rable to prolong the fourth quarter until September 30th and to begin the new quarter’s activities on October 1st. Sufficient funds ^ - were available for this purpose, expenditure during the //' summer months having been on a reduce! scale. 3. As foreseen in my despatch No. 164 (4 5/107/45) of April 26th, medical relief work has claimed increased attention during the summer months. A supply of British patent medicines to the value of £l,G.C was obtained through the United Kingdom Commercial Corporation and distributed to suitable institutions, including the C/.S. hospitals at Isfahan and Kerman and the Persian Government hospital at Ahwaz. A share of these medicines was also given to a small dispensary financed by the Fund which has beep opened in Sennandathe principal tov/n of the province of Kurdestan, on the initiative and under the control of Major R.S. Oakshott, O.B.E., the Area Liaison Officer there. According to a report from the latter dated August 10th, 'the propaganda effect (of,this dispensary) has exceeded expeqtations and the Imam Jomeh (Chief Priest) on Friday quitb spontaneously made a most flattering reference to the clinic in the big mosque, praising the British for their help to the poor of the district'. In Yezd, a share of the same consignment of medicines has been distributed under the supervision of the Reverepd H.C. Gurney, C.M.S. Mr. Consul..Barlow wrote from Kerman on June 25th: 'In Yezd also we have earned some measure of goodwill; in particular both doctors and patients are enthusiastic about the drugs recently sent. One doctor rang up Gurney .and d;old him he had performed what seemed to him a ’miracle’ of life saving with a drug which he had riever had the chance of handling before'. 4. Apart from drugs, the commodities most in demand for poor relief work are sugar, tea and cloth, and special efforts have been made to obtain supplies of these. By arrangements with the Middle 3ast Supply Centre, Tehran, we have succeeded in purchasing twenty tons of -sugar from stocks held by the United Kingdom Commercial Corporation,at Khor ram shah r and an order has been placed in Bombay for half a ton of tea, which is now being shipped. Cloth is more difficult to procure at reasonable prices, but we are trying to obtain supplies through the Government of India. 5. The activities of the Relief Committee have continued to provide useful material for our publicity; a collection of items published since March 31st is transmitted as the second enclosure to this despatch. As regards the direct propaganda effect of the Fund in the provincial centres where relief 'work has been undertaken, the majority of the reports which I have received from the consular officers concerned are sufficiently encouraging to justify the continuation of the work in the present circumstances. Moreover, I do not think the Fund’s activities pass altogether unnoticed in Tehran. At any rate, an article^in a Tehran newspaper a few days ago, before taking the Allies to task fqr the recent arrest of the Persian suspects, found it necessary to admit that the Allies had given the Persians 'bread, medicines and lorries': the allusion to medicines may well include medical relief work under the Fund. I may mention also that at a meeting of the Relief Committee on July 19th, Dr. Taheri, one of the Persian members (he is Vice President of the Majlis), proposed a motion in the following terms, expressing appreciation of the valuable help given by His Majesty’s Government through the Funa, m organising food relief during the past winter and spring „ ver y glad to see that the condition of the ^people s food supply at the present time, by comparison ^with when the Committee was first formed, has made conspicuous progress, thanks to the assistance rendered lf ^y British Government and the relief committees. f w Relieve that the Chairman, His Excellency Monsieur Ala '{Vice Chairman) and the other members of the Committee »r a ^ e n? accord ^ith me and will permit that this should be inserted in the minutes of today’s meetinp-'. Detailed evidence of the usefulness of the Fund from the propaganda point of yiew, expecially in South Persia, where our interests are greatest, may be found in a demi-official letter from Mr. Holman of this Legation to Mr. Caccia in the eastern Department of the Foreign Office No. 1124/10/43 of August 13th last. . ' • - * l r I 6. Private donations to the Fund during the fourth quarter have included a gift of Rls. 25,000 from Consortium Kampsax, the Danish consulting engineers. m 7 9 TJie Glance standing to the credit of the Fund °- n .^ ugust , 31st &gt; after the allocation of grants to Rio 730 U 50 0 to ' tallin g Rls. 1,012,300, amounted 10 K1S.730,509.80 or approximately £5,700. Of this balance however, approximately £2,500 is already earmarked for /further© further expenditure debit able to the current quarter, in respect of the sugar mentioned in paragraph 4 above, the cost of which is not yet known, and of additional supplies of patent medicines which have been ordered from the United Kingdom Commercial Corporation. We shall thus enter the December quarter with only some £3,000 in hand, and I have the honour to recommend that, if possible, a further grant of £10,000 may be made by His Majesty’s Government to meet expenditure under the Fund during the three months October 1st to December 31st. Detailed proposals for relief work during these first three winter months have not yet been received from the provincial centres concerned, but expenditure is likely to be considerably heavier than during the summer. 8. I shall be grateful for a telegraphic reply to this despatch in order that the new quarter’s programme may be arranged as soon as possible after October 1st. In spite of the good harvest there will be much distress this winter, on account of high prices for which the presence of the Allies is largely responsible, of shortage of goods, and, probably, of epidemics of typhus and typhoid such as occurred last winter. I consider that it is incumbent upon us to help to relieve this distress, and politic to use the method of relief - a method which I regard as having been on the whole a decided success - to counteract the factors making for unpopularity in this country. I have, etc. , (Signed). R.W. Bullard.Copy ^GLO-IRANIAIT K -LI^?AIND Position at July £Qth, 1945. r; i b 04 v». i 'i**. t* ’yntontt-.* ■ - BUSMIRP,. Third quarter, 20/2/42 - gQ/6/43. Seventeen tons of dates were imported from Iraq, for distribution to the poor. 500 c.c• of T.A.B. vaccine were imported from India. Some of this was handed ov-r to the local Iranian Government hospital and the balance was advertised in a local newspaper as bavins' been provided by the Anglo—Iranian Relief Fund and as being available .for free issue on application• A caravanserai for destitutes was opened on June 22nd, under the control of the British Consulate-General. The inmates, who number IRQ, receive free food, shelter and lighting- v ork on a new stone facing and a concrete spillway for the rainwaterrdam was very nearly completed during the quarter, Both the dam and the , ab-ambar t (watyr-tank) in course of construction in the town are expected to oe ready veil before the next rains. A gift of Rls.10,000 was made to the Bushire Charitable Committee, to provide clgthing for destitute persons. Fourth quarter, 1/7/45 - o0/9/4o. The following grants have been made:- Rls. Grant for caravanserai for destitute persons 90,000 Issue of clothing to poor villagers 52,000 Provision of free burial for paupers 6,000 148,000 SHIRAZ. Third quarter . Medical attention and financial and practical^, assistance to in- and out-patients and their dependents continued to be given during the third quart*r under the bare of the C.M.S. hospital. Hudh helpful work was done and relief in one form or another was afforded to 132 men, 340 women and 27 children at a cost of Rls-.i02,410, i.e. an average of Rls.206 p r head. , Arrangements/Arrangements were made for a food kitchen, fr-ora which 11,660 free hot meals were servedJaetween February 27th and April 25rd, at 0 total cost of Rls.45,658.25. fhe scheme was discontinued when the outbreak of typhus and typhoid made the assembling of large crowds undesirable. A donation of Rls.15,000 was made -to the. S.ociety for the Protection of Children, for the institution of a Foundling Home. A donation of Rls.18,000 vas made to the Central Shiraz Relief Organisation for the maintenance of a number of additionals beds, urgently required, in the maternity Home. A second allocation of Rls.25,600 was made to the relief scheme for assisting necessitous school boys and girls and students. The total sum of Rls.51,200 given for this purpose was brought up to Rls.68,750 by private donations to the Department of education, and with this money altogether 260 boys were fitted out with suits and 150 girls were provided with frocks and shoes^ Payments in cash and gifts of food or clothing were made to particularly deserving and necessitous cases at a cost of Rls.8,030. This included the gift at Noruz to fcvery in-patient of the C.M.S. Hospital of;a parcel containing sweets, cigarettes, a box of matches, soap, a pair of socks or stockings and a handkerchief. The parcels, which were decorated with cro.ssed British and Iranian flags and inscribed in Persian- 'A New Year Gift from the Anglo- Iranian Relief Committee' - were distributed by the wife of the British Consul and w-ere gre-atly appreciated. Fourth quarter . The following grant has been made:- For cash disbursements at the discretion of the British Consul at necessitous and deserving cases j Rls. 12,800 KmRMAN. Third quarter. The Kerman food kitchen remained open till Day 17th. Altogether 205,908 cheap meals were provided at a total cost of Rls.448,000. The C.k.S. hospital continued to treat poor patients at the expense of the Fund. Fourth/© Fourth quarter . The following grants have been made:- £200 for the Kerman Orphanage for installing bathrooms and now kitchens £100 for the G.M.S hospital for continuing free facilities for poor patients Supply of medicines from the U.K.C.C. for the G.M.S. hospital to the value of £200 25,600 12,800 25,600 64,000 YEZD. Third quarter . The sura of £200 voted fer food relief during the third quarter reached Yezd too late for the Rev.H.G. Gurney, C.M.S. , to be able to arrange for the continuation of the existing food relief scheme, the last distribution of food having taken place on April 19th. Further food relief in Yezd has therefore been postponed until next winter. The grant of £200 for drugs v/as used to purchase drugs from the U.K.C.G. These drugs are being distributed free (except for a supply of insulin, which is not a drug used by the very poor and for which a reasonable fee is therefore charged). The drugs are issued either directly through local doctors or, in the case of ampoules and tablets, through the Rev. H.G. Gurney against doctors’ prescriptions. Certain of the drugs are being used in a bi-weekly clinic for the treatment of syphilis cases. ISFAHAN. Third quarter. Rice and lentils were distributed families, each family receiving 6 kilos of lentils. to of about 5,000 rice and 3 kilos The C.M.S. Hospitals treated 302 in-patients and 225 out-patients with funds provided by the Committee. Drugs to the value of £200 were obtained for the C.M.S. Hospitals from the U.K.C.C. The Fereidan Armenian Hospital received a donation of £50, and drugs to the value of £100 were obtained for the hospital from the U.K.C.C.0 Fourth Quarter . The following grants have been made:- Distribution of rice and lentils Advance for purchase of clothing and fuel for the December quarter £600 for the C.M.S. hospitals for the treatment of about 60 in-patients and 50 - out-patients a month £50 a month to the Fereidan Armenian hospital for the 4 months June - September 192.000 256.000 76,800 25,600 550,400 K3RMANSHAH. Third quarter . With the advent of warmer weather, the four popular restaurants were all closed down by May 22nd. The food relief scheme, which was inaugurated on January 27th, cost altogether Rls .242,266.10, and. probably saved the lives of many half-starved people, besides satisfying the hunger of many others. Cloth to the value of £200 has been ordered from the Government factory at Bohshahr, but has not yet arrived. RAMADAN. Third quarter . The £200 granted for the distribution of shirts and trousers to the poor was spent on obtaining 640 metres of cloth from Isfahan sufficient for making some 250 shirts and trou se rs . Fourth quarter. Arrangements have been made to purchase medicines for the Ramadan Government Hospital from the U.K.C.C., with a sum of £100 allocated for medical relief in the second quarter but not previously spent. MESHED/ME SHED, ^,BUL. LAHIJAN and BIRJAND . Third quarter . 0 Drugs to the value of 2,600 Rupees were purchased in India from the grant of £1,000 allocated for this purpose. With the grant of £100 allocated to ZAHIDAN for medical relief in the first quarter, arrangements were made to purchase £50 worth of drugs in India. The remaining £50 has “been set aside for defraying expenses incurred in the treatment of Iranian typhus patients hy the Senior British Medical Officer in Zahidan. Fourth quarter . A grant of £600 has 'been made of which £100 is to he allocated to Zahul 76, 800 AHWA2 ♦ ‘ Third quarter . The supply of free bread from a special bakery was continued. Arrangements were made for the maintenance of 15 beds in the Iranian Civil Hospital at Ahwaz for Anglo-_ Iranian Relief Committee patients at a cost of Rls. 6,500 a month. Fourth quarter . The following grants have been made:- Grant for the upkeep of 15 A.I.R.F. beds in the Iranian Civil Hospital for three months 19,500 Supply of medicines from the U.K.C.C. for the Iranian Civil Hospital to the value of £100 12,800 £200 for the Abadan and Khorramshahr typhus control camps 25,600 57,900 TEHRAN/TEHRAN ■■H Third quarter. Various houses damaged by the heavy spring rains were repaired, wholly or in part, at a total cost of Rls.10,500. A sum of Rls.1,680 was paid to the authorities of the British Army Typhus Hospital, for incidental expenses incurred in the treatment of Iranian typhus patients. A donation of Rls.25,000 was received from Messrs. Kampsax. SENNANBAJ. Third quarter . With the sum of £100 allotted to Kermanshah in the first quarter for relief work in Sennandaj, arrangements were made to open a small dispensary under the control of Maj. R.S. Oakshott, O.B.E., the British Area Liaison Officer, giving free treatment to about 30 poor patients a day. Fourth quarter. Supply of medicines from the U.K.C.C. for the A.I.R.F. dispensary, to the value of £100 12,800 BANDAR ABBAS. Third quarter . The £500 given for food relief was earmarked for the purchase of dates from Basra and medicines from India, orders for which were placed. Fourth quarter . The following grants have been made;- £150 for local Poor Relief Society 19,200 £300 for supplying wheat to bakeries for issue as free bread 3o,400 £150 for free distribution of cloth 19,200 £100 for cash relief in cases of destitution 12,800 89,600 TOTAL ALLOCATIONS FOR THE FOURTH QUARTER Rls. 1,012,300PUBLICITY GIVEN TO THE WORKING OF THE ANGLO-IRANIAN RELIEF PUNP^ April - September, 1943 . Daily News. Tehran. 7th April. 1943 . In addition to the construction of a rain-water dam at Undur- Bundur the work of the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee in Bushire has included provision for the erection of a large ^h-amhar in the centre of the town, the ground for which has heen given hy a local philanthropist. Dates, rice and cash donations have 'been sent to the local Anjoman-i-Mustamandan (Charitahle Relief Committee;. Dates have also 'been sent to relieve distress in all the coastal areas from Hist Daudi in the north to Lingeh in the south. Gifts of cotton cloth have 'been made to the poor in Lingeh and tea and sugar are 'being sent for distribution in local centres of the Shibkuh ports. Daily News. Tehran. 30th May, 1943 . Supplies of a number of important drugs to the value of Rials 19,655, generously donated to the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee by Mr. D. Kettaneh, have been sent to hospitals in Isfahan, Kerman and Shiraz for medical work there amongst the poor. Translation of an article published in the Bushire newspaper 'Khali n-i-Iran^ of June 10th. 1945 . WE ONLY TALK. 200 words are not equal to half an act. There is water in the jug, and we are wandering thirsty. For some months water has been the only topic of conversation in public and in the newspapers. People are talking much about it, one mentioning Khaviz and Shabankareh waters, and the other xialaileh and Chah Talkh. Engineers also have so far drawn 30-40 thousana Tomans as travelling expenses from Tehran to Bushire ana return; and people’s opinions are based on their statements. ihey make comprehensive records of the case; but nothing has yet happenea. Where is Bushire’s water supply ? Bushire people have not considered the means God granted to them; they go and search about Khaviz and Shabankareh; then they express their disappointment. It would be better for these gentlemen to go by car 5 metres from the Under Bundur valley at Bushire. This valley th nus of rain water floods during hundreds of years has P£eP a £ec i.o for this time. In a few hours it will be full; they have it and perhaps have also thought of it. ^his valle,, it constructed ?n a technical method with cement and covered with^ timber will ensure Bushire drinking water at least Though As an experiment Mr. X.Y.Z. made a dam in a part of it. -hough the dam has now been faced the valley s sides have no cemented aVd some water has escaped into the ground. Still, a considerable amount of water was held up in the valley, sufficient for more than a year of Bushire’s consumption. Of course, when later rains fall, more water will be caught m th spot. In addition, wells situated in the valley and it&amp; neighbourhood are all full of sweet water, 0 Q S tat Bushire and its suburbs. In my opinion before it is too late the respected Engineers should follow this liable act of hr. • and leave the question of waters which are f r a - Y +hio va ii ev a impracticable, and use their utmost efforts to make this reservoir, such as are constructed in many great foreig Mf-; -Daily News. Tehran. 20th June, 1943 . The British Government have contributed a further Rials 1,280,000 to the Anglo-Iranian Relief Puna, thus bringing the total of their contributions to this Fund to Rials 5,120,000. Daily News. Tehran. 7th July. 1945 . The food kitchen set up by the Anglo-Iranian Relief Gommittee in Kerman last November remained open for six months and provided altogether 203,906 cheap meals for the poor people of Kerman during that period. The work of the Gommittee was greatly assisted by the local Supply Department who provided rice for the food kitchen at favourable rates. In addition, presents of dates were received from H.E. the Ustandar and Messrs. A.K. Amery and M.K. Amery. Daily News, Tehran. 8th July. 1943 . The four popular restaurants opened by the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee in Kermanshah last winter served cheap meals to the poor throughout the four months Bahman 1321 - Ordibehesht 1322 at a total cost of Rials 242,226. The Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee in Isfahan recently distributed six kilos of rice and three kilos of lentils to each of 3,000 poor families. The Committee has also arranged for 500 patients of local hospitals to be given free medical treatment at the expense of the Angloriranian Relief Fund. Daily News. Tehran. 10th July, 1943 . ANGLO-IRANIAN RELIEF COMMITTEE HELPS POOR IN SHIRAZ. A local Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee has been set up in Shiraz consisting of the Farmandar, the local managers of the A.I.O.C. and the I.B.I., Dr. Zabi Ghurban and the British Consul. Since 1st Esfand the following charitable relief has been organised in Shiraz at the expense of the Anglo-Iranian Relief Fund:- Medical attention and financial assistance has been given to nearly 500 poor hospital patients and at Noruz each in-patient of the local British hospital received a special gift parcel of sweets, cigarettes, soap, etc. Of hot meals 11,660 were served to poor persons from a free food kitchen. A donation of Rials 15,000 was made to the local Society for the Protection of Children, for instituting a Founding Home, and a /l donation of Rials 18,000 to the Central Shiraz Relief Organisation for the provision of a number of additional beds in the local Maternity Home. Sums totalling Rials 68,750 were given to provide clothes for poor school children. Suits were bought for 260 boys, and 150 girls received frocks and shoes. The principal contributor to the Anglo-Iranian Relief Fund, from which this and other relief work is financed, is the British Government, which has made several large donations totalling over five million Rials. Other important contributors have been the A.I.O.C. and the I.B.I. and the Fund has also benefited by numerous pj'iya'te donations both British and Iranian.A number of poor householders in Tehran whose homes were damaged by the heavy spring rains took advantage of the offer made by the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee some two months ago, to apply for assistance in carrying out necessary repairs. In five cases repairs have been effected under the direction of Messrs. Kampsax, who gave their technical advice without charge. No further repairs are contemplated in view of information received from Tehran Municipality that this form of relief work has been undertaken by the Tehran Central Relief Association. Daily News. Tehran. 26th July. 194 5. At a recent charity performance of the film ’’Captains of the ’’Clouds” at the Cinema Horaay in Meshed, the sum of Rials 27,770 was collected for the Anglo-Iranian Relief Fund. Those present at the performance included H.E. the Governor-General and many leading officials and citizens of Meshed. Daily News. Tehran. 3rd August. 1945 . Work under the Anglo—Iranian Relief Fund has recently been extended to include Bandar Abbas. A local Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee has been set up there, the members of which include the Governor, the local Managers of the Banque-Mellie and the A.I.O.G., Agha Haji Mushir (Deputy for Bandar Abbas), and the British Consul. Arrangements have been made to purchase dates and wheat for distribution to the poor and the Committee is also investigating the possibility of importing supplies of medicines from India. Funds totalling Rls. 153,600 have been placed at the disposal oi the Bandar Abbas Committee by the central Anglo-I ranian Keliet Committee in Tehran. Daily News. Tehran. 13th Aug ust. 1943. ANGLO-IRANIAN RELIEF COMMITTEE IN BUSHIRE. The activities of the local Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee in Bushire during the three months April - June included.- The import of 17 tons of dates from Iraq for food relief; The free distribution of anti-typhoid vaccine; The maintenance of a caravanserai providing free food, shelter and lighting for 160 destitute inmates; The gift of Rls. 10,000 to the Bushire Charitable Committee, to provide clothing for destitutes. The chairman of the Relief Committee is the British Consul-General, Bushire. Daily News. Tehran. 26th August, 1943.. ANGLO-IRANIAN RELIEF COMMITTEE OPENS FREE ^ CLINIC IN SENNANDAJ: BRITISH DRUG SUPPLIES. A free clinic recently opened ty the Anglo-Iranian Relief immittee in Sennandaj is reported to te giving , some thirty poor patients daily. The Anglo-1 ranian Relief Committee recently obtained a ipply of important drugs, to the value of £1,000, for meaica^- • relief work in the provinces. These drugs, all of them British products, have Been distributed as follows:- Jond-i-Shahpur Hospital, Ahwaz; Government Hospital, Hamadan; C.M.S. Hospitals, Isfahan and Kerman; Anglo-Iranian Relief Clinic, Sennandaj; Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee'ts representative Yezd. Daily News. Tehran. 3rd September. 1943 . ANGLO-IRANIAN RELIEF COMMITTEE’S ACTIVITIES. The following is a summary of a report on the acti\dties of the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee which appeared in a Meshed newspaper some few weeks ago:- ”The Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee which was established last ’’summer in Tehran extended its range of activities^© Meshed in ’’February of this year. The committee in Meshed is presided over ”by the British Consul-General and its members include various ’’distinguished residents of Meshed, including a lady well known for^ ”her charitable work. The following is a summary of the committee s ’’activities: - Purchase of drugs . **A donation of Rls. 30,000 has been made to the poor house at ’’Zabul. ”Rls. 10,000 have been allocated to the purchase of drugs for ’’medical relief work in Birjand under the super-vision of H.^. ^mir ”A’ lam. **170 suits of clothing have been purchased for poor persons in ’’Meshed; charcoal has been bought for 63 poor families; rice has ’’been distributed among 266 people in poor families; and clothing ha ’’been distributed to 473 poor persons through the Anjuraan-i-Parvin. ”A sum of Rls. 4,000 has been paid as an aid to the families oi ’’discharged prisoners and help has been given to 91 droshky-drivers, ”to enable them to maintain their horses and continue business. Medical treatment. ”A donation has been made to the American hospital for medical ’’treatment of the poor and the provision of free druss, food and ’’clothing. iiA sura of Rls. 128,000 has be*en allocated to the purchase of ••drucrs from India for medical poor relief and drugs worth Rls. ”25,000 have already been purchased and are due to arrive shortly. ”The total sums ’’charitable purposes thus spent by the Meshed committee for during last winter exceed Rials 150,000.’wmmmmmrnMmmmmam f r s ^&gt; 1.(^ i'// FOREIGN OFFICE, 28th August, '1^4^. /! r-v r* j 4d5b 2,8 AU(i 1943 / ai V With the Compliments of the (E 5024/6/34). y n(j ; ev Secratary of State f ©f For**gr» Affaire x. )^? You will remember expressing:doubts, in paragraph 2 of your letter No.S.50020 of the 26th March, about the value which we were getting for our contributions of £10,000 a quarter to the Anglo- Irani.an Relief Fund. Ca r* t ' f T \* i f &gt; F** ft - ; ^ ( rr *■ f r • r 'F • f' q \ ^ rt F o o ^ o r * •You will since have seen Tehran despatch No.164,lenclosed in my letter No*E 28fD76/34 of the “E^ndTHlyv which contained some evidence of the propaganda value of the Fund. We have now had further information from the Legation to supplement- that evidence, and you may be interested to have some account of it. In the first place, the activities of the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee form a useful theme for 1 the propaganda of the Public Relations Bureau, who have so little bread to cast upon the waters of Persian indifference (or hostility) .that they are c* glad of all the crumbs the Anglo-Iranian Relief Fund can provide. The value of this publicity is difficult to estimate, but it is significant that it hhs provoked an elaborate effort by tne Berlin wireless to prove that it is derogatory to Persian dignity to accept alms from tne British. The Germans would hardly go out of their way to “debunk' the Fund in this ; manner if they did not at least expect it to produ.ce results contrary to their interests. * \ But/ nBiaai/v C.H.M. Wilcox, Esq., Treasury* C,M x/nijnoo** * v v u t^JBut providing grist for our propaganda mill is only a secondary function of the Anglo-Iranian Relief Fund; its main purpose is to achieve a direct propaganda effect in each of the centres in which it operates by means of the humanitarian work undertaken, and by its success in this direction it must stand or fall. The Legation have recently obtained the^views.of Consuls on this aspect ,of the Committee’s work* An analysis.of the reports shows that the results vary greatly from district to district. The-best results have been achieved in South and Central Persia, where we have spent the greater part of the funds and where t our largest interests lie. The report from Busnire includes the following observations:- j i*- 1 Ci ‘ •’ X w XV is OQ ‘ * 0 1c 1 •'*••• i .. :■&gt;. u il I 0 . “As regards Bushire port itself: the atmosphere 'has kept a firm tone (even during the 'Stalingrad* period), 'and Persian Officials are nearly invariably co-operative 'to the limit, (i.e. their own limitations). Sir Geoffrey 'Prior is of opinion that our efforts to relieve distress 'have played their part in bringing this about. O v J i i o X 1. A i iji. JA wl Xi L. v.JuiJ'JjLAX-i.Ij . 'We are now just beginning to 'cash in' on that 'part of Persian goodwill which was previously 'restrained by fear of backing a losing side; 1 'and it would be a thousand pities to drop our .’.'facade of numanitarianism, and become the Nazi 'type of occupying power just because we can now 'do without Persian goodwill to a .larger extent 'than before. 'We have so far had no trouble from Russian 'competition here, but we cannot entrench ourselves . 'too firmly; and there is no doubt that our 'position here does not escape their observation. 'We read continual reports of how they attempt to 'make/entirely, may be largely due to the tact that th© c osssilttee* a operation© in ftea&amp;aen have been on © comparatively am©11 «calt- f vith the result tb»;t ©% distributions tm&amp;sr the whsM so ^ *r«iun syes to be nothing mor*s t &gt; ©n insaer^te / douceurs* *• yrepose to suggest to Tenren that, mther then reinforce © failure, it soul a be better for the present to concentrate on those sixes ehere result© ere 4ore promising. Gem:roily, the Casulttee try to pr^a^rve me Anglo-Iranian nature of tne FunU. There i« clenr value for us in achieving any sort of Allgle-?er*l«A co-o oration; on« has only te Iseglse the Of mans still in ^er#U saa to reflect hos irritated, end aurpiclous, we should be if they eet up a ^SerssS-1rsnian belief 'society**. The t&lt;lSitls&gt; report that they have been successful in getting Persians, including provincial governor*,, to sit on the local »an&amp; fe ing ssMitteee, in sddlttsii te the central mgiu- Oseslitee in Tehran; end that this give® the Fwtd © useinines* quite distinct from the propsgsnds value of the relief work undU rtaken. 8U;ji *iP* althougn the evidence is conflicting, the Legation fond we arc satisfied th/?t the Fund hu© been worth the sonsy spent on it. it has bets a useful propaganda stopgap in the absence of any really ^uAstsntlal contributi ?n to Persian w^lf^re in the economic field and it h«» been particularly vslsebls in maintaining our position in outh and . outh&lt;—ssstsm Persia wiiere our interests sr© greatest* If the time should cone when *e were not only anyiou® but able to give perais definite material assistance, ??ucb as &amp;lone could raiiceliy alter public opinion in our favour throughout the country, we should, I think, be rcaiy to admit that th« Fund had outlived its usefulness aflta thxi it would ao no greet harm to iiwinir h «■ r',luaily the volu © oi our .subi 5 cri'.&gt;tio.n©, if not to withdraw them t/ltogr tbor. ut until then %s h^pe you will be sole to continue the grants*With the cenrollments of Mr, E 2370/6/34. 8.49294. tear Hankey, G.H.U. V/ilcQK TREASURY CHAMBERS, S.W.l. r- 26 th nay, 1943t &lt; In i*eply to your latter of 22nd May, I write to aay that la the olresumetanceo we agree to a further grant of f,10.000 for the work of the ^nglo-Merolan Helief Jomittee in respect of the ;&gt;ertod 22nd May to 23rd August, 1^3. have you heard anything fraia Tehran yet on the question of audit and la there any sign of any aeeounts (vide cy letter to ^•'Ciw^a of 1st April, 1943# your referenee 35 /6/34;? I lam sending copies of this letter to Ororas Lae and to Yoare sineorely, j- (Sgd.) C.H.M. .-J joii»y. r.on,,^ /T /W ,-&lt; f EXT pypc; omo-;, a. . 1 . r om piimerits ^ a ' 7 &gt; *2 miv m,,. for* Foi’ei&amp;fJ MifaiiHi Itjh ^*3 ■ W t ; Pear llieox* Tn hia letter Ko. 1 S171/6/M of the 19th April $ Young gave some of the reasons why we do not wish to see any interruption In the work of the Anglo-Persian el let ^oiiaaittae* I now enc lose a copy of i eh ran despatch So* 164 of the 86th April, which contains further evidence of the useful effect which the activities of the Cosraittee are producing* tiqpire, lately Counsellor at rehraa end now His Majesty # a Minister designate at Kabul, who is at present in London, strongly endorsee the view th t in the areas where the Commit tee has been active*, the effect both on our popularity and on our prestige hue been most beneficial and T can endorse this from say own observation^? . the activities of the Goiaraittee have ao far been ifcainly confined to the areas in i^outiiem, iouth- .astern and Central Persia, i*e* those areas in which for military and political reasons we are most directly concerned, and where we are in the best position to ensure that the funds allocated are employed for useful ends. Hitherto it h^s not been possible, with the funds at our disposal, to extend the Coiaraittee's activities to cbhrsn, where the imusdlate political effect would probably be greater than in the provinces* vne Secretary of &gt;tate is at present v ry concerned to make tie moat of any mane open to us for mitigating the effects of the high cost of living In Persia and its reactions on our popularity and prestige. So lon^ as it continues to be our policy to use Persia as a supply iV X,' \ ^ C &gt; $ 1^, ‘v. ' ■ &amp; -'V' route to ruasia, with the ^Icruptior. of Persian economy which this Involves, conditions ere likely to be increasingly difficult. On the other hand, without a comprehensive revision of our policy (which we eannot present contemplate/ no radical .remedies sre open t i ua, and it is essential to make the most of those palliatives which have proved their usefulness* ue therefore regard it as most important to continue the quarterly grants of £10,000 to the Committee. e hope thet w© have your sanction as soon as possible for the grant in respect of the period the 22nd Mav to the T'Sra August, 1943* X am sending copies of this letter to Peel at the Indio, office and drives I&amp;w at the Ministry of Info motion* j. -XL^_ “ 1 ( *A* lii^nkey) .r ^NGLO-IRMJ^N^ReLIEF^FUND^ Po si tipn_at_Agri1, 201h A _1943 2725 BUSHIRil S econd_.auar ter JL _ 2 .^Zll/42_-_19/2/43 &gt;1 The rain-water dam at Undur-Bundur sustained some damage by a cloud burst which occurred when the dam was within a few days of completion, but arrangements were made for its repair and a contract was signed for a new spill-way. A contract was prepared for a large ! ab-ambar’ m the centre of the town, the ground for which had been given by a local philanthropist. A grant of £350 was m P .dQ for these drinking- 3 50 and dates, rice and cash donations were sent to the local An joman-i-Mustamandan (Charitable Relief Committee). areas from Hiat Daudi in the North to Lingeh in the South* The dates were sent to local Khans or&amp;abits and letters of thanks and appreciation hp,ve been received. Cotton cloth was distributed to the poor in Lingeh by the British Consul when on tour there. A further consignment of dates &amp;&amp;d 2 small quantities of te.a and sugar vers purchased and sent for distribution in local centres of the Shibkuh ports. water projects Dates were distributed at the British Consulate-General Dates were sent to relieve distress in all the coastal Th ir d_qu^r t er j l „20/2/42 __-_2 2/5/4 3. The following grants have been mades- £500 for distribution of clothing £500 for distribution of foodstuffs 500 50 C2r 2 ^ - 2 - made in the first quarter. Individual outdoor relief was given in 138 oases, the average scale of relief being Rls.225. The scheme worked well thanks to the energetic and-wholehearted devotion of Aghq Hooshang, the Hospital Almoner, and of Dr. Honriquos and the other hospital workers. On February 10th approximately Rls.95,000 were still in hand, but expenditure has been on/mounting scal'o, viz s- November ................... Rls. 3,950.- oc„mbcr * 3,800.-- January » ;u,800.- Fcbruary Ist-lOth « 10,000.— There was some delay in collecting maize at Darab and getting it to Lar for the famine relief scheme, owing to a general shortage of animal transport, but arrangements for transport are now Oeing made, A ftbm of £200 was allocated to a relief schema for assisting necessitous school boys and girls and students with clothes, medicines and other material needs, ' - ' - contributed to chc. feisty for the Protection of dhiiuren in Shiraz, under the patronage of Princess Firouz. This society distributes clothing to children, supports f amilie s ^ with children and runs a food kitchen. It is also planning to open an orphanage. Cash relief, totalling Rls. 3,930 up to February 10th was givnn :i c a 3 e 3 of dostitution. Further projects in hand are s- (1) The institution of combined re st-room? and food kitchens (a supplementary allocation of £500 was made to Shiraz 500 for this purpose)# (2) The oscablishment and maintenance for a period of a number of bods for maternity c-ses ' u y c^.363, and a scheme for the ox- tension and improvement of the feeding of orphans. 1 f 850t er j. Tho following grants havo boon mados- £500 for C. M. S. hospital ^00 £1,000 for food kitchens, etc. 1*000 £500 for students 1 relief scheme 500 £300 for Protection of Children Society 300 £300 for orphanage and maternity work 300 KERMAN.. S ond_£uar t er... The Kerman food kitchen served 1,500 cheap meals of rice, potatoes and dates a day and the schamowas widely known and appreciated. A gift of 10 kharwars of dates was roceivod from Agha Mohammad Khan Ameri and 2 0 tons of rice were obtained at a favourabl© rate from the local Food Department. Sufficient funds remain d in hand for the thirad quarter. The grant of £100 to the C. M. S. Hospital was used to continue the existing facilities for the free treatment of poor patients. J’i 3 ;iLd_quar t or i A grant of £100 has been made to the C. M. S. , p 1 10 Q hospital. YEZD. S££Q£d_quar t er*. Up to February 25th, under the food relief scheme organised by the Rev. H. C. Gurney, C.M.S., 500 persons had each been givon sufficient rice, lentils and barley to cook 5 ’ash 1 moals a week for 6 weeks. A quantity of barley was given free by Agha Jalal .dashti. Of the 500 people receiving help 300 were Moslems and 200 Jews. The help given made all the differenco between starvation and at least a bare sufficiency 4,550(22) ^ - 4 - 0 A further £300 was given during th© «ocond quarter for food and with this money additional supplies have been bought, Z ZZ-ZZZZZZ 2 ^ i £ ^ _ 3. ii 9: i - TIhe following grants have been mades- £200 for food relief £200 for free distribution of drugs on medical prescriptions. K 300 ^oo 200 ISFAHAN^ Second_quarter^ With the £1,050 allocated to the C«M*S. Hospital, plus a balance of Rls.,57,600 remaining from the first quarter 202 in - and out - patients were assisted. Besides normal hospital expenses, help was given either in the form of cash or clothes to those patients in real need. Sufficient fundfl are in hand for the third quarter* The grant of £2,000 for winter relief was spent on the distribution of clothing and charcoal. 1,200 families received 18 kilos of charcoal each and 900 families received gifts of clothes. A sufficient balance remained at the end of the quarter to provide charcoal for anolther 300 families and clothes for another 400 families. ^hirdj_ quarter^ The following grants have been* madas- £2,650 for issue of 12 kilos of rice to about 2,200 2,650 families to supplement their bread rations*^ o . £ 200 for purchase of drugs for C.M.S. hospital 200 £ 50 for the? Feraddan Armenian hospital 50 £ 100 for purchase of drugs for the Fereidan hospital 100 17250 3 S B 3 S35 - KERMAN SHAH,, SQcond_guarter t 35 poor persons were given, raadica 1 tora^tmojat at tJlQ American Mission Hospital. 500 metres of cloth were given to the local poor- centre. 48 bed sheets and 24 pillow slips were presented to the local Lion &amp; Sun Hospital. Shirts and trousers were distributod to the poor. 32 cotton suits wore given to the most destitute priaan&amp;rsr in the local gaol. wore opened Four popular ret .aurants^serving 1,200 meals of me at and vegetable soup and bread a day for 2 rials each (or free to the very poor). The necessary funds were advanced against the allocation for the third quarter. The rate of expenditure in Keihaanshah increased to approximately Rls»3j000 a day, of which about 2,850 rials was on the popular restaurants and the rest on clothes. £ ?Hird_£uarter^ The following grants have been madej- 41,500 for popular restaurants (already started in second quarter) 1*500 £ 200 for distribution of clothing to the destituta 200 £ 100 for free medical treatment of poor patients 100 at the American Mission Hospital HMADANjl 330 blankets purchased in Isfahan were distributed to inmates of the local poorhouso and lunatic asylum and in dividually to destitute half-nek.ed persons found in the streets of the town. 10,050£ -6 - A aupply of cotton print is prico from the govornmont factory at ^ng for tho poor. being obtained at cost Bohshahr for making cloth- 11 111—£•— £200 has boon allocated for the distribution of shirts 200 and trousers to tho poor- MESHBD x _ZABUL a _ZAHI DAN_AND_BIR J AND.. 2 ocond_ 2 Bartor^ Grants wore made in Meshed to the American Mission hospital, and to a local charitable society known as the An- j uman-i-Par vin Society, Two tons of coal and gifts of cloth' ing wera presented to the local Society for Aid to Mothers. Assistanco was given to needy school porters and to discharge* p risonor s• A sum of 30,000 rials was allocated from the Meshed grant for relief in Zabul. £}.,000 has been allocated for the purchase of 1 # 000 medicines from India sufficient for one year for distribution in Meshed, Zahidan, Zabul and Birjand. AHWAZ^AND_KHgRRAMSH4E jL quart or *. AHWAZ, Supplemented by local subssriptions totalling Rla* 404,900 by March 15th, the grant of £700 for food relief was used in running a bakery supplying bread for about 4,000 persons daily. The British Military Authorities supplied about 660 kilos of grain a day for this bakery at less than a third of tho current market price. 11,2507 /to KHORRAMSHAHR. The grant of £EOO we&gt;s divided equally b^tw-e-on JKhorramshahr and Abadan* The Abadan share of the grant was given to a dis pensary supported by the Persian clerks of the A. I. 0. C, The Khorramshahr share of the grant was used to pur chase foodstuffs for the local Municipal Poor Housos. £ Z!li£d__qu ar t or ^ The following grants have been mades- £3,000 for A^wp.z bakery 3^000 £ 500 for other charitable relief in Ahwaz and 500 K h o r r am s ha h r TEHRAN^ ^£ g o n d_ qu a r t or _ i- The sum of £500 allocated to charitable organisation , in Tehran was given to the Bongah-i-Kheiriyeh Tehran to finanoa the provision of over 28,000 additonal cheap meals by the Bon- gah’s soup-kitchens. d quarter^ A number of houses damaged by heavy rains, which the owners cannot afford to repair, are being repaired at the ex» pense of the Fund. SULTAN A3 AD. Thir d _quar t er .. £500 has been allocated for a food kitchen or other 5Q0 suitable form of poor relief, if feasible. BANDAR^ABBAS^ ar t er ^ A grant of £500 has been made for food relief 500 15&gt;7SOmam.i-ir r PUBLICITY GIVEN TO THE FORKING OF THE ANGLO- IRANIAN RELIEF FUND MliRING_THS_qUIRTER__ENDING_MARCH_31ST &lt;J&gt; _1943 i (Most of the items were printed in the 'Daily News 1 &gt; the Tehran English newspaper published by the Public Relations Bureau* Nearly all of them were also inserted in the Persian press and broadcasted from Radio Tehran)* z^zzzzzzzzs Extract from the programme for a charity cinema performance on February 6th, 1943, in aid of the Anglo-Iranian Relief Fund and 1 he_.Ir ano-Amer i can_B eney o le n t_S oci e ty^ The Anglo-Iranian Relief Fund was inaugurated in August, 1942, with the aim of bringing together British and Iranians in a common endeavour to improve the condition of tho poor of Iran* A number of local Anglo-Iranian committees have been sot up in the provinces to administer funds allocated by the General Gommitteo in Tehran and sums totalling 2,000,000 rials have been or are being spent on various schemes for charitablo relief, in cluding the provision of froo medicines and hospital treatment and the distribution of food, fuel and warm clothing in necessitous areas, especially in tho South* Thus in the Biishire district 22,000 kilos of dates are being distributed to tho poor, and in the Jahrum and Lar areas 130,000 rials worth of maize* In Kerman a food kitchen has boon opened, providing over 790 poor persons overy day with a cheap meal of rice, moat, peas and dates* In Isfahan, besides making generdus contributions towards the running expenses of tho two C* M* 3* hospitals, the Commit'iiQe is financing a winter relief scheme, for distributing charcoal, fbod and clothing to needy families. In the Tehran area a grant of over 35,000 rials was made tow&amp;rds the cost of sending out two travelling dispensaries* Near Bushire, where there is a shortage of drinking v ater in tho hot weather, the Committee has financed tho building of a rain-water dam, at a cost of over 46,000 rials, to provide storage for ovor a million gallons of sweet water* ^§liiY_Mo_s_^anuar y_61 h A _19 4 3^ A special Anglo-Iranian Charitable Relief Committee, sot up to administer a grant of 128,000 Rls* from tho Anglo —Irani an *’ un( *&gt; is providing cheap meals this winter for the poor of Kerman* The food is coolcad and distributed in a kitchen placed at the disposal of tho Committee by Agha S a lar Muzaffar and the Committee has also benefited by the valuable advice and co-operation of tho Rais-i-Shahrdari, Agha Sar Rasht&amp;dar* oo mo * °^ or 79 *? P oor persons are fed every day and more than 22,112 M *ls:of Dampukht, a mixture of rice, meat, peas and dates, have already been served each at a price of only 40 Dinars. Vi • 1 ? ar ^ lt th - t 130,000 Rials worth of maize, bought in arab, is being distributed amongst the poor of Jahrum and Lar, at the expense of the Anglo-Ir^nian Relief Fund. Slidi o TQhran^_ Ja nuary_llt h i __194 3. With the QVl . /'' r * 3w pravanting hardship in Bushira osusod by 'r„ln h T °l watar, particularly in ths hot weather,the .mglo-Iranian Relief Committee has financed the building of a r=inw»tor dam at Undur-Bundur where the outfall of one valley paafos throughfta narrow placo. Tho da^., which has cost over 46,000 Rials* i» nearly complete and during the recent rains the valley filled, up, storing over a million gallons of sweet water. This water will partly be used direct from the reservoir so formed and partly will seep into the ground thereby sweetening the area from which the most important group of drinking water wells in Bushire derive their water. We have previously given particulars of the relief work done by the Anglo-Iranian Relief Fund in Shiraz., Kerman and Bushiro. Here are items on Isfahan,- Qua, Kashan and Khorramabad, * sum over 128,000 Rials has been spent by the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee on the provision of clothes, blankets and fuel for poor families in the town of Isfahan. The local Anglo-Iranian Committee set up to administer this grant included the Ustandar and the British Consul among its members, as well as a local newspaper proprietor and the Anglican Bishop, It has distributed 23 kharwars of charcoal, 200 lahafs, 100 namads, 6 0 men’s overcoats, 50 men’s suits, 100 women’s overcoats, 160 women’s dresses, 130 girls’ dresses and 80 boys’ suits. The ^nglo-Iranian P^elief Committee has also given over 100,000 Rials for medical ''elief in Isfahan and has distributed tickets admitting patients to special wards in local hospitals for men and women. As regards other centres, medicines to the value of Rials 24,129,50 have been purchased by the Ministry of Health for the medical relief of the poor of Qum, Kp.shan and ^horramabad from funds provided by the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee, Tehran. 5£.4 1 - Y._Nq ws ,_Fobr u ary_71h194 3 . A sum of over 128,000 Rials has been spent by the Anglo- Iranian Relief Committee on the provision of clothes, blankets and fuel for poor families in the town of Isfahan. The local Anglo- Iranian Committee set up to administer this grant included the Ustandar and the British Consul among its members, as well as a 1 coal newspaper proprietor and the Anglican Bishop. It has distributed 23 kharwars cf charcoal, 200 lahafs, 100 namada, 60 mon’s overcoats, 50 men’s suits, 100 women’s overcoats, 160 wo men's drosses, 130 girls’ dresses and 80 boys' suits. The iinglo-Iranian Relief Committee has also given over 100,000 Rials for medical relief in Isfahan and has distributed tickets admitting patients to special wards in local hospitals for men and 7/omen. * ^sdi.o _ Tehran* February .9thj_194 3. The p 1 ' -^forraance of the film 'Gone with the Wind”, held at the uinema Iran, Tehran, on February 6th (Bahman 17th) for the benefit of the Anglo-Iranian Relief Fund and the Irano- Amorican Benevolent Soviety resulted in the satisfactory sum of Rials 92,882 being raised for those two funds. Each fund will receive therefore the sum of Rials 46,441 to help on the excellent work they are doing among the poor both of Tehran and the provinces. The Anglo-Iranian Relief Fund has in addition recently received large contributions from the A. I. C. n n d the I. B. I.!&gt;age 2. Two travelling dispensaries from the Ministry of HoftXth* each staffed by a doctor, an assistant doctor and a nurso, recently mn.de a tour of 28 villages in the Talghan and Ka^vin districts and treated over 3,000 sick persons free of charge* The costs of the tour were borne by the Anglo-Iranian Relief Fund. additional to tho donations already made from the Anglo- I ranian Relief Fund of Rls* 129,280 for medical attention and financial aid to hospital patients in Shira^, and of Rials 128,000 for the purchase of maize for poor relief at Lar, the following charitable aid in Shirar. has been financed from funds allocated by the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committees- Rials 25,600 to assist poor school boys and girls with clothes and other necessities to be administered by a small committee set up by the Director of tho Educational Department. Rials 15,000 for the improvement and maintenance of tho homa for abandoned children to be administered by tho Society of Protec tion of Children, Shiraz.* Also Rials 6,400 as a donation to the s am© Socioty. Rials 18,000 for the maintenance of 10 extra bods for poor people and maternity cases and the promise of Rials 16,800 for feeding 200 destitut) poor daily for three months, of which Rials 25,600 is paid for the first month, Tho last two contributions to be administered under the auspices of Shiraz Central Charity Committee and personal supervision of tho well-known and respected Shiraz physician, Dr. Ghurban. Daily Ne; ws^ The charitable work of the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee in Kermanshah has included the purchase of bed-lirten for the local Lion and Sun hospital, the provision of free medical treatment for a number of poor patients at the American Hospital and tho distribution of free clothing to the destitute. In addition* no los than four popular restaurants have been opened in the poor districts of the town. Already 1,000 meals are being provided every day at less than half price, and it is hoped shortly to cater for up to 1,500 persons, at a cost of about Rials 3,000 a day. M-&amp;H£H_5 thj, _ 19 4 3. The latest provincial town to set up a local iinglo-Iranian Relief Committee is Khorramshahr. The members of the Committee include Agha Sami and other prominent personalities of both Khorramshahr and Abadan, ^ ..lie ths 7/ork of the Committee is under the general supervision of the Governor and tho British Consul, The Committee held its first mooting in the Municipal offices, Khor— ramshahr, on February 3rd, and decided to use the funds allocated by the central Anglo-Iranian Relief Comraitto in Tehran for the purchase of foodstuffs for the municipal poor houses in Khorramshahr as well as for tho purchase of cotton piece goods for a poor house in **b - dan supported by voluntary contribution. ^£ilZ_Kews J __,Mar ch_ 9 th Jt _19 4 3 ± Between the middle of November and the middle of February1943 over 70,000 cheap moals wq£g provided for the destitute of ^Kerman city from funds provided by the ^nglo-Iranian Relief Com mittee. Fifteen hundred people are now being provided daily with cheap meals. Rials 1,500 has been subscribed by British troops in Ahwaz and made over to tho Prosident of the iknglo — Iranian Relief Committe for the purchase of clothing for destitute children. 5 S; i 11 _ N 2 E 9 ei ~ M 3; 12 ll L i 2 i 3 ^ U grant of ton thousand Rials was recently m^de by the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee towards the cost of a poor-house for beggars in Birjand, the Committee in charge of which is under the chairmanship of th&lt;/S&gt;iaukat-ul~Mulk• A sum of Rials 143,600 has also been allocated by the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committo for charitable work in £abul and Meshed• In Meshed a local Anglo- Iranian Committee has bean set up under the chairmanship of the British Consul-Gonoral and with the following members Mrs. Ziai, Agha Gulkani, Agha Fiyuzat, Mrs. P. F. Skrine and Doctor Cochran. Arrangements have nude by this Committee to assist two local charitable organisa.tions, the Bungah- i- Himayat-i-Madaran (Society for Aid to Mothers) and the Anjuman- i-Parvin, and a grant has also been made to the Anorican Mission Hospital for medical and poor relief. •2. £ i 1^ ® £ jl Mar c h„l^i^a_i222a The Anglo-’Irani an Relief Committee recently presented 8 tons of rice and a sum of over Rials 24,000 to the B ongah-i-..&lt;. i i Kheiriyyeh Tehran, with a view to p romoting the excellent work which this Bongah is dcii&gt;. e xu. feeding the ooor of t®i«» an t/Wnugh various soup kitchens in the poor q-ucL*'t&gt;oj.-s of the town. As a result of the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee 1 s gift over 28,000 additional eheap meals v/il^uo served during the next four weeks at the Bong&amp;h r s food kitchens in tho Jalilabad quarter, the Bagh Firdaus and avenue Gumruk. During the 3 months «.zar-Bahman sums totalling Rials 343,436.80 were spent by the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee on charitable work in Isfahan. In addition to assistance to hospitals and to the local orphanage school a clothos distributing centre was opened in tho Maidan-i-Sh&amp;h a nd another one £or charcoal nearby. Between 1,600 and 1,700 noody families received presents of fuel or clothing, or both, at these centres. The various articles of clothing distributod were as follows:- 248 lahafs, 279 namads, 128 men's overcoats, 2 02 men r s suits, 207 TOmen^s co a ts 400 women's dresses, 372 girls' dresses and 203 boys' suits. Daily Mews^^Mar ch_ 2 _0th JL _19 4 3* &gt; Charitable work financed by the Anglo-Iranian Relief Committee in Yezd during the throe months Azar-Bahman took the form of a free distribrv'* Ion. of rice, barley and lentils. Five hundred poor people were given sufficient of these ingredients to cook five 'ashbmeala per week for more than six weeks at a cost of some 25,000 rials. About half of the barlov distributed was received from Agha Jalal Rashti of Yezd as a free gift.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000363_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/824</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000363</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/824</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 2725/43 'Anglo Persian Relief Fund'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1943</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-26T23:12:49</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (32 folios)</extent><extent>The file's contents are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 34; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists primarily of letters, telegrams and reports regarding the Anglo Persian Charitable Relief Committee to Iran.The file contains two reports entitled 'Anglo-Iranian relief fund.' These reports list the cities that received aid from the fund and the amounts. The file contains another pair of reports entitled 'Publicity Given to the Working of the Anglo-Iranian Relief Fund during January to March 31st 1943.' These reports describe the actions the fund have took to alleviate poverty in Iran as reported on by the
                           Daily News, the Tehran English newspaper. Finally, the file contains letters from the Foreign Office regarding whether or not to contribute £10,000 to the Anglo-Iranian Charitable Relief Commitee.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Daily News</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Humanitarian assistance</topic></subject><subject><topic>Disaster relief</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Information</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Tehran</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Iran</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Charities</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000363#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>