<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001af_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T05:58:05.951Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">ff CONFIDENT! Serial No.^? REPORTS FROM Lieutenant-Qeneral Sir P. H. N. Lake, K.C.B., K.C.M.Q Commanding I. E. F. ' D ' ON Operations against Arab tribesmen on the Euphrates Line, January and February 1916 GENERAL STAFF, INDIA C292GSB m la government central press 1916CONFIDENTIAL. (Diary No. 44-304) No. 168-18-0., dated General Headquarters, 4tli March 1916. jTrom The General Officer Commanding, Indian Expeditionary Force ' D. To—The Chief of the General Staff, Army Headquarters, India. 1 have the honour to forward, for the information of His Excellency the Commander-in-Chief, three reports on operations against Arab tribesmpn on the Euphrates Line, which occurred during the months of January and ± ebruary 1916 - Eor the purposes of publication in the London Gazette and of bringing to notice the names of those commended, the subject of these reports will be included in a despatch covering the period in which they occurred, and a list of officers and others favourably mentioned will be rendered at the same time. 2 On January 7th, a mixed force under the command of Major- General Sir G. F. Gorringe, K.C.B., C.M.G., D.S O., was mo^ed from Nasiriyah to Butaniyah (12 miles north-west of Nasiriyah) for the purpose of demonstrat ing towards Shattra. It was hoped that the Turks might be induced to weaken their forces oppos- intr General Aylmer on theligris.by detaching troops to guard the lines of approach along the Shatt-al-Hai. Although the demonstration from Isasinyah failed to accomplish this, it succeeded in attracting largo numbers of hostile Arabs who might otherwise have joined the Turkish forces around Kut. 3. Beport A* deals with an engagement during a reconnaissance between Butaniyah and Suwaij on January 14ith, 1916. 4. Report B.\ describes a rear guard action when the column was heavily attacked on February 7th, on the occasion of the withdrawal to Nasiriyah. The unsatisfactory behaviour of certain Indian units during this action forms the subject of a separate communication which is being addressed to you to-day under No. 14:25-1-A. 5 Report OA gives an account of punitive operations undertaken by Bri gadier -General H. T. Brooking, C.B., on February 9tb, in consequence of the treacherous behaviour of certain sections of so called ' friendly triDes. C292G8B • Page 2. t Pago 8. x Pago 15.2 t ' A.' Dated Headquarters, 12th Indian Division, Butanijah, 18th January 1916. From— Major-general Sir G. F. Gorringe , K .C .B., C .M.G., D.S.O., Com- mandiog, 12th Indian Division. To—The Chief of the General Staff, General Headquarters, I.E.F. M D,'' f lia\ e the honour to submit for the information of the Army Commander this my report on the action between Butaniyah and Suwaij on Uth January 1916. Report on action between Butaniyah and Suwaij, 14th January 1916. 1. In compliance with instructions received in your 1008-249-0., dated 5th January 1916, to induce the enemy to believe that the movement of a large force up the Hai was intended, i started at 9 a.m . with an escort of the 12th Cavalry, less 2 squadrons, to personally reconnoitre the country between Butani yah and Suwaij, a distance of 6 miles. __. P. e General Officer Commanding, 12th Brigade, and friendly Shaikhs of Khattaja came with me, the l-5th Queen's and one section, 30th Mountain Battery, following in support of the cavalry. 2. Suwaij was reached by the cavalry, without incident, at 10-35 a.m. The inhabitants were friendly and warned me of hostile gatherings of Khaffaja Arabs collecting north, north-west and north-east of Suwaij. 3. As Arabs could be seen moving out of the neighbouring villages and as shouting could be heard, the infantry and guns, who were then beginning to arrive, were ordered to take up a covering position in an irrigation cut about 1,800 yards south of Suwaij, and the cavalry were ordered to withdraw, and passing through the infantry to form advanced and flank guards for the with drawal to camp. The infantry and guns were to cover the movement as a rear guard. 4. At th© same time, as a precautionary measure, instructions were sent to camp Butaniyah for two battalions and the remaining section of the 30th Mountain Battery to move out under the General Officer Commandino-, 34th Brigade, along the Suwaij road. 5. At 11-15 a.m ., the Arabs commenced firing and began to advance with considerable determination and gradually increasing numbers against my flanks and rear. The ground was covered with brushwood and much intersected with deep irrigation cuts, which very much favoured their attack, as it enabled them to advance without offering any targets for our fire. The weather was also un favourable for observation. 6. The withdrawal was carried out with great steadiness by the Queen's and one section, 30th Mountain Battery; but was considerably hampered by the difficulty of getting away the wounded and manoeuvring in such country. 7;. when a point about four miles from Butaniyah on the Suwaij road was reached, the West Kents, 114th Mahrattas and remaining sec tion of the 30th Mountain Battery, under General Officer Commanding, 34th Brigade, were met. The General Officer Commanding, 34th Brigade, was instructed to take up $ a defensive position, and to let the 12th Cavalry, Queen's and section 30th Mountain Battery under General Officer Commanding, 12th Brigade, pass through his troops, which were to cover the further retirement to camp. 8. This was successfully accomplished by 5-30 p.m ., when the troops under command of the General Officer Commanding, 34th Brigade, reached the io y 110 which had been strengthened by the General Officer Commanding, Iztn Brigade. The ground in front of the outpost line about three miles from camp Butaniyah is of a much opener character than that further north. The Aiabs showed no disposition to cross the open ground and the attack died away. 00 P® 1 cached camp without further molestation by 6 pm . C292Qsa J3 The night passed quietly, 9. On information given by a friendly Shaikh who came in this morning, and other sources, I estimate that the enemy's casualties were 36 men known to be killed, and about 140 wounded. Some Arab accounts give as high as 300 casualties. They include 3 or 4 minor Shaikhs and the son of the Shaikh at whose house the Khaffaja and Abudah tribes are said to have met to concert measures against us. j 10. At the beginning of the action the enemy consisted chiefly of Khaffaja tribesmen. Later on Abudah men under Khaiyun-el-Obeid are said to have arrived. The Shaikh estimates that about 3,000 joined in the attack. These mostly belonged to hostile sections of the Khaffaja and Abudah (list ' A attached), but doubtless many men from friendly sections, whom their Shaikhs were unable to control, joined in. I attach lists of casualties (' B ') and ammunition expenditure, (' C ') and a sketch (' D ') of the country traversed.8 « B. M No. B,M.-2012, dated Nasiriyah, the 18tli February 1916. From— B rigadier -G eneral H. T. Brooking , C .B., Commanding, 12th Infantry Brigade, To—The Chief of the General Staff, General Headquarters, I. E. F. ' D.' I have the honour to forward the report on the rear guard action on the 7th Pehruary, together with names brought to notice. The report is accompanied by a map, table of ammunition expended and a casualty list. I consider that the losses on this day would have been quite 50 per cent less, had the two Indian infantry units (44th Merwara Infantry and 90th Pun jabis) not broken. I have come to the conclusion that not much reliance can be placed on these units at present. As far as I have been able to gather, the men of these units ran and then walked awayi many allowed themselves to be shot in the back, without any attempt to fight. Although the Arabs got to considerable numbers—reports place them at upwards of 5,000—still they were not supported by guns, and any stand imme diately checked them. This is proved by the way in which 178 rifles of the 2nd Battalion, Royal West Kent Regiment, could hold them. These men bore the brunt of the fight. . ' 2. The behaviour of the 2nd Battalion, Royal West Kent Regiment, was beyond all praise. The 30th Mountain Battery should be bracketed with the 2nd Battalion, Royal West Kent Regiment, for their gallant behaviour. Some of the drivers of this battery used rifles and bayonets obtained t from wounded infantry, and thus materially assisted. 3. When I came into Nasiriyah on the 5th February, I did not anticipate any severe action. I thought it quite probable that the Khaffaja and Abudah tribes, who had opposed Sir George Gorringe's reconnaissance, would follow the column to the neighbourhood of the sandhills, where their land ends. The approximate boundary is marked on the map. Butaniyah village, the \ illages just north of the sandhills and all villages along the road belong to the Albu Hamera section of the A zairich tribe. I thought them friendly. They have been so for many months. 4). In order to be on the safe side, I sent all available troops, consisting of— 1 squadron, 33rd Cavalry, l-2nd Sussex Battery, 4:4th Merwara Infantry (800), * 1 90th Punjabis (400), to a position slightly more than halfway to the Butaniyah Camp, to come under the orders of Brigadier-General Tidswell, D.S.O., who was commanding the Butaniyah force, to assist, should their services be required. The baggage and supplies came right through to Nasiriyah unmolested. 5. It has been hard to get any reliable figures as to the enemy's losses ; the numbers killed vary from 318 to 750. 1 think that 500 killed is a conservative estimate, and several leaders were seen to fall. As regards the number of their wounded, no Arab considers a man wounded unless he is so badly hit as to be incapacitated. As far as I can gather, the Arab casualties must have been at least 1,000. 6. I endorse all Brigadier-General Tidswell's recommendations, and con sider that all those who have been brought to notice are thoroughly deserving of reward. I wish to add to this list the name of Brigadier-General E. C. Tidswell, D.S.O. C292gsb9 Ko. 185-B. M., dated Nasiriyah, tlie 13th February 1916. From— Brigadier-General E. C. Tidswell, D.S.O., Commanding, 84th Indian Infantry Brigade, To—The Gentral Officer Commanding, Nasiriyah. I have the honour to forward herewith an account of the action of Fehru* ary 7th, to«rether with a list of my recommendations. Jccount of the retirement of a Force under Brigadier- General E. C. Tidswell,. D.S.O*, from JButaniyah to Nasiriyah, on 7th February 1916. Reference attached sketch.* At 8-30 a.m . one double company, lUth Mahrattas, under Captain B.C. Wilson, occupied Leaning Tower, relieving the night piquet of the 2nd Battalion, Royal West Kent Regiment, and reported about 20 Arabs about 2,000 yards north of their post ; aid at 9-10 a.m . that Arabs were collecting from all sides. At 8-30 a.m . one double company, 114th Mahrattas, under Captain H, Weaver, occupied Mound 82 and reported at 9-30 that Arabs were moving from north and east about 1,300 yards away. At 8-12 one squadron and machine gun section, 12th Cavalry, one section, 30th Mountain Battery, and one company, l-5th R,OTal 'West Surrey Regiment, under Major S. M. Tahourdin, 12th Cavalry, occupied the sand hills on Nasiri yah road and reported all clear. At 9-15 a.m . 30th Mountain Battery, less one section, and 114th Mahrattas, less two double companies, Brigaded machine guns and Brigade Headquarters, took up a position at Ruined Tower. At 9-i:0 a.m . the baggage moved clear of camp to starting point with escort of l-5th Battalion, Royal West Surrey Regiment, less one company. The 2nd Battalion, Royal West Kent Regiment, occupied the site of camp and prevented Arabs from entering it. About 9-15 a m. the guns from Ruined Tower opened fire on party of Arabs near Leaning Tower. At 9 -36 a.m . Captain R. C. Wilson's double company from Leaning Tower withdrew towards Mound 82, and the 2nd Royal West Kent Regiment about 500 yards clear of camp, which was at once occupied by Arabs who opened tire. About 10 a.m . the baggage was clear over the sandhills and the force with drew, Captain H. Weaver's double company on Mound 82 withdrawing when Captain R. C. Wilson's double company was in rear of it. The double company from Mound 82 was afterwards reported to have suffered heavy losses in this retirement, but this was not known by the Officer Commanding, 114th Mahrattas, at the sandhills. At 9-40 a.m . information was received that Headquarters and one squadron 12th Cavalry and one squadron 33rd Cavalry, both from Nasiriyah, were in position on the sandhills at 9 a.m. About 10-20 a.m . the force retired and took up a position on the sandhills. Arabs followed into open ground and were seen continually going round our ri^ht flank far out and also on the east side of Butaniyah Lake. Very few casualties had occurred up to then with the exception of those suffered 'by Captain H. Weaver's double company. Arabs were seen sitting quietly in villages west of road north of sandhills, who after troops bad passed walked out as spectators, then produced rifles from beneath their coats and shot into the backs of troops. In this way they shot c202qsb ^ Fage 14.10 several of the 114th Mahrattaa, killed them on the ground and look their rifles into the villages. One of these villages was hea\ily shelled at short range by the 30th Moantain Battery. After this I ordered all villages that were 'close on onr left flank to be cleared and one squadron 12th Cavalry and the 2nd Battalion, Hoyal West Kent Kegiment, to support each other from village to village. One squadron 12th Cavalry had occupied Butaniyah village and the one south of ir, both of which they cleared; the remainder of the cavalry were on the right flank of the sandhills with the maxim guns about 500 yards back. About 10-30 a.m . information was received that the 44th Merwaras and 400 rifles 90th Punjabis were occupying a position about one mile from sandhills towards Nasiriyah (this appeared to be nearer two miles than one mile) with the l-i'nd Sussex Battery, E. P. A., on its right rear, all under the command of Colonel Dunlop, 44th Merwaras. On receipt of this information I informed Colonel Dunlop that we would retire through him and that ho would cover our retirement. One double company, 114th Mahrattas, with brigaded machine guns retired about 1,500 yards on our right flank and were joined by another double com pany, 114th jMahrattas, when the sandhills were vacated. The 30th Mountain Battery (less one section) on the left, retired, leaving 2nd Battalion, Royal West Kent Regiment, and one double company, 114th Mabrattas, holding the sandhills. About 11-45 a . m . the dismounted cavalry retired and the retirement pro ceeded normally. At 12-45 p.m . I received a message from Royal West Kent Regiment that they required reinforcements and I sent up one company, 41th Merwaras, from the position occupied by the 44th Merwaras, which I had then reached. ColonelDunlop showed me the position he had taken up, 44th Merwaras on right and left of road with right flank well thrown back, and one double company and 90th Punjabis 800 yards in rear with the l-2nd Sussex Battery about 1,500 yards on right rear of first line. The 2nd Battalion, Hoval West Kent Regiment and 114th Mahrattas now passed through the 44th Merwaras an 1 90th Punjabis. Colonel Dunlop shortly afterwards informed me that his infantry would not stand and British reinforcements were wanted, so I sent the Royal ^ West Kent^ Regiment into the firing line again and sent for the l-5th Battalion, Royal West Surrey Regiment, to return from escort duty. I saw in the centre the Indian infantry collect into a mob of about 300 and the Arabs go close up to them and shoot them. The cavalry on the left 1 ere made a small charge, which with the accurate fire of the 30ih Mountain- Battery and the steady courage. of the 2nd Royal West Kents took off the pressure. Some of the 44th Merwaras and some of the 90th Punjabis still went on retiring and would not stop in spite of commands and threats till they reached the line near the second sandhills taken up by the l-2nd Sussex Battery, 30th Mountain Battery, less one section, and machine guns and the 134th Mahrattas. The cavalry on the right flank were at this time heavily attacked and suirered most of their losses. The l-5th Royal W est Surrey Regiment were oa the right rear about 4 p.m. This was practically the Arabs' last effort and they gradually withdrew aftsr having lollowed us persistently since about 9 30 a m . trying to turn both yanks. ' a Xlie force then withdrew unmolested into Nasirivah.11 Butaniyah Column Order No. 17, dated Oth February 1916. 1. Outposts will be found to-night as follows :— No. 1 Night Post ... ... 1 British officer and | double companr, l 1 i4th M ah rat t as. No, 2 Night Post ... 1 company, 2nd Royal West Kent Regiment. No. 3 Night Post ... ... 1 N. C. O. and 6 men, 114th Mahrattas, No. 3 Post will withdraw at 7-0 a.m . to-morrow. Nos. 1 and 2 will remain in position until relieved bj the 114th Mabrattas to-morrow. 2. At 8-30 a.m . to-morrow, one double company, 114 )th Mahrattas, will relieve No. 2 Night Post at the Leaning Tower and one double company, ll lth Mahrattas, will occupy No. (?) Day Post on the Mound on a bearing of 82 degrees from camp. No. 1 Night Post will withdraw when the latter double company is in position. These double companies will report if all is clear or not on reaching their posts and again when leaving them. 3. The troops at Butaniyah will retire to Nasiriyah to-morrow. Transport is allotted as follows Mules. Camels. 84)th Brigade Headquarters ... ... 17 Squadron 12th Cavalry ... ... ... 70 30th Mountain Battery ... ... ... 70 2nd R. West Kent Regiment ... ... ... 70 40 l-5lh Queen's Regiment ... ... ... 281 60 114th Mahrattas ... ... ... ... 374 Bearer Sub-Division, No. I2-C. Field Ambulance ... 25 ... 12th Brigade Signal Section ... ... ... 16 Telegraph ... ... ... ... 12 Wireless ... ... ... ••• Riding moles ... ... ... ... 30 Supply Section ... ... ... ... 50 90 Loading ropes will be drnwn from the officer in charge transport at 3-30 p.m . to-day or on arrival of the convoy if later, and as many loads as possit&gt;l« roped np to-night. Units will send representatives to draw transport at «-l5 a.m . to-morrow. 4. A column of all arms is lenving Nasiriyah at 8 30 a.m . to-morron r to meet the Butaniyah Column. The cavalry will meet the Butaniyah Column on the sandhills about three miles from camp on the Nnsiriyah road, the infantry and artillery on the Nasiriyah road about five miles from camp. 5. At 8-30 a.m . a force as in the margin under Major Tahourdin, 12th. , ,. 19t , p. , rv Cavalry, will occupy the sandhills three 1 squadron nnd machine puns, 12th Cavalry. 1 ji xt • • i. j 1 sectiou, Mountain Biittery. miles trom camp oa the INasmyan road ; i company, i-6th Qaeeu's Raiment. 0I1 arr i va [ 0 f ^he Cavalry from Nasiriyah, the Officer Commanding squadron and machine guns 12th Cavalry, will come under the orders oi the ollicer commanding cavalry from Nasiriyah, the in fantry and artillery will rejoin their units as they pass the sandhills. Reports will be submitted as to whether all is clear or not and of the position of the Nasiriyah Column on arrival at the sandhills. 6. At 9-30 a.m . a force as in the margin, under Lieutenant-Colonel Andrew, 114th Mahrattas, will be in a 30th Mountain Battery (ie3si section). position near the Ruined Tower to act Mncbines gnns of 2nd r . w. Kents, i-5th as ricflit flank guard to the Column as it chUhoim^ 1I4th M8hraUas ' under Licuten *' t retires. He will withdraw the day out- C n«h Mahrattaa less 2 doable compames. posts detailed in paragraphs when the rear of the convoy detailed in paragraph 7 is clear of camp. In the event of the artillery leaving this force., i double, company, iMth Mahrattas, will act as escort.15 ' C.' Memo. No. B. M.-1981, dated Nasiriyah, the llth February 1916. From-BRiOADTBR-GENERiL H. T. Brooking , C.B., Commanding, Uih Infantry Brigade, To—The General Staff Officer, General Headquarters, Basrah. Forwarded. During the rear guard action on the 7th February 1916. the Alhu Hamera section of the Azairich tribe, whose Tillages are situated along the Shattra ro. between about the 4th and 9th mile from Nasiriyah, and who hitherto have been friendly, turned treacherously on our troops retiring before tho enemy, as ey passed their Tillages. This treachery hampered the column Tery much and was responsible for a large number of the casualties. I considered a lesson abso- lutelv essential so I ordered out a column under Brigadier -General E. C. Tidswell D S.O. to surprise, attack and destroy Tillages of this treacberois section of Arabs. This was carried out most successfully with few casua.ties. I followed two hours later with another column consisting of 2 squadrons, 12th Cavalry ; 1 squadron, 33rd „ Sussex Battery ; 4i4th Merwara Infantry ; 90tli Punjabis ; to cover the retirement of General Tidswell's force. The attempt of the Arabs to turn the right flank of General Tidswell's Column was frustrated by my send ing half a battalion and machine guns to deal with this outflanking movement. The work of General Tidswell's Column was very well done and I am of the opinion that this action will have a good effect, but nothing but the rell ® f Kut-al-Amarah will have any real effect here. The tribes are in a great state of ferment. Memo. No. 176-B,M., dated Nasiriyab, the 11th February 1916. . From -brigadier -GENERAL E. C. Tidswell , Commanding, 31th Infantry Brigade, To—The General Officer Commanding, 12th Infantry Brigade. Herewith report on the operations of the Column under my command on the 9tli instant. Eeport on the operations of Brigadier-General R C. TidsweW* Column on 9th February 1916, General Tids well 's Column consisting of 2nd Royal West Kent Regiment l-5th Queen's Regiment 114th Mahrattas Brigaded machine guns of the above units 30th Mountain Battery ••• * Section, 2nd Sappers and Miners ThVznd fuSed a small'advarced'suard and the lUth Mahrattas a rear guard. 10 officers. 294 R. &amp; P. 21 „ 210 „ 10 British officers 538 „ 11 Indian „ 4 British ,, 254 „ 4 Indian „ 1 British ,» 36 „ 1 Indian ,, c 292 gsb1G By daybreak about 6-30 a.m . flank guards of l -Sfch Queen's and 114th Mahrattas were thrown out and normal day formations adopted, the force then having gone about three miles. At 7 a.m . the column reached the sandhills four and a half miles north of Nasiriyab. At 7-20 a.m . the first village, about 800 yards north of the sandhills was burnt by the 2nd Royal West Kent Regiment. The force then advanced to about six miles from Nasiriyah burning a total of four villages and blowing up one large tower. At 9-35 a.m . the retirement commenced. At 10-30 a.m . the column reached the position on the sandhills occupied by General Brooking's column and General Brooking took over command of the force. No resistance was experienced during the advance ; during the retirement the Arabs endeavoured to turn the right flank of the column but did not press the retirement with great vigour. Casualties. Unit. Killed. Wounded. 2nd Royal West Kent Regiment 2 R, &amp; F, 3 R.&amp; F. l-5th Queen's Regiment ... 2 „ 30th Mountain Battery ... 1 „ Ammunition expended. Unit. Eifles. Macliine guns. « Shells. 2nd Royal West Kent Regiment 2,695 120 • •• l-5th Queen's Regiment ... 4,050 293 • •• 114th Mahrattas ... 191 • •• 30th Mountain Battery ... • •• 179 C292aSB-30~ 7-11-16-GCBP Simla I</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001af_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/107</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001af</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/107</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Reports from Lieutenant-General Sir P. H. N. Lake, K.C.B., K.C.M.G., Commanding I.E.F. "D", on Operations against Arab Tribesmen on the Euphrates Line, January and February 1916'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-31T00:55:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume, including 2 maps (12 folios)</extent><extent>This printed report is divided into lettered reports, each containing numbered paragraphs and tables.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover, and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio (except for the front cover where the folio number is on the verso).Pagination: The volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This report, printed by the General Staff, India (Simla: Government Central Press, 1916), consists of a letter (No. 168-18-O) from Sir Percy Henry Noel Lake, General Officer Commanding, Indian Expeditionary Force D, to the Chief of the General Staff, Army Headquarters, India, dated 4 March 1916.It encloses three reports:Report A deals with an engagement during a reconnaissance between Butaniyah and Suwaij on 14 January 1916 (ff. 2v-3);Report B describes a rearguard action when the column was heavily attacked on 7 February 1916, on the occasion of the withdrawal from Nasiriyah [al-Nāṣirīyah] (ff. 5v-8);Report C gives an account of punitive operations undertaken by Brigadier-General H T Brooking on 9 February 1916 (f. 9).These reports give tables listing tribes, casualties and expenditure of small arm ammunition involved in various actions. The front cover is marked 'Confidential'. In addition, there are two maps (folios 10-11): 'Sketch Map of the Retirement from Butaniyeh Camp to Nasiriyah' and 'To Accompany Report on Operations Against Arab Tribesmen on Euphrates Line'.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Mesopotamia Expeditionary Force</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commander of the Mesopotamia Expeditionary Force</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Mesopotamian Campaign (1914-1918)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001af#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>