<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003bf_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T14:45:16.543Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CONFIDENTIAL. \ Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received December 6 , 9*30 a.m.) Tehran, December 5, 1912. (jN°. o 21 .) ^ 'December 6 , 10*35 a.m.) MINISTER for Foreign Affairs told me yesterday that the railway concessions had practically been agreed to by the Cabinet, and that he could promise me that all the concessions now being sought, incln ding exchange of telegraph lines, Tehran-Meshed and Ivhaf—Seistan, would be grarilecl provided that the two Governments would accept reconstitution of present Cabinet. His Highness made a somewhat similar communication to mv Russian colleague. (Sent to St. Petersburgh.) [1297 148]Minute Paper. Register No. Secret Department. Letters from f .0 Dated' Bee. 191Z • Under Secretary.. Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary.. Secretary of State Date. Initials. (Uck yiu- ZT. SUBJECT. /n &lt;fj~ Copy to Jy\A\ &lt;- FOR INFORMATION. Previous Papers :— 11856. 1.1990. 2000.—10/1911. [2127/10.]-2SDS CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley (Tehran). (No. 403.) R. rS-o'' Foreign Office, July 3, 1912, 120 YOUR telegram No. 390 of 1st July : Telegraphs. I concur. (Repeated to St Petersburgh, No. 533.) COPY TO INDIA 1911- S£ 0 !TN APV'SN^ri... I 767-44jCONFIDENTIAL r Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received July 2, 8 a.m.) (No. 390.) Tehran, July 1, 1912, 9’30 p.m. YOUD telegram No. 384 : Exchange telegraphs. Unless the question is considered of urgent importance, I would suggest that it be postponed for a time. Present weak Government has its hands full of difficult questions without the addition of another that has raised opposition, even if same was unjustifiable, in the past. /. Moreover, director of the [? Government of India] telegraphs is negotiating definite conclusion of arrangement made respecting the extension of concessions and taking over of the Arabistan line. To raise exchange question anew might hamper his negotiations. (Sent to St. Petersburgh.) COPY TO INDiA | 1 9 i SEC! ■ vTtNP.,.*.?..... jCONFIDENTIAL. r Vn.’ Si?' Edward Grey to Mr. O'Beirne (St. Petersburgh). (No. -538.) E. ^ Foreign Office, June 27, 1912, 6*30 p.m. MY telegram No. 384 to Tehran . Please telegraph views of Russian Government regarding the opportuneness of present moment for the exchange to be effected. (Repeated to Tehran, No. 385.) COPY TO INDK si.T S£CIUr i'ALY’S --ir £’ —i—- [514—972]CONFIDENTIAL Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley (Tehran). (No. 384.) Foreign Office, June 27, 1912, 6'15 p.m. MR. MARLING’S telegram No. 301 of 21st October, 1907 : Exchange of telegraphs. It would be desirable if possible that question of exchange of control of the telegraph lines Tehran-Meshed and Khaf-Nasratabad should now be carried to a conclusion. As opposition from the Medjliss need not at present be feared, do you consider the moment opportune for the exchange to be effected and for raising the question at Tehran ? It is desirable also that telegraph line should be built to Nasratabad from Kuh Malik Siah, where necessary material is ready at hand. Do you see any objection to making application to Persian Government ? (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 537.) j COPY TO INDIA I 1 I SECIII : liV NS,.,#.....) [514—971]Minute Paper. Register No. 3^32- Secret Department. Letter from vfe Dated Rec. 191 1 Date. Initials. Under Secretary /f OM Secretary of State lL \ 1 Ai_ Committee •*' £ Under Secretary Secretary of State SUBJECT. // H / Previous Papers :— L &amp; crstci . % 7^ !/£-*. /X Copy to 5n&lt;)rc, FOR INFORMATION. ,•V'' CONFIDENTIAL Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received July 22, 3o0 p.m.) (No 278.) y Tehran, July 22, 1911, o 50 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 214 [ ]• T 1 1 1 . . e , ■ + If Shuster remains after the present crisis, I think that m view oJ his great influence with the Medjliss we shall have good chance. Shuster is on good terms with King Woodland has led latter to believe that he will support Arabistan hue agreement provided it is not given a political significance. ,Ul.Tu^r*yL Mr [731—214]CONFIDENTIAL. 3 &lt;p i- 24 JUL1S11 Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 214.) Foreign Office, July 21, 1911, 6T5 p.m. YOUR despatch No. 246 of 1910: Arabistan Convention. Is there any likelihood of ratification ?In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote n ° &lt;r£ / and address— I The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, I .ondon. 2 s 1 / 26 JUL 1911 J 7'/^ Uuder-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 19 //. Reference to previous letter: d/pA rf (j1 Mr Description of Inclosure. [ 12 3CONFIDENTIAL. T his document is the property of the Secretary of State for India in Council. In reply to your letter No. 23,120, dated the 21st June 1911, regarding proposed agreements of the Indo-European Telegraph the working and maintenance of certain telegraph lines in Northern Persia, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to enclose, for the consideration of Secretary Sir E. Grey, copy of a Note by the Director- in-Chief of the Indo-European Telegraph Department upon the subject. It will be seen that the proposed agreement with the Persian Govern ment is at variance in important matters with the arrangements that have been entered into by the British with the Russian Government, and that, in the opinion of Mr. Kirk, it is very desirable that the Convention regarding the Arabistan lines should be ratified so as to secure the renewal of the British Telegraph Conventions until the 1st January 1945. / The Marquis of Crewe concurs generally in the views expressed in Mr. Kirk’s note, and would suggest that, if Sir E. Grey sees no objection, the reply to be made to M. Pagenkopf should be in the sense proposed in its final paragraph. In addition, it would seem well to convey to him a warning as regards what is said in his letter to M. de Klemm as to a possible extension of the telegraph line from Meshed to Herat, that no scheme of telegraphs into Afghanistan could be carried out except after consultation with the British Government. As regards the ratification of the Arabistan Convention, it is presumed that this is a matter in which the Persian Government will be advised by their newly-appointed Treasurer-General, Mr. Morgan Shuster. Lord Crewe would suggest, however, that if Sir E. Grey has no recent information in the matter, His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran might be asked his opinion as to the likelihood of the Convention being ratified. India Office, 17th July 1911. Sir, Company with the Russian and Persian Governments respectively, for I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) R. Ritchie. The Under Secretary of State Foreign Office. S. 82.a [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] I HAVE the honour to report that no progress had latterly been made towards obtaining the ratification by the Medjliss of the Arabistan Telegraph Agreement, and Assadullah Mirza, the Minister of Posts and Telegraphs, had constantly replied to the private representations of Mr. King Wood, the director of the Indo-European Telegraph Department, that the moment was not an opportune one for presenting to the Parliament an agreement which contained such delicate matter as the prolongation of the existing telegraph concessions. A short time ago, as repeated in my telegram No. 464 of the 20th November, the Minister of Posts and Telegraphs applied to Mr. King Wood for the loan of one of his staff to place in temporary order the Mohammerah-Ahwaz and Borasjan telegraph lines. The department consented to comply with this request on the express understanding that their doing so should not prejudice in any way the agreement for the transfer of these lines to the department now awaiting ratification. This assurance has now been given in writing by Assadullah Mirza, and an officer of the department has been dispatched to Arabistan. In the same document Assadullah Mirza has also expressed his readiness to influence his colleagues of the Cabinet to agree to present the convention to the Medjliss as soon as the last annual account for terminal charges between the department and the Persian Government had been settled in full. In this account, Mr. King Wood had under instructions from his chief in London debited the Persian Government with the sum of some 1,200Z., representing the actual had supported Mr. King Wood’s action in a note to the Persian Government. In view, however, of his Excellency’s recent assurances, I have at the request of Mr. King Wood let the Persian Government understand that if assurances are forthcoming that the claims in question will be paid with the least possible delay the account will be settled in full. CONFIDENTIAL. PERSIA. [January 16 .J Section II. [1708] No. 1. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received January 16, 1911.) (No. 246.) Sir, Tehran, December 30, 1910. damages sustained by his employes, owing to the prevalent disorder when in the performance of their duties. Assadullah Mirza had demurred at this deduction, and I I have, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. [1845 9 —II]INDO-EUROPEAN TELEGRAPH DEPARTMENT.^ 344 Minute \ Losses incurred by the staff of the Indo RECEiVEoS European Telegraph Department through high way ^ohlery u &gt;APn. J 3 W } JNDjA Qi-FiCt in Pay's in are rat* aver able from i e Persian Goverruxe nt either directly or by short payment of sums due to that Government by the Department. There is at times great aelay in the settlement of these claims; ana to relieve the telegraph employes from the hardship consequent on long delays in payment of their claims, the Director in Chief proposes that the Department shculc pay all duly certifud claims against the Persian Government for losses incurred by the members of the staff in assaults and robberies carried out against them while in the ordinary perfofinance of their duties. The amounts so paid will be treated in the accounts as advances against the Persian Government, for settlement with that Government as soon as such settlement can be arranged either directly or by short payment of sums due by the Department a opdoCounc il It is submitted that this proposal be approved[This Document is the Property of His Britatoic Majesty’s Government.] WITH reference to previous correspondence, I have the honour to forward a convention which I have this day signed with the Persian Government placing the control and supervision of the Arabistan telegraph lines under the Indo-European Telegraph Department till 1945, and prolonging the telegraph concessions held by that department in Persia until the same date. I also enclose copies of the notes exchanged simultaneously with the signature of the convention recording that the arrangement requires the ratification of the Assembly. It will be observed that the share in the cost of the construction and maintenance of the Arabistan lines to be borne by the department is fixed at 5,000/. towards the construction and 300/. a-year towards the maintenance, which is considerably less than the department was prepared to spend. The credit for this satisfactory arrangement belongs to the director of the Persian section of the department and to Mr. King-Wood, who have conducted the negotiations with the Minister of Telegraphs with much skill and patience. I should also wish to accord my appreciation of the sensible and conciliatory spirit shown throughout by the Minister of Telegraphs, Mukhber-ed-Dowleh. Unfortunately he was not allowed a free hand, but met with much obstruction from certain members of the late Cabinet, the stupid and reactionary Minister of Finance, Kavem-ed-Dowleh, in particular. Had it not been for the ignorant and corrupt obstruction of this Minister, the convention would have been signed some months ago, when there would not have been the same necessity for the ratification by the Assembly, as the constitution had not been restored, though the Ministers responsible for the conclusion of the arrangement would doubtless have been vehemently attacked in the Medjliss for having consented to the prolongation of concessions without the consent of year 1945. Other expenses, such as the changing of the wooden posts for iron ones and the annual expenses of the maintenance of the above-mentioned lines, which may be in excess of the 5,000/. and the annual amount of 300/., shall, after the completion of the work, and the submission of the accounts, be paid gradually to the British Telegraph Department by the Persian Government. CONFIDENTIAL. PERSIA. Section 16. [July 5.] [25142] ^IJo. 1. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received July 5.) (No. 125.) Sir, Gulahek, June 17, 1909. the nation. I have, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. Inclosure 1 in No. 1. Anglo-Persian Convention, signed June 17, 1909. Article 1. TO improve the telegraphic communication between Borazjoon and Mohammerah and Borazjoon and Dizful it is arranged that from the date of this agreement until January 1945 the above-mentioned telegraph lines shall be under the control and supervision of the British Government telegraph officials now controlling the international lines in Persia. Article 2. 1 he British Government agrees to pay for the cost of the construction and the establishment of the above-mentioned lines, such as iron posts, wire, insulators, &amp;c., which may be required, up to 5,000/., and also to pay an annual sum of 300/. on account of the maintenance of the above-mentioned lines, and the pay of a mechanician up to the [2339 e—16]Inclosure 2 in No. 1. Copy of Note signed by Sir G. Barclay and Saad-ed-Dowleh. Your Excellency. J une 17 y 1909 . I HAVE the honour to state to your Excellency that it is fully understood between us that the convention for a telegraph line between Borazjoon and Mohammerah and between Borazjoon and Dizful, which your Excellency and I have signed together, will require the approval of the Persian National Assembly. I avail, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. JEYAD, SAAD-ED-DOWLEH.With reference to your letter of April 11th, relative to the delay in the submission of the Arabistan Telegraph Convention to the Persian Mejlis, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward G-rey to transmit to you herewith copy of a telegram from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran suggesting that he should authorise the Director of the Indo-European Telegraph Department at that capital to refuse the settlement of the overdue departmental annual account with the Persian Minister of Telegraphs till the Convention has been passed by that Assembly. 1 am to state that, subject to the concurrence of Yiscount Morley, Sir E. Grey would propose to authorise Sir G. Barclay to act as he suggests. The Under Secretary of State, I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, India Office.Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 26, 4*30 p.m.) (No. 3&lt;36.) Tehran, September 26, 1910, 2 , 50 p.m. ARABISTAN Convention. Director of Indo-European Telegraph Department has used every effort to induce Minister of Telegraphs to put convention before Medjliss. Minister has frequently promised to do so, but continues to procrastinate. Settlement of departmental annual account with the Telegraph Minister is overdue. Minister presses for settlement. I would propose to authorise director to refuse settlement until convention has passed Medjliss. To withhold settlement would be, however, somewhat high-handed, and you may not concur with me in thinking that such a course is warranted by delay in ratifying a convention which was made subject to ratification. I therefore await instructions. [592—514]‘3// CONFIDENTIAL AM- vljl . &gt;\t I ■s /Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 96.) ^ Foreign Office, April 12, 1910, 5*10 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 140 [of 4th April: Arabistan Telegraph Convention]. I leave it to your discretion both as to offering inducements mentioned in paragraph 1 of my telegram No. 87 [of 1st April] to secure approval of convention in its present form, and as to offering modifications indicated in paragraph 2 to secure acceptance of alternative draft. ' i . / r &gt; . 1 ' f O /V' n t&lt;0 ,9 »■) In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote xo. 11473/10. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, '**■ Foreign Office, London. Sir-- (f\ v '6 APR IQ|n * ) X : -&gt; I am directed by Secretary sir Edward Grey to in- Foreign Office April 6th, 1910. form you that, on the receipt of your letter of the 26th ultimo relative to the Anglo-Persian convention respecting the Arabistan telegraph lines and to the renewal of the telegraph agreements of the Indo-Euro pean Telegraph Department, he addressed a telegram to His Majesty* s Minister at Tehran enquiring whether he had any objection to urge to Viscount Morley*s or 0, \\A proposals. I am to transmit to you herewith copy of a tele gram from Sir G. Barclay in reply / from which it will be seen that, while he does not consider that conces sions are likely to improve the chances which the convention has of being accepted by the Mejlis, he has no objections to offer to the suggested modifica tions in the alternative draft. he Under Secretary of State, India Office. 1 ^ 1 °(11473/10). I am to request that Sir E. Grey may he favoured, in due course, with an expression of Lord Morley's opinion on this telegram in order that the necessary instructions may he sent to Sir G. Barclay for his guidance in the matter. I am Sir Your most obedient humhle servantCONFIDENTIAL. 9 Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received April 4, I'lO p.m.) (No. 140.) Tehran, April 4,1910, 2’10 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 87 [of 1st April] : Arabistan Convention. As far as my present information enables me to judge, I do not think that by increasing our offer we should improve our chances of Medjliss accepting our con vention. I gather from the lobbying that I have done that if the convention is rejected it will not be because our terms are not good enough, but because of the Medjliss’s distrust of Russia, and their fear that it may provoke some demand from her for compensating advantages. I see no objection to proposed modifications in alternative draft.J / CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 87.) Foreign Office, April 1, 1910, 6 p.m. YOUR despatch No. 18 : Arabistan telegraphs. India Office consider that if Medjliss unwilling to accept convention as it stands owing mainly to distrust of article renewing telegraph concessions, it should if possible be persuaded to change attitude by offering (1) not to exercise right to claim for ordinary damages to Indo-European Department’s lines in Persia, and (2) to advance sum not exceeding 10,000?. against next ten years’ minimum rental of Central Persia line. . , Convention is valuable apart from its provision for renewal of concessions, and alternative draft should therefore be brought forward omitting that provision if necessary. Barker’s draft is generally suitable for this puipose, but if fuither con cessions are required it should be modified so as to provide foi expenditure by His Majesty’s Government for benefit of Persian Government of sum not exceeding 1,000?. for providing material on the line, and annual sum not exceeding 600?. for maintenance. This has already been sanctioned by Treasury in letter of 13th August, 1908. If this modification is adopted, it appears unnecessary at present to consider pro posal to waive charge of 4 per cent, interest upon total amount due by Peisian Government under article 2, which would involve correspondence with Treasury. India Office letter and memorandum by director-in-chief follows Have you any objection ? 'I 1 ' • (Ur.Z-r Political and Secret) Reference Paper. Department, j Letter No. 3 ^SZ?, Rec. 19 ^- ^Referred to syk day of 19/0 . ^ ' ■ !( vtfh. lie a 3 ih) ! i/v*t ) 4 f ' The terms of the alternative draft convention do not appear to he of a kind likely to prove altogether acceptable to the Mejliss. They are noc as favourable to the Persian Government as those it was proposed to offer in 1908. The papers under Register No.2786'show that the survey of the Arabistan telegraph lines and temporary repairs were estimated to cost £300, the more permanent repairs £1000 and the annual maintenance of the line £600. Judex Register Not^bl/ there is the copy of a letter from the Treasury to the Poreign Office,dated 13th August 1908, saying that, in view of tne assurance now given by the Secretary of State for Poreign Affairs that the control of this line is of the highest political moment, the Treasury will accept the charge to the Imperial Exchequer of an initial expenditure not exceeding £650, ana a recurrent expenditure not exceeding o£300 a year^, being one half of the cost involved in taking over and maintaining tne line. 2. Mr.Barker in framing his alternative convention seems to have made too little of the fact that it is \ 5609. I. 723. 1000.—4/1909.■ 4-f TV is of great political importance we should obtain con trol of the Arabistan lines. In writing to me he stated he had made the terms of the alternative convention stiff, because in the negotiations for the original convention he had adopted the line that the Department was not so much interested with Arabistan lines as in the renewal of the Telegraph concessions. As however we want to obtain the control of the Arabistan lines it seems desirable that we should offer more liberal terms than are proposed by hr Barker. The survey of the Arabistan lines has already been carried but, but if the alternative Convention contained clauses to the effect that £1000 would be spent in provision of materials and placing them on the line, plus £600 per annum on the maintenance of the line, free of cost to the Persian Government, the transfer of the control of uhe line to the Indo-European Telegraph Department would be more likely to be made acceptable to the Mejliss. The charge for half of this expenditure has, as I have shewn, been accepted by the Treasury. 3. Sir G.Barclay contemplates the possibility that the Mejliss will refuse to ratify the Convention that is to be presented to it. If this happens he desires to have an alternative convention ready, dealing only with the Arabistan lines and making no mention of the renewal of the other concessions. But before accepting the refusal of the first Convention it might perhaps be useful to offer further inducements to have itV t' it passed. The Persian Minister of Telegraphs has not, as far as ray information goes, 'been told that although we are not prepared to forego the right of claiming compensation in the, event of the telegraph lines suffering serious and extensive injury owing to internal disorders, yet on the ratification of the Convention we would in future not put forward claims for com pensation for acts of ordinary damage. This was ex plained to the Poreign Office in India Office letter dated 4th July 1907,(Register Ho.3230). Also though sanction has he^n given bo offer the inducement to the Persian Government of allOY/ing an advance payment up to £10,000 on account of the rental of the Central Persia line (see papers under Register Ho.4130 of December 1908) the original Convention was obtained without bringing forward this offer. Perhaps if the Mejliss rejects the original Convention as it stands, these further inducements to pass it might bring about a successful result. 4. Should however the Mejliss prove unyielding the only course appears to be to bring forward the alternative Convention as drafted by Mr.Barker, but, I should say, modified to the extent suggested by me in paragraph 2 of this memorandum. 5, The foreign Office ask that the Secretary of State should express an opinion on the proposal to waive the four per cent interest payable on the total cost in curred under Article 2 of the draft alternative Convention Sir*. * Sir George Barclay suggests that permission should be given|to waive this claim for four per cent interest if necessary. Taking into consideration the importance of obtaining the control of the line, the interest might be asked for in the first instance, and the claim might be dropped later if the negotiations showed thisbe SO BBAFT TO FOHETOnOFFICE. n Jio^L '^'iV Sir, I ofo direotecl by the S, of S. for India to acknowledge the receipt of you?' letter Ho. 7009, dated the 4th 11 arch 1910, regarding the Anglo-Ter aim Convention - now awaiting ratification by the lledjlisc - which has been arranged with the two-fold object of securing the control of the Arabist an lines by the Indo-European Telegraph Dept., and the renewal of the Tele graph Conventions of 1868, 1872 and 1901. Copy of a Ifemo. by the Direct Of*-in-Chief of the I.E. Tel. Dept, upon the subject is enclosed. Viscount 1 lor ley concurs in the view of /&gt;. KirK that, if the Medjlies is unwilling to accept the Convention as it stands, owing mainly to its distrust of the Article renew ing the telegraph concessions, it would be very desirable to persuade it, if possible, to adopt a different attitude by offering the further in ducements referred to in para. 9 of the Memo., viz. (1) the non-exercise of our right to put forward claims for acts of ordinary damage to the Dept's lines in Persia; and (2) the advance of a sum not exceeding £10,000 against the next ten yenrs 1 minimum rental of the Central Persia Line. Lord Morley also agrees in the view that, even apa^t from the provision1 [ •- r provision for the renewal of the telegraph concessions, the Convention is of considerable value, and that it would he desirable,in the event of that provision having to he dropped, to bring forward an alternative Convention^ ^ ^ For this purpose Hr. Barber's draft■ seems generally suitable, hut Lord Forley would suggest that, if circumstances should mabe further concessions necessary, it should he modified so as to provide for the expenditure hy the British coi't., for the benefit of the Ter si an novt., of a sum not exceeding £1,000 in the provision of telegraph material on the 1 uSt‘ ULCud*~-j line, together with an annual sum -of £600 for maintenance. As pointed out hy Ur. Kirb, the L. 0. of H. M's Treasury have already consented to hear a moiety of this expenditure. If tjammodification of the Convention in the interests of the Ter si aii Govt, is decided upon, it as~Y&gt; appears unnecessary to consider the proposal to waive the charge of 4fo interest on the total mount dm hy the Persian Government under Art.8 on aocounf of the supply of posts, insulators &amp;c. This proposal could not he accepted vdthout further correspon- d noe with the l.C.of H.M.Treasury, whic' a urgency of the matter renders undesirable.If Secretcrry Sir E.Grey conoous Lord Morleij would suggest that H.M. Minister at Tehran should he instruc ted in the sense of the foregoing renarhs, it being left to his dis cretion to make the best terns possible within +he Units indicated.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote so. 7009/10. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, I ) London. Sir:- Foreign Office March 4th, 1910. v &lt;'.Vd f/W') h^clrlyfo Sd^o. f( With reference to Sir G. Barclay's despatch No.125 J L&lt; b| A o f June 17th last, copy of which will he found in Persia Confidential Print, July 5th section 16, rela tive to the Anglo-Persian Convention for the improve ment of the Arahistan telegraph lines and their con trol by the Indo-European Telegraph Department and for the renewal of the telegraph agreements of 1868, 1872 and 1901, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a further despatch on the subject. It will be observed that Sir G. Barclay contem plates the possibility that the Mejlis will refuse to ratify this Convention and that, in order to fore stall such an eventuality, an alternative draft conven tion has been prepared from which the provisions most likely to be distasteful to that assembly have been omitted Ihe Under Secretary of State, India Office.(7009/10). omitted. I am to request that Viscount Morley will te so good as to furnish Sir E. Grey with his ohservations on this draft which, as appears from Sir G. Barclay's despatch, has already been submitted to the Director- in-chief of the Indo-European Telegraph Department, and that he will at the same time express an opinion on the proposal to waive the four per cent interest payable on the total cost incurred by His Majesty's Government under Article 2 of the/ convention. I am, Your most obedient,Copy. No.O (7009) V 6-^ / TEHRAN, i 1 ebruary 8 th 1910. &lt; ^^0 {c^ ^ jyyir^ ^ /Jj '&lt;0 £c&amp;~l - (i Sir:- In my despatch No.125 of June 17th 1909 I forwarded a convention signed by the Minister for Foreign Affairs and by me for the improvement of the Arabia tan telegraph lines and their control by the Indo-European Telegraph Department, and for the renewal of the telegraph agreements of 1868, 1872 and 1901. It will be remembered that this Convention was not to come into operation until it had been ratified by tne Medj- liss. It is shortly to be submitted to the Medjliss, and Mr. Barker has thought it well to prepare for the contingency of refusal to ratify it. He has, therefore, submitted to Mr. Kirk an alternative draft convention dealing only with the Arabistan lines and making no mention of the renewal of the other concessions, which is the part of the signed con vention most likely to prove unpalatable to the Medjliss. Sir E. Grey, Bart., &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c. II inclose a copy of the new draft together with a summary 7 . statement of how the provision proposed for that cost of construction and maintenance would work out in practice ac cording to Mr. Barker’s estimate. I trust that the contingency of having to negotiate a new Convention will not arise, but should it do so, it is well to have an alternative ready in order to avoid delay. Mr. Barker’s draft appears to meet the case and 1 would only suggest that v/e should be permitted to waive the 4% interest if necessary. As to the chances of the signed convention’s receiving the approval of the Medjliss, I am not in a position to speak with any certainty as 1 have purposely abstained from feel ing the ground in order to incur no unnecessary hostile agi tation. Serdar Mansur, the Minister of Posts and Telegraphs, has promised to give me two or three days' notice before the question is raised in the House, which will leave me plenty of time for such lobbying as seems desirable. I have &amp;c., (Signed) G. Barclay.t D . In the event of the Persian Assembly refusing to ratify the agreement for the renewal of the concessions of the \W Indo-European Telegraph Department, -the alternative propos- ’ als made herein mi^it be put forward. ip Article 1. To improve telegraphic communication between Borasjun and Mohammerah and Borasjun and Bizful it is arrang ed that from the date of this agreement until — the above mentioned telegraph lines shall be under the con trol and supervision of the British Government telegraph officials now controlling the international lines in Persia. Article 2. The British Government agrees to procure for the Persian Government at a reasonable price all the posts, wire insulators &amp;c. that may be requisite for the work, and to arrange for the carriage of the stores to the sites required. An account of the expenses incurred for this purpose and certified in so far as they have been in curred in Persia by the Director of the Indo-European Tele graph Department, and in so far as they have been incurred outside Persia by the Director in Chief of the Department shall be submitted as early as possible to the Persian Government.- - *H&gt;g First charge. Krans. Cost of Inspector say 25,000. Cost of annual repairs 20,000 Salaries of Grholaras 15,000. Horse allowances 15,000 Contingencies 5,000 Total 80,000. Second charge. 4% on sey &lt;£10,COO = £400 say = 20,000 Krans. First and second charges total Krans 100,000. Taking the average annual cash collections for mesi v originating and terminating in Persia as Krans 150,000. Deducting 1st and 2nd. charges of Krans 100,000. Balance available annually in redemption of capital is Krans 50,000.—305-D ( mn I'oroh IP 10. ) % I. Tm question of the improvemnt of teleqraphio oorrmmioption vHth Ahwoz and Hoharymrah, nay he said to have first assumed praotioal form in a letter of the Government of India -v* dated the Pth Pay 1P07* In this i Approx, distonobhey draw attention to the inoonven- the tn&amp;fftoisnt nanaqemnt of the line hy the I erst an Authorities, and grounds, that the Persian Govt, should he induced to improve their line would never work satisfactorily unless it were taken over by the Indo- European Telegraph Department. Copy of their letter was forward ed to the Foreign Office, together with a copy of a Fete in vfnioh the Director-in-Ghief of the Indo-European J Telegraph Dept, referred to the possibility of Germany obtaining control over the line, and the Sec retary of State expressed his view on the s'uggested control of the Fo twiner ah - Boras jun line by tM Ahwa? to Eohammrah Ahivar ' Boras fun Eiwar ' Bizful 100 rt ienoe arising at these place* from IhJh Boras fun t* on the Info European Tel. Dept, line from Tehran to Erthire . All places are in the neutral rone. existing Borasfun - Ahwar - Eoihaamerah urged on political and commercial x Foreign Dept., Secret Bo. 78, iii, cm/or. arrangements. The Govt, yf India believed that the Ahwaz - Boras fun, j ; {' v , i /-’.o. to July 1907» Sfioret Ttenpatoh to n O”t. of imlin, 'T 0 . ?*. P Au«'Mt 1907. 9954/07. Tnao-European ?&amp;lvgranh B&amp;pt. in ths f ol 1 0 'vi ng tern 9: - 'The political advantage a of emh an 'arrangement, if it can he effected, 'are isnqiwetionahle; and if Sir Edward n 0reg thinha it expedient to give 'effeot to the propoa tl, ;^. ; r orley 'would he prepared to euhnit to the Qo'Jnoil of India that half the oosi 'ehould he home by Indian revenues, 'the British Treasury hearing the 'other half. 'Before, hoxo&amp;ver, the matter is con- 'sidered further it seems desirable 'to ascertain whether there is any 'prospect of the Persian oovt. 'agreeing in present circumstances to 'grant any further privileges to 'foreigners. ' The Foreign Office did not, however, consider the moment opportune for raising the question, and *he covt. of India were informed accordingly. Viceroy's telegram,! Sept. 1907. P. In September 1907, after the iwijor. signature on the 91st August 1907 of the Anglo-Buesian Convention, the Oovt. of India again brought fonoard the proposal, referring to the foot that the line was in the neutral zone. F. 0. to I. 0., IS Seotmber'07. The Foreion Office considered that, 8658/07, in view of the temper of the Persian national Assembly, no action was for the moment possible, hut stated that Bis Majesty Is Minister at Tehran would'0 V •' ; r i c Wfi/I Initruotvci to bring the proposal forward at a favourable opportmity: the natter night fitly he negotiated at the sane tim as the renmoal of the British Telegraph Concession? in Persia. These* it nay he explained, mre due to expire in 1925* The Concessions had hem given under three Conventions as follows:- 2 April 1868, for construct ing r md wording the Gtoadur-JasK Coast line* 2 Decmh&amp;r 1872* for word ing a telegraph line frovi Tehran to Pus'lire, ami allovHng trie T.p. Tel. Dept* to resum charge of a line fron Tehran to KlvmiHin at any tine while tm Convent toil was in force: 16 August 1901, for con structing and maintaining the Central Persia line. Per a fuller description of these Convention's, see 2r. Kirk's Ifeno. of 2K&gt; April 1907, copy annexed. 1 f F.O. to T. 0 ., PI Dec. 1907. 4121 ] 07. T.Q. to F.O ., 18 Feb. 1908. 2786j QQ. 2. At the end of the year, at the instance of K. H. Charge d'Affaires at Tehran, the question of taking active steps to control the Arabist cm lines ms once more considered, and trie Foreign Office were informed by this Office that the survey of the Hohanmrdh - Bor as fun line and its temporary repairs v'svc estimated to cost some £300, more permanent repairs - to be carried out later -of the Tnfto-Eitrapecsn Telegraph Pept., ?v * KtTb$ rvoorz-wnded that in the event of tin I'inister of Talejraphe making the proposal above referred to, hie Dept % ehould he prepared +o oaoept it, an-d , provided the Persian Telegraph Dept, maid undertake to prooure an extension of oitr oonoexa- iom up to W4B t should offer to reoonetrmt the Arabist an lines on their behalf at a cost of som AC,000 and to spend in addition som £€00 per annum in maintaining it. Further, the Indo-European Telegraph Department here , if n&amp;oe&amp;sary, to offer to ad vance to the Persian Telegraph Depart ment a limp sun not exceeding £10,000 - being ten years 1 rental of the Central Persia Line, a line covered by one of ^he Conventions proposed to he renewed. Dr. KirH suggested that the stip ulations with regard to the Arabistan lines might he as follows:- ft (g *)* 1.0. to P.C. 22 Deo . 1908 . (a) Che transfer of control up to 1945, (v) Permission to employ telegraphists of the InUo-Puj-opeun Telegraph Dept* at telegraph offices in Mchammerah , Ahwaz, and at the station on the Teh&amp;ran-Dushire line to which the Arabistan line may be connected. (c) Permission to connect the Arabist an linn to the Teheran-Bush ire line for purposes of through working. (d) Permission for the Xndo- European Telegraph Department to erect a second sire for its own use should this be desired during the period of its control. (&amp;) Guarantee from the Persian Government that, with the exception of employ&amp;s of the Indo-Euroj ean Telegraph Department required for the purposes of control, it will allow the ersployment in the telegraph offices dnd on the lines of Persian subjects only.' A copy of Mr. Kirk's Memo, was forwarded to the Foreign Office on the 22nd Dec. 1908 with for Sir E.Gray's views. u request In our letter it was observed as follows:- * A point that /.as to be 'considered before a aecision is 'arrived at is whether the Russian 'Government'Government, u?iQi&gt;&amp; consent looujid he 'necessary, u)ould be willing to agree 'to the arrangement jjroj osed by Mr, 'Kirk, which has for them the 'advantage of excluding the influence 'of any third Power from the sphere of the telegraph system in Arabistan, 'as well as of *,&gt;'***trig to them the 'control of the Teheran-Khunihin line 'till 1945'. We had already agreed tp m^ke over our rights with regard to the Teharan-Khanikin line to the Russian Government. 2907 Aide-m&amp;moire from Russian Govt., 29 Jan. 9 09. 'OCj 5. On the 26th January 2909 Sir A. HicoIson forwarded to the Foreign Of ice c py of an aiae-m'metre in which he had explained fully to the Russian Gcb&amp;nvmnt our proposals with regard to the Arabistan lines. To these the Russian Government took no objection, beyond expressing a hope that Russian telegraph officials, if necessity should arise, might be permitted to work on the apparatus of the telegraph stations in Arabistan. T}i&amp;ywished, however, to separate negotiations on the question of any new concessions from negotiations as to the exchange between Great Britain and Russia of their control over Ifa Tehran-Meshed and Xhaf-Seistan lines, for^‘ ■ ’TWS Aide-memoire to Russian Government&gt; 6 March *09, 3042 -ism Tel, to Sir A.Nioolson, Plo, 20?, 19 Feb. *09 'Me'/277,5 Mar. '09 dcnd-l ^9 for which arrangement had bean made between the two Governments at the time of the Anglo-Russian Convention. 6. After some correspondence between the India Office ami the Foreign Office, Sir A.Ificolson informed the Russian Government that their wish as to signallers could be met by the conclusion of a Secret Agreement between the British and Russian Gov&amp;rruaents, the projos id Agreement with the Persia n Govt, stipulating that, without the concur rence of the British Govt., no others than Persian subjects and the members of the staff of the I.E. Tele- gruph jOept. should he employed in the offices or on the lines of the system. Sir A,Nicolson was also instructed, if necessary, to explain to the Russian Government our view as to the desirability of proceeding with the negotiations as to the Arabist an lines before those relating to the Tehran-Meshed and Khaf-Nasratabad lines. Tel. from &gt;' ir 1 .Parclav, No. 137, 8 MarM09. 3039 7. At this point un addition was made in the draft Agreement that was being negotiated at Tehran as to the Arabistan lines, securing the right of His Majesty's Govt, to cooperate in the constriction and maintenance of anyI ^ any extension cf those lines. The possession of such a right ujould prevent acquisition by u third Power of an extension from Mohomtmrah to Basrah. The Pus si an 0 vt. were asked if they had any objection to thm at the same time that the right referred to would be waived in the event of the t&amp;legrajsh lines being extended in^ho the Russian sphere. telegraphed that the Persian Minister for foreign Affairs was prepared to sign a convention well within the lines l^id down, on condition of an exchange of notes recording that it was not to become operative until approved by the Assembly. Some further correspondence followed between the India Office and the Foreign Office, with the result the Arabistan Telegraphs Convention was signed on the 17th June 1909. Its text was received here on the 21st ing of A rt i cl a 9 is us fo 11 ows:- ' ,f Tho Persian Government agrees n not to employ in the telegraph offices of the above-mentioned lines. Aide-memoire to Russian Government IS March *09. this a dd it io n, it bei ng exj la mad t o On the 21st May Sir G. Barclay July 1909, and a copy is annexed. 9. It will be seen that the wordr without■ »W' 1 Aide-me .oi ?\i from masi un ' rovi* 9 Si? . I r ay 9 09 3640 7T^ 'without the concurrence of the 'chiefs of the British Telegraph 'Department, anyone except Persian 'subjects or mmb&amp;rs of the British 'Gov&amp;rrm&amp;nt Telegraph Department'. In connection with this Article, it had previously been arranged to conclude a Secret Agreement with the Russian Govemment providing that 'the British Govt &gt; will not put 'obstacles in the way $/' in time it 'should appear necessary to the 'Russian Govt, to despatch their own 'telegraph officials to the lines 'meritioned for the transmission of 'telegrams in the Russian language, on principles analogous with those 'which have been established in 'relation to the Khaf-Sets tan line, ' Telk from Sir A.NicoliLon, further Do. 279,30 Day*09 It was/agreed that the Russian • * »» tt ,, n hr -° • 390,3 ^ une'09. signaller's 'should be attached to 3430 1903 ,f t?ie Indo-Paropean Telegraph Dept. Tel. to Sir A.Nicolson,No*739, 1 1 10 June *03. 'and considered as employes of that JObfcirtment'. 10. As to the exchange of the control over the Tah ran-M shed and the Khuf-S&amp;istan lines, the Russian Government ware informed that 11. M. 'Jcvt. would propose that the rej&gt; resent at ives of the two Govts. /f 351 jjUUD Ai ae-memc ire to Buss i m ovt. 11 June *09 3640 TTH Ditto . Tel. to Sir A.HicoIson, Jo. 761,17 June *09. 3562 ~~TUT}9 atTal* from Sir KJh*relay, , F.O* to I.n. 4 Mar. 9 10, 3050 -mo. at Tehran should h&lt;i authorised to briny ths question before the Persian Oov&amp;mm&amp;nt at the first favourable OJPJ ortmipy. Sir G.Barclai/ telegraphed, however, on the 19th June last tf S. it nut ion has oh a ng&amp;d. 'Feeling ag ains t Russla is so strong 'that no Minister oonld dare consent 'to exchange of telegraphs for fear 'of the Assembly . 11 . ’Hi 3 letter no v rec .iv jd f rom the Foreign Office deals with the possibility that the Mejlis will ^Isc refuse to ratify our A/xibistan Convention .[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Govenimpyif. ] PERSIA. [May 9.] CONEID ENTIAL. Section 1, [15166] No. 1. India Office to Foreign Office.—{Received May 9.) Sir, India Office, May 8, 1907. WITH reference to Sir F. Campbell’s letter dated the 19th April, 1907, relative to the question of renewing the contracts of the Indo-European Telegraph Depart ment in Persia, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Morley to forward herewith, to be laid before the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, copy of a Memorandum on the subject by the Director-in-chief of the Department. Mr. Morley agrees generally in the views expressed by Mr. Kirk, and he would propose, subject to Sir E. Grey’s concurrence, that His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran should be instructed, in accordance wdth the suggestion made in his telegram of the 17th April, to address the Persian Government in the sense of the 7th paragraph of Mr. Kirk’s note, the Russian Government being informed of any action that may be taken in the matter. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) A. GODLEY. Inclosure in No. 1. Memorandum on the Renewal of the British Telegraph Conventions with Persia. ON the 16th March last I wrote to the Director of Telegraphs at Tehran telling him that the Indo-European Telegraph Company had arranged in June 1906 with the Persian Government that the term of its telegraph Concession, which ran to 1925, should be extended for a further period of twenty years up to 1945. I pointed out that in lb91, after this Company obtained the extension of its Concession from 1905 to 1925, we also went to the Persian Gevernment to have the British telegraph Concessions renewed for the same peiiod, and that this was duly arranged. He was instructed to remind the British Minister at Tehran of what had taken place regarding the renewal of the British Concessions up to 1925, this action being taken in order that what happened on the last occasion of the renewal of the Company’s Concession might not escape attention on this. 2. From the telegram of the 17th instant that has been received from the British Minister at Tehran it would appear that the present time may prove to be favourable for obtaining an extension of the British telegraph Concessions, as there would have to be a payment to make for their renewal, and money is very badly wanted by the Persian Government. In order to obtain the renewal of these Concessions in 1892 a present of 5,000/. was made to the Shah, and a watch of the value of 500/. was given to the Persian Prime Minister, this expenditure being debited to the capital account of the Indo-European Telegraph Department. At the same time the Persian Minister of Telegraphs was made a K.C.I.E. for his services in the matter. 3. In 1891 we obtained the extension from 1905 to 1925 of the two following Conventions:— (1.) The Convention, dated the 2nd April, 1868, for the construction and working of the coast-line from the Persian frontier near Gw^adur to Jask. (2.) The Convention of the 2nd December, 1872, for the working of the telegraph line from Tehran to Bushire. Since 1891 another Telegraph Convention has been entered into, dated the 16th August, 1901, for the construction and maintenance of the Central Persia line, practically a telegraph line from Tehran to Robat on the Indian frontier. This Convention remains in force until 1925, or for such longer period as the debt due by Persia for the construction of the line remains unpaid. [2474 i —I]1 4. It is necessary for the proper consideration of the British position as regards telegraphs in Persia to show what would happen if ^ e ^ ens ^ on , °p t eSe + . ire ^ Conventions beyond 1925 cannot he arranged. Taking first the Jask Convention of 1868 its non.renewal would mean the loss to the Persian Government of an annua royalty of 3,600 tomans, equivalent at present to about 5006 The line would be of no use y to tlm Persian Government, as it is a detached land line a ong the coast, and is used as an alternative to a cable. The Persian Government may therefore be expected to extend the Concession for this line, as there is nothing to he gained by not doing so and its non-renewal means a direct loss of revenue Coming to the Convention of 1872 for the working of the Tehran-Bushire line, should the renewal of it beyond 1925 not he granted, the Persian Government would be forced, under their Agreements with the Indo-European Telegraph Company, to hand over this section of the line to the Company, and for doing this they would receive no payment nor compensation oi any kind*. It is therefore to the advantage of the Persian Government to renew the Concession of the British Telegraph Department, if they can obtain a payment for doim? so It is also to the interest of the British Government that the Concession Should be renewed, because the withdrawal of the British Department from this section of line would mean a loss of prestige and influence to the British Governn'ent. At the same time, as the Company that would take over the line is m Persia under the official protection of the Russian Government, there would be an increase of Russian influence in a part of the country where previously British influence had prevailed. 5. The Convention of 1901 regarding the Central Persia line extends to 192o, or for such longer period as the Persian Government may take to pay off the debt for its construction. This debt under the arrangement contained m tfle Convention would he paid off in thirty-three and a-quarter years from the completion of the line, and as the line will he completed this year the debt would be cleared off m 1940 It is laid down in the Convention that in 1925, or later, when the debt has been paid otl, the Convention may, if necessary, he renewed or revised. It would seem, therefore, that if the Persian Government did not agree to the necessity of its renewal, the Convention would come to an end, and the line Tvould have to be handed over to that Government to he worked by the Persian Administration, or by any one that the Government chose to appoint. This freedom of action might possibly result m arrangements being made that would seriously affect British interests. ^ To explain how this might he done it has to be borne in mind that the Convention of 1872 allows the Indo-European Telegraph Department to resume charge of the section of line between Tehran and Khauikin, a town on the Persian frontier not tar from Bagdad. This Concession would come to an end with the termination of the Conven tion of 1872 in 1925, and it does not become transferable to the Indo-European Telegraph Company under its Agreements like the charge of the Tehran-Bushire line does. This Company, recognizing the value of the Concession, has obtained a document from the Persian Government, in which it is told that there is no objection to the Company coming to an understanding with the British Government as to taking section of line. The document does not appear actually to over and working this bind the Persian Government to allow the transfer of the line, if it took place, to remain in force for the term of the Company’s Agreements—that is, up to 1945—so that, should the British Concession for the Tehran-Bushire line come to an end in 1925, the Concession for the working of the Tehran-Khanikin section would apparently end at the same time, whether the British Department or the Company then possessed it. In this case, in 1925 the Persian Government could dispose of the Tehran- Khanikin line Concession in any way they chose. It is known that the German Telegraph Administration has been making inquiries regarding this line. It is possible that the Germans might obtain control of the line in 1925. It has been shown that the British Concession for the Central Persia line might be terminated at the same time, so that the Germans, even if they had to advance money to pay off any debt remaining on the Central Persia line, might obtain for themselves the Concession for working this line also from that time. We should then have the line from Bagdad through Tehran to the Indian frontier at Robat being worked under German control, which would he a very undesirable state of affairs as far as British interests are concerned. 6. I have shown that it would be to the interest of the Persian Government, for financial reasons, to renew the British Concessions of 1868 and 1872, and that it is advisable in British interests that they should be renewed, as also the Concession of 1901 for the Central Persia line. But we shall have to pay for these renewals, and the question is w r hat should he paid. In 1891 we paid 5,000/. to the Shah, and gave-— - * ------ lent {oi Qcesaii 'om Is iment, ndeitii B'lissm ailed, - I W'io,* | del ‘o! Dventi tlieli 9t It paidol, lierefotf, isvaitk rtotkt that tit result ii expkii m ectioutf far ta Conw -Basfe jtainedi object total® jtuallyi place, —sott in fii 3 a present of the value of 500/. to the Prime Minister for the renewal of two Concessions. If the grant of the renewal of these two Concessions still rests entirely with the Shah—of which there would seem to he some doubt, since such matters may require the consent of his Parliament—similar amounts as on the last occasion might he offered for a renewal of the two Concessions. Eor the third Concession, relating to the Central Persia line, we have under the Convention to pay 1 per cent, on the capital expended on construction of the line subject to a minimum of 1,000/. per annum. When the account for the construction of the line is made up, this 1 per cent, will he more than 1,000/., though how much more it is impossible to say until the accounts are made up. Por the renewal of this Concession we might anticipate the annual payment of 1,000/. to the Persian Government, and pay 10,000/. at once as an advance, being the equivalent of ten annuel payments. The difference between 1,000/. and the sum that 1 per cent, on the capital cost of the line will amount to will also be paid yearly to the Persian Government for the same time. The Indo-European Telegraph Company advanced 10,000/. for the late renewal of its Concession to 1915, but this advance has to bear interest. I have proposed an advance of 10,000/., hut if a smaller advance should be accepted so much the better 7. When the question of these renewals is raised with the Persian Government i', might be pointed out that, as they have renewed the Company’s Concession for twenty vears, it will be according to their previous custom if they now renew the British Conventions for the same term, and that this is our reason for applying for them. It could be explained that the 1863 Convention provides the Persian Government with a royalty of 3,000 tomans, and that the non-renewal of the 1872 Convention would mean the handing over to the Indo-European Telegraph Company of the Tehran-Bushire line without payment of any kind. A.s to the Central Persia line, it could be pointed out that it has been constructed, as shown in the Convention relating to it, for an alternative line to the Tehran-Bushire one, so that it is only reasonable and right that the Conventions for the two seetions should have the same limit of time. As to the payments or advances to be made lor these renewals, it seems to me they will have to be arranged with reference to the authority in Persia, who can now sanction them. If this should prove to be the Shah alone, the matter will probably be more easily carried out. (signed) jj A . K I1!K. April 25, 1907.( l r~ [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government.] control and supervision of the Arabistan telegraph lines under the Indo-European Telegraph Department till 1945, and prolonging the telegraph concessions held by that department in Persia until the same date. I also enclose copies of the notes exchanged simultaneously with the signature of the convention recording that the arrangement requires the ratification of the Assembly. It will be observed that the share in the cost of the construction and maintenance of the Arabistan lines to be borne by the department is fixed at 5,000/. towards the construction and 300/. a-year towards the maintenance, which is considerably less than the department was prepared to spend. The credit for this satisfactory arrangement belongs to the director of the Persian section of the department and to Mr. King-Wood, who have conducted the negotiations with the Minister of Telegraphs with much skill and patience. I should also wish to accord my appreciation of the sensible and conciliatory spirit shown throughout by the Minister of Telegraphs, Mukhber-ed-Dowleh. Unfortunately he was not allowed a free hand, but met with much obstruction from certain members of the late Cabinet, the stupid and reactionary Minister of Finance, Kavem-ed-Dowleh, in particular. Had it not been for the ignorant and corrupt obstruction of this Minister, the convention would have been signed some months ago, when there would not have been the same necessity for the ratification by the Assembly, as the constitution had not been restored, though the Ministers responsible for the establishment of the above-mentioned lines, such as iron posts, wire, insulators, &amp;c., which may be required, up to 5,000/., and also to pay an annual sum of 300/. on account of the maintenance of the above-mentioned lines, and the pay of a mechanician up to the year 1945. Other expenses, such as the changing of the wooden posts for iron ones and the annual expenses of the maintenance of the above-mentioned lines, which may be in excess of the 5,000/. and the annual amount of 300/., shall, after the completion of the work, and the submission of the accounts, be paid gradually to the British Telegraph Department by the Persian Government. PERSIA. [July 5.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 16. [25142] No. 1. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey,—{Received July 5.) (No. 125.) Sir, Gulahek, June 17, 1909. WITH reference to previous correspondence, I have the honour to forward a convention which I have this day signed with the Persian Government placing the conclusion of the arrangement would doubtless have been vehemently attacked in the Medjliss for having consented to the prolongation of concessions without the consent of the nation. I have, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. Inclosure 1 in No. 1. Anglo-Persian Convention, signed June 17, 1909. Article 1. TO improve the telegraphic communication between Borazjoon and Mohammerah and Borazjoon and Dizful it is arranged that from the date of this agreement until January 1945 the above-mentioned telegraph lines shall be under the control and supervision of the British Government telegraph officials now controlling the international lines in Persia. Article 2. The British Government agrees to pay for the cost of the construction and the [2339 e —16]Article 3. In return for the expenses incurred gratis by the British Government, and referred to in article 2 for the construction and maintenance of the above-mentioned lines, the Persian Government agrees to consider the following conventions to be in force and binding up to 1st January, 1945 :— The Telegraph Convention of the 2nd April, 1868. The Telegraph Convention of the 2nd December, 1872. The Telegraph Convention of the 16th August, 1901. Article 4. The pay of the telegraphists, and other workmen, such as gholams and ferrashes, batteries and instruments, and the hire of telegraph offices, will be borne by the Persian Telegraph Department. Article 5. Guards and telegraph gholams, who must be Persians, will be required for the maintenance of the above-mentioned lines ; the control and payment of these will be in the hands of the director and British staff. Article 6. In order to ensure the proper working of these telegraph lines the British director will be at liberty to station British telegraphists, at the expense of the British Govern ment Telegraph Department, at any telegraph office on the above-mentioned lines which he may consider necessary. Article 7. In case of necessity, and with the permission of the Persian Government Telegraph Department, the British Government Telegraph Department can join the above- mentioned lines at their eastern extremity to the line between Tehran and Bushire. Article 8. If the British Government Telegraph Department considers it necessary it can, at its own expense, add a second line for its own use to the above-mentioned lines. Article 9. ihe Persian Government agrees not to employ in the telegraph offices of the above- mentioned lines, without the concurrence of the chiefs of the British Telegraph Department, anyone except Persian subjects or members of the British Government Telegraph Department. Article 10. It is agreed that, should'; the Persian Government in the future wish to extend the above-mentioned lines in any direction, the co-operation of the Indo-European Telegraph Department m the construction and maintenance of such extension will be asked for. Done at Tajriche in duplicate on the 17th June, 1909. (Sealed) G. BARCLAY. (Sealed) DJEYAD, SAAD-ED-DOWLEH.force anJ “''m Uirecte i Goverc- &amp; Inclosure 2' in No. 1. Copy of Note signed by Sir G. Barclay and Baud ed-DnJfeh. Your Excellency. J une 17 , 1909. I HAVE the honour to state to your Excellency rhat it is fully understood between us that the convention for a telegraph line bet\ ee &lt; ^ -razjoon and Mohammerah and between Borazjoon and Dizful, which your Excell&lt; ncy and I have signed together, will require the approval of the Persian National Assembly. I avail, &amp;c. G. BAftCLAY. JEVAB, SAAD-ED-DOWLEH.Lf.U^ [This Docmnent is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government,] [October 25.] Section 1. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received October 25.) (No. 180.) y Sir, Tehran, September 29, 1909. I HAVE the honour to transmit to you herewith copy of a despatch which I have received from His Majesty’s consul-general at Bushire in regard to the assumption by the Indo-European Telegraph Department of the Arabistan telegraph lines. enclose at the same time copy of the reply which I have addressed to Captain Trevor. I have, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. Inclosure 1 in No. 1. Major Cox to Sir G. Barclay. -&lt;V (No. 04.) Sir, Bushire, July 29, 1909. I HAVE the honour to forward, for your information and such action as you may consider possible, a copy of a letter addressed to me by Lieutenant A. T. Wilson, in which, in connection with the contemplated assumption by the Indo-European Telegraph Department of the Arabistan telegraph lines, he submits certain views and suggestions. From the practical point of view Lieutenant Wilson’s recommendations appear to me to be to the point, and generally have my support. Especially, it would be a great convenience, both practically and politically, if the arrangement advocated in paragraph 8 of his letter could be unobtrusively brought about during the course of the present measures for the transfer of the control of the lines, and provided that the necessary measure of control of the Persian office remained with the sheikh, as at present, I think we might depend on his tacit co-operation in arranging the location of the English office to suit us. I have, &amp;c. P. Z. COX, Major, British Resident in the Persian Gulf, and His Britannic Majesty's Consul-General for Pars, fyc. Inclosure 2 in No. 1. Lieutenant A. T. Wilson to Major Cox. Sir, Mohammerah, July 3, 1909. I HAVE the honour to address you on the subject of the assumption by the Indo-European Telegraph Department of the control of the Arabistan telegraph lines, a step which has, I understand, received the final sanction of the Government. 2. I venture to suggest that the department should be moved to make a start with as little delay as possible, as not only are local political circumstances propitious, but the rapid growth of British telegraph service more necessary than ever. 3. It would be convenient if the Indo-European Telegraph Department could make some statement as to their future policy with regard to the existing lines, offices, and operators, for the information of this consulate and of the British firms chiefly concerned. 4. As regards control of the lines, I venture to suggest that before the line is renewed on iron poles, the working of the existing lines and of the telegraph offices should be taken over as soon as possible by the department. 5. It would be well if the reconstruction of the (1) Ahwaz-Mohammerah line (2) Ahwaz-Borasjun line could take precedence over the remainder of the system, as [2451 bb—1]2 the Dizful-Shusliter-Ahwaz line affects British interests but little. I have already recommended the relaying of the Mohammerah-Ahwaz line down the left hank of the Karun. 6. As regards operators, I would point out that only one telegraph office in Arabistan (i.e., at Ahwaz) is at present officially open for messages in European languages, and that although such messages can usually be sent from Mohammerah to Ahwaz, they cannot be sent elsewhere, as the telegraph clerk at this place, for the above reason, refuses to transmit them. Such telegrams, therefore, if destined for (e.g.) Bushire, Tehran, or London, must be sent from Mohammerah to an agent in Ahwaz and readdressed from there, involving a double payment of part of the charge. 7. It is greatly to be desired that the telegraph office at Mohammerah should be at once officially authorized to accept messages in European languages for transmission over the Ahwaz-Borasjun line. A recommendation to this effect has already been submitted to His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran by Mr. McDouall. 8. As regards the provision of telegraph offices at Mohammerah, I would point out that the present Persian office is 2 miles from the consulate, around which are grouped the customs office, Messrs. Lynch Brothers’ warehouses, Messrs. Lloyd, Scott, and Company’s offices, and the Wonckhaus agency. The provision in the British Considate of a separate telegraph office for messages in European languages (Persian messages being sent, as now, from the town office) would be a great convenience to users of the wire, and, if undertaken now, would probably meet with no opposition. It would also be desirable on other grounds into which I need not enter. 9. There is at the present moment room in the consulate for a telegraph office, and, should this proposal meet with your approval, I am ready to submit a detailed plan of the consulate, and of the relative position of the town office, considate, &amp;c. Such a proposal, of course, involves two operators, one for English and the other for Persian work, but a saving of cost might be effected by converting the present British ix&gt;st office into a postal telegraph office, with a trained telegraphist as postmaster. The provision of a separate office for European messages would leave the Persian office, as now, to some extent under the control of the sheikh, a state of things which I consider desirable at present. The sheikh could then, as now, keep himself informed of the purport of all messages in Persian passing over the wire, though not of the English messages. This is a matter upon which he would, I believe, if approached, lay great stress, as it gives him a sense of security against plotters, and enables him to control, in the same way as Persian governors elsewhere, a channel of communication between his subjects in various parts of Arabistan which might easily be used against him. I have, &amp;c. A. T. WILSON, Indian Army. Inclosure 3 in No. 1. Copy of a demi-official letter, dated the 23rd, April, 1909,/rom Lieutenant A. T. Wilson, Indian Army, to Mr. J. C. Smitn, Indo-European Telegraph Department. I GIVE below, for your information, my reasons for thinking the east bank of the Karun preferable to the west bank for a telegraph wire to Mohammerah. 1. Distance .—I think that it will be found that there is nothing to choose in this respect between the east or the west bank, but the east bank may have a slight advantage. 2. Facility for inspection .—The east bank is practically always passable to horsemen, even when the west bank is flooded in places. 3. Security .—The east bank is always perfectly safe ; the west bank less so, owing to the fear of the Bani Turuf and Hawaizah people. It is doubtless on this account that the present wire hugs the bank all along instead of taking a straight line across country. If the latter course were adopted on the east bank several miles would be saved. 4. Economy .—A proposal, regarding which you will no doubt hear from Mr. Reynolds of the C.S.L. in due course, has been made that the C.S.L. should have the use of one or two wires between Nasiri and Mohammerah, and pay the Indo- European Telegraph Department a moiety of the cost of installation as well as ofthe upkeep. This would only be possible if the line went down the east bank. If the east bank were adopted, it would be necessary to carry the wire across the river not at Ahwaz but near Mohammerah. I should say that a 300-yards span would suffice, as long as the poles were high enough for the wires to clear the masts of the ‘ Malamir ” and “ Musrat.” I HAVE received Major Cox’s despatch No. 61 of the 29th July last enclosing a despatch from Lieutenant Wilson, in which he makes certain proposals in connection with the assumption by the Indo-European Telegraph Department of the Arabistan telegraph lines. The arrangement concluded between the late Government and the department has not yet received the final sanction of the Persian Government, and requires the ratification of the Assembly before it can come into force. In the event of the Assembly’s ratifying the arrangement, Lieutenant Wilson’s suggestions will be considered by the department, but at present Mr. Barker, to whom I have submitted Mr. Wilson’s despatch, is of opinion that it is premature to make any comments. Inclosure 4 in No. 1. (No. 19.) Sir, Sir G. Barclay to Acting Consul-General Trevor. Tehran, September 28, 1909. I am, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY.ASM 'S In case you may think it worthwhile showing the papers to Mr. Kirk, so that he may have early cognizance of the suggestions made, I venture to send you direct a copy of a letter No. ()4^8!Lh of July (with enclosures) fca which I have addressed to Sir George Barclay in connection with the coming change in the management of the Arabistan Telegraphs. Sir Richmond Ritchie, Political Department, India Office, LONDON.Precis 1 a l&amp;tib of 1909 • iiritioh Residency and Oonsulate-Genoral, •liusiiire, ^ July 1909, / 1 have the honour to forward for your information such action as you may consider possible, a copy of a Rc* 21 dated oru July 1&gt;09. $ letter addressed to mo by Lieutenant -A * X * ii ilaon in which, in connection with the contemplated assumption by the Indo-Purcpaan Telegraph SSI department of the Arabistan lelegraph Lines, he submits certain views and suggestions* From the practical point of view a* Lieutenant Wilson 1 s reconMendationa appear to me to be to the point and generally have my support* Especially, it would be a great convenience both practically and politically if the arrangement advocated in paragraph 8 of liia letter could be unobtrusively brought about during the course 6f the present measures for the transfer of the control of the lines, and provided that the necessary measure of con trol of the Persian Office remained with the Lheikh as at present, I think we might depend on his tacit cooperation ■excellency ~ir uaorge Barclay, ^.0.. , i., G.V*0., •B*. *8 ^nvoy Extraordimotty and Minister Plenipotentiary T in at tlie Jourt of Persia, Teheran. (c/o Foreign Office London)mmin arranging the location or the .English Office to cult us I have the honour to be Sir, lour arioellency f s most obedient, humble sorvrnt, {&amp;d) Qtm. :.ajox* f British Resident In the Persian Oulf, a K«B»*s Ooneul*0aneral for ^'ars etc*Copy No. 21 of 1909. H.B.M*s Consulate, :lohanmerah. Dated 3rd July 1909. From Lt. A.T. /ilson, I.A., To The Political Resident in the Persian ^lulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to address you on the subject of the assumption by the Indo-European Telegraph Department Of the control of the Arabistan Telegraph Lines, a step which has I understand, received the final sanction of Government. 2. I venture to suggest that the Department should be moved to mafce a start with as little delay as possible, as not only are local political circumstances propitious, but t,he rapid growth of British telegraph service more necessary than ever. 3. It would be convenient if the Indo-European Telegraph Department could make some statement as to theie future policy with regard to the existing lines, offices and operators, for the information of this Consulate, and of the British firms chiefly concerned. 4. As regards control of the lines, I venture to suggest that before the line is renewed on iron poles, the working of the existing lines and of the telegraph offices should be taken over as soon as possible by the Department* 5. It would be well if the re-construction of the (1) Ahwas- Mohammerah line (2) Ahwaz-Borasjun line could take precedence over the remainder of the system, as the Dizful-Shushter-Ahwaz line affects British interests but little. 1 have already recommendedEnglish and the other for Persian work, but a saving of cost might be effected by converting the present British Post Office into a Postal Telegraph Office with a trained tele graphist as Postmaster• The provision of a separate office for European messages would leave the Persian Office, as now, to some extent under the control of the Sheikh, a state of things which I consider desirable at present. The Sheikh could then, as now, keep himself informed of the purport of all messages in Persian passing over the 7/ire, though not of the English messages. This is a matter upon which he would, I believe, if approach ed, lay great stress, as it gives him a sens© of security against plotters, and enables him to control, in the same way as Persian Governors elsewhere, a channel of communication betv/een his subjects in various parts of Arabist an, which might easily be used against him. I have etc.Copy of a demi-official letter dated the 23rd April 1909, from Lieutenant A#T. Wilson, I,A*, to Mr. J.C. Smith, Indo- European Telegraph Department. I give below for your information my reasons for thinking the S# bank of the J^arun preferable to the W. bank, for a telegraph wire to Mohammerah• 1. Distance . I think that it will bo found that there is nothing to choose in this respect between the E. or the W. bank, but the E. bank may have a slight advantage. 2. Facility for inspection . The E. bank is practically always passable for horsemen, even when the . bank is flooded in places. 3# Security . The E. bank is always pfs perfectly safe, the W. bank less so, owing to the fear of the Bani Turuf and Hawai- zah people. It is doubtless on this account that the present wire hugs the bark all along instead of taking a straight line across country. If the latter course were adopted on the E. bank several miles would be saved. Economy . A proposal regarding which you will no doubt hear from Mr. Reynolds of the C.8.L. in due.course, has been made that the C.S.L. should have the use of one or two wires between Easiri and Mohammerah and pay the I.E.r.D* a moiety of the cost of the installation as well as of the upkeep. This would only be possible if the line went down the E. bank. If the E. bank were adopted, it would be necessary to carry the wire across the river not at Ahwaz but near Mohammerah* I should say that a 300 yards span would suffice, as long as the poles were high enough for the wires to clear the masts of the 'Malamir* and f, !iusrat w .Uo3l h In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote and address— Tbf^Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. London. Th e Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Sffairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for —^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop j of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Reference to previous letter: to- g 1 . Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. AR/tol. ^MM r Nos 161, | 3572b LS£? 27 i909 CtU HiO/C t August £4 1909. olr. I venture to oscpresB respectful PTvproctotl^n of* the congratulations conveyed to re in your despatch No; 99 (*,-.4240) of* the 8th u It tiro on the conclusion of* the Arab1st an Telegraph Convention.! did not fail to transmit to hlr Barker,Director of the Indo-hhjr-rean Telegraph Department and to Nr King-Wood of the Depart ment your message of appreciation of their services and they now request that X will convey to you their thanks. I snail soe that the Convention is submitted to tne Assembly as soon as possible after it roots and I earnestly hope that that body will make no difficulty about its ratification. I have the honour to be, with the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedient, humbl o s ervrmt. IMinute Paper. Register No. ¥¥* w Secret Department. Letter from Dated Bee ted , j j X, 19^3^uo / , I . [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] ceMo PERSIA. ^CONEiEENTIAL. 125142] / &lt;?- v ' :(2l JULI9C9 V ’ DE.P^V' V No. 1. [July 5.] Section 16. 8*V G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received July 5.) (No. 125.) Si r , Gulahek, June 17, 1909. WITH reference to previous correspondence, I have the honour to forward a convention which I have this day signed with the Persian Government placing the control and supervision of the Arabistan telegraph lines under the Indo-European Telegraph Department till 1945, and prolonging the telegraph concessions held by that department in Persia until the same date. I also enclose copies of the notes exchanged simultaneously with the signature of the convention recording that the arrangement requires the ratification of the Assembly. It will be observed that the share in the cost of the construction and maintenance of the Arabistan lines to be borne by the department is fixed at 5,000/. towards the construction and 300/. a-year towards the maintenance, which is considerably less than the department was prepared to spend. The credit for this satisfactory arrangement belongs to the director of the Persian section of the department and to Mr. King-Wood, who have conducted the negotiations with the Minister of Telegraphs with much skill and patience. I should also wish to accord my appreciation of the sensible and conciliatory spirit shown throughout by the Minister of Telegraphs, Mukhber-ed-Dowleh. Unfortunately he was not allowed a free hand, but met with much obstruction from certain members of the late Cabinet, the stupid and reactionary Minister of Finance, Kavem-ed-Dowleh, in particular. Had it not been for the ignorant and corrupt obstruction of this Minister, the convention would have been signed some months ago, when there would not have been the same necessity for the ratification by the Assembly, as the constitution had not been restored, though the Ministers responsible for the conclusion of the arrangement would doubtless have been vehemently attacked in the Medjliss for having consented to the prolongation of concessions without the consent of the nation. I have, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. Inclosure 1 in No. 1. Anglo-Persian Convention, signed June 17, 1909. Article 1. TO improve the telegraphic communication between Borazjoon and Mohammerah and Borazjoon and Dizful it is arranged that from the date of this agreement until January 1945 the above-mentioned telegraph lines shall be under the control and supervision of the British Government telegraph officials now controlling the international lines in Persia. Article 2. The British Government agrees to pay for the cost of the construction and the establishment of the above-mentioned lines, such as iron posts, wire, insulators, &amp;c., which may be required, up to 5,000/., and also to pay an annual sum of 300/. on account of the maintenance of the above-mentioned lines, and the pay of a mechanician up to the year 1945. Other expenses, such as the changing of the wooden posts for iron ones and the annual expenses of the maintenance of the above-mentioned lines, which may be in excess of the 5,000/. and the annual amount of 300/., shall, after the completion of the work, and the submission of the accounts, be paid gradually to the British Telegraph Department by the Persian Government. [2339 e —16] t- iArticle 3. In return for the expenses incurred gratis by the British Government, and reterrec^ to in article 2 for the construction and maintenance of the above-mentioned lines, th Persian Government agrees to consider the following conventions to be in force and binding up to 1st January, 1945 :— The Telegraph Convention of the 2nd April, 1868. The Telegraph Convention of the 2nd December, 1872. The Telegraph Convention of the 16th August, 1901. Article 4. The pay of the telegraphists, and other workmen, such as gholams and ferrashes, batteries and instruments, and the hire of telegraph offices, will be borne by the 1 ersian Telegraph Department. Article 5. Guards and telegraph gholams, who must be Persians, will be required lor the maintenance of the above-mentioned lines ; the control and payment of these will be in the hands of the director and British staff. Article 6. In order to ensure the proper working of these telegraph lines the British director will be at liberty to station British telegraphists, at the expense of the British Govern ment Telegraph Department, at any telegraph office on the above-mentioned lines which he may consider necessary. Article 7. In case of necessity, and with the permission of the Persian Government Telegraph Department, the British Government Telegraph Department can join the^ above- mentioned lines at their eastern extremity to the line between Tehran and Bushire. Article 8. If the British Government Telegraph Department considers it necessary it can, at its own expense, add a second line for its own use to the above-mentioned lines. Article 9. The Persian Government agrees not to employ in the telegraph offices of the above- mentioned lines, without the concurrence of the chiefs of the British Telegraph Department, anyone except Persian subjects or members of the British Government Telegraph Department. Article 10. It is agreed that, should 1 the Persian Government in the future wish to extend the above-mentioned lines in any direction, the co-operation of the Indo-European Telegraph Department in the construction and maintenance of such extension will be asked for. Done at Tajriche in duplicate on the 17th June, 1909. (Sealed) G. BARCLAY. (Sealed) DJEYAD, SAAD-ED-DOWLEH.Si) ’ c s ami l feastfs, he PI isHirecta .sh Goto- the ate i Telf 1 anT e y aske^®' Inclosure 2 in No. 1. Your Excellency. , June 17, 1909. I HAVE the honour to state to your Excellency that it is fully understood between us that the convention for a telegraph line between Borazjoon and Mohammerah and between Borazjoon and Dizful, which your Excellency and I have signed together, will require the approval of the Persian National Assembly. I avail, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. JEVAD, SAAD-ED-DOWLEH.In any further eomn-m men tion on this subject, please quote no. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. ■y The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, $ , 190 Tj. Reference to previous letter Description of Inclosure. Name and Date “Tf- (f-H ^ ■%- -v rr : [This Document is the Property of Hi{ PERSIA. COPY TO IN on / JU! !9C? Majesty’s Government.] A ,N [June 21.] CONFIDENTIAL.| ^ Section 6 . [23025] M SzV ^4. Nicolson to Sir Edward Grey .— 'Received June 21.) (No. 375.) Sir, St. Petersburgh, June 14, 1909. ON the receipt of your telegram No. 739 of the 10th instant, I addressed a note to the Russian Ministry for Foreign Affairs, of which I have the honour to transmit a copy. The terms of my note were in accord with the sentence of my telegram No. 96 relating to the exchange of the telegraph lines, on which you were good enough to authorize me to take action. After the despatch of my note I received your telegram No. 743, which intimated that it would he better to defer action on the exchange of the telegraph lines until the Arabistan convention had been rati tied by the Persian Assembly. I would beg leave to submit that it would be undesirable to follow up my note of the 11th instant by another one which would appear to postpone to a somewhat nebulous date the initiation of negotiations for the exchange of the telegraph lines. Before the question of the Arabistan convention arose both Governments were desirous of taking advantage of the first favourable opportunity to approach the Persian Govern ment for effecting the exchange. When the Arabistan convention was being dealt with the Russian Government, at the desire of His Majesty’s Government, agreed to await its conclusion and to give it precedence, and, in fact, practically to suspend all treatment of other telegraph questions. Now that presumably the Arabistan convention has been signed, it might give rise to misunderstandings were we to propose that a further postponement should occur. It is, I submit, feasible to proceed without delay to the construction of the second wire from Tehran to Shahrud, as the matter appears to be practically settled with the Persian Government; and this work could doubtless be commenced before discussions were opened for the exchange of telegraph lines. It is proposed to leave to the two representatives at Tehran the choice of a favourable opportunity to commence discussions with the Persian Government as to the exchange, and it seems to me that it would be better to leave the matter in that position. The two questions to which the Russian Government apparently attach much importance are the exchange of the telegraph lines and the construction of the second wire to Shahrud. They have evinced good-will in meeting our wishes in other respects, and I should not like that they should consider that hesitation was being shown on our side to carry out an arrangement on which the two Governments came to an agreement nearly two years ago. I would propose, therefore, to address a second note to the Russian Government simply stating that His Majesty’s Government have no objection to the immediate construction of a second wire from Tehran to Shahrud, and that there are no accounts between the Persian Government and the Indo-European Telegraph Company as to the Tehran-Khanikin line, which is worked entirely by the Persian Telegraph administra tion. I should be grateful if your views were kindly transmitted to this embassy by telegraph. I have, &amp;c. A. NICOLSON. Inclosure in No. 1. Aide-me'moire. ^ J HIS Britannic Majesty’s Embassy had the honour to receive the aide-memoire which the Imperial Ministry for Foreign Affairs was good enough to address to it on the 16th (29th) May relative to telegraph lines in Persia. His Majesty’s Embassy is now in a position to inform the Imperial Ministry for Foreign Affairs that His Majesty’s Government agree to the wording proposed in the above-mentioned aide-memoire of the secret agreement to be made between the two Governments in respect to the employment, if necessary, of Russian signallers on the [2306 x —6]2 Arabist&amp;n lines ; and they also agree to a clause being added, as desired by the Impel lal Ministry for Foreign Affairs, that such signallers should be attached to the Indo- European Telegraph Department, and considered as employes of that department. As to the exchange of the control over the Tehran Meshed and Khaf—Nasratabtid telegraph lines, His Majesty’s Embassy would propose that the representatives of the two Governments at Tehran should be authorized, to bring the question before the Persian Government at the first favourable opportunity. His Majesty’s Embassy will do itselt the honour of addressing a further aide- memoire to the Imperial Ministry for Foreign_ Affairs in regard to the remaining points to which reference was made in the aide-memoire of the 16th (29th) May. St. Petersburgh, May 29 (June 11), 1909.[This Docmaent is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. f” COPY jfO INDIA 904.! rS! [June 7J [21132] 2u.« Section -14. No. 1. , . ^ \ r Q 4 ' 4 ^^ ' (No. 339.) Sir, Sir A. Nicolson to Sir Edward Grey.—{ELeceived June 7.) St. Petersburgh, May 28, 1909. 1 iiiNQUiKED of M. Tcharykoif a day or two ago when I might expect to receive a reply to the aide-memoire which I had addressed to him on the 18tlrt\larch, relative to various questions connected with telegraph lines in Persia. He said that M. Klemm had prepared a memorandum in reply, but that there were one or two points which required elucidation, and he would be much obliged if I would send one of the embassy secretaries to talk over the matter with M. Klemm. He could tell me that the Russian Government had no objection whatever to the construction of a second line in Shahrud, and were most anxious that the exchange of the control over the Tehran-Meshed and Khaf-Nasratabad line should take place as soon as possible. I commenced to speak to M. Tcharykoff on certain other questions which had been touched upon in my aide-memoire, but he said that he would be glad if I would not enter into a discussion upon them, as he would prefer if the matter were treated with M. Klemm, who was better acquainted than he was with the subject. I asked Mr. Kidston to see M. Klemm, and I have the honour to transmit a copy of a memorandum which he drew up in regard to a conversation which he had with the latter and M!. Hartwig. The results of the conversation seem to me to be satisfactory | and I trust that I shall very shortly receive an official reply embodying the views of the Russian Government. It would be better to await the memorandum before any action is taken, so that there should be no possibility of any misunderstanding. I trust that the exchange of the Meshed and Seistan lines will be accomplished, as I submit that it would be well to complete the arrangement without further delay. I have, &amp;c. A. NICOLSON. P.S.—May 30. Since writing the above I have received the reply to my aide- memoire, of which I have the honour to transmit a translation. A. N. Inclosure 1 in No. 1. Memorandum on a Conversation between Mr. Kidston, M. de Klemm, and M. Hartwig. I WENT by appointment this afternoon to see M. de Klemm (late consul-general at Meshed, and now head of a department in the Ministry for Foreign Affairs) on the subject of Persian telegraphs, and found M. Hartwig with him. It was the latter who did all the talking. He began by saying that the moment was most favourable for effecting the exchange of the Tehran-Meshed and Khaf-Nasratabad lines. Perhaps such a favourable opportunity might never occur again ; the present Persian Minister of Telegraphs was an able and sensible man, who had always shown himself easy to deal with, and all the circumstances were propitious. Of course, if His Majesty’s Government wished to delay matters a little longer in order to put through their Arabistan arrangements and the extension of their concession to 1945 the Russian Government would offer no objection, but he urged the advisability of not letting so favourable an opportunity slip by. He had always been of opinion that the question of the exchange should be treated at Tehran as a purely administrative matter, and that the best attitude for the Ministers to adopt was to represent to the Persians that their respective telegraph administrations had plagued them for so long over the question that they were anxious to get it settled for good and all. The purely administrative and utilitarian nature of the measure could be based on the geographical position of the lines to be exchanged, [2306 g —14]which made it easier for the Russians to forward material for the Tehran-Meshed section and for the British to perform a similar service for that from ?sasratabad to Khaf. M. Hartwig then turned to more particular points. Arabistan Lines. —He said that the Russians would have no objection to the stipulation that the Indo-European Telegraph Department should co-operate in the construction and maintenance of any extension of the Arabistan lines, on the under standing that the rights would be waived in the case of an extension into their sphere. He showed some curiosity as to the true object of this stipulation, and I thought that there was no harm in telling him confidentially that it aimed at preventing the acquisition by a third Power of an extension from Mohammerah to Bussorah. With regard to the possible employment at some future date of Russian signallers on the Arabistan lines, he expressed some dissatisfaction with the proposed wording of the agreement with the Persian Government. The phrase: “ that without the concurrence of the British Government no others than British subjects and the members of the staff,” &amp;c., was, in his opinion, too vague and left it open to the Persian Government, even in spite of any secret agreement between Great Britain and Russia, to insist that Persian consent was necessary for the admission of Russian signallers. After much discussion I suggested as an alternative formula : “ that, save with the consent of the British Government, only Persian subjects and the members of the staff,” &amp;c. Both M. Hartwig and M. de Klemm expressed themselves as completely satisfied with this superficial alteration. Tehran-Shahrud Line. —With regard to the construction of the extra line from Tehran to Shahrud, M. Hartwig said that, far from opposing the project, the Russian Government would be only too glad if it were taken in hand at once. In fact, he gave me to understand that the pressure which the Persian Telegraph Administration was bringing to bear on the Indo-European Telegraph Department was due to constant representations from the Russian Legation. He explained that this was the main line of communication between the Persian and Russian systems, that the work was far too heavy for a single line, that the line was subject too frequent break-downs, and that consequently the Russian Legation at Tehran was constantly compelled to have recourse to the Indo-European Telegraph Company’s line, and that this meant an enormous increase in their telegraph bill. He quoted figures to show how heavy this charge had been during his period of office at Tehran. Tehran-Khanikin Line. —M. Hartwig characterised the action of his Government in taking over this line as a purely generous one. It was in a shocking condition and would cost them a large sum of money and bring no advantage. They only consented to take it over in order to prevent any third Power from acquiring control over it. But before the actual transfer was effected they wished to be assured as to the financial position of the line. He had read somewhere in Hertslet that the Indo- European Telegraph Company had paid over to the Persian Government a large sum of money in connection with some arrangement regarding this line. He had made enquiries of His Majesty s legation and of the head of the Indo-European Telegraph Company at Tehran as to the object and conditions attaching to this payment, but had never been able to get to the bottom of the transaction. What the Russian Govern ment now feared was that if they took over the line the Persian. Government might suddenly come down upon them and present a bill for this amount. They therefore wanted to make sure, before taking any further steps in the matter, that they would take over the line free of debt. I told M. de Klemm and M. Hartwig that the negotiations respecting the Arabistan lines^ were now proceeding smoothly, and gave them the substance of Sir G. Barclay s telegram No. 409. In these circumstances, I said, there would probably be little delay in effecting the excha^m? of the Tehran—Meshed and Khaf— Nasratabad lines, which His Majesty s Government were quite as anxious as the Russian Government to carry out at the earliest possible opportunity. I begged, them to furnish Sir A. Nicolson as soon as possible with a memorandum m reply to those which he had sent on the 21st February (6th March) and the 5th (18th) March, and they promised that this would be done at once. St. Petersburgh, May 28, 1909. G. J. KIDSTON.Inclosure 2 in No. 1. U (Translation Aide ' me ' moire commu ni cated to Sir A Nic o lson, i&amp; AUy t‘&gt;o&lt;t dated the 21st question of the HAVING studied the aide-memoire of the British Embassy February (6th March)^ and the 5th (18th) March, 1909, on the 4 u t3 suon oi rne telegraph lines m Persia the Ministry for Foreign Affairs is of opinion that the method proposed _ by the British Government for guaranteeing to the Bussian (^vernment the right of appointing, m the event of necessity, Russian telegraph o cials to the Arabistan lines by means of the conclusion of a special secret agree- ment on this subject between both Governments appears in principle to be wholly acceptable. The Ministry _ deem it only necessary to draw the attention of the embassy to the fact that m the drawing up of the text of an agreement between t e British and Persian Governments with reference to the Arabistan lines, it is necessary to seek such a formula as would not place the appointment of Russian omcials to the lines mentioned m dependence on the will of the Persian Govern- Tru' u P0r n ,0 , n J 0 L the P ro P°f d text of the agreement cited in the aide-memoire of the embassy dated the 21st February (6th March), 1909, reads thus : Without the concurrence of the British Government no others subjects and the members of the staff of the Indo-European Telegraph should be employed m the offices or on the lines of this system.” than Persian Department Such wording does not exclude the right of the Persian Government to oppose the appointment of Russian officials to these lines, even should the assent of the British Government have been given. For the removal of such a difficulty it is desirable to revise the above-quoted text in such a manner that the possibility of opposition by the Persian Government to the admission of Russian telegraph officials to the Arabistan mes shall be absolutely excluded. After this a secret agreement approximately in the following terms could be concluded on this subject between the Russian and British Governments :— “ Reserving for itself, by means of a special agreement with the Persian Govern ment, the right of control and repair on the Persian telegraph lines in Arabistan and having the intention to admit for work on these lines and offices only Persian subjects and officials of the Indo-European Telegraph Department, the British Government will not put obstacles in the way if in time it should appear necessary to the Russian Government to dispatch their own telegraph officials to the lines mentioned for the transmission of telegrams in the Russian language on principles analogous with those which have been established in relation to the Khaf-Seistan line.” The Imperial Government on their part place no obstacles against the Indo- European Telegraph Department reserving for itself the right to take part in the construction and maintenance also of other telegraph lines which may be constructed in Arabistan besides the Mohammerah-Ahwaz and'Tehran-Bushire lines mentioned in the aide-memoire of the embassy dated the 14th (27th) January, 1909, and take note of the declaration of the British Government that this right of the Indo-European Telegraph Depaitment will not be extended to portions of new lines which would enter within the limits of the Russian sphere of influence. As regards the placing of a second wire on the Tehran-Shahrud line, respecting which mention is made in the aide-memoire of the embassy dated the 5th (18th) March, 1909, the Imperial Government deems the immediate realisation of this measure, which the Russian Mission at Tehran has long urged on the Persian Government as a guarantee of a more regular telegraphic communication with Russia, to be extremely desirable. J With reference to the Tehran-Khanikin line, the Ministry for Foreign Affaiis permits itself to express anew the wish put forward in its aide-memoire dated the 16th (29th) January, 1909, namely, that now it should be clearly established that any financial accounts between the Indo-European Telegraph Department and the Persian Government which may arise with respect to the construction or maintenance of this line should be adjusted directly between the aforesaid department and the Government of the Shah, and shall not in any way affect the Imperial Government. The necessity of such a limitation arises from the circumstance that, on the one side, the financial position of the above-named line remains up to the present unexplained, and, on the other hand, there are several indications which give grounds to believe that certainfinancial accounts with respect to this line do in fact exist between the Indo-European Telegraph Department and the Persian Government. In conclusion, the Ministry for Foreign Affairs considers it their duty to again draw the attention of the embassy to the extreme necessity of realising as speedily as possible locally an actual exchange between the two Governments of the lines Tehran- Meshed and Khaf-Seistan. In the opinion of the Russian Minister at Tehran the present time seems to be a very opportune moment for doing this. The Imperial Govern ment already long ago furnished their charge d’affaires at Tehran with instructions on this subject, and it would be highly desirable that the British Minister at the Court of the Shah should be instructed to enter as soon as possible into an agreement on the necessary lines with M. Sabline. St. Petersburgh, May 16 (29), 1909.j (risv CONFIDENTIAL. Sir A. Nicolson to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received May 24, 9*30 p.m.) (No. 272.) St. Petersburgh, May 24, 1909, 8'44 p.m. PERSIAN telegraphs. Your telegram No. 691. Russian Government are not yet ready with their reply to my last Memorandum, but I am taking steps to hasten it. [452—155]In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. 22708/09. and address — The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office Foreign Office, London. Sir June 22nd, 1S09 With reference to previous correspondence^I am directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you, to he laid before the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty's Minister at Teh ran reporting the signature of the Arabistan Telegraphs Convention. Sir E. Grey would suggest, for Viscount Morley's consideration, that satisfaction should be expressed to Sir G. Barclay at the successful issue of the nego tiations and that he should be requested to convey to Mr. Barker and the other officers concerned of the Indo-European Telegraph Department the acknowledgments of His Majesty's Government for their important share in the conduct of the negotiations. I am Your most obedient Sir humble Servant The Under Secretary of State India Office.CONFIDENTIAL. (/ .0 Sir Edward Grey to Sir A. Nicolson (St. Petersburgh). (No. 761.) ^ Foreigji Office, June 17, 1909, 5‘30 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 299 [of 12tli June : Persian telegraphs]. I agree that you need say nothing to the Russian Government about deferring action at Tehran until ratification of Arabistan agreement. Sir G. Barclay can decide what would he first favourable opportunity of raising the question of exchange with the Persian Government. He may be trusted to use every endeavour to prevent the Russian representative at Tehran from taking any premature action, should he show any disposition to do so. [452—600]3s^3- CONFIDENTIAL. ■Cl ^ f Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received June 17, 10 p.m.) (No. 474.) Tehran, June 17, 1909, 8 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 289. Arabistan telegraphs convention signed to-day. (Sent to St. Petersburgh.)r j'Tvk In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. 22044/09. I and address — The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. / Foreign Office June 15th, 1909 toned i ate. With reference to your letter of the 9th instant I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you, to be laid before the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty’s Ambas sador at St. Petersburg!- stating that the Russian Gov ernment might misunderstand the motive of His Maj esty's Government, should the suggestion be made to defer approaching the Persian Government respecting the exchange of the Nasratabad-Khaf and Meshed-Tehran Telegraph lines until the Persian Assembly has rati fied the proposed Arabistan Telegraph Agreement, In view of the considerations advanced by Sir A. Nicolson, Sir E. Grey proposes, if Viscount Morley concurs, to say nothing more on the matter to the Rus sian Government and to leave it to His Majesty's Minis ter at Tehran to decide as to what would be the first he Under Secretary of Statd, favourable India Office.(22044/09). favourable opportunity of raising the question of the exchange with the Persian Government, Sir G. Bar clay is aware of the views of His Majesty's Government and may he trusted to use every endeavour to prevent the Russian Representative at Tehran from taking any premature action, should he shew any disposition to do so. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,t9 M i! CONFIDENTIAL. Sir A Nicolson to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received June 12 , 3*55 p.m.) (No. t ■ i , , ^ .v &amp; ivc:ai m .yuui teiogiam i\o. ton, i nacl already addressed memorandrim to the Russian Government stating that His Majesty’s Govern- nient are or opinion that the two representatives at Tehran might bring question of the exchange of telegraph lines before the Persian Government at the first favourable oppor tunity. Russian Government are most anxious that the exchange should be effected as soon ass possible and I think that if I were now to suggest that it should be deferred until the Assembly had ratified Arabistan convention they might consider that we were continually delaying the execution of an agreement arrived at in 1907. I think it ^ ° i j i • j^ er s ?y nothing more to the Russian Government, and Sir G. Barclay could decide as to what would be first favourable opportunity. CCONFIDENTIAL. ♦ Sir Edward Grey to Sir A. Nicolson {St. Petersburg^). (No. 744.) ^ Foreign Office, June 11, 1909, 5 p.m. WITH reference to my telegram No. 739 [of lOtli June : Persian telegraphs]. Of course it is understood that no expense should be entailed on the department by the arrangements for Russian signallers. COPY IN SECRETARY'S M* , (i] ISO?2 CONFIDENTIAL « •vN ' ’Lx / 1 i ■' \ .V’ Sir Edward Grey to Sir A. Nicolson {St. Petersburgli). (No. 743.) 1 Foreign Office, June 11, 1909, 5 p.m. MY telegram No. 739 [of 10th June : Persian telegraphs]. We have no objection to the immediate construction of a second wire from Tehran to Shahrud, but please suggest to Russian Government that it would be better if action on the proposed exchange of telegraphs could be deferred until Arabistan convention has been ratified by Persian Assembly; postponement would facilitate construction of the second wire from Tehran to Meshed, the cost of which the Persian Ministry of Telegraphs have made arrangements to defray. Should the question of the exchange be raised with the Persian Government, it might prove impracticable to proceed with the construction of the second wire till the Meshed—Tehran line had passed under Russian control, when the matter would no longer concern the British Government. There are no accounts between the Persian Government and the Indo-European Telegraph Department as to the Tehran—Khanikin line, which is entirely worked by the Persian telegraph administration. (Repeated to Tehran, No. 291.) LlCRCTArL b LMINUTE. v /Xi fc&gt; ^ /j*-* 'CtCs^ hj i^~t) C&amp;wt&lt;*y\~4 ^ I&amp;sTUv^A . &lt;' [/) C~^&gt; J^r^Cfxjr^ v j|^rfZC^n^r' —^ Ci 'VWuSK InA'u^. tu ^rv^ »7 /&lt;W&lt;. ^lO _ /^i TtVlU t'l-u ^ ^L&lt; ^ '^A-.tA u^ l ' ( $L^ /t_A* t&lt;i 'X/l' /6 \Aj^yU^. f diS-xr\ L n-^z. /&lt;—&gt; dJHhJ t li^. thLo^ ] Ic U^, ju^r t Ur^ k 7 a sj r-&gt;^ ^ (Li/yv^ L'lX'fc* ^y^ca tiX^x / ]rzsCc^-c^ ^ ||fl time this second v;ire was up the Assembly might have passed the Arabistan Convention, and the transfer of the line could then be pressed for without detriment to British interests, and also to Russian interests as far as the Khanikin line is concerned. The reservation of Russian rights on the Arabis tan lines. The final proposal on this subject is that if Russia should wish at any time to employ signallers on the Arabistan lines, such signallers should be attached to the Indo-European Telegraph Department and considered employes of that Department. The proposed arrangement is not altogether desirable, but it could be worked, and might therefore be agreed to subject to the condition that the Indo-European Telegraph Department was not put to any expense by it. The Russians do not apparently remember that their Russian telegrams will have to be transmitted over the Indo-European Telegraph Department’s lines to get to or from the Arabistan lines^and their efficient transmission will not then rest with Russian signallers. They could be informed of this when the time comes that they wish to employ Russian signallers on the Arabistan lines and it might make them less disposed to avail themselves of the proposed arrangement. .ihe construction of an extra line from Teheran to ghahrud• I have already dealt with this question, ihe Persian minister of Telegraphs has asked the Indo- European IIQ ^ l i J European Telegraph Department Director to get the second wire erected, and has arranged for payment of the cost of the work, so that it can be commenced at once I have instructions to carry it out. 4. The financial position of the Teheran Khanikin line ✓ Sir G.Barclay’s telegram of the 27th Tfay shows that the Russian Government desire information especially as to a payment made by the Indo-European Telegraph Company in connection with this line. By an Agreement, dated 14th June 1906, the Company obtained from the Persian Govern ment a renewal of its telegraph concessions up to 1945, and the agreement shows that to obtain this the Company made to the Persian Government an advance of £40,000. On the same date the company received from the Persian Government a document to the effect that H.M.the Shah had no objection to the Company coming to an understanding with the British Government as to taking over the Khanikin line, and that if the line was taken over the conditions for its working were to be settled by a Convention between the Persian Government and the Company. The existance of this document may prove of value to the Russian Govern- % ment, as if they came to terms with the Company for working the line, the British rights over the line could be passed, over nominally to the Company without possibly the oppos ition the direct transfer to the Russian Government may raise. It will be seen that the payment, made by the Company was for a renewal of their concessions, and , notnot in connection with the t^hanikin line.. It appears to me that it is very important that the Anglo Persian Agreement should be signed as soon as possible^as we shall then have an Agreement ratified by the executive of the Persian Government. 'Whatever may happen later in the Assembly, the executive part of the Government could not afterwards accept any arrangement by which the concessions shewn in the Agreement could pass into other hands, and with regard to the Arabistan line this is an important matter. It would help our position also if the signing of the Agreement could be kept secret until it has to be put before the Assembly.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote and address — The Under-Secretary of State, No. 21295/09. Foreign Office, London. June i? 1909 Sir:- / With reference to my letter of the 5th instant relative to the proposed settlement between His Majes ty's and the Russian Governments of questions connect ed with telegraph lines in Persia, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a further telegram from His IVfe.jesty's Minister at Tehran on the subject. The views of Viscount Morley respecting the imme diate signature of the Anglo-Persian Convention were asked for in my letter above referred to, and with regard to the remainder of the telegram I am to state that Sir E. Grey proposes, if His Lordship concurs, to infom Sir G. Barclay that the preamble quoted appears to His Majesty's Government to be sufficient for the purpose for which it is intended. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, he Under Secretary of State ^ India Office.CONFIDENTIAL Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received June 7, 12’50 p.m.) (N°. 44/.) Tehran, June 7, 1909. 11'20 p.m. ST. PETERSBURGH telegram No. 290 [of 5th June : Persian telegraphs]. May I now sign convention, subject to exchange of notes proposed (see my telegram No. 409 [of 21st May]) ? Preamble runs as follows :— The following agreement is made between the Governments of Persia and Great Britain.” I presume that this is sufficient ? [453—549]In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote s„. 20919/09. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. nmediatQ. /■ Sir:- With reference to my letter of yesterday, rela tive to the exchange of telegraph lines in Persia, I am directed hy Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a telegram from His Majesty’s Ambassador at St. Petersburg, conveying the consent of the Russian Government to the immediate signature of the Anglo-Persian Convention respecting the Arabistan line without alteration and also a suggestion that a clause should be added to the proposed secret Anglo- Russian Agreement providing that any Russian signal lers employed on these lines should be considered as / servants of the Indo-European Telegraph Department. I am to enquire whether Viscount Morley concurs in the proposal for the immediate signature of the Anglo-Persian Agreement and whether he sees any objec tion he Under Secretary of State, India Office. ■J Agreement of the clause desired by the Russian Govern ment. Sir E.Grey would he glad to receive an expres sion of Lord Morley's views on these two points with as little delay as may he convenient.■ I— In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. 20229/09. and address — The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. mediate. Sir:- iv /r Vu •/. / . r Foreign Office June , 1909. &amp; With reference to the letter from this Department of the 25th ultimo and your reply of the 28th ultimo, I am directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you, to he laid before the Secretary of State for India, copies of correspondence, as marked in the mar gin on the subject of telegraphs in Persia. It will be seen that four points have been raised by the Russian Government. 1. The proposed exchange of the Tehran-Meshed and Khaf Nasratabad lines. 2. The reservation of Russian rights on the Arabistan lines. 3. The construction of an extra line from Tehran to Shahrud. 4. The financial position of the Tehran Khanikin line. In he Under Secretary of State, India Office. COPY TO INDIA ^ • :: , •(20229/09). In view of the fresh stage now reached by the question, the course proposed in the previous letter from this Department will no longer meet the case: and Sir E. Grey would propose as regards point 2, if Vis count Morley concurs, to await a reply from the Russian Government to the enquiry addressed to them whether they would be satisfied as regards the Arabistan lines with a declaration by His Majesty's Government on the lines indicated in the telegram from His Majesty's Am- y bassador at St. Petersburg No. 279 of the 30th ultimo. As to point 1, Sir E. Grey sees no reason for abandoning the course indicated in the last paragraph of the letter from this Department of the 25th ultimo and he considers that a communication in that sense should be made to the Russian Government. I am to enquire as regards point 3, what are the views of Lord Morley of Blackburn on the subject of the proposed duplication of the line to Shahrud: and I am to say that Sir E. Grey proposes to deal with point 4 by informing the Russian Government that there are no accounts■ (20229/09). accounts on the Khanikin line, which is entirely worked hy the Persian Telegraph Administration. I am to suggest that this Department should he favoured with a reply at Lord Morley * s early conven ience. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,Sir Edward Grey to Sir A, Nicolson (St, Petersburgh). (No. 717.) Foreign Office, June 3, 1909, 5*30 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 279 and Sir G. Barclay’s telegram No. 423 [of 30th May: Arabistan Telegraph Agreement]. Please inquire whether Russian Government would he satisfied as regards Arabistan line with declaration which they suggest. It seems desirable, in view of what Sir G. Barclay says, to sign Agreement at once and without alteration. [452—515]h* 1 \ CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey .— (Received May 30, 10*30 p.m.) 423.) Tehran, May 30, 1909, 9 p.m. SIR A. NICOLSON’S telegram No. 275 and my telegram No. 409. 1. I agree that the present moment is favourable, but unfortunately it is pretty Indo-European Telegraph Department any but Persians or the employes of the Indo- European Telegraph Department. (End of R.). Possibly Russian Government might be content with an undertaking from us to support their demand for Russian signallers, should the case arise. I presume that reservation as to Russian sphere will form subject of a secret arrangement between His Majesty’s Government and the Russian Government. 4. I know nothing of any such [? payment], and I hesitate to inquire of the Company here. But it seems to me that we are now merely concerned with an arrange ment by which Russia takes our place as regards the line. We have rights over it, but come to a suitable arrangement with Persian Government respecting any liabilities of the line. (Sent to St. Petersburgh.) 2. Convention is already prepared for signature ; delay would be undesirable, and to alter it now would arouse suspicion. Wording of Article [group omitted] is :— certain that the opposition which the exchange will encounter [ ? ] from British interests affect unfavourably the chances of the Assembly’s ratifying our Arabistan Convention. (R.) Persian Government agree not to employ without the concurrence of the no present liabilities (see last paragraph of Kirk’s Minute of 4th February). Should the Russian Government desire to exercise these rights later on, it will be for them to TO INDIA[ This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government] PERSIA. ONFIDENTIAL. [May 30.] Section 1, [19978] No. 1. Sir Edward (No. 706.) (Telegraphic.) P. PERSIAN telegraph lines. Grey to Sir A. Nicolson. ^Foreign Office, May 30, 1909. We are submitting points in your telegram No. 275 of the 27th instant to the India Office for their views. [2266 gg 1] f. r lg&lt;5Uv_t ^ 'ISggr Sir A. Nicolson to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received May 27, 4'30 p.m.) (No. 275.) St. Petersburgh, May 27, 1909, 4'5 p.m PERSIAN telegraphs. In an interview with experts yesterday at the Ministry for Foreign Affairs stress was laid on the following points :— 1. Advisability of seizing present favourable moment for effecting exchange of lines. 2. Russian signallers on Arabistan lines. Russians object to proposed wording of the Agreement with the Persian Govern ment as too vague, and as leaving it open to the Persian Government to insist that their consent to the employment of Russians would be necessary. Instead of “ without the concurrence of the British Government no others than,” &amp;c., they would prefer “ save with the consent of the British Government only Persia,” &amp;c. (see your despatch No. 60). They have no objection to the stipulation as to possible extensions, with reservation as to the Russian sphere. 3. They urge that extra lines from Tehran to Shahrud should be begun at once. 4. They desire information as to the financial position of the Tehran-Khanikin line, especially as to a payment made by Indo-European Telegraph Company in connection with this line. They fear that Persian Government may afterwards call upon them to make good this debt and take over other obligations contracted for lines. I am promised official reply very shortly in the above sense, and it would be prudent to wait for it before taking any action. (Sent to Tehran.)111 - -3if$T&gt; CONFIDENTIAL Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey .— (Received May 30, 10'30 p.m.) (No. 423.) t / Tehran, May 30, 1909, 9 p.m. SIR A. NICOLSON’S telegram No. 275 and my telegram No. 409.® Tehran, May 30, 1909, 9 p.m. 1. I agree that the present moment is favourable, but unfortunately it is pretty certain that the opposition which the exchange will encounter [ ? ] from British interests affect unfavourably the chances of the Assembly’s ratifying our Arabistan Convention. 2. Convention is already prepared for signature ; delay would be undesirable, and to alter it now would arouse suspicion. Wording of Article [group omitted] is :— European Telegraph Department. (End of R.). Possibly Russian Government might be content with an undertaking from us to support their demand for Russian signallers, should the case arise. I presume that reservation as to Russian sphere will form subject of a secret Company here. But it seems to me that we are now merely concerned with an arrange ment by which Russia takes our place as regards the line.^ We have rights over it, but ^ no present liabilities (see last paragraph of Kirk’s Minute of 4th February). Should / the Russian Government desire to exercise these rights later on, it will be for them to v, come to a suitable arrangement with Persian Government respecting any liabilities of the line. (Sent to St. Petersburgh.) (R.) Persian Government agree not to employ without the concurrence of the Indo-European Telegraph Department any but Persians or the employes of the Indo- arrangement between His Majesty’s Government and the Russian Government. 4. I know nothing of any such [? payment], and I hesitate to inquire of the (452-472]DECYPHER Si* A* Nicolson, St Petersburg, d, 4,5 p.m, r, 4,30 p MAY MAY 27th. NO 276. Persian Tolographe Uk ' t . . J In an intorriovr vrith exports yostordap at the Minist^ for Foroign Affairs stress T?as laid on tho follorzing points; (l) Advisibilitj r of seizing prosont favourc^blo Eiomont for effectirg exchange of linos, (2) Russian signallers on Arabistan linos. Russians object to proposed wording of tho Agreement vrilh tho Persian Govt as too vague and as loading it open to tho Porsia n Govt to insist that their oonsont to the employment of Russians v/ould bo nocossary. Instead of 'rrithout tho concurrence of the British Govt no others than, otc M they vrould prefer 'scn-vo '^ith the consent of tho British Govt only Persia etc, 'rSoo j^our despatch No 60. (d) Tho.y urge that oxt r, linos from T oh -an to Shahrud should over other obligations contracted for linos. I am promised official reply very shortly in tho above seme it would ho prudent t ^ va.it fof it before taking arfy action. Sent to Tehran. They have no objection to tho stipulation as to possible extensions with roe or/at ion aa to tho Russian sphere. (4)Thoy doe ire information as to tho financial position of Kharikin ^j_ no ospecially as to e*.payment made by Indo- €OPY TO ih ' ’ ASr I mmediate. In any further communica- * tion on this subject, please quote No. 19164/09. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. : fO s N. A ' 'hN 'v l / &lt;-v wcs C / 1 ?** i Foreign Office 25th, 1909. Sir:- With reference to previous correspondence/I am directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you, to he laid before the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty*s Minister at Tehran reporting that negotiations are almost completed for the proposed transfer of the Arabistan Telegraph lines to the charge of the Indo-European Telegraph Department and that the Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs is prepared to sign a suitable Convention provided notes are exchanged agreeing that its pro visions are not to become operative until they are ap proved by the National Assembly. Sir E. Grey proposes, if Viscount Morley concurs, to authorize Sir G. Barclay to sign such a Convention on the conditions proposed and to inform him that it is presumed that His Majesty*s Ambassador at St. Petersburg Ehe Under Secretary of State, India Office. ^ f J-f ' (o -* V 3^' (19164/09). St. Petersburg may be instructed to request the Rus sian Government to take action on the lines of the suggestion made by His Excellency in the third para graph of his telegram No.96 of the 24th of February last a copy of which was communicated to your Depart ment on the same day. I am, Your most obedient, humble Servant, ' !CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received May 21, 2*45 p.m.) Tehran, May 21, 1909, 10-30 a.m. (No. 409.) ARABIST AN Line. Negotiations when almost completed were obstructed by late Minister of Finance and subsequently delayed by disorganization of the Government. Minister for Foreign Affairs is now prepared to sign a Convention well within the lines indicated in your telegram No. 36 of 27th January on condition of an exchange of notes, recording that it is not to become operative until approved by Assembly. To sign it without this reservation would be breach of spirit if not of letter of Articles 23 and 24 of Constitution which has been restored. After consultation with the Director, and with a person in close touch with the Nationalists, I am disposed to agree to this condition. i'm fThis Docnment is the Property of His Britannic Ma,iesty’s Government.] PERSIA. ONPIDENTIAL. [February 18.] Section 3. [5273] No. 1. Sir C. Spring-Rice to Sir Edward Grey.—[Received February 18.) (No. 21.) Tehran, January 27, 1907. I HAVE the honour to transmit herewith a translation of the Persian Constitu tion which has been prepared by Mr. Churchill. It provides for a National Assembly, composed of from 100 to 200 members, chosen by popular election, and of a Senate of sixty members, half of whom are elected and half nominated by the Government. The Assembly is elected for two years, and the Shah, by a separate Rescript, has promised not to dissolve it before the expiration of its first term. After the first term it can he dissolved on a motion passed by two-thirds of the Senate and approved bv the Shah. The members take oath “ so long as the rights of the Assembly are respected to be loyal to the Sovereign and the rights of the nation.” The Ministers, who are appointed by the Sovereign, can be summoned before the Assembly to s:ive explanations as to their conduct of affairs, and are made responsible to the Assembly for any derogation of their powers, or infraction of the laws. _ They can address the Assembly on the invitation of the President, and have the right of proposing Bills in person. ^ # The Assembly must give its consent before any concession is granted, or loan foreign or internal is concluded, and must be consulted as to any Treaty with a foreign Power, except such arrangements as, in the opinion of the Government, should be kept secret in the public interest. It has control of all financial matters, and must give its consent before the Budget is passed, or any new tax is instituted. The Senate has concurrent legislative power, except in financial matters, on which, however, it appears to have the right of veto. . . , , In case of disagreement between the two Houses, a joint Committee is appointed, and if an Agreement is not arrived at, the Senate can, by two-thirds majority, require the dissolution of the Assembly, provided that this does not take place more than once in the two years’ term. ^ . , ,,, ^ , General powers of examination into the conduct of affairs by the Government, and of direct access to the Shah are provided for. The members are inviolable, and the proceedings are public, with certain reservations as to the proceedings ol secret Committees. , • i xi • • +- o Pull liberty of reporting proceedings and of comment, provided this is not ot a libellous character, is accorded to the press. # _ J ^ It will be seen that, if the Constitution is carried into effect, the Persian Govern ment is now a limited monarchy, the Ministers, however, although responsi e or eir conduct to the Assembly, being nominated by the Sovereign, and not elected The powers of the Assembly include financial control, and no loan can e ma e y Government without its consent. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) CECIL SPRING-RICE. Inclosure in No. 1. The Persian Constitution. In the name of God the all Merciful! ^ WHEREAS by our Exrman of the 5th August, 1906, we commanded the constitution of a National Assembly for the progress and welfare of the State and nation, the strengthening of the foundations of the kingdom, and the carrying out of 12352 s—3] B2 the laws of Islam; and whereas, in accordance with the clause by which it is provided that, as each individual member of the State has a right to take part in the superintendence and decision of public affairs, we therefore have permitted the election and appointment of Deputies on behalf of the nation; and whereas the National Assemblv has been opened through our gracious benevolence, we have decreed the * folio win o 1 Articles of constitutional Regulations for the National Assembly, including the duties and business of the Assembly, and its limitations and relations towards Government Departments. Concerning the Institution of the Assembly. Article 1. The National Assembly has been instituted in accordance with the Imperial Pirman of the 5th August, 1906. t i . .. v ‘ 4 rt 9 . The National Assembly is the representative of the whole Persian nation which shares in political and domestic affairs. * i , i ; m i Art. 3. The National Assembly is composed of members elected at lehran and m the provinces, and the place of their meeting is at Tehran. Art, 4. The number of Deputies for Tehran and the provinces is at present, in accordance with a separate election Regulation, 160 persons, and if necessary may he increased to 200. . , , . „ Art. 5. The Deputies are elected for two whole years, and this period begins Irotn the dav on which all the provincial Deputies assemble at lehian. Aftei the lapse or two years, Deputies must be again elected, and the people are at liberty to re-elect members if they are pleased with them. ^ ... Art. 6. The Tehran Deputies had the option of instituting the Assembly and starting discussion and debates. Their dicisions by majority during the absence of the provincial Deputies will be valid, and are to be carried out. ; Art. 7. When debates are started at least two-thirds of the members must be present, and when questions are put to the vote three'quarters of the members must be present. A majority is obtained when more than half oi the members present give their votes. . ' Art. 8. The time of recess and of sitting of the National Assembly is to be fixed bv the Assembly itself, according to the internal Regulations. After the summer recess the Assembly must again sit and begin its labours on the Sth October, which is the date of the celebration of the opening of the Assembly. Art. 9 The National Assembly may convene extraordinary sittings during the recess. Art 10. When the Assembly opens, an address must be submitted to His Imperial Majesty in reply to a Speech from the Throne. Art. 11. As soon as members of the National Assembly join they must take the following oath and sign it:— r lhe Oath. “We who have signed below, invite God to be our witness, and we take oath by the Koran that, so long as the rights of the Assembly and the members of the Assembly are protected and carried out in accordance with these Regulations, we will carry out the duties intrusted to us, as well as possible, with the greatest sincerity and straight forwardness, and to our best ability, and we will be true and truthful to our just Sovereign, and will not be traitors to the foundations of Sovereignty or the rights of the nation, and we will have no other object but the advantage and the interests of the Govern ment and nation of Persia.” Art. 12. No person will, by any excuse whatever, have the right to proceed against any member of the Assembly. Should by chance one of the members be guilty of a public offence or crime, and should he be caught in the act of committing t le offence, the carrying out of punishment must still be with the knowledge ot tie Assembly. # ,, Art. 13. In order that the result of the discussions of the National Assem y should be carried out, their proceedings must be public. Newspaper reporters ant the public have the right to be present and to hear, in accordance with the i n ^ r j ia Regulations, but without the right of speaking. The newspapers may print al ^ debates of the Assembly without altering their meaning, so that the public shorn e aware of all their proceedings, and any one who has suggestions to make shou o] y tHij ate eitie is able to do so in tlio papers, and so tliat no matter should be bidden from any one. Therefore all newspapers, so long as their publications are not contrary to any of the Articles of the constitution of the nation or State, are empowered to print matters of public utility as well as the debates of the Assembly, and the obseryations of the people ^ on those debates. Should any one publish an untrue report of the debates with personal motives, or make a libel, he will be liable to an inquiry, proceedings, and punishment. ° # Art. 14. The National Assembly, in accordance with a separate Regulation entitled the internal Regulation, will regulate its own personal affairs, such as the election of a President, a \ ice-President, Secretaries, and other members, as well as the debates, &amp;c. fcaili Bani®;. irti to rci.; oita is::: lemta i sspreseta jc istotefe er tk ill itokrjii igsdurD|i toihF •must te- 'tleM s' jp ata 1 Respecting the Duties of the Assembly, its Limitations and Rights. Art. 15. The National Assembly bas the right to discuss truthfully and sincerely all matters it considers to be desirable in the interests of the vState and nation to investigate ; and, subject to the approval of a majority, to submit them, in the enjoy ment of the utmost safety and confidence, with the approval of the Senate, to His Imperial Majesty the Shah, through the first person of the Government, for His Majesty's signature, and to be then put into execution. Art. 16. In general all laws necessary for the strengthening of the Government and kingdom, and the regulation of State affairs, and for the constitution of Ministries, must receive the sanction of the National Assembly. Art. 17. The necessary Bills for making new laws, or for the alteration, amplifi cation, or cancellation of existing laws, will, when desirable, be prepared by the National Assembly to be submitted to His Imperial Majesty the Shah for signature with the approval of the Senate, and to be then put into execution. Art. 18. The regulation of financial matters, the modification of the Budget, the alteration of the arrangement of taxation, the refusal or acceptance of impositions, as well as the inspections which will be undertaken by the Government, will be done with the approval of the Assembly. Art. 19. The Assembly will have the right, for the purpose of reforming financial matters and facilitating the relations of the Governors and the apportioning of the provinces of Persia, and the reappointment of Governors, after the Senate has given its approval, to demand from the Government authorities that the decision arrived at should be carried out. Art. 20. The Budget of each Ministry must be finished for the succeeding year in the last half of each year, and must be ready fifteen days before the 20th March. Art. 21. Should it be necessary with regard to the constitutional laws of the Ministries to make a new law, or to alter or cancel existing laws, it will be done with the consent of the National Assembly, whether its necessity be first pointed out by the Assembly or by the responsible Minister. Art. 22. Whenever a part of the revenue or property of the Government or State is to be sold, or a change of frontier or border becomes necessary, it will be done with the approval of the National Assembly. Art. 23. Without the approval of the National Assembly no concession whatever for the formation of Companies or Associations shall be granted by the Government. Art. 24. Treaties, Conventions, the granting of concessions, monopolies, either commercial, industrial, or agricultural, whether the other party be a native or a foreigner, can only be done with the approval of the National Assembly. Treaties which it may be in the interests of the Government or nation to keep secret are excepted. Art. 25. All Government loans of any nature whatsoever, whether internal or foreign, will be made with the knowledge and approval of the National Assembly. the Government, by Associations or Companies, whether native or foreign, can only be undertaken with the approval of the National Assembly. received the Imperial sanction, by misrepresentations obtain the issue of a written or -3] B 24 verbal order from His Imperial Majesty the Shah, and excuse himself thereby for his delav and negligence, he will by law be responsible to His Imperial Majesty the Shah. Art. 29. ^Whichever Minister who in a matter of matters should not be able to answer for his actions in accordance with the laws approved by His Imperial Majesty, and if it should be apparent that he has broken the law and transgressed the stipulated ' limitations, the Assembly will petition His Imperial Majesty for his dismissal, and when his fault has been determined by the Courts of Justice he will not again he allowed to serve the Government. ..... Art. 30 The National Assembly has the right whenever it considers it desirable to make petitions direct to His Imperial Majesty by the means of a body composed of the President and six members elected by the six classes. I lie time for the audience must bo arranged for through the Minister of Court. Art. 31. The Ministers have the right to be present at the sittings of the National Assembly and to sit in the place set apart for them, and to heai the debates of the Assembly; and should they think it necessary they may ask the President for permis sion to speak and give the necessary explanations for the discussion and investigation of affairs. Respecting the Statement of Affairs to the National Assembly. Art. 32. Any individual member of the public may make a statement of his case, or complaints or criticisms, to the office of the Assembly, and if the matter concerns the Assembly itself, a satisfying answer will be given to him ; but should the matter concern one of the Ministries, it will be sent to that Ministry for investigation, and in order that a satisfying answer be given. Art. 33. New laws which are necessary will be prepared at the responsible, Ministries, and will be given to the National Assembly by the responsible Minister or by the Sadr Azam, and after receiving the approval of the Assembly will receive His Imperial Majesty’s sign-manual and be put into execution. Art. 34. The President of the Assembly can, if necessary, of his oavu initiative or by the desire of ten members of the Assembly, or of a Minister, form a Secret Committee, without the presence of newspaper reporters or spectators, composed of a number of persons chosen from among the members of the Assembly, at which the other members of the Assembly w T ill not have the right to attend. The result of the deliberations of the Secret Committee can, however, only be put into execution when the Secret Committee in the presence of three quarters of the persons elected accept the point at issue by a majority of votes, and if the matter be not passed by the Secret Committee it will not be stated in the Assembly, and will remain secret. Art. 35. Should the Secret Committee be instituted by the President of the Assembly, he has the right to inform the public of any part of it he thinks fit, but if the Secret Committee is instituted by a Minister the publication of the debate can only be subject to that Minister’s permission. Art. 36. Any one of the Ministers may withdraw at any stage of its progress any matter put before the Assembly by him, excepting when his statement is called forth by the initiative of the Assembly, in which case the withdrawal of the subject must be subject to the agreement of the Assembly. | . Art. 37. Should the Bill of any Minister not be passed it will be returned with the observations of the Assembly. The responsible Minister can, after refusing or accepting the criticisms of the Assembly, again send it to the Assembly a second time. . Art. 38. The members of the National Assembly must definitely and explicitly either refuse or accept the points at issue, and no one will have the right to influence them in giving their decisions. A refusal or acceptance on the part of members of the Assembly must be made in such a manner that the newspaper reporters and spectators may be able to observe it—that is to say, their decision must be made by visible signs, such as blue and white cards, or the like. ‘I'he Statement of Matters on the Part of the Assembly. Art. 39. Whenever a case is brought up by a member of the Assembly it will only be subject to debate when at least fifteen members of the Assembly approve o its discussion, in which case the matter in point will be submitted in writing to t ie President, wdio has the right to give it to the Committee of Investigation.Art. 40. At the time of debate and inquiry into a matter, as above stated in Article 39, whether by the Assembly or by the Committee of Investigation, should the matter have reference to one of the responsible Ministries, the Assembly must notify the responsible Minister, so that if possible he should attend in person or send his representative in order that the discussion should take place in the presence of the Minister or his representative. A copy of the statement and its appendices must be sent beforehand from ten days to a month, with the exception of urgent matters, to the responsible Minister. The day on which the debate will take place must likewise be previously determined. After an investigation of the case in the presence of the responsible Minister, in the event of the Assembly approving by a majority of votes, the statement will be formally written and delivered to the responsible Minister in order that he should take the consequential step. Art. 41. In case a responsible Minister on grounds of expediency is not in accord with the Assembly in a matter raised by it, he must adduce his proofs and convince the Assembly. Art. 42. In any case concerning which the National Assembly desires explana tions from a responsible Minister, the latter is obliged to supply an answer, and this answer must not, without an excuse, be delayed beyond a reasonable time, with the exception of secret matters, the secrecy of which for a stipulated period is desirable in the interests of the Government and nation, but after the expiration of the stipulated time the responsible Minister is obliged to state the circumstances of the case to the Assembly. Respecting the Conditions of the Institution of the Senate. Art. 43. Another Assembly, called the Senate, will be constituted, composed of sixty members, whose sittings will coincide, after its constitution, with those of the National Assembly. Art. 44. The Regulations of the Senate must receive the approval of the National Assembly. Art. 45. The members of the Assembly will be chosen from among the enlightened, intelligent, orthodox, and respectable persons of the State, thirty persons on behalf of His Imperial Majesty, of whom fifteen from among the inhabitants of Tehran and fifteen from the inhabitants of the provinces ; and thirty persons on behalf of the nation, of whom fifteen persons elected by the people of Tehran, and fifteen persons elected by the people of the provinces. Art. 46. After the constitution of the Senate all affairs must receive the approval of both Assemblies. If those affairs are initiated by the Senate or by the body of Ministers, they must first be determined in the Senate and passed by a majority, and then be sent to the National Assembly for approval; but affairs initiated in the National Assembly will, on the contrary, pass from that Assembly to the Senate, with the exception of financial matters, which will be the prerogative of the National Assembly, and the Senate will be informed of the arrangements made by the Assembly regarding these affairs in order that the Senate should make its observations on the same to the National Assembly, which is, however, at liberty, after the necessary investigations, either to accept or to refuse the proposals of the Senate. Art. 47. So long as the Senate is not constituted affairs will require only the approval of the National Assembly and the sign-manual of His Imperial Majesty to be put into execution. Art, 48. Whenever a question initiated by a Minister is, after having been passed by the Senate, referred to the National Assembly and not accepted, and in the event of the matter being an important one, a third Assembly, composed of an equal number of members of both Assemblies elected by each, will be constituted to inquire into the subject at issue. The result of the deliberations of this Assembly will be read to the National xissembly. If an understanding is come to so’much the better; but if not, a report of the matter will be submitted to His Imperial Majesty the Shah. Should His Imperial Majesty confirm the decision of the National Assembly, it will be put into execution ; but should His Imperial Majesty not confirm it, His Imperial Majesty will command that the question should be debated and investigated afresh, and if still a settlement is not arrived at, and if the Senate by a majority of two-thirds vote for the dissolution of the National Assembly, and if the body of Ministers separately recommend the dissolution of the National Assembly, His Imperial Majesty the Shah’s Rescript dissolving the National Assembly will be issued, and His Imperial Majestywill in the same Rescript command that fresh elections should take place, and the dpodIp will have the risrlit to elect the former Deputies. P Art 49 The new Tehran Deputies must be ready withm one month and the nrovincial Deputies within three months, and as soon as the Tehran Deputies are S™ Assembly will open and commence ite ou^ but hey will no^d = th noints at issue until the provincial Deputies arrive. But when all the members are nresent and a full maiority vote as in the same sense as before, His Imperial Majesty wUl approve the decision of the National Assembly and will command that it be put into ^ u 5 t “ n p uring each term of election-that is to say, during two years-a general ' Art si It is decreed that the Sovereign who succeeds us should protect these limitations and Articles, which aim at the strengthening of the State and of the faun- dations of the kingdom, and the protection of justice and contentment of the nation wMch we have decreed and put into execution, and which they must look upon as their duty to fulfil. Tn +hP month of Zilkade the unclean, 1324. O God the Almighty ! The Constitutional Laws of the National Assembly and the Senate, containing 51 Articles, are correct. 14th of the month of Zilkade, 1324 (December 30, 1906).’ In the handwriting of Muzaffer-ed-Deen Shah : It is correct. (Sealed) (Sealed) Valiahd (Mohammed Ali Shah). Mushir-ed-Dowleh (the Grand Vizier).Minute Paper. Secret Department. Letter from it lie Bee. J ^ ^ Formally acknowledged ^ 'x o- Date. Initials. Under Secretary 12- i, Secretary of State /I fU Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State A. SUBJECT. ^lJLJjCLjL ^^JZ-r\y&lt;L-exr&gt;^.[This Document is the Proc PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. * ' ^ w 3o((jf ^ of yA Britannic Majesty’s Government.] GC-J ''V&gt; ^2! APRiSCg, Section 3. [11794] (No. 178.) Sir, No. 1. Sir A. Nicolson to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received March 29.) St. Petersburgh, March 19, 1909. I HAVE the honour to transmit herewith copy of an aide-memoire, which I have addressed to the Russian Government, respecting telegraph lines in Persia, in accordance with the instructions contained in your telegram No. 323 of the 17th instant. I liav© &amp;c S fhxj/o#) (Signed) A. NICOLSON. Inclosure in No. 1. / ide-me'moire. HIS Majesty’s Embassy would wish to inform the Imperial Ministry for Foreign Affairs that it was thought desirable in the negotiations which are proceeding between the Persian Government and the Indo-European Telegraph Department to seek to acquire the right for the latter to co-operate in the construction and maintenance of any extension of the Arabistan telegraph lines. His Majesty’s Embassy would desire to inquire of the Imperial Ministry for Foreign Affairs if it has any objection to the step which the Indo-European Telegraph Department has taken, it being, of course, clearly understood that the right above mentioned would be waived in the event of the telegraph lines being extended into the Russian sphere. _ # , In connection with the question of Persian telegraphs, His Majesty s^ Embassy would further wish to inform the Imperial Ministry of I oreign Affairs that it^ is quite possible that the Persian Minister of Telegraphs will urge on the Indo-Euiopean Telegraph Department to proceed to the construction of a second line to Shahrud. It might be im desirable in the present stage of the negotiations regarding the Arabistan telegraph lines to meet this request, if it were made, by a direct refusal, as thereby the negotiations might be jeopardized. His Majesty’s Embassy would therefore be glad to know if the Imperial Ministry for Foreign Affairs would wish the Indo-European Telegraph Department to undertake preliminary work, which could be abandoned when the negotiations as to the Arabistan telegraph lines were completed. ^ e t? • His Majesty’s Embassy would be grateful if the Imperial Ministry for r oreign Affairs would kindly give a reply at its earliest convenience. ‘F?) 3f (rtrftqi J St. Petersburgh, March 5 (18), 1909. [2191 3]D R A F T Foreign Office Sir, I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 9th inst. No. 9097, enclosing copy of a telegram No. 137 from H.M. Minister at Tehran reporting, with reference to the negotiations with the Persian Govt, for the transfer of the control of the Arab is tan lines to the I.E. Tel. Dept., that he has inserted a danse in the draft Agreement, securing to H.M. Govt, the right to co-operate in the construction and maintenance of any extension of those lines. In reply I am to say that it seens to Viscount Morley that the rights to be secured by the clause may prove valuable hereafter. He would suggest that the action of H.M.Minister might be approved, if Sir E.Grey is satisfied that the arrangement contemplated will cause no difficulty with the Russian Govt., Cx&amp;L on the condition, suggested by Si r G.Bu relay, that tha proposal will be dropped if it proves likely to cause delay in a settlement on the lines already app ro v ed b y H.M• Go v e nun en t. h.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. 90S7. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Foreign Office March 9th. 1909 4 Sir:- - I am directed by Secretary Sir E. drey to trans mit to you,to be laid before the Secretary of State for India,the accompanying copy of a telegram,as marked in the margin,respecting the negotiations with the Persian G-overnment in regard to the Arabistan Telegraph line. Sir E. Grey will be glad to be furnished with the observations of Lord Morley on this telegram. I am. Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant. Ihe Under Secretary of State India Office.3&lt;fTf ,2— CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir A. Nicolson (St. Petersburgh). (No. 277.) _ Foreign Office, March 5, 1909, 5'45 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 96 : Persian telegraphs. You need not raise question of British signallers on Sharud and Meshed lines. If the Russian Government press the point of procedure to be followed at Tehran, your Excellency should use language in the sense of my telegram No! 207.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government,} ^^4 ■ PERSIA. fU CONFIDENTIAL. * [9766] Sir A. Nicolson to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received March 15.) (No. 150.) gi r&gt; f' St. Petersburgh, March 8 , 1909. WITH reference to your telegram No. 207 of the 19th ultimo, I have the honour to transmit herewith a copy of an aide-memoire which I have addressed to the Russian Ministry for Foreign Affairs respecting various questions awaiting settlement in connection with the Persian telegraphs. I nciirA Aro (Signed) ’ A. NICOLSON. Inclosure in No. 1. Aide-memoire. HIS Majesty’s Government have had under their consideration the aide-memoire of the Imperial Ministry for Foreign Affairs of the 16th (29th) January last respecting the various questions awaiting settlement in connection with the Persian telegraphs. As regards the wish expressed by the Russian Government that provision should be made for the employment of Russian signallers on the Arabistan lines in the event of the future development of Russian trade in the south making it desirable, His Majesty’s Government are of opinion that this wish could be met by the conclusion of a Secret ^gj &gt; g 0 jQ 0 ] 2 't; to the desired effect between the Pritish and Russian Governments, while the proposed Agreement with the Persian Government should stipulate that, without the concurrence of the Pritish Government, no others than 1 ersian subjects and the members of the staff of the Indo-European Telegraph Department should be employed in the offices or on the lines of the system. } With regard to the Tehran-Khanikin line, it appears to His Majesty s Govern ment that the exchange of the Memoranda of the 10th (23rd) June and 11th (24th) August, 1907, constitutes sufficient record of the Agreement arrived atj between the British and Russian Governments. Should any further Agreement on the subject with the Imperial Government be necessary, it would be preferable that it should be deferred until the consent of the Persian Government has been obtained to the proposed Arrangement in regard to the Arabistan system. St. Petersburgh, February 21 (March 6 ), 1909. [2191 11] &amp;UJ. /S’ kIn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. 7553/09. and address — The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, * f- Lond011 * February &lt;25' , 1909. Sir: - With reference to your letter of February 11th con cerning the Persian Telegraph Lines, I am directed by r./ Secretary Sir E. G-rey to transmit herewith, to be laid V Jo' before Viscount Morley, a copy of a telegram from His kal es ty’s Ambassador at St. Petersburgh on the subject. It will be seen that Sir A. Eicolson thinks that the Russian Government will probably object to the employment of British signallers on the lines from Sharud and he shed to the frontier, and that His Excellency suggests that he should inform the Russian Government that the question oi the exchange of the lines might be brought before the Persian Government by the Russian and British Representa tives at Tehran at the first favourable opportunity. Sir E. Grey would be glad to be favoured with Lord Morley*s views on these suggestions. 1 am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, Under Secretary of State, India Office. Foreign OfficeSir A. Nicolson to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received February 24, 3‘20 P.M.) (No. 96.) St. Petersburyh, February 24, 1909, 2*20 p.m. 24j^ February, 2 p.m. L r Persian telegraphs. Your telegram No. 207 [of 19th February]. I would submit that Russian Government will probably object to British signallers on the lines from Sharud and Meshed to the frontier on the ground that these lines are in Russian sphere, while Arabistan lines are in neutral zone. Assistant Minister for Foreign Affairs mentioned this latter fact as enabling Russian signallers if necessary to be employed on the lines in question. I do not think that they would have made the request if the lines had been in the British sphere. I would also suggest, as regards exchange of control of Tehran-Meshed and Khaf- Seistan lines, that I should tell them that two Representatives at Tehran might bring question before the Persian Government at the first favourable opportunity. This would enable Sir G. Barclay to take it up when he thought desirable, while if I tell them that exchange had better be dependent on conclusion of the arrangement of Arabistan lines, they may reply that the latter question is a\^ fi-mportuuatqftme chiefly of British interest, while the other is practically part of the Convention concluded a year and a-half ago, for the settlement of which we have from time to time pressed. I am sorry that the pressure of work delayed my submitting these observations earlier.2i&gt;l% Tolegrara to Sir A. Hicoloon.. ..St. Petorsburg. F.O. Eeb 19th. 1909. 1 p.n. -v, 19 FEB 'Sin r Xv. vC '” oep#' No.207. i- Your aeopatch Ho.71 (of Jan 30 ).Persian Talegrapho, Your Excellency nay inf ora the IMssian Govorninent of the ,Y subotanco of ante-penultimte paragraph of India Office letter of Feb lOtii. You may also coiiiaunicate our view as to the order in which the questions should be dealt with. T’o entirely share desire of Russian Govern',lent for speedy settlement of exchange of control on Yohran-Meshed and Khaf-Nasratabad lines but wo consider that Persian Govt are more likely to waive their ejections to this exchange if the-have first been well disposed, by the financial a '-antages arising from the transfer to us of control over the Arabistan line. Indo-European Dept are bein'; instructed again to hasten negotiations as to Arab- istan line and proXonnation of concesions;and we fear that any attempt to rush throng exchange of Tehran-Ileshed ana Khaf- Hasratabad lines first would have the opposite effect to that deCuiroci0 0 ^ CONFIDENTIAL. f Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received February 17, 5*45 P.M.) (No. 103.) f Tehran, February 17, 1909, 12*35 P.M. YOUR telegram No. 36. I have received a note from the Persian Government stating that Minister of Telegraphs has been instructed by command of the Shah to make necessary arrange ments with the Indo-European Telegraph Department for the repair of the Arabistan telegraph line as soon as possible. Minister of Telegraphs has requested Mr. Barker to report on the state of the line. We are now in a position to discuss details, and Barker is awaiting final instruc tions from Mr. Kirk. I hope that these will not be delayed.3oo^&gt; Copy of a telegram, dated 1st February 1909, from Mr.Barker, Teheran, to the Director in Chief. 83/28. as £6000 and £600 or less will not be sufficient for permanent construction and annual maintenance should Persian Minister of Telegraphs accept the offer, please explain by telegraph how you propose without offering loan difference will be raised. Copy of a telegram in reply, dated 18th February 1909. 27/l. Although amount may not be sufficient for the purpose of total construction and maintenance it would go a long way. Any assistance required could be promised on reasonable terms for balance required that inspection of line shows is necessary. H.M.the Shah originally desired gradual replacement wooden by iron posts. If anything not clear instructions contained in my telegrams of 28th and 29th January last, please consult me by wire.CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay {Tehran). (No 36 ) Foreign Office, January 27, 1909, 6*5 p.m. * YOUR telegram No. 61 : Arabistan telegraph. . The arrangement we litwc jnst come to with the Russian Government was as follows:— On the receipt from the Persian Minister of Telegraphs of the proposal referred to in your telegram No. 423, the Indo-European Telegraph Department would he prepared to accept it' and, provided the Persian Telegraph Department undertake to procure an extensloLof the Concessions till 1945, would offer in return, m the first xnstance to reconstruct the Arabistan line on behalf of the Persian Telegraph Department, at a cost of some 6,0001, and to spend some 6001 per annum m mamta,^ In addition to this, should it prove necessary m order to se f’ ir ® °g d t0 Concessions, the Indo-European Telegraph Department would be offer to advance to the Persian Telegraph Department a lump sum not exceeding 10,000Z., being ten years’ rental of the Central Persian line. Necessary details are being telegraphed to Mr. Barke ' These are the lines on which we should like Agreement concluded.il ; &gt;\ &gt; 1 ^ ( JU-U ) Note on Noreign Office letter No .3470,dated 29th January 1909 . I have telegraphed to Mr .Barker at Teheran that, among the stipulations for our control of the Arahistan lines, there should he a guarantee that the Persian Government will allow the employment of no others than Persian subjects and staff of the Indo-European Telegraph Department in the offices or on the lines, except with the concurrence of the British Government. With a stipulation in this form the suspicions of the Persian Government should not he aroused, and the agreement, as to the employment of Russian Signallers should the future development of Russian trade in the south of Persia make it desirable, can he made privately between the British and Russian Governments. This possible introduction in the future of Russian Signallers into the Araoistan telegraph offices is not altogether desirable, and was not anticipated. If it were carried out entirely for trade purposes the employ- ment would only -be in the comparatively large centres of busi ness such as Mohammerah and Ahwaz.and this would not be of much importance one way or the other. As to the further agreement referred to in the third paragraph on the subject of the transfer of the righto over the Teheran-Khanikin line, the Foreign Office telegraphed to Mr Marling on the 26th February, 1908. 'Your telegram No.42. Cession of rights over Teheran-Khanikin line. Exchange of hnemoranda appears sufficient as record of agreement between ftwo Governments and no further formality is contemplated.' TheThe information I have received is that the Persian Minister of Telegraphs is much opposed to the transfer of the Teheran-Meshed line to the Russians, and there is little doubt that if this question was pressed on him the settlement of the other telegraph questions would be delayed, v v 30th January 1909. The Russian Aide Memoirs, since received, brings to notice that the Russian Government reserve to themselves the right to induce the Persian Government to make over to them the control of the lines from Shahrud to the Russian frontier and from Meshed to Askhabad, on similar conditions to those now existing on the Meshed- Seistan line. The employment of British signallers on the Me shed-Seistan line is one of the existing con ditions, and if the employment of Russian signallers is agreed to on the Arabistan lines, it seems a matter for consideration whether the Russian Government should not be asked to agree to the employment of British signallers on the lines they state they may have to take over from Shahrud and Meshed to the Russian frontier. It has also to be noted that the Russian Govern ment ask that the negotiations for the renewal of British concessionsconcessions and the control of the Arabistan lines should be kept separate from the negotiations for the transfer of the Me shed-Teheran and Meshed-Seistan lines, so as to preclude any delay in the settlement of the latter question Whereas the view adopted on our side is that if this latter question is pressed on the Persian Government at once this action will probably delay the settlement of all telegraph questions now under negotiation. The last paragraph of the Aide Memo ire refers to financial accounts between the Persian Government and the Indo-European Telegraph Department regarding the Teheran- Khanikin line. There are no such accounts, as the line is worked entirely by the Persian Telegraph Administration.Ijj any further eomintmie^- tion on this subject, please quote No. ^ C V ' OC \ I— * The Under-Secrf'tary of 3tato, Foreign Office, London. £Cj 1+ The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents &lt;j ■ his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for d*vdux and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop '■/ of the under-mentioned paper. i ? 1 Foreign Office, 3 , igo T Reference to previous letter: go y&lt;js Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. cJL_ A/^ JLto induce the Persian Government to transfer to thr ctar ■••• of the iunsian telerraph Establishments the lines'fro: Shalxrud to tt.e Russian Frontier and jfrom i •- d to Askhahad. on similar conditions to t ose now existing on the Meshed- -^feiota]) Line.As regards e from Ghah.n d to the Russian Frontier, constituting the most important link connectnr the Russisun and Persian t h' raphic By»tem» # t m—m -ti. ons to the Government of the Shah on the subject of placing it in prone ‘ repair; nevertholeso the condition of t is line remains 9 as formerly,extremely unsatiefae ory« Will Is notif'irm the Etrbassy as above « the Imr or ir-3 Ivinistr.' d^or it the * r duty to explain, that in t.he-i r or ini on, it appears to b'” urgently necessary to sej-arate ne •otiations on the quest ion of any new Concessions fm-rn jotlations on the emtter of an exchange between Russia Sc ClS a d England of t eir 'espective lines, to ’• ■' - -elude any delay in 4 he decision of this latter questim which has born already perfected and regulated by b'-h Qovernnents* If is doubtless known to the Embassy, hat x oKt ; ho fi.rs r rur ours of the intention of both Powers o 'x- - change the right of control over the line* na«e$ ; the Persian Government and the Jejilis regarded this fac uv extreme suspleion f so a ce IC&lt; 1 f &lt; •' e ^ l r r 4- he Persians ),&lt;.&gt;? the practical division of Persia o.u the basis of th~ Russo-^nglish Agreement. In order io '•acif ‘ he ^ersle^o* / and an end l a s » hhe Russian and English Ministers deemed it necessary to exoliange lines the character of i .p r t rivate agreenent. between t lie Russian and Ind- -Sw so. 3470/09. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. mediate. I am directed ty Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you, to t:e laid before the Secretary of State for India, copies of telegrams, as marked in the margin, on the subject of the negotiations relating to Persian Telegraphs. Sir E. Grey is disposed to think that there is no objection to acceding to the desire of the Russian Gov ernment that Russian signallers should be employed on the Arabist an line in the contingency named; but pro vision for this could more conveniently be made in a secret agreement between Great Britain find Russia, and not in the understanding with the Persian Government, as the mention of such an eventuality might arouse the suspicions of the Persian Government and thus delay the . progress of negotiations. As The Under Secretary of State, India Office.(! g c f j (3470/09)• As soon as che Persian Government have agreed to the extension of the telegraph concessions till 1945 , including one prolongation of British rights over the Tehran-Khanikin line, a further agreement might he con- cluded with ohe Russian Government, providing for the transfer of British rights over the Tehran-Khanikin line to Russia. Sir E. Grey is inclined to deprecate raising with the Persian Government the question of the exchange of control over the Tehran-Meshed and Khaf-Nasratahad lines, until the other negotiations referred to have been concluded. He considers that if, as is appre hended, the Persian Government is reluctant to assent to the exchange, the fact of raising this question con currently with the others might in the end retard rather than expedite the fined, solution of the several points under discussion. Sir E. Grey proposes, subject to any observations the Secretary of State for India may desire to make, to telegraph(3470/09). telegraph In the sense of this letter to His Majesty's Representatives at st. Petersburg and Tehran. I era. Sir, Your most obedient. humble Servant,CONFIDENTIAL. fyuZ/' I (s&gt; L&lt;.(w . 7 26 Tt-^ Sir A. Nicotson to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received January 26, 3’10 p.m.) (N°. 32.) St. Petersburgh, January 26, 1909, 1 p.m. PljRbiAN telegraphs. Your despatches Nos. 16 and 28 [of 13th and 20th January respectively]. I communicated Memorandum to Russian Ministry for Foreign Affairs, giving substance of above despatches. Assistant Minister for Foreign Affairs informed me yesterday verbally that the Russian Government agreed with all our proposals, and that he would let me have a written reply in a day or two. They would like, however, that in regard to conditions concerning control over the Arabistan lines the ’ employes should not be limited to British and Persian nationality, but that Russians might be employed also as signallers if future development of Russian trade in the south might render such employment desirable. I hope that this will be conceded. I doubt if advantage is likely to be taken of the permission for some time to come, and I think that it is only desired as a compliment. They would also like negotiations as to exchange of telegraph lines to be kept distinct from the others. This I think is also your view. They wish that all these telegraph arrangements should now be hastened on.CONFIDENTIAL 2 1’] Am &gt;&lt;) Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 36.) i Foreign Office, January 27, 1909, 6*5 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 61 : Arabistan telegraph. The arrangement we have jnst come to with the Russian Government was as follows:— On the receipt from the Persian Minister of Telegraphs of the proposal referred to in your telegram No.*423, the Indo-European Telegraph Department would be prepared to accept it, and, provided the Persian Telegraph Department undertake to procure an extension of the Concessions till 1945, would offer in return, in the first instance, to reconstruct the Arabistan line on behalf of the Persian Telegraph Department, at a cost of some 6,000/., and to spend some 600/. per annum in maintaining it subsequently. In addition to this, should it prove necessary in order to secure the extension of the Concessions, the Indo-European Telegraph Department would be further prepared to offer to advance to the Persian Telegraph Department a lump sum not exceeding 10,000/., being ten years’ rental of the Central Persian line. Necessary details are being telegraphed to Mr. Barker by Director-in-chief. These are the lines on which we should like Agreement concluded.J3I 2 ^ &lt;7 - CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received January 26, 5*4-5 p.m.) (No 61.) Tehran, January 26, 1909, 1 p.m. MY telegram No. 423 [of 8tli December]. # . An Agreement in principle for control over Arabistan [?] line was come to verbally yesterday afternoon between Minister for Foreign Affairs, - mis er o Telegraphs, and the Indo-Enropean Department. Ministers have now to submi proposal in writing for Shah’s consent, which we hope to receive very so( m- I have ventured to authorize Mr. Barker to consent to forego immediate Payment for the iron posts in event of repairs and control of the line being intrusted to the Ind °lf wouM b J[?] hopeless ^rlttempt to obtain control desired if we were to insist on immediate payment. We hope that later such sum as may e ue on accoun o iron posts may be used as a quid pro quo for prolongation of our telegraph concessions.In any further oornmanie&gt;%- iion on this aubject, please quote No. and address- id address— f, „ The Under-Secretary of State, io •* t * Toreign Office, London 1 1 ^ wr % The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for i and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop / of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office,Prv,!/lfl f ^ ' 26 ~h-£~^ £&lt;^ej . Cj l FEO J_ St. Petersburr, Jan. 26, 1909. bl » With, reference to ;-orr despatches hoc. 16 and 2£ of the If J 'h, and 20th. instant, I have the honon ' to trans mit copy of an aide-ner.oir e which I tranBrnitted to the bus si an iristry Po;-eirn Affairs, relative to various questions connected v-ith telegraph lines in Persia. I spoke to bonsieur Tcharykoff yesterday on the subject, and he told me that the Russian Government ayreed with all he proposals which were put forward in the aide-mono t *~e. They \/ould, however, like 'hat tne con dition referring to the sole enployr.cnt of Persian and British signallers and officials on the Arabia an tele graph lines should be modified so as to permit of Russians hein: admitted as airnallers should the necessity arise. Hons let ir T char y k off remarked, that it was posniolc in th future that Russian trade in Southern Persia ni^ht dove- lope, and l f night then be of advantage if there were Russian signallers at certain points on the lines. He observed that the lin's were neither in the British nor in the Russian zones, and therefore he hoped that no difficulty would be made in meeting this request. I told him that I woi Id enquire of you. I trust that it nay be found possible to grant the -equest of the Russian Government, as I doubt if it will be acted uyoh for some time The tirlr Hon. Sir R. Grey, Bart. '.P.time, and I inarinr that it would be rerarded as a con- pi iment • Monsieur Ycharykoff further said that the Hussian Government -hourht that the negotiations as to the ex change of the telerraph lines between Tehran and Meshed and Xhaf and ' asratabad should be kept distinct from the discussions on the other questions. The above were J he only modifications which the Hussian Government would propose to the aide-memoire which I had communicated. He hoped to send rm a reply in writing in a day ot' two. I have the honour to be, With the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedient, humble ServantW?3 r ' %cu ^ AIBE-l^HOIR^. H.I .Embassy would wish to recur to the question of tele graph lines in Persia, and to explain that since the date of the aide-memoire which H.' .Eribass- had the honour to c mmunicate to the Imperial ? 'ir:istry for Eoreirn Affairs on Sept. 20th ., 1908, and to which a reply is still awaited, certain fresh el s hare 'been introduced on Whlca II.It.Embassy would he glad to have the opinion of the Imperial Russian Government* There have been already hefoe the I perial Russian Government:-(1) the extension of the existing British telegraph concession to 1945; (2) thf transfer to the Irqierial Russian Govern ment of the rights over the Teheran-Khanikin telegraph line, and (3) the exchange of the telegraph lines between J Teheran and lie shed and between Khaf and tasra- , tabad. 'meMttrrrt elements of which mention has been mane art the following. HHie Persian Government are anxious to Improve and repair the telegraph linee In Arab! 8 tan, ard the Persian Telegraph Department not tavuv' the req; isi e funds have applied to the Indo-European telegraph Depart- Jl ment to ascertain if that Department would be prepared to carry out the necessary works and to take control of the lines. The Indo-European Telegraph Department vould rot be unwilling to meet the,wishes of the Persian Telegraph Department, on the condition:- 1. That the control should Iasi till 19 . 2. That it should be permitted o employ 1 \{ ■ . rrayhists of the Indo- Tt 'uropean Telerraph Bepart- ner at telegraph offices at i ohammeraii, hwaz, arc?, at the station on the Tehran-Bushire line to wi.i ha Arable fan lined tmy be q d. 5. That permission he accorded to connect the Arab!stan 11ne to the Tehran-Bushire line f 0 ' the purposes cf through working# 4. That permission be accorded to erect a second wire fo* the use of the Indo)European Tel Bept* should this be desired durinr the period of l 4 ' &amp; control. I # Tha a guarantee he riven bp the Persian Tovt. that, rh fh the exception of the employes of the Indo-European Tel. Dept., only Persian subjects will be employed in the telegraph offices and on the lines. ’he replacing of the wooden posts at present in r.sc b. iron posts, and the general I ? and upkeep the 1 would, it is calculated, entail an initial rrr^r^e o about i’fOOO and an annual expenditure of about . fOu. H.' •Embassy would wish to point out that it is deeiraule tliat the question of control over the Araoistan Imeu Bhovld settled as soon as possible, so as to excl’ide - he influence of any third Power in the telegraph syst.e: of Arab istan. At the same time the opportunity should not be of existin-r: telegrapli concessions to I'M ; and K. rba-sor considersconsiders that the extension of the concessions should be connected ith the acceptance by the Indo-European Tel. hept. of the proposal nade to it by the Persian Tel. Dept. H*. c , .Embassy s non Id add that the former Department would be prepared to make an advance to the Persian Tel. Dept, of ten years* rental of the Central Persian Telegraph,- or £10.000. The prolongation of the concessions to jo m .would of course apply also to the Tehran-Khanikin line, ||the rights over which will be transferred to the Imperial iRussian Government • The other fresh element is a proposal which has been made by the Persian Ministry 6f Telegraphs to the Indo- European Tel. Dept♦ to erect a second wire from Tehran to Shallrud. In view of the impending transfer to the Imperi al mian overmen' the sontrol or y v the Tehran** Me shed line, and also to the fact that the line is within the Russian sphere, the British Government wish this proposal to remain in abevance until the transfer has been effect ed, when the Imperial .Russian Government will be able to UrCi&lt;. consider whether they would wish to erect the second liiae. H.lw.Embassy would express the earnest hope that all these questions should now be arranged with as little delay as possible, as a postponement of their settlement mav lead to inconveniences and difficul’ies later.N o / / i [This Document is jjhe Property of His BrifauiniA/iyr^y, Gow PERSIA. Pi* CONFIDENTIAL. &gt; /$v- - -k S' \ tfc\ d' ( y [January 13.] Section 5. Sir Edward Grey to Sir A. Nicolson. [44857] No. 1. (No. 16.) Slr ’ WITH reference to your telegram No. 290, ELeLncfthe accompanying copy of a letter, dated the 22nd December, 1908, from the India Office respecting the steps to be taken to secure the control of the Arabistan telegraph hne Telegraph De^nk ^ “ ° n ° f Conc6ssio “ s of ^European In view of the small amount of financial assistance to the Persian Government which is involved I do not consider that an advance of 10,000h to the Persian Government need be regarded as inconsistent with the policy of His Maiestv’s Govern ment m regard to Persian finance. . I W accordingly to request your Excellency to inquire whether the procedure indicated m the Memorandum of the Director-in-chief of the Indo-European Telegraph Department meets with the concurrence of the Russian Government. ^ ^ I am, &amp;c. (Signed) E. GREY. [2088 n —5] h jl (hhi 1 iNote on Sir G,Barclay»s telegram Ho.423, dated 3th December 1908, and Sir A.Mcolson’s telegram No.290 dated 9th December 1908. From the information I have received from ray Depart ment the position appears to he that the Persian Government are pressing their Minister of Telegraphs to provide efficient telegraph lines in Arab is tan, that he represented that this cannot be done unless iron standards are erected on the lines, and that he asked his Government to supply funds to purchase the iron standards required* To this demand the Persian Government replied that it could not afford at present to give the money the Minister of Telegraphs asked for, and that in the meantime the wooden post lines were to be repaired by him. In an inter view v/ith the Director of Telegraphs the Minister stated he thought he could provide 10,000 krans, about £190 for this purpose. To get rid of his responsibilities in the matter the Minister is anxious to have the control of the lines transferred to the Indo-European Telegraph Department. Sir G.Barclay^ telegram states that this offer to transfer the control will probably be made shortly, and that the Shah desires the gradual replacement of the wooden posts by iron. The telegram further states that Mr .Barker, the Director of Telegraphs, suggests that this offer might be used for obtaining the prolongation of the British telegraph concessions in Persia up to 1945, by our demanding this in return for our services in reconstructing and maintaining the Arabistan telegraph lines. * 2.2. In a memorandum, dated 25th April 1907, to the Politi cal Department, i pointed out that in 1891 we had paid £5000 to the Shah, and had made a present of the value of £500 to the Prime Minister, for the renewal up to 1925 of our two con cessions of 1368 and 1372. I suggested that similar amounts might he offered for the renewal of these concessions up to 1945, and that for the renewal of the Central Persia line concession the annual payment of the minimum rental of £1000 might be anticipated by the payment in advance of the next ten years’ rental, that is by the paynent of £10,000 in one sum. I understand these suggestions were approved at the time. Por the renewal of its concession to 1945 the Indo-European Telegraph Company advanced £40,000 to the late Shah as a loan to bear interest. 3, It may be that for political reasons the direct payment of a large sum of money to the Shah may now not be approved of, and that such a payment could not be made while the present conditions of government last in Persia. These unsatisfactory conditions may continue for years, and therefore no progress would be made towards obtaining the renewal of the concessions, and if eventually the Shah had to rule with a constitutional Assembly, it is probable the Assembly would not allow the concessions to be renewed. Put tne taking over of the control of the Arabistan lines would allow of the offer of an indirect form of payment for the prolongation of our telegraph concessions. The arrangement, as i‘&gt; stands at p » is that in taking over these lines we are prepared to spend £300 in a survey of the lines with any temporary repairs tnat can be effected, £1000 in permanent repairs later, and £600 yearn year in maintaining the lines. Jn this arrangement there was no intention of providing iron standards for erection on the D lines. It appears however that the Shah is desirous that the lines$&amp;ould 'be made permanent with iron posts. If therefore the question of the prolongation of the concessions can he linked with the question of taking over the control of the Arahistan lines, the offer might he made that, in addition to the expenditure shewn above, we would he prepared to supply on these lines, free of charge to the Persian Government, iron posts and their fittings to a cost of £5000, provided all our telegraph concessions, along with our control of the Arahistan lines, were prolonged to 1945. It will he seen that the expen diture of £5000 proposed is the amount it was intended to offer to the Shah, hut it would he of more advantage to us that this amount should he expended on the Arahistan lines than that it should he presented to the Shah. 4 t Should there he no objection to the direct payment to the shah of amounts, as shewn in the second paragraph of this note, then the question of the prolongation of the concessions could he kept apart from that of the transfer of control of the Arahistan lines, more especially, as pointed out by Sir A.lUcol- son in his telegram, if the combination of the two questions should cause confusion in the minds of the Russian Government. If a direct payment be not approved, then the transfer of con trol of the Arabistan lines gives an opportunity of offering an indirect payment for the prolongation of the concessions. The telegraph rights over the Teheran-Khanikin line would be extended to fa.(■■■—— to 1945 if our telegraph concessions were renewed to that date, ^so that it would appear to he to the advantage of Russia to accept our combining the questions of the Arabiatan lines and the prolongation of the concessions^ if progress cannot be made with regard to the latter question in any other way* 5. It is very important both for British and Russian interests that our telegraph concessions should be renewed, and I think it will be found that to bring this about it will be necessary to allow money to pass* This might be arranged as a telegraph matter by informing the Persian Minister of Tele graphs that, if he can bring about the prolongation of the con cessions and the transfer of control of the Arabistan lines on the terms shewn in the third paragraph of this note, the Indo- European Telegraph Department would be prepared to advance him for the purposes of his Administration, subject to the sanction of the Persian Government, the minimum rental due by the De partment on account of the Central Persia line foi the next ten years. The advance would be a Departmental matter between the two telegraph administrations and how this money was even tually employed would not be our concern* Sir G. Barclay asks what special stipulations are desired in regard to the Arabistan lines. These stipulations might be as follows- (a) The transfer of control up to 194o. (•b) Permission to employ telegraphists of the Indo-Euro pean Telegraph Pepartment at telegraph offices in Mohammerah, Ahwaz, and at the station on the Teheran-pushire line to whichwhicn the A^abistan line may be connected. (c) Permission to connect the Arabistan line to the Teheran-Biashire line for purposes of through working. (d) Permission for the Indo-European Telegraph Department to erect a second wire for its own use should this be desired during the period of its control. (e) Guarantee from the Persian Government that { with the exception of employes of the Indo-European Telegraph De partment required for the purposes of control^it will allow the employment in the telegraph offices and on the lines of Persian subjects only. 14th December 1908.Iii any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. 42912. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. [mrnadiate. Sir:- ^ ^ { ‘ ; 9C8 k I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you the accompanying copies of telegrams, as marked in the margin, from His Majesty's Ambassador at St. Petersburg and His Majesty's Minister at Tehran res pecting Persian telegraphs. I am to request that Sir E. Grey may be furnished with the observations of the Secretary of State for India upon the subject as soon as possible. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, / IaajxImA' The Under Secretary of State, India Office.of reconstr lohammera. gradual rep according ti ' obtaining pi in return h our Concess Ibanikin ri; Department and IM-l ths finally it would be extension ol !f His as to limit c Depart: occasion ar stipulations desirable. I have yonrviews. (Sent t6/Fz? CONFIDENTIAL. 0 geiwtS' ,9MC'303 L, K Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received December 8, 2T5 p.m.) Tehran, December 8, 1908, 2-30 p.m. (No. 423.) YOUR telegram No. 324. As the result of the negotiations, Indo-European Telegraph Department will probably shortly receive from Minister of Telegraphs proposal for it to assume control of reconstruction and maintenance of Arabistan telegraph line—Borasjun to Mohammerah and Ahwaz to Dizful. Department is informed that Shah desires gradual replacement of wooden posts by iron, which will cost from 6,000Z. to 14,000b according to the class used. Barker suggests that this is a good opportunity for obtaining prolongation to 1945 of our telegraph Concessions, which we might demand in return for our services in Arabistan, which would include partial or complete supplies of posts and our annual share in the expenses of maintenance of line. It was originally proposed to handle those two questions together (see your despatch No. 161 of last year), though later Russia was told that the prolongation of our Concessions must be treated simultaneously with the transfer of our Tehran- Khanikin rights. She would, of course, benefit by the prolongation of these rights. Possibly our demand for the prolongation may retard agreement with the Persian Government as to the details of control over Arabistan line, but the demand need not be made until Persian Government has finally committed itself to the principle of Department’s control. At a pinch negotiations for the exchange of the Tehran-Meshed and Khaf-Nasratabad line might be resumed directly after Persian Government has thus finally committed itself, but as the exchange negotiations threaten to be difficult it would be better, if possible, to postpone their resumption until we have secured the extension of the Concessions. If His Majesty’s Government concur in the above suggestion, please inform me as to limit of the assistance towards cost of iron posts which may be offered in return for prolongation of Concessions. Department propose to stipulate for the erection of a wire for its own use should occasion arise, jand that it shall retain control till 1945. Are any other special stipulations desired ? In view of the possible changes of Ministry, early reply is desirable. I have not thought it desirable to sound Russian Charge d’Affaires before learning your view^s. (Sent to St. Petersburg!!.) ■ \i jCONFIDENTIAL. Sir A. Shcolson to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received December 9, 5 p.M.) ^ 0 'pFK«ir4W + 1 i, o- n -d ,^1 -Drifter 9, 1908, 3-59 p.M. i: lliKblAJN telegraphs. Sir G. Barclay’s telegram No. 423. I am afraid that we shall cause confusion in the minds of the Russian Government ]. we com »me prolongation of Concession with the question of Arabistan telegraph line as it was understood m the spring of this year that the prolongation should he treated with the Khanikm telegraph rights, but that exchange of Meshed-Seistan me should have priority. Arabistan line is a new matter, in regard to which we have dealt independently of the Russian Government. I am still awiating the views of the Russian Government in regard to Khanikin line (please see Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs’ letter of 3rd March (o.s.)), and I also am waiting for the reply to my last Memorandum in respect to the exchange of the telegraph lines. I would suggest that the Russian Government should be informed either through the Russian Ambassador in London or through me of discussions with Persian authorities in regard to Arabistan lines, and that they be requested to give us their views as to the other two questions, and also be asked to make no difficulty as to the prolongation of the telegraph Concessions.tritannic Majesty's Government.] PERSIA. [February 20.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 8. [5944] No. 1. India Office to Foreign Office.—{Received February 20.) India Office, February 18, 1908. Sir, IN reply to your letter dated the 5th instant, I am directed by Mr Secretary Morley to inclose a copy of a Minute by the Director-in-chief of the Indo-European Telegraph Department, as to the cost involved in the proposal to obtain from the Persian Government the control by the Department of the telegraph line from Borasiun to Mohammerah. It will be seen that the survey of the line and its temporary repairs (if they can be effected) are estimated to cost some 4,500 rupees (300/.), and more permanent repairs, to be carried out later, some 15,000 rupees (1,000/.). The cost of maintenance of the line, when in order, is estimated at 9,000 rupees (600/.) a-year. THE Foreign Office ask for information as to the approximate cost of the proposed’ survey and temporary repair of the line from Borasjun to Mohammerah. The length of this line is believed to be about 331 miles. As regards temporary repairs, the only thing that could be done would be to buy poles locally, if they can be purchased locally, and connect up the wire where it is broken. If there is no spare wire along the line to repair the breaks, and if poles cannot be obtained, this would put a stop to temporary repairs. I think the survey of the line and temporary repairs, if they can be effected, would cost about 4,500 rupees (300/.). There would also be the more permanent repairs, to be carried out later ; but until a survey has been made it is impossible to estimate what these would cost. I should say that an expenditure of some 15,000 rupees (1,000/.) would be required for the purpose. As to the cost of maintenance, when the line had been put in order, I estimate it would come to 9,000 rupees (600/.) per annum. This estimate is for maintaining the line much as the Meshed line is maintained at present. commenced on an early date, as the summer heat in the districts through which the line passes is very great, making outdoor work almost impracticable. February 7, 1908. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) A. GODLEY. Inclosure in No. 1. Minute by Mr. Kirk. I desire particularly to point out that, if the survey is to take place, it should be [2836 u — 8][This Deoament is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Gevernm«nt] WITH reference to my letter of the 4th June last, relative to the extension of British telegraph concessions in Persia, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Ambassador to St. Petersburgh,* forwarding copy of an aide-memoire handed to him by the Russian Minister of Foreign Affairs, intimating the acceptance of his Government in principle of the cession to them of the rights exercised by His Majesty’s Government over the Tehran-Khanikin telegraph line, and stating that they have no objection to the prolongation for 20 years of the concessions for the Tehran-Bushire, Jask-Gwaddar, and Kachan-Bohat lines. Sir E. Grey would be glad to be informed whether Mr. Secretary Morley would wish that instructions should he sent to His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran to approach the Persian Government with a view to obtain the renewal of these concessions. Before sending such instructions it would he necessary to await the exchange of ratifications of the Anglo-Russian Convention, and Sir E. Grey would further propose to leave to Sir C. Spring-Rice’s discretion the choice of the best moment for acting on them. PERSIA. [September 13.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1, [29521] No. 1. Foreign Office to India Office. Sir, Foreign Officey September 13, 1907. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) LOUIS MALLET. * Sir A. Nicolson, No. 428, August 26, 1907. [2633 n —1]V. [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] [B] PERSIA. No. 1. - ioNPIDENTIAL. [21776] Sir A. Ni'colson to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received July 2.) g| r ^ St. Petersburgh, June 25, 1907. IN accordance with the instructions conveyed to me in your telegram No. 90 of the 21st instant, I handed yesterday to M. Isvolsky an aide-memoire, of which I have the honour to inclose a copy, relative to the question of the prolongation for twenty years of the Concessions of certain British telegraph lines in Persia. His Excellency said that he would look into the matter and give me a reply later. 1 nQArp rvC* (Signed) ’ A. NICOLSON. Inclosure in No. 1. Aide-me'moire communicated by Sir A. Nicolson to M. Isvolsky. HIS Maiesty’s Embassy had the honour to receive the aide-memoire dated the 16th (29th) Mav, in which the Imperial Ministry for Foreign Affairs raised certain obiections to an application being now made to the Persian Government for the prolongation for twenty years of the Concessions of the telegraph lines from Tehran to Bushire, from Jask to Gwaddnr, and of the Central Persian telegraph line to Robat. His Maiesty’s Embassy would beg leave to state that His Majesty s Government always considered that the maintenance of existing Concessions as provided tor m Article III of the draft Convention, implied their renewal if the Persian Government agreed thereto, and this view His Majesty’s Government still maintain in principle. His Maiesty’s Em bassy is, however, in a position to make the following proposal as a solution of the difficulty, viz., that the Imperial Russian Government shou d not obi'ect to the renewal of the above-mentioned Concessions, and m return His Maj s y Government would surrender to the Imperial Russian Government their rights over the Tehran-Khanikin line. . -i • x xr + i i In order to avoid introducing questions relative to these telegraph lines into discussions on the draft Convention, His Majesty’s Embassy is authorized to propose to the Imperial Russian Government that the seat of the negotiations respecting the telegraph questions might be conveniently transferred to London, and, if the Imperial Government see no objection, that the Russian Ambassa or m on 011 e V fhn&lt;?p to conduct them. These negotiations could be carried on concurrently mth those at St. Petersburgh respecting the draft Convention, m order that both may be simultaneously concluded. St. Petersburgh, June 10 (23), 1907. [2561 b—2] m[This Doenment is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's GovernmA»&gt;+ ] PERSIA. [May 9.] CONEIDENTIAL. Section 1, [15166] No. 1. India Office to Foreign Office.—(Received May 9.) India Office, May 8, 1907. WITH reference to Sir F. Campbell’s letter dated the 19th April, 1907, relative to the question of renewing the contracts of the Indo-European Telegraph Depart ment in Persia, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Morley to forward herewith, to be laid before the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, copy of a Memorandum on the subject by the Director-in-chief of the Department. Mr. Morley agrees generally in the views expressed by Mr. Kirk, and he Tvould propose, subject to Sir E. Grey’s concurrence, that His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran should be instructed, in accordance wdth the suggestion made in his telegram of the 17th April, to address the Persian Government in the sense of the 7th paragraph of Mr. Kirk’s note, the Russian Government being informed of any action that may be taken in the matter. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) A. GODLEY. Inclosure in No. 1. Memorandum on the Renewal of the British Telegraph Conventions with Persia. ON the 16th March last I wrote to the Director of Telegraphs at Tehran telling him that the Indo-European Telegraph Company had arranged in June 1906 with the Persian Government that the term of its telegraph Concession, which ran to 1925, should be extended for a further period of twenty years up to 1945. I pointed out that in lb91, after this Company obtained the extension of its Concession from 1905 to 1925, we also w^ent to the Persian Gevernment to have the British telegraph Concessions renewed for the same period, and that this was duly arranged. He vas instructed to remind the British Minister at Tehran of what had taken place regarding the renewal of the British Concessions up to 1925, this action being taken in order that what happened on the last occasion of the renewal of the Company s Concession might not escape attention on this. # . . , 2. From the telegram of the 17th instant that has been received from the British Minister at Tehran it would appear that the present time may prove to be favourable for obtaining an extension of the British telegraph Concessions, as there wou id to be a payment to make for their renewal, and money is very badly wanted by the Persian Government. In order to obtain the renewal of these Concessions in IbiK a present of 5,000/. was made to the Shah, and a watch of the value of 500/. was given to the Persian Prime Minister, this expenditure being debited to the capital account of the Indo-European Telegraph Department. At the same time the Persian 1 mis ei of Telegraphs was made a K.C.I.E. for his services in the matter. 3. In 1891 we obtained the extension from 1905 to 1925 of the two following Conventions:— (1.) The Convention, dated the 2nd April, 1868, for the construction and working of the coast-line from the Persian frontier near Gwadur to Jask. (2.) The Convention of the 2nd December, 1872, for the working of the telegraph line from Tehran to Bushire. Since 1891 another Telegraph Convention has been entered into, dated the 16th ;ust, 1901, for the construction and maintenance of the Centm lersia me, dically a telegraph line from Tehran to Robat on the Indian frontier. This vention remains in force until 1925, or for such longer period as the debt due by sia for the construction of the line remains unpaid. [2474 i —1]2 4. It is necessary for the proper consideration of the British position as regards telegraphs in Bersia to show what would happen if the extension of these three Conventions beyond 1925 cannot be arranged. Taking first the Jask Convention of 1868, its non-renewal would mean the loss to the Persian Government of an annual royalty of 3,000 tomans, equivalent at present to about 500/. The line would be of no use to the Persian Government, as it is a detached land line along the coast, and is used as an alternative to a cable. The Persian Government may therefore be expected to extend the Concession for this line, as there is nothing to be gained by not doing so, ▼ and its non-renewal means a direct loss of revenue. Coming to the Convention of 1872 for the working of the Tehran-Bushire line, should the renewal of it beyond 1925 not be granted, the Persian Government would be forced, under their Agreements with the Indo-European Telegraph Company, to hand over this section of the line to the Company, and for doing this they would receive no payment nor compensation of any kind. It is therefore to the advantage of the Persian Government to renew the Concession of the British Telegraph Department, if they can obtain a payment for doing so. It is also to the interest of the British Government that the Concession should be renewed, because the withdrawal of the British Department from this section of line would mean a loss of prestige and inlluence to the British Government. At the same time, as the Company that would take over the line is in Persia under the official protection of the Bussian Government, there would be an increase of Bussian influence in a part of the country where previously British influence had prevailed. 5. The Convention of 1901 regarding the Central Persia line extends to 1925, or for such longer period as the Persian Government may take to pay off the debt for its construction. This debt under the arrangement contained in the Convention would be paid olf in thirty-three and a-quarter years from the completion of the line, and as the line will be completed this year the debt would be cleared off in 1940. It is laid down in the Convention that in 1925, or later, when the debt has been paid off, the Convention may, if necessary, be renewed or revised. It would seem, therefore, that if the Persian Government did not agree to the necessity of its renewal, the Convention would come to an end, and the line would have to be handed over to that Government to be worked by the Persian Administration, or by any one that the Government chose to appoint. This freedom of action might possibly result in arrangements being made that would seriously affect British interests. To explain how this might be done it has to be borne in mind that the Convention of 1872 allows the Indo-European Telegraph Department to resume charge of the section of line between Tehran and Khanikin, a town on the Persian frontier not far from Bagdad. This Concession would come to an end with the termination of the Conven tion of 1872 in 1925, and it does not become transferable to the Indo-European Telegraph Company under its Agreements like the charge of the Tehran-Bushire line does. This Company, recognizing the value of the Concession, has obtained a document from the Persian Government, in which it is told that there is no objection to the Company coming to an understanding with the British Government as to taking over and working this section of line. The document does not appear actually to bind the Persian Government to allow the transfer of the line, if it took place, to remain in force for the term of the Company’s Agreements—that is, up to 1945—so that, should the British Concession for the Tehran-Bushire line come to an end in 1925, the Concession for the working of the Tehran-Khanikin section w’ould apparently end at the same time, whether the British Department or the Company then possessed it. In this case, in 1925 the Persian Government could dispose of the Tehran- Khanikin line Concession in any w r ay they chose. It is knowm that the German Telegraph Administration has been making inquiries regarding this line. It is possible that the Germans might obtain control of the line in 1925. It has been shown that the British Concession for the Central Persia line might be terminated at the same time, so that the Germans, even if they had to advance money to pay off any debt remaining on the Central Persia line, might obtain for themselves the Concession for working this line also from that time. We should then have the line from Bagdad through Tehran to the Indian frontier at itobat being worked under German control, which would be a very undesirable state of affairs as far as British interests are concerned. 6. I have shown that it w r ould he to the interest of the Persian Government, for financial reasons, to renew' the British Concessions of 1868 and 1872, and that it is advisable in British interests that they should be renewed, as also the Concession of 1901 for the Central Persia line. But we shall have to pay for these renewals, and the question is what should be paid. In 1891 w r e paid 5,000/. to the Shah, and gaveWipB a present of the value of 500/. to the Prime Minister for the renewal of two Concessions. If the grant of the renewal of these two Concessions still rests entirely with the Shah—of which there would seem to he some doubt, since such matters may require the consent of his Parliament—similar amounts as on the last occasion might be 1 offered for a renewal of the two Concessions. Por the third Concession, relating to the Central Persia line, we have under the Convention to pay 1 per cent, on the capital expended on construction of the line subject to a minimum of 1,000/. per —annum. When the account for the construction of the line is made up, this l per cent, will be more than 1,000/., though how much more it is impossible to say until the accounts are made up. Por the renewal of this Concession we might anticipate the annual pavment of 1,000/. to the Persian Government, and pay 10,000/. at once as an advance, being the equivalent of ten annual payments. The difference between 1,000/. and the sum that 1 per cent, on the capital cost of the line will amount to will also be paid yearly to the Persian Government for the same tune. The Indo-European Telegraph Company advanced 40,000/. for the late renewal of its Concession to 1945, but this advance has to bear interest. I have proposed an advance of 10,000/., but if a smaller advance should be accepted so much the better 7. When the question of these renewals is raised with the Persian Government 1, might be pointed out that, as they have renewed the Company’s Concession for twenty years, it will be according to their previous custom if they now renew the British Conventions for the same term, and that this is our reason for applying for them. It could be explained that the 186S Convention provides the Persian Government with a royalty of 3,000 tomans, and that the non-renewal of the 1872 Convention would mean the handing over to the Indo-European Telegraph Company of the Tehran-Bushire line without payment of any kind, p to the Central Persia line it could be pointed out that it has been constructed, as shown in the Convention relating to it, for an alternative line to the Tehran-Bushire one, so that it is only reasonable and right that the Conventions for the two sections it limit of time. As to the payments or advances to be seems to me they will have to he arranged with reference to the authority in Bersia, who can now sanction them. If this should prove to be the bhah alone, die mat 11 will probably be more easily carried out. (signed) H. A. KIRK. April 25, 1907.Minute Puper, Register No. ( Secret Department Letter from 'tv Q Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. . Undersecretary vv Secretary of State 17- n Under Secretary Secretary of State U SUBJECT. Copy to 'Pxfrl^ 21 hrm* I £ 0*1 hlt.trho. Tm 1CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran), (No 321.) Foreign Office, November 21,1908, 3 p.m. EXCHANGE of telegraphs. Your telegram Nor374. I approve your action, provided the Ahwaz-Borasjun negotiations are not indefinitely prolonged. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 609.) / ( 4 $U04 L In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No , 39755. and address — The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. rr Immediate. \ « &amp; 1 'NOV 1903 £ Foreign Office November 16th, 1908. Sir:- I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to trans- j| mit to you, to be laid before the Secretary of State for India, the accompanying copy of a telegram, dated 111 November 14th, from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran, respecting the proposed exchange of the Meshed-Seistan and Meshed-Tehran telegraph lines. I am also to enclose the draft of a telegram which subject to the concurrence of Lord Morley, Sir * i 1 E. Grey proposes to send to Sir G. Barclay in reply. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office.Telegram to Sir G. Barclay. Foreign Office, November 1908. Exchange of Telegraphs. Your telegram No.374. I approve your action, provided the Ahwaz-Boras- jun negotiations are not indefinitely prolonged.CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 14, 12*35 P.M.) (No. 374.) Tehran, November 14, 1908, 1*30 P.M. RUSSIAN Minister under instructions suggested to me to-day that the two telegraph Directors might now reopen negotiations respecting the exchange^ of lines. Mr. Barker’s return, he thought, made the moment opportune. I told hiro confi dentially that our Department was trying to obtain the consent of the Minister of Telegraphs to their undertaking the repair of the Ahwaz Borasjun line, and I thought that it would prejudice the success of these negotiations, which are proceeding smoothly, if the Department were to treat the two questions simultaneously. This is Mr. Barker’s view. Russian Minister said he would telegraph in this sense to his Government. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh.)In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. 32036. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. onfldsntlal. I am directed 'by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith decypher of a telegram from His Majes ty’s Charge d*Affaires at Tehran relative to the ques tion of telegraph lines in Persia together with copy of a telegram which he has addressed to Mr. Marling in reply to his communication. Viscount Morley will observe, from a perusal of the latter message, that Sir E. Grey is of opinion that the completion of the negotiations having for their object the acquisition by His Majesty’s Govern ment of the control of the Ahwaz-Borasjun-Moharamera line is of greater importance to British interests than the consent of the Persian Government to the proposed exchange of control with Russia and that the solution The Under Secretary of State India Office.r the lines indicated. of the former question should he expedited even at the cost of some delay in that of the latter. I am accordingly to ask that, if Lord Morley con curs in this view, he will cause instructions to he sent to the Director of the Indo-European Telegraph Department at Tehran to conduct his negotiations on I am. Your most obedient, humble Servant, /J 1 . 1 ' •—Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling {Tehran). (No. 262.) Foreign Office, September 18, 1908, 12'50 p.m. ' EXCHANGE of telegraphs and acquisition of control of Ahwaz line. Your telegram No. 307. . ,, Latter question is, from our point of view, the more important, and we should elo all we can to hasten its satisfactory solution even at the cost of some delay to the othei question, which Russian Government are anxious to expedite. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 369.) ^ J ^ 709—158] ■-jL ; •' yS *•&gt;CONFIDENTIAL h ^5 0 Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 14, 8'45 P.M.) (No 307 ) Tehran, September 14, 1908, 5-30 p.m. YOTTR tplporam No 251 : Exchange of telegraphs. . Icting Superintendent of Indo-European Telegraph Department sounded Minister n f Telporanhs recently, hut found him unwilling to agree. . Russian Minister thinks, however, that matter could be carried thioug . Onlv obSon I can s^e is that to move at present may jeopardize and J 11 certainly delay negotiations for Ahwaz line, about which Superintendent is mclmec o be hopeful. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh.) 7699—363]</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003bf_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/106</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003bf</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/106</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 3414/1906 Pt 3 'Persia: telegraphs; exchange of telegraphs with Russia and Anglo-Persian convention for improvement of Arabistan telegraphs'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1908/1911</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-03-24T11:52:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (236 folios)</extent><extent>The subject3414 (Persia: telegraphs) consists of 5 volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/104-108. The volumes are divided into 5 parts with each part comprising one volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 236; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence discusses the exchange of telegraph lines with Russia.Telegraph lines discussed are the Seistan line; Arabistan telegraphs (Mohammerah-Ahwaz); North Persian line (Tehran-Khanikin and Tehran-Shahrud). The signing and ratification of the Arabistan Telegraph convention is also discussed.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Arabistan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Mohammerah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Telegraph lines</topic></subject><subject><topic>Telegraphs</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003bf#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>