<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00004a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T08:14:28.069Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">i . T«ltgraia Fr oai To Inter* His Majesty's iinbaasador, Ba^ad. Secretary of State for Foreign Affaire, London* o.58 Repeated ^)ated 7 th received 8 th Far ah i &gt;39. Ills Majesty's ®iwinter, Jedda. ITo.Xl Political Resident, Bushire. ^o*i3 itary area 3uri told me this morning that he had declaration of military law over Hina id i taken advantage of 4WWm / oi introduction of a press censor (which has now been withdrawn) to remind - in , forcibly that as worasanaer in fhie.t' of army Hie ajesty could not allow himself in matter of these broadcasts license which was denied to others. King had promised to conform to this point of view &amp;nd turi was certain that there would be no more objectionable broadcasts* T cold uri that I would transmit his assurance* But I must point out first that it was no more h than repeat!on of assurance he had already given me on '•'arch let (see my telegram : * : o.48) which had turned out to be worthless) and it was a poor look out if lug's attitude could only be kept within bounds by fortuitous and artificial arguments such as these* I insisted that I .'itual regard h&amp;ahid .(-dll as responsible* l added that X was seeing ' iug tomorrow and intended to speak frankly* intereon0 Telegram Inter. From His Majesty's Ambassador, Bagdad. To H.M. Secretary of state for Toreign London. Ho. 62 Repeated H.M. Minister, Jedda. Ho.12 Political Resident, Bushire. Ho. 14 Dated and received 9th March 1939. telegram No*58. Aa I anticipate! ICing this morning entirely collapsed ae soon as I mentioned Kuwait. Hie Majesty 1 s very in-coiierent explanations were to the effect that he had no intention of attacking Kuwait but wished only to egg on its Ruler to concede liberal institutions. I asked fhether His M&amp;Jssty really imagined Iraq could offer herself aa an example at the present time* I had repeatedly warned him of the impropriety of using his private trans mitting set for propaganda of any kind and abuse was aggravated when in view of this qaeetion propaganda was of nature to cause ns annoyance if not embarrassment. I went on to insist that His Majesty should disclose his real reason for sponsoring these attacks. King then said ^j?oreigninfluences to which his broadcasts referred were Persian and that both he and his Government were seriously concerned over influx of Persians into Kuwait which they regard as ? endangering Iraq*® communications in the event of war. I replied that we could be trusted to look after that our selves* I added, that while his last Gevernsient had shown gome interest in this question and while I had obtained same information on the subject to communicate to them (your telegram Ho.3 Having) present Government -viTL lt; had /sham no interest in the subject whatever and I had not therefore communicated the information. His Majesty must surely realise that matters of this kind were better handled through diplomatic channel than in the unfortunate manner which .tie had selected. King professed reat regret and made fullest promises of amendment. 2feadless to say none of these is of any value whatsoever. PetersonTelegram From To Repeated I&gt;ated the Inter. His Majesty's Ambassador, Baghdad. . „ *10 ‘ His Majesty 8 oeoretary of ^&gt;tate for foreign Affairs, London. Ho.66 (?) Political Resident, Bushire. No.16. His Majesty’s Minister, Jedda. No. 11. 12th and reoeived the 13th March 1939. telegram No.66. Nuri called today to press suggestion he had advanced last night at King’s request to the effect that I should urge Shaikh and his advisors to refrain from punitive action pending inauguration of process of conoiliaticn set forth in my telegrajfi under reference. I refused to do anything of the kind and made it clear that events in Kuwait were in evitably the outcome of malicious propaganda from here and particularly of palace broadcast. Nuri and X am to see His Majesty as scon as possible and at Hurl’s suggestion we will probably tell His Majesty that it has been decided to withcld all telegrams addressed to paiaoe unit these telegrams appear main cause of misohie^ since His Majesty is unable to resist ? flattarx which they contain. PETERSON•r l &amp; Telegram 3 Political Heaident, ’Bughire. To Secretary of State for India, London He peated Government of India, New Delhi. H.M. Ambassador, Bagdad. H.IC, Minister, Jedda. Copy by post to Political igent, Kuwait. No. 130 Dated the 14th March 1939 Important My telegram No.122 of lith March. .jhaikn has nominated Advisory Council under Presidency of his cousin Abdulla Salim consisting of four members of Shaikh’s family and nine notables including two members of previous Council. I had instructed Political Agent to inform Shaikh that even though nominated (which was ■Shaikh's own decision) and not elected Council must be a representative body and this it appears to be. and in this connection Ambassador’s attitude towards Iraq Government (vide his telegram No.66 of 12th March to foreign Office) should be most helpful, I have hopes that Kuwait ,5 * Shaikh has received telegram of congrat ulations from Ibn 3aud on his suppression of disorder. 2 . if only Iraqis will leave Kuwait alone, will settle down Br i t c one ulJ Kuwait Receipt @ No lA~fr~ Da lei1 - Telegram yrora -His Majesty*s Ambassador, Baghdad. To Secretary of State for foreign Affairs London. No.78 Political Resident, Bushire, ^ 19 Minister, Jedda 15 Political Agent, Kuwait 5 Dated the 15th and received the 16th March, 1739. My telegram No. 70. King received me in the presence of NURI PASHA this morning. His Majesty began by saying that, on advice of His Prime Minister, he had taken necessary measures to discontinue any broadcast from his private station which could give offence or be represented as propa ganda. At the same time His Majesty had arranged that he should be spared himself from dealing^ with numerous telegrams and messages which were at present directed to him personally. I mentioned that Baghdad State Broadcast station had recently been closed down. Impression created was that His Majesty desired to obtain a monopoly for his own station. This seemed to me most unfortunate and should be remedied. King and Nuri Pasha both assured me that closing of Government station had been due to technical alterations and that it would be reopened on Saturday. (Arrived ?) then told His Majesty that on the strength of these assurances given in presence of his- 2 - his Prime Minister, I was prepared to convey to Your Inrdship His Majesty's earnest hope that there would he no more punitive measures in Kuwait. His Majesty and Prime Minister hoth enquired as to the fate of conciliatory proposals contained in my telegram No.66. I said that these had no doubt necessitated refer^ence to Government of India and that (inundation?) which I feared must he dreadful was that mischief can he made much more quickly than it can he repaired. - Ambassador -GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). Oonfi&amp;entlal — —- [N,B. This it an ORIGIN A L message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on. receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. o/lll Dated Simla New Delhi , the Political Agency, Kuwait 17th March, 19 39 . The Hon'hle the Political Eesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Reference The Shaikh informed me on the 15th that SAYID HAMID an NAQ.rB, a deputy for Basra in the Iraq. Parliament, had written to him to say that he wished to visit him shortly 'to give him all the political information about Baghdad from high quarters’*. 2. The Consul, Basra, informed me privately on the 16th that the Embassy had told him some days ago that HAMID is bringing apologies from NHRI. 3 . I imagine that the 'apologies'* will probably have a sting in the tail. (Sgd.) G. S. de Gaurv Political Agent, Kuwait. {Signature) {Designation) s. 44. MFP—1534 S&amp;P-(M-2835)—24-6-38—10,000.By Air Mail. CONFIDENTIAL P.Z. /3A2 Ktiivait AV 313. ' ' ' INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 41 - Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to by Mail. The Foreiffl i Socrotey-, -Oovernmcnt of India. The Political Recidontr in the Pciftian Gulfr o ruMJtJA 3681CONFIDENTIAL. CONFIDENTIAL No. 226-3 of 1939. 1 13 Fun-ait, Fee ■[ I No Dale. I Z&amp;j J | The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to I© The Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.....??-.?.^. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Subject. , \a Jedda Savingrara TIo.2 of 20th February 1939. Iraqi Propaganda against Br it ish ijlmbassy , Bagdad Savingram No.^3 of 24th February. Kuwait.COPY 0? TjjjLdlGRAM prom To H.M.Minister The Hon*ble the Political Resident Bushire. J edda No. 2 Dated February 20th, 1.939, Time despatched 13.00. Adiiressed to Foreign Office No.27 repeated to Bagdad No.9 and Saving Cairo No.10 Bushire No.2. Ibn Saud is much worried by broadcasts fr cm Bagdad alleging that Kuwait people desire union with Iraq. He says that he could have engaged in much more effective propaganda for securing union of Kuwait with Saudi Arabia but refrained partly out of friendship for the Shaikh but mainly out of deference to the interests of His Majesty’s Government. 2. I have a feeling that he wants to be assured that the Iraq propaganda does not enjoy approval of His Majesty’s Government. I have given my personal assurance that it does not but your official confirmation would be welcome to him. 3. He is also worried though less acutely about Iraq propaganda regarding Bahrain.'I © COPY 0? TELEGR-AM From T o H.M. Ambaasad or Foreign Office, London Fn clair. By Air Mail ’to F• 0* Uo,22 Saving Bagdad Bate: 24th February,1939 Addressed Foreign Office No.22 Saving repeated to Cairo No.8 Saving, Jedda No.3 Saving, Resident Bushire at Kuwait No.3 Saving. Jedda telegram No.28 to you and ray telegram No. 21 Saving. I think it would be an excellent thing if Ibn Saud were to make representations to Iraqi Government. Peterson; By^ Air Mail. P.Z. / 19 ^ No 27 V CONFfDENTlA L Kuwait R D vceipt INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to by^l 1 - Mail. J Sear Fho Foroiffn Sccrctaiy, Quvcrmncnt ul India. The Political .Resident in the Persian Gblf. 3681ENCLOSURE IN FOREIGN OFFICE COVERING LETTER DATED fc? UhBVBfti [Tnls Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty*^ Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] From SAUDI ARABIA. Decypher. Sir R. Bullard (Jedda). 6th March, 1939, D. R. No. 30. 3. 30 p.m. 5.10 p.m. 6th March, 1939. 6th March, 1939. o • • • A' (.sy tL V— Bagdad telegram No 0 54 of March 4th. According to Yusuf Yasin Bagdad wireless March 5th declared Koweit Council with four abstentions have demanded annexation by Iraq etc. It is evident that Ibn Saud is still restrained from intervention by the fear that His Majesty's G-overnment though disapproving Iraqi action might be forced to fall in with it. I have told Yusuf Yasin that I see no reason why Ibn Saud should not make it clear to Iraq that Saudi Arabia is interested in the maintenance of the position of the Sheikh of Koweit. 2. The chief Mecca newspaper has published a guarded article in which Ibn Saud is shown as supporting the Sheikh of Koweit personally in this matter. After studying it carefully I may telegraph a summary which could be broadcast on March 7th if Bagdad wireless continues the campaign today. Addressed to Foreign Office; repeated to Bagdad telegram No. 11 and Bushire telegram No. 3.CONFIDENTIAL. No^89-S of 1939 | CONFinZKT IA L CONFWESTIAL A “ 1 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. V 2. The Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documeriWM^. . on^y. Bushire Printed letter No.180-3 of British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 15th March, 1939» Reference to previous correspondence: A ■ Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Iraqi propaganda against Kuwait. 1939.I irrom Pol it leal Res ident, Busnire. To Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated His Majesty's ambassador, Bagdad. Copy by post to Government of India, External Affairs Department, Hew Delhi. * rt * * Politioal Agent, Kuwait. No. 135. Dated the 15th March, 1939. Bagdad telegram Ho.66 to Foreign Office of 10th March. I concur with Ambassador * a views i. e. acceptance of one and two but indefinite postponement of three. 2. It will however be for Ghaikh to decide. I tould propose informing him Verbally through Political Agent that His Majesty's Government approve of on© and two but are doubtful about three. fay I approach him on these lines ? 3. Three may appeal to Shaikh's vanity and if it is suggested to him by bearer of letter, and h© accepts, 1 do not see what we can do, - Britconsul. V. L.Telegram Fr □ra To Repeated Copy by post to 3 political Resident, lushire* Secretary o/*Jtate for India, London. His Majesty’s Ambassador, Hagdad. Government of India, Hew Delhi. political Agent, Kuwait. No.14b dated the 31st March 1959. A I4y telegram No. 136 of March loth. For information. Political .Agent, Kuwait, reports that one of the Naqib family has written to Shaikh that he wishes to visit him uhortly. Ghaikh will doubtless hear further privately from this source of Iraqi proposals. BritooneulCONFIDENTIAL. No - 245-S of 1939. i CONFIDENTIAL s t~t;—:— Fulfil ic t't’Cfipt \ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1 His isxcelleficy Sir Maurice Peterson, KOMS., • Hi B Majesty* a Amtasaador,Bagdad. 2 sir Aubrey Metcalfe, KCI 3 . »CSI. ,)IVO., Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs department. Hew Delhi. 3. G. de Gaury Esquire, MC., Political Agent, ICuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). 2, Enclosures are those received under your Printed letters *[os.c/S4, C/104 and c/l05, dated the 8th March anu iSt.i March 1939 renpect ively. r ‘ f British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 2.4th. March.. 1.9.39 Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Letter Ho.244-3 of the 24th March 1939 to R.T.Peel Hsquire, MC.,The India Office, with enclosures. Subject. Iraqi propaganda against Kuwait.•Abdilla an4 Tuauf Ohania ha4, I hear* been promised 'aontracte* for the Xu#&amp;it port eto* by the Iraqi*. * * I am sending a copy of thie letter with encloaurea to Peterson anh tletc&amp;lft* and without* to do ilaury. Yours sincerely. ad. T.C.5*owle * eent under Printed letter ire.343~3 of the 24th Marsh* 1939. •— =Telegram Inter- From To Charge d* Affaires, Baghdad. Political Besident, Bushire. No.21 Poreign Office, London. No. 87 Political Agent, Kuwait. Ho. 7 Dated and received the 24th March, 1939. Your telegram No. 145 to India Office. You may think expediency to advise Shaikh to postpone reception of King Ghazi’s messenger until my representations concerning recent Police incursions into Kuwait and demands of local autho rities for arrears of taxation have Been satisfac torily met. - Houston - Boswall ^0I 1* } CONFltlKSTh'.!.' Kutrui: Receif't NofJ j ^ ’“ZLs^h 3 ° Telegram From To Repeated to R Foreign Office, London. Charge d*Affaires, Baghdad No.87 Political Resident, Bushire Political Agent, Kuwait No. 1 Minister, Jedda. Dated the 24th and received the 25th March, 1939. rt^V Jedda telegram No. 39. I had been on point of informing you that, subject to concurrence of Shaikh of Kuwait (Sir T. Fowle's telegram No. 136 to India Office) first and second points “conciliatory H procedure were acceptable to His Majesty's Government. 2. But if report given in Jedda telegram under reference is correct, there can clearly be no question of this procedure being accepted at present. 3. Please therefore telegraph whether, in your opinion, propaganda has in fact continued to such an extent as to render it undesirable that any enquiries should be addressed to Shaikh. Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsCONFIDENTIAL. 5/ No - 263-3 •Vc 3 ^ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1 , The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affaire Department, . Hew Delhi 2. The Political Agent, Kuwait and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRB. Dated March .1,939. Reference to previous correspondence : To !• Residency Printed Letter Ho*254-3 of 25th Larch 1939. v*. \ ' To 2* Bagdad telegram Ho.91 of 25th March 1939 to the Foreign Office. # if) Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Political Resident’s telegram 2T0.169 of 27th March. Subject. — \ Iraqi propaganda against Kuwait•@ telegram S, to ?r am Political Heaideut, Buehire. Secretary of State for mala, London Repeated Hie Majesty’s Ambassador, Bagdad. Copy by post to SoTernraent of India, external Affaire Department, Sew Delni, and Political ent, ;^await. Ho. 169. Dated tde 27t)a March, 1939. Bagdad telegram Ko.9l to Foreign Office March S5th Meaner of Haqib family at Basrah with letter of regret {Bagdad telegram Ho.66 to Foreign Office *farcn 10th) has now apparently grown into ‘'envoy* frora Bagdad with instructions to offer official advice to iuler of Kuwait. Shaikh's date gardens, of the impression of Iraqi aims left on Charge d*Affaires as indicated in his paragraph 4, of the probability that the arrival at Kuwait of an Iraqi on an official mission would occasion pro-Iraqi demonstrations, and that an undesirable precedent would be established, I am now strongly of opinion that we should not a^rtie to the proposal. 3. I venture to suggest that Iraqi Government should be infomed that by our treaties with Kuwait Uitchiaon Volume KX page 262) luler la precluded from receiving the represent* tive of any foreign ?er, and that if Iraqi Government wish to aead a letter of regret (which is certainly called for) they should do ao tiirough charge d* Affaires Bagdad. In view of this, of the forcible seizure of It ia possible that Iraqi attitude is inspired / by wmmm© -3- by GeriaRn influence (though Charge d*Affaires ia in better position than I am to confirm this)* Iraqi propaganda referred to Kuwait as “Sudetanland of Iraq” and Attache of German U&amp;basay just ISagdad hafl^/asked for visa for Kuwait. • Brl taafiflul.CONFIDENTIAL. CONFIDENTIAL Kuivait iu-cf-ipt N°. 265-S ! No 3&amp;I Daiii'i _ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Secretary tc the Government of India, External Affairs -Department, New Delhi. The Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^ 2dth March 1939. Rritish Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated \VA ' Q \ Reference to previous correspondence : To 1 only. Bushire feinted Letter No.254*3 dated the 25th March 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Bushire telegram No.175 dated the 28th March 1939. Subject. Ira^i propaganda against Kuwait.By Air Mail. P.Z. 10 ^ Kurro 3t&gt;r INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, LV '7 3^. Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to hyg? Mail. T-he Fnreip-n Soeyetnry, Government of India. The Political Resident in the Persian GrrHA / 368 'l‘ ^ P.2, 1639/39. INDIA CPF r OS , WHIT: H .LL, S. .1. 1?th Marcu, 1939 - Dear Baggallay, v f «ouid yoa please refer to Bagdad telegrams Nos. Go and 66 a of the 10 th and 12 tn .larch and to the n* &gt;!° 1 2 Political Resident’s telegram fTo* 1 36 of the 15th March (copy sent to the Foreign Office under cover of India Office letter of the 16th March, No. P.2,1639/39) regarding the Ira^i rime Minister’s suggestions for composing the strained relations bet.veea Iraq nd owe it. /e agree with Fowle in concurring in the nmbas ador’p vievfs on the three suggestions and should be glad to .no.,' if ou agree that he may be authorised to appro ch the A 'ti oheiih as proposed in paragraph 2 of iis telegram. Thei»e is only one small ^oint that strikes us. It is proposed tliat the letter to the Sheikh should he from General Nuri, whereas the reply is to be from the Sheikh to the King. This seems a rather curious arrangement* but as both the .aabassador and Fowl© have accepted it, it is perhaps unnecessary fox* us to raise the point. pH As regards paragraph 3 of Fowle’s telegram it is worth recalling that an Iraqi decoration (Order of the Rafidain, Class I, Civil was conferred on the Sheikh when he visited in Feisal in epte iber, 1932. But presumably Nuri will act in accordance witi the ambassador’s view in which Fowle concurs. Yours sincerely, (SOD. ) it. PSNL. H. • Baggallay, s^. , Foreign office37 COPY OF tIlEGEAM. From H.M. Ambassadob, To Bagdad. Bate .25th...March Jl ....1939 ?&lt; No Time despatched. Addressed to Foreign Office No. 91, repeated to Bushire No. 24, copy to Koweit By bag No. 11/Saving. £1 As it happened, just after Bushire telegram No. 149 to India Office reached me on March 23rd, I was summoned to the Palace and was received by the King of Iraq in the presence of the Prime Minister, Minister for Foreign Affain and the Minister of Finance. After discussing other matters the King and the Prime Minister stressed His Majesty’s friendly feeling for the Shaikh of Koweit and pressed me to expedite acceptance of friendly overture mentioned in Sir M. Peterson’s telegram N6. 66. Having heard them out I said I thought the Shaikh would need a lot of convincing of the friendly sentiments which His Majesty had told me he entertained towards him and proceeded to protest with as much force as I could command against the disgraceful behaviour of the Iraqi police who, I said, had evidently been encouraged to commit these outrages by the unrestrained and harmful propaganda which had so long been conducted in this country. 2. The King and his Ministers expressed astonishment and denied knowledge of these events. His Majesty said he would cause the offenders to be punished. I said that was the least he could do. The Prime Minister observed that these incidents only showed how necessary it was that no time should be lost in despatching an envoy from here to Koweit, and that the individual, whom they had in mind, was well equipped in every way to undertake such a mission. He would be able to advise the Shaikh on how to administer his D 45758-000 X E-HP countrycountry and to convince Hie Highness that tho King of Iraq*s sole idea was to render assistance in bringing that backward territory up to date. The &amp;ing then alleged that the Shaikh employed Persians as police and im encouraged Persian/migration in order to enable him to con4 trol his own people. I denied this and, when the Prime Minister went on to say how pleased His Majesty would be to send Iraqi police at any time to help the Shaikh to keep order, I observed that I should have thought Koweit’s recent experience of Iraqi police would have been enough. 3. Nothing I could say would shake the King and the Prime Minister from their idea of sending an envoy and later of inviting the Shaikh to Bagdad to be flattered and decorated. They again begged me to seek your approval for the project. But I hope that the Shaikh will be discouraged from responding, at any rate, until he has received an apology for these three latest violations of his territory. If and when an apology has been received and the Iraqi Sovemment have given proof of good faith by genuine cessation of propaganda, it will be for consider ation whether it might not be impolitic to continue to discourage the despatch of King (xhazi’s messenger of friendship. Possibly if as one hopes his relations with Ifen Saud are shortly to be put on a more regular footing, the Shaikh would be in a stronger position than he would seem to be today to resist Iraqi blandishments. 4. The impression left on me by the proceedings at the Palace was that the Iraqis are aiming effectively to take over the protection of Koweit while nominally leaving the Shaikh and His Majesty’s Government in their present position. 5. Protests from this Embassy regarding propaganda hav« hitherto had little effect. I spoke to the Prime Ministej on March 22nd about the broadcast referred to in your tele gramtelegram Ho, 87* I also expressed disappointment that the King in a broadcast to the nation on His Majesty’s Birthday, in sending greetings to other Arabs in whose future and welfare he was interested, had seen fit to mention those of Koweit, together with those of Palestine and Syria, The Prime Minister pointed out that he had deleted the three names from the original draft and from the account issued to the press, I said, nevertheless the Oriental Secretary had neard the broadcast, (There was nothing offensive in the broadcast, but I thought it well to mention it,) 6 » I have today reinforced my oral representations about JAHRAH with a note requesting an apology (a copy of which is being sent to you by Air Mail), but I do not expect any concrete result. HOt • 3T0UN-B081ALLCONFIDENT I \ L Kutrait Receipt No Dale.I ! Telegram - S ! From - Political Resident, Bushire. T° - Political Agent, Kuwait. No. - 174 Dated and received the 28th March, 1939. Baghdad telegram No. 91 to Foreign Office, March 25th (copy to you hy hag from Baghdad). I have sent telegram, copy of which you will receive hy post, strongly (deprecat?) ing despatch 'Envoy' or any Iraq.! on official mission. ResidentTelegram From S Political Agent, Kuwait. To - Political Hesi&amp;ent, Bushire. No. - C/143 Dated the 29th March, 1939. Yuur telegram No. 174 of March 28th, and in continuation of my telegram No. C/135 of March 27th. 2. Shaikh confirms that he will not receive messenger (NAQIB has reached Basra and telegraphed to him). 3. In this connection Shaikh informs me that he could not visit Baghdad without first paying his long outstanding return visit to Ihn Saud. He has therefore now enquired through the Saudi Agent when it will he convenient. 4. Prom his remarks to me it seems that Shaikh would fall for flattery from Iraq. - PoliticalTelegram From To Repeated to Dated the 30th and R H.M's Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. E.M's Charge d’Affaires, Baghdad No. 98 Political Resident, Bushire Political Agent, Kuwait, received the 31st March, 1939. Your telegram Ncr. 91. I entirely approve of your language. 2* It is deplorable that y in spite of friendly sentiments expressed by King Ghazi and his Minister of Propaganda against / (fxsipaKxt?), violations of Kuwait territory continue. Latest incursions of Iraqi Police are indefensible^and it would ; in any case^be impossible for His Majesty’s Government to advise Shaikh to receive (King's?) messenger until adequate amends of these incursion^ have been received. 3. It now appears moreover that messenger would be (sent?) / / on an official mission^and that it is even contemplated that he should give advice to Shaikh about administration of his country. 4. Shaikh is precluded by his Treaty engagements from receiving agent or representative of foreign power except with consent of His Majesty's Government and it must be A clear to Iraq. Government that His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom could in no circumstances permit any interference of internal affairs of Kuwait. If, therefore, Iraqi Government wish to make to Shaikh any communication other than message / i of mere courtesy this should be made in normal way through you. / i- 2 - A* 5 . If you see no objection, you should speak to Minister for Foreign Affairs in the sense of the foregoing paragraphs. : 6 . You should also urge him strongly to agree to Iraqi cooperation in early demarcation of frontier in order that risk of incidents may 'be lessened - see Political Resident's telegram No. 150. , ^ i l &gt;|' ■ 7 . I do not wish to hold up credits negotiations on account of Iraq, attitude towards Kuwait or to use treaty at this stage. But assuming that negotiations lead/o agreement, it may he difficult to put that agreement into effect unless Iraq attitude has meanwhile (im£rav££ ? ) • - Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsCONFIDENTIAL Kuwait , © Telegram Inter. H.M’s Charge d'Affaires, Baghdad. Secretary of State for foreign Affairs 'From To No. 103. Repeated to - Political Resident, Bushire. No. 23 Dated and received the 1st kpril, 1939. Your telegram No. 98. During past week I have 'been in constant touch with the Prime Minister about Kuwait. He maintains that recent (events?) have been entirely due to undesirable influence in Palace and he appears at his wits end Ghazi’s impulsive activities He spent nearly five hours discuss(ing?) whole matter with me yesterday. He is seeing? King today and will probably arrange for me to have lengthy talk with His Majesty tomorrow. I shall then report. Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 13 - Houston-Boswall -1, i ) Telegram ■From To No. Political Resident, Bushire. Politiaal Agent, Kuwait 193. Dated and received the 1st April, 1939. b . 1 ^ J Your telegram No. 143 of March 29th. See also paragraph 4 of Foreign Office telegram No. 98 to Baghdad, March 30th. It is possible that NAQIB, with or without secret instructions from Iraq Government, may (^ath&amp;y crash'?) into Kuwait, unless very firmly put off by Shaikh. Please arrange for Shaikh to send NAQIB firm«^ refusi a^ to latter's telegram if he has not already done so. - Resident -&gt; 1M). iTo.0/148 • oiitiool ^genoy, Kuwait. 1 st ^pril, 1989. ^ Shaikh tell® me that the *Qas r Eihour n oroadeast last night, as on severs 1 nights, attacked 'the colonists in Palestine, the Zionists, the French in Syria, quoted telegraa® trm Iraqis encouraging the Iraq ^risy to enter Syria, and poems in praise of %azi, the Iraqis etc. He said that he felt that such a broadcast is most harmful to the good mm of the ^rab Kulers, and that he cofcld hardly, bear to listen to it. He i a It that something ought to be dona about stopping such inelegant and dangerous unrestraint. Yours sincerely, Phe Uon’ble Lt-Colonel 4r Trane hard Powle, K.C.I.L., Political Hesi dent in the Persian Oulf,CONFIDENTIAL, tf- r No. G/150. The Political A.gent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). for information. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 1st April 1939, Reference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Late. • \gb Subject. 1 . Copy of trgfislation of letter dated 17/3/1939 from Sayid Hamid Bey an-Naqib, Basrah, to H.H.the Ruler of Kuwait. 2. Copy of translation of letter dated. 18/3/1939 from H.H. the Ruler of Kuwait, to Sayid Hamid Bey an-Naqib Basrah. ^ r\ 3. Copy of translation of letter dated 29/3/1939 from Sayid Hamid Bey an^Naqib, Basrah, to H.H.the Ruler of Kuwait. Visit of Sayid Hamid Bey an-Naqib, Basrah Deputy, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. ) i JM( Translation of letter dated 17th March 1939 from Say id Hamid B e y an-ilaqib, Basrah, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments. I arrived in Basrah today in good health and comfOri;. I have received your letter dated 12 th instant which I read with pleasure, as it gave me the news of your welfare. May God preserve you. Please continue sending me your pleasing letters and instructions. Usual Ending. I ' I ' * * :Respected Sir, I have already written in my letter which I sent you from Baghdad about my efforts there, and I am now giving more details about that. After my arrival in Baghdad, and following an invitation from His Excellency the Minister of Finance, I met His Excellency Nuri Pasha as-Sai f d, and informed him of the bad effect of the Press and Broadcast in Baghdad, and that it is not to the advantage of the two countries that the friction should increase, but, on the contrary, by mutual understanding, that both points of view get closer to one another, I mentioned to him about your high character, nobility and sincerity to the Arabs, and that the Government would surely, in the future, notice that your friendship with them is far better for the public interest than hostility, and that His Highness the Amir was and still is blaming the Iraqi Government for not helping in the settlement of the question of his estates etcetera. After a long talk, His Excellency Nuri Pasha was convinced, and said, ”1 have old acquaintance with A1 Subah and I knew nothing of that which happened in Iraq.' He promised to put a stop to the attacks of the Press and to do his best with His Majesty to stop propaganda by the Broadcast against you. I requested him to write a letter to you which I will present to you so that the misunderstanding may be removed and matters may resume their ordinary course, anc , agreed to do so. Meanwhile, news were received about is recent incursions and events and, naturally, the ituation has become disturbed somehow, but I did not „fter that, but went to him and saidto him, 'If you have still the same previous idea with regard to good understanding and the removal of what took place between the two countries, I am prepared to complete this desire, and that I hoped that His Highness the Amir would accede to my request.' After some argument, he replied, 'No harm, I personally like A1 Subah and respect them, and I also wish that there should be friendship between Iraq and all the Arab Amirs, but the matter has now taken another form, and I wish to know the inclination of the British policy before I write a letter*' I, therefore, took leave from him to proceed to Basrah, and told him that I was awaiting his letter. He promised that as soon as he gets the result, he would send me a letter for Your Highness at Basrah. Immediately I receive his letter, I shall send you a telegram about/ my departure to your side. I will let you know the rest of the details verbally after my arrival.Translation of letter dated 27th Muharram 1357(18-3-39) from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, to Sayid Hamid Bey an-Naqib, Basrah. After Compliments. I have received your kind letter dated 17th March 1939 and ?ras glad to know that you are in comfort and that you have arrived in Basrah in complete safety which I always desire for you wherever you will be. Usual Ending. (0 Supplement, I have gone through the enclosure of your kind letter and thanked you for your good intentions and kind efforts which I appreciate highly. As regards what you have referred to, be sure that I am very anxious that the good relations should be ffcrm, and that I am preserving the neighbourly rights with all my power. I do not like, and always do prevent, the occurrence of anything that may disturb the friendly relations between these twin countries* How happy I become when I find that there is complete good understanding and genuine declaration which are in the interest of all* I will, if God willing, when I meet Your Excellency, to which I hope you will agree, tell you what is necessary. At any rate, matters are subject to destiny, and there is an end for everything. I pray the Almighty God to continue bestowing his favours on all of us, and lead us to the path of prosperity.Translation of* letter dated 29$ii March 1939 from Sayid Hamid Bey An Naqib, Basrah, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait# After Compliments, I arrived in Basrah yesterday in complete safety and wired to you about my arrival and received your reply* May God preserve you* Please continue sending me letters and instructions, Usual EndingMy dear Brother. I have already written to you from Baghdad about the progress of the relations between the two countries and received your satisfactory reply, but the recent events that took place in Kuwait, and later in Iraq, changed the situation. During my last visit to Baghdad, I met the Ministers, and particularly His Excellency the Prime Minister, and afterwards I was received by His Majesty in the presence ' of His Excellency the Prime Minister. I expressed to them your good intentions, your Arab sentiments, and your desire that there should exist good relations and friendship between the two countries, and I felt compelled to submit your letter and its enclosure to His Majesty and the Prime Minister with which they were very pleased. All of them revealed kind thoughts towards Your Highness, and that whatever has taken \ place can now be remedied and improved. They are deciding to depute me to Your Highness, and if your approve, that I should carry a letter from Your Highness to His Majesty containing cordial and brotherly expressions, His Majesty will invite you to visit Iraq, and to meet him, when the hostility will disappear between you, and matters will resume their ordinary ibkk course. I have arranged and settled the matter in this manner. My departure to your side will be further delayed for some days, how many I do not know exactly, but Your Highness will, of course, realise this. I should suggest that the prisoners - your subjects may be accorded a better treatment. I am sure they are your loyal subjects, and although they might have been at fault, yet your forgiveness, mercy and kind-heafctedness, which are well known to all the people, are above that. By taking this action the friction between the two countries might probably go down. At any rate, Your Highness knows your own interests best.Confidential D«0« Ho. C/151 Political Agency, Kuwait, 1st April, 1939. ly dear Sir Trenchard, lill you please refer to my Printed Letter Ho. 0/150, dated the 1st April, conveying translations of letters between the Shaikh of Kuwait and Sayid Hamid an Haqib, the Iraq.! Deputy of Basra. They are dated 17th, 18th and 29th March, 1939. The Shaikh gave me the last dated one this morning and X extracted the other two in succession, later in the day. Saiyid Hamid, it now seems clear, is the 'messenger» from King Ghazi; who is endeavouring to negotiate with the Shaikh by letter from Basra. 2. As Saiyid Hamid has owned property here for very many years, and has half shares in the Monopoly Transport Company and some other local enterprises, it might be difficult for the Shaikh to refuse to receive him, if he insists on coming as a 'private visitor', but that aspect does not arise at the moment, and the Shaikh has confirmed to me that he will not receive him as a messenger. (I have since writing this received your the Shaikh to put off the Haaib firmly). 5. Houston-Boswall when discussing this matter telegram Ho 193 of April 1st and shall again remind with/with me recently was most emphatic about not letting the Shaikh go to Baghdad. I received the impression that there were in his mind suspicions about which he would not care to be more explicit. 4. I think myself that nothing is past the Iraais, There are Kuwaiti malcontents in Iraq, and there are Germans who might encourage anything, and apart from that the Shaikh, who is most susceptible to flattery, by brother Arabs, would be 'out of his depth” and almost certainly, enthusiastically, make some serious mistake. 5. In any case, as I have already telegraphed to you, His Highness desires to pay his long postponed return visit to Ibn Saud, before making a visit to Iraq., the idea of which seems to please him. Yours sincerely, ) G, S. de GauryConfidential. D.O. No. C/153 Political Agency, Kuwait, My dear Sir Trenchard, J; u D VH Since writing to you my demi-official letter No. C/148 of April 1st, the 'Qasr az Zihour' broadcast by two successive and even more outspoken broadcasts of the same kind has caused considerable comment. The general venlict is that King Ghasi must either be (a) off his head or (b) pro-German, or possibly both. Yours sincerely, oi The Hon’ble Sir Trenchard Nowle, KCIS., JBE., Political Resident in the Persian vxUli, Bushire. «SOCKET Air Liaison Office Basrah. 2^.5.1939. Dear In connection with yoxir recent mention of JAHAKAH |tha following rumour which was repeated to me yesterday may be of interest,though probably is not now news to you. Legislative Council Koweiti antagonists of the Shaikh in colla- | boration with Iraq Government officials in Baghdad had formul ated a plan whereby a number (not stipulated but stated to be small) of Iraqi armed cars were to make a dash on JAHABAH and occupy the town. Simultaneously the 'Shubban” of KOWEIT would rise in resistance to the Shaikh. The idea seems to be based upon the lack of interest l the supposed inactivity of the British Authorities internal dissention in KO¥/EIT,and the fact that JAHARAH was built to protect KOWEIT against the AKHWAN onslaught is the strategical key to KQWEIT,so that a very small force would be sufficient to turn the tables on the Shaikh and secure the domination of Koweitis. (Ktt&amp;or). What the ramification of the plan was to have been is unknown but it was certainly coloured by local rumour to the effect that 5 battalions of the army were shortly to arrive in Immediately prior to the dissolution of the last Basrah.These, according to official circles, were to be dispatched to the KOWEIT border to 'protect Iraqi oil interests at JEBAL SAN AM' whilst the populace supposed that they were to be employ ed in the occupation of KOWEIT territory.5 The basis of this rumour is obscure.May*be it is an exaggeration of the idea expressed in a recent broad cast by the King who is believed to have said that he H looks forward to the day when Syria,Palestine and Koweit are attached to Iraq' coupled with a 'stand-by' warning to milijfary units in the South#In the latter respect it must be borne in mind that the King,whose life was recent ly seriously threatened,attended the opening ceremony of KUT Barrage which had been postponed until yesterday (28/3) so that it is not unreasonable to assume that adequate precautions would be taken for his protection.lt has been reported that a large police force was dispatched from EASIEIYAE to KUT on 23/3 and there is,furthermore,a hint of trouble amongst the Mayyah tribe of the Gharraf though JAHABAH question,that prior to the occupation by Iraqi armed cars,a preliminary attack by paid Najdis in lorries should be carried out upon the town in order to intimidate Koweitis and spread the rumour that large Iraqi forces were approaching.A further rumour states that Iraqi bedouin tribes instructed to approach the Koweit borders. a figment of the imagination is difficult to say. That knowledgeable Iraqis should countenance the idea in fantas tic but it is at least very damaging to British prestige and I hope the matter will be taken up in no uncertain my information is to the effect that FADDAGHIYAB was sequestrated against a court-claim by Beit Az Zuhair for I.D. 19.000 and that the estate of FAO has suffered a simi lar fate in lieu of Miri due to the extent of I.D.24.640 this ii It has also been «ngga&lt;Btad,to refer back to the g' A. ( How much of the above is truth and how much is terms In regard to the Shaikh*s properties in BasrahRepresentatives 0 f the shaikh were made to sign the sequestration order and many of the fellahin in receipt of a monthly wage from the Shaikh (as opposed to those having 'Sirkala' interests in the land) were turned out and replaced at the order of the Mudir FAO,and rents of shops,houses,etc.are in future to be collected by govern- mento 9. Your agent who reported to the Consulate last Monday had nothing further to add to what he had already told you,though he suspected that further sequestration of land might occur on the expiry of the ten-day notice for the payment of monies demanded. Incidentally he told me that only FADDAGHIYAH had been sequestrated,which was contrary to my information,and that he would keep the Consul informed of the situation.However you are probably in possession of the full facts.I have not heard from him since* So far as 1 can ascertain there is no question of any trouble,police forces are not in evidence and the matter seems to be a case for the Embassy and the govern ment to decide between them*After all,the blame really lies at the door of the British Authorities of old* I'm afraid this letter is rather garbled as I'm writing in a hurry but it may possibly be of some use to you*Please let us know when you intend visiting Basrah again so that we may kill the fatted calf* Captain G.S*de Gaury,M.O. Basrah* Political Agent,Conf idential . D.O. No. 0/157 Political Agency, Kuwait, April 4, 1939. My dear Sir Trenchard, A I enclose a copy of a ♦secret and personal* letter received from the Air Liaison Officer, Basra, which may he oi interest. It gives an idea of the atmosphere in Iraq, created by the recent propaganda from Baghdad. It is also interesting that both the Naval and Boyal Air force Intelligence Officers in Basra should indepen dently have produced a more or less similar story frora Iraq, officials about a plan for occupation by Iraq, of the northern half of Kuwait territory. 2. It looks rather as if there were a plan, as they heard; its lines perhaps being that the Iraq. Army forces would only carry out movements near the frontier which could be explained away by the Iraq Government to us afterwards. A few cars from Safwan (patrolling after smugglers), some paid Nejdis, (for whom responsibility could be disowned), Iraqi tribesmen, (some of whom in any case come into Kuwait territory at this time of year for the grazing) were to demonstrate, so that the ’Youth Party’ of Kuwait could take advantage of the atmosphere thus produced, supplemented by the Baghdad Broadcast propaganda, and by the movement of the Iraqi Army forces near the frontier, to carry out a coup in favour of themselves and Iraq., fortunately the * Youth Party* was never strong and is/ Tbe Hon’ble Sir Trenchard fowle, KOIS., QBE., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.is now non-existent, a fact which the few Kuwaiti malcontents presumably did not disclose to their Iragi patrons, 3, The only parts of the plans faithfully carried out (a) King Ghazi’s propaganda (b) leKKi ji»i fendi and the frontier Police who duly shot up Jahra village, and as a preliminary, closed the frontier to travellers. All this does seem to lit with the impression received xfj • 3 by Mr. Houston-Boswall (see paragraph 4 : of his telegram To.91 of March 25th, 1939), and her seizure of the Shaikh’s gardens in Iraq, just about the same time also seem to indicate that there was a fully concerted Iraq Government move to this end. 1 j ((fa U | 5. The action taken here on the 10th March, reported in my letter No. 0/95 of larch 12th, was just in time. Had it not been taken, and had the Iraqis not had their own internal trouble in Baghdad on larch 12th, and so been able to push their plan to its conclusion, we might by now have been in more trouble with Iraq than we are. 6 . I attach an appendix, tabulating for easy reference some relevant dates. Zero day seems to have been March 19th.* were Yours sincerely,.APHSHDIX (a) Comencement of violent anti-Kuwait propaganda from King Ghaai Tireless Station which did not cease, in spite of representations, until larch 26th February 12 th. Mention of the Iraq. Army in connection with annexation of Kuwait 'began on about March 7th. (h) Closing of Kuwait frontier by Iraqi Police... March 18th. (c) Incursions by Iraqi Police began on March 15th and continued on larch 19th. (d) Seizure of 3haikh*s gardens in Iraq. March 19th.CONFIDENTIAL. No. c - 'k' b ^ The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIR2. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^. for information. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Bated the. 5th AP ri11 « Keference to previous correspondence: printed letter No.C/l50 date^f lst April 1959. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. C Name and Date. Subject. Copy of translatio the Ruler of Kuwe. n of letter from His Highness it, to Sayid Hamid Bey an-Haqib.^ter from His Highness Shaikh sir Ahmad al Jabir as-Subah, aA-fe; Basrah.’ ° f KuWalt * t0 Sayid HaBld Bey, My dear brother, I have already written to you definitely about the love and admiration that Ihad towards the twin country and particularly towards that sitting on its throne, and his family. Be confident that the good relations, sincerity and cordiality have been existing between us and the House of HASHIM since the time of our ancestors, Pemiciousness started by certain narrow-minded individuals never affects really friendly relations and really good intentions. With regard to your statemnt that I should send with you a letter to His Majesty, I do not deem it necessary as I have confidence in your kind brotherhood and faithful intentions, You stated that by according a better treatment to the prisoners, the friction between the two countries may // go down, I assure you that the prisoners were sent to jail ( for offences committed by them intentionally. Had they been given a free hand, the bad results of their actions would have burnt the green grass as well as the dry. This question is a purely internal concern which effects me in the first place, and I feel sympathy for them more than anyone wise whatever position he may put himself in, since they are my own people. Anyhow, I sincerely thank His Majesty and His Excellency As-Sai’d for their good intentions. My only hope is that you should be confident that I am doing my best for the prosperity if my country and welfare of my people, as I am also doing my best efforts always to strengthen the ties of friendship and alliance between Arab countries, and that I do give my best attention to what matters touching the twin Iraqi country.*11 « y iof /V«^c-^ ^ fl 6s?*i\ My dear brother, I have already written to you definitely about the love and admiration that I had towards the twin country and particulary towards that sitting on its throne and his family. Be confident that the good relations, sincerity and cordiality have been existing between us and the IfruihimifrisQ since the time of our ancestors. yfrpiflvwg net ter j- - ereato-d by certain narrow-minded pe-rsonc dever affects friendly relations and good intentions. With regard to your statement that I should send with you a letter to His Majesty, I do not deem it necessary as I have confidence in your kind brotherhood and faithful intentions. You stated that by according a better treatment to the prisoners, the friction between the two countries may go down, I assure you that the prisoners were sent to jail for offences commited by them intentionally. Had they been given a free hand, the bad results of their actions would have burnt the 4 * CroCC 0A*C-J ^ C a. Cc'i- X&lt; ' greeiP dry. TS**** question is a purely internal ©jw* which me first place, and I feel sympathy for them AQ**&amp;&amp;r*tG more than anyone else whatever position he may put himself in, \jd/ ’4 r they flre my own people. Anyhow, I sincerely than,:. His Majesty and H.3.As-aai'd for their good intentions ■Qrj»p roe i€r44reft -of-- iaatte-P-s .■ At the same time, I welcome your visit to your country '■w- and brothers. My only hope is that you should be confident that I am doing my best for the prosperity of^my country and welfare of my people, as I wn also doing my/efforts alwajrs to strengthen the ties of friendship and alliance between /CrU-- J ^ Arab countries, and give my best attention to what the twin Iraqi country, m ■ ■ X:. b'r\CONFTD ;NTIAL \ Kmixii: Rc No 3GCf . ; 70 Telegram From To No. Political Resident, Bushire Political Agent, Kuwait 213 Dated the 5th and received the 6 th April, 1939 \0 My telegram No. 159, 'March 25th. I have now received from Consul, Basra, a copy of letter dated March 29th to you from Air Liaison Officer Basra. 2. Does this hear out information (given hy?) Naval Staff Officer and are you previously (mut?) drawn not necessarily hy Iraq Government hut perhaps hy Iraq Army? 3 . Scheme was not put into effect hut if even contemplated gives us line of what we may expect in future especially in view of present situation in Iraq - ResidentTelegram - s ^ rom “ Political Agent, Kuwait To - Political Resident, Bushire No. - C/159 Dated the 6 th April, 1939. Your telegram No. 213 of April 5th. A. '1 2. A letter from me on subject is in hag due Bushire April 9th. 3 . I think it certain there was some authoritative plan, which will he carried out later on unless they are given really sharp warning. 4. My personal conviction is that lack of this in i past and long past over consideration for the feelings of the Iraq Government has led up to the present situa tion. - Political -V UL^- By Jkir Mail. RZ. /rG( INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, It Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by ^ Mail. - J Sea The FuiuigirSecietary, Ouvoi'n inent of India. The Political Iterttem in llitrRersian Oulfr 3681P.Z.1561/39 29words. Cypher telegram from Secretary of State to Political Resident in the Persian G-uif ? dated 14th March, 1939. SECRET XXX Imoortant. 487. Addressed Political Resident. Copy hy mail to Koweit and India. Bagdad telegram of the ir 10th March to Foreign Office ''no.66, repeated to you no.15. Iraqi propaganda against Koweit. I shall he glad to have your views on suggestions of Iraqi Prime Minister.ENCLQKSU«E IN FOREIQN OFt-‘ICE COVERING LETTER DATED ft. *&gt;. [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] rTom IRAQ . Decmher. Sir M. Peterson (Bagdad), 10th March, 1959. D. 5.20 p.iii. 10th March, 1959. R. 5.00 p.m. 10th March, 1959. No. 66. — -it My telegram No. 62. [? grp. omtd. ] states that with approval of the Ring he would like to send a member of the Naqib family of Basra to Koweit. Latter would convey letter from General liuri to the Sheikh expressing regret lor events of last few weeks which would be described as the work of ill-intentioned persons profitting by General Nuri's absence. It would be suggested that Sheikh should reply by a letter to the King. Thereafter Sheikh would be invited to Iraq and o.ecorated by His Majesty, I told General Nuri I should have to consult you. I am inclined to recommend acceptance of suggestions first and secona but indefinite postponement of the third. Addressed to Foreign Office No. 66, repeated to Bushire No. 15 and Jedda No. 15. : III ‘ &lt;CLOSURE ISJ FCSREfCSN OFP.n- tivva-rtiMn Ltrrm dated B‘ H*.:S twannM* - sv^ cv^ js*&gt; No. 107. ($ 1023/474/93) FOREIGN OFFICE, &amp;.W.1. 24th February, 1939. The Prime Minister of Iraq called on 21st February to see me before leaving London to return to Bagdad. 2. After some general observations regarding the i Palestine Conference and the evils of political Zionism, General Nuri al Said turned to the position in Syria. He had been asked some weeks ago to convey a message from the Turkish President to the Syrian Government, but he had not hitherto passed on this message. It was to the effect that the Syrian Government should accept the present position as regards the Hatay and cease from making anti-Turkish propaganda in this connexion; the Turkish Government further desired to make it clear that, apart from the Hatay, Turkey had no wish to change her existing frontier with Syria; the message proceeded to affirm that Turkey entertained friendly feelings towards the Syrian Government, and sympathised with them in their present difficulties. It appeared that General Nuri did not now intend to take any action with regard to this Turkish message, since the Syrian Government had resigned in the course of the last few days. The General declared, however, that he was very anxious regarding the position in Syria and thought that the refusal of the French Government to ratify the Franco-Syrian Treaty of His Excellency Sir Maurice Peterson, K.C.M.G. , etc. , etc. , etc. , Bagdad.of 1936 would have very serious consequences. He believed that the anti-French feeling in Syria was incited by foreign powers, and he wondered whether, if complete confusion were to prevail in Syria as a result of trouble between the Syrians and the French, the Turks might not seek to take advantage of the situation. The French were, in his opinion, pursuing a very dangerous policy in Syria and it was partly due to the French that the Damascus Government had so little influence in various outlying districts, such as the Jezireh. 3. I suggested to His Excellency that the Syrian Government would do well in their own interests to keep on the best possible terms with both the French and the Turks, and I understood him to express his general agreement with this view. 4. I then referred to the Iraqi Government’s recent request for credit facilities and said that I understood that he had in the course of the last few days had a full discussion with Mr. Nixon, the General Manager of the Export Credits Guarantee Department, and that as a result he was arranging for Mr. Hogg, the British financial adviser to the Iraqi Government, to pay a flying visit to London o engage in further financial discussions. General Furi confirmed this and stated that he had also discussed he situation with a representative of Messrs. Baring, position briefly was that there were three courses which might be open to the Iraqi Government in this matter, as they hoped, they could obtain financial credits from HisHis Majesty’s Government; the resulting contracts would of » course he placed with British firms; failing such credits they might decide on a loan, in which case the contracts would be placed with whatever firm offered to supply their requirements on the most advantageous terms, and the orders might well go to other than British manufacturers; lastly the Iraqi Government might decide simply to cancel their public works programme, in which case also the contracts would be lost to British industry. 5. General Nuri then said that he had received telegrams from Bagdad, including one from King Ghazi, referring to a dispute which had arisen in Xoweit between the Sheikh Of Koweit and his Council, and expressing the hope that the Sheikh would not take drastic action against that body. 6. In conclusion General Nuri asked for my views on his Government's idea of negotiating a Treaty of Alliance with Egypt. I informed him that there would be no objection whatever, so far as His Majesty's Government were concerned, to his undertaking such negotiations, hut I would ask to he kept informed of their progress, and to he given an opportunity to study the draft text of any new treaty, if the negotiations reached that stage, in order to have an opportunity of offering comments. General Nuri agreed to this, and explained that his intention was to suggest that the new treaty should he on rather different lines from the Anglo-Iraqi Treaty of Alliance, for he thought it should provide that each country should send troops to the other to assist i\ f »assist in case of need. The Iraqi Government would be prepared in certain circumstances to send troops to help Egypt if attacked. He hoped that an undertaking from Egypt similarly to assist Iraq would have a steadying and very beneficial effect upon Iraq’s relations with Persia. I am, with great truth and respect, fir, Your Excellency’s obedient Servant, (For the Secretary of State)3681 CONFIDENTIAL O By Mail. P.Z.JVS^ — Kuwait Receipt \ N° i / ^ i INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - ' Sea The Secretary, Qov^TiniPnt nLJndia. The Political4WdcaiT]n Eorcian ■^kilf.iLMCt-asimE FOfteioN office caveRiwa letter oated MARI?^. 1 1 {This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] From IRAQ Decypher. Sir M. Peterson (Bagdad). P.Z. 1387 ! O -r Dc 9.40 p.m. R. 8.15 p. m. March 3rd 1939. March 3rd 1939. March 3rd 1939. No.53. IMPORTANT . My telegram No.52. There was further broadcasting tonight from Palace [?Bean] Koweit. I therefore recommend procedure of question and answer in Parliament. I shall renew representations to the Prime Minister and the King at the earliest possible moment. Do you wish me to press for suppression of Palace station? vne may have trouble ifBy Arr Mail. P.Z. CONFIDENTIAL Kuu'o.i. Receipt INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, &gt; 3 . Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. * A copy has been sent to by Mail. - J Sea T bp Fnrpjyn Sp.nretaTV. QnvprnmftntJxLhldht The Political Resident in-die Pei ohm Calf. 3681g&amp;iCLOSURg iM FORCIQN OFFICE COVEKINQ LETTER DATED u.»P:io?c [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s (Whrernment,' and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required tor official use.] I 0 ! (B 1705/66/91) To SAUDI ARABIA, Cypher telegram to Sir R. Bullard, (Jedda). Foreign Office, 20th March, 1939, 10 p a m. No. 40. 0 : 0 : 0 : 0 : 0:0 IMPORTANT . Your telegram No. 30 [of March 6: Iraqi propaganda against Koweit]. You may assure Ihn Saud that there is no likelihood whatever of His Majesty's Government being 'forced to fall in' with Iraqi action or to consent to any modification of the status of Koweit by such factitious agitation.ogxvo aaxxB'i onimsado [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned Ibn Saud has sent me a copy of anti-British broadcast from Iraq about Koweit heard March 19th, He has telegraphed to Iraqi Government protesting against the statement that he would [grp. omitted] no objection to the annexation of Koweit by Iraq provided that he secured free port and has asked for it to be contradicted. Addressed to Foreign Office No. 59 March 21st, repeated to Bagdad telegram No. 15. From SAUDI ARaBIA, Decypher. Sir R. Bullard (Jedda) 21st March, 1959. D. 9 a. m R. 10.45 a.m, 21st March, 1959. 21st March, 1959.i CONFIDENTIAL. No. 364-3 of 1939- The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Secretary to the Government of India, external Affairs Department, New Delhi. The Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documentsj^c British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. DatedT el eg ram 3 © To i’rom Political Res ident, Bushire. Secretary of State for India, London Repeated His Majesty's CHargfe d* Affaires, Bagdad, Copy by post to (lovernment of India, External Affairs Intelligence Officer in Basrah was also received by Poli tical Agent. Political Agent and I are of opinion tn a t, following on the failure of the Iraqi engineered outbreak in Kuwait, some scheme was hatched, not necessarily by Iraq Government but by Army extremists encouraged by German influence, for despatch of Iraqi armed cars into Kuwait territory, possibly to seize Jahra. repetition of such a wild cat scheme would not be impossible, and I venture to suggest that it might be considered whether a broad hint might not be given to the Iraq Govern ment that any invasion of Kuwait would of course be resisted by the armed forces of His Majesty's Government. Department, hew Delhi, and Political Agent, Kuwait. Ho. 246. My telegram Ho. 159 March 25th. 2. Report to similar effect from Hoyal Air Porce In present conditions in Iraq I imagine tne Britc onsulSAV INGRAM, Telegram From To Copy 'by post to Dated the 20th Inter. H.M's Charge d 1 Affaires, Baghdad. Foreign Office, London. No. 40/Saving. Political Resident, Bushire No.4/Saving Political Agent, Kuwait. No, 2/Saving, and received the 25th April, 1939, Bushire telegram'No. 246 to India Office. Danger of revival of any such scheme (if indeed it ever existed) has “been much diminished 'by the death of King Ghazi. Fact that Kuwait is under British Protec tion is well known to Iraq. Government, and hint, as suggested, would appear to them to he a (great?) threat. It would, I consider, he a sign of His Majesty’s Govern ment to protect a Protectorate ; which is better left as a foregone conclusion. Moreover, since it is not suggested that there is danger of incursion being planned by the Government, hint to them would, I think, be (misunder stood? ). - Mr. Bostoun-Boswall -Office of the senior ITaval Officer, Persian Gulf, c/o »D., Basrah. T have the honour to forv/ard herewith may consider desirable* I !iave the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient servant, fM} Cosmo Mo GhraWft. CAPTAIN SI'BIOR NAVAL OP: ‘IC'JN PERSIAN GULF. Ilo.461. 15th April 19159. ir # THE HON. Tit: POLITICAL PaAr. iT IN THE PEJ'SXAN GULF. Copy to:- The liolitij The PollticpO_Agent Kuwait*No. 288/52/39 CONFIDENTIAL Knuai' lit'ccipt ? N o (f- g- f' i •/ jy) 4- HIS Majesty’s Charge d’Affaipes at Bagdad presents his compliments to the Political Agent, Koweit, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned dooum’ents. Bri tish assy A Bagdad. 2 Oth April f 193 9 Reference to previous correspondence : | Bagdad telegram No. 13 dated 31st March, 1939 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. / • M Bagdad despatch No. 178' dated 20th April, 1939, Koweit smuggling. to Foreign Office, London.on to rots*; Irrelevant ob^eotiona to the movemente of the Poll tiAgent in tmmtt* 'hen X vieited the Friae Minister on April 11th# I Hie txetllenoy that I ooula not transmit euoh g reply to my aovemment aikt I have ®lnc^ written him r,n official letter urging that mn independent &amp;.xul author!tstiv© enquiry should be onrrled out at nsKie end that s full report of the result should he Q*mmmkmia&amp; to an* ,. riv^tsly, .the I»ti1 'ini#ter promlsod m to 4m hie best to persuade tue Ministry of the Interior to nominate ® apeoiel official for this tsaX and to aoeooiote with him the British *n»i&gt;««Ung imoer of Police- at ^sre. H* admitted# however# that it would not be lor Ma to atowe the Minister of the Interior to do this* it ^ * ».*4i $bmz$m% § he weld# who on nooouxtt of hie dislike the -hei had oh® true ted t&amp;e prompt trensmisaim of an order to the Butasarrlf of Mbt® (» politician who h®&amp; been appointed by the Mlototor of the Interior in Ihiri el aid* a absence in '.AoMon, with the express objoet of ore®ting trouble with 1 owe it) to eaneol the attachment of the Hhai'ch’s properties, spa. the * $ rim Minister forssaw that, for similer reasons, the Minister of the Interior would find a variety of excuses far not tearing strong action properly to investigate tee slleged oisoonduot of the Basra pal ice* ttwatloB of MRiggllBS' * ««* *af®unded *ri**^na* ■hlafc alw»ya seea® to or.-p up *h«n«*«r * protect 1* •'*“*« ** aa * pl *oa» sott^a toaaiilJig toe &gt;s&amp;»ista’e interest.. » violoue proteet U m«» to to* Xra«il »*«»t • ions into .Kaweit tiwsy oounter *lto *«*»»l»l«t* MnsgXlngt and t»han®**p *n »*t***t 1* **d* to ^ *gwg«Xing to* Shatto proteat* that no •etlafaatl &gt;n &gt;** ! ' yer ~he mw* Kl slater of eourae aS'*m raised the In f»at, to a«»e boon esUbU»*«-d. '/■hen o circle seciss. beenbmmn given to him atnnplmlnta of incur®i ms by Ira^l poU/o« into hi® territory. 12* l Bhmll Qonllnm ocvertiele ®3 to ore©® for a a&amp;Usf&amp;otary to s^r representations aoncernin* the attiichaa properties aa4 t^a recent ^ieben&amp;viour of the WU~- u „ £ Voi 13* In mm?$-unm with ta* in^truo.ti^^ in paragraph 6 of your telegram ^' of r^rsh 30to, * h^v« strongly advissefl the , rim® Minister to #onai4er fie poeaihillty of making early arrengenNmts for the ration of th« Kuwaiti-Iraqi frontier* He received the suggestion without enthusiasTi saying it would not stop smggllng. I aligerradt however* that a line of he sc on a would in sjy ooini^n ^ j a@rv® as s useful reminder of a p et, both to the Iraqi police and to intending rmgglers* I propose to diacuss ■**&gt;4 / *' / this setter with him Again sad iwam fully, wo soon e» the ? I pel lee incursion® at Jehrsh *md. the atteehe^nt of the V 1 i '* properties have been diepoeM of. ^L) : s 14. I am eeMing aopl«« of title despatch to the : rslitlael l KeeMoat in the Persian (mlf and to the .. olitioel Agent at Kom it* 1 |Mtfn the honour to ’fe® with the highest i'eapect. My JwOfti* tour l*or4ohip f © scoet obedient# humble servant.A No. 235/10/39 HIS Majesty’s Charg4 d’Affaires at Bagdad presents his compliments to political Agent, Koweit, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Bagdad. 2 01 h Apr il, ? 193 ...? Reference to previous correspondence : r Bagdad despatch No. 288/52/39 dated 20th April, 1939 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Af ' Bagdad despatch No. l^S Koweit smuggling. dated 2Qth April, 1939, to Foreign Office, London. 1 1 I 3479 12360 k 2 ) / 1Bi*Itlsh t %{th April, 1959, /aoj sjr uw&amp;, | In aw lea pa tan fi 0 . 1?8 of 8c l April, j JUidic«te4 thut the quest loft of smuggling from loftoit pus once mre b#lii^ taken up with vigour by the Iraqi Ciavernsseat, and 1 now have the honour to report in greater detail the meaner la whieh this is being done* g * th * ***»&amp;**** eauee of the revival of this pereimial problem *ae f as i have already related, the representations against anti~.*©weit propaganda erdlch *ir i aurlee i eterson ssade to the Iraqi Q&amp;wmmmt and which I have continued, mud mm ee eeinily the protests which i have had to nake about the recent incurs ions of Iraqi police into the territory of the Shaikh of kcweit. I had hoped that the news, contained In • ir Reader „ 'Mn m v\\ Bullard teiegrsua ho. 44 of Aarch 16th, that the negotiations for the conclueion ©f an agreement between oweit and .audl ^rsbia sere now well advanced, ooinbin. d with the unuertakings given fey the holer of oweit that when the :au«U trade blockade ©f his territory was raised he would stop smuggling into Iraq, would place w in a position t© give a satisfactory answer to the Iraqi aovemment if they should raise the question of smuggling* 4* unfortunately, 1 find tint «y attempts to reawsure them with argusautts on these lines have not had the desired effect* The rrine Minister insists that Iraq can hope for no 7 he hight Honourable The Viscount Halifax, g• €*•* , d*(J* '.: *i* , 0 * d* 1 * -A* , etc*, etc*, etc*- - ^ ■ V, no advantage tmm nxmh m arguaa Vmt tm mining ©T ttia ^audi trade fttaeluu* ©f i o«eit »ui aggravate and nat a^Xiomte the angling problem* ;•&gt;© soon as the blockade t» rmimd the wUi take their gocda frcm &amp;«*#it into Arabia and eauggie thence into Xr«^. un ccnaequmioe the Ira^i aoves^mt eill have to watch the whole frontier from the Ahor Abdallah to the Jabal .nahsea* instead of wntchifig the Acmeiti frontier sdoae. lie fereecee that they will ala© become ari^railed in iarm^rablfc renatioue frontier Iheidentn with the Aaadi arabiaa authorities* The i'tim ^laieter # a the® la le tha t caravans frott iajd trade nomally with the liaaa port® and not with and that r if trade between ha^d and goarelt is reopened, it will be solely for the purpose of aesaggliag into Xra^« For these reasons he elaiiTis that it is airldexit that Aoweit will continue to be the centre of mK&amp;filing unless the *,oeeiti tariff* are raised to the Iraqi level or import# into owait are restricted. 6 . Ca April llth, when 1 had to coiaj lain to the rriae Pinister ©f hie failure to give a&amp;tlefaction to ^ protest about Iraqi police meureioae into Aoweit daring 1 &amp;rch# hi® ^XMlXWMMT 4***lop*«t »l»Uar **‘*'“ ia#nt * • t * r ** t,,f i * n ® tiu ** H «nt ov«r th* itictcr/ of the vain e forts *niah n*a *&gt;««» “o' 1 * since 1M2 to solve the problem of awaggliag end co^plaine^ that the Shaikh had always stubbornly refused to adopt any prep&amp;aal* which were in. the laaat likely to be effective. Tit only OMHiaaraa which could be of value were, he repeated, tliosc vhidt had bean 4 ia«m»ed with Ta^iq duwai.li in ondon last i et© bar.1 ex.-laiii timt tlm whioli it to eoiieiyd© : : os©it and im^ 4 i Arabia provided the eic^o ©orstroi ©f ai earavana or r^rohaf^ia# l#ftTiag ^oiseit and that it •#tia^d to me thftt aach control should prevent the develop®ent of the sitazatlon ehioh His .xceliejjcy h«d described. 8 . The JPriM mmiMU* would not* however, accept these *rjpaM«t« and, taking hia stand on hie admittedly greater knowledge of desert econosi^r and the habit a of the Hedoain Arabs, contended that the control envisaged in the agreement woaid do nothing to prevent saaiggling from gaweit into Ira% be^ng developed, on a large scale via aadl Arabia# X am advised bjr those here who have seise knowledge of the mormmnta of Maid! earavens that the Frlae minister*a contention that there is no natural flew of trad# between Bald and Eewelt la net .altogether sound. • aai told that, on the eontrar/, once the blockade is raised a eonslderebie volume ©f trade betveea kiadh and the i ereian Gulf would move naturally threa^h ^yweit. This argument is also borne out by the rss»i*£a about ; oweit as a port for llajd mad# by Tie | Majesty*s Minister at de Ida in the third paragraph of his despatch I*o. $24 of .&gt;ecest?er oth, 1989* 1. . it appears, nevertheless, that there are #o»s gro'UBde for the i mm i ini star’s fears that tm opming of caravan traffic from Keeelt to Bajd sill lead to the extension of snaig'gilug aloftg the whole of the southern- frontier of ira%* ^aheed, such a davslcpsent would appear to be inevitable unless, as 1 have endeavoured to argue, the control established by the proposed agrecsent between i owe it end oaudl irmbia will effectively prwrmt it# 1 have m% Myself sux ^ ioient imowledgsknowledge ot %m&amp;m mrmmnta in isegd to be ^bio to form iya opinion on knkft point § nnd i ahould notto^dingi/ be gi^d if i cool 4 be furtuehod with the views of the aothoritiee in the ffts**!** It eouree, iaost deeirmble that I should if po^B-ible, bo provided with Cuiielueive facts with which to ^set the ^''riisjo ^ihieicv 1 # erguaente thet* far froas hein e ; es nmdlgeemt which Will solve the problem of srnu jlin^ aoro^o her eouthem frontiery the deweit - seudi Arebiaxi egr^esioht will oalx the situation worse. 11* 1 «R sending copies of this despatch t© Hi a : ajestp*e v inister at d edda, the olltieel Keel-eat in the ere inn Oulf and the Political Agent at ©weit. 1 have the honour to be with the highest respect. Tour uordekij^e ?^oet ©bo j lent, huiflbie servant, ; Signed) W. E. HOUSTOUN^BOSWHLLw GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. —Department. EXPRESS LETTER Confidential From Political Agent, Kuwait To Hon'Rle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire. * No. C/184 DatedZOth April, 1939. Soon after king Ghazi’s death there were strong rumours and reports in Iraq, that a Kuwaiti delegation was to pay a visit to Basra in order to mourn for the King, 'being given travel faci lities by Mutassarif, who, according to one version, it was said, had sanctioned their passage both coming and going without pass ports. The British Consulate received this information, and Shaikh and the Kuwait authorities sent the Kuwait Police to JAHRA to turn back mourners, who had started out from Kuwait. authorities by the Iraqi Press might be mentioned to the Iraqi Government, quoting the above example from paragraph 2, as an unpleasant one. telegraphed it briefly to the Embassy. 2. The newspaper *AL KARKH 11 of Baghdad now reports that the 3. This is entirely untrue. Not one man left Kuwait for this purpose or was turned back. 4. I think these continuing factitious attacks on Kuwait Political Agenf, Kuwait.By Air Mail. F.Z. ASp 19 M :J D-&gt; INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, JL(&gt; 1? , Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to 3681 ^ t, A ' ^ ’ Air Mail. by rp p r gocrotnry) Government C&gt;t India. Resi The Political l^sid^OT-rirthe Persian Onffi.... @302/39 .»©. 101 Foreign Office t . .1 l@th A^rll, 1939. (S @@41/177/@g &gt; wlr In mjr debate© ,o. i© of the 89th arch, I informed .you that the Amir Felaftl haa mmi .&gt;ir Laneelot Oliphant on the Mth Mareh issmedleteljr after hie eonvereetion wit,, ^eelf mm h»u continued with him the alecueaion of certain joints ariain^ out of the £*rlmo rinlster’e letter or the 23rd aren. diet Eo/al Ighneaa told air aanoelot Oliahant that he was very appreciative of the warm term* in which the . rl e Ulnlstoi*** letter was couched and than enquired, a© I recorded in my despatch under reference, In what form, *nd how quickly Saudi Arabia might expect help should a situation arise in which the community of interests between oaudi Arabia, and Great Britain led to their beln* raced ^ with a common ene y. This is a point on which you will ' receive instructions in dae course. 3. His Royal nlghneos then alluded to the phraaa **potential aggressors” #hlch occurs In the sixth ps agrsph of trie rime laister 1 s letter, ha «sk«d whether it was the opinion of tha foreign Office that, in the present unstable state of th* world* some fom of aggression might be exercised against v»audl Arabia* P.c '-m* toll that any net of aggression in the near future seemed very doubtful* ndeed, Kerr i ltler*s recent activities could not have been welcome to those who had/ er Bullard, KG' C., Oil*, etc*, etc*, ©tc*, J«Ma,(/o7) Ibf ma hitched their chariot to hie star, and it wa» unlikely that any country which had xone so would willingly undertake intensive activity In Arabis, But in Herr Hitler’s case it ee no longer a question of dealing with a normal, logical man, and it was always possible that he might incite those who * he regarded ae hie friends to follow him •wen now* It might, however, be doubted whether Italy, if pursuing her claim© against France, would simultaneously e ow any aggressive action in the East* It was not possible to sa, ; .' any more than this. 4. His doyal Highness then spoke of oweit, and asked whether there was any likelihood of His ejeaty* s QoTernmsnt nllowlxig its incorporation In Iraq. The answer was an emphatic negative, b. His Royal Highness finally turned to the situation in the Persian Oulf. He «as assured that, far from it being the policy of His Majesty’© Government to encroach upon the autonomy of the local sheikhs, Hi© Majesty’s Government had always been most careful to preserve their autonomy. He wee reminded that his brother, the Amir Gaud, when he had visited Bahrein some fifteen months ago, had been impressed By the absence of any signs of dictation by His Majesty’s Government* He was also told, by way of illustration, that although Uie majesty*• Government had met with considerable difficult/ in establishing, an air i^ort on the Truclal toast, yet l«ttr , wh«n the dhetkh of ^ebal saw that the freedom of the ,hei&lt;h of Gharjah had been in no wise diminishes since the Imperial Airways service had been introduced, this bhelkh had hire elf pressed for the air port to be transferred to I^bai. 6 . Hi© £oy*l Highnee© seemea satisfied, and left after a conversation which had lasted nearly an iiour* 7 Sri, etc. , For the Secretary of Btate, w«d. L/.C. iVHiQALLAX. \India Office, 'fnitenaXl, S.W.l. 5tn April, 1939, P,Z, 1978/39. dear powle, T 7ith reference to the correspondence relating to the recent campaign of propaganda in Iraq against the Shaikh of Kuwait I enclose for your information a copy of a letter sent to tne Foreign Office which is self- explanatory. We should be grateful for any comments you may wish to make on the points raised by the Foreign Office and in particular with regard to King Ohazi’s allegation about the Shaikh* s policy of using Persians in his police and encouraging Persian immigration. fours sincerely, sd. K.T.Peel. The Hon 1 ble Lt.Col. Sir T.C.W.Fowle, His Britannic KCIE.,CBS., Majesty’s Consulate-ueneral, husnire.&lt; S &gt;, 0 . P.Z*1978/39. India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. 5th April,1939, Dear 'Zyres, 'Then you came round to see us laat week in connexion witn the Iraqi-Kuwait troubles you mentioned tnree points on which it was thought desirable that Fowle might be consulted. rnese were - (a) What is the strength of the alleged pro-Iraqi feeling in Kuwait and how far is it responsible for the recent trouble V This is partly answered by the Kuwait Intelligence Summary for the period l6-28th February ^copy to Foreign Office with India Office letter P.Z.1744/39, dated 28th Marcn), in paragraph 24 of which it is stated that M there are in fact a few nuwaitis wno would like to join Iraq, estimates varying between 10 and 80, their leader being Abdulla as Saqr, a man wno owns estates in Iraq, which he is frightened of losing, and who owes the Ruler money”. It seems unlikely that the strength of pro-Iraqi feel ing in Kuwait is of any consequence or would have given any trouble if it had not been encouraged from Iraqby propaganda against the Shaikh and possibly by other means. (b) What substance is there in the King J s allegation A) (Bagdad telegram 91) that the Shaikh employs Persian police and encourages Persian emigrants in order to enable him to control his own people ? Houstoun-Boswall denied this, and on our present information we have no reason to doubt that ne was right. There is of course a considerable Persian minority in Kuwait about which the previous Iraqi liovernment made &lt;'' ' ✓ ■yS^ enquiries (cf. Fowle's letter to Peterson of the 12th January, Kfo.50-S, copy enclosed with India Office letter of the 9th / February H.M.Byres, Fsq., Foreign Office.V ® \ o February, P.2.851/39, and connected correspondence) and the Iraqis seem to be genuinely (though mistakenly) uneasy on tne aubj ect. (c) How can we carry out our obligation to protect Kuwait if force should be used by Iraq ? Th^ question possibly has reference h v,nhl A&gt; jvpl pM to Fowle’s telegraiia 15B and 159 (India Office numbers p.2.1898-9, copy to Foreign Offi ce on 27th March) regarding the report of an Iraqi scheme to occupy Kuwait territory up to tne 2or ridge. As Fowie says, aggression on this scale sounds unlikely, and it seems possible that the Shaikh’s police might be able to deal, at any rate in the first instance, with an Iraqi incursion on a modest scale. It would certainly be paradoxical and unfortunate ii the Political Resident had to call on the Royal Air Force in Iraq, with whom responsibility for the defence of Kuwait rests, in order to repel an invasion of Kuwait territory by Iraqi forces* We will let you have in due course any further comments on these points that we get from Fowle. fours sincerely sd. R.PeelConfldentl *1 Political Agency, Kuwait, 27th April, 1939. D.O. No. C/189 5Iy dear Sir Tnanchard, 10 to Could you please refer to your demi- official letter No. 380-S of the 2lst April? There are no ?ersians f or j^ersons of even remote Iranian origin, in the Sh aikh Police. He does not encourage ianigration of Persians, ard on the contrary, has forbidden it, an order which dates back several years. i , ;. \ . Yours sincerely, The Hon # ble Sir Trench ard Powle, KCIE., CHS., Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. \ v . * k\CONFinXNTLAL Telegram Prom To No. Q Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait. 282. Dated and received the 4th May, 1939 . Baghdad despatches Nos. 178 and 179 of April 20th. Please let me have your comments hy post - Resident - c5'lCONFIDENTIAL. 1 )! /A No. 437-S of 1939• | _ CO SFJD EN TIA L l I \ NoJ&amp;l. %£■ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents bis compliments to 1 . Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, KCFS. ,CSI. .MVO. , Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. S? 2. G. de Gaury Esquire, MC., Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated... Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date 1 . r\'i India Office letter No.P. 2 . 1978/39 of the 5th April 1939, with enclosure, v fl 2. Letter No.436-S of the 3rd May 1939 to R.T.Peel Esquire, MG.,The India Office, London. Subject. Persians in KuwaitIndis Office FhltfthPlX, S.v’.l 5th April, 19^9. P.^ # 197B/39 My derr Fowl©, Kith reference to the corresoondence relating to the recent campeign of prooegrnda in Iraq against the Shaikh of Kuwait I enclose for your infornation a cc of a letter sent to the Foreign Office which is self- explanatory, Ke should be grateful for sny comw^nt? you may wish to make on the ooints raised by the Foreign Office end in narticuler with regard to King Ohazi*? allegation about the Sheikhas oollcy of using Persians in his police and encouraging Persian immigration. Yours sincerely sd, B,T,?eel The Hon.Iit.Col.Slr T.C.W.Fowle, KCTE. ,CBE., His BritPimle Wrjesty's Consuifte- General, BushireP*Z.1978/39. Indlf Office, Whitehall, S.r.i. ^th ^pril, 1339. Deer Eyres, *hen you esme round to se* UP Uet . e -v ln connexion vlth the Irsqi-Kwrlt troubles you mentioned three notnts on -*’hlch it was thought desirable that Fovle mi^ht be consulted* These vere - (e) Vhet is the strength of the alleged oro«treqi feeling in JCmait end ho? far is it responsible for the recent trouble ? This is partly answered by the Kurrit Intelligence Summary for the period 16th~£8th February (cooy to Foreign Office with India Office letter F.7.1744/39, dated £Bth March), in paragraph £4 of which it is stated that 'there are in fact a few Kuwaitis who would like to join Iraq, estimates varying betwe n 10 and 80, their leader being Abdulla as Stqr, a man ’ho owns estates in Iraq, which he is frightened of losing, and who owes the Ruler money'. It seems unlikely that the strength of pro-Iraqi feeling in ^uralt is of any consequence or would have *iven any troiible if it bed not been encouraged from Iraq by proosgfmd© against the Shaikh and possibly by other means* (b) What substance is there in the King's allegation (Bagdad telegram 91) that the Shaikh employs Persian police and encourages Persian emigrants in order to enable him to control his own people ? Boustoun-Boswal denied this, and on our present information we have no reason to doubt that he was right. There 1 ? of course a considerable Persian minority in Kuwait about which tho previous Iraqi Government made / enquiries H.M.Eyres, Esq., Foreign Office.u V - 2 - enquiries (ef. Forte's letter to Peterson of the IPth January, No.50-S, copy enclosed t 1th India Office letter of the9th February, ?.Z.851/39, and connected correspondence) end the Tresis seem to he genuinely (though mistakenly) uneasy on the subject. (c) Ho* can ?e carry out our obligation to orotect Kureit if force should be used by Iraq ? The, question ppsslbly has reference to Fo^le T s telegrams 158 and 159 (India Office numbers ?.Z.1898-9, cony to Foreign Office on 27th March) regarding the report of an Iraqi schema to oocuoy Kuvrtt territory uo to the 7or ridge. As Fo*#e srys, aggression on this scale sounds unlikely, snd it se^ms possible that the Shaikh 1 s police might be able to deal, at any rate in the first instance, with an Iraqi incursion on r modest scale. I It would certainly be paradoxical and unfortunatetf the i Political Resident had to call on the Royal Air Force in Iraq, with whom responsibility for the defence of Kuwait rests, in order to repel an invasion of Kuwait territory by Iraqi forces. We will let you have in due course any further comments on these points that we get from Fovle. Yours sincerely, sd. B.T.Peel.CONFIDENTIAL. The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon^le the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* i i and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). with the remark that the Director of the paper is apparently the Assyriai who was formerly an Iraqi Government British Adviser*s clerk. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 6th_ May, 1939. Keference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Li 1 Extract from Newspaper **ATHRA H edited in Beyrouth dated April 15th, 1939.Saturday. April tsth, 1939 «'§ n IRAQ GN THE OF HITLE 1 - (CONTD FROM P. 1 ) Kuwait was subjected to'| England’s political influence which had on several occasions intervened to prevent it passing into the possession of the Wahha bi State. In 1850 Kuwait was recommended by General F. !\. Chesney as the terminus of his proposed Euphrates valley railway ; and 50 years later it attracted much attention as a suitable site for the terminus of the Berlin-Baghdad railway. In 1898 Turkey, under German influence, made an attempt to oceupy Kuwait which was met by a British protest against infringment of the status quo, and in 1899 Shaikh Mubarak ibn Sabah who died in 1915 after a reign of 20 years placed his in terests under British protection. The great war put an end to the Berlin railway scheme and British military units were stationed there in connection with the blockade of the Turks, with whom the sympathies of Salim, son of Mubarak, were engaged. During Salim’s reign relations with former Najd — nov Saudi Arabia —were unsatisfactory and in 1919 a Wahhabi attack was repulsed by British aeroplanes. Another Wahhabi attack took ATHEISM IK IRAQ place during the frontier troubles of 1927-8 without success. The present ruler of Kuwait is Amir Shaikh At;mad tbn Jabir, a grandson of Mubarak, who succeeded in 1921 on the death of Salim. The boundaries of Kuwait and Najd were fixed by the treaty of Muhammarah in 1921. But for the malicious propa ganda recently conducted against the Amir which resulted in riots at one of which the ruler of Kuwait was wounded, the provin ce has enjoyed a period o f proportionate peace and growing prosperity as is admitted by the Iraqis themselves other than cer tain official circles whose false « persecution propaganda » gave rise to a British protest. It is now an established fact that agitators and trained disturbers of peace in the guise of teachers and merchants were sent to Kuwait . to bring together some diicorded voices and ask for unity with Iraq, just on the lines of Hitler. This problem has many other aspects involving as it does the future interests of Iran and Sa’udi Arabia which we will treat in next issues of Athra, not forgetting the constant travels of Captain Degorry, a former British Intelli gence Officer in Iraq, now the political resident in Kuwait. The Young Moslem looks af life f BY Tv MurbyT. Titus D D; Ph* D ( 1937. PR. -I6F ^67&gt; f I 1 J B I I 1 1 1 I I I I « I £ K B I IB I &lt;! C 1 1 ! I K I i M CHIVALRY OF (CONTD FROM P. 1 ) is thus that I appeal to you and to many others with the firm hope — ’ * ' ’ ~ with your means and your cons cience. Let us place ourselves for THE YOUNG MOSLEM LOOKS AT RELIGION ; Are you a Moslem ? I asked a young man as we stood talking together at Ur junction in the heart of the Mesopotamian desert while waiting for the train hr Baghdad. Am I a Moslem ? repeated the young man. Well, I was, but re cently I joined the anti-God so* ciety. To-day I am an atheist. 1 don’t believe in religion. It divi des people, and makes them fight each other, and hinders progress Irak would be better off without any religion at all. It * uld be better, if we all gave up cur sen seless differences, and began to work together for the good of our country. Then the Jews, and these Assyrian Christians here , and the Moslems could make a great country out of this ancient land of Irak. But as it is, 1 see no chvnce. Are there many Moslems who have joined your anti-God socie ty ? Not very many, for the idea is new to us Moslems; we are a very conservative peop’e. But we are spreading our atheistic ideas and the number is growing slowly. &amp; II 'ffi ES K 01 U W OBi £38 liS 0-4 The Foreigner student in America (Near East p. 70) BY Philip K. HittlK— *X\ ***»: .gz All communicaMons should be addressed to^* VUSUF MALEK DIRECTOR, ATHRA P - Box S57 iflF '■ BEYROUTH OFFICE : RUE DE SYRIE , ^ First Year N° 19 z^mmx*. 3iEa^»eieK=a®(®3K ANNUAL SUBSCRIPTION RATES SYRIA &amp; LEBANON ^ 40 French Frcs. ( OTHER COUNTRIES A fortnightly political review One Guinea * aeJ ****** ***^)» **— -****g GERHAN STSTE OF ESPIONAGE Satf ^jSy, Acfll 15t| 1939 Price 5 L- S- Piastres IS A GERMAN EMISSARY ? F OR sometime now, an insignificant number of Assyro-Chal- deans have been talking of an emigration plan to Paraguay which they said was put up to them by one John Dzirne’ who had told them that he was the Consul for Paraguay. Some of them did in fact ask me to express my opinion ; that was over two years ago. I waited for developments and with the items of news which I have been able to gather from those whom the said Consul emplo yed as dupes, I am now in a position to express my personal opi nion from which I hope my compatriots will benefit. It is now over two years since Mr. John Dzirne’, a medical doc tor, approached some Assyrians and discussed with two or three of them in an isolated room in rue des Franfais in Beyrouth his plan of emigration, yet we find that his plan has been kept secret and this fact forces into us the belief that that plan, with all its at tractions and temptations, is a cover for some underhand work. Although the seed sown by the German espionage system among the Assyro-Chaldeans must fall on barren soil, yet we find it high time to warn our compatriots to be on their guard so that they may not be caught from within and without by the diabolical organisa tion which will have devastating results. This same system was res ponsible tor districts to be despoiled of crops and cattle, villages and towns to be destroyed and famine in its most terrible forms to reign in Armenia during the world war. The yataghan which the Ottoman Turk employed was German make. The idea of the Germans is to organise intelligence service in virgin lands and to infuse into every unit a spirit of lawlessness and a determination to disturb the peace and public order : and they offer piece goods and cash inducements as part of their plan of silent campaign. A mere is a aangtntiieaa irwe ao ncu cane aie vvarmng aeriousi'y particularly in this troubled period of Europe. We must realize at once the importance of keeping all sincere hands at work and, as a whole, stand firm and by concerted action make the penetration impossible and counteract these and other grave menaces, and greater caution must be taken to prevent the infiltration of German emissaries in our new Home, failing which there will be wide spread disorders. . The Germans are displaying their marvellous system of spie by sending out to the East hordes of religious Missionaries, artistes merchants, medical doctors, architects and archaeologists, but they are all linked up together working hard for one and only one oh ject at present — the fomentation of disturbances. Every Nation has its parasites and opportunists and so we have, but we ask the sincere and loyal servants of Assyro-Chaldea to re main alive to the best interest of their Nation, and we trust it will be made virtually impossible for the Germans to continue their intrigues which may he encouraged by the absence of adequate con trol and lack of knowledge of their methods, some of which we are nationally bound to expose. We ask the authorities to act with rapidity and boldness and to vigorously destroy all hotbeds of Nazi subversive activities. Our journalistic investigations leave no doubt that Mr. John Dzirne is a German emissary or else why be in Austria at the present time, a country subjected to German invasion ? Dzirne’s presence at this time in the occupied territory of Austria was repor ted to us by an Assyrian student in that country, and it is quite pos sible that Dzirne has a net of agents in addition to soma either de moralized and freebooting demagogues. YUSCf MALEK. IRAQ ON THE FATH OF HITLERISM SEEKS EXPANSION AT THE COST OF KUWAIT w i J a i. i i i i i iiiiiimiiiiiiigiM IRAQ HAS GONE BANKRUPT Sayyid Nuri Sa’id, the Iraqi Premier, broadcast a speech from the Baghdad broadcasting Station on the night of March 30, 1939 on the occasion of his cabinet pro gramme. He was compelled, in order to condemn his predeces sors’ rule, to admit that « The unfortunate events of the past also seriously affected the finan cial position of the country. The State has been unable to carry out any important development schemes since 1936. In 1936 the Treasury had a reserve of Iraqi Dinar 700,000. To-day the State is indebted to the extent of about one million dinars, and the reve nues from the oil royalties, which amount to about two million dinars annually, have been pledged as security... Such a state of affairs is very hard on the country. Not only have we no reserve at present but there is an actual deficiency of about Iraqi Dinar 800.000, in addition to a further sum of Iraqi dinar 652,000 which we are bound to pay although no authority has ever been obtained for the expenditun of this amount ». On the other hand, Sayyid Ja’far Abu Timman the prominent Shi’i leader (Minister of Finance in Hikmat’s cabinet) did accuse in a public speech he had broad cast on the overthrow of Yasin a! Hashimi’s cabinet in which th&lt; present Premier was a member, that that government was res ponsible for the ruination of tin country financially due to the bad organisation of authority and it; abuse for personal ends. I m the Shi i Euphrates in seasonal t u r m o i 1 against the minority Sunni government of' igluiad ; the four northern Kurdish pro vinces awaiting their opportunity to disrupt their artificial ties with a rule they have disowned froh) the very start ; the Yazidis ambi tion for unity with Syria under French protection ; the eveiir present separatist movement ijj Basrah; the Assyro-Chaldeans desire to leave the country ii| which they have been forced ti&gt; stay ; the fearful division in thfe Iraq Army and Air Force and t h e deeply - rooted habit of leading internal and external politics by the Army; the swinging of the Iraqi people between Nazism which has penetrated in all government and public servi ces, and between Communism with its active agents at work’; the annual problem of unbalanced budget, the artificially united Iraq faces to-day some of. t h outstanding issues to which \vi have alluded briefly, and no^ auas a dew pibin^m ' That Q0 seeking expansion at the cost of Kuwait because Hitler is teariiig the map of Europe and invading ■mall countries. In our previous editorial we have given an outline of Iraq’s inimical attitude towards the Amir j|^vuwait, an attitude not inspireci by any true patriotism, but with the object of making room for the ever increasing demands ofseekers of government employment which in the East supplies milk and honey in abundance. Kuwait ia a port situated at the N. W. angle of the Iranian gulf, 29° 20’N and 40* OO’E., lying on S. side of a bay of 20 m. long and 5 m. wide, the mouth of which is protected by two islands forming a fine natural harbour with excellent anchorage in 4 to 9 fathoms of water. It engulfs a territory of some 4000 square miles with a populalion of some 80,000 Arabs and Iranians. It is 80 miles due S. of Basrah and 60 miles S. W. of mouth of Shat al Irani-al-Arabi. Some years ago political reasons gave an impetus to the development of the A Hasa ports, the province of the former kingdom of Najd, exten ding soum along the West coast of the Iranian gulf, with an average width of 50 miles from the frontier of the Kuwait enclave. » (CONTD ON P. 2) THE CASE OF PALESTINE BY 314 pp. DOUGLAS V. DUFF. London : Herbert Jenkins. 1938. Net 12s. 6d. REVIEWED BY D. EARSUM PERLEY Here is an exceptionally scho larly work written objectively by a man who himself had filled a Poor Knight’s Saddle for some ten years, having fir*t mounted into it in 1922 as a young officer of British Gendarmerie « in char ge of the peace of the Holy Ci ty ». In the first chapter of three witty pages ' ( THE RIDERS IN THE SADDLE ) he defines the title of his ^book, the purpose of his visit to&gt;Palestine, and the ba sic issue involved. The Knights Templar, in the days of the First Crusades, were called the Poor Knights, who were enlisted to be the armed defen ders of the roads to, and the kee pers of the peace of, Palestine. Today Britain *its in their Saddle and the issue is, « How does she fill it ? » The author, in the Autumn of _ 1937, re-visited Palestine when 11 the partition-scheme was first published, and travelled through out the land in an old Dodge to study the reactioiis among every community to the scheme. The result of the study is presented in the form of a symposium with 'SiHISIElISillllligHIIlIillllii CHIVALRY OF BARTON Czechoslavakian Consul refuses to .acknowledge Nazi invasion No conscionable person can fail to be moved b y the appeal made by Mr. Willianj M. Gvyynn, t h e American Consul in Beyrouth, on behalf of Mr. Barton the Czechoslavakian Consul in Beyrouth who refused to acknowledge Nazi invasion of his country and remained loyal to his Mother-land under most humiliating circumstances. The appeal of Mr. #'Yynn is personal, dictated purely by humanitarian instinct and cannot be said to be political with the object of augmenting hatred against the Nazi methods which have received general disapproval and deprecation. To our knowledge no one was ■wayed by the humbug of the D. N. B. on this affair and when democracy puts down the inhu man hand of dictators and give an end to oppressive and mis-governments, Mr. &amp; Mrs Barton will have occasion to forget their heart - breaking hardships and will fejwe t h e everlasting honour having remained faithful to their dear country which has been ravished. Mr. Gwynn’s letter, which is reproduced below, was in French, but its translation into English has been done by Athra for the easy reference of its English readers. The circtilar letter ran as follows : BEYROUTH, MARCH 20, 1939 you are no doubt aware Mr. and Mrs. Barton are in a very difficult position. The very foundations of their lives are shattered and what constituted their livelihood exists no longer. They have very litlle money at their disposal and they do not know what to do or wbat is to become of them. They have made m,.T' friends in Rebut, which in all probability will he their last post. The idea has probably occured to you, as it has to many others, that you would like to do something for them, or see something done to help them through this critical period until they can see their way more clearly and attempt to reconstruct their lives. Several persons of the Consular Corps and of Beirut society have spoken to me on this subject, and I took it upon myself to ask the permission of Mr, and Mrs Barton to collect funds for They accepted with gratitude, but I should add that this senti ment was not unmixed with something approaching humilia tion and despair. However, thev realise that this is not the mo ment for false pride. They have authorized me to act, and it ( CONTD ON P- 2 ) conclusions, and the group of symposiarchs includes men and women from overy walk of life in the country. In a simple style, men as well as events are dra matized without venturing into the realm of misrepresentation. Partition is shown to be popular with nope. And curiously, the indigenbias Orthodox Jews look upon Jewry as a religion and ob ject most strenuously to the for mation of a Jewish state, as pro posed, because « it is not of God, but too maij made..to be of per manent service to Israel » (p. 234) ; Sir Horace Rumbold cannot restore the Chosen Race to its ancient glory — the Call must come from the real Messiah. Until then it is « arrant blas phemy » to talk*of a Jewish King dom. So holds, a representative speaker, Rabbi Moses. It is a sad commentary, but Palestine is, as it ever has been, a hot-bed of fanaticism, characteristic to every faith. Palestine must be a land of endless erusades ! At present^ it is an open sore ( it would seem ) that nothing could heal I (CONTD ON P. 2) IE TAUREAU ARE ASSYRIEN Quand, parqul, Comment et 0 C 1 fut trouve le Taureau ail6 a face humaine des Assyrlens ? et qu est ce qu’il symbolise ? M. Botta berivit alors a I’am- bassadeur de France a Constan tinople pour 1’avertir de ce qui passait. Grace k 1’insistance de I’ambassadeur, la porte finit par accorder I’autorisation de pour- suivre les travaux. Les habi tants de Khorsabad reejurent la permission de vendre leurs mai- sons et d’aller s’etablir momen- tanbment au pied du monticule. Les fouilles purent etre reprises a la condition de retablir, lors- qu’elles seraient achevbes, le ter rain dans son etat primitif, afin PAR ASHM que le village pfit btre rebati sur le meme emplacement. Enfin un commissaire turc fnt envoyb a Moussoul pour preveuir de nou- veaux empechements. Toutefois, ce ne fut que le 4 Mai 1844 que, les firmans que Botta rbclamait depuis sept mois, arriverent. A la meme bpoque, un grand nombre d Assyriens nestoriens, chassis de leurs montagnes par les Kurdes &gt; vinrent se rbfugier a Moussoul et dans les villages des environs. (6) (a suivre) (6) Bedir Khan Bey, le plus cruel des chefs Kurdes, en 1843, envahit la contrbe des Tiyaris (la plus fameuse tribu assyrienne) et apres avoir massaerb, avecune sauvagerie inou'ie, 10,000 de ses habitants, emmena en captivite un grand nombre des femmes et des enfants. Une partie de ces prisoniers furent libbrbs par 1’in- tervention de Sir Stratford Can ning qui amena la Porte a envoyer un commissaire en Kur distan dans 1 intention d’engager Bbdir Khan Bey et les autres chefs Kurdes a les laisser fibre, mais, des centaines de ces rbfu- gibs tombbrent ehsuite ■ous 1’in- fluence nocive des maladies in- fectieuses et surtout de 1’bpidbmie de la fievre maligne. il(IIIIIIig]gijlllsyiIIllllilIijllllII[I l Ii n ii g|IIH|||lv|Kala&gt; MURDER OF BRITISH CONSUL IN MOSUL FOUR ARABS OF MOSUL HAVE MURDERED THE BRITISH CONSUL IN MOSUL WE WILL COMMENT LATER ON. LEBANON Visit the summer resorts of Lebanon. It is a country you would like to see.I IJgJLIJLjLS SSOEST , From Political Agent, Kuwait., To Political Resident, Bushire, Ho. 0/206 dated Kuwait, th© 5th May, 1959, t Refereno© pai’agraph 4 of enclosure to India Offi ce Printed Letter Ho. P.Z.2393 of April 21, 1939, 2. It ocours to me that a year or so ago the same reply might hay© 'been given about seizure of the Shaikh # s date gardens in Iraq., which demonstrably our influence at Baghdad has since been unable to prevent., According to Baghdad telegram Ho, 160 of April 25th to Foreign Office (copy to you under Ho. 36), the view there now is that the Royal Air Force in Iraq, is not to be used for the protection of luwait, and further, vide your telegram Ho, 165 of March 26th to Baghdad, it is not to be used to demonstrate our readiness to protect it. At the same time, it is regarded by the Charge d* Affaires as Inexpedient to give a broad bint to the Iraq.! Government which would deter it from occupying Kuwait, or part of it, (see Baghdad telegram Ho. 40/Saving of 20th April to Foreign Office, ami copy to you under Ho,4/Saving) although I see that you are still pressing for this broad hint to be given - your telegrams Has, 260 of £4th Auril ones, in regard to Kuwait are shown to be worth little (see Baghdad Hot© Ho. 128 of 25th March to Sayid Hurl as Sayid), and in any case Iraq Cabinets are notoriously unstable, while, vide Baghdad despatch Ho. 178 of 20th April, 1939, the Prime Minister admits that he cahaot and 268 of 27th April to India Offlea. 3. Moreover, Iraqi Government promises, even written Ncannot always ensure execution of his own orders. 4. Boyal Naval, Boyal Air Force and Special Intelligence reports all independently confinE that there is so:ae sort of Iraqi plan for the occupation of Kuwait, or a part of it, now in existence (see your telegrams No. 159 of 5« Oh Piously too, the continued successful occupation of the Shaikh’s gardens will have an encouraging effect on those who are pursuing an anti-Kuwait or/and anti-British policy. 6 . The possibility of occupation of Kuwait territory by Iraqi forces, therefore, cannot be disregarded, and. 1 suggest that we should in view of the above now consider what action, if it occurs, or is apparently about to occur, will be possible by (1) us and (2) the Kuwait authorities* 7 • Uhder the Kuwait Order in Council, Iraqis in Kuwait com© under the jurisdiction of the Shaikh, but it would be difficult for his small force to eject Iraqi forces in any strength, and if we advise him to eject the Iraqi forces from his territory, he will, I can confidently assume, immediately deny his ability to do so, and, ask us to imple ment our promise of protection* / As I understand our policy, the British forces in Iraq are not to be used to eject the Iraqi forces from Kuwait, or deter them from entering Kuwait, as a clash between Iraqi and British forces is undesirable, although no ground forces other than the Boyal Air Force Armoured cars in Iraq could arrive here under several days* On the other hand judging from past experience the Iraqi Government are not so sensitive or so courteous towards the British Authorities, or strongly in control of their own forces and aaninistration, as is sometimes sugges- Harch 25th and 213 of April 5th).suggested, and diplomatic representations alone may, a-nfl almost certainly will, fail to secure immediate withdrawal of the Iraqi forces* If this is so, every day they stay will have a worse effect in Arabia, where our promise of protection of Kuwait is widely known. It seams to me, who am perhaps not in a position to know all the relevant facts, that this situation is not a happy one, and I suggest that to relieve the mind of my successor, he he informed how His Majesty’s Government have decided to prevent occupation of Kuwait by Iraqi forces; how they intend in fact to support the 'emphatic negative' of 3ir Lancelot Oliphant to His Boyal Highness the Emir Eeisal on the 24th March, 1939, mentioned in the despatch which I have quoted. If, however, we have no^| plan, and no relevant facts are unknown to me, then ray suggestion is that without delay the Shaikh of Kuwait be helped by us to fora a military force efficient enough to deter the Iraqis from occupation. A tribal Levy force is what, in that case, comes to my mind, and An which I attach a very brief note. If the broad hint, already suggested by you, is not to be given to the Iraqi Government, and the facts are as above, I can see no alternative to this course and I would recommend swift attention to this matter, for, the occupation of part of Kuwait territory by an Iraqi General might well lead to embarrassing repercussions in Iraq and Arabia. Political Agent, Kuwait.\ /Z'f, i'' Cost to His Majesty’s Government of suggested British fostered force under the Shaikh of Kuwait. ) Approximate . £, per (a) Otxe British Officer, from Indian frontier, to he annum, second in Command under the Kuwait Oomaiander-in- Chief, responsible for training of force in peace 1,000 (b) One British Mon-Ooramissioned Officer... 500 (Shaikh of Kuwait to provide suitable quarters). (c) Contribution towards pay aM maintenance charges of the corps... t,500 (4) Overhead cost of supply of additional equipment, gift of machine guns, L.A^ and gift of light Armed cars signalling stores etc. i.e. in first instance only.... 3,000 Total £ 3000/- down, and £ 3000/- a year thereafter. Note: - Kuwait Arabs are fine fighters (they left 700 IKH7AN Arabs dead on the battlefield of JAHRA in 1921, and fought a dashing and successful action against DIJSHAN .Arabs in 1929). Many are really magnificient shots, and the Political Agent has seen them hit flying birds with a rifle shot. Advantage, therefore, should be taken of this native ability; local dress, custom and tactics not being destroyed in favour of other forms, since they appear, and are, more formidable as they are. Development of extra hitting power and greater celerity of communications by means of Field Wireless Telegraphy are the main points upon which a frontier officer would probably find it desirable to concentrate in training.Co nfidential D # 0« No. 0/217 My dear Sir Trenchard, You will hare noticed that the Iraqi Government are in the hahit of maJslng statements f 'based on no subs tantial facts 9 hut for which the Embassy require a reply by this Agency, through you* I quote three very recent instances: (a) statements about Persians being introduced by the k . | d (a ,; fiT I Shaikh {Your letter No, 3803 of 21st April 1939) (b) Nuri’s statements to the Charge ^Affaires about increase of smuggling if the Saudi Blockade of Kuwait is terminated (see Baghdad despatch Mo. 179 (q) The Nut ass arIf Basra’s implications that I have been improperly questioning Iraqi police officers etc. (Baghdad Nos. 152/5/39 of 10th April and 152/10/39 Of 17th April, 1939). Beplies take time, are sometimes difficult because littl or no data is given, and gave this Agency unnecessary work. I wonder if you would care to suggest that in future the Embassy should (a) discourage or (b) require from the Iraqis fuller details of the basis of such Iraqi statements, before passing them on to us for reply iu/eiu. iKua . b. !vl&gt; Tours sincerely, The Hon’ble Sir Trenchard Yowla, KOIE Hon’ble Sir Trenchard Yowls, KOH., OER # , Political Be silent in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.Secret Political Agency Kuwait, Hay 5th, 1939. D.O. Ho. C/207 l' ? lly dear Sir Trenchard, Tour telegrais Ho. 282 of May 4th. I have no very useful comments to make on Baghdad despatch ^0 % 1 Ho. 178 (288/58/30) of 20th April, 1939, hut it occurs to me, on reading this despatch, on reflecting on the past attacks on Kuwait, which appear to have coincided with the accessions to power of Huri as Sayid, and recalling that hi a brother-in-law, the late Ja’afar Pasha al Askarl, under whose unfluanoe Huri came, was ardent for inclusion of Kuwait in Iraq., that Huri himself is hy no means unpleased at the Iraq.! movement against Kuwait, and that it may have his concealed approval, and even his secret encourage ment . 2. This is a matter of doubt hut it seems clearer that recent Iraqi action has been designed to demons trate to th© Shaikh of Kuwait that while on the one hand Iraq, can ham him, we, on the other hard, are unable to protect his interests, or prevent him being attacked. Hence the continuation of Press Wireless attacks, and Police Incursions, even after protests, and hence th© continued occr^ation of his gardens in spite of our protests. This lesson having been made unmistakably clear to the Shaikh, a •messenger* was to be sent to him, to pursue, and follow up, the Ira^i plan/ The Hon'ble Sir Trenchard Bowie, KCXS., CBB., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.) 0 ^f plan for domination over the Shaikh, ard over Kuwait. PI 3. It may he of minor interest that the Shaikh tells me that when Naji Shavkat came here some years ago he was particularly hospitable and very liberal towards him . The effect of this seems to have been nil. 4. I, of ocurse, entirely agree that the early marking of the frontier is very desirable, but, if my view of Iraqi policy is correct, I think it will be difficult to make the Iraq Government take action with us to do this, and I venture to prophesy endless delays, unless we press very hard for it. Yours sincerely,SBOKET. D.O. Ho. 0/208 / \ \ -Political Agency, Kuwait, May 5th, 1939 . dear Sir Trenchard, n! Will you please refer to your telegram Ho. 282 of Hay 4th in which you ask for my comments on Baghdad despatch Ho. 179 (235/1C/39) of 20th April, 1939, to Foreign Office? \ 2 * The statements of Huri as Sayid given in paragraph 4 of the despatch are, I notice, not supported hy any details leading up to his conclusions, and I think are not likely to he home out in fact. 3. A certain quantity of merchandise is absorbed by ITeJd and ^asim, ??herever it may be landed, ^ n c i most of it is very heavily taxed by the Saudi Government. f If the cost of import can he cheapened somewhat for the people and merchants of these areas, by the intro duction of the merchandise over the easier route from Kuwait, as it was formerly introduced, instead of being taken over the more tortuous routes via Jedda, Bas Tanura, Qatif, or al Uqair, it will he slightly advantageous, both in this way and in time to the Saudi receiving merchants, and of course financially advantageous to Kuwait. On the other hand the close control of the caravans from Kuwait, which has already been devised, will ensure both that the goods are taxed at the Saudi frontier, and that they reach their destination. Once they have been so taxed and/ Ehe Hon’hie Sir Trenchard Fowls, KOIS., OHS., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.- 2 ** Qtf) and reached their distant destination in Central Arabia it would appear to he madness economically to send them’ ) off again in the direction of Iraq for smuggling, and if this were not so, then they would he so sent off now, and smuggled now. I entirely agree with the statement made hy the Charge d'Affaires in paragraphs 7 and 9 of the despatch. It is true that Kuwait first came into existence as the port for Central Arabia. Yours sincerely,and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp Kuwait. Dated .?7 th 1^39, Reference to previous correspondence : Senior Naval Officer’s letter No.461 of 15th April 1939 Description of Enclosure. C Name and Date Letter in original dated 11th April 1939 from Khalid Sulaiman al Saadani, Basra, to Political Resident.. Subject. Kuwait Agitation. j -1 $ /? • '—’ ^ f\ to*™ or ' J ST /V75 Utouq njutxu^b . . ^ kxsL /3«^AA.e^ M ■p Iak l&lt; m(u Telegram From To Repeated to - No. Q, Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire. His Majesty's Arobassador, Baghdad. C/259 Dated the 21st June, 1939. Visit of Iraqi Forei n Minister to Saudi Arabia via Kuwait. Shaikh received today a letter from HAMID AN N\QIB stating that Iraqi Foreign Minister is proceeding on June 24th or June 25th to Saudi Arabia and that he wishes to travel via Kuwait. NAQXB hoped that Shaikh wou d entertain the Foreign Minister when opportunity could be taken to discuss Kuwaiti Iraii affairs. If Shaikh did not wish to entertain the Foreign Minister he (NAQIB) would put him up in his house in Kuwait. 2. Shaikh is ansv/ering that he will be pleased to entertain Foreign Minister as his private guest but that he cannot on any account discuss Kuwait Iraqi affairs. 3 , The Shaikh's reply seems to be the only reasonable one and I think Shaikh will adhere to not discussing Kuwaiti Iraqi affairs. Should matter arise Shaikh proposes to reply that all negotiations must go through the JtaiitlaaixAgan British Government. I i-' - Political Agent -Telegram From His Majesty # s Ambassador, Baghdad, H.M*s Secretary of State for Foreign R To Affairs, London. No. 226 Repeated to • Political Resident, Bushire. No. 42 Political Agent, Ku ^it. No. 24 Saving 'by Bag to H.M’s Ambassador, Cairo. No. 18 Dated the 21st and received the 22 nd June, 1939 . My telegram No. 225. Minister for Foreign Affairs will leave Basra by road for Kuwait morning of June 26th and will spend one or two days in Kuwait before going on to Riyadh to visit IBN SAUD. He will be accompanied by HAMID AL NAQIB from Basra and hopes to use opportunity of his passage through Kuwait to see Shaikh and to do something to dispel uneasi ness at the atmosphere created by events earlier in the year. I assume that Shaikh will wish to offer him Minister for Foreign Affairs will come back to Iraq, by the same route and will give warning from Riyadh of date of his return to Kuwait. In Riyadh Minister for Foreign Affairs expects to discuss (a) tribal raids on the frontier and machinery for settlement e.g. joint commission. (b) demarkation of frontier at MUQUR. He hopes to be able to avoid arbitration (c) to ascertain nature of Ibn Saud’s misgivings concerning Iraqi attitude towards creation of monarchy in Syria. rv-'-'T hospitality during his stay Mf. NEWTON -Telegram From Political Resident, Bushire To H # M*s Secretary of State for India Repeated to - H.M’s Ambassador, Baghdad Copy by post to Government of India* No 345 Dated the 22nd and received the 23rd June, 1939. Important* ,b rD ' My immediately preceding telegram in which I repeated Kuwait telegram No. 259, June 21st to India Office, and Baghdad telegram No. 226 to Foreign Office, 2. Since NAQIB (whose letter was first intimated to Kuwait of proposed visit) definitely stated that Foreign Minister would discuss Kuwaiti Iraqi affairs, Shaikh had no alternative but to reply as he did. It is of course the declared policy of His Majesty’s Government that Kuwaiti Iraqi affairs should be conducted through proper channer, i.e. the Embassy (0*g« vide paragraph 4 of Foreign Office telegram No. 98 of March 30th, to Baghdad). )p W 0 3 . Even though politics cannot be discussed, I dare say that meeting between the Shaikh and Foreign -inister will improve atmosphere. June 21st Resident -^ ^ • 7- Translation of an article published in -AL-BA-AeTSoamat- an 'Iraqi daily news paper. ^ ^ m Aiil a a-^V«I« &gt; BAOHDAD - Monday, 20 th May T I 94 fi . ;«IM WILL THE DISTRICT OF KUWAIT RETURN TO ttto nAcJL . PRWltJCE - KUWAIT teiHClkLlTV'-- i Iq rlntfa-'i, i.S., 3A, %iS COMiiSG UHDER BfelSH l^TI^T^T^HV' ^ KilCTEb imTo the Kimrorm-'Q],- P ‘ J °R- By - Sabri Abdullcadir Al-Hashemi. Betired Captain. I read in tbe last publication of 'AL-BA’ATH AI&gt; 0 Awmt» No. 72 dated the 14th May, 1946 the following telegram;- ^ ♦♦IBAQ CLAIMS KUWAIT” The Damascus paper 'Alif Ba' pfiblished the telegram the origin of which was Baghdad. It seems from a rumour circulating in the verandahs of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Baghdad that the »Iraq (Government will lay claim to the area of Kuwait and that they may raise this matter when negotiations for the revision of the Anglo—Iraqi Treaty taiie place. This Amirate is situated at the end of the Gulf of Basrah, and is adjacent to the borders of ’Iraq. It is situated between* t? 7 o great Arab governments - ’Iraq and Saudi Arabia - and its bound aries extend from Urn Qasr, south of Zubair, to Al Batin, and end e# at Has al Qubla, south of Kuwait. Its length is 180 miles and its width about 20 miles* Its area is about 50,000 square miles. Its population about 120,000, all Arabs following the creed of Iman Malik, and related to the Mutair Tribe. It is one of the principal ities under British protection. This principality came under the desteatable imperialist protection in 1913 as a result of the plot made by shaikh Mubarak as Subah with his son to assassinate shaikh Abdulla Ruler of Kuwait, and his brother larrah, so that he might seize power. Mubarak indeed put his plan into operation and murder ed Shaikh Abdulla while Mubarak’s son murdered Jarrah, shaikh Abdullas brother. Thus he seized the rule, but the free men of Kuwait were indignant at this faefc- deed. , The children of the murdered shaikh fled and took refuge in Basrah where they demanded that the Turkish Wali of Basrah should take action in connection with the affair and punish shaikh Mubarak and his son. In answer to this request, the Wali of Basrah sent a Turkish battleship carrying some officials to inform shaikh Mubarak that he should go to Constantinople and choose between two alternative - either to be a member of the Mejlis ud Dawlah, or to live outside Kuwait S territory on a pension allotted to him by the Ottoman Govern ment. As soon as Shaikh Mubarak heard that the Turkish vessel had left Basrah he wrote to the British Agent in Bushire asking his protection. The British Agent hastened to send a warship on the wings of speed. It arrived in the harbour of Kuwait before the Turkish battleship and forbade her to approach the port or to take any action. So the Turkish battleship returned whence she had come. In this deplorable and detestable manner, this province came under the de facto protection of the British Government from that date. Following this strange event the British Government concluded an agreement with the murderer Shaikh on the lines of the agreements with the rulers of those countries which the British intended to colonise, to the effect that Kuwait should not have relations with anj foreign country whatsoever. This means that Kuwait is forbidden o communicate with ’Iraq or Saudi Arabia. Thus the British through the intermediary and by scheming rendered impossible the assimilation o /this smallI — 2 — (B5J this small principality with 'Iraq or Saudi Arabia, Although we do not know the facts of this new claim of 'Iraq, there is one point that must be realised - that the struggling Arabs are not satisfied with the conditions prevailing in Arab countries in general and in the principalities of the Arab Gulf in particular. There are evident differences between one part and another of the Arab world, but everywhere the struggle continues to rid it of the hated coloniser whatever his race, except in the protected principalities and Sheikhdoms under British protection. We have not yet heard that such and such Amir has demanded that the British evacuate his country, or at least permission for closer relations with the independent Arab states bordering his Amirate to increase the bonds between sons of one motherland. It seems that their Highnesses have made up their minds to keep Greater Arabia cut limb from limb, ] preferring for the sake of false power, the security of British protection to the union of the Arab lands. Whatever may happen it is certain that the Arabs, zealously struggling in the way of Arabism, will one day reach their goal of Unity of the Arabs and removal of all the obstacles at present dividing brother from brother. Indeed the boundaries set up between the Arab countries after the last Were were established to weaken them in their countries and to colonise them indivudually, and to force them to work for the benefit of the coloniser in ex ploiting the e wealth of these lands; to facilitate imports from the (coloniser's) country and to surround them with a strong Economic Wall; and to prevent the inhabitants opening any but a few faafcaxtExiii factories..... Although these facts were previously unnoticed the present Arab awakening has made the sincere among our sons begin to stir up the honour of their kinsmen and guide them in the right direction. However strong the control of the coloniser and however strict his supervision the powerful and growing Arab renaissance will take on itself to amash all the obstacles standing in the way of the unity of the Arab nations, and tangible (sic) proof of this is the bursting of the dawn of the Arab Leaque and the union of the count ries forming it on all matters which lead to the benefit of the 'people of Dhad'. Returning to the question of Kuwait, I say that the indorp- oratlon of this country in the Kingdom of 'Iraq is essential and inevitable for many reasons. Kuwait is one of the districts of Basrah province and has no boundaries dividing her from 'Iraq except the colonial boundaries separating brother from brother. The continuation of Kuwait under British protection is a military threat to 'Iraq. How can a country like Kuwait maintain her existence in present world currents unless (God Forbid!) she decides to remain under British protection for ever thereby forgetting Arab sentiment and also the presence in 'Iraq of the many properties and possession* which belong to the Amir of Kuwait in the Basrah province. All these are crushing arguments in the hands of the 'Iraqi negotiator. A beginning was made with negotiations on the inclusion of the dis trict of Kuwait in the province of Basrah in the reign of His late Majesty King Ghazi I, but Nemesis intervened, and thus the question c of the incorporation Kuwait into 'Iraq has remained pending unti now. Therefore it has become necessary for the 'Iraqi plenipotenti* try to raise the incorporation of Kuwait into 'Iraq during the legotiations with the English for the revision of the Ang Teaty which, it is absolutely certain that they will take place iooner or later in view of the Prime Minister's statement in the ihamber of Deputies and the knowledge of the whole Arab world, and ‘oreign world too, of these statements. As the revision of this ,reaty has become part of the programme of the existing Ministry^ iherefore demand that the present Government keeps its promise end benefits from the present international position and seize ^ &gt;pportunity before it passes to initiate discussions with ^ 3ritish to regularise the relations of 'Iraq with them in a manner^ in keeping with the Charter of the United Nations A ^ liver of success.Trnaslation of an item from the newspaper 'AKEBAR' of Baghdad dated the 2nd July, 1946. H ALI KHAiN - THIS? OR POLITICAL REPUGEB? 1 * ACCUSATION AGAINST BRITISH CONSULATE Hi IRAN. Moscow. The newspaper M Rah'bar ,, published in Tehran has stated that the British Consulate at Bandar Abbas has given protection to the notorious brigand 'Ali Khan* and his gang, who have recently been looting, robbing and killing. The Gendarmie at Bandar Abbas have at the reguest of the British Consulate guaranteed txhe safety of the thieves. The Military command at Kurmaisar (sic) has protested against British interference in Iranian affairs. LES.CONFIDENTIAL ~x No. 0/448 (^y , The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his oompliments to:- The Hon'hie the Political He silent, Persian Gulf, oaaip, BAHRAIN . and has the honomr to transmit to him the undermentioned document(s i 'y THE POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. 1 . 2 . 3. Dated the 13th July, 1946 . DESCRIPTION OE ENCLOSURE. NAME AND DATE Extract from Baghdad news paper ' AL BAVATH AL-^AWM P dated the 20th Say, 1948 Extract from Baghdad news paper ' AL-NrDA ' 1 dated thei 29th May, 1§46. Extract from Baghdad news paper ' AL-J M AD 'dated thei 18th June, 1946. SUBJECT POPULAR ♦IRAQI NEWSPAPERS* ■St [RAQI NE? ATTITUDE^TWARDS PERSIAN SHAMHDOMS. LES/‘ti) **&gt; CONFIDEmAL No. 90 - 3. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Kuwait.^' and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document, ' /^v PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 14th January, 1947. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of enclosure : Number and Date ’ Subject i ? Letter No. 1314 (32/17C/46), » dated the 6 th December, 1946,’ Arab Youth movement from the British Embassy, 1 M A1-Ansar”. Cairo. ’ » i i t i i f* TCR/HME. No. 1314 32/176746 0 l+( CAIRO. 16th December, 1946. Sir, In its issue of October 26th last the weekly- review 'Akhbar El-Yom' published an article regarding an Arab Youth movement called '’Al-Ansar' which it stated existed clandestinely in all Arab countries and was directed by a secret organization called 'Council of Companions' in which all Arab countries were represented. The report mentioned that 'Al-Ansar' was keeping a close v/atch on the Arab League which it regarded as a British instrument and would eliminate every Arab leader whom it regarded as a danger to the cause of Arab unity. It would be prepared to supplant the Arab League itself if it considered that the*latter was failing in its mission of unifying the Arab world. 2. The writer of the article stated that he had obtained his information about this organization from Istanbul, Aleppo and the Lebanon. 'Al-Ansar' is stated to be desirous of organizing Arab youth clubs or hostels to facilitate the exchange of visits between the nationals of one Arab country and another and to grant special facilities for students in this connection. 3. I enclose a copy of a letter dated 4th December from Defence Security Officer, Egypt, in paragraph 3 of which the programme of 'Ai-Ansa.r' is summarized under eight headings. The Defence Security Officer reports that according to one source the leader of this movement is the ex-Mufti and that in Egypt the chief is either Mohammed Salah-el-Din Bey, who, as Nahas Pasha’s righlt-hand man in 1942, took a prominent part in the initial discussions which eventually led to the formation of the Arab League. Colonel Jenkins also mentions that Saleh Harb Pasha, the anti-British President of the Young Men's Moslem Association in Egypt, is stated by another source to be the chief of the Egyptian Branch of 'Al-Ansar'. i 1 . 4 . I would invite attention to paragraph 7 of /olonel Jenicins’ letter in which it is stated that this lovement is specifically anti-British and is said to lave the backing of both Russia and France. Azzam &gt;ashe has told Brigadier Clayton that the Arab League ire watching this movement. 5. I also enclose an extract from the 'Egyptian iazette' of 1st December containing a Reuter report on m Arab organization which is stated to be developing a Dara-military formation among its adherents and which nay conceivably be identical with 'Al-Ansar • 6 . I am sending copies of this despatch with enclosures k o nis Maiestv’s Representatives in Bagdad, ueirut, ferusalenfjedda, Amman and the Political Resident, Persian half. I have the honour to be, With the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, Sd. Ronald Campbell. The Right Honourable Ernest Bevin, r.P., Foreign Office, London, S.W.l.1'QF SECRF.T. /^ry l ^ COPY/HME. TOP SECRF.T . Ko.-.,DS(£) aOO/ 11 ?, DEFENCE SECURITY OFFICE CAIRO. ’ 4th December, 1946. Dear Ravensd&amp;le, cailed ”A 1 Ansar' k !^the d DlIciple oJtSppo?te?,^^hich a bir ti0n sen sev, up in the Arab world recently. Information rn%M sssr s this - • This movement comprises youth elements thrcuehmit tho and D F*vri d ^ « the Letencn.^anl^rdan^ and E^ypt. Its aim would appear to be to keep a watchful eye on the activities of the Arab League. Whenever A 1 Ansar considers chat the League leaders have deviated from the ' path of true pan Arabism, they will arrange for their Sentence will be passed by the council and one of the^ supporters’ will carry it out. The League, A 1 Ansar, maintains, needs watching as it is the tool of the British 3 ' Apart from its primary role of assassination, the movement is based on a programme of eight points. a. The formation of a united Arab States which will recognise all Arabs as equal citizens. This will enable them to be as powerful as their European counter parts. b. To build a strong Arab army, equipped with modern weapons, as recent history has shown that that is the most effective method of winning respect of the Imperialist powers. c. To introduce an Arab currency similar to sterling which will ensure the economic independence of the Arab States. d. To win back Palestine as an Arab state. e. To regard the Arab League as guilty of not having found a solution to the Palestinian problem. f. To organise Youth clubs in every Arab country and combine them under one central control. g. To issue special documents enabling Arabs to travel freely within the Arab States. 4. The movement is organised on a secret cell basis, the members of one group being unknov/n to members of another group Moreover, the members of each cell will be aware of the identity of one other member only, the cell leader. 5. According to one source, the leader of the movement is the Mufti. Another indicates Emir Shaklb ARSLAN, a member of the Druze family recently returned from Switzerland.COPY/HME. EXTHaCT FROM TH E 'EGYPTIAN GAZ RTTT. '. 1st December, 1946. \ TAL KS OF __ M SECRET ARAB ARMY AGAINST IMPERIALISTS ' Baghdad, November 30th. 'tt/e believe that the Arab world, and especially the Arab League, is xacing extreme dangers from the jealousies of the Big Powers - dangers we must avoid and neutralise.' , lln ^^ s ? nu tshell, is the aim of the newly-formed Pan- Arab Oiganisation for the defence of the Arab league and nrab world as described in an interview with Reuter’s correspondent by the leader of the Iraqi-branch of the organisation who has asked that his name be not divulged. The organisation's headquarters, he said, are in Cairo, with branches in Baghdad, Beirut, Damascus and Jerusalem. The Iraqi leader, a 3€-year-old Oxford graduate, who speaks, apart from English and Arabic, his rother tongue, Turkish, French, and Persian, has already written three books on western Imperialism, the Road to the Far East, and on British Colonies, using different pen-names on each book. He refused to disclose the name or anything connected with the 'Supreme Chief' of the organisation’, but volunteered information on its aims. The anonymous leader said, 'Every member of our organisa tion will be fully trained to use every kind of wear on - as any ordinary soldier. I am sure that within two years ouiL organisation will be able to put on a war footing no less than 1 , 000,000 fully-trained 'soldiers and officers'. 'Theirs will be the task to defend our homeland from any foreign aggression.' 'Our organisation is similar in many respects to the old Arab organisation that helped our prophet Mohamed control the entire Arab world within a very short time. Our array will consist of storm-troopers, as v/ell as defence an- auxiliary forces.' Interference Saying that the Arab world was facing a crisis, the leade] went on to say, 'British imperialism and American economic interference in our world, together with their interests in our oil and Middle East markets generally constitute the main danger* besetting us today. We must, therefore, stand firm and face this danger. Referring specifically to the Arab League, the Iraqi leader states : 'Although everyone knows that the League was established for the benefit of the Arabs and the Arab world, it is unfortunate that the League today is indirectly working under semi-British influence. There is no doubt about it. 'It will be our task to defend the League against Fore: influence - from whatever quarter it may be.' Watch out ....Watch out ae continuea ; 'Une of our main duties will be to watch out carefully that every Arab statesman, journalist and everyone who works for the Arab League, does his job pronerlv ™ aim ’ narael y&gt; to strengthen the league for the benefit of the Arab cause and not for the interests of any foreign power. If any of them fails to work for the realisation of this aim he will be sent to a People's Court for trial and punishment according to the organisation’s Referring to Soviet in the Near and Middle East influence 'spreading like fire the Iraqi leader said : The Russians talk too much about democracy, but they believe in imperialism just as any other imperialistic power. V agu e ’‘They are trying to gain a footing in our countries, using vague w, ords. The masses probably believe them, but the intelligentsia understands the truth behind this mask.. Persia is a good exampie ol boviet influence. No Arab wishes to see his Homeland become a second Persia. 'Our religious beliefs, traditions and customs all run counter to Soviet ideology. Besides, we believe that the Russians are like other big nations, after our oil and resources.” (R). Copied. G.A.M.C/462. /f-T No. The Political Afrent at Kuwait presents his compli m entsrt e:Hon , bl the Re8ideat Persian Gulf, Bahia n, //. i Htj and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s) THE POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT, 23rd June, 7 . Dated the of 194 REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE- DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE(S) NAME AND DATE Et-Ll-hJlTTra.: aii article fro the Arabic Daily Newspaper 'AS-SIJH' of Baghdad published on the 29th slay, 1947.7ft&gt; h&gt;(? Translation of extracts from an article written by Taha al Fayadh, editor of the Arabic £aily Newspaper AS-SIJIL ' of Bagdad, published on tl*^ ^Sth liay,1947. Th£ POSITION OF HIS HIGHNESS THB RULLK Off KITWA1T TOWARDS THE ZIONISTS . Upto date the Zionists have despaired of establi shing a bridge in the Arab World. The reason is that the Arab Principalities have maintained their traditions and are proud of their nobility and glory, in spite of the fact that their advancement in general education has been slow, **nni*%£ tn th* pulse of these Principalities, and have tried to make a breach into wV,-&lt; ch they can disseminate their pcircn and make a base for the direction of their organised movement. As soon as His Highness the Sahikh of Kuwait knew this he ordered them to be deprived of their passports and banished so as to avoid an evil which might become dangerous and difficult of solution. Thvwu steps prove that this principality, which is a neighbour of Iraq, is well awake to and aware’ of the danger, and they will help in preventing these evil tentacles from spreading to other Arab Principalities stf&amp;h as Bahrain, Muscat etc. •••«•••••••• K How badly we need the Intelligence of the Shaikh of Kuwait 2 We should folloW his leadilo cleaning his country from the filth of Zionism. But how can we do tliis when some of our leaders are captives of the Zionists who showerj?them health in divers ways. .. y/j* - / \ Tn-day 7,i 18 te 1 influence is penetratirg to important points. If the Government intends to uproot the seeds which have been sown, they must do what the Shaikh of Kuwait has done,. Esx'ecially since the evidence of their evil intentions is more apparent here than in Kuwait, but the difference the two is great. There all is being done for the welfare of the Arab World, where as here all things are opposite. ^ ft* / / i, ■ • -/ /. J \ \C \ N S\s \'vTelegram From To No. 151. Dated 16th, received 17th Feb * S’ (Apency') Political Resident, Bahrain Political Agent, Kuwait. , 1948. €&gt; It is reported that one Khalid al Atsani of Kuwait sends newspaper containing anti-British articles to people in Bahrain. Please make enquiries and telegrarh any information available regarding this man. Repgu Mb.Telegram 1 S’(Agency) From Political, Kuwait. To Pepgu, Bahrain No.165. Dated the 27th February, 1948. Your telegram No. 151 February 16th. 2. Khalid al Adsani is a Kuwaiti opponent of the Shaikh and of the present form of Government. He lives in Iraq and never visits Kuwait. A biographical note follows by mail. x Political MBThe Political Agent, Kuwait presents his compliments tos- The 08 Grotary th,; llof-’ble iiho Political r.i -he Persian dulf# and has the honour to transmit document(s) THE POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. to him a copy of the undermentioned REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE: Kuwait iijmcy telegram 'to.165 da'iad the xebi«ajy. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE(S) Name and Date :fcte dated the,29th fron the Political ii- ; ,snt» Subject Khalid oi AdcunHole, on Khalid bin Sulaiman ,al Maani, /5&gt;i IQialid bin Sulaiman al Adaard was bom in Kuwait and is now about 40 years old. H@ received primary education in Kuwait and was fond of reading the daily papers and Magazines from Iraq, $gyp'k* ^d Syria. Most of his education is the result of such reading. When the Majlis was formed in 1936 he was appointed as Secretary and President of the Young Men*s Society (KUTLA) which was opposed to His Highness. When the Majlis was dis solved he managed to escape from Kuwait and walked all the way to Basra, where he continued his disloyal actions supported by his Iraqi friends. He later on settled in Zubair and opened a business house in Basra with funds supplied by his Iraqi friend His chief work was smuggling from Kuwait into Iraq, and he is 2 said&gt; to have made a fortune during the war. He returned to Kuwait when His Highness issued the akmnosty order and ran his business between Basra and Kuwait. He used to go to Syria and the Lebanon with his father and members of his family every summer. In 1946 he made up hia mind to reside in Iraq, where he could have more freedom to write the book he intended to publish in 1946 (a surraary oi this book was publisneo. m pamphlet form last year entitled 'Half a year ol democracy in Kuwait 1 *). The pamphlet was confiscated by the Kuwait Government and Khalid dare not now come to Kuwait. He has purchased a housejin Baghdad where he is living with his iamily and he visits Basra to inspect his office work there. MB Kuwait. Dated the 29th February, 1948..</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00004a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/127</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00004a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/127</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2/1 II IRAQ PROPAGANDA. (Absorption of Kuwait by Iraq). Relations etc.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-27T23:04:29</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (154 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 156; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-154; these numbers are also written in pencil, but, where circled, are crossed through.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains correspondence in the form of telegrams, and confidential papers sent between British officials in the Gulf regarding Iraqi propaganda against Kuwait. Communications were made with former Iraqi Prime Minister Nuri Pasha al-Said and the Ruler of Kuwait, in this regard. The correspondence also contains reports about members of Al-Naqib family from Basra who were appointed as envoys from Baghdad with instructions to offer official advice to the Ruler of Kuwait. A particular name that appears in the volume is Sayid Hamid Bey Al-Naqib, Basra Deputy to the Ruler of Kuwait.The correspondence also discusses the following: the refusal by Ibn Saud of any form of unity between Iraq and Kuwait, the issue of encouraging Persian immigration to Kuwait, and the petitions raised by members of the Legislative Council in Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait, to assist in releasing political prisoners in Kuwait.The correspondence also contains letters and newspaper extracts regarding Khalid Sulaiman al-‘Adsani, Secretary of the dissolved Legislative Council in Kuwait, and about the Arab Youth movement called al-Ansar, which calls for Arab unity. Most of the correspondence in the volume (ff 2-136) is dated 1939.The main correspondence is between the British Embassy, Baghdad, the Political Agency, Kuwait, the Political Residency, Bushire, the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London, and the British Embassy, Jeddah.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Newspapers</topic></subject><subject><topic>Broadcasting</topic></subject><subject><topic>Zionism</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Kuwait Legislative Council</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Basra</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Palestine</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Annexation (International law)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Propaganda</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arab nationalism</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00004a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>