<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000f3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-10-09T17:26:43.626Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Telegram From Q Major A.C. Stewart, Bahrain. To Political Agency, Muscat. No. 124. ) / Dated and received 2nd ^aooaxy February, 1947. IMMEDIATE. Please pass following to ? Major Hudson. steamer Star of Mexico is ashore at Ras al Had and that Master requires assistance to remove Arab guards who have boarded vessel. 2 . One of His Majesty’s Ships has been asked to proceed to spot of call calling at Muscat enroute. 3. If you can get to spot before His Majesty’s Ship's arrival please do so. If not please ask Saiyid Shahab to allow you and any other representative he suggests to proceed in His Majesty's Ship. I will telegraph later expected time of arrival at Muscat. In mean time please do what you can to secure removal of any guards at present on ship. If guards are required to ensure ship's protection, they can be on shore f Jo jo but should not board vessel unless invited fynut) so by Master. 4 . Please telegraph any information you may have. Ends. -STEWART-Telegram, dated 2nd February, 1947 from Major A.C. Stewart, at Bahrain to the Political Agency, Muscat. IMMEDIATE. Please pass following to Eaajor Hudson. begins. Senior iiaval Officer, Persian Gulf, reports steamer Star of Mexico is ashore at Ras al Had and that Muster requires assistance to remove Arab guards who have boarded vessel. 2. One of His Majesty's ships bias been asked to proceed to spot of call calling at Muscat en route. 3. If you can get to spot before His Majesty's Ship’s arrival please do so. If not please ask Saiyid Shihab to allow you and any other representative he suggests to proceed in His Majesty's Ship. I will telegraph later expected time of arrival at Muscat. In mean time please do what you can to secure removal of any guards at present on ship. If guards are required to ensure ship's protection, they can be on shore but should not board vessel unless invited to do so by Master. 4. Please telegraph any information you may have. Ends. -STEWART- No.C.79. POLITICAL AGENCY AND HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S CONSULATE MUSCAT, Dated 2nd February, 1947, / Copy forwarded to the Military Adviser to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat, for information and favour of necessary action. Consul Muscat.Telegram, From. Q Political, Muscat Repgu, Bahrain To. No.C 49 Dated the 3rd February, 1947. Immediate. f /. 2. Please pass following to Major Stewart. Your telegram No. 12i( of 2nd February. Have no information on the subject. 3 , Am leaving tp-dayby launch Nasr al Bahr with State representative and small Levy Escort. Will collect Wall of Sur en route and will remove Arab Guard. 4 . Will await His Majesty’s Ship at Ras al Hadd. Consider now no need H.M's ship to call at Muscat. 5 . will telegraph myE.T.A. at Ras al Hadd later. Ends. Hudson. Political. Telegram. From To No. 125 Dated and Important. Enclair Major Stewart, Bahrain Political, Muscat received the 3rd February, 1947. For Hudson. Expected Time of Arrival Warship Wren about 1500D February 4th repeat fourth. STEWART.© h r* V Political, Muscat Repgu, Bahrain Telegram From To No.C 50 Dated the 4th February, 1947, Following for Political Agent, Muscat. Begins. Reference Muscat telegram No.C 4° February 3rd. Captain Hudson left for Ras al Hadd at 7 a.m. today. Ends. POLITICAL*C!BrT 7&gt;9 [' • . 'iO'I n.ta'irffi - • O'T . •i.n! . '?^?L % x*atrt&lt;S9% bn$i JaecfaG m pf _1 t f ■ , HfTT-} 'I' t r^’ Mo ' 7 rroYi '■ •■ fr t xj 7 &gt;qsH 0 ? 0 . V/i . '\V I t ' • ,r - •••• i* ' ' C'k 1 s( . ii 5 oa:-V t irv^-Jvv f^oiiMoH 'ro‘t 'rsh:-' C.[o’ : t . ' ■• ^TB:n‘ff&gt;' 9^1 O.oh c - *.t SSSOBlll OOii vT»*&gt; ■'■ • m.fl V &amp;b bbB:-« Xc afifl toft cTr^I noahv''''? •-&lt; ra.- ’; ::• ) ^ 'i fr-' : ?t b ^cooe't bn hniaCI .j-' : 1 'ion.':GTC Telegram. Political Resident, Bahrain Political Agent, Muscat received the 9th February, 1947 k. Following fron H.M.S WREN February 7th, Begins. Have abandoned salvage attempts owing to lack of proper equipment. Ship could probably still be saved by salvage vessels but will become total loss if left much longer. 2. Have given Master assistance with fresh water and stores as far as was rkkusscx reasonable and sent message to his owners. 3* Governor of Sur and AMr representative are ? remaining on board her and have assured ? me that they will provide protection from pilfering and that drinking water and food can be obtained locally. 4. If ship breaks up crew can land safely under most conditions and go overland to Sur. 5. There seems to be no more I can usefully do am returning to Bahrain. E.T.A. 1030D February 10th. 6 . Political Agent Muscat please inform Gray Mackenzie who are agents for this line. Ends. From To No.160 Dated andI \ ( Copy of telegram No. 160 dated the 9th February,1947, ) ( from the Political Resident, Bahrain, to the Political ) ( Agent, Muscat. ) Following from WREN February 7th. Begins. Have abandoned salvage attempts owing to lack of proper equipment. Ship could probably still be saved by salvage vessels but will become total loss if left much longer. 2. Have given Master assistance with fresh water and stores as far as was reasonable and sent message to his ov/ners. 3. Governor of Sur and Amir representative are remaining on board her and have assured me that they will provide protection from pilfering and that drinking water and food can be obtained locally. 4. If ship breaks up crew can land safely under most conditions and go overland to Sur. 5. There seems to be no more I can usefully do am returning to Bahrain. E.T.A. 1030D February 10th. 6 . Political Agent, Muscat please inform Gray Mackenzie who are agents for this line. Ends. HAY. No.C 90-19/3-G Political Agency, Muscat. Dated the 10th February, 1947. Copy forwarded to Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Muscat, for information. Political Agent, Muscat.mm - /'N Ho*C 94-19/3-C Hie PrJtannic joety* s Consulate, Moaoet. Sated the 10 th Febr^ry, 1947* Dear Mr, Jamali, mxtty thttnke for your letter of this nomine. It vaa ^ood of you to *elcoe»e n*a Imck to luacat* J enjoyw} my journey throvMil the Hatln&amp;h i^nensely and hod no difficulty on the road* Keg«ruing tlo »te or Star of exico, atjici ran arround at Pea &amp;1 Hatkl, you will appreciate that when a ship, in distress, oi^rv-&gt;ls th^.t siie is in need of assistance, this is no tin© to at©nr on cerencio'• 2 have however again reffcrrad to the letter of Eis Elghnasa, to rhioJ you refer, and aitice Uis leaves one or two points about which I as in doubt, 2 think t)wit j.erhepa ycu will agrae that it would be better for at; to rafor the whole natter to his highness either by letter, if opportunity occurs, or vtir.en I !r. All ikiha ed Al Jamil, Secretary to Hi* Highness the Sultan of -^fesoat &amp; Goan, Jfewafc*visit him, which I hoy* will bo in the very near future* In the neentine it my perhaps help to clear nsttars if ve vore to discuss the question ourselves, end if you agree I should be very glad if you would take tea with ns tocDarrcm, at say, 400* if this is convenient to ywu, if not, perhaps you ttould sug gest eccther siore suitable tirae. I trust that you are well a)id that all in hugest proB:*rs. Yours sincerely,Telegram From To No.C 60 Dated the Q Political Agent, Muscat ,4.1 Reference my telegram No. 124 January 2nd issued from Bahrain for Hudson and referring to grounding of Star of Mexico. 2. I have received letter from Secretary to Sultan in which he observes «* firstly that such information should have been sent to him secondly that Saiyid Shihab is not the authority to be approached for representative 3 . Secretary gives as reference a letter which Sultan sent me shortly before his departure, copy forwarded to you under my P.L.No.C 840-8/92 dated 19th December, 194o. ^ t Lht, ?/ f j 4 # I have replied to Secretary that Sultan’s letter under reference leaves points open for doubt and that I consider whole matter one for reference to His Highness. 5 . I am sending copies of relevant correspondence to you by mail due here on 13th February. If you agree attitude I propose take with Sultan is that services of valuable British Officer cannot be placed at disposal of State, if, he is x to be regarded as person of no authority with whom communications cannot be held even in emergency, except through their officials. I will use opportunity for early decision that Hudson should be placed in charge during Sultan’s xkxxkx absence. Hudson reports that he had full co-operation from Secretary but experienced difficulty with Saiyid Shahabin matter of launch, latter claimed Nasr al Bahr was under repair though this was doubtful and he finally left in H.D.M.L belonging to Khimji Ramdas. Political'r'S u-, r c OFFICE 0? THE SECRETARY TO THE SULTAN CE MUSCAT AND GkAN, Muscat the ixth february 1947. £&amp;UGAyt UiJ Thank y«u very much fsr y«ur letter of the 10th February 1947. I quite A£ree with you that when n ship is in distress or danger immediate aid ©ut;ht to be rendered, and it was on that consideration that all possible assistance was given to the steamer M Star of Mexico H when asked for by the Commandant of Muscat Infantry• In fact / the yali of Seer went himself to the scene of the accident, as soon as ho had heard of the ncciden^ and before the arrival of the Commandant of Muscat Infantry at that place, and rendered the necessary help® But I am not sure as to whether the request for such a help should not necessarily be sent direct te the appropriate authority of the Government. I thank you for your kind invitation to tea to-day at 4.30.pm. I shall be delighted t© be at your place at that time. Major A-C. Stewart H^fi.M’s Consul Muscat•No.C 96-19/3-G Political Agency # Muscat* Dated the 12th February, 1947. Dear Colonel Kay, . (&lt;* • Please refer to my telegram No.C 60 dated the 10th February, 1947. 2 . I fomard herewith for your information copies of letters exchanged between myself and Nioharaed al Jamali, the Sultan^ Secretary, on the subject of ray request for assist ance for the steamer M Star of Mex w . 3. I feel that Jamali is^within limits, in the right. and that the Sultan^ instructions do, more or less vaguely leave him in-charge at Muscat, perhaps therefore I should have inst ructed tiy office to take the matter up with him rather than with Hudson• 4. At the same time I feel that it would have been more appropriate had Jam&amp;li made his protest verbally. The real point, however, is that it seems to me quite inappropriate that Hudson, who after all is an officer of the Indian Political Service, and a possible future Consul at Muscat, should find him self in the position of having to take orders from the Sultan*s Secretary, even though these orders may be tactfully conveyed, and, if you agree, since it provides a suitable opportunity, I will use the occasion to press for Hudson's appointment as Adviser in-Charge at Muscat. 5. Should the Sultan not agree to appoint Hudson as Adviser, I think we should suggest that he be replaced by a Military Officer, of less value, as soon as possible, Hudson thereby The Hon'ble Lt—Col.W.R.Hay, C.3.I., C.J.K*, Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain.thereby being made available for work on the normal political cadre* 6 , I have not spoken to Hudson about this though I know that from this point of view, he would regret leav ing Muscat, where he likes the work and is very happy. Yours sincerely, P.S. When I saw Jamali nothing fresh transpired and Jamali stuck to his point that it the Sultan's intention that, apart from ceremonial purposes, he should be in charge, though he indicated that the Sultan had wanted to avoid making any very clear distinction.Telegram Enclair from YnHl AiD AX*ii«XAN£RlA To Captain Hudson care Gray Muscat. No. nil Dated and received the 12th February, 1947 Please advise Master our STARk^A salvage assistance from Karachi due soon and request him not to abandon steamer. Please keep us advised position. YAH1AS. Telegram. Enclair From Political Agent, Muscat To Senior Naval Ofxicer Persian Gulf, Bahrain Radio No.C 64 Dated the 12th February, 1947 Following has been received fromYAHlAb Alexandria. Begins. Please position. Ends. 2* I have no means of communication. Would it be possible for passing ship to transmit message by visual signal. ? 122035D PoliticalGray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES. HEAD OFFICE: 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E. C. 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BfcISREH. BUNDER-ABBAS. AMARAH. LINGAH. KUT. BAHREIN. KHORAMSHAHR KOWEIT. AHWAZ DUBAI. BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR SHARJAH BUSHIRE* MUSCAT. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR ■N REPLY PLEASE QUOTE GMC/ 15. No Muscat, I3^h^ February iq The Political ft gent &lt;k H* B, M f s Consul, Muscat* Dear Sir, 3» 3. 3T\H 0? MSX, ^ Grounded at Has al Kabh 25 miles south oi Has al Hadd» Messrs, Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Coy., Karachi, on behalf of Underwriters have authorized us to engage launch and arrage discharge of cargo on ooard the above wreck* We have requested the Director General of Customs, Muscat, to grant us a letter on the Amin of Customs, our to &gt;_;iv8 us all necessary help in landing and storing the cargo at Sur, pending further instructions* We have also requested the Secretary to, H*H* The Sultan of muscat oc Oman, ^uscat, to grant us letters on the Governor of Sur and on Wnir All bin Hsonid : A 1 Hamooda for all necessary help for all the work in connection withe wreck* We have appointed Messrs. Khimji Ramdas to land and /v store cargo and are sending our Office clerk to supervise the work. are also arranging t o send 6 skilled tindels and coolies from here to assist Sur coolies for discharging the cargo. We shall now be grateful if you will kindly grant us a letter for all necessary help we need in connection with the work of the above wreck on parties concerned at Sur and Has al Kabb. W© intend to leave at 4/00 P.M. to-day* Thanking you, Yours faithfully, For GEAY MACKJBKIE l 00,/LlI).To 1 s - all whoa it aay concern, A representative of Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Company Ltd. is visiting Sur and Has al Kalba to arrange discharge of cargo from S.S. 'Star of Mexico’' which ran aground at Has al Kalba. It will be appreciated if he is given all assistance he may stand in need of. His Britannic Majesty*s Consull Muscat. Dated 13 th February 19^7*Political Agent Muscat should telegraph to Muscat passing on news from SNOPG asking if any information available and suggesting that Hudson and others should proceed to spot to deal with situation if transport available. He should tell them that one of H.M* s Ships has been asked to proceed to spot calling at Muscat en route to pick up Hudson and company if necessary. (ITD.) W.R.H. 2/2/47 ATTESTED for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf.\ Telegram From SNOPG To H.K.S. ,, \^^en ,, Repeated C-in-C., East Indies. No .TOO 012143 C Dated and received 1st February 1947. I! Ilimi ATS Pass to Political Resident. Following received from Abadan. Begins. From Master ’'Empire Evesham'. Steamer 'Star of Mexico' ashore Has al Hadd. No radio. Have advised F.O. Bombay of his requirements. Master reports vessel in hands of Arab guard and requires assistance to have them removed. Ends. Request P.A. Muscat may take action. Ikould like H.M. Ship to proceed there. Position received corrupt but appears to be on Oman coast. Am endeavouring to obtain check. - NAVYCHARGE -Telegram From Political Resident, Bahrain. To Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf (H.M.S. u \,Ten' please pass) No.121. Dated the 2nd February 1947. MEDIATE Your TOO 012143 C. Political Agent Muscat who is here is endeavouring ascertain situation. Meanwhile though I am doubtful if stranfied ship is in danger from tribesmen should be grateful if H.M*s Ship could proceed to spot calling at Muscat on way to pick up Hudson Military Adviser and other representatives of Political Agent and Sultan if they have not already proceeded to spot. - HAY -Telegram From Enclair• Political Resident, Bahrain To Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf H.&amp;.S. Wild Goose, Bahrain Radio Repeated H.M.S. Wren, Bahrain Radio, No. 127 Dated the 3rd February, 1947. Hudson with ^tate Representative and Levy escort has left for Has A1 ilaod by launch No need for Wren to call Imscat.Telegram Enclair From Political Resident, Bahrain To Political Agent, Muscat No. 188 Dated and received the 14th February, 1947. Immediate. Following is repetition of SNOPG’s telegram 132130C for such action as you consider necessary. Begins British Industry reports that s.s.Star of Mex in danger from local arabs and is standing by to take off crew at daylight february 14th. Request you inform Political Agent, Muscat. Ends. HAY 1Printed in England. May. 1943 ( 1000 pads) CABLE AND WIRELESS (MID-EAST) LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) L.S. 1715. SERVICE TELEGRAM. VIS DE GZGP. FROM - BRITISH DESTINY 21 U 13OO = POLITlCAL AGENT MUSCAT = STAR OF MEX WAS ABANDONED THIS MORNING MASTER AND CREW ON BOARD BRITISH DESTINY DUE ABADAN MONDAY = MASTER./X .A Enclair Political Agent, Muscat Political Resident, Bahrain SNOPG. Bahrain. Telegram From To Rep No. C 66 Dated the 14th February, 194V. Immediate. ^ ^ ICj . Your telegram No. 18B February 14th. I have no information bjct request that I may be permitted proceed to Star of Mex in H.M.I.S. Dhanush which is now in Muscat. 141320D P0 T ITICALH.B.M's Consulate, Muscat. Dated the 14th February, 1947. (v Dear Mr. Jamali, ^ I attach a copy of a telegram received from Colonel Kay with ray reply. £ ^ . If we get off I h&lt; pe it will be this evening. In which case do you think you could arrange for a represent ative of His Highness to come with me. I suggest Major Hudson with a few levies and one other person in authority. I am sorry to have to disturb you on a Friday. Yours sincerely, sd. A.C.STEWART. 14-21 14-2-1947. Dear Mr. Jamali, I have not yet had a reply to my signal to Col. Hay, but I have since heard that the Star of Mex has^abandoned, ship.Officers and crew being taken off in the British Destiny. If the P.R. and S.N.O. agree, I propose leaving in H.M.I.S. ’’Dhanush * 1 about 10 p.m. this evening. ■' — *Telegram Enclair From Political Resident, Bahrain To Political Agent, Muscat Rep. SNOPG, HMS• WREN, BAHRAIN RADIO. No. 192 Dated and received the 14th February, 1947. Immediate. Your telegram No.141320D. No objection. HAY.Printed in England May. 1943 ( .000 pads) 8JRX NAZ 0330 FOR PA MUSCAT = FROM DHANU FOLLOWING RECEIVED BEGINS ADDRE . CABLE AND WIRELESS (MID-E .INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) SERVICE TELEGRAM. (R) DHANUSH FOCRIN PR BAHREIN FOB CINCEI NO 10 KARACHI FROM SNOPG AAA FOLLOWING SIGNALS HAVE BEEN RECEIVED AAA 1 NO 10 KARACHI 141635 2 AAA PA MUSCATS 141320 3 PRPGS 141955 AS IT WOULD APPEAR THAT HMIS DHANUSH IS PROCEEDING TO ST AR=OF=MEXI CO AND BRITISH DESTINY HAVE HER CREW ON BOARD-PROPOSED TO TAKE NO FURTHER ACTION TOO 142101 AAA MESSAGE ENDS AAA SUGGEST'YOU COME ON BOARD AT O53O AND WE GO AT 0600 = 0302 =No.C./^3 .-19/3-G. POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated 15th February, 1947. To The Officer-in Charge, Gable and Wireless Limited, Muscat. Dear Sir, I shall be glad if the enclosed message may please be transmitted by wireless to Major A.C. Stewart, O.B.E., on board H.M.I.S. rt Dhanush f *. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Muscat.MAJOR A.C. STEWART ON BOARD H.M.I.S DHANUSH. JAMNADAS WHO RETURNED FF.Oi^I RAS AL KAEB THIS MORNING REPORTS THAT STAR OF MEX BEING PLUNDERED BY APOITT EIGHT HUNDRED ARMED PEOPLE OF SUR AND AL HAMUDHA STOP WALT OF SUR AND AMIR'S REPRESENTATIVE EXPRESS THEIR INABILITY TO CONTROL SITUATION STOP KHIMJI'S AND GRAY MACKENZIE'S STAFF ARE AT SUR AWAITING . JLITAP.Y ASSISTANCE TO UNLOAD REMAINING CARGO. Pol ITtCfrL.■ ■I(£4/8^' Gatle and Wireless Limited, Muscat# 15th February 1947# The Political Agent, Muscat# Dear Sir, X* With reference to your letter No.C.123- 19/3-&amp; of todayfe date: We are endeavouring to make contact with H. M# I*.S#.Dhanush by wireless and to send the message for Major Stewart as requested. As the message is of 3 importance we suggest you should also despatch it at once as an Immediate Government telegram via the normal route v/hich is via Bahrainradio. We will advise you i£ we-are able to dispose of the message direct but our communication with H. M. I# S#-Dhanush is quite unofficial and irregular and she may not attend to us for some time. Yours faithfully, 6u03=&lt; Off icer-in-0.large.No.C. -19/3-G. KIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S CONSULATE, JJfUSCAT, Dated 15th February, 1947. To The Secretary to Rin Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oinan, Muscat. Memorandum. Mr. Jamnadas of the firm of Messrs. Khxtaji Raradas, who returned from Has al Khabb this morning reports that 'Star of A* Mex'^being plundered by about 800 armed people of Sur and al Hamudiia. The Y/ali of Sur and the Amir's representative expressed their inability to control situation. f^essrs. Khimji Ramdas' and Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie's staff are at Sur awaiting military assistance to unload remaining cargo. for His Britannic^Majesty's Consul, Muscat.Telegram From To Rep NO. Eridlair Political, Muscat Major Stewart, HMIS DHANUSH ( through SNOPG ) Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain ( for information ) C 67 Dated tbe 15th February, 1947. Immediate. Jamnadas eontractor Grays returned from Ras al Kabb this morning reports Star of T, ex being plundered by about S00 armed arabs of Sur and Al Hamudha. *7ali of Sur and Amir’s representative express inability to control situation. Contractors and Gray Mackenzie’s staff at Sur awaiting military assistance to unload remaining cargo. Ends. Political 151130D Telegram Enclair From Political, Muscat To Headquarters British Forces, Aden No. TOO 151100D Dated the 15th February, 1947. Please pass to Salalah. Following for Sultan from Major Hudson. Unclassified. C 6 B 15/2 Ship Star of Mex abandoned at Khabba. Am going with Levy escort in HMIS DHANUSH to investigate. Request permission urgently to use H.D.M.L to retuin Levies. Please telegraph authority to Secretary as present position most unsatisfactory. Ends. Consux. 151100D POLITICALTelegram From To No.C 69 Dated the 15th February, 1947. E nclair Political, fluscat Political Resident, Bahrain Your telegram 14th. Political Agent left for Has al Kabb 150700D. POLITICALTelegram Enclair From Political, Muscat To SNOPG, HMS. KEEN, Bahrain radio No. TOO 151525D Dated the 15hh February, 1947. Immediate. ^ Hi*}! Please pass to Major Stewart on H? r IS DHANUSH. Following from Secretary to Kis Highness. Begins.- Unclassified. C 70 15/2 Kindly wire immediately existing situation at Khabba and action taken.''' Ends. Political 151525D£ Telegram Q From Political Resident, Bahrain No To Political Agent, Sfuscat 195 Dated the 15th received the 16th February, 1947. 2 Your telegram No.C 60 February 10th. Secretary^ contentions described in paragraph 2 / VS appearrs to be in accordance with Sultan’s letter and strictly speaking Hudson should have been addressed through Secretary. course is when you see him to excuse your action on grounds of urgency and being without your files and if necessary offer apologies. It would be most unwise to use case as an argue- ment for place* Hudson in charge at Uluscat. This could only be done if you had tried to follow procedure prescribed for and it had not ? worked . 4. It is difficult to suggest what you should say next to Secretary until I have seen correspondence with him but if it is still possible kst antoyfc I think best attitude to adopt is to admit the mistake, explain reasons for it and express readiness to comply with procedure described in Sultan’s letter in future. /■ ( Copy of signal No.A 21 dated the 16th February, 1947 from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman.) FOR MAJOR HUDSON. BEGINS. w RECEIVED YOUR MESSAGE REGARDING STAR OF MEX. YOUR MESSAGE IS RATHER VAGUE. ON WHOSE BEHALF THIS INVEST* IGATION IS REQUIRED AND WHETHER YOU CONSULTED NADHIR ADDAKILIYYAK AHMED BIN IBRAHIM ON SUBJECT. IS SITU* ATION AT KHABBA NECESSITATE TAKING OF LEVY ESCORT. HAVE JUST RECEIVED REPORT FROM WALI SUR AND SHAIKH ALI REGARDING THE SHIP IN QUESTION WHICH IS SAID TO BE EGYPTIAN SHIP. HOWEVER AM TELEGRAPHING SECRETARY AS REQUESTED. DETAILED REPORT SHOULD BE SENT TO ME FIRST OPPORTUNITY. ENDS’*. 3 V 72.6 No.C 1S4-19/3-G Political Agenty, Muscat. Dated the 17th February, 1947. Copy forwarded to iMajor J.E.H.Hudson, Military Adviser to Kis Highness the Sultan of iMuscat &amp; Oman, Muscat, for Information. . ' 6 . 2.^7 Aozu '&amp;MU4 &gt; J c .No.C.127-19/3-G HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S CONSULATE MUSCAT, Dated 17th February, 1947. To The Secretary to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman Muscat. Memorandum, The following telegram dated the 16th February, 1947 has been received for you from Nis Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Dhofar. ’•Have received telegram from Commandant Hudson regarding ship Star of Mex flying Egyptian colours at Khabba. The message is rather vague. He requested to use launch to bring back Levies after investigation at Khabba. He is permitted to use launch for this purpose. Telegraph situation and whether Ahmid bin Ibrahim has been consulted and what investigation is required and on whose behalf as no report came from you. All possible help should be given re garding the ship as far as we are concerned.” Said. Muscat. Consul ■’V' a - Z « Ant.Telegram From To No. En clair Warship Dhanush. Bahrain Radio Political Agent, ?.fuscat. 162143c. Dated 16th and received 17th February, 1947. ETA 0700Z 17th February. Request you inform Levies and ask for transport at 0800 DTG.*- Starofmex both, boix^rs engine room fxooded depth one foot above floor plates furnace full sea //ater stop our opinion Basset Trawler unaasireaDle stop Hatch ^o.i 1 tweendeck one steel boat lowerhold iron corrugated sheets hatch No#2 tv/eended one steel boat lowerhold under water unknown hatch No.3 tv/een deck coal lowerhold/general cargo. Natch A,i u.o decx one motor truck (gib) stop all fittings ropes caoin aoors and removeaole articles taken stop ship stinxing facing sea both anchors heaved up. stop salving cargoes diiiicult hatched one and three being in unseitered position stop salving only profitable provided arranged Local Government fixing salving charges at certain percentage of salved.stop we condiser totloss. - - Grayphmbhhhhhhhhi Telegram Q From Political Agent, Muscat. To Political Resident, Bahrain. b) No. C.71. vd Dated 17th February, 1947. VJ/ I arrived at Has al Khabba at dawn on 16 th and ^Co [^5 Wall of Sur with his guards on board Star of Mex. There were no tribesmen on board and it seems they had made off the night before after stripping the ship of all fittings and looting one and two holds tween deck hatches. 2 . Wall's story is as follows: On 12th lighters arrived from Sur and 180 motor tyres and 70 bags sugar (figures all approximate) were discharged and despatched to Sur, IViaster agreeing pay one third of cargo for services of lighters and crew. 3 . On 13th 'fester entered into engagement wnth local Shaikh, against his (Wall's) advice to supply 60 tribesmen to transfer balance of cargo to lighters. Early on morning l/ + th tribesmen were allowed on board and immediately a sked for sweepings of damaged cargo (sugar coffee etc.) which they were allowed to have this incited them to loot. Crew were at the time ashore under protection of Wall's guard only Wall and Captain being on board and Wall found himself unable to control situation. Gray Mackenzie Agent arrived on board during morning and gave matter letter from ov/ners asking him not to abandon ship. But Master declared situation to be out of control and as boat of Tanker was standing by left with his crew. They apparently all took with them their own personal e; ects and tLeii departure was not impeded. 4 . So far as I could judge, whether or not, Wall's story is true it would have been extremely difficult for tribesmen to board ship if Master had not agreed to let them on board.to work cargo and T think to this extent Master is to blame for what followed. 5 . Sultan's representative has instructed Wali to receive as much of the looted cargo as possible,though _ doubt If' 1 I he will succeed, he has also instructed him to stay on board with his guards until relief can be sent and see that no further looting takes place. 6 . Tribesmen have already taken nearly all cargo which can be readily moved and I think it unlikely they will return and since there was nothing further I could do, have returned to Muscat. 7. It seems unlikely that ship could be salvaged unless heavy aid of xaray salvage tug is forthcoming soon, even then task would be difficult. Task of salving balance of cargo which is coal and corrugated iron sheets would also be difficult and expensive. Gray Mackenzie’s Agent is submitting report to owners on salvage aspect. 8 . I understand Master-had tyro, Sia-chine guns on board and took them with him when he left. -POLITICAL-CONFIDENTIAL. No.C.128-19/3-G* Dear Colonel Hay, POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated 17th February, 1947. A-^ Please refer to r»y telegram No.C.71, dated the 17th February, 1947. Following is a more detailed report concerning the ahip •♦Star of £!ex M . 2. We arrived at Raa al Khabb at dawn on the morning of the 16th and sent a boat ashore with Saiyid Ffeisal bin Said and Hudson, who accompanied me as representatives of the State. When they arrived on the M Star of Mex rt , they found only the Wall and three or four of his guards on board, though it was apparent that the ship had been pretty well stripped oi all fittings. They brought the Wall back on board H.M.I.S. 'Dhanush*, where we heard his story of events as follows: Shortly after H.M.S. Wren’s departure on the 6 th, a storm arose and fearing that the ship would Dreak up, the master and the crew landed and campeo on the shore. The next day the storm abated and though the ship had changed its position considerably, it was still intact, so the Master again boarded the ship. In the meantime messages had been sent to Sur to fetch lighters to discharge the cargo and also to Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Muscat, to send assistance. As a result of these messages, lighters arrived from Sur on the 11th and after some bargaining re garding the payment for their services the master agreed that tho lighters and crew would be entitled to l/3 share of any cargo salvaged by them. On this basis, approximately 180 actor tyres and 70 bags of sugar were discharged and sent off for Sur. After the departure of the first lighters, the Master entered into an engagement with the local ShaiKh to send on board 50 or 60 tribesmen to work the balance of the cargo. The Wall swears that this engagement was entered into against his advice. Whether this be true or not, the tribesmen were allowed on board on the morning of the 14 th at a time when the crew were on shore under the protection of the Yfali’s guards. It is the Wall’s story that after arriving on board, the tribesmen saw sugar and coffee beans which had been damaged by water. They asked the master if they could have this and their request was granted, having attained so much for nothing, their natural cupidity was aroused and they commenced ransacking the ship. The Master and the Vfali were still on board, but wer© unable to control the situation. While the ransacking was going on, a launch carrying the Agent of Gray, Mackenzie together with a representative of the Customs at Muscat, The Hon’ble Lt. Col. W.R. Hay, C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BJUUULIJ*- arrived • ••••••••arrived on the scan® with instructions from the ship's owners requesting the Master not to abandon the ship and to r eport about the assistance he required. The Master, however, found the situation to be out of control, and since his crew were already standing l&gt;y in a launch sent ashore by the B.T.C. Tanker ’♦British Destiny*, he decided that he could do nothing further and abandoned the ship himself. So far as X can gather, neither the Master nor his crew suffered personal interference, nor were they prevented from taking their own personal effects with them. 3 . X find it hard to believe the l^ali's statement entirely, but at the sane tine I feel it la unlikely that the incident would have taken place had (a) the owners been more expeditious In arranging for aid to be despatched to the ship and (b) if the Master and the crew had remained on beard with the guards provided by the ^all, and token steps to prevent any tribesmen from boarding the ship. It. Is possible however that after the first storm, the Master felt the ship's position to be too insecure to .justify him in retaining the crew on board. 4 « I was not able to establish who was first back on board the ship after the storm, if, as I presume the master boarded first the point is, In Itself, unimportant, but if it was a Muscat subject, It is possible, X am not well up in salvage laws, that the ship could be regarded as a derelict and as such the prise of the State. 5 . T was not in possession of the ship's manifest and I was therefore unable to estimate the extent of the looting. One and two tween-deck hatches had however been entirely emptied and all the ship's fittings of value had been removed. No.3 hold containing cc»l and the lower hatch of No.l hold, containing corrugated iron sheets, appeared to be Intact. No.2 hold was flooded as w?s the engine room and the whole ship was in an indescribable ness. The Captain and the Chief Engineer of E.M.7.S. 'Dhammh*, who Inspected the ship, were of the opinion that the ship could only be salvaged with the aid of a properly fitted and bc. r Yy salvage tug* Bven then, the task would be difficult and rendered more so by the fact that the engine room was flooded. It wrn else considered that the balance of cargo being heavy and difficult to shift- without winches could only be salvaged at great expense, which would possibly not be jus tified. The Agent of Cray, Mackenzie, who is also the Agent for the owners of the *Star of Mex*, an&lt;^ whom I took with me, is reporting to Ms principals at this aspect of the matter. 6 . The Sultan's representative has placed the wreck and the balance of its cargo in the direct charge of the Itoali and his grjarda, and has told him to endeavour to recover as much of the looted c*rgo ss possible. Since there appeared to be no further action I could take, I returned to Muscat on the 17th morning. 7. I attach a copy of a telegram despatched by Gray Mackenzie* Agent this morning. Yours sincerely,Telegram Q From Political Resident, Bahrain To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 227 Dated the 24th received the 25th February Jfy telegram No. 195 February 15th. • 2. I have now received your letter No.C 96-19/3G February 12th and its enclosures. You should speak to Sultan on the lines proposed in para No.3 of my telegram when you go to Dhofar and if possible avoid further written correspondence. 3. It is not perhaps necessary t 6 say anything further to the Secretary but you should be careful to comply meticulously with the ( omm) prescribed for by Sultan in future. Hay.r p » As\ * N Vrom Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd. Muscat* TO oil 6 S^ 7l (7 . The Political Agent Consul, Muscat. No . (MC/ 23. Dear Sir, Muscat, 3th. March 19 47. /R.SCK ' STAR OF MHIX Snclosed we hand you a copy of our letter No.GMC/22 of 7th.. instant, addressed to the Secretary to H.H. The Sultan of Muscat and Oman, in connection with the above wreck, for your information. Yours faithfully, . For GRAY MACKE^E &amp; Q0 tTD, Snell Agents for Shipowner.Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) HEAD OFFICE: 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E. C. 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE Muscat, 7th. March. 19 47* The Secretary, To H. H. The Sultan of Muscat &amp; °man, Muscat. Dear Sir, WR&amp;CK “STAR OF M£X. ^ We have to acknowledge receipt of your letter No.158/2 of 6th. instant informing us that Saiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim, Nadhir al Dakhiiiyah has returned from ooor and Khabba and that he had recovered most of the goods said to have been sold by the Master of the above wreck and of the goods reported to have been unloaded by the Local dhows with the permission of the Master and that deliveries had been goven to our contractors Messrs. Khimji hamdas. We thank you and the Nadhir al D/.khiliyah f or the recovery. We shall be glad uo know whether Madhir al. Dakhiiiyah has been able to recover anything from the parties who had looted all equipments, furniture, fittings and other removable materials from the ship including c-abin doors in the presence of the Governor of d U r and the Amir's representative since the morning of 14th. February 1947. Please confirm that one life boat and one steel boat lying on the beach shown to us and to Hi s Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat, by the Governor of ?ur have been delivered to our contractors. We still await arrival of 180 tyres and 70. bags of sugar received by the Governor of ^ur from the Master of the above wreck under a receipt on condition that 1/3 (one third) cargo for carriers to Muscat against the expenses and the remaining 2/3 (two third) for the Agents. This matter had been confirmed by the Governor of Sur to His Britannic Majesty s Consul, on the 16th. February 1947. Please note that this cargo of 250 packages have been received prior to 14th. February 194/. We regret to learn the observation of Dahir al Dakhiiiyah while on board the wreck ,l star of Mex ^ regarding the way our contractors were following to unload and coluect BRANCHES: BUSREH. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ B UNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSHIRE. BUNDER-ABBAS. UNGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEACE QUOTE GMC/ 22. RAS TANURA EL KHOBARw) cargo. We having fall confidence as regards to the ability and sincerity of Messrs. Khimji Ramdas, who haa nandled the Government work at Has al ^add and kasirah auring th~ last vVorld War and they having a firm at i^or since years ana taeir Mr. Jamanadas Khimji who is well known in oor circles being aopointed in charge the salvage work with their motor boat at his disposal, were at entire satisfaction regarding tne salvage work, 3oon on receipt of your letter we have taken up the matter strongly with iSessrs. Khimji Kamdas and nave also sent our Hamdin Moosa to Khabba per the sailing boat on the 6th. instant, to send us first hand information, soon posoiol-. .e / shall advise you as soon as we hear from Messrs, nhimji nam^d.s and in the meantime shall be obliged if you will kindly let us know whether the observation of Nadhir al Dakhiliyah was of the first or the second day of the unloading and coixecting of the cargo ex the above wreck. l f possible please advise us the date of the observation.A' A Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) HEAD OFFICE: 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON, E. C- 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. The Secretary* To H. H. The BRANCHES BUSREH. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAWSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR SUSHI RE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. !N REPLY PLEASE QUOTE GMC/ 24. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Hnsoat., 9th. Mar ch 10^7. /'Y'N. Sultan of Muscat &amp; Gnan, Muscat. ' Dear Sir, -/RSCK M STAR O F JgSX[L u. In continuation of our letter No. (3JC/22 of instant, w ®^tg a ^^g rin W g 0 ^ a ^ a xe«rnt n tha? r sar^heir^Soor 8 Branch 3 ^ received nothing ^o^^^^ecIiv^V sugar out of lotofl30 ^ ' the Master of the above ^:chTor n0 desgtch r trMuscatTrior to 14th. February 1947 on condition stated in our letter of 7th. ^^t^are^iying^ de spa t ch^' to' Muse at 3 only ° on* 1 p e rm i s s i o n from the Director General of Customs, Muscat. We shall therefore be obliged y°u will kindly obtain * Let from “* ?^ij a *to D SS i JSlS.2toS‘»fSri. Khl«gi SSrtoS “S tStoiVoVs/, of 5th. instant to enable us to know the position clearly. Thanking you, Yours faithfully, Far GRAY MACKENjU^^ifcTl. Copy to: 11 The Political Agent &amp; H. B.M* s Consul, Muscat. Agents.I -I H [/) / » PI I'li- 6 ' X S) ■n No.3£3-S ^ -/ | The ilon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to - 1) The Sfjnior ftaval OiTloer, Persian Gulf, 2) The Political Agent, Muscat . 3) The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the wmmmmmm33/134 Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Bahrain. To India Office, London. Repeated Government of India, New Belhi. R.te.Ambassador, Cairo. fro.£ 01 . Dated tile 17th February 1947. B.B.C. announced on February 10 th that the “Otar of Sex” had been looted off Bahrain. 2. Facts are that Star of Hex a cargo vessel ovned by the Alexandria steam Navigation Company Alexandria vith an Egyptian ere** proceeding to Basra ran aground just south of Has al Hadd in i.uscat territory on or about February ls?t# heports having been received that Master required assistance to remove Arab guards who had boarded vessel ti.M.B. “^ren” proceeded to the spot to render assistance. Military Adviser to Sultan also went to apot in launch. H.M.S. “Wren* was unable to get ship off arid left on February 7th after giving Master such assistance as was possible. Sultan*s representatives were then on board and promised to prevent pilfering end arrange local supplies. Crew abandoned ship on February 14th apparently from fear of local Arabs and nent aboard “British ^)estiny ,, a tanker outward bound from Gulf. On February 15th a report was received from Muscat that armed Arabs were looting ship and Multan's representatives were unable to control situation. Political Agent Muscat has proceeded to spot in h.M.I.M. 'bnanuFu' and further report is awaited from him.Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENOLAND) BRANCHES HEAD OFFICE: 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E. C. S. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BbISREH. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAWSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSHIRE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. !N REPLY PLEASE QUOTE Nc. umc/ as . RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Muscat. 12th« March 47 s The Political Agent dc H. B. M l s Consul, Muscat. / Dear Sir, Wr eck ** atar o^ iiex . ,t . Enclosed we hand you for your iniormation and necessary action copy of our letter No. Gm y^S of data, adaressed to The Secretary to H. H. The Sultan of Muscat dc Vman, with copies of the report and lists of goods, submitted to us by our contractors Messrs. Khimji Haind.i-,. Yours for GBAY MACKE £nelss Agents for Ship twner*r iRXY, MACKENZIE A Co., U'J Muscat, 12th. March The Secretary, to H. H. The Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, Muscat* GMC/ 25 . 47 * Dear Sir, Wreck n Star of Mex We refer you to our letters Nos. GMC/22 and Gi'aC/ 24 of 7th. and 9th. instant in respect of the above wreck. In continuation enclosed we hand you a complete report received by us from Messrs. Khimji Hamdas for your information and necessary action# Before we comment on the subject matter, shill be obliged if you will kindly let us know soon possible, what steps you are taking for the return of the following cai^goas infull to Muscat, to enable us to advise Lloyd* s Agents at Bahrein and the ship owners at Alexandria: 1 . 2 . 3# 180 (onehundred and eighty) Tyres and 70.(seventy) bags of Sugar received by the Governor of 3oor,under a receipt to the Master of rt Star of Mex rt . ‘11 cargoes recovered by the Nadhir al Dakhiliyah confirmed in your letter No.158/2 of 6th. instant but unreceived by our contractors Messrs. Khimji Bamdas as advised in our letter No.(l!C/ifl 24 of 9 th. instant# all cargoes in possession of Mr# Said bin Rashid Sanani as enlisted by Messrs. Khimji Ramdas, copy of which is attached with the copy of the report enclosed herewith#- ■ B ;r KH I M J I RAM DAS. MUSCAT &lt;P. GULF ) CON, SHEET NO. 3 MUSCAT &lt;P. GULF ) i aiao O-fered to pay daia vAshid a ruasona le ai'^unt for his ve3sel comin : ovqf th«rs on d&amp;iyid Ahsied's r, equs9t but. all ^as in vain ant. all iuy arguiiionts x-ell to deaf ears and at the and he Dxank^y refused t lq accecie to my requests to get the work, stopped. 1 still continued ray efforts to persuade Saiyid Ahmed Bin ... ^ . , -v, Iorahim,Haa^ir al Dakhiliyah to agree to my reasonable demand and after much ArgmBents he at la'st agreed to let ma l-ive half the quantity of the cargo wnile th# ,other half to be salved oy ^did A&amp;ahii men. ..uring this interval laid Hashids men haa already taken out 320 Mo tor frutk Itibes ana 70 Motors tyres. I ixaving no altamatlve started to unload cargo or; 24th February on the above terms but to my utter surprise after a short while Saiyid Ahmed ordered ug? man to stop work auu so witii great despair a I returned to my launch,.^ith my party. ' v.n 2oth Februax*/ i was allowed to unload cargo but bafore - r*usn.tuiiag work x noticed that in hatch No*3 there vver^u'doine cases open v»ita contents short.This matter had noticed jy thedKadiiir ai bakiihli., ah. r ' A - 1 ihe following articles were unloaded by my party on the 2oth uxtimp xi'on nedsteads 19 rundlas liywood planks. 20 ’ iiotor iruck Tubes. 35 Nos. Motor Truck Tyres. 21 ^Broken with contents short) containing- nospital equipments. die Pori people also continued tnsir salvage work on that day and were ^ule to take out the following articles. * V * % ,, ... ■ / \'T' 'KHI M J I RAM DAS, MUSCAT (P. GULF.) CON. SHEET NO, 4 .Nos• Iron Bedste^us. 8 3*dies Plywood planks . 5 ca^es containing Hospital equipn^ents. i « * Motor Generator. The Bori people cienianded from us half of the cargo salved by us .ut we succeeded at last in arranging the salve cargo to our dhow after much persuation. The next day the 26th ultimo ^aiyid Ahmeu left the place requesting me to see hiiii at Bore on the 2Bth ultimo to discuss over the goods salved by Sori People. Mjr people unloaded the following cargo on the 26th uiti-*o; ifauh 12 y Iron Bheets. ***' small rowing boats. K-tt- dori people unloaded 74 Iron sheets on the saiue day. I doubted that there were Iron Drums containing ghee in the second hole «*na so on the 27th ultimo though it was too uifficuit to take • them out oy ordinary labour 1 tried to do so by the help oi some diver* ao it was my bounden duty to salve as much cargo as possible and the absence of any ox‘ your representative on the spot made me to try still more.Hence X settled with divers to take out those drums on The conuition to give them one drum out of each five drums taken out - ■ ^ tnem.in this way we wei'e able to salve 13 drums nett ( i.e. -*fter giving the divers their share in kind according to above terms) The dori people also salved 13 drums in the same way. 1 continued th proceed in the same way and was able to salve 16 ai*ums nett on the next day the 28thultimo. The Bori people also a salved 16 drums likewise.In the eveining X left for Sore to see .jalyid Ahmeu Bin Ibrahimy Madhir al Dakhiliyah as instructed.! saw 1 im on the same night and again on the next morning the 1 st instant.KH I M J I RAM DAS, MUSCAT (P. GULF.) CON, GHEFT NO, I was ej.oatftad with him Tor the most part of the day *nd we arrivja ut tne following aecision : ( 1 ) daid Hashid danani the owner of the Maw dhow should accompany me to iasal Kabb ana hand over to me two third of the cargo salved by his dhow crew oesides the motor generator. (2) Regarding the remaining one third of the salved cargo both the ^ parties i.e. i and baid Rashid should act according to the decision of Muscat Government viz. whether to pay baid Rashid a reasonable amount or to give him one third of the salved cargo against his labour of salving. 13) baiyid Ahmed Bin lorahim should arrange to hana me over 47 bags ^ugar and 108 kotor iruck Tyres being two third of the cargo a^re*dy salved oy daid Rashids dhow m crew oefore my arrival at aasal l&amp;bb. baiyid Ahmeu Bin Ibrahim £*£ offered to give me a list of the goous ^aia to be purchased by bori people from the Captain of b.S. bt-*r of Mex but X refused to have it stating that it would not oe of any use to me.I informed him that I was ready to take delivery of sala purchased goods if he could arrange to do so.He did not Agree,to do so on the reason that oori people had paid &amp; 5500/- (Hupaas Five thousand five hundred) for the same.I offered him to pay them the above amount against delivery of all the said purchased goods but oori people refused through him to accept it on the ground that they had to un iergo other heavy expenses and labour in having these goods. baiyid ahmea Bin Ibrahim left bore for Muscat on the morning of 3 rd instant while I left for Rasal Kabb the same night.Before leaving 1 asked baid iashid to accompany me to A&amp;sal kabbKH I M J I RAM DAS, MUSCAT (p. GULF.) CON. SHEET NO, 6 for delivering the goons as per agreement out he refused to do so promising to loilow me the next morning.I waited for him at Easal hahu out he did not turn out until the 6 th instant when 1 was informed by the of his^ves^ei that the goods wij .1 b« ueiiver%d to me at iLhorgrama.Both his vessel ana 1 lex t ior hhorgrama the same day. ^The fo l^^ing goods were salved during the interval eetween the 1 st *na 6 th instant including ^oth days, by us; 811 Mos. Iron sheets. By lori people Hos. iron sheets. The only goods now remaining in the shipare some sig iron j earns «niuh can possibly only oe ta^en out by mechinical^crone out stilx 1 have made arrangements to try to take them out if possible ana hept dhows ready there to bring them over here.ihe beams are immersed deep in *ater and divers hesitate to take them out due to fear of loss to their lives.Besides the aoove there are lying soma iron sheets also which will be salves if possible, file Hawaldar Major with his infantry men has accompanies me and ^arrived at Muscat with me as he saw that there was nothing lelt in the ship which can possibly be taken out. I witt my party reached khorgrama at midnight on the 6 th instant ^ and -sok delivery of the following goods from the master of daia Hashids vessel on the morning of 7th instants Hos. Iron sheets. 47 Nos. Motor Truck ,yres. 3.3 » Motor Truck Pubes i^ ” ii’on dedsteaas. • 5^ bundles Plywood planks. 1 Motor deaerator. &amp; cases containing Hospital equipments. 13 drums gnee.KHI MJI RAMDAS, MUSCAT tP. GULF.) CON, SHEET NO, 7 i with part/ iaft Khorgraaia X'or oor^ at a ..out *.M. on ♦ ciduiie day after compietiag the aoove work. In tna way I saw 6 aia tasaiu g ing to khorgrama in a boat.He called 2 ^ and I picked him up in the launch ana informed hiia tnat his man had .* otor denarator to me ana aaked him to arrange to hanu me over Uie aaii two drama.U« agreed to do so ana gave me a chit adarasa- eiiver me the said two ux’ume.l sent the eame chit to khorgrama wiUi my meesengor ana askeu him to have those drums. The matter was ov^r there out a abort while ai’t.r a*y arrival at ..ore to 2 */ utter surprise I received a chit from daid Rashid in which he threatened that he was going to umoaa half the saLVed ghee and the generator which aas handed over to me by the of his veasei aa tiio ssas wad delivered to me in his ausenos.tn receiving this chit 1 called some icaamg people of .vore ami showed theja the chit I informed hi® through them that 1 not going to allow hi© to have even a single article frosi thi se which ware aireaay in my possession ana ha *&lt;*a at liberty to try to loot my vassal if he aaral to do so. vk'ter av'^ted discussion it settled through them that he may hand me over tha two druais of ghee in return of the motor generator. I informed the captain of my dhow to act accordingly, how X am going to request uaiyid Ahmed Bin Ibrafcll ,Nadhir al laidi.iliyah to arrange to 1st me have the delivery of Motor Generator as agreed by him at ^ora. Let me mention here that the help of military was muchCON. SHEET NO. 8 KHIMJI RAMDAS, MUSCAT (P. GULF.) apjurieiajle during the whole period of operation ana specially when thoy offered to fight out haih Hash .Ido men in case they try to *raot from me ghea ana Motor Generator as mentioned aoova. He: to tor Truck : It was unloaded by dpri i-eople ani it is a till under t air possession. Ho: Fuel Coal : Saiyii Ahmed in Ibrahim a;e what arrange- ^ints 1 was to make about it and in reply -I tgld him that I was &amp; instructed by you to tirow the Bunker Goal in the oea,&amp;ftiuuixfcft j ; , if- 1 '^.. ' : 4 ' ^ yyyi vt.^ av Wancx k xxiyxxshaas.ii^vx.xiaxJjuwaraxaxxx.aK&amp;xtig tb make room to ■ unload general corgo soon possible.Hence he pertuitted Bamau din jaoha-.ed din Juwed od ..ore to un 4 . 0 aa.the The list of all cargo handled by Us ana ^ther parties are enclosed herewith. , v ’x ( . . ■ ' &gt; ' v~ * » h The report ends here v .J ' In reply to the fir at para,-’ of your letter jo . 'lhC/21 dated t .e 7th instant we wish to 3 '..ate that the stateaent of *&gt;aiyid Ahmed 3 in Ibrahim,N«Jhir il Jakhiiiyah a :oaL hinding o\fir as tha gvods 'B-kid to na/e bean solo by the .aster of\ytar oi rex to oori people anu the goods said to have -sen received '^tn t^e latter‘ 3 permi- ssion by the local dhows and recovered by h|^ v from them la not correct. ve shall be glad if you wi ^.1 .request hi-^ tc give the detaixs of such ..oods handed over to us The goods' .-.apt with our ^ ; 1 \ . '■ luaowled&amp;e at bore Customs are 47 oagS; bugar ^ slack condition ana 10b ;..otor Truck Tyres as stated in our report a.ST aoove. These packages kepe m possession of ^ayad bin Rashid, dai^ani. Thii^Nbargo is part V cai'gv of 70 bags nigaT ana ibu* 180 «.ott&gt;r Tyres received by Governor of ^.ore from Ue faster of b/b -t r of; Mex\o| Uie specific condition Lnat two third of the goods is for the agent;of ship owner and oneKHI MJI RAMDAS MUSCAT (P. GULF.) hi CON. SHEET NO. iO bs le beg to infom you that our vessel Ganeshpasa in which we have unloaded 411 the salved goods will oe leaving Khorgrama within a day or two and we shall let you know on ito arrival here. Thanking you in anticipation. we are. Yours Faithfully, For Khing i Kamdas, . mm . I :r • # or lUi jUy i ^ ■aHdaa, * -Cy-/ I KHIMJI RAMDAS. MUSCAT (P. GULF.) CON. SHEET NO, . ^ List, oi* goo^s lying in ooor Customs said to oe part cargo of the goods racaivad oy dovemor of door unaer a receipt to the Lasted of ‘dtar - ■£. of toex' before li/d/17 — . — ' I \ x7 Bugs ougar in axack condition. 108 foe. Motor frucK lyres.'iHFROM ' Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd. MuhC t • TO 4\ A (m The Director General of Cufc&gt;tora 6 . f 4 Muscat* No. 4^. Dear Sir| Muscat ^ 4th« 'pril 1 9 47 • 50* DruaJB Ghee 2 . ^ rt (converted into IS tins) Salved car^o ex Wreck ^ Stg.r of ?&gt; We have to advise having received the, following telegraphic instructions from Ship Owners at Alexandria s rt Starofmex yours third authorise you sell by auction an ghee stop guidance total consignment ghee was 120 drums value as advised by shippers 6750 sterling. ’ We are therefore arranging to sell by Public Auction the above mentioned drums of ghee plus the number we may receive tr^ni Goor, on .fonday the 7th. instant from 10/00 ‘ .M. We are informing all interested merchants at Muscat and Muttrah as per copy of our notice enclosed herewith# Yours faith Fqi Git AY MACKEHjffi Copy to i The Political Agent A H.B.M’s Consul| Muscat# The Secretary, To H.H. The Sultan of -nscat &lt;k Oman, * Muscat# \gents- Ship Owners# IPGRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; CO., LTD.* MUSC At* 'll Merchants of Mus c at &amp; Mut irah* Muscat, 4th* ''pril 19 47* NOT ICS, It is hereby notified for the information of all merchants and persons of Muscat and Muttr&amp;h that 50*(fifty) Drums and 18. (eighteen) Tins of Ghee salved ex Wreck rt Star of Mex ' now lying in Muscat Customs and other drums of Ghee which nuy be receiveu from Soor will be sold by Public Auction on Monday the 7th* April 1947 from ID/00 *.M. on the following terms and conditions^ 1 # The drums and tins of Ghee will be kept open lor inspection of quality on the day of auction* 2* The Agents for Ship Owners will only pay Customs Wharfage charges upto the day of auction sale* 3 . *11 other charges such as: Customs dty t weighing charges and coolie hire etc* will be on account of the purchaser. The purchased Ghee will be delivered at Customs only after receipt of full auction sale value, 'ny Customs charges or other loss due to delay in making the payment will be on account of the purchaser* NOTSI. It has been kindly agreed by The Director General of Customs, that DUTY will be cly*rged on the highest bid arrived in open public auction thoroughly and widely advertised by a public notification issued by 'gents- Ship Owners*mrv i ■ I Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES. HEAD OFFICE: 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E. C. 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. SbISREH. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR 3USHIRE* RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. !N REPLY PLEASE QUOTE GMC/ 43* Muscat| 12th* ./‘aril The Director General of Customs., Muscat* ; Dear Sir, 5* Drums Ghee Salved ax '' Wrack St^E— g-itJ In continuation of our leLLer No* Gtv:C/42 of AtK in*t.ant *ia have to advise that the above five drums will also be aold'by Public Auction on Monday the j-4th. instant tt 11/00 M 4 . on conditions ana terns, notified in our notice of 4th* idem, He „ r a informing all insterestad merchants at Muscat and Mutrahfor the Public \uction dale. Yours faith tor GUAY MACKE Copy to: The Political Agent, Muscat* 'gents- ohip Owners* The Secretary, To H. H. The Sultan of ^sc»t &amp; Oman, Muscat*A?/ - ' S S’ » .. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. LTD. . HEAD OFFICE: 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E. C. 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: 9ENTLEVS COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: aUSREH. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSHIRE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH MUSCAT. !N REPLY PLEASE OUOTE QUO/ 51. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Mus c at, 20th. Apri 1 19 47« The Director General of Customs., Muscat. / Dear Sir, TrteCK STAR OF MilX We have to advise having received the following telegram from Owners of the above wreck t rt Starofmex ourtel sixteenth and yours seventeenth authorise auction sale 2583 pieces Hangar 11 cases 378 pieces tyres 13 packages tubes 439 bags coffee 300 cases soap 120 drums ghee 40 bales wrapping / paper 3 cases gum 5 cases Aloes. We are therefore arranging to sell by Public Auction the materials salved ex the above mentioned original quantity vizs / . 263 Bundles Corrugated sheets( 2629 pieces; 1136 Pieces iron beams, angles etc for a H*ngs 6 Packages containing wooden and iron piece. 193 Pieces Tyres 8 Bundles (233 tubes^ 4 Cases Soap. and other miscellaneous articles such as wooden pl» drawers, etc received from Soar Customs, on Thursday the 24th. April 1947 at 10/00 A.M. Tyres and tilbes will be auctioned the last Copy to* /r ' /: 1L r*. Telegram From To No. Political Resident, Bahrain Political Agent, Muscat 478 Dated the 22nd received the 23rd April, 1947. STAR OF MEX. @ 2 . I have been instructed to ask you to ? enquire unofficially if there is.any likelihood of compensation being paid to owners and whether Egyptian Government have taken diplomatic action to secure com pensation. 3 . You told me at Muscat that Sultan had received notice from Egyptian Government that they would hold him responsible for loss of vessel and cargo. In what form was this notice received ? 3. What prospect is there of Muscat author ities recovering looted property or its value and making restitution ?19/3-G. Telegram Q From Political Agent, Muscat. To Political Resident, Bahrain. No. C.194. Dated 26th April, 1947. - / (SW v Your telegram No.478 April 22nd. 2 . Sultan’s Secretary now informs me that all that was received from Egyptian Government was a request for a report of the incident and steps taken to protect the ship. Following this he received telegram from the owners stating they held Muscat Government responsible for loss of ship and cargo. 3 . There is little likelyhood of compensation being paid. 4 . Cargo which remained intact in vessel has now been discharged and sold by auction by ship’s agent. Cargo off-loaded by Master before he abandoned ship and despatched in dhows to Sur has been recovered. Minister for Internal Affairs claims that cargo looted has been recovered but I am certain this claim is without foundation. 5 . Guards are still on ship but owners appear to be doing nothing to salvage vessel and State will probably remove them before monsoon starts when it is most likely vessel will break up. -POLITICAL-Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) HEAD OFFICE : 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BRANCHES: BUSREH AM A RAH KUT KHORA MSHAH R Ahwaz BUN DA R-SHAH POUR BUSH IRE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BUNDER-ABBAS LING AH BAHREIN KOWEIT DU BA I SHARJAH MUSCAT IN reply please quote no. April |g 47* The Political Agent &lt;&amp; H* B, M's Consul, Muscat* Dear Sir, Vreck 11 3t&gt;sr o£ Mex.*' Enclosed we hand you copy of our letter No. GEIC/55 of date, addressed to the Secretary to H* H* °ultan of Muscat A Oiuan, in connection with the above wreck, for your information said necessacy action. Agents - For Ship Owners.Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd, / (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES HEAD OFFICE : 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED C BENTLEYS COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH A M A RAH KUT KHORAMSHAHR Ahwaz BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE m:/ 55 # RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR )luL?Q!ct&gt;) 19 The Secretary, :o H. H. The Sultan of Itoscat A maen, Muscat* Dear Sir, BcmL Star Of Hex, Res 360# Packegef* Btill in possession of Mr* Saiii tin H&amp;ghid Srganl ef Soor, We have to acknowledge receipt of your letter No* 273/2 of 22 ma. instant, enclcsine a copy of Haohir ^ddakliiliyah , » Arabic letter Ne*S&lt;JL /6 of 22nd.* instant, in reply to our letter No. QMC/49 ef 17tn* instant, for which we thank yen# Wo rogrot to loam that with all our roquosts it is not confirmed that Mr* Saia bin Raahid Sanani has been ordered to come to nuecat with the 360 packages including a case of motor generator, so that true facts will be known c efore final decision by Muscat Government# Ne would request you to note tnat oii 17th# February, the day of our return from £s#abba y we met in connecx»ion with **he above wreck# At this time vre personally requested you to take over the salvage of the balance ef cargo in the wreck# To this request ef ours you replied thut juscat Government would not take over the salvage work but would give all necessary Military assistance for the safety of the cargo and the salvage party. You further advised us that Saiyid Ahamed bin Ibrahim, ^adhij. Addakhiliyah is leaving to-day f«* Soar and Kabba and in the event of his recovering cargoes from the people of boor ana Kkbba, to whoa ho should deliver the recovered cargoes# #e replied that whatever recovered may kindly be delivered to Messrs# Khiaji Ramdas, Soor, against a receipt# With all that we fearing no possibility of any other party taking over the Salvage work advised Lloyd* s Agents at Bahrein as under* ft Salving profitable provided arranged throughTo OMitsrs of th .8 ship at Alexandria we telegraphed as undert * Prospects salving balance cargo difficult without stesm and gear stop trying obtaining best ter 10 s possible Jbft&amp;n’Ulae requeat you arrange through Egyptian Governnient to request ifluscat ^ovariiiwent to undertake cargo salving work* 14 On the 19th* February we rceived the following telegram from Lloyd 1 s Agents, at Bahreint * Star of max yours seventeenth arrange salvage remaining cargo best terms possible. M We again personally approached you with the request to take over the salvage work at best terms posoible and you again declined for saas* We then requested you go kindly persuade Hsgi Bhacker to take over the salvage werk as so far Messrs. Khimji Ramdas are reluctant to undertake the salvage work* ¥ou kindly did all you could s»d m? xhankea you same in our letter Ku.u^CA? cf 22nd. Feiruary, reouestxng you to give ^equate Milltory^Aaeistanca for ^ ^ f carge and the salvage party ox Messrs • Khimj i Kamcias* On 22ud. ffebx^ary, -&lt;«»srs. R»afi*» with the r.*a*ty lei't fot* the week v,ith u letter £roa MeOllr- Abaakhiiiyeh informing him th*t Messrs. Khimji '2^' ere coming ever to salve cargo ex the wreck on behalf ^ tr« AaenteanS also that the 14 tUlitary aunMs are also to be handefl over to them for their safety. Messrs. hart also a letter from the Military Advisor addressed to the Jemadar in charge the detachment • On 4th* March, after the return of Nadhir Addakliiliyift you enquired from us the terms of the salvage and we immediately replied you aa undart * To salve all cargoes and deliver same to us at Muscat Customs at tiia rate either As. 100 /- oer shipping tan or 50* of salved cargo excluding Bunker coal, whichever approved by Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie 4 Coy., Uc., Lloyd's Agents at i-ahrein.*' Qn the 6 th. March, we received your letter H©.loo/2 informing us that Hadhir AddakhUiyah has ^covered most of the e-code reported to have been been unloaded by *hzL~caX_ Shorn with the permission of the Master end the goods said to have bean sold by the Master, and delivered same to our contractors Messrs. Shinyi Ramdas*wmmmmmmmmmmmmmmmm On enquiry from Messrs* KMmji Hamdss and as confirmed by us in our letter NO.GMC/24 of 9 th. March, it has been concluded that Nadhir Addakhiliyah recovered and delivered nothing to our contractors Khiroji Hamdas. In your letter of 6 th. March it was also conplained regarding the working of our contractors. To this a full report from our contractors Messrs. Khiinji Hamdas was sent to you under cover of our letter Ho. GMC/25 of 12.3.47. #e again requested you vide our letter Ho.GMC/34 of 16th. March, to kindly make necessary arrangements for the recovery of the cargo enlisted in over letter No.GMC/25 of 12th. March. After this *e were asked to c ome over to come to a conclusion on con^liedited matters. Accordingly on the 20th. March, your goodself, Nadhir Mdakhiliyah, we and Mr. Jamanadas Khiiaji of Messrs. Khimji Hamdas, met together to solve the complicated matters and came to the following conclusions:. 1 . 108 Tyres and 47 bags sugar( out of 180 tyres and 70 bags sugar said to have teen received by the Goreracr of Socr under a receipt to the Master of the wreck) now lying in Soor Customs are to be brought to Muscat for delivery to us, 2. Messrs. Khimji Pamdas to pay unloading charges at Rs» 6 Q/~ per ton to Mr. 3«id bin Rashid against the receipt of 359^ packages infull, a likewise lumpsum amount to be paid to the 3oori people for the delivery of the motor truck. After this, all cargoes to be accounted for as salved by Messrs. Khimji Bandas. 3. The Nadhir Addakhiliyah, Muscat Government, to advise us soon possible what cargo can be recovered from the goods said to have been sold by the blaster of the wreck and the goods said to have been received by the local dhows with permission of the Master and the terms. 4. The Nadhir Addakhiliyah, Muscat Government, to advise soon possible what articles from ship's fittings and furniture can be recovered from the parties who looted the ship. To our surprise we received a letter in Arabic No.471/6 of 6 th. April, received by you from Nadnir Addakhiliyah stating contrary to what was concluded in the meeting of 20 th. March 1947. In reply we requested you again vide our letter No.GMC/44 of 12th. April, to request Nadhir Addakhiliyah toreview the whole matter thoroughly und sympathetically in the interests of all concerned *nd order Mr. Said bin Rashid to come to J&amp;iscat with all cargoes for final decision by uluscat Government. We have also pointed out that any loss in this respect is due to the appointment of Mr. Said bin Rashid to salve cargo ex the wreck without our knowledge. This request was again confirmed vide our letter No.GMC/49 of 17th. instant« in which we conforraed what was decided in the meeting of 20th. March 1947. We also advised that 47 bags sugar, 108 tyres and the truck though without dynamo, carburetter and fan belt etc., have been received by us. We again specially requested you to give your valueable assistance to settle coiqplicated matters. In reply to both our letters, we again received a disappointing letter in Arabic which have been translated by us as unders Copy of letter No.541/6 dated 30th. gimad A1 Awal 1366 fcom ffaohir Addakhiliyah to Secretary to H.R. The Sultan. * We have to acknowledge receipt of your two letters No.251/2 dated 21st.Jamad A 1 Awal 1366 and No.269/2 dated 29th. Jamad A1 Awal 1366. We understood the letters as well as the translation of the twe letters addressed to you by the Agents. In reply Nadhir Addakhiliyah did not undertake to do anything for them in the meeting •£ which was held on the 20th. March except what «as permissible and Justifiable in the execution of his duties. He therefore performed his duties in this respect, accordingly. They have received the 47 bags sugar and 108 tyres vide his letter and this is the 2/3 of 70 bags sugar and 162 tyres which were unloaded by the Master on condition of 1/3* As for the second para of his letter addressed to you regarding the cargo said to have been lying with Said bin Rashid as alleged by him we explained you the real fact of the case vide our letter No.471/6 dated the 13th. Jamad AX Awal. If the Agent has anything more to say, the Judgement is the decisive boundary between the disputants. As to the third para regarding the cargo purchase by Soori people, the purchasers would not hand over such cargoes unless they are refunded what they have paid to Captain Mahmood bin Ibrahim.r 5. fib * They should therefore refer to the Captain about the amount he has received from them. Aa for the fourth para regarding the parts of the wreck, we have stated all facts in connection with this c:;se in our letter No.364/5 o&amp;t&amp;d i&amp;tn.H&amp;bi A 1 Aichar and we have therefore no tiling more to add on the subject. rt Ae trust that you wilt oe easily able to note how ai i the letters from Madiiir Addakniiiyah differ from each other in view of what had happened and what was decided in the meeting. The mere fact that if Mr. I3aid bin ft&amp;hhid Sanuni of Soor would not have been authorised by dlir llddakhiliyah to salve cargo ex the wreck, the 360 packages including a case of motor generator would not have been held back at Sour uy laid bin Rnshid ana there would not have been no need to ask for repeated assistance to get the cargo to idiscat. Xt is to your knowledge tnat all salved cargoes except the above mentioned 360 packages have been received by us and most of them have already been sold by Public Auction. Further it is clear without any doubts that any actions taken by JTadhir Addakhiliyah without our knowledge are not binding to us nor to our contractors who have agreement with us only for the salvage of cargo at the specified terms and they have therefore no authority from us to settle anything on our behalf. As pointed out in the meeting of 20th. March, in addition our contractors have lodged a cl44a which amounts to Hs.3116# 4.0. being waiting charges for their 75 coolies, and 4 dhows for one day and their Motor Launch for 9 days due to following reasons* 1. Though they having boarded the wreck with full authorities from all concerned to salve cargo, were disallowed by Hadhir Mdakhiiiyah to resume salvage work on the first day. On the second day they were allowed to resume work on strict condition that both the parties viz. Our Contractors aid &amp;•. Said bin Hashid Sanani should salve cargo. In other words our contractors must deprive theujcelves from their legitimate rights or should turn back to Sfiusoat empty handed# 2. Due t© both the parties performing the salvage operations Mr* Jaioanadas knimji had to remain in their launch by the side of the wreck, during day and night to x.eep a correct record of the cargoes salved by Mr. 3aid bin Las hid and also th?t he had to proceed to door to meet N&amp;dhir Addakhiliyah to settle disputed matters quoted in the report of our contractors dated the 9th. March 1947.6 . As reveal ad by us, if Mr. Said bin Sashid agrees ta ^ £sr.!. p r^onS.&amp;£ / ;. p withd^f their claim of K *. 3l ^* 4 *°-.^Khl„“^S^das ^he^rtu^safp^ 1 ' f^ve^r^the^, they ^ad been S^i“d of their l«g^imata rights wi^out any cause whatsoever by Hadhir Addakhiliyah. The 11 D in^^hid, Add ?f ^wTa^d etcetera? £ Sectors bonded’the week 0 made 11 it clear thrt prior arrangements were made by iJadbir Addakhiliyah with Soori people for the salvage of oaTeO th ^ vou declined to our repeated requests since Ifth. ^e ?ver the savage work. Under the the c ltina tr losses arising in connection with the above are at the responsibility of Muscat Government. As regards the cargoes said to have been purchased h tha doori Deoole from the Master of the wreck, we &gt;,ouid refer ■ 4 to wh«t w 4 decided in the meeting da your presence and would therefore request you to kindly let us have a complete list of roods ourchased by tho Soori people showing the appropriate amounts at which they were said to be purchased to «nuDle us x. know the oosition and if necessary to refer the aia^oer t0 1,116 S^rs o/the weck at Alexandria, in the absence of such a list ^rsCiSVe lift ^ ^rr^rJ^iS^-fi^taronrin^S to the refunds claimed by the purchasers. Please send us a copy of Nadhir Audakhiliyah^ No.364/6 dated the 18th. Rabi 1 Akhar in regards to the parts of the wreck. In conclusion we would add that we have once more .cad the whole matter at a glance before you and trust that you Sill realize the unnecessary dificulties placed celore us in connections with matters which wara ®° the best’to March 1947. As far as we are concerned we have tt“ • come to an amicable settlement and in our opinion accepted by our contractors viz. hs f g or J ' 0 t , ^ left liberal for Mr. Said bin Rashid bonani of ^oor. It ib now lett in the hands of Sfcscat Government to amend the acts of their rdprafteirt• tives^ ear from you for satisfactory decisions and thanking you in anticipation. Yours Foi GRAY■ ■ ■■■ —1—fc ••air : &amp;—i—— JL -——:U-WlJUitUi. No# 605 &lt;• S* Dear Donaldson, Please refer to correspondence ending with my printed letter No. C/99 f dated the 31«t arch, 1947. 2. While at fcalalah 1 advised the Sultan to get all available evidence regarding the loss of the w £tar of atox* and the looting of her cargo carefully recorded. 3* Since we left ^alalah Stewart has told »e that the sultan has already received notice from the Egyptian Government that they hold him responsible for the loss both of the vessel and of her cargo. 4. the Sultan as an independent sovereign will presumably have to fight his own battle with the Egyptian Government but ) think we should he ready to offer hia advice. I know practically nothing about ffaritlme law. fcould it be possible for your legal expert to let us have his comments on the case ? I think practically all the facts are given in the reports I have sent you but if any further inforaatlon is required I will do my best to supply it. 6* If the gyptlan Covernment and the Sultan fail to reach an agreement Is there any tribunal to which the case could be referred 7 6. (n the 9th April we sailed close Inshore and had a look at the M 3tar of lex'. She is lying alongside the beach and the waves are breaking over her but she appears to be still Intact and has not heeled over. She will presumably break up when the monsoon starts. 7. I understand that essrs. Grey, Mackenzie, acting for the owners have removed moat if not all of the cargo that remained on her. I am told that this action is Irregular as once the ship was abandoned she and her cargo became the property of the Sultan and he ought to have arranged for the disposal of the cargo. 5. I a® sending a copy of this letter to His vajesty 1 * labassy, Cairo. Yours sincerely, L&gt;o. V*. It. **AY. PE! SIAff (JULF hr,3I0ESCY, BAHRAIN. the 16th Aprllf 1947. /1 (~-'7 fc. J*. iioneld.on, Eaquir., C.4.Q., India Office, hONuOM. C.A.^.PERSIAN GULF RESIDEKCY BAHRAIN. » mm$ mm Dat«d Froa To No Political Resident, Persian Gulf. His pasty's Secretary of State for India, LONDON. 767 - S. the 29th April, 1947. Your express letter No. Ext.718/47, dated the 14th April, 1947. M Star of ^ex*. 2. Sultan's Secretary has informed Political Agent that all that was received from Egyptian Government was a request for report on incident and cn steps taken to protect vessel. Following this a telegram was received from the owners stating that they held the Muscat Government respon sible for loss of ship and cargo. There is little likelihood of any compensation being paid. 4. Political Agent reports that cargo which remained intact in vessel has been discharged and sold by ship's Agent and that cargo off-loaded by faster before he abandoned ship has been recovered. 6« Muscat Government guards are still on vessel, but owners appear to be taking no action to salvage vessel and State will probably remove guards before monsoon when vessel is likely to break up. 6. A copy of paragraph 2 of this express letter is being forwarded to His Majesty's Ambassador, Cairo. Sd. W. R. HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. hirnmi Sd. J. Croning for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. No. 758 - S. Bahrain, the 29th April, 1947. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, MUSCAT.'Tjrp FROM GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; CO., LTD. Agent© f«r Ship Owners •» Muscat* n s 1 t ° The Director General of Customs., Muscat* No. GMC/ 60* Dear Sir, Muscat, 5th* May 19 47* We have to aovise having received the following telegram fron Ship Owners at Aiexandriai * Starofmex authorise auction sale Sugar Jeep and Hospital equipments* 11 The 47 bags of sugar and Jeep will therefore be sold by Public Auction ® n i n8 ^ an t'« We are still awaiting final decision of die Owners in respect of Tyree and Tubes, and Hospital equipments as we are afraid that these commodities’will not fetch reasonable value in Public Auction Sele* Yours f r, D , LTD, Agents- for dhip Owners. Copy tos The Political Agent A H.B.M’e Consul, Muscat• The Secretaxy | A To H. H. Tha 3ult*n of IfUBCt * Oman, Ifrjacat•CONEIDENTIAL, No. 1137-3 . ' ^ ^ U^\&amp;cjLj The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to ihe Political Agent, auis cat, / and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s)„ tor favour of a further report re: paragraph 3 of the foreign Office letter of ?nd oune. Dated the 13th June 1947 . PERSIAN'GUTF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. Reference to previous coxrespondence s Residency endorsement ho. 7b8-o , dated 29th April 19 47 . Description of enclosure ; Number and Date India Office demi-official letter No. Ext.1231/47 dated the 5th June, 1947. G.A.M. Subject &gt;. rooting of the ‘'Star of u.qjl' • ! ? 6 0J- is/t /&lt;f 7FOREIGN OSFFIDB, S. .1. (J.2155/50?/l6). brsjricted 2nd June, 1947* i diplomatio action vis-ai-vis the Sultan of uaoat no oificial Foreign office legal advice need he tendered for the moment. 2. This, mowever, is roughly the line vm shoul 1 The only ground on \-jhich the Sultan ought to pay compensation wouJ be if, given the character of his territory and the locality \shere the incident took place, he and his officials and police did less than they might reasonably be expected to do to protect the ship. • 3 . This can wo think be Judged better on the facts ty the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf than Xrj departments in London. But the main issue - and we should be grateful ii you could ascertain the fact of the matter on this point - is whether the Wali of Bur’s assertion is true, namely that all the damage vras done because the Master of the w dtar of Mesf over-rode the Wall’s advice not to mvite the tribesmen on board. If this is true, it looks as though tlie Master is to blaiae. Tiiere seems still to be a little doubt hov/ever in tne minds of the jjeople in the - ersian Gulf, .hie , this is cleare acoray, our own views will be clearer. Yours sincerely* (dgd.) D.I .H. Ricfies. F.A.K. Harrison, dsq., India Office.i r Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES HEAD OFFICE: 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON, E. C. 3 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. SblSREH. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR 9USH1RE* BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. GiJIC/ 75 RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Muscat^ 23rds June 1Q 4 The Political Agent &lt;k H« B, JPs Consul, Muecf.t • Dear 3ir, s.s. 11 Bt.^r of i-ilexs ^ Snclosed we hand you copies of our letters N’os# (MC/ 73 and 74 of date, addressed to the Secretary, to H* H. The Sultan of Muscat and Qaan, in connection with the above vessel, for your information and necessary action,, Cnclss 2 Yours faithfully, for GRAY MAC^t^UJI). Agents- f or Ship Owners 0m Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES. BUSREH. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAWSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSHIRE. BUNDER-ABBAS. IN REPLY PLEASE OUOT* HEAD OFFICE: 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E. C. 3. LINGAH. BAHREIN KOWEIT. GUC/ 73. Nc. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. COOES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR MascAt, 23rd. Jun® 47, 19 The Seer ataxy, _ A ^ T# H. H. The Sultan af Muscat wuum, Muscat. Dear Sir, s.s. 11 Star af M ax. “ el* the vessel, vide their l received here an loth, instarit, -vr The Alexandria Havigatiea Cay., xandria Navigatian Cay., S.A.S. Owners vide their letter af 29th. April 1947, instant, write ta us as under: rt Further t© aur ta-day's letter, and with reference ta yaur yasterday s cable, we end herewith capy af aur telsgrea sent ta the Minister of Foreign Affairs, i4iscat, tagether with capy af aur letter af the 22nd. February tc the saise Department, helding them respansible far all lessee and damages sustained ta ship's personnel, carge and prapertyas a result af the attacks, ©t the s time reserving all eur right® far adequate cempensatien in respect thereaf. We shall, therefere, request yau te maintain eur claim asking the Lecal Gevernment Autherities te cenfira admission ef their liability far damages *^6 le* s sustained through looting. rt w* take this opportunity in asking property through looting# We await te hear from you at an early date# Thanking yeu.Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES. BUNDER-ABBAS. 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E. C. 3. KHORAMSHAHR BAHREIN. KOWEIT. GUC/ 74, Nc. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH I RE. BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Muscat, 23rd, June 10 47» The Secretary, Tu H, K* l'he Sultan ef i^iBcat &amp; Oman, Muscat* Dear* Sir, s.s. ' smr tox - H«i 3o0. Packagsa still in possassian af ivlr* Said bln Rashid Sansini at* iia©r* We refer you te our letter No.QMC/5h 27th* *pril 1947. end a av ourjtajj^ ot m.**at ** s-nHl 'l Cftk lift witli a reclv at MX the 360 packages in possession Mt Mr* Said bin Rashid cf So or* We weuld add that as explained in our letter - . » . _ 1 l k tim 4* Vk A t anv loss to the Ship Owners or to the ill be the liability of the Muscat Government referred above* any loss to the snip owners Undvii’wi'itrrs will be the liability of the Muscat as the less is due t© the acts ef their Ofticials Waiting to hear frem yeu aoon and thanking you in antic ipot^on, '^ie^roliticai /\gent 8 i|jiusca^‘i’ ,»#• 3 7% Offitt *f the Secretary t# the Smltan ef If*scat and Oxm*. Muscat 9 dated 7^h July,1947 The Agent, Grab Mackenzie &amp; Ce. Ltd., Muscat Dear Sir, With reference te yenr letter Ke.GJIC/74 dated 23rd Jnne 1947,Sniehin Rashid Alsinani has act yet teen able to teue te Mneeat,hut X will inferr yen when he arrives. Yenr remarks in the adore letter that 1 any less te the •hi# owners ••• will he the liability of the Muscat Gerernaient ao the loss is due te the acts ef their officials * are net ment officials or ignorance ef the in#ertant facte in the issue. It is most im#re#er that such an arbitrary and swee#ing ntingttnn allegation shewId hare been made by yen acainet the Got erlament officials,and yen are requested to make your formal n#elegiee,threngh me, te the Mneent GeTernment. Ce#y te Hha j^ritAnma hajesty’s Consul Museat.4 Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) HEAD OFFICE: 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E. C. 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BRANCHES. BUSREH. BUNDER-ABBAS. AMARAH. LINGAH. KUT. BAHREIN. KHORAMSHAHR KOWEIT. AHWAZ DUBAI. BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR SHARJAH. BUSHIRE. MUSCAT. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Muscat t 10th. IN REFLY PLEASE QUOTE auc/ si. Nc July 10 47. /■v The Secretary, Te, H, H. The Sultan ef Muscat &amp; Oman, Muscat• Dear Sir, Wreck rt Star Of Mex » rt Be: 360# Packages Merchandise still in possessien ef Mr* Said bin Rashid ef Seer / f ealved since March 1947« We have te acknewledge receipt ef yeur letter Ne*378 ef 7th. instant, informing us that Mr. Said bin Rashid Alsanani has not yet been able te ceme te Muscat but yeu will inferm us when he arrives, fer which we thank yeu. We have also noted that eur remarks fer the less are net accepted and that this reveal either a prejudice against the Government officials or ignorance ef the important facts in the issue. Further yeu censider that it is meat improper that such an arbritrary and sweeping allegatien sheuld have been made by us against the Government Officials and therefore we are requested te make a formal apelegies, threugh you, to the Blue cat Sevemnemt. From the abeve we observe that the whole matter which was placed befere you vide eur letter Ne.GMC/55 ef 27th. April 1947, te which we did net get a reply till date, has not even received sympathetic consideratien. We shall therefere be obliged if you will kindly not# that our acts have been without prejudice and shall remain witheut prejudice. As regards *e eur ignerance abeut the important facts in the issue, it is quite clear that unless and until we did net get a satisfactory reply te eur letter en the subject matter, it is net pessible fer us te learn the important facts in tho issuo. Further in the absence of such replies, it is net possible for us to txplainmR i -a- |b&gt;‘ ■the mutter te the ^hip Ownere fer v/hich we act as Agents, ^e shall therefore be grateful if yeu will kindly put us in a positien te explain te the Ship Omers that 1 , The appeintment ef Mr. Said bin Rashid Sanani te salve carge ex the wreck without informing yeu er us by the Nadhir Aidakhiliyah, was in the interest ef the Ship Owner er Underwriters* 2* Te disallow eur contractors Messrs. Kniroji Ramdas to s-lve carge on the first day and then te order both the parties te s alve cargo were in the interest ef the Ship Owners or Under wir it era * Pleat e note that as advised in eur letter Ne.GMC/55 ef 27th. April 1947, Messrs. Khixnji Ramdas have lodged a claim fer the sum ef Rs.3116.4.0* being their expenses fer net working on the first day and the engagement of their launch in connection with the dealings with Nadhir Addakhiliyah at Bur and Khabba* 3. hy the cargo of 360 packages salved by Mr. Said bin Rashid aince March 1947, still remains unfixed for reaching J&amp;scat* 4* All inpertant facts in the issue he which we are kept ignorant* By learning the above eur position as Agents fer Ship Owners will be clarified te a great extent, and weuld be able te explain te Messrs. Khimji Ramdas regarding their claim alse*, accordingly* Please note that we have had net the slightest intention te bring any allegations against the Mjiseat Gevemment Officials but the silence en the subject matter which is being discussed since eur letter Ne.GSC/25 ef 12th. March 1947, we in view ef what had been explained in eur letter Ne.GMC/55 ef 2 7th* ^pril 1947, and what had been done, came te the cencluaien that the mat tar is net still bsing avt dealt adequately* New, if eur cenclusien been censidered as incerrect in the epinien ef the Muscat Government, we are ready te apologise for eur actien, keeping in view the leng eutstanding cordial relatienship with the Muscat Government* Please therefore, cenvoy eur sincere apologies te the Muscat Government* Before we cenclude, we ence again wish to make it clear that in the absence ef your replies te eur letters en the subject matter, eur position as Agents fer Ship Owners has been very awkward end we therefore again request yeu te kindly put us in a pesitien to knew the important facts in the issue* Thanking you, ^nnUFTPENT-UI. Ho. C.405-19/3-0 THE POLITICAL AGENCY MUSCAT, Dated 14th July,1947 To The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum A Reference Residency Printed Letter No. 1137-S dated the 13th June, 1947. It is not possible to confirm definitely that the 2 Halt of Sur's assertion is true. 3. The Alexandria Navigation Company, through their agents Messrs.Gray Mackenzie and Company, have now asked the Muscat Government to confirm admission of the liability for damages and loss sustained to ship^ personnel, cargo and property through looting. Copy of Messrs .Gray Mackenzie and —-— j ^ ^0 Company's letter is attached. 4. I understand that no reply will be given to this letter until it has been referred to the Sultan. In any case I consider it most unlikely that the Muscat Government will admit to any liability for the damage and loss sustained. A Offg. Political Agent, Muscat.f S^e^w. ^ A. !&lt;&gt;i ulO' Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES HEAD OFFICE: 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E. C. 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE CODE. SblSREH. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAWSHAHR AHWAZ B UNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE- BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE GMC/ 86. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Jfcjacat, 11th. August 47. Tha Director General of Customs*, Muscat* Dear Sir, tfrtiGk rt Star of Mex* We are instructed by th.e Owners of the above wreck to sell all balance cargo by auction sale and advise them details account sales soonest possible* We are therefore arranging to sell by Public Auction the following, lying in the Customs, on Wednesday the 13th* instant at 10/00 A*M* s 193* Pieces Tyres 8. Bundles Tubes* (233 pieces) &amp;* Nongs Bowing boats* 79* Iron Bedsteads* 2. Nongs Steel Cupboards. 25. Cases Hospital Equipments ^ ' 2 5: M&amp; 6 pl ^a8?* %l pl * ces) 9* Pieces Mattresses 4* Bundles *do. 349. Cop^r Muscat* The Secretary, to H.H.The Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat*M.O.W/F &amp; 19/3-D Telegram From To GTC Political Agent, Muscat. Residency, Bahrain. No. G.247. Dated 23rd August, 1947. Among cargo salvaged from Star of Mex and now being auctioned is a new X-Ray set A.C. So far as can be Judged it is in excellent condition and is to go for less than Rs.lCOO/-.. Are you interested? If so reply urgently. POLITICALconfid ential. D#0 .No. 1519-5 the 19th August 1947 cJiJL^r t With reference to correspond-ehce ending with Hudson’s memorandum No. C*405-19/3-Gf dated tlie 14th July 1947 I enclose copy of my demi-official letter No. 1518-S of today to Donaldson. 2. I stould he glad if you would visit Sur after the close of the monsoon and enquire into the matter there 3. You will not fail to realise the importance to the Muscat Government of the value of establishing the truth of the Wali of Sur’s assertion. Nevertheless, in making your enquiries you will, of course, keep an open mind. ^ Major A.C. Stewart, O.B.E., Political Agent, MUSCATgsMsumAk* THE RE3IB33SC3Y, BAHRAIN, the 19th August 1947* My dear Donald3on 9 p Isa os refer to your demi-official letter Mo*Mat•1251/41 dated the 6th June 1947 to Hay about the 'Star of Hex*. 2* Hudson* who has Been unable to visit Sur owing to the prevailsoe of the monsoon* reports that it has not Been possible to confine definitely that the Wall of 3ur f s assertion is true# I m asking Stewart to visit Sur After the does of the monsoon at the end of September and to enquire into the matter* 5* In the meantime the Alexandria Navigation Company have asked the Muscat Government through Grty Maokensle and Company to confirm admission of the liability for damages and loss sustained to ship , s personnel* cargo and property through looting* A copy of Gray Maokensle v s letter is/attached* 4* Hudson adds that he understands that no reply will Be given to this letter until it Is referred to the Sultan and that in any ease it is most unlikely that the Muscat Government will admit mny liability* Yours sincerely* Sd. A.C.GAU.OWAY M*2&gt;* Donaldson miquire* C*M.O,, Commonwealth Relations Office* King Charles Street* Whitehall* DQ»DON ,ir ,A Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE: 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E. C. 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BUSREH. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR 3USHIRE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. !N REPLY PLEASE OUCTE OHC/ 100. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Mugcatt 29thG ^pteicber 1Q _47 &gt; Salvors of Cargo ex Wreck n St^r Of i^ex rt . Muscat. f Dear Sira, \€^ (j / Hes 360. Packages Merchandise in possession of Mr. Paid bin Ha&amp;hid Assinaai of : ; ur ex v'reck rt Star Of Mex rt . V/e are advised by the Secretary, to HsH. The Sultan of Muscat dk Otoan, that an agreement has been concluded between you and Mr. Said bin haehid Assinani in respect of the above, resulting that Mr. S»id bin Rashid to purchase the 360 packages at a net value of 3s,4643/-, all Customs Charges to be by him, and that out of this sum of .464^3/- Mr. Said will deduct the sum of Ks .3443/- as his charges for salving and storing the 360 packages, paying you the balance of Rs.1200/-. * In this connection we hp.ve to inform you that we have no objection to dispose the 360 packsges at the net value ef hs.4643/- providedyou confirm that we are free from ^11 Customs Ch^rgea and^uiat youfclaim against us for the sum of Hs.3116.4,0. is now null and void. a *■ Please remit with your confix*mation the sum of Rs.4643/ fqi &lt;z£m*' a Agants- for &gt;hip Owners. Cepyte* The Political igent &lt;1 H.B.M*s Consul, i^jscat. The Secretary, to H. H. The Sultan of Muscat 3c uman, Muse at. The Director General of Cuatoaa, Muscat. ? cr ! /a' sGray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES HEAD OFFICE: 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E. C. 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BUSREH. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWA2 BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE OUOTE CMC/ 101. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR V;, Muscat, 6th» October 19 47» The Secretary, To H, H. The Sultan of Muscat &lt;&amp; a&amp;an, Muscat* Dear Sir, Re: 360 Packages Merchandise in possession of Mr. Said Bin Rashid Assinani of Sur ex Wreck ^ntar Of Mex*. We refer you to your letter No #462/^ of 7ths ultirae, and our letter No.(SMC/100 of 29th. ultimo, addressed te Messrs. Khimji Ramdas, with a copy to you, in respect of the above, Messrs. Khiwji Ramdas have replied to us as under vide their letter of 4th. instant: Reference to your letter No.GMC/100 dated the 29th. Sept,1947, we beg to inform you that the representatives of Mr. Said bin Rashid Alsanani have confirmed before the Muscat Government that ail the Customs Charges will be paid by Mr. Said bin Rashid and hence you are free from all Customs Charges. As regards our claim for Rs.3116-4-0• we confirm that same is now null and void as in consideration of the circumstances we had to agree to the demands of Mr. Said bin Rashid Alsanani. We send herewith the sum of Rb• 4643/- being net cost of 360. packages. * We shnll be glad if you will kindly note that we have no objection to the agreement concluded between Mr.Said bin Rashid Assinani and Messrs, khimji Ramdas. ■ Cepy t o: / /? w TJiofi'l /EXTRACT SECRET MUSCAT INTELLIGENCE SUMMARY NO. 16 FOR THE PERIOD 16th to 31st August, 1947. LOCAL AFFAIRS. 227. Reference Serial 55 of 1947. Several of the minor Shaikhs from Sur District have been summoned to Muscat for examination in connection with the investigations being carried on into the looting of the H Star of Mex”. 'Saiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim, ivlinister of the Interior, who went to Sur some months ago to hold preliminary investigations and recover as much of the loot as possible, returned to Muscat stating that he had recovered everything but so far none of the recovered goods have found their way to Muscat and it is now generally believed that all that he did was to exact a share for himself. If so, he now regrets it, for the Sultan is not letting the master slide and the investigations will undoubtedly be carried on with more vigour on his return to Muscat. Yaqub bin Abdullah, the Lali of Sur, has already been discharged from his appointment on the grounds of incompetence and in the belief that even if he did not connive at the occurrence he at least took a rake-off after it had happened. Saiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim, seems to fear a similar fate. .-A*.P.O. Mo. C. 546-19/3-0 Political Agency, Muscat. 19th October 1947. Will you please refer to Colonel Galloway^ demi- official letter No. 1519-S dated the 19th August 1947. 2. I did not fail to realise the importance to the Muscat Government of establishing the truth of the Wall of Sur^ assertion mentioned in paragraph 2 of iqy letter No. C. 128-19/3-G dated the 17th February 1947 and whilst I was on the spot with all the witnesses present, made the most thorough enquiries. I also pointed out to the Muscat State representative the importance of establishing the truth of these assertions. In spite of my endeavours, however, I was not able to collect any precise evidence, nor indeed was I greatly surprised since it seemed to me most unlikely that a dispute of this nature between the Nall and the Master of the vessel would have taken place in public and in the presence of witnesses. On the whole I was inclined to believe the Wal^s assertion that he protested against the discharge of the cargo by other than his own people, if only for reasons of cupidity^ since it is clear that if he had control of the working of the cargo any profits accruing legally or illegally from this work would come to him alone and would not have to be shared with / other parties. 3. In the months which have intervened since the 'Star of Mex' went aground, very little if any of the looted cargo appears to have been recovered^ I attribute this, and indeed / it The Hon'ble Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident Persian Gulf, Bahrain.2 mr / it is the general belief, to corruption amongst Muscat State officials who were sent from time to time to carry out enquiries into the event. It therefore seems to me that if I now proceed to Sur to make further enquiries I am not only unlikely to obtain more precise evidence than I was able to obtain on the spot at the time of occurrence, but am also likely to come up against considerable opposition from State officials who would probably assume that I was making ray enquiries in an attempt to build up a case against the State, rather than, as in fact would be ray purpose, in the interests of the State. In the circumstances would it be preferable to let the matter of further enquiries stand over until the Sultan’s return and then urge him, in his own interests, to make a more searching investigation ? Personally, I doubt if it will ever be possible to obtain reliable and irrefutable evidence as to the Ifali’s assertion. He was in any case suspended from his appointment shortly after the incident.CONFIDENTIAL PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY , D.Q. N0.1865-S BAHRAIN , the 29th October, 1947 \ / f i / n i u Please refer to your demi-official letter No,C/546-19/3 dated the 19th October, 1947, about the M Star of Mex n . 2. I am inclined to agree that there is little hope of obtaining further information in this case until the Sultan returns to Muscat but I would suggest that you should take an early opportunity of visiting Sur in the ordinary course of your duties but not with the avowed object of making enquiries into the ’'Star of Mex' case and see what further information if any you can pick up there Major A.C. Stewart, O.B.E., Political Agent, MUSCAT * LB 1 Ifl /olo ntnow y ' 20A &amp; 19/3-0 Telegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Muscat. To Political Resident, Bahrain No* 0*522 Dated 25th November 1947* I propose leave for Sur on tour 26th November returning Muscat 30th November* POLITICALCONFIPFNTIAL / D*Q* Mo, C&gt;592 - 19/3-Q Political Agenoy, Moacat* 30th Kovaafcar 1947. Will you ploaaa refer to your D.O. latter Wo* 1865-6 dated the 29th October 1947* I visited Sur leaving Muscat on November 26th and 2. spent an Interesting day seeing the town and exchanging calls with the Wall and four principal Sheikhs, Naslr bln Mobamraed, Hamad bln Khalfan, Salim bln Naslr and Abdullah bln Naslr. 1 think ay visit caused some curiosity and shortly 3. before I mas due to leave Muscat X received a letter from Salyld Ahmad bln Ibrahim, Minister of the Interior, asking If I mould be good enough to give passage to two of his men shorn he wished to send to Sur on urgent business. I saw no object in refusing but have the feeling that their business mas primarily to find out mine. I mas In aiy case closely shepherded throughout my visit and unable to find out anything fresh in connection with the 'Star of Max' incident. 4. On the may back I paid a visit to Khor Jarama, which \ is only about two hours by launch from Sur. I was moat impressed by what I saw. It la a large inlet sheltered, and with a deep though narrow and winding entrance, and must be a very fine sea plane landing place. There Is a petrol store In excellent condition on the Southern shore and there mas I understand, until recently a mooring buoy, this has elthar sunk or been removed. I mas greatly impressed by the * nl *fc &lt; * possibilities as a landing place and could not help but be surprised that the Royal Air Force had not asked us to Include It when negotiating the Air Agreement. The Hon'ble Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Resident Persian Gulf, Bahrain.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000f3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/468</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000f3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/468</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File No: 19/3-G Name: Boarding of Star of Mex (by Arabs)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-02-20T10:53:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (125 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 127; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 83-111; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding an incident in which an Egyptian-owned merchant vessel named
                           Star of Mexicoran ashore at Ras al Hadd and was reportedly boarded and 'looted' by locals. The correspondence discusses the initial incident and events subsequent to it, including attempts to disembark the vessel's cargo and whether it was salvageable or not.This correspondence is between British officials (primarily at the Political Agency and Consulate in Muscat), Ali Muhammad al-Jamali (the Secretary of the Sultan of Muscat and Oman) and Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited (the agents of the owners of
                           Star of Mexico).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited, shipping agents</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000f3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>