<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00001a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T04:04:40.941Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">$UlOO It is requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, LONDON, SAV. 1. 20th April, 1937« I am directed hy the Secretary of State for India to refer to the correspondence of which copies were sent to the Colonial Office under the printed letter from this Office, dated 5th February Ho.P.S.730/37# regarding the acquisition of an additional site for an Admiralty oil fuel storage tank at Aden. I am now to enclose, for the information of the Dated / Secretary of State for the Colonies, a copy of a letter from 31st / March/ the Government of India, from which it will be seen that oo far ao the Government of India are concerned they would have had no objection to waiving recovery of the rent of 2 pieo per square yard in respect of the site in question. As the administration of the Aden Settlement is now a matter for the Colonial Office, Lord Zetland assumes that Mr. Secretary Qmsby-Gore will pursue this question with the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty. A I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, :&gt; IQ The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, S.F.l.Dated New Delhi, the 31st March 1937. Acquisition of an additional site for an Admiralty Oil Fuel Storage Tank at Aden. Sir, With reference to the letter from the India Office, No. P.Z.730/37, dated the 6th February 1937, I am directed to state that as far as the Government of India are concerned, they have no objection to waiving recovery of the rent of 2 pies per square yard in respect of the site in question. 2. The presumption contained in paragraph 3 of the above letter is correct. 3. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Chief Commissioner, Aden. /jod. mi. 19 APR 1937 INDIA OFFICE] .. v V. ■ Lm9*m I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Deputy Secretary to the Government /of India, ( % p./ ! -Admiralty to refer to India Office letter dated 28th December 1936 No. P.Z*9125/36 concerning the site for an Oil Fuel Storage Tank at Aden, and to a.cquaint you for the information of the Secretary of State for India that My Lords have approved the payment of £2,000 as compensation for the buildings on the site. Payment of this sum will be made on completion of any necessary legal document by which the Messageries Maritimes Co. will relinquish the land and buildings to the Port Trust. Possession of the land and buildings will be taken by the Admiralty as soon as the Port Trust give i»heir consent, and while it has hitherto been assumed that Admiralty occupation would be on the same terms as the Messageries Maritimes Cie. held the land viz: an annual rental at 2 pies per square yard (approximately £6 per annum), My Lord_s desire to know whether following the precedent of Their occupation of the main storage site rent free (India Office reference No. P.Z.5439/35, 13th August 1935), and for the sake of uniformity this rental The Under Secretary of State, of... India Office, Whitehall, sf S.W.l.of 2 pies per square yard will be waived. If a formal document recording Admiralty' occupation of the main site is considered necessary, My Lords- suggest that the site now in question could well be incorporated in the same document. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,!CrCH^ffli (90 words.) (COPIES CIRCULATED) JL&amp;JLjLJ LJ Q-F .. T E L E S R A M. - Prom Chief Conmissioner, Aden, io Secretary of State for Indi a. Dated Aden, 23rd December, 1936. Received 2.15 p.m., 23rd December, 1936. ft? 2S21L Reference to your letter P^Zo5575/36 of 19th ? 19365 , to Foreign and Political Department, Government of India? regarding the resumption of the site from the a eager! 03 Maritimes Company for the Admiralty, Chairman of Aden Port Trust states that compenaation of £1500 offered (? by, omitted) Admiralty was inadequate as against £4012 claimed by Maesageries Mari times Company and that he had suggested £2000 as being fair compensation, to which Principals, Measageries Mari times, hare now agreed,, I understand that the Admiralty have intimated that they would seek authority for payment of compensation of £2000, if Mnis figure was considered as tending to fair settlement by me* I agree that compensation now proposed is equitable* 24 DEC 1930 fJD £ OFFICEFroiE wm. I To '3!! ? COI v Ho* F, 590-^1 •/36# The Addl. Deputy Secy, zo the Oovermeent of Inaia in the Foreign and Political Department The Chief Commissioner* Men. Dated Simla, the 9/^ September 1936. Proposed acquisition of site at Aden by the Admiralty. I am directed to refer to the correspondence ending with the letter trom the Governosenu of India in the Foreign and Political Department i o. F.297-U./34, dated the 25th September 1936, and also to the India Office letter fio. P.2. 6575/36, dated the 19th August 1936, (copy sent direct) and to request that the action referred to in paragraph 2 of the India Office letter may kindly be taken and the result communicated to the Government of India, in due course. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant.» * r “ . ■ V./U’ .dC\.4-0C3 .% .oH 4^* i V&lt; 1 ' &gt; V* jw®I Joi^movoU ariJ oir . T^oeB ^to&lt;g»a a ;r ^ ■ ' ■ ■: £.80x4 ilo^ bru: A,; ai t TsnoxsaifsnoO 'ioidO erit • iI9 b;'; • &amp;£bt t circle bd^;ja ki^bA Jh s»Ji® lo ii©l^iuiup©a • &amp;riJ \rcf - i ; i ‘ I .,!« »0«»I&gt;fi0q»e '''*0© 04- T^i^T oJ 09lib R5« X jiibal lo tmmaT&amp;T 9 $ mid jeo 4 *! i9*&amp;6l &amp;tti dflw %alhue t*£\.K-V9S.t *0 A J Xaoi^iXo^ bUCI OrW ttl (*iU- 03' oeiA bae »5Sex i^cfmsXqea d^as saA be*3^b iif&amp;X 9h$ bssaf) #S. f i «ou tsJ'XsX eAJ J ‘itij leasip^t o3 bsta {Joe’xXb Sma zqoo) «oS€X f-oilAO BifcnX sritf 1c S dqar.-x’T^q ai o3 iioijojs bo^roinr'Tfcoo Xluso^t ertf hm mtinf od* ^IbnXA &amp;6ta “isAisI *98tuoo 9Jib ni &lt;&amp;i bill 1c 3 .ieCiLTrsvoQ adj o3 * 9 cf o 3 Tucnori ©d^ oviid I &lt;Tia ♦ jafr/*T9 3 Jasibsdo jaotii *xucY , no aa J ( A -\bS ..tstbnl lo tmumBToV ©rfX o3” ^tuq«C© Mr. Waltxdn, ^ '(6 So far as I can see we are merely a postoffice in this matter. The only point which is of more than local interest appears to be that the French Government may possibly take an interest in the acquisition by Government of this property, at present occupied by the Messageries Company, because they (the French Government) have a financial interest in the Company. But that hardly seems to be our business and is not, presumably, any bar to the proposed action being taken. It may, however, be worth suggesting to the Admiralty that the Foreign Office might have a copy of the correspondence.Draft Paper, The foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Sir, Foreign &amp; Political Department, Simla, India. of S Pz. 5 J^ DRAFT LETTER. of State to refer to the letter from the I am directed by the Secretary political Department 19 AUG 1956^ © Admiralty dated 1st August, No.C.E. in C. 4303/36/22 h, copies of which were forwarded to the Government of India and desire to acquire the site,lettered A'BEj) AD PIE) on the plan enclosed with the correspondence, v/hich is at present occupied by the Compagnie des Messageries Government of India see no objection, the Chief Commissioner may be instructed to \M\tZaXC \A~iaU*A/i fcfrkre the necessary n t eps Ser £he noted that any agreement arrived at as to conditions should be on a provisional Commissioners of the Treasury will be required before terms can be finally concluded. 3. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Chief Commissioner, Aden. Copy to 1 to the Chief Commissioner, 0 n the 0 ua C o. , , i.8 Aoii (958 13th August, regarding Oilfielda Storage at Aden, from which it appears that the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty 2. I am to request that, if the acquisition of this site. It will be basis, since the sanction of the Lords {SMjxawAiam 4794 5000 5.36 ,1© Draft Paper. P.Z. 5575/3 5. political Department. The Secretary, Admiralty, S.W.l. / F o. c o /' 18 DHAF 1 LETTER. Ml 61956 Sir, With reference to the letter from the Admiralty dated 1st August, No.C.E.in C.4303/36/22 b, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward for the information of the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty copy of a letter which has been sent to the Government of India requesting them iv^/vw/ to re-qiiect- the Chief Commissioner to the necessary steps for the acquisition of the site required for F&lt;*jdL Oil^iretd^ Storage. 2. In view of the possibility that the French Government may be interested in the transaction a copy of this letter and its enclosure is jbeing sent to the Foreign Office. I am j |to suggest that a copy of the Admiralty letter irr reply might also be sent to the Foreign Office. / /? cAa ^ d/io luiUA /^/ $a ( ^ tu Ct ^ ^ tfaM. Ik fceHijjudi ■ fid.) J. C, WAJjffOM, 4794 5000 5.36 ■-n 70 SI CO © O 3 m s r m o 70 CO 04 s m H o m o TO m G s m H -o H &gt;► TO 04 “D m O £D m &gt;► r~ d o 04 05 r- -n r- O r~ m M ^ c Any further comnmnicatio should be addressed to — The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.W. 1 quoting * • CEinC . 4303/ 3 5/2 Sir, LP—No 8 y! dmiralty, S.W.1. /. 1936 . I am commanded LUI'^S' commissioners of the Admiralty to refer to India Office letter dated 13th y August 1935, No. P .Z.5439/5 5 concerning the site for Oil Fuel Storage at Aden and to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that, as part of that installation. My Lords find it necessary to erect a single tank on the site shewn in red on the enclosed plan No.504/36, and lettered A, B, E, D. 2. Prom informal discussions and correspondence (copy enclosed) that have taken place between the Admiralty Officer in Charge of Works, Aden, and the Chairman, Aden Port Trust, it appears that this site is occupied by the Compagnie des Messageries Maritimes under the terms of a letter (copy also enclosed) dated 19th October, 1#61 from the then Political Department, Aden, which letter reserves the power of resumption if the land is required for a public purpose subject to the payment of compensation for any buildings erected by the Company on the site^ * The X Under Secretary of State, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. V v . t d AU61936 N *J 3./V 3. It is understood that the Port Trust Authorities anticipate no difficu ty in resuming the area and transferring it to the Admiralty for the purpose required on the same terms as those granted to the present tenants, but it will be observed that the Chairman of the Port Trust in letter dated 9th March 1936, refers to the possibility of the French Government being interested in the transaction. 4. In the circumstances, I am to ask that the Secretary of State will be good enough to initiate the necessary action to secure the resumption of the area of land required and its transfer to the Admiralty with the least possible belay, and on the most favourable terms that can be arranged. In this connection I am to observe that My Lords are advised that payment for the buildings should not exceed £1,500. They note from the letter from the Chairman of the Port Trust dated 9th March, 1936 that it is possible that in addition compensation may have to be paid in respect of the land but they presume that the terms of the letter of 19th October 1861 and of the Aden Settlement Rules under both of which compensation for land is definitely precluded will be borne in mind in negotiating terms.5. I am to request that any agreement arrived at as to conditions may be on a provisional basis aa the sanction of the Treasury will be required before terms can be finally concluded. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Enc : Plan No.504/56 Copy correspondence^S— ,. JJ), iMMPI. 11 COPY Chairman, Aden Port Trust. hn 1- ; ■&gt; • I’. ' 5575 j , i .J Admiralty Oi^. Fuel Depot, Hedjuff, Aden, 4fch February 1936. f a*A' \ Dear Sir, The Admiralty wish to consider the acquisition oP the land shown edged in red on the attached Plan O.C.W. Aden No.^8&gt;in connection with the storage of Oil Fuel and to enable them to do so it is requested that I may be informed what amount of compensation would be required for all the buildings on the Site and what the total annual rendtwould be for the land. Yours faithfully, (Sgd. ) J.P. LUMLEY Officer in Charge of Works No. 54 Enclosure O.C.W. Aden Drawing No.8COPY No. 488 of 1936. Port Trust Office. Prom: To: j.s'T/ The Chairman, Port Trust, Aden. The Officer in Charge of Works, Admiralty Oil Puel Depot/ Hedjuff. Dear Sir, i qr?/. I - in rece ipt Of your letter dated 4th February the 6 Adm-frnompa-nying plan from which it is observed that edSed^n to . consilie r the acquisition of the land aulntlv ft ^°Z e ? entioned Plan and that, conse- quently, it is desired to know what amount of compensation ZZlt be SrtotaT f ?n a1 ^ on tLZfCZnZZat wouia oe the total annual rent of the land. wh • , J 11 re Ply I am to say that the portion of the site which, for reference, I have marked A.D.E.B is held hv Messageries liaritimes on lease and that, consequently^the information required as to that land and the buildings thereon should be obtained from them. g . // th re S ar(i “to the portion marked A.B.C. this was specially purchased by the Aden Port Trust from the Messageries Maritimes in October 1930 as part of a general scheme for the housing and segregation of coolies engaged m connection with Shipping, in an attempt to put aS eflto or limit the magnitude of, the periodical outbreaks of Plaaup considered the PaSt ’ scheme^ 6 two 1 00^1 d p^hi ^ f ^ llc importance and of which the €?Ptti’omei+ P ^ llC ? 0dies ^ the Aden Port Trust and the Aden Settlement, bore between them half the cost, the balance being contributed by the Shipping Agents concerned. P * n T q iS 7T la n d W 5 S then leased ^ ^e Port Trust to the ‘* f. u * b# / Go * dor constructing accommodation for the coolies employed by them thereon. after 3 u _ estion .^as only selected for the purpose t f J hQ ost careful consideration as being the only Wharves^ Sr ° Und Wlthin reasonable distance of the P. &amp; 0. It is submitted that the acquisition of this la-nH -fm- any purpose other than that for which it is at present used should be a matter of the very gravest consideration. +h Should it be held that, after due deliberation, no other land will meet the requirements of the Admiralty it is necessary to draw attention to the fact that, in the Deed whereby the Messageries Maritimes surrendered to the Port declared^ 11- riSllt tltle anii interest in this land, it is♦ 1. The Trustees shall use the said Land for the purpose only of granting same on lease to the P. &amp; Q. S. N. Go. for the purpose of accommodating Coal and Cargo Coolies. 2. Should the said land not in fact be used for the purpose specified in the last preceding clause or should it at any time in the future forvany reason cease to be so used and should the Trustees not intend at that time again to put it to such use the Messageries Maritimes shall have the option of resuming possession of the said land. Therefore in respect of this area, the Admiralty would have to compensate the P. &amp; 0. S. N. Co. for the cost of large blocks of buildings and smaller outhouses all built as late as 1931 and negotiations with regard to the land itself would, presumably have to be conducted with the Messageries Maritimes. Yours faithfully (Sgd.) M.I.C.E Chairman Aden Port Trust Enc : O.C.VY. Aden Drawing No.8.COPY No.699 of 1906. Prom: To: Port Trust Office. 9th March 1936. The Chairman, Port Trust, Aden. The Officer in Charge of Works, Admiralty Oil Fuel Depot, Hedjuff. Dear Sir, I am to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated 22nd February 1936, and to say:- That although the original letter of grant under which the Messageries Maritimes site is held provides for resumption by Government whose rights now vest in the port Trust, and no mention is made for compensation for the land itself, but only of the buildings, nevertheless, it is believed, from experience with land held similarly by another Company in Aden that, if negotiations were actually undertaken to resume land in the occupation of the Messageries Maritimes, it would be found, in practice, that compensation would have to be paid or another site given to them in exchange. It is not known how far the French Government too, might be interested in these negotiations, in view of the financial agreement between that Government and the Messageries Maritimes. The only rent paid by the Messageries Maritimes is 4u.it rent at the nominal rate of 2 pies per sq.yard which, on the area marked A.D.E.B. on Plan 0.0.W. Aden No. 8 would amount to 7644 sq_. yards @ 2 pies - Rs. 79.10.0. per annum. With regard to the land at present in the occupation of the P. &amp; 0. Company the Messageries Maritimes, it is true have the option to resume same on payment to the Port Trust of a sum of Rs.15,012.8.0. if it ceases to be used for its present purpose, but it is not certain that the Admiralty would be entitled to take over the site at the same figure from i,hem. The cost of the buildings erected by the p. &amp; 0. Company was Rs.28,035/- and they are practically new. An annual Quit rent of Rs.93,13.3. is paid on this ground, being 3002^ sq. yds. at 6 pies per sq. yd. (the rate for Building sites). Yours faithfully, (Sgd. ) Ag. Chairman Aden Port Trust. Accompt . 1 PlanCOPY / ENCLOSURE Extract from Form A for grant of leases under Aden Settlement Spies. (a-a) Cancel this portion where rent is paid on the hasis (b) If the said plot of land or any portion thereof shall be declared by the Lessor to be required by Government for Public purpose (which declaration shall be final and conclusive) the Lessor may without notice re-enter upon the said plot of land or such portion as may be so required, freed from all claims and liabilities created by the Lessee or any person claiming through him, and thereupon this lease shall be determined in respect of the said plot of land or such portion thereof. AND in case of re-entry under this condition, the Lessee shall be entitled to compensation as follows:- (a) (A sum equal to the purchase money paid by the Lessee for the right of lease or, if re-entry is made upon a portion only of the land, then a sum bearing the same proportion to the amount of the purchase money as the area of the portion of the land resumed bears to the whole area together with ) (a) The actual value of the buildings, if any, constructed under due authority by the Lessee and in existence bon the portion of the land resumed at the time of re-entry such actual value shall be determined by a committee of arbitra tion appointed in accordance with the rules under the Aden Settlement Regulation, 1900. And the Lessee shall be entitled to no other compensation save as hereby expressly provided: And the decision of the committee of arbitration as to the actual value of the buildings,if any, as aforesaid, shall be conclusive. (c) Nothing herein contained shall be construed to exempt the Lessee from the payment of such quit-rent, assessment, rates, taxes and other dues, as may be leviable on the said plot of land under the law of rules having the force of law for the time being in operation.COPY No.583 of 1861 Political Department Aden, 19th October 1861. Prom, Captain R.L. Playfair To, M. G-iwette, Inepecteur Oeneral des Services, Mari times des Messageries Imperisles. 4r, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter °f yesterday’s date, requesting certain concessions required for service of the Company you represent at Aden. 2. I have no hesitation in granting all the points you have mentioned, subject ftowever to the confirmation of the Government '/ of Bombay to which I am subordinate; the terms which I shall spe the c ify hereafter will be the same as those imposed on the Peninsular &amp; Oriental S.N. Company. 3. To avoid the possibility of mistake I shall recapitulate the concessions thus granted to your Company. I. Permission to occupy the entire bay, part of which is now in the possession of Messrs.Pastre &amp; Co. as a Coal Depot on the production of written authority from that firm abandoning their claim to it. II. Permission to construct a pier in front of the Coal Depot. 111. Permission to erect in the same place the buildings necessa ry for your establishment as well as a condenser if required. IV. Permission to lay down moorings in the harbour. V. Permission to construct a residence and office for your Agent to the West of the hotel. I specify this site, as there is no suitable position available on the hills around the harbour. 4. The conditions attached to these concessions are as follows;- 1. The ground to be occupied as a Coal Depot will not be granted to your Comneny in perpetuity but subject to resumption by Govern ment, should such a course be absolutely necessary for a public purpose . In which event fair and just compensation will beallowed for the buildings situated on it, the amount of which will be settled by Arbitration. This ground will not be transferable to any other party,without the consent of the political Resident,and a nominal assessment will be charged at the same rate as the quit rent levied on ground granted for the purpose of building (vide condition IV). II. No assessment will be charged on ground recovered from the sea • III. All buildings must be of stone and lime, with terraced tile or slate roofs. No erections of an inflammable nature will be allowed. IV. The ground required for building near- the hotel will be granted in perpetuity, subject however to resumption by Government in case of necessity, in which case compensation will be awarcted and another site granted. Buildings erected on it must be construc ted according to a prearranged plan, and a sketch of the proposed frontage must be submitted for the approval of the Resident,before the work is commenced. A quit rent to be fixed from time to time will be charged, the rate now in force is two per square yard per annum Rs.62-8-0 for 6000 square yards. 5. You solicit my opinion as to the advisability of erecting a condenser. I believe that when the reservoirs are once filled there will never be any scarcity of water in Aden at the very moderate rate of Rs.l/- per 100 gallons. The water produced by the Government con densers cost seven times that amount, but Government have authorised the issue of it to the public at the rate of three rupees per 100 gallons. 6. A sketch of the ground on which you propose to store your Coal will be prepared by the Executive Engineer and a copy supplied to your Agent and a grant of the ground at Steamer Point will be made out according to the attached form. I have etc.27 *# H0.211-P. &amp; L(3)/36. Government of Xnaia. department of Gommerce* r ! 2844 \ Hew Delhi, the 31st March, 1936* do o 4 5 TELEGRAM Prom The Secretary to the Government of India, Department of Commerce, The Chief Commissioner, Aden. Your memorandum Ho. 1864 dated 14th March. Provision of additional oil 'berths at Aden. Governor General in Council sanctions proposal made 'by Trustees. I 5 '/. 1 ^ ♦With 2 spare copies. H0.211-P.&amp; L(S)/36. Copy, with a copy of the letter replied to, forwarded, for information, to *ti) The Foreign and Political Department, (ii)The Accountant General, Bombay. By order, etc. , Sd/« G.Corley Smith, Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. (HOIK FOREiaN 8EO \ 3 2 M UtterBelow letter Mo,738 dated 12th M^rch 19^6, from the Chairman, Aden Port Trust,md enclosures. Subject;- Provision of two additional berths for accommodating vessels taking Oil Fuel at Aden# No, 1864# THE BSSID1MCY, Aden, 14 larch 1936# Forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Go Vermont of India, Department of Comnerce, New D Ini, for favour of sanctiiona s required by section 27(2) of the Aden port Trust Act, the cowers under which are reserved by the Govenior-Creneral in Council# I request that the sanction mny be communicated to me by tele : ;x\jp# Sd. Chief Coirrnissioner, .,g / / : 'I r / / /iM4*W* * * L ^ Jf J&gt; \ Gopy of a latter No.728 of 1926, dated 12th M^rch 1056, from the Chainmn, Port Trust, ndexi, to the Civil Secretary, Aden. Subject:- Provision of two additional berths for accommoda ting vessels taking oil fuel at Aden. At a Meeting of the Board held on the 24th August 1935 it ms decided to make provision in the Budget Estimates for 1936-37 for two Berths suitable for use as oil fueling berths. Tenders have been received, for the supply of t he necessary moorings and an Estimate amounting to Rs.1,47,657/- based t^oreon was passed by the Board vide copy of Resolu -• tion Ho .206, dated 12th Iforch 1936, enclosed herewith, pro vision for which exists in the Budget Estimates for the year 1926-37 patssed by the Trustees on the 24th February 1936. lith the progressive expansion of the supply of Oil Fuel a t this Port there has been a demand for an additional number of Oil Berths and bya re-arrungoment of the berthing accommodation at Nos.2 and 4 moorings, a 'Head out' as well as a 'Head in' oil berth can be installed in place of the » 3 xisting No. 4 ordinary berth. For two oil berths based on one central mooring, three breast buoys with moorings are required and it will there fore be necessary to purchase on© complete central mooring and buoy, and three complete breast moorings, each with buoy, and, typical 1st class moorings, as standardised at this Port, have been eatirruted for* The mooring at present in use at Ho.4 Berth, not being quite up to this standard, will bo taken into reserve and * used in due course for moorings at other berths. As the Estimate oxdeeds R3.5Q,Q00/-, the sanction of Government is required undex' Section 27 (2) ox the Aden Port Twust Act and I am to ask therefore that the Estimate may a - ——? i J , :/}■ . '/ -1 ii be forwarded to Government and that sanction iiuy be accord ed by telegram, if possible, in order that the most favourable tender may be accepted and the work taken in hand as early as possible. The very satisfactory financial position of the Port is in no wqy disturbed by this expenditure. /} i /Extract from the proceedings of a meeting of the Board of Trustees held on the 12th I&amp;.rch 1936* 206 considered Estimate amounting to Rs.1,47,657/- submitted by the Port Engineer for the provision of two oil berths in lieu of No.4 Berth* RESirLUTION:* That the Estimate amounting to He. 1,47,657/- be sanctioned, subject to the approval of government as required \ 2 nder Section 27(2) of the Men Port Trust Act* ,i' : . / u )!] .1 f ™ mm 11 -mmim ~ - Mm» —» .iiuhfM «No.C-556 THS iESIIEHGT, A13BN, 19 August 1935. From Lieut-Golone 1 M.G, Lake, Acting Chief Commissioner, Aden. The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and political Department, Simla . Subject:- Naval 011 _St or^9 _s ite_ .at-^AMP« With re IS re nee to your telegram N0.731N, dated 5th July 1935 addressed to the Secretary of State for India and repeated to me, I have the honour to forward herewith a copy of a Memorandum No. 7443, dated 9th August 1935, from the Chairman, Aden Settlement, and to request instructions as to the reply that I may give to the Executive Committee, I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- M.C. Laks, Acting Chief Commissioner. To Sir \ INDIA F REI3N SECRETARY'S | Letter il ^ 8 M. | Dated ' 2 6 8 E R 1935 ENCLOSURE iNGopy of memorandum No,7443, datiod the 9th. August 1935, from the Chairman, Aden Settlement, With reference to your No, G-447, dated 8th July 1935 and telegram No. 73IN, dated 5th July 1935, from the secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and political Department, Simla, the gxecutive Gommittee of the Aden Settlement have expressed their wish to he informed if the question of compensation for this land will he considered at some future date or whether they are to understand that no payment for this land will he made. jKg. I,£*7-3/34• i'rom The Deputy secretary to the aovexment of India In the foreign and political Department, To The Ohlef CoBiaiesiooB r, Aden. With reifexenoe to your letter No. 0.506, dated the 19th August 1965, I am directed to say that the Oow'rniaent of India, Foreign and political Department, tele graft Ste* 761-N, dated the bth July 19o 5, agreeing to the free transfer of the site, was issued, after the whole question had been fully examined in the li^ht of the remarks contained in the letter from the India Ofiioe No. P.Z.2782/55, dated the 27th May 1965, a copy of which was »©nt direct to Aden. 2. as a result of this re •examination, the Government of India cam® to the conclusion that the position taken up 5y the India Office was correct, and a» the sit© in question held 5y the Aden Settlement Was Crown land in charge of a municipal authority or local body, and therefore at the disposal of the Government of India, if required for imperial purposes, the Government of India agreed to its free transier. Dated Simla, the ^ September 1965. Subject!- Naval Oil Storage site at Aden. Sir,ay. * • • * *Ik the circuisstances, the question oi payment of ooHipensattoK does not arise, and 1 &amp;n to request that the Executive OQM&amp;i ttee of the Aden Se ttleisent icay he informed accordingly. 3* A copy or the recent letter on the subject Trom the Inala Office Bo* p.^5439/3fc f dabed the lath August 1935, Is enclosed ror your Inionaatlon. I have the honour to be, &amp;ir f Tour jsost obedient servant, 3d/- 0. K* 0AH)B, Deputy Secretary to the Gover^ent of India#INDEXED S-ONFIDENTTAI,. # V'' i f \ &gt; \ ! * '&lt; * vV iM No. F.297-N/34. 1935 From To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London. Dated Simla, the / ~ August 1935. •rt ■Jj.U . estion of improvement of the existing 'acilities for oiling at the Port of Aden. -x-x-x- fa Sir, With reference to your letter No. P.Z.4244/35, dated the 28th June 1935, I am directed to forward for information and communication to the Admiralty, a copy of a letter from the Chief Commissioner, Aden No. C.494, dated the 20th July 1935, together with a copy of its enclosure. I have the honour to he. Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. ^ ■ Copy to the Chief Commissioner, Aden, for information. [I ^Copy of a letter No. C-494, dated Aden, 20th July 1935, from the Acting Chief Commissioner, Aden, to the Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. I have the honour to refer to the India Office letter No. P.Z.4244/35 dated 28th June 1935 regarding a scheme for the improvement of the existing facilities for oiling at the port of Aden, and to enclose for communication to the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a Memorandum dated the 16th July 1935 from the Chairman, Aden Port Trust, on the subject.CONFIDENTIAL. Copy of a memorandum dated Aden, 16th July 1935, from the Chairman, Aden Port Trust, to the Civil Secretary, Aden. With reference to copies of correspondence forwarded under your endorsement No.C-455 dated 12th July 1935, I am to say that no scheme for the provision of an additional 'al tide' berth for oil bunkering to the westward of the existing oil berths is at present under consideration by the Trustees of the Port. In pursuance of the progressive policy adopted by the Port, the possibility of the need for expansion in that direction at some future date has, however, not been lost sight of and the undersigned has given some thought to what would be the most suitable existing berth to which oiling facilities could be extended if the demand arose but the matter has not progressed further than that as no request for additional berths has been received from the Anglo-Persian Oil Co. Ltd. who provide at their own expense the actual installations from the storage tanks ashore to the berths. In the absence of any demand from the Oil Company for further facilities, despite the fact that 6434,000 tons of Oil were supplied to Shipping last financial year without delay to any vessel, it is not considered that the equipment of the Port in this respect can be described as 'restricted'. The interest taken by the Admiralty in the matter and their projected programme for the construction of a large number of additional storage tanks at Aden opens up another aspect of the question however.II A If it is the intention of the Admiralty to make a correspondingly greater use of the Port, it would appear that congestion and delay will almost certainly occur unless the number of berths is increased and it cannot be expected, in equity, that the Trustees should bear the expense of providing extra berths, the need for which is caused by the increase in Naval requirements alone, without being recompensed by the Admiralty for their outlay. The provision of more berths might even necessitate further dredging in addition to the cost of moorings. I shall consequently be grateful if you will kindly bring this to the notice of the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty.It is requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S.TF. 1. .5439/35. 12th August, 1935. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary o£ State to refer to your telegram oi 5th July, ho. 731 M, regarding the grant ox land situated outside the old cantonment area at Aden to the Admiralty for the construction of Oil Fuel Storage Tanks, and to forward, lor the information of the Govern m ent of India, copy of a letter dated 7th August from the Admiralt, conveying the thanks of the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to the Government of India for their action in this matter. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, iSgci.) M. J. CLAUSGN The Sen etary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department.L.P.—No. 8 nst 19 $3 . Sir ■ ' .•• With reference to your letter of 9th July 1935, P.Z.4628/35, concerning the proposed construction of Oil Fuel Storage Tanks at Aden, I am commanded hy My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to request that the Secretary of State for India will he so good as to express to the Government of India Their Lordships* appreciation of their action in agreeing that the site on Metal la Plain shall he handed over free of cost. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant^ Political Department India Office, S.W.l. L 8AUG19 xi PPliPMBBBSw w r Y 1 &gt;U £ 3601, IT/DIA (28 wowis) • From Goverament of India, Foreign &amp; Political &amp;igpa.rtm®nt, to (COPIES Secretary ox“state for India* Cl EMULATED) Dated Simla 0 Btd July s 1935 c 13IN 9 Mdressed to Sec retary of State for India and repeated to Chief Commissioner, Men, Continuation of our telegram dated June 20th, 670N» Government of India have now decided that land situated outside old cantonment area at Men required by Admiralty Received 5th July, 1935 may be given over to them free of cost^ -t,— - —indexed The Secretary of the Admiralty, Any further communication, should be addressed to— , ,s - i. / 5 &gt; June /.9j5. !»0 0 J London, S.W.l quoting QEinQ.. 0114/35/74a* Sir {mg. With reference to the proposal to extend the Admiralty Oil Fuel Storage Installation at Aden, which proposal has 'been the subject of recent correspondence (India Office communication dated 1st April 1935, P.Z.2192/35 and Admiralty letter C.E.in 0.069/35/1513, dated 18th April 1935) I am commanded 'by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that They learn that the Aden Port Trust have under consideration a scheme for providing an additional 'all-tide ’ 1 berth west- v/ard of the existing oiling berths, having in mind the restricted facilities for oiling at present available at the Port. 2. My Lords anticipate that the completion of the proposed additional storage will involve an increased turnover of oil; They are therefore interested to learn that an increase in the oiling facilities is contemplated The Under Secretary of State for India India Office, / CUIU.# iNCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER I No . 9 6 2 7JUN1»35 /and. •OP MAU* £ 3S 'A lOJUN 1935.- 2 - ana would be glad to be made acquainted with the progress of any scheme that may be decided upon. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant ,? —-—- —6 6/ 3 &lt;r Department. 22 m 1935 ^ith reference to your letter of appointment of Mr. J.P. Lumley for duty at Aden as Officer in Charge of Naval Works, I am directed by the S. of S. 1^. &lt; nA / for I. to enclose ,copy of a telegram of 19th June addressed to the G. of I. and repeated to the Chief Commissioner, Aden, together with a copy of the G. of I.'s reply of 20th June. 18th June, No. , regarding the (84.) J. C. WALTON,CWP/DIA W03? B E C 0 D E o. g TELES ' + ' From CGOFIES CIRCULATED) Bated Received Government of India.,. Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India. Simla, 20Ui June, 1935. 20th June s 1935 , 2-45 pcixu 61QN e Your telegram dated. 19th June, 1S1 O c . Naval oil storage site, Mem We have already instructed Chief Commissioner, Aden, to hand over site when required by the Admiralty without prejudice to the question ©f cost, which is being considered here, and a further communication from us {'? omission) Chief Commissioner being asked to afford usual facilities for Lumley to carry out his dutiesc Mdfessed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to AdenDRAFT TELEGRAM. P .x. SECRETARY' OE STATE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN AN] POLITICAL DEPARTMENT.' (Retamilla) ^ ' JsJJ- X ^ Repeated to Aden &amp; My telegram 25th May, No. 1624. Naval oil storage site, Aden. / s s ^ ^ Mr. J.P. Lumley, civil engineer, has been appointed by Admiralty for duty at Aden as officer in charge of naval works, and leaves England 29th June, arriving Aden about 20th July. Will you please confirm as soon as possible by telegraph that site will be ^ ^ handed over and that the usual facilities will be given to Lumley to ^ enable him to carry out his duties. tnp : %&amp;■ (r . ta i W539tl ioSTT ^ m ] : jgl '9£^ATCii£d^ 174‘t 1000 3.33p. 7 4215 Any further commujiication should be addressed to— ^ The Secretary of the Admifalty, liondoi, S.W.l I .. ' ons/ss/esA - - 7 s- / / ®.. -L.P.—No. 8 Admiralty, S.W.l. June /. With reference to your letter dated 23th May 1935, P.Z.2732/35 on the subject Additional Naval Oil Storage at Aden, I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to state for the information of the Secretary of State for India that Their Lordships have appointed Mr. J.P.Lumley, A.M,Inst.C.E., Civil Engineer, for duty at Aden as Officer in Charge of Naval Works. He will leave England on 29th June arriving at Aden about 20th July and I am to request that you will be good enough to cause the usual facilities to be extended to enable him to carry out his duties. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, S'ENT LY Atrt MAIL m 'll- ^Please pass quickly. Mr. CLEARY. Mr. CROMBIE. Mr. RUMBOLD. Mr. LAITHWAITE. Mr. WALTON. Mr. POPE.Minute Paper f.z. zirz/, De- epartment i. Please see the Admiralty letter of 27th November last at P.Z.7307/34 regarding the desire of the Admiralty to take over certain land at Aden belonging to the Settlement authorities in connexion with the enlargement of the Naval Oil Fuel Installation at Aden. In paragraph 2 of that letter tke Admiralty refer to the general obligation undertaken by the Government of India in 1928 to provide land free of cost to the Defence Departments of H.M.G. at Aden. In his express letter of 19th January 1935 at P.Z.2037/35 to the Government of India the Resident at Aden argues that the Government of India’s undertaking extends only to providing land for the Air Ministry and the War Office and not for the Admiralty, but the Government of India in their reply of 9th March to the Resident (also at P.Z.2037/35) accept their obligation as extending to the Admiralty as well as to the other two defence departments. They contend however that their undertaking was limited to land situated within the old Cantonments area at Aden and, since it has now been confirmed that the land required by the Admiralty is outside this area, they state in their telegram of 27th March at P.Z.2192/35 that they cannot agree to the supply of the land free of cost. The Admiralty have now sent us a letter (P.Z.2782/35) contesting the Government of India’s view and pointing out that neither the Viceroy’s telegram of 28th March 1928 accepting the obligation in question nor our letter of 25th April 1928 forwarding that telegram to the War Office mentions* any such limitation as that referred to by the Government of India. 2956 6000 7 34 The relevant papers in the 1927-30 correspondence which/which was occasioned hy the proposal made in 1627 to absorb the old Cantonments area into the Aden Settlement^ will be found in the attached volume flagged from M A' to The War Office letter of 8 th December, 1927 (Flag A) describes the obligation, which it was suggested that the Government of India might accept, as “a general obligation similar to that devolving on Colonial Governments vis-sl- vis the War Department'. The Viceroy's telegram of 28th March 1928 (Flag B) says that the Government of India 'accept general obligation similar to that devolving on Colonial Governments'; while our letter of 25th April 1928 to the War Office also refers to a 'general obligation similar to that devolving on Colonial Governments vis-a.-vis the Defence Departments of His Majesty's Government'. The later correspondence! (flagged ”D H to M F M ) refers only to two Defence Departments (i.e. the Air Ministry and the War Office) as benefiting by the Government of India's undertaking but it is quite clear from the earlier correspondence that the Admiralty were also intended to be included, j and indeed the Government of India themselves agree that this is the case. There is no suggestion anywhere | in the correspondence that the undertaking to provide land free of cost was intended, as the Government of India now suggest, to be limited to land in the old Cantonments area. Indeed, since under the Cabinet decision of 192? the Government of India were bound to surrender outright to the Defence Departments the land and buildings in the Cantonments Area, it would have been a poor bargain for the latter to have allowed the Government of India to retain the reversionary rights to that property in return merely for an undertaxingMinute Paper. Department. to provide free of charge land required at any future date in the same area (i.e. land which had reverted to the Settlement authorities as surplus to military or naval requirements but was again required by the Defence Departments). It might have paid the Defence Departments better to sell or lease any land in the Cantonments Area which at any time became surplus to their immediate needs. 3. One other point may be mentioned. The latter part of para.4 of the War Office letter at Flag A might perhaps, read by itself, give the impression that the obligation resting on Colonial Governments was merely to provide free of cost to the Defence Departments an equivalent for lands and buildings already surrendered by the Defence Departments to the Colony and that anything in excess of this equivalent might be charged for. This, however, is not the case and the wider obligation mentioned in the first sentence of para.4 of the War Office letter is not affected by what follows in the rest of the paragraph. This is clear from para.11 of the Colonial Office despatch of 30th December 1894 from which the War Office quote and a copy of which is attached below. The point is mentioned here merely for the sake of completeness and in case of possible misunderstanding since the Government of India have not themselves raised it. 4. In the light of the above we should, I think, be justified in supporting the contention of the Admiralty that the obligation accepted by the Government of India in 1928 to provide land at Aden free of cost for defence purposes was a general obligation and not limited to land situated in the old Cantonments area. A/Draft Paper P.Z.2782/35 POLITICAL Department. DRAFT LETTER. AIR MAIL. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, F.&amp; P.Department, SIMLA. Copy £0 MM 1936 Aden / Admiralty® &amp; MAY J936 2 7 MAY 1935 Sir, 3436a 5000 1.35 I am directed hy the S/S for I. to CE in C refer to Admiralty letter Lo.^ 6 ^^ 35 ' /Y5b of 18th April, 1935, (a copy of which was forwarded to the G.of I. hy the air mail of 26th April, 1935, under Do.P.Z.2782/35) and to the previous correspondence ending with the G.of I's telegram Ro.28-0R of 27th March, 1935, on the subject of the site required hy the Admiralty at Aden for the construction of additional oil fuel storage tanks. It will he observed from the Admiralty letter under reference that the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty were unaware that the general obligation accepted by the G.of I. in 1928 to provide land at Aden free of cost for defence purposes was limited to lands situated in the old Cantonments area and that they have pointed out that no such limitation is expressed in the correspondence of which copies were sent to the Admiralty at that time. 2. After careful examination of the correspondence which passed between 1927 and 1930 on the subject of the absorption of the old Cantonments area into the Settlement of Aden, and in particular H.E. the Viceroy's telegram D 0 . 68 OS of 28th March 1928 in which the G.of I. accepted a 'general obligation similar/similar to that devolving on Colonial Governments” in thisrespect, Sir Samuel Hoare finds it difficult to support the G.of I's contention that the obligation then accepted by them is limited to lands in the old Cantonments area in the absence of any expressed reservation to this effect. It is in fact doubtful^ if such a reservation had indeed been made at that time, whether the War Office would have agreed to the retention by the G.of 1. of reversionary rights to the lands and buildings in the Cantonments area which had been transferred to the Y/ar Department by the Cabinet decision of 1927, since it might well have been more profitable to them to seller lease j any lands or buildings which might happen to be surplus to their immediate requirements. The S/S, as at present advised, is therefore disposed to agree with the views expressed in the Admiralty letter of 18th April, but he would be glad to receive in due course any further observations which the G.of I. may have to make. 3. The G.of I. will no doubt bear in mind the further consideration that it is proposed to transfer to H.M.G. in the near future the control of the civil administration of the Settlement of Aden under the new constitutional reforms, when the position in regard to the provision of land at Aden for defence j purposes will presumably be definitely assimilated/Department. assimilated to the existing position in other colonial territories. In view of the impending transfer of Aden it seems in any case doubtful whether a claim for compensation for the land in question should be pressed. 4* Meanwhile it will be seen that the Admiralty are anxious to commence the construction of the new tanks at an early date and I—am -h- i-rrri Pm ^ tn X L&lt; CAuxL sp ‘2S'^4y a? , that,—ir..4;hQ r 1 T— rn. m nrs n-K arrangements may now be made without delay, as requested by the Admiralty, to hand over the site to the Haval authorities when required^without prejudice to the final settlement of the question of the terms on which the transfer is to be made. 5. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Chief Commissioner at Aden. (34.) J. C. WALTON.COLONIAL OFFICE, DOWNING STREET, 30th December 1894* Sir, From correspondence which has taken place respecting colonial military lands and buildings - that is to say, lands the fee simple of which is vested in the Crown, represented by the colonial government, but of which the War Department has a right of perpetual user for purposes of defence, and the buildings on such lands, in certain colonies - since my predecessor's circular despatch of the 9th June, 1890, it appears that the exact meaning of the proposals enclosed in the circular as to the mode of dealing with such lands, when no longer required for military purposes, has not been clearly understood, 2, Her Majesty's Government have carefully reconsidered the question and have decided to adhere to the proposals adopted by their predecessors, and communicated to the colonial governments in Lord Khutsford's circular despatch, and with the view of removing any misunderstanding they have thought it desirable to formulate their proposals in the following terms, viz:- ''The free surrender to the colony of all colonial military lands and buildings no longer required by Her Majesty's Government on the engagement by the colony that, in the event of lands and buildings being required then or in the future for the defence of the colony, the colony shall provide an equivalent for the lands and buildings so surrendered towards the satisfaction of the above-mentioned requirements, and to that intent the value of the lands and buildings surrendered shall be ascertained and recorded, and any lands and buildings provided out of that value shall be held by Her Majesty's Government on the same tenure as those/2 those surrendered. n 3* This proposal is based upon the assumption that the colonial military lands in question constitute a permanent defence fund of the colony, the integrity of which ought to be preserved, in kind or value, even though the original lands themselves may be diverted to civil purposes* Accordingly, whenever such lands which have been set apart for defense purposes have, from change of circumstances, or from an altered scheme of defence, or from any other reason, ceased to answer the purposes for v/hich they were set apart, and are in consequence surrendered by the military authorities their value should be treated as forming a capital applicable either immediately, or from time to time, so far as it will extend, to providing other lands or buildings which may be required in the colony for such purposes* U. Effect would be given to the above proposal in the following manner If the colonial government should not desire to retain the lands and buildings to be surrendered, they will be sold in the open market, and the proceeds paid into the colonial treasury, when the amount would be entered in a special account to the debit of the colonial government* In the event of any new lands or buildings being immediately required for the defensive purposes of the colony, the amount of the above-mentioned proceeds, or a sufficient portion of them, would be paid out as required for the purchase of the new sites, and for the construction of the new buildings; the amounts so paid out being entered in the special account to the credit of the colonial government. should the new sites, instead of being purchased from private owners, be located on Crown lands in the possession of the colonial government, the necessary lands would be given over to the military authorities, and credit taken in the special accounts for the market/3 market value of the fee simple of the Crown lands so given over. Should new lands or buildings not be immediately required for defensive purposes, the above-mentioned proceeds would stand in the special account to the debit of the colonial government to be paid out in the same way, in the event of funds being ever required in the future for providing lands or buildings for defensive purposes. 6 . Whenever the colony desires to retain any lands which the military authorites give up, such lands, instead of being offered for sale, would be valued, and the market value of their fee simple at date of surrender would be entered in the special account to debit of the colonial government, together with the fair selling value at that date of any buildings which might be upon that land. In the event of the surrender of any buildings now existing, which in the past were erected at colonial cost, it would only be necessary to record the value of the site. The amounts so entered would be paid out as required for the provision of the lands or buildings for the defensive purposes of the colony, and the amounts, as in the case of sale, credited to the colonial government, the like credit being given in the event of new sites being provided on Crown lands. Should no new lands or buildings be immediately required the amounts entered would remain to the debit of the colonial government until such time, if ever, as lands or buildings should become necessary for defensive purposes. 7. Valuation of lands or buildings, when required under the circumstances above mentioned, should be made by the colonial and military authorities conjointly, or in the event of their disagreeing, by an independent and competent iSurveyor, to be chosen by agreement between the home and colonial/4 . colonial governments, whose report should he final. The cost of employing such surveyor would he home by the colonial government, hut should he placed to its credit in the special account. 8 * Any lands and buildings provided hereafter for defensive purposes under this arrangement, including land required for rifle ranges or other purposes conducing to the efficiency of the garrison, would be occupied by the military upon a right of perpetual user only, the fee simple of the land remaining in the Crown represented by the colonial government. In the event of any such lands being at any time surrendered by the military authorities they would be dealt with in the manner above detailed. 9« Before any buildings are commenced, the cost of which will be chargeable to the special account, the govermr will be informed of the nature and estimated cost of the proposed buildings in order that any observations that he may wish to offer upon them may be duly considered by Her Majesty^ Government. 10 . It is not proposed to re-open any transactions already closed, and lands which have already passed out of military occupation will remain the property of the colony, subject of course to any conditions which may have been attached to them at the time when they came into the possession of the colonial government. 11. The foregoing proposal relates solely to the terms on which colonial military lands, in the hands of the War Department, should be surrendered to a colonial government. It does not affect the obligation of a colony to provide other lands required within its borders for military purposes, whether under some special agreement or under the general obligation that rests on every colony to contribute according to its means towards its own defence. Whatever the/\ the circumstances of a colony may he, it is obviously within its means to maintain its colonial military lands intact, in money or kind, for defensive purposes. 12 . I request that you will lay this despatch before the Legislative Council and House of Assembly, and convey to them my earnest hope that the proposals of Her Majesty’s Government will be accepted as a fair and equitable solution to the advantage alike of the Mother Coin try and of the colony, of a question which has in some colonies been the subject of considerable and prolonged controversy. RIPONAny further communication should be addressed to— CONFIDENTIAL, (6^) L.P.—No. 8 Admiralty, S. W. 1. O l Q ' ■' ) X / April I**- The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.W.l quoting CEinC* 069/3 57i 5b, I | ; Sir, X 4 j 9 ^ r, | f With reference to- your* letter dated 26th March 1965, P,Z.2037/35, enclosing copy of correspondence between the Government of India and the Chief Commissioner, Aden, on the subject of the site required by the Admiralty at Aden for the construction of additional Oil Fuel Storage tanks, I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that ihey note with satisfaction the confirmation by the Government of India that their undertaking to provide free of charge lands required by the War Department and Air Ministry extends also to the Admiralty. My Lords regret to learn, however, that so far as Aden is concerned, this undertaking is limited to lands situated within the old Cantonment Area, which in 1929 was absorbed in the Aden Settlement, and They desire me to point out that no such limitation is expressed in the correspondence of which copies have been received in the The^Under Secretary of State, /Admiralty Political Department, India Office, S.W.l. A COPY SENT BY AJR MLAii. of ™ niiM mm Admiralty. Indeed, the wording of the telegram dated 28th March 1928 from His Excellency the Viceroy of India is that his G-overnment would n accept the general obligation similar ’’to that devolving on Colonial (Governments”, in regard to which My Lords know of no such similar limitation; nor did India Office letter to the War Office dated 25th April 1928 imply that any limitation was in mind. 2. In general terms, the arrangements which are in force with Colonial (Governments in regard to Admiralty require ments of land are that the Colony will provide free of charge any unoccupied Crown land required on which the Colony has incurred no expenditure for acquisition, improvement, etc. that if money has been so spent the Admiralty will compensate the Colony for their outlay. Only in certain cases in which private land has had to be acquired by a Colony for Admiralty purposes have the Admiralty been called upon to meet the cost of acquisition. 3. With these arrangements as a guide it seems to My Lords that the Government of India should have no difficulty in accepting the contention in the final paragraph of Admiralty letter to the Ihdia Office of 27th November 1934, that the site on Maala Plain, which is unoccupied and undeveloped should be transferred to the Admiralty without charge, and I shall be glad if you will be good • • • •good enough to communicate to that Government the sense of the foregoing remarks. 4. My Lords expect to he in a position to commence the construction of the new tanks at an early date, and are anxious that there shall he no delay in obtaining possession of the site. I am accordingly to suggest that the Government of India he asked to make arrangements for the site to he handed over when required, leaving the question as to the terms of the transfer to he dealt with subsequently. I am. Sir Your obedient Servant. 2192 0. 1774. (COPIES CIRCULATED) I_P F T g L 1 0 R * M. From Secretary Dated Delhi, 27th March, 193S. Received 5p.m., 27th March, 1935 ,31 1 f3 )0&lt;/ c&lt;UJ»t ■SSdffls. Continuation of our telegram dated 13th ^rch^651| Naval oil atorage site, Aden. Chief Commissioner having confirmed that the site is „ outside the old cantonment area, to which alone 1929 undertaking applies, Government of India cannot agree to the supply of land to a Defence Department free of cost, and support suggestion for compensation at the rate stated in Ms telegram of 19th January, 43, see papers sent by air mail of 15th March, 42(&gt; £) Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated Aden*VNDE-* tD zu “''y / Telegram Ho.43, dated 19th ^r^Qj d^Ot^T _J affiar 7 1935. ^ vA^' Prom ...... Chief Commissioner, Aden. To ........ Foreign, Hew Delhi. EXPRESS. Your express letter dated 4th January, ib.297-H/34-, Site proposed for new Admiralty oil tanks is suitable and I consider that Executive Committee, &amp;den Settlement, in whom this land is vested and who have not yet been consulted, should agree to lease it to Admiralty for this Imperial purpose. As regards price of this land, it (unlike that of Haval Wireless Station which is on Isthmus between Aden proper and Sheikh Othman) is situated on Haala plain which is only remaining open space in Aden peninsula^ available for building expansion. Price of land in this area to ordinary purchaser varies at present from minimum 2s. 2/8 a square yeard to maximum 2s. 5 a square yeard for 99 years lease and these rates will doubtless be enhanced if long contemplated plan for extension of Aden harbour in this direction with wharves on Maala foreshore ever materialises. In 1921 Railway Department of the Government of India paid Aden Settlement 2s. 5 and 2s. 2/8 a square y^ard for two sites on Haala plain. In 1924 site for existing Naval oil tanks in this area was leased by Settlement to Admiralty in perpetuity at concession rates a&gt;f Re. i/4 a square yard (that is half of ordinary minimum rate) I consider that compensation at latter rate should fairly be paid to Aden Settlement for loss of site now required by Admiralty which though at present undeveloped, has considerable prospective building value. Obligation of Government of India to/land free to which Admiralty refers, appears from Government of India(and-ar® not W)Army Department letter dated 1st July 1929 No. 1671-AD4 to Government of Bombay to apply to land * required lS/3raquired^by -Air Ministry and War Office for defence purposes* As far as I Isnow, this obligation does not extend to Admiralty and the purpose for which site is now required, is not local defence* On tne contrary, existence of large fiaval tank storage might increase the liabilities of Aden to attack* Unless, therefore, obligation of the Government of India has wider application than correspondence available here indicate, and unless Aden Settlement is bound by such obligation, I recommend that the latter should receive payment for this site at the rates I have suggested, or at such other rates as Government of India consider reasonable in the circumstances or alternatively, that Admiralty should pay Aden Settlement an annual rental based on of purchase price.Government of India 5breign and Political Department* SSCPRaSS LETTER* From ib reign, Mew Delhi. 3b The Chief Commissioner, Aden. Ho. r.89?-V3^ Bated March 193 5 * Tour telegram dated the 19th January, 43. 2. From papers here it ie clear that correspondence leading up to issue of Army Department letter Ho. 1671-A.D.4, dated the 1st July 1929, accepting obligation to provide land free to ^ar office or Air Ministry, was conducted with Admiralty as well, and omission to specify Admiralty in that letter was accidental. In any case. Government of India feel that diecriminatory treatment of Admiralty in this matter could not be justified* 5. Government of India also consider that the natural impliestior of an under taking to give land free for defence purposes would be that it extends to any of the three defence Departments for any purpose which would facilitate their operations, and they are therefore of opinion that it could hardly be seriously argued that provision of oil tanks to enable the Mavy to operate from Aden isa purpose unconnected with either Imperial or local defence, 4, But it would appear that the present case will fall for decision on other grounds. The land required on the Maala plain is presumably outside the area of the old Aden Cantonment (as absorbed in the Settlement in 1929}» to which alone the considerations advanced in paragraphs 2 and 3 above can be held to apply* There is therefore no obligation on the part of the Government of India to provide this land free of cost to the Admiralty or to any other Defence Department* Subject to your confirmation of the assumption that the Maala plain is situated outside the old Aden Cantonment area f the suggestion made in the concluding portion of your telegram will be referred to the India Office. The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd. O.K.Caroe&gt; Deputy Secretary to the Government of India,.wV. XXX ^— ''T'l ■ -T- £51. Addi'essed to Secretary of Stalje for India and repeated to Men. Your telegim of 11th instant, 791. Naval oil storage at Men. We addressed Men 9th March and are sending you correspondence by air Bail of 16th instant.Government of India, foreign and Political Department. EXPRESS LETTER . - 8 FEB 1935 From Foreign, New Delhi, To Chief Commissioner, Aaen. No. F.297-N/34. Dated ^ January 193 5 , Reference correspondence ending with Government of India Foreign and i olitical Department endorsement NO.F.297-N/34, dated the 24th Au^st 1934. Please see India Office Express letter (Air Mail) No. I * :j. 7307/34, dated the 7th December 1934, copy of which enclosed and telegraph if there is any objection to Admiralty proposal. o* The map which is sent in original, should be returned. The issue of the above has been authorised. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S Letter DulOcI Received .Mo. I 935 M. 28 JAM. 1935 Sd/- O.K.Caroe, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.Any further communicatio should be addressed to— i L.P.—No. 8. The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.W j 7834,1 quoting “ .CE.ill.G..«.] 0150/54/4 60.. &gt; ^ ^ z r Admiralty, S.W.1. : D.e.Q.e.inbe.r., 193 4. Sir, I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a letter that has been addressed to the Air Ministry, asking that Department to carry out a survey of the proposed site for additional Naval Oil Fuel Storage at Aden, referred to in Admiralty letter dated 27th November 1934, CEinC.0145/34/42B to the Under Secretary of State. 2* My Lords will be glad if the necessary facilities may be afforded the Air Ministry. I am, Sir , Your obedient Servant,,C0PY CEinC. 0150/34/45a. f CONFIDENTIAL. | 1 * e j j December ,1934. Sir, { 1954 J I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to refer to your letter No.S.32967/S.6 of the 23rd February 1934, and to Admiralty letter CEinC.1029/34/21c of the 18th June 1934, in reply, concerning the proposed extension of the Admiralty Oil Fuel Depot, Maala Plain, Aden, and to acquaint you, for the information of the Air Council, that They are advised that the area most suitable for the purpose is that indicated on print No.859/34, three copies^of which are forwarded herewith, showing in red the area to be surveyed, and, in blue, the area on which contours at five feet intervals are required. My Lords understand that the area in question is vested in the Aden Settlement Authority by the Government of India. My Lords would be glad if the survey of the site could be made as soon as convenient to the Air Council, as a charge to Navy Vote 10. They desire that the survey should show the boundaries of the existing Oil Fuel Installation; Protestant and Mohammedan Cemeteries, Isolation Hospital, any reserved area for development, and any roads or water courses in existence. The survey should extend as far South and West as the 50 ft. contour line. The levels of oil pipes and floor level in pumping station are also required. My Lords would be pleased to be supplied with any information likely to be helpful in the preparation of contract particulars, such as the nature of soil and sub-soil and depths, rock and masonry for roads, foundations of tanks and 'bunds etc., water supply for domestic and boiler purposes, and whether electric light and power are available. Two copies of Chart No.3660, Aden Harbour are forwarded herewith as requested. he Secretary, Air Ministry, Adastral House, Kingsway, W.C.2. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, SSIgnecf) V W. BADDELEV&amp; &amp;6..C. £ 3)64 5000 10.34 7 DEG 1954 Prom Secretary of state To Government of India, Foreign &amp; political Dept. Your express letter dated 24tii August, P.E97-N/34, and connected correspondence. Investigation of sites at Aden in connection with enlargement of Naval Oil Fuel Storage there, please see letter from Admiralty dated &amp;7th November, No. CEinG . sent herewith. I should he glad of early report on points raised by Admiralty. J. G. laithwaite.L.P.— Any further communication should be addressed to— PON^^D^NTT t Ij AdlTllTCllty^ S. Wd . The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.W.l quoting “ C ElnC • ” 0/45 /34/42'b. .P.—-Wo. 8 « With reference to Admiralty Letter, ^EinG. _l(j 29/34/89a, dated 8th September 1934, relating to Naval Oil Fuel Storage at Maala Plain, Aden, I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, the enclosed Chart No.3660, Aden Harbour, on which is approximately indicated by red hatching an area on Maala Plain adjacent to the existing Naval Oil Fuel Installation (shewn in blue). That area has been inspected and subject to professional survey, appears to be suitable for the erection of the additional tankage in contemplation; it extends to about fifty (50) acres and is the minimum required for the purpose in view. As, however, it is possible that a detailed survey may disclose that surface contours at the southernmost portion of the site would render tank construction difficult or impracticable at that point, an additional The Under Secretary of State, /area India Office, S.W.l.area has been indicated on the plan as an alternative to that portion. 2. The site of the existing Naval Oil Fuel Installation was acquired by the Admiralty from the Aden Settlement in 1922-34 by purchase. At a recent interview between the Admiralty 1 s Civil Engineer and the Chairman of the Aden Settlement, the latter Indicated that the land now proposed to be taken over was the property of the Settlement, and proposed that the area required should be purchased by the Admiralty. It appears that in making this proposal the Chairman of the Aden Settlement was unaware of the under taking given by the Government of India in 1928, whereby that Government accepted a general obligation similar to that devolving on Colonial Governments vis-a-vis the Defence Departments of His Majesty’s Government, to provide free of cost land required for purposes such as that now under consideration. The undertaking is referred to in War Office letter to the India Office dated 8th December 1927, (1 9/Abr o ad/ l.- (D.L.l.a)), and in Hr. Wakeley ’ s reply of • ■ th April 19 8, (P.1516), and in telegraphic correspondence — . * from His Excellency the Viceroy of India to the India Office l ? dated 22nd September 1927 and 28th March 1928, of which documents My Lords have received copies from the War /Department...Department and the India Office. In consequence, My Lords presume that They will not be called upon to purchase the proposed site, which is et present undeveloped, and while They are not yet in s position to proceed actively with the scheme, They will be glad to learn that the Government of India would be prepared to place the site at Admiralty disposal free or on nominal terms. It would of course be understood that as in the case of the Admiralty's tenure from the Government of India of the sites of their Wireless Telegraph and femote Control Stations at Aden, which were transferred in perpetuity free of charge, the reversionary rights in the land would remain with that Government. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, ’AM’ uL&lt;L. Enel : Chart ITo. 3660, Aden Harbour# i , - J1 ^ i I k , With reference to Admiralty letter of the 18th hep 1834 ^*7; Jiiie 1934, GEinG^ 1029/34/21d, concerning the proposal to { —-T ']4^ t^-.i 2 |crease the Naval Oil Fuel Storage at Aden, I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that Mr.T.F.Allen, A.M.I.C.E., Civil Engineer in charge of Admiralty Works, Ceylon, is proceeding to Aden in s.s. ’’Cathay”, leaving Colombo on the 12th September 1934, and arriving at Aden 18th K : September, approximately. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, Ur&amp;ZJ SGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Foreign &amp; Political Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). v ' 5727 1934 I — - This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL vjhich provides a means of communication more expeditions than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended tt&gt; be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department^ No. F.297-N/34. Dated Simla the Q KU* AUgUSt Z,934. To His Majesty T s Under Secretary of State for India,! ' r # LON D ON. Keference^ letter, from the Military Department, India Office, No. M.3899/34, dated the 21st June 1934. Please intimate direct to Aden approximate date when Allen expects to visit Aden in connection with investi gation of possible sites for enlargement of naval oil fuel storage there. Issue of the above has been authorised. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India ki Copy to Aden for information with reference to his Express Letter No.5055, dated the 11th August 1934. (Signature) S. 44. DCTP— 1124S&amp;P~(M-1314) —4&gt;8-32—J2,000. (Designation)From No* F.297-N/34. » ~r r Xhe Chief Gomiissloner, Aden. Af. 5^3 Simla, the July 1934. Proposed investigation of possible sites for enlargement of naval oil fuel storage at Aden. Sir, I am directed to refer to the letter from the India Office No. 369 9/ 34, dated the 21st June 1934, copy of ufoich was sent direct to Aden, ana to say that the Government of India would be glad if necessary facilities could be afforded to Mr. Allen for his investigations at Aden. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Sd. 0. K. Caroe, ^Deputy secretary to the Government of India ! Lottnr N 0 \f2; I-2053 5000 7.33 ■H DRAIT LETTER to— Put away after issue Return to Mr. Copy for Reminder on Special Instructions to Registry -1 Examined in Registry In the case of letters to India, a short subject should be given. Subject: Military Dept. (Form 10). No. of copies- 4c&lt; Ghf (I* A d_ o 4 / iU. India Office, Iif reply -4o—your letter of the? I am directed to Mrlorm—you thatr a ff h J) *. Mtu. iki* iyju ^ * ^ u ' nL ’ Of ymconfidential, Any further communication should be addressed to— The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.W.l quoting “__.GEtoC_*. 1029/34/21d, Admiralty, S, W.1 ,d 1 1 1 * June 3 3 9 9 | ;So4 j Sir, I am commanded Dy My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that My Lords have under consideration a proposal to increase the Naval Oil Fuel Storage at Aden on a site contiguous to, or in the near neighbourhood of, the existing installation on Maala Plain. They have accordingly issued instructions for the Civil Engineer in charge of Admiralty Works, Ceylon, • A11 en, A.M. I. C.E., to proceed to Aden to make a pieliminary investigaoicn of likely sites and to report to the Resident on arrival. My Lords will be glad if the Secretary of State will be good enough to arrange for all necessary facilities for his inspection to be accorded to Mr.Allen. he Under Secretary of State, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00001a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1491</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00001a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1491</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 1/53 'Aden. Enlargement of naval oil fuel storage'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-26T14:34:50</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (92 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 92; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains papers regarding the proposed expansion of the Admiralty fuel depot on the Maalla plain [Al Ma'alla] near Aden harbour. The file mainly consists of correspondence between the Admiralty, the India Office Political Department, the Aden Chief Commissioner, the Aden Port Trust, and the Government of India Foreign Department.The topics discussed include: possible sites for the enlargement, with reference made to Admiralty Chart No. 3660; the appointment of a Civil Engineer to conduct a site survey; the possibility of the Admiralty acquiring the land free of charge, under the terms of a 1928 agreement which stated that Crown land in the charge of a municipal authority or local body could be made available free of cost for imperial purposes; and negotiations with the Compagnie des Messageries Maritimes, to acquire a harbour site currently occupied by them.The file includes Admiralty map 504/36 (folio 22) showing a section of the Aden harbour and the area identified for the fuel depot expansion.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 1).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Chief Commissioner, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Aden Port Trust</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Al Ma'allā'</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Oil tanks</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00001a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>