<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000354_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-24T08:54:22.480Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/ f 'Jfi ’©I Brigadier H. M. BURROWS, C.I.E.. 122 CHATSWORTH COURT. KENSINGTON, W. 8 Lt.-Col. R. R. YALLAND, D.S.O. 31st May 1949 Dear Sir, The FA^.IR OF IPX. Thank you very much for your letter of yesterday,and the trouble you have taken to find these particulars of the kaqir of Ipi. I will ask you kindly to keep this note about him handy,so that I can see it in original,after the Punjab Prontier Porce Centenary Celebrations (10th to 12th June)*Tnere will be many officers there who believe they know Waziristan as well as the palms of their hands. , At present the principal value of your note is that it suggests that the Paqir of Ipi’s influence began to increase from 1924,when he was only 23 *It contradicts the^xia* that he was unknown before 1936 * statement in the press You prove him to be a much younger man than is generally believed. Your remark about his accepting little or no H Shukrana M confirms the idea of his fanatical enthusiasm.My Persian dictionary trans lates shukran as M gratitude M or 'grateful w ,so I think it may be assumed that shukrana means what all priests expect 0 ' offerings !? Tel. western 8251, Ex. 122. DIRECTORATE INDIA” Mag^lzine published b/' PUBLIC RELATIONS. )/ PRINCES. ^To K.R.Crook Esq, ^^Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing St.,S.W.l,PoI.Sxt.^f4S/49 OCLtC^bidL Otr-aJiJ a Cofinonwea1th Relations Office, Downing Street. 30 ^* 1949. /L^ ^LrrrttJf- ■VT*, m i referei.c# tc your letter of 4th May about the i'sgjjir of Ipi, it is much regretted tfiet there should have &gt;een so much delay in replying; this was caused by the fact that the file containing the vital reference was not immediately available* The infor tion on record here about the F £ir prior to hie becoming a public figure in 1936, is exceedingly scanty. In fact the only thing vhich might he of use to you is a note prepared in 1956 which run* as follows:- Haji Mirm^AX* KfeiiMSS in 1956), kno^n as the Fa ^ir of Ipi\son of Mullah .nrsala Khan, Rangal Khel Maddi Khel.Haibati Tori Khel -azir of Khajuri. He in rcti&amp;lfliijli (Tali^) of Mullah Alam Khan of Ipi, and moved from Khajuri to Ipi about 1920, r.cccV\ nied y hir brother 'bgrsr irn, who still lives with him* His proficiency in religious knowledge is said to be a— below the usual standard as among teullahs. As a FaciSiir he is much reenacted in Lower Dawar, but has little influence in Upper Dawar or among the Wazirs. Prior to 1924 he was comparatively unknov/n, but after that year his influence began to increase gradually. Hie popularity may be partially due to the t that he accents little or no wa® the most important dlvlngtff of North aBirastan to accompany the ir m ashkr-r to loghalgai 9 host, durinp the 1 is turb^- ncer. of -f '5. Brigadier H. M. Burrows, C.I*S., 122 Chats^orth Court, Keneington, S. . 8*« -'oH \ In /pril 1956 he lefl a larpe £aeM^C Las ^ r» ? consisting mainly of Lower Da wars, into the IChsisora Valley as h means of exercising pressure on the Government in the decision on a case relating to a Hindoo girl of Bannu alleged to have been kidnapped and converted to lelanu e trust? that this information will serve your purpose, but if there ie anything more ve can do please do not hesitate to let us know.. 4 s / 'fy***&lt;) x 5 . (f/Too/C-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000354_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1393</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000354</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1393</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Pol Ext 6943/49 'Brigadier Burrow's request for early history of the Faqir of Ipi'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-11T22:06:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (7 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 9; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding a request by Brigadier Hollis Martin Burrows for information from prior to 1936 on Haji Mirzali Khan Wazir, known to the British as the Faqir of Ipi. As well as Burrows, the other primary correspondent is the Commonwealth Relations Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Mirzali Khan Wazir</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Historical research</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commonwealth Relations Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000354#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>