<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0000e2_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:52:52.280Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Thit document in the property of Her Majesty's Secretary of St ate for India. Confidential. _ 1899 . British Interests in Persia and the Gulf. (Letter from Foreign Office, dated 5th May 1899. Pol. 1963/99.) Competition for influence in the Persian Gulf is increasing, and the Intro- question arises whether our interests can now be clearly defined, and whether ^ uctor y- they require the adoption of any measures besides the constitution and re-arrangement of consular offices. This note will briefly review former declarations of policy made by the India Office. It will then examine the position of the vanous competitors, and summarise the leading diplomatic understandings or agreements. Possible courses of action will be stated, and some suggestions thereon will be submitted for the orders of the Secretary of State. 2. The attitude of the India Office has not been as firm of late as it used to be. i P 1 ? ^ t May J 874 Northbrook minuted (India Letter No. 123, ated 7th Juno 18 /5) “ An attempt to extend Russian territory, or a Russian P ro tecturate to the shores of the Persian Gulf would be so direct a menace &lt;t t0 lndia ; hat lt . w °uld, in my opinion, justify a resort to arms for the , purpose of securing our present supremacy in the Persian Gulf. But the ft ol Her 1 testy’s Government under such circumstances should be left free and unfettered by any previous engagements.” Sir Henry Norman agreed generally, and Lord Napier of Magdala considered it necessary to prevent Russia from possessing Northern Persia, or wielding ersian resources, for then “ what would be the use of retaining the shores ?Lr he r Pe , r8 J a v i Gulf ’ ? In pressing the Foreign Office, 17th August lo7o, Lord Salisbury was “ not disposed to dissent from the views expressed on this question by Lord Northbrook.” On 5th March 1887 the India Office addressed the Foreign Office in these t6rins i Previous declaration of policy. Whether this proposal can be acted upon at once or not, Lord Cross would suggest that the recently framed concession for the construction of a railway from Ahwaz to Teheran, together with rights of navigating the Karun, should at any rate be vigorously pressed upon the Shah’s attention. The establishment of British influence in Southern Persia, and the openim- of commercial communications in that portion of the Empire by British traders is the best, if not,^ indeed, the only countermove that can be made by tliis country to the rapid extension of Russian influence over northern if ersia. dj 111 ® 1887, the India Office wrote “His Lordship considers it to ;&lt; !' e /~ 1 »My desirable, in the commercial as well as the political interests of Lutish India, that a commanding influence in Southern and Central ‘ I ersia should be secured for the English Government.” More recently, * H.C., 1274/95. on ^ nd °1 March 1896, we wrote* that it would be impolitic to make any communication of our views or intentions in the event of a Russian occupation of Persian territory. “ It is very difficult to determine before- “ da f d whether the occupation by England of points upon the southern “ httoral of Persia would not place us in a disadvantageous position. Such a question must evidently depend upon the particular circumstances of the ^ time, and upon the general aspect ot the political and military situation.” bluet those vieus weie expiessed, action has been taken in two directions. t Political, 319/99. 23rd January 1899,f we made a treaty with Koweit preventing the A S. 24.2 Competitors. Russia. Persia. Germany. France. Turkey. alienation of the Sheikh’s territory to any power except the British. In Muskat we have prevented Erance from acquiring a position at Bunder Jisseh ... , for a coaling station; and we have * Political, 19-4/99. notified to the Persian Government* (Foreign Office telegram, dated 7th April 1899) that our political interests are not compatible' with the exercise of any control or jurisdiction by a European Power over the ports on the Persian Gulf. On 17th April the Persian Government replied that the Shah &lt;{ would not admit in the Gull ports, or elsewhere in Persia, anything which may be incompatible with “ the sovereign independence of the country.” 3. The competitors for interest in the Persian Gulf are Pussia, Persia, Germany, France, Turkey, Muskat, and ourselves. Russia exercises a predominant influence over Northern Persia, and the pressure of her advance from her territorial base is being felt in three directions. It is felt first on the north-east of Persia where the cart-road from Asterabad to the Meshed frontier, the completion of the rail-road via Merv to Kushk, and Russian action in Khorassan, are pushing foward the hand of Russia so that it may hereafter reach to Birjand and Kerman, and eventually to the Gulf. It is felt, secondly, on the north-west where the railway to Kars, almost finished, is to be extended to Erivan in the direction of the Tabriz frontier; the Nestorian community in Urumiah are being converted to a proper sense of Russia’s mission ; and Russian eyes are directed to Khanikin, whence, if the Kapnist scheme is realised, a railway line may cross Mesopotamia to Baghdad or Koweit. Thirdly, it is felt along the new road from Enzeli to Teheran, whence it is no far cry via Hamadan and Kirmanshah to Khanikin. Another line of advance might be Ispahan, where there is a Russian Consul, then Shiraz or Ahwaz, and thus Bushire or Fao might prove most attractive objectives. We have heard lately of movements to seize a port on Kishm (Kesso), of Russian agents at Koweit, of a scientific investigator M. Zarudni, in Sistan, and other incidents of a similar character. Under the Kapnist scheme of a line from the Mediterranean to the Persian Gulf, Russian control is reserved for the branch from Khanikin to Nedjef via Baghdad. Persia has latelyf assured us that she will not part with her ports or any sovereign rights. But her internal f 1924/99. condition might produce revolution, and her army is practically useless, and of such stuff that little could be made of it. On the north, Russia’s weight is irresistible, and Persia is already a puppet in her hands. Germany is no negligable quantity. Already she holds an important position in the railway system in Asia Minor, and if the Anatolian railway is extended to Baghdad, her interest in a port in the north-western corner of the Persian Gulf will be vital. X P.W. 5o2/99. Germany, too, is acquiringt direct telegraphic communication with Asia Minor, through Kustendje and Constantinople, and the Emperor’s recent tour, as well as the trend of his policy at Constantinople, indicate a possibility that, in the event of a serious conflict with Russia, Germany may be a factor on our side, or at least to be reckoned with. Not only may the Kapnist scheme assist German designs, but also we have lately heard of a concession for internal railway communication in Persia being granted to an Engineer who is negotiating with German capitalists. (Foreign Office, Asia, Prints, 4th April and 1st May 1899.) France has tightened by recent events her right to protect Muskat, and, unfortunately, Muskat includes Gwadar, a port on the Baluch coast, and also a long line of Arab coast, which, in the belief that India was the real protector of Oman, we have chosen to regard as part of Muskat. The French have a fleet, and the Persian Gulf is very near the Karachi port of India. Turkey certainly possesses Fao and one side of the Shat-el-Arab. Her right to the El Katif coast has been practically admitted by us. South of Bahrein she has a garrison at El Bidaa. She claims a right to Koweit, which we dispute. There have been rumours of her granting concessions to pearl fisheries in the Gulf, and in Asia Minor, at least, she holds territories reaching to the Gulf.t3 3 Muskat’s ruler, the Sultan, cannot exercise the slightest authority outside Muskat. his isolated capital. There and at Mattra, his subjects are only restrained by threat of punishment by us. We have upheld his rule at Dhofar, and without our subsidy the administration could not continue. But the joint Declaration of his independence signed with France on 10th March 1862 ties our hands, and detracts from the secret engagement of 1891, under which the Sultan cannot part with his possessions to any power except the British. The British Government, except in Baluchistan, owns no territories washed England, by the waters of the Gulf. Gwadar, the best port in Baluchistan, belongs to Muskat. From Aden to Kas Sair, where Muskat rule is held to begin, we have a protectorate over the Hadramaut tribes. From that point°we share with France a protectorate over Muskat. Bahrein, off the El Katif coast, is under our protection. Koweit has treaty relations with us. On the Persian coast we hold nothing, but we have a possible right of reversion to Bassidore on Kishm Island. Ormuz Island now belongs to Persia. The Indian frontier begins in Gwettar Bay, and Karachi is our nearest port, for Ormarah is a mere roadstead. We have no troops in Indian Baluchistan i.e., Mekran. From Gwettar Bay to Koh-i-Malik Siah, just south of Sistan, our land frontier marches with Persia, and at that point the Afghan boundary begins. We have, however, for many years kept the maritime peace in the Persian Gulf, and we alone protect trade in those waters which carry a sea-borne trade that is mainly British. 4. From a consideration of tlm jarring^ interests of these competitors, I Diplomatic pass to the diplomatic understandings which at present keep them apart, under- first with reference to the Gulf, then to Persia itself. Muskat and its sidings, dependencies, which include Gwadar on the Baluchistan sea-board, are under a joint French and British guarantee of independence. There are signs that this protectorate is being used by France to stimulate a trade in arms, and to w r ork against British interests. Next to Muskat comes the Pirate coast up to El Katr, with whose independent chiefs w T e have agreements of March 1892, which prevent their receiving foreign agents, or parting with their territories except to the British. Then begins the sovereignty of Turkey which extends with intervals to Mohammerah, and which appears, “ where firmly established on the coast,” to be recognised by the Despatch No. 13, dated 5th January 1880, to Sir H. Layard.' But from the correspondence of 1888 it is not clear that the Porte was formally advised of this. At any rate, Koweit is regarded by us as independent of Turkey. From Mohammerah on the Shat el Arab to Gwettar Bay, Persian rule is acknowledged ; but in April 1899 Persia w^as again told (Foreign Office telegram No. 10, dated 7th April 1899, to Sir M. Durand) that our political interests are not compatible with the exercise of any control or jurisdiction by a European power over the ports on the Persian Gulf. From the frontier of Persia to a spot near Karachi, the coast line, except at Gwadar, is, subject to the Kelat State, under British protection. The island of Bahrein is under our protection, and at Bassidore, on the island of Kishm, we still maintain a footing and occasionally fly our flag. Angaum (Henjam) was once occupied by us, but has been abandoned. Ormuz belongs to Persia. But the sovereignty over Angaum and Larak might raise a controversy, as they once belonged to Muskat. As to Persia itself, the sincere desire of Russia and Great Britain to maintain its independence and integrity rests upon declarations exchanged between the two Powers in 1834, 1838, and 1888, printed in Blue Book, Miscellaneous No. 2, 15th July 1898. The boundary of Persia with India has been demarcated. That between Afghanistan and Persia, especially in the neighbourhood of Herat, has never been accepted by the Amir, and further south on the Sistan line the Afghans object to what we regard as the Persian boundary. In this corner an encroaching spirit might lead to trouble. 5. The question arises whether these understandings are sufficient for our Courses of purposes. It must be admitted that they have not prevented Russia from action - increasing her pressure on Persia, from sending Cossack escorts with medical explorers even as far south as Sistan, from obtaining concessions in 5. 24. A 24 the matter of railways and roads in Persia denied to us, and, if rumour is to be trusted, from considering the question of occupying Kishm or a port near Bandar Abbas. At any rate there is a stir, and it seems a co-operation m French and Bussian movements which makes the Persian Gulf decidedly interesting. Are we then— i. to do nothing; ii. to agree with Russia as to our sphere of influence, as we did with France in Siam ; or iii. to take precautionary steps on our own account ? i. In favour of inactivity there is the argument that the future is unknown. We do not know where Russian pressure will emerge, whether Germanv will become an influence in Asia .Minor, what India s vujneiablc points will be when the Amir dies, and whether Russia will hold together. Why commit ourselves to engagements which wo may be unable to keep r 3 The future onlv can tell whether Russia s expansion from its tenitorial base will compel Russia at all hazards to have Koweit^or Fao, or Bandar Abbas. It may be unwise to look too far ahead or commit ourselves to indefensible positions. So argue one party. On the other hand it may be too late if we delay. Russia may secretly acquire rights, while Persia, seeing us inactive, may cease to resist or to warn us. Hitherto the theory of the Persian Gulf being our special interest, and the common belief that we will not allow our selves to be ousted from Southern Persia, and Sistan in particular,‘have been generally accepted. Every year of inaction will weaken our rights founded on the past, and prejudice our position when the inevitable struggle comes. As I believe that Russian contact with India will be little short of fatal to our rule there, I venture to think that we cannot sit still. Sphere of ii. Shall we then come to terms with Russia ? Sir Mortimer Durand traces influence in ^ line from Sistan, vid Kerman, Ispahan, ITamadan, and Kermanshah, to Persia. Khanikin as marking the line up to which our influence should extend ; he notes that the Persian Gulf ports are at the mercy of our ships, and he states the principle which is to govern his conduct in the future, i.e., letting it be understood that “ aggressive action by Russia in the north of Persia ■would immediately result in decided action by us in the south. I do not gather that he w r ould inform Russia to that effect, but he would warn Persia, and Persia no doubt when pressed would tell Russia. Looking, however, to the great interval which separates Indian garrisons from any part of Persia, and to the fact that the Indian army and exchequer are unequal to lending Persia material aid, I do not see the advantage of tracing the Khanikin to Sistan line without an agreement with Russia, which I understand is not to be hoped for. Even with such an agreement difficulties might arise. We may yet find that our western Afghan line is embarrassing if Herat is attacked. But to Yezd or Ispahan would be a much further cry. Moreover, Persia has no core, no power of self help or resistance, and therefore does not fulfil the needs of a buffer State. Its deserts and want of roads are better allies than a protectorate would be. iii. Let us, then, take our own action. Maintenance First, I think we should rigidly maintain our policy of excluding foreign of supremacy Powers from the Gulf ports, and, where possible, of acquiring rights ot pre in the Gulf, occupation. If ever territorial pressure forces us to give way at any point, we can do so on terms, whereas a present abandonment of our past policy would leave a vacuum into which a foreign Power would rush without Survey mouth of Gulf. Exclusion of rivals from Sistau. arrangement with us. i c Secondly, let us at once have a military and naval survey made ol every position or island at the mouth of the Persian Gulf. If Henjam is held to be a place suitable for a fort, let us arrange, by lease or otherwise, to take, hold, and fortify it. If we secure the mouth of the Gulf, the late of Turkish ports on it will be less important. Thirdly, although it is premature to extend the railway either by the Helmand, which we unfortunately gave to the Amir, or by the desert road, yet let us seek military expert advice as to the value of a railway from Quetta by Sistan to the Persian Gulf. If we are advised that such a railway would not be strategically valuable, at any rate let us keep control over Mekran*4 p]xclusive control over Maskat. and watch Gwadar. As regards Sistan, let us give Persia to understand that we allow no railway to be made to it without our consent. Such a line from the north w r ould be only useful for a Ptussian advance upon India. Fourthly, let us resist French encroachments on Maskat, and let no opportunity slip of getting rid of the joint Declaration of 1862. The arms traffic there may prove a serious danger to us. Finally, the question remains whether w r e should let Russia and Persia Declaration know that w r e regard the Gulf and Sistan as places in which w T e shall not of P ol,c . v - tolerate the presence of foreign European military or naval armaments. Already Persia has been told of our interests in its ports, and she has been warned that we shall let other parties, if they seek security for loans in those ports, know of our views. By similar means we can let all whom it may concern know that encroachment upon Sistan or the Persian Gulf ports would be regarded by us as indicating an hostile attitude towards India. If it be the case that a friendly and reliable agreement with Russia is impossible, then it seems wise and conducive to peace to declare formally wdiat ports and places we must regard as under our exclusive influence. 16th May 1899. W. Lee-Warner.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0000e2_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C94</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0000e2</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C94</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'British Interests in Persia and the Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1899/1899</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-27T10:43:16</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>This file consists of a single letter.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 82, and terminates at f 84, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of a letter concerning British interests in the Persian Gulf by William Lee-Warner of the Foreign Office. It questions if interests are clearly defined and reviews former declarations of policy made by the India Office.It includes the following:the attitude of the India Office;the position of competitors;a summary of leading diplomatic understandings and agreements;suggestions of possible courses of action.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign policy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0000e2#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>