<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024054342.0x000093_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T22:19:28.933Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024054342.0x000093_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/25, ff 67-68</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024054342.0x000093</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private
            Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/25, ff 67-68</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No 47 of 1822 from William Bruce, Resident at
               Bushire, Bassidore [Bāsaʻīdū] to Mountstuart Elphinstone, President and Governor in
               Council, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1822/1822</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-02T15:40:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter provides details of the Resident's journey
            from Shiraz to Bassidore [Bāsaʻīdū], detailing his stopping points and length of stay.
            Outlined in the letter is the assistance provided to him by the authorities in Persia to
            assist with this journey, along with the marks of respect paid to him by local chiefs.
            It provides details concerning the Resident's planned return to Bushire, and
            proposed trip to Bussora [Basra]. In the process, it also includes details of various
            stopping points and various matters he intends to take care of during his
            journey.It notes the Resident's opinion that Bassidore is a
            very suitable location to base a military force in the Persian Gulf, and reports that
            the troops currently stationed there are very healthy. The letter further informs the
            Governor of Bombay that he has ordered the reservoirs there to be put into good order,
            and that he has selected a suitable site to base the Residency.Also covered in the letter is the settlement of the matter
            of a battille captured from Shaikh Mahomed bin Qucazieb, which has been returned by
            Sa‘īd bin Sultān Āl Sa‘īd, the Imam of Muscat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024054342.0x000093#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>