<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000ac_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T21:36:22.562Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Ho. 2.3 ^ of 1926. itish Residency and ConsulateHjeneral. # Tu Buehire, October 1926. eJ A copy of the under mentioned paper received from the Colonial Office, London, with despatch No.6, dated the 2nd September 1926, is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain , for informatiiin. By order, Captain f for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Report by His Majesty's Government on the administration of Iraq for the year 1925. t ^ b fa*. im, ■ l/C^ fly. y/oBo. of 1346 Office of ^he Adviser to the Government, Bahrain, Dated, 5th Dul Qaad 1346 The H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum Ref, your Ko. 231/1928. Do you wish the Bahrain Government to issue a proclamation on the subject. Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. /Qj U. t✓ To Ho. ^ 0 ' ^ of 1928. British j^sidenoy,A OonsulatQ-General • -J Bushire, the 3 June 1928• % -^y- -j' ' V &lt;}i A N The Political A^ent, IZasoat The Political Igent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Kuwait His Majesty's Consul &amp; Asst. to the Resident, Bandar Ah^bas His Majesty^s Consul for Khuzistan, AJiwaz. His Majesty's Consul, Kerman The British Vice-Consul, Muhanmierah. Memorandum . The Hon'tjle the Political Resident wishes me to invite your attention to Circular Memorandum 339 dated the 1st March 1923 in which you «rere requested to send three copies o^any letters you address him on Important subjects which are likely to 'be forwarded to the Grovernment of India# He observes that the instruct ions are not 'being followed in several instances at present with the result that a lot of unnecessary lalxmw is caused in having to type copies in this office# Please, therefore, note to observe the instructions in future• By Order, pi F.B.des. I jJ. AP c- C V ^ v x Major, ^ Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ; hia. aZ- ^ yL 'Tvn. a— ^ 'iMfc No.1135 of 1928. British Residency &amp; OorLSulate -Creiieral, Bushire, the 16th June 1928. To The Political Agent, Muscat. The PoMtical Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Kuwait. ^ H.M T s Consul &amp; Asst.to the Resident, Bundaraobas H.M T s Consul, Kerman. The British Vice-Consul, Mohamnierah. M emorandum . In order to he in a position to arx^ange the necessary postings consequent on clerks proceeding on leave the Hon'hle the Political Resident directs that on the 1st of April and the 1st of October each year, you will submit a return showing the leave contemplated hy your clerical establishment during the 2nd half (i.e. 1st July to 31st December) and the 1st half (i.e.1st January to 30th June) each year, respectively. The first such return to he sent will he on che 1st October 1928, showing leave contemplated during Lhe 1st half of 1929. Order, r (Sd) H.R.V.Dickson Major Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian G-uli. Please note. (Id). C.B. 26/6Ko. I t7^of 1928. British Residency and Consulate-General^ Bushire, the 9th September 1928. , CIRCULAR. It is notified, for information, that Major H«R#P.Dickson, C.I.E., Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf will proceed to Shiraz on the loth September 1928 and will remain there till the return of the Hon'ble the Political Resident,(probably during the first week in October). Captain Russell, Under Secretary, at present at Shiraz, on relief by the Secretary will return to Bushire and take over charge of the Residency Office there. By order. Sd/ H.R.P.Dickson, Major, Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Copy forwarded toj- The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrein, S The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty's Consul, Kerman. His Majesty's Consul, Shiraz, H.M f s Consul &amp; Asstt. to the Resident,Bandar Abbas# British Vice-Consul, Mohammerah, for information. By order. 1 Maj or. JJjr v i. U.t5 X # tH* 1 ^ Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf.Tc HO. of 1950 0 British iesileaoy &amp; Ocnsulate-CreaGral. Bushire, the 22^ February 1930. 04 The Political £gent ^ Consul, ifuscat The Political Agent, Bahrein. The Political A^ent, Kuwait• E.B.M's Consul St Asstt. tc the Resident, Bandar abhas. His Britannic ^ajesty^s Consul for Khualstan, ahwag. His Britaiinic iajoatj-'s Consul, Keraan. The British Vice Oonaul, KohaiaBierah. Circular ^eiacrandum ^ Despatches are sanetlnieb received in this clTice with paragraphs unnusibered which makes reference difficult. It is; requested that in future the- paragraphs be numbered. By Order, , ^ Major, Secretary tc the Political ie^ident in the Persian Gulf. 3^ V.-W. INo.485 of 1930. British Residency &amp; Gonsulate-G-eneral. Bushire, the 1st March 1930. The Political Agent, Muscat. The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Kuwait. H.B.M(s Consul &amp; Astt.to Resident, Bandar Abhas. His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Kerman. The British Vice-Consul, Mohammerah. Circular Memoranauin . Oases have r^otintly occurred in which cleriis nave applied for leave at too short a notice oexoiG tuey wisn to go on leave. It is extremly difficult in these circumstances to effect the necessary relief arrangements and it was precisely to ohviate this difficulty that this office circular Memorandum Jo.1135 dated the 16th June 1928 was issued. The Hon'hle the Political Resident, therefore, directs that intimation of intended leave 'by clerks should he sent in due time accx as required by the aoove circular. Cases of real and sudden emergencies, however, can of course be sent in all any time. The ofiicer forwarding such an application should satisfy himself that tne case is really urgent. ^ ^ By Order, v^ (Sd) .T.C.Fowle Major, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf. Cadre- All clerks to initial as seen. (Id) C .G .P. 4/3X r Z Nc. l Dl% cf 1930. British Residency &amp; Consulate -General, Bushlre, the 3 C ^'April 1930. !■ ... ....aa ic Political Agent, bahrein. Memcrandnrn &gt; Beference ycur Nc.^l-C dated the 24th April 1930 which was addressed to me. Please see this office Circular Memorandum Nc .2662 dated the 19th Ncvemher 1929 and note that all confidential correspondence should 'be addressed to the Hen*hie trie Political Resident. By order, *, &lt;. * nJ^ Maj or, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf..X-lfi i lit * Trans iat ion. Jrom tae protocol Depaartiinfent ox' tine Ministiry for JToreign AXi'airs aaaressea to His Majesty^ ijegatLon, aatea Azer 24tih 1309( Dtioember 15tn, 1930) No. 810014/25797. Clroular Memorandu if: Tile Protocol Department of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs has the honour to inform the Honourable Foreign Legations in Tehran that trie name of Nusratahad the • f chief town ^ sis tan has 'been changea to zahul, and that of Duaciap to Zahidan. It is requested tnat tnt Lugation may 'bw so gooa as to inform tneir Government accox'aingiy. (3ealea) protocol iJtpartment of tne Ministry for Foreign Affairs.No. n Of 1951. BritLih—esidcnoy &amp; Ccnsulate-General, Bushlro, the Z^^January 1931 • To The Pciltloal Agentf Muscat. The Political A.sent, ^ahr^ln The Political Ar.ent, Kuwait. The Kesideticy Agent, tihargah. cnculvl ^o^andijm. The Hon'ble the Political neaiaent in the Persian ^ulf airects tnat in future he should ue addressed by you as - The non'ble the Political \nsident in the Persian Gulf ' only and the use of the covors with the printed address 'Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf and H.B.H's GLnsul-^eneral for Pars, etc.. should be discontinued. By order Captain, Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. *i • ' « i v I * . 0v9~s H j O - ono:^u Political Agency, Bakrein,tke 18tk February 1931 To, Tke Secretary to tke Hon T ble tke Political Resident in tke Persian Gulf, Buskire. Memorandum . Please refer to your circular memorandum No:170 dated tke 24tk January 1931. I kave over 200 covers in tkis Agency addressed 'Tke Hon T ble tke Political Resident in tke Persian Gulf &amp; H.B.M t s Consul General for Pars &amp;c., ,T . Since it is desired tkat tke latter portion of tke address skould be discontinued I propose to paste over tke latter kalf and to use tkese 200 envelopes in tkis manner. You will no doubt arrange to supply us witk envelopes witk tke first kalf of tke Residents title only printed on tkem in future. Political Agent, Bakrein.No•14-T or 1951. orrioe or t&gt;lie Politilcai ±tBsiaenti in Liie Persian uuir. Camp, Muscat, DatucL 'one 14t»n February 1931, Sir, At tne end or this montn tne mdo-European Telegrapn department will cease to exist, xhe Department Has run 'one cables in zhe Persian (iuir and certain telegrapia lines in tiJie interior of Persia for about 60 years, iney will leave 'benind them a record of service under most tjrying and arduous conditions of wnicn the members or the Department may well reel proud, jjuring this period they nave toeen Drought into the closest contact with Political orx 'icers serving in Persia and many members or the department have 'been in political charge or their posts. The Department has consistently rendered to orricers or the Political department the most valuable services in their olTicial capacities and much assistance to them in their private capacities. 2* I&gt; therefore, desire on 'behair of the orficers of the Political department serving in Persia to ask you to convey to the members of the Indo-European xelegrapn department our regret at the abolition of the department; our most cordial and sincere thanks for all the help they have given to us in the past, and.our 'best wishes for their future welfare and prosperity. 1 have the honour to be, Sir, lour most o'bedient servant, Sd. H.V.Biscoe, dt.uolone^ Political resident in the Persian uulf. i The director. Inao_E ra!|g uuil g £^si?oSt r1&gt;men11 'INDO EUROPEAN TELEGRAPH DEPARTMENT • (Persian Uuir Section). From xne Direccor, Persian Grulf Section. To Tlie Hon'oie tne Political nesidenn in the Persian G-ulf, B U S H I R E , Enclosure - No. 241A/42d4, Karachi, the 25rd Jieoruary 1951. Sir, On 'benall* or tne j.n(io-ii:uropean lelegraph Department, i nave tne honour to thank you Tor your very kind letter No. 14-T, dated the 14Tin jje'bruary 1S51 a copy of which is l)eing supplied to each menfDer or the stalT. On their 'behair x would like to take this opportunity to express their great appreciation or the unrailing help, courtesy and hospitality which they have received from Officers of the political department which has done so much to mitigate the arduous condi tions of their service. i have the honour to lie, Sir, Your most ©'bedient servant, Sd. s. deSmith. Director, Persian G-ulf section.1 4uti . Ho. of 1931. British Hecidency c Gonsulate-Oeneral, £ B ^shire, the ^ ^ starch 1931. ?rora The Under Secretary to the Hon'hle fie Political Resident in t^e ^ersian Oulf. To The Political A^ent, B a H R 2 I H. Menoranda'n. wws the Accountant- General, Central Revenues, has asked this office to send to hin monthly a consolidated rhsent ee stp.teiaent coniprisinj all the offices under this Residency, please send as soon as possih] e after the lEonth to v .-^ich the statei:i «nt refers, 'beginning from 1st April 1931, a copy of th« absentee statement furnished by ycu alon - '.vith the ecfcahl i''^sient salary 'bill. By Order, Captain, f Under secretary to the Political ^iesident in theno. /g+v of iy3i. Brltiisli Residency &amp; Consulate G-eneral. sit Bushiro, the 2-6 ~ August 1931 • To The Political Agent- Muscat. The Political A.gent- Bahrein. The Political Agent- Kuwait. H. B. M's Consul - Bandar-Ahhas. H. B. Jll's Consul - Ahwaz. H. B. M's Consul - Kerman. H. B. Id's Vice-Oonsul- Mohammerah. ^too' !Jatt *--?-}/■ * ■-, ■ - i,~ - - y Circular Memorandum. A case occurred recently; where an Officer,after arriving at his destination^en joyed the balance of the maximum period of Join ing time permissible to him under the rules he- fore taking over charge of his duties. The Accountant G-eneral, Central Hevenues, has now held that under Section 304 S. H. joining time expires with the arrival of a Grovernment servant at the station to which he has 'been posted. It is requested therefore that in future it should he arranged for Grovernment ser vants to take over charge of their duties on the day or the day following their arrival according to whether they arrive 'before or after noon. By Order. — Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ^ (M. /// / f^/c Pu-c S- ' ' 7' 1'' u Z^ 6 - ^ ' C*~ Ce \ 1 , a. Reference alDove^* There is no change in the joining time allowed as far as Bahrain is concerned hut the rule would seem to clash with the recent orders received from Bushire vide page 30 flagged in file 15/3. 2. The two files are kept separately to make it easier for the office to find out references.C's. p. P.—L (in) 977—400-1-30—k. No. / 3 of 1931. T he P olitical A gency, B ahrain, Dated the Is' Deca rJter 193I. To T he S ecretary to the H on'ble the P olitical R esident in the P ersian G ulf, BUSHIRE. MExMORANDUM iitjase refer bo yoar kmor&amp;adua :.o;loOG dated the 36th August 1931 and the paper forwarded with your indorse ment '0:ZL!$ datsa t.'.e 16th October 1931 • It vwuld appear titat tbe orders regard ur; join in,; time clasii v/ith the circular conveyin^- the ruling of the Accountant General thiit joining tii.e expires with the arrival 01 a Cwommout sorvant at the station to which he 'ma hoaa posted^ Ii # If a CrOYemiivsnt ourrant is entitled to 3 days 1 juijiiii^ tirae -lr«. .addition to the number of days occupied in th'? traaamlesion of u raail ietterj,! do not see ^hat authority the Account ant General has to arrxid or alter these xmles,. 4» Aprjrt frui this-there are objection to an officer handin; over directly his successor arrives. It is fre- (nently mploa^nt to remain in a place after one has divested oneself of author5.ty and I have hnoroi cases where a certain amount of friction has been caused. Let us suppose that a Political A^ent hnnda over at Bahrain to one who arrives by the down raail from ^asra» It would clearly be impossiblQ to kmd over and proceod to India in the same steamer and yet,if he were to hand ovar directly his successor arrived,he would be left in an invidious position for a whole week. agent, Bahrain.o ^JL ( o &amp; ar-viz-wv-' ^ ^ ^mr c-ct ^ ci i i u l a n. I ^O'ITATIOM 0? 1^3ONII, T -?^:0TS 'TJ^NITITl^ &gt; STOKES ■^tcj* &gt; i:tto pt^sia. In order to avcid difficulties '/it:! the CuGtcrns authorities on arrival Into Persia the follc.Tia^ points in ccnneotion v /ith the Persian govern:lent : s Trade Monopoly Lav/, introduced in I.'aroh i3ol should oe home in ;aind:- Theoretioally no goods may he imported unless a corresponding amount of Persian produce is first exported. Individuals in the vorvico of foreign Govcnuionts in Persia may howvVur obtain permission tare ugh tnu ir l.ogations in Tehran from tn.. '/inistry of :iational Economy for th^ import ation of articles ±(:r tn-.ir personal us^ \/itiiout ooli^aticn to zepor t. 2, .articles are divided into tv;o classes- (1 j pixhibit^ d ( i. e. ^oods ,. r hich cannot imported for x^urposes of trade even against Persian Exports), (2)» Permitted . 'Then importing goods falling under the 1st category care should 'De taken to ootain a permit 'before theli , arrival in Persia as othereise such goods can only De cleared after the payment,besides customs duty of a fine amounting to five times the custome duty. In the case of permitted goods,these will merely oe retained hy the customs until such time as permits are received and cleared on payment of the ordinary duty only» 3. As regards travellers personal effeets,fairly wide latitude is alioeed for aoccmpanied luy.a^e . Clothes personal belongings,furniture(except musical instruments) table andr dgc I linen 6t/c« ? cun og iinpcrtjgd In tjlj-is manner wiuiicua permits and if net nev; are exempt ircm easterns Duty out nc liquor cr rccd sturf can oe sc imocrted * 4 \ list cf prchi'oitGd articles is attached. Since permits take aocut six eeks tc coatin^persens desiring to 'bring in geeds iiguring cn this list should take steps tc make applications through the Officer in Charge cf the post to 'vhich they are 'being appointed at the earliest possible j until moment and refrain from importing such goods iflttifcTsat permits have 'been obtained. Captain., Secretary tomthe Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.cf 1931. British Residency &amp; Gensuiate-General. Bushire, the/l'T ijecemt)er 1931. Tc y' / if, v • •s '' , •: - The Political Agerit, bahrein. Kemcrandura. Heference your memracrandun Nc. 1331 dated the 1st Deoemoer 1931. r^he ruling cf the Accountant General was □ased on Supplementary Rule 304 which lays down that a Journey and consequently joining time terminates on arrival at destination. The whole question has since Deen taken up with the Government of India and it has been settled that in future Joining time shall include three days at destination. Supplementary Rule 304 is being altered accordingly. r By Order, v 3 Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. O vw\ &gt;.British lesidenoy &amp; Ocusulate-General, v BasJiire t the January 1966. Joicnol ■i'owle would lae very grateful if ycu wculd be sc gcca as uc have paragraphs numbered in all dpspatohes and meocrandums issuing rrcm your cfi 'io The numbering of paragraphs hy the issuing office fa oil Lta tes references, especially if such references have to be made lay telegraph# Lieutenant Colcnel Gr. Loch, I.A*, Political Agent, 3 a h r a i n . /% ♦ S.I 311 ; .&gt;r^receivei&gt;' yo \\ ■ vvv ^ \3BAHRl^ai Ho.636-3 of 1933. British ^eaideroy ^ Consulate-General, BUSRIRS, the 10th June,1933. The Political Agent, I&amp;rwait. The Political Agent, Bahrain, 1 The Political Agent, Muscat. m^mprandypn. As there is at present a certain lack of uniformity in the supply of spare copies of letters and enclosures thereto received from Agencies it is requested that in future spare copies may be furnished as follows. When the correspondence shows that copies are forwarded hy this Residency to (a) the Gorernraent of India only 2 siaare copies (b) His Majesty's Government ) and the Government of India ) Additional snare copies, up to a total of 6, should be furnished in cases in which it is likely that copies will be forwarded as well to other posts, such as Baghdad, Jed da, etc# As 8 flimsies can be struck at one impression this would involve no additional typing at the Agencies and save much at this 'Residency. Sd. T# C. ^owle. at^st-gp , Lt.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. for 3«er«tary to the 'olltieal Resident in the Persian Gulf.uy No. A.B. of ^933. British Consulate-General, Bush ire, tlie 20 th. July i332. Tq The Political A^ent, Bahrain. Memorandum, Reference your Endorsement No. 773, dated the 3th July 1933. Mr* Saffar Islam is appointed as 2nd clerk , 'Bahrain, sub protttm vice Mr. Hahmat Ullah g^io .is provisionally confirred as 3rd clerk Bushire; consequently T 'r. Rahrut Ullah's nume should he omitted from ^rour Ahser tee statenent and Wr. 2affar Islam's name 'be included instead with particula -rs as follows Name Zaffar Islam Pay Es. 104/- Officiating appointment:- clerk, Muscat Date of appointment to present poet:- Date of promotion to present pays- • Next increment due s- Date of hirtli s - 4-1-33. 4-1-34 14-3-1903 . By Order, • ^ Secretary to ulie J-'jliliain Resident in the Persian Gulf . m *- u Res. P. O. No. 32. ' s f\c r ' - _ fa No. of I9i3. ^ \ *( , , British Residency and Consulate-General, Bush ire, the 193^ A copy of the undermentioned pap or is forwarded to : — The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrein, The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty's Consul and Asstt. to Resident, £ under Abbas, His Majesty's Consul, Kerman, His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Mohammerah, ^or information and guidance with reference to this office endorsement &gt;r6. , dated the _ . By order, |v q_w Secretary to Eical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Letter ftom tlto Govofumcut of India in Uie No. , dated the (Rcjeivod-Jidtb Foreign and—-t'olitieai—Deparlmeu No. dated the 1-9— euduiseiueat / in tores t Caloulation Saldoa AUd HaaOy nec^cncrs /or u&amp;e in iiOOOUQt Offices* G1FI&gt; -254 pi? Bashiro -10-10-31—2,000. i IHP S nres, p. g. vo. 32. No. 2-4 o I of 19?^ British Residency and Consulate-General, Busbire, the/^ ^ 1933 1 ^ Ncvemtoer A copy of the uudermentioned paper is forwarded to : — The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrein, The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty's Consul and Asstt. to Resident, £ under Abbas, His Majesty's Consul, Kerman, His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Mohammerah, ^or information and guidance with reference to this office endorsement Ko. 4 _ _ y. -&gt;iated the 19 105/166? 5th W g U3t By order, .mfuiwsk Secretary to the Political Resid 'ersian Gulf, v jDe^artment or education Health « Letter from the GoTerumeiit of India m the Lands t Department No- i.VE-S/S^ted the 27th oepteinbel9 (Received with Foreign and Political Department endorsement No. 141 -a /Wed the 30 th Ootctoek^ GIFO -254 PR Bushire -10-10-31—2,000.DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION, HEALTH AND LANDS. NOTIFICATION. Education. Simla, the 27th September 1933. No. F. 72 3132. —The following additions and alterations are made in the rules for the encouragement of the study of oriental languages- published with this Department notification No. F. 72-3132-E., dated the 16th June 1933 (1) Rule X. —For the syllabus in Pali substi tute the following for the existing entries :— ' (a) Construing, with readiness and accuracy, from the undermentioned books— (t) Anderson's Pali Render up to page 70. (it) Dhammapada Chapters I to XTV (Pali Text Society Edition). (Hi) Khuddakapatha, the whole (Pali Text Society Edition). All these books may be had through Burma Book Club, Rangoon. (b) Translating accurately and Avith correctness of idiom and grammar not less than half an ordinary octavo page of plain English into Pali. (c) Translation of easy unseen Pali passages into English. (r?) Grammar and Philology : a paper will be set in these subjects consisting of questions based upon the ' Practical Grammar of Pali ' (by Duroiselle), omitting derivation and prosody and the ' Hand Book of Pali ' (by Frankfurter).'' (2) Bule X.—Substitute the following for the concluding paragraph :— £&lt; Candidates to be successful in the above examinations in Sanskrit and Pali must obtain 50 per cent, of the marks in the aggregate and not less than 60 per cent, of che marks in the translation of the unseen passages and 35 per cent, of the marks in each of the other subjects.' (3) Rule XV. —In paragraph 1 for the words after an interval of two years ' substitute the words ' with the sanction of the Board Df Exa miners (Army Department) '. G. S. BAJPAI, Secy, to the Govt, of India.- h153ehl—1,200—5-10.33—gips-— To Ho. A. 3. /5/21 Of 1954. British Residency i Gonsulate-Geneial, Bushire, the ^ay 1954. The Political Agent, Bahiain. Memorandum. 2 v . a y a' ^ C*- 4 ■ xiefei'nce your endorsement No. 738, dated May 1^34, forwarding the Absentee Statement for April 1934. Th3 pay of Mr. Zafar Islam is shown as Rs. 104 ■whereas his pay is Rs. 10Q/-/- from the 4tli January xJ54. Please correct your Absentee Statement accordingly. k xiy Order, Secretary t^^the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ■ i J /fNo. A.B. 5 1934. British Residency li Censulate-General 9 Bashire, the /^//' ? June 1934. Te The Political Agent, Bahrai Bahrain, Memorandum. Reference Articles 7 and 13 and Vom I of the Ressurce Manual. Please report what 8teps 9 if any, hare been taken ts ensure that Xaxtreasurers and sther dsTemment Serraats under ysur control, who are entrusted with the charge of public funds, furnish sufficient security to protect GoTernment against loss due to negligence, fraud or other cau&amp;es. By Order, Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf.- yj r, ' I,., ' - CONFIDP^NTI AIj . m.jU 67/1 The Secretary to the Hon'lile the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Muscat. The Political Agent, Bahrain. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BU8HIRE. Dated...Wxe. ,/^j^uae, .1944. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Memorandum No.]?.463-x/33, dated the 19th ^ay 1934, fron the -deputy Secretary to them G-ovt tT Ind^a, F &amp; P l^ept, Simla. Subject. Grant of diplomatic status to the , . British Jfinvoy, Nepal. L MLJj'rcm - The -deputy Secretary to the Govt cf India in the -ccr^lgn and x'clttloal iJepartment. To - X X X X X ,x ihe Hcn'ble the Pclitioal resident In tne Persian Ckilf. X X X X X X Meracrandum Nc.F.465-x/i53. Simla, the 19th May 1954• viuuject;- Grant of diplciaatic status to the British jmvcy, nopal. It is hereby nctiried tiiat His liaj esty the King has been pleased to raise the status or the British Envoy at the Court of ^epal to that of tsnvoy .axtraordiiiary and Minister Plenipotentiary A Lieutenant Oolonel Q.T, Daukes, G.I.is., the British present British Jfinvoy,Nepal, has been appointed as His T/aJesty's Minister at the oourt of Nepal and will present his credentials to His Majesty the MaharaJadhiraj of aepal on the 20th iiay 1934. sd. Deputy Secretary to the Govt of India,C'sP.P—L (III) 129—500-431. ^ ^ ' v \ No. ' p ' of 193 The Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the 6th Jfrly 193 4. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. * MEMORANDUM. Hcference your Memorandum Ko«A»B*626 dated the 14th June 1934# fhe duties of the treasurer are at present carried out here by the Head Clerk of the Agency and so far, no steps have been token to demand a security fron hiiri# inhere is no record in this Agency to chow that in the past each security waus demanded from the rreusurer# 3* fhe surplus cash of this Agency is deposited in the eastern Bank Limited, Bahrain, and the Head Clerk keeps m m r.inwi.iimww'iwi a small amount to meet dally payments* 4# iihould f In the future, the posts of Treasurer and Head Clerk be divided it might be considered edvisablo for the Treasurer to give a security for 500/(Five hundred) rupees# As&gt; for Political Agent, Bahrain. 7? ^0 OKTFIDENTIAL ]&gt;oonco lofaj Uated, the May 1934 x'ravelling allowance to ol© r iG a l jjsta 13113111116111 on leave® Supplementary Knle 30^ as it now stands allows a oleric to take leave wltnouv tne stipulation tiiat in order to draw travellxng allov/anoe four montiis* leave or over must 'be taken# 2^ supplementary j^le U4 wiien read witn Supplementary jiule 305 entitles tile clerk to tiiree 2nd class passages without food to/from Karachi, whicn, from Bus hire amounts to Es 141 x 5 x a Rs b46A This is a large expenditure from the iraveiling Allowance funds and means that a clerk if ne gees without his family can put at leas^ Es 550/- in his pockety wnicn represents so many months• pay or thai; clerks 3o ihe Hesideno would 'be glad if when th^y recommend leave for clerks the cone emeu would 'bear tho ahove considerations in viewo 9 Lieut-0cionel a.Loch, I # A.&gt; Political Agent, Bahrain.Oircular No. |7^ The January 1935. To The Political Agenti Muscat. The Political Agent, Bahrain,^ The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty's Consul, Keriaan. is Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abbas. His majesty's Vice-Consul, i^aimnerah. In order to facilitate dealing with correspondence please ay bill matter for the Confidential and Town Office separately and enclose 'both in separate covers, marking the word 'iown 1 on the non-confidential cover. By Order, il/v for Secretary to the ^orT ^ble the Political Resident in the Persian 3ulf. % i 1 v SfoExtract from the Gazette of Inciian, Part I datea th March 1935. Foreign and Political Department. Notifications. New Delhi, the 14th March 1935. XXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXA 1 • % i N o .156- N . - It is notified for general information that the Government of Persia have aeciaea that from 21st March 1935 they will no longer employ the woras 'Persia' and Persian' when referring to that country and its people, and have requested that the woras 'Iran' and 'Iranian' should be used in their stead. The Government of India have decided to accede to this request in official correspondence. Sd/- H.A.F.Metcalfe, Foreign Secy.to the Govt.of India xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx I This should be circulated in oil ice arid tnen Ulea ? A. ■ ff y, ^ cU-hU limine*ef- yp. 4, j/* (Ue \\ ([(( d inRes. P- G. No. 32, - ' No^-iii—«f 19 ® 6 13/163 Pritisli Residency and Consulate-General, Bush ire, the XIIt April 10 35, A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to : — The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrein, ^ The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty's Consul and Asstt. to Resident, £ under Abbas, His Majesty's Consul, Kerman, His Majesty's Vice-Consul^ Mohammerah, lation and guidance By order, Secretary to Vie PoUticarResident in the Persian Gulf. Deputy Secretary to Letter from^the Government of India in the Xo . r « 40 ' N /8 ^1 a ted the 6ttl April 19 55, r. &amp;p. Department v.; gifd-254 pr bushire-10-10-31—2,000.IV om ■■P s&amp; No.F.40-H/S5 The Deputy Secretary to the Oovt. of India in the Foreign and Political Department. To The Hon'hlo the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. x xi New Delhi, the 6th April l935o Sir, I am directed to forward a copy of Gazette notification N o .156- N # , dated 14th March 1935 and to request that, (with the permission of the Governor in Councilj instructions may kindly 'be issued to ensure that the change 'becomes universally known, and that effect is given to it in official correspondence and conversation# 2* It is however important that the Persian Gulf should continue in official parlance to he referred to as such. The term 'Iranian Gulf* should not h e used* I have eto. Sid/- OeK.Caroep Deputy Secy* to the Govt, of India®yoreign and Political Department. Notification. New Delhi, the 14th March 1935. No.156 -N .-It is notified for general information that the Government of Persia have decided that from 21st March 1935 they will no longer employ the words ••Persia* 1 and '•Persian' when referring to that country and its people, and have requested that the words ^Iran - and ^ Irani an' 1 should he used in their stead# The Government of India have decided to accede to this request in official correspondence. H.A.F.Metcalfe, Foreign Secretary to the Govt, of India15/3. 1268/ 5 political Agency, Bahrain, j uly to i'he secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum# I encloee a copy of the July 1936 iseue of Imperial Airwayo Gazette on pace 6 of which you v 111 cee that 'Iranian Gulf' has been used instead of 'Persian Gulf'# Your attention is bein# dravm to the matter for such action as you nay consider necessary in view of the instructions v- 0 contained in Govemr ent of India 1 s letter N o # F # 40-N /36, dated the 6th April 1^36 (copy received under your printed C] letter No,826/13/163, dated the 29th April 1936). I .( J a ^ lieutenant, . for officiating political Agent, Bahrain.■ ■ - '2 i m W IMPERIAL AIRWAYS—YESTERDAY, TO-DAY AND TO-MORROW {The following article, which was written by Mr. G. E. Woods Humphery, the Managing Director of Imperial Airways, was published in a recent issue of ' The Aeroplane ' and is reproduced by permission of that nezvspaper) When Imperial Airways came into existence in 1924, the policy of the British Government was to regard the company as the British national air transport company, with a specific mission to develop commercial aviation on an economic basis. The state of aeronautical science at that period was such that some form of financial aid was necessary during the first years of the company's existence to give a measure of financial stability, and secure healthy development. As payment for carrying out a minimum programme, Imperial Airways was therefore given a subsidy on a gradually diminishing scale. The subsidy was not paid to resuscitate or bolster up a flagging industry, but to speed up the development of an entirely new service of communications that promised to be one of the most valuable links of Empire, and a commercial asset to the Empire as well. I make no apology for emphasizing these facts, because I believe that many people interested in aviation and the development of British commercial air services, do not appreciate the peculiar responsibilities and obligations under which we must work. It was an understanding attached to the subsidy agreement between the Government and Imperial Airways that the company was to steer its development on a strictly commercial and economic course ; the company was not, and is not, free to follow any other. _ . . Although in the first year or two of the existence of Imperial Airways the company confined its operations to Europe, it lost no time in planning the long-distance routes of the Empire, applying its own and its predecessors' experience of operating various services in Europe to the problems of the routes to India and through Africa. foreign politics It is one thing to operate air services within the frontiers of one country or even in Europe, but it is a very different matter to operate them, as we and our associated companies are now doing, over four continents and nearly thirty countries. A company which operates international air services has to face problems which are either peculiar to air transport, or which do not confront railway companies or steamship companies to anything like the same degree. Of all the difficulties which are encountered in operating air services crossing foreign territories, none is greater than those that arise from international politics, for they are based on the uncertain and shifting foundations of national aspirations and prejudices. The ' nationalism ' which has developed in all countries since the War has militated against the successful development of international air transport. An air transport company is not a free agent in the selection of the route which its services follow over foreign territories, but has to conform to the wishes of the various foreign governments concerned, many of whom have air services of their own, and who sometimes regard the operation of a foreign service over their territories as impairing their national prestige. This country built the foundations of its commercial prosperity upon the freedom of the seas, a doctrine which has brought untold benefits to mankind, and, until air transport is regarded with the same liberal attitude of mind, it can neither make the greatest use of the latest scientific discoveries in its own development, nor confer upon the world its full potential benefit. the economic factor Apart, however, from political consideration, the overriding feature of Imperial Airways' policy is the economic one which really governs everything, and the company endeavours to provide the services required for the least subsidy. This entails, first, the provision of a fleet which will earn in receipts from traffic carried the largest possible proportion of the cost of operation. Who can say, on a review of Imperial Airways' history to date, that our policy has been wrong ?- the results do not offer a fragment of evidence in support of such a conclusion. The volume of our traffic is the envy of our competitors, who have for years been trying their best to obtain more of our traffic than the comparatively small fraction they now carry. The worst that can be said with truth against the British policy is that our fleet-replacement programme is late, but there is a very good reason for this, which the ordinary observer can hardly be expected to see in the absence of some explanation. If we had proceeded to replace our fleet on the basis of the existing surcharged air mail system, the far-reaching plan—to use the Secretary of State's words—which has now been adopted by the Air Ministry and the Post Office, and is as yet still under consideration by the Dominions and India, of carrying by air all the letter mails on the Australia and Africa routes, would have been postponed for some years until the commitments had been liquidated. While this truly revolutionary scheme was under consideration, it would have been worse than unwise to have embarked upon a programme of fleet-replacement which might well have left the national company with a legacy of aircraft unsuitable for the plan finally adopted. On the expiry of the existing agreements the Government would have three main alternatives open— (a) to leave commercial and financial influences on civil aviation to take their course, having fostered the establishment of commercial air services for over a decade, (b) to continue its benevolent interest in such development for a further period with any necessary modifi cations to suit the changing conditions, but having as a main line of policy the continuance of air mails on a surcharge basis, and (c) to adopt a progressive policy under which all letter mail within the Empire should be carried by air without surcharge, and thus place the benefits of the airservices at the disposal of the largest proportion of the public. In face of the support given to the other national air companies by their respective governments, the policy of leaving British commercial aviation to look after itself and stand entirely on its own feet is obviously impossible, and there can be no doubt about the wisdom of the adoption of the all-mails-by-air policy. Clearly, however, entirely different fleets and types of aircraft might be required, depending on which of the three alternative policies or variations of them was adopted by the Government, and, until that policy was decided, neither Imperial Airways nor the Aircraft Constructors could proceed in regard to future types of aircraft. It is generally agreed that the design and production of a new type of aircraft of the size required for Empire services, which shall show an advance in efficiency over the types in use, takes about two years, andimperial airways gazette Aircraft Constructors in this country have been equally handicapped in looking ahead for the main British markets of the future. In America; on the other hand, no fears of a major change in air policy had worried air transport contractors up to the time of the cancellation of the air mail contracts, and, therefore, constructors knew the type of aircraft to develop for their own enormous home market. It is therefore equally unjust to chide British constructors for not developing a type of aircraft for which there is no home market, and probably also none in British territory overseas. Up to the present time, British con structors have produced civil aircraft which have been as great a success in their own sphere as have the aircraft of any other nation, and there is no reason to doubt that in the new policy for commercial air developments in the British Empire, British constructors will be found at least equally capable of producing the desired aircraft as the constructors of any other country, and I believe they will be better aircraft than any in the world. speed as an economic problem It is mainly on the question of speed that unfavourable comparisons are made between British and American aircraft. Everybody wants to increase speed. It is one of the fundamental dreams of mankind to annihilate time and space, and the increase of speed in air services follows that longing. Those who say that Imperial Airways is opposed to increase in speed are either ill-informed or have an axe to grind. The truth is that the company is as anxious as itcould be to increase the speed of its services, but cannot do so regardless of cost. Nevertheless, all the units of the fleet of which we have taken delivery within the past year have a top speed in the region of 170 miles an hour. America has gone to high cruising-speeds, because, without high speed, their internal air services cannot hope to compete against their efficient rivals, the railways. Moreover, as petrol is cheap, speed is relatively much less cpady. ;e European air companies have adopted high-speed aircraft because military aviation must have high speeds, anU their civil air services are, in fact, operated with a military motive. Some have bought fast American aircraft because the aircraft are good, are sold at a reasonable price ' off the shelf,' and because they just fit for the cir cumstances of the services on which they will be employed. Still others have adopted high-speed aircraft in the hope of augmenting their own slender national traffic by attracting some of the foreign traffic that would other wise travel by the foreign national lines. In fact, it is unquestionably true to say that the foreign air companies have cast covetous eyes on the British Empire mails and have shaped their policy to secure a share of them. The new plan of the Government will at any rate remove any need for Dominion or Colonial Governments even to consider the dispatch of British mails to the Empire territories by foreign air services. Imperial Airways operates its services at a speed which was, until recently, the most economical one. Aero nautical developments of recent years have increased the optimum economic speed, but unless one is able to accelerate obsolescence—i.e., unless one is in a financial position to write off the fleet at a quicker rate—one must use the aircraft already in service for their full budgeted life. It would be fatally easy to be persuaded into buying aircraft which would have a high cruising speed, but which would not be either suitable for the peculiar conditions of the services of Imperial Airways or which would prove to be uneconomical in operation. The problem of speed is purely economic. The Eastern and African lines will not stand high rates and fares, and therefore cannot carry a high speed economically—I believe I am right in saying that there is no ship operating these lines at over 20 knots, and they are worked mostly at about 16 knots, whereas, for example, the Atlantic, even before it became a field of competition for national prestige, could stand much higher speeds. We desire to operate our services at the highest speed that economic considerations permit, but if foreign competition sets the pace with uneconomic speeds, I do not doubt for one moment this country's ability to meet it adequately. To be continued. LONDON—OSTEND — LE ZOUTE SERVICE The Belgian Air Lines (S.A.B.E.N.A.), for which company Imperial Airways acts as the General Agents in Great Britain, opened their service between London, Ostend and Le Zoute on 29 June instead of 5 July according to their current timetable. • &lt; 1 j S.A.B.E.N.A. has its own staff stationed at Ostend and Le Zoute until 15 September so that all bookings should be addressed to these places direct and not to Brussels as formerly. QUARANTINE REGULATIONS FOR PASSENGERS PROCEEDING TO AUSTRALIA We wish to draw the attention of our Agents to the Quarantine Regulations for Australia as we have been advised that there have been two instances recently where passengers have arrived in Australia and have been unable to produce the prescribed certificate to prove that they had been vaccinated within three years before arrival. Any person who fails to produce such a certificate will be compulsorily vaccinated at Darwin before being allowed to proceed. • • u- u Visitors in Australia are also obliged to report to the Chief Quarantine Officer in the State or territory, in which they then are, any sickness which they suffer within eighteen days after departure of the aircraft from the last landing place outside Australia, that is Koepang. • 1 • 1 Non-compliance with these regulations incurs liability to penalties not exceeding £50 for which Imperial yVays and its associated companies can in no way be held responsible. NEW FACILITY FOR PASSENGERS IN ALEXANDRIA Through the courtesy of the proprietors of the Albert Metzgers hotels. Imperial Airways' passengers in transit through Alexandria are allowed to dine at the Casino San Stefano and to go into the Cabaret and Dance without any additional charge. A private bathing beach is also available. Eull particulars as to transport and so forth may be obtained from Imperial Airways' Bureau in the Cecil Hotel, Alexandria.4 CLIMATE AND TOURIST SEASON April to November : Hot. December to March : Warm with exhilarating breezes. Both seasons : Dry, with chilly nights in winter. The tourist season is from November to March inclusive. HOTELS Winter Palace (closed from mid-April to mid-November). The Luxor (open throughout the year). Savoy (closed from May to September inclusive). THE TOWN, ANTIQUITIES IN THE NEIGHBOURHOOD Luxor is the principal tourist centre in Upper Egypt. It is situated on the east bank of the Nile in a fertile district. East and West of the river valley are ranges of hills. Sport includes riding, sailing on the Nile in feluccas (native boats), and during the season camel and donkey gymkhanas. The chief interests of Luxor are the antiquities in the district. Luxor is so rich in these that it is not possible to mention all of them here, and only the more important have been described below. On visits to these, halts may be made at other places of lesser interest. THE TEMPLE OF LUXOR (situated immediately south of Luxor) This Temple was built by Amenophis III (1411-1375 B.C.) and was dedicated to Amun, the Sun God, his wife Mut, and their son, the Moon God Khons. Ramses II (1292-1225 B.C.) constructed a colonnaded court in the front of the Temple, and a massive pylon. Six colossal statues of Ramses II (two sitting and four standing) were situated in front of the Pylon. Only two sitting and one standing remain in position to-day. The Temple now contains the Mosque of Abu '1 Haggag, a saint of Luxor. f THE TEMPLES OF KARNAK (One mile north of Luxor) THE GREAT TEMPLE OF AMUN (the Sun God) The foundation of this temple was during the second century B.C. Most of the Pharaohs took some part in its building and enlargement. The Great Hypostyle Hall, one of the most wonderful pieces of Egyptian archi tecture, probably left in an unfinished condition by Amenophis HI, was completed by Sethos I and Ramses H. Very successful excavations have here been undertaken by the Egyptian Department of Antiquities. From the top of the first Pylon in the Temple, over 140 feet high, a beautiful view of the surrounding landscape may be obtained. GUIDE TO IMPERIAL AIRWAYS' AFRICA ROUTE For the guidance of our agents, readers and potential travellers, we have prepared a series of notes on each stopping place along the Africa and India and Eastern routes. The first section of these notes covers the Africa route. Notes on Alexandria, Cairo and Assiut have already appeared and we continue with Luxor. LUXOR 2,737 miles from London, 5,167 from Cape Town. 235 feet above sea level. HISTORY Luxor is built near the site of ancient Thebes, the origin of which is uncertain. rn The Egyptian name for the city was Weset or Newt, ' The city.' The name of The Tem P le 0 f Q ueen 'otshepsu ot Thebes Thebes was bestowed by the Greeks. ' Luxor' is from the Arabic, ' El-Qusur,' and means * the castles,' having reference to the extensive temples of Luxor. It is known that was the capital of a' nome 'or district of ancient Egypt in the 6th Dynasty (2420-2270 B.C.), and as such was ruled by its own princes. In the period of the Middle Empire (2100-1700 B.C.) the princes of the nome of Thebes extended their power, and united the whole of Egypt under their rule. Thebes was the capital city, and was famous also for the worship of the deity Amun, the Sun God of Karnak. Thebes became the favourite seat of the Pharaohs, and an oriental metropolis. Under the Princes of the 21st Dynasty, the Royal residence was transferred from Thebes to the Delta in the north, but Thebes, with a large part of Upper Egypt, formed a distinct political entity governed by the High Priests of Amun. Thebes subsequently suffered from Ethiopian and Assyrian attacks, and in the time of Alexander the Great and the Ptolemies the city was decadent. Despite several rebellions, Thebes was unable to preserve its independence and became economically and politically weakened. Owing to conquests, many of its buildings were ruined, and their decay was aided by the overflowing of the Nile. By the beginning of the first century A.D. Thebes had sunk to a place of insignificance. The work of destruction of the buildings in the ancient city was continued in the time of Theodosius I (A.D. 379-395) by the Christians who built churches and dwelling-houses in the temple halls, using blocks and slabs of stone from the old monuments. Luxor has become to-day the chief tourist centre of Upper Egypt.5 IMPERIAL AIRWAY S gazette SACRED LAKE Situated south of the Great Temple of Amun. The water is saline. On the north bank is a giant Scarabaeus (beetle), dedicated to a Sun God, Atum Khepre, who was pictured in that form. CONNECTING BUILDINGS BETWEEN THE TEMPLE OF AMUN AND THE TEMPLE OF MUT These include a series of Pylons and the Avenue of Sphinxes, the latter built by Haremhab (1350-1315 B.C.). TEMPLE OF MUT (Wife of Amun) Built by Amenophis III (1411-1375 B.C.). It consists of a gate and two courts, one of which contains colossal statues of Amenophis III. Beyond the Temple, to the south, is another sacred lake. Other interesting temples are those of Khons, the Moon God, Epet, the Hippopotamus God, and Ptah, the Patron God of Memphis. THE WEST BANK AT THEBES (By ferry boat and then by car. All the remains are within a radius of between three and five miles of Luxor, but it is recommended that a day's excursion be made on the west bank, when a complete tour may be made.) The west bank was the burial place or Necropolis of Ancient Thebes, and in connexion with the work of burial a city grew up here in the time of the new Empire (1555-712 B.C.). The most interesting antiquities are as follows :— THE TOMBS OF THE KINGS TJj ^ j tombs date from the iSth-aoth Dynasties. The structure of all is very similar ; corridors led into the in -jrs, and from these there were chambers and recesses for the tomb furniture. At the end of these corridors was an anteroom, and then the main hall, where lay the sarcophagus. The walls of the tombs were covered with texts and pictures, illustrating, for purposes of instruction, the forthcoming journey to the underworld. Sixty-one tombs are known in the valley, of which seventeen are accessible. The most interesting are those of Ramses VI, Menephtes, Amenophis II, Sethos I, and Tutankhamun. GREAT TEMPLE OF DEIR-EL-BAHARI, BUILT BY QUEEN HATSHEPSU This temple lies in a great semi-circular basin in the rocks. It dates from the beginning of the New Empire, and was built by Queen Hatshepsu, the co-regent of Thutmosis III. The temple was mutilated by Thutmosis III, on his expelling Hatshepsu from the throne, and, after her return, upon her death. Under Ramses II and later Euergates II some restorations were undertaken. The temple was originally dedicated to Amun (the Sun God), but there were also chapels devoted to the worship of Hathor, Goddess of Joy and Love, Anubis, God of the Dead, and to the worship of Queen Hatshepsu. On the introduction of Christianity, a community of monks was established in the Temple—the name ' Deir- el-Bahari ' is due to this, being the Arabic for ' northern territory.' The Temple is constructed in three terraces, connected by inclined planes. The stages were cut out of the slopes of the hill which backs it. THE RAMASSEUM A large mortuary temple built by Ramses II, and dedicated to Amun. THE COLOSSI OF MEMNON These two famous statues are nearly 7° f ee ^ high. They were built nearly 2,000 years before Christ, and once flanked the entrance to the mortuary temple of Amenhotep III. The northern Colossus, in the time of the Roman Empire, was said to give out a musical note at sunrise. MORTUARY TEMPLE OF SETHOS Built by Sethos I (1313-1292), and devoted to the worship of his father Ramses I. Ramses II embellished this temple with very beautiful reliefs. IMPERIAL AIRWAYS* SERVICES TO LUXOR There are two services a week by Imperial Airways to Luxor, leaving London on Wednesdays and Sundays, and arriving at Luxor on Saturdays and Wednesdays, a journey of three days. TRAVEL CONNEXIONS FROM LUXOR By air : Imperial Airways. Two services a week between Luxor and England. Services leave Luxor for the Sudan, East Africa and South Africa (Johannesburg) on Saturdays and \\ ednesdays, the service which leaves Luxor on Saturdays continuing to Cape Town. FARE CONCESSIONS TO MEMBERS OF FLYING CLUBS Imperial Airways (in common with certain other Air Transport Operators) has for some years allowed certain rebates to members of Flying Clubs. Introduced with the dual object of inducing the public to use Air Transport and of aiding Clubs to attract new nv pers, these concessions, at the time that they were granted, served a useful purpose. Oi .ecent years, however, the whole aspect of the matter has changed ; in many instances membership of Flying Clubs has been taken out for no other object than to secure rebates which exceed the Club subscription. The whole object of the original concession has therefore been rendered nugatory, and we, as an Air I ransport Company, have suffered a loss without any corresponding benefit being gained by the Flying Club. The rebate on a single journey from London to Nairobi was enough to cover five subscriptions to some Clubs, and great difficulties were also introduced on Continental journeys particularly where foreign services were involved. It was with regret, therefore, that after full consideration Imperial Airways has decided that it will be necessary for these rebates to be withdrawn. As from 1 July 1935, rebates ceased to be available to Members of all Fly ing Clubs and similar organisations.mperial airways gazette MPERIAL AIRWAYS GAZETTE Changes in the East The Imperial Airways Gazette is published every month for the information of the Agents of the C ompan\ and for others who are interested in air transport. A copy will be sent free of charge every month to any ona fide applicant from the Publicity Manager's Office, Imperial Airways, Ltd., Airways House, Charles btreet, London, S.W.i. _ , , o u i • ♦ School children must make their application through their Schoolmaster or schoolmistress. . . Full information about the services of Imperial Airways may be obtained from the orhces ot the pnncipa travel agents, or from Imperial Airways Ltd., Airway Terminus, Victoria Station, S.W.i, or rrom Ain\a&gt;s House, Charles Street, S.W.i. Telephone, Victoria 2211. Telegrams Imparhm, London. Airways Terminus is open day and night. _. • ■ d Details of all the services of Imperial Airways and other Air Transport Companies are given in Bradshaw s International Air Guide, which is published every month and may be bought from any newsagent in the United Kingdom, price is., or from the Proprietors at 5 Surrey Street, Strand, London, W.C.2. AS OTHERS SEE US We have received the following tribute to the ambulance section of our Special Charter service from a member of the Nurses'Co-operation of Portland Place:— . ■ . uu 'I feel I must write you a personal letter to thank you for all the trouble you have taken in connexion \\ ith my patient on my recent journey from Croydon. , , , • j ' It would be difficult to express our grateful feelings for the comfort and the courtesy we experienced. ' I want particularly to say that, strange as it may sound, my patient arrived in Edinburgh trom Biarntz (1,000 miles journey done in record time) feeling actually better than when we started. I his should be a great recommendation for air travel when expediency and comfort are essential. THE SUEZ CANAL OF THE AIR We reproduce with acknowledgment to The Times excerpts from a series of articles by Mr. Arthur Moore on the changes which have taken place during the last few years along the Iranian Gulf. ' We left Karachi aboard the long, comfortable biplane Hadrian and new to the north-west up the coast of Baluchistan. Two halts were made on the eastern shore ; one at Gwadar (which belongs to the friendly Sultan of Muscat far across'the water), a lonely spot where Imperial Airways maintains a little post ; the other at Jiwani, an even lonelier desert landing ground. But the Hadrian, the Hannibal, and other heroes drink enormous quantities of petrol, and since they may not fly up the Persian coast, they must have a last drink before they swing just east of the Iranian frontier out over the Gulf of Oman to the Arab coast. Hence a petrol dump at Jiwani; just that and nothing more, except a little knot of light-hearted Baluchis, men, women, and laughing children. ' The men bundle the petrol tins along to be pumped into the thirsty 'plane, while the women and children squat and peep by the side of the shack where the tins are stored. Camels bring fresh supplies from Gwadar, where the B.I. ships land it. When Hadrian had had his fill the Second Officer walked away with the last tin and sprinkled the remaining contents over the desert. 'We ,^ a have to do that,' he explained. 'We used to give it to the tribesmen, but they did not understand its inflamma- bilitv and got themselves into lots of trouble. They used to fling it on their fires, and set themselves ablaze. ' Soon we were cruising over the clear, sunshot depths of the Gulf, where the colours vary with the sand and sea weed that make the floor turn from pale blue to violet, mauve, and dark purple. Great rays (stinging fish), that looked as if they must measure several feet across, were constantly to be seen, and one envied passenger saw a shark. Luncheon was served in the air after leaving Jiwani. Surely this is the ideal way to travel home, thought, as I munched an excellent prawn cutlet and looked down in comfort on the blue below. THE SHEIKH AT HOME • It is past history now, but the fort arose out of a spot of trouble over the choice of a landing ground. 1 here was talk of having it at Dibai, which lies a short way to the south along the coast. But the Sheikh of Dibai was not in a hurry whereas Imperial Airways was anxious to get on with the good work, and the bheikh ot bharjah came to terms. It is said that his brother sheikhs accuse him of indecent haste and of letting down the semi-royal equivalent of the trade union of the Trucial Coast. The pearl industry has suffered heavily from the world depression and the Japanese cultured pearl, but the airport has brought much money, artesian wells, and regu ar mails to Shaijah, so that envious eyes are cast upon it. Every sheikhdom would like to be a port ot call. 1 here Miles 0 m m 300 4 00 Kemnan ( ^ ^ -wi ooas o k. ^ dam fur i .O' 'in-: -- Tc Karachi The route of Imperial Airways along the Iranian Gulf —or as it is more familiarly known—the Persian Gulfimperial airways gazette Sheikh of Sharjah's Guard were loc-d mutterings of war from Dibai when the first manna began to drop from the sky upon Sharjah. But now there is peace. ' An invitation from the Sheikh to call upon him awaited me. An officer of Imperial Airways accompanied me, and in wicker chairs on a motor-truck we drove through the barbed wire to the Arab town. In front of his house the Sheikh met us, surrounded by members of his family and decorative guards, armed with enough picturesque swords and daggers to satisfy anyone. The Sheikh himself wore a great gold-hilted curving sword, as do most of his order. He is a fine Arab gentleman with a frank, pleasing countenance and most hospitable manners. Leading us through a court to an inner room, he introduced his young son, entertained us in Arab style, and discussed the affairs of the day. ' Though there is peace between the sheikhs, desert precautions are still taken, and I noticed that the outer door was shut fast after we entered and had to be unbarred again at our departure. It was the sunset hour. The Arabs who came out with us stepped on a little eminence in front of the Sheikh's house, and, turning towards Mecca, knelt to pray, as we rumbled off in our truck to the fort . . . ' At Bahrein, which is a morning's flight of 284 miles from Sharjah, I left the Hadrian, or rather it left me. I spent three days on the sometimes delectable island. This was one of the delectable times, and for the information of those who meditate a visit to a place of rapidly increasing importance let me say that in March and April Bahrein is still cool. Indeed on all sides 1 heap! the remark that the climate of the Gulf is changing, that the winters are milder, and that the hot wr^^Nr sets in later than of old. I did not once wear any of the summer kit for which I had made unwilling provision in the exiguous luggage that the air traveller packs. ' Bahrein is clearly on the upgrade. Let me enumerate its blessings. Sheikh Hamed bin Isa al Khalifah, whom with two of his brothers I met during my stay, has been in power 10 years and is a most progressive ruler. He has in Mr. Belgrave, formerly of the Sudan Service, an admirable Minister—Minister for progress, so to speak—and as the local branch of the Eastern Bank acts as an accounts department, the whole administration of what is really a little group of islands costs very little. The Budget balances and there is money for roads, schools, hospitals, public gardens, and for the appurtenances of an efficient municipality, supervised fish and meat markets, bazaars that have the spicy smells of Araby and the picturesque medley of copper, brass, leather, and old brass-bound and highly ornamented chests which the craftsmen of Asia continue to produce in inexhaustible quantities .... OUT OF FASHION ' Such things, like the pearling industry, the date gardens, the plentiful springs, and new artesian wells, con tribute to the mingling of old and new in Bahrein. Modernity, coming with a rush, is more largely represented by air, oil, and the British Navy. ' For Great Britain, now that Persia has resumed her proper position on the other side of the Gulf, the Arab coast has become all important; and Bahrein is the chief centre on that coast. The Gulf is becoming, as it were, the Suez Canal of the air, an essential channel of communication with India, Singapore, and Australia. From Koweit round to Aden every sheikh has a treaty of friendship with Great Britain. Difficulties with the Persian Government regarding commercial air services have resulted at the moment in total prohibition for Imperial Airways. The Arab sheikhs, on the other hand, show for aeroplanes the zeal they entertain for motor-cars. They send their pearls for sale by air, and use only the air mail. They clamour for airports, artesian wells, post offices, and what not .... ' Manama—it is pronounced to rhyme with Panama—is the main island of Bahrein. The civil aerodrome is on the adjacent small island of Muharraq and is probably the largest in the world, being just an enormous expanse of safe, hard earth.' DISTINGUISHED TRAVELLERS Since the last issue of the Gazette, many distinguished people have used the services of Imperial Airways and we reproduce photographs of some of them. CONCESSIONS ON 4 4 t FARES -BRUSSELS, I2TH INTERNATIONAL PHARMACY CONGRESS- 30 JULY TO 6 AUGUST In conjunction with the Belgian Air Lines (S. A.B.E.N. A.), for which company Imperial Airways acts as the General Agents in Great Britain, we have agreed to allow a 10 per cent, rebate on both single and return fares for delegates attending this Congress in Brussels. The period of validity will be, on the outward journey, between 27 July and 5 August, and on the inward journey between 30 July and 8 August. LEIPZIG AUTUMN FAIR Wp ^ve also agreed, in conjunction w ith the Belgian Air Lines and Cesko- sK skd Leteckd Spolecnost of Prague, to grant a 10 per cent, rebate on published single and return fares to passengers proceeding to the Leipzig Autumn Fair. Signed air travel vouchers, obtainable from the Organizers of the Fair, must be presented at the time of booking for in the absence of a voucher no rebate will be granted. The rebate applies on the journey London-Prague between 27 August and 7 September and on the journey Prague-London between 31 August and 12 September. The Sultan of Muscat who flew from Gwadar to Karachi recently M. Lucien Robert (left) and H. C. Bouillon, the trainer and jockey of the famous French racehorse ' Brantome ' photographed just before leaving for London by Imperial AirwaysI No.lO^Uj Politico! Agency, Bahrain, April 29, 193C-. To *he Kabtcrn Bank Limited^ B A. F ^ A T N , Oentleraen, I should he glad if you would he good enough to furnith me with a certificate, in duplicate, on the Ibt of every month bhowing the credit balance on the la&amp;t working day of every preceding month in the Treeeury Account thie Agency, v our8 faithfully, A f 7A Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain. Crft-# /l^ 1 Res. P. G. 32. No. u7o of 19^7 rr British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, the ^ / ^ j UT)e ^ 19 37 A oopy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to :— The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain, 1 ^ The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty's Consul, Bunder Abbas, His Majesty's Consul, Kerman, Hie Majesty 's Vice-Consul, SfetofiBftk' Fhorramflhahr . for information and guidance with reference to this office endorsement No. , dated the 19 By order, for Secretary to the tit/cal Resident in the Persian Gulf. Notification Fo.3, dated Kew Delhi the 1st April, 1937, from the Office of the Secretary to the Opvemor-Creners 1. Letter from tne Government of India in the Dep? )epartment No. , dated the 19 (Received with Foreign and Political- Department endorsement No. , dated the 19 .) GIPD—190 Poll. Hes. 'Bushire—25-8-33—3,000.y or-ft (w 0? tft? seorllltakt to th1? governor -gwrbal. Notlfi cntloTi. Few Delhi, the 1st April, 1937. No. 5. Tti supercesslon of all previous orders on tbe subject, His Excellency the viceroy Is pleased to permit the title • , Ho , nou^a'ble ,, to 'be home during their term of office hy the following officers in Indlat- (1 (2 (3 (4 (5 (6 ((7 f 9 ^he Members of the Governor-Gen er a 1* s '^Tecntive Council. The President of the Oouncil of State. The President of the Indian Legislative Assembly. The Hhief Justice and Judges of tbe federal Court. 'Hie Chief Justices and Puisne Judges of Chaptered High Courts. The Governors* Ministers in the Provinces. Residents of tbe 1st class. 'Hie Presidents of Provincial Tjegislatlve Councils, ^he Speakers of nrovlncial Tjegislatlve Assemblies. i (lo) The ^lef Judge find Judges of the Chief Court of Oudh. r ll &gt; Members of the Council of State. J.Cr. LAITHWAITB. Secretary to the Governor-General. A\ Copy forwarded to T ^is Britannic 1 a t 1esty , s Consul General, '^ushire, 'Iran) for information.wo. l jLfU 15/14-TT dated tbe 16August, 1937. To ^h© Political Apent, Bahrain. vemo^a^autn « T am directed to invite your attention to this office circular ^o. 175, dated the 26th January, 1935, r^^ardln^ despatch of confidential and non-confi' dential correspondence for this Residency and to observe that instructions contained therein have not 'been carried out properly by your office. Will you, therefore, please see that in future the instructions are adhered to. 'By C^der, Secretary tp/tt^eFolitj, era 1 Resident in the Ppr^lan Gulf./')/■ OIHCTOAH Ho. 1851 18/14 3epteBt)«r gsrfl 19! (S copies) - His Majesty*® Ocmsul-General for Khora8fm 9 Hfished Polltleal Agent, Viiscat. y Political Agent, Babralti. ^ Political A«ent f Ktnralt. - Kls Fajesty 'a Ootisu I, FermaTt His Majesty's Vlce-OoTistJl, Khorramshahr^ 1^2^ To enable this office to have at all tlwi^ Information of the sorenenta of the aexahers of the Persian Gtflf Olerleal Oaflre ( 'both English anfl Vemact sections) it Is requested that officers oonoemed shouia ItiTarlahly furnish this office with a report or the following lines whenerer any change in the Inounhency of a post under their Jurl8aictlon t ocoiirsi* (l) Name of the cleric relieved. (s) Name of relief, (5) Dste of handing and taking over, (4) jPerlod talren as Joining tine, (5) Authority for the change (d) Leave or Transfer. ( If leavettbe nature and period should he given.) By Order, Hfcc^etpry to the Political Reslden In the Persian Gulf.to no,900-8 of 1^37. British Resiaency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 30tn December 1937. The Political Agent, Kuwait, pSThe Political Agent, Banrain, The Political Agent, Muscat, r.ub.lect : Supply of spare copies. M'.-mornnaaa. As there have been several instances recently of papers being received without spare copies, or with o.n inadequate number of spare copies, attention is invitua to Residency memoranaum No,G36-s, aattd the lOtn June ldo3. /f-Ui. So. T, C, Fowle, Political Kesiaent in the Persian Gulf. kiiisihv* j for Secretary to the Political Kesident^ln tne Persian Gulf.\0 Semi Officir.l Telegram ^ T o. 05 d: . d - ei -^ j fi;ci;. the Political ^.osiclent, Bushire. i Telegrams betv/een (?) ( a ) Political Agent, Bahrain and myself and (b) Senior ^ T aval Officer Persian ^ulf Division and myself will have to. pass through T ' T uscat and be addressed to ■ Political Agent, . 2. Telegrams ( a) in both directions with group BALA!'. A Telegrams ( b) in both directions wil] begin with group SODE1T• 3. Telegrams ( a) and ( b) to Bushire will be rebooked by cable and tireless Ltd., T,r 'iscat showing office of origin as Muscat# 4. Purpose C ?) o^ above indicating groups is that officer in charge of Cable and /ireless TTuscat in r.i in rr -i r. -.r-- 1 &gt; can automatically without reference to thi. Political Agent, and in his absence, rebook telegrams. . Political A.gent TT uscat should e xp la in to this officer and ask him to comply. Manager Karachi is being informed. 5. As Persian Telegraph office at Bushire may impose restric- ions at any moment above procedure should be brought into force forthwith. - Fowle-CIRC11L &gt;K HO. M l . dated U* Mey^ 1938* HI 5 Political Agent, Muscat, The Political J Agent, Bahrain, The Folitical Agent, Kuweit, His Majesty 's Consul, Bunder Abbas, His Majesty's Consul, Kero^n, His Majesty's Vice-consul, KhorraiLShahr Th# Honourable the Political Reeident in the Persian Gulf wishes to remind oflicers proceeding on leeve to remember to intimate previoixsly their addresses while on leare, to Bushire. Order in the Persian Gulf.i I f Telegram »»Q' From Political Resident, Bushire, on s.s. v arsova # To Secretary to Political Resident, Bushire. Copy given to Political Agent, Bahrain. No. T/1S5 Dated 18th June 1938. Until Bushire Muscat cable conununication is restored telegrams exchanged between ^ushire and Bahrain should be addressed to British Consul, Basra, * who will relay them. Same indicating prefix should be used. - FOWLE - M ✓^Copy for E.O. v o &gt;tf (r-■ — V Printed in England. (Sept. 1985.) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (Message Forms 5/- 171.) AJV/O- X vJI -^^V .. i*. V w P(-W). MARK YOUR REPLY 13' No enquiry respecting this Telegram can be attended to without the production of this Copy.No.O.T.Vo ' 1V92-1I The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Kesid'ent to the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Politioal \gent - Muscat, y The Political Agent - Bahrain, The Political Agent - Kuwait, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents^ for inf oroiat ion and guidance. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. VvA rri Dated.. Dec.e roJae.r., ..^3 8. Reference to previous correspondence Description of Euclnsure, Name and Date. Letter from the Secretary to the Governor General (Public) to the Secretaries to Gover nors, .No.7/;d/38-G. G., dated the 10th October, 1958 and enclosures• (Received with endorsement Vo. i'.Gll-G/SS, dated the Ist December, 193 8, from the Govern- ment of India in the External Affairs Department) Subject. Loyal and congratulatory messages to His Majesty the King iSmperor w rNo. 7I2I38-G.G. OFFICE OF THE SECRETARY TO THE GOVERNOR GENERAL (PUBLIC). F rom T he H onourable M r . J. A. THORNE, C.S.I., C.I.E., I.C.S., Secretary to the Governor-General {Public), To T he SECRETARY to HIS EXCELLENCY the GOVERNOR of MADRAS. T he SECRETARY to HIS EXCELLENCY the GOVERNOR of BOMBAY. T he SECRETARY to HIS EXCELLENCY the GOVERNOR of BENGAL. T he SECRETARY to HIS EXCELLENCY the GOVERNOR of the UNITED PROVINCES. T he SECRETARY to HIS EXCELLENCY the GOVERNOR of the PUNJAB. T he SECRETARY to HIS EXCELLENCY the GOVERNOR of BIHAR. T he SECRETARY to HIS EXCELLENCY the GOVERNOR of the CENTRAL PROVINCES and BERAR. T he SECRETARY to HIS EXCELLENCY the GOVERNOR of ASSAM. T he SECRETARY to HIS EXCELLENCY the GOVERNOR of the NORTH-WEST FRONTIER PROVINCE. T he SECRETARY to HIS EXCELLENCY the GOVERNOR of ORISSA. Twi SECRETARY to HIS EXCELLENCY the GOVERNOR of SIND. « Simla, the 10th October 1938. S ubject -.—Acknowledgment of loyal and congratulatory messages to His Family ^ Emperor and other Members of the Royal S ir, I am directed to address you on the subject noted above. at . 2 - M ® ssa i ^ s of a purely personal and private nature addrp^pd +n TTie dozt Z ^ ment circular letter no. P. 96 (2)-H.|31, dated the 14th April 1932 (copy eneffl)!M 2 It will be observed from the Memorandum that on several occasions snch messages are required to be acknowledged in India, The form of acknowledg ment, whether provisional or final, is however left to the discretion of the authorities in India. In the absence of standard forms, occasions have occurred in the past when messages have not been acknowledged in altogether suitable terms. His Majesty has expressed his desire that such loyal messages should be adequately and promptly acknowledged, and accordingly it is proposed that messages received from persons residing in the Province of M ^ ras&gt; - ^ ehould in future be dealt with in your Office instead of the Provincial Ministerial Sec retariat, and acknowledged in accordance with the instructions enclosed, the acknowledgment being headed ' Government House 3. I am to request, that with the permission of His Excellency the Governor, these instructions may be observed in future, and that all messages intended for transmission to the India Office should be forwarded to this Office and not to the Government of India. I have the honour to be, S ir, Your most obedient servant, J. A. THORNE, Secretary to the Governor General (Public)^ No. 7|2|38-G.G. A copy is forwarded to the— Chief Commissioner of Coorg, Chief Commissioner of Delhi, Chief Commissioner of Andaman and Nicobar Islands, Chief Commissioner of Ajmer-Merwara, Chief Commissioner of Panth-Piploda, Hoirble the Agent to the Governor-General, Resident and Chief Commis sioner in Baluchistan, with the request that the instructions contained therein may be followed mutatis ftiuiavidis in respect of messages received by him. No. 7|2|38-G.G. inform ^ forwarded to the Private Secretary to H. E. the Viceroy, for No. 7|2|38 -G.O. A copy is forwarded to the Political and Defence Departments, for informa- tion j and necessary action] t(in continuation of the endorsement from the late P. and P. Department no. F. 96 (2)-H.|31, dated the 14th April 1932). By order, J. A. THORNE, Secretary to the Governor General {Public)~ j 1o the Political Department, f ( ) To Defence Department only.Instructions for acknowledging loyal and congratulatory messages to His Majesty the King Emperor and other Members of the Royal Family. 1?^! messages forwarded by the India Office for suitable acknow- following form- should be acknowledged as nearly as possible in the His Lx'celloricy the Governor has received the commands of the King-Jumper or to convey to Mr Imperial Majesty's appreciation of the ioyal sentiments'to'which s loiter or gives expression.' 5.—Provisional acknowledgments should be worded as follows 44 The Secretary to the Governor i s directed to acknowledge he receipt ot the loyal message addressed to the King-Emperor by. •••.•*; aild ^ inform him that it will be torwarded for submission to His Imperial Majesty forthwith.' C. Messages from persons classed in the Memorandum of 1932 as &lt; mi- fl ?o^p an n, iT{; en address ® d to f/ 1 authority in India are acknowledged in India . ; (l tlle names only ot the senders are communicated to the India Office which transmits them to Buckingham Palace with the remark that thev have ' HiS S^! llen 7 the 5 overnor desires to acknowledge the message from Mr which will be for ^ a e r( Jed submission to the King-Emperor forthwith. Mr. may be assured of His Imperial Majesty's appreciation of the loyal sentiments (greetings) to which it gives expression.' r „ raessaees 8 from a ^nowledgment would not be suitable, t&gt; i* messages iiom Kulmg Chiefs under 11 guns, messages «?pnt on hp&gt;ialf Kulmg 1 nnces of eleven guns or over, important Committees and Associations an acknowledgment based on the terms of the form in ' A ' above mav be embodied m a signed letter from the appropriate authority. r p^lph % « m b&gt; randum of 193J. As stated in naraoTAnli (1 ^ (^\ nf it i ^ i tlie ilemo- K-ir xt ' i ■ li? i apn (J.) (c) of that Memorandum, such messages are {in&lt;5WPTv&gt;f? 1? I k 7 hlinSeIf ' ^ a personal message of thanks si^ed ' SrR I ' statiW that he has been commanded to transmit the message to the sender. * g l349hd—275—8-10-38—gipsLetter feom the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, to the Secretary to the Government of Bombay^ Political Department ; the Chief Secretary to the Government of Bengal ; the Chief Secretary to the Government of the United Provinces ; the Chief Secretary to the Government of Assam ; the Hon'ble the Resident at Hyderabad , ihe Hon ble ihe* Ivesident in Mysore ; the Hon'ble the Agent to the Governor-General in Central India ; the Hon'ble the Agent to the Governor-General in Rajputa'na ; the Hon'ble the Agent to the Governor-General and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan ; the Hon'ble the Chief Commissioner and Agent to Governor-General, North-West Frontier Province ; the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ; the Hon'ble the Agent to the Governor-General in tefe States of Western India ; the Hon 'ble the Agent to the Governor-General, Punjab States ; the Resident at Baroda ; the Resident in Kashmir ; the Resident AT GwALIOR j THE POLITICAL OFFICER IN SlKKIM ; THE AgENT TO THE GoVERNOR- General, Madras States, no . F. 96 (2)-11.131, dated Simla, the 14th April 1932. In continuation of letter from the Government of India in the Foremi and Political Department, no. F. 96-H.|30, dated the 11th May 1931, I am directed to enclose a copy of a memorandum received from His Majesty's Secretarv of State for India setting forth the procedure as finally approved for dealino- with messages of a purely personal and private nature addressed to His Majesty the King, and to say that this will supersede the rules and instructions at present in force in India for the transmission and acknowledgment of such messages. 2. I am to request that (with the permission of the Governor in Council) the revised procedure may kindly be adopted forthwith. Copy of the foregoing letter with enclosure is forwarded to the Home and Army Departments and to the Chief Secretaries to the Governments of Madras Punjab, Burma, Bihar and Orissa and the Central Provinces and the British Envoy at the Court of Nepal, for information, [in continuation of endorsement from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department no F H.|30, dated the 11th May 1931.] ( ) To local Grovernments only. | Not to Home and Army Departments.Memoba'ndum regarding the method oe dealing with messages oe a purely personal and private nature addressed to HlS majesty. (1) (a) When messages signed by the following are addressed direct to Buckingham Palace the replies will be issued from Buckingham Palace and will be signed in the name of the King :— The V iceroy. Governors of Provinces. The Commander-in-Ohief in India. Euling Princes of 11 guns or over. The Prime Minister of Nepal. The Aga Khan. The Chamber of Princes or its Standing Committee. The Presidents of the Legislative Assembly and Provincial L.egislative Councils. The President of the Council of State. Officers Commanding Regiments and Battalions with which the King is associated. (h) When such messages signed by an}^ of the above are addressed direct to the India Office, they will be at once transmitted to Buckingham Palace where they will be dealt with as under (a). (c) When telegrams signed by any of the above are addressed to local officers or to the Government of India, they will be treated as follows. The local officers will at once telegraph the list of names of senders to the Viceroy. These lists, together with the names of any who have addressed messages direct to him, will be telegraphed personally by the Viceroy to Buckinsrham Palace. After 24 hours have elapsed the Viceroy will telegraph to the senders a personal message of thanks signed George R.' T. which he will state he has been commanded to Iransmit to them. The India Office will subsequently receive the texts of all telegraphic messages from the Government of India and communicate them to the Palace. (d) When letters signed by any of the above, other than His Exalted Highness the Xizam, or oral messages are addressed to the local officers or the (rovernment of India, they will be provisionally acknowledged and forwarded through the Government of India and India Office to Buckingham Palace. 1 hey will then be acknowledged by His Majesty's Private Secretary direct to the senders. (e) When letters signed by His Exalted Highness the Nizam are addressed to the Resident or the Government of India, they will be provisionallv acknow ledged and forwarded through the Government of India and India Office to Buckingham Palace to be dealt with as under (a). 2. When messages from individuals (other than those referred to aboveV who are personally known to His Majesty are addressed to Buckingham Palace they will be dealt with as under {a). 3. When messages by telegraph or otherwise sent on behalf of anv of the above or trom any of the following are sent direct to Buckingham' Palace viz. :— ^ ' Ruling Chiefs under 11 guns, Darbars, Abdicated Ruling Princes, Committees, Associations, etc. Individuals not known to His Majesty, li'* ' )( ail ' s ™i^e ( i to the India Office and acknowledged bv letter through the Government of India. ^ ^ 64. When messages by telegraph or otherwise sent on behalf of'any of those mentioned in (a) above, or by any of those mentioned in 3 above are addressed to the India Office, they will be transmitted to Buckingham Palace and acknowledged by letter through the Government of India after they have been laid before His Majesty. In unimportant cases they will be acknowledged at once and only the names of the senders transmitted to Buckingham Palace for information. 5. When messages by telegraph or otherwise sent on behalf of any of those mentioned in (a) above, or by any of those mentioned in 3 above are addressed to the local officers or the Government of India, they will be at once provi sionally acknowledged by letter, and forwarded by letter through the Govern ment of India and the India Office to Buckingham Palace : after they have been laid before His Majesty they will be further acknowledged by letter through the India Office and the Government of India. In unimportant cases the Government of India will forward only the names of the senders to be transmitted to Buckingham Palace and no further acknowledgment will be sent. f I i— 21 fy ~ 12 10-38—GIP8No. -13/92. v-' £ &lt;,^he 1 &gt;7 {&lt;li The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident id the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political /igent - Muscat The political Agent - Bahrain The Political Agent - Ku-ait and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. for inforica tion. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. .IXth. J a .nuaxy.».. 193 9. Reference to previous correspondence: Buehire printed letter »o.^10-13/92-11. of 22nd December, 1938, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Memorandum ITo. J.611-G/36, dated the 17th Decembe r 9 1938, from the Goyernment of India in the External Affairs De- pa rtment • Acknowledgment of loyal and congratulatory messages to His Majesty the King Bmperor and other Members of the Royal family.Ho. ■S'S' Dated the 13 tn January, 193 9, To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memoranduirj .ease refer to this Residency Circular No. 1851/18/14, dated the 23rd September, 19'37, and furnish a report on the movements of;- 1. K.S. Mirza Isnsil Barduli, Head Munshi , Bahrain. 2. Uirza Jassim bin Mohammed, 3rd Munshi, Bahrain. 3. Mr. Abdulla Jassim Boodai, Officiating Munshi, Kuwait. on the lines indicated in the Circular referred to above. By order, f jh _ for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Ho. ^51 -67/29. Dated the 11th March, 1939 A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded The Political Agent, Muscat, ^ The Polilioal Agent, Bahrain,^ The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty's Consul, Kerman, His Majesty's Consul, Bandar Ahhas, His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr, for infoiraation and necessary action. for Secretary to the Political Resident Office Memorandum from the Govemhient of India in the Labour Department, Ho. A.48, dated the 3rd February, 1939 to: By order in the Persian Gulf» (Heceired uith the Government of India, internal Affairs Department, endorsement No. D.655-Q/39, dated the 18th February, 1939).Copy of Office Menorandum from the Government of India in the Labour Department to ell Pepartment8 of the Government of India, Ho.A.48., dated the 3rd February, 1939. Ml bub e of Government stationery and service postage stamps. The attention of the Government of India has recently been drawn to cases in which Governnent envelopes and service postage stamps were used by Goverrcnent officers for the purpose of sending returns relating to their personal assessments to the Income Tax authorities in contravention of rule 55 of the 'Rules for the supply and use of Stationery Stores and Clauses 7 and 354 of the ?ost and Telegraph Guide which enjoin that Government stationery and service stamos should on no account be used by Government officials for other than bona fide public purposes. The undersigned is directed to request that necessary steps may be taken to prevent this kind of mi suae of Governratnt stationery and service stamps in future.Code. Prom. To. No. TELEGRAM . G.T.C. Briticonsul, SKIiecx Bushire at Shiraz. Britconsul, Basrah repeated to Bushire and Bahrain. T/153• Despatched # 3-8-39. Receieved. My telegram 414 December 12the 1938. Gable communication between Muscat again interrupted Grateful if you could relay telegrams bearing prefix BALAM to Bahrain as before. Fovjle. L -V l ATelegram ' qw From Political Agent, Muscat. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 223 Dated ana received 8th August 1959. Received from Political Resident for you begins. Telegraphic communication Muscat restored. Telegrams from ana to Bahrain will be sent via Muscat as heretofore. Ends. 4. PA £&lt; o - POLITICAL - L -ci ill &amp; Ccx. \C V ' ll rs v /l^t ijf'Vf \Ho.0/689 of 1939. oe fef the PoIltioAl Httidtnt in the Persian (hiXf 9 Jamp, Kuwait• Dated the 9th KoTeraber t 1939. The Polltloal Agent f Kuwait* Trie Political Agent, lahraln. J The i^olitioal A^eut, Muscat* The Secretary to the 1 olltioai :ieaidant in the iereian Gulf, Buehire* Memorandum• The outer oover of all letters to the India Office should, in future, he addreebed to The secretary, * Political (External) ^e^art^peut, India Offioe. ad. C.G.Prior. irolitioal iiesident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. for secretary to the ^olitioal Ke&amp;ident in the Persian Gulf.Mmioafc.. Confident ial # Circular Ko # 105. British Consulate-General, Bushire,tAe 19tn January 1940. To The Political gent, Muscat* The Political gent, Bahrain. The Political gent, Kuwait. His Majesty 's Consul, Feman-Bandar bbas, Ker;nsu. Hia Majesty's Vice-Consul, Khorramshar. Uenorandum . The Hon*tie the Political Kesiaent is pleased to direct that whenever an officer receires instruction in a foreign language from e Gorerninent seryant serving under him such tuition should invariably be ^ald for. By order, :he Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 29th January 1940. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to Captain J.R. Howes, Political Officer, Trucial Coast, for information. k Of ^for Political Agent, Bahrain,Ho. 495' Dated the 10th April, 1940* To g circular ito. 1, The Politioal Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain,*-^' The Political Agent, Kuwait, H.B.M' s Consul, Kerman, H.B.M's Consul, Bandar Abbas, H.B.M's Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr. It is a common practice in mapy Agencies and Consulates to append Circular Notices and Instructions to the specific files in regard to the subject matter of which ths notices have issued. In due course these files are closed and bound and the circular notices overlooked and lost to sight. In order to obviate this and to assist officers when taking over charge, all circulars issued by the flushire Residency will in future be sent out in duplicate. The duplicate copy should in each case be filed in a special file to be opened for the purpose, which should be given to the officer taking over charge. This will ensure that an officer will find readily available in a compact and accessible form all circular instruo* tions which have been sent to the post. 2, In order to ensure that the collection is as complete as possible, where earlier circulars which are still in force come to notice, a copy should be extracted, and placed on the file. will be convenient if two such files are opened, one for confidential instructions and the other non-tfonfident ia3 instructions and circulars. By order. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. il M€) 1^0.327-3 of 1940. Residency &amp; Consul&amp;te-General, Busliire, the 23rd May, 1940. To The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Kuv/ait, xhe rclitical Agent, Muscat. ./ ICeiuorandum. O- i.h A copy of letter No.D.839-lT/ 32 » dated the 2nd March 1932, from the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department is enclosed for information and guidance, with the remark that a copy should he placed on the handing over file in each Agency. 2. The term 'positions of importance 11 may be interpreted as referring to positions approximating to those of the European employees of the Bahrain State. sd. G.G. Prior. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Atte sted. Reaident^r-tne Persian Gulf.cofy. ^ * £f) HO.D.839-K/32. prom The Deputy Secretary to the Goverriment of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated Hew Delhi, the 2nd March 1922. Employment of MrSteele as State Engineer, Bahrain. Sir, In reply to your letter lTo.343 of 1932, dated the 14th February 1932, i am directed to say that although the Hules contained in paragraph 56 of the Manual of instructions to officers of the Political Department of the Government of India do not apply to the Arab States in the Persian Gulf, the Government of India consider it desirable that all cases in which the Rulers of these States show a desire to engage the services of Europeans (which may be understood as including Australians and .Americans) should be reported to them before hand. The same aisb applies to the engagement of Iraqis, Syrians, Palestineans, Egyptians and natives of Kbrth Africa in positions of importance. 2. The Government of India see no objection to the employment of Mr.W.B.Steele as State Engineer, Bahrain. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, ^our most obedient servant, sd. F.V.Wylie Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.No.871 British Consulate-General, Bushire the 3rd July 1940. To The Political Agent « Muscat. The Political Agent - Bahrain The Political \gent - Kuwait. CIRC UIAR . Owing to the difficulty and delay involved in obtaining visas for Iran, all clerks who proceed on leave and are subsequently posted to Iran should be instructed to apply for their visas to the appropriate Iranian Consul in ample time before their leave is due to expire; at the same time they should inform this Consulate General of the place at jhich they have applied and the date Uhe visa is required, jo that His Majesty 's Minister at Tehran may he asked to help in obtaining sanction for the visa. By order, Sd/- A. C. Stewart. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gu3f.8^ - /j No, 1 JDbted the 3rd July 1940 To The Political Agent - Muscat The Political Agent - Bahrain The Political A ^ent, - Kuwait. / CIRCULAR 1 Owing to the difficulty and delay involved in obtaining visas for Iran, all clerks who proceed on leave and are subsequently posted to Iran should be instructed to app&amp;y for their visas to the appropriate Iranian Consul in ample time before their leave is due to expire; at the same time they should inform this Consulate General of the place at »vhich they heve applied and the date the visa is required, so that His Majesty's Minister at Tehran may be asked to help in obtaining sanction for the visa. By order, No•1318-15/3 Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Political Agency, Bahrain^ 10th July, 1940. Copy of the foregoing is forwarded to !'r. Ghulam Haidar Khan for information. f/C fnptiain-,— for Political Agent, Bahrain.(i No. -39/24. x) a ted the 11th October 1940. To I The Political Agent, Muscat The Political Agent, Bahrain . The Political Agent, Kuwait His Majesty's Consul, Keroian Hia Majesty 's Vice-consul, Kho&gt; ran•hrhr MKMO ^ANDUM The enclosed copy of w instruct ions regarding the procedure to be followed to obtain visas for entry into Iran' dated the 20th September 1940, is forwarded for inrormati on # 2. Political Agents are requested to inform this Residency of passport details of all persons *ho proceed on leave to enable this oifice to notify Hi a Majesty's Legation at Tehran in case they are required to rejoin in Iran at the conclusion of their leave. By order. Secri^jLapy^tT) the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.N *-A Inatruotions regarding the proc^dux^e to be foJlo ed to obtain Tiaas for entry into Iran, 1. Aa the Iranian regulatione now require th t fll appllcatlona for Tlaaa for Iran ahouid be relerred to Tehran, the following Inatruotlona are leaued for the guidance of Brltlah aubjecta intending to proceed to Iran, 2. An applicant for a Tlat. for Iran ahouid In the flrat Instance aubmit hla application for a rlaa to the appro priate Iranian Conaulrr authority aa long aa poealble In adTance of the date of hla departure for iHxn* of auch application ahouid at the a^me tiaie be aent to the Brltlah Conaular authority concerned far cc.amunlcation to Hi a Majesty 1 a Legation, Tehran. 3. In the caae of peraona proceeding on leave who expect to return to poata in Iran application ahould, in the first inatance 9 be ■ade to the authority which laauea the exit visa*, atating the time and route of the proposed re-entry Into Iran and the Irani, n Conaulate at ahlch It la dealred to obtain the entry Tlaa, and requesting tn t inatruction^ to laaue the rlaa may be aent from Tehran. Details of auoh application ahouid at the aame tiae be aent to the Britlah Conaular authority concerned for communication to Hla Majeaty^ Legation, Tehran. (Sd. ) For ecretary to the political Resident In the Peraian Gulf. Brltlah Healdency 4 Conaul^te General, Buahlre, the 20th September 1940*^ { I A y Ho*01/4X3 of X940. Office of the Jr 'olltlcel Rfeldent in the Persian Gulf, Gonp, Bahrain* Bated the 50th Ootober 9 i94o« To Th« Secretary to the Political Heeident in the jreraian Gulf, Bushire • The Political A^ent, Batirain. / The PoXitioaX Agent, Kuwait* The PoliticaX Agent, Huecat* His Majesty's Consul, Ftrman* His Majesty^ Vioe Consul, KhorraxoBhahr• ClrcuXar liersorandum » Will you please instruot all nieiobers of the olerioal staff that the use by then of the address ♦•British Consulate-General*, ^Political Agency* etc#, it irregular, 2* The words '•care of* should in future be prefixed to all private communications received by them at the official address of any Consulate or Agency# sd. C.G .Prior# Political Resident in the iersian Gulf# ,tte sted . Confidential Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 0 &gt;V7 l- M /. ^ ^ W rD.O. No./3 0 5-10/48. ytfith reference to Bahrain Agency memoranda No.1815 and 1845 dated the 2btn September and 1st . October 1940 respectively, I am desired to inform you that all correspondence addressed to the Hon'ble the Political Resident, except tnat of a purely routine nature, snould be signed by the Political Agent himself. Major R.G.E.W. Albsn, Political Agent, Bahrain. 1Relative file with P.A, Both thes^ letters mentioned in the D.O. below were approved by Mr. Weightman. The letter at page 29 was discussed by Captain Howes with P.A. and nara^raphs 6 and 8 were added by P.A. The letter at page 1 of file 10/4 Was drafted by Mr, Weightman himself. May renly that both the letters were issued under the approval of I r. Weightman but that the instructions have been noted for the future. % L v-%, v I // /! % I JIJ 11 1 jfi,.' B .o. d-o. . L ^ Confidential Ho.^66-S of ld41 Britibh HffBidency and Con&amp;ulete General, Busliire &gt; the 30th April 1941. To The Political Agents Kuwait* The Political Agent, Bahrain*^ The Political Agent, Muscat* Copy to Hie Majesty's Minister, Tehran, Hie Maje&amp;ty^ Consul, Baera* Memo randum It has been learnt that when I im on tour on the Arab Coaet the Consulate at BaerB experiences some diff iculty in deciding whether peckagea addreeeed '•Hie Brit annic Majesty's Consul-Genera 1, Bushire 1 * and sent to Basra for onward transmission should be forwarded to Bushire or sent to me wherever I may be, e*g* at Kuweit* Ji* In order to obviate this difficulty all matter for transmission to Bushi re should be enclosed in separate covers addressed to •♦His Majesty's Consul , Bushire' and only that intended to be forwarded to me wherever I am should be enclosed in covers addressed 'His Britannic Majesty's Consul General, Bushire'* Safe hand matter from other posts, e*g* Indie Office, Mice, Jedda etc*, are addressed to me as •♦Consul General' or 'Political Heiident in the Persian Gulf H , and automatically fell within the latter category* (ort^ Hi) Sd. C.G. PRIOR X olitical Htsident in the Persian Gulf. Attested | tary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. L /&gt; K CIRODLAR. Ho. 6«/ V' \ 11 To I i British Conaulate-Greneral, Buehire. Dated the If fa May, 1941, )• A ■ / ■ ^ The Political Agent, Muscat. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Tne Political Agent, Kuwait, MEMORANDUM. Arrivals and departures of all Political Officers at or from Agencies should be reported by telegram for tne information of the Hon*ble the Political Resident. By order. Secretary to the Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf.CIRCULAR D.O.Uo.614-13/92. \h Buahire, tne May, 1941. c It iiaa been poiutecL out by the GoTemment of India th^t ofl'icers of the Indian Political Serrice below the rank of Residents of tne 1st and kind Class frequently arrive in Delhi or Simla on casual leave without notice having been given to the Political or the External Affairs Departments. I am, therefore, to request jPortTthat you should inform tne Under Secretary, Political Department, as far in advance as possible of your intention of visiting Delhi/Simla on casual leave (with dates). Major R.G.E.W. Alban, O.B.E., Political Agent, Banrain.k i 7 /. J. A '' '■ - ^ -&amp;-/?/?, £it aJ*-r 'V»:6/Lf Af //- i^r/ r '' P.U.C.I . Noted. ! ay be filed after the staff have noted? I.A. ' . 1 * '■» n c.o. ^ l ^ : ., E.O. ,■ * y/ A.0. V ^ V P.T.T.C.2 . To be shown to Llessrs Jackson and Pelly on their return. File? Incidentally^ I may point out that these circulars etc are important enough to be placed on the handing over file vide instnxctions from P.R. at page 1, Since the issue of this .circular Bushire have not carried out their instructions as they said they would do. To begin with all circulars should have serial numbers so that when a P.A. goes through the file he can find out if any circular is missing. But it will be seen that no circular from 3ushirc has been given No,2. The circulars are being numbered from the outward correspondence register. Again circulars in duplicate as promised by Bushire are not being received, tfe have to make out our own copies for respective files.British Conaulate General, Bi shire. Dated, ishe 2^11 September 194!• To (1) The Political Agent, Muecat, (2) Tiie Politics! Agent, Bahrain, (3) The Political Agent, Kuwait, y Circular Memorand um Officers performing the duties of a Political A^ent during the latter^ temporary absence frca hie post, whether on recess or otherwise, should in future sign all letters, which would in tne normal course be signed by the political A^ent himself, as Mn the absence of the Political Agent* and not as hitherto •J'or Political Agent*. particular attention should be paid to this point when addressing letters to Coiananders of H # M «Ships 0 By order. Seqx^tary to the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf*Ho, 1028-13/14 n British Consulate General, Bushire 9 Bated 9 the 2nd October 1941. To The Political Agent, Muscat The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Kuwait He mo rand urn In future all moTementa of senior British officials of State goTernments should be reported by telegram for the information of the Hon f ble the Political Resident* By order, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf*87-S of 1941. Britiati Besiaency &amp; Oonsulate-Genera! Bushir*e. Dated the 16th OctolDer, 19A1. ♦ To The Political A^entf Muscat, Eeference his letter No,0/461, S d^ted ^Oth August, The Politioal Agent, Bahrain. 1941. The Political Agent, Kuwait. r j^bmobandum It is requested that in future rupee figures in all stateiBents he shown in lakhs. 1 3d. O.G.Prior Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.yh V.o.lV ^ VM Britisb^Consulate-General, ^ Rprf!DT^?b/ BusMre. ;/ ^No... ■fX® Dated the K«f April 1942. The Politic?! Agent, Muscat, The Political. Agent, Bahrain,.-' The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty's Consul, Bunder Abbas, His Majesty 1 s Consul, Kernan, ilis Majesty 1 s Consul, Khorramshahr. 777 Circular lAemorandum • Will you please issue instructions to all clerks serving in your area that thay shoulc invariably come and report to the Secretary, if the stay of the ship permits, when they pass through Bushire on transfer. h&lt;,L- By order, A. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. V.&amp; V K. iAy BRITISH CONSULATE GENERAL BUSHIRE, the • ta -' 1 June 1942. 1) The Political Agent, Muscat, ✓ 2) The Political Agent, Bahrain,/ 3) The Political Agent, Kuwait. 4) Hhs Majesty 1 s Consul, Bandar Abbas. 5) His Majesty 1 s Consul, Kerman. 6) His MajestyV^-Qonsul, Khorramshahr. MEMORANDUM . Will you please bring it to the notice of all clerks serving under your orders that I am now maintaining a list of those clerks whose leave is extended on medical certificate. By order. t ^4^ r ' urc '^ &gt; * ^ Secretary to the Political ^ Resident in the Persian Gulf.BRITISH CONSULATE GENERAL BUijlJIRE. The 7th July 1942. To 1) The Political Agent, Muscat, US) The Political Agent, Bahrain, 3) The Political Agent, Kuwait. 4) fflis Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abbas. 5) His Majesty's Consul, Kerman. 6) His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr. jk&amp;mohariduka ^ s ^^ /s\ j Would ^ou please s^na^me a statement showing which of the clerks in your office'are qualified in (a) stenography and (b) M speed writing.' Their maxiiiiuiii speed may ^indly be notedi (a) as claimed by applicant at previous tests, (b) as displaced at present, after test. By order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian GulfWo.1466-1/17 Political Agency ? Bahrain. 18th August ? 1942. To y *4 ^ i ^ The Secretary to tW ^n'ble the PoliMcwl Resident ih t^e Persian Gulf ivo *1 tj ~ r Memorandum♦ f / ^ I ^1 xi Reference your Memorandum Ho.778-64/238 dated the 7th July. K 2. ?iesBrs, La RiW and Shanua of this office are qualified in stenography. The former holds a certificate obtained in 1938 from the London Chamber of Commerce, vjhich gives him a speed of 120 v/oi'da par m5.nutc. His present speed Is 130 words per minute. The later possesses a certificate issued at a private Commercial College in Lahore in 1932 which put his speed at 120 words per minute. Owing to lack of practice Mr. Sharm? cannot now be used as a stenographer but would probably require only a short period of regular practice before he bec^ne reasonably proficient. A ~ 3. None of the clerks in this office is qualified in speed writing. ^ 7 A for Political Agent, Bahrain.£IHCUUE A case has recently occurred in tvhich a clerk) signed a certificate on a T # A. Bill to the effect that he had transported with him on a joiTrney twenty mfunds of kit and incurred as a result exper^iturt of over £3. IbOO/ -. Enquiries showeo the t the nT-our-l of kit actually transported was about thrue aaunds find that the expenditure incurred on it was negligible. The main line of defence adopted by the clerk vas that the si &amp;ning of certificates or T.A. bills vas merely a matter cf form. It is necessary that this idea if it exists elsewhere amongst the staff subordinate to we should be dispelled at once. The obtainini of money by the signing of a false certificate is ^ust as heinous as the obtaining of it by purser/, eiibea ^le&amp;iunt or theft. The clerk concerned in the case referred to in. this circular has lost a chance of promotion T£d been rsduced eighteen months in the time scale. If any further case of this kin* comes to my notice I shell feel myself compelled to avrard a much severer pimishmant, i expect ai3. controilin^; officers carefully to scrutinise the T,A. bills of their subordinates and to bring 1:0 my notice any case in which a false certificate has been recorded. This order is to be shown to all officers and members of the ministerial staff under the control of tnis Residency. W. R. HAY Political Resident in the Persian Gulf t 3ushire BUoHIRK, the 2nd August 194: 2.No•1176- British Consulate General Bu shire. 9tfe October 1942. To The Political Agent, Muscat, ^he Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty^ Consul, Kerman. His Majesty^ Consul, Kiiorramsheiir. Memorandun. The undersigned is directed to say that when a reference is made in a telegram to any fund of a secret or confidential nature, the portion of the telegram dealing v/itn that fund should invariably be cyphered. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.No.1206-64/238 British Consulate Genera3. BUSHIRFi. 15th October 1942. To The Political iigent, Muscat. J2he Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty's Consul, Kermen. Eis Majesty^ Consul, Khorramshahr. Memorandimi. The Hon^le the Political Resident directs that, for the duration of the war, any member of the minis terial establishment going to India on leave, shall be given a letter in duplicate addressed to the Kavy Sea Transport Officer at Bombay or Karachi, as may be most appropriate, requesting him to illot the bearer a priority second class passage to Bushire (unless other orders have been passed regarding his posting on return from leave), in the ship most appropriate to the date of the expiry of his leave; and to telegraph him the date when he should reach the port of embarkation, 2. All clerks going on leave should be instructed to show this paper to the Navy Sea Transport Officer immediately on their arrival in India, and to inform him of their address on leave, 3. On receipt of a telegram from the Naval Sea Transport Officer instructing the recipient to be at a port by a given date, all unexpired leave will be auto matically cancelled, and failure to report by the required date will be treated' as overstayal of leave without permission. ^ Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,i No. 1221 - 79/64 British Consulate Oeneral, Bushire, the 19th October, 1942. To The Political Agent, Muscat %tie Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent^ malt' His Majesty's Consul, Kerman His Majesty's :&amp;d«eeConsul, Khorramshahr. Circular The Crovernment of India have intimated that the question of free insurance cover for effects of G-overnment servants from marine war risks is still under consideration, and that in the raaantime all Grovernment servants should effect insurance. Failure to obtain suitable cover will be at the owners 1 risk. 2. It is also notified that whatever compensation may eventually be sanctioned, will only cover goods in transit, and not at places of residence. ' t 'tirkyU ySecretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.N0.1001 -13A 4 . To ^ 3 ^ *3 British Residency and jZ Consulate-General, Bushire^ ^ ^ 11th June 1943. The Political Agent, Kuwait The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Muscat His Majesty 's Consul, Khorramshahr His Majesty•s Consul, Kerman His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Bandar Abbas, nrnv* .t It has recently been observe^ that the instmc- tions contained in this Residency Circular No.176 dated the 26th January 1935 are not being observed by some offices, with the result that papers are unnecessarily delayed. 2. The Residency is divided into two sections — the Main Office (previously referred to as Town Offte and the Confidential Office. In order to facilitate dealing with correspondence in Bushire and in parti cular when the Political Resident is on tour, i't is requested that non-confidential correspondence be addressed to the Secretary, way-billed separately and enclosed in a separate envelope marked 'Uain Office'. 3. The Main Office deals with applications for the export and import of all commodities, except food stuffs. Other matters normally dealt with in the Main Office are staff, finance, Toshakhana and all routine macters. Secretary' Resident -o the Politi the Persiar cal Gulf. i'No.1651-13/14. &amp; \ BRITISH EESIXEUCY AKD CONSULA.TE GENERAL BUSHERE The 6th Octo'ber, 1943. To The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Muscat The Political Agent, Kuwait His Uajesty's Consul, Kennan His Hajesty's Consul., Bandar A'b'bas His liajesty's Consul, Khorramshahr, CIRCULAR &lt;4 Please ensure that instructions regarding addressing of correspondence to this Residency, contained, in this office Circular No. 1001-13/14 dated 11.6 # 1943 are carried out in future« It is observed that some offices are still sending confidential and non-confidential mail under one ws£y 'bill. OTA. Secretary\to the Political Resident im the Persian Gulf • - v ^ aJ. O.llo. 1923-13/271. / .y. njn— 23 10% ' U / iA' T imiTISII ESSI.JSNCY iklTJD CONSTJIATS GSNEEAi BUSHIBil The 18th 'ove] 'her, 1943. A Pu^. It is cteerv^ed that some officers address emi-official letters to the resident; as * Jear Sir Geoffrey Prior ..* This appears unnecessarily cuni'bersome and I am to suggest that the 'Prior' should 'be omitted in future. You will observe from a Chancery letter which is issuing separately tliat Sir G-eofTrey has given up the use of his Military rank. lajor T. Hickinhotha , 0. .1^., Political i-gent, Bahrain. sm.Now C/454 CIRCULAR / A S • //* Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. Dated the 21st November 1943. Dear Agency, On 'being dubbed the Resident elected to be known in future by his second name and his correct style and title will there! ore be I - The Kon'ble Sir Geoffrey Prior, K,C.I.Hi., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Yours ever, RESIDENCY. The Political Agency, BAHRAIN p' v Z:'l ITS? isB, sc included for SharJahJ -ofj »• iiliarjah. Copy to tha Political ufficar, iTucial Coast, .4 I ,* ^ ' v Wf. .-fa &gt; - * J \ V /I . JC- No .2131-13/14 • EEUTISH EBSIUENOY AKD CONSUIATE OEtffiRAL BUSHIKE The 20th Decern Der, 1943. The Politica l Agent, iluscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain, ^ The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Britannic Majesty* s Consul, Keman, His Britannic Majesty's Consul, l^andar Ahhas. His Britannic Majesty^ Consul, Khorramshahr. W&amp;iO'B&amp;JSm In order to avoid delay and unnecessary extra work in the Besidency office all Persian and Arabic documents despatched to Bus hire must 'be accompanied 'by their English translations. i Secretary to the Political SM,. President in the Persian Gulf.-Ll. I 1 fe /^r No.161-33/57. To BRITISH EbiSIi^NCY AMD GONbUlATS GE1IEBAL BUSHTRhi The 22nd Jan'uary &gt; 1944. The Political Agent, Lluscat, ^The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent. Kuwait, His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Keraan, His M-tannic Majesty*s Consul, Kiiorramshahr, His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Bandar A'b'bas. MTftJfTRATmTM 1.^Memorandum No.852(l)-S dated the ^2nd 0cto'ber,1923 ? from the Government or India in the foreign and Political Department. 2. Memorandum No.47-S dated the 22nd June, 1925, from -do-. 3. Endorsement No.iF.130-^2Bdated the 10th July, 1929, from -do-. A copy of the marginally noted correspondence u-z is forwarded for information. It is possible that the Government of India endorsement No.IMSO-E/^S of the 10th July, 1929, is now oteolete. Secretary to the Political Besident jin the Persian Gulf'-J.-., /A I \ f y t&gt; Copy of a lemorandum No.852(l)-E dated the 22nd Octooer, . 1923, from the Assistant Secretary to the Government of India v in the foreign and Political Lfepartment, Simla, to the Hon*'ble the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf, Bus hire. Massing c harges on His Majesty's ahios Your letter No.994, dated the 16th June 1923. The Government of India are pleased, in the circumstances represented, to pemit the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf and officers serving under his orders, when touring on board His Majesty's Ships, to recover from Government the full amount of the difference 'between their daily allowance and their messing charges on the scale prescrilDed at items III and IV of the table appended to paragraph 1541 of the King* s Regulations and Admiralty Instructions. 2. Whenever they tour on board R.I.M.vessels, the Political Resident and officers serving under his orders may similarly recover from Government the full amount of the difference between their daily allowance and their mossing charges on the scale prescribed at items III and IV of the table appended to paragraph 304, Marine Regulations, India Volume I. ^— 3. A copy of this memorandum has been sent to His Excellency the Naval Gommander-in-Chief, East Indies Station. Copy of a memorandum No.47-E dated the 22nd June, 1925. from the Assistant Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department, Simla, to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Messing charges on His Majesty's Ships and Royal Indian Marine Vessels. Your letter No.1035, dated the 30th May 1925. 2. The Government of India are pleased to permit the subordinate establishments serving under the orders of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, when touring on duty on board His Majesty's Ships and Royal Indian Marine Vessels, to recover from Government the full amount of the difference between their daily allowance and their messing charges on the scales prescribed in King's Regulations and Admiralty Instructions and in Marine Regulations, respectively. 3. These orders will have effect from the date of issue. ^ No.ir.l30-£/28. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for information. By order, etc., Sd/- Illegible, Under Secretary to the Government of India. • -Foreign and Political Department, Simla, The 10th July, 1929. Letter from the Government of India, Marine Department, No.l959-M-. dated the 26th June, 1929, with enclosure. SM.Copy of letter No # 1959-M dated the S6th June 19P9, from the Assistant Secretary to the Government of Tndja f Marine Department, Simla, to The Flag Officer Commanding and Director, Royal Indian Marine. Revision of the rates of table money payable by high'officials when travelling on duty In Royal Indian Varine shins. With reference to the correspondence resting with yonr letter No.6461-^., date! the 11th October 1PS3, I am directed to state that the Government of India sanction the revision of the rules 5n paragraphs 304, 307 and 308, Marine Regulations, India, Volume I, as indicated in the attached enclesure. 2, The Regulations alluded to above will be amended 5n due course. NKD.Substitute the following for paraprrphs 304 f 307 f and 308 Marine Regulations f India, Volume I # HJGH 304 # The foil owing scales of table money are payable to Coramanderi of R 9 I 0 M # vessels by the imdermentlone&lt;! high officials when travelllnr In t v their official capacity! Class i { Passengers 9 1-- — All^ngeg ) per diepi For males 9 females Scales for hlrh o^^ldals For children of both 16 and 7 year? TT nder 7 !• lit HI. IV. Viceroy and Governor- General of India. Bach member of his suite Rs # 30/- for the first 7 )) days. Rs.10 /4 afterwards, RslOA for every day. Governors and Rs,20/- for Commander-ln- the first 7 Chief days, Rs,7/- afterwards. Each member of their suite Rs .7/- for every day. Bishops of Rs, ISA for Calcutta, the first 7 Bombay,Madras days, Rs,7/- of Chief Cdm- afterwards, missioners. Each member of their suite Rs ,7 A for every day. Members of Concll JF^.ISA for tHe first 7 General offi- days, Rs ,6A 6#y», Fed iti ^afterwards, al Residents, Secretaries to Govts,, of India, Madras and Bombay, Political Rs ,PA for agents, Asstt,the first 14 ) Political days, Rs ,6A) agents, Asstt,afterwards, ) Political Residents and Chief 6ommlsion ers of Andam^ns and Nlcobar Islands, Rs,6/» RK.S/- Bs.3/- Rs.??/. P8.V- RsS/-/o J * Note I, The above rates do not Include wines or smoVes, wHlch will be charged for at the usual mess rates. Guests will also be charged for at the usual mess rates. Note II # The above rates will be charged when the officials named travel on vessels In their official capacity; when travelling as ordinary passengers the rates laid down In paragraph 314 will be allowed. A Charges for senior passengers 307. TChen more than one distinguished persor Is embarked at the same time, the person of the highest rank will be cahrged according to the scale, and the other or others only at the rate of Rs.10/- or Hs7/- per head as the case may be. Private 308. The sums specified Include provision for a reason- servants. able number of private servants. VTelegram From To No. Da tod Pahr? n Re .eipt G .t.c.no „.s.55 Political Resident, Rushirc. Political Agent, Bahrain. 2306 23rd received 25tli Docember 1944 Please ask any of your staffs who nay contemplates sending ne Christmas Card or message of greetings to ^ take tlie will for deed and refrain.f. 1^/2 ft ' No. 2639-64/238. ERITISH EKSIIENCI ANt) OONSUIATB QSNEEAL, BUSHIHE. Dated 23r(i Decein'ber, 1944, To The Political Agent, Muscat. The Political Agent, Bahrain*/' The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty*s Consul, Bandar AlDbas. His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr. His jlajesty's Consul, Kerman. . Receipt f! TRnTTT.ATi SJRMQRANTITM. Ba Wam hi $ -• The home address of any meraber ot the Ministerial Establishment should he obtained 'before he proceeds on leave and this should he immediately forwarded to Bushire. Secretary tV\ the Politidal ResidentMin the Persian Gulf.K / -L British Residency A Consulate -General, Bushire, the 17th January, 1946 KU .iAIT. BAHRAIN• MUSCAT. ''ajrain receipt The Political Agerit, The Political Agent, The Political Agent, CIMUU.A -jJAOii^ma NO, 78-S A case recently occurred in which a presentation was made by one of the Services to a Xuler with the knowledge of the Political Apent but without this Residency being informed. It must be clear that any presentation, of other than a trivial nature, will almost certainly have a political repercussion, and in this case the Ruler lost no time in making caDital out of it. 2. Should any of the Services, or for that matter any non-Arab person or corporation ( other than the oil company - if any - holding a concession for that area ) desire to make a presentation to a Buler within your jurisdiction you should immediately inform this office before countenancing the matter. in any v/ay. A copy of this circular should be placed on your handing over file. Sd/- GiiOKFRLY PRIOH Pclitlcp.l Resident, Persian Gulf, iiT'faSTED. Sd/- J. CRWII'-IG. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. DLG. o ^ v rv-i ^ h C ~ oOOVKKNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER , u JV. B. —Tins is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by ^)ost to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treaty - on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save nni&lt;? arid formalities it is worded and signed as if it had 1 been so despatched. Lk 175-13/92. To Dated Bu shire oilS. Political, iuscat, Political, iahrain.^/^ Political, luwait. Britconsnl, Bandar Abbas. Br it consul, Kenan. Lritco isi 1, horra shahr. the20th January, 194 5. - * - - ■ .Date. Circular No. 601 dated 15 th I-ay, 1941' (sent to A. encies only)' and Express Letter No. 1138-13/269 dated 11th Hay, 1944 (sent to Consulates only) are cancelled. * 2. Political Resident ust be informed by telegran ' henever c Political Officer or C(nrsnl -ar officer arrives at or leaves a ost. This includes movements of officers when proceeding on. or » arriving fror. leave, transfer or visits to other posts. -britconsul- v The issue of the above has been authorised. 'N Secret Vy to the Political AGL. Resident^in the Persian Gulf, MFP—275 S &amp;P—6768—(M-6T6)—27-7-43—1,000,000.IK GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. DEPARTMENT. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B.— This ia an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication mor« expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department. Lushire, No. 54-51/36. Datedthe mh iVbruary, ^45- To Political, ^ ahrain , CIRGULAE. The telegraphic address of this Consulate-General will 'be 'BRITAIN, BUSHXHS' with effect from the 22nd .larch, 1945, -ERITC ONSUL- The issue of the ahove has 'been authorised. N3. His ?ritar\ic ^ajesty*s Consul, Bushire. S. 44. MGIPC—S2—2278 (Genl) MFP—(6806/M-20l3)—13-3-43—25,00U.^-w ' ^ l/b GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. DEPARTMENT. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B. This is an ORIGINAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the tdegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department. Jr-ushlre f No. ''81-51/56. 17ttl Fa-bxwy, ^45- To % , ' ahraia Kece .&gt;!: . Political, v., No....//6^ Qatr _^&lt;c2 ■ 2 -U i Bahrain. _ _ _ h C; I 1-i U U A Reference my express letter No. 754-51/36, dated 17th February, 1945. 2. Telegrams intended Tor the 'Residency should 'be acidressed 'FRIOB, BUUHIBS'. -PHIOK- ****** J The issue of the a'bove has teen authorised. 4 Secretar:; ^ the Political 'Resident in rcio Persian dull'. NS. S. 44. mgipc—s2—2278 (genl) mfp—{6806/m-2013)—13-3-43—25,000,GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. DEPARTMENT. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B. This is on ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it /— is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department. ^ 0 * 871 .Doled .,£■ xLthe 19 V MM' i-e^ruary, 4b I V Political, Pahrain. / Bahrain Aectipt _ J ^ i; li L A i . 'hfei telQurnvnio vAiiro** or tba Uonsulate \A 'noceuk, ♦ ' ho tsamm ot a &gt;oto tmt t-eeri auti.oriBtriU tai'y oll-icjl resident In tho Gulf# / w - Kb, S. 44. MGIPC—S2—2278 (Genl) MFP—{6806/M-2013)—13-3-43—26,000.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B.— This it an ORIGINAL meBsige sent by AIR MAIL which providif a mtam of communication mort expeditious than the ordinary mtil ani is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition a$ if it hii been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is aulhenlieated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 1575-51/36. To DaiM****., the Nei~' r '~ yL ' 19 Reference ///////zZ/ 6th April, 1946. // yomiUH NK* UtilMl ?• &amp;. V. NK« BalLHI G. H. Q. m* Duiiiil pbourqma CAIRO umm cairo ib&amp;GO CAIRO AIBU^BCH HikBhaNIXAH b. N« 0. P. a. BAHRAIN (?A^b TO OOdJ^Ujtik ~ Hi * CHLitf, POLITICAL KDvVAII POLITICAL s POLITICAL kUbOAT BBIIuiOi^rX bHAtUAH BKIT A IH BASRA momcm bactkdad PBQjihOMiS jmua ^ • A* jB*« SBLiJjifill Ai^ROb AikiN ClKUULkU^ . ■ I'l? My circular iilxpress letter No. 781-51/36 dated 17th JFeteuary, 1945. 2. Telagrane Intended Tor Residency should s O bo 'be addressed ' BRITAIN BUSHIRiS ' with effect from 1st May, 1945. PRIOR '.r The issue of the atxrve has 'been authorised. Secretary to tfte Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. G.A.M. S. 44. (Signature) {Designation) MGHPC—SI—2385(S&amp;P)MT , P—{M-1744)—3-12-40—20,000.? Telegram From To dtf o» S4#r»). Political Resident, Bushlre. Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 923 Circular. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 929 Circular. Political Agent, Muscat. No. 930 Circular. Dated the 16th and received 17th May, 1945. narmi - j.33 My Circular telegram dated April 16th. 2. Please restrict use of ConTidential 11 Q' Code as much as possible. Unless there are special local reasons routine telegrams regarding food supplies, stocks et cetera should be sent in Indian Word Code or Government Telegraph Code. - GALLOWAY - R.M. I.R. 358.W\ x n » , lm jC! 1 $s:uiUj&amp;' Telegram Cypher. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 1722. Dated 24th received 25th November, 1945. Circular. You should not initiate correspondence direct with Government of India and repetition of your correspondence to it should ordinarily be confined to cases where Government of India has repeated to you correspondence addressed Bushire. (p) LEI. I.a.No.687 = PRIOR =No, 186 BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. the 10th January, 1946 To I A / The Residency Agent, y Sharjah. MEMORANDU ^i Xn future please send English translations of all letters, receipts, etc. which you may send me, as there is no * present. Secret* ^1 Resident alf. No. 186 Bushire, the 11th January,1946 Copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Rahrafn Receipt No...Date. .CV.Q..I.»No. Lob - 77/7. BRITISH RESIDENCY AND ; A CONSULATE GENERAL, /Ml BUSHIRE. ^ V y 'to 6 22nd January, 1946o jt.^ To The Political Agent, Muscat. The Political Agent, Bahrain.-/ The political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty's Consul, Kerman. His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr. His Majesty^ Consul, Bandar Abbas. ...in..: isZJUd MEMORAN DUM No Reference paragraph 3 of Residency Circular No, 133 dated the 26th January, 1940. 2. It occasionally happens that an officer has to leave his post before his successor arrives, or that there is insufficient time for the successor »to check and take over properly the books which belong to Government. In these cases, the Treasury Officer, the Superintendent or the Head Clerk (as the case may be) of the office should take the books over, sign for and be responsible for them until such time as the new officer assumes charge. By;Order, Secretary t^o JJae-VfrLitical Resident 'IxT the Persian Gulf® G.A.M.Bahrain Receipt *•— Data i / ■ V V Telegram G.T.C. Political Resident, Bushire Political Agent, Bahrain. 607. 20th April, 1946. From To No Dated Circular, Until further orders please address to Kerman all cypher telegrams for Consul Bandar Abbas and all other telegrams requiring his personal attention. PRIOR \ OL 1.-^1, .y^«/3 1 1 b No.581-S Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire. 7th May, 1946. To The Political Agent, Kuwait •The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Muscat Circular Memorandum . Communications in the form of a 'Chancery 1 letter are not considered suitable for correspondence between the Political Agencies and this Residency. The use of this form should be avoided in future. Sd. Geoffrey Prior, Political Resident, Persian Gulf Attested Sd. J. Croning, for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. /Copy/SARMA' GOVERN/WENT OF INDIA BRITISH RESIDENCY AND WPWtWPJfa/ CONSULATE GENERAL, mSEIM ' LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B.— This an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] to. Sv/i'-80/46. n . , 0 18th May, 1946. '// • To The Political Agent, Muscat The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Kuwait His Majesty's Consul, Kerman His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr His Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abbas. « . l Wflftyfrf/ Government of India have drawn my attention to a few recent cases wherein offices subordinate to this Residency have been applying direct to the Export Trade Control authorities in India for permits for requirements. This is contrary to the correct procedure. All applications for export permits should be addressed to this Residency and repeated to the External Affairs Department of the Government of India to whom my recommendations will be sent. In no circumstances should outside authorities be approached direct. -BJLI..TJULN. THE ISSUE OF THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. ) the Po] :he PersJ {Signature) s. 44. MFP—1015 S&amp;p—(M.1870J—9-2-39—20,000. {Designationis /2». Off loo of the ho, a/6 6 4. Political Rosldentt Porslan Crulf 9 Camp 9 Bahrain* To tha 14th August 1946 # The Adrlser to tha Bahrain OoTernmont. Tha Direotor of Cuatoras^ Bahrain* Tha State i £nginaer 9 Bahrain* Memorandum * The Camp office of the Hon v ble the Folitical Reeidentt Persian Uulf y will be located at Jufair with effect from the 17th August 1946 until further notice* 2* aU letters for the Kon'ble the Political Resident tfid the Residency should please be sent to H *B*li* , s Political Agent, Bahrain, from *here arrangements will be made to collect them daily* j 1 ' 2, Jt for Uaoretary to tho Political Residentf Persian Gulf* RHL. ✓ Copy to: The Political• Agent, Balirain, with the request that he will please give instructions for all mail for the Residency to be accepted by his office, from where it will be collected daily by a Residency messenger Contidentuii. BAHRAIN U2CEIPT,GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. /&lt;■/!&gt; EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). 12-9 [N.B.— Thia is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the teUgraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it hod been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form ojQf O^f is fa ^tvlicated' by the signature of a respontible officer of the Vepartmen^^ ^ Ofti ReSidWt, Pars lan Uulf, 0/699. Camp, Bahrain 9 the 20 ^ August 2^6 To Politloal Agent, Kuwait, at quetta* Political Agent, Muscat, at Karachi* Political Agent, Bahrain Political Kuwait* Political Muscat* Copy to Secretary to Political Resident, at Bushire* His Majesty^ Government have decided that for the present my headquarters will be located at Bahrain and I and my camp office hare taken up quarters in the JMaTal Base at Jufair* 2* My main office is still at Bushire, and its more is not likely to he completed for two or three months* 5* until further notice (a) all confidential office correspondence should he addressed to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain, (b) all main office correspondence should be addressed to the Secretary H*B*M* 's Consulate-General, Bushire, and (c) copies of all main office correspondence which (i) is not purely routine or (ii) can be dealt with more expeditiously at Bahrain than at Bushire should be sent to the Under Secretary, Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain* Bahrain Receipt Attested * 3d* W*R # HAY* Political Resident, Persian Gulf* for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf* RHL* v\ S. 44 MFP—1450 s &amp;P—{M -2386) —26 -3 -40—16,000. (Signature) {Designation)^e\ ■,' 'f 130 v Copy of Express Letter No.c/796 dated the 29th August, 1946, from the Hon'ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. To Retaxandum, London, etc., etc. Copy to Political, Bahrain. The telegraphic address of the Hon'ble the political Resident, Persian Gulf, at Bahrain will in future be 'REPGU BAHRAIN'. Bahrain Receipt 5^0 v' • . ✓ ''A , OFFICE OMJER MO.36 aa _ ^ V i !• When the political Heiident it p*oa««&lt;liag on or returning from tour or leare ha should ha faan off or he waleoMed by the Secretary or in hie absence by the Under Secretary. 2 m He should also be seen off or welcomed by the Political Agent Bahrain or in his absence the Assistant Political Agent provided he departs or arrives between 8 a .m. and sunset. If the^Political Resident departs or arrives by sea there isNecessity for the Political Agent (or Assistant Political Agent) to go off to the vr .w) S» If the Political Agent Bahrain (or the Assistant Political Agent) does not meet the Political Resident mr on anival curing to the proviso in the last para he should call on hin la office hours on the first opportunity* 4. Paras 2 and 3 do not apply when the Political Resident leaves Bahrain for a period not exceeding three days on a pleasure trip. 5. OTficers seeing off or meeting the Political Resd&amp;ent should wear a suit with tie and hat. 6. The above rules apply when an officer arrives to take over as Political Resident or departs after handing over the duties of Political Resident. 7. Wtyen a new paraaaent Political Resident arrives or an officer who has held the post departs after handing over substantive charge all gasetted officers should if possible welcome him or see him off. Secretary to the Political Resident9 Persian Gulf. Persian Gulf Residency Bahrain 23rd April| 1947. Copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Salfr ^ S.0. No. 1994-15/3 Dated th« 14th June, ia47» / C, Please refer to the second sentence of paragraoh 2 of Persian Gulf Residency Ofrice Order No. 35 of 1947, which reads; M If the Political Resident departs or arrives by sea there Is necessity for the Political Agent (or Assistant Political Agent) to go off to the ship. 2. Is this correct or should it really read, 'there is No^ necessity'? Yours sincerely, G.N* Jackson, Esquire, y &gt;tary to the Ilon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,8 ' ' ^ D.O.No.1467-74/7. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. The 24th June, 1947, c&gt;-i Please refep^Bo Ranee's demi-official letter No•1994-15/3 dated the 14th June, 1947, to Jackson, The word 'no' has been omitted. The sentence should read 'If the Political Resident departs or arrives by sea there is no necessity for the Political Agent (or Assistant Political Agent) to go off to the ship,' 2 SWA. C. J, Pelly, Esquire, 0,B.E., I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain, ' talr No 3sy(I to No.1744. ■ el M * PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY r BAHRAIN. The 11th August, 1947. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to The political Agent, Bahrain, ^ The political Agent, Luscat, The political Agent, Kuwait, His Lajesty's Consul, Khorramshahr His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Btshire, for favour of communication to the officers concerned. By order. ^ CFl ir a. n for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf \ u ENCLOSURE Government of India in the Department of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations telegram No.6426 CIRCULAR dated the 7th August, 1947. SWA.. I I .Telegram Code From Government of India, New Delhi. To Political Resident, Bahrain. No.6426 CIRCULAR Dated 7th and received 8th August, 1G47. It has been decided that officers appointed by Secretary of State to a Civil Service or post in India whose services may be terminated or who may decide to quit service owing to present constitutional changes shall be reimbursed the actual cost oi transport by road rail or steamer of personal effects from last place of their employment in India to place ox residence in ,niced Kingdom up to a limit of 60 maunds in the case O- l married officers and 40 maunds in the case of unmarried officers. Please inform all officers. - FOREIGN -Co^ 1 Telegram from \^j\. To .O.T.C. Political Resident, Bahrain. &gt; ^ Political Agent, Bahrain, (by hand). Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Muscat. H.H 1 s Consul, Khorrarashahr. H.M's Consul, Kerman. No. A/636. Dated the 19th August 1947. My telegram No. A/629 August 14th. 2. Following is repetition of India Office telegram No.10676 August 14th addressed to Government of India, New Delhi. Begins Your telegram No.6677 of August 11th. Passage Gratuity for Indian Political Service Officers serving in Persia and Persian Gulf. 2. Sanction granted provided that officer has not earned full pension under rules. - Ends. = RJSPGU = ' s ^.dKr. Telegram From To Enclair. Political (^2 , Bahrain. Political Agent, Bahrain, (by hand). Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Muscat. HsM 's Consul, Khorramshahr. H.M 1 s Consul, Kerman. No. A/637. Dated the 20th August 1947. Following is repetition of Foreign telegram No. 1838.E.E(P) of August 12th. Begins j - Applications for payment of compensation should be submitted to Secretary Services and General Department Commonwealth Relations Office (India Section) Whitehall accompanied by release certificate or Provincial Govern ment's letter that applicant proceeded on leave prepa ratory to retirement on or about 16th August. Applica tions should state officers age or length of service i as case may be and amount of compensation claimed. Please inform all Indian Political Service Officers accordingly. - Ends. /Mi ♦ REPGU ♦ RS.From Political Resident, Bahrain. To Political Agent, Muscat. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain. (By hand). No.917. Dated the 19th August, 1947. CIRCULAR. In future India Office will be known as Commonwealth Relations Office, King Charles Street, Whitehall; telegraphic address RETAXANDUM. Please v address mail accordingly. -GALLOWAY-N o © 2 c !•- • PERSIAN GULF HE BAHEalN. 3rd Novemberj 1947. The political Agent, ✓^AHRAIN/rJJSCAT/KUl AIT, Memorandjjp. • In all correspondence the subject matter should ordinarily be stated either as a heading or in the opening reference to previous correspondence. This is especially necessary in reminders and similar communications in which the subject matter is not expressly referred to. It is not however necessary to state the subject matter of a telegram of a routine nature when this is made clear by the opening v r ords</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000ac_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1437</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000ac</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1437</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 15/3 Rules and Regulations received from the Residency Office – Bushire, etc.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1923/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-29T00:12:26</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (165 folios)</extent><extent>File papers are arranged chronologically, according to the date they were circulated to the Political Agent, Bahrain and others.</extent><extent>Foliation: numbered 1-7, 7a, 8-11, 11A, 12-14, 14a, 15-42, 42A, 43-52, 52A, 53-61, 61A, 61B, 61C, 62-155. The numbering is written in pencil in the top right corner of the folio and encircled. The numbering starts at the front of the file, on the first file enclosure (f 1) and ends on the last enclosure at the back of the file (f 155). The file cover, title page and one blank folio at the front of the file and the inside cover at the back of the file have not been numbered. Folio 3 is folded in half.The most complete secondary foliation system occurs in the second half of the file, where folios 73 to 144 are also numbered 68 to 135 in the top right corner, in pencil but not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains mainly circular memoranda issued by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire to the Political Agent, Bahrain and others. These contain local instructions about personnel management, office administration and several miscellaneous topics, including:Permitted occasions upon which British subjects and British protected persons ashore on both sides of the Persian Gulf might fly the Red Ensign flag, 1928;The classification, translation, copying, transmission and addressing of official correspondence sent by the Political Agencies of the Persian Gulf to the Political Residency at Bushire, 1920s-1940s, together with revised arrangements following the removal of the Residency from Bushire to Bahrain, 1946-1947;Procedures for the importation of personal effects into Persia by Persian Gulf officers and clerks, together with a list of prohibited articles, 1931;Procedures to be followed by clerks in the British Agencies of the Persian Gulf, for obtaining visas for entry into Iran, 1940.The file also contains the Political Resident’s routine reporting requirements about the promotion, transfer, leave, travel and skills of Persian Gulf officers and clerks, together with the Political Agent’s submissions to the Political Resident about these, in respect of Bahrain Agency staff, 1930s-1940s.The file also contains circular letters and memoranda received by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, mainly from Government of India departments, which he then forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain and others for information. These also constitute office instructions on various topics, including:Procedures to be followed by officers and clerks in the Persian Gulf service, claiming the refund of messing charges incurred aboard British and Royal Indian Marine ships when touring on duty, as notified by the Government of India Foreign and Political Department and Marine Department, 1920s;Changes of Persian country and place names made by the Persian Government, 1930 and 1935, as notified by the British Legation, Tehran and the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department;Correct forms of address to be used in official correspondence, as notified by the British Embassy, Baghdad in 1933 and the Office of the Governor-General of India in 1938.The file also contains several miscellaneous items, mainly correspondence, including:Letters of thanks exchanged between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Director of the Persian Gulf Section of the Indo European Telegraph Department in 1931, following the abolition of the lndo European Telegraph Department after 60 years;A copy of the
                                 Imperial Airways Gazette, issue No 7, Volume 7, July 1935.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Office services</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000ac#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>