<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002c7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:03:30.884Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">FILE COPY &lt;jD IlsJD-XEO Any reply to this letter should be addressed to the Director, Petroleum Dept. 1647 PETROLEUM DEPARTMENT ^ (Mines Department), Dean Stanley Street, Telephone: Victoria 8155. Telegrams : Minindust, Sowrst, t Millbank, Reference No.:-P.D. London, S.W.l. 19th Tarch, 1940. Dear Gibson, Your letter P.Z. 147/40, of the 11th January, enclosing copy of a letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf about the sales in British territories of the products of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company and of those of the Bahrein and Hasa fields. I am sorry I have been so long in replying, but I have been awaiting the outcome of a review we have been making for the Oil Control Board of sources of supply of petroleum products with a view to making the best possible use of the tanker tonnage available. This, as you will appreciate, is a conplex problem, and we have not yet been able to secure decisions on some points. Yfe agree that so far as practicable it is desirable that Bnpire countries, such as India, Burma, Australia, New Zealand and South Africa should be supplied to the fullest possible extent by the Anglo-Iranian Oil Conpany. At the moment, however, in view of tanker difficulties, we cannot neglect any opportunity of having these countries supplied by tankers which might not otherwise be available to us, and this I believe is the case v/ith most of the tankers used by Caltex. In these circumstances, any action on the lines sup-bested in Prior’s letter must stand over for J. P. Gibson, Esq. India Office, •Whitehall, S.W. 1. RECb. POL.DEPt. 20MAR940 INDIA OFFICEDraft Paper.The Residency, the 23rd December, 1939. &lt;D Would you please refer to Starling’s letter Uo. P*D. 98/2* Part 2, dated the 8th November 1939, which was forward ed to us with your air mail Printed Letter No.P.Z.7051/39, dated the 20th November 1939 ? 2. When I was in Bahrain, Weightman shov/ed me the programme of the deliveries of the Bahrain Oil Company for the next month or two, and drew my attention to the fact that the vast majority of the consignments were sent to Empire destinations such as India, Burma, Australia, New Zealand and South Africa. It appears to me, however, from what I have heard of the activities of the Anglo-Iranian Oil .Company, that these are markets which they normally cover themselves and that whatever the value of the Bahrain oil may be to us on a long term view, every ton of oil now sent by them to an Empire destination probably means the sale of a ton less by the entirely British Company from Abadan. Could you very kindly ask the Petroleum Department whether this view is correct ? As you are aware neither the Bahrain Petroleum Company nor the California Arabian Standard Oil Company have in any way restricted either their output or their development programme• R.T.Peel Esquire, C.B.E., M.C., The India Office, London. RECo. POL. BEPr.l -9JAM940 I INDIA OFFICE |</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002c7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/324</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002c7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/324</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 147/40 'Oil: question of desirability of supply to British territories by British owned companies'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-05T22:04:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (4 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 6; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The correspondence in this file relates to the desirability of ensuring that supplies of oil to British territories are made, as far as possible, by British owned companies.The main correspondents in the file are the Lieutenant-Colonel Charles Geoffrey Prior (Political Resident in the Persian Gulf), Frederick Charles Starling from the Petroleum Department, and John Percival Gibson and Roland Tennyson Peel from the India Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Oil supply</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Division</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002c7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>