<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00009b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:51:55.578Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Secret. British Protectorate over the Arabian Coast from Shaikh Said to Oman (Muscat). Secret Letter, No. 22, dated 14th February 1873. Secret Letter, No. 38, dated 11th April 1873. 1. In February 1873 the Government of India, in bringing to notice that the Turkish authorities in Yemen had sought to induce the Chiefs of certain tribes near Aden to acknowledge the supremacy of the Sultan, expressed their opinion that any inter ference on the part of the Turkish Government with those Chiefs who had treaties with or received stipends from us was most dangerous to our in terests at Aden, and should be “ most peremptorily “ prevented.” The Government of India further stated that, under certain contingencies, they would be prepared, if Her Majesty’s Government con sidered such a course desirable, to take the Chiefs directly under their protection, and to engage to defend them from aggression. 2. The Secretary of State for India (Duke of Argyll) having telegraphed to the Viceroy (Earl of Northbrook) that the Foreign Office wished for dis tinct proof of the right to take the Yemen Chiefs under protection, the Government of India replied, on the 11th April 1873, that the question of the right of the British Government might be viewed in two aspects, viz., 1st, our right as regards the alleged claims of the Turkish Government, and, 2ndly, our right as regards the Chiefs themselves. 3. With regard to the first aspect of the question, the Government of India mentioned,— (a) That the Chiefs were, and for the last century had been, independent of Turkish influence and control. (b) That the British Government had already entered into treaty relations with these Chiefs, without reference to Turkey or any other foreign Power, and might conclude fresh engagements with them, if deemed expedient. (c) That the Chief of the largest and most im portant tribe, the Abdali, had distinctly claimed British assistance, and asked for protection. (d) That the Chiefs, while independent of Turkey, had not been so of the British Government, which for years had paid them stipends, and frequently interfered to settle their intertribal quarrels. 4. In regard to the question of the rights of the British Government as regards the Chiefs them selves, the Government of India, while considering themselves free to impose any measures on the 16211. I. 2491. A1 I kid Chiefs deemed essential for the safety of Aden, stated that it was far from their intention to have recourse to any forcible measures, and they pro posed to secure the objects in view w r ith the consent of the Chiefs, and by negotiation ■with them. 5. The Duke of Argyll having also inquired as to the extent of protection to be afforded, the Go vernment of India replied that the protection of the British Government should extend to the nine tribes marginally noted,* with whom treaties had been at various times concluded. 6. As to the degree of protection, they thought it would be sufficient,—1st, to require the Chiefs to abstain from political intercourse with foreign Powers without the consent of the British Go vernment, and to refer all disputes with foreign Powers, or with each other, to the British Go vernment for settlement, and, 2ndly, on our part to engage to defend them against unprovoked aggres sion by foreign Powers. 7. The reasons of the Government of India for affording protection to the tribes were communi cated to the Porte by Her Majesty’s Ambassador, with an intimation that protection would probably not be withheld from them if they should ask for it. Assurances were thereupon given by the Turkish Government that it was not their desire to interfere in any way with the tribes in friendly relations with the Government of India, but notwithstanding this disclaimer the local authorities in Yemen continued their encroachments on the independence of the tribes. Further representations were addressed to the Porte, by whom renewed orders were sent to their officials in Arabia to abstain from all inter ference with the independent tribes. 8. The Government of India having pressed for a decision on the question of a Protectorate, the Prime Minister (Mr. Gladstone) recorded his ob jections to this measure in the Memorandum marginally noted.f 9. At this time matters were in a critical state. In spite of the assurances of the Turks, their troops occupied Houshabi and Lahej, and the Viceroy of India had instructed the Besident at Aden to send troops to protect the Sultan of Lahej. The Turkish forces were, however, withdrawn and a collision was averted, and the Porte having made a request for the withdrawal of the British troops, the Secretary of State for India (Duke of Argyll) declined! to admit the right of the Porte to make such a request, “ since the relations of the British “ Government with the tribes around Aden are in- “ dependent of Turkey, whom we do not admit to “ have any locus standi in that region.' The question of a British Protectorate appears to have dropped on the withdrawal of the Turks. * 1. Abd»li (Lahej). 2. Fadhli. 8. Akrabi. 4. Hushibi. 5. Alawi. 6. Amiri. 7. Subahi. 8. Yaffai. 9. Aulaki. f Minute by Lord Granville. I suggest to Mr. Gladstone that we should make another representation to the Porte, telling them that such a measure has been proposed, but, before taking it into con sideration, we think it right to make another representation to them of the absolute ne cessity of their bond fide carrying out their assurances. (Signed) G. October 1873. Memorandum by Mr. Gladstone. I entirely concur in Lord Granville’s memorandum just received. There is every imaginable objection to the proposed Protectorate. It involves the most indefinite obligations. It binds us to support those over whose conduct to others we have no control. It threatens to impair, and that chronically, our good understanding with Turkey, which is so necessary to the peace of the East. Nothing but absolute necessity can warrant our interference, and then only within the limits, moral and local, to which that necessity extends. What we are fairly entitled to ask is, that Turkey shall commit no act of aggression against the Chieftains, and this we have every reason to believe we can obtain from our general experience at Constantinople. It would be unpardonable to make another Gold Coast of this. (Signed) W. E. G. 17th October 1873. X 23rd December 1873.}.Q. In 1874, the Turkish Ambassador in London having, in a note remonstrating against the pro ceedings of the Resident at Aden in sending the rebellious brother of the Sultan of Lahej a prisoner to Aden, advanced a claim on behalf ol the Turkish Government to sovereignty over the tribes “ near Aden ” as well as over the whole of Arabia, to which the Sultan was assumed to be entitled in virtue of the ancient dominion of the Caliphate, the Secretary of State for Eoreign Affairs em- . phatically repudiated these pretensions in a Despatch addressed to Her Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires at Constantinople, dated 30th April 1874. In this Despatch, the terms of which were approved by the Secretary of State for India (Marquis of Salisbury), Lord Derby said :—“ The position which “ the Government of Great Britain has always “ maintained upon this subject is clearly defined. “ As Lord Granville pointed out in his Despatch of “the 30th January, ‘Whatever rights of sove- “ ‘ reignty the Porte, in times gone by, might have “ ‘ had in Yemen, it is notorious that since the “ ‘ year 1633 Yemen has been under the rule of “ ‘ Arab Chiefs independent of the Porte.’ It is “ unnecessary to discuss what was the extent of “ the possessions of the Caliphate, as those posses- “ sions passed out of the occupancy of the Porte “ more than 200 years ago, and fell into the hands “ of independent tribes over whom the Porte did “ not attempt to exercise control until the present “ century, when the troops of Mehemet Ali ex- “ tended their conquests as far as Mocha.” Lord Derby went on to say that Great Britain main tained that the tribes in the vicinity of Aden were entirely independent, and would not permit any interference with those stipendiaries on the part of the Turkish officials, and that Great Britain did not acknowledge the title of the Porte to the country lying at or beyond the mouth of the Red Sea. 11 This announcement was repeated in 1883, on the occasion of a complaint made by Musurus Pasha as to the purchase in February 1882 by the Aden authorities of two villages from the Sultan of Lahej. In his reply, Lord Granville added that he declined to recognize the right of the Porte to raise any question as to the dealings of Her Majesty’s Go vernment with the rulers of Lahej or Dhali. 12. In the autumn of 1885 the subject of British relations with the tribes in the vicinity of Aden, and the difficulties created by Turkish encroachments at Dhali, were considered by Major F. M. Hunter, C.B., and Lieutenant-General Schneider, C.B., formerly Resident at Aden. The main points comprised in the proposals submitted by them are :— («) That the Abdali, Subahi, Akrabi, and Fadhli tribes should be brought under a British Protectorate. (6) That the Hushibi, Alawi, and Lower Yaffai should be induced to agree not to alienate A 2 16211.4 9 3 i territory and not to accept the supremacy of a foreign Power. (c) That the Upper Yaffai and Upper Aulaki should be left independent and unbound by agreements. ((/) That diplomatic pressure on the Porte in respect of the Amiri should be relaxed, and that the tribe’s “ hamlets on the up lands ” should be left to gradual absorption by the Turks, the Chief, and perhaps his son, being allowed to retain a pension. (^) That subordinate tribes, like the Kotaibi, who can trouble the trade routes, should be dealt with, as circumstances arise, directly by the Resident at Aden, and not, as at present, through the nominal responsibility of the Amiri Chief. IS. The Government of India accepted these proposals, but recommended an extension of the scheme of Protectorate by including within it certain tribes* occupying portions of the Hadramaut Coast north-eastwards between Aden and Muscat territory. The Chief of one of these tribes, the Mahri, is also Sultan of Socotra, which has been placed under British protection. The Government of India remarked that in respect of the Hadramaut Coast it had hitherto been their policy to exclude the Turks, and that the intrusion of other foreign Powers might also be very inconvenient, and they summed up their recommendations in the following words : “ We recommend that a small sum of money “ should be spent in establishing once for all an “ effective Protectorate over the Arab tribes from “ Shaikh Saiyid to the frontiers of Oman, thus “ excluding all chance of foreign interference in “ Aden, or between Aden and Muscat. We would “ then ask the Turks to consent to a delimitation “ of our protected territory in the direction of “ theirs. If they agreed, we would enter into a “ formal convention with them. If not, we would “ lay down the limits of our Protectorate without “ their consent, and would require them to respect “ it. As to the Dhali territory, we would make “ some concessions to the Turks if they could in this way be induced to enter into a convention. “ In dealing with other tribes in the vicinity of ‘ Aden, it would be necessary to avoid including within our limits any tracts which would be “ likely of their own accord to gravitate to the Turks ; and the same difficulty might probably “ arise in a more embarrassing form on the “ Hadramaut Coast.” 14. These proposals, however, were not pressed to a conclusion, in consequence of a report from Her Majesty’s Ambassador at Constantinople that the Sultan would feel considerable irritation and anxiety if he heard that any such arrangements were in contemplation. Sir W. White added, that if the negotiations could be conducted quietly with- Secret Letter, 10th August 1886. # Lower Aulaki. Dthiaibi. Dhongaibi. Mahri. Kaieti.5 out attracting attention, it might perhaps be possible to avoid increasing the suspicions of the Sultan in connection with British policy and pro ceedings in that region. 15. The Viceroy of India having been communi cated with telegraphed on the 5th May 1887 that the Resident at Aden was prepared to-undertake negotiations with the tribes other than the Amiri in a manner which would not excite Turkish sus ceptibilities, and that the moment was favourable for dealing with the Mahri. Wahidi, and Akrabi. The Secretary of State for India (Viscount Cross) accordingly proposed to the Foreign Office that the Resident at Aden should take the necessary measures for concluding Protectorate Agreements with the tribes in question. 16. Negotiations were then in progress at Con stantinople for the conclusion of a convention with Turkey in regard to Egypt, and the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs was of opinion that it was very desirable that nothing should occur to excite suspicion or distrust on the part of the Sultan or his ministers, and, in consequence, the Resident at Aden was instructed not to enter into Telegram to Viceroy, 17th May 1887. negotiations with the Aden tribes without further orders. Secret Letter, 19th August 1887. 17. The Government of India having now ex pressed a hope that the scheme advocated by them will not he postponed to “a very distant date,” Viscount Cross has proposed to the Foreign Office that instructions should be issued to negotiate with the Mahri, Wahidi, and Akrabi tribes for the con clusion of Protectorate Agreements, based on the model of our recent treaty with the Sultan of of Socotra, and has solicited an expression of the views of the Marquis of Salisbury on the general scheme of a British Protectorate over the Arabian Coast from Shaikh Said to the borders of Oman. 18 The risk that will be incurred in establishing a British Protectorate over these tribes is that Turkey may protest against the measure as an infraction of her sovereign rights over this portion of Arabia, but Her Majesty’s Government have repeatedly repudiated this claim to sovereignty on the part of the Porte, and, therefore, the pretensions of the Sultan need not be considered an obstacle in the way of sanctioning the proposals of the Govern ment of India. But whether it is prudent in existing circumstances for Great Britain to take a step calculated to provoke the ill will of the Porte is a question for Her Majesty’s Government to decide. E. N. Secret and Political Department, India Office, 1st November 1887.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00009b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B47</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00009b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B47</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'British protectorate over the Arabian coast from Shaikh Said to Oman (Muscat)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1887/1887</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-22T14:40:30</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (4 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at f 136, and terminates at f 139, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 5-149; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same poistion as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This printed memorandum, compiled on 1 November 1887 by E Neel at the Secret and Political Department of the India Office, contains excerpts of correspondence sent and received by the Government of India between 14 February 1873 and 19 August 1887.The main subject is the extension of the British Protectorate scheme to tribes on the Hadramaut [Hadramawt] Coast, between Muscat and Aden.On folio 139 there is a reference to 'Map of Arabian Coast from Shaikh Said to Oman (Muscat)' which says: 'See IOR: Maps W/LPS/18/B.47 (i)'.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office, Assistant Secretary to the Political and Secret Department,</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Aden</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Hadramaut Coast</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Protectorates</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00009b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>