<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00014e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T03:42:35.448Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Previous ReUrences. Later References. R n - m IOR NEG MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE *wigw■ ■' &lt; \t MIL. No. 3 &lt;f ' ,7 / /; .,© Political Agency, Bahrain, the 9th January 1934. To Messrs B.R.Herman and Mohatta Limited, Vulcan Iron works, Queen*s Road and wood Street, KARACHI . Dear Sirs, Would you kindly let me know whether you can supply me wix»h an Admiralty pattern anchor weighing 120 lbs (one hundred and twenty pounds) and forty fathoms (two hundred and forty feet) of 3 ft (three- eighth ) inch chain cable, as used in naval 50* pinnaces. If so, I should be obliged if you would inform me, by air mail, of the price of the anchor and chain and whether it would be available from stock. 2. I should probably require a duplicate set, i.e. two anchors and two 40 fathom lengths of cable. 3.. It would be convenient if you would let me know the approximate weight of 40 fathoms of this cable. d- Yours faithfully, /I Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, BahrainPolitical Agency, Bahrain, the 9th January 1934 Prom Lieutenant Colonel Gordon Loch,I.A*, Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Flag Officer Commanding and Director, Royal Indian Marine, BOMB AY. Sir, I have the honour to enquire whether you can supply me with an Admiralty pattern anchor weighing 120 lbs (one hundred and twenty pounds) and forty fathoms (two hundred and forty feet) of 3 M (three- eighth ) inch chain cable, as used in naval 50* pinnaces. If so, I should be grateful if you would inform me, by air mail, of the price of the anchor and chain and whether it would be available from stock. 2. I should probably require a duplicate set, i.e. two anchors and two 40 fathom lengths of cable. 3. It would be convenient if you would let me know the s approximate weight of 40 fathoms of this cable. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain.TE LEPH O N E: G E R R A R D 6351? TELEGRAMS^ VIDALABAK, PICCY, LONDON. ^ CABLES'- BA SH EE, LONDON. BEA'TLEY’S; CODE. r t F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. The Political Agent, Bahrein, Persian Gulf, CITY OFFICE: 9-10, BOND COURT, WALB ROOK, E.C.A. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE) 20. BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST, W. 1. PLEASE QUOTE N9 J We have the pleasure to enclose herewith statement of account from which you will see there is an amount of £10.1.10 due to us. 7e trust you will agree this figure and give instructions for the amount to he remitted to us. Placing our services entirely at your disposal,\ ir v ) No: From, To. of 33-34. Royal India n jlar ine Headquarters Bomto^^anuary.. t 93 4 / u ?&gt;. ' . © THE FLAG OFFICER COMMANDING. ROYAL INDIAN MARINE The Political Agent, Bahrain. V A Sir, With reference to your letter No. 40, dated 9th January 1934, I have the honour to inform you that the anchors and chain cable can he supplied from stock at the rate quoted below ?. No. 561 - Anchors Iron and Steel Boat iron-stocked 120 lbs ungalvanised. Bate Bs. 28-6-0 each. P. No. 996 - Chain, Cable, iron sea service fitted with ordinary Joining Shackles 3/8'. /, ? » Bate Bs. 8-14-0 per fathom. Approximate weight of 40 fathoms * 3 cwts. 14 lbs. Bates are exclusive of overhead charges of 15 / and subject to audit. I have the honour to be, Sir, ' Your obedient servant. Vice-AdmiralI (U Branch Offices: Charing Cross, LAHORE. and Meerut City. Metal Stock Yards: Jalloo, LAHORE. and Meerut City. CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Telephone No-4 7. T ELEGRAMS: Expansion, Karachi, Code: B e n t l e y’s Phrase. © ESTABLISHED 1883. B R HERMAN $ MOHATTA LTD ENGINEERS AND SHIPBUILDERS VULCAN IRON WORKS QUEENS ROAD 2 WOOD STREET KARACHI ‘ihe Political Agent, LCAL'-o r 'v ■ 0 — 24th January 1934. JKef. No.75/85/w. 7 - f rr. i-JW Vj ^ ptft Dear Sir, ' ' «ie thank you for your esteemed enquiry wo, 39-17/2 of the 9th instant and have pleasure in quoting as followss- 1. 120lbs Admirality Pattern Anchors ... Rs.35/-/- each 2. 40 fathoms 3/8' chain cable... ... 3s. 106/-/-the lot Prices are P.O.b. Jiarachi. Delivery 1 week. Ihe approximate weight of 40 fathoms of 3/8' Chain Cable is 36 0 lbs. ie note you will probably be requiring two sets. iSsteeming your valued orders. lours faithfully,7 'H . n • • X Q ATT A HOM s a ? \\ ;\ C 'AV.'' c\ f '. r ■ x v , T : 3% &lt; c jOOWftaAOH 8W3dUi /. . r AO.. I -■ , &gt; ' jTibis fender isjsi/bjectjtp\the following conditions:— 'ucir, U \ -SJ^Il pnc;es are subject to alteration without notice and to confirmation at the time the order is received. 2. Promises of delivery are given without Guarantee, and; whilst every effort will be made to adhere to them as closely as possible, we_ do not .hold ourselves responsible for delays arising from any cause whatever, and in no case shall delay in delivery be ground for rejecting goods. Offers of delivery of goods from stock are subject to the goods remaining in stock at the time the order is received. t* * ’ ' v ’ 5. All goods will He despatched' at Owner’Risk unless specially arranged to the contrary. We do not hold ourselves responsible for'any damage'that may occur in transit, but if desired Insurance 'can be eFFected By us to cover risk - ,y. •, pf damage, in transit, .rates for whicli wili fee quoted on application 4. ; .Our terms, of payment, are one-third value with order, and balance against Railway Receipts or Shipping Documents. Rupee quotations for goods to be imported for Forward Delivery are based on the Rate of Exchange existing at ’ the time of quoting. Payment must, however, be made based on the Rate of Exchange existing at the time goods are invoiced to the Customer.’ 5. 6 . 7. 8 . Illustrations and Particulars of Machines are not binding and are subject to alteration in detail. ' &gt;'• SC Mien '• . j C . -.-Jc.r eg All goods not of our own manufacture carry the maker's Standard Guarantee beyond which *We accept no'liability. Custorrters are requested to note that when goods are sent by Steamer or Kail, the responsibility of B. R. Herman &amp;- Mohatta Ltd. ceases with the receipt of a clean Bill of Lading or Railway Receipt. In cases of breakage or short delivery, consignees must claim on the Steamer or Railway Company. COUNTERMANDS. The ri S ht is reserved to refuse countermands, which cannot under any circumstances be accepted in the case of goods in process of manufacture or ready for despatch.” X : ,• 'Jo X. ••^xjjjvaoBYAIR^AIL. No.266 /17/2/II. * O' \ v c &lt;■ % ^ r A © Political Agency| Bahrain, the 7th February 1934. To Messrs B.R.Herman and Mohatta Limited, Vulcan Iron Works, Queens Road and Wood Street, KARACHI. Dear Sirs, I beg to refer to your letter No.75/85/W dated the 24th January 1934 and to enquire (a) what the breaking strain of the chain cable is and (b) whether it is - galvanised. it is not galvanised what would the cost and breaking strain of similar galvanised cable. 1 know that galvanised cable is sometimes regarded as less strong than ungalvanised, but as the cable will not be used frequently, it might be preferable to have galvanised cable to prevent rust. I would be glad of your advice. Yours faithfully, A Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain,CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Branches: CHARING CROSS, LAHORE. BAGHPAT ROAD, MEERUT. Metal Stock Yards: JALLC LAHORE a MEERUT Telegrams: EXPANSION, KARACHI, 47 &amp; 326 EXPANSION, LAHORE, 2330. EXPANSION, MEERUT, 206. Telephones: ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD., near Sir, Rej An o h or an d Ch&gt;lg. We thank you for your letter No.266/i7/3/n dated the 7th instant in connection with your above mentioned requirements. ah exit tons* hut the tensile test loads* generally known as the Admiral!ty Proof Loads are approximately equal to the formula* 12 tons* where D is the diameter in inches of the iron of the chain. The Proof Load then works out at 1.6 odd tons, hut the safe working load, when the chain is to he used as crane or sling chains should he taken as half the Proof Load The chain is not galvanized and we would not advise it as the cost is nearly 100* more. If the chain is to he carried on board a launch it should he stowed in a chain hox* with drain holes in the bottom helow deck, and once a week should he laid ENGINEERS &amp; SHIPBUILDERS, CODES: Bentley’s Phrase, 1st &amp;. 2nd; A. B. C. 6th Edition &amp; Universal Trade. Vulcan Iron Works, Queen's Road &amp;. Wood Street, Karachi, 1 * « ary 193 4 7 5/86/W. gSB-AlB Hlf L The Political Agent (4) The breaking strain of the chain offered by us is /I2 - on the deck and the box dried out* A good practice on a launch is to keep a small drum capable of holding say a gallon, and Into this drum, be put all waste oil, which should be kept and used for swabbing the chain before stowing and after each drying. If this practice is carried out the chain will always be in good condition* Yours fai thf^lly, B* H* HBBMAN A/MOHATTA LTD BIBECTOR. BEH/DG/BS.No. 4910 ! . /ft i lO 03 2 , UPPER JAMES STREET GOLDEN SQUARE, W.l. ^/. &lt;Z ' lu'mtn'D jrom^JLi* tjMMxjrf the sum of Po ^ .... / ~ s . Shillings Sfeto- Pi for F. P. BAKER &amp; Co. Ltd. £ / • JD^■asyac ‘V /&gt;*v £tUt no. uzh-nli- Political Agency, Bahrain, the 19th March 1934. To Messrs B.H.Hermem /aid Mohatta Limited Vulcan Iron Works, * wood Street, Queen's Hoad, KARACHI. Dear Sirs, Would you kindly send me a price list of Manilla rope from size \ n to !£”• Please state the length of rope to a coil in each case. Yours faithfully, h) ic Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain.f,y . j ii 1 '* l Hi&gt;i no Sfoiiis 6 ) No. 50&amp;-I7/J.. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21st March 1934. To Messrs P#P* Baker and Company Limited. 2, Upper James Street, Golden Square, Regent Street, LONDON, W.l, Dear Sirs, I should be glad if you would please supply this Agency with the following stores and let me have a bill for payment in due course t- 1. Paint Brush ( for ship painting, size 3'}. 1 dozen 2. Needles for sewing canvas 1 ' 3. Linseed Oil ( boiled ) .10 gal. 4. Turpentine ••.10 N 5. White Enamel Paint (in half gallon tins).. 6 M 6. Red Oxide paint (28 lbs one keg ) •••••• 6 kegs. ?• White Zinc M M ' ' M 12 ' V 8. Phenyle 6 gal. 9. Soda Common ••••.. ••••• 50 lbs. 2« They should be insured and shipped direct in one of the ships of Prank C. Strick and Company Limited. Yours faithfully, Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain^ ^ (&lt;« No. 5si-n It. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 5th April 1934* To Mr* Khalil bin Ibrahim Kanoo, Bahrain* Dear Sir, I am considering the possibility of getting a 50/60 h.p* Kelvin Sngine in the new launch in place of the 70 h*p* fhornycraft Engine which I now have, but the question is largely one of cost* I should be obliged if you would inform me of the price and Specification of the Kelvin Engine and what you would be prepared to offer for the 'Thornycraft Engine, as part payment for the Kelvin Engine* 2* You are at liberty to examine the Thoraycraft Engine at any time if you will kindly inform me or my office a short time before, so that my Engineer may be present* 3* An early reply would be convenient* Yours faithfully, Lieut*Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain*B Y AIR MAIL , No, (oStf- 17 /i. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 17th April 1934, To Messrs B.R.Herman and Mohatta Limited Vulcan Iron .forks, Queen*s Road, wood Street, KARACHI , Hear Sirs, I beg to refer to your letters Nos,75/85/W dated the 24th January and 14th February 1934 respectively, and to request you kindly to supply the followingj- (i) One anchor 120 lbs of Admiralty Pattern Rs.35/- Rs,35/- (ii) Two forty fathoms(two hundred and forty feet each) lengths of 3/3 M (three-eighth) inch chain cable @R?,106/- each Rs.212/- „ 0 tal • • • • • Rs, 247/—&gt; y o • f ^ Form No. Branches l CHARING CROSS, LAHORE. LOKHAN BAZAR, BHAVNAGAR. CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Telegrams I Telephones } % 1 woiw1 1 ■ »n g Jr EXPANSION, KARACHI. 47 &amp; 326- EXPANSION. LAHORE. 2330- EXPANSION, BHAVNAGAR. ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. Engineers, Shipbuilders &amp; Metal Merchants- Codes: Vulcan Iron Works, Queen's Road &amp;. Wood Street. Bentley's Phrase 1st &amp; 2nd A. B. C. 6th Edition &amp; Universal Trade. Karachi, 3ist March 193 4 The Political Agent Dear Sir, . ^ 75/87/S. UtiH PfRSIKHJ^i With reference to your valued enquiry No. 484 - 17 /L dated 19-3-34 for Manilla ropes, we heg to offer our lowest quott tion for the sane f.o.r. Karachi as follows:- M an ilia Pope 'Aeroplane brand' from i£' to 4i“ Cir: @ Es 30/- per cwt. “ 'Light Homs brand' --- do @ Rs 35/- per cwt. Approximately there are 720-ft rope in one coil. The relative samples are sent separately. Soliciting the favour of your valued commands which will receive our immediatel attention. • Yours faithfully, ’tV t Mlf/SN. sfA U( Ul % Subject to the conditions at back hereof. ii.E. &amp; MOHATTA IT1 . This Tender is subject to the following conditions:— All prices are subject to alteration without notice and to confirmation at the time the order is received. 2 . Promises of delivery are given without Guarantee, and, whilst every effort will be made to adhere to them as closely as possible, we do not hold ourselves responsible for delays arising from any cause whatever, and in no case shall delay in delivery be ground for rejecting goods. Offers of delivery of goods..from stock are subject to the goods remaining in stock at the time the order is received. 3. All gocxls will be despatched at Owner’s Risk unless specially arranged to the contrary. We do not hold ourselves responsible for any damage that may occur in transit, b\it if desired Insurance can be effected by us to cover risk of damage in transit, rates for which will be quoted on appli cation (providing an Insurance Company will accept the risk.) 4. Our terms of payment are one-third value with order, and balance against Railway Receipt or Shipping documents. 5. Rupee quotations for goods to be imported for Forward Delivery are based on the Rate of Exchange existing at the time of quoting. Payment must, however, be made based on the Rate of Exchange existing at the time goods are invoiced to the Customer. b. Illustrations and particulars of Machines are not binding and are subject to alteration in detail. 7. All goods not of our own manufacture carry the maker’s Standard Guarantee beyond which we accept no liability. 8. Customers are requested to note that when goods are sent by Steamer or Rail, the responsibility of B. R. Herman &amp; Mohatta, Ltd., ceases with the receipt of a clean Bill of Lading or Railway Receipt. In case of breakage or short delivery, consignees must claim on the Steamer or Railway Company. ‘•COUNTERMANDSThe right is reserved to refuse countermands, which can not under any circumstances be accepted in the case of goods in process of manufacture or ready for despatch.**I f 8. 0, MF. 17-3000—9-33. &lt;ra nchesI CHARING CROSS, LAHORE. LOKHAN BAZAR, BHAVNAGAR. CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Telegrams I Telephones EXPANSION, KARACHI. 47 &amp; 326. EXPANSION, LAHORE. 2330. EXPANSION, BHAVNAGAR. ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. ENGINEERS, SHIPBUILDERS &amp; METAL MERCHANTS, VULCAN IRON WORKS. Codes ! Bentley's Phrase 1st &amp; 2nd A.B.C. 6th Edition &amp; Universal Trade. QUEENS ROAD &amp; WOOD STREET, KARACHI, 21st April 1934 ilie Political Agent, Bahrain . l-t'ersiaT- Aulf). Ref. No. 75/89/«. Dear S ir, We beg to acknowledge the receipt of your valued order No. 654-l7/2dated 17-4-34 for une Anchor and Ito - 40 j« a thorns of Chain cable, This is receiving our prompt attention. Thanking you for the order and assuring you of our best services at all times, am/DU/bS. Yours faithfully, B. R. Herman &amp; Mohatta, Ltd.TELEPHONE: GERRARD 6351* TE LEG RAMS: VIDALABAK, PICCY, LONDON. C A E» _ iS: BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. ! r. CITY OPFICE: 9-10, BOND COURT, WALBROOK, E.C.A. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE) 20, BRIDLE LANE. BEAK ST., W. 1. r The Political Agent, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 2813* PLEASE QUOTE N9 q Lo .U* IN REPLY Bear Sir, In further reference to your order for ships stores No. 7/2&gt; item 8 calls for 6 gallons Phenyle, our suppliers are unable to trace this particular material, and in the circumstances they think that you require Phenol which is used to prevent distemper and other materials deteriorating in tropical temperatures. In the circumstances we have instructed them to supply this. 4 your Placing our services entirely at disposal, We are,Dear Sir, Yours faithfully, P.P. BAKIN AND GO. LTD. S•a***-' 5&gt;0 0 BY A I R MAIL No. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 9th May 1934. To Messrs P.P.Baker and Company Limited, 2, Upper James Street, Golden Square, Regent Street, • LOJTDON, W.l. With re fe re nee to your le tter No•2813/C.D. 9 A date d /v the 20th April 1934, I have to inform you that I do not require Phenol. I require eight gallons of disinfecting fluid for the use of bath rooms and water closets. The makers of this disinfecting fluid are 'The Killgerm Company Limited, Cleekheaton, England'. Yours faithfully0 &gt; &amp; ^ t / 7 TELEPHO N E: GERRARD 6351* TE LEG RAMS! VIDALABAK, PICCY, O NOON. F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. CABLES’- BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. r The Political Agent, Bahrain, Persian PLEASE QUOTE N9 2813. IN REPLY C.D. 9 A. Dear Sir, J h April CITY OFFICE: 9-10, BOND COURT, W A L B ROOK, E.C.A. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE) 20, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST, W. 1. © 193 4 We are duly in receipt of your letter of the 21 st March, ref. 502 / 17 / 2 , and thank you for the esteemed order for ships stores contained therein. We are immediately placing these orders in hand and will despatch at the first opportunity. Placing our services entirely at your disposal. We are,Dear Sir, Yours faithfully, F. P. BAKEl^AND- .CO* LTD.M ®! No '• 7f 7- (7/4 Political Agency f Bahrain, the 10th May 1934# To T^essrs B*H*Herman and Kohatta Limited, Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Hoad, wood Street, KARACHI ♦ Dear Sirs, I beg to refer to your lettar No.76/8?/S dated the 31st March 1934 and to request you kindly to supply the followingi- Two coils of Manilla Rope size 3/8 (three-eighth) inch of Light Horns Brand# Yours faithfully, Jt*' Political /{gent, Bahrain.-v :-y: II'M Tfc : .-.'At. . ^ 4/^-0 w No. 9/3., Political Agency f Bahrain, the 13th May 1934 To Maesrs B # H.Herman and Mohatta Limited, Vulcan Iron Works, Queen* 3 Boad, Wood Street, KARACHI» I enclose a list and am sending you a parcel containing wooden samples and sketches of rudder fittings, which I require for a motor dhow (45* heel, 50-60 h*p*). 2. Would you kindly let me have by air mail an estimate for making them in anti-sea-metal (copper-brass). Dear Sirs, Yours faithfully Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain.— • p.i r Requirements for the Rudder Fittings as oer the following Sketches. 'A' Brackets with 6 brass bolts.and nuts. 'B' Bye bolts with 3 nuts and 6 screws. 'C” Brackets with 15 brass bolts.and nuts.\ ^ CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT Branohbs. CHARii.'TG CROSS, LAHORE. LOKHAN BAZAR, BHAVNAGAR 2- I Telegrams : Telephones. EXPANSION, KARACHI. 47 &amp; 326 EXPANSION, LAHORE. 2330. EXPANSION, BHAVNAGAR. ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. CODES: Bentley’s Phrase 1st &amp; 2nd A. B. C 6th Edition &amp; Universal Trade. ENGINEERS, SHIPBUILDERS &amp; METAL MERCHANTS. Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Road &amp; Wood Street, RACHl, 5 til May The Political Agent, Bah rein. TPeriTSn Gulf). 1/0.5449. D^ar Sir, 1934 , / { Letter of Delivery No. Nil We have pleasure in enclosing Hfarigh KxaryT-ft-g-g-gTfrt dated 5-5-1934. for the undermentioned goods in compliance with order No. 654-17/2 dated 17-4-1934. Trusting the material will arrive safely and esteeming your further orders. \wmmm xzx txxx xxxxy v.xxx xX • Messrs. B. R HERMAN &amp; MO H ATT A Ltd. request Iheir constituents to see, before taking delivery of parcels from Jho Kailway, that the., weights agree exactly with those noted in the Railway Receipts, and also that the parcels have no appearance of having been tampered with in transit. All claims for damage or deficiency must be made a* th e ti me of deliver y as the Railway companies decline all responsibility once a cleir receipt is in iheir hands. N. B —Our responsibility ceases with the de livery of the goods to the Railway ^t Auraclii.1 n .c- v i r © fyNs* SJfy \/&gt; No. glq-r) f\.. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 26th May 1934. To Messrs B*R*Herman and Mohatta Limited, Vulcan Iron Works, Queen 1 s Road Wood Street, ^ WUB * v, &lt; Dear Sirs, A I enclose a Supply Bill No.9223/2 dated the 24th ?!ay 1934 for Ps.256/8/- in full settlement of your hill No.’tf/717 dated the 11th ray 1934, being cost of an anchor and chain cable* 2. Kindly acknowledge receipt* Yours faithfully, '\ &lt;r For Political Agent, Bahrain* Zimi'H iip rii' a» 9 * 0 Form No. 2fe Branches CHARING CROSS, LAHORE. LOKHAN BAZAR, BHAVNAGAR. CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Telegrams l EXPANSION. KARACHI. EXPANSION, LAHORE. EXPANSION, BHAVNAGAR. Telephones ! 47 &amp; 326- 2330. , ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. Engineers, shipbuilders &amp; Metal Merchants- Codes : Bentley's Phrase 1st &amp; 2nd A. B. C. 6th Edition &amp; Universal Trade. Vulcan Iron Works, Queen's Road &amp; Wood Street, Karachi, 28 th May 193 4 . Ref. No. 7 ^- The Political Agent, Bah r ain . (Persian Gulf) Dear sir, We thank you for your valued order No. 797-17/2 of 10th instant, for Manila rope. We regret to advise how ever that we have no stocK of Manila Rope rope size 3/8*. This material is not available in the local market either. We can offer you from stock rope o f l^ w circumference which is equivalent to nearly 1/2' dia.. Will you kindly let us know if rope of this size v.ould be suitable. The material shall be despatched promptly on receipt of your reply. Yours faithfully, SNV/VMG. 3.K.HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA LTD. &gt; Subject to the conditions at back hereof.1. This Tender is subject to the following conditions:— All prices are subject to alteration without notice and to confirmation at the time the order is received. 2. Promises of delivery are given without Guarantee, and, whilst every effort will be made to adhere to them as closely as possible, we do - not hold ourselves responsible for delays arising from any cause whatever, and in no case shall delay in delivery be ground for rejecting goods. Offers of delivery of goods from stock are subject to the goods remaining in stock at the time the prder is received. 3. All goods will be despatched at Owner’s Risk unless specially arranged to the contrary. We do not hold ourselves responsible for any damage that may occur in transit, but if desired Insurance can be effected by us to cover risk of damage in transit, rates for which will be quoted on appli cation (providing an Insurance Company will accept the risk.) 4. Our terms of payment are one-third value with order, and balance against Railway Receipt or Shipping documents* 5. Rupee quotations for goods to be imported for Forward Delivery are based on the Rate of Exchange existing at the time of quoting. Payment must, however, be made based on the Rate of Exchange existing at the time goods are invoiced to the Customer. (k Illustrations and particulars of Machines are not binding and are subject to alteration in detail. 7. All goods not of our own manufacture carry the maker’s Standard Guarantee beyond which we accept no liability. 8. Customers are requested to note that when goods are sent by Steamer or Rail, the responsibility of B. R. Herman &amp; Mohatta, Ltd., ceases with the receipt of a clean Bill of Lading or Railway Receipt. In case of breakage or short delivery, consignees must claim on the Steamer or Railway Company. “COUNTERMANDSThe right i* reserved to refuse countermands, which can not under any circumstances be accepted in the case of goods in process of manufacture or ready for despatch.** Ai llllMp.i ll.ll'P*^ V&gt; CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Branches: CHARiNG CROSS, LAHORE. BAGHPAT ROAD, MEERUT. Metal Stock Yards: JA^'O, LAHORE 6, MEERUT. Telegrams: Telephones: EXPANSION, KARACHI, 47 &amp; 326 EXPANSION, LAHORE, 2330. EXPANSION, MEERUT, 206. ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD., ENGINEERS &amp; SHIPBUILDERS, CODES: Bentley’s Phrase, 1st &amp; 2nd; A. B. C. 6th Edition 6. Universal Trade. PBfi AIK MAtU Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Road &amp; Wood Street, iiie Political Agenfc, • ttatoaln » (Persian liulf). Dear air. KARACHI, u n 0 1934 Ref. No. 75/91/* # / A -IY 3 - ^ We thank you for your letter irfo v 8i2 dated the 13th may* in which you say that a parcel containing wooden samples and sketches had heen sent us« We regret to say that these samples did not reach us in time to allow us to quote hy last Air Mail* ihey arrived per S.S. •Vasna'. We trust their late arrival has not greatly inconve nienced you, ahd we now quote for them* Xfe 0 g-A 2 Hudder -Brackets 11* long x 2* de*p x S/8* thick. ... ••• ••• ••• - Ss«22”0-0 the lot. 1kem_&amp; 3 Eye nolts complete with nut and wood screws 8s*35-0»0 the lot • e • item C 3 Brackets 27* long x 2* deep x 3/8- thick with holts. ••• k.46-0-0 -the lot' : &gt; - - '' ' ^| V? CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Branches: CHAR^MG CROSS, LAHORE. BAGHPAT ROAD, MEERUT. Metal Stock Yards: O, LAHORE a MEERUT. Telegrams: Telephones: EXPANSION, KARACHI, 47 a 326 EXPANSION, LAHORE, 2330. EXPANSION, MEERUT, 206. ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD., CODES: Bentley’s Phrase, 1st a 2nd; A. B. C. 6th Edition a Universal Trade. ENGINEERS &amp; SHIPBUILDERS, Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Road a Wood Street, KARACHI, Ref. No. - 2 - 193 i tem B 2 ^rackets 11* long x 2' deep x 3/8* thick mlth holts 3/8* x 3/4** long ••• 0s.35-0-0 the lot item_B 1 icudder *in ll f long x l' diameter V with collar and grub screws, rin to have round head*.. ... ••• ••• 0s # 35-0-0 ihe whole supply, with the exception of Item 3, will he made of the best quality brass and copper, care fully oast and well finished. Item 3 will be made from the best quality bronze bar. *e trust the above prices are acceptable, to you, and that we shall in due course be instructed to carry out the work. xours faithfully, x&gt;.H. iflrajUN &amp;/U0HATTA LTD. P/flZ &gt;*'- ' « •• DIRB0T0S. ber/do/bs.C VY, MACKENZIE *'C9 AND GRAY, PAUL &amp; C9 LIMITED Telegraphic Address: 'mespersV Codes used: Bentley's Complete Phrase Code. SaatfeTiLiiHT-Cdiliun. T’ae PolicicsA.1 Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We send you herewith per hearer a small box which was brought forward by the s.s• *Barod&amp;* as a favour parcel. Please acknowledge 7t5ceipt. The Glundai'U Snipping Cod2 A.B-.O-S* 1 * CWriuii, N? ' 6 tn JUUE /&lt;? 34 Yours faithfully, 'fat LNo. il}. political Agency f Bahrain, the 7th June 1934. To The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited, BAHRAIN . Dear Sirs, The small box forwarded with your letter No.L/418 dated the 6th June 1934 has been duly received with many thanks. Yours faithfully, 4 For * oliVical \gent, Bahrain, (2 ?-6i h? i 1 1 TELEPHO NE: G E R R A R D 63 51* '' L E G R A fwf s: V I tp , ABAK, PICCY, LONDON. CABLES’. BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. r F. P. Ba ker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, , GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. ;i865) ;) CITY OFFICE: l 'VJ 9-10, BOND COURT, WALB ROOK, E.C.A. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. warehouse (Entrance; 20, bridle Lane, BEAK ST., W. 1. The Political Agent, Bahrein, PERSIAN GULF. I# ATT C ^L Rejt 'o .).^ 7 S 1 ? 1934 J PLEASE QUOTE N9 Jl 63 2 • IN REPl C. D. 9 A. 23rd May 193 Dear Sir, (r * '1 'He are very sorry indeed /o see from your letter of the 9th inst. No. 789-17/5 to hand that the Phenol despatched to you is not what you r equire. We trust, however, in view of the fact that it has already 'been shipped, you will he able to make use of it. ¥e also see fro?i your further enquiry that you require disinfecting fluid for the use of hath rooms and water closets, and in accordance with your request we enclose herewith details of the Killgerm fluid, the manufacturers quoted as under: Killgerm Black or white disinfecting fluid, guaranteed Rideal-¥alker co efficient 18/20 in 10 gallon drums... in net io£ 5/6, 10 gal 7.on drums Cj tf »l wholesale price: 3/- 3A pe: and 2/1 2/5 subject of 5/* hor^e in due course These are the to our commis be favoured with*your esteemed instructions to supply. ¥e are,Dear »3ir, Yours fait) 4 - 1 *”' 1 F.P.BAKEJ gallon ft only toI ft—20 times stronger than pure Carbolic Acid—Killgerm Fluid is the most highly concentrated disinfectant manufactured ^day. Killgerm, too, is non-corrosive—it will not burn or stain —it is non-injurious. Killgerm is soluble in cold water—it mixes instantly. Killgerm Fluid is not only a disinfectant, it is a deodorizer and an antiseptic. Killgerm Fluid is economical Killgerm Fluid is economical to use—it goes further than any other disinfectant. For all ordinary purposes, one part Killgerm Fluid to four hundred parts water is sufficiently strong. One teaspoonful of Killgerm will give you four pints of first- grade disinfectant. Each batch tested by of5r own bacteriologists &gt;—vrhe Killgerm Co., Ltd., have special facilities for obtain ing the raw materials and up-to-date methods of manufacture. Killgerm Fluid is supplied in various grades. It has a guaranteed co-efficient by the Rideal Walker test against Bacillus Typhosus. And at every stage of manufacture Killgerm is subject to the famous Killgerm laboratory ^sts by qualified chemists. Above is a section of the Killgefm Laboratory in which the quality of Killgerm Fluid is safe guarded. Killgerm daily tests are your safeguard against inferior disinfectant fluid. INION - COMOSIIV/I WIIILL NOT IBy U INI Ml II &gt;X&lt; IE S IF U IE IE ILif WITH COLD WAT IE 1 ! KILLGERM KEEPS FAITH WITH CUSTOMERS Made from Chemically Pure A^ds made in our own works Killgerm is made from chemically pure acids and manufactured in the most up- to-date plant in this country. Killgerm has special facilities for obtaining the purest and finest raw materials. Killgerm therefore, is 100% dependable. Consist ent dependability to the last drop. You can use Killgerm for every need and be sure it is germicidal. I THE CONSISTENT DISINFECTANT'gSlemorcmdum. Teuegramss EXPANSION, KARACHI. Cooes: BENTLEY’S PHRASE. Telephone No. 47. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA LTD. VULCAN IKON WORKS. Enginssrs, Founders &amp; General Contractors, QUEENS ROAD, &amp; WOOD STREET, No. K a rac h ftth v une 1^4 To c The Political Agent, . o / A^ /7 £ A H B A I K . •ssr——- Sir. ) We beg to acknowledge with thanks the receipt of your favour No 86r9 - 17/2 dated 26 th May 34* covering y T(1T1 f or 256/8/- (Rupees Two hundred fifty six annas eight^nly. in full settlement of our Bill No. W/717 tor which xxxtivxxixxxifajdxkrxxxxiiexk please find enclosed stamped receipt. Esteeming your further orders. Yours faithfully, B. R. HERMAN MO IIATT A Ltd. lj, ii, i j.uj iiimy (t i s\\* Enclo'. Beceip tO^vu-v? 0 CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Branches’ C. ING CROSS. LAHORE. LOKHAN BAZAR, BHAVNAGAR. Form No. 2« Telegrams? Telephones 3 EXPANSION, KARACHI. 47 &amp; 326- EXPANSION. LAHORE. 2330. EXPANSION. BHAVNAGAR. ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. Engineers, shipbuilders &amp; Metal Merchants- Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Road &amp;. Wood Street, Codes: Bentley’s Phrase 1st &amp; 2nd A. B. C. 6th Edition &amp; Universal Trade. Karachi, 20 th jane 193 4 . Ref. ITo. 75/92. The political Agent, £a hra i n. (Persia n Gulf) Dear sir, / X We are in receipt of your-letpo. 961/17/2 dated the 11 th instant and thank you for your order contained therein. The work has 'been put in hand and we hope to ship the completed materials in a fortnight. Yours faithfully, B.R.F5RL1AY / MOYA IT A LTD. Director. SBH/ViiG. I Subject to the conditions at back hereof.1* Ibis Tender is subject to the following conditions:— All prices are subject to alteration without notice and to confirmation at the time the order is received. 2. Promises of delivery are given without Guarantee, and, whilst every effort will be made to adhere to them as closely as possible, we do not hold ourselves responsible for delays arising from any cause whatever, and in no case shall delay in delivery be ground for rejecting goods. Offers of delivery of goods from stock are subject to the goods remaining in stock at the time the order is received. 3. All goods will be despatched at Owner’s Risk unless specially arranged to the contrary. We do not hold ourselves* responsible for any damage that may occur in transit, but if desired Insurance can be effected by us to cover risk of damage in transit, rates for which will be quoted on appli cation (providing an Insurance Company will accept the risk.) 4. Our terms of payment are one-third value with order, and balance against Railway Receipt or Shipping documents. 5. Rupee quotations for goods to be imported for Forward Delivery are based on the Rate of Exchange existing at the time of quoting. Payment must, however, be made based on the Rate of Exchange existing at the time goods are invoiced to the Customer. 6. Illustrations and particulars of Machines are not binding and are subject to alteration in detail. 7. All goods not of our own manufacture carry the maker’s k Standard Guarantee beyond which we accept no liability. 8. Customers are requested to note that when goods are sent by Steamer or Rail, the responsibility of B. R. Herman &amp; Mohatta, Ltd., ceases with the receipt of a clean Bill of Lading or Railway Receipt. In case of breakage or short delivery, consignees must claim on the Steamer or Railway Company. COUNTERMANDSThe right is reserved to refuse countermands, which can not under any circumstances be accepted in the case of goods in process of manufacture or ready for despatch.'*I® 8. 0. M.—F. 17—3000—&gt;9-33. Branches! CH NG CROSS, LAHORE. LOKHAN BAZAR, BHAVNAGAR. CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Telegrams Telephones EXPANSION, KARACHI. 47 4 326. EXPANSION, LAHORE. 2330. EXPANSION, BHAVNAGAR. ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD ENGINEERS, SHIPBUILDERS &amp;. METAL MERCHANTS, VULCAN IRON WORKS. QUEENS ROAD &amp;. WOOD STREET, KARACHI, 20 th Jane 193 4 Tine Political Agent, Bahrain. ^Persian Oulf) Dear S ir. Ref. No. 75/95/y/. We beg to acknowledge / the receipt of your valued order No. 961-l7/2 dated 11-6-34. for £aac .h parts. I | This is receiving our prompt attention. Thanking you for the order and assuring you of our best services at all times,CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Branches: CHARING CROSS, LAHORE. BAGHPAC ROAD, MEERUT. Metal Stock Yards: JA^O, LAHORE a MEERUT Telegrams: TelephonesV EXPANSION, KARACHI, 47 a 326 EXPANSION, LAHORE, 2330. EXPANSION, MEERUT, 206. ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD., secured \9i tb copper rivets* It is absolutely esseuti?! tLet nil straps are fitted very snugly to the wood, and then drawn well together. To achieve this withe brass bolt and cut, without stripping the thread or ehearin the bolt nil p ether is, to ray the least of it, difficult. *ith copper rivets, the constant hamrering required to head the ends, draws the two straps together in such a manner as to .ake them fit closely to the timber, my thing siacK in r. helm fitting in the constant cause of trouble and anxiety, specially for a rudder such as yours which has a pin 11 ft. long. ENGINEERS &amp; SHIPBUILDERS, CODES: Bentley’s Phrase, 1st &amp; 2nd; A. B. C. 6th Edition &amp; Universal Trade. Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Road &amp; Wood Street, SX^lrJjaij The Political Agent, fia hrft i m. ( Persian Crulf) I)eta six'. Fu r t h er to our i c t: er a ck n ow i ed.g i ng y o orCONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Branches: Telegrams: Telephones: J/. JD, LAHORE &amp; MEERUT CHARING CROSS, LAHORE. BAGHPAT ROAD, MEERUT. Metal Stock Yards: EXPANSION, KARACHI, 47 &amp; 326 EXPANSION, LAHORE, 2330. EXPANSION, MEERUT, 206. ESTABLISHED 1883. . HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD., Te would suggest that the holes In the straps he enlarged to 1/2' and copper rivets used in preference to bolts *nd nuts. 7e note you have ordereb the rudder straps with £ jaft openiog of 2’ and assume the thieic ,e r of the fini shed rudder is 2e3/4« allow! iig 3/8 ,, on each side for the _ 1 1 ps which shoulb )e sunk into the wood to the thickness of the brass, thereby taking the weight 01 the rudber on ■ ■ f t )p edges of straps and not on the rivets or bolts* *e. are sending this letter by Mr ail on the /th . ictant and it will, we think, reach you on the 29th. If then you will kindly cable or lolt«, we shall uoderstand the former to uean that all holts and nuts ordered are to be substituted by i/£' copper hai rivets of suitable lengths for rivet ting and if the latter, to send what you have ordered* ’'very thing will bo 'Hade re^ay and on receipt of your cable we shall bore the holes* rough pencil sketch of your bqat’s or r , J(1(ier pogt . CODES: Bentley’s Phrase, 1st &amp; 2nd; A. B. C. 6th Edition &amp;. Universal Trade. ENGINEERS &amp; SHIPBUILDERS, Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Road &amp;. Wood Street, KARACHI, 193 2 Ref. No. The prices will remain the sr.xe. Fhouia you flesire, ana if you •' send us aBranches: CHARING CROSS, LAHORE. BAGHPAT ROAD, MEERUT. Metal Stock Yards: J. -O, LAHORE a MEERUT v&lt; CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. ESTABLISHED 1883. © Telegrams: Telephones: EXPANSION, KARACHI, 47 a 326 EXPANSION, LAHORE, 2330. EXPANSION, MEERUT, 206. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD., ENGINEERS &amp; SHIPBUILDERS, CODES: Bentley’s Phrase, 1st a 2nd; A. B. C. 6th Edition a Universal Trade. Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Road a Wood Street, KARACHI, 193 5. Ref. No. and the rudder, we nay he able to offer ?one helpful surges tion. BEH/VMG-.r' l ^onn No. 2S CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Branches: CHARING CROSS, LAHORE. LOKHAN BAZAR, BHAVNAGAR. Telegrams Telephones : EXPANSION, KARACHI. 47 &amp; 326 EXPANSION, LAHORE. 2330- EXPANSION, BHAVNAGAR. ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. Engineers- Shipbuilders &amp; Metal Merchants- Codes: Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Road &amp;• Wood Street, Bentley’s Phrase 1st &amp;. 2nd A. B - C. 6th Edition A Universal Trade. A) Karachi, 7 th July Ref. No. 75/96. 1934. The Political Agent, Bahrei n. (Persian Oulf) Dear sir, Hel m fittings. Your above fittings are ready and packed and will he shipped to you by the Mail Steamer leaving here on Sunday the 8th instant; we trust they will reach you safely. In the box of fittings, will be seen three 1“ steel bolts, made to fit the rudder pin holes exactly. We have included these to help your boat builders to fit the rudder correctly. • We may say that, it is by no means an easy job to fit a rudder having five hinges with a single pin ll* long. Great care must be taken and if our following suggestions are carried out in sequence we think the job will be done with the minimum of trouble. It would De if at a future date, ^ C'tTKS/cLzr you wish to fit another such rudderthe advisability of Subject to the conditions at back hereof.1. I his lender is subject to the following conditions:— All prices are subject to alteration without notice and to confirmation at the time the order is received. 2. Promises of delivery are' given without Guarantee, and, whilst every effort will be made to adhere to them as closely as possible, we do not hold ourselves responsible for delays arising from any cause whatever, and in no case shall delay in delivery be ground for rejecting goods. Offers of delivery of goods from stock are subject to the goods remaining in stock at the time the or der is received. . 3. All goods will be despatched at Owner’s Risk unless specially arranged to the contrary. We do not hold ourselves responsible for any damage that may occur in transit* but if desired Insurance can be effected by us to cover risk of damage in transit, rates for which will be quoted on appli cation (providing an Insurance Company will accept the risk.) 4. Our terms of payment are one-third value with order, and balance against Railway Receipt or Shipping documents. •5. Rupee quotations for goods to be imported for Forward Delivery are based on the Rate of Exchange existing at the time of quoting. Payment must, however, be made based on the Rate of Exchange existing at the time goods are invoiced to the Customer. Illustrations and particulars of Machines are not bindino- and are subject to alteration in detail. • /. All goods not of our own manufacture carry the maker’s Standard Guarantee beyond which we accept no liability. 8. Customers are requested to note that when goods are sent by Steamer or Rail, the responsibility of B. R. Her max &amp; Mohatta, Ltd., ceases with the receipt of a clean Bill of Lading or Railway Receipt. In case of breakage or short delivery, consignees must claim on the Steamer or Railway Company. ‘COUNTERMANDS: ^jjj|||g|p||j(p|^-ved to refuse countermands, which can any circumstances be accepted in the case of goods in manufacture or ready for despatch.*’ not under process ofB, R« HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. / A 2. utilising only 3 tiinges, of stouter construction and with 3 separate holts, one for each hinge, in preference to a , -tv pin, runing in one length from top to bottom, through five a hinges. We have not a drawing of your craft,hut we can guess roughly and enclose a sketch which should he read in conjunction with the following suggestions. 1. Mark off in pencil or chalk the approximate position of the hinges on both the St(Hh/post (S) and the Rudder ( R ) • 2. Fit the bottom S hinge so that the top edge f (Z- is at exactly 90° to the line of the ste* post. Use a steel square to determine this. 3. Fit the Bottom R hinge. If possible, to get the correct position of this hinge, pack up the rudder into position, and with a straight edged piece of wood or steel rule, draw in pencil an extension of the line given by the top edge of the bottom hinge S. This line will then give the exact position for the bottom edge of the hinge R. 4. fit the top hinge S. 5. Put the rudder in position, slip a steel pin through the bottom hinge, and mark off the exact position of the top hinge R. 6. Drill one hole only and secure the top hinge R, with one bolt and nut for the time being.B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA; LTD. r-\ 3. 7. Slide the brass pin into position, first removing the steel pin in the bottom hinge, and see that the rudder moves freely, 8. Remove the rudder slide the brass pin through all S hinges and tightly fix the 3rd 4th and 5th s hi ng es. % 9, Remove the brass pin, replace the rudder and put steel pins into the top and bottom hinges. 10. Mark off correctly the positions of the R hinges 3, 4, &amp; 5. 11. Fix No. 3 R hinge with one hole and one bolf&gt; and nut for the time being. 12. Fix 4 &amp; 5 in the same way, being careful to put the brass pin through after each temporary fitting of the hinges. 13. When all are fitted and the brass pin in through all the hinges^ wi thou t removing the rudder^ drill out the remaining holes of the hinges R 3, 4 &amp; 5 / put in the copper bolts and rivet them up. Then take out the temporary bolts and put in the -$ast of the copper rivets. 14. Test all rivets, by placing your finger on one end so that the finger makes contact^at the same time^with the rivet and the brass strap. Hit the other end of the rivet lightly with a hammer. If any movement between the brass and copper if felt, the rivet is slack•&gt;t&lt;.rrTM&lt;raTy*,ror,'J' c J\ B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. 4. 'bat if the soaad is hard aodno movement is felt the rivet is tight. We trust the above suggestions will he of use to you, and that you will not hesitate to write to us, should you require any further information. Yours faithfully, B. R. DIRECTOR. behAmg.r*!+ ~~ m* v - CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Brunches. CHARING CROSS, LAHORE. LOKHAN BAZAR, BHAVNAGAR. Telegrams: Telephones: EXPANSION, KARACHI. 47 &amp; EXPANSION, LAHORE. 2330. EXPANSION, BHAVNAGAR. ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. Codes. Bentley’s Phrase 1st &amp; 2nd A. B. C. 6th Edition &amp; Universal Trade. ENGINEERS, SHIPBUILDERS &amp; METAL MERCHANTS. Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Road &amp; Wood Street, KARACHI, 7th _July 193 4 The Political Agent, Bahrain, w IV T) Dear Sir. Letter of Delivery ^Lading We have pleasure in enclosing 3Bciflax«:X3|Cia:xKKXjcr No. 72 7 7.7.34 dated Arith order No. 961-17/2 D/ll.6.34 for the undermentioned goods in compliance A i Trusting the material will arrive safely and esteeming your further orders. EnclJ- Letter of Delivery 2 C/s Contg. Yours faithfully, 2 Nos. Ruider Brackets 11' longx2'deep B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, Ltd. x3/8 thick. 3 Nos. Bye holts complete with nuts &amp; wood screws. 3 Nos. Brackets 27* long x 2' deep x 3/8' thick. 2 Nos. ' 11' ' x 2' ' x ' with holts &amp; 3/8' x 3-4 ' long. 1 No. Rudder pin 11' long x 1' Di~. with collars &amp; gruh x&amp;s£x screws. VLT. 1 IMPORTANT SEE OVERLEAF.* \ 1^1 | Messrs. B. R. HERMAN «fc MOHATTA Ltd. request their constituents to see, before taking delivery of parcels from the Railway, that the weights agree exactly with those noted in the Railway Receipts, and also that the parcels have no appesrnce of having been tampered with in transit. All claims for damage or deficiency must be made ^ the time of delivery as the Railway companies decline all responsibility once a clear receipt is in their hands. N. B: —Our responsibility ceases with the delivery of the goods to the Railway at Katachi. — y-rrrrrr*-—*— s ~—f ft Tj n j £ X^ © CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Branches CHARING CROSS, LAHORE. LOKHAN BAZAR, BHAVNAGAR. Form No. 2» Telegrams I Telephones i EXPANSION, KARACHI. 47 &amp; 326- EXPANSION, LAHORE. 2330. EXPANSION, BHAVNAGAR. ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. Engineers. Shipbuilders &amp; Metal Merchants- Codes: Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Road &amp;. Wood Street, Bentley’s Phrase 1st &amp;. 2nd A. B. C. 6th Edition &amp; Universal Trade. Karachi, 3rd July 193 4 Itt The political Agent, Bahrein. (Persian &amp;ulf) Dear sir, OyA* We thank you for your cable reading ' Expansion Karachi - Rivets - political. w from which we understand that all dolts and outs ordered are to 'be replaced dy 1/2* Copper Bar rivets. The fittings are all ready for doring and will de despatched dy the steamer leaving this port on Sunday next the 8th July. Yours faithfully, B.R.HEB^N/&amp; MOHATTA LTD. DIRECTOR. BBH/VMG. Subject to the conditions at back hereof.1. This Tender is subject to the following conditions All prices are subject to alteration without notice and to confirmation at the time the order is received. 2. Promises of delivery are given without Guarantee, and, whilst every effort will be made to adhere to them as closely as possible, we do not hold ourselves responsible for delays arising from any cause whatever, and in no case shall delay in delivery be ground for rejecting goods. Offers of delivery of goods from stock are subject to the goods remaining in stock at the time the order is received. 3. All goods will be despatched at Owner’s Risk unless specially arranged to the contrary. We do not hold ourselves responsible for any damage that may occur in transit, but if desired Insurance can be effected by us to cover risk of damage in transit, rates for which will be quoted on appli cation (providing an Insurance Company will accept the risk.) d. Our terms of payment are one-third value with order, and balance against Rail ivay-Receipt or Shipping documents. . •J. Rupee quotations for goods to be imported for Forward Delivery are based on the Rate of Exchange existing at the time of quoting. Payment must, however, be made based on the Rate of Exchange existing at the time goods are invoiced to the Customer. b. Tllustiations and particulars of Machines are not bindino* and are subject to alteration in detail. /. All goods not of our own manufacture carry the maker’s Standard Guarantee beyond which we accept no liability. 8. Customers are requested to note that when goods are sent by Steamer or Rail, the responsibility of B. R. Herman &amp; Mohatta, Ltd., ceases with the receipt of a clean Bill of Lading or Railway Receipt. In case of breakage or short delivery, consignees must claim on the Steamer or Railway Company. '‘COUNTERMANDSThe right,', reserved to retese countermand., which can not under any c.rcm.tances be accepted in the case of good, in process of manufacture or ready for de8patch. ,, --\ V c A » i1. This Tender is subject to the following conditions All prices are subject to alteration without notice and to confirmation at the time the order is received. every effort will be made to adhere to them as closely as 7. All goods not of our own manufacture carry the maker’s Standard Guarantee beyond which we accept no liability. 8. Customers are requested to note that when goods are sent by Steamer or Rail, the responsibility of B. R. Hekm w &amp; Mohatta, Ltd., ceases with the receipt of a clean Bill of Lading or Railway Receipt. In case of breakage or short delivery, consignees must claim on the Steamer or Railway Company. J 2. Promises of delivery are given without Guarantee, and, whilst ;iit- .MinjfL-i io hi Lera non m detail'. “COUNTERMANDS: The right i&gt; reserved to refuse countermands, which can not under any circumstances be accepted in the case of goods in process of manufacture or readj for despatch.' process ofF. P. Ba ker &amp; Co. Ltd. TELEPHO N E: QERRARD 63S1* TELEG 'I-^Va B A rams: K , P I C C Y, LON DyO N. CABLE*'. BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. The Political Agent Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 4+to •V'* CITY OFFICE: 9-10, BOND COURT. WALBROOK, E.C.A. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LfP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE} 20, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST., W. 1, PLEASE QUOTE NP /J WH. ,N reply 29th May 193 4 2313. i Dear Sir, we have pleasure in enclosing herewith one Bill of Lading and Clearing invoices covering the shipment of 22. packages, containing. Oil, Turpentine, paint, brushes, and a steel safe etc., ordered by you, marked as under, per the s.s. -cm OP CHRISTiBiA’*, which vessel sailed from London on the 24th May, and is we understand from the shipping Company due at Bahrain on about the 21st June, 1934. We have to remind you that it will be necessary for you to surrender the attached documents to the shipping company*s Agents at Bahrain to enable you^ to obtain release of the packages. lours faithfully, sAKSK &amp; CO.,LTD. BAHRlIBNo. 504 IMPERIAL ECONOMIC CONFERENCE H. REEVES &amp; CO.. 32 St. Mary Axe, E.C.3 (1) Here insert Manager, Chief Clerk, or as the case may be. (2) Here insert name of firm or company. (3) Here insert name of city or country. (4) These words should be omitted where the manu facturer or supplier himself signs the Certificate. (5) Here insert particulars of any special arrange ment. (6) Insert ' United Kingdom ” or name of other part of British Dominions. 27/9/33 • FORM “B.” '' • Combined Certificate of Value and of Origin and Invoice of Goods for Exportation to British Colonies. I, (1) of (2) of (3) manufacturer , A . , of the goods enumerated in this invoice amomitmg to. suppher D hereby declare that I J(4) have the authority to make and sign this certificate on behalf of the aforesaid manufacturer supplier and that I] have the means of knowing and do hereby certify as follows:— * * * *. v VALUE. 1. That this invoice is in all respects correct and contains a true and full statement of the price actually paid or to be paid for the said goods, and the actual quantity thereof. . 2.., That no arrangements or understanding affecting the purchase price of the said goods have been or will be made or entered into between the said exporter and purchaser,, or by anyone on behalf of either of them either by way of discount, rebate, compensation or in any manner whatever other than as fully shown on this invoice, or as • • o . follows (5).. ORIGIN. (In the case of goods exported to Gambia, Gold Coast or Sierra Leone the following portion of the Certificate dealing with Origin should be struck out.) (Delete whichever of 3 (a) or 3 (6) is not applicable. If 3 (a) is used delete 4 and 5. If 3 (b) is used insert . required particulars in 4 and 6.) 3. (a) That every article mentioned in the said invoice has been wholly produced or manufactured in (6) » 3. r (b) That every article mentioned in the said invoice has been either wholly or partially produced or manufactured in (6) - 4. As regards those articles only partially produced or manufactured in (6) (a) That the final process or processes of manufacture have been performed in that part of the British Dominions. * (b) That the expenditure in material produced in (6) and/or labour performed in (6) calculated subject to qualifications hereunder, in each and every article is not less than °i^? t F t jt h 0 f the factory or works cost of such article in its finished one-half J state. (See Note below.) 6. That in the calculation of such proportion of produce or labour of the (6) none of the following items has been included or considered— “ Manufacturer’s profit or remuneration of any trader, agent, broker, or other person “ dealing in the articles in their finished condition: royalties: cost of outside ' packages or any cost of packing the goods thereinto; any cost of conveying “ insuring, or shipping the goods subsequent to their manufacture.” Dated at this day of, 19. Witness Signature Note. —In the case of goods which have at some stage entered into the commerce of, or undergone a process of manufacture in a foreign country, only that labour and material which is expended on or added to the goods after their return to the United Kingdom shall be regarded as the produce or manufacture of the United Kingdom in calculating the proportion of United Kingdom labour and material in the factory or works cost of the finished article.\ jmo. 504. IMPERIAL ECONOMIC CONFERENCE. hTreeves sTax. ,, |J •* 32S..M^A«e, ^ lo FORM B. _ _ • * * ' t A-J . . Combmed Certificate of Value and of Origin and Invoice of Goods » _ for Exportation to British Colonies. (1) Here insert ■ t ' ■ t ' ■' Manager, Chief Clerk, or as the case may be. 1 .A.1JBILRT....'i£D.WARD■ (1) ^.c.CQ.untaitt.*.... (2) Here insert ’ name of firm or of (2) •F-i-F i BAK13R-&amp;-00vLTB'rf of ( 3 ) London company. (3) Here msert 'nf the goods enumerated in this invoice amounting to name of city or suppher (4) UU These words hereby declare that I [(4) have the authority to make and sign this certificate on behalf of the should be omitted n*uwifaet«Fes- where the manu- aforesaid ^—t—-— and that I] have the means of knowing and do hereby certify as facturer or supplier' supplier .*■. .* himself signs the „ - : . . - . Certificate. tOllOWS :— . . - . . . VALUE. 1. That this invoice is in all respects correct and contains a true and full statement of the price actually paid or to be paid for the said goods, and the actual quantity thereof. 2. That no arrangements or understanding affecting the purchase price of the said goods have been or will be made or entered into between the said exporter and purchaser, or by anyone on behalf of either of them either by way of discount, rebate, compensation or in any manner whatever other than as fully shown on this invoice, or as particulars of any follows (5) special arrange ment. • -.‘I v..- ) ORIGIN. (In the case of goods exported to Gambia, Gold Coast or Sierra Leone the following portion of the Certificate dealing with Origin should be struck out.) (Delete whichever of 3 (a) or 3 (b) is not applicable. If 3 (a) is used delete 4 and 6. If 3 (b) is used insert required particulars in 4 and 5.) 3. (a) That every article mentioned in 3. (b) That every article mentioned in the said invoice has been wholly produced or the said invoice has been either wholly or manufactured in (6) .U„K.« ^ar&amp; 0 #VyT&gt;roduced or manufactured in (6) Insert “ United Kingdom ” or name of other part of British Dominions. ( 6 ). (e; 4. As regards those articles Afaiy paj&gt;fially produced manufactured in (а) That the final process or processes of manufacture have been performed in that part of the^British Dominions. (б) That the expenditure irynaterial pro^aCed in (6) B labour performed in f#) calculated to qualifications Weunder, in each and every article is not less the factory or works cost of such article in its finished one-*'' 1 */ ^ J state. lote fw.) That in they calculation of such proportion of produce or labour of the .y/.nonb of the following items has been included or considered— “ Manufactvfrer’a profit or remuneration of any trader, agent, broker, or other person “ dealing dir^the articles in their finished condition : royalties : cost of outside “ packages or any cost of packing the goods thereinto; any cost of conveying ' insuring, or shipping the goods subsequent to their manufacture.” Witness Dated at L.Qilp.Q.H*.. this £.d.1iiu...day of .... 19 .. 34 . Note.—I n the case of goods which have at some stage entered into the commerce of, or undergone a process of manufacture in a foreign country, only that labour and material which is expended on or added to the goods after their return to the United Kingdom shall be regarded as the produce or manufacture of the United Kingdom in calculating the proportion of United Kingdom labour and material in the factory or works cost of the finished article. 27/9/33D&gt; * * No. 504. H. REEVES &amp; CO.. 32 St. Mary Axe, E.C.3 (1) Here insert Manager, Chief Clerk, or as the case may be. (2) Here insert name of firm or company. (3) Here insert name of city or country. (4) These words should be omitted where the manu facturer or supplier himself signs the Certificate. (6) Here insert particulars of any special arrange ment. (6) Insert “ United Kingdom ” or name of other part of British Dominions. 27/9/33 IMPERIAL ECONOMIC CONFERENCE. FORM “B.” Combined Certificate of Value and of Origin and Invoice of Goods for&lt; Exportation to British Colonies % (1) of (2) of (3) of the Roods enumerated in this invoice amounting to suppher hereby declare that I [(4) have the authority to make and sign this certificate on behalf of the aforesaid manu actu f er an( j that T] have the means of knowing and do hereby certify as follows :— VALUE. 1. That this invoice is in all respects correct and contains a true and full statement of the price actually paid or to be paid for the.said goods, and the actual quantity thereof. * 2. That no arrangements or understanding affecting the purchase price of r the said goods have been or will be made or entered into between the said exporter and purchaser, or by anyone on behalf of either of them either by way of discount, rebate, V compensation or in any manner whatever other than as fully shown on this invoice, or as A * follows (5) ORIGIN. (In the case of goods exported to Gambia, Gold Coast or Sierra Leone the following portion of the Certificate dealing with Origin should be struck out.) (Delete whichever of 3 (a) or 3 (fc) is not applicable. If 3 (a) is used delete 4 and 5. If 3 (b) is used insert required particulars in 4 and 6.) 3. (rt) That every article mentioned in 3. (6) That every article mentioned in the said invoice has been wholly produced or the said invoice has been either wholly or manufactured in (6) partially produced or manufactured in (6) 4. As regards those articles only partially produced or manufactured in (6). (6). (а) That the final process or processes of manufacture have been performed in that part of the British Dominions. (б) That the expenditure in material produced in (6) and/or labour performed in (6) calculated subject to qualifications hereunder, in each and every article is not less than ODe ' fop T th of the factory or works cost of such article in its finished one-half state. (See Note below.) 6. That in the calculation of such proportion of produce or labour of the none of the following items has been included or considered— “ Manufacturer’s profit or remuneration of any trader, agent, broker, or other person “ dealing in the articles in their finished condition: royalties: cost of outside “ packages or any cost of packing the goods thereinto; any cost of conveying ' insuring, or shipping the goods subsequent to their manufacture.” Dated at. this day of. .19. Witness Signature. Note. —In the case of goods which have at some stage entered into the commerce of, or undergone a process of manufacture in a foreign country, only that labour and material which is expended on or added to the goods after their return to the United Kingdom shall be regarded as the produce or manufacture of the United Kingdom in calculating the proportion of United Kingdom labour and material in the factory or works cost of the finished article.I No. 504. H. REEVES &amp; CO.. 32 St. Mary Axe, E.C.3 (1) Here insert Manager, Chief Clerk, or as the case may be. (2) Here insert name of firm or company. (3) Here insert name of city or country. (4) These words should be omitted where the manu facturer or supplier himself signs the Certificate. (6) Here insert particulars of any special arrange ment. (6) Insert “ United Kingdom ” or name of other part of British Dominions. IMPERIAL ECONOMIC CONFERENCE. . FORM “B.” Combined Certificate of Value and of Origin and Invoice of Goods for Exportation tc British Colonies ALBSBLT.. J^.V/AHD..ivlA l IITHIi7irjS... ; (l) •...A.c.c.oun.tan.t of (2)..F..BAi.wER...£i....C.O.*JuTD.^ of (3) London mafUJ -^ acl:urtf of the goods enumerated in this invoice amounting to £5^ • .♦.M.* suppher hereby declare that I [(4) have the authority to make and sign this certificate on behalf of the ‘and that I] have the means of knowing and do hereby certify as aforesaid supplier follows :— VALUE. 1. That this invoice is in all respects correct and contains a true and full statement of the price actually paid or to be paid for the said goods, and the actual quantity thereof. 2. That no arrangements or understanding affecting the purchase price of - the said goods have been or will be made or entered into between the said exporter and fv purchaser, or by anyone on behalf of either of them either by way of discount, rebate, compensation or in any manner whatever other than as fully shown on this invoice, or as follows (5) ORIGIN. (In the case of goods exported to Gambia, Gold Coast or Sierra Leone the following portion of the Certificate dealing with Origin should be struck out.) (Delete whichever of 3 (a) or 3 (b) is not applicable. If 3 (a) is used delete 4 and 5. If 3 (b) is used insert required particulars in 4 and 5.) 3. (a) That every article mentioned in 3. fty^hat every article mentioned in the said invoice has been wholly produced or the Scjjdin voice has been either wholly ot manufactured in (6) U.JC, pprCudly produced or manufactured in 4. As regards those articlesy'only. partially producecL''’'ar manufactured in (6) •- {a) That the final propi^s. or processes of. mamjf^cture .have been performed in_^ that part of tbe'TSritish Dominions. yr «y--. c (b) That the expenditure in material pro^-fced-in (6) and/or/labour performed in calculated fct to qualifications Wfeunder, in each and every article is not less ^o ne-four th fa^totv or works cost of such article in its finished one-half state. (See Note be} 5. XThat in the calcu}e(ion of such proportion of produce or labour of the (g) nond^of the following items has been included or considered— “ Manufacturer’s profit or remuneration of any trader, agent, broker, or other person “ dealing in the articles in their finished condition: royalties: cost of outside “ packages or any cost of packing the goods thereinto ; any cost of conveying “ insuring, or shipping the goods subsequent to their manufacture.” Dated at...L.QI.ID.QH this....Lw.1iil^ day of 19 .7) 4 • Witness Signature. Note. —In the case of goods which have at some stage entered into the commerce of, or undergone a process of manufacture in a foreign country, only that labour and material which is expended on or added to the goods after their return to the United Kingdom shall be regarded as the produce or manufacture of the United Kingdom in calculating the proportion of United Kingdom labour and material in the factory or works cost of the finished article. 27/9/33No* /0 S5 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 7th July 1934* To Messrs F«P* Baker and Conpany Limited, 2, Upper James Ltreet, Golden Square, Kegent Street, Dear Sirs, LONDON, W.l. I enclose a draft for £.58$18:11 (Pounds fifty- eightf eighteen shillings and eleven pence only) in full settlement of your invoice No.jg, 1869 dated the 28th May 1934 forwarded with your letter No.WH*2813 dated the 29th May 1934 in respect of steel safe and paints. Kindly acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain© isi 4 - no, 11 m- Political Agency f Bahrain the 16th July 1934* To Messrs B»H•Herman and L'ohatta, Limited, Vulcan Iron Works, vueen^s Road, Wood Street, ■ K..A1 A P H 1 f Dear Sirs, 1 A / With reference to your letter Mo.75/94 dated the 23rd June 1934, I beg to confirm my telegram dated the 2nd July 1S34 ' ar/ETS*. This means that copper bar rivets of suitab lengths for rivetting are to be substituted for bolts and nuts ordered in r/y letter No*961 dated the 11th June 1934* 2# I thank you Jor your offer to make suggestions re garding the stern of the boat and I am accordingly enclosin ^ herewith a rough pencil sketch of boaVs stern and rudder# Yours faithfully, I*C*S# Oftgm Political Agent, Bahrain*f jam 1 Ho. /17/2, Political Agenc/t Bahrain# the 13rd July 19^4* i k TO m Messrs B*R«Hermaa St Mohatta Limited# Vulcan Iron Works# Queers Road# Wood Street# Karachi* Sear Sira, I enclose a Supply Bill N0.923Q/B dated the 23rd Jhly 1M4 for fta.l??/- and postage stamps to the yalue of anaas four (Total Rs.179/4/-) in full settlement of your hill Ho.W/0.5617 dated the 14th July 1934. 2. Kindly acknowledge receipt* rt ts Yours faithfully. k I.C.S. Offg. Political Agent, Bahrain. *•1CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Branches CHARING CROSS, LAHORE. LOKHAN BAZAR, BHAVNAGAR. Form No Telegrams I Telephones ^ EXPANSION, KARACHI. 47 &amp; 326- EXPANSION, LAHORE. 2330. EXPANSION, BHAVNAGAR. . 29^*) ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. Engineers, Shipbuilders &amp; Metal Merchants- Codes : Bentley’s Phrase 1st &amp; 2nd A. B. C. 6th Edition &amp; Universal Trade. Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Road &amp; Wood Street, i Karachi, 2aa August 193 4 Ref. No. 75/98. The Political Agent, 3 abr ain. ( Persian G-ulf) fr No. 1124/17/2 Dear sir, Te thank you for under cover of which you have sent us a SKetch showing the stern of the boat to which the helm fittings, recently made ■by us are to he fitted. The sketch sent by us is very similar and if consulted when reading our letter, we think you will have the minimum of trouble. He enclose another sketch now, on which will be seen shaded portion^ indicating wood which should be cut away^thereby allowing the propeller to work in as solid a block of water as possible. It has been ascertained that by having thick Bow Stems and stern posts upto Z0% of the engine Horse Power Cc. n be absorbed, and so^ with this in view it is always beneficial to stream line the underwater parts as much as Subject to the conditions at back hereof.1. This Tender is subject to the following conditions:— All prices are subject to alteration without notice and to confirmation at the time the order is received. 2. Promises of delivery are given without Guarantee, and, whilst every effort will be made to adhere to them as closely as possible, we do not hold ourselves responsible for delays arising from any cause whatever, and in no case shall delay in delivery be ground for rejecting goods. Offers of delivery of goods from stock are subject to the goods remaining in stock at the time the order is received. •1. All goods will be despatched at Owner’s Risk unless specially arranged to the contrary. We do not hold ourselves i esponsible for any damage that may occur in transit, but if desired Insurance can be effected by us to cover risk of damage in transit, rates for which will be quoted on appli cation (providing an Insurance Company will accept the risk.) I. Our terms of payment are one-third value with order, and balance against Railway Receipt or Shipping documents. o. Rupee quotations for goods to be imported for Forward Delivery are based on the Rate, of Exchange existing at the time of quoting. Payment must, however, be made based on the Rate of Exchange existing at the time goods are invoiced to the Customer. (&gt;. Illustrations and particulars of Machines are not binding and are subject to alteration in detail. 7. All goods not of our own manufacture carry the maker’s Standard Guarantee beyond which we accept no liability. 8. Customers are requested to note that when goods are sent bv Steamer or Rail, the responsibility of B. R. Hermax &amp; Mohatta, Ltd., ceases with the receipt of a clean Bill of Lading or Railway Receipt. In case of breakage or short delivery, consignees must claim on the Steamer or Rail wav Company. •COUNTERMANDS.—The right is reserved to refuse countermands, which can not under any circumstances be accepted in the case of goods in process of manufacture or ready for despatch.*’- B, R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. possible. © /&gt; u 2 . T .7e have noticed that the Bows of ell the Craft in your port are very sharp* bat in addition to the thick stern post yoa have a rudder post, which if not stream lined will have an adverse effect on the speed of the boat. A rudder post is quite useless and we would suggest that it be done away with in any future boat you build. TCe cannot advise it in this case because we are not conversant with the stern design. 'fe trust the foregoing will be of interest to you, and that you will not hesitate to write to us should there be any further information required. Yours faithfully, B. R. KERMAN &amp; MOHATTA LTD. c MOHATTA LTI DIRECTOR. BEH/VMG.Ho. /27? /17/8. © Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th August 1934* To Messrs B. R. Herman Mohatta, Limited, Vulcan Iron Works, Queen's Road, Wood Street, . K...A g ..A gJU U Dear Sirs, I beg to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No.75/98, dated the 2nd August 1934, enclosing therein a sketch of boat’s stem and to thank you fpr your suggestions which are being adopted. Yours faithfully, tr X . c. s. , Offg. Political Agent, Bahrain. i, X,■? . A6C c X BRANCH OFFICE: CHARING CROSS, LAHORE, METAL'S^tOCK YARDS: JALLCO. LAHORE. Meerut city. From, B. R. HERMAN 8: MOHATTA LTD. VULCAN IRON WORKS, Engineers, Founders &amp; General Contractors, Qcjkens Road &amp; Wood Street. No. Karachi, 193 audun*. TEL '-6 EXPANSION, KARACHI. codes: BEN TLEY'S PHRASE TELEPHONE NO. 47. i .© The Political Agent, Political Agency, BAHRAIN. Sir, dated We beg to acknowledge with thanks the receiji of yo«r favour No. 1157/17/2 suoply bill Sc stamps 23rd ultimo covering 1 for Rs. 179/4/- (Rupees One hundred seventy nine and annas four only i/ in full settlement of our Bill No. fleasb find enclosed our stamped receipt. Esteeming your further orders. V Enclo. Receipt. MA for which Yours faithfully,TELEPHONE: GERRARD 6351* T t L K G rams: VI D A L A B A K , PICCY, LONDON. CABLES'. BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. r F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. The Political Agent, Bahrein, Persian G-ulf. tu CITY OFFICE: 9-10, BOND COURT, WALBROOK, E.C. A. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE) 20, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST, W. 1. (S) PLEASE QUOTE N9 3632. C D. 9A. IN REPLY 1st August 193 4 Dear Sir, AH* /'In further reference to our letter of the 23 rd May, we should he interested to hear if our quotation for Disinfecting Fluid met with your approval and if in due course we may he favoured with your esteemed instructions to supply. Our services are entirely at your disposal in the event of your requiring further information.Political Agency, No, 7 /17/2. Bahrain, the 22nd August 1934. To Messre F.P. Baker &amp; Company Limited, 2, Upper James Street, Oolden Square, Regent Street, LONDON, W.I. : h: , k I i\ Dear Sire, / I thank you for your letter No.3632/C.D.9-A, dated the let August 1934, and to inform you that ae I have revieed my requirements, I am not placing an order for Disinfecting Fluid with you this year. Youre faithfully. &lt; I.C.S., Offg. Political Agent, Bahrain.BY AIR MAIL. / ^0- nl^ - Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th October 1934, To Mr. Abdulhusein Jafferji New Market KARACHI. Dear Sir, I have sent by ordinary post to your address, two samples of Manilla rope . Will you please supply *e the followings- 1. One coil of ticker rope as per sample 2. Two coils of thinner rope M ' 3. One and half cwts of cotton waste, preferable of white quality. The cost will be remitted to you on receipt of your bill. Yours faithfully Offg. Political Agent, Bahraintish Consulate-General, Bushire, Persian GulT* 18th October 1934. Dear Sirs, I beg to refer to your advertisementt in the 'Staybrite Book* 1 page 417, and to request that you will kindly send me an Illustrated ^rice list of your yacht fittings in Staybrite steel suitable for a 60-foot locally built launch. The launch is heavily built on the lines of a Scottish fishing boat and is fitted with a £&gt;$ H*. • Thomycroft engine. The price list should be addressed to: His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrain, Persian Gull* • To Lieut••Colonel. Messrs.Vesper &amp; Co•Ltd., Portsmouth*Str BY AIR MAIL. No* mV 19/a&lt; cz) Political Agency, Bahrain, th« 11th December 19 To Mr. Abdnlhteei* Jafferji, New Market, K A R A C H ;,'V &lt; Dear Sir, The article* asked for in my letter No*1517/ 17/2 dated the 16th October 1934 '(copy enclo*«d for ready reference) have not yet been received and yon a therefore, requested kindly to expedite their supply ait an early date* 2. If yon are nnable to *npply the article*, please pas* on the order to a merchant who can supply the articles. Yours faithfully, T • C • S • , Assistant Political Agent, Bahrainestablished 8 6 5 V/' CONTRACTORS TO ADMIRALTY WAR DEPARTMENTS CROWN AGENTS FOR THE COLONIES AIR MINISTRY TRINITY HOUSE FOREIGN GOVERNMENTS VOfPIR&amp;COlTD PORTSMOUTH SHIPBUILDERS &amp; ENGINEERS SHIP REPAIRERS Ou. R fe JPH/te^ OLiB Rl , TELEGRAMS REPSOV PORTSMOUTH • TELEPHONES 2137 2 LINES NIGHT SERVICE 7th November, 1934* His Britarmic Majesty*s Political Agent, BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. Dear Sir, ¥ S' fogr f \ We thank you for your letter of 18th October, and, as requested, have pleasure in enclosing our price list of ^taybrite Yacht and Boat Fittings; also illustrations. We trust that this will give you all the necessary information, and that you will pass us an order for the fittings required in due course. Assuring you of our best attention. We remain. Yours faithfully. For VOSj .. ENGINEER MANAGER.q. f SHIPBUILDERS &amp; ENGINEERS VOSPER « V^O. BROAD STREET, PORTSMOUTH TELE GRAMS: PHONE: REPSOV. 2137 &amp; fn) Manufacturers of all kinds of YACHT &amp; BOAT FITTINGS in ‘ FIRTH STAYBRITE ’ RUSTLESS STEEL or GUNMETAL © GALVANISED SIMPLEX STOCKLESS ANCHORS © REPAIRS OF ALL DESCRIPTIONS © PATENT SLIPWAY © YACHT &amp; LAUNCH BUILDERSmmQ nW •. ' MAMA &amp; COMPANY GOVERNMENT CONTRACTORS AND MERCHANTS - Telegrams :-“CONCRETE” Telephone :-248. Codes :-Bentley'S A. B. C. 5th a 6 th Edition a private. No. 1045/A IMPORTERS a EXPORTERS. AGENTS FOR JAPANESE PORTLAND CEMENTS QBE ASANO DDD BRAND * ~CCC BRAND AND K. M. K. MOTOR TRUCK SPECIALITIES CORRUGATED STEEL BARS. M. S. ROUND &amp; SQUARE BARS. TIMBER OF ALL KINDS. PAINTS, MANGALORE ROOFING TILES. WHITE PORTLAND CEMENT a TILES. UK GRANT ROAD, KARACHI, December 1934 A The Political A^ent, Bahrain . Dear Sir, ./? X A copy of your letter No.1517/17/2 of 16th October last —~~~~— I I ..in, — addressed to Abdul Husein Jafferji, New Market, Karachi has this « day been forwarded by him to us for disposal with the samples of Manilla Rope. (j v &lt; vve have this day forwarded by you by sample post Manilla Rope we stock which is from l/2 u to circumference rising by l/2 inch. Our price for same B.O.B. Karachi are as under Rs.32/- per cwt P.O.B. Karachi ^ W' ty* l 4 &lt; 0 * ‘ .^e have also sent you 1 sample: of cotto % t e rate for same are as underi- Rs.30-8-0 per cwt P.O.B. Karachi. T r usting to be favoured with your esteemed orders and soliciting further enquiries&gt; We remain , V i! ^ v - \ 1 Mj -r- ^ I Yours faithfully,Store File. TtJtT As desired i submit below a list showing our store requirements. 10 tins in st£k. 4 dozens are required. lt*^ usually obtained from the market. 2 in stock ana 12 in use. 12 of size 2' are required. ^ 3.White enamel paint. 3 kegs in stock. 12 kegs of i gallon each are required. n 3 cwts are required. Nothing in .stock. / 4. Snow white ready made paint l 5. Copal varnish. 2 kegs in stock. 10 gallons are required. Nothing in stock. 56 lbs are retired. 1 keg in stock. 8 gallons are required. 3 gallon in stock. 20 gallons are required. Nothing in stock. 2 Cwts are required. i/ lO.Cocoanut oi l. J 11.Life belts. J 12.Fire iiixtinguisher* 1 gallon(Phiryne Syringe^ /f?;^ , 1 gallon in stock. 8 gallons are required it is obtainable locally in 4 gall.tins. 6 are required for the crew ana 3 of waste coat type for the passengers. L 13.Manilla rppes. r ihe following sizes are in stock. 7/8' 204 feet. 5/8' 672 ' . li' 93 ' . s/j 1' 184 ' . ^ The tollovving sizes are required. one coil. 3/8 ,T f ’ ” .(Light horns Brandj. i Tt M ” .(White Sasiq line.for launch fa]^ sthifs). As regards waste cotton and ropes please see pages 45 and 47 \* I of file Nq. 17/2. Althougn we wrote two letters to Abaulnusein Fafferii,Karachi, ordering the same but he has neither supplied the articles nor replied-'our letters. 4.3.35No:530--17/2. Political Agency, Bsiircjin, the 31ot Mtrch 1935 To, UessrB- A. M. Yateeni and Brotners, Bahrain. Lear Sirs, 1 be;' to request you to sene me quotations for various kinds of Lite Belts. Yours faithfully, f Captain, Ong:* ron tioal Agent,Bahrain.&amp; No: ^2—17/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 31st Jfcrch 1935 To, Messrs.F.F.Baker and Company Limited, 2, Upper James Street, Golden Square, Regent Street, LONDON, W.l. . Dear Sirs, Please supply this Agency with the following stores. Your bill will be paid immediately upon receipt of the consignment. 1. Paint Brush^flat, black fib€\p. size 3').. 1 dozen. 2. nhite iinamel Paint(in half gallon tins}..12 gallon 3. Snow hite Ready Made Paint.' 3 Cwts. 4. Copal V&amp;rnish(in half gallon tins; 10 gallon 5. Soda Caustic V So Lbs. 6. Phenyle(disinfecting fluio. for the use of bath rooms ana water closets; 8 gallon 7. Turpentine 20 *’ Q. 'Foam' Fire Extinguisher 1 one 9. Grey Ready Made Paint... 2 Cwts. 2. The above articles should be insured ana despatched on one of Messrs.Frank.C-Strick ana Company T s ships. Yours faitnfuliy, Vi U . Captain, Offg: Political Agent, Bahrain.S 0 MAMA &amp; COMPANY GOVERNMENT CONTRACTORS AND MERCHANTS Telegrams ^“CONCRETE” Telephone :-248. Codes :-Bentley's A. B. C. 5th a 6th Edition a Private. NO. 117,9/A IMPORTERS a EXPORTERS. AGENTS FOR JAPANESE PORTLAND CEMENTS USE ASANO DDD BRAND * “Ecc' BRAND AND K. M. K. MOTOR TRUCK SPECIALITIES CORRUGATED STEEL BARS. M. S. ROUND ft SQUARE BARS. TIMBER OF ALL KINDS, PAINTS. MANGALORE ROOFING TILES, WHITE PORTLAND CEMENT &amp; TILES. GRANT ROAD, KARACHI, i??.?... The Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir, /? We are in receipt of your favour 1*0.532-17/2 dated 31st I&amp;trch 1935 contents of which are noted. Re sManilla Hope ?- This rope is not at all coining in 3/8 M and 1/4' circumference. The thinest size is 1/2' circumfernce. Other size we can ✓ supply 1 M » l£' 2 ,, upto 4-J-' circumference. We therefore request you to let us know what actual size you require so that we may forward the goods. ^ 2 cwts Cotton ftaste also^be supplied to you after the receipt of your reply. Y 0 urs faithfully, fn vu '2T ! Qkt TCl it* tMBHBi mtm C.D.9. ,N REPLY Dear Sir, F. P. Ba ker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. The Political Agent, Bahrain Persii CITY OFFICE: 9-10, BOND COURT, WAL B ROOK, E.C.-*.. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK i-TP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. warehouse (entrance; 20, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST.,W. 1. J 11th April 193 5 . We are duly in receipt of , your letter of the 31st March,No.531-1f/ 2 , and thank you for the esteemed order contained therein for ships stores v/hich we are placing in hand and will despatch in accordance with your wishes. Placing our services entirely at your disposal. We are Yours F.P.BAK ?ar Sir,»o$813-17/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 11th May 1936. To Messrs* Mama and Company, Grant Road, Karachi . Dear sirs, J 0 with reference to your letter Ho. 1179/A dated the 15th April 1935, please supply the following dimensions of rope i- Manilla (1) diameter or ) 14 w circumference ) One coil (2) 3/8*• diameter or 1-1/8* ) circumference ) One coil white Line (3) diameter or 3/4* ) circumference ) £ coil* If you cannot supply the above, will you please send me two coils of 1-1/2 H circumference. The cotton waste is urgently needed, so I request you to give this order your imnediate attention. Yours faithiUlly, Lieutenant, Agent, Bahrain. Assistant PoliticalNo:^^-17/2 II Political Agency, Banrain, aatea tne 30th May 1935. To, Messrs, a. M. lateem Brotners, BAHRAIN. Dear Sirs, With reference to your letter dated the dtn May 1935, will you please order one dozen f, KAP0K” pattern life jackets for this Agency. The goods should be addressed to His Britannic Majesty r s Political Agent, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 2. The cost of the above will be paid on the receipt of your bill. Yours faithfully, I . A Lieutenant, for^ffg.Political Agent ,BahrainMAMA &amp; COMPANY government contractors AND MERCHANTS Telegrams :-“CONCRETE” Telephone :-248. Codes i-Bentleys A. B. C. 5th a 6 th Edition a Private. No. /^ . % IMPORTERS a EXPORTERS. AGENTS FOR JAPANESE PORTLAND CEMENTS USE ASANO _ B R AND » ccc brand AND K. M. K. MOTOR TRUCK SPECIALITIES CORRUGATED STEEL BARS. M. S. ROUND flk — SQUARE BARS, TIMBER OF ALL KINDS. PAINTS. MANGALORE ROOFING TILES. WHITE PORTLAND CEMENT &amp; TILES. GRANT ROAD, KARACHI, 21 s t May 1935. The Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, ‘ \v. As desired in your letter Nos 813-h.7/2 of 11th instant we have to advise having shipped per s.s. Baroda sailed hence on the 19th instant for your port, the following:- Manilla Rope li* circumference 2 coils. ^ Cotton Waste It cwt. 1 bundle. /f and now enclose our hill and the relative B/Lading for favour or 7 k payment* Yours faithfully. It •yAgent* far: Manglore Roofing Tiles. SPECIALITIES:- CORRUGATED BARS. ROUND &amp; SQUARE IN ALL LENGTHS. MILD STEEL. BARS. RODS &amp; CHANNELS. TIMBER. TEAKWOOD OF RANGOON &amp; PYNKADOE, PANE WOOD OF MALABAR LOGS &amp; SCANTLINGS OF ALL SIZES. PAINTS A OILS. MARINE ENGINES, CASTOR &amp; LINSEED OILS, WHITE CEMENT GRIFFIN BRAND MANILLA ROPE. FIRE BRICKS A OL A Y. PRICES ON APPLICATION. Telegrams: ‘•CONCRETE' Karachi Telephone No. 248. BILL No. 786 Agents for JAPANESE PORTLAND CEMENT. ASANO Reg. Trade C.C.C. Mark. Corrugated Bar. GRANT ROAD, Karachi;' 18 * ^ 19^ The Ass istant Political Agent. D**- BAHREIN. TO, MAMA &amp; CO., METAL, TIMBER, “WHITE CEMENT” &amp; “aSANO” PORTLAND CEMENT MANGLORE ROOFING TILES 8t GUNUINE * LINSEED OILS MERCHANTS &amp; CONTRACTORS. Interest ($ 9% will be charged if not paid within 7 days.Agent* jar. Telegrams-. “CONCRETE' Karachi Telephone No. 248. BILL No. 786 Agents for JAPANESE PORTLAND CEMENT. ASANO Man&amp;lore RooSng Tiles. SPECIALITIES CORRUGATED BARS. ROUND &amp; SQUARE IN ALL LENGTHS. MILD STEEL. BARS, RODS &amp; CHANNELS. TIMBER. TEAKWOOD OF RANGOON &amp; PYNKADOE, PANE WOOD OF MALABAR LOGS &amp; SCANTLINGS OF ALL SIZES. lleg. Trade C.C.C. Hark. Corrugated Bar. GRANT ROAD, Karachi 8 181 19^ The Assistant Political Agent, D^* BAHREIN. PAINTS A OILS. OIL LUBRICATING FOR MARINE ENGINES, CASTOR &amp; LINSEED OILS, WHITE CEMENT GRIFFIN BRAND MANILLA ROPE, l FIR E BRICKS A CLAY. CO ALTAR. TALLOW . PRICES ON APPLICATION. TO, MAMA &amp; CO., METAL, TIMBER? WHITE CEMENT’’ &amp; ASANO” PORTLAND CEMENT MANGLORE ROOFING TILES &amp; GUNUINE'LINSEED OILS MERCHANTS &amp; CONTRACTORS. Interest ( 0 ) 9% will be charged if not paid within 7 days. Description. Bieng Cost ofi- Manilla Rope Cotton Waste Steamer freight on above Bund les. Quantity. Nos. T. C. Qr- lbs. T. eft. I. Pa. Guj. V V * - 3 26 1 2 0 Rupees Eighty s \c V\&lt;$CODES &lt; A.B.C. 5 TH EDITION BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE CODE BROOMHALL'S IMPERIAL COMBINATION CODE * PRIVATE &lt;Jc- A. M. YATEEM BROTHERS BAHREIN SOLE AGENTS FOR: THE GENUINE ROSKOPF PATENT WATCHES Bahrain YATEEMS BUILDING, 2nd June 1935, Big Britannic uajegty'a Political Agent, Bahrain, Beraian liulf. m*J fur Dear Sir, We thank you for your kind letter ho. 954-17/2 n of the 30th ultimo which contains an order for one Bozen'KAPOK' pattern life jackets for the Agency. We have pleasure in informing you that same has been passed to the manufacturera for prompt execution, and we hope to receive the game in due courae of time. Thanking you, we remain, dear Sir, loura faithfully, M. YATEEjVi J 3 RO L o A.h.TE LEPH O N E: GERRfARD 6351* telegrams: VIDALABAK, PICCV, LONDON. F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. CABLES: BANStlEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. CAV) 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. r The Political Agent, Political Agency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf* ' l C- please quote n&lt;? m 2694 CITY OFFICE: 9-10, BOND COURT, WALB ROOK, E.C.4.. IN REPLY Dear Sir, BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE; 20. BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST., W. 1. 193 We enclose herewith one Bill of Lading ana two Clearing Invoices, covering the shipment of 33. packages, containing goods as enumerated on the attached invoice ordered by you, marked as under, per the s.s. TABARISTAN', which vessel sailed from Lonaon on the 22nd May and is we understand from the Shipping Company due at Bahrain on about the 20th June 1935. We have to remind you that it will be neceesary for you to surrender the documents to the Shipping Company*s Agents at Bahrain Messrs. The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Ltd. to enable you to ootain release of the packages. Trusting that the packages open out to your entire satisfaction on arrival at destination, and we shall appreciate your further enquiries and instructions which snail at all times have our careful and prompt at tention•'Telephone : GERRARD 5748 5754. TELEGRAMS : VIDALABAK, PICCY, LONDON. CABLES: BANSHEE, LONDON, BENTLEY’S CODE. F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W.l. CITY OFFICE f 9 10, BOND COURT, WALBROOK, E.C. 4 . BANKERS : WESTMINSTER BANK, LTD. LOMBARD STREET, E.C. 3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE) 20, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST. W. 1. 29 th ti ay 193 J To__ The Political Agent, Bahrain W h IILREBY CERTIFY that the following interest has been declared as attaching to our Floating Policy of Insurance at Lloyds, No., 57 f which has been declared by order and for account of F. P. BAKER &amp; CO., LTD. excluding breakage * including breakage £ 'TABARISTAH' on Oilman * a stores, fire ejctinguishejg etc* r s.s. From London to. destination via Banrain and we hereby agree to hold the amount recoverable on the said Policy so far as the above interest is concerned at the disposal of yourself _ or y° ur order. F. P. Bi ALL RISKS (as specified). 1 Ids Policy covers such Goods and/or Merchandise includina^JPgrsonal and/or other effects as may be declared hereon from any port^^^place in the United Kingdom to destination named. With average each package and including tfw risks of hook breakage and fresh water, oil and other cargo damage, pilferage, theft and war, and personal and/or other effects against all risks of every description including w T ar. Glass, Pictures, Earthenware, China, Marble, Cast Iron and all brittle articles free of claim for breakage unless specially insured for such. NOTICE. —In the event of damage or loss exceeding £2 a survey should be called for from Lloyd’s Agent, but it is necessary that notice to survey should be given immediately after the arrival of the goods at the Destination named herei n in the event of loss arising, otherwise the Underwriters will accept no liability for such loss. It is quite sufficient if clients address their letter LLOYD’S AGENT PORT OF BAHRAIiG ? and after survey the Agent’s report should be sent to us together with particulars of the claim to enable us to recover from the Underwriters. The fee paid for survey is recoverable in addition to the amount of the claim. Unless the property is insured for its full value, claims for partial or total loss or damage will only be recoverable proportionately. In the event of a claim arising under this Policy F. P. BAKER &amp; CO., LTD., agree to pay such sums as may be recovered from the Underwriters without prejudice as customary, on the understanding that they shall be indemnified by the Insured against all reasonable expenses incurred.M.H / / TELEPHONE: GERRARD 83 51* telegrams: VIDALABAK, PICCY, LONDON. In Acer, with F. P. Ba ker &amp; Co. Ltd. CABLES: BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. Reference No. D.2066 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. The Political Agent, Political Agency, Bahrein,Persian Gulf, SQ.th.pMay. As we work on a very small margin we ask clients to help us by complying with our term* of business, namely, remittance onf receipt of invoice. If an account is overdue we are compelled to charge interest at 6%, with collection charges, and to cancel all discounts or concessions. l^o! 15148. Bankers: Westminster Bank, Ltd., Lombard Street, E.C.3. P. A. Gallons ,f Lion'Brand Disinfecting Fluid. ^ r 1 - MAJSRAIN.20 Gallons Best American Turpentine 5 2 - * 56 lbs. Caustic Soda 4 10 Gallons Copal Varnish 7 lb _ * 12 Gallons White Nicolac Enamel paint 14 6 3^ 12 3' Black Flat Paint Brushes 2 3 9^ 3 Cwt.Snow White Ready made Paint 7 2 Cwt.Grey Ready made Paint. _! 11 - -^42 6 3 / 5$ Commission 2 2 4 / Freight,Primage ,Dock Dues,Port Rates,Bills of Lading and Postage on above and on Fire Extinguisher. 1 Case No.l. &amp; Packing Cartage to Docks £65 Insurance Customs Entry &amp; Clearance 3 19 3 2 9 1 / / / / / 4 18 -/ /9J5 Shipped ner s.s.'TASARISIAN'. Sailed 22nd.May 1Q35* With Compliments. E.&amp;.O.E. Please Return this Account with Remittance. £49 ^ 7 .M.H a® ' VeLEPHONE: GERRARO 8351* TE LEG R AM S: VIDALABAK, PICCY, LONDON. In Acer, with F. P. B a ker &amp; Co. Ltd. CABLES: BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. Reference No ,2Qt h .May The Political Agent, Political Agency, Bahrain,Persian Gulf. As we work on a very small margin we ask clients to help us by complying with our terms of business, namely, remittance on receipt of invoice. If an account is overdue we are compelled to charge interest at 6%, with collection charges, and to cancel ail discounts or concessions. U.&amp;.J.317. Bankers: Westminster Bank, Ltd., Lombard Street, E.C.3. P.A. 1 Phomene Fire Extinguisher. BAHRAIN. 5$ Commission 2 11 - / 2 7 ^ x £2 13 7. /'\ F.P.B. 30 With Compliments. E.&amp;.O.E. Please Return this Account with Remittance.No. 504. H. REEVES &amp; CO.. 32 St. Mary Axe, E.C.3 • . &lt; 9IMPERIAL ECONOMIC CONFERENCE. FORM “B.” (1) Here insert Manager. Chief Clerk, or as the case may be. (2) Here insert name of firm or company. (3) Here insert name of city or country. (4) These words should be omitted where the manu facturer or supplier himself signs the Certificate. Combined Certificate of Value and of Origin and Invoice of Goods for Exportation to British Colonies. h ( 1 ) of (2) of (3) manufacturer , ,, , - - — of the eoods enumerated in this invoice amounting to supplier . hereby declare that I [(4) have the authority to make and sign this certificate on behalf of the aforesaid an&lt; ^ that IJ have the fiaeans of knowing and * do hereby certify as follows :— VALUE. 1 — • F. * That this invoice is in all respects correct and contains a true and full statement of the price actually paid or to be paid for the said goods, and the actual quantity thereof. 2. That no arrangements or understanding affecting the purchase price of the said goods have been or will be made or entered into between the said exported and purchaser, or by anyone on behalf of either of them either by way of discount, rebate, compensation or .in any manner whatever other than as fully shown on this invoice, or as J6) Here insert follows (5) particulars of any special arrange ment. (6) Insert 'United Kingdom” or name of other part of British Dominions. ORIGIN. (In the case of goods exported to Colonies not granting preference to British goods the following portion of the Certificate dealing with Origin should be struck out.) (Delete whichever of 3 (a) or 3 (b) is not applicable. If 3 (a) is used delete 4 and 5. If 3 (b) is used insert required particulars in 4 and 5.) 3. (a) That every article mentioned in 3. (b) That every article mentioned in the said invoice ha* been wholly produce^ or the said invoice has been either wholly or manufactured in (6) partially produced or manufactured in ( 6 ) 4 As regards those articles only partially produced or manufactured in (6) - , ♦ [a) That the final, process or processes of manufacture have been performed in that part of the British Dominions. (b) That the expenditure in material produced in (6) ^ * and/or labour performed in (6)...». calculated subject to qualifications hereunder, in each and every article is not less than ^ of the factory or works cost of such article in its finished ‘ state, (See Note below.) 6. That in the calculation of such proportion of produce or labour of the (6) none of the following items has been included or considered— “ Manufacturer’s profit or remuneration of any trader, agent, broker, or other person dealing in the articles in their finished condition: royalties: cost of outside ' packages or any cost of packing the goods thereinto; any cost of conveying ' insuring, or shipping the goods subsequent to their manufacture.” Dated at. -.this day of 19 Witness Signature Notf.— In the case of goods which have at some stage entered into the commerce ol, or undergone a process of manufacture in a foreign country, only that labour and material which is expended on ox added to the goods after their return to the United Kingdom shall be regarded as the produce or manufacture of the United Kingdom in calculating the proportion of United Kingdom labour and material in the factorv or works cost of the finished article. 6/3/34No. 504. H. REEVES &amp; ~CO. 32 St. Mary Axe, E.C.3 • (1) Here insert Manager, Chief Clerk, or as the case may be. (2) Here insert name of firm or company. (3) Here insert name of city or country. (4) These words should be omitted 1 where the manu facturer or supplier himself signs the Certificate. (6) Here insert particulars of any special arrange ment. (6) Insert 'United Kingdom” or name of other pait of British Dominions. 5/3/34 IMPERIAL ECONOMIC CONFERENCE. f ^ FORM “B.” Combined Certificate of Value and of Origin and Invoice of Goods for Exportation to British Colonies. I, (]) Acc ount ant (2)....F.^p. # ~£R..&amp;..C. 0 ;:.LTEt of ( 3 ) London. supplier £ 0 °d s enumerated in this invoice amounting to £.4-P..*....i2.A....i a hereby declare that I {(4) have the authority to make and sign this certificate on behalf of the suppiier an( tiia * ^ have tiie means of knowing and do hereby certify as aforesaid follows :— VALUE. 1- That tllis invoice is in all respects‘correct and contains a true and full statemeuu of the price actually paid or to be paid for the said goods, and the actual quantity thereof. 2. That no arrangements or understanding affecting the purchase price of the said goods have been or will be made or entered into between the said exporter and purchaser, or by anyone on behalf of either of them either by way of discount, rebate, compensation or in any manner whatever other than as fully shown on this invoice, or as follows (5) ORIGIN. g0 °? S eX ?°r te ^ t0 Golonies not granting preference to British goods the following portion of the Certificate dealing with Origin should be struck out.) (Delete whichever of 3 (a) or 3 (b) is not applicable. If 3 (a) is used delete 4 and 5. If 3 (b) is used insert required particulars in 4 and 5.) 3. (a) That every article mentioned in 3. (4) That every article mentioned in the said invoice has been wholly produced or the said mVoiSb has been either wholly or manufactured in (6) .V.Et* partia (6) y produced or mfactured ( 6 ). 4. As regards those articles onlv/partially produced^or manufactured in [a) That the final process that part of the Britisl &gt;rocesses of manufacture have been performed in Jominiops. (6) That the expenditure/ih materiaj/produced'm (6). and/or labour^erfonned ih (6).„/l calculate subject to qualifications hereunder, in each and every article is not less of the/factor/ or works cost of such article in its finished than ,, ,, oq^-half state. (See Note tx^Gw.) 5. That in the calculation of such proportion of produce or labour of the (6) ;; none f Jte following items has been included or considered— ‘‘ Manufacturer’s profit^ remuneration of any trader, agent, broker, or other person dealing in the articles in their finished condition: royalties: cost of outside packages or any cost of packing the goods thereinto; any cost of conveying insuring, or shipping the goods subsequent to their manufacture.” Dated at .kQ^QN this 2Qth„,...day of 19...3L5 Witness Signature Wrf Notf.— In the case of goods which have at some stage entered into the commerce of or undergone a nrocesc pr0p0rti0 ° U “ ,Cd 'a— -d materia,M.H, ll/P/RfMP f irir i : i'l J lif V , 4^ •State here general nature or class of goods. D.2066. Kirf’ w\ninr Place and Date, LOlTDCIJ dQth.May 19 3? • *IN VOICE Tl (FP- at ine. by F.P.BAKZH &amp;, CO.LTD. t0 The Political Agent, to be shipped per S *S • n TABAHl£TAN n • Order Number Eailea 22nd.Kay 1935 supplied of 2, Upper lames Street, Golden Sq.usrre ,London ,¥.l. The 'Political Agency,Bahrain, Persian Gulf, of Country of Origin Marks and numbers on packages. Quantity and description of goods 13P74. Current domestic values in currency of exporting country See pars. 3 and 4 of certificate.) * @ 2 Drums Nog»V4» 21 T x 1/;.” 0. '5»17 .containing: - Airier a. 20 Gallons Best American Tument ine 5$ C ommi ss i on Amount - Selling price to the purchaser - &amp; 2 ! - 5 ' 2 £5712 ^ a &gt; &gt; &gt; jr _ . . t Enumerate the following charges and state whether each amount has been included in or excluded from the above current domestic value :— Amount in currency of exporting country. State if included or excluded (1) (2) (3) Cartage to rail and /or to docks Inland freight (rail or canal) and other charges to the dock area including inland insurance ... “ Labour in packing the goods into outside packages ... II f /f (4) Value of outside packages (5) If the goods are subject to any charge by way of royalties ... State full particulars of Royalties below :—No. 502 -^^=======^= tJ W HARLK*, 9 Oft'..i hiiu 1 .!! Lni.utj, E-.ej. H. BEEVES &amp; CO., 32 St. Mary Axe, E.C.3 &lt;1) Here insert Manager, Chief Clerk, or as the case may be. (2) Here insert name of firm or company (3) Here insert name of city or country (4) These words should be omitted where the manu facturer or supplier himself signs the Certificate. NON-PREFERENTIAL AND FOREIGN. * Certificate of Value and Invoice or Goods for Exportation to British Dominions. Hr ALBERT...EB&amp;&amp;RD (!)• A.C. c.ount.an.t. Of (2).... 1..C0..LTD 0( (3) London ataauiarXuiai supplier enumerated in this invoice amounting to £.5 . .7..« £'.* hereby declare that 1 [(4) have the authority to make and sign this certificate on behalf of the aforesaid ma»«f»ct«rer- supplier I] have the means of knowing and do hereby certify as follows :— ^ ■S' VALUE. 1. That this invoice is in all respects correct and contains a true and full statement of the price actually paid or to be paid for the said goods, and the actual quantity thereof. 2. 1 hat no different invoice of the goods mentioned in the said invoice has been or will be furnished to anyone; and that no arrangement or understanding affecting the purchase price of the said goods has been or will be made or entered into between the said exporter and purchaser, or by anyone on behalf of either of them either by way of discount, ^rebate, compensation, or in any manner whatever other than as fully shown on this invoice. (5) Here insert or as follows (5) particulars of any special arrangement (6) Here insert “ warehouse,' ■' factory ' or ** port of ship ment.” 3. That the domestic values shown in the column headed “ Current Domestic Values ' are those at which the above-mentioned firm or company would be prepared to supply to any purchaser for home consumption in the country of exportation and at the date of exportation identically similar goods in equal quantities, at (6) subject p&amp;-«®t. cash discount, and that such values the cost of outside packages, if any, in which the goods are sold in such country for domestic consumption. 4. That the said domestic value includes any duty leviable in respect of the goods before they are delivered for home consumption, and that on exportation a drawback or remission of duty amounting ^ allowed by the revenue authorities in the country of exportation. Dated at....L9iX^.P‘: this .?2.t : .^..?....day of Hay 19 ^ . Witness Signature. 28/11/32M.H ^vT^Hvr© I If •State here general nature or class of goods. INVOICE T ttFP 0nt ine ’ by F .P. BAKER &amp; CO. LTD. to The Political A^ent, Place and Date, LONDON 29 th.May 19 35 • supplied of 2,Upper James Street,Golden Square,London,W.1• of The Political Agency,Bahrain, to be shipped per S *8 * ^TABARIoTAN • Sailed 22nd.May 1935* D.2066. 0rderNumber Persian Gulf.28/11/32 No. 502 NON-PREFERENTIAL AND FOREIGN. • J w. SftRLBV, J 3 4 * * * CUkOlMll JU H. REEVES &amp; CO., 32 St. Mary Axe, E.C.3 (1) Here insert Manager, Chief Clerk, or as the case may be. (2', Here insert name of firm or company. (3) Here insert name of city or country (4) These words should be omitted where the manu facturer or supplier himself signs the Certificate. (5) Here insert particulars of any special arrangement (6) Here insert ' warehouse,” ' factory ” or ” port of ship ment.' Certificate of Value and Invoice of Goods for Exportation to British Dominions. U, ALBERT. JJ0.Wai.i5 i&amp;J.TiMS (i; Accountant of ^2) r.P.B^H &amp; CO.LTD of . London mwi-Hfaeturer n c n supplier S 00 ^ 8 enumerated in this invoice amounting to • 7 • ^ • hereby declare that I [(4) have the authority to make, and sign this certificate on behalf of the . mamrrfectirrdr aforesaid ~ r .— suppher follows :— and that I] have the means of knowing and do hereby certify VALUE. 1. That this invoice is in all respects correct and contains a true and full statement of the price actually paid or to be paid for the said goods, and the actual quantity thereof. 2. -hat no different invoice of the goods mentioned in the said invoice has been or will be furnished to anyone; and that no arrangement or understanding affecting the purchase price of the said goods has been or will be made or entered into between the said exporter and purchaser, or by anyone on behalf of either of them either by way of discount, rebate, compensation, or in any manner whatever other than as fully shown on this invoice or as follows (5) 3. That the domestic values shown in the column headed “ Current Domestic Values ” are those at which the above-mentioned firm or company would be prepared to supply to any purchaser for home consumption in the country of exportatiorwnd at the date of exportation identically similar goods in equal quantities, at (6) (X X . subject to..rr^Vf. per cent, cash discount, and that such values the cost of outside packages, if any, in which the goods are sold in such country for domestic consumption. /I x 4. That the said domestic value includes any duty leviable in respect of the goods before they are delivered for home consumption, and that on exportation a drawback oi remission of duty amounting to allowed by the revenue authorities in the country of exportation. Dated at -LONDON this.. L. 2.9-til.,..day of ... W\ y 19...35 • Witness j6, .... Sigtiatwe.C iD \ - ' ^morandMm. Front, MAMA &amp; CO. ')l^ v METAL &amp; TIMBER MERCHANTS AND GOVERNMENT CONTRACTORS. GRANT ROAD Karachi , 15 th Ju ne Dear Sir, TELEPHONE No. 248. Telegraphic Address: “CONCRETE’* -; qOL ^ 'he Political Agent Bahrain i EH SI AIT GUL^. We acknowledge receipt of ,86-13-0 by Money Order ^Ain payment of our bill Bo.786 for which we thank you, ) We enclose our stamped receipt for same Thanking you, Yours faithfully, i28/11/32 N °' 503 - NON-PREFERENTIAL AND FOREIGN. ' J-W , fc % Certificate of Value and Invoice of Goods for Exportation to h. reeves &amp; co., British Dominions. 32 St. Marv Axe. E.C 3 before they are delivered for home remission of duty amounting to *^5 allowed by the revenue authorities in the country of exportation.'I V/ll» No. 502 NON-PREFERENTIAL AND FOREIGN. &lt; J ' TV. CiiaOjui ^ Ijiaut, H. REEVES &amp; CO., 32 St. Mary Axe. E.C.3 Certificate of Value and Invoice of Goods for Exportation to British Dominions. A r- i No.lJilO-17/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14tn July 1935 To, xMessrs. F. P. Baker ana Company ^td., 2, Upper James Street, Golden Square, Regent Street, LONDON. W.l. dated 29th May 1935, I enclose a certificate of short landing of eight gallons 'Lion' brand disinfecting fluid said to have been shipped by S.S.Tabaristan. O Dear Sirs, 2. Please take any action you consider necessary. Yours faithfully, . Lieutenant for Offg. Political Agent, Bahrain.TELEPHO N E! GERRARD 6351* TE LEG R AMS! VIOALABAK, PICCY, LONDON. CABLES'- BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. r F. P. Ba ker &amp; Co. Ltd. Bahrain, Persian Gulf, J 9-10, BOND COURT, WALBROOK, E.C.A. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE^ 20, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST., W. 1. PLEASE QUOTE N&lt;? We are in receipt of&gt;yohr advice Ox tne 14th inst,, Ref, 1210-17/2 and regret to learn that the s.s. 'TABABISTAh' short landed 6(six) ^gallons H Lion '• brand . di sinfecting fluid, and we are immediately taking the matter up with the Shipping Company concerned as we hold a copy of the original Bill of Lading. .i/e might mention that probably the ship, unon her return will,land the missing packages at a near* port, and we hope that you have already requested the ship»s agents Messrs. The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Ltd., to take this matter on your behalf. P fTE LEPM O N £! G E R R A R D 6 3 51* telegrams: VIDALABAK, PICCY, C. O N b O N. F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. CABLES: BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY'S CODE. r 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. The ^oliticau. ^gent, Bahrain, Persian Julf. v J -7 (ZC) CITY OFFICE: 8-10, BOND COURT, W A L B ROOK, E.C.A. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.O.3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE) 20, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST., W. 1. PLEASE QUOTE NO ■ »H IN REPLY Hoy 5th iepteiaher -j 93__5 / Dear Sir, nt ,/i th reference to your advice of I the 14th July enclosing short landing Certificate in respect to Drums of disinfecting fluid, we have now received information from the Shipping Company in London that they are unable to trace these two drums. ' /e suggest that to expedite the matter it would be a much better plan for you to make a claim on the Shipping Company at Bahrain, and for that purpose we return herewith the Certificate, but if you find any difficulty in obtaining settlement, upon receipt of your advice to this effect, we will take the matter up witn their London Office on your behalf. Your ,5 faithfully, F.P. B^xCCa Cc CO.,LTD.© No./?*£■-17/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, the liith October l^hb To, The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited, B A H H Alik Dear Sirs, 1 enclose a certificate of short-landing oi ttfo arums of disinfecting liquid shipped by Messrs.F.P.Baker ana Company Limited, Lonaon, by the S*S.'’Tab^ristan'’ which sailed for the Persian Quit on the 2hnd May 1035. 3. Messrs.F.P.Baker ana Company to whom the matter P V* was referred inform me that I shoula make a claim on the Shipping Company at Bahrain. I, therefore, request that you will take what action you consider necessary. Lieutenant, for Officiating Political Agent, Bahrainf mirtb-vt/u. PoXilio&amp;l h Bahrain, the 16th October 11/36. to fc'eat.rs. Prf. Baker and Ooapaaj limited. 3, Upper Junes Street, Golden Square, ae^ent Street, London, S.I. oV \A ' Dear Sirs, iTith relerenoe to the stotesfent oi account enclosed aith your letter Ko.Sji.Sf/42/IV dated the 16th ‘/ept other 193&amp;s U) afiQdS .ft/fi U.31? Ar.£^a3j.? and 2.2066 tor £.4$.6.7. fha tpieation of the missing arums of disinfecting / fluid hrus been takan up «ifch sue ioo;il ^hip ing OOfS; any- ’ ride your latter Ko.ol 3 dated the 5th i)eptambor 13%. hen they are received your bill sill be settled in lull. (2) i&amp;stiB. a/o *.38?. .lor £.3.U.d. In the absence of details it is diflioult to trace on those account the goods were sue, lied, and. ae stated by you, they my possibly bare been purchased ay the Eonourable Lieut(ansmt-Uolonei Gordon Loch, C.I.3., lor his personal use. Dould you therefore please furnish me with iUrther details, as Oolonol inch is at precent in Bushire. 1 »ll' H (2) fiffgfiji VSJiiikfeZL M I..mtilZaS ,.&gt;^g.gLv«&gt;■»f.lp»2» .These accounts have bean nettled/* please see the first paragraph of your letter dated the 16th September enclosing a receipt So»1620 dated the 10th September for the total amount, via. £.3jf».7.3. nli'&lt; V'(4) SOQdB a/c lor One teapot end two eauoer* wen nod broken. I aaaoloee Lloyd*e Surrey Oertifioatc ^0*30 and ro^keat you to replace Site brealrag©®* j aii tor this eutrey «pb oae gaiaea a j-ng taxi hire, the total eggngattnr ludSdSUO (eae duplicate receipt enclosed £or your iaforaatioa); this aaount will bo deducted iroai your biU, which will be settled «h«» the replacements are received. Tours faithfully. Sd/- H. D. Metcalfe Lieuten^t, for Officiating political Agent, Bahrain.3 f INCORPORATING: STEPHEN LYNCH 8, 09 LYNCH BROTH E RS, L T P GRAY, MACKENZIE 8. C9 AND GRAY, PAUL S. C9 The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation, (0 Telegraphic Address&gt;- 'mespersV Codes used: 1 Bentley's Complete Phrase Code. Scott'sTenth Edition. * The Standard Shipping Code. A.B.C. 5! 1 ? Edition. N ? Z/g'J Dear Sir, Short-lu.naed ex.S .a* H Tabariijt&lt;u.n“ v*26 f We refer you to your letter No.1758/17/2 uateu the 12th ultimo, ana have to inform you that since we have so far failed to locate the above 2 Drums, we suggest you send in your Claim Bill in duplicate, supported by the re lative Original Shippers Invoice, to this Office, and we will put it before the Bteamshlp 'c.concerned for necessary action. _ „ ^ours faithfully, ry., ? \ ' ■ • v / Vv ?(v AGENTS. 'STRICT LINES'*TELEPHO N B: GERRARD S351* telegrams: VIDALABAK, PICCY, LONDON. CA B LE 9: BANSHEE. LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. ' f ' / \ / , F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, ax REGENT STREET, k) LONDON. W. I. CITY OFFICE: flltl. 1 9-10, BOND COURT, V» WALB ROOK, E.C.A. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.O.3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE) 20, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST, W. 1. The Political Agent, Bahrain, PERSIAN GULP ICALAtj*: ,®V 23 1335 PLEASE QUOTE N9 0 • D • 9 • IN R E p LT ..£.th.... 193 8316 Dear Sir, Jf^ar t are duly in receipt of your letter of the 27th'November, and have the pleasure to enclose herewith receipt for your remittance value £51 .0*2. We also thank you for passing us a copy of your letter to the Mesopotamia Persia Cpn.Ltd. dated the 26th November , and we are making the necessary claim on the underwriters. disposal, Placing our services entirely at your l We are,Dear str, Yours faithijm-Ly, p.p.bakiMAnd GO.LTD, uTE LEPH ONE: GERRARD 6351* TE UEG R AMS: VIDALABAK, PICCY, LONDON. nr v F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. nt CITY OFFICE: 9-10, BOND COURT, W AI_B ROOK, E.C.A. CABLES: BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. r 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. ~ * X The Political Agent* Bahrain, PERSIAN GULF. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE) 20, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST., W. 1. G.D.9. PLEASE QUOTE NP Q T j g IN REPLY 1 9th B eeember 193 ij- It*' to* [4 i Dear Sir, „ , u Ij/further reference to our letter °5 D n th . :Lnst * with regard to the question of the claim for the dis-infectant fluid ant was short landed, we see that you have deducted £1 , whereas the value of the two drums was 5/- plus our buying commission of bh. In the circumstances we should aporeciate it if you will deduct the value of these two drums from the amount of the invoice j- or tne disinfectant fluid and favour us wioa your remittance in due course . We can then make the necessary claim on the underwrit ers• Placing our services entirely at your disposal, We are,Dear Sir, Yours faithfully, P.P. BAKERiV AIR MAIL. © /1 No. 25'&gt;/i7/g. Politics! Agency, Bahrain, the 2tth January 19J56, A 1 V&gt;' To Mesers F.P. Baker and Company Limited, 2 , Tipper Jamea Street, Golden Square, Regent Street, LONDON, Vr’.l. Dear Sira, V/ith reference to your letter No. 0 .D. 9. 831S dated the 19th December 1935, I beg to encloae a Priti&amp;h Postal Crder for 1 ^/° (fourteen shillings and nine pence only) in aettlement of your claim in respect of disinfecting fluid. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, Captain, For Political Agent Bahrain,^ AIR . '/ML. © No. lfb/17/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, the gcth January 1956. v&gt; To Messrs F.P. Baker and Company Limited, 2, Upper James Street, Golden Square, Regent Street, LONDON, Vr’.l. Dear Sirs, V/ith reference to your letter No.C .D. 9. 8316 dated the 19th December 1935, I beg to enclose a f-ritish Postal Order for 14/9 ffourteen shillings and nine pence only; in settlement of your claim in respect of disinfecting fluid. Please acknowledge receipt. A. J •i « telephone G E R R AR D 6351* TE LEG R A M S: VIDALABAK, PICCY, LONDON. n|&lt;/ F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. CABLES: BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY'S CODE. A. B.O. CODE. ETC. ETC. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.0.3. r PLEASE QUOTE N9 C.D.9* 830 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. The Political Agent, Bahrain, PERSIAN IN REPLY 6th_ February 193 6 WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE) 20, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST..W. 1. Dear Sir, We are duly in receipt of your letter of the 26th ult. No.253/17/2, and have the pleasure to enclose herewith receipt for your remittance value 1 U/Sd for v/hich we thank you. Placing our services entirely at your disposal,No. By 2, UPPER JAMES STREET GOLDEN SQUARE, W. 1. (TiV) ^ KfU'ttU'D C^QkSha^, us^y^.'. the sum of ™ Pounds • &gt; Shillings .(sJI’w'va-- Pence for F. R. BAKER &amp; Co. Ltd. -r. ft,No.-17/2 Political Agency, Bali rain, the 3 th June 1933. To Messrs. Mama anu Company, Gran t Roa d, KARACHI. Lear Sira, Please supply this Agency with the following articles. Your bill will be paid on the receipt of the consignment 1. Waste cotton (good quality) 1 cwt. 3. Manilla rope, 1&amp;' circumference .. 1 coil. Yours faithfully, iP- for Qffg. Political Agent, Bahrain.M fia4 CUSTOMERS'CARS AND CYCLES DRIVEN AND STORED ENTIRELY AT CUSTOMERS* OWN RISK AS REGARDS FIRE OR DAMAGE ALL ORDERS CONTRACTS AND AGREEMENTS ARE CONTINGENT UPON STRIKES ACCIDENTS AND OTHER CAUSES BEYOND OUR CONTROL PHONE N9 62S TELEGRAMS 'AUTOMOBILE' e i l o O X i NARAINDAS &amp; C° AUTOMOBILE ENGINEERS CODES BENTLEYS GENERAL MOTORS &amp; PRIVATE GARDEN ROAD KARACHI tA&gt; Tha Political Agent, Political Agency, BAHRAIN. 12th June-1926* _ „ ^ A ^ ^ Dear Sir, We thank you for your esteemed order No: 1^49/ 17/2^ dated 8th June and beg to state that we are arranging to despatch mobil oil by boat sailing next week* As regards your order for bulbs, we beg to state that your order is not clear to us. Please infom us for what purpose idn^ these bulbs are required and also state voltage, current D.C. or A.G. All particulars may kindly be furnished to enable us to ensure correct supply. Awaiting the favour of your early reply, we remain, 1 mmm**'No.1664-17/2 irolitical Agency, Baiimin, the 25th Jime 1936 Messrs. Naraindas and Company Limited, Bundar Boad, Karachi# Lear Sirs, yf * ^ Please refer to your ieiter No#3344 dated the 13th June 1936* fhe particulars of the bulls are as follows •— 40 watts, 230 volts, Alternative current, (for the use in the office) •lh. 25 watts, 230 volts. Alternative current, l for the use in the verandah) lo* 12 volts, 75 C.P., Li root current, ^for motor launch &amp; motor car)♦♦••••••• o. lours faithfully, {jp--* for Offg. Political Jigent, W w 1 T\I / • CUSTOMERS'CARS AND CYCLES DRIVEN AND STORED ENTIRELY AT CUSTOMERS’OWN RISK AS REGARDS FIRE OR DAMAGE ALL ORDERS CONTRACTS AND AGREEMENTS ARE CONTINGENT UPON STRIKES ACCIDENTS AND OTHER CAUSES BEYOND OUR CONTROL PHONE N? 62S TELEGRAMS AUTOMOBILE’ NARAINDAS &amp; C° AUTOMOBILE ENGINEERS CODES BENTLEVS GENERAL MOTORS &amp; PRIVATE / c &gt; A ? ^ ‘Jl Cm kJ 0 w GARDEN ROAD KARACHI 4th July-1536• F^irther to our letter No: 384^ ?ated 13th June we beg to enclose herein Bill of Lading No: 58 for 3 c/s of Oils shipped to you and shall be glad to receive your acknow ledgment. fhe bill for the sane is attached hereto. Awaiting the favour of your further esteemed orders, we remain, Yours faithfully, NARAINDAS 6c CO-, ForTele S ^'^•“CONCRETE' ' phone No. 248. From, AM A &amp; company GOVERNMENT CONTRACTORS, MANUFACTURERS* REPRESENTATIVES, IMPORTERS &amp; EXPORTERS. _ Dated, 3 Oth June 193 6* Sb« Political Agency, BAHRAIN. Codes Used A. B. C. 5th &amp;. 6th Editions, Bentley’s Code, Schofield’s &amp; Oriental 3-Letters Code 3t Private. Dear Sirs 193 We thank you for your order No* 1548-17/2 dated the 8th inst# for Cotton Waste and Manilla Rope # We have shipped the material per s#s* Bandra sailed hence on 28th inst* for your port and now enclose our hill together with the shipping documents. We shall he obliged if you fovour us with a remittance at your early convenience. Yours faithfully. FOR MA.MA &amp; COMPANY.Agents for: ir wr T elegrams: “CONCRETE” Karachi. BILL No. 867. * u Telephone No. 2 2 4 8 i(«) Mangalore Roofing Tiles. SPECIALITIES : CORRUGATED &amp; MILD STEEL BARS ROUND &amp; SQUARE IN ALL LENGTHS AND CHANNELS. PAINTS &amp; OILS RE[L LEAD DRY. WHITE ZINC MOIST. CEN T: D. B. LINSEED OIL &amp; COAL TAR. CEMENTS. ANCHOR, GANPATI, B B B, COLOURED AND GRIFFIN BRAND WHITE CEMENT. PRICES ON APPLICATION. Political Agency, GRANT ROAD, &gt;Arm T 27th June. 19Z6. 1Q3 Dr. BAHRAIN. To MAMA &amp; CO., METAL &amp; CEMENT MERCHANTS, GOVERNMENT CONTRACTORS &amp; GENERAL SUPPUERS. Interest at 9% will be charged if not paid within 7 days. Description. Cotton Waste Manilla Rope r£-'Circumferncls Steamer freight etc. Rupees Fifty ihree and annas fo E. $ 0. E. Bund les. No. Quantity. T. C. Qr. Lbs. Rate. Rs. A. P. Per. Rs. A. P. ulrtden only. 8 0 Cwt. 0 0 53 14 lii^ I ak 1 t Messrs. B. B. IPSBMAN &amp; MOHATTA, Ltd. request their constituents to see, before taking delivery of parcels from the Railway, that the. weights agree exactly with those noted in the Railway Receipts, and also that the parcels have no appearance of having been tampered with in transit. All claims for damage or deficiency must be made at the time of delivery as the Railway companies decline alt responsibility once a clear receipt is in their hands. N. B.—Our responsibility ceases with the delivery of the goods to t he Railway at Karachi. : |BRANCHES! contractors to government. CHARING CROSS LAHORE LOKHAN BAZAR. BHAVNAGAR. NAYA BAZAR AJMER. EXPANSION. KARACHI. EXPANSION. LAHORE. EXPANSION. BHAVNAGAR. EXPANSION, AJMER. 47 &amp; 326. 2330 ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. ENGINEERS. SHIPBUILDERS &amp; METAL MERCHANTS. CODES; VULCAN IRON WORKS, QUEEN’S ROAD &amp;. WOOD STREET. Bentley’s Phrase 1st &amp; 2nd A. B. C. 6th Edition &amp; Universal Trade. KARACHI, 193 Dr. O. NO. TERMS:— 7 Days from date Of delivery after which INTEREST will be charged. BILL NO. M. D jL • 2 • T0» a*I. fliifirtxUs 5/16' (!£• long) ' Shaoi&lt;’l3S 5/16' (l - long ) Shipping oharges under j- freight at amp on B/Lsding Lighterage wharfage cartage QUANTITY RATE T. C. QR. Lbs. PER AMOUNT RS. A. P. (Bupeea ft ir hundred ninety annas fourteen and pies nine only) * Your order W.50-.iM...!^8,a c s^ Bh Brokers. 1 B.R. Herman No 3 • • • • Da tddl# .6.». t.V' 6 1 osed herewith. D. M. No of date YLT. tiLXXXkAtSi 490 14 9 -mmmmmmmmmn tic# 0^ 2 # ta Ltd*i 1 V Through contractors to government. Branches: CHARING CRCSS, LAHORE. BAGHPAT ROAD, MEERUT. Metal Stock Yards: JALLO, LAHORE &amp; MEERUT. Telegrams: EXPANSION, KARAOHL EXPANSION, LAHORE. EXPANSION, MEERUT. Telephones; 47 A 326. 2330. 206. ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, Ltd- v Codes: Bentley’s Phrase 1st A 2nd A. B. C. 6 th Edition &amp; Universal Trade. ENGINEERS &amp; SHIPBUILDERS. Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Road A Wood Street, KARACHI, t-h .Tnop 1936 . Xhe Politic-l .jw/entt -BehralB^- Dr. Terms of Payment: — Bills not paid within 15 days interest @ 9% will be charged. Order No. Bill No. 0/2&gt; Delivery order No. Datemm V Through Vf J Branchea: CHAEING CROSS, LAHORE. BAGHPAT ROAD, MEERUT. Metal Stock Yards: JALLO, LAHORE &amp; MEERUT. CONTRACTORS TO GOVERNMENT. Telegrams: EXPANSION, KARACHL EXPANSION, LAHORE. EXPANSION, MEERUT. Telephones? 47 A 326, 2330. 206. Codes! Bentley’s Phrase 1st &amp; 2nd A. B. C. 6 th Edition &amp; Universal Trade. ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA. Ltd* ENGINEERS &amp; SHIPBUILDERS. Vulcan Iron Works, Queen’s Road &amp; Wood Street, KARACHI, 25t'i , T unp 193 . 6 Terms of Payment: — Bill* not paid within 15 days interest @ 9% will be charged, *■40 No ah the terms^ppovisions and conditions of the Indian Carriage of Goods by Sea A&lt; are to a^ply to the contract contained jn this Bill of Lading, and the Compan all p e ih'ileghs, rights and immunities contained in such Act, and the Schedule th&lt; specifically set out. ' If anything herein contained be inconsistent with the said ich inconsistency and no furthof be null ^nd void. It is hereby expressly fi of Article 7 of the^chedule to the said Act, that the carriers’ lia Tom the shii, shall be governed by the condi /provision! subsequent to the discharge^ f / 1 Lading PARTICULAES DECLARED BY SHIPPER. Leading Marks. Distinctive Numbers. Number of Packages or pieces or Description. Quantity or weight. b/l/A'hvL but it JSdtistf tl 3i Steam IRafioatfon Company, % w (Incorporated in Ingland.) 'requested to note particularly the terms and conditions of this Bill validity of their Insurance upon the Goods. The Goods are shipped and this Bill of Lading granted subject to the f&lt; Any claim for short delivery of or damage done to Goods, and all other cla Company’s option at Port of Discharge, or at Ports of Calcutta or Bombay and at &gt; claim for damage will be admitted unless notified in writing before the Goods kshort landing, non-delivery, total loss, or any other c fless made in writing fithin one month fr $7 Jf fdud ’ Number of Packages (in worlds) but with liberty either before or after proceeding whatsoever (although in a contrary direction to, Discharge) once or oftener, in any order, backwards or any purpose whatsoever, and all such ports, places, also with libertv to tow and assist Vessels in all also to sail with or without pilots : CltSLC lAAt. being marked and numbered as per margin. The said goods to be carried and del conditions of/Tjs Bill of Lading in the like good order and condition at the Port &lt; AND WEIGHT. The Company shall not be liable for loss, damage or delay directly or indirectly causes or perils, howsoever occasioned ; viz.. Act of God ; King’s enemies ; piracy ; : without violence on board or elsewhere and whether bv persons in the service of tl restraints of princes, rulers, or people; riots and commotions ^^fckes, lock barratry; jettison; collision; fire; Petroleum vapo rbreakage or ®Page ; vei holds ; climate ; rain ; injurious effect of other goods, whether ly contact or othe and accidents of the sea, rivers or navigation ; unseaworthiness, unfitness, or defect tackle, equipment, Engines or appurtenances at the commencement or any stage meads 'SiAv* jjeen taken by the Company at the port of siipment to prevent wlmtawtever of piTotg uiaster, officers, mariners, engineers, stevedores or other server flDornpany oh board^mr elsewhere, in the management, navigation or otherwise belonging tb tke Compkny, or in the loading, stowing, carriage, unloading or deliver The Company i» to fce at liberty to carry the goods to their Port of Destinati steamer of steamers, ship or ships, Motor vessel or vessels eitier belonging to tl ■y and to tranship or land, and store the goods either on shore or afloat and to re-ship a expense but at shippers or consignee’s risk ; and at the like risk, to deviate as abovey arritge to. r that Port to proceed to, of, or beyond, the ordinal .ards, [or loading or dischs ''sailings, ihall be deemed inc it ions suuljt) deviate forj In all cases and Under all circumstances the Company’s liability shall absolutely/ the vessel’s tackle and thereupon the goods shall be at the risk for all purposes or Consignee, .Freight at the rate of payable in. per margin vessel and/or cargo lost or not lost.Indian Carriage of Goods by Sea Act, 1925, and the Schedule thereto is Bill of Lading, and the Company is to be entitled to the benefit of in such Act, and the Schedule thereto as if the same were herein itained be inconsistent with the said provisions it shall to the extent of nd void. It is hereby expressly further agreed in pursuance of the the said Act, that the carriers’ liability, prior to the loading on, and , shall be governed by the conditions and exceptions of this Bill of 3nMa , 'W«*S T AS ation Company, Ximlteb Incorporated in Ingland.) terms and conditions of this Bill of Lading with reference to the their Insurance upon the Goods. of Lading granted subject to the following express conditions:— e done to Goods, and all other claims whatsoever, to be presented at orts of Calcutta or Bombay and at no other Port. notified in writing before the Goods are removed, n-delivery, total loss, or any other claim whatsoever, in respect to the made in writing fithin one month from the date of arrival of the vessel. g toward^that Port to proceed to, and stay at any ports or places o, or o/nt of, or beyond, the ordinary or usual route to the said Port of rds pytfpwards, for loading or discharging cargo or passengers, or for sailings, ihall be deemed included within the ii^enled voyage : 1 ^ftj^Stions deviate formic purpose of savinglifir or property le said goods to be carried and delivered, ytiject f t the terms and order and condition at the Port of.. or his or their assigns. image or delay directly or indirectly resulting from any of the following of God ; King’s enemies ; piracy ; robbery ; theft or pilferage with or ther bv persons in the service of the Company or not; arrests and and commotions ^^B[kes, lockouts or other labour disturbances ; vapo 'breakage or ^j^age ; vermin ; sweat; rust; temperature of 'oods, whether by contact or otherwise howsoever; perils, dangers jnscaworthiness, unfitness, or defect of any kind in hull, machinery, .t the commencement or any stage of the voyage (provided reasonable t the port of skipment to prevent same); any act, neglect or default tigineers, stevedores or other servants or agents whatsoever of the nagement, navigation or otherwise of the vessel or of any other vessel •wing, carriage, unloading or delivery of the cargo. ie goods to their Port of Destination by the above, or any other el or vessels either belonging to theaCompany or to other persons, :r on shore or afloat and to re-ship aim forward same at the Company’s at the like risk, to deviate as above/mentioned. ’ompany’s liability shall absolutelyy ocase when the goods are free of 1 be at the risk for all purposes kmaf in every respect of the Shipper / payable in. largo lost or not lost. / / M. M. 140. 7/29. Mitness whereof the Commander or Agents of the said vessel have affirmed to... true Bills of Lading, all of this tenor and date ; one of which Bills of Lading being accomplished the others to stand void. Gonoral avtrago to be adjusted according to York-Antwerp Rules, 1924. This Bill of Lading is issuod subjoci to tho following turthor conditions :— Weight, contents and value when shipped unknown. The Company is not to be responsible for any loss, damage or delay, whatsoever, directly or indirectly resulting from insufficiency of the address, or packing, internal or external : nor for condition or contents of re-shipped or re-exported Goods. * a - Company reserves the right of charging freight by weight, measurement or value, and of re-measuring or re-weighing f the. floods and charging freight accordingly before delivery. Freight on salt, saltpetre, dates, fruit and perishable godds is to be paid on the weight shipped, and no allowance will be made for wastage, shrinkage, or dryage on the voyage. The Company does not guarantee room at ports of transhipment and is not to be responsible for any detention or delay there or at arry n ttiwr sta ge of t he voyage howsoeVer caused. Packages weighing more than 3 cwts. (excepting bales and boxes of manufactured Goods) are only carried at advanced rates of freight and by special agreement. The Company shall have a lien for freight unpaid on these Goods, or upon any portion of the Goods covered by the Shipping Order or Advice Note granted in respect thereof, which may not have been shipped, and for any charges herein stipulated to be borne, or customarily borne, by the Shipper or Consignee of the Goods. Should all or any part of the within Goods not be found, or if from bad weather or other cause the Goods cannot be landed during the Vessel’s stay at Port of Destination, the Company reserves the right to convey same to any Port before the final or to the final Port’of the voyage to be returned thence at the Company’s expense, but at the Shipper’s or Consignee’s risk ; and should necessity arise for detaining and storing the Goods, it shall also be done at the Company’s expense and the Shipper’s or Consignee’s risk ; and the Company shall not be answerable for the result of any delay or risk so occasioned or for loss of Market. The Company will not be accountable for Gold, Silver, Bullion, Specie, Jewellery, Precious Stones, Precious Metals, Plated Ware, Documents, Works of Art, Watches, Silks or other precious or valuable article?, in any respect, or for Goods of any description whatever the value of which is more than one thousand rupees ■ per freight ton, nor for goods of which the value exceeds five hundred rupees for any one package, unless the value* thereof shall have been declared in writing prior to shipment, and a special written Shipping Order or Advice Note granted for same which must be presented to the Commander at time of shipment and the Bill of Lading signed with the nature and value of the goods appearing thereon and extra freight in respect of same agreed upon and paid. A wrong description of Contents or false declaration of value shall release the Company from all responsibility in case of loss, seizure, or detention, and the Goods shall be charged double freight on the real value, which freight shall be paid previous to delivery. The only condition on which Glass, China, Earthenware, Iron castings, or other fragile Goods of a like character will be carried is that the Company is free from liability for breakage however caused. If medicinal fluids or any other Goods of an explosive, inflammable, damaging or dangerous nature are shipped without being previously declared and arranged for, they are liable upon discovery to be thrown overboard, and the loss will fall upon the Shipper or Consignee of such fluids or Goods. The Shipper or Consignee will not only be liable to the penalties imposed by Statute but also for all damages sustainedi^j^fcquence of the shipment of such fluids or Goods. The Goods are to be distinctly marked witbrthe marks, fl^Bers and Port of Destination, or the Company is not to be responsible for detention or wrong deliVexw. H * '■ 'h ■ Pi ■*. Bills of Lading must be presented ajjdrdgnverefwp cancelled before delivery of Goods will be granted. The Company is to have the option of delivering these Goods, or any part thereof, into receiving Ship, or boat or craft, or landing them at the risk and expense of the Shipper or Consignee as per scale of charges to be seen at the Agents’ Offices, and is also to be at liberty until delivery to store the Goods or any part thereof in receiving Ship, godown, or upon any wharf, the usual charges thereof being payable by the Shipper or Consignee. The Company shall have a lien on all or any part of the Goods against expenses incurred on the whole or any part of the shipment. Fire Insurance will be covered by the Company’s Agents on application. Gold, Silver, Bullion, Specie, Jewellery, Precious Stones, Precious Metals, Plated Ware, Documents, Works of Art, Watches, Silks or other Precious or valuable articles will not be landed by the Company. They will only be delivered on presentation of Bills of Lading on board, and will be carried on, or stored, at risk and expense of Shipper or Consignee, if delivery is not taken during the vessel’s stay in Port. Notwithstanding anything herein contained to the contrary in the event of restrictions of Quarantine, Prohibition, Sanitary or Customs or Labour Regulations, Lockouts or Strikes, Blockade or Interdict at the Port of Discharge, war or disturbance or other like cause preventing or threatening to prevent the ordinary discharge of the Goods or any portion thereof, at the Port of Destination, such Goods or any portion thereof may at the vessel’s option either be put into other vessels or be retained on board and landed and warehoused or otherwise disposed of as circumstances may admit wheresoever most convenient to the vessel, and re-shipped thence to destination as soon as conveniently may be after such restrictions as aforesaid have been removed or be returned to Port of Shipment, and all expenses whatsoever incurred in such landing, warehousing, transhipment, over carriage or return carriage or otherwise shall be borne by the Shipper or Consignee, the Company having a lien on the Goods therefor. The Company shall not be responsible for loss or damage of any kind which may result directly or indirectly from the above causes or any of them, and the Goods shall throughout be at the Shipper’s or Consignee’s risk. Delivery by the Company of packages externally in good condition as received shall be conclusive evidence of delivery of full weight 4 ml cquUsttS. 1 ~ ^ / !/* i fTTi Capta m. for Agents.\0 No. Political Agency Bahrain July 21, 1936 To The Kaetem Bank Limited BAHRAIN Gentlemen, v;ill you please istue the following three drafts on Karachi and debit the cost to the Treasury Account of this Agency 1. P-s. 538-3-0 in favour of B.R, Herman A Mohatta, Limited, 2. Re* 53-14 ' in favour of Mama and Company, 3. Re* 75-7-0 in favour of Naraindas and Company. Yours faithfully a Capta in Offg. Political Agent, Bahrain A.-17/^ Political Agency, Bahra in, July 22, 1936. T v Meetre B.R. Herman &amp; Mohatta, Limited, Engineers and Shipbuilders, Queens Road, KARACHI . Gentlemen, I enclose a cheque No. L.I. 1962^ fo^ Rs. 538-3- in full settlement of your bills Nos. S/1573A/2341 and ft® 9/D 7784 dated the 30th and 26th June 1936 respectively. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, Captain, Offg. Political Agent, Bahrain. 7^ i i i j /BY AIR -mT, . No, IT/ft, Political Agency, Bahrain, July 22, 1956. To Mesara Naraindas and Company, Automobile Engineera, Garden Road, KARACHI , Gentlemen, I end08e a draft No. L.I. I96p6' for ^b. 75-^-0 in full Bettlement of your bill No. 4296 dated the 4th July 1936 and request the favour of an acknowledgment. Yours faithfully, 7 a: Captain, Offg. Political Agent,Bahrain,wmm n L Political Agency, Bahrain, July 22, 1936, Messrs Mama and Company, Grant Road, KARACHI, Gentlemen, I enclose a draft No, L.I. 19(3^? fo*r Rs. 53-14-0 in full settlement of your hill No. 867 dated the 27th June and request the favour of an acknov* ledgment. Yours faithfully, 'ffg. Political Agent, Bahrain. Captain, /I - CUSTOMERS' CARS ANO CYCLES DRIYEW^fflD STOREI -lERiMW RISK AS REGARDS FIRE OR DAMAGE ALL ORDERS CONTRACTS AND AGREEMENJ#kRE CONTING (IDEA! AND OTHER CAUSES BEYOND OUR CONT [r PHON^. N? 62 8 RAMS 'au'i mobile' - NARAINDAS &amp;C° AUTOMOBILE ENGINEERS GARDEN ROAD KARACHI CODES BENTLEYS GENERAL MOTORS 4 PRIVATE 15th July-1936* — il ■ m Z A The Political Agent Political Agency, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, Vie thank you for^the^ favour of your esteemed letter dated 25th June and beg to state that we are arranging to despatch the bulbs in question in couple of days# Always at your service,BHANCHr*: Charing Cross, L.AHORF. Lokhan Bazar. BHAVNAGAR From. No. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA LTD. VULCAN IRON WORKS. Engineers. Founders &amp; General Contractors, QUEENS ROAD &amp; WOOD STREET, Karachi, 29-7- 36 3f&gt;cmoran&lt;&gt;um. To TeLCGRAMS: EXPANSION. KARACHI Cooesi BENTLEY’S PHRASE. Telephone No. 47 193 tlQal jx£ enjt % rT' 1 04c 2- v Sir v V Jo warns' 51 / rW§SA5i® tv« beg io acknowledge with thanks the receipt of your favour No. dated 2^7-36 covering a Cheque f or R °- b 3 Q/'i/- (Rupees Five Hundred Thirty -light &amp; Ae.Three Only. m full settlement of our Bill No.? S/l573A/234l and CD 778 4. official receipt is enclosed herewith. Esteeming your further orders. Yours faithfully, B. R. HERMAN MOHATTA Ltd 7 Enclo.Tolo \ g» , ams:-“CONCRETE” lele ? phone No. 248. From, Memweinhntti. MAMA &amp; COMPANY GOVERNMENT CONTRACTORS, MANUFACTURERS’ REPRESENTATIVES, IMPORTERS &amp; EXPORTERS. Dated, 28th July 193 g To, Political Agent, Bahrain. Codes Used :• A. B. C. 5th &amp; 6th Editions, Bentley's Code. Schofield's &amp;. Oriental 3-Letters Code &amp;. Private. Grant Road, KARACHI. Dear Sir, We thank yo&gt;r f^r your favour of 22nd instant enclosing a draft for Hs.53-14-0 which amount we have realized and credited to your account. As desired we now enclose our stamped receipt for the same* Yours faithfully. Enel: 1(RECEIPT) N.tele{ 0 Phone 7028. Grams:—AUTOMOBILE. PARTS &amp; 155 ESTABLISHED 1905. Vi i i Statement of Account for the month of j. P „ fl - ( CLa^, 193{) Ur. NARAINDAS &amp; CO., AUTOMOBILE ENGINEERS. KARACHI. JV? 57 Note:- Bills not paid on presentation are subject to 12 per Date. t v Voucher No. DESCRIPTION. ^ ' 4 L 'ey VwGENERAL MOTORS INDIA LIMITED AN INDIAN INDUSTRY OPERATING STATISTICS YEAR 1935 NUMBER OF EMPLOYEES:— INDIAN . . . 752 BRITISH AND AMERICAN ... 21 TOTAL ... 773 Salaries and Wages . . . Rs. 9 , 00,000 Taxes paid . • . ,, 2,00,000 Rentals paid ... „ 1,50,000 Paid to Railways and Coastal Shipping „ 10,00,000 Other Expenditures for materials, travel, insurance etc. ,, 15,50,000 Total Expenditures in India... Rs. 38,00,000 BECAUSE of the operation of the Assembly Plant at Sewri ... This Rs. 38,00,000 has remained in Ind ia. ^ Seven hundred and fifty Indians have employment, which gives them training in modern industry and business methods. ^ Purchasers of General Motors cars paid Rs. 12,00,000 less for their cars than would have been necessary if the cars had been imported complete from Western countries. 37 % of all motor vehicles sold in INDIA, BURMA, and CEYLON were assembled and sold by GENERAL MOTORS INDIA LIMITED PONTIAC LA SALLE CHEVROLET VAUXHALL B U I C K BEDFORD OLDSMOBILE CADILLAC OPEL G. M. CNo. ^2^ -17/2 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 18th October, 1936 . To Messrs. Herman ana Kohatta Limited, Vulcan Iron »«orks, ^ueen f s Hoad and ifiooc street, Karachi. Lear birs, Please supply this Agency with 20 (twenty) gallons Red Anti-sea fouling paint. 2. Your bill will be paid on the receipt of the consignment. Yours faithfully, for Ofig. Politic?1 Agent,Bahrain.Telephone No. 47 . Post Box No. 11 . ESTABLISHED 1883. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, LTD. VULCAN IRON WORKS. ENGINEERS &amp; SHIPBUILDERS. Telegrams: “ EXPANSION ” KARACHI. _ A CODE: Bentley’s Phrase Code. The Political AgonX, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Office and Works: Queens Road, KARACHI. 31st October 193 6. Bill of Lading We have pleasure in enclosing No. 573 dated 3iat inst. y for the undermentioned goods in compliance with order No. 2625-17/2 I/18.10.36 Trusting the material will arrive safely and esteeming your further orders. End;- 1 B/Lading. drums Antifouling paint No. 2 . Yours faithfully, VLT. IMPORTANT SEE OVERLEAF.l 'i \H A \ 81 X.M O Messrs. B. R. HERMAN &amp; MOHATTA, Ltd. request their constituents to see, before taking deHverjr of ■ paroeli from the Railway, that the weights agree exactly with those noted in the Railway Receipts, and also that the parcels have no appearance of having been tampered with in transit. All claims for damage or deficiency must be made at the tim^ of 'delivery as the’ Railway companies decline all responsibility once a clear receipt is in their hands. N. B.—Our responsibility ceases with the delivery of the goods to the Railway at Karachi. X .ot. j i: ; s • w u i 0 ^ - '\ if •i iV e iiA'i iKind Snow white (Nicolac)Enamel paint List of Stores Required for the Current Year, 1937. a************ For What Purpose Launches Light oak waste cotton manilla rope, 7/8 M circumference ^4 . S'^-O-o 30- 9.0 IS- 0-0 / 5 ) 2 nieces sailing canvas^ thin quality, n for ^ails. Union Viceroy flags, size 6 f x S 1 Flags, L.G.4, Launches') L. \~rK 8 ) gallons. Vacuum mobile oil ’’A” . 10) 3 cwts. Snow white ready made paint Agency building. Grey bitumastic ready made paint 12 ) ^6 kegs (2 Red Oxide paint S' £5-0.* &amp; 1 -Z .0 Agency building and /g 1 -^^ launches. Agency tO~ Q-o s» drains etc. Agency building. Flagstaff/ ru-'WH' No. 43 b- 17 / 2 . Political iigency, Bahrain, the 20tu February 1337. To i Mesors. Iiaramdas anu Company, Automobile engineers, Garden Roau, K AImCHI. Dear Sirs, Please supply tms Agency witn tne tollowing articles, four bill will be paid on the receipt oi the consignment Vacuum mobile oil, T, A' ^ gallons. '3B' 3 for •Political Agent, lianrain.CUSTOMER'S CARS AND CYCLES DRIVEN AND STORED ENTIRELY AT CUSTOMERS’ OWN RISK AS REGARDS FIRE OR DAMAGE ALL ORDERS CONTRACTS*. AGREEMENTS ARC CONTINGENT UPON STRIKES ACCIDENTS *. OTHER CAUSES BEYOND OUR-CONTROL ACCIDENTS NARAINDAS &lt;5- Co. AUTOMOBILE ENGINEERS PHONE No. 7028. ^LEGRAMS ‘V., rOMOBILE” GARDEN ROAD KARACHI . CODES BENTLEY’S GENERAL MOTORS PRIVATE f c, f The Political Agency/ ^ BAHRAIN. V' &gt; X Dear Sir, 2/th February-1937. re i;!,. \ W'e thank you for the favour of your/dated 20th instant and beg to state that each c/s of Mobil Oil contains 6 gallon tins and hence, we are sending you 3 c/s ccraplGte containing 18 gallons of ..ohil Oil i.e. 9 tins each type ,f A' and 'BB' to minimize the freight charges. We hope you *a111 kindly approve of our action. Always at your service, Yours faithfully.CUSTOMERS'CARS AND CYCLES DRIVEN AND STORED ENTIRELY AT CUSTOMERS'OWN RISK AS REGARDS FIRE OR DAMAGE ALL ORDERS CONTRACTS AND AGREEMENTS ARE CONTINGENT UPON STRIKES ACCIDENTS AND OTHER CAUSES BEYOND OUR CONTROL PHONE N? 628 TELEGRAMS 'AUTOMOBILE' AO Q 4 a U 0 NARAINDAS &amp; C° AUTOMOBILE ENGINEERS GARDEN R0A1 KARACHI CODES BENTLEVS JENERAL MOTORS &amp; PRIVATE 27th Pebruary-19I57e The Political Agent, Political Agency, BAHRAIN. If 16 \i K ‘WL * 1 ^ v Dear Sir, A'* Further to our letter dated 24th instant, we beg to advise thet we are arranging to send you 3 c/s of Lubricating Oil by the mail sailing on Sunday the 28th February and request you to kindly take its delivery and oblige. The Bill of Lading alongwith the invoice will follow. Awaiting the favour of your further esteemed orders, which we assure you, will receive our prompt attention, we are, for Yours faithfully, NARAI t-f.Established 1918. Cable Add .-'CONCRETE' Telephone { Office 248. Nos. i Residence 338. Codes used A. B. C. 5th &amp; 6th Editions, Bentley's Code, Schofield's &amp; Oriental 3-Letters Code &amp; Private. GOVERNMENT CONTRACTORS, MANUFACTURERS’ REPRESENTATIVES, IMPORTERS &amp; EXPORTERS. SPECIALITIES Corrugated Steel Bars. M. S. Round &amp; Square Bars, Timber of all Kinds, Paints, Mangalore Roofing Tiles, White Portland Cement e? Tiles, and 'ANCHOR' 'GANPATI' 'BBB' Rainbow Colour Cements. BANKERS:- Bear Sirs, Reference to your letter Ho.434-17/2 of 20 th ultimo, .ve beg to inform you that we regret we are out of Stock of Manilla Rope of the size required by you, and is not available in the - Karachi market as well. If approved we can supply you 1 M and 3 / 4 M . Assuring you of our best services at all times. Yours faithfully, NS/Ss. JT7 ® No. 654-17/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 19th Harch 1937. To Messrs Mama and Company, Grant Hoad, Karachi. Gentlemen, Reference your letter ted the 4th March 1937. Pl^ ase supply Manilla rope of the size originally ordered by me when it becomes available. In the meantime as the cotton waste is urgently required I should be glad if you would despatch it at your earliest convenience. Yours fa : thfully,♦ GERRARD 6351* TELEGRAMS: VIDALABAK, PICCV, LONDON. BANKERS: WESTMIN&amp;+ER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. r C.D. 9. PL 3E QUOTE N&lt;? 1 229 ■ ' nr F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUAR REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. The Political AgVit, Political Agency, \ Bahrain, PERSIAN GULF. BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. WAREHOUSES: 8-9, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST, W.l. 33-34-, GT. PULTENEY ST, W. 1. We are duly In receipt of your letter of the 20 th ult, ref• 433 - 17 / 2 , and thank you for your kind order for various paints etc. You may rest assured that this is receiving our close attention. There are,however, one or two items in it that we shall have to refer hack to you for further details. With regard to the sailing- canvas, thin quality it is necessary for us to know the length of the piece you require, it is usually approximately 50 yds, and also the width and the weight of the material you require.Thin quality is, of course, a comparative tenn, and it would he of very great help if you could give us an indication of the use to v/hich this sailing canvas is to he put. With regard to the 6 rolls of copper wire gauze this again is rather difficult, you ask for wire gauze and then state 16 meshes per square inch. We attach hereto a sample of w'oven copper 16 meshes per square inch and the price 36 ” wide in 19 gauge as sample would he 10 ^-d per square foot, this is the net price and subject only to our commission of 5%. We would expressly draw your attention to the fact that we cannot possibly guarantee that tois quotation will hold good for any length of time as raw material prices areThe Political Agent .- 2 - rising somev/hat rapidly at the moment. We look forward to the pleasure of receiving your instructions in connection with these items and in the meantime we are proceeding with the remainder of your order* Assuring you of our best attention at all times P'*’ TalU-s- Wo- CUSTOMER’S CARS AND CYCLES DRIVEN AND STORED ENTIRELY AT CUSTOMERS’ OWN RISK AS i, &lt; ' REGARDS FIRE OR DAMAGE XLL ORDERS CONTRACTS AGREEMENTS ARE CONTINGENT UPON STRIKES &amp;• OTHER CAUSES BEYOND OUR-CONTROL 4 PHONE No. 7028. TELEGRAMS “AUTOMOBILE” NARAINDAS &amp; Co. AUTOMOBILE 0MGINEE GARDEN :ROAD KARACHI CODES ENTLEY’S GEN|RAL MOTORS PRIVATE March-1937. s The Political Agent, Political Agency, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, We beg to enclose Inmiaa herein B/L No: 29 for 3 c/s Lubricating Oils already shipped to you and shall be glad if you will kindly acknowledge receipt thereof. The bill is attached hereto. Assuring you of our best services at all times, for Yours faithfully, NARAINDAS &amp; CO., , NIN REPLY r F. P. Ba ker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. The Political Agent, Political Agency, Bahrein, PERSIAN 1 GULP^- CABLES: BANSHEE,LONDO BENTLEY’S CODE. WAREHOUSES: 8-9, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST., W.l. 33-3A, GT. PULTENEY ST. W. 1. 9t h March -(93 7 13 Dear Sir, In further reference to your letter of the 2^5th ult. we find that a further difficulty arises in regard to the 'brass eyelets and punch. You order 5/16” and j” eyelets 'but do not state whether these are inside or outside measurements, we shall 'be glad if you would let us have this information so that this portion of your order can be dealt with. Placing our services entirely at your disposal, We are,Dear Sir, Yours fai-f|ifully P. P. BAK&gt;j LTD. I '7*No. 875-17/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th April 1937 To Messrs F.P. Baker and Company Limited, 2, Upper James Street, London. Gentlemen, , / ./ith reference to your letters Nos. C.D.9-1229 dated the 3rd March and 9th ?Tarch 1937, I furnish the follov/in^ required by you:- 3a 11 ingc Canva s 15 to 20 toner Yacht. Wire Gauze. Eyelets and punch. particulars which are Length of piece 50 yards Width 1 yard. Medium size. 16 meshes per inch i.e. 256 neshes per square inch. 5/16 H and 3/4'* are inside measurements. Yours faithfully,TELEPHON E: QERRARD 6351* TELEGRAMS: VIDALABAK, PICCY. LO N D O N. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. r F. P. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. The Political Agent, Bahrain, PERSIAN GULP. J CABLE S: BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. WAREHOUSES: 8-9, BR IDLE LANE, BEAK ST, W.l. 33-34., GT. PULTENEY ST, W. 1. PLEASE QUOTE N&lt;? C.D. 9. 2351 IN REPLY 22nd April 193 7 Dear Sir, • - h ^ 3 We are duly in receipt of your letter of the 14th inst.ref.375-17/2, and thank you for the further infornTSTtion in regard to the canvas,gauze and eyelets and punch, we are now proceeding with the order and will despatch as soon as possible. Assuring you of our best attention at all times, We are,Dear Sir, Yours faBAG \O ne Case per SS.'GCRJISTAN 11 D P Messrs. Compton's Ltd., London, have sent us a Parcel Receipt and their hill amounting to £3-2-6d in res pect of the above case coming forward per 33.'GORJISTAN' which vessel is due here at 4 p.m. tomorrow the 19th inst. We shall be glad if you will kindly let us have your instructions regarding clearing end forwarding of same once it is landed on the Customs Pier. Messrs. Compton's have asked us to reir.it to them the amount of their bill by sterling draft, and no doubt, you will kindly make arrangements to let us have this draft in the name of Messrs. Compton's Ltd. Yours faithfully, Co.. LiP l - ^ .,-r • /e P '*1 4 ICODES used: BENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE CODE GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; Co., Ltd. ( 1 ^ PflrffnP ATCrr&gt; U*- CNQLAND. ) BAHREIN KOWEIT DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT 147 In reply, please, quote No.J^/.QQ^. * Bahre in^ 18th Lay, 1937. V The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, V VF Ax 17 Packages per 33.^GCHJISTAN 11 i ALTDI? TTT The above shipment is coming forwai'd per 'GCRJISTAN' which vessel is due here at 4 p.m. tomorrow the 19th instant, and we hold a joint Bill of Lading for same, together with two packages intended for the Government of Bahrein. r — —- Invoices and advices have been forwarded to us by Messrs .F. P. Baker &amp; Co.,Ltd., London, and we shall be glad to have your instructions if you desire that we should have these packages cleared once they are landed at the Customs Pier. Yours faithfully,NMCIMmI — t » telephon e. GERRAR 15 6351.* TELEG RAMS: VIDALAB^AK, PICCY, LO N D O N . - Cab i_e s: TROPIKITS, LON DON. Bentley’s code. NO REPLY CAN BE DEALT WITH UNLESS THE FOLLOWING N? IS QUOTED jH.iaao r ’ F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. EAST INDIA AGENTS, MERCHANTS AND SHIPPERS. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET. G O L D E N SQ U A R E , R E G E N^STR E , DON CITY OFFICE: 9-10, BOND COURT. WALBROOK, E.C. A-. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTD LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE,) 20, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST., W. I. LO \ The Political Agen' Bahrein, PERSIA!! % A S.S. 'Gorjistan' on 26th April, 1937. 27th April, ]93 7 Sailing from London Dear Sir, We have the pleasure to advise you that we have shipped as mark below the following goods ordered by you per the above steamer. Paints, etc. We understand from the Shipping Company that this steamer is due at Bahrein on or a b 0 ut 25th May, 1937 and the goods are being consigned to the following Agents at that port. Messrs. The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation ltd.. We shall be glad if you would be kind enough to communicate direct with the Agents giving them disposal instructions for the goods, which we trust will reach you in good condition and be to your entire satisfaction. MARKS &amp; NUMBERS. Yours faithfully, F. P. BAKER &amp; CO. LTD. B P.A. Bahrein. ll U LrJf c -' v r*'TELEPHONE: GERRARD 5748 6754. TELEGRAMS: VIDALABAK, PICCY, LONDON. CABLES: BANSHEE, LONDON, BENTLEY'S CODE. F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W.l. CITY OFFICE: 9 10, BOND COURT, WALBROOK, E.C. 4. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK, LTD. LOMBARD STREET, E.C. 3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE) 20, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST. W. 1. 23rd April, 193 7 ToTiie Political Agent, Bahr ein, \\ h HEREBY CERTIF Y that the following interest lias been declared as attaching to our Floating Policy of Insurance at Lloyds, No. 66 1 which has been declared by order and for account of F. P. BAKER &amp; CO., LTD. £ 75-0-0« excluding breakage £ including breakage £ on paint a, etc, (17 packages) per s.s. Gorjiatan From Londo n to destination via Bah rein and we hereby agree to hold the amount recoverable on the said Policy so far as the above interest is concerned at the disposal of yourself 0 r your order. F. P. BA CO., LTD. ALL RISKS (as specified). I his Policy covers such Goods and/or Merchandise including l/m^sohal and/or other effects as may be declared hereon from any port oj?-*T5Tace in the United Kingdom to destination named. ^ With average each package and including the risks of hook breakage and fresh water, oil and other cargo damage, pilferage, theft and war, and personal and/or other effects against all risks of every description including war. Glass, Pictures, Earthenware, China, Marble, Cast Iron and all brittle articles free of claim for breakage unless specially insured for such. NOTICE. —In the event of damage or loss exceeding £2 a survey should be called for from Lloyd’s Agent, but it is necessary that notice to survey should be given immediately after the arrival of the goods at the Destination named he rein in the event of loss arising, otherwise the Underwriters will accept no liability for such loss. PORT It is quite suflicient if clients address their letter LLOYD’S AGENT, and after survey the Agent’s report should be sent to us together with particulars of the claim to enable us to recover from the Underwriters. The fee paid for survey is recoverable in addition to the amount of the claim. Unless the property is insured for its full value, claims for partial or total loss or damage will only be recoverable proportionately. In the event of a claim arising under this Policy F. P. BAKER &amp; CO., LTD., agree to pay such sums as may be recovered from the Underwriters without prejudice as customary, on the understanding that they shall be indemnified by the Insured against all reasonable expenses incurred. *■ . I ! inNo. 504. H. REEVES &amp; CO., 32 St. Mary Axe. E.C.3 (1) Here insert Manager, Chief Clerk, or as the case may be. (2) Here insert name of firm or company. (3) Here insert name of city or country. (4) These words should be omitted where the manu facturer or supplier himself signs the Certificate. (6) Here insert particulars of any special arrange ment. (6) Insert ' United Kingdom ' or name of other part of British Dominions. 27 / 9/33 IMPERIAL ECONOMIC CONFERENCE. , FORM. “B.” Combined Certificate of Value and of Origin and Invoice of Goods for Exportation to British Colonies. 1, 0) of (2) of (3) manufacturer ^ enumerated in this invoice amounting to supplier hereby declare that I [( 4 ) have the authority to make and sign this certificate on behalf of the aforesaid manufactu I er an( j that IT have the means of knowing and do hereby certify as suppher follows:— VALUE. 1. That this invoice is in all respects correct and contains a true and full statement ^ of the price actually paid or to be paid for the said goods, and the actual quantity thereof. 2. That no arrangements or understanding affecting the purchase price of the said goods have been or will be made or entered into between the said exporter and purchaser, or by anyone on behalf of either of them either by way of discount, rebate, compensation or in any manner whatever other than as fully shown on this invoice, or as follows (5) ORIGIN. (In the case of goods exported to Gambia, Gold Coast or Sierra Leone the following portion of the Certificate dealing with Origin should be struck out.) (Delete whichever of 3 (a) or 3 (b) is not applicable. If 3 (a) is used delete 4 and 5. If 3 (b) is used insert required particulars in 4 and 5.) 3. {a) That every article mentioned in 3. (b) That every article mentioned in the said invoice has been wholly produced or the said invoice has been either wholly or manufactured in ( 6 ) partially produced or manufactured in ( 6 ) ( 6 ). ( 6 ). 4. As regards those articles only partially produced or manufactured in (a) That the final process or processes of manufacture have been performed in that part of the British Dominions. (b) That the expenditure in material produced in ( 6 ) and/or labour performed in ( 6 ) calculated subject to qualifications hereunder, in each and every article is not less than —^-- foprth of the factory or works cost of such article in its finished one-half state. (See Note below.) 5. That in the calculation of such proportion of produce or labour of the none of the following items has been included or considered— “ Manufacturer’s profit or remuneration of any trader, agent, broker, or other person “ dealing in the articles in their finished condition: royalties: cost of outside ' packages or any cost of packing the goods thereinto; any cost of conveying “ insuring, or shipping the goods subsequent to their manufacture.” Dated at. this day of. .19. Witness Signature - jjotb.—I n the case of goods which have at seme stage entered into the commerce of, or undergone a process of manufacture in a foreign country, only that labour and material which is expended on or added to the goods after their return to the United Kingdom shall be regarded as the produce or manufacture of the United Kingdom in calculating the proportion of United Kingdom labour and material in the factory or works cost of the finished article.No. 504. H. REEVES &amp; €0.. 32 St. Mary Axe, E.C.3 (1) Here insert Manager, Chief Clerk, or as the case may be. (2) Here insert name of firm or company. (3) Here insert name of city or conn-try. (4) These words should be omitted where the manu facturer or supplier himself signs the Certificate. (5) Here insert particulars of any special arrange ment. (6) Insert “ United Kingdom ” or name of other part of British Dominions. 27 / 9/33 IMPERIAL ECONOMIC CONFERENCE. FORM “B.” Combined Certificate of Value and of Origin and Invoice of Goods for Exportation to British Colonies. $ t Arb.er.t.. .Kdw.ar.&amp; wjs (i).... Ac C.QU&amp; . of ( 2 ) p ¥ -P ¥ Bak-e.p-cS:...Go»-Ltd^., of (3) London aforesaid follows of the goods enumerated in this invoicearaounting to ....... £. 60 # . 9 * . e that I [ (4) have the authority to make and sign this certificate on behalf of the ■'in 'fo /'FiiT*OT* and that I] have the means of knowing and do hereby certify as VALUE. supplier 1. That this invoice is in all respects correct and contains a true and full statement of the price actually paid or to be paid for the said goods, and the actual quantity thereof. 2. That no arrangements or understanding affecting the purchase price of the said goods have bqpn or will be made or entered into between the said exporter and purchaser, or by anyone on behalf of either of them either by way of discount, rebate, compensation or in any manner whatever other than as fully shown on this invoice, or as follows (5) ORIGIN. (In the case of goods exported to Gambia, Gold Coast or Sierra Leone the following portion of the Certificate dealing with Origin should be struck out.) (Delete whichever of 3 (a) or 3 (b) is not applicable. If 3 (a) is used delete 4 and 5. If 3 (b) is used insert required particulars in 4 and 5.) 3. (a) That every article mentioned in 3. (b) That every article mentioned in the said invoice has been wholly produced or the said invoice has been either wholly or manufactured in ( 6 ) partially^tmy5jAced or manufactured in ( 6 ). 4. As regards those articles 'partially/' produced oj^manufactured in )f manufacjalfe have been performed in (a) That the final process or processes^, that part of the British Doniinioj (b) That the expenditure in material produce^fh ( 6 ) / and/or lajxfur performed/m (6) .yT..... calculated subject/fo qualification/ hereunder, in each and every article is not less thaja /^? 6 --? 0 ^ 1 of the factory or works cost of such article in its finished one-half / fate. (See Note below.) in the calculation/of such proportion of produce or labour of the none'' of/ne following items has been included or considered— Manufacturer’s profit/or remuneration of any trader, agent, broker, or other person “ dealing in thy articles in their finished condition: royalties: cost of outside “ packages or any cost of packing the goods thereinto; any cost of conveying “ insuring, or shipping the goods subsequent to their manufacture.” Dated at this 26.tiL day of AprJ.1 19.....£7 # Witness. t Signature. ^ 19....^/. Note. —In the case of goods ^fhich have at some stage entered into the commerce of, or undergone a process of manufacture in a foreign country, only that labour and material which is expended on or added to the goods after their return to the United Kingdom shall be regarded as the produce or manufacture of the United Kingdom in calculating the proportion of United Kingdom labour and material in the factory or works cost of the finished article.Place and Date London April 26 th 19 37 •State here general nature or class of goods. •INVOICE of Turpentine. b y Messrs P.P.Baker &amp; Co.Ltd. to The Political Agent supplied of 2,Upper James Street, London, 7/. 1 • of Bahrein, Persian Gulf. to be shipped pefc. S. ’’Gor j istan' sailed 26-4-37* Order Number State full particulars of Royalties below :—7 / 11/35 H. REEVES &amp; Co.. 32 St. Mary Axe, E.C.3. (1) Here insert Manager, Chief Clerk, or as the case may be. (2) Here insert name of firm or company. (3) Here insert name of city or country. (4) These words should be omitted where the manu facturer or supplier himself signs the Certificate. (5) Here insert particulars of any special arrangement (0) Here insert “ warehouse,” “ factory ” or ” port of ship ment.” NON-PREFERENTIAL AND FOREIGN Certificate of Value and Invoice of Goods for Exportation to British Dominions. 1L (1) Account ant.. °f (2) i?.*.P*.Bak&amp;.F....ch.. .Q.q. 0 . Ltd...,, of (3) London supplier enum erated in this invoice amounting to .‘^. 5 ......f?:* hereby declare that I [(4) have the authority to make and sign this certificate on behalf • iriciDtifyi ctursr &gt; ^ of the aforesaid SU p p ii er and that I] have the means of knowing and do hereby certify as follows :— v -' VALUE. 1. That this invoice is in all respects correct and contains a true and full statement of the price actually paid or to be paid for the said goods, and the actual quantity thereof. 2 . That no different invoice of the goods mentioned in the said invoice has been or will be furnished to anyone; and that no arrangements or understanding affecting the purchase price of the said goods has been or will be made or entered into between the said exporter and purchaser, or by anyone on behalf of either of them either by way of discount, rebate, compensation, or in any manner whatever other than as fully shown on this invoice, or as follows (5) 3. That the domestic values shown in the column headed ' Current Domestic Values ' are those at which the above-mentioned firm or company would be prepared to supply to any purchaser for home consumption in the country of exportatian and at the date of exportation identically similar goods in equal quantities, at ( 6 ) subject toSr/&lt;« pw-eent? cash discount, and that such values ~ U 4- e the cost of outside ✓o packages, if any, in which the goods are sold in such country for domestic consumption. 4. That the said domestic value includes any duty leviable in respect of the goods before they are delivered for home consumption, and that on exportation a drawback or remission of duty amounting to ^ allowed by the revenue authorities in the country of exportation. Dated at Witness... L.Qnuan. this .Signature 2£.th..dav of Apr.Ll 19 37Mo. 1225-17/3 Political / rency, Bahrain, f ay 21, 1927. To eLtrfc Gray, ''ackenzie and Comp an// limited, BAHRAIN. Gentlemen, |? N 7 ith reference to your letters Nos. T/G42 and T /646 dated the l^th May 1957, would you please send me k the delivery )rders to take delivery of the consignments from the Customs. j he cost of Delivery Orders will be remitted to on receipt of your bill. 2 . On receipt of the consignment the sterling draft for £.5*2*6 will be forwarded to you. /ours faithllilly, r? ' for Political Agent, Bahrain,Re/rlster-e Air Mb 11, No. 1262*17/2. Political Agency* Bahrain, the 27th Tr ay 1937. Fessrs Facia and Company, Grant Road Karachi. Gentlemen, With reference to my letter ?Jo. 654-17/J dated the 19th arch 1937 (copy enclosed for re^dy reference), I request that the cotton v»aste may please be supplied at ycur earliest convenience. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.No. 1334-17/2. Political Arrency, Bahrain, the 7th June 1937. Messrs F.P. Baker and Company Limited, 2 Upper James Street, Golden Square, Regent Street, London• * Dear Sirs, A I * 1 With reference to your invoice dated the 26th April 1937 I enclose a bank draft for £.65-16-2 in your favour and request the favour of an acknowledgement. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.*TE LE PH o N E: GERRARD 6351* TELEGRAMS: VIDALABAK, PICCV, LONDON. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. r PLEASE QUOTE N&lt;? F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Lt 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. D. CABLE S: BANSHEE, LONDON. B ENTLEY’S' CODE. WAREHOUSES: 8-9, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST, W.1, 33-3A, GT. PULTENEY ST, W. 1. The Political Agent, \ Bahrain, \ I Iranian Gulf. C.D. 9. 2351 IN REPLY 193 7 Dear Sir, further reference to our letter of the 22nd ult. we regret that the further information you have given us regarding the sail cloth and the wire gauze is not really sufficient for us to execute the order and he certain that we shall he supplying your exact requirements. v The sail cloths that we have had offered to us unfortunately vary in price very considerably. The 'D' fine sail quality as per the attached sample is quoted to us at 1/11 d per yard and is available in pieces of about 100 yards each. Alternatively if you require the heavier quality we can offer you the Gourock Tent Duck and the Gourock Cotton cloth, these are available in 50 yd.lengths 36 ” wide at 2/- yd. for the Tent Duck and 2/2d per yard for the Cotton Cloth. Delivery is from stock. With regard to the wire gauze v/e attach sample of 256 meshes to the square inch the price of this being 39/6d per 100 sq.ft.36” wide and it is available in rolls of 50 ft. The sample we are sending of this gauze is painted but of course we are quoting for copper. We should be glad if you would let us know if this quality is fine enough and strong enough for your purpose./-N 'he Political A.xent... . contd. ’ uia All prices quoted are net and subject to the addition of our 5% buying commission. V/e look forward to hearing further from you, and assuring you of our best attention at all times,No.1369-17/2 Political Agency f To Bahrain, the 14th June 1937* Messrs F.P. Baker and ^ompany, Limited, Regent S^fapet, London. Dear Sirs, With reference to your letter No.C.D.9.2351 dated the 5th May 1937, I regret to i form you that the wire gauze and sail cloths are not required now and the order may please be regarded as cancelled. Yours faithfully, f or political Agent, Bahrain.No. 504. IMPERIAL ECONOMIC CONFERENCE H. REEVES &amp; CO.. 32 St. Mary Axe, E.C.3 (1) Here insert Manager, Chief Clerk, or as the case may bo. (2) Here insert name of firm or company. (3) Here insert name of city or country. (4) These words should be omitted where the manu facturer or supplier himself signs the Certificate. (6) Here insert particulars of any special arrange ment. (6) Insert “ United Kingdom ” or name of other part of British Dominions. 27/9/33 FORM 'B:’ Combined Certificate of Value and of Origin and Invoice of Goods for Exportation to British Colonies. l t ALBERT EM/^...M.TTIIMS ( i) Of (2) E..P*BAKER...&amp;...C.O..LTD* of (3) jaanufacturar supplier of the goods enumerated in this invoice amounting to Ac.oomtan.t London £ 2 . n. a. hereby declare that I [(4) have the authority to make and sign this certificate on behalf of the aforesaid supplier and that I] have the means of knowing and do hereby certify as follows :— VALUE. 1. That this invoice is in all respects correct and contains a true and full statement of the price actually paid or to be paid for the said goods, and the actual quantity thereof. 2. That no arrangements or understanding affecting the purchase price of the said goods have been or will be made or entered into between the said exporter and purchaser, or by anyone on behalf of either of them either by way of discount, rebate, compensation or in any manner whatever other than as fully shown on this invoice, or as follows (5) ORIGIN. (In the case of goods exported to Gambia, Gold Coast or Sierra Leone the following portion of the Certificate dealing with Origin should be struck out.) (Delete whichever of 3 (a) or 3 (b) is not applicable. If 3 (a) is used delete 4 and 5. If 3 (b) is used insert required particulars in 4 and 5.) 3. (a) That every article mentioned in 3. (b) That every article mentioned in the said invoice has been wholly produced or the said invoice has been either wholly or manufactured in (6) .v. *!£... partially product or manufactured in (6) . 4. As regards those articles only partia^y^ produced or ipoffufactured m ( 6 ) (а) That the final process or proces^s of manufacturjjxfTave been performed in that part of thtj British Domimons. (б) That the eLpAd/tp^^n m^erial produced m/(6). and/or L^nr per fanned in (6) .yr... calculated subjectr^o ^(fua^ifications hereundpr’f in each and every article is not less than -^f the factory/6r works cost of such article in its finished stat$. £»6e Note below.) / 6. That ip^he calculationsuch proportion of produce or labour of the (6) none .of^tfie following items has been included or considered- “ Manufacturer’s profU/or remuneration of any trader, agent, broker, or other person “ dealing in the articles in their finished condition: royalties: cost of outside “ packages or any cost of packing the goods thereinto; any cost of conveying “ insuring, or shipping the goods subsequent to their manufacture.” Dated at...^.9?^.9?^ this 27.!fcitk* day of May. 19.....3.7* Witness Signature... Note.—I n the case of goods which have at some stage entered into the commerce of, or undergone a process of manufacture in a foreign country, only that labour and material which is expended on or added to the goods after their return to the United Kingdom shall be regarded as the produce or manufacture of the United Kingdom in calculating the proportion of United Kingdom labour and material in the factory or works cost of the finished article.Telephone ( Office 248 Nos. ' Residence 5138. BANKERS:- Lloyds Bank Ltd. - - . Karachi Mercantile Bank of India Ltd. Sind Provincial Co-op.- Bank Ltd. „ Yokohama Specie Bank Ltd. / V ESTABLISHED 1918. Mama &amp; Company government contractors, MANUFACTURERS' REPRESENTATIVES, IMPORTERS e? EXPORTERS. Cable Add -'CONCRETE' Codes Used &gt; A. B. C. 5th C? 6th Editions, Bentley's Code, Schofield's &amp; Oriental 3-Letters Code &amp;. Private. GRANT ROAD, IMPORT DEPT. J«at 1937, The Political Agency. Bahrain . Bear Sirs, We are in receipt of your letter of the 27th ultimo, for 1 cwt Cotton Waste, which we have shipped the same per s.s.Bandra saild from here on 13th instant, and enclose herewith original copy of the Bill of lading and our bill in duplicate amounting to Rs.47/4/- and trust the same will be found in order. Funner we beg to inform you that we deal in Iron.Cemen Coloured Cement and all kind 0 f building materials etc. and if you are interested in any of these, please let us know, and we shall be. glad to give our prompt attention in executing the same. Assuring you of our best services at all times. SGP. Eels.2. ^ &gt; • —A' rw s l\mmAgent* for : Manglore Roofing Tiles. SPECIALITIES:- CORRUGATED BARS. ROUND &amp; SQUARE IN ALL LENGTHS. MILD STEEL. BARS, RODS &amp; CHANNELS. TIMBER. TEAKWOOD OF RANGOON &amp; P^XADOE, PANE WOOD OF MAu.. \BAR LOGS 6^ SCANTLINGS OF ALL SIZES. PAINTS &amp; OILS. OIL LUBRICATING FOR MARINE ENGINES, CASTOR &amp; LINSEED OILS, WHITE CEMENT GRIFFIN BRAND MANILLA ROPE. FIRE BRICKS &amp; CLAY. COALTAR, TALLOW. PRICES ON APPLICATION. Telegrams-. “CONCRETE” Karachi. Telephone No. 2248. BILL No. 330 • GRANT ROAD. Karachi, 14th J une 193?. The Political Agency, Bahrein* TO, MAMA &amp; CO., METAL, TIMBER, “WHITE CEMENT” &amp; “iNDIAN” PORTLAND CEMENT (anchor, GANPATI &amp; B B B &amp; coloured) MANGLORE ROOFING TILES &amp; GENUINE LINSEED OILS MERCHANTS &amp; CONTRACTORS. Interest @ 9% will be charged if not paid within 7 days.F. P. Baker &amp; Co Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, CA B LE S: BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Iranian Gulf. WAREHOUSES: 8-9, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST, W.1. 33-34., GT. PULTENEY ST, W. 1. please quote npG. D. 9. IN REPLY 23rd June Dear Sir, We have the pleasure to enclose herewith statement of account from which ^-11 see there is an amount of £80.7.1 due + -P-i . We trust y° u will Be able to agree this figure and remit in due course. Placing our services entirely at your disposal, ^ We are,Dear Sir, Yours faithfully, f.p.baM/ AITD*1G0. LTD. m *telephone GERRARD 6351 ★ TELEGRAMS: VIDALABAK, PICCV, LO NOON. CABLES BANSHEE. LON DON. b.m. STATEMENT F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LON DON , W. I . BENTLEVS CODE A. B.C. ETC. CODE. ETC To BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. WAREHOUSE (ENTRANCE,) 20, BRI DLE LAN E , BEAK ST., W. I. Reference No. 95/2. 23rd June 193 7 The Political. Agent., ^ Bahrain Psrsian...Gulf # Please note that our terms are for Cash on receipt of Invoice. Interest at 6% is chargeable on all overdue accounts together with collection charges and all discounts or concessions cancelled. 1937 TO Bankers : Westm *nster Bank, Ltd., Lombard Street, E.C. 3 . February 18 Shipping Ghgs a/c B 635. ' 5 April 26 Goods a/c &amp; Chgs a/c D 1477 50 May 27 Goods a/c S 1^4 2 June 2 Goods a/c &amp; Chgs a/c E 1726 Balance due 12 11 21 15 £ 80 7 1 F.P.B. 32 Please Return this Account with Remittance.for Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agency, Bahrain, July 15, 1937. BY AIR MAIL . No/ -17/2 To Mes&amp;rb P.P. Baker and Company Limited, 2, Upper James Street, Golden Square, Regent Street, LONDON. W. 1 . Gentlemen, r With reference to your letter No. 6.D.9.9f/2 dated the 23rd June 1937, I enclose a demand draft for £.2-11-8 being the coat of punch and eyelets supplied to this Agency. 2* ihe sum of £. 21-15—7 will be remitted to you on receipt of the steel cupboard at Sharjah. First two items for £. $-12-11 end 50-6-11 are not understood as no goods were suoplied to this Agency during the months of February and April 1937. Will you please furnish full details of these two items. Yours faithfully,TELEPHONE: GERRARD 6351* TE LEG R A MS: VIDALABAK, PIGGY, LONDON. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. r c.d. 9 . PLEASE QUOTE NO F. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. Tlie Politick. Agent, Bahrain, Iranian Gulf. IN REPLY Pear Sir, CABLE S: BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. WAREHOUSES: 8-9, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST, W. 1. 33_ 3A, GT. PULTENEY ST., W. 1. J 24th June A js 7 193 We are duly in receipt of your letter of the 14th inst.ref.1369-17/2, and in accordance therewith are taking no further action in regard to the wire gauze and sail cloths. Assuring you of our best attention to your commands, We are,Dear Sir, Yours faithfully. &lt;y^ -1for Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agency, Bahrein, July 24, 1957. \ '\ To Meeart, I. Thorny croft and Company Limited, Marine Motor Yiorka, Woleey Road, CAVERSHAM, READING, ENGLAND . Gentlemen, shall be glad if you will please arrange to send by registered air mail the following spare parts required for this Agency motor launch 1. One armature complete, mounted with slipring, pinion and ball bearings, 2. One friction couping No. 05499 for B.ff.H. iagneto Ho. 9.H. 253302 Type O.A. C. T.3. The parcel should be addressed to H.B.M’s ^oliti^al i /igent, Bahrain (Persian Gulf). The cost of the spare parts / will be remitted to you on receipt of your bill. Yours faithfully, /The following spares are required for deep sea cruising 1. 2 . 2. One armature complete,mounted with slipring,pinion,and ball bearings. &amp; One friction coupling,No.05499 for x Magneto No.0.H.253802 Type G.A.6. T.3. It is requested that the above may please be asked for from Thornycraft,London, by air mail.r - P EPAKTMENT ■ r - ',OVN iwai 2 6JUU937 Hie H # B* M # s Political Agents .Bahrai n (Persian Gulf) f Dear Sir r Enclosed please find our Official stamped receipt No.1864 of date for Bs* 47-4-0 in full payment of our Bill No* 330* Thanking you, and awaiting the favour of your further *Jr Established 1918. OHt^anu CEMENT &amp; METAL MERCHANTS \1 SPECIALITIES Reinforced Mild Steel Round Bars In All Sizes. White Portland Cement 'ANCHOR', 'GANPATI' and Coloured Cement. GRANT ROAD, KARACHI, July 193 7. iours faithfully, )h Ends- 1 Stamped Keceipt3ERRARD 6351* TELEGRAMS: VIDALABAK, PICCY, LONDON. F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. BANSHEE, LONDON. 0 E NTLE Y’S CODE. WAREHOUSES: 8-9, BRIDLE LANE, With regard to the item of £50.6.11 we are very sorry indeed that this should have heen posted to the wrong accoun t , it should not he for you at all. We enclose a copy of the charge for £5.12.11 , this refers to an order placed hy The hrolitial Resident in the Persian G-ulf, his letter dated the 24th December 1936, No.^31-S of 1936, in v/hich we ordered us to ship 7 Mannlxher Schonauer Detachable Rifles to you, and charge to your account. We note your further remarks in regard to the sum of £21.1h. I and we would again express our regrets that we should have troubled you in regard to the item which was not for your account. Co We are,Dear Sir, Yours faithfully, F.P.BAKRR AND CO.LTD.A.W. TELEPHONE: GERRAPD 6351* TELEGRAMS: VIDALABAK, PICCY. LONDON. In Acct. with F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. CABLES: banshee. London. BENTLEY’S CODE. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W.l. Reference No. ^ ^35 • The Political Agent, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 18th February / qj 7 • A* we work on a very small margin we ask clients to help us by complying with our terms of business, namely, remittance on receipt of invoice. 5561 * Bankers: Westminster Bank, Ltd., Lombard Street, E.C.3. Shipping charges on 3 packages shipped per s7s. **Wildenfels ” sailed 10-2-57 . ) Freight &amp; Primage. Cartage to Docks. Dock Dues. Customs Clearance. Port Rates. Bills of Lading &amp; Postage^ Cases &amp; Packing for Cartridges &amp; Gun Cases. £200 Insurance &lt;3 17/2. 2 18 11 19 - 1 1 5 - &amp; O.E. With Compliments. £5. 12. 11. Please Return this Account with Remittance.HEAD OFFICE A SALES DEPT. THORNYCROFT HOUSE, SMITH SQUARE, WESTMINSTER, LONDON, S.W.I. John I. T i m TELEGRAMS : THORNYCROFT, READING. THORNYCROFT, LONDON. TELEPHONES: READING 71518. VICTORIA 8000. &amp; 0° ]_^ M1TED MARINE MOTOR WORKS, Caversham, Reading. ENGi-OSURES Refer to bwf/uh 30th July 1937 f s Political Agent, BAHREIN, Persian Gulf. Dear Sirs, We are duly in receipt of your letter of the 24th inst., calling for one armature complete and one friction coupling No.09499 for B.T.H./GA.6. magneto No.253802. You do not state the type and number of the engine for which these parts are required but from your particulars of the magneto we assume that it is of our RD/6 type having a spigot mounted magneto and we have put the parts in hand accordingly. We find that we shall have to obtain the armature complete from outside Suppliers but expect to obtain delivery of this within a day or two when we will at once despatch by airmail, together with the friction coupling. Yours faithfully, JOHN I. THORNYGROFT Co. LIMITEU. READING MARINE MOTOR WORKS. MANAGERThohnycrofT • ; : w.y; ■ • ■ John I. '7 C &amp;C0. - LIMITED ATTENTION!! This consignment was CHECKED TWICE. Should the contents of this package appear to have been tampered with, and not agree with this packing note, please return this packing note immediately with complaint. SHORTAGES ARISE FROM. Goods being “Left in cases” or “Thrown out” with the packing. Goods being “Sold before they ar e checked and examined’ , with invoice. Two or moi e invo ice s being unpacked at the same time” causing confusion. Cases being “Opened or broken in transit^ and “Goods stolen or lost” forIMPOiv TANT. Please note that by reason of the Railway Companies General Conditions:- That in case of:- (1) LOSS FROM DAMAGE OR DELAY to a consignment of goods. Claims must be made in writing to the Railway Company within three days of receipt of the goods. Goods which are damaged or in bad condition should be signed for as “damaged” or “not examined”. (2) NON-DELIVERY OF A CONSIGNMENT OF GOODS. Claims must be made in writing 14 days after the goods have been despatched. W e hei eby give notice that we can accept no responsibility or in any way be liable for loss occasioned by failure to comply with the above requirements and that it is essential 3 ou should notify us as well as the Railway Company of any claim in time to enable us to comply with the requirements of the Railway Company. PARCELS SENT BY POST. The Post Office is liable for all damage or loss in transit, but the Post Office should be notified of any damage or loss on day of delivery. Should damage or loss occur, notify the Post Office at once and keep Parcel exactly as received for inspection, also advise us, so that we can make a claim. On no account must the Goods or Parcels be returned to us until they have been inspected by the Railway Company or Postal Officials. The above is given for your information. If not acted upon we (the senders) cannot accept any responsibility and the damage or loss will be your risk. ”Tf.I/Rphowf. : 71518 READING 5&gt;r. to invoice. /'Y? Tbi.korams : THORNYCROhT, READING. All Accounts strictly Net, and payable at— HEAD OFFICE, THORNVCROFT HOUSE, SMITH SQUARE, LONDON, S.W. 1. &amp;.C0. LI M ITE D CAVERSHAM, READING. H. B. M's Political Agency, Bahrain,.... Persian Gulf. Date .. 2iu£« 37* Our Heferences :— RR R, P.29210 R.s 22545 Your Reference:— No. 1635-17/2. The Motor Goods herein mentioned are only sold on the condition that they are not to be exhibited either directly or indirectly at any exhibition in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland without the written authority of the seller.X' To Mebsrb John I. Thornycroft and Company limited, CAVERSHAM, READING, ENGLAND. AV Gentlemen, With reference to your hill No. R.P. 20210 dated the 24th August 1937, I forward a draft for £. 5/14/4 and request the favour of an acknowledgment. Yours faithfully, L V‘r Captain, Political Agent, BahrainBY AIR MAIL Political Agency, Bahrain, February 1, 1938. To Messrs F.P. Baker and Company Limited, 3, Upper James Street, Golden Square, Regent Street, LONDON« ’M . Dear Sirs, Please supply this Agency with the following paints. Your bill will be paid on the receipt of the consignment Snow White (Nicolac) Enamel paint .... 10 gallons, Anti-Sea fouling paint 20 gallons. 2. The above stores should be insured and despatched by one of Messrs Frank C. Strick and Comoany’s ships. Yours faithfully, I • C .8. Political Agent, Bahrain. ABY AIR MAIL. /■ No. ns -17/2 ■ / Political Agency, Bahrain, February 1, 1938. To Messrs Mama and Company, Grant Road, KARACHI . Dear Sirs, Please supply this Agency with One Cwt ^/aste cotton, white quality. Your bill will be paid on receipt of the consignment. Yours faithfully, I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain.TE LE GERRARD 6 3 51* TELEGRAMS: VIDALABAK, PICCY, LONDON. BANKERS: WESTMINSTER BANK LTP LOMBARD STREET, E.C.3. r F. P. Ba ker &amp; Co. Ltd. CABLE S: BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. WAREHOUSES: 8-9, BRIDLE LANE, 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. BEAK ST., W.l. 33-3A, GT. PULTENEY ST, W. 1. The Political Agent, Bahrein, Iranian Gulf. J PLEASE QUOTE N&lt;? C.D.9. 925 IN REPLY 10th February 1 93 8 Dear Sir, We are duly in receipt of your letter of the 1 st inst. Ho* 177 - 17 / 2 , and thank you for the esteemed order for paint which we have placed in hand and will despatch at the first opportunity. Assuring you of our best attention at all times,ASSOCIATED CEMENT COMPANIES LTD. » « ^ .-r A™ 11 ' jamlwilMli » V Selling Agents:- / 7 lanta REINFORCED CONCRETE SPECIALISTS CEMENT &amp; METAL MERCHANTS grant road KARACHI Telephone GOVERNMENT HOUSE, DARJEELING, REBUILT IN CONCRETE AFTER THE BIHAR EARTHQUAKE OF 1934 Telegrams: CONCRETE 2249 M\ V n. Political agent, &lt; ' '''' ■ fS l5th 1338. BAHRAIN * ■ u \ -j) Bear Sir, . In execution of your order No. 178-17/2 of 1st instant, we have shipped 1 Bale of Cotton /aste per s.s.Varela,and beg to send you herewith a Bill 0 f Lading No.7 and our bill No.M/l089 in duplicate for Rs.49/- and trust you will find the same in order imes • Assuring you of our very best services at all t Enel:- 3. Yours faithfully* h -t-rC L-v'TU'3'A*- ,' Agent* for Telegrams: “CONCRETE” Karachi. Telephone No. 2248. BILL No. H/ 1 089. Manglore Roofing Tiles. SPECIALITIES:- CORRUGATED BARS. ROUND &amp; SQUARE IN ALL _ LENGTHS. ' MILD STEEL. BARS, RODS &amp; CHANNELS. TIMBER. TEAKWOOD OF RANGOON &amp; PYNKADOE, PANE WOOD OF MALABAR LOGS &amp; SCANTLINGS OF ALL SIZES. PAINTS &amp; OILS. OIL LUBRICATING FOR MARINE ENGINES, CASTOR &amp; LINSEED OILS, WHITE CEMENT GRIFFIN BRAND MANILLA ROPE. FIRE BRICKS &amp; CLAY. COALTAR, TALLOW. The- Corrugated Bar. GRANT ROAD, KARACHI, 15th February ^ 938' Bahrain* PRICES ON APPLICATION. Description. Cotton Waste White* freight,Measurement &amp; Sh Cartage &amp; forwarding chai w s' TO. MAMA &amp; CO., METAL, TIMBER, “WHITE CEMENT” &amp; “iNDIAN” PORTLAND CEMENT (anchor, GANPATI &amp; B B B &amp; coloured) MANGLORE ROOFING TILES &amp; GENUINE LINSEED OILS MERCHANTS &amp; CONTRACTORS. Interest @ 9% will be charged if not paid within 7 days. Bund les. 1 jPing ges. E. &amp; O. E. Charg Rl ESE3 Nos. Quantity. T. i C. Qr. Lbs. T. eft. I. Pa. Guj. V. V. * 1 0 0 2 S FORTY - - GWt» Rs. A. P. 38 0 0 9 6 0 1 10 0 49 0 0HEAD OFFICE: 122. LEADEN HALL STREET, L0ND0N.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE CODE. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: BUSREH. . BUNDER-ABBAS. AMARAH. LINGAH. KUT. BAHREIN. KHORAMS HAHR KOWEIT. AHWAZ (for DUBAI. BANDAR-SHAH POUR) SHARJAH. BUSH I RE. MUSCAT. 1 IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE Ho. L/466. The Political 4gent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Bahrein, 5th April, 1938 * We have to inform you that Messrs. F. P. Baker and Co.,Ltd., London, have sent us documents covering a ship ment of four drums Anti-Sea Fouling Paint and one case White Enamel Paint per SS.'Kohitan', consigned to you. This ship ment has arrived here, and is now awaiting clearance. We shall be pleased to know if we may do the need ful and have the packages cleared through the Customs, on your behalf. Yours faithfully,\n yi /- 17/2 Political Agency, Bahrain,the 7th April 1938 To Messrs Gray 'ackenzie * Co I.td., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, In reply to your letter ? r o. L/46 dated the 5th April 1938 , I should be grateful if you would clear the shipment and send to the Agency. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.r hBny thanks for your letter of the 5th April and the enclosures from Thornycroft, which I return herewith. 2. ihornycroft prices are a long way beyond my capaci ty i and I wonder if it would be possible to obtain quota tions for similar sets from other more reasonable firms such ns Potter. I should be most grateful if you could help me further in this matter and would be good enough to write to one or two likely firms in England for quota- Z7&lt;£ Be Steele, Esquire State Engineer,•State here general nature or class of goods. ♦INVOICE of °aint. by P. J . BAK&gt;iR A 00. LTD. t 0 The Political Agent, to be shipped per s. a. ’’Kohistan* Sailea. consigned of 2,Upper James Street, Golden Sq.Lon ran. W.l* of Bahrain, P rsian Gulf. 2 ^. 2 . 36. Order Number a. 1360. 6011.3359. Country of Origin u.x. Marks and numbers on packages. Quantity and description of Goods. Selling price to purchaser BAHRAIN Drums 1.2.3.4. each. .leas. 17 w x 11* Gr.V/t. 3 qrs. 11 lbs. each containing 5 Gails Anti Sea Pouling Paint = 20 galls. Case No.5. lie as. 3*^:1 ’b^xl * 1 ” Or. Vt. 1 cwt. 2 Q.rs.26 lbs. Containing:- 10 Galls snow whit? nicolac enamel paint. 5£~ Com: Case freight and Primage Dock Dues Port Rates Bills of Lading an - Post gel* Cartage to D cks. £35 Insurance @ 2o/- Customs ^htry and Clearancbl. Amount. 11 11 2J 3 3 7 1 11 18 6 2 6No. 504. IMPERIAL ECONOMIC CONFERENCE H. REEVES &amp; CO., 32 St. Mary Axe, * E.C.3 (1) Here insert Manager, Chief Clerk, or as the case may be. (2) Here insert name of firm or company. (3) Here insert name of city or country. (4) These words should be omitted where the manu facturer or supplier himself signs the Certificate. (5) Here insert particulars of any special arrange ment. (6) Insert 'United Kingdom” or name of other pait of British Dominions. 6/3/34 FORM “B.” Combined Certificate of Value and of Origin and Invoice of Goods for Exportation to British Colonies. 1, (i) Asfi.Qun.tfiat. of &lt;2) of &lt;3) tomm. of the goods enumerated in this invoice amounting to. .£27r..3,...£,. mTnrfaretnrer supplier hereby declare that I [(4) have the authority to make and sign this certificate on behalf of the in F-C t—- aforesaid —— —— and that I] have the’means of knowing and do hereby certify as supplier 0 j s follows :— VALUE. 1. That this invoice is in all respects correct and contains a true and full statement of the price actually paid or to be paid for the said goods, and the actual quantity thereof. 2. That no arrangements or understanding affecting the purchase price cC* the said goods have been or will be made or entered into between the said exporter and purchaser, or by anyone on behalf of either of them either by way of discount, rebate, compensation or in any manner whatever other than as fully shown on this invoice, or as follows (5) ORIGIN. (In the case of goods exported to Colonies not granting preference to British goods the following portion of the Certificate dealing with Origin should be struck out.) (Delete whichever of 3 (a) or 3 (b) is not applicable. If 3 (a) is used delete 4 and 5. If 3 (b) is used insert required particulars in 4 and 5.) 3. (a) That every article mentioned in 3- (6) That every article mentioned in the said invoice ha? been wholly produced or the said invoice has been either wholly or manufactured in (6) partially ^produced or manufactured in ( 6 )..~, ' ( 6 ). As regards those articles only,'partially produced or rrmntffacturcd in 'have been performed in (a) That the final process that part of the Brhi (b) That the expendi Ire in material produced i processes of manufacti Dominions. and /or la one-half ftate. (See Not 5. That in the calc none performed in (6) calculate^ subject qualifications hereun 'one-tourfh of the facto: Tow in each and every article is not less or works cost of such article in its finished itiopr of such proportion of produce or labour of the the following items has been included or considered— “ Manufacturer’s profit or remuneration of any trader, agent, broker, or other person ' dealing in the articles in their finished condition: royalties: cost of outside ' packages or any cost of packing the goods thereinto; any cost of conveying “ insuring, or shipping the goods subsequent to their manufacture.” Dated at...L.QND:.l5L« -.this „£i.t'.h....day of lA&amp;r.Cll. 19 38 Witness ijL Signature. Notf.— In the case of goods which have at some stage entered into the commerce of, or undergone a process of manufacture in a foreign country, only that labour and material which is expended on or added to the goods after their return to the United Kingdom shall be regarded as the produce or manufacture of the United Kingdom in calculating the proportion of United Kingdom labour and material in the factory or works cost of the finished article.T E L E P M &lt;Xp GERRARD 6 TELEGRAMS: VIDALABAK, PICCV, LONDON. B A-N K E R S : WESTMINSTER BANK LTP PLEASE QUOTE N&lt;? C# D« 9* 95/2 l^'D F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. CABLE S: BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. WAREHOUSES: 8 — 9, BR IDLE LANE, BEAK ST., W.l. 33-3A, GT. PULTENEY ST., W.l. IN REPLY liSfySS- 10th May 193 8 Dear Sir, V/e have the pleasure to enclose herewith copy of our account amounting to £ 27 . 3. 5&lt;2 in case by chance the original should have gone astray. You will see this is on account of paint supplied in March last and we trust you will find it to be in order and let us have a remittance in due c ourse. Assuring you of our best attention at all times. REMEMBER - - - If you send measurements, you can have sent on to you; Men’s wear, underwear, tailoring, footwear, gloves, waterproofs, almost any i clothing. F. P. BAKER &amp; CO., LTD. 2 Upper James Street, Golden Sq., Regent Street, W. I We are,Dear Sir, Yours ^faithfully, P.P.BAKER AND GO.LTD.Mr. I MIS EiET KSI A I ET/^r\ M ri Rfl I M ITir D RT MJIC y'ii &lt;k '■&gt; ' •'' r*.-’ .*’•?• ' . 7 , HI c- &lt;&gt;3 MAI. . . J H A U '.. &gt; 3 03 O O T 3 3 irre TW 3 . 03 F, 6/3/34 Dated at.-.I^ONDf^SLi -.tins „ii.tiii....day of k&amp;&amp;r.ClL 38. Wttness &gt;.&gt;rvcv^' Signature 1 )■ Notf.— In the case of goods which have at some stage entered into the commerce of, or undergone a process of manufacture in a foreign country, only that labour and material which is expended on or added to the goods after their return to the United Kingdom shall be regarded as the produce or manufacture of the United Kingdom in calculating the proportion of United Kingdom labour and material in the factory or works cost of tire finished article.6/3/34 Dated at...L.QND.',)iiL of [A&amp;r.Cll. 19 38» Witness U. Signature^ Notf. —In the case of goods which have at some stage entered into the commerce ol, or undergone a process of manufacture in a foreign country, only that labour and material which is expended on or added to the goods after their- return to the United Kingdom shall be regarded as the produce or manufacture of the United Kingdom in calculating the proportion of United Kingdom labour and material in the factory or works cost of tire finished article.H2- 713/17/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 17th ?.fay, 1938. To i'eaaera F.P. Baker and Company Limited, 2, Upper James Street, Golder Squfire, Regent Street, London W.l Dear Sirs, dated the 10th May 1938, I enclose a bank draft for £. 27-3-5 in full settlement, and requeat the favour of an acknowledgement. Yours faithfully, tkl or Political Agent, BahraiiIN REPLY Hi ® F. P. Baker &amp; Co. Ltd. 2, UPPER JAMES STREET, GOLDEN SQUARE, REGENT STREET, LONDON, W. I. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Iranian Gulf. C AlSt E S: BANSHEE, LONDON. BENTLEY’S CODE. WAREHOUSES: 8-9, BRIDLE LANE, BEAK ST, W.1. 33-3 4., GT. PULTENEY ST, W. 1. 23rd May 8 193 Dear Sir, We arp^auly in receipt of your letter of the lyth'inst, and have the pleasure to enclose herewith receipt for your reraittence value £ 27 . 3 * 53 for which we thank you. Assuring you of our 'best attention at all times, We are,Dear Sir, Yours faithfully, F. P* BAKER AND GO.LTD. SILVERWARE and TABLE CUTLERY j For yourself or as a present. You can ( not get belter value or designs elsewhere, anywhere. AND above all consider the saving of expense to you— REMEMBER ‘BAKER’S’ FOR SILVERWARE j F. P BAKER &amp; CO., LTD. &lt; 2 Upper James Street, Golden Sq., Regent Street, W. I 4 ^I I No. 8277 2, UPPER JAMES STREET GOLDEN SQUARE, W.l. Sir 19ZZ Hcrribi'D from x. the syip 'of 1U. . Shillings for F. P. BAKER &amp; Co. Ltd. . £ : a :\ No. Ii(&gt;y -17/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 17th September 1938. k To Messrs. Mama and Company, Grant Road, Karachi. Dear Sirs, Please supply this Agency with 100 Goa brooms, /our bill will oe paid on receipt of the consignment. Yours faithfully, H- J for Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain,*1 (2^5, j' S«No«27 Letter No.75/9l/W dated the 5th June 1934 from B#R.Herman and Mohatta Ltd, Karachi. Accept by next air mail. G.L. 7/6/34. P.A. Draft submitted for approval please. S.No.28 k ^r/t&gt; Letter Ho.961 dated the 11th June 1934 issued to Herman k nd Mohatta. S• Ho.29 Letter Ho. 75/94 dated the 23rd June 1934 from Messrs Herman .and Mohatta Ltd, Karachi. P.A. S.Uo.30 '^avid states that it will be advisable to have bolts an^ nuts, so that in case if any plank breaks in future a new plank can be replaced. If secured by rivets it will be difficult to replace a broken ^lank. May we wire to Herman as follows:- Expansion Karachi• Bolts* Political. * Az A ^ r 2p Khrachi 3,131 dated the 2nd ,Tuly 1954 issued to Herman « Mohatt,According to your order through H.C., I cuornit for your information the pooition of our Launch and other etores, with proposals, where necessary, for their annual replenishment. 1. DliCK CI^^lhG BRICK S. There are 6^ bricks in stock and no more will be required. 2. DhCK CLiLdTIG BRUSHES . We have 40 brushes in stock which are sufficient. • 5. PAINT BRUSIILS . There are 2 in stoct. and we • may order for a dozen. (3' ) 4. HOOP CILaNING BRU3HLS . tfe have 2^ in stock and no more will be required. # 5. COnh TOR ST-imJ:; IxaUNGII . we will not require if John Lamber is going to be sold. 6 . GOT TON VAioTh. 7 . OIL GAITS . 8. DUNGARY CLOTH. .. 9. G AID/A 3 . 10. GOa broom 11. I^LLTS 12. Ga UG-u GLa33L3. 13. jhfn BaiiLTG. we have 136 lbs in stocA cut they are very u.irty ana order for ^00 lbs. There are 5 in stoch and no more will be required. We have 48 yards in stock and no more will be required. There is a balance of 2u4’ in stocK and no more will be * required. 'We* have 340 in stocK and no more will be required. The re are 6 in stock and will be sufficient. There are *6 in stocic and no more required. We have 6 ana no more required/ P .A. Draft ordering for stores is submitted for your approval. 2. There is no mileage book of the launch. One of the crew writes their daily work in a boo*. I have taken from it the dates and places when and where the launch travelled and have entered in the attached register. 3. Draft to Arsenal.^u^tta for Flannelette is submitted. We send small orders to Herman when we require a thing urgently. Big orders are placed with Bakers. Please see page 98 and 181 in the attached file. ( 17/2). 2. Subject to your approval the last item in the draft i.e. Manilla rope may be ordered from Herman and the remaining from Bakers with the exception of bulbs which being a small quantity can be ordered from any Electric company by parcel post. 3. Register of the Motor Launch is resubmitted. &lt;u^vr ltThe Succani reports that the flexible wire of steering wheel of “Diana” is broken and a new wire is required* The cost of 60 yards is Rs*6/- May be purchased please?S.lTo. 15. Letter Up .75/37/S dated, the 31ct March. 1934 From B*R.Herman &amp; Mphatta, ‘Ltd., Karachi. o H.C . yyC re qu ire 2 coile of size. Please see the note oi 27.1*34. ,^e may order, if P./i. approves, from the 'Light Hoi-ns bra.nd n it 19.4.34. P&gt;A. 1 he Manilla rope of 'Light Horns brand' seems to be saJt better and stronger* 2e require 2 coils* May we order? Draft submitted for approval please* M- 7 41 —*- iy cIm^~ 5 ^ j \Jl^ * Iz j- . „ % ? rVy-L U(r r A.P.A. In August 1933 we brought two coils and cost of these 34JL- was Hs. 23-2-3, please S.No.310 of File No.17/2 submitted below. I have checked, the size required is i'* ^h.a sample is enclosed herewith please. A.P.A. jc The length of coi 7 is 720 feet, ^he approximate weight of a coil is 28 lbs.The price of 'Light Horns brand' is Rs.35 per cwt. n he cost of each esx±^ coil will be Rs. 3-12-0. .May we* order t.vo coils? Draft submitted for approval please. o] ^ # 7 v/i'The Nakhuaa says that he requires tnree tins of tallow ana one bag of lime for the new launch. 2c.11.34I i It $ P.A. The Nakhuda Rashid states that the bottom of all local and launches are painted with Wadak (Tallow) and ?Toora and not with fish oil and request if he should paint our new launch with Wadak and *Toora please. - Wa- /6a3 iw \ n [a/ /U^ jrC^v^✓ I r ^Letter IJoj1216-a dated tde 21st Lay 35 from ^essrs.L and company, Karachi. f\Xl Letter dated 2nd June 1935 from A-M. Yatee/ii 13ros, jjaur^m ' r ‘ : y be filpd ? p.63. Letter No.WH 2c94 dated 29.5.35 from Messrs.Baker,Lonuon. ^ // f ^ Mf K— All the stores have been receiveu with the exception of two one gallon arums of Lisinfecting fluia. I have askea the Customs authorities to prepare a Certificate to the effect that these two arums are short. kb•6*35 LL j stores receiveu have been entereu in the Stock Book. On opening tne case in which the varnish ana enamel paint were packeu, it was iouna that one half gallon tin of Enamel painty(^uite empty - its contents leaked in the case. Ail the rest have been found in perfect conuition. yt ko *0.00 7-7 M j vide the P ■; v/l e t he r q j merit of ,j Shold t The disinfecting fluid has not been rtceiveu-- dhorta~e certificate attached. I waioed. tj cee uhe firm wo Id uave informed ns aoout ^u.e liou-sui^ t,hese , out we have nof so far heard iron tnem. Should they be informed of the shortage ? 1 (lau Ml i up issued letter _Oil210 dated the 14th _uly 1935 to aker — v*0.Ivv*'* ^ou mentioned to me this morning that the Guard clock was twenty minutes slow one da} recent!}. ill you kindly make enquiries as Mr. Jasim is responsible for keeping the clocks at the right time after checking from the Telegraph Office. / ' - ^ . /• * *&gt; ^ x ' cX. Zjeya. Xs^&gt; ' ^ T (ji. ^ cr- (Jww A- Lw ^ ^ ^ 2-«W- -iwv-* ^ ^ ... //JT Our clocks have been set by G-reenwibh time to which 3 hours and 23 minutes have been added. Iraft to Messrs .Baker is submitted for approval J 14.lh35 issued netter ho,1977—17/2 dated the 14th November 193b to Messrs. Baker, London.Jv I ^ - 120, P.A. Re fee. your ^uery of 2.0.36 at note sheet ho.25, regarding flags. Our records show that every tine we nave paid for flags and the bill has been adjusted through A.O.C.R- € ; 1 30.7.36. Bill of Naraindas &amp; ^o. for bulbs. P.A . The bulbs have been received correct. May the bill be paid please ? i 1 H % - U 1^. c 'wi- 4 A 3 * _ _ i^rv /?A. J ju^l J C’ ^S|«. «-A •'•Ati T*7ir. A.P.A . The ease containing tin sheets has been cleared from Customs and handed over to David. It is for P.A. and found in good order. ^ 14.8.36.17/2. A. P. A. I submit below a list showing our requirements of stores for the current year. If approved they may be ordered from the following firms Items Mos.l, 2, 5, 10,11, 12, j from P.P.Baker &amp; Go., 13,14,15,16,17 and IB. Z? London. i 4 Items Nos. 3, 4 and 21 # Items Nos.8 and 9. Submitted for orders ) from Mama and Co. , Karachi. ) from Naraindas A Co., Karachi. ■£^\\ * e jl, ^ CjtiO. ^ C ^ ,r - 'fc CocaV ^ 5&gt;. cxak_ V 1. Prices are put against each item in oencil. Total cost will be about DS . 800/- excluding the cost of flags which will be adjusted through the A.G.C.R. by book debit. 2. There is a provision of 1,000/- under C.C.G. for the current year for panelling of A.P.A f s Office, L.0., and V.0. and the white paint will be used for painting these rooms and the C.0. 3. The stores will arrive here sometimes in April (i.e. next financial year) and the cost will be debited to the various funds for the year 1937-38. 130 . 17/2 10O. 110 . 111 . Issued letter No. 433 dated 20-2-37 to Baker and Go, London. Issued letter No. 434 dated 20-2-37 to Mama and Co, Karachi, -i-seued letter No. 435 dated 20-2-37 to Naraindas &amp; Co,Karachi Letter dated 24-2-37 from Narain &amp; Co, Karachi. Letter dated 27-2-37 from Narain A Co, Karachi. Letter dated t-3-37 from lama and Company, Karachi. ^ef . 10° and 110. j will arrange to clear the consignment fmm the Customs when it arrives. Pile? Ref. 111 . David says that manilla rope l u and will be of no use to us. D.F.A. submitted please. 112 . 113. 114. Issued letter No. 654 dated 19-3-37 to Mama &amp; Co, Karachi. Letter No. C.D.£.1229 dated 3-3-37 from Baker A Co, London. Letter dated 10-3-37 from Naraindas and Company, Karachi. Letter No. C.D.9.1229 dated 9-3-37 from Baker &amp; Co, London. B£££^J.2_jand_jjL4. D.F.A. submitted please. RefL^lS. Lubricating Oils have been received. Pay? 115. lie 117 119 Issued letter No. 875 dated 14-4-37 to Baker and Company. Issued letter No. 876 dated 15-4-37 to Naraindas, Karachi. Letter No. C.D.9/2351 dated 22-4-37 from Baker &amp; Co, London. File? \ ^ . ; Letter No. L/642 dated 18 - 5-37 from Gray Mackenzie, Bahrain. . Letter No. L/645 dated 18-5-37 from Gray Mackenzie, Bahrain. . JLetter No. WH.1220 dated 27-4-37 from Baker and Co. London. Egf„ 1 1 and 117 . D.F.A. submitted, Ref. 119. What are these? B.L. 18/5 2&lt;&gt;ir £»// ?-^.0 ,; Ref. 119. , .. This is an Annual supply of stores for the Agency /bl iv li? 7 vl ^ » . n.in.n.s-.,, U-4™^. \ L ' 1 VfU £i£SS®_S£e_pag£_137. We have not received reply to our letter Po. 654-17/2 dated the IPth March 1957. May a reminder be issued as the waste cotton i 6 urgently required.a.F.A.^ Ref. S.No. 116 . May a drSft f0r £ ’ 3 / 2 / 6 « favour of 'essrs Compton be obtained from the Bank and the cost debited to Bushire ‘ Residency as the map is for R.A. Shariah. The map will be sent to R.a. by the next down mail. Ref. S.No. 11Q _ Te haVe reCe ^dZ&amp; various paint-^t^b^r^T on Charge. May £. 65/16/2 be remitted to Baker, please? jlm ^ ^ fS A/s-v ; C •' f/Y Hi Shf 'Ir ^ V^tr/r r; o. Issued letter No. 1 333 dated 7-6-37 to Cray, Macken 2 i 9 Bahrairf Issued letter No. i 334 dated 7-6-37 to Baker * Co , London. Letter ^ d ^ D - 9 * 235:L dated 5-5-37 from Baker and Company, Pps. please B.T. 24/5 Please see pages 138, 142 and 143. On second thoughts I think it would be wise to cancel the order as|the stuff will not be required in the near future. It is no good keeping wire-gauze in stores as it gets rusty. Wire gauze and tail eln+.h*^ ,IT/ 2 121. Letter No. C.D. 9-95/2 dated 2?-6-37 from Ba’ter A Co, London. V Acct. Check pi. iff i B.T. 14/? Bakers* account is incorrect. We did not receive goods worth £. 50/6/11 from Baker in April. Shipping charges incurred in February 1937 (£.5/l2/ll) are not understood. The sum of £. 2/ll/8 it the cost of punch and eyelets for the launch. May be paid and debited to Launch Grant. The last item (£.21/15/7) is for the steel cupboard for the R.A. Sharjah. We have asked the R.A. to report when he receives the steel cupboard and when we hear from Sharjah we will remit £. 21/15/7 to Baker. D.F.A. submitted, please. &lt;i|1 6ir/. 15'k ‘s' A^JZ-a. &gt;!T-7- 51 t +-c_» 122 . O' ft Letcsr No. C.D. 9.43 Q 0 dated the 26-7-37 from Baker and Co, London Llease set paragraph 3 and put up ppe. c ^ * ^v-«rK' W • \*/ # 0( ^ / — The file (30/16) has been taken by P.A. to Karachi. Perhaps ■ chis could await his return from recess? A. P.A.' I- think we might await P.A f s return fr^m Karachi. —.TV-/) fTZu s. &amp; K) 5 Ccksla* ^ 1 / _jb</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00014e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1599</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00014e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1599</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 17/2 II Stores for the Agency Steam Launch etc.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-01-07T18:04:22</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (265 folios)</extent><extent>The material is arranged chronologically and includes a section of file notes at the rear of the file between folios 233-267. Entries in the index correspond to the circled numbers written in blue and red coloured crayon throughout the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 267; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Two additional foliation sequences are also present in parallel between ff 2-230 and ff 233-264; these are mostly written in pencil, with a few typed numbers, and numbers written in blue crayon.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the acquisition of supplies, equipment, and replacement parts for the Bahrain Agency's launch. Most of the file is made up of bills, receipts, and acknowledgements of orders placed with suppliers; this includes correspondence related to queries regarding orders placed, or prospective orders. There are also a few internal agency notes listing existing stocks for the launch and which items require replenishment.The correspondence is between the Political Agent, Bahrain (Percy Gordon Loch, Tom Hickinbotham, and Cornelius James Pelly), and the companies involved in supplying parts and materials for the launch. The principal companies involved are as follows: B R Herman and Mohatta Limited, Karachi; Messrs F P Baker and Company Limited, London; the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation; Mama and Company, Karachi; Messrs A M Yateem and Brothers, Bahrain; Naraindas and Company, Karachi; Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited; and Messrs I Thornycroft and Company Limited.The file also contains the following notable items:instructions from B R Herman and Mohatta Limited on how to fit a new rudder to the launch (folios 47-51) and recommendations for streamlining the stern (folios 64-66)—sketches are included;an information leaflet on Killgerm Fluid Disinfectant (folio 38);General Motors India Limited propaganda poster (folio 157);a sample of copper wire mesh (folio 173) supplied by F P Baker and Company Limited;samples of sailcloth with wire mesh (folio 193) also supplied by F P Baker and Company Limited;a sketch showing the stern of the Agency's launch (folio 236).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>B R Herman and Mohatta Limited, Karachi</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>F P Baker &amp; Company Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Naraindas and Company, Karachi</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>A M Yateem and Brothers, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Mama and Company, Karachi</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Launches</topic></subject><subject><topic>Materials</topic></subject><subject><topic>Maritime equipment</topic></subject><subject><topic>Supplies</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00014e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>