<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100056379988.0x000003_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-25T14:23:12.050Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">^ny reply to this letter should be addressed to — The Secretary, Treasury, \\ HITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1, and the folioicing number quoted. S/ 6594. Sir, nr' H TREASURY CHAMBERS. M i U I have laid before the Lords Commissioners of nis Majesty's Treasury Lr. Shuckburgh's letter of the 28th ultimo, (P.8662), wi+h reference to a proposal made by the Hijjt Corniiiissioner, Baghdad, that the Ba@»dad ana Mosul branches of the Imperial Ottoman Bank should be permitted tp settle, by mutual consent between bank and client, transactions dating back to the period before the Bntisn occupation, which have hitherto been held in abeyance undej the terms of the Notifications permitting the reopening of the branches. In reply I am to request you to inform the •Secretary of Si®** India imOonncil. that, wnile Their Lordships would have regarded it as preferable to decide by legislation trie principles on which such transactions should be settled, They are prepared to concur in the present proposal if Mr .Montagu is satisfied that in the special circumstances of the case tnis is the1 M ’ \ v w.m./h.p. O ,C' h p (&amp;) L o . -J 6697, s 920 COPY O T J L E J Prom High Commissioner, Baghdad, to Secretary of State. Dated Bagdad, 4* 12. 20. Received 7th, lO.a.m* — 14605* lour telegram dated 1st December, 3743. Notification ■ i wr } 3rd January refers t© Bagdad Branch on the same terms as notification itai T 14th March with additional clause. Begins ,r branch shall not dispose of nor send out of occupied territories any of assets ifo which it is entitled at date of this order except with consent ©f Civil Commissioner or of an officer authorized By him • Ends.* 2503 3000 10/20 Minute Paper. O /3 1U) Department. No. 41. NOTIFICATION. \\ HhPkAS the Mosul Branch of the Imperial Ottoman Bank has been closed since (be occupation of Mosul by the British forces. And whereas the Imperial Ottoman Bank has applied to re-open the Mosul Branch and u is expedient that it should be authorised to do so subject to the conditions hereina.lier mentioned: Now, therefore, it is hereby ordered as follows: — The Imperial Ottoman Bank ’’s hereby authorised to open its Branch at Mosul subject to the following conditions, namely: — All transactions of the Brain' ; previous to this date shall remain in abeyance until after a date to be fixed by order subsequent to the Declaration of Peace : and in particular, no debts or liabilitio. whii li are due to or from the said Branch in the Occupied Territories at ihis date shall be suable for, or re coverable by action set off or otherwise until after the said date to be so fixed by order. A. S. COBBE, Lieut.-Geneeal, Cowmanding-in-Chief, Mf*. E.r. Force. I Baghdad, this 14th day of March, 1919. From Iliqh Commissioner, Mesopotamia, ]Qth November 1920. P. 8305 5876 See proclamations of f? 10th January) and 14th March 1919. Ottoman Bank proposes to issue notification permitting settlement (by) mutual consent between bank and client of transactions held in abeyance under procla mations. Clients will include residents in non-occupied enemy territory. This is calculated to simplify considerations of disputed transactions and afford (? data) for formulation of legislation to apply to disputed transactions. Do you concur ? From Secretary of State to High Commissioner, Mesopotamia, 1st December 1920. P 8305 0743 Your telegram dated the 16th November. Ottoman Bank notification 3rd January cannot be traced. Is it in same terms as notification 14th .March .ELEPH 0 NE 6 : 111 CLYDEBANK &lt;2 LINES.) elforams: Bonaccord, GLASaOW.'’ emorandum . DRYSDALE &amp; CO., LTD., BON. ACCORD WORKS, YOKEF, GLASGOW, W. 13th Deer. 1J20 ^»eaI , Sir, have your letter cf the 10th inst., and note your further comments In regard to the Bagdad branch of the Imperial Ottoman Bank, for which thanks. Yours faithfully, FOR/^YSDALE 8; CO., LTD.x.j .DirtfGTOi♦ Diy. LAWRANCE,WEBSTER,MESSER &amp; NICHOLLS. ALLAN E MESSER. ARTHUR E NICHOLLS. TELEPHONE N?® CITY 6273 6274 TiJ^^ R APHIC ADDRESS, RANCH B^US, STOCK, LONDON. 10th December /J?3l £.C. 2 1 vjn? j CT , j (Fl^ l h ^ , q ^ ^- A - , // ' /^c %-frrtj «'&lt;bZ ^ ^ Deer Sir, ^ , '/' i^lL^ — On behalf of our clients, Jiessfs w. &lt;Sc A.W. Hulse ?u ^ ^ 11 &lt;1 ,w • ! ^ ; of Birmingham ’A© are formulating a claim to a ?um received hy the Imperial Ottoman Bank at Baghdad in the month of July 1918. \,e are informed that a British proclamation was isued in Baghdad on the 3rd January 1919 ordering “all “traneactione of the Branch f ottoman Bank) previous to this 'date should remain in abeyance until after a date to be 'fixed by Order subsequent to the declaration of peace'. we are desirous of obtaining if possible a copy of the Proclamation in question and it has been suggested that we should apply to youfor that purpose, we shall be obliged if you can if possible, forward to is a copj of the proclamation in question, -r4a i£- f 1 - D » •0' t il3 ^ rtl * j - ® i , .■■ j c • / • &gt;10X ^Xut •c -' .. XAort ^Uita .• t 9 +t bfci . „ : , *, «£ &amp;M r A ^ q - rf ,oiio^ ^Oitstg 9«J *C ?itei^o»err 9 ^ I ^ ,? ' ,fIj »Off*v.®tfp fri rl i..3- ^Xi;o&lt;&lt;» ^s&amp;' .'^C i J » ■ j.LEPHONt* : 111 Clydebank ( ■ &gt; lines.) 'LEaRAMS : “ Bonaocord, Qlabqow.” JD/J! . ^Memorandum) l 1 DRYSDALE &amp; CO., LTD., BON-ACCORD WORKS, YOKER, GLASGOW, W. 3rd Dec*, 1920 \\ EMPLOYER .UHlilijUi ^tf Under Se cret ary of State_ for India, Political Dept., India House, ~~ L“0 F D 0 it. svr.i— Dear Sir, 11'^ Reference P We have to acknowledge receipt of your letter of 2nd December, and while thanking you for same we are somewhat surprised that the information asked for is not in your possession, and shall do our best to secure the information elsewhere. ^ k Yours faithfully, FOP DRYSDALE 8t CO., LTD. . • ^ C1DI-1920 T Y A— !L~JL .DIRECTOR’4 Jopy. 13.344/13344/44) 'JK. n I Drysdale and Company Limited q B on-Accord Works, Yoker, Glasgow 27th. October, 1920. Dear Sirs:- We have an order this morning for Pumping plant for Bagdad, and our customer asks us to accept payment at the Imperial Ottoman Bank in Bagdad. Having in view the amount of trouble that is at present in Mesopotamia, we are doubtful as to whether we should accept such a method of payment or not, and we should like you to say whether the Imperial Ottoman Bank is a sound and safe institution at Bagdad, also we should like to know if it is any longer a Turkish Institution at all, and if so, is it backed and guaranteed by the British Authoritiess Yours truly, For Drysdale and Co. Ltd., (Signed) George Reid. Director. e Secretary Foreign Office, London. y i ao^ v» a10 1766 I 1899 1000 9/19 POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Letter Telegram from Dated Rec. Formally acknowledged 19 Date. Initials. To Under Secretary.. Secretary of f^tate. Committee Under Secretary. . Secretary of State Mw % Previous Papers :— SUBJECT. FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. 71reply to this letter should be addressed to — The Secretary, Treasury, Whitehall, London, S.W. 1, TREASURY CHAMBER February, 1920. and the following number quoted. 5753 20 . Sir, In reply to Mr* Shucicburgh* s letter of the 4th instant ('P.744) enclosing copy of a telegram from the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, No. 96, dated 3rd January, with reference to the position of the Imperial Ottoman Bank in Mesopotamia, I am directed by the Lords Commission ers of His Majesty*s Treasury to state that Ihey concur in the reply which it is proposed to send to the Civil Commissioner. I am Sir Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State India Office.4 In any farther cammaniojvtion f on this subject, please quote N »- 176304/M. E./44A. I and address, not to any person by name, but to — “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. r' © Hf-}^ \u&gt;S kk£(5N Office. February llth,1920. «rw Sir:- O l(/4 k KL /j.a ■4- I am directed by Earl curzon of Kedleston to acknowledge receipt of your letter No.P.744 of the 4th February, end to state that Lord curzon concurs in the terms of the draft reply which Mr.Secretary Montagu proposes to send to Civil commissioner, Baghdad, with reference to the position of the Imperial Ottoman Bank in Mesopotamia. I am. Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, t The Under-Secretary of state, India Office. rV'/////// c 27th January, 20. Sir, At our request our Bagdad Branch has approached the Authorities there for permission for Mr H it .Saltmarsh and Mr D J3 •Jones to proceed to Mesopotamia on business for the Bank. We have just received a cable from Bagdad informing us that the Authorities approve / and instruct us to apply to you. This, we presume, is an indication that you have heard from them direct and that you will be prepared to issue the per mits in question. We shall be glad to know if this is the case . I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, The Secretary, India Office, Pall Mall, S.W.V Dated 3rd Jmuar} r , 1920. (Received 10th, 11 a.m.) 96. Lord Goechen with party ia visiting Mesopotamia shortly to visit his son’s grave at Arnara. I imagine ie will also take the opportonity to visit principal tranches in this country of the Imperial Ottoman Bank, of which he is a director. Altitude which I propose to s.dopt, subject to your concurrence, is that we can recognise no prior rights or privileges of the Imperial Ottoman ^ank in this country, and i-v'i, waii e we ave no intention of restricting their activities a bank, they must not look to us for any special facilities osier than those which we give to banks generally. In this connection, please see enclosure to Foreign Office- letter, dated (? April 2cth), nunber P.2216.4 la aay further cammanica- lioc on tms subject, please quote A and The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, /-n London, S.W. 1. if • o 4 Ci •. • » / ‘ -f • J *■ ■’ 8 i O THE Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the imder-mentioned paper. Foreign Oftcc, , 1919. Letter -to- from Reference to previous correspondence : Foreign Office : £ /&amp; Ck. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. V /? &amp; i^l ('r» MAYlSIfl)’ ^Similar letter sent to G —1604 S^A. /« I^E,&lt;IAL OTT(MAN BANK, 26 hrogmorton itreet,. .0.2. May 2nd 1919. Sir, . We have to adcnow^dge with many thanks receipt of your letter No.5^?’3/M.E./44 of the 11th ultimo,from which we note that for the moment the question of the payment of revenues into our Branches in Mesopotamia and Palestine is one which concerns the Military Authorities responsible for the administration of the occupied territories. While we quite understand that no undertaking can be given for the moment by the Foreign Office,we shall be * / glad to be assured that this matter will receive their full consideration when the Military Authorities have ceased to be responsible for the territories in question. I am # etc., (Signed) Manager. E ' t Under secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office, s.vs.l.4 - *vr+ r ? ♦ In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote ffcJFTW ’ bOblL. / 1919 - ress- T / *&lt;5, and address- The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, ^ c jf' £ London, S.W. I. .¥ THE Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Ofice, » 19194 a a i In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. 6602/W/44. r and address, / Foreign OrncE not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. I j January 17th, 1919 Sir:- With reference to your letter No.p.5444, of December 11th, relative to permission for the Imperial Ottoman Bank at Basra to correspond with its Head Office at Constantinople, I am directed by Earl Curzon oi Kedleston to state for the information of Mr. Secretary Montagu that the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty's Treasury have expressed their vdllingness in the circumstances to authorise such communication, and that His Majesty's High Conmissioner at Constantinople has also signified his concurrence in the proposal. Your most obedient humble Servant I am, Sir fche Under-Secretary of State, India Office. '(2Cifi65/W/44) The Under-Secretary of state for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under secretary of state for India and begs leave to state that India Office letter of December 11th (p.5444) has been referred to the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty*s Treasury at their request for observations. A reply will be returned as soon as these have been ^ obtained. i r ^ Foreign Office, January 13th, 1919Draft Paper. POLITICAL ai:d secret partment. (&gt; ^M C 1 The Secre-tary, Imperial Ottoman Bank, London Agency, 26, Thrognorton Street, E.C, 2., vj. *f/i. nf U- Cjp 4 ^ I ,/ o&gt;. h. /• J INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W. 1., /6-November, 1918. Sir, With reference to correspondence ending with your letter of the 4th November, 1917, regarding the proposed visit of Mr. H.R.Saltmarsh to Mesopotamia, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to inform you that a telegram has been received from the Civil Cornnissioner, Baghdad, suggesting that Mr. Saltmarsh should be instructed to extend the scope of his enquiries so as to include the Mosul branch of the Imperial Ottoman Bank, which has been closed by the British authorities pending further investigation. I am to request that your Directors will take Captain Wilson’s suggestion into consideration and will furnish Mr. Saltmarsh with such additional instructions as they my think desirable.TliLIX&gt;HA 7 i TROll POLITICAL, B ACID AD. dated nth mmmm, 1913 . (EECD. 12th, NOVMBER, 3 p.m.) 9708. telegram of 1st October. Imperial Ottoman Bank. Saltmarsh is I understand en route for Basra. Suggest Directors be requested to instruct him to enquire also into the position and functions of Mosul branch of Imperial Ottoman Bank which I have ordered to be closed pending further.investigation. Addressed Secretary of State repeated to Delhi.12 ] f r ^ In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote N and id address— ( • /1918 The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, ^ London, S.W.l. Name and Date. 1'he Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the UnderSecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop — of the under-mentioned paper. ^ Description of Enclosure. Subject. /u L 5 *-—&lt;rz- ■/ L^£jL tf/i .fldliA 0 f he: A^ftXr-y 1518 / (Similar letter sent toV LONDON AGENCY, *1. 26,Throgmorton Street, e.c. 2. (+IUO TELEGRAM S '01 OTTO, STOCK, LON DON.' 4th November, 1918 Dear Sir We reoeived a telegram from our Manager in Alexandria, dated the 29th October, as follows:• H Saltmarsh and Humphries proceeding destination today.- 11 ana have now received this one:- H Referring to our telegram of 29th, for your guidance, 'Humphries Saltmarsh still in Egypt, Authorities having 'postponed departure at the last moment•- The Secretary, Political Department INDIA OFFICE'Immediate and confidential. ( iLvTOf Reference :—Letter to Foreign Office. (*‘k\^0 ^ 1 \u5° ' ' 7he Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State foi India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of Q. telegram , as marked in the margin. Foreign Office. (Smritnr it iiu M'td to- l SO SEPttrt ' 15 a |^0 TT o MMfi V' LONDON AGENCY, 26,Throgmorton Street, e.c. 2. TELEGRAM S 'BIOTTO, STOCK, LONDON' 23rd September, 1918 Sir, We beg to acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 19th September (1° P.4140) with beet thenke. Mr Saltaareh has taken the necessary steps. We are. Sir, Yours faithfully Th. 8.ov*tary. Political D.partaont, INDIA 07S1CX, S.W.l ~ S£P0?3\ kWL) any further commanication ■f^on this subject, please quote no. 156 555A/44. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,’ Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. * 1 i &gt;y i 3 Foreign Office SeptemlDer 17th, 1918 Sir, In reply to your letter, P.3909, of the 12th instant, relative to the deputation of certain officials of the Imperial Ottoman Bank to Bagdad, I am directed by Mr Secretary Balfour to state that he concurs in the suggestion of Mr Secretary ontagu that the application contained in the Bank's letter to the India Office of the 27th ultimo should be supported, and that Mr Saltmarsh should be assisted in his application for a passport. I arn, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office.Draft Paper. Department. tr JLk,'Dear Sir, Referring to your letter of the let August (P.3270) we have been in telegraphic communication with Mr. Crltchley who points out that the difficulties are very great for his leaving Egypt at the present time owing to lllness 9 depletion of Staff and the near approach of the Cotton Campaign. To get over the difficulty we are arranging to send out from here Mr.E.R.Saltmarsh of this Office whom we propose shall he joined in Egypt by Mr.E.E.Humphrles; the two will then proceed to Bagdad. CHAIRMAN Secretary of State for Xndla t Political Department, \ India Office,a' /o /??ws&gt;n 7th Auguet 1918. Dear Sir, 1 hare to thaak you for your letter of the lot instant in aeoordanoe with which we have telegraphed to Mr Critchley to arrange to proceed as soon as possible to Bagdad for the purpose of diseusslng matters with the CiYll Comissloner. We have requested Mr Critehley to wire us when he can start and to report to us from Bagdad with his reeommenda- -tions, on reeeipt of which we hope to be in a position to l give him definite instructions. Yours faithfully, -C+. Chairman The Under Secretary of State for India Pelitieal Department nOM- India Office ^ ^ • S.W.Draft Paper. political Department. % \ The Chairaan, Imoerial Ottoman Bank, LONDON AGENCY. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL S.W. Jwiy-, 1918. 1 • » tty Lord, In continuation of previous correspondence regarding the proposal to reopen the Baghdad branch of the Imperial Ottoman Bank* and with special reference to Mr. Barry’s visit to this office on the 17th July, 1918, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to inform you that he has been in further telegraphic co-muni cation with the Mesopotamian authorities, who agree to the proposal that Mr. Critchley should proceed to Baghdad on behalf of the Bank for the purpose of discussing the whole question with the Civil Commissioner and of taking, in consultation with the latter, such further steps as may be found practicable.9 tl ■ 1 ■ J) i 3 Orfui&amp; i.O. 1 */y//f COPY OF TELEGRAM . X From Viceroy, Foreign Department, Dated 16th June, 1918. ######***#*#** Secret. Baghdad branch of Imperial Ottoman Bank. Since deapatch of our telegram of June 8th we have received Cox's telegrams of 8th and 10th June and provided demand on us for rupees does not exceed 3 lakhs and amount is not required till say September when we shall have received and coined up substantial quantity of American silver we are prepared to withdraw our opposition to proposal in Cox's telegram 4183 dated May 13th, Addressed Secretary of State repealed to Baghdad.TELEGRAM EROM POLITICAL BAGHDAD 14th JUKE 1918. (Received 15th 10.30 a. 9 ].) 5044. My telegram of 10th Jure 4946. It is estimated that reserve cash and notes in currency chest at Basra at end of June vdll be Rs. 30 lakhs coin, Rs . 60 lakhs notes. No demands for coin have been made on India for past 3 months and none are probable for next 3 months. Addressed Secretaiy of State repeated to Foreign.; ^ y ■ Am J i y (Received 11th 1.3C p.m, ) 4946 Government of India telegram of June 8th crossed my telegram 4887 of same date. In support of statement made in last sentence thereof I submit following further observations for consideration. The provision of additional banking fiacilities at Bagdad for the public is calculated not to increase our (? sp«cifT) requirements but to reduce th^m materially. Within a few weeks of opening Imperial Ottoman Bank would probably obtain over Rs 3 lakhs in casj^deposits from clients who at present are not banking their money. The absorption of specie in this country is abnormally large at present owing primarily to stagnation of trade and inadequate banking facilities. We are purchasing this year practically the whole surplus agricultural and pastoral produce of Mesopotamia and South, West Persia. This must ultimately be paid for either in cash or by importation of commodities. I therefz&gt;oe submit that steps best calculated to keep down prices maintaining our note issue and economising silver, are, firstly, the encouragement of trade, and secondly, the provision of banking facilities at least as good as those available before the war when the turnover of cash transactions in the country was less than it is now. Addressed Secretary of State repeated to Foreign^— ••• W7-*s * Tslegrtuii from Viceroy, Foreign Dspt. Dated 8th June 1918. '1 PT ' Q Ti it -m ^ Received Q'fch at 11 Secret. Your telegram of the 30th iiay. Bagdad branch of /Ottoman) Bank. Repayment of creditors in rupees as proposed would be most undesirable in our present circumstances, so we oppose Civil Conmssioner 1 s suggestion. We are not aware of any valid reason why Bagdad branch should be reopened at the present tin®. Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to bagdad,Telegram from Political, Baghdad. Dated 8th June 1918. Received 9th at 2 p.m. 8 .j 4887. Secretary of State’s telegraurof' 50thrtS,y. Greater portion of liabilities £133,000 are payable in Europe * and in part consist of proceeds of bills collected for British firms. Immediate requirements to liquidate local liabilities would not exceed Rs300,0Q0 and would not afiect currency situation. Addressed to Foreigi, repeated to Secretary of State for India. ,T l*T S'- V., v Y ft* 'v ‘ 1'^' ,•&gt; 1*^ - -1. 26,Throgmorton Street, e.c. 2. Conficfntlal Mar Sir Referring to ay letter of the 31et ultimo, one of js Vni the diffloultiee referred te le the following ^Doee it net ooour to the Political Officer that if an 'Rstahliehaent adopted the system of repaying deposits (made in 'Turkish Currency Notes) at the rate ruling for that Turkish 'Currency at the date of deposit a dangerous precedent might be 'created and taken adrantage of in other towns. 'The effect of such a precedure might he to do exactly 'what the Political wishes to avoid, namely, to give an t 'enhanced value to Turkish Currency Rotes that are being held. '2f such a precedent is created, the effect might be to 'put up the value of Turkish Currency Rotes in other towns; 'because certain enterprising individuals might think that they 'could then pay them in to establishments in these ether towns 'and that whatever might happen get out eventually the counter- 'part at the exchange ruling at the date on which they paid 'them in. 'Therefore, these enterprising individuals might seek te 'buy up Turkish Currency Rotes, we will say in Uesopotaiaia, 'have them sent to some tther town not occupied by the Allies, 'cause the rate to go up, fluid pay them in to some Bstabliehiaent■H 2 •to thmir credit, thus making a regular traffic* 'Although we are net thercughly informed, it eeeme to 'us at the preeent moment, the peeitien ie: that Turkish 'Treasury Votes are etill doing circulated at a price. This 'we gather from the letter of the Controller of Hostile 'Trading Concerns* 'Therefore, can Liabilities be paid back in them ? ' 2 on, Lear Bir, Tours faithfully SSCfQSTABAT Hie tfajeety 9 e Under fteeretary of State for India, Political Department, XKDIA 07FI0B,Y\ . ? ^ 0TT0M ^,. V V LONDON AGENCY, A 26,Throgmorton Street, e.c. 2. TELEGRAM S Dear Sir, Ve have received your letter of the 30th Hay (K° 2164) which we will lay before the Committee. At first eight, it seems to present some difficulties. Yours faithfully His kajesty's Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, Wvr India 0m ° e&gt; S.W.l•8 Ano at Deloitte, Plenoer,Griffitk6 &amp;€? Sir William Plcnoer. Percival D.GRiFriTHS. ^REoward Davis. Lionel Maltby. A. E. Cutforth. R, C, Martin. R. Kerr. Cardiff, Petrograo &amp; Moscow. New York, Chicago, Havana &amp; Mexico City. Montreal &amp; Vancouver. Buenos Aires, Rosario,Tucuman, Rio de Janeiro &amp; Pernambuco. Johannesburg, Bulawayo, Care Town, Salisbury &amp; Durban. telegrams: DELOITTE. Telegrams;- DELOITTE (AVE ) LONDON. Telephone No. 3000 London Wall (3 lines) 31st May, 1918. The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, S.W. 1. Sir, BRITISH KSTAbLISHMi?iNT Or lAlPllRlAh OTTOMAN DANK. ba^daa branch. 1 am obliged for your letter of yesterday's date and note the contents of your communication of the same date to the chairman of the Bank in London, ol which you have been kind enough to send me a copy. 1 am, Bir, Your obedient Servant,^^ 0Tr0M ^B M V V LONDON AGENCY, / T_ 26,Throgmorton Street, e.c. 2 TELEGRAMS BIOTTO, STOCK, LON don!' 21 5 4 I m I R 2&gt;«ar Sir, With r«f«renc« to tho Manager f s conTcreation the other day with Mr Shuckburgh, we shall be pleased to hear if he has anything further to tell us. Secondly, we beg to enclose you copy of a letter which is sent out by the Controller of Hostile Trading Concerns, Bagdad. In this letter, the Controller states that the Turkish Currency Note is at a heavy discount; and yet conveys the idea to the recipient of his letter that the Imperial Ottoman Bank,London, should pay full faee value. Ignoring the fact that if this were dene an artificial value would be immediately given to the Turkish Currency Note all ovar enemy territory* Our experience points to the fact that the Controller's letter has not created in the recipients 1 mind? the impression wished, because the recipients seem to consider that this letter ♦ entitles them to be paid at the full face value of Turkish Currency Netee received on the other side; this is, so far as we can perceive, entirely contrary to the views set out in your letter of 17th August last, and plaeee us in an awkward position* !/ Furthermore, 1* ' ;Furthermore, the Controller does not point out, what we understand to be a fact, that the proceeds even paid in paper money of these Engagements were sequestrated by the Enemy. vV* X am. Pear Sir, Yours faithfully, His tfajesty , s Tinder Secretary of State for India, Political Department, INDIA OFFICE,(COPY) CONTROLLER QJ HOSTIUB TRADING CONCERNS Baghdad, 26th hareh 1918 Proro Controller of Hostile Trading Conoeme, Baghdad To Mosers Bsnigno Crdspi -JL l X &gt; a. Boar Sirs, In reply to your letter of the 12th January 1918, 2 hare pleasure in enclosing copy of a letter vritten to you lay the Imperial Ottoman Bank Baghdad and dated 21st Hot, 1917, in regard to the bills eont to them for collection. The Army Commander has prohibited the Branch of the Ottoman Bank at Baghdad from continuing trading, but it is not prohibited from meeting its liabilities and no winding up order has been made. The Baghdad Branch is not in a position out of its local assets to meet its liabilities except in Turkish Treasury Notes, In pursuance with the Turkish Law of the 12th April 1916, which made the acceptance of the Turkish Treasury Votes compulsory, a large proportion of its debts during the war were collectsd in Turkish Treasury Botes. Thsss Botes are now at a very heavy discount. 2t le Open to you to take proceedings against the Bank in the Courts which haws been recently opened here, but such pro ceedings are not likely to be fruitful as they would probably lead to a winding up order for the protection of the creditors generally. In these circumstances it is suggested that you should approach the Managers of The Ottoman Bank in Xngland. Yours faithfully4185. Your telegram if 1st May 0 Under Tuilr at the time they were paid Turkish Treasury note be accepted at their face value and in existing law it is quite possible Bagdad Counts might dr'c such credits should be repaid in rupeps at a rat calculated on the face value of Treasury notesg would be inequitable. I consider creditors win prove that they paid in their credits in Turkic notes should be giv^n option either of demanding repayment of their loan in rupees at the ma rke t v; of Treasury notes when paid in (which can be ascer* and notified officially) or of waiting of their claim*until after the war. On receipt 0 prepared to recommend G-.O.C^-in - Chief to take actt^ Ottoman accordingly by proclamation^. Manager Imperial/Bank concursDear Sir, In reply to your letter Ho P.1592, we beg to inform you that we will communicate to you directly we are able to give a definite reply* We are endearouring to find a solution to those Currency difficulties mentioned in your letter of 17th August last. We are, therefore, in telegraphic communication with Mr Beid, Manager of our Basra Branch, who having a permit has arrived in Bagdad. . This question of Currency and the actual present value of sums paid in in Turkish currency presents considerable difficulties and if not carefully handled might lead to the consequences mentioned in your letter of 17th August* It has already led to eome misunderstanding as you will see from the enclosed copies of correspondence* The statement in the Mote, paragraph three, does not seem to us to agree with the above mentioned letter of yours dated 17th August and that of 26th October last. Will you kindly put the matter right with the Foreign Office so as to remove the misunderstanding. Copy irf added of letter from Paris showing the'remselgnements' given to lieeers Giraud Friree. May the Manager come and see yeu on the currency question about 12 on Monday? Ve add a little Memorandum. Z am. Dear Sir, Yours faithfully CHAIRKAH His Majesty 9 e Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department # IKDIA OPPIOS, S.w.lMemorandum re Currency Confidential If the Branch in Bagdad relmburecd Local deposit ere who haws deposited Currency Motes during Turkish rlglme at the faee Y&amp;lue, there might be much speculation at other places whore Kotes can be obtained at a big discount, ▲Iso if Allied remitters of bills which hoYs been en» cashed in the same way mere to bo reimbureod at the face Yalue, the same result might eYentuate.Dt&lt;a April Received 6t 1 a April 11.30 3Co8. Lly t^l^graa of 3rd March. 2116.Imperial Ottoman Bank. Should be glad to know how matter stands. French Con3ul t Basra, is pressing me to insist on Bank f paying its French creditor.D«ar Sir, Referring to your letter of the 26th ultimo (P.1190) and my reply of the 27th idem, Z beg to Inform you that we are advised that Mr Reid, the Joint-Manager of our Basra Branch, was due to arrive at Bagdad on the 31st ultimo. We have cabled to him for certain necessary information with regard to Cash etc. and await receipt of his reply. Z am. Bear Sir, Yours faithfully CHAIRMAN Hie Majesty^ Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, INDIA orezcs. S.W.lDeloitte, Plender,Griffiths &amp; C (|M WHICH IS MERCeOTME flHM OF WElTOH k BONO) Sir William Plsnoer. ’spcival D.Griffiths. “Howard Davis. Lionel Maltby. A . E. ClITFORTH. R.C.Marti n . r 7 .) P.1190. The Under Secretary of State for India, Politicai Depart ment, India Office, Whitehall, S.W. I. Sir, BRITii^i hSrADLISHMbiVr Oi? I.vLPTiUAh OTTOMAN DANK. Ba^ndad Branch, I am much obliged to you for sending me with your letter of the 26th ultimo a copy of your communication of that date addressed to the Chairman of the Bank.Draft Paper. Department 7Vt) * INDIA OFFICE, , WHITEHALL, S.W. 1., March, ,1918. •The Chairman, Imperial Ottoman Bank, London Agency. 26, Throgmorton Street, E. C. 2., By Lord, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to invite reference to Sir A. FirtzePs letter No. 1624^ dated the 23rd April, 1917, on the subject of the decision to close the Baghdad Branch of the Imperial Ottoman Bank until the end of the war. t A communication has now been received from the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, recommending that the above decision should be reconsidered, in the altered circumstances of the present time, and asking for authority to notify that the Bank will be permitted to resume business at Baghdad, as from the 1st April, 1918. H.M* s Government after careful consideration of the question, are prepared to accept the Civil Commissioner’s recommendationrecommendation; but they think it necessary, for reasons which they feef sure that your Lordship will appreciate, t to make it a condition that the Bank will not parade the name 'Ottoman” in Baghdad, or exhibit any Turkish or quasi-Turkish insignia or titles. On hearing from you that this condition is&lt;accepted, the Secretary of State will authorise the Civil Commissioner to make the necessary notification in Mesopotamia, He will be glad to know by what date, not «^)er than the 1st April, you can arrange for the resumption of business at .Baghdad. . t ( 'c io UtfciMKkJt 2I am accordingly to suggest that the London agency of the Bank should be informed accordingly, and that it should be explained to them that only on this understanding will they be permitted to re-open their branch at Bagdad. _• I, am, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, ♦ To^ -sJ O’ I coFf o? TL^am c l _jp ■' o J Dated 3rd iiarcia Hec^rTed y ' ?c 7 - z&gt;/v/ r 3 vil coLzassioinm Baghdad k. 4th March 7 2116* LIy telegram of 16th February 1620, la3t sentence* In vi^w of prolongation of war, exp^di^ncy of adjusting commercial claims as far as possible ( and importance of doing whatever is possible to improve financial position in Bagdad which is increasingly difficult owing to large outlay of money by force in return for labour and produce which is not counterbalanced by corresponding imports of Irak, I think time has come to recomsider decision communicated in your telegram of 21st April that the Bagdad Branch should be closed till the end of war. Twelve months has now elapsed during which time Controller of Hostile grading Concerns Bagdad has throughly investigated all local enemy concerns and has ascertained precise position ' # of Bank and its principal clients. Law courts have been opened and the Turkish moratorium has come to an end* If Baghdad Branch were now allowed to open. Basra and London Agency would presumably be ooliged to come its assistance with funds and local merchants and others creditors, would have some prospect of obtaining satisfaction. At present trie action of government in closing Bagdad Branch enables Bank to evade obligations which others are compelled by law to meet. If above proposal meets with approval I would ask that London Agency be informed and tuat I may be authorised to notify that the Bank will be permitted to resume business as from 1st April*(° Fi om Sir P.Gox, Baghdad, Pith February 1918. It',20 Your Despatch dated 13th December, No. 4987 F. No com- i ivu nfoation has ever'reached Controller Hostile (; irand Freres. Imperial Ottoman Hank lias collected all bills sent to t e v - nd Freres and duly advised them to that effect on 31st Ikdobei I! ,', k has^een prohibited from undertaking new transactions, 1 &gt;&gt; ‘'t » no prohibited Iron! meeting its liabilities nor from collecting outstanding credits Vo winding-up order has been made. ni l • u icily .h. hi ol In '-S Treasury notes, so it is impossible loi them to n ? , Wect I import ion of their debts. I propose to address you further on the subject shortly.And at V. Cardiff, Petroqrao &amp; Moscow. New York, Chicago, Havana *. Mexico City. Montreal &amp; Vancouver. &gt; Buenos Aires, Rosario,Tucuman, Rio de Janeiro &amp;. Pernambuco. Johannesburg, Bulawayo, Cape Town, Salisbury &amp; Durban. , telegrams; DELOITTE. Deloitte,Plender,Griffiths&amp;C? iSir WlLtlAM PLENOER. &lt;cival D.Griffiths, zaro Davis. Lionel Maltby. A.E.CUTFORTH . If Te lmmmi. DELblTTE (AVE) LONDON. T.l.phon. No. 3000 Lo.oo. W.ll (3ti.,s) P.3444 21st September 1917. The Under Secretary oi State, Political Department, India Office, S.W. 1 Sir, I „ much obliged for yo«r of je.teriay e date enclosing ooty of the Banb'e letter to you of 5th instant# I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, Is v s ' \S^f (niS) 'f’n LONDON AGENCY * 26 ,Throgmorton Street, e.c. ws/sw September 6th 1917. telegrams- 'BIOTTO STOCK.LONDON” Dear Sir, We hare received your letter of the let September (Wo.?*3444) and we note the conclusion at which Mr«Secretary Montagu has arrived* We therefore abandon the idea of Mr* Critohley’s visit for the present. But in arriving at this decision we would point out that we do so from a desire to fall in with the Secretary of State 9 s views but are unable to accept the arguments submitted in his letter of September 1st* We have not appointed a local Bagdad Manager slnwe the British Occupation and we do not think that the individual the Chief Political Officer refers to is competent to conduct the investigation and make the report we require* Consequently, the Report to which reference is made it not what we want, and the figures convey nothing for the reasons of currency mentioned confidentially in your letter of the 17th August* Z am, Bear Sir, Your obedient Servant for CHAIRMAM His Majesty 9 e Under*Secretary of State for India Political Department, I RBI A OFFICE.er Deloitte, Pi ender,Griffiths &amp; C° Sir William Plenoer. Percival D.Griffiths. •Edward Davis. Lionel Maltby. A E.Cutforth. And at 1 Cardiff, Petroorao 4. Moscow. New York, Chicago, Havana &amp;. Mexico City. Montreal &amp; Vancouver. Buenos Aires, Rosario,Tucuman, Rio oe Janeiro 4 Pernambuco. Johannesburg, Bulawayo, Cape Town, Salisbury 4 Durban. 'I telegrams; DELOITTE Telegrams.-- DELOITTE (AVE) LONDON. Telephone No. 3000 London Wall ( 3 lines) 4th September 191?« P» ^444&gt; The Under Secretary of State, Political Department, India Office, fhitehall, S.W. 1 # V J Sir, BRITISH ESTABLISHMEUT OF Bagdad Branch. I am obliged for your memorandum of yesterday * 1 2 s date transmitting for my information copy of (1) The BanJ^s letter to you of the 20th ultimo (2) Your reply of the 1st instant* Your obedient Servant,Telegram from Sir P. Cox Dated 24th August 1917 Received 6 p.m. (25th). X \ Cvtbc/yJtjty^ 5399. ^our telegram of the 17th August. Muttah.* 1. Permission to proceed to Baghdad cannot in any case be granted unless the exact nature of his mission is known so tail his presence eaen at Basra would only be embarrassing. 2.. In March last London Directorate authorised Reid, Basra /yyvfVvv. C*- 7 to proceed to Baghdad to report on situation but permission to ^ was refused by Military Authorities. It was therefore obviously considered possible then for local man present to report and/jnnda statement to the contrary is consequently not convincing. 3. Have ascertained that local Baghdad Manager submitted detailed report on whole situation in April of which he has no$ yet received any acknowledgment. he seems quite competent to answer any queries and give such further details as may be necessary. 4. For above reasons regrst cannot alter view as to inexpediency of his visit unless furnished with full details of proposed scope of his mission ultimate object of which appears to be to reopen business which cannot be allowed. \ i11 Deloitte,Plender,Griffiths&amp; C° i Sir William Plenoer. ^Percival D.Griffiths. Eowaro Davis. Lionel MalTby. A.E.Cutforth. Cardiff, Petroorao 4. Moscow. New York, Chicago, Havana 4 Mkxico City. Montreal 4 Vancouver. Buenos Aires, Ros ario.Tucuman , Rio oe Janeiro 4 Pernambuco. Johannesburg, Bu lawayo. Cape Town, Salisbury 4 Durban. Telegrams:- DELOITTE (AVE) LONDON. Telephone No. 3000 London Wall ( 3 lines) P.315I 23rd August 1917. The Under Secretary of State, Political Department, India Office, S-W. 1 Sir, BRITISH ESTABLISHMENT OF IMPKRIAL OTTOMAN BANK, BAGDAD BRANCH. I am much obliged for your Memorandum of yester day's date enclosing copy of LordBe8^borou^gl• s letter to the India Office dated the 3rd instant with copy of your reply dated the 17th instant. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, /si \?3/&lt;r 26 ,Throgmorton Street, e g. TELEC R AM S&gt; “BIOTTO STOCK.LONDON.' Mat Sir, X «a in reo«ipt of pour lottor (P.3151) of tlio 17th instant• hr Montagu rightly understands that Mr Orltohley 9 s 4 m ^ functions, while in Hssopotsmin, would bo confined to Inresti- gstion and the nuking of n Report, and that there is no intention on our part to raTiwa for the present the question of re-opening the Bagdad Branch. I have te thank you for the confidential inforaation that you hare been good enough to giro no. CHAIHMAH Hie ](ajesty*s Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office,26 ,Throgmorton Street, e.c “BIOTTO STOCK,LONDON Mar Sir, We have received your letter of the 30th July (P.3072) and very much regret te etate that it ie inpeeeible for us in view of all our various responsibilities to our Shareholders and Clients, British and Allied, te he satisfied with the reply therein. as far as we are aware, sufficiently acquainted with our affairs te justify his categorical statement that the interests in Mesopotamia of our Shareholders can he adequately looked after hy the Management of the Basra Branch, still less to report that no useful purpose would he served hy the visit oi Mx Critcbley to make a report decided upon as necessary hy • respensible body with full knowledge of their requirements. make clear the composition of this Bank, which being as it is. obliges us as British Subjects protecting British sad Allied Shareholders and Clients to ask again that Mr Critebley, a British-born subject and a practical Banker with experience and knowledge derived from a reeidenee in Mesopotamia, ehouio be forthwith permitted to go te Bagdad in order te enquire into the Me submit that the Felltleal Officer at Basra ia net. ft nave in our previous corrsspondence endeavoured topresent and future interests of our Shareholders and Clients, to oolleet information and make a Report to us, K fbe age and experience of our Representative at Basra do not fit him to supply us with the data and advice that we expect to receive from Mr Critchley, and it would therefore be useless for us to entrust him with such a mission. Under the circumstances, with our views as set out before him, Mr Montagu will we are sure be the first to realise that we are unable to have the pleasure of complying with his desire, but are obliged to press most strongly that our request be granted. yA / 7 Z am, Bear Sir, Your obedient Servant CHAIKUAU His Majesty's Mhder-Seeretary of State for India, Roll tlcal Department, ibdia omcR, S.W. 1I V'\ X tl 3»Il00 • eloitte. Plender,Griffiths &amp; C° SirWilLIam Plender. ^Percival D.GRirFiTMs. * dV*aro Davis. LIONEL MaLTBY. bt.,' Pi ■ m A. E. Cuteortm. CAROl FF, Petroorao 4 Moscow. New York, Chicago, Havana 4 Mexico City, Montreal 4 Vancouver, Buenos Aires, Rio oe Janeiro 4 Tuouman. Johannesburg, Bulawayo, Cape Town, Salisbury 4 Durban. TELEGRAMS DELOfTTE J’f. ZH Telegrams: DELOITTE(AVE) LONDON. Telephone No. 3000 London Wall (3 lines) P.30'72 7th August 1917. ' The Under Secretary of State, Political Department, India Office, S.ff. 1 Sir, IMPERIAL OTTOMAN BANK . BAGDAD BRANCH. I am much obliged for the copy correspondence and telegram send under cover of your note dated the 3rd instant. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, tnj! ip 8 VDrTELEGRAM FROM SIR P. COX, BAGHDAD, DATED 26TH JULY, 1917, (REPEATED TO POLITICAL BASRA). (Received at India Office 27th 11.30a.m.) 2792. Your telegram of 24th Critchley. Please see my No. 2374 of June 30th which was sent after receipt of your despatch of May 2nd. Basra management can look after Bank's interests and Critchley's presence can in my opinion serve no useful purpose. Suggest his being informed accordingly#Deloitte, Plender,Griffiths &amp; C° t) g^SiR William Plcnoer. t ^^^ERCIVAL D.GRIFPITHS. Eowaro Davis. Lionel Maltbv. A.E.Cutforth. P.3007. The Under Secretary of State, Political Department, India Office, S.W. 1 Sir, BRITISH KSTABLISHMUNT OP IMPERIAL OTTOMAN BANK. I am obliged for your Memorandum of yesterday* s date enclosing a copy of communication dated the 24th in stant from the Secretary of State to Sir P. Cox. I am, Sir, your obedient servant, fO Cardiff, &gt;c) PETROGRACjlsf Moscow. ' New York, Chicago, Havana &amp; Mexico City. Montreal &amp; Vancouver. Buenos Aires, Rosario,Tucuman, Rio oe Janeiro &amp; Pernambuco. Johannesburg, Bulawayo^ Cape Town Salisbury &amp;. Durban. telegrams: DELOITTE. Telegrams:- DELOITT^ (AVE) LON DON. Telephone No. 3000 London Wall ( 3 lines) 26th July 1917-OTTOMAN LONDON AGENCY 26 Throgmorton Street, e.c. TELEC RAMS&gt; B I OTTO . LONDON Sir, We confirm our letter of the 26th April an* we shall be glad to hear whether Ur Critchley may now proceed to Boora and Bagdad to enquire into our interest* there. I understand that other British subjects hare been permitted to go to Bagdad. Vjv v 2 am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, CHAIKUAY Sir 7.A.Hlrtzel t K.C.B., I3TDIA 0771CB, Whitehall, ■ S.W.l*2. S A6^ e ft*' X Telegram from Sir P. Cox Dated Baghdad 30th Jane 1917 Received at India Office 2 p.m. (let July), O * 7 A I « V O ^ i / 2374. Your telegram of the 15th June. Imperial Ottoman Bank. Objection to even temporary opening of Baghdad branch remains as before. If it is desired to liquidate any of {? account of) Baghdad branch mentioned in my telegram 885 of 25th March the Basra branch is in a position to do so and I shall always be prepared to give any legitimate assistance. Trust natter may be considered closed.&gt;12) THU UNION DISCOUNT .COMPANY OP LONDON LIMITED. 39, COHNHILL, |3 LONDON. E.C. 9 4 J P H I 24th May 1917 sir. i o &gt; ? i ✓ i f We annex copy of ■ letter we hove received from lx K.A.Zilkha Bagdad, in regard to which we are informed by the secretary, Trading with the Znemy Branch 'Treasury that before business relations can be resumed v/ith a firm in Bagdad, it is necessary for us to obtain from the Foreign Office a statement under the Proclamation of the 16th February 1915 that Bagdad is in friendly occupation within the meaning of that Proclamation. We shall therefore be glad to receive your direc tions in the matter, ^ and remain &amp;c, For The Union discount Company of London Ltd. (Signed) Chao* Bergel ’’orei n dept. Manager. ! Majesty’s Secretary of tate Tor Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office. London S.W.In any further communica tion on thL; subject, pfcase quote [oL[ S'/S. | c address— I | Tlie Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, Ixwidon. — 2280 The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for - ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copscH# of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Sl : , 191 J Reference to previous correspondence Foreign Office: Letter fkpm Description of Inclosure.Draft Paper. Department. INDIA OFFICE, miTEUALL S .'V. The Manager, /6-June, 1917 . Imperial Ottoman Bank, Sir, With reference to your letter of the 31st May, 1917, regarding certain business matters at Bagdad in which the Imperial Ottoman Bank is interested, I am directed oy the Secretary of State for India to suggest that you should forward the documents relating to these matters to your Basra Branch, with instructions to . act in consultation with the Chief Political Officer, Basra^ to whom Mr. Chamberlain is addressing a telegraphic communication on tne subject, The enclosures of your / / letter are herewith returned. JL ■X I % i mDeloitte, Plender,Griffiths &amp; C° William PliNoeR. j ercival D.Griffiths. Eowaro Davis. Lionel Maltby. H*i .II.IBB. A.E. CUTFORTH. No. P. 1716. The Under Secretary or State for India, Political Department, India Office, S.W.1. Sir BRITISH BSTABUSHTIENT OP IMPERIAL OTTOMAN BANK . BAGDAD BRANCH. I am much obliged for the copy of your communication, davted the 2nd instant, addressed to the Chief Political Officer at Basra with its various enclosures. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant,\.v' LONDON AGENCY ^ LONDON AGENCY 26,Throgmorton Street, e LONDON AGENCY. TELEGRAMS:- “biotto,STOCK,londonT TELEGRAMS:- URGENT YwsAm 26tR April, 1917 Dear Sir, We beg to enclose copy of two telegrams reeeiYed from our Basra Agency, and in regard to the second one, we shall be much obliged if you will authorise us to instruct Mr Chanteduc to proceed to Bagdad and take with him Rupees 10 9 000.- for the purpose indicated. from Bagdad amd for whom our Basra Agency found temporary employment. Z am. Dear Sir Your obedient Servant His Majesty^ Under Secretary of State for ZBDIA Whitehall S.W. 1Copy of Telegram from Mr MURAD, I.O.B. Baara dated April 18th 1917 to Direction, I.O.B. London, received April 19th 1917 Bagdad ask us to confirm their telegram of 17th March replying to your telegram Basra Agency concerning our position inform you that our interests in the City are entirely safe, writing. Staff indemn Manager Amon« We have today remitted 10,000 rupees to pay salaries Referring to our telegram of 15th March have no Information Political Office Reid refused passage.• he is unable to resULt Rupees 10,000 Bagdad, can we send them by Chanteduc permitted by Authorities proceed there soon 7 MURAD Copy of telegram from Mr MURAD, I.O.B. Basra, dated 21st April 1917 to Direction, I.O.B. London, received 23rd April 1917 Refer to our letter dated 12th March Ho 169 regarding new &gt; our telegram of 17th Political now writes MURAD1. London agency, 26.Throgmorton street, e.c. telegrams: ‘BIO TT O. STOCK. LONDO AX Sir, / r/zs/r 26th April, 1917 We liare received your letter of the 23rd April (p.1624) acknowledging ours of the 10th and 11th instant regarding the Bagdad Branch, and in reply I hasten to point out that the French and British Shareholders cannot be held responsible and made to suffer for the doings of the Bagdad Branch while under control of the enemies, after the direction and control of the Committee of Paris and London had been forcibly suspended, and the British Director General and French Director General Adjoint had been sent away. To show how complete this control of the Committee in Paris and London has been, we enclose the following extract from a declaration made by Djavid Bey in a stance of the 19th February, when the Ottoman Senate discussed a project of Lae relative to the privileges accorded to the Credit National Ottoman, communicated to us by our Paris Office, as handed to them by their Ministry of Foreign Affairs: Vous saves. Messieurs, que le privilege d'etre la Banque d'Btat appartlent encore 4 la Banque _0ttomane . dont les capltaux sont en majeure parti e anglais et fran^ais. Ces capitaux qui, 4 I'origine, 4taient r4partis par moitie entre ces deux pays devinrent ult4rieurement en grande partie fran$ais. Cependant la Banque Ottomane est dirig6e par deux Com!14s se trouvant I'un 4 Paris et l 1 autre a Londres. Toutes les decisions prises 4 I'^gard de la Banque doivent revetir 1 'approbation de ces deux Comitls. C'est dans ces \VVbusiness can be continued or reconstituted under another name, and also to make arrangements to investigate the pre-war bills, goods eto. v entrusted to us by our London and Manchester clients. opening of our Bagdad Branch, we earnestly request that permission ^or Mr Critchley to proceed to Basra may be granted without delay. v We anticipate that when the full knowledge of the facts, including the important one that there was no intention of re opening under the management found there, is before them, the local Authorities will change their views. I am, Sir Your obedient Servant vWV&lt; CHAIRMAN ' I Sir 7. A. Hlrtz.l, K.C.B., I TIMA 077ICS, Thitahall S.W. 188 ®ni 8 ifQ- &gt;*8 t *tiii 84 In any further communica- icn on this subject, please quote KO.W. S03XU-/ , W- in d address— ^ The Under-Secretary of State, a Foreign Office, London. ■ THE Under lL 3niad:o itiotLsa .A A tlS 019&amp; 'i a* afjrft compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copt£yd of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Letter ^ )in Foreign Office : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^ v^* flayijJU^ Xl+ /rfiF UK ‘ {'( 28 APR 1917 \ Dr V / -41^0^ a Or V ^' ^ § ^ ! Jr\ W * (Similar letter sent to •). Copy \ . 4/1V. »I‘ /■' U/ •• 1C. 9 April ^ 1917. My Lora :- idth reference to yoar letter of the Ibth instfmt, relative to the proposed despatch of . utchley to Bagdad, I am directed by Lord ruCeeil to state that he understands that the decision of the local British Political Authorities not to permit the reepenis oi tme iwnrt^ Ml due te Uie fact ttat the Lapdad branch of your bank has been identified with enemy interests and has been conducting enemy business for the last two and a half years, being recognised as a Government bank by tne Vurkish Authorities# lord Hobert Cecil resets the inconvenience to ^ which this decision has exposed your bank, but he feels convinced that in view of the consiuered opinion expressed by the local british * utliorities, an opinion which is unlikely to be reversea, r.Critchley’s proposed visit to j&gt;agdftd would have merely exposed him unnecessary trouble and expense. I era, ^ y Lord, Your most obedient humble Lcrvant, {Signed M- • The Chairman, Imperial Cttoraan i ank, 26, Thropjnorton btreet, .C. - 1 aA' 1Copy. NO. W.71569/17 ^ (**X3Z4) I IMPERIAL OTTCIviAK BAIMK. 26, Throgmorton Street, London, S.C. 18th April, 1917. Dear Sir:- I am in receipt of your letter of the 16th April, and note that a telegram was despatched to Egypt requesting Mr. Uritchley not to proceed to Mesopotamia. I must express our regret that before this telegram was sent, we here in London were not consulted. Mr. Critchley spent several years as Manager of this Bank in Bagdad. Consequently, he knows the country, and we are confident that his presence in Mesopotamia could be made useful. We have already received requests from sundry British firms to ascertain the fate of Bills at Bagdad which they had entrusted to us ior col-Lection oefoie ono War, representing goods exported from this country. Apropos of the‘whole matter, however, we oeg to refer to our letters of the 11th and 13th April to the Foreign Office. We would add, however, that it occurs to us that when the political Officer recoimended the branch to oe closed he did not know the steps that haa oeen taken from here to send Britishers out, and that he no doubt had some idea that leaving the Bank open meant leaving Sir Ronald Graham, K.G.M.G., Foreign Office.I leaving it under the Staff which apparently he found there, and that was not intended. I am, &amp;c., (Signed) sessoorough. chairman. • p.S. We received this instant a letter from Messrs. Samuel Montagu and company, of which we enclose a copy.baimiel Montagu and Company. 60, Old Broad Street, G.P.G. Box 5£5. London, E.C. The Imperial Ottoman Bank. Lear Sirs:- We siiall de obliged by your telegraphing to your agent at Bagdaa to: ,f pay the American Consul Seizer Bagdad the equivalent of £300 a/c Jewish relief. Instruct Consul American funds for April May June consequent Elkers unaole continue Jewish relief’ 1 . We enclose our cheque for £300 and await your confirmation with note of telegraphic charges. Thanking you for your kind attention Yours faithfully, (Signed) somuel Montagu and company. &gt; wr In any further communication the subject, please quote No&gt; W. 76894/17. ai ect, please quote W.76894/17 1624 Foreign Office and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, April 16th, 1917 London. Sir: I am directed by Mr.Secretary Balfour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter, No.P,1472, of the loth instant, relative to the disinclination oi the British Authorities at Bagdad to permit the reopening of the local branch of the Imperial Ottoman Bank, and to state, in reply, that he concurs in the terns of the draft answer which Mr.Secretary Chamberlain proposes to return to the Chairman of the Bank. I am Sir Your most obedient humble Servant The Under-Secretary of State * India Office.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote N'. address - / . rGr and address— The Under-Secretary of State; Foreign Office, London. INK Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the i nder-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop Cftfof the under-meutioned paper£ r Foreign Office, , 1917. Reference to'Previous correspondence : , Letter Foreign i^mce : from ^ / Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject.MINUTEop: • W.71569/17 ^pril 16th, 1917 Sir:- N. I am directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to inform you that he has been advised by His Majesty's High Commissioner for Egypt that the Manager of your branch at Alexandria had been instructed to proceed to Bagdad. In view of the fact that in present circumstances the British Authorities at Bagdad have closed the branch of your Bank at Bagdad and propose to keep it closed until the end of the war - a course which has been approved by His Majesty's Government - Mr. Balfour has telegraphed to dir A. f/ingate requesting him to ask Mr. Critchley not to proceed to Mesopotamia since his presence there would, for the above reason, serve no useful purpose. Balfour has received a telegram from the Chief Political Officer in Mesopotamia, dated the.10th v j instant, conveying a message to you from Mr. imion to | the effect that the staff of the Bank at Bagdad are I am at the same time to inform you that Mr. \ all well. I fan, dir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, fBiqned) R Graham. toe Chairman, Imperial Ottoman Bank, Throgmorton street,In any further communication on the subject, please quote r ‘ 148 7 no. W.69924/17. Foreign Office and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, April 12th, 1917. London. Sir:- In reply to your letter, P.1239, of the 3rd instant, relative to the establishment of a branch of the ottoman Bank at Bagdad, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to state that he concurs in the view of Mr. secretary Chamberlain that the Bagdad branch of this Bank should remain closed until the end of the v/ar. Copy tc Indsa I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Under secretary of State, India office.7th SERIES, No. 34. IS) CONFIDENTrAf.. SUMMARY OF INTELLIGENCE. 3.30 p.m., Monday, thk 9th April, 1917. * ^ ^ Tl/R k £ y 4* * * «**«»*- «•««-, direc &lt; to?of b ( e h i ^,h PPOi K nte ? Mi u ister ° f Finance - Jafid 1 % resigned the post of mana-ino- *~ ■ 1I “'' i - m «fV. ftttnJi 1 ! v 1 , niStU !' n f , Fi T' C ? lnade interesting statements in the Chamber about the whiehTs Chieliv U F, “'h“ n't At PreSC,lt hnncrial Ottoman Banlr the capital of Turkov' n 'll F xk’ a ? d ’ t0 SOme exten t, English, is the only privileged bank in r P , n out break ot war the French and English directors had to leave l urUey, and the management of the bank was handed over to Turkish bank officials/ Uelations with this bank have been correct during the war, but will undergo an alteration^ at er the conclusion of peace; the fact that the privileges of the bank expire in 1924 wil be taken into consideration, but up to that date the Government will not interfere with these privileges. 'I he new Ottoman National Credit Bank is not a State bank, and its prerogatives will in no way run counter to those of the Ottoman Bank. It is possible that after 1924 the new bank will obtain the prnileges of the Ottoman Bank and be allowed to issue bank notes. Lp to the closing day, 28th February, the shares of the National Credit Bank were in great demand. A law was proposed and accepted by the Chamber authorizing the Government to subscribe a large sum. The share capital of the bank is four million 1 urkish pounds, and as 50 per cent, of this sum must be paid up, it is assumed that the Government will subscribe about one million Turkish pounds in order to complete the required amount. (See Summary of the 16th March.)LONDON AGENCY, 26.Throgmorton street, e g. TELEGRAMS: 8IOTTO, STOCK. LONDON.” Bear Sir, / / &lt;&gt;//: 11th April, 1917 The Official Supervisor of this Bank has sent us a copy of your letter of the 3rd April on the subject of the Bagdad Branch. This comes as a shock and a surprise to us, as after the occupation of Basra by British forces, the India Office authorised this Bank to reopen its Branch at that place, and if we are permitted to trade with the Port of Bagdad we cannot understand the refusal to permit us to do so at the Commercial Centre itself. The Proclamation issued to the inhabitants of Bagdad laid stress upon facilitating trade and commerce. The Bagdad Branch of this Bank, opened in 1892, was for very many years the only Institution there with cm Office in London facilitating commercial British business both of the district round about and the transit business with Persia, and the help it gave to British trade during all these years was most considerable. Thus it seems to us that the closing of this Branch is not in accord* ance with the intention expressed in the Proclamation. Vvre the Imperial Ottoman Bank a Bank financed by Turkish money, a prohibition against its Branch at Bagdad being allowed to do business during the currency of the War would be obviously onable, but as is well known the great majority of the Capital3. We shall he obliged if you will inf ora us if the reason for the recommendation that the Bagdad Branch of the Imperial Ottoman Bank should remain closed until the end of tne War j.s tnat sa it is undesirable that the name 'Imperial Ottoman Bank' should appear. I am, Bear Bir, Your obedient Servant, CHAIRMAN ?.3 Your latter of the 3rd April haring been addressed to the foreign Office, wo hare renturod to s.nd a copy of this letter to them. His Kajesty's Secretary of st ?3? T . for IHDIA, INDIA OffICS, rVY. *j^ ^1,61 Ud'- Zl SoW • 1^MOTiow^ inNnnwAr, pwrv LONDON AGENCY, 26.THROGMORTON STREET. E C. r /•//sro// XOtb April, 1917 'BIOTTO, STOCK. LONDON.' I Sir V« to hand you herewith copy of th# following tologra&amp;e : Our tologron of 12th March to our Basra Agency, and their reply of the 15th idem, Their further telegram of 4th A$ril, Telegram from Mr Oritchley, our Manager at Alexandria, dated 9th April. With regard to the laet named, we would explain that we instructed Mr Critchley to proceed to Bagdad together with Mr Heid, another British Subject by birth, and as Mr Critchley ^ pfter embarking at fort Said ba* on receipt of an official communication decided to return to Alexandria, wer ehall be obliged if you will give us further information ori the subject. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant for XMMXA*Copy of telegram from Imperial Ottoman Sank, London to I«0«23* Basra dated 12tL karcL 191 OU*in leave from Authoritlea to aacertain position Bagdad Branch as aobn as possible and report fully. We authorise Reid proceed there if permitted.- Ottoman Bank Copy of telegram from Imperial Ottoman Bank, Basra, dated 15th Larch to X*0»£« London, received 10th Larch 1917 Political wired ha^dad for information communication not expected before ten days Be id promised passage soon political intimate Bagdad Manager must be British probably Supervisor unrequired,- Copy of telegram from Mr Murad, Manager of‘‘'the Imperial Ottoman Bank at Basra, dated 4th April, to the I.O^B.London, received loth April 1917 Understand unofficially question Bagdad referred Secretary of State Office closed Bncaisee nll«- MBBAP Copy of telegram from Lr Oritchley, Lanager of Imperial Ottoman Bank Alexandria, dated Cairo 9th April, to London, received 10th April 1917 Embarked Port Said Sunday, but owing important official communication disembarked came Cairo and journey postponed,writing reasons, returning Alexandria. - CRITCHLBY[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Governme nt. and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unles s required for official use.] Deaypher* Sir R, '/ingato (Cairo) April GtAu 1917, D* 1,55.p.n, April 9th, 1917, R, 4,55,ppn, ] T 0 w* 399, (R), Your telegran Nc^ 364, I have induced Mr, Critohlay who wag already on board steamer net to proceed. In course of interview he informed me that he was telegraphing to his London Beard and would write to them asking for permission to visit Basrah,Ano at J Deloitte, Plender,Griffiths &amp; C° SirWilliam Plendbr. Percival D.Griffiths. »var o Davis. Maltby. &gt; . Chevalier. A.E.Cutforth. Caroi ff, PetroqrAO A Moscow. New York, Chicago, Havana a Mexico City, Montreal a Vancouver. Buenos Aires, Riooe Janeiro a Tuouman. Johannesburg, Bulawayo, Cafe Town, Salisbury a Durban. P9 TELEGRAMS DELOITTE Telegrams:- DELOITTE(AVE) LONDON. Telefhone No. 3000 Lonoon Wall (3 lines) 10th April 1917 . Th^ Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, S.W. 1. Sir, BRITISH £STABU SHIIE1TT OF IMPERIAL OTTOMAN BAIIK, Bagdad Branch, I am very much obliged for the copy of your letter dated the 3rd instant to the Foreign Office which you have hindl v sent me and I observe its contents. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, i/.X- £0 IN AO) ^\1This Document is the Property of Hi/ Britannic Majesty s Government. and shoald bo returned to the Foreign O ffice when done with unless required tor official use.] (71569/17) FIL 1 &amp; O iiLY. Cypher telecrMia tc yir K. 1/innate (Cairo) Foreign Office, April 7th, 1917,.. Z.lh.V.n, Nc. 364, Ycur telegram Me, 361 (of April 2nd). British ant her i ties at Bagdad have reccrnendcd that branch of Ottoman Bank at Bagdad he closed until the end of the war and this has been approved by His Imjesty's Government, In the circumstances Mr. Critcliley's visit to Bagdad would serve nc useful purpose and he should bo requested net tc proceed.Ttec. Ll (Aj&gt;ri£ Formally acknowledged To Under Secretary Secretary of State Committee ....L... Under Secretary . J Secretary of State SUBJECT.1 Immediate and Confidential. ^ 5 2- b//p//.y Reference :—Letter ^ from Forei 9 n Office The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of telegram , as marked in the ^mtargin^ * Foreign Office,±liiLL;( *3 f f r. A v«&gt;| fc V' &lt;W r tim FRUi: SIR P. cox, BAGDAD, DATED 25TH LAM, received at. India Office 5 p.m. 26th 'arch '17. IS. (iw. T.885. Bagdad branch of Ottcraan Bank. Case clitiers troiii that of Basra branch, — la. latter cane under our control few days after outbreak of war before it had opportunity for hostile trade. Bagdad branch had been doing enemy business up to date of our arrival and was recognised by Turks as Government bank. It has no cash at all and assets in Bagdad are insigftijLcant. Liabilities amount to about £133,000, made up as follows in round figures. (1) to British and allied creditors £44,500; (£) to Ottoman Bank £6,500; (3) to inhabitants of Bagdad £57,700; (4) to monies collected on account of London and Paris branches £2^,300. host of above have been, received by bank in Ottoman paper money of which market value is only one-fifth of face value (one group undecipherable) if head office of bank were required or allowed to liquidate these liabilities in cash now it would have’effect of enhancing value of Turkish paper ''Which is presumably not desired. I recommend that Bagdad branch remain closed until end of the war. Insuructions requested. Addressed to Foreign, India, repeated to Secretary of State and Basra.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100056379988.0x000003_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/531/1</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100056379988.0x000003</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/531/1</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 74/1915 Pt 4 'Mesopotamia: Imperial Ottoman Bank, Baghdad Branch'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1917/1921</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-04-25T10:32:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (210 folios)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This part contains correspondence and India Office Minute Papers relating to the Imperial Ottoman Bank in Mesopotamia [Iraq], mainly concerning the Baghdad branch.It includes papers regarding:The decision of the British Government, on the recommendation of local British political authorities, to close the Baghdad branch of the Imperial Ottoman Bank for the duration of the First World War, on the grounds that the Bank was identified with enemy interests, and it continued to do enemy business up to the date of the British occupation of Baghdad, and was recognised by the Turkish authorities as a Government bank.The proposal of the London Agency of the Bank to send their representative Mr Critchley to Baghdad to enquire into the interests of the Bank’s shareholders and clients in Mesopotamia, and their later proposal to send Mr H R Saltmarsh and Mr E E Humphries instead of Critchley.The proposal of the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, that the Baghdad branch of the Bank should be allowed to re-open.Permission being granted to the Imperial Ottoman Bank at Basra to correspond with its Constantinople [Istanbul] Office.The visit of Lord Goschen, a director of the Imperial Ottoman Bank, to Mesopotamia.A query by Drysdale and Company Limited about whether the Imperial Ottoman Bank at Baghdad was ‘a safe and sound’ institution, in response to a customer asking the company to accept payment at the Imperial Ottoman Bank in Baghdadthe proposal that the Baghdad and Mosul branches of Bank should be permitted to settle transactions dating back to the period before the British occupation.The correspondence largely consists of correspondence between the India Office and the following: the Foreign Office; Sir William Plender, appointed by the Treasury as Supervisor of the Imperial Ottoman Bank’s London Agency; the Imperial Ottoman Bank, London Agency; the Viceroy of India, Foreign Department; and the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad (telegrams addressed from ‘Political, Baghdad’). The file also includes copies of Foreign Office correspondence with the London Agency of the Imperial Ottoman Bank, and Sir Reginald Wingate, High Commissioner, Egypt.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ottoman Bank</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Egypt</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Baghdad</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Basra</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Mosul</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Constantinople</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100056379988.0x000003#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>