<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000376_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-08-15T10:27:45.918Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">BRITISH CONSULATE MUSCAT PILE NO: 6/36 NAME OP PILE: FOREIGN INTERESTS: IRAQ MINISTER’S PROPOSED VISIT TO MUSCATw VI FOREIGN INTKHh^ST^ * IRJiQ (1) Iraq Ministers propose visit to Muscat* From To Previous No.From H.M's Ambassador, ba^dad. To H*M* s Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London. No • 286 Repeated to Political Kesident, bushire. no. 22 Rated 10 th received 11 th December 1935. For reasons of health Nuri Pasha is thinking of going from Basra to Bombay and back in Slow Mail visiting Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat en route. He proposes to make short calls on Rulers at these places and to assure them of the friendly interest of ’Iraq Government. In particular he wishes to dispel fears of Shaikh of Kuwait that ’Iraq has designs on his territory. Plan appears to me to be good and I hope it will be possible to arrange facilities.r* r* Telegram H 35 ^rom Political Heeident, ±iuahlre» h.M f a Ambaaeador, .Baghdad* TO Repeated to h.M's Secretary of State for xndia, London• Copy by air Government of India, foreign and Political Department, flew Delhi* No* 1009 Dated 12th December 1935* - . w ■ ‘ Your telegram No* 286 to Foreign office Subject to His Mgj esty’s Government’s approval I concur that plan is a good one* Please telegraph when Nuri Pasha proposes leaving -Basra and I will instruct Poll tical Agent* to arrange facilities.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000376_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/175</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000376</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/175</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 6/36 Foreign Interests: Iraq Minister's Proposed Visit to Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-29T22:21:08</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (4 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 6; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of correspondence between British officials regarding a proposed visit to Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat by the Iraqi politician, Nuri Pasha [Nūrī al-Sa‘īd].</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>State visits</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000376#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>