<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000133_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:13:40.282Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">7471 Wt 23481/P 215 2000 8.38 INDIA OFFICE, POLITICAL (EXT) Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). \&amp; (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, ToEepeated to Government of India, External Affairs Department, ' ' Political Agent* Bahrein Dated 2nd May, 1940 No. P* 2.2483/40 I shall he glad to receive your ohservations on the enclosed copy of a letter from Petroleum Concessions Ltd* dated 29th April ) regarding the employment of foreign personnel by the Company in Qatar. Do you consider that Company might he given general authority to employ Portuguese Goanese in place of British Indians if their requirements and the quality of the labour available justify this course? Subject to your views I would accept the Company’s explanation of the employment of American and French personnel, on the understanding that the approval of H»M.G. continues to be sought in individual cases. F A Issue of the above message has been authorised. -mm 4 &gt; * mw&amp;ot*■■■■Hi -b © GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETT [xV. —This is an ORIGINAL MFSSAGF y sent by post to sa^e telcgrnphio expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be trroied, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sa e time and formalities it is worded a d signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Agent, Bahrain. To L No, C/591 - 10/3 Political Resident, Bushire* Dated 6th May Reference India Office Express letter Ro. P.^.2483/40 dated the 2nd May 1940 regarding the employment of foreign personnel by Petroleum Concessions Limited in Qatar. i V 2* The CoB$&gt;any*s letter attached to the India Office Express letter under reference mis-states facts considerably. What has -i ts £ occurred is this. On the 10th of April 1940 I received a request for a Ro Objection Certificate to be telegraphed to Bombay on behalf of a Portugese subject whom the Company wished to employ in Qatar. I ascertained that this man was to be employed as a clerk and in view of the terms of the Political Agreement between His Majesty^ Government and the Company ■ ■ ' ■ ' '! ■ ! , and in the absence of any special reasons for the employment of a Portugese clerk I declined to issue a Ro Objection Certi ficate. Mr. Packer came to see me on this subject and appeared b. P -400S&amp;P ,M 480 26 7-34 2 0 &gt;00 '2 to be under the belief that the relevant clause in the Political Agreement was a dead letter# I pointed out to him that on one occasion the Company had asked the permission of His Majesty’s Government to employ a French geologist on the grounds that there were no suitable British geologists available and that similarly the Company had sought permission for American drillers to work in Qatar. His Majesty’s Government had agreed in view of the assurances given by the Company. (I might have added that we had similarly agreed, locally to a few Iraqis who had been trained by the Iraq • petroleum Company being employed In Qatar to Instruct and control local unskilled labour). But this case was different. No technical knowledge was required and there were literally thousands of British Indian subjects looking for clerical work. I could see no reason therefore for facilitating the employment of a Portugese. 3. It is not true to say that I referred to the 'large numbers of Indian employees who are Portugese Goanese'. It is I believe a fact that half a dozen Goanese are employed as house servants in the Qatar Camp and naturally no objection has been raised owing to the difficulty of obtaining British Indian s rvants* 4* I do not think that the Company should be given general authority to employ Portugese Goanese in place of British Indians. Neither for the purpose of the Political Agreement nor for any other purpose can a Portugese be regarded as a British subject as suggested by the Company, but as indicatec above if they wish to employ a Portugese house servant in the absence of suitable British Indian applicants it would only be necessary for the Local Manager to explain this to the Political Agent in order to receive the requisite No Objection Certificate. For the rest the Company should be required definitely /-*«*► 2 &gt; *'• definitely , as suggested in the India Office Express letter, to seek the approval of His Majesty*s Government in each individual case in which an American Is to be employed* Political Agent, Bahrain*CONFIDENTIAL BAHRAIN, DO/CAM.5/1955 Dear /'i* X s / 'Vv: PERSIAN GULF. 7th May, 1940. m P.G.L. - FOREIGN EliPLOYESS. I mentioned in my last monthly report to London the Political Departments views on the recruitment of foreign clerks and servants with particular reference to Portuguese Goans who have been very frequently engaged by the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co., Bombay, on our behalf. I also brought It to their notice that comment has been passed on the necessity or otherwise to Introduce American and French geologists into Qatar, although M No Objection Certificates” have always been supplied. I now understand the Company propose to approachj the India Office on both questions. Meanwhile I have asked the A.I.O.C.,Borabay, not to recruit any more Portuguese Goans. H. Weightman,Esq.,I.C.S., The Agency, Bahrein.CONFIDENTIAL. 1 i i The Hon’ble the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1# Hie of wtate for india, London 2* the Secretary to the Government of India in the -Internal Affaire lepartment# Liisla* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). v/ Copy forwarded with compliments to Political Agent, v Bahrain, for information. with the remark that the Political hesident a*£rees with the consents contained in paragraph 4« British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated loth Pay 1940 * Name and Date. Reference to previous correspondence : Subject. Bahrain Expreee Letter Ho* C/39i-ip/5* dated 6th my lM0 - H.h b- Aayloyimn t of foreign per sonnel by in /TELEGRAMS : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED Reference conversation between Mr. Y/ei girt man and Mr. Packer on the 19th May. Mr. Akin arrived by B.I. steamer on the 20th May and proceeded to Q,atar on the 21st. He has a visa valid for Qatar for any number of journeys un to 8th December 1940 issued by your office when Mr. Akin was here last year. Mr. Akin is an American subject, and will be taking over as Head Driller in Qatar from Mr. 0.J.ROwntree. ORS : i Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) iw, C.B.E. dI, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) er, C.B.E. ilbenkian (formerly Armenian) Kessler (Dutch) i B. Lloyd my (French) side! (U.S.A.) ellers BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF PCL/AL.1/6762 H.B.M*s Political Agent Bahrain. 21st May, 1940. Dear Sir, MR. GILBERT NESBITT AKIN Yours faithfully, For 8c on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSION LIMITED MANAGER. ACMS. 44. (Designation) GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). Confidential — This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL lohich provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated^ on receipt, with the same expedition as if it hod been telegraphed. To save t ime and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature Of a responsible officer of the Department.'] ^, ine Political Agency, No. 10/3• Bahrain, ^ted ^25th May 1940 x2@c To The Political Resident, Bushire* laployme nt of foreign personnel by Petrole um Con- cessions Limited at Qatar . 3£y v A Reference correspondence resting with your Printed letter No. 296-8 dated the 16th May 1940. #&gt;» 2. An American named Mr. Akin arrived in Bahrain on the 20th May by steamer and proceeded to Qatar on the 21st May on the strength of a visa for Qatar issued last December by this office when Mr. Akin was on a visit to Petroleum Concessions Limited 1 s operations near Zekrit. I am informed that Mr. Akin is to take over duties permanently as head driller in Qatar. I recommend that the India Office be invited to call on Petroleum Concessions Limited for an explanation for sending Mr. Akin to Qatar for permanent employment there without obtaining the prior consent of His Majesty’s Govern- ment* ^ ? 3. I have today telegraphed to you with reference to another American subject named Mr. Keck, on whose behalf the Consul at Baghdad has enquired whether a visa for Qatar may be granted. Enquiries indicate that Mr. Keck also is marked for permanent em ployment in Qatar by Petroleum Concessions Limited. In my telegram I have recommended that a visa be refused pending the approval of (Signature) His /- wmzmBSBKS5&amp;! ESBKBi jO 4. The eixplanation invariably put forward by Petroleum Concessions Limited when wishing to send Americans to Qatar is that there are no British drillers. In point of fact I understand that there are British subjects who have been trained as drillers in Iraq but that these men have no experi ence so far of deep drilling such as is necessary in Qatar. I recommend that the Company should be called on to say whetner they are not able to send at least two of them at a time to Qatar to be trained in deep drilling. It would then be possible in future for the Company to carry out their obligations under the Political Agreement. 5. ihe action proposed above does not involve any impediment to the Company's operations and it is recommended solely for the purpose of drawing the Company's attention sharply to the need for honouring their undertaking. Political Agent, Bahrain&gt; J TELEGRAMS : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED ORS : Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) w, C.B.E. &gt;1, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) ;r, C.B.E. Ibenkian (formerly Armenian) BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF Kessler (Dutch) B. Lloyd ny (French) idel (U.S.A.) illers PCL/SAC/1992 CONFIDENTIAL To H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, lune, 1940. 1 1940 AMERICAN DRILLERS - MR. SCHOLDER We are expecting a driller named Scholder about the middle of June who will be arriving direct from America. This driller is for service in Q^tar from one to three years, and he is urgently required to complete the drilling crew of the second well. It is probable that a No Objection Certificate will be called for by the Consul at Baghdad or Basrah to permit of the issue of Bahrain and Qatar visas. We shall be grateful if any suitable action can be taken to expedite the issue of such visas. As regards the recruitment of American (foreign staff) our London principals have presumably referred the case of Mr.Scholder to the India Office (vide para 3 of the Political Agreement) as we have drawn their attention some time ago^the desirability of coming to a permanent understanding with H.M f s G. on the question of such engagements. We believe the matter is now under correspondence. Yours faithfTilly, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED. £ rA y A' ^ ( y t-LJ £ L L (S.r.-d^V 0 ; \ TL ! Confidential No. C/469 - 10 / 3 . I he Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: — The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. c has U Lonour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s) ror information. be granted^ntil thi t India Offic^iSttaate^hat't. h h0U ^ d n0t approved the employment of Mr. slhSdS in Qatar. 7 V6 The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf, Dated the 6th June 1940. Reference to previous correspondence: Descmption of Enclosure^ Name and Date. Letter No.PCL/SAC/1992 dat the 5th June 1940 from the Manager, Petroleum Coneess- 1 ions Limited, Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. nr \ 0 _ Subject. C 9 Employment of American personnel by P.C.L. in Qatar.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, WYTR BWftT. aFTPATRS DEPARTMENT. ( [N. B.—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched i\ From To BRITCONSUL, BUSHIRE. (Repeated - Secretary of State for India, London. ) ( - Political Agent, Bahrain.^ ) D. 2509-N/40. Dated Cf (A June 1540. Reference India Office letter No. f P.Z.2483/40 of the 2nd May. A 2, So far as the Government of India are concerned, they have no objection to the Company being given general authority to employ Portuguese Goanese in place of British Indians on the lines proposed. The issue of the above has been authorised. 0.6 .DflFP — ] ia7«^P— ra.i —■M.R.'ti * on ooo.PETkOLKUu a.PAR13B3»iT tvWJU*»Ufci IJj&amp;jL XmHiX'i i. f (MIHEo MiPARTMSIT) ,vf/ Pi /E.3/Irc t DKAH KiTAMiXY ST. , MILLBANK, a. .1. S9th May, 1940, Denp reel. Qatar Gil Concession , We have had submitted to us by the Iraq etroleum ompany Limited their 1940/1941 Drilling Programme* Chia included a proposal to continue drilling at Tatar with the present rig but to increase to two rigs as soon as equipment can be obtained* We learn unofficially from the Company that they would not object if we asked them not to increase their drilling at Qatar but they prefer I to have a definite instruction in order to counteract any pressure from U.8.A* members of the development company (Petroleum Development Ltd.} For our part we feel that in present circumstances there is no justification for additional development work in Qatar and that we ought not to authorise the purchase of the steel requirements for the extra rig. I should be glad to know whether you see any objection to our iforming the Company accordingly, X have written in similar term* to Baggallay. Yours sincerely. eel, Esq* , Inala office. (agd .j y. .otarllng.CONFIDENTIAL. r No. 406-3 of 1940 V s j^ I The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (£). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated...tV?**^ 1940Tel egrazn 1'r ora Q,* Political Resident, Buahire. Secretary of State for India, London, flopy Ly post Political Agent, Banrain. Ho. 388 Dated 15 th June 1940. Political -agent reports American naraed AKIH arrived Bahrain by steamer liay 20th and proceeded Qatar May 21st on visa for Qatar issued last December when he visited Company’s operations near LeLrit. AKIN is reported to have been engaged as head driller. I suggest Petroleum Concessions be called upon for explanation for sending AKIH to Qatar lor p e rraan en t eiap 1 oy men t w 11 ho ur ob tai ni n g s anc t i on. Petroleum Concessions liave also applied for Ho Objection certificates for two other Americans KLCK and SCHOUDBR for Qatar. I am refusing it ■i ) these until approval to their engagement has been obtained. BritconsulGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, -, Department, oafidential t^' This is an OlilGIiS AL MESSAGE, sent by post to $a r e telegraphic expense and undue use of the inres, bar intended to be treated, on receipt^ with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sa e time and formalities it is tvoraed a d sig / ed as if it had been so despatched,] From to Political Agent, Bahrain. Polltical Hesident, Bushire. No* C/512-10/5 Dated 20th June li&amp;b Keierence your telegram I5o. 383 dated tae 15th June 1940. P.C.L. American employees for tatar. 2* leek ciirived in Bahrain on the 27th May ana proceeded to Jafc&amp;r oelore I knew of ius arri'val on the strength of &amp; visaffor Bahrain and Qatar is sue a by the Consul, Basra. I a- us informed -tn Basra tnat the Qat.ar visa was granted on receipt of a telegram from the Consul, Baghdad, stating that the American Legation there had made a special request for it. Political Agent, Bahrain.■-&lt;^111 uminMi' TsfcL:.:. Telegram From To No. f, Q M . Political Resident, Bushire. Political ^gent, Bahrain. 416. Dated and received the 21st June 1940. Following from India Office No.3076 dated June 18th begins. 'Your telegram No.388 dated June 15th. Americans &gt; Company have referred to general perri 1938 (vide Political Resident’s telegram July 8th 1938 No. T/172) for employment of four American drillers in Qatar and suggest that to avoid unnecessary correspondence it might suffice if their manager in Bahrain keeps Political Agent informed of any changes in American personnel drilling i staff. in Qatar. ^ - Tl See my Express letter June 11th, In present circumstances I am disposed to agree unless you see any objection'. Ends. 2. I have no objection if Akin, Keck and Scholder are included among the four American drillers referred t-o in India Office telegram No.1189 dated June 28th 1938. confirm that they are not extra men. PleaseLIST OF AMERICAN SUBJECTS EMPLOYEES OF PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT( QATaR) LTD. STATIONED AT DUKHAN CAMP - QATAR. &gt;r 4 ^ ^ v u* s '&lt;S J Mr. N.T.Langh^m - Geologist Mr. G.N.Akin - Tool Pusher (and Driller) Mr. C.H.Looper - Driller Mr. H.C.Keok - Driller En route from America l Mr. J.Scholder - Driller Bahrain, 24th June, 1940.Telegram 'Q' From Politica 1 Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire Wo. Dated 24th June 1940* yV Your telegram Wo. 416 dated 21st June. 2. Persons named in paragraph 2 are replacements for original American drillers. There is one additional American geologist employed by Company in Qatar. Political -TELEGRAMS : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN PETROLEUM IS : adman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) C. B.E. D. S.O., D.S.C. (French) C.B.E. enkian (formerly Armenian) ssler (Dutch) . Lloyd (French) el (U.SA) PCI/SAC/2045 !&gt;■ CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE SIGNS LIMITED BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF B7th June, 1940. To H.B.M*s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, MR. J. SCHOLDER Reference your No.1334-29/14 dated 13th. June 1940, we have received a telegram from our Baghdad office pressing us for the No Objection Certificate, and we shall be glad to be informed, when convenient, of the present situation as we have one Driller short and No.2 Well has already been started. If you are now in a position to issue a No ^/ctPbjection Certificate we shall be grateful if a telegram can be sent to the British Consul, Baghdad, at our expense. NO * A 3 Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED I ! !&gt; ACMTelegram Q.T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain* To Political Resident, Bushire* No. I8&amp; \ Dated 29th June 1940. ^ \ My telegram No. 199 dated 24th June. Petroleum Concessions Limited request No Objection Certificate for Bahrain be cabled to Consul Baghdad for J. Scholder American driller. Collect. - Political - Iforwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, cal Department, India Office. copy has been sent to. I , Air ..b y-g— M ail. ') Xhr F nrn ign -flm mTyr^overnmiTy^ The Political RestdrotHm^hc PersraTr-GtfTfr^ Wt.27899/P.287* y otlos «U1 i?l«» U f obMniit ’^1 | •&lt;i# ^14 4ufi om French id* me ./ ./ 3679b INDIA OFFICE, M 5 i®!' 7 Political DepaktmEnt. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so desj&gt;atched.) From Secretary of State To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Repe ^* d „5 0 Tr 1 rH» Political Agent, Bahrein, Repeated to Government of India, ]Jated External Affairs Department, llth June, 1940. 4 No. 2&gt;4U 3278/1940. J r^J \ ^ Reference your memorandum of the 16th May, ho.£96--, \ Employment 6 of 6 foreign personnel in ^tar by Petroleum Concessiono Ltd A copy of a further letter from the Company is enclosed horew/ith Please let me have your views on their proposals regarding the four American drillers (reference your predecessor's telegram 6 of the 8th July, 1938 No.T/172) and the geologist Langham. • LL The issue of the above has been duly authorised. (Sgd.) R.,2.3278/1940. ^Jectioa im ificiplt, ia ^ obuiniii? l m, ste., fani necM»ii) .a. eliO’iilfi i^iaufcl me or Kmeft or«d. sleepily, ,) n. PEEL Petroleum Conoessions Limited, King's Head Hotel, Horsham, Sussex. 6th June, 1940. &lt; i Lear Mr. Peel, y Reference the last paragraph of your letter P.Z.2999/40 dated the 30th May. Permission to employ four American drillers in Qatar was accorded in India Office letter P.3.4804/38 dated the $th^ July, 1938. Nothing was said in that letter about obtaining the approval of H.M.&amp;. in each individual case, and I suggest that, to save unnecessary correspondence, it might be sufficient if our Manager at Bahrain keeps 4,h@ Political Agent, Bahrain informed of any changes in the American personnel of our drilling staff. The American drillers employed at the moment are: G. N. Akin H. C. Keck C.H. Looper and a fourth man, J. Scholder, is now en route to Qatar to replace J.C. Mason. India Office letter quoted above does not cover the employment of American geologists at Qatar, and I am sorry to say that the necessity of obtaining H.M.G.*s approval was overlooked when Noel Ihomas Langham, aged mo, was engaged 1 s year and sent to Qatar in March, 1939. he should be greatly obliged if this omission may be overlooked, and approval accorded ex post facto. We would like to keep Langham where ne is, as he is doing very well there, as you will see from our Chief Geologists report on him (copy att^acjaed). Yours sincerely, jk - ^ (Sd.) H.H. Wheatley, D. Peel, Esq., idia Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.•y\© COPY* T*han&lt;xhQm Xi0VJ employed a© Resident Geologist in atar. Southeastern Arabia. Ue are well pleased with this man and 'believe that he offers considerable promise. He is especially well qualified in the mechanical or petroleum engineering phase of a Resident Geologist’s job. He is conscientious, hardworking and possesses the a ;ililies to cope with local conditions in extremely remote areas where ’’guts 5 * and initiative ar essential. Langham has extremely nice personality and is well liked by everyone.S/44. (Designation) [N.B. This ts an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.’] No. To s©i-s of im^ ate lummu'™ 6 istwuiy 1940# auenxxx Hie Majesty's Secretary of state for India, London» Repeated The Secretary to the Government of India. External Affaire Department, Simla* ■n £ vouiThe Political Agent, Bahrain* Keterence ^=r XXJUULXXXk J with ooiiy of telegrars referred to below* Your Sxp raaa Letter Ho*i **a*SB 78/1940 dated llth ^une 1940, ' ■ - . ; - ■ r • ’ ' ■ ' ' , ' ' '■' 1 1 Y,' ..: . received nth July 1940* Asericane employed by Petroleum Oonoessions Limited in N&amp;tar* V Z. You will have seen, vide vsy telegram Ho*439, dated the 25th Tune 1940, that X have no objection to employment of Mesere ^ Akin, Keok,Looper and soholder as replacementa for four Americans, whose employment was approved in 1938* 3* In regard to Geologist* In view of explanation now given by Company I have no objection to ex post facto approval being given* sd* a*0*Prior* Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Attccted Resident Seore in the 1 \A (Signature)—Tele grain From Political Resident, Bushire. To Secretary of State for India, London* Copy 'by post to Political Agent, Bahrain, Ho.439* Dated 25th June 1940, Reference your telegram No,3076 of 19th June, Americans in Qatar .» L * ^ ^ / r 2, Political Agent reports drillers now being imported are replacements for original Americans and I have therefore no objection, 3* There is one additional American geologist employed by Company in Qatar* W,L* Britconsul,TELEGRAMS PETCONCESS, BAHREIN PETROLEUM | CONCESSIONS LIMITED •RS : Sadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) rS**. Cr.LEa-H- ro/VES , D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) , C.B.E. jenkian (formerly Armenian) essler (Dutch) , ? c &lt;3 I. Lteyd. L.M LEFKOY ''J.S.A.) PCL/GAA.3/2151 To H. B. M.*s Politioal Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF M. J. A. mm (FRENCH) We have been asked to inform you that the abovenamed has resigned from the Board of Directors of Petroleum Concessions Ltd. and its Subsidiaries. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of BUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED MANAGER ACMFrom Telegram M Q fr To Repeated No. Dated India Office, London. Political Resident, at Kuwait Bahrain Petroleum Company (P.$. Bahrain ?) 7849 7th December 1940. Qatar Oil. 2. P.C.L. wish to send COLBY Marine Superintendent f'iv'Alw'-r. vv^ , at Haifa to Bahrain Petroleum Company and Qatar for pre liminary investigations into sites for sea loading line for shipments in future of oil from Qatar. C. who is American has been employed since 1933 by Iraq Petroleum Company who vouch for his character and pro-British views. Visit may last one or two months. 3. Do you agree that visa may be granted ? RetaxandumTelegram '0' From To Repeated No. Rated Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, at Kuwait India Office, London. 446 9th December 1940. India Office telegram No. 7849 December 7th. Colby. 2. On receipt of assurances from Local Manager of Petroleum Concessions Limited regarding short duration of Colby 1 s stay and his character permission was given for issue of single journey visa. 3. Colby has since arrived and is in Qatar. - Political -Dated and received 8th December 1940 India Office telegram No. 7849, December 7th. Colby. 2. Have you any objection ? - 'Resident• • • DO/CAL.3/2279 ‘ ^ PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAH RAIN PERSIAN GULF. CONFIDENTIAL 1st February, 1941. Dear Reference our telephone conversation on the 29th instant, I have informed Mr. Dickson, our Engineer-in- Charge, that you expect to visit Qatar according to the undermentioned itinerary of which the times are approximate. Wednesday. February 5th Leave Bahrain (P.C.L.Jetty, not BAPCO pier) 06.00 hours - arrive Zekrit Pier 11.00 hours. t Leave Zekrit Pier (direct) 11.15 hours - arrive Riyan 14.00 hours. Return to Dukhan Camp arriving 18.00-18.30. Probably sleep Wednesday night in Dukhan Camp. Thursday. February 6th Leave Qatar early for Bahrain (time to be fixed with Mr. Dickson). In connection with your itinerary, the following may be of interest (a) Your launch will probably take 5 hours for the trip in favourable weather conditions and up to 6 or 7 coming back if there is a strong shamal. (b) Zekrit jetty (Qatar) is 6 or 7 miles from Dukhan Oamp, and you can save ^ hour if you go straight to Riyan (the Shaikh f s house). (c) The car trip to Dohah takes - 3 hours according to speed. It is a bad track. The Shaikh has a house at Dohah but usuallyn-fy DO/CAL.3/2279 (contd.) ^receives” at Hiyan, 3 or 4 miles west of Dohaii, and practically on tlie Zekrit-Bohah track. It is quite easy to return to Dukhan Camp from Bohah after dark. (d) The journey Bahrain-Zekrit-Dohah-Dukhan is a very tiring and full day, and it is inadvisable to try to add the sea trip back to Bahrain by night. The route includes shoal waters, and Company navigation marks are not visible by night. Even in daylight the marks are not very much good unless their significance is known and which side of the mark lies the channel. Getting in to Sitrah is exceptionally difficult in the dark as there are awkward shoals, and even our pilots go wrong at night. (e) The Shaikh likes to know the time of arrival of his guests, particularly if they arrive direct at Riyan without touching Dohah, as it now takes him time to get down his stairs and outside the gate to 'receive' people. Qatar Personalities - Company y s Contacts The following are usually present when the Shaikh receives :- Shaikh Ali - the eldest son (a nonentity) Shaikh Hamed - the heir-apparent Saleh el Mana - Secretary and Adviser (particularly on Foreign Affairs). The youngest son, Hassan rarely appears. Abdullah Darwish, foster brother to Shaikh Hamed and his confidant and evil genius, is usually hovering about in the back ground. One of the few respectable persons of good status and repute is the leading pearl merchant, Moh*d Abdul Latif el Mana, our agent, when the interference of Shaikh Hamed, Abdullah Darwish and Saleh el Mana allow him to function as such. The Shaikh keeps his numerous brothers and cousins very much in the background and their shares in the oil• • • 3 DO/CAL.3/2279 (contd.) monies are very small. They are very dissatisfied. The Shaikh and his entourage regard the Company as a cow to be milked as much and as often as possible. Their demands are usually quite unreasonable and involve a degree of interference which, if tolerated, would dislocate our work. To counter this interference we have evolved the following plan which has worked well for four years and reduces interference to a minimum. The Engineer-in-Charge refers the Shaikh’s demands to the Manager (Bahrain). The Manager visits the Shaikh as infrequently as possible and keeps things running smoothly by small presents and a few minor concessions. If the Shaikh and his son, Earned, could be brought to realize that interference in the conduct of the Company’s operations, particularly the persistent attempt to control recruitment and extort money from employees hinders progress, relations between the Co. and the Shaikh would be easier and the work would proceed more smoothly. At present the Shaikh, or rather his son Earned, exploits to the full every conceivable opportunity to interfere with the Company’s employees and business for personal profit. Topics of Conversation with the Shaikh Oil Wells No.l (at Dukhan Camp) 5685 feet - good oil and in good quantity. No,2 (10 k.ms. South) 5700 odd - good signs and oil expected at 5900. Drilling to go on as deep as possible as Test Well. Next location a mile or so North of No.l - other locations also selected with a view to locating the extent of the field at Dukhan (hills).DO/CAL.3/2279 (contd.) _Q,atar Terminal - (Terminal to oil lines for export of oil). Survey party now on the east ooast of Qatar look ing for a suitable anchorage for tankers. Water Test wells have been put down at Dohah and Biyan (for the Shaikh) and at Zekrit and Dukhan for the Co. No potable artesian water has been located. At present supplies of Bombay water are imported for Europeans and Indians, and Bahrain water for Arab labour. Concession Payments The Shaikh drew ij lakhs for the first five years. It increases to three lakhs per annum from May 1941. There is also provision for the salaries of two Shaikh’s representatives in the concession. We pay Bs.1250 per month of which Shaikh Earned takes Bs.1000 per month and Saleh el Mana gets the rest. Qatari Employees Qataris employed are restricted to one or two junior clerks with a smattering of English, Drivers (very bad and still half trained), a few artizans, House boys (of doubtful antecedents and still half trained), Big coolies, Unskilled labour. The Shaikh taxes the pay of employees and is constantly pressing the Company to create more work and absorb more men. As each discharge involves loss of money or tax, its justice is fiercely disputed by Shaikh Earned with a view to overriding the decision of the executive concerned. A straight hint from high authority against «DO/CAL.3/2279 (contd.) meddling in employment matters would be of inestim able benefit at this stage and before labour reaches a large scale. The Company’s rates of pay to Q,ataris compare favourably with those of BAPCO and CASOC to their Arab labour and, in addition, the Company supplies I . free food (which BAPCO and CASOC do not). Yours sincerely, Major R. G. Alban, H. B. M. f s Political Agent, Bahrain.PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAH RAIN PERSIAN GULF. DO/CAL.3/7856 3rd February, 1941. Dear I enclose herewith (a) Staff List (b) Copy of my date. - Qatar Telegram to SJatar of today’s I have just heard that Dickson is arriving in Bahrain today from Qatar presumably on some unexpectedly urgent job in connection with the Well but Mr. Ensor, his assistant, will make all the necessary arrangements for you. Please let me know if there is anything else we can do. Yours sincerely, Enel. 2 Major R. G. Alban, H.B.M. *s Political Agent, Bahrain.Page Two of Two {No ,8£ BT SSft political AGiENT HOT require AT DGHtH 01? PRESENT SEND SEHV-.ST shaikh HAS OF POLITICAL BY HOSES (Sgd.) K r. Pother. ACM MANAGER/PCL oontd.) j.Bi.MXiltLD FULLS TOP STATES DOES COMPANY HOUSE so UNNECESSARY plans TO OR PROYISIOJE SKIN INFORMED AGENTS VISIT = Packer - 4.2.41mmmmmrn PETROLEUM DSVELOPMBNT (QATAR) LTD. - QATAR STAFF LIST J # 1 Mr. 0. S. Dickson - Engineer-in-Charge Mr. P. R. A. Ensor - Administrative Assistant Mr. G-. N. Akin - Tool Pusher (American) Mr. C. H. Looper - Driller ( ' ) Mr. H. G. Keck - Driller ( ' ) Mr. 1. K. W. Scholder - Driller ( ” ) Mr. W. Stiff - Maintenance Mechanic Mr. W. Barnfield - Ship’s Officer (absent Qatar Terminal Survey) Mr. W. V. Clemence — Engineer (Buildings) Mr. N. T. Langham - Geologist (American) Mr. I. M. Ross - Assistant Accountant - leaving end of February for Commission R.A.S.C Mr. R. N. Anderson - Motor Mechanic * flCM- h/tltfifjvrjtuUa] Mr. E. A. Lovell - Workshop Foreman Mr. S. M, Morison - W/T Operator &amp; Electrical Engineer (absent Qatar Terminal Survey) TEMPORARY DUTY - 40 MILES NORTH OF DO HAH - . r * ^ ^olby - i/c Qatar Terminal Survey (American) Mr. T. K. Ferguson - Qatar Terminal Survey. •. IX)/CAL. 3/2343 * ^ 0 !/ 9 ' 5 OJ' ^ PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. I BAH RAIN PERSIAN GULF. 13tli March, 1941. L)'l Dear The following is the situation up to Thursday, the 13th March, v/ith regard to the Political Resident’s visit to Qatar 10th March we telegraphed Dukhan to notify the shaikh of the date and time of the visit. On the 13th we despatched an Arabic letter to the Ruler giving the P.R’s itinerary and asking for an acknowledgment. All arrangements are in train for the stay in Doha on the night of the 18th. Should, however, the P.R. decide w?-i? e £ Urn t0 ? u ^ han on the night of the 18th, no inconvenience will be caused to us. We should like, however, to give Dukhan notice of the change. * 6 vp-tv °P e nations, etc., in Qatar, there is very little to add to our No.2279 dated the 1st February. •dg- 11 (16 kilometres south of Dukhan Camp). eonn $fiP in T g r i ? continuln 6 int0 the oil horizon at about made f Up to tile 13th March i no actual tests had been Qatar Terminal Survey . at thPf J re PS 1 v ary surve y of the east coast was completed PossiblflocatL^^- Soundl ^ s were ^^en of three Ras-Laffan (40 miles north of Doha) (% miles south of the village) ° ff nt e l a ?l hi11 area in the south ( wel l north oi Odaid).w DO/CAL.3/2343 (contd.) 2 - A report on the survey is being compiled in Haifa. The final selection of a location is likely to take some time. Considerable correspondence with London will be necessary and perhaps more detailed surveys of one or all of the alternatives. When the decision is reached, there will be a final and meticulous survey of the anchorages and approaches to them. Qatar Staff There are minor changes to the staff list sent you under our No.7856 of the 3rd February. Mr. Clemence, Mr. Ross, Mr. Anderson, Mr. Colby and Mr. Ferguson have gone. Mr. Freeman, ex Kirkuk, has arrived to supervise the test of Well No.2. Mr. Ball, accountant, has taken over from Mr. Ross. Shaikh 1 s Movements I understand the Shaikh intends to camp out for another month or six weeks. J Smallpox The outbreak of smallpox on the east coast, which I mentioned on the telephone, seems severest in the village of Khor, 30 miles north of Doha. If there is any other information you require, please let me know. Major R. G. Alban, H.B.M.’s Political Agent, Bahrain.INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL,S•W *1• P.Z. 1548/41. -^tylfiarch, 1941. Gentlemen, I am directed Ly the Secretary of State for India to thank yon for your letter of the 26th March in which you report that oil has heen struck in a second well in Qatar. I am. Gentlemen, Your obedient Servant, fS^d '&lt; J P essrs Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd.liUROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED. onfidential P0.30 King * s Head Hotel Horsham, idential . Sussex* 26th March, 1941. ftder Secretary of Stat India, Political Department India Office, S.W.l. ^ ' ir letter P0.30 of the 20th October ^39, and to report that a second ill at Qatar about ten miles south the first well, has struck oil .d ajjpears to be capable of a 'oduction at least as high as that the first well. Production tests e now being carried out and the suits will be communicated to you en received* We are similarly informing the broleum Department* We have, etc. •'or Petroleum Development (Qatar) (Sgd.) H.H.Wheatley* Htd* Lr We have the honour to refer toTELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN , ^ ( CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED Mr. G. H. Looper, American driller, left on the 9th June on repatriation to the U.S.A. As you are probably aware, it is not possible for us to obtain experienced British drillers. We, therefore, wish to replace Mr. Looper with another American driller - James Leo North (age 43). This replace ment will not increase the total number of Americans in Qatar. We shall be grateful if you will telegraph to the British Consul, Basra, at our expense authorizing him to issue the necessary visas for Bahrain and Qatar both for one year and any number of journeys. You will realize that it is desirable to dislocate our drilling operations as little as possible and it will be appreciated if a telegram can be sent as early as convenient. n, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) G&amp;Sr. &amp; *-£&amp;/*-76 J.S.O., D.S.C. (French) :.b.e. BAHREIN #• kian (formerly Armenian) :ler (Dutch) PERSIAN GULF PCX,/aI . 8/8409 11th June, 1941 To H.B.M.* s Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir, AMERICAN STAFF - QATAR Yours faithfully, For 8c on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED Copy to Basrah Petroleum Co. Ltd., Basrah. ACMTelegram From To Repeated No• 205 Q. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire India Office, London. Dated the 14th June 1941. Petroleum Concessions Limited wish to engage American driller James Leo North in place of C. H. Looper repatriated to U.S.A. on the 9th June. If no objection, they request Consul Basra be authorised to issue visas for Bahrain and Qatar for North. 2. I see no objection. Political. imMamammu .. Telegram Political Resident, Bushire British Consul, Basra. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 657 Dated 16th received 17th June 1941. t tf; i '§ a •«% A p j /W No objection to grant of visa for Bahrain and Qatar to American driller James Leo North.? l^igTTnrTmi HBMI . A No* C/632 Political Agency^ Bahrain, the 19th June 1941. To The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, B A H H A I N &lt; Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No. PCL/AI. S/8409 dated the 11th June 1941, regarding Mr* James Leo North* 2* The British Consul, Basra, has been telegraphed that there is no objection to the grant of visas for Bahrain and Qatar to Mr* James Leo North, American driller* Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain.■vmm m spare copy for c.o.0 Ho.1376-28/20 Political Agency, Pa lira in. 17th July, 1941. From The Political Agent, Bahrain. To p&gt; yj&gt; O' 7 A)' ' / w The Hon T b'e the' Political Resident in the Persian (iulf, Bushire. SUBJECT Radio Telephone 'Sir, ^ f * ^ ^ I have the honour to forward herev;ith a copy of letter ITo.PDQ/AB.6/2543 dated the 9th July 1941 from'the manager. Petroleum development (Qatar) Limited requesting permission to instal a radio telephone set in his office at Manama, Bahrain, for communication with Dukhan and with the launch 'Ghazni'. t o P U- l , 1 ! 1 ■^ e position is that sometime in 1936 the Company were allowed to instal a similar set at Doha which I understand is now removed to the Company’s Camp at Du-khan and, in 1940, r marine radio telephones were installed on the Company’s C* launcnes fl Gazal li and Tl Shahin', with the permission of the Bahrain Government. |0 ^ 3 * ^As regards communications between the Manager,/ resident in Manama^and the Company’s Camp at Dukhan, messages are^ transmitted daily at fixed times between Bahrain and Duknan through Messrs. Cable &amp; ,wireless Limited who receive payment i. or messages^ sent. The proposal to instal a private radio uelephone set in^ITanajna office for direct communication _c, a karris somewhat similar to the proposal by the Bahrain etroleum Company in 1934 to instal a transmitter for communi- cation with stations ’outside Bahrain, and even with the mainland, tnat occasion, the Political Agent was authorised (vide with Resident’s telegram Mo.410 dated the Both Aprn 1934; to advise His Highness the Bhaikh not to allow tne company to use the radio telephone set outside a limit of three miles from the coast line of Bahrain. A similar pennission o Petroleum Development (Qatar; Limited would not meet their wishes and^the only alternative would seem to be for Cable and tireless Limited to instal and operate a radio telephonic set fr! +u e 2p ense ? f petr °leum Development (Qatar; Limited, similar oo the ^ oi j_ er which they made to the Bahrain Petroleum Company and whicn was not accepted. V a§v&lt;~^ if ^ ^muGjvm^pres-aed by the--arguj^ie.ri4rS put for.vard A u Lana;rer m juatif ication-of-tlTc propooal, although it ‘H is true teat the present arrangement would not be adequate:* if some emergency due to the war were suddenly to arise* The objections to the proposal appear to be : (a) that if agreed to, it might be followed by a similar request from Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited; (b) that telephonic communication cannot be censored; and (c)/ •smmmmmm mmam.•• - 2 - SeKtfM installation thLs.lvss, as mentionod above. _ T ,Mould be grateful to receive instructions as to the reply to be givenlo Messrs. Petroleum development (Qatar) Limited. 1 have the honour to be, sir. 7 Your most obedient servant, sd. R.G.E.^.Alban Major, Political Agent, Bahrain. V 111 I tv(Original at page 37, 3.0.file 28/20) Copy of letter No. PDQ/AB.5/2543 dated the 9th July 194t from the Manager, Petroleum Development (oatar) Limited, Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Radio Telephones As you are aware from previous correspondence, we have installed a radiotelephone set on our launch f, Ghazal% which can send messages to, and receive messages from our Dukhan Camp, Qatar. As an additional security measure in these times, it is desired to c omplete our communications by the ins tallation of a similar radio telephone set in the P.C*L. office, Bahrain. By the use of this set it would be pos sible to contact with Dukhan Camp and the 'Ghazal'. It will be realized that such an installation would be of great service in many circumstances particularly with regard to the safety of personnel and launches. Cases also occur in Qatar of accident and serious sickness. Cur existing arrangements for communication between Oatar and Bahrain in conjunction with Cable &amp; Wireless, Bahrain, are not sufficient to meet such emergencies. We suggest that in general the use of the Bahrain set could be confined to emergencies, launch movements and particularly urgent business. We would draw attention to the fact that our Qatar staff are in a particularly isolated location in times which are far from normal and any additional communications which can be established will give an increased sense of security to our European, American and Indian staff. It would be very much appreciated if a decision can be given us as early as possible.Conf ic ential (Original in E.O.file 28/20 page 41) No. 18-S of 1941 British Residency &amp; Consulate General Bushire, the 22nd September, 1941 To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to: His Majesty’s Secretary of State ) with copy of for India, London. ) Bahrain letter ) under reply and The Secretary to the Government ) with reference to of India, External Affairs ) India Office Department, Simla ) telegram No.970 ) dated the 18th April 1934 Subject:- Request by Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd.for installation of a radio ^telephone set in their Bahrain office. Memorandum Reference your letter No. 1376-28/20 dated the 17th July 1941. 2. With the Allied occupation of Syria, Iraq and Iran the likelihood of an emergency in oatar due to the war is negligible, and for ordinary emergencies and the Company's normal working the existing system of daily communication at fixed times should suffice. Under present conditions, therefore, the installation of a radio telephone set in the Company’s office at Bahrain is not so much a necessity as a convenience, to the sanctioning of which there are strong objections. 3. Please inform the Company accordingly. Attested Sd/- C.G. Prior Political Resident in the Persian Gulf J. Croning for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.jBhbbbbbb (Original at page 42,S.0.fi.e 28/20) No. 2061-28/20 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th October, 1941 / To The Manager, Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No. PDQ/AB.5/2543 dated the 9th July, 1941, regarding the installation of a radiotelephone set in your office in Manama. 2, I am to say that with the allied occupation of Syria, Iraq and Iran the likelihood of an emergency in Qatar due to the war is negligible. For ordinary mergencies and your Company 1 s normal working the existing system of daily communication at fixed times should suffice. Under present conditions, thereforethe installation of a radio t elephone set in your Company premises at Bahrain is not so much a necessity as a convenience, to the sanctioning of which there are strong objections. Yours faithfully, Sd/- H. G. Alban Political Agent, BahrainCONFIDENTIAL. V t r ;t- 'svn.c 3 N °- G/574 of 1941# ^ , ^(ix The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1* His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India f London* j 2* The .Political Agent, Bahrain, ■ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^. Name and Date. Subject. Letter Ho.C/573 of 19th Hovember 1941 to the Visit of the Political Secretary to the Government Resident to the Qatar of India, External Affairs Peninsula* Department, New Delhi* ! i-—It\ A \K CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE 'ROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED EsTb L R 'm A ™’ P S f ; D :?: C - ( ^ RgNCH) ’ - W - FRASER &gt; C B f- &lt;=• S. G UL B EN K.AN (FORMERUY ARMENIAN) ES, J. B. A. KESSUER (DUTCH), L. M. UEFROY. J. A. MENY (FRENCTi), H. G. SEIDEL (U.S-A.), R. W. SELLERS, J. SKLIROS Directors: Lord G. Legh-jones BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 2nd December, 1941. PDQ/AI.10/9099 To H.B.M. f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, We are finding it almost impossible to recruit combustion engine mechanics, fitters, etc., from India due to war conditions. In these circumstances, we wish to give a trial to an Iraqi named Yeram Mukhudich who appears suitable and who has worked in our associated companies before. He is at present in Bahrain. We shall be pleased if you will confirm that there is no objection to his engagement. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED -jShsu jQ- No.C/1144-10/3. Political Agency, Bahrain, 8th December 1941. To The Manager, Petroleum Development (Oatar) Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, i) ^ Reference your letter No. iW/A1.10/9099 dated the 2nd December 1941. 2. There is no objection to the engagement of Yeram llukhudich as a mechanic. # Yours faithfully, L, Political Agent, Bahrain.(7 PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. © BAH RA IN PERSIAN GULF. 9 - Reference our conversation regarding Mr. Dickson 1 s wife and small child coming from India to join Mr. Dickson in Qatar. The position is that the Company agree to her. coming to Qatar where good accommodation already exists and excellent air-conditioning. Major Alban gave me to under stand that^there were no objections to wives coming to Bahrain and considered this would apply to Qatar also in the case of Mr.Dickson which was the case under discussion. If it is considered that’ she should not proceed beyond Bahrain the situation is not quite the same. Suitable accommodation with a sufficient water supply for air- conditioning is not available. Added to this, Mr. Dickson will be involved in considerable expense in furnishing and maintaining a second house including duplicate domestics. The Company also f eel that it is unsatisfactory for the man in charge of the Qatar camp to be separated by such a small distance from his wife for reasons which are obvious. If a possible objection to Mrs. Dickson* s presence is from the security point of view, we would submit that our six years* experience in Qatar shows that general security is excellent. In addition to this, the camp is equipped with air-raid shelters and a launch i s always available for evacuation of personnel at short notice. The Company is in constant wireless communication with Bahrain. If you are putting up this matter to Mr. Wakefield perhaps you may wish to draw his attention to the above aspects of the matter. Yours sincerely, G. N. Jackson, Esq., The Agency, Bahrain.Telegrarii u Q ,f From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, at Kuwait. No. 155 Dated 25th February, 1942. Dickson in charge Oil Camp Qatar wants to bring wife and small child from India to join him Datar. I see no objection but solicit orders before replying. T/irs. Dickson was allowed visit Qatar 1938.liayTiatif»n \ X f '| f. V» if Telegram Political Resident ? at Kuwait. Political Agent ? Bahrain. T/48 , . p,• 28th February 1942 v our telegram No. 155 February 25th. 2. No objection provided Dickson agreeable to send his family away if advised by you to do so * 4-V - Resident - • M 1(■ Ho. C/248 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd March 1942 To The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, BAHRAIN Dear Sir, There is no objection to Mr. Dickson bringing his wife and child to Qatar, provided that he agrees to send them away if at any time it becomes necessary for me to advise him to take this step. Yours faithfully, Politic ^gent, Bahrain(Taken from “Residency file 86/32-1) Mr. Packer when he recently came to see me brought up the question of direct radio communication between his office at Bahrain and the Company's camp on the Qatar peninsula# At present communications between Bahrain and the Company’s camp are carried out through Cable and Wireless at Bahrain and the Company's installation in their camp. Cable and Wireless keep a watch at 4 set times a day. fir. Packer admits that this is sufficient for business purposes and only asks for direct communica tion for security purposes in the event of an emergency. Mr. Packer has probably heard something of the proposal to permit radio communication between BAPCO and CASCC and he will undoubtedly put up a request if this is sanctioned, though the circumstances are entirely different. Have any pp. regarding his request ? 2. Mr. Packer informed me that his Company at Qatar were communicating direct by wireless with Basra. This is presumably irregular but the Bahrain representative of Cable and Wireless is unofficially aware of it and has not raised any objection. Id/- W.R.K* 18.3.42 1. Your para.l PI. see pp. 1-4 corres. 2. Your para 2. The right of Pet.Dev.oatar under Article 6 of their Concession (Vo.P.91 p.30) limited by Article 8 of the Connected Political Agreement (ibid p.36) are the same as those of the K.O.C. in Kuwait. In any case, except for any contractual obligations P.D.Q. may have entered into with Cable and Wireless in connection with their working with the latter's Bahrain Station (about which we have no information) Cable and Wireless have no locus standi in the matter as they possess noWKKMM&amp;L: flBHHHBBBHBHBBHHBflEBIHBH rights in ^atar. From prepage «J* C • 19/3 P.R. P.A#B. should see this noting* So far as Mr- Packer’s request in para 1 of my note dated 18/3 is concerned my views coincide with Col. Prior’s. Bapco and Casoc are in production and any concession granted to them is to facilitate this production for war purposes. No such good reason exists for granting the concession asked for by Mr.Packer* 2. Ref. para 2 of C.A’s note. It is true that C &amp; W have no locus standi in Qatar, but they must lose business if P.C.L. use their Qatar v/ireless for communications with Iraq. I am also surprised that the defence services permit this. They presumably pick up messages passing between Qatar and Basra and must be aware of what is going on. W.R*R* 20/3 P.A. BahrainC ONF TDF.FT TA L Petroleum Concessions Ltd DC/SA.2/3425 7£ /K V'13 10th April, 1943 Ly dear Wakefield You will remember that the majority of the Trucial Coast Shaikhs demand payment of our concession obligations in silver. With the knowledge and o par oval of F.B.TWs. Political Agent, Bahrain) who has in the past authorised ' export from Bahrain, their demands have been complied with to date. Cur Managing Director gave the following ruling in this connection f, The Company agrees to bear the extra cost of payment 'in silver but whether or not we should continue’ to 'pay in silver is a matter for the Political Agent to 'decide and you should abide by his decision.' 2. The annual concession payment to the Shaikh of n atar of Rs.3,20,000 odd is due on May 17th and w e had arranged with the Eastern Bank, Bahrain to bring this in silver from Bombay to Bahrain this month. The Manager, the Eastern Bank, Bahrain informs us today that the Beserve Bank Currency Department, India, refuse to allow the shipment of the' silver i^upees for the purpose required (i.e. oil concession payments). It is assumed that this refusal will not aonly to this condignment alone, but all future concession payments will come under a similar ban. 3. You will understand that it is not practicable even if it were desirable for us to obtain the required silver by local purchase here in Bahrain. 4. We feel that it is reasonable for the Bhaikh of batar to ask for silver under the existing conditions on the Trucial Coast. It is understood that in Dubai and Sharjah from 4 to 10 c $ is charged on notes. British Overseas Airways and Messrs. Gray Mackenzie in these locations demand payment in silver. Under these circumstances, it is impossible for us to convince the Shaikhs that their claims to silver are unreasonable and they should be prepared to accent losses on notes as unavoidable and a result of the war. 5. We feel that the situation is such that we have no alternative but to seek the assistance of TT.M’s. Government. It would seem that the Shaikhs should be Inducdd to accept a position in which they and all classes of the communities In their Sheikhdoms accept notes in all circumstances, • If this is not feasible, perhaps the Shaikhs could be Informed formally by H.B.M’s. Political Agent that the Company is within Its rights in making payments In notes which are legal tender. 7. The above possible solutions to the Company’s problem assume that the Reserve Bank of India cannot he prevailed upon to re-consider its decision. / 8. Whatever1 L S - 2 - 8. hatever the solution eventually adohted, it is most desirable that the Company should avoid sayina ,f extra ,r in note as a form of compensation to cover the exchange of the notes into silver by the ihaikhs themselves. This is a solution \hich will doubtless occur to the Shaikhs. It would give rise to interminable arguments with the Shaikhs on the rate to be usedj and result in the lulers now being oaid by remittances into Banks, also clamouring for the additional nercentages. 01 * reanwhile, it is submitted, it would seem very desirable as an interim measure that Political Agent should notify the 'Tilers that the Company has tried to get silver from India to make concession payments to them but soa-r at least the Government has refused to sanction the export. 10. If it is in order, also, for the Pulers to be advised (bv the P.'.) to accept notes, this might have the desired effect and settle the problem. 11. T,r e should appreciate an early reply in view of the fact that the tata^ annual nayment is due shortly, and shall be very^grateful for any advice or assistance.' v ours sincerelv, 3d/- 3.”. Packer. S.B. Wakefield 3sq., T.C.3 Political Agent, Pohrain. ?DO/SA.2/3426 h /2 CCI T FrDS?!TT''L. ■ql® Vet ''*o 1 eurn Coneessions Ltd., Bahrain 13 th a nri1, 1943. Ly dear Wakefield, CC W GTISSICIT P,A l rT d3FT3 ITT Slid In continuation of.our letter No. HO/^LA.2/3425 dated 10th April 1943 and reference our teleonone conversation this morning. Our requirements of silver up to the end of 1943 by months are as under r~ Larch April I lay June July August September October November December ib • 12.000 - overdue. 1 , 000 314,000 ~ Oatar annual oayment 33.000 1,000 1,000 33,000 1,000 1,000 33,000 430,000 The above figure does not include payments to Dharjah, Dubai and ruscat, which are made by remittances into Banks. The total for 1944 including certain additional payments is expected to be Ps.5,79,000. Dhould, however, Sharjah, Dubai and Nuscat also be allowed silver, a further Ps.3,38,000 would be required. In making these estimates, we have worked to the : 3 nearest thousand. vours sincerely, 3d/- N.V. Packer. N. 1 ^. Wakefield, Ksq. , T.C.S., F.B.F’s. Political 'Agent, Bahrain.Telegram Fr©m To Political Resident, Bushire. Government of India, lew Delhi Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain* Mo • 865 Dated 15th; received 16th April 1943* fy immediately preceding telegram repeating Bahrain telegram No, 282 April 14th, 2. Reference Political Agent’s paragraph 2. Please see _ correspondence ending with Residency rrinted Leyter Mo, 0/^60 December 14th 1941, 1 3. I concur with Political Agent and request that action be taken for (a) immediate grant of ICxport I ermix. for sums in his paragraph 1 and (b) grant approval for export as required of sum mentioned in his paragraph 4. - Britconsul - -V _s Government of India f New Delhi, Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain, received 28th April, 1943. /pi Your telegram 865 dated April 15th, Export of standard silver rupees is out of the question but Goverament of India can make quarternary rupees available if these are required for purpose in view Please confirm that they are acceptable. Telegragi From To Repeated No. 3318 Dated 27th - FOREIGNA;/&gt;o /ij i fa Telegram 8 From Political i gent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated Government of India, New Delhi. Ho. 317 Dated the 1st Kay, 1943. / Foreign telegram 3318 April 27th. It is confirmed that quaternary rupees are acceptalile. - POLITICAL - NCJI '' &lt;M0* WlA/'.&gt;.'/*/ CJ J I , .'&gt;•3 ^ ^ ^ ^ — C * j^^4*il j w*s«5 ji 4 ? l !! La* _*■*«» ^ **i£ &gt; ^** , 3 * jji ^ 4 UJ^ UuT. n*^f '** ■ . ■*• i &lt; : •r* ;/SA*2/3474 Bombay to Bahrain and deliver it, as promised, to your Representative at Zekrlt* 4, With all due respect we would point out that letters to the Company containing arguments on the interpretation of rticles of the Concession will not get the result required, that is, an export permit from India. . e repeat, if you do your part and get us the permits, we will do the rest and deliver the silver at the earliest possible moment. 5. If, however, you wish us to send you notes this can be arranged immediately. he have the honour to be Your Excellency’s most obedient servant s, For &amp; on behalf of petroleum QmmiQmmm (catar) ltd. -7 r (Sjd.) E. r. Packer MMAGISB /No. C/480 CUHa’IBS^T IAL Q Office of tine Political Resident in the Persian Gulf , Camp, Bahrain, hated the 29th November 1943 . 0 with compliments, to Copy of the undermentioned telegram is forwarded, The Political Agent, BAHRAIN Telegram No. 26915 dated the 24th November 1943 from His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London/ 7 9/14-4d Telegram From To Repeated ^o. 2691&amp; Dated 24th S(B) / / Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, at Bahrain, (iovernment of India, $ew Delhi. correction received 28th November 194S. Proposals have recently been under discussion here at high level regarding development of oil supplies in Kiddle East. Plans have already been formulated in America for development oi oil fields there to highest capacity and it has nov^ become matter of urgent necessity ? in face of change in war situation to con sider as complementary measure opening up more cruae oil production in Iraq Persia and Persian Gulf. Factors concerned are growth of neeas of Pacif ic and Indian Ocean areas, requirements of occupied areas of Europe as these are freed and easier to movement of oil from Kiddle East through M&amp;ditterranean. 2. following schemes have now been approved in principle here for joint consideration of Washington in regard to supply and priority of equipment in follow ing order of priority : UJ Drilling of Agha Jara field in Persia and linking with Abadan refinery which will represent additional supply of four million tons of crude oil per annum. (ii) Laying of second pipe line from Ki)|kuis: to Haifa with capacity of three million tons. liii) Resumption of ? field development at Qatar. 3. As regards (iii) Petroleum Concessions Limited have put forward proposal for resuming development of operations. Original drilling rig now stored at iiara- chi cannot be satisfactorily reconditioned in absence of workshop facilities at Qatar and Company wishes to order three new drilling rigs in U.S.A. to enable them to run continuous two rig programme at Qatar. Shaikh will no doubt welcome proposal but he should not be informed of it at present stage. 4. instructions have been approved for issue through Eiae&amp;st ana PAIC permitting relaxation where necessary oi denial measures including permission for Bahrain Petroleum Company to prepare well sites to facilitate ?installation of drilling equipment andgeneral prepara tions to minimise delay once sanction received to return wells to production. RETAXA.NDUM IIJHTELEGRAMS : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED S: tman, G.C.M.G. (Cfrairrwn} ).S.O., D.S.C. (French) :.b.e. ikian (formerly Armenian) Uer (Dutch) French) (U.S.A.) P/CA.3/3600 To H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 3rd January, 1944. \ -V— CHANGE OF REGISTERED ADDRESS With effect from the 29th October 1943 ? the new address of the Head Office of the undermentioned Companies is Ling House, Dominion Street, London, E.C.2. Petroleum Concessions Limited Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited. We shall be pleased if this change of address can be registered in the Agency. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED ACMProm i secretary of state. To s Political Kejaident in the Persian Gulf (Buheire)* Repeated Govemment of India, External Affaire Department. Dated 27th January 19 44. 2To. EXT.320/44. Addressed Bush ire repeated Hew Delhi. iy telegram 27330 November 28th. oil Control Board here have now approved in principle proposal for development of oil at Kuwait with equal priority to jatar• Batter has been referred to Washington for final decision itoich may tabs up to 4 months. The is43ue of the above has been duly authorised. 3d. R.T. mBL. No. 207-S . British Residaioy &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 6th March 1944. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to 1. The Political Agent, KUWAIT . 2. The Political Agent, ^ BAHRAB'T.■ 3eceived unde r Itidici Office endorsement J]xt&gt; 3654&gt; 1_944 _ dated 2nd oeptembe r 1944. t iCxt &gt; 5 270/44 \ India Office&gt; Whitehall, London, 3.W.I. 0 ^ , 14th August 1944 Dear Bridgeman, A Many thanks for your letter of 21st July aoou t oil developments in Qatar. There are one or two points in this connection in which we should be glad to have your observation. It is not quite clear to us whether the increase in world refining capacity regarding which the Petroleum Administrator for War has_ asked for your views, is concerned solely with war requirement or how far it is also related to post-war development for peacetime needs. What we are of course interested in from the political point of view is that when the war ends the oil companies holding concessions in the undeveloped Arab states should not find themselves unable to proceed with operations for lack of equipment, for which I understand we are so largely dependent on America. In the case of Muscat, the Political Resident informed us recently that according to the Political Agent at Muscat who has been in almost daily contact with the Sultan, the latter is very keen on oil development, but is not convinced that the company intend to exploit their concession. We should be very grateiui for your comments on die above points and for any information that you can give us as to the latest plans of the Petroleum Division regarding the supply of oil equipment after the war» I am sending a Foreign Office. :opy of this letter to Vikely at the Yours sincerely, Sgd R. Peel. » The Honourable M.R. Bridgeman, Petroleum Division, Ministry of Fuel and Power, Dean Stanley Street, S.W.l. COPY Bxt . 5 60 4/1944. Mini stry of Fuel and Power , Petroleum Division, 7, Millbank, London, S.W.l. August 1944. Dear Peel, thanks for your letter of August 14th. The enquiry by the Petroleum Administrator for War relates solely to war requirements. / It might3! s f It rnugtit be thougnt that the time is now approaching when oil projects should be supported, or the reverse, on the basis of whether or not they are in the general interest, without special reference to the war elfoit# Unfortunately, however, it is still impossible to get priorities for equipment, etc, in the U#S#A* without ple&amp;cung some war necessity* Moreover, I . A ♦ V/ • themselves t.av e onl&gt; a wartime mandate, and cannot therefore request our views on post-war developments. As regards the supply of oil equipment, materials, etc. after the war, we have already done a good deal of research in tills Department, and have come to the conclusion that about 80 % of our oil equipment requirements over the next live years could be manufactured in this country, proviced we are given an adequate allocation of man-power, raw materials one manufacturing capacity. We are in coreespondence with the Treasury ana the Ministry of Production on this subject, out the statistics are rather voluminous and this general indication ray be enough for your purpose. As regards the balance of 20 % which we should need to obtain from the United States, we do not expect any trouble in obtaining it, provided the Treasury are prepared to release the necessary dollars. It is, however, to prophesy the course of events in til the new International Oil Concession has begun to operate. difficult at present I am sending a copy of this letter to Wikely Yours sincerely, Sgd. M.R. Bridgeman. R.T. Peel, Esquire, CBE, MC,, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. CONFIDE N TIAL No. C/3iq Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Shiraz, 26th September 1944. Copy forwarded with compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to India Office endorsement No. Ext. 3270/\§44, dated bth Augucu 1944. r v jvC ONFIDEN TIAL P.C.L., Balirain. I enclose my letter Q,/SA.2/3825 dated the 30th September 1944. If you feel that any of the paragraphs would be better omitted at this stage, I shall be grateful if you will let me know and give me an opportunity to re-draft the letter. 2. I enclose also a letter addressed to Mr. Wheatley, which is a copy of q/SA.2/3825, for the information of our Managing Director. If you can include it in your India Office bag, I shall be grateful, providing of course a re-draft is unnecessary. Tours sincerely, Enc Is. 2 Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.E., O.B.E., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE FROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED DIRECTORS: LORD-CADMAMf G.C. M .G. (CHAIRMAf*) t R. CAYROL, D.S.O., D.S.C. (FRENCh), W. Fraser, C.B.E., C. S. G ULBENKI AN (FORMERLY ARMENIAN) G. Leoh-Jones, J. B. a. Kessler (dutch), L. m. lefroy, a..meny (French), H. G. Seidel (u.S.a.), r. w. Sellers, J. Skliros COOTIDENTIAL BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF q/sA. 2/3825 30th September, 1944. To H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, BOUNDARIES BBT ISBN QA-TAR AND BAHRAIN 1. We have the honour to bring it to your notice that our Managing Direct) r, in acknowledging receipt of our letter conveying the information that normal relations between Bahrain and Qatar have been restored, comments that the time may now be considered opportune to raise the question of boundaries between Qatar and Bahrain with the Hon r ble the Political Resident, with particular reference to the boundaries between the Bahrein Petroleum. Company and Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, as a result of the 1940 Oil Agreement between the Bahrein Petroleum Company and the Ruler of Bahrain. 2. He states also that he will be making a similar approach to the India Office. 3. We have received no instructions to offer^any comments on this boundary question, but we venture to point out that, in addition to the composition of the Hawar group of islands and the extent of their territorial waters which is of obvious importance to us, we believe that there are other reefs and islets between the two sheikhdoms outside the territorial waters of both, which constitute possible drilling locations and on which Bahrain cairns appeared about 1939/40.2 # Q,/SA. 2/3825 4. We should be interested to hear if these cairns are recognised by as constituting ownership and whether Qatar’s claims or interests were taken into consideration at the time of demarka- ti on. 5. We may add that we believe that the Bahrain Petroleum Company carried out geological work on some at least of these 'locations”. Copy to: Managing Director, Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd., Ling House, Dominion Street, London, E.C.2. ACLc\ W COKj IjJfcMTIAL D.O.Wo.C/1412. 1st October 1944 [y dear Pa 1 PIetisp' refer to ycur detai-offielal letter No* SA*2/3826 dated the 30th September 1944* 2* I tflll certainly Include your letter to the Managing Director in our India Office btu&gt; X confess that I would prefer not to have had the question raised at all at the present time as I aia particularly anxious not to disturb the very recent resumption of friendly relations by raising a further question of jurisdiction over islets lyin^ between the two countries* However, since the matter is being raised In L ondon In any case according to paragraph 2 of your letter No*Q/SA*2/3825 of the 30th of September there does not seem to be any objection to clearing up certain minor points here without necessarily making any direct reference to the 3* j. I shall be glad to know to what reefs and Islets you are referring in paragraph 3 of your letter No*Q/3A. I ■ ■ ■ 2/3825 and whether you do in fact claim that they are part of the area covered by your concession agreement with the Shaikh of Qatar. icker. Esq* , Yours sincerely, ssrs* Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd. Eulers concerned* Bahrainp CONFIDENTIAL P.C.L., Bahrain. 28th October, 1944. \ ^ vM- c\g D0/3A.2/3844 Dear Major Hickinbothari, BOUNDABINS BSUfFSN QATAR AND BAHRAIN I very much regr^tr We delay in replying to your D.0.No.C/1412 dated the 1st October 1944. You will realise that I am not in a position to commit the Managing Director in any way without prior reference to London on such an important matter. As you know, I sent a copy of my No.Q,/SA.2/3825 dated the 30th September 1944 addressed to you to London, but no comment has yet reached me. I am following it up with a note on the situation as it appears to me from knowledge that is limited and which may possibly be inaccurate in some respects. I think you will agree that it is essential that 1 wait for the Managing Director’s views befariB proceeding any further in the matter. W Yours sincerely, Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.E., O.B.E., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.HP* Bahrain Receipt ^ ^ c\ TELEGRAMS : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN AMS : • BAHREIN BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED u (l @ •C.B.er tjrtf-Xcr/V&amp;S D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) C.B.E. BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF inkian (formerly Armenian) isler (Dutch) 18th November, 1944 P/CU. 1/3849 s: (u.s.a.) CONFIDENTIAL To s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, SILVER REQUIREMENTS - P.C.L e6R The TSar 1945 1. You will doubtless recall that the Indian G-overnment have admitted in past years in principle that we require silver rupees to make payments in Q,atar and to certain of the Trucial Coast Rulers in discharge of our obligations under the oil concessions held by us. E. Our requirements for the year 1945 will be Rupees Four lakhs, and we shall be very grateful indeed if the necessary sanction for the export can be obtained for us from the Indian Government. 3. We would add that it is possible that the Company may be taking up additional concessions during 1945, and, should the Rulers concerned insist on silver, it might be necessary for us to apply for a supplementary export permit. 4. Should our operations in Qatar or on the Trucial Coast recommence in 1945, our silver requirements would also increase in proportion to the scale of the operations. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED MANAGER ACM........ - 'X .... . .. &gt; ' _v -. &lt;- GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER -TMa is an OF.MIN'AL MESSAGE, sent by post to eave telegraphic expense and undue use of the fc-ires, but intended to be treated, ©a receipt, with the same expedition as if •it had bdea telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it 'had been so despatched. 103 /1676. Dated Bahrain, the gist Novembeir' 4 1944, Politioal Resident, Camp Bahrain* Petrole um gonce -sions uirnltfid .Silver requirements tor 19457 / / Reference Government of India telegram No.3525 dated 4th May 1943. || • j.o mc_t concs^^ion obligations Oil Company require four lakhs rupees in silver during 1945. I consider the request reasonable and request that Government of India be ask.d to authorise Reserve Bank of India to permit the import of this amount* | V' Political Agent, Bahrain. F . 3 2®9)—24-11 -42— bOO.OCO,COI^IDl^TIAL EXPRESS LETTER Prom Political ReBiaent, Persian Gulf, To Foreign, Delhi, epeateci Political, Bahrain. Bo • C/LEO Dated the ELnd November 1944. Camp, Bahrain. \N Petroleum Concession Limited^ Silver Requirements for 194b. Copy is unclosed of Bahrain Express Letter Do. C/1676 aa tea 21st November 1944. 2. 1 agree with the Political Agent and request that the necessary authorisation may be acco rdeo • V Sd, Geoffrey Prior Political Resident, Persian Gulf a 11 e s t ed • i? or Secretary to The Hon’ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf.Telegram From To Repeated No* 16306# Government of India, New Delhi. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain# Dated and received the 9th December, 1944. vO A 1 • - , ' :' , t Your Express Letter No.C/520 dated November 22nd# 2. Although quaternary Rupees were supplied last year Government of India are unwilling to take action which might imply that metallic Rupees are of highter value than notes and Qatar ? oil concession agreement does not stipulate that payment will be in coin. 3. Grateful to know why payment cannot be made in notes. - FOREIGN - R.U. I.R., 1055.CONFIDENTIAL Political Agency, To The Manager, Messrs, petroleum Concessions Ltd., Reference your letter No.p/CU*1/3349 dated the 18th November 1944. 2. The Government of India have pointed out that under the Qatar Oil concessions it is not obligatory for the Shaik to be paid In rupee coin and have enquired why payment shou not be made in rupee notes. I shall be glad to learn your present objections to paying in rupee notes. The primary reason advanced by my predecessor last year was the negotiations then in progress between the Company and the Shaikh of Qatar. Bahrain c\°\ X MEMORANDUM Political Agent, Bahrain.-apr Telegram From To No. 2217. Dated the 11th and received 12th December, 1944. Q* Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. \0 Government of India telegram No. 16036 dated December 9th. At present juncture the less favour we show Sheikh of Qatar the better. Please see article No. 20 of t - , .• - Oil concession. / - PRIOR -■HMHBHI V-* CQN?IDEI'ITI,U V' DO/CU.1/3878 V' i' ; • C • Xj • , Bahrain. 8th January,* 1945. 10 Dear Major Hickinbotham, SILVER CUMHINCY - QAT.AJI Reference your No. C/1751 dated the 10th December 1944.’ LjjiOo 2. The only reason the Company have paid in silver is that the Ruler of Qatar refuses to take notes or to recognise a credit to his account in the Eastern Ban Ltd.T Bahrain. Under the terms of the_Concession the Comnany can discharge its obligations in respect of the annual concession payment by payment into the Banji, but the Shaikh in 1943 and 1944 steadily refused to accept this method in spite of the fact that the political Agent (Mr. Wakefield) wrote to him pointing out that the Company was within its rights in using the Bans. At this time there was considerable correspondence on the matter, much of it unreasonable, illogical^ana acrimonious on the part of the Shaikh. ’ during his recent visits to Bahrain for dental treatment, made it quite clear that his father would insist on silver again in 1945. The reason t he_ Qatar shaikhs insist on silver is probably as explained in Mr.Wakefield letter D.O.No. c/1021 dated the 28th July 1943 (vide enclosure to a general note attached), from which the following is an epctract v—-- \&gt;\M 'Bedouin are unlikely ever to attach the same 'value to paper currency as to silver coin; and 'as long as Bedouin buy and sell in the markets 'of the Trucial Coast there will always be a 'tendency for silver coin to be regarded as more 'valuable than paper currency.' This probably applies particularly to Qatar which has no direct contacts with the outside world. 3. If the Government of India decide that silver is not to be made available, we would very much appreciate your assistance to avoid a deadlock with the Ruler such as occurred before under similar circumstances.^ 'We feel that a letter from you putting the matter in veryJr 4 p»p' x UO/CU.1/3878 * JI!B r oj tllo mci'i f +r •j. ^ V*- r - 3 - ,i/ 3 c As J »&lt; tn plain terms will 'be necessary, //e v/ould suggest that the following points could be made with advantag (a) That the Government of India has refused to allow the export of silver from India for payments by the Company to the Ruler of Qatar and in these circumstances the Company are unable to obtain silver. Even if the Company could manage to collect silver by any other means, they might not be allowed to export it to Qatar from Bahrain. lb) That notes are legal tender in Qatar. (c) That if the Shaikh will not accept notes the Company is fully within its rights in fulfilling its obligations by payment into the Shaikh’s account with the Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain, and under the terms of the Concession there is no obligation to pay either in silver or notes, 4. Some other aspects of this matter are incorporated in a general note attached to this letter. Yours sincerely, acti 1 5 « 5 ! If it „ - tie s % CO? etifi® • m we ii Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.E., O.B.E., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. 'anager, Petrol ei Bahrain,COPY DO/CU.1/3503 25th July, 1943. j- My dear Wakefield, CURRENCY - TRUCIAL COAST • • As you know we are interested in currency matter^s on the Trucial Coast. Recently we heard that the Shaikh of Dubai had issued a notice that notes and silver rupees were to be accepted as of equal value for purchases or transactions in the bazaar but that any one wishing to acquire silver rupees could be charged up to 3%, We should be interested to hear if this is correct and if the Shaikh has been influenced in making this proclamation by instructions from the Agency. If it is in onder we should also like to Mfl know the situation regarding the tendering of notes and silver in all the shai khdoms and if .i we are correct in assuming that the acceptance i'Jbh n0 ' tes now obligatory on the Trucial ade •ntH* Q 0as -^ generally or only in the sheikhdoms where . ■ snecific proclamations have been made. a has ref® ^ er from theR^ er: ' Yours sincerely, (Sgd. ) E.V.Packer D.B.Wakefield, Esq., I. I.C.S., , cce pt# H.B.M’s Political Agent, Digitsi;,; Bahrain.^BSK£Bifii|RWPl KSK^i COPY D.O. No.C/1021 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 28th July 1945. CURR My dear Packer, Will you please refer to your letter No.DO/CU.l/ 3505 dated the 25th July 1943. 2. The report which you received about the notice issued by the Shaikh of Dubai in regard to rupee notes and silver rupees is correct. A similar notice has been issued by the Shaikh of Sharjah. The Shaikhs of Dubai and Sharjah issued these notices at my suggestion since trade was beginning to suffer as a result of the heavy premium on silver rupees at Dubai and Sharjah. 2. I have given no advice on this subject to other Rulers on the Trucial Coast and I imagine that in Abu Dhabi, Has al Khaimah etc., the silver rupee isat a substantial premium over the rupee note. Bedouin are unlikely ever to attach the same value to paper currency as to silver coin; and as long as Bedouin buy and sell in the markets of the Trucial Coast there will always be a tendency for silver coin to be regarded as more valuable than paper currency. SNCY - TRUCIAL COAST Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) E.B.Wakefield S.Y. Packer, Esq., Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain. cpd/ACMCONFIDENTIAL NOTE ON SILVER CURRENCY - QATAR - JANUARY 1945 (Enclosure to P.C.L. letter No. DO/CU.1/3878 dated the 8th January 1945 addressed to Political Agent, Bahrain.) From the year 1937, when the Concession payments were taken over, the Company acceded to the Ruler of Qatar’s request to he paid in silver rupees. It was understood^that silver coins were necessary for payments to the pearlers and subsidies to Bedouins. In addition, Qatar was and is largely dependent upon the dhow traffic of her neighbours for the majority of foodstuffs and commodities, and silver was in general the most acceptable form of currency. Incidentally, for some years notes were very difficult to obtain in Bahrain. A situation was thus created in which silver was preferred for circulation and notes even if required or acceptable were unobtainable in sufficient quantities. This established a precedent as regards the Company’s payments to Qatar. With the outbreak of war silver was in great demand and Government measures, it is understood, had to be published to introduce and stabilise the general use of notes in Bahrain and on the Trucial Coast. Up to quite recently 4% to 10% was charged on notes at Dubai and Sharjah. The situation in Dubai and Sharjah at one time resulted in Airways and Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. themselves demanding payment in silver. Qatar, in its somewhat isolated position, that is, without regular steamer com munications, has very naturally been among the last to lose suspicion of notes. The precise position^at the^ t moment in Qatar and the Trucial Coast on the silver vis-a- vis note Question is not known, but it would seem natural to assume'that, if the Ruler is very insistent on silver, this points to the fact that he still expects to lose on notes or lose possible advantages from silvejj^ Copies of two letters No. DO/CU.1/3503 dated the £5th July 1943 and DO.No. e/1021 dated the 28th July 1943, which passed between the Company and the Agency on this subject, are attached. fC~J As far as the Company is concerned, the position is that the Shaikh can be expected to refuse to accept a credit to his account in the Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain, or pay ments in notes. In 1943 he refused to acknowledge the Company’s action in crediting his account, and returned the Bank’s advice. As will probably be remembered, it was eventually arranged for him to be paid in silver some months after the payment was due. For 1944 the Company was again permitted to obtain silver. It was assumed that general currency conditions in Qatar accounted for the grant of the permit. Minor recurring charges and salaries are still paid by the company in silver. It is not known if there is any legislation affecting this currency problem in Qatar. Naturally the Company would prefer to pay the Shaikh’s dues as they arise by crediting his account in the Eastern Bank Ltd. and other miscellaneous payments in notes, but in order to preserve amicable relations, the Company is prepared to continue payments in silver as long as silver is procurable and the freight, insurance and other Bank charges are v/ithin reason.■hhMnmh jmmumamm - 2 - If the Government of India does not sanction the export of silver for 1945 (and subsequent years), tnerc will be a repetition of the 1943 deadlock as regards Qatar unless H.M.G. intervenes. From the Company's experience in 1943 it would seem that the only effective form of intervention will be a very definite intimation by the British Government that the Ruler of Qatar must accept notes and ensure that his subjects also accept their wages in notes. An ordinary notification that notes are legal tender will not meet the case. Some similar intimation may also be expected to be^ necessary in respect of rulers and tribal leaders entering into new oil agreements with the Company. In this con nection please refer to our letter No.P/CU.1/3849 dated the 18th November 1944 para 3. L-h r In April 1943 the Managing Director gave a ruling und er : - 'The Company agrees to bear the extra cost of 'payment in silver but whether or not we should 'continue to pay in silver is a matter for the 'Political Agent to decide and you should abist© u by his decision.' Ends: 2 P.C.L. , Bahrain, 8th January 1945. ACM ^-i VSKlgmCONFIDENTIAL No.C/41. Political Agency, Bahrain, 9th January 1945, From To Sir, or T* Hickinbotham, C.I*E., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. The Hon’lde the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I haYe the honour to refer to your telegram No.2217 dated the 11th December 1944 and to enclose a copy of a letter, No.DO/CU.1/3878 dated the 8th of January 1945 with enclosures, which I have received from the General Manager of Messrs. Petroleum Concessions Limited which was in answer to my mamo- randum No.C/1751 dated the 10th of December 1944 (a copy of which is enclosed) which was issued on receipt of Government of India telegram No.16306 dated the 9th December 1944. 2. The Shaikh of Qatar f s present unreasonable and stubborn attitude is in some measure due to the policy of appeasement which it has been necessary to follow for the past few years but I consider th^t the time has come when it is no longer desirable for such a policy to be continued and that we should advise the Company to adhere strictly to the conditions of the Qatar Oil Agreement. 3. I therefore suggest that I inform Messrs, petroleum Concessions Limited that the Hon f ble the Political Resident is not prepared to press the Government of India to permit the export of quarternary rupees as, in accordance with the provi sions of Article 20 of the Qatar Oil Concession Agreement, the Company are within their rights in either making payment in rupee notes or by crediting the shaikh*s account with the Eastern Bank Limited, Bahrain. 4. I do not consider it necessary or desirable for any communication to be made by this Agency to the shaikh of Qatar /atV mammmm at this juncture. Should he protest to us however against payment by the Company not being made in silver coin then I suggest he be told that there is no condition of the Agreement which prescribes silver coin as the medium of payment and that the Company has acted entirely correctly in making payment in accordance with Clause 20 Of the Agreement. ■ I shall be grateful for telegraphic instructions. I have the hohour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, r W9/. Political Agent, BahrainiTelegram Q. i . , f ^ 1 From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain* No. Nil. Dated the 15th and received 16th January, 1945. Your letter No. C/41 dated January 9th Payments to Shaikh of Qatar. 2. I agree. , ' i . PRIOR -ts/b No.C/116, Political Agency, Bahrain, 23rd January 1945. ( 3 ) To The Manager, Messrs. Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM y- 0 I have been instructed by the Hon'ble the Political Reference your DO/CU.1/3878 dated the 8th January 1945. 2 . Resident in the Persian Gulf to inform you that he is not prepared to press the Government of India to permit the export of quarternary rupees as, in accordance with the provisions of Article 20 of the Qatar Oil Concession Agreement, the Company are within their rights In either making payment in rupee notes or by crediting the Shaikh f s account with the Eastern Bank Limited, Bahrain. / /r 2r/ political Agent, Bahrain.— *.*“ ; sap® ^■■bhhumshhh CONFIDSHTXAL V DO/sA.2/3911 ©i P • 0 # L • ) Bahrain, EOth February, 1945. 3^ My dear Major Hickinbotham,. V I enclose a draft which I propose to send to the Shaikh of Qatar. I trust the wording of my reference to the Govern ment of India is in order. Yours sincerely, Fncl. Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.E., H.B.M 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain.draft \\^&gt; H,E*Shaikh Abdulla bin Q.asim al Thani, Ruler of Q,atar. Your Excellency, We have the honour to refer to the annual concession payment which falls due on the 17th May 1945. We regret to have to bring to your notice that we are unable to obtain silver rupees from the Government of India, and in these circum stances we should be pleased to hear if Tour Excellency wishes us to pay the sums due into the Eastern Bank, Bahrain, as is provided for in Article 20 of the Concession, or if you would prefer us to deliver the amount in notes at Ziekrit. We have been notified that notes, besides being legal tender, are now accepted everywhere on the Trucial Coast, and there is no justification for making any exceptions in the case of Q,atar payments. Re would add tliat it is useless foi\us t&lt; press \he Government x $o reconsider \©cision, and we ^an do r^p more \n this r&amp;atter.\ more £j We have the honour to be, v ~vr«iv- ' - Confidential No.C/274 &lt;g) igi The Political Agency, Bahrain, the 24th February 1945. To - E*V. Packer, Esquire, Petroleum Concessions Ltd., Bahrain. Memorandum Reference your letter D.O./SA.2/3911, dated 20th February 1945. 2. I see no objection. 7c - Political Agent. S. ' ' ^BISIRRSRUHnt&amp; HOTS gQR DISCUSSION WITH THE P.X.' 9TH OF APRIL 1945 rrenoy for Concession and yments in Qatar - Situation 5th BB3E35T^5yTX [ I ) The Buler was informed on the 14th March 1945 that the Company was unable to obtain silver currency for the payment of the annual concession payment of 3 lacs odd due on 17th May 1945 {see Q/SA. E/3927). In his reply the Buler made the following points (i) Payments must be in silver as this is the legal and official currency in Qatar. (ii) The Buler has the right to refuse any other kind of currency. (iii) Previous payments have always been in silver. (iv) In recognition of the Company*s difficulties, the Buler was prepared to accept j half silver, half notes, for j 1945 only. The Buler is fully aware that under Article 20 of the Concession the Company’s obligation is dis charged by paying into the Eastern Bank. This has been repeatedly brought to the Shaikh's notice and was actually confirmedvi by Mr. Wakefield in 1943 in his No.C/969 dated the 18th July 1943 to the Buler. In effect the Shaikh deliberately ignores Article 20 sheltering behind what amounts to 'the divine right** of Rulers to interpret or change Concession Agreements as they wish. He also ignores Mr. Wakefield's ruling. Experience has shewn that it is quite useless for the Company to expect the Shaikh to listen to their arguments, and unless silver can be procured, or some strong influence brought to bear by the Political Department, a deadlock is inevitable. In these difficult circumstances, the Company is wondering whether the Political Department would consider addressing the Buler direct in the matter and notifying him of the contents of the Political Agent’s No.C/116 dated the 23rd January 1945 addressed to the Company, which states the attitude of the Hon'ble the Political Resident and also puts on record that the Company are within their rights in making noE - payments in Hupee notes or by crediting the Shaikh’s account with the Eastern Bank. There4re grounds for belief that such a notification might have the desired effect in 1945. e Company is faced with three ternatives in respect of the 1945 yment. ) To accede to the Ruler’s demand I for half silver, half notes. This happens to be possible as the Company have some silver deposits in the Bank. An export permit covering 1| lacs odd will j be necessary. i) To insist on the Shaikh accept ing notes. It is feared that^ this will cause considerable ill-* feeling and it is to be expected that some form of Government support on the abovementioned lines will prove necessary. ii) To pay the whole amount to the credit of the Shaikh’s account with the Eastern Bank. 1 This conforms to Article £0 of the Concession. It is to be expected that the Shaikh will repeat his previous tactics and repudiate the transaction entirely unless Government influence is brought to bear in this case also. (i) and (ii) are discarded (iii) comes almost essential as, should controversy continue beyond May th, the Company must cover itself der Article SO of the Concession. I . all the circumstances, and as May is close, it would appear desir- le to adopt course (i) for this ax explaining to the Shaikh that * fortunate chance the Company this ar happened to have some silver posits already in Bahrain. Condi- ons might change in 1946. e Shaikh’s policy in the whole matter pears to be to confine the issue 1 himself and the Company. He is ^lly convinced that the Company, if ‘eased and harassed sufficiently, •11 collect the silver by hook or r crook, and the Company will be able • obtain H.M.G’s co-operation as iquired. It is this conviction which t necessary to dispel, and the only ithod would appear to be by direct mtact between H.M.G and the Shaikh. IHBB /C : ! .. A-. *£U. CONFIDENTIAL P.C.L., Bahrain. /i 'Vr DO/3A.2/3947 15th April, 1945. My dear Felly, OATAF ANNUAL CONCSSSIQN PAWlENT - MAY 1945 1. With reference to correspondence on the subject of payments to the Ruler of Qatar in silver, which ended with your C/116 dated the 23rd of January, and our sub- seouent conlversation on the 9th of April, v-fa )| ^ 2. We confirm herewith that in all the circumstances, we feel that our best course is to accede to the Ruler’s request, for the annual payment for 1945 to b e made half in silver and half in notes. As explained on the 9th of April, this happens to be possible this year as the Company has some silver deposits in the Eastern Bank, Bahrain, but, in view of your C/116, we shall not inform the Ruler to this effect until we get your confirmation that this course is approved. 3. The silver we hold in the Eastern Bank was^ imported by the Company at Company expense for payments in connec tion with concessions, and is held by the Eastern Bank for safe custody only. We mention this to show that silver in or for circulation in Bahrain will not be affected by the Qatar transaction. Yours sincerely, C.J.Felly, Esq., I.C.S., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, ^ D D.O. No. C/472. Dated the 21st April, 1945. '^• XN My dear packer, • Taank you for your letter No. DO/SA.2/394.7 dated zhe 15th April, 1945. I approve of the course of action referred to in paragraph 2 thereof. • Yours sincerely, vsfeE? &amp;#■ packer. Esc*., Messrs. Petroloi^ra concessions, Ltd., 3 a h r a i n.J*Ji 10/3 Telegram. , Q. From. To. Repeated No. 13621 I Dated 16th and received 17th June 1945. Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. f nL Iraq Petroleum Company propose to send Mr. 7/atts to Bahrain,Qatar to investigate prospects of obtaining labour A for development of Qatar oil field. Please telegraph whether any objection. - 13TAXANDUM - LR I.R. 415eg) -ts&gt; , Leg ram. )rn. 10/3 Q. Political Agent, Bahrain. H.M’s Consul, Bushire. ' 373 ed 19th June 1945. Reference India Office telegram No. 13621 dated 16th June I have no objection but it may be well to inform |hatts that there is no repeat no labour available in Bahrain ■and amount available at end pearling season in October is ■tful. Qatar may be worth trying. POLITICAL88/27. ,1 \ C Telegram From To No.1112. Dated tne 20th June, 1045* Britain, Bushire. Secretary of State for India, London BAHRAIN RECEIBT. No.,/i7. Data... l J...h■/.££■■■ Your telegram No.13621 June 16th. Watts. 2. No objection. 3. Political Agent Bahrain reports that while labour may be available in Qatar, none is now obtainable in Bahrain and availability at end of pearling season In October Is doubt ful. Suggest Company be informed accordingly. LB* - BRITAIN - CONFIDENTIAb No »(i72-S ^ , Persian Gulf Residency, BUSHIRE, ® 0 ~£.?J..fZ.Da.te..(0. ■)■ Vr 2Cth June, 1945. Copy forwarded with compliments tos- The Political Agent, BAHRAIN , with rei'orence to ills telegram No. 378 dated the 19th June, 1945. LB.\ &gt;A PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN RECEIPT, BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. DO/SA. 2/4025 Dated 17th September, 1945 My dear Pelly, I enclose herewith in original a letter from the Shaikh of Qatar on the subjects of the re-opening of Qatar oil operations and an advance of money. A draft of my reply thereto is also enclosed. Before despatching the letter to the Shaikh I should like your assurance that my references to the Political Agent and His Majesty’s Government in paras 2 and 4 are in order and there is no objection to them. next day or two and if possible I should like to send the Shaikh a reply by it. If you return the enclosures I will send you copies in due course. There is a launch returning to Qatar within the Yours sincerely, C. J. Pelly, Esq. , I.C.S., H. B. M’s Political Agent, B a h r e i n.D.O. No. C/894 The 18th September, L945. f } My dear Packer, Reference your letter No* DO/SA*2/4025 dated the 17th September, 1945. I an afraid I can find no record that the suspension of the Company’s operations in Qatar was H explained to Your Excellency by H.B.M.»s Political Agent, Bahrain”. Nor is it clear from my file that ”the company’s operations in Qatar were suspended under arrangements made, by His f^ajesty’s Government.' i have no doubt that the phrasing you use in the first sentence of paragraph 2 of your draft does express fairly well what happened but, as I say, my records do not confirm the specific expressions used. I am having a further search made in them which may result in my being able to give you the assurance you ask on these points. c ' 2. It is, however, quite clear from my record that the suspension of the Company’s operations was made in agreement with His Majesty’s Government and perhaps some phrase to that effect would suit your purpose. 3. I see no objection to the reference made to the Political Agent in paragraph 4 of your draft. 4. i return the enclosures to your letter and should be glad to receive copies in due course. 5. Since I returned from Shiraz on the 6th of this month, I have had a great deal of work to do. When the pressure is less I hope to be able to go to see you. cker, Esq., M.B.E., srs. Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., Yours sincerely, CDO/SA.S/4026 Wy dear Pelly, Reference your D # 0. No. September, 1945. C/894 of the 18 th I enclose a new draft with specific references to your correspondence with the Shaikh and you ?d.ll note that I quote the specific expression used by the Political Agent to explain the suspension. Please return the draft and the Shaikh’s letter and I will send you copies in due course Yours sincerely, C. J. Pelly, Esc., I.C.S., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Enel: 2./ 'i ■■ POLITICAL AGKNCY, BAHRAIN. IX) 0.0. No. C/900. The 20th Saptenter, 1945. S 3 '') My dear Packer, Reference your letter No* DO/SA*2/4026 dated the 19th September, 1946* The references to the political Agent in paragraph 2 of your new draft are quite in order and there is no objection to them. 2. I return to you the Shaikh*3 letter and the draft of which, I have noted, you will be sending me a copy. Yours sincerely, 7 &lt; r. Packer, Esq., M.B.E., Messrs. Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., // Bahrainwm ‘ L — 1 Q/SA.2/4025 Bahrein, 23rd September, 1945. His Excellency Shaikh Abdulla bin ^asimAl r Thani, Ruler of Qatar, D o h a h. * Excellency, v iV We have the hp^our to acknowledge dated 23rd Ramadhan 1364 / (31st August, 1945)^. 2. Your Excellency will remember/that in the Political ^gent f s letter No.C/924 of 1942 of 28th June 1942 you were informed that 'as a result of the war His Majesty* s Government have found it necessary to direct the Oil Company to suspend its operations in your territory’. The conditions of the suspension were the subject of an agreement between 2 Your Excellency and the Political Agent dated 28th Dul Q,adah 1362 (26th November 1943). The reason neighbouring Companies were permitted to continue their work was that at the outbreak of war they were already producing petrol and kerosene ready for use for war purposes. Your Excellency will understand that the Company having spent very large sums of money in Qatar so far without any return for this expenditure, is just as anxious as Your Excellency to produce oil and thus get money. ihe Company could not resume operations without the agreement of the Government. ipwo days ago we received a letter from our Managing Director, London, instructing us to inform Your Excellency that the company has been authorised to reopen Qatar operations. The first stage, commencing early in 1946, will be the preparation of Dukhan Camp for the drilling programme. Mr. Dickson and our Assistant Manager, Haifa, have already visited Dukhan to ascertain what is necessary. We will give Your Excellency at least two months* notice of the reopening of the camp. The actual drilling, it^ is hoped, will commence towards the end of 1946. The extent of the drilling programme depends on the supply of drilling machinery, other necessary equiament and qualified personnel. Our Managing Director realises the importance Your Excellency attaches to the early development of the Qatar oil field and has promised to keep us all informed if the situation improves and the work can be expedited or expanded. 4 . With regard to the question of an advance of money the arrangement made at my last visit to Your Excellency was that we should wait for the arrival of the Managing Director or his personal representative and put the matter to him verbally. We discussed the reasons for this procedure. Unfortunately the long promised visit has not materialised■IflHMflMMlMMHMHHllM - 2 - although expected as soon as the hot weather is over. If Your Excellency wishes to change the plan and would like a letter to he written this can he done immediately. Your Excellency will understand that the Company is expected to keep the Political ^gent informed on all matters affecting the teims of our oil concessions and applications for advances in respect of oil royalties would come under this category. We shall await confirmation from Your Excellency before writing .any letters. Usual ending. We have the honour to be Your Excellency’s most obedient servants, For &amp; on behalf of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited (s^d,) jc. r. fw** 7 '' Manager./Zr COI'CFIDENTIAL » No. C/ 963 . political Agency, Bahrain, The 4th October ’ 1945 ' The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compli ments to: The Hon«ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the document ( s.) ^ f or information* Reference to previous correspon entioned Description o f enclosure NAME &amp; DATE SUBJECT P*C.L. letter No. Q/SA. 2/4023; Re-opening of Qatar Oil dated the 23rd September' ; Operations 1945, to the Ruler of Qatar. ; NS. i »CONFIDENTIAL DO/SA. 2/4070. My dear Colonel Petroleum Concessions Ltd. Bahrain. 3rd December 1945. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. NO...O./.4 ADVANCE OF OIL ROYALTIES TO THE RULER OF QATAR. The Shaikh of Qatar has approached me on the subject of an advance of oil royalties of five lacs of rupees. I am referring his request to Mr. Skliros, our Managing Director. Yours sincerely, Lt.-Col. A. C. Galloway, O.B.E., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain./ jfl ■ Reference my printed Letter No. c/963, dated the 4th October, 1945. 2. Mr. packer has informed me that the Sheikh of Qatar has asked for an advance of five lacs of rupees on P.C.L. oil royalties and that he is referring matter to Mr. Skliros. 3. The Sheikh has said nothing to me of the matter, but no action seems called for at this stage* N3. political Agent, Bahrain.DEHTIAL ,.2/4080 B AHR XVi nrrnjr-r-prp ETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. f BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. 18th December 1945 My dear Bird, ADVANCE ON FUTURE OIL ROYALTIES TO THE RULER OF QATAR. 5-35 in my No #4-070 dated 3rd December we Informed Col# Galloway that the shaikh of Qatar had approached us for an advance of five lacs of rupees on future oil royalties and that we were referring the matter to our Managing Director, London* 2. London have agreed to the advance without interest, recoverable by annual instalments not exceeding twenty per cent of the advance. Recoveries will only be made in years when oil royalties exceed three lacs# Our Managing Director adds that his agreement is subject to there being no objection from the Political Agent# Y/e understand that The Eon*ble the Political Resident is now in Bahrain, but Colonel Galloway is away. In these circumstances and to take advantage of the presence of the Political Resident we are not waiting for Colonel Galloway 5 s return# If it is appropriate perhaps you will be good enough to bring the matter to the Political Resident 5 s notice# Yours sincerely. Capt R.E.R.Bird,’ &gt; EXPRESS LETTER . prom - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - political Resident, Bushir No. C/1143. Dated the 27th of December, 1945. / Reference my memorandum No. C/1118 of the 10th December, 1945. 2 . 3 . • Packer has written to say that 'London have agreed to the advance without interest, recoverable by annual instalments not exceeding twenty per cent of the advance. Recoveries will only be made in years when oil royalties exceed three lacs. Our Managing Director adds that his agreement is subject to there being no objection from the Political Agent.' (a) With regard to the loan itself the terms seem generous. / / (b) With regard to the political aspect, the point occurs to me whether we should permit the Sheikh of Qatar to make whatever use he likes of the loan, or advise him that a certain sum should be utilised for State improvements in education, medical facilities etc. 4. think, soon have to be done in Something will,.I connection with such facilities but T am of the opinion that now, for one reason because of the postponement in drilling necessitated by the war, we need make no reference to the Sheikh and may inform P.C.L. that there is no political objection to the loan. 5. Packer. I should be grateful to know what I may reply to Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. for Assistant Political Agent, jd Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OR INDIA; Dbfabtmint, lONITDSKTIAL. EXPRESS LETTER [N, B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] ?ROM Po lit i oal Re si de^t, ’ P er s ±^a Gulf. Do Copy to The Political Agent, Bahrain. Vo. s* S' rj OQ * H.ijr.'s Secretary of State for India, The India Office^ LOPTXP T&gt; , The Secretary to the Government of Inara / una , -i rexer- in the External Affairs Department, )ence. xSoMdt BM -SSM* 9^ .' the nth January 1946. loan to Shaik h of j^atar ^'“petroleum peveXop ment twith copy of } c oiamun 1 ca t i qvj d. MaiCE^TDLTM. q \ a.'S.'V Reference your mefflorandup V.o.O/lllo, ■i-O th &amp;. 1945, and your Bxpreae letter Ho.C/1143, dated 27th Decemoer x. 2. 1 agree with the views expressed in P a ^fraph 4 of your Express letter under reference. The sura is not large in corap-xison ^enta and i igarding the disposal ^ -- ,. . , - a Packer that there is no political objection to tne lo-«n • Sd. GBOWRSY PRIOR. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested. . for Secretary to the Lticai Resident, Persian Gulf. KEL. ■ S, 6. S&amp;P—(M-820)—23-7-30—300,000. REOEira |li} f*n D » Q.No.C/94 « Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the 21st January, 1946, O \ / ' ! &gt; \ \ &gt; ) ^£2Sr - My dear Packer, Please refer to your letter No.DO/SA.2/4080 dated the 18th December, 1945 to Bird. I am to inform you tha.t there is no political objection to the loan. Yours sincerely, E.V.Packer, Bsqr., Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain.) - &gt; \r ({ ' r- .A N 1% tr',/ \ PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAH RAIN PERSIAN GULF. DO/QOM.12/4180 10th April, 1946 My dear Colonel, As you have probably heard, we are to open up our Qatar camp very shortly and the question oi the rate of pay to be given to our labourers has now to be decided. 2. 1 have had a letter from the Shaikh pointing out reasons why the pay should be high. I think he is more interested in the guards and the Customs man whose salaries are paid to him than he is in the ordinary labour paid direct by the Company, but I feel it is probably desirable to state' the Company T s case clearly at this juncture. 3. In framing my letter I have decided to explain the situation quite frankly and give the rate and conditions the Company intend to adopt. That is, in quoting a ra e of Rs.l/8/- plus free food I leave no margin for the usuc?&gt;l bargaining tactics of the Shaikh. I could have mae a ess strong case for paying Rs.l/4/- and then rrsen to Rs.1/8/- under pressure. I prefer to put forward a perfec b . case and the final considered offer, and 1 ^ ^ permit me to refer to you as I do in tne attached sug 0 este draft the Company’s proposals will be accepted. 4. If the Shaikh should refer this matter to you in con versation I should like to be in a position to Kin v you agree with the Company’s contentions in ray 5 . If you can spare the time to give me your comments I should be most grateful as this is an impor S a controversial matter which may have repercus Bahrain and on the Trucial Coast. 6 . Our comparisons with Bapco may not oe considered desirable from some aspects but we are on ^ ° re f ^^-©t the Shaikh of Qatar in quoting otner Companies. I3 —w' A - 2 - DO/qCM.12/4180 (contd.) in first with a legitimate comparison it may keep him from bringing in more remote places such as Kuwait where conditions and rates are unknown to us and argu ment correspondingly difficult. Yours sincerely, ifincls. 2 Lt.-Col. A.C.Galloway, O.B.E., H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain.) IH TRANSLATION From: Abdulla bin Qasim al Thani, Ruler of Qatar. To: The Most Respected Manager of P.D.Qo Ltd* I wish to bring to your notice an important point to which I have referred in some of my previous letters. You are doubtless aware of existing conditions and the crisis from which people are suffering in these days. It is known that prices of all commodities have increased with the unsettled conditions. These unsettled conditions here caused many changes resulting in high prices and living has been difficult. The cost of the requirements of the employees have increased much more than the corresponding increases in wages. In Qatar we have felt this depression in the same way as it was felt elsewhere. As a result of this we are not able to get employees on anall wages. Your wages for employees are small viewed under present conditions, for example, the gaards, the chief of Customs and the guard commander cannot be obtained on such pay as you are giving. In fact it does not support them due to the high cost of living. You are aware that the situation of all employees in all districts is being considered in the light of present conditions. We hope that you will give this your attention and judge it fairly and do what appears to you the right thing. I write this on the occasion of the reopening of the Company*s work in a short time. Hoping that you will agree to what I have stated and make the increases to the employees in accordance with present conditions. Please accept compliments. (Sealed) Abdulla bin Qasim al Thani. Date - Djanada l/5/l365-.April 7/1946.draft /&lt;// H.S.Shaikh Abdulla bin Q,asim al Thani, Ruler of Qatar, Doha. Excellency, We have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated the 5th Jamad I 1365 (corresponding to 7th April 1946). We would bring to Your Excellency’s notice that the fact that there has been increase in the cost of living due to the war in this area has been taken into consideration by all the employers of labour and a committee has been working in Bahrain throughout the war under the guidance of the Political Agent to agree on equitable rates for this area. As Your Excellency is aware increased cost of living can be minimised by careful control of the prices and equal dis tribution under arrangements made by the Governments concerned. It is well recognised that increases in wages alone does not help an employee if prices are allowed to rise with wages, and only the merchants grow rich. All these factors have been taken into account by the committee in fixing equitable wages and the help that can be given to employees. The greatest difficulty is to help the employee get food without giving up all his pay to profiteers. This help is firstly provided by the Government controlling issues and prices and secondly by employers helping where circumstances make this advisable by supplying some items ox food at cheap rates. In some cases employers provide food and make their rates of pay araller. Our policy regarding this matter is to conform as closely as possible to other local employers with due regard to circum stances, and, in fixing our rates f or‘the reopening of the work in Qatar, we must take the advice and get the approval of the Political Agent. It may be difficult to get him to agree to the conditions we propose because they seem better than those of the Bahrein Petroleum Company, the biggest employer of£ /tCs labour in the area. On the grounds that at the present time it is very difficult for our Qatari employees working at Dukhan to purchase and cook their own food and their families cannot share the daily purchases of such food, we propose to supply for some time to come food free. Your Excellency will realise that the Company can only supply items which they are able to procure but in any case this food will cost the Company very much money. The Bahrein Petroleum Company do not supply free food and their normal basic rate to new labour is Rs.l/12/- which is increased to Rs.l/l4/- after 1 month and rising to Rs.£/- in six months. These rates do not apply to casual labour for which the rate is Rs.l/e/-. From this pay the majority of their labourers have to meet Company transport charges at the rate of 6 annas to 8 annas per day which reduces their daily money considerably. Our proposal under present conditions is to pay labour at the rate of Rs.l/8/- per day and free food and our justifica tion for these conditions which are better than Bapco is that the employees are a long way from their homes and families and have to provide for them separately. It may be mentioned that in Bahrain the married labourer pays for his own food as well as that of his family whereas this Company T s labourer pays only for the food of his family. We would add that the war is now over and special war allowances to labourers have been discontinued in this area. We would add that as we do not require very many labourers at the commencement of work it will soon be apparent by the numbers of labourers applying for jobs as to whether or not our terms are attractive. Since the news has got round here that we are reopening Qatar the office has been besieged with applicants for work. We trust that the Political Agent will have no objection to our rates of Rs.l/ 8 /- per day.) - 3 - c I think Your Excellency will admit that the Company in the past has enjoyed an excellent reputation for the treat ment of its employees in Q,atar and I think you can rely on the Company to continue to treat them with consideration and equity. I am pleased to inform Your Excellency that Mr. Dickson has now arrived in Bahrain and will he reopening Dukhan camp in a few days f time. At first our requirements of labour will he small hut as more equipment arrives there will he a steady increase. Mr. Dickson will he sending to Doha for his first requirements of labour and no action should he taken until he sends a written request stating the number. As regards Your Excellency 1 s request for a revision in the pay of the guards and guard commander and the Customs representative at Zekrit we have the following points to bring to your notice (a) The guard commander and the guards were concerned in the pulling down and the theft of over 10 miles of the Company’s telephone wire, that is, of property which they were paid to safeguard. In these circum stances it is difficult for us to recommend to London that they should be given more pay. On the under standing that the persons concerned in the theft will not he sent hack to any Company camps we are prepared to recommend that the guards’ rate he increased from Rs.45/- to Rs.60/- per mensem. (h) As regards the guard commander and the Customs rep resentative at Zekrit, it must he taken into account that the war is now over and the cost of living is on the decline. As, however, the general standard of wages has risen and seems likely to remain at its present level for some time to come, we propose to recommend an increment of Rs.50/- per mensem in each il 1 ‘i case.- 4 - In conclusion, we would bring it to Your Excellency f s notice that the Company have examined the question of the pay of labourers very carefully, and in making this decision to pay labourers at the rate of Rs,l/8/- plus free food, provided the Political Agent has no objection, the Company has reached its limit and we trust the Company’s good intentions will be recognised by every one concerned. It should be clearly understood that the Company does not undertake to continue to supply free food but should this arrangement be cancelled wage rates will be reconsidered./ Translation of letter dated 11th Jamad auwal 1365 (13-4-46) from H.H. the Huler of Bahrain to the Political Agent, ^ nanraxn, ' ’ A.C. V B’or your information I forward herewith a petition submitted to ns by a number of diving chiefs regarding the engagement of Bahrain people for work in Qatar, Your Excellency is aware that the diving work in Bahrain comes in the first grade after oil. The war has ended and we hope that the diving work will resume its previous importance. In this country large amounts of money have been invested in diving work, and it is the sole business to which the Bahrain Arabs have been giving much importance. We have heard that the Qatar Oil Company (P.C.L.) have been recruiting labourers to work in Qatar, from the Bahrain residents and our subjects among whom there are many diving sailors. The Qatar Oil Company (P.C.L.) has been giving conditions which will cause a greyious disturb ance in the local situation. It is that the Company wants to encourage our subjects to go to Qatar by giving them wage** higher than the average of the highest wages prevailing at present in Bahrain. In view of the present circumstances we do not desire to allow them to go to Qatar. You know that the positions in Qatar are very much different from those in Bahrain. In Bahrain we have regulations to protect the rights of all people, but in Qatar they are no regulations. For this reason we cannot allow them to go from Bahrain to Qatar, unless we are given guarantees for the protection of their rights, and that they will be treated justly, which will be impossible unless the British Government appoints a representative in Qatar on her behalf to whom our subjects can put up their grievances, when necessary, or we will have a representative with the Company to look after the interests) fTo r !? n ^w ion 0:fk P e1:ition dated llth Jamad auwal 1365 ^13^4-46;from the undersigned persons to His Highness the liuler or Bahrain. A.C. We, the undersigned, are diving nakhudas and pearl- merchants in Bahrain. We submit to Your Highness that the Qatar (Oil) Company has started to recruit labourers from tae Bahrain people. Your Highness is aware that most of these, who will be employed by this Company, are diving sailors and they are indebted to us with large amounts. Besides they have taken the 'tisqam' (money advanced in winter) for the 1365 season. This action will weaken our business, hinder the diving system and our monetary position, and our monies will be wasted for the benefit of Qatar people. We will come into unsuitable position as a result of this action. We are aware of the efforts you have been taking to improve this country and its people. We also draw Your Highness * attention to a more important question, and it is that when the pearl-diving season approaches, some of the sailors try to leave Bahrain as sailors in sailingcraft or other else with the intention of running away from diving, through which the money of the nakhuda will be wasted, It is impossible to stop it unless you issue your high order to the Passport Department to prevent any of the diving sailors or those who have connection in diving trying to leave Bahrain as it was the practice. We request your high kindness to consider our case with justice and attention, because it is one of the important matters. U.E. 36 Bahrain nakhudas signed.No.C/407. The 17th April, 1946 My dear packer I have received a letter Prom His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain in which he states that P.C.L. (Qatar) Limited are engaging Bahrain divers with the object oi taKing then to Qatar for work in the oil field there, 2 , in view of the present circum stances he does not wish then to go there since it is doubtful if, he states, their rights will be fully protected. He requests me to look into the question and says that he is prepared to come to an understanding. To what understanding he does not say. 3. I should be grateful if you would let me have your comments. Yours sincerely, ^•Pucker, Ssq., M.B.B., Messrs, petroleum Concessions Limited Bah rain.\ i@) /^to r.O. NO.C/408 The 17th of April, 1946 My dear Packer, Will yon please refer to your letter No. no/ QCM.12/4180 dated the 10th April, 1946? 2 . I do not like the idea of your starting to issue free rations, especially while at the same time, so far as I know, the rates you are proposing compare favourably with the basic rates of pay in Bahrain. You do not say what the value of the ration is, and without knowing that approximately it makes it even more difficult for me to comment. rates - whatever you may propose they should be - and at the same time make provision for rations on repayment? 3 Is there any reason why you should not pay normal Yours sincerely, vil Packer, Esq., M.B.E., Messrs. Petroleum Concessions Limited BAHRAIN.l / 1, I i / cS/ ^ CONFIDENTIAU DO/^CM.12/4201 lly dear Colonel, PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAH RAIN PERSIAN GULF. 21st April 1946. s V Will you please refer to your ^io.C/407 dated the 17th April 1946. 2. In your first para I notice you use the word 'divers' and not 'labourers' and the possibility occurred to me that 'divers” was a typing error for 'drivers'. 3. In any case the company’s principle is to engage Qataris only until such time as all Qatari categories which are employable are absorbed. 4. In cases where Qatar cannot produce a man with the necessary qualifications for a particular post, it is understood that the Company is at liberty under certain conditions laid down in the ] A L. Concession to recruit non-Qataris. Before recruiting any / Bahrainis we should make it our business to ascertain that there Mu is no objection from H.H. the Ruler of Bahrain (through you ?) or ***»**&gt;» H.E. the Shaikh of Qatar. 5. Unofficially, I think you will agree with me that the Shaikh of Qatar will object to Bahreinis being employed by us even more strongly than His Highness. Since drafting this letter I have received a letter from the Shaikh of Qatar impressing on us that no non-Qataris should be taken on as long as there are Qataris who can perform the work. 6. I suggest, if you think it appropriate, that you should assure His Highness that Company Recruiting Officers in Bahrain and Dukhan (Qatar; will be instructed not to engage Bahreinis direct. I would, however, add that it is our custom to send to Dohah for recruits who are vouched for by the Shaikh’s representa tive. This means that it might be possible for Bahreinis to be engaged if they went to Dohah but improbable in view of para 5. This would seem also outside the province of the Company and a matter for settlement between the two Rulers. 7. Meanwhile, if Mr. Dickson has inadvertently engaged a Bahraini for work in Qatar, which I think is most unlikely, I will take steps to see that the man is discharged or employed in Bahrain. Confidential. Bahrain receipt. Date 2- A -4 • 4.4- T ^e»4K&gt;DO/QCM.12/4201 Incidentally we engaged here for Qatar several Qataris employed by us in Qatar previously who have been working during the war in Bahrain. (One of them recently resigned from the Bahrain Police and his discharge certificate shows him as a Qatari. I referred this case to Mr. Belgrave who replied there was no objection to our employing the man particularly as we proposed to send him back to Qatar). 8. While on this subject I would add that the population of Bahrain now includes many Arabs and Persians from neighbouring countries and sheikhdoms. It would be easy for such persons to discard their Bahrain nationality documents and present them selves at Dohah for engagement. Mr. Belgrave points out, how ever, that such types attempting to be taken on by us in Bahrain for transfer to Qatar could be sent to the Bahrain Passport Office for identification. 9. If you think it appropriate perhaps you will be good enough to give His Highness our assurance that in principle we will not recruit from his subjects for working in Qatar. Should any special circumstances arise in that a Bahraini with special qualifications applies to us and we can use him with advantage, we suggest for His Highness 1 consideration that we should refer to him for his approval before engaging him. If, however, His Highness wishes to make no exceptions whatsoever, perhaps we can be informed. Yours sincerely, Lt.-Col. A.C.Galloway, O.B.E., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain./ D.O. No. C/45L Tho 29th of April, r&gt;16. My dear Packer, Please refer to your letter No. DO/QCM.12/4201 dated the 21st April, 1946. 2. The word is 'divers* not 'drivers'. His Highness has received a petition from the diving nakhudas of Bahrain in which they state that in the event of P.C.L. recruiting workers from Bahrain most of the men recruited would be pearl divers. As the divers are indebted to the nakhudas for large sums and have been advanced their !t tisqara' for the coming season the latter are perturbed at the prospect. His Highness shares their concern and has, in addition, expressed his anxiety that, now that the war is over, the pearling industry should resume its pre-war importance. 3. I would, therefore, add to your recommendations, with which I agree generally, the further stipulation that the company should not knowingly engage any person who has been contracted by a Bahrain nakhuda for the coming pearling season, even if the man so contracted is a Qatari. Permission to employ Bahrainis who are not affected by the above stipulation should be obtained from His Highness through this Agency. 4. Before replying to His Highness in the above sense I should be grateful if you would let me know if you agree. Yours sincerely, s *v. Packer, Esq., M.B.E., Messrs. Petroleum Concessions Limited BAHRAIN. N3.CONFIDENTIAL \JU*' PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. DO/qCM. 12/4207 29th April, 1946. BAHRAI N PERSIAN GULF. My dear Colonel, Will you please refer to your letter no.C/408 dated the 17th of April 1946. 1. I am assuming from your letter that you would prefer us to discard the practice of issuing food (or even dry rations; free to our Qatar labourers and to adopt the system used by -bapco and Aramco of making provision for rations on re-payment. 2. Unfortunately it has been the custom in the Iraq Petroleum Company and its subsidiaries to supply cooked food free to employees working in isolated camps remote from their homes and families. 3. This isolation affects the employee in several ways (a) The cost of maintaining his family is higher when the family is divided. (b) Enforced separation from wives makes the Job unattractive packet. 6. The c ond iti ons work have made it an they come under the”isolated” category, is due in Qatar in October 1946. . A large geologists 1 party Confidential. Bahrain receipt, , N0...4&amp;.V?. Date..£.^r.:..4.£ • • •- 2 - • • • DO/QCM. 12/4207 (contd.) *7, When our operations originally commenced in Q,atar, Dukhan camp 60 miles from the nearest town also came under the isolated category and the free food facility. 8. In the above described circumstances and if the free food facility on the reopening of operations is now to be withdrawn throughout Qatar, there seems to be a strong case for an additional inducement over and above those of Bahrain where general conditions of work are more congenial. It is suggested that this inducemen should take the form of a field allowance to labourers of 4 annas per day, that is, a Qatari labourer working at isolated camps will draw bIvoo's basic rats of Rs.1/12/- plus 4 annas field allowance and thereafter hapco’s increments of 2 annas after one month a 2 annas more after 6 months. 9. The charge for food supplied on payment ^e at 8 annas per day which will leave the man not less than ' , , from their envelope. It is our contention that labourers separated from their families should not be expected to support themselves and thei families on less than Bs.l/8/- per day in cas 10. While on the point of comparisons it may te mentioned that been supplied for work away from the owns. 11. We submit that our case for the payment of a field allowance is a strong one. 12. The Company's standard of food ““/g^overheads are be justified, bapco and Aramco, if ell ^ on ent taken to account probably subsidise ^ ^ to the extent of Bs.12/- to Bs.i / p . -u een verified, it must be admitted that this statement has not been verm 4 -« ■pr\'i i nw the nrinciple of a reasonably 13. This Company proposes to fol tlie P em pioyee. The Company balanced diet at reasonable pri g sil0 ^ d be sufficient to takes the view that its scale lacouring man, and, in this preserve the health and streng -possible to its prewar standard case, the scale should be as nea S ortages will permit. In other as far as post-war restrictions and “ages^ ^ ^ ^ words, the ration 18 ^ * ti £ es this ration costs from 5 to 7 cost which -ries^mpre^ ^ appro2imates to a rU pee. •+vi rsdco is not unreasonable as the charge to The comparison with Bap per month ^ ks.15/- j Company approximates to ks.io/ ^- 3 - • • • DO/Q,CM. 12/4207 (contd.) is deducted from the man^ pay envelope. As the world food situation gradually improves, the Company’s subsidy will decrease and it is within the bounds of possibility that the day will come when subsidies will no longer be necessary. 5. In conclusion, we would reiterate that we consider that •here is ample justification in that our labourers are separated ’rom their families and remote from towns , firstly, for the paymen &gt;f an additional 4 annas per day field allowance over and a ove japco’s basic rate of Bs.l/12/- and, secondly, for the supply of reasonable quantities of food on a ^asonabiy balmced diet et reasonable charges. Jiirther, the Company feels that &gt;f the fact that the men's wives are not there c °°^ ^ Lt is in the best interests of the Company and the men that the jompany should make the cooking arrangements. L6. We shall be pleased to hear if you agree that ^° T ® ost _ war proposals for Qatar are reasonable in the light op conditions and comparable with conditions 0 s ® isolation of territories of her neighbours with due regard to the isolation camps in Qatar. v. Lt.-Col. A.C. Galloway, O.B.E., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.D • 0 • TT o. c/ 492 • The 14th May 9 My dear Packer, I am sorry I was not able to reply to your letter No.DO/QCM. 12/4207 dated the 29th April, 1946, before, / e but this was due to my absence on L- 5 tour. 2. I think that the arrangements you now suggest are excellent and by them you should be able to control the food in-take of your labour. It seems to me that the capacity of those people is not gauged by the stomach, or even the eye, and that the only control they recognise is one of cash. Yours sincerely, Packer, Esq., M.B.EU, Messrs. Petroleum concessions Limited, B a h rain.( Qrigi nalyin K.O. File 29/10). -) ; &gt; ^ PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 14th April, 1946. DO/QCR.1/4190. My dear Colonel, RATIONED &amp; CONTROLLED FOO D ITEMS - QATAR. As mentioned in previous correspondence we are opening up Dukhan Camp, Qatar, within the next few days and the situation at present is such that it will be necessary for the Company to supply food to its employees including the Qatari local labourers for some time to come. Part of the food for all categories of foreigners and locals consists of rationed and controlled items. To enable the Company to make practical messing arrangements it . will be necessary for the Company to draw these rationed and controlled items in bulk. 2. We understand that you control the issues to Qatar via Qatar's local representatives here who take over wheat, sugar, tea, etc., from the Bahrain Food Controller in bulk. These local representatives send the food in bulk to Dohah where the Ruler of ^atar has his organisation for the distribution at controlled amounts and urices. It would help us considerably if we could be informed^ (as replies from other sources are very evasive): - (a) the ration strength of Qatar at present (b) the food items and scales for which you make arrangements. (c) prices paid by the Bahrain representatives to the Food Controller. (d) present controlled prices as paid by the Ruler to his Bahrain representatives. (e) period for which the rations are drawn - presumably in advance. (f) whether there are any arrangements for reserves and where these are maintained. (g) any other information you are able to furnish which will'be useful to us in obtaining our rations at the proper scale and prices. 3. As regards the drawing of these rations ^or the Company employees in Qatar, it would see give the Ruler stances the correct procedure would efor^u^ cat | gories and ask our monthly strength of all nci ^ 10r } d A . . to us i n bulk at him to authorise the issue ^^ghouldle holding in Dohah. controlled prices from tne stocxs n 4. m practice, however, we have serious this procedure will not materia^ s - stocks are not off with plausible excuses as to the reason available. ^ 5. In these circumstances, we are seeking ^ ^uPP^to our suggestion that.our quota fthe^ompany ^ direct from the various Qatar rep /6. We do not think : !i j &gt;6. We do not think deductions from existing Qatar quotas need be necessary as the majority of Qataris we shall be engaging in Qatar will be returning from other areas such as Arabia, Bahrain, Dubai and Sharjah, where they have found work during the years the Company 1 s operations in ^atar have been suspended. Such a scheme, of course, would entail an addition to existing Qatar quotas as arranged by you commensu rate with the strength of the Company employees and your authority to the Food Controller and Qatar’s representative in Bahrain to divide the quota. 7. If you approve of our proposals, we suggest that we write to the Ruler of Qatar pointing out the advantages to the plan to draw company rations direct in Bahrain and bringing it to his notice that you have no objection to the scheme. 8, I am afraid you may think that we are giving you trouble unnecessarily but our experience so far in Qatar leads us to believe that sooner or later this food problem will come before you, and, in our view, it is better to examine the possibilities now and try at least to put the matter on a sound basis while numbers involved are still small and, if necessary, we can get enough food of some kind to carry on from alternative sources. Yours sincerely, Sgd.A 3.V. PACKER Lt-Col. A•C. Galloway, H.3.M.’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Copied.HBQttMMH ( Original in 2.Q. F.29/1Q )' D*0« No. 1397-29/10. The 2nd of May^ 1946* Please refevAo your Demi-Official letter No. DO/QCR.l/4190f dated the 14th of April, 1946, addressed to Colonel Galloway. 2. As we are mainly concerned only with the preliminary arrangements for obtaining supplies of wheat and sugar, and not with the control of prices or rationing, I am unable to give exact information on all the points you ask, but subject to this limita tion, the answers to your questions are as follows (a) There is no organised rationing in Qatar. (b) Wheat, sugar and tea; maximuras of 80, 15 and 1 ton respectively per month, often less. (Wheat at present is 72 tons). (c) U.K.C.C. rates are charged for wheat, and sugar and tea are sold at cost price plus Bahrain charges such as pier fees, storage charges, etc. (d) Not known. (e) Drawn as and when supplies are available. (f) No arrangements for any reserves in Qatar. 3. The suggestion made in your paragraph 5 is agreed to in principle. 4 . it is not possible to comment on the questions raised in your paragraph 6 regarding the necessity of increasing the food quotas for Qatar, until you can supply detailed figures of the labour you intend to employ and the dates from which you intend to employ it. Yours sincerely, Sd.A H.D.H. RANGE E.V. Packer, Esq., M.3.2*, Messrs. Petroleum Concessions, Bahrain. Limited,PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. yz 3 /(oL o 7 'I COWi’IDEN'iTAL DO/CM. 12/4240 My dear oolonel, V BAH R Al N PERSIAN GULF. 29th May, 1946. Will you please refer to your letter No.C/451 dated the 29th of April 1946. I regret the delay in replying hut I wished to discuss recruiting in general with the Shaikh of Q,atar. I arranged with him during my visit to Doha between the 9th and 12th of May that the Company would recruit labour only from personnel registered by Saleh al Mana on behalf of the Shaikh, and any persons presenting themselves at Company camps in Qatar would have to show proof of registration and that they were eligible for engagement. 2. It would seem, therefore, that as recruitment is controlled by the Qatar Government through this system of registration, e most effective way of preventing the engagement of ^ ta ^ s ^ obligations to Bahrain nokhodas would be to enlist the oo-operatio. of the Qatar (government (in effect, in this ease, ba e a i. S. We are, however, of course prepared to give the undertaking you refer to in your para 3, namely, that the W ^ X J; “ in knowingly engage any person who has bee “ °° n . j a ° h g ^ s0 contracted nokhoda for the coming pearling season e , , uoh a rilaIL be is a Qatari. You will realise, however that should suchaman^ sent us in a batch by Saleh al liana or s o P inadverten tly carrying Saleh-s authority for ^^ehould he be die- engaged, explanations might be a littl charged and we were pressed for an explanation. 4. As already explained, we do ^^“^g^^ci^cumstances in Bahrain for service in Qatar excep P pemission for which the procedure has been laid down by you, i.e., must be obtained from His Highness roug fi-ip night to engage and 5. In this connection, the Company in tiie case of bring in technicians not availa approval of the bahrainis it would seem desirable to obtain the app Ruler of (Qatar. , f i a -bour from neighbouring shai 6. Incidentally, the employment 01 ^ ^ such importe d doms needs the approval of the K ITc?. • •lb'* DO/Q,CIvi. 12/4240 (contd.; labour would presumably also come under the Q,atar Government registration scheme. 7. In conclusion, I feel that it is inevitable that some Bahrainis will get themselves registered in Doha and find their way to our camps. In such cases it is assumed that the situation will eventually be reported to you by His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain and we shall subsequently receive instructions via the Shaikh of Qatar to dispense with their services ? I think you may agree that if the persons concerned were vouched for or sponsored by the Qatar Government their discharge should come from the same yours sincerely, Lt.-Col. A.G.Galloway, O.B.E., H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain.\.+ \/ *«.H t t ££?A kJ lh&gt;b No.C/601. The 6th of June 1946. \n I 1^ Ji IIP* 4$ ^K., ,j. II (*■«% fSb*0ff .^i-Jla.'v [ - j-oui r^U J^Hf dr’» r,~ * s * * , A ~ «jh-s *—Wsis l % &gt; &gt;** ft J : P J—«#i3 J^»ai8- t g ife ;^, l .»n?'w.it^?^l» y %jLm^.^jS ^0 LjI . 'J* «— ajo 'Vjl ( J—gfcpv jjii'awrg ^^fexrntUi dr.i^ni—. J ^ oV tJUiS 1 tijjifc 1 is *&gt; ^1 J =^1 y# aU ^ U.l^i1 1^ ■I t l%i mm ' y* JvJjS t _^ tlf i ■W^«* ■A-. ^ ^ : # DS&gt;— To ( His Highness Shaikh Sir Salman bin Hamad al Khalifah, K.C.I.E., Ruler of Bahrain. After compliments: .l|0 Your Highness ma^r/please refer to your letter of the 13th April, 1946. VI 2. I have written to Mr. Packer who ■ / has replied that it is the principle of his company to engage only Qataris for v/ork in Qatar, and that if he wishes to employ a Bahraini he will first obtain Your Highness» consent before engaging him. n 3. He has asked me to assure Your Highness that the Company f s Recruiting Officers in Bahrain and Dukhan (Qatar) v/ill be instructed not to engage Bahrainis direct. If, inadvertently, a Bahraini has already been employed in Qatar Mr. Packer promises to take steps to see that the man is discharged or• employed in Banrain. ^ tX**$ ^u-j* j 4. He mentions that he has engaged in Bahrain several Qataris who worked for his company before, and who have been working during the war in Bahrain. I think it is right that these men should now be given an opportunity to return to Qatar. /5. in regard...*| ^ ml 1^ ^ * /I s*Jt j jT ^Ic'^cT 4 ^ 1 tJ Jrf 1 ? i^jlf pplf 4aaJ^iaiwi»_ #»«*1 # ^ Y* % ^i^wairAl »*4^$***$^«**^* I ^J%-^ Ul iU. J^mrnmj^ ^hj—nnTniiin** iS|^»Na«»a%.;:;? ^P'- u ^ twUnMI '.ffV 1 # jUit |^B»3&lt;90 y* 1-4% ^ tj- , v I J-l ^ykttwmrnm*.® 1 ^fct^Jl 4jg '**' ,v &gt;&gt; t 1 ^ 2U#lk^,Ji il»««&amp;*u 5* in regard to Your Highness's statement about the recruitment by the P*C.I*. of Bahraini pearl divers, I wrote to Mr. packer and asked him not to engage any man who is under contract to a Bahrain nakhuda for the 1365 season. He has replied pointing out that some of the divers under con tract to Bahrain nakhudas may be Qataris and that if these persons are sponsored by the Shaikh of Qatar difficulty will arise. I suggest that if any such case comes to light it might be dealt with at the time. Perhaps Your Highness will let me know if you agree. Usual ending. f s political Agent, Bahrain. NS.CO^FIDMTIAL PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. My dear Colonel, DO/QCM.12/4279 6th June, 1946 HATES OF PAY AMD CCTOITIOlMS OF SERVICE - QATARI LABOUR l&amp;en I was in '^tar recently, I explained to the Shaikh the terms for Qatari labour, namely, a basic rate of Rs.2/- per day with deduction of 8 annas per day for food, and the Shaikh stated that he considered this equitable. If you can find it appropriate, I shall be grateful if you will confirm to the Shaikh that these terms were approved by you. If you can see your way also to explain that the Company's original plan*to supply food free were changed on your advice, so much the I put this forward in case the Shaikh has another after thought and tries to increase the basic rate of Rs.2/- per day or to revert to free food as well as Rs.2/-. better Yours sincerely, Lt.-Col. A.C. Galloway , O.B.E., H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. ConfidentialCONFIDMTIAL DO/qSD.4/4373 Ifiy dear Colonel, ENGAGmmT OF PERSIANS LrvTM&gt; IN BA ERAII^ FOR SERVICE P.D.Q,. QAl'AR S ' You will remember that it was arranged that we should not recruit Bahrain subjects for work In Qatar except with the consent of His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain to be obtained thiopgh you. 2. There is a category of Persians living in Bahrain without Irani or Bahrain passports or Certificates of Identity, many of whom have lived here since childhood. 3. We are experiencing great difficulty in obtaining drivers and artisans, and we should like to draw on this category. 4. If you agree in principle that this category can be engaged and reference to His Highness Is not involved, we presume that it will be necessary (a) to submit names and particulars to you in order that you can satisfy yourself that applicants are not Bahrain subjects entailing reference to His Highness. (b) to arrange for Certificates of Identity and visas for Qatar. (c) to arrange for a Bahrain visa vhich will enable a man to return to Bahrain, this visa to cover as usual aiy number of journeys. This procedure assumes that a man will be allowed to return and settle down In Bahrain again if he so desires and that he does not forfeit his Bahrain status, such as it is, by talcing out a Certificate of Identity. 5. In connection with (a), if there is any preliminary investigation which could be carried out by the Company before the applicant presents himself at the Agency for his Certificate of Identity, we shall be pleased to assist. ... ' 0rO :. ite.DO/QSD.4/4373 (eontd.j © 6. If the above arrangements are not possible for any reason, we should appreciate any suggestion from you udiich would enable us to utilise the services of the category we have described* It would seem a great pity if a large number of men are to lose chances of employment due to a formality which might be overcome, apart from the fact that the Company is in very great need of skilled men. Yours sincerely, Lt.-Col* A.C.aalloway, C.I*E., Political Agent, Bahrain. 0«B«E., c.c. PI.7 fileDear Packer CONFIDENTIAL D.O.No.C/847 Will you please refer to your demi-official letter Ho. DO/QSD. 4/4373 dated the 22nd July, 1946, to Colonel Galloway. 2. I am afraid I cannot agree t the employment of any Persian inhabit ants of Bahrain for work in without referring the matter to tne Bahrain Government. If y 0 ^ still wish to employ these men please let me know and I will take the matter up with the Adviser. Yours sincerely, i E.V. Packer, Esquire, Petroleum Concessions Bahrain. m.b.e., Limited JANC.CONFIDENTIAL PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. DO/QSD.4/4389 1st August, 1946 My dear Ranee ENGAGMENT OF PERSIANS LIVING- IN BAHRAI FOR SERVICE P.D.Q. QATAR AND TKCJCIAL COji Many thanks for your No. D.O. C/847 dated the 30th July 1946. If you think that His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain will agree to some arrangement for the employment by us of these Persian inhabitants which will be practicable and you can supply a suitable form of Travel Documents, then we should like you to proceed further in the matter. We should like to employ such personnel in Qatar or the Trucial Coast. We still have to overcome possible objections by the Shaikh of Qatar to the employment of what he may consider as thinly disguised Bahrainis. yours sincerely, Capt. H.D.H.Ranee, The Agency, Bahrain. r » .* r Bahrain receipt.c. D* 0* Ho* C/ &amp;7£? s® (MV dated the 5th Au^u^t, 1946* Dear Belgrave, ... 5f ou £ ofer to the correspondence ending ny letter Bo.C/601 dated the 6th June, X946, to his Highness^to \?hich I have not yet had a reply* h* P.C.L. now wish to know whether His Highness would agree to their employing in Qatar and on the 1 racial Coast the category of I'ersian who has long lived in Bahrain, in niany cases since childhood, with- out either a Persian or Bahrain passport or Certificate of Identity* The Company badly needs skilled aen for its operations and would like permission to recruit this type as drivers and artisans* 3* Would the Bahrain Government agree to Persians of this category being employed as suggested, and to their being issued with Certificates of Identity, which would enable them to return to Bahrain when their services are no longer required by Utow P.C.LS Their names and particulars would jOf course.be sent to you in the usual way for your cor lents before any Certificates of Identity were issued* Yours sincerely, BalryapI© Belgrave, ^sq., C*ii*B., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, MMM' TP INo. ///^f ^ 0 f 1365 Office of the Adviser to the GovernxiBnt, Bahrain Dated 11th Raniadhan 1365 August 8 , 1946• ^ . B.»r H. 3. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum;- Reference your D.O.No.c/876 dated 5th August, 1946. 1 have referred the matter of employment of local Persians in Bahrain by the Petroleum Concession Limited to His Highness. His Highness has written to me stating that he is unwilling to allow any of his subjects to go to work in Q/atar, until the present misunderstanding between himself and the Shaikh of ^atar has been removed. &lt;1 M. Adviser to the Government. ^ 1 BAHRAIN RECEIPT. JJe...*,!„V.f.k.Date.. ■ e - * C - »»»»»» »»+»»$ »&lt;H»I •S-4 3 CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE ETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED It/I' &amp;/9SS V'*i* MGTV. t x v J Directors: Lord Cadman, G.C.M.G. (chairman), r. Cayrol, d.s.o., d.S.C. (Fremsm}, W. Fraser, C.B.E., C. s. gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) G. legh-Jones, J. B. a. Kessler (dutch), j. a. meny (French), H? Ct Bbibei. (u,g a,), r. w. sellers, j. Skliros R. cU M^jCSLCtu, t&gt;'A ■*»*/&gt;+*jx&gt; BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF Dated. 10th August, 1946. Q/SD-4/3389 Political Agent, Bahra in. Bguloration Programme Qatar. We have received a telegraphic communication from our New York agents requesting permission for the Seismic Party who will be operationg in Q,atar from 1st October, 1946 to operate wireless sets on frequencies of 4000 Kilocycles or alternatively 1652 Kilocycles. Three sets at 10 watts and two sets at 50 watts will be required. Communications will be strictly confined between crew units. 2. Article 6 of the Qatar Oil concession states that w The Company may construct, maintain and operate telegraph and telephone installations and their lines and wireless stations ,, . 3. We shall be grateful if you will inform us whether there will be any objection to the use of the wireless sets abovementioned. 4 aq wo been asked by New York to advise them by cable we have to-day written to Cable and Wireless, Bahrain, requesting them to inform us whether they have any objection to the use of the above frequencies. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of 4, DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. ^^7«Date /i0 - VN AUER.No. C/OS&lt;t The Political Agency, Bahrain Dated the 11th August, 1946- The Comnander, T T r it n f -r- ^ . 7 © Jnfair ! The Officer Commanding, Muharraq, Bahrain. (No. C/3f©) MEMOHuiHDUM Concessions Limited propose j ° !lse three 10 watt and t¥/o 50 watt wireless 1 or operations in ^atar* These sets will work on frequencies of 4000 Kilocycles, or, alternatively, of 1652 Kilocycles. Please inform me whether you have any objection to the use of either of these 'frequencies. Sd/~ H.D.H. RANGE, Political Agent, Bahrain Attested for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. L.R.3^3 I7^f hi D.O. Ho. C/888 The 11th August, 1946, Dear Packer, Please -refer to your deal-official letter ?To. OC/QSD. 4/4389 dated the 1st August, 1946. 2. His Highness has inforaed a© that he Is not willing to allow the engagea^t/of his subjects for work in Qatar until the Present aisunderstanding between niaself and the ruler ox Qatar has been removed♦ / ^ y , Yours sincerely, E*V* packer, * Petroleaa ’ Bahrain# L«K« i—■■■■■11 ' I ■HHHHHHHMhhmhmi - ? r ( I / 17, FROM.:- The Commanding Officer, H.M.S # 'JIIEAIR m . DATS;- 15 August 19^* TO;- 'THE POLITICAL AGLNT, THE AGENCY, HAILUA, BAHKEIN. havai ^gaaiass EHEijnENGi^s With reference to your letter Ho. C/889 dated 11 August 1946, 4000 Kilocycle 3 is allocated to the Royal Kavy, but there is no Naval objection to the use of 1652 Kilocycles, COaLANLER R.N.R* II I CQMK1ANL. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. ^From. To. IMPRESS LKTTBR Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. Dated the 20th August, 1946. 'I fe No. C/929 nofo-r'driee correspondence ending with „ 3 He £ wt rdated the 8 th August, your Endorsement No. o/o^u aa 1946. p p«-hroleum Concessions Limited have tSf?Llr N.. 1 = permission for the Seismic Survey tQ to operate in Qatar from 1st ^t^ wireless setSo dse three 10 watt and tw frequency of These sets will be operated on^ limited and 1652 kilocycles. Their 2 units only, communication will be between crew u ^ Messrs. Cable &amp; Wireless/the j 4 ,) X* Mess -d a p . Bahrain, and the Officer Commanding, ’ T 71 f a ir, ,haVe no Commanding Officer, H * • * ^52 kilocycle objection to the use of the x_ g of the Q atar frequency, and in view o reason why these Oil Concession there seems no^re^^ Jf sets should not be QP e « j propose to inform see no objection, there ' * the Company accordingly- ^CL. Sd/- HeD.B. RANGE, Political Agent, Bahrain. Attes ted. f'ords'istantCONFIDENTIAL QSA. 2/4430 PERSIAN GULF 20 th August, 1946. To H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. QATAR CONCESSION - INCREASES IN SALARIES OF SHAIKH'S REPRESENTATIVES In May 1946, the Ruler of Qatar drew attention to the fact that during the war salaries in general had been increased and the increased rates were still being paid. In these circumstances he felt it only equitable that the Company should increase the salaries of his two representatives. 2. The matter was referred to the Managing Director, London, who has authorised an increase in the combined salaries from Rs.1250/- to Rs.2000/- per mensem. The offer was made to the Ruler and accepted. Incidentally Baleh al Mana is one representative, but the identity of the second has never been officially disclosed. There is every reason to believe, however, that Shaikh Earned draws this second salary. It is highly probable also that Saleh gets a very small part of the Rs.2000/- although it was made clear to the Ruler that the Company had in view Rs.1000/- to each representative. For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED MANAGER ACM Confidential* BAHRAIN RECEIPT. ~ , 92,.BAHREIN To H.B.M’s Political Bahrain. CONFIDENTIAL QSA.2/4431 20th August, 1946. PERSIAN GULF QATAR CONCESSION - USE OF QATAR PORTS In May 1946 the Ruler of Qatar reminded the Company that under Article 6 of the Concession the Company was restricted to the use of Doha for its imports, and that his agreement in 1937 to the use of Zekrit had resulted in financial loss. He felt that the Company should compensate him. He suggested a monthly payment of Rs.5000/-. (The position was known to Colonel Galloway, but no official correspondence has passed prior to this letter.) 2. The matter was referred to the Managing Director, London, who authorised an offer of Rs.2500/- per mensem in exchange for permission to use any Qatar port for the Company’s imports. 3. Mr. Packer discussed the offer with the Ruler of Qatar on lOth-llth of August 1946, and it was eventually agreed that the Company could use Zekrit, and its new oil port (when constructed) for both imports and exports. A copy of the Agreement is attached. For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED y MANAGER Enel. Confidential. ACMCONFrDKSTTAI. . No. C/937. To / The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 22nd August, The Hon f hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum. I forward herewith a copy of a letter No. QSA*2/4430 dated the 20th August, 1946, from Messrs. Petroleum Concessions Limited, regarding increases in the salaries of the Shaikh of Qatar’s two representatives. 2. I can see no objection to these increases. Sd. H.D.H. RANGE Political Agent, Bahrain. Attested. *Tc. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. JANG.CONFIDENTIAL . No. C/938. Bahrain. Dated the 22nd August, 1946. To The Hon’ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, / ^ Bahrain . Ln ) MEMORANDUM. y 1 c I forward herewith copies of letter No. QSA.2/4431 dated the 20th August/1946, from Messrs, petroleum Concessions Limited, and its enclosure. 2. Although there is nothing on record here to show how much of the position was, in fact, known to Colonel Galloway, I think it probable ^hat he was aware of Mr. packer*s intention of negotiating this new agreement. 3 . The Shaikh of Qatar had previously complained of the Company's failure to use Dohah as a port of entry for all their imports, and the solution now arrived at appears to be one satisfactory to both parties. 4 . m view of this I suggest that I be authorised to inform the Company that His Majesty s Government have no objection to the new agreement. Sd. H.D.H. RANGE political Agent, Bahrain. Attested. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain, JANC.Ko. C/738. Hi Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Gamp, Bahrain, Bated the 24th August 1946. To The Political Agent, Bail rain. lu&amp;lOKAfcTDtM. Reference your Express the 20th August 1946. 2. There is no object ion to Petroleum Concessions Limited using the wireless sets mentioned during the operations of their Seismic Survey Party in Q,atar. 3d. W.R.HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attests * for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. 'da'.. BAHRAINI :0 ® I ? T j v At O 1 ■ ..Date.No. C/951 The Political Agency, Bahrain Dated the 26th August, 1946. To. The Manager, Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, &lt;5- c Will you please refer to your letter No. q/SD- 4/3389 dated the 10th August, 1946. Survey Party using the wireless sets mentioned in your letter under reference during the operations in Qatar, on a frequency of 1652 Kilocycles only. They should not be operated on the frequency of 4000 Kilocycles however, as this frequency has already been allocated to the Royal Navy. There is no objection to your Seismic Yours faithfully, L.R. political Agent, Bahrain.GQIiFimmiAJL, S o &gt; C/7 56 » To Copy to;- Office of the Political Resident, Persian Pulf, Gamp, Bahrain, dated the 25th August 1946, i The Political Agent, Bahrain. H.M.’s Secretary of State for India, ) with copy The India Office, London. ) of coram- ) un i cat ion The Secretary to the Government of India) under in the External Affairs Department, ) reference. hew Delhi. ) Increases in salaries of Shaikh of Q,atar ! s Representatives with Petroleum Jon cess ions j-*td. Memorandum . / , Reference your Memorandum ho. C/937 dated the 22nd August 1946. 2 0 The Political Resident agrees tnat there is no objection to the increases. Under Secretary to the Foliti oal Resident, Persian Gulf. RHL. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Na.i.LV. .Date.No,758, The Hon’hie the political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahra in, and has the honour :o trsnsmit to him a copy of the under mentioned document ($) Persian Gulf Residency ’ Dated^^-^ 194o Camp, Bahrain. v ' • . — — 'f* '' ' 1 Reference to previous correspondences Description of Enclosure. Name and Date s Residency Express Letter J No. C/757 dated the 25th * August 1946. ^ Subject, Use of ^ehrit instead of Lohah by Petroleum Concessions Ltd., in Qatar. r BAHRAIN RECEIPT. NaJJL'.S Date..n.hL^'GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B .—Thif is an ORIGINAL message tent by AIR MAIL which provides a meows of corntnunicafion more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than, the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.^ No. C/757 . Dale(Lif^=^, the 28th August 1946 , To - Rotaxaridum London* Repeated - Foreign Hew Delhi* A copy of Bahrain memorandum Ko*0/938 dated 22nd August 1946 and its enclosures ie forwarded herewith* 2* A» there is no political representative of H*M*G. in Qatar xwi of* paragraph 4 of the Political Agreement of 5th June 1935 between H.M.G. and the tfca Company and as it appears that Galloway was kept informed of the progress of the negotiations I do not think any objection need be raised to the agreement on the ground that it was negotiated direct between Petroleum Concessions Ltd* and the Shaikh of 4&amp;tar* in itself the agreement appears quite unobjectionable* 3* Grateful for confirmation that H*H.G. have no objection to the agreement being approved* 3d* W.R.HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf* Attested * Sd. iS. Thomas. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian uuli* RHL* {Signature) S. 44. MGIPC—SI— 2385(S&amp;P)MFP—(M-1744)—3-12-40—20,000. (Designation)Mo. C/957, To. The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 27th August, f 46 The Manager, Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Will you please refer to your letter No. ASD.4/4421 dated the 17th August, 1946. 2. The Hobble the Political Resident agrees that there is no objection to these increases. Yours faithfully. A.J.S• Political Agent, Bahraina I CODES BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE fi5 ROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED : Lo^D Cadman, G.C.M.G. (chairman), R, Cayrol, D.S.O., o.S.C. (fren®w), W, Fraser, C.B.E., Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) Directors i hsQ£ .. G. legh-Jones, J. B. A. Kessler (dutch), (French), , Seidel (u.stRt^, r. w. sellers, j. Skliros ft. aU ^icyUJuLtfu/ 3&gt;. 4• sA+foimJ-* . BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF End September, 1946. qCP.2/4459 To il.B.M*s Political Agent, Bahrain. We have had a case in our jDukhan camp, Qatar, where a Persian carrying Certificate of Identity No* 284 of 1946 from the Agency and employed by us was flogged by the commander of the shaikh of Qatar’s guards for eating during the day in Ramadhan. We shall be grateful if you will inform us whether a person m the above category can be tried and punished in Qatar y Ruler’s representative. If this trial was irregular perhaps you will inform us of the correct procedure in such cases. 2. Qatar Orders in Council doubtless but there are so many cross references to legislation not in our possession that we find it difficul rulings we seek. For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED ACM _ BAKUW RECEIPT. *»»*•».No. C/1006 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 6th September, 1946 The Manager, petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, Bahrain Dear Sir, Will you please refer to your letter ^ S No. QCP.2/4459 dated the 2nd September, 1946. 2. Article No.4 of the Qatar Order in Council recognizes the Shaikh of Qatar's jurisdiction over the subjects of the Shaikhs of Bahrain, Kuwait, and the frucial States resident in Qatar, who for the purposes of this Order are 'Qatar subjects', or over any Moslem person, not being a British subject. It would seem to cover the case you mention. Yours faithfully Assistant political Agent, Bahrain (In the absence of the political Agent). NS.I' .Q. No.?99-G Confidential r'acker informed Colonel Hay recently that the Political Agent had requested the Petroleum Concessions Limited not to employ Bahrainis in Qatar. I am desired to enquire the reason for this prohibition. Captain H.D.H. Ranee, Political Agent, BAHRAIN. NPG. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT Date..*?./?/D.O. Ho, C/1091 Confidential g) The 1st October, 1946. Dear Felly s Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No* 799-S dated the 28th September, 1946. 2* In June this year His Highness having complained that petroleum Concessions Limited were engaging pearl divers from Bahrain for their Qatar operations a * gentleman’s agreement’ was arranged whereby Packer before engaging Bahrainis was to ascertain through this Agency that His Highness had no objection to their working in Qatar* In July packer Informed me that he wished to employ certain Persian residents of Bahrain who possessed neither Persian nor Bahrain passports or Certificates of Identity, for work in Qatar, and asked me to arrange Certificates of Identity and Qatar visas for them provided this did not involve reference to His Highness, I replied that I would have to refer the matter to the Bahrain Government and that if ha wished me to do so he should let me know* He wrote asking me to do this, but added that he would still have to overcome possible objections from the Shaikh of Qatar, since he might consider these persons thinly disguised Bahrainis* 3. I then communicated packer’s proposal to Belgrave, and received a reply that His Highness was unwilling to allow any of his subjects to work in Qatar until the present misunders tanding between himself and the Shaikh of ,)atar had been removed* I Informed Packer accordingly and have not heard from him on the subject again# Yours sincerely, * J# Polly, f sq# O.ii.b*, I.u Secretary go the political Secretary to the Political Resident• in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain#GOVERNMENT OE INDIA. Department, EXPRESS LETTER [H. B—This is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched*] From Political Resident, Persian Gulf. To Political Agent, Bahra in. iVo. 834-S. Dated the 2nd October 19% 46* l /^ $T7 Reference India Offide Express totter Ho. Ext. 6130/46 dated the 25th September 1946. Agreement between Petroleum Concessions limited and the Shaikh of Qatar regarding use of ports in Qatar* 2 . please take action accordingly. Sd. W.R.HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf Attested. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Guli . / RH1. Confidential. Bahrain receipt. n©...L£1i? d ta...?. 1190 S&amp;P—(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000.2,i I ^ No.C/1119. POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. The 6th October, 1946. To The Manager, petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd., No.QSA.2/4431 dated the 20th August, 1946 His Majesty f s Government have no objection to the Agreement. Yours faithfully, political Agent, Bahrain. NS.'ft ?«/3 DO/QSD.4/4574 PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULP. 15th November, 1946. My dear Ranee, Marine Survey - Qatar You may be .itt,». ,he Caapany* s oil terminal. The party consists of Mr. Colby t.American) Mr. Langham (American) Mr. Macrae (British) all on the Company’s staff. You rs sin cerely, Capt. H.D.H.Ranee, The Agency, Bahrain. tody sent to P.R. under i^idu. / o. C 2 P Lri« ri '46 with reference No. C/1285 dated 18.11. n to his X.L. No. 834-S dated 2.10. 46. c.n 'i Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRAS TROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED iJ A /£■ i/. Bi 7 ' 0 ^ Directors i • - - - - - (- ^ - ©avrol. D.S.O., D.S.C. (pr«n«»), W. Fraser, C.B.E., C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) G i!eoh!jones: J. B. A. Kessler (DirrcH);' M^ (gnEi.r M ) H fi RfinEi^L.S.U. R. W. Sellers. J.Skuros a ^ . BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 23rd November 1946. Q,SA. 2/4598 CONFIDENTIAL To H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. !&lt;M' 9ATAR OIL TERMINAL SITS We attach herewith a draft of a letter we propose to send to the Ruler of Q.atar if you ave no objection. As the Ruler has objections to the ®* t ® th and presumably these objections may exten Y keen alternative farther south, we think it desirable to keep him informed of the situation wi ;!* ing him to put his objections and reason P P action This is necessary before the Company can take any action to overcome the Ruler’s opposition. 2. The excuse put forward verbaliy hat ^Shaikh cannot guarantee security south o . ^ border of non-Qataris is to be leave with do:£er does^ot tear exa^na-^ proposed terminal site in th 3. It is telieved that the^uler^s^objection^^ colltrol is based on the fact that J , f tiie family* If the is in the hands of ® not f ^^ysitf, it remains to Company selects the “ os £ h ? 0 s£aikh will persist in his be seen whether or not the snaixu w object!ons. 4. In connection with this^southerly ®^ or , 0daid) it is important tharifshoild be established that it is well y ^ BAHRAIN REOBIW. _ fSS 8- Date.. * b2 Q^SA* 2/4598 (contd,) within Q,atar territory. As the southern boundary of Q#tar is, we understand, still unsettled we should like an assurance that this site is well clear of any disputed territory. For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED MANAGER Enel.D.O. No.C/1409 The 20th of December, 1946 My dear packer Will you please refer to your letter No. QSA.2/ 4598 dated the 23rd of November, 1946, to which I am sorry to have been so long in replying? The reason is that the digging out of records takes time. point 15 miles north of Khor Odaid is in Qatar terri tory. The Saudi claim gives Nikyan al Katar to Qatar and leaves Khor Odaid to Saudi Arabia. We do not admit that Saudi Arabia has any egress to the sea in that area, and I should hope that we should be prepared to withstand an advance of claim at this stage to 15 miles north of the Khor. 3. We, as you know, consider the north bank of the Khor as Abu Dhabi territory. In any case vis a vis the □atar-Abu Dhabi frontier question, I presume that there would be no difficulty raised between Petroleum Concessions (Qatar) Limited and petroleum Concessions (Trucial Coast) Limited? 4. The above are my views and of course need confirm ing. I suggest that before I put the matter up to His Males tv’s Government we await the return of H.M.5. t, Challenger !, when we shall hope to learn the map co-ordi. of the site in question. Do you agreed 2 So far as I can see there is no doubt that a vours sincerely V. Packer, Esq., M.B.E., Messrs, petroleum concessions Ltd., Bahrain. NS.3 ? n. CODES: * 6'* Jj BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE JROLEUM DEyELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED DIRECTORS 1 Lord Caoman, e.c.M.G. (chairman), R. Cay G. legh-Jones, J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch), iw , •DrS'-'C. (PKojMCnij^W. Fraser, C.B.E., c. s. gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) ^ A. meny (French), H. G. 8 »bbl (u.S a,), r. w. sellers, j. skliros ^) , Q &amp; R. cU. ^(fyt^LL^PUf BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF QSA.2/4642 CONFIDENTIAL 15th December, 1946. To H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. QATAR OIL TERMINAL SITE We shall be pleased if yon will refer to our No.QSA.2/4598 dated the 23rd November 1946 and its enclosure, to which we note so far no reply has reached us. 2. We understand H.M.S. CHALLENGER, which arrived in Bahrain recently, has now left or is about to leave for the east coast of Qatar to make a survey of the approach to Wakrah, and later to continue the survey down to El Arrif, the alternative terminal site to Wakrah, to which we referred in para 4 of our above- mentioned memo as the location some 15 miles north o Khor Odaid (also in the draft letter to the Ruler as some 20 miles south of Wakrah). . We are assuming that the Captain of the CHALLENGER arries letters of introduction from you to the Ruler nd does not require anything of this nature from the ompany. . Meanwhile, it is desired to commence the construe- ion at an early date, of a launch jetty s0 ^ in ile lone and a' pilot's house near Wakrah which will be ieaeJ SieSo?!™ of .hloh IS fl^lly elected for the terminal. A copy of our draft to tne haikh on this subject is attached. r BAHRAIN RECEIPT. , . JSf * •*■aanMMHMHB mmmm - 2 - QSA.2/4642 (contd.) 5. You may also be interested to hear that the Company propose to construct a new boat harbour on the west coast some 22 miles south of Zekrit at a place called A1 Hamlab. The aim is to provide a harbour in the vicinity of the permanent camp sufficient to unload two 12? feet barges and to afford shelter for tugs, dhows, etc. It is also intended to construct a road from this point across the Peninsula to Wakrah with branches up to Doha and down to El Arrif. 6 . We should like your assurance that you see no objection to the above programme and our draft letter to the Shaikh to which we referred in para 4. For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED Enel. ACM■ ■ draft H.E,Shaikh Abdulla bin Qasim al Thani, Ruler 0 ** Qatar. Your Excellency, We have the honour to refer to our letter No.QSA.2/4622 dated on the subject of possible alternative sites for our oil terminal in the vicinity of Wakrah or Fasht el Arrif. 2. It will be necessary in connection with the marine and land surveys to be made of both possibilities to have a jetty at which launches and small craft can land personnel from H.M.G f s survey ship and later from Company craft engaged in the more detailed survey work. It is proposed therefore to construct as soon as possible a launch jetty approximately half a mile long in the vicinity of Wakrah together with a pilots house. This construction is covered by Article six of the Company*s Concession. We have the honour to beQ^A.2/4668 (contd,) 2, V/e assume that there is no objection to the Company informing the Ruler of propositions (b) (c) (d) and (e). 3, As regards (a), we note that you wish to learn the map co-ordinates of the El Arrif site from H.M.S* 'Challenger” before confirming that the site is in Qatar territory. Unless this information can be furnished in the near future and as a Company marine party recently visited the area and more activity is planned apart from the appearance of H.M.S. 'Challenger' on the scene, we feel that our communication to the Ruler should not be delayed, and there is no harm in assuming El Arrif is in Qatar territory for the purpose of this communication to him. 4, Will you please return the draft forwarded with our No.4598 as we shall be changing it to cover the above propositions including (a! if you agree. Yours sincerely, Lt.-Col. A.C. Galloway , O.B.ii., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.EXPRESS LETTER prom - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Political Resident, Bahrain. No.C/ll. Dated the 4th of January, 1947. Reference correspondepe'e ending with my Endorse ment No. c/1285 dated the 18th ifovember, 1946. I enclose a copy of a letter received from petroleum Concessions Limited. 2. My comments are (x) that there is no objection to the Shaikh of Qatar being informed of (b), (c) and (d). information should not be conveyed yet to the Shaikh since it is dependent on (a). in that area of,the frontier is that the Saudi Arabian Government consider that Nikyan al Katar belongs to Qatar and that south of that, point is Saudi Arabian territory. This means that they claim the Khor Odaid and a few miles of the coast to the north. His Majesty’s Government, however, maintain that the north shore of the Khor Odaid is the north-western extremity of Abu Dhabi territory and that northwards is Qatar territory. north of the Khor Odaid and may, therefore, lie in disputed territory: it certainly must be close to it. The site is of the greatest importance to petroleum concessions Limited, and before I can give a definite opinion whether or not it is in disputed territory, I must know its exact situation. I, therefore, request that H.M.S. 'Challenger'' may be asked telegraphically to inform me of the map co-ordinates urgently. 4. In the meanwhile I should be grateful for con firmation that (b), (c), and (d) may be conveyed to the Shaikh of Qatar. (y) As regards (e) it seems to me that this (z) As regards (a) my estimation of the situation 3 Al Arrif is said to be situated some 15 miles Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY political Agent, Bahrain ATTESTED. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. NS.B.o. No. c/36. V The 8th of January, 1947. My dear packer, X asked the political Resident to telegraph 'Challenger 1 * regarding Al Arrif, but before he does so he requests further details. X am under the impression that 'Challenger* knows enough about Al Arrif to answer the question, but this ffi ay not b ® correct so would you please mant «* «*« «£»** T w *'£ h olease return - what area you wish to Include in the term Al Arrif. Its southern limit is the most important, of course# 2 . I hope to give you an early reply to poJjnts (b), (c) and (d), and return your draft letters— vours sincerely. i. ■ f ,V* Packer, Esq., M.B.E.* Messrs, petroleum concessions Ltd., B a hrain. NS. ). * i 11GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, PERSIAN GUL? RESIDENCY ..Dspaetmint, BAHRAIN. [N % B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of (die wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From REPGU BAHRAIN CONFIDENTIAL No. 61 - S. the 7th January, 1947. ^ • c &lt;y(n S ' 0 Vi--' Paragraph 4 of your express letter No. C/ll, dated the 4th January, 1947. 2 , (b), (c) and (d) may be conveyed to the Dhaikh of Qatar. = REPGU = The issue of the above been authorised. Secretary'to tEe rdfitical Resident JU^-the Persian Gulf. G.A.M. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Date.. /I:. !:&amp; S. 6. MFP— 1407 s&amp;p —/M-2339V—25-5-37—300.000.D*G* No.C/56 1947 The 11th of January, My dear packer, Will you please refer to the correspondence ending with my demi-official letter No*c/36 dated the 8th January, 1947? 2. I am to inform you that there is no objection to your Informing the Shaikh of Qatar of propositions (b), (c) and (d). yours sincerely E.V. Packer, Esq., Messrs, petroleum Concessions, Ltd., Bah rain.1. I am afraid, I am not in a position to mark on your chart the area we require for the 'i'erminal Dock site, and I do not think the engineers have reached a stage when this can be done. Everything depends on the results of the 'Challenger's' survey and our own marine and land surveys. 1 am. referring your query to London, but X am sure the situation is as explained above. ~ ^ 2. Meanwhile 1 feel as explained in para 3 of my letter Xio.QjSA. 2/4668 that we should inform the Huler of Qatar of our plans in general terms assuming for this purpose that the Terminal oil dock in the vicinity of El Arrif will be in Qatar territory. w . As brought to your notice in previous correspondence the Huler has expressed objections to the use of ^akrah and this southern area in general, and we feel that it is highly desirable that he should be induced to accept the situation before a stage is reached when opposition might dislocate a co-ordinated programme with resultant loss of time and money to the Company, ^ IVhen making this communication to the Sheikh X should like, with your permission, to mention that the H.B.M*s Political Agent has been informed of the Company* s plans. 5 # Reference your para 2 we note that you omit any reference to our sub-para (e) on the question of a road across the peninsula. 6. Your chart is returned herewith. \ » Yours sincerely, tncl: Chart. Political Agency, Bahrein. BAHRAri'f RECEIPT. Dat e J..h;.L t gTelegram From To TRepgu, Bahrain. political resident, aboard S.Y. Nearchus No.87. Dated 20th, received 21st January 1947. From Felly. In-compliance with signal from SuOPG Southern spoke to me about Fl frrif. Only area of that name he knows is Fesht al frrif shovm on Gulf Eastern Sheet No. 2857a and mentioned at page 182 and 185 Ninth Edition of Persian Gulf Pilot, jm I to make further reference to him ? It is difficult to see how he can be expected to define shore limits of area. Relevant file is with you. _ RhPGU - NPG. CONFlDlin'-i la-u No.C/8. Office of the Political Resident Persian Gulf, aboard S.Y. 'Nearchus”, ’plst January, 1947. Copy forwarded with compliments to The Political A gent, Bahrain , for favour of discussion.EXPRESS LETTER . Prom: Political Agent, Bahrain, On Board L.T. n Nearchus M . To: Political Resident, Persian Gulf No.Tc/7. f/% Dated the S2nd of January, 1947, Reference our discussion on your Endorsement No.C/8 of the 21st January, 1947.^ ?/] 1 ; 2. I raised the question of the limits of A-l Arif and the area required for the terminal site with the Manager, Petroleum Concessions (Qatar), Limited, before I left Bahrain. He has replied: 'I am afraid, I am not in a position to mark on your chart the area we require for the Terminal Dock site, and I do not think the engineers have reached a stage when this can be done. Everything depends on the results of the 'Challenger's' survey and our own marine and land surveys. I am referring your query to London, but I am sure the situation is as explained above'. 3. From the above it is clear that 'Challenger' has been given an area to survey, and that petroleum Concessions Limited are making land and marine surveys of the region. When these surveys have been co-ordi nated, and the P.C.L. engineers have decided upon the site they require only then can it be said whether the site lies within Qatar territory or not. 4. It seems, therefore, that no further reference need be made to 'Challenger'. I am awaiting the reply from London. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY Political Agent, Bahrain ATTESTED. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. NS.CONFIDENTIAL D.O. No. 119 - S PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY. BAHRAIN. the 16th/18th January, 1947 Mundy me this morning and said that Gray Mackenzie *s hoped in about six months to start operations at Hamlab and later to transfer their activi ties to El Arif or whatever port may be selected by Petroleum Concessions Limited on the east coast of Qatar. He also said that his Company would want greatly to extend their activities at Dubai in about eighteen months 1 time to keep pace with Petroleum Concessions Limited^ developments on the Trucial Coast. He asked me whether the Shaikhs of Qatar and Dubai were likely to prove obstructive. I said I thought they would probably open their mouths pretty wide but apart from this I did not think there would be much difficulty. He then asked me whether we would assist in keeping the Shaikh’s demands within reason. I said we would do what we could but that I could not guarantee anything. I then suggested that either his headquarters in London should write to the India Office or the firm’s represen tatives here to the Political Agent stating exactly what was required. He replied that his firm had not yet reached a final agreement with Petroleum Concessions Limited but that when this had been done Meikle would be instructed to write to you on the lines proposed. Lieutenant Colonel A. C. Galloway, C.I.E., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain.% From: EXPRESS LETTER. Political Agent, Bahrain, On Board L.T. 'Nearchus'. ft J To: Political Resident, Persian Gulf. No.Tc/9. Dated the 23rd of January, 1947. Reference your Express Letter No.Sl-S dated the 7th January, 1947. 2 . I told Packer that he might inform the Shaikh of Qatar of (b), (c) and (d) and he replied requesting authority to inrorm him also of (a) and (e). He states that the Shaikh of Qatar has expressed objections to the use of Wakrah and that southern area in general. He, therefore, feels that it is highly desirable that the Shaikh should be induced to accept the situation before a stage is reached when opposition might dis locate a co-ordinated programme with resultant loss of time and money to the Company. 3. While I should not contemplate permitting the Shaikh of Qatar to dislocate so important a programme, if Petroleum Concessions Limited feel that they wish to avoid any possibility of this by informing him now I think we should agree. Decision whether the terminal site is in Qatar territory or not should not be allowed to hold up information being conveyed to the shaikh in view of P.C.L.*3 request. An actual decision is bound to be long delayed unless it is to be unilateral, since the other interested party is Saudi Arabia. 4. Packer, if he receives permission to communicate (a) and (e) to the Shaikh wishes to add that the political Agent has been informed of the Company’s plans. I see no objection to this, and request authority to inform packer so and that he may convey (a) and (e) to the Shaikh of Qatar. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. ir/t- for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. NS. - - T *''.. -X&gt;.D. RO.TC/16, On Board L*T* * f Hearchus f S at Saa, The 2?th January, 1947. My dear Packer, , £\0 Will you please refer to your letter Ho. D0/Q3A.2/4683 dated the 11th of January, 1947? 2. There is no objection to your informing the Shaikh of Qatar of propositions (a) and (e). 3. Your paragraph 4. You may mention in your letter to the Shaikh of Qatar that the political Agent has been informed of the Company’s plans. Yours sincerely, jS&gt; E.V. Packer, Esq., Messrs, petroleum concessions, Ltd., Bahrain. NS, \V JI OONFIDMTIAL DQ/qSA.^/4778 My dear uolonel, Will you please refer to correspondence ending witii your i)0. wo. Tc/l6 dated tiie 27td January 1947. 1. On receipt of your adovementioned letter, we notified tne miler of Q,atar of tne Gompany’s proposi tions and tne situation regarding tnem. we attacn a copy of nis reply, from wnicn you will see tnat ne does not approve of the use of wakrah or its vicinity oy tne oompany but gives his general approval to the remainder of tne company 1 s programme. 5. We have notified our London principals. 4. A party of our senior engineers from London is due on March tne 11th and will doubtless be instructed to re-examine the Wakrah proposition among others. We will keep you informed of any fresh developments. Yours sincerely, ^4/ wnclo. Lt.-Col. A. C.Calloway, C.I.K., s Polit ic al Agent, Bahrain. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. DateTranslation rrom Abdulla bin .aaim &amp;1 Tuani, Huler of Hatar. To The Manager, Tetroloum Pavelopn^nt ( ^atar5 Ltd. After compliments - Te thank you for your letter Ho. 8A.2/4?25 dated the 13th February 1947, and appreciate the efforts you are making to rush through the work. We note the situation regardin'-, the company’s plana oi intended operations, md trust you have the assurance that we support and approve of every one which would ultimately lead to the goal we all aim at of expediting the production of oil. .We are indeed keen on doing our utmost to encourage those in charge to cope with the work necessary to attain the goal, and it wives us pleasure to see mutual co-operation e xenon gel bj both the sides in sincerity and good will to see the speedy execution of the work in an atmosphere of friendliness and unity of purpose, which would realise the common aim of expediting oil production, re naturally realise that it is in the interest of ell to join shoulders to cope with the tremendous amount - work involved, and believe you have by now seen the effects of nw* f*n-onfiration we have so far shown and the facilities we aiu granting in matters requiring minute attention as occasioned cy situation and circumstances, re believe the company fully realist this and appreciate, it from us and treats us likewise. To be brief, we would ask the C^pany to nave the assurance that all that is possible from our side is being d J e. / 1 J ?or y r.eason8 letter'^avoided. «• tnerefore do not ooneiaer »u.ia vicinity of wakratt, riol do we it suitable to have it Itt tne v^cx-.i-.v ^ » hK G0/ .p Qn y approve that it be constructed u itu e, i - i-nilarlv the house may not know but which we fully realise, alailariy, (is out of the question). we propose therefore Jen an alternative) is^f ^ be built on the (South) eastern end or ’ in the vicinity of possible to construct ^ positions/pointed out 5 r-r,:.-. o,.a„=uo„ - ua. jetty. We feel confident that .you will *§*** to our prop0sal ^ realise ur views «r« correct. A. s,. f cl “i fSSS'iriJfSS.- ffiSS “1 = U oc.„ '« a W»'t It th. tie.,!* it merits. U su 81 end in S ■* (Sealed) Abdull® bin ns ini. nl Thani). Dated 10th Kabi al Thani 13$^ c/t 2nd March i34?.The matter was not raised by the Shaikh so I took no action. ltd. Jt.C.G. 29/6/46. (52) Letter No. DOASD/4/4373 Dated the 22/7/46 1 from P.C.L. ,'Bahrain. 1 _ The Bahrain Government are very touchy at the moment, and with reason, on the subject of Persians resident in Bahrain_(cf. para 132 of Bahrain Intelligence Summary No.12) and it is suggested that we ask for the Adviser’s coinments on the proposal that P.C.L* should employ this class of -Persians. Incidentally, the only reason why a Persian who has lived here since childhood does not have a C of is that he has never travelled ^abroad. At present &lt;a C of , I, allowing the owner to return to Bahrain, is granted by us after the Adviser has,certified that the Persian in question is an old resident of Bahrain. It is not seen how we can depart from this practice in respect of tnose Persians whom P.C.L. wish to take to ^atar. 1 ' ' ■ ' ■ . ,-A ' - ' vVe may also ask Mr. Packer for more, details about these Persians and the areas in which, they are resident. P. A. i \ OL/V1 L t ■bj. c&gt; chji- 3 *- (£*xAas\ &amp; CaJcVL*—, J Iax lA&gt; JIaI *Y Y _ a. ^i/f U-k&gt; Csr •3S7i- A^r':v&lt; r ?-;r: &gt;&amp;7*: papers are at s.65 and 80. izl- j&gt;. 12 7 It is understood that company's assumption in para* 3 of p.u.c. is correct, and it is presumed that excuse mentioned in para.2 was made in connection with site just south of Wakrah. However, Qatar territory south of Wakrah seems to be given over to the bedouin in their seasonal migrations, many if not most of whom come from Hasa and other territories outside Qatar and own allegiance to ibn Satt^* There would seem therefore to be some reason in Shaikh's objections to the southern terminal sites. Moreover the second alternative site should be located well into the jabal &gt; Nikhan and very near the frontier claimed by Saudi Arabia, see red line in enclosure to Residency X.L. at s.91 of F.38/11 (submitted separately). Fasht al Arrif is not traceable on any of the maps so far consulted - but please see p.C.L. blue-print below. please see also s.ll and 13 of F«ll/5 below* 'fX' w P.A. r, 14/12/'46. - tXJ &amp;- y i- / r e' 7^ ' f2 / Ko . e/,4 0 9 2 oexi -bt 'trh'*' Pu, IjlL rtc 6!a.i//fH9 /:k ' Wv j £Ul; “ f llpt f. TWc lH- » ' . L 1 C'tv 'ti C\S nv—Hlw-i-V' ^ Cj\XS E U^J w. (&lt;£) iW kr&gt;Pi dU^, &lt;: |^efbrH ^ (ifi-A-'ie</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000133_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/864</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000133</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/864</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 38/3 I, P. C. L. Qatar Concession'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-04-24T09:36:19</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (238 folios)</extent><extent>The volume is arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 5-223; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains correspondence relating to the work of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, a subsidiary of Petroleum Concessions Limited, in Qatar. The correspondence is principally between the Political Agent in Bahrain, the Political Residency in Bushire [Persian Gulf Political Residency], representatives of Petroleum Concessions Limited (at their offices in Bahrain and the United Kingdom) and Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited (in the field in Qatar), the Foreign Office, the India Office, the Government of India, the ruler of Qatar, Abdulla bin Qasim al Thani [‘Abdullāh bin Qāsim Āl Thānī], and the ruler of Bahrain, Salmān bin Ḥamad Āl Khalīfah.The papers contained in the volume cover the following matters:the employment of foreign workers within the oil industry in Qatar, particularly that of Americans, Portuguese Goans, and Bahrainis;the expansion of drilling operations during the early stages of the Second World War;plans for a sea terminal on the Qatari coast, and a pipeline to any such port;the striking of oil at a new second well in March 1941;the form and method of payment of the concession royalties to the Shaikh of Qatar by the oil company;measures taken by the Oil Control Board to ensure continuing supplies of oil during the Second World War;the reopening of the Qatar oil fields following a short closure due to war;rates of pay and provision of meals for oil workers.Also within the volume is a report by the Acting Political Resident, William Rupert Hay, on his visit to Qatar on 13 November 1941 (folios 64-66) and a petition to the ruler of Bahrain (folios 148-52) signed by thirty-six Bahraini pearl merchants and boat captains; it complains that higher wages in the Qatar oil industry are attracting essential divers away from the pearling boats (folios 148-52).At the back of the file (folios 224-37) are internal office notes.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Qatar Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Qatar</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Oil Control Board</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Qatar</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Labour relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Employment policy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Qatar</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000133#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>