<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00028a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:49:08.385Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NO. 2/6 From A.Steele, I«U*D* 9 Medical Officer in chr Victoria Memorial Hospital and quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. To The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that I arrived Karachi in the afternoon of the 2nd October, 1945, on expiry of my leave. I assumed charge of the duties of the Medical Officer in charge, Victoria Memorial Hospital and quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, in the afternoon of the 25th October, 1945: vide my charge certificate sent separately. The period of my stay in Karachi may kindly be treated as joining time as I was waiting for a boat for all this period. 2. a salary slip may kindly be issued in my favour and forwarded to me by air mail at an early date. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, % 3/1 I Medical Officer in charge, I Victoria Memorial Hospital and quarantine medical Officer, Bahrain. POLITICAL AGRNCY, BAHRAIN, 3fi*V October, 1945. &lt; 2 &gt; ^ \u :No. 4236 - 52/4. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. No- Bair - Pr-pipt M'S 4 ? and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 20th October , 1945. Reference to previous correspondence : Bahrain memorandum No.2989 dated 22nd July 1945. N f. /7&amp; Description of Enclosure. A * - Name and Date. Subject. Notification No. 277 - E dated the 2nd October, 1945, from the Government of India Leave of First Class Military Assistant SurgeonNO. 277 - E. Government of India, External Affairs Department. Dated New Delhi, the 2nd October, 1945. NOTIFICATION First Class Military Assistant Surgeon M. L. A. Steele, Quarantine Medical Officer, m Bahrain, has been granted two months leave on average pay with effect from the forenoon of the 20th July, 1945. Sd. R. R. Burnett. Secretary to the Government of India. Copy forwarded to the : - Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Accountant General Central Revenues. By order, etc. Sd. Raja Ram. ‘ for Under Secretary to the Government of India. Copied. ^ ‘5* ? G.A.M.OFFICE OF THE A.G.C.R. HEW'DELHI. HO. (33 58-21-3727. Dated the. The political Agent, &lt; ’ ^ Bahrain. H (D air (£) w Mail Kef:- This office memo. TTo.GD 58-21-2077, dated 19.9.45 authorising payment of Joining time pay and leave Salary to Lt. M.L.A* Steele, medical Officer, Bahrain. &lt;1 i 5 joining time and leave admissible to Lt. M.L«A» Steele, I.K.A. have been recalculated a s under:- (i j Joining time from 20.7.45 to 3.8.45 (15 days). (ii) L e a\e on Average pay from 4.3.45 to 1.10.45 (i.e. the date immediately proceeding the day of the Officers 1 arrival at Karachi on retam journey). You are hereby authorised to disburse to Lt. Steele Leave Salary at Hs.630/- (Rupees six hundred and thirty only)P.lv:. for 1.10.45 (one day) also. 2. From 26.10.45 onwards Lt. Steele is authorised to dra* the folio wing:- pay Rs.500/-p.m. special Fay. • • • • • ns. 130/-p.m. Compensatory allowance.^. 50/-p.m. Dearness allowance . . ns. 175/-p.m . ns.855/-p.m7 (Rupees eight hundred and fifty five only)Per mensem. 3. Lt. Steele arrived at Karachi ( the fixea po^ht) on 2.10.45 ana joined duties at Bahrain ogfl the d afternoon of 25.10.45. He, therefore, availed himself of joining time for 24 days agqiast 15 days admissible. As the extension of joining time under S.R.294 A requires the sanction if the Governor General in Council requisitx orders sanctioning the grant of the soq* extension may please be obtained and furnished to this of lice. Authority for the payment J of joining time pay to Lt. Steele for the above period will be f? issued on receipt of orders. 4. Lt. Steele may kindly be informed. Lfti. n xe/ NO. !£)0 C fO- 2/6-A POLXIXCAI, AGENCY BAHRAIN, iXlXOiiAJ iiUiljUOij ,—^ BAHRAIN, ^ (T December, 1945. To ' The Secretary to the Hor^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . wIBMORANDU^ :-- Reference my memorandum No. 4560-2/6, dated the 31st October, 1945. 2. On expiry of his leave Dr.U.L.A.Steele arrived at Karachi on the 2nd October, 1945, and joined for duty at Bahrain on the afternoon of the 25th October, 1945. He, therefore, availed himself of joining time for 24 days against 15 days admissible. of India for the extension of his joining time under S.R. 294-A be obtained and sent to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, direct with a copy to me. It is requested that sanction of the Government for Political Agent, Bahrain. 7From Lt. M.L.A. Steele, Medical Officer in change, V.M. Hospital, Bahrain. To Sir, The Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to state that on the 15th June next I will be due for retirment, and to request that I may be informed as to whether my services will be terminated on that date, or be extended for any further period. In the former case I request that two months leave prior to retirament may be granted me and my and my wife*s passage to the United Kingdom be kindly arranged with the Middle Hast Sea Passage Priority Board for next April or May. In the latter case a passage for my wife only will be required. I have etc., Bahrain, 10th Jan,, 1946. Sd. M.L.A. Steele. No.156-2/6 A. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 13th January, 1946. Forwarded to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, for favour of disnosal. v Sd. R.E.R. Bird, for Political Agent, Bahrain.BRITISH RESIDENCE AND CONSULATE GENERAL From The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Qulf* The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Nev Delhi. Reference Gazette Notification No. 227 - E, dated the 2nd October, 1945, from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. Surgeon Lieutenant M. L. A. Steele, exceeded the Joining time admissible to him under S. R. 294 - A by nine days due to the late arrival of a mall steamer to take him to Bahrain. As according to standing orders of the Government of India such overstayal of Joining time has to be treated as leave, a draft Gazette Notification is enclosed sanctioning him extension of leave on average pay for nine days. Copy to the political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to his memorandum No. 5090 - 2/6 - A dated the 11th December, Memorandum No. 292 - 52/4 Dated Bashire, the 16th January, 1946. 2 While returning from leave Military Assistant for Political Persian Gulf No. 293 - 52/4 Bushire, the 16tn January, 1946 1945r'&amp; DRAFT GAZEITt. MOl'IFICATION / Reference Gazette Notification No. 227 - E dated the 2nd October, 1945, by the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. Military Assistant Surgeon Lieutenant M. L. A. Steele, Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, was granted an extension of leave on average pay for nine days. /cr~ No. 581 - 52/4 K The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, -•* V and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. 14 , British Residency ^22 ^ ” and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated . the ^ 7th &gt; February h 1946 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Notification No. 13 - E, dated the 16th January, 1946 from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. Subject. Medical Officer-in-Charge, Victoria Memorial Hospital, and Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain.No. 816 - 52/8. The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. 'i British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. No // 5 ? • 2 : Dated.. the. 22nd t February, 1946. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. /• ^ BY AIR ivIAIL From - The Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. To - The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum No. F.27(34)-E/45. Dated Simla, the 23th August, 1945. Subject : Extension of tenure of appointment of Military Assistant Surgeon Lieutenant M. L. A. Steele, Quarantine Medical Officer. Bahrain. In continuation of Government of India, External Affairs Department memorandum No. D.2068- E/45, dated the 25th May, 1945. p Y Y/&lt;y/n ) 2. A doubt having arisen as to whether Lieutenant Steele's tenure of appointment began from 1st June, 1941, or from 26th xMay, 1941, i.e. the date from which he was struck off the Military strength for employment under the Civil, it has been held by the Government of India that the tenure of his appointment as Quarantine Medical Officer began with effect from 1st June, 1941, i.e. from the date he actually took charge of his duties at Bahrain, the intervening period - 26th May, 1941, to 31st May, 1941 - being treated as joining time. The extension of tenure should therefore commence from 1st June, 1945. 3d. P. N. Krishnaswamy, Under Secretary to the Government of India. Copied. G.A.M.No. Political Agency, Bahrain, The &lt;s £/^ FebrUur y&gt; 1946. To The Accountant ueneral, Central Revenues, Mew Delhi. uieupranduia: Reference para 3 of your memorandum No.GD. 58-31-3727 of the 22nd November, 1945* ^ f* • / 2. I enclose a copy of memo. No.292-52/4 of the 16th January, 1946 from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, to the Government of India regarding extension of leave to Lieut. M.L.A. Steele. Kindly expedite issue of authority for drawing his leave salary from the 2nd to the 10th October, 1945 and join ing time pay from the 11th to the 25th October, 1945. for Political Agent, BahrainE.O . Telegram Code. From Britain, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 341. Dated 33rd received 24th February, 1946. Demi-official Pelly to Galloway. Reference your endorsement No. IStf-2/6A v dated the 13th January. Kindly telegraph whether (a) Steele would like an extension (b) you recommend him for one. = BRITAIN = P LSI. i-K-No Ly.From li't* M.L*A* Medical Officer in charge, Victoria Memoraial Hospital, Bahrain. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, With reference to a copy of the attached memorandum No.G/14643, dated the 24th September, 1945 from the Deputy Assistant Controller of Military Accounts, I have the honour to request that the Director General, Indian Medical Service may kindly be requested to forward I.A.F.S.A. 311 and 312 Retirement Rolls to the Deputy Controller, Military Accounts for necessary action as directed in the above quoted letter. Forwarded to the Director General, Indian Medical Service, New Delhi, for favour of disposal. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 4th March, 1946 No. 787-2/6 A. Bahrain, Political Agency, Bahrain, The 9th March, 1946. for Political Agent, BahrainCopy of memorandum No.G/14643 dated from the &lt;5: P.* Pension Branch Gantt, to Lt. JI.L.A. Steele, I.m.D., Srinagar, Kashmir. 24-9-45 , Lahore Park Hotel Subs Pension. Refs Your letter dated 6-9-45. Under item 13 of the table appended to rule 17 P.R.I. part III (1940) claims for retiring pensions and gratuities of I.xA.D. (Asst. Surgeon Branch) I.A.F.S.A. 311 &amp; 312 (Retirement Rolls) are required to be submitted by the O.C. Unit to this office through the D.G.I.i-I.S., Delhi. Please, therefore, apply to the officer under whom you are serving at present. On receipt of the documents referred to above from the U.G., IMS. , necessary action to sanction your pension and arrangements for its payment through India Office, London, will be taken by this office. Sd. Dy.Asst. Cont.Mily.Acctts.■■Mil Bahrain The 19th ^rch, 1946* The Accountant General 5 Central Revenues ? I have the honour to request that I may be informed as early as possible of the total amount of leave on average pay that I would have zo my credit on the 14th June^ 1946^ assuming that 1 would be on continuous duty up to that date. From Lt. M.L.A. Steele, I.ii.D., To New Delhi Sir I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, r|——r k GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. BRITISH RESIDENCY AND consulate general, Department. BUSHIRE. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL) nUM.—Thit it an ORIGINALmitaige tent by AIR MAIL which proviitt a meant of communication mart expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It t« intended to be tr j' a f e f&gt; on receipt, with the tame expedition at if it had been telegraphed. To save time and lo obviate formalities it it drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a Subject* Tenure of appointment of Military Assistant Surgeon Lieutenant M#L*A# Steele, Indian Medical Department, Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. In accordance with the orders contained in Memo randum No. F.27(34)-E/45 dated the 28th August, 1945, from the Government of India in the External Affairs _ . first class Military Assistant Surgeon Lieutenant^M.L.A. Steele s present tenure of appointment will expire on the 31st May, 1946, and he will attain the age of fifty-five on the 15th June, 1946. He has applied for an extension of service for a further period of one year from the 1st June, 1946. the Political Agent, Bahrain, and the Residency Surgeon, Bushire, I agree with their recommendations and request that Dr. Steele s tenure of service may be extended for a further period of one year from the 1st June, 1946. | &gt;(5opy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to his telegram No. 73 dated the 26th Februar , responsible officer of the Department.] No. 1237- Bushire, To Rahrain Receipt Foreign New Delhi 2# Steele is doing excellent work at Bahrain and his request for extension has been strongly recommended both by •Britaia- The issue of th# abo 1 thorised Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. No. 1238jr52/8. Bushire, the 26th March, 1946 1946 (Signature) V.S.R S. 44. MGIPC—SI—2385(S&amp;P)MFP—(M-1744)—3-12-40—20,000. (Designation). ,1 . GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. v BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL , Department. BUSHIRE• EXPRESS LETTER JV B -This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save lime and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. No. 1301-26/1*. Dated Bushire, the 29th March, 1946. V Bahrain Receipt political NoJJJ.i D»te.A/&amp;/.SfA- Bahrain -» 'Your endorsement No. 156-2/6A January 13th. 2. Since extension oi tenure of Steele’s appoint ment has been recommended, please confirm that passage to the United Kingdom Will be required only for Mrs. Steele, please also furnish usual details required for priority passage. = Britlan =GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dbparimes't. EXPRESS LETTER [N. B.— This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the unves, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.] From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN* To BRITAIN, BUSHIRB. No. 1132-^/6. Bahrain, Dated 10th April, 1946* • Reference your Express Letter No.1301-26/1 dated the 29th March, 1946. 2. It is confirmed that a passage,for Mrs. Steele only &gt; will be required if the extension of tenure or Steeled appointment is sanctioned. The following particulars are furnished:- (a) Age - 54 years. (b) Approximate date passage is required - 1st to 15th May, 1946. (c) When last in the United Kingdom - 1927. oOo POLITICAL - The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. C. S. 6. MFP—501 S&amp;P—(M-820)—23-7-36—300,000.'\ ✓ \ No. 83-E. Government of India. External Affairs Department. Dated New.Delhi 3, the 20th March, 1946. NOTIFICiiTICN . The leave on average pay for two months granted to First Class Military Assistant Surgeon, M.L.A. Steele, Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, « • in the External Affairs Department notification No. 227-E uated the 2nd October, 1945, was extended by nine days. Sd. H. Weightman. Secretary to the Government of India. Copy forwarded to 1. the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 2. the Account an-; General, Central Revenues. By order, etc., Sd. M. O’Meally. Under Secretary to the Govt, of India. //True copy/ AFrom To Regis tered/F rioritv ^ No .28-1/46-(IMD)-P.I. V The Director General, Indian Medical Service. (®) The Political Agent, )3 k ^ * *• • 1t,,STii , t , • fttl New Delhi, the . 3-1946. Subject:- Retirement of Lt.M.L.A. Steele,I.M.D., Medical Officer-in-Charge, V .M. Hospital, Bahrain. Sir, X With reference to your Endorsement No. 787-2/6-A., dated the 9th March, 1946, I have the honour to enclose herewith Forms I.A.F.A-311 and I.A..F.A-312 (in duplicate) for completion and return to this office. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Captain, for Director General, I.M.S.6. Statement of Disability. (To show whether the disqualification for further service has been occasioned by wounds received in action or by ill-health resulting from military duty, or by intemperance or irregular habits.) o Station Dal *— Signature of Medical Officer. 7. Opinion of the Medical Board. Station Date .President, \ Members.INSTRUCTIONS. 1. When a departmental officer, a warrant officer of any department, a soldier mechanic of the Ordnance Department, a Sub-Assistant Surgeon or a Veterinary Assistant Surgeon, is considered unfit for further service, this roll is to be prepared in duplicate and laid before the invaliding board, and when completed with their remarks, should be returned to the officer under whose orders the individual concerned is serving, for transmission, together with a copy of A. F. B-200 in the case of unattached list ranks, through the head of the department (in sufficient time to admit of verification and return for correction, if necessary, and transmission) to the M. A. Department for issue of the Pension notification, etc., at least a fortnight before the individual is timed to leave his station. In the case of those of the I. M. D. in military employ, the roll is to be submitted through the prescribed channel to the D. M. S. in India, for transmission to the D.-G., I. M. S. The rolls of those in civil employ will be forwarded through the Civil A. M. 0. of the Province, etc., to the D.-G., I. M. S. With a view to accelerate the notification of the grant of pension by the Military Accounts Department, the Officer Commanding the hospital from which a Sub-Assistant Surgeon or a Veterinary Assistant Surgeon is about to retire should take steps to obtain from the audit officer concerned verification statement on I. A. F. A-357 showing the rates of pay and* allowances drawn by the Sub-Assistant or Veterinary Assistant Surgeon during 3 years preceding discharge from the service or during 3 years ending on the date of the medical board invaliding the individual from the service, as the case may be, and to forward the same with the claim for pension. This work can be taken in hand as soon as it is known that an individual is retiring within six months. An individual should be declared unfit for service and invalided if the Medical Board is satisfied that he is not capable of discharging efficiently each and every duty pertaining to the to which he belongs. 0 2. A similar procedure is to be observed in the case of a departmental officer, warrant officer, a soldier mechanic of the Ordnance Department, Sub-Assistant Surgeon or a Veterinary Assistant Surgeon applying to retire on the pension of his rank, but in this case statements 6 and 7 need not be completed. 3. In the case of special pension authorised in paragraph 172, Pension Regulations, to soldier mechanics of the Ordnance Department the head of the department concerned should obtain the recommendation of the Govern ment of India as to the rate of pension to be granted to the men and forward the recommendation together with men’s discharge documents, through the Officer-in-Charge of Records concerned, to the Commissioners of Chelsea Hospital with a view to the pension being awarded. In such cases the D. 0. F. &amp; M., or the D. 0. S., as the case may be, should be considered the ‘ head of the department . 4. In all cases the officer under whom the individual is serving will be held responsible that the transaction is completed in sufficient time to admit of the individual being transferred to the Pension Establishment and furnished with the necessary papers before leaving his station. 5. In all applications of departmental warrant officers, other than those of the I. M. D., the retirement certificate (I. A. F. U-1748) should be attached for completion and signature by the head of the department and returned to the retiring warrant officer. 6. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons, service with the 44th Merwara Infantry prior to 1st April 1905 should be shown as Civil (Merwara) and service with the late Hong Kong Regiment and the Asiatic Artillery as Military (Hong Kong Regiment) and Military (Asiatic Artillery), respectively. All periods of service, including those in any particular grade, should be entered in columns 3 and 4, the particular department such as Civil (Merwara). etc., in which passed being only shown in column 2. If the Sub-Assistant Surgeon has not been in continuous receipt of English qualification pay for the last three years of his service, the period or periods during those years for which such pay was drawn should be specified. 7. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons and Veterinary Assistant Surgeons of and above the rank of Jamadar three specimen signatures should be furnished on the space below each copy of the roll. In case of others below that rank, the impressions of the balls of the thumb and all the fingers of the left hand should be recorded. 8. This form should be used in all cases of compulsory retirement. 9. A last-pay certificate and a no-demand certificate must be furnished when applying for payment of pension. 10. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons and Veterinary Assistant Surgeons who are invalided from the service, the statement of the case and the proceedings of the Medical Board recorded on pages 5 to 8 of I. A. F. Y-1948 in accordance with the instructions printed thereon, should accompany the claim for pension (I. A. F. A-311). 11. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons and Veterinary Assistant Surgeons who are invalided from service on account of disabilities attributable to military service and who were in service on the 20th July 1926, a certificate whether they have elected to come under the new rules governing the grant of disability pensions or have elected to remain under the rules which were in force before the above date should be furnished. MFP—1072 C 1 (H)—rFT-212)—20-0-40—2,000.6. Statement of Disability. .ill hi«ltl 7 8 r°, W ir' het !* er f °r further aemoe has been occasioned by wounds raceivod in action or bv all-health resulting from nnhtary duty, or by intemperance or irregular habits.) oc i ea ,n action or by Station Date Signature of Medical Officer. 7. Opinion of the Medical Board. &gt; Station Date .President. ► Members.INSTRUCTIONS. 1. When a departmental officer, a warrant officer of any department, a soldier mechanic of the Ordnance Department, a Sub-Assistant Surgeon or a Veterinary Assistant Surgeon, is considered unfit for further service, this roll is to be prepared in duplicate and laid before the invaliding board, and when completed with their remarks, should be returned to the officer under whose orders the individual concerned is serving, for transmission, together with a copy of A. F. B-200 in the case of unattached list ranks, through the head of the department (in sufficient time to admit of verification and return for correction, if necessary, and transmission) to the M. A. Department for issue of the Pension notification, etc., at least a fortnight before the individual is timed to leave his station. In the case of those of the I. M. D. in military employ, the roll is to be submitted through the prescribed channel to the D. M. S. in India, for transmission to the D.-G., I. M. S. The rolls of those in civil employ will be forwarded through the Civil A. M. 0. of the Province, etc., to the D.-G., I. M. S. With a view to accelerate the notification of the grant of pension by the Military Accounts Department, the Officer Commanding the hospital from which a Sub-Assistant Surgeon or a Veterinary Assistant Surgeon is about to retire should take steps to obtain from the audit officer concerned verification statement on I. A. F. A-35/ showing the rates of pay and allowances drawn by the Sub-Assistant or Veterinary Assistant Surgeon during 3 years preceding discharge from the service or during 3 years ending on the date of the medical board invaliding the individual from the service, as the case may be, and to forward the same with the claim for pension. This work can be taken in hand as soon as it is known that an individual is retiring within six months. An individual should be declared unfit for service and invalided if the Medical Board is satisfied that he is not capable of discharging efficiently each and every duty pertaining to the to whicl1 belon g 8 - ^ 2. A similar procedure is to be observed in the case of a departmental officer, warrant officer, a soldier mechanic of the Ordnance Department, Sub-Assistant Surgeon or a Veterinary Assistant Surgeon applying to retire on the pension of his rank, but in this case statements 6 and 7 need not be completed. 3. In the case of special pension authorised in paragraph 172. Pension Regulations, to soldier mechanics of the Ordnance Department the head of the department concerned should obtain the recommendation of the Govern ment of India as to the rate of pension to be granted to the men and forward the recommendation together with men’s discharge documents, through the Officer-in-Charge of Records concerned, to the Commissioners of Chelsea Hospital with a view to the pension being awarded. In such cases the D. 0. F. &amp; M., or the D. 0. S., as the case may be, should be considered the ‘ head of the department 4. In all cases the officer under whom the individual is serving will be held responsible that the transaction is completed in sufficient time to admit of the individual being transferred to the Pension Establishment and furnished with the necessary papers before leaving his station. 5. In all applications of departmental warrant officers, other than those of the I. M. D., the retirement certificate (I. A. F. U-1748) should be attached for completion and signature by the head of the department and returned to the retiring warrant officer. 6. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons, service with the 44th Merwara Infantry prior to 1st April 1905 should be shown as Civil (Merwara) and service with the late Hong Kong Regiment and the Asiatic Artillery as Military (Hong Kong Regiment) and Military (Asiatic Artillery), respectively. All periods of service, including those in any particular grade, should be entered in columns 3 and 4. the particular department such as Civil (Merwara). etc., in which passed being only shown in column 2. If the Sub-Assistant Surgeon has not been in continuous receipt of English qualification pay for the last three years of his service, the period or periods during those years for which such pay was drawn should be specified. 7. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons and Veterinary Assistant Surgeons of and above the rank of Jamadar three specimen signatures should be furnished on the space below each copy of the roll. In case of others below that rank, the impressions of the balls of the thumb and all the fingers of the left hand should be recorded. 8. This form should be used in all cases of compulsory retirement. 9. A last-pay certificate and a no-demand certificate must be furnished when applying for payment of pension. 10. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons and Veterinary Assistant Surgeons who are invalided from the service, the statement of the case and the proceedings of the Medical Board recorded on pages 5 to 8 of I. A. F. Y-1948 in accordance with the instructions printed thereon, should accompany the claim for pension (I. A. F. A-311). 11. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons and Veterinary Assistant Surgeons who are invalided from service on account of disabilities attributable to military service and who were in service on the 20th July 1926, a certificate whether they have elected to come under the new rules governing the grant of disability pensions or have elected; to remain under the rules which were in force before the above date should be furnished. MFP—1072 C 1 (HWH 212)—20.&lt;M0—2,000.6. Statement of Disability. ill-he^th 7 8 res^tin^from^ atl0n for service has been occasioned by wounds received in action or by m neaitn resulting from military duty, or by intemperance or irregular habits.) n&gt; Station Date Signature of Medical Officer. 7. Opinion of the Medical Board. .President. Station Date * Members.INSTRUCTIONS. 1. When a departmental officer, a warrant officer of any department, a soldier mechanic of the Ordnance Department, a Sub-Assistant Smgeon or a Veterinary Assistant Surgeon, is considered unfit for further service, this roll is to be prepared in duplicate and laid before the invaliding board, and when completed with their remarks, should be returned to the officer under whose orders the individual concerned is serving, for transmission, together with a copy of A. F. B-200 in the case of unattached list ranks, through the head of the department (in sufficient time to admit of verification and return for correction, if necessary, and transmission) to the M. A. Department for issue of the Pension notification, etc., at least a fortnight before the individual is timed to leave his station. In the case of those of the I. M. D. in military employ, the roll is to be submitted through the prescribed channel to the D. M. S. in India, for transmission to the D.-G., I. M. S. The rolls of those in civil employ will be forwarded through the Civil A. M. 0. of the Province, etc., to the D.-G., I. M. S. With a view to accelerate the notification of the grant of pension by the Military Accounts Department, the Officer Commanding the hospital from which a Sub-Assistant Surgeon or a Veterinary Assistant Surgeon is about to retire should take steps to obtain from the audit officer concerned verification statement on I. A. F. A-357 showing the rates of pay and allowances drawn by the Sub-Assistant or Veterinary Assistant Surgeon during 3 years preceding discharge from the service or during 3 years ending on the date of the medical board invaliding the individual from the service, as the case may be, and to forward the same with the claim for pension. This work can be taken in hand as soon as it is known that an individual is retiring within six months. An individual should be declared unfit for service and invalided if the Medical Board is satisfied that he is not capable of discharging efficiently each and every duty pertaining to the j^rTrLat to wticl1 belon g 8 - ^ 2. A similar procedure is to be observed in the case of a departmental officer, warrant officer, a soldier mechanic of the Ordnance Department, Sub-Assistant Surgeon or a Veterinary Assistant Surgeon applying to retire on the pension of his rank, but in this case statements 6 and 7 need not be completed. 3. In the case of special pension authorised in paragraph 172, Pension Regulations, to soldier mechanics of the Ordnance Department the head of the department concerned should obtain the recommendation of the Govern ment of India as to the rate of pension to be granted to the men and forward the recommendation together with men’s discharge documents, through the Officer-in-Charge of Records concerned, to the Commissioners of Chelsea Hospital with a view to the pension being awarded. In such cases the D. 0. F. &amp; M. ( or the D. 0. S., as the case may be, should be considered the ‘ head of the department \ 4. In all cases the officer under whom the individual is serving wdll be held responsible that the transaction is completed in sufficient time to admit of the individual being transferred to the Pension Establishment and furnished with the necessary papers before leaving his station. 5. In all applications of departmental warrant officers, other than those of the I. M. D., the retirement certificate (I. A. F. U-1748) should be attached for completion and signature by the head of the department and returned to the retiring warrant officer. w 6. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons, service with the 44th Merwara Infantry prior to 1st April 1905 should be shown as Civil (Merwara) and service with the late Hong Kong Regiment and the Asiatic Artillery as Military (Hong Kong Regiment) and Military (Asiatic Artillery), respectively. All periods of service, including those in any particular grade, should be entered in columns 3 and 4, the particular department such as Civil (Merwara), etc., in which passed being only shown in column 2. If the Sub-Assistant Surgeon has not been in continuous receipt of English qualification pay for the last three years of his service, the period or periods during those years for which such pay was drawn should be specified. 7. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons and Veterinary Assistant Surgeons of and above the rank of Jamadar three specimen signatures should be furnished on the space below each copy of the roll. In case of others below that rank, the impressions of the balls of the thumb and all the fingers of the left hand should be recorded. 8. This form should be used in all cases of compulsory retirement. 9. A last-pay certificate and a no-demand certificate must be furnished when applying for payment of pension 10. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons and Veterinary Assistant Surgeons who are invalided from the service, the statement of the case and the proceedings of the Medical Board recorded on pages 5 to 8 of I. A. F. Y-1948 in accordance with the instructions printed thereon, should accompany the claim for pension (I. A. F. A-311). 11. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons and Veterinary Assistant Surgeons who are invalided from service on account of disabilities attributable to military service and who were in service on the 20th July 1926, a certificate whether they have elected to come under the new rules governing the grant of disability pensions or have elected to remain under the rules which were in force before the above date should be furnished. MFP—1072 C I 212)—20-0-40—2,000.6. Statement of Disability. 9 ^ ill t ^ e( l ua ^ ca ^ on ^ or father service has been ocoaaioned by wounds reeeivod in action or bv ail-healtn reaulting from military duty, or by intemperance or irregular habits.) 7 Station Date Signature of Medical Officer. 7. Opinion of the Medical Board. Station .President. ''v Date * Members.INSTRUCTIONS. 1. When a departmental officer, a warrant officer of any department, a soldier mechanic of the Ordnance Department, a Sub-Assistant Surgeon or a Veterinary Assistant Surgeon, is considered unfit for further service, this roll is to be prepared in duplicate, and laid before the invaliding board, and when completed with their remarks, should be returned to the officer under whose orders the individual concerned is serving, for transmission, together with a copy of A. F. B-200 in the case of unattached list ranks, through the head of the department (in sufficient time to admit of verification and return for correction, if necessary, and transmission) to the M. A. Department for issue of the Pension notification, etc., at least a fortnight before the individual is timed to leave his station. In the case of those of the I. M. D. in military employ, the roll is to be submitted through the prescribed channel to the D. M. S. in India, for transmission to the D.-G., I. M. S. The rolls of those in civil employ will be forwarded through the Civil A. M. 0. of the Province, etc., to the D.-G., I. M. S. With a view to accelerate the notification of the grant of pension bv the Military Accounts Department, the Officer Commanding the hospital from which a. Sub-Assistant Surgeon or a Veterinary Assistant Surgeon is about to retire should take steps to obtain from the audit officer concerned verification statement on I. A. F. A-357 showing the rates of pay and allowances drawn by the Sub-Assistant or Veterinary Assistant Surgeon during 3 years preceding discharge from the service or during 3 years ending on the date of the medical board invaliding the individual from the service, as the case may be, and to forward the same with the claim for pension. This work can be taken in hand as soon as it is known that an individdM is retiring within six months. An individual should be declared unfit for service and invalided if the Medical Board is satisfied that he is not capable of discharging efficiently each and every duty penaining to the g^^ment to wllicl1116 belongs. ^ 2. A similar procedure is to be observed in the case of a departmental officer, warrant officer, a soldier mechanic of the Ordnance Department, Sub-Assistant Surgeon or a Veterinary Assistant Surgeon applying to retire on the pension of his rank, but in this case statements 6 and 7 need not be completed. 3. In the case of special pension authorised in paragraph 172. Pension Regulations, to soldier mechanics of the Ordnance Department the head of the department concerned should obtain the recommendation of the Govern ment of India as to the rate of pension to be granted to the men and forward the recommendation together with men’s discharge documents, through the Officer-in-Charge of Records concerned, to the Commissioners of Chelsea Hospital with a view to the pension being awarded. In such cases the D. 0. F. &amp; M., or the D. 0. S., as the case may be. should be considered the ‘ head of the department \ 4. In all cases the officer under whom the individual is serving will be held responsible that the transaction is completed in sufficient time to admit of the individual being transferred to the Pension Establishment and furnished with the necessary papers before leaving his station. 5. In all applications of departmental warrant officers, other than those of the I. M. D., the retirement certificate (I. A. F. U-1748) should be attached for completion and signature by the head of the department and returned to the retiring warrant officer. 6. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons, service with the 44th Merwara Infantry prior to 1st April 1905 should be shown as Civil (Merwara) and service with the late Hong Kong Regiment and the Asiatic Artillery as Military (Hong Kong Regiment) and Military (Asiatic Artillery), respectively. All periods of service, including those in any particular grade, should be entered in columns 3 and 4, the particular department such as Civil (Merwara). etc., in which passed being only shown in column 2. If the Sub-Assistant Surgeon has not been in continuous receipt of English qualification pay for the last three years of his service, the period or periods during those years for which such pay was drawn should be specified. 7. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons and Veterinary Assistant Surgeons of and above the rank of Jamadar three specimen signatures should be furnished on the space below each copy of the roll. In case of others below that rank, the impressions of the balls of the thumb and all the fingers of the left hand should be recorded. 8. This form should be used in all cases of compulsory retirement. 9. A last-pay certificate and a no-demand certificate must be furnished when applying for payment of pension 10. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons and Veterinary Assistant Surgeons who are invalided from the service, the statement of the case and the proceedings of the Medical Board recorded on pages 5 to 8 of I. A. F. Y-1948 in accordance with the instructions printed thereon, should accompany the claim for pension (I. A. F. A-311). 11. In the case of Sub-Assistant Surgeons and Veterinary Assistant Surgeons who are invalided from service on account of disabilities attributable to military service and who were in service on the 20th July 1926, a certificate whether they have elected to come under the new rules governing the grant of disability pensions or have elected to remain under the rules which were in force before the above date should be furnished. MFT— 1072 c 1 OT) — (H 212)—20-9-40—2,000.RECORD OR SERVICE. s ^ I. A. F. A-312. Statement of the total and Imperial service of the undermentioned Officer up to the date of Discharge, Grant of Reward, or Death, as the case may be. Name Rank Corps or department Date of commencement S- of pension or reward j Cause of retirement Domicile (Asiatic or non-Asiatic) Date of birth Age when pensioned or Age when attested (a) Reward granted Date of grant of pension or reward r J Rank. 0 ) Total seryicb. Corps or department. ( 2 ) (5) Service rendered in or otrx of India to the Imperial Government specifying where. From (3) To (4) iYears. Months (5) 1 (6) Station. (7) Nature of employ ment. ( 8 ) From (9) To ( 10 ) Years. (H) Months. ( 12 ) ( c ) Service under the Civil or Marine Department. Deptt. Appointment held. F rom To Years. (a) Good Conduct medal, annuity or gratuity. (b) This heading i (c) Under this heading Service, if any, under Central Government (Civil Department), each Provincial Government and Marine Department should be shown separately. I certify that, according to the records in my possession, this is a correct statement of the total and Imperial service and age of the abovenamed officer. Warrant officer. Signature _ Designation Note 1.—Columns 5, 6, 11 and 12 should be left blahk. Note 2.—For instructions regarding preparation of the ttecord of Service please see reverse.Instructions for preparing the record of service- 1. The incidence of pension follows that of pay. Pension is not, therefore, finally chargeable to Indian Revenues except for service in respect of which the ^arra^tTgcerT^eSr P a ^ ^ as ^ eeu borne as a final charge on these revenues, or a pension contribution has been received from the officer or his non-Indian employer. 2. Imperial Revenues are chargeable with the pay and consequently with the pension of ^arraiuTfficerf etc no ^ on ty from the date of embarkation from India for Imperial service to that of disembarkation on return but also for the following special periods, viz. :— (а) Service at the Depots in India of units employed on Imperial service. (б) During special South Africa, China, Somaliland and Iraq leave. (c) During all other leave granted at the expense of His Majesty’s Imperial Government. (d) In respect of a who was employed on Imperial service during the Great War (1914-1919) the following periods of service will be showm as “Imperial service” in the record of service :— (1) Service overseas and service in India with Depots of units serving overseas and with special formations from 1st June 1919. (2) Service in India during which pay is chargeable to His Majesty's Govern ment other than with Depots and special formations from 1st March 1920. (e) Service rendered in Aden during the Great War is not Imperial service. Service in South Persia after 31st May 1920 and in East Persia after 28th February 1921 is not also Imperial. MFP—645 0 1 (H)—(H’l34)-24-8-39-2,000.r: /*»- A RECORD OF SERVICE. Statement of the total and Imperial service of the undermentioned Officer up to the date of Discharge, Grant of Reward, or Death, as the case may be. fa I. A. F. A-312. Name Rank Corps or department Date of commencement ^ of pension or reward J Cause of retirement Domicile (Asiatic or non-Asiatic) Date of birth Age when pensioned or Age when attested (a) Reward granted Date of grant of pension or reward 1 Rank. 0 ) Total service. Corps or department. ( 2 ) From To Years. Months Station. Nature of employ ment. (3) (4) (5) (6) (7) (8) (b) Service rendered in or out op India to the Imperial Government specifying where. From (9) To ( 10 ) Years. (ID Months. ( 12 ) (e) Service under the Civil or Marine Department. Deptt. Appointment held. From To Years. 'a) Good conduct medal, annuity or gratuity. (b) Phis heading is intended to include all Hntisb {service trom date ot enlistment. (e) Under this heading Service, if any, under Central Government (Civil Department), each Provincial Government and Marine Department should be shown separately. * I CERTIFY that, according to the records in my • possession, this is a corre«t statement of the total and Imperial service and age of the abovenamed officer. Warrant officer. Station Date Signature .19 . Designation Note 1.—Columns 5, 6, 11 and 12 should be left blank. Note 2. For instructions regarding preparation of the Record of Service please see reverse.Instructions for preparing the record of service- 1. The incidence of pension follows that of pay. Tension is not, therefore, finally chargeable to Indian Revenues except for service in respect of which the w^a^tTffi^ers/ etc. P a ‘ V ^ as 1)6611 borne as a final charge on these revenues, or a pension contribution has been received from the officer or his non-Indian employer. 2. Imperial Revenues are chargeable with the pay and consequently with the pension of Departmental officer? ^ , f ^ 0 f embarkation from India for Imperial service to that of disembarkation on return but also for the following special periods, viz. : (а) Service at the Depots in India of units employed on Imperial service. (б) During special South Africa, China, Somaliland and Iraq leave. (c) During all other leave granted at the expense of His Majesty’s Imperial Government. (d) In respect of a wl10 was employed on Imperial service during the Great War (1914-1919) the following periods of service will be shown as “Imperial service” in the record of service :— (1) Service overseas and service in India with Depots of units serving overseas and with special formations from 1st June 1919. (2) Service in India during which pay is chargeable to His Majesty’s Govern ment other than with Depots and special formations from 1st March 1920. (e) Service rendered in Aden during the Great War is not Imperial service. Service in South Persia after 3lst May 1920 and in East Persia after 28th February 1921 is not also Imperial. A1FP—645 0 1 (H)—(fi*l34)—24-8-39 —2,000.of the (3?) ~ £ v — I. A. F. A-311. Koll of of the (No. , Rank and Name) &gt; w ho is considered unfit for further service, and is recommended to be transferred to the Pension Establishment, or who is compulsorily retired, or who requests to be allowed to retire on the pension of his rank, un er the rules of Date of birth (calculated from age given on attestation) Nationality-Domicile (Asiatic or Non-Asiatic), (a) and place of attestation or appointment to I. M. D. or I. A. V. C. of arrival in India and the name of the ship in which arrived —“Date of joining the • ~ Dept. Date of promotion to warrant rank * * * § — T&gt; . | ” £ 05 I ” S3 l :&gt; Character (warrant officers only) § Date from which retirement is desired of transfer to the Unattached List of joining I. U. L. -—^ Furlough rules under which serving - Cause of retirement — Intended address on retirement ♦Personal appearance and identification marks, (b) Place at and Distt. or Independent Brigade in which desirous of drawing pension J Date from which in continuous receipt of English qualification pay (Sub-Assistant Surgeons only)* Rank.(c) Total service in each class (Civil and Military Service separately) from date of Regiment, Department attestation or appointment (Civil or Military *t)- W&gt; L M. D. OB L A. V. 0. Service rendered out of India to the Imperial Govern ment, specifying where. From 3 To 4 Yrs. Mths. 6 6 Stn. Nature of employment. From 7 8 9 To 10 Yrs. 11 Mths. 12 2. Period of absence from duty (no t applicable to those serving under the 1889 Furlough Ru les) Nature of leave (excepting Privilege. Periods of leave Fr om To Years. Days, without pay should be clearly shown as such). Furlough ... Leave Total Period of leave allowed to count as service Balance counting against service Unattached f Regimental service counting for pension (vide copy of A.F. B-200 attached) List only \ Departmental service counting for pension * Sub-Atisistant Surgeons only. Total Civil Service— Total Mily. Service 2-A. Period of forfeited service, if any, from Total service counting for pension to * See paragraph 6 of Instructions as to completion of form in respect of Sub-Assistant Surgeons. t Reeimental service up to date preceding that of joining department should be shown separately and a line drawn across the page. ± The place should be one of those mentioned in the Financial Regulations, India, Part I, Appendix IV. § This information is only required in case of voluntary retirement of members of I. M. D. •o) Whether European, Anglo-Indian or Indian. lb) Applicable to Sub-Assistant and Veterinary Surgeons only. , , ... (c) Paid acting or sub-protem rank* held during the Great War of 1914-19 should also be shown separately m the case of members of the I. U. L.3. I certify that the dates given in this statement of service are correct, as far as can be ascertained from the records in my possession. Station Date Signature of officer under whom serving. 4. I certify that the particulars given in this statement of service have been verified from the records in my possession and that, as far as can be ascertained, they are correct. Statu/ri Date Signature of officer in possession of original record^ duplicate attestation . 5. Remarks by the officer under whom applicant is serving. War services and wounds, if any, to be noted. (To be in the handwriting of the officer submitting the roll.) r Station Date Signature of officer under whom serving. Station Date — Countersignature of Head of Department.of the I. A. F. A-311. Roll of (No. x *,v/. , Rank and Name) Department &gt; w ^° 1 ' 8 considered unfit for further service, and is recommended to be transferred to the Pension Establishment, or who is compulsorily retired, or who requests to be allowed to retire on the pension of his rank, under the rules of Date of birth (calculated from age given on attestation) Nationality-Domicile (Asiatic or Non-Asiatic), (a) T3 . J » ° § &lt;i 31 :: •tj QJ 2 a i $ Is 43 a P and place of attestation or appointment to I. M. D. or I. A. V. 0. of arrival in India and the name of the ship in which arrived the . Dept. of transfer to the Unattached List Date of promotion to warrant rank of joining I. U. L _j—-- Furlough rules under which serving Character (warrant officers only) Cause of retirement — § Date from which retirement is desired Intended address on retirement ♦Personal appearance and identification marks, (b) Place at and Distt. or Independent Brigade in which desirous of drawing pension J Date from which in continuous receipt of English qualification pay (Sub-Assistant Surgeons only)*_ Date of joining Rank.(c) Total service in each class (Civil and Military Service separately)from date of Regiment, Department attestation or appointment (Civil or Military*t)- T0 OR Service rendered out of India to the Imperial Govern ment, SPECIFYING WHERE. From 3 To 4 Yrs. Mths. 5 6 Stn. Nature of employment. 7 8 From 9 Nature of leave (excepting Privilege. Periods of leave without pay should be clearly shown as such). From Furlough Leave To Total Period of leave allowed to count as service Balance counting against service Unattached f Regimental service counting for pension (vide copy of A.F. B-200 attached) List only (^Departmental service counting for pension * Sub-Assistant Surgeons only. Total Civil Service Total Mily. Service 2-A. Period of forfeited service, if any, from Years. Days. Total service counting for pension —to * See paragraph 6 of Instructions as to completion of form in respect of Sub-Assistant Surgeons. + Regimental service up to date preceding that of joining department should be shown separately and a line drawn across the page, t The place should be one of those mentioned in the Financial Regulations, India, Part I, Appendix IV. § This information is only required in case of voluntary retirement of members of I. M. D. (а) Whether European, Anglo-Indian or Indian. (б) Applicable to fchib-Assistant and Veterinary burgeons only. , _ , , . (c) Paid acting or svb-protem ranks held during the Great War of 1914-19 should also be shown separately m the case of members of the I.U.L.3. I certify that the dates given in this statement of service are correct, records in my possession. as far as can be ascertained from the SteUion Date Signature of officer under whom serving. 4. I certify that the particulars given in this statement of service have been verified from the records in my possession and that, as far as can be ascertained, they are correct Signature of officer in possession of original record^ duplicate attestation. 5. Remarks by the ojfuser under whom applicant is serving. War services and wounds, if any, to be noted. (To be in the handwriting of the officer submitting the roll.) Station Date — — Station Date _ Signature of officer under whom serving. Station Date .— — Countersignature of Head of Department.di&gt;3; I. A. F. A-311. • •' • • • . : )• .. . 1 : • ' . ‘ ‘ : . -, % . . Koll of oi the ■■ -r —— rr. (No. , Rank and Name) Department - » w ^° ’‘ 8 considered unfit for further service, and is recommended to be transferred to the ension Establishment, or who is compulsorily retired, or who requests to be allowed to retire on the pension of his rank, under the rules of Date of birth (calculated from age given on attestation)— Nationality-Domicile (Asiatic or Non-Asiatic), (a) &gt;9 . I •1 p M L 3. S C3 I a D and place of attestation or appointment to I. M. D. or I. A. V. C. of arrival in India and the name of the ship in which arrived the - . Dept. — of transfer to the Unattached List • - , —Bat? of promotion to warrant rank T ___ of joining I. U. L. Date of joining Character (warrant officers only) — § Date from which retirement is desired Furlough rules under which serving Cause of retirement * Intended address on retirement ♦Personal appearance and identification marks. (6) Place at and Distt. or Independent Brigade in which desirous of drawing pension J Date from which in continuous receipt of English qualification pay (Sub-Assistant Surgeons only)* — Rank.(c) Total service in each class (Civil and Military Service separately)from date of Regiment, Department attestation or appointment (Civil or Military*!)- TO I - M - ^ 0R !• A - v - °- From 3 To 4 Yrs. Mths. 5 6 Service rendered out of India to the Imperial Govern ment, SPECIFYING WHERE. Stn. Nature of employment. 7 8 2. Period of absence from duty (not applicable to those serving under the 1889 Furlough Rules) Nature of leave (excepting Privilege. Periods of leave without pay should be clearly shown as such). Furlough ... Leave From To Total Period of leave allowed to count as service ... ... ... Balance counting against service Unattached f Regimental service counting for pension (vide copy of A. F. B-200 attached) List only\Departmental service counting for pension * Sub-Assistant Surgeons only. Total Civil Service— Total Mily. Service 2-A. Period of forfeited service, if any, from Years. Days. Total service counting for pension —to * See paragraph 6 of Instructions as to completion of form in respect of Sub-Assistant Surgeons. t Regimental service up to date preceding that of joining department should be shown separately and a line drawn across the page. 1 The place should be one of those mentioned in the Financial Regulations, India, Part I, Appendix IV. § This information is only required in case of voluntary retirement of members of I. M. D. ta» Whether European, Anglo-Indian or Indian. (6) Applicable to Sub-Assistant and Veterinary Surgeons only. tr\ Pni.1 nctimr or gvb-protem ranks held during the Great War of 1914-19 should also be shown separately in the case of members of the (cj Paid acting or aub-protem, I. U. L.S. I certipy that the dates given in this statement of service are correct, as far as can be ascertained from the records in my possession. Station Date Signature of officer under whom serving. ' — ■ ■ ■■ ■ - 4. I certify that the particulars given in this statement of service have been verified from the records in my possession and that, as far as can be ascertained, they are correct. Statiori Date Signature of officer in possession of reoor ^^ duplicate attestation. 5. Remarks by the ojfwer under whom applicant is serving. War services and wounds, if any, to be noted. (To be in the handwriting of the officer submitting the roll.) Station Date Signature of officer under whom serving. Station Date Countersignature of Head of Department.Roll of - ^ ^—t — of the (No. , Rank and Name) Department » wto is considered unfit for further service, and is recommended to be transferred to the Pension Establishment, or who is compulsorily retired, or who requests to be allowed to retire on the pension of his rank, under the rules of Date of birth (calculated from age given on attestation)^ Nationality-Domicile (Asiatic or 4 £ 0 j 0 ) 3 P to [ ” P - 3 l » Non-Asiatic), (a) and place of attestation or appointment to I. D. or I. A. V. C. of arrival in India and the name of the ship in which arrived the Dept. of transfer to the Unattached List Date of promotion to warrant rank Date of joining Character (warrant officers only) § Date from which retirement is desired of joining I. U. L — Furlough rules under which serving Cause of retirement— — Intended address on retirement ♦Personal appearance and identification marks, (b) Place at and Distt. or Independent Brigade in which desirous of drawing pension J Date from which in continuous receipt of English qualification pay (Sub-Assistant Surgeons only)* Rank.(c) i Total service in each class (Civil and Military Service separately) from date of Regiment, Department attestation or appointment (Civil or Military*t)- TO I. M. D. OR I. A. V. C. Service rendered out of India to the Imperial Govern ment, SPECIFYING WHERE. From 3 To 4 Yrs. Mths. 5 6 Stn. Nature of employment. From To Yrs. 7 8 9 10 11 2. Period of absence from duty (not applicable to those serving under the 1889 Furlough Rules) Nature of leave (excepting Privilege. Periods of leave without pay should be clearly shown as such). Furlough ... Leave From To Total Period of leave allowed to count as service Balance counting against service Unattached f Regimental service counting for pension (vide copy of A.F. B-200 attached) ‘I 1 41 List only (^Departmental service counting for pension * Sub-Ausistant Surgeons only. Total Civil Service Total Mily. Service 2-A. Period of forfeited service, if any, from Years. . — Days. — Total service counting for pension —to * See paragraph 6 of Instructions as to completion of form in respect of Sub-Assistant Surgeons. t Regimental service up to date preceding that of joining department should be shown separately and a line drawn across the page. 1 The place should he one of those mentioned in the Financial Regulations, India, Part I, Appendix IV. t This information is only required in case of voluntary retirement of members of I. M. D. (a) Whether European, Anglo-Indian or Indian. lb) Applicable to Sub-Assistant and Veterinary Surgeons only. (c) Paid acting or sub-proten* ranks held during the Great War of 1914-19 should also be shown separately in the case of members of the I. U. L.3. I certify that the dates given in this statement of service are correct, as far as can be ascertained from the records in my possession. Station Dote Signature of officer under whom serving. 4. I certify that the particulars given in this statement of service have been verified from the records in my possession and that, as far as can be ascertained, they are correct- Station Date Signature of officer in possession of origin al record^ duplicate attestation. 5. Remarks by the officer under whom applicant is serving. War services and wounds, if any, to be noted. (To be in the handwriting of the officer submitting the roll.) c Station Date — Signature of officer under whom serving. Station Date Countet signature of Head of Department.No. fclo - 2 /6 Political Agency, Bahrain The^May, 1946. To The Director General, Indian Medical Service, New Delhi. With reference to your letter No.28-1/46- (IMD)-P.l dated the 29th March, 1946, I have the honour to state that Lt. M.L.A. Steele has already filled in the necessary forms (I.A.F.A.311 and I•A.F.A.312) and forwarded them direct to the Residency Surgeon, British Residency &amp; Consulate General, Bushire, on the 28th March, 1946. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant for Political Agent, Bahrain./ M.O. 52/8 Telegram From To No. Dated the G.T.C. Political Resident| at Bahrain. Government of India, New Delhi. T/184 22nd May, 1946. Q-t - 0 My Express Letter 1237-52/8 March 26th 1946. Extension for Steele, Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrain. 2. Grateful for early orders. - HAY - &amp;U..C/1&amp;&gt; Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain. Dated the 22nd May, 1946. ««, * *■ * r Copy forwarded with compliments to i- V The Political Agent, Bahrain. NCJTelegram G.T.C. rt Government of InrH.a, New Delhi. Political Resident at Bahrain. From To No. 4837. Dated the 29th and received 30th May 1946. e 4 ° Your telegram T/184 of May 22nd. Extension for Steele, Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrain. Proposal still under consideration. Decision being expedited. FOREIGN E m / ! l A. J. S • No. 0/ ^3 Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Camp Bahrain. Dated the 1st June 1946. Copy forwarded with' compliments to Political Agent, Bahrain. with reference to Residency EndorsmentT'lfoT C/140 dated the 22nd Kay 1946. Pahra'a Receipt No^39^/ Date 2.. Q BAHr . v ,/&amp;&amp; Office of the Ho« G/443 &gt; Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Gamp, Bahrain, Bated the 9th July 1946. To The Political Agent, Kuwait The Political Agent, Bahrain, Indian Medical Department Officers in ciril employ — grant of increased rates of pay. mjsmoramdum . A copy of External Affairs Department Express Letter Ho. P.7(4)-E/46, dated the 24th June 1946, and of its enclosure, is forwarded herewith. 2. Please conuminicate the enclosure to Asstt. Surgeon C.£*Hynea, Quarantine Medical Officer, Kuwait, Asstt. Surgeon M. L. a.S teele Quarantine Medical Officer, and, if he desires to elect the new terms sanctioned, please obtain from him and forward to this office in duplicate a written certificate electing these terms. Bahra in Sd. W.R.HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf At tested. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf Rahrri TUcsW!: Rtf L,Government of India* External Affairs Department EXPRESS LETTER. From To Eoreign, Simla* Britain, Bush ire. Bo. F .7 (4)-E/46. Dated Simla* the 24th June 1946. Subject:- Indian Medical Department Officers in Civil employ - grant of increased rates of pay. A copy of letter from the Government of India Health Department, Bo. E.42-29/46-M.1. dated the 24th May 1946 on the subject noted above is enclosed for information and communicatio n to the Indian Medical 1. Assistant Surgeon C.E.Hynes, j Quarantine Medical Officer,Kuwait• ) Department Officers 2. As sit. Surgeon, R.Easey, Sub-charge*) Residency Dispensary, Bushire* &gt; mentioned in the 3. Asstt. Surgeon M.L.a. Steele, Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. ) margin. If the Officers are desirous of electing the new terms sanctioned in the enclosure, written certificates electing those terms may kindly be obtained from them and forwarded at sn early date direct to the Director General, Indian Medical Service. Issue of the above has been authorised. 3d. P.B.XR ISHS A3 WAMT. Under Secretary to the Government of India.Copy of lattor Bo. 42-29/46-V.I. dated the 24th Bay 1946 from P. Madhara Menon ^sq. # it.B.E. 9 X.C.3• 9 By. Secretary to the uort. of India, Departxaent of Health to the Director General, Indian Medical Service. Indian Medical Department Officers in ciril employ - * 5rant of increased rates of pay. I am directed to say that the Uovemor General in Council has been pleased to sanation the grant of the following special terms to Indian Medical Department Officers in civil employ on the analogy of the terms sanctioned for Class f B 9 Service officers of the Indian Army Medical Corps. U) Pay In the following scale subject to the proris ions of sub-para. Ill) below i- tfirst 6 months (Licentiates) &amp; 250 first 6 months (Graduates) 500 After 6 months (Licentiates) 500 After completion of 5 years 550 After completion of 5 years 400 Aftei* completion of 7 years 450 After completion of 9 years 550 The officers concerned will, however, nave the choice of continuing to draw the existing scales of pay* if they so desire, (11) An officer will be eligible for an antedate for the fixation of his initial Pay, in consideration of his professional experience, equal to 5 months of every 12 months of the period from the date of his medical qualification to the date of this letter, subject to a maximum of 2ir years. In the case of an officer who received his basic register&amp;ble qualification elsewhere than in India, the period of professional experience for the grant of antedate will reckon'from the date of his registration as a licentiate. Any period of ante* date will count as service for the purposes of increments of pay. Bo back pay will, however, be admissible on account of the grant of an antedate. 2. The concsss ions sanctioned in paragraph 1 above will take effect from the 1st April 1945 and arrears of pay be granted from that date. these concessions will be admissible only for so long as the provisions of Amy Instruction (India) Bo. 114 of 1943 remain In force. 3. The eligibility of officers, who elect to draw pay on the scale referred to in paragraph 1, to the special pay and allowances which are at present attached to par ticular posts is undsr consideration and each case will be reviewed and decided on its merits. in the meantime I am to convey the sanction of the Governor General in Gounoil to the drawal by suoh offioers of the special pay and allowances at the existing rates. Any revision or withdrawal of the existing rates as a result of the review will take effect only from the 1st March 1947 unless Army Instruction (India) Be. 114 of 1943 is itself withdrawn earlier.mm 3 ^ No.2399-2/6. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 24th July, 1946. To The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Camp, Bahrain. p 4 Memorandum. Reference your memorandum No.C/443 dated the 9th July, 1946. 2. Lieut. M.L.A. Steele does not wish to elect the new terms. for Political Agent, Bahrain, 4 /&amp; . ' t.l no : \ No. ^ LsS'S - ^ Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahraij September 2, 1946. Copy to:- Bahrain Receipt The Political Agent, . 'W Bahrain. iu € for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. * «r -tfO. 00 — 2/6 Victoria lieraorial Hospital Bahrain, 29th Septoiabor, 1946. From i-«t*iii.a.A.Steole, i.ii.D., Medical Officer in charge, Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain. To The Accountant General, Central Revenues New Delhi. Sir I have the honour to refer to your letter No.GD.58- 21-537C, dated the 12th April, 1946 and to forward herewith a copy of memorandum No.F.27(26)-iji/46,dated the 22nd August, 1946 from the Government of India, External Affairs Department for information. In this connection it will be seen that I have been compulsarily retained in service from the 15th June, 1946 for a period of six months or till such time as I am relieved. I may therefore please be informed whether the leave at my credit at present will still be admissible to me on the 14th December, 1946 and also to what further leave I will be entitled to on that date. Reply may kindly be sent by air mail. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Medical Officer in charge Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain.N0 * SPf?- 2/6 To POLITICAL AGENCY| The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Bahrain. MTi'.ijnn AunTTr.i ; - _ y\ '' ' Reference your endorseraent No.658-S, dated the 2nd September 1946. J y 2. Copies of letter No. 3200-2/6 dated the 29th September 1946 from Asstt. Surgeon ii.L. A. Steele to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi and of the latter * s reply thereto are enclosed for information. 3 . As Asstt.Surgeon Steele has been(compulsorily) retained in the interests of the public service, it would appear unfair that he should have to forfeit the leave at his credit on the date of his retirement. It is requested therefore that this question should kindly be represented to the Government of India. 4 . It is also requested that a copy of Defence Department letter No.F.28-18/41-1 .ii.D. dated the 21st October 1941 may kindly be furnished for the information of Asstt.Surgeon Steele? vide my telegram No.464- dated the 8 th September 1946. :4 U.6L4 &lt;/ Political Agent, Bahrain.S‘3 NO. 3?S'3- 2/6 VICTORIA ifiSMORIAL HOSPITAI., 5-3 „ BAHRAIN, C c November, 1946 From Lt*i'/LL«A*Steele, Medical • Officer in charge, Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain. The Military Accounts Officer, Lahore Cantt. SUBJECT:- Leave salaray contribution of Lt.U.L.A.Steele, 1.M.D. I have the honour to refer to your letter No.M/IV/ dated the 26th September 1946 and to furnish required'information as under (1) I was attached to B.G.H.Karachi from 14th June 1937 to 26th May 1941 and was then appointed as Asstt.Surgeon,Victoria Memorial Hospital and Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, with effect from the 1st June, 1941. (2) My service documents are in possession of the D.G.I.M.S. New Delhi. Medical Officer in charge, Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain. To o Sir I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant•N E PS D. 0. No.3658 i/&lt; © S S s ©//J2i 52/1 PERSIAN GULP KLSIDENCY, BAHRAIN. the 7th Deceniber, 1946* ' / Jo i'V ' i D A as Coloner Hay is away on tonr I am myself writing to let you know that we h&amp;ve/recommended a years extension for Steele with effect ,from the 16th December, 1946, and that, on the retirement of Greenway on the 15th January, 1947, he should be appointed to act as Residency Surgeon in aduition to his own duties until such time as an Indian Dedical Service Officer becomes available to fill the post of Residency Surgeon. Perhaps you would be good enough to let Steele know of theseBY AIR iilA.IL&gt; No f-2/6 POLITICAL AGENCY December,1946. From Lt* M.L.A.Steele, Medical Officer in charge, Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain To The Controller of Military Accounts A Pensions Lahore Cantt. SUBJECT:- Passage to the United Kingdom rt Sir Would you kindly inform me by air mail whether I am entitled to a passage to the United Kingdom on my retirement. I am Lieutenant in the Indian Medical Department, and am at present attached to the Foreign and Political service in the Persian Gulf Residency'as the Medical Officer in charge, Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain. My service commenced with effect from the 21st April, 1913. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant V/C Lt• I.M.D. Medical Officer in charge, Victoria Memorial Hospital,Bahrain. ikux-j' Lt. I.M.D Medical Officer in charge,&lt;11 Persian Gulf Residency Bahrain, 11th January, 1947. I write in continuation of Pelly^ demi- official letter No.3658-5^/1 of the 7th December, 1946, to say that the Government of India have agreed to Steele*s acting as Residency Surgeon in addition to his duties as Quarantine Medical Officer, pending the appointment of an I.M.S. officer as Residency Surgeon. 2. Colonel Hay understands that Steele is v/llling to stay on as Quarantine Medical Officer, after the l.M»S. man arrives, provided that no change is made in the status or duties of the Quarantine Medical Officer/and the Government of India have accordingly been asked to sanction a yea^s extension for Steele from 15th December, 1946, on these terms. ^ Receipt y ^C'ce-ie^f (S.J.L. Olver) Lt. Col. A.C. Galloway, C.I.E., O.B.E., ii • vs • KJtXXJLyJVi % Political Agent Bahrain.No.258-2/6 dat^d the 21st January *47. My dear Olver Please refer to your deni official letter No.83-o2/l dated the 11th January* 1947, addressed to Colonel Galloway. 2. Steele confirms that he is willing to stay on as Quarantine iedicul Officer on the terras stated in paragraph 2 of your letter. • J.L. Olver, Gsq., Jnder Secretary to the non'ole the Political resident in the Persian Gulf, Yours sincerely JufairCopy of Govt, of India, Defence Department, letter No.F.£8-18/41, I.II.D. dated the 21st October 1941 — received vith External Affairs Department Express Letter No.F.27(26)-E/46 dat^d the 20th March 1947. Compulsory retention In the service during the present emergency of membefs of the Inuian Medical Department (British and Indian^CacTres) who attain the age for superannuation J. w oct ^ Olio, o ; JLIl UOUnCi-JL ^has decided that, during the present war, i^fsistant Surgeons of the Indian Medical Department (British...ami' Indian Cadres) who reach the age limit for compulsory retirement, may, under the provisions of paragraph 48, Regulations for the Medical Services oi the Army in India, 1987, be required by the Director General, Indian Medical Service, at his discretion, to continue in the Service for so long as he may consider necessary, provided they are found suitable and medically fit and their retention does entail an excess in the number of Assistant Sur geons authorised for war expansion needs. 2.^ The terms and conditions on which members of the Indian Medical Department should be compulsorily retained in the service under these orders will be issued later. No. 766-52/8. PER. I^N GULF RESIDENCY Copv forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with refeience to para 4 of his memorandum No.2749-2/6 dated the 16th November 1946. I am directed to say that ' Bahrain 7th April 1947 for Seer* v Political Resident, Persian Gulf.mmm f ^ X OFFICE OF THE A.G.C.R, NEW DELHI. No. GD 58-21-328. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. &lt; y A Dated the. 3 ^ Due to the promotion Of Lt. M.L©A. Steele, I.M.D., M.O. Bahrain to the rank of Captain with^ffect from 20.^.45, he is authorised to draw the following:- ' 1. Arrears of joining time at Es.l50/-p.m.(Rupees one hundred and fifty only)p.ra. for the period from 20.7.45 to 3.8.45. 2. Arrears of leave salary &lt;xt Ks.5/13/- (Rupees five hanj&amp;yed j -/13/-)p.m. for the period from 4.8.45 to 10.10.45. 3. Arrears of joining time pay at Rs. 150/-p.m.(Rupees one hundred onIy)p.m. from 11.10.45 to 25.10.45. 4. Arrears of pay at Rs. 150/-p o m. (Rupees one hundred and fifty only)p.ra. from 26.10.45 to 30.4.47. He is also authorised to draw the following pay and allowance with effect from 1.5.47:- Pay. at Rs.650/-p.m. Special pay. at Rs.l00/-p.m. -do- at Rs. 30/-p.m. Compensatory allowance, at Rs. 50/-p.m. Dearness allowance. at Rs. 175/-Pom 0 Rs.l005/-p.m. (Rupees onA thousand and five only)p.m. ^rawal of the dearness allowance is subject to the revised orders that may be issued by Government. t |cNO. 2-2&gt;S~' -2/6 • POLITICAL AGENCY ^BAHRAIN, iJune, 1947* To The Accountant General, Central Revenues G.D.Section, New Delhi. Sir I have the honour to forward herewith the Last Pay Certificate of Captain M.L.A.Steele, I.M.D., who took over charge as Residency Surgeon, Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, on the forenoon of the 15th January, 1947 • I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant for Political agent, BahrainA. T. C. 5 {Sec Pava (5) of Annex A to Chap. 2 of Section IV, Audit Code.) LAST-PAY CERTIFICATE. Last pay certificate of CpL- Lr,-»--•). Medical 0 r ficer .in..char. 9 t.or...U.QS^.v. Bahrain proefeding to take over as Residency Surgeon p^«edin^ PSFsl'^'Crair’RSSTO 2. He has been paid up to a«d -f-0*r -14-1—194? at t,ic TO»owing rates Particulars. Substantive Pay mmiftie**. s.p feyheroccCcrni Comp• allcp. ’ D earne s s ’ * al Ice*’ Deductions. Piate. Tis.500/ -p.m* ~ i^s* 100/- M ^ Ps. 30/- ” ^ ks. 50 /- ' */. Us* 175/- ' ^ ^3. He made over charge of the office of /////////V///r///rVVr?\ , 'rV? /, ’ ; // //•///////////////////^yy//// //f/ 4, Recoveries are to be made from the pay of the Government servant as detailed on the reverse. 5. He has been paid leave salary as detailed below. Deductions have been made as noted on the reverse. Period. Pate. Amount. a month. at Rs a month. at Rs a month. From ... to From ... at Rs ... From ... 6- He is entitled to dratf the following :— 7. He is also entitled to joining time for days. 8. The details of the income-tax recovered from him up to the date from the begining of the current year are noted on the reverse. (Signature.) Dated Jti- 19 * 1 / . Vr, x 7^' (Designation) ^ Treasury Officer, J Bahrain*REVERSE. Details of recoveries. Nature of recovery Amount Rs To be recovered in instalments. ^ \ Deductions made from leave salary. From to -Vn account of From to ’ oi\account of. From to on account of Rs Rs Rs. Names of months Pay. Gratuity, Fee. etc. Funds ajid oilier Amount of Income-Tax Deductions. recovered. _ April 19 May 19 June 19 July 19 August 19 . September 19 October 19 November 19 December 19 January 19 February 19 March 19 NAP—7003/S 17—4-4-45—100,000 Remarks. ( nPERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. The 24th July, 1947. A copy of the undermentioned paper-is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain. PahraH ' By order, Ml II •««&lt;*« M 4 I«« LV for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ENCLOSURE Government of India*, Department of External * Aiiaia.s anu Commonwealth Relations, Express ' • J ' °*F.E7(26)-E/46 dated the 9th June, 1947. SWA,Department of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations. From EXPRESS LETTER . Foreign, New Delhi S, To Repgu, Bahrain. . No.F.27(26)-E/46. Dated the Sth June 1947. Subject Extension of the tenure of Military Assistant Surgeon Lieutenant M. L. A. Steele, Indian Medical Department, Quarantine Medical Officer,Bahrain. Reference^cprf'espondence resting with your express letter No.3665-52/8, dated the Sth December 1946. 2. Sanction is accorded to the extension of the tenure of appointment of Lieutenant M.L.A. Steele, Indian Medical ! Department, with effect from the 15th December 1946, and to his compulsory retention in service for a further period of one year or, till such time as he is relieved under the provisions of Dpfence Department letter No.F.28-18/41-HDD, dated the 21st October 1941, or otherwise, for continued employment as Quarantine Medical Officer and Medical Officer Victoria Hospital, Bahrain. While so employed, Lieutenant Steele will continue to get pay and allowances at the usual rates, pending the issue of terms and conditions governing compulsory retention in service of Indian Medical Department (British Cadre) officers. °• Sanction is also accorded, as an ad hoc concession, to the grant to Lieutenant Steele, prior to or after his retirement of leave refused up to a maximum of 6 months provided it is to his credit. This will be subject to revision in the light of the decisions on the terms and conditions for.-compulsory retention in service of J.r.D. / (British Cadre) oilicers beyond the date of superannuation. The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd/- P.N.Krishnaswamy, Under Secretary to the Government of India.3 23-7'J /£ From PKRtflAN GULF RKSIDrlNCY, Captain M*L#A.Steele, Residency Sur^eon^ iiahrain* To The Accountant Geneiai, Central Revenues, x'lsv Jolhi. I have the honour to refer to your memorandum No.GD. 58-P1-5370 dated the 12th April 1946 informing me that leave on average pay for one month and five days will be admissible to me on the 14th June 1946. Will you kindly now inform me how much leave will be admissible to me if I remain on uninterupted duty till the 31st ^aroh 1948. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, (ju^ ^ / C; ^ Captain. ‘ Residency Surgeon, Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. rv ^ t-r v, t ^ A- . AJ -//'^ 3A.T.C. 5. A / A. (See Para (5) of Annex A to Chap. 2 of Section IV, Audit Code.) LAST-PAY CERTIFICATE. Last pay certificate of.... G£L.pt&amp;i.n.. L#X.» A ....ST fifilfi.*....R&amp;sid.£L)Cy x*Mr.. .3 ur.ge.an.,.. .Ba lir.a in, : proceedin|r on to. — .' 2. He has been paid up to. .9,ttd •.Inc 1 lad 1 ng. • 3^.2^1.948 at the following rates Particulars. Substantive Pay - ' ' ' -!^* . V^-Y • stingray IScial^T ^ 5 Exchange Compensation A«*^rton8atory al 1 0’.V a nee Tl Rate. %.550/- 130/- 333/5/- Deductions. .•uear.ness allowance Total Mil. 56/11/- 111 /- '■.1291/- p.ra. ». He made over charge of the office of... Qtfg.:.. Residency .-S-urgeon,,...Bahrain. on the..f .OXe.noon of.. 4th..F.ebr-uar.y. y . 1.948. 4. Recoveries are to be made from the pay of the Government servant as detailed on the reverse. 5. He has been .paid leave salary as detailed below. Deductions have been made as noted on the reverse. Amount. 7. He is also entitled to joining time for days. 8. The details of the income-tax recovered from him up to the date from the beginning of the current year are noted on the reverse. (Signature.) * Dated 6th Larch, 19 AQ.. o Mo.IJgt.Try.13.' _ (Designation.) r. o. i 0 ^ Persia* Gulf Residency, The Political *gent, Bahrain. Bahrain. 01 P 1 f ■ •Ml REVERSE. Details of recoveries. Nature of recovery Amount Ks * To be recovered in instalments. Deductions piade from leave salary. y - to.. ....on account of Rs From on account of Rs, From - rr.r.r.... ..xto.. on account of Rs • Names uf Pay. - X Jratuity, Fee,* etc. • i Funds and other Deductions. Amount of | Income-Tax 1 recovered. Hemai ks. * April 19 . , May 19 . June 19 . July 19 . . • • J- August 19 September 19 . October 19 November 19 . December 19 January 19 February 19 March 19 . 1 ‘ 1—982 (Audit) MFP-(7003/M-780)-10-10.45 -100,000.Telegram From To No„ Dated 10th* 2 . En Clair. Political Agent, Bahrain. A.G.C.R*, New Delhi. % 152 13th March, 194-8. • • • • • 4-3 J. Residency Printed Letter 365-52/1, February Grateful if Captain Steeles salary slip could be sent early POLITICAL AMO.Bahrain, 3rd April, 1948. From Captain M.L.A. Steele, MBE, Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrain. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I should be grateful for information on the following points which have arisen with regard to my continuation in service under His Majesty’s Government after the date on which I was due to retire from Indian Government service. 2. On the 15th Jtme 1946 I completed my full term of service under the Government of India, but was com pulsorily retained at my post until the 31st March, 1948, With effect from 1st April 1948 I become entitled Vide A.G.C.R's No.GD-58-21-1617 dated the 10th November, 1947, and (b) an ad hoc concession of 6 months Military furlough, vide Political Resident's No.321-52/1 dated the 5th February, 1948, to the Government of India, New Delhi. I should be grateful for confirmation. 1 hsve agreed to serve Eis Majesty's Government until the 15th May, 1948, and I presume that from the 1st April, 1948, I will be serving under a new contract drawn up by His Majesty's Government. I should be grateful to be informed in this connection whether previous sanction should be obtained from the Government of India for my em ployment under His Majesty's Government while on leave rend ing retirement. F 4. Under Government of India Rules I would have received free passages and luggage allowance for my wife and myself to Nairobi on completion of my service. I should be grateful for confirmation that these will still be available to my wife and myself at the end of my service under His Maiestv's Government. J to: (a) 3 months and 4 days leave on average pay Your most obedient servant, I have the honour to be, Sir, Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain.No. HZLl The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: 4 The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Politic*! Resident in the Persian Gulf* B«thr*in « •md h*s the honour to forward a copy of the^mder- mentioned document* with the request to let know what replies should be given to Dr. Steele to the points raised by him. Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 7th April,1948. KNCLOGURii;. Cooy of letter No.18/2/B.3/109/4* dated the 3rd April, 1948, from , Captain M.L.A. Steele, M.B.E., Quarantine Medical Officer,C) ^ \ \ ' \ No, -2/6 POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN 3r8th- April, 1948 To The Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain Reference my endorsement No,1121 dated the 7th April 1948. Dr. M.L.A. Steele. 2. In the absence of instructions to the contrary Dr! Steeie has been paid his salary for the month of March 1948 at the rates sanctioned in his last Pay Slip from the Accountant General Central Revenues, New’ Delhi. I should be grateful to know at what rates Dr. Steele should be paid from 1st April 1948. for Political Agent, BahrainNo. B/49 Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. Dated the 24th April, 1948 Captain M.L.A. Steele, M.B.3., Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Sanction has been accorded to your employment as Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, from 1st April 1948 to 15th May, 1948, both dates inclusive, on the following terms:- (a) Rs.1005/- per mensura free of British Income Tax (b) Any State allowance, plus (c) Free Quarters. (Authority: Foreign Office telegram No.31 dated 20th April, 1948). (Sd.) Secretary to H.E. The Political Resident, Persian Gulf.ji \ POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, /-v No.R.32 The 30th Jixy 1943 To The Secretary to His Excellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, M iW 0 R A N D U M Reference your inemorandura No.B/49 dated the 24th April 1948, to Dr, Steele. 2. Kindly convey the necessary sanction for continued uayment tiff Dr, Steele after 15th ?£ay 1948, until he is relieved, $ For Political Agent, Bahrain. ;V ■ NNRPOLITICAL AGENCY The undermentioned paper is forwarded to: The Secretary to His Excellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, iiiay 1948 from Captain M.L.A. Steele, Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. for necessary action For Political Agent, Bahrain. Letter No.3-3/140/48 dated the 3rdv No.3-3/140/48 Bahrain, 3rd May, 1948 From Captain M.L.A. Steele, M.B.E., Quarantine Medical Office Bahrain. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, Reference Residency express letter No.1080 dated # 18th April. I have the honour to request that Government of India be asked to Gazette my leave of Three Months and Four days on average pay, vide A.G.C.R*s No.G.D.58-21-1617 of 10th November 1947 and A.G.C.R. be authorised to issue my leave pay Certificate from 1st April 1948, the leave pay to be paid at Bahrain. 2. With reference to express letter from External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations (No.F-27(26) E/46 of 9th June 1947), application for sanction of the six months leave (AD HOC Concession) has already been made. As my contract with His Majesty’s Government be in the station if and when leave salary be dealt with in expires on 15th May, I will not the sanction arrives, may this the same way. please# I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant,warn mmm &amp; / No. \ 2 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain , and has the honour to forward the undermentioned document vith the remark that the request seems reasonable. Dated the 25th April, 19431 Political Agency, Bahrain. tiN CLOSURE . Copy of Letter No.3-3-/130/48, dated the 22nd April, 1948, from Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain.No. 3-3//3*A ^ * VICTORIA MEMORIAL HOSPITAL, BAHRAIN. Dated the 22nd April, 1948. From Captain M.L.A.Steele M.B.E To The Political Agent, Bahrain Sir I have the honour to place the following before you for consideration. I have always used ray car for Quarantine work and have never drawn any car allowance. Since last February, the Quarantine work has Increased, as I have to visit in addition to the usual B.I.Boats, the Aero Plane L!arrine Base and Moharraq Aerodrome. The former 2-3 times a week and the latter once a week, and to Sitra when required. I therefore request the matter be placed before the Bahrain Government for consideration. The Quarantine Medical Officer Kuwait draws Rs.70/- P.M. and has much less to do than I have. If a taxi was hired for this work, the monthly cost would far exeed Rs.70/- as there would be waiting charges. Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain.Copy EXPRESS LETTER PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAimAIN . From: Prodrome, Bahrain To: Foreign, New Delhi. No. 1080-52/1 ' Dated 18th April, 1948 Reference my No.321-52/1 dated February 5th. 2. I should be grateful for a reply to paragraphs 2 and 3. 3. It is proposed to employ Steele temporarily after 1st April 1948. I presume there is no objection to his accepting such employment during the period of his leave and/ or furlough. 4. On termination of his employment Steele wishes to proceed direct to Nairobi as his elected place of retirement. I presume he will be entitled to free conveyance there for himself and his family since his services were compulsorily retained. =PR0DR0ME= The issue of the above has been authorised. (Sd.) Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copy to Dr. Steele, Political Agency, Bahrain, for information.■■■Ml No. 1008-2i/S. \H [18 5 ? The Secrefc c ary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf 9 presents his compliments to 1. His Majesty's Vice-Consul, JBushire. 2* The Agency Surgeon, Bahrain. 3. The Agency Surgeon, Kuwait. 4. The Agency Surgeon r Muscat* and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^ with the request that one copy be completed and returned to this office. PSHSIAN GULF RSSIDBHCY, BAliRAIN. Dated.. 9th April, 1948. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Name and Pate. Subject. I.A.F. form I-1122-B in duplicate. CsA^ KINDIAN MEDICAL DEPARTMENT. Additions to Record of Service Year 19 If Branch. 1% A I. A. F. Lim-B, \ Assistant Surgeon SufryAasistant Surg-eon- Departmental No. (Sub-Assistant Surgeons only) ^-Rank —— N ame _ a utfA + cfJ Promoted to ^ , y/Je Gazette of India Notification No. ^&gt;0 of 19^ ^ • II.—Nature of employment during the year. Indian Government. Imperial Government (out of India). Mrtrfrary or Civil. From ' To Nature of employment. From To /- /4-/ (,7 &gt;Asi &gt; O * t ’C • y .p* Civil (Department or Province to be stated) A 1 Lrar- ^ \ * 6 XJX,—Departmental and language examinations passed and medical qualifications obtained during the year. Subject of examination. Degree of proficiency obtained or qualified for promotion. Where. On what date ^uote authority. fV i L IV.—War services during year. Medals and clasp received during year Campaign. Battle, siege or action. Date Appointment held on the occasion. Name or officer in chief command it wounded, state nature of wound. / L- s- -varr TK NIL Instances in which the ss^is^ai^ 0 Surgeon ^ as ^* s ^ n 8 u i 9 ^ ec l himself by gallant or skilful conduct; or of special duties on which he may have been employed ; when where and on what occasion, and whether noticed or thanked in orders, or otherwise. (Attach copy of letter received).When. Where. To whom. &lt; Wife living at date of return. # Yea •Urn (Delete word inapplicable.) VII.—If there are any legitimate children during the past year, specify- N ame Date of birth. Where Baptised. /V lu ——, VIII.—Names and addresses of next of-kin. ( a) &lt;2j? ■ j'* T t £ £ /fl y-V. ^ J /■&gt; /C ^ r ,o ^ ^7.i/!rr rt) a (c) IX.—Statement of all furlough and leave taken during the year. Nature of leave, whether privilege, on full pay on Medical certificate or private affairs, and under what furlough rulerf. Authority quoting the number and date of order. Period actually taken. In cases of leave out of India give precise date of embarkation and of disembarkation in India on return. From To Months. Days. i ' • l true Station hereby declare that to the best of my knowledge and belief this statement is correct and Dated 1st January 19 £ i^t -• . Assistant Surgeon. / ^ 0 Signature of —^—:—. ~- Sub-Assistant Sitrgetm. INSTRUCTIONS. On the 1st of January annually every medical subordinate will complete the form, retain a copy for his own use and submit the form to the officer under whom he is serving. The latter will forward the form, to the A. D. M. S. a^g^e^A^ea un( ^ er whom he is serving for transmission through the prescribed channel, to the D, M. S., India, who will forward it to ths D. G., I. M. S, When possible, these documents should be forwarded to Army Headquarters collectively bv the respective military areas concerned N. P.—G. 37—10,000—*9-4-41.No. B/49 Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. Dated the 24th April, 1948 To Captain M.L.A. Steele, Bahrain . MEMORANDUM Sanction has been accorded to your employment as Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, from 1st April, 1948 to 15th May, 1948, both dates inclusive, on the following terms (a) Rs. 1005/- P© 1, mensem free of British Income Tax, p_lus (b) Any State allowance, plus (c) Free quarters. (Authority: Foreign Office telegram No. 31 dated 20th April, 1948). of the subordinate medical staff for one year with effect from 1st April, 1948, on existing rates of pay subject to one month's notice. (Authority: Foreign Office telegram No. 31 dated 20th April, 1948). Sd. A.L.A. Dredge Secretary to H.E. The Political Resident, Persian Gulf Wo. B/50 Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. Dated the 24th April, 1948 Copy forwarded, with edmpliments, to The Political Agent, Bahrain . 2. Sanction has also been accorded to the retentionNo. /7S9- Va cated 8th June, 1948. Captain M.L.A, Steele, M.B.E., Is proceeding on leave pending retirement. He may please be given such assistance as he may properly require from the Representatives of His Britannic Majesty*s Government and other kindred authorities. Captain Steele served in this Agency for seven years. K.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain*No./- l//'? D VICTQRLl miORriL HOSPITAL, BAHRAIN. Bated the 7th Jiane, 1S4S. From Captain ''.L.A.Steele T'.B.B. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to report tliat I have handed over the duties of Quarantine Medical Officer, and Medical Officer Victoria Memorial Hospital ■with effect from the forenoon of the 7th, June. I am leaving for Nairobi by Air on the morning of the Oth Instant. Sir I have the honour to be. Sir, Your Obediant Servant, Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. Address: C/o BARCLAY S BANK, NAIROBI,F4 ( w 'b To Bahrain 9 7th June 1948* The Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain* c\ Sir, I shall be very grateful if my pay and other dues for the period that I am on leave could kindly be drawn and credited to my account in the Eastern Bank Ltd. Bahrain* I have given them instructions* My address in afrlca will be* c/o Barclays Bank Ltd., D *C*0 * , Nairobi, East Africa* I RESIDENCY vllZZPT I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, Copy to the Political Agent Bahrain* P.S. I enclose herewith twelve signed payblll blank forms which may kindly be carefully kept and used when my leave salary etc* is drawn and credited to the Eastern Bank*&gt; 'JHHI'!'%J J ffg 1 —— t^&gt; No.B/204 (4/157) The Political Agent, BAHRAIN MEMORANDUM 0 (f PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN the 29th June 1948 ^calag^ 3 - JUL 1943 ( fZ~n' Sahrau 1 - / r \jJ\ Reference your Memorandum No.R.82 dated the 30th May 1948. 2. The Foreign Office have sanctioned payment to Dr. Steele up to the 6th June 1948. Please take action accordingly. Secretary, to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf.no.acfe - 2 / 6 . Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 7th July, 1948. To The Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, I shall be grateful if you will kindly transfer a sum of Ks. 1206/- ( Rupees one thousand two hundred and six only) from the Bahrain Agency-Foreign Office Account to the Account of Captain M.L.A.Steele under intimation to this office. Yours faithfully, Bahrain. Copy forwarded for information to Capt.M.L.A.Steele C/o Barclays Bank Ltd., D.C.O.Nairobi, East Africa. The amount represents his pay from ^st May to 6th June 1948 as sanctioned by Foreign Office, London, vide memo. No.B/204(4/157) dated 29/6/48 from the Residency,Bahrain, copy enclosed.Captain M.L.A*Steele, C/o Barclays Bank Ltd,, D#C,0*Nairobi, East Africa. Memoi^ndTjm / £-6/ The Accountant General Cez^tf-al Revenues, dew Delhi, in his letter No.SD 58-21/683 dated •ne 1st July 1943, vide copy enclosed, has asked to be furnished with a copy of you^ charge report. Will you please sign the attach ed 4 copies of your charge report and return them to me by air mail. fOiy Political Agent, Bahrain 'MSNo.-SW -2/6. Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 26th July,1948. To Captain M.L.A.Steele, C/o Barclays Bank Ltd. , D.C.O.Nairobi, East Africa. Ivlemorandum . The Accountant General Central Revenues, New Delhi, in his letter No.GD 58-21/683 dated the 1st July 1948, vide copy enclosed, has asked to be furnished with a copy of your charge report. Will you please sign the attach ed 4 copies of your charge report and return them to me by air mail. for Political Agent, Bahrain., MS.v-K, iff Copy of le ter No.GD 58-21/683 dated the 14th July 1948 from the Accountant General Central Revenues, New Delhi, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, and the Director General of Health Services, New Delhi. ' I have the honour to invite a reference to the Ministry of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations Notification No. 189-E.II dated 7-6-48 sanctioning leave preparatory to retire ment for 3 months and 4 days from 1-4-48 to Captain M.L.A. Steele formerly Quarantine Medical Officer and Agency Surgeon Bahrain and to request you to furnish ” (i) the charge report of the officer. (ii) Place payment of leave salary. (iii) present address.No.4734-2/6. Political Agency,' Bahrain. Doited the 23rd Sept. 1948, To The A^oountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. Sir, With reference to your letter No.GD 68- 21/683 dated the 14th July 1948, I have the honour to forward herewith charge report of Dr. Steele In quadruplicate. Ke wishes to draw his leave salary from the Agency Bahrain. His present addrdss is:- C/o A.B.Gili P.0. Bon 1010 Nairobi. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant,% r No. -2/e. To tr Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 2Cth Se&gt;'tlumber,48. The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. Sir, With reference to your telegram No.GD58- 68/991 dated the 24th September, 1948, I have the honour tc forward herei/ith the bast Pay Certificate of Capt. M.L.A.Steele. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant,A. T. €. 5 {See Para (5) of Annex A to Chap. 2 of Section IV, Audit Code.) LAST-PAY CERTIFICATE. V Last pay certificate...9.1.9.5....It.G a - Medical Cfficer in charge Victoria Me morial Hospital, . of tl,e &amp; Bahrain proceeding on .f.O?.• Mfc-y-and-• • 181*• to 2. He has been paid up to./fc?Mvk&amp;W?.. f?/ .at the;following rates :— Particulars, Pate. . ioo^I r ’it r ''*) ' so/- ” ) ory allowance*.... ' 50/- ) jompensav _ _ _ Dearness •••allowaiwe-# •••••••••• ' 175/- 1065/- ' MxbieiiM&amp;sx. 1*Paid for the month of May 19-18 as above.... Hs. ffotii''Ist 'to‘'6fh‘'3*irhe 1948 ” .... ' V ^ ) 1005/- 201 /'- 11667 - 3. He made over charge of the office of.tb.0..U.fedical*--Oi*f-icer-&gt;-V-.}vw-IiOSv&gt;i-twi- 3.ahmin on the.f.o.r.a..noon of...7th...Jujaa...l248» 4. Recoveries are to be made from the pay of the Government servant as detailed on the reverse. 5. He has been paid leave salary as detailed below. Duducticns have been made as noted on the reverse. Period. - Pate, Amount* From f .....a month. • From From 6. He is entitled to draw the following :— /“r. He is also entitled to joining time for .days. 8. The details of the ineome-tax recovered from him up to the date from the begining of the current year are noted on the reverse. (Signature.) Poli^^al Agort, Dated 26th Sept. 1&amp;£. . lc A Bahrain. (Designation.)REVERSE Details of recoveries. Nature of recovery Amount Rs To be recovered tn instalments. Deductions made from leave salary. From ...on account of. Rs Rs From ....on account of Rs Names of months. Pay. Gratuity, etc. Foe. Funds and other Deductions. Amount of Income-Tax recovered. Bernards. A Z April 19 * 1 May 19 ' ' June 19 July 19 • August 19 . September 19 . • October 19 • . November 19 December 19 anuary 19 ' v February 19 March 19 ! NAP.—7003/S 17—4-4-45-100,000OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL CENTRAL REVENUES NEW DELHI From The Accountant General, Central Revenues, To Copy of Telegram No GD 58-21-991 dated 24th Sept 48 from the A.G.C.R., New Delhi to the Prodrome Bahrain Furnish Last Pay Certificate Captain M.L.A. Steele urgently. By Air Mail \ No: GD 58-21/1230 27 Sept 1948. Copy by post to the. Political Resident Persian Gulf Bahrain in confirmation and necessary action. The L.P.C- of Capt. Steele may be sent by return air mail. (Sd). Asstt. Accountant General., Central Revenues.H.E. Col. A.C. Galloway, CIE., QBE., Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Major A.L.A. Dredge, MBE., Secretary to' H.E. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Mr. A,J. Johnson, MBE., Administrative Officer. Col. W.J. Moody, Residency Surgeon. Mr. C.G. Horner, Asst. Resident Engineer. Mr. E. Thomas, Assistant Secretary. Staff. Mr. Farrell. Mr. A. Braganza. Mr. Smith. Mr. MacPherson. Mr. Mani. Mr. Oldham. Mr. Bainbridge. Mr. Domingo, Mr. Christdas. Mr. Shafiuddin. \ Reference Ministry of Works letter and form below. Will you please state whether you will require any minor alterations painting etc., to the building occupied by you during the year 1st April, 1949 to 31st March, 1950? Secretary toastie Political Resident in ''the Persian Gulf. Copy to 1 ) 2 ) 2 ) The political ^gent, The political Agent, The Political Agent, Bahrain, Kuwait, Muscat, for early completion and return please.Telegraphs 'Travaux, Wire, London n Telephone: Reliance 7611 Ministry of Works, Lambeth Bridge House, Albert Embankment, LONDON - SE.l July, 1948. Sir, ESTIMATES FOR THE YEAR ENDING 31st MARCH 1950 I am directed by the Ministry of Works to ask that you will be good enough to furnish particulars of any services for which, in your opinion, provision should be made in the Estimates of this Department for the financial year beginning 1st April next. Particulars should be stated on the enclosed forms and a full explanation should be given as to the necessity for any special requirements. * 2. It will not be possible, except in cases,of urgency, to carry out any services for which provision is not made in the Estimates. It is essential therefore that the forms should contain a complete forecast of your requirements for the year. 3. Where furniture requirements can be met locally, the estimated cost of local purchase should be indicated. 4. The completed forms should be returned not later than 31st august next to Senior Architect, Ministry of Works, British Embassy, CAIRO. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, Sd/- P.AUEIOL BARKER 8022 (TRUE COPY)Telegraphic Address : Accounts. All commuuioatious should be addressed to the Acoonntant General, Central Revenues. CENTRAL R] NEW No. From OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL, 4 - MV I948p at/oe-21-14.16 dated tl § The ACCOUNTANT GENERAL, CENTRAL REVENUES, To Ihe S^crttury to the, Govt, of Indta, Mijalstry of External Affairs and Commonwealth FialatimiSi !Tev' Delhi. Enclosure. Sub*» Captain Steels Rajloyucnt during leave pending retirement. Sir | ^ I have the iicnoui* to irvits a refer^n^e to your letter No*64-1-48 I^D(F) data.. 4.9.48 on the above subject *»id to request you to state the emoluments that will h° awn by Caawain Steele for the period! of Ms osrnloyment from 1.4.4IS to 8.5.48 during his leave pending retirement. Attention is invited in this connection to S^.S. decision No. (8) below F.R, 69which restricts the amounts of Ij leave salary to the aiiount of pons ion. It however, appears from the L.?.C. furnished by tho Political Agent, Bahrein that Captain Sts ale drew pay and allowances at full rates hr was in rweblpt of while on duty, t!J.s office has no concern with t'na duty pay that ulll be ^iven to him by the Crc , .' , n la r*spent of the period of his re-eianlo^irment, the amounts uaia to Caotain st^cie* by the Political Agent Bahrein from 1.4.48 to 6.5.48 will be sot off against the lea^* salary due for this period. As the rate of pension to which the leave salary Is restricted in such cases will no doubt bs less than what he has drawn^ I would, request that steos -aay be taken to reiularlse the amount overdrawn by Captain Gteele during the period of his r e-^an! oyment. Yours f aithfully, u a &amp;oc^ \94S Ass- &lt;^L Accounts Officer# No.GD/56-21-1437 dt. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrein, Persian Gulf for information. Attention is however, invited to this office endt. No.GD/58-21-4482 dated 31-3-48. Please state the circumstances in which compensatory allowances were paid to Captain Steele during leave preparatory to retirement. Besides, it is pointed out that the rate of dearness allowance authorised in this office endt. No.GD/58-2174482 dated 31.3.48 was at Ks. 100/- p.m. and not at Ite.l75/-yas paid. . Please state /he reasons for this excess payv&gt;^^v^ $• \(&gt; Asst. Accounts Officertw No. j7/» -2/6. Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 14th November, 1948. The Accountant General, Contra! Revenues, New Delhi. / /•{ ' 'iv With reference to your Endorsement No.GD/56-21- 1437 dated the 2 th October 1948, I have the honour to state that Dr.Steele, viedical Officer, Bahrain, was paid his pay and allowances upto the 31st March 1948 at the following rates Pay.•••••••••• .Rs. 650/- Specie 1 pay. ' l n 0/- »* w *» 30/- Compensatory allowanc. M 50/- Dearness allowance.100/- 93^/- p.m. S' Thereafter he was paid at the rate of Rs. 1005 /- p.m. as fixed by Foreign Office,London, vide memoranda Nos.B/49 and B/204/4/167 dated 24th April and 29th June 1948 respectively received from the Residency,Bahrain-Copies enclosed herev/ith. 2. As will be /Seen*from Foreign,Kew Delhi, ivill be N T o.F.$?7(2&lt; Express Letter No.F.£7(26)-E/4f dated the 9th June 1947 ( copy enclosed herewith) the tenure of appointment of Dr.Steele was extended till such time as his services were required in Bahrain as Quarantine Medical Officer. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 9) foi/Political Agent, Bahrain.,1 0 PtirtSlAJI GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 15th November, 1948. Y\ {K (113/34/48) Dear Agency, / VT\C, &gt;L A3.0 r' —— ' 2 0 s^UV 1948,1 ^AHRAlb 1 - M , 4 — We enclose, in original, Dr. Steeled travelling claim. 2 . We should be glad if you would pay this, less any advance you may have made to him. 3 . The amount should be charged in your Foreign Office Account as an advance on behalf of Government of India. Yours ever, RESIDENCY. HR (1 enclosure)!»0./'A/ -2/6 Politi al Agency f Bahrain. Dated the 24th November f 1948. To The iianager* iiastern Bank Limited, Bahrain Dear Sir, I shall be grateful if you will kindly credit a sum of Bs*2002/- ( Rupees two thousand and two only) to the private account of Dr.M.L.A.Steele by debit to this Agency Foreign Office Account under intimation to this office. Copy forwarded to Capt. M.L.A.Steele C/o Barclays Yours faithful y olitical Agent, Bahrain Bank Ltd., D.C.O.Nairobi, East Africa, for information. The amount represents his T.A.Bill.16th December, 1948 SIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN, CY, (JfT) (113/47/48) l Dear Agency, We have heard from Captain Steele at Nairobi that in his Last Pay Certificate which you have forwarded to the Accountant General Central Revenues, you have shown him as having been paid up to 6th June, 1948. This date would appear to be incorrect so far as the Government of India is concerned as Captain Steele proceeded on leave under that Government with effect from the 1st April, 1948 - (fore-noon). Would you please verify the above by a reference to the office copy of the Last pay Certif cate and if necessary forward a revised certiiicate to the Accountant General Central Revenues under intimation to this office and to Captain Steele. His address is P.CLB. 1010, Nairobi. Yours ever, RESIDENCY The Political Agency, — Bahrain.Political Agency, Bahrain# No.^^-2/6 Dated 27th November,1948 To Capt# M.L.A.Steele, C/0 Barclays Bank Limited, KertS# .. NAIROBI. (East ilfrica) NAIROBI MEMORANDUU Please refer to your letter dated the 7th October,48 regarding your Last Pay Certi r icate. and thereafter has already been taken up with the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, vide the copy of my letter No.5118-2/6 dated 14.11.1948, enclosed herewith for your information. In view of this a ^resh Last Pay Certificate is not necessary unless asked for by the Accountant General, Central Revenues. 2 The question of your pay etc. drawn on 31.3.48 RVR/- litical Agent, BahrainNo .R-6 -2/6 Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 5th January, 1S4S. /H i Dear Residency, Pleas* refer to your letter No.(113/47/48) dated the 16th December, 1 a 48, regarding Last Pay Certificate of Captain i.L.A.Steele. 2. »Ve have already furnished to the Accountant General Central Revenues, New Delhi the information about pay etc. drawn by Captain Steele upto 31/3/48 and thereafter, vide my letter No.5118-2/6 dated the l^th 1 ill November, 1948, copy enclosed herewith, and in view of this we do not consider a fresh L.P.C. is necessary unless asked for by the A.G.C.R. 3. We have also informed Cant. Steele. Yours ever Agency To The Persian Gulf Resid Bahrain.Political Agency, B&amp;hrair• kd. /i'?-?/?. Dat^d th* 18th January,1949, To Sir, The Accountant General, Central Revenues, Mew Delhi. v'H /- S ' 7 ° fn continuation of my letters Nos. &lt;752-9/6 and 511^-2/6 dated the 26th September and 14th November,1948 respectively, I have the honour to forward herewith a revised Last Pay Certificate of Captain M»L.A*Steele showing him as having been oaid upto 31st March 1948, while serving under the Government of India. I shi.ll be i grateful if you will kindly let me know by cable if any decision for payment of his leave salary and pension fcas been received fro a the Government of India so far as he is in urgent need of money, and it is now well over 7 months since the officer left Bahrain. I have the honour to be, Bir, your most obedient servant, ^ fo^/PcliticalU Agent, B* Bahrain. Copy forwarded to Captain M.L.A.Steele C/o Barclays Bank Ltd., D.C.O.Uairnbi, East Africa, for information. -&gt; M7Political A.’j^ncy, B&amp;hriiin. P«t*d th« 19th January,1949 D«ar R« 3 id®j!cy, V7»» hav« so ?*r not rac^iv^d -ny ir\for:aation nlthvr frora th# Gov«rnai#?nt Indik or th» Accountant Gtnar^l,Ctntral nav«inu^s^ Haw Balhi *bout th#* l*a\ y a rant in* Mtd3cl*l , Bahrain, who *.v«s on l®av« pandin^ retirement after 31st '.•larch 194?• Captain 3te«le Is in urgent need of money and has asked us to ap;r^ach the Indian authorities with a visw to got an early settlement of Ms cast* Would you therefore kindly ask the Government of India telegraphically to expedite th* matter. We have written to than separately but a c*hle might help* Cooy forwarded to Cap\ain M*L*A*Gteele C/o Barclays Bank Ltd., D.C.O.Nairobi, Sast Africa, for Information. *ul*ry and pension of Captain M.L.A.Steele, lately Yours ever The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL, CENTRAL REVENUES, NEW DELHI. No. dated the GD-58-21-2333 , QdG From , * 0 ^ 1949 * 1 .- ' • The ACCOUNTANT GENERAL, CENT HAL RE YEN UES, The Secretary to the Govt, of Indi. Ministry of F..A. &lt;4 J.R.j New Delhi. Sub:- Cant&amp;in W.L.A. Steele Fraployraent during leave pending retireraent. Sir, I hive to invite a re£^rence to this office letter No.GD-5^21-1436 iated 28.10.48 and to request the favour of an'*early renly. a - A cony of Political igent, Bahrein letter No.5118-2/6 dated 14.11.48 is enclosed for/your information. 5 / (A.K. Ghatak) Asst. counts Officer.by AIR No. GD-58-21-2334 »' 3 S * Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrein, Persian^ulf with reference to his No # 51l8-2/6 dt* 14.11.48. As captain Steele was reeepliyed w.e.f. 1.4.48 by the Foreign office, London his pay and allowances during the period of his reemployment from 1.4.48 to 6.6.48 are the liability of His Majesty^ Govt., ca 1 Agent, Bahrain of the Pol.iticel Resident. ./ith reference to your letter British Residency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 26th January, 1949p'rom Prodrome, Bahrain, to Foreign, hew Delhi. Sir R. Hay. No: 2 Saving. 26th January, 1949* Captain M.L.A. Steele late Indian 1.edieal Department employed as uarantine Medical Officer RaclueauLii Bahrain, proceeded on leave pending retirement on 1st April, 1948. States not yet in receipt of leav^ salary and pension. Grateful if payment could be expedited as officer now in urgent need of money.With the compliments of the Political Resident./ (2/65/48) PFSSI/N GTJI.F RFSTCFNCT, M£Eil£. 23rd April, 1948. Pleas* refer to the statement of account enclosed with your note of 20th April, 1949. The receipt is enclosed herewith. ') iVould ycm be kind enough to arrange future payments until further notice as under i- (1) Fs.200/- per mensem on account of Quarantine expenditure to H.B.M’s Political Agents account with the Krstern Bank, Bahrain ; (11) Fs.150/- per mensem Quarantine ?^edical Officer^ allowance plus Ps.70/- per mensem car allowance to Major J.D. Grant*s account with the Eastern Bank, Bahrain. .h*B« Snow, State Medical Officer Government of Bahra BAi-RAi;; .| Sd/- W.J. MOODYI (COPY) GOVERITENT OF BAHRAIN Medical Department . Bahrain, Persian Gulf The Manager, The Pastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain. 26th April, 1949. Dear Sir Please kindly carry out the following standing monthly orders 1. Bs.200/- to be credited to H.B.M’s Political Agent’s account, the first payment being due 1st Sh.aban 1368 = 29th May 1949. 2. Bs.150/- and Bs.70/- to be credited to Major J.D.Grant’s account, the first uayment also being due }st Shaban 1368 = 29th May, 1949. month, and debit the above three sums regularly to the Public Health Account. Please make all payments on the 1st of each Arabic Yours truly, Sd/- B.H. SNOW State Medical Officer, Bahrain.■■■■ 1 7 V Telegram From To Enclalr. political Residency, Bahrain. To Foreign Office, London. Telegram No. 381. Following for Personnel Department. Ma^or J.D. Grant, Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain (your file P.F.8751) has applied for two months' leave in the United Kingdom and proposes to leave on 27 August. I presume there is no objection.s GULi* iiEblDiJ^CY, BAHiGilN. (77/97/49) 19 th August, 1949. Your letter No. 111/49 of the 30th July applying for leave. I am afraid this matter has been held up as a result of the non-availa bility of the medical files. Sanction for leave must be given by the Foreign Office and your application has now been referred by telegram. I do not imagine that there will be any objection. Incidentally, although I may be mistaken, I should have thought your application should have been sent through the Political Agent. / v 1 Major J.D. Grant, Quarantine Medical Oliicer, BAHhAlN.(2/97/49.) Kl PERSAIN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. feted 30th August 1949. Subjects- quarantine bdlcal Off 1 corOloy/aace*, References- i^ajor Grant ( ^arantine l^edlcal Officer letter Nos 110/49 of 3Iet July 1949. With effect from 1st August 1949 the monthly allowance of Re 150/- hitherto paid direct to the Quarantine Medical Officer may please be sent to the Political Agent, Bahrain. The travelling allowance of Re 70/-P.M. should continue to be paid as before direct to the Quarantine *4dical Officer. ( W.J. Moody) Medical Adviser to Political Resident. The State Ledical Officer, Government Hospital, Bahrain. »i tii^i i Persain Gulf A ^esidency, f?2 According to the terms of i-ajor Grant's contract ( Para 6 of F.O. (PF 8751) dated 18 Iv^ay I94§&gt; Gee attached extract) the quarantine allowance of Rs 150/ per month paid by the Government of Bahrain will . be credited to His Lkjesty's Government with effect ^ from 20th July 1949* This allowance is paid monthly and the State f.hdical Officer who makes the payment has been requested to pay Bs ISO/- monthly to the Political Agent,Bahrain, with effect from 1st August 1949* Political Agency, Bahrain# ( Y/.J.MOODY) Medical Adviser#4 EXTRACT OF FOREIGN OFFICE. LONDON.No (PF875I) Dated I8th May 1949, Para ( S) . Para 6. Should opportunities arise for you to engage in private practice, 30°2? of the fees derived therefrom after I9th July, 1949. would accrue to His l&amp;jesty's Governaant • The allowance Paid to you by the State of Bahrain for your quarantine services will also accrue to His Tajesty’s Government.i y\^ ^'Vl Office of the A.G.C.R.,New No:GD 58-21-1056 /^N 0, &amp; Delhi To 'V The Political Agent, Bahrain, Persion Guljfl* Subs Issue of leave salary slip in favour of Cap t • M«1 • A • ot eele • Refs Your No 157-2/6 dt.l8.1*49. It will be appreciated if a set of 3 speci; men signature of Capt.Steele is forwarded to this office for onward transmission to - the Treasurer Nairobi alongwith the leave salary certificate of the officer* ita^' S£P 1349 istant Accountant General, Central Revenues. rw&lt;&amp; Political Agency, No.157-2/6 of January 18th, to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, a copy of which was forwarded to you, I enclose herewith a copy of letter No.GD 58-21-1056 of August 1st, received from the Accountnat General Central Revenues, and suggest that you should forward three specimens of your signature to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, direct. Yours faithfully, H.G.J&amp;kins Political Agent. Capt. M.L.A. Steele, c/o Barclays Bank Ltd., D.C.O. Nairobi, East Africa.•r v i ,te ! ( 2/102/49) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN • Dated 9th September 1949* i^ear Agency jL ■MBIiVi..,, , Please refer to my 13/49/49 of 30th August regarding the payment of‘ the Quarantine Nodical Officer’s allowance. I am informed by the State medical Officer that the allowance of Rs 150/- per month for July and August had already been paid to Ilsgor Grant’s account. The sum of Rs 203-4-0* i.e. Rs 53-4. for July and Rs 150/- for.August should therefore be recovered from Major Grant and credited to His Majesty’s Government. Yours Sincerely, ( W. J • Moody)(2/112/49) PERSIAN GULF RSSIOSNCY? BAHRAIN. 1949. Following a telegram from the Foreign Office stating that Grant's return from leave was being postponed on account of ill health. I have received a personal telegram from him that he hones to be back within three weeks. &lt;r ( W. J./^oody) J. A. Gethin, Esq., Political Agent, Bahrain. V' i/i, //Political Agency, Bahrain, December 26, 1949. The Accountant General, Central Revenues, Government of India, New Delhi. Memorandum V/ith reference to your memo randum No.GD.58-21-1056 of the 4th August 1949, I enclose herewith three specimens of the signature of Major M.L.A.Steele, M.B.I2. I may draw your attention here that Capt.Steele was promoted to the rank of 'Major' on 16th May 1946 (vide Gazette of India Nofification 2037-B dated the 9th August 1947) so that this fact may be taken into consideration while preparing the Leave Salary Certi ficate of the Officer. for Political Agent. - *■'V NNRVICTORIAMEMORIAL HOSPITAL BAHRAIN. 9 Dated 5th January, 1950. ' ( The H.B.l/Ps Political Sgent, Bahrain. Subject : Air passage to U«K. According to the terms of ny contract, I am entitled to a free reuna passage to the United Kingdom on completion of 18 months service. As this period expires this month, I am sending you an invioce in respect of this passage and $2Foreign Office, S.W.l (PF8751) 18th May, 1949 Sir I am directed by Mr.Secretary Bevin to offer you an extension to 19th July, 1951, of your appointment as Quarantine Medical Officer at Bahrein. 2. The appointment, which would be subject to continued satisfactory service and conduct, would be terminable at one month*s notice on either side. It would be on a temporary basis and would not entitle you to any claim for salary or pension when your services terminated. 3. The appointment would carry a taxable salary of £700. a year and a non-taxable foreign allowance of £900. a year, with free furnished quarters. The foreign allowance would-be subject to review having regard to changes in the cost of liging and/or the rate of exchange in accordance with the procedure laid down in the Foreign Office Circulars on the variability of foreign allowances copies of which may be seen at your post 5 the foreign allowance is also subject to adjustment in the light of information supplied in quarterly life certificates. You would also receive a conveyance allowance the amount of which would be determined from time to time. 4. You would be entitled to free passages to the United Kingdom for yourself, your wife and any members of your family resident with you at the post on the termination of your appointment and to one free passage to the United Kingdom, and back for yourself, your wife and resident members o^ your family, on leave after the completion of 18 months service from the beginning of your original appointment. 5. You would be entitled to leave at the rate of 60 days per annum including travelling time. The rate of foreign allowance payable during leave whether taken during, or at the end of the period of appointment would be determined in the light of Foreign Service Regulation Chapter II Regulations. -^ 6 . Should opportunities arise for you to engage in private practice, 30$ of the fees derived therefrom after 19th July,1949 would accrue to His Maiesty*s Government. The allowance paid to you by the State of Bahrein for your quarantine services will also accrue to His Majesty*s Government. 7 . I am to request you to notify this Department whether you are prepared to accept the extension of your appointment on these terms. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant Sd/xx xx Dr. J.D. Grant (TRUE COPY)No. 3 -2/6 Political Agency, Bahrain, 12th January,1950 According to the terms of his contract No.(PF8751) of 18th May, 1949 (Copy enclosed for ready reference) the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, is entitled to a free return passage to the United Kingdom on completion of 18 months service. Dr.Grant will complete 18 months on 24th January 1950 and we presume his return passage for leave from which he returned in November last may be paid to him after that date. 2. An early reply will be appreciated. Yours ever, Bahrain Agency.’ The Finance Department, Foreign Office, London S.W.lNo. -2/6 © Political Agency, Bahrain, 9th January, 1949 Dear Sir, With reference to your bill dated the 9th June, 1949 for Ks.400/- on the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, in respect of Yellow Fever Vaccine supplied on 19th May, 1949, I enclose herewith a . cheque for amount in full settleme 2. Will you please return to me your bill and the enclosed voucher in duplicate, all duly receipted? for Political Agent, Bahrain State Medical Officer, Bahrain Government Hospital, Bahrain.—URGENT Political Agency, Bahrain, 9th January, 1950 No. tO 11 -2/6 Dear Sir, ^— Please let me have a sterling draft for £144-12-7d. 'favouring Messrs.Burroughs Welcome &amp; Co., London. The cost of the draft should be debited to this Agency^ Foreign Office Account with you. 2. Please advise me the rupee equivalent of the above draft debited by you. Yours faithfully for Political Ageht, Bahrain The Manager, The Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain.No. i* 0 -2/6 Political Agency, Bahrain, 12th January,1950 Dear Sirs With reference to your invoic Nos.FC 3577, FC 5271 and FC 5634 date^ 8 th June, 18th October and 28th November 1949 for £95-18-Od, £23-5-0d, and £25-9-7d respectively, on the Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain, for Yellow Fever Vaccine supplied, I' enclose herewith a bank draft No.L/ta 89756 dated 11th January, 1950 in your favour for £144-12-7d in full settle- enclosed receipt in duplicate duly signed at your earliest convenience? ment 2 Will you please return to me the Yours fai for Political Agent,Bahrain Messrs.Burroughs Wellcome &amp; Co., 183-193, Buston Road, London N.W.lPolitical Agency, No./^V - 2 / 6 . Bahrain, 12th January,1960 Memorandum: $. 1 ^ With reference to your memorandum No./80/49 of llth December, 1949, I have to inform you that the bill of the Government Hospital, Bahrain for ^s.400/- as well as the three invoices of Messrs.Burroughs Wellcome Sc Co., London for an aggregate sum of £144-12-7d. enclosed with your letter have now been paid. for Political Agent The Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain.VICTORIA MEMORIAL HOSPITAL, BAHRAIN. Dated 8th January, 1950. The H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject: Vaccination Fee. I have a bill of Rs. 1863/- outstanding since last January, agaimst Haji Mohammed Tahir Al Sharif for the Vaccinating and issuing of certificates to coolies employed by him in connection with the discharge of ships' cargoes at Has Tannora, Mishaab and Qatar. ,,, J . . T Despite several reminders, Haji has not yet settled this account. I understand that his reason for not doing so is that he considers that this work should have been catered for under the mass vaccination drive carried out by the Bahrain Government at that time and in which this hospital Co operated. In this drive, people were vaccinated free of charge but certiflca es wp»yv 3! nnt. t ssued- this case as most of it was done outside office hours and as rry clerk says *they came to me in the dead of night*. I may add that similar work was done for Gray Mackenzie s and in their case the bill was duly settled. n , , I am sorry to trouble you in this matter but I would be grateful your advice as to how I should proceed further. that this work should be done/to charge a fee of Rs. _3/- per cooly. This is the usual rate for work of this kind and I do not think it is excessive in E.M. 1 / V ft 6 ^ ft N. r&gt; Sno. /y/-y&lt; To Political Agency, Bahrein, 14th January. 1950. The Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. Memorandum. s./33 Your memorandum No.11/60 of 8th January on the subject of vaccination fee due from Hajl Mohammed Tahir A1 Sharif. 2. I have seen Mohammed All, son of Mohammed Tahir A1 Sharif, in connection with this natter. He denies his father*s liability and says that Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., are liable for the charges claimed by you. 3. From what Mohammed All said, it would ap pear that there is some question as to who is liable and it is suggested that the bills be now presented to Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd. Political Agent. I GThank you for your letter N. 177-2/6 of 14th instant. I am glad to inform you that the matter has S now been sttled. \ With many thanks for your help.ORIGINAL IN FILE 2/23 and copies in Files 2/6 and 4/49 61/238/49. Dear Agency, There has been some misunderstanding among Accountatns regarding the accounting side of our medical arrangements. 2. The Foreign Office in their Despatch No.58 of 15th November, 194 , sanctioned a budget to cover the cost of our medical establishments and medical supplies. The establishments include medical Officers and subordinate staff. 'Medical Supplies' in addition to covering the cost of medical and surgical stores, includes incidental expenses incurr ed in running the dispensaries, hospitals, and quarantine service. It does not include the main tenance of buildings but does cover the cost of water, electricity, washing etc. All expenditure debitable to this budget including salaries and wages of medical staff should therefore be entered in one schedule which we suggest should be called “Medical Supplies, Quarantine and Medical Services'. It will undoubtedly make things easi r for the Organisation and Finance Departments of the Foreign Office if all our accountants headed their schedule with the same title. 3* Under the Foreign Service Medical Scheme (F.O. Circular O^O of 1948) expenditure is incurred for the treatment of United Kingdom based staff and the instructions in that circular should be strictly carried out. Expenditure is also incurred for the medical treatment of the remainder of our staff, beyond the facilities of our own establisliment. This includes hospitalisation, X-ray, laboratory investigations, physiotherapy etc. Such expenditure should be charged to the same head as that incurred under circular ©80, and the whole should be called 'Medical Treatment (Foreign Service Medical Scheme)'. The items charged under this head for other than United Kingdom based staff should be entered on this schedule after the total amount referred to in circular ©80. The cost of this service is not covered by the budget r ^erred to in Para 2* 4. Revenue is derived from certain services in connection with quarantine (Deratization Certificates, inoculation etc.) and for a refund of^percentage of fees received by medical Officers. All such revenue should be credited in the first schedule i.e. 'Medical Suoplies, quarantine and Medical Services', full details being shown on the schedule foq^each item. In case of any doubt please refer to this office before completing a quarter’s schedule. Yours ever, Residency. &gt; \V? The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, 24th December, 1949 The Political Agency, Bahrain. (Copy)Je&amp;r Establishment &amp; Organisation Oepartnent, Please refer to your letter AiS10/£I (13/49) of 12th January, regarding the monthly allowance payable to the Royal Air Force Nursing Orderly at uharraq# 2 . propose to pay the allowance rith effect f*©m 1st December, 1949 (nee our II/6I/49 of 2 :nd Deceinber 1949, second paragraph) • 3. Negotiations are now taking place for the handing over of all quarantine arrangements in Bahrain to the State and it is hoped that this will become effective with Bahrain State's ne* finanical year i*e« October, I960* 4 . The arrangement in force at Suharraq has been made with the knowledge nnd agrf ' lent of the Officer Coor'•aniing, ^oyal ^ir orcc, uiarr^q. Yjuts ever, Hr^SlDMECYf Establishment and Organisation Departnent, Foreign Office, I . o N o ■ «■ r 4 XSI0/9I( 13/49)) FOREIGN' OFFICE, S.W.I. 12th January, 135Q« Dear Residency, Your letter II/6I/49 of 22nd December on the question of the monthly allowance payable to the Royal Air Force medical orderly at' uharraq. 2m ve agree that the allowance may be inc reased to Rs«50 per month so long as the present arrangements continue. We shall be glad to know what date you propose to pay the increased rate of allowance, and whether it is anticipated that arrangements can be made soon to transfer these duties to tne State oflicials at the airfield as evisaged in paragraph 28 of Colonel Noddy's report* . ' ve a ssume that the present arrangement for paying the medical orderly was initiated with the knowledge and agreement of the Royal Air Force authorities concerned. y\ Yours ever, ESTABLISHME;T AND ORGANISATION DEPARTMENT. The Political Residency, Bahrain.FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.1. Please refer to your letter No.3-^/6 of 12th January, about the refund of return fares to the United Kingdom to Dr.J.D. Grant, after service specified in his letter of appointment. Would you please also refer to our telegram of 25th August, 1949* wherein it is definitely stated that the fares for the journey would not be chargeable to public funds? Until some evidence is produced as to the necessity for Dr. Grant to travel home when he did, we will be unable to consider repaying him his expenses.. We would point out that Officers are allowed to anticipate their paid leave journey entitlement 17 th February, 1950. Dear Agency, the expiry of the eighteen months period of only under special circumstances Finance Department Yours ever Political Agency, Bahrain.9 f - No. /,Q -S/6. Dear Finance Department, Political Agency, Bahrain, 27th March,1950 Please refer to your No.(XF043843/150) of 17th February regarding Dr.Grant’s passage on leave to the United Kingdom. 2. Special circumstances exist in this case which we think merit consideration and these are set forth in the following paragraphs. 3. His original contract was for 12 months from July 1948 at the end of which he was entitled to two months leave. He had therefore made all arrangements for his leave before his contract was renewed, and in fact his wife and son had already left, chiefly because his accommodation was inadequate during the hot weather and there were no air conditioning units. Even now he has not been supplied with adequate quarters for a family. 4. He is required to fit in his leave with Dr.Moody, the Chief Quarantine Medical Officer whose duties Dr.Grant has to perform in Dr.Moody's absence, no other relief being available. 5. Dr.Grant arrived in July 1948, and to have waited 18 months for his leave would have entailed doing two hot weathers in Bahrain, including Dr.Moody's work in addition to his own from June to August 1949, and then taking home leave in February and March when the climate in the Gulf is at its best. This would appear to contradict the very principles on which leave from the Gulf is based. 6 . We therefore consider that the circumstances in this case justified the anticipation of paid leave and trust that you will see your way to repaying his expenses. The Finance Department, Foreign Office, London. Yours ever, Bahrain Agency. 4British residency, Bahrain. 10th March, 1950. Mease rel'er to our letter 61/238/49 of 24th December, 1949. Certain points have been raised by the Foreign Office about medical schedules in your quarterly accounts. 2. It will no longer be necessary after iipril 1st to separate the salaries of medical staff, which should be shewn on the same schedules as those of the rest of tne staff. Also, a separate schedule should be px*eparea for the receipts from quarantine anu medical fees, which should not be netted on the payment schedules. Thus for Medical Supplies (Quarantine and Medical Services) two schedules, one on each of the debit and credit sides of theHo. / ^ -2/6. Polltictl Agency, Bahrciin, 28th March, 1960. The Accomtant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. Subjects Leave Salary and difference of oay - Uulo r !&gt; «L.^tee^e. mmmm . s * ’ Your attention is invited to my memorandum No.3707-2/6 of 26th December, 1949. 2. Will you please expedite the matter of settlement of Leave Salary and Difference of Pay due to the above named Officer? He has now been kept waiting more than eighteen months for his dues. 3. The difference of pay has arisen on account of the fact that the Officer drew his pay and allowances on the Captain* s grade till handing over even though he was promoted to the grade of Major on 16-6-46 (Vide Gazette of India Notification 2037-B dated 9th August 1947). 4. Your prompt attention to this matter will be greatly appreciated. for Political Agent, Bahrain. ^/C Copy forwarded with compliments to Maior ii.L.A. Gteele, P.O.Box No.lOlO, Nairobi, for information with reference to his letter of the 2nd March,1960*Reference P.A.’s note on Major Steele’s letter below. Correspondence on the subject of Leave Salary and Pension of Major Steele has been going on between this Agency and the Government of India since June-July 1948. Relevant papers flagged below. A.G.C.R. wrote to us asking for three specimen signatures of Major Steele (Vide S.112) which were obtained and furnished to the A.G.C.R. with our letter dated 26th Dec. 1949 at S.125. Since then there has been no intimation from the Go”t. of India on the subject. In March this year Major Steele wrote to us urging us to send a strong • reminder (Vide S.142) and we accordingly sent a reminder to the A.G.C.R. at S.143 on 28th March. The present position is that In August 1949, tljifPolitical Agency, Ho. I&amp; 9 -2/6. Bahrain, 2nd Alay t 1950. Subject:- Laave Jalary, ension etc., of * J *« T A II 12 V Major M«L»A.Steele, U.B.K., formerly Q.M.O., Bahrain. Sir In inviting your reference to the correspondence resting with the Persian Gulf Residency Saving No.2 of 26.1.1949 on the above subject (copy enclosed for ready reference), I have the honour to inform you that although Major Jteele proceeded on leave preparatory to retirement in June 1948 his following claims are still pending settlement a) Leave salary from 7.6.1948 b) Difference of pay due to rim owing to his promotion to the rank of Major on 16.5.46 (Vide Gazette of India notification NO.2037B, of 9.8.47), c) and finally his pension. by the Accountant General, Central Revenues frcaa time to time concerning these claims have been supplied to him by this Agency, but it is a matter of regret that no steps to authorise the payment of the Officer’s legitimate dues appear to have yet been taken with the result that he has unnecessarily been kept waiting for about two years now. 3. The last letter I had received from the Accountant General, Central Revenues was his No.GD-58-21.1056 of 9.8.49 in which he asked to be supplied with 3 sets of Major Steele s specimens of signature for transmission to the Treasurer, Nairobi, along with leave salary certificate of the Officer. These were obtained and forwarded to him under this office letter No.3707-2/6 of 26-12-49, and a subsequent reminder No.1112-2/6 of 28-3-1950 urging him to expedite the matter was issued to which no reply has yet been received by me. 4 # it is, therefore, : equ st&lt;?d t at the Accounts Dept, may be asked that steps necessary for a very early settlement of the Officer’s outstanding dues may please be taken under intimation both to him and myself as he is in urgent need of money. His present address is:- 2. All the necessary information and data required Major M.L.A. 3teale # P.0. Box S^IO, Nairobi, Kenya- I have the honour to be, 3i v - Your obed servant. The Secretary to the Government of India, Ministry of Kxtem&amp;l Affairs, New Delhi. &amp; for Political Agent,Bahrain.Ho.3.0./43^-2/6. Political Agency, Bahrain, 2nd May,1950. Dear Steele, I am in receipt of your letter of 14.4.50 and agree with you that the Accounts Department have taken a long time to settle your dues. So far as this office is concerned I the case has not been lost sight of and you must / how have received the copy which we forwarded to /■ you of our letter Ko.1112-2/6 of the 28th March to the Accountant General, Oentral Revenues, New Delhi • * J . J s. m £ 2 . I enclose a copy of the letter which I am now sending to the Government of India and which I hope will help in expediting the matter. Yours sincerely, Major M.L.A.Steele, P.0. Box 3710, Nairobi, Kenya.t St Political Agency, Ho. -2/6. Bahrain, 3rd May, 1960. Dear Sir, y J I should be glad if you will let me have a sterling draft for £l0-4-7d f favouring Officer-in-charge, Comnand Pay Office, Egypt, M.E.L*F*17 and debit the cost thereof to this Agency^ Foreign Office Account • 'A* with you. 2. Please advise me the rupee equivalent debited to the account. Yours for Political Agent,Bahrain The Manager, The Eastern' Bank Ltd Bahrain.HHflM * Political Agency, Bahrain, 4th May, 1950. No. /Lffo -2/6, The Officer-in-charge, Command Pay Office, EGYPT, M.E.Ti.F.17 Memorandum : i ^ With reference to your memorandum CPF/2/D/ of April I960, to the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, I enclose herewith a draft for £l0-4-7d. on the Eastern Bank Ltd., London, made payable in Egypt. Will you please return to me the attached receipt in duplicate signed? for Political Agent,Bahraini. r f •;- &lt; - » ry \b t No. /Si/SO &amp; VICTORIA MEMORIAL HOSPITAL, BAHRAIN. 6th May, 1950. Subject;- LEAVE / l tq I beg to apply for 3 months leave on urgent private affairs from 1st July, 1950 or date of availing. No relief will be required as Colonel W. J. Moody is Twilling to carry out my duties during the period of my absence. I appreciate that the amount of leave on pay may be limited to the amount standing to my credit at the time of my departure and that the arrangements for my passage will be my own responsibility The Political Agent, Bahrain. HPOLITICAL AGENCY 3AKRA1N. 10th May, 1950. Dear Residency, We enclose/herewith a copy of letter No*133/50 of 6th May 1950 from Col*J.D.Grant, Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, applying for three months leave from Is^ 1 rkC ^ leave applied for may be granted* Yours ever, Agency. The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.' No.1723-2/6. • * POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. 28th May, 1950. Sir, 'S' / In continuation of this Agency letter No.1419-2/6 dated the 2nd May 1950, I have the / honour to reproduce below an extract from a letter of 12th yay 1950 from Major M.L.A.Steele which is self explanatory:- 'The Accountant General Central Revenues still persists in addressing me and making out my dues for the rank of Captain despite the numerous reminders he has been sent. I am getting my pension for the Hank of Major. This is paid by the C.R.O., London, who has transferred the accounts to Nairobi Treasury. It was from the C.R.O., London, that I learnt of my promotion to Major. He gave me the Government of India notification as well as the London Gazette Order'. 2. Since the Officer is being paid his pension of Major’s Rank under authority from the Commonwealth Relations Office, London, his claim for difference of pay and leave salary should be admitted by the Accountant General Central Revenues. He informs me that he has also referred the question to the Accountant General, Central Revenues through the Treasurer, Nairobi. I should be grateful, therefore, if the macter could be expedited. I liave che honour to be, sir, your obedient servant, for Political Agent. The Secretary to the Government of India, Ministry of External Affairs, New Delhi. Copy to: Major M.L.A.Steele, P.O.Box 3710, Nairobi with reference to his letter dated 12th May 1950.Conmand Pay Office Egypt. -i. E. L# P • 0PP/0ASH/3/6877 19th May, 1950. Political Agency, Bahrain. 17. 7d. ^ ^'H/g wxun your JLeiixer wo. 1450- 4th May 1950 is hereby acknowledged. As the ’’Form B H , which is required by the Egyptian Exchange Control Department, was not forwarded, the draft has been sent to London for clearance. As soon as this has been effected your form of receipt will be forwarded. r BD/&lt;*Sr POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. No.R.^ 7 0 -2/6. 19th June, 1950. @&gt; Dear Residency, We would be grateful for an early reply to our letter No.R-206 about Colonel Grant’s leave. Bahrain.i. 71 tfyfo jim /fv/v r $%&gt;•?&gt; OFFICE OF IHE A.G.C.R.IEW DELHI.' / 5~5” r ;5 JUN 10:0 o.GD. 58-21/520 To The Secretary to the Government of India, Ministry of External Affairs, ' \ . , ) Nev Dellii. V ^. s '4 &lt; . &gt;30 . {A, SuhjectJ Agpointment of Major M^L^A^Steele as Residency Surgeon Bahrain for the period from the 15th Jan, *47 to the 3rd Feb, • 48, Sir •••••• i am to invite a reference to your remo,No.D,3741-&amp;II /47 dated the 19th November *47 on the above subject v/herein 1*1©.jor M,L,A,Steele was granted the following terras during his tenure as Residency Surgeon Bahrain*- Pay Rs,650/- P,M,( as a Captain) Special pay Rs,333/V- P*H# Compensatory Allowances* 66/1V- P*'i» Additional pay 20^ of pay as a Captain Cost cf Living Allowance ) Local compensational Alice, ) As admisi bio, //, From the Defence Department notification 110.20373 dated the 9th August , 47(published in the Gazette of Jfndia dated the 9th August f 47 , page 1145) it is seen that the Officer was promoted to the rank of Major from the 16th May *46, It may please be staged whether the intention of uhe Government of India was deliberate in allowing him captains 1 rank pay and additional pay 80# of such basic pay during his appointment/from the 15th Jan. *47 to the 3rd Feb, *48 as Residency Surgeon (Bahrain. If it was not the case the letter under reference may please be suitably amended and a eppy thereof fur lished through the Ministry of Finance to enable this office to pay him the difference of pay and allowances if any due. This may please be treated as very urgent. - . f i *R* ( S.R.Sharma) Yours faithfully, ■■■Kf Assistant Jacounts Officer. Central Bew.nv**. //V /'• 'V \ - BY AIR MAIL ' No.GD,58-21/521 Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain for information .with refer-nee to his le:ter No. 112-2/6 dated the 28th March *^0. m 1 —— ( S.R.Sharma) Assistant Accounts OJJ^ctt, C[) Central Revenue*. /&lt; •V\VG A * •• C *1^Lf 7 \ hu . F .44- Ell/50 Government of inaii ministry of External Affairs A *ew Eelhi,the [^June 1950. From Shri V.B.Moharir, n.A.LL.o., lAssistant Secretary to the Government of India. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Sub:- Leave salary, Pension etc. of Maj 0 r M.L.A.St eele, MBE, formeriy uahrain. * d r 3 With reference to your letter No.1419-2/6 dated the 2nd May 1950, on the subject noted above, I am airected to say that the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, has been advised to expedite settlement of the question of leave salary of Major Steele. 2. 1 am to add that a further communication will follow with regard to the questions of payment to Major Steele of difference of pay on account of his promotion to the rank of major and of settlement of his pension claim. 3. A copy of this letter is being sent to Major Steele direct. KLN.7.6. fours faithfully, Assistant Secretary.VICTORIA MEMORIAL HOSPITAL, Bahrain (Persian Gulf) 11th June, 1949. Sir Thank you for your letter (PF8751) of the 18th May, 1949, offering me an extension to 19th July, 1951, of my appointment as Quarantine Medical Officer at Bahrain. I am prepared to accept this extension on the terms men tioned by you provided that the furnished quarters,of fered in paragraph 3 of your letter,are made available. My present official quarter is in a bad state of repair, inadequately furnished and without air-conditioning. On that account I was allowed to occupy, as a temporary measure, the Assistant Political Agent*s house since last February but have been given to understand that this arrangement may terminate in the near future. Under the circumstances, it will be necessary either to repair and furnish my official quarter for habitation under local condition or provide suitable alternative accommodation. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant (J*D. GRANT) G.H. Middleton, Esquire, * Foreign Office, LONDON,’ S.W.l.(17/47/50) 23 rd June, 1950. y,.'*. bs! om Dear Agency, ft / Please refer to your R.2?0 - 2/6 of 19th June regarding Dr. Grant T s leave. 2. £ copy of Foreign Office No. P,F.8751 of 13 th June, sanctioning 48 days leave is enclosed herewith.. Copy of a letter No.FFf751 13th June, 1950 from Mr, Turner, Foreign Office, London, to Mr. Pinhey, First Secretary, Political Residency, Bahrain, I am writing in reply to your letter to Middleton (17/43/50) of the loth May about Grants application for leave this sumrrer, 2, As Grant was on leave for 89 days, he will have only 28 days due to him on the 1st July this year. We can, however, agree to his anticipating a further 20 days of his entitlement for 1950 provided that he returns to Bahrain after his leave. The total of 48 days is inclusive of travelling time* Such a short period of leave would not permit of his travelling by sea, and we therefore see no objection to paying the coat of his air passage, subject to the condition laid down in paragraph 6 of E.N.Smith 1 s letter to Felly (XFO 4 / 3843 / 250 ) of the 18th May, 1950*FOREIGN OFFICE, 3. W. 1. 18th May, 1950 &lt;T' V Ul II 4 Will you please refer to Bahrain Agency letter No.29-2/6 of the 27th March aboux Doctor Grant’s passage to the United Kingdom on leave in August 1949. 2. Doctor Grant’s original contrac-c provided for repatriation to the United Kingdom, at public expense on termination of the appointment, provided he had not resigned within one year. It specified that termination would be by one month’s notice on either side. It also provided for sixty days leave after one year’s service if the contract were not renewed. , 3. In the event, the contract was extended by Foreign Office letter FF8751 of the 18th May, 1 949 by the terms of which Doctor Grant was entitled to a leave passage at any time after eighteen months service. He is still entitled to this passage and he can take advantage of this entitlement at any time this year subject to the exigencies of the Service. 4. We cannot, however, agree to make any contribution from public funds in respect of the leave Journey in August 1949. That Grant had no entitlement under his current contract to a paid passage at that time was emphasized in Foreign Office telegram No .506 of the 23rd August, 1949, and we see no grounds at all for retrospectively altering that posit ion. 5« We cannot moreover see how the fact that Doctor Grant doubles’ with Colonel Moody for leave purposes affects the issue. Colonel Moody toolC'leave from June to August 1949, but this does not lead us to the supposition that Grant, whose contract did not permit of a leave Journey until 1930, was obliged thereby to take leave when he did. Indeed^ no member of the Foreign Service, of whatever graae, would be entitled to a paid leave Journey from Bahrain after only twelve months; nor coula we in similar circumstances make any contribution retrospectively towards the cost of such a leave Journey which would have to be made entirely at the officer’s own expense (as was the case with Doctor Grant). 6. This brings me to the question of the cost of the fares to the United Kingdom of Mrs. Grant and her son. Incidentally from the very beginning of his appointment Grant has reported ’ in his Life Certificates that his son was at boarding school in the United Kingdom, and this leads us to ask whether Master Grant’s visit was intended to be temporary or permanent. The cost of these fares, amounting to £l46.6s.2d. , was paid by* the Agency in September Quarter 1949, but we have not been able to accept the charge as proper to public funds, nor can we, on the information at present available to us, find any grounds for doing so. There was no liability created by Doctor Grant’s contract to repatriate his wife and son much less than one year after its conmencement. We consider therefore that unless there are very good grounds for special consideration of this /particular C.J. Felly, Esq., 0. B. S. , Bahrain.particular point, in which case we sha^l be glad to have your views, we should make Grant’s orlxitlement to a leave journey in 1950 contingent pri the prior refund of the sum of £1 46 .6s.2d. We hptfe seen the correspondence resting with Bahrain Agency letter No.F71-4/53 of the 27th April to Finance Department on this question, but , I am afraid we should have to see a fuller and more detailed case made out before we could reconsider. 7. I am sorry to be unhelpful, but the regulations on these points are binding. Yours sincerely, (B.N. Smith)Minutes. It appears from Clause 4 of the Q.M.O’s contract that he is entitled to free passages to the United Kingdom for himself, his wife, and any members of his family resident with him (1) on the termination of his appointment, and (2) (to the United Kingdom and back) on leave after the completion of 18 months service from the beginning of his original appointment. 2. As I understand it, the Finance Depart ment have turned down his application for free passages for himself and his son last year be cause he had not completed 18 months service from the beginning of his original appointment. 3. It seems to me that the only chance of having the passages,taken by Mrs. and Master Grant last summer,paid by H.M.G. is to show that although they were taken before the com pletion of 18 months, etc., fcfcxfc NO passages for Mrs. and Master Grant will he claimed after the expiry of 18 months. 4. As regards recoupement of losses. If I understand to be the case, the 30% of private practice fees has been credited to the Finance Department and I do not think therc» is any hope of recovering any of ^ f * 14-6-50.m BniTISH RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. (17/48/50) Unclassifiad. 1st July, 19fO Will you pl«ase refer to your letter XK043843/ 250 of the 18th M a y on the subject of payment of passafes for Dr. Grant and his family. 2. I afree that you cannot be eypected to rmhe any contribution from public funds in respect of Grants leave journefr in Aupust, 1949. 3 # As ro ards the cost of fares to the United Mnfdom of ’rs. Grant and her pon f I think there are f ood grounds for special consideration of this case, hey are as follows Although he was at a boarding school in the United Kingdom faster Grants visit was intended to be porraanent - in the sense that ho would stay out here until he could accompany his father on leave after IP months of his father^ contract had expired. The reason that :rs. Grant and S&amp;ster Grant had to be repatriated was that the living accommodation provided for Dr. Grant was not suitable for a family - particularly in the hot woathsr since r.c ilr-conditioning was (or indeed has since been) provided? although Grant had only accepted the extension of his contract on the condition that suitable accomr-o/ation would be made available. As you say in your letter f there was f of course, no 'liability' created by Grants contract to repatriate his wife and son much less than one year after its conaencament; but I think you will agree that circum- stances compelled him to do so. This being the case, I think it not too much to ask that public fun^s should bear the cost of the fmees amounting to £.146/6/2d provided, of course, that Grant does not claim at any future date the cost of the repatriation of his wife and son. 4 # I am sending a copy of this letter to Adams.-—ifo,00.53-23/530 To JIAM HIA YB N r' . ,201 ■OFSTuCE OF rdE A.S.C.K.rEW BSLia. ••• - - •• oJUNK^^. fho Secretary to the Oovermnent of India* I-Unlstry of eternal Affairs. Hew Delhi. Subjecti Appointment of tiajor M.L^A.Steele I # M.D»(B*C # ) as Residency Surgeon Bahrain for tlie period Tvom the 15th Jan* *47 to the 3rd Peb*»48 f •••••• Sir. t am to invlie a refer^ice to your neino.IJo.D.374X.EU /47 dated the 19th Hover^ber *47 on the above subject wherein Major MtL.A^Steele was granted the folloSln^ terms during his tenure as Residency Surgeon Bahrain*- p ay as a Caotaln) Special pay Rs.333/5/- Compensatory mo^ance^^Vll/** P.M* Additional pay 20^ of pay as a Captain Cost of Living Allowance ) Local coi?pensatioml Alice, As admls£ ble 9 Prom the Defence Department ratification IJO.3037B dated the 9th August # 47&lt;publiahed In tlie Gazette of India dated the 9th August *47 . page 1145) it is seen that the Officer was promoted to the rank of Jfejor frcca the 16th !2ay *46. It may please be sta od whether the intention of the Goveroueat of India was deliberate in allowing hir. captains* rank pay and additional pay &amp; 20/* of such basic pay during his appointment from the 15th Jan* 1 47 to the 3rd i J, eb # , 43 as Residenc; Surgeon {Bahrain* If it was not the case the letter mid$»r reference nay please be suitably amended and a thereof fur dshed through the Ministry of Fina^w to enable this office to pay him tdie liffOrence of pay and allowances if any duo* This may please be treated as very urgent* ♦R* Yours faithfully f ( S*R*Sharzaa) Assistant Accounts UJ)*cet Central Revenues.From The Under Secretary to the Government of India, Ministry of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations, To - The Accountant General, Central Revenues, v NEW DELHI . Memorandum Nc. D. 3741-EII/47 Dated New Delhi 3, the 19th November, 1947. Subject:- Emoluments of Capt. M.L.A. Steele during the period he officiates as Residency Surgeon, Bahrain, in addition to his own duties. Reference late External Affairs Department notific ation N#. 196-EII dated the 14th June 1947, copy endorsed to you. 2. Sanction is accorded to the grant at to Capt. M.L.A. Steele Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, for the period he officiates as Residency Surgeon, Bahrain, in addition to his own duties, the pay and allowances detailed below:- Pay Rs • 650/- p.m. CAs a Captain) i&gt; /(b) Special Pay Compensatory allowance 333- 5- 0 p.m. 66 -11- 0 p.m. d) Additional pay at 20# of pay as Captain M 130/- p.m. (e) Cost of living allowance) (f) Local compensation ) As admissible. allowance ) 3 o Since His Majesty f s Government have taken over the administration of the posts on the Arab side of the Gulf w.e.f. 1.4.^±7, only the expenditure prior to that date will be borne by the former Government of India and His Majesty 1 s Government in moieties. ' mSZ ' w- -v ~ .. r /■ -- a Sd/- Devi Diyal. Under Secretary to the Govt, of India. Copy forwarded to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in tiie Persian Gulf with reference to his telegram No. A/538, dated 30th July, 1947. Copy for information to the Director General, New Delhi. Health services * By otder, UnJer Secretary to the Government of India.COPY Copy of letter No.G-D 58-21-2505 dated 11.1.oO iroin b jie .G.C.R. , New Delhi to the assistant Secretary to one jo/o.oi India, Ministry of External Affairs, New Delhi. Subiect:- Employment during leave pending retirement of Capt.M.L.A. Steele (ex-L..D/BC). r 0 127 / “S C ift! 48 : 'tE e ef 6?48 (fOTlooon Sd to stole that troa the charge renort of Capt. Steele received in this office (^original,reports enclosed) SS his L.P.O. both received l4fs&amp;S°i 0 K: 6 8 “s C ffd'iKitiie ?§ . the period 1 4 48 to 6 6.43 only and not upto /.6.48. It is, therexoie, requested that an amendment to your letter under reference may please be Issued If considered necessary. 9 Incidentlv it may be added that the other three officers namely Dartors C.E. Kynes, A.l.T. -athenes and q* f n S ° belpnged to the ; same class ^service as Ca^.Stecp^^er^ Qf States* decision 'below ^1/69 and with reference to your ^0.11°. 4306-EII/49 dated 12.7.49, they have been granted full leave salary as otherewise admissible for the periods of their re-employ^ent under tne corwn during leave pending retirement. Tt mflv therefore please be stated whether the omission to include it may ther^rore P^ase ue ^ ^ t s de leberate or\\ it Is intended thltlhis else si^ld also be (talt^with on the same vf n p' iS there of the other three officers mentioned above, if thl lattehfthe D.G?1 F.ls,, Ministry of Defence may be asked to issue int he case of Capt. ouecle also. An early reply is requested^ Yours faithfully, True copy 8.3.50No. 5.^*) -2/6 POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. 11th July, 1950. The Assistant Secretary to the Government of India, Ministry of External Affairs, New Delhi. Subject:- Leave Salary, Pension etc. of Will you please refer to letter of 25th June, 1950 from Major K.L.A.Steele addressed to you and copy sent to me, and also to your letter No.F.44-Ell/50 of 10th June, 1950, on the above subject? attention as the matter has b en outstanding for a considerable time. Copy, with compliments, forwarded for information to Major M.li.A.Steele, P.O.Box No.1010, Major M.L.A.Steele, MBE, formerly Q.M.O., Bahrain. Sir 2. We would be grateful for your very earliest I have the honour to be Sir Your obedient servant 0\5&gt;V' r ' Political Agent NairobiPolitical Agency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf* With further reference to your letter 1450-^6 dated 4 Hay 1950 * enclosed please find receipt in duplicate for £10. 4. 7&amp;. (Conversion LZ. 9.963 ra/ras) Captain. Canraand Cashier,(265/33/50) OFFICE ORDER 33 With effect from 13th October 19 50 (1st Moharrum 1370) (I) the Office of the Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrain will be transferred from the administration of the Political Agency to that of the Government of Bahrain (2) the appointment of Quarantine 'edical Officer and Agency Surgeon Bahrain under His Majesty^ Government will be terminated, and the appointment of Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrain will be reconstituted under the Government of Bahrain (3) the appointment of Dr. J. D. Grant under His Majesty's Government will be terminated and he will assume the appointment of Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrain under the Government of Bahrain. 2. The duties of Agency Surgeon in medical attendance on the staffs of the Political Residency,and Political Agency Bahrain will be taken over by Dr. W. J. Moody in addition to his other duties. 3. I'he office of the Quarantine ?s!edical Officer, and the Agency Dispensary will remain until further notice in the building of the Victoria Memorial Hospital. (L. A. G. PinheyJ FIRST SECRETARY British Residency, Bahrain. 12th October, 195°*21 OCT 1950 The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to ; H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned dsKiameotsx Office Order for information. Adviser's Office, Manamah, Bahrain. No ^^ - /&lt;? Dated October 19, i960. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. Copy of Office Order Quarantine Medical No.53/10 dated 18th Officer. October 1950. \l Reference to previous correspondence :■Kj. ^3 — 1 0 or 1370 Office of the Advleer to the Goverraaent, Bahrain Da ted 9 6 th ttuharr eai 1370 October 16, I960* office order With effect from let tfuh&amp;rrata 1370 (13th October 1950):- (I) the Office of the Quarantine Uedioesl Officer Bahrein will be transferred from the administration of the ^political A&amp;ency to that of the Government of Behrain (2) the appointment of quarantine Medical Officer and Agency Surgeon Bahrain under Hie Majesty's Government will be terminated, and the appointment of Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrain will be recons tituted undar the Government of Bahrain (3) the appointment of Or* J. B. Grant under Hie -Gjesty'a Government will be terminated and he will assume the appointment of orrantine Medical Officer B*hrsin under the Government of Bahrain. 2 * The office of the Quarantine Medical Officer, and the Agency Dispensary will remain until further notice in the building of the Victoria memorial Hoepi al« / ^ 4 , (, j c J Adviser to the Goverr^ient*t 4) (lib, K Ot F.44=ai/£0. //' 25 OCT 1950 Copy (with 1 spare co;y) forvarded to the Ministry of Finance for co r.iinic/tion to tr.e De.uty Accountant General, (GaD), Centrrl Revenues, Curgon Road, New Delhi* Sanction has been given with the concurrence ef that Ministry vide their U*0*No.7.^80-EA/50, dated the 29 tby September, 1950• 2, The Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference te his letter No. 1419-^/6, do tea the 2nd iiay 1C50. As regards pension, the retirement rolls (IAF.A.311 and 312 ) in respect of Major Steele v.ere forwarded to the Coism on wealth Relations Office, London, by the C.M.A. (F), Allahabad, under his letter No.Gl/14643, dated the loth November, 1948, fer necessary action. The retirement el ^ajor Steele has already beer, published in the Secretary of States 1 Weekly list vide Weekly list No.l of 1949, dated the 6th January 1949 (extract enclosed). The C.R.O., London may plea* be contacted for further information. 3. Major M.L.A. ele, P.0. Box No.1010, Nairobi. 4. Directorate-General Health Services, New Delhi, with reference to their D.0.Ne.64-19-l/48-lMD/P dated the 10th July, 1950. By order,etc., Assistant ^Secretary.&amp; ■ t * Copy of an extract from Secretary of States Weekly List No. 1 of 1949 dated the 6th January, 1949 regarding Military personnel of the Indian Establishment granted extension of leave, or retired from the service etc. RETIREMENTS PERIOD SERVICE RANK NAME CORPS Major. Sttele MX .A. I.M.D.(B.C.) 5.7*48 Rs.500/- p.m. Letter No.0658/IV/49/Coord(A), dated 7th February, 1949, from Ministry of Defence placed on file 43-3/49-P refers. / /0^ r v^ i u I The bills at pages 111-13 ( enclosure to 3.No.73) on account of cost of carpets and curtain materials purchased for the Q.M.O’s house are still outstanding. These were sanctioned by the Residency in their memo. St page 99 and are to be paid from the Ministry of Works Account. If you approve we may obtain Mr.Horner’s approval before making payment. f n A/ 0 - /*—e*-&lt;^ /&gt;• ft f&lt;°L (l* . XK a I. p\A^XwvA-AT / \T-S '7h O' Letter below should issue to the P.R. before I leave on June 5th. It should go with clean unreceipted copies of all bills pending. If there are more bills than one the letter should be modified accordingly. Meanwhile the pend ing bills should be paid from the V.M.H. Fund so that the merchants need not wait for their money any longer. As soon as /the P.R. makes arrangements for the payments the amount ' • A M can be recredited to the V.M.H. Fund. - - * ' • f 4 * *» ltd. C.J.P.i I,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00028a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1059</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00028a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1059</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2/6 III Assistant Surgeon: Appointment, Recess, Leave Etc'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-10T16:11:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (244 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes at the end, on folios 218-245. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 246; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 5-121; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains notes and correspondence between the Assistant Surgeon and Quarantine Medical Officer at the Victoria Memorial Hospital in Bahrain, Dr Steele; the Office of the Accountant General at New Delhi, the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain; the Political Agent at Bahrain; and the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf. The main subjects of the correspondence are Dr Steele's pay, leave and retirement, in 1948.From 1950 the Office of Quarantine Medical Officer at Bahrain, occupied by Dr J D Grant, was transferred from the administration of the Political Agency to that of the Government of Bahrain.The file also includes correspondence related to yellow fever vaccination fees.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Accountant-General, Central Revenues</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Medical Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Personnel management</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00028a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>