<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00018d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:29:28.563Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">INWARD TELEGRA (TUt « Q/V% 0*W\AC * ■ ( 3 J +*- ~*y ZMjnj OI^^lovv FILE COPY ^'l lotted to aconoiTil-c D s^aj^tment , 0o, o .E sc tesffla l b7i f MM c, t 0 .^om To CY PiBSH Xai^caAM (Otg.P.) ^ r j Governrasnt of India, External Affairs Dept. Tehran No S6*^' Repeated to Secretary of State for India. Dated Hew Delhi ; OS. 55 hours, 89th May 1946. Reed. 03*55 hours, 89th May 1946. 4825 . ' An Indian firm, Messrs Saapen end Company of Bombay, hath offered 5000 tens of Persian barley at Rs. 345 per ton f.o/o. Khar am she hr tc Government of India (Food Department) who are accepting offer subject to grant of export licence by Persian Gover ruxent. 8. Mesors Saapen are approaching Persian Government direct for export licence 'hrough their principal's Me sgi* a Michel Saab of Tehran, hut suggest Ministry of Commerce Tehran be informed that Government of India are buying this grain on Government } s account. 3 0 if you see no objection, grateful if you would inform Persian Government of offer and express Government of India's hopes vhat export facilities will be granted.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00018d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1144</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00018d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1144</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 3777/46 'Offer by Messrs Saapen and Co of Bombay of 5000 tons of Persian Barley to Government of India'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-14T23:36:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (1 folio)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 3; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains a telegram from the Government of India, External Affairs Department to presumably the HM Ambassador to Persia detailing an offer made by the Indian firm, Messrs Saapen and Company of Bombay to export 5000 tons of Persian barley to the Government of India, Food Department and the need for an export licence should the offer be accepted.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Food Department</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Barley</topic></subject><subject><topic>Food rationing</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00018d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>