<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000114_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T09:52:19.879Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Telegram From OTP. Prodrome, oiahrain To Political, Kuwait. No.20. Dated and received 4th November, 1948. IITEDIATF.- Following received from Foreign Office November 1st telegram No.356 to Foreign Office, begins. ,f Ily telegram No. 355. Jir Hu.gli /eightman who still hopes to obtain concession for under sea oil off the Kuwait Neutral Zone has been informed by the Nandi Arabian Minister of Finance that if Sir ilugh heightman closed Tconcession with the Shaikh of Kuwait for latter 1 s share he is prepared to grant him Saudi share on similar terms but Shaiivh ^i.bdullah adds deal ?must be arranged within about 10 days otherwise he may grant the Saudi rights to luainco. Sir Hugh ,/eightman flies to Sahrain October 31st and will await permission there ff . Znds. Please see my two following telegrams. -Dredge-Telegram OTP Prom Prodroiue, Bahrain To Political, jaiwait Jated and received 4th November, 1948 Poliowing received from Foreign Gfiice telegram TIo.256 November 2nd. Begins 'Jecret. addressed to Washington telegram : T o. 11823 Noveinber 2nd. Repeated to Jedda, Bahrain, Baghdad, Tehran for information. seems clear unless we are definitely to favour interests of an American company at the expense of a British (mut) ?attempt to restrain Weightman from approaching the Shaikh of Tuwait. Bubject therefore to the views of the Political Resident we do not feei we can refuse Weightman facilities to visit Kuwait though we do not propose he should be given any special assistance and after he has arrived in Kuwait he will have to make is own approach presumably through th- Bhaixh’s Secretary. Before he goes we w ould also propose the Political Agent should tell phe Jhaikh that since we know oil comcany are most interested in gaining concessions to exploit oil believed to exist beneath the sea bed we have (mut) upon that to mean whereby the Rulers of the Gulf States could extend their jurisdiction over the sea bed in order to open way for the development of any oil and hope very shortly po be able Po inform him of our views. In the meantime should he be approached by any oil company we hope he will ensure that all conversations which may ensue will be entirely secret and non-committal since premature disclosure may adversely affect his interests. We should be glad if you would explain position Jedda telegram No.356. In the circumstances as now reported by Jedda it as stated above and in Jedda telegram No.356 to Btate Department. £XZ&gt;S. S&gt; I -Dredge-Dredge- Telegram OTP Prom To. _.e peat ed No.22. Dated and IiaEDL, Following received from Foreign Office telegram No.256 November 2nd. Begins. ^ ’» Jecret. My telegram No. 11823 to .Washington. v/e do not consider we can obstruct any efforts Neightraan may make to go to Muwait. If therefore he applies to you for permission he should be allowed to proceed. 2. Regarding statement that it is proposed that the Political Agent should make to Shaikh we suggest in order that ohai.ch may not believe that it is aimed specifically against Weightman Political ..gent shoul 1 add that it is not our intention to prejudice his mind against any specific oil company. 3. Telegraph immediately if you agree and when weight man leaves’ 1 . Fnds. Have sent copies of relevant telegrams to Kuwait. Intend informing '.'Weightman that he can proceed to Kuwait but he should not raise matter with Jhaikh until Political ngent Kuwait receives your instructions. **■130 telegraph Foreign Office. Pro i rorne, Da hra in. Demin, Cairo. Telegram No.13. Political, Kuwait. received 4th November, 1948. T2.-&gt;y—- - V .-tgy—» 4 « Telegram ifrom To No.33. ^ated ohe 6th November INNilTJI VTN. OTP. Political, it. Prodrome, London. , 1948. /'**'&gt;* ^ I (!) Please pass to Hay, Cairo as my telegram No. C/13 November 6th. Bahrain telegram No.13 of the 4th November to you and foreign Office telegram No. 11823 to .Washington. 1 am informed that Heightman arrives morning of the 7th. -‘•S I have not received instructions I shall’ask him not to approach Bhai^h until he gets clearance from me. Galloway KB-Dredge- OTP Telegram Froi Bahrain To Poliuieal, Kuwai d. No.24. Dated the 6th November, 1948. Following received from Foreign Office telegram No.265. Begins. 'Secret. Following received fro:. Washington telegram No.5077 November 4th Begins. Bepeoted for information to Bahrain (Immediate) Baghdad, Jedda and Tehran. Foreign Office please jess to Bahrain as my telegram No.8. Your telegram No. 11823. Off Shore Oil in the Persian Gulf. State Department agree that in the circumstances proposed course of action is the right one. . f 2. From our reading of Fedda telegram No.356 to you however it appears to us and State department that if Shaikh of Kuwait is to be asked to be 'non-committal' Jir Hugh .'/eightman will not be able to (omission) ?t ell iaudi Arabian Minister of Finance that deal is arranged, in which case laudi rights would presumably go to ^minco. State Department suggested Shat Shaikh of Kuwait should only be as^ed to Keep any conversation s secret and that 'non-committal' should be omitted 3. This might seen to be the reverse situation in that, if Sir Hugh '/eightman can obtain Shaikh of Kuwait T s share, Aminco would be cut out. But State Department and we believe in practice that Saudi Arabian authorities would not reneat not be prepared to grant their share without careful consideration of any alternative offers including one which, from mention of 10 days ultimatum, has presumably already been made by .tminco. If that is so balance between competing companies would not repeat not be disturbed. ,/e assume ^ir Hugh /eightman is still representing both Superior and Central Mining. 4. State Department agree to proposal regarding Muscat in your telegram No. 11575.'. Knds.Telegram -tf’rom OTP. Prodrome, Bahrain To Political, x Aiwa i z . ■^ated 7th, received Sth Novembei Following received from Oeiro. Secret. addressed to Foreign Office telegram No.437 November Sth repeated Bahrain and Jedda for information. Folowing from Hay. ^ y Your telegram No.2^6 to Bahrain Off -&gt;hore Oil I see no objection to action proposed except that if Shaikh complies with request that conversation with any oil company should be non-committal it is impossible for deal with '-/eightman to be concluded within period stated by shaiKh Abdulla see Jedda telegram No.356. If it is not possible to permit ShaiKh of huwait to commit himself even provisionally ^eightman’s approach to him may be wasted effort. Sven so I consider it preferable to allow approach to be made in the hope that Shaixh Abdullah will wait longer than he has proposed. 2. If you see no objection please telegraph final instructions direct to Galloway repeating Bahrain. 3. V/eightman leave Bahrain for Kuwait by air November 7th. 4. 'ill Bahrain please repeat to Kuwait. — -hemin-OTP. Prodrome, Pahrain Political, Furait. Telepram From To N 0 .P 8 . Dated &amp;nd received Pth November, 1948. B£MFDIATF. .5V Secret. Your telegram No.C/13. Please do not apr^roa^ch ShaiVh or allow Weightman to do so before you receive explicit instructions from (groun omitted) ? Foreipn Off1ce or myself. Dredge MB. ITelegram From To No. 30 OTP. Prodrome, Bahrain Political, Kuwait. jJated 9th, received 11 th November, 1943. 3ecret . My telegram No.24. Please read in paragraph 1 'Shaiith was trying to interest Magnolia and Superior Submarine drilling Companies Tl . Bnds. -Dredge-Telegram OTP. Prom Cd5 No.32. Prodrome, Bahrain Political, Kuwait. Dated 10th, received 11th November, 1948. Poliowing from Foreign Office. Begins. ,T 3ecret. addressed Bahrain telegram No.276 November 9th repeated for information to Baghdad, Tehran, Fedda, Washington. Please pass iimedlately to G-alloway. ./ashington telegram No.5077. Off shaore oil in the Persian G-ulf. I am reluctant to see Jhaiich of Kuwait enter any commitment so long as proposal for a series of pro clamations is still under discussion and I should prefer to retain the word 'non-comi: ittal” in communication to be made to him about Weightman*s visit^ You should therefore act on the lines of my telegram No.11283 to Washington. ^ £ 3* Che Kuwait Oil Company and Shell who are believed to be interested in obtaining concessions in Kuwait but who have hitherto held back at our request are being informed today that as American Independent Oil Company has initiated negotiations for a concession of Continental Shelf off Kuwait - Saudi Arabia Neutral Zone they are free if they wish to discuss grant of concessions with the Shaikh of Kuwait. Ministry of Fuel and Power are explaining to their (omission) that Shainh is being asked not to commit himself to any concessions for the time being. 3. You will note tnat pending further instructions 1 the ban is raised only in respect of Kuwait and that instructions in my telegram No. 11823 to .Washington applies to any approach made by any company ti^it may appear on phe scene, h s v 4. /ashington should please inform otate Department ,, . Ends.Political, Iluwait. Prodrome, Bahrain rfx^ \\ _ &gt; n Telegram Prom To No.C/14. Datod 11th November, 1949. rour telegram No.30 apparently does not refer to your telegram No.24. Please send correction. -Nallov/ay- .Telegram Trom To No.C/16. Dated the 17th November, 1948. OTP. Political, coav/ait. Prodrome, Bahrain. *9 Your telegram No.33. .’/eightman ha 3 seen JhaiKh who told him that he considered him first on the list for the area for which he v/ished to conclude an agreement. At the same time he stated that he would maKe no final reply since he was not aware of his authority over the area concerned. He stated that on hearing from His Ida jesty ’ 3 Government on this point he would communicate with heightman and would come to no final agreement without first hearing his proposition more fully. -Galloway-fele^ram ^roin To No. 40 OTP Prodrome, Bahrain Political, Nit lit. &amp; approached Shaikh Please confirm that 3 r ou/(r35kh:) (^akt) on lines suggested in foreign Office telegram to Washington No.11823 and report his reactions. * -Hay- i,;b.(True Copy) FOREIGN OFFICE No Knvait he'ccifu iJaiiuX Cypher Addressed to Foreign Office No.444 of 6th Nov. SECRET. Following from Hay. i Bertram Thomas is coming to Bahrain about November 12th and intends to visit Trucial Coast to renew his acquaintance with Shaikhs. I have asked him not to mention sea-bed oil. 2. Noonan has today received Nutall's letter of October 21st in which he is asked to render assistance to Thomas. 3. Please telegraph to me at Bahrain nature of assistance which should be given to him and whether he should be permitted to mention to Rulers desire of his company to obtain sea-bed concession.(True Copy) ' M ” Telegram From Foreign Office, London. To Political Resident, Bahrain. No. 277 Dated 9th received 10th November 1948. I ■.-E.-.IiiTE . Secret. Your telegram No. 444 Bertram Thomas may be given the bag and telegraph facilities and facilities to move about freely. He should nfct otherwise be given any special assistance which is not ofxered to representatives of other Companies. 2. He should not repeat not discuss sea-bed concessions with Trucial Shaikhs; but see my immediately preceding telegram regarding Kuwait. ^9 «19 With the compliments of the Political Resident. d C-£~ British Residency, Bahrain, Persian G-ulf.Telegram 'M' From Political Resident, Bahrain, To Forejgn Office, London. Telegram No. 279 Dated 9th December, 1948. i SECRET . Your telegram No. 277. Bertram Thomas is now here. He has apparently been instructed to inform Rulers that Shell are desirous of obtaining concessions anywhere including the Gulf Continental Shelf. I have asked him not to mention the Continental Shelf to any Ruler except Kuwait. 2. He is anxious to obtain information about other competitors for sea-bed concessions especially Americans. To what extent am I at liberty to give him such information?With the compliments of v the Political Resident. r^&lt;yv i ,r-)&lt;a*A. British Residency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. / (P *U-Telegram From Foreign Office, London. Political Resident, Bahrain To Telegram No. 334 Dated 13th received 14th December, 1948 SECRET * Your telegram No. 279.^' So far as we are a?/are all the areas excepting the Continental Shelf and the Saudi share of the Neutral Zone are already covered by existing concessions. We see no objection to Bertram Thomas discussing matters affecting these areas with the Shaikh of Kuwait, but in his relations with other Rulers we hope he will avoid speaking of the Continental Shelf. 2. Your second paragraph. Our view is that it is reasonable for us to keep interested British Cil Companies informed regarding concessionary activities of U.S Companies and we are generally keeping their London offices so advised, but are not betraying any information which would enable British Companies knowingly to outbid American rivals. It would however be a breach of confjdence for us to give any British Company information regarding the activities of another British Company. To ensure that our attitude in this respect is impartial we are not repeat not giving British Cil Companies any information about the activities of their British competitors. W f e feel that these should be the principles which must guide you in considering what information you pass on to Bertram Thomas./ &lt; vujf) /T' With the compliments of the Political Resident. British Residency, Bahrain, Persian G-ulf. . 19 ^.SECRET. The Political iigency Kuwait. 20th January, 1949. No. C/&gt;f (b/12) Will you please refer to your confidential slip 226/6/48 dated 18th December, 1948. 2. Bertram Thomas has seen the Shaikh who informed him that at present he had nothing definite to say regarding a marine area. He added that in tiie event of an area becoming available for grant of a concession he would inform him. H.E. Sir W.R. Hay, KCIE., CSI., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BAiIRhIN.PERSIAN GULF iiKSJDBNCY, JAHR/il N • 2Cth January, 1349• (115/4/49) Please refer ta correspondence endinj' with your telegran ^ o•334 of the 13th Dece&gt;ioer, 1948, about &lt;3ertra a Thomas. ^ Bert rax: Thomas arrived in daiirain at the end of the first week of December. He left for the frucial Coast on the 15th December and left there on the £3rd December by sea for rvuwait. He returned to Bahrain in the 20th January- and left for Cairo on the 23rd January. • Dn the Trucial Coast he renewed his acquaintance with the various Chaikhs and I understand did his oest to sin&lt;j the praises of ’ Bheir' as an oil company, but made no mention of cuf-shore oil. At huwait he approached the bhaiKh regar- iing the continental shelf of both Kuwait proper and the • eutral Zone and received a reply that'the Shaikh intended to put concessions xo^ ooth up to auction when the time .fas ripe and to grant them to the highest bidders. j • Bertram Thojfias was in bad health throughout his stay in the Gulf as a result of hi h blood pressure. ^ay be also interested to know that Yeightaan ^)ust been staying with me for a few days, lie came here iroi Kuwait where he talked to the Shaikh about his company's desire for a concession for off-shore oil and received an an swer that the door was still open and that he would oe infor- ed when circumstances permitted negotiations. The 3hai*h apparently said nothing to him about his proposed auction. a eightman reminded ae that he was still anxious to compete ior ^atar and Abu Dhabi off-shore oil and expressed so/ie an xiety about Bertram Thomas*/visit to the Trucial Coast/ 1 told him that to the best of my knowledge Bertram Thomas had not mentioned off-shore oil to any of the Ghaikhs. l * Dongrlgg was here at the aume time as jertraxa ThomaJ and .eightman and regarded both with a good deal of suspicion, de told ne that His Corn, any was not interested in off-shore oil in the Gulf on account of the Ked Line, but that he was taking steps to obtain from the Shaikh of &lt;*atar and the Trucial Coast Shaikhs lists of the islands and shoals which were re garded as belonging to them and covered by his Company*s con cession, so as to ensure that these islands and shoals with their territorial waters are excluded from any concessions which may subsequently be granted for off-shore oil. 3 asked Longrigg whether he regarded any of his Com pany’s existing concessions on the Trucial Coast as covering the sea-bed (compare para 6 of my despatch Ko.448-8 of the ^Ist February, 1948 to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for Co rnonwealth Relations), and he replied that he was doubtful ji t; is was the case because the word 'territory* in the con cessions was translated by 'Aradhi' (l.e. lands) a term which he did not think could be held as applying to the sea-bed. F * I am sending a copy of this letter to the British middle Last Office. a.A.o. Burrows, sq., Foreign Office, London. (Signed) W. R. HAY.(E 14671/1271/91) COilFrDKlTTIAl FOKEIjIT CEFXCE, S.’.V.1 9th December, 19i4-9. I have been told in very strict confidence by Mr. John Howard, whose firm have been carrying out construction work in Saudi Arabia for some time, that he is about to try to ^ obtain the concessions for the sea-bed off the Seudi-Kuwait neutral zone* He is proceeding himself to Jedda next week in order to try zo obtain the concession for the Saudi share and he is sending two members of his firm, including Mr. Soanes (who is incidentally a son-in-law of Ur. Churchill) to Kuwait to try to obtain the Kuwait share. His idea is to form a new company in which 25^ of the shares would be held by Ibn Baud, 25% by the Sheidh of Kuwait and 50^5 by his own company. The main price of the concession would be the free gift of these shares to Ibn Saud and the Sheikh. Howard is telegraphing direct to Jakins at Kuwait telling him of the proposed visit by Mr. Soames and his colleague and asking for assistance in approaching the Sheikh and also asking whether accomodation can be arranged. We have no doubt that Jakins will give all proper assistance, though without of course giving the impression that we have any particular reason to favour this company as opposed to any other that might seek the concession. We have not yet had time to study the implications of the proposal and shall be glad to have any comm nts which you and Trott feel inclined to send us. I am sending copies of this letter to Trott and Jakins. Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., Bahrain.Confidential Political agency, No.C/300(5/12) Kuwait. December 26, 1949 Dear Sir Hupert 2 Your telegram No. 515 of December 16. The Howard party duly arrived on the 17th and left on the 22nd. Captain Soames did not appear, rather to my relief, because the SheiKh has such a high regard for Mr. Winston Churchill ( of whom he has a signed photograph ) that it would be a pity for any one to appear desirous of making commercial capital out of it. Lord Fairfax came in Captain Soames* place and was accompanied by a Mr. Tippler. The latter was an engineer formerly employed in England by the Standard Oil. I gather that he served in the Ministry of Fuel during the war and he claimed to have had much to do with 'Pluto '. He gave an impression of competence and surprised me by saying that L.he Howard concern was fully able to undertake sea water operations. ( You will remember that Superior Oil claim that they are the only company able to tackle drilling in the sea ). 5. One declared object of the visit was to obtain a concession for the Kuwait share of the Neutral Zone continental shelf. Howard himself, I gather, was simultaneously tackling the Saudis for their share. Fairfax and Tippler were completely charmed by the Sheikh who received them most cordially and said he would convey his decision to them in due course. hen they as.^ed if they might call on him again the Sheikh said it was not necessary but they had a sub sequent meeting with Abdulla Mulla, the Sheikh’s political secretary. tacts with the Kuwait Oil Company and to sell equip ment to the company ( the discarded Howard equipment in Arabia I understand ). They were very well received and shown round by Jordan. Tippler was most impressed with Ahmadi and particularly with Mena al Ahmadi. He said that the scale of operations was an eye-opener to him and that the Persian Culf was obvious ly an area with a very great future. He regretted the waste shown by the Company’s burning gas products and suggested that Howards should form a company to bottle end sell the gas for commercial and private use. As he claimed and appeared to have intimate knowledge of this branch of the oil industry I encouraged him in his suggestion which might well solve many light ing, refrigerating and air-conditioning difficulties throughout the gulf. Tippler said that gas bottled in Le Havre was shipped for consumption in Algeria. 4 Another object of the visit was to make con- 5/ H.E. 3ir Hupert Hay, KCIE. , CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain5. Fairfax said that their company was entirely British and that if they obtained the concession they would try to bring in Australian interests. Consider ing thao Howards have already had experience of the Persian Gulf I thought that both Fairfax and Tippler were surprisingly ignorant of the general situation, particularly with regard to oil interests, in ohe Gulf. They assured me that they had learnt a lot during their stay here but seemed to be still pretty ignorant on gulf matters when they left. 6. In soiteof his youth Fairfax made a not un impressive concession-hunter although even with Tippler’s technical qualifications, they struck one as being a rather amateurish pair. 7. Of the firm of Howards you will xnow more than I. V/her I was in Bahrain I heard very prejudicial reports con their work in Saudi Arabia. I was told that the men they brought out lived in the most squalid conditions and their equipment was little better than old junk. What truth there was in this I do not .aiow but I gather that the firm left Saudi Arabia prematurely. 8. According to a lightly-disguised telegram from Jedda received for Lord Fairfax after his departure Howard seems to be fairly sanguine of success with the Saudis• 9. I am sending a copy of this note to the Eastern Department and to Jedda. Yours sincerely, H.G. Jakins</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000114_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/265</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000114</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/265</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 5/12 Concession for under-sea oil of Kuwait Neutral Zone'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-17T16:39:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (31 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 33; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence among various British officials in London and the Persian Gulf regarding the continuing negotiations on oil concession rights in Kuwait, and particularly the sea bed within its territorial waters.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Sea bed mining</topic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000114#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>