<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000169_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T05:57:11.373Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">-t CONFIDENTIAL. No.338-S of 1937. ; / © The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to S3 The Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents $)// A' V] / n V British Consnlate-Genera), BUSHIRE. Dated Reft rence to previous correspondence : Political Resident's Printed letter No.c/75 of the 12th April, 198 7. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Kote No. 145 of the 31st March 1937 from His Majesty'^ Minister, Tehran, to the Iranian Minister for Foreign Affairs, Tehran. Copy, without enclosure, 1. His Maj esty 1 s Subject. Seizure of a Kuwaiti boat by Iranian Customs authorities at Qusbah. 2. The Secretary to fo^wgpded,with compliments, tot Secretary of State for India, London.V the Government of India, External Affairs Department,Simla. 3. ’His Majesty's Minister, Tehran. 4. The Senior-Naval, Officer, Persian Gulf. 5. His Majesty's Ambassador, Bagdad. 6. His Majesty's Consul, Ahwaz.Jn any further communication on this ^ubject, please quote 7 fisi/f/. and address —not to any person by name, butr to— 0 No - /£ 2&lt;f3o // o any person by name “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, * - i i THE Under-Secretary of State Affarfs presents his ^ compliments to ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, r^\ transmits herewith cop Foreign Office, 193 y. of the under-mentioned paper. Reference to previous correspondence : -ti&amp;r -o. / -/;jery/ r / Description of E?iclosure. Name and Date. Subject.No.. ,168 r :j b 3 2 British Legation, 1 3 Tehran, April, 19 37 His Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of dhow 'Furat* Khoweiti Reference.- Te 2 irQr) despatch Ho. 101 of 14th tarch, 1937. Private letter No. 260/42/37 froci H.J. Seymour Ssquire (His Majesty f 8 Minister at Teliran) to Hie Excellency Monsieur Enayatollah Samiy (Iranian Minister for Foreign Affairs) of the 26th April, 1937. Copies also sent to: India No* 76 Bush ire No. 38 Kerman Ho. 13a../ U L. , English text of letter No* 360/42/37, dated 26th April, 1937, from His Majesty’s Minister to Hie Excellency Monsieur Enayatollah aaraiy, Iranian Minister for Foreign Affairs* Your Excellency will remember that I called on you cm the 16th March last (25th Esfand, 1315) and left with you a note respecting the arrest by an Imperial warship of the Koweiti dhow ’’FuratS? In the fourth paragraph of that note I also invited Your Excellency’s attention to the fact that no reply had ever been received to Mr* Butler’s note No* 438 of the 31st July, 1936 (9th Mordad, 1316), regarding an incident which took place on the night of the 14th ??ay, 1936 (24th Qrdibeheaht,1316) when an Iranian Customs launch fired without warning on the Koweiti dhow 'suhail* and seriously wounded one of the crew# 2* As I pointed out to Your Excellency , incidents of this nature cause a most unfortunate impression and arouse great resentment; and I m de the request that these cases should receive urgent attention and that strict instructions should be issued that Iranian vessels should refrain from any interference with Arab dhows outside Iranian territorial waters* 3* As almost six weeks have now elapsod since I left this note with Your Excellency, I am venturing to send you this private letter to remind you that my Government regards X, these incidents as possessing both great importance and great urgency* A most serious impression will be caused unless they are rapidly and satisfactorily settled, and I would therefore express the strong hope that Your Excellency will be able to furnish me with a reply to my note at a very early date* (Signed) H.J* Seymour*Seizure of the Koweiti dhow 'Furat M by an Iranian sloop. The dhow was seized off the coast of Cman on or about 25th January. The cargo consisted silk of which it was apparently intended to smuggle into India. It was released on the 28th February and all the cargo was returned except 16 piece lengths of silk. The Political Resident has suggested that H.M.Minister at Tehran should make a strong protest to the Iranian Government with a demand for compensation for the missing silk pieces.A /&gt; r w4T&gt;EX£ u 4 any further communii communication on tliis subject, please quote No - ^///^ ^/JSf / a/ and address— not to any person l(y na/ne,A)\s\ Xo— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.VV. t. f 2 6 9 6 indiaZdirect I . ^ THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to &lt;A&amp;Ce and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, affize 193./. / Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. if ,4 X Name and Date. | Subject. V yUc. _ vW W Pr ' • * ' Similar letter sent to 14-6130 14007 ( 4 )No • 1Q5 / t) * f' £ -m \ J * J } t 2 ~ 16th March 19S57* Sir, With reference to my deapatch o.lol of March 14th, I have the honour to report that I called on the Ministry of Foreign Affaire to-day and handed to him the note respecting tjne arrest of the Koweiti dhow ”Furat”,a copy of which was enclosed in ay despatch above referred to. 2 # After describing the incident to His Excellency, I pointed out that the action of the Iranian vessel appeared unjustifiable; I thought it well to add,as the Iranian authorities are no doubt aware of the fact,that it might well be that the dhow’s cargo was intended for smuggling purposes and that I had in fact heard that it had been hoped to smuggle the cargo into India. But even if this were so it provided no justification for the behaviour of the Iranian vessel. I added that these incidonts,if continued,(mist inevitably lead to some really serious incident and loss of life,and that it was really important that proper instructions to prevent them should be given. 2. Bather to my surprise Monsieur Saoiy did not con test the right of His Majesty’s Legation to make representa tions on behalf of the Arab rulers. He may however have been ignorant that this was the usual gambit for an Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs and may well raise the point in his written reply. He undertook to look into the matter at once and did not attempt,for the moment,any defence of the action of the Iranian vessel. 4. I sm sending copies of this despatch to the Foreign Secretary to the government of India ho.51,to the Honourable DM /theRMMMM political Reside at in the ‘ersian oulf Uo.22 anc to His Majesty f s Consul at Kerman Ho. 11. I have the honour to he with the highest respect, humble Servant,CONFIDENTIAL. ' £ n p t.. o &lt; j ^ &gt; No. 29J-S of 1937. V* JO/ n The Hon’ble the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1* ilia Majesty* a Secretary ot, State lor Ina ia, London# 7 2# Tne foreign Secretary to tne lioverraaent ot India mew Delnl# 3# Tne Senior flaval Officer,, Persian (iulf. 4« Tile Political Agent, Kuwait# 5# Tne Political Agent, Bsfcrain# and has the honour to transmit to him a copy documents (s). of the undermentioned British Consulate-General, BUSHIKE. Dated...??.^..^?.T®^..f.^7.T, Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed letter* ao*0/37 ot 19tn Marcn 1907. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Express letter .uOol9 of 6tn Marcn 1937 to nis Majesty’s Minister, renran, witn enclosure# ’ 9 APR Seizure of a Kuwaiti dnow by an Iranian sloop#Regarding tne Kuwaiti cinow seized toy tne Iranian sloop Consul , Aa ordered I proceeded to Lingaii Oy s.s• 'Baaiora* 1 on tne 25tn February, and arrived tnere on tne 26tn morning, Aa tne steamer was under quarantine, I was released from quarantine on tne 27tn. On tne same evening, I was informed tnat tne Customs at Lingan nad received instructions from Bushire by s.s.'Barpeta', wnicn called at Lingan on tne 25tn, to release tne dhow witn cargo intact, Tnis was done, i*ne cargo returned to tne ixaJcnuda was 130 bags containing 2b92 pieces Cnina silic, wnereas ne claimed tnat tne cargo was 130 bags containing 2606 pieces of cnina silic, and tnat 16 pieces were missing, out tne Customs mentioned tnat tney nad actually received from tne sloop 'Babr* only 2n92 pieces! ine dhow sailed for Duoai on Sunday tne 26tn February, towed oy a nired motor ooat, Tne following is tne statement made by tne naicnuda t* 'It was only naif an nour after sunrise itne actual date was not remembered by tne Naknuda) wnen the Fast wind was ratner blowing strongly wnicn made tne voyage difficult. We cnanged our course toward tne Knasab narbour wnere we intended anchoring to take snelter and $mA nad just passed 'Ras-a-Snaikh' and were about a mile^s distance from tne Oman Coast and about tne same distance from Ras-a-SHaikn as we could see tne people on shore. On noticing a sloop approacning us we instantly noisted tne Kuwait flag but tne sloop seized tne anow and towed it to Lingan after anchoring at henjam for tne nignt. me seizure of tne dnow was noticed by tne initebitants of Ras-a-Snaikn wno reported tne incident at Snarjan and Dubai,** During tne time of tneir detention at Lingan tney were given /- 2 - given a room in tne Customs and were under tne Amnion- guards* The Nakhuda on being questioned mentions tnat ne nad orders to proceed to (iwadur rrom wnere ne would get furtner instructions as to tne course ne ougnt to take. His manilest or 'Pass' as ne terms it, was issued by tne Customs at Dubai showing cargo as 'nil' on board. Tne following are tne names of tne individuals con cerned j- Kationality of vessel - Kuwait. Owner of Dnow Owner of cargo Snipper Naknuda Crew -- Ibrahim bin Abdul Aziz Motav a - lusuf din naarzooq. - Morsnid El O’Saimi - onulam bin Ali - 24 persons. I nad tne opportunity of seeing tne manifest issued by tne Duoai customs and actually saw tnat it showed tne dnow nad 'nil' cargo on board. Iusui Marzooq nad visited Lingan and stayed tnere for a day. Tne snipper Morshid nad also come to Lingan and was among tne crew until tne dnow left for Dubai. I again coniirm my opinion tnat tne cargo was meant to oe snuggled into Britisn territory. Bandar Abbas. 4tn Marcn 1937. sd. A.ueiladary.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. \ V' o u I COT3f idential ^ EXPRESS LETTER fAIR J ’ Thts is an ORlCTNAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary nuiU and is che,aper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it hid been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 300-3 of 1937. Dated x e *mri’ the xxxxxxx To XX 26th March, 19 *1. From To Reference ~~ my Political Resident, Bashire. His Majesty’s Minister, Tehraa• :no. 9 - 3 ./ Secretary of State for India, London* v The Foreign Secretary to the Gov eminent of India, Hew Delhi. Senior Haval Officer, Pers ian Gulf. I The Political Agent, Kuwait. bj' / ^ i The Political Agent, Bahrain, witn refei’ence to his letter ao.c/193-1.a/23 of 13th March 1937. His Majesty’s Consul, Kenwn. Subjecti Seizure of a Kuwaiti dhow by an Iranian sloop. Reference paragraph 4 of enclosure to Kerman Ex press letter Ho,15, dated the 15th February 1937,(Bushire Printed letter ^ ITo,252-3, dated the 24th February 1937). 2, The facts are that it is impossible for the Residency Agent, Sharjah, to garahtee the correctness of manifests as corresponding with the cargo alleged to be carried. All that he might do is to 1 attest the signature of tne individual signing the manifest** ^apfusst I IA 1 OFFiCt attested. ad. T.C.Fowle, Lieut.—Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. forHjecretaxy to the Political Resident in th. jPweian (WT^Synotare) S. 44. MFP—1374 S&amp;P—(11-2013)—15-1-30—10,000. {Designation)sort (E 2009/1359/91) My dear Lacy, X am sending you herewith toy tomorrow's bag &amp; copy oi a brio! aurnmory that BeiXiy hoa lafide l*or the ilinistor on his return of several outstanding cases in which the ; ersitux aithorities have interfered with jrab dhows, Tou mey find it useful in talk with Soheiiy -ind in other connections. fours ever, (signed/ heviie Butler.In view of the number of these o/ieea at present unsettled, a brief summary of them may be useful. 1* The ease of the Koweiti dhow Suhail’, which was fired on off Lingah on the 12th May !9o6, three members Within 3 mile limit. of the crew being wounded. Ko repl^ has ever been received to our note of protest dated 31/7/36 - paper 582/2/36. Our last reminder is £60/26/37 (the note protesting about the seizure of the silk-smuggling dhow). within ft* The case of the omani dhow which was seized off territorial waters as claimed by Bondar Abbas on 22nd October and releaeed on November lot. Iran. two rifles being retained. The action which we proposed to take is stated in 675/17/36, e telegram to Bushire dated December 18th 1936. fte deferred action ponding confirmation from Bushire that the crew of the dhow were kuscati subjects, Bo reply has ever been received from Bushire and we have said nothing to the Iranian Government* This case started badly with Mr jor Lincoln^ absurd delay over reporting, and it has remained slightly ridiculous. It seems rather doubtful if we can do .anything now. 3. The seizure of the koweiti dhow which was to smuggle silk into India. The dhow was seized off khnsaab on the 25th January and released on the 28th February, 16 pieces of silk being missing. 1 Mile off Arab tt'e protested in our note Bo*260/26/37 handed to Staaiy shore♦ by Hie Majesty^a Minister on the 16th March, 4. The case of the three Debui dhowa which were sailing to the Batineh coast and 2 of which wex*e searched near thekusoat territorial quo!no aloo on January iiSth. They wore not detainea. Oar Ini'ormation is now complete, r*nd we are ready to 1 mile rrom Arab onoro; doubtful whether Muscat or h as aalfehoimait waters. Doubtful protest, £57/9/37. 5* fhe Ouse of tne i&gt;ebai jolly-boat which was searched (? by the Chohrokh) on voyage Xrom Khassab to JDebai on the 16th February. Report oni^y just received - protest suggested, linked with 4* 581/1/57. 6. The case oi the koweiti sambuk eeisied at Qusbeh on or about February 8th when returning empty down the h &lt;tt filter cctrrying shingle from Subiyeh to Abadan. 585/1/57. Report only just recaivod. Further enquiries suggested, with preliminary note to Ministry of Foreign Affairs.CONFIDENTIAL. I @ r-,- ^ y ♦ The Hon’ble the Political Residen t “in the Persian Gulf presents his 1. Thus Senior HnTml officer, iereian uulf, 2* The political Agent, Kttifeit, 3 # The Political Agent, Bahrein* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). Political Resident's sprees letter no*3Q0~3 of, 26ta hareh 1957, (go*9-B to Tehran). 1. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India,London^ 2. The Foreign Secretary to tne Government of India, » tiff ice of the Political Heel dent In the Persian Gulf, Camp, Hwait. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated... xxsrxxxxxx xxxxxxxxxxxx xxxxxx Reference to previous correspondence: Name and Date. Description of Enclosure. Subject. oespatch o.lOl of the 14 th tfaroh 1957 fr m Hie Majesty's Minister, Tehran, to the Foreign office, with enclosure. Seizure of a Kum iti dhow tQr an Iranian sloop. Copy forwarded, with compliments,to* New Delhi. 3« His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. 4* His Majesty's Consul, Kerman.HO. 101 i:. / 2 '5 4 J 13 5 7 2-*. 14 th If arch, 1937. Sir, Xl5&gt; With reference to iny telegram Ko.9 saving of the 18th February,! have the honour to inform you that an unusually flagrant case of interference by an Iranian vessel with an Arab dhow ocourred on January 25th when a Khoweiti dhow was actually arrested within two miles of the Arab coast,towed to Lingah and detained there for a month. 2. The particulars of the case are given in the note,copy of which is enclosed,which I am addressing to the Iranian government. I had arranged to present this note personally to the Kinister for Foreign Affairs to-day,but His Excellency was at the last moment unable to receive me. I will,hovever,take the first opportunity in the next few days of presenting the note to him and drawing his attention to the very serious situation which is likely to arise if the activities of the Iranian naval vessels in the oulf cannot be controlled. in the meantime,in order to avoid missing the bag which goes to you to-day,l enclose as stated above,a copy of my note to the Minister for Foreign Affairs. 3. I am sending copies of this despatch to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India Ho.49,to the Honourable the political Resident in the Persian &lt;?ulf no.21 and to His Majesty's Consul at Kerman Ho.In. I have the honour to be with the highest respect.Copies to; F,0. IKDIA BUSHIRE KERMM ,0.112 p ^ 6 .9 f- ^ \ .9,. O ■? 07 v &gt; '’11th i'areh 9 1937. Monsieur le Minlstre, I hare the honour to inform Your Excellency that my attention has recently boon drawn to a serious case of interfere.nee by a ship of the Imperial Iranian iiavy with a Khoweiti dhow,flying the i howeiti flag,outside Iranian terri torial waters, fhe facts are as follows; 2* The name of the dhow in question is the Furat her nationality *howeiti. She is owned by Ibrahim son of Abdul Aziz Kotawah and her E&amp;khuda is ohulam son of All. On January 21th (1th Bahraan) the dhow wae bound for Owadur with &amp; cargo of 2192 pieces of silk 9 paeked in 130 sacks, the property of Yusuf son of isurzook. About half an hour after su rise the dhow was maxing for /assab Bay to take shelter from a strong easterly wind. After passing Rue Gheikh fcahsud and when about a mile distant from the shore,the oiiow which was flying the Khoweiti flag, was stopped by an Iranian sloop,believed to have been H.I.M.S. Babr,and was towed to Lingah. The arrest of the dhow was witnessed from the shore, on arrival at Lingah the cargo was landed and the dhow and crew were detained at Lingah until /theth« 28th February ( { ith when the cargo was returned,except for sixteen pieoee of ulljc which eoula not be traced and the dhow was released and left for 5&gt;abai. 3. Your j xceilaaoy will obeerYe that the cuiow was yeissed not only many railes outoide Iranian territories but aetually within two uJLlea of til© Arab coast. I am eompolied to make to your Excellency a strong protest at the action of the Iranian warship coneernea,and I have the honour to request that Your excellency will be so good as to cause a strict enquiry to be made into the circumstances of the seizure,and instructions to be issued for the immediate return of the sixteen missing pieces of silk and for the payment of compensation for the loss suffered by the owner of the dhow through the detention of the vessel for over a month. At the same time I have the honour to remind your Excellency that on July ^lat 1936 (9th Kordaft 1315), rr. Butler BdcireeBeC to you uot. (ito.tjjg) V«^ardia&lt; th. inolBeat which took pitee on the ;iif&lt;ht of til. X4th May 1V36 (24th Orditseheeht 1216) when tui Iranian customs iau. ah fired without warning on the . howeiti dhow '5;uhall' and seriously wounded one of the crew. iso reply hasoeeti rooalvod to that lUiilcauion. b» I m confidant that Your Kxc alXeno/ will appreciate that incidents of this mature Kmat inevitably cause a iaoat unfortunate i ipreBsion and arouse great resentment• I am sure also that the imperial oovernAent are as anxious aa are His Majesty^ aovernment in the United Hag&amp;a* una the Oovernment of India,mat any such incidents should be avoided. i have therefore the honour to request that tne oases brou^xt to your ^&gt;xcellenoy , s notice ciay reoelve urgent attention.aud that strict ix^s true lions may be issued that Iranian vessels should refrain from any interference with Arab dhows outside lrarJ.an territorial waters. I avail myself of this opportune ity to renew to your .xcellency the aesura ce of my highest consideration. (Sinned) £♦&lt;?. say^ our(E ^89/1559/91) Telegrcm (en clalrj from ‘ r. aeymour /iehran)* D« By Mg) 18th Februai^yt 1^57* H* 15th m*fo 9 1957. Ho. 9. Saving, / Addressed to Bushire Ho. 11. Your telegrams *oa. 25 and 25. — ■— / ifv * It seems clear from Bandar Abbas telegram Bo.6 that dhow was smuggling. But if it was seized outside Iranian territorial waters, l agree with you that protest will be desirable. in on the other hand seizure took place within three-mile limit off Hen Jam, as one report received by Consul, i ersaaa, would suggest, no protest can of course be made. First step therefore seeac to be to establish accurately position of dhow when seized. There are at the moment four conflicting reports on this. 2. From enquiries made of inistry of Interior It seems certain that Ciagah Is not In German Consular district, as agreed by Iranian Gover meat, but In youraT In any case I much doubt whether Lincoln would be given any facilities by local authorities, except on instructions from Tehran, and I am reluctant to approach Ministry of Foreign Affaire till we are more sure of our ground. Xn olrcum tanees I think beat coarse would s be for his interpreter to go to Llngsh as soon as passible and X ' am telegraphing instructions accordingly. This would not pre/ elude request f r facilities for Lincoln to go there later circumstances seem to warrant It. repeated to a.M.Consul, Kerman (at Bandar Abbas) Ho.5. Copies by b»g to Forviftn Office. Kja.y -.aTUur. and to Qoverr of India Mo.B saving.To f/inister, Tehran. r • Copy by Air Kail to India Office. „ P.A. Kuwait. Copy giren to Goyernment of India.) Para.2 of my telegram of 6th larch. Seizure of Kuwaiti dhow. Grateful if I could be informed whether you have seen your way to making the euggeoted proteat. COLONEL FOWLS AND N BRANCH. mi ENCLOOURE IN INDIA F r .RY 3 j f\ Uttar D it- 18 'W ; f/ A ,.1937CONFIDENTIAL. No. c/37 of 1 937# r -I ) A - ' 1 ^ H i The Hon’ble the Political 'Residbbt in the Persian compliments to lo Hi8 MHje8t;y , 8 Secretary of State for Lonctou# nlr bresents v-kis 2* fne Foreign Secretary to tne ixovemment of India, £ jaew Delni* 3# Tne Political Agent, Kuwait. 4* ine Senior Officer, Persian clulf, h.M.S.Bideiord. 5. His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman, at Bandar Abbas. 6. Tde Political Agent, Bahrain* and has the honour to transmit to him documents W Office of tne Political nesident in tne Persian tiulf. Camp, BAHRAIN* a copy of the undermentioned Dated...Iptn.^rqn,.. 1937., -V’ Reference to previous correspondence: Political Resident’s Printed letter i*o*C/27 of tne 8tn Marcn 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Telegram no*24 of tne I6tn . Marcn 1937 from His Majesty’s Minister, Tenran* Seizure of a Kuwaiti dhow by an Iranian slo op. /CONFIDENTIAL.; No. c/21 of 1*37 C/21 of 1*37. .* (.■•( )&lt; &gt; I O vV O \ The Hon’ble the Pc litical| §b$jjd 9 it in^the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1* His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London* 2. Tne foreign Secretary to tne (rovemment of India, flew Delm* 5. Tne Political Agent, Kuwait* 4* ‘fne Senior Officer, Persian uulf, n.M.S. Bideford. 5* Tne political Agent, Banrain* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned British Consulate-General, BUSHIKE. Dated.... To (l),(2),(3) &amp; (4)* Residency Printed letter ao. 270-S of 1st Marcn 19d7. To( 5)* Residency Printed letter flo.2d2-S of 24tn Ji’efarifetry 37* documents &lt;//./ Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Bandar Abbas telegram flo* 11 of 4tn March 1937 to Tenran# Seizure of a Kuwaiti dhow by Iranian sloop.CONFIDENTIAL. No- 252-S of 1937. litical lls l % J (A ' | '—J 193/ 31 The Hon’ble the Political P&amp;jsM^ht m the ^Persian Gulf presents his compliments to !&lt;, His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London, 2. Tile Foreign Secretary to the Government of Ijjdia, • Hew Delhi. 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 4. The Senior Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S«3ideford. 5. The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). 2* To Bahrain only. The Hon’iile the Political Resident will discuss the last paragraph of the sub-enclosure with you on his impending visit to Bahrain. &lt;f * // i&lt;( / y British Con ulate-Genersl, BIJSHIKE. Dated....^ 1 .^. f! etiruary 1937 Reference to previous correspondence: To(l), (2) ,(3) &amp; (4). Residency Printed letter Ko.235-S of 20th February 1937. To( 5) Residency Printed letter Ho.20 4-S of 13th February 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Express Letter No. 15 of the 15th February 1937 from His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman at Bandar Abbas, to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran* with enclosure. Subject. Seizure of a Kuwaiti dhow by an Iranian 31oop.•rr -• Copy. Confident i&amp;l. EiCPRESS LETTER. ( I ♦ f v #• i i Prom - Britconsul, Xerman, at Bandar Abbas. To - H*M.’s Minister, Tehran. Repeated to Britconsul, Bushire. Ro. 15 . Ro .14 T. Bated at Bandar Abbas the 15th February 1937 Subjects Seizure of Kuwaiti dhow by Iranian sloop. Reference my telegram Ho. 6 and 18 t o Bushire. I forward, herewith, for your information further report referred to. sd. C.H.Lincoln, Maj or, H.B.M.’a Consul.Kuwaiti dhow seized by the Iranian Sloop 'BABR” near Quoin Island (Salamah). Consul. For your confidential information, I beg to repprt the following, which I heard from a reliable friend of mine who was going to Muscat by the s.s. M BARALA M * 2# The dhow in question belongs to Yusuf SI Fahad Al Marzooq of Kuwait, who has a branch at Karachi and whose agent at Diarah (Dubai) is Murahid Al F’Saimi* She was loaded with 120 gunny bags containing 4,200 pieces China silk with her manifest showing M Nil M cargo on board, intended for smuggling into British territory. The fact is that the Nakhuda had instructions to land her cargo at a fishing village called 'Charnah M near Karachi, where transport would await the dhow’s arrival and take the cargo into British territory and then the dhow would continue her voyage to Karachi, and, in order to satisfy the Customs Authorites there, her manifest showed cargo on board as 'Nil”. On her way near Quoin Island (Salaxnah) the sloop M Babr M met her and thinking that the cargo was intended for Persian Gulf coast, she seized and brought her to Lingah. Usually these sloops when they come across dhows, ask for their manifests, and if they are not satisfied with the contents thereof, then only they search the dhows to see if they have ary contraband goods. 3. There is some ulterior motive about this case. 4. The main point at issue is whether dhows leaving for India from the Trucial Coast generally have their manifests signed by the Residency Agent at Sharjah, or does he issue any certificate ? If the reply is in the negative, I may add here that the Residency Agent is quite awar e /2 - aware of these arrangements, as the Residency Agent’s (Mr. Abdul Razak) clerk at Sharjah named Alii Al E’Saimi is his brother- in-law and a relation to Murshid Al E’Saimi, the shipper and owner’s agent at Dubai# Bandar Abbas, 14th February 1937. Id# A.R.Or.CONFIDENTIAL. f No. 270- S of 1937. f~ ‘ ' x j Vv’ V./ VX \^ r\ \Oi^y \ The Hon’ble the Political Evident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1» his Majesty's Secretary or State lor lnai&amp;» i^onaon 2. the Porei^n secretary to tne Grovernnent ol India, hew Delhi* 3o The Political Agent, Kuwait* 4. The Senior Ofl icer, Persian liull, h.M.S.Bideford. / and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents I mi 1 a British Consulate-General, BUSHIKE. Dated. 1st March, 1937* Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed letter ho.202-h of 24th February 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Bandar Abbas telegram ho 9 of the 26th February 1937 to Tehran. Subject. Seizure ol a Kuwaiti dhow by an Iranian sloop*Telegram q# From Consul 9 K at Bandar Abbas* To h.*Me *s Minister, Tenran. isto*9 # Repeated Political Keeii ent 9 Busnire. iio.23* Dated and received tne 26tn February 1937. Bushire telegram wo.33. Interpreter lelt yesterday ior Lingan ostensibly on a visit to relations. My explicit instructions to nim were i'irst to see and interrogate crew as to exact position oi' dhow wnen seized secondly endeavour to examine dhow*s manifest tnirdly ascertain wnetner dnow was flying flag wnen seized. ne did not anticipate being faced witn any difficulties as ne formerly was a resident of Lingan and ne Xnows practically all tne people tnere and is on friendly terms witn Iranian ofiicials especially tne police* Britconsul.m c l / t :j M,* pjU? si CONFIDENTIAL. No. 235-S of 1937. 1 ' 1 ,2n vww , 13 / The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1« His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London, 2# The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi® 3. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 4. The Senior Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S.Bideford. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). -— x y ■b British Comulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated....^?.?.^..?. 6 .^.^^. Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed letter No«226..S of 19th February 193 7. To(2),(3) &amp;(4) only* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. • Tehran telegram No*11 of 19th February 1937 to Bushir e. Seizure of a Kuwaiti . Political Resident’s tele- dhow by an Iranian sloop. gram No. 33 of 20th February 1937 to Tehran. pc! 15 MAR 1937 y- OFFICE jTelegram From Political Resident, Tkiehirrr From His Majesty's Minieter 9 Tehran* Ko* 33* Repeated Hie Hajeety'e Conniil, Cerman at Bandar Abbas. by Iranian authorities to Interrogate crew ./hicn seems un likely his report will prooably make us no surer of our ground than we are already, and in any case some delay must result before his report is received. the Incident outside Iranirn territorial w&amp;te e, which is the point at issue and later report from Consul Kerman vide his telegram 80 .4 of 11th February corrected hi a previous report of the incident having taken place off Henjam, Government be possible especially as Iranian author!lies appear to have an uneasy conscience on the mat er vide Bandar Abbas telegram # 0.7 of 18th February 7 Such an approach would serve to elucidate Persian version and might also, by showing that we were watching tne cnug, have a deterrent effect against any savage action against tne crew of the dhow under the Smuggling law. No. 248. Hated the 20 th February 19&amp;7. Your telegram 11 of 19th February. Unless special facilities are given to interpreter 2. Three out of the four conflicting reports place Would not a tentative approach to the Iranian Br itconsul. - —CONFIDENTIAL. No. 282-fl of 1537. rsian Gulf presents his 1. Sanior Officer, Pere iaa Gulf, Deptford. 2. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 3. The Foreign Secretary to the Gorernment of India, Sew Delhi. 4. Hla ^ajeety’s Secretary of State for India, London, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents British Constalate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 17th February 1937. Reference to previous correspondence: /6?r. Reeidency Printed letter Ko.216- : of 16th February 1937. ^' Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Political Residents telegram 'Io.2d of the 17th February 1937 to Tehran. Seizure of a Kuwaiti dhow by an Iranian sloop. POL B£F 15 MAR 1937 . INDIA OFnrCONFIDENTIAL. 193/ j The Hon’ble the Political RSSfJent m ttie Persian Gulf presents his compliments to !• Tfta Senior officer, Persian Gulf, H. .U* Dept ford* 2. The Political Agent, Xu^rait* 3. The Foreign Secretary to the Ooreriwent of India, Ne*e Oelhi. 4. Hia Ilajeaty’s Secretary of state for India, London. ^ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dafced *-*-x^t‘V**‘ehTU'‘f'j**!**' 7 Reference to previous correspondence: Reaiuency Printed letter Xo«214-3 of 16th February 1937. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Bandar \boas telegram ^o.6 of 15th Februery 19 &gt;7 to Tehran. Subject. Gei^ure of a Kuwaiti dhow by an Iranian Sloop.1Q 7 yram To Hepoated to iolltioal iooldont, iiuehlre* m. 18 Dated 15th reotlved 16th ^‘ebruaiy 1937, to-day aa follows*- Owner of dhow Is Yheuf el Fahd al Marzook of uwait who also h^a busineaa braiich at r irachj. 311k which waa packed In 120 sacks, not In bale a, and contained 4,aOC pieces was shipped fr&lt;» Jaurah (Dubau) by rueuf *s a;ent narned Pur- ihere was either tea nor su^ar on boaxti, wakhuda-s iastwuctioue v/ere to land silk at ilshlius village oharnah near Karachi where it would tie net by/transport and snuggled into British ^ err itory, Jhcw was to oontiiiue the voyai^e to Karachi• Ohow’a manifest showed cargo as nil on board to satisfy customs authorities at nraohi, Iraniaii sloop stopped dhow examined manifest whioh allowed cargo nil searched aud discovered silk so concluded that it was intended for -giing into a Persian dulf port seised aiiu took her to Liiigah* Jti port ant My telegrstt Jfo«5 (No. i? to BuahlreX. &gt;iummaiy of further reliable report motor Report being sent by poet Brit consul1937 i Tel^ram q. from iML 9 § Con«ul # Kernant at Bandar Abbaa To H.M.’o Minioter, Tehran So.3 Repeated Political Resident, Bishlre. *10.17. Dated 13th received 14th February is&gt;3' Your telegram So.2. Paragraph 2 of Buehlre telegram So.21 to you. 1 am prepared to proceed to lin^ah but is TV vie it there mi^ht be regarded as interferenoe. 1 would not be given any aeaietanoe by loeal author it lee and in all probability crew would be prevented from seeing me. There la no telegraphic ootwriunioation at ^ingah. this consular interpreter who has several of his relations there. He ostensibly could be on a visit to them and easily obtain all information. It tfaa he who reported this incident to me. Could copy of Butler’s despatch *»o*4ol of October 1st to Foreign Office be sent to me please 7 J^ingah in Kerman-Bandar Abbas Consular district 7 If not In theee circumstances I suggest that 1 send Britconaul.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 2G&amp;- ' of 1937. The Hon’ble the P compliments to l s ent in the Persian Gnlf presents his 1. The iienior officer, Pere ian Sulf, H.iil.O. Jeytfora. 2. The political A«iewt f Ku4pait. 3. The Foreign Secretary to the GoTernaent of India, Haw 'elhi. 4. His J&amp;ijesty’s Secret xy of State for Indi*, London and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). 1 British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.... IJtn reoruary igs? Reference to previous correspondence: Heaidency X^inted letter Wo. 190-s of 10th February 1937. Description of Enclosure, 1. Name and Date. %*ndar Abbaa telegraju ifo.4 to Tehran, of 11th February. Political No.23 of Tehran. Re&amp;ident’* t 13th Fehruc*ry ele^rar 1937 to Subject. Seizure of a Kuwaiti dhow by an Iranian sloop.Telegram q* ?rom Consul, Minister, Tehrau. Ho.4. Abbas. To Repeated -olisioal 'evident, Buehlre. Ho. 16 Jated and received 11 th Febru«*ry 1^37. Important. ^ ^Uprees letter Ho. 11 of February 3rd Ho. 10/T to BueHire. Latest report received to-day is that dho« sailed from Xueait and was bound for G*adur and wae seised off Jaslraq .1 sal amah (one of quoins Islands). Bri toons ul.CONFIDENTIAL. 190-1 of 1937. 1937 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Senior officer, Persian Ouif, JLif. ‘eptford. 2. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 3. The Foreign Secretary to the Oovernmor t of Ind i&amp;. 4. Hia lajeety’a Secretary of ^tate for India, London. New i&gt;elhi and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 10th February 193 7 Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. 1. Express letter No. 11 of 3rd February 1937 from Tis n $a j ea ty' a Cons ul, Car man , at 3andar Abbas, to Tetiran, with enclosure* .'eixure of a Kuwaiti dhow by an Jr«n ian sloop* 2. Political Resident 9 a tele gram ^o.21 of 10 th February 1937 to Tehran. iCopy Jonf o n r* D 0 □ , 1937 j jtxpa ::y : - ?roa - Hie Hajoaty^ Consul, Ksra»n (At 3?\ndar Abbas), To - Hia Majesty’s Kinioter, Tehran. Ho.U. lepeated Political Reaidsr^t in the Persian 3ulf, :?• • 10.T. Dated at 3&amp;odar Abbas, 3rd February IW?. Bubjecti Seizure of a Kuwaiti dhow by an Iranian sloop. I forward, herewith, for your information, a report which I have received from a relit ole source regarding tne seizure of a Kuwaiti dhow by one of the Iranian sloops. sd. C.H.Lincoln, Major. H. B.M. * s Consul, &lt;ermn.■ (937 r eport r«ctiv«d on tho 2nd r&gt;J«rrdin* til seizure of h Kuwaiti dhow cy an Iranian eloo,.«* Cn or abjut 1iVi« 25rd J&amp;njary one of the Iranian eloope (believed to be the *V^P') eeieed a Kuwaiti dhow near Hen Jam which ehe towei into Ling ah anvi handed over to the Iranian Author it iee at that ^©rt. One report aaye that the dhow was seized while anchored off Henjaa t and another that she was seized when under tail about 17 miles to the south of Henjam* The dhow had a cargo of about 160 bales of chins silk and abo it 30 packages consieting of tea, granulated and loaf sugar, on board, which she was carrying from Karachi to Kuwait. Ae the men were regarded as a muggier* the cargo has been landed at the cuetoms house at Lingah* The dhow and the crew which aumbere about 17 souls are being kept at Lingah under ?olice surveillance pending investigations.^ PA. kail m * ‘ * Hu,In any further communication on tins subjecy please quote, No. f — and address —not to any person syt*1/35i/v r- jT- son by nam», but to— I j » J. !MD!A DIRECT @ 'he Under-Secretary of State, ,, Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. j a q f) / O U o THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^6^. ^ ^sy~ q jI-y and, by direction of the Secretary of State, vJ' transmits herewith cop v of the under-mentioned paper. y Foreign Office, , 193/44a r~ O U ^ c. British Legation, Tehran, 3rd September, 19 37 His Majesty's TepreseAtative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of the Koweiti Sambuq. 'Hibat al Karlmi** Referenee:- Despatch Wo. 74 of the 3rd September, 1937, from His Majesty^ Minister to O.K. Caroe Esquire,C. I.E., Acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copies also sent to INDIA No. 157 BAGHDAD No. 71 S.N.O. No. 385/14/37.^jT S: V jKjS •; \l The boat was seized on or about the 8 th February. Q,usbeh is an Iranian customs post on the Iranian side of the Shatt-el-Arab, but the river forms part of Iraq territorial waters. The Political Resident has suggested that His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran should protest to the Iranian Government and ask for the immediate release of the dhow. % ^ Hr (/\y CLcu^vy* ’■l.U-'fo) ' * IT 2P‘- (V.IND1A?DIRECT n any further communication on thiisubject, please quote no. sjzr/ / /strf 7i(. and address —not to atiy person by name, | bin f6 — “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. O Q O v • £ 'J KJ , ^3 7 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to '£&amp;*.*&amp;* and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^y of the under-mentioned paper. /1 Foreign Office, , iosX J S' Reference to previous correspondence : JuJU ^ tz ■ Mr,/y4 ^ ! /«+ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^ w. /u- ^ j0 - /Lf-S. as.COMFIDSNIIaL No.C/116 The Politis;a.l_Agency, , KUVVMJp-r Dated the 5th February,_1948 * tJ * , Sub.iect: - Interference with •Ku wait dholvs ■ir dear Sir Rupert, In pursuance of your verbal instructions I have informed His Highness that the Iranian Government have denied the accusations of the Kuwiati nakhodas against their gunboats and have suggested that the nakhodas concerned approach the Officer Commanding the Iranian Navy in Khorramshahr for redress. 2. The Shaikh replied that there was little point i in their doing so as the chances of their obtaining redress were negligible and added that he hoped the fact that complaints had been lodged by His Majesty 1 s Government would be sufficient to prevent a recurrence. Yours sincerely, Sd/- M.P.O'C Tandy. The Hon’ble Lt-Colonel Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN% No. jUU 476 I f x7s HIS Majesty’s . ,4 ** presents his coiuplimenTs to v HI 8 i.|_ and has the honour to transmit to him documents. at Tehran ajcBty’a principal the under mentioned Secretary of tate for ¥\ • British rrtbaeayv ..Tehran# Reference to previous correspondence: 2Tth noTwrb#r 194 ? PA- 441 Description of Enclosure. Name aud Date. Subject. Copy of note Ho* 6803 frora Iranian Ministry of foreign Affairs* Interference with Kuweit I&gt;howa* — 3479 a 25019—2 (4)COii From: Ministry of Foreign Affairs, To: H. B. Embassy, Tehran. No. 6802 lift ted: 16 th November 2904 Tehran. The Imperial Ministry of Foreign affairs present their compliments to H.B.M. Embassy and with refei*ence to their note No. 467 of the 16th Aban 13^36 (5th November 1947) about the detention of the Kuwaiti dhows, have the honour to state that the Ministry of Var have written to say that at the time of dealing with the complaints received from the Embassy the dhows mentioned in the Embassy’s note were not in Ehorramshahr. The Ministry of War have therefore requested that the owners of the dhows may be instructed to approach the Officer Commanding the Navy in Kherramshfthr so that if the complaints of the owners of the dhows are found to be true the guilty persons be prosecuted and punished* With regard to the dhow which had sugar on board, the k.F. a. have to state that the Central Customs Dept, have considered it to be of smuggled nature and it has been seized by the Central Customs Dept, in accordance with the relevant regulations. The Central Customs Dept, hove been requested to tai&amp;e speedy action in dealing with the case. H3M Enbassy will, of course, be informed of any result which may be obtained./ &lt;9 SB£L tiO« 457 * )/L4$ &gt; O * British Krabaasy, Tehran. 4th Novenjber* 1947. Hia ^ajeaty’s ^ibaeay present their ooinpliKients to the imperial Ministry of Foreign Affaire and have the honour to state that the competent British authorities have furnished the following particulars in respect of the incidents referred to in correspondence resting with tne note Ho* 2875 of 24th July, addressed by His i£xcel.i.ency U. Homayunjah to His Hajesty*© Ambassador; (1) The dhow stopped by an Iranian naval vessel north-west of Kharg Island was the , Himr # f Kuwait Registered :o* 618 which is not equipped with an engine. (ii) Particulars of the two dhows which were stopped by an Iranian naval vessel on 18th March are cis follow^; — (a) 'Mutairan'', master Ahmad al Fahad, 85 tons, Kuwait Registration Ho. 143, carrying cargo of timber and split bamboo; (b) 'Uosasd', master Abdul al Tura, 80 tons, Kuwait Kei istered No* 475, carrying cargo of wooden ribs. Both craft are ocean-going two-masted booms without auxiliary power* 2* In addition, it has been wrought to the notice of His Majesty’s Kctoassy that in Marcu, the Kuwait dhow 'Tarrad” with a cargo of sugar and ghee was intercepted by an Iranian patrol launch and towed to Bushire where she has been detained for no less than six months. His Majesty’s Embassy have the honour to request that the Ministry may be so good as to arrange lor an urgent investigation of this matter, in order that the dhow may be released without further delay. /a. •. *.A -a. e &gt; c J ^ M.Homayunjah that the^o^s* i'-i Hla ^oellency direct to the Irani™ MkvI? -V* question should refer it is considered by the con et«nt U ’t£??f*i.** - horranahahr, . that in a matter to which Hi! “‘horities considerable iwwrtano* the^iJ^iff?* a i ? over? ‘™ent attach capital should at o^l be ^ aut horitles in the complaint. ..t the same I«2 t£? 1 £?.'f legitimate he h^py to forward copies of the pr^ent 8 ^^!* 7 ? 1U and of cortriunications which thev mi, ? 1 oorre epondence occasion to addrese to the ImnSi.f 7 su ? 8e&lt; iuently hove Affairs to His Majesty*! rn^ni 1 ? 1 ' lnieti y foreign transmission to the Irani t “h° rra!Ile hahr for post. Iranian naval headquarters at thatCONFIDENTIAL Mo.1707-S. 9ocr Mr^\ *4} Tlie Hon’ble the Political Resident in ' Persian Gulf presents his compliments to - His Majesty's Secretary of State for u/' Commonwealth Relations, LONDON , * The Political Agent, Kuwait . and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 1st October 1947. Reference to previous correspondence: C.R.0. : Tehran printed letter No.275 July 30th. Kuwait: Kuwait Agency letters Nos.C/627 and C/628 dated 22nd September 1947.Telegram From S .4 EXT o ' &gt; 7 i * i i (CYPHER TELE afcS - o.t.p . - SECRET) Political Resident, Bahrain. To H.M*s Ambassador, Tehran. Copy by ( Commonwealth Relations Office, London, bag to ( ( Political Agent, Kuwait. No.1013. ^ated the 30th September 1947. Your printed letter No.13 July 30th. INTERFERENCE WITH ARAB DHOWS. 2. Motor dhow mentioned in para 2 of Persian note is not repeat not identical with craft concerned in incident reported in para 2(a) of my telegram No.513 April 26th. Kuv/ait dhow encountered vras M Nimr M registration No.618 and is not equipped with engine.^ In statement recorded last April master stated he had heard from crew of Persian vessel that they had left Khorramshahr that morning. He may have been mistaken over the date. 3. Para 3 of Persian note. Following are further particulars (a) ''Lutairan' , Master Ahmad al Fahad, 85 tons, Kuwait registration No.143 carrying cargo of timber and split bamboos. (b) 'Musaad 1 *, Master Abdul Wahab at Tura, 80 tons, Kuwait registration No.475 carrying cargo of wooden ribs. Both craft are ocean-going two masted ,, booms ,, without auxiliary power. 4. Dhow mentioned in my telegram No.557 May 3rd is still detained in Bushire. Grateful if her release could be secured. 5 . Procedure suggested by Persians for reporting cases of interference is not likely to secure speedy redress and I would therefore prefer to continue present procedure. - GALLOWAY -From;- Mmi3try of Foreign Affairs, (Third Political Department), TEHRAN. His Majesty's Ambassador, TEHRAN. No. 2875 Dated: 24th July, 1947 . M. I'Ambassadeur, In reply to Your Excellency's letter No. 272 dated the 22nd May, 1947? in which several points were raised regarding interference by Persian naval vessels with foreign khows on the high seas, I have the honour to offer the following observations j- According to the information which the Ministry of Foreign Affairs have received from the competent authorities no Persian naval vessel stopped any dhow in the vicinity of Kharg Island on the 11th March of the current year. It is however reported that on the 21st Isfand (12th March, 1947 ) the Persian naval ship M Simurgh ,, moved out of the Shatt-el-Arab, and about 8 miles outside the Shatt-el-Arab met a Persian motor dhow which was coming from Eushire with a cargo of fruit. As this motor dhow had no rear gear and as the sea was rough she collided with the M Simurgh M and sustained slight damage. Concerning the second part of Your Excellency's letter I would point out that no description is given of the two dhows which you state were searched in the neighbourhood of Bandari Tahiri. Nevertheless according to the information which I have received from the competent authorities the officials of the Customs Department and the port officials warned all dhows which were in the port of Khorramshahr that the Masters of any dhows which may have been searched on the date of Your Excellency's letter should report to the official sent from Headquarters so that their representations and demands may be investigated. Only the crew of dhow No. 372 belonging to Abdul Vahab, son of Abdullah of Kankan who were taking a quantity of charcoal and firewood to Basra have reported in the manner indicated. The Master of this dhow, named Isa, son of Jasim (identity card No. 2046 issued at Kankan) has stated that no harm was done to them and that money was paid for the goods purchased from the crew which were on the dhow's cargo list and which were purchased by some of the crew of the Persian naval vessel and some customs officials, by agreement on both sides. For these purchases a sum of 2,280 Rials Wc?s paid and a receipt obtained. In making these facts known I request Your Excellency to give me the number and other particulars of any other dhow which may have been involved in the incidents referred to in your letter so that further enquiries may be undertaken and a settle ment arranged. At the same time I should be glad if Your Excellency would cause instructions to be given that the dhows in question should also refer direct to the Persian Naval Headquarters at Khorramshahr so that their complaints may be investigated ana the necessary action taken. I avail myself of this opportunity to renew to Your Excellency the assurance of my highest consideration. Sgd/- Muhammad Ali HumayunjahEXT 1 33 FOR lor FPI'” 9 . . 1. 1st Jul/, 1947* (E 5579/66/91) SECRET f iy-ctu- fairtLJsO, \XZo •bout Persian interference with British protected Arab dhowa* 2« Tehran Embe&amp;s^ have no objection to your instructions of the 26th October* 1936 being confirmedp and we should be glad if you would now do so* 3* 7e think that if* despite the representations which have been made* Persian ships continue to inter fere with Arab dhows, it might be useful to warn the Persian Government of the orders given to His Majesty' ships* I enclose a copy of a draft despatch to the Ambassador on this subject and should be glad to know if you concur in its terms* 4 I am sending a copy of this letter to Harrison at the India Office* Yours Sinoorsly (L.F.L* Pyman) •» G.C.B* Dodds, sq, Admiralty*B 5572/66/31 MSSS* Sir J, lo Hougetel f i • C# - • • ^ I • G» Tehran* Copy to:- Mr. Dodds, Adnairalty* Ur* Herr is can, India Office. I have to refer to Y.S* f s despatch No* 174 of the 27th May, 1947 concerning interference by Persian naval vessels with British protected Arab dhows, and to inform you that the Lords Conmissioner of the Admiralty have instructed the Commander in Chief, East Indies that their instructions of the 26th October, 1938 (the text of which was contained in Foreign Office despatch No* 345 of the 3rd November, 1938) concerning the protection of vessels of the Arab Lheikhdams under British protection are to be regarded as still In force and are to be carried out if oosaslon arises* 2* If, despite the representations wihch Your Excellency has made, Persian Naval vessels continue to molest British protected Arab vesais outside the three mile limit of Persian territorial waters, it might be desirable that thePersian Government should be warned of the instructions which have been given to H«M» ships* You are according ly authorised to inform the Persian • * Government of these instructions at any time when it may appear to you to be advantageous to do so* 1:j3&amp;. No. 174- I’ r' . ■ O l\o‘ 2&gt;o 5l H1 s Majesty’s Ambass^cjor at T^hrejn _ r _— presents his oompliments to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary State for Force :n Affairs and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Embassy, TEHRAN .-W, 1947 Reference to previous correspondence - F.O, letter E3393/66/91 of 10th May, 1947- Desci-iption of Enclosure Name and Date Sub j e c t ?*&gt; Note No. 272 of 22nd Hay, 1947 to Iranian Mini;try of Foreign Affairs. Interference by Persian Naval vessels iTith Koweit dlec^/SeBrltlah rnbuasy, 9kT9J*» 28ndr^ayr'i947. on*l«ur X« s?tnl»tr# I hav« th# hoA4dr to lr»o^ th« in or ?%aiiin. Xy frequent practice of Inter ference by Iranian naval veeaeXa with Kow-iti and other Arab dhowa, ax&amp;d to refer in particular to two rscant cases of such Interferons:* whidh have b^en brought to th&lt;? notloe of t^ls llaj*sfcy , s f overrent • 2* is majesty 1 * loverna^nt ars informed (1) that on tbs Ilth arob on* dhow was afcoppe - at a polr mllea Korth «eai oi the ialano^y^ an .-.ranian naval vessel which oatiaed serious damage in oozing alotg aids. It appears that 'Jfcie boarding party failad to boar! the dhow owliif to heavy seas; (2) that on tha 18th i arch two tihowa wars stopped by an Iranian naval vessel 18 sdles from the near&lt;s at point of the Iranian eh ore in vicinity of Sabiri* Both these di owe were boar tad and searched* a few artlels# were stolen and in each caa^ a aun of Rupees 1,000 was demanded, although this dhews were eventually released upon payment of a small levy. 3. X ar-i to poi; t out to Your ,acalle*ae| that the dhows concerned in these inai- d-ints, sP'ieti were returnimi to howeit from India, were flying the flag of kowelt and were stationed well outside Ir&amp;uian territorial waters when ih*y were intercepted. X am therefore to ask you to be so good as to arran* e for 1 tha issue of instructions to Iranian haval veasels not to Interfere with foreign dhows on the hl i: s^aa. • I am further to aphasia** that this practice of a tapping fCovaltl and otner Arab dhows on the M# aeaa is likely to lead only to constant friction which It ia the earnest desire of Hi a Sajcsty'a (■overament to avoid. 4. i ateall be fateful to receive four xe^llcncy’s assurance th*at adequate Ftfiasure* will be tak^r by the co patent tasperiai authority to prevent a recur- - u ce •v'' 5 I POHEIGK OfFICS, S.»?K 31st May, 1947. (B 4193/66/91) Secret fl. 19 on (KJSjS •w. 1 ' &amp;-~b--€L^so t Will you please refer to your letter of the 14tti May about the Persian interference with Arab dhows. fa are consulting Tehran about the desirability of endorsing the 1933 instructions for the protection of Arab vessels. With regard to the Incidents referred to in the first two paragraphs of your letter, you will now havo received a copy of Baxter’s letter to the .v basoador 3393/66/91 of the 10th May. Youf* Sincerely G«C* 5. Dodds, Oso., Admiralty. mAdmiralty, S.W.1. Whi* 9000 Ext. 808. l+m, 1947. Jfy dear Pyman, you will ao doubt have seen telegranKa Iff. ff/144 of the 12th ifK April and No. 5^3 oif the 26th April from thfe Political Resident in the Persian Gulf td the India Office reporting interference by a Persian Naval gunboat with Kcweiti dhcwrs. 2. The Political Resident has suggested that the j ersian Government should be asked for an explanation of these incidents and you will no doubt let me knew if such action is being initiated as a result of the suggestion made in the first paragraph of Harrison’s letter Ext. 989A7 of the 8th May. 3. In the meantime the Senior Naval CtfYicer, Persian Gulf, has asked whether, if these representations prove ineffective, he is to regard the instructions which the Admiralty gave on the 28th October, 1938 for the protection of Arab vessels of the protected states against Persian interference on the high seas and in Arab territorial waters as still in force. Tou will find a copy of these instructions 2&gt;o in your file (Hie India Office reference is not clear ^7-from our files but P.2.2970/37 “ay give a clue). 7 w. 4. Subject to confirmation by you and the India Office that pbhwc the Arab states are as much under our protection now as they were then, we feel that we should continue to give this assistance and that in auy case not to give it would affect our prestige in the Persian &lt; ulf • Tou for your rart will probably feel that in spite of our improved relations with the Persians and our efforts to rehabilitate their Navy, we should now allow them to maraud in the Gulf. 5. We should like your agreement to our endorsing the 1933 instructions. We hope of course that it will be possible to stop this illegal behaviour by diplomatic neans. I am sending a copy of this letter to arrison. Yours sincerely. G. C. B. DODOS L.F.L. Pyman, Esq*, Foreign Office, London, S.W.1.V r-T ■ w r bOUKIOl J XO-., 3. .1. (liaD9S/66/9l) nwraafTiAL. &gt;/ v ill you please refer to the Poiiiiicai HoSldent, Persian aull’s telegram N o,515 o f the ^7th '‘-pri 1 so ut two cases of interference by^ersisn naval vessels with Koweiti dhows* It would seeirt that both these incidents occurred outside not only the 3 ‘nils linit of territorial waters which we recognise, but even the 6 mile limit which the Persians elai i. ye should be grateful if you would bring these incidents to the notice of the Acting Minister of Foreign Affairs or of the Prime Minister and ask that instructions should be sent to Persian naval vessels not to interfere with dhows on the high seas outside Persian territorial waters# You should point our that if the Persian naval authorities persist in stoooing Koweit and other Arab dhows on the high seas, this ie likely to lead to constant friction which it is our earnest desire to avoid* By Persian territorial waters we still mean, of course, waters within the three mile liait, but there would be no point in getting involved in a fruitless argument with the Persians on this point. I am sending copies of this letter to the Political Resident c^d to senior Naval Officer, Persian C-ulf* Sir John Lekougetal, • • *G*, •C*, Tehran • (C. • Baxter)■■ issued at Hmran originally for 1500 bags of sugar but later clurrally altered to read 1284 bags sugar and 68 cases tea all consigned to Koweit*. Master of Vessel has failed to report to His Majesty’s Consul-G-eneral although (? invited) to do so* Bushire customs have reported matter tc Tehran a 3* There is no evidence whether interception took place in territorial waters or on high seas but it seems probable that vessel was engaged in smuggling* In the circumstances I do not press at present for any particular representation to be made regarding the incident*The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. His Majesty* s Secretary of State for India, LONDON.' 2. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, NEW DELHI. 3. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. V*ILD and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN. Dated the 29th April, 1947 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of enclosure : Number and Date Subject Telegram No. 514, dated the 26th i 1,. ;.1947, f r om the Hon*.bie '''the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Persian naval interference with Arab dhows.33/105. L From To Telegram S. (A). Political Resident 9 Bahrain. H. M f s Consul General f Bushire 514. the 26th April, 1947. No. Dated i In continuation of my telegram No. 513, Following report received from Political w * An Iranian patrol /MMX launch is reported to have intercepted on high seas the Kuwait dhow Tarrad, captained by Salman Abdul Latif and owned by Abdul Latif Mohammed Thunayan and towed it to Bushire. Its cargo of 1,200 bags sugar and 400 packages ghee consigned from Lahej to Kuwait were confiscated and sold. Exact details not available as craft has not yet been released but incident probably occurred in the first week of March.” Agent, Kuwait. Begins t Have you any confirmation ? Ends. * HAY * G.A.Mjfi** ^ U !i&lt;5b^EJiNMENT 0F1NDIA, W PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, Department. BAHRAIN. EXPRESS LETTER INDEXED n [N.B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] CQNFILEBIIAL From POLITICAL RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULF To HIS MAJESTY*S SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA, LONDON. No. 763 - S. Dated the 29th April, 19&amp;7. Correspondence ending with my telegram No. 513, “ 65 dated th e 26th Ap rils—1947. 2 . I presume the Admiralty instructions forwarded under India Office printed letter No. P.Z.7331, dated the 29th .COA. October, 1938, still hold good. T 2 T. 3. Please confirm. Sd. W. R. HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ATTESTED for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf• S. 6. MFP—1407 S&amp;P-(M-2339)—25-5-37—300,000.,m.*+ . LI. : ^ ■ , 1 mm mm, lUf ■■W’.- M ' *%' HI HI INWARD TELEGRAM t ~\ o H c&gt; fJ . v J “ 'lix l*® oase ttie coiarflunicat/ion^of 'tbs dont/Cntis of tiliis •nt^o^on/yperson orr^«id« British or tfilSv ftorernm&amp;nt Service is authorised, it must he paraphrased)* Allot ted to External Department* ll j ■—■11 m I w »■&gt; Cooiea to ; - pem.US* I&gt;epy*US« Apst.US’s* US.for Burma* Asst .US; for Bums* PSTto S3 PS.to US. PS.to Parly*US. Mr. Turnbull * Mr* Joyce* Resident Clerk* GYPHEE (O.T.P.) Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Secietary of State for India Tehran and Bushire, copy to Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf 0 Bahrein, 18*00 iiours, 26th April 1947 07.15 hours, 27th April 1947 X tt- tfu Prom To Repeated to Dated Received \ No.513 . My teXegr«n -p hl* iftt.h. interference by Persian Naval vessel with Roweit dhows* 2. Following are details of- incidents as given by Masters of vessels - (A) On March 11th one Oh ova was stopped 30 miles North-’ I W« 8t of Kharg Island* by Persian naval vessel which caused serious damage 11 in coming alongside* &lt;T)v‘ Boarding party failed to board dhow owing to heavy sea* (B) On March 18th 2 dhows were stopped by Persian naval vessel 18 miles from nearest point of Persian shore in vicinity of Tahiri. Both were boarded and searched* A few articles were pilfered and in each case a sum of rupees 1,000 was demanded but dhow was eventually released on rupees (?S 0 ) being paid* All dhows concerned were returning to Koweit from India and were flying Koweit flag. 3 * I would suggest that these incidents be brought to notice of Persian Government and that they should be / asked for an explanation ywfLo p/l. (M*- t ^ Sr- tl * kINWARD TELEGRAM f EXT ^/foJ (If ,in any case the communication of the contents of this document to any person outside British or U,B. Government Service is authorised, it must be paraphrased*) A llotted to External Copies to :~ Perm* US. Depy\US. Asst*US 2 s* US. for Burma. Asstolie. for Bui*ma. Department. PS. to SS. PS. to US* PS. to Parly.US. Mr. Turnbull. Mr c Joyce?. Resident Clerk. CYPHER Prom To Kept. to ' ; : Dated Received T/144» Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Secretary of State for India Tehran and Ser^ i tie. Naval officer, Persian Gulf Wa i'lth P April ? 947 e&gt; Portishead 18,52 hours, 13.15 hours, 12th April 1947 ^ . P 0 !- 1 '-i Gal ^.gent .Koweit rept;rts that complaints have been received ot interference by Persian naval vessel with Koweit sa3ling craft returning from India on high seas on three occasions during March. He is.collecting detailed evidence an 1 will if necessary (? telegraph) further on receipt of this. ™ An-nn i A ),+^ k ^ aa - Wh0 vi ' s ^ te:d Kho:r Q^wai recently reported that n April -,th F ,j rs^an naval vessel Nairo accompanied by two smaller craft wa^ stopping sailing craft between Lingah and basiau ^i*e* presumably in Persian territorial waters) and enquiring about their cargos. /C . JU+vaA**- * h / is Cm**' laM**- Do ■ vipz—31at 1 &amp;roh 1937 _iG. 143 1^73/37) i onsieui' ju* Kirdstre, X hiiVe the honour to Inform Your Kxeollency that X hay* learnt that on or about the 3th February (19th B»hman} the Iranian cub toms authorities at usbeh seised a Kowelti Bambuk t nafued the ^fibat al ^arim^and that,a» far as I am aware,this boat is still detained at uebeh. ^he tacts In this ease are as follows; 2. The bout has been engaged for some ti e la carrying sand and shingle from ho we it to Abadan. vhen seized,the boat had recently ta*c«m a oa. go of shin^e to Abadan and was returning empty down the river. She was carrying fcoweiti nation ality pa -era # a .a wan flying the Kowelti flag. The usjdxiiAa of the boat.whose name is I’uhiimad bin Husein and the four meabers of the crew are all Iranian subjects. The homes of some of them fire at usbeh, and the boot therefore went to cuebeh in oruer that they might see their fa«ailies. tfhen the boat arrived at usbeh,she was boarded by a Custom* official who detained bar on the ground, that aha belonged to tha 2 ?akhud&amp;,an Iranian subject. The K&amp; iiu&amp;s. protested and proved by the boat*® registration His ixcelleacy, t oneieur aiayatollaii sasaiy. Minister for Foreign Affairs,//r. papers that sh« was of Koweiti nationality hut the Custoiae official 2 xev«rtheless Infiisted on detaining the boat and obliged the liakhuda to give a security for Hiale 6000 pending a settlement of the case. available,the exact position of the boat when eelzed is not altogether eleer. I asa oaueing further enquiries to be made, and it may be necessary for me to address to Your hccellency a further note on this point# Meanwhile I desire without delay to draw Your 'xcellenoy , » attention to the seriotic loos and inconvenience suffered by the owner of the boat through her detention. K© question of any Customs offence would ap ear to arise, since the boat had come from Ibadan,where she had delivered her cargo,and carried no cargo at all at the time of seizure. Her nationality pa pers appear to have been in crder.and I therefore find it difficult to u derstand why she wae detained. I shall be grateful if your l^ccellency will be so good as to make immediate enquiries into the reasons for the boat's detention,and if no adequate reason can be found,to cause Instructions to be Issued for her release. I avail myself of this opportunity to renew to Your Excellency the assurance of W highest consideration. from the information at present t i,^.a.) a.j. b .Ygrr-COi Y. (E 2009/1*169/91) r;» &lt;389/2/37 . I BRITISH L GATION» TEHRAN. .^7th M rch, 1937. My de^r Lacy, I am sending yon herewith by tomorrow's bag a copy ot a brief summary that eilly has made for the minister on his return of several outstanding cases in which the Persian authorities have interfered with Arab dhows. You may find it useful in talk with oheily and in other connections. Yours ever, (signed) Nevile Butler H. L* Baggall?*y squire, The Foreign Office, LONDON. S. r • 1.1 Mile from Arab shore; doubtful _ . whether :,;u 6 ca 1 r ebruar% y by the Chahrokh) on voyage from Khaesab to Debai on the 16 th or Ras'*^* khaimah waters. Report only Just received - protest suggested, linked with 4. 381/1 37. Doubtful 6 . The case of the Koweiti s mbuk seized at Qusbeh on or about February 8 th when returning empty down the dhatt after carrying shingle from Subiyeh to Abadan. 385/1/37. eport only just received. Further enquiries suggested, with preliminary note to iniatry of Foreign Affairs.* f Jplt'ny further communication on iliis subject, please quote No - e~2oLS ' f / and address— not to any person by jtame, bur \p — “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. 2 6 9 5 .! Q THiii Under-Secretary of State for fore i gn A ffairs presents his compliments to ^ ijfcid and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, '' t/fe* J/ , 193 /. Reference to previous correspondence : 6Xce / J Z / //. '■'Description of Ericlosure. Name and Date. Subject.NO DISTRIBUTION. Decode, His Majesty's Vice Consul (KHorramshahr) 6th April 1937, Do R. No:- Savingo 15th April 1937, Addressed to His Majesty's Representative Tehran No. 4. Tehran uelegra ; i o. 24, Koweit dhov/. 2. I have interviewed Nakhoda who states that for the last seven months he has been in partnership with Koweit owner to carry sand to Abadcni, profits to be divided between owner and Nakhoda» Two months ago dhow w r as ashore at Gusbah being cleaned customs official accused him of buying a foreign boat without an import licence or paying duties. Customs refused to recognise partnership ana took guarantee of 600 tomans, 3. Customs have now ordered return of boat to Koweit and are cancelling guarantee. Repeated to Political Resident Persian Gulf, copy by post to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and Foreign New Delhi, His Majesty's Representative Bagdad, Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf,Telegram From Political Resident, Buahire, at. Bahrain. His Majesty's Minister, Tehran* Copy by post to H.M's Becretar, of State for India, London. Government of India, Foreign and Political department, New delhi. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Political Agent, Kuwait. H. M * s Consul, tevr&amp;z . H.lvi’s ^ice-Consul, Khorramshalir. No. 1/33 Dated 12 th April 1937. tCONFIDENTIAL. No. c/44 of 1937. O R 0 9 ^ The Hon’ble the Political kesid^nt in the Persian j A '• / compliments to • ■ 3. 4. b- His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, TJae Foreign Secretary to tne Goverrment of India, New Delni. His Majesty’s AfliOassador, Bagdad. Tne Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Tne Political Agent, Kuwait. {t' presents his iih London. / and has the honour to transmit to him a document //y Office of tne Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf, Camp, KUWAHT. copy of the undermentioned Dated.. . 6t , n . Reference to previous correspondence :.V!* 4fP r GOVERNMENT OF INDIAN Department. Jj\. / • 1800 | 1957 } Conf ident ial* EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B •—This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more ecpeditious t /an the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated^ on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sate time and to obviate formalities it i« drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a \esponsible officer of the Department^ No. C/25 of 19o7. Dated To xx xxxx xxxxxxx 7 th ;^rch 37. From - political Resident, Bushir e, • at Bahrain, Office of the political Resident sim1a the Persian G If, New Leiki ’ Camp, Bahr a in. ■ 4rjt 1 &gt;q - Hie Majesty’s Minister, Teiran. Repeated Secretary of State for India, .London. Reference Government of Ind la, hew Deini. His Majesty’s Ambassador, Bagdad. Senior Officer, Persian (Hilf, M.M.S.Bidelord* political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty’s Vice Consul, Knorrarasnanrtwtthout enclosure) • Subject: Seizure of a Kuwait boat by Iranian Customs Autnorit ies at ^usbea* I enclose herewith a copy of a letter x&lt;o*c/B7 ol &lt;snd ^ March 1937 from the Political Agent, Kuwait, on the above subj ect. 2. Ausbeh is an Iranian Customs post 0 n tne Iranian aide -o of tne 3hatt al /jrab, but the river forms art of Iraq territorial waters. It would seem therefore tmt the Iranian Custoias authorities had no right whatever to seize the dhow, especially as it had no c*irgo on board, 3. I venture to suggest therefore that a protest be addressed to the Iranian Government asking for the intnediate |17MARt93£ ‘PiA €&gt;FFl€ wit —ii m ''mr**** release of the dhow Att est ed . ad. V.C.i'owle, (Signature) L i eut. - C ol one 1, Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf • S. 44. MFP—1374 S&amp;: ftzfr Secretary to the Pers i an Gulf. (Designation) Polit icalNo* c/87 1800 rli Palitical Agency, Kuwai t» e 2n&lt;i March, 1957. !937 From - captain G.S.de Gaury, MC*, Political Agent, Kuwa it • To Tne non’ble tne political nes ident in the Persian ault, Busnir e. Sir, I have tne honour to forward a translation of aletter received by me from the Ruler, reporting tne seizure by the Iranian Customs at Qusben of a Kuifle-iti sailing boat, which was engaged in carrying sand from Kuwait to Abadan. 2 . I enclose in tabulatef form the information as required under instructions contained in yoir letter no.c/143 dated 29th March 1934. 3. From these particulars it will be seentnat tne boat, at the time of its seizure, was carrying its nationality papers to show that it was a Kuwaiti owned and registered boat and was also flying its Kuwaiti flag although the naiaiuda and its crew xzjb were Iranian subjects. 4. I also enclose for information a copy of the statement of one of the crew who came back to Kuwait to give news of the boat’s detention to the Kuwaiti owner. He is returning to Qusbeh where the naknuda and remainder of the crew still are. 5. If you see no objection, may steps be taken to nave tne boat released and tne amount of security refunded as the owner, a Kuwaiti, is being put to financial loss through the detention of his boat. 6 . I am sending a copy of this letter to His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Khorramsnanr, for information. I nave tne honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. sd. li.S.de uaury, Captain, Political Agent, Kuwait.Translation of a letter no*R/b/401 dated tne 24tn February 1957 from His Excellency tne Ruler of Kuwait to tne Political Agent, Kuwait* After compliments, I beg to inform you tnat tne Sambulc called 'Hibat al Karim', no.478, belonging to Ibrahim bin Ahmad bin Ibranim, which is engaged in carrying shingle from Kuwait to Abadan, was caugnt at ^usben on her return journey from Abadan by tne Iranian official who demanded from tne Sambuk customs dues* The naknuda told tne ofi icial that he had no right to demand anythin from a sailing mol craft carrying a Kuwaiti flag and papers but tne oil icial would not listen to him and kept some guards on tne beat. rhe boat was empty arh nothing dutiable was in it to give cause to the official for complaint* I would be grateful if you would kindly give this case your favourable consideration and have it represented to the authorities concerned* Usual endiggoParticulars of tne incident in taoulated form* The Sambuk was detained on or about btn February 19 37* Seized at qua ben* Name of vessel 'hibat al Karim'. Nationality of vessel Kuwaiti. The boat was flying Kuwaiti flag* Nationality papers carried. Nakhuda Muham&amp;d bln nusein 9 Iranian subject* Crews- Khalsif bin husein, Iranian subject. Shaban ' Husein Yusuf • Anmad All ' husein No passenger on board. No cargo carried* Sailed from Kuwait ab out 3 months ago.Statement of KJialaf bin nusein one of tne crew. ithalaf bin Husein an Irani and one of tne crew wHo brougnt tne news about tne detention of tne bambuk states tnat about tnree montns ago tne SambuJc left nere witn a cargo of sand for Abadan® After di scnarging tier cargo tne Sambuk returned to Subiyan where she again carried shingle for Abadan# As some of the crew nacL tneir families at qua ben the Sambuic went to tnat place in order to give a chance to the crew to see their families^ On arrival there the Customs official came on board and detained the Sambuk on the ground that it belonged to tne aaknuda wno is an Iranian subject and not a Kuwaiti. The haknuda protested and snowed the registration papers of tne boat to tne ofiicial but he did not listen to nim. Ttie Kakhuda has given a security for jt is.600 as security for the boat pending settlement of tne case.Outstanding \C&gt;ho w Csg os . *it*iin d mile 1 Its it* In view of the number of tneee cases et present unsettled, &amp; brief summary of titem m'*y be useful. 1. The case of the Koweiti dhow Viuhail ’, which was fired on off Lingfth on the 12th tf.y 1936, three me-nbers of the crew being wounded. No reply Ussever been received to our note of protest dated 31 V36 - p^per 682/8/36. Our last reminder is 260/26/37 (the note protesting about the seizure of the siIk-smuggling dnow; 2. The ctise of the Omnni dhow which was seized off Bandar Within territorial waters as Abbas on 2 nd October and released on :;oveober 1st., two riiies elsimed by Iren. 1 Mile off Arab shore. being retained. The action which we proposed to take is stated in 676/17/36, a telegram to Buohire dr ted December l^lth 1036. *e deferred action pending confirmation from Bushire that the crew of the dhow were Muscati subjects. No reply hrs ever been received from Bushire »nd we have side nothing to the Iranian Government. This case started badly with M*Jor Lincoln’s absurd delay over reporting, and it hr^s remained slightly ridiculous. It seems rather doubtful if we can do anything now. 3. The seizure of the Koweiti dhow which was to smuggle silk into India. The dhow was seized off Khassab on the 26th January end released on the 28th February, 16 pieces of silk being missing. fee protested in our note J 1 ©. 260/26/37 handed to ciaaiy by His majesty’s inister on the 16th March. 4. The case of the three Debai dhowa which were sailing to the Bat inch coast snd 2 of which were searched near the quoins Muscat territorial also on January 26th. They were not detained. Our inform tion waters. is now complete, and we are ready to protest. 237/9/37. * The case of the Debsi Jolly-boat which was searched (7 6.1 INDEXED In any further communication on this subject, please qu )te ^ *° ebfz3JI&lt;+l5 *1 and address —not to any person by name, bit to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Qffice, Londoi, S.W 1 to • M ( ° THE Under-Secret.ary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his J JNo.JIQ. 44 g... ( &amp; 8 a/ 8 /^ 6 ) E- 658 ^ &lt; P. Z. i|l9 OCT 1938 7587 ! riti$h Legation, Tehran, 3rd October ^36 //$ Hi^ Majesty^ Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Firing on a Koweiti dhow by an Iranian launch near Ling ah Referenee:- io&gt;' Tehran despatch Wo,412 of September 2nd. Wote to the Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs Wo.582/8/36 Of September 30th.British legation, 30th September,1936. jgo.5B£ (68&amp;/8/36) j|o iBieur le Miaiatre, I haY6 the honour to inrite your Kxcello/loy , 8 attention to the foot that I have not yet received any reply to fifty note $o«4£8 of the 31st July last (9th tfordad 1315) regarding an incident which occurred on the 14th fcay last (£4th Ordlbehesht 1315) when an Iranian motor launch fired without warning on a yeweltl dhow off Llngah and three members of the crew were wounded, h. I am confident that your Excellency will appreciate that this inoideut has made a most unfortunate impression,and I should therefore be very grateful if Your Excellency would be so good .s to Inform me of th. result of the enquiries made by ths Imperial OOTernasut at your ear Hast convenience. I avail myself of thle oppor tunity to renew to Your excellency the assurance of ay highest oonsidoration. (Signed) Revile sutler. His '^xcellenoy, yonsieur Enayatoll&amp;h naraiy, Minister for Foreign Affairs, fKKXAJUIn any further communication on thii subject, please quote so-erii't Iu* q{ an address—wo^ io any person by ntme, but to “The Under-Secretary of State,” Fofeign Officej London, S.W. 1. I SI THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to J and, by direction of the Sec/etary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under=menH^ned paper. r \ i resents his O'/' i Cn-tc, L ITT Foreign Office, ■ £% , 193 ( 5 . icmS 7011 Reference to previous correspondence/: znc^. jyv 30 tr&lt;k VCL UUL Ko. 2 . (z&amp;syfsC Description of Enclosure. I Name and Date. Subject. 'S-Ttto'i d^cr-uj l6Uv \k ~° S £P] h Similar letter sent 14—6130 12343 (2) &lt;0 .412 BiyrameMyn: (582/5/36) E 5§T7 - 19 -w His Majesty's Representative His Majesty Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies ni 56 mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the suijebt of ! 7011 Firing on I5hot7 “by Iranian Launch ne l Lln£alu J Referenee:- Koweit, Teliran Despatch No* 382 of 31st July, 193G, Note from His Majesty’s Legation to the Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs, No* 481 (582/5/36) of the 2nd September, 1936* Copies also sent to: INDIA No. 204 BUSHIRE No. 67 SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER No. 582/3/36.— a Copies to:- F.O. Ho.412 IHDIA Ho.204 Bushire Ho.67 S.N.O. B^itlBh Legation, 2 nd. September, 1936 HQ. 481 (5B2/3/36). Kia tlajeety’a legation present their compliments to the Imperial Ministry of Foreign Affairs and hare the honour to enquire when they say expect to receire a reply to Mr. Butler’s Hote no. 428 of July 31st last {9th Mordsd 1318) in regard to an Incident which took place on May 14th last (24th irdihehesht) whsn an Iranian »otor-boat fired without warning on a Kuwaiti dhow in ths neigh bourhood of Lingah.vf' - CONFIDENTIAL. 0 138 - - j . /i ^ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Oharge d* Affaires, Tehran. His -Majesty's Secretary of State for India, Icndcn The Foreign Secretary tc the Government of India, Simla The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, The Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). F- R ^ 7 u o i.. / Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. damps Shiraz. L. o a \ w v.’ u : Dated 26thAagu-3t 19'36. # \ iSe * '■ ^ ir. V. U-- J -is ri fj a Y\\% Reference to previous correspondence: Political Resident’s Express l»etter No. 4 -B/ 573-8 dated the 10th July 1936. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. .Express Letter No. 71-1936 dated the 1 st August 1936 from His Britannic L. a j es ty’s Consul, Kerman. Firing on a Kuwaiti dhow hy an Iranian launch near Lingah.Ocpy cf Express Letter Nc* 71-1936 dated the 1 st August 1936 from His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Kerman, to the Hcn’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject:- firing on a Kuwaiti dhow W an ' Iranian Launch near Lingah* - CQ97 i . J / Beference your Express Letter No* 4-B/673-S j dated 10th July 1936. The only information which has reached me in regard to the incident is as fcllcws:- Iranian Naval Motor dhow No. 1 attached to the Customs Department at Lingah, which was under the charge cf MAHNAWI I Mahmccd Iskandary, was returning to Lingah after visiting Maqam to bring Mirza Ahmed Bardcli (Jfcidir cf Maq.am) to Lingah, as he had been transferred to Bushire. 2 . Just after sunset, and when about six miles from the land, the Motor dhow sighted the Kuwaiti dhow and chased her, and as she would not haul down her sail, the dhow fired to make her stop. Two or three cf the crew are reported to have been wounded. The Customs inspector cf Lingah Hassan Kccsah (a Bushiri) was also on board at the time. This offi cial has now been transferred to Bushire. 3. I also hear that the incident was not reported by either the M a hnawi or the Inspector to the Customs authorities at Lingah when the Motor dhow returned to that port.No ?8? (582/2/36). J ( 95 AUG 1936 British Legation, Tehran, 31st July, 193° . His Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Koweit, Firing on Dhow by Iranian launch' : neap Lini;ah. 619^ jw W S C/vJ \ Reference'- Express Letter from Busiiire to Secretaiy of State for India* ife; 573 - S of 10/6/36, Note from His Majesty’s Charge d*Affaires to the Iranian Minister for Foreign Affairs, No. 428 (582/2/36) of 31st July, 1936. Copies also sent to: INDIA No. 188 BUSHIRE No. 63 SEIIOR NAVAL OFFICER No. 582/2/36.British Legation, Gulhek, 31et July, 1936# BQ» -taa (682/2/56). Monsieur le lllnlatre, I have the honoui* to in form Your ixoellenoy Uaat I hare learnt that on the 14th (ay last (34th Ordibehesht, 1315) an Iranian motor boat fired vithout warning on a Koweit-dhow in the neighbourhood of Lingaiu Ihe facte of this case are as follows!- 2. the dhow in question le named the *&amp;ihall' and bears the number 273 Koweits she is of the type. The owner of the dhow, who was not on board at the tide of the inci dent, le itahamiaad ath-Tfcanayan of Koweit, The nakhuda is named Ibrahim ibn ;ihayi'r, and the dhow had a total crew of 23, The dhow was on her way from Hombaasa, :2aet Africa, to Koweit with a cargo of wooden beams for Koweit, and carried papers of owner ship and manifesto from Mombaasa for the cargo. Her laat port of call /before His iaceellency Monsieur nay a to 11 oh Satsiy, Minister for Foi-eign Affairs*—I • (g) hi® thigh and shoulder* for which he la now receiving treatment at the America iosjital at ISowelt. the sea the motor launch came alon^reide the diiow* The na cauda asked why he had been fired upon, and was told that it was because he had not lowered the sail* He pointed out that no warning or orders to lower the sail had been given and proteated at the action of the launch crew. He was at firat ordered to pro ceed to hlngah, but while throwing a cats* on board the dhow, the crew of the launch shone an electric torch on the dhow*a stern and caught sight of her registration number, 'They then asked to what country the dhow belonged, and being told to Kowelt, said that the dhow might proceed on her voyage. The launch then left the dhow to proceed. £&gt;• It should be added that it was too dark for tne crew of the dhow to be able to see whether the launch was flying any flag, or whether the launch crew were in uniform. lor was for them to gather any detail* or tne j launch or its crew, ho member of the launch wont on board the dhow. All that could be noticed wua that the crew of the launch spoke Persian, with the exception of one man who spoke Arabic hen the sail had fallen into /withwith • Bftsrcui accent. 6. 'The Ohow later oallftd at #Ia j Ieland f where the nakhada aadc enquirlea about the launch. But he eo»jl4 diecover aeither its uaae /u&gt;r number. He wuc however informed that the captain was ont Mamoud from Buehlrft. Tite dnow tiien sailed direct to Xomlt. but owing to continuous contrary winds, she did not arrive there till the 13th June (23rd Khordad, 131b). T. l am confident that Your loceeileney will agree that this is a most unfortunate case. A trading duov. proceeding on an ordinary commercial voyage, with all tier zmpere in order and stiowing her lights, was fired upon without any warning whatsoever, and furthermore, the firing continued al thou ;h toiedlate steps were taken to lower the dhow's sail. That the captain of the launch knew that his action was unjustified Is clear fra* the fact that once the nationality of the dhow was known, he did not make any atteapt to search her for contraband nor to take her to an Iranian port for examination. Aa it was, three Innocent persona were wounded, and it was only by good fortune that no lives were lost. I fear ttmt this eaae will make a moat unfortunate&gt;, ' r .— • i • i i, Inpresaion and I th*refor« timro tim honour to rsq^oat Your .wjellenoy to too ao good as to can a© an Imediat© and seareniag enqnirjr to to* made, and to take »t*j&gt;a to a© cure that strict orders art itsautu to the &amp;GiamB concerned ifiilch shall «n«u3?t t)mt there It no repeUtlon of such oocurrenee in I avail m/eelf of thie to renew to Tour xoeUenoy the assurance of ay higheat aonsicieration&lt; (fiigtted) 30 Vlie Butler*GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. /V&gt; -Qpftfia ert lal. EXPRESS LETTER Department. 3C 11 [N.B.-rai» w an OHIO INAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditions than the ordinary mait and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended tb be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of « responsible officer o f the Department.] 4~B/573-o # Buehire # . ^ Timta 10th July J ; , /, No. Vo Xrom • To Dated ----It., the Kao ltdtii' 6 Political Keeldent 9 Bnshire# j w w U r v— i H1 * Hojesty's Charge d'Affalreu, Tehra^i U 0 .4-B. Repeat 9 ^ Secretary of fitate for India, London Government of India, Rimla. ^I9S26S ar ! , '‘‘ J(?Kior Wa '* al Officer, ^emian (nlf. my Bolitioal Agent, Kuwait* Hi? t*ajeety»* Coiwwl, Kerman, irith a request that any info mat ion nhich Me may nare heard In regard to thla incident may be reported* Firing on a Konaitl dhon by an Iranian launch near Idngah'* ^0 O- 'U r&gt; j° I • no lone herewith copy of « iett er Mo.&lt;/»6 dated the S4th June 1936 from the Political Agent, temajt, with encloaure A further reference to him h aB elicited the fact that under (Sj of Me letter, the dho. «. . te mil. B frm Ujfl&gt; #Bd (M r|, s , nU on ^ apd were Kuwait subjeete. S. Bilefly, you will see that according to the etatement of the Natbada and his crew the launch opened fire on the dho. without warning. «nd tMc fire w- continued notwithatand in R the fat that the nails ware imediately lowered. A* « reeult three of the Kuwaiti, were wounded, on* seriously. T “* a9Pears t0 Hc «fremely bad case of Iranian \ Ki. ‘Kaohah / S. 44. DCFP—1124S&amp;1’—(M-1314) ~ 4-8-32 ~ ] 2,000. ( Desir/fiation) he -5 AUG 1936 I'lNDiA OFFICE __3 Vlaunch knen that ha nan In tha wrong aaowB to be proved by the fact that, far from taking tha dhow to tha nearest Iranian port, he did not even attempt to search her for alleged contraband* This, of oouraa. Is not the first case that has occurred of Interference with Arab dhows by Iranian craft, vide correspondence ending with your despatch No. 581, dated the 29th December 1934, to His Majesty*a Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. 4. I venture to hope that you will see your way to lodging a strong protest with the Iranian Government coupled with a demand for a strict enquiry. Unfortunately, as it was dark, details as to tha identity of the launch and its crew are wanting. sd. T.C.FdwIc Lieut••Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Attested .2 2, X woul/d add In ordor to aluoidata the report that beving seen tbs mater and the crew 1 hare asoartainec 0 from them that . * • f (a) f Kho Iranian boat was a motor beet roundabout 40 feet long# (b) It was too dark to notice if she was oarrying a flag, but presumably not 9 it being night. U) iha Iranian boat was not showing lights# They used a torch on coming alongside# The ..uwaiti boat was showing har'lights# (4) ons of those on board, a aaaber of the cravr of the Iranian boat epoke with the aocant of an era ia iraq f the others spoke Persian# (e) It was rviy dark (the S^rd of the lunar fiaonth of oafar) and it was not notioed if those on board the Iranian boat aare in uniform or not# (f) Uo laember of the Iranian boat onoe aboard nor did they seo the mounded sawn# (g) r ihe three wm:C^ wan era ttl 'w'iauii now attending ^uerie&amp;n Iloapitnl in Kuwait for his wound 9 in thigh and shoulder# i^ehri whose wound has healed# It was a grama on his forehead# iba , 14 who had a slight wounT 1 !? the chest which has healed# Vhe Kuwaiti dhow after leaving Yae Island sailed for Kuwait direct, th* lone time taki* - a? days - being due to contrary (North) winds# They arrived is Kuwait on the ihth June and reported the matter on the 15th (after unloading on the 14th). The (uler sent them to m on the l?th June# I have the honour to be 9 ;&gt;ir f Your most obedient servant 9 ^d#0#i&gt;,de Gaury, Captain, Political ^&gt;ent, Kuwait#Translation of a lattar dataA the S7th r;abi # ^imal 135b, corresponding to the 17th June 1956, from His vxoellonoy the Kuler of Kuwait, to the Political ^ent, Kuwait* After oompliments, KeTarcl^ the Kuwaiti dh w whose ea&amp;e with the Irenlan iorerruent *5 lauuhh I have reported to you verbally** 'The dhow Is of the 'Bum' typo, named 'Buh&amp;il*, numbered 275 and owned by ...uhe ima&amp; ath~Thuftalyan« Her nakhuda is named Ibrahim bln Lhayl*, and she was oomlng from .enzlbar with a cargo of wood tru^dca for Kuwait* The wind was moderate whemal (horth), and the Chow was tsoking uud^r one sail opposite to Has 11 wan near lings. hen they thought they were near enough to lanu, they turned into a se; ward angle, and just ss the dhow took her course the launch appeared to them at a distance. Thinking it wes a sebU fishing boat, the nakhuda ordered Uis eteerer to turn a little to the starboard for fear of the dhow colliding with It. Hut as they cams nearer to It, a rumOn*; fire was opened at them without warning. Than they knew that it w*k the Iranian Government** launch. Therefore, the nakhu&amp;a at once ordered the sail to be brout^ht down. Hurlng the process, however, fire Increased, and the man on the sails was shot. He let go the rope saying that he was mounded, and the anil descended In disorder, for the other crew hid themselves on account of heavy firing. The rope In its rushing flow pushed with It a place of ooir matting which was entangled In the big pulley fixed to the deck. The sail stopped st half-oast* All the while firing wes going and two other crow got slight grazi&amp;ges ono on the fereheed and the other on the chest, am for the first crew wounded, the bullet hit him on the thigh, pierced It, grazed his shoulder and passed on to the is&amp;st and stuck there. After great effort, however, the crew were able to release the sail rigging. The sail fell into the sea, because owing to the heavy firing; the crew dared not show themselves to collect it.——m r\ - s - Tli» Un», mhm thin ooourr*a, wo a about £ o'olook at ni«ht (Arabia tlaa - 9.00 p.a.) on the « 8Srd „afar lass, oorraapontilng to tha Htb uay 1936 . ban thB aall hod .fallen Into aaa and tlto launoh ootw oloae to the dhow, the nalchudo about ad to thaa aatt aald, ' What la the reason for nj thla henry firing at a ay onow whloh la trarelling on a safe 3 »k? (Translators iiota 1,«. a aa». whai’e peace ralgna or should do so) Tou bare wounded three of m y crew, ace eorloualy . The launch pei’aoanel replied, 'ihy die you not bring doiro the a ail?' The iitlcbuda, 'You did not apeak to us or mim any signal neither about bringing the anil down nor about anything else, but directly opened fire at u* without warning, ho you think tliat 1c right?” The lauch -»U .u., no. p»oo.« ,o uo,.. TO, All right, glTa us a cable”. vho len .oh personnel, ”You set your sell on, and we win foUow on with you'. This discourse took place while tbs launch waa alongside the dhow. Then the launch personnel asked to eee the 'declaration' (of natluaallty; and the ssnnlfest. hen th« nakhuda wanted to haM these over to them, they throw a caaL and touched the (Sticm* *i.t thla aoAcmt they Xit an eleCtrlo torch and looked at the dhow** atom* ; aeinn dhow*a number, they said, 'Let ^&gt;0 our cable, so ag not to collide against the dhow”. This haring been done, they a eked, 'To what country you belong, and e*«e whose property le yoor dhow?” The Kakhuda replied, '*iia belong to Kuwait, and our dhew la the property of Uunenund and Thunelynn al ihanla”. The launch personnel, 'You are pernittt'd to go'. The nakhuda, ' hy you do ouch with us? Tou hare sounded three of ay crew for nothing, and at lest you a/jy we or* permitted to go'. But the launch left thaa and went away. This Is what exactly has befallen the dhow from the aboronisntioned launch. Z hare ordered Use nakhuda, one of his eteerere and the foreman to report at your of floe, as you might like !• a - llfc« to wnke further oiiquirio® froa them about th® oaaa* X ooAdtciar th® quention to he iki Important one, for sjuoh an a^greattion of the Irtmiun Xeuyucii in a safe soa la a matter ahloh bodea 1XX« ;n her ea/ the mow celled at ^ala 1 aland where ti* nakhuda made anqulrlea about the launch f but could not dlaoorer ita name and nuuaber, ^oiaeone, however, told him that the captain of the launch was oojd from Duahlre iiaaeo Aiahmud # I beg you kina ly to aubatlt th« oaso to the responsible authorities «dth a view to the nalntenanoe. as It ought to be, of peace and security in the tkilf, Usual ending3HITISH LEGATION, TEHRAN. 27 th MfiTCh 1937. My dear Lacy, I am sending you herewith by tomorrow^ bag a copy of a brio! aunasujry that Reilly has made for the Minister on his return of several outstanding cases in which the Persian snthorities have interfered with Arab dhows. You may find it useful in talx with Soheily .‘nd in other connections. Yours ever, (signed; Revile Butler.(/u Within 3 mile limit. Outstanding D how Cas es In view of the number of theae casts ut present unsettled, a brief summary of them may be useful. 1. The case of the Koweiti dhow Suhail', which was fired on off Lingah on the 12th May 1936, three members of the crew being wounded. ho repl^ has ever been rec ived to our note of protest dated 31/7/36 - paper 582/2/36. Our last reminder is 260/26/37 (the note protesting about the seizure of the silk-smuggling dhovr). Within 2. The case of the omani dhow which was seized off territorial waters as claimed by Bandar Abbas on 22nd October and released on November 1st, Iron. two rifles being retained. The action which we proposed to take is stated in 675/17/36, a telegram to Bashire dated December 18th 1936. vVe deferred action pending confirmation from Bushire that the crow of the dhow were Muscati subjects. No reply has ever been received from Bushire and we have said nothing to the Iranian Government. This case started badly with Major Lincoln^ absurd delay over reporting, and it has remained slightly ridiculous. It seems rather doubi-fui if we can do anything now. 3. The seizure of the Koweiti dhow which was to smuggle silk into India. The dhow was seized off ivhasaab on the 25th January and released on the 28th February, 16 pieces of silk being missing. fte protested in our note No.260/26/37 braided to Samiy by Hie Majesty’s Ministei* on the 16th March. 4. The case ox the three JDebai dhows which were sailing to the B&amp;tineh coast and 2 of which were searched near the 1 Mile off Arab shore.Muscat territorial 'll 1 mile from arub shore; doubtful whether Muacat or Raseaikhaimah waters. Doubtful 2. quoins also on January 25th. They were not detained. Our information is now complete, and we are ready to protest. 257/9/37. 5. The case of the Debai jolly-boat which was searched (? by the Chohrokh) on voyage from Khassab to Deb&amp;i on the 16th February. Report ona.y just received - protest suggested, linked with 4. 381/1/37. 6 . The case of the Koweiti sambuk seized at Qusbeh on or about February 8 th when returning empty down the Shatt efter carrying shingle from Subiyeh to ^badan. 385/1/37. Report only Just received. Further enquiries suggested, with preliminary note to Ministry of Foreign If f air a •&amp; C 3 ^ jS? ' \ 1218 l Tv ^ vAr®*' - O' r/* V' The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London, The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. The Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (4). V&gt;h7 6'° British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. .the. February. 1935. Reference to previous correspondence : Bushire printed letter Ho. dated tte diet ^ 53/12-S.23 December 1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Despatch No. '5, dated the 22nd January 1935, from His Majesty's Minister, Tehran. Subject. Arrest, of nakhuda Muhammad Ali Kharji, by Persians at Kharg Island and subsequent wreck of his dhow at Bushire.iQ-u ..5.« -britisti Legation, Tehran, January 22nd, 1935. Sir, I have received your despatch N 0 . &gt; of Decemher 31st last and I concur in the view expressed in the sixth paragraph thereof that no further action can properly he taken in the case of the dhow from Duhai which was wrecked at Bushire while detained there hy the Persian authorities, unless and until the owner of the cargo lodges a claim in the Persian Courts against the Customs Administration. I am, Sir, Your most obedient Servant, Sd. H.M.Knatchbull-Jbiugessen. The Political He si dent in the Persian Gulf and His Majesty’s Consul-General at Bushire.V£6 Notes. Register No. P. z SECRET. Minute Paper. 510/35 POLITICAL DEPARTMENT Dated 193 . Rec. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State.... Date. Initials. SUBJECT. 1 . 1 . Persian Gulf. Arrest of a dhow from Det&gt;ai by the Persian Authorities at Kharag Island. Copy of to SWN |*a_lTlCAU oC lorcea oy a s-corm t&gt;o uaice reiuge N waters beside Kharag Island. It Previous papers :— FOR INFORMATION. Please see P.Z. 2390/34 below. It will be seen that there has been considerable delay in obtaining the correct details of this incident which seems to have taken place in January 1934. The facts appear to be that the dhow, which was loaded with a cargo of dates from the Shatt-al-arab, was forced by a storm to take refuge in Persian was arrested there by the Persian Authorities, apparently on suspicion of smuggling, and forced to proceed to Bushire for examination, where it was detained on one pretext or another for several days until another storm arose which wrecked the vessel with the loss of a considerable part of the cargo. Unfortunately, contrary to our earlier/earlier information, it has now been established that the dhow was the property of a Persian subject resident at Debai, and that the Nakhuda was also a Persian, so that no action can apparently be taken by us on their behalf. The unfortunate third party who was the owner of the cargo, the remains of which may still be lying at Bushire, is a Koweit subject. In the Resident’s opinion, the only course open to the latter for obtaining compensation would be to lodge either personally or through an agent a claim in the Bushire Courts against the Persian Customs Authorities, when the Consulate General would use their good offices on his behalf as far as possible. The Koweiti in question has not, however, taken action up to the present, apparently because he fears that, being a Koweiti, it would be difficult for him to enter Persia and doubly difficult to get away again owing to the refusal of the Persian Authorities to recognise Koweit certificates of indentity. In this connection please see the d.o. letter of the 27th April last/which v/as addressed to the Political Resident. We have had no reply to this letter, but, from information separately received, the position at present appears to be that the Persian Authorities, while not actually confiscating Koweit certificates of identity, ignore them altogether, and issue to the holders ”Ilm-o-Khabar” or Persian Travel Documents, as if they were Persian subjects. The case is an unsatisfactory one, but nothing can apparently be done unless the owner of the cargo can be persuaded to risk the journey to SSBTN &amp;QL}T ZA I msn't &lt; I 0Z^FIDETTTIAL. ! ) . Z. ) * _ .510 i ! S'J5 l v 2 6 ja/v \m y 1 he Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to tiis Majesty’s Secretaiy cf state for India, London, The Foreign Secretary to the Government cf India, i»ew Delhi, ihe pclitioal Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment {/). 33^ lur British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Da ted.. t.U 6 $!t .. . 1 4. Reference to previous correspondence : Bushire printed letter N c * IO-b/311-s, dated the 19th March 1934. Description of . Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 4 Despatch to nis MajestyAs Jinvcy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at the ocurt cf Persia, Tehran, *c. even date. Arrest cf nakhuda Muhammad Aii Kharji, hy Persians at Kharg island and subse quent wreck of his dhow at Busnire.iiritisli ocnsulate-aeneral, ijusnire. liC- oi/li-3.23 /17L 2X2.SL I ; C 5 5 Arrest of a dhcw from Babai toy Persians at Ktoarg Island. air, I have the honour tc refer to uiy ocnfideatial despaton No* lO-lV^U-3 cf tne 19th j/[aroh 1934. 2. There has toeen a ccusideratole delay in obtain ing tae correct details of this case owing tc the absence from Busnire cf tne nalhuda and crew cf the dhow who returned some time age tc the Arab side of the Grulf. 3. The following facts However nave no# been estabiisnedj- 1. The dhcw was the property cf a Persian snojeot resident at Dubai. 2. The nakhuda is a Persian subject. 3. The crew of the dhow whe were British Protected Persons (from Qubai, Sharjah and Muscat ) were repatriated to their hemes shortly after the dhow was wrecked without any molestation from the Persian authorities. 4. It is beyond dispute that the dhcw was wrecked and the cargo damaged oy a storm which arose while the vessel was in bu shire anchorage preparing tc resume her voyage after completion cf an inquiry toy the Oustcm*s officials. o. it would appear tnerefere tnat the only course open tc tne owner ct the cargo (a British protected Person - subject cf Kuwait) for obtaining compensation for the damage sustainedw culd be tc lodge personally His Majesty’s Envoy Extraordinary and Minister plenipotentiary at the court cf Persia,or through an agent a claim in the Law courts in Bushire against the Persian Customps authorities. This ocnsuiate-Generai could then use their good offices on his Dehaif sc far as possible. The above suggestion has already been made by me bo the owner through the political Agent, Kuwait, and tne sueikn, cut up to the present no action has been taken by the man. 6. Having regard to all the circumstances of the case I am of opinion that it is useless to proceed with tne matter further until such time as the owner of the cargo taKes tne action suggested to him v lie paragraph 5 above. I nave bhe honour to be, Sir, your most obedient, humble servant, ^signed) T. C. FOWLS, His majesty's Consul-General, Bushire. a-2531 5000 2.34 Draft Paper. Dr&amp;KT LETTK^ . ly dear Powle 2 7 APR 1934 Many thanks for your confidential Koweit ohow oy the Persians on Khar&amp;j Island. We note that enquiries have been made, the result of which will he communicated iater, and I write now only with reference to the point wnicn fallows, arising out of para.5 of Dickson's letter^ No.0.86, of 28th February. 2. Dickson's statement is, I think, anything to show whether this refusal is based on their vague claim to some with passport questions in the past, or is part of their general contention that they cannot recognise our right to speak on behalf of the Arab Sheikhdoms of the Persian Gulf, ^vs you wiPi—Hoare's telegram of 20th April, No.56, to the Foreign Office, of which copies go to you by The Hon'ble Lt.Col. T.C.W. Fo wl e, C. B. £. The Residency, Bushire. despatch of 19th larch, No. 10-B/311-3, about the arrest of the Nakhuda of a 6/^ the most definite evidence we have yet had of Persian refusal to accept British certificates of identity in the case of Koweitis and we should be COP v BY MAIL of — interested to know whether there is suzerainty or control over Koweit of which we have had hints in connection this/indexed CONFIDENTIAL. KM Lj No. 10-B/311-S of 1934 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1* His Majesty^ Minister, Tehran. No.lO-B. 2* His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, v London. No.311-3. 3. The Foreign Secretary to the Grovernment of India, New Delhi. No.311-S. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). Z+ Enquiries are 'being made result of which will he communicated later. / •(vNkW » * NX .S/ V British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. 3 Dated. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Arrest of narkhuda of a Kuwait dhow hy Per- -sians at Khara.i Island.&amp; OO^IDKKTlrtX •to fpTz. lolltioal A^ncf t q K uwait* 1 Dated the 26th ^ehru T^om To lt-jolou«l H*H.?. Dlckuoi., C*T 9 V '*9 !•*.* lolitioal k&amp;nt 9 Kuwait* The Hon’hle the f’olitioal Heoldent in the j-eraiaa Xiir, r^uehlre. wrreet of ^khuda, Mwhaned ,4.1 Kharjl, a Kuwait subject, by Persians at Kharaj Islaiid ai^d the subsequent wreck of his coat at buuhlre, with the loss of half the oar^o Sir, I have the honour to forward t ansl&amp;tlou of letter b H2/1436, dated the 13th February 19;54 from His Excellency the :?uler of Kuwait to uyself enolo- sln^ translation of the following two letters* (a) Petition, dated the icth 5*bruary 1954|? submitted uy Khalld bln Abdul Latlf, and Brothers, meroiiants of Kuwait to Hie Ex cellency the Kuler of Kuwait* (b) letter dated Bush!re, the 2nd ?ebruary 1934 from Hakhuda itohamed /4.1 Kharjl, a Kuwait subject , to Ahmad bln Abdul Latif of the firm of Khalld bln ^odul Latlx roe*, of Kuwait* which all three speak for UiemselTea* 2* iht whole case appsara to revolwe round the question of the nationality of the tfuhuda iohaaed v All Kharjl* necause the tasui v s surnaoe happened to be ,l x:&lt;*arji* ^whlch literally interpreted means *of KharaJ') the Persian Director of Just ms on Fharaj leland appa»\ rently saw fit to arrest his on the ground that he was a Persian subject, and subsequently ill*treated him in the way described, with the result that a perfectly in- \ nocent third party's cargo has become an almost total loss at itashlre* 3* 'JfiL.. _ i a&lt;m • 2 - &amp; 3. In point of actual fact the Nakhuda f-ohaaod ^li Kharji, is a subject of Kuwait, and he a d hie family have been resident on the Island of *'alaika f a Kuwait Possession, for the last hundred years* it is not denied that the loin’s ancestors oriodnally Jr came from Kharaj Island,&gt;who number some thousand souls, but to-day they are all perfectly i£ood Kuwait subjects, and are claimed as such by the iiuler of Kuwait in just the same way as he claims some ten thousand other per sons of distant Persian origin who to-day reside in 1uwait town* 4* Before sending on this case to you, I have gone to the trouble of sending for idimad bin Abdul Latif oi the firm of Khalid bin Abdul Latif brothers, who are ths owners of the^fcaa^d : 1 cargo, now in the hands of the Persian customs authorities at Bushire, and have discussed the whole business with him and from every an^le* the man a very respectable merchant told me that he had instructed a certain . ohamed ^ssi.j behani to act as his ^.gent in the matter, with instruc tions to try and get some sort of satisfaction out of the local Customs authorities, but that he had little hope of anything resulting* i 5 # $ien I advised that he himself should try and get across to Bushire somehow and m-ke his complaint personally, he pointed out that it was so diiXioult for him to enter Persia and so doubly difficult ^or him to get av/ay again, that he felt it was quite useless to try. T^is, in fact, is true, seeing that the dushire Pass port authorities do not accept a British Certificate of Identity, arguing t hat Kuw ait belongs to Persia. Oie result is that as there is no existing machinery whereby a Kuwait subject can get to mchire and baok in the ^ course of ordinary business, it becomes impossible, au far as I can see, for the principal injured party in present case \the owner of the coniiscatfd cargo) tg \. lodge a complaint at Bushire, or even • • • • * or evenor tv«a hopt for jujtice f and it would apioar to o* oqually loxouolblo for tht ocaond injured p^rty* the rumlt ^akhuda* to roooTtr the raluo of his •ailing craft, or «Y«n himooir leave iiuehlro for hie hooe* 0# la forwardlhe. the above facte, 1 would aak that you o* eo ^ood a» to uee your ut«&amp;oat e^eavoure to fc*t (a) the Sa^ibuk releaeed \ if ml a total wreck)! ' (b) the ’hkuda e&lt;fut back to Kuwaiti (o) that portion of the car^o which wae salved and ie now in the hands of the Jus tome au thorities, released and handed over to Uoharsed passim Behbehani of 3uehire« 7• 1 do not know whether oha&amp;ed n jehbeijaiii has any ohanoe whatsoever, of tettlntf any darm^ea out of the nuahlre Customs authorities on the (jrou^ds of ne^li^noe but In any case 1 trust you will be able to see your way to put his ajeety’s minister in Tehran in possession of the above facts with a view to hie drawing the Persian Government 9 e attention to the hl&lt;^h~handed methods ox* their Custom# officials in the Persian Oilf, fc• I am sending a copy of this to ttu* senior aural Officer, persiaii Julf a*d trust you will approve of my dein&lt;£ so* I I have the honour to oe, Jir, Your most obedient servant, 4* K*3*l • Jickeon, It-Colonel, Poll tieb.1 ^usait*Translation of letter ao 1^3/1436, dated the 26th Shauwal 1352(13-2-34) from His Excellency ;&gt;ir Ahmad al Jabir as-iiabah, J, ;&gt;.!.* i&lt;uler Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. After JompliifaentSf I enclose herewith two letters, in original, one from Muhammad Ali Kharji, uakhuda of a sailing ship, and the other from Khalid bin Abdul Latil al Hamad &amp; Bros, a subject of Kuwait. ^rom the statement of the mkhuda you will be able to learn of the ill usage that befell at the hands of the Director of the Persian Customs at Kharag, v/hich was directly the cause o. is ship being wrecked, and his cargo being damaged and lost. We trust that you will look into this Un justifiable ill-treatment and aggression on the part of the above-mentioned Director (of Customs) and will submit the case to the Hon'ble the Political Resident. Usual Ending.Traaolation of a petition dated the 25th ^hauwal lo52 (lC» 2 *i 54 ) submitted fcy Khalid bin Abdul Latif al Ha a d $t mere:ante of Kuwait# to His .xcellsiiOy the AUler of V'uwait* oe., respeotfull; to inform our nxoellency that some days a*go we chartered a sailing uiiip (aambuh) belonging to a oertaia :jakhuda by name oh^oed ali frharji# resident of the Island of /alaiha* 1 close to Kuwait) aud loaded her with 400 bags of maims ex jasra axid 551 baskets of dates from the wanyuhi district situate on the psrsian side of the Shatt-al-Arab. asYing duly taken out his manifests from the Customs Houses of Gt sba in Persia a: d -ao in •Ira*, the akhuda sailed for Yemen* but when he got out to sea# his ship began to yield under the strain oi the wind# and he was compelled to seek shelter under the let of KharaJ island# which belongs to Persia. On his arriving there a grave act of injustice was inflicted upon him by the local director of Customs who resided there# as you will see from trie akhuda** letter# which we enclose# here- with for your perusal. Therefore# tre beg to request that Vour ^ixotllenoy will kindly take up the matter against the aboveme*.tinned director# who unjustifiably interfered with our goods aud properly# and was directly responsible for the wreck of a chip chartered y ua t and of very serious daraage to our cargo at iiyshire. * by loUtloal ,v^ent . ftOaik. Islaiid belongs to Kuwait• e • • behind Translation of letter dated Bushire the 17th ahauwal 1352 (2«2»34’’ from nakhuda ^luha^njinad All Kharjif to yN* .dimad bin Abdul Latif v of the firm of F^ialid bin Abdul 3Latif al Ha^ad and Bros) Kuwait. nfter Compliments, Regarding the cargo of maize and dates oe- l0Ilb iua to you, which i had tak.n on ooard iay ship at AB har (Basra) and Manyuhi (Persian side of Shatt al Arab) respectively, I beg to inform you that after we had pro ceeded with your agent Baqir bin MBhammad Husain Bafar to both the Customs Houses at ousbah and ^ and had finished with both, and had got o«r sailii'g papers (Sanifeats) from each place, the Persian «Jawaz« for peralssion~to export the dates was taken by your said_ AgnmBaqir, iod the two manifests only remaining with_ ^ 'then sailed from the mouth of the Bhatt-al-Arab TrTthe night of the 28th Knoadnan, but shortly afterwands the wind became strong and he sea rough, and our ship could no longer withstand the waves. Barly morning found us near the island of Kharaj, and we were obliged to make for it and take shelter in its harbour. We reached there with difficulty and pr ceeded to land in order to take in some supplies from the town, but when we came aBhore, we were asked by the Director of Customs to pro- duce our 'Jawazea' but we naturally could not. *e showBd ^ w ' him, however, the manifest i taken at Pao) but he said th~t ,^^t«^it was neither signed nor had any date, and that we must therefore proceed to Bushire ana be examined. » next ' aen t a s: Idler on board our ship, caused much trouble to v UB&gt; and de tained us five days at Kharaj. On the fifth day he embarked on board our ship, together with the Governor of the Island, a Sakhuda, a steerer, and a soldier, and ordtrfd us to proceed to Busbirea At Bushire I and my crew, less five leit behind</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000169_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3794</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000169</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3794</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/77 'Koweit: Persian interference with Koweiti dhows.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-11-21T11:00:59</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (179 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 180; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns reports of interference with Kuwaiti dhows by Iranian (also referred to as Persian) customs and naval authorities. The papers contain witness statements, letters of protest by the Shaikh of Koweit [Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ, Ruler of Kuwait], reports, discussion of the incidents by British officials, and representations by HM Minister at Tehran (later HM Ambassador, Tehran) to the Government of Iran.The papers concern four main incidents:The arrest of the nakhoda of a Kuwaiti dhow at Kharaj (also referred to as Kharg) Island [Jazīreh-ye Khārk], February 1934 - March 1937 (folios 160-178).The firing on a Kuwaiti dhow by an Iranian launch, near Lingah [Bandar-e-Lengeh], June 1936 - March 1937 (folios 132-158).The seizure of a Kuwaiti dhow by Iranian customs authorities at Qusbeh [Qoşbeh-ye Manī‘āt], February - April 1937 (folios 64-130).The seizure near Lingah of a Kuwaiti dhow (the
                              Furat)outside Iranian territorial waters, by an Iranian naval sloop, thought to be HIMS
                              Babr, February - May 1937 (folios 5-62).Folios 72-110 consist of later correspondence, dated April 1947 - February 1948, also on the subject of interference by Iranian naval vessels with Kuwaiti dhows, which has been misfiled. A note on folio 3 states that the file 'seems to have got out of order'.The file also contains significant correspondence from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Political Agent, Kuwait; and the British Consul, Kerman.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HIMS Babr</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Kharaj</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul, Kerman</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Qusbeh</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Lingah</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kharg</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Territorial waters</topic></subject><subject><topic>Great Britain--Foreign relations--Iran</topic></subject><subject><topic>Dhows</topic></subject><subject><topic>Customs administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000169#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>