<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003a5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T13:11:23.010Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/ h N °- 587 » (444/9/36) HIS Majesty’s Ambassador Bagdad presents his compliments to H.^’s Principal Secretary of State lor Foreign Affairs, f*' and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Embassy.*... Bagdad. r I&gt;Z. * 1 0 ^ ! QS^Be-c^mber. -, 1936. Reference to previous correspondence : Bagdad despatch No. 529 dated 26th October,!936. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Note No. 594 dated 4th December, 1936, to the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs. Iraqi visas on Indian Pilgrim Passes.iSNCLOSURE IN BAGDAD DESPATCH NO. 587 OP 4.12.36. m*, m Hi8 8 praaent their coapllaenta to the ministry of foreign Affaire and hare the honour to Inrite a reference to the correapondenee ending in the Ml at* try's note No. 10601/56^17 of uctoher I5th f ecmcemlng the desire of the Iraqi Goremwent that Iraqi visas ohould he ohtained hy all claaoes of peraona proceeding froa India to Iraq, including thoec trarelling on pilgrin passes. 2. HI a Majesty's i^ahasay hare nor learned froa the Covema^nt of ndia that the necessary instructions to the authorities in India were issued on September 28th la at* His Majesty's Kabasny arail thraselrea of this opportunity to renew the expression of their highest iA &lt;s&gt; In any further connim nicuU on on this subject, please quote No. y i/3yF bnd address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. 5 ^ 819/ i THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign lAffairsv presents his compliments to y v* 1 ' W- an( j^ direction of the Secretary of State, f? transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, // fo, 193 . Reference to previous correspondence : £&gt;. Tb T/turst/ss*/$??etf ' — cSfafe-**. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. icyvs hH*T- TVloJtirfcY Au&lt;* tfctc/ • z. 6 &lt; Subject. &amp;vyfoy 'vd/i 0 I 4 cah Similar letter sent to 14 - 61 }o 13667(2)' No. 529 . (444/8/36) 8197 1936 HIS Majesty’s Ambassador at Bagdad presents his compliments toH.M’s Principal Secretary of State fbr ^ Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Embassy.,. fcag&amp;ad,. S.Gth.L.cto.'be.r.., 193.6* Reference to previous correspo7idencc : Bagdad despatch No* 469 dated 19th September, 1936. Descriptio7i of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Note No.10501/38/17 dated 15th October, 1936, from the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs. Visas on Indian pilgrim Despatch No.44^8/36 dated 26th October, 1936, to the Government of India. passes.SNCLO.itJRij IK B.^ODAD DK3PATCH NO. 629 OP 26.10.S6. »o.10501/36A? The Ittnistry for ^oreiga Affairs yresent their oorapliwents to riis ? iltaanio majesty’s ^baasy, mgrtad, and, with reference to their aote ?lo«477 dated X9th Septet^ber^ 1936, have the honour to state that the Iraqi authorities oonoemed agree to the arrangeTnents set forth in the esteemedKmbassy*s note under referenoo. it is * however observed that the assumption in paragraph 4 of tv* note that pilgrim passes will continue to be accepted for entry into Iraq without visa pending a notification by the Government of India putting into operation the arrangement referred to in the said para^aph of the Embassy's note is contrary to the explanation made by the Ministry in paragraph s of their note :io»4B01 dated 30th xsLXtk ? r ay, 1936, that the arrangement previously in force did not provide for exemption from visa but only authorised the issue of visas by competent officials in the Government of India* The Ministry request the esteemed Embassy to be so good as to advise them in due course of the issue by the noverr^ent of India of instructions putting the abov** mentioned arrangements into operation, in order that ther may inform the Iraqi authorities accordingly for the latter in their turn to issue the necessary instructions to frontier posts. The Ministry avail themselves of this opportunity to express their highest consideration and esteem. ritdnaio Majesty's Krobassy, Bagdad. 'inistry for I'ore i ^a-Af^ai^, 'aglad, Ibth October, '1936. o u /ENCLOSURE IN BAGDAD DESPATCH NO. 529 OP 26.10.36. (444/8A«) Bagdad. 26th October, 1036. o ny Lord* X have the honour to refer to the despatch Ifo* S*4661-If/36 of August 37th addressed to me hy the Foreign locretary to the Ooremment of India concerning the vlah of the Iraqi aovemaent t*hat Indian pilgrims travelling to Iraq, lihould obtain &amp; rlaa for Iraq In India* 2# It la of course the case* as stated in the' despatch* that the Iraqi Govern men t wish that Iraqi visas should he obtained by all persons travelling to Iraq* whether travelling on pilgrim passes or on passports* and not that the system of pilgrim passes should be terminated* I regret that this misunderstanding should have arisen* The Iraqi Government Ivrre now informed ms that th*?y agree to the arrsing»:*®-.“nta proposed by the Government of India and set forth in pnragraoh 3 of the despatch under reference. They will ba glad to learn when the necessary ittntruotione have been issued by the Oovem»ent of India* in order that they may advise Iraqi frontier poata of the entry into force of the new procedure* I note that last ruction.* were already under His excellency The Viceroy of India* Foreign Department* Ha- J^.KI.© under Issue at the date of the ! orcign Bearetary** despatch ah ore-quo ted, ami I ohall he glad vo learn, for the information of the Ira&lt;|l Goverrnacnt, th«j date as from which the Indim authorities affooted have hcen iastmeted to coaply therewith. 5. X aa Bonding a copy of this despatch to His Uaieaty'a i riacipal Beoretary of fctate for Foreign affaire. .•&gt;*'»** •v pir- , ^' V • I hare the honour to he. My I,ord, Tour Lordship's moat obedient servant. A§&amp;) Archibald Clerk Kerr, k( k n. * No. 469. (444/5/36) HIS Majesty’s Charg6 d’AfYaires at Bagdad presents his compliments to H.M , s Principal Secretary of State for , , , . Foreign Affairs, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British..Ift&amp;assy'S * • f m ! Bagdad. J 7404 : | \ . .fleet ember, 1 93 .6. syw&gt;. Reference to previous correspondence : Bagdad despatch No.^331 dated 3rd July, 1936. Descidption of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Despatch No. D. 4861-N/ 36 dated 27th August, 1936 from the Govern ment of India. Issue of visas to Indian Pilgrims visiting Iraq. Note No. 477 dated 19th September, 1936 to the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs. 54/5 10871 (2)Enclosure in Bagdad despatch No, 469 dated 19.9.36. No. D.4b61-N/36. From The Foreign Secretary to the (tovemment of India, To His Majesty’s Charge d ? Affaires, Bagdad. Dated Simla, the 27th August, 1936. Sir, I am directed to reply to your despatch No.444/3/36 dated the 3rd July 1936, addressed to His Excellency the Viceroy. There would appear to he some misunderstanding in the statement made in paragraph 2 (a) of your despatch that the Iraqi Government desire to terminate the system of pilgrim passes throughout India. From the letter from the Iraqi Ministry for Foreign Affairs No. 4601, dated the 20th May, forming an enclosure to your despatch, it does not appear that the Iraqi Government desire that the system of pilgrim passes should he terminated, hut only that Iraqi visas should he issued to all classes of travellers to Iraq including pilgrims travelling on pilgrim passes. The point is of some material importance inasmuch as a pilgrim pass is issued free, while fees would he demanded for a passport. 2. The Government of India have considered whether they should attempt to maintain the position sought to he established by your note No. 556, dated the 8th November 1935, addressed to the Iraqi Ministry for Foreign Affairs, forming an enclosure to your despatch No. 63/32/35, dated the 3th November 1935, namely that in the absence of an Iraqi consular authority at Indian ports other than Bombay Iraqi visas and visa fees should he dispensed with altogether They have also considered whether it would he possible to /dispense/■* dispense with the collection of visa fees in cases where such visas on Indian pilgrim passes were issued by British authorities at ports other than Bombay. They conclude, how ever, from your despatch that the Iraqi Government are no longer open to a suggestion that visas should be dispensed with, while the second suggestion is open to the objection that pilgrims proceeding from ports other than Bombay would enjoy an advantage which would tend to divert the pilgrim traffic from Bombay and constitute a source of reasonable grievance both to the Iraqi Government and to pilgrims who took the Bombay route. On general grounds, moreover, it is desirable that charges for the pilgrimage via Iraq should be the same for pilgrims proceeding from all parts of India, whether or not an Iraqi consular authority is stationed at all ports of egress. 3. The Government of India are therefore prepared to comply with the Iraqi Government’s request in the form that:- (1) pilgrims via Bombay should be required to obtain Iraqi visas on their pilgrim passes from the Iraqi Consulate-General at Bombay, (2) in the case of other ports visas for Iraq should be given by the British authorities, and (5) in both cases the Iraqi visa fee of 10 gold francs (Rs.9/-) should be charged, the realisations in the case of visas granted by the British authorities being under the existing practice retained by the Govern ment of India. In the latter case it will also be con sidered whether such realisations could be credited to the HaJ funds of the ports concerned. Instructions to this effect are under issue. I have, etc. . .. (Sd). H. Metcalfe. Foreign Secretary to the Government of India.Enclosure in Bagdad despatch No. 469 dated 19»9»36. IIP. 477. Hi# Majesty*# ^basay present their oottpllaent* to the Ministry of Foreign Affair# and hare the honour to invite a reference to the Ministry*# not# Ho. 4601 of ^«y 20th last, concerning the desire of the Iraqi Govcrmaent that Iraqi visas should be obtained by all classes of persons proceeding from India to Iraq, including those travelling on pilgrim passes. 2. His Majesty's Aabassy have the honour to infora the Ministry that the Oovemr.cnt of India are now prepared to coiaply with the Iraqi Government*a suggestion# in the following manner:- (1) Pilgrims via Bombay should be required to obtain Iraqi visas on their pilgrim passes from the Iraqi Consulate-General at i&gt;o«d&gt;ay* (2) In the case of other ports, visas for Iraq should be given by the British authorities. (d) In both cases the Iraqi visa fee of 10 gold franc# (Rs.9/-) should be charged, and in the case of visas granted by the British authorities, the sums realised should, under the existing practice, be re tained by the Government of India. 3* On learning that the Iraqi Government concur in these proposals. Hi# Majesty*# Kabaasy will request the Government of India to issue the necessary instructions, with the least possible delay, to the officials empowered to grant visas for Iraq. 4. Hi# Majesty's Embassy assume that bearers of pilgrim passes will continue to be admitted to Iraq with out an entry visa, pending a notification by the Government of India to the effect that the necessary Instructions have been issued.3479 10871 (2) HIS Majesty’s chapgi d'/tffftires 2 sj Bagdad presents his compliments toH.H f 8 Principal Secretary of* State to* and has the honour to transmit to him the under-menFioneS^ffocumenfej!* British...ifcibGi&amp;Qy.,... Bagdad# ...3rd. J.uly. , 193^. Reference to previous correspondence Bagdad despatch N o. 63 dated 5th February, 1935. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Note No#9394 dated 27th October* 1935, from the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs# I Subject. ssue of visas to Indian Note No#556 dated 8th Nov# ^ 1935,to the Iraqi Ministry for Foreign Affairs# Despatch No#444/3/36 dated 3rd July, 1936, to the Government of India (with enclosure)# Pilgrims#ENCLOSURE IN BAGDAD DESPATCH. No. OF 3&gt;. . £Vo . No&gt; 556 His Majesty's Embassy present their complioents to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and, with reference to the note from the iiini :try No.9394 of October 27th, have the honour to observe that die statement that, in the past, the Iraqi Government permitted Indian pilgrims in possession of pilgrim Passes to enter Iraqi territory on a visa from the Government of India, is incorrect. The practice has always been that Indian pilgrims in possession of Passes are admitted into Iraq without any visa whatsoever. 2. If it is the desire of the Ministry to disturb the existing practice by requiring British-Indian pilgrims proceeding to Iraq via Bombay to obtain visas from the Iraqi Consulate there, a serious anomaly will be created, since Indian pilgrims arriving from Bombay possession of visas for Iraq, while pilgrims arriving from other Indian ports will have no visas. 3# His Majesty's Ambassy will therefore be grateful if the Jiniotry v. r ill, on reconsideration, consent to continue the existing system, whereby British-Indian pilgrims in possession of Pilgrim Passes are allowed to enter Iraq without visas. The Ministry are no doubt aware that some 4,000 Indian pilgrims enter Iraq annually and spend there an average of Rs.200/- each to the benefit of the country in general and of the Holy Cities in particular. It would therefore appear to be contrary to the interests of the Iraqi Govern ment to require these pilgrims to take visas for Iraq - a course which might well deter a considerable number of persons from under taking the pilgrimage. 4. The Government of India have already been informed that all Indians other than pilgrims coming to Iraq via Bombay are subject to the formality of obtaining a visa for Iraq from the Iraqi Consulate at Bombay. His Majesty* s Embassy avail themselves of this opportunity to renew the expression of their highest considerationo British Embassy, Bagdad. 8th November, 1936.ENCLOSURE IN BAGDAD DESPATCH. hO, • 3 &gt;il OF -S'® (* 4 VV 0 «) r^ Brttiah ra'briseyt Bagdad. 3rd July, 1936. My Lord, In hi» dospateh Xo* 8V5B/86 of ?ioy«abep 8th, 1986, sir h. OlMk Kopr oent to Tour xeclleney's ppedoc-. eo;&gt;r • tpsuialation of a no to from the iwu£ ! ini a try af foreign Affairs ooncomlng tho Issue of ;&gt;ao»eu to laUtn pilgritte, togetlwsr with a copy of the reply front this Jfcaasy, la which the ira^i Ooremaont were urged to agree to th® contl muuwer of the present system, hy which snob paasoa are issued tiirou^rout India. 2* X have ths honour to trail colt to four Jccollwney a tranelatioa of a further note whit* I have raealved fraa the inistry on till a subject. ths Iraqi oovewwvwnt bow ( a) request that Your i xc«*lloney may he inforswd of tiieir deal re to teralnBite the system of pilgrta peases tij-ousSiout India, and (b) suggest that rioae should be loaned to all elauses of travellers to Iraq by the Government of India autiiorltias at present eapowered to issue pH grin passes (of. herd 'miing&amp;on's despatch He* y.8ao-a/36 of deptcaher 4th, 1936), on exception, however, being made for the district of the Iraqi uoaeulate^hcncral at Conbay where* visas oust be obtained from the Iraqi consular authorities. 3. It is not, J imagiaa, open to dispute that the Iraqi Ctovemnant are entitled, if they wish, to teralnuto, at any Hie xceileney the Viceroy of India, Foreign o-mrtwent, Ll. La . tiae,jit ti*e, th* pasts ayetora fen- I ail an pllgrisaa, ana It la trw&gt; that In tha copree, &lt;ma.«noa loading op to the •atabllahEK nt of tho Ira^l onsulate-ocneral at taaba?, the MiniUtpy state*! (of, first onolosure In {ilr Francis Hwtptors’ daopatoh Mo. &amp;S/4/SS of January SMth, HM») that they could only aatiartaiw not to diaturh that ayater. for the currant pllgrltaage seasjon. gore than a yoar has paaaad einee than, *. J shall titerafore he glad to loam whether your xcellency la prepared to giro offeot to the wlahea of Irani Goremaent. 1 hare the honour to he,ENCLOSURE IN BAGDAD DESPATCH. fix OF ^ ' ^ • »•. 4231* Ministry for 9»roign Affair^ 20th Mny # 1936. Ih® Ministry for florslgn Affairs prsssnt thsir oozaplioants to His Britsnnic idsjssty^ jab*say, Bagdad, and. with reference to tha Kmbassy v s not® Bo. 556 da tad 6th Noromber, 1935. regarding risas on Indian pilgrin pass®®, hive th® honour to stats that by thsir not® i»o. 9394 dated 7th October. 1935. th® Ministry intended to explain that the procedure of granting visas to Indian pilgrim® proceeding to Iraq was observed in the observance past and that th® xdocjgxkx of this procedure was suspended only t«mporarily and on account of a certain specific causa, namely the absence of Iraqi consular establishments in India. This 1® confirmed by th® content® of the Consular Secretary to the High Comissioaer's letter No. 790 dated 17th January. 192^ in which it was suggested that compliance with the demand of the Criminal Investigation Department requiring the grant ef visas on pilgrim passes might be put off for some other time so long as no representative existed in India for Iraq. Similarly, upon the establishment ef the Iraqi Consulate in Bombay the esteemed mbaesy. in their note He* 35 dated 24th January. 1935. expressed the hope that it was not intended to siter in that year the procedure allowing entry into Iraq on passes from the Indian authorities* In thsir nets Bo* 670 dated 2nd February. 1935. the ministry replied that the procedure in question would continue to be observed only for the next pilgrim season.• 2 • 2 * The I real xepertaente concerned consider that Tlee fees are trifling and nLW not therefore constitute e difficulty 0 {&lt;lcva»teu to deter persons from undertaking the pilgrimage to Iraq end to reduce the number ef nilgrlmii. 3 . as regards paragraph 2 of the abassy^ net# referred to nhovo. the iraej. Depertaente concerned sug£est thet officials in the Gorerriment ef India (with th* exception of th« Boob*/ dietriot) empowered to issue pilfrim pamvas* inight be authorised to grant Tisas on behalf of the ixeqi GcTonuaent, under the ministry's noUficatlon Ko # 10 , of which e cop; is enclssed, until such tim? ae it Kmy be possible tu delegats such power in 6 *r&gt;r.r*l to Iraqi ccnoulw* 4. Iho ilinistry wish to invite the attention sf the eetemd Enbaesy tc the fact that ten-ebeerranoe in the or no of Im’irn pilcrlmt of the procet^uro of granting entry Tiea# for Iraq will natux^lly open the way for other grcvex'm&amp;onts tc elf im airdler treatment fer their subjects* Hence the inability to ignore the procedure in Question* G. Therefore tfeo ministry recuctt the esteemed Imbaesy to be so good as to convoy to the Government ef India thaix point of view as eteted shove. The ministry avail thomeelv^s of this opportunity to exprccc their highest consideration and ssteem* Kia Britarmic peaty's ixabasey, Bagdad*Vraal&amp;Uon of Motlflctton la TMireuaae* of tho oowor reatod in cm by Council of ».iniatpr«' resolution adopted at their ■tooting on Slat January, 1936, and in ardor to giro offset to the provisions of Article 6(a) of tho I*® 1 !! Residence lot* of 1922, I hereby authorise British officials authorised to grant visas to grant, in districts not covered by Iraqi consular districts, entry visas for Iraq on behalf of the Iraqi Osvornmant,o From in the Foreign and Political Department, To The Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political and Reforms Department. Dated New Delhi, the February 1935. Consul-General for Iraq at Bombay. Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with your letter NO.308/34-A, dated the 19th September 1934, I am directed to forward a copy of despatch from His Majesty’s Ambassador, Baghdad, No.63/4/35, dated the 24th January 1935 with enclosures. It will be observed that the Government of Iraq have decided to appoint Ahmad Zaki Beg al Khayyat as Consul-General for Iraq at Bombay and that he will be proceeding to Bombay shortly. 2. I am to request that, with the permission of the Governor in Council, the Government of India may kindly be informed of the date of Ahmad zaki Beg al Khayyat*s arrival. I have the honour to be. Your most obedient servant, Sd. H.Trevelyan, Under Secretary to the Government of India.N (63/4/35). British Embassy, “ _lad. 24th BaM; h January 1935. My Lord, With reference to my despatch No.189/54/34 of December 13th last, I have the honour to transmit to your Excellency herewith a copy of a note which I have now received from the Iraqi Government Informing me that they have appointed Ahmad Zaki Beg al Khayyat Consul-General at Bombay. This gentleman is at present Mutasarrlf of Kerbala Llwa. 2. Your Excellency will observe that the Iraqi Govern ment agree not to disturb, for a year, the arrangement by which pilgrims from India are allowed entry Into Iraq If supplied with passes from the authorities of the Government of India. It is Incorrect to speak of a pilgrimage season in this connexion, since the great majority of pilgrims from India come to this country not to take part in the ’Haj’, or annual pilgrimage to Mecca and Medina, but to visit the Holy Cities in Iraq itself, and this they do all the year round. I have not thought it necessary to call the attention of the Iraqi Government officially to this misapprehension. 3. It seemed to me desirable, however, to seek from the Iraqi Government an assurance that the officials of the Government of India will continue to grant Iraqi visas at places other than Bombay, and a copy of my note on this subject is enclosed. I shall not fail to inform your \ Excellency of the reply of the Iraqi Government on this point, 4. I am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majes- - ty*s principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.^ \ J I have the honour to be I Your Lordship's most obedient servant. Sd. F.H.Humphrys. His Excellency The Viceroy of India, Foreign Department, New Delhi.Mo,t 23 -S. Ministry for Foreign Affairs, Bagdad, 13th January, 1935. The Ministry for Foreign Affairs present their compliments to His Britannic Majesty’s Embassy, Bagdad, and, with reference to the Embassy’s note No.722 dated 13th December, 1934, have the honour to state that the Ministry have appointed Ahmad zakl rargHT Beg al Khayyat Consul General for the Iraqi Government at Bombay. Ahmad Zakl Beg will proceed to the place of his appointment at the earliest possible date. The Ministry request the esteemed Embassy to be so good as to inform the authorities concerned accordingly, with a view to their extending to Ahmad Zaki Beg the facilities necessary for the discharge of his duties. The Iraqi Government agree not to disturb the existing procedure excepting persons carrying pilgrim passes from obtaining entry visas for Iraq, only during the coming pilgrim season. The Iraqi Government will reconsider this question at next year’s pilgrim season, doing so not less than three months before the commencement of the said season. The Ministry avail themselves of this opportunity to express their highest consideration and esteem. His Britannic Majesty’s Embassy, Bagdad.His Majesty’s Embassy present their compliments to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and, with reference to the note No.219 of January 13th from the Ministry, have the honour to Inform them that they have acquainted the Government of India with the appointment of Ahmad Zakl Beg al Khayyat as Iraqi Consul General at Bombay. 2. His Majesty’s Embassy note that It Is not Intended this year to disturb the arrangement by which pilgrims are allowed entry Into Iraq if provided with passes supplied by the authorities of the Government of India. 3. His Majesty’s Embassy will be glad to receive an assurance as soon as possible that the authorities of the Government of India will continue to grant Iraqi visas in cities other than Bombay, such as Karachi, Aden, Calcutta and Madras. His Majesty's Embassy avail themselves of this opportunity to renew the expression of their highest consideration. Bagdad. 24th January, 1935.COPY Or No. 66. (63/7/36) • ^RINO LfJ' .1 268’ HIS Majesty’s tbasshtior at M OFFICE baijaad presents his compliments to H.. f 8 principal Secretary of L*tate for and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned document?. ^ 8&gt; British .J.Vfi&amp;ftftlW.ii Reference to previous correspondence : Bagdad despatch No. 62 dated 24th .January, 1936. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Note No. 670 dated 2nd i eon.ary, 1936 from the i inistry of Foreign /d'TairB, Bagdad. -41 try Into Iraq of peroons carrying pilgrim passes after appointment of Iraqi Oonsul- oeneral at itombay. (Copy to the Government dated of Inuia in despatch No.63/7/35 6th February, 1936)enclosurf in 68 KO, 670, BAGDAD DESPATCH. 6.2.55. ' 1 F ministry for Foreign Affaire, Bagdad, 2nd February, 1935 . The ministry for Foreign Affaire oresent their comnliifi&amp;nts to Hie Britannic ^ajeety'e Embaeey, Bagdad, and, with reference to tho Eiabasey’e not# No.33 dated 24th January, 1935, hare the honour to elate that the ’Irac.i GOYernment agree not to dieturb the exitting procedure excepting oereone carrying Pilgriia p«eaee from obtaining entry Yieae for ’Iraq* only during the ooulng Pilrrlm eeaeon, and that the queetlon will be reconeidered at next year* a Pilgrim eeaeon, as mentioned in the ministry's note No. 219 dated 13th January, 1935, The 'Iraqi authorities concerned agree that oeraone entering 'Iraq from Karachi, Aden, Calcutta and *iadrae, not pae. ing through Bombay, may be granted 'Iraqi entry Yisan by the Indian authorities concerned. The Jainietry aY'Hil themeelves of this opportunity to exorees their highest consideration and esteem. Hia Britannic m^Jeety'e FTubaasy, BagdadENCLOCoi.L IN Bagdad despatch. OF 24.1.35. No. 52 ais ( 63/4/36)» hritinh , •fanuiiry, 1936. My hord, ith referencie to ay de*patch Ho. 139/54/34 of 13th laat, I have the honour to transwit to Yev w mllona* herewith e copy of a note which 1 have now received from the Iraqi Government Info^iin.; thut the/ have appointed Aimed }*&amp;1 leg al /liuyyat Oonsul-vrenerel at MUl gentlemen ie at present Mutaearrlf of Aerhala hiwa* 2 . lour i.xcellency will obaerve that the Iraqi Dovom- tkCnt agrte© not to ui: turb # for a year, tl'k* arrun^oaient by ehieh pllgriae iroia indla ws allowed entry into Iraq if supplied wlrtx pnaeos froai the authorities of the /overment of ^noia. It ia incorrect to ayea^c &lt;yf a i&gt;ij.gz'iL.i»^re season in this connexion, rlnce the great isaiority of pilgrims fro^ India oomti to this country not to take part in the HieJ*, or annual pilgrimage to Mecca and feuina, hut to visit the holy Cities in Iraq itself, ?md this they do all the year 'Xjund. I hfiivc not thought it necessary to call the attention of the Iraqi Government officially to this mieauprenensioA. 3. It seemed to lac deairabl©, however, to seek froci the Iraqi oovern&amp;ent an assurance that the officials of the ovi x-nwent of Xudia will continue to grant Iraqi visas at pieces o Aior tiian xjombay, and a copy of ay note on this subject is enclosed. I who 11 not fail to infona four xeellency of the reply of the Iraqi ^ovsrnfe^nt on tnia point. 4. I aa sending a copy of this despatch to His Majes ty’s Principal Secretary of Stats for foreign affairs. I have th* noneor to be Your hordship's meet obedient tq&amp;rvant. excellency The Viceroy of India, foreign I^epurtaent, tfht ^Ehia. (Sgd.J F. //. Humphry*.ENCLOSURE IN BAGDAD DESPATCH. No. b2 OF 24.1.35. Ministry for foreign i^Tfairs, xiugdad, 13th January, 1935. I^o. 219* r Tho Ministry for Foreign Affairs present their compliments to His Britannic Majesty's Embassy, Bagdad, and, with reference to the Kmbasay’s note tfo. 722 dated 13th December, 1934 have the honour to scate that the Ministry have appointed Alimad 2aki Beg al Khayyat Consul- General for the li’a^i Govemuujnt at Bombay. Ahmad Zaki Beg will proceed to the place of his appointment at the earliest possible date. fhe Ministry request the esteemed Embassy to be so good us to inform the authorities concerned accordingly, with a view to their extending to Ahmad Ziuci Beg the facilities necessary for the discharge of his duties. Mho Iraqi Government agree not to disturb the existing procedure excepting persons carrying pilgrim passes from, obtaining entry visas lor Iraq, only during the coming pilgrim season. Ihe Iraqi Government will reconsider this qiiestion at next year's pilgrim season, doing so not lose than three months before the commencement of the said season. The Ministry avail themselves of this opportunity to express their highest consideration and esteem. his Britannic a jesty r s Kmbassy, Bagdad.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003a5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3380</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003a5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3380</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 27/18 ‘Passports. Iraq. Passports for Indian pilgrims travelling to Iraq.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-20T00:17:29</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (39 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 41; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains papers relating to visas for Indian pilgrims travelling to Iraq, including papers concerning the question of whether Indian pilgrims in possession of Pilgrim Passes should be admitted into Iraq without any visa.The main correspondents are as follows: HM Ambassador, Baghdad; the Ministry for Foreign Affairs, Baghdad; and the Government of India Foreign and Political Department.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Afghanistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Visas</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003a5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>