<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024102474.0x000022_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T11:55:47.213Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">To, From, The Commissioner in Sind, No. 539 of 1870. Kurrachee. ( 7 ) The Political Superintendent, Frontier Upper Sind. Commissioner''s Office, Kurrachee, 2&gt;Qth August 1870. Sir, I have also to-day received your No. 1212, of the 27th instant. 2. Difficulties, if they exist between yourself and His Highness the Khan of Khelat, are, I must observe, entirely of your own making. Instead of adopting and maintaining a friendly attitude towards that Sovereign, as you were bound to do, and as has been the practice of every Political Super intendent on the Frontier, since the creation of that appointment, you have been led into a system of undisguised antagonism, which cannot fail to bo productive of the worst possible results^ ami which 1 must express my marked disapprobation of. 3. I am not aware from anything that has yet passed, that the Khan has acted in a manner to lead to the conclusion that he desires to ignore local &lt;D authority. The change of the Vakeel, in the case alluded to in the corres pondence forwarded by you, is by no means an unusual one, and has always been conducted in the manner described. His Highness the Khan formerly often required the presence of his Vakeel at Khelat, and when he did so, sent him orders to that effect, which the Vakeel immediately communicated to the Political Superintendent on the Frontier, mentioning the arrangements that were made for the transaction of business during his absence. It w T as always open for the Political Superintendent to object, if he wished, when His Highness was referred to, and other steps followed. The necessity of a direct application from the Khan was never considered necessary, and con sequently never entertained. 4. Comment on the tenor of your letters to the Political Agent at Khelat is not necessary, as I have fully entered on that subject in my previous letter of to-day's date. But with reference to the 5th para, of your letter No. 1212, I would call to your recollection that I both wrote and expressed my opinion that the Political Agent at Khelat should remain as much as possible with His Highness the Khan. Last year, owing to disturbances, it was con sidered expedient he should not do so, but this year there is nothing to( 8 ) prevent it, and the longer lie remains the better. Uuder these circumstances, you should have abstained from calling Captain Harrison away from Khelat, until you had at all events referred in the first instance to me. I must request therefore that you will rescind the above order, and direct Captain Harrison to remain at Khelat until further instructions are communicated to him through you. I have, &amp;c,, ; W. L. MEEEWETHER, Colonel, Commissioner in Sind. Literal translation of letter from His Highness the Khan of Khelat to Moolla Peer Bux. Whereas I have now appointed Moolla Mahomed Khan, \ akeel, to per form the duties at Kedj, and have required you in hoozoor (before me), it is ordered that, on receipt of this letter without any hesitation and excuse, be lieving my kindness to be with you, and being with settled heart, you should present yourself before me as as |bo&gt;^as possible. Ihis is my hearty desire. The execution of this order shoulcj. be considered very urgent, and acting up to it, feel yourself in duty. . Dated this 19th day of Jamatll-ool-awul 1287. 'C' p. s. —You have been ord^ed here for service under Captain Ilarrison, . leaving your brother Moolla Azeern Khan there ; you yoursell should, without loss of time, come into my presence and the Sahib above-named. (True translation) STLTJMOODIK, For Translator, Commissioner's Office. J ' \ i/ C • - . V . * v ^ • V -I No. 551 of 1870. Political Department. Commissioners Office, J r - - ' r * * ' C?' Kurrachee, 2nd September 1870. V V- -- Submitted to Government {or information, in continuation of previous correspondence. W, L. MEKEWETHER, Colonel, 1 Commissioner in Sind.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100024102474.0x000022_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/22, f 152</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024102474.0x000022</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/22, f 152</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No.539 of 1870 from Colonel William Lockyer Merewether, Commissioner in Sind, Kurrachee [Karāchi] to Colonel Robert Phayre, Political Superintendent, Frontier Upper Sind</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1870/1870</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-29T16:31:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>3 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Letter informing Colonel Phayre that any difficulties between himself and the Khan of Khelat [Kalāt] are entirely of his own making, and stating that the Khan had acted entirely in his own rights to remove the Vakeel from Phayre's court and that this was something that had often occured in the past, with the only information for British officials being notification from the Vakeel that he had been recalled to Khelat and stating who his replacement would be. There had never been any previous necessity for an application from the Khan to be required and was never entertained.The letter concludes by informing the Colonel that he should have abstained from calling Captain Harrison away from Khelat and instructing him to rescind the order and direct the Captain to remain at Khelat.Enclosed with the letter is a true translation of a letter from His Highness the Khan of Khelat to Moolla Peer Bux requesting that he present himself to the Khan as soon as possible following Moolla Mahomed Khan, Vakeel's appointment to Kedj and stating that he required him to work under Captain Harrison.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024102474.0x000022#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>