<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000235_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-05T10:35:47.197Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000235_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1248</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000235</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1248</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 7265/47 'Major R F Pemberton (enquiry about Sir Denys Bray)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-06-19T22:02:04</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (4 folios)</extent><extent>The file's contents are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 6, these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between R F Pemberton and J Ross, Secretary at the India Office in London, regarding the name of a British Political Officer. In a letter, R F Pemberton informs Ross that he is writing a short historical play regarding the evacuation of civilians from Kabul between December 1928 and February 1929, and that he wants to know the correct name of an official who features as a character in the play. The officer referred to is Sir Denys de Saumarez Bray.The file includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Playwriting</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000235#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>