<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000393_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:36:14.616Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">\ I © ir File Ho. 06a.q Correspondence regarding the land 'beneath the sea outside territoria l waters * Volumes ii From s June 1949 To: %SECRET . No.C/S- 81 . URGENT. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 8th June, 1949. To Mr. All Bustani, Clerk-in-Charge, British Agency , Sharjah. Memorandum . I am sending herewith letters to all Trucial Shaikhs except Kalba. You should open one of them and read the contents most carefully. 2. You are familiar with the question of the pos sibility of drilling for oil in the land beneath the sea outside territorial waters. You know that at the moment, the sea beyond the 3 mile limit has never been claimed by anyone. The attached proclamations are intended to be a formal claim by the various Shaikhs to the sea-bed lying off their shores, yet outside the 3 mile limit. 3. Each Shaikh should take the following action. He should publish the attached proclamation in exactly the form in which it is given. He should also sign it. He may publish it either by reading it in open Majlis, or by displaying it in a public place. If this is done, His Majesty's Government will recognise the sea-bed lying off his shores as being his by right. 4. The Shaikhs must issue their proclamations as follows: (a) Abu Dhabi : As soon as possible. You should hire any necessary transport to get down there within two days. You should inform the Medical Officer, Trucial Coast, that you will require the Ford Saloon on my instructions. Please go personally and promptly and ensure that Shaikh Shakhbut issues his proclamation immediately whilst you are still in Abu Dhabi. (b) Dubai : About 3 days after Abu Dhabi has issued their proclamation. (c) Sharjah : 1 day after Dubai. (d) Umm al Quwain, Ras al Khaimah. Aiman : At your convenience during the next week. 5. Please report by telegram to me after each Shaikh has issued his proclamation. Ask them for a letter confirming this has been done. 6. As these instructions are important, please ack nowledge receipt of this letter by sending me an immediate telegram as follows: To Political Bahrain 'Instructions received” Britagent. Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram - G.T.C. ^ rorn - Brits^gent, Sharjah - Political, Bahrain No, 557 Dated: 11th June 1949. h. Inrportant. Reference para 4 (a) of your Memorandum No. G/S- 81 dated the 8th June 1949. 2 • Letter delivered to Shaikh Shakhhut bin Sultan, Ruler of Abu Lhabi, in presence of his brothers, Hazza, Khalid and Zayid. He signed the attached proclamation in my presence and published yesterday evening in a public place during my stay in Abu Dhabi. 3. Letter of confirmation follows by bag. Britagent -Telegram G.T.C • Prom - Britagent, Sharjah To - Political, Bahrain Ho. 567 Dated: 14th June 1949. ■ ’T) ' ^ * Important• / Reference paras 4 (Id) of your Memorandum lTo*C/S- 81 dated the 8th June 1949* yS — 2* ‘ Two days ago Shaildi Said 'bin Maktum left for - X &gt; - Khamir (Persia) for a change of climate. Letter delivered to his son Rashid who sealed and signed in my presence. He y issued his proclamation at 11.00 a.m. while I was in Duhai• 3. Letter of confirmation follows hy fcag. - Britagent -Telegram - G.T.C. Hrom - Brit agent* Shar.iah To - Politic 1* Bahrain l;o. 576 Bated: 16-6-49 »&gt;U | Reference para (4) of your memorandum l'o.C/S-81 dated the 8th June. 2. Shaikh Muhamra d bin Saqr sealed and signed in my presence. He issued his proclama tion this morning. 3. Letter of confirmation follovs by bag. - Britagent -Confidential. No.C/S-127. Political Agency, Bahrain, October 13, 1949. In connexion with the sea-bed concessions I wrote to all the Shaikhdoms on July 10 last saying that if they considered that the existing oil con cession covered the submarine area they should inform me in writing. I enclose a copy of Arabic and English text of this note. 2. The replies received were varied and I enclose for your information copies in Arabic and English of those received from Abu Dhabi, Ajman, Umm al Quwain, Dubai and Has al Khaimah and of two replies received from Sharjah. 3. As you will see the Abu Dhabi and Ras al Khaimah replies are quite satisfactory and although Dubai goes off the rails in the first sentence of the s econd para graph the error is corrected in the last paragraph. The Sharjah reply is inconclusive; Ajman and Umm al Quwain do not seem to have understood the point at issue. Would you therefore take an early opportunity of explaining the matter to these three Shaikhs and get a proper reply out of them? You will of course appreciate that we do not wish to influence them one way or the other. For your information I add that the point of the enquiry is so that we can tell P.C.L. exactly where they stand. Naturally any proposed fresh concessions would have to be referred to us for approval. P.D. Stobart, Esq., Political Officer, Trucial Coast Sharjah.@ 16 2 P.S. In case there is no copy of the Ajman agreement in your archives I send one herewith. You will notice that territorial waters are not specifically mentioned although the Political Resident considers the expression 'territories” might be held to cover them. Sir Rupert thinks the Company will have to take up the matter with the Ruler and try to reach an agreement with him on the subject if they think it worth while. This will depend, l^ er alia, on the reply now given by Ajman.I Translation of letter dated the 16th Shuwal, 1368, equi valent to the 11th August, 1949, from Shaikh Said bin Maktum, «uler of Dubai to Mr. H.G. Jakins, H.B.M's Political Agent, After Compliments: Reference your letter No.C/S-93 dated the 10th July, 1949, equivalent to the 14th Ramadhan, 1368, in which you referred to Mr. Felly’s letter No.C/S-65 dated the 30th ^ay 1949 equivalent to 2nd Sha’ban, 1368, regarding our discussion with the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, in connection with the submerged area' outside the three mile territorial waters You mantioned that His Excellency the Political Resident has given us full authority to grant a concession for the submerged area about which we issued a notice and to any company. You also mentioned that we should not grant any conditional concession within the extent of the present con cession, but should be subject to any rights that may be proved according to the contents of the present concession in order to avoid failure in case of arbitration between us and the company given the concession. We confirm emphatically to Your Excellency that the new submerged area is not included in the present concession but is a novelty and that it may have its separate concession and we will not give any company a concession that may abuse or injure the rights of the present company. company for the new area we would submit to you the terms agreed to before the signature is made to enable to you to inform His Excellency the Political Resident and obtain his approval. limit. When the negotiations are made between us and any other Usual ending.P.C.L. AJMN CONCESSION. Translation. This Agreement was concluded at Ajman on the first day of the month of Saphar, 1358, A.H., corresponding to the 23rd day of the month of March 1939 A.D., between His Excellency Shaikh Rashid bin Humaid, Ruler of Ajman and its territories (hereinafter called M the Ruler')) of the one part) and Mr. B.H. Lermitte for Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., (a British Company registered in London), hereinafter called 'the Company', of the other part; and agreement has been reached as follows:- (1) Ihe expression 'the Ruler' includes both the present Ruler and any Ruler to whom may in the future belong the ad ministration of Ajman and its territories. (2) The Ruler grants to the Company an exclusive right for the search for mineral oils and similar substances within the Territories subject to his rule and under his administration as Ruler of Ajman and its territories. The Company may employ all the means of search and exploration. The Ruler undertakes to assist the Company and protect its employees and property to the full extent of his ability; but the Company shall have no right to claim against the Ruler for any damage in respect of any failure to comply with this obligation. (3) Whenever the Company, after its explorations, shall be persuaded of the existence of oil within the territory, an Agreement shall in such case be concluded between the Ruler and the Company with the consent and free choice of both, to cover all that concerns the rights end obligations (which shall exist) between the Ruler and the Company. (4) This Agreement shall remain effective from the date of signature until the end of its period. But the Company shall have no right by any means to search on any territory, of our territories, but after a written or verbal permission (is given). (5) The Company shall pay to the Ruler within twenty days from the signature of the Agreement fifteen thousand rupees (Rs.15000) in respect of the first year, and after the end of that year shall pay three thousand rupees (Rs.3000) every three months in advance. (6) The Company shall have the right to surrender the whole.of its rights end obligations arising out of this Agree ment at any time after the passage of one whole year following signature, after giving three months written notice. (7) The period provided for the exploration under this Agreement is five years, and at the end of that period if the studies and explorations of the Company are not completed, and itx requires an additional period to complete them, then the Company shall have the right to a prolongation of the period for one further year. (8) (a) The Company undertakes that its personnel shall not interfere in the government of the country or in any thing which may injure the local administration. And if any aggression happenedhappened by any of the native labourers belonging to either of the two parties within our territory, the action (to be taken) will be according to the formality of the Mohammedan Shari*s (law) in our country. (b) The Company shall pay the salaries of the guards who shall protect the exploration personnel, and the number of such guards shall be fixed by agreement between the two parties according to the conditions and circumstances. Signature Signature For Petroleum Development Ruler of Aiman (Trucial Coast) Ltd. B.K. Lermitte. Rashid bin Humaid. Witness. Witness Ali Tajir B.H. Lermitte.Confidential. No.C/S-137. Political Agency, Bahrain, October 27, 1949. My note No.C/S-130 of October 15. 2. I send herewith a copy of the Arabic text and English translation of the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi*s re ply. 3. He has not produced the undertakings required in paragraph 5 of my letter of September 7 No.C/S-114 and he does not seem to realise that the matter has now passed into the hands of the Political Resident. 4. Will you please explain and get the desired undertakings in writing. If he were to give then to you in unsealed letters so that you could check them it might save time. P.D. Stobart, Esq., Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. VvWTranslation of letter dated the 5th Dhil Hajjah, 1368 (28.9.49) from the Ruler of Abu Dhabi to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After compliments: We have received your letter dated the 7th September, 1949, corresponding to the 14th Dhil Qa’dah, 1368, in which you mentioned that the Company claim sea-bed rights and that they wish to proceed to arbitration. We inform Your Excellency that there is absolutely no mention or any suggestion of the sea-bed in the agreement. The Company's statement that we had not replied to the letters they addressed to us in the matter until the date fixed for appointment of arbitrators expired is against the fact as evidenced by the letters exchanged between us and the Company - copies of which are in our possession and the Company's. We received a letter dated the 7th June, 1949, equivalent to the 23rd Sha'ban, 1368, from the Company before the expiry of the period to which we sent a reply asking the Company to appoint an arbitrator on their behalf so that we might take similar line in turn, but our letter met with no success until the 18th July. 1949, corresponding to the 23rd Ramadhan, 1368, and so because of this that the time lapsed. And if the Company compel us to go to litigation, the place of arbitration will certainly be London and we shall appoint as our arbitrator one of the barristers, with whom we shall establish contacts to furnish him with details of our case. If the Company have a claim to make then we shall have ours and we shall place the Company's concession before the judging body for 1 scrutiny. The Company is free to choose her way but the qu&lt; stion of arbitration which you referred to should wait until such time as we deem appropriate to take up. Usual ending.,./2 yVo - -/•■/' 1 ' // No. C/S-144. Political Agency, Bahrain. H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The P.O.T.C., Sharjah, and forward herewith a copy of the undermentioned document(s) Reference to previous correspondence; Paragraph 3 of Mr. Jakins' S.O.No.C/S-127 of 13-10* 49 Description Translation of letter No.14 of 2nd November, 1949, from Shaikh Muhammad bin Saqr Al-Qasim, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Subj ect Sea-bed rights. Dated November 8, 1949Translation of letter No.14, dated the 10th Muharrara, 1369, (2-11-49) from Shaikh Muhammad bin Saqr Al-Qasim, brother of the Ruler of Sharjah (now acting as Deputy Ruler), to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After compliments: Reference your letter No.C/S-94, dated the 14th Ramadhan, 1368, corresponding to the 10th July, 1949, in which you referred to His Excellency Mr. ^elly* s letter No.C/S-66 of 30th May, 1949. that. We hereby declare that we do not recogniseConfidential. D.O.No.982-063? British Agency, Sharjah, Dated,2nd November,1949. Will you please refer to Jakins letter No.C/S 130 about the proposed arbitration over the Abu Dhabi sea-bed. 2. On 30th October, I spoke to Shaikh Shakhbut on the lines suggested by Jakins and handed him the revised translation. The Shaikh said that he replied to Jakins letter on 28th September 1949 and that he casually handed in his reply at one of the P.C.L.camps. There is, therefore, every reason to suppose th-t this letter must hav§ gone 9 ladX astray. He gave me, however, a copy of which translation is attnrhed• 3. You will notice that his reply completely evades the issue. I asked the Shaikh what his real reason was for adopting this evasive attitude. He replied that he was trying to delay arbitration until such time as his finances allow him to face any sort of legal costs without fear. At present, he said, he could not guarantee to pay the fees of a King's Counsel as the Political Agent suggested. I gather that the Rs.400,000 loan made by P.C.L. in June of this year has largely been expended already on consolidating his position in Buraimi. I think also he is hoping that Superior Oil Company will eventually engage and pay his King's Counsel for him. He then said that he wished, at the same time, to put to arbitration a number of other point? in the concession. I asked him what points he had in mind, but he was unable to specify them. He said, however, that the concession was 'full of injustices'. T^is attitude on his part dates from the first visit of Sir Hugh^in March 1949 and at that time, both Pelly and I had good reason to believe that Sir Hugh had deliberately, and with the authority of a former Government Servant, convincingly, put into/--I Q.V - 2 - intp Shakhbut's mind the idea that the P.C.L. concession was a piece of trickery from beginning to end, Lermitte has probably told you of the difficulties which the Abu Dhabi Shaikhs have been creating for the Company in their recent operations, Shakhbut has appointed a number of guard commanders to the camps in his territory, and at Ghanadha and Ras Sadr, these men, (who try to affect the title of Emir after the model of the Saudi guard commander in ARAMCO Camps), deliberately try to create trouble among the Abu Dhabi labourers. There have been numerous petty strikes over trivial issues. Apart from this, visits to the camps by the Ruler's relatives often result in similar ill-feeling. Protests by the Company have only resulted in increased friction. 5. I have visited the three camps of the Company with Mr.Henderson, the Dubai Dubai Representative of P.C.L. and it is my impression that, whilst the strikes, on the whole, are the result of deliberate interference by the Shaikh's guards, the standard of administration in the camps might well be improved. For example, the water distilling plants at Ras Sadr are unreliable and I think that the complaints about lack of water may have some foundation. Well water could easily be delivered in dhows if necessary. I learned that sufficient cooking utensils are only just arriving in camps which have been established for two months. I suggested to ■ Mr. Henderson that he would strengthen the Company's position by looking to such points as food, water and living conditions. He replied that he had been asking for a Camp Administrative Officer to be sent to take charge, but that his company had not found him one as yet. 6 . Hitherto, P.D.(T.C.) have been accustomed to dealing direct with the Trucial Coast Shaikhs on all matters except the those requiring H.M.G's intervention or sanction on some specific point. This practice was acceptable to all parties • as/-as long as the Company's activities were limited to survey work, but Henderson agrees that the only hope of improved relations at present lies in our insisting that all complaints of a major nature by either the Ruler or the Company, be made through the Political Officer, Trmcial Coast. Ty&gt;is is a nuisance, in that the Agency is some 80 miles from the camps and some 100 miles from Abu Dhabi town, but in the interests of stopping trivial complaints and petty interference on the one hand, and of providing some sort of disinterested check on living conditions on the other, it is a procedure which X am bound to recommend. 7. I propose, subject to your approval, to inform the Ruler firstly that the P.C.L.concession was made with H.M.G’s approval, and that H.M.G. is interested in ensuring that its terms are carried out by both sides. (The Shaikh has been trying tp propagate the story that because the Agreement bears no signature by H.xM.G^ representative, it is purely a private document as between himself and P.C.L.). Secondly, I propose to tell him that all complaints or requests concerning the Company of anything but a routine nature should be made through the P.O.T.C. and that under no circumstances should his guards or relatives interfere with the operations in the various camps. I should be grateful for your instructions. J.A.F.Gethin, Esquire, H.B.M's Political Agent, BAHRAIN.Translation of letter dated the 5th ]Dhul Hajjah 1368 (28-9-1949) frora Shaikh Shakhhut bin Sultan^ Ruler of Abu Ihabif to the Political Agent* Bahrain* After CoinpliraentB. I acknovledge the receipt of your letter dated the 7th September 1949 equivalent to the 14th Phul Qa f adah 1368 in which you stated that the Company wishes to go to arbitration and claims certain rights to the sea-bed* I write to inform you that there is no mention what soever of any type of sea-bed in the Agreement* A&amp; regards the Company , 8 statement that I sent no reply to the letters %friich they had sent to me on this subject until the expiry of the time allowed for the appointment of an arbitrator* this is against truth and facts* The Company and myself have the letters exchanged between us* I received from them a letter dated the 20th June 1949 corresponding to the 23rd Sha f aban 1368 and before the expiry of the limited time I sent them a reply and asked them to appoint an arbitrator for me in order to rank with them but my letter met no success until the 18th July 1949 corresponding to the 23rd Ramadhan 1368* This is the cause for the expiry of the period* If the Company compels me to enter into litigation with them it is certain that the place at which arbitration is to take place will be London* I will appoint as an arbitrator one of the advocates of the Courts of Justice and will be in direct contact with the proceedings and details of my case. Instead of the Company 1 s claim to what I Have (right to) I will claim from them my rights and will subject their Concession to examination and criticism without prejudice to both sides* The Company has rights and obligations and has to choose either this or that. The question of arbitration to which I refer is to be postponed until such time as I find appro priate for carrying out what is necessary* Usual Ending*-™'*i ■ \( ■ ^ 0 . 17th December, 1949. POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN, No. C/S-155. C&lt;—^ Please refer to your letter No.982.0630 of the 2nd November, 1949. 2. Please explain to Shaikh Shakhbut as in Jakins' letter No. C/S-137 of the 27th October and press for his written reply agreeing to meet the cost of the arbitrator selected on his tehalf, however large a sum may be involved, and to meet his share of tne cost of any referee that it may be necessary to appoint according to the terms of his agreement with Petroleum Concessions Limited. 3. You may also address him in the terms pro posed by you in the first sentence of paragraph 7 of your letter under reference. P.D. Stobart, Esquire, Political Officer,. Trucial Coast,Confidential &amp; Personal: D«0 »No • -0629 HUTISH AGENCY, SHARJAH, JANUAHY 10, 1950. Dear Henderson, The Shaikhs of Has al Khaimah have approached me for advice over the question of arbitration for the sea-bed of their territory. They are at a loss to understand Why your Company is calling them to arbitration, when they have not been approached by any other Company with a view to a sea-bed concession. F understand all Rulers have now been likewise called to arbitration. ^ have given them no advice beyond explaining to them roughly what arbitration involves, anc. I h^ve deliberately avoided dwelling unduly upon the he vy expense and difficulty involved in engaging i mgs Counsels in London, because I do not suppose your Company intends to take them to arbitration in .London employing expert legal and, the expenses of which none o- the Shaikhs other than Dubai and Abu- Dhabi would be able to afford unaided. Would you please confirm that this is so ? 3. It would be outside my province to try to offer your Company unsolicited advice in the raanage- r nt of its own affairs, but I cannot help observing that your action in calling the Rulers to arbitration at this time, is open to unfortunate misinterpretation and liable to harm the good relations with the Shaikhs which you and your predecessors have worked so hard to maintain. It would be difficult to convince those lesser Rulers of the Trucial Coast, who have not as yet been approached by any other Company, that your object is merely to clarify the present uncertain status of the sea-bed which has accrued to them. They are, unfortunately more liable to fear that you intend to hustle them through arbitration before they are able to enjoy, as they no doubt think Abu Dhabi enjoys, the advice and support of an outside Oil Company. This, I am sure is not the case. 4. I should like to make clear that the views which I have expressed in this letter are not necessarily those of H.L.G. to whom, as far as I know, the question has not been referred. I h?ve no objection, however, to your quoting me as having expressed them, provided you at the same time point out their unofficial nature. Yours sincerely, lf/&lt;&gt; E. Henderson, Esquire, Representative, Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., Dubai.^ Wzl i o I ^^ 1 ^ 1 ^ ^ Jj. Jl ^ co ii I Translation of letter dated the 12th .labia 1 al Thani 1369 (30-1-50) from Shaikh Shakhbut bin Sultan, Ruler of Abu- Dhabi, to .Mr. F.D. Stobart, the Political Officer, Trucial Coast. After Compliments. 1950 corresponding to the 25th Rabia 1 al Av/v/al 1369. You mentioned that you have received a letter from the Political Agent, Bahrain, about arbitration betv/een me and the Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, and you mentioned that an arbitrator will be appointed on behalf of me by the Political Resident. I have to inform you that I did not request His Excellency the Political Resident and the Political Agent and I did not authorize them in thing like th:,s. The place of arbitration between me and the Petroleum Development (Trucial Coa^t) Limited is in London. I am prepared to resist against the Company which do concern me. This is an important thing to my right and concern my own affair. I have received your letter dated the 14th January Usual Ending.Translation of letter dated the 12th Rabia 1 al Thani 1369 (30-1-50) from Shaikh Shakhbut bin Sultan, Ruler of Abu Dhabi, to Mr. P.D. Stobart, the Political Officer, Trucial Coast. After Compliments. I have received your letter dated the 14th January 1950 corresponding to the 25th Rabia 1 al Awval 1369. You mentioned that you received a letter from the Political Agent, Bahrain, concerning arbit ration between me and the Petroleum Develo ment (Trucial Coast) Limited. You mentioned that an arbitrator will be appointed on my behalf by the Political Resident. I inform you that I did not make such a request to His Excellency the Political Resident and the Political Agent and did not authorize them to do anything of this sort. The place of arbitration will be in London and I am prepared to defend myself against the Company. This deeply concerns my own rights which are my own business. Usual Ending.British Agency , Confiden tial. Sharjah, D.0.No.hl-v-i&gt;ei'.9. February 20,l&amp;o0. Dear Felly, Your letter C/S-156 of 17th December 1949 ebout Abu Dhabi*s arbitration with PeC.L. 2# I have tackled the Shaikh both verbally and in writing on this subject, but he still claims to be unable to pay the large sums involved in arbitration by King Councils and therefore has failed to give a satisfactory reply. I do not consider there is much chance of his agreeing to undertake his own case when he hears of Superior Oil Company's parti cipation in the ^atar arbitration and of their promise to do so in the case of Dubai. 3. Smith of Superior has not appeared as he promised, and I think that Shakhbut's inflated deraand-s have probably made his Company decide to leave the concession alone for the while, but the Shaikh probably still hopes that they will eventually prepare his case at arbitration for him. When one considers the al bu Falah's ignorance of the outside world, it might be as well in the long run if Superior, or whichever Company obtains a conditional concession for the Sea Bed does undertake to provide the Shaikhs legal advice. I cannot see much progress being made if a Council of brothers decide to go to London and brief their own Kings Council! 4. It is unfortunate that this question should still be hanging fire, as it has the effect of straining relations between the Shaikh and the Company at a time when the Company can least afford bad relations. 5. The well at Ras Sadr was 'spudded in' on 16th February after a ceremony at which the Shaikh and I were present, we stayed the night in a special Camp and the excelJent hospi tality arranged by the Company did.much to restore their former good relations. It was, therefore, doubly unfortunate that on the next day, Brigadier Longrigg, accompanied by Lermitte and Jackson, having arrived by air at Sadr, and after shaking hands with Shakhbut at the landing-strip, should have studiously end obviously avoided him in the Camp and taken off again without a word of warning or explanation or without even taking leave. As I myself had been invited to return to Sharjah in the same aircraft, the Shaikh felt that both of us had been treated in rather cavalier fashion. I sent a message to Longrigg suggesting he might at least call in on the Shaikh on his way back to Bahrain, but he could not see his way to doing this. He may feel I rather exceeded my duty in trying to teach the Chief of I.P.CIS siyassin how to behave towards Shaikhs, but if there is ever any ill feeling between the Shaikh and the Company, I invariably find myself in the position of having to pull the company's chestnuts out of the fire , and I therefore felt that my intervention was not entirely out of place, particularly as the incident was quite unnecessary. Yours sincerely, sd.P.D.Stobart. ,C.J.Felly, Esq., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain.British Agency# COKYIifciHTlAL: Sharjah# Ko.l96»0c{29 February 21# 1^50* Dear Agency# Ve forward herewith the following document bj (a) A letter dated 18th February from Shaikh Said bin Maktum of IXib&amp;i to HiB Excellency the Political Resident together with 3 enclosure* ft* (b) Tranfllations of the above for Political Residen 1 (c) A spare set of translations for your file. All concern arbitration with Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited* 2 . You will note that the Shaikh claims only the sea-bed outside territorial waters# 3 # The Shaikh has behaved most correctly in this matter both as regards Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited# and as reg rds H#M#G# 4 # He informs us that the only agreement vfaich he has made so far with Superior is an agreement to negotiate a Concession with them assuming a evccessful issue to the arbitration# You will note that Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited have to nominate their arbitr tor before 9th April ( 60 days from 8th February)# and in the event of their failing to do so# presumably the Shaikh will ask the Political resident to do so 0 n their behalf# Yours ever# ghar^ah#v Translation of letter dated the 25th Kabia* al Thani 1369 (13-2-50) froi?? Shaihh Said bin Midctuin f O.B.E*, - ul^r of Dubai, to Sir Hup rt Hay, His I^xcellency the Politic 1 Resident in the Persi n U ulf, Bali rain. After CompliiDentB. I beg to inform Your Excellency that on 16th Safar 1369 corresponding to 7th December 1949, ve sent a letter to the Representative of The Petroleum Development ( i, ruci&amp;l Coast) Limited and herewith a copy of it. And on 13th vabia* al Avwal 1369 corres ponding to the 3rd January 1950, *e sent a second letter to him and herewith a copy of it. On 12th uibia* al Thani 1369 corresponding 31st January 19. F 0, we appro-ched the Represent tive of the Company and we discussed verbally the matters touching our rights which are mentioned in the 2 letters attached. And we informed him in our discussion that we have selected as arbitrator in the arbitration between us and the Company, Hr. Pox Andrews, K.C. On 20th Rabin* al Th ini 1369 corresponding to the 8th February 1950, we confirmee in writing of our choice of the abovementioned arbitrator. And we asked him to inform us of his owe arbitrator’s name, in wr5tlng and I rend you a copy of this letter of mine a} so. Therefore, I wish to inform ycu of the above. U- ual Ending.U.cb^- 1 Tranal tion of letter (7-12-49) frrm Shaikh of Dubai, to Mr. E.H. Petroleum Beveloprent dated the 16th Safar 1369 Said bin Kaktutt* Ruler Lermitte, Repreeentative of The (Trueial Coast) Lirited. After Compliments# Reference your letter PTC/TS/10/19/7287 dated tAe 10th April 1949 corresponding to the 12th Jamadi al- Thani 1368# I declare that vhat I understand from your letter io contrary to the truth because I did not agree cither verbally or in writing to what you mention regarding the sea and submerged lands outside the Coastal boundaries# It \ ac not set cut in the existing Agreement between us both* as we do not agrie wither verbally or in writing th at tho Vc.-t yre^l^lng oi^tside the Coastal waters ( ' ) ox* that the sea-bed or the subsoil lying under it outside a boundary o 3 miles* cither in past* present or future are included in the Agreement. Ueu-1 endingTranel tion of letter dated the 13th Ko/bia* al A%»val 1369 (3-1-60) from ShalWi S&amp;id bin Kaktum* Ruler of Dubii# to Itfr. i.H* Lermitte, Representative of The Petroleum Develo ment (Trucial Coaet) Limited* After Cornplirrents. V.e draw ycur attention to our letter of 16tn Safar 136S corresponding to the 7th December 1949. In reply to your letter TSL/17/8831 of 11th December 1949 cor responding to the 20th Safar 1369* I do not maintain what the Company maintains concerning possession of sea and submerged lacds outside the Coastal boundaries, near the ter itorial [ 1 i/atora. I do not belter* that the Agreement eontair.e ur -j-tV,trig of that sort, /.nd should any dispute arise between us in this cornexion I do not ob. ect to reBortii.fe tc arbitration. Usu 1 tending^ctxr^^ - Transl ition of letter dated the 20th Rabia* al Thani 1369 (8-2-50) from Shaikh Said bin Maktunif O.L*x.«# Ruler of Dubai, to Mr. D.F. Henderson, Manager of The Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited. * After Compliment e. » \ve sent you tvo letters the first 16th Safar 1369 corresponding 7th December 1949 and the second on 13th Rabia* al Awval 1369 corresponding 3rd January 1950. Ve confirred that ve did not admit (your contention) On 12th Rabia 1 al Thani 1369 corresponding 31st January 1950, we approached you at the Company’s house and explained to you the natters touching our rignts in the sea-bed and the sub-soil beneath the sea outside the boundary of 3 miles of the territorial Coastal vaters. Ve informed you verbally that we appointed on our behalf n arbitrator in the arbitration Mr. Fox Andrews, K.C. And now we confirm to you in writing that we have appointed the above mentioned as arbitrator in this case as you should inform us of the name of your own arbitrator in writing and we are awaiting your answer. Usual Ending,October 15, 1949. I send herewith a copy in Arabic and English of letter No.C/S-114 of September 7 that I addressed to the Ruler of Abu Dhabi about the proposed arbitration on the question of sea-bed rights to which I have received no reply. I now notice that the expression King’s Counsel has been mistranslated as ” . In English of course it means a barrister who is so eminent that he is given the honorific title of King's Counsel for which he has I believe the privilege of performing legal services to His Majesty free of charge'. The point to make is that when acting for any one except His Britannic Majesty his charges are extremely heavy. vVe have now changed the translation to II l_£ ^-&gt;*0 I dJU I dj (^&gt;1^ ,Jw3 UJ i J ^ U-&gt;J ^ CrS* 1 JL&gt;- I ' • « The translation of eminence in paragraph 4 as '2 ; »' is again not too happy and we have changed this to ' a j —&amp;— Finally I see that the real meaning of however in paragraph 5 was missed and this passage has now been changed to '' Iq1*«J 1 j I «JLU 1.- 11 . I think you had better substitute the present translation for he earlier one explaining the position to the Shaikh where necessary and, above all, getting a written reply out of him. P.D. Stobart, Esq., Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. L* *</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000393_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/4/9</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000393</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/4/9</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 0629 Correspondence regarding the land beneath the sea outside territorial waters'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-03T10:48:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (45 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 47; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-44; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding the issue of oil concession grants for land beneath the sea beyond the three mile territorial limit. The correspondence is principally between the British Agency at Sharjah, the Political Agency at Bahrain, and the ruling shaikhs of the Trucial Coast [United Arab Emirates].The matters covered by the file include:British instructions to the Trucial shaikhs to make claims to the subsoil of the seabed beyond the three mile limit;the case of arbitration between Petroleum Concessions Limited and individual shaikhs over whether this potential extension of territory was included in the original 1939 concessions.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Territorial waters</topic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Trucial Coast</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000393#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>