<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000080_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T01:37:14.888Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">4 • I ■ m J TX THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Isi^nd, Persian Gulf, December 20, 1938 His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Sir, We enclose British passports of employees as per attached list for Registration for the year 1939 and return. The necessary registration fees are sent herewith. Yours very truly, Snclos: Chief TirE B..HK .GK Representative tQLEDM CCI-tPAN? LTD.Imperial Airways Ltd. Bahrain, i+th January, 1939. The Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir I am forwarding herewith Passports Nos. 90810 and 91757 and the sum of Rupees Two only as registration fee, with a renust to have the necessary entries made in .the passports and and sent to me at your convenience. No. 90810 S. P. Bernhardt No. 91757 Mrs. M. A. Bernhardt Thanking you in anticipation. Yours faithfully, End:— 2 S.P.BESITHARDTIMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD. BAHRAIN ISLANDS PERSIAN GULF Codes : Bentley's &amp; I.A.T.A. Telenkone : 43M nr i . * t&gt; ' lelegrams : Airways, t5 aPH/P.2/20 4th January, 1939. The Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I enclose herewith the following passports for registration together with tiie sum of Rs# 3/— In payment of relative fees:- G.P.Hayward Passport 0.72656 ) L.G.Hearson Passport 5092/ T. Millard Passport 71857] If possible I should be grateful if an unofficial receipt could be forwarded in order to support my debit. Yours faithfully, For IMPEBiyiL AIRWAYS. LTD., STATION SUPSRINfENDENT. End:the Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali, B ahrein I sland, P ersian G ulf, No. PA-109. January 9, 1939 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein* Dear Sir, Me enclose British and British Indian passports of employees as per list attached for registration and return* The necessary registration fees are also enclosed* Yours very truly Einclos Chiet THE B VHRE kb#the Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. NO;PA-110. January 14, 1939. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We enclose British and British Indian passports of employees as per list attached for registration and return. The necessary registration fees are also enclosed. Yours very truly. Chie The Bahre ck Representative leuni Company Limited. Ends: M(llir (ta^trru ^ank.Wimtt^. ALL LITTERS TO BC ADDRESSED TO THE EASTERN BANK LIMITED. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS EASTERTIDE. ( I N C OP PORAT ED IN ENGLAND.) / 11th January 39, The Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear f^ir, We enclose Joint Passport TTo» 107023 of Ifr. A: Tfrs. M, A. Ranookapathy for favour of necessary i-e^stretion and return. A sun of ^e.l/- Is sent herewith f or t his purijose.The Bahrein petroleum company limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. NO:PA-112 . January 14, 1939. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, It would be much appreciated if you would please return to us the passport of Mr. D.E. McRobb^ after registration by Tuesday, January 17th. We are sending herewith Mr. D.E.McRobb f passport and the necessary registration fee. Yours very truly. Chief The Bahrein BI^CK Representative jtroleuiii Company Limited. M.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, February 19, 1939. No;PA-152. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, Me enclose British and British Indian passports of employees as per list attached for registration and. return. The necessary registration fees are also enclosed. Yours very truly. •—BUTiCK Chiejf I^cal Representative The Bahi^jin Petroleum Company Ltd. Ends: M.4 o THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awall ( Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, N0;PA-131 « Januairy 26, 1939. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We enclose British and British Indian passports of employees as per list attached for registration and return. The necessary registration fees are also enclosed. Yours very truly, J.S. BLACK Chief Local Representative The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. Ends: M.w i Dear A.L,0., Bahrain. JA!\L 1939 \ « ference to our tele phone conversation yesterday I att ach a list of the British Indians employed by A.M.W.D. in Bahrain whose ^ passports have been sent to Basrah. We will send you their pass ports for registration when we rec- eive them from Basrah. Many thanks for the very speedy delivery of the drink chit, come and have some of it sooni LO - ^ J ' fr- cPolitical Agency, Bahrain, the 18th March 1939. To The Secretary to the Hon 'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. v'l \J Memorandum . Reference your memorandum No. 138/7/17 dated the 19th January 19r%. 2. I enclose statements in respect of Bahrain and Qatar, and the Trucial Coast. for Political Agent, Bahrain• OL^- ( ^ ^ iPolitical Agency, Bahrain, the 9th January 1939• The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I return herewith Bombay passport No- 112849 of de Souza which was produced before me in an arbitration case. 2. I note that this passport had not been registered at the Agency for 1938, and possibly there are other private servants of members of your Company whose passports have also not been sent for registration. I hope, therefore, that you will ensure that private employees of British Indian aubjects are acquainted with the contents of my notice No. 2023 dated the 26th December 1938 on this subject. Yours faithfully. IM si ' r for Political Agent, Bahrain.ITo. 2229-13/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 18th December 1939• To The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Please refer to correspondence resting with your letter No. PCL/AL-9/3 ;43 dated the 14th January 1939. 2. Will you kindly send me as soon as possible any corrections in the statement of British subjects etcetera at Qatar? Yours faithfully, k for Political Agent, Bahrain.2223-13/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 18th December 1939. To The Residency Agent, Sharjah. Memorandum Reference paragraph 3 of Circular No. 1296 dated the 9th July 1937 from the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf^Ccopy forwarded under this office printed / letter No. 1672 dated the 31st July 1937). 2. Please forward a statement of British, British Indian and British protected subjects on the Trucial Coast. for Political Agent, Bahrain. Ac ^/vi 13/1. Political Agency, . Bahrain, the 19th December 1939. NOTICE British subjects residing within the limits of Bahrain are reminded that they should register themselves at the Political Agency within the first week of January of each year or within one month of their arrival in Bahrain. 2. Persons already registered should apply for a renewal of their registration within the first week of January of each year, 3. The fee for each registration or renewal is Re.,1/-. 4. A British subject neglecting to obtain registration shall not be entitled to be recognised or protected as a British subject and shall be liable to a fine not exceeding 25/- for each instance of such failure. for Political Agent, Bahrain.i a To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I hare the honour to send herewith the following passports for registration. As these pasapprts^belong to Grovermnent servants on duty at this station'-, 1 presume, they will be exempted from registration fees. I may mention, for your kind information that under (xovernment of India certain notification, bonafide goTermnent servants are even exempted from passport fees. 1 V I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant (i) Passport of Mr. K.P. Chakravaty. (ii) ' (iii) • (iv) 11 ^ Mr.&amp; Mrs. G-. Ramaswamy * Mr. &amp; Mr s. Z .H. Kh an ' Mr. P. Beg. ^0' t55&gt;'3\Tb- | ^ i iy fh- I/o.; Pilot Bullooa Observatory, BAHRAINL IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD. BAHRAIN ISLANDS | v t) PERSIAN GULF Cojes : Bentley's &amp; I.A.T.A. Telephone : 43M BA.H /V3220 /P .2. Telegrams ; Airways, Bali t ain 28th.December,1939. The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, With reference to your notice number 2238/13/1 of the 19th»December, I enclose the following passports for registration:- Place of Issue Number LONDON LONDON LONDON OTTAWA RAJKOT KARACHI KARACHI BOMBAY 152501 - , 3152U0 178717 &gt; 71857 v-' W.I,s.A /10050 kOQ 11023 , 90810 J,' Name Mr. H.J.M.Stuart-Wortley Sir.E.S.Moore Bt. Mr. E.H.Macquarie Mr. T. Millard Mr. M.T.Sheth Mr. C.^'Sylva Mr. L.A.Sass Mr. S.P.Bernhardt The sum of Rs.8/- to cover the cost is enclosed. Kindly acknowledge receipt of the passports on the enclosed copy of this letter, and return them as soon as convenient. Yours faithfully. Station Superintendent. CD.Form 103 C. 3.38. TELEGRAMS; PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES: BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS: Lord Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) G. Legh-Jones R. Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Frajer. C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenklan (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy J, A. Meny (French) H. G. Seldel (U.S.A.) R, W. Sellers J, Skliros PCL/AI.9/5865 BAHREIN PERSIAN 2nd January, 1940. I H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, BRITISH SUBJECTS &amp; BRITISH PROTECTED PERSONS - QAT a R With reference to your No.2229-13/1 dated 21/12/39. We forward herewith the revised numbers; (a) British Subjects ... 6 (b) British Indian Subjects 9 (c) British protected persons Americans 5 Portuguese Indians ... 7 Somali 1 Iraqis 4 Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED M u MANAGER. ACMNo•1 ^41-13/1 Political Agency, Bahrain* 13th June, 1940• To The Secretary to the Hor^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Buahire • Menaor^rid^iU Reference your reminder No •768-21/44 dated the 6th June, 1940• 2* I enclose sLateiaenta in respect of Bahrain and tar, and tae Trucial Coast* for Political \gent, Bahrain. ■k ^&lt;LStatement showing approximate number of (a) British Subject (b) British Indian objects (c) British Indian Protected Persons living in Bahrain and Qatar and the number employed in oil as on 31st December 1939. KaM of stati n British subjects Oil - Otherwise• British Indian Subjects Cil - Otherwise British Indian Prot ec ted subjects . Oil Otherwise. Total —— Bahrain .a tar 191 65 335 9 737 72 (a) British Subjects (b) ^riti sh Indian subjects (c) British Indian Protected subjects 262 .. 1081 72 Grand Total .. 1415Statement showing approximate number of (a) British Subjects (b) British Indian Subjects (c) British Indian Protected lersons living on the Trucial Coast and the number employed in oil as on Slst December 1930• Kame of station Abu Jhabi Duliai S'iaxvjah Ajc®31 Un al u /a in Has ? 1 F. iairaah Kalbn British subjects Oil - Otherwise# 12 BriLish Indian sub.iects British Indian Pro tected Persons * Oil - Otherwise oTl - Otherwise I ota 1 6 60 253 (a) British subjects* 12 (b) British Indian subjects* 329 (c) British Indian Protected Persons* - Grand Total : 341No•2387—13/1—III Political Agency, Bahrain. 26th December, 1940• N 0 T I C British subjects residing within the limits of Bahrain are reminded that they should register themselves at the Political Agency within the first week of January of each year or within one month of their arrival in Bahrain. Persons already registered should apply for a renewal of their registration within the first week of January each year. The ^ee for each registration or renewal is Hs.l/-* A British subject neglecting to obtain registration / v shall not be entitled to be recognised or protected as a British subject and shal3. be liable to a fine not exceeding fis.26/- for each instance of such failure. Sd/- R* !• Hallows. for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to j- . l.The Adviser to the Bahrain Government. \ X2.The Air Liaison Officer. 3.The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer. - 4.The Director of Education. 6.The iitate Medical Officer. 6.The State Engineer. X^.The Defence Officer. - 8.The quarantine redical Officer- 9.The Observersin-Charge. 10.The Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd^, 11.The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited 12.The Eastern Bank Limited© 13.The British Overseas Airways Corporation.v 14.The Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd.^V N 15.The California Arabian Standard Oil jCompany® 16.The Petroleum Concession Limited, v 17.Messrs. Halloway Brosi ^IS.The Sub—Postmaster. •19.The Arabian Mission,Bahrain. 20.The Mukhi of the Hindu Community. 21.The Read of the Indian Muslims, s 22.The Head of the Indian Bohra Community. •&gt;&lt;23.The Clerk-in-Charge, Naval Base, Jufair. 24.The Agency Notice Board. Z 3 .0 ' . V v *No •2388-13/1-111 Political Agency, Bahrain. 26th December, 1940. To The Residency Agent, Sharjah. ' emoi^andum* Reference paragraph 3 of Circular No.1296 dated the 9th July 1937 from the Hon f ble the Political Resident in tVe Persia n Gulf (copy forwarded under this office Printed Letter No«1672 dated the 31st July 1937). 2. Please forward a stateraent of British Indian and British Protected subjects on the Trucial Coast. | for Poli ical Agent, Bahrain. Ik 1-5IA- No .2389-13/1-111 Politic- 1 Agency, Bahrain. 26th lecenber, 1940. To The Manager, he Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain* Dear Sir, ilease refer to correspondence resting with your letter N o. PCL- a V6866 elated the 2nd January 1940. -Vill you kindly send me as soon as possible any corrections in the statement of British subjects etcetera at Qatar? Yours faithfulj.j , * 1 a. for Political Agent, Ftehrain. hCM c's. p. p- l (...) noa S00 -.1 -31. No. 788 OK 13/1 The Political Agency, Bahrein, Dated the 29Ui iVpril^ 1941* To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. MEMORANDUM. Reference your memorandum No .138-7/17 dated the 19th January, 1938. 2. I enclose statements in respect of Bahrain and Qatar, and the Trucial Coast. K-( for Political Agent, Bahrain.mnm» — i TZZzy 'V ) Statement showing approximate number of (a) British subjects (b) British Indian subjects (c) British Indian Protected ^ersons living in Bahrain and Qatar and the number employed in oil on 31st December, 1940. Name of station British subjects Oil - Otherwise. British Indian subjects Oil - Otherwise British Indian Protected subjects Oil - Otherwise Tot^l ♦164 8 ♦ 162 employed by Bapco* « P.C.L. ♦♦ 306 13 Bapco P.C.L. 56 ♦♦318 32 640 (a) British 92 subjects.. 227 (b) British Indian subjects.. 990 (c) British Indian protected subjects.. 93 Grp nd t ota 1.. 1310 aStatement shoeing approximate number of (a) British subjects (b) British Indian subjects (c) British Indian Protected Persons living on the Trucial Coast and the number employed in oil on 31st Decamber, 1940. Name of station British subjects British Indian subjects British Indian Protected subjects Total Oil - Otherwise Oil - Otherwise Oil - Otherwise Ahu Dhabi • 7 (a) British Dubai subjects — • 8 -- — 60 — — (b) British Sharjah 8 262 — Indian Ajman «• ' «» r-TIO-* •• -rtP-tOW- subjects — -339 (c) British Urn al Quwain -- — Indian Protected Has al Khalraah — 20 -- — subjects — • • • Kalba — • — Grand total — 347No.2474-13/1-111 • The 23rd T)ecenber,1941. NOTICE . British subjects residing within the limits of Bahrain are reminded that they should register themselves at the Political Agency within the first veek of January of each year or vithin one month of their arrival in Bahrain. 2* Persons alrca iy registered should apply for a renewal of their registration within the first «ek of January each year. 3. The fee for each registration or renewal is ^e.l/- 4. A British subject neglecting to obtain registration shall not be entitled to be. recognised or protected as a British subject and shall be liable to a fine not exceeding r *s.25/- for each instance of such failure. c Political Agent, Bahrain. Usual distribution. 1 (no. jUff-r' ia/i Political A^oncy t Bahrain♦ 30th Doconber, 15J41 # To The Residency Agent, SharJah. Memorrmdam . Reference paragraph 3 of Circul r No. 1295 dated the 9th July, 1937, from the lion'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Galf (^opy forwarded under this office Printed Letter No. 1672 dated the 3l3t July, 1937). 2» Please for\'rard a statement of British Indian and British Protected subjects on tlie rrucial Coast. Political Ardent, Bahrain,Ho. 2.V^ -13/1 Politic 1 A : :ncy, B- hrain. 30th Df&gt;cnmber f 1941. To The iilaiiager, The Petroleum Concession Limited, Bahrain^ Itear ^ir, Please refer to correspondence resting with your letter Ho # PCL~Aiy5865 dat^ the 2nd January 1940. 2 * ill you kindly send r^c as so n as possible any corrections in the ctater-ient of British subjects -ti^eeteass, at Qatar? Yours faithfully, C i Political v^ent, ^irain #No•40-13/1-III of 1942. FOLITTCAL ACTTCV, BAHRAIN. The 12th January, 1 94:^ To Tlie Station .Superintendent, British Overseas Airways Corporation, RHKRAIN. ^ear Sir, Please refer to your letter No•BAH/1/702/ /P-2 of the 31st lecember, 1941• 2. The two Americans engineers of the i an-Ainerican Airways) you mention do not need to be registered at this Agency# Yours faithfully, /. . Political Agent, Bahrain. ' fO^No•629-13/1 Political Agency, Bahrain. Date 23rd Tferch, 1942. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Memorandum. Reference your memorandum No.138-7-17 dated the 19th January, 1938. 2. I enclose statements in respect of Bahrain and the Trucial Coast. for Political Agent, Bahrain.i n n Statement showing approximate number of (a) (c) British Indian Protected Persons living in oil on 31st V &gt; British subjects (b) Britis_h Indian subjects on the Trucial Coast and the number employed December, 1941. Name of station British subjects British Indian subjects British Indian Protected subjects Oil - Ctherviise. Oil - Otherwise Oil - Otherwise Total Abu Ohabi Dubj?.i Sharjah Ajmn Um al Qawein :{as al Kliaimsh Kalba 34 6 74 232 23 j (a) British subjects ••34 (b) British Indian subjects ..... .335 (c) British Indian Protected Persons •... Grand total 365'Politico 1 Agency, Bahrain# 29th December 1942• British «ubject« reaiding within th« limits of Bahrain ar« raminded that they should register themselves at ths Political Agency within the Tirst week O'f January or each year or within one month oT their arrival in Bahrain# 2. Persons already registered should apply for a renewal of their registration within the first week of January each year* 3* The fee for each registration or renewal is He.lA. 4. A British subject neglecting to obtain registration shall '-mot be entitled to be recognised or protected as a British subject and shall be liable to a fine not exceeding Hs »26/- for each instance of such failure* CIRCULATED t« i- ti 1' &amp; for Political A gent, Bahrain 1• Ths Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. 2. The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer. 3» The Director of Kducation* 4. The State Medical Officer. 6. The State Engineer. 6. The Quarantine Medical Officer. 7. The Public Relations Officer. 8. The Observer-in-Charge• 9. The Subpostmaster. 10. The Eastern Bank Limited. 11. The Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., 12. The Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., 13. The Petroleum Concessions Ltd., The British Overssas Airways Corporation*• 1- • The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., 16. The California Arabian Standard Oil Company 19. The Arabian Mission 18. The Mukhi of the Indian Muslims. 19. Ths Mukhi of the Indian Bbhra Comnunity. 20. The Mukhi of the Hindu Community. Copy sent to each of the following :- H.C *I *C. A .L .C. Defence Officer. C/C HAF Levies. One copy exibited on the fligency Notice Board. Cne ' ' Customs ' 11No•2317-13/1 Political Agency,Bahrain. 29th Dccombcr 1942. NOTICE. (jD Gult British subjects residing vjithin the limits of Bahrain are reminded that they should register themselves at the Political A.^cncv ^ _.in tne first weei: of January of each year or vjithin one month of*' their arrival in Bahrain. 2* ^ Persons already registered should apply for a renewal of tiieu iegistration vjithin the ' irst week of January each year. 3 • The fee for each registration or renewal is Re.l/-. 4 V , A British subject neglecting to obtain registration shall not be entitled to be recognised or protected as a British subject and shall be liable to a fine not exceeding Es.25/- for each instance O— such failure. CIRCULATED :• tical Agent,Bahrain 1. The 2. The X. 3. The 4. The XS. The X 6. The A 7. The 8. The 9. The 10. The 11. The 12. The 13. The 14. The 4^ 15 ' The \ 16. The 1®. The 18. The X 19. The 20. The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain Director of Customs &amp; Port jOffictr St^.te Engineer director of Education. • Wfcj L H 0 ■ of the Indi 1 • ian rus 1 ims ir r Bohra C lompany Ltd . aA&gt;*sf*U~ ommunity. X!&gt;**y 9 r h ^ —— ^No•2317—13/1 Political Agency,Bahrain. 29th December 1942. NOTICE. British subjects residing within the limits of Bahrain other than members of the Armed Forces, are reminded that they should register themselves at the Political Agency within one month of their arrival in Bahrain. 2. Persons already registered should apply for a renewal of their registration within the first week of January each year. They need not appear in person, but should send their passports to the Agency. 3. The fee for eaeh registration or renewal is Re.l/-* 4. A British subject neglecting to obtain registration shall not be entitled to be recognised or protected as a British subject and shall be liable to a fine not exceeding [is. 26/- for each instance of such failure. si- * (K for Political Agent,Bahrain.C.t 2.37. TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES: BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS: LuiJ C-iilman, G.C.M.G. (Chuhmutt) Ai A;new, C.P.E*. ' J t&gt; /s£ t R. Cayrol, D .s .O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser. C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy P/l. 9/1325 R. W. Sellers ' ' J. BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 2nd January, 1943. To H.B.M.'s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, BRITISH SUBJECTS &amp; BRITISH PROTECTED PERSONS IN QATAR Reference your No.2319-13/1 dated the 29th December 1942. After the first two weeks in January 1943, no British subjects or British protected persons belonging to this Company will remain in Q,atar. S.A.S., P.S.Dhami, an ex-Company employee, is however being retained by the Shaikh as his private physician. This is with the knowledge and approval, we believe, of Mr. E. B. Wakefield. It may interest you to know that the Company repres entative will be visiting Zekhrit monthly, and Dohah every three months, and it will be possible for this representa tive to obtain news of Dr. Dham^s welfare. Yours faithfully. For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED ^ 1 1 ^ * MANAGER ACMif J X '•N \ &gt; ■ « x V t INLAND : Immediate Class for telegrams rmpm-tant. ' • Express Ordinary • / To be issued on 1st 'Reminder 2nd Reroinder 3rd Reminder Heading: Cnac or Diary No, If post copy of telegram required .Date of despatch of above List of enclosures /T DEPARTMENT. BRANCH. * t-V r. Utter | 3rart M emorandu m Telegram FOREIGN ! Immediate Important/ Ordinary Without priorit Issued on (Code word for telegrams.) To /C h i Dated * 19 . /3- 3- Vi I ^ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, March 1st, 1943. No, PA-756 HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S POLITICAL ACSKT, Bahrein. Dear Sir, Herewith are enclosed 178 British and British Indian Passports of our employees as per list attached for registration for the year 1943 and return* Please also endorse Bahrein V^isas on the passport^of Messrs. J, Gomall, 77. H^, Jones, E« J. Lawton, C^. F. Orr, R. E. S # Wright and Mesdames M. E. Agar, C. M# J'c2es, L. Lafcton, 7'. R. Malcolm E. O^drke &amp; 0, M. Wake and return them along with the other passports. Passport of Mr, R. E« S» Wright expires on March 14th and enclosed in the passport you will find Application for its renewal. Please renew the same valid for five years from the present expiry date# Fee to cover cost of registration, Bahrein Visas and renewal should be deducted from our deposit with you and please quote this letter number when rendering your account for this charge# Yours very truly, W. P. ANDERSON Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Ends; a list of 3 pages 178 Passports. 1 Renewal Application. .. fX. ~ ti-uy- L £ ^ ^ 21*, —3B THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED No. PA-807. A w a 1 i ahrein I sland , P ersian G ulf, March 27th, 1943. HIS BRITAKNIC MAJESTY'S POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrein. Dear Sir, The following British and British Indian Passports are sent herewith for registration for the year 1943 and return: MR. R. L* DAVIS v/ BOOTA SINGH T. S. VASU y M. DAI4LE / C. D. SHARMA \/ NOOR BUX MR. MDHAMED IBRAHIM MOHD ISEAy v/ N. S. IYER V/ MOHD ISMAIL v/ NAZ-TR AHMED ^ A. H. hammond Also are enclosed nerewith passports of Messrs. R. A. obler and J. P ^Pureal l which require Bahrein Visas# Please endorse Bahrein Visas on them and return along with the other passports. Fee to cover cost of registration and endorsements should be deducted from our deposit with you and please quote the above letter number when rendering your account for this charge# Yours very truly, W. P. ANDERSON Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PSIRQLEIM COMPANY LIMITED Attachments: 13 passports » • ^ fu** /U* ^ y £AA- &lt;^ccov * Xm**Prints in England. Aug 1941. (S.fKK) pads) CABLE 5/-168 AND WIRELESS (incorporated in enolano.) RV46/R S BUSHIRE 18 16 1730 BG A POLITICAL BAHRAIN A/462 WHEN MAY RETURN CALLED FOR IN RESIDENCY CIRCULAR 1295 NINETH JULY I937 BE EXPECTED - BRITCONSUL - *7 fin// U MARK YOUR REPLY t&lt;s V2a Jm/ieSua£ NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY.No.821-13/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 20th April 1943 To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire Memorandum Reference your memorandum No-138/7/17, dated the 19th January 1938. 2. I enclose statements in respect of Bahrain and the Trucial Coast# 0 l ^ ^ for Political Agent, Bahrain.Statement showing appro: number of (a) British subjects, ^b) British Indian subjects and (c) British Indian Protected subjects living on the Trucial Coast and the number employed in oil on 31st December 1942. Fame of station* Abu Dhabi Dubai Sharjah Ajman Um al Quwain Baa al Khaimah Kalba British sub.iects Oil Otherwise British Indian sub.iects Otherwii Oil 13 .se British Indian Pro- tected subjects* Oil Otherwise Total 4 86 245 23 (a) British subjects.. 13 (b) British Indian subjects 358 (c) British Indian Protected subjects — Grand total 3711,0 •• -13/1, •) Political Aj &amp;icy, Bahrain » TIig 20th January, 1944, NOTICE *V ^ 5 # British subjects recidin • within the limits of ■ '.liiam are reminded t.iat they should re 'istor themselves at the Political A^aicy as soon as possible in January each year or within one month of their arrival in Bahrain. '■ * n ^Persons already registered should airjlv for a renewal of their registration in tTanuaiv each year. 0# ^■ ie ^ ee j0or each registration or renewal is He,]/-* 4# ^ British subject nejlectinc to obtain registration ^Lall not be entitled to be recognised or protected as a ^ 1 -p S ? ^ ia sha11 be liablG to a' fine not exceeding Ps. 25/- for each instance of such failure. for Political A^ent, Bahrain. CliftGULAT^D TOt- 1. The Ad#-is er to the Government of Bahrain!^) 2. The Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain. ' S. The State Sn^inecr, Bahrain, 4. Tlie State Medical Officer, Bahrain. 5. The Director of Education, Bahrain. j^. Messrs. Cable and Wireless Ltd., BahWiyi fe/ Tlie Eastern Sank Ltd., Bahrain. AiZ 8. The British Orerseas Airways Corporation, Bahrain. Trie California Arabian Standard Oil Co., Ltd., Bahrain. /\ /h $ ♦ 10. The Petroleum Concessions Ltd., Bahrain 11. Messrs. Gray Mackenzie d Co., Ltd., Bahrain, 12. The quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. aA 13. The American Mission Hospital, Bahrain, 14-. The ijub-Postmaster, Bahrain. v Ihe Cbserrer-in-Charse, P.fl .O,, Bahrain. CLV^— rhe Public Relations Office, Bahrain, 17. The Head of the Muslim Community, Bahrain. « ' IS. rho Head o ' the Hindu Community, Bahrain, IS. The Head of the Jewish Community, Bahrain. 20. Phe Head of the Borah Community, Bahrain. 15 167 . X 7 3 3 c LI k (ta&amp;texnlB $5 ALL LETTERS TO 0E ADOPESSED TO THE EASTERN BANK LIMITED. (lN COR POP AT CO fM ENOtANO &gt; Telegraphic Address EA5TERT,DE 'W/w Hth March, /V/44, To/- Political Agent, Bahrain. D«ar Sir, Mr a. B RIDGET MAHY MAT THfiV/ S - 1 forward herewith ni^ wife's Passport together with the required fee of one Kupee for favour of registration and return. Yours faithfully, (P.A.MATTHEWS), 1 Passport. ) Oiifc Kupe e. ) \i No.' 7 7$^ -13/1. Political Agency, Bahrain. Thc^^ Tarch 1944. To The Secretary to the Kon'ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Galf, Bushire. lIl^IO^ANnUn. Keference your nemorandnn Fo.138/7/17 dated the 19th January 1938. - 2. I enclose statements in respect of Bahrain and the Trucial Coast. for Political Agent, Bahrain 6 tc/o The Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd., AWALI, 10th May 1944. H. B. M.'s Political Agent, The Political Agency, MANAMA. Sir, While submitting herewith Passport No, / J /S~Zj 3 issued in the name of my servant, Kunhiraman Nair for registration, I regret to state that I did not send the same earlier as I was under the ♦ : erroneous impression that it would be valid for one year from the date of last registration. I, therefore, request that I may kindly be excused for this oversight. 1 ■ T '■ The usual registration fee of Re.l.- (Rupee one only) is also enclosed. End: Passport &amp; Re.l.- I beg to remain. Sir, Your obedient Servant, K. m. mencn.ZJi. z (Lhc (!}astern \i ALL letters TO Be ADOPESSED TO the eastern bank limited. Telegraphic A dor ass 'EASTERTIDE'.' To/- (iNCOBPORATtO IN C NO LAND ' 23rd May, , //44. Follticol t. MEL-i^9ffi§Ag- We forward herewith the Passport of the above Cleric of this office for registration and return. The Hegistration ifee of to*!/- (Rupees ONE) Is sent herewith.f PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LB.5ITED P/l.7/2159 TL To H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Bahrain, 9th July, 1944. REGISTRATI ON OF PASSPORT NO.155513 . K. P. BALAKRISHNAN We enclose herewith the above passport for annual registration with the necessary fee. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED MANAGER '■ ; •• ' t End: Passport Re.1/- |/- No .47 '13/1 • mm r^i Political Ag«ncy, / Bahm in, ^th January, 1945. To Th« Heaidency Agwnt, Sharjah. Memorandum. P k «fercnc« paragraph 3 of Circular No.1296 dated the 9th July 1937, from the Hon'ble th« Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (copy forwarded under this office Printed Letter TTo.1672 dated 3l3t July,1937). 2. Plea go forward 1 statement of British Indian and British Protected subjects on the Trucial Coast. V v for political An^nt, Bahrain. vcjONo. -13/1. Political Agency, / Bahrain, ^th January, 1945. 1 s v. Th« Manager, The Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Please refer to corrtspondonce ending with your letter No, P/1. 9/1399 dated the 26th January 1943. 2. »/ill you kindly send me-as soon as possible any corrections in the statement of British subjects at Qatar? — Yours faithfully. for Political Agent,Bahrain.No ■to - 13/1. political Ag«ncy, . Bahrain, ^th January, 1945• NOTICE British subjects r«siding vjithin th« limits of Bahrain, oth«r than m#mb«rs of th« Armed Poro«s, ar« reminded that they should register themselves at the Political Agency within one month of their arrival in Bahrain. 2* Persons already registered should apply for a renewal of their registration within the first week of January each year. They need not appear in person, but should send their passportd to the Ag«ncy. 3. The fee for each registration or renewal is Re.l/-. 4. A British subject neglecting to obtain registration shall not be entitled to be recognised or protected as a British subject and shall be liable to a fine not exceeding fls.26/- for each instance of such failure. for Political Agent, Bahrain, Circulated to:- 1. The Adviser to the Govomment of Bahrain. 2. The Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain. 3. The State Engineer, Bahrain. 4. The State Medical Officer, Bahrain. 6. The Director of Education, Bahrain. ^6. Messrs Cable and tireless Ltd., Bahrain. . ■ 7. The Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain. 8. The Imperial Bank of Iran Ltd., Bahrain. 9. The British Overseas ^Virways Corporation, Bahrain. 10. The Arabian American Oil Company, Bahrain. 11. The Petroleum Concessions Ltd., Bahrain. 12. Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. 13. The Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. 14. The American Mission Hospital, Bahrain.- 16. The Sub -Postmaster, Bahrain. 16. The Observer-in-Charge,P.B.O. Bahrain. 17. The Public Relations Office, Bahrain. . 18. The Head of the Muslim Community, Bahrain. 19. The Head of the Jewish Comnunity, Bahrain. 20. The Head of the Hindu Comnunity, Bahrain. 21. The Head of the Borah Community.|o7 ^ . -13/1. political Agency, .• Bahrain 9 &gt;th January| 1945. F c T I w J • British subjects residing within the limits c. Bahrain, other than members of* the ^rnod forces j are re. im.-oc. Lhrt^ they should register themselves at the Politic?1 Agency within one' month of their arrival in Bahrain. 2. Persons already registered should apply icr a renewal of their registration within the first week of January each year. They need not appear in person, but should send thnir passports to the \gency. ~ - 3. The fee for each registration or renewal is He.1/-. 4. A British subject neglecting to obtain registration shall not be entitled to be recognised or protected as a^ British subject and shall be liable to a fine not exceeaing ia.25/- for each instance of such 'ailure. for Pol \gent, Bahrain. • C ire ula ted to:- 1. The \dviscr to the Gov rnnent of Bahrain. 2. The Director of Customs and Port^OJficer, Bahrain. 3. The itat« Engineer, Bahrain. 4. The State Medical Officer, Bahrain. — ^ ^ 5. The Director of Education, Bahrain 6. ressrs Cable and /ireless Ltd., Bahrain.— £ in. * '-'Vr 4 7. The Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain. ^ 8. The Imperial Bank of ^ran Ltd., Bahrain 9. The British Overseas lirways Corporation, Bahrain. - 10. The Arabian .Imerican Gil Company, Bahrain. 11. The Petrolt ui Concessions Ltd., Bahrain. 12. Messrs Gray Ilackenzie c Co., Ltd., Bahrain. 13. The '^uaraitt^lnfr-t^iical Cffr.ccr, Bahrain. V 14. The Americ&amp;n T ission Hospital, Bahrain. 15. The &gt;ub-Postmastcr, Bahrain. 16. The Cbsewer-in-Charge, I'.B.C. Bahrain. 17. The Public delations Office, Bahrain. — 10. m hc I ead of the ruslim Corviunity, Bahrairi. ^ » 1; . rhc Head of the Jewish Corn lunity, ^.hrain. 2C. The Head of the rindu Corriunity, Bahrain. —- |^-1) ^ 1: ^ ^cad of the Borah C q ^ .unity.PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED Bahrain, P/l.9/2345 / 8th January, 1945. i To H.B .M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. . Dear Sir, Ko.../?/. Reference your No.48-13/1 dated the 6th January 1945. There are no British Auijects or British protected persons in Qatar at present and none were resident there during the year 1944. Yours faithfully. For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED MANAGER/)3y -13/1. ( / Political Agency, s Bahrain, 16th February, 1946. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum. Reference your memorandum No.138/7/17 dated the 19th January, 1938. 2. I enclose statements in respect of Bahrain and the Trucial Coast. For Political Agent,Bahrain.Statement showing approximate number of (a) British subjects, (b) British Indian subjects, and (c) British Indian Protected persons living in Bahrain and Qatar and the number sS. emplyed in oil on the 31st December 1944. Name of Station. Britis }h Subjects. British Indian Subjects. British Indian Protected Persons, Total. Oil. Otherv/ise. Oil. Otherwise. Oil. Otherwise. 1. Bahrain. * 318. &gt; 2. Qatar. 66. 416. 621. *♦* 92. 81. (a) British Subjects. 373 (b) British Indian Subjects.1036 (c) British Indian Protected Persons. 173 Grand Total... 1582 BAPCO liaployees. P.C.L. Eknplyees. ArabialaL American Oil Co. Employees. ♦ 317. 1 - ♦♦ 410. 3 2 **♦ 92. - OJ H 00 r- 1 4 2Statemenfc showing approximate number of la) British subjects^Cb) British Indian subjects, (c) British Indian Protected Persons living on the Trucial Coast and the number employed in oil on 31st Decemberj1944# Name of Station. sHtn on: h sub.iects. Otherwise. British Indian subjects. Oil. Otherwise. British Indian Proteeted Pers Oil. Otherwise. Total, Abu Dhabi. Dubai. Sharjah. A;) man. Um al Qaiwain. Ras al Khaimah. Kalba. Bakha. 1 106 222 24 1 (a) British subjects. (b) British Indian subjects. (c) British Indian Protected Persons. Grand Total... 7 353 360No. 19-13/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated 3rd January, 194-6, N 0 T I C E . British subjects residing#within the limits of Bahrain, other than members of the Armed Forces, are reminded that they should register themselves at the Political Agency within one month of their arrival in Bahrain. 2. Persons already registered should apply for a renewal of their registration within the first week of January each year. They need not appear in person, but .should send their passports to the Agency, 3. The fee for each registration or renewal is Re, 1/-, 4. A British subject neglecting to obtain registration shall not be entitled to be recognised or protected as a British subject and shall be liable to a fine not exceeding Rs. 25/- for each instance of such failure. 1, The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. 2, The Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain, 3, The State Engineer, Bahrain, 4, The State Medical Officer, Bahrain, 5, The Director of Education, Bahrain. 6, Messrs. Cable and Wireless Limited, Bahrain. 7, The Eastern Bank Limited, Bahrain. 8, The Imperial Bank of Iran Ltd., Bahrain. 9, The British Overseas Airways Corporation, Bahrain, 10, The Bahrain Petroleum Company, Bhrain, 11, The Arabian American Oil Company : Bahrain. 12, The Petroleum Concessions Limitec., Bahrain, 13, Hessrs. Gray Kackenzie and Company Limited, Bahrain. 14, The Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, 15, The American Mission Hospital, Bahrain. 16, The Sub-Postmaster, Bahrain. 17, The Observer-in-Charge, P.B,0,, Bahrain, 18, The Public Relations Office, Bahrain, 19, The Head of the Muslin Community, Bahrain. 20, The Head of the Jewish Community : Bahrain. 21, The Head of the Hindu Community 3 Bahrain, 22, The Head of the Borah Community, Bahrain, Circulated to Political Agent, Bahrain, V'CNO. 55, -13/1. To:- Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated January, 1946, The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, SHAHJAH. Memorandum . Reference paragraph 3 of Circular No. 1295 dated the 9th July, 1937 fron the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (copy forwarded under this office Printed Letter No. 1672 dated the 31st July, 1937). 2. Please forward a statement of British Indian and British Protected subjects on the Trucial Coast. for Political Agent, Bahrain.No. ^{7 -13/1. Political Agency,Bahrain Dated January, 1946. To:- The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, B„A_H_R_A_I_N. Dear Sir, Reference correspondence ending with your letter No, P/I.9/2345&gt; dated the 8th January, 1945. 2. I should be grateful if you would let ne know how m£.ny, if any, of /our employees (British and British Protected persons) were stationed at Qatar on the 31st December, 1945. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain,PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED C^) Bahrain, PI. 9/2835 | Q- ' \ lOth January, 1946. To ti.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ ^ Receipt Dear Sir, Date ^ * Reference your No.66-13/1 dated the 8th January 1946. We had no British nor British protected persons in Qatar on the 31st December 1 1 j 45. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCJfiSblONS LIMITED MANAGER ACM-13/i. Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated January, 1946. To:- The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B_U_S H_I R fi. Memorandum . Reference your memoranduia No. 138/7/17 dated the 19th January, 1938• 2. I enclose statements in respect of Bahrain and the Trucial Coast. J. ■ for Political Agent, Bahrain. H.Statement showing -ipproximcite number of (a) British subjects, (b) British Indian subjects and (c) British Indian Protected Parsons living on the Trucial Coast and the number employed in oil on 31st December, 1946. Name of Station. Abr jjhabi. Dubai• oharjah. Ajman. Tim al Qaiwain. Bas al Khaimah. Kalba• British bub.iects . Oil. Otherwise. British Indian Subjects. 10 on: Otherwise. British Indian Protected Persons . Otherwise. Total. 0il7 24^ (a) British Subjects. 10 (b) British Indian Subjects. (c) British Protected Persons. Grand Total. 360 370BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. EXPRESS LETTER Britain Bushire. Political Bahrain, /fiflf 5th May, 1946, f V : :c. f - Reference your memorandum No. 353 - 13/1, dated the 29th January, 1946. 2. As the file concerned was destroyed in 1941, kindly forward us a copy of this office memorandum No. 138 - 7 /17, dated the 19th, January, 1938, together with connected correspon dence, giving instructions for the sending of Returns of British Subjects. - BRITAIN - The issue of the above has been authorised. His Majesty^ Consul, Bushire.GOVERKalENT OP INDIA, D kparikent. EXPRESS LETTER [iV. J5,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telrgravhic expense and undue tne of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition a* if it had been telegraphed. To save time and fonnaUties it is wordtd and aiyned as ij it futd been so despatched,] From Political, Bahrain, IVi Britain, Bushlre . if*, -13/1. Dated [(j/C May,194-6. , Reference your Express Letter No. 1814, dated the 5th May, 1946. p M &gt; 2. A copy of your memorandum No. 138-7/17, dated the 19th January, 1938» together with copies of connected correspondence, x? is enclosed as requested. - POLITICAL - The issue of the above has been authorised H. 8. 6. mfp—1206 8&amp;p—(m-l 723)—4-2-36—200,000 4 . Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. r,(y Mahmood Abduljabbar Kooheji &amp; Sons T ele. A dd. 'KOOHEJI' • C odes: B entley's, O riental a P rivate REF. NO. IMPORT, EXPORT. MERCHANTS o , ^ COMMISSION AGENTS Ul^l; !A1N, 194 6 (P. GULF) H.B .M 1 s Political i -gent BAHEiilN &amp; I / • — Dear Sir: Eef. Passport No»110594 Issued on the 22iid February 1928 by the Passport authority of Bombay- The above mentioned Passport was issued in favour of my son Ibrahim who was born in Malabar and when he came from India to Bahrain the above mentioned Passport was issued to him* Upon ais arrival we sent this passport to ^our Passport department for yearly registration. i \s my son now wishing to leave for India and when we made an inquiry with the Passport Department for the Passport we have been given to understand that the Passport is not traceable• V*e would request ^ou to ii.inoXj' issue one passport for my son Ebrahim to leave for India and return. Thanlcing you in anticipation. or Yours faithfully alimood ^/'llJuljalLar 9Uu ons,M ah mood Abdul Kooheji &amp; Sons / Vj Tele. Add. -KOOHEJI' • Codes: Bentley's, Oriental a Private refr ^o. IMPORT, EXPORT, MERCHANTS &amp; COMMISSION AGENTS 0 ^ j, BAHRAlNi^-^ August i 94 6 (P. GULF) E.B.M's Political Agent, bAiii uCil^ , Dear sir*, Kef^ Passport uate of issue 22-2-1900 By the passport authority of Bombay. y in 1 beg to inform you that my son iibranim travelled from Bombsy to Bahrein on the above mentioned Passport in ly58 and upon the arrival he brought hie passport to the Passport Olerfc for annual registration. Myself, my sons and my men approached many times the Xassport clerk, and requested him to give tae passport 'hat all the times he told us that tne possport is not irJtne agency. Seeing no vother alternative on the I6Ln June Iv^o we wrote you one letter btating the whole matter and in reply we have been informed by tue passport alert that the Passport has been found out # and when we demanded for the same, he asked us tp pay it3.X2b/~ being the penalty. In txiis instance we beg to point out to you taat tne Passport clerk could not give our Passport in time and for his fault, it wouxd be quite XK^U5±jdELix in justified if we are asked tp pay ths penalty while we are innocent. We would request you to advise the passport clerk to give us the Passport duly registered against our payment of usual annual registration fees only. BaWaia Receipt , £' : _ ^ Yours faithfully, cJi&gt;r QJla/imooJ ffilUuljuLLar kKooLeii &amp; ofc Tfy Z 3ni No. -13/1 • Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated IS'^ August, 194-6. Mahraood AbdulJabbar Koohi,']!, BAHRAIN. Memorandum. Reference your letter of 13th August, 1946. 2 You have been fined Rs. 7?/- for having failed to register your passport for the years 1942, 1944 and 1945 and Rs. 100/- for non registration of your son^s passport for the years 19435 1944, 1945 and 1946 under the rules. These fines were Imposed on you only after it was established that you failed to register these passports through no other reason but negligence. You should, therefore, arrange to pay these fines as soon as possible, in default of which you will not be considered entitled to British protection. H.No.30?^ -13/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated September, 194-6 • To:- ^} n ^ Dr. E. George, American Mission Hospital, B_A_HJR_A_I_N. Memorandum. Reference your letter dated the 15th f September, 194-6. 2. I have imposed on you a fine of Rs. 25/- for having failed to register your passport for the year 1945. Please forward this amount to this office and your passport will be registered for 1946 and returned to you. * Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain. H.No. 4065-13/1. Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated 14th December, 1946, C IRCULAR . British subjects who have left their passports at this Agency for registration for the year 1946 and who have not yet collected them are advised to collect their passports before the close of this month so that they may be able tc present them again for registration in January next. 1. The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. 2. The Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain. 3. The State Engineer, Bahrain. 4. The State Medical Officer, Bahrain. 5. The Director of Education, Bahrain. 6. Messrs. Cable and Wireless Limited, Bahrain. 7. The Eastern Bark Limited, Bahrain. 8. The Imperial Bank of Iran Limited, Bahrain. 9. The British Overseas Airv/ays Corporation, Bahrain. 10, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. 11, The Arabian America.i Oil Company, Bahrain. 12, The Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain, J -3. Messrs. Gray Mackenzie and Company Limited, Bahrain, 14, The Quarantine Medical Officer. Bahrain, 15, The American Mission 'iospital, Bahrain. 16, The Sub-Postmaster, Bahrain. 17- The Observer-in-Charge, P f B,0 t , Bahrain, 18, The Public Relations Office, Bahrain. 19, The Head of the Muslim Community 3 Bahrain. 20, The Head of the Jewish Community, Bahrain. 21, The Head of the Hindu Communl.ty, Bahrain. 22, The Head of the Borah Community, Bahrain, * \ l ^ r- \ r 1 ^ for Political Agent, Bahrain. Circulated to ;No a 26-13/1. Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated 4th January, 194-7. II 0 T I C E . British subjects residing within the linits of Bahrain, other than nenbers of the Arned Forces, are reninded that they should register thenselves at the Political Agency within one month of their arrival in Bahrain. Persons already registered should apply for a renewal of fieir registration within the first week of January each year. They need not appear in person, but should send their passports to the Agency, 3- The fee for each registration or renewal is Re, 1/-. 4, A British subject neglecting to obtain registration s_iall not be entitled to be recognised or protected as a British subject and shall be liable to a fine not exceeding Rs. 25/- for each instance of such failure. Political Agent, Bahrain. Circulated to s- 1 c The Adviser to the Governnent of Bahrain, 2, The Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain, j. The State Engineer, Bahrain, 4o The State Medical Officer, Bahrein. 5, The Director of Education, Bahrain. Oc Messrs. Cable ^nd Wireless Limited, Bahrain, 7, The Eastern Bank Limited, Bahrain. 8, The Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain. 9, The British Overseas Airways Corporation, Bahrain, 10. The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. 1]. The Arabian American Oil Company, Bahrain. 12, The Petroleum Concessions Xilmitej, Bahrain, 3.3. Messrs. Gray Mackenzie and Company Limited, Bahrain, 1^-, The Quarantine Medical Office^, Bahrain. 15. The American Mission Hospital, Bahrain, 16. The Sub-Postmaster, Bahrain, 17, The Observer-*in»-Charge, Piloi# Balloon Observatory, Bahrain, 18, The Public Relations Office, Bahrain, I7, The Head of Itfie Muslim Community, Bahrain, 20, The Head of the Hindu Community, Bahrain. 27. The Head of the Borah Community, Bahrain. 22. The Head of 'khe Jewish Community, Bahrain. H,N g . fpf -13/1. Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated // January, 194-7. To:- The Manager, Petroleun Concessions Limited, Dear Sir, Reference correspondence ending v/ith your letter TTo. PI # 9/2835 i dated the 10th January, 1946. 2. I should be grateful if you would let me know how many, if any, of your employees (British, British Indian and British Protected Persons) % were stationed Qatar on the 31st December, 194-6, Yours faithfully. vf • H. for Political Agept, Bahrain,J ik No. [pi -13/1. To:- Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated //^January, 1947. The Political Officer, Trueial Coast, SITARJAH . remorandnn . Reference paragraph 3 of Circular No. 1295, dated the 9th July, 193 , 7 from the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persia-n Gulf (copy forwarded under this office Printed Letter No. 1672 dated the 31st July, 1937). 2. Please forward a statement of British Indian and British Protected subjects on the Trueial Coast, H. 6j f for Political Agent, Bahrain.VM No.A,f ^-13/1. Political ^gancy, Bahrain. Dated /S February, 1947. To: - The Secretary to the Honourable th- Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B A il R A I_N. Memorandum . Reference your memoranduni No. 118/7/17 dated the 19th January, 193S. 2. I enclose statements in respect of Bahrain and the Trucial Coast. for Political Agent, Bahrain. (0* *Statement showing approximate number of (a) British subjects, (b) British Indian subjects and (c) British Indian Protected Persons living on the Trucial Coast and the number employed in oil on 31st December, 1945 Name of Station, Abu Dhabi. Dubai. Sharjah. Ajman. Um-al-Qaiwain. Ras-al-Khaimah. Kalba. British oub.lecta. Oil. Otherwise. 2 6 British Indian oub.iects . Oil. Otherwise. 116 260 24 British Indian Protected Persons. Oil. Otherwise. Total, (a) British Subjects. (b) British Indian Subjects. (c) British Indian Protected Persons. 8 400 409Mo. 43-13/1 5 • POUTXC^ju AOiiiicr, BAHHAII. The 7th Januaryt 1948. firltish subjects residing within the limits of Bahrain 9 other than members of the Armed Forces, are reminded that they should register themselvs^ at the Political agency within one month of their arrival in Bahrain* ii. Persons already registered should apply for a renewal of their registration within the month of Jan uary each year. fh»y need not appear in person, but should send their passports to the Agency. 3. lliw fee for each registration or renewal of legistration is iie.i/- 4. British subjects neglecting to obtain regist ration will not De entitled to be recognised or protec ted as British subjects and shall be liable t^ a fine not exceeding iis.Jsfi/- for each instance of such failure* 6* British Indians are informed tiat, wuen appxy- ing for the registration of passports, births, marriages or deaths they should specify whethoi they .are citizens of the dominion of India or of the dominion of Pakistan* G.N. Jackson, for Political i^ent, Bahrain.British Agoncy, Sharjah No. 36.0601 Dated 12th Jan,1948. ' i ■ 1' ^ C^ S -s- To, The Political Agent, Bahrain. Reference paragraph 3 of Circular No. 1295, dated the 9th July, 193V from the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 2. Herewith the required statenent showing the numbers of British subjects, British Indians and British protected persons Abu Dhabi Dubai. Sharjah Ajman (a) British subjects Nil (b) ' Indians Nil (c) tf protected Nil (a) British subjects 6 (b) ' Indians 100 (c) M protected Nil (a) British subjects 4 (b) ' Indians 137 (c) tf protected Nil (a), (b) &amp; (c) Nil TJram-a 1 -o awa in (a), (b) &amp; (c) Nil Ras-al-Khaimah- a) British subjects Nil b) n Indians 1 (c) ' protected Nil Kalba (a), (b) &amp; (c) Nil (a) British subjects Nil (b) n Indians 1 (c) ' protected Nil 3. In reporting the number of British subjects,the R.A.IT. Personnel stationed in Sharjah have not been taken into account. BakhaBRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION BAHREIN XSS.1050X.2528 LI; 28th January, 1 The Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, PASSPORTS - INDIAN STAFF I have the honour to state that I have been advised by my Indian Staff that you require a statement from all our Indian Staff as to whether they are citizens of Dominion of India or Pakistan, before you can register their passports. 2• Certain staff would like, if possible, to postpone their decision on this subject, and I should be glad to have your instructions as to whether an immediate decision is essential. A I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient^servant. (G.F.W.Parker) Station Superintendent,■ ' r®E,I POLITICAL AG-INCY, BAHRAIN. No. 383-29/13 The 8th February 1948. To The Station Superintendent, British Overseas Airv/ays Corporation, Bahraia* L to Dear Sir, r^ Kefer«nce your letter No. jcss, 1050a..25^3, dated 28th January, 1948. 2, British Indians, when applying for the Registration of passports, should specify whether they are citizens of the Dominion of India or of the Dominion of Pakistan. Since this information is required only for purposes of statistics, there should be no objection to your employees stating now whether they are from the Dominion of India or the Dominion of Pakistan. Yours faithfully. for Political A^ent, Bahrain. VU' v. K ^ No.293-7/7. PEKSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHEitlN, Dated Srd Feoruary, 1948. To The Political /igent, Bahrain, v pernoranaurn. REGISTRATION OF BRITISH SUBJECTS. With reference to your Circular N0.4S-13/5, dated the 7th January, 1948, will you please inform me whether it is necessary for trie staff of this Residency to register themselves at the Agency? Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ^ • 0e A§'\ ^AHRA^'\h No.I04tX510 To, British Agency, Sharjah Dated 29th Jany, 1948. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Memorandum. I forv/ard herewith Mr, D. Scott 1 s passport for favour of registration and return. Hs. 1/- on accouwt of registration fee is enclosed. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. 1 INo* 469-13/1 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 12th February, 1948. To The Secretary to the iion , ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Meinoranduia Reference your memorandum No.293-7/7, dated 3rd February, 1943. 2. It is not necessary for tuo membbrs of the staff of the Residency to have their passports regis tered at this Agency. MMA for Political' Agent, Bahrain, lw&amp;- BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION BAHREIN X33.1050X.2753 11th February, 19U8« xhc Political Agent, ^ Bahrein. .0 Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter No.383-29/13 dated the 8th February 19U8. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obe^ienfr servant. (G.F.W.Parker) Station Superintendent, 1 iDear Sir, Please find enclosed herewith British Indian Passport No.137181 belonging to the above-named servant of Chief Accountant of this Company. I shall be grateful if you will kindly register his passport for the year 1948. Mr. D f Cruz is citizen of the Dominion of India. Charges in this connection should be deducted from the Company's deposit 'with you. R.M. BROWN, Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. •r , ^ CP vtf' ^ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. 25th January, 1948. PA-580 His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein, LIR. A. D* CRUZ File 038.4 Yours very truly. iCncl:-l Passport.POLITICAL AGiiNCY BAHRAIN. No.760-13/1 The 8th iarch, 1948 To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain . Pie*se refer to your letter No.PA-580, dated 25th January, 1948. 2, The Passport of Mr. A. i^'oruz w%.3 not received in this office along ».itn the letter referred to abov- .and i&amp;r. Asarpota of Bahrain Petroleum Company was duly informea of this. i«Iay arrangements please be made to forward the passport? Dear Sir Yours faithfully, for Political Agent,BahrainNo.653-7/7. PtsiHSlAN OULF RiiSIDENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 8th March 1948. To ^The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Kuwait The Political Agent, Muscat. Memorandum. Memorandum No.281-13/1 of 27-1-1948 ^ Reference your Memorandum No.270-4l/7 of 18-2-1948 Express Letter No.37-7/25 of 27-1-48 2. Please confirm that the list includes women and children. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian GulfCABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED Banrain Brancn 5tn April 194^ v n No.2/313. Xae Political Agent, BAHRAIN# Dear Sir, Annual ReKi&amp;tr^tion P-a&amp;^&gt;&gt;Qrts.»1948 . Kindly refer to our letter of even reference dated 12tn February,1948. Passports Nos. C.36498, 32347, 365968 and 12169 were returned to tnis office, on request, as tne Holders were leaving tne station. Tnese passports were not registered for tne year 194^ altnougn tne Fees were paid. Would you kindly confirm tnat tne sum of Rs.4/- remains to our credit ana can de liquidated in event of furtner registrations-. Yours faitnfully./11 No. 1046-7/7. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 14th April, 1948. To / The Political Agent, Bahy^in/Muscat . MEMORAHDUM. i? t ?-ii Reference correspondence ending with your memorandum No. 845-13/1 / 96-7/25 dated 15th March, 1948 / 29th March, 1948. 2» Please confirm that the term 'Indian' in the list in question includes 'Pakistanis'• - ' Secretary to the Political R^sidept in the Persian Gulf,V: 0. 1460-13/17. PERSIAN GULB 1 RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 31st May, 1948. To The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Muscat, MEMORANDUM. POPULATION STATISTICS. Reference Government of India letter No. F.23/21-AWT/48, dated the 11th May, 1948. Please furnish statistics direct to the Gov eminent of India with a copy to us. Indians do not include Pakistanis. Secretary to the Political Resident^in the Persian Gulf. f15^ No. F.23(2l)-A^T/48. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. OF EXTERNAL AFFAIRS AND COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS. New Delhi {3), the. From -H* May ^ 8( The UNDER SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Ulnistry 0F External Affairs and Commonwealth R elations. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulff BAHRAIN. The British High Commissioner in Palestine* Subject Population statistics of Indians overseas Sir 9 I am directed to say that no up*to «aato figures of the number of Indians residing abroad are available with the Government of India* Questions on the subject have often been asked in the Indian Legislature* Even otherwise It nould be most useful for the various Ministries of the Government of India to have these figures handy* 2* The Government of India would 9 therefore t be grateful if you could klnly take steps to collect the latest statist ice in respect of t 8nd communicate them tc this Ministry at a very early date* I h.-ve the honour to bet Sir. Your most obedient servant f Under Secretary to the Govt, of India* Copy forwarded tot* 1* the Political Agent, Muscat, 2* the Political 'igent, Kuwait* ^ ^3* the Political igent, Bahrain* / By orderi etc., 'ijUiivli-w t/ BAHRAIN RECEIPT. I5[d.**«h» t 0 . Under Secretary to the Govt, of India*No.1777-13/1 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAiiHAIN, The 7th June 1948. To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, S ^ a r .1 aji. Heiqorandiya : a ^ ; Reference correspondence resting with your memorandum No.36.0601 dated the 12th January 1948. 2. Please forward a statement of British Indian subjects, (Pakistanis excluded) stationed on the Trucial Coast as on 31st December 1947 and 31st May 1948. For Political Agent, Bahrain. NNRPOLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, No.1778-13/1 The 7th June 1948. To The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain* Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No.QI-9/270 dated the 13th January 1948, regarding state ment of British Indians stationed at Qatar as on 31st December 1947. 2. 1 should be grateful if you would forward me a statement of British Indians, (Pakistanis, excluded) stationed in Qatar^s on 31st December 1947 and 31st May 1948. NNR Yours faithfully, For Political Agent, Bahrain. IC^- ■No.R.106-13/1 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 7th June 1948• To The Secretary to His Excellency the Politicctl Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain . M K 0 R A N D U M . ^ Cj Reference your memorandum No.1046-7/7 dated the 14th April, 1948. 2. It is confirmed that the list in question includes 'Pakistanis'. For Political Agont, Bahrain NNRIM p.p.6.47 Tele gra ms : PETCONCLoS, BAHREIN c Codes: BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE A PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (Qatar) LIMITED 01.9/4309 H.B.M's Political Agerft, Bahrain. Dear Sir, BAHREIN. PERSIAN GULF. 26th June 48 BRITISH INDIAN SUBJECTS AT QATAR Reference your 1778-13/1 of 7th June 1948. We enclose herewith a statement of British Indian subjects (excluding Pakistanis) as on 31.12.47 and 31.5.48 -which we trust will meet your requirements. Enc: Yours faithfully. For &amp; on behalf of DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LTD , MANAGER. JB:NCJ jv{# No.639.0601 BRITISH AGENCY, SHARJAH. The 14th July, 1948. To, The Political Agent, Bahrain. ' EMORANDUM. . Reference your memorandum No. 1777'- 13/1 dated the 7th June, 1948. 2. I forward herewith a statement of British Indian subjects, (Pakistanis excluded) stationed on the Trucial Coast as on 31st December, 1947, and 31st May, 1948. ncy Agent, Sharjah,POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, No. 3/^'?-ISA The 24th July 1948 ' To The Under Secretary to the Government of India, Ministry of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations, New Delhi. pV Sir, t xV V Please refer to your letter No.F.23(21)- Awt/48 dated the 11th May, 1948, addressed to His Excellency the Political Resident, Bahrain v regarding statistics of Indians residing abroao.. 2. I have the honour to enclose herewith statements in duplicate showing the figures ot the number of Indians stationed in respect of Persian Gulf Shaikhdoms as on 31st December 1947 and 31st May 1948, I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, o/t For Political AgVnt, Bahrain. i.gent, Copy to: The Secretary to ^ , His Excellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, with reference to his memo- - randum No•1460-13/17 dt.31st May 1948. MBJm STATEMENT SHOWING THE FIGURES OF THF NUMBE3 OF INDIANS (INDIANS DO HOT IN CLUDE PAKISTANIS) RESIDING IN RESPECT OF THE PERSIAN GULF SHAIKHDO ?S, AS ON 31-12-1947 and 31-5-1948. British Indian Subjects stationed at Bahrain As on si-iz-mz 418 British Indian Subjects stationed at Truclal Coast. 51 British Indian Subjects stationed at Qatar TOTAL* s94 As on 31-5- 19*$. 786 56BY AIT. IAIL No. F .23(21)-AWTA s government of india. OF EXTERNAL AFFAIRS AND COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS, A ev; Ddhi {3), the July 194$ From The UN DEE SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT OF INT )IA Ministry of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations To The Secretary to the Hon f ble the Political Resident in t e Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN. » Subject:— * population statistics of Indians overseas, ^ Sir, 1^ ^ I am directed to refer to this Ministry^ letter No. ^ F.23(21 )-AWT/4^ f dated the 11th .ay 194^, on the above subject, and to request for favour of an early reply. So far we have only received figures in respect of Kuwait from Political Agent Kuwait** Yours faithfully, Sd. J.S.Mehta. Under Secretary to the Government of Indi^&lt; Copy forwarded to;- \ ■: 1, The Political Agent, liuscat. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain.Copy to:- 1. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Co. Ltd., Bahrain. 2. The Representative, Arabian American Oil Co., # Bahrain. .. 3. The Station Manager, British Overseas Airways Corporation, Bahrain. .on t + a 4. The Manager, Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. L.a., 5. The Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain. I .. . .No.130-13/1 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 18th January 1949 To The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Dear Sir, I should be grateful if you would kindly furnish me with a statement of your Company^ employees with particulars as under as on the 31st December 1948t- 1. British subjects.I 2. Indians belonging to the Indian Dominion. 3. Indian Protected Persons belonging to the states of the Indian Dominion, 4. Pakistanis belonging to the Dominion of Pakistan. 5. Pakistani Protected persons bahrain belonging to the states of the Pakistan Dominion Yours faithfully. AGENT, BAHRAIN NNRII w ♦ POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, No.131-13/1 The IRth January 1949 Dear Agency, ]Ak should be grateful if you would kindly furnish 0$ with a statenent of British subjects, Indians and Pakistanis with particu lars as under as on the 31st December 1948 on the Trucial Coast:- 1. British subjects, 2. Indians belonging to the Indian Dominion. 3. Indian Protected persons belonging to the statos of the Indian Dominion. 4. Pakistanis belonging to the Dominion of Pakistan. 5. Pakistani Protected Dersons belonging to the states of the Pakistan Dominion. To The Agency, sharj^h. NNR Yours ever, age n c y. *BRITISH AGENCY, SHAH J AH. Ko.64.0B01 THE 18th JANUARY 1949. The Political Agent, Bahrain. ' % MEM ORANDUM . Heference paragraph 3 of Circular No. 1296, dated the 9th July, 1937, from His Excellency the Political Resident in the Persien Gulf. 2 ' Herewith the required statement showing the numbers of British subjects, British Indian and British protected persons:- Abu Dhabi Dubai. Sharjah. Ajman. (a) British subjects Nil (b) ' Indians Nil (c) ' protected Nil (a) British subjects 7 (b) ' Indians 106 (c) ' protected Nil («) British subjects 3 (b) ' Indians 220 (c) 11 protected Nil (a) British subjects Nil (b) ' Indians Nil (c) ' protected Nil L'fflgi- al-^ awaia Ras al K haim ah. (a), (b) &amp; (c) Nil Kalba (a), (b) &amp; (c) Nil («), (b) &amp; (c) Nil In reporting the number of British subjects, the R.A.F. Personnel stationed in Sharjah have not been taken into account; j^ijw UA Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah.POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, No.209-13/1 The 26th January 1949. Dear Agency, r ^ With reference ^to your memorandum No,64.0601, dated the 18th January 1949, kindly furnish us with a statement of the Trucial Coast subjects as requested by us in our letter No.131-13/1, dated the 18th January 1949. Yours' ever, agency.&gt;1 v Dear Agency, British Agency, Sharj&amp;h. The 23rd February 1949 r . ^ o Reference your letter No.131-13/1 dated the 18th January 1949. 2. We forward herewith a statement of British subjects, Indians and Pakistanis , as on the 31st December 1948 Dubai. Sharjah. (a) British subjects (b) Indians belonging to the Indian Dominion (c) Pakistanis belong ing to the Dominion of Pakistan. (a) British subjects (b) Indians belonging to the Indian Dominion (c) Pakistanis belong ing to the Dominion of Pakistan. 49 67 To The Agency, BAHRAIN Yours ever, agency. 27 193IA i No.of British Subjects. 5 No.of British I No.of Pakistanis I No.of British |No.of Br±Hr9h— j[ Indians. I \ { Protected PersonsjProtected persons: 5 J 5 Hindustan {Pakistan^ Total No.of British-J Total No.of Indians belonging tol Pakistanis Dominion of India. 5 belonging to £ } Pakistan, 3/^?1. Date of despatch 2. List of enclosures. DEPARTMENT/OFFICE. File No. Serial No. Letter Draft Memorandum Telegram No. Dated * \ S-5 (Small) B. P. 6767/A/S-109—10-2-42—50,000 pads.u3 HO LLOW AY BROTHER S (LP NDON) LTD. PUBLIC WORKS CONTRACTORS. . No. PA. 165 bahrain PERSIAN GULF. 29th September,19U91 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Dear Sir, Passport Registration We forward herewith Passport No, 232732, the property of Mr, K. Winter, who has arrived to work in our organisation here in Bahrain, Will you kindly register. Yours faithfully, For MESSRS. HOLLOWAY BROS(LONDON)LTD. Agent, RC/INC M noNo.2664 {m Political Agenty Bahrain, October 4, 1949 Dear Sir, With refarence to your letter No.PA-165 of Septenber 29, I return herewith Mr.Winter's passport v/hich is expired. He should first obtain a new passnort and present that for registration. A form of aoDlioation for a new passport is also enclosed^ Yours faitWully, H.G. Ja ins The Agent, Messrs. Ilolloway Bros. (London) Ltd., Bahrain.Political Agency, Bahrain, No.R-O'i^ December 12, 1949, Dear Residency, We should be glad of your advice on a matter which is causing us some difficulty. Under Article 65 of the Bahrain Order in Council we are to charge a fee of He.l/- for each registration or renewal of registration of British subjects or British Protected oersons. On the other hand, Consular Fee stamps only are to be affixed to passports, and these stanps are not issued in denominations lower than six pence. We therefore have to fix stamps worth lsh.6d. on all such registrations, and as the value of the ruoee is fixed at l/4d. for Consular Fee purposes, to make up the difference we have to recover Rs.l/2/- r rom each person who registers. This is, of course, contrary to the Order in Council and requires the anproval of the Secretary of State. furthermore, the value of the ruuee may fluctuate, which would lead to more complications. The best solution v/hich offers itself would appear to be to amend the Order in Council to read 'Ish.ed.' in place of Re.l/-, and the rupee value could then be recovered according to the rate prevailing at the time. We should be glad to know if you would be prepared to take ud the question of this amend ment, or whether you have any other suggestion co offer. To substitute Court Fee stamns for Consular Fee stamps, as has been done in the r)ast, is ir regular and against the spirit of the Regulations. Yours ever, Agency. The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.85/90/49 /t/f 4 The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. Dear agency, 24th December, 194-9 With reference to your letter Wo. xi-535 of the 12th December about the registration fee, we understand the practice at Kuwait is to affix stamps worth Is. 6d # and to charge a fee of xi. 1 only. In the accounts the difference is shown as loss on account of exchange. as it is clear ly illegal to recover Rs.1/2 we suggest that you adopt this practice. ours e The The Agency, Bahrain. cal Agents • **irt 33/lo/bO British Agency, Dohs, 25th May, 1950. &lt;1 .1 1. I trying to come to grips with the problem of registration of persons find coroppnies in Qpter subject to the Order-in-Council, and at the same time to tie it up with the registration of British residents in Qatar, as prescribed in Chapter X of Foreign Service Instructions. The principal difficulty is that both systems of regitration seem® to require the personal attendance of the indivi dual concerned, with riis passport. In the case of the 800 odd employees of the Company who are affected, the problem of netting them, myself, and their passports in one place at one time seems almost insuperable, while the twm-over of Indian and Pakistani, and to a lesser ^ extent European, staff is so large that the process would have to be repeated at intervals of at the most one month. Do you think that in the case of the C^pany's, staff some thing less than the full procedure laid down in the Order-in-Council could be accepted? 2. Could I. for instance, vorking with the latest Company Staff list, endorse the collected passports without the individual being present? I should also propose to waive registration under Chapter X for British subjects etc. employed by the Company. In the case of British subjects not employed by the Company I should carry out the full procedure,'but for Company employees, I think that they are in any case already so fully docu mented, obtainable in emergency if required and unlikely to come on our hands as distressed, that none of the purposes of registration under Chapter X would be deafeated by its omission. Y^lould you send us a specimen entrv from your Register, showing what particulars you includes o. If you think that full registration under Chapter X is necessary, would you please ask the Foreign Office to supply urgently a further 1000 Blue Registration Cards and 500 white? Could you in any case obtain for us one filing box suitable for holding an 8' by 5' card, and in the event of full registration being necessary, sufficient boxes for 1000 cards. 4, What stamps do you use for these registrations- Consular or Court Fee? And if Court Fee, are there any forms or books prescribed or available for accounting ior them? Would you in any case obtain for us 1000 stamps of the appropriate type and denomination. 5. I would be most grateful too if you could manage to lend us, until such time as the rubber stamps asked for in our 2/cA/bO of 28th April arrive, an appropriate rubber stamp for endorsing a certificate of registration m pass ports, and also obtain for us an ordinary date stamp ^suitable for use v ith the nn^jr 'H card.) 6. As far as registration of Companfies is concerned, C. J. Pelly Esq., OBE, ^re Political Agent, Bahrain.REGISTRATION CITIZENS OF THE UNITED KINGDOM AND COLONIES CARD AND BRITISH SUBJECTS WITHOUT CITIZENSHIP Reference No. Surname (in block letters) Date of Registration Christian or given names Place and date of birth Occupation Particulais of Passport (if any) Particulars of Naturalisation Certificate (if any) National status Other nationality or Commonwealth citizenship (if any) M335 37679—1 (6) Single, married, widowed or divorced (For married women only). Name of husband and his nationality, if not British Address Name and address of next of kin or other person to be notified in case of necessity Signature of person registered Dates of Renewals [P.T.O. o*&gt;are Messrs. F.D. (Q) registered with you in Bahrain? Do you consider that they should be registered in both terri tories, or do you wisn to transfer their registration to us? Could you also let us have a specimen entry showing the form in which you register companies and of the certificate which you issue to them? C. J. Pelly Esq., O.E.E., Political Agent, Bahrain.agference • 1 . v^e register British saojeots 'ac io^di i 0 to the provisions of the xJajirain Order In council ani have never, perhaps, done the registration as prescribed under Chapter A of Instructions. Tne m^iiter of personal attendance the persons concerned has never been a problem for xs because we hardly ever insisted upon tne persons attending themselves for the pmnpose of re^istra ion. P.-rhaps, P, , Jona, also may be instructed to do the saine thin^, which shild ooviate aJ-l hustlin- in trie of i ^e and be far less iifipracticaole. T e registration bein^, ^nnua 1 „ the turnover of Indian and Pakistani employees need not create any ad litional d i ' icult l ^ sx if only it is made clear that every new corner should jet himself FBjistered at the A^&lt;?ncy within one month his rcrxib^cii or her arrival. Here also registration extendsover the whole year.acitmax^ii Para 2. also have in practice waived the registration prescribed under F.S.ins truetions and P.O.Doha also may be asked to ignore that for th® time being. 'e may send a specimen* ''entry from our Register of iirltish subjects for the P.O's guidance. Para 3. If we are asking P.O.Doha to waive this registration this do&gt;s notarise immediately. Para 4. ^e use consular Fje stamps and not court fee stamps if. P.O. Dona is also charging only xie V- for registration it should be made clear to him that stamps to the value Is 6d should be cancelled for every Jlsl/- collected ani that at the end of the quarter t.ie loss on account 3f registration sho ild be snown oy ui^ans of a separate sciiedule tj be attached to the 'I 1 form. Po. r-,&gt;. 5 . ^e do xacx« not have any rubber stamps to spare. »&lt;e have already indented for a set of ruo^er stamps for the P.O.Doha and he may be .^sked to await receipt of that. Pcxra S. This may be deal! with in the English Office. jv-oixvul- yluueu^ rtf-yjisy&amp;ia-oi &lt;Q-U 1/&amp; • Oh- P- 2^- ( ^ ^ V^C/VS.0.NO.|^4^ -13/1 POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. 16th June, 1950. Dear Wilton, I am replying to your letter No.33/13/50 of the 25th May to Pelly about coming to grips with registration. 2. The broad answer to your first 3 paragraphs is that in the Gulf I feel Orders in Council should be followed rather than Foreign Service Instructions, in so far as they overlap. We have never carried out registration under Chapter X of the Foreign Service Instructions (nor did they do so at Kuwait while I was there), as you will see from the specimen entry from our register enclosed: so you will not need the cards you ask for in Para 3. 3. As regards personal attendance, this has never been insisted upon. The easiest procedure would seem to be for you to endorse the collected passports, and then ensure that any new comer should have their passports registered within one month of arrival ; which is the system here. 4. As regard stamps, we use consular fee stamps: for every Re.l collected, stamps to the value of Ish. 6d. are cancelled, and at the end of the quarter the loss on account of registration is shown by means of a separate schedule attached to the 'I* form. 5. As for the rubber stamps, I am afraid we have no spares available at the moment: we could get you a date stamp, but I doubt if you want that now. Your order should not be long in coming through. 6. No 2 om P an l es are registered with us, as the whole question of the registration of companies is still under consideration. We can look into your point in para 6 when such registration starts. Yours sincerely A.J.Wilton, Esquire, Political Officer, Doha, Qatar.BRITISH HESIDi^CY, BaHKAIN. 1^3 177/10/500 13th June, 1950. ■jv* ■ Dear agency, [(I. Will you please refer to our letter 177/8-/500? 2^ When may we expect a reply? Yours ever, Political iigency, Bahrain.No. -13/1 POLI':, B1ICY, BAHRAIN. 11th May, 1950. Dear Sharjah, Could you please let me have at an early date complete figures of zne number of British and Foreigners by nationality (including Indians and Pakistanis shown separately) at present resident in Irucial Coast? Yours over, Bahrain The British Agency, Sharjah.m A \u No, 15^0-13/1. POLITICAL AGCNCY, ' BAIIKAIN. 11th May, 1950. Dear Agency, Could you please let me have at an V early date complete figures of the number of British,Porelgmars by nationality / (Including Indians and Pakistanis shown separately) at present resident in Qatar? , tours ever, Agency. The British Agency, Doha.,c v&gt; &gt;v oo/12/50; British Agency, Dobs. 18th M?y, 1950. ■J /. Dear Agency, Your 1520-13/1 of 11th May. 2. There are 6 British subjects permanently resident in Doha, and the Oil Company employs^another 145 in its camps and installations elsewhere m the Peninsula. These latter have also 28 wives and children, making a total of 179 for the^ whole of Qatar. The Company at present employs i;88 Indian. 1 subjects, the Eastern Bank in Doha 1, and there is Mr. Sha'aban, at present working for Mohamed A1 Mem whose origin is obscure, but who has a British pass port. The Company employs 172 Pakistani, the Eastern oank 1, and Messrs. Gray Mackenzies 1. All these figures are liable to fluctuate. There is p -lso a fairly lar^e body of miscellaneous British subjects and British Protected persons, mainly from Aden and East Africa, of whom we cannot keep track, pome work for a while 3m with the Company and (Others hope to do so, but all are fundamentally migratory. Q Also subject to our jurisdiction are 21 - ^ Dutch subjects 5se Indian and'house servants. Yours ever. Doha. The Political Agency, Bahrain. 4-Telegram : From ; To : No. 51. Dated the 18th Lay, 1950, JnclalB. Political, Doha. Political, Bahrain. 2. Letter follow. Your 1520 of 11th Fay. British Subjects Ind ian PakistaniPolitical Agency, M Bahrain, No.R- J 1 / 24th June 1960 i)ear Residency, We forward herewith a statement, In duplicate, showing as far as possible complete figures of the British and foreigners by nationality at present residing In Bahrain, Qatar and Truclal Coast as desired In your letter NO.177/8/60G dated the Ist May 1960, Yours ever. AgencyIf UF GL Ao 3 IF IS D British Hesidency, Baiirain. -iOth l ove.nber, 1950. A Sir Rupert has heard a rirnour that quai^antine and visa fees are nov; being recovered from Bahrainis -ho enter Saudi .vrabia, as 'ell as from other foreigners. Gould you kindly let —e miov ix' there is any truth in this report? G.J. ^elly, ~-sq., 0.3.J., Political Agent, Bahrain. HjSI. y ^ (PA . . AAbout a fortnight ago, it was widely rumoured in the Bazaar that a quarantine fee would be imposed on Bahraini traders who take goods with them from Bahrain to Saudi Arabia for sale overthere. This rumour spread for five days and then vanished as it was untrue. The usual half a riyal is still being charged on every Bahraini entering Saudi Arabia. This is a very old practice and the Bahrain Government here, charge every Saudi entering Bahrain, half a rupee, as a reciprocal term. Submitted; 23 j.] .60 - P. A. a —Unclassified. No. Political Agency, - Bahrain, 29th November, 1960 Dear Plnhey, Your letter No,411/1^/50 of the 20th November. 2. There Is no truth In the rumour that quarantine and visa fees are now being recovered from Bahrainis who enter Saudi Arcbia. Yours sincerely, L .A .G. Pinhey, Esq., O.B.E., The Residency, Jufair. ho-ih ,The Political Agent, bahrein, Persian Gulf# Dear Sir, . ii to re; Registration of Canadian Citizens I heve been asked by the Department of External Affairs, Ottawa, to institute and raaintftin a coniplete record of Canadian citizens resident in any particular territory and in order to commence and build up such a register I would be most grateful if you could let me have the names and addresses of any Canadians who happen to have registered themselves with you. Whilst registration of Canadian subjects is purely voluntary it is, nevertheless, desired that as complete a record as possible be maintained by this office so that in the event of an emergency accurate information is readily available. Should no such records be held by you I would much appreciate receiving your confirmation to this effect. Any assistance that you may be in a position to afford in this respect will be most welcome. Yours faithfully. JjMo BOyer Canadian Government Trade Commissioner^3 No. 3723-13/1 Political Agency, Bahrain, 16th Dec. 1950. n. i Sir, Please refer to your letter of the 24th November (104-1-2/102). 2. A detailed census of all British subjects resident in Bahrain is being undertaken next year. Perhaps you will be good enough to comraunicate with me again next lay. iii I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, Political Agent Canadian Government 'irade Commissioner, Post Office Box 1770, Cairo. -—.ft •&gt; j i v -</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000080_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1393</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000080</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1393</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 13/1 III Registration of passports of British subjects etc.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1951</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-21T10:06:15</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (217 folios)</extent><extent>File papers are arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: numbered 1-51, 51A-64, 64A-102, 102A-214 in pencil in the top right hand corner. The file cover is not foliated. The numbering starts at the front of the file, on the first file enclosure (f.1) and ends on the last file enclosure (f.214) at the back of the file.There is an incomplete and secondary foliation system that starts towards the centre of the file. Most documents are numbered from 1 to 100 in red or blue on the first page and encircled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists mainly of lists of British and British Indian company employees who were living and working in Bahrain. British residents were required to register their presence with the Political Agent, Bahrain on arrival and then annually. This was often done for British workers by their employer. The lists in the file were submitted to the Political Agent, Bahrain by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO), Petroleum Concessions Limited (P.C.L.), The Eastern Bank Limited, Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited and others, 1939-1950.The file also contains several annual statistical returns of population. These were compiled by the Political Agent, Bahrain and either the Residency Agent, Sharjah or the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, also based at the British Agency, Sharjah. The statistical returns provide the number of British subjects, British Indian subjects and British Protected persons living in Bahrain, Qatar and the Trucial Coast Sheikhdoms and the numbers employed in oil, 1938 to 1950. The statistical returns include Indians and Pakistanis from 1948; Americans and other foreigners from 1950.File correspondence also discusses: appointment of a doctor formerly employed by an oil company in Bahrain, as the Sheikh’s private physician, 1943 (folio74); provision of population statistics about Indians living and working in the Persian Gulf, to the Government of India, 1947 (folios 154, 171); practical problems regarding the bulk registration of employees by their companies (folios184-192); payment of registration fees in rupees and the issuing of fee stamps and other revenue stamps (folios185-186); the British Agency at Doha, Qatar reporting problems in maintaining registrations and compiling reliable statistics, 1950 (folios197-198); proposal for the voluntary registration of Canadians, 1950 (folio 212); proposal for a detailed census of all British subjects resident in Bahrain in 1951 (folio 213).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000080#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>