<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ab_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T07:07:22.661Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">TT Pile No. I - V.O. cellaneous Correspondence witii tiie Schools and Club. File No.A* Translation of invitation letter frora the Girls School,Mamama to Mrs.Loch. After Compliments. The Khalifeyah Hidaya School for girls in Manama will 9 - hold its annual celebration on Friday the 16th,Safar 1352 (9/6/33) at 10.30 Arabic -and we request your presence in the school which will be deemed as encouragement for education. U.JE. J.M. 7a#Translation. At.204 AL-AHLIYAH SCHOOL To captain JS.H.Gastrell, Political Agent ; .Bahrain After Compliments / By the grace of God we are going to perform two dramas in our school. 2. The first one is in English- 'Hero of Switzerland'. This will he played on Friday night(in English Thursday night) the 4th Jamad al Auwal(24/25.8.33) at 2.15 Arabic(9 P.M.)after the *loha prayers. 3. The second one is in Arabic-Fath-^Amuriyahf. This r t will be performed on 4th Jamad al Auwal( 25.8.33) at 9 Arabic after »Asr prayeft(3.45 P.M.). 5. As i&amp;xjunue we cm know that you encourage literature we request yolii to honour our school by coming at the above time. • umaal Endings. Bated 30th Rabi* II 1352' 21.8.1933 Sd. Ibrahim.As the yearly examination of the Ithadiyah Mi Hi School will take place, you are request to give us the honour of your presence on the following days at three hours before sun set:- Tuesday - 10.4.34 Wednesday-11.4.34 Thursday -12.4.34 Friday -13.4.34 Dated 16th Dhul Hijjah 1352- 1.4.34 1 - . / I i .After Compliments, The A1 Khalifiyaii School for boys will hold its yearly celebration at 2 Arabic(8#30 P*M.) on Sunday the 23rd -bhul Hijjah 1352(Sunday night) equivalent to 8th April 1^34. This will take place in the girls school in Manamah„ After giving an account of the work done by the Education Department during the year they will play two dramas:- The Eirst: Justice by the Islam or the Sacrifice The Second: Uncle Sam. You are requested to give us the honour of your presence* This is a personal invitation which should be shown at the time of entering.i l£tii Anniversary i f, ip. i-&gt;) As tlie final and entrance examinations of tiiis school have finished so the public examination and the ceremony will take place on the 20th, 21st and 22nd days of Zil Hijja (26th, 27th and 28th March 1935) at 9 to 12 Arabic (3i to 6i P.M.). It is requested that you will be kind enough to come to the school on the above days and oblige the founders and the workers. Tuesday 5th Perweruin 131* (^uran, religious lessons and (26.3.35) Arabic language Wednesday 6th Perwerdin 131* Sd- A.Pakrawan Head Master of ittihadiya school(Persian school) (27.3.35) Irani language. History and Ge ography English language and exercise Thursday 7th Ferwerdin 131* (28.3.35)TRANSLATION. Celebration of the 14th year of establishment. as the final and internal examiniations have come to an end, the 14th celebration of this school will start from Tuesday ana ena un Friday the 28th Dhul Hijjah irom 9.30 to 12 o’clock iirabic(3.30 to u.00 P.M.). It is requested that you may kindly call at the school at the abovementioned hours and oblige the employees and founders of this institution. Munir of Ittihadiyah Mi Hi School at ^ahrain. Sd. A.Pakrawan.TS ZJ^. t &lt;7 2)^ ^ ' . &gt; , 3-^ *-v ^ 4. GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. EDUCATION DEPARTMENT. The Bahrain Government Education Department requests the pleasure of the company of Mr. &amp; Mrs. Weightman at the Annual Dramatic Performance by the boys of the Government Schools at the Manama Girls School on June 6th 1938 at 8 P.M. Sh. Abdulla Bin Sh. Issa Al-Khalifa, * Minister of Education.iar. ijeightman regrets he is uanble to accept the invitation oi the Bahrain Gcvermcnt Education department tor the 6th June 1938 as he will be away on the Trucial Coast.- • - a ■ ■A 5 ■ ; *AHLI CLUB MANAMA-BAHRAIN © , cn ^' _ &gt;Ut 14th.June 47 .atta/ma - 1c) a jhUI C. J. Pelly, UiSq., I.C.o. The Political Agent Bahrain. Bear Sir, I beg to bring to your notice that the Ah^i Club Dramatic Society is intending to perform the drama of 'ABDUL RAHMAN AL-NASIR M ; the famous historical drama of Islam Caliphjfepoch in Spain, The drama will be held in Hacji Hasan Gosaio^s premises adjacent to the big Mosque on Thursday 20th.June at 9.15 p.m and the Chairmanship will be for H.E.Shaikh Abdulla bin isa,minster of Education. H.H.Shaikh Salman bin Hamad Has kindly consented to grace the occasion with his presence. One quarter of the proceeds will be donated to the ’'Orphans Building Fund' and the rest for constructing a new building for the Club. We enclose herewith a blank ticket for attending the performance and shall appreciate your generosity if you will enable us to give the show a success. Thanking you in anticipation. We are, 7 Yours faithfully, For: Ahli Club Hon.PresidentNo. //7 ^fcted The X7th June, 1947 To The Honorary President, Ahli Club, lianamah, Dear dir, Thank you for your Invitation to your dramatic Society^ perl'ormance on Thursday evening June 20th. I enclose a subscription of Hs.30/- with my best wishes for the success of the show. Yours faithfully, H.3.M*s Political Agent,Bahrain. «M0. /</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ab_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1948</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ab</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1948</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File H/1 Miscellaneous Correspondence with Manama Schools and Club'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-09T12:25:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (68 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 70; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 4-44; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains a variety of documents sent by various schools and clubs in Bahrain to the Political Agent's office. These include al-Hidaya al-Khalifiyya School, the Ittihad School, Nadi al-Uruba, and Nadi al-Ahli. They are primarily invitations to performances and celebrations. The file also contains occasional publications by schools, and works by distinguished students. Of note are the examination schedules of the Persian School in Bahrain (f 11, 29), and literary publication of the al-Hidaya al-Khalifiyya School comprised of short student essays and translations. (ff 50-67).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Clubs</topic></subject><subject><topic>Education</topic></subject><subject><topic>Schools</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ab#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>