<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000123_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T09:53:37.041Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(1060/2/49 ) 4th N ov emh er, 19 49 Dear Agency, The Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs have asked for a copy of 'the Agreement between Kuweit and the American Independent Oil Company'. If this document is one that can be made available to the Iraqi Government, will you please send us two copies ? If not, will you please indicate the lines on which you consider we might reply ? Yours ever, CHANCERY.— I ll ■ (A ($&gt; ill* GULl 7 i^SIDiuNCY, BAHRAIN 9 17th September, 1949. Dear Burr 07 /s, Hart, the United States Consul- General at Dhahran recently asked me a number oi questions about the concession obtained by Weightman for the qatar sea-bed and enquired whether the agreement was regarded as secret. It was clear that he was anxious to obtain a copy of it. I replied that we usually kept oil concessions secret, not for political considerations, but in the interests of the concessionaires. 2. Would you kindly let me know whether there is any objection to my showing Hart Weightman^ concession or giving him a copy of it, and whether it will be in order for me to let him know the details of any further oil concessions that may be granted. In tne case of Weightman^ concession the otate Department could presumably obtain a copy from the Superior Oil Company of america if they so wished. Yours ever. W.iw HAY, h.A.n. nurrows, nsq. , The foreign Office, j.finupn. a.'A.l.COPY (£11762/1271/91) c;_qki-i^iial FOaSIGH OFflCIS, S.W.l. 5th October, 1949. Dear aupert, Will you please refer to your letter ho. 5/252/49 of the 17 th September about the desire of the United States Consul-General, Dhahran, to find out details of the v^atar sea-bed concession? I am afraid you will have to tell Hart that all oil concessions are regarded by His Majesty's Government as confidential to the parties and to His Majesty's Government and that it is not possible for us to reveal the terms of the Qatar sea-bed or any other oil concession. It is, as you say, up to Hart to approach the State Department and ior the latter to obtain a cop. from the Superior Oil Company if they can, though of course it is by no means certain that the Company would wish to reveal the terms of the concession to the State Department. Yours ever BiidNAxiD BUxiBOWS, Lieutenant Colonel, Sir xtupert Hay, K.C.I.£. , C.S.I.,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000123_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/272</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000123</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/272</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File C 5/20 Oil concessions in the Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-17T16:57:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 7; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains a short series of letters relating to requests made by oil companies to the British authorities in the Persian Gulf to share oil concession agreements already signed with local rulers.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Contract law</topic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000123#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>