<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000151_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T20:10:40.933Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">MlI&amp;lftyn any further communication Qot this subject, please quote No - a lO and address, not to any verson by name, but to— | “The Under-Secretary of State,” I Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. 1 o &amp; i j is • 1,* Foreign Office. October bEnd Oir, ■ r I’b In reply to your letter x^o* ±. • 0^5^ o.^ Giie i.btli ultimo, relative to expenditure incurred in connection with a depot at i 1 ao for'tne Persian Ouif Lights and .buoys service, 1 ani c. irected tne xarquess burton ox Kedleston to state that he has obtained the sanction of the Lords Gommissloners of his majesty’s treasury to Viscount Peel’s proposal that one half of tne expenditure thereon of one thousand four hundred and twenty five rupees should be accepted as a charge on Imperial funds. 1 am, oir, Pour obedient servant. P*VED~ the Under I -v * OCT 1923 ^ becre tary °\^ hf \ \&gt;y ^ &gt; India Office. 23 ^t.k cjiRa » ^ ^ fin-irg— 1 a He g 5 VT 75 T w ' . ' Ho t 978-H, GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. MARINE DEPARTMENT r O 52 /O &lt;/ - , fo Sir s 7 difeotea to refer to the correspondence ending with tele- -nm L £0 04 dated the B9th hecimher 1922, from the night Eon’ole Sects fery-of State for India, on the above subject ana to say - t the combined buoy depot at -‘ao v:as ready for occupation in June 1921 hut, as His Ha-jestf's Government declined to contribute towards the cost of the depot, it was'not occupiea. It has now heon found possible to manage without this depot, as the ^nSo-Persian Oil Company have', for the present allowed a. retention of too =he£. S e toP. the OMt ?ln». in tM,e ^“VJy the necessity for economy, ohe -ao aepoii ^xxx - n.^ A oo n t but tte Persian Gulf lighting and buoying y^hixshment at p.es.nt, it is available for occupation whenever necessary, 2 fhe port’Director, Basra, acting under instructions from the ^ x .p t ''T^-T'Tnpi carried out &amp; coxisio-e*aD—e late director, ^oyal ^’ dir ,/facilities aM the depot amount of work xn^^.p-ovino the '^eadr it would be occupied on the understanding that v^hen J-t a Tt .' n depot is now by our establishment as t/elil as tha - nfl^the^ have represented being used by the Iraq f/it had it not been that they would, not nave s^.en. so mach . 011 consequently contemplated to use it as a fo 5 )_ fodcom^ensation. fhe submitted a claim amounting v&gt;o 5/ ci^ia cannot justly Government of India are of ^a S-at bdepot will have to be resisted and since ® t 'they have sanctioned the pay- be established at w’ao in the ^ be shared in moieties ment of the claim, rhe ex I &gt;enai ? 1 .' tKa Government of India, between His Majesty's Government and the -overnnen I am, s ir, vqux mosb obadicnb sgtv&amp;u^j Ksb Deputy Secretary to the Goveranent of India. »‘&gt;1 ? 4 SEP 1923', a.P*4603« PERSIAN GULF LIGHT SERVICE! DEPOT . In 19C8~9 a Committee consisting of Major P.Z. Cox (Sir Percy Cox), Mr.Hood of Trinity House, Qomiocioner Litchfield R.N* and ^rrmToToner Beauchamp R.I •N* examined locally the Persian Gulf’s requirements for lights and buoys. Their recommendations (presented on 29th April 1909 for a very complete scheme of lighting included the provision of a depot at Koweit, the initial cost of which, including purchase of site and equipment, was put at £22,000. During 1909-11 these recommendations were closely examined by Government and much reduced. In the course of this examination Koweit was found not entirely suitable, for political reasons partly and partly on account of bad water supply, for the establishment of a depot. Trinity House got in touch with the Anglo Persian Oil Company and in July 1912 the latter agreed to lease an area on Abadan Island (where they were building piers etc, for their oil refineries) up to 2 acres, at a rental of £1 per acre per annum, and to carry out for Government, such works as might be required for the establishment of a lighthouse depot. Detailed plans and specifications of these were to be worked out by the local manager of the Anglo Persian Oil Company, Naval Officers and the Government of India’s lighthouse Engineer (Mr.Komer). Matters proceeded rather slowly as Mr.Homer was much engaged on the more urgent work of erecting the actual lights; there were various difficulties on technical points, and by the date of the outbreak of war nothing more had been done than to select and fence the area on Abadan Island. With the beginning of the Mesopotamian campaign the Anglo Persian Oil Company became very fully occupied in extendingextending their refineries etc* for the production of oil required by the Force, and to meet the Admiralty*s growing demands for heavy oil: and though Mr• Homer ! s difficulties were cleared up-by the end of 1914 and the Company were urged early in 1915 to carry out their under taking, they could not do so owing to urgent war requirements* The site selected was occupied for boat building for the river campaign and later for the Company greatly extended oil woxks* The Abadan project was therefore left in abeyance and finally abandoned during the war. The site selected is no longer available*My dear Monteath, T iVp The Treasury ar€^ asking us questions shout the light and buoy depoty^t Fao, referred to in your official letter Ho. P 3886/6f October 14th. It is not clear from the correspondence in our files whether the depSt which it is to replace was ever actually established at Abadan or whether it was merely projected and the site lent by the Anglo—Persian Oil Company and then not utilized after all. Could you kindly let me know the facts of the case? i, T. Monteath, Esq., O.B.E. ' — i09 COPY OP TELEGRAM PROM VICEROY, ARMY DEPARTMENT, SIMLA, TO SECEETAEY OF STATE FOE IKDIA, DATED SIMLA, ISth Aug.1921 Received 10 a,m. 15th August, 1921. 1472. 12/8. Correspondence ending with our Foreign and Political Despatch No.6, Secret, January 16th 1916. Lighthouse Depot for Persian Gulf. Anglo-persian Oil Company at Abadan are pressing for evacuation of land lent for lighthouse depot. Consequently fresh site has to be found as soon as possible. Port authorities at Basra are about to establish light and buoy depot of their own at Pae (sic - ?Fao) utilising disused military buildings which can be made suitable with trifling alteration. Director, Royal Indian Marine, who has been thoroughly into the question with the authorities concerned on spot, suggests a joint lighthouse and buoy depot at Pao. High Commissioner of Baghdad and Political Resident in Persian Gulf agree. Estimated cost debitable in moieties between Home and Indian (?Goverlaments - omitted) Rs.1,895 initial, and Rs.8,070 annual recurring, plus an indeterminate amount on account of crane charges. We consider propos;als suitable and economical, and recommend them for acceptance and early sanction.Extract from Letter to Treasury dated 17th Feb. 1922 P.391. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India repair of the Tanb Island and 4uoin Island light houses and the repair of the Has ul ATM beacon might conveniently be dealt with at the same time. The Secretary of State for India is prepared to approve the aovermient of India 1 © proposals provided the present division of their cost as between Indian and Imperial Kevenues is maintained. / to address you regarding financial responsibility in the / ncl.I. Foreign Office to Inaia office 4th April 1921. ) immediate future and :n office to India office i April 1921. ) eepeeiaTly after ,51 st ''arch y (Army Dept.) to S.of s. / * Aur.1921 1472, * ) next in resnect of the ncl.II.( 17th Jan.,73. 1 27th Jany.1922. ncl.IIl Viceroy (Anny Dept.) to 2.of S 24th Jany.1922 118 n 3 l.IV. Viceroy (army Dent.) to .df S 11th Feb.1922 232 } lighting and buoying of the ) Persian Gulf. a cony of th ) marginally noted correspond- ) x ) once in which the question j is raised in its general and also in its more pressing aspect is enclosed for reference. x x X X X X'll - j’QiiSIGK OiTi’IClS, 3.' *1. jJec eiab er 16 th, 19 31 (13 13551/937/34). Jesr Chadwick:- In reply to your letter of the 3rd instant which referred to our letter (3 1G55S/837/M ) oi October 7th on the subject of lighting ®ni buoying arrangements in the Persian Gulf. X enclose herein a copy of a private letter from the India Office. X would like to draw your attention, at tne same time to our attitude in this matter which is (P /^fe) stated in our letter ( ? 937/037/34) of April 4th to the India Office of which X enclose a copy. CS&lt;0. ,) . ki any further communication n this subject, please quote f No. md address- not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. \ f* r&gt; Sr ^ ' .V-\- \Y Ylliiik '\i+ THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his —c?6t^v- sqS compliments to f jp , and, by direction of the Secretary of State, 1r transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ^ f - ,192/ . 10 OCT 1921 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. OCy /'D/ 7- a\ y qCT 1^ •m Similar letter sent to -F.O.P. 5000 9/21 (6940)N to the Treasury. g 10559/937/34 Foreign Office a .w a • October ?th, 2921. X a-n directed by the Marques® Curzon of Kedleston to transmit to you herewith, to be laid before the Lords Commissioners of - is Mej esty 1 s Treasury, a copy of a letter from the Inaia Office recommending thet a depdt be established at Fao for the lighting and buoying arrangements in the Persian Quit • 2* Lord Onrson hope® that their Lordship® will accept a moiety of the expenditure involved rs a charge on Imperial revenue®, pending a uecision as to the ultimate incidence of expenditure in the Middle Mast. I am. htr. Your obedient servant. ne secretary0 8730o 3689 \&gt;rh'^ tc Seer „ ‘ India, Dated Simla 0 13th August^ 1921 0 Received 10 aom 0 15th Aug 1472 0 12A^o ^ Oorrespondence^-^^itfth our Foreign and Political Despatch Noo 6 d Secret» Jeuuary 16th d 1916 0 Lighthouse Depot for Persian Gulfo Anglo-Persian Oil Company at Abadan are pressing for evacuation of land lent for lighthouse depoto Consequently fresh site has to be found as soon as possible 0 Port authorities at Basra are about to establish light and buoy depot of their own at Fae (sic - ?Fao 9 ) utilisirg disused military buildings which can be made suitable with trifling alteration^ Director, Royal Indian Marine, who has been thoroughly into the question with the authorities concerned on spot, suggests a joint lighthouse and buoy depot at High Commissioner of Baghdad and Political Resident in Persian Gulf agreeo Estimated cost debitable in moieties between Home and Indian (? Governments ^ omitted) Rso 1^895 initial 8 and Rs 0 8,070 annual recurring 0 plus an indeterminate amount on account of crane charges 0 We consider proposals suitable and economical, and recommend them for acceptance and early sanction 0 FAQM-! v o To No. 6 op 1916. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. r SECRET. External. v 1 1316 The Eight Honourable AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN, JLis Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Ih 1 Z2 0 , / Delhi, the 21st January 1916. Sir, We have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your despatch No. 14 (Secret), dated the 25th June 1915, regarding the proposed lighthouse depot at Abadan. , , _ . 2 In view of the letter, dated 8th June 1915, from the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Limited, to Trinity House, which formed an enclosure of the despatch referred to above, we are of opinion that the erection of the Abadan depdt should be held over for the period of the war. 3. With reference to paragraph 3 of your despatch, we forward a copy of letter No. C.-W. 11368, dated the 15th October 1915, from the Government of Bombay', explaining the reasons why no progress had been made, at the time of the outbreak of the war, with arrangements for the construction of the lighthouse depot in question. We also forward a copy of a telegram from that Government stating tha the fencing of the site cannot be completed at present. We have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servants, Is sUrgent and Confidential. C.W.—11368 of 1915. PUBLIC WOBKS DEPARTMENT. From Bombay Castle, 15th October 1915. H. F. BEALE, Esq., M.Inst., C.E., Secretary to the Government of Bombay; To The SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of INDIA, Marine Department. Sir, Referring to your letter No. 748-M., dated 27th August 1915, calling for a report as to why no progress had been made at the time of the outbreak of the war, with arrangements for the construction of the lighthouse^ depot at Abadan and as to the reasons for the delay in the matter, I am directed to state that the delay in submitting the plans and estimates is much regretted, but it was due to the difficulty in obtaining the required information about certain details of the design and about the rates at which the work could be carried out. It was also, no doubt, due to the fact that Mr. Homer was very busily engaged in the arduous work of lighthouse construction. 2. Mr. Homer was the expert (lent by the Government of Burma) who was appointed for the design and construction of lighthouses. He was ordered to prepare the plans and estimates for the Abadan Depot and reported that the plans were ready in October, 1913, for all but the buoyshed and tbe slipway. For these he required special instructions from the Political Resident and the Commander, R. I. M. S. Lawrence. In March,^ 1914, Mr. Homer was at Abadan, still collecting information in connection with the dep6t. 3. In July 1914, the Executive Engineer, Karachi, reported that plans and estimates would be ready in September 1914, and he stated that a fencing on the North-West and South-West sides of the area would be provided for m the estimates, as the Anglo-Persian Oil Company already had a ln T fche m ° r ori East and South-East boundaries. Tbe rate for this fencing had to be obtained from the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, and it appears that a re erence, made to them on this subject in December, 1914, was not replied to tih June, 1915. Tbe Chief Engineer in Sind has now arranged to have the fencing done at once. 4 The delay in enclosing the area is very much regretted. The «—«« ,o ' &lt;*** »«i£S8: SmSZi Executive Engineers, which took place dealt with by tbe Bombay Government 5 There were also changes in the Persian Gulf. Mr. Homer s period of deputation ended in June, 1914, when he had to return to Burma and Mr. Storrs, temporary Sub-Engineer, took over charge of the light sub-division from him. In the following October Lieut. F&gt;t Z patrick, Assistant Engineer in charge of the Persian Gulf sub-division, wa recalled for mifitary duty, and Mr. Storrs then had to , t ^ e . sub-division also and do double duty, until it was possible m May 1915 to send another Assistant Engineer to take charge of the Persian Gulf sub- division. a 327 cos6 The estimates for the whole work seem now to be practically com pleted; and the Chief Engineer in Sind has been asked to treat the case as a very urgent one. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, H. F. BEALE, Secretary to Government.Telegram, No. 13974 T., dated the 23rd (received 24th) December 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government o£ Bombay in the Public Works Depart ment, Bombay, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Army (Marine) Department. Kindly refer paragraph 3 of my letter C.-W. 11368 of 15th October. Fencing site Abadan dep6t lighthouse cannot be done at present as site is being used by Government for boat building and will not be vacated for six months.1916 . DELHI. FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. SECRET. External. No. 6, DATED THE 21ST JANUARY 19i6. Letter to EU Majeety'* Secretary of State for India. Abadan Lighthouse Depot. F, A P. D«pL Ptom—Ao. 176-13-1-16- 64 *My dear Hirtzel, \ Please refer to your letter ilo.P £2£0, dated the 12th Hovember 1915 regarding the lighthouse depot on Abadan island. The case is under the consideration of the Marine authorities v r ho ha.ve been asked to dispose of it as soon as possible* We hope to send a. final, reply shortly. V J Yours sincerely.India Office, London, 25th June 1915. Secret, No. 14. To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. My Loud, AVitli reference to my predecessor’s telegram, dated the 22nd October 1912, regarding the proposed lighthouse Lighting and buoyage of the Persian Gulf ; construct ion of depot on Abadan Island, I forward, for lighthouse depot on A badan Island. the information of Your Excellency in Council, copy of correspondence^ with Trinity House showing that the Anglo- Persian Oil Company do not see their * From Trinity House, No. L. 1726, dated 15th June 1915, with enclosure. to carry Qllt the work of COUStruct- To ditto, No. P.2220, dated 21st June ^ ^ ing the depot in the near future. 2. I shall be glad to learn whether you are content to leave the work in abeyance for the present, or whether you consider that alternative arrange ments for its execution should now be made. 3. I do not understand why, as would appear from the correspondence, no progress had been made, at the time of the outbreak of war, with arrangements sanctioned so far back as the autumn of 1912. I shall be glad to receive a report on this point. 1 have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) Austen Chamberlain.4 S. 2'72. ENCLOSURES. :—Trinity House to India Office. Trinity House, London, E.C., Sii ENCLOSURE No. L. ] 72(&gt;. Sir, 15th June 1915. A\ ith reference to your letter of the 6 th August 1912 relative to the establishment of a lighthouse depot on the Island of Abadan, in the Persian Gulf, I am directed to transmit, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, copy of a communication which has been received from the Anglo- Persian Oil Company, Limited, stating that in view of other very urgent work in connection with military operations, &amp;c., they are unable to proceed with the erection of the depot in the near future. The Company therefore request that the work may be allowed to remain in abeyance for the present, or, if this is not convenient, that a contract be entered into for the erection of the depot with their Agents, Messrs Strick, Scott and Company, Limited. I am, Ac., The Under Secretary of State H. G. Willett. for India. Annex : Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Limited, to Trinity House, Gresham House, 24, Old Broad Street, London, E.C., 8 th June 1915. It was arranged in 1912 that we should lease to the Government of India the area required for a lighthouse depot on the Island of Abadan, and that subject to the approval of the estimates, we were to carry out the works required in connection with same. In January 1913, the site of the proposed depot was approved by Mr. Homer of the Public Works Department, but for reasons of which you are doubtless aware, the necessary plans have not been submitted to us. We have, however, received a cable from Mohammerah informing us that the matter has now been revived, but we beg to point out to the Elder Brethren that it will be extremely inconvenient, if not impossible, for us to proceed with the erection of the depot in the immediate future owing to (a) the large amount of constructional work w r e have in hand in connection with extensions to the refinery, and (b) further work of a very urgent nature in connection with military operations. As regards (n) v r e may add that at the request of the Admiralty the vvor v has to be completed as expeditiously as possible. _ . „ In view of the above we trust the Elder Brethren will allow the erection ol the lighthouse depot to remain m abeyance for the present. ... If this is not convenient our agents—Messrs. Strick, Scott A Co., Limited — might, through their outside Engineering Department, be willing to undertake the erection ol the depot by a contract on the usual contracting terms. I have, Ac., The Secretarv, Trinity House. ( ’- fc - ^ L!U . KA C Chairman. ENCLOSURE No. 2 i—India Office to Trinity House. p 999 /v India Office, ‘ 21st June 1915. In reply to your letter of the 15th June 1915, No. L. 1726, as to the establishment of a lighthouse depot on Abadan Island, I am directed by t e Secretary of State for India to inform you that a reierence has been made to the Government of India on the subject, and that a iuithei commumca mnwi be addressed to you on receipt of their reply. 1 have, Ac., The Secretary, Trinity House. T. W. Holderness.p \S*J J c. • ?/ r' Q '• L, v ' Auy further communication ox this subject should be addressed ^ tc THE SECRETARY, TRINITY HOUSE, TOWER HILL, LONDON, E.C: and the following letter and numb!’ should be quoted : — Telegraphic Address T— DIOPTRIC, FEN, LONDON. Cxtinitjx Sum turn, ®.C. 15th June 1915. ( 'A ^ '» ‘ ^ ^ ^7^ ‘.2920 Sir, he Under Secrets of State for India, India Office, Whitehall, With reference to your letter of the 6th August 1912 ' relative to the establishinent of a Lighthouse depot on the Island of Abadan, in the Persian Gulf, I am directed to transmit, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, copy of s communication which has been received from the Anglo-Per si an Oil Company, Limi ted, e ta ting that in view of other very urgent work in connection with # military operations, ac. they are unable to proceed with 'the erection of the depot in the near future. The Company therefore request that the work may be allowed to remain in abeyance for the present, or, if this is not convenient, that a contract be entered into for the erection of the depot with their Agents, Messrs Strick, Scott and Company, Limited I am, JUtJ19f5 i sir ’ Your obedient Servant, _ \ t F? £ c f ; v p ED S.' ■ ' As regards (a) we may add that at the request of the Admiralty tne work has to he completed as expeditiously as possible. In view of the above we trust the Elder Brethren will allow the erection of the Li^nxliouse depot to remain in abeyance for the present. If this is not convenient our agents - Messrs S trick, Scott and Company, Limited,-might, through their outside Engineering Department, be willing to undertake the erection of the depot by a Contract on the usual Contracting terms. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd.) ■ C. S CHAIKliAH.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No - $5^} 5 and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. ) / v- » ^3/ ta -M* ! o.; 3 The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State forjl\ f &lt; cc - — —~ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. 7 Foreign Office, i^3 ty &lt; ^ , igiS . Reference to previous letter : 7k xL* Description of Inclosure. r 12 i (Stmilar letter sent to8575/13. 28th. February, 1913. ^ith reference to your letter of 28th. October last, regarding the establishaent of a Hothouse Lepot on the la land of Abadan, x am director by Secretary air idward Grey to inform you that he has since been in communication with the becretary of btate for India on the subject. The L^arqueas of Crewe has now received a telegram from the Government of India to the effect that the crane lifting five tons which is at the present time on your company’s jetty at Abadan is no?; considered to be sufficient ior all ordinary requirements and that other purposes can be aae- v quetely met by a derrick of eight or ten tons lifting power on the lighthouse tender. in the circumstances, therefore, the supply of a ten ton crane will not be necessary. 1 am, dir a our most obedient, humble Servant :ie Vice Chairman, Anglo Persian Oil Company Winchester House, Old ,road btreet13485. I. 961. 10,000.-7/1912. V |./- Departments are requested, if they suspect that there is any mistake in this telegram, to communicate n/*' / ' K immediately with the Private Secretary to the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State. COPY OF TELEGRAM. FuaM Dated Received at London Office From Viceroy, 3rd February 1913. Foreign Secret. Please see letter from Trinity House of 7th October and paragraph 4 of letter from Foreign Office to Anglo-Persian Oil Company of 19th October, and paragraph 3 of letter dated 28th October received with Political Secretary’s letters 42 and 43, and 47, respectively. Homar and Commander R.I.M.S. “ Lawrence ” report that crane lifting five tons now on Anglo-Persian Oil Company’s jetty should meet all ordinary require ments, and derrick of 8 or 10 tons lifting power on lighthouse tender will suffice for other purposes. Director of Royal Indian Marine agrees with this view in which we concur.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. , and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copoj of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Reference to previous letter : y O tL+ f $fn. Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. /*y '' \ L 20 NOV 1912D r 12 i (Similar letter sent toi j r ' /■'£? h^&gt; 781 ). WINCHESTER HOUSE, Sir:- 44b.b 1 | 9 OLD BROAD STREET, ''Y LONDON, E.C. October 28th, 1912. I bag to acknowledge receipt of your letter No. 43458/12 of the 19th Instant. As stated at a recent interview with Mr.Laxwell the proposals contained therein are all quite acceptable by my Corapany, and our Agents at Mohammerah will be instructed by the outgoing mail to give effect to the various requests indicated in your lettex, via., (1) for our Refinery Works Manager, in concert with the Coiamander of the Royal Indian Marine Steamer 'Lawrence', to draw up for approval a ground plan sh&amp;w=- ing the buildings required by His Majesty's Government and their connection with the Jetty. (2) To carry out all works required at actual cost plus a reasonable remuneration, the plans and sp||Cfi cations tor such works being first submitted to an officer »ho is to be deputed by the Government of India for that purpose, all facilities and information that he / 3ie Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office./ J he may require being provided by the Company’s repre sentatives. (3) To discuss and arrange with the said officer i (a) the proposed pile foundation to the jetty necessary to enable it to carry a fixed crane capable of lifting 10 tons, and (b) the character and capacity of the Oil Tanks to be provided. I also note that the Company’s offer to supply Oil for Illuminating purposes will be considered on com pletion of the necessary trials. I have &amp;c., (Signed) C.Greenway. Managing Director.j In any further communication on this subject, please quote N „. 43453/12. A Jrgent. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir: - * * I am directed by Secretary Sir S. Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of 14th respecting the Lighthouse Depot on Abadan Island. I am to inform you that a letter, in the sense of the memorandum enclosed in your letter, was addressed to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company on October 19th. Mr. Greenway, of that Company, has intimated un officially that the terms of that letter are acceptable to the Company, and this will be confirmed in writing forthwith. Sir E. Grey concurs in the terms of the draft telegram enclosed in your letter. I am, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, he Under Secretary of State, India Office. Rbp*-; f V^O 1 23 OCT 1912 i i $ \ n-su./- j. mge^ C ' C ' WAFT TELFGRM'. Secretary oj State to Viceroy, Foreign Department. Foreign- secret. Your telegram of 20th September Lighthouse Depot. Acceptance oj conditions is heinc/ communicated to Anglo-Persian Oil Company with request that they will instruct their local representative to concert with Commander of P.I.J'.S. n Lawrence n as proposed. QL d . ) As regards plans and specifications referred to under head 2 of Greenway r s letter of 19th July, sent UK by mail of 9&amp;k-Au&gt;§iwt, Trinity House suggest mutter should he referred to Horner (see your letter to Government of Bombay, 24th August, received with your Secretary's letter 29th August). Please instruct him accordingly if you see no objaction® Company being ashed to instruct their local representative to give facilities and- informution. (H. ) Very desirable that all arrangements at depot should, noio be comprehensively investigated on the spot in concert with Company’s representative so that work there may proceed igrth as LfLUu as possible.(\ ir &gt; 1 In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. /f 3 6 V and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, z-'x London. I W w I C ; i *'■ &gt;1 \ % / &lt;y The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for (}w d &lt; ^ ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop Ij of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, S - ’ 191 2 ' Reference to previous letter: Description of Inclosure. [ 12 ]434l;0/UR. \~~x LJS , i r ■'! ! 91 2 I 9 th« Octobur, 1912 . uir:- ath reference to previous correspondence, i an directed by secretary uir Urey to make the following oomrr/unication to you:- 1. His majesty’s Gov anient accept the offer of the Anglo-Persitm Oil Company to lease to the Government of India the area required for a lighthouse depot on the island of Abadan up to a total of two acres for a period of /orty-nine i-L !~ L. years fror i the 29th. ■ ay 1912 at a rental of One pound per acre. 2. 1,3 re, ; ;ords the location of the site, the Government Li. of India have posted that the Comander of the l oyal Indian l arine Chip ’‘Lawrence* 4 and the Uaxmgpr of the Company should draw up In concert for approval a ground plan showing the buildings that*8X8 required by Government and their con- Coorotary Anglo*Persian Oil Company.connexion with the iandi A; - jetty. Hi, . ajeet- B ^yemnent support this Bastion and would be glad if the uorapany will issue the necessary instructions to their local representative. • ^uuject to approval of the estiu.ates, Hi* ..ejesty's Qovomr-;erit accept the oiler oi the Coiapcny to carry out the. work® required in connexion ?/ith the depot at actual coat ^ reasonable reiBUnerat 1 on to b© settled in such manner as ^^reod acre alter • these were shortly described in the letter from the frinity house to the India Office dated the 25tk. April last, i-nd the Uompany -asked in their letter of the 19th. duly to uc supplied with plans and specifications by the .ulder Br@thr«fi* it has, horovar, ai&gt;ioe been suggested by the latter that the question of the plans uut specifications aliould be referred to an officer of the Gov©rumenL of India appoint ed to deal with the pothouse service of the Persian ^ulf. fhat brovernment are beiiip infomed of this s^^estion, and. r / quested if they see m objection, to issue the necessary in- structions to tnoir officer. is hajest^ govern-ont wonlt be glad if the Jompany* a local representative could be in structed( 43450/12 ) ♦ instructed to giva to him any facilities and iniormation that ho ..iev require. They consider it very desirable that all arrangements at the depot should now be comprehensively in- v8si%Eteo on the spot f so that work there ‘my proceed with as little delay as possible. 4. it imiy be added that tlm alder brethren have recently suypested the substitution for the travelling crane at first proposed, of a fixed crane to carry a load of ten tons, and that they have recommended that a pile foundation should be constructed for it under the direction of the Company 1 a engineers. This is a .matter that will presumably be investigated by the officer of the Government of India locally • 5. he set® applies to the character and capacity of the oil-tanks proposed to be provided. 6. as re yards the offer of the Company to supply oil for illurninatin..: roroosea, the matter will be further con- Bidorod on the comolotion of the necessary trials, etc., by the trinity house. I an, Sir Your most obedient, }ra: ble servant.CONEIIMHIAL. 'i ,, dated the ^ October 1912 for the ANGLO -PERSIAN OIL COMPANY. U fvUldL' 1* Ins Majesty's Government accept the offer of the Anglo ~i ersian Oil Company to lease to the OoveTTvnent oj India the area required for a lighthouse depot on the island oj Abadan up to a total of two acres for a period of 49 years from the 29th May 1912 at a rental of Ml per acre. 2. As regards the location of the site, the Government oj India have suggested that the Commander of the 1.1.1 .G. 'Lawrence* and the Manager of the Company should draw up in concert for approval a ground plan showing the buildings that are required by Government and, their connection with the landing jetty. His Majesty's Government support this suggestion and would be glad if the Company will issue the necessary instructions to their local representative. 2. Subject to approval of the estimates, His Majesty's Government accept the offer of the Company to carry out the 'works required in connection with the depot at actual cost plus a reasonable remuneration These were shortly described in the letter from the Trinity House to the India Office dated the 25th April last, and, the Company asked in their letter of the 19th July to he supplied with plans and specifications by the 1 Ider Brethren. It has, however, since been suggested by the latter that the question of the plans and. specifications should be referred to an officer of the Government of India appointed, to deal with the II c/ht houseLighthouse Service of the Persian Gulf. Th,at Govern- me711 ' u ' re 0Qz * n 9 i 71 J^ 0 rmed of this sizggest ion, and re quested,, if they see no objection, to issue the necessary instructions to their officer. His Majesty's Government would he glad if the Company's local repre sentative could, be instructed to give to him any facilities and information that he may require. They consider it very desirable that all arranoements at the depot should now be comprehensively investigated on the spot, so that work there may proceed vnth as little delay as possible. 4. It may be added, that the Elder Brethren havd recently suggested the substitution for the travelling crane at first proposedy of a fixed crane to carry a load of ten tons, and that they have recommended that a pile foundation should be constructed for it under the direction of the Company's engineers. This is a matter that vnll presumably be investigated, by the officer of the Government of India locally. 5. The same applies to the character and capacity of the oil-tanks proposed to be provided. 6. As regards the offer of the Company to supply oil for illuminating purposes, the matter will be far ther considered on the completion of the necessary trials, etc., by the Trinity House., m l r Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to THE SECRETARY, TRINITY HOUSE, TOWER HILL, LONDON, E.C., and the following letter and number should be quoted: ^ L. 2521 Telegraphic Address — DIOPTRIC, LONDON. frinitg foirn, toitfum, (6.®. -- . 7th October 1912. v. hr, With reference to your letter of the 6 th August last, (P.2920), further relative to the establishment of a a Lighthouse Depot on the Island of Abadan, I am directed to state as follows As regards the request of the Government of India, referred to in the second paragraph of your letter under reply, to be furnished with plane and specifications of the work referred to in the penultimate paragraph of my letter of the 25th April last, the Elder Brethren under stand that Mr. Homer, one of the Engineers in charge of the Lighthouses in Burma has been appointed to the Light House Service in the Persian Gulf, and ^ am to suggest tnat it would be the better course to refer the matter to him. He could then Confer with the local representatives of the Angl©-Persian Oil Company and a.rrange wi tn them tixe best location for the depot convenient to all parties and The Under Secretary of State, India Office, S, W, the H OCT *912 INDIA OFFiOE-.J ED Av OCT Y3U;) &amp;X&gt;/| .'N ) It is triers! ore suggested that the idea of a travelling Crane he abandoned, and that a fixed Crane be erected instead on one of the ends of the jettv. i'his Crane could lift its load of 10 tons from a Vessel alongside th- , deposit it on a Trolly for : conveyance to the Buoy yard. I:,e esteloli shment of this Crane would necessitate the construction of a Pile foundation at a considerable cost which work I would suggest be carried out throu-h the r\ Anglo-Persian Oil Company^under the direction of their Engineers^ elio are in possess?*.on of all detail drawings and are fully acquainted with the local conditions. The lowest tender for the travelling Crane was Seven E'S Ti MATd- hundred and ITinety pounds (The Trinity House was Eight A hundred and was approved by your Department} f.o.b. England The estimated cost of a fixed Crane f.o.b. England is Three hundred and Einety•pounds showing a saving of Pour hundred pounds on the cost of the travelling Crane, which amount would be available for the construction of the necessary foundations for the fixed Crane. In either case a truck for the conveyance of Buoys from / tne;ici ^ ) , ii i i .7 t le Pier would be necessary at an estimated cost of One hunclr ed p ound s, As regards the final paragraph of your letter / relative to the test of oil to he supplied by the Anglo- Persian Oil Company, I am directed to acquaint you that the Alder Brethren will he happy to carry out the necessary 0r 1! ~ Li •&gt; - :C • tnerewitn^ inf omiing you of the results obtained in due course. I am, / Sir, Your obedient Servant, for Secretar; 1 = &lt; AAn y further communication on this subject should be addressed to the secretary, TRINITY HOUSE, TOWER HILI , LONDON, E.C., and the following letter and numbeiy+ should be quoted: B 2321/1912, Telegraphic Address — DIOPTRIC, LONDON. Sir, ©tinitg louse, fmtium, (6.®. 19th September 1912. r' v &gt;i ii M to \vitn reference to your letter dated the 14th Instant (P 3496) enquiring when a reply will be sent to your letter of the 6 th August 1912 (p 2920) on the subject of the proposed Lighthouse Depot on the Island of Abadan in the Persian Gulf, I am directed to acquaint you for the information of the Marquess of Crewe that it is not yet possible to send a reply thereto as owing to a question having arisen as to the stability of the existing Jetty at Abadan, on which it is proposed to place a ten-ton Travelling Crane, this Corporation’s Engineer-in-Chief desires to have an interview with a representative of the Firm who originally built the Jetty, and owing to the intervention of the holiday season he has not been able to arrange an appointment for an earlier date than the middle of next week. The Under Secretary-of-State,In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. -If adH address— Under-Secretary of State, r ^Foreign Office, London. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secret ary of State for skAca —' '— v —' — and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop u of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, i 15 , 1912 Reference to previous letter: CD. / o 'O Name and Date. Description of Inclosure. Subject ,0 (/ ' Oct l Ui (Q. i ( L /&lt;&amp;' ' \ 26dl)U9% ■A ■S' [12 3 R&amp;Cv''.&lt;g[ 1 28 JdLl9 ^ 2 1i WINCHESTEP HOUSE, OLD BPOAD STREET, i ~'\~ i - | LONDON, E.C. • | )6x, \ , 2 'i 2 C I 19th Jul y&gt; 1912 * I iDeg to acknowledge receipt of your letter No. 29476/12 of the 16th instant transmitting con fidentially copy of a letter from the Trinity House to the India Office, and of a Memorandum prepared in the latter department relative to the proposed establish ment of a lighthouse depot on the island of Abadan. With reference to the enquiries contained in your letter I have to reply as follows:- (1) My Company will be pleased to lease to the Government of India the area required for the proposed depot up to a total of 2 acres foi a period of 49 years from the 29th May 1912 at a rental of £1 per acre - i.e. for the same period I as we hold the land’ from, and at practically ohe same rent as we pay to the Sheikh of Moharmerah. (2) We shall be pleased to carry out the works 'he Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.' ' ' k ' ‘ , 2 . 2 s” 1 % orkb referred to in the penultimate-paragraph of the Trinity House letter. We cannot give an estiinate of cost without plans and specifications. If the Trinity House will supply us with these we will send them to cur Agents, Messrs. Stride, Scott and Cornpany, Limited to prepare an estimate, hut in the mean time it may ho taken for granted that the work will he undertaken at actual cost, plus a reason able remuneration. (3) We can supply Oil to the specification of the 9th paragraph of the Trinity House letter. as we are arranging to produce Kerosene of 150In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote tion on this subject, please quote and address— ’ The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, P 1 London. his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith coputs of the under-mentioned papery Foreign Office, lb , , igi2. Reference to previous letter : Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. j JUL1912mf iountial • 'ith reference te the meetine hel at the India Office on rd April last, at which Fr. Oreenway was present, I m directed by Secretary Sir Edward drey to tranmlt to you herewith for the confidential information of your Coripany copy uf a letter from the Trinity House to the India Office unu of a Memorandum prepared in the latter department relative to the proposed establishment of a lighthouse depot on the island of Abadan. I am, at the same time, to request that you will It. 8u good as to inform Sir E. Grey at your con venience: - 1. whether your Company are prepared to lease to the Government of India the area required for the establishment of the proposed depot within your Con- he Vice Chairman, Anglo-Persion Oil Company. cession(29476/12). rj “7 Q K £. I O | S i 2 .. . •mmr mrn ConcesBion at, Abadan: and if so, on what tenns. Such a sub-lease, it would be understood, would not fora a precedent for any other sub-lease. 2. whether you are willing to carry out the works montioned in the penultimate paragraph of the Trinity House letter enclosed herewith; and if so, at what cost. 3. whether you can supply oil to the specifica tion in the ninth paragraph of the Trinity House letter; and if so, when y^u will be in a position to do so. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, i i -/AC&lt;fv- JLO si ^ ^ r2 ^- j CL-'tr^d&lt;. ^ , / f— a /u,Jl C d' Ini. tj±£, £^~ “A»'-a^ ^ t£uj t^lL^ h c^rt^c-j o*^r ^nrvU^o ,:-J tfcj^ TC^kj Ikrv^JL (t ^fev. y &lt;kJ.~ (a-A^^~ c^A^. ($j t^l^Mi^ c^JLL /^// ^y- £b tfr\JL C-'^.^/s^'i/v. {/VK. cjt* j^^M- j ^ r^-H^ fa j (SS^ L ABRAHAMS. ^-K.' A. £c_ Ac? •DRAFT TELEGRAM. SECRETARY OF STATE TO VICEROY, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla) /ju A 3'. 6 , i ■ C , Despatched 3 ^ / 7; Ay V* , / /wiuu £$roo A* ^ From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, . 14:th May 1912. Foreign Secret. Trinity House letter of 25th April, sent by mail of 26th April. Lighthouse depot. Do yon agree to letter being communicated to Anglo-Persian Oil Company with inquiry whether they can comply with requirements as therein set out. Have you any other observations ? 12304. I. 242P. 500.-11/1911mmmmrnmm /n? &amp; Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to the secretary, TRINITY HOUSE, TOWER HILI, LONDON, E.C., and the following letter and number should be quoted: L. 1597 A Telegraphic Address- DIOPTRIC, LONDON. Irimtg louse, toniron, «.(£. ■ 6 th June 1912, Sir, Adverting to previous correspondence relative to the proposed arrangements for lighting the Persian Gulf and the provision of a Depot at Abadan, I am now directed to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State, that cXf c ommu nic cl is x o i'i lx cl &amp; ix s 't D 0 on 1 * 0 c 0 x v 0 ci t?o in the Anglo-Persian Oil Company that the heaviest Crane erected on their jetty at Abadan has a lifting power of five tons only. As the weight of the Acetylene Buoys which are being supplied to the Persian Gulf is considerably beyond this, and as it is desirable they should be lifted out of the water on to the wharf for cleaning and storing purposes, the Elder Brethren will be glad to be informed whether steps should be taken for the provision of a 10-ton Crane and trolley as suggested in the letter from this House j dated 25th April last,B.1220/1912. The cost of such a Crane as already stated f.o.b. 800 England, would be approximately Eight hundred pounds. 1118 Under Secretary of State, India Office, 3. W.am to &amp;da that the Anglo-Persi&amp;n Oil Company report that in other respects they will hare no difficulty in complying with the requirements of the India Office, as indicated at the Conference with them on this subject which took place at the India Office on the 3 rd April 1912. I am, Your obedient Servant, Hr O r 'V/rD JUN1912 INDIA OFFICE.Trinity House to Ixdja Office. v ^o. i^-U. Trinity House, London, E.C., Sir ’ t . 25th. April 1912. /• With reference to previous correspondence (P. 1149, &amp;c.) on the subject of the lighting scheme for the Persian Gulf, and to the Conference held at the India Office on the 3rd instant, which was attended by Captain H. Acton Blake, Deputy Master of this Corporation, and Mr. D. W. Hood, of the engineeiing staff at this House, I am now directed to submit for the consideration of the Secretary of State for India the following observations in icgard to the proposed lighthouse depot at Abadan on the River Euphrates in the Persian Gulf. ^ as ascei tained from Mr. Greenway, a Director of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, who was present at the Conference above-mentioned, that the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, on whose property at Abadan it is proposed to establish the lighthouse depot, took over their concession two years ago. The property is situated on the left bank of the Euphrates, about 40 miles from the outer buoy at the Shatt-al-Arab, and about 12 miles below Muhammera, and extends to one square mile, nearly all of which has been fenced in. Extensive oil tanks, refineries, workshops, power houses, &amp;c., have already been established, and more are in contemplation. J. It is understood that every facility will be offered by the Company to the Government of India for leasing the required area of land for the establishment of a lighthouse depot, and it was proposed by Mr. Greenway that the two acres suggested by the Elder Brethren as necessary for the purpose could be acquired for a term of fifty years (the duration of the Company’s lease of the property) for a small, or even nominal rental. In the letter from the Trinity House to the India Office dated 26th March 1912 (Ex. 874), it was suggested that an area of two acres would probably be necessary for the accommodation of the depot, the establishment of which would involve considerable expenditure, as it was understood that nothing whatever was available for adaptation to lighthouse purposes, but it now' appears that this is not the case. 4. As already stated, extensive workshops, largely staffed by European mechanics and fitted with modern tools, have been established, and it has been suggested that an agreement might possibly be arrived at between the Government of India and the Company, whereby all repairs necessary for the working parts of lighthouses, light vessels, and gas buoys, wmuld be executed by the Company’s engineering staff, thus rendering the establishment and equipment of lighthouse workshops unnecessary. Ot was also assumed that a considerable area would be required, and expense incurred, in providing for the storage of steam coal for the tender. This can, how'ever, be obviated, as already suggested by the Elder Brethren, by the whole or partial use of oil fuel, which can be supplied on the spot; but as the depot will be within a few miles of Muhammera, wffiere a coaling station exists, no provision need be made for extensive coal storage at the depot. S. 153.(pm C. A carbide store has already been erected, presumably, as Mr. Greenway suggested, in connection with the acetylene buoy already laid at the Shatt-al- Arab. It may, therefore, only be necessary to enlarge it on the establishment of additional buoys. /. An extensive pier or wharf has already been built at, it is understood^ a cost of about 20,000b, alongside of which large steamers can lie, and from which several lines of rails for wagons and trolleys have been laid to various parts of the concession, including the area proposed for the depot, distant about half-a-mile. A small area, it is anticipated, can be acquired for the storage of spare buoys on the river bank in the immediate vicinity of the pier. £ Provision was also made in the estimates submitted by the Elder Brethren for extensive oil storage tanks. This also may be unnecessary, as Mr. Green way stated his Company can supply any description of oil that may be necessary. In order that this point may be verified, however, which is a most important matter in lighthouse illumination, the following is the specification of ordinary lighthouse oil as used in the Trinity House Service, with which supplies for lighthouse purposes must conform, viz. :— /, Specific gravity to be not less than O'810, nor greater than 0-820 at 60° Fahr. ; flashing point not lower than 145°, nor higher than 160° Fahr. ; to distil between 302° and 572° Fahr., the temperature of the vapour, not that of the liquid, being taken. lo. AVith the above facilities so readily available, it would now appear that the establishment of a lighthouse depot at Abadan to meet the immediate requirements is a comparatively small matter, and might be restricted to the erection of a storehouse for lighthouse stores, such as cleaning stores, mantles, spare parts, gas buoy lanterns, &amp;c., another for ropes and ship’s stores, and one for engine-room stores. A space is also required for a buoy yard and chain lockers. ((. In regard to the storehouses, one building containing three storerooms and an office of two rooms, with a roomy loft overall, would, it is considered, meet the present requirements. The lighthouse store and engineer’s store room to be each about 15 feet square, and the general store about 40 feet by 15 feet. This building, together with the buoy yard and chain lockers, could, it is believed, be accommodated on a site approximately 100 feet by 50 feet, or about one-eighth of an acre, which it would perhaps be found possible to procure near the pier. Such ground as would ultimately be found necessary for dwellings, &amp;c., could be arranged for on the more remote part of the concession near the southern boundary, as proposed by Mr. Green way, but it would be a great convenience for working if the site could be procured near the pier instead of a position distant half a mile from it. /2. Information should be obtained from the Anglo-Persian Oil Company as to whether they have on their pier a crane capable of lifting 10 tons from the deck of a vessel alongside; and, if so, whether it is a travelling crane that could be run from the pier into the buoy yard to unload a buovfrom a trolley there. It should also be ascertained from the Company what is the gauge of their tramways, and if laid and ballasted to carry heavy loads. /kin regard to the cost of such a depot, the Elder Brethren would suggest that as the Anglo-Persian Oil Company are still carrying out works at the site, they be asked for what sum they would be prepared to erect the ■Inecessary buildings as described in this letter, with concrete floors, lay a tramway into the depot from their pier of sufficient gauge to carry a 10-ton load, provide four chain lockers (which are usually brickwork chambers about 10 feet by 6 feet roofed with one end open), and fence in the whole area. ly lf a 10-ton crane and tiolley are not already available, they could be provided through the Trinity House at a cost of about eight hundred pounds f.o.b. England. I am, Sir, Tour obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State H. G. Willett for India.Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to THE SECRETARY, TRINITY HOUSE, TOWER HIL1, LONDON, E.C., and the folloAving letter and number should be quotecl: irphi \ A Telegraphic Address — DIOPTRIC, LONDON. Sir, CO-y to INDIA 26 APR 1912 GECrcETARV’S N2 1 7 With reference to previous correspondence, (P.li49,&amp;c.) on the subject of the Lighting Scheme for the Persian Gulf, and to the Conference held at the India Office on the 3rd Instant which was attended Ky Captain E. Acton Blake, Deputy Master of this Corporation, and Mr. D. W. Hood of the Engineering Staff at this House, I am now directed to submit for the consideratioTlof the Secretary of State for 'W £ 0 u «*7 £ m \pr n9U INDIA OFFICS. the 3hatt-al-Arab, and about 12 miles below Muhammera, and Under Secrete;.ry'' of State, extends India Office, 3.W. India the following observations in regard to the proposed Lighthouse Depot at Abadan on theHiver Euphrates in the Persian Gulf. It was ascertained from Mr. Greenway, a Director of * the Anglo-Persian Oil Company who was present at the Conference above mentioned, that the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, on whose property at Abadan it is proposed to establish the Lighthouse Depot, took over their concession wo years ago. The property is situated on the left bank cf the Euphrates, about 40 miles from the Outer Buoy at2 necessary j ij, ( H extends to one square mile, nearly all of which has been fenced in. 'Ex-.ensive oil tanks, refineries, workshops, power houses, &amp;c. have already been established, and more are in contemplation. It is understood that every facility will be offered by the Company to the Goverhment of India for leasing the required area of land for the establishment of a lighthouse depot, and it was proposed by Mr. Greenway that the tv/o acres suggested by the Elder Brethren as necessary for the purpose could be acquired for a term of fifty years (the duration of the Compaiw*s lease of the property) for a small, or even nominal rental. In the letter from the ((u-q Trinity House to the India Office dated 26th March 1912, (Ex*874) it was suggested that an area of two acres would probably be necessary for the accommodation of the depot, the establishment of which would involve considerable Expenditure, as it was understood that nothing whatever i was available for adaptation to lighthouse purposes, but it now appears that this is not the case. As already stated, extensive workshops, largely staffed by European mechanics and fitted with modern tools, have been established, and it has been suggested that an agreement might possibly be arrived at between the Govern ment of India and the Company, whereby all repairsi necessary for the working parts Qf Lighthouses, Light Vessels and Gas Buoys would he executed by the Company^ 'Engineering staff, thus rendering the establishment an'd eq,uipir ent of Lighthouse workshops unnecessary* required, and expense incurred, in providing for the stor age of Sweain coal for the tender. This can, however, he obviated, as already suggested by the Elder Brethren, by of Muhaimnera, where a coaling station exists, no provision need be made for extensive coal storage at the depot. A carbide store has already been erected, presumably, as Mr. Greenway suggested, in connection with the Acetylene Buoy already laid at the Shatt«*al-Arab. It may, therefore, only be necessary to enlarge it on the establishment of An extensive pier or wharf has already been built at, it is understood, a cost of about Twenty thousand pounds, alongside of which large steamers can lie, and from which several lines of rails for wagons and trolleys have been area, it is anticipated, can be acquired for the storage lo was also assumed that a considerable area would be on the spot j but as the depot will be within a few miles the vfoole or partial use of oil fuel, which can be supplied additional buoys laid to various parts of the concession, including the area proposed for the depot, distant about half a mile. A smallof spare Buoys of the Pier* on the river bank in the immediate vicinity Provision was also made in the estimates submitted by the Elder Brethren for extensive oil storage tanks. This also may be unnecessary, as Mr. Greenway stated his Company can supply any description of oil that may be necessary. In order that this point may be verified, however, which is a most important matter in Lighthouse A v ■ ' &gt;’ illumination, the following is the specification of ordinary Lighthouse oil as used in the Trinity House service, with which supplies for Lighthouse purposes must conform, viz:- . - - v ' •-tW' .. . r - — ■ ’ - 1 h . _ . p-: Specific gravity to be not less than 0*810, nor greater than 0*820 a.t 60° Fehrenheit; flashing point not lower than 145°, nor higher than 160° Fahrenheit; to distil between 302° and 572° Fahrenheit, the t&amp;nperature of the vapour, not that of the liquid, being taken. ■ With the above facilities so readily available, it would now appear that the establishment of a Lighthouse / depot at Abadan to meet the immediate requirements is a comparatively small matter, and might be restricted to the erection of a storehouse for Lighthouse stores, such as cleaning stores, mantles, spare parts, gas buoy lanterns, &amp;c. another for ropes^ ship's stores, and one for engine-■ ■ • ^ space is also reciuired for a Buoy yard room stores chain lockers. In regard to the storehouses, one building containing loft overall, would, it is considered, meet the present requirements. The Lighthouse store and Engineer*s store- room to be^about 15 feet square, and the general store about 40 feet by 15 feet. This building, together with the Buoy yard and chain lockers, could, it is believed, be accommodated on a site approximately 100 feet by 50 feet, or about one-eighth of an acre, which it would perhaps be found possible to procure near the pier. Such ground as would ultimately be found necessary for dwelling$,&amp;c. could be arranged for on the more remote part of the con cession near the southern boundary, as proposed by Mr. Greenway, but it would be a great convenience for working if the site could be procured near the pier instead of a position distant half a mile from it. Information should be obtained from the Anglo-Persi&amp;n Oil Company as to whether they have on their Pier a crane capable of lifting ten tons from the deck of a Vessel alongside; and, if so, whether it is a travelling crane that could be run from the pier into the buoy yard to unload a buoy from a trolley there. It should also oe 5 . V three storerooms and an office of two rooms, with &amp; a roomy ascertained—;ascertained from the Company wh&amp;t is the gauge of their tramways, and il laid and ballasted to carry heavy loads. In regard to the cost of such a depot, the Elder Brethren would suggest that as the Anglo-Persian Oil Company are still carrying out works at the site, they be asked for what sum they would be prepared to erect the necessary buildings as described in this letter, with concrete floors, lay a tramway into the depot from their pier of sufficient gauge tocarry a 10 -ton load, provide four chain lockers (which, are usually brickwork chambers about 10 feet by 6 feet roofed with one end open) and fence in the whole area. If a 10-ton crane and trolley are not already avail able, they could be provided through the Trinity Rouse at a cost of about light hundred pounds f.o.b. England. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,'ZUr 1 TraHiTr House, London. E.C. 2 nd April 1912, Confidential Dear Sir In re^ly i;o your letter of yeeteruarV’s datf, (Ho.P.lJ 49 ) etatir^ that It is proposed to hold the Conference relative to tne proposed lighthouse Depot on Atoadan Island, in the Persian Gulf, at the India Office on Wednesday, the 3 rd April at 11 a.m. I have to inf orm you, in confirmation of my telephone message tni£ afternoon^that Captain E, A c :on Slake, Deputy Master of ,Lis Corporation and Mr. D. Hood, a member of the Engineering Staff at .ik is House, will be happy to attend the Conference tomorrow at the time prooosed. ^ecretarj', Political Department, India Office, Yours faithfully, for 3ecretarv,S. 146. A CONFIDENTIAL. Un uu - 1 ' / IV Ex. 874. frinity House, London, E.C. Sir, Lighthouses. 2. Idle iist aeeompnnying the India Office letter dated the 2nd instant provides for the establishment of three lighthouses, viz., at Little Quoin, lamb Island, and Sheikh Shuaib Island, and the proposals relative to these are as follows :— At Little Quoin, the dioptric apparatus to be of the second order the intensity ot the light being 200,000 candles, and the range of visibility I I w-\ i I At Iamb Island, the dioptric apparatus to be of the third order, the intensity of the light being 100,000 candles, and the range of visibility 20 miles. At Sheikh Shuaib Island, the dioptric apparatus to be of the third order, the intensity of the light being 100,000 candles, and the range of visibility 17 miles. The Elder Brethren suggest that the lighthouses for Little Quoin, Tamb Island, and Sheikh Shuaib Island be constructed of open iron frame work, the upper portion being enclosed to act as a service or watch-room. The structure to be surmounted by a lantern of the usual type adopted in the Trinity House service. The lighthouses to be constructed in England from designs to be prepared at this House, the lantern, dioptric apparatus, burners, &amp;c., being fitted and tested before shipment. ^ 3. It is suggested that the foundations for receiving the structures should be designed and constructed by the local authorities, the necessary information in connection therewith being supplied by the Trinity House, also that the quarters for the keepers, landing places, roads, access from landings to sites, water storage tanks, &amp;c., be designed and constructed by the local authorities, who are best acquainted with the nature of the requirements. 4. The Elder Brethren propose that a competent mechanic be sent from England to the Persian Gulf to take charge of the erection of the towers from the foundation level and bring the lights into action, all necessary assistance, plant, labour, hoisting tackle, &amp;c., being supplied by the local authorities. 5. The cost of the work to be supplied from England, including freight to the Persian Gulf, is estimated to be as follows :— 6. With reference to the establishment of a light vessel at Shatt-al-Arab, four or five miles to seaward of the existing British outer bar buoy,’.the Elder Brethren now suggest that the light be on the incandescent' system, Little Quoin, 7,000L Tamb Island, 5,000L Sheikh Shuaib Island, 6,000Z. | including mechanic from England C for erection of same. same. Light Vessel.consuming oil, instead of the illnminant being oil-gas as originally proposed. It is recommended that the vessel be built m England, and when completed placed on a station for trial and adjustment before being- despatched to the Gulf, to which she could be towed by the lighthouse tender w r hich it is proposed to construct. The cost of the vessel is estimated at 9,500L, including delivery to its destination, but the Elder Brethren desire to point out that this figure is liable to variation in consequence of the frequent and considerable changes which take place in the cost of shipbuilding. The intensity of the light would be 40,000 candles, and the range of visibility eleven miles. Buoys, Lighted. 7. Either oil gas or acetylene would be suitable illuminants for the pro posed lighted buoys, but in view of the fact that the number of buoys required at stations is only six, the expenditure which would be involved in establishing oil-gas producing plant, and fitting the lighthouse tender with transport receivers, gas compressing pumps. &amp;c., would, in the opinion of the Elder Brethren, hardly be justified, and they accordingly recommend that the six buoys be of the same type as the acetylene lighted buoy already established at Shatt-al-Arab, which was constructed by the Inter national Marine Signal Company, and is known as No. 8 C. The buoys complete, with lanterns and moorings, should be supplied from England, the estimated cost, including freight to the Gulf, being 600/. each. Two buoys of this type are ready, and arrangements have been made with the manu facturers to hold these at the disposal of the Elder Brethren for a few days, and on hearing that the India Office wish them to be supplied they could be despatched at once. The remainder could probably be completed in ten to twelve weeks from date of order. Buoys, Unlit. 8 . Three buoys of this type are included in the list, with top-marks and moorings complete, viz.:— Task - _ _ _ 5th class conical buoy. Bunder Abbas - - ihid class can buoy. Bahrein - - - - 5th class conical buoy. In regard to this proposal I am to state that the Elder Brethren are of opinion that a 5th class buoy is too small for a position of the importance of Task, and they consider that a 2nd class buoy would be more suitable which would increase the cost of this part of the scheme by 100/. It is-suggested that the buoys and moorings complete should be supplied from England, their cost including freight to the Gulf would be as follows : —Jask (2nd class) 200/., Bunder Abbas 200/., Bahrein 100/. Lighthouse Tender. 9. In the third paragraph of the India Office letter, dated the 2nd March, the hope is expressed by Lord Grewe that a reduction may be made in the original estimate of the cost of the lighthouse tender, viz., 30,000/. Accom panying the papers, however, is a letter from the Secretary to the Government of India, dated the 31st January last, stating the approximate dimensions to which the Iloyal Indian Marine Committee desire the vessel to be built. The estimate of 30,000/. is based on the cost of steam vessels constructed foi t-h® Trinity House service. Ihere are certain parts in connection with these vessels which would not be necessary in a tender for the Persian Gulf, whilst, on the other hand, the latter might require various fittings for the convenience of the officers and crew which are not necessary in this service. Hie sum above mentioned is considered a reasonable estimate for such a3 Wi„ m the letter r.I,,,.,, ,„ 2,,,,. ZSjSSXS&amp;^SZ'''' mi.,™r°e^„t.ru°«X 0 TS, i ™,rbi,“t •*, *» ~ »&lt; j ^ S^r- ' sI ”'* 3 « 6 ~“- “i£f 0 .^“ 5 rfw Depot. 10. it is observed that it is now proposed that the depot should be on the property m the Anglo-Persian Od Company on Abadan Island, in the river Euphrates, mstead of at Koweit, as originally suggested. It appears to the Elder Brethren that this is a matter that the local authorities are better abic; to decide, it being a question so materially affected by local conditions and facilities ; the latter proposal offers the important facility of easily proem mg fresh water lor lighthouse purposes, thus rendering a distilling plant, as suggested by the Committee of Enquiry, unnecessary. The modified scheme of lights adopted by the Government of India, as compared with the more comprehensive one proposed by the Committee of Enquiry (out which it may be intended eventually to carry out), naturally influences the area of land to be obtained and the form of construction of the buildings, but the Elder Brethren recommend that ii possible not less than two acres be secured as a site for the depot which would admit of future developments of the establishment. H- paiagraph 1 of the India Office letter of the 2nd instant, inquiry is made as to the possibility of substantially reducing the estimated cost of the depot, viz., 22 y 000b This estimate included 9,500/,. for a spare Light Vessel, and the cost of the essential general spares for the buoys, &amp;c., as mentioned in the statement submitted with this report. The scheme put forward by the Committee of Enquiry included several Light Vessels, in which case a spare ship was, of course, necessary, hut as it is understood not to be the practice in India to provide a spare for a single station, the spare vessel might, for the present at least, be dispensed with, and a corresponding saving in cost effected. 12. The Elder Brethren are unaware as to the intentions of the Government of India in regard to the housing of their officers, crew, and workmen at the depot. The authorities in India will themselves be able to prepare estimates to suit their requirements in that respect; but it is considered that, provided no pier work or wharfing is necessary, the requisite storage for lighthouse oil, steam coal, carbide, and general stores, workshop, buoy yard, chain lockers, &amp;c., all of which should be made of iron framing covered by corrugated sheeting, could be established and equipped with the necessary spare acetylene and unlit buoys, spare moorings for Light Vessel and buoys, rails, cranes, and trolleys, for a sum well within the balance of 12,500/., and that, as the lighthouse service in the Gulf increased, the depot accommo dation could be increased to meet th.e additional requirements. 13. It would be necessary to send from England for the depot the spare buoys, moorings, and 10-ton travelling crane. All corrugated iron buildings, rails, hand cranes, trolleys, workshop equipment, &amp;c., could, it is understood, be obtained at Bombay. 14. With regard to the date for completion, bearing in mind that the various works to be supplied from England would be undertaken by various contractors, the whole of the buoys could be shipped in four months, and the three lighthouses and the Light Vessel in nine months from the date oi order. 15. A statement is forwarded herewith showing the works it is suggested should be supplied from this country, with estimated cost an o er particulars. S. 14,6. A. 24 LG. As tlie work is understood to be urgent, much progress could be made at once by the local authorities in the preparation of the concrete foun dations of the towers, construction of the landing places, keepei s dwellings, roads, &amp;c., during which time the iron towers could be under construction in England. 17. In this connection 1 am to state that the Elder Brethren have at the present time under construction for the Colonial Office an iron tower and third order single flashing light which would be suitable for Tamb Island, and if the matter is very urgent the Elder Brethren would be disposed, if the Marquess of Crewe considers it desirable, to approach the Colonial Office on the subject with a view to the tower and apparatus referred to being utilised for lamb Island, and the Colonial Office work delayed to some extent. If this were done the material for I amb Island could be shipped m August. 18. The drawings of the concrete foundations for the three towers will be ready for despatch to the India Office in time for next week’s mail to India. 19. The time for the manufacture of the work for all the lights is based on the ordinary routine of business; but, should the India Office require quicker delivery, no doubt this would be possible if a premium were paid to the various contractors. 20. If it is still desired to hold a Conference on the subject of acquiring a site on Abadan Island for a lighthouse depot, the Elder Brethren will be glad to arrange for a member of this Board, together with their Engineer-in- Chief and Mr. Hood, to attend. I am, &amp;c., The Under Secretary of State for India. H. G. Willett. I^ERSJAlSr G UEE. Statement showing the Lighthouses, Light Vessel, 13noys, &amp;o., proposed, to be supplied from England</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000151_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/442</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000151</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/442</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 50/1914 Pt 9 'Persian Gulf: Lighting and Buoying'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1912/1923</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-03-30T09:53:21</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (129 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 131; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains letters relating to the construction of a lighthouse depot on Abadan Island, in Persia. The papers are exchanges between British authorities in the Persian Gulf, Trinity House in London, and the British Government of India. The bulk of the papers relate to the replacement of the former site of the depot for its new location at Fao at the mouth of the Shatt al Arab waterway.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>maritime transport</topic></subject><subject><topic>Harbours</topic></subject><subject><topic>Marine navigation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Maritime equipment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000151#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>