<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000be_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T18:57:19.544Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">&gt;- T1 \L Telegram I*F # 0*1927 and 30. Daiv ■ ipt From British Embassy, Baghdad. To Political Resident, Bushire, No.24. Foreign Office, No.175. Kuwait, No.15. Dated and received the 14th July 1936. My immediately preceding telegram to Foreign Office. Prime Minister said that two sons of Shaikh of Mohammerah had called upon him recently and alleged that their father had before his death expressed a wish presenting some rifles to Iraq Government. There is nothing in writing. The rifles are said to number some 2000 to be partly British and partly Turkish and to be at present in a house in Kuwait probably in a cellar ? which formerly belonged to Shaikh of Mohammerah. S Shaikh’s two sons wish to proceed Kuwait to collect them but Prime Minister is not anxious for them to go unless Shaikh of Kuwait woula be willing to release rifles if they exist and unless His Majesty’s Government have no objection. given to Shaikh of Kuwait and that Persian Government should not become aware of this matter. He added that the two sons wish to be become Iraqi aibjects. Could discreet enquiries be made to establish whether rifles exist and if so whether Shaikh of Kuwait would object to them leaving Kuwait. Prime Minister is most anxious that no offence be Prodrome -^■7-yt. Telegram From To I.F.0.27, 50. Political Resident, Buahire. Political agent, Kuwait, India Office, Baghdad. Copy sent by sea mail to Government of India. No. 535. Dated and received the 15th July 1936. Last paragraph of telegram July 14th, No.24. Subject to sanction 4of India Office you should approach Shaikh confidentially and verbally and report the result. -Britconsul- H.C. Put up for me to see. G.S.de G. 14.7.36. P.A. I think the above refers to attached telegram from give Baghdad, although P.R. does not say source of telegram quoted by him nor the subject thereofpl:Vl.&gt;! Secretary of State for India, London* To Political Agent, Kuwait* .. Copy to Political Hesident, Bushire, and Government of India, Simla, by sea mail* Ho.2124, Dated 18th received 19th July 19556. . 1 ^' 1 — Political hesident* s telegram 53S °£ JH-7 15th* Please act as suggested* Secretary of State for India*GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER us 18 an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent bijpost to save teleqraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated on ) cceipt, with the sanie expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it hadbeen so despatched.] From:- Political Agent, Kuwait* To Political Resident, BusKire. /f/7 / r ^o-C-253. miAlT Datedthe 29 th JptXy 1936* / / Late Shai&amp;h of liohaiamerah t s property in Kuwait* Reference your telegram Ho*533 of the I5th July and other relevant correspondence. 2 . I have made the enquiries requested* There is a large number of old arms, the property of the late bhaikh of Mohamzaerah, in the Shaikh of Mohammerah*s Palace here said to be packed in cases, listed and under seal in charge of the negro caretaker, one Jerry Muhaisan* 3. The Shaikh of Kuwait did not seem to have any objections to the Iraq Government getting hold of them but he would of course have to prevent than if it came to his knowledge that they were doing so illegally. 4* Naturally if the caretaker here were faced by the two sons mentioned, wishing to remove part of the family property and without the full legal authority applicable in such a case from the family lawyer and agent he would apply to the Shaikh of Kuwait for assistance in preventing removal.- 2 - &amp;• Tlie family la^ar and agent is Khan Bahadur Mirza Muhammad of Basra who holds a power of attorney from the late Bhaikh of Mohammerah and has all property, here and elsewhere, listed, as presumably the two sons man* tioned must know. 6 . There are, I understand, 13 sons of the late Shaikh in Iraq, 6 in Iran and 1, the eldest - Chasib, in Belgium, and it will presumably be a long time before the estate can be settled and divided according to the Share* Law among these and the various other relations.ct m m rrtcea / ADVOCATE. ★ Telephone No. 02-372 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS : MUHAMMAD code used : BENTLEY’S rvr — r jyti\ ^ — j! a Jl No 2596/2/241. lot A, 5th Novomber 1936. Sir, On behalf of the undermentioned heirs of the late Shaikh Khzaal.from whom I hold powers of attorney in regard to theirs shares in the deceased's estate at Kumit # vizt- 1. Shaikh Bhasib. son of the late Shaikh Khazaal. 2. Maratib # daughter of ” w 3. Badriyah H h n 4. Mansur ah w »» n 5. Ha jar n n n 6. Zahra n t» « 7. Nasrah w M w 8. Zolaikha ff n « 9. Khairiyah n ” » I beg to state that Shaikh Abdul Majid and Shaikh Muhammad Said,sons of the late Snaikh Khzaal, are said to have proceeded to Kuwait,ostensibly for the purpose of 'seeing what has been left behind by their late father '. As I am afraid lest they might cause trouble to Jeri al-Muhaisin, who is in charge of the articles belonging to the deceased , and to Shaikh Khzaal»s widow , who is in charge of the household effects available at Shaikh Khzaal's house at Kuwait, I have thought it necessary to represent the fact to you and to request,on behalf of the aforesaid heirs,that you will be good enough to suggest to His Excellency The Ruler of Kuwait not to permit them to interfere with anything belonging to the estate of the deceased until such time as all the heirs of the deceased can be legally represented by duly authorized attorney or attorneys. I remain. Sir, Your most obedient servant. General Attorney for Shaikh Chasib,Maratib and six other heirs of the late Shaikh Khzaal. To, The Political Agent, Kuwait.c/ tncie/ ct in ?n &lt;% ADVOCATE. ★ Telephone No. 02-372 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS : MUHAMMAD ★ code used : BENTLEY’S 1 t — • X j ykJ I joc — J'jl&gt;* No 2609/2/241. ctdia A, 6th November 1936* Sir, I beg to state that Shaikh Chasib returned to Basrah last night and informed me that he had paid you his respects . He added that he had duly delivered previous letter to you and that you were pleased to take the necessary action in the matter. / ^ I take this opportunity to convey to you my best thanks for the prompt steps which you have been good enough to take with a view to protecting the interests of the heirs of the late Shaikh Khzaal, and I trust that you will accept my gratitude. I remain. Sir, Your most obedient servant.iOimpjINTlAL. POLITICAL aGUNCY, KUWAIT. The 15th November 19 5 ®. No.C-389. From Captain G.o.de Gaury, ^i.C. , Political Agent, Kuwait; To The Hon’ble the Political Resihent in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire Late Ghaikh of ^ohaiamerah* s Property in Kuwait. Sir have the honour to refer to my Express Letter No.C253 of the ,29th July 1956 in reply to your telegram Jo.533 of the 15th July 19 36 , and to report that a somewhat dramatic incident took place iBre on the 5th November arising out of the desire of Abdul Majid and Mohammad Said, sons of the late Shaikh Khaza’l Khan of Mohaiomerah, to partake of their father’s property without delaying for the distribution under ohara T Law. 2. They decided late on 12ie 4th to make a dash the next morning from Basra for Kuwait intending as their elder brother Chasib'believed, to sell or raise money locally on the movable property of the late Shaikh and possibly seize the arms mentioned in the telegram and letter to which I refer above. 3. They chose for their journey a 12 cylinder Buiok car in which they probably hoped to outdistance any pursuers by several hours. Chasib hearing of their intention very sensibly stayed to obtain from the late Chaikh’s Agent in Basra, Khan Bahadur Mirza Mohammad Ahmad of Basra, who holds power of attorney for Chasib and a number of the heirs, a letter to the Political Agent seeking his good offices in the matter. He was able to set out after his brothers only a few minutes behind them at the start, but in a Chevrolet oarThe Buick was driven here at break neck speed, as I well know since it passed me as I was entering Kuwait early on the morning of the 5th but only an hour or so later Chasib arrived at the Agency, having established a record for the Kuwoit-Basra road and hastily presented to me his lawyer’s letter, a oopy of which I attach. 4 . His :ibccellency the &lt;uler was absent on a hawking expedition and I therefore sent for and handed the letter together with a letter also attached, to his Secretary, reminding him verbally at the same time that the export of arms was in particular a care of yours under Hie agreement for the suppression of arms trade. 5 . Ghasib returned to Basra on the 5th and his brothers on the 7th^ having confessed themselves to local acquaintances defeated by Chasib and without,as far as is known to His Excellency,having removed any property of the family. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant Captain Political Agent .KuwaitCOPY. |U No.2596/2/241. MOm&amp;lAD AH14JiD, ADVDCATii, Basra, 5 th Nov amber* 36. Sir , On behalf of the undermentioned heirs of the late Shaikh Khaza’l, from whom I hold powers of attorney in regard to their shares in the deceased’s estate at Kuwait,viz:- 1.Shaikh Ghasib,son of the late Shaikh Khaza'l, 2. Maratib, &lt; 3. Badri yah 4 # Mansur ah 5 #Hajar 6 •Sahra 7.Nasrah B.Zolaikha 9.Khairiyah I beg to state that shaikh Abdul Majid and Shaikh Muhammad Said, sons of the late Shaikh Khaza’l, are said to have proceeded to Kuwait, ostensibly for the purpose of n seeing what has been left behind by their late father'. As I am afraid lest they might cause trouble to Jeri al-Muhaisin, who is in charge of the articles belonging to the deceased, and to Shaikh Khaza’l’s widow, who is in charge of the household effects available at Shaikh Khaza’l’s house at Kuwait, I have thoa^it it necessary to represent the fact to you and to request, on behalf of the aforesaid heirs, that you will be good enough to suggest to His Excellency the Bular of Kuwait not to permit them to interfere with anything belonging to the estate of the deceased until such time as all the heirs of the deceased can be legally f represented by duly authorized attorn^ or attorneys. I remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant, od.Muhammad Ahmad, General Attorney for Shaikh Ghasib, Maratib and six other heirs of the late Shaikh Khaza’l. aught er ' »* m To The Political Agent, KUWAIT.^ / «H ’ / (&gt; '3&gt; Copy* (Bilingual) To iO POLITI CaL AGiSNCY, KUWAIT. The 5 th Hovember 19 36. His ulxc alienoy Shaikh Sir Ahmad al Jabir as-Subah, K.O.I.iiJ, , C # S.X., Ruler of Kuwait, After Compliments, I have the honour to forward herewith to Your Excellency, for any action that Your Excellency sees fit to take, a copy of a letter to me from Mirza Muhammad, Advocate, Basra, No.2596/2/241, dated 5th November 1936, which has been brought to me by Shaikh Chasib bin Shaikh Khaza* 1 . Usual Ending, Sd.Gr.S.de Gaury, Captain, Political Agent, Kuwait.CONFIDENTIAL. No. c/270 of The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Ambassador, British Embassy, Bagdad. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). Office of the Po3.itleal Resident in the Persian Cxulf, Camp, Kuwait. British* TfoTiS date' General! “RITSTITK^]. Dated, 4th December 1836 , Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. xN'ame and Date. Subject. Kuwait letter No.C/329 dated the 13th November 1936, with enclosures. LATE SHAIKH OF MOHAMMERAH* S PROPERTY IN KUWAIT. ^opy forwarded with t o t he ‘Pol it ica 1 compliments Agent, Kuwait. &gt;/t &gt; 3 Confiuential . D.O.No. C- A'KI My dear Sir Trenchard, Political agency, Koweit• The yth Leoenber, 1957. Seventeen members of the family of the late Sheikh of Mohammerah are visiting Koweit to look round the family property here, i.e. the 'Palace', consisting of the very large buildings at the Jtest end of the town, a 'harem' and 'diwniya', some smaller town houses, and various things stored in them, before their final disposal. On the : th the lawyer -han Bahadur Mirza Mohammed, —s accompanied by ^akhri-suitana (now called Madam Butoul Mafi) the late shaikh’s senior and 'permanent' wife, and Mirza Hussain Shakkaqi, her brother-in-law arrived, and in the next day or two sheikh Chasib, the eldest son is expected. -ail have visited the agency, and have recountec. to me their troubles, with their o.,n family, and the Iranian and Iraqi authorities. 2. Disposal of the property here is to be undertaken at once. home thousands of pounds worth of carpets are ^ found to be so moth eaten as not to be worth so many pennies. The buildings, now in bad condition, nay be bought by His Highness the Bhelkh of Koweit, whose property and the Agency they adjoin. Bilver, and other small objects will be divided or sold locally. There remains two very old carriages, which were offered to the Agency but which seem unlikely to be saleable except as fire wood, and the ^rms and Ammunition, to which I first referred in ray letter IIo.C-255 of 29th July 1956. The Hon’ble Lt-Colonel Sir Trenchard Jowle, K.C.I.E., C.B.l., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BUS HIRE.The latter have been opened up and I inspected them this morning, and found, that there are:- Rifles. Short Lee Yufield 227 Long S4 Turkish 138 blansers 13 Martini Carbines 9 Long Martinis 7 428 The weapons are in fair condition, as weapons go in this part of the world. They would be condemned by any British Service Turkish about b0,000 j&amp;glish about 100 , 00 J The ammunition: is much of it loose in sacks, and would take long to count. It appears to be mostly dated about 1917. 4 # I have of course informed the Ruler and agent of the heirs that the arms are not to be exported from .uoweit without your wishes being first ascertained. On visiting the Ruler today I spoke to him about their weapons and the a .munition, and I gather that ^he family wish to sell them to him and that he would like to purchase them as a reserve for emergency. the arms and ammunition are already 'imported' I do not see that we can object, and it seems to be quite the best solution for their disposal. Unless I hear from you I will not therefore demur, and shall report when he transfer has taken place, which may not be for some little time as both parties wish to drive a good bargain. Yours sincerely,Translation of telegram dated 9th Decemher 1937, from, Shaikh Chasih Shaikh Khazal, Basra, to. The Political Agent, Kuwait, Please do not permit' sale removal our father's \ properties as I wish in future to 'bring it to Iraq, my brothers Abdul Majid and Mohammad Sa'eed has sold their shares to me. Copy of telegram No. 291 dated 10.12.37 from, the Political Agent. Kuwait. To, Shaikh Chaslb Shaikh Khaz'al, Basra. Your telegram 9th December removal of goods matters for Local Authorities but in case export of arms I must have prior and full application before sanction can be given.B A S H CL VO lolitical agency, Koweit The f38th December, 19^7 In continuation of my letter N 0 .C-DO 6 of ^7th December, 1 j 57, I have now been favoured ith His Highness f s remarks. I understand that he is not averse to purchasing the arms, and would pursue the natter direct with you, were it not that Jhaikh Chasib T s agreement appears to be lacking. Initiation of any further action in the matter therefore appears to me to be once more with you. 2 . I take this opportunity of offering you my Best wishes for the New Year. uharomed Ahmed Bs uire advocate&gt;|(© Political agency ^oweit The 27th lecenber, 1927 &gt;Vith regard to the statement signed by the heirs, which is attached to your letter to me of the 25th December for which I thank you, I should inform you for their information that export without permission is prohibited. They could ofcourse apply for permission giving destination and details. manage a sale, and remit the value to the heirs, but I will certainly, particularly because I know the regard which ray Government had for the late Shaikh Khaz^a} Khan , do ray best to facilitate the matter of theifr^dT^osal in an appopriate manner, and I will take an early opportunity of speaking to His Highness the Huler, and ascertaining I feel too that it is not within my role to reply Advocate BASRA{/lammct c/J&amp;A m etc/ ^ W ^ (£3 ADVOCATE. ★ Telephone No. 02-372 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS MUHAMMAD ★ tVT —r jyui jop cope used : BENTLEY’S Wo 3.‘i3l/3/283P. £$ad&gt;€iA, 25th )e&lt;,€Blb ® r I th*5t I h*=iva berai unable to write to you befo^o in regard to the arras ani ^iinunition available at the palace of the late Shailh Khaa&amp;’al Khan at Kuwaiti and I beg now to offer you the *inoer© thanks of his heirs for the great interest which you have been good ©nou^i to t Jce in the matter* Befora we returned to Basrah#! obtained a document from the h irs who hai assembled «t Kuwait#agreeing that the arras and arar ujiition should be place d at your disposal and that the same should be sold to any party or body you consider desirable* and 1 beg to enclose for your information a oopy of the doonmant and its translation in triplio te* 1 need hardly add that the heirs shall be extremely grateful if you will be pleased to accord them your good offices in effecting the sal© to Hla Highness The Tul &gt;r of Kuwait at ouch a figure as y u may consider fair and j st with due consideration to th© heirs. I conclude with renewed thanks# and respectful cop Ilmen ts , Captain S.i.de Oauray# Political dgent# IUW4IT,&lt;Si ! The reeaon fbr writing this document is That we, ths undersigned heirs of the late Shaikh Khazaal Khan, do sol^nnly adnit and truly deolnre as follows!- ^here*'® there are the undermentioned arms at the palace belonging to our late father,Shaikh Khzaal Khan ,at Kuwaitt- Bri~ish rifl#a,(aho»*t) Do do-— (long) Turkish rifles jiau* er * Martini rifles,known as 'Dickson* Rifles known as 'l^li'ah' 227, 54. 138. 13. 6 . 3. 7. 478. And one hundred rounds of a^ounition, more or less. And whoreas the sale of arms is prohibited «*t Kuwait and so is th ir exporta tion from that place, we have,therefore, agreed and arranged between ourselves to place the aforesaid arms unier tho manageratnt of His Honour the Political Agent at Kuvmit and we authorise him to sell the same to any party or body he considers desirable and to remit the value to us. He have given this iocuraent in order to explain this fact. Dated 8th December 1937. (Signed)Abdul Asi* ash-Shaikh Khzaal. Abdul Karin ash-Shaikh Khzaal. Abdullah ash-^haikh hzaal. Abdul Majid ash-Shaikh L hzaal. Shaikh Khzaal. Amsr al-C asibi,general attorney for Zinah bint ash- haikh Khzaal. J|| ii cr, &gt;ti m ct &lt;A i l im&lt;za / ADVOCATE. ★ Trlkphone No. 02-372 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS : MUHAMMAD ★ code used : BENTLEY’S No 3331/3/283P. Jilfty tvt — • r jyUI ^ &gt;ui * ^JctdlizA, 25th Dep arab or 1^37, I ras-et that I hara bean unable to write to you before in regard to the arms and munition available at tire palace of the late Shaikh That’al Khan at Kuwait, and I beg now to offer you the sincere thanks of hi. heir, for the great interest which you have been good enouj* to take in the matter* Before we returned to Basrah.! obtained a document from the heirs who assembled at Kuwait.agreeing that the arms and ammunition should be placed at your disposal and that the same should be sold to any party or body you consider desirable, and 1 beg to enclose for your information a copy of the dooumont -md its translation in triplicate. I need hardly add that the heirs snail be extremely grateful if y OU Will be Pleased to accord them your good office, in effecting the sale to His Highness Ihe Ruler of Kuwait at su,h a fi^re a. yo. »ay consider fair and just with du© consideration to tho heirs. I conclude with renewed tn.udcs.and respectful compliment. . Captain S..vl.de Gauray* Political Agent, KUWAIT,The reason for writing this document is That we, the undersigned heirs of the late Shaikh Khazaal Khan, do solemnly admit and truly declare as follows*— Whereas there are the undermentioned arms at the palace belonging to our late father,Shaikh Khzaal Khan ,at Kuwait*- And one hundred rounds of ammunition, more or less* And whereas the sale of arms is prohibited at Kuwait and so is th ir exporta tion from tliat place, we have,therefore, agreed and arranged batwehn ourselves to plaoe the afor9said arms under the managoraent of His Honour the Political Agent at Kuwait and we authorise him to sell the same to any party or body he considers desirable and to remit the T&amp;lue to us* We have given this document in order to explain this fact. Dated 8th December 1937. (Signed)Abdul Asis ash-Shaikh Khsaal. Abdul Karim ash-Shaikh Khzaal* * Abdullah ash-Shaikh Khzaal. ' Abdul Majid ash-Shaikh Khzaal. Abdul Ke-zim Sultan al-Chasibi,general attorney for Badriyah bint ash- Shaikh Khzaal. Amer al-C asibi,general attorney for Zinah bint ask-shaikh Khzaal* * Muhammad Ahmad,general attorney for Shaikh abdul Hamid al-Khazaal,on his own behalf and as guardian of minor heirs. Shaikh Mansur al-Khazaal. M&amp;sud&amp;h al-Khaz&amp;al. Maratib ' Sareh n Khairiyah ' Najmah * Zahra ' Mmsurah H Madame Batul liafi,on her own behalf and as guardian of her minor son, Nizam-ed-Din * I I confirm this document (Signed ) Muhammad Amin, Clork to the Secretary to the Ruler of Kuwait. 9.12.37. British rifles,(short) 227. 34* Do—-do— (long) Turkish rifles Maua er 11 Martini rifles,known as 'Dickson* Do—■■———do— Rifles known as 'Tali*ah” 138. 428.r 4 I regret that I have beesri unable to write to you before in regard to the arms and ammunition available at the palace of the late Shaikh Khaz'al Khan at Kuwait; and I beg now to offer you the sincere thanks of his heirs for the great interest which you have been good enough to take in the matter# Before we returned to Basrah,I obtained a document from the heirs who had assembled at Ku-wait,agreeing that the arms and ammunition should be placed at your disposal and that the same should be sold to any party or body you consider desirable; and I beg to enclose for your information a copy of the document and its translation in triplicate. I need hardly add that the heirs shall be extremely grateful if you will be pleased to accord them your good offices in effecting the sale to His Highness The Ruler of Kuwait at such a figure as you may consider fair and just with due consideration to the heirs. I conclude with renewed thanks,and respectful compliments , ^ f - - —— Captain S.M.de Gauray, Political Agent, KUWAIT*The reason for writing this document is That we, the undersigned heirs of the late Shaikh Khazaal Khan, do solemnly admit and truly declare as followst- Whereas there are the undermentioned arms at the palace belonging to our late father,Shaikh Khzaal Khan ,at Kuwait*- British rifles,(short) Do do (long) Turkish rifles Mauser M Martini rifles,known as M Diokson w Do do Rifles known as ”Tali , ah M 227. 34. 158. 13. 6 . 3. 7. 428. And one hundred rounds of ammunition, more or less. And whereas the sale of arms is prohibited at Kuwait and so is their exporta tion from that place, we have,therefore, agreed and arranged between ourselves to place the aforesaid arms under the management of His Honour the Political Agent at Kuwait and we authorize him to sell the same to any party or body he considers desirable and to remit the value to us* We have given this document in order to explain this fact. Dated 8th December 1937. (Signed)Abdul Aziz ash-Shaikh Khzaal. n Abdul Karim ash-Shaikh Khzaal. ” Abdullah ash-Shaikh Khzaal. ' Abdul Majid ash-Shaikh Khzaal. ” Abdul Kazim Sultan al-Chasibi,general attorney for Badriyah bint ash- Shaikh Khzaal. ” Amer a 1-Cliasibi,general attorney for Zinah bint as^-SJiaikh Khzaal. M Muhammad Ahmad,general attorney for Shaikh Abdul Hamid al-Khazaal,on his own behalf and as guardian of minor heirs. Shaikh Mansur al-Khazaal. Masudah al-Khazaal. Maratib ” Sareh n Khairiyah M Najmah ” Zahra M Mansurah H Madame Batul Mafi,on her own behalf and as guardian of her minor son, Nizam-ed-Din . I confirm this document (Signed ) Muhamnad Amin, Clerk to the Secretary to the Ruler of Kuwait. 9.12.37. 7^ 31 Translation of a letter from Basrah dated 26/12/37 from the sons and duagthers of the late Shaikh Sir Khaz*al Khan of Muharnmar ah to t he Po litical Age nt, Kuwait. A/C Herewith we heg to enclose copy of a letter which we have sent to H.'~. the Buler of Kuwait after perusal we would request you to settle the matter. Kuwait 1 . ecelpt' Date! Translation of the copy of their letter to the Euler of K uwait, referred to above. A/C Our Brother Shaikh Ahdul Majid has negotiated with ¥our Highness about the sale to you of the Arms left among the propeties in Kuwait left to us By our late father and By this application we all agree to the sale of the arms t to Your Highness and that the proceeds Be diveded among the heirs according to the law. We request final settlement of the matter and thank you in anticipation.JonflO ?ntial Political Agency, Koweit. D.O.No.C- H The 12th January, 1958, My dear Sir Trenchard, T vUll you pleas© refer to my Demi-Official Do. 0289 of 9th December, 1937, 2. The Sheiich of Doweit on the point of purchasing the anas for £.3,200. I shall report when the transfer is completed. Yours sincerely, Sd.G.S.de Saury. The Hon’bie Lt-Colonel Sir Trenchard Fowle, K.C.I.D., C.3.K., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Abdulla Mulla Saleh Kuwait 1 7th Jan’ 1937 ^^ Dear Mr.Bhasin, I have pleasure in returning the telegram you so kindly gave me yesterday. Thanking you,T el aftram . Translat Ion, From, Abdulla Shaikh Khaz*al, Basra. To, the Political Agent, **uwait. dated 15th January 1938. Rely on my acceotance of the purpose for which my brother# are present before you 0 »emlt my share after comoletion through lawyer Muhammad Ahmed.Confidential . D.O.No.C- -v-3 u) Political Agency, Kuwait. The 20th January, 1938 Q ^ .fill you please refer to my D.O.No.C-14 of 12th January, 1938. 2 . The arms have now been bought by His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. Th^Hon’ble Lt-Colonel Sir Trenchard Fowle, K.C.I.E. , C.B.jS., Political Resident, Persian Gulf.No 236/3/282P 25th January 1938, 1 oeg to acknowledge the receipt of your letters Nos 0306 &amp; So? of the 2 7th and 28th Deoemoer last* and to thank you for the same* His Highness The A?nir telegraphed to me on the 16th instant suggesting that I may fonmrd to him copies of the povrers of attorney held by me from those heirs of the late Shaikh Sir Khazaal who are represented by me^dulv certified by the Notary Public of Basrah and the Political Agency at Kuwait*but as ms indisposed and unable to visit Kuwait,I caused the copies to be duly certified by the Notary Public and by H # B # M*s Consul,Basrah,and forwarded them to His Highess with a covering let tor by registered post today . I beg to enclose a oopy of my letter to His Highnes and its enclosure for your perusal* I trust that the action taken by me in the matter will meet with your approval and that of His Highness, and that I will receive a draft for the shares of my clifuts so that I may issue the necessary receipt or receipts for the same. I conclude with best thanks and an expression of my high esteem. Captain G*3,deGauray, Political Ag«it, KUWAIT,Translation » BASKAH The 20th January 19S8 0 To# His Highness# Shaikh Sir Ahr*d al-Jabir as-Sabahi , K # 0#S # I„ K*C.I p * Mir of Kuwait and Uoporfl ®oio., ,C * * ** KUVrkIT. After due respects «d inquiriou after your august health, i have had the honour to rooeive your telegram regarding the aumbi s ,io* of certified copies of the powers of attorney heid by me from my eXients.members of the family ° f y0Ur Unol9 * S1 -^ ^hsaal Khan, and I desired to pay respects to Your Highness but could not do so,unfortunately for me.owingto indisposition. I beg of you to acoept my exouse,and I trust to be able to oall on Your highness in the near future. I now have the honour to forward herewith thirteen copies of the aforesaid power, of attorney, 7Z °' “ 1 •' '■ 5, Shap:h Abdul Karitu Khan bin Shaikh Khzaal. 4* shaikh Abduilaii Khan n » 5. Shaikh \bdil Jalil Kh«n M » 6. Madam# Mansurah bint 3hailc)| Khaiaal. T« ' Has rah *♦ ^ Khairiyah* M «t rt Sarah « n * Najmah ' * * Zahra a tf Maratib n « Batul Mafi Fakhive^Sultanah.widow of the deceased, on her own behalf „nH as guardian of her minor son. Hisam-ed-Din bin shaikh Khsaal. ' f &amp; 8. 9. 10 11 12 . 13. also submit herewith a statem^t allowing the divisloyi of the value of the arms and ammunition amongst the partie. who are ry clients. Year Highness will note, my clients oensist of nine of the sons and twelve of the duaghtor. and also the widow of the deceased, who is entitled to on^.ighth ofthe total value, the ^ount due to th*. i. . therefore. * 35.373.4.0. or Dinar, 3.496.601 . 1 would re 9 ue,t.therefore. thai you will be pleased to order that a draft for the same may be issued on any Bank her. or on any other party.so that the amount. i.e.DWe 3495.601 . may be paid *, me and t ,o necessary receipt be taken from me either in the shape of one receipt or separate receipts on behalf of each of my Clients.as I an keeping separate files fbr each. I reiterate my deep regret at my inability to pay Your Highness w resp6ots at present and I wuld solicit to be excused. (Usual complimentary aiding ) (signed jHUharmad Abroad.c/ tzr/ i ci ?? r m cf ADVOCATE. S ★ Telephone No. 02*372 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS : MUHAMMAD ★ code used : BENTLEY’S No 235/3/282P. -u*' J rvt — • r jyui w O ^Scidict/i, 25th January 1938. /“N 1 beg to acknowledge the receipt of your letters Nos 0306 &amp; 307 of the 2 7th and 28th December last, and to thank you for the same. His Highness The Amir telegraphed to me on the 16th instant suggesting that l may forward to him copies of the powers of attorney held by me from those heirs of the late Shaikh Sir Khazaal who are represented by me,duly certified by the Notary Public of Basrah and the Political Agenqy at Kuwait,but as was indisposed and unable to visit Kuwait,I caused the copies to be duly certified by the Notary Public and by H.B.M»s Consul,Basrah,and forwarded them to His Highess with a covering le^oer by registered post today . I beg to enclose a copy of ny letter to His Highness and its aiclosure for your perusal. X orust that; 'the action taken by me in the matter will meet with your approval and than of His Highness, and that I will receive a draft for the shares of my clients so that I may issue the necessary receipt or receipts for the same, I conclude with best thanks and an expression of my high esteem. Captain G.S#deGauray, Political Agtnt, KUWAIT.u / Baerah, 12th September 19 38 To, The Political Agant Kuwait • Bear Sir I learn that my brothers with Aghai Husain Sheqaqi will be visiting Kuwait shortly in connection with the estate of my late father there• Should they approach you with regard to the estate, I request that you will take no action in that connection in my absence* But if my brother and Aghai Sheqaqi are accompanied by Sayed Muhammad Ahmad, advocate, I will then agree to any action that you may take and which both you and Sayed Kuhammad Ahmad consider proper in connection with the above estate, although I be absent from Kuwait* Thanking you in anticipation*0 V C onfidential No. C/438 Political Agency, Kuwait, April 26, 1942. My dear Scott, I am enclosing a communication which X have received from the Chief Engineer, Bases and which T shall he glad if you will return to me after perusal. 2. Could you very Kindly let me know what the requirements will he for 2(h) and if you could assist with 5 provided the Electric Company are unahle to undertake the work. Yours sincerely L. D. Scott, ^squire. M.C OUUvv, C , 'A • U • , General Superintendent, Kuwait Oil Company Limited, Kim IT.CONFIDMTIAL 6' %-Q D.0/24 2 &gt; 0 KUWAIT. ARABIA. 28th April, 1942, 0tC4L+ ^ I acknowledge receipt of your D.O. 6/438 of 26th April 1942 and return herewith the letter and drawing sent therewith. I also append a note on the water supply and electricity arrangements. Major T. Hickihbotham, O.B.E., Kuwait.1. WATER SUPPLY : M ain Storaj^e Tank ; gallons, 4 sections each 13 * x 12* x 8', Xaorx*- Each section to have a rectangulai* isanhole in the roof, as shown — Pilling by hose through manholes. Delivery by suction hose through manholes. Cleaning by hand through manholes. Pumping to Service Tank on roof of building : Allow 50 ft head and 10 ft suction. s Electrical purqp preferable but hand lift and force pump could be used. Pipe and fittings required: Delivery : Line, ij' or 2 n dia galvanised water pipe with fittings screwed to suit. 100* run galvanised water pipe screwed and coupled. 1 pair flanges and bolts, or coupling to fit pump delivery and delivery line. 4 screwed anot collared bends. 1 screwed Tee. 1 screwed Valve. 1 screwed Plug. 2 spare screwed collars. Hoof tank and services; 1 wooden tank 1,200 gallons. Size of delivery fittings stated The following are the requirements of pipes and fittings to supply water to three sinks and one faucet in court-yard vide drawings, all imst be supplied as Oil Company has none available for sale. 20 staples for fastening pipes to walls. Drains from sinks to outside of buildin g; Pipes and fittings required. 80* run l-Jf' galv water pipe screwed &amp; collared. 5 - li* screwed A collared bends. 2 - n unions. 3 - pairs 1 Screwed flanges with bolts. The Kuwait Oil Company will carry out the work if required, provided material is supplied. The town electrical simply is 220 Volts D.G., the house is not at present connected to it. The occupier is recommended to supply own lighting set but if this is not available the house could be connected to town supply. 10 I ;] .suJ ahoir Is cnq a is IUT fl O* *• ^ illi X a position for pump Suction: 1 - Suction hose with foot valve and strainer fitted with coupling to pump. Length, say, 20 ft. as 1^** or 1 M , latter preferable as Oil Company has no stocks and dies for 400 ft run galv water pipe, screwed A collared. 12 spare collars for above. 1 pair screwed flanges with bolts. 1 screwed valve. 7 * unions. 1 * A collared bend. 15 * elbows. 3 ' Tees. 4 M taps (faucets) for sinks. 3 ' nipples 6' long. 2. ELECTRIC LIGHTING A POWER;Political x^gency, Kuwait. 30th April, 1942. Ko.C 23/7. To The Chief Engineer, Bases, Basrah. Reference your meraorandum No.CEB/S/48, dated the 20th April, 1942. 2. (a) I am endeavouring to purchase iron tanks but if they are not available I will have a wooden one constructed. Arrangements are being made to strengthen the roof. (b) I enclose a note compiled by the General Manager of the Kuwait Oil Company. (c) No reinforcing available so I am having a tank of concrete blocks built below ground level. This is a very satisfactory means of construction and the cost will be fe.3469/4/-. The work is in hand. 3. Army funds at present with me amount to fe.7356/8/- and for the^ water Tanks programme I shall require fe.17,100/- as I have given an advance of fc.5000/- to the carpenters. I suggest that Ife.20,000/- be sent here as soon as possible. 4. This will be gone into later. 5. See note from the Kuwait Oil ConqDany enclosed. Political Major, Agent, Kuwait.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. MEMORANDUM. (N.B .—This form is oniy to be used for correspondence of minor importance with subordi nate authorities-) From To No. Dated 19 . ') Reference letter memorandum No. dated S. 153. MFP—1647 S&amp;P-{M-2690)—30-5-40—100,000.Telegram ■From Siiaibah To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. E243. Dated and received 6 th May 1942. IMMEDIATE. Lieutenant Lumley R.E. and another officer will visit Kuwait about 1030 hours 9th. Also necessary discuss ShaikhKHazal’s Palace may he necessary these Officers stay night.CONFIDENT! Kuwait keceip Dateii Telegram Erom To No. Dated 7th May Enelair Political Agent Shaihah. nil 1942. Kuwait. I MPORTA NT. 'll Your S243 May 6 th. 9th will not he con venient hut I can see Officers concerned at Shatt al Arah hotel on 8 th afternoon or here after 11 th. PoliticalR.A.F. Form 96A. MESSAGE FORM Office Serial No £7 No. of Office Date Stamp Call IN Groups and GR Preface OUT TO * S i t u (Above this line is for Signals use only). PROM* - Originator’s Number Dat In reply to Number and Date 'Is ( Write horizontally) V , VkUtvVr'O, /S P'tA. V &lt;y*-eje /F Jib / ~—W fefeS*-9&gt; 15 rtftn / &gt; 20 rr'*tr ^ &lt;&gt; ifrt A r ttScAS- 25 r A, 30 r 9- a/- rSiZ 40 45 50 7^ /—'v 55 - 60 This message must be sent AS WRITTEN and mayj be sent by W/T. Signature This message must be sent IN CYPHER and mayt be sent by W/T. Signature Originator’s Instructions* Degree of Priority. ^^Originato^o^inser^W^O^^^message^s^iot^tc^oJb^tV/^^ve^irivjgar^^^if^routf^^Below * 1 £0U4*4U/ slow tms line is tor Signals use only). TIME OF ORIGIN. T.O.R. System in Time in Reader Sender System out Time out | Reader Sender System out Time out Reader Sender T.H.I. * The Signal Department is responsible that these details are transposed to the appropriate portion of the message form and that all possibihty of compromising distinguishing signals, etc., by omitting to remove their significat ion from the address, etc., is avoided. Before delivery o f the me ssage thes e details are to be re-inserted in P/L. Ml 3188/147 7.37 70,000pds. lOOfms. CT&amp;CoLtd Gp.51-100.'V CONFIX x r i HP. Dated /fy* _ I lOG-K DATED 7th APRIL, 1942 TO THE ALL 1 STAET POLITJOAL ADVISER, BASRA. XXXXXXX* XXXXXXX XX xxxx xxxxxxxx ocxx I am infonried tliat Sheikh Chasib, eldest son of the ol^ Shaikh of Mohanmerah, Khazal, has been down at Fao very redentl^/ (about 1/4/42) and has been getting his agents to visit the Arabs of Gusba and Shahdgan on the Persian side in order to try to stir up trouble between them and the Persian ofiijciais. lie is giving out that he has some 20 C 0 rifles and amnuni t^ ion at Kuwait with which he can supply them if required. In his case as you are aware he is anxious to establish himself as the ruler of this district and is trying to get all the Arabs to recognise him. Re lives in Basra and he was warned only last year to desist from such activities. xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx xxx. x xxx xx xxxx Forwarded with compliments to Political Agent, Kuwait, for his information. fVo. 4. 4z. 'in &lt;o Confidential The Residency, Bushire, the 27th May 1942 D.O.No •488-S The Governnient of India have informed me that they concur in the views expressed in my demi-official letter No*0/337, dated the 8 th April 1942, to you, on the subject of Shaikh Chassib f s intrigues. Major T*Hickinbotl: Political Agent, Kuwait •H*Q. L: OF Cs ARLA No: 200/46/Q* Basra Apr 42 e P.A. KUWEIT 6 SBAIKH CEtlSSIB 1 s HOUSE» ^43 3 0 L Ref: your wire of 1st Apr 42. Arrangements have been made with Shaikh Chassib for the leasing of his house which will be utilized for accommodation purposes. The C.E. Bases, has been ordered to get on with alterations and repairs which are necessary.■ ’^1 ~ / kSIlAIKH HAZA1 ' S PALAGA KW T • Political Agent, Kttweito V -I** Chief Engineer Iraq. Base, CEB / 279 / /E-2. 14 May 42. 'll CONFIDENTIAL Kuwait Receipt —*- ; A await Keceipt /l &gt;n0 J xVc b^Q Paced 'Ll.S.. X Aft Hef: - Your c/439‘~23/1''^etied~3Q^4 t^- His.,! It:, is noted that you have accepted estimate of its, 3469 / 4 /- for construction of tank for 30,000 galls, below ground 0 V. With regard to filling of this tank, can you arrange for this to be done from large tank at Schwck by means of tanks mounted on lorries, by a local contractor. \ S After it has been filled once, the unit occupying Shaikh * Hazal’s iabce will be responsible for filling. 3 Regarding the pipe and fittings required by K.O.C. for water service and drains it has been necessary to apply to Baghdad for release of these. It is hoped that release will be granted very shortly and the pipe and fittings can then be despatched to the Oil Co. straight away. l\ . 1 should like to take this opportunity of thanking you for your assistance in this matter and the Asphalt scheme and for the hospitality offered to my officers. ?. A. U ^ ' V ' ’^3 ^ CHI Copy to:- ”Q” - .RE. , BNGIHnER, Iraq ‘ Base.As instructed, I saw Sheikh HemoodUal- Jabir,Pre sident of The Municipality and asked him if he could arrenge Lorries with water tanks to carry water from Sheweikh to t e new water tanks. He asked me to convey his compliments to you and to state that he is quite prepared to do so. He said that they have a Lorry which is used for watering the streets,the capacity of its tank be is 1000 xallons. This Lorry is ready to/placed at your disposal. As to the charges for the same,Sheikh Hemood refused to quote any charges and he said that he will leave that to you. His only intention is to offer his service to the Oovt. and to do whatever he can to co-operate with her. ?-A. ALv Y k ^ trVVc Vq ^ V Vq ^A' WvAAA \^-ACc V O cLa-v^&gt; ^ btvi^v^VC U-fc-u '^Vu-qkvA ' ^^ % b &gt; . ^ c i -, ^ \. ~ A \AM13188/147 7.37 70,000pds. lOOfms. CT&amp;OoLtd Gp.51-100. R. A.F. Form 96A. S. 575A. (Naval). MESSAGE FORM Office Serial Ko. CaU IN (Ifld No. of Groups GR Office Date Stamp Preface OUT TO* (Above this line is for Signals use only). FROM POT.TTTO AT. KTP'A THT 1 Originator’s Number Date In reply to Number and Date 3%/ ( Write horizontally) FOR CHIEF ENGINEER BASE 6 BASRA BWNS YOUR /V' 0 o LETTER MAY 10 14TE AAA TANK AT KHAZAL HOUSE HAS BEEN FITTED AND 20 WATFP SERVICE AND DRAINS • COMPLETED ttrjrl x IliXi 25 ENDS POLITICAL 30 35 40 45 50 /7 55 60 This message must be sent AS WRITTEN and mayj be sent by W/T. Signature This message must be sent IN CYPHER and mayt be sent by W/T. Signature Originator’s Instructions* Degree of Priority.* TIME OF ORIGIN. T.O.R. System in Time in Reader Sender System out Time out Reader Sender System out Time out Reader Sender T.H.I. • The Signal Department is responsible that these details are transposed to the appropriate portion of the message form and that all possibility of compromising distinguishing &lt; s_gnals^etCj ; Jjy_omittingJo_remove^heir i significationJrom_theaddress i etc ;i Jsjivoided ; _ &gt; J3efore^ENGINEER STORE ADVANCE BASS DEPOT. Shalchiya. Baghdad, No. 34/1275/A 1/6/42. CE. Bases for Kuweit, Oil Coy. Copy to:- Director of Works, HQ. Tenth Army, Baghdad Subject:- Desp atch of 6 tores. REF:- DDW(S) 1.0. No. 2999 One bag containing water supply fittings have been despatched to you through A.M.F.O. Baghdad on 30/5/42. Please acknowledge receipt of the consignment. Captain I.E. O.C. E.S.A.B.D.mm No. JT 7^ The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to Messrs. Kuwait Oil Company Limited, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). for in^onr^tio-n. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 20th ^June, 1942. Iteference to previous correspondence : DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Stores for Kuwait Oil Coirosny.•aI Subject:-SCHEME ROSS. ,t Q*- &gt;. y uniei ^ngineervworKs )ZV± 9 Dated' 17th June 1942. ^4g. ^v ; 9 Please note that water tank at Shaikh ikzal I^lace KWT. has been filled and drains k water services cojupleted. Lt.Col.,Sanceau # R.£. f on his visit stated verbally that the palace would not be occupied by his survey group but this has never been confirmed. No further work will be carried cut at Shaikh IIasal f s Palace in view of this. CONFIDENTIAL Copy to:- Kiiwait Receipt 1 *VQsH 3 UaudJzS-Ji-MlJ „ r, ——— — 1 mi or. n. t For Chief Engineer tWorks)201, P.A. Ef/T for information, (ASW/17/6)* ' ^elegrnm ^rom To ,T o. PC TnGlair. Political gent, Tu rrit. Chief Engineer, forks 101, Basra* 388. Dctei the 14th Oeptenher, 1 Q/ 1. 'That is position regarding Shaikh Th° 7 ,al ’s T - T ouse? If you do not propose to occupy it I presume you have no objection to voluntary canteen for troops being run there. - POLITIC 4.1. - c -^ v ^u-,,t4)‘ O AT 'ITAIT. To:- -d^i i ±a h -e n t - Kuwait (2) Go- y to:- HQ. 40 Ind t Inf Bde. ! A lT‘iv*T , nr^Q ( T v’o -*•— v # £ V-/ O.J.X-A- ✓ VA. w • B.A.D. Hirings (Iraq) Ref. H.Q. L of G letter No. 200/46/Q dated 13 Arr 42. I have had the visit of Fr. G-urchi re-oresenting himself as the accent of ..teed Kohd al Ghanim of Kuwait, who informed me that SheikK Khazal* s Palace which had apparently been placed free at our disposal by his heir Sheikh Jassib - building at present occupied by the D.C.R.U.-had been bought two or three months ago by Ahmed Kohd el G-hanirn. The new owner is desirous of obtaining possession of his property and proposes to offer alternative accommodation. As this property has been offered free of rent to the British Forces / the Area, Commander is anxious that every effort should be made to give satisfaction to the owner. Will you therefore kindly contact Aimed Mohd al Ghanim and in conjunction with the D.C.R.E. inspect the alternative accommoda tion offered and report on the possibility of his move there. There appears to be no record in this office of the occupa tion of this building. It is essential that all hirings should be dealt with by this office and I would be grateful for informatiqn if any other property is occupied in Kuwait, either landvor building*or which this ofiice has at present no ;mowledge. * tr . The terra hiring comprises all .D. holdings whether rent is ■: paid or not, including Government Property, and the Army Hirings office acts for the three services and Allied nations. The only exception to this is permanent R.A.F. and Naval bases. For information the only hiring in Kuwait on ssay records is:- The R.A.F. Hospital Accommadation rented from Thaniyan bin Thaniyan al Ghanim. Area Hirings Officer, Captain (J.G. LAXTON): JCL/SIn&amp;ja. Toj - The Political Agent - Xu^it (2)%/ D.C # R # E. Ku^vait. v Copy to:- 40 Ind Inf ode, h. A. D. Hi rings (I r aq } No. 328/Jfeg, Hiring Office. Basrah, £f/3/45. Ref. X.Q. 1 of C letter No. 200/46/0 dated. 18 Apr 42. I have had the visit of Mr. Gurchi representing himself as the agent of Ahned Mohd al (rhanam of Kuwait, who inronnod me that SheikH IQiazal* a Prilace which liad apparently been placed free at our disposal by his heir Sheikh Jassib - building at present occupisd by the D.C.R.B. had been bought two or three jnonths a^o by Ahmed Mohd el Ghanim. The ner CTOier is desirous of obtaining possession of his property and proposes to offer alternative accornmodation. As thin property has been offered free of rent to the British Forces the Area Camander is anxious that every effort should be made to give satisfaction to the owner. Will you therefore kindly contact Aimed Mohd al Ghanim and in conjunction with the D.C.R.B. inspect the alternative acccnmoda- tion offered end report on the possibility of his move there. .. There appears to be no record in this office of the occupa tion of this building. —w- It is essential that all hirings should be dealt with by this office and I would be g&amp;ateful for infomation if any other property, is occupied in Kuwait, either land cr building ox which oms office has at present no Knowledge. The tann hiring^conprisas all W.D. holdings whether rent is * paid or not including Government Property and the Amy Hirings office acts for the three services and Allied nations. bases. The only exception to this is permanent R.A.F. and Naval For information the only hiring in Kuwait on sSr records is*- The R.A.F. Hospital Accccmadation rented fren Thaniyan bin Thanivan al Ghanim. JCI/3I.r 2. There is no D.C.R.E. Kuv/ait and never has been. 3. The building in question never has been occupied. 4. It was hired in April 1942 and was intended for use as a map reproducing center but in June 1942 after a water tank had been constructed at a cost of Rs.3500/- and various water pipes had been fitted the details of which are on the files of the Chief Engineer Iraq Base it was decided that the house would not be occupied. 5. In my opinion no alternative accommodation is required and I suggest the property be handed over to Ahmad Mohammad al Chanim, who has purchased the property( and is anxious to reside in the building forthwith, provided he will pay the original cost of the water tanki I further suggest that the fittings be put up for sale for what thev will fetch and the amount obtained credited to the .rmy Account which I maintain in my office. 6 . No property other than the R.A.F. hospital is leased to or occupied by any military formation. His Highness the Shaikh had handed over rent free certain buildings at Shuwaikh to the American army but their work completed they have vacated the premises. \ Major, Political Agent, Kuwait. \\ »&lt;7 V,X HIRINGS - KUWAIT. Q\ No. 8001/HKa. ' No. 8001/Hp;a. ' To:- The Politioal Agent kHwai 1 m The contents of your letter No # 907 dated 4-9-43 ha«e been noted. THiNIYAN bin THANIYAN al GHANIM was addressed through the Kuwait Oil Coy on account of my predecessors having always dealt with him through the same channel, probably due to the fact that this having been the original tenant of the building was instru mental in obtaining these premises for us and negotiations appear to have been carried out through its good offices. The owner also approached me through the same channel in May this year when a cheque in his favour was mislaid. I would much prefer however treating these matters through f our agency and as this is also your desire I shall avail myself n future of ysur help in all dealings in Kuwait relevant of my department. The contents of your letter No. 902/V14 of 2.9 f 43 have been conmunicuted to the Area Cocmander for his decision and orders and it is hoped to give satisfaction to the owner very shortly. Area Hir JCL/SI~u', jt. Apent ■ Kuv/ail uwaiL Receipt «i m m**** m U - . 328/Hgs. (^6 'in o Office, rah, ^/9743. 40 Ind Inf Bde ^ I' ef A/Q T s verbal instruction to the , (Hirings Offican together with a copy D*A.D. Idrings (Irao)(of letter Ho. 902 - 1/14 of 2-9-43. Ref. your‘letter No. 902 - 4/14 of 2-9-43 and in continua tion of this office letter No. 600j/Hgs dated 7-9-43 last para. Ay^ The Area Qonnander has approved the. proposals suggested in para 5 of your f/o letter. ill you kindly take the necessary steps to implement these and advise the Area Commander on their completion witn a cony to this office. JGL/SI,( P.GULF.) Telegraphic Address ARAB I. Code O'sed Bentley. - r* OUR REPeRENCE 36/292/43. September 16 , 1943 , Political A^ent, Kuwait. dir, Thank you for your letter wo.223 -4/14 of 16 th. September 1943? and accordingly enclosed please 1‘ind cheque NC.C305159 of Ks.3300/-(Rupees three thousand five hundred) only as the price of the water tank, mentioned therein. Also we noted with interest tne last para of your letter and shall let you know about our offer for the tanks and pipes in the house in due course. Kindly acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, for AHMAD MUHAMMAD ALGHANIM, Y.A .ALGHANIM. SNCs ^ / ''***- ■ ^ Afatf-Zlccvu /uZcAjfrO &lt;0 &lt; / &amp;C, ^ j/U f j* * **■*%*- X^cr . &amp;*- £ ^ wAtt $~Jrv~\y\. / V&gt;v&lt;n&gt;^DVt &lt;lc . m* u Messrs.Ahmad Muhammad Al-Obanim, Kuwait. Dear Sirs, Reference your leoter No.58/292/43 dated the 18th September, 1943. 2 . I am sending you the keys of the house. I have arranged to remove today the few articles of Government furniture lying in the house. I shall be grateful for an early decision regarding the pipes as I v r .ish to complete the matter. Yours faithfully, d Major, Political Agent, Kuwait. fj&lt;^KUWEIT. ( P.GULF.) Telegraphic Address ARAB I. Code Used Bentley. % \ OUH REFtRENCE ( ) 12 th Cctober 1943 . H* Political Agent, Kuwait* Bear sir, Enclosed please find my cheque for Hs: 75C-U-U (Rupees seven hundred &amp; fifty only) in payment of the cost oi water tank &amp; fittings in sheikh Al~js.azal f s palace Kindly acknowledge receipt &amp; oblige. 11 Yours faithfully, for AHMAD MtlHAMMAD ALGHAITIM.No.//7z^ To ^ m &gt; Politicijl Agency, 0 \ /oL it, 12th October, 1943* ft' Messrs. Ahmed Muhammad Al-Ghsnim, Kuwait. Dear Sirs, I acknowledge, with thanks, the receipt of a cneque for Rs. 750/- forwarded with your letter dated the 12th October, 1943. fV Yours faithfully,m Printed In England. Sept. 1943. (400) Coimter No. CABLE WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) PREPAID REPLY FORM. Lid' A . The charge for a reply to Telegram No. handed in at on the 27 /L addressed to:' having been prepaid by the Sender, this Form will be accepted WITHIN THREE MONTHS of the date of its issue, at any of the Company’s Branches in pay ment, or part payment, as the case may be of an ordinary full rate, or other class of telegram, where admissible, to the value of_ (Signature of Issuing Officer) Date, i Words. The value of unused prepaid reply forms will be^ refunded to the Sender of the Original Telegram if the form be returned to the ISSUING OFFICE within\ three months of the date of issue. If the charge for a Reply Telegram is less than the amount deposited in payment of the reply, the difference will be refunded to the Sender of the original Telegram on application within three months, providing that the amount to be refunded is not less than one shilling and eightpence or its equivalent. 5/-23S No. of Telegram « ^ ■.JkoEd'bT''“ „ HANDED IN AT Time. 1 Excess Charges. Instructions. Sent at No. and Circuit, Sent by ! i (Clerk's Name and Date Stamp) To Receiver’s Name, Address r I request that the above Telegram may be forwarded subject to the Conditions printed on the back of this form ^ by which I agree to be bound. d Signature and Address of Sender, Telephone Ko. (not to bi: telegraphed.) The Declaration on the back of the form must be signed for Deferred or Letter Telegrams. : i (P.T.O.CONDITIONS. I 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose ; but in such case the amouht paid for transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay, or error, ' or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such * non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall 5 be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Govermnent Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or &gt; delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. THE FOLLOWING DECLARATION MUST BE SIGNED FOR DEFERRED OR LETTER TELEGRAMS I certify this telegram is written in the language, the text is entirely plain language, and it does not bear any meaning other than that which appears on the face of it. Signature ....Address. ...Date. .19..f H.C. What is the position about the Beit Khazal? Are we in fact still in charge? If so we had 'better get the key 'back from the Al Ghanims. T.H. 14/8 P.A . Beit Khazal is still in our possession and we have heard nothing so far from the Military to the contrary. If you agree, I will get the key from Al Ghanims. A.A.K. 14/8 Yes please T.H. 15/8 P.A. I have spoken with Yusuf Al Ghanim about the key of the Beit Khazal. He says that repairs are being ' carried out and it will take at least one month more to complete the work. Progress of work is very slow due to difficulty in getting building materials i.e. gutch etc., 2. He has raised the question of ownership of the house and said that he bought the house from Shaikh Chassib. He has also informed me that Shaikh Chassib gave the house to Military without any rent and no lease exists, /&amp;IL 6/q&gt; . Xsk? *V- *** n, , T Jjh. ' 4' u</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000be_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/199</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000be</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/199</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/14 Property in Kuwait of Late Shaikh of Muhammarah (Khorramshahr)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1943</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-02T22:35:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (95 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 97; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Two additional foliation sequences are present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. One of the additional foliation sequences is written in red pencil between ff 15-29.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding property in Kuwait that was previously owned by the late Shaikh Khaz'al bin Jābir al-Ka‘bī, the former ruler of Mohammerah [Khorramshahr]. In addition to the property itself, the belongings inside it are also discussed including a large number of rifles and ammunition.The correspondence is mainly between British officials, primarily those of the Political Agency in Kuwait and the Political Residency in Bushire. However, the file also contains a limited amount of correspondence with the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jaber al-Sabah, a Basra-based lawyer who represented Shaikh Khaz'al's heirs named Muhammad Ahmad and the heirs themselves. Much of this correspondence is in Arabic accompanied by translations in English.On folio 88, the file contains a blueprint plan of Shaikh Khaz'als property (or 'palace') in Kuwait.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Property</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000be#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>