<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000133_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T04:16:28.844Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">l£ 19/t i $ Telegram R, Froir. Political, Bahrain. To High Commissioner, Baghdad, No.51-C. Dated 3 6th received 16th April 1923. It is reported that Bin Saud sent a large force to renew attacks near Ebha about six weeks a^o. Political.9 The Agency, Confidential ^ahrain , ars-in yj. -» sf/o. 22/4/230 The Hon T blQ the Politic:- ! Resident in t ie ?e raicixi xUlf Buahire• l-«Lioranciusa I ba^ to report for your information, 'etails of a roo.iut occur renca. On April 20th,a fight tooi pla«e in the bazaar an u najii &amp; a Persian .Both stere of th j cooly class. 411 Taj Ixs m 'the Bazaar, collected, amed rith sticks ft r^ssiles, &amp; injured the Persian and Hnoth.'-r who cuuo to his assistance .They also beat the Police who endeavourea to arrest the ringleaders. The fracas ocurraa just outside the Office of Ahdalia ■'.osaibl.tha Fajd Agent hare,v ho however saw fit to bolt his door &amp; i-sfce no effort to control the ; ajuis. Suoseiaantly j IChan Bahadur raha.miad '.harif.who is in charge of the 'unicipaj-ity , arrived on the scene rith ; ore police &amp; aucceaded in arresting four only, of the large crowd of Hajdis aaseiabled. I referred t.» case to the ••adhi to ta ;e evidenc ' '• report. The latter took oertaia avilanoa ' requested that the case aight oe postponeu till i.oe •. ic fi.it. .of tte assaalt had sufficiently recovered to give eviaoneo.He fc-so reco; .-..ended that the accused be released ..eanwhlie,provided a-suitable t nafil' was forthcoming.having ascertained fro., the doctor tr t the condition of the injured ;an,one of v hom Mas st ,iret .op^±L,nd to be dangerously ill. .. such that t^ra WW no likelihood of vary serious results.I released the j ceased after taking a written 'Kifaleh' 'ro.i Abdulla 'os-.ibi. Shortly after this -o^ibi v roto aa a letter accusing K.B. Ttuhan-^ Jharif of having brought police &amp; beaten Kajdisl.aclafin a high-handaa u nnar.He added that the affair was of no iuportance &amp; that had he been present he would have intarvaned ft stopped it at once,instep of using force as K.Sharif had dona. Xatsr he caaa to sea me « tnon dai. ; - - ^ shut hiusalf in his office as » he thought the affiir./as not one in _ which he need intarfare- I si.id his action - as not consistent ,1: ■ what ha had written ft I thought that it was a pity ^ o 1... ijad iiot BUSHlRf BFSIOENCY. b .^*r fc- %&gt;L tall... ooHFiotsiu. UoCnaiy 19/109 &amp; 19/116. T»l&lt;igra.E P. From Cox, Baghdad, To R©sid«nt, Bushtr^. N0.223-S. Dat«d 25th r«9C«iv«d 26th April 1923. Subject of Bahrain. D«mi-official. '•inisit^r has r@p®at«d to si* his telegram No.6!l, I should b® int®r«8t»d to rocsive a copy of any reply you raay s®nd # Is th« Bahrain Order in Council in operation? What is the position with regard to it? Cox. Tslsgram P.X. From Rssidont, Bushire. To High Comnissionar, Baghdad. No.400. Dated 27th April 1923. . • (T«xt of Ewsident'e tsltgram No.9?/^9? datod 2Eth April 192S.)•...#••• VVitk r®f«rsncft to your tttl^grain No.22?-Sf, the abov® is th® text of my rsply to Minister^ toltgram No.PI Bahrain Order in Council is still in operation. 'Bin Saud attitude or rather that of his Bahrain agent adds considerably to our difficulties and weakens our position. I hope that you have received my Demi-official letter No.184-S. of the 17th April and also telegram No.398 of todays date, which reports events that must make the position acute. Knox.Telegram P. From. Resident, Buchire.- To Foroign, Simla, No.?9B, Rapeated to r ahran, No#9 /!1 -; and Baghdad No.598. Datod 27th April 1923 # I hava rec«ived infornation fron th« Political Agent at Bahrain that on th« 29th April a fracao took plac« in the Manama bazaar between a Persian and a Ne.ldi, which developed irto a riot between Nejdis and Persians. No great harm was actually done and the police easily quelled the disturbance, butie Persians are^ Politic# 1 understands, telegraphing protests to Tehran. Political reports that Bin Saud's Agent, Qasaibi, behaved very badly. He is believed to have incited the Nejdis to the fray and loclrod himself in when mischief was well afoot. He was in the end apologetic and offering to pay compensation assessed for injuries inflicted. Am I authorised to tell Bir Saud flatly that we will not tolerate the presence of Qaraibi or any other Nejdi ag^nt in Bahrain, and will deport him to Al Ahsa, unless he confines his activities to merely commercial ends and refrains from interfering with administrative official matters. The position in Bahrain is quite complicated enough without Nejd interference. Qasaibi has been arrogat -ing to himself the position of Consul, and the present affair is merely the culminating point of a long series of petty complaints against him. Fnox. C o t y by post to the Political Agent, BAHRAIN.n 19/163 and 19/166 Decyphcr of Tel, fron Political Bahrain to Resident Bdaiiire NO 60/C Dated and received 10/5/83 Priority Another a&amp;rious disttirhance between Peraiane and Najdia today, casualtiea aeven or eight dead and large number injured. Have atopped the disturbance for the time being but the matter haa aaaumed reldgious aspect and has serious possibitios if tho locals join in: Details by post,• 1 r If gtoboat could visit hero as aAAn aa poeaible and remain till end of Ramazan it woxild have ateadying influence.19/l0^ and 19/166 Tologram R prom Resident Buahire To Foreign Simla ^ No. 424 Dated 10/5/23 'PiZi(r£i~y. Following from political Bahrain begins, 'Another serious disturbance between Persians and Najdls today, casualties seven or eight killed and largo number Injured. Have stopped the disturbance for the time being but the matter ha# assumed religious aspect and has serious possibilities If the locals Join in. Details by post. If gunboat could visit here as soon as possible and remain till end of Raanazan It would have steadying Influence • * Ends I support Daly*3 request for gunboat and should be glad If It or S«N«0. could take me to Bahrain.19/163 and 19/166 Telogram P Pfcon Resident Bushire To Foreign Simla No, 425 Dated 10/5/S3 T /Vo Is it possible for you to assist me in insisting on expulsion of QasaiHi, Bin Gaud 1 s agent ffcom Bahrain as I suggested in my telegram No, 398 of 27th April T The greatest danger Inhere is Wahabi and reforms and Persian proolanation must come after Bin saud has been warned.h' 19/163 and 19/166 C^logran P Fron poroign Sinla To Regident Bushlro No, 623/S (?) Batod and Rooolvod 11/5/23 Tho Govemnont of India In tholr telegram No; 620 /s made tho following oonnonts on your Tela Nob # 424 and 425 /*? v ' to the secretary of State. Orders hav© 'been issued to the Resident to proceed inmediately on one of H.M.ships to BaJirain and report actual situation. It is presumed that Colonial Office will send him instructions with regard to Bin saud# It will be unfortunate if he has to Initiate his relations with Bin Saud with a stern comrmknination but in the circumstances this seoms inevitable unless he finds that Qasaibi is so frightened by events as to turn in^o a useful tool* Ends. You should ma3cr» yfcur own arrangmonts direct with Senior Naval Officer unless you have already done so. /19/109, 19/lfl5 # 19/166, it 61/6. Telegram P. To Foreign, Simla • Repeated to Colonial Office, London. No.429. Dated llth May 1923. Please refer to my telegrams Nos.484and 425, I propose to take the following action with a view to pacification of the Island: Arrest Qasalbl and take him to Kuwait where he can be handed over to Bin Saud's agent for Customs negotiations, and returned to Nejd for his master to deal with. I would send a/letter to Bin Saud telling him that his agent has caused serious trouble ih Bahrain, and that I hold that agent responsible for bloodshed which has bean caused, for it is unthinkable that Persians are the aggressors. I may have to get rid % of a Persian or two as well, but will act after appreciation of causes that led to present trouble. I would at the same time warn Dowasir headmen in Bahrain that if there is any recrudescence of trouble, I will have their boats Kept out of this pearling season, and to help them to be respons- -ible for their coreligionists, would express readiness to deport at once to A1 Ahsa any turbulent ringleaders whom they choose to point out. With regard to the return of any agent of Bin Saud to Bahrain, I would point out to him that we have warned off French, Germans and others and we do not propose to allow him to upset status quo , and that he must consult us about new agent, who must have definite instructions to confine himself to purely cora-ercial ends and hold strictly aloof from Consular functions and internal administration of Bahrain. This would be best done from Kuwait where I propose to go on as soon as I can safely leave Bahrain. I see the possibility of putting the CustomsIz IV 11. queetlonx at Kuwait in the way of settlement. Daly's recent letters from Bahrain encourage me to hope that we can either get a proclamation out of tlw Sheikh or permission to deport foreigners, and would ask permission for free hand to settle Bahrain difficulty in one of these ways, whichever appears the most feasible. The time of the proclamation, whether from us or the Sheikh, preferably from the latter, would be postponed until after departure of the gunboat from the island, for I entirely share the view of advisability that Sheikh should appear to act of his own free will, and I do not despair of carrying him with me. If you agree, kindly have instructions sent to the S.N.O. Persian Gulf to give all assistance in his power. I have warned him of my requirements. . Knox« H Telegram P. From Resident, Bushire. To Hinister, Tehran. No.105/446. Dated ISth May 1925. / I repeat for your information my telegram No.429 dated 11th May f adiressed to Foreign, Simla and repeated to Colonial Office: Begins........(text of above telegram)..# Ends. Knox. 115 19 /163 &amp; 19/163. Z~i &gt;- Resident, Babr ^.in. Tnr* i/gn , ;*&gt; ials . kixxlfciter, TehTAu; a-nd ColoniAi Ctfioe, Londoii. TelegrajL P. PTcm To Reputed No. B-l. Dated 1511-1 1923 My interview tnis morn Lag with tii* Political Agent ar^ Siiaikh fc^XLAd encourages me to hope th&amp;t th^re will toe no reci'^deocence ol &lt;5ibt-irb«»noe6 . rbn S*j£l has left fox Riyadh. Tne T^clitioal Agents re^orta ehow that ^asattol w^s Intimately concerned with these second diaturbances also, and I think it advisable to rio Bahrain oi hi&amp; by aaKing hiffi bear a letter to Ibn gaud ^oaplaining ot hi^ conduct and ask ing Ibn Faud to deal with hia and not to send another agent to Bahrain without cone-ilting the Britisn Oovarmnent who have t *ken the^e If?lands ^inder their protection, whether such ohoioe eftect be acceptable. Triis must be done 3peedily for a salutary /on others , ard unleae specifically forbidden 1 shall take action in trree dayp . secondly Rajnisan and the .ap it caching Id enable me to defer exchange of vifcit- with Shaikh Is^. until -the 19^^ May . This give? me time tc consider with th'S Political ^gent the beat net hod of oorzEvn ice ting the w c rningj of your Ho. 475-S of the 17tr ^pril, authoxieed In Pecre+ery of State(3 telegram NO2 1269 • prrom reports X have received 1 doubt if 3*aikh lea is mentally capable of appreciating their effect , aad tne only poeaible course, to which 1 would ©odeavour to guide con— vey^a-tionfi , would be virtual abdication in favour oi naiaan , while still preserving the nominal Shaikhdom to old Shaikh. Tne Polltioel ^igent eees no necessity for deportation of Abdullah, who has been behaving irreproachably ofmmmmmmrm nl —' °f b 4 &amp; /C&gt; 1 Tele^rar P. Fror. Foreign, Sir la. To Resident, Bahrain and Bushire. Fereated to Secretary of State for Indie, ptfl 'iriste:- Tehran. .'&gt;o • P52- S . Dated 19th recei ved 19th . f ay 1927. i-, |U • • Yout telegran No.Bl. was received yesterday and repeated to Secretary of State for India. H. .3ovt s orders can hardly reach you by tomorrow, and you should defer action with reward to Qasaibi until their receipt, if thif is praeticahle. Presume you do not propose in your coT -mnication to Bin Saud to imply that British protection Bahrain is anything new. The ?ovt. f of India consider your- nroposed tactics over the reforms-suitable. Foreign. f/£ 7 19/162. Tele^ra^n P. From Secretary of State for India. « To Resident, Bahrain, repeated to India. NO . lS4«lr. Dated 19th received 19th May 19??. TlaiB foil owing telegrara to your address from the Ssoretary of State for the Colonies is repeated for your guidance, begins Ji You are authorised to send a letter to Ibn Saud 'by Qasaibi as proposed in your telegram No.B.l of the l&lt;?th ^ay. It is understood that you withdraw your previous proposal to place the individual named under arrest and remove him forcibly in a British vessel to Kuwait. To treat Ibn Saud 1 s ardent in this way would be open to grave abject- -ions, which you have no doubt recognised especially when the gravity off the crisis seems to nave worn off. In measures necessary to bring obiectionable activity to an end, you have our fullest support, but at the same titoe both on this subject and in regard to oil concessions (see separate telegram) your communications to Ibn Saud should be framed in terms of studied courtesy and conciliation. b'ov one thing this is your first communication to him as the official channel of correspondence with H.7. Govt., and for another, the recent decision to discontinue his subsidy must make him particularly sensitive. Special caution should be observed in the method of intimating the conditions that will govern our consent to the appointment of a new agent. Those suggested in your telegram No.429 have my approval. 4 * Enos. oyW ■ Subject to India's remarks I approve other proposals in your telegram. Secretary of State for India.19/16?. xele^ram P From To Resident, Bahrain. Secretary of Atate for India Repeated to Foreign, Simla No.B.2. Dated 19th May 192^ I received your telegram No.lB44 in t^ood order I took action last nip;ht with regard to Casaibi, who took the communication without a word and l.eft immediately although I had given him until midday today. Although the communication to Ibn Saud was despatched before receipt of your telegra/n sanctioning it, I have every confidence that it entirely corresponds with the directions now received^ except that I laid down no conditions snd merely asked before sending the nw agent he woula ascertain from ri• sr .Govt. that his choice was acceptable to them. I trust that this leaves us free to communicate conditions when he applies. There are some indications that Casaibi will be made a scapegoat. Official visits with Sheikh Isa have been exchang- -ed this morning, and serious conversations commence with interview this afternoon with Sheikhs Hamad and Abdullah, and tomorrow morning with Sheikh r §a. Knox • *J\ Bahrain 1st March 1925 To, The Secretary of Siite for India LONDON May it please Your Lordship, 7e, the undersigned, Merchants and Inhabitants of Bahrein - (which city is under the kind protection of the benign British fk)ver -nment) be? humbly and respectfully to piece before your Lordship - the following few lines with a fervent hope that the same will - - receive your kind consideration. That the late Haji Mansoor Pasha and his brother Haji Abdul - Hussein Aljoma of the town of Bahrein but residing at Katiff (near Bahrein) were men of great influence and respect and were respected by all the people of Bahrein Katiff Rassa and Mesopotaiiiia,Mujtabids the Persians and the Persian Officials. That these men had immense properties at Katiff and ^esopota- -mia,and had also many charitable institutions ,all the needy people of Bahrein and the neighbourhood were aided and treated by them and their fame for the charity and good work is well known to all the - people of Bahrein,Mesopotamia and Persia. That after the occupation of Katiff and Hassa by Ibn Saud the Sultan of NeId, at the instigation of the enemies of these two men - and other interested persons the Sultan of Nejd had HaH Abdul Hussei Al -joma arrested (Haji Mansoor Pasha died before this incident) and secretly put hdim ( Haji Abdul Hussein Al-joma)to death and confis - -cated all their properties at Katiff and ordered his troops to - - plunder, i That after tkis incident the children of these two deceased - persons fled from Katiff and several times petitioned the Sultan of * Ne.id for the return of their properties at Katiff but to no avail. 2.That at their failure to set back their properties at Katiff from the Sultan of Nald the children of these deceased persons for the sake of their honour and prestige be^un to sell their remaininf properties which were in Iraq.(Mesopotamia)for their maintenance ar and they are now in a very pitiable condition and penniless. . riat after the death of these two persons the religious - - freedom which the people of Katiff and Hassa had enjoyed was put to an end and the people of these two places were and are ill - - treated by the Sultan of Nejd. Ve have placed all the above facts before your Lordship and ; now most humbly and respectfully pray that your Lordship be ^ood e: enough as to do somethini? for the children of these two unfortun?tf persons,who are at present in ?reat distress,that they may e^et - back their properties at Katiff from the Sultan of Ne.idand we are confident that your Lordship's efforts will be quite succesful and: we have approached your Lordship as we know that the benign Britisl Grovernment is just and the defender of the weak against Might,a nd we are not only appealing on our own behalf but also on behalf of the people of Katiff and iiassa (who through fear of being prosec- -uted by the Sultan of Nejd cannot openly join us in our appeal) and we again beg to express our confidence in your Lordship that your efforts will bear good fruits and* for which not only we but all the people of Bahrein Katiff Hassa and Mesopotamia and Mujta- -hids (Hi^h Priests) from bier and small will be highly obliged to your Lordship and will pray for your Lordship's Ion? life and |)r®y prosperity. Ve shall esteem it favour if your Lordship will please reply our humble petition through the representative of HIS MAJESTY'S BRITISH Consul at Bahrein iife have the honour to be 'Vour Lordship's Most obedient and humble sevants.If) \ &gt; ■ ON —• - -V IP/l'?. and BS/1. Telegram R. Fro - Political, Bahrain. To Resident, B^shire. No,71-0• Dated und receive^ 2nd June 19S?. Priorit y. Sayed Hashim has co^e fro^ Bin Saud to see you. 1 Should he ceo direct to Kuwait to -eet you there. Daly. The above telerra^ repeated to the Heeideit at Kuwait under this office nunber 50^, dated 2nd June 19?'. Tele-ram R. From Resident, Kuwait. To Political, Bahrain. Repeated to Political, Bushire. No.K.5. » •Dated and-received 3rd June IQSr 7 . r Priority . Sayed H shim had better co-e to Bushire, where I arrive on Friday next, and A^ha Kne^lil will nut him un. Secondly, with reference to my telerra^ No.K.to Simla, repeated to Bahrain, nlease ta v e action on instructions and at the same time inform ?heikh Hamad that the A.P.O.C. are a firm approved by ri.' .Govt., • and n:ive MacVie such assistance in obtaining a concesoion as he may properly asV from you by usi:-^ your influence wi th Sh ei Irh Har ad . Knox Copy to A.S« for the information of Agha Khali 1.19/16? and 19/165. Telegram P. From Secretary of State for the Colonies. To R-esident, Bushlre. Repeated to Baghdad. No.253. Dated 5th received 6th June IQ^I 7 • Situation at Bahrain. Your telegram of the 24th May, addressed to Govt, of India, repeateu to Secretary of State for India. You should inform Tbn Baud in such terms as you think best of the transfer of Bahrain administration to Sheikh Hamad as regent for his father. You should add such explanations as' appear to you necessary and desirable c^ tne circumstances that have led up to this step. Devonshire.' 'J* Telegram R From Da5.y Bahrain To Resident at Uohammerah Dat'ed 5/6/£2 My Telegram Jo, 71 G I Isarn from Doc6or Abdulla that Seyid Hasim has come from Bin Saud regarding Qaisaibi. Bin Saud aaid to recognize he was a bad select ion as an a^ent ■j^ut mildly protests aganst Qaisaibi naving been Qisraissed before he was told. I explained that time did not permit. To interferef?) I replied 11,nought that you would not tolerate him here at present but that his brother could stay if he gave n o trouble. D octor Abdulla informs me privately that Bin Sa^d was 0 nly making mild protest to save his face before others. A1 1 J- t_lat was necessary was to reply that 'action taj^ori in noi way affected his prestige DALYBritish Residency and Consul at e-G- enoral, Eusl ire, l5tli Jime 192^. To His Highness Sheikh Sir Abdul Aziz 'ben Abdor Rahman A1 Faisal As S-ud, G tt C.I .E 0 , Sultan of No^a and Dependencies* A^Ca Your Highness, I ht ve the pleasure to inform yrrj. that, at the moment of writing, I am looking forward to the visit of Your ill hness* o^cr tcry, Gaiyed Hi-shem, who is expected at the Residency in about half an hour. I have myself only returned to Eushire two days 3 s L ound myself obliged to -oroceed to Kuwait and thence to ] ohammerah and i^hwaz • '■ - i travelling h^s made it impossible up to the present to acquaint Your Highness with Events that have occurred at Bahrain since my letter to Your Highness of the 18th -ay. How that I am at comparative lelsrure I hasten to j. iorm Your HiThness of theae mattere which I feel sure must h of grc.it in -orest to you. I am the more inclined to do this, as I have the advantage of the presence of Your Highness Confidential secretary «hO will, no/ doubt, transfer my lettori to Your Highness hy sure and speedy means. t Per : '0\; l-ie past, affairs in Bahrain had been unsatisfactory, sheikh Isa's increasing age had made it impossible for him to exercise that vigilant supervision over aff. irs, 'ich is so necessary in an Arab state 1 , and, owin,^ to t is vreaimess, m^ (irresponsible) petty tyrants had been 5ro ' Tin S 1 ' B ahr a in, criiefly irresponsible members of the al Khalifa family and the Be^^rinah were grievously pppressed by them, iiore than this, the increased intelligence of the' lov7or classes, who are now constant readers of newspapers and al soy* so also ( ncouraged by various agitators for their own ends, had rendered those classes far less -oatient imder misrule and oppression than they had 'been in the past. They Trere very numerous and thoro was constant danger that they light take advantage of their numbers and rebel against their masters when foreign sympathy, especially Persian and Shi.?, might have made British supnort of the al Khalifa difficult, Darti^ularl^ as there was no shadow of doubt that the Baharinah had valid grievances.• Further owing to the weakness of Sheikh Isa'r rule, the rights of the Sheikh of Strain were either Vttaifllhing or being frittered away by being subdivided among nurrsrous persons 14 no way entitled to those rights. The British Government were unable to tolerate uch a state of affairs. It was hopeless to exiDect sheikh Ira, on account of his age, to enter on the stony Dath of reforrc arfl the Government ardently desired that Sheikh Isa would, in his own interests, see the advirability of adbication but unfortunate ly our old friend could not bo brought to see this and it ^as necessary for me^under direction of my Government, to tell him that hile he might remain in Bahrain and retain the titular dignity of Sbeikh, he was to stand aside and allow his heir apparent, Sheikh Hamad, to endeavour to set the Bahrain affairs in order and bring that Government up to the plane of modem civilization without interference or dictation of .^ny kind ^rom his father. T is is 'e position. Sheikh Isa is still Siieikh of Bahrain but the direction of affairs has been handed over to Hamad as fully empowered a^ent for his father whom he is in no way bound to consult. I have troubiec* Your Richness with this long d-oscrip _on in the hope that the British Government may rely on your sincere and lasting friendship to accept the present ^ v of affairs and explain tjie situation to others who are in eres-ec . We firmly believe that the steps that the Briti Government has been reluctantly forced to take win eventually co v ^c to he stability of the rule of the al Khalifa family.Will prevont foreign interference and preserve the essentially Sunni influence in the administration of the islands and the nrogress of all Sunni elements of the population. I feel sure that Your Highness will sympathise with the aims and objects which the High G-ovemment hag in view and will exert your powerful and highly valued moral influanoe to assist in their realisation- U sual ending » LtA^y —^ Lieut- c ol •, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,,D .0 uio . *-^1? mm id Th* H®eid©rxoy f Biahir*, 19th Jun« 1923 My d«Ar Daly , la letters which will follow ,ycu will that Bin daud haa mad# heavy waath^r about Uoliasmad Sharif. Ha ob jects to hid dual ^odition ao Haad of tiia Police aad working in^nbar of the municipality. Aptarently Abdul ^zia and ^yed ha^him are under the im^re&amp;dion that he id ^revident of the xDunioii-alit^^ieiil am pretty sure tt is not the oaae for 1 understood that Shaikh Ham ad was . Of oojrae, In the neg- otiatione ^bdul Aziz w^a anxious that ^ohamxnad Pharif should be dismissed as a sort of counterpoise to the action we took against Abdul la al ^asaibi • poth you and 1 are firmly oonvlncei that MOl^ammed Sheriffs guilt, if ^ullt there was, is as nothing compared to the ^asaibi responsibility. Perhaps you will not be pre pared to admit any guilt at all on the part of Uohanj&amp;ed 3 her if, and in any case it woild merely stir up sleeping dogs if any in^airy was made as to their respective responsibilitiej • But 1 think it will do no harm if yoa call up ]»oh» ammed anerxf and warn him of what he probably kiows , that he is now a marked man and held by the Hejada responsible for thrir disccmfiture . It therefore behoves h^ to walk very warily and circumspectly for some mcntha at least; perhaps this will suffice # Yours sincerely t Major C. k. Daly, politic?.! Agent, Bahrain •Tha i3aid eacy 9 ]3iiaLiir« # 2Cwh Jua« 1^23. My 4«^r Daly 9 1 4Bi lOfWcUTulag^ JU tdJt Ad copies ot corredponaence acccadiiig to th* atAtdaaax •noio^ed . 1 as* * Air aid tfo . 8 is jtill i&amp;iii^iiig Aod will b« seat here a iter with' number a of the variouA letters wnea aot^lly available. * Uatcrtuaate ly 1 am very bacly aerved by my vernacul ar oil ice whioh id very weak hence the delay* Duxiug the negotiations there waa consider ble talk about Abdul .iziz ^aaaibi and 8yed Lashis greased me hard to give hitt a letter to the Sultan of Jejd aaying that Abdul ^zia ai ^aaaibi w^a a peracn acceptable to the Britiah Government provided he com plied witn the two conditions laid down in letter Ho. 7« 1 intonned dyed hashim that while ny personal opinion was that, subject to those conditions , ^.bdul ~ziz .\1 ^asaibi would be a person entirely accertable to His Majesty's frov- ernaent, 1 was unable to coi&amp;i&amp;it myself in any official letter without conaulting Political /vgent, P^hr^in, India and home. It tne Sultan of ilejd aaw his wy to writing a letter asking me officially if Vodul Aziz *1 ^asaibi was so acceptable, I would consult the authorities concerned and entertained every ho^e that ny application would be aucceas- ful. Personally 1 had no objection Put 1 could qi-uite appreciate that the Sultan night be averse, possibly think it inocffij.atible with his dignity, to make 30 complete a surrender. In such case I suggested that the Sultan should write to xibdul AMtm a1 ^fasaibi privately informing him of the conditions under which his appointment as Ibn Sa , ud'a private apent would be acceptable to Lis kajeety's Government, warning ^bdul *ziz to lie low for a time and let him gradually grow ui-• I used a homely simile to the envoy to comfort him, telling him that if ^bdul iais onlyf '£&gt;&lt;£&gt; oaly followed out our advio# aiid laalructlooi, a® would ily find ou* tliat he would b© able to couoh a o »Bi «l in tne Political Agent's drawing-rooia while ^hdul , by the former x&amp;ethodd jwould find it isposaible to introduce a mou^e wrapped in a napkin into a corner of the Politioal ^geat^ oooiirOund 1 hOi-e thid will aake the siVoatica fairly clear to you and to ^end you a copy ot my official report on these matters by the aucceedliig mall. Youra sincerely, To iaajor C . Daly , Political Agent, Bahrain*iff trom- H.H.Shaikh Sir A^dol Aziz ban Abdor Rahnah Al-Faisal Aa-Saud, a.O.I.E., Sultan of Hajd and dependencies, Riadh. To - The llon'ble Lt-Golonel S.S.Knox, C.S.I., G.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian &gt;iulf, Bushire. Dated 24th Shawiral 1341 (=10th Jxan© 1923). A.C. I received your letter dated Snd Shawwal 1341 (=19/5/23). I received formerly a similar letter by Abdollah Al-ftasaibi to which I sent a reply through my protege, Saiyed Hashem, and certainly ±t nas reached you and perhaps you have looked at it carefully and attentively as expected and desired and I do not see it necessary to repeat what I have already informed you, but I hope that you will not leave rn© in my great sorrow and extreme grief. You should know that I am impatiently waiting tor your _a r oura;:le reply and pray trod to inspire ooth of us the right path and prosperity.■ - • ■ ■ .l jV t d . o. JO . yi&lt;£ -s I • British Residency , Pus hi re , 3Cth June 1923 My dear Taly f ly. ? ^ Your L/O. No. 84—C dated 2oth June. ?yed Bashim was fairly clear that he desired the return of ^bdulla .is an indication to Pin Faud that hia tia© with ire at Pushire had hot been entirely wasted from the point of view of His High ness the Pultan. I think that we may well afford to give way in this little matter, and if Abdulla's return will save face of the preat nbdul xxziz pin Pa' jd , 1 find it diffic ult to resist so cheat a bargain. It he is obstreperous we can pet him removed again by formally cciLi,laining of him to the Pultan . Your memorandum No. 85—C dated 26th June is a much more serious proposition. 1 have an idea that I heard some- where that Pin Saud was considerably indebted and therefore in the hands of the Q^saibi family. The question , therefore, of whether it would b® possible ^o oust the ^asaioi influence altogether will very much depend on the Sultan's attitude to wards the t mily. I think you will ^gree with me that 1 nothing would be more dangerous to Dr • Abdulla Faeed than tnat 1 should give a hint to the Fultan ol Jejd that he would b« a persona grata. You will r«niember that we rather protested against his receiving a decoration on that ground , and one knows exactly what the®*# Oriental potentates are . 1 think we can only watch and wait in regard to pin baud's private agent. If Dr. Abdulla himself could manage to get nominated that would b« quite a different thing. Has he, by the way, returned from Baghdad ? As far as 1 can make cut, he did not cut much ice there. Sir Henry Dobbs 1 attitude w^a coldly correct. Yours sincerely, Major O.K. i^aly , Political Agent f Bahrain19/163 • 47 u* Extract from a letter dated 22nd Zil-iadeh 1341 ''yth Julv 1923) from His Highness the Sultan ol Nejd to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf , 'Now I reply to your second letter (No . 174 dated 15th June 1)23) in which you have explained the state of affairs at Bahrain , the actions which were taKen by you. and Phaikh Isa's retirement from afiairs , etc. My friend, you are better aware of the aims of your policy about which all that we know is its well-known justice to Arab chiefs and its permanent affection to them, but I do not conceal effect from you how much regrettable/ the latest events in ahrain and the actions taken against the authority of the old Shaikh isa , Chief of Bahrain, with whom you stated to have maintain ed friendly relaticns for the last fifty years , have had oh the public. Yes , it is certain that you did not take this step to your new policy unless you were confident of its fudbure good result • But 1 hope that our exalted iriend ^Government) takes right steps in her just way towards her iirab friends as she is well-known for it. This is what has to be said and may you be preservedH I hi* st NO. poiifiomiA. &lt;uvflai. ,: DOWNING STREET, Sir, lour , 1923. ) W \p* - j 0 to acknowledge the receipt To t n. 10 Aus^. I have the hon&lt; of your despatch No. 314 S, dated the 23rd of June, 1923, transmitting a report on recent negotiations with the representative of His Highness the Sultan, of liejd, and to 0 t . r transmit herewith for your information copies of corres- do. pondence with the India Office on this subject. 2, While I see no objection to the return to Bahrein of Abdul Aziz al Q^saibi in a private capacity, his return as representative of Ibn Saud could only be approved by His Majesty*s Government on the conditions i. * stated on page 5 of your letter No. 1^2 dated the 14th/ 20th June 1923 addressed to the Sultan of Nejd. Before taking any definite action in this matter you should communicate with the Government of India as suggested in paragraph 2 of the letter from the India Office above referred to. 3. In order to enable me fully to appreciate the question of visas on passports of Nedji subjects, 1 shoula be glad to be furnished with your further observations on the question of the grant of such visas, with special reference to that aspect-of the matter which is referred to in paragraph 3 of the letter from the India Office. 4. t. t'o &amp; &amp; 4. I observe that in your letter No. 179 dated the I9th/20th June, 1923, you address Ibn Saud as 'Your Majesty'. I consider that his status does ) not warrant the use of this mode of address which should be discontinu- ed v I have the honour to be, Sir, . , Your most obedient, humble servant. *3 / # •Q*Cr m C m vL(*Urffi U yj 1 O DESPATCH ^ • f *■ &amp;' I ' ^ ^ No. ^ OF 3/f/^ • Copy. No. 35971/1923. DOWUIHG STREET, 10th August, 1923. 23rd June 19 23, K Sir, I am directed by the Duke of Devonshire'jto refer to this Department * s letter No. 26957 dated the 2nd of June 1923 transmitting a copy of a telegram addressed to the Political Resident at Bushire regarding the termination of the subsidy paid to Ibn Saud and to forward herewith to be laid before Viscount Peel a copy of a despatch (with enclosures) which has been received from Lieutenant Colonel Knox regarding certain negotia tions with Syed Hashim, Ibn Saudis Envoy. 2. I am to invite His Lordship 's attention to tr.e terms of the communication No. 173 dated the 14th of June, 1923, addressed by Lieutenant Colonel Knox to Ibu Saud on the termination of the subsidy ana to say tr.at Hia Grace Yiews the suggestion made therein that ''the door of help has not been flnaJLly closed' as liaole to misinterpretation by Ibn Saud, since it is not the intention of His Majesty*s Government to resume payment of the cub sidy to this ruler in any circumstances what ever* He considers however that it would not be practicable at this juncture to repudiate the suggestion which was made by Lieutenant Colonel Knox. S, His Grace proposes, subject to nn^ observe...-, which Hio Lordship may offer, to inform Lieutenant Colonel Knox that he sees no objection to the return to Bahrein of Abdulla El qasaibi in a private capacity, but that his return as representative of Ibn Saud could only be THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, INDIA OFFICE.1 s'S be approved by His Majesty's Government on the conditione stated on page 5 of the letter l T o • 172 dated the 14th/ 20th June, 1925, addressed to the Sultan of IJeja. 4. His Grace observes that in his letter No. 179 dated 19th/20th June, 1923, Lieutenant Colonel Knox addressee Ibn Saud as 'Your Majesty' • He considers it desirable to instruct the Political Resident that this \ raode of address should be discontinued. 5. His Grace further proposes to approve the attitude adopted by Lieutenant Colonel Knox in regard to the question of passport facilities for this ruler's subj ects. 6, His Grace wiH be glad to learn whether His Lordship concurs in the issue of instructions to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf in this sense. I am et c ., (Sgd) H. Young, for the Under Secretary of State.j3 S2# India Office, Whitehall, London, S 0 W.l, 21et August, 1923 Sir, In reply to your letter (lio .35971/1923) , dated the 10th August 1923, on the subject of the relations of His Majesty's Government with Ibn Saud, I arn directed 'by the Secretary of State for India to say that he concurs generally in the instructions which it is proposed to issue to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, He would, however, be glad if the Government of India were consulted on the question of the return to Bahrain of Abdul Aziz al C^usaibi, and he would suggest that Colonel Knox should be instructed on receipt of replies from the Political Agent, Bahrain to his demi official letters on this subject to communicate direct with the Govemmert of India before taking definite act ion• In regard to the question of visas on the passports of Kejdi subjects^ Viscount Peel observer that Colonel Knox, in the 9th paragraph of his report of the 23rd June, states that 'Iraq and India, to which two countries his (Ibn Saud^) subjects chiefly travel, are inclined to insist on the visa of a British Consul'. In his reply to Ibn Saud Colonel Knox makes no suggestion as to how Nejdis travelling direct to India should obtain British visas. Lord Peel has not up to the present received any communication from the Government of The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office. i5^ rv of India on the subject, 'but as the question will probably be raised in due course, and as Iraq is also concerned therein, he would suggest t^at Colonel Knox might be requested to forward a more detailed report on this aspect of the passport question 0 I have etc•, (Sgd) R,7/.Garrett.Arnm I „ /&gt; v yW ^Cr^lA r (/; /£: Tci'^y $&lt;LO(uk ctuS C 2 / *S 'fad'H*** (flj fv A-4^ (MiC ik clyj~ J^t Uj t* &lt;*** J** U*t t bfytfl J ^f hu^^j 4 /4cx jicu , P/ n ■ i^- , I O h^? 4 0 (J Letter No . 8 dated 3 rd September 1923 with enclosures , from Colonies . SECRETARY . There is very little in the letter cited above . The spare copy should be sent to P.ii. t Bahrain, to be filed in his archives. I think we have already sent to him my despatch No. 3l4~S dated 23rd June 1^23. We might ask him for any observations he may have to ofier on the subject of Abdul az I z al ^asaibi to gether with a report as to where the gentleman in question now is , e .g . whether he has return ed to Bahrain , and secondly , whether there are any indications to show that he possesses the &amp;*jv''UuU. ol the Sultan of Nejd • thirdly, whether he has shown any aggressive tendencies such as the political Agent had reason to com plain oi in the past . In para 3 0: i Colonies letter cited , T 1 am asked for further observations , especially in regard to how Nejd is travelling direct to India should obtain British visas . as the Political Agent , Bahrain^ will ncdoubt quickly appreciateappreciate . the reason for my makine no sugg estion is that the number oi N«jada who travel to India direct without passing through either Bahrain , Kuwait and possibly Muscat , must be so very limited that their cases could probably be dealt with individually by India without much trouble and I have thferelore not thou^- ht it nec essary to raise the point. I shall however be glad to be furnished with any observations which the P.a. pahrain , may send me , and espec ially I shall be plad of an estimate from him as to the number of such Nejada who are li&gt; el to travel to India in this way and what route and means ot travel they might be expected to select. I do not consider that this letter from Colonies needs any other actican and as the reply from Bahrain will probably take gome time to reach us I am afraid I shall be ccmpelled to leave it over for my successor to deal with. 2Rth September 1 j23 it f} 3 -ic-iCGi^F IDiitWT iAL • a *l Iql'U A '- Iq , , J / No.S'^'i- -t? of 1923' prltleh Residency and Oonsulate-Gsneral » Bushire, 4Uh October 19^3 • ProB i). 0 . Law , Esq . , 1.0 .S . , georetary to t^ie Political ReEident In the Ptrslaui Gulf To The Political /kgent, Satcrain. f. n Sir, . / 1 aa. directed to torwaxd a copy of a despatch No. 0 dated 3rd September 1923 and enoioturee from His Majesty's Secretary of ?tate ^or the Colonies and to ask for any obser- vations you may have to cfler on the subject of /ibdul A^ia al qaeaibi together wl%h a report as to where the ^entl^man in question now is , e .g. whether he has returned to Bahrain', secondly , whether there are any indicationa to show that he possesses the confidence of the Sultan of ^ejd f thirdly whetn^ er he hae shown any aggressive tendencies such as you had reason to coaplain of in the past. 2, In paragraph 3 ^he despatch, Colonel KncA is asked for further observwtions , especially in reg rd to now Nejdis travelling direct to India should obtain British vls^8&gt; hs you will no doubt quickly appreciate , the reason for his making no suggestion is that the number of Nejada wno travel , C i • . to India direct without passing through elthar Bahrain, Kuwait and possibly Muscat f must bo «o v^ry limited that their cases could probably be dealt with individually by India without m-icU trouble and he has therefore not thought it necessary to raise the point. He would however be glad to be furnished witn any observations which you can send him t and especially '1 L . of an estimate of the number of itfejada who are likely to trave. to A ' rn No #288/353/604. Political Agency,Bahrain, Dated 29th September 1923 To 3 o ~s~ : \ The Hon*tie the Political Resident V j iv. in the Persian Gulf^B U S K I R 1. .v- i MEMORANDUM. A Bahrain! named Haji Ahmad bin Muhammad Ali Khaiyat has filed a suit in the Joint Court for recovery of a house in Qatif- has replied The Amir of Qatif /that the house was the property of one Mansur bin S&lt;U^ OubttJ bin Juma* ,nov/ deceased,and that the latter was owed a sum of nuc money by the Plaintiff for which the house was mortgaged.On the other' hand,the heirs of the late Mansur are some of them here in Bahrain,fcs.: and state that they have no desire whatever to hold the house for the debt .The real facts are that the Sultan of Nejd seized all the property of Mansur bin S (I imagine there must be a file on the matter in the Residency records,or among the files transferred re cently from Baghdad.),and among the papers found^the Sanad from the « present Plaintiff and used it as an excuse to seize the house in question.The heirs of Mansur some months back petitioned the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,London,for redress.I write to ask whether tt is advisable to c!o anything in the matter or whether a reply should be given to the Plaintiff that he must fight his own case in (^atif. / iVS * m Maj orfl .A., Political Agent,Bahrain.Confidential The Agency, tiahrain, 17/10/23 lUSHiSt JliSfOna ». t U i — 10 /Q - ^&gt;-1- '' QSSFIOfcSIIA. J ron t o. 2ht -Political Agent, Bahr^-in. -the £ion f bl« tha Political Resident, Bushire• Kf /? I a lr f / i have the honour in reply to your Ne 555a'tate that A bdul Aziz ^osaibi returned te Bahrain from Bombay in •'une last. Your letter under reply &amp; the attched (letters, give me the impression that thef£ has been some confusion in the names of the ^oaibi brothers. It was Abdulla ^osaibi who was temporarily acting in Bahrain as Bin gaud's Agent^whe was expelled &amp; who it was originally suggested should be allowed back on private affairs, As already pointedout in my JNe 84/ 0 of 27/6. When Abdul Aziz returned from India he advised his brother ^bdulla to give up the idea of returning te •^Rhrain,which he was only desirious of deing te give the impression that the 3ultan had compelled Government to cancel the order for his removal.The matter has been entirely dropped ^ i think is better left se.Meanwhile Abdul Aziz Q. is keeping very quiet &amp; trying to get over the bad impression made on us by his brother.Ea no longer constantly talks about being -^in maud's Agent &amp; does not interfere in affairs of iie^dl subjects as in the past. He acts as a post office for forwardir ing to me ^letters from the Sultan.Letters to the Sultan I forward by another route to the Amir of Ojdir *&gt; a s long es ^bdul ^ziz continues to act as a purely private Agent of the D Sultan here &amp; refrains from interference ,he cannot de much harm ® might t^ be al.lowed te continue as such^without further need to definitely define his status, ■^in ^aud has also ceased asking me to refer te hi* in matters concerning Najada in Bahrain,which wrs treating him as aConsul &amp; caused him to interftre in all raanntr of Blatters w^ich did not concern hiw. It is not however anlikely that he encourages malcontents among Al Khalifeh family to agitate against Shailc Hemad but it is probable that any other iiejd representative would de like- wis«.^9 is at present very friendly with lusuf X .anoo ,with whom,in the ppst he has been on bad terms.This is probably due te their mutual disgust at the reform of the customs which has put an end to a profitable arrangement they had with the late Director. With regard to para 2 of your letter under reply, I am of opinion that the number of Nevada who travel to India or Iraq other then /la iCawait .Bahrain or Muscat is quite negligible. A very fow mi^rht embark at Dubai &amp; th^y could get a Visa from the Residency ^p-ent at Shergah without difficulty. I have the honour tte be bir. Political Agent19/163 &amp; 19/165 • Proia D^ly , Bahrain. To RBsidfat, B'-whir®. No . 1^6. ISatal r^cetv^d ^Sth October 1925. 4- pyUO&amp;lTi . Your X*l*ssr&lt;m No. 9^7 • r^vad in Medjlias . Biuoii TSllev^d • e&lt;*id reforaa oo-ot^r- aticn(?) reforiiiB but that le opposed by intrigues of Sunni tribes and b^ga E.i4»(Jovt. to usaist hie by (i) removal from Bahrain of Ahmed J)o&amp;at±, Ainaed bin La he J and Abdul Wa^Ab Z^iyani wbo agitated ^nd persistently preaohed disobedience. (2) H-^-Oovt. to forbid tribal he^ds leaving Bahrain out of coatuiiiaoy and wsrn Qp.tar and Kuwait ana Bin ?aud not to har- bour th^iu • H^sbd gaid that (? ) puoh action would (j*»fin- itely suppress opposition to reforms » Requests due to refusal of tribal h^ads to obey Ham-ad's order to attend Med J liss t^nd Gtrr.r flagrant dl^obedieno* . Hews now :recrived that Ahmed Dosarl with following and family left for ^atif Coast to a place offered by Bin Pavd . Thia will inevitably involve Bahrain with Bin Saud . Their divers are ill &gt;ere and they will endeavoia tooje the Baiirain pearl bank, affording Bin Saud opportunity he has lon^, soh^med for. Bin Saud believed mtrigaing with tribes , offering terms h© will b^ak later to attract t^iem, and establish peaurl trade. We ehould h&amp;v® precedent with Bin Saui via. Sliammar refugees m Iraq whose return to him we have approved in principle. He forbids hi® subjects leafin nis territory with families. It seems unfriendly act to give asylum to Dosari without consulting Bahrain or ii.k.aovt. Agitator# mentioned are notorious. They nave collected lakh for agitation of wnich there are strong indications thai Abdul la gave Rs iC ,OCC/- . Agitation w a planned in kay (to) take plave after diving.•/V I am reporting urgently In oaee you snould wiah to refer to Oovernment of India to enable you to de«l with situation when you oome. pirn action to bring Sunnia to order seems essential preliminasy to main regormB and X reoommedd tliat requests of Hamad be acceded to if considered poaaible. Daly Telegram . P. From Resident, Busnire. To Political, Bahrain, i^o. 959- Dated 29th October 1923 • fM \ your 156. Am telegraphing India to ask whether if Hamad arrests parties mentioned Government will convey them to India and detain them there, also whether there is any objection to my writing to neighbouring rulers to request them not to 1 reoeiv# contumacious tribal heads• In regard to Ahmed Dosari can't Shaikh Hamad 1 seise his property and boats and detain them until he returns' 1 X don't think we had better mention Shammar. . Trevor♦19/163 &amp; 19/165. Telegram p.. Prom Resident, Bushire. To Foreign, Simla• No. 960. Dated 29th October 1923. PEicam. Bahrain retorma . PolltlOAl ^gent telegrapha that shaikh Hamad tells him that strong opposition to reforms is being made b/ Sunni tribes at instigation of Aimed ^osari , nhm d bin LaheJ and ^bdul Wahab Zayani who agi%ate persistently and preach disobedience. They also practiee it having refused to obey Shaikh's order to attend Majlis and committed other flagrant acts of disobedience. Sfhaikh Bamad i.rays that Ooveinment will assist him (1) by removing these three agit ators (2) by forbidding tribal heads from leaving Bahrain, out of contumacy and (3) by warning Bin Saud and Shaikhs of ^atar and Kuwait not to receive or to harbour such persons. 3naikh Hamad thinks such act in would definitely suppress opposition to relorms. political Agent reports three agitators ment ioned are notorious: they hav^ collected Hi one lakh for pur poses of agitation and resistance to reform^ of w.iich good grounds for believing Ahmed contributed 10,000/- . He thinks and 1 agree, that these men should be severely de It with. In regard to Shaikh's first request therefore, if ^haikh Hamad arrests these men would Oovarnment be pre pared to receive and detain them in India ? If eo will Government please telegraph infltructl ns urgently so that 1 can inform Shaikh Hamad who will certainly raise question dur ing my forthcoming visit to Bahrain on 1st November. In respect of (2) 1 might perhaps warn tribal Heads that Govern ment will view with disf vour any attempt on tntir part to leave Bahrain out of contumacy and that if they do they must take consequences and expect retaliatory measures from the ruler******* ■■■■I - ■ ■ 4/f/^3 y Ji oi/r Telegram r» From Hesident, Eusliire. To Colonial Office* Repeated to Foreign, Delhi, and Baglidad. lTo.994. Dated 9th Hovemfefer 1923. xRIORxxX. In the course of my visit to Bahrain last week I found good ground for suspecting Bin Baud of intrigue with local Sunni tribes with a view to getting thefc to migrate tib his territory (with success in the case of the Dowasir tribe, who have left Bahrain). I v/as about to recommend that if they saw no objection i-i.k.Govt. might remind Bin Saudthat although the subsidy had ceased, they still had means to bring pressure upon him by restricting supplies from India and Iraq., and would be compelled to apply them, if he- persists in disregard- -ing Article 6 of the treaty with the British Government In the circumstances., I beg to support Sir Henry Dobbs* recommendation that a categorical warning be given to ±iin oaud. The foregoing refers to Baghdad telegram do.596. TrevorNO. Sj y j \ y ^ BUSHIRt lH\ &gt;■• •• L &gt;{L* ' ■ - — — OONfiOmiA. HU'wfiOl Downing Street. /Jr /} ? January, 1924. r\ Sir, w I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your despatch No. 605S of the 28th of October,1923, regarding the representation of His Highness the Sultan of Nejd at Bahrain and in reply to inform you that, after consultation with the India Office, I concur in your proposal that the question of the return of Abdulla Qasaibi should be left in abeyance, and that Abdul Aziz should be permitted to remain in Bahrain in the capacity of a purely private agent of Ibn Saud. . * . I have the honour to be, Sir Your most obedient, humble servant. THE POLITICAL RESIDENT IN-THE PERSIAN GULF, •• BUSHIRE. 25 -C^cr-^vC&lt;3 u uji { X ^ ;■ I /, .5 / Ca V'.a in ,I CQWTIPPTIAI,. 7 4 U. blW I* fl to. S7/5/4 Of 1925 Political A*ency, -aahrein. Reg ; :. _ Tke 26th July 1925. i ■' flOENT! I RECORDS The Hon'hle the Polltleal Resident in the Perelan Uukf ( Bushlrc* Subject. - xi'-IZ aQSAiai. MemoranAme Reference your telefrwi »o. AAA dateA 16th July. After making a eareful translation of the aeeeaee eontalne^ therein. I forwariei it un«er a eoTering letter to Ihn Saui through Khan Bahadur Ab'ul Aziz r/ s i i, from who* I haTe obtained a reeeipt» 1 requeet a ruling: ae to whether I asi outhorieei to use Km B. Abdul Aals qoaaibi as i in Saufi' a agent for this purpose In the future* I woul« invite your attention to the eorrespond- -enee ending with Colonial Offiee despatch No. 3 dateJ llth January 1924 on the subject. In this despatch the position of Abdul Aalx in Bahrein is defined as that of a purely prirate agent of Bin Saud. S ot the last two years letters froa the Sultan hare been receired through him, while letters addressed to the Sultan by yourself or the Politiea Agent hare been forwarded by another route. In the recent matter of the Hindus at ^ati f, I was directed to negotiate with the Amir through Abdul Asiz. This was j as I YenturM to point out at the tiraej a new departure from the custom of the last two years* ^ In flew of your attitude in this matter^ deciile to forward the letter in question to Ibn Saud through At ul As^iz. But I am aware that there may be objections to my continuing to do this In the future. I11 I saanot see hownrtr that the mere faot of forvr .riin* letters to Bin 8au4 through the eane a«ent through whom letters are reeeire- from the Sultan foul4 ^ tantamount to eleratinj th« former alWTe hie present eipaeity as a purely prirate a «en , 1 hare not a sufficiently high ojinion of Abi/ul Aziz himself, or of the honesty of his motires to a^roeate any aiYanss in this ilirestion. 1 wouli merely point out the inoonvsnienoe of the -cruntlo*. an* is apt to he the oauss of some slight sstran.e- -ment between the Politisal Agent ani Ihn Sau*. j Captain, X«A Political Agent, Bahrsin.ii ■ COH ?ID !F1T 1' IAL . 11o» 26&amp;-S of 1925. Britxeh Residency tmd Consulate-General, Bushlre, let August 1925* To The Political A^ent, Balirain. Hejd Agent in Bahrain. t I MRMOKANDUM . Your confidential iQ&lt;anoianduza Ho. 67/5/4, dated the 26th July 192t&gt;.- The Hon 1 hie the Political fieeident considers that there appears to be no Reason at present why Khan Bahadur Abdul Aziz Qpsaibi should not be used as a post office. 2. As regards using AlWul Aziz's services for other purposes he proppses to defer a decision on that point until Colonel Prideaux returns, though he personally sees no harm in utilizing Abdul Aziz as long as the latter's attitude is good. 3. Have you any suggestions to offer as to any alternative person whom you could utilize in such matters as the case of the Hindus at Qatif ? By order, 1 c I 1 'A Capt•, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Schfiii. gOr7ID aiTT .L JTo. T.Z 0 s.s. Ohakdcra Dated bhe 22nl ITovem'ber 1927 WWgMIAUMOWB. The Secretary to the Hon'hie the Politic- 1 Heoident in the Persian Gulf, 5 U 3 H I R S. Sir, I have the honour to suh-.iit for the orders of the ^on'hle the lolitical Resident a tr .nsl tion of a coim;:unication addressed to Capt- in A1 -an 'by His Excellency Shaikh H- rn -id forw rdin^ s petition address -ed to him 'by certi'n Shi^ah inhabitants of Qatif, who claim to he Bahrain subjects. I append a note made 'by my assist nt Khan Sahit ^irza 'Ali giving such particul; rs is he was ihle to obtain about each of the petitioners. It will be seen frt the ajority are Bal.aran h ( origin- 1 Shiah inhabitant of the Bahrain islands ), who left Bahrain about 25 ye /s i.jo, owing to the tyr 71 .is s p.'actijed by Shaikh •Tsa \1 ir 1' r 1; ant lis rel .tion it that time latif vas under the aduiHistration of th t e Turks and there is little doubt that the lot of the Shi^hs was happier under tl eir rule ti ,n that of the unreformed Government of Bahrain. After the, conouest of Hasa and Qatif by Tbn Sa'ud, the petitioners remained there and they appear bo have enjoyed religious toleration until the early part of the present year. V a ^ Tn al:)0ut '-arch 1927 I first heard that the hi 1 ah/s(were 'being compelled to conform to W^haM ■ 1 rules s to pr Jing In mosr'fes 'behinda^iba'bi I , C This man Is evidently the ' hoy ' to whoii the petit -ioners allude in their application to Shaikh Harrd(2) Hamad. However desirous the petitioners may 'be, to reverse tVieir emigration of 25 3re rs ago 'by returning to ti,a rule or ohe now refor ed Govern lent of* 3 ^ in. thejr find themselves checked 'by the Najdian G-overnors, who do not desire to lose the industrious Baharanah traders and cultivators who add to the wealth of the territories und ?r their ch r^e^ I am given to underst nd that the procedure adopted is to tell the petitioners that they hnve full lihertj 7 ' to go to Bahrain, 'but that t! ey m? y ni}t take their Vvomen with them. Pressure also 'brought to hear through the property in Qatif which the petition -ers possess. The ruler of Bahrain is precluded hy treaty with H.r.Government from having direct relation with a foreign power such as the newly established state of Hijaz and Najd, and so he has correctly re. erred the petition for the orders of the Eon*ole the Political Resident. As the petitioners have heon so long resident in ~&gt;atif, and considering the circumstances in which they originally emigr ted I do not consider th; t they have any call on Shaikh Eaird's jrotection, even though some of them have ex^t up a connection with Bahrain either as traders or owners of property 'both in Bahrain and at Tarut or Cat if in ITaJd territory. ^y enquiries. |how that no difference of nationality is recognised between the subjects of the various Shaikhs of the Gulf areao A man transferring liis demicile from Duhai to Attl D, ahi l^or inst ace would have no further claim on the Shaikh of Duhai. I put a hypothetical c- se to Shaikh 3a•id hin Kaktum of Duhai md he said that ti e most he \ ould do1 (3) &gt; do, r ^ if a former subject • sked for his intervention, r.ould 'be to /rite a letter to the Shaikh of AJdU •&lt; Dhahi and ask him to do some thing to please the he? rt of such and such person, 'but he would not consider himself ras ^onsihle in any wr y nor would he expect a favourable reply. This ans&lt;|wer was in accordance wit! waht I had expected from my experience of the relations of Ara 'b rulers inter se. tul The Turks may have introduced nativity laws nd naturalisation into the territories under their immediate control, hut they are not indigenous to the ^ country, I expect that Hijaz Nationality Law of 22nd Hahi al-Awal 134.5, corresponding to 29th September 1926, will he found to he the first essay of a purely Arah administration in this direction. Hule 10 of th&amp;fc Law which presumably applj .es to ITaJd and its dependancoes reads ' ■ H 'Every resident of the Hijaz will he considered a Hijazi from the d te of publication of this law, unless he is in possession of valid official documents which prove his foreign natiotiali ^y •*. If it should be decided to bring the treatment of the Baharanah of 'atif and Tarut to the notice of His I'ajesty the king of Hijaz and JTaJd he would probably q_uote the above mentioned Poile to contest the right of His ITajesty 's Crovernment to interfere in the jnatter. The Shi'ahs in latif and Tarut have undoubted cruse for complaint, but T do think the Government of Bahrain can move in this matter officially. I propose if the Hon'ble the Resident agrees to bring ifegx^saxt this point of view to the notice of His Excellency Shaikh Hamad, who, I have no doubt will drop the question. 1 x&gt;. •7 r(4) S3 I have the honour to 'be Sir, Tour most ohedient servant ^ /^-cxxxjc A ^t * * *, Jor, Political Agent, Bahrain./ Tetition froin the Shi •ah community in Qatif Dated 2Cth ruharram 1346 addressed to H.I., Shaikh H'.nu d hin •Isa al-XIialifj h O .S .I,, Deputy Hule; of Bahr in After Coi'pli- ents. ¥ith due suhmisyion v/e most humhly take the liberty to suh] it this petition to Tour Excellency to state our complaint and trust tl ?t it will 'be favourably he rd. Te h ve ot no one else to t horn we c n st te our cornel int except Tour Excellency 'because you are (defen: edt and helped 'by God ) the refuse of the aggrived and the helper we have ^ot in this t'me. T7e are, as Tour Excellency kno ^s, ^ -ur subjects and have adopted this part of the world as our residence in order to he the medium of friendliness snd commerce and other similar relations that exist between ti e nations of the v/orld, 'I'Ut ti e GJ-overn' ent of T.T'.j •AMul 9 Azls bin v^a'ud ha9 t unfortunately u* brought a pressure to bear upon ^v /hich cannot be tolerated and persecute us in a manner unprecedent. Tt has oreered us to follow a boy in our pr yers • Itl .ugh it is an innovation in our religion. If F /e •./ere to enumerate what the Akhwans have done to us in otl er matters our petition ■m- .j;.i**V J. 1 'i '» sh- 11 become very lenghty: even if we want to leave the country they would not permit us to do so. T7e implore Tour Excellency to protect us against their evils nd to w; rd off their molestion as we he ve lost our religious freedom and we nigl.t lose our r:i ji.ts ;.nd property as well. T7e therefore depend upon Tour ^xcel 1 ency to help us in this clai ity nd to save us from this affliction. Hay G-od save you from your enemies and may he appoint you as one of the helpers of His apostle and His religion. This is what was necessary to st' te to Tour Excel! mcy may ysnNote 'by Khan 3abi'b !. r irza 'All. ITo. 1. Has a house in Bahrain and his relatives are Hajji Ahmad 'bin Khamis and Hajji Tusuf hin Rust am. He left Bahrain in 1903a: approximately He had gone to Catif owing to the oppressions of the ruling chiefs in Bahrain, NOo 2.He has a house in Bahrain. He vent to 'atif 20 or 22 years ago owing to the oppression of the ruling chiefs in Bahrrin hut was in the hahit of coming to Bahrain and remaining here from time to time before returning to Qatif. No. 3. Is the son of No. 2 and is 'born in atif,his ^e is 25/26 years* He was in the hahit of coming to Bahrain and rei - ining for some time before going 'back to Sinahis Oatif. No. 4. do. do. . territory with HisE coming to his 'bin FhaiDis his 1'uhai lad sons of Ahmad are ■ Iso his c rosins.He No. 5. He was horn in Sinahis Bahrain. He is the nephew of No.l. and has relations in Bahrain He now resides in Taroot Qatif district.His father was living in Bahrain until 1903 and went to Taroot with No .l. He kept up communication with Bahrain during the period his father st yed there. No. 6. He is the son of No.l. He is horn in Taroot Q,atif and is 21/22 years old. No. 27. He has got a house in Bahrain. He went to latiT on account of the encroachment of the ruling family in Bahrain,hut he iept cor j unicotion with Bahrain. He went to Najd his father some 25 years go. co ;] unlcation consists of his rel-tives such as TT ^,1i Vhm d cousin and Bashid an&lt; Ahmr d 'bin Hash id who st ,ys with them for sorie days ^ nd then goes hack to Taroot. No. 8.'His father Hajji Vbdullch hin Hahih is in Bahrain. He has got a house here and went to Qatif on account of the cruelty of t.ae ruling Shaikhs in Bahrain some 20 or 22 years ago. He is hoajn in Taroot Qatif and is 25/26 of age. He went to Q .atif on account of the oppression of the ruling family some 23 ye rs ago. His rel; tives such as his uncle n ied II ji A dull h hin Haji E/bih, are in Bahrain 0 Brother of tl e ahove. Fatr 3r of bhe preceding two,has got a house nd garden at Qatif. He spends Most f his time in Bahrain. He was 'born in Ba' rain and went to Qatif on y ^ account of the oppression of the ruling lamil in Bahrain some 23 or 25 years ago. He has got relatives in Bahrain and-owns 1 nded ^ro^erty in the Bahrain islands. No.13. Nephew of the ahove No. 14. Grrandson of T I Jji .hdullr h hin r .ahih is horn 'n Qatif • ndis 23/3' ye; rs No. 15. Brother of the ahove and is 'bout 27 No. 16. Born in Bahrain and v-ent to T &gt;Jd territory some ten years a^jo. His house is in Bahrain He went to Q- tif 'to do business a^d reaai ?ed ■j^ q ere. Brother of the ahove.He is horn in Bahr in nd h ut 25/26 ye? rs old. Born in Bahrain, went to .a'tiJ' some 20 years_ ago 'bee; use lew nted to 'better his conditior 'by commerce. No. 9. No.10. No.11. No.12. No.11.He old. years old No.17. No.18.!To.l9. Born in Bahrain feDd has got a bouse in Bahrain He went to Qatlf 25 years ago 'because of the oppression of the ruling chiefs in Bahrain. TTo .20. Son^of the ahove . He is horn in ^atif and is a 'bout 25/26 years old. Ho. 21. do. do. nd is ahout 23/24 years old. Ho.?.2. Nephew of No. 11. He is horn in Qatif and is 2O3 ahout 20 years old. Ho. 23. Son of NOcl9. Born in Bahr -.in and is 25 ys rs old. No. 24. T y7ent to ^atif 25 years a^o, on account of the oppression of the ruler of Bahrain.His reiati^ rel- tives live in Bahrain and he is in the hafeit of visiting Bahrain freuently. No.25. He has got house in Bahrain, v /here he \/as horn. He went to ^atif for trade. No.26. Son of the preceding arson. He is horn in Bahrain and is ahout 25/26 years old. No.27. Born in Bahrain, h s got a louse in Bahrain. Went to ^atif 'because of the oppression of 3h: ikh Abdullah hin Isa. No.28. Brother of the ahove. Born in Bahrain and is 26 ye- rs old. No. 29. Brother of the ahove. Born in Bahr- in ■ nd is 30/51 years old. No.30. ditto and is 22 years old. No.31. Born in Bahrain went to Qatif on account of the cruelty of the ruler of Bahrain 3 or 9 years ago. He has got house in Bahrain and keeps up coit unic tions with Bahr? in, which he visits frer uently. No.32. Born in Bahrain . Tent to Najd territory 8 or 9 years ago ov account of opp^ression of the ruling family in Bahrain, keeps up oommuntcai -ion with Bahrain. Has got a house in Bahrain. No.33. Brother of No.31. Born in Bahrain nd is 24/25 years old. No.34. Uncle of No.33. Born in Bahr in end is 39/40 years old 110.35.' Brother of ahove. Born in Bahrain and is36/37 ye rs old. No.36. Nephew of the &lt; hove. Born in Bahrain 'no. is 30/31 years old. No.37. Has got a house in Bahrain ; nd went to ^atif 12 years ■ go to tr de. He frequently visits Bahrain. No.33. Born in Bahrain here he h. s a louse . '.Tent to Najd territory because of the oppression of the rulers in Bahrain 24 ye; rs ago. Keeps up coi unication with Bahrain. TTas got a house in Bahrain. His father's house is also in Bahrain. Nephew of the above. He is supposed to have i&amp;s been born in Bahr in; his children are in 3 hr in. fd*- is 43 ye rs old. Born in Bahrain, has got his relarives in Sxkxa Bahrain ani ent to Najd territory with his father because of the oppression of the rulers in Bahrain. His rel tives are in Bal rain. He keeps up coin-tunication with Bahrain. Brotl er of the preceding person. He was born in Bahr in and is about 30/31 ye-rs old. Cousin of the hove, .ent to Qatif seven years ago for trade and to better his condition. Keeps up coi mini cat ion with Bahrain. His sons are in Bahrain and is 45 years old. Son of No.38. Born in Bahrain and is 26/27 years old. Son of No.11. Born in Qatif ?nd is about 20/21 years old. His house was plundered by Shaikh Abdullah bin Isa some 20 ye rs ago. He was born in Bahrain. No.39. No.40. No.41. No.42. No.43. No.44. No.45.'^e Ir s got a house in Bahrain. He keeps up GOimuni cation in Bahrain. Fo.46. Has got a house in Bahrain where he keeps a wife, keeps up oommunicatlon wltb, Bahrain. Went to IJaSir with No e 25 for trade. He went to Qatif 25 years ago 'because of the oppression of the rulers in Bahrain. Has f^ot relatives and a house in Bahrain* Keeps up coiui unic; tion vith Balirr in. No infor ation is • v.- il itile ahout him. Born in Bahrain, he is the nephew of lTo.16 He is 17/18/years oldC. Born in BahrainpEfcs father's house is in Bahrc. kepps up com. iunic tion with Bahrain.Brother of No.49. He is 30/31 ye? rs old. Brother of the ahove. do. is 35/36 years old Son of No.51. Born in Q, tif and is 0 ye' rs olc Uncle of the prec ding person.Born in Catif and is 20 years old. Son of No.25. Born in Bahrain and his con is in Bahrain. He is 40/41/ years old. Son of No.19. Born in T tif and is 25/26 years old® No.47. No. 48 No. 49 No. 50 No.51. No.52. No.53. No. 54. No o55. o19/163. flV It ia i think deoirable to keep thi subject on international lines, hence ay telegram below to Political, Agent, Bahrain, it is no good giying up a right which Bahrain poseesses internat ionally. L. H(aworth;. 20/1/28. Telegra* Code. Fron Political Resident, at Mohanuierah, To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. T -l. Dated 20th January 1928. Your T-2, dated JNoTe«ber 22nd. If no action taken keep matter pending. RESIDENT.Telegram Code From political, Bahrain To Keaident, i^uenire Words 5 jjo.tea the Zbth January i9ii8. Your T !• Action tajtcen i3th January. political. Telegram Code From Political, Busnire To Resident, G/0 Highcoma, Baghdad Ho. 78 Dated the id6th January ^9^6, Telegram dated E5th January from Bahrain begins XX, XXXXXX ends.CONFIDENTIAL. 1 IL ' r i ' No. 91- D . of 1928. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 218t February 1926 T* The ''olitical Agent, Bahrain. ^MORAMPUM . Peference correspondence ending with your telegram ?' 'No. 34, dated the 26th January 1928, regarding the grievances of the Hhi'ah inhabitants of Q.atif. The Hon'ble the Political Resident has decided to keep this question pending. In the event of his meeting Ibn r^aud the Political Pesident will mention the matter to him. By order, Capt., * for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.u 1 19/163. Extract iron letter TTo. 1407, dated 9th November 1929 from Political A^ent, Bahrain . x x x T would be glad to know to what extent it ir jopslbl to extend onr protection to Bahraina in Hasa. They, not unnaturally, are under the Impress ion that we are suppoeed to do so. X x ' x Extract from letter to the Political Agent, Bahrain, No. 274b, dated 30th November 1929 (from Secretary). / X XX Regarding the Shiah B&amp;harinah. Those doml« -ciled in Qatif or Hasa for generations are clearly Bin Saud's subjects. On the other hand there my be a few recognised Bahrain subjects, who do business or reside on the Hasa Coast and they are clearly entitled to our prot- -ection. ors i Telegram rrom To % To • 1679 Dated, c-nd received the 15th Decemher ^1929. 'Jole political Agent, Bahrein. Political Resident ^ratrick otev/art 4 * between 200 and 300 Bahama have fled from Qatif and taken refuge at 'aim and ^anahis leaving families 'behind. Cause 'believed to 'be imposition of war surtax. - POMTTCAL - i.e. ^ 5^ A * lUf'S.K IS 'iv /./f /irk-^ x_&lt;v ? ^' r /'x. lode Telegram Frorrr' '' Political Resident -Patrick Stewart^ To 'Foreign and Political Lept. New Delhi [Repeated Secretary of 3tate for Colonies, London. No.T.61 Dated 15th December 1929. Following from Political Agent at Bahrein of 15th December 'begins. Betv^een 200 ^ war surtax. .'jnu.G. Both places mentioned are on T'anama Island. - RESIDENT -cjX En Glair Political Agent, Bahrein Political Resident, 'Patrick Stewart 1 * Telegram From To No.1716 Dated and received ISth December 1529. 1° Num'ber of refugee Bahama now estimated at one thousand. Families left behind. - POLITICAL - y V-Y. f\ A A &gt;p. Politi -al Vgent, Bahrein• Political Resident, Patrick Stewart. Telegra Fl'Ql: T j No 141. Dated 21st DecemlDer 1929. 3ee my despatch of tomorrow♦s mail regr rding Bahama refuges. Deputation is coming tomorrow to ask for assistance in getting families and movable property releasee I propose to support genuine emigrants and asking Amir to release families and movable property if there are no claims against them. He will prohahly . l epl^ that Jihey owe war tax. Incidentally I hear that their homes have already 'been looted. Political. P- Political resident, Patrick Stewart, Political Agent, Bahrein. Telegram From To No T77. Dated 21st December 1929. 'an these Bahrarna still he regarded 'as Eahren subjects. ? If so I approve your suggestion. If their nat'ionali y is in doubt a non-committal reply would seem pref ;rable. i ■' Foregoing refer4s to your telegram No 141. .'Resident./Op of c ^ p No. 142 C. Confidential. The Agency, Bahrain. 21st December 1923. From The Political gent, Bahrain. To The Hon'ble the Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the question of Shiah refugees from (^atif, and to invite a reference to my prede cessors T .2 dated the 22nd November I927 ; and Captain Watts reply Mo. I6-S dated the 8th January 1927. My copy of this letter T 2 states in the concluding paragraph 1 but I do think the Government of Bahrain can move in this matter officially 1 whereas it ould appear from the rest of the letter that the contrary is meant, and evidently a 1 not 1 between theMo'and the 1 thinl^has been omitted. In his T I of the 20th January 1928 and his $I-S dated the 21st February the Resident appear ed to reconsider the instructions conveyed in Captain Watts above mentioned letter. « 1 2. As the matter did not appear to have been defin itely decided I raised the question, and in his letter 2745 dated the 30th November 1929 Major Fowle instructed me that * a few recognised Bahrain subjects who did, business or resided on the Hasa Coast were clearly entitled to our protection. I had intended to discuss the question with you at Bahrain, as I knew of the coming exodus from Q,atif, but in the press ure of work it escaped my memory. V 3. Yesterday morning ? I had gone to Sakhir to hawk with H.E.Shaikh Hamad, and when we halted for lunch he was surprised to see a deput-tinn P t-tion approaching us over Wf e sanc*- mmmmPag e 2. sandhills. They turned out to be a deputation from the re fugees) and their object was to ask Shailch Hamad lor assis tance. though he is not interested in their case since they are Shiahs, and fit objects for persecution, His Exceli lency told them that Bahrain and Hasa were just the same, and if they wished they could come and live here. They men tioned the property they had left behind, and he then said that they had better see me, and I undertook to hear them we next day. An amusing piece of comic relief was provided by the servants,who were only able to start on the remains of the lunch as the deputation approached, and whose anxiety to consume as much as possible before the deputation were invited to share it ; was most diverting to behold. 7 4. The instructions contained in your T 7:7: of to- 7 days date arrived in time, and the first two men who inter- viewed me were clearly Bahrain subjects, having been born in the Islands,and having only left it in the last eight years. I accordingly said that I would give them letters of good offices to the Amir. I asked them what they had to complain of, and they replied 1 Nothing yet, but that they feared gxs greatly. 1 One of them made a most illuminating remark. He stated that as he was known to be a Bahraini, he had not been molested, but that he wanted something to show in case they changed their tactics. This shows that our interference on behalf of, or protection of genuine Bahama, is expected, for nothing else would have persuaded the Amir's men to leave him alone. 5. Later Some twenty Shiahs came to see me, and of these only one could make any real claim to being a Bahrain subject. I asked them what they wanted, and they said f Help I asked how they could be helped, and they said that the British Government could not bear to see their sufferings unmoved, and must protect them. I showed them clearly that they had no claim on us, and they only replied that if we could not help them, it was better that they should commitPage 3. suicide. They said that those whom they had left behind were 'besieged in their villages by the tax col ectors who were demanding a far greater sum than they could possibly pay, and that they were subjected to every form of injustice. I again askrd how the British Government could help them against their ruler, and they merely repeated that we should go there and protect them, as we had protected people elsewhere. I told them th t I had no private army with which I could in vade the territory of a friendly power, and finally as they would not leave, I told them that I would represent their case to you, and that if you could help them you would. They then left. 6. I have never seen sa seen a body of men so dispi rited and dejected, and there is no doubt that they have reachr ed the limit of human endurance. They fully understand that ^cannot ^ whatever their n; tionality has been in the past, theyTclaim protection as Bahrna now, end they are simply awaiting some miracle to occur and save them. I do not icnow whether it is possible for any action to be taken on their behalf, and it is quite probable that any reference to Bin Saud might have the effect of making their lot even harder, fot it is *?***&amp; clear that the ordert for the collection of this war- tax has emanated from him and no one else. I would be glad to know whether it is possible to hold out any hope to these unfortunate people. 7. I cannot agree with the concluding paragraph of my predecessor's letter T 2 mentioned above, and it appears thri.t oir 1 one 1 Haworth afterwards withdrew his approval df the piop^sition outlined therein. The crux of the matter ' seems to me to be the test for Bahrain nationality. If a, per son can show a reasonable claim to recent Bahrain nationality, by birth, residence or other cogent reason, it srkjxix would appear impossible to deny them our protection. The inhabi- tants of these islands are becoming increasingly critical of(p2&gt;\ Page 4 our somewhat half hearted protection of their interests abroad, and ijfcxx the criterion of this protection, if our claim to protect Sahrkna is sincere, should be not the ex pedience in any particular instance, but the right that the individual has to it. It is clear from the conversation I mentioned in paragraph 4 that the authorities at ^atif are expecting that we shall support genuine Bahama, and with your approval I propose to continue doing so, confining aye such protection, however, to particular instances, and only then after careful scrutiny of theii credentials of the clai mants. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Politic^r^gent, Bahrain.^.7? 5 29 Zo/n/icj H,3. the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I h^ve the honour to suhrcit to Your Excellency thfct on the 1st November 192^ 1 hud submitted to His Honour the Political Agent, Bahrain, my peroohal cftse against the Government of ■ % atif. He must have referred it to Your iSxcellency and you must have viewed it as required by justice. As I am cure to get a result, it is sufficient for me only to make a hint about it here. I now invite your attention to the present state of affairs * in ^atif, al Hasa, and its dependencies, as it fully effects «• our personal and national interests, and it also warns the Government of Great Britain to whom the changes in the Gulf are more Important than the others. The Naui. Government has become extremely weak in those rslaces and she is in danger of breailng down. The inhabitants of the towns, specially those of Qptif, al H^sa, and al Jubail despise her for her cruelty, high handedness, and exorbitant taxes, -nd they wish to get rid of her by all means. They are looking for an opportunity to revolt and to turn out the Government. The l-iog d Government has no influence in those places. She is carrying cut administration as a matter of course. T^e hearts are still full of fear as her strength and her victories are widely published. In brief, both the parties, the Government and the inhabitants are full of fear and uneasiness. iind what has helped in the continuation of the present state is fear of people from the control of the AKHV7AU, and from their oppression if they took the place of the Government of Najdf as they are in doubt from the Government of Great Britain, whether in case of necessity she would protect them oX' not. Translation. ToJiQ a result, the key of the situation is in the hands of your high Government, and she alone can relieve those unfortunate people from the uncivilised iiedouin Crovernment 'by hoisting the fla^ of the British Government on those towns. I Circumstances from all sides are helpful to achieve this end. -AnYour Government do not wish to act openly, there are other reasonable ways that can 'be adopted so that the British policy may not 'be harmed. 'We have a notable centre there and can achieve this object very easily and without troubling the Government to us f^H help and to act openly, which nay be against her neutrality. The easiest way at present is that we should try to effect an understanding between the towns people and the Bedouin rebels and to make orders binding them together and by this way the towns people can,with the help of the rebels turn 1 out the Government. Then a legal way will be paved to hoist •iVitish flag over the towns. In the end, myself and all members of my family are ready to follow the line that you nay fix for them. ?ron your obedient friend, lojharnna d 3aeed XL J -Qiaah. 13th DecemberIHO No. fSoy of 1929. The Politic al Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 31st December 1929. BUSH I RE RS61DPNCY. Prom W rtltilotTIaL RECCflDS* i ^nim-iiri r- ■ - rnr. ii —- mi* Captain C.G.Prior, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire Sir, I have received the following petition from an T Alam of Qatif named Shaikh Muhammad Ali Al Jishi on behalf of certain inhabitants of Qatif. It is not certain what proportion of these can legitimately claim to be Bahrain subjects, but the proportion will be a small one. I propose to discuss the matter with you upon arrival. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your mast obedient servant, \jUL- p &lt;. ^ Politicji Agent, Bahrain. » ^ &gt;/' 6 Mo. 9 -3 of 1930. British Rciiiency anci CormuuLat^-General t Bushire, tth January 1930. From To Sir, fh« Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel H.V. Biscoe, Political ReaicLent in the Persian Gulf, The foreign Secretary to Uie OoTemiaent of India, \ New Delhi. ' I haT_e tJie honour to invite a reference to my r telegram no. T -61, dated the 16th December 1929, reporting that between 200 and 300 Bahama had fled from ..atif and taken refuge in Uanama laland belonging to Bahrain. The Political Agent subsequently informed me that the number of refugee Baharna had risen to about 1000 and that they had been compelled to leave their families behind. 2, On the 20th December Captain ^rior was out hawking with the Deputy Kuler of Bahrain when a deputation of these Bahama arrived to see Shaikh Hamad. His Ijtcellency was not disposed to be sympathetic to their grievances as they were Shiahs but he told them that Bahrain and Hasa were the same and they couid come to Bahrain, if they liked. They complained however that their ftoilies were being detained by the Hasa authorities and the Shaikh therefore referred them to the ?&gt;olitical Agent. Captain 'rior has now reports that he received a deputation the following day, but before doing so he had informed me by telegram that these persons were coming to see him, and I had warned him that only in case 0f persons of undisputed Bahrain nationality should he hold out any hopes of being able to asaist them. The Political A&amp;ent states that the first two rarn #iom he saw * were clearly Bahrain subjects, having been born in the Island and-having only left it in the last few years: they/'1 • 2 • they stated that being known to to Bahrainia they were not moleetedt whidri le of interest since it shows that our interference on belwlf of genuine Baharna is expected lay the ^tif authorities, otherwise they would certainly have made ao distinction between them and their own subjects. Of some twenty others who came to see the Political Agent only one could make * real claim to being a Halirainjaubject and in the caes of these three indiriduals the Political Agent has given them informal letters to the Amir of (^atif. The other members of the deputation^ while .being members of a community resident in Hasa and generally known as Bahama and probably of Bahrain origin« have been settled so long on the mainland that it seems difficult to re gard them as Bahrain subjects and Cai^tain Prior held out no hopes that the British authorities wou&amp;d intervene on their behalf. 5* The grievances of these individuals were that excessive taxes were being forcibly collected from them by the i^atif authorities and that they were subjected to every form of injustice. It would seem, however, to be the war sur~tax which is now being levied that has brought matters to a head and has induced them to seek refuge in Bahrain^ As, however, the Najd authorities have prevented them from removing their families, and as many of them own immoveable property it is clear that they are in no position to migrate• 4. As regards the general question of protection to such individuals, the ^litical Agent writes : 'If a person N can aliow a reasonable claim to recent Bahrain nationality 'by birth, residence or other strong grounds, it wouid 'appear impossible to deny thai our protection. The in habitants of these islands are becoming increasiagly 'critical of our somewhat half-hearted protection of their 'interests abroad, and the criterion of this protection V 'should/'should be not the expedience of any particular instance 'but the ri^it that the indiyidual has to it. It is clear 'from the conyersation mentioned above that the authorities 'at i-atif are expecting that we shall support genuine 'Bahama, and with your approval I propose to continue 'doing bo , sonfining such protection, however, to particular 'instances and only then after careful scrutiny of the 'credentials of the claimants'. I think this view is correct and that there is no objection to the Political Agents making representations informally to the Amir of (^atif, with whom he constantly communicates on minor matters of mutual interest, on behalf of individuals of undoubted Bahrain nationality, but that other so-called Bahama, who yc hajl long ago severed their connection with Bahrain, should be informed that they can no longer be treated as Bahrain subjects. 5* I am sending a copy of this letter to His Uajest^ Secretary of State for the Colonies. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. J/frr C-_ ' Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the 'ersian Gulf. ik It -i. Hfj lj ^ I $'■Britieh Hcsid&lt;»ncy arid ConeulKlt-renerul, Buohirc, 8th January 1930. No. 2/30- II h ; n Uy Lord, With reference to the correspondence ending Witt! By telegram No. '-61 of the Ibth December 1929. I haTe the honour to forwurft for the inlortutlion of Hio MujeBty'a (!o -*ernnient a copy of ny letter to tlie Govemiaent of India in the Toroign and Political Dcpartiwnt, Wo. 9-r&gt;e of even date. I have the honour to be. My Lord, Your Lord ship* b raoot obedient, huzable Bervant, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Tleaident In the J'erttian Culf k k- np The Right Honourable Lord asofield, '^.G., H.U'a. Secretary of State for the Coloniea, Colonial Office, LONDON.No. 18-S of 1930. British R«aidency and Consalate-Gencral Bushirc. 14th January 1930. 7^ ItV The Political Agent, Balirain. Menioran4uii . Baharna Refuge ea . I aia directed to say that the Hon'ble the Political Pesiaent agrees with tlie principles set forth in paragraph 7 of your letter Mo. 142-C, dated the 2i®t December 1929. diA for Secretary to the Political T :e»icent in the Persian Gulf.19/16?. J Telegram Corte # From Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ Political Hesident, at Ibn Saucl r F Camp No. 158. Dated 25th received ?,6th January 19^0. Result of ^ATIF trip very satisfactory submitting report. POLITICAL AGENT.-Pag e 2. &lt; question to me was to ask what I proposed to do aoout the matter, and the feeling that has been prevalent amongst the Bahama for some time that we were not fulfilling our duty of protecting their interests has increased. 5. I have an invitation from the Vmir of ^atif to visit him, and before taicing any other steps I propose to go over and see him, and see if it is possible to arrive at an amicable settlement. It is possible that we have not had the full facts, and it is also likely that they fear some general intervention on behalf of all the '^atifis. The Amir, I hear, has written direct to the King, and has urged some clemency towards the ^atifis whom he s'id have ' only their skeins left. 1 It appears that this general persecution has been set on foot by the Q,usaibis, who of course pay no Jihad, and who are rapid ly buying up all the landed property of the unfortunate refu gees for ridiculously low prices. 6. If thr facts are as stated, and the Amir gives me no satisfaction, it wi ^l be necessary to consider what steps are to be taken. It will be impossible to do nothing. We are expected to protect Bahama, and having made use of the Islands in every way thf&lt;t suits us, we cannot refuse to pay the price. We have deprived the State of the power of protecting itself, and since we allow Nejdis to fatten in Bahrain and enjoy a pri vileged position, we cannot refuse to take up the case of their opposites in ^atif. The political effect of tuese two instances, and the similar case that I have reported separate ly in C^atar has been deplorable. 7. Bahrain is in a very strong position if only it' is allowed to majce use of it. If the Nejd government contin- nue to molest Bahama we should in the first instance icrease the customs duty on cargo to 3,4 or 5 per cent, and ex plain the-t ve are doing this to provide for the sufferers at. their hands on the mainland. This would very soon bring them to their senses. If they imprison Bahama for no reason, we. Jt f Page 3. could threaten to imprison one or two leading Nejdis. If they levy war tax on Bahrain subjects, we should levy an-exactly similar amount in 'Bahrain to compensate them, and I thinic we should find that the trouble ceased almost at once. The Shaikh of Q,atar has shown that he was quite capable of protecting his 1 interests against the Persians, and. since we have d.eprived. Bah rain of a fren hand we must be prepared to face our obiig-xtions. 8. It may be thought that there is something unsuual in my giving a letter of good offices to a Bahrain! travelling to or living in Q,atif. It is quite a common thing, and is done far more frequently by the Nejd authorities that ourselves. Although he knows that he is not allowed to correspond direct on official matters, the Xing of Nejd has frequently addressed letters to Shaikh Hamad regarding Cc.ses in which his subjects were involved, and it is quite common for the Amir at ^atif to givp similar recommendatio-ns, so he cannot raise any objection at this stage to my doing so. 9. I hope to visit (^atif on the I9th January, if you see no objection, and may be away two days. I will submit a further report upon my return. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your mosVnpbedient servant. Foliti^Kl Agent, BahrainT / V ^ . !&gt; Honf identic 1.« No. 4 C. The -'gency, Bahrain. 15th January I9JC. From v To Captain C.G.Prior, I.A. Political Agent, Bahrain BUSH^ I FESIDEN r Y. Km. » 3 y^BfitTIAL ffiCOf.OS. The Hon f 'ble Lt.Col. H.V.Biscoe I.A. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. f. m Sir, I have the honour to state that on my return from Eushire, I found that the question of the protection of Bahar na at Q,atif had ta.zen an acute form. # 2. It will be remembered that I had given a letter of good offices to a certain genuine Bahraini, one Ahmed bin *bbns, who hr.d not been interfrere^ with, but who feared that he might be mo'ested. Directly I returned I wa.s told that when he gave the letter to the Amir, the latter had ordered him to be thrown into prison, saying T Let tne person who is sued the letter come and release you. 1 3. 'nother case has just occurred. One JAahsem bin H f ji Ibrahim, a Bahrani born in Manamah and resident here, went over to Q,atif on a Bahrain pass. He was forced to ta^e out a ,T ejd pass describing him as a Nejd subject, and he was also forced to pay a contribution of 60/- Rs as a contribu tion to the Jihad. He has no property in ^atif, but owns a mortgage over n house in which he iceeps an Iraqi wife. The ^atif authorities refuse to allow her to leave ^atif and re turn with her husband to Bahrain. 4. In each case we have only heard one side of the question, but there appears little doubt that the facts are s stated, 3nd the action of the Nejd authorities has roused the greatest resentment in Bahrain. H.E.Shaikh Hamad's firstIV&gt; The Agency, Bahrain. I8th January 1930. bushfpe residency. /to *1^, have not yet had a rieply fron tiic 'inirj regarding my proposed, visit. '.hen I heard from him oefore coming to Bushire he asked me to let him know a convenient day, and - as some time has now elapsed he is perhaps taxing permission again from Bin Saud. BeIp:rave has had several rumours tli ■t t^hy are refu sinp Bahama permission to go there, and that Q,us^ibi is issuing letters couched lilce pajizR passports to the few ..ho are admitted. Also an extra passenger tax on al 1 non- Q,usaibi launches. We have not had time to confirm any thing, and I will let you xcnow when we hear anything dp.fi- • /# nite. I think there is some trouble in the oiling, .hat |usaibi and a. few other Nejdi merchants^is to ^rive a.;.: the advantage they can from Bahrain and its good government and lace such difficulty in the way of Bahama traders that they cannot move out of Bahrain. This would 01 course oe intolerable. If only I can see the Amir I think I can settle everything, especially as his uncle is just asKing me for a chit to Isa bin^ Abdul Latif and the Shaikh of S%rgali to help him settle claims there. There are some other things I wanted to write about but there is no time.Copy of letter IIo.l209/9A dated the 14th Sha T 'ban, 1348, from the Adviser, Bahrain Government, Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. case of oppression I have to 'bring to JoBt^nQtice of lahrain suhject in iatifl^* jne .ehstftlun Uaj i vmSuyhorn in Hanamah and resident here, has heen trading between Bahrain and Qatif for many years. I e has a 1 ah rain pass which has 'been vised several times by the Customs authorities in Qatif. Three days ago he went over to Qatif, his pass was said to 09 invalid and he was compelled to take out a ^ejd pass describing him as a subject of ejd, he was also forced to pay Hs.60/- as a contribution to the -Jehad. Ee owns no property in 4atif but holds a mortgage over a house in which he keeps one of his wives, an Iraqi woman from Kathe/main. The authorities -in Qatif refuse to allow her to leave Jatif and return with her husband to Bahrain. I understand that the i'ejd Government have appointed one uyed ..akki bin 3yed Aliiwi, a BahraintShia, as Customs Officer, and this renegade Bahrani is the cause of much of the present trouble. The imprisonment and oppression of Bahrain subjects travelling between Bahrain and Qatif is causing very voilent feeling among the Bahama in Bahrain. Ko. of 1930. The Political Agency, Bahrain. - Dated the ^January 1930. The foregoing copy is forwarded to the Hon T ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire, for information. Jtywf 1/^ GH. rndian Assistant p or Political Agent, Bdirain. //vConfidential. Mo. 10 C. From ,. v j -31 The Agency, Bahrain. -26th January 1950- Bur: fa bu. /*v • 2^' 3° To Captain C.G.Prior I.A. Political Agent, Bahrain. The Kon'hle Lt.Col.H.T.Biscoe I.A. political Resident, lersian Gulf. V w Sir, I have the honour to say that after cohsider- ahle delay I received a reply from the Amir of Qatif saying that he w )uld he glad to see me as arranged, and that my letter had been delayed four days hy the launch that took it being starnded on a reef. 2. I arrived in the afternoon and was recei ved by tie brother of the Amir and Abdullah usaibi in the Amirs launch, the water being too shallow for my launch to approach the pier. The Amir met me at the door of his house and took me to my rooms. We talked for some time, but being unable to shtu.e off Abdullah Qusaibi I went for a drive to Dammam and Seihat. The former, far from being the ruin mention ed in the handbook of Arabia, contains some 500 mem bers of the Dowasir tribe, lately of Budaiyya in Bah rain, and Seihat is a large town of some 1500 inhabi tants, all Bahama hy origin. 5. I was unable to shake off the persistent Abdullah Cusaibi till the second day, and then dis cussed the question of the Persians who had been fired on while collecting stones at a reef near Dammam. TT e told me that he was still making investigations, and that if he discovere : who the cuplrits were, he would make an example of them. The ineffable Abdullahst u- saihi now interrupted us again, and J went xor a drive.0 ^ Page 2. to the nortehrn end of the Oasis. , r 4. The Amir seent the afternoon with me and 1 d'iscussed the question of the Bahama fully. I told him that the Kejdis in Bahrain had a privileged posi tion, and mentioned that we expected good treatment for all genuine Laharna in Qatif, and th^t we consider ed it our duty to see that they had it. I.mentioned a that we had to take up their case as far away as L'u- hamuerah. e said that they considered Bahrain and atif as one ( a remerk that one often hears, and s^one which Shaikh Hamad himself is fond of using ) and said that they gave even better treatment to Bahrana that to to Qatifis. 5. directly I mentioned the case of Ahmed bin Abbas he said that he had been imprisoned for smug gling and said that his goods were still in the gus- toms at Se^hat where he lived. When I mentioned that we had heard that he had tr|on up my letter, he appear ed genuinely horrified, and said that it would be im possible for him to do such a thing. I said that I had of course not believec it, and had merely mention ed it so that he might know what had been said. lie ap eared to mow nothing about the case of -ah- sem bin l aii Ibrahim, and said that he would make in quiries. He added that he Beared that illminded pe©- pie had being trying to create trouble and that he was very glad to have had the opportunity of discussing the matter with me. 6. He then asked me what 1 considered should be the rule regarding the liability of BahSana to Jihad. Tr hy should they escape if other persons who did not ren der military service had to pay. I said that apart from Customs dues to which all persons were liable, the usual practice was that travellers or persons visit -ing a country for a short time to do business did not■I flO 13^ Page 5. did not pay full taxes, but that if they bought houses and settled down, they would be liable just like the others. I quoted an instance of the pearl bjiyers who came to Bahrain for four months every year, and said that they would not have to pay. 7. Te appeared relieved at this and said that that was what his instructions were. He then asked me how long a man would have to stay in a place to be con- sidered domiciled in a ^iace, and I said that it was difficult to say in all cases and to lay down a defi nite rule, but that at least six motnhs in a year would usually be considered necessary. 8. e then asked me how they were to say who were Bahama and who were not. I explained that the Bah rain Government were only issuing passes to those who had been born in Bahrain, and were in no way interested in anyone else. I told him that on my return from Bushire, I had informed a deputation of Gatifls, with your authority, that they could espest nothing from us if their claim to be Bahama was not absolutely gen uine, and he ap eare' much relieved at this and question ed me about it. He si^ad that he had been oblitged to report to Bin Saud that the Bahrain Governments had welcomed the emigrants even without passports, and that they had taken arms with them, contrary to all laws. 1 said that it was not correct to say that they had been welcomed, and it was certainly incorrect to say that they had,arms, but that Shaikh Hamad s attitude was that Bahrain was 1 maituh. f open to all Arabs who chose to come there. 1 was about to mentiong that we had raised no objection when they had se sheltered the Dow- asir when they left Budaiyya, but did not do so in case he should imagine that we were now retaliating. 9&gt;-. '^'he possibility 7 suggested in my letter 4 C of the T^th January appears correct and we have appa rently received a very onesided account of the inci-jU a ge 4. ents, and - also think that the uncertainty of our attitude with regard to Qatifis in general has undoubt edly alarmed them. I think the Amir is now fully re- assured on this point, and he clearly realises that we may be expected to resent any injustice done to such persons as are undoubtedly Bahrain subjects. He cer tainly went out of his way to be friendly to me and we pactec on the best of terras. 1 personally have little ooubt that much of the trouble has been deliberately fpmented by the usaibisbas a T}art of their policy of excluding Bahrain merchants from the Qatif trade, and J shall watch their future move ents with attention. 1 have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political^Agent, Bahrain. Crj-K, vtwC lr JuM / Yfe^/wu'wai Ko. 48-b of i930. British Hesidcncy &amp; Coneulate-oeneral, iiuuhire the ■14 th jrebruaj'y 1950. -y £.\ From The Hon'ble Lt.-Colonel h.V. iJiBCoe, Political Kebident in the Persian Gulf, To The Foreign Secretary to the Governnent of India, kbw mmi. Sir, In continuation of my despatch iio.9-S of 8th January 1930, I have the honour to forward herewith for the infor mation of the Government of India a copy of a letter receiv ed from the Political Agent, Bahrein, regarding a visit he paid to the Amir of Katif and a discussion which took place there regarding the Bahama, 2. King Bin Saud also mentioned the subject of chese Bahama to me when I visited him recently, he stated tha^ they were quite useless as fighting men, and that as they would not fight they were being ta^ed in lieu. I told him that I had instructed the Political Agent, Bahrein, to in vestigate very carefully the cases of those who claimed to be Bahrein subjects, and only to give good offices in cases where there was no doubt about the individuals right to be considered a subject of the Bahrein State # and expreised a hope that instructions would be issued to ensure that genuine Bahrein subjects proceeding to iiejd territory would not be molested. Bin Saud was quite satisfied und in view of Captain trior's discussion with the Amir of iCatif I hopt that there will be no further difficulties aboutm 2 about these Bahama and a satisfactory modus vivendi established regarding Bahrein subjects who visit Wejd territory temporarily# I am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty's Secretary of Btate for the Colonies. Political Kesident in the ^ersian Gulf. I have the honour to be air, Your moot obedient servant Copy forwarded to the Political Agent at Bahrain for information. By Order Captain, for Secretary to the Political Kesiaent in the Persian Gulf. 14th February 1930.&amp; /Vtf British Hesidency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 14th February 1930. No. 4. 2# Lord, . A ' ^ - In continuation of my despatch No. 2, dated 3th January 1930, on the subject of Baharna refugees from Qatif, I have the honour to forward for the inform- -ation of His Majesty's Oovarnment a co^y of my letter to the aovernment of Inaia in the Foreign and Political Lepartment, No. 48-S, of even date. , T have the honour to 'be, lw Hy Lord, Your Lordship's most obedient, humble servant,^ v ^ 'C4-&lt;. Political Hesident in the rer&amp;l&amp;n Gulf. The Bight Honourable Lord Passfield, P.O., H^M's. Secretary of State lor the Colonies, Colonial Office, LONDON.No. C The Agency, Bahrain. Confidential. I5th March 1930. i »*: • • ur : . :-3IDF. From ! v ^ — (yf nn Captain C.G.Prior, I.A. To Political 'gent, Bahrain. The Hon f ble Lt.Col. H.V.Biscoe, I.A. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. 1% Sir, I have the honour to refer to my despatch No. 10 C. dated the 26th January 1930, and to submit a further report on the state of the Bahama at Q,atif. 2. It will be remembered that some ^atifie had taken refuge in Bahrain before the close of the year, and that many of them claimed Bahrain nationality. To some 143 of them the Bahrain Government gave nationality papers, after the closest investigation, and with the full authority of Shaikh Hamad. When Bin Saud approached Q.atif His Excellen cy became nervous and. told the Adviser that it would be bet ter not to issue any more while the King was in the vicinity and only four more were issued. 3. Shortly before Bin Saud embarked on the Pat rick Stewart, news reached Bahrain that a number of those who had returned to Q,atif with passes had been flogged and their passes taken from them, and that three men had been so brutal y beaten that they died. I did not take action at the time,since apart from one man who told Mr Belgr^ve that he had been at the floggings and had helped to bury onne of the victims, there was no confirmation of the nev/s, and the Shiah Q,adhi, who has many relatives on that side, did not bring any further p though he had claimec he could e' sily do so. Also, since we have no capitulations in Q,atif our intervention would have achieved little,though I had con-templated sug eating that Shaikh Abdullah and Khan Bahadur * Sayyid Sidriq Hassan might be sent over there to ascertain the facts, and it seemd to me ,that the sooner the Bahama in ^atif were able to come to terms with their Government the better it would be for them. 4. It is known that shortly after his return, Bin Saud sent )hai_vli rich to ^atii to look into matters, and some 13 of the Bahama were summoned to Hasa. They arrived -fter ^in 'au^ had left and were greeted with a letter telling them that if they had had a grievance they should have re ported it to him instead® of taking.shelter with foreign Governments and creating trouble. He al o left orders that they should each have bishts given them, and a relio^le man ■ i.om jj. .c 1 sent over to C^atif happened to see them as they came back with the Amir, and he said they seemedwell satis fied with the turn events had taken. 5. I how know that the attitude tov/ards the Bahama has definitely changed. I had written to the Amir of i^atif ie c ,c .ding -hmeo bin .-boas ( para 5 of my above mentioned letter ) and had received no reply. As the Bahrain Govern- c ■ 1 ' 1 ' or thereto oy the mank relatives, continued to ^ress me for some information regarding him, I sent a cppy of the er by a special messenger and received the following as- tonishing reply. ' l^rom Vbdur Rahman as Suwailim, ;unir of ^atif, dated the I3th Showal. a.c. In reply to Your Excel- lency 1 s letter No. oOv dated 21st Ramadan ( 20.2.30 ) fol lowed by the last No. 445 dated 10th Showal ( II.3.30 ) regarding the query about Ahmed bin Abbas al Barazi and his ' imprisonment. I regret to inform Y.E. that the man in ques tion i Q subject of my Lord the King whom Y.E. has no Eon- cern to ask about, and I have no authority to give you any information about him or anyone else of his kind. 1 ;.e. 6. Pe had just returned from s eing the King when - ..rote this letter, and he had no doubt sh ^wn him my firstPage 3. letter to Bin 3aud, who evidently worded this reply, since it is quite unlike the Amir's usualyfetyle. A second letter of friendly messages accompanied it explaining that he wa^s sorry he had not replied earlier but that he had been away, 7. Now th ,t this impasse has been reached, it would appear that the matter should be taken up with Bin Saud by the Residency. There is not the s ightest doubt that this man is a genuine Bahrain subject, and whatever mibtive there may be for imprisoning him there is no excuse for lying about his nationality. I discussed his case with the Amir, and it was never questioned for a moment that he was a Bahrain born Bahrain subject. Some action will have to be taken, for the case has attracted great attention, and even the al Khalifa Shaikhs who seldom interest themselves in the affairs of Shi^as, have spoken warmly about the injus tice done to this man. 's regards the question of the floggings, I do not consider that we can move usefully in sand^ the matter, since what has been done has been doneV'funless. the matter is raised again in an acute form it may be allow ed to drop. The ^Tejd auhtorities have their reply already prepared, rnd that is that the men were flogged for having taken away to Bahrain arms that were given them to protect them from the Manasir and other tribes some six months ago, and it would be difficult to disprove it. 8. Rumour here states that the passes issued have been collected and sent to London with Hafiz Wahba together with a complaitjn that though the British Government have v encouraged a rapprochement between the ^Tejd and Iraq Govern ments their representatives here have endeavoured to stir up trouble amongst the B^arna at Q,atif. The Political Resident is said to be in bad odour with the monarch for causes unknown: The Political Agent for requesting him to limit the number of his followers on the Patrice Stew art, and the Political Agent, Kuwait, for telling the13? /3 8 Page 4. Shaikh of Kuwait that he should not go and see Bin Baud, an unwarranted interference between two Arab rulers I 9. There is some evidence to show that Bin Saud asked Shaikh Hamad some question about the passes on his way through Bahrain, and Shaikh Kamad denied all knowledge of any having bnen given. The King is said to have been very angry on hearing this. I am seeing Shaikh Hamad at a truffle hunt tomorrow, and while informing him of the AmirS reply, I sh',11 raise the question of the passes and see what he has to say about it. I am expecting some reliable information from C^atif in three or four days regarding the flogging incident, and if it is forthcoming will forward it by next mail together with anything of interest that H-E Shaikh Eamad may have to say. 10. I should be glac to know what reply I should make to the Bahrain Government when they again refer to the case Imad bin 'bbas al 'narazi. In the meantime they are being informed of th• substance of the Amir f s reply, to which they will undoubtedly reply that he is mistaken in his facts. I have ohe honour tobe. Sir, Your most ptr^dient servant. Poli ^ent, Bahrain■ 'f i Letter No. 19-C., dated the : Ibth March 1930. i&amp; 1 ■ British Hesiciency and Coneulate-Oeneral, Bus hi re, Uie 24th idarch 1930. 8i ^ V/ith reference to my despatch ao. 4 of the 14th February 1950 on the subject of Bahama refugees from c^atif, I have the honour to forward for the informa tion of liis liajesty f s Government a copy of a further conmunication cited in the margin from the Political Agent at Bahrain on the subject noted above. 2. It will be seen from Captain Dior's report that the Amir of tyitif, who I was formerly inclined to adopt a reasonable attitude | in this matter, appears now, as a result of Bin Saud's visit to hasa and apparently on instructions from him or his advisers, to be taking up a different ine and is refusing to acknowledge as Baiirain subjects even those persons whose nationality is undisputed. _ As regards the position of these Bahama, as His Majesty^ Government are aware 1 have all along held the view that our protection should only be extended to persons who are of undisputed Bahrain nationality, HIP MAJESTY* 3 SECRETARY 0* 1 8TA3'E K&gt;R THF COLOHIKS, COLONIAL OFFICE, LONDON.nationality, and Captain Prior lias acted accordingly. The question is not a new one. In 1927 certain Bahama submit te&lt;^i)e tit ion asking to be allowed to return to Bahrain from atif, and Colonel Barrett, the then Political Agent, in reporting to the j^olitical Hesident wrote as follows: 'The ruler of Bahrain is precluded by treaty with His Majesty's uoTerniient from having direct relations with a foreign power such as the newly established state of Hijaa and iiejd, and so he has correctly referred the petition for the orders of the Hon 'ble the Political Kesident. 'As the petitioners have been so long resident in ^atif, ajrid considering the cir cuius tan eel in which they originally emigrated i do not con sider that they have any call on Shaikh Hamad's protection, even though some of them have icept up a connection with Bahrain either as traders or owners of property both in Bahrain and at Tarut or (;.ati^ in Kejd territory. 'Uy enquiries show that no difference of nationalfttir is recognised between the subjects of the various Shaikhs of the Gulf area. A man transferring his domicile from Dubai to Abu Dhabi for instance would have no further claim on the Shaikh of Dubai. H 1 put a hypothetical case to Shaikh Sa'id bin Maktum of Dubai and he said thaithe most he ' would do, if a former subject asked for his incer* vent ion, would be to write a letter to the Shaikh •f Abu Dhabi and ask him to do something Ho please the heart* of such and such person, bat he would not consider himself responsible in any way nor would he expect a favourable reply. •Uhis(oax. hi • 3 - 'ThiB answer was in accordance with what I had expected from my experience of the rela tions of Arab rulers inter se. 'The Turks may have introduced national laws and naturalisation into the territories under their immediate control, but they are not indigenous to the country. I expect that Hijaz Nationality Law of 22nd Hahi al -Awal 1«54&amp; # corresponding to 29th September 1926, will be found to be the first essay of a purely Arab administration in this direction. ••Rule 10 of this Law which presumably applies to Mejd and its dependencies reads: '•Every resident of the Mijaa will be considered a Hijazi from the date of publication of this law/ unless he is in possession of valid official documents which prove his foreign nationality''* ' 1 •If it should be decided to bring the treat- j ment of the Bahama of Qatif and larut to tne notice of His Majesty the lULng of^Hijaz and Kcjd he would probably quote the above-mentioned rule to contest the right of hie Majesty's Government to interfere in the matter.' 4. The provisions of this law hotiever seem to me to be exceedingly arbitrary and, if enacted in Persia, would certainly have evoked protests from all foreign governments. There are many Indians who arrived in Persia when the Anglo-.t'ersian Oil Company commenced operations and have resided in this country ever since, but have lost their certificates of identity* These individuals are now taking out pass ports, and every government is of course entitled to insist that foreigners resident within its territories 'territories uhall be inposseBBion of valid documents of nationality, but it ia not, I submit, open to any government suddenly to promulgate a law to the effect that any one who at the time of the publica tion of the Iwlh is not in posBession of valid docu* ments automatically becomes a subject of the state in which he is resident. Reasonable notice must be given to foreigners to provide themselves with the requisite docwments and especially so in a country poesessing such primitive administrative arrange- ments as ftejd. 5. Further# as stated in my despatch ho. 48-b, dated the 14th .February 1930, to the Government of India, of which a copy was forwarded to Your Lord ship under cover of my despatch Ho. 4 of the same date. Bin Saud mentioned the matter of these Bahama to me when we met, and appeared quite satisfied with my explanation that 1 had no intention to intervene on behalf of so-called .tfahama in general, who had bee: settled in Hasa for a long time, but only on behalf of persons of undisputed Uaurain nationality. I feel loath to believe therefore that if the case of these individuals is brought to his notice again he will not issue suitable instructions to the Amir of i^atif. 6. I would therefore suggest, if HiB Majesty's Government see no objection, that his Jaajeaty's y SUfUA^ Charge d'Affaires at Jeddah ^ be instructed to bring the facta to the notice of the hejd Govermaent with a view to ensuring good treatment by the hasa authorities to Bahrain subjects holding certificates of identity issued by the Baiirain Government and the recognition of these certificates. 7. If this proposal is approved X would sug gest that the Hejd Govern!lent Bhould be informed that in;vW&amp; 11^ - 5 - in December last a number of person® locally known as liahama and claiming Maiirain nationality proceeded from qatif to Bahrain alleging oppression at the iianda of the Hejd authorities. Before proceeding to investigate their alleged grievances the Political Agent at Bahrain, under instructions from the Political Hesident, called on them to substalitiate their claim to Bahrain nationality. It was iound that in the large majority of cases these individuals had been settled in Masa for considerable periods and had, to all intents and purposes, oevered their connection with Bahrain, and they were informed that they could no longer be regarded as Bahrain subjects. A limited number however were Ondieputably Bahrain subjects by bi^tli and had maintained their connection with Bahrain and ftad only proceeded to Hasa recently or for temporary purposes and they were accordingly i^iven sertificates of identity as Bahrain subjects. His Majesty King Bin Saud mentioned the matter to the | Political Kesident at their meeting in January and the latter informed His Majesty that certificates would only be issued after full investigation and to persons of (indisputable Baxirain nationality, and iiie Majesty seemed quite satisfied with tlULs reply. The Political A^ent at Ba irain has however now reports ed that a certificate of identity was issued to one Ahmed bin Abbas Darazi who was of Undisputable Bahrain nationality but this certificate lias been taken from him and he has been imprisoned. on making a reference to the Amir of the Political Agent has received a reply to the effect that Ahmed bin Abbas is a Nejd subject and that the Amir has no authority to give him any information about him» Itorthcr, reports have reached the Political At&gt;:ent that other persons to whom passes were given have had/U V had their passes taken from them. In vievf of the fact that these certificates of identity are only issued to persons of undisputable Baiirain nationality after full investigation. His Majesty's (jovemment trust that instructions will be issued to the officials of the JNejd Government that they should he respected and if any have been token away from the holders they should be at once restored to them. 8. A copy of this despatch is being forwarded to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department and to His ttajesty^ Charge d , Affaires at Jeddah. I have the honour to be, 3 * Sir, J- Cf- J- ^ „ . - Your most obeaient, humble servant. Q ' lit# •col., Political Kesident in Uie Persian Gulf.CONglDENTIilL, -v NO 2L&gt;-C ■A » The Agency, Balirain 23rA March 1930o Fr«in Captain C, G« Priox^, loAo» Ptlitical Agent, Bahrain, .. -?• at • T» The Hen'ble Lt-Celenel H, V. Biscee, I.A®, Pelitical Kebident, Persian Gull'. Sir, In continuation of ^letter ef the 15th torch 1930, number 19 C, I have the honour to confirm that, tuc leadere have come to aomc agreement with Bin Saud or have received such promisuo as to satisfy then for the time being. My informant, whose information can be relied upon, Betid that though floggings had no doubt taken place, there was nothing to show that any one had been killed by them. Two ef the refugees who received the severest beatings were aaid to be persons who had been in the receipt of salaries irom the Nejd Government, and the feeling was that these tv.o, at any rate, had only got v/hat they might have expected• In tixe circumstances it will be host, I consider, to allow the matter to rest, both in our interests and those of the Bahama, 2. The matter of Ahmed bin Abbao is en a diiieient footing. The Shaikh is constantly being pressed by the man's relations to take action on his behalf^and His Excellency in conversation told ne that he i eu it oux dutj to move in the matter. I request that I may be informed what reply I should make. 3. His Excellency Shaikh Hamad told me that Bin SaudSaud did net raise the question nf tlie passes with hin, but I am net altegether certain that he was speaking the tx^uth. I have the heneur te be. Sir, Your most oJiM|dient servant, A ^ u Political iigent, Bahrain CpAfBritish Residency and ConBulate-Qeneral, B ub hire, SXst March 1930. Mo. 12. 7^ i, :S l '23rd*iiarch 1930. Sir, *'1 In continuation of my despatch Mo. 10, dated the 24th March 1930 c regarding the treatment of Buhrain subjects by the Mejd authorities, 1 have the honour to forward herewith copy of a further despatch received from the J^litical Agent at Bahrain on the subject. 2* It will be seen that Captain jprior reports that the question of these so-called Bahama in , general appears to have been solved in a satisfactory fashion and some arrangement has been come to between them and the Bejd authorities. The general question % however of the recognition by the iiejd author!tiee of certificates of identity issued by the Bahrain Govern ment and the particular case of Ahmed bin Abbas still remain unsettled, and I see no reason therefore to modify the suggestions contained in my despatch referred to above. 3* Copies of this despatch and of its enclosure / / are being forwarded to the foreign Secretary to the K Government of India and Mis esty v s Chares'^ d v Affaires at Jeddah. ^ s, y Z 7 / /l+if-S. 1 th « honour to be. of ' J f * 3 • A' Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. Ifjc Lt.-Colonel, JPolitical Resident in the i/eroian Gulf. HIE MAJKSTYfcS SFCRBffARY 07 STATE FOR THE C0L0HIE3? COLONIAL OFFICE, LOUDOj*. 0&lt;^a3 roEDTQ/S*^-^-1 11 'WW- |1f I'.' &gt;-lPpi «i 19/lCrt. Telegram Code. Political Aeent # To Rewiclfent., 'Patrick Stewart', i\o. 776, jjated 8th received 9th May 1930. Your letter ? iT o. 10 of ?&gt;4th inarch, paragraph 7, and your letter No. 12 of 31i&gt;t. March to Secretary of State for the Colonies. Ahmed bin Abbas has been released but obliged to give undertaking to remain in ^atif for the next three months. His relatives hp.ve expressed gratitude at the action of H.M^ s. Government, POUT 10AI AGENT Telegram Code, From Political Resident, 'Patrick Stewart'. To Secretary of State for Colonies, London. Repeated H.M.'s. Charge d*Affaires, Jeddah. No. T-84. Dated 9th May 1950, / r My despatch No. 12 of 31st March. Ahmad bin Abbas has been H.-^s. Government. RESIDENT.Please telegraph whether you concur in action recommended in paragraphs 6 and 7 BISGOE's despatch 10 of Larch 24th to Colonial Office-copy to you direct Colonial Office are favourable.162o. Telegram R. No.1625-3, dated 21st Iv'ay 1930. From Viceroy, F. &amp; P. Department, Simla. secretary of State for India, London, Your telegram of 16th May, Ko.1606. &gt;-e concur.•'oreign Office, 14th la/, 1930. l5i(- ;7ith refere-ice to lujr despatch No.76 of the 25th March last, I transmit to you the accoinpanying copv of a letter fro.ii the Colonial oi 1 ics regarding the refusal of the ^lejdi authorities in Catif to recognise as iahreinis certain persons holding certificates of identity as Bahreini subjects issued by the Governinent of Bahrein. Copies of the despatches from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf of the 24th and ^Ist r,arch referred to in the Colonial Office letter have been sent to /ou direct. 2. The Bahrein! subjects in question are entitled to British detection while in Nejd, unless the./ are at the same time Nejdi nationals under Nejdi law. If therefore you see no objection on this or other grounds, I shall be glad if you will ta ^e up the matter with the Ilejazi iroverniueiit, as suggested by the Colonial Office, on the lines proposed in paragraphs 6 and 7 ^ Lieutenant-Colonel 3iscoe T s despatch of the 24th March. j I SL-ii j t C • ^ (3d.) .ONT AGLE (?or the Secretary of State) Sir Andrew Ryan, ^.3.^. ,C.i. .G., etc., etc., etc. , Jedda,n ft IBS aoffiFijJiiiiTi.a.. Ho. ?. 464-1-1/29. K m rv A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the .ion ''ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, in the continuation of the Government of India /Si endorsement No. F.464 -17 /29, dated the 23rd lay 1930. 2. The papers are forwarded for information only and no official action should be taken on the:.. (•Ml By order, etc.. for Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, fa Foreign and Political Department, Simla; ^ . tc The June 1930. ; Letter from the Colonial Office to the India Office, No. 79005/30, date! the 2nd I ay 1930. Letter from the India Office to the Colonial Office, No. 2759, dated the 27th I r ay 1930. Letter from Colonial Office to India Office, No. j) 79005/30, dated the 23rd I ay 1930. tvi'i th Ji spare copy ) ^ &lt;****' f L /K*. 3'7 ^-7-2ni Hay 19 30, Sir, With reference to your letter Ho. P. 1330 of the 19th llarch regarding the treatment of the ISaharna refugees from ^atif in Bahrein, I am directed 'by Lord 24th larch Paasfield to transmit to you, for such observations as 51st Harch |\^&gt; Mr* Secretary Benn may have to offer, copies of two despatches on this subject from the Resident in the Persian Gulf. 2. Subject to the vi^ws of Mr. Benn, Lord Passfield is inclined, for ^is part, to agree with the course of action proposed by the Resident in paragraph 6 and 7 of his despatch of the 24th llarch. 3. A similar letter is being addressed to the Foreign Office. X am, etc., Sd/- J. H. iirtLL. THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, INDIA OFFICE. w\S1 P.2759/30. w 1 /s IHDIA OJFICK; ♦ WHITEHALL, L01TD01T f S. W. 1. 27th Hay 1930. Sir, '/I I an directed 'by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of the 2nd 1 ay. Ho.79005/ 30, on the subject of the treatment of Bahrain subjects in Q^itif. After consultation with the Government of India T.Tr . Benn agrees with the proposal of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf that representations should be made to the Hejd Government by His Majesty t s Representative at Jeddah on the lines suggested in paragraph 6 and 7 of the Residents despatch of the 24th March. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office. X am, etc., Sd/- J. G. Walton. THE UNDER SECRETARY OP STATE, OOLOHIAL 05TICE.THE 23 nay 19 30 / j\ Si-i' &gt; , ] With'reference to the letter from this Department of the 2nd regarding the treatment in Bahrein of the Bahama refugees from !^atif» I am directed by Lord Ists r Passfield to transmit to you, to laid before lir# Secretary Benn, a copy of a telegram from the Resident in the Persian Gulf relative to the particular case of Ahmed 'bin Abbas. % 2, Although this man has now been released, there still remains the general question of the recognition by the Nejd authorities of certificates of identity issued by the Bahrein Government. 3. A similar letter is being addressed to the Foreign Office. I am, etc•, Sd/- 0. G. R. Williams. UNDER SECRETARY 0? STATE, I ED®A OFFICE.CONFIDENTIAL. ! fL i |a[ b &gt; No.2( c of 1930. Political .agency, Bahrain. The 26th October 1930. —T— ' T NC S ' 0 - ^ From To \\ V 10^ t Captain G.G. Prior, I. A., ' r Political Agent, Bahrain. The Hon T ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to bring to your notice instanc es of the continued aggression of the King of the Hedjaz anc. his agents the Qusaibis, an aggression, if not checked, will have a serious effect on our position in Bahrain. It wixl be remembered that during the summer Bi oaluwi, the Amir of Hasa had written to Shaikh Hamaa ( and to me ) in a somewhat peremptory fashion demanding the surrend r of certain persons^he consid^reu to be of Nejd nationality and he also sent men tj fetc^ them , an act whi^/c was much resented b/ the Ruling family. Actually the Shaikh refused to admit that they were other than ih* Bahrain sub jects, in fact they were Dowasir who have liijed here for many years though not without trading connections on the mainland, ana the men were not returned. I took advantage of the opportunity to/ point out td) Bin Jiluwi that Bin Saud had himself requestea that the practice of surreniring persons shoula cease, i .nd that it was at his request that we haa ceased asking mainland Amirs to send men to Bahrain. 3* While I was in Karachi a theft occurred on a dhow in Bahrain Harbour and both the accused ana the Nakhuda were liasawis. Apparently considering a conviction unlikely the Nakhuda went to Hasa and informed Bin Jiluwi of the occurrence, and he immediately wrote to Shaikh Hamad telling hiid to have uhe men sent to Hasa lor trial. The case w; referr^a/(' Itf) referred to me and I gave instructions that the men were on % ^IX. no account to sent to Hasa b*rb hut that tne}- ^ere dealt with according to law at Bahrain* 4. On my return here I find that when a promi nent merchant, Mohammad Yateem, recently ran ovei a Nejdi in his car he was at once summonea hy the Qusaihis wxio seve? c. ly reprimanded him for having injured a subject ox II . I e . King Ibn Saud. He was later prosecuted by the Police, out their action caused much comment. 5. Again a few days before I arrive.d, as a result of a squabble at a well, some servants of the Qusaibis at Eafaa armed with rifles assaulted a servant of Shaikh Rashid, the son of the Ruler t s brother Shaikn Muhammad, and tying him up with a rope, took him to the Q,usaiuis f house and confined him there* The Rifaa Arabs took this as an insult to the Al Khalifa and a riot nearly ensued, but the Imam oi mosque managed to calm them, and when A dquj. A ^iz ^usaioi cam*- to the house at night the man was released^ 6. As a result of tow* pressure by Shaikh Muhammad, Shaikh Hamad ordered the heir-apparent to go and tell the Qusaibis that they must apologise and he conveyea a message to this effect to Hassan Qusaibi. No notice, however was taken of this, ana finally Shaikh Sashid and Shaikh Muhammad had the Police set in motion and a case registered. The case was brought up before me^out at cue ±as^ moment. Shaikh Rashid came and said that the 4 usa i D i s ^ iaa ueeii see the Ruler, and that he had asked Shaikh Muhammad to get his son to stop the case proceeding. He himself, he said, would not on any account have allowed them to escape scot frue, ou- he was unable to stand against the expressed wish of the Ruler. I therefore allowed the case to ue compromiseu, arid the matter was settled. 7./A r- ?• I did not aadress the Qusaibis or take an/ action against them in any instance although their action in 'both the two last mentioned cases was intolerable. Had I called t them to account^they would have said in the first instance that the man was a friend or a servant of theirs and that they intervened in a friendly spirit, and in the secona^that the./ had no knowledge of what had happeneaed ana nad hasten ed to release the man when they aiscoverec what had been done. 1 do not wish to quarrel with them unless they give me an unmistakeable Belli, but if I see xfurther signs of their interference I shall take the matter up* 8 The last instance is much more serious and affects the King himself. When I arrived 1 found that he had recently sent Shaikh Hamad two letters,. One was com- plimetary and signed and the other which was attacuea to it and was in the same hand-writing was not signed and, as you will see most objectionable in tone, i have careful-iy checked the translation and it gives an accurate interpre tation of the original. The Ruler had not replied to it -pm pending my return, ana when I got an opportunity to dis cuss it with him ; in the presence of Shaikh Abdullah and heir-apparent Shaikh Salman, I could clearly see that they were much incensed hy it. 9. ' What does he mean by saying that his people pay heavy taxes ' he said ! * they pay nothing but the C )&lt;? customs which our people pay, and they are fax' more heavily taxed in their own country. Nor have I ever heara of any oi them complain of ill treatment. In iact they lieu from oppre ssion in their own country and come here for justice which they cannot get from him. Let them return to Hasa if they prefer it ' . He then referred to the thinly veil/ed reference to the re-export concession, ana saia, as he iias done before, but this time in far more definite language, the- former reduction from 5 Jo to 2 ^ had been forced on them and that this concession made Bin oaud greedy to pay notiiing at all. tT Let him use another port if he cannot pay 2 ^ for ourI 1 ■ I 4^ for our expenses here ' he said. 10. I raised the ^uestinjof a reply, and suggested that he should await your arrival before sending it. This he was loath to do, as he said the letter had been some time awaiting a rreply ana to aelay further would suggest that he could not or would not meet the charges contained in it. It was therefore decided that he should reply in similar style^ a complimentary letter dated and signed , ani an unsealed attachment which should ask in the same abrupt language as the King had used / what exactly he referred to when he spoke of heavy taxation and ill treat ment of his subjects. 11. This has been done and I have just received his letter anc enclose a copy of it. In its way ; it is an excellent reply ana will have the support of a^l his broohers. Technically the reply should have been^through Bushire, but, in the circimistances^ it^seemed best to follow the mode employed., especially as the King had ^imseli oho-' chosen it. I should add that the references to the persons ' who would protect his interests M mentioned in the King 1 * letter, are assumed by the Shaikh to refer to H.M.&amp;overnment. He laughed when he read this and said ' Well they are my friends too, I have nothing to fear from the High Government. ' 12» I have dealt with the matter in some haste, but it seemed important that I should place you in possession of the facts as soon as possible, in view of your impena- ing departure from Bushire. . I venture to hope that the VUmmau action taken by His Excellency will meet with your approval and I regret that the labour involved pre cluded a telegraphic reference to you. I hav« the honour to be, I Your/tfcT^t obedient servant. Political Agent, Bahrain.i bx n In the name of God the Merciful. Postscript to letter Mo.IS dated 3rd Jamad al Auwal 1349C i.e.26th September 1930. May you live long, Since a long time our subjects have been complain ing about the treatment they receive in Bahrain and extra duties they are charged and also there was a question about fa nationality. The Qatif people who ha&amp;l 'been living in Qatif for over fifty, sixty and hundered years ago claimed to be Bahrain subjects. We could see no reason for this except the object of creating trouble. Your Highness, may you live lon^ y knows that we never neglected our claims over many things, but we did not wish to create y^trouble betv/een us and * » « Bahrain on any subject and our desire that the interests or A both be the same(safe guarded) and that our subjects should be at peace. But the peace jfcpi our subjects could not be had We therefore thought to send Your Highness this(letter) so n that you may think over this matter and consider the questio of our subjects and the duties taken from them^as also on the goods that come to Bahrain and the affairs of our subjects. Should Your Highness desire an agreement of these matters v/e are ready,'toiienever you ask, to send, you our representative to discuss with you the matters which are beneficial to all, so that we and our suojec^s Know the way we should follow. We are afraid you v/Q^ild say the r®. tter is not in your hand. This is a matter for you, but you may know that we are going to claim this from any of our friends.whether it be Your Highness or any other one until natters are settled in a satisfactory manner which keep&amp; our souls at rest and prevents further aggression against our subjects. You doubtless know that some people in whose hand certain matters are entrusted^ J^y are our friends and wil, notnot hesitate to protect our rights, but v/e cannot say any thing about the affairs concerning your country before referr -ing the natter to you. W' We request therefore that you would give the mattei your due consideration in order to remove the difficulties and continue our friendship, so that our subjects may enjoy peace. If Your Highness have a desire for this your brother would be grateful. If you have any excuse in tte matter I i+xiJL hope you would not blame us as every one would prefer his ' V own interests and that of his country / and you would excuse your brother, as it is the duty of every one to protect his own interests and those of his country*llsi Translation of Postsrcipt dated 4th Jamad ath- Thani 1349(i.e.26.10.30) from His Excel .ency Shaikh Hamad bin 'Isa al Khalifah, C,S.I.,Deputy Ruler of Bahrain to His I.lagesty 'Abdul 'Aziz bin 'Abdur Rahman al Fa sal as- Sa'ud, King of Hijaz, Najd and Dependsncies• Brother. May you live long. ^ Your Majesty informed me that since long time your subjects have been complaining ol the treatment ^ney get in Bahrain. You also mentioned eCbvtfi the Qatif people My brother, may you live long, you have disturbed the mind J I Km ^ C of your brother very much and have A been more displca^oa. I therefore ask Your Majesty to inform me about the duties^ frsyv _ I uZYC*?) and in what way they are considered to be A injustice. As regards the Qatif people, I have always consid ered there was no difference between Qatii and Bahrain. Your Majesty mentioned that certiten people in whose hands/matuers are entrusted, were your iriends. I hope from Almighty God to increase your friends,as your fnands are ours, and that your enemies may be forsaken. As regards the interests to which your Majesty hafl referred, Your Majesty knows that your brother prefers your interests io those he likes for himself. U.E.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 60-T. 1930 Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I.a.T.S. 'PATRICK 3TEWAHT', At S e a, 16th NoTember 1930. From The Hon^le Lieut-Col. H.V.Biscoe, I.A., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India New Delhi. Sir, P r ; I have the honour to forward herewith a copy of y a letter No. 217-C, dated 26th October 1930, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, enclosing translations of post scripts to letters exchanged 'between the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd and the Shaikh of Bahrain. Ihn Saud's communication was somewhat 'bluntly worded, and it will be seen that Shaikh Hamad 1 s reply was equally 'blunt. 2. As regards the high handed acts of the (^usaibi family at Bahrain, there is a possibility that their in- -fluence with King Ibn Saud may be declining. They have / hitherto enjoyed customs exemption on all goods emported by them into Hasa. Recently however Ibn Saud has sent a customs inspector to Ilasa and I am told that he hss in- -formed the ^usaibis that they can no longer be allowed to import goods without payment of customs duty and that if the Kin^ wishes Jdun to accord them any concession it must take the form of a definite rebate or refund of customs duty to be granted to them after they have paid duty in the ordinary way. I saw Abdul Rahman ^usaibi in Bahrain and2 \\cl and he openly expressed to me his dislike of the Syrian officials employed 'by the King, and it was evident that there was no love lost 'between them. This, coupled with the action of the customs inspector, makes it probable that the Syrian element are endeavouring to undermine the influence of the ^usaiMs. If they are successful it will 'be all to the good as far as Bahrain affairs are concerned. 3 # I am sending copies of this letter and of its enclosures to His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India and to His Majesty's Minister, Jeddah. I have the honour to 'be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Col., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.COSFIOSNTIAL. MHO JNo. 61-T # of 1930. Office of the irolltlcaX Resident In the Persian Gulf. I.G.T.S. 'PATRICK STEWART^, At Sea, 16th November 1950* •,\oC&gt; i Un I have the honour to forward for the Infomatlon of 4 a -ajeaty a Government a oopy of my letter 5o ^60 »I, of today's date, to the Government of India, encloalng trnnalationa of oomBunioationa exchanged between the King of the Hejas and of Hejd and the Shaikh of Bahrain. I have the honour to he. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, Jo my Lieut - Co1 '. Political Resident i^i the Persian Oulf # Mia Majeaty'a Secretary of State for india, India Office, Ahitehall, iOHDoB, B.M.l,* 1 % Ut&lt;~ the matter la»t year from tiny atandpolnt of law, aa as* uivder- Qtood nationality lav* Reference was made to on /vrablan principle that all&amp;glunee depoiMis an re. Idarusc, a principle which Dm ^a'ud, who .lovea Ivavlng tMlnga both wiuya f would tiouoUeas not admit aa applicable to Hejclla In Bahrain but srouia like to asaert aa regards Bauralnis In Hejd* In tbla connection I \fould refer more particularly to ^ragmpiiia 3 and 6 of the quotation fro® ColBarett In paragraph 3 of Col» Jlacoe'a despatch of llax^h a4th 1930» Thla gives a peculiar aspect to the queatlon and num^esta that It could only uae* fully be ijuraued In a general dlacuaaloti of queatlons out~ atandlng between Ilejd and Bahrain, a dlacuaalon on which His Majeaty^ CHmmtommt do not wlah to embark pmaaturoly# (c) tfhen I waa dlacuaslng the Law on Uatlonnallty with Sheikh Yuaaul' Xaaln on Februa^fy 4th, I «ald th«t tht? Lhw interested ua 3 ,utfcX'alla fi^osa the point of view of Its effect on special oategoriM of persona with whoa we were o :&gt;neemed ami I iaen~ tlonod In casing Bahralnls* The ihelkh at once remarked tlmt their case wculd coac under the head of Bahrain quest- Ions* For obvious reasons 1 did not parauc the aatter but what he said conflms the view stated at the end of the pro- ceding sub-v paragraph* 3* In the circumstances X think that It would be Imprudent to embark aa a diplomatic discussion of the iaatter, so long aa any sort of local ssodus vlvendl can be preserved, even If It I© disturbed by occaslontil Incidents such as occun^ed last year# If, however, the dlacuaslon becooea necouaary. Inde pendently of future possible negotiations on other questions, I consider that we should ourselves have a clear view both as to what Is ©cent by ^good treiit«MNat t * and what persons we Intend to claim as Bahralnl sublets* 4s regards the first j^olnt, the difficultiesBo. JL28-3 o£ i93i. Britibia nesideacy &amp; Goaaulate-Generai, Jushire, tne i5th Marcn 1951* To Tiie Political Agent, BAHRAIN. i\ i ). . X, . iiuV' - A Mem0randUm&gt; f 4 U Reference tnis Office despatch ^10.12, dated the SJlst March i930, to the Colonial Office (attested cojy of v/hich was sent to youj. l forward, herewith, for your information, a ■ copy of despatch Uo.60, dated tne 10th February 1931, from His Majesty^ Minister, Jeddah, to the Jforeign ofiice, London. 3. The Hon*Lie tne Political Kesident will be ^lad to be informed how the question of the iJaharna in Hasa stands nowadays, i.e, wnetner you still receive complaints from them i^l*treatment at the hands of ijejd authorities or whether their treatment is now satisfactory. By Order, sit. Captain, k Secretary to the Political resident in the Persian Gulf.BY AIH MAIL. CONZIpl^xIAL. BUSH' RcSiDF.N' Ft At /s-7 ■ Dsib. CCNFIDENTlAt fitOCfiGt No. D.1536-N/31. 4 A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Iio:j f ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, with reference to the correspondence ending with the endorsement froin the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, No, P.464-N/29, dated the 85th June 1930. 1 } 2. It is requested that his views on the Express LetCer from India Office No. P.Z. 1951/31, dated the 17th April 1931, may be communicated to the Government of India by Air Mail. By order, etc., C ..4. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, Ml Foreign and Political Department, SIMLA: «r The May, 1931. • • • • • • . ' 1. Letter from the Foreign Office to the India Office, No. E.1072/1078 /25, dated the 30th March 1931, (without enclosure). 2. Express letter from the Secretary of State for India, No. P.Z. 1951/31, dated the 17th April 1931. /SeE 1072/1072/25. FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. 1. 30th March, 1931. Sir, With reference to the letters from this department N 0 s. E.224^/917/91 of the 15th May last and T 2758/150/378 of the 17th instant, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Henderson to transmit to you, for any observations which Mr. Secretary Benn may v /ish to offer, the accompanying copy of a despatch from His Majesty's Minister at Jedda regarding the question of the position of Bahreinis in the Hasa. V v^ 0 2. Mr. Henderson is in general agreement v /ith the views expressed by Sir A. Ryan in this despatch, and I am to enquire whether Mr. Benn is prepared to concur in Sir A. Ryan's proposal that he should be authorised, unless an acute situation should arise, to defer making the representations contemplated in Foreign Office despatch No. 145 of May 14th last.j- 3. A similar letter is being addressed to the Colonial Office,. I am, etc., Sd/- C.W. BAXTER. The Under Secretary of State, India Office.INDIA OFFICt, POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. EXPRESS LETTER (BY AIR KAIL). Prom - Secretary of State. To - Government of India, Foreign and Political Depa rtment. No. P.Z. 1961/31. 'Bntui n'i fijrU m/. ^ nlo Foreign Office letter dated 30th March (copy by mail of 1st April). Position of Bahreinis in the Hasa. Please let me have your views on proposal to defer making representations to Hejazi Government. Sd/- G.G. Laithv/aite. THE ABOVE HAS BEEK AUTHORISED FOR ISSUE.Telegram From To No. G.T.Cocie. Resident, Bushire. political Agent, Bahrain. 297. Dated the 9tn May -4.951, My memo ran duiii ^ o .128-s of 15th March, para graph 5. Does situation call for any further action at present time? -HESIDEHT-|e* It o- Confidential. :To. 52-0. The ency, J!ahrai n. BUSHIIE RESIDENCY. sr /V r / J/ cth Hay 193(6) OGHFIOtNTIAu BtCO^ X-N. l 0 The Secretary to the Hon 1 ble the Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf, 3 shire. ^ v ':or ndu:: . Please ref^r to your i eMorandiun the 13th I'nrch 1931. j,\ A - ^ L .nu o./ I2S- S dated 2. I ould he glad if you would inform the Hon*ble f the Politi of 1 le-icent tliat I have he^rc^no recent co.npTc.ints of the illtreatment of Bahama ( or rather lahrainis ) by the ' ejd authorities, ' rid it is clear that Bin Saud has rea lised that it is better to keep the cow alive and mlk it r-^t' er than kill it by harsh treatment. 3. There appears little doubt, however, that these unfortun' te people, particularly the Bahama or older settler who are now considered as Pejd subjects, are gradually being dispossessed of their lands and that these are being bought up by Sunni capitalists, notably the ubiquitous ^usaibis. It is impossible for us to intervene in such a matter, nor is it now expected of us, public opinion being amply satisfie A with the return of Ahmed bin Aboas to his relatives,last year for which II. P. Government received the credit. 4. ovt 1 '- - t Kedjaz Govern ient no Ion jer fear- that we are attempting to ar ert control over the Bahama the whole ^itu;-tion is e sier, and genuine Bahrainis are not interfered with and th^ir nationality papers are respected. 5. I fully agree with the view expressed in para 3 of Sir Andrew Hy- n's despatch I'o. 60 dated the loth of 'eb- ru.ry, namely that it is better not to take the matter up diplom.tic; lly so long as a local modus vivendi can be arrang edanr there is no doubt that the moment an attempt was made/H \ii Page 2. to regularise the situation endless difficulties would aris The sease of nationality is in itself so incomplete and so new r conception in these parts, that it is far better o Te've the mat er *.lone unti' action is forced u on us. cal .gent, 1. h rainConfidential . S 1956—2,000—9-14—(E2) No. 260-8. of 1951. Forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Kxprese Letter Department, for information, 0 ^ n . a .. .! this office toier**' No. , wrxlorinTnnBt Spl-Resdt P G 118 . dated the 12th May 1031 . 2« A copy of the eftclosure Is being sent also th the India Office and to M . jTs . Minieter at Jeddah. Becreta^y Bushire: StfJW&amp;y, irtviTOc'o the Politico I By order, ft y Resident in the Persian Gulf. The 12th May 1931. l&amp;tx . Subject ; Position of Bahrainis in Hasa. List of Paper?, ■ Memorandun Mo. 52-0, dated 9th May 1931, from the Political Agent, Bahrain.A^ 2i / u ^ H/j APPENDIX. Nationality Law. Consolidated text shewing the effect of the Amending Regulation of February 1931 on the original Regulation on Hejazi Nationality promulgated on Rabi-al-Awwal, 1345 (September 29, 1926). Amendments in the original text are shown in italics. Relevant provisions in the amending Regulation which cannot be so shewn are noted in brackets. Several articles the text of which is not expressly changed are nevertheless affected by the extension of the Regulation to Nejd as well as the Hejaz. Regulation of Hejaz-iVejd Nationality, (Article I of the Amending Regulation provides that the Regulation, the title of which is thus altered, shall apply to subjects of the Hejaz and of Nejd and its Dependencies. Article I\ provides that ' All dealings and acts done in accordance with the original Regulation since its promulgation up to the promulgation of this amendment shall be deemed lawful, effective and unchangeable.') Article I. Persons of Hejaz origin or residence who were Ottoman subjects before the Great War are considered Hejazis. Article II. Persons born of Hejazi parents, or whose father is a Hejazi, are Hejazis. Article III. (Modified throughout). Every person born in the territories of the Hejaz or Nejd mil be deemed a Hejazi or Nejdi national, subject to the 'provision that persons born in those terri tories of foreign parents shall have the right to opt for the original nationality of their parents during one year after they reach the age of 18 and, if they fail to notify the Hejaz-Nejd authorities of thetr choice during that fixed period they shall lose their right to opt. Article IV. Any Moslem who is not a minor and has resided in the Hejaz for three consecu tive years is entitled to adopt Hejaz nationality after application to the authorities either directly or indirectly. Article V. Hejaz nationality may be granted by a special royal irada to any Moslem, when such appears to the advantage of the Hejaz. Article VI. A Hejazi cannot adopt foreign nationality, either in the Hejaz or abroad, without proper authorization from the Hejaz Government, which can only be by royal irada. Article YI of the Amending Regulation adds the further provision that ' Hejazi or Nejdi nationals who renounce their nationality and become naturalized as nationals of a foreign state without permission of the Hejaz-Nejd Government will not be allowed to reside in or return to the Hejaz or Nejd.') Article VII. Hejazis who accept military service under a foreign government without previous authority from the Hejaz Government may lose their Hejaz nationality. Such persons may also be prohibited from returning to or residing in the Hejaz. Article VIII. A woman of alien nationality who marries a Hejazi becomes a Hejazi, and will not lose her Hejaz nationality on termination of the marriage, unless she resides abroad and re-adopts her former nationality. A Hejazi women who marries an alien reassumes her Hejaz nationality on termination of the marriage. Article IX. When a Hejazi adopts a foreign nationality, his young (minor ?) children do not assume that nationality while they are resident in the Hejaz. If their residence is in a place other than the territories of the Hejaz or Nejd and the nationality regulation of the. country in which their father has been naturalized does not entitle them to adopt that nationality they will remain Hejazis or Nejdis but if such regulation of the country in which their father has been naturalized entities them to adopt that nationality they will have the right to revert to Hejazi or Nejdi nationality when they reach the age of 18 if they choose to do so. Article X. (Modified throughout). Every person who was resident in the territories of the Hejaz or Nejd at the date of the promulgation of the Regulation on nationality of Rabi-al-Awwal 1345 shall be deemed Hejazi or Nejdi unless his foreign nationality is proved by official documents. Article XL This regulation is to be considered effective as from the date of promulgation. Our Viceroy is charged with the application of this law. (Article IX of the Amending Regulation empowers the Viceroy to issue instructions relative to the application of the provisions of both Regulations. Article X brings the Amending Regu lation into force from the date of promulgation.) PC89FD—20- 5 5 31—(HPS^ Coniidential. »\ v KO.D.1968-N/S1. HE3!Dt.NC v Re.. Oil' . . OOHfiu: V- i&gt;,w A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon'lDle the Political resident in the Persian Gulf, lor information Vvith relerence to the correspondence ending with his express letter No.259-3 of 1931, dated the 12th Fay 1931. \ By order, etc.. Assistant Secretary to the (rovernirient of India. A Foreign and Political Department, Simla, The ^ ' I'ay 1931. Sxpress letter to the Secretary of State for India, London,No.D.1968-N/31, dated the Kay 1931. (ifcith 1 s.c.)Con!ident ial. n 1^ ^o.D. 2039-N/31. (u r _ Bu5^; ri: residencv. AO Oaia. . COHFlOyTlAu RECOflDS % A «op/ of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon 1 ole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for information with reference to the correspondence ending with his endorsement No.&lt;i60-S of 1931, aated 12th Ma/ 1931, By order, etc., V ;r etsu Assistant Secretary to the Government of Inuia. Foreign and Political Department, Simla; The;^ June 1931. . Letter from the Colonial Office to the Foreign Office, No.89005/1931, dated the 24th April 1931. (With 1 spare copy).&lt;i4th April 1931. 89005/1931. vV \ Sir, 1 am directed b/ Lord Passfield to / acknowledge the receipt oi your letter No,E.1072/1072/25, of the 30th March, enclosing a cop/ of a despatch from His Majesty's Minister at Jedda regarding the question of the position of Bahreinis in the Hasa, and to state that he concurs in the proposal contained in Sir A. Ryan's despatch. X am, etc., Sd. O.G.R. Williams. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.I *i #'■. ^ Oonfldential « S(u346 «S of 1931. British. Residency &amp; Gonaulate- General, Bushire, the X2th June 1931 • To The Political Agent f 2. &amp; ^ * a MEMORAHDUM . RefeVenoe correspondence ending with yo /&gt;. 17 7 memorandum H0.52-C, dated the 9th May 1951. 2* His Uajesty 1 * Government hare concurred in the proposal to defer indefinitely the making of representations to the Hedjaas Government regarding the position of Bahrainis in Hasa* By Order. f ■ for Secretary to t;he Political Resident in the Persian Gulf*X. ICiniH'VTAL. (qh^ RH CCNflQtMiAl ALOORDS- No, F.169-N/31. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon t tile the Political Resident in the Persian A G-ulf, for information, in continuation of the endorsement from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, No. F,169-I n 1/31, dated the 22nd July 1931. v \ap &gt; By order, etc.. emus Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. M foreign and Political Department, Simla ; The j p' July 1931. • • • • • • # # • Letter from the Foreign Office to His Majesty*s Minister, Jeddah, No. 250, dated the 25th June 1951. (with 1 spare copy)« f 'nenfy i 2*6 o I )1 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. the ia: F ndta O ffice, W hitehall. 4098 L ondon, S.W. 1. so to theCOHriQES. irw RtwuHDo j A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon f 'ble Uie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ( for info rmati on ^ with reference to the correspondence ending witlj the endorsement from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department^ No• D.2039-1T/31&gt; dated the 2nd June 1931. :. By order, etc. , Assistant Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department. 3 i m 1 a; v The July 1931. Letter from the India Office to the Foreign Office* No. P.2.3560/31, date^ the 22nd June 1931. M yK V (with 1 spare copy)(E 3047/1072/25) FOREIGN OFFICE, 25th June, 1931 0° Sir With reference to your despatch No. 60 of the 10th February, 1931, I have to Inform you that 1 am In general agreement with the views expressed by you therein regard ing the position of Bahrelnls In El Hassa. 2. I concur In your proposal that, unless an acute situation should arise, you should postpone making to the Hejazl Government the representations contemplated in my despatch No. 145, of May 14th, 193®. I am, etc., (For the Secretary of State) V Sd/- 0.17. Baxter. Sir Andrew Ryan, K.B.E., C.M.G., e be», etc., etc. Jedda.-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000133_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/334</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000133</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/334</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 19/163 I (C 33) Bin Saud's relations with Shaikh of Bahrain. Nejdi Agent's activities in Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1923/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-11-26T11:06:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (201 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.</extent><extent>Formerly a bound correspondence file, its sheets have been unbound and are now loose. Foliation starts on first page of the volume and continues to the last page of writing. Foliation in pencil numbers in top right corner of recto. An additional foliation sequence, also in pencil numbers in top right corner of recto, starts with 1A, 1B on f.1. The two numbers converge at 57-60 and only one set of number is present from f.61 to f. f.121. Two sets of numbers again appear from f.122 to end. The following foliation errors occur: f.1 is followed by f.1A, f.25 is followed by f.25A, f.111 is followed by f.111A. f.112 is contained in an envelope on f.111.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains documents regarding relations between the British, Bin Saud and Shaikh Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa between 1923 and 1931.The documents discuss the Persian-Nejdi violence that occurred in Bahrain in 1923, the activities and expulsion of Bin Saud's agent in Bahrain (Abdullah Al Qusaibi), the resistance to reform of Sunni tribes in Bahrain and the arrival in Bahrain of Shia refugees from Qateef.The file contains correspondence regarding the status of Shia communities in Hasa and Qateef and whether or not they are Baharna and thus fall under British protection or not.The file also contains correspondence between Bin Saud and the British and petitions to British authorities from the Shia community in Qateef.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia 'Abd al-'Azīz bin 'Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa'ūd</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Hugh Weightman</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Khalīfah (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Resistance to government</topic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>National Economy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Religious conflicts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rights of states</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arab nationalism</topic></subject><subject><topic>Social reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Economic reform</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000133#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>