<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000103_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:53:33.454Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Further Papers respecting the Slave Trade on the East Coast of Africa, and the System pursued for its Suppression. No. 1. The Secretary to the Admiralty to Mr. Otway.—(Received April 5.) Si r? Admiralty, March SI, \S69. 1 AM commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit herewith, for the information of the Earl of Clarendon, a copy of a letter from Commodore Sir Leopold Heath, and of its inclosure, reporting on the state of the Slave Trade on the East Coast of Africa during the year 1868. With reference to the statement of the Commodore that the proceedings hitherto adopted for the suppression of the Slave Trade have proved complete failures, I am to request you will inform Lord Clarendon that, while my Lords will be prepared to take such steps for carrying out the policy of endeavouring to suppress the Slave Tradeon the East Coast of Africa as his Lordship may advise, they hope that, if it be determined to employ a larger force for this purpose, political measures will be taken which may render the employment of that force thoroughly effective. Their Lordships doubt whether a mere increase of the squadron would result m material benefit to the object in view. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) W. G. ROMAINE. p,S. Some photographs which accompanied the Commodore's letter are transmitted herewith, and it is requested they may be returned when done with. Sir, Inclosure in No. 1. Commodore Sir L. Heath to the Secretary to the Admiralty. ' Octavia,' at Bombay, March 1, 1869. IN accordance with the 7th paragraph at page 16 of the Slave Trade Instructions, I forward for the information of their Lordships, the following Report for the year 1868. 2 Their Lordships will remember that at the end of the previous year Her Majesty's ship ' Penguin ' was the only vessel in the squadron available for service against the Slave Trade the remaining ships having been withdrawn to join in the Abyssinian Expedition. The fall of Magdala, however, happened at the very beginning of the slaving season, and I was enabled whilst the troops were on their return march, to dispatch three vessels on short cruizes, which resulted in the destruction of nine dhows and the liberation of 244 slaves ; the vessels returning to Annesley Bay in ample time for the re-embarkation of the ^3 The expeditionary force having been embarked by the middle of June, the whole souadron (' Vigilant,' which was found rotten, excepted) again became available for its usual work and 1 am glad to be able to submit the following abstract of captures, &amp;c., showino- an' amount of success far exceeding the average of recent years ;— Total number of dhows captured Total tonnage of captured dhows Total number of slaves liberated 66 7,233 -47 1,097 I4. I attribute these results mainly to the energy and activity of the officers com manding Her Majesty's ships on this Station; but something may also be due to the system which has been adopted of pouncing down from Indian ports upon the line of traffic, instead of operating, as has hitherto been the practice, from Zanzibar as a centre. Under the new plan the traders remain in perfect ignorance of the intended movements of the cruizers, which was not always the case under the old one. 5. Finding that many years had elapsed since any flag-ship bad been to Zanzibar, 1 proceeded to that port in the month of August, and I hope that some good may have been done by the visit, and some impression left upon the mind of Sultan Majid by the earnest language used by me at the interviews which His Highness was pleased to grant me. The proposals made on these occasions are recorded in an inclosure to my letter to their Lordships, No. 237 of 1868. 6. An Embassy from the Sultan left Zanzibar for England in the autumn ; and, although its members were charged principally with the duty of endeavouring to obtain a release from the obligation to pay an annual subsidy to Muscat, they were also empowered (as I was informed by the Sultan) to discuss questions relating to the Slave Trade. The results of this mission will be recorded in the Report for 1869. 7. I observe that it is not unusual to close these reports with an expression of hope that the heavy blows which have been dealt at the trade during the past year will go far to check it for the future. I can express no such hope. The Trade is far too profitable, and will not be affected by a risk so small as that incurred by the proceedings of Her Majesty's ships. It supplies a want which has not been left unsatisfied for many centuries past,—a want which, sanctioned by the religion of the country, has grown almost into an instinct. To put down this trade requires far more effort and far more energy than England has yet shown in the matter. Twenty-five years have elapsed since the first Treaty with Muscat, and all that time we have been contented with the capture of a very small per-centage of the total exports,—a per-centage large enough to irritate the legal traders, who are harassed and annoyed by the visits of our cruizers, but too small to affect materially the illegitimate trade. We must do far more than this to insure success. We must double or treble our squadron. We must establish Vice-Consulates at the ports of export, but, above all, we must force the Government of Zanzibar into active acquiescence in our views, and, if necessary, purchase or take possession of that island. 8. I attach some illustrative photographs taken by Commander Sulivan on board Her Majesty's ship ' Daphne,' and a water-colour drawing by Mr. Henn, Sub-Lieutenant of that ship. The wretched emaciated condition of the slaves shown in photograph No. 3 is due entirely to the avarice or carelessness of the Arab dealers; but the drowning of men, women, and children incidental to running dhows on shore to avoid capture, as shown in Mr. Henn's drawing, is entirely the result of our proceedings. Five full dhows were seen to run on shore during the recent cruize of the ' Daphne,' and many other similar cases have been observed during the year. 9. I would most earnestly submit for their Lordships' consideration whether it is right to follow the present unsatisfactory mode of attempting to put down the East African Slave Trade. If I am right in supposing that the only result of those proceedings has been to liberate less than 5 per cent, of the slaves exported at the expense of drowning some hundreds a-year, and of discouraging legitimate commerce, it would seem to follow that we should withdraw from the attempt, or make it with far greater vigour. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) L. G. HEATH. No. 2. The Secretary to the Admiralty to Mr. Otway.—(Received July 1.) Sir, Admiralty, June 29, 1869. I AM commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit, for the information of the Earl of Clarendon, a copy of a letter from Commodore Sir Leopold Heath, dated the 7th of June, forwarding an account of an engagement between the boats of the ' Nymphe' and Arabs, at Zanzibar, and the capture of a dhow with 136 slaves on board. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) VERNON LUSHINGTON.he officers com- 0 be due to the upon the line of sibar as a centre, ed movements of m to Zanzibar, I 1 may have been id by the earnest grant me. The y letter to their n; and, although obtain a release empowered (as I ,de. The results pression of hope ear will go far to )o profitable, and of Her Majesty's enturies past,—a ; into an instinct. England has yet aty with Muscat, 11 per-centage of ;raders, w 7 ho are 3t materially the We must double 3 of export, but, uiescence in our ulivan on board , Sub-Lieutenant (holograph No. 3 Irowning of men, are, as shown in dhows were seen ;her similar cases on whether it is down the East hose proceedings ense of drowning d seem to follow G. HEATH. / 1.) Tune 29, 1869. to transmit, for idore Sir Leopold etween the boats th 136 slaves on JSHINGTON. Sir Inclosure 1 in No. 2. Commodore Sir L. Heath to the Secretary to the Admiralty. 'Forte,' at Aden, June 7, 1869. IN forwarding this Report, for their Lordships' information, and recommending the officers therein named to their Lordships' consideration, I have to state that on inquiry for the names of the coxswains of the cutters, I find that they are not men deserving, in other respects, of advancement. 2. Mr. Clarke is a Sub-Lieutenant of more than three years' standing, and Mr. Hodgson has been invalided on account of his wound. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) L. G. HEATH. Inclosure 2 in No. 2. Commander Meara to Commodore Sir L. Heath. Sir, ' Nymphe' Seychelles, May 5, 1869. I BEG to report to you that while lying at Zanzibar, information was sent to me by Dr. Kirk, Acting Political Agent and Consul, at MS, a.m ., on the 11th of April, 1869, that a dhow had embarked slaves and was to sail immediately, and requested me to send a boat to take her, as he had the Sultan's permission for so doing. The two cutters were immediately dispatched in charge of Acting Lieutenant Clark, Mr. T. Hodgson, Sub-Lieutenant, and Mr. T. Maxwell, Acting Sub-Lieutenant. Half-an-hour after their leaving the ship, I heard quick firing of musketry. At S'lS a.m . the second cutter returned, reporting the dhow captured, with, I regret to say, the loss of one man, William Mitchell, A.B.; Mr. Thos. Hodgson, in charge of the second cutter, severely wounded in the left wrist with a musket ball; and Acting Lieutenant Clark, wounded in the leg with a spear. The dhow was brought alongside at 4 a.m ., with 136 slaves on board. The chief firing was opened on the boats from the shore, the dhow being only 20 yards off, with a stern line line to the shore; the crew jumped overboard after the boats had boarded. I cannot close this despatch without bringing before your favourable notice the gallant conduct of Acting Lieutenant Clark, Mr. T. Hodgson, Sub-Lieutenant; and Mr. T. Maxwell, Acting Sub-Lieutenant. Acting Lieutenant Clark has reported to me the conduct of the men under him as being most exemplary. I beg to inclose you his despatch. I also beg to inclose you a copy of a letter from Dr. Kirk, the purport of a communication received from His Highness the Sultan relative to the capture of the dhow. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) E. S. MEARA. Inclosure 3 in No. 2. Acting Lieutenant Clark to Commander Meara. gi rj il Nymphe' Zanzibar, April 16, 1869. IN compliance with your orders relative to capturing a slave-dhow in Zanzibar Harbour, 1 have the honour to report my proceedings as follows:— I left the ship on the 11th April, 1869, at 1 o'clock, a m ., in charge of the two cutters with Mr. Thomas T. Hodgson, Sub-Lieutenant, and Mr. Thomas E. Maxwell, Acting Sub-Lieutenant. On approaching the dhow, which was about twenty yards from the shore, secured by a stern-line, I at once convinced myself that she was shipping slaves, and on boarding, found she was full, the crew having jumped overboard with the exception of one man who was in the bow, and he tried to cut the cable to allow the dhow to drift on the beach. I gave orders for the cutters to take the dhow in tow, and before they had time to do so, we received a volley of musketry from the beach, and the man (supposed to be the i4 captain of the dhow) that remained in the dhow for some time and trying to cut the cable. I attempted to cut him down, but only succeeded in striking him on the arm, but he wounded me with a spear in the leg, and then jumped overboard. I returned the fire with Sneider rifles, and the firing was kept up with great rapidity on both sides. After the Arabs ceased firing, I took the dhow in tow with one cutter, sending the other one on board with Mr. T. Hodgson, Sub-Lieutenant, wounded in the wrist with a ball, and W. Mitchell in the thigh, who I am sorry to say died shortly after he was brought on board. Their firing at times seemed to be too high, as I had a bullet pass through my cap, and several of the men had bullets through their upper clothing. Shortly after 3 a.m ., 1 arrived on board with the dhow and 136 slaves. The darkness of the night greatly favoured the Arabs, as they had a clear view of the dhow and boats against the horizon, and the Sneider rifles at so short a distance are likely to throw high. I estimated the number of Arabs with fire-arms to be between thirty and forty, but there were a considerable number with spears, swords, &amp;c. I beg to recommend to your notice the steady and gallant manner in which Mr. T. T. Hodgson, Sub-Lieutenant, Mr. T. Maxwell, Acting Sub-Lieutenant, the coxswains and crews of the two cutters, behaved, whilst under a heavy fire from a superior force. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) N. L. H. CLARK. Inclosure 4 in No. 2. Dr. Kirk to Commander Meara. Sir, Zanzibar, April 11, 1869. IT is with the greatest pleasure that I now report to you the purport of a communication received by me this day from His Highness the Sultan, in reply to my intimation of what happened last night, in the capture of a slave-dhow, in His Highness' Harbour of Zanzibar. 1. His Highness entirely approves of your proceedings, commends the gallantry of your men, and condoles with you on the loss of one of your seamen, and the wounding of your officers. 2. He places the dhow and slaves at your disposal, through me. 3. He desires that the slaves may be sent on shore in gangs of fifteen at a time, each gang to be returned before another comes on shore,—and this, for the purpose of ascertaining from each slave where, and by whom he was sold, that all engaged in this transaction may be punished. I have further to inform you, that I have found in the correspondence taken in the dhow, evidence to implicate many people in the Slave Trade ; and also letters of a seditious nature, which have already led to the arrest and imprisonment of their authors. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) JOHN KIRK. No. 3. The Secretary to the Admiralty to Mr. Otway.—(Received July 6.) Admiralty, July 5, 1869. I AM commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to send you, herewith, for the information of the Earl of Clarendon, copy of a letter from Commander De Kantzow. Her Majesty's ship ' Star,' dated the 9th of June, reporting generally on the Slave r l rade on the East Coast of Africa, and his proceedings for its suppression ; also copy of another letter from the same ofiicer, dated the 9th of June, stating that the ' Star ' had captured off Cape Guardafui, an Arab dhow with 236 slaves on board, on the 26th of May, bound to Muscat. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) VERNON LUSHINGTON.• f Inclosure 1 in No. 3. Commander De Kantzow to Commodore Sir L. Heath. Sir, ' Star,' at Aden. June 9, 1869. IN obedience to my sailing orders, dated the 31st of March, 1869, I have the honour to report that after fifty-six days' cruizing for the suppression of the Slave Trade (during which period 112 dhows were boarded, all proving legal traders), while lying at anchor under the north-east Cape of Ras Hafoon, ready for shipping, on the 26th of May, at 1 p.m ., a dhow hove in sight, standing in for the Cape. I immediately dispatched Lieutenant Jekyll in the cutter to board her. After the lapse of about fifteen minutes the dhow, on catching sight of the ship cast anchor off the point, and commenced hauling ♦in for the shore to land her slaves. The cutter was stf&amp;n alongside, and seized her. She had 236 slaves on bard (as noted in the margin),* was eight days from Zanzibar, bound to Muscat, with a crew of eleven, and sixteen passengers, the latter being slave traders and the owners of the slaves. On the cutter capturing the dhow, a small portion of her slaves had already landed, with some Arabs. A few shot were fired by these Arabs, ftfdden behind the rocks, and who eventually escaped. All the slaves were recovered, and Lieutenant Jekyll showed in this instance (as he has already done on a previous case), care, energy, and proper prudence in their recovery. I may here, however, observe that a dhow standing in for the Cape must find it next to impossible to escape; her course up along the coast is cut off by the presence of this ship at anchor. Should she attempt to bear up again or stand out to sea, she would be immediately chased and overhauled by the 'Star,' and her only course left is to land her slaves at once; but as the nature of the ground between where we were at anchor and the Cape is a deep ravine, with ridges of sharp rocks intervening, and the landing at the Cape must necessarily take time to scale a difficult precipitous cliff, the recovery of the slaves on landing is almost certain. On clearing out the dhow shortly after her capture, she was found in an unseaworthy and very filthy state. The slaves, on the other hand, were healthy and in good condition, and overjoyed at their release. Those who had landed had been driven from the dhow at the point of the Arab After all the available wood had been added to our fuel in the bunkers, the remains of the dhow were scuttled. The Arab prisoners I had placed on board the Arab dhow named in the marginf (which had anchored near us on the evening of the 27th of May), at their own request, and with the consent of her captain, whom I supplied with a sufficient quantity of provisions and water for their use. On the 1st instant, a case of small-pox breaking out amongst the slaves, 1 left Ras Hafoon (there being no provisions for the slaves on board for a voyage to Seychelles), arriving at Aden on the 9th. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) H. S. DE KANTZOW. Inclosure 2 in No. 3. Commander De Kantzow to Commodore Sir L. Heath. Sir, ' Star,' at Aden, June 9, 1869. REFERRING to the subject of slave movements which have occurred under my notice during our present cruize for the suppression of the Slave Trade, I beg to submit— . _ , , p . 1. During our cruize between the 1st of April and the 9th of June, a period of sixty- nine days, 112 Arab dhows have been boarded, without suspicion attached to their lawful rallino' 2. A dhow boarded on the 7th of May, off Ras Hafoon, had a crew of thirty-six persons, exclusive of seven Africans, having all the appearance and condition of slaves. As 1410J * 35 men, 46 women, 155 children, f ' Futhelkhair,' of Marmora.they did not claim protection, and the dhow was loaded with wood, no proof existing that she was engaged in the Slave Trade, I have registered her as a free trader. 3. On the 26th a dhow was boarded by the cutter, in sight of the ship, and captured, with 236 slaves on board, viz., 35 men, 46 women, and 155 children. She was nine days from Zanzibar, bound to Muscat, and had stood into the Cape to refit her sails and steering gear, under shelter, and complete her water at the village near here. 4. Regarding the route taken by the slave dhows moving north during the monsoon, I am of opinion that none of them can, or rather do, carry sufficient water for the whole voyage ; and that the places of call for water are Has Mabber, Ras Hafoon, and Gollonseer Bay, for the dhows for the Persian Gulf; and Ras Mabber, Ras Hafoon, and Guardafui for those going to Maculla and the Gulf of Aden, 8rc. At those places we have visited during our cruize the information obtained is not reliable, the natives being in the Slave Trade interest, rather than our own to suppress it. # 5. Ras Mabber, I believe, from all the evidence gathered, to be the first place of call during fine weather, and when the voyage is necessarily prolonged ; Ras Hafoon, when it blows strong, comes next; and the other places as circumstances demand. 6. In order to intercept a slave dhow, I believe the best chance is for a cruizer to be kept exclusively under weigh in an east and west line off the north-east Cape of Ras Hafoon, with two boats down in-shore of her, with a store of water and provisions for their use placed in one of the coves under the lee. 7. With reference to the legal traders running up, which, being honest, as a general rule, are not afraid, and give no trouble, being stopped for boarding. The information obtained from them was to the effect that this year the northern Slave Trade was seriously crippled by the presence of an English man-of-war at anchor at Zanzibar, and the supposed Treaties or Concessions made by His Highness the Sultan Said Majid to our Government; at any rate, to his Edict prohibiting, under severe penalties, the purchasing or smuggling off to Arabia of slaves from his ports. Instances were mentioned to me of his sincerity to prevent the traffic, for example, the destruction, at Jamo, by his orders, of northern dhows found engaged in it. 8. Most of the trade running up was principally in grain and wood, for Maculla and other Arab ports, which, I was told, paid well ; but I was surprised to find some regular Badein dhows, with a Soory crew, for the Persian Gulf, running up in ballast. They stated no slaves could be got from the Sultan's ports, and the trade is this season almost annihilated. These dhows, I feel reasonably certain would have brought up slaves had it been possible to get them. 9. Speaking generally to the masters of Arab trading-dhows, touching the subject of carrying domestic slaves (so-called), they stated that they had no slaves working on board, nor did they carry any of any description, be it ever so few, the reason given being that ' the risk was too great; they would be sure to lose their dhow if discovered by one of the many English cruizers about, one of which was sure to overhaul them at some period of their voyage.' The fact of our not having come across any in all these 112 dhows boarded, and the easy means they all have of obtaining free labour when proceeding out of the Sultan's territorial limits, are defined by Treaty, has led me to conclude that no legal trader out of the Sultan's dominions looks upon this rule as a hardship; on the other hand, few of them look upon the purchasing, selling, or carrying of slaves as a crime, and would certainly engage in it jointly with their legal cargo if no penalty was attached ; were it otherwise, I see no possible means? of preventing any dhow evading the law, engaging in the Slave Trade, of its extending its present limits and threatening, by small importations and means, to become universal. 10. On the subject of selling slaves of any description no confidence whatever can be placed in the Arab, especially if his interests or pecuniary difficulties are before him. As an instance of the dread an African entertains of an Arab when hard up, I may mention that, on this ship's capturing a slave dhow on the 26th May, besides a number of slaves which were found to have been stolen and kidnapped from Zanzibar, three free native Africans were discovered in the dhow. They claimed protection; and when brought before me refused to accompany the crew, stating, now that the Arabs had lost their slaves and dhowj and almost bankrupt, they would be sure to sell them at Muscat, and they therefore wished either to join this ship or to be set down safe in an English Colony. 11. On examining the slaves, their former history is only a repetition of the old tale : viz., native tribes fighting in the Nyanza district, Arab traders purchasing the prisoners, marching them down to Keelwa on the coast-, transporting them to Zanzibar, and then selling them in the market for the Northern Arabs. Numbers of the girls and women of this dhow were found much burnt about the head and body. They stated that when their native villages were set on fire they got singed and burnt when running out, and were7 caught and sold almost immediately. They told me they were hurried on board the dhow after having been kept a long time waiting at Zanzibar, and after a previous attempt had been made to embark them ; that an English man-of-war had prevented it, but that this ship had now left full of slaves, which had been taken from two dhows attempting to get off (one of them at night, by her boats, under fire, in which two men were wounded). 12. A great blow has undoubtedly been struck this year against the Northern Arab Slave Trade. If this tight rein is kept up, I believe these Northern Arabs will soon find it to their interests to give up this disgraceful Traffic, and take to some more honest pursuits for their livelihood. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) H. S. DE KANTZOW. No. 4. Sir F. Rogers to Mr. Otway.—{Received July 14.) Sir, Downing Street, July 13, 1869. I AM directed by Earl Granville to transmit to you for the information of the Earl of Clarendon, and with reference to your letter of the 5th ultimo, a copy of a despatch from the Governor of Mauritius, forwarding a report from the Civil Commissioner of the Seychelles, respecting the distribution of two ship-loads of captured slaves, recently landed by Her Majesty's ships ' Daphne' and 'Nymphe,' in those Islands. Lord Clarendon will observe that the Governor desires that Her Majesty's Govern ment may be able to make arrangements for the disposal of captured slaves elsewhere than in Mauritius and Seychelles. A copy of Sir H. Barkly's despatch has been sent to the Admiralty. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) FREDERIC ROGERS. Inclosure I in No. 4. Sir H. Barkly to Earl Granville. My Lord, Mauritius, May 31, 1869. ADVERTING to my despatches, noted in the margin,* I have the honour to invite your attention to the accompanying extract from a Report made to me by the Civil Com missioner of Seychelles respecting the distribution of two ship-loads of captured slaves recently landed by Her Majesty's ships ' Daphne' and Nymphe,' in those Dependencies. 2. It will be perceived that Mr. Ward again describes the difficulty of finding suitable employment for these people, and expresses apprehensions as to large future arrivals owing to the prosecution of the Slave Trade on the East Coast of Africa more vigorously than ever. 3. There is, as I have previously stated, very little demand for the services of Africans in Mauritius where Indian labour is greatly preferred for agricultural operations, and as the transport of the former hither from Seychelles in hired vessels would put the Colony to very considerable expense, I trust that it will be in the power of Her Majesty's Government to make arrangements for their disposal elsewhere. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) HENRY BARKLY. * No. 68, April 2 ; No. 224, September 2, 1867.In closure 2 in ISTo. 4. The Civil Commissioner of Seychelles to Sir H. Barkly. (Extract.) May 6, 1869. 6. I TAKE this opportunity of mentioning that I have been able to distribute these Africans solely from the fact that the inhabitants are under the impression that no more liberated slaves are to be brought to Seychelles, an impression which I sincerely trust is fraught with truth. Should another cargo of slaves arrive I am quite convinced that I should be unable to distribute one of them ; and the cost of their detention and transport to Mauritius w T ould amount to a very heavy sum ; an expenditure much better avoided. But according to the accounts received by me from the Captains of Her Majesty's ships who touch here, the Slave Trade on the East Coast fostered, in a great measure by the protracted absence of the cruisers during the war in Abyssinia, and by the arrangements made for keeping the whole squadron north for the past nine months, leaving all south of Socotra unprotected, is now carried on more vigorously than ever. 7. The slaves brought here by Her Majesty's ship ' Nymphe' were captured almost in the town of Zanzibar, from a Northern Arab dhow. The boats which took her were fired upon from the shore, two officers were badly wounded, and one man was killed, all this taking place within earshot of the Sultan's Palace. The ' Nymphe' had taken 27 dhows within a very short period; other vessels in like proportion. The ' Star' now cruizing off the East Coast of Africa may bring a cargo of slaves here at any moment, as Zanzibar is swarming with Northern Arabs ; over these Arabs the Sultan of Zanzibar has no control of any kind, their ostensible pursuit is Slave Trade, and they are only waiting at Zanzibar for the change in the monsoon to enable them to run their cargoes north. 8. According to private information received from the Commodore all Her Majesty's cruizers are coming south and they will probably fall in with many dhows. Although no actual Order exists with respect to these captured dhows, it is generally under stood that all cargoes captured south of the Equator are to be brought to Seychelles, those taken north of the Line being taken to Aden. We may. therefore, expect more Liberated Africans at any moment, and heavy expenses consequent upon their being landed here, A difference in the number formerly taken by our cruizers may, perhaps be caused by the fact that nearly all the Slave Trade between the East Coast of Africa and Madagascar where any amount of slaves can be absorbed is carried on in dhows under French colours which our cruizers cannot touch. The Arab owners obtain their papers at Mayotte or Nossibe; not for one journey but for a whole year, during which period they are solely engaged in the Slave Trade. I inclose herewith a copy of one of these papers which I obtained from the Captain of Her Majesty's ship ' Nymphe.' The papers are perfectly en regie, but not a man on board the dhow could speak a word of French. 9. But, notwithstanding this outlet, the trade to the north is carried on to such an extent that in all likelihood the Seychelles will be inundated with a mass of Africans who, even under the most favourable circumstances, can do but a minimum of good to any country could they be disposed of as labourers, but who, under the present aspects of the labour-market, will put the Government to very heavy expense. The islands are now overstocked, not only with the African in his normal state, but with his offspring, the fecundity of the women being quite remarkable. Twins are very common ; and upon two occasions I have seen three at a birth. 10. With the present race of proprietors, men who can hardly be said to cultivate the land but a small quantity of labour suffices. A more enterprising class would naturally absorb a much larger proportion, but of enterprise here there is small prospect. The further arrival of liberated Africans must put the Government to very considerable expense an expense which I venture to submit, ought not to be borne either by the parent Colony or these islands.10 II est pont^ avec deux mats, et il est actuellement attache au port de Nossi Be. Prions et requdrons tous Souverains, Etats,amis et allies de la France, et leur subordonnds, mandons h tous fonctionnaires publics, aux Commandants desbatiments de I'Etat et k tous autres qu'il appartiendra, de le laisser surement et librement passer avec son dit batiment, sans lui faire ni souffrir qu'il lui soit fait aucun trouble ni empechement quelconque, mais au contraire de lui donner toute faveur, secours et assistance partout ou besoin sera. Delivre au port de Hell-Ville (Nossi Be), le 28 Juillet, 1868. Par autorisation du Ministre Secretaire de la Marine et des Colonies. Le Commandant Particulier, (Signed) No. 5. Mr. Otway to the Secretary to the Admiralty. Sir, Foreign Office, July 21, 1869. I AM directed by the Earl of Clarendon to transmit to you to be laid before the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty, the accompanying copies of two despatches, with their inclosures in original from the Acting British Consul and Political Agent at Zanzibar, reporting the proceedings which have taken place in the Vice-Admiralty Court in that island in the cases of two dhows captured and destroyed by Her Majesty's cruizers on the East Coast of Africa on suspicion of their being engaged in the Slave Trade. It will be seen that in the case of a vessel belonging to the Government of Mombas, destroyed by Her Majesty's ship ' Nymphe,' judgment has been given against the captors, giving rise, therefore, to a claim on the part of the owners of the vessel against Her Majesty's Government for compensation. Lord Clarendon would wish to call the particular attention of the Lords of the Admiralty to Dr. Kirk's observations respecting this case, and generally to the unsatisfactory system at present pursued by Her Majesty's cruizers in dealing with vessels suspected of being engaged in Slave Traffic on the East Coast of Africa. As regards vessels taken with large numbers of slaves, no difficulty can arise if captured beyond certain limits, and at certain seasons of the year; their cargoes afford sufficient evidence of the illegal nature of the voyage on which they are engaged, and the Commanders of Her Majesty's cruizers will be justified in destroying them if they are not fit to send to a port of adjudication. But in the case of vessels detained on suspicion of being engaged or being about to engage, in the Slave Traffic, or for having slaves on board forming part of the crew of the vessel, it appears to Lord Clarendon that the only safe mode of proceeding is to send the vessels with a part on the whole of the crew, to a port of adjudication. Even if the Commanders of Her Majesty's cruizers were themselves in a position to understand the papers found on board native vessels, and i,o communicate freely with the crew and passengers on board detained vessels, it is placing Her Majesty's officers in a most difficult and objectionable position to throw upon tliem the responsibility of destroying vessels, and thus practically of becoming judges of their own acts. But where, as is almost invariably the case. Her Majesty's officers arc unable either to translate the papers found or produced on board a detained dhow, or to communicate with the persons on board except through an interpreter, who may himself, as sometimes happens, understand but imperfectly the documents or language he is called upon to translate or interpret, the position of a Commander of a cruizer becomes still more embarrassing, and it is not to be wondered at if mistakes arise, and honest vessels are destroyed, as has been the case in the one belonging to the Government of Mombas, which would not have happened if the dhow had been sent to a port of adjudication. Moreover, under the present system of dealing with suspected slavers on the East Coast of Africa, when the vessels are destroyed, their crews are, if Lord Clarendon is correctly informed, sent ashore at the first convenient spot, and their owners or other parties interested in the vessels are left in ignorance where the case of their vessel will be adjudicated in the event of their wishing to defend their property. This will account, therefore, for the owners of native vessels seeking to place them, as the Reports received from the Commanders of Her Majesty's cruizers on the East Coast of Africa show that they are extensively doing, under the French flag, with the view to withdraw them from the action of British cruizers.•t de Nossi Be. 3ur subordonn^s, ! I'Etat et ^ tous ion dit batiment, uelconque, mais soin sera. rticulier, hly 21, 1869. laid before the iespatches, with ent at Zanzibar, f Court in that cruizers on the ie. mt of Mombas, nst the captors, sel against Her 3 Lords of the nerally to the ing with vessels Ity can arise if r cargoes afford ngaged, and the if they are not being about to the crew of the » is to send the in a position to freely with the r's officers in a ,ty of destroying rc unable either :o communicate If, as sometimes called upon to )mes still more nest vessels are Mombas, which ion. jrs on the East d Clarendon is wners or other ir vessel will be ) place them, as ic East Coast of th the view to I Their Lordships will, no doubt, concur with Lord Clarendon in opinion that this state of things is unsatisfactory, and should not be allowed to continue ; and with the view to consider, whether it is not possible to provide a remedy, his Lordship would propose that the Reports which have been received from the East Coast of Africa, and the instructions under which the Commanders of Her Majesty's cruizers are acting, should be referred for the consideration of a Commission composed of three or four competent persons whose knowledge of the state of things on the East Coast may enable them to suggest a remedy. ^ Lord Clarendon would consider the present moment an opportune one for dealing with this matter, inasmuch as his Lordship hopes shortly to be able to make certain proposals to the Sultan of Zanzibar for the more effectual abolition of the traffic in slaves from his dominions, and he would wish to assure the Sultan that legitimate traders will not be interfered with; and, moreover, Mr. Churchill, Her Majesty's Consul and Political Agent at Zanzibar, is now in England on leave of absence, and his intimate knowledge of the state of things on the coast could not fail to be most valuable. If their Lordships should concur in this proposal. Lord Clarendon would suggest that Mr. Churchill, and Mr. Rothery, the Registrar of the High Court of Admiralty, and Legal Adviser of the Treasury on Slave Trade matters, should be members of the Commission, and should meet any officer whom their Lordships might think fit to select, who, from having recently served on the East Coast, may be enabled to bring his experience to bear upon the subject. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) ARTHUR OTWAY. s No. 6. The Secretary to the Admiralty to Mr. Otway.—(Received July 26.) Sir'. Admiralty, July 24, 1869. I HAVE received and laid before my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty, your letter of 21st instant, with copies of despatches from the Acting British Consul and Political Agent at Zanzibar, relative to the proceedings in the Vice-Admiralty Court in that island, in the cases of two dhows captured and destroyed by Her Majesty's cruizers on the East Coast of Africa; in one of which cases, that of a vessel belonging to the Governor of Nombas, destroyed by Her Majesty's ship ' Nymphe,'' judgment had been given against the captors. 2. My Lords desire me to request that you will inform the Earl of Clarendon that they concur in the proposal to appoint a Commission to inquire into the system pursued by Her Majesty's cruizers in dealing with vessels suspected of being engaged in Slave Trade on the East Coast of Africa, and to consider the Reports which have been receivedi and the instructions under which the Commanding Officers of Her Majesty's cruizers are acting. 3. Their Lordships have selected Captain Henry Fairfax, R.N., who served for three years on the coast in Her Majesty's ship ' Ariel,' to act as a member of the proposed Commission; and they have forwarded a copy of your letter and its inclosures to Commodore Sir Leopold Heath, desiring him to furnish specific information and explanation on the points raised therein. T am, &amp;c. (Signed) VERNON LUSHINGTON. P.S.—It is requested that intimation may be made of the time when Captain Fairfax will be required to attend at the Foreign Office.12 No. 7. Mr. Melvill to Mr. Otway.—{Received August 24.) (Confidential.) o#ce, 25, 1869. ^ WITH reference to Mr. Otway's letter of the 5th, and to my reply of the 18th June last on the subject of the distribution and condition of slaves liberated at the Mauritius, Aden &amp;c I am directed by his Grace the Duke of Argyle to forward to you herewith, for the information of Lord Clarendon, copy of a letter from the Assistant Resident at Aden which has been received in answer to the communication addressed to him on the subject, T c 1 am, &amp;c. (Signed) J. COSMO MELVILL. Inclosure 1 in No. 7. Captain Goodfellow to the Under-Secretary of State for India. ^ r eCret ' ) Aden, July 13, 1869. IN acknowledging the receipt of your letter dated 25th ultimo, and inclosures, calling for information on the subject of the condition and distribution of slaves landed and liberated by Her Majesty's cruizers at this port, I have the honour to report, for the information of his Grace the Secretary of State for India, that the subject of exempting this settlement from the charge of cargoes of slaves captured by Her Majesty s ships has already been represented to his Excellency the Governor in Council of Bombay, and the Commodore Commanding-in-chief East Indies, is aware of the strong objections that exist which render it undesirable to overburden this confined and already overstocked settlement, comprising an area of only about fifteen square miles, more than halt of which may be styled uninhabitable, with the presence of any large numbers of these unfortunate helpless beings, hence I presume that any further remarks on the subject of the concluding paragraphs of Mr. Otway's letter would be unnecessary. With regard to the distribution and condition of the slaves that have been landed and liberated at Aden, I do myself the honour to submit a Tabular Statement of the numbers that have been discharged here, and beg to remark that the fact of so many having to be sent to the Presidency of Bombay, goes to prove what 1 have already stated in regard to the necessity that exists for exempting this port entirely at the present as it can absorb no more as a depdt, or, at any rate, should it be decided to constitute Aden an entrepdt for manumitted slaves that, owing to the limited and scanty accommodation and necessarily small establishment to supervise as well as the dearness of food and water and expenses of transit, some limit should be put on the numbers to be landed here. In the statement which accompanies I have to observe, with regard to the numbers that have been distributed locally, that most of them have been intrusted in the care of respectable natives of India resident at Aden, some have been employed in the Harbour Department, some by the Peninsula and Oriental Company, and others have been able to obtain employment for themselves, and several women have been legally married. In a barren solitary settlement like Aden, where we are so completely hemmed in on all sides, it is an impossibility to find employment for this class ; there are no schools or instructors, nor is there any legitimate means of affording them employment: their condition during detention here cannot, therefore, be said to be much bettered. Nor can I report that the mode of assignment for service or apprenticeship is as satisfactory as it should be ; it is so far so that they are virtually free, and in time able to obtain employment for themselves —chiefly as sailors on board the steamers and vessels, as well as some country craft which frequent this port, as also in other ways when they have learned the language and become, • .as most of them soon do, dissatisfied with their new mode of life, and, in their anxiety to sfeek a change, run away from their protectors, and then give this Department endless trouble as well as responsibility, which it is hoped may be averted. Owing to the limited accommodation at our disposal, and the proximity in all parts of the Peninsula to military cantonments, the care of these truly unfortunate beings on first arrival here is a hard one ; on being disembarked from the man-of-war there is always at first a fear of some contagious disease existing, such as small-pox, &amp;c., hence they are located in the only available detached position we have, namely, an Island in the Inner13 Harbour, and here some sheds have been erected to protect them from the weather (the Government of Bombay have sanctioned the erection of permanent pendalls to accommo date 150, with the necessary out-house and hospital, and it is hoped these will soon be finished); this island is completely isolated, and all provisions and water have to be conveyed to it by boat from the town—a distance of more than two miles—the available space for exercise is limited, and there is no means of amusing or employing the liberated slaves, and there is the fear of contagion, consequently they may, so to speak, be said to be imprisoned, until one by one they are applied for by the residents of this place or sent ott in parties as opportunity offers to the Presidency. An apothecary or hospital-assistant is appointed to their medical charge, and they are visited weekly by the principal medical officer • and I have to record the sense of obligation that this Department is under to Sumeon-Maior Turner for his kind attention and the interest displayed by him in these unfortunate beings for the past five years; and the small force of Aden native police is taxed to supply a certain number of persons to look after them and study their wants and comfort, and a European constable periodically visits the island. The above is the present condition of the liberated slaves at Aden during detention, and we have now nearly /00 ot these unfortunate beings in charge awaiting transport to Bombay. t . , In conclusion 1 trust I may be pardoned for entering at such length into the subject, but as T am of opinion that the present difficulties to be contended against cannot be even imagined by Her Majesty's Government, I trust my representations may have the eftect ot the organization of some proper establishment to look after and supervise and superintend the distribution of this unfortunate class, if it be desired, m connection with the Vice- Admiralty Court at this place, to establish a depot for liberated Africans at Aden ; and on this point I would respectfully suggest that the Political Resident, Sir Edward Russell now on leave in England, be referred to, that the statements made by me may have the benefit of his corroboration, and that Her Majesty's Government may be in possession of his views as well on this subject. 1 have, &amp;c. (Signed) W. R. GOODFELLOW. Inclosure 2 in No. 7. Memorandum of Number of Slaves landed and liberated at Aden, and how disposed of. Number of Slaves landed at Aden and liberated. Landed in 1865 1866 1867 1869 (up to June 30) . 249 949 231 524 1,044 Total 2,997 How Disposed of. Sent to Bombay in 1865 1866 1867 „ 1868 1869 Awaiting transport 1869 Distributed on service locally, up to July 1869 Casualties— Allowed to seek employ on liberation, and permitted to return to their country* . Totfd .. • • 57 48 221 92 106 743 684 1,046 2.997 # During the Abyssinian expedition numbers of slaves were shipped on board ships leaving this port. There was no record kept apparently. (Signed) Aden Residency, July 13, 1869. W. R. GOODFELLOW, Captain, Assistant-Resident in charge, Aden. [410] ENo. 7*. Mr. Rothery to Mr. Oho ay.—{Received August 24.) Sir, Admiralty Registry, Doctors' Commons, August 23, 1869. I HAVE to acknowledge the receipt of Mr. Murray's letter of the 15th of June last, forwarding, by directions of the Earl of Clarendon, copy of a despatch from Her Majesty's Acting Political Agent and Consul at Zanzibar, with the papers, in original, relating to the cases of ten Arab dhows which had been captured by Her Majesty's ship ' Nymphe,' and condemned in the Consular Court at Zanzibar for being engaged in the Slave Trade. I have delayed answering Mr. Murray's letter, as there was until recently a Bill pending before Parliament for the purpose of defining the jurisdiction of the Consul in cases of this description; and ft seemed uncertain whether that Bill would become law. The Bill, however, was passed just before the close of the session, and 1 now, therefore, propose to state the position in which these cases stand. As you are aware, the authority under which the Consul acted in these cases was Her Majesty's Order in Council of the 9th of August, 1866, the 29th section of which provides that ' Her Majesty's Consul within the dominions of Zanzibar shall, for and within the said dominions, and for vessels and persons coming within those dominions, and in regard to vessels captured on suspicion of being engaged in the Slave Trade within those dominions, have all such jurisdiction as for the time being ordinarily belongs to Courts of Vice-Admiralty in Her Majesty's possessions abroad.' It will thus be seen that the jurisdiction thereby conferred upon the British Consul was smpjy over vessels engaged in the Slave Trade, either coming within or captured within the dominions of the Sultan of Zanzibar. Now of the ten dhows in question, the nrst appears to have been captured off Dalrymple Bay, in Madagascar; the four next at Majungo m Madagascar ; the two next in Boteler River, also in Madagascar ; the eighth m Delgado Bay, the ninth in Mungollo River, both on the East Coast of Africa; and the tenth in the harbour of Zanzibar. The last case, no doubt, falls within the terms of the S 0011 ' 1 ' as ?? also ' P^bably, the eighth and ninth cases; but in the first seven cases the Consul would seem, so far as can be ascertained from the papers, to have acted without any authority whatever, and to have condemned vessels over which he had absolutely no jurisdiction at all. Commi^?nn With f u™™ . meet , ca if s of this description that I was directed by the Lords M? t ' er r Maje f y S 10 P re l ,are a short Bin ' ha ™8 for ^ object to IhctW ttn l 8 , su ! al Zamth-M jurisdiction over all Zanzibar vessels captured, nation nnw'I? ^ ^ommions of Zanzibar, as also over all vessels name and The Bi» T ent ed t0 , da ' n the Flection of the flag of any State or nation, irant the nlST 086 ?' am0n8 f 0tller tbiD ? s ' t0 em po w er the Lords of the Treasury to Order in Council ou ? 'r 8 on ' e ca .P tu r e ot any such vessels, a power not given by the ^e^ of the grounds for passing the Bill is Juris«clL h nTzaS^l at t d 'iifin.? i JL WaS passed ' and is entitled ' The Slave Trade provides that Her r ^ u ^ 33 Vict ' ca P- 75 ' = ^ 2nd section the commencement nAh* 3 ^^have, and shall be deemed to have, always since belongs to Vipp AH ' if 6 saul 0rder m Council had ' all such jurisdiction as ordinarily beyond the d^minbns^nf 7^ ^ T* Zanzibar VesSels ca P tu ^ whe ther within o^r 4th section nrov dlTth .1 fvf'! an ^ over vessels name an d nation unknown. And the of being engao-ed in nr 6 • C j r a PP^ to cases vessels captured on suspicion Majesty's Consul at 7 a n Slave Trade, and adjudicated upon by Her So far ?hpLf .T' Wheth J er bef0re 0r after the P assin S of thi s Act.' ^ previously irreguW fh/A f 86 * and , s ™ llar cases ^ which the Consul's Decrees were niigbt be^vell pal 1 n0 p d0Ubt ' haS rendered them valid - At the same time, it case, before adiudioatino- on ^ s attention to the fact,^ and to direct him in any future Order in CounHI nr ff 1 V ^ r^ Ulte certa ^ 11 ^at it comes within the terms of the absolutely invalid inH ^ Kf i ^ i lament ' ^ 0r ' otherwise, his proceedings would be Her Majesty's Go'vernment ^ dem ' dnds for c o m P^s a tion being made upon carefully vvatched^v^n ^ proceedings before the Consul are stated to have been prop^ty. This TfK 0 * Hls . Hi S h '^ the Sultan, in defence of his subjects' eno-a^ed in the SI- ivp T^ 8 ^n 01 ?' aS 1 j a ^ or d s the best security that only vessels actually —tx:^ ••— * be, as I believe it is, a port to which not only great numbers of Arab15 vessels, but also Her Majesty's cruizers in those seas, frequently resort, it is a very strong reason for giving junsdiction m the case of these Arab dhows to the British Consul at that place; it might even be a matter for consideration whether the proceedings in the case of Arab dhows captured on the East Coast of Africa ought not always to be taken before the British authorities at Zanzibar, possibly also at Muscat and Aden; for I can conceive no greater ^justice to a Zanzibar ship-owner or merchant, whose property has been seized in the neighbourhood of Zanzibar, than to compel him to proceed to the Cape of Good Hope the Mauritius, or perhaps, even, to some more distant port, to protect his property from the 'Nymphe''~ a CaSe WhlCh haS 0nly recentl y occurred in connection with a capture by The mclosures to Mr. Kirk's letter, which you were good enough to forward to me, I have retained for reference, in case an application should be made by the captors for the bounties, under the provisions of the recent Act. I am, &amp;c, (Signed) H. C. ROTHERY. Inclosure in No. 7*. Slave Trade Jurisdiction {Zanzibar) Bill, 1869. Explanation of the Provisions of the Bill. THE object of this Bill is to confirm and supplement the provisions of an Order in Council of the 9th August, 1866. By that Order it was, amongst other things, provided, that the British Consul at Zanzibar, in pursuance, no doubt, of concessions made by the Sultan, should, ' for vessels and persons coming within the Sultan's dominions,'' and in regard to vessels captured 'on suspicion of being engaged in the Slave Trade within those dominions, have all such juris diction as for the time being ordinarily belongs to Courts of Vice-Admiraltv in Her Majesty's possessions abroad.' It will thus be seen that the Order in Council refers only to vessels coming within or captured within the dominions of the Sultan of Zanzibar; and not to vessels captured without his dominions, and destroyed on the spot by the captors, as being unfit for a voyage to Zanzibar or to any other port of adjudication, although these vessels also might have been captured in pursuance of some Treaty with the Sultan. Again, the Order in Council gives no power to the Lords of the Treasury to award the usual slave and tonnage bounties to the captors in respect of vessels or slaves con demned by the Consul, all the existing enactments relative to the award of bounties being confined to those cases in which the vessel or slaves have been condemned in some Admiralty or Vice-Admiralty Court within Her Majesty's dominions. Nor does it regulate the procedure before the Consul, nor provide any course of appeal from his decisions. The objects, then, of the proposed Bill are briefly these: I. To confirm the jurisdiction of the British Consul at Zanzibar in slave trade cases, as expressed to be conferred upon him by the Order in Council. II. To extend in two points only the jurisdiction so conferred : (1.) To cases of vessels captured in pursuance of any Treaty with the Sultan of •Zanzibar, but not being at the time of seizure within the Sultan's dominions, nor subse quently brought within those dominions. It is necessary to provide for such cases, as very frequently the captured vessels are found to be unfit for a voyage to a port of adjudication, whether Zanzibar or any other, and are therefore destroyed at sea by the captors. (2.) To cases of vessels not entitled to claim the protection of the flag of any State or nation, wherever they may have been captured; Such cases are not specified in the Order in Council, but it is obviously convenient that the Consul should have jurisdiction over them, and there can be no objection to giving it. Moreover, it not unfreqnently happens, that Zanzibar vessels are either without flags or papers, or when on the point of being captured throw their papers overboard ; and there being then no evidence of the vessel's nationality, they are obliged to be proceeded against as vessels of name and nation unknown, and not entitled to claim the protection of the flag of any State or nation. 111. To empower the Lords of the Treasury to award the usual bounties to the16 captors in respect of vessels and slaves condemned by the Consul at Zanzibar, whether before or after the passing of this Act. j ,, IV. To extend to the decrees of the Consul at Zanzibar in slave trade cases the same right of appeal to Her Majesty in Council, which is now allowed by law from the decrees of any Vice-Admiralty Court within Her Majesty's dominions. , . , . V. To confirm the past decisions of the Consul in such cases, subject to the right ot appeaLj ^ ralJ to ex tend, so far as may be necessary, to cases brought for adjudi cation before the Consul at Zanzibar, the procedure which prevails in the Vice-Admiralty C0Ur The prevalence of the Slave Trade on the East Coast of Africa, especially in the neighbourhood of Zanzibar and other parts of the Sultan's territories, and the fact that within the last six months of the year 1868 no less than 27 slave vessels have been condemned by the British Consul at Zanzibar, in exercise of the powers conferred upon him by the Order in Council, suffice to show that an Act to the above effect is not unnecessary. ., ,, it • ^ 4.1, It will also, if passed in the present session, effect a considerable public saving, lor the captors being unable, under the existing statutes, to obtain an award of the bounties on a condemnation by the Consul at Zanzibar, will no doubt institute fresh proceedings in the High Court of Admiralty, which has concurrent jurisdiction in such cases, for the condem nation of their prizes; and the costs of these proceedings, averaging probably about 30/. in each case, will, where the bounties do not exceed 1,000/., have to be defrayed at the oublic expense, in accordance with the usual practice in such cases. (Signed) H. C. ROTHERY. May 1869. No. 8. Mr. Kirk to the Earl of Clarendon.—(Received August 30.) (No. 21.) My Lord, Zanzibar, June 2S, \869. I HEREWITH inclose the proceedings in the Vice-Admiralty Court here in the case of a dhow having 52 slaves on board, which was taken by Her Majesty's ship ' Daphne,' under the command of Commander Sulivan. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) JOHN KIRK. Inclosure 1 in No. 8. Decree of the Vice-Admiralty Court at Zanzibar. Her Majesty's ship 'Daphne' v. an Arab Dhow, name unknown. In the Instance Court of Vice-Admiralty of Zanzibar. IN the matter of Her Majesty's ship ' Daphne ' v. an Arab dhow, name unknown, before John Kirk, Esq., Acting Political Agent, Judge of the said Court, on the 28th day of June, 1869, Commander George Lydiard Sulivan, Lieutenant George Moncrieff Loch, Navigating Lieutenant George White, and Mr. William Henry Tozer, Acting Carpenter 3rd Class, of Her Majesty's ship ' Daphne,' personally appeared and produced before the said Judge the declarations hereunto annexed, and which set out the circumstances under which the dhow, name unknown, of the following dimensions, viz., length 65 feet, breadth 19 feet, girth 38 feet; poop, length 21 feet, breadth 18 feet, height 5 feet; of i08 , 65 tons; with a crew of twelve persons, besides five passengers and 18 men, 17 women, and 17 children, slaves (total 52 slaves), on board, was captured on the 16th day of May, 1869, by the said Her Majesty's ship ' Daphne,' being in latitude 13° 21' north, and longitude 53° 16' east, and after examining the said officers concerning the said declaration, and the said officers having prayed that the said Court should proceed to adjudicate in this matter, and whereas it appears to the said Judge of the Vice-Admiralty Court, that there is sufficient proof that the said Arab dhow, name unknown, of the dimensions hereinbefore certified, was actually engaged in the Slave Trade, and was, therefore, a lawful prize to17 the said ship 'Daphne;' and whereas it further appears to the said Judge that it was impracticable to bring the said vessel into port for adjudication, that the aforesaid Arab dhow was lawfully captured by the said Her Majesty's ship &lt;£ Daphne,' and was a lawful prize to the said vessel, and that it is further decreed and adjudged for the Captain and officers of the said vessel that they were justified in destroying the said dhow, and whereas the full number of 52 slaves have been landed and liberated at Seychelles. In testimony whereof I have signed the present Decree, and caused the seal of the Vice-Admiralty Court to be affixed thereto. (Signed) JOHN KIRK, Judge of the Vice-Admiralty Court at Zanzibar. I certify that no costs were incurred in this matter. Inclosure 2 in No. 8. Report of Surveyors. 'Daphne,' at Sea, May 16, 1869. IN accordance with your orders of this day's date, we, the Undersigned, have carefully surveyed the slave vessel detained by this ship, this day, and beg to report that we consider her to be unseaworthy. We have, &amp;c. (Signed) GEORGE M. LOCH, Lieutenant. GEORGE WHITE, Navigating Lieutenant. W. H. TOZER, Acting Carpenter, 3rd Class. To Commander G. L. Sulivan, Her Majesty's ship ' Daphne.' Inclosure 3 in No. 8. Certificate of Admeasurement. WE, the Undersigned, officers of Her Majesty's ship 'Daphne,' do hereby certify that we have carefully admeasured in the manner prescribed by Rule II of the 22nd section of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1854, the Arab dhow detained by Her Majesty's ship' ' Daphne,' on the 16th day of May, 1869, on the ground that she was engaged in and equipped for the Slave Trade, and we certify that her dimensions are as follows :— Feet. Length on upper deck from outside of plank at stem, to outside of plank at sternpost .. 65 Main breadth to outside of plank .. .. .. .. ,, ,, j 9 Girth of ship under the keel at main breadth from upper deck on one side of the ship, to the upper deck on the other .. .. .. .. .. .. 33 Tonnage:— Tons. Tonnage under tonnage-deck ,. .. .. .. ,, ,, 89 • 75 Closed-in space above tonnage-deck: poop length, 21 feet; breadth, 18 feet; height, 5 feet .. .. .. .. .. .. .. is-go Total .. .. .. .... .. 108*65 Signed this 16th day of May, 1869. (Signed) G. M. LOCH, Lieutenant. GEORGE WHITE, Navigating Lieutenant. W. H. TOZER, Acting Carpenter, 3rd Class. (Approved) Geo. Sulivan, Commander, Commanding Her Majesty's ship ' Daphne.' Inclosure 4 in No. 8. Certificate as to the Destruction of the Vessel. I, THE Undersigned, George Lydiard Sulivan, holding the rank of Commander in Her Britannic Majesty's Navy, and commanding Her Majesty's ship ' Daphne,' do hereby certify that on the 16th day of May, 1869, I directed a survey on board the Arab dhow, [410J . F18 name unknown, detained by me on the 16th day of May, 1869, on the ground that she was engaged in and equipped for the Slave Trade, and that the Surveying Officers have reported to me that the said Arab dhow, name unknown, is not in a sufficiently seaworthy condition to be sent to a port of adjudication, as from the Report of Survey annexed hereto will more fully appear : the said vessel has been destroyed by my order, this 16th day of May, 1869. (Signed) GEO. L. SULIVAN, Commander, Commanding Her Majesty's ship 'Daphne' Inclosure 5 m No. 8. Certificate as to the State of the Prize at the time of Detention. I, THE Undersigned, George Lydiard Sulivan, holding the rank of Commander in Her Britannic Majesty's Navy, and commanding Her Majesty's ship ' Daphne,' do hereby certify that, in exercise of the authority vested in me, I did, on the 16th day of May, 1869, at sea latitude 13° 21' north, longitude 53° 16'east, detain an Arab dhow, name unknown, on the ground that she was engaged in and equipped for the Slave Trade. And I further certify that she had on board at the time a crew of twelve persons, five passengers, and thirty-five male and seventeen female slaves. And I further certify that my reason for detaining her was that she had fifty-two slaves on board. (Signed) GEO. L. SULIVAN, Commander, Commanding Her Majesty's ship ' Daphne.' Inclosure 6 in No. 8. Receipt. Port Mahe, Seychelles, June 7, 1869. RECEIVED from Commander G. L. Sulivan, of Her Majesty's ship 'Daphne,' eighteen men, thirteen women, four girls, and seventeen boys, liberated Africans. (Signed) SWINBURNE WARD, Her Majesty's Civil Commissioner. No. 9. Mr. Hamilton to Mr. Otway.—{Received August 31.) Sir, Treasury Chambers, August 30, 1869. I AM directed by the Lords Commissioners of Her Majesty's Treasury to state, for the information of Lord Clarendon, that Mr. Rothery has drawn the attention of this Board to a correspondence between himself and the Foreign Office respecting the proceedings of Her Majesty's Consul at Zanzibar in connection with certain captures made by Her Majesty's ship ' Nympheand to state that my Lords fully concur in the observations made by Mr. Rothery in his letter of 23rd August. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) GEO. A. HAMILTON. No. 10. Mr. Hamilton to Mr. Otway.—{Received September 7.) Si r &gt; Treasury Chambers, September 6, 1869. I AM directed by the Lords Commissioners of Her Majesty's Treasury to transmit to you, herewith, for the information of Lord Clarendon, with reference to your letter of the 21st July last, copy of Report from Mr. Rothery respecting the dhows lately captured by Her Majesty's ships 'Peterel' and 'Nymphe,' and also copy of letter to the Admiralty on the subject. My Lords are disposed to concur with Mr. Rothery in his opinion with regard to19 round that she .g Officers have ently seaworthy- Survey annexed •der. ommander, :ip ' Daphn Commander in hne,' do hereby y of May, 1869, name unknown, Ive persons, five le had fifty-two mmander, ,ip ' Daphne.' June 7, 1869. ;hip ' Daphne,' deans. WARD, Commissioner. mst 30, 1869. ury to state, for .ttention of this respecting the n captures made r concur in the 1AMILTON. mber 6, 1869, 'y to transmit to our letter of the tely captured by o the Admiralty with regard to these captures, and they will be prepared to take steps for carrying out his suggestions on learning the opinion of Lord Clarendon on the subject. I am, &amp;c (Signed) GEO. A. HAMILTON; Inclosure 1 in No. 10. Report by Mr. Rothery respecting Dhows lately Captured by Her Majesty's ships 'Peterel' and ' Nymphe.' To the Right Hon the Lords Commissioners of Her Majesty's Treasury. May it please your Lordships, IN obedience to your Lordships' commands I have perused and considered the documents herewith returned, consisting of a letter from the Honourable Charles Spring Rice, dated the Foreign Office, 21st of July ultimo, transmitting copy of two despatches of the 21st and 22nd of May last respectively, with their inclosures in original from John Kirk, Esq., the Acting British Consul at Zanzibar, reporting the proceedings which had taken place in the Vice-Admiralty Court established in that island in the cases of two slave dhows captured and destroyed by Her Majesty's ships 'Peterel' and 'Nymphe' respectively, on suspicion of being engaged in the Slave Trade. In transmitting these papers Mr. Spring Rice states that Lord Clarendon would be glad to receive any observations which your Lordships' legal adviser upon Slave Trade matters may have to offer upon the ca&amp;es to which the papers relate. He adds that in one of the cases that destroyed by the ' Nymphe,' where the vessel belonged to the Governor of Moubas, judgment had been given in the Vice-Admiralty Court against the captors, and that Lord Clarendon fears that if the practice of destroying vessels suspected of being engaged in the Slave Trade which now prevails to a great extent on the East Coast of Africa is continued, not only will it give rise to large pecuniary claims on Her Majesty's Government, but in some instances vessels may be destroyed, and their owners, from not knowing where their case will be adjudicated, may be unable to obtain a hearing and defend their property, and that this injustice will be done to honest traders, a state of things, he observes, which it is on every account the object of Her Majesty's Government to avoid. The first of Mr. Kirk's despatches, that of the 21st of May, relates to the capture by the ' Peterel,' of which he states, that he had as yet received no official information, but at the express desire of the Sultan of Zanzibar, the evidence of the master and supercargo of the dhow had been taken before the Acting Consul on the 12th and 15th of May last. According to this evidence, and the other documents forwarded in Mr. Kirk's despatch, the dhow was the property of Abdulla-bin-Alarve, a Dolab, then lately deceased, who is described by another witness as having for many years dealt largely with Messrs. Oswald and Co., whose agent at Zanzibar was also the agent for winding up Abdulla's estate. The dhow, it seems, had sailed from Zanzibar with a crew of twenty sailors, of whom six were freemen and fourteen slaves. Some of the slaves, by the master's account, had been with him on former voyages. They were supplied by the owner and received a little pay; the freemen had been engaged by the master himself. There were also ten passengers, one of whom, a girl, was the supercargo's domestic slave, who had come to him, as he said, with his wife at the time of their marriage, and had been bought many years previously. The dhow had a cargo of 500 kegs of powder, 85 bales of American cloth, 5 bundles of kaniki, and 6 boxes of Kutch goods; the total value of which, as shown in a paper inclosed by Mr. Kirk, and drawn up by Messrs. Oswald and Co.'s agent at Zanzibar, from the statements of those on board, was 2,931 dollars 28 cents; in addition to which, the passengers had goods of their own, valued at 105 dollars. In the same document, the price of the vessel is given as 700 dollars. She had, it is said, a pass from the Sultan, and was bound with her cargo and passengers for Madagascar, to buy ebony, hides, and bees'-wax. After a voyage of twelve or fourteen days, in the course of which the vessel stopped at Quiloa and took in a few baskets of corn, she arrived at a place called Mosimbata near Cape Delgado. Near this place she fell in with a steamer, apparently the ' Peterel,' whose boat or boats boarded the dhow about 9 a.m ., but on what day the accompanying papers do not state. ■ t il I j I20 It is said that the Sultan's pass, which was in Arabic, was shown to the officers of the boat, but was torn up by them, and that the officers asked why the dhow had no pass from the Consul, and said that she could not go to Madagascar. The dhow was then taken alongside the ship, to which her goods were transferred, the dhow's crew and passengers being told to keep their personal effects. The mast, boat, and fittings were also taken out, with everything that was of use, after which the dhow was set on fire. The supercargo states that there was no interpreter among the ship's people, but that one of the dhow's men could speak with them, and explained what they said. The ' Peterel ' then steamed away to Mambi, where the dhow's crew and passengers were landed for five days, while the ship was refitting, their request to be taken to Comoro or Madagascar being refused. Eventually the ' Peterel' took them to Mozambique, where there was lying a steam-vessel called ' Tynemouth,' belonging to Hassan Bey, and bound to Zanzibar. The supercargo states that they were asked to pay 4 rupees each for their passage, but as they had no money, the captain of the man-of-war arranged for their passage, and supplied them with some biscuit and cloth for the voyage. None, even of the slaves, it is said, were retained on board the ' Peterel,' and the master of the dhow adds that the slaves were then working as before, as sailors, and had gone some ten or fifteen days before to Pemba, in another dhow belonging to the same owner. Of this evidence Mr. Kirk observes that in his opinion it confirms the suspicions on which the officers of the ' Peterel' seem to have acted. He states that on the return of the dhow's crew to Zanzibar, due notice was given that anv appeal or statement must be made in time to be sent in the ' Tynemouth ' to the Cape of Good Hope, where, in all probability, their case would be tried before the Vice-Admiralty Court; but that His Highness and those concerned neglected the opportunity, although the vessel remained at Zanzibar for nearly a month, and Mr. Kirk adds that he had warned those interested that by this wilful neglect of the proper steps for their self-defence, they had, in his opinion, forfeited all right to be again heard. It would appear, however, that the Sultan of Zanzibar has expressed his dissatisfac tion at the destruction of the dhow, and insists upon the fact that none of those who were on board the dhow were ever suspected by the ' Peterel' to be slaves, for that they were all, including the female slave, sent back to Zanzibar, and he contends, therefore, that it could not be on the ground of having had a slave on board that this dhow was destroyed, but for some other reason to him unknown; and Mr. Kirk states that His Highness desires to be informed what the grounds were on which the vessel of his subject has been burned, and if condemned in the Vice-Admiralty Court at the Cape, the reason why. 1 must confess that, on view of the evidence as reported by Mr. Kirk, the Sultan's dissatisfaction with the proceedings of the captors in this case appears to be far from unreasonable. Except the presence on board of the slaves, of whom 14 are said to have been employed as sailors, not only at that time, but on former and subsequent voyages, and the other is stated to have been a domestic slave purchased many years previously; the nCe j e ^ n( ^ a PP ear disclose any plausible ground even for the detention of this ow; and, if that were really the ground of detention, the captors were bound, unless unavoidably prevented, to send all the slaves to the port of adjudication. Nor, again, would the fact that there were slaves on board be enough to justifv the seizure, unless there were also reason to suppose that thev had been shipped for exporta tion, which is direct y contradicted, not only by the evidence of the master and the supercargo, but by the conduct of the captors themselves. At present, however, vour -Lordships are in possession of an ex parte statement only, and it would be evidentlv premature to express a decided opinion upon the case. Possibly the demeanour of the witnesses and other circumstances attending their raammation may ha'e been such as to throw doubt upon their evidence, and to lead Mr. Kirk to the conclusion that the dhow was engaged in a questionable voyage- but 4S^«pllation 006 al0ne ' the COndUCt 0f the ca P tors oertainl y ^ Of the second case, that of the dhow captured by the ' Nymphe,' fuller details are g'ven in the accompanymg papers It came before Mrf Kirk, as Acting Judge of the W vessel resulted ln a decree for the restitution of the captured vessel. Ihe crcumstauces, as tney appear from Mr. Kirk's letter of the 22nd of Mav and the inclosure therein, are as follows A Mombas Arab named Ali bin Wassur, also described in these paners as the Governor of Mombas, had sent a dhow to Zanzibar, with instructions to agent, an21 Indian merchant named Laka Kangi, living there under British protection, either to sell or charter her, at his discretion. Not finding a purchaser, he chartered her to a company of Mombas Arabs, who placed on board a valuable cargo of cloth and powder, and sailed in her for Lindi, a port about fifty miles south of Quiloa. After landing part of their cargo at Quiloa, they proceeded on their voyage; but on passing Kiswara harbour, about twenty miles farther to the south, they ran out of watjr, having met, it is said, with contrary winds. On entering the bay they were seen by Her Majesty's ship ' Nymphe,' Edward Spicer Meara, Esq., Commander; and being ordered to go on board, they lowered their boat and . did so. It would seem that Commander Meara, and most of the officers, were then in the boats near shore; but on his return to the ship, the dhow was examined, and it being found that, of 42 persons who were on board, 6 were slaves; she was detained on the ground that she was engaged in the Slave Trade. A pass which she carried from the Sultan is eaid to have been destroyed by the captors. The detention seems to have taken place on the 3rd of April last, and on the 5th of that month, or, as would appear from Mr. Kirk's despatch, on the next day after the detention. Three of the ' Nymphe's ' officers who surveyed the dhow having reported that she was not in a sufficiently seaworthy condition to be sent to a port of adjudication, she was, after being measured, destroyed by command of Meara's orders; the passengers and crew of the dhow were then sent on shore, excepting the six slaves and three of the crew, who refused to land, and were carried by the captors to Zanzibar. The case was brought before the Acting Consul as Judge of the Vice-Admiralty Court at Zanzibar on the 14th of April last, at the suit of Commander Meara. It was defended by the Sultan's agent. It was contended that the dhow was liable to condemnation on the following grounds:— 1. Because she had 6 slaves on board, some of whom it was alleged were to be sold at Ugao, the region between Cape Delgado and Rovuma. 2. Because the goods and merchandize on board were intended for the purchase of slaves. 3. Because she had on board slave papers and lists of slaves. But on all these grounds the captor's case seems to have entirely failed. On examination of the papers found on board, it appeared that the greater part consisted of native correspondence on matters of business, which had no reference in any way to the Slave Trade. Amongst other documents produced in Court was a translation of the Sultan's pass, the original having, it would seem, been destroyed by the captors at the time of the detention. There were, indeed, two slave lists on board; but these were respectively a year and a-half and eight months old, both of them, as Mr. Kirk remarks, having been made out at a time when slavingVas allowed by Treaty along 500 miles of the Zanzibar coast; and Mr. Kirk observes that it was the duty of the interpreter to have pointed out the dates to the captors ; but that it appeared in Court that he could read neither Arabic nor Sowahili, and could not translate the Sultan's pass, which he had himself assisted to destroy. As to the goods and merchandize there seems to have been no sort of proof that they were intended for the purchase of slaves. There only remained the fact that 6 slaves had been found on board. But from their evidence in Court it was clearly proved that they were, and long had been, domestic slaves in the service of the merchant passengers. It was further argued by the Sultan's Agent that the dhow had a pass from His Highness granted in due form ; that she was on a voyage from Mpmbas to Zanzibar, and thence to Ugao, where she was to buy grain, oil, and copal; that the Arab agents for the sale of the cargo were on board ; that the 6 slaves found on board were only the necessary attendants of the Arab merchants; and that the idea of taking slaves from Mombas and Zanzibar to Ugao was as absurd as to take English goods to England for sale, an argument in which Mr. Kirk seems to have fully concurred. In reply. Commander Meara could only fall back on the wording of a single clause in his instructions, which specifies the presence of slaves on board as one of the grounds for detaining a vessel. No other ground appears to have been advanced by the captor ; and after a very careful examination of the evidence, Mr. Kirk came to the conclusion (and I do not see how he could have arrived at any other) that the dhow was not engaged in the Slave Trade, and that there was not any proof that she was intended for it; but, on the contrary, that she was a legal trader. And seeing that the vessel had been destroyed at so short a distance from Zanzibar, in a case where there was so little proof, and that she had been taken with a valuable cargo on board in one of the Sultan's harbours, he pronounced the summary destruction of the dhow was unwarrantable, and that her owners were entitled to compensation for the loss of the property and goods, [410] ' G22 Such then are the facts of these two cases, so far as they are present known to your Lordships'; and there are several questions that arise out of them, and which deserve your Lordship's most serious consideration. T • .i, , The first to which I would wish to call your Lordship s attention, is the ground alleged by Captain Meara in the second of the two cases under consideration for capturing and' destroying the dhow, namely, the presence on hoard her of some domestic slaves; and as a justification for so doing, he refers to the 51st Section of the Slave Trade Instruc- tions, which declares that an officer will be justified in concluding that a vessel is engaged in or equipped for the Slave Trade if he finds any slaves on board. It is hardly necessary to observe that as a general rule it is unsafe to rely upon a single clause without reference to the context or to the general scope of the Instructions, and that such a course must almost necessarily lead to the greatest absurdities. But in the present case it appears to me that Commander Meara has confused two things which are essentially different, namely) slavery and the Slave Trade. The clause on which he relies is taken from Instructions issued in 1865 to the Commanders of Her Majesty s_ships employed in the suppression of the Slave Trade ; not instructions for ,the suppression of slavery, but of the Slave Trade, or, in other words, the illegal transport of negroes for the purpose of consigning them to slavery, and of selling them as slaves. The instructions speak throughout of the Slave Trade, not of slavery. And here I may observe that so far as foreign nations are concerned, we have no right, nor do the Instructions authorize our naval officers to interfere with the domestic institution of slavery, or with the employment of domestic slaves in such manner as the laws of the country allow. All that the Instructions seek to do is to direct naval officers how to deal with any vessels, which they may meet, suspected of being engaged in or equipped for the Slave Trade. It is true that the section in question says that a vessel may be presumed to be engaged in the Slave Trade if there are found on board any slaves, and that it does not add that the slaves are to be those only who are being transported for the purpose of being consigned into slavery and sold as slaves; but surely such a limitation is unnecessary in Instructions referring exclusively to the suppression of the Slave Trade. Indeed I should have thought that no one, much less a naval officer, could have so misinterpreted the Instructions were it not that in a recent case, that of the ' Dahomey,' the capturing officer alleged as a ground for seizing and sending in for adjudication a Portuguese vessel, consigned with a cargo of palm-oil to this country, the fact that she had at the time on board three domestic slaves, who had been engaged to assist in shipping and unshipping the cargo. If, as I observed in that case, such a principle were once admitted, it would justify the seizure and condemnation of almost every British vessel entering the ports of a country in which slavery at the time existed. It is, however, not necessary that I should say more on this point, as your Lordships appear, from Mr. Hamilton's letter to me of the 12th instant, to have taken the same view of this question. But if the idea generally prevails amongst naval officers that they are entitled to capture any vessel, on board of which they may happen to find a domestic slave, on the ground that the vessel is engaged in carrying on the Slave Trade, it would be matter for consideration whether a circular ought not to be at once sent by the Admiralty to all the commanding officers engaged in the suppression of the Slave Trade, instructing them as to their duties on this point. Another point which seems to deserve your Lordships' attention is the statement that in both these cases, the Sultan's pass was destroyed by the officers of the capturing ship. If this was really done, it is conduct deserving of the strongest censure; for the only object of destroying the pass would seem to be to remove the best evidence of the lawful character of the dhow, and to afford some apparent justification for what would, in that case, have been grossly illegal acts of the captors in seizing and destroying her. Moreover, it is in direct violation of the Instructions issued to the commanders of vessels engaged in the suppression of the Slave Trade, which are very precise on this point. Section 58 directs the capturing officer to cause all the vessels' papers to be numbered and lettered consecutively, and a certificate thereof to be at once drawn up. Section 69 directs him to deliver the vessels' papers to the prize officer charged to take the vessel into port; and section 85 orders the prize officer to deliver them all into Court. There could therefore be no justification for the destruction of the Sultan's pass in either of these cases ; and if capturing officers will so entirely disregard their Instructions, and commit acts of so illegal and unjustifiable a character, they must not be surprised if your Lordships should hereafter refuse to relieve them from the necessary consequences of their misconduct. A still more important point, however, and to which it is necessary that I should call your Lordships' attention, is the practice which appears to prevail on the East Coast ofknown to your jh deserve your is the ground &gt;n for capturing lomestic slaves; : Trade Instruc- issel is ens to rely upon a he Instructions, •dities. But in 0 things which se on which he Majesty's ships suppression of negroes for the rhe instructions erned, we have srfere with the slaves in such ;ek to do is to et, suspected of the section in ! Trade if there are to be those lavery and sold ring exclusively it no one, much that in a recent for seizing and palm-oil to this , who had been d in that case, nation of almost e time existed. Drdships appear, ime view of this ;hey are entitled nestic slave, on ie, it would be y the Admiralty ade, instructing 3 the statement f the capturing :ensure; for the evidence of the for what would, destroying her. nders of vessels ; on this point, e numbered and action 69 directs 1 the vessel into Sultan's pass in eir Instructions, , be surprised if ry consequences lat I should call le East Coast of 23 Africa, of immediately destroying a dhow, after what I may call a kind of pro formd survey has been held upon her, and she has been reported unfit to proceed to a port of adjudication. The practice has become so universal that it is rarely or ever that a captured vessel is not burnt or destroyed within two or three days of her capture. There might possibly have been some excuse for such a practice when the nearest ports of adjudication were the Cape of Good Hope or the Mauritius; but there is no such excuse at present, for, for several years past, there has been a Vice-Admiralty Court established at Aden; and since August 1866, jurisdiction to try vessels captured in or brought into Zanzibar waters has been given by Order in Council to the British Consul at Zanzibar. It is certainly difficult to believe that vessels, immediately on their being captured, should be generally found to be incapable of completing the very voyages on which they were at the time engaged; but such would seem to be the case, if the certificates of unseaworthiness given by the capturing officers are to be relied upon. Moreover, naval officers seem to overlook the fact that, if the vessel was not sufficiently seaworthy to perform a voyage to Zanzibar from the place at which she was captured, it would be very strong evidence that her master and crew could have had no intention of shipping a cargo of slaves for conveyance to that, or possibly a much more distant, port. Take, for instance, the two cases under consideration. In the first of them the vessel had sailed from Zanzibar, having on board a crew of twenty sailors and ten passengers, and laden with a valuable cargo. She had been twelve or fourteen days out, and at the time bound to Madagascar. Is it conceivable that such a vessel was, at the time of her capture, not in a fit state to return to Zanzibar ? And yet the captors destroyed her, on the ground that she was not seaworthy. In the second case, that captured by the ' Nymphe,' the vessel had come from Mombas to Zanzibar, there a valuable cargo consisting of cloth and powder had been put on board of her, and she sailed with a crew and passengers of forty-two persons in all for Lindi, a port about fifty miles to the south of Quiloa. After landing a portion of her cargo at Quiloa she proceeded to the southward, but finding that she was running short of water she put into Kiswara Harbour, about twenty miles south of Quiloa, and on entering the bay was captured by the ' Nymphe.' And yet this vessel also was destroyed immediately on her capture, on the ground that she was not in a sufficiently seaworthy condition to be navigated to a port of adjudication. But is it credible that a vessel with a valuable cargo and forty-two souls on board, bound on a voyage to Lindi and thence back to Zanzibar, was not in a sufficiently seaworthy condition to be taken back to Zanzibar ? Nor can it be here pleaded, as in the case of domestic slaves found on board a dhow, that the instructions to cruizers are not sufficiently clear on the point, for the 390th section of the Slave Trade Instructions, p. 98, is as follows:—'If you have detained a Zanzibar vessel upon suspicion, and are unable to send her into the proper port of adjudication, you will not destroy her without (if practicable) having first ascertained at the nearest Zanzibar port, by inquiries from Her Majesty's Consul and others, that she was engaged in or equipped for the Slave Trade.' In the second case, therefore, at least where the vessel was captured in Kiswara, one of the Sultan's ports, the duty of the captor, if the dhow was not seaworthy, was to have left her there in charge of the authorities whilst he made inquiries into her character. And it is the more remarkable that this was not done in the present case, as it appears that the ' Nymphe,' after destroying the dhow, went straight to Zanzibar, carrying with her a portion of the persons found on board her, and there instituted proceedings before the Consul to obtain her condemnation. The evil, however, has now become so great that it is necessary to consider whether some means cannot be taken to put a stop to it; and it appears to me that possibly this might be done by making some alteration in regard to the bounties. Your Lordships are aware that it has hitherto been the practice, in addition to the usual slave or tonnage bounties, to award an additional bounty of 1/. 10s. a ton wherever the vessel has been broken up and entirely destroyed. The grounds upon which the additional bounty is granted, are as follow :—Formerly, when a vessel was condemned for being engaged in the Slave Trade, she was sold as she then stood, with all her equipments and furniture. As, however, the slavers were at that time of a peculiar construction, built to sail fast and to carry light cargoes, it was found that when sold after condemnation they were almost invariably bought by the slave dealers, and were employed over and over again in the Slave Trade. Accordingly, it was determined that all slavers after condemnation, instead of being sold whole, should be broken up, and the materials thereof publicly sold in separate parts. Objection, however, was taken that this would materially affect the interest of the captors, who were entitled to the net pro ceeds realized from the sale of the prizes after payment of the expenses of condemnation, and it was urged that a vessel fully equipped and in sailing condition must necessarily I t i mirealize much more than the same vessel when broken up and sold in separate parts; accordingly it was decided that, as a compensation to the captors for the loss which they would sustain by the vessels' being broken up, there should be paid to them, in addition to the net proceeds realized from the sale of the materials, a bounty of 1Z. 10s. a ton on the tonnage of the vessel. The first Act, which was passed granting this additional bounty, was the 1 and 2 Vict, cap. 47. This, however, applied only to vessels captured under aTreaty or Convention with come foreign Power ; but other Acts were subsequently passed, extending the same pro vision to all other description of capture. The words in the different Acts are the same, they provide that, where the vessel ' shall have been or shall be entirely demolished, and the materials thereof publicly sold in separate parts, as well as her cargo,' there shall be paid, in addition to the net proceeds, a bounty of 1/. 10s. a ton on the tonnage of the vessel. Now, if we are to look strictly to the words of the Act of Parliament, the only cases in which, properly speaking, the additional bounty would be payable, would be those in which the vessels had been brought into port, broken up, ' and the materials thereof publicly sold in separate parts.' Thpse were the cases, which the Act was intended to meet, and not the cases of vessels destroyed by the captors at ssa. Now it should be observed that, when the Act of the 1 and 2 Vict., cap. 27, was passed, slavers when captured were almost invariably sent into port for adjudication; but cases sometimes occurred in which the slaver having been run ashore to avoid capture, was entirely destroyed, or where, after an action she became so disabled as to be incapable of being taken into port. And in such cases it was thought that the captors were entitled to the grant of the additional bounty of 1/. 10s. a ton on the tonnage of the vessel, although ie the materials thereof had not been publicly sold in separate parts.'' Subsequently, under the influence of the strong prejudice which prevailed in favour of the captors of slave vessels, the construction of the Act was still further extended, and the additional bounty came to be granted in all cases in which the vessel was destroyed, whether the vessel had been brought into port or not. And the only case now in which the additional bounty is not granted, is that in which the vessel having been taken into Her Majesty's service, the appraised value thereof is paid to the captors. It will be seen then, from what has been said, that the captors receive the additional bounty of 1/. 10s. a ton whenever the vessel is destroyed, and that too in cases which were not only not contemplated at the time of the passing of the Act, but which are not even covered by the words of the Act if strictly construed. The captors, then, receiving the additional bounty, whether the vessel is brought in or not, and the proceeds which would be realized from the sale of the materials being very trifling, they not unnaturally prefer to destroy the vessels rather than have the trouble of bringing them into port for adjudica tion ; and this too, although their instructions are, as I have shown, most precise upon the point, especially in the case of Zanzibar vessels. The only remedy then that I can see for so unsatisfactory a state of things is, not to grant to the captors the additional bounty of 1Z. 10s. a ton except in the cases con templated by the Act, namely, those in which the vessel has been brought into port, and there entirely demolished, and the materials thereof sold in separate parts. If this were done, I doubt not that many vessels, which are now thought not to be sufficiently sea worthy, would in some way or other be taken to the port of adjudication. Probably your Lordships might after so long a course of practice, hesitate without a fresh enactment, to put this construction on the Statute, and to withhold from the captors the grant of the additional bounty in cases such as those now under consideration, although I am strongly inclined to think that according to the strict wording of the Act you would be entitled to do so. But at all events, it would be a matter for consideration whether it would not be proper that an Act should be introduced at the earliest possible period, limiting the grant of the bounties as I have proposed, and in the meantime the most stringent directions should be given to naval officers engaged in the suppression of the Slave Trade on the East Coast, not on any account to destroy the vessels they may capture without the most urgent necessity. In immediate connection with this part of the subject, is the practice which prevails of landing the crews and even the passengers, of these Arab dhows upon the coast, and without any regard to their safety or convenience. Such a practice can hardly be sufficiently reprobated—nor again in this case can naval officers plead that their instructions are not sufficiently precise. The sixty-sixth section of the Slave Trade Instructions (p. 25) is in these words: ' You will send in the vessel to the port of adjudication all the cargo slaves, passengers, the master, mate, or boatswain, the cook or other person belon^mL' to the vessel previously charged with feeding the slaves, and if practicable, the whole of the crew. If, however, it is impracticable for you to send in the vessel the whole of the crewyou will send at least two or three of them, and forward the remainder by the first opportunity. Now let us see how the captors treated the crews and passeneers in the two cases under consideration. In the first case, the vessel having been destroyed, the crew and passengers it is said, requested to be landed either at Comoro or at Madagascar, to which the vessel was bound, but the captors refused, and instead thereof, put them on shore at Mozambique, whence they tound their way in a merchant steam-vessel, the 'Tynemouth,' to Zanzibar The capturing vessel herself went on, Mr. Kirk thinks, to the Cape of Good Hope. In the second case, out of forty-two passengers and crew all included, the ' Nymphe,' took six domestic slaves, and three of the crew, who refused to go on shore, to Zanzibar, the rest were apparently sent ashore, and of thes^ Mr. Kirk says, only one had up to the date of his despatch, yet reached Zanzibar; so that, although the case had been heard, and the vessel and cargo notwithstanding the absence of the principal persons on board, ordered to be restored with costs and damages, Mr. Kirk states that he had as yet not been able, owing to the absence of the owners to make up the claims. It is difficult to imagine anything more calculated to bring discredit on this country and upon her naval officers, than the perpetration of acts such as those that are attributed to the capturing vessels in these two cases; namely, to seize vessels engaged in lawful commerce, burn them, land the passengers and crew upon a barbarous coast, and then sail or steam off to some distant port to obtain behind the backs of the owners a condemnation of the vessel as a slaver. Mr. Kirk appears to have thought in the case of the ' Peterel s prize, that it was the duty of the owner of the vessel and cargo, to have forwarded by the 'Tynemouth' to the Cape of Good Hope, evidence in their defence, and that by not doing so, they have forfeited all right to be heard. I confess, however, that I do not take so unfavourable a view of these persons' conduct. I will ask how were these semi-civilized Arabs to know that the Commander of the ' Peterel' intended to institute proceedings for the condemnation of the vessel at the Cape of Good Hope ' How could they have known that he would not go to Aden, to the Mauritius, or to have even waited until his return to bring his case before the High Court of Admiralty of England ? The supercargo says that they tried to find out the name of the captain and of the ship, but could not; how then could they know where she was going, and much less where she would institute proceedings for the'condemnation of this vessel? Assuming however, that the owner had ascertained the name of the ship of war, and that the proceedings were to be instituted at the Cape of Good Hope—in what form should the evidence have been sent so that it would have been admissible before the Court ? to whom could it have been sent ? and how could the owner have instructed an agent to defend his interest on the trial ? I confess that all these questions appear to me to be extremely difficult to answer. If it be said that the owner should have sent an agent down to the Cape of Good Hope to defend his interests, it must be remembered that the distance between Zanzibar and the Cape is nearer 3,000 than 2,000 miles, and that to an inhabitant of the tropical climate of Zanzibar, a journey to the Cape with its comparatively cold climate and stormy seas would appear to be full of the greatest dangers and difficulties. It seems to me that it would be as reasonable to require the owner of a British coasting vessel, which had been captured and destroyed in the channel by a Zanzibar ship of war, (if such there were), to go before a tribunal in Zanzibar or Madagascar to protect his interests, telling him at the same time that if he did not do so quickly, his vessel would be forfeited beyond redemption, and that possibly with all his dispatch he might not arrive in time to prevent it. I doubt whether the British shipowner would be altogether satisfied with so scant a measure of justice. The only mode in which it seems to me that such proceedings can be stopped is by forbidding naval officers to institute proceedings for the condemnation of these Arab dhows m distant ports. And now that the British Consul at Zanzibar has by the recent Act, the 32 and 33 Vict., cap. 75, full jurisdiction to entertain all such cases, it appears to metha't no possible inconvenience can result from such an order being given. Zanzibar is a central point both for the captors and the captured ; it is, I believe, a port to which our cruizers m those seas are in the frequent habit of resorting, .and is a port either of call or of departure for most of the Arab dhows. It certainly appears to me that our cruizers ought not to be allowed to institute proceedings in the Vice-Admiralty Courts of the Cape of Good Hope or the Mauritius to obtain the condemnation of any Arab vessels that they may have captured and destroyed in or near the territories of the Sultan of Zanzibar; and it may even be a matter for consideration whether Aden, which is some 2,000 miles from Zanzibar, may not be too distant a port, except in the case of vessels captured very far to the north of Zanzibar. If, however, captors were compelled, instead of destroving the [410] H '26 vessels that they might capture, to send them in for adjudication, together with all the crew and passengers, they would soon find which was the most convenient port both for the captors and the captured. j u iv/r ir- i i,- u ri • a There is another circumstance mentioned by Mr. Kirk which likewise deserves your Lordships' serious consideration. He says at the conclusion of his letter of the 22nd May that he had 'just received from the Bombay Government thirty-six freemen—negroes, but sailors who had been passed to Bombay from Aden among the sixty slaves taken last vear by Her Majesty's ship ' Star,' near Brava;' and he adds, 'it is very singular, indeed, that upwards of half the so-called slaves should have to be sent back at Government expense to Zanzibar, after the dhows from which they had been freed have been condemned.' The cases to which Mr. Kirk refers are no doubt the twenty-four dhows captured in November 1868, at Brava and Morka, which were all condemned at Aden on the 13th of January last, and upon which I have recently reported to your Lordships. The circumstance mentioned by Mr. Kirk seems to raise a question whether these dhows were properlv condemned, and it may be a question for your Lordship's consideration whether you will not recommend to the Lords of the Admiralty that the distribution of the bounties in those cases should be stopped until inquiries shall have been made not only of the Commander of the ' Star,' but also at Aden, Bombay, and Zanzibar into the facts stated b) M In conclusion I would beg to observe that the matter to which Lord Clarendon has called your Lordship's attention appears to me to be deserving of the most serious consideration ; for if the system which appears to prevail on the East Coast of Africa is continued, not only as Lord Clarendon observes, will it give rise to large pecuniary claims upon Her Majesty's Government, but in some instances vessels may be destroyed, and the owners, from not knowing where their case will be adjudicated, may be unable to obtain a hearing and defend their interests, and thus injustice be done to honest traders, a state of things which it is on every account the object of Her Majesty's Government to prevent. It only remains for me to say that, should your Lordships concur in the opinions that I have ventured to express, it will be proper that copies of this Report should be sent to Lord Clarendon, as well as to the Lords of the Admiralty, and that the Commanders of Her Majesty's ships Peterel' and ' Nymphe ' and ' Star ' should be called upon for such explanations as they may be able to give of their proceedings in the several matters which have been respectively alleged against them, their attention being at the same time called to the 58th, 66th, 69th, and 390th sections of the Slave Trade Instructions, which require the capturing officer to preserve all the vessel's papers ; to send the vessel and all the crew and passengers, together with the papers, to the port of adjudication ; and in the case of a Zanzibar vessel, expressly prohibit him from destroying her until he has first ascertained at the nearest Zanzibar port, by inquiries from Her Majesty's Consul or others, that the vessel was actually engaged in or equipped for the Slave Trade. It might also be well that further inquiries should be made both at Aden and at Zanzibar as to the persons stated to have been captured as slaves by the ' Star,' and subsequently sent back to Zanzibar. All which is most humbly submitted to your Lordships wisdom. (Signed) H. C. ROTHERY. Doctors' Commons, August 21, 1869. Inclosure 2 in !No. 10. Mr. Hamilton to the Secretary to the Admiralty. Sir, Treasury Chambers, September 4, 1869. 1 AM directed by the Lords Commissioners of Her Majesty's Treasury to transmit to you herewith, for the information of the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty, copy of Report from Mr. Rothery, respecting the capture of certain dhows by Her Majesty's ships ' Peterel' and ' Nymphe.' My Lords consider that there is much force in thie observations made by Mr. Rothery, and thev would be glad to be furnished with any remarks which the Board of Admiralty may wish to make on the general subjects referred to in the Report. In the meantime, my Lords request that the Board of Admiralty will, if practicable, issue immediate instructions for postponing any of the payments to the officers, &amp;c., of Her Majesty's ship ' Star,'' on account of tonnage-bounty, which have formed the subject of correspondence from the Department within the last few months; and that they will call for explanations from the officers in command of Her Majesty's ship 'Peterel,' 3' Nymphe,' and ' Star,' with reference to the cases which are specially referred to as suggested by Mr. Rothery. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) GEO. A. HAMILTON. No. 11. The Secretary to the Admiralty to Mr. Hammond.—(Received September 16.) Sir, Admiralty, September 15, 1869. I AM commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit, for the information of the Earl of Clarendon, the inclosed correspondence (in original) forwarded by Commodore Sir Leopold Heath, in his letter dated Trincomalee, 14th July, respecting a dhow captured in the Persian Gulf by Commander Columb, of Her Majesty's ship ' Dryad,' and condemned as a lawful prize in the Vice-Admiralty Court at Aden. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) VERNON LUSH1NGTON. Inclosure 1 in No. 11. Lieutenant-Colonel Pelly to the Secretary to Government, Bombay. Si rj British Residency, Bushire, April 12, 1869. I HAVE the honour to transmit a copy of a letter, with accompaniment, received from the First Assistant Resident, Bassadore, reporting the alleged destruction of a Persian craft near Mogoo by Her Majesty's steamer ' Dryad.' 2. Mogoo, the port whence the Persian Governor protests, is about twenty-five miles distant from Lingah, and fifty miles from Bassadore. 3. The Persian Governor appears also to be protesting to his own Government, and, as providing for any reference which Her Majesty's Minister at Tehran may make, I am instructing the First Assistant Resident at Bassadore, and the British Agent at Lingah, to collect whatever evidence may be available. I have, &amp;c. (Signed; LEWIS PELLY. Inclosure 2 in No. 11. Captain Way to Lieutenant-Colonel Pelly. gj r Bassadore, March 29, 1869. I HAVE this day telegraphed to you the following:— ' 'Dryad,' when en route to Bushire, burnt a bugla belonging to Mogoo. Governor has protested.' , t » • • i. a I have now the honour to submit the Governor's letter to the British Agent at Lin§i Th e Agent reports that the Passport Agent has requested an explanation from him in regard to the matter, and informed him that he will report to his Government. In accordance with orders, no answer has, or will be, given either to the Governor of Mogoo or the Passport Agent. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) A. COTTON WAY. Inclosure 3 in No. 11. Sheikh Sultan, Governor of Mogoo, to the British Agent at Lingah. PERHAPS you have heard, but I again write to inform you, that Suliman bin Sooltan took dates to Debay for sale. When he was returning with the price of the dates and the amount of some debts he had collected, he was met by a ship and was hailed by her. His28 bugla was then seized, and the money taken out of her. The bugla was then burnt. The crew were landed at Henderabee. The ship then left. I don't know why this occurred. Please tell me what I am to do. I won't let this matter drop. Please answer me. Suhman was detained two days by contrary winds at Shenas, and when passing round the Island was met off the Fort (Khelat). (True translate of purport.) (Signed) A. COTTON WAY, Her Britannic Majesty's First Assistant Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Inclosure 4 in No. 11. Lieutenant-Colonel Pelly to the Secretary to Government, Bombay. &gt; _ British Residency, Bushire, April 24, 1869. IN continuation of my letter dated April 12, 1869, I have now the honour to inclose translated purport of an extract from a letter written by the Governor of Mogoo to the authorities at Bushire, complaining of the burning of the Mogoo craft, and removal of its cash arfd goods by Her Majesty's ship ' Dryad.' 2. The Governor threatens to call on the Arab tribes for aid and retaliation. I inclose a copy of my reply to him. W ^ at ^ ha T e seen Captain Colomb, commanding 'Dryad,' I feel sure he would be the last man in the world to injure property irregularly and wilfully, and the evidence to be collected may still show that the craft was fair prize. at t ^ e same .^ me experience on the African coast assures me that the most careful officer may be mistaken in regard to slaves; and there are some points in the case which it may be difficult to meet:— .1st. The Slave Treaty with Persia provides for the presence of a Persian Com missioner being on board any British vessel seizing slaves from a Persian craft at sea. 2nd. The craft now in question is alleged to be a Mogoo (Persian) vessel, which had run a cargo of dates to the Arab coast, and was on her return voyage, with the proceeds m cash, when chased by the ' Dryad.' 3rd. The craft is alleged to have been seized within gun-shot of the Persian shore and therefore,, constructively, within Persian territory. But the Treaty does not give us the right to seize slaves in Persian territory. • -i 4tIl i' T - he Cr f ft a PP ears to have been burnt on the spot, without reference to any civil authority, whether English or Persian. j A, ? n t ^ e a ^ ser ) ce of any report from the naval authorities, it is impossible to come to a defmitwe conclusion. But 1 think it would be well for me to be placed in a position either to meet the Persian complaint or to acknowledge our mistake, if it be one, and atiord compensation. 6. I would suggest, also, that when one of Her Majesty's vessels may be ordered to C u U1Z , e ] ^ r ; J the P eace of which 1 arn responsible, it would be desirable that I should be informed of the fact, and of her sailing orders; and that any seizures of craft or collisions with the tribes should be reported to me, as arbitrator of the Maritime Truce to which these tribes are subscribers. ^?f ra Ph sta tions at Jask and Angaum lie on the course of a vessel entering the Gulf; and if a commander telegraphed to me thence, I could arrange for deputing a rersian blave Commissioner and an Assistant Resident to some specified point. «. In the present instance the 'Dryad' was in the Gulf, and the seizure made before I was aware of these facts. Nor was it until her arrival at Bushire that I had an oppor tunity of detaching my Assistant, Captain Smith, with her to the Arab coast. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) LEWIS PELLY. Inclosure 5 in No. 11. SheM Sultan, Governor of Mogoo, to Mirza Mahmood Khan, Slave Commissioner. (Extract.) within'Toon ^ th Z ? h ^f 4 ^ Marc h)abugla belonging to one of my people was seized within 1,000 paces from the shore, and in four fathoms of water, by an English vessel The money and other property in her taken, and then burnt. I was not pleased ^2,29 and went with my people to the Passport Agent at Lingah and informed him. Doubtless he has written to you, but it was necessary for me to write also. I hope that you will recover the amount from the Resident at Bushire, and send it quickly, as I have been oppressed; and if not that, you will refer the matter to Tehran, that I may recover my property quickly. I have not written to the Governor at Shiraz, but to you only. Inshallah! you will quickly make arrangements for the recovery of my property, and send it by this vessel; and if not, tell me what I am to do. If not, 1 will solicit assistance from the Arab Chiefs and retaliate. (True translated purport.) (Signed) A, COTTON WAY, Captain, First Assistant Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Inclosure 6 in No. 11. Lieutenant-Colonel Pelly to Sheikh Sultan, Governor of Mogoo. (A.C.) Qth Mohurrum, 1286 (April 22, 1869\ THE Persian Slave Commissioner at Bushire has shown me your complaint regarding a bugla alleged to have been irregularly burnt near Mogoo. I have requested the Lingah Agent and Captain Way to take evidence in the case, and justice will be done. But in respect to your threat of requesting the Arab tribes to put to sea for retalia tion, I beg in a friendly but explicit manner to inform you that any such breach of the peace at sea will be prevented. (Signed) LEWIS PELLY. Inclosure 7 in No. 11. Commander Colomh to Commodore Sir L. Heath. Sir, 11 Dryad' Trincomalee, July 9, 1869. IN reply to your Memorandum of the 2nd July, inclosing a copy of correspondence on the subject of a dhow recently captured and burnt by me in the Persian Gulf, and directing me to furnish information connected therewith, I have the honour to make the following statement. 2. I am firmly of opinion that the vessel was not of Persian nationality at the time of capture; and I may here state the grounds on which I then formed that opinion, and now adhere to it:— (o.) The captain of the vessel produced neither papers, colours, passes for slaves, nor any other objects showing Persian nationality; and having been examined by the boarding officer, and by me, and having besides the fullest opportunities of communication with three Arab interpreters on board the ' Dryad,' he never claimed that his vessel belonged to any Persian port, and certainly not, as is now alleged, to Mogoo. {b.) The captain of the dhow, in the presence of the boarding officer, and afterwards in mine, distinctly asserted that the vessel belonged to Hassein, on the Arabian coast. When the capture was complete, I offered to land the captain and crew wherever they wished, and to the best of my recollection I especially mentioned Mogoo and Hussineh. The captain asked to be landed at the nearest town (Hussineh), and was so landed near it. It was to the last moment open to him to have claimed to be landed at Mogoo, which was in sight, or to have asked me to communicate with the Governor there before capturing him, but he never did so. (c.) It is true that he at one time stated that he was bound to Mogoo, as well as other places; but he immediately denied it on being asked why he was standing away from the place he was bound to- (d.) The wind was fair for Mogoo from the place and at the time of capture, and had been so for some days. 3. As respects the alleged distance from the shore at which the capture was made, in Colonel Pelly's letter No. 80 of 1869, ' within gun-shot of the Persian shore,' and in that of Sheikh Sultan, Governor of Mogoo, 'within 1,000 paces of the shore, and in 4 fathoms water,' the annexed affidavits show that the distance was over three miles ; and it will also be seen that this is not an estimate formed after the event, as I especially took the opinion of two officers before the capture was made, in order that I might not commit '4101 I30 a violation of Persian territory. The Persian Gulf pilot states (page 180) that a shoal, with less than 3 fathoms on it, exists a mile off-shore, near the place where the capture was made. . « 4. lam not in possession of a copy of the decree of condemnation of this dhow issued by the Vice-Admiralty Court at Aden; it was, however, in the usual form, and certified that the vessel was actually engaged in the Slave Trade, and was a lawful prize to Her Majesty's ship ' Dryad,' that one slave was landed at Aden from her, and that 1 was justified in destroying her. 5. Neither am 1 in possession of a copy of the sworn evidence offered before the Vice-Admiralty Court; but it was to the effect that the dhow or bugla drew suspicion on herself by her unaccountable alterations of coarse; that she had one slave for sale, but neither colours nor papers; that she claimed to belong to Hassein, and was seized more than three miles off shore. I submitted all the papers found in the vessel to the Court at Aden, and warned the Judge that I expected a claim of Persian nationality would probably be set up. The Judge made no special remarks on the case, except to admit the legality of my proceedings. 6. The annexed affidavits (four in number) sufficiently refute the allegations made by the Governor of Mogoo in respect to this transaction; but I wish to draw your attention to the singular fact of the Governor of Mogoo threatening to raise the Arab tribes to retaliate for damage to alleged Persian property, and suggesting, what I believe the truth, that she was really, as represented to us at the time, an Arab, and not a Persian vessel. 7. I append a tracing from our chart showing the place of capture, and of landing the crew. You will observe that the Governor of Mogoo, for his own purposes, falsely declares the capture to have been made nearly thirty miles west of the true locality. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) P. H. COLOMB. Inclosure 8 in No. 11. Chart showing the place where Dhow was captured by Her Majesty's Ship 11 Dryad' Inclosure 9 in No. 11. Affidavit of Commander Colomb. I, PHILIP HOWARD COLOMB, a Commander in Her Majesty's navy, do most solemnly and sincerely swear that, being in command of Her Majesty's ship 'Dryad' on the 24th day of March, 1869, in or about latitude 26° 32' north, and longitude 54° 22' east, in the Persian Gulf, I captured and destroyed a dhow, or bugla, without colours or papers, but carrying one slave boy, who stated he was for sale, and claimed my protection. And I further swear that the captain of the said dhow never in my presence, or to my knowledge, claimed Persian nationality for his vessel, or that he belonged to Mogoo; that, on the contrary, he claimed her to belong to Hassein on the Arabian coast. And I further swear that, to the best of my knowledge and belief, the vessel was not in territorial waters at the time of capture, and that it is falsely alleged she was seized within 1,000 paces of the shore. And I further swear that it is untrue that the said vessel was met off the fort (Khelat), or that the crew were landed at Hinderabee, for the vessel was met off Jibbel Yarid, and the crew were landed at Hussineh. And I further swear that the said dhow, being brought into the Vice-Admiralty Court at Aden, and all the circumstances of her capture being deposed to on oath, she was condemned as a lawful prize to Her Majesty's ship ' Dryad,' and it was decreed that I was justified in destroying her. And I make this solemn affidavit, conscientiously believing the same to be true. (Signed) P. H. COLOMB. Sworn to at Trincomalee, this 10th day of July, 1869. Before me: (Signed) A. B. Mason, J. P. for Trincomalee.7? .80) that a shoal, here the capture on of this dhow usual form, and a lawful prize to ?, and that 1 was OTered before the rew suspicion on ave for sale, but I was seized more jl to the Court at y would probably dmit the legality allegations made sh to draw your to raise the Arab ig, what I believe and not a Persian 3, and of landing i purposes, falsely ue locality. H. COLOMB. hip ' Dryad.' 's navy, do most ship ' Dryad ' on longitude 54° 22' ithout colours or ed my protection, ly presence, or to mged to Mogoo; n coast. he vessel was not ;d she ^as seized met off the fort is met off Jibbel e Vice-Admiralty &gt; on oath, she was is decreed that I i to be true. H. COLOMB. 31 Inclosure 10 in No. 11. Affidavit of Lieutenant Walker. I, HENRY CHAPMAN WALKER, a Lieutenant in Her Majesty's Navy, do most solemnly and sincerely swear that, on the 24th day of March, 1869, being then Senior Lieutenant of Her Majesty's ship ' Dryad,' Commander Colomb called my attention to a dhow without colours which was then about to be boarded, and directed me to estimate her distance from the shore; that I then estimated it as between three and four miles, and that I have since seen no reason to think otherwise. And I further swear that it is untrue the said dhow was seized within 1,000 paces of the shore, or that she was met off the Fort (Khelat), or that the crew were landed at Hinderabee; for the vessel was met off Jibbel Yarid, and the crew were landed at Hussineh. . tt - And I further swear that the said dhow was afterwards condemned in the Vice- Admiralty Court at Aden as a lawful prize to Her Majesty's ship ' Dryad.' And I further swear that although the wind was fair for the dhow to proceed to Mogoo she was not standing for that place either at the time of boarding, or for at least an hour beforehand. And I make this solemn affidavit, conscientiously believing the same to be true. (Signed) HENRY C. WALKER. Sworn before me: (Signed) A. B. Mason, J. P. for Trincomalee. Trincomalee, July 12, 1869. Inclosure 11 in No. 11. Affidavit of Lieutenant Hayward. I, WILLIAM HENRY HAYWARD, a Navigating Lieutenant in Her Majesty's Navy,'do most solemnly and sincerely swear that, on the 24th day of March, 1869, being then Navigating Lieutenant of Her Majesty's ship ' Dryad,' Commander Colomb called my attention to a dhow without colours, which was then about to be boarded,and directed me to estimate her distance from the shore ; that I then estimated it as between three and four miles ; and that I have since seen no reason to think otherwise. And I further swear that it is untrue the said dhow was seized within 1,000 paces of the shore, or that she was met off the Fort (Khelat), or that the crew were landed at Hinderabee; for the vessel was met off Jibbel Yarid, and the crew were landed at And I further swear that the said dhow was afterward condemned in the Vice-Admiralty Court at Aden, as a lawful prize to Her Majesty's ship ' Dryad.' And I further swear that although the wind was fair for the dhow to proceed to Mogoo she was not standing for that place either at the time of boarding, or for at least an hour beforehand. ^ . u And I make this solemn affidavit, conscientiously believing the same to be true. (Signed) W. H. HAYWARD. Before me: (Signed) A. B. Mason, J. P. for Trincomalee. July 12, 1869. Inclosure 12 in No. 11. Affidavit of Sub-Lieutenant Farr. I WILLIAM FARR, a Sub-Lieutenant in Her Majesty's Navy, do most solemnly and sincerely swear that, on the 24th day of March, 1869, being then Senior Sub-Lieutenant of Her Majesty's ship ' Dryad,' Commander Colomb directed me to board a dhow without colours near the ship; that I boarded the said dhow and took from her one boy slave, whom I conveyed to Her Majesty's ship ' Dryad.' And I further swear that the captain of the said dhow distinctly told me the vessel belonged to Hassein, on the Arabian coast, and that his replies were too confused for me32 ascertain whither he was bound; also that he never, in my presence, claimed Persian nationality for his vessel, or that she belonged to Mogoo, And I further swear, to the best of my knowledge and belief, the said dhow was more than three miles from the shore when I boarded her. And I make this solemn affidavit, conscientiously believing the same to be true. (Signed) W. FARR. Sworn to at Trincomalee, this 12th day of July, 1869. Before me : (Signed) A. B. Mason, J. P. for Trincomalee. Inclosure 13 in No. 11. Commodore Sir L. Heath to Sir S. Fitzgerald. 'Forte' at Trincomalee, July 13, 18fi9. I HAVE the honour to forward, for your Excellency's information, and to be dealt with as your Excellency may think fit, an explanatory letter from the Commander of Her Majesty's ship ' Dryad,' accompanied by affidavits from himself and others on the subject of the dhow recently captured by him in the Persian Gulf, and referred to in the letter No. 1,719 of 1869 with its inclosures addressed to me by Mr. Secretary Gonne. With respect to the second paragraph of Mr. Gonne's letter, I beg to point out that the presence of a Persian officer on board the capturing vessel is necessary only when the vessel captured is of Persian nationality. The two points raised in letter No. 80 of 1869 from Colonel Pelly, namely, first, whether the vessel was Persian; and second, whether, if not Persian, she was in Persian waters when seized, are fully met by the inclosed affidavits. The third point, namely, u the burning of the vessel without reference to any civil authority, whether English or Persian,' appears to me beside the question. From Commander Colomb's point of view the vessel should, if possible, have been taken to the nearest English Vice-Admiralty Court, and as she was not seaworthy for such a voyage, he was quite justified in burning her after survey, and taking upon himself the responsibility o the damages which would be claimed should she not eventually be condemned. With respect to the sixth paragraph of Colonel Pelly's letter, it will be in the recollec tion ot your Excellency that the date of the ' Dryad's' sailing, and the general nature of Commander Colomb s instructions, were settled in* concert with your Excellency, and I am mformed by Commander Colomb that the fact of the capture was made known to Colonel Pelly upon meeting him, and that if any official statement had been asked for on the subiect it would have been freely given. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) L. G. HEATH. No. 12. The Secretary to the Admiralty to Mr. Otway.—{Received September 18.) ^ r ' t a i \/r j , , _ Admiralty, September \7 t 1869. I AM commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to send you herewith copy of a letter and its inclosures, dated 31st July last, received from Commodore L Heath, respecting the inefficiency ot the interpreters employed by officers of Her Majesty s ships engaged in suppression of the Slave Trade on the East Coast of Africa and suggesting a mode for securing the services of a better class of interpreters • and to MSI'' ' * . C T™ ttee . appmirted to inquire into the sylte^ Majesty s crmzers in dealing with vessels suspected of being engaged in the Slave Trade may be instructed to favour their Lordships with their opinion on the subject. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) VERNON LUSRINGTON.33 Inclosure 1 in No. 12. Commodore Sir L. Heath to the Secretary to the Admiralty. 'Forte,' at Sea, Lat. 5° 14' S., Long. 66° 32' E., Sir, July 31, 1869. I INCLOSE you, for their Lordships' information, a copy of a letter from the Acting Political Agent at Zanzibar, complaining of the unfitness of the interpreters attached to the squadron. 2. It is of the greatest consequence, for the credit of Her Majesty's Service, that everything should be done which can in any way help the officers commanding Her Majesty's ships employed in suppressing the Slave Trade in the difficult task of discriminating between legal and illegal traders ; and since there is a general concurrence amongst the Indian Political officers in the opinion expressed by Dr. Kirk, and since the Sultan of Zanzibar has recently made a similar complaint, I beg to suggest that the responsibility of selecting and examining interpreters for service in Her Majesty's ships should be left in future with the Bombay Government, who have in the native seafaring population of Bombay a large field from which to select candidates, and who have Boards for examination in Oriental languages at their command. This plan would not only insure efficient interpreters, but it would relieve Her Majesty's officers from the disagreeable accusation now sometimes made against them of destroying innocent vessels on the sole evidence of illiterate interpreters chosen and selected by themselves. 4. I do not propose establishing an organized body of interpreters, but merely that men should be found, examined, and supplied as they may be wanted upon application to the Secretary in the Marine Department of the Bombay Government. 5. Interpreters are now paid as able seamen; it would be advisable, in order to insure respectable and intelligent men, to raise the pay to that of a first-class petty officer, viz., Is. 1 Id!, per day, or perhaps to the rupee {2s.). 6. Should their Lordships think proper, I beg that the Secretary of State for India may be moved to give the necessary instructions in this matter. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) L. G. HEATH. Inclosure 2 in No. 12. Dr. Kirk to the Chief Secretary to Government, Bombay. Sir, Zanzibar, May 16, 1869. WITH reference to the communications marginally noted,* I have the honour to report, for the information of the Right H n ourable the Governor in Council, that 36 negroes have been delivered over to me by Abbas-bin-Abdulla, Master of His Highness' ship ' Prince of Wales.' I have carefully examined these men individually in their own langurge, and find that they are all free and thankful to return to this country, where they can work as sailors and are among their friends. His Highness Seyed Majid desires me to express his thanks to the Bombay Govern ment for having sent back those who were no slaves, and whose position, if treated as such, might be worse than it is here. Such a mingling of slaves and free men as has taken place in this instance, which is certainly no exception, could only occur through inefficient or dishonest interpreting, and I regret to say that, as a class, those who embark in our cruizers as interpreters are an illiterate and worthless set. At this moment I am engaged with the trial of dhows destroyed on suspicion by Her Majesty's ship f ' Nymphe,' and I regret to say that the interpreter, on whose authority many of these dhows have been burned, is a man who cannot read Arabic or Suakeli, and who, therefore, cannot explain to the officers the nature of the papers under which the dhow is sailing. The interpreter who was on board Her Majesty's ship ' Star when most of the thirtv-six free men now sent back were taken is a man equally incompetent. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) JOHN KIRK. * Government Resolution, Political Department, No. 469, FebruaryJ,2; Government Resolution, No. 787, March 10; the Commissioner of Police to the Political Agent, Zanzibar, No. 591, March 24, 1869. [410J KII 34 No. 13. Sir F. Rogers to Mr. Otway.—(Received September 24.) Sir » Downing Street, September 24, 1869. I AM directed by Earl Granville to transmit to you. for the consideration of the Earl of Clarendon, and with reference to the correspondence noted in the margin,* a copy of a Report by the Emigration Commissioners on the observations made by the Commis sioners of Seychelles as to the disposal of captured slaves landed in those islands. I am to request that you will call Lord Clarendon's attention to the 4th paragraph of the Emigration Commissioners' Report. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) FREDERIC ROGERS. Inclosure 1 in No. 13. Mr. Murdoch to Sir F. Rogers. sir ' t tt a ttt? . , , Emigration Office, July 19, 1869. 1 HAVE to acknowledge your letter of the 13th instant, with a despatch dated 31st May last, from the Governor of Mauritius, and a Report from the Civil Commissioner of the Seychelles on the subject of the landing of liberated Africans in those islands. 2. It appears that two ship-loads of captured slaves have recently been taken into the Seychelles by Her Majesty's ships; that there is reason to apprehend the arrival of more the Slave Trade on the East Coast having been unusally active lately; that there is no demand for these Africans in Seychelles nor even in Mauritius; and that if taken to either they will be likely to put the Government to considerable expense. Sir H. Barkly under these circumstances expresses a hope that Her Majesty's Government will be able to dispose of them elsewhere. 3. The principal difficulty of doing so arises, I believe, from the description of vessel in which these slaves are captured. They are captured in small Arab dhows which are not fit for a long voyage, and they could not be transferred to Her Majesty's cruizers for conveyance to a distant Colony even if there were accommodation for them, without withdrawing the cruizers for too long a period from their cruizing ground. Otherwise they might be taken to Natal, where the settlers would probably be able to employ them advantageously. It is, however, for the Admiralty to decide whether this could be done consistently with the efficiency of the service. If not, I see no way of relieving Mauritius and the Seychelles but by sending all the people to Aden. 4. I beg to call attention to the fact mentioned by the Civil Commissioner that the dhows employed m the Slave Trade between Africa and Madagascar sail under French colours, and are furnished with French papers. Earl Granville will probablv think it right to call the attention of the Foreign Office to this fact. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) T. W. C. MURDOCH. 1! No. 14. Mr. Briggs to Mr. Otway.—(Received September 28.) ^ r ' mrTp t i ^ . . Admiralty, September 24, 1869. DennrfmL * C ° m ™ ssi0ners of , He r Majesty's Treasury having forwarded to this Adm^X nnT y of , t . he . ^J 011 of Mr - ^othery, the Registrar of the High Court of and ' 9l n r''' f V ^ ^ capture by Her Majesty's ships « Peterel,' ' Nymphe,' rnmm.nrWl k ^ A^n • sus P ected of bein g engaged in the Slave Trade, I am msfrnpHnn« wh'oi?' 0 t ^ 0mmissi0ners ; of the Admiralty to transmit herewith a draft of the snnnrpsdrm 0r c d f to * ssue f or ^e guidance of the officers employed in rre43rnn m . 0 l - ^ f T ^ With a vieW to P revent the recurrence of the irregulanties complained of, should the Earl of Clarendon approve of those instructions. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) JOHN HENRY BRIGGS. * Colonial Office to Foreign Office, July 13; Foreign Office, September 18, 1869.35 Inclosure in No. 14. Proposed Draft of Instructions to Her Majesty's Naval Officers on the East Coast of Africa Station, with reference to General Instructions for Suppression of Slave Trade. THE attention of the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty having been called to serious irregularities and mistakes committed by officers commanding Her Majesty's ships employed in the suppression of the Slave Trade on the East Coast of Africa, their Lordships are pleased to issue the following order :— It is not intended by this order to alter the printed Slave Trade Instructions which are furnished to Her Majesty's ships, but merely to point out and explain to officers, in the most marked manner, certain provisions of those Instructions, which on some occasions have been misunderstood or neglected, and to bring to the notice of officers the provisions of the recent statute 32 and 33 Vict., cap. 75. 3. As to what Vessels are liable to Capture. {Articles 50, 51.) The 50th Article of the General Instructions gives the general rule as follows:— ' If, in the course of the search, you are satisfied that the vessel is engaged in, or equipped for, the Slave Trade, and that she is subject to your authority, you will proceed to detain her.' The 51st Article gives auxiliary rules :— ' You will be justified in concluding at a vessel is engaged in, or equipped for, the Slave Trade— ' 1. If you find any slaves on board. ' 2. If you find in her outfit any of the equipments hereinafter mentioned.' (Then follows an enumeration of the equipments, taken from the Statute 5 and 6 Vict., cap. 91, sec. 4.) In construing the words in this Article, 'if you find any slaves on board,' reference must be had to the general scope of the Instructions, and particularly to the language of the preceding Article, which speaks of the vessel being ' engaged in, or equipped for, the Slave Trade.' ' Slave Trade must for this purpose be carefully distinguished from slavery; with which, as existing in foreign States, or on board foreign ships not being in British territorial waters. Her Majesty's Government does not claim, either by Treaty or otherwise, to interfere. As a fact, slavery as a legal institution exists in several States (amongst them Zanzibar) with which Great Britain has Treaties for the suppression of Slave Trade. The mere finding, therefore, of slaves on board a vessel will not justify an officer in detaining her, if there are other circumstances which show that these persons are slaves by the law of the country from which the ship has sailed or to which she belongs, and that they are not being transported for the purpose of being sold as slaves. Thus, for instance, where the slaves found on board are very few in number, are unconfined, and appear to be on board for the purpose of loading or working the ship, or attending upon the master or the passengers, and there is no other evidence that the vessel is engaged in, or equipped for, the Slave Trade. It is quite otherwise where the slaves are found crowded and chained together, and are obviously being carried as cargo to be sold as slaves. Between these two classes of cases there are intermediate cases, some of a doubtful character. It must rest with the officer to distinguish to what class any particular case belongs, by a careful consideration of all the circumstances, bearing in mind always this, that it is his duty to detain the vessel if he is reasonably satisfied that she is engaged in, or equipped for, the Slave Trade, but not otherwise. Officers serving on the East Coast of Africa must further remember the 388th Article of the Instructions, which informs them that the right is expressly reserved to the subjects of the Sultan of Zanzibar of transporting slaves within certain limits there specified. 2. As to Documents found on hoard the detained Ship. {Articles 58, 69, 85.) These Articles, which prescribe measures for the preservation and final delivery to the Court of Adjudication of all papers and documents found on board the detained vessel, are to be carried out with perfect fidelity and scrupulous care. The unexplained loss of any such document, and still more its destruction, on any pretext whatsoever, will lay the officer open to very serious imputation.36 3. As to the Destruction of Vessels. (Articles 60, 61.) These Articles give authority to the officer to destroy a vessel which on search he •Tpffto he eiLLed in or equipped for, the Slave Trade, if, after survey held, it appears that she if lot in a suffleiently seaworthy eondition to be sent to a port of adjitotion that ^ de5t ti of a vessel is only to be resorted to as an extreme measnr?. Nothing will excuse the ofhcer m not sending in the vessel to a port of adjudication, except facts showing satisfactorily that doing so would ha Tnt£^^ - t0 ' vessels^—- ^ ^ sp i c i on an d aie unable to send bar into the proper port of adjudication, you will not destroy her wrthont (rf Parable) having first ascertained at the nearest Zanzibar port, by inquiries from Her Majesty s Consul and others, that she was engaged in, or equipped for, the Slave Trade. You are also strictly to observe all similar Articles with respect to vessels of other nationalities to be found in the Special Instructions. 4. As to the Port of Adjudication. (Articles 63, 65, 389.) The two first-named of these Articles prescribe the general duty of forwarding the detained vessel with as little delay as possible to the port of adjudication, and direct the officer to refer to the Special Instructions to ascertain the proper port. The 389th Article, referring to Zanzibar vessels only, is as follows ' The proper port of adjudication for a Zanzibar vessel is the nearest or most acces sible port at which a British Admiralty or Vice-Admiralty Court is established. Since the issuing of these instructions, certain powers have ^era conferred on Her Majesty's Consul at Zanzibar, by Order in Council of 9th August, 1866, and the statute 32 and 33 Vict., cap. 75. The 29th section of the Order in Council is in these words. ' And it is further ordered, that Her Majesty's Consul within the dominions ot the Sultan of Zanzibar, shall for and within the said dominions, and for vessels and persons coming within those dominions, and in regard to vessels captured on suspicion ot being engaged in the Slave Trade within those dominions, have all such jurisdiction as tor the time being ordinarily belongs to Courts of Vice-Admiralty in Her Majesty s possessions abroad.' , « j i.* • • The Act of Parliament extends the Consul's power; for the 2nd section is in these terms I——' 'j' ' Her Majesty's Consul at Zanzibar for the time being shall have, and shall be deemed to have always, since the commencement of the said Order in Council, had, all such j uris ' diction as ordinarily belongs to Vice-Admiralty Courts in Her Majesty's possessions abroad in regard to vessels captured on suspicion of being engaged in, or equipped for, the Slave Trade, in the following cases:— . ^ rp ' (1.) Where a Zanzibar vessel shall have been captured in pursuance of any ireaty with the Sultan of Zanzibar, either within or beyond the dominions of Zanzibar; '(2.) Where the vessel captured shall not be entitled to claim the protection of the flag of any State or nation.' Officers will therefore observe that:— (1.) All vessels captured in Zanzibar dominions are to be taken for adjudication to Zanzibar: (2.) All Zanzibar vessels, wheresoever captured, and all vessels, wheresoever captured, which shall not be entitled to claim the protection of the flag of any State or nation, are to be sent for adjudication to Zanzibar, if that be the nearest or most accessible port at which a British Admiralty or Vice-Admiralty Court is established. In cases where the vessel is run on shore and wrecked, or is destroyed as unseaworthy, the same port of adjudication is—excepting in very special circumstances, to be resorted to for pro curing the Decree of Court, as that to which the vessel ought to have been sent if in a seaworthy condition when captured; more especially is this to be observed where persons are found on board the vessel.ST 5. As to Persons and Property found on hoard the Vessel.—{Articles 66, 67, 77, and 78.) These Articles prescribe that, wherever practicable, all persons and things found on board the vessels shall be sent with as little delay as possible to the port of adjudication, and if possible in the vessel herself. Nothing short of necessity will justify any officer in landing any such persons on the coast at random near the place of capture, or in taking them to any port other than the port of adjudication. Their Lordships regret to be obliged to remind naval officers of this simple duty so clearly imposed upon them, and to have to state that the purpose of taking the captured vessel to the proper port of adjudication is not to procure, as a matter of form, a decree of condemnation, but to obtain a full and fair trial of the case, at which trial those concerned in the property may have all reasonable facilities to defend their interests. 6. As to reporting Captures. {Articles 48, 49.) Officers commanding Her Majesty's ships are required by these Articles to furnish a detailed report of every capture, and especially of any circumstances which may have induced them to depart from the appointed course of conduct. In conclusion, their Lordships are most anxious to assist and protect officers in the right performance of their duties in suppressing the Slave Trade, but they must warn all such officers that, if they transgress the instructions on this subject, they will fall under their Lordships' serious displeasure; they will also be liable to be called upon to pay heavy costs and damages. No. 15. The Secretary to the Admiralty to Mr. Otway.—(Received September 28.) Sir, Admiralty, September 27, 1869. I AM commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit to you, for the information of the Earl of Clarendon, the accompanying copy of a letter from Commander Sulivan, of Her Majesty's ship ' Daphne,' reporting the capture of a dhow on the 16th of May last, with fifty-two slaves on board. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) JOHN HENRY BRIGGS. Inclosure in No. 15. Commander Sulivan to Commodore Sir L. Heath. Sir, 'Daphne' Seychelles, June 6, 1869. I BEG to report that after leaving Aden on the 11th of May T returned off Maculla and from there steering eastward chased and boarded several dhows; but finding to the eastward of the longitude of G-uardafui that the monsoon had evidently set in, I shaped a course for Seychelles, capturing a dhow on the 16th May with fifty-two slaves on board between Socotra and the mainland. I landed the crew at their request on the east end of Socotra, and arrived here on the 6th instant where we landed the slaves. We experienced severe squally weather on the passage. We leave this to-day for Zanzibar. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) J. L. SULIVAN. No. 16. Mr. Briggs to Mr. Otway.—{Received September 29.) Sir, Admiralty, September 28, 1869. I AM commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit herewith, for the information of Earl Clarendon, a copy of a letter from the India Office, [410] L38 dated 17th September, and its reply dated the 22nd instant, respecting the capture of a vessel engaged in lawful commerce, by Her Majesty's ship ' Daphne.' I am, &amp;c. (Signed) JOHN HENRY BRIGGS. Inclosure 1 in No. 16. Mr. Melvill to the Secretary to the Admiralty. Sir, India Office, September 17, 1869. I AM directed by the Duke of Argyll to forward, for the information of the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty, copy of a letter recently received from the Government of India, respecting the case of a vessel engaged in lawful commerce, but captured by Her Majesty's ship ' Daphneand I am to request that you will invite the special attention of their Lordships to the 3rd paragraph of the above letter, wherein it is suggested that the action of Her Majesty's cruizers might be restricted ' to cases in which native craft are clearly employed in carrying a number of slaves for the purposes of unlawful sale.' I am, &amp;c. (Signed) JAMES MELVILL. Inclosure 2 in No. 16. Mr. Briggs to Mr. Melvill. ^ r ' Admiralty, September 22, 1869. IN reply to your letter of the 17th instant, forwarding a copy of a letter from the Government of India respecting the capture of a vessel engaged in lawful commerce by Her Majesty s ship ' Daphne,' and calling their Lordships' special attention to the suggestion contained in the letter, that the action of Her Majesty's cruizers should be restricted to cases in which native craft are clearly employed in carrying a number of slaves for the purposes of unlawful sale. I am commanded by the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you for the information of the Secretary of State, that the case referred to is now under their Lordships' consideration, and regulations are being drawn up foi the guidance of Commanding Officers of Her Majesty's cruizers engaged in the suppression of the Slave Trade with the view of preventing illegal captures. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) JOHN HENRY BRIGGS. No. 17. Mr. Merivale to Mr. Hammond.—{Received September 30.) ^ r ' T . India Office, September 29, 1869. iW continuation of my letter of the 23rd August, 1869, I am directed by the Duke of Argyll to forward for the information of Lord Clarendon, copy of a letter from ombay, inclosing a statement as to the number of slaves landed, &amp;c., at Bombav durinar the past five years. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) HERMAN MERIVALE. Inclosure 1 in No. 17. The Secretary to Government, Bombay, to the Under-Secretary of State for India. ^ t aa/t r . j . Bombay Castle, August 3\, 1869. 1 AM directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter dated 25th of June last, with accompamments, and, in reply, to inclose, for the information of Her Majesty's Secretary or fetate tor India, a statement showing the number of captured slaves landed at Bombay39 during the past five years, the places from which the slaves have been received, and the way in which they have been disposed of. 2. I am to add that, in addition to the number entered in the statement, a party of 350 liberated slaves, forwarded by the Acting Resident at Aden, were landed at Bombay on the 24th instant, and that another party of 350 is expected to arrive from the same settlement very shortly. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) A. C. GONNE. Inclosure 2 in No. 17. Statement showing the Number of Captured Slaves received in Bombay during the past Five Years, the Name of the Officer and Place from which Received, and the Manner in which they were Disposed of. How Dispose( i of. Year and Month. Number of Slaves Received. Name of the Officer, and Place from which Received. Sent to Nassick School. Obtained employment. Sent back to Zanzibar. Escaped at Aden before the Vessel left. Died on the way to Bombay. Died in Bombay. Total. Sept. 1865 Aug. 1866 Mar. 1867 Apr. „ Aug. „ Jan. 1868 Nov. „ Feb. 1869 Mar. „ 57 48 132 5 89 92 20 60 46 The Political Resident, Aden Ditto Ditto The Political Agent, Kutch .. The Political Resident, Aden Ditto The Officer commanding H.M.S. ' Nymphe'. The Political Resident, Aden Ditto 55 40 19 8 88 5 88 85 20 67 36 *2 2 14 'i 11 'l 4 3 57 48 132 5 89 92 20 106 549 Total . 114 361 36 2 17 19 549 (Signed) A. C. GONNE, Secretary to Government. Bombay Castle, August 31, 1869. No. 18. Mr. Otway to the Secretary to the Admiralty. Sir, Foreign Office, October 4, 1869. I HAVE laid before the Earl of Clarendon your letter of the 24th instant, inclosing a draft of the Instructions which the Lords of the Admiralty propose to issue for the guidance of naval officers employed in the suppression of the Slave Trade, with a view to prevent a recurrence of the irregularities complained of on the East Coast of Africa; and I am to inform you that his Lordship entirely concurs in the proposed instructions. There is, however, one important question, namely, that of the best places for landing liberated slaves taken from vessels captured on the East Coast, which is not referred to in the instructions. The point is one which will have to be considered by the Commission which will shortly meet for the discussion of Slave Trade questions on the East Coast, and Lord Clarendon would therefore suggest that the proposed instructions might be referred to the Commission before they are finally adopted. I am to return the draft Instructions in accordance with your request. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) ARTHUR OTWAY.40 No. 19. Mr. Briggs to Mr. Otway.—(Received October 6.) Sir, Admiralty, October 5, 1869. I AM commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to send you herewith, for the information of the Earl of Clarendon, copy of a letter from Commodore Sir L. Heath, dated 16th September, reporting his proceedings on the Eastern Coast of Africa, and stating that he had paid a visit to the Sultan of Zanzibar. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) JOHN HENRY BRIGGS. Inclosure in No. 19. Commodore Sir L. Heath, to the Secretary to the Admiralty. Sir, 'Forte' at Aden, September 16, 1869. I BEG you will inform their Lordships, in continuation of my previous Report that I sailed from the Seychelles on the 14th, and arrived at Zanzibar on the 23rd August. I left that port on the 1st September, and after showing the flag at Brava, Magadoxa, and the intervening towns and villages, and after looking into Ras Mabber and Ali-Besh-Quail, T anchored under Cape Guardafui on the 10th instant, leaving on the 12th, and reaching Aden this day. 2. At Zanzibar J paid, with the officers of the ' Forte,' a state visit to the Sultan, and at a more private interview I discussed with His Highness the question of the Slave Trade. 3. His Highness expressed as strongly as last year his wish to work with us, and appealed to the difficulties he had thrown in the way of the Arab dealers in the spring of this year, and to the information given by his officers which has resulted in the capture of a dhow by the ' Nymphe ' as proof of his sincerity. 4. His Highness expressed his satisfaction at the establishment of a Vice-Admiralty Court at Zanzibar, and his confidence in the justice of its decisions. 5. I was informed by Dr. Kirk, the Acting Political Agent and Consul, that correspondence found on board the dhow captured by the ' Nymphe' implicated a great number of the grandees of Zanzibar as being concerned in the external Slave Trade; and although I believe the Sultan to be personally desirous of working with us in putting it down, yet the influences surrounding him are so strong and his Government is so mild and weak, that I fear we must not hope for any real help from him unless very strong pressure is brought to bear by Her Majesty's Government. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) L. G. HEATH. No. 20. Dr. Kirk to the Earl of Clarendon.—(Received October 11.) (No. 27.) , Zanzibar, August 8, 1869. 1 HA Vh the honour to inclose a copy of the proceedings in the Vice-Admiraltv Court here before me in the case of the officers of Her Majesty's ship ' Nymphe ' versus an Arab dhow which had been destroyed on suspicion of having been engaged in the Slave Trade at Keonga, on the African mainland, within the dominions of His Highness the Sultan of Zanzibar. In this instance I have been compelled, after a careful consideration of the evidence and the arguments advanced in both sides to declare in favour of the Arab dhow owner and to award full compensation to the owner, the master, and crew. It is with much satisfaction that I have to inform your Lordship that Captain E. S Meara and the officers of Her Majesty's ship ' Nymphe'' have expressed their willingness to settle at once all claims that may be proved before me, and this I hope to succeed in doing before the return of Her Majesty's ship ' Nymphe ' in September. 1 have the honour to solicit your Lordship's instructions regarding the settlement of claims for losses sustained by those interested in the dhow of Ali-bin-Nassur, which was destroyed by this ship, a Report of the proceedings in which case was forwarded to vourjn 41 Lordship in my despatch No, 20 of the 22nd May. It seems to me that the most just and ready way would be to authorize a Commission, consisting of myself and Sheikh Suliman-bin-Ali, the Sultan's Secretary, to examine and decide all claims brought before it, empowering me at the same time to disburse the sum allowed. It is of great importance that all such matters should be settled speedily, as thus alone will the Arabs be convinced of our justice; and I would bring to the knowledge of your Lordship that this is the first instance in which a decision has been obtained in favour of one of Seyd Majid's subjects. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) JOHN KIRK. f No. 21. The Secretary to the Admiralty to Mr. Otway.—(Received October 13.) Sir, Admiralty, October 12, 1869. I AM commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to send you herewith for the information of the Earl of Clarendon, a copy of a letter from Commodore Sir L. Heath, dated the 22nd September, relative to Slave Trade on the East Coast of Africa. With reference to your letter of the 4th instant suggesting that the instructions which my Lords propose to issue for the guidance of naval officers employed in the suppression of Slave Trade should be referred to the Commission which will shortly meet for the discussion of Slave Trade questions, in order that some decision may be come to with regard to the best places for landing liberated slaves taken from vessels captured on the East Coast; their Lordships, in bringing the inclosed despatch under Lord Clarendon's notice, would suggest whether it may not be expedient at once to issue the instructions, leaving the question as to where slaves should be landed for the consideration of the Commission. Copies of the instructions, when printed, will be sent to Foreign Office. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) VERNON LUSHINGTON. Inclosure in No. 2]. Commodore Sir L. Heath to the Secretary to the Admiralty. Sir, 'Forte,' at Aden, September 22, 1869. IN reply to your letter of the 14th July with its inclosures, on the subject of the alleged unsatisfactory system at present pursued by Her Majesty's cruizers in dealing with vessels suspected of being engaged in the Slave Trade, and directing me to furnish their Lordships with specific information and explanations on the points raised in the inclosures, informing me also of the intention of forming a Committee to report upon the whole subject. I have the honour to refer in the first place to my letters to their Lordships Nos. 112,214, 231,233, 237, of 1868, and Nos. 03, 92, 93, and 123 of 1869, and to request that copies of them and of their inclosures may be laid before the Committee. 2. With respect to the specific cases referred to by Mr. Otway, viz., a capture by Her Majesty's ship 'Peterel,' and one by Her Majesty's ship 'Nymphe,' I have to state that the ' Peterel' being on the Cape of Good Hope station, I am not in communication with her Commander. With respect to the vessel captured and destroyed by the ' Nymphe,' and for which compensation has been decreed by the Vice-Admiralty Court at Zanzibar, I beg to point out that an appeal against the decision of the Court is as open to the captors as to the captured, and to state that I understand Commander Meara is about to appeal against Dr. Kirk's decision, and that although doubtless in this case the Government would pay the compensation if the judgment of the Vice-Admiralty Court should be maintained, yet the claim will not be against the Government as stated by Mr. Otway, but against the captors, 3. On the 9th April, 1868, in my letter, I reported to their Lordships the opinion given by the Advocate-General at Bombay that the presence of domestic slaves on board a dhow was not evidence sufficient to convict her as a slaver, I gave reasons in that letter against this opinion, and I pointed out that if the Advocate-General was borne out by the Law Officers in England, it would be necessary to revise the instructions given to naval officers. I would now again urge an immediate answer to that letter, for it is a hardship to the officers commanding on this station that notwithstanding the numerous precedents [410] M42 condemning dhows for having domestic slaves on board, and notwithstanding the distinct instructions to them at page 22 of the book especially drawn up for them by their Lordships viz.: u You will be justified in concluding that a vessel is engaged in, or equipped for, the Slave Trade.' 1st. ' If you find any slaves on board, &amp;c.they should yet be subject to adverse decisions on this very point. 4. Dr. Kirk states that the vessel having been taken in one of the Sultan's harbours south of Quiloa could only be captured under the letter of Sayd Saed of the 6th May, 1850. Dr. Kirk must have written this in ignorance of Lord Stanley's decision in his reply of the 24th December, 1866, to Dr. Seward, in which his Lordship states England will not at present respect the Sultan's temtorial waters in any part of his dominions. Upon my recent visit to Zanzibar, I brought this letter to Dr. Kirk s notice. 5. The Political Agent also states, ' It would be absurd to think that Zanzibar slaves would be sold at the coast.' I do not think such a supposition is at all absurd; it might as well be said it was absurd to suppose a London horse would be sold in Yorkshire. There are numerous cases proved by intercepted correspondence that, just as unsound horses are sent for sale to distant fairs, so domestic slaves of troublesome character are sent out of Zanzibar with instructions to sell them for what can be got. So long as a man is a slave, so long is he a saleable article, liable to be sold, and as such England must, if she continues her contest with the Slave Trade, forbid his being exported. 6. Dr. Kirk states also that the season for slave-trading with Madagascar was over; it was in fact just about to begin. 7. The complaint made of the illiterate characters of the men generally engaged as interpreters in men-of-war is, I think, fully justified. I have addressed their Lordships proposing a remedy in my letter of 31st July, 1869. These are the only points raised by Dr. Kirk upon which I can afford their Lordships any information. 8. Referring now to Mr. Otway's letter to their Lordships of 21st July, 1869, calling attention, by Lord Clarendon's desire, to the unsatisfactory system at present pursued by Her Majesty's cruizers in dealing with vessels suspected of being engaged in the Slave Trade, and suggesting that when there is not a full cargo of slaves on board, the vessels with a part or the whole of their crew should be sent to the port of adjudication, &amp;c., I have to state that orders have already been given, under instructions conveyed in your letter dated 12th March, 1869, to send into Court the master and a portion of the crew of such vessel; but it is in most cases practically impossible to take the vessels themselves into port owing to the strength of wind and currents, and I may quote, in illustration of this statement, the case of the ' Daphne ' and ' Star,' in the autumn of last year—the one capturing fifteen and the other twenty-four dhows near Brava, and it being as much as the men-of-war could do to reach port themselves, so nearly was their coal expended. To have towed even a single dhow would in those cases have been out of the question. 9. It is a mistake to suppose that suspected dhows are always destroyed. Their Lordships will observe in many reports that officers have attempted to tow these vessels, and been obliged, after a few days, to destroy them from their weakness ; but when vessels are near a port, as when the ' Highflyer' made captures under Cape Guardafui in 1867, or the ' Daphne ' at Maculla in the spring of this year, the vessels were themselves taken in for adjudication. 10. I have been informed by Dr. Kirk that the correspondence taken in a dhow captured at Zanzibar on a recent occasion showed that a great many individuals, some of them of high standing in Zanzibar society, were interested in that cargo, and the habit of slave-dealing, either wholesale or retail, is so universal amongst the Arabs, that I think the reports of some of the Commanders, under my orders, to the effect that almost every large Zanzibar dhow, trading to the south, carries in the course of its rounds slaves to Madagascar, may to a considerable extent be true; and if so, it remains doubtful whether the transfer of dhows to the French flag is prompted, as Mr. Otway supposes, by the habit of landing the crews of captured vessels at the nearest convenient place, or by a wish to carry on Slave Trade without molestation from the English cruizers. I would refer on this point to Commander Meara's letter inclosed in mine of June 1869. 11. Ihe printed Slave Trade Instructions enjoin the bringing into Court of the master, crew, and passengers of captured dhows; the practice has, however, for many } ears been generally abandoned in deference to the wishes of those persons themselves. I am, however, of opinion that its revival under the orders given in their Lordships' letter of 12th March, 1869, will be beneficial as insuring a full representation of both parties in suits before Vice-Admiralty Courts. 12. I believe that the last-mentioned order—the establishment of a Vice-Admiralty Court at Zanzibar, and the improvement which will, I hope, under my letter of 31st July,43 1869, be made in the supply of interpreters, together with the personal liability of the captors for damages in cases of illegal destruction of vessels, are sufficient elements of protection to honest traders, and that any further restriction on the proceedings of our cruizers will diminish their efficiency as suppressors of the Slave Trade. ] 3. Their Lordships are aware of my opinion that we are even now doing but little good, and that, to succeed, we must put forth far more strength and energy, and that the most efficient step that England could take in this matter would be the purchase of the sovereignty of Zanzibar; whilst the very least that should be done is the forbidding of all further exports of slaves from Africa to Zanzibar or its dependencies—except in certain fixed and limited numbers, and for a limited period under the personal responsibility of the Sultan. So long as the domestic trade is unlimited, so long will foreign trade flourish. 14. I shall soon be at Suez, within a week's post from England, and I shall be most happy to answer any specific questions which the Committee about to sit upon this subject may wish to put to me. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) L. G. HEATH. No. 22. Dr. Kirk to the Earl of Clarendon.—{Received October 16.) (No. .) My Lord, Zanzibar, August 7, 1869. I HAVE the honour to inclose a copy of my decision in the case of the officers of Her Majesty's ship ' Nymphe'' v. two Arab dhows which were condemned by me as Judge in the Vice-Admiralty Court here, on the ground that they were engaged in the Slave Trade. It is much to be regretted, however, that the dhows themselves were destroyed previous to adjudication. I have, &amp;c. (Signed) JOHN KIRK. No. 23. Mr. Otway to the Secretary to the Admiralty. Sir, Foreign Office, October 19, 1869. I HAVE laid before the Earl of Clarendon your letter of the 12th instant, inclosing a report from Commodore Sir L. Heath upon the system pursued by Her Majesty's cruizers on the East Coast of Africa in dealing with captured slavers, and suggesting that the Instructions which their Lordships have recently framed upon this subject should, under the circumstances, be at once communicated to Her Majesty's naval officers, without waiting for the opinion of the proposed Commission. In reply, I am to request that you will inform the Lords of the Admiralty that in view of the evident need of immediate steps being taken to put a stop to the irregularities which have been brought to the notice of Her Majesty's Government, Lord Clarendon concurs with their Lordships in thinking that the amended instructions should be despatched at once, and that the question of the best places for landing the liberated slaves, and any other points requiring further consideration, may be left for future decision. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) ARTHUR OTWAY. No. 24. Mr. Otway to Dr. Kirk. (No. 8.) gj rj Foreign Office, October 22, 1869. ' 'WITH reference to your despatch No. 11 of the 16th of April, respecting the case of ten Arab dhows captured by Her Majesty's ship ' Nymphe,' and condemned in the Vice-44 Admiralty Court at Zanzibar, I am directed by the Earl of Clarendon to inclose, for your information and guidance, an extract of a Report from Mr. Rothery, the Legal Adviser to the Treasury on Slave Trade matters,* relating to questions affecting your rights of jurisdiction in cases of this nature. I am also to inclose a copy of the Act of Parliament passed last session, to which reference is made in the accompanying Report; and in calling your particular attention to Mr. Rothery's remarks regarding your power of jurisdiction, I am to instruct you to he very careful in dealing with Slave Trade cases, to guide your proceedings by the Order in Council and the recent Act of Parliament, and to be certain that they come within the limits therein defined. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) ARTHUR OTWAY. No. 25. Mr. Hamilton to Mr. Hammond.—{Received October 22.) Sir, Treasury Chambers, October 21, 1869. I AM directed by the Lords Commissioners of Her Majesty's Treasury to transmit to you herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State, with reference to your letter of the 4th instant, copy of Report from Mr. Rothery respecting the additional Slave Trade Instructions issued to naval officers by the Admiralty; and my Lords request that they may be informed, before communicating with the Admiralty, whether Mr. Rothery is correct in his impression with regard to the 388th Article of the Instructions. 1 am, &amp;c. (Signed) GEO. A. HAMILTON. Inclosure in No. 25. Report. To the Right Hon. the Lords Commissioners of Her Majesty's Treasury. May it please your Lordships, IN obedience to your Lordships' commands I have perused and considered the documents herewith returned, consisting of a letter from Vernon Lushington, Esq., the Secretary to the Admiralty, dated the 14th instant, transmitting for your Lordship's consideration a copy of the additional instructions which have been prepared for the guidance of naval officers employed in the suppression of the Slave Trade, and which Mr. Lushington states the Lords of the Admiralty have proposed to Lord Clarendon to issue at once, without waiting for the Report of the Commission which has been nominated to inquire into the subject more at large. And I have the honour to report to your Lordships that, having carefully perused the accompanying instructions, 1 am of opinion that they are well adapted to meet the evils referred to, and which appear to have become but too common on the East Coast of Africa. I have made a few trifling corrections in the margin for their Lordships' consideration. The statute referred to near the bottom of the first page is, no doubt a misprint for the 2 and 3 Vict., cap. 73, sec. 4. On the second page also there is a reference to the 388th Article of the Instructions. I have, however, an impression that some agreement has been recently made with the Sultan of Zanzibar, by which he has waived the right which was reserved to his subjects of transporting slaves within the prescribed limits. Whether this be so or not will probably be known at the Foreign Office; and it might be well to make the inquiry before issuing the instructions With these trifling alterations I venture to think that it would be well to issue the instructions at once, without waiting for the Report of the Commission that has been nominated to inquire into the subject. All which is most humbly submitted to your Lordships' wisdom. r&gt; * &gt; n ^ 7 ™ (Signed) H. C. ROTHERY. Doctors Commons, October 20, 1869. * See Inclosure in No. 10.45 No. 26. Mr. Otway to Mr. Hamilton. Sir, Foreign Office, October 23, 1869. IN reply to your letter of the 2nd instant I am directed by the Earl of Clarendon to request that you will inform the Lords of the Treasury that in the year 1863 the Sultan of Zanzibar undertook to prohibit entirely the transport of slaves from port to port within his dominions during the months of January, February, March, and April, when the Northern Arabs from the Persian Gulf and Red Sea frequent the coasts of the Sultan's territories for the purpose of procuring slaves. Lord Clarendon is not aware that the Sultan has extended that prohibition to the remaining months of the year; and it would appear by his letter to Mr. Churchill of December last that he has not done so, as he therein demands ' that the British navy should no longer molest the ships of our subjects found between the limits within which the carrying of slaves is allowed, namely, from Keelwa to Lamoo, save during the four months at which time, in accordance with the wishes of the British Government, we have prohibited the carrying of slaves in our own dominions.' I am, &amp;c. (Signed) ARTHUR OTWAY. No. 27. Mr. Otway to Mr. Hamilton. Sir, Foreign Office, October 23, 1869. I AM directed by the Earl of Clarendon to transmit to you, to be laid before the Lords of the Treasury, copies of two Orders in Council, granting among other rights of jurisdiction to Her Majesty's Consuls in Muscat and Madagascar, the powers ordinarily given to Yice-Admiralty Courts in Her Majesty's possessions abroad in regard to Slave Trade matters; and I am to request that you will move their Lordships to refer these Orders to their legal advisers on Slave Trade matters, with a view to the preparation of enactments granting to the Vice-Admiralty Courts in Muscat and Madagascar, powers in regard to bounties and the adjudication of Slave Trade cases similar to those given to the Court at Zanzibar, by the Act of last Session entitled ' The Slave Trade Jurisdiction (Zanzibar) Act.' I am, &amp;c. (Signed) ARTHUR OTWAY. No. 28. Memorandum by Mr. Churchill respecting Slave Trade on the East Coast of Africa, Information. Suggestions. 1. In the Indian Ocean dhows are en gaged in the Slave Trade from the south point of Madagascar, and the southern end of the Portuguese Colony of Mozambique, to the upper extremity of the Persian Gulf. The nationalities to which the said dhows belong, are the following: Portuguese, Mal- gash, French, Johanna, Mohilla, Zanzibar, Kutch, Somali, Turkish, Muskat, Persian Gulf, Soor, and Makulla. As a rule, large dhows when new do not engage in the Slave Trade ; it is only when a vessel has become worthless that she is employed in this traffic, for the good reason, that if she is captured the loss sustained thereby is inconsiderable. There is little in [410] N46 Information. a slave dhow to distinguish her from a legal trader. The fittings are almost the same. Matting, large tanks, and large cooking-pots are no criterions. Nor does slave food differ from that used by the crew and native pas sengers. It all consists of cassava-root and milfet; the only difference is, that a slave gets barely enough to keep him alive, while a sailor gets sufficient to grow fat upon. Since the abolition of slavery in the United States, few, if any, square-rigged vessels are engaged in the Slave Trade on the East Coast of Africa; but owing to the arbitrary proceedings of our cruizers many dhows have adopted the French flag, and this is easily obtained at Mayotte and Nossi Be ; the formalities required for the purpose vary very slightly. 2. Our Treaties with the Imam of Muskat give us the right of arresting dhows engaged in the Slave Trade between the African pos sessions of the Imam and the coast of Arabia. A few years ago, in order to faci litate the operations of our cruizers, the carrying of slaves in the dominions of the Sultan of Zanzibar was prohibited from the 1st January and the 1st May, and the terri torial rights of the Sultan were tacitly con ceded to Her Majesty's Government by Seyed Majid during that period. Our men- of-war insist upon all dhows having papers descriptive of their nationality; in the ab sence of which they assert their right of seizure. Passes in Arabic are issued at Zanzibar,* 1 Johanna, Mohilla, and on the Arabian coast, but as it is only at head quarters that these passes are issue^, it now and then occurs that dhows are arrested on the African coast without papers. There are, indeed, many small dhows built on the coast that never go to Zanzibar, but ply along the coast carrying cowries, carrots, and cassava-root, and timber; nor is it just that they should be considered as being engaged in the Slave Trade, merely because they have no papers ; and yet the rules and regulations connected with the Slave Trade distinctly say that the absence PL papers is a sufficient reason for detaining a vf^sel. The Sultan of Zanzibar objects to the capture of his shipping if it is not patent that they are engaged in the Slave Trade, and, unfortunately, it is very difficult for new hands to make out the difference be tween a slave and free negro; and when one slave on board of a vessel is sufficient to condemn it, papers become of the utmost importance. But whatever stress may be laid on the necessity of having papers, the passes actually issued by the native authorities can throw little light on the matter, for being I have seen as many as 20 per cent, of dhows under the French flag in the port of Zanzibar, and it is notorious that they were the bond fide property of Zanzibar Arabs and Hindus under British protection. This is undoubtedly a concession, for it gives us the faculty of searching his ports, and arresting slavers in his dominions during this period of the year; but a more valuable concession, and one that would be more effectual, would be to allow Her Majesty's cruizers the faculty of stoppin^dhows laden with slaves at all times of th?%ear beyond certain limits on the coast. Opposite the islands of Zanzibar and Pemba, between which limits alone slaves might be carried freely from the 1st May to the 1st January. Commanders of Her Majesty's vessels of war should be instructed not to detain dhows for want of papers alone. It would, nevertheless, be conducive to the interests of the Arab authorities in the, Indian Ocean, to issue printed passes con taining, in English as well as in Arabic, where it is practicable, a full description of the vessel. They should likewise be urged to issue articles of agreement similar to those issued by our shipping -masters, and the Governors on the Coast of Africa might receive from the Sultan of Zanzibar permis-20 per cent, of g in the port of 3 that they were izibar Arabs and tion. mcession, for it ching his ports, ominions during a more valuable would be more v Her Majesty's ingxlhows laden :h(#*^ear beyond st, Opposite the 'emba, between light be carried the 1st January. v ; jesty's vessels of , to detain dhows je conducive to uthorities in the ited passes con- il as in Arabic, ill description of kewise be urged nent similar to ng-masters, and ; of Africa might Zanzibar permis- 47 Information. written in Arabic, they are, in nine cases out of ten, unintelligible for want of an inter preter on board to read them ; and they do not in any case mention the names of the crew or the number of passengers. A part of the crew may be landed, and slaves may be embarked in lieu thereof, or slaves may be embarked as passengers. It is, however, of vital importance, that mistakes be not made in seizing legal traders, whom it is desirable to encourage as much as possible. A certain latitude must necessarily be given to commanders of Her Majesty's cruizers to enable them to grapple with the Slave Trade, but they are liable frequently through inexperience, and the interested motives of their subordinates, to being led astray and to act unjustly. 3. Nature of the cruizers required. Steam launches and coast-guard boats. 4. Difficulties have been experienc p in the disposal of the slaves once captured, and a vessel has frequently to abandon the [410] sion to issue provisional certificates of regis try and articles of agreement to dhows navigating exclusively on the coast. Every man-of-war employed on this coast to suppress the Slave Trade should have an Arabic and Soahili interpreter. Malta or Aden should be able to furnish good Arabic scholars, and the youths brought up at the Nassik school at Bombay would make very good Soahili interpreters. These should be salaried servants of the Crown, and should have no personal interest in the capture of dhows. Officers should remain longer on the station, and experienced Commanders should not be removed just when they are becoming efficient, which is but too often the case. To put a stop to all dissatisfaction on the part of the local authorities, captures should be brought before the Vice-Admiralty Court established in the countries to which the captured dhows belong. Thus the capture of a Zanzibar, Johanna, or Somali dhow should be brought before the Zanzibar Court, and a Muskat, Soor, or Bahrein dhow before the Muskat Court. In the same manner a Mokulla, Shahr, or Djedda dhow should go before the Aden Court. Commanders of Her Majesty's cruizers may then destroy dhows if they consider themselves justified in so doing; but the case being tried before the proper Court, plaintiffs will be in a position to obtain damages if they have been unjustly deprived of their property. The captain of a captured dhow should always be informed in writing, under receipt, of the port of adjudication of his dhow, and he should be taken there if possible. In my opinion the 'Nymphe' and ' Daphne ' class of vessel is too large for the nature of the work assigned to it in the Indian Ocean. A better class of vessel would be the 'Lynx' and 'Penguin' class, for such vessels can follow up a slaver in shallow water, and can be easily beached if anything goes wrong. They can do quite as much as a larger vessel, and are by no ineans as ex pensive. They burn less coal and do not require so many hands. They should be furnished with steam launches, made to con sume wood and coal indifferently, and capable of holding thirty men; such launches would be invaluable to go up the creeks. The Political Agency should have at its disposal a sailing-vessel, if not a small steamer, capable of being employed as a cruizer and as a mail-boat to bring the mails from the Seychelles. The presence of such a vessel at Zanzibar would be very desirable. I do not pretend to offer a perfect remedy to this evil, but if slaves captured in the neighbourhood of Zanzibar are brought toW 5 'si Th !i ViCe ' Admiralty Court at Zanzibar has already, as it is, increased in a consider able measure the work of the Political Agent and his small staff, and the new mea- sures proposed will increase it still more. Suggestions. Zanzibar they could be easily disposed of there. The children might be handed over to the Christian Missions, Catholic as well as Pro testant, to instruct and educate them, while the adults might be either farmed out as they are at the Mauritius, to the Europeans, Hindus, and nations, or they might be handed over to the Sultan. I should prefer the former mode, and the inhabitants of Zanzibar would view this step with great gratification. They are in want or labour and they would have free labour at their disposal instead of slave labour; by this m eans the Kutchus under British protection and Captain Fraser will be on almost the same footing as the natives, which thev are not at present, as they can procure' free labour nowhere, and are obliged to emplov slaves, although they do not possess their slaves as such. Indeed, I thmk that the bringing back of all slaves captured on the high seas to Zanzibar, the great slave-market of the East Coast of Africa, will have the effect of over-stocking the market, as it were, and of decreasing the trade; for no one will buy a slave if he can get free labour as cheap and as good. r ^ Measures will have to be taken for the due registry of all captured slaves found at Zanzibar, and printed certificates of freedom will have to be returned. An officer should be appointed for that Agent 86 ^ the COntr01 0f the Political All captures made to the south of the Equator could easily be brought to Zanzibar. Ihose made m the neighbourhood of Sokotra might be disposed of otherwise. A tele- graph statioii is, if lam well informed, to be established m an island in the neighbourhood if , hy could not slaves be landed there until such time as it maybe convenient to send them to Zanzibar or elsewhere ? The officer appointed as Registrar should be instructed to place his services as an assistant at the Vice-Admiralty Conrt at the disposal of the Political Agent The Political Agent should'be furnished with printed forms of Decrees for the plaintiffs and defendants with blank spaces parties ^ PriJ l T™* intere sted S?' ? i' 8 of ^'ificates re quired, and receipts for slaves, stores, &amp;c s '™' arth °f e used in the Colonies. The Vice-Admiralty Courts in the Indian thre^ent of t b likeWi8e enIi S hten cd as to me extent of their powers m awarding gSm 0 ' Asiti ^eyfiave nothing to S49 Information, Suggestions. What, for instance, should become of the property saved out of dhows destroyed by Her Majesty's navy ? I have seen kegs of powder landed by Her Majesty's navy in front of the Consulate and sold in the public market before the case was tried. Such acts appear to me to be unwise, to say the least of it; for everybody knew whose pro perty it was, and our men-of-war were simply looked upon as pirates. I had no authority to prevent it. No. 29. Mr. Otway to the Secretary to the Admiralty. Sir, Foreign Office, October 25, 1869. WITH reference to your letter of the 12th instant, inclosing copy of the proposed amended instructions for the guidance of naval officers employed in the suppression of the Slave Trade on the East Coast of Africa, I am directed by the Earl of Clarendon to transmit to you for the consideration of the Lords of the Admiralty, copies of a corre spondence with the Treasury* regarding a point raised by their legal adviser on Slave Trade matters, and not noticed in the instructions respecting the relinquishment by the Sultan of Zanzibar of his right to transport slaves from port to port within his dominions during certain months of the year. I am, &amp;c. (Signed) ARTHUR OTWAY. * Nos. 25 and 26. printed at the foreign office by t. harrison.- -28/10/69.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000103_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B84</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000103</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B84</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Further Papers respecting the Slave Trade on the East Coast of Africa and the System Pursued for its Suppression'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1869/1869</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-10T11:25:14</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (25 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in rough chronological order, with the earliest correspondence at the beginning of the file and the latest at the end of the file.</extent><extent>Condition: contained within a bound volume that contains a number of other files.Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at f 67, and terminates at f 91, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 5-134; these numbers are written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding their attempts to monitor and prohibit slave traffic on the East Coast of Africa. The correspondence dates from March 1869 to October 1869.Of particular interest are the following folios:Folio 71 - French Government boat registration papers that had been given to 'Arab Dhows' allowing them to travel under the French flag.Folio 73 - A chart entitled 'Memorandum of Number of Slaves landed and liberated at Aden, and how disposed of'.Folio 74 - A copy of the Slave Trade Jurisdiction (Zanzibar) Bill, May 1869.Folios 89-91 - 'A Memorandum by Mr. Churchill [Henry Adrian Churchill, Britain's Agent in Zanzibar] respecting Slave Trade on the East Coast of Africa'.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Zanzibar</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Slave trade</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000103#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>