<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000175_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-20T14:40:29.742Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">V 1 cu/^&lt;st. No. 4/ flof' Jbushire, 29th December, 1940. The undermentioned papers are forwarded, with compliments, for favour of comments to:- 1. The Political agent, Bahrain, 2. The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* t- Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division. 1 . Copy of letter No. I/a 10-2-1229 dated the 5th December, 1940, from the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, to the Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division, Bushire* 2 . Copy of note dated the 23rd December, 1940, from the Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division, Bushire, to the Secretary to the Hon r ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire.Copy of letter No# Wa 10-2-1229 dated the 5th December, 1940* from the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New- Delhi, to the Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division, Bushire. Subject:- Y/ater borne sanitation in the Agency Building at Bahrain - With reference to the correspondence resting with your endorsement No. 4/594, dated the 10th October, 1940, I have the honour to enquire if the execution of the work of running and maintenance of the(electrically driven pump referred to was entrusted to the Political agent himselfi and if so to observe that the orders of the Government of India in the External Affairs Department contained in their ] ') { X y c' tf ♦ memorandum No. F.lO^-a/38 dated the 10th June, 1940, do not seem to contemplate such an arrangement and orders of the ;| competent authority for such an arrangement should be obtained and intimated to this office, if it has not already ' been done.Copy of note aated the 23rd December, 1940, from the Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division, Bushire, to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* | — Placed below is a letter No. WA 10-2-1229 dated the 5th December, 1940, from the accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. The Political agent, Bahrain, was running and maintaining the electrically driven pump installed in the !| agency buildings, in connection with the v/ater borne sanitation. According to the letter,under reference, this service should have been performed by the Public Works Department, and the amount spent thereon, recovered from the Political agent. If this method is adopted, then the Political agent will have to send all the bills pertaining to running and maintaining the pump to me for payment, after they are paid, then I am In order to avoid this the Government of India in uhe moved to transfer this service Bahrain, under para 482 note 1 Code. Forward to Political ^tgent and to recover the amount from him procedure, I would request that! Department of Labour, may be to the Political ^xgent, of the Public Works Account 1 ask his comments first. (Intd) A.C.S. 23/12No.29-18/6 Political Agency, Bahrain. 6th January? 1940 . To The Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf 3ub-T)ivision, Bushire• Memomn dum. Refej'ance your endorsement No.4/80^ dated 29th December, 1940. ^ h ' 2. I entirely agree with the suggestion contained in paragraph 3 of your note dated 23rd December, 1940, to the Secretary to the Kcn'ble the Political Hesident. Major, Political f\gent, Bahrain.Telegram GTC. From Asstenger, Bushire. To Political, Bahrain. No. Nil Dated 12th, received 13th July, 1941. Following for Supervisor. Your despatch No.30 of July 6 th. Estimate renewing cement and pudlo plaster sanctioned, work should be commenced immediately.Telegram GTC. From Political, Bahrain • To Britconsul, Bushire. No. 163 Dated 13th d uly, 1941. Assistant Engineer’s telegram dated 12th July. Grateful if estimates 1 &amp; 3 of despatch 30 c^n also be sanctioned early so as to complete work before my return from recess.7 ® From Assistant Engineer, Bushire. To Political, Bahrain* No* Nil Dated 16th July, 1941. Two estimates sanctioned, estimate reconstructing verandah roof will have to b e ( ' ) ? government of India.2 Copy of letter No. AV/46 dated the 14th Hay, 1941, from the Assistant Secretary to the Government of India, Depart ment of Labour, New Delhi, to the Hon f ble tha^litical Resi dent in the Persian Gulf* e the*4^1i Subject:- Water borne sanitation in the \ agency building at Bahrain - V f J With reference to your letter No* 177 dated the 8 th February, 1941, I am directed to say that the Government of India presume that the running and maintenance of the electrically driven pump in the Agency Building at Bahrain is carried out by the Bahrain State Electrical Department on behalf of the Political Agent, Bahrain. I am to reuest that this presumption may kindly be confirmed and this Depart ment informed as to the method adopted in effecting recoveries of the expenditure from the Political Agent* No. 4/ Bushire, 17th July, 1941. A' Copy forwarded, with compliments, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to his memorandum No. 29-18/6 dated the 5th January, 1941, for favour of remarks. Assis Independent Persi ginfeer,Vl fiuiif* Sub-Division.No.1490-18/6 Political Agency, Bahrain• 2nd August, 1941. To The Assistant Ingine r, Independent - ensian Gulf :&gt;ub-')ivision, Bushire. ! emorandum. Reference your endoi*sement !To .4/448 dated the 17th July, 1941. 2 . The running and maintenance of the electrically driven pump in the Agency building at Bahrain is carried out by this Agency, and any expenditure for the maintenance of the rump is as already explained in this office letter No.1694-18/6 / dated 10th September, 1940 paid for privately by the Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent,From No. 4/ llht ■ Bushire, 25th July, 1941• The Assistant Engineer, Ind, Persian Gulf Sub-Divn., Bushire* x . To Sir, The Political Agent ? Bahrain* cX 0 6/ 4J?&gt;' 1 *^ s' f-* In continuation^^ this office telegram^ dated the 23rd July, 194^1 have the honour to for&amp;£rd herewith Supply Bi^l^o* 096595/68 dated the 25th July, 1941, for Ks. 80&lt;V- drawn in your favour on the Bombay Treasury, in recoupment of the advance granted to Mr. Mohd Ishaq, P. W. D. Supervisor, Bahrain. Kindly acknowledge receipt* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Assistant B^gineehjP Independent Persia &amp;£lf Sub-Division. No 4/ t/- ^ , r, u. • ^ Copy 10 Mr * Mohd Isha&lt; 3-&gt; P- w. D. Supervisor, Bahrain, for information, with reference to this office endorsement ho. 4/457 dated the 23rd July, 1941.GTC. Ublegram From Political, Bahrain. To Britconsu}., Bushire. No.180 Dated 31st July, 1941. Following for i^sistant ^nginec.r begins. ,f Your 426 12th July. Sanction my be telegraphically expedited to enable work to be completed before Najor Albany return.'Telegram From To GTG. Asstenger, Bushire. Political, Bahra n. Unnumbered. Dated 2nd August, 1941. Folio.;ing for supervisor. Ref ex'© nee estimate Verandah roof item No.7 and item No.10 unnecessary item No.5 and item No .6 approved rates ofs.3/- and .s. 120 /- start work if you ^ fir&gt;u,/') 7 complete within these x^ates telegraph reply urgent.14) Telegram G.T.C From To Political Agent, Hahi-'ain. Britconaul, Bushire. No. /S' 1 ' •18/6 Dated 4th August, 1941. Following for Assistant Fngineer§ fron; Supervisor i- Your telegram August 2nd. (a) Item No#7 and 10 quite essential, former to liiake walla damp procf and latter to match work with other verandahs already completed. (b) Work can only be completed within estimate amount if carried out atonce as since submission of estimate cost of material ha* risen by 5 Further delay might cause revision of whole estimate owing to daily fluctuations. PoliticalA'TT^ \ju&lt;jlaA , ^ ^M\’ No. 26/ Bus hire To v/t iuigust, 1941* Subject:- Sir, The Political Agent, B&lt; The Political Agent, Muscat* The Political Agent, Kuwait. The H. B* M*s Consul, Bunder *iDbas* Schedule o±* Demands under 50-Civil v/orks- External Affairs - 1942 - 43 I have the honour to request you to kindly state your requirements of Original V/orks and Additions and Alterations ^ which you consider necessary to be carried out in tiie^Agenc^ Building|^ during the financial year 1942-43* As the Schedule of Demands are required to reach the Government of India by the 15th October, 1941 vide para 3 Appendix 8 of Public ubrks Account Code, it is requested that the information called for in para 1 above may kindly be furnished through the Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, so as to reach this office by the middle of September, 1941* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, istaift: Engineer, - Independent Persian &lt;0^ Sub-Divi s i on ♦D•0.No•1939-18/6 ’)ated 21st September! 1941 Please refer to Urtaza’s circular No.26/496 dated the 14th August 1941 asking for our requirements of Original Works, additions and alterations in the Agency building during 1942-43. floor of.the south verandah is in a bad state and needs renewal and the roof beams in various places ai*e sagging and require either to be turned over or replaced. addition to the above, the present confidential office and accountant’s office are very dingy and airless and any improvement in this direction would be welcome. The passport office and the adjoining room require panelling and flooring. 4. Mohamed Ishaq, vho has been in hospital since August is still seriously ill and unless I may call in private advice from the town, it will be impossible to submit proper detailed estimates by October 16th. 6. The waiting room started in July last is still unfinished, although Alban was very anxious that the room should be ready as soon as possible. Captain A.C. Stewar, I .A., Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushlre .© EXPRESS LETTER [N, B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receiyi, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it .Wi been so despatched,] 1- Political - Bahrain* 2 . Political - Kuwait. 3* Britconsul- Bondar .yobas* So. 26 / fd’ 3 . Bushire, Dated 18th September, ^41 * subject;- Schedule of .demands under 50—Civil Worley internal affairs - 19 4 2 - 1 9 4 3 Heference is invited to this office letter No. 26/496 dated the 14th August, 1941, and to request that the statement may please be sent at a very early date* S. 6. MFP—1014 S&amp;P—(M-1645)—29-11-39—400,000.Telegram - GTC. From - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - H.B.M’s Consul-General, Bushire No. - 260. Dated the 6th October, 1941. p .jo Reference my memorandum No.1838 dated the 30th September, 1940. Work left incomplete by late overseer and it is imperative to complete before rains this month. Request telegraphic sanction to complete work with local labour at once. Please also telegraph what works have been sanctioned and amounts available. - POLITICAL -Telegram From To No. Dated 6th - GTC. - Assistant Engineer, Bushire. - Political Agent, Bahrain. - Nil. and received 7th October, 1941. „ — g) MURTAZA arriving this week. - ASSTENGER -Telegram From To No. Dated 6th in hand. - GTC. - Assistant Engineer, Bushire. - Political Agent, Bahrain. - Nil. and received 7th October, Your telegram No.2&amp;0. 1941 Incomplete work may be taken - ASSTENGER --J To V Politicf:! Agency Bahrein, The 17th Mrrch 1342. The Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf -ub-Division, Pernor rnduin. Bushire. The Reserve Pnnk of Indie Remittance No. i9i t dated *2-0-42, for :s 28-11-0, forwarded under cover of your No.4/142,dated the i.2th Mrrch 1942, ha s been receiver, wi'th thrnKs. hv^ I M- * V % For Political Agent,Bahrein.To .0 ( 2 ?) / 3fu. Bushire, 15th August, 1942^ V K The Political i^gent, Baiirain* The Political Jigent, Muscat* The Political Agent, Kuwait* The H*B.M f s Consul, Bandar Abbas. Subject:- Schedule of demands under 50-C.W. Sxternal Affairs - 1943-44* (43-44) • Sir, I have the honour to request you to kindly state your requirements of original works and additions and alterations which you consider necessary to be carried out in the agency build ings, during the financial year 1 9 4 3 ~ 4 4 * As the schedule of deamnds are required to reach the Government of India by the 15th October, 1942 vide para 3 Appendix 8 of Public '.forks Account Code, it is requested that the ihformution called for in para 1 above may kindly be furnished through the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, so as to reach this office by the middle of September, 1942* I have tiie honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, P *a&gt;«n (iulf Sub-DtTMlw. ^ THE POLITICAL AGENCY, Jl/° « BAHREIN. /?/( / , f y. . * • t * To The Assistant Engineer • Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division, Bushire. Subject;-Schedule of demands under 50-C.W. External Affairs -1943-44. Sir, In reply to your Circular letter No. 26/352. dated the $5/17th August 1942,1 have the honour to inform you that, unless some unforseen contingency arises,no original v.»orks,additions or alterations in the Agency buildings will be required during the financial year 1943-44. I have etc., For Political Agent,Bahrein ILtelegram *roin xO uQ • ^ated f assistant isingineer, ^ushire* political, Balirain. K ■J \ \\^&gt; 26th January, 1243* x»esident has noticed unsatisfactoiTy accommodation provided for Bahrain Confidential ^f^ice and wish it to be completely overhauled# rrovision exists in current rublic »orks depart ment budget for v converting 2 small rooms of confidential office into one laig’e room /# if you consider this sufficient please have the estimates prepared by Bahrain -ovemment engineer, C since there is no xublic itorks depart* ment sub-ordinates at •‘■'ahrain )* if however you consider more extensive recons traction is required please have the estimates prepared accordingly and telegraph cost.The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to : H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahra in. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents. Advisers Office, No ^ 3 5/ Manamah, Bahrain. Dated:— February 15, 1945. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. Plans prepared by the public Works De par trie nt. Reference to previous correspondence :' 4 Tel: Fro mi To: No: Dated: G.T.C. Political, Bahrain Britconsul, Bushire 73 18.2.43 iour tel. January 26th Bahrain confidential office. After consultation Capt. Shaw H.iii. professional architect, I have had estimate prepared for approximately Rs 2000. This covers substantial extent!on and overhaul existing accocmodation. POLITICALTel i t^rom i To t Dated: Reed t G.T.C. ^ Assistant iiigineer, Bus hi re Political, Bahrain 20.2.43 21.2.43 Your tel.73 (Mut) carry out work (Mut) locally estimate (Mut) and bill for the work done must be sent to reach this office before March 31st. ASSTENG2RNo. &amp; —18/6 Political Agency, Bahrain. Date April 194S. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to : — The Assistant Engineer, Bushire and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document (s) cm Reference to previous correspondenoe This Agency telegran No.112,dated the 31st March 1943 No. &amp; date of enclosure Subject l*Bill dated 30.3.43 from the Supdt.P•'#.D. Bahrain Government for hs 1212/3/- Bahrain Confidential Office - alterations to. 2.Bill dated the Supdt. Government 31.3.43 from P.'V .D.Bahrain for fis 433/-/- 3 v C *I • i?. j£l- 3 • '3 H ® Tel T.e. From Assistant Engineer, 3u shire. To Political, Bahrain. Dated 11.4.43 ■ Reed. 13.4. 43 ■lire description and measurement of work done confidential office. ASSTETTGEH Blu« print and statement showing the descript!errand measurements of work done forwarded to the Assistant Engineer, Bus hire, under P.L.No. %oJ -18/6,dated / ^ : April 1943IG.C.P.—M 21 — 2 , 00 , 000 - 6 - 21 —P 4 * (st) . ^ J 3o - V3 EXPRESS LETTER. ^ Gob 156 c. J [N.B.—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.] rVf From « v . \ O' \ * * I. P. G. Sub-Division, Busnire. The Assistarit Engineer, // To The PolibiCcU. Agent, Baiirciln • 4/oob. ^^dshii^ Dated—2D tin Lay , 1943 « With referenc^to^your dated tii_e.,_4_oh_ , _i^&gt;±3 4 _; enclosed please^muster rolls cis desired. ai -estimate fan tiie v^ork ndaitions ana Alterations Lo the Confidential Office in the Agency at Bahrain amounting to •Rs. 1649/- has bee n p repared ana sanctioned aria arran^e i aent s are being mane to sena you the amount* In the meantime the v/ages of the coolies may be paru by you P.-fru' Lj\ The Political agent, Bahrain. Memorandum Reference your endorsement Ro. 807 -18 dated 19-4-1943. A Govt. Draft No. G/48/099018 dated 3-7-1943 for Rs. 1647/14 is sent herewith for payment to the contractor in connection with the work, ' Additions &amp; Alterations to the Confidential office in the agency at Bahrain'.' The acknowledgement and signature of the contractor may please be taken on tile bill and the work order which are enclosed herewith. The amohnt has been shown as a temporary advance against your name in the books of this office which will be cleared on receipt back of the bill duly acknowledged. f V ^ assistant l&amp;igineer. Independent Persian Gulf, Sub-Division.To 7 No. 26/nW Bushire, 9th. iuigust f 1943. The roliticul j\ger*% 9 Baiiraln.^/ The Political /igent, Muscat. 'Ihe Political -.igent, Kuwait. The H.B.M’s Consul, Bandar abbas, iubject;- Schedule of demands under ICxtemal affairs - 1944-46. Sir, I have the honour to request you to kindly state your requirements of ori^ijial works and. additions and alter ations which you consider necessary to be carried out in the agency build ings, during the financial year 1944 - 46. as the schedule of demands are required to reach the Government of India by the 16th. October, 1943 vide para 3 appendix 8 of Public Works account Cede, it is requested that the information called for in para x above may Kindly be furnished through the Secretary to Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, so as to reach this off5.ee by the middle of Septamber, 1943. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Divn.I , 'a, bV 1 G.T.G. Political A^ent, Bahrain Britconsul, Bushire UM 7 422 8th November 1943. hi' Telegram From To No. Dated Request sanction for expenditure uf Hs.BjbOCl, in current year for essential additional accommoda tion for English uffice. Flans have been examined and approved by Political Resident PoliticalTelegram From To No. Dated G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain Britconsul, Bushire 423 8th November 1943. n Request provision of Ps.1350 in current year for essential alterations to bedroom side of Agency to provide additional accommodation. PoliticalThe Executive Engineer, Independent Sub-Division, Persian Sulf, ausnire. f7 The cal ^gent, Bahrain. with referen eptemoer 1547/14 j. nave e to your memo no ^l^-itt/b dated o returning tlje j^ank uraft for tne nonour to state^that the iytn Hs 15 bill has since been corrected as desired bjr you and a fresh Dank j^raft iNo34521-y dated the ld&gt;th October ly^o lot ks io^u/o/- is lorvfardea Herewith. Please furnish the actcnowledgement receipt for the same at an early date. ^he bill which has already been acknowledged has been retained in this office for transmission to the Accountant General Central Revenues New uelhi. i have the honour to oe, §ii. ( | i. Jfi' ^ our mot? t c m 4 /j Executive Engineer, i’.G.i. uivin. ^»v^ Bushire - a y,*Mo. 447 From Political, Bahrain, ro Britconsul, Bushire. Dated 17th November 1943. iteferenee my telegrams Nos, 422 , 423, 424, dated November 8th. 2. nequest that sanction nay be accorded as soon as possible as opportunity now exists of obtaining materials and skilled workers. POLITICALv- \ Tel. tio. t'rom To Date cl 2 . 566 political, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushire. 28th November 1943. Keference your telegram No. A/1775, tfork v.dll bo can-ied out by* Bahrain Government P.W.D. who drew up plans. POLITICAL A28th November 1943 D.O.No.C/1648. My dear Belgrave, Thank you very much Indeed for permitting your P.W.D. Supervisor to supervise the construction of a room • at the Agency. I am going to tres$pass further on your kindness and ask you to allow him to supervise an enlargement to our down-stairs office. There is no immediate hurry about it and if you could see your way to making him availab when not required for State work I shoul be grateful. Yours sincerely C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain.hfom Political Bahrain To Brltconsul Bus hire Hope a ted HO ■ U r’(?r&lt;rii:n ) o# Jelhi •iRted nunry 194^1 The flyproof vfirr of the Agency la in a very dilapidated atntc due to the dessp elinfite of Balm in* Ac it will only stand a couple of montho raore it i'j essential that it should be renewed, but it cannot be bought locniiy^. I have tJieref re placed nn order i&lt; r six rolla from India* It is re ’-esteci ti^it the Govemnent of In ie ray kindly be asked tt allow ita exnort from India and t&lt;&gt; sdivi he expoi^t license urgently to the Army Kavy dtcrcs, Xamchi*NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY. The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named :— Prefix Letters and Number of Messaje, Office of Ori(in, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructi ons—if any. Printed in England. jut-Y 1U40. (5.000 pade.) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.)' 5/-168 V- -ft Clerk's / Time J / J* Z 7 //d / XRV77/M S BUSHIRE 41 11 1600 BG ANTEN. POLITICAL BAHRAIN /hit E/9 REFERENCE YOUR TELEGRAM NO 466 DATED TWENTYEIGHT NOVEMBER STOP PLEASE WIRE PROGRESS OF WORKS AND • INTIMATE WHEN BILLS WILL BE SENT FOR PAYMENT AS FINAL BUDGET REVIEW CANNOT BE SENT TO GOVT OF INDIA WITHOUT THIS INFORMATION BRITCONSUL. N MARK YOUR REPLY *2tia €?m/ietua£,- © Statement ehouing expenditure incurred by the Political Agent, Bahrain, up to 31.12.43, in connection *ith the hoctene ion to i-nglieh 01 lice, vide eanction contained in Buehire telegram No.A/1775, dated 25.11.43. 25.11.43. Goet of 175 window glaeeeb,vide receipted bill attached. Re.275/- Rupeee two hundred and eeventyfive only. no. -i8/tiv. Political Agency, Bahrain. The J anuary. 1944. lorwarded, with compliments, to the Executive Engineer, Independent Persian Gull Sub-Division, Buehire, lor favour of an early settlement. lor Political Agent,Bahrain r-« Citateraent bhowing expenditure incurred by tbe Political Agent,Bahrain ,during the month of January 1944 in connection v.ith the extension to Englibh Office, vide sanction contained in Bushire telegram No.A/1775, dated the 25th November 1943. 19-lr44 Particulars . Amount. Paid to the Superintendent ,Bahrain Govt.P.'fc.D.wages of labourers as per Muster rolls attached. 228- 10-0 — do —tio— being cost of materials as ptr receipted bills attached. 398-10- 0 a otal C27- 4-0 Rupees six hundred and twenty seven -/4/-only. -4/18-IV. Political Agency, Bjihrain Ihe February 1944. hor'Aarded with compliments to the -executive i.rgineer Independent Persian dull sub—is i^n , Bushire lor favour of an early settlement ,with reference to telegram Uo.A/%775, dated the 25th November 1943 from the Secretary to the Bon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Crulf, But hire. v Polit ical Agent, Bahrain.0)77 g.t.c. Political Agont, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushirc. Tel. From To No. 120 Dated 19th February 1944. Your telegram E/9. Bed room and English office completed. Confidential office nearing completion. All bills being paid and passed on to Executive Engineer for adjustment. Anticipated savings: Dressing room Rs. 200/. Confidential Office Rs. 400/. V Additional funds required for following essential items not provided for in estimates. 1. Removal fans to new office. 2. Additional fans and lights in both offices 3. Revomal and relaying existing wooden floor from present English office to new room. And cost additional wood. 4 ‘ ^ en if savings are used for these items further Rs. 450 Required for purchase extra wood. Please wire sanction. -Political-QGvr.RjiM'-nT or ba.irain STaTE SHGIMEER'S dspahticnt NO.'.re/' | /63 Bahrain. I7th Febr., 1944 Dated: ?.2nd Saffar, 1353 The Superintendent, Public Works Department, Bahrain. Memorand’im:- With reference to your verbal request in connection with wiring the Agency new rooms. The cost of wiring for three light points complete would be approximately Rs. 90- 0- 0 60- 0- 0 18- 0- 0 -ditto- three fan points -ditto- three plugs This allows for thirty feet of twin lead covered wire for each light and fan point, and 10 feet per switchpiug.Any extr*No. -18/6. Political Afjoncy, Bnhrain. Tinted /- February 1944. A To The Army and Navy Stores, Comer of Somerset &amp; Clarke Street, Camp , Karachi ITemo random. Reference your letter dated the 1st February 1944. 2. ‘/ill you please supply as early as possible six rolls of copper #nuze of 30 mesh. As req ested a Bank Draft for us. 1,000/- is enclosed. Please acknowledge receipt and later on send a detailed account. 3. As already informed in my memorandum No. 13, dated the 1944-the Government of India has been requested to issue an export licence and to forward it direct t° you. ^ v v for Political Agent,Bahrain?04. V — — Pi-m-aifd Britconaul. Buahira. No. _12S1=V44 Dated [ 2--T 194 ^ Reference you , ' Expr«38 letter No. 14 dated 3rd e January 194 4 Flyproof wire for the Bahrain Agency, 2 . Export license issued t»o t»hQ Aruiy an d Na .vy Stores, Karachi e The issue of the above has been authorised.The fir*t line of thi* Telegram contain* the following particulars in the order named :— Prefix Letters end Number of Messeje, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Due, Time bended in end C 's^l instruction!—if eny. Printed in England. Aug 1941. (9,000 pads) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Clerk’s Time Circuit. Nafne^-I Received. 2225 A A^_/£ £ 3^ • &amp; XRV48/BG S BUSH IRE 16 22 1600 BG ANTEN NO E/14 POLITICAL BAHRAIN YOUR TELEGRAM NO 120 DATED 19TH FEBRUARY ADDITIONAL RUPEES 450 SANCTIONED BRITC0NSUL 'W MARK YOUR ‘REPLY ~ &lt; VZa £m/ie?ual^ NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION Of THIS COPY.D.O. No. 377-43 Bahrain, Feb f v, 20, 1944 For the last month Mr. A. M. Jafar, the Superin tendent of the Public Works Department, has been occu pied with work at the Agency. As I found that he was unable to carry on this work and also properly super vise other jobs I gave him instructions to stop all Government work 'till he had finished what you needed. He has now applied for leave in May, when he is due leave to India, and will be a way ^or about five months. There are several building works which I want to get completed before he goes; one job has been started and is waiting till he is free, for completion. I gather that there is another building project at the Agency which would probably take some time. Under the circumstances it will not be possible for him to undertake this because as soon as he has finished his present work at the Agency I want to put him on to some of the more urgent Government work. My difficulty is that 1 have only Mr. Jafar and two not very capable overseers for all the repairs and upkeep of the existing buildings and any new work that it is neces sary to carry out. If I was not so short handed I could make some one else available. Major T. Hickinbotham, G.I.S., O.E.E., h.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.*0 •No . ill - l%k Political A^Gncy, Bahrain. Bated Fob run ry 1944 I quite appreciate your difficulties and am very {rrateful to you for your cooperation in allowing Mr. ' »V • Jafar to advise us and superintend the v/ork that lias been and is bein£ done* 2. I know of no other building project in view. If Sir Geoffrey proposes to erect offices he will presumably send his Bushire overseer over here• •D.Belgrave Esquire, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, BahrainURGENT No. f/S -18/6 Political Agency, Bahrain. The 24th February,1944 To The Kxocutive Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Division, Bushire. MEMOKANDUK The undermentioned payments have been made by this Agency on your behalf in connection with the extension of English and Confidential Offices and repairs to the Agency Sitting room. 1. Vide my endorsement No.291-18/6, Rs. dated 27th January,1944. 275-00-0 2. Vide my endorsement No.292-18/6, . dated the 27th January,1944. / 1,144-7 -6 3. Vide my endorsement No.455-18/6, dated the 17th February 1944. 627-4 -0 / /' 4. From the 1st to the 24th February, 1944,(Account will bo sent after the close of the month.) 2,669-10-0 Total 4,716-5 -6 2. Will you please refund mo Rs*4,716-5-6 by the first available mail to enable me to recoup my Deposit Account from which other payments cannot at present be made for want of funds. 3« The sanctioned grants for the works mentioned above are Rs.6,300/- out of which Rs.4,716/5/6 have been spent. The balance of Ps.l,583/10/6 may also be remitted to me by \ first available opportunity to enable me to meet the charges as I have no funds at my disposal from which to make payments on your behalf• * &gt; ^ f ^ * 5 k i h -&gt; /}. Political Agent, Bahrain. o~-eyi &amp; ■ 3- ^ 3 / &lt;r/-No. 6 o 7 ' £/ 3 of 1363 Office of the Adviser to the G-overmrient, Bahrain Dated, 14th R/Awal, 1365 March 9, 1S44. H. B. M T s political ^_ent, Bahrain. ' J . ^ 7% // . &lt; • Memorandum: - When the public '.'forks Department began work on the Agency Office as no cement was provided 33 bags of cement were used from the public Works Department stock, which is very snail. The cost of this cement has been paid. Would it be possible for you to allow us to refund the price of the cement and to receive an equivalent number of bags of cerent from your stock in place of the cement used by the Public Works Dept.? Adviser to the Government. S.2G.T.C. Fi^om Political Agont, 3 all rain* To ITavy Charge, Karachi No. 200 Dated 16th Narch 1944. Following for M.W.T. Representative b egins. Army and Navy stores Karachi have applied to you lor shipment one package conpcr gauze for me. Please assist, as gauze required urgently, ends. 3AF. Political Agent.-18/6 POLITICAL AGENCY, i Bahrain. The fC LL. March 1944 To The Advisor, Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Memorandum. Reference your memorandum No. 507-43, dated the 9th March 1944. 2 . I am ready to issue 33 bags of cement at Rs 4/^per bag. Please instruct your P.tf.D. Superviseor to collect them on payment. ij a i}‘ w '' . Political Agent, Bahrain. „ •No l/oT-18/6 To POLITICAL. AGENCY* BAHRAIN. Tlic /S tx April 1944. The Army &lt;P: Navy Stores* Comer of Somersets Clarke Street, Karachi. Monorandom. Reference your letter dated the 4th April 1944. 2. ‘/hen the copper gauze is despatched I should be advised telegraphically. for Political Agent, Bahrain.,.£-■&lt;030 S'? • ') ■ H Wo. PY/Q-26/ /ig- BRITISH HhSIDEtTCif AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. - Dated the ^ July 1944 *om:— To s- The Executive Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division* The Political ^gent, Bahrain. 'y/ p I Subject:- Schedule of demands under 50-C.',/#C*- Bxternal Affairs for the year 1945-46. Sir, I have the honour to request you to state your requirements of Original Works, additions and alterations, and special repairs, which you consider absolutely necessary to be carried out during the year 1945-46. 2. As the Schedule of demand for 1945-46 is required to be submitted to the Government of India by the 15th Octobei 1944, vide para 3 Appendix 8 of P.V/.a. Code, it is requested that the information called for in para 1 of this letter may kindly b e furnished through# the Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf so as to reach this office by the 7th of September 1944 at the latest. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Executive Engineer.I enclose herewith for your inforrantion and comments a copy of letter TTo. P/D-2G/133, dated the 24th July 1944, received from the Sxecutive * v &gt; ^ 2ngine er, Bushire. 2. .1 understand that in ? ,T arch last when the Sxecutive Engineer jas at Bahrain you discussed viith him the question 1 of construction of a new office for tlie Political Resident and showed him the site. I understand you also discussed projects for a new gateway for the Agency and for covering the Agency stairs with wood. Unfortunately there arc no papers in the office. 3. fould you please let me know what action you iish me to take. c/o U. Bunn, Esquire Manager, Eastern Bank Ltd., Karachi.Printed la England. (4,100. pad Prefix OfficiaPrinted in England. Sept. 1942. ( 4 , 100 . pads, f CABLE AND WIRELESS . LIMITED. (incorporated in enolano.I 5/-16 8 The first line of this Telegram contains the Prefix Letter* and Number of Message. Office of OrigH^t Number o^-Wprds, Date, Time handed Official instructions—if any. particulars in the order named:— in and J — 7^ Clerk's Tlmjf CK „ A Name. ReceivVd- RAT / b' QV129/T DF KARACHI SUB 11 l 8 QD FIL LC POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN = GOODS SHIPPED BILL FOLLOWS = / = ARMY NAVY STORES = \ 1 1 * MARK YOUR REPLY *Dla Jm/ie?uaC ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.' ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES. POLITICAL BAHRAIN = ^ A I N '' E/124 YOUR TELEGRAM NO 549 DATED SEVENTEENTH AUGUST STOP PLEASE TELEGRAPH AGE OF CEMENT STOP PAYMENT CANNOT BE MADE TILL . ESTI MATE FOR RESIDENTS BAHRAIN OFFICE IS SANCTIONED = = EXECUTIVE 'ENGINEER = MARK YOUR REPLY 'tjg Jm/ieSua&amp;ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES. RV53/BG S BUSH IRE 2C/19 27 1800 BEGETAT IMPORTANT POLITICAL BAHREIN A /1443 SHIP BY FIRS T REPEAT FIRST OPPORTUNITY bOO HALF 1 200 BAGS PWD CEMENT TO BUSH I RE ” H I C K I N b 0 T,H A / “ IxO. orfs . MARK YOUR REPLY “Via SmA&amp;uaC20/2, r 1 2 n 3 t X o f, » 26/4/37 m v«»* * rfOtE STRIKE CLAUSES (b) (c) This Policy coveu^-' (a) the risks excluaW'from the Standard Form of English Marine Policy by the clause:— 'Warranted free of loss or damage caused by strikers locked-out workmen-or persons taking part in laoour disturbances riots or civil commotions, theft or pilferage by, or other loss of or damage to the property hereby insured caused by, strikers locked-out work men or persons taking part in labour disturbances riots or civil commotions. destruction of or damage to the property hereby insured caused by persons acting maliciously. The above-mentioned clauses shall not cover theft pilferage loss or damage caused by hostilities warlike operations civil war, or by revolution rebellion insurrection or civil strife arising therefrom. Warranted free of loss or damage proximately caused by delay inherent vice or loss of market, or of any claim for expenses arising fro 1 ” delay except such expenses as would be recoverable in principle in English law and practice under York-Antwerp Rules 1924- General average and salvage charges payable (subject to the terms of these clauses) according to Foreign Statement or York-Antwerp Rules if in accordance with the contract of affreightment Claims for loss or damage within the terms of these clauses shall be payable without reference to conditions of average. Held covered at a premium to be arranged in case of deviation or change of voyage, or other variation of the adventure by reason of the exercise of anv liberty granted to the shipowner or charterer under the contract of affreightment, or of any omission or error in the description of the interest vessel or voyage. In the event &gt;f the exercise of any liberty granted to the shipowner or charterer under the contract of affreightment whereby such contract is terminated at a port or place other than the destination named therein, the goods are held covered in terms of these clauses at a premium to be arranged until sold and delivered at such port or place, or notice be given to Underwriters to terminate the policy whichever first occurs; or, [ he goods be forwarded to the destination named herein or to any other destination, until arrival at destination (suoject to the provisions of clause 4 as to the period covered after discharge overside from the overseas vessel at final port) This insurance attaches from the time the goods leave the Warehouse and/or Store at the place named in the policy for the commencement of the transit and continues during the ordinary course of transit, including customary transhipment if any, until the goods are discharged overside from the overseas vessel at the final port. Thereafter the insurance continues whilst the goods are in transit and/or awaiting transit until delivered to final warehouse at the destination named in the policy or until the expiry nf K davs (or 30 days if the destination to which the goods are insured is outside the limits of the port) whichever shall first occur 1 he time limits referred to above to be reckoned from midnight of the day on which the discharge overside of the goods hereby insured from the overseas vessel is comoleted. Held covered at a premium to be arranged m the event of transhipment, if any, other than as above and/or in the event of delay in excess of the above time limits arising from circumstances beyond the control of the Assured. 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 n 12 13 M 15 t6 17 18 to 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 43 44 45 46 47 48 49 5C 5» 52 53 54 NOTE —It is necessary lor the Assured to give prompt notice to Underwriters when he becomes aware ot an event for which he Is 'held covered' under this po Icy and the right to such cover Is dependent on compliance with this obligation 1 -/ 8. U. A.I [iJVOD VOi iO I t»(ii ■'(d vdo 1 imBiiBW’* joo-b^Joc! onudiuJiiiu Aiiq io td) aiari YHaqo-iq oaisq to 11901 to noinmlMb (D) 519 Q xd b^^uBO bsnoiJneta-avodB 9 f' i jiliieoii xd bazoBO aafitn^b o to nohosnuzni nodlouai I 1o sail baJnK-nfiW mlozaol io 9 ‘jiv Jnoit Ini znvqxa dona Jqaoxa x- - 1 oY t 'bnu aoilociq bne v’«I one ogBiavB IsTinaO anibiODos ^sauBb oxorii &gt;j ad i d iiw soqBbioooB ni • nsb no asol lol amUIO j sonoia^si JiiodJiw aldByifq r ••“. • - bftt OJ boincia xn^dit xd* vpji 1 o io .mooiidsisinB .‘j^BXOV to Itusaav ,19X9 9 dn&lt; Inaya aril nl Bilnoo adi labnu laionBdo tdq io Jioq » is boiBfiicfn^j baiavoo bbd sts abooa sd* ilab bns bioa lilnu bsaOBTiK qiuiiansi oi sidthwiabnJ oi sdl oi bsbiEvviol sd aboos a,; *. •,2»t&gt; V r\ gtflT ) yrf-.V InaxiiUfdznini 'rib i l; nft aril tB bae&amp;v 2K98i«''' jj ?1 jiansti ni sis «boos 9 'i arii u a toq od: aooi so ,02 aril aril lafiriv- datsw (Biifl , ?i ^o srii abiaiuo oi banal at o aatfidoain baislqmoj lamaid^nBti \U 20/2/43 INSTITUTE CARGO \ loK! 6 1 j. This insurance attaches from the timo the poods leave the Warehouse and/or Store at the place 2 named in the policy for the commencement of the transit and continues during the ordinary course of 3 transit, ineluding customary transhipment if any, until the goods are discharged overside from the 4 overseas vessel at the final nort. Thereafter U*e i$ l pjra,ico continues whilst the poods are in transit 6 and/or awaiting transit until delivered to final ^irdfiousc at the destination named in the policy or until 6 the expiry of lo days (or 30 days if the destination to w hich the poods are insured is outside the limits 7 of the port) whichever shall first occur. The time limits referred to above to be reckoned front mid- fc) night of the day on which the discharge overside of the goods hereby insured from the overseas vessel 9 is completed. Held covered at a premium to be ananpod in the event of transhipmont, if any, other 10 than as above and/or in the event of delay in excess of tho above time limits arising from circumstances LI beyond the control of the Assured. 12 2- Including transit by craft, raft and/or lighter to and from the vessel. Each craft, raft, and/or 13 lighter to be deemed a separate insurance. The Assured are not to be prejudiced by any agreement .4 exempting lightermen from liability. 15 3. Held covered at a premium to be arranged in case of deviation or change of voyage, or other [ti variation of the adventure by reason of the exercise of any liberty granted to tho shipowner or charterer 17 under the contract of affreightment, or of any omission or error in the description of tho interest vessel 8 or voyage. .9 4- In tho event of the exercise of any liberty granted to tho shipowner or charterer under the !0 contract of affreightment whereby such contract is’terminated at a port or place other than the destina- ;‘l tion named therein, the goods are held covered in terms of the policy at a premium to be arranged i'2 until sold and delivered at such port or place, or notice be given to Underwriters to terminate the policy 53 whichever first occurs; or, if the goods be forwarded to the destination named herein or to any other 54 destination, until arrival at destination (subject to the provisions of Clause 1 as to the period covered 55 aft«\r_discharge overside from the overseas vessel at final port); provided always that no liability shall !G atU 1 . , to this policy for loss or damage occurring after the termination of such contract of affreightment 57 and-proximately caused by delay or inherent vice or nature of the subject matter insured. 5 . Warranted free from average under the percentage specified in tho policy, unless general, or the iding this warranty the Underwriters are to pay Warehouse u warehouse clause. Craft, Ac., clause. r&gt;oviatiwu clause. Liberties clause. Termination of contract of affreightment. Average clause. Bailee clause vessel or craft be stranded, sunk or burnt, but notwithstanding mis warranty me L/naerwriiors are to pay the insured value of any package which may be totally lost in loading’ transhipment or discharge, H also for any loss of or damage to the interest insured which may reasonably be attributed to fire,’ collision, or contact of the vessel and/or craft and/or conveyance with any external substance (ice included) other than water, or to discharge of cargo at port of distress. This clause shall operate during the whole period covered by the policy. 6 . General Average and Salvage Charges payable according to Foreign Statement or per York- G/A clause. Antwerp Rules if in accordance with the contract of affreightment. 7. The Assurred are net to be prejudiced by the presence of the negligence clause and/or latent Bill of Lading defect clause in the Bills of Lading and/or Charter Party. The seaworthiness of the vessel as between ‘*c., clause, tho Assured and the Underwriters is hereby admitted and the wrongful act or misconduct of tho ship owner or his servants causing a loss is not to defeat the recovery by an innocent Assured if the loss in tho absence of such wrongful act or misconduct would have been a loss recoverable on tho policy. With leave to sail with or without pilots, and to tow and assist vessels or craft in all situations, and to be towed. 8 . Warranted free from liability for loss of or damage to the goods whilst in the custody or care of any carrier or other bailee who may be liable for such loss or damage but only to tho extent of such carrier’s or bailee’s liability. Warranted free of any claim in respect of goods shipped under a Bill of Lading or contract of carriage stipulating that tho carrier or other bailee shall have the benefit of any insurance on such goods, but this warranty shall apply only to claims for which the carrier or other bailoo is liable under the Bill of Lading or contract of carriage. Notwithstanding the warranties contained in this clause it is agreed that in tho event of loss of or damage to the goods by a peril or perils insured against by this policy for which the carrier or bailee denies or fails to meet his liability tho Underwriters shall advance to the Assured as a loan without interest a sum equal to the amount they would have been liable to pay under this policy but for the above warranties the repayment thereof to bo conditional upon and only to the extent of any recovery which the Assured may receive from the carrier or bailee. It is further ag direction and control carrier or bailee as the underwriters snan require ana tne underwriters agree to pay suen propo of the costs and expenses of any such suit or proceedings as attach to the amount advanced under the policy. 9. Warranted free of capture, seizure, arrest, restraint or detainment, and the consequences thereof or of any attempt thereat; also from the consequences of hostilities or w-arlike operations, whether there be a declaration of war or not; but this warranty shall not exclude collision, contact with any fixed or floating object (other than a mine or torpedo), stranding, heavy weather or tiro unless caused directly (and independently of the nature of the voyage or service which tho vessel concerned or, in the case of a collision, any other vessel involved therein, is performing) by a hostile act by or against a belligerent power; and for the purpose of this warranty ‘‘power” includes any authority niaiii’uiiiin^ naval, military or air forces in association with a power. thcr warranted free from tho consequences of civil war, revolution, rebellion, insurrection or ‘ arising therefrom, or piracy. Should Clause No. 9 be deleted, the Institute War Clauses (25.1.43) shall be deemed to form part of this insurance. 10. Warranted free of loss or damage caused by strikers, locked-out workmen, or persons taking part in labour disturbances riots or civil commotions. 1 Should Clause No. 10 be deleted, the Institute Strike Clauses (26.4.37) shall be deemed to form part of this Insurance. f. c. A S clause. Furt civil »^Mfe bsiueti | lotInava isTUkaA aiU )o loilnoo 8A 3fti T*1 /Uie 8939 n ?.i tl-r .aiOB Strikes, hols and civil commotion clause. It is necessary for the Assured to give prompt notice to Underwriters when he becomes aware ol an event for which he is “held covered” under this policy and the right to such cover Is dependent on compliance with this obligatlcr miudad ol ni&amp;h U. Ar * B OoY] s.'43- INSTITUTE i'/ R CLAUSES. Sta»irfard Form of English Marine Policy 1 2 3 4 5 6 ; 8 o i6 n 12 13 14 15 16 1/ 18 1 his Policy covers:— (a) the risk- excluded by the clause:— “Warranted free of capture, seizure, arrest, restraint or detain ment, and the consequences thereof or of any attempt thereat; also from the consequences of nostilities or warlike operations, wnether there be a declaration of war or not; but this warranty snail not exclude collision, contact with any fixed or floating object (other than a mine or torpedo), stranding, heavy weather or fire unless caused directly (and independently of the nature of the voyage or service which tne vessel concerned or, inthecase of a collision, any other vessel involved therein, is performing by a hostile act oy or against a belligerent power; ana for the purpose of this warranty ‘‘power” includes any authority maintaining naval, military or air forces in association with a power Further warranted free from the consequences of civil war, revolution, rebellion, insurrection, or civil strife arising theretrom, or piracy.” (b) loss of or damage to the property hereby insured caused by:— 19 (1) hostilities warlike operations civil war, revolution rebellion 20 insurrection or civil strife arising therefrom. 21 ( 2 ) mines torpedoes bombs or other engines of war. . 22 but excluding loss or damage covered by the Standard Form 23 of English Marine Policy with the Free of Capture &amp;c. Clause (as 24 quoted in I (a) ) inserted therein. 25 U &gt;©twlthstandlng the foregoing: — 26 k a) the insurance against the said risks shall not attach to the interest 27 hereby insured or to any part thereof 28 (i) prior to being on board an overseas vessel, 29 (For the purpose of this Clause 2 an overseas vessel 3° shall be deemed to mean a vessel carrying the interest 3» from one port or place to another where such voyage 32 involves a sea passage by that vessel) 33 (ii) after being discharged overside from an overseas vessel at 34 the final port of discharge 35 or 3b after expiry of 15 days counting from midnight of the day 37 on which the overseas vessel is safely anchored or moored 38 at the final port of discharge, 30 whichever shall first occur, 4 t&gt; (Hi) at a port or place of transhipment to another overseas vessel 41 after expiry of 15 days (counting from midnight of the 42 day on which the overseas vessel entering with the interest is 43 safely anchored or moored) until the interest is on board 44 the on-carrying overseas vessel. 45 In the event of the exercise of any liberty granted to the Shipowner 46 or Charterer under the contract of affreightment whereby such contract 4/ is terminated at a port or place other than the destination named 48 therein such port or place shall be deemed the final port of discharge 49 for the purpose of this Clause 2 . 5© (b) this policy is warranted free of any claim based upon loss of, or frustra- 51 tion of, the insured voyage or adventure caused by arrests restraints 52 or detainments of Kings Princes Peoples Usurpers or persons attempt- 53 ing to usurp power. 54 If anything contained In this policy shall be Inconsistent with this Ctause 2 55 it shall to the extent ot such Inconsistency be null and void. 56 j. Warranted free of loss ©r damage proximately caused by delay inherent vice 57 or loss of market, or of any claim for expenses arising from delay except such 58 # expenses as would be recoverable in principle in English law and practice under 59 y Vork-Antwerp Rules 1924 . bo 4. General average and salvage charges payable (subject 10 the terms of these 6) clauses) according to Foreign Statement or York-Antwerp Rules if in accordance 62 with the contract of affreightment. 63 &gt;. Claims for loss or damage within the terms of these clauses shall be payable 64 without reference to average conditions. 65 t. Held covered (subject to the terms of these clauses) at a premium to be 6 t. arranged in case of deviation or change of voyage, or other variation of the 67 adventure by reason of the exercise of any liberty granted to the shipowner or 68 charterer under the contract of affreightment, or of any omission or error in the 60 description of the interest vessel or voyage. 70 *0TE,—It Is necessary for the Assured to give prompt notice to Underwriters when they become aware of an event for which they are “held covered” under this policy and the right to such cover Is dependent on compliance with this obligatioa. ft U. A.AGENCY. oOnm^^rty of ut Policies -issued abrorul payable in the United Kingdom , required- by law to have a Government Stamp affixed i iin 10 days after receipt in the United Ki ngdom. 44/12375.’ table in Karachi • )xch. °EES nium at 900/- 6-10-05? plus 1.7/40$ i0 %=Rs. 15 2 8 3 ar 2 .^10/. \p Duty.’ -ef,® w m *?&amp; } Warranted free of f 9at&gt;tur%)feiiure Out rest k^ehraitU or ■J detainment, and the consequences thereof or °J attempt thereat: ® $\PQ?riot?Tioil war, revolution rebellion j insurrection or civil strife arising therefrbm, or piracy. Warranted free of loss or damage caused by strikers jf/pedout workmen or persons taking part in labour itnturbances riots or civil commotions. Should the risks excluded by Clause 1 (F. C. &lt;k S. Clause) be reinstated in this policy by deletion of the said \ Clause, or should the risks or any of them mentioned in the same clause or the risks of mines torpedoes bombs or other engines of war be insured under this policy, • then notwithstanding anything in this policy to the fcontrary, Fa) the insurance against the said risks shall not attach to the interest hereby insured or to any part thereof (i) prior to being on board an overseas vessel. (For the purpose of this Clause 3 an overseas vessel shall be deemed to mean a vessel carrying the interest from one port or place to another where such voyage involves a sea passage by that vessel). (ii) after being discharged overside from an overseas vessel at the final port of discharge or .... after expiry of 15 days counting from midnight of the day on which the overseas vessel is safely anchored or moored at the final port of discharge, whichever shall first occur, at a port or place of transhipment to another overseas vessel after expiry of 15 days (counting from midnight of the day on which the overseas vessel entering with the interest is safely anchored or moored) until the interest is on board the on-carrying overseas vessel. In the event of the exercise of any liberty granted to the Shipowner or Charterer under the contract of affreightment whereby such contract is terminated at a port or place other than the destination named therein such port or place shall be deemed the final port of discharge for the purpose of this Clause 3. • (b) this policy is warranted free of any claim based ■ upon loss of, or frustration of, the itisured voyage or adventure caused by arrests restraints or detain ments of Kings Princes Peoples Usurpers or persons attempting to usurp power. If anything contained in this policy shall be consistent with Clause 3 (a) and 3 (b) or. either , tl^n it shall to the extent of such inconsistency i^l and void. INSTITUTE DANGEROUS DRUGS CLAUSE. It is understood and agreed that no claim under this -plicy will be paid in respect of drugs to which the Vternntional Opium Convention of 1912 applies unless (1) The drugs shall le expressly declared as such in the policy and the name of the country from which, and the name of the country to which they are consigned shall be specifically stated in the Policy and (2) The proof of loss is accompanied either by a licence, certificate or authorization issued by the Government of the country to which the drugs are consigned shouting that the importation of the consignment into that country has been approved by that Government, or, alternatively, by a licence certificate or authori zation issued by the Government of the country from which the drugs are consigned showing that the export of the consignment to the destination stated has been approved by that Government and ( 8 ) The route by which the drugs were conveyed was usual and customary. In the event of damage arising under this Policy no claims will be admitted unless notice of the damage be given to '3&amp;ortli Clitna Snsurantfu Companp, Utmtteb. to* **A“»*3'* *'&lt;“•*■*“* Mmbfr ‘' nmiM) 3n tfje iSatne of #ob: amen. Messrs.Mackinnon Ifeickenzie &amp; Co.C &amp; B.Dept•,Karacni, Be it known that „ . r ftrw1 th - vame or Names of all and every other Person or Persons to ^SViTe^dS. nmy. orshan a^in i^o “in all do m and hereby cause himself or themselves and them, and every of them, to bo Insured lost or not lost, at and trom ^KARACHI TO BAHREIN. upon Goods and Merchandise, or Treasure, in the good Ship or Vessel called the 'WO SANG' r whproftf is Master under God, for ibis present voyage . __ *1 _ or whosoever else shall go for Master in «}« ^^^Yhe^ Mo^MerchaJ.dUe from the Master thereof, is or shall be named ®f.called: MCMtNING the Athenture^upon^ne^Mua and Merchand , 8e shall be Lading thereof on board the said Vessel, and so p ort 0 ’ ( Destination, including risk of craft to and from safely delivered from, on bowd the .said, V^ at Port Mues^nmn,^ ^ ^ ^ sUy at any p ort8 sni Merchandise, for so much as concerns the Assured are and shall be insured for ^ ’RUPEES NINE HUNDRED ONLY,0U J 'r' li*. 13&amp; The Political Agent, - 1 „ Bahrein case Ely Proof Wire. Terms t-W. P.A.Theft, Pilferage, Non-delivery, including War,Strike,Riot &amp; Civil Commotion risks -n as per clauses attached. WHEN THE RISK OF Cft^fTTO THF cam — I II —II ' ~ KEXrRESfiv ccvrr.rn S*f D VESSEL -MAY TO J 5TH ^ ^ ^ CL ^YE) GOODS LV (--r lN ' THE VESSEL at PORT OF Ln'ar tK HCNGStC ^ : Rcrvanfcs or aSSI' to^? labou^and travel for, in and about the Defence, Safeguard and Recovery of the said agreed that no acts of Insurer or ^ lir t ed er ‘^’j tu’p said COMPANY that this Writing or Policy of INSURANCE the rate arranged. ^ 4 v, n as per margin AND FURTHER, the said NORTH CHINA INSURANCE COMPANY, LIMITED. DO HEREBY covenant. promise and agree, and bind themselves, their Heirs, Executors, Goods and Chattels, in case of Loss happening to satisfy and uavKhe sum of Money by them so Assured. The settlement of all Losses or Averages, aite being duly adjusted .. , .. of the COMPANY there shall be payable by the ^UNDER3IGNEI) AGENTS, agreeably to the tenor of this PoUcy, and according to English Law and Usage. *** q n i* Saltpetre Sugar Jagry, Rice, Corn, Flour, Ghee, Seed, Grain, Tobacco, Hides, skins, Spirits, and other Lloudrs are warranted’free from Particular Average under Ten per cent. Tea and Silk under TA«e per cent, and all other G&lt;?ods free of Average under Five per cent, unless general, or the ship be stranded, sunk, or burnt. 3ln (LiHitneSg whereof we, the Agents for the 'CijUltl SltSfUTdllCf (Coiltpdlip, ILittlltcb, on beh.tH #f the said (CoiliPiUip, have hereunto subscribed our name in 1 Kfi 1*8 CVl 1 , n 14th Dayof AUgUSt Hundred and Forty ^ f OUT* t0 tl of the same tenor and date, one of which being accomplish* Regd. Rpr.Pro .Mack! one thousand Nine ,o p^ies the non Mackenzie &amp; Co. /the other ^ one to be void the nearest Lloyds Agents. V? 7 revious to the survey and certificate be signed him or diem.No. 2486-18/6 From neA POLITICAL AGSNCY/ HAHnAIN • The 31st August 1944. hinjor T« Hickinbotrinm, CO.B.fi., political Agent, Bahrain. To The Bxccutive Engineer, Indopedent Pc sian Gulf Sub-Division, Bushire. Ji'i Sir, with reference to your letter No .P7D- 26/138 dated the 24th July 1944, I have the honour to confirm my conversation of the 27th of August. ’Vo^ks arc required to be carried out in the Bahrain Agency in the following or.ler:- Stair case; No. 2. Bed -roon;v. Iron gratings; S Entrance gate Cement floors;^ Hoofs I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ^ political Agent, Bahrain. i\/ Uo To * - 18/6 Political Agency, Bahrain. The 4th September, 1944 ’-m * 0 48 The Manager, # MC S3 -Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Bahrain. MoraoranciuiTi VJill you please arrange to collect from tills Aj’oncy 30 tons of cement in 600 te/ts for shipment to the British Consulste^ Bushirej l , by the first available steamer. for 4 ^ . or Political Agent, Bahrain. lFROM XX. GRAY, MACKENZIE 8c CO., LTD. Bahrein. TO His Britannic i-lajesty’s Political Bahr e in. &lt; 4, No. v m. . Bahrain Receipt ^ ii.4iai...D«*pa&gt;^-.^.-Sf hrein » ilth Jept » 44 * Bear Sir, British^HfliCLlate General Bushire (S^Nil, 600-Bags cement, per s*s.Barjora V.334 to Bashire. With reference to your letter No 25/8-18/6 of 4th Sept, 1944. we send you herewith Bill of Lading No.l in duplicate covering the above shipment, receipt of which please acKnowledge. Encloss B/L No.l in duplicate. Yours faithfully. for GRAY, MACKENIK &amp; CO., LTD. A (y i: «» SAC.uy- er and condition by } / Obit) OHi a i •3-^4 BAHtlrilw tov a-n. gin (measurement, weight, qua is, conditions and provisions I ick, at her berth or anchorage i without deduction, vessel or cs ion, vessel or cargo lost or not elegraphic advices of non-paym&lt; » »hall not b« reaponsible for the Act of ( Htraints of princes, rulers or people, restrictioi bances. combinations of workmen or others directly or indirectly thereby and any circi iption resulting from any of the following ci get through handling, inaccuracies, obliterat ere, machinery, ruat, vermin, breakage, lea a of other goods, effects of climate or heat of at, risk of craft, or transhipment, or storage accidents to or defects latent or otherwise in 1 ess to receive and carry cargo provided the o :y, jettison, lose by thefts or robberies by se nice of the Company or otherwise, accidents l ny act neglect or default whatsoever or erro there ; collision stranding or wreck however navigation of whatsoever nature or kind an or default of the Egyptian Government or tl &gt;yment of the Company’s vessels in or asaiati erties reserved by the shipowners, they shal stage of the voyage, to delay the sailing frot n their opinion or in the opinion of the Mas lischarge to proceed to and stay at any port s ordinary route to port of discharge onoe or mails or bullion, or embarking or diaembi i or adjusting compasses, or repairing, or fo ided subsequent voyage, and all such ports, j e ; such liberty not to be considered as rest sr descriptive of the voyage or otherwise, or with liberty to sail with or without pilots, a i from the voyage for any purpose whateoevi s goods do not satisfy the imporUtion reguli shippers undertake to indemnify the shipow ;of and in the event of some or all of the go&lt; land them at any other port whatsoever nc additional freight and all expenses incurred •noe or existence of any of the following 1 —¥ ■nment of intercourse, commercial or otherw itrol or direction by any Government or othe he vessel; the Carrier and/or his Agent* and, sogers or any of them or cargo or any part th e said War, Civil War, prohibition, restrictio e voyage alter or vary or depart from the iin the vessel and/or discharge the cargo (for cut being liable for any loss or damage whals [oods are so discharged at such port or porti nsk of the Owner of the goods and the Car ng notice of such discharge to the Consignei d or implied herein, shall have liberty to cor call, delay, detention, discharge (for deliv , or any Department thereof, or any person meet thereof or by any Committee or perso i such orders or directions, and if by reaso is by the Carrier of any other liberty menti tract. Discharge under any liberty raentioc and the Owner and/or Consignee of the goo he full freight stipulated herein if not prep id/or Consignee of the goods, and if freight to carry contraband, explosives, munitions &lt; munities conferred upon the Shipowner by 'tions being imposed and/or measures being done or not done in compliance with this &lt; its or the goods and/or consignees thereof tl ensequent upon the operation of these clan id value when shipped unknown. The Com irrctly resulting from insufficiency of the add ^-exported goods. ote particularly the terms and conditions of tl loaed against shipping goods of a dangerou damage and also render themselves liable liosive, dangerous or damaging nature or igement or any goods contraband, or prohic ■ty be thrown overboard or may be dischai md the Company shall not be responsible fo any consequent loss, damage, expenses, pi wledge and consent shall become a danger rendered innocuous by the carrier without ipany reserve the right of charging freight ■ the same and charging freight accordn aokage is distinctly correctly and per man sad also with the name of the port of delr i will the Company acoept responsibility for to a description of the goods declared by tion. An incorrect description of the natnn entitle the shipowners to charge as and to double the freight which would have r&gt;ds being subjected to loss, seixure or detei visibility. Any lift weighing over one to (early on the package, and if the actual wi ddition to paying the above-mentioned doi to any property or persona whatsoever an owts. are carried only at advanced rates i ay be discharged as soon as the ship is real lays included, and if the consignee fails to y shall be at liberty to land the said good* y authorised Agent of the said vet»1\ V £ er and condition by i/JtttlOHia J ui'ai'• .• :■ LVi. (kb M M3 .034 ‘/+3 ror ouri&amp;aa t o B’JSHIKE slxhundj««d PIECES AND OR PACKAGES MERCHANDISE ftln (measurement, weight, quantity, brand, contents, condition, quality and value as declared by the Shipper but unknown to the Carrier) and t&lt;&gt; be is, conditions and provisions hereinafter contained, in the like good order and condition but the Company’s liability ceases as soon as the goods are sck, at her berth or anchorage at the Port of or such other Port or place as is provided hereafter (or so near thereto as she may safely get, lie and Sffs iiicle?m the^conslJiTees!^for'tfie goods, with primage, if any, shall be due and payable by the Shipper on without deduction, vessel or cargo lost or not lost. If freight is not so paid on shipment at port of loading it shall be due from and payable on demand ion, vessel or cargo lost or not lost, in which case freight shall be calculated and paid at any additional rate applicable when freight is payable on elegraphic advices of non-payment. non-payment. m shall not b« responsible for the Act of God, The King’s Enemies, pirates, straints of princes, rulers or people, restrictions and consequence, of quarantine, bances, combinations of workmen or others whether ashore or afioat or oiril directly or indirectly thereby and any circumstances beyond the shipowners’ iption resulting from any of the following cause, or perils, mr., insufficiency of ges through handling, inaccuracies, obliteration or absence of marks numbers era machinery, rust, vermin, breakage, leakage, ullage, hook holes, ohafage, a of other good,, effects of climate or heat of holds, chemical action, fumigation, St, risk of craft, or transhipment, or storage afloat or on shore, fire or water on accidents to or defects latent or otherwise in hull, tackle, boilers or machinery or ess to receive and carry cargo provided the owners have exercised due diligence :y, jettison, loss by thefts or robberies by sea or land, and whether by persons rice of the Company or otherwiae, accidents loss or damage or any oonaequenoea ny act neglect or default whatsoever or error in judgment of the Itaater, Pilot, there ; collision stranding or wreck however caused, and all penU dangers and navigation of whatsoever nature or kind and howsoever caused ; any accident or default of the Egyptian Government or the administration of the Sues Canal jyment of the Company’s vessels in or assistance rendered by them in the per- ertiea reserved by the shipowners, they shall have liberty to change the route stage of the voyage, to delay the sailing from the port of loading, or to put into n their opinion or in the opinion of the Master render thin, advisable ; and after iischarge to proceed to and stay at any ports or places whatsoever although in » ordinary route to port of discharge once or oftener in any order, backwards or mails or bullion, or embarking or disembarking passengers or bunkering or d or adjusting compasses, or repairing, or for any purpose whatsoever whether ided subsequent voyage, and all such ports, places, sailings and drydocking shall e ■ such liberty not to be considered as restricted by any words in this BiU of It descriptive of the voyage or otherwise, or by any implication which otherwise with liberty to nail with or without pilots, and to tow or be towed, and to assist i from the voyage for any purpose whatsoever. ...... .. e goods do not satisfy the importation regulations in force at destination as the shippers undertake to indemnify the shipowners against any expenses including mf and in the event of some or all of the goods not being imported or passed for land them at any other port whatsoever not excluding the port of landing and additional freight and all expenses incurred for which the ship shall have alien, noe or existence of any of the following.: -War between any nations or civil war ; mment of intercourse, commercial or otherwise, with any country from at or to itrol or direction by any Government or other Authonty of the use or movements he vessel; the (’arrier and/or hi. Agents and/or the Master, if he or they consider ingcre or any of them or cargo or any part thereof will be subject to loss, damage, e said War Civil War, prohibition, reatriction, control or direction, may at any e voyage alter or vary or depart from the proposed or advertised or agreed or un the vessel and/or discharge the cargo (for delivery or storage or transhipment) cat being liable for any lo« or damage whatsoever directly or indirectly sustained •cods are so discharged at such port or ports place or places they shall be landed risk of the Owner of the goods and the Garner’s responsibility shall cease at the nr notice of such discharge to the Consignee of the goods so Ur as he is known, d or implied herein, shall have liberty to comply with any orders or directions as call, delay, detention, discharge (for delivery or storage or transhipment)!. , or any Department thereof, or any person acting or purporting to »&lt;&gt;t with the ment thereof or by any Committee or person having under the terms of the war such orders or directions, and if by reason of or in compliance with »n.v such ,* by the Garner of any other liberty mentioned .n th.. Clause anything in don, tract. Discharge under any liberty mentioned in this Clause shall constitute due and the Owner and/or Consignee of the goods shall bear andpay all c ^ r ***“ he full freight stipulated herein if not prepaid, shall on such discharge tmesms id or Consignee of the goods, and if freight ha. been prepmd the Camer .kail he to carry contraband, explosives, munition, or warlike stores, and may sail armed inanities conferred upon the Shipowner by the War Rmk. claure. in th.s Bill of •ion. being imposed and/or measure, being take, by any TX^tpXrwm n*: cl7»y - .ot to k* responsible for a.y irectly resulting from insufficiency of the address, or packing, internal or external, ote particularly the terms and conditions of this Bill of Lading with reference to ,«ed against shipping goods of a dangerous or damaging nature a. by so doing d.mage and also render themselves liable to penalties impoeed by statute, and uoeive dangerous or damaging nature or liable to spontaneous combustion be gemrnt or any goods contraband, or prohibited by the law of ports of shipment, % lie thrown overboard or may be discharged at any port or may be otherwme .nd the Company shall not be responsible for their loss and the shippers and oon t; conTqr/tL., damage, excuses, penalty or responsibility to the ship or whig, and consent shall become a danger to the ship orcargo '*‘ ,k * rendered innocuous by the earner without liability on the part of tk « “''V ,panv reserve the right of charging freight on the goods by weight, measurement .^he same and charging freight accordingly before yd wj no* b. aokaue is distinctly correctly and permanently marked by the Merchant before and also with the name of the port of delivery, which last must be in letters not , will the Company accept responsibility for delivery to other than hmdmg maria ,0 a description of the goods declared by the shipper, to the shipowners. The lion An incorrect description of the nature of the goods or an untrue declaration entitle the shipowners to charge as and by way of liquidated and ascertained to double the freight which would have been charged if the goods had been A. wfin, subieotod to low seuure or detention through being wrongly described h ^ aCTuft WhiM oyer one ton grow must be declared in wnt.ng Cly on'the pickige^and ^the «tual weight be in excess of that declaredth. dition to paving the above-mentioned double freight, shall make good and bear ro any pro^rty or persons whatsoever and sh.ll also pay all additional charge. »U are Srrhrf only at advanced rate, of freight and by special ‘greemeu r/r'r.T “ y authorised Agent of the said vessel hath affirmed to col jO two or discharge into hulk, laiaretto or emit or any other-suitable place without notice and the goods may lie stored by them at th risk and expense of the shipper, or consignee, any custom of the port to tire contrary notwithstanding eomngnw. to pay charges for sorting and stacking the goods on wharf or in shed a. per scale of charge, to be seen at the Offleoe. Th. Company shall have the option of making delivery of good, either over the ship .side or from hghter, or , ‘ or '‘k'P v Custom House or Warehouse or dock or wharf or quay at Consignee, risk. In all cawre the Company s liability is to cease as soon a. the good, are lifted from and leave the ship's deck. Should a port be inaecewibl. or should entry and/or discharge or continuance of discharge at a port Ire deemed by the Master unsafe or inadvisable or liable to subject the steamer to any whatsoever the Master shall have liberty to discharge the good, at some other port or plans at the n.k anu expense of the shippea and consignee, and such discharge shall Ire deemed to I* due fulfilment of the contract of affreightment. Hbould all or any part of the within goods not be found, or if from bad weather or other cause the goods canaot be landed during the vessel . stay at port of destination, the Company reserves the right to convey same to any port before the final or to the final port ot t voyage to be returned thence at the Company's expense, but at the shipper's or consignee s risk ; and should necessity arise I or detaining and storing the goods, it shall also be done at the Company's expense and the shipper, or ron.igfbre. risk , an.lt he Company shall not be answerable for the result of any delay or risk so occasioned or for low of market. Delivery by the Company of packages externally in good condition as received shall be conclusive evidence of delivery of full weight and contants. 11. nAMHPnnJT. The Company have liberty ta carry the goods by the above or other steamships or vessels belonging to themaelvw or other, by anv route direst or indirect and at ship's option and expense but at consignee, risk to tranship at any place or places to any other vessels, or to land or store or put into hulk, craft or lighter, to reahip in the same or other irswi proceeding by anv route or forward by lighter, rail or any other conveyance whether such other vessel, store, hulk, craft, lighter or other conveyance belong to the shipowner, or not. With liberty also to overcarry the goods Ireyond or away from thoir port of destination notwithstanding the arrival of the carrying steamer at such port. Goods so overcarried or carne* away from dwtmation and good, in eouree of transhipment may be placed or stored in craft or 'bare and reoh.pped or forward^ or returned by land or ms at the Company's option and expense but at consignee, nsh. The Company to be ,r '« “ ,- for anv low. depreciation or damage arising from overcarriage or return carriage or for low of market. In the event of th g being consigned to any port or place to which the steamer cannot enter the next tide after having arrived as near as she can safely get thereto withoutdischarging and lie always afloat, the Master shall be at Kbertyto discharge the '^e or any parto the cargo into lighter, at consignees' risk. In case, where the ultimate destination at which the Company ma&gt; have to deliver good, is other than the .reamer's port of discharge the Company reserve the nght to forward «uch «ood,byra,K Goods forwarded by rail are deliverable at any railway station within or nearest to the destination named sodmustbetsk away by the consignee, immedistely sfter arrival otherwise the consignees will be liable for any expense, incurred Whenever through Bills of Lading are granted by the Company and shipment tronshipment carnage or d elivery °&lt; tbe «oods .. W be performed or partly performed by the vewel. or agent, or rerv.nts of other shipowner, such shipment ‘xwbipmeot c. r sge ir delivery is to be subject to the condition, and exception, of the forwarding conveyance supp emented by those herein and at consignees' risk. Tran.hipment of cargo for ports where this ship dow not call or for the Company • P«fpo~ • to b« «t the Compauv* expend, but coiuugne**’ risk from the time the good* are lifted from and lea\e the .Ship , where the Company’■^reapoiuibility shall ceoae. (iood- to be forwarded a. aoon a- pr^t.cable but the Ompany douot guarantee that steamers Vhall have room at Porta of transhipment snd accept no liability for detention, * n -' “Bf”***. storing or warehoustog to be born, by the consignee. For dutiable cargo transhipped, shipowner. and a. Custom, require at port of transhipment respecting dealing with cargo at port where 4 u tv '• pay.ble and ami risks incurred shall be on account of the Consignee. Consular few on cargo, if any, are to bebornebytbe Company act as forwarding agent, only from their steamer's port of discharge and in all case, their liability is to cease as above li. ' VALUABLE CARGO AMD PERISHABLES. The Company will not in any event he accountable for gold, k' 11 '*'' specie, jewellery, watches clocks, precious stones or metals, bank note, or secuntie. for money, pa.nl,ngs, P^ tu ^‘' oVother work, of art. nor for good, of which the value is more than £10/ .per cubic foot for m*-*»&gt;-rement “ r J* r cargo, nor for goods of which the value exceed. £100/- for any one package, unlew the value thereof shall have been decl ared ^ writing prior to shipment and entered on the shipping note which must he presented to the Lomrnsndc .t time d sh pm ^ sod the Bill of Lading signed with the nature and value of the good, .j.peanng thereon sod « ~ '''f^ .greed upon and paid; aor for low. injury or detention to package, intended for diflerentconsigsce. butenHowdin M* pock.gr unless the rontenU snd v.lu. of each separate pwkage lie given before shipment end P^* * ch , n » for breakage or damage to castings, cast iron pipes, showewes, unprotected goods, marble, earthenware or any gaod. of a brittle or fragile nature, from whatsoever cause arising, all such cargo be ng convened at4he ns of the shippers and Lnsignees. Fish, fruit* vegetables, snd all perishable goods and livestock sod all cargo carried on deck U C QDAIfAHTHfE.* 1 fn'^h^event ^of 'quarantine or sanitary or other similar regulation, or restnctions whatsoever or.berm soever anaing the good* 1 may be discharged into any depot/ laxaretto. hulk or other vewel or cr.ft a. reqmred £ ‘he ship s despatch, or should the Master conatder this impracticable he may discharge the good, at » P™' The the risk and expense of the consignees; and the ship's responsibility sh.ll reawwhenth, goods »'“ d,,ch * rg ' d shipper, and consignee, and each of them shall be liable for all quarantine expense, of whatever nature or kmd_ ^ ^ IV OPTIONAL DELIVERY. Optional delivery is only granted when arranged pnor to the shipment of g exprewed in the Bill ol filing- Consignee, desiring to avail of the option so expreswd'mu.t give notum to t he Couapw iy. A £Ht the hat port of steamer's call named ,n the option, at least 24 hours prior to steamer, amval there other.me the goods will be landed and the Company’s responsibility will cease. „, rvln - IOO&lt;1&lt; IS. SALVAGE. In the event of any veaael belonging to the Company rendering service ■ *. u eh reward enumerated this BUI of Lading entitling the awisting vewel to salvage reward “ or remuneration shall he treated in the same mann.r w if the wai.t.i.g vewel belong'd to aether Oouspany w peaoo ^ ^ li LAW APPLICABLE The contract evidenced by thi* Bill of Lading •hall be governed by the La g ... —— -p— r «e -*«-»■»« ■*“ Adjurtcrsou ail ,»,nUon Thfch such Rule.* contain no provision, and the Average .uteme.t to be drawn up in th. United King.bjmor ‘t «iy port of ^“^fvel Iren^u^th*: ^Tr'™^ freight Td al» for dead freight upon any ,»rtion of It g,md”'ovJred by ThT 8hi pptng Orde * gran tedl respe^ereof whi^ may not have been shipped and for a.I charge, stipulated ir'S^r Btt'&amp;g rnlir -d ^ivered up coaeelled before delivery of goods will be granted. tmtammam mmmwmmm of the goods, the operation of this clause to be in the discretion ol the slnpowncr nnu o. wre m'' lEFORK LOADING AND AITEN DISCHARGE. Mie Sin,anil,,', .hull not f r.'.jarasiblc for loss or damage to the goods prior to loading on and subsequent to discharge from ttffcliip, hoaevet caused. ished. the others to stand void. Bills of Lading, all of this tenor an FOR Tv oni' ifortlhe Muster, VTF • Co., T.tc ■is Agents.“ Disciosure of the contents of this Bill of Lading now in or off the Port of to any unauthori ;ed person may involve an offence against the (50 USC 3 Sbippefc in apparent good order and condition by Vi- in the Steam or Motor Vessel ^ j • 3 34 BAHtlrllN’ B/L tio.l SbiooeS in apparent good order and condition by Vii «L_\* * ! .it r* Co. L‘W* (ak Ag«itn). MM3 ^ ' 1/ 43 X&amp;l o w»ixllUnGJ i ‘n( , » PIECES AND OR PACKAGES MERCHANDISE marked and numbered as per margin (measurement, weight, quantity, brand, contents, condition, quality and value as declared by the Shipper but unknown to the Carrier) and to be \ (■ £ ')f f!-)o ( HI tCd StatCS discharged, subject to the exceptions, conditions and provisions hereinafter contained, in the like good order and condition but the Company’s liability ceases as soon as the goods are . lifted from and leave the ship s deck, at her berth or anchorage at the Port of or such other Port or place as is provided hereafter (or so near thereto as she may safelv get, He and . amended ) or against the discharge) unto the order of UoiietU*!* Bushire •and 1920 or the n e f ence 0 L t0 nl8 or their w ^ch persons Tr? TTeTein included in ffle term the consignees. Weight for the said goods, with primage, if any, shall be due and payable by the Shipper on ~ ' shipment at port of loading in cash without deduction, vessel or cargo lost or not lost. If freight is not so paid on shipment at port of loading it shall be due from and payable on demand (General » Ktji llat’.on of ihe United Ringdooi 05 by the consignee at port of destination, vessel or cargo lost or not lost, in which case freight shall be calculated and paid at any additional rate applicable when freight is payable against the Defence of India Rules 1939', r.spiOnano and 5 2 a official secrets Act i 91 British fjnhfa Steam navigation Company limiteh The liatililj/ of i/rmken of the Comporty it Limited. (/near paroled , a teflond.) PARTICULARS DECLARED BY SHIPPER. Leading Marks. - Distinctive Numbers. Number of Packages or pieces or Quantity or weight. Description. SKIT 1321 CC 13 SULATK GENEHAI. BL3HIKL. 600 baga cement Bag&amp; mouths tied with etriiig. Not responsible for bursting and loss of contents. Number of Packages (in words y bundled only. MEASUREMENT AND WEIGHT. Tons. Feet. Inches. Tons. Cwt. Qrs. Lbs. 3 aid to ! HRElGbr oes 30 r paid - N feAHf mnfk 1 t|- delivery, together with the cost of telegraphic advices of non-payment. 1. GENERAL IMMUNITIES. The shipowners shall not be responsible for the Act of God, The King’s Enemies, pirates, robbers or thieves by land or sea, arrests or restraints of princes, rulers or people, restrictions and consequences of quarantine, riots, strikes, lockouts or other labour disturbances, combinations of workmen or others whether ashore or afloat or civil commotion or loss, damage or delay caused directly or indirectly thereby and any circumstances beyond the shipowners’ control; accident loss or damage of any description resulting from any of the following causes or perils, wi*., insufficiency of packing or packages wear and tear of packages through handling, inaccuracies, obliteration or absence of marks numbers address or description of goods shipped, boilers, machinery, ruat, vermin, breakage, leakage, ullage, hook holea, ohafage, sweating, evaporation or decay, injurious effeetN of other goods, effects of climate or heat of holds, chemical action, fumigation, rain, spray, snow, frost, steam, coal or coal dust, risk of craft, or transhipment, or storage afloat or on shore, fire or water on board, in hulk, in craft or on shore, explosion, accidents to or defects latent or otherwise in hall, tackle, boilers or machinery or their appurtenances ; unscaworthiness or anfitness to reoeive and carry cargo provided the owners have exercised due diligence to make the vessel seaworthy and fit; barratry, jettison, loss by thefts or robberies by sea or land, and whether by persons directly or indirectly in the employment or service of the Company or otherwise, accidents loss or damage or any consequences arising from overcarriage or loss of market: any act negleet or default whatsoever or error in judgment of the Master, Pilot, Officers, Engineers, Manners, Stevedores or others ; collision stranding or wreck however caused, and all perils dangers and accidents of the seas, rivers, land carriage and navigation of whatsoever nature or kind and howsoever caused ; any acoidcnt, loss, damage, delay or detention from any art or defsult of the Egyptian Government or the administration of the Sues Canal or arising out of or consequent npon the employment of the Company’s vessels in or assistance rendered by them in the per formance of His Majesty’s Mail service. 2. DEVIATION. In addition to all other liberties reserved by the shipowners, they shall have liberty to change the routs before the commencement of or at any time or stage of the voyage, to delay the sailing from the port of loading, or to put into and remain at any port should circumstances in their opinion or in the opinion of the Master render this, advisable ; and after proceeding towards or arriving at the port of discharge to proceed to and stay at any ports or places whatsoever although in a contrary direction to or out of or beyond ths ordinary route to port of discharge once or oftener in any order, backwards or forwards, for loading or discharging cargo, mails or bullion, or embarking or disembarking passenger* or bunkering or drydockmg with or without the cargo on board or adjusting compasses, or repairing, or for any purpose whatsoever whether connected with the present voyage or any intended subsequent voyage, and all such ports, places, sailings and drydocking shall be deemed included within the present voyage; such liberty not to be considered as restricted by any words in this Bill of lead ing, whether written or printed and whether descriptive of the voyage or otherwise, or by any implication which otherwise might be drawn from this Bill of Lading. Also with liberty to sail with or without pilots, and to tow or be towed, and to assist any vessels in all situations and also to deviate from the voyage for any purpose whatsoever. 3. IMPORT RESTRICTIONS. If any of these goods do not satisfy the imporUtion regulations in force at destination as the result of which they cannot be discharged the shippers undertake to indemnify the shipowners against any expenses including detention costs incurred as a consequence thereof and in the event of some or all of the goods not being imported or passed for importation at destination the shipowners may land them at any other port whatsoever not excluding the port of landing and shippers undertake to pay the shipowners any sdditional freight and all expenses incurred for which the ship shall have a lien, the goods to be at shippers risk throughout. 4. WAR RISKS, fn the event of the imminence or existence of any of the following!:—War between any nations or civil war ; prohibition restriction or control by any Government of intercourse, commercial or otherwise, with any country from at or to which the vessel normally proceeds or calls ; control or direction by any Government or other Authority of the use or movement* of the vessel or the insulated or other space in the vessel ; the Carrier and/or his Agent* and/or the Master, if he or they consider that the vessel or her Master Officers Crew Pasastgcr* or any of them or cargo or any part thereof will be subject to loss, damage, injury, detention or delay in consequence of tbs said War, Civil War, prohibition, restriction, control or direction, may at any time before or after the commencement of ths voyage alter or vary or depart from the proposed or advertised or agreed or customary route or voyage and/or delay or detain the vessel and/or discharge the cargo (for delivery or storage or transhipment) at or off any port or ports, place or places without being liable for any loss or damage whatsoever directly or indirectly sustained by the owner of the goods. If and when the goods arc so discharged at such port or ports place or places they shall be landed or put into craft or vessels at the expense and nak of the Owner of the goods and the Carrier’s responsibility shall cease at the vessel's rail, the Carrier, Master or Agents giving notice of such discharge to the (Jonsignee of the goods so {at as he is known. The vessel, in addition to any liberties expressed or implied herein, shall have liberty to comply with any orders or directions as to departure, arrival, route, voyage, ports of call, delay, detention, discharge (fur delivery or storage or transhipment) or otherwise howsoever given by any Governmenv or any Department thereof, or any person acting or purporting to act with ths authority of any Government or of any Department thereof or by any Committee or person having under the terms of the war risks insurance on the vessel the right to give such order* or directions, and if by reason of or in complianoe with any such orders or directions or by reason of the exerciss by the Carrier of any other liberty mentioned in this Clause anything is done or is not done the same shall be within this contract. Discharge under any liberty mentioned in this Clause shall constitute due delivery of the goods under this Bill of Lading snd the Owner and/or Consignee of the goods shall bear and pay all charges and expenses resulting from such discharge, and tke full freight stipulated herein if not prepaid, shall on such discharge become immediately due and payable by the Owner and/or Consignee of the goods, and if freight has been prepaid the Carrier shall be entitled to retain the same. The vessel is free to carry contraband, explosives, munitions or warlike stores, and may sail armed or unarmed. . 5. SANCTIONS. The rights liberties and imnuinities conferred upon the Shipowner by the War Risks clause in this Bill of Lading shall be exercisable in the event of sanctions being imposed and/or measures being taken by any Government under the covenant of the League of Nations. Anything done or not done in complianoe with this clause and the said War Risks clause to be within the contract voyage and the ownca oi the goods and/or consignees thereof shall pay the fall freight oncarrying or additional freight and also all other charges oeasequent upon the operation of theee clauses. 6. MARKS, CONTENTS. Weight contents snd value when shipped unknown. The Company is not to be responsible for any loss, damage or delay, whatsoever, directly or indirectly resulting from insufficiency of the address, or packing, internal or external, nor for condition or content* of reshipped or re-exported goods. 7. INSURANCE. Shippers are requested to note particularly the terms and conditions of this Bill of Lading with refereno* to the validity of their insurance upon their goods. 8. DANGEROUS GOODS. Shippers are cauUoaed against shipping goods of a dangerous or damaging nature as by so doing they become responsible for all consequential dsmage and also render themselves liable to penalties imposed by statute, and if chemicals, liquids or other goods of an explosive, dangerous or damaging nature or liable to spontaneous combustion be shipped without previous declasntion and arrangement or any goods contraband, or prohibited by the law of port* of shipment, discharge or call, such goods upon discovery msy be thrown overboard or may be discharged at any port or may be otherwise dealt with according to the Master's discretion sad the Company shall not be responsible for their loss and the shippers and con signees, and each of them shall be liable for sny consequent loss, damage, expenses, penalty or responsibility to the ship or cargo, and if any such goods shipped with knowledge and consent shall become a danger to the ship or cargo they may in like manner be landed at any place or destroyed or rendered innocuous by the carrier without liability on the part of the carrier. 9. FREIGHT AND DESCRIPTION. The Company reserve the right of charging freight on the goods by weight, measurement or value and of re-measuring or re-weighing the same and charging freight accordingly before delivery and will not be responsible for correct delivery unless each package is distinctly correctly and permanently marked by the Merchant before shipment with a mark and number, or address, ss«l also with the name of ths port of delivery, which last must be in letters not less than two inches long. In no circumstance* will the Company accept responsibility for delivery to other than leading marks The freight has been calculated and based upon a description of the goods declared by the shippers to the shipowner*. The shippers warrant the correctness of such description. An incorrect description of the nature of the goods or an antrue declaration of their value or weight or measurement shall entitle the shipowners to charge as and by way of liquidated and ascertomed damages and not as a penalty, a sum equal to double the freight which would have been charged if the goods had been correctly described ; and in the event of the go^ds being subjected to loss, seizure or detention through being wrongly described the shipowners shall be released from all resjornibility. Any lift wceighing over one ton gross must be declared in writing before shipment and the weight be stencilled clearly on the package, and if the actual weight be in excess of that declared the shippers and consignees and each of them m addition to paying the above-mentioned double freight, shall make good and bear any loss, damage or delay caused in handling to any property or persons whatsoever and shall also pay all additional charges of handling. Packages weighing more than 4&lt;&gt; cwt*. are carried only at advanced rates of freight and by special agreement. 10. DISCHARGE OF CARGO. The goods nuy be discharged as soon as the ship is ready to unload and as fast as she is able, continuously day and night, Sundays and holiusy* included, and if the consignee fails to take delivery of his goods immediately the ship is ready to discharge them the Company shall be at liberty to land the said goods on to wharf or quay or into warehouse IN WITNESS whereof the Master, or duly authorised Agent of the said vessel hath affirmed to Freight @ - ton 2$ sWT, Total Rs. Dated at this tith * day J • or discharge into hnlk, lazaretto or emit or any other-suitable plaee without notice and the goods msy fie stored by them at the risk and expense of the shippers or consignees any custom of the port to the contrary notwithstanding consignees to pay charges for sorting and stacking the goods on wharf or in shed as per scale of charges to be seen at the Agent* Offices. The Company shall have the option of making delivery of good* either over the ship’s ride or from lighter or store ship or hulk or Custom House or Warehouse or dock or wharf or quay at Consignees’ risk. In all cases the Company’s liability is to cea*e as soon as the goods are lifted from and leave the ship’s deck. Should a port be macoeaiubie or should entry and/or discharge or continuance of discharge at a port lie deemed by the Master unsafe or inadvisable or liable to subject the steamer to any risk whataoever the Master shall have liberty to discharge the goods at some other port or place at the risk an* expense of the shippers and consignees and such discharge shall lie deemed to lie due fulfilment of the contract of affreightment. Should all or any part of the within goods not be found, or if from had weather or other cause the goods cannot be landed during the vessel’s stay at port of destination, the Company reserves the right to convey same to any port before the final or to the final port of the voyage to be returned thence at the Company’s expense, but at the shipper’s or consignee's risk ; and should necessity arise for detaining and storing the goods, it shall also be done at the Company’s expen*e and the shipper's or conrigifee’s risk ; and the Company shall not be answerable for the result of any delay or risk so occasioned or for lo*s of market. Delivery by the Company of packages externally in good condition as received shall be conclusive evidence of delivery of full weight and contant*. 11. TRANIHIFMENT. The Company have liberty to carry the goods by the above or other steamships or vessel* belonging to themselves or others by any rout* direct or mdiroct and at ship’s option and expense but at consignees’ risk to tranship at any place or places to any other vessels, or to land or store or put into hulk, craft or lighter, to reship in the same or other vessel proceeding by any route or forward by lighter, rail or any other conveyance whether such other vessel, store, hulk, craft, lighter or other conveyance belong to the shipowners or not. With liberty also to overcarry the goods beyond or away from their port of destination notwithstanding the arrival of the carrying steamer at such port. Goods so overcarried or carried away troip destination and goods in course of transhipment may be placed or stored in craft or ashore and reshipped or forwarded or returned by land or sea at the Company’s option and expense but at consignees’ nsk. The Company to be free of liability for any loss, depreciation or damage arising from overcarriage or return carriage or for lose of market. In the event of the goods being consigned to any port or place to which the steamer cannot enter the next tide after having arrived as near as she can safely get thereto without discharging and lie always afloat, the Mast«r shall be at Hberty to dmcharge the whole or any part of the cargo into lighters at consignees’ risk In cases where the ultimate destination at which the Company may have engsged to deliver goods is other than the steamer’s port of discharge the Company reserve the right to forward such goods by rail. Good* forwarded by rail are deliverable at any railway station within or nearest to the destination named a*d must be taken away by the consignees immediately after arrival otherwise the consignees will be liable for any expense* incurred. Whenever through Bill* of Lading are granted by the Company and shipment trannhipment carnage or delivery of the goods i* to be performed or partly performed by the vessels or agent* or servants of other shipowners such shipment transhipment carriage or delivery is to be subject to the conditions and exceptions of the forwarding conveyance supplemented by those expressed herein and at consignees' risk. Transhipment of cargo for ports where thin ship does not call or for the Company’s purpose*, to be at the Company’s expense, but at consignees' nsk from the time the goods are lifted from and leave the Ship's deck, where the Company’s responsibility shall cea»e. Goods to be forwarded as soon a* practicable, but the Company do not guarantee that steamors shall have room at Ports of transhipment and accept no liability for detention, any expenses for storing or warohousing to be borne by the consignees. For dutiable cargo transhipped, shipowner* may give such undertaking a* Customs require st port of transhipment respecting dealing with cargo at port where duty is payable and all charges and risks incurred shall be on account of the Consignees. Consular fees on cargo, if any, are to be borne by the Consignees. The Company act as forwarding agents only from their steamer's port of discharge and in all cases their liability is to cease as above provided. 11. VALUABLE CARGO AND PERISHABLES. The Company will not in any event be accountable for gold, silver, bullion, specie, jeweller)-, watches, clocks, precious stones or metals, bank note* or securities for money, paintings, pictures, sculptures, or other works of art, nor for goods of which the value is more than £10/-, per cubic foot for measurement or per cwt. for weight cargo, nor for goods of which the value exceeds £100/- for any one package, unless the value thereof shall have been declared in writing prior to shipment and entered on the shipping note which must he presented to the Commander at time of shipment and the Bill of Lading signed with the nature and value of the goods appearing thereon and extra freight in respect of same agreed upon and paid ; nor for loss, injury or detention to packages intended for different conrignees but enelosed in one package unless the contents and value of each separate package In? given before shipment and freight paid accordingly ; nor for breakage or damage to castings, cast iron pipes, showcases, unprotected goods, marble, slate, glass, glassware, china, earthenware, or any goods of a brittle or fragile nature, from whatsoever cause arising, all such cargo being conveyed at-the risk of the shipper* and consignees. Fish, fruit, vegetables, and all perishable good* and livestock and all cargo carried on deck are conveyed solely at the risk of the shipper. 18. QUARANTINE. In the event of quarantine or sanitary or other similar regulations or restrictions whatsoever or where- Moever arising the good* may be discharged into any depot, lazaretto, hulk or other vessel or craft as required for the ship’s despatch, or should the Master consider this impracticable he may discharge the goods at a safe port of call, in his option, at the risk and expense of the consignees ; and the ship’s responsibility shall cease when the good* are so discharged. The shipper* and consignees and each of them shall he liable for all quarantine expenses of whatever nature or kind. 14. OPTIONAL DELIVERY. Optional delivery is only granted when arranged prior to the shipment of the goods and is expressed in the Bill of Lading. Consignee* desiring to avail of the option so expressed'must give notice to the Company’s Agent at the first port of steamer’s call named in the option, at least 24 hours prior to steamer's arrival there otherwise the goods will be landed and the Company's responsibility will cease. 13. SALVAGE. In the event of any ve**el belonging to the Company rendering service to the vessel carrying the good* enumerated in this Bill of Lading entitling the assisting vessel to salvage reward or remuneration for such service, such reward or remuneration shall be treated in the same manner as if the assisting vessel belonged to another Company or person. 14. LAW APPLICABLE. The contract evidenced by this Bill of Lading shall be governed by the Laws of England and in accepting this Bill of Lading the shippers and consignees expressly accept and agree to all its stipulations, exceptions and ondition* whether written, stamped or printed as fully as if signed by him or them 17. AVERAGE. Average payable according to York/Antwerp Rules, 1924, supplemented by the practice of English Average Adjusters on all point* on which such Rules contain no provision, and the Average statement to be drawn up in the United Kingdom or at any port *f discharge or other piaoe at the option of the shipowners. 18. LIEN. The Company shall have a lien upon the good* for unpaid freight and also for dead freight upon any portion of the fp&gt;od* covered by the Shipping Order granted in respect hereof which may not have been shipped and for all charges stipulated herein to be borne by the shippers and/or consignee*. 18. DELIVERY. Bills of Lading must be presented and delivered up caneellcd before delivery of good* will be granted. Gold, silver, bullion, specie, jewellery, precious stones, precious metals, plated ware, documents, works of art, watches. Silks or other precious er valuable articles will not be landed by the Company. They will only be delivered on presentation of Bilb of Lading on Board, and will be carried on. or stored, at risk and expense of shipper c consignee, if delivery is not taken during the vessel’s stay in port. 90. NOTICE OF CLAIMS. Any claim that may arise in respect of goods shipped in the Company s steamers, for which the steamer is responsible, must be preferred in writing to the Company's Agent at the place of delivery within thr*e days after discharge and before the goods are removed from the quay or ship's side or place of discharge otherwise the Company shall l»e free from liability. The Company’s liability in case of loss or injury to goods for which they may be responsible within the limits of this Bill of Lading to be calculated on and in no case to exceed the net invoice cost and disbursements. 81. FORT RESTRICTIONS. Notwithstanding anything herein contained to the contrary, in the event of restrictions, actual or apprehended, on account of Ice or Quarantine, Sanitary, Customs, or Labour Regulations, Lockout*, Strikes, Blockade. Prohibitions, Interdict, War, Imminence of War, General Dieturlmnces or other like cause or cause* at any port or ports called at or intended to be called at by the vessel preventing or (hreatening to prevent the usual and prompt discharge of the good* or any portion thereof at the Bill of Lading destination, such goods or any portion thereof may. at the vessel s option, Ik* transhipped, retained on l»oard l landed, warehoused, finally discharged or otherwise disposed iof wheresoever most convenient to the vessel and such action taken under this clause shall l*e deemed to la* due fulfilment of the contract of affreightment so far as cargo so disposed of is concerned and all oncarrying or additional freight and expenses and risks whatsoever and howsoever incurred or connected in any way with such dis|H&gt;sal aforesaid,sliall Ik* borne by the Shipper and/or consignee and or receiver of the goods, the operation of this clause to be in the discretion of the shi|»owner and/or the Master and/or the Shipowner* Agents. 22. BEFORE LOADING AND AFTER DISCHARGE prior to loading on and subsequent to discharge from t two Bill, of Lading, all of thin tenor an FOE Tv as* n*s|K&gt;u*iblc for los* or damage to the go«d&gt; ished. the others 10 stand vuid. Muster tie Muster, &gt;o., T.ta ds Agents.No•2639-18/6-IV Political Agency, Bahrain, © Dated 17th September, 1944. Messrs. Amy &amp; Navy Stores, Somerset Street, Snddar, Karachi. Memorand um. Reference your letter dated the I9th AUf^ust 1944 enclosing a bill for Rs.1125/-/-. I 2. The bill aprears to be very high. As regards the first item you have charged Rs.170/- per roll, whereas you had quoted Rs.150/- in your letter dated the 10th January, 1944. I an doubtful about the correctness of Rs.70/- charged for freight etc. 3. fill you please let me have the detailed list of charges incurred on the wire gauze at an early date and justify.then in detail supported by receipts, vouchers, etc. before I consider payment. • for Political Agent, Bahrain.4p. Rabbin Recrpt -Vf Telegram Prom To No. A/1536 Dated Please pay Rs.2400 repeat 2400 to the Political Agent on account of the cost of cement supplied to the Public Works Department by debit to this Residency account. Draft for the amount being sent by mail for credit our account. G.T.C. No 4&gt;IX ....Dato,. Britconsul, Bushire. L itical Agent, Bahrain. received 20th September, 1944. —BRITCONSUL-1 No. of 1363 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 9th Shawwal, 1363 ill] -j— /'ty '•* 0 . Memorandum : I forward herewith a cheque for Rs.1,000/- being cost of 250 bags of cement which you so kindly allowed the Bahrain Government to purchase. Please acknowledge receipt. Adviser to the Government. i i 1 YG.No. w- 13/6. Political Agenc/, Bahrain. The October, 1944 To » The Adviser, Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Meiaorand-ga. f v ~ k v i \ ' I acknowledge receipt of cheque for Ps*1000/- sent with your memo. No. 1798-*43 dated the 26th September, 1944. * \ for Political Agent, Bahrain.Registering ClerkNo. 11. I MACKINNON MACKENZIE &amp; CO., Telegraphic Address: L “MACKINNONS.’ POST BOX No. 40- ^0. &lt; 3^atacVv\ &gt; ^44 The Army &amp; Navy S tore s, Kar achi. Dear Sirs, is The undernoted amount ace outstanding against you in our Books and we shall be obliged it you will kindly send us a remittance in settlement of same at an early date. Thanking you in anticipation.Politi L'cal Agent, Bahrain. NO. SO Sj&gt;- 18/6-IV To '% 12-3 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, OCTOBER, 1944. -— Messrs Army &amp; Navy Stores, Somerset Street, Camp, Karachi &gt; &lt;T^ Memorandum: - LnM Reference your letter dated 'the 23rd September, 1944# 2#’ I send herewith a bank draft for Rs#125/- (Rupees one hundred and twenty five only) being the balance of your bill dated the 19th August, 1944, for Ss. 1125 /- in connexion with the cost of wire gauze supplied by you to this office.ties* Telegran From To TT o. Dated G.T.C. Political \gcnt, Bahrain. Dritc onsu1, B us hire. 834 14th Docombor 1944. Following for Executive Engineer. Reference my letter 2486 of August 2. Agency roof is leaking and overseer reports that practically whole area nedds repair. Estimates :tf.300/- required to meet cost of rendering water tight. Grateful if expenditure may be sanctioned. -POLITICAL AI TO. A.T\ A,.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA ' l3 m Department. EXPRESS LETTER N. B. — This in an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, by powt w» «ihv« telegraphic expense and nndna use of the wire*, but intended to be treated, qu reenipt, with the name &lt; ipedmoQ aa il it ha&lt;i been oeleyraphed. To save Cteae and forinailtle* it i* worded and signed at» if it bad been so despatched. ^°-64-6- 18/6. Datea Bahrain, t %)th February, 1 %?946. To Britconsul, Bushire. Please draw Executive Engineer's attention to promise made by him in August that Agency works, parti cularly the new entrance, would be taken in hand by January 1st, 1945. Grateful if I may be informed when the works will be commenced. i/t Political Agent, Bahrain. S.6. MFP— «27 SAP— 6788 —(M-1259)— 24-11-42 —800,000.D.O.No. ftfS' Political Agency, Bahrain The 3rd March, 1945. My dear Belgrave A new main entrance is about to be constructed into the Agency grounds in front of the Court building. The present entrance which is not impressive and is very dangerous will be closed. I shall be very grateful if the telephone and electric light wire pole on the sea front could be moved so as not to obstruct the new entrance and if the path to the public latrine can be carried to the west. 1 believe the Residency Executive Engineer did discuss these projects with Khan Sahib Mohammed Jaffer last year. While this is being done I suggest that the telephone and light wire pole which now obstructs the entrance into Dr. Steeled house and renders an already dangerous corner more so be moved. I shall be grateful if these works could be carried out as soon as possible as it is hoped to start'work on the Agency at once. Yours sincerely, C.D. Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. r A-V.A. cA*-A~&gt;No.1660-13/6 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 22nd April, 1945. To The State Engineer, Bahrain. Memorandum. Will you kindly send your wireaan to instal a- permanent line pf lead wire from my office upstairs to my Superintendent’s office with tv/o sockets on each end.D,0,No*1995-18/6. Political Agency* Bahrain, The 15th May, 1945. My dear Belgrave, Will yon kindly let me know whether it is not possible to have the causeway to the public latrines near tho Agency gato ra^nded? 2. I see my predecessor in his letter No. . • — f« 815 dated tho 3rd March 1945, suggested the causeway should be moved further to the west. Could this be done at the same time as the repairs? Yours sincerely, Dalrymple Belgrave, Ksq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain.No.2014-18/6 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 16th May, 1945. To The State Engineer, Government of Bahrain Bahrain. Memorandum. Subject: Electric installation in the servants 1 quarters. . I should be grateful if you^please let me have an estimate for providing one light point in each room of the block of 10 servants’ quarters. The connection can be made either from the overhead mains or from the Indian Assistant’s Court building, whichever is con sidered more suitable. One meter is to be provided for the whole block. A for Political Agent, Bahrain.-'•f GoygRTg,^^ of ba:thaih ST^iTE T ’NGIIJETiJR' S DEPARTMENT NO.P^/26 /64 Datedi BAHRAIN. 22nd May, 1945 10th j/Thani,1364 H.B.M’s Political AQent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- Xq 3Q$1.....Dote. S' Reference your memorand dated 15th May,1945. dm No.2 2014-18/6 The cost of wiring for one light point in each room of the block of 10 servants* quarters will be approximately -%300/-/-. Please let us know if you wish us to put this work in hand*No.2$88-18/6 Political Agency, Balirain, The SSthi May, 1945. To The State Engineer, Governi’.Qnt of Bahrain, Bahrain* \ ' Meiiioranduia * ^ ' ' ; “*&gt; I thank you for your aemofandtm Ko. PA/26/64 dated the ,22nd May, 1946, regarding the wiring of the servants 1 quarters, but do not wish the *ork put in hand as yet for Political Agent, Bahrain* irNo•2398- IB/6• Political Agency, Bahrain, The 11th June, 1945• To The State Engineer, Government of Bahrain, Bahrain* Memorandum, Can you please supply this Agency with 50 R*ft* of 2 M diameter G.I, pipe with necessary sockets and also detail a plumber or pipe fitter to lay the pipe in the Agency compound? The exact position will be shown to the fitter by the P,W*D. Supervisor of this Agency, Bill of charges may please be submitted to this office.ML To His Britannic Majesty* s Political Agent Bahrain. Sir I beg to put forth following few lines for your kind consideration:- There is a water tank in the sea facing the Agency for washing clothes etc. It was constructed in time of Hon'ble Sir Geoffrey Prior when he was here as Political Agent. As it is in the sea, the water becomes dirty and is of no use when there is high tide and strong wind is blowing. Besides as the surroundings are dirty, it gives very bad smell at all times. If I wash my clothes over there my washing is spoiled. I therefore request your honour that the water tank may kindly be removed from that side to somewhere behind the Indian Asstt.’s Court. This will greatly facilitate my work as sometimes when the Agency work is pressing and urgent it will be convenient for me to wash the clothes over there. This will improve my washing to a very great extent. The work can be done by joining some extra pipe line. I therefore humbly request your honour that rny above prayer may kindly be granted. Hoping to be excused for the trouble, I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant (i.e. Maikoo Dhobi) Agency Dhobi.Supdt. asked me regarding the Polishing or oiling of the Stair-case and I told him that about a month back Ihe P.A. had instructed me to arrange this. Accordingly I suggested that the Launch crew may do this - • This suggestion was approved and I had instructed the headman 'Mizal' to get the needful done everyday. For one week I got it done under my supervision and told him to carry on in the s^me way daily. For sometime it ^as done and then it appears that the work was stopped. I asked hiir today in the presence of the Supdt. and Mizal replied that it was the duty of the Sweeper. He was therefore admonished and told him that he lias to get the oiling done every third day &amp; cleaning with cotton waste is to be done every day as was done before. Supdt. may kindly see that he docs not neglect this again.I No. ^0 - l^b POLITICAL AOKNCY, BAHRAIN. Datod the 19th June, 1945. (Ij) My dear Belgrave, It seems to me that the police guard on the Agency are now entirely wrongly placed. The large main gate is really the place where a guard is most required though the question of their accommodation there may well arise* I should he glad of your views* Yours sincerely, 'C* Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E*, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, B a h r a in. 4D.o.iioy^T'-'^ /&lt;^&gt;W Adviserate, June 15, 1945 ..Cc^» Reference your D.O.No. 2570-18/6 dated 20th June 1945. I have given orders that the sentry is to be stationed at what is now the main gate, the guard remaining where they were before. I an repairing and painting a sentry box which could perhaps be put at the gate. C. J. Pelly, Esquire, O.B.3., I.C.3., H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain.No.2663-18/6. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 26th June, 1945. My dear Belgrave, Reference your demi-official letter No. 1227-9 A dated the 26th June, 1945. Thank you. This is a great improvement. Yours sincerely, C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Bsq., C.B.B., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain.,. C.To Political Acency, Bahrain, 30th July 1945. The State Engineer, Bahrain Government, Bahrain. hccoranauc. Please supply this Agency with the l'cllov/ing articles: 30 feet pipe (li n diameter) 1 1-1“ bend 5 1^“ sockets 1 1” bend i reducing socket 1 i* tap. for Political Agent, Bahrain* \ No.3180*18/6. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 7th August, 1945• My dear Anderson, \ Would you very kindly allow Freeman to come down here and repair one of my air conditioners as soon as possible? Yours sincerely, Mr. Ward P. Anderson, ^ The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain.No*3216. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 9th August, 1946. To Mr. M.D. Minasian, Contractor, Bahrain. Memorandum. As soon as your carpenters Mohammed and JaTar finish their work at the new office building,they will be required to be employed by this Agency for some time. It is therefore requested that you may instruct them accordingly to report at the Agency after your work is completed. for Political Agent, BahrainPolitical Agency’s Bahrain* The 11th August* 1945* My dear Freeman, Soon after you left and had completed the repairs to the A«C. unit in the dining-room I found the frigidaire unit in No.4 bedroom was not functioning either] I am sorry to trouble you again but the gc»s has all escaped I think and the master valve is not functioning. Couli you kindly come dowii again and have a lock at it whenever convenient? Yours sincerely, E.W. Freeman* Esq.* C/o The Bahrain Petroleum Co.* Ltd.* Bahrain.V J Ho. 26/ °ILb British Residency ^nd Consulate-General, D«-.ted Bush ire, th« /Jr/Tjuly, 1945 • »* 3x:ecutive Engineer, The From To Bahrain. 2. The Political ^gent, Muscat. 3. The Political i*gent, Kuwait • 4. His Majesty f s Consul, Bunder ^Jobas. Subjects- Schedule of demands under 50. C.W.C. External xid*fairs for the year 1946-47 • Sir I have the honour to request you to state your requirements for original works, additions and alterations and special repairs which you consider absolutely necessary to be carried out during the year 1946-47. **s the schedule of demands for 1946-47 is 2 . required to be submitted to the Government of India by the 15th October, 1945, vide para 3 ^appendix 8 of P. J. A. Code, it is requested that the information called for in para 1 of this letter may kindly be furnished through' the Secretary to the Hon r ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf so as to reach this office by the 7th of September, 1945 at the latest. I havte the honour to be, Your most ofotedient servant Y17/7. Ind. Per „ . 'n.No.3690-18/6. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 4th September, 1946. To The Secretary to the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Maigganflm* £j f At for 50 C.W.C&gt;&gt; Reference Executive Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub Division, Bushire circular letter No.26/926 dated the 18th July, 1946. 2. List of works proposed to be carried out during 1946-47 is given below under the respective heads and showing the approximate estimated cost against each item. ■OriLEtosA .waste, \lU 1. Constructing Sentry shed near the main gate. Ss.600/- 2. Providing wooden floor in the English Office room. 2100/- x 3. Constructing for the Agency garden near P.R .*3 Office. - 150Q/- v 4. Constructing gate and^appro-si^h road from cycN apound ^tQ the P.P/^s-OffTce. — 809/ - 6. Constructing incinerator for burning records. 600/-. AdcUttPh? qnd / j l I® ^ 1. Additions and alterations to the bed room No.3 1 ; 2000/- Special repairs. i. Renewing copper wire gauze to doors and windows. 11000/- 2. Cement plaster &amp; pointing to jetty including ^ repairs. 2600/- * 3. Special repairs to the store room near guard room. 2000/- 4. Renewing floor with cement concrete and cement plaster over platforms in Toshakhana. 300/- 5. Renewing cement and gutch plaster outside and inside guard room. 1600/- v' 6. Renewing water pipe lines from the artesian v 7 well in the Agency garden. 1600/- 7. Renewing cement plaster to walls and other repairs in the old record room of the Agency. 300/- 8. Special repairs to the roofs of the Agency buildings. 1000/-. 0 tJo for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded to the Executive Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub Division, Bushire, Camp, Bahrain, for information and necessary action. \y , Ir- y £ fijf its cno. 5747- iy° Political Agency, Bahrain, 13th September 1945. To The State Engineer, / Bahrain. f Memorandum. Reference my memorandum No.3072, dated 30th July 1945, 2. The following parts were found to be surplus to our requirement: 12 feet pipe 1 Bend 3 Sockets 3. Ilease send me an amended bill, and the original is enclosed herewith. for Political Agent,Bahrain. 61 oNo.3741-18/^6. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 15th September, 1945. To The Secretary to the lion'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum. Subject: Schedule of demand under 50 C.W.C, 6 E xterna l Aff^rs fo r 1946 - 4? t ^ ' Reference this Agency memorandum No.3590-18/16 dated the 4th September, 1945, it is requested that the following amendments be made to the list of works:- Original works. Item 3. For gate read wall. Item 4. To be omitted. Additions and alterations. Item 1. For No.3 read No.2 bed-room. for Political Agent, Bahrain. t \ Copy forwarded to the Executive Engineer* Independent Persian Gulf Sub Division, Bushire, for information and necessary actionReference our conversation with the P.A. yesterday* Please put up an estimate at’once for^- a) Making a door in the proposed waiting room in H.M's office. b) Installing a fan. c) Doing up the walls and tell me how you would account for the cost. Mr. Oadri. Intd • H.E.H.I3. 13-9-45. a) Door can not be provided at the proposed place as there is a pillar. Hence the door will have to be provided in place of the existing window. The cost of this door including removal of window and repairing wall and jambs will approximately be Rs. 200/- . b) State Engineer may be asked for this. The wiring of the present light will also be required to be changed as the switbhjof the same is in the ’7.C. l c) It is proposed to line up the walls with ply-wood of old Tea Boxes. I enquired from M/S Dhamanmal Isardass if they could arrange to supply us the required quantity. They said they might be able to collect from the bazar and the price will be Rs. 2/8/- to 3/8/- per box. After wards they informed me that they will only be able to collect about 50 to 60 boxes whereas our requirement is 150 to 200 boxes. They also suggested that we should try through the local Customs Office. Accordingly I asked Mr. Purshotam who promised that he will be able to get us the required quantity of these boxes from the Customs and also from the shopkeepers to whom the issue tea. For this purpose he said that a sum of Rs. 200/- be paid to him and he would furnish ud with a consolidated voucher after he procures the required number of these boxes price of which will be Rs. 1/8/- each. The estimate of cost for this work will be as under:- 1. Cost of 200 old tea boxes (® Rs. 1/8 each. 300/- 2. Cost of battens' etc. L.S. 100/- 3. Cost of nails etc. '* 15/- 4. Wages of carpenters and coolies. 200/- 5. Cost and labour of Painting . 50/- Total Rs. 665/- Total cost of items (a) &amp; (c) above will therefore be Rs. 865/- only. The entire expenditjpe should be met from the P.7.D. budget under the Head 'Additions &amp; Alterations or Special Repairs'. A.P.A. ^19-9-45. (Zc«jL « dL, cvw \j****£A*r Ll*. P* A • ^ x«oo/. ^ -j ft r A «=» a - j . */ -v &gt;■ _ ' (aJ O-A-t— Ac iH-i id PH. ~~ot rdi £.£. ^ s^. c.No.3022-18/6 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 22nd September, 1945. To The Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum. Subject: Converting a portion of a room and existing water closet into a waiting room and converting a godown near the kitchen into a water closet in the Agency building at Bahrain. . — There is no waiting room for visitors in the Agency and the steady stream of callers for interviews with the Political Agent or Assistant Political Agent are obliged to sit in the Assistant Political Agent*s or Head Munshi*s office. In practice this results in the dislocation of work in both offices and I consider it essential that there should be a waiting room for visitors. 2. I recommend therefore that a portion of Head Munshi's office room is converted into a waiting room. This room is not big enough for the purpose and the adjoining water closet should be removed and form part of it. A new water closet could be made in a godown near the kitchen. These additions and alterations will cost approximately Its. 2000/-* I consider this work of a very urgent nature and would therefore be grateful if you could allot this sum for expenditure during this year and telegraph sanction, so that the work is started immediately. I would then submit a detailed estimate. Political Agent, Bahrain. \No.4131-18/6 Political Agency, Bahrain The 1st October, 1945. To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum, Subject: Dhobi ^hat The existing tank and platform on the outer side of the sea wall, is not satisfactory as a dhobi ghat. It is, therefore, proposed to build a new dhobi ghat near the servants* quarters, as shown on the accompanying rough plan, and it is requested that the necessary sanction may please be accorded at a very early date. A plan and estimate for the same is forwarded herewith for scrutiny in the office of the Executive Engineer, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. Ends. Estimate 1. Site plan 1 C.mmmgmm N«. 4//o75' Bushir#, October, 1945• Te The Political Affent, Bahrain* Memorandum« Dhobi Ghat. , (t&gt; • Reference your memorandum No* 4131-18/6 dated lat October, 1945. Sanction is hereby accorded to start the above noted work at the estimated cost of fo*.1,326/-. The estimate will be sanctioned on return of the ®cecutive Engineer from India. / f ^ i ^ ^ j ecretary to 1/iie Politic^: lesident in the Persian Gulf.No. 2&amp;/lo&lt;f2, British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Dated Bushire, the October, 1945. The Political .agent, Bahrain. , ^ ^to Memorandum. Subject: Converting a portion of a room and existing water closet into a waiting room and converting a godown near the kitchen into water closet in the ^igency buildii at Bahrain. Reference your memorandum No. 3922-18/6 dated the 22nd September, 1945, on the above mentioned subject. 2. The following minor works to be carried out in Bahrain during 1945-46 were included in the budget:- (a) Providing new entrance main gate in the agency building at Bahrain. Rs. 1,500/- (b) Constructing approach road from the main gate to the Agency building at Bahrain. ,r 1,000/- (c) Providing cement concrete floor in the Agency building at Bahrain. ' 3,000/- (d) improvements to bed room, bath room and dressing room in the Agency building at Bahrain. ,f 2,500/- Total Rs. 8,000/- 3 # The Government of India however did not sanction the total amount budgetted for,with the result that it was only possible to provide Rs. 7,000/- for the Bahrain Minor Y/orks. of this amount Rs. 4,440/- would appear to have been spent as follows:- ' (it) Provision of teakwood staircase. Rs. 1,420/- (b) Construction of new entrance gate and approach road. ,f 3,020/- Total Rs. 4,440 4 . as far as can be ascertained from the Bahrain P. d. Office (the Executive Engineer is on leave) neither you nor the Bahrain Supervisor have ever been informed of the final amount provided for Bahrain. Nor do you appear to have been informed of the Minor V/arks for which the provision wasmade. Items (a) and (b) of para 2 have been completed. Will you please confirm that items (c) and (d) have not yet been taken in hand? If items (c) and (a) have not been taken in hand then there is no objection to the balance of fis. 3,560/- being utilized for the construction of the proposed waiting room^, if you consider it more important than the outstanding works. If you decide to utilize fis. 3,560/- for the immediate construction of the waiting room please let me know by telegram^and provision for items (c) ana (d) (assuming of course that they have not yet been taken in hand) will be considered in December when the budget will be reviewed, alternately if you decide to give priority to items (c) and (d^ the provision for the waiting room will be considered at the time of reviewing the budget. In any case an estimate for the proposed v/aiting room may kindly be prepared and sent to me as soon as possible, as far as possible it should be kept within the figure of Rs. 2,000/-. \ in the Persian Gulf- I No*4381-18/6. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 17th October, 1945. To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. Please reserve -eirght ceiling fans for this Agency from the consignment arrived here recently.’^A fj No.PA/C/ So THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 29th October, 194-5., H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM :- With reference to your memoranduni N 0 . 438 I-I 8/6 of the 17th inst, Mr, J.E, Khedouri has now cleared the consignment of ceiling fans. /acic Please arrange to collect from his office the #4§ht fans reserved for the Agency, Bahrain Receipt , DIRECTCR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFEER, BARS IN.for Political Agent, Bahrain. No.4863-18/6 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 25th November, 1945. To The Secretary to the Hon t ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to say that fans are required for the following rooms of the Agency building at Bahrain. a) Head Munshi's office room. b) Waiting room (to be constructed). c) Old ninglish Office room. d) Record room. e) Dressing room to No.2 bed room. f) Verandah in front of drawing room. I have reserved six ceiling fans for the above, from a consignment of fans recently received from the United Kingdom by a local merchant and the enclosed two estimates amounting to Rs.1386/- for the office portion and Rs.693/- for the residential portion of the Agency building are forwarded to you for favour of sanction of expenditure during the current financial year. I have the honour to be, Sir, Yottr most obedient servant,C (itt) '-Jy No.4737 Political Agency, Bahrain The 14th November, 1945. To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain* Dear Sir, I shall be grateful if you will please let me know whether you can supply this Agency with the following wood from old packing cases, and if so, kindly quote the price including transport charges. I will confirm the order on hearing from you* i. li” to li' thick, 3” to 4' v/ide and not less than 4 1 long battens, i ton. ii. to I'” thick, 3 H to 6” wide and not less than 4 f long planks. ton. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.No.4983-18/6. To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 4th December, 1945. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Will you please refer to this office letter No.4737 dated the 14th November, 1945? I shall be grateful if you will please let me have a reply at a very early date. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain. C.No.6045-13/6 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 9th December, 1945. To The Secretary to the Hon’ble Political Resident in Bushire. the the Persian Gulf Sir, Subject: Walt inn roora With reference to your memorandum No.26/1093 dated the 19th October, 1945, I have the honour to say that in accordance with para 3 of your memorandum under reference, the unspent balance appears to be Rs. 2560/- but the following minor works have not been accounted for:- i. Electric lights over the main gate of the Agency. Ps. 500/- ii. Providing locks for the Political Residents 314/- 250/- office building. iii. Teak wood fireplace in P.R's office room, iv. Teak wood pillars and beams in the staircase 260/- of P.H's office. v. Providing ceiling fans in certain office 1336/- rooms of the Agency. vi. Providing ceiling fans in some residential 693/- 1326/- 2000 /- rooms of the Agency building, vii. Dhobi ghat. viii. Waiting room. Total Its. 6719/- 2. Out of the above, items 1 &amp; 2 have since been done but not yet paid for; items 3 &amp; 4 are being put in hand; items 5 &amp; 6, the fans have been reserved and sanction applied for vide my letter No. 4863-18/6 dated the 25th November, 1945. I propose utilising the money sanctioned for item 7 against item No.8 which is urgently required and shall be glad to receive sanction for the baliuice of 13.674/- &amp;s early as possible. Item No. 7 can be postponed till a later date. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant for Political Agent, BahrainThe Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali• Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. December 1st, 1945 Captain R. E. R. Bird, Assistant Political Agent BAHREIN. \ L U Bf B E-R File #209.5* Dear Sir; We can supply you- with the amount of planking as requested in your letter No.4737 of November the 14th, 1945* lumber is, however, in the pile, whifeh requires considerable labour to remove and sort it. At this time such labour is exceedingly scarce. However, if you do urgently require this lumber we would permit you to have your men remove it from the pile. We would be in a position to transport it for you. If your requirement is not too urgent we would be able to perform this work in the next thirty to sixty days. Our charge for this used lumber is RsxlOO/-/* (ftipees One hundred only) jper 1000 (one thousand) board feet, plus our charges for removing from pile and grading plus transportation to Manama. Yours very truly W. P. ANDERSON CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLED}.? COMPANY LIMITEDc Political Agency, Bahrain, The 30th April, 1946. Messrs. Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Karachi. Dear Sirs, The following materials are required very urgently and it is therefore requested that these nay be shipped by the first available boat and consigned to His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrain. The bill of lading and that of your charges should be sent by air mail. i. Solignum 15 gallons (in 5 gallon drums), ii. Wax polish for furniture and wooden floor 50 lbs. (in 1 lb. tins), iii. Copal varnish 10 gallons (in 1 gal. drums) iv. Paint brushes iinglish make 4” Nos. 6. do. do. 3' 1' ii 6 . 6 . Yours faithfully, bL for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded to the Kxport Trade Controllei Karachi, with the request that the export permit for the above may please be furnished direct to Messrs. Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Karachi. ^ I 7$ , IQ / J4AGENTS FOR i— P. ft (i. S. N. Co. B. I. 8. N. Co., Ltd. MINISTRY OF WAR TRANSPORT THE MAIN LINE STEAMSHIP Co.. Ltd. ISTHMIAN STEAMSHIP LINES Ltd, LLOYDS NORTH CHINA INSURANCE Co., Ltd. COMMERCIAL UNION ASSURANCE Co., Ltd. GANHES ROPE Co., Ltd. JENSON A NICHOLSON (India) Ltd. GOU REPORE Co., Ltd. proprietors: KARACHI LANDING A SHIPPING TELEPHONE 2838—2839 two hneft. Telegraohlo Address:— MACKINNONS. ' Codes Used:— Bentley's A . B . C . No. 21. 1. All goods are tandled and forwarded by us on the express understanding that no responsibility is accepted for any loss or damage howsoever caused. Goods are despatched subject to the terms and conditions laid down by the transport company concerned. 2 . Goods lying in our godowns awaiting despatch or shipment are entirely at the risk of the owner unless covered by insurance. 3 . All sailings, fares, freight rates and other particulars quoted herein are subject to alteration with or without notice. nDachinnon HDacheniie &amp; Co. MCLEOD ROAD, 9th Lay POST BOX No. 40. KARACHI, ^/eatinrj dy Q/ciivat(/iny 194 6 \j The Political Agent, Bahrein. In reply please quote :— MS. )£■ n: Dear Sir, We are in receipt of your letter No. 1367-19/6 of the 30th ultimo and in reply would advise that we can supply the following:- 3x1 Gallon drums *Uuprinol M Wooa Preservative standard. Green Shade 4 &gt; 1 Gallon drurrs ,, Cuprinol , • Wood Preservative Brown u. 25 Tins Jensons Wax Polish Hotel size (Contents 2 lb. 3 oz. each) packed in one case 10 x one o.m. gallon tins M Jensolin w standard copal varnish ... 10 gallons packed in one case Rs.9-14-0 per ex godown. Rs.9-14-0 per gal, H 5- 0-0 per tin ex godown. M 11-12-0 per gal ex godown. We regret,English Paint Brushes are not available in the market at present. The prices quoted above are without engagement and subject to fluctuation without notice. Kindly let us have your further instructions per return Airmail. Yours faithfully. Pro. Macjs«mon Mackenzie &amp; Co. PEb/LbG. p.g . Please note the c^rmnokf^l^^^entToned above are manufactured by M/3 # Jenson &lt;* Nicholson (India) Ltd.,Calcutta.No.1698-18/6. To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 20th May, 1946. Messrs. Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co., McLeod Hoad, Karachi. •o rtf- Dear Sirs, r With reference to ^our letter No.G/C &amp; F dated the 9th May, 1946, it is requested that the following may please be supplied without anv delays - i. 3x1 Gallon drums 'Cuprinol' wood preservative brown U shade, ii. 10 Tins of 21bs. 3 oz. each Jensons wax polish. iii. 10x1 Gallon tins w Jensolin H Standard Copal varnish. Bill of lading and that of your charges should be sent by air mail. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain Copy forwarded to the Export Trade Con- ^ troller, Karachi, with the request that the exp&lt;* permit may please be issued direct to the above firm. ^ , c n &lt;p. HTlpl? f 19/, 19 2*.53 S (^) IS/ No.1699-18/6 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 20th May, 1946. To Khan Sahib Abdul Hussein &amp; Brothers, Bahrain. Dear Sirs, Please arrange to supply the following English made paint brushes and send the bill of your charges to this Agency. Paint brushes, 4”, 3” and 1” - 6 of each size. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain xical 'wy . CI ZSL No 3 n /i Btathinium HlaAtiijic S £o. ■—KAMACHI 2838 POST BOX NO* 40 27 th l-aY U)tJ bvAir-l^J^ * Duplicate by Sea * ai 1. /?^6. The Political Agent, Bahrein. DQar oir, _ . ^ tj //~ Be are in receipt of your letter No.lo^d-lJ/o of the 20th instant asking us to supply you the foliovdng:'- I 3x1 Gallon drums M Guprinol rt wood preservative brown U Shade. H 10 T ins of ? lbs. 3 oz. each Jensons wax polish % III 10x1 gallon tins 'Jonsolin** standard Copal varnish. Be have applied to the Export Trade Controller for the necessary Export Licence and will diip the goods aP soon as the licence is granted. Yours faithfully. Pro. Mackinnon IdaCKenzie &amp; Co. -Tlu PDS/LSR. MlHo.1789-18/6. To Political Agency^ Bahrain, The 5th June, 1946. Messrs. Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Post Box No.40, Karachi. r Dear Sirs, Reference your letter No.G. C &amp; F., dated the 30th May, 1946. 2. Please accept the Umbrella Copal Varnish. Yours faithfully, V for Political Agent, Bahrain. t’ c. S &lt;P-ISs ?for Political Agent, Bahrain No,1765-18/6 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 4th June, 1946. To The State Engineer, Bahrain. Memorandum. The telephone instrument installed in the Agency general office (62 m) is^very old one and does not function satisfactorily. I should be grateful if you would arrange to provide a new instrument in its place as soon as possible.I*/* GOVSRMIvlBHT OF BAHRAIN STATE ENGINEER'S DEPARTMENT NO.TEL/1‘l /65 BAHRAIN. 5th June, 1946 Dated: &gt; Rajab, 1365 H.B.M’s Political Agent, BAHRAIN. r I jb./rf Ref .your letter'-f^*i , ^h“18/6 dated Memorandum:- 4th June,1946. We have no new telephone instruments in Stock at present, but as soon as new instruments on order are received, the old instrument in the Agency General office will be replaced, BaV-r t Receipt No ..^/2 ..D .ft! State Engines: Government of Bahrain.m &lt; - Telegraphic Address “ MACKINNONS No. Eg. 204 1 BkeenClkB KARACHI 282* The Political Agent, Bahrein. ly* iiladuiuiou Hlatfenijic &amp; Co. POST BOX NO* 40 dfaiadi] 14th _Jun.e 6 Dear Sir, &amp; 3 DruiiB Wood Preservative Brov/n U Shade. oz 1 Case containing 10 tins of 2 lbs. 3 each Jenson Wax Polish. 1 Case containing 10 x 1 gallon tini \H#.E£l.i a ..l2ml. y i ah , _ With reference to your letter No. 1789-15/6 of the 5th instant, we are arranging to diip the above consignment shortly. Insurance is being arranged against F.P.A. &gt; Jettison, Washing Overboard, Theft, Pilferage, Non-delivery, breakage ^and leakage in excess of 3% on each package. 3V/LSG. Yours faithfully. Pro. Iviackinnon Mackenzie k Go.e&gt; No.2590-18/6« Political Agency, Bahrain, The 10th August, 1946. The State Engineer, Bahrain. ^ \ yM! Memorandum. Reference correspondence resting with my letter No. 2188-18/6 dated the 28th May, 194&amp;^ 2. Will you please let me have an up to date estimate for providing one light point in each room of the block of 10 servants 1 quarters of this Agency. t &lt; d Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain. 1 / /, ;, i ■A ' •^V i -'&gt; Uh % NO.S2/10520 To Custom House, Karachi Dated 26t h July 1946. The Political Agent, Bahrein. o Reference your letters Nos.1367-13/6 and 1593-13/6 dated 30. 4 .1946 and 20.5.1946. The Government of India to whom the matter was referred, have accorded permission to the export of 15 gallons Solignum and 3 gallons 'Cuprinol* wood preservative. A licence is being accordingly issued to Messrs: Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co., Karachi. Shipping bills for wax polish and Copal varnish filed by Messrs: Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co., have already been passed by this department. Export of Paint Brushes is permissible and shipment will be allowed on presentation of the shipping bill. Bahfa'a Receipt No 7- Date A .Rai. Assistant Export Trade Controller For Export Trade Controller,elegraphlc Address : '^V^ACKINNONS ” No.:__ ax. 204.244 Telephone:— KARACHI 2838. \^/4 . (&amp;) No 3. HUriumion ^lachcu^ic &amp; ®o. POST BOX No. 40. e WaracAi; 26.tii Au^ai ^4 &amp; He^i^t^red Air Lail.. Uapiicate by dea Lail. The Political 4gent, Bahrein* Dear 3ir, 3 Drums Wood Preservative 3Jkil^.. Printed For^. Ae enclose a Bill of Lading in respect of the above g ods siapped to Bahrein on /our account per s.s. 'Barpeta' and shall be glad ^f^ou mil kindly acioi owl edge receipt. . T item has been shipped against vour order of the 20th liav 1946/lo tikt of ^ Polish and 10 tins of Lopal Varnish against this order .will be shipped per s.s. ^Bamnrar. - 9 fne three oundles of printed forms have been shipped under instructions from the Manager of the Forms Tress Central i&lt;orms Store, Government of India, Calcutta. Our bill for freight and shipping charges will be oent to you in due course through Messrs. Gray Mackenzie h * j. j.# , nanrein. Bahrain Reccint Enel:- 1 PDS/LSa. tn v ours faithfully. Pro. Lapidnnon -Jackenaio &amp; Co. (P.■Mi legraphic Address € “ MACKINNONS ” Yum on ,v* ® J? 3 ;ul;rn;ic &amp; Co. Ko. Ex. 2Q4 POST BOX NO* 40 1 —kaNacm&lt; 3828 spataoL] 3rd Septemb er /f6 ar.i^ijaal., ejrel Aii. &gt; Duplicate oy Sea Mail. The Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, 1 Case ttax Polish 1 Case Copal Varnish. (?' With further reference to our letter No.Ex.204 ? 224 of the 26th ultimo, we enclose the relative Bill of Lading in respect of the above shipped to Bahrein per s.s. H Ban-ora 11 . Kindly acitfiovl edge receipt. Our bill of charges will follow. Enel:- B/Lading 1 r/lso.C / (5?) No. 2945-18/6 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 9th September, 1946. To Messrs. Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co., Post Box No.40, Karachi. Dear Sirs, I acknowledge receipt of your letter No. Ex.204 dated the 3rd September, 1946, and the enclosed bill of lading. Yours faithfully, Captain. for Pt^aitical Agent, Bahrain*■ ; v A Nos 26/ &lt;3^ » From To Dated Bushire, the-uigust The assistant Sngineer, . . Independent Persian Gulf oub-Jivision, Bushire• ft ^ I y The Political agent, Bahrain. ^ The Political agent, Muscat. The Political agent, Kuwait. H.B.M's Consul, Bunder abbas. H.B.M , s Consul, Bushire. Subject:- Schedule of Demands under 50-C.W.C. External ..flairs 0 +h. v-Aar 1947-48. —— Sir, I have the honour to request you to state your requirements for Original Works,(Minor stezk* &amp; Major), .additions and Alterations and Special Repairs, necessary to be carried out during the year 1947-48. 2&gt; ji S the schedule of demands for 1947-48 is to be submitted to the Government of India, by the 15th October , 1946, ( vide para 3 Appendix 8 of P.W.A. Code), it is requested that ■the information called for in para 1 of this letter may Kindly be furnished through the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, so as to reach this office by the 15th of September 1946, at the latest. list 1 ^ I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ^/f Assistant Engineer, ^ Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division.No. 3161-18/6. POLITICAL AGFNCY, v - BAHRAIN. The 26th September, l q 46. To The Secretary to the Hon T hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN . Iffl.MORANDHM. I enclose herewith a copy of Debit Note No. BI/121 dated the 17th September, 1946, from Messrs. Gray, Mac :enzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Landing charges on items 3 and'4 have been paid by this office. Charges on items 1, 2. and 5 are payable by the Residency and! «! i ji.nu.nj.m ri ci mmiim mmm t Uo.JS'?? -I 8 / 6 -IV To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 2nd November, 1946, Tht Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN . Memorandum: Subject: Schedule of demand under 50 C.W.C., 1 .A. for I947»» 1 48 Reference Assistant Engineer. Independent Persian Gulf Sub Division Circular letter No. 26/363 dated the 21st August, 1946. ? 2. List of works proposed to be carried out during 1947-48 is given below under the respective heads and showing the approximate estimated cost against each item. / ! I, Orl^ln^.l works - minor works. 1. 2 . 3. 4. Building two garages *in the Agency Compound Rs. Additions and alterations to the main Agency building Additions and alterations to the subsidiary buildings attached to the Agency Building Officers’ Lavatory in the Agency Building (Q '%**•*'. Total (Original works) 5 , 000 /- 3 , 000 /- 2 , 500 /- ZPOZr. 11 , 200 /- II. Special Repairs. 1. Special repairs to the Agency main building 2. Special repairs to the P.R.’s Office building 3# Special repairs to the subsidiary buildings attached to the Agency 4. Renewing copper wire gauze to doors and windows Total ( Repairs) 2 , 500 /- 2 , 000 /- 2 , 000 /- . 5 , 000 /.- 11 , 500 /- Grand total of I and II Rs.22.700/- Copy forwarded to the Executive Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Dub Division, Bahrain, for information and necessary action. -A S TPNo.3884-13/6 Political Agency* Bahrain, . The 26th November, 1B46. To The oecretary to the hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Jenorandom: Reference correspondence resting with my memorandum No.3741-13/6 dated the 15th Septem ber , 1946. 2. Twelve estimates in respect of the works to be done in this Agency are sent herewith for the teclinical sanction of the Executive Engineer. for Political Agent, Bahrain. No.3886. Copy v/ith compliments to the Executive Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub division, Bahrain.No.129-18/6 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 12th January, 1947. The Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. i/Iemorandura: l.eference my meiaorandum No.3884-18/6 of the 26th November, 1946. 2. An estimate for repairs to the boundary wall and the construction of two partition walls in the Agency, is sent herewith for the teclmical sanction of the Executive migineer. It i$ requested that very early sanction be accorded, as the wall in the garden has in error already ueen demolished and the hedge by it cut down. TP for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy with compliments to the Executive dn-ineer, Independent Persian uulf Sub divi sion, Bahrain.No. 836 -58/32. P RSIAN GULF RESIDENCY Bahrain April 1947. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. No £ r 2?T.Date .(..^4 gZMOI^NlJUii Reference enclosed extract of a statement of information in respect of Government buildings in Bahrain received from the Government of India. 2. It is requested that the information contained therein be verified and any further particulars as are available in your office be supplied at a very early date. In particular details of the various buildings together with any amounts spent since 1940 on their upkeep and repair from funds other than “SO-Civil Works - Central' may be intimated. S. The Executive Engineer is also being asked to provide such information as he can from his records so that it is not necessary to incorporate in your reply any information not contained in your own records. Secretary to the political Resident Persian Gulf. ys s \v2&gt;ns 46 - J r No. 1422 - 18/6. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 24th April 1947. r X. \ T\ ^ &gt; f i &gt; '' J To The Secretary to the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Bahrain. \&gt;' MEM01'.ANDUM i Reference your memorandum No.836-68/32, dated the 11th April 1947 regarding Government build ings in Bahrain. 2. I enclose a summary of all the information available on the subject in the records of this Agency. It must be realised that the figures given are only approximate, since no records for the period 1917-1930 are available. 3. The only fund other than '50 - Civil Works - Central ,l , available for repairs is the C. C.G. and amounts spent from this grant since 1940 are shown separately in the attached statement. W z' for POLITICAL AGKNT, BAHRAIN, ids KMS&amp;) x %\\ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. DEPARTMENT. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N-B .—This is an ORIGlN'AL\ message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of commumcalion more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram .. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the -Department. „ x „ . PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY No. UI6-58/c2r To ted Bahrain, 21st April 47* POLIUCyc., Bahrain Executive Engineer, P.Vv.D. Bahrain 5* \ cx P SS . (/ ■ ct P pf^:^^-^ r -feMo r andum No.8g6 -58/£2 J Endorsement No.828-5^32 aated 11th April 1947. Government buildings. 2. Please expedite reply. = BEPGU = The issue oi the above has been authorised \\ ^ Secretary to tjie Political Resident. Persian Gulf. S. 44. MOIPC—S2—842(Gnl)MFP—(6806/M-620)—29.8.42—25,000.fa Government State Engineer's Department BAHRAIN (PERSIAN GULF) (ARABIA ) 9*/, 26th April, 1947. Bahrain. Dear Sir, Reference your memorandum dated 17th April, 1947, in connection with the electricity wiring in the Agency, This has been inspected and tested and it is considered that it requires replacement owing to its age. The Approximate cost of re-wiring would be between Rs.800/1000. Yours faithfully.No. 1485 - To POLITICAL AG3NCY, BAHRAIN. 18/16. The 30th April 1947. xK) ) The State lingiUieer. Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. MBMOKANDUM Reference your letter No.PA-23-66, dated the 26th April 1947, reporting on the wiring in the Agency. 2. I should be grateful if you would kindly let me have a detailed estimate of the work to be done, including the exact cost involved, so that the rewiring can be carried out as soon as possible. i/ KM3 »” for POLITICAL AGLNT, BAHRAIN. V HiGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. I 1 Persian Gulf Residency f Dira.rtmint, Bahrain, EXPRESS LETTER (iV. B, This is an ORIGIN AE MESSAGE, sent bp post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To Sai t time and formalities it iA worded and signed as ij it had been so despatched,] From To REPGU, BAHRAIN POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. No. 1087-93/7 £W~* Dated 9 th May ^47- ■ V ' Reference your Menorandu* No. 3577-18/6-4 Novenber 2nd. 1946» Minor works 1947-48. As a result of transfer of control of Persian Gulf administration to HUS.G. , revision of demands has to be made and^os, works Included which cannot be postponed owing to inherent urgency or owing to advanced stage of manufacture etc. Fresh recommendations if any giving detailed reasons for information of H.M.G. are required fw each work to be recommended. I propose to cut out fmx from current year's/budget all the items listed in the memorandum under reference, unless you can produce very strong reasons to the contrary. 3 * If necess ary further communication will follow regarding iiajor works and special repairs. possible. Y ' Ur COMler ‘ t£ on P ar a 2 a^^^ojild be sent as early as =s; =^cs:ser:«;cs*: The issue of the above has been authorised. e Political Resident^ .*.v GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N, 7&gt;, This ts an. ORIGIMAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on / receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To saee time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,) From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN, RKPGU, BAH1- AIN. A'o. /4S;i -18/6 Dated 14 th 1947 * W*. \ Reference your express letter No.1087-93/7 dated the 9th May 1947. 2. The only two minor works in the list given at paragraph 2 I of my memorandum No. 3577-18/6-IV dated the 2nd November 1946, which cannot be postponed are 'building two garages in the Agency compound' . 'in'iese are required for the two Government vehicles sanctioned in your Memorandum No. 668-30/19 dated the 21st March 1947, delivery of which is expected before the end of the year. = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorisedr ^ ASSISTANT POLITICAL AGENT, 0 0 r, BAHRAIN.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Persian Gulf ResJciency,— Dbpabtmnt, Bahrain. EXPRESS LETTER [N. B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,} From REPGU, BAHRAIN. To POLITICAL, BAHKAIN, No. 1159-58/32 £ 7' Bated 17th May, mi 1 r teference correspondence resting with your Memorandum No. 1422-18/6 dated April 24th, 1947. 2. Please send urgently estimate of present-day value of any land owned by Government of India or His Majesty•s' Government in Bahrain* 4 REPGU + The issue of the above has been authorised. VA *\ * 1 L £ 1 * Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.£ \&gt; No* 1770-18/6 Tos POLITICAL AGENCY? BAHRAIN* The 26th May 1947. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain • Memorandum. I should be grateful if you would kindly let me have urgently an estimate of the present day value of (a) the land an which the Agency and attached buildings stand; and (b) the land on which the Victoria Memorial Hospital is built. k/ for Political Agent, Bahrain, .5 13 ./'■ ,; 'iI ^GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. ^(£0 / 12 . CTC y , ^ W LAND DEPARTMENT Wik ^ISL «• 2ZP No: S&amp;6 Dated 10th Hajab,1366 ^ f ‘ 29th May, 1947 The Political Agent, \ ^ ft Bahrain. * C V&gt; S ' Memorandum:- I \ Reference y&lt; 26th May,1947. ,ter No:1770-18/6 dated The land occupied by the Agency is assessed at Rs.2/-/- per square foot and that occupied by the Victoria Memorial Hospital at Rs.2/8/- This is a conservative estimate of its value. Small plots in the neighbourhood have recently fetched Rs.3/8/- per square foot but large areas sell for lower rates than small sites. Government of Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OE INDIA, S. 6. 'y / \&gt; ; _JDepa rtment, EXPRESS LETTER B % —This is an 01UG1NAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use oj the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed* 1 o save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it nod been so despatched*] From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN• No. 1978-18/6 T&gt;ateS tha 11th June, 79 47; Your express letter No* 1159-58/32 dated 17th May 1947. 2. Following are conservative estimates of present- day value:- (a) Land on which the Agency and attached buildings stand; Rs. 2,90,000 assessed @ Rs 2/= per sq*ft.) (b) Land on which Victoria Memorial Hospital is built Rs* 83,000 assessed* (@ Rs 2/8 per sq.fty 3* Please confirm that tfee figures are not required in respect of the land belonging to His Majesty’s Government in the Naval Base. * POLITICAL « uMA The issue of the above has been authorised*ANo. 1420-58/32 Reference your Express Letter No 0 1978- 18/6 dated the 11th June, 1947. Present day value of Government owned buildi^s. 2. Your paragraph 3. Confirmed. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf f 'i ^GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, PERSIAN GI JLi' 1 h:-,SIRKiICY Dbpaetiiint, EXPRESS LETTER [N, B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] D. To POLITICAL BAHRAIN. No. 1511-93/2-A. Dated the 1st July, iP/47. A deputation^consisting of M.Y.Moghal, Executive Engineer, and Abdul Qayum, ^antity Surveyor, arrives Bahrain by air July 3rd. Purpose of visit is to make a thorough examination of all Govern ment lands and buildings and to arrive at an estimate of the present day value of the property. They will also examine the current Budget and works programme of the Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division of the Public Works Department. 2. The deputation are expected to remain in Bahrain until July 6th and will primarily be assisted in their work by the Executive Engineer. Should however the necessity arise they will be instructed to consult you. - REPGU - The issue of the above has been authorised. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian GulfGOVSRMaENT OF BaHHAIN state engineers departi:E irr No.P^ -30 -66 Bahrain II•B*!;! 1 s political -agent Bahrain. 27th June, 1947 Dated: £Jth Shaban^: 1566 Memorandum: - Ref: your memorandum No.1485 - 18/16 dated 30th April, 1947. There are at present in the Agency building 46 light points 38 plug points 24 fan points The wiring for all of these circuits requires replacement owing to its age. The actual quantity of lean covered wire required cannot however be accurately determined until the new circuits are run. It is considered that it could be reasonably assumed that the cost of re-wiring would be between Rs.800/1000/-No.T-iSn -18/6 ' © To The Secretary to the ^on*ble the Political . Resident in the Persian Gulf* Bahrain. MEMORANDUM:. • The electric wiring in this Agency is badly worn out in several places* resulting in a leakage of current and danger of fire. The State Electric Depart ment have estimated that it will cost approximately Rs•1000/- to rewire the building. The Central Contract Grant at my disposal is unlikely to suffice to meit the cost of rewiring; and* ordinarily, extra funds would be asked for in November. As I understand the past procedure for surrender and re-appropriation of funds will be in abeyance by then* I sh*!lc&gt;be grateful if a sum of Rs.1000/- could be placed at my disposal for this purpose now. Sd. G.N. Jackson* Political Agent, Bahrain Attested* POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The &lt;^ 2 'July* 1947 Superintendent * Political Agency* BahrainI ^ ■ - '--f - ■ 1 Telegram From To G.T.C. Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Agent, Bahrain, (by hand) Political Agent, Muscat. Political Agent, Kuwait. No. A/832. Dated the 23rd October, 1947. IMPORTANT Please telegraph urgently estimated provision required for works next financial year under following headsi- (a) Ordinary repairs. (Central Contract Grant). (b) Special repairs. (c) Minor works. (d) Major works. and (e) Replacement and repairs of office furniture equipment« Until ownership of buildings is decided provision should only be made for unavoidable expenditure. 3. Rough details of minor and major works should be given. Here again expenditure must be confined to essentials 4. To Kuwait only . Include provision for house for Quarantine Medical Officer. Coast Agency buildings with rough programme of construc tion for next and subsequent financial years.GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, Deparimknt, (A T , I\ 2 his is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE^ sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue uve of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sa&gt; e time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had bt&amp;u so despatched,] From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. 1 REPGU, BAHRAIN. No. Dated- m S U -18/6 5 10th H©ve5niber f 47. Reference your telegram No.A/832, dated the 23rd October, 1947. 2 * Ihe following provision is required for works in the Bahrain Agency for the next financial yeari- a) Ordinary repairs (Central Contract Grant)Rs.5000 b) Special repairs Rs.3000/- c) ildinor works Rs. 5700/- d) Major works 1* Nil e) Office equipment ^ 2500/- j' 1 ■1 Details of minor works: (1) building two garages; Rs•5000/- vide Agency Express Letter No.1652, dated 14th May, 1947, (II) Provision of lavatory in the Agency office;Rs.700/- 3 * The existing Agency building on the Trucial Coast is not the property of the Government of India or of His Majesty’s GovemneAt and no provision has been made for repairing or al tering it,Rs.200,000 will be required in 1948 to build a new Agency building in Sharjah with accommodation on the 1st floor for a Political Agent. A further Rs.50,000 would be required in the subsequent financial year to provide a separate house for a British clerk. F v*- tvivO ^ t = political = The issue of the above has been authorised. s. 6. MIT*—601 B&amp;P—(M-820)—23-7-36—300.000. \c iW| :S- Pelitical Agent, Bahrain.PERSIAN fPULE-EESIDSNGY Dbpabtu^t, BAHRAIN EXPRESS LETTER —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Political Agent, Bahrain* No. ^*^4- 61/4 Dated 5 th November, 19&amp;7. Subiect : Budget Provision for works ^ for 1948 - 49* Reference this Residency telegram No.A/832 dated 23rd October, 1947. 2. Please expedite reply. - RB PCrll - The issue of the above has been authorised. * /'O for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. S. 6. MFP—1407 S&amp;P-{M-2339)—25-5-37—300,000.UVt No* 65-93/2(b) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BiiHRA IN • Cth Jkiiukry, 1948* To The politic*! Agen RaHRAIN/MUSCAT Memorkndum. In order that Tunas should not lapse will political agent's please ensure that works, Tor which Tunas have been proviued, are carrieu out beTore the enu oT the current Tinancial year. a list oT works oT your Agency is appendeu. I a Secretary to th#* Political Resiuent^n th6 Persian Gulfpolitical agency, Bahrain. Item No * Name ol Wurk s Ebtimatea cost . 1. Builain^ 2 garages in the Rs 0 5,006/- Agency compound. —^■Bx. t;o. P35- ,v POLITICAL AGEI1CY Bahrain. , The 25th •'enuary, V&gt;48. To The Secret ry to the Ho-'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Subject: Construction of Garages in the Agency. MEMORANDUM. u l Reference your memorandum No. 65-93/2(b) date' the 9th January, 1948, reg*»rding the works to be carried out in this Agency. 2, I should be grateful for an advance of Pc. 1,000/- to me t the immediate expenses of unskilled labour etc., as it wil 1 not be possible to proceed with the work until necessary advance as requested is made. for Political Agent, Bahrain.No.645-18/6 POLITICAL AGENCY, Bahrain. T]Je 26th February, 1948. To The State iingineer, Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Memorandum Reference your memorandum No.PA-30-66, dated the 27th June, 1947. 2. The recent damp spell has hastened the deterioration of the wiring in the Agency and so increased the danger of fire. 3 . I should therefore be grateful if the work of re-wiring could be taken on hand now, or as soon as possible. MMATelegrams Add: 'ALMOAYYED' Telephone No j\&gt;S YOUSUF KHALIL ALMOAYYED GENERAL MERCHANT &amp; COMMISSION AGENT BAHRAIN P. Gulf (Jb Jilj) • Lil ^*1) o jjii - Manama iQth torch .1948 j &lt;toUI YOf/i^ i&lt;£F Ot/R REF HBMPABP/5/48. Political Agent. Bahrain. P. Gulf. . Dear Sir, RE VyIRING YOUR OFFICE AND RESIDENT OFFICE ^ith refrence to your interest in having an estimate for the replacement of all the old umisefull electric wring in your 4c resident office. We have sent our electriction to examine all the electric wiring in this house. We are pleased to give below our cotation for the worK that atst be done, to put the building in safe condition for long period. 54 Points in the first flat which called as your resident has to be replaced wiflE complete new lead cover wiring which need not less than 2800 ft. to as. 6/- per foot. Qmrk 1 dozen Join Boxes, 24 pets Clips, 8 lbs Nails, 1 dozen Lamp holders, 2 dozens Blocks, 4 dozens Connectors, 8 pets Raw1 Plug, 8 pets Screws, 1 dozen Switches, which all required to be used for fitting the wiring, value...... Wireman labour charges for doing the above job Rs. 1050.00 ris 500.00 500.00 ft». 1650.00 Rs If you have no objection in getting the job done by only replacing the damage wring and keep the rest „hich may work for an other one year, that we can do the job at not more then Rs. 700.00. RE OFFICE 29 Points in the office has to replaced with complete new lead cover rire which need not less than 1400 ft. b as. 6/- per ft. Another electric accessories required to fit the above ^ points and make them in good working condition, value Wireraan labour charges for doing the 29 points Rs. 525.00 Rs. Rs. Rs. 150.00 165.00 840.00 If you have no objection in getting the job by only replacing the damage wi^inf^keep the rest which may work for another one year that we can do the job at not more than Rs. 450.00, We anyhow advise that the replacement in the wiring for the mentioned points is very neccesery to portect the building. Awaiting your kind suggestion. Your faithfully. Y. K. ^IlJGAYYED.0.0. No 803-18/6 The 11th March, 1948 'htictr* P-J X enclose a sample of the wire which Y.K.Almoayyed proposes to instal in the Agency f and about which I spoke to you this morning. 2, Would you be kind enough to get one of your technical people to examine it and let us know whether it is likely to give satisfactory service and also whether the price of Annas 6 per foot for which Almoayyed is asking us, is a reasonable one ? Group Captain H.P.G. Leigh, The State Engineer, . Bahrain. Yours sincerely, fe f&gt;Bahrain Government State Engineer's Department u 1 t cf-Wl '-yp - &lt;£/?*/• D.UNo. BAHRAIN (PERSIAN GULF) l A Ft A B I A ) 9&lt;*a&gt; 11th March, 1948, Dear / r i u r T&lt;i This wire is quite suitable for rewiring of individual light points, but not for circuits controlling several numbers of lights, tfor the latter^ twin 3/.036 Lead Covered «^ire is recommended. The cost price of wire sent is As.3/S/- per foot (Less customs duty). Yours % / Patrick Stobart, Esq., The agency, Bahrain.POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. No.1065-18/6 Th« 5th April, 1948. To The State Engineer, Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Memorandum 0 Reference your memorandum No.PA-7-67, dated the 1st Mu.rch, 1948, regarding the rewiring of the Agency. 2. After careful consideration I have come to the conclusion that it would be better if the rewiring could be done by you. I am therefore enclosing a cheque for Rs.1000/- towards the cost of rewiring, and shall be grateful if the work can be put “in hand as early as possible. 3 . Kindly acknowledge receipt of the draft. MMA for Political Agent, Bahrain.No Political Agency, Bahrain, the May 1948 The State Engineer, Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Memorandum * r 5 Receipt is acknowledged o£ the sum of sent with your memorandum No. PA/ie/67 dated May 1948. for Political Agent Rs. £50/- the 24th , Bahrain./ POLITICAL AGENCY, Nc.R-171 BAHRAIN, The 12th July 1948 © To The Secretary to His Excellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bahrain MEMORANDUM We want urgently 200 yards wire gauze for use in the Agency. It is available locally but your authority for the purchase of this quantity is requested. The cost will be Rs.1/12/0 per yard. For Political Agent, Bahrain NNR&amp;\4' . Ak- e^ju^r tZ /u-^v fX. irU(Jz. ^ /W^- ^ ^ Z 7 ^ / ^^^XjW^a-4— WAZ- a&gt;^4 , ^ 4 /£. l ^ J ‘ ^ - lo^y^ , ^t^*'. /— ^ : - (b 1 ^ n A_M- I am sorry, by P.O. I meant P.A» ( i»e. officer /^ in charge of current duties as P-A.) The p.u»c« only covers the Agency building and we receive such letters once every year. The building occupied by the Publicity Office is not included in this estimate and hence is not included in the 'Agency building'. This building now belongs to P.W.D. and any additions or alterations can be done withoa by direct reference to the Asstt* Engineer ? PeWeD#* Bushire* who will include the cost in his own requirements and obtain the necessary sanction^ from the Government of India* P*0. in the Persian Gulf» I presume is his own controlling officer an&lt; ^ directly under P.R., he can therefore refer the question of the accommodation of his staff direct to Secretary Bushire* In any case the p*u*c* does not deal with any building not under the direct control of P.A. ^^Jkl I ^T/Vvw (tzfrt ~ A ^ ■ 11y '9/ . ✓ R ef&gt;ll &gt; P.ps- pages 14-15. 3/, This Agency although provided for the renewal of the floor of the south verandah and the turning over of the verandah roof beams which are sagging and required replace ment during the year 1942-43,vide p.15, but it seems that no action has so far been taken on that provision. No proper detailed estimates for the abovementioned provision were submitted at that time as the Superviser in charge was seriously ill in the hospital. I have enquired from Mohsin on the above subject who states that nothing downstairs is required to be altered or additions made thereto excepting the proposal made for the south verandah during the year 1942-43. Unless any additions or alterations are required to be made upstairs we may inform thefiAsst.Engineer, I. P.G.Subr Division,Bushire, that our requirements for Original Works- for 1943-44, additions and alterations in the Agency building/are the same as intimated vide page.15. Submitted pi. 31/8/42I L I spoke to Mr. Mohammed Jafar, P.W.D., who states that the cement is not available in the market for sale# He says that he has been carrying on with the work in the Agency with cement from his small stock. But he suggests that you approach either the Naval or H.A.F. authorities to supply you with cement. He says that they have a stock of about 60,000 tons of cement. If. they supply you with it, the cost will be about Rs.5/- per bag please. 9-1 l/w Lu^-U, a • 'f/i y//o IT' Mr.Malak of the P.W.D. says that the estimated amount required for repairs in the Agency Compound is 300 bags (rough estimation) please.P. A cj 'J The gardener reports that there are long cracks in the walls of the cistern in the garden, which require repair. If you approve the mason who is now working on the tennis court may be asked to do it please.a/o WZ-oLJ 3-7 /11 it to Jp-^ 6*n) Kindly sec Supdt, P.'Y.D’s note cUited the 17th February 1944 submitted below* 'fork in P*A*s Dressing Hoorn and English Office is finished, tfork in Confidential Office is still in progress and will finish soon. There will be anticipated savings of Hs* 600 from the grants sanctioned for P.A’s Dressing Hoorn and C.O. The estimate for Hhglish Office (pages 49-50) provided for glass and masory only and for this Rs* 2600 were pKflichstKot estimated. Similarly estimate for Confidential Office (page ) provided for dismantling and alterations Mow the following extra works not provided for in the original estimates are rdquired to be carried out ^drer* under orders of the P.A: English Office: Removal of 3 fans from old room and fitting them in the new room. Fitting of 3 new lights. Removal of wooden floor from the old room and re laying it in new room, which is bigger than the old room. C onfidentia1 Offic e: Extra fan and lights. charges on /SV. The P.tf.D. Supdt. says he can meet xxxt fans and lights from the savings of fejsdxrH&amp;m xxh C.O., and from the savings of bed room the cost of transferring wooden floors can be met. If it is decided to- purchase extra wood for new English Office an extra sum of Rs* 450/- is required, but if the Supdt 1 s suggestion is appro/ed no extra money is required. Submitted for erders. /&amp;!. It It-. a/*- * L . A/p /j£7-/v/ litf , A//Ol■1 /'I • 0) rj.. J?-a -&gt; erf a ■ ‘7-&lt;+i~ (i S ' &lt;=■ A /U»* 3 ^ /-J * 5 * 4* J n^JU* cS?c The present dhobi ghat is entirely unsatisfactory and more so because its use involves running water through the small 'Bircha' near the Indian Assistant's Court and all my efforts to have this water economically used and only turned on when it is required have failed. A lock which I had put on the tap was stolen. 2. It is a sorry state of affairs when the Agency is continually complaining to the State of waste of water and at the same time wast^it in large quantities itself. ^ 3. A new dhobi ghat will have to be built where the water can be used economically. There was a previous proposal and I should like to see the papers though my impression was that the scheme put up by Mr. Qadri was rather too expensive. A.P.A. 10.9.'45. =?;&gt;? od? P ) cr ~ tl &lt;X_jL 5 J . ' H' 1 . /- ki Ov^T-® AM'• g. ■ - L*et [ - mC ■ iv 3t.8-o /}. -J j ^ . fLjr ^- I Please see pages &amp;42 to 147. Oc?.? The question of provision of electric light in the servants' quarters of the Agency was raised in May, 1945 and the estimate for fixing up light points in the 10 rooms w£s called for from the State Engineer. He gave an estimate of Rs.300/- for fixing one light point in each of the rooms; but the work^was not put in hand as the then P.A. did not want it don(f^th«4li*vide n. paras 735 to 237) The Agency dhobi,who is occupying one of the rooms, is making repeated requests r or a light in his room to enable him to work in the nights. He is willing to pay the entire con sumption changes. As the building belongs to the govt.,PWD will pay the installation charges, but sanction from Bushire is necessary. Jt* The amount involved is not big/ the Supervisor thinks that the Executive Engineer will sanction the work} ’..hen a reference is made to him. For orders if we may approach Bushire. 330 4 » 7 OU+r Mi /Ve ui ( •fi i*- .. ^ tUrnJbl. i « I ■5&gt;y ■</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000175_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1638</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000175</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1638</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 18/6 IV Agency Buildings. Special Repairs. Vols I to III.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-25T22:08:38</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (296 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 298; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-218; these numbers are also written in pencil or crayon, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of papers, mostly correspondence, relating to works to be carried out to the Political Agency in Bahrain.It includes correspondence between the Political Agent, Bahrain, and the Executive Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division, regarding requirements of original works and additions and alterations, which the Political Agent considered necessary to be carried out in the Agency Buildings for particular years.It also includes correspondence between the Political Agent and the Army and Navy Stores regarding the despatch and shipment of six rolls of copper gauze.In addition, the file includes correspondence relating to the following: water borne sanitation in the Agency building; repairs needed to the Agency roof; fans required for rooms in the Agency building; the rewiring of the Political Agency (this correspondence includes an envelope, folio 242, containing a sample of wire).Other correspondents include: the Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division; the State Engineer, Government of Bahrain; the Superintendent, Public Works Department, Bahrain; the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf (‘Britconsul, Bushire’ in the telegrams); and Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain.Detailed file notes are found on folios 249 to 297.The file includes a letter in Arabic (folio 37).The file includes architectural drawings on folios 28 [IOR/R/15/2/1638, f 28], 50 [IOR/R/15/2/1638, f 50] and 53 [IOR/R/15/2/1638, f 53].</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Independent Persian Gulf Sub Division, Executive Engineer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Architectural plans</topic></subject><subject><topic>Architectural drawings</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Bahrain, State Engineer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Public Works Department, Superintendent, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Army and Navy Stores Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Sanitation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000175#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>