<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000043_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-10-04T11:39:13.470Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Telegram A.ld — “NASIB” Muscat. &amp; K. B. NASSIB BIN MAHOMED &amp; SON. .X) ^ ^ j j J J ^ 9 ^o. A/70/'9, To, ^ The Political Ascnt T T # p # M’s Crnnsul, Muscat. landing charges on ±\ A ^ Transhipment c&amp;Erio. In continuation of our letter No. A/67/^9 dated £ 6 th Oct. , 19 4 9. w e leg to inform you that the Director of Customs has r landing confined to accept half the^/charges on the cai'go transhipped ex steamer direct to the country crafts without bringing it on shore ^ especially the cor go consigned to A. x landing Therefore^ the^/charges will be acceptable as under / gallon tin^ as. 2/- each, 55 ] itre dx-um barrels small and large cases as. 6 /- each. Thanking you in anticipation, w e beg to remain : oUj.- most obedient servants, Khan Pahadur.1 stTelegram yliW.-—“NASIB” Muscat. K. uA ■ B. NASSIB BIN MAHOMED &amp; SON. 8 -X) y j j j J TTo # A/67Z 1 9. To, The Political Ardent Muscaj;. MUSCAT, £6th Ootoher 194 9 (ARABIA) ^ H P M*s Consul, Sir, jAp: ' L a Chares on Chaj.*go Transhipped , in uscat Hart our. ^e trace are advised hy our Principals at Abadan that they have heen informed hy Political Resident Bahrein, for the recovery of the Landing Charges,on goods transhipped in Ifuscat Harbour at half the normal rates, in future. A consignment for transhipment to 4 4 5 at Masirah has recently been brought here on 22 nd instant. While paying the landing charges,theDirector General of Customs presses us for full charges, in reply to our request in the above mattei’ ,TT e shall therefore,be grateful if you kindly please inform him 00 collect haljf charges on the goods tx*anshipped now and being transhipped in future alsq on ^45 Account. Thanking you in anticipation. p f , / * Y- a-*t+Lii ^ nug uo x-emain, Sir, Your most obedient servant i For P; P ; Has sib pin Fohamed &amp; So: C- .Na.'nager. To,PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY 27th August, 1949 BAHRAIN (256/5/49) s,9 Please refer to your letter No. (8/8/96/49) of the 11th August about charges in respect of aviation petrol ^ C $ transhipped in Muscat harbour. You appear to have overlooked my letter 134/6/49 of the 14th May to the Anglo-Iranian Gil Company and the Company’s letter 10.N/9 of the 7th June received in reply. A copy of this correspondence was sent to you. If it cannot be traced please let us know. R.Mc.C. Andrew, Esq., Political Agent, Muscat.110.(^/8/96/49} British Consulate Muscat August ll f 1 9 4 9 Dear Mr. Rashid In accordance with our conversation of the 10th August, I am writing to confirm that I consider your redrafting of para I Chapter X of the Muscat Customs Manual, contained in your letter to Ellison of May 8 th, should prevent any ambiguity in xuture on the subject of transhipment and I agree to the proposed amendment. Yours sincerely, Mr. M.A.Rashid, Director General of Customs,_ A . .ANGLO IRANIAN OIL COMPANY LTD. ^ 1 ■' ■ ■■.! ■•«■■■.• .., 1 ,. &gt; ■ ■ Ml COPY No.lO.N/9 Abadan, Khuzistan, Iran. 7th June, 1949. H*3.M.’s Political Resident, The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. Your Excellency, Fuel Supplies Transhipped in Muscat Harbour. $ We beg to acknowledge your letter No.256/2/49 of 14. 5^49 and wish to express -j our.gratitude for your representations to the Muscat Authorities on our behalf. V/e note that landing charges in respect of goods transhipped in Muscat Harbour will be recovered at half the ordinary rate, and have to advise that the refund claimed in our ll.J/9 of 29th March 1949 has been received. We have the honour to remain. Your Excellency*s Most humble and obedient Servants, FCR aNGLC IRANIAN CIL COMPANY LTD. SIGNEDMM ■■■■■■■ mi NO.(8/8/96/49) Political Agency, Muscat. August 11, 1949* c Dear Jakins, / ^ I am not certain whether Ellison ever discussed with Sir Rupert Hay at any time the case of charges in respect of aviation petrol transhipped in Muscat harbour to which Sir Rupert’s letter 134/4/49 of the 15th March refers; but as no action has been recorded on the file I am writing to let you know the present situation. 2. The relevant passage in the Muscat Customs Regulations is certainly ambiguous on the question of transhipment, as it says that charges are leviable on f, All cargo whether manifested or not, except passenger’s baggage carried by steamers and intended for Muscat” : the Arabic text, which is usually considered the authentic, is more explicit, and reads ” All cargo...... brought on steamers to Muscat”• Legally the Anglo Iranian Oil Company appear to have a good case, though I find that in a similar case during Major Stewart’s time it was ruled by this Agency that the regulations covered transhipment. 3# However, I understand from the Director General of Customs that they have dropped their demands against Anglo Iranian Oil Company in this cases but he is introducing a more comprehensive clause reading ” All cargo........ including all transhipment goods, carried / by steamers,••• R.G.Jakins, Esquire, Acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN .• -Aby steamers, launches, barges or tugs, but excluding country craft, arriving at Muscat..”. This should cover any similar case that might occur before the issue of the new Customs Regulations on which Woods- Ballard is now working. 4. As regards the other points, I fully agree that exemption from duty does not entitle the Royal Air Force to make their own arrangements in of contravention/the landing monopoly. The question of Royal Air Force petrol is one on which the Sultan is extraordinarily touchy: it is the only subject over which he insists I must deal direct with him and not through Woods Ballard, and brings it up every time I see him. I have no reason to think the landing contractor’s charges exorbitant: the rate is an overall one of 4 annas per package ( except very large ones), a system which makes for facility of accounting and gives a very fair general rate. To claim that their own agents can land at Rs. 4 /- per 100 tins is an exaggeration: if they did so at the present rates of wages it would involve them in a very serious loss. Yours sincerely AAM Will P.A. please see Serials 2 pnd 3 of this file, my note of 24th April anti a rough draft to Sir Rupert Hay which was not issued by Mr. Ellison? 2. After drafting this S.O. letter Mr. Ellison saw His Highness and mentioned this case to him who said th-t he presumed, without prejudice to this case, that the English text is the correct version and that the Arabic text is only a translation. He suggseted to discuss the case with Director General of Customs. The English text was compiled by the then^Director General of Customs. 3. After his return from the palace, Mr. Ellison saw the Director General of Customs and had a long talk with him on the subject. Unfortunately no minute of the discussion was left but I believe it was agreed that the Landing Contractor ^ill be persuaded by the customs to waive the charge but an amendment was suggested in the Customs Manual to avoid any misinterpretation of Rules in the future and the S.O. letter from Mr. Rashid is the outcome of the discussion.RrtHRnlN 14th Way 1949 a representative of yours Cjinje to see me on the ±2th March to complain regarding a demand received from the Muscat director of Customs that landing charges should be paid in respect of aviation petrol transhipped in Muscat harbour direct from bar es into uhows ror on/^rd ship ment to Masirah. I have discussed this matter re ently in uscat ^nd the ' us cat Government are v/iliin^ to aive their emand (or make a refund if payment has already been made) in respect of the transhipment in question, but in future propose to recover landing charges at half the ordinary rcite in respect of goods transhipped in Muscat harbour. Yours faithfully, The General manager, i»nglo-Iron ion Gil Co., abadan, Jshuzistan, IRaN. (Signei) W. R.L The Palace Muscat 20 th June 1949 S 5 Please refer to your letter Ho*(5/8/96/49) dated 7th June 1949 addressed to our Minister for Poreign Affairs, We regret that the proposal made l^y the A,I, 0 *Conipany Limited is not acceptable to us and they should pay the full customs duty and other charges on importation into Salalah and Mas i rah. / . ^7“^ • T /0 Tuif. • • on, His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat.NO.(5/8/96/49) BRITISH CONSULATE MUSCAT. June 7*1949 Sir I have the Jaonour to enclose herewith an extract from a letter No. 11./J/9 of the 29th March received from the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company* Limited, Abadan and shall be glad if you will Inform * me whether the proposal outlined In the enclosure is acceptable to the Muscat Government. I have the honour to be Sir Your obedient Servant The Minister of Foreign Affairs, . M U S .. C ,jL£* AAf / • • • » Political Agent, • •••••••••••&lt;&gt;••••• Muscat. (26/65/49 ) For favour of action on the last sen tence of the third paragraph. With the compliments of the Political Resident. British Residency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. •' .. .S'Zth .ArsU 1949.1 X COPY Noai.J/s Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Itcl. Abadan, Khuzistan, Iran. 29th March 1949. H.B.M’s Political Resident, The Naval Base, Jufair, Bahrain. Your Excellency, jn -- 1 Fuel Supplies to Civil Aircraft at Masirah and Salalah. Following recent conversations on the above subject we write to confirm the points raised by us and we hope that a summary of these may be of value. Our London Principals have recently concluded a temporary agreement with the Air Ministry whereby civil aircraft may be refuelled at Masirah and Salalah, on our behalf by the R.A.F. These aircraft are at present exclusively casual operators and permission to refuel at these points has to be obtained from H.Q. British Forces, Aden. Fuel to meet their expected requirement has been despatched to the points in question by the same method as fuel to meet the R.A.F’s normal requirement there. It has been forwarded to Muscat in our craft, the greater part however being sent in towed k-parges and not by ship and there transhipped to dhows for onfor- 7 warding to destination. The fuel is being delivered to the R.A.F. at these points and will be stored by them until such time as it is issued, and on this account it is suggested that Customs and any other duties payable to the Mifscat Authorities should be paid monthly on the basis of actual issues to civi^l aircraft. These will be communicated to us by the R.A.F. and we in turn propose that we should advise our Muscat Agents accordingly, authorising them to make the proper payments. We should be glad to know if this proposal is acceptable to the Muscat Authorities. ^ * In this connection we must mention our submission that the transhipment at sea of these cargoes does not come within the exclusive province of the Muscat Landing Contractor in so far as his activities are defined in the Muscat Customs Manual Chapter X and.XV, and that we are free to employ any contractor or other party for the purposes of this transfer. We therefore claim the refund of a deposit of Es.3134/- recently paid to Muscat Customs against full landing charges. ^ ^ % In conclusion we must express our gratitude for the assis tance which we have received in this connection and ask that our claims may be fully represented to the Muscat Authorities. We have the honour to remain, Your Excellency’s 0 Most Humble and Obedient Servants, For ANGLO IRANIAN OIL COMPANY LTD. (G.W. MARSHALL)© /?-■ I ! u CUSTOM HOUSK, MUSCAT, th« 8th May, 19^9 /jLcU/l/ 'Ttyl/ In th* light of our conversation, I suggest that pare 1, chapter X, page 33 of the Muscat Customs Manual, vihich reads as follows, 'All cargo whether manifested or not, except passenger's baggage carried by steamers and intended for Muscat, Matrah or Gwadur, shall be landed by the Landing Contractor appointed for the purpose# Merchants will have no right to arrange for their landing directly', may in future be read as the following, 'All cargo whether manifested or not, including all transhipment goods, except passenger's baggage, carried by steamers, launches, barges or tugs, but excluding country craft, arriving at Muscat, Matrah or Gwadur, shall be landed from the carrying vessel to the Customs wharf or from one vessel to another by the Landing Contractor appointed for the purpose. Merchants ana owners will have no right to arrange for their landing directly'. This will come into force immediately and will apply to local as well as British subjects, as soon as you agree to the proposed amendment.PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 15th March, 1949. A Mr. Bird of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company came to see me on the 12 th March to complain regarding a demand received from the Muscat Director of Customs that landing charges should be paid in respect of aviation petrol tran shipped in Muscat harbour direct from the barges into dhows for onward shipment to Masirah. The barges I understand were brought to Muscat by the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company's tug 'Tavana'. 2. Bird claimed that landing charges were not payable because (a) the goods were never landed at Muscat, and (b) they were unloaded from barges and the landing contractor is only entitled to recover charges in res pect of goods unloaded from steamers. He also seemed to think that as the goods were intended for the R.A.F. they should be exempted from payment of landing charges. I understand that the Muscat customs department are interested as they receive 15$ of the landing charges. 3. Will you kindly let me have your comments ? Prima Facie it would appear to me that the argument at (a) is sound unless the landing contractor's monopoly specifically covers the transhipment of goods at sea. I am not very much impres sed by the argument (b) and while the R.A.F. are exempt from customs duty, I am doubtful whether they are entitled to make their own arrangements for landing in contravention of the landing contractor's monopoly. 4. Incidentally, Bird complained that the landing con tractor's charges were exorbitant. They have to pay him at the rate of 4 as. per tin for kerosene etc., landed at Mus cat, whereas their own agent can arrange to land their goods at the rate of Rs.4/- per 100 tins. Muscat. ■■■■■■</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000043_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/292</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000043</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/292</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/96 Muscat State Landing Contractors.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-20T23:13:38</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (18 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 20; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file relates to landing contractors at Muscat. The correspondence concerns the question of whether goods transhipped in Muscat harbour should be subject to landing charges. It follows a complaint from the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company regarding charges incurred for transhipping aviation petrol at Muscat.Notable correspondents include the following: the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company; the Sultan of Muscat and Oman [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd]; the Government of Muscat and Oman's Director of Customs.The Arabic language material consists of letterheads on two letters from Messrs Khan Bahadur Nassib bin Mahomed and Son.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Muscat and Oman, Director-General of Customs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Cargo handling</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Harbours</topic></subject><subject><topic>Customs administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000043#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>