<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000016_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-13T12:39:27.226Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NAME OP PILE: MUSCAT STATE AFFAIRS: NA*IM TRIBEVi 11 muscat STATE AFFAIRS .TRIBES- Naim Trite. From - To Previous numberf IkJt utility#**** v ,. v ^»rv.rV- ■ '''’'• iSS* ITAIM 1845-1869. 'v ^rom a summary of the question of tne 'Vahabee advances on Berayraee written by the Foreign Secretary in 1870. ' From the Bombay Selections re 0 ardin o the Persian luff, it appears that the 3 ? ort of Beraymee ^ r as bailt by the '‘.'ahabee General Syud bin J r ootluk, and was hela by the T 'ahabees until the decline of their power, when it was taken possession of by the Naeem tribe, who inhabit the surrounding country. It is really the key to Oman. 1 In 1845, ''’''hen the '/ahabee forces were march ing to demand tribute from Unseat, the Fort of 3erayin.ee again fell into the hands of Syud bin Mootluk, and the Chiefs of the Naeem and other nei^iibouriug tribes ten dered their allegiance. The Beniyas Chief reduced the . f 'Oit of Beraymee and defeated the '/ahabee troox*s in 1848, but the aha bees recovered it the following year and appea lo have held it ever since till it was taken by Azan bin i.rheis in June last. It was always considered as the V.aha- bee outpost towards Oman, and held by a T 7ahabee Governor, and in 1853 Syud Thoweynee, then Chief of Muscat, agreed to the permanent occupation of Beraymee by the 'ahabees. During the recent contest for power in Muscat oideyree, the bahabee Lieutenant of Beraymee, was pledged to the side of Syud Salem. He was murdered, however, by the Chief of Shargah on 7th April last year. On his death the Naeem tribe, according to Colonel Disbrowe, who ’com plained bitterly of oppression suffered at the hands of Sideyree, the late hahabee Lieutenant, resolved in their minds how they could free themselves from the Tahabee yoke and resorted to the expedient of inviting Azan to take possession of Beraymee. Azan and Khulelee not being the men to allow grass to grow under their feet, the offer of the baeem was accepted.* The proceedings of Azan were most probablyprobably hastened by a peremptory demand made on him by the V/ahabees for payment of tribate. At any rate the result v/as tnat Azan loarched on l^eraymee Tt, ith about 1,500 men, and took it on the 18th of June after a very slight resistance.“c NAIM. On 5 th Jany 1885, the T, « r ali of Sohar, Hamad bin Naser, wrote Sultan Saif came 10 me when he heard that I had made his subsidy payable from une Muscat treasury,which course became difficult to him,but after much endeavour,! settle with him that he should receive it from the said treasur and paid fx’om tne Sohar treasury every six months. The people of the Jizzi valley have ^iven me tneir covenant and I have appointed men from amon^ them to p;uard it with fixed salaries,and am waiting for the proof of their loyalty. There is no other vexation but the other branch of the Naim,the Saluf.But as for Muhammad bin Ali bin Hamad, he has hiven me ^ood answers as I expected from him.S HiMKH SfJLTyUT 3 Hi ltO}iAj r Jlr]T) ~]L SAIF of the KL XiUir«M He took a leading part at the battle of Dank on tne bth of October 1870, 'vhen Seyyid Toorkee at the nead of a large force consisting of the Kaeem, A1 Amree Al tfeneoeh and. the Aar ad tribes, conpletely routed the lorces oi the Imam Seyyid Azsan bin IQiaio who has at last to escape to Sohar. The haeem at the time were led by Sultan bin ! ohammed and ihu f an bin Fadal both of whom greatly distinguished themselves. About 1877 Sultan led t-.n expedition against the Beni Yas and in the engagement which occurred at Kifeifeh completely defeated them. Following up this victory he gave the Beni Yas in the iollowing year another battle at Jubal near Berieiuee in wnich also the Beni Yas were defeated with a great loss. He was considered a powerful and important Sneikh. He wa ® Temeeraeh of the Khawatar a fakhidh of the Naeem.KAIK 1875 No. 143 of 187o 60 After the death of Khuleylee the Meeaheh sub tribe of the J31 Nain took the fort of 3u Sinein and of- ferred their allegiance to H.H. Seyjid Toorkee ^ho had then assumed power. This led to a collision between Sheikh Burgash of the SI Amir sub-tribe of the Naim and Sheikh Mohammed Din Suliman of the SI Meeaneh. Sneikh Bur^ash plundered tne village of Rooba and on returning he also took the fort of Juss. Sheikh Ilohainmed endeavoured to relieve Juss out Sneikh Burgash refused to restore it until Bu Sinein -'as given up by the SI Keeaheh. No. 321 of 1873 120 When Seyyid Toorkee led an expedition against Seyyid Ibrahim bin Xais at Sohar in July, 1873, a party of the SI Naim had started to join H.H. at Muscat, but on reaching Semail found that H.H. had already left for Sohar. T.iey accordingly turned their steps thither, and vhile passing Saham which was then in the hands of Ibra him bin Kais, they attacked and j^limdered it, carrying off ’''hat booty was found there. No. 368 of 1873 1 n0 H.H. after having invested the fort of Sohar for some days entered into negociations with Ibrahim througn the mediation of Mohammed bin Ali, V/alad el Saif SI Nairn! which resulted in Ibrahim giving up Sohar in consideration of receiving 5000 dollars and a monthly allowance of 100 dollars to be paid under the condition of his residing in or near Heebee and not approaching further Hast.Sheikh Ilohammed bin All , ;; ]1 haimi ^ r rote to Sey^id Mohammed bin Toorkee, Governor at Sohar, demanding payment of the tribute formerly paid to the hah,,bee Chief at Bereymi. In the event of non-compliance, he threatened to raid the Batinah and attack Sohar. It ap pears that Seyyid Mohammed first wrote to Mohammed Ali on hearing that the latter intended to commit distur bances in the Batinah and demanded his intentions, ■^ohammed Ali then v, rote demanding the tribute as related. Afterward Mohammed Ali ' Tr rote a conciliatory letter to H.H. ey^id Toorkee complaining that Seyyid Mohammed had stopped his usual subsidies and presents and .denying that he intended entering the Batinan and commit depre ciations. It is believed that Mohammed Ali v^as instigated to ^rite to Seyyid Mohammed as he did by Sheikh /'aid bin Khalifah ^ho is not on terms with H.H. Seyyid Tookee. X-XX X * M * * * XyKAIII. The Naeen -ere fo.'- rmn; years the head tribe in Seer but this position T: as ac-paired by the Joasraees after the latter formed an alliance ~itn the Persian Governor of Ormus A.3.174&amp;. 3?a.s.:-oav r. 3 oo£</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000016_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/247</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000016</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/247</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/64 MUSCAT STATE AFFAIRS: NA'IM TRIBE'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-19T22:04:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (8 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 10; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of brief notes on the branch of the Na'im [Āl Na'īm] tribe based in Beraymee ['Al Buraymī, Oman]. The typewritten notes appear to have been compiled during the 1930s. They consist of excerpts from 19th century British correspondence and memoranda, covering the period 1845-1881, and are primarily concerned with the tribe's relations with the Sultan of Muscat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Na'īm (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000016#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>