<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000d0_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T02:38:31.199Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">HOME DEPARTMENT. NOTIFICATION. E stablishments. New Delhi, the 14th December 1933. No. F. 387/33. —The following Resolution by the Secretary of State for India in Council is published for general information. In exercise of the powers conferred by sub section (2) of section 96 B of the Government of India Act, the Secretary of State, with the concurrence of the majority of votes at a meet ing of the Council of India held this 14th day of November, 1933, hereby makes the following amendments in the Superior Civil Services Rules, namely; — 1. In Table A of Schedule VII to the said Rules: — (a) in Part 1, in the column relating to Bombay, for the figures '80', '70', '97', and '142', the figures '79', '69', '96', and '140' shall be substi tuted, respectively. (b) in Part 2, in the section relating to Bombay, under the heading 'Superior Posts', for the figures '26' and '80', the figures '25' and '79' shall be substituted, respectively. These amendments shall have effect fi*om the 6th November 1933. M. G. HALLETT, Secy, to the Govt, of India. No. F.-387/33-Ests. Copy forwarded to all local Governments and Administrations including the Chief Commis sioner, Andaman and Nichobar Islands; the several Departments of the Government of India; the Director, Intelligence Bureau; the Director of Public Information; the Public Ser vice Commission; the Registrar, High Court, Calcutta*; and the Auditor General, for inform ation. W. D 1 ALMEIDA, Asstt. Secy, to the Govt, of India. * By usual letter. GU'D—L401HD-20-12-33—1,784.HOME DEPARTMENT. ( NOTIFICATION. Establishments. New Delhi, the 11th January 1934. No. F.-10/34 •—The following Resolution by the Secretary of State for India in Council is published for general information:— In exercise of the powers conferred by sub-* section (2) of section 96 (B) of the Government of India Act, the Secretary of State, with the concurrence of the majority ot' votes at a meeting of the Council of India held this 5th day of December 1933, hereby makes the follow ing amendment in the Superior Civil Services Rules, namely: — In Schedule VIII to the said Rules, in the Table 'F. Indian Service of Engineers— Posts remunerated on the Time-scales plus Special Pay' to the entries under the heading 'United Provinces (Irrigation)', the following entry shall be added, namely:— Divisional Officer employed on Irrigation research work in addition to his ordinary duties . . . . Senior Rs. 250.' T. SLOAN, Joint Secy, to the Govt, of India. No. F.-10/34-Ests. Copy forwarded to all local Governments and Administrations (including the Chief Commis sioner, Andaman and Nicobar Islands, all De partments of the Government of India, the Director of Public Information, the Director, Intelligence Bureau and the Public Service Commission, for information (with reference to that Department endorsement No. E.-39, dated the 8th January 1934). { By order, W. D'ALMEIDA, Asstt. Secy, to the Govt, of India. () To Industries and Labour Department only. GIPD—479HD—26-1-34—1,750.s o r HOME DEPARTMENT. NOTIFICATION. Establishments. New Delhi, the 12th January 1934. E.-10-2/34.—The following Resolution passed by the Secretary of State for India in Council is published for general information: — In exercise of the powers conferred by sub section (2) of section 96B of the Government of India Act, the Secretary of State for India, with the concurrence of the majority of votes, at a meeting of the Council of India held this 12th day of December, 1933, hereby makes the fol lowing amendments in the Superior Civil Ser vices Rules, namely: — In Table F of Rules; — Schedule YII to the said (1) In Part 1, under the head 'United Pro vinces (Irrigation)' for the figures 43, 1, 26 and 70 the figures 39, 1, 24 and 64 shall be substituted respectively. (2) In Part 2, under the head 'United Pro vinces (Irrigation)', under the sub head 'Superior Posts'— (a) After the entry '2 Posts of Personal Assistant to Chief Engineer and Under-Secretary (6)' the following entry shall be inserted, namely:— '1 Post of Personal Assistant (Hydro- Electric) to Chief Engineer, Western Canals (6)'; (b) in the entry '34 Divisional Posts' for the figures '34' the figures '29' ■hall be substituted. T. SLOAN. Joint Secy, fo the Govt, of India. No. F.-10/2/34-Est8. Copy forwarded to all local Governments and Administrations including the Chief Commis sioner, Andaman and Nicobar Islands; the several Departments of the Government of India; the Director, Intelligence Bureau; the Director of Public Information; the Public Service Commission; the Registrar, High Court, Calcutta*; and the Auditor General, for informa- tion (w^h reference to their No. E.-61, dated the 8th January 1934). % By order, W. D 'ALMEIDA, Asstt. Secy, to the Govt, of India. * By usual letter. ( ) For I. Sc L. Department only. , f &lt;j|IPD —48lHD—2fl-l-S4 MTOC\ % FINANCE DEPARTMENT. NOTIFICATION. New Delhi, the Ist February 1934. No. P.-4 (3)-R.-I/34. —In exercise of the power conferred by sub-rule (2) of rule 33 of the Civil Services (Classification, Control and Appeal) Kules, the Governor General in Council is pleased to make the following further amend ment in the Superior Otvil Services Rules, namely: — In Appendix A to Schedule IV to the said Rules, under the heading 'B—Posts' after the entry 'Two posts of Deputy Director of Com mercial Intelligence' the following entry shall be inserted, namely; — 'The post of Chief Inspector of Lighthouses in British India (while held by Mr. John Oswald)'. This amendment shall have effect, and shall be deemed always to have had eflec -t, from the 18th January 1934. A. A. L. PARSONS, Secy, to the Govt, of India. No. F.-4 (3)-R.-I/34. Copy forwarded to all Minor Local Govern ments; to the High Commissioner for India; to the Departments of the Government of India (including the Financial Advisers, Posts and Telegraphs and Military Finance); to the Mili tary and Private Secretaries to His Excellency the Viceroy; to the Auditor-General; to the Central Board of Revenue; to the Controller and Deputy Controllers of the Currency; to the Mint Master; and to the Master, Security Printing, India. Copy also forwarded to all Accountants- General (including Comptrollers, Assam and North-West Frontier Province); the Deputy Accountant-General, Central Revenues, Cal cutta; the Director of Railway Audit; the Con troller of Railway Accounts; all Railway Audit Officers under the control of the Director of Railway Audit; the Chief Accounts Officers, East Indian Railway, Calcutta; Eastern Bengal Railway, Calcutta; Great Indian Peninsula Rail way, Bombay; North Western Railway, Lahore, and Burma Railways, Rangoon; the Director, Railway Clearing Accounts Office, Delhi; the Director of Army Audit; the Audit Officer, Indian Stores Department; and all other Audit Officers. Copy also forwarded to all provincial Govern ments for information By order, etc., G. K. S. SARMA, Offg. Asst. Secy, to the Oovt. of India. \ &lt;JIPD—L890FD—8-2-34—3,200.-^v FINANCE DEPARTMENT. NOTIFICATION. New Delhi, the 1»t February 1934. No. F.-31-I-Ex.-I/34. —In exerc'se of the powers conferred by sub-rule (2) of rule 33 of the Civil Services (Classification, Control and Appeal) Rules, the Governor General in Council is pleased so make the following further amend ment in the Superior Civil Services Eules, namely;;— In Schedule III tc the said iiules, under the heading 'Central Services' the entry relating to the Zoological Survey shall be omitted- A. A. L. PARSONS, Secy, to the Govt, of India, No. F.-31 Copy forwarded to all Minor Local Govern ments'; to the High Commissioner for India; to the Departments of the Government of India (including the Financial Advisers, Posts and Telegraphs and Military Finance); to the Mili tary and Private Secretaries to His Excellency the Viceroy; to the Auditor General; to the Central Board of Revenues; to the Controller and Deputy Controllers of the Currency; to the Mint Master; and to the Master, Security Printing, India. Copy also forwarded to all Accountants- General (including Comptrollers, Assam and North-West Frontier Province); the Deputy Accountant-General, Central Revenues, Cal cutta; the Director of Railway Audit; the Con troller of Railway Accounts; all Railway Audit Officers under the control of the Director of •I-Ex.-I/34. Railway Audit; the Chief Accounts Officers, East Indian Railway, Calcutta; Eastern Bengal Railway, Calcutta; Great Indian Peninsula Railway, Bombay; North Western Railway, Lahore and Burma Railways, Rangoon; the Director, Railway Clearing Accounts Office, Delhi; the Director of Army Audit; the Audit Officer Indian Stores Department; and all other Audit Officers. Copy also forwarded to all Provincial Govern ments for information. By order, etc., J. B. SHEARER, Under Secy, to the Oovt. of India.-J! faM-J/ Res. P. G. 32. No. ~so/ii ia 34. British Residenov and Consulate-General, Bushire, the April ]9 34. h A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to : The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty's Consul, Bunder Abbas, His Majesty's Consul, Kerrnan, His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Mohammeraji, for information and guidance ^vith roforcnce to this office ondoroomontr -Net datod the By order. for w' Secretary to the PoliticahlTesident in the Persian Gulf. Letter from the Government of India in the ^ &amp; P Department No. p. 15414)-v dated the 3rd April 19 34. S/54 1 (Received with Foreign and Political Department endorsement No. , dated the 19 .) aav QIPD—190 Poll. Res. Busbire—25.8-33—3,000.Nci. 67/23-1II. 0 &gt;1 (ft 10 I he Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Polltical AgenWS • j^anrain. V &gt;\ | and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents for infcrraaticn* British Residency and Consulate-General, HUSH I UK. Dated. id. Reference to previous correspondence hesn iptinn of Enclosure. 'Received under Foreign and Pel it ical Department endorsement NO.F.5-B/34 dated the 14th March 19S4. Name and Date. (1)Notification hy the Government of India -in the Home Department nc. ^•78-Il/32 t dated the 19t February 1934» (2)Notification hy the Government of India in the Home Department No. F.346/33,dated the 20th Fearuary 1934. (3)Notification hy the G-overnment of India in the Heme Department No. F-96/34,dated the 21st February 1934. Subject. Amendments to the Superior Oivil Services 'Rules • lc* ii N/^y v HOME DEPARTMENT. NOTIFICATION. Establishments. \ New Delhi, the 19th February 1934:. No. F.-78/11/32. —The following Piesolution by the Secretary of State for India in Council is pubiiMhed fcr general iniormation; — In exercise of the powers conferred by sub section (2) of section 96JB of thg Government of India Act, the Secretary of State with th« concuvrenca of the majority of votes at a meet ing of the Council of India held this Ibth day of January hereby makes the following amendments to the Superior Civil Services liules, namely: — In the said Eules: — (1) In Schedule III, under the heading Indian Medical Service (Civil^ for the entry relating to Inspectors-General of Civil Hospitals, the fol lowing shall be substituted, namely— Inspectors-General of Civil Hospitals, ^ United Provinces, Punjab, Burma, Biuar and Orissa, Central Provinces, Assam ana North-West .Frontier Pro vince. (2) In Schedule VII, in Part 2 of Table A, under the heading 'Central Provinces' under the sub-head 'Inferior Posts' (a) for the figure '6' against the entry 'Assistant Commissioners' the figure '5 ' shall be substituted; and (6) for the figure '4' against the entry 'Sub-Divisional Officers in Indepen dent Charge' the figure '5' shall be substituted. (3) In Schedule VIII (a) in Table A, under the heading Government of India, against the entry relating to the Commissioner, Northern India Salt Revenue, for the figures '250' the figures '200' shall be substituted. {b) In Table C, under the heading Bengal, against the entry relating to the 'Divisional Forest Officer, Darjeehng Division,'' for the figures '50' the tjgures '25' shall be substi tuted. (4) In Schedule IX in Table A, under the heading Government of India, in the entry in the column headed 'Explanations' against the entry Deputy Controller of the Currency, Bombay' for the figures '1932' the figures '1934 shall be substituted. Amendment 3 (a) shall be deemed to have had effect from the 2bth May 1933. M. G. HALLETT, Secy, to the Govt, of India. No. F.-78/II/32 -E8t8. Copy forwarded to all local Governments and the Auditor General and the Eegistrar * High Administrations, the several Departments of Court, Calcutta the Government of India, the Director, ' * _ A Intelligence Bureau, the Director of Public ^ order, Information, the Public Service Commission, -r., . T . W. D ALMEIDA, Asstt. Secy. to the Govt, of India. * By u-sual letter. GIPD—5 97HD—5-3-34—201tHOME DEPARTMENT NOTIFICATION. Establishments, New Delhi, the 20th February 1934. Schedule VII to the said No. P.-346/33. —The following Resolution by the Secretary of State for India in Council is published for general information: — In exorcise of tho powers conferred b^ sub section (2) of teciion 9613 of the Government of India Act, the Secretary of State, with the concurrence of tne majority of votes at a meet ing -jf the Council of India held this 21st day of November 1938. hereby makes the following amendments in the Superior Civil Services Rules, namely; — 1. In Table A of Rules;— I. In Part 1— (a) in the column relating to Bihar and Orissa, for the figures '63 ', '14', '54', '21', '75', and '110', the figures '01', '13', '53', '20', '73' and '107' shall be substituted respectively, • ((&gt;) in the column relating to Central Pro vinces, for the figures '45', '39', '54', and '79', the figures '44', *'S8', '*53', and '77' shall be sub stituted respectively. II. In Part 2— (a/ under the head Bihar and Orissa— (1) Under the sub-head Superior P osts (i) the entries '1 Political Agent and Commissioner, Orissa Feudatory States'' and '1 Assistant Political Agent, Orissa Feudatory States' shall be omitted; and (li) for the figures '63', the figures '61' shall be substituted. (2) Under the sub-head Inferior PoxU, J or the figures '19' and '21' the figures '18' and '20' shall be substituted respectively. (b) Tinder the head Central Provinces— (i) the entry '1 Political Agent, Cen tral Provinces Feudatory States' shall be omitted, and (ii) lor the figures '45' the figures '44' shall be substituted. 2. In Table A of Schedule VIII to the said Rules; — (i) under the head Bihar and Orissa, the entry relating to the Political Agent and Comimssioner, Orissa Feudatory States shall be omitted; and (ii) under the head Central Provinces, the entry relating to the Political Agent, Central Provinces Feudatory States shall be omitted. These amendments take effect from the 1st April 1933. M. G. HALLETT, Secy, to the Govt, of Indii. No. F.-346/33-Est9. Copy forwarded to all loca 1 Governments and Administrations (including Andaman and Nicobar Islands) [with reference to their letter No. 2877-A. R., dated the 11th July, 1933] ((with reference to their letter No. C.-1095/ 1019-III, dated the 23rd June, 1933)), to all Departments of the Government of India, the Director, Intelligence Bureau, the Director of Public Information, the Public Service Com mission, the Auditor-General, and the Registrar,* Calcutta High Court. By order, W. D'AHMEIDA, Asstt. Secy, to the Govt, of India. [ ] To B. &amp; O. only. [( )] To C. P. only. ♦ By usual letter. GIPD—603 HD—6 3 34—2000.HOME DEPARTMENT. NOTIFICATION. Establishments. New Delhi, the 2l8t February 1934. No. F.-9G/34. —The following Resolution by the Secretary of State for India in Council is published for information: — In exercise of the powers conferred by sec tion 96B(2} of the Government of India Act, the Secretary of State, with the concurrence of the majority of vote'* at a meeting of the Coun cil of India held this 16th day of January 1934, hereby makes the following amendment in the Superior Civil Services Rules, namely:— In Schedule IX to the said Rules, under the heading Provincial Governments, in column 2 of the entry relating to Deputy Inspectors Gen eral of Police including Commissioner of Police, Madras, the following words within brackets shall be omitted, namely:— (Plus Rs. 150 special pay to Deputy Inspector General, Crime and Railways, Central Pro vinces, for acting as Inspecting and Advisory Officer for the Police in the Hyderabad Adminis tered Areas.) M. G. HALLETT, Secy, to the Govt, of India. No. F.-96/34-Ests. A copy is forwarded to all local Governments and Minor Administrations, including the Chief Commissioner, Andaman and Nicobar Islands, all Departments of the Government of India, the Director, Intelligence Bureau, the Director of Public Information, the Public Service Com mission, and the Registrar,* High Court, Calcutta. By order, C. F. V. WILLIAMS, Under Secy, to the Govt, of India. * By usual letter. GIPD—616HD—28-2 34—2015No. ftX - 67/23-in. I he Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to . - The Political A^eat, Banrain and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the nndermentioned document^ for information. British Residency and Consulate-General, HUSH IRK. Dated h2V. 934, Reference to'previous correspondence: hescription of Enclosure Name and Date. xieceived under Foreign &amp; Politioal ifepartment endorse ment No* ^.5-2/54, dated the ^th March 1934 c (1 Notification by the G-overnment of India in the finance Department No.5 , .4(64)-Rl/33,dated the 25th January 1934. (2)Notification t)y the Government of India in the Home itepartment Mo.y. 10/4/34 f dated the 14th February 1934# Subject. Amendments to the Superior Civil Services Rmles. Le* ^ n ku ur FINANCE DEPAETMENT, NOTIFICATION. New Delhi, the No. F.-4 (64)-R. 1/33.—In exercise of the powers conferred by Regulation 15 in Schedule IV to the Superior Civil Services Kules, the Governor General in Council is pleased to direct that the following shall be substituted for Eegulation (3) in Part I of the Supplement ary Regulations published in the Finance De partment Notification No. F.-35-C. S. B../26, dated the 6th February 1925: — 05th January 1934. '(8) When the officer engages the passage or passages he will present the certificate to the steamship company and if the cost of any passage engaged by him exceeds the amount entered in the certificate, the difference must be paid by the officer himself.' A. A. L. PAESONS, Secy, to the Govt, of India. No. F. 4 (64)-R. 1/83. Copv forwarded to all Provincial and Minor Local Governments; to the High Commissioner for India; to the Departments of the Govern ment of India (including the Financial Adviser, Posts and Telegraphs and Military Finance); to the Military and Private Secretaries to His Excellency the Viceroy; to the Auditor-General; to the Central Board of Revenue; to the Controller and Deputy Controllers of the • J Tl *■ J w&gt; 4- /-v T' r* /■&gt; Railway Accounts; all Railway Audit Officers under the control of the Director of Railway Audit; the Chief Accounts Officers, East Indian Railway, Calcutta; Eastern Bengal Railway, Calcutta; Great Indian Peninsula Railway, Bombay; North Western Railway, Lahore and Burma Railways, Rangoon; the Director, Rail way Clearing Accounts Office, Delhi; the Director of Army Audit; the Audit Officer, Indian Stores Department; and all other Audit Officers.HOME DEPARTMENT. NOTIFICATION. E stablishments. New Delhi, the 14th February 1934. No. F. 10/4/34. —The following Eesolution by the Secretary of State for India in Council is published for general information:— In exercise of the powers conferred by sub section (2) of Section 96-B of the Government of India Act, the Secretary of State, with the concurrence of the majority of votep at a meet ing of the Council of India held this 9th day of January 1934, hereby makes the following amend: ment in the Superior Civil Services Eules, namely:— In Part 2 of Table A of Schedule VII to the said Kules, in the entries relating to the Government of India, under the sub-head 'Inferior Posts', for the figures '2' and '10' the figures '3' and '11' shall be substituted respec tively. M. G. HALLETT, Secy, to the Govt, of India. No. F.-10/4/34 -Est8. A copy is forwarded to all local Governments and Minor Administrations, including the Chief Commissioner, Andaman and Nicobar Islands, all Departments of the Government of India, the Director, Intelligence Bureau, the Director of Public Information, the Public Service Com mission, and the Registrar*^ High Court, Calcutta. By Order, W. D'ALMEIDA, Asstt. Secy, to the Govt, of India. * By usual letter. QIPD—585HI&gt;—19-2-34—1,968.HOME DEPARTMENT. NOTIFICATION. E stablishments. New Delhi, the 14th March 1934. No. F. 508/33 •—The following Resolution by the Secretary of State for India in Council is published for general information; — In exercise of the powers conferred by sub section (2) of section 96-B of the Government of India Act, the Secretary of State, with the concurrence of the majority of votes at a meet ing of the Council of India held this 20th day of February 1934, hereby makes the following amendment in the Superior Civil Services Rules, namely:— In Table A of Schedule VIII to the said Rules to the entries in the section relating to the United Provinces, the following entry shall be added, namely;— 'Assistant Commissioner, Junior 100' Naini Tal. This amendment shall be deemed to have had effect from the 1st November 1933. M. G. HALLETT, Secy, to the Govt, of India. No. F. 508/33-Ests. A copy is forwarded to all local Governments and Minor Administrations, including the Chief Commissioner, Andaman and Nicobar Islands, all Departments of the Government of India! the Director, Intelligence Bureau, the Director of Public Information, the Public Service Com mission, and the Registrar*, High Court Calcutta. By order. W. D'ALMEIDA, Asstt. Secy, to the Govt, of India. * By usual letter. QIPD—890HD—27-3-34—2000Rea. P, G. 32. No. of 19 Resid//c/^( 34. British Residency'and Consulate-General, Bushire, the April 19 34. A oopy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain, ^ His Majesty's Consul, Bunder Abbas, His Mnjesty's Connnl, Korman, Hie Majooty'a Vice-Consul, Mohammc'rah, for information and guidance .^vith reference to-^his-o^ee -endorsemeii^- , datf^d the 40- By order. Secretary to th^-iMljtical Resident in the Persian Gulf. Letter from the.Government of India in the xicme Department ,35 r No. dated the 27 th -P'ebrua^ r 19 (Received with Foreign and Political Department endorsement No. • 9 dated the ^ q . i ch. jg : v^- 1 GIPD—190 Poll. R cb . Bauhire—25-8-33—3,000.)Qr HOME DEPARTMENT. NOTIFICATION. Establishments. 'New Delhi, the 27th February 1934. No- F.-10/10/33.—The following Eesolution by the Secretary of State for India in Council is published for general information:— In exercise of the powers conferred by sub section (2) of section 96B of the Government of India Act, the Secretary of State, with the con currence of the majority of votes at a meeting of the Council of India held this 16th day of January, 1934, hereby makes the following amendment to the Superior Civil Services Kules, namely:— (1) In Schedule VII to the said Kules, in Table H relating to the Political De partment— (i) In Part 1— (a) for the figures '70' against 'Num ber of Superior posts', the figures '76' shall be substituted, (b) for the figures '37' against 'Num ber of Inferior posts', the figures '36' shall be substituted, (c) for the figures '107' the figures '112' shall be substituted, (d) for the figures '105' against 'Total number of posts to be filled by officers of the Political Depart ment', the figures '110' shall be be substituted, (e) for the figures '16 against 'De putation reserve' the figures '14' shall be substituted, (/) for the figures '11' against 'Train ing reserve' the figure '9' shall substituted, and (g) for the figures '169' against 'Total strength of the Department' the figures '170' shall be substitu ted. (ii) In Part 2— (a) For the head 'Baroda Kesidency' and the entries relating thereto the following head and entries shall be substituted, namely, 'Gujarat States Agency and Baroda Eesidency. Superior posts—1 Agent to the Gov ernor General and Resident. 1 Secretary.' (b) After the entry relating to 'Kash- gar the following heads and en tries shall be inserted, namely:— 'Eastern States Agency. Superior posts—1 Agent to the Gov ernor General. 1 Secretary. 1 Secretary and Poli tical Agent-' Deccan States Agency and Kolha- pur Residency. Superior posts—1 Agent to the Gov ernor General and Resident. 1 Secretary.' (2) In Schedule VIII to the said Rules* in Table H relating to the Political Department under the head '(6) Ex-cadre Appointments', after the entry relating to the 'North-West Frontier Province' the following shall be inserted, namelv:— 'Aden. Civil Secretary to the Chief Commis sioner, Aden and District Magis trate. 100', (3) In Schedule IX to the said Rules, in Table H relating to the Political D'e- partment— (a) For the head 'Baroda' and the entry thereunder, the following shall be sub stituted, namely:— 'Gujarat States Agency and Baroda Residency. Agent to the Governor General and Resident ... 3,000 13.6.S'' (b) After the entry relating to 'Nepal' the following shall be inserted, namely:— 'Eastern States Agency. Agent to the Governor- General ... 3,000 13.6.8' 'Deccan States Agency. Agent to the Governor- General and Resi dent ... 3,000 13.0.8'' Amendments (1) and (3) shall be deemed to have had effect from 1st April 1933 and amend ment (2) from 19th April 1933. M. G. HALLETT. Secy, to the Govt, of India. No. F.-lO/lO/SS-Ests. A copy is forwarded to all local Governments and Minor Administrations, including the Chief Commissioner, Andaman and Nicobar Islands, all Departments of the Government of India, the Director, Intelligence Bureau, the Director of Public Information, the Public Service Com mission, Calcutta. and the Registrar*, High Court, By order. W. D'ALMEIDA, Asstt. Secy, to the Govt, of India. 5 ! S • By usual letter. HIPD—L63 4HD -13 3.34-2 .015n fw* Res. F. 6. 32. No . no of 19 3 4. 67/33 British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 2^ Apr 11 19 34. A oopy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to :— The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty's Consul, Bunder Abbas, His Majesty's Consul, Kerman, His Majesty's Vice-Consul, MohammcraJi, -9 MAY 1934 * J for information and guidance • ^ith roforonoo to thio office cndorsfcmcnt ivo, ; dated the — . By order. Tor Secretary to the Poliucal Resident in the Persian Gulf. Letter from the Government of India in the Heme No?' 13 ?/ 34 - , dated the24th March 1934. . Jists • Department (Received with Foreign and Political Department endorsement No^iii|irS , dated the 9 to April 1954. .) (iaD GIPD—190 Poll. Rei. Boshire—25-8-33—3,000.IsO 135/o4-J3s ts. Go ve rDine n t ot India, Home Department. New Delhi, the 24th rarch 1934, k&gt;ubjc ct: -DiscontirjUcinoe 01 transfers 01 Gove r^^ent % servants without travelllrj^ allova-jce and/or pay during Joining time as a punitive measure in consecju-rjcc oi mis■ conduct. ihe undersigned is directed to say thai; the Govern- mc no of Indiu. have decideo. that in view of the promulga tion of the Givii 3ervices (Giassilicatio:.-. Co'trcl and appeal) Eules and the Hules made thereunder m record to discipline and conduct, the former pr^ccice of transferring a Government servant without travelling alienage..- and/or pay during Joining time, as a punitive measur? in conseq/u-nce of his own misconduct, should 'be discontinued; l^e.. transfers should, in future, u? made o l^ior the puhlic convenience or at the request of a Gover nment servant. The Government oi India consider that cases of misconduct can now be adequately dealt v/itn oy imposing one or more of the appropriate penalties prescribed in Glassific^tion Rule 49 or rule 5 of the Eules published in the Home D parr^ent Notifica tion ro.Ir. 9-i9/30-j;sts. , dated the 27 th Tebruary, 1932, as the case may be. The n cessary amendments to oupplemen tary Eule 114 and Note 2 under lundamental EuL: 107 hav already been issued separately by the finance Dcnnar tment. 3d/- G.I . Trivedi, Deputy Secretary to uhc Government of I.di^. . - n ■ • - - /v &gt;&gt;? rue ^opy. &lt;:nnd x-oli-.ical D-part^ nt. e/jj# Supe^TTTe nde nt, L^bue Bran ioreign and Political iMpartment•Frcm To He15(14)-^/34. The Addl.iteputy Secretary tc the Govt of Xndia in the Jtereign and Pclltioal Department. The Hcn'ble the Politioal aestdent in the Persian Gruli zxxxxxxzz iiated jtfew x^ihi, the 3rd April 1934. yiXATION 0? NOT SOALUS OF PAYS FOB THE FUTUHB ENTRANTS. Sir, I am directed tc refer-- memoranduia lfc.197 5 dated the 24th September 1932, and tc say that the Grcverncr - G-eneral in (Jcuncil has heen pleased tc sanction the continuance of the existing rates of pay to future entrants to Grovemment service in the various posts of subordinate and menial estaolislaaent in t he Persian u-ulf t xxxxxxxxx. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, sd. V.^arahari xtao, Addl.Deputy Secretary tc the Govt of India.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000d0_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1473</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000d0</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1473</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 15/30 The Superior Civil Service Rules Amendments re:-’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-22T00:15:03</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (22 folios)</extent><extent>File papers are arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>There is one complete foliation sequence from the first folio of writing until the last folio of writing. This sequence is in pencil on the top right corner of each folio with some entries written in brackets and others not.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains the following Government of India printed documents, which were circulated by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the Political Agent Bahrain and others, for information and guidance:Home Department Establishment Notifications, 1933-1934, containing the text of minor amendments to the Superior Civil Service Rules, mainly updates to the number and type of posts in various government services;Finance Department Notifications, 1934, containing the text of minor amendments to the Superior Civil Service Rules, about travelling expenses claims and the number and type of posts in various government services.The file also contains the following Government of India memoranda, circulated for information and guidance:Memorandum dated 1934 from the Foreign and Political Department to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, confirming the continuance of existing rates of pay for future entrants to clerical and domestic posts in the offices of the British Residency and Agencies in the Persian Gulf;Memorandum dated 1934, from the Home Department to the Foreign and Political Department, regarding the discontinuance of the practice of punishing the misconduct of an officer by transferring him without travelling allowance or pay, under the Civil Services (Classification, Control and Appeal) Rules governing discipline and conduct;Memorandum dated 1933-1934 from the Railway Board, containing the text of a minor amendment to the application of the Superior Civil Service Rules to post holders in the Railway Department.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000d0#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>