<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000083_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-13T09:59:30.694Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">go, 1 of 1^34, Political Agtncy d Conaulat« 9 kuacat• gewo for the perioa from 1st to 15th January 1934* X. The British hgent f (iwadur f reports that the French Air Uner «iswny« en route to France with the Governor of Indo-China ana 6 passengors on hoard arrived at awadur on the 6th January* The Juiner whilst lanuln&amp; ourst one ox itt; tyres and damaged the undercarriage• The N*Qveraor t with mails t proceeded on the 8th by the relief machine ’^ambu 71 and after being repairta the ‘Vasamy' left on the 10 th* 2, iui 'Iraqi tourist naxaed hafa&amp;t Halmi bin daji ikhsihim arrived from Bahrain on the 6th January and leit for h&amp;rachi on the 14th instant* He gave out that he was touting the world* *e is paying his way by begging ana selling cards* The wtffittircajm anu minimum temperatui'es registered at Jait-al-FalaJ during the period under report are*- lieelc ending 7th maximum on 7th 78*1 H « w on 6th 50*9 it * 14th maximum on 9th 86.S ' ** minimum on 8th 55*8 4* The price of dollars is Bs 85/- per 100 dollars# Major, Political Agent «* H#B#M's consul, muscat# PlstJibutltn as usual*CQMFIDKNTIAL. No.3 of 1934. Political Agency &lt;3c H.B.M'b Consulate, Muscat. News for the period from 16th to 28th February 1934. BRITISH INTEHB3TS. 11. Reference paragraph 6 of diary no 0 2 of 1934. Major C.B.U.Bremner, k.C., Political Agent,Muscat, with ^arty returned in H.k.S. H Bideford M on the 19th February. Except for a regrettable outbreak of scarlet fever amongst the Muscat^ labour personnel on board, which involved one death, the reconnaissance passed off without incident. 12 0 The Agency flag was flown at half mast on the day of the funeral of the late Ring Albert of Belgium. MOVEMENTS OF H.M.SHIPS. 13. H.M.S. ,, Fowey M arrived on the 23rd February and left on 24th February. After saluting the State, the usual calls were exchanged. % MOCAL INTERESTS. 14. Reference paragraph 8 of diary No.2 of 1934. Saiyid Malik, uncle of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat with some of the Sultan f s followers arrived on the 22nd February. 16* Subedar Major Fateh Khan, Officiating Commandant of the Muscat Infantry left on 24th February for India on leave preparatory to retirement after 13 years service in Muscat State. At an inspection prior to his departure, the Subedar Major was presented by His Highness the Sultan with his Commemoration Medal. METEOROLOGICAL. 16. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaj during the period under report are:- Week ending 22nd Maximum on 20th 93.7 w mm minimum on 18th 68.0 M ' 28th maximum on 23rd 89.9 w ' minimum on 24th 59.0COMFIDiilNTIAli« NOo 4 of 1934# Political Agency &lt;$c s Consulate,Muscat. Nwws for the period from 1st to 16th March 1934. BH1TI3B INTi£R^3T3. 18. Mr. V.A.L.Mallet, Counsellor of the Legation at Tehran arrived in H.M.S. i, 3horeham H as a guest of the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, on the 2nd March and left the same night. 19. Group Captain Saul arrived by flying boat from India on 10th March and left for Bahrain on the 12th March. 20. The Cable Ship w Lady Denison Pender” arrived on the 10th March raci: to extend the present cable to enable the removal of the Imperial and International Communications Company to their new offices. She sailed the same day. MQVhMLNTS OF K.M.SHIPS. 21. Captain J.V.Creagh, D.S.O., Commanding H.M.S.’’Shore- ham” arrived on the 10th March and after exchanging usual calls left on the same night. AVIATION. 22. Two flying boats visited Muscat during the period under reporto LOCAL INTLRLSTS. 23. Reference paragraph 14 of diary No.3 of 1934. The balance of His Highness the Sultan's 46 followers which were still due from Dhofar arrived on the 2nd March. FOREIGN INTKtkiSTS. 24. Monsieur Y.Okada, a Japanese merchant arrived from Bombay on the 14th March. He is busy in gathering all possi ble trade information concerning piece goods and is due to proceed on the same mission to all Persian Gulf ports of note METEOROLOGICAL. 26. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait al-Falaj during the period under report are*-COBFIDEFTIAX Ho* 5 of 1934. Political Agency &amp; Consulfcto, Muscat* Hows for tho poriod from 16th to 31st March 1934. BRITISH IHT3RESTS. 27* Tho British ^ont at Gwadur roports that tho Hon'blo Liout-Colonol T.C.Powlo, Political Rosidont in tho Porsian Gulf, Bushiro, accompaniod by Mrs* Fowls, arrivod thoro by tho oast-bound air mail on tho 16th March on routs How Bolhi. On thoir roturn from Delhi thoy again passod through Gwadur on tho 22nd March* AMERICA# IHTERESTS. 28. His Excolloncy Mr. Paul Knabonshuo, Ministar Plonipotontiary and Envoy on Spocial Mission, accomp^niod by his son and Socrotary (Mr* Jamos S. Mooso) arrivod at Muscat on 18th March* Tho objoct of Mr. KnLibcnshuo’s visit was to convoy tho folicitations of tho President of tho United States of America to His Highness tho Sultan on tho occasion of tho centenary of tho Treaty of Friendship and Commerce between tho United States of America and Muscat* Opportunity was taken of tho Minister’s visit to open officially tho American Mission Hospital at Matrah* Though considerable stress was laid on tho fact that tho hospital had boon built for tho public, was tho property of tho public, and for tho benefit of tho public, no mention was made of tho foes charged to tho public* Tho humour of this somewhat appealed to 'the public” j 'i. present, who meanwhile flock to the Agency hospital for fref &gt; treatment* His Excolloncy s nd party departed on 21st March. LOC;X IHTEREoTS. 29. His Highness tho 3ultan of Muscat snd Oman loft for Sur by tho 8.S.”Barpeta' on the 30th March* Tho boat was specially diverted to that port for the occasion.SECH&amp;T No* i Of ly34. Political Agency &amp; H* B* M's Consulate, Muscat* April Intelligence Summary for the period from 1st to 15th May '34* 0 O 0 ROYAL NAVY. 1. H. M. S# ”Ormonde n arrived on the 4th April and after coaling left on the 6th April. ROYAL AIR FORCE* 2* During the fortnight under report four land machines and two flying boats visited Muscat* LOCAL INTERESTS * 3* Reference paragraph 29 of diary No.5 of 1934. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman returned from Bur by o. 3* 'Bankura' on the 11th April. METEOROLOGICAL. 4. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait al Falaj during the period under report ares- Week ending 7th April maximum on 5th 106.5 t» n it it minimum on let 69.0 It w 14th ' maximum on 8th 98.8 It N It It minimum on 14th 65.8 MISCELLANEOUS. 5. The price of dollars is Rs 87/- per 100 dollars. Major, Political Agent &lt;&amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. Usual DistributionSECRET No. 2 of 1934. Political Agency &amp; H. B. M's Consul ate, Muse at. Intelligence Summary for the period from 16th to 30th April 1934. ---oOg BRITISH INTERESTS. 6. Major C.E.U.Bramner, M.C., Political Agent and H.B.M f s Consul, Muscat, left for Gwadur on tour on the 17th April in R.A.F.flying boat. ROYAL NAVY. 7. H.M.S. w Bideford rt arrived at Muscat on 28th April when the Commanding Officer, Captain Brown, called on His Highness the Sultan saset on assuming command. H.M.3. H Bideford M sailed on 30th April. LOCAL 1NTLRBSTS. 8. Through the efforts of H.M*s Government certain nations in Treaty alliance with the Government of His High ness the Sultan of Muscat have, together with H.M f s Govern ment, accorded their assent recently to an increase in the Customs Tariff from 5% to 10%. Without any prior warning, and without the courtesy of intimating the Political Agent of his intention, the Sultan has issued orders, dated 30th April, bringing into effect from the 29th April, and increase on import duties up to 10% on the following commodities*- Carpets of all kinds. Musical instruments and accessories. Matches. Watches and accessories Liquors of all kinds. Perfumery. Silks and artificii}. silks Cigarettes and manufactured tobacco Toys of all kinds. Vegetable ghee Opium and drugs. The local trading community, British and otherwise, are very justly incensed at this entire lack of consideration-2- by the State, which they attribute with considerable dagree of correctness, to the interested activities of the Direc tor of Customs, one K.S#bulichand* METEOROLOGICAL. 9. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at hait al Falaj during the period under report are*- Week ending 21st April maximum on 18th 102.1 n *» w » minimum on 19th 70 • 3 n * 30th M maximum on 30th 106.4 « « m * minimum on 25th 68.9 HISCELLASTDOUS. 10. The price of dollars is Rs 90/- per 100 dollars. 5 A XT Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M*s Consul,Muscat. Usual DistributionSECRET« No* 3 of 1934* Political Agency dc Consulate, Muscat* Intelligence Sunsaary for the period from 1st to 16th May r 34. BRITISH INTEREST&gt; 11• Reference paragraph 6 of Intelligence Summary NOo2 of 1934* Major C.E.U.Bremner, M.C., Political Agent and Consul, Muscat, returned from tour to Grwadur on the 8th May, having visited Karachi in the interim. SHIPPING. 12. S.S. w Litiopa M arrived here on 1st May to seek medical aid for a man suffering from dysentery. This was granted by the Agency Medical Officer on the ship f s arrival* The ship left on the same evening* 13. L.T. f, Nearchus M arrived from Basrah on the 10th May and after repairing the Agency flagstaff left on the 11th May* METEOROLOGICAL. 14. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait al-Falaj during the period under report are*- l J 0 ■* C 1 Week ending 7th May maximum on 4th l ^ 104.3 *r. ; w « h n minimum on 6th 78.7 Ul- ! n » 14th ' maximum on nth 106.8 w t» n n minimum on 13th 75.0 MISCELLANEOUS. 15. The price of dollars is ^ 39/- per 100 dollars. d Major, s Consul,Muscat* Usual distribution*jjsoeu'tf *lo Z .oz t ^^AXuanoD s'M.H.K jb ^©nd^A Isoixiloq .££’ rfXdl aJ- J-al aoil iboircsq srt^ *iol ^xsisnaja soxis^XIIs.tnl ♦ T^aji^iTKI HcilTIHa ytBjmuc* 9D^$iIl9XnI lo 8 liqist^iaq; 9f&gt;aa‘i9leE .XI .&gt;021 lo S.oK cto?£A XisoiJ-XIo'-I , «0.M t r i3xi*ii0ia. T J•£.0 'ic ^bM 9 ur ,io 'iij-QBWi; oJ tljo^ ao*rl iDsxx'ix/Xai t XiJ3iioO e’ -.a.K .fixiu^nl oxlj nl iiloxsiaX ba^Xaxv gniv.ori ,^g!l riX8 Sal xxo B‘i9rf ixovi'rua H j8qoJtJ k XJ[ M .cl.8 .51 &amp; 3 W alrfT .^ # I9 J*ii93v 6 ino c il gnl'isTiun nr.n r, to! hlis Ij30xb©m a ’ qXrfa orfj- no nsoXHO XnoxJ:-9M vone^A snj- x&lt;S oojxibi^ • 5 rtX X3V9 anme odS no ^lol qlria orfT dSOI 9dS no ilsnu.sS nonl ftovi-rra 11 8x/ifonnsK M .T.J .01 exir no vtlol lls^a^sll ^oxaaA axit ^ninlBqon neJ-xB nrus -^b4 banoJ’ai^sn aennJ’Bneqmi’ nu/mxnlm bn*^ mniiilxaa dnT . M .tnoqoT: nabnu boi^isq srij ^nr‘iub ^sIjs'i-Xb j'lsS cfn 0 ♦ X;I xfJ’^ no nxwaixjftffl xU'V yiibflp alssW V.8V rlJO no f«£rmlnXiH ^ * M 8.301 rtSLl no i^mlXjMK M rfj&gt;I H H 0.3V ff«t0I no iimsJtnim H ^ *• . oUOSHAJJaO GIM . final!oB 001 neq -\^8 ^ al enBllob lo solnq srCT .31 c nok*k .^BoanM e Ix/anoO a ’ i.a.h J’nogA ijsoxqxXo^ .noiJ-ncUnJ'sXb IjajjeUS£CK£T. Ho*4 of 1934* Political Agency &amp; His Britannic Majesty's Consulate, Muscat* Intelligence nummary for the period from 16th to 31st May 1934. k ■■ *1 BHITI3H 1HTHRH3T3. 16. The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel T.C.Fowle, C.B.L., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, accompanied by his Under Secretary and Confidential Assistant, Captain A. C. Galloway and Mr. J.droning, respectively, arrived here on an official visit on the 16th May and left by H. U. s. w Bideford w on the 21st May. 17. His Excellency the Viceroy accompanied by Lady Willingdon and two a.B.Cs., Captains Beattie and Freeman- Thomas arrived at Gwadur by the Imperial Airways Liner 'Helena” at noon of the 16th May 1934. Under the orders of the Political Agent special tents had been erected for Their excellencies accommodation during their short halt and every precaution taken for their safety* The landing ground was unostentatiously picketed by His highness*s Arab askaris whilst a picked body of 12 Agha khan Boy Scouts were deputed to mount guard on Their Excellencies' tents. Their Excellencies were received by the British Agent and the Wali of Gwadur; the latter presenting the Viceroy with a letter from His Highness the Bultan. Their Excellencies left for Bhargah at 12.52 p.m. the same day. mtiLim- 18. H.M.S.'Bideford' arrived at Muscat on the 16th May and left for sea on the 21st May. LOCAL IHTEHEST5. 19. His Highness the dultan of Muscat left on a tour of inspection of the Batineh Coast on the 26th May but owing to ill health had to return to Muscat on the 31st », ay-2- Highness has since deputed his uncle baiyid ^amad to proceed in his stead, with orders as to the method of assessing and collecting zakat* MaTBOROLQGICAL * 20. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaj during the period under report arei- Week ending 21st May maximum on 16th 110.4 w *» n it minimum 6n 17th 33.1 « « 31st M maximum on to s 106.1 It H ft ft minimum 6n to 00 76.9 MISCELLANB0U3. Rs 21. The price of dollars is/93/- per 100 dollars. Major, Political agent &lt;sc H.B.M's Consul, Muse at. ASN. d. Usual distributionSECRET &gt; No# 6 of 1934. Political Agency &amp; His Britannic Majesty’s Consulate, Muscat. Intelligence Summary for the period from 16th to 30th ^une ’34. BRITISH INTERESTS. 26. * On the 4th June, the anniversary of His Majesty the King-Emperor, the Agency flagstaff was dressed, tinder a Guard of Honour from the Muscat Infantry. His Highness the Sultan’s battery fired a Royal Salute of 31 guns on the hoisting of the Colours. An official reception was held at the Agency, which was graced by the members of the Ruling Pamily in the absence of His Highness the Sultan who unfortunately had been indis posed for several days. The leaders of the British Community, together with all local notables, attended to offer their felicitations on the happy occasion. (It is regretted that owing to a clerical error this paragraph was omitted from the proceeding Intelligence Summary) • 27. Major D.L.Mackay, I.M.D., agency Medical Officer, left on 3 months recess on the 16th June. ROYAL AIR FORCE. 28. Reference paragraph 22 of Intelligence Summary No.6 of 1934. Captain R. Wilson, R.E., returned to Basrah on the 19th June. FOREIGN INTERESTS. 29. S.S. H Nankwa Maru”, with a general cargo of cement and rice, arrived from Cochin on 19th instant. She landed some 4,000 bags of cement of a brand considerably superior to any Japanese cement yet seen in the Muscat market. 30. Monsieur Georges Cassin, French Vice-Consul at Bushire, landed for an hour from the up mail on the 19th instant. He called informally at this Agency but made no mention of the,object of his visit, which is-2- reported to be the delivery of an important despatch to His Highness the Jultan, on whom he did not however call* LOCAL IfirTICK&amp;STS * 31. aheikh Mohammad bin Isa bin aalih el Harithi, arrived in Muscat on 19th instant. He was deputed by his father, the lieutenant of the Imam of Uuan, to visit H. H. the bultan in an endeavour to settle certain cases between Muscat and Omani subjects. During his stay in L^uscat he was the guest of His Highness and prior to departing on the 28th instant he called at the Agency. His visit forms the subject of a separate report. 32. A Sub-Assistant Surgeon of the name of ^angha Ham arrived from Bombay on 27th June for service under the Muscat Government. e is said to be already appalled by local conditions in so far as they concern himself. Tin usually severe climatic conditions prevailing this year have no doubt added to his horrors. His services are said to have been enlisted by the Director of Hevenues. ^T^OHGGICAL. 33. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-falaj during the period under report are*- Week ending 22nd June maximum on 17th 112.3 '* ' minimum on 15th 84*6 30th M maximum on 24th 104.7 ' * M minimum on 30th 87.0 LIjCHLLANHQUH. 34. The price of dollars is Rs 98/- per 100 dollars. GnHHHAli * 35. The prevailing climatic conditions are locally regarded as being of exceptional severity. Muscat and Latrah have been evacuated by ail, rich and poor alike, who are not compelled Dy circumstances to remain. Both towns resemble cities of the dead. The Political Agent and the 2 H.^.F.Wireless operators are the sole remaining white men in Muscat^—3- whilst His highness the Sultan merely awaits the hurried completion of his camp to proceed to Kantao. The Agency hospital is daily crowded with a multitude afflicted with boils, blains and sores directly attributabl to the abnormal conditions. Several cases of heat stroke amongst local inhabitants are reported, and an Hindu in patient had an attack of this complaint whilst lying in hospital. (. ' jiia j or, Political r*gent oc H.B.M’s Consul,Muscat* 1. His Majesty’s Secretary of ktate for J-ndia* 2. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India* 3. The Senior General Officer, M.0.3.,Army Headquarters 4. His Majesty’s Ambassador, Baghdad. 5. His Majesty’s Minister, Jedda. 6. The Chief Vomraissloner, Aden. 7. The Staff Officer, Naval Intelligence Centre,Colombo. 8. The Senior Naval Officer,Persian Gulf, division. 9. The Air Officer Commanding, ’Iraq Command, Baghdad. 10. The Officer Commanding 203(F.B.)Squadron, E.a.F.B asrah. 11. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 12. The Political ^gent, Bahrain. 13. The Political «.gent, Kuwait*Secret Bo. 10 of 1934. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate^Muscat. Camp Office, Karachi, 3rd October 1934. Intelligence summary for the period from 16th to 31st August 1934. 6666666666666666 Royal Bay;/. 65• H.M.Ships 'Po^ey' and ”Lupin w arrived at Muscat on the 22nd August, the former left on tne same day and the latter on the 23rd August. The Commander of H.M.S. •‘Lupin' paid an official call to His Highness the Sultan ^hich w as returned on the same day. 55. H.M.S. 'Lupin' returned to Muscat w ith three cases of smallpox for isolation on the Haramil Isolation Camp. The threo Somali ratings are progressing satisfactorily. Local Interests. ^* li is reported that 500 tins of kerosene liave been imported from Karachi marked 'The Mills Store Co.Karachi Lahore ihebe tins w ere consigned by Vallabdas Ctmarsi of Karachi to a local merchant named ITarainji Hirji. The Anglo-Persian Oil Co. at Abadan are rather perturbed and are investigating the matter through their Agents here. Meteorological. 58 * maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait al Falaj during the period under report:- w eek ending 21st August maximum on 19th 101.6 •T ' ' ' minimum on 17 th 82.0 ' 51st ' maximum on 24 th 101.2 * * ' minimum on 31st 79,5 Miscellaneous. 59 • The of dollars is Rs.98/- per 100 dollars. Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. Distribution os usual VSecret, Ho. 11 of 1934. Political Agency &amp; Consulate, Camp Office, Oc.U( */oX 1934. rn-au-- liitttlli^ence summary for the period from 1st to 15th September 1934. Royal Air Force. 60. The British Agent G w adur reports three flying boats of the Royal Air Force Basrah passed through O w adur en route Australia on the 6th September. Local Interests. 61. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman left for Sohar on the 4th September by the slo w mail steamer to settle some pending cases. 62. On the night of the 15th September at about 8 P#M. four prisoners incarcerated in the Matrah prison managed to take possession of 3 rifles ^na 72 rounds of ammunition belonging to the police and escaped leaving the policeman on duty bound. One of the escaped prisoners immediately reported the matter to Saiyid Hamad, the M ali of Matrah. The M ali took prompt action in sending policemen in search of the prisoners w ho w ere arrested on the 3rd day on their :// ay to Sib. The prisoners are no w locked up in the Muscat prison. Meteorological. 63. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait al Falaj during the period under report are;- '“'eek ending 7th Septemoer maximum on 2nd 103. » H H ' ' 14th « H It S Miscellaneous. The price of dollars minimum on 1st 79,9 H maximum on 10th 105.7 M minimum on 9 th 72.6 is Rs.97/- per 100 dollars. d Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul, Major, Muscat.SSCH&amp;T Noo 12 ef 1934. Political Agency &amp; Consulate, Muscat. Intelligence Summary for the period from 16th to 30th September 1934* BHt i Kai i IliTg.BS3£§&gt; 66. Reference paragraph 27 ef diary No.6 of 1934. Major D.L.Mackay, Agency Medical Officer returned from recess on the 19th instant. LOCAL 66. Reference paragraph 61 of diary No.11 of 1934. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman returned from 3ohar on the 21st September. 67. H.M•S. ,, Bideford ,, arrived here on the 26th instant. The usual calls were exchanged between the Sultan and the Commander of the sloop. 68. Reference paragraph 66 of diary No.10 ef 1934. The three Somali ratings who were said to have been suffering from smallpox left Muscat for Henjam to re-join their ship, H.M.S.'Lupin', on the 26th instant. METEOROLOGICAL. 69. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-FalaJ during the period under report were*- Week ending 21st Sept, maximum on 16th 101.9 ' ' ' ' minimum on 19th 77.2 ' ' 30th ' maximum on 27th 104.1 ' ' ' ' minimum on 26th 71.8 MTaCai.I^NROlIS. 70. The price of dollars is fe 98 per 100 dollars. Usual distributionS'-SCKKT. Ho.13 of 1934. Political Agency S Consulate, Muscat. Intelligence Summary for the period from let to 15th Oct. BRITISH IKTaRaSfii. 71. Nothing of importance. WCM IKT:?K3STS. 72. Ho thing of importance. HOYAI HAVY. 73# Reference paragraph 67 of diary Mo. 12 of 1934, H. M .3.^Bideford* left Muscat on the let instant, R0YA1, AIR FORCE. Ms Royal Air S'orce aeroplanes called at Muscat during the period under report. jCgT^OROLOaiCAI^ 7c. rhe maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait al.Malaj during the period under report were:- * '^eeis: ending 7th October maximum on 4th 102.8 * minimum on let 71.3 14th • maximum on 14th 98.9 1$ Mu n minimum on 8 67.0 Mia cel1an eo hk. 76, The P rice of is ^ 99 p*r 100 dollars. SR - C. ..IT. dreamer, Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.-i'e con* 1, Kuacat. Dietrioution as usual,ggCHBT. Ho.14 of 1954* political Agency &amp; II* B* Consulate, Muscat* Intelligencs Siumxry for the period fro** 16th to 51st Oct. V7. Major r&gt;, JL.Macltay harir*^ handed oyer charge of the duties of the Agency Medical Officer to Dr. R. JSasey, left for Lahore on the 26th October* Local Interesvs* 76* ills Highness the Sultan of Muscat and left lor India on the 26th October* He has appointed his uncle Laiyid Shahab bin iUiaal to represent him during his absence. Mg tpo.rp.14gi cal ♦ ^hc maximum and minimum temperatures regie* iG/ed at B&amp;it-al-Falaj during the period under report were:• -eejc ending 21st October maximum on 17th 95.3 * minimum on 16th 63.5 31st * maximum on 30th 96.7 9 minimum on 30 th 66.0 jjscelianeau«. price ox doliars is 100 rupees per 100 dollars* Usual distribution 84/* 0. i£« U. Bremner, Major leal Agent A ^.B.M t s Consul 9 ^useat«&lt;iO« X&amp; of Political Aganoy « a* a* M f # Censulat#, fcuacmt. Inv^lXlg^P 1 ?* i&gt;usr3na2*y for xjao period tvoei lat lo doth hov • * d4* JSSM» uwing to the absence of the Political ingent fron Head^uertere no XateULlgesioe dutoeasy mui leaued for the period i*ihth jtovesaber ana the present awMtwry cavers the entire month of havember* aiUia., HI* the rolitlcai *ge&amp;t accompanied by dalyid ttmimud, representative or h«Jt* the duitan y sailea freet Ms&amp;eoat in ii.ii.^.^Uipln* 1 on the 7th gevenber f for the purpose of locating and estabiiahing a Xorniiog ground JTor ii*A.*. aeroplane* in the vicinity of den^Tah bey* The expeditiont having aocoippiished its mission eaccesafuiiy f returned to muscat on ddrd November* h Separate report of the proceedings has been submitted. 82* a* hamokrishiumf inspector of ^eteoroiogicai dbccrvetoricsi visited meoat during the month* He eta tee that it is proposed to move the observatory at present established at dalt el rmlaj to dharjah in April next* 83* Mr* a*hartin 9 agent ef the xnglo»?er8ian ^11 company et a«adur 9 visited Muscat on 14th November to investigate the importation ef cheep fceroeine oil iron indie* ihe introouction of this supply is of recent origin and Is likely to seriously affect &lt;vngio*rer*ian uil Cot^ary *8 interests in Muscat 9 which have hitherto been In the nature of a monopoly* 84* Mr*d • h t • tyndis*discos 9 an instructor attaehsd to ths Madras flying ^lub f arrived in dwadur on the 4tli Novem ber piloting an aeroplane intended for an Indian Prince* He unfortunately crashed in a fog on taking off next dayjiteiUsdL* i*6»16 ot ^oXltlccd Mt M»0*ll t a wariiiuXat«| Kuncat* X»t4iiig«nct ^uc-tiary for tha period from lei to 16th Uecesu H..^, I. i * 9S« MIL. &amp;&gt;« MIL* M* ^os^e three yearo ago 400 aw of the ihodhoriycoxi (daai lr&gt; of lioqaln Ctmw&gt; applied for protoutloa to sheikh iiilol bin limstik Ual ^aad/ t roaiaiat noar In reopoaeo to the appeal sheikh iiilal occupied teo forte at Ho^&amp;in hut failed to take a third which reK&amp;iaea in the hernia of other U&amp;ul uhefir* ^ The latter having lodged a protest with the i»m against dheikfc Uil&amp;X + s ectioui a eonference was celled to which the dhoikh was invited to come with Id followers* however, attcaaed with 600 anaea followers* as the outcome of the eonferauce the imati pro- miaed dhelkh Ullal to either haou over or deniolish the fort in dispute within two i&amp;onths* In the intex'Val one of sheikh dilal's followers was hilled hy Haul halfean at Honaln* fhe dheikh refused mediation or olooumoney ami cUKi&amp;nded the iasasaiate ue- nolltion of the oifenulog fort and surrender of the tiurt^ertre of his auhcrcut* this waa refused and till a month ago matters have kung fire* A golden opportunity then afforaed in the arrival el two Baal dhslir dhow* from ^ehai ana Bahrain respectively &lt; deiaing an opportunity dheikh Hilal captured ana impri* eoneu the crews of doth dhows, mm* 64) souls in all* dhaikhs of the dan! dhafir laeteuiately approeohed oneon% iMlismn bin ^eruin ol ind sought hXu olTices ao Interxeuiary lor the rei«&amp;s« of the prisoners* ihe alec scuaht to ose his laflusae# but sheikh Hilsl rm\t.in&lt;u&gt; obdurate |, dea^anaing (a) the aemoiitioa ol tns oilejacir^ Jkflrl fort end (hi the surrenacr of the murderers sULuasd to* rsrsussion nsvls^ fsllsd 9 in aia^kovember ths vihsfiri ,iheifcn.s deputed Abdullah bln .ittshld al Usshlml of ifcri, iiaaii al hmlbaal of al Alnaln and sheikh ^ullasn Cabove) to propose U Sheikh ullal the release of the deni uhafir prisoners egzXnat the demolition of the fort f provided the sheikh would not persist In his dsmsuad for the #urr«Mder of t^s jnurderers of his followers* Jhelkh itemmd having eventually i»greed 9 the Ohaflrl prisoners were released* thereupon the Uhsflrl dhelhhs refuted their part of the dhelhh ullal has therefore co^ancea to oulla e fort in the close vicinity ol the Qhafiri fort with the lues of subduing by fores* fesnwnile a two a^onths truce ties been arranged between the parties by ^ullisan bin uea&amp;u of iaa*ul* 9h* At the ena of ^cnremoer 3 men of hakhl (Uttaxi&gt; 9 enroute to heel Ui&amp;anj were waylaid by three inalvlouals of tae iitthl laihaii &lt;uia dslmi tribes in the territory of the No’ub* Im vietlms wet's stripped end relieved of $ 1X00 and jewellery with which they were proposing to trade* 96* the private house at barxah of balyld bhahab, the ;*oltan's present representative In Muscat was gutted by fire early In the month* rue act was one of inoeodarlsm and one &amp;iid bin tJxnlfan is oiuipected* Mo is a well known baa casr&amp;cter who ratmm Uit country slue with a gang of 40 companions* A sand storm unfortunately obliterated tracks* this individual was shot at anu wounded fcy askaris of daiytd »4*^hab t when the latter was *ali of dirkah last year*vLCxiuT» Ho*17 of 1934« - Intelligence auuiBDary for the period from 16th to 31st i^ecr* Political Agency &amp; H.ii.M*® Consulate, Muscat. 34ITI3M 103. Ho thing of importance. iBBBai aaBimah 104. Dr. W.H#Stonn of the American mission arrived here from Bahrain on the 16th and returned to Bahrain on the 13th December in 3*6* H Bamora H • hmk.Mxmtwsn 106. Keference para. 94 of diary Ho.16 of 1934. It is reported that the Imam of Oman, dhaikh Mohammao bin Abdullah, has deputed on his behalf ohaikh aaif bin Hamad al Ghobri and Mohammad bin balim al Baqaishi to effect a settlement between flani Ghafir and the inhabitants of Hoqain. bhaikh Hilal bin Hamad al baadi and Mohammad bin baid al Mardhoof have also gone to Hoqain to attend the meetings aQY&lt;d, MVY. 106. H.^^.S.• , ^,upin' , arrived on 16th and left on 19th December. H.«.d.' l Fowey* arrived on 23rd and left on 30th December. RPYM, AIR mtCtt. 107. HU.. The average price of dollars was 9i 109 for 4 100 Sd/- C.EsUsBremner. Major, Political Agent H.BeM’s Consul,Muscat. Usual distribution.SECKKT No. 1 of 1936 No. 1 of 1936. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate,Muscat. Intelligence Summary for the period from 1st to 16th «Jany. BRITISH INTaaaSTS. 1. Heavy rain from daylight on 1st January augured an auspicious year. Owing to prevailing conditions no reception was held at the Agency but the customary salute was fired by the State battery and all flagstaffs were dressed. LOCAL jDWERESTS. 2. Id-il-Fitr was observed on 7th January and the customary courtesy call on His Highness or his representative was paid on the 8th instant. This year's celebration was conspicuous for an unseemly exhibition of the bad blood which exists between various members of the Ruling Family. Instead of the usual visits of felicitation, which are paid by the members of the family to His Highness's representative (in his absence) with the exception of Saiyid Nadir and one junior member, the various Saiyids trooped over to Matrah to pay their respects to Saiyid Hamad bin Faisal, Wall of Matrah the hated rival of Saiyid Shahab, His Highness's representative. Many local notables were induced to follow suit. Saiyid Mahmud and his younger brother departed for Kantab on the eve of the Id, in order to avoid calling on either Saiyid Shahab or Saiyid Hamad, each of whom he cordially dislikes. This unfortunate exhibition of the strained relations existing in the Ruling Family is said to have been engineered by a foreign official in the State service. 3. It is reported that at the beginning of January Amer, whose father Saif of the Bani Ali is one of the advisers of Saiyid Majid bin Faisal, half brother of His Highness the Sultan and now acting Naib Wall of Barkah, collected a force and with the help of Khalifat biHilal bin Ghusn also of the Bani Ali attacked Yankul (a place in Dhahirah) whose chief is Suleitoan bin Sinan (Bani Ali). The attack was abortive and Amer had to beat a hasty retreat with the loss of 16 men. 4. No ships of the Boyal Navy called at Muscat during the period under report. MBTBOHQLQGICAL. 5. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered during the period under review were*- Week ending 7th January maximum on 7th 81.9 M M M rt minimum on 3rd 53.5 w M 14th H Maximum on 9th 84.1 w * n minimum on 14th 58.1 1.2 M of rain was recorded during the fortnight under report. MTSGELL^NEQUB. 6. The average rate of dollars was Rs 109 per 100 dollars. Political Agent d H.B.M's Consul,Muscat. ABN. Usual distributionSECKliiT i'jo• 3 ot 4 V^} Political Ageac/ oc H.BJA’a Consulate, Muscat* Intelligence Sur^imary for the period from 1st to 15th Feby. 14. The Hon'ble Licut-Colonel C.J.Fowle, C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, accompanied by hie Under Secretary Mr. J.Croning, arrived by flying boat on the 13th February. LOCAL INTERESTS. 15. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman returned from his visit to India on the 6th February. His Highness^ arrival was preceded and followed by torrential rain, which was regarded as an auspicious portent locally. GEHMrui lirriiAhoiL. 16. Herr Heinrich Wilinow, a German national and partner in the firm of Messrs F.Undated! &amp; Co., arrived from Basrah on the 3rd ana left for Bahrain on the 6th February by 3.5. ,, Barala M . Herr (wiUnow, who is an ex German Naval Officer, speaks excellent English. The object of his visit was to deal with the problem of barter, in as far as it affects local exporters of M kasna f ’ (fish manure) who have hitherto icuna market# in Germany. 17. S.3. &lt;, Nuenfels ,t arrived from Lushire on the 3rd February and left for Port Gaid on the same day. FBENCH INTEH^TL. 18. The French oloop “Bougainville'V*ith Hear Admiral Bivet, commanding the French Naval Forces at Beyrout arrived on the 8th February and left on the 9th February* Customary calls were exchanged between the Admiral, Political Agent and tnc Bui tan. The Admiral and many of his officers speak good English.KOYAL NAVY. 19. H.M.S.Fowey arrived on the 1st and left on the 3rd February. Customary calls were exchanged with the State• H.M.3. M Shoreham rt arrived on the 5th February and left on the same day. ROYAL AIK FQKCa. 20. One Rangoon arrived on the 13th instant and left on the following day. MISCLLLARLQUS. 21. The installation of electric power in the buildings of the Political Agency at Muscat, which was started on the 6th of November 1934, was sufficiently completed by the 6th February to afford current on the 8th February 1935. The power house building remains to be completed and certain minor re-adjustments have yet to be made. 22. The average rate of dollars was fc 108 per 100 j£ METEOROLOGICAL. 23. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at B&amp;it-al-Falaj during the fortnight under review were*- Week ending 7th February maximum on 4th 88.1 w mum minimum on 6th 62.0 rt w 15th w maximum on 15th 75.7 M M * n minimum on 15th 54.3 Rainfall during the 1st half of February has been (2.1 M &gt; unprecedented and the total rainfall to date (7.93') has been phenominal. Even the barren rocks of Muscat harbour are now verdant with green and grazing every where is abundant. A severe gale occured on the 4th instant and carried away a portion of the Agency roof and uprooted some of the few trees existing in Muscat proper. Political Agent &lt;k H.B.M's Usual distribution. Major, Muscat.SECRET. flo.4 of 1935 .Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate, itusoat. Intelligence Stuitiary for the period fro* 16th to 28th February 1935. BRITISH IRTSREST3. Z*- The Hon♦bla Lieut-Colonel T.C.Fowls, C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, acconpanied by Mr.J.Croning, fl.B.E., 3sft by flying boat for Bahrain on the 20th February. A salute of 15 guns was fired by liie State battery on his departure fron Muscat. 25. His Excellency Mr.H.H. ^natehbu 11-Hugeseen, C.M. G., His Britannic Majesty* s Enroy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of Persia, accompanied by Mrs. Xhatchbull-Hugessen arrived in H.M.S. rt Shoreham’* on the 20th February in the course of a short unofxicial visit. During his stay t he minister called privately on His Highness the Sultan. RDYAh AIR FORGE. 26 • oae R.a.F. 'Rangoon* arrived on the 18th and left on the 20th February. ROYAL HAVY. 27 * H.il.S. 'Shoreham' arrived on the 20th and left pn the 22nd February. She saluted the port on arrival. LOCAL INTERESTS. 28* Information lias come to hand that during a severe gale off Gwadur on 27th January five local dhows, conveying merchandise to the anil, were sunk with the loss of Rs. 25000/-worth of cargo. 2®* 1* reported that during the last week of February Madhad bin Diyan of Bani Aaab carried off 400 goats from Murair and 4 donkeys from Balaidah. It is also ■tot.d that some women and children hare been kidnapped by bedwins from Shinas.SECRET. No.6 of 1935. Political Agency 4 H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat. Intelligence Summary for the period from 16th to 31st March. BRITISH INTERESTS. Major C.E.U.Bremner, M.C., Political agent, Muscat, accompanied by H.H. the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman left for Khasab on the 20th in H.M.S.'Shoreham H and returned on the 26th March. • 2. M.Hafiz Mohammad Ismail, newly appointed British Agent at Gwadur arrived at Gwadur on the 24th March and took over the charge of the Agency on the same day. 3. Mr. J.Kirkpatrick, a Director of Messrs the Mesopota mia Persia Corporation Ltd., arrived from Basrah on the 29th March xn connection with the visit of the American Tourist ship ’‘Stella Polaris” which is expected to arrive here on the 5th April. ROYAL AIR FORCE, 4. The following Royal Air Force aircraft visited Muscat j- One «Victoria” arrived on the 23rd &amp; left on 27th March Four “Wapitis” arrived on the 27th &lt;* left on 29th March. royal navy. 5. H.M.S. M Shoreham n visited Muscat on 18th &amp; 26th and left on the 20th &amp; 27th March respectively. MISCEIiLAMEOire. 6. The average rate of dollars for the fortnight under report was Rs 112 per 100 dollars. METEOROLOGICAL. The maximum and minitoum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Falaj during the period under review were;- For week ending 21st March maximum on 20th 98.4 minimum on 16th 63.7 w maximum on 23rd 99.8 ' minimum on 23rd 70.0 w ♦I w n « 31st n dfl/- C.E.U.Bremner, Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul,Muscat.SECRET. Ho.7 of 1935. Inttlligtnc# Summary for th* period from 1st to 30 th April. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M'e Consulate, Muscat. It is regretted that owing to the absence of the Political Agent from Headquarters no Sur.mary was issued for the first half of April. Present Summary covers the period 1st to 30th April. BRITISH IHTERE3TS. 1 * Agency Free Hospital Musnat . The extremely parlous financial condition of this charitable public institution has been the cause of MKBxxxixg increasing anxiety of late. Owing to the widespread depression of the last few years, the voluntary subscriptions, on which the Hospital is dependent, have practically ceased. At the same time increased poverty has bred increased sickness and the unusually heavy rains this winter were productive of a grester incidence of maleria and other ills than usual. Inspite of rigorous economy the resources of the Hospital had reached such a low ebb by the end of March, that urgent meaeu s had to be devised to find funds. At the suggestion of the Sultan, a public meeting wsc celled at the Barza on 3rd April at which a joint appeal by His Highness and the Political Agent was made to the assembled British and Muscat Subjects and the urgency of the appeal was fully explained. As a r.sult of this app.al iis. 2105 /-hsY. b.«n subBcrtbsd and furth.r donations h»rt bs.n promised. His Highn.se g.nerously contritmt.d 2s.500/-to the fund as a donation in honour of Their liaj.sti.e' Silver Jubilee TOURS. 2 2 ' At ^ s P« cisl r.qu t of the Sultan th. Political Ag.nt accompanied His Highn.s; to Gwadur on 5th of April*nd was his gutst in camp thera for savarel days. ijH On th.« l?th of April Political ^gant procaedad to Dalhi raturning on tha 16th of April to Karachi' to assist tha oulten in carta in matters thara. On the '1st oi April His Highnass, accomp&amp;niad by tha Political Agent, returned to Gwadur, where tha Sultan transhipped to H.M.S.'Lupin' to proceed to Bur while the Political .Agent returned to Muscat. H.M. S.'Lupin' returned bringing His Highness and party f: VISITS. Luring the dult*n T s stcy at our, the retiring Senior liavcl Oflicer, Persian Gulf Division, Captain J.V.Croigh, L.S.O., paid him a visit of farewell there. His Highness was much touched at Captain Creigh’s courtesy and friendly thoughtfulliesB in going so far out of his way to say goodbye to him. The presence of two sloops at our at tha same time, considerably enhanced the Sultan’s prestige at this somewhat wild spot. His Highness ?/as quick to recognise this fact and to express hie gratitude. ROYAL AIR PORCH. 4« Two flying boats of 2 &amp; 3 Squadron visited Muscat on 25th and l.ft on 27th April. Thay th.nc. proceeded to Masirah Island, and, returning via Sur, visitad Gwadur on 28th April. One ''ictoria arrived^Muscot on 13th April and returned on 16th. Pour Wapitis of Ho.55 Squadron visited Muscat on 17th April and left on 19th for Sharjah. loqal iET::a.:. -?s. Det.ila of His Highness' movements during the month have already been given. Shortly prior to his visit to Gwsdur an abortive-3- V*?0f •ttampt w«E mad* to prev.nt th* Sultsn r ,oin s th«rV. a t*l.gr B m, addr*BB*d to th. Director of Revenues from . n unknown •K.dicsl Officer' was received 8 t Muscat stating that a severe epidemic of cholera had broken out at Gwadur This information was proved to be entirely false. His Highness* visit was most opportune and resulted in . web of intrigue being laid bare, which had apparently been going on for some time under th. auspices of th* Director of Revenues Muscat State. Separate reports of these incidents have bean submitted. SEA TRAKdl ORT. 6# during the month a mastltss, Brhrain built, motor dhow has mad. its appearance. It normally p ii. s for hire between Muscat and Mat rah. but proceeds to Sur and th* Batinah Const if inducement offers. It can comfortably accommodate fifty passengers for short trips. The normal chargee are ot follows:- Muscat-Me trah Muscr t-Sib Muses t-Birqs Musea t-Maenah wJ 5 ! 1 ?? 8 for • single seat 1/2 dollar -do- 1 dollar -do- li dollar -do- Its 8dv » nt hailed with joy by a hojirdfof th younger generation of Muscat who enjoyed free edv.rtisem.n joy rides for the first three days. The welcome extended to the 'Launch' by the local taxi drivers wos however less cordial. Finding themselves confronted with a serious rival they petitions the Sultan accordingly. His Highness* reply took th. fom of a brief, but apt. question.- 'Did you consider this point when you deprived those hoori owners of their daily bres.d, who plied betwaen Muscat and liatrah?' gRICE OP 'rLVKR . 7 * Th * repidly increasing price of silver with the attendant rise in the price of the dollar is having • -st prejudicial effect on business concerns, Consider.blonxitty is bting tvinctd by smaller tr*d«rs, and ruptas ara gatting daily scarcar in tha marlcat. AMBRICAH INTERESTS. Q* Tha steamship *otalla Polaris*, a Horwagian ship chartarad by an ^marican concarn for a luxury world cruisa, arrivad hara on tha 5th April. Invitations to visit tha ship wara axtandad to tha Sultan and tha Political Agant by tha Captain and tha Director of tha cruisa. His Highnass daputad hie uncla Salyid Shahab for tha purpose. Tha passengers wara somewhat disappointed that tha Multan ’’hadn’t coma off to be presented to them.* from their conversation and many questions it was evident that their conception of Sultans and .Shaikhs was founded on tha bast traditions of Hollywood. A copy of tha Sultan’s appeal for the Muscat Hospital was considerately posted on board by tha shipping agents. Inspite of Dr. Harrison’s kindly efforts to mislead all and sundry on board to the affect that ^ tha Muscat Agency Hospital was a Government institution, built and maintained throughout at Government expanse’’, a subsciption has bean promised by tha Director of the cruisa. Dt* Harrison of tha American Mission proceeded to our on 8th April with tha Sultan’s permission and is still there. Mrs Harrison has left Muscat an route for tha United States. PUBLIC HEALTH. 10. Tha large increase of malaria during March and e&amp;rly April has bean a serious source of anxiety alike to tha Medical and State authorities, who have been co operating earnestly to combat the evil. The main breeding ground for mosquitoes is the large drainage pond outside the old town walls. Being below tea level it is impossible ever to wholly evacuate all water therefrom.-5- If th« fallacy that moaquito^s cannot bre&gt; 5 d in salt or brackish wat«r had not long ago b«®n axplodad by madical rastarch, ampla proof to th» contrary has always b«tn av^i.lcbl® in the Muscat ’’pond”. So thick wara larvaa this ya©r tnat 1itcmjLy handfuls could ba scooped from the water. Specimens thus recovered and hatched out by the Medical Ofiicer revealad anopheles mosquitoes in abundance. Examination in situ by two successive Principal Medic®! Officers of the Roygil Air Force and the Principal Medical Officers of the Royal Hevy, apart from the Medical Officer Muscat, reveals the fact that this pool is a veritable paredlse for all forms of mosquitoes to breed in. Regular and plentiful oiling of the surface of this pond hcs already begun to improve the situation. MRTROROLCQICAL. 11. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered nt Bait-al-Falaj during the period under report were; Maximum on 16th .April Minimum on 9th ' 98.2 60.0 MISCELLANEOUS. 1C. The sverrge rrte of dollars for the month of April was IU. 150/-per 100 dollars. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M'a Consul, Muscat. GHK V oSECRET. No.8 of 1935. Intolligonco Summery for tho poriod from 1st to 15th M*y Political Agtncy &amp; H.B.M’s Oonsulatt, Muscat. KHITXciH INTERESTS. 1. Silvr JuMlto . Tho outstanding avant of tha pariod undar raviaw h»s baan tha calabration of His Majasty tha King’s oilvar Jubilaa, which was aegarly lookad forward to by all alika in Muscat. Undar tha parsonal suparvision of tha Political Agant decorations ware carried out along tha whole saa front on which tha Agency and other Government buildings stand. Festoons of rad, white, and blue cloth, suspended low from poles draped in scarlet cloth, each of which bora a colour or pennant, converted tha usual drab aspect of tha saa front to one of brilliancy throughout its length. A continuous line of bunting, hung at first floor level, and extending from tha Agency Main Entrance Gate to tha Customs House, added a further touch of colour. Tha Agency building itself was festooned with red, white and blue cloth ’’buckled’’ at intervals with alternating Union Jacks and Muscat Stafce flags. The balcony above the Main Door of the Agency was similarly festooned, whilst over the Entrance itself were draped curtainwise an immense Union Jack end its Muscat counterpart. To the gaiety of the decorations was added the brilliant hues of the various traag and flowaring craepers that hava bean succassfully raarad in the lest two years in a formerly barren courtyard. For the purpose of illuminations at night the Agency Main Gate, the Main Entrance Doorway, and the entire face of that side of the Agency which overlooks the see, were brilliantly outlined in red, white and blue electric lamps, whilst a festoon in these colours wss also suspended fromtht yard arm of th# Agancy Flagstaff. Tha sea and land entrances to the Palaca His Highness the lultnn v?ert brilliantly outlined in -wt-ita 1ighte. Accession Day, Leing the day appointed throughout the Kmpire as r dy of Thanksgiving ana Geiebrsition, was observed as a public holiday and His Highness the wUitan proclaimed a State holiday on th, ug»ta. All shops and places of business were closed and a truly holiday spirit pervadod the local township. Proceedings on the fith hay commenced with the firing of a Hoys 1 ! 8*lut# by His Highness the Sultan r s Battery at 8 a.m. imultaneously at the Agency, a Boyal Guard of Honour acccmipaniedL by the hutcat Iniantry band, kindly ordered for the occasion by His Highness tho Sultan, saluted the Colour a they were broxen nt the iiscsidiuaEd mast-head. At the conclusion of the salute, God lave the King was pl»y&lt;*d nnd throe cheer j for Their I/^jesties were given. The Agency Flrgsteff, tho Palace, Hie Highness* forts and all public buildings, even dhows in tas herbour were dressed for the occasion. At 11.15 a.m. the Political ^igont &amp; H.3.M f s Consul held a Durbar at the Agency. The ceremony was grtced by His Highness rnd 14 members of the Ruling Family, tpart from some 150 other guests/ The interior quadrangle of the Agency had been converted on the ground floor to a reception pavilion, and on the first floor into s Durbsr Hall for tae purpose. Both floors were thickly carpeted, whilst that reserved for the Durbar was lined throughout with purple, blue and green curtains. Immediately over the d?is reserved for His Highness the Sultan and the Political Agent, was hung a splendid oil painting of His Majesty the King, lent for the purpose * by the Sultan.-3- On #ith*r sidt of th« dais, at a suitabla distune®, wara hung portraits of His lata M*jasty i^ing i^d^ard, His S •'T Royal Highnass tha Irinca of ^alas, Hia Highnase ''aiyid ffaisal th* Sultan’a grand fathar and 3ir Saiyid Taimur, His Highnasa' fathar. Durbar baing daclarad opened, a short spaach was m&amp;ae by tha Poiiticel Agent. This was followed by a most felicitous spaach by His Highness. Brief and very excellent speeches, wall delivered, were then made by the leaders oi the Ahoja, Hindu and Agalchani communities. On the close of the Durbar and after the departure of His highness and party, the leaders of the British Community jointly requested that their dutiful homage ©nd loyalty might be humbly conveyed to Their Majesties for whose health, long life and prosperity they ever prayed. On the conclusion of the foregoing ceremonies the Political Agent attended the distribution of food, issued on a very generous scale, to some four hundred and fifty poor folk. Ab funds for this purpose were not available the Political Agent was himself happy to bear the entire cost in commemorat ion of the Jubilee. The joy and gratitude reflected in the faces of the recipients were in themselves an adequate repayment of the expenditure. At 8.15 p.m. a Reception and firework Display was held at the Agency. His Highness and the Ruling Family honoured the occasion with their presence, besides some hundred other guests. The events of a very memorable day in Muscat were brought to a nappy conclusion at 10.30 p.m. An interesting sidelight on the Jubilee Celebrations, as showing how ra£)idly rumour travels, was voiced in a tel® which a few bazaar gossips had alter the arrival of the last down mail. According to the story, the xersian Oovernment had forbidden any celebrations or receptions to taBe place inSTuCRIST • lo. 9 of 1935. Intelligence Summary for the period from 16th Mey to Slot June 1935. Political Agency &amp; H.B.H'a Consulate, Muscat. BR ITIr^H IKTSftiSSTS. 1. Major J.J.Rooney, I.M.s. f Residency burgeon Bushire, arrived at Muscat on the 16th Hay on on inspection tour of the Quarantine Medical Stations on the Arab side of the Gulf. Ho left the same day for Bahrain. 2. Major C.E.U.Bremner, M.C. left for the United Kingdom on leave on the 6th June, by a Royal Air Porce flying boat via Iraq, having handed over charge of the duties of the Political Agent by telegram to Major R.P.Watts, I.A., Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Major Bremner^ hurried departure hod been sanctioned on medical recommendation on the grounds of ill health and the necessity for his leaving Muscat as quickly as possible. ROYAL AIR FORCE. Two R.A.P.flying boats, with Air Commodore Goesage, B.3.0. ,M.C., and Group Captain R.E.Saul, D.P.C., on board arrived on the 5th June and left the next day. 4. One R.A.I*. ,, Yictor4s ,, arrived at Muscat on the 29th June and was expected to leave on the 1st July. ROYAL ff/VY. 5. H.M.S. *Bideford’’ called at Muscat to pick a fire engine which was lying at the Mokalls Coal Depot on the 21st June and left the some day. 6# H.M.d. *Lupin M arrived at Muscat on the 29th June and left the next doy. LOC L IETERaoTS. 7. Sometime in January 1935 in the course of a quarrel in the Soham bazaar, one Salim,servant of Saiyid Saif bin Bader, /ali of Scham stabbed end killed a man of the Hawosine tribe. The Hawasinah sheikhs demanded Salim from the Wall2- &amp; ■ Well 3cif who however refused to hand hia over end offered bloodmoney instead. As the matter could not be settled, the Wall sent his servant to Muscat. Hie Highness the Sultan of Muscat sentenced Salim to be shot end the execution was carried out publicly at Muscat on the 21st May. 8. On the 14th June His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman proceeded by the 8*ote motor dhow as far as , l -ur and returned on the 19th June. 9. It is said that on the 17th of June Suleiman bin Hamyor cl Hiyami of Jobal Akhdher had gone to Ja’lcan to try and effect a reconciliation between the Beni Bu Ali and Beni Bu Hasan. The result is not yet known. Mi3T.3 PROLOG IGAL. 10. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Folaj for the period Fortnight ending May n June » M ft * • * under report 31st maximum * minimum 15th maximum * minimum 30th maximum * minimum were:- on 26th May 108.0 on 17th May 74.0 on 6th June 108.6 on 6th June 76.9 on 18th June 114.1 on 20th June 80.2 MI SCELIu JTSOUS. 11. The average price of dollars for the period under report was Ks.l32/-per 100 dollars. Major, Political -Agent &amp; H.B.M f s Consul, Muscat. PI8TRIBUTICB . ^ £. iis Majesty’s Secretary of State for India. 2. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of findia. 3. The Chief of the General Staff, Army Headquarters, India 4. His Majesty’s Ambassador, Baghdad. 5. His Majesty’s Minister, Jcdda. 6. The Chief Commissioner, Aden. 7. The otaff Officer, Havel Intelligence Centre, Colombo. 8. The 3enior Haval Officer, Persian Gulf Division. 9. The ir Officer Commanding, ’Iraq Command, Baghdad. Officer Commanding Ho.203 (F.B. ) Squadron,R.A.F.Basrah, 11. The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 12. The Political Agent, Bahrain. 13. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 14. Hie Majesty’s Consul, Basrah.oECRBT♦ So.10 of 1935. Intelligence Sunmory for the period from 1st to 15th July 1935 , Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat. BRITISH INTERESTS. 1. Reference paragraph 2 of Intelligence Summary Jio .9 of 19 Kojor R.P. ,'atts, I. A., Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat arrived from Bushire on the 2nd July, He called official^ on His Highness the mltan of Muscat &amp; Oman on the 11th July and the latter returned his visit on the some day. BOYAL AIR FORCE. 2. A 'Rangoon' flying boot from Bo.203 Squadron R.A.P. Basrah arrived on 5th. On July 7th a Plight from Bo.84 Squadron Basrah arrived. On 8th the 'Rangoon* with the Officer Commanding So.84 Squadron Plight and the Political Agent on board left to examine the landing grounds at Rns-al-Hodd and Mosiroh Island. They returned to Muscat the following day. The Rangoon and the 3 land planes all left for Basrah on 11th. METEOROLOGICAL. ihe maximum and minimum temperatures registered at Bait-al-Faloj for the period under report ore:- Week ending 7th July maximum on 1st July Uo.l ' » ia+i, « mlr| knum on 3rd July 80.6 « » i. . “oximum on 10th July 107.0 minimum on 13th July 85.9 m iscsLi/mious. 4 4- The average price of dollars for the period under report was Bs.l31/-per 100 dollars. VVS 10 ■ Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. ofC USUAL DISTRIBUTIOH.Secret. No. 11 of 1935. V”/ Intelligence eummary for the period from 16th July to 16th August 1935. Political Agency &amp; H.S.M’s Consulate # Muscat. Royal Navy. 1. H.M.S. 'Po^ey' visited Muscat on the 31st July and left on the same day. Shipping. 2. Statement attached. Aviation. 3* One Royal Air Force aeroplane 'Victoria M arrived on the 20th July and left on the 22nd. 4. One “Victoria' arrived on the 16th August and is due to leave on the 19th. British Interests. 5. The Upper Air Observatory xiiaustu* stationed at Bait-al-Falaj was closed do-'n on the 16th July and tne observers left for Sharjah on the same day. The '“ork of the surface observatory has been trans- fened to the Political Agency. 6* Major R.P.tfatte, I.A., Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul left on recess to Shiraz on the olst July. Local Interests. ? * H1S Hi Shness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman proceeded by S.S. 'Barpeta' to Sohar on the 27th July and returned by land on the 11th August. Meteorological. 8 ‘ Th * maxilnum and minimum temperatures registered at this Agency for the period under report were:- Fortnight ending 31st July 1935 max. on 22/7 109.9® ' ' 16th a ', * I min ' ' 18 / ? 82.8° » » ^ h Au ^ uet ' max. » i 4 / 8 105 .8 a Miscellaneouw . ' min ‘ H 6/8 83.00 9 ’ The aVerag ' prlce of d0 H a rs for the period under report -vas Rs.132/. per 100 dollars. Pit tribution. As usual. ua Fajor Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’e Consul,MuscatSECRET. Ho. 12 oi’ 1935 Intelligence Summary for the period from 17th to 31st August *35. /r ROY/X NAVY. 1. Ho visits. SHIPPING. S. Statement attached. ^flATIOH. 3. Royal Air Force. Reference paragraph 4 of Summary Ho.11. The Victoria left on the 19th August. LOCAL INT5RB3TB. 4. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat on his return from Sahar on the 11th August brought with him 25 men of the Boni Umar tribe and placed them os night watchmen on one of the two gates in Muscat, os a result of which 17 men of the local Police force have been dismissed. Another botch of 20 men from the Alhawasin arrived on the 28th August and wece placed in charge of the other gate. It is further reported that some more men from the Abrini tribe are expected, who will be posted at Matrah. The pay of the tribesmen has been fixed at Bs.7 per mensem. Two bogs of rice and 2 bags of coffee were also given as a present to the men at each gate. 5. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman left for Bombay by S.S? H Bamora' on the 31st August. METliOROLOGICAL. 6. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at the /gency for the period under report were:- Moximum on 18.8.35 89.0 Minimum on 27.8.35 78.0 MISCELLANEOUS. The average price of dollars for the period under repoi was A.130/-per 100 dollars. Au) Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. Bated at Shiraz, the 5th Sept.1935. Bistribution as usual.SECRET /&gt; Ho. 1935. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M* Consulate, Muscat. Intelligence Summary for the period from 1st to 15th September 1935. ROYAL HAVY. 1* Ho visits. SHIPP IHG. 2. Statement attached. AVIATIOH. 3. Royal Air Force. Ho visits. FOREIGH IHTERE5TS 4. Telegraphic instructions were received on the let September from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to observe Court mourning till 11th September for the late Q,ueen of the Belgians, and the flog of this Agency was flown at half mast on the 3rd September, the day of the funeral. METEOROLOGICAL. 5. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at the Agency for the period under report were*.- Maximum on 15th 100.3 Minimum on 1st 78.2 MISCSLLAHEOUS. 6. The overage price of dollars for the period under report was Ks.136 per 100 dollars. ^ Major, Political .'gent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. #' Muscat. Doted at Muscat, the 27th September 1935. Distribution os usual£ ; e aSCHBT Ko. 14 ©f 1936. © Intelligence Jummary for the period from 16th to 30th September 1936. ROYAL NAVY. 1. The senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, Captain V.3. butler L.b.O. in H.k.o. ohoreham arrived on tne 18th and left next day. 3. The senior Naval officer Persian Gulf called on baiyid chahab, the Representative of His Highness the dultan of Muscat and Oman on 18th. Gaiyid bhahab retui’nea the call immediately on H.i, .3. tihoreham and when leaving received a salute of 13 guns. 3. H.M.S. Ghoreham returned to Muscat on the 27th and left for the Gulf on the following day. 4. calls between the Political /gent and H.M*s Consul and tne Senior Naval Officer were exchanged on the 28th. GRIPPING. 6. Statement attached. AVIATION. 6. Royal ^ir Force . On September 26th, 2 *Wapitis* of No. 66 Squadron arrived from daera and left on 27th on their return flight. On September 26th, 3 ''Vincents’' under the command of Plt./Lt. Nutt&amp;ll, R.k.F. of No. 84 Squadron arrived in Muscat and left the next day to carry out an examination of the landing ground at Masirah Island which had been reported unsuitable for certain types of air-craft. This unsuitability was confirmed by Flt./Lt. Nuttall and as a result of his report Squadron Leader Fogarty with 4 ,, Vincents ,, of No. 84 Squadron arrived in Muscat from Basra on the 30th September for the purpose of proceeding to Masirah Island for inspection of a new landing ground which had been found by Flt./Lt.Nuttall on his previous flight.BHITISH UJT&amp;RI&amp;jTS* 7. Mr. p.i;. Bunker, Maniiger ef the Karachi Section of the Gable and tfirelea* Limited, landed from S.S. 'Bankura” on the 24th September and after inspecting the local office proceeded t© Jask by the eame boat. 8. Major h.p. Watts, 1.^., Political regent and H.M's Consul Muscat returned from recess in Shiraz via Bushire on the 27th September, LOCAL INTLHKSTS» 9. Saiyid Hamad bin Faisal, the Wali of tfatrah returned from Bombay on the 24th September, A dispute, which at one time looked like having serious developments,took place recently between two of the Saltan’s uncles, Saiyis shahab, the sultan’s representative and Saiyid Hamad, the Wali of Matrah, The latter who had been to Bombay for medical treatment returned to Matrah in the last week of September. On his arrival he issued a public notice announc ing that he had resumed charge of his office. Saiyid Shahab hearing of this, ordered the acting Wali ©f Matrah to ignore the presence of Saiyid Hamad and to continue in control of the administration of the town. The quarrel between the two uncles for a little time threatened to break out into an actual disturbance but the disputants were persuaded by the Chief Justice of Muscat, Shaikh ^ubair bin ^li, to keep the peace until the arrival of the Sultan, who is now investi gating the matter. 10. Beference para 4 of summary No. 12. another batch of 26 men of the Bani Umar tribe arrived a during the period under report and were posted as/guard on the Matrah gate. METEOROLOGICAL. 11. The maximum and minimum temperature registered at this agency for the period under report was*- Maximum on 19th September 1G1 # Minimum on 22nd September 78.3°MISCELLANEOUS 12. The average price of dollars for the period under review was Rs. 127 for 100 dollars. GWADUR NEWS. 13. It is reported from Gwadur that numerous pilgrims have arrived there from Sind and Dera Ghazi Nhan en route t© Mecca. These people are said to be practically desti tute, having no passports or money and many being in rags. Their practice is to obtain a little money by begging in Gwadur and take passages in dhows to remote ports in Muscat territory whence they proceed in other sailing vessels to Mokalla, from which place the majority make their way overland to Mecca. 14. The trade of Gwadur is in a depressed state. Mdctanis who used to buy their requirements from Gwadur now go to Pasni for that purpose in ©rder to save the payment of double duty on their goods (one paid at Gwadur and the other to the Kalat State). Previously no duty was levied by the Kalat State on goods purchased in dwadur and taken Xs to the Mekran. 15. The fishing industry on which most of the people of Gwadur depend for a livelihood is in a poor way this year. In spite of the scarcity of fish, prices in Colombo which is the principal export market, have fallen unexpectedly low and the traders who shipped fish there during the last two months are stated to have sustained considerable losses. Major, Political Agent d H.B.M's Consul. Muscat, the 8th October 1935. Usual distributionSSCBET. No. 15 of 1935. Intelligence Summary for the period from 1st to 15th October 1935. BOYaL NiiVY. No visits. SHIPPING. Statement attached. hV I AT ION. 3. Boyal ^ir Force . Reference para 6 of summary No. 14 of 1935. SZ-udr. Fogarty with one Flight of No. 84 Squadron accompanied by the Political .vgent left for Masirah Island - first o i ^na October, a descent having/been made on the old landing ground, the new ground which is situated some 4 miles to the southward, was visited. This new ground was found to be in an excellent condition, requiring no work to be done on it, and apparently better in every respect to the former ground. xhe flight returned to Muscat the same day. as the inhabitants of the village near the old landing ground were reluctant to undertake the work of transporting a quantity oi petrol and oil to the new site, arrangements were made from Muscat to send down a motor dhow to carry out the task. The dhow returned to Muscat on 14th and reported that the petrol and oil required had been trans ported to the new ground. S/Ldr. Fogarty and the 7 machines of his Squadron left Muscat for Basrah via Sharjah on the 4th. BBITISH INTB&amp;BBTB. 4. Cable Be-organisation . The Cable Ship 'hady Benison Pender” arrived from ,.den oa 9th October. She laid the shore end of a new cable at ^ he gabm the gap to the east of the agency and left for the Persian coast on the 12th laying out the cable on her way. It is reported that this new cable was connected to the Jask Karachi cable on the 13th at a spot some 300 miles to the £ast of the former place and Muscat is now consequently in direct cable communication with Karachi. The Muscat end of the old Jask cable has been taken up and the remainder which is reported to be old and unserviceable is to be abandoned. Similar action, it is understood, is to be taken at Jask as regards the cables leading in to that station. AS a result of this change an extra operator of the Cable and Wireless Limited has arrived ana it is expected that an Officer in Charge and another senior signaller will be shortly transferred from Jask to Muscat. LOCAL IHTLHLSTS. 5. His Highness the Sultan returned to Muscat from Bombay on the 2nd October. His sudden departure to India on the 31st August about which no previous mention of his intention had been made, was due to His Highness’s decision to unaergo an X-ray examination to discover the cause of some internal trouble which he had apparently developed during his recent tour of the Batinah. The result of the examination which was carried out by some German Jewish refugee doctors in Bombay was most satisfactory - the trouble being found to be not of a serious nature. His Highness spent a considerabi* time and displayed great pleasure in showing the Political .kgent when the latter called on him a number of X-ray photo graphs of the interior of various parts of his anatomy. The Sultan announced soon after his return that he would shortly be leaving for Dhofar. In an interview with the Political ^gent, His Highness stated that the reason for his departure being fixed nearly a month earlier than he had originally intended was due to the fact t&amp;si the Moghul -Steamship Company of Bombay with whom he had arranged to xaxe him to Dhofar not having another steamer available after/ 8. after October for several months. His Highness stated that the Steamship Company was charging Hs. 4000 to divert one of their steamers from their regular Bombay Karachi and Red Sea Ports run to Muscat and tauve him xama and some fifty of his followers % X to Dhofar. The steamer the S*S* Jehangir arrived in Muscat on the 12th and left the same evening for Dhofar with His Highness and 50 of his followers and servants on board* 12 riding horses and some camels were embarked in dhows and left for Dhofar a few days later. In the Sultan* s absence Saiyid Shahab bin Faisal will act as his representative. 6. Reference para 9 of Summary JSo. 14 of 1935. The dispute between the two uncles of the Sultan was referred to him on his return. His Highness evidently thought this was a good opportunity of getting rid of Saiyid Hamad with whom he has not been on the best of terms for some time. accordingly public notices were displayed in Muscat and Matrah to the effect that owing to Saiyid Hamad’s ill * health he was unable to continue in his office and that the Sultan had been pleased to relieve him as Wali of Matrah by Saiyid Mahmud - another of his uncles* The change will probably be for the good as Saiyid Hamad though a strong character and having a pleasant personality, had been grossly neglectful of his duties as Wali of Matrah. 7. While a party of prisoners were working on the Muscat- Matrah road on October 15th, two of their number made a dash for freedom. They endeavoured to escape by climbing up the rocky hills overlooking the road but were overtaken by the Police guard and refusing to stop in spite of warnings were both shot dead.8. The Political ^gent called on H.H. the Sultan on 7th October and the latter returned the call on the 9th. The Sultan called on the Political /igent again on the 11th October. 9. Khan Bahadur Ahmad Shubaili, His Highness r s Private Secretary arrived from Bombay by S.S. Jehangir on the 12th and accompanied the Sultan to Dhofar. saws . 10. Beference para 15 of Summary No. 14 of 1935. It is reported that the prices of dried fish at Colombo have improved considerably and some of the merchants who shipped consignments during the end of September have made good profits. The fishing season is, however, now over and the rise in prices has come too late to be of much help to exporters. 11. Mr. Fateh *JLi Shaikh, assistant engineer, P.W.D. Bushire accompanied by Mr* Pradhan Singh, Overseer Muscat, arrived on the 22nd September. They came to inspect the site for a new bungalow for the political *gent, and returned to Muscat on the 23rd September. METEOROLOGICAL. 12. The maximum and minimum temperature registered at the political agency Muscat during the period under repw report was*- o Maximum on 1st October 92.2 Minimum on 15th October 73.0° MISCELLANEOUS* 13. The average dollar rate during the period under review was Rs. 137 for 100 dollars. Maj or, Political ^gent &lt;k H.M's Consul,Muscat The 16th October 1935. Distribution as usualSiSCEST. No. 16 of 1936. MUSCAT Intelligence Summary for the period from 16tli to 31«t October 1936. ROYAL MAVY. 1. Mo visits. SHIPP IMG. 2. tto Foreign vessels entered Muscat during Uae period under review. wwim- 3. Hoval -.ir Force . ^ 'Valencia* with Flying Officer Woodworth in command arrived at Muscat on 19th from iiaghdad on a training i light in the Gulf. On 21st a visit was made to Masirah Island. The Political vgent accompanied the flight to see that the petrol had been properly dumped in the correct place on the new landing ground vide paragraph 3 of Diary Mo. 16 oi 1936. The worM was found to have been carried out sati si actor ily. The aeroplane returned to Muscat the same day and lelt lor Basrah and Baghdad via Lharjah on 22nd. A Flight of 4 'Vincents', Squadron Leader Hope in command,arrived on the 29th October. The Plighc J-Cos &lt;&gt;ae machine which had been slightly damaged in landing at Muscat left for Dhofar on the 30th. HAITIJH XITT^ELoTa . 4 . Cfoble and Wireless Limited . Reference paragraph 4 of nummary ho. 16 of 1936. Mr. G.W. Watson ana Mr. Lobo, as Officer in Charge ana operator respectively for the local office arrived from Karachi on the 22nd October. 6. Major R.P. Watts, 1.^., Political Agent k H.M’s Consul Muscat left for Karachi on 26th October to obtain technical adviceadvice in connection with certain schemes which are being carried out to improve the towns of Muscat and Matrah. LOCitL IHTKBBSTS. 6. Shaikh Mohamed son of Shaikh Isa bin Saleh al Harithi of Onan arrived at Muscat on the 17th October, with the intention of proceeding to Zanzibar. It is said that owing to a quarrel with his father, who is the assistant to the Imam of Oman, Shaikh Mohamed had left his country for good and a anted, to go to Zanzibar to settle clown there. At the request of Shaikh Isa, however, Saiyid hadir, one of the Sultan 1 s uncle5 was able to persuade Shaikh j^ohamed to return to Oman. The latter returned to Qabil, his place of resi dence on the 24th October. m&amp;teokological. 7. The maximum and minimum temperature registered at the jPolioicai. Agency Muscat during the period under report was* — Maximum on 21st October 91.7° Minimum on 18th October 74.1° MISChLuANZOUS. 8. The average dollar rate during the period under review was Rs. 136 for 100 dollars. gwadur news. 9. Trade in Gwadur is exceedingly dull. The fishing season is now over and the fishermen are in a bad way. Merchants are discouraged with the lack of trade and many are talking of migrating to other places. 10. a large quantity of cotton has been imported from Persian Baluchistan by Baluchis, who will accept only silver when selling it and refuse to take notes, as a result most ol the silver has been taken away from Gwadur and there is a scarcity of coin in the town. political Agent &amp; H.ai's Consul. Muscat, the 12th November 1335SECRET. No. 17 of 1935. MUSCAT intelligence Summary for the period from 1st to 15th November 1935. ROYAL NAVY . 1. H.m.S. ’’Lupin’ 1 arrived on 13th. 2. H.M.S. ’’Deptford' arrived on her first visit to the Gulf on the 14th. She fired the national salute of 21 guns which was returned by the State Battery. SHIPPING. 3. No foreign ships called during the period under review. ROYAL AIR FORCE. 4. Reference paragraph 3 of last Summary. The Plight returned from Dhofar on the 2nd and left for Basrah via Sharjah on the 3rd. 5. 2 'Vincents” with Flt./Lt. Nuttall in command, arrived on the 5th and returned the same day to Sharjah. They came back on the 10th and returned to Basrah on the 11th, accom panied by the aeroplane which had been damaged in landing (vide para 3 of last Summary) and which had since been repaired with new parts sent from Basrah. 6. a Flight of 3’Vincents” with Flight Lieut. Evans in command arrived from Basrah on the 15th. BRITISH INTERESTS. 7. Reference paragraph 5 of last Summary. The Political Agent returned from Karachi on the 5th. 8 * Cable &lt;k Wireless Limited . Mr. P.E. Bunker, Manager of the Persian Gulf Section of the Cable Wireless Limited landed from s.S. 'Bankura” on the 15th. After inspecting the Cable and Wireless office and calling on the Political Agent, he continued his journey to Karachi by the same ship. 9. Lighting and Buoying . L.T. 'Nearchus' arrived on the 5th and renewed the gas cylinders in the lighthouse. She sailed forsailed for the Gulf on the 6th, 10. armistice Day . Two minutes silence was observed at the agency and by the British subjects of Muscat and Matrah on the 11th Hovember. LOCAL INTiaiKSTS, 11. The Compounder of the American Mission in Muscat left for Dhofar in the first week of November, taKing with him a supply of medicines etc. in order to open a dispen sary. It is said that Dr. Stonn of the .jnerican Arabian Mission, who is reported to be at present in Jedda, is leaving^for Dhofar at the invitation of the Sultan ana will stay there in charge of the Medical Work until nis Highness returns to Muscat in ~pril next, METEOROLOGICAL • 12. The maximum and minimum temperature registered at this agency during the period under report was*- Maximum on 1st November 87.9 Minimum on 8th November 70.4° miscellaneous, 13. The average price of dollars during t/iie period under review was Rs, 127 for 100 dollars. Political Afent oc H.M's Major, Consul. Muscat, the 19 th Novemoer 1936. Distribution as usual* \So,18 of 19^6 krf: MUSCAT inteiiigtiuce ^xua^ary ior the period froi,x 16th to JOth Novcanber lyju. Political ..gency 4 Consulate, muscat. 1. dafaraaoa paragraph 1 of last ^uiu.ary. K,ki,S« ^, Lupin' , sailed oa the 16th, S, Official tails between the x^olitlcal Agent a h.B.k's toneul, Muscat; ana the Com andtr of H ieptfoni M were exchanged on the i6Ui, auiu oetween the latter and ~&lt;aiyiu ^naiiab, the rei&gt;resentative of His liighneaa the .-uitan on tne 18 tn* o, “jeptford 1 * left for the Persian Uulf on the 19 tii* 3,S, 'Wietaenfels’* ai^rived at i atrah on the 21st from Basrah anu left for &gt;rc en via :ed aea on the following oay. a cargo of 27o2 pachage# dried fish was shipped by this vessel* An interesting fact has come to light in coxinection with the shipment of this cargo. The export of dried fish from Muscat which hitherto see formea one of tine principal articles of traue of the country has recently decreased to almost negligible quantities owing to the orders of the Berman Government restricting imports to those countries taking a certain quaiitity of uer.i ; -*n inanufactures* ^ince there is practically no market for German goods in Muscat owing to the influx of cheap Japanese articles the local trade with Germany had been severely hit. The present export of dried fish has been effected by means of an arrangement made oetween the leading Muscat merchant in this commodity ana a certain rersian merchants whereby the latter iiave undertaken, for a premium of 16A,- 2 - to import into Persia German goods of equal value to the dried fish exported from Muscat to Germany. HQYAL AIR FOHCii,. 5. Reference paragraph 6 of last Summary. The Flight returned to Basrah on the 16th. BRITISH IhTBiibSTS. 6. The flag at the Agency was half masted on 25th November being the funeral day of Lord Jellicoe. JuQCAL INTMiSLTS. 7• Sheikh Khamis bin Hilal al Ma t ja , al ) Sheikh of Masirah Island arrived on the 15th and left on the 18th. He came in connection with the Royal Air Force stores at Masirah. METEOROLOGICAL. 8. The maximum and minimum temperatures registered at this Agency for the period unaer report were:- maximum on 16th November 86.5* Minimum on 26th November 70.7* MISCELLANEOUS. 9. The average price of dollars during the period under report was Hs.127 for 100 dollars. GiALUR NEWS. 10. A proclamation was issued on 9th November by a^L order of the Amin of Gustoms that^ fishermen must in future bring the whole of their catches irrespective of where taken, in to Gwadur port for sale and no.'where else. The object of this order is understood to be to try anri increase the Custom*s Revenues which have decreased considerably. d / &gt; / C. Political Agent &amp; H.n.M's Consul Muscat, 2nd December 1935. Maj or, Muscat. A USUAL DISTRIBUTIONSEGRiST Ko, 19 of 1935. MUSCAT Intelligence Suiamary for the period from 1st to 16th December 1935. koyal NAVY. !• H.M.S. rt Deptford n arrived on the 12th and left for Gwadur on the following day. SHIPPING. 2. No foreign ships called during the period under report. HOYAL AIH FQBCE. 3. One ••Victoria 11 arrived on the 3rd and returned to Iraq on the 5th. 4. A Flight of 3 Vincents' 1 , Squadron Leader Fogarty in command, arrived from Iraq on the 3rd and returned to Iraq on the 4th. 5. Air Vice-Marshal W.G.S. Mitchell, C.B., C.B.L., D.S.O., M.C., ...F.C., Air Officer Commanding Iraq, visited Muscat on the 3rd as a passenger in one of the ’‘Vincents’*. He returned to Iraq on the 4th. 6. Lieutenant J.A. Hasler, ft.E., attached to Hoyai ^ir Force, arrived on the 3rd. He is preparing materials for conveyance to Masirah Island to build a permanent petrol store on the new landing ground there. 7. A Flight of 4 M Vincents’* arrived from Iraq on the 6th and returned on the 9th. BRITISH INTLRQSTS. 8. Mr. F.a. Todd, H.B.M*s Vice-Consul Bushire arrived on his annual commercial tour of the Gulf on the 6th and left for Bushire on the 11th. 9. Mr. H.i*. Majid, I.C.3., of the Punjab Commission arrived on the 3rd on a private tour of the Gulf and left for Iraq on the 11th. 10. Major R.P. Watts, I.,.., Political Agent &amp; H.M*s Consul Muscat left for Gwadur in H.M.3. “Deptford** on the 13th. MHTBOROLOGICAL.1 METEOROLOGICAL. 11. The maximum and minimum temperatures during the period under report werei- o Maximum on 4th December 85.7 o Minimum on 9th December 65,0 MISCELLANEOUS. 12. The average price of dollars during the period unaer review was Rs. 121 for 100 dollars. GWADUR NEWS. 13. It is reported that large quantities of cotton are being imported into Gwadur from Persian Baluchistan and are being sold at high rates. 14. Local merchants are said to have suffered severe losses on the last two consignments of fish despatched to Colombo. kajor, Political i-tg ent &lt;£ H.M's Consul, muscat political agency &amp; H.B.M»s Consulate, Muscat, the 20th December 1935. Distribution as usual.SECRET. Ho.20 of 1935 / f x **• '**“4'* J* MUSCAT Intelligence Summary for the period from 17th to 31st December 1935. RUfAD HAVY. !• Reference paragraph 1 of last Summary. H.M.S. H Deptford n returned from Gwadur on the 17th and sailed for the Gulf the same evening. SHI11IHG. 2. Japan . S.S. 'Ohiomaru” of the Yamashita Steamship Company on her return voyage from Ihe Gulf called at Muscat on the 28th and landed 6,000 bags cement. ao T -&amp;L air force. 3. Reference paragraph 6 of last Summary. Lieut. J.A. Hasler, R.E.,left by Air for Masirah on 19 th. 4. One 'Valencia” arrived from Iraq on the 17th and left for Masirah on the 19th returning to Muscat on the 21st. It departed to Iraq on the 22nd. 5. A flight of 3 'Vincents” Flying Officer Allsop in Command arrived from Iraq on the 28th and left for Masirah on the 29th returning to Muscat the same day. RAi'l'loH INTERESTS. 6. Reference paragraph 10 of last Summary. ilie roli ti cal Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat, returnee from Gwadur in h.M.3. H Deptford M on the 17th. ^ Captain G. JByard, the newly appointed Commandant of the Muscat Levy Corps arrived from England on the 26th, and assumed charge the same day. Accompanied by the Political iigent he called on Saiyid Shahab, the Representative of ras Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, the afternoon of his arrival. -LL&gt; 'd,-&gt; j-i 'iAiUj tj To . 8. The ^azi of Dhofar recently arrived in Muscat and left shortly after for Lingah- his native town. it is understood that Ihe tiazi had been dismissedby His HigHness on account of railing objections to the proposed demolition of a mosque in DHofar. 9. The Ramdhan Id was celebrated in Muscat and Matrah on the 28th and a salute of 21 guns was fired* The Agency flagstaff and the Sultans forts were dressed. The political Agent paid the Id visit on His Highness* s representative on the 30 th* MBTEOHOLUGIQAX. 10* The maximum and minimum temperatures recorded at the Agency during the period under report were*- ilaximum on 23id December 80° Minimum on 18th December 65° .20 cents of rain fell on the 31st December. MISGExXAHXOUb . 11. The aveiage price of dollars during the period under review was jus. 115/8 per 100 dollars. Ma j or, Political Agent Sc H.B.M* s Consul,Muscat. political Agency Sc H.JB.M* s Consulate, Eu sea t, the 5 th J anua ry 19 36 • Distribution as usual</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000083_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/356</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000083</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/356</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File [XI A/14] Political - Muscat Diaries'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-09-06T22:05:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (83 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 85; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains the daily political diaries of the Political Agent in Muscat. It includes information categorised under the condition of the country, arrivals and departures of naval and commercial ships, movement of British representatives, missionary enterprises, military and civilian aviation and other subheadings. Unlike previous files in the same series, this file's diary entries include some new subheadings such as 'Local Interests' and 'British Interests'.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Political affairs</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Oman</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000083#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>