<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001a1_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T02:35:45.787Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Pi —mmmm mmmmmmmmmrn COPY. (E 7567/608/34) British Legation Tehran* 13th December, 1935 Uy dear Oeorge, My despatch No. 52£ of the 26th November related a few of the latest stories about our rnillionai re 'nonaron. I now learn that he has ordered from a Dutch firm a motor yaoht costing 5^,000 florins. This yacht is to tr ^ .r the Shah from one port in the Caspian to another. It f s headquarters will be at Pahlevi. I also hear that nearly 13 million are to be spent In the next few yeara in developing Bander Shahpur ae a naval base to take the plaoe of Jtohamierah. The Dutch are well in tne running for this oontraot. You will remember that a Dutch firm (The Netherland Port and Harbour Works, Amsterdam) is hue constructing a port at the plaoe now called No-Shahr formerly Deh-No on the Caspian coast. Yours ever, (Stfd.) Victor Mallet. GW*, iiendel, Hsr., C.K.C., The foreign Office*3. I shall accordingly &gt;e glad If you furnish me uith a report fpon the present position ^ith regard to the inpoS'^tetion of goods t&gt; 7 t?6y of l/johasK^ex^h Bandair Shahpur respectively* together Bitheay li^foraation \?hich you can obtain concerning the radii ties available for shipping at the latter port* and uiih your obaervatione upon the deal, mb ill ty* having reg^rl to the sens idem t lone advanced in paragraph 2 ct foreign )ffioc Qc^somndus ^ ^S4/6b i 84,/3‘V‘ of BeceH&amp;er 9th herein# of taaicing representations to the l^ereion Government regard 1 g conditions at that port© 4» 1 an sending a copy thia despatch to His i/taJesty^Q didba^aador at Bigdad# in v ,er? of the possible bearing of thi© matter on the ceiesiton of ereo^Iraqti relatione in the Shatt&lt;*el^Arab a 2 ©Ki# ^it i greet tvuth and regard# 8ir&lt;. Your obedient Servant# (For the sroz»etary of State) IXV £- 15030/1V35, rsum C. 8TRIC4C 0 CO. LTi&gt; #f 117-121 Street, LOU&amp;Q#, K.C.3, 19th Sorember, 1955. Z£jU&amp;&amp;^%.kmtio&amp; The Ooaptroller-Generel, Depart: ent of Qvmram&amp;t Trade, 9-H-, Street, X#C. 2 . Deer Sir, Bender Shehpour le now the official ©rt of dleelierge for ell General 4erehandlse dess lined for Xr+n also stores and Equipment tor account of the Iranian Boremment lueludln^ Iren Helleeye* The facilities at Bandar Bbahpear for the discharge of vesaela with cargo for the i^ort are restricted to a Jetty which will aocouasodate one veaael only. This Jetty la in each a bad state of repair that the atnoat care haa to be exercised in putting a reesel alor*gaid* to avoid the danger of apringing the Jetty and ad doing damage to the Railway aetala thereon. Originally there waa a steam mmm on this Jetty whieh haa been aent to hwax, proa inably for repair, but no information oaa be obta liied ae to the date of its return* Apart fmm the Jetty there ere only two ightere available, one of which la useless for cargo owing to its Icahy condition* The other lighter can take 150 tone, and la flttad with a derrick and hand winch. With only one steamer in the art, the rate of discharge la unsatisfactory, but aa la now a fre uent oaeurrance with several steamers arriving about the same tine the resulting delay haa he some a serious matter* fe venture therefore to ask you If it la possible to have the position reprseented to the Iranian Authorities at ieheran through the proper channels*Hi . . '.■«*»* i. - . tvm*! Xt la poaalbli tba Itmnlaa Authorltlca are not aware of the etete of affairs existing st the - ort the/ hswe oreated to handle all Imports into Iran and which will certainly hare an adverse influe nee on the trade to that *wrt unless props r fa el 11 ties are provided to deal with the cargo for discharge there* Yours faithfully* For raMat c. *muc&amp; a ou* imu » (Agd«; ••••«,*«•»***••••The Foreign Office present their ooapXl .ente to the Depertnent of Orereee* Trede «nd» with reference to the letter 9 e Morandw Ho. 16055/1^ of B9th ^weaher, regerdirsg the facilities for the discharge of cargo at the port of Bandar shehpur# desire to eat^lain that this port does not fall within the eeope of the negotiations now proceeding Between Iraq, and Persia regarding their eotmon frontier# nor within the waters which it is hoped to Bring under the control of the proposed shatt-el-AraB Conservancy Board. 2. In general the Foreign Office would prefer not to urge the Barslan Oover ^ent to undertake improvements at Bandar Shi^hpur which night have the ultiaate effect of attracting chipping fro&amp; the ahatWl«-AraB. They would not however feel justified on these grounds in refusing to take eueh steps on Behalf of British shipping usi g the port ss would Be pemisslBle in alullar circuustances slsewhere# provided# they can Be satlaf led that this shipping cannot# without losing cargo to its rivals# oaks us# of any other port# or alternatively that moat of this shipping also proceeds to the l h»tt-cl~ ra*B, either Before or after discharging at B&amp;ndar tfhahpor. 5. Before sending instructions to His hajeaty’a Minister, therefore# the Foreign Office would Be glad to receive further information regarding Messrs. £trick and Coapany 9 * statement that ^haamerah is now the 'official 'port/'port of di &amp; charge for getmrtkl »«rctondl&lt;i« **• It is undei'^tood that all military vnd other as tor ial ordered by the •rslsn OoY«rii»ent f ana a{«tur*lly all railway mate rial f vast be shipped to that port# and it la no doubt the desire ot the Arslan Ooverment to eneourage its use generally* Bat the Foreign Office are not clear whether the shipping company*a statement means that official Instructions hove been leaned ranking it obllgetory for general merchandise* or certdn elaasos of general nerclmndise# to be la tided at Bandar i&amp;ahpur instead of )* 0 hammerah# or nerely that such cargo can be landed there and that certain facilities In the way of special shipping dues# reduced landing charges# etc. &gt; are obtainable if it is so landed* 4» The Foreign Office would be glad to receive the further ©bservat om of the hopmHMwl of &lt; versos* Trade in the light of the considerations advanced in the present atemorandum* POKEm* OFFICE# S*V*I. 9th Be eerier# 1930*1A0MA93*. 0 OHPX 01 TXAL. KXIKOlAVlVli In their eonfidential to the Impart sent of orereeae Trade (X 6984/6984/^) on the subject of e plaints node by ^aers* : triek and Coapany regarding the faoilitiee for the discharge of cargo at the Port of dander h&amp;hpur, the Foreign Office stated that before sending instructions to El a Majesty 9 * Minister at Tehran they would appreciate the receipt of further particulars regarding Messrs* s trick and Co pany's statesaenta that 4*mdar uhahpur is now the official port of diacharge for general merchandise. g. As a result of further enquiries Irt the sane quarter the position appears to be that, aecordbg to kesara. ttrlek and Company, the Iranian Government is endeavouring (although no official regulations are known to exist on the subject/ to divert all possible traffic il«e* not certain classes of asrchandlee only to their new port and railway, and are apparently influencing shippers to route their traffic vld Bandar hahpur by mctriode of persuasion that the shipowner cannot well evade. Moreover, traffic cannot be routed viS loimmmr&amp;h since navigation on the Karun Elver is si s standstill owing to the closing of the Gustos* Mouse at Ahwss. !4esam. trick and Company are quite definite upon the feet that that Custom© house has been closed. 3. Another consideration that might be adduced is thatif. owing to congestion m% bandar ahsiipur, eaarB. atriok and Company war* foraad to carry ilia cargo for that port on to Haara and discharge It there they would hero to hear the expense of re-forwarding the cargo beak to B&amp;ndar hahp\u*. 4 . It is hoped that the information now supplied nay be considered a sufficient basis upon which to sand instruc tions to his Majesty's Minister with a view to eliciting what ia th actual state of affairs at Bandar haiipur. (mud.; Department of overseas Trade# 55# Old ueen Street# j ondon# S* i # 19th December, 1955#COK/IDENTIAL. Enclosure in Foreign Office covering letter dated 7th January 1936, No.E.77/77/34. (E77/77/34). NO DISTRIBUTION. Cypher telegram to Sir A. Clark Kerr (Bagdad). Foreign Office, 6 th January 1936. 11.30 p.m. No.l Saving* Following from Mr.Rendel. My letter E.7429 of January 2nd. Shatt-el-Arab. In your discussions with Irakis you will no doubt bear in mind possibility that if Persians do not obtain adequate share in control of Shatt-el-Arab as proposed in draft Conservancy Convention they may well decide to intensify development of Bundar Shahpur even if this involves sacrificing interests of Mohammerah and Abadan. In that event they might even succeed in obliging Anglo- Persian Oil Company to ship their oil from Bundar Shahpur instead of from Abadan, and effect might be most serious not only on economic position in the Shatt-el-Arab as a result of withdrawal of tanker traffic but also in other obvious directions. (This danger was certainly regarded as real in 1932, when Elkington showed me confidentially detailed plans which Anglo-Persian Oil Company had prepared for taking oil to Bundar Shahpur for shipment, should developments make this necessary, but this should of course not be quoted). It seems clear that Persians in their present frame of mind might not hesitate to .sacrifice Persian/Persian ports on Shatt-el-Arab if they felt they were not being given a square deal over participation in the Conservancy Board - Iraqis would therefore be well advised in their own interests not to be too niggardly in their proposals to Persian Government over participation in proposed Board. Addressed to Bagdad No.l Saving; repeated to Tehran No.l Saving.P.Z. 535/36. EXTRACT PROM DIARY No .11 OP 1935 OP H.B.M’S. CONSULATE FOR KHUZISTAN, AHVAZ, FOR THE MONTH OP NOVEMBER 1935. ^tO 1 ?• Ports - Bandar Shahpur. In view of the delays experienced by vessels calling at Bandar Shahpur, particularly if the visit coinciaes with that of any ship landing military stores, the Hansa Line and Messrs.Strides have come to an arrangement with the Customs authorities whereby goods consigned to Bandar Shahpur may be landed at Khorramshahr or at least unloaded into barges there. The Railway authorities, who thus lose their freight, are naturally opposed to the cutting out of Bandar Shahpur and various merchants have been moved to lodge objections to the proposal on the ground that the shipping documents are not in order, and that complications are bound to arise.&lt;@ v.z. 636'i t COPY. (E 5755/4793/34) NO^ 378/20-2/1. BRITISH LEGATION TEHRAN. 9th September, 1933. Dear Department, Many thanks for your letter E 4793/4792/34 of August 22nd about Bander Shahpur and Mohammerah. 2. We agree that there is very little likelihood of the Persian Government abandoning Bander shahpur altogether, but v/atkinson, who is on a visit here, states that they are meeting with many difficulties there. The quays and jetties apparently need re-building and the sea-bed in their immediate vicinity is silting up. If Persia got satisfaction about the Shatt-el-Arab no doubt she would feel inclined to rely more upon Mohammerah, but we imagine the chances of agreement with ^raq are still fairly remote. It is quite possible that in view of these difficulties. Bander Shahpur will be kept in reserve, so to speak, as an 'all Persian water' port for the importation of military stores and for use in emergency. The withdrawal of the Anglo-persian Oil Company from Mohammerah is also making a number of houses available there for the use of the Persian authorities (the Navy seems to get the lion's share) and facilitates development. 3. The Commercial Secretary is reporting separately a 300 metres, call for tenders for the construction of a three hundred metre concrete jetty at Bander shahpur, which does not look as if its abandonment were contemplated. 4. We are sending a copy of this letter to Ahwaz. Eastern Department, The Foreign office yours ever, CHANCERY.PORKIGW OPFICI, 3.W.1 (S 4793/4793/34) Confidential* 2£nd August, 1933 J Dear Chancery, You may be interested in the accompanying extract from the Imperial uanlc of Persia’s Mohammerah Marlcet Report of the liith July about the future of Mohammerah and Bander Shahpur* We were given it by Eldrid, of the Band’s London office, who explained orally that he found it difficult to believe the statement that Bander Shahpur would be scrapped. Yours, etc., EASTERN DEPARTMENT The Chancery British Legation Tehran.M’HaCT FROM Tlia XttegKia. OF ?gRSU MOtUMtiiSflAH MAiU-gT REPORT PAm 12TH JULY. 1W4 . Mg' CPSTOtfj' f’RSMloSS . plans have been drawn up and submitted this week to Teheran for the construction of new Customs Offices and go- downs on the present site* The buildings are to be semi circular In shape with go-downs underneath and offices above and are estimated to cost Rials 7,500,000* Rumour has It that the work will be carried out under the supervision of A*P.0*C. engineers. A jetty is also to be built to enable ships to come along side. Apparently the idea of the Government is to be in a position to levy port dues as at present ships discharge In mid-stream which Is Iraq water, a subject which has caused considerable controversy between the Governments of Persia and Iraq for some time past. It is also rumoured a railway line to Ahwaz will be constructed the site for the station being behind the dank bungalows. The Port of bunder Shapoor has apparently proved to be of little value and will apparently ultimately be scrapped. The present Customs premises are totally inadequate for the volume of merchandise imported and exported at this port.&lt;T 63 ) 225 . No. British Legation, His Majesty's Repres compliments to Tehran, ay 6 th 33 19 . His Majesty's Principal SecretarjT-oT STareT7f•Fereign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents Port mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Charges at Bandar Shahpur. Referenee:- Despatch No. 28 dated 18th April 1933 from His Majesty’s Consul* at Ahwaz*?io. 28 BRITISH CONSULATE 18th April 1932. Sir I h&amp;y® tht* honour to forward herewith translation of the temporary regulations in force rernin^ Port Chargee at Bandar Shahpur together with pro fon&amp;a charges on reseele calling there. general traffic there hue been h small amount of export trade by vessels calling at Bandar rhahpur with railway and other government stores, as reported in tay monthly hi ary, a beginning has been made on premises for the customs Administration, but it ir understood that worx has for the time bean stopped, ns the present Railway Administration has failed tc come to an understanding with the Ministry of finance with regard to taxing over the buildings when completed. 3. a rj ort S&amp;nit&amp;ry Officer has been appointed and is in residenoo at Baud&amp;r$hshpur. Various complaints have been mad© at the unnjoaessary delay caused to vessels by ♦ Vw 4 #n '4* -P 1 4 ** 4 Ak *1 Though the Port has not yet been thrown open to Your most obedient H.B.fc* C BSUL ?Oh I have the honour to be Sgd. A.E.Watkinson hutnole servant Sir His Britannic Hajesty 9 * Minister e to., e tc., e to., British legation, TehranH Traaelfttioti* i* CftXiju irai*ort«A oy «ii ire®o©l« will pay a %otzl X^x ot Z kr*iQfe p»tr kb^Sfar ot 100 mounds or betmansj ( 2 t krans J ort aad iiota^a ?••«, nad 10 oh'his for ort- S*.L:ite.rjr services). exported «iil ^ay a tax of 3 kraoe por 100 sutuads for I'ort and Pilotage P'S 48. £. 'vary Yasc-ul aatari^; th- -ort aiih sargo am leaving it with c^go will pay tha taxes raoutioasd in ; ©otion 1 in rsspoot of ©very kharTar of oar^o oouei,;aad to the *ort of Pahlovi. Z. very veecel enterin,; th« Port in b&amp;iiaft will pay 10 ohchlff per registersi ton on catering and on io»ving. 4. 'very' rasssi anterior ths ort with otr jo and leavin.; in Ballast, or antarin^ in oailast and leaving with cargo, will pay only once on entry or on departure the tax of £ krnzz per kh^rv^r of cargo Owmsigaed to ths Port of whievi, huh on condition that tho as&amp;duat of tax ptiiu on the cargo is not loss than the e.&amp;ount of U.x pegr»hitf on the tonneg- of the vessel. Otherwise the vesssl will be required to psy the tonnags tax (10 ohahis per ton) without paying the tax on the cargo. 5. ''very vesfcel of which the cargo is consigned to Ports of the Caspian See, and which unloads less th^n 4 tons of cargo at th*.; port of ’ahlevi will p&amp;y 1C ohahia per registered toanags, bcin* oonaiderad as a ?««&amp;•! in ballast, if it unloads 4 tons or raore, the r ort authorities will be at liberty to levy either 10 oh&amp;hi* per registered ton or 3 krins for each kharv&amp;r of cargo consigned to the Port of Tahlevl. ^he ohoioc of these methodE of o-iloulation will be dictated by the financial interest of the Persian Government. 6 . The nsceseary instructione will be given to the doctor in charge of Sanitary ^orvicce of the Port that ^he /shallCOPY **). 13. CONr&gt;UIATE, AH. A?,. © PelDruary 27th, 1936. Sir, With reference to your despatch No. 3 (111/3/36) of February 4, 1936, regarding the port of Bandar Shahpur, I have the honour to report that, so far as I am aware, that port neither is nor ever was 'the official port of discharge for all merchandise M destined for Iran”, as stated by Messrs. F. C. Btrick and company in their letter of November 19 last to the Department of Overseas Trade. Much of the information contained in the Department of Overseas Trade Memorandum No. 15055/1933 of i&gt;ecember 19 is also quite out of date. If the word 'an' were substituted for the word ’the' in Messrs, strick’s letter, the statement would be correct, at: Bandar Shahpur is now supposed to be equipped to deal with all types of cargo, whereas formerly only military and other Government stores and railway material were landed there. 2. ^hat Messrs. F. C. i&gt;trick and Company no doubt mean is that every effort has been made during the/ His Britannic Majesty’s Charge d*Affaires, British Legation, Tehran.the lest year to induce importers to use the port of Bandar Shahpur as is erident from the instructions to shippers in the United Kingdom referred to fcy the Foreign Office in paragraph 2 of their despatch No. 9 of January 7. Kiat these instructions have not had any appreciable effect is shown by the statistics of ships calling and imports at Bandar Shahpur and at Khorramshahr during 1935# which are attached. 3. Of the 32 British vessels which landed cargo at Bandar ahahpur# 24 belonged to the stride Line or Kllerman’s City Line and associated lines, while 172 British ships called at Khorramshahr during the same period, of which Messrs. Strides agent dealt with over 50. Since last October, the British India Steam Navigation Company’s 'Blow Mail' steamer has called once a month at Bandar Shahpur, landing a very small amount of cargo. Almost without exception, all British vessels calling at Bandar Bhahpur before or after discharging there proceeded to Korramshahr. Most other vessels also called at both ports or at Basra to pick up return cargo. 4. The vast bulk of cargo dealt with at Bandar Shahpur consists of shipments of military and railway material by the Hansa Line boats, which call there twice a month and sometimes more often. Japanese vessels, for which the Hansa Line representative acts as clearing agent, come next in importance, landing cement for railway construction and small consignments of general merchandise. 5. Facilities for handling importations at Bandar/Bandar Shahpur arc ae described by Messrs* Stride and Company. The one small jetty ie in need of repair; a somewhat antiquated steam crane is used on a truck which is run up and down the railway between Bandar Shahpur and Salehabad mostly at the behest of the military authorities; two very inadequate old lighters, which I believe were supplied by Messrs. Ltrick them selves, are shortly, it is said, to be increased to five; the rate of discharge is most unsatisfactory and if more than one vessel is there at a time there is every sort of irregularity, priority being in any case always demanded for military stores. The coolies are under the sole control of the Customs Department, which is not always c satisfactory arrangement. 6. The authorities who are aware of this state of affaire at the .Port, which was created with a view to handling all imports by the Persian Gulf, are now for the most part in prison. Nonsense is from time to time published in the Press about this up-to-date modern port, and it is not long ago since I heard that one of the l^eputies for Ahwaz refused to believe that there is no public telephone nor Post Office at Bandar Shahpur. He had not been to see. Many schemes have been produced but nothing whatever is done. There is not even any fresh water at Bandar Shahpur yet, which is indispensable before any serious improvements can be carried out. I was in Bandar Shahpur about a month ago and I could see no change whatever in the appearance of the place compared with two years ago. 7. Since/7. Since the Cuatoiae fire at Khorramehahr last August, the Ahwaz Cub toms House has “been open to ueal with a limited amount of up-country traffic, under the direction of the Provincial Director at Khorramehahr. More recently importers and shipping agents have been informed verbally that the Cuetoms Office at Ahwaz is open for all purpo.eB, and through cargo has now been acceptea here for eome time, though no public notice seems to have been issued to that effect* Probably the Custom^. Department dare not issue such a notice, as it would destroy the effect of the Bandar Shahpur propaganda which is by order of the All Highest* More recently still, the office of the Provincial Director of Customs at Khorramshahr has been abolished. At present the local Directors of Customs at Ahwaz and at Khorramshahr have each been placed directly under the Customs Department in Tehran and both the premises and staff at Ahwaz have been increased with a view to dealing with more through cargo here. 8. hether this state of affaire will continue, which is welcomed by the local merchants and forwarding agents for firms in the interior, depends partly on the settlement of another problem which has been created by the Naval Authorities. 9. A notice was issued some time ago by the Khorramshahr Naval port Office, which claims to have Jurisdiction over all traffic on the kiver Karun as far as Ahwaz, to the effect that the total breadth of tugs and barges may not exceed 14 metres. This makes it Impossible/iapoBsible to tow even one barge alongeide a tug. Hitherto, the &gt;nglo Iranian oil Company, the Iran Transport Company (Mesopotamia Iran Corporation), and others have been towing barges to port and to starboard and sometimes others astern. The Imperial Iranian Navy hat decided that, in future, they should all be towed astern, which is said to be impracticable owing to the shallows end bends in the river. This interferes seriously with the existing arrangements of the Anglo Iranian Oil Company, and, in the case of general merchandise, I am told that it will have the effect of trebling the freight from Khorramehahr to Ahwaz. rossibly this is another manoeuvre to drive shipping back to Bandar Shahpur with consequent benefit to railway revenues. The shipping interests concerned are fighting this strenuously. Meanwhile the regulation is only enforced in the Karun at Khorramshahr up to a point above the usual moorings of the Iranian sloops. As &amp;r as there, for a distance of some three miles, barges must be towed singly. 10. The question of the desirability of represent ations being made to the Iranian Government regarding conditions at Bandar :hahpur is hardly one on which I am qualified to offer an opinion. So far as I can juuge, there is now nothing to prevent British shipping from using the &gt;ort of Khorrarashahr and landing cargo consignee to the interior, or trans-shipping through cargo for Ahwaz there, without running the risk of losing cargo to its rivals. Possibly Messrs. Strick ant company’s agent at Khorramshahr, who is an Iranian/Iranian euTaject, may hold other views, being peculiarly open to the methods of persuasion, to which hit principals refer. 11. The question of Bandar Shahpur is not without interest to the Anglo Iranian Oil Company, with whom it might profitably be discussed. For some time the Iranian government has been endeavouring without success to inuuce the Company to take a practical interest in its envelopment. The matter will assume greater importance wnen they open up the Southern Area, situated to the North and Fast of Bandar chahpur. It is perhaps in this connexion that the issue of the present negotiations between the Governments of Iran and Iraq may have some bearing. 12. A picture of Bandar Shahpur would not be complete without reference to the local representative of the Hansa Line, a German called ^engoborsky, who has spent most of his time there curing the last year or more. He has considerable influence there and it is largely due to him that the Port .ervices function at all. He is the only European permanently connected with the place and is in close touch with his colleague, i another German, at Bushire. v Both of them are familiar with the whole coast anc hinterland. Reference to their activities has been made from time to time in ray Monthly Diary. Mr. iengoborsky, for reasons of hie own, personal commercial, and possibly others, would much like to see improvements at Bandar hahpur, for which he would no doubt/doutt claim much of the credit. It is not improbable that he himself inspired Messrs. Strides to refer the subject to London* 15. A question which should be considered in connexion with this latest problem of the Persian Gulf is perhaps, therefore, not so much the risk ol lo^in^ trade to our rivals, who already have most of it in their hands for reasons well known to those at home, but of giving political support to other interests shoulo British shipping be led to concentrate entirely on the bhatt-al-Arab. 14. I enclose a spare copy of this uespatch in case it may be of interest to His Majesty^ Ambassador at Baghdad to whom 1 normally send direct copies of all reports on commercial subjects. I have, etc. (Signed) A. E. ATKINSON. H. B. M* S CONSUL FOR KHUZISTAN.(K 54/346/84) MM JUk ±2£. JtmL ac »•• the Foreign Of Hoc present taeir oompltmentk to the l epartracnt of ovcreea^ Traoe and # with reference to taeir letter K 740^6964/^ of tae ^th January, encloaint; a copy of a despatch accret aeo to ai^ jeetgr' e ^.init ter at Tehran regarciin^, the facilltiee for the t?charge of vesae is at the port of Bandar hahpur , traneait the accompanying copy of a deepatch froa Hia ^aja*ty'e Charge d*Affairea in reply forwarding a copy of a despatch from His i^ajoaty** Consul at awes on this uibject* 2* Subject to the observation^ of tiie iepartment of Oversee* Trade, the Foreign Office are inclined to snare Mr. hutler 1 * opinion, as expresses/expressed in paragraph &amp; ot his despatch, that in view of the position now revealed, no sufficient grounds exist for diplomatic representations to the Persian Zor&amp;nsmnt in this matter. FORE IG i 9 3. .1. &amp;9th April, 1936P.Z. 1360/36. a EXTRACT PROM DIARY OP H.B.M'S. CONSULATE POR KHUZISTAN, AHWAZ, POR THE MONTH OP DECEMBER 1935. 447. Railways. Mr.Park, the Chief Engineer at the Ministry of Roads and Communications, accompanied by Aqa Mushar, the Director of the Railways Department at Ahwaz, proceeded to Bandar Shahpur with three Dutch Engineers in connection with plans for improving the port there. It is reported that the Iranian Government has decided to spend a considerable amount of money on this, but for the present it is decided to purchase two large barges for unloading of merchandise and the Manager of the Kansa Line has undertaken to import them from Germany*COPY (B 345/345/34) r J. 1 • Extract from Tehran Intelligence Summary No« 26 for period ending 28th December» 1935 * B&gt; (Ports ) In view of the delays experienced by vessels at Bandar Shahpur, particularly if the visit coincides with that of any ship landing military stores, the Hansa Line and Messrs. Strides have come to an arrangement with tne Custom authorities whereby goods consigned to Bandar Shahpur may be landed at Khorramsuahr or at least unloaded into barges there. The Railway authorities, who thus lose their freight, are naturally opposed to the cutting out of Bandar Shahpur and various merchants have been moved to lodge objections to the proposal on the grounds that the shipping documents are not in order, and that complications are bound to arise.With Mr. Baggallay*8 compliments M/vo 'b0&lt;£ • a040/S}040/:H) . Foaxios omox, s.sr.i. S»th May, 1940. Hy d«ai&gt; r:caiaby 9 1 under, t4** &amp; tht&gt;t about a ya^r ago Eaaara. Kalia and Company, a firm of British contractor , approaohod the Export Cradlte Oasrantac Dapart^ont with regard to I a contract ehich they thought they might be able to secure for reelamtlon work ir and around the port of Bandar flhfthpor in Iran* a* At thr»t the ort Oredite Qua rente# Department went into tl*te question anu aao&amp;rtalned that, ao moat of the expenditure would be made in local eurremc./ on account of local labour, and ae tlie export of Mi ted Kingdom good® wee only involved to a very email ext nt, the trF*naaetion vaa not one vhleh they could aeslat under the poeere which ttsey at that ti e poaeeaeed. 5* The aai?Hs f ira has now again raised the matter* l understand that the Export Credit# Guarantee Departrwnt atlll eee the iMe difficult, about giving any guarantee or indemnity in connexion with thi* contract, but in view of the interest which Hie &amp;a&gt;ety*e Government are now showing in the strategic use a of the railway leading north from Bandar 3hahpur they are anxi^ua, before turning do*n the fina , a approach again, to aaocrtaln whether othsr departnettta might wish then to interest themselves in the qovation for reasona aimil&amp;r to tho^e for which they have been aeked to aupport the contract for the construction of part of the Tehren-Tabria railway* tfe^or A* * Wallaby, v/ar Office*&amp; 4* At one tlKHJ the An* Xo-Xrenlen Oil eere atrongly urged by the Irenien Goirer? ^ ent to develop thie port on their behalf, but the expense, •ore £10,000,000 wee to bo borne by the Company end, ao far ee Z eia ewere, nothing h*a been done in the leat year or eo# Of eoeree, we h&amp;we little interest fra* the ommerelal point of view in the develepcaent of the port of Bandar 3hahpur, but X abound be grateful if you- would let rsie know whether, on atmtegio grounda# V\* Mur Office think it deairable, in view of the support which they are giving to the conet met ion of the railw&amp;v, thfct Hi a Maje«ty # a Oovemmcnt ahouid do anything to aaaiat in the development of Bandar ;hahpur* 5* I am aending a copy of thia letter to 3 omervllle»dmith at the Export Credita Guarantee Oerjartment, Bowie/ at the Treasury, and Ru* bold at the India Office* YOURS SINCERELYIn anfS MO .408 i». zT”! 7717 | 195 7 j 30th October,1^37. Sir, Mth roforenoe to say despatch 30.369 (392/30/37) of 24th September last,I have the honour to inform you that a notice was published by the Customs Administration in 'L# Journal de Teheran” of 12th October inviting tenders for the construction of a wharf (debaroadere) on the Karun Kiver at # Khorramshahr. A further notice was published on the 27th October in connexion with the construction of ’un grand debaroadere dans le Chatt-el-Arabe a ^rhorramahahr”. 2. It seems clear from these announcements that the Iranian Government have no intention of diverting trade on a large scale in the near future from the liar un to Bandar Shahpur and the railway. 3. I am sending copies of this despatch to the Department of overseas Trade.unnumbered t His Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz xfo.b3,to His Majesty^ Ambassador at Baghdad Mo.31. I have the honour to be with the highest respect, Sir, Your moot obedient, humble Servant, •» etc., (Signed) Hevile Butler. His Majesty'* ^ulster. THh FOKMiaa omen.( 3 ) COPY (E 600l/' 76 /34) Ho.369 (392/30/37) r ; 6946 1 193 7.. British Legation, n Tehran, 24th September, 1937, Sir, 'With reference to my despatch No.247 of the 3rd July, I have the honour to inform you that the Acting British Consul at Khorramshahr reports that the Sherkat Kashtiriani Karun continues to make suprisingly good progress. The new Company has succeeded in speeding up considerably the landing of cargoes from ships calling at Khorramshahr. Captain Stewart suggests that its success is due largely to the fact that it has the blessing of the local port authorities and therefore has not be contend with the innumerable petty delays and difficulties experienced by less fortunate Shipping Agents. Prom the point of view of British shipping firms the change may thus be regarded as beneficial, so far at any rate. But it is unfortunate that Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie and Company have lost what has been in the past a remunerative business. 2. At the same time there has been a considerable increase in the amount of goods cleared from the Customs, and the position in this respect has improved appreciably. Imports received at the Customs have also increased. This is attributed not to an increase of total imports into Iran, but to the fact that ships are now avoiding Bandar Shahpur owing to the very bad conditions prevailing there. Work/ The Right Honourable Anthony Eden, M. C. , M. P. , etc., etc., etc., The Foreign Office.r' Work on the new Customs buildings and warehouses at Khorramshahr, which was stopped some time ago when it was rumoured that the Khorramshahr Customs were to be made subordinate to those at Bandar Shahpur, has now begun again. 3. River transport on the Karun is now reported to be almost entirely in the hands of the Sherkat Kashtiriani Karun, which is v/orking this part of its business also with success. It has however no monopoly of river navigation, as opposed to transport from ship to shore at Khorramshahr. As far as I am aware, Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie and Company are still operating the tug ’’Shirin” for the Iran Transport Company. They have been given permission to tow two barges abreast until the 22nd December next. After that date they must comply with the new regulations limiting the total width of tugs and barges together to 14 metres. 4. Captain Stewart reports that there has been a notice able improvement in the attitude of the naval authorities at Khorramshahr in recent months. At the beginning of the year Colonel Bayendor and his brother Major Bayendor, the Port Officer, repeatedly interfered in shipping matters to the inconvenience of shipping firms, and it is satisfactory that they are now showing themselves more helpful. Interference in minor matters however continues, and recently shipping agents were ordered to employ only Iranian coolies instead of the Iraqi coolies formerly employed. Captain Stewart adds that the local authorities, and in particular the Naval Authorities, have recently shown a much more helpful attitude towards His Majesty’s Vice-Consulate. 5&lt; 3 &gt; 5. With regard to the congestion now existing at Bandar Shahpur, I am informed that the Iranian Government have recently signed a contract with 'Sofitee' the Swiss constructional firm hacked hy Messrs. Julius Berger, which obtained the contract for the Tehran Railway Station, for improvements at Bandar Shahpur at a cost of Rials 12,500,000 (£.156,250). The improvements are said to include a second berth to the existing jetty, which is to be reinforced by metal construction. 6. I am sending copies of this despatch to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Baghdad Ro.76 and to His Majesty’s Consul at Ahwaz No.46. I have, etc., (Sgd) H. J. Seymour.FILE C any further communication on this subject, phase quote No. /3+ ami address— not to any person by ttnu/v, but/to— * “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreij'n OiRce, London, S.W.t . O THE Under-Secretary of State 14 f Jm - V—' A-^iirs presents his compliments to S^c ^ c/2l&lt;£ ^ o and, by directional tln^ Secretary c&gt;f State, transmits herewith cop- x of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 2i, 193/. pf' Vi Reference to previous correspondence : -&lt;~o £~3*^2 ^ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER 1 Mo 31 5 AUG 1937 14—6130 Similar letter sent to 14649 (4)Copy (E 4122/76/34) No. 24 7 (392/^9/37) !'. Z. 5014 . p. -y I O / } BpiTISH LEGATION) TEHRAN. 3rd July, 1937. Sir, With reference to my despatch No. 183 of lay 20th transmitting a copy of a memorandum prepared by His Majesty*s Vice-Consul at Khorramshahr on the subject of the formation of the monopolistic Iranian Landing Company known as the Shirkat Kashtirani Karun, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a copy of a despatch By Captain Bazalgette reporting on the progress made during the first two months of its existence. 2. Although the company appears to have made a good start, it is as yet early to say whether its continued operation will prove satisfactory and in particular whether the new agreement mentioned in paragraph 2 of Captain Bazalgette , s despatch between the Company and the Customs will give satisfaction to the various shipping agents concerned. I have, etc. (Signed) H.J. Seymour. The Right Honourable Anthony Eden, M.C., M.P. etc., etc., etc. THE FOREIGN OFFICE.f No. 9/11/879. &lt; 3 ) British Vice-Consulate, Khorramshahr, (Iran), May the 22nd, 1937. Sir, I have the honour to submit the following report on the progress made by the Shirkat Kashtirani Karun during its first two months as a monopolistic landing company. 2. Contrary to expectation, the Shirkat is now functioning with creditable efficiency and economy. The new agreement approved by the Central Customs Authorities has not yet been published in Khorramshahr, but the Shirkat now admits its liabilities and responsibilities for cargo in its charge. Foreign Shipping Agents are satisfied with the 'boat-note” receipts signed by the Shirkat’s representative and so far no disputes have arisen, except for the outstanding receipt for the S.S. 'Bandar Shahpur” (my telegram No. 14 of 14th April 1937). 3. The success achieved by the Shirkat is largely due to the co-operation and help instituted this month by the Director of Customs, presumably as the result of orders from Tehran. Space has been found for cargoes where it was alleged there was no space before. Barges are unloaded into the Customs sometimes even the same day as the discharge of cargo from merchant ships. Such speed and efficiency is almost unprecedented. This economy in lighterage enables barges/ His Majesty’s Consul for Khuzistan, Ahwaz( 'barges to carry many times their previous monthly capacity, allowing the few available craft to cope with the cargo arriving and making a considerable saving per ton of cargo landed. Up to date there have been no delays to merchant ships on account of barge shortage. 4. In spite of the present success, it is too soon to say that it will be permanent. A few months ago it was thought that the Khorramshahr Customs Compound were already filled to capacity. Comparatively little merchandise has been cleared and forwarded up-country, although the Manager of the Imperial Bank of Iran tells me that his bank are doing considerable business in advances for the clearance of goods, but some time must elapse before the accumulation of years is cleared. 5. Further, I understand that in spite of a large office staff, the Shirkat has no proper system of accounting or office routine. Apart from Mirza Jellal Movaugher himself, the Shirkat has only two men with any experience of shipping. The remainder may be classed as hangers-on. Hiranand Hingorani, who was at one time with the Mesopotamia Iran Corporation, Ltd. and was dismissed under a cloud, confines himself to superintending the unloading of cargo at the ship’s side. A great deal of the efficiency of the Shirkat is due to his hard work, and it is unfortunate that he has been seldom able to keep straight in the past. The other, Navidi, (see para 4 of my despatch No. 9/ll/243 of 27th February 1937) has barely started work for the Shirkat, and although Mr. Spence and Mr. Battey report him to be a good interpreter and ratine clerk, he is not said to be an accountant. Mirza Jellal Movaugher has been trying to enrol Mr. Z.H. Khan, late of African &amp; Eastern/Eastern (Near East) Limited, but the latter appears to be waiting and watching before committing himself, although he has held charge of Mirza Jellal Movaugher’s private affairs during his recent visit to Tehran. Mirza Jellal Movaugher appears to see the weakness of the position, and has asked Messrs. African &amp; Eastern (Near East) Limited to help him to engage a cadre of trained shipping clerks in Basra. 6. Finally, the new agreement requires interpretation and Mr. Battey tells me that difficulties are likely to arise between the Customs, Shirkat, and Foreign Shipping Agents unless the details are settled in a spirit of give and take. I am, etc., (Sgd.) J.E.A. Bazalgette. Captain, His Majesty* s Vice-Consul.In any further communication on I hia subject, please quote No. and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretery of State,” Foreign OfRce, London, S.W. 1. THE Under-Secretary of State ! I P7, 3961 ioJC, ..EOTer^Vi Affaii4 presents his © comi ipliments ito ~ cr^ f’ftXc (JhjI**** ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop cC* of the under-mentioned paper^S* ' i/// Foreign Office, 1 6 JTN»B&gt;3j£ Reference to previous correspondence : f o. £ ?-T~7 &lt; if-)(&gt; ll&lt;p c-jt- f'C fZb- Description of Enclosure.'7 Copy. (3 3072/76/34). No. 183 ^31/19/37) . rj • ? r c 0 ^BRITISH LEGATION, TEHRAN. ^Oth May, 1937. Sir, With reference to my despatch No. 133 of Aoril 9th last, concerning the closure of the Ahwaz customs and also the more general question of congestion at the Gulf ports, I have the honour to transmit herewith a copy of an interesting despatch from His Majesty’s Consul at Ahwaz which has been written in reply to Mr. Butler’s letter No. 151/6/37 of February 20th, a copy of which was forwarded to Mr. Baggallay. 2. It will be observed that although Mr. Gardener considers it possible that at some future date Bandar Shahour may be destined to become the only Persian Gulf port for imports for North and Central Iran, there are at present no signs that the Ahwaz Customs house will shortly be closed nor, so far as he is aware, are active steps being taken to divert traffic from Khorramshahr to Bandar Shahour. Since that despatch was written, His Majesty’s Vice-Consul at Khorramshahr has, however, reported that he has heard from a reliable source that the customs house at Khorramshahr is to be transferred to Bandar Shahour and that the move is to be made as soon as possible. Caotain Bazalgette is nevertheless of opinion that large sums of money would have to be spent and considerable time would nave to elapse before Bandar Shahour would be capable of dealing- with the increase in shipping caused by such a move. Witn regard to the general question of congestion at The Right Honourable, Anthony Eden, M.C., M.P., etc., etc., etc., THE FOREIGN OFFICE. the/tne ru.lf ports ? 7 nave the honour to transmit* to you herewith a cony Of a memorandum which has been orepared by Captain . azal^ette clealin with the congestion at the h ho r rams ha hr 0 us tons j its causes and be oart it has nlayed in hr inline; aoou tne formation of t ie monopolistic Iranian Landing Company (Shirkat hashtirani harun^, 4c l am sending copies of this despatch to his majesty's Ambassador at baghdad Fo. 36 and to Kis Kajesty’s Consul at Ahwaz l‘o, 27 0 I i'iave ; etc, (Signed). IhJ SCYhOUihTTOo 50, ft- n ']y ; /' ' 'S ! - . . V.,' w ^ i 193 7 ^bMOWMaftinrJM „%+*'•*&gt;• ■ '****•*• BRITISH CONSULATE, AIT.VAZ, 17th A-^ril 1937 0 Sir, I have the honour to refer to !r. Butler’s letter to me No. 151/6/37 of the 20th February received on larch 21st last, calling for a report on the prospect of traffic being diverted from the port of Khorramshahr to Bandar Shahpur. 2 0 From recent despatches addressed to the legation you will nave learnt tnat the general chaotic conditions in the Customs and harbours of the Persian Gulf have been worsened by one action of the Iranian Navy in forming a monopolistic landing company at Khorramshahr with no effective guarantees of speedy despatch of ocean ships or of the safe delivery of the cargo they discharge. Just before this event the Strick and Hansa lines (being the largest shippers to Bandar Shahpur) had decided to restrict if not to refuse cargo for the ports of Bushire and Bandar Shahpur and to continue their traffic with Khorramshahr„ I imagine that t ue two companies had decided to continue their trade with iuhorramshanr oecause in that port at any event they had control of the discharge of their ships and so could prevent inordinate delays. row the situation in Khorramshahr is equally confused. With such a background of chaos and ineptitude it is difficult to trace any long term policy of the Iranian Government in determining the route to be followed/ Jc Seymour 3 Esquire, C. .G., Bis Britannic Tajesty’s finister, etc., etc., etc., Br i t i s h Leg a t i on, Tehran.V followed 'by future imports. All the views and inferences mentioned hereafter are therefore offered with all reserves. 3. It is certainly logical to assume that the Iranian Crovernment after creating a port, not on the Shatt-el-Arab, and linking it by rail to the forth had in* mind the prospect of canalising alonp that route all imports, destined for the interior and the i orth. As regards the meeting held at Ahwaz in Seotemoer last oetween the Governor General and the shipping agents, the account of it given in paragraph 2 of ! r. Butler’s letter under reference is confirmed by IT. Soence of Tesoers, except that a representative of Kespers was not nresent. I have been unable to see Mr. Wengoborski. No attempt would seem to nave been made since to enforce the use of Bandar Shahpur at the expense of Khorramshahr. I imagine this may have been because the limitations of Bandar Shahpur were recognised. 4. however when the Shah was recently in Khorramshahr he is reported to have asked why such quantities of cargo were discnarged in that port instead of in Bandar Shahpur. t am informed (out i cannot guarantee the information) that the provincial Direccor oi Customs at Khorramshahr and a high military officer explained that the capacity of Bandar Shahpur was limited. I am inclined to think that the Shah did not entirely accept this explanation when he visited Bandar Shahpur as a great deal of window dressing was done for his visit - cargo being piled up to give appearance of ample storage room etc. However as I have already reported the Shan ordered the prolongation, of the existing jetty to a total length of 300 metres to accomodate two ships alongside. Mr. Fritze of the Eansa Line also informed me that the jetty is to be/oe widened to oake two railway tracks 0 j suppose this will be oaid for oat of the item 5 million rials for ''building expenses at bandar Shahpur inscribed in this year’s budget. Larges and a tug have been ordered, as also twelve locomotives ana one hund.red railway trucks. 5. l would therefore infer that at some future date, &gt;andar Shahpur is destined to be the only Persian G-ulf 'Port i or imports for ■ orth and Central Iran. ,/ith the present facilities aaid indeed for some time to come, the capacity of ti.ie port must oe admitted even by the Iranians as inadequate for such a r6le and therefore Khorramshahr must continue to oe used. In any event, the Iranian Government would seem illadvised to ban tne use of Khorrams ha hr because the Karun River- affords cheap transport to Ahwaz where the merchandise for tne orth can be pu on the railway. The only loss to the railway would be the transport of the goods over the 106 kilometres from _andar eraLour to Ahwaz and compensation for this mignL oe sought by cnarging the same freight rates as from Bandar Shahour. 6. In regard to the rumoured closing of the Ahwaz Customs house I have no information to suggest that this will oe done. The Cherkat-i-Sakhtemdn were about to build a new Customs house and warehouses on the right bank of the Karun. This monopoly Company having been dissolved, the Director of Customs here informed me that he had applied to Tehran for permission co build it himself and was daily awaitin a reply. This was some time ago and admittedly the absence of a reply aoes not augur well. On the other hand, the Customs here is responsible for Bandar Shahpur as well as for posts on the ,raq frontier. So far there have been no signs that the Customs/Li us corns xacilities at .'.andar Shfitlipur are to be aiv monte cl „ ..t biie ore sent Lime a ^reat c eal of the merchandise landed at t;j.a t 30 r l is cleared tnrou^ii the Customs House at Ahwaz,, If L^e customs ouse here is closed, it would seem obvious that Cue ^us tou.'S facili cies at . andar 1 ha ho ur must first be increased. This process must take a considerable time as the marsh around tne port has first to be drained, and Customs house and warehouses must be built as well as dwelling houses for cue scc^Lf. _ supply of fresh water must also be provided. 7# li; ° recapitulate, I would repeat that I have no information which would surest either that the Ahwaz Customs nouse will shortly be closed or that active steps are at present oeinp taken to divert traffic from Kho rra ms ha hr to Bandar channur. I would however re-iterate the reserves already formulated and amplify them by remarking that modern Iranians seem obsessed with a nationalistic bias which leads Ltiern lo take over enternrises 'Previously conducted by foreigners and launch new ones like Bandar Shahpur. Owing lo their lack of experience and efficiency Iranian administrations in general are not able to carry these tasks oul efiiciently. Their failures do not seem to be recognised and so Gixe ordinary rules of prudence and cornmonsense do not seem co apply. This blind persistence may make for national neatness buc it can be extremely irritating. 0= Copy of this despatch is being sent to His Majesty’s Vice Consul at Kho mams ha hr, Ho. 567 I have, etc. ( bd. y ii.. &lt;j . JPc II. B. M’S, cor ST” F ■2 KHUZISTAU.% ' 1 :., 'J ' *- y r *. f' ' o v./ * * i 19 37 J »urir*t ■ ~ ~ *** EPTE Oil SS lAl'DJKl- OF CAI^-0 AT khoizra: shahr. oince the jj-el^ian experts, previously in cliar^e of tiie Customs, lianded over their duties to Iranian Officials, the Customs have cot into an increasingly chaotic state. The Or eat ?ire of August 1935 did lout little to ease the situation, and in fact, increased the muddle, Co Tne main and original causes of Customs conyestion are (a) tne complicated office routine, which a^oears to vary from aa,y to day or montn to month as new and contradictory orders are received from Tehran, (bee para, dl of my Annual Commercial Report for the Iranian Year ended the 20th larch 1937), (o) tile shortage of cranes to unload 'barges, and the Icick. of means to carry ^oods from the wharves to co— downs or stackyards, (c; tne complete lack of method in stacking poods and the general disorder in tne Customs areas. (d) the ipnorance, laziness and unreliability of most ox L-.-e Customs Oificials and the lack of ord.er and method in their offices. 3. The congestion has been increased durinp the last year by (a) the difficult, importers have experienced in obtaining Foreign jxchanpe to take un their shinping documents from the Banks, (b) the spate of poods imported by the I ononoly companies, who appear to have ordered a y r ear 7 s requirements to arrive/arrive in the last few months. 4. The overcrowding of the Customs Compound proper has led to overflows of cargoes oeing dumped in and around Khorramshahr town in any available open space. For instance (i; j otor Cars in Abadan (bein L ; assembled by Tessrs. The Anclo-Iranian Oil Company) 0 (ii) ho to r uars in the Anglo-1ranian Oil Company’s Compound in Khorramshahr (landed by lessrs. the Anglo- Iranian Oil Company). (iii) eneral Cargo in i : e. r srs. Cray, Mackenzie £ Go’s old house. (iv) Tea and sugar.in Anglo-Iranian Oil Company’s old general office. (v) Heavy building material, girders, iron beams, cement, also tea and piece-goods at Diwanieh and Fahlieh (oheikh Kiiazal’s old palcces on the bank of Shatt-al-Arab two miles up river). (vi) Packages of general cargo in ITusseinia (place close to the Vice-Consulate). (vii) .iece-goods, iron beams etc. in Kut-i-Sheikh, (viii) Sugar and piece-goods in loshi Kohen’s ^o-dov/n. finally (ix) Parses in the river. 5. The overcrowding, varied dumping grounds, lack of Customs staff and general inefficiency lias prevented barges oeirg unloaaed and iias caused a barge shortage. As a result British Shipping gents have been forced to bring in extra era.it from nasra. j essrs. Cray, Mackenzie A Co^, limited we re able to utilise spare barges owned by their Basra office, ^uc iG s e r s. -•'•C. St rick &amp; Co. , ltd. and lessrs. African A Eastern/Eastern (i-ear jiJast) limited T .vere forced to hire at hi^h rates. . ocal oar^e owners, when tney saw tliat Agents were ready to pay Dinars 5 per c.iem for a barge, raised their rates to Rials 500/-, 6. Delays in unloading barges and the increased hire rates increased the costs of landing goods, and Shipping encs, after running at a loss (see para 3 of my despatch l T o. 1511 of 21st December 1936 regarding ' essrs, P.0, Strick d Co., ltd., and oara 6 of my despatch ho. 9/11/203 of 17th February 1937 regarding . essrs. African d Pastern (rear East) limited) out up their landing c arges to cover their expenses. (The esopotamia Iran Corporation owning their own barges or utilising cnose of cneir .’asra Office were able to carry on vi bn out slijxic loss, . For instance in ’ arch it cost Fessrs. prank C. Strick d Co., limited approximately g. 3,000 to land approximately 3,000 tons from the S.S. i? Kuhistan ; . To oalance their books they were forced to charge from Rials (^/- bo Rials 90/- per ton in landing c targes on this cargo. 7. The naval Authorities cite the case of the -Kuhistan 4 as the final cause of the monopolisation of the landing of csrgo, and major L-hulam hussain hayendor says in a letter to j essrs, -rray, ; ackenzie I Co. , limited — ,: ln order to terminate the coercion of Steamship Companies’ Agents towards importers the question of landing cargo has been entrusted to Ciie ivc.run avi^ation Company 1 ’. (it is interesting to note that no reference whatsoever has been made to orders or .■-ns bi uc oions from Teliran, as is usually done by local authorities when enforcing a new order. N ‘ 8. One cannot forget, however, that when Sarhang . ayendor floated both the still-born Shirka c-i-TJaqlieh and the Shirkat/\ V -*Ji m&lt; *' r\ Shirkat KashtIrani Karim (see my despatch Vo, 9/11/1519 of /31st April 1937) that ne said that he hoped to obtain monopoly rights for these companies 0 I do not thinly tiiat Sarhan£ jjavendor visualised a fort of Khorramsliahr Authority * or “Khorrarnsnanr f ort Trust*' with all the responsibilities and duties undertaken by such bodies as the ''ort of London ..ucnority or the bomb ay ort Trust* I am inclined to think c i lc. t, nis sole motive was to 'keep tne money in the country' 1 and to keep local affairs of any kind under his own control. The volume of correspondence between the ' aval Port Officer, the Director of Customs and Kanacinc Director of the Shirkat Kasiioirani hi run passing the baby of responsibility for goods 11 om one io a no c ne r snows tnat neither i^arliang nor Kajjor Dayendor nad foreseen tnat any responsibility was entailed. They liave displayed considerable ignorance of Shinning and business mecnods on otrer occasions and I am of opinion tiiat they did not realise wijat their liabilities would be if the oixi^ka i .aasntirani Kcrun obtained monopoly ri nts or that they would be responsible to any one other than themselves. In fact, ± tnink Colonel Dayendor imagined that the Shirkat Kashtiram narun would ^ive him increased power and money, and the gratitude of his imperial majesty the Shah and all ±i anians ox iranianising a lucrative business, previously in tne hands of foreigners c C. Since the Shirkat Kashtirani Karun received monopoly ri^iics foreign shinping' nas avoided r.horramshahr to a certain encexic. Durijig the first half of x^pril only six shins called Here i_&lt;.s iead of the usual ten, and of these 4 were the 3.I.S.F. uo’s Fast or Slow hails. This Company is handing over their cargoes ’'under strict protest , although the T aval Authorities after/,r\ after asking for a definition of orotest repudiate its admissibility. Messrs, frank C..btrick ' Co , :imited f s steamers and the fansa j ine are avoiding this port, and I have seen a letter from the latter company stating that while they do not wisn to impede the trade of Iran they cannot allow delays to their ships on account of inefficiency. n?hey are collecting a lar^e consignment of ;,oods for Iran into one shin at hasra and are sending her to Bandar Shahpur. If she cannot oe unloaded immeuiately, she is to proceed to Bombay and dispose of the car^o there*. he srs. Prank C; trick f COc , limited appear to be workiipj in conjunction with the r.ansa line. inis amounts to a form of limited boycott, as su^Bested in hr. hardener’s d^Bpatch No. 44, dated t'ne 16th April 1937. 9, ,/itii tiie limited amount of cargo arriving at present it is hard to say whether the Shirkat Kashtirani Karun will be able to develop into an efficient landing company. It is interesting to note that their charges were immediately 2 Oh above those last quoted by Gray, hackenzie h Co., limited, and tnat the instructions that they must insure cargo in their barges between ship and shore with the Agence Istufani Tehran nad not tnen been given. Their barges, tugs and launches are old and even tne uest would hrr' ly pass a strict survey. Thev nave enga^eo. blacksmiths and carpenters to natch certain other ^ers to augment tneir ileet, and talk of placing orders in ermany ioi ne^v iron caries. .-it present they nave not the money to make purchases, but will require credit and foreign .exchange from tne Iranian Government, which will be hard to obtain wicn the failure of the German-Iran clearing agreement- Again, they are not employing men renowned either for their knowledge/Such men as knowledge of shiopirvj or business integrity. Hiranand Kin^orani (see my despatch lo. 13/11/1422 of 24th noveiiioer 1236 wno is their Shipping Superintendent, and 2 .H. Khan (see para 243 of my Diary Fo 0 16 for 1936) who was dismissed oy iessrs. African '■ .Eastern ( ear Past) limited for inefficiency and dishonesty some months ajo, are not likely go insnire the public with confidence. I feel sure, nov/ever, that rather tnan admit their own inefficiency, they will Dlame any possible failure on the lack of co-operation of foreign Steamship CompanieSc 10. The British Shirnins cents, for different reasons nope that txie Shirkat Kashtirani Karun will fail. : essrs ra ^ 5 M ackenzie c. Co. , limited know that Mesopotamia Iran uorporation made a satisfactory profit out of the landing business in the past and hope to do so again. 1 essrs. prank stride Co., limited and : essrs, African &lt;T-. eastern (rear Cast; -td. are not finding their dealings with the Shirkat's representatives, chiefly Ir. 1 iranand Hing.orani, any too easy. Tne latter refused essrs. Prank C. Strict ft Co., limited any receipt for cargo discharged from the S.S. ‘‘Bandar Shahpur- recently. (See my telegram Fo, 14 of 14th April 1937 ). 0n Clle other ilant:l tue &gt; are no t anxious to resume landing cargo Wiiicn nas been a tiresome and unremunerative business for them siiice tney do not own their own barges. All the gents are anxious about their responsibility for cargo as they cannot obtain any valid receipts until the Customs Storekeeper checks the cargo by the manifest on shore, which may be weeks after cne car 50 was discharged from the ship. 11. The landing of cargo and clearance of goods, whether by foreign Aants or by a monopoly company, cannot be an efficient/efficient business until the bottle neck of the Customs is cleared, the complicated and expensive procedure of clearing goods simplified and the general disorder in both offices and compounds is straightened. It is not for me to say whether Ciie Iranian overnnient would re-employ foreign Customs Directors as in the ^ast, but were it Possible a great obstacle to foreign trao.e uoulo. oe removec., if the Iranian Government decided on such a retrograde 1 'step, they might, too, agree to employing expert tort Officers to form an efficient and remunerative ; ort Trust. I fear, however, that such is beyond the bounds of possibility’Copy to: Mr. Baggallay No. 151/6/37. Reference Foreign Office despatch Ho. 23 (S. 7885/735/34) of 16th January, 1937. No. r^l/6/37 20th February, 1937. Your despatch No. 1 of the 7th January about navigation on the Karun. 2. We have heard from the Foreign Office that the Euphrates - Tigris Steam Navigation Company (i.e. the owners of the old Shattrah and the Shirin, managed by Mespers as agents for the Iran Transport Company) and Stricks are alarmed by further reports of measures contemplated by the Iranian Government to divert traffic from the Karun to Bandar Shahpur and the railway, in particular by closing once more the Customs house at Ahwaz. The r&gt;ritish interests concerned are naturally perturbed by any tnreat to Khorramshahr and the Karun, since o^ the one hand they would lose the river traffic to Ahwaz, and on the other British ships would be greatly delayed if they used Bandar Shahpur, which is still hopelessly ill-equipped. The Foreign Office have tiierefore asked us for a report on the present position with regard to the diversion of traffic from Khorramshahr and the Karun to Bandar Shahpur and the railway. 2 . It appears that the present enquiries arose out of a meeting which took place at Ahwaz early in Sentember, 1936, when a representative of Mespers, Mr. Wengoborski of the liansa Line and certain forwarding agents were summoned by the Governor-General to discuss the feasibility of bringing/ A.J. Gardener Esquire, His Majesty's Consul, Ahwaz.bringing all Ahwaz through cargo hy rail from Bandar Shahpur instead of by river from Khorramshahr. Later on the same day the 3-overnor—General told Mr. Wengoborski that if his company would book through cargo to Ahwaz by rail, traffic on the Karun would be stooped. Mr. Wengoborski said that he must consult his head office in Bremen, and told Mespers that he was definitely against the proposal, so long as conditions at Bandar Shahour remained as at present. 3. Yfe do not appear to iiave heard before of this meeting at Ahwaz in September, nor iiave we recently heard anything to suggest that the Ahwaz customs house v/ould shortly be closed, or that active measures would be taken to divert traffic from Khorramshahr and the Karun to Bandar Shahpur and the railway. On the other hand we have seen reports in the press of work on the quay at Khorramshahr to improve landing facilities there. It is certain that Bandar Shahpur is quite incapable of dealing with the present volume of traffic, while we hear that Khorramshahr is so busy that the Anglo-lranian Oil Company had to help by unloading and assembling heavy lorries at Abadan and by organizing unloadings at Khorramshahr. As long as this state of things continues, it seems most unlikely that the Ahwaz customs will be closed. 4. We should be very grateful if you could let us have a report on the position in an official despatch, and in particular could let us have: (i) any information about the possibility of the Ahwaz customs being closed: (ii) your views of the effect which the closure of the/I the Ahwaz customs, if carried through, would have - i.e. would it really tend to divert traffic to the railway? (iii) any information about otner measures to divert traffic from Khorramshahr to Bandar Shahpur. 5. I am sending a copy of tnis letter to Baggallay at the Foreign Office. (Signed), D.P. Reilly for P.N. Loxley.• r ■ ■■ m COPY (E 2279/76/34) 133 V x5l/l4/37) ,-ni ^ I . / U s ‘- ^ BRITISH LEGATION, Tehran, 9th April, 1937. Sir, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a copy of a despatch from His Majesty f s Consul at Ahwaz regarding the closure of the Ahwaz Customs. It will be seen that Mr. Gardener confirms the view expressed in my despatch Xi+'+'S No . 77 of the 27th February that it is most unlikely that the Customs at Ahwaz will be closed at any time in the near future. 2. While this is satisfactory, it is to be feared that the difficulties of British shipping companies due to congestion at the Gulf ports and to the action of the local port and customs authorities, are not likely to decrease. I have the honour to enclose a copy of a further despatch from Mr. Gardener, which shows that despite the assistance of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, there had been no appreciable improvement in the situation by the beginning of March. Further difficulties have been caused by the restriction of the conveyance of cargo from ship to shore at Khorramshahr to a local Iranian Company which is most inadequately equipped to carry out this work. The position with regard to this question is at present somewhat obscure, and I propose to defer reporting in full on this subject until the completion of further enquiries which I am making. I have, etc., The Right Honourable, Anthony Eden, M.C., M.P., etc., etc., etc., Foreign Office. (Signed) H. SEYMOUR.CONFIDENTIAL ^No. 23. BRITISH CONSULATE, AHWAZ. 5th March, 1937. Sir, I have the honour to forward the following information in amplification of my despatch No. 9 of the 26th January. 2. A reliable report states that in the Customs at Khorramshahr three hundred thousand packages are lying unprotected from damage by sun, rain or pilferage while in /diwaz there are foixteen thousand. A similar state of affairs is known to exist in Bandar Shahpur where no warehouse accomodation exists and a quantity of wheat awaiting shipment has been considerably damaged. 3. In neither Khorramshahr, Bandar Shahpur nor Ahwaz is there a proper Customs house or warehouse facilities. Barges are used as storehouses and the number of barges being limited, landing charges have increased enormously. Barges are being hired from Basra at Prohibitive charges while a cargo of cement at Bandar Shahpur had recently to be unloaded by tran shipment into small boats (bellurnsj. 4. Apparently strong representations have been made/ H.J. Seymour, Esq., C.M.G., His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, etc., etc., etc., British Legation, Tehran.made to the Central authorities 'by the Customs and proper accommodation has been promised. Considerable time must elapse in any case before this can be provided. 5. The same source stated that the Ahwaz Customs House would be built at once and that Ahwas would evenually become the provincial centre for Khuzistan Customs. 6 . In amplification of the postscript of your despatch under reference, I would add that the late Davar requested the help of the Company in assembling motor vehicles. This was agreed to by the Company in return for a payment of Rials 40,000 a month (please see Ahwaz diary for January 1937 - paragraph 4). The accumulation of motor vehicles is however only one factor of congestion. Other goods, notably tea etc. continue to accumulate, as a result of the monopoly system, the shortage of ready cash to pay duties, delays in granting import licenses and finally the ineptitude of the Customs Administration. 7. I am sending copy of this despatch to His Majesty r s Vice Consul at Khorramshahr (No. 349). I have, etc., (Signed) A.J. GARDENER. H.B.M’S CONSUL FOR KHU2ISTAN.No. 30. BRITISH CONSULATE, . Conridential AHWAZ. 16th march, 1337. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the first paragraph of your despatch No, 77(231/7/37) of February 27th to the Foreign Office (No. 14 to this post) cone em in g Cu s toms dispositions in Khuzistan, and also to my despatch No. 12 of February 10th. 2. Last night I was able to take advantage of the dinner given in celebration of H.I.M. the Shah’s birthday to have a conversation with the Director of Customs. He told me that to the best of his knowledge there was no intention of closing the Customs here. Indeed he stated that he had been in telegraphic communication with Tehran and expected daily to receive sanction to build Customs Offices, warehouses etc. on the right bank. He added that he had received sanction from Tehran to transfer to Ahwaz the fifteen ton steam crane installed at Bandar Abbas. As a further point he mentioned that his average receipts here amounted to five million rials a month. I am not certain but I thinkthat this figure includes the Bandar Shahpur receipts as this latter post is, he informed me, under his control. 3. As regards Bandar Shahpur, the Director of Customs added that one steel barge of a capacity of 250 tons had already/ H.J.Seymour, Esq., C.M.G-., His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, etc. , etc. , etc* , British Legation, Tehran.already arrived there from Germany and was being erected. He expected three more from the same source within a short period, together with a tug which he said had been loaded in Hamburg ten days ago. With this equipment together with a fifteen ton steam crane which, he said, had already arrived he would be able to handle one thousand tons of cargo a day. This is, of course, a very optimistic estimate but it is certain that a considerable advance will be thus made in the facilities of that port. He also informed me that some warehouses were being constructed in Bandar Shahpur. 4. Discussing the future of Bandar Shahpur, the Director of Customs said that owing to the absence of quays etc. at that port, it was impossible to dispense with Khorramshahr Customs at present. He was of the opinion that the port would in time be completed and that as far as possible all traffic would be concentrated there. 5. Copies of this despatch are being sent to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, (No. 400) and to His Majesty*s Vice Consul at Khorramshahr, (No. 401). I have, etc., (Sgd.) A.J.Gardener. H.B.M's Consul for Khusistan.! CO’Y (S l7 1 , /7«/5*) ! ^37 SrltlBh 1&gt;g«tlon, T*hr®n. '•-v TWUf/vr) ?%7th v «brui*ry, \9W With reference to certain report* which ara current regarding tho navlg* tlon of the Karun, T have the honour to state that l have no information which would euggeat that tha Iranian doveraneBt arc oonteroloting tha closure of the Cu tow a houre at ^hwai, or othtr Imaiadlate ^teoa to divert traffic fro** the K run to bandar hahour, ^nd the railway, ’ha Iranian Oovernment are undoubtedly aware that ^andar ' hah^ur cannot ^oeaihly deal with the nraaant volirse of traffic, and it sea-na unllVcly that they will be ao foolish a» to prevent traffic through Khorraoahahr and the Karun route in tha near future. I hava however racua^tad Wia ‘ aje ity* a Cattail at Ahwas to oreoa a a report on thia ru&lt;5 .tlon, and I $hall not fail to In or^ you of hie vlewa in the light of local knowledge. If it should or ova nattaeaary to »aha any raoraeantationa to the Iranian Oovernwant regarding tha clorura of the Ahwae airtatta, I agrea that reoreeantationa hasad on traaty rights hold out little hone of auceaae. ^he Iranian Gov^gnmant would certainly deny ’ha oreaent validity of the . 190S Convention and would resent any mggeetlon that their right to ooen and clo a cuytfvra houaae when and where they choote ia in any way limited by treaty. think therefore that any reoreaentatt©tta ahoild be baaed on conelderationa of practical convenience. ^ut as I hfve said, have no reason to aunooaa that the closure of the /hwai ouato»ra house ia nro^oaed at nreaent. 8. I have no apeclal infomatlon regarding conditions at ^ufblre, but T have no loubt that the congeatlon la due to the Tha sight Honourable, Ant*«!*• at all th« tulf t&gt;artF. ’’hera are two am In oau^aa ^a) th# fact that ©o*na of the vartoue monopoly eow^anlaa haaa aade the at eta** of or iartng in single son&amp;lfirosienta th* aninpllea whieh they need for a whole year’s forking and ^h) tha difficulty of obtaining exchange to ol ar gaada tvm the ourtoaa # 'hno ahnor^allir large ouentittea of goods have arrived at the Cttsiaaittt which are already nicked with otherc. that cannot he cleared for l^ck of exchange* torage soace la hoocle»Bly Inadeqn^te, fnd lighters nmet be used for etorage and cannot be unloaded for weeks, «o that they are not available for unloading At ?horra^ahahr it haw been nece aa y to bring lighters from Basrah at exorbitant rates of hire, «nd It aea^s clear that the »a^e troribi* h** occurred at Bushire where there Is no alternative source frow which lighters can be obtained* £♦ he rranlan lovemunt are undoubtedly fully a*are of this oosttlon, and acutely embara-eed by it. ^hey ara doing what they can to i*»orov&lt;j landing facilities* at fhorra^shahr, and are considering a modest scheme for improvements at ^^ndar hahnur, which It ahould be possible to realise without great delay. -a reported in my deanstoh under reference, they have annealed to tht '.nglo-Trantan 11 Company to helo ther out of their difficulties at 1 horremehahr. The situation Is Indeed still moat unsatisfactory. Nevertheless T do not think that anything would be gained by reoreaentatlone to the Jranian Government. I fear that they would only be irritated by oomolainta regarding conditions fro- which they are tht*meelvaa suffering eaverety, and that they wo\ild not be s^ lrr *d thereby to any greater efforts to improve the no**lUon. 4. I am sending conies of this despatch to tht honourable the olitlcal evident In the Vreian Gulf, ftnehire To.is * n a to Hi a 'a^e ty f a Consul at hwas Bo. i4 f eithout enoloaures. I have, etc., (Sgd. ) H. v. Seymour.ooii.0 .;ric. *1 • Q l.) b « j X was told yastarday th«kt tho oon^aatioa oonfueloa at (julf porta i« vorae, Ono Brltlah istwaruer with o&amp;rtfo for Khorrafliahahr land ad it all at Baa raj a fierman eteswiar aftor waiting for four flayf? (at a coat of f&amp;o par diom) raported that It would hava to lana ita cargo olaavhora. It Bazaar Sha^pur whoro only ooe a hip am odbio alongeide at onoOjfiY* woro in port the other day. A report in tt-day's journal d« Trheran «ftya that ao Italian and aeraaB eteawor were da*H&lt;«d at Bandar rha^pur duririg a middon etora. Unloading faoilities have ehanged little reoertly,though to- cay inetead of the ordinary hand-hauled oa«e« t huge pieces of maohinery.Bieael engines etcetera ^re daily heirjg Imported owing to railway construction arid induntriuliRation. E. At Khorraawhahr fifty notcr cara fell into the »e«u Tmo lighters full of motor spare parts which had been waiting indefinitely to he u loaded,gradually filler with water and sank. Total lootsee are said to aamu t to 400*000 towari* £ (60,000). The loss of spare &gt;&amp;rts is particularly important *a X rue told that one of the wain reasons for the huge rise in tr&amp;naport rates is laa* of tyres aud eparee which has resulted in uiany trunks being laid up. Of 800 wotcr vehicles which arrived at horramahahr in Kove'r.ber,it is said that not wore than £S had been cleared up to a few fttgre ago aid a further large oonoigmuent is due shortly. luring the last few (souths additional lines (Japanese t wutoh-Java and American) have started regular services to the Gulf f which will certainly not nslp to relieve the existing congestionthe Secretary of State for India in Council a copy of a letter addressed by the Senior Naval Officer* Persian Gulf to the Commander-in-Chief* East Indies Station, on the subject of the Persian Navy* 2. A similar letter has been sent to the Foreign Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, INDIA OFFICE, S.W. 1 . 1 KECo. POL DEPtH 3 0 OCT 1936 j INOIm r'iCE,COPY* SUBJECT: PROM ••• The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H#M*S* SHORE HAM at Bomhay. DATE ••• 9th September 1936* No* 188/574* TO ••••• The Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station. The attached correspondence is forwarded for information* 2* ^he contents of paragraphs 3 and 5 of British Consulate, Ahwaz, letter No* 51 of 7th August are confirmed by a conversation I had with Sarhang Bayendor* 3* Paragraph 4 is new and of great interest* It would appear from this that new motor launch being built for Shah is definitely intended for the Caspian Sea. (signed) V.S*Butler. CAPTAIN. SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER, PERSIAN GULF. *. \T I l&gt; / j * % CONFIDENTIAL. 775'! 1936 ivy: IRANIAN NATIn any furtlier communioution on this ^bjectl please quote N '£ 'jo ?(j- 'and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Oflce, London, S.VV. I THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents hi^ fw'^) 1/7 iiipliinents to J and, by direction of the rr tnansmits herewith cop Foreign Office, od-io ’ 19 %' of the under-men ti oned paper Reference to previoiite ear Name and Date. iiH 14 6no 1.3667 ( Similar letter sent toiio.4^4 {bW./a») E ^6269 Sir, British Legation, tmxm- 14th September, 19&amp;6. 7 \ * J a 1,1th reference to ray despatch oi the &amp;6th - June,I hate the honour to transmit you re with a copy of a despatch from the Acting British Consul at Ahwaa regarding the new floating dock which has now been anohored by the Iranian naral authorities at Bandar nhahpur. g # x had delayed forwarding a copy of this despatch to your Depart neat in anticipation of Mr. Todd 1 b visit to Tehran which has Just taken place,as I hoped that he mi^it then be able to furnish more definite information about the dock. It proved, however.that KT. Todd was not able to add anything, and I felt therefore that I should forward this despatch without further delay,though I realise that it contains little definite infomatioa. The difficulty of obtaining information from the Iranian naval and adlit&amp;ry authorities will oe appreciated. It is.however.hoped that His 'a^esty*s Vice- Consul at Khorrarashahr will shortly be aole to visit Bandar Shahpur. I will not fail to report any further information which I a&amp;y receive on this subject. 3# x am sending copies of this despatch to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India ]fo.2o8,to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Baghdad lo.68,to the Honourable the j&gt;olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf !lo.69,to Hie majesty’s consul at JUrwas Ho.51,to His Majesty’s Vice-Consul at Khorraashahr Ro.14 and to the senior laval Officer commanding the Persian oulf Division ilO*56d/4/36. I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, fhe Sight Honourable, f jfe^iesty’s Charge d’Affaires, Antnony i*Xien il.C*,M.P«, • t0 *The Ailim ortici. (Signed) P H. Loxley.OOH^IP.aiMAL British Consulate, lihwaz. 7th August 1936. Ho • 51 • Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your despatch Ho*38 (560/2/36) dated the 26th June last dn the A^hjeot fo^the Iranian Hary and a proposal to transfer nayal to Aha dan to interview Kr« Clegg, the Acting Manager of taie .^nglo Iranian Oil Company,in regard do this question. He informed me that the floating dock had now finally been fixed into position at Bandar Shahpur with the help nf the Company's tugs6 It appears that the site originally decided upon for this dock was near the mouth of the Harun river opposite Ito hammer ah - see Mr* «&amp;&amp;itt&amp;on T e telegram Ho.18 to you of the 27th July 1935. The reason for the change of site is not clear. One version is to the effect that the Italian suppliers persuaded the Iranian Government to order a larger dock than they originally Intended In order to aoooitsaodate cruisers of 8 t 000 to 10,000 tons displacement which the Iranian Goveraueat are said to he thinking of purchasing. However that may be, the dock aotuall supplied by Italy was far too large to be moored in the Harun River and it had perforce to be placed elsewhere* It is impossible to say definitely whether this was as the result of a blunder by the Havy Department or whether the site wc deliberately changed in pursuance of a definite policy* the part of the Iranian Government to transfer the naval base A headquarters to Bandar Shahpur. I took the opportunity afforded by a recent visit Mr* Clegg had no knowledge of the rumoured intention on /from His Majesty's Charg4 d'Affaires British Legation, Tehran.from ilhorramahahr to Bandar Shabpur. lattor port will protie feodd the iiavol headyuarterfa hat it will prore to he ^ a coatly undertaking as a large amount of land reclamation work will have to be taken in hand first of all. The policy of the Government is to make Bandar Shahpur the chief port of Iran as the terminus of the tran&amp;Iranian nailway and the naval question will probably be deferred until the railway is completed and in actual operation. It is howevor safe to assume that the transfer has been decided upon in principle but that the work will not be commenced for the time being owing to lack of funds. The country cannot stand the cost of simultaneously building the railway and creating a naval base out of the marSnes at Bandar ^hahpur - unless recourse is had to a foreign loan. 4. I also understand from Ur. Clegg that the Government has decided to dam the mouth of the Karan and divert the river into the Bahmanshir channel as a result of their dispute with Iraq about shipping rights in the Shatt-el-Arab. Whether this scheme will materialise remains to be seen. 5. From another source I have been informed that naval headquarters only will be transferred to Bandar iihahpur whilst the workshops remain at Khorramshahr where they are now situated. This will be effeoted when the port at Bandar Shahpur has been Constructed but this will not be ready for a few years. The Shah is said to be very anxious that the port should be finished when the railway line from Korth to South is in operation over its whole length,and for this purpose has prdered the Ministry of Communications to spend about seventy million tomans on the construction of a town capable of housing five thousand persons with five more jetties at the port ete. 6. I have also discussed the question with the Senior tfav&amp;l Officer,Persian Gulf,who although cognisant of these rumours was I unable to give any definite information about them. ■ / : I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, (S if H T ignedJ f odd,j^Jn any further communication on this s £ 5 Lfr3~ and address —person by nam&lt;, but to “ The^^^^y&gt;Setary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents compliments to (J^ ^J^qWT ’ /-&gt; .J ^ 'T , and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop Foreign Office, n^rymretails for the Light Bouys in Khor i^usa for piloting the Sea- ; going Vessels between Band.'r Shahpour and Outer Bar, a distance trf' y v 48 na ut i ca x li i 1 e s s - Bo. .!. - Elec t ric Beaco n Light , on the pier at the port of Bandar Shahpour flashing light with green sector of 10 Miles T range, 1 /B r ■ Single flash every 4 seconds- he. S - Light Bony, Shite single flashing light of 8 miles® range 0.5 / 2.7 single v/hite flash every three seconds. No. 7 - Light Bou va white double flashing % light of 6 Liles' range 0.3 / 1.2 / 0 «o / 1.2 - a 5 r, '' a B of 2 white flashes every 6 seconds. No. 8 - Light Bouv , V/hite triple flashing light of 6 Miles 1 range, 0.5 / 1.5 / 0.5 / 1.2 / 5,7 -a group of 5 white flashes every 9 seconds. No. So. - Lig ht Bony , white single flashing light of 6 miles’ range, 0.3/5.7 - a single white flash every 3 seconds. No. 9 - Light Bony , Red single flashing light of 6 Miles’ range, 0.5 /2c 7 - a single red flash every 5 seconds. No. 10 - Light Bony , Red double flashing light of 6 lilies’ range, 0.5 /lc2 l 0.3 /i.2 r a group of 2 red flashes every 6 seconds. No. 11 - Li fit Bouy s white double flashing light of 6 miles’ range, 0.3/1. 2 /0.3/1 .2 - a group of 2 white flashes every 6 seconds. No. 12 - Light Bquy , Red triple flashing light of G Miles’ range, 0.5 / 1.2 / 0.5 / 1.2 / 0.3 / 5.7 - a group of 5 red flashes every 9 seconds No. 13 - Light Bouy , white triple flashing light of 10 Miles’ range, 0.5 / 1.5 / 0.3 / 1.2 / 0.3 / 5.7 - a group of 3 white flashes every 9 seconds. No. 15 - Light and Whistle Bouy , white flashing light of 13 miles’ range, 0.6 / 3.4 ~ a single flash of Q .6 seconds’ duration every 6 seconds. Notes * - A - The light &amp; Whistle Bouy No. 15 is situated outside the Khor Musa Bar at long. 49, 12, East, Lat. 29, 52 North. B - Vessels arriving from the sea bound for Bandar Shahpour will find pilots by the Light and Whistle Bouy No. 15. C - Between Bandar Shahpour and Khor Abou Khozayer 4 beacons wiJ be placed at positions 2, 3, 4, &amp; 5 whence navigation at nights will be possible for all the sea-going vessels throughout Khor Musa.Jr .Z.4851/1936 Extract from Diary of H.£.M 1 s Consulate for Ahuzistan, Ahwaz, for the month of May, 1936. 169. havy . Mrs. Bayandor, wife of Sarhang Bayandor the Officer Commanding the Iranian Navy in the South, left Khorramshahr for the United Kingdom via Iraq on the loth. The Patrol vessel 'Chahrokh” returned to Khorramshahr from the Gulf on the 5th. The Patrol vessel 'Karkas' left Khorramshahr for the Gulf on the 7th. On the 23rd May a floating dock of 6000 tons capacity with 4 anchors of 100 tons each, was imported for the use of the Iranian Navy and permanently stationed at Bandar Shahpur. The dock was towed by a vessel of the Dutch Steamship Company called the H Humber n and chartered by the Iranian Government from Italy for a sum of £7500. The dock was held in position by means of a buoy. Luring the last week of May owing to a strong wind the dock broke away from its moorings and was carried out to sea. It was recovered by a naval tug, brought back to Bandar Shahpur and fastened to the jet^y. This resulted in considerable difficulty for the ships calling there to unload their cargo. Sargord Ghulam Hussein Bayandor the brother of Sarhang Bayandor who went to Italy to purchase the floating dock arrived at Bandar Shahpur on the 22nd with his younger brother. They proceeded to Khorramshahr via Ahwaz on the 30th. 30 sailors and a petty officer are now stationed at the Naval Base at Bandar Shahpur. It is said that the Naval Headquarters may be transferred there. The Italian engineers are supposed to have refused to go as they do not consider Bandar Shahpur a fit place to live in.P.Z. 4518/36. 3«&gt; T^° EXTRACT PROM DIARY OP CONSULATE FOR KHUZISTAN, AHWAZ, FOR THE MONTH OP APRIL, 1936. 133. Ports - Bandar Shahpur. The total number of vessels visiting B a ndar Shahpur during the Iranian year ending on March 20, 1936, was 66, as compared with 39 during the p/evious year. Of these 33 were British, 15 German and 12 Japanese. 93,657 tons of cargo were landed, an increase of 56,350 tons over the year before. Japanese vessels now head the list for tonnage of cargo landed, consisting mostly of cement for railway construction. Gun Tragacanth and skins have also been shipped in small quantities to Japan and to London.COPY (E 1954/345/34) rs 126. (111/4/36) BRITISH LEGATION, TEHRAN. 14th March, 1936. Sir, In your ceapatch No. 9 of the 7th January encloeing correepondence with the Department of OverBeae Trade and Meters. Frank Strick you instructed me to furnish a full report on the present position as regards the importation of goods through the ports of Bandar Shahpur and Ehorranehahr respectively, and my observations on the desirability of making representations to the Iranian Government regarding conditions at the former port, bearing in mind the considerations set out in Foreign Office memorandum No. E 6984/6984/34 of the 9th Lccember. Messrs. Strick in their letter of the 19th November had asked that His majesty’s Government should represent to the Iranian Government the unsatisfactory state of affairs at Bandar Shahpur partly at least on the ground that this must have an adverse influence on trace to the port, which, so Messrs. Strick alleged the Iranian Government had created to handle all imports to Iran. 2. on receipt of your despatch I invited His Majesty’s/ The Right Honourable Anthony Eden, M.C., M.P., etc. , etc. , etc., The Foreign Office■■MU Majesty*e Consul at Ahwa* to report on the whole subject, and I now have the honour to enclose herein a copy of his reply which appears to state the facte fully. 3. These show that whatever future intentions may be as regards Bandar Shahpur, the Iranian authorities are not at present making it the sole port for imports. There is moreover, as I reported in my Secret telegram No. 87 of the 2nd March, good reason to believe that the development of the port on a big scale has been shelved, probably for at least two years until the financial position of the hah's Government has been put into a sounder position. I understand that a representative of a Netherlands group who had drawn up ambitious development plans for Bandar Shahpur has remained there with instructions to design on a much more modest scale. I would further remind you that His Majesty’s Minister reported in his telegram No. 42 a remark of the Iranian Minister for Foreign Affairs on the subject of the Bhatt-el-Arab to the effect that the Iranian Government had their own plans for the development of Khorramshahr. 4. As regards paragraph two of the Foreign Office memorandum you will observe that the facts and figures given by Mr. Vatkinson demonstrated first that British vessels can and do use jfhorraashahr considerably more than Bandar Shahpur; and secondly that those calling at Bandar dhahpur almost without exception have already proceeded/proceeded or will proceed to Khorramehahr. I have no evidence ac to loea of cargo to rivals caused fcy using the latter port; it is however probable that Messrs. Strides vessels are made to suffer delay in discharge at Bandar Shahpur through priority being given to vessels (mainly German) bringing equipment for the Shah's military forces, it is not possible to prevent this practise, but it appears that two 300 ton barges are being acquired for the port which, it may be hoped, will improve the unsatisfactory position. favour of diplomatic representations to the Iranian Government do not in my judgement exist which would outweigh the objection referred to in paragraph two of the Foreign Office memorandum. It is indeed possible, in view partly of their new policy of reuucing expenditure, that the Iranian Government would resent representations on the subject of Bandar bhahpur unless these were confined to very minor details of Port administration, such as control of coolies and the dearth of lighters, I would also draw attention to considerations arising from the 12th and 13th paragraphs of ;,{r. ^atkinson's despatch. the state of affairs on the Karun river referred to in paragraph 9, and that I hope to discuss shortly with Fir. Fraser of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company the subject In the above circumstances, reasons in 6 I should add that I am considering separately raised/raised in the 11th paragraph. 7. I am sending a copy of this and of Mr. Watkins on* s despatch to His Majesty^ Ambassador at Baghdad No. 21. I have, etc. (Signed) NKVILE BUTLKR.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001a1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3849</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001a1</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3849</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/120 'Development of the Port of Bander Shahpur &amp; Khorramshahr.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-28T22:25:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (105 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 107; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns development, facilities, and customs at the Iranian ports of Bandar Shahpur (also referred to as Bander Shahpur) and Khorramshahr.The papers include reports from the British Consul, Khuzistan, and the British Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr, statistics of shipping, and a letter of complaint from Frank C. Strick &amp; Company Limited to the Department of Overseas Trade about facilities at Bandar Shahpur in 1935.There are no papers in the file dated 1938-39.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Bandar Shahpur</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul, Khorramshahr</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Khorramshahr</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Harbours</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001a1#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>